<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20141121103714|634815972" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1271927" pageid="1271927" ns="0" title="Gender equality"><revisions><rev timestamp="2014-11-21T10:57:09Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{multiple issues|
{{expert-subject|date=November 2012}}
{{refimprove|date=June 2013}}
{{lead too short|date=June 2013}}
}}

[[Image:Igualtat de sexes.svg|thumb|upright|One of generic symbols for gender equality]]

'''Gender equality''', also known as '''sex equality''', ''' gender egalitarianism''', '''sexual equality''' or '''equality of the genders,''' refers to the view that [[Man|men]] and [[Woman|women]] should receive [[Social equality|equal treatment]], and should not be [[Discrimination|discriminated]] against based on [[gender]], unless there is a sound [[Biology|biological]] reason for different treatment.&lt;ref&gt;United Nations. Report of the Economic and Social Council for 1997. A/52/3.18 September 1997, at 28: "Mainstreaming a gender perspective is the process of assessing the implications for women and men of any planned action, including legislation, policies or programmes, in all areas and at all levels. It is a strategy for making women's as well as men's concerns and experiences an integral dimension of the design, implementation, monitoring and evaluation of policies and programmes in all political, economic and societal spheres so that women and men benefit equally and inequality is not perpetuated. The ultimate goal is to achieve gender equality."&lt;/ref&gt; This is the objective of the United Nations [[Universal Declaration of Human Rights]], which seeks to create equality in law and in social situations, such as in [[Democracy|democratic]] activities and securing [[equal pay for equal work]].

== History ==
An early advocate for gender equality was [[Christine de Pizan]], who in her 1405 book ''[[The Book of the City of Ladies]]'' wrote that the oppression of women is founded on irrational prejudice, pointing out numerous advances in society probably created by women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The Real Wealth of Nations: Creating a Caring Economics|author=Riane Eisler|year=2007|page=72}}  See the article [[Riane Eisler]].&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Shakers, an example of equality ===
{{Further|Shakers}}
As a group, the [[Shakers]], an evangelical group which practiced segregation of the sexes and strict [[celibacy]], were early practitioners of gender equality.  They branched off from a [[Quaker]] community in the north-west of England before emigrating to America in 1774.  In America, the head of the Shakers' central ministry in 1788, Joseph Meacham, had a revelation that the sexes should be equal, so he brought [[Lucy Wright]] into the ministry as his female counterpart, and together they restructured society to balance the rights of the sexes. Meacham and Wright established leadership teams where each elder, who dealt with the men's spiritual welfare, was partnered with an eldress, who did the same for women. Each deacon was partnered with a deaconess. Men had oversight of men; women had oversight of women. Women lived with women; men lived with men. In Shaker society, a woman did not have to be controlled or otherwise owned by any man. After Meacham's death in 1796, Wright was the head of the Shaker ministry until her own death in 1821. Going forward, Shakers maintained the same pattern of gender-balanced leadership for more than 200 years. They also promoted equality by working together with other women's rights advocates.  In 1859, Shaker Elder Frederick Evans stated their beliefs forcefully, writing that Shakers were “the first to disenthrall woman from the condition of vassalage to which all other religious systems (more or less) consign her, and to secure to her those just and equal rights with man that, by her similarity to him in organization and faculties, both God and nature would seem to demand."&lt;ref&gt;Frederick William Evans. ''[http://books.google.com/books?id=fg2bS2pDUVMC&amp;pg=PA17 Shakers: Compendium of the Origin, History, Principles, Rules and Regulations, Government, and Doctrines of the United Society of Believers in Christ's Second Appearing : with Biographies of Ann Lee, William Lee, Jas. Whittaker, J. Hocknell, J. Meacham, and Lucy Wright]''. Appleton; 1859. p. 34.  Note, this is an online Google book.&lt;/ref&gt; Evans and his counterpart, Eldress Antoinette Doolittle, joined women's rights advocates on speakers' platforms throughout the northeastern U.S. in the 1870s. A visitor to the Shakers wrote in 1875:
:“Each sex works in its own appropriate sphere of action, there being a proper subordination, deference and respect of the female to the male in his order, ''and of the male to the female in her order'' [emphasis added], so that in any of these communities the zealous advocates of ‘women’s rights’ may here find a practical realization of their ideal.”&lt;ref&gt;Glendyne R. Wergland, ''Sisters in the Faith: Shaker Women and Equality of the Sexes'' (Amherst: University of Massachusetts Press, 2011).&lt;/ref&gt;

The Shakers were more than a radical religious sect on the fringes of American society; they put equality of the sexes into practice. They showed that equality could be achieved and how to do it.&lt;ref&gt;Wendy R. Benningfield, Appeal of the Sisterhood: The Shakers and the Woman’s Rights Movement (University of Kentucky Lexington doctoral dissertation, 2004), p. 73.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the wider society, the movement towards gender equality began with the [[suffragette|suffrage movement]] in Western cultures in the late-19th century, which sought to allow women to vote and hold elected office. This period also witnessed significant changes to [[women's property rights]], particularly in relation to their marital status. (See for example, [[Married Women's Property Act 1882]].)

===Post-war era===
{{Further|Anti-discrimination laws}}
{{See|Timeline of women's rights (other than voting)}}

After [[World War II]], a more general movement for gender equality developed based on [[women's liberation]] and [[feminism]]. The central issue was that [[women's rights|the rights of women]] should be the same as of [[men's rights|men]].

The [[United Nations]] and other international agencies have adopted several conventions, toward the promotion of gender equality. Prominent international instruments include:

*In 1960 the [[Convention against Discrimination in Education]] was adopted, coming into force in 1962 and 1968.
*The [[Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination against Women]] (CEDAW) is an international treaty adopted in 1979 by the [[United Nations General Assembly]]. Described as an international [[bill of rights]] for women, it came into force on 3 September 1981.
*The [[Declaration on the Elimination of Violence Against Women]] was adopted by the [[United Nations General Assembly]] in 1993.
*In 1994, the twenty-year ''Cairo Programme of Action'' was adopted at the [[International Conference on Population and Development]] (ICPD) in [[Cairo]]. This [[Non-binding resolution|non binding]] programme-of-action asserted that governments have a responsibility to meet individuals' reproductive needs, rather than demographic targets. As such, it called for [[family planning]], [[reproductive rights]] services, and strategies to promote gender equality and stop violence against women.
*Also in 1994, in the Americas, [http://www.oas.org/juridico/english/treaties/a-61.html The Inter-American Convention on the Prevention, Punishment, and Eradication of Violence against Women], known as the ''Convention of Belém do Pará'', called for the end of violence and discrimination against women.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.oas.org/en/mesecvi/convention.asp&lt;/ref&gt;
*At the end of the [[Fourth World Conference on Women]], the UN adopted the [[Beijing Declaration]] on 15 September 1995 - a [[United Nations General Assembly resolution|resolution]] adopted to promulgate a set of principles concerning gender equality.
*The [[Maputo Protocol]] guarantees comprehensive rights to women, including the right to take part in the political process, to social and political equality with men, to control of their [[reproductive health]], and an end to [[female genital cutting|female genital mutilation]]. It was adopted by the [[African Union]] in the form of a protocol to the [[African Charter on Human and Peoples' Rights]], and came into force in 2005.
*The EU [[Directive (European Union)|directive]] ''Directive 2002/73/EC - equal treatment of 23 September 2002 amending Council Directive 76/207/EEC on the implementation of the principle of equal treatment for men and women as regards access to employment, vocational training and promotion, and working conditions'' states that: "Harassment and sexual harassment within the meaning of this Directive shall be deemed to be discrimination on the grounds of sex and therefore prohibited."&lt;ref&gt;http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=CONSLEG:1976L0207:20021005:EN:PDF&lt;/ref&gt; 
*The [[Council of Europe]]'s ''Gender Equality Strategy 2014-2017'', which has five strategic objectives:&lt;ref&gt;https//wcd.coe.int/ViewDoc.jsp?id=2105977&amp;Site=COE&amp;BackColorInternet=C3C3C3&amp;BackColorIntranet=EDB021&amp;BackColorLogged=F5D383&lt;/ref&gt;
:*Combating gender stereotypes and sexism
:*Preventing and combating violence against women
:*Guaranteeing Equal Access of Women to Justice
:*Achieving balanced participation of women and men in political and public decision-making
:*Achieving [[Gender mainstreaming|Gender Mainstreaming]] in all policies and measures



Such [[legislation]] and [[affirmative action]] policies have been critical to bringing about changes in societal attitudes. Most occupations are now equally available to men and women, in many countries. For example, many countries now permit women to serve in the [[armed forces]], the [[police|police forces]] and to be [[fire fighter]]s – occupations traditionally reserved for men. Although these continue to be male dominated occupations an increasing number of women are now active, especially in directive fields such as politics, and occupy high positions in business.

Similarly, men are increasingly working in occupations which in previous generations had been considered [[women's work]], such as [[nursing]], [[Maid|cleaning]] and [[child care]]. In domestic situations, the role of [[Parenting]] or child rearing is more commonly shared or not as widely considered to be an exclusively female role, so that women may be free to pursue a [[career]] after [[childbirth]].  For further information, see [[Shared earning/shared parenting marriage]].

Another manifestation of the change in social attitudes is the [[Married and maiden names#Feminism and preserving one's personal name|non-automatic taking by a woman of her husband's surname on marriage]].

Many people consider that the objective of gender equality has not been fully achieved, especially in [[Non-western|non-Western]] countries.

A highly contentious issue relating to gender equality is the role of women in [[religious law|religiously orientated societies]]. For example, [[Cairo Declaration on Human Rights in Islam#Contents|the Cairo Declaration on Human Rights in Islam]] declared that women have equal dignity, but not equal rights, and this was accepted by many predominantly Muslim countries. In some [[Christianity|Christian churches]], the practice of [[churching of women]] may still have elements of [[ritual purification]] and the [[Ordination of women]] to the priesthood may be restricted or forbidden. Some Christians or Muslims believe in [[Complementarianism]], a view that holds that men and women have different, but complementing roles. This view may be in opposition to the views and goals of gender equality.

In addition, there are also non-Western countries of low religiosity where the contention surrounding gender equality remains. In China, [[Sex-selective abortion and female infanticide#Cultural preference|cultural preference for a male child]] has resulted in a [[Missing women of Asia|shortfall of women]] in the population. [[Feminism in Japan|The feminist movement in Japan]] has made many strides and has resulted in Rethe [[Gender Equality Bureau]], but Japan still remains low in gender equality compared to other industrialized nations.

There are also countries that have a history of a high level of gender equality in ''certain'' areas of life, but not in other areas. An example is [[Finland]], which has offered very high opportunities to women in public/professional life, but has had a weak legal approach to the issue of [[violence against women]], with the situation in this country having been called a [[paradox]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.academia.edu/992154/The_Paradoxical_Approach_to_Intimate_Partner_Violence_in_Finland&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.scottishaffairs.org/backiss/pdfs/sa48/sa48_McKie_and_Hearn.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;According to a report by Amnesty International: "Finland is repeatedly reminded of its widespread problem of violence against women and recommended to take more efficient measures to deal with the situation. International criticism concentrates on the lack of measures to combat violence against women in general and
in particular on the lack of a national action plan to combat such violence and on the lack of legislation on domestic violence. (...) Compared with Sweden, Finland has been slower to reform legislation on violence against women. In Sweden, domestic violence was already illegal in 1864, while in Finland such violence was not outlawed until 1970, over a hundred years later. In Sweden the punishment of victims of incest was abolished in 1937, but not until 1971 in Finland. Rape within marriage was criminalized in Sweden in 1962, but the equivalent Finnish legislation only came into force in 1994 – making Finland one of the last European countries to criminalize marital rape. In addition, assaults taking place on private property did not become impeachable offenses in Finland until 1995. Only in 1997 did victims of sexual offenses and domestic violence in Finland become entitled to government-funded counseling and support services for the duration of their court cases." (pp. 89–91) –  ''Case Closed – Rape and human rights in the Nordic countries'' [http://www.amnesty.dk/sites/default/files/mediafiles/44/case-closed.pdf]&lt;/ref&gt;

Not all ideas for gender equality have been popularly adopted. For example:  [[topfreedom]], the right to be bare breasted in public, frequently applies only to males and has remained a marginal issue. [[Breastfeeding in public]] is more commonly tolerated, especially in semi-private places such as restaurants.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Jordan|first=Tim|title=Social Change (Sociology and society)|publisher=Blackwell|year=2002|isbn=0-631-23311-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Humankind's underlying gender biases ==
The above picture of Western progress on gender equality can be seen as severely oversimplified.
Namely, the text below aims to describe and analyze the gender biases underlying at least some of our human cultures.

Indeed, it is the contentious meaning of the term "equality" itself that makes measuring gender equality "progress" inherently problematic. Newman and White suggest that equality can be understood in three distinct ways: identical treatment, differential treatment, and fair treatment.&lt;ref name="Newman, Jacquetta A. 2012"&gt;Newman, Jacquetta A., and Linda A. White. Women, Politics, and Public Policy: The Political Struggles of Canadian Women. Don Mills, Ont.: Oxford UP, 2012. 14-15. Print.&lt;/ref&gt; Identical treatment is the claim that equality means the deployment of generalizing, abstract, content-less reason, unaffected with regard to the gender it addresses.&lt;ref name="Newman, Jacquetta A. 2012"/&gt; This view assumes that gender differences are entirely socially constructed concepts, and that an underlying, gender-neutral human should be the target of equality. Next, the differential treatment notion of equality is the claim that biological ("sex") differences do, in fact, exist as tangible and real, and that structuring treatment around these differences is not unequal, so long as these biological differences are accurately defined (that is to say, so long as differential treatment is not random).&lt;ref name="Newman, Jacquetta A. 2012"/&gt;

The third view, that equality is fair treatment, is in a sense a reaction to both of the previous two claims. Equality as identical treatment assumes that the criteria we use to define human nature is itself objective, neutral, and fair for each human, and differential treatment assumes that there are inherent, empirical, tangible, biological differences that the binary categories of male-female derive from. Theorists like Judith Lorber, Michel Foucualt, Judith Butler, and many more attack both of these essentialist stances, articulating that any claim to an underlying human nature is absurd. In short, this is because what it is to be a human is at bottom a product of constructive discursive discourses. As Judith Lorber puts the point: "the paradox of 'human nature' is that it is always a manifestation of cultural meanings, social relationships, and power politics".&lt;ref name="Kimmel Aronson"&gt;Kimmel, Michael S., and Amy Aronson. The Gendered Society Reader. New York: Oxford UP, 2011. 14–17. Print.&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, theorists like Catharine MacKinnon claim that all circulating articulations of this fictitious "universal human" actually reflect socially male biases.&lt;ref name="Kimmel Aronson"/&gt; That is to say, unadulterated, objective, pure reason is merely a tacit disguise for patriarchal reinforcement. It is clear, then, how the identical treatment model fails on this view. Similarly, by this logic, the differential treatment is shown to merely use male rationality to define and construct the gender difference - as a result, true equality is precluded.

This tacit inequality in our sexual concept poses a particular problem, because Western Liberal Democracies are premised on descriptions of people that describe them as equal, yet this exists alongside a description of women and men that describes them in terms that makes them unequal. So the above claims of this article that "Non-Western" countries are less gender equal than Western countries must not be so quickly accepted. Since this acceptance of inequality in sexes is perceived as a natural difference between men and women, it thus permeates into society relatively undiagnosed. Disguised as objective, the subjective/biased nature of these claims for equal treatment become particularly difficult to address. This allows the state/laws to appear to be gender-neutral and universally applicable, while ignoring the backdrop of the underlying forces that have structured our legal system and personal cognition in such a way as to promote [[equal opportunity|equality of opportunity]] for social category male at the price of inequality for social category female. As Judith Lorber says: "it is the taken-for-grantedness of such everyday gendered behaviour that gives credence to the belief that the widespread differences in what women and men do must come from biology".&lt;ref name="Kimmel Aronson"/&gt; On such a view, then, addressing equality must take on more than formal equality, and become "fair treatment".&lt;ref name="Newman, Jacquetta A. 2012"/&gt; That is to say, the male paradigm cannot be seen as natural and objective, thus bias and preference and affirmative action to address past discriminations to women should be seen as furthering equality. Lorber describes the "bathroom problem" to articulate the inequality of overarching, gender-neutral laws.&lt;ref name="Newman, Jacquetta A. 2012"/&gt; She articulates how men's bathroom norms are used as the standard by which to determine how many and how large public bathrooms should be. For various reasons, however, women make more frequent use of the bathrooms than men, and as a result there are too few bathrooms for women, and sufficient amount for men. ). This tacit structural underpinning of male dominance is particularly dangerous for it creates the space for certain instances of female oppression to be viewed and experienced as the woman’s choice. For instance, a woman might choose not to pursue a job that is not compatible with her domestic obligations, while ignoring the structure of the patriarchal family in assigning those domestic roles to her, and furthermore the structuring of workplaces that tacitly stream out women that have this domestic duty in virtue of their strict required hours or inflexibility with days off, etc. As such, the fair treatment model of equality addresses the weaknesses of purely formal/de jure equality in addressing such tacit structural and systematic inequality for women.

==Efforts to fight inequality==
{{rewrite section|date=June 2013}}
{{see also|Gender inequality}}

World bodies have defined gender equality in terms of [[human rights]], especially [[women's rights]], and [[economic development]].&lt;ref name="Smart"&gt;{{cite journal |author=World Bank |title=Gender Equality as Smart Economics: A World Bank Group Gender Action Plan (Fiscal years 2007–10) |date=September 2006 |url=http://siteresources.worldbank.org/INTGENDER/Resources/GAPNov2.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="MDG3"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.endpoverty2015.org/goals/gender-equity |title=Goal #3 Gender Equity |accessdate=2008-06-01 |publisher=United Nations Millennium Campaign |year=2008 |author=United Nations Millennium Campaign}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[UNICEF]] describes that gender equality  "means that women and men, and girls and boys, enjoy the same rights, resources, opportunities and protections. It does not require that girls and boys, or women and men, be the same, or that they be treated exactly alike."&lt;ref name="UNICEF"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.unicef.org/gender/files/Overarching_2Pager_Web.pdf |title=Promoting Gender Equality: An Equity-based Approach to Programming |accessdate=2011-01-28 |publisher=UNICEF |date= |author=UNICEF}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[United Nations Population Fund]] has declared that men and women have a right to [[Social equality|equality]].&lt;ref name="UNFPA"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.unfpa.org/gender/ |title=Gender Equality: An End in Itself and a Cornerstone of Development |accessdate=2008-06-01 |publisher=United Nations Population Fund |date=February 2006 |author=UNFPA}}&lt;/ref&gt; "Gender equity" is one of the goals of the [[United Nations Millennium Project]], to end world [[poverty]] by 2015; the project claims, "Every single Goal is directly related to women's rights, and societies where women are not afforded equal rights as men can never achieve development in a [[Sustainability|sustainable]] manner."&lt;ref name="MDG3" /&gt;

Thus, promoting gender equality is seen as an encouragement to greater [[Prosperity|economic prosperity]].&lt;ref name="Smart" /&gt; For example, nations of the [[Arab world]] that deny equality of opportunity to women were warned in a 2008 [[United Nations]]-sponsored report that this disempowerment is a critical factor crippling these nations' return to the first rank of global leaders in commerce, [[Education|learning]] and [[culture]].&lt;ref name="ejoussour"&gt;[http://www.e-joussour.net/en/node/1511 Gender equality in Arab world critical for progress and prosperity, UN report warns], E-joussour (21 October 2008)&lt;/ref&gt;  That is, Western bodies are less likely to conduct commerce with nations in the Middle East that retain culturally accepted attitudes towards the status and function of women in their society in an effort to [[cultural globalization|force them to change their beliefs]] in the face of relatively underdeveloped economies.

In 2010, the [[European Union]] opened the [[European Institute for Gender Equality]] (EIGE) in [[Vilnius]], [[Lithuania]] to promote gender equality and to fight [[sex discrimination]].

Gender equality is part of the national curriculum in Great Britain and many other European countries.  [[Personal, Social and Health Education]], [[Religious education|religious studies]] and [[Language acquisition]] curricula tend to address gender equality issues as a very serious topic for discussion and analysis of its effect in society.

===Violence against women===
{{Main|Violence against women}}
[[Violence against women]] (in short VAW) is a technical term used to collectively refer to violent acts that are primarily or exclusively committed against women. This type of violence is gender-based, meaning that the acts of violence are committed against women expressly ''because'' they are women, or as a result of patriarchal gender constructs. The UN [[Declaration on the Elimination of Violence Against Women]] defines VAW as "''any act of gender-based violence that results in, or is likely to result in, physical, sexual or psychological harm or suffering to women, including threats of such acts, coercion or arbitrary deprivation of liberty, whether occurring in public or in private life''" and states that:&lt;ref&gt;http://www.un-documents.net/a48r104.htm&lt;/ref&gt;
:"violence against women is a manifestation of historically unequal power relations between men and women, which have led to domination over and discrimination against women by men and to the prevention of the full advancement of women, and that violence against women is one of the crucial social mechanisms by which women are forced into a subordinate position compared with men"

Forms of VAW include [[sexual violence]] (including [[war rape]], [[marital rape]] and [[child sexual abuse]], the latter often in the context of [[child marriage]]), [[domestic violence]], [[forced marriage]], [[female genital mutilation]], [[forced prostitution]], [[sex trafficking]], [[honor killing]]s, [[dowry killing]]s, [[acid attacks]], [[stoning]], [[flogging]], [[forced sterilization]], [[forced abortion]], violence related to accusations of [[witchcraft]], mistreatment of widows (e.g. [[widow inheritance]]).
Fighting against VAW is considered a key issues for achieving gender equality. The Council of Europe adopted the [[Convention on preventing and combating violence against women and domestic violence]] (Istanbul Convention).

===Reproductive and sexual health and rights===
{{Main|Reproductive health|Reproductive rights}}
{{Further|Forced sterilization|Forced pregnancy|Forced abortion}}
The importance of women having the right and possibility to have control over their body, reproduction decisions and sexuality, and the need for gender equality in order to achieve these goals are recognized as crucial by the [[Fourth World Conference on Women]] in Beijing and the UN [[International Conference on Population and Development]] Program of Action. The World Health Organization (WHO) has stated that promotion of gender equality is crucial in the fight against [[HIV/AIDS]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.who.int/gender/hiv_aids/en/&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Maternal mortality]] is a major problem in many parts of the world. [[UNFPA]] states that countries have an obligation to protect women's right to health, but many countries do not do that.&lt;ref name="unfpa.org"&gt;http://www.unfpa.org/webdav/site/global/shared/documents/publications/reducing_mm.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; Maternal mortality is considered today not just an issue
of development, but also an issue of [[human rights]].&lt;ref name="unfpa.org"/&gt; According to UNFPA:&lt;ref&gt;http://www.unfpa.org/public/publications/pid/4968&lt;/ref&gt;

:"Preventable maternal mortality occurs where there is a failure to give effect to the rights of women to health, equality and non-discrimination. Preventable maternal mortality also often represents a violation of a woman’s right to life."

The right to reproductive and sexual autonomy is denied to women in many parts of the world, through practices such as [[forced sterilization]], forced/coerced sexual partnering (eg [[forced marriage]], [[child marriage]]), criminalization of consensual sexual acts (such as [[sex outside marriage]]), lack of criminalization of [[marital rape]], violence in regard to the choice of partner ([[honor killings]] as punishment for 'inappropriate' relations). Amnesty International’s Secretary General has stated that: "It is unbelievable that in the twenty-first century some countries are condoning child marriage and marital rape while others are outlawing abortion, sex outside marriage and same-sex sexual activity – even punishable by death."&lt;ref&gt;https://www.amnesty.org/en/news/sexual-and-reproductive-rights-under-threat-worldwide-2014-03-06&lt;/ref&gt; All these practices infringe on the right of achieving reproductive and sexual health. High Commissioner for Human Rights [[Navi Pillay]] has called for full respect and recognition of women's autonomy and sexual and reproductive health rights, stating:&lt;ref&gt;http://www.chr.up.ac.za/images/files/news/news_2012/Navi%20Pillay%20Lecture%2015%20May%202012.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

:"Violations of women's human rights are often linked to their sexuality and reproductive role. Women are frequently treated as property, they are sold into marriage, into trafficking, into sexual slavery. Violence against women frequently takes the form of sexual violence. Victims of such violence are often accused of promiscuity and held responsible for their fate, while infertile women are rejected by husbands, families and communities. In many countries, married women may not refuse to have sexual relations with their husbands, and often have no say in whether they use contraception."

===Gendered arrangements of work and care===
Since the 1950s, social scientists as well as feminists have increasingly criticized gendered arrangements of work and care and the male breadwinner role. Policies are increasingly targeting men as fathers as a tool of changing gender relations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Bjørnholt | first1 = M. | authorlink1= Margunn Bjørnholt | last2 = | first2 = | year =2014 | title = Changing men, changing times; fathers and sons from an experimental gender equality study | url = http://www.margunnbjornholt.no/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/Changing-men-changing-times-fathers-and-sons-from-an-experimental-gender-equality-study.pdf | format = PDF | journal = [[The Sociological Review]] | volume = 62 | issue = 2  | pages = 295–315 | doi = 10.1111/1467-954X.12156 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Girls' access to education===
{{Main|Female education|Gender and education}}
In many parts of the world, girls' access to education is very restricted. Girls face many obstacles which prevent them to take part in education, including: early and forced marriages; early pregnancy; prejudice based on gender stereotypes at home, at school and in the community; violence on the way to school, or in and around schools; long distances to schools; vulnerability to the HIV epidemic; school fees, which often lead to parents sending only their sons to school; lack of gender sensitive approaches and materials in classrooms.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.teachers.org.uk/node/12978&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.campaignforeducationusa.org/obstacles-to-education-for-girls-and-women&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://plan-international.org/files/Africa/progress-and-obstacles-to-girls-education-in-africa&lt;/ref&gt; [[UNFPA]] states:&lt;ref&gt;http://www.unfpa.org/gender/empowerment2.htm&lt;/ref&gt;
:"Education is important for everyone, but it is especially significant for girls and women. This is true not only because education is an entry point to other opportunities, but also because the educational achievements of women can have ripple effects within the family and across generations. Investing in girls' education is one of the most effective ways to reduce poverty."

===Economic empowerment of women===
{{Main|Women in the workforce|Female economic activity}}
[[Female economic activity]] is a common measure of gender equality in an economy.
[[UN Women]] states that: "Investing in women’s economic empowerment sets a direct path towards gender equality, poverty eradication and inclusive economic growth."&lt;ref name="unwomen.org"&gt;http://www.unwomen.org/ru/what-we-do/economic-empowerment&lt;/ref&gt;

Gender discrimination often results in women ending in insecure, low-wage jobs, and being disproportionately affected by poverty, discrimination and exploitation.&lt;ref name="unwomen.org"/&gt;

===Marriage, divorce and property laws and regulations===
Equal rights for women in marriage, divorce, and property/land ownership and inheritance are essential for gender equality. CEDAW has called for the end of discriminatory [[family law]]s.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ohchr.org/EN/NewsEvents/Pages/Equalityinfamilyrelationsrecognizingwomensrightstoproperty.aspx&lt;/ref&gt; In 2013, UNWomen stated that "While at least 115 countries recognize equal land rights for women and men, effective implementation remains a major challenge".&lt;ref&gt;http://www.unwomen.org/lo/news/stories/2013/11/womens-land-rights-are-human-rights-says-new-un-report&lt;/ref&gt;

Laws regulating marriage and divorce continue to discriminate against women in many countries. For example, in [[Yemen]], marriage regulations state that a wife must obey her husband and must not leave home without his permission.&lt;ref&gt;http://www2.ohchr.org/english/bodies/hrc/docs/ngos/Yemen%27s%20darkside-discrimination_Yemen_HRC101.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Iraq]] husbands have a legal right to "punish" their wives. The criminal code states at Paragraph 41 that there is no crime if an act is committed while exercising a legal right; examples of legal rights include: "The punishment of a wife by her husband, the disciplining by parents and teachers of children under their authority within certain limits prescribed by law or by custom".&lt;ref&gt;http://law.case.edu/saddamtrial/documents/Iraqi_Penal_Code_1969.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; In the 1990s and the 21st century there has been progress in many countries in Africa: for instance in Namibia the [[marital power]] of the husband was abolished in 1996 by the Married Persons Equality Act; in Botswana it was abolished in 2004 by the Abolition of Marital Power Act; and in Lesotho it was abolished in 2006 by the Married Persons Equality Act.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.nyulawglobal.org/globalex/lesotho.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

Violence and mistreatment of women in relation to marriage has come to international attention during the past decades. This includes both violence committed inside marriage ([[domestic violence]]) as well as violence related to marriage customs and traditions (such as [[dowry]], [[bride price]], [[forced marriage]] and [[child marriage]]). Violence against a wife continues to be seen as legally acceptable in some countries; for instance in 2010, the United Arab Emirates's Supreme Court ruled that a man has the right to physically discipline his wife and children as long as he does not leave physical marks.&lt;ref&gt;http://edition.cnn.com/2010/WORLD/meast/10/19/uae.court.ruling/index.html?_s=PM:WORLD&lt;/ref&gt; The criminalization of [[adultery]] has been criticized as being a prohibition, which, in law or in practice, is used primarily against women; and incites violence against women ([[crimes of passion]], honor killings). A Joint Statement by the United Nations Working Group on discrimination against women in law and in practice in 2012 stated:&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ohchr.org/EN/NewsEvents/Pages/DisplayNews.aspx?NewsID=12672&amp;&lt;/ref&gt; "the United Nations Working Group on discrimination against women in law and in practice is deeply concerned at the criminalization and penalization of adultery whose enforcement leads to discrimination and violence against women." UN Women also stated that "Drafters should repeal any criminal offenses related to adultery or extramarital sex between consenting adults".&lt;ref&gt;http://www.endvawnow.org/en/articles/738-decriminalization-of-adultery-and-defenses.html%29&lt;/ref&gt;

===Investigation and prosecution of crimes against women and girls===
Human rights organizations have expressed concern about the legal [[impunity]] of perpetrators of crimes against women, with such crimes being often ignored by authorities.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ohchr.org/EN/NewsEvents/Pages/ImpunityForVAWGlobalConcern.aspx&lt;/ref&gt; This is especially the case with murders of women in [[Latin America]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www2.ohchr.org/english/bodies/cedaw/docs/ngos/CDDandCMDPDH_forthesession_Mexico_CEDAW52.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.unwomen.org/en/news/stories/2013/4/femicide-in-latin-america&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://cgrs.uchastings.edu/our-work/central-america-femicides-and-gender-based-violence&lt;/ref&gt; In particular, there is impunity in regard to [[domestic violence]]. High Commissioner for Human Rights, [[Navi Pillay]], has stated on domestic violence against women:&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ohchr.org/en/NewsEvents/Pages/DisplayNews.aspx?NewsID=9869&amp;LangID=E&lt;/ref&gt;

:"The reality for most victims, including victims of honor killings, is that state institutions fail them and that most perpetrators of domestic violence can rely on a culture of impunity for the acts they commit – acts which would often be considered as crimes, and be punished as such, if they were committed against strangers."

Women are often, in law or in practice, unable to access legal institutions. UNWomen has said that, "Too often, justice institutions, including the police and the courts, deny women justice".&lt;ref&gt;http://progress.unwomen.org/&lt;/ref&gt;

===Harmful Traditional Practices===
''Harmful traditional practices'' is a technical term referring to forms of violence which are committed primarily against women and girls in certain communities and societies, and have taken place for so long that they are considered, or presented by perpetrators, as part of accepted cultural practice, and justified as such.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.gbv.scot.nhs.uk/gbv/harmful-traditional-practices&lt;/ref&gt; They occur in an environment where women and girls have unequal rights and opportunities.&lt;ref name="ohchr.org"&gt;http://www.ohchr.org/Documents/Publications/FactSheet23en.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
These practices include, according to the [[Office of the United Nations High Commissioner for Human Rights]]:&lt;ref name="ohchr.org"/&gt;

:"female genital mutilation (FGM); forced feeding of women; early marriage; the various taboos or practices which prevent women from controlling their own fertility; nutritional taboos and traditional birth practices; son preference and its implications for the status of the girl child; female infanticide; early pregnancy; and dowry price"

Female genital mutilation is defined as "procedures that intentionally alter or cause injury to the female genital organs for non-medical reasons".&lt;ref name="who.int"&gt;http://www.who.int/mediacentre/factsheets/fs241/en/&lt;/ref&gt; The practice is concentrated in 29 countries in Africa and the Middle East, and it often has serious negative health consequences.&lt;ref name="who.int"/&gt;

Son preference refers to a cultural preference for sons over daughters, and manifests itself through practices such as sex selective abortion; female infanticide; or abandonment, neglect or abuse of girl-children.&lt;ref name="ohchr.org"/&gt;

Early marriage/child marriage is prevalent in parts of Asia and Africa. It can have harmful effects on a girl's education and development, and may expose the girl to social isolation or abuse.&lt;ref name="ohchr.org"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.unicef.org/protection/57929_58008.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.hrw.org/topic/womens-rights/child-marriage&lt;/ref&gt;

Abuses regarding nutrition are taboos in regard to certain foods, which result in poor nutrition of women, and may endanger their health, especially if pregnant.&lt;ref name="ohchr.org"/&gt;

Women's ability to control their fertility is often reduced. For instance, in northern Ghana, the payment of [[bride price]] signifies a woman's requirement to bear children, and women using birth control face threats, violence and reprisals.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.popcouncil.org/uploads/pdfs/councilarticles/sfp/SFP301Bawah.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
Births in parts of Africa are often attended by traditional birth attendants (TBAs), who sometimes perform rituals that are dangerous to the health of the mother. In many societies, a difficult labour is believed to be a divine punishment for marital infidelity, and such women face abuse and are pressured to "confess" to the infidelity.&lt;ref name="ohchr.org"/&gt;

Other harmful traditional practices include [[marriage by abduction]], ritualized [[sexual slavery]] ([[Devadasi]], [[Trokosi]]), [[breast ironing]], [[widow inheritance]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.krepublishers.com/02-Journals/T-Anth/Anth-13-0-000-11-Web/Anth-13-2-000-11-Abst-Pdf/Anth-13-2-121-11-720-Wadesango-N/Anth-13-2-121-11-720-Wadesango-N-Tt.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.un.org/womenwatch/daw/egm/elim-disc-viol-girlchild/ExpertPapers/EP.4%20%20%20Raswork.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ohchr.org/Documents/HRBodies/CEDAW/HarmfulPractices/GenderEmpowermentandDevelopment.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.kit.nl/net/KIT_Publicaties_output/ShowFile2.aspx?e=1415&lt;/ref&gt;

===Portrayal of women in the media===
{{Main|Exploitation of women in mass media}}
The way women are represented in the media has been criticized as interfering with the aim of achieving gender equality by perpetuating negative gender stereotypes. The [[exploitation of women in mass media]] refers to the criticisms that are levied  against the use or portrayal of women in the [[mass media]], when such use or portrayal aims at increasing the appeal of media or a product, to the detriment of, or without regard to, the interests of the women portrayed, or women in general. Concerns include the fact that the media has the power to shape the population's perceptions and to influence ideas, and therefore the sexist portrayals of women in the media may impact on how society sees and treats women in real life.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.coe.int/t/dghl/standardsetting/equality/03themes/women_media/Media%20and%20the%20Image%20of%20Women,%20Amsterdam%202013%20-%20Abridged%20Report.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
{{rewrite section|date=June 2013}}
{{portal|Gender studies}}

===General issues===
*[[Complementarianism]]
*[[Egalitarianism]]
*[[Feminism]]
*[[Gender inequality]]
*[[Gender mainstreaming]]
*[[Masculism]]
*[[Men's rights]]
*[[Right to equal protection]]
*[[Sex and gender distinction]]
*[[Sexism]]
*[[Women's rights]]

===Specific issues===
*[[Bahá'í Faith and gender equality]]
*[[Female economic activity]]
*[[Female education]]
*[[Gender Parity Index]] (in education)
*[[Gender polarization]]
*[[Gender sensitization]]
*[[Matriarchy]]
*[[Matriname]]
*[[Mixed-sex education]]
*[[Patriarchy]]
*Quaker [[Testimony of Equality]]
*[[Shared Earning/Shared Parenting Marriage]] (also known as [[Peer Marriage]])
*[[Women in Islam]]

===Laws===
*[[Anti-discrimination law]]
*[[Danish Act of Succession referendum, 2009]]
*[[Equal Pay Act of 1963]] (United States)
*[[Equality Act 2006]] (UK)
*[[Equality Act 2010]] (UK)
*[[European charter for equality of women and men in local life]]
*[[Gender Equality Duty in Scotland]]
*[[Gender Equity Education Act (Taiwan)]]
*[[Lilly Ledbetter Fair Pay Act]] (United States, 2009)
*[[List of gender equality lawsuits]]
*[[Paycheck Fairness Act]] (in the US)
*[[Title IX]] of the [[Education Amendments of 1972]] (United States)
*[[Uniform civil code]] (India)
*[[United Nations Security Council Resolution 1325]]
*[[Women's Petition to the National Assembly]] (France, 1789)

===Organizations and ministries===
*[[Afghan Ministry of Women Affairs]] (Afghanistan)
*[http://www.cedpa.org/ Center for Development and Population Activities (CEDPA)]
*[[Christians for Biblical Equality]]
*[[Committee on Women's Rights and Gender Equality]] (European Parliament)
*[[Equal Opportunities Commission]] (UK)
*[[Gender Empowerment Measure]], a metric used by the United Nations
*[[Gender-related Development Index]], a metric used by the United Nations
*[[Government Equalities Office]] (UK)
*[[International Center for Research on Women]]
*[http://www.societyforpeace.com/ International Society for Peace]
*[[Ministry of Integration and Gender Equality (Sweden)]]
*[[Ministry of Women, Family and Community Development (Malaysia)]]
*[[Philippine Commission on Women]] (Philippines)
*[[The Girl Effect]], an organization to help girls, worldwide, toward ending poverty

===Historical anecdotal reports===
* [[The New York Times#Discrimination in employment|New York Times]]

===Other related topics===
*''[[Global Gender Gap Report]]''
*[[International Men's Day]]
*[[Potty parity]]
*[[Women's Equality Day]]
*[[Illustrators for Gender Equality]]
* [[Gender apartheid]]

== References ==
{{reflist|30em}}

== External links ==
{{cleanup-rewrite|section|date=June 2013}}
* [http://www.unrol.org/article.aspx?article_id=28 United Nations Rule of Law: Gender Equality], on the relationship between gender equality, the [[rule of law]] and the [[United Nations]].
*[http://www.HillarysVillage.net HillarysVillage], Forum for women, minorities, members of the gay community and those who are otherwise marginalized.
*[http://uk.oneworld.net/guides/gender The OneWorld Guide to Gender Equality]
*[http://www.un.org/womenwatch WomenWatch], the United Nations Internet Gateway on Gender Equality and Empowerment of Women
*[http://www.undp.org/women/ Women's Empowerment], the United Nations Development Program's Gender Team
*[http://www.oecd.org/dac/gender GENDERNET], International forum of gender experts working in support of gender equality. Development Co-operation Directorate of the [[Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development]]
*[http://www.oecd.org/dev/gender Gender at the OECD Development Centre], gender activities at the OECD Development Centre
*[http://web.worldbank.org/WBSITE/EXTERNAL/TOPICS/EXTGENDER/0,,menuPK:336874~pagePK:149018~piPK:149093~theSitePK:336868,00.html Gender Equality as Smart Economics] World Bank
*[http://www.vineetnayar.com/women-leadership-yes-she-can, Women Leadership: Yes she can!]
*[http://www.thelocal.se/guides/equality/Equality+in+Sweden/ The Local] Gender equality in Sweden (news collection)
*[http://www.womencandoit.no Women Can Do It!]
*[http://www.return2workmums.co.uk Return2WorkMums For women returners to the workplace]
*[http://www.ihatesexism.com/ Sexism Discussion Group]
*[http://ccr.sagepub.com/content/33/3/265.abstract Sexual Equality and Romantic Love]
*[http://www.mdgmonitor.org/map.cfm?goal=&amp;indicator=&amp;cd= Gender Equality Tracker]
*[http://www.genderwork.ca/ Gender and Work Database]
*[http://www.gendersite.org/ Gender and the Built Environment Database]
*[http://www.witec-eu.net/  WiTEC – The European Association for Women in Science, Engineering and Technology (SET)]
*[http://www.gell.it/  Gender Equality in Labour &amp; Life – Online Course focus on PA (SET)]
*[http://transequality.org  National Center for Transgender Equality]
*[http://www.annette-boeckler.de/liturgie/EgalitarianServices.html Egalitarian Jewish Services A Discussion Paper]

{{Library resources box 
|by=no 
|onlinebooks=no 
|others=no 
|about=yes 
|label=Gender equality}}

{{Navboxes
|list =
{{Feminism}}
{{Masculism}}
{{Sexual identities}}
}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Gender Equality}}
[[Category:Gender equality| ]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>