<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20080911053247|237654413" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1271947" pageid="1271947" ns="0" title="First-wave feminism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2008-09-26T00:22:41Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[Image:Suffragette banner carried in picket of the White House.jpg|thumb|300px|Suffragette with banner, Washington DC, 1918]]
{{Feminism sidebar |expanded=Waves}}

'''First-wave feminism''' refers to a period of [[feminist]] activity during the [[nineteenth century|nineteenth]] and early [[twentieth century]] in the [[United Kingdom]] and the [[United States]]. It focused on ''[[de jure]]'' (officially mandated) inequalities, primarily on gaining [[women's suffrage]] (the right to vote). The term ''first wave'' was coined retroactively in the 1970s. The women's movement then, focusing as much on fighting ''[[de facto]]'' (unofficial) inequalities as ''de jure'' ones, acknowledged its foremothers by calling itself ''[[second-wave feminism]]''.

== United Kingdom ==
{{Expand|section|date=June 2008}}

[[Mary Wollstonecraft]] published the first feminist treatise, ''[[A Vindication of the Rights of Woman]]'' (1792), in which she advocated the social and moral equality of the sexes, extending the work of her 1790 pamphlet, ''[[A Vindication of the Rights of Man]]''. Her later unfinished work "Maria, or the Wrongs of Woman" earned her considerable criticism as she dared to acknowledge the existence of women's sexual desires, which was taboo in [[Georgian era|Georgian]] England.

Wollstonecraft is regarded as the [[Feminist history in the United Kingdom|grandmother of British feminism]] and her ideas shaped the thinking of the [[suffragette]]s, who campaigned for the women's vote. After generations of work, this was eventually granted − to some women in 1918, and equally with men in 1928.

== United States ==

''[[The Great Lawsuit|Woman in the Nineteenth Century]]'' by [[Margaret Fuller]] has been considered the first major feminist work in the United States and is often compared to Wollstonecraft's ''A Vindication of the Rights of Woman''.&lt;ref&gt;Slater, Abby. ''In Search of Margaret Fuller''. New York: Delacorte Press, 1978: 89–90. ISBN 0-440-03944-4&lt;/ref&gt; Prominent leaders of the feminist movement in the United States include [[Elizabeth Cady Stanton]] and [[Susan B. Anthony]], who campaigned for the [[abolition of slavery]] prior to championing women's right to vote. Anthony and other activists (such as [[Victoria Woodhull]] and [[Matilda Joslyn Gage]]) made attempts to cast votes prior to their legal entitlement to do so, for which many of them faced charges. Other important leaders include [[Lucy Stone]], [[Olympia Brown]], and [[Helen Pitts]].  

First-wave feminism involved a wide range of women, some belonging to [[conservative Christian]] groups (such as [[Frances Willard (suffragist)|Frances Willard]] and the [[Woman's Christian Temperance Union]]), others resembling the diversity and radicalism of much of [[second-wave feminism]] (such as [[Matilda Joslyn Gage]] and the [[National Woman Suffrage Association]]).

The end of this wave is often linked with the passage of the [[Nineteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution]] (1920), granting women the right to vote. This was a major victory of the movement, which also included reforms in [[higher education]], in the workplace and professions, and in healthcare.

== See also ==
* [[Second-wave feminism]]
* [[Third-wave feminism]]
* ''[[The Subjection of Women]]'' by [[John Stuart Mill]]
* [[Timeline of Womens Rights (other than voting)]]
* [[Oberlin College]], the first American college to regularly admit women.
* [[Seneca Falls Convention]]
* [[George Gissing]], The Odd Women; novel
* [[Lily Braun]]

== Notes ==
{{reflist}}

== Sources ==
* [http://www.historyguide.org/intellect/wollstonecraft.html Biography of Mary Wollstonecraft with links to works].
* ''[http://www.victoria-woodhull.com/ Woodhull &amp; Claflin's Weekly]''
* [http://www.class.csupomona.edu/his/skpuz/hst202/Woodhull/WQart.html Woodhull's attempt to run for President].

[[Category:Feminists|1]]
[[Category:Feminism and history]]
[[Category:Women's rights|1]]
[[Category:Women]]

[[et:Esimese laine feminism]]
[[el:Φεμινισμός πρώτου κύματος]]
[[nl:Eerste feministische golf]]
[[sh:Feminizam prvog vala]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>