<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20131114054828|581588481" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1271947" pageid="1271947" ns="0" title="First-wave feminism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2013-11-14T19:59:35Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Feminism sidebar |History}}

'''First-wave feminism''' refers to a period of [[feminist]] activity during the 19th and early twentieth century throughout the world, particularly in the [[United Kingdom]], [[Canada]], the [[Netherlands]] and the [[United States]]. It focused on ''[[de jure]]'' (officially mandated) inequalities, primarily on gaining [[women's suffrage]] (the right to vote).

The term ''first-wave'' was coined in the 1970s.{{by whom|date=March 2013}} The women's movement of that time, with its focus on ''[[de facto]]'' (unofficial) inequalities, acknowledged its predecessors by calling itself ''[[second-wave feminism]]''.

==Origins==
{{Main|History of feminism|Protofeminism}}
According to Miriam Schneir, [[Simone de Beauvoir]] wrote that the first woman to "take up her pen in defense of her sex" was [[Christine de Pizan]] in the 15th century.&lt;ref name=Schneir-1994&gt;{{cite book|author=Schneir, Miram|title=Feminism: The Essential Historical Writings|year=1994|first=1972|publisher=Vintage Books|page=xiv|isbn=0-679-75381-8}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Heinrich Cornelius Agrippa]] and [[Modesta di Pozzo di Forzi]] worked in the 16th century.&lt;ref name=Schneir-1994 /&gt; [[Marie de Gournay|Marie Le Jars de Gournay]], [[Anne Bradstreet]] and [[François Poullain de la Barre]] wrote in the 17th.&lt;ref name=Schneir-1994 /&gt;

[[Mary Wollstonecraft]] published one of the first feminist treatises, ''[[A Vindication of the Rights of Woman]]'' (1792), in which she advocated the social and moral equality of the sexes, extending the work of her 1790 pamphlet, ''[[A Vindication of the Rights of Men]]''. Her later unfinished novel, ''[[Maria: or, The Wrongs of Woman|Maria, or the Wrongs of Woman]]'', earned her considerable criticism as she discussed women's sexual desires. She died young, and her widower, the philosopher [[William Godwin]], quickly wrote a memoir of her that, contrary to his intentions, destroyed her reputation for generations.

Wollstonecraft is regarded as the [[Feminist history in the United Kingdom|grandmother of British feminism]] and her ideas shaped the thinking of the [[suffragette]]s, who campaigned for the women's vote. After generations of work, this was eventually granted − to some women in 1918, and equally with men in 1928.

[[File:8marta.jpg|thumb|upright|right|A 1932 Soviet poster for [[International Women's Day]].]]

[[File:Louise Weiss.jpg|thumb|right|[[Louise Weiss]] along with other Parisian suffragettes in 1935. The newspaper headline reads, in translation, "THE FRENCHWOMAN MUST VOTE".]]

== United Kingdom ==

In 1918 [[Marie Stopes]], who believed in equality in marriage and the importance of women's sexual desire, published ''[[Married Love]]'',&lt;ref name="google2004"&gt;{{cite book|author=Stopes, Marie Carmichael and McKibbin, Ross (ed.)|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=M13Q0aymFJoC|title=Married love|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=0-19-280432-4|year=2004|first=1918}}&lt;/ref&gt; a sex manual that, according to a survey of American academics in 1935, was one of the 25 most influential books of the previous 50 years, ahead of ''[[Special relativity|Relativity]]'' by [[Albert Einstein]] and ''[[The Interpretation of Dreams]]'' by [[Sigmund Freud]].&lt;ref name="autogenerated811"&gt;{{cite journal|doi=10.1098/rstb.2005.1781|author=Short, R.V.|date=August 23, 2005|title=New ways of preventing HIV infection: thinking simply, simply thinking|journal=Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences|volume=361|issue=1469|pages=811–20|publisher=The Royal Society via PubMed (U.S. National Institutes of Health)|pmid=16627296|pmc=1609406}}&lt;/ref&gt; The right to vote was granted to some UK women in 1918, and equally with men in 1928.

===Early 20th century===

During the early 20th century, English women achieved civil equality, in theory. [[World War I]] saw more women go to work outside the home. In the beginning of the 20th century, women were limited to factory labor and domestic work. Women gained the right to sit in parliament, although it was only slowly that women were actually elected. Women started serving on school boards and local bodies, and numbers kept increasing after the war. This period also saw more women starting to become more educated. In 1910, "women were attending many leading medical schools, and in 1915 the American Medical Association began to admit women members."&lt;ref name="autogenerated1995"&gt;[http://www.wic.org/misc/history.htm, "Women's History in America"], Excerpted from Compton's Interactive Encyclopedia, 1995&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Representation of the People Act 1918]] had given women the right to vote if they were property holders and older than 29. In 1928, this was extended to all women over 21.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Phillips, Melanie |title=The Ascent of Woman: A History of the Suffragette Movement and the Ideas Behind It |year=2004 |publisher=Abacus |location=London |isbn=978-0-349-11660-0}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Sex Disqualification (removal) Act 1919 opened professions and the Civil Service to women, and marriage was no longer seen to stop women from working outside the home legally. A Matrimonial Causes Act in 1923 gave women the right to the same grounds for divorce as men. However, the recession which started in the 1920s meant unemployment rose, which women were the first to face. Many women served in the armed forces during the war. In World War II, around 300,000 American women served in the Navy and Army performing jobs such as secretaries, typists and nurses. Many feminist writers and women's rights activists argued that it was not equality to men which they needed but a recognition of what women need to fulfil their potential of their own natures, not only within the aspect of work but society and home life too. [[Virginia Woolf]] produced her essay ''[[A Room of One's Own]]'' based on the ideas of women as writers and characters in fiction. Woolf said that a woman must have money and a room of her own to be able to write. "[[New Zealand]] was the first country to grant women the right to vote at a national level, while [[Finland]], as well as some American states gave women voting rights at a state level before [[Australia]]n women obtained that right across the nation."&lt;ref name="autogenerated2"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.abc.net.au/ola/citizen/women/women-power.htm#3 |title=Women, Power and The Public Sphere |first=Anita |last=Seibert |first2=Dorota |last2=Roslaniec |publisher=Abc.net.au |date= |accessdate=2012-09-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== United States ==
[[Image:Suffragette banner carried in picket of the White House.jpg|thumb|Suffragist with banner, Washington DC, 1918]]
''[[The Great Lawsuit|Woman in the Nineteenth Century]]'' by [[Margaret Fuller]] has been considered the first major feminist work in the United States and is often compared to Wollstonecraft's ''A Vindication of the Rights of Woman''.&lt;ref&gt;Slater, Abby. ''In Search of Margaret Fuller''. New York: Delacorte Press, 1978: 89–90. ISBN 0-440-03944-4&lt;/ref&gt; Prominent leaders of the feminist movement in the United States include [[Lucretia Coffin Mott]], [[Elizabeth Cady Stanton]], [[Lucy Stone]], and [[Susan B. Anthony]];  Anthony and other activists such as [[Victoria Woodhull]] and [[Matilda Joslyn Gage]] made attempts to cast votes prior to their legal entitlement to do so, for which many of them faced charges. Other important leaders included several women who dissented against the law in order to have their voices heard,([[Grimké sisters|Sarah and Angelina Grimké]]), in addition to other activists such as [[Carrie Chapman Catt]], [[Alice Paul]], [[Sojourner Truth]], [[Ida B. Wells]], [[Margaret Sanger]] and [[Lucy Burns]].&lt;ref&gt;Dicker, 2008. pp. 28, 47–48.&lt;/ref&gt;

First-wave feminism involved a wide range of women, some belonging to [[Christian right|conservative Christian]] groups (such as [[Frances Willard (suffragist)|Frances Willard]] and the [[Woman's Christian Temperance Union]]), others such as [[Matilda Joslyn Gage]] of the [[National Woman Suffrage Association]] (NWSA) resembling the radicalism of much of [[second-wave feminism]]. The majority of first-wave feminists were more moderate and conservative than radical or revolutionary—like the members of the [[American Woman Suffrage Association]] (AWSA) they were willing to work within the political system and they understood the clout of joining with sympathetic men in power to promote the cause of suffrage. The limited membership of the NWSA was narrowly focused on gaining a federal amendment for women's suffrage, whereas the AWSA, with ten times as many members, worked to gain suffrage on a state-by-state level as a necessary precursor to federal suffrage. The NWSA had broad goals, hoping to achieve a more equal social role for women, but the AWSA was aware of the divisive nature of many of those goals and instead chose to focus solely on suffrage. The NWSA was known for having more publicly aggressive tactics (such as picketing and hunger strikes) whereas the AWSA used more traditional strategies like lobbying, delivering speeches, applying political pressure and gathering signatures for petitions.&lt;ref&gt;Dicker, 2008, pp. 40–43.&lt;/ref&gt;

The first wave of feminists, in contrast to the second wave, focused very little on the subjects of abortion, birth control, and overall reproductive rights of women. Though she never married, Anthony published her views about marriage, holding that a woman should be allowed to refuse sex with her husband; the American woman had no legal recourse at that time against [[Spousal rape|rape by her husband]].

In 1860, New York passed a revised Married Women's Property Act which gave women shared ownership of their children, allowing them to have a say in their children's wills, wages, and granting them the right to inherit property.&lt;ref name="Dicker, 2008, pp. 30, 38"&gt;Dicker, 2008, pp. 30, 38.&lt;/ref&gt; Further advances and setbacks were experienced in New York and other states, but with each new win the feminists were able to use it as an example to apply more leverage on unyielding legislative bodies. The end of the first wave is often linked with the passage of the [[Nineteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution]] (1920), granting women the right to vote. This was the major victory of the movement, which also included reforms in [[higher education]], in the workplace and professions, and in health care.

Different accounts of the involvement of African-American women in the Women's Suffrage Movement are given. In a 1974 interview, [[Alice Paul]] notes that a compromise was made between southern groups to have white women march first, then men, then African-American women.&lt;ref name="test"&gt;[http://memory.loc.gov/ammem/awhhtml/aw01e/aw01e.html The Library of Congress], 2001.&lt;/ref&gt;  In another account by the [[National Association for the Advancement of Colored People]] (NAACP), difficulties in segregating women resulted in African-American women marching with their respective States without hindrance.&lt;ref&gt;The Library of Congress, 2001.&lt;/ref&gt;  Among them was Ida B. Wells-Barnett, who marched with the Illinois delegation.

==Persia==
While in some distance in culture and language, the events of the [[Conference of Badasht]] presented progress on the concerns of first wave feminism. There is a synchronicity in time and a likeness in theme and events between Persia (later named Iran) and the United States between the conference at Badasht and the [[Seneca Falls Convention]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last = Miller | first =Bradford W. | title =Seneca Falls First Woman’s Rights Convention of 1848; The Sacred Rites of the Nation | journal =Journal of Bahá’í Studies | volume =8 | issue =3 | publisher =Association for Bahá’í Studies |year =1998 | language = |url =http://www.bahai-studies.ca/journal/files/jbs/8.3%20Miller.pdf | accessdate = 4–4–2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Penn | first =Michael L. | coauthors =Rahel Nardos | title =Overcoming violence against women and girls: the international campaign to eradicate a worldwide problem | publisher =Rowman &amp; Littlefield | edition =illustrated | year =2003 | pages =1–2 |url =http://books.google.com/books?id=yfpCY3PdpDoC | isbn = 978-0-7425-2500-9 }}&lt;/ref&gt; First the conference happened over three weeks from late June to mid-July 1848 and the Seneca Falls Convention happened in mid-July 1848. Both conferences had women ([[Tahirih]] and [[Elizabeth Cady Stanton]]) take strong stances on the role of women in the public arena that some attending reacted to harshly. And lastly leading men present ([[Quddús]] and [[Frederick Douglass]]) supported these calls during the meetings healing the breach. Some even see a parallel in the background discussions that are partially documented to arrange how things would be brought up and settled.

The conference of Badasht is considered by [[Bahá'ís]] as a signal moment that demonstrated that Islamic [[Sharia]] law had been abrogated&lt;ref name="holy"&gt;{{Cite book |title = Holy People of the World: A Cross-cultural Encyclopedia | editor-first = Phyllis G. |editor-last = Jestice | year = 2004 | publisher = ABC-CLIO | isbn = 1-57607-355-6| first = Moojan | last=Momen | first2=B. Todd | last2=Lawson | chapter = Tahirih | location = Santa Barbara, CA | ref = harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="maneck"&gt;{{cite web | url = http://bahai-library.com/maneck_women_bahai_faith | title = Religion and Women |last = Maneck | first = Susan | location = Albany | publisher = SUNY Press | year =  1994}}&lt;/ref&gt; as well as a key demonstration of the thrust of raising the social position of women.&lt;ref name="MM"&gt;{{cite journal | last =Momen | first = Moojan | title =The Social Basis of the Babi Upheavals in Iran (1848-53): A Preliminary Analysis |journal =International Journal of Middle East Studies | volume =15 |issue =2 | pages =157–183 | publisher =Cambridge University Press | date = May, 1983 | url =http://www.jstor.org/stable/162988  | jstor =162988  | accessdate = 2012-04-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although the unveiling led to accusations of immorality&lt;ref&gt;
* {{cite book | last =Rev. Wilson | first = Samuel G. | editor-last =Wilder | editor-first =Royal Gould | editor2-last =  Pierson|editor2-first =Delavan Leonard| editor3-last =Pierson | editor3-first =Arthur Tappan | editor4-last = Sherwood | editor4-first = James Manning | chapter =Bahaism and the Woman Question - II | chapterurl =http://books.google.com/books?id=nnEJAQAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PA915#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=true  | title =The Missionary review of the world | publisher =Funk &amp; Wagnalls | volume =37| year = 1914 | pages =915–919 | url =http://books.google.com/books?id=nnEJAQAAMAAJ }}

* {{cite book | last =Rev. Wilson | first = Samuel G.  | editor-last = Armstrong | editor-first =William Park | title =The Princeton Theological Review | chapter = The Bayan of the Bab | chapterurl =http://books.google.com/books?id=z_sLAAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA633#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=true|publisher =MacCalla &amp; Company Inc | volume =13 | year = 1915 | pages = 633–654 | url =http://books.google.com/books?id=z_sLAAAAIAAJ}}

* {{cite book | last =Rev. Wilson | first = Samuel G.  | title =Bahaism and Its Claims: A Study of the Religion Promulgated by Baha Ullah and Abdul Baha | publisher =Fleming H. Revell co | year = 1915 | pages =171–172 | url =http://books.google.com/books?id=DHtLAAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA171#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=true }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="vaw"&gt;{{cite book | last = Milani| first = Farzaneh | title = Veils and words: the emerging voices of Iranian women writers | publisher = I.B.Tauris| series =Contemporary issues in the Middle East| edition = illustrated| year =1992 | pages = 295, esp. 3, 8, 27, 49, 53, 61, 63, 77–82, 90  | url = http://books.google.com/books?id=Z4Iqv2dDySwC&amp;lpg=PR9&amp;pg=PA8#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false| isbn = 978-1-85043-574-7}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[the Báb]] responded by supporting her position and naming her ''the Pure'' (Táhirih).&lt;ref name="PSmith"&gt;{{cite encyclopedia |last= Smith |first= Peter |encyclopedia= A concise encyclopedia of the Bahá'í Faith |title= Táhirih |year= 2000 |publisher=Oneworld Publications|location= Oxford |isbn= 1-85168-184-1 |pages= 332–333}}&lt;/ref&gt; Modern women scholars review this kind of accusation as part of a pattern faced by women leaders and writers then and since&lt;ref&gt;
* {{cite book | last = Milani| first = Farzaneh | title = Veils and words: the emerging voices of Iranian women writers | publisher = I.B.Tauris| series =Contemporary issues in the Middle East| edition = illustrated| year =1992 | pages = 295, esp. 3, 8, 27, 49, 53, 61, 63, 77–82, 90  | url = http://books.google.com/books?id=Z4Iqv2dDySwC&amp;lpg=PR9&amp;pg=PA8#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false| isbn = 978-1-85043-574-7}}

* {{cite journal| last = Nafisi | first = Azar | authorlink = Azar Nafisi | title = The Veiled Threat | journal = New Republic | volume = 220| issue = 8 | pages = 24–29| date = February, 1999 | language = | url = | accessdate = }} (at the time Azar Nafisi was a visiting professor at the Johns Hopkins University School of Advanced International Studies.)

* {{cite web | last =Mfon | first = Victoria | coauthors =Elizabeth Selander| title =Azar Nafisi: Voices from the Gaps
| work =Artist Pages| publisher = University of Minnesota| date =20–12–2006| url = http://voices.cla.umn.edu/artistpages/nafisiAzar.php|accessdate = 4–2–2012}}

* {{cite journal | last = Zahedi | first = Ashraf | title = Contested Meaning of the Veil and Political Ideologies of Iranian Regimes|journal = Journal of Middle East Women's Studies | volume = 3 | issue = 3 | pages = 75–98 | date = Fall, 2007 | url =http://www.jstor.org/pss/10.2979/MEW.2007.3.3.75| accessdate = 4–2–2012}}

* {{cite journal | last = Shahidian | first = Hammed | title = International trends: Islam, politics, and problems of writing women's history in Iran | journal = Journal of Women's History | volume = 7 | issue = 2 | pages = | date = Summer, 1995 | url = | accessdate =4–2–2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; in a way that [[Azar Nafisi]] says "…the Islamic regime today… fears them and feels vulnerable in the face of a resistance that is not just political but existential."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | last = Nafisi | first = Azar | authorlink = Azar Nafisi  | title = Iran's women: canaries in the coalmine; The battle for emancipation is part of a proud tradition that will shape the future of the regime and Islam itself| newspaper = The Times of London | page = 21 | date = November 27, 2010 | url =http://www.sais-jhu.edu/pressroom/pdf/nafisi_112810.pdf |accessdate = 4–2–2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
See the [[Bahá'í Faith and gender equality]].

== Australia ==
The first wave of Australian feminism, which dates back to the late nineteenth century, was chiefly concerned with suffrage (women's right to vote) and consequently with women's access to parliaments and other political activities.&lt;ref name="autogenerated2"/&gt;

[[Rose Scott]] is an excellent example. In 1882, Scott began to hold a weekly salon in her Sydney home left to her by her late mother. Through these meetings, she became well known amongst politicians, judges, philanthropists, writers and poets. In 1889, she helped to found the Women's Literary Society, which later grew into the Womanhood Suffrage League in 1891. Being left her mother's home, Rose hosted a salon there, leading politicians such as [[Bernhard Ringrose Wise]], [[William Holman]], [[William Morris Hughes]] and [[Thomas Bavin]] met and discussed the drafting of the bill that eventually became the Early Closing Act of 1899.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/legis/nsw/num_act/eca1899n38176.pdf |title=Early Closing Act 1899 No 38 |format=PDF |date= |accessdate=2012-09-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Tribute to the Suffragettes, close up.jpg|thumb|right|''Tribute to the Suffragettes'' memorial in [[Christchurch]], New Zealand. The figures shown from left to right are [[Amey Daldy]], [[Kate Sheppard]], [[Ada Wells]] and [[Harriet Morison]]]]

== New Zealand ==
Early New Zealand feminists and suffragettes included [[Maud Pember Reeves]] (Australian-born; later lived in London), [[Kate Sheppard]] and [[Mary Ann Müller]]. In 1893, [[Elizabeth Yates (mayor)|Elizabeth Yates]] became Mayor of [[Onehunga]], the first time such a post had been held by a female anywhere in the [[British Empire]]. Early university graduates were [[Emily Siedeberg]] (doctor, graduated 1895) and [[Ethel Benjamin]] (lawyer, graduated 1897). The Female Law Practitioners Act was passed in 1896 and Benjamin was admitted as a barrister and solicitor of the Supreme Court of New Zealand in 1897. See [[Women's suffrage in New Zealand]].

== Timeline of first-wave feminism worldwide ==

; 1809
* USA, Connecticut: Married women were allowed to execute wills.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://memory.loc.gov/ammem/awhhtml/awlaw3/property_law.html |title=Married Women's Property Laws:Law Library of Congress |publisher=Memory.loc.gov |date= |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
; 1810
* Sweden: The informal right of an unmarried woman to be declared of [[legal majority]] by royal dispensation was officially confirmed by parliament.&lt;ref&gt;Christine Bladh (Swedish): ''Månglerskor: att sälja från korg och bod i Stockholm 1819–1846'' (1991)&lt;/ref&gt;
; 1811
* Austria: Married women were granted separate economy and the right to choose their professions.&lt;ref name="Richard J Evans 1979"&gt;Richard J Evans (1979). Kvinnorörelsens historia i Europa, USA, Australien och Nya Zeeland 1840–1920 (The Feminists: Women's Emancipation Movements in Europe, America and Australasia, 1840–1920) Helsingborg: LiberFörlag Stockholm. ISBN 91-38-04920-1 (Swedish)&lt;/ref&gt;
* Sweden: Married businesswomen were granted the right to make decisions about their own affairs without their husband's consent.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.se/books?id=rfIfkhOcZ7QC&amp;pg=PA56&amp;dq=kvinnor+n%C3%A4ringslivet+1864&amp;hl=sv&amp;ei=4t_TTob4CZPZ4QSduYTeBg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=3&amp;ved=0CD4Q6AEwAg#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false |title=Mansdominans i förändring: om ledningsgrupper och styrelser : betänkande - Sverige Utredningen om kvinnor pĺ ledande poster i näringslivet - Google Böcker |publisher=Books.google.se |page=56 |isbn=9789138219539 |date= |accessdate=2012-09-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;
; 1821
* USA, Maine: Married women were allowed to own and manage property in their own name during the incapacity of their spouse.&lt;ref&gt;[http://mootmagazine.com/2012/08/16/woman-up/]{{dead link|date=October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
; 1827
* Brazil: The first elementary schools for girls and the profession of school teacher were opened.&lt;ref&gt;A companion to gender history by: Teresa A. Meade, Merry E. Wiesner-Hanks&lt;/ref&gt;
; 1829
* India: [[Sati (practice)|Sati]] was banned.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gktoday.in/abolition-of-sati-by-lord-william-bentinck/ |title=Abolition of Sati by Lord William Bentinck - Indian History - General Knowledge Today |publisher=Gktoday.in |date= |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Sweden: Midwives were allowed to use surgical instruments, which were unique in Europe at the time and gave them surgical status.&lt;ref&gt;{{sv icon}} Stig Hadenius, Torbjörn Nilsson &amp; Gunnar Åselius: ''Sveriges historia. Vad varje svensk bör veta'' (''History of Sweden'': "What every Swede should know")&lt;/ref&gt;
; 1832
* Brazil: Dionísia Gonçalves Pinto, under the pseudonym [[Nísia Floresta|Nísia Floresta Brasileira Augusta]], published her first book, and the first in Brazil to deal with women's intellectual equality and their capacity and right to be educated and participate in society on an equal basis with men, which was ''Women's rights and men's injustice''. &lt;ref&gt;http://books.google.com/books?id=2nl9p8SOH9gC&amp;pg=PA3&amp;lpg=PA3&amp;dq=nisia+floresta+1832&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=0p2UQx74LV&amp;sig=3YX3wtSbJh7KDvP2XQfGoSsh4do&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=p9daUo2VJomQkAft6YCIBg&amp;ved=0CHkQ6AEwDQ#v=onepage&amp;q=%22first%20feminist%22&amp;f=false&lt;/ref&gt; It was a translation of ''Woman not Inferior to Man'', often attributed to [[Mary Wortley Montagu]]. &lt;ref&gt;http://books.google.com/books?id=PtyD_4e8gVUC&amp;pg=PA29&amp;lpg=PA29&amp;dq=%22Maria+L%C3%BAcia+Garcia+Pallares-Burke+%22+nisia+floresta&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=GBzJaLgQYH&amp;sig=j7o4DN5bxQXjPj7vGCV0vUDfQD0&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=S9ZaUp_IEZCvkAfYsYCIAg&amp;ved=0CCgQ6AEwADgK#v=onepage&amp;q=%22Maria%20L%C3%BAcia%20Garcia%20Pallares-Burke%20%22%20nisia%20floresta&amp;f=false&lt;/ref&gt;  &lt;ref&gt;http://www.utexas.edu/cola/depts/anthropology/courses/25931&lt;/ref&gt;
; 1833
* USA, [[Ohio]]: The first [[co-educational]] American university, [[Oberlin College]], was founded.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www2.northcoast.org/member/oberlin |title=Oberlin College &amp;#124; NCAC: North Coast Athletic Conference |publisher=.northcoast.org |date= |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Guatemala: Divorce was legalized; this was rescinded in 1840 and reintroduced in 1894.&lt;ref name="autogenerated3"&gt;Women's Roles in Latin America and the Caribbean by Kathryn A. Sloan&lt;/ref&gt;
; 1835
* USA, Arkansas: Married women were allowed to own (but not control) property in their own name.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.encyclopediaofarkansas.net/encyclopedia/entry-detail.aspx?entryID=4745 |title=Arkansas Married Woman's Property Law |publisher=Encyclopedia of Arkansas |date=2011-11-18 |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Pitcairn Islands:  The [[Pitcairn Islands]] granted women the right to vote.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=JqCEF9P_O0EC&amp;pg=PT173&amp;lpg=PT173&amp;dq=1839+pitcairn+women+vote&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=u8wIpEj7Cf&amp;sig=C-uFXVLiRDv0RmCjasNvjGFJ0Hg&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=yvlmUKKyFerv0gGwjoHoCA&amp;ved=0CDAQ6AEwAw#v=onepage&amp;q=1839%20pitcairn%20women%20vote&amp;f=false |title=Yes Means Yes!: Visions of Female Sexual Power and A World Without Rape - Jaclyn Friedman, Jessica Valenti - Google Books |publisher=Books.google.com |date= |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
; 1838
* USA, Kentucky: Kentucky gave school suffrage (the right to vote at school meetings) to widows with children of school age.&lt;ref name="google7"&gt;{{cite web|url=https://docs.google.com/viewer?a=v&amp;q=cache:zop0OLgJmasJ:faculty.wcas.northwestern.edu/~mdo738/research/Doepke_Tertilt_Voena_1211.pdf+1844+maine+married+women+trade+license&amp;hl=en&amp;gl=us&amp;pid=bl&amp;srcid=ADGEESi1XhOMpToup3xsQkyHWb2bZq5vuE9M4m62gtjJJZzfpNup4goXO025pYR8s6jxVBBruyUKucddtmcGUuZ0_pyjc1grZguLsDb3VNeRc6HDvA3aARutK4Fcg1ERAH-YV8FYUvNh&amp;sig=AHIEtbTyu855NHZdjm8RJLEe9wv91m92tA |title=Powered by Google Docs |publisher=Docs.google.com |date= |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* USA, Iowa: Iowa was the ﬁrst U.S. state to allow sole custody of a child to its mother in the event of a divorce.&lt;ref name="google7"/&gt;
; 1839
* USA, Mississippi: Mississippi was the ﬁrst U.S. state that gave married women limited property rights.&lt;ref name="google7"/&gt;
* Great Britain: The [[Custody of Infants Act 1839]] made it possible for divorced mothers to be granted custody of their children under seven, but only if the Lord Chancellor agreed to it, and only if the mother was of good character.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.historyofwomen.org/custody.html |title=British Women's Emancipation since the Renaissance |publisher=Historyofwomen.org |date= |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* USA, [[Mississippi]]: The [[Married Women's Property Act 1839]] granted married women the right to own (but not control) property in their own name.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.se/books?id=3mK6xQMF2wQC&amp;pg=PA92&amp;lpg=PA92&amp;dq=Mississippi+Married+women+1839&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=zWcfbt4ppO&amp;sig=xY61RtDJTbMldNcFMhVE7xNeOos&amp;hl=sv&amp;ei=D1TTTsalBsre4QSslYAX&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=9&amp;ved=0CGQQ6AEwCDgK#v=onepage&amp;q=Mississippi%20Married%20women%201839&amp;f=false Janet L. Coryell: Negotiating boundaries of southern womanhood]&lt;/ref&gt;
; 1840
* USA, [[Texas]]: Married women were allowed to own property in their own name.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.se/books?id=3mK6xQMF2wQC&amp;pg=PA92&amp;lpg=PA92&amp;dq=Mississippi+Married+women+1839&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=zWcfbt4ppO&amp;sig=xY61RtDJTbMldNcFMhVE7xNeOos&amp;hl=sv&amp;ei=D1TTTsalBsre4QSslYAX&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=9&amp;ved=0CGQQ6AEwCDgK#v=onepage&amp;q=Mississippi%20Married%20women%201839&amp;f=false |title=Janet L. Coryell: Negotiating boundaries of southern womanhood |publisher=Books.google.se |page=92 |isbn=978-0-8262-1295-5 |date= |accessdate=2012-09-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;
; 1841
* Bulgaria: The first secular [[girls school]] in Bulgaria was opened, making education and the profession of teacher available for women.&lt;ref name="google1"&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.se/books?id=EFI7tr9XK6EC&amp;pg=PA189&amp;dq=feminist+history+serbia&amp;hl=sv&amp;ei=xjvQTuT_ItHS4QTkspBl&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=2&amp;ved=0CDQQ6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false |title=The Oxford encyclopedia of women in world history, Volym 1 Av Bonnie G. Smith |page=189 |isbn=978-0-19-514890-9 |publisher=Books.google.se |date=2008-01-23 |accessdate=2012-09-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;
; 1842
* Sweden: Compulsory [[elementary school]] for both sexes was introduced.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ub.gu.se/kvinn/portaler/kunskap/historik/ |title=Kampen om kunskapen av Christina Florin, professor i kvinnohistoria |publisher=Göteborgs universitetsbibliotek |date= |accessdate=2012-09-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;
; 1844
* USA, Maine: Maine was the ﬁrst U.S. state that passed a law to allow married women to own separate property in their own name (separate economy) in 1844.&lt;ref name="google8"&gt;{{cite web|url=https://docs.google.com/viewer?a=v&amp;q=cache:zop0OLgJmasJ:faculty.wcas.northwestern.edu/~mdo738/research/Doepke_Tertilt_Voena_1211.pdf+1844+maine+women+separate+economy&amp;hl=en&amp;gl=us&amp;pid=bl&amp;srcid=ADGEESi1XhOMpToup3xsQkyHWb2bZq5vuE9M4m62gtjJJZzfpNup4goXO025pYR8s6jxVBBruyUKucddtmcGUuZ0_pyjc1grZguLsDb3VNeRc6HDvA3aARutK4Fcg1ERAH-YV8FYUvNh&amp;sig=AHIEtbSa1jbWHdw8DrbXe1CSIg-8BnSaoQ |title=Powered by Google Docs |publisher=Docs.google.com |date= |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* USA, Maine: Maine passed Sole Trader Law which granted married women the ability to engage in business without the need for their husbands' consent.&lt;ref name="google7"/&gt;
* USA, Massachusetts: Married women were granted separate economy.&lt;ref name="spanalumni.academia.edu"&gt;{{cite web|last=Roberts |first=Evan |url=http://spanalumni.academia.edu/ERoberts/Papers/251656/Womens_Rights_and_Womens_Labor_Married_Womens_Property_Laws_and_Labor_Force_Participation_1860_1900 |title=Women's Rights and Women's Labor: Married Women's Property Laws and Labor Force Participation, 1860 1900 |publisher=Spanalumni.academia.edu |date=2006-09-16 |accessdate=2012-09-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;
; 1845
* Sweden: Equal [[inheritance]] for sons and daughters (in the absence of a [[Will (law)|will]]) became law.&lt;ref name="Lilla Focus Uppslagsbok 1979"&gt;Lilla Focus Uppslagsbok (Little Focus Encyclopedia) Focus Uppslagsböcker AB (1979) {{sv icon}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* USA, New York: Married women were granted patent rights.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=tsQnAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA2072&amp;lpg=PA2072&amp;dq=1845+married+women+patent+rights+new+york&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=n8A-0osZO3&amp;sig=GkLA0Pbh3lUXvoRzFHmXDmK-pqc&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=DQlnUPH8KeWA0AHzoYDwDQ&amp;ved=0CC0Q6AEwAg#v=onepage&amp;q=1845%20married%20women%20patent%20rights%20new%20york&amp;f=false |title=The revised statutes of the state of New York: together with all the other ... - New York (State) - Google Books |publisher=Books.google.com |date= |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
; 1846
* Sweden: Trade- and crafts works professions were opened to all unmarried women.&lt;ref name="ub.gu.se"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ub.gu.se/kvinn/portaler/arbete/artal/ |title=Viktiga årtal |publisher=Göteborgs universitetsbibliotek |date=2011-12-21 |accessdate=2012-09-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;
; 1847
* Costa Rica: The first high school for girls opened, and the profession of teacher was opened to women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.se/books?id=xl1rbaPN7mIC&amp;pg=PA36&amp;dq=women+history+costa+rica&amp;hl=sv&amp;ei=iALcTsyLK6eA4gS6rd2QDg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;sqi=2&amp;ved=0CDoQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false |title=Ilse Abshagen Leitinger: The Costa Rican women's movement: a reader |publisher=Books.google.se |isbn=978-0-8229-5543-6 |date= |accessdate=2012-09-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;
; 1848
* USA, State of New York: Married Women's Property Act grant married women separate economy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mccarter.org/Education/mrs-packard/html/MRS.%20PACKARD%20Married%20Women's%20Property%20Act%20Hyperlink.pdf |title=Married Woman's Property Act New York State (1848) |publisher=Mccarter.org |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* USA, on June 14–15, third-party presidential candidate [[Gerrit Smith]] made women's suffrage a plank in the [[Liberty Party (1840s)|Liberty Party]] [[Party platform|platform]].&lt;ref&gt;Wellman, Judith. [http://books.google.com/books?id=IV6rt59asF8C ''The Road to Seneca Falls''], p. 176. University of Illinois Press, 2004. ISBN 0-252-02904-6&lt;/ref&gt;
* Persia (now called Iran): The [[Conference of Badasht]] was held June–July.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://reference.bahai.org/en/t/nz/DB/db-35.html |title=Bahá'í Reference Library - The Dawn-Breakers: Nabíl’s Narrative of the Early Days of the Bahá’í Revelation, Pages 288-301 |publisher=Reference.bahai.org |date=2010-12-31 |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bahaiglossary.org/words/badasht |title=How to pronounce 'Badasht' - Baha'i Glossary, A Spoken Dictionary of Baha'i Words and Phrases |publisher=Bahaiglossary.org |date= |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* USA, State of New York:  A women's rights convention called the [[Seneca Falls Convention]] was held in July. It was the first American women's rights convention.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.npg.si.edu/col/seneca/senfalls1.htm |title=Seneca falls &amp;#124; National Portrait Gallery, Smithsonian Institution |publisher=Npg.si.edu |date= |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
; 1849
* USA: [[Elizabeth Blackwell]], born in England, became the first female medical doctor in American history.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.nlm.nih.gov/changingthefaceofmedicine/physicians/biography_35.html |title=Changing the Face of Medicine &amp;#124; Dr. Elizabeth Blackwell |publisher=Nlm.nih.gov |date= |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
; 1850
*  England: The first organized movement for English feminism was the [[Langham Place Circle]] of the 1850s, including among others [[Barbara Bodichon]] (née Leigh-Smith) and [[Bessie Rayner Parkes]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.oxforddnb.com/public/themes/93/93708.html |title=Oxford DNB theme: Langham Place group |publisher=Oxforddnb.com |date= |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; They also campaigned for improved female rights in employment, and education.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books/about/The_Langham_Place_Circle.html?id=8OBLLwEACAAJ ]{{dead link|date=October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Haiti: The first permanent school for girls was opened.&lt;ref name="haiticulture.ch"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.haiticulture.ch/Reperes_chronologiques.html |title=Femmes d'Haiti : Repères chronologiques |publisher=Haiticulture.ch |date= |accessdate=2012-09-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Iceland: Equal inheritance for men and women was required.&lt;ref name="helsinki.fi"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.helsinki.fi/science/xantippa/wle/wle14.html |title=SJFE : Women and Law in Europe: politics - women and politics in Scandinavia |publisher=Helsinki.fi |date= |accessdate=2012-09-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* USA, California: Married Women's Property Act granted married women separate economy.&lt;ref name="google3"&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.se/books?id=4cwioT5k0IgC&amp;pg=PA485&amp;dq=Massachusetts+1854+married+women+property+act&amp;hl=sv&amp;ei=RcnTTpzBFefi4QT7mKB8&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=6&amp;sqi=2&amp;ved=0CEYQ6AEwBQ#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false |title=History of the United States by Charles Austin Beard, Mary Ritter Beard |publisher=Books.google.se |page=485 |isbn=978-1-60620-216-6 |date= |accessdate=2012-09-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* USA, Wisconsin: The Married Women's Property Act granted married women separate economy.&lt;ref name="google3"/&gt;
* USA, Oregon: Unmarried women were allowed to own land.&lt;ref name="Richard J Evans 1979"/&gt;
* The feminist movement began in Denmark with the publication of the feminist book ''Clara Raphael, Tolv Breve'', meaning "Clara Raphael, Twelve Letters," by [[Mathilde Fibiger]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=tCBpiKsi7a0C&amp;pg=PA67&amp;lpg=PA67&amp;dq=clara+raphael+tolv+breve&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=RKYeoi7b0X&amp;sig=N486_BisgPQTZ3SEH6qH_Or501k&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=2RVnUOO1MYff0gG3wYGICA&amp;ved=0CCQQ6AEwAjgU#v=onepage&amp;q=clara%20raphael%20tolv%20breve&amp;f=false |title=Historical Dictionary of Scandinavian Literature And Theater - Jan Sjĺvik - Google Books |publisher=Books.google.com |date= |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="google9"&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=133bkwvienYC&amp;pg=PA49&amp;lpg=PA49&amp;dq=1857+denmark+trade+and+crafts+women&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=p0vy2AP1Rd&amp;sig=zorjnW-s1G-TBQCmdcQdZ9o6av8&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=Dw1nUMWvCaP30gHO7ICgBw&amp;ved=0CCoQ6AEwAg#v=onepage&amp;q=1857%20denmark%20trade%20and%20crafts%20women&amp;f=false |title=The Growth of Scandinavian Law - Lester B. Orfield - Google Books |publisher=Books.google.com |date=2002-05-30 |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
; 1851
* Guatemala: Full [[citizenship]] was granted to economically independent women, but this was rescinded in 1879.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.se/books?id=mVHA9YVC6GQC&amp;pg=PA281&amp;lpg=PA281&amp;dq=guatemala+women+citizen+1851&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=9zn2i4hoQa&amp;sig=p69KeTpCVV-f53s3WAxAymRQuoo&amp;hl=sv&amp;ei=82nTToqIEZTb4QSmmMQc&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=5&amp;sqi=2&amp;ved=0CEkQ6AEwBA#v=onepage&amp;q=guatemala%20women%20citizen%201851&amp;f=false |title=Sisterhood is global: the international women's movement anthology by Robin Morgan |publisher=Books.google.se |page=281 |isbn=978-1-55861-160-3 |date= |accessdate=2012-09-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Canada, New Brunswick : Married women were granted separate economy.&lt;ref name="google4"&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.se/books?id=AZyE1YVnydMC&amp;pg=PA40&amp;dq=canada+married+women+1859&amp;hl=sv&amp;ei=4dLTTpeVEeij4gTjzck_&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=9&amp;ved=0CGUQ6AEwCA#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false |title=Courtship, love, and marriage in nineteenth-century English Canada by W. Peter Ward |publisher=Books.google.se |date=1993-03-31 |page=40 |isbn=978-0-7735-1104-0 |accessdate=2012-09-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;
; 1852
* USA, New Jersey: Married women were granted separate economy.&lt;ref name="spanalumni.academia.edu"/&gt;
; 1853
* Colombia: Divorce was legalized; this was rescinded in 1856 and reintroduced in 1992.&lt;ref name="autogenerated3"/&gt;
* Sweden: The profession of teacher at public primary and elementary school was opened to both sexes.&lt;ref&gt;Inger Hultgren (Swedish): Kvinnors organisation och samhällets beslutsprocess (1982)&lt;/ref&gt;
; 1854
* Norway: Equal inheritance for men and women was required.&lt;ref name="Richard J Evans 1979"/&gt;
* USA, [[Massachusetts]]: Massachusetts granted married women separate economy.&lt;ref name="google3"/&gt;
* Chile: The first public elementary school for girls was opened.&lt;ref&gt;The Oxford encyclopedia of women in world history, Volym 1 by Bonnie G. Smith&lt;/ref&gt;
; 1855
* USA, Iowa: The [[University of Iowa]] became the first coeducational [[Public university|public]] or state university in the United States.&lt;ref name=Roch&gt;{{Citation | first = A.J. | last = May | title = University of Rochester History | url = http://www.lib.rochester.edu/index.cfm?PAGE=2319 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* USA, Michigan: Married women were granted separate economy.&lt;ref name="google1"/&gt;
; 1857
* Denmark: Legal majority was granted to unmarried women.&lt;ref name="Richard J Evans 1979"/&gt;
* Denmark: A new law established the right of unmarried women to earn their living in any craft or trade.&lt;ref name="google9"/&gt;
* UK: The [[Matrimonial Causes Act 1857]] enabled couples to obtain a divorce through civil proceedings.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/familyhistory/bloodlines/familysecrets.shtml?entry=matrimonial_causes_act&amp;theme=familysecrets |title=Family History Research Timeline: Family Secrets |publisher=BBC |date=1970-01-01 |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.womenpriests.org/historic/18divorce.asp |title=Divorce and Matrimonial Causes Act (UK): 1857 |publisher=Womenpriests.org |date= |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Netherlands: Elementary education was made compulsory for both girls and boys.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.se/books?id=6PAldcfPLOMC&amp;pg=PA67&amp;dq=women+rights+netherlands&amp;hl=sv&amp;ei=I_TjTsfLC-X54QTHmt2gBQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CC4Q6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false |title=The Modern Woman's Rights Movement - Kaethe Schirmacher - Google Böcker |publisher=Books.google.se |page=67 |isbn=978-1-4068-9616-9 |date= |accessdate=2012-09-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Spain: Elementary education was made compulsory for both girls and boys.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.se/books?id=JCccGd-1upgC&amp;pg=PA156&amp;dq=women+universities+spain+1882&amp;hl=sv&amp;ei=CQfVTvW1L-HO4QT7j_jZAQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;sqi=2&amp;ved=0CDEQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=women%20universities%20spain%201882&amp;f=false |title=The Educated Woman: Minds, Bodies, and Women's Higher Education in Britain ... - Katharin Rowold - Google Böcker |publisher=Books.google.se |date=2008-10-15 |isbn=978-0-415-20587-0 |accessdate=2012-09-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* USA, Maine: Married women were granted the right to control their own earnings.&lt;ref name="spanalumni.academia.edu"/&gt;
; 1858
* Russia: [[Gymnasium (school)|Gymnasiums]] for girls were opened.&lt;ref name="google2000"&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.se/books?id=VDBC0hupLqsC&amp;pg=PA35&amp;lpg=PA35&amp;dq=women+history+russia+1753&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=B50loPO3ju&amp;sig=Wbl3e_uzS0ygjD3S8XFGrF40fWQ&amp;hl=sv&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=mtP1TtzJHLD74QTs7sWNCA&amp;sqi=2&amp;ved=0CCgQ6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false |title=Barbara Alpern Engel: Women in Russia, 1700–2000 |publisher=Books.google.se |page=35 |isbn=978-0-521-00318-6 |date=2003-10-13 |accessdate=2012-09-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Sweden: Legal majority was granted to unmarried women if applied for; automatic legal majority was granted in 1863.&lt;ref name="Lilla Focus Uppslagsbok 1979"/&gt;
; 1859
* Canada West: Married women were granted separate economy.&lt;ref name="google4"/&gt;
* Denmark: The post of teacher at public school was opened to women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=dFJ9Ch8NSeYC&amp;pg=PA176&amp;lpg=PA177&amp;ots=dy00_5Lt-o&amp;dq=1859+denmark+teacher+public+school+women#v=onepage&amp;q=%22royal%20resolution%20of%204%22&amp;f=false |title=Women Educators: Employees of Schools in Western Countries - Google Boeken |publisher=Books.google.com |date= |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Russia: Women were allowed to audit university lectures, but this was retracted in 1863.&lt;ref name="google2000"/&gt;
* Sweden: The posts of college teacher and lower official at public institutions were opened to women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Sidansvarig: KvinnSam |url=http://www.ub.gu.se/kvinn/artal/ |title=Årtalslistor |publisher=Göteborgs universitetsbibliotek |date= |accessdate=2012-09-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* USA, Kansas: The Married Women's Property Act granted married women separate economy.&lt;ref name="google3"/&gt;
; 1860
* USA, New York: New York passed a revised Married Women's Property Act which gave women shared ownership of their children, allowing them to have a say in their children's wills, wages, and granting them the right to inherit property.&lt;ref name="Dicker, 2008, pp. 30, 38"/&gt;
; 1861
* South Australia: South Australia granted property-owning women the right to vote in local elections.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://docs.google.com/viewer?a=v&amp;q=cache:DXMQ_7gAwNIJ:www.parliament.sa.gov.au/education/teachers/Documents/Women's%2520Petition%2520Photograph.pdf+south+australia+local+elections+womenvote&amp;hl=en&amp;gl=us&amp;pid=bl&amp;srcid=ADGEESi1mxaSuObTpRruzOkkQAREDCQfpDtbas_oQtxWs_VlwPivv_5TBC2_acDEqRJ8sbkLZ6pZNWlMnq_aBcKaT3ksnanV9elgPvscl_MpBDGcbF0yxM_0RP1BcpMDm6_vGj3QU5fE&amp;sig=AHIEtbRALA9ELTvNUAOJ1P3dSv3ei1yVDQ |title=Powered by Google Docs |publisher=Docs.google.com |date= |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* USA, Kansas: Kansas gave school suffrage to all women. Many U.S. states followed before the start of the 20th century.&lt;ref name="google7"/&gt;
; 1862
* Sweden: Restricted local suffrage was granted to women in Sweden. In 1919 suffrage was granted with restrictions, and in 1921 all restrictions were lifted.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.db-decision.de/CoRe/Sweden.htm |title=European Database: Women in Decision-making &amp;#124; Country Report Sweden |publisher=Db-decision.de |date=1919-05-24 |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
; 1863
* Finland: In 1863, taxpaying women were granted municipal suffrage in the country side, and in 1872, the same reform was given to the cities.&lt;ref name="google10"&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=e00JAQAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PA41&amp;lpg=PA41&amp;dq=finland+women+vote+municipal+1863&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=NzYUatA1rZ&amp;sig=FtuKu3dUaIZrNtWP87QIet-h8NM&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=ixJnUNySC83F0AHK0YDwCw&amp;ved=0CDIQ6AEwAw#v=onepage&amp;q=finland%20women%20vote%20municipal%201863&amp;f=false |title=Woman suffrage: history, arguments and results - Google Books |publisher=Books.google.com |date= |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
; 1869
* United Kingdom: The UK granted women the right to vote in local elections.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/pathways/citizenship/brave_new_world/women.htm |title=Exhibitions &amp;#124; Citizenship &amp;#124; Brave new world |publisher=The National Archives |date= |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* USA, Wyoming: Wyoming granted women the right to vote, the first US state to do so.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.history.com/this-day-in-history/wyoming-grants-women-the-vote |title=Wyoming grants women the vote — History.com This Day in History — 12/10/1869 |publisher=History.com |date=1929-12-12 |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
; 1870
* USA, Utah: The Utah territory granted women the right to vote, but it was revoked by Congress in 1887 as part of a national effort to rid the territory of polygamy. It was restored in 1895, when the right to vote and hold office was written into the constitution of the new state.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://historytogo.utah.gov/utah_chapters/statehood_and_the_progressive_era/womenssuffrageinutah.html |title=Women's Suffrage in Utah |publisher=Historytogo.utah.gov |date= |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* England: The [[Married Women's Property Act 1870|Married Women’s Property Act]] was passed in 1870 and expanded in 1874 and [[Married Women's Property Act 1882|1882]], giving English women control over their own earnings and property.&lt;ref name="google8"/&gt;
; 1872
* Finland: In 1872, taxpaying women were granted municipal suffrage in the cities.&lt;ref name="google10"/&gt;
; 1881
* Isle of Man: The right to vote was extended to unmarried women and widows who owned property, and as a result 700 women received the vote, comprising about 10% of the Manx electorate.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gov.im/mnh/heritage/museums/houseofkeys/socialchanges.xml |title=Social Changes - Isle of Man Government Manx National Heritage: |publisher=Gov.im |date= |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
; 1884
* Canada: Widows and spinsters were the first women granted the right to vote within municipalities in Ontario, with the other provinces following throughout the 1890s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://hera.minisisinc.com/ROW_IMAGES/Online%20Exhibits/Notice.pdf |title=Notice ! The Township of Woolwich fonds contains nomination and election notices from the period 1977 tp 1905 for representatives to the Township of Woolwich Council and Waterloo County Council |publisher=Hera.minisisinc.com |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
; 1886
* USA: All but six U.S. states allowed divorce on grounds of cruelty.&lt;ref name="google7"/&gt;
* Korea: [[Ewha Woman's University]], Korea’s first educational institute for women, was founded in 1886 by [[Mary F. Scranton]], an American missionary of the Methodist Episcopal Church.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://english.visitkorea.or.kr/enu/SI/SI_EN_3_1_1_1.jsp?cid=749914 |title=Official Site of Korea Tourism Org.: Ewha Womans University |publisher=English.visitkorea.or.kr |date= |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
; 1891
* Australia: The New South Wales Womanhood Suffrage League was founded.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=R5wBvA2mD6kC&amp;pg=PA246&amp;lpg=PA246&amp;dq=%22womanhood+suffrage+league%22+1891&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=qrEL1_QQ5R&amp;sig=cLSyjp11LYPuL3UL9iv237KVG0E&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=pBlnULPjOauw0QGQsoGoDw&amp;ved=0CDYQ6AEwBQ#v=onepage&amp;q=%22womanhood%20suffrage%20league%22%201891&amp;f=false |title=Woman Suffrage in Australia - Audrey Oldfield - Google Books |publisher=Books.google.com |date= |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
; 1893
* USA, Colorado: Colorado granted women the right to vote.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nps.gov/jeff/historyculture/the-virginia-minor-case.htm |title=Virginia Minor and Women's Right to Vote - Jefferson National Expansion Memorial |publisher=Nps.gov |date=2012-07-23 |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* New Zealand: New Zealand became the first self-governing country in the world in which all women had the right to vote in parliamentary elections.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nzhistory.net.nz/politics/womens-suffrage |title=New Zealand women and the vote &amp;#124; NZHistory, New Zealand history online |publisher=Nzhistory.net.nz |date=2012-10-04 |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Cook Islands: The Cook Islands granted women the right to vote in island councils and a federal parliament.&lt;ref name="nzhistory1"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nzhistory.net.nz/politics/womens-suffrage/world-suffrage-timeline |title=World suffrage timeline - women and the vote &amp;#124; NZHistory, New Zealand history online |publisher=Nzhistory.net.nz |date=2012-08-30 |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
; 1894
* South Australia: South Australia granted women the right to vote.&lt;ref name="nzhistory1"/&gt;
* United Kingdom: The United Kingdom extended the right to vote in local elections to married women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://docs.google.com/viewer?a=v&amp;q=cache:It_iY_MwXGEJ:www.theatreworksusa.org/uploads/studyguide/studyguide_969.pdf+&amp;hl=en&amp;gl=us&amp;pid=bl&amp;srcid=ADGEESgjkRqm1CxV1Wms0Ue-SwDqiW6uxIKG0dZl751R0a1lkfVd0e-15p1aSSvIp8-gsYUULCYX28kDjuITxRhHoRUC6NeFS1PKHHuGadwNSqScYCMO9pRjFMTjR_DN13DruSYAfu8S&amp;sig=AHIEtbQqQG_yJ7zNG9ouGx5eBDLWbpG59g |title=Powered by Google Docs |publisher=Docs.google.com |date= |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
; 1895
*USA: Almost all U.S. states had passed some form of Sole Trader Laws, Property Laws, and Earnings Laws, granting married women the right to trade without their husbands' consent, own and/or control their own property, and control their own earnings.&lt;ref name="google7"/&gt;
; 1896
* USA, Idaho: Idaho granted women the right to vote.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Hart |first=Arthur |url=http://www.idahostatesman.com/2006/01/24/12752/idaho-women-win-right-to-vote.html |title=01/24/2006: Idaho women win right to vote &amp;#124; Idaho History |publisher=Idahostatesman.com |date=2006-01-24 |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
; 1900
* Western Australia: Western Australia granted women the right to vote.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.womenshistory.com.au/timeline.asp |title=Australian Women's History: Timeline |publisher=Womenshistory.com.au |date= |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Belgium: Legal majority was granted to unmarried women.&lt;ref name="rosadoc.be"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rosadoc.be/site/rosa/english/pdf/factsheetsenglish/01.pdf |title=Milestones in the history of women in Belgium |publisher=Rosadoc.be |accessdate=2012-10-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Egypt: A school for female teachers was founded in Cairo.&lt;ref name="North Africa 1999"&gt;Women in the Middle East and North Africa: restoring women to history by Guity Nashat, Judith E. Tucker (1999)&lt;/ref&gt;
* France: Women were allowed to practice law.&lt;ref name="autogenerated4"&gt;Gender and crime in modern Europe by Margaret L. Arnot, Cornelie Usborne&lt;/ref&gt;
* Korea: The post office profession was opened to women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.se/books?id=QDWkn7Fj-b4C&amp;pg=PA102&amp;lpg=PA102&amp;dq=Yun+Ko-ra+western+clothes&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=fV_z_MM5zB&amp;sig=7nqyRX_Qr_9dTc7dpVz1C74_acY&amp;hl=sv&amp;ei=Vi3UTqGqDbL24QTu5K2hAQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;sqi=2&amp;ved=0CB8Q6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false |title=Gender and Modernity in Colonial Korea - Jennifer J. Jung-Kim - Google Böcker |publisher=Books.google.se |page=102 |isbn=978-0-549-71329-6 |date= |accessdate=2012-09-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Tunisia: The first public elementary school for girls was opened.&lt;ref name="North Africa 1999"/&gt;
* Japan: The first women's university was opened.&lt;ref&gt;Japanese women: new feminist perspectives on the past, present, and future AvKumiko Fujimura-Fanselow, Atsuko Kameda&lt;/ref&gt;
* Baden, Germany: Universities opened to women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.se/books?id=_SKPLZtwulQC&amp;pg=PA10&amp;lpg=PA10&amp;dq=switzerland+university+women+1865&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=jTTe4BGfIr&amp;sig=9tKXuJLYP5P-75TAt3Znu2lhWwI&amp;hl=sv&amp;ei=dOLTTtqjB4n_4QS-t4Ub&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;sqi=2&amp;ved=0CCUQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false |title=Gender and the Modern Research University: The Admission of Women to German ... - Patricia Mazon - Google Böcker |page=10 |isbn=978-0-8047-4641-0 |publisher=Books.google.se |date= |accessdate=2012-09-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Sweden: Maternity leave was granted for female industrial workers.
; 1901
* Bulgaria: Universities opened to women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.se/books?id=EFI7tr9XK6EC&amp;pg=PA189&amp;dq=feminist+history+serbia&amp;hl=sv&amp;ei=xjvQTuT_ItHS4QTkspBl&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=2&amp;ved=0CDQQ6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false |title=The Oxford encyclopedia of women in world history, by Bonnie G. Smith |publisher=Books.google.se |page=189 |isbn=978-0-19-514890-9 |date=2008-01-23 |accessdate=2012-09-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Cuba: Universities opened to women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.se/books?id=sXiTQpR3crwC&amp;pg=PA48&amp;dq=universities+women+mexico&amp;hl=sv&amp;ei=SADVTua0Iq7Y4QSa06mYAQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=3&amp;ved=0CEEQ6AEwAjge#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false |title=Latin American women and the search for social justice by Francesca Miller |page=48 |isbn=978-0-87451-558-9 |publisher=Books.google.se |date= |accessdate=2012-09-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Denmark: Maternity leave was granted for all women.&lt;ref name="kvinfo1"&gt;[http://www.kvinfo.dk/side/341"/]{{dead link|date=November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Sweden: The first Swedish law regarding parental leave was instituted in 1900. This law only affected women who worked as wage-earning factory workers and simply required that employers not allow women to work in the first four weeks after giving birth.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://docs.google.com/viewer?a=v&amp;q=cache:aq4cQ8XAa8UJ:www.espanet2010.net/en/378.file/p_A.Borchorst-L.Freidenvall_Gendering.pdf+&amp;hl=en&amp;gl=us&amp;pid=bl&amp;srcid=ADGEEShn_VpNKwEHNnTLu6WijW5NjCDE0OTNW4G5x0vI-8HQEp8z-Bqdya9qYurwfCrTWjOA2X9ntR6QZK9pXkaZqNw0bmTkIqVJb3SH3Wtv_IrVx9HmBehnHjHLj0Iw88z49p7S2J0y&amp;sig=AHIEtbS6nY_LWyvfg0MkAhTUGtChvGgMNA |title=Powered by Google Docs |publisher=Docs.google.com |date= |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Commonwealth of Australia: The First Parliament was not elected with a uniform franchise. The voting rights were based on existing franchise laws in each of the States. Thus, in South Australia and Western Australia women had the vote, in South Australia Aborigines (men and women) were entitled to vote and in Queensland and Western Australia Aborigines were explicitly denied voting rights.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aph.gov.au/About_Parliament/Parliamentary_Departments/Parliamentary_Library/pubs/rp/rp0001/01RP10 |title=The Parliament of the Commonwealth of Australia and Indigenous Peoples 1901-1967 – Parliament of Australia |publisher=Aph.gov.au |date= |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aph.gov.au/Visit_Parliament/About_the_Building/History_of_Parliament_House |title=History of Parliament House – Parliament of Australia |publisher=Aph.gov.au |date= |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
; 1902
* China: [[Foot binding]] was outlawed in 1902 by the imperial edicts of the [[Qing Dynasty]], the last dynasty in China, which ended in 1911.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bridgew.edu/soas/jiws/vol1/li.htm |title=Women's Movement and Change of Women's Status in China |author=Yuhui Li |publisher=Bridgew.edu |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* El Salvador: Married women were granted separate economy.&lt;ref name="googlecivil"&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.se/books?id=IgtwlsSHLToC&amp;pg=PA43&amp;dq=women+civil+code+argentina+1869&amp;hl=sv&amp;ei=lineToXNC4n34QTL6d2cBw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CC0Q6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false |title=Carmen Diana Deere, Magdalena León de Leal: Empowering women: land and property rights in Latin America |publisher=Books.google.se |page=43 |isbn=978-0-8229-5767-6 |date=2001-08-30 |accessdate=2012-09-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* El Salvador: Legal majority was granted to married women.&lt;ref name="googlecivil"/&gt;
* New South Wales: New South Wales granted women the right to vote in state elections.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.parliament.nsw.gov.au/prod/web/common.nsf/key/HistoryEarlyFederalPeriod |title=Parliament of NSW - 1901 to 1918 - The Early Federal Period and the First World War |publisher=Parliament.nsw.gov.au |date=2003-06-07 |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* England: A delegation of women textile workers from Northern England presented a petition to Parliament with 37,000 signatures demanding votes for women.&lt;ref name="autogenerated1900"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/radio4/womanshour/timeline/1900.shtml |title=BBC Radio 4 - Woman's Hour - Women's History Timeline: 1900 - 1909 |publisher=Bbc.co.uk |date= |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
; 1903
* Bavaria, Germany: Universities opened to women.&lt;ref name="google5"&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.se/books?id=_SKPLZtwulQC&amp;pg=PA10&amp;lpg=PA10&amp;dq=switzerland+university+women+1865&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=jTTe4BGfIr&amp;sig=9tKXuJLYP5P-75TAt3Znu2lhWwI&amp;hl=sv&amp;ei=dOLTTtqjB4n_4QS-t4Ub&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;sqi=2&amp;ved=0CCUQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false |title=Gender and the modern research university by Patricia M. Mazón |page=10 |isbn=978-0-8047-4641-0 |publisher=Books.google.se |date= |accessdate=2012-09-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Sweden: Public medical offices opened to women.&lt;ref name="autogenerated5"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ub.gu.se/kvinn/portaler/arbete/akademiker/ |title=Akademikeryrken |publisher=Göteborgs universitetsbibliotek |date=2010-11-17 |accessdate=2012-09-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Australia: Tasmania granted women the right to vote.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author= |url=http://www.utas.edu.au/library/exhibitions/clark/womens_suffrage.html |title=Andrew Inglis Clark _ women's suffrage_Library - University of Tasmania |publisher=Utas.edu.au |date= |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* England: The [[Women's Social and Political Union]] was founded.&lt;ref name="autogenerated1900"/&gt;
; 1904
* Nicaragua: Married women were granted separate economy.&lt;ref name="googlecivil"/&gt;
* Nicaragua: Legal majority was granted to married women.&lt;ref name="googlecivil"/&gt;
* Württemberg, Germany: Universities opened to women.&lt;ref name="google5"/&gt;
* England: The suffragette [[Dora Montefiore]] refused to pay her taxes because women could not vote.&lt;ref name="autogenerated1910"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/radio4/womanshour/timeline/1910.shtml |title=BBC Radio 4 - Woman's Hour - Women's History Timeline: 1910 - 1919 |publisher=Bbc.co.uk |date= |accessdate=2012-11-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;
; 1905
* Australia: Queensland granted women the right to vote.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.communities.qld.gov.au/women/leadership-and-community/centenary-of-suffrage |title=Centenary of suffrage - Community Services, Department of Communities, Child Safety and Disability Services (Queensland Government) |publisher=Communities.qld.gov.au |date=2005-03-08 |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Iceland: Educational institutions opened to women.&lt;ref name="Richard J Evans 1979"/&gt;
* Russia: Universities opened to women.&lt;ref name="Richard J Evans 1979"/&gt;
* England: On October 10, [[Christabel Pankhurst]] and [[Annie Kenney]] became the first women to be arrested in the fight for women's suffrage.&lt;ref name="autogenerated1910"/&gt;
; 1906
* Finland granted women the right vote.&lt;ref name="finlande1"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.finlande.nl/public/default.aspx?contentid=112162&amp;nodeid=35916&amp;contentlan=2&amp;culture=en-US |title=Finnish women won the right to vote a hundred years ago - Embassy of Finland, The Hague : Current Affairs |publisher=Finlande.nl |date= |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was the first country in Europe to do so.&lt;ref name="autogenerated6"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/radio4/womanshour/timeline/1900.shtml |title=BBC Radio 4 - Woman's Hour - Women's History Timeline: 1900 - 1909 |publisher=Bbc.co.uk |date= |accessdate=2012-11-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Honduras: Married women were granted separate economy.&lt;ref name="googlecivil"/&gt;
* Honduras: Legal majority was granted to married women.&lt;ref name="googlecivil"/&gt;
* Honduras: Divorce was legalized&lt;ref name="autogenerated3"/&gt;
* Korea: The profession of nurse was allowed for women.&lt;ref name="google6"&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.se/books?id=QDWkn7Fj-b4C&amp;pg=PA102&amp;lpg=PA102&amp;dq=Yun+Ko-ra+western+clothes&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=fV_z_MM5zB&amp;sig=7nqyRX_Qr_9dTc7dpVz1C74_acY&amp;hl=sv&amp;ei=Vi3UTqGqDbL24QTu5K2hAQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;sqi=2&amp;ved=0CB8Q6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false |title=Jennifer J. Jung-Kim: Gender and modernity in colonial Korea, University of California, Los Angeles |page=102 |isbn=978-0-549-71329-6 |publisher=Books.google.se |date= |accessdate=2012-09-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Nicaragua: Divorce was legalized.&lt;ref name="autogenerated3"/&gt;
* Sweden : Municipal suffrage, since 1862 granted to unmarried women, was granted to married women.&lt;ref name="runeberg.org"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://runeberg.org/nfbo/0225.html |title=417–418 (Nordisk familjebok / Uggleupplagan. 15. Kromat – Ledvätska) |publisher=Runeberg.org |date= |accessdate=2012-09-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Saxony, Germany: Universities opened to women.&lt;ref name="google5"/&gt;
* England: A delegation of women from both the [[Women's Social and Political Union]] and the [[National Union of Women's Suffrage Societies]] met with the Prime Minister, Sir [[Henry Campbell-Bannerman]].&lt;ref name="autogenerated1900"/&gt;
* England: The word suffragette, intended as an insult to women in the [[Women's Social and Political Union]], was used for the first time, by the Daily Mail.&lt;ref name="autogenerated6"/&gt;
* Britain: The [[National Federation of Women Workers]] was established by [[Mary Reid MacArthur]].&lt;ref name="autogenerated6"/&gt;
; 1907
* France: Married women were given control of their income.&lt;ref&gt;French women's writing, 1848–1994 by Diana Holmes&lt;/ref&gt;
* France: Women were allowed guardianship of children.&lt;ref name="autogenerated4"/&gt;
* Norway: Women were granted the right to stand for election, although this was subject to restrictions until 1913.&lt;ref name="autogenerated1997"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ipu.org/wmn-e/suffrage.htm |title=Women's Suffrage |publisher=Ipu.org |date=1997-05-23 |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Finland: The first female members of parliament in world history were elected in Finland in 1907.&lt;ref name="finlande1"/&gt;
* Uruguay: Divorce was legalized.&lt;ref&gt;Asunción Lavrín: Women, Feminism and Social Change in Argentina, Chile, and Uruguay, 1890–1940&lt;/ref&gt;
* England: The [[National Union of Women's Suffrage Societies]] organized its first national demonstration, which became known as the "[[Mud March (Suffragists)|Mud March]]" because of the terrible weather at the time.&lt;ref name="autogenerated6"/&gt;
* England: [[Emmeline Pethick-Lawrence]] and her husband Frederick launched the suffragette newspaper "Votes for Women". 
* England: The [[Women's Freedom League]] was formed when [[Charlotte Despard]] and others broke away from the [[Women's Social and Political Union]].&lt;ref name="autogenerated6"/&gt;
* England: The [[Qualification of Women Act 1907|Qualification of Women Act]] allowed women to be elected as mayors and to borough and city councils.&lt;ref name="autogenerated6"/&gt;
; 1908
* Belgium: Women were allowed to act as legal witnesses in court.&lt;ref name="Richard J Evans 1979"/&gt;
* Denmark: Unmarried women were made legal guardians of their children.&lt;ref name="kvinfo1"/&gt;
* Peru: Universities opened to women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.se/books?id=V-CKcuRAu8EC&amp;pg=PA64&amp;dq=women+universities+peru+1918&amp;hl=sv&amp;ei=pwLZTqrpJ4na4QT04YXXDQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;sqi=2&amp;ved=0CDQQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=women%20universities%20peru%201918&amp;f=false |title=Women's higher education in comparative perspective, by Gail Paradise Kelly,Sheila Slaughter |publisher=Books.google.se |page=64 |isbn=978-0-7923-0800-3 |date= |accessdate=2012-09-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Prussia, Alsace-Lorraine and Hesse, Germany: Universities opened to women.&lt;ref name="google5"/&gt;
* Denmark: Denmark granted women over 25 the right to vote in local elections.&lt;ref name="kvinfo2"&gt;{{cite web|last=Nielsen |first=Jytte |url=http://www.kvinfo.dk/side/680/article/2/ |title=KVINFO All About Gender - Women's History - How Danish women got the vote |publisher=Kvinfo.dk |date=1915-06-05 |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Australia: Victoria granted women the right to vote in state elections.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://australia.gov.au/about-australia/australian-story/austn-women-in-politics |title=Australian women in politics |publisher=australia.gov.au |date=2011-09-21 |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* England: On January 17, suffragettes chained themselves to the railings of [[10 Downing Street]].&lt;ref name="autogenerated6"/&gt; [[Emmeline Pankhurst]] was imprisoned for the first time.&lt;ref name="autogenerated6"/&gt; The [[Women's Social and Political Union]] also introduced their stone-throwing campaign.&lt;ref name="autogenerated6"/&gt;
; 1909
* Sweden: Women were granted eligibility to municipal councils.&lt;ref name="runeberg.org"/&gt;
* Sweden: The phrase "Swedish man" was removed from the application forms to public offices and women were thereby approved as applicants to most public professions.&lt;ref name="autogenerated5"/&gt;
* Mecklenburg, Germany: Universities opened to women.&lt;ref name="google5"/&gt;
* England: In July, [[Marion Wallace Dunlop]] became the first imprisoned suffragette to go on a hunger strike. As a result, force-feeding was introduced.&lt;ref name="autogenerated6"/&gt;
* Women were first elected to the procurer of the Bahá'í [[Local Spiritual Assembly]] of Chicago - the Bahai Temple Unity. Of the nine members elected by secret ballot three were women with Corinne True (later appointed as a [[Hand of the Cause]]) serving as an officer.&lt;ref name="wabf"&gt;{{Cite book| editor-last =  Sharma| editor-first = Arvind | last = Maneck| first = Susan | title = Religion and women | publisher =SUNY Press|year = 1994 | location = | pages = 211–228| chapter =Women in the Bahá'í Faith | chapterurl =http://books.google.com/books?id=2Oeq-yXuJrYC&amp;lpg=PA256&amp;pg=PA211#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false| url = http://books.google.com/?id=2Oeq-yXuJrYC| isbn = 978-0-7914-1689-1 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
; 1910
* Denmark: The Socialist International, meeting in Copenhagen, established a Women's Day, international in character, to honor the movement for women's rights and to assist in achieving universal suffrage for women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=CMS User |url=http://www.un.org/ecosocdev/geninfo/women/womday97.htm |title=International Women's Day |publisher=Un.org |date= |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* USA, Washington: Washington granted women the right to vote.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.secstate.wa.gov/elections/timeline/suffrage.htm |title=The History of Voting and Elections in Washington State |publisher=Secstate.wa.gov |date= |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Ecuador: Divorce was legalized.&lt;ref name="autogenerated3"/&gt;
* England: November 18 was "[[Black Friday (1910)|Black Friday]]", when the suffragettes and police clashed violently outside Parliament after the failure of the first [[Conciliation Bill]]. [[Ellen Pitfield]], one of the suffragettes, later died from her injuries.&lt;ref name="autogenerated1910"/&gt;
; 1911
* England: Dame [[Ethel Smyth]] composed "[[The March of the Women]]", the suffragette song.&lt;ref name="autogenerated1910"/&gt;
* Portugal: Legal majority was granted to married women (rescinded in 1933.)&lt;ref name="countrystudies.us"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://countrystudies.us/portugal/50.htm |title=Portugal - Women |publisher=Countrystudies.us |date= |accessdate=2012-09-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Portugal: Divorce was legalized.&lt;ref name="countrystudies.us"/&gt;
* USA, California: California granted women the right to vote.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.capradio.org/articles/2011/10/10/100-years-of-women's-right-to-vote-in-california |title=100 Years of Women's Right to Vote in California |publisher=capradio.org |date= |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Austria, Denmark, Germany and Switzerland: [[International Women's Day]] was marked for the first time in Austria, Denmark, Germany and Switzerland on the 19th of March. More than one million women and men attended IWD rallies campaigning for women's rights to work, vote, be trained, hold public office and be free from discrimination.&lt;ref name="internationalwomensday1918"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.internationalwomensday.com/about.asp |title=About International Women's Day 2012 - Glenda Stone re. Global IWD Arts |publisher=Internationalwomensday.com |date=1918-03-08 |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* South Africa: [[Olive Schreiner]] published [[Women and Labor]].&lt;ref name="autogenerated1910"/&gt;
; 1912
* USA, Oregon, Kansas, Arizona: Oregon, Kansas, and Arizona granted women the right to vote.&lt;ref name="constitutioncenter1"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://constitutioncenter.org/timeline/html/cw08_12159.html |title=National Constitution Center - Centuries of Citizenship - Map: States grant women the right to vote |publisher=Constitutioncenter.org |date=1919-01-01 |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* England: [[Sylvia Pankhurst]] established her [[East London Federation of Suffragettes]].&lt;ref name="autogenerated1910"/&gt;
* The all-male administrative bodies in the United States of the [[Bahá'í Faith]] were completely dissolved by [[`Abdu'l-Bahá]] during his [[`Abdu'l-Bahá's journeys to the West#Journey of `Abdu'l-Bahá to America|visit to America]] replacing them with integrated institutions.&lt;ref name="wabf"/&gt;
* Palestine: During the periods her brother was away in America, [[Bahíyyih Khánum]] was empowered as the acting head of the Bahá'í Faith, which was a rare position for a woman to be in at that time.&lt;ref name="PSmithBahiyyih"&gt;{{cite encyclopedia |last= Smith |first= Peter |encyclopedia= A concise encyclopedia of the Bahá'í Faith |title= Women |year= 2000 |publisher=Oneworld Publications |location= Oxford |isbn= 1-85168-184-1 |pages= 86–87}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Bramson"&gt;{{cite book | last = Bramson | first = Loni | year = 2004 | title = Holy People of the World: A Cross-cultural Encyclopedia | editor-first = Phyllis G. | editor-last = Jestice | publisher = ABC-CLIO | isbn= 1-57607-355-6 | chapter = Bahiyyih Khanum | place = Santa Barbara, CA | pages = 102–103}}&lt;/ref&gt;
; 1913
* Russia: In 1913 Russian women observed their first [[International Women's Day]] on the last Sunday in February. Following discussions, International Women's Day was transferred to 8 March and this day has remained the global date for International Women's Day ever since.&lt;ref name="internationalwomensday1918"/&gt;
* USA, Alaska: Alaska granted women the right to vote.&lt;ref name="constitutioncenter1"/&gt;
* Norway: Norway granted women the right to vote.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.db-decision.de/CoRe/Norway.htm |title=European Database: Women in Decision-making &amp;#124; Country Report Norway |publisher=Db-decision.de |date=1997-05-06 |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Japan: Public universities opened to women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.se/books?id=8UD158VM3nMC&amp;pg=PA469&amp;dq=japan+women+education+1874&amp;hl=sv&amp;ei=tjTVTpC6Es344QTglIG5AQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=9&amp;sqi=2&amp;ved=0CFsQ6AEwCA#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false |title=A companion to the anthropology of Japan by Jennifer Ellen Robertson |publisher=Books.google.se |isbn=978-1-4051-4145-1 |date= |accessdate=2012-09-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* England: The suffragette [[Emily Davison]] was killed by the King's horse at the [[Epsom Derby]].&lt;ref name="autogenerated1910"/&gt;
* England: 50,000 women taking part in a pilgramamge organized by the National Union of Women's Suffrage Societies arrived in [[Hyde Park, London|Hyde Park]] on July 26.&lt;ref name="autogenerated1910"/&gt;
; 1914
* Russia: Married women were allowed their own internal passport.&lt;ref name="google2000"/&gt;
* USA, Montana, Nevada: Montana and Nevada granted women the right to vote.&lt;ref name="constitutioncenter1"/&gt;
* England: The suffragette [[Mary Richardson]] entered the National Gallery and slashed the [[Rokeby Venus]].&lt;ref name="autogenerated1910"/&gt;
; 1915
* Denmark: Denmark granted women the right to vote.&lt;ref name="kvinfo2"/&gt;
* Iceland: Iceland granted women the right to vote,subject to conditions and restrictions.&lt;ref name="autogenerated1997"/&gt;
* USA: In 1915 the [[American Medical Association]] began to admit women as members.&lt;ref name="autogenerated1995"/&gt;
* Wales: The first Women's Institute in Britain was founded in North Wales at Llanfairpwll.&lt;ref name="autogenerated1910"/&gt;
; 1916
* Canada: Alberta, Manitoba and Saskatchewan granted women the right to vote.&lt;ref name="scholastic1"&gt;{{cite web|author=From Grolier |url=http://teacher.scholastic.com/activities/suffrage/history.htm |title=History of Women's Suffrage &amp;#124; Scholastic.com |publisher=Teacher.scholastic.com |date=1920-08-26 |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* USA: [[Margaret Sanger]] opened America's first birth control clinic in 1916.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://jwa.org/encyclopedia/article/birth-control-movement-in-united-states |title=Birth Control Movement in the United States &amp;#124; Jewish Women's Archive |publisher=Jwa.org |date= |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* England: The [[Cat and Mouse Act]] was introduced for suffragettes who refused to eat.&lt;ref name="autogenerated1910"/&gt;
; 1917
* Cuba: Married women were granted separate economy.&lt;ref name="googlecivil"/&gt;
* Cuba: Legal majority was granted to married women.&lt;ref name="googlecivil"/&gt;
* Netherlands: Women were granted the right to stand for election.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.iwdc.org/resources/suffrage.htm |title=International Women's Democracy Center: Women's Suffrage: A Timeline |publisher=Iwdc.org |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Mexico: Legal majority for married women.&lt;ref name="googlecivil"/&gt;
* Mexico: Divorce was legalized.&lt;ref name="googlecivil"/&gt;
* USA, New York: New York granted women the right to vote.&lt;ref name="constitutioncenter1"/&gt;
* Belarus: Belarus granted women the right to vote.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://un.by/en/publications/thema/belwomen/19-02-04-4.html |title=Belarusian Women as seen Through an Era |publisher=Un.by |date= |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Russia: The [[Russian SFSR]] granted women the right to vote.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Articles by Bernstein, L. |url=http://jsh.oxfordjournals.org/content/early/2011/09/29/jsh.shr063.extract |title=Equality &amp; Revolution: Women's Rights in the Russian Empire, 1905–1917. By Rochelle Goldberg Ruthchild (Pittsburgh: University of Pittsburgh Press, 2010. xviii plus 356 pp.) |publisher=Jsh.oxfordjournals.org |date= |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
; 1918
* Cuba: Divorce was legalized.&lt;ref name="autogenerated3"/&gt;
* Russia: The first Constitution of the new Soviet State (the Russian Socialist Federative Soviet Republic) declared that “women have equal rights to men.”&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://docs.google.com/viewer?a=v&amp;q=cache:NVfpqOJlVJQJ:apps.americanbar.org/rol/publications/russia-cedaw-eng.pdf+&amp;hl=en&amp;gl=us&amp;pid=bl&amp;srcid=ADGEESj2oV0y6Pwy29rYD8grlVrQFMOp9eWKc9zSyGyxVceV29Z9QeKWrzVhflxszl9yfWAgGH-cG-3v05Ov62Lnq9SiKUQurIZyyHGuH7Xq7nEcvVFtKtF6cN8OfSibULCbd4ynzgz4&amp;sig=AHIEtbTFCJi9G2xZLLXVQ2fOfFu61goluA |title=Powered by Google Docs |publisher=Docs.google.com |date= |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Thailand: Universities opened to women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.se/books?id=HzTHaIEduwYC&amp;pg=PA98&amp;dq=women+history+universities+Thailand&amp;hl=sv&amp;ei=tJrbTs3_JqX24QSh1PzVDQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=8&amp;sqi=2&amp;ved=0CGIQ6AEwBw#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false |title=Patit Paban Mishra: The history of Thailand |publisher=Books.google.se |page=98 |isbn=978-0-313-34091-8 |date=2010-08-19 |accessdate=2012-09-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* England: In 1918 [[Marie Stopes]], who believed in equality in marriage and the importance of women's sexual desire, published ''[[Married Love]]'',&lt;ref name="google2004"/&gt; a sex manual that, according to a survey of American academics in 1935, was one of the 25 most influential books of the previous 50 years, ahead of ''[[Special relativity|Relativity]]'' by [[Albert Einstein]] and ''[[The Interpretation of Dreams]]'' by [[Sigmund Freud]].&lt;ref name="autogenerated811"/&gt;
* USA, Michigan, South Dakota, Oklahoma: Michigan, South Dakota, and Oklahoma granted women the right to vote.&lt;ref name="constitutioncenter1"/&gt;
* Austria: Austria granted women the right to vote.&lt;ref name="scholastic1"/&gt;
* Canada: Canada granted women the right to vote on the federal level (the last province to enact women's suffrage was Quebec in 1940.)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.elections.ca/content.aspx?section=res&amp;dir=his&amp;document=chap2&amp;lang=e |title=Elections Canada Online &amp;#124; A History of the Vote in Canada |publisher=Elections.ca |date= |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* United Kingdom: The [[Representation of the People Act]] was passed which allowed women over the age of 30 who met a property qualification to vote. Although 8.5 million women met this criteria, it only represented 40 per cent of the total population of women in the UK. The same act extended the vote to all men over the age of 21.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.parliament.uk/about/living-heritage/transformingsociety/electionsvoting/womenvote/overview/thevote/ |title=Women get the vote - UK Parliament |publisher=Parliament.uk |date=2010-04-21 |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* United Kingdom: The [[Parliamentary Qualification of Women Act]] was passed allowing women to stand as Members of Parliament.&lt;ref name="autogenerated1910"/&gt;
* Czechoslovakia: Czechoslovakia granted women the right to vote.&lt;ref name="scholastic1"/&gt;
; 1919
* Germany: Germany granted women the right to vote.&lt;ref name="scholastic1"/&gt;
* Azerbaijan: Azerbaijan granted women the right to vote.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.today.az/news/vdiaspora/87899.html |title=History of Azerbaijani and US women’s rights to vote discussed at US Congress Library |publisher=Today.Az |date= |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Italy: Women gained more property rights, including control over their own earnings, and access to some legal positions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.keele.ac.uk/history/currentundergraduates/tltp/SUFFRAGE/DOCUMENT/FEMITALA.HTM |title=Š The Civil Code of 1865 and the Origins of the Feminist Movement in Italy |publisher=Keele.ac.uk |date= |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Great Britain: The [[Sex Disqualification (Removal) Act 1919]] became law. In a broad opening statement it specified that, “[a] person shall not be disqualified by sex or marriage from the exercise of any public function, or from being appointed to or holding any civil or judicial office or post, or from entering or assuming or carrying on any civil profession or vocation”. The Act did provide employment opportunities for individual women and many were appointed as magistrates, but in practice it fell far short of the expectations of the women’s movement. Senior positions in the civil service were still closed to women and they could be excluded from juries if evidence was likely to be too “sensitive”.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.historyextra.com/feature/women-first |title=Women first &amp;#124; BBC History Magazine |publisher=Historyextra.com |date= |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Luxembourg: Luxembourg granted women the right to vote.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.db-decision.de/CoRe/Luxembourg.htm |title=European Database: Women in Decision-making &amp;#124; Country Report Luxembourg |publisher=Db-decision.de |date= |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Canada: Women were granted the right to be candidates in federal elections.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.elections.ca/res/eim/article_search/article.asp?id=84&amp;lang=e&amp;frmPageSize= |title=Elections Canada On-Line &amp;#124; Electoral Insight |publisher=Elections.ca |date=2010-06-14 |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Netherlands: The Netherlands granted women the right to vote. The right to stand in election was granted in 1917.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.db-decision.de/CoRe/Netherlands.htm |title=European Database: Women in Decision-making &amp;#124; Country Report Netherlands |publisher=Db-decision.de |date= |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* New Zealand: New Zealand allowed women to stand for election into parliament.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=EC |url=http://www.elections.org.nz/study/education-centre/history/votes-for-women.html |title=Votes for Women &amp;#124; Elections New Zealand |publisher=Elections.org.nz |date=2005-04-13 |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* England: [[Nancy Astor]] became the first woman to take her seat in the [[House of Commons of the United Kingdom|House of Commons]].&lt;ref name="autogenerated1910"/&gt;
; 1920
* China: The first female students were accepted in [[Peking University]], soon followed by universities all over China.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.se/books?id=N0ths5DOgGgC&amp;pg=PA737&amp;lpg=PA737&amp;dq=china+beijing+woman+student+1920&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=bV7iSWWVfG&amp;sig=FblBiOG4MWmMdWuU9WuZFa0IJqk&amp;hl=sv&amp;ei=CpevS7muFsm4-QaZtfnmCg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=3&amp;ved=0CBMQ6AEwAg#v=onepage&amp;q=china%20beijing%20woman%20student%201920&amp;f=false |title=Routledge International Encyclopedia ... – Google Böcker |publisher=Books.google.se |page=737 |isbn=978-0-415-92088-9 |date= |accessdate=2012-09-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Haiti: The apothecary profession was opened to women.&lt;ref name="haiticulture.ch"/&gt;
* Korea: The profession of telephone operator, as well as several other professions, such as store clerks, were opened to women.&lt;ref name="google6"/&gt;
* Sweden: Legal majority was granted to married women and equal marriage rights were granted to women.&lt;ref name="Lilla Focus Uppslagsbok 1979"/&gt;
* USA: The 19th Amendment was signed into law, granting all American women the right to vote.&lt;ref name="google7"/&gt;
* England: [[Oxford University]] opened its degrees to women.&lt;ref name="autogenerated6"/&gt;
; 1921
* England: The [[Six Point Group]] was founded by [[Lady Rhondaa]] to push for women's social, political, occupational, moral, economic, and legal equality.&lt;ref name="autogenerated6"/&gt;
; 1922
* China: [[International Women's Day]] was celebrated in China from 1922 on.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Thursday, March 8, 2012 by Jessica Sager |url=http://www.gurl.com/2012/03/08/what-is-international-womens-day-2012/ |title=What Is International Women's Day 2012? Celebrate Women Today! |publisher=Gurl.com |date=2012-03-08 |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* United Kingdom: The [[Law of Property Act 1922]] was passed, giving wives the right to inherit property equally with their husbands.&lt;ref name="autogenerated6"/&gt;
* England: The Infanticide Act was passed, ending the death penalty for women who killed their children if the women's minds were found to be unbalanced.&lt;ref name="autogenerated6"/&gt;
; 1923
* Nicaragua: [[Elba Ochomogo]] became the first woman to obtain a university degree in Nicaragua.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.historia.fcs.ucr.ac.cr/articulos/esp-genero/2parte/CAP12Vicky.htm |title=Josefa Toledo De Aguerri: Her Life And Her Legacy |publisher=Historia.fcs.ucr.ac.cr |date= |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* England: The Matrimonial Causes Act gave women the right to petition for divorce on the grounds of adultery.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/radio4/womanshour/timeline/1920.shtml |title=BBC Radio 4 - Woman's Hour - Women's History Timeline: 1920 - 1929 |publisher=Bbc.co.uk |date= |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
; 1925
* UK: The Guardianship of Infants Act gave parents equal claims over their children.&lt;ref name="autogenerated6"/&gt;
; 1928
* UK: The right to vote was granted to all UK women equally with men in 1928.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bl.uk/learning/histcitizen/21cc/struggle/struggle.html |title=The struggle for democracy |publisher=Bl.uk |date=1928-07-02 |accessdate=2012-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Second-wave feminism]]
* [[Third-wave feminism]]
* ''[[The Subjection of Women]]'' by John Stuart Mill
* [[Timeline of women's rights (other than voting)]]
* [[Timeline of women's suffrage]]

==References==
;Notes
{{Reflist|30em}}
;Bibliography
{{refbegin}}
* Dicker, Rory Cooke. (2008) ''A History of U.S. Feminisms''. Berkeley: Seal Press. ISBN 1-58005-234-7
* Rupp, Leila J. (2011): [http://nbn-resolving.de/urn:nbn:de:0159-2011051243 Transnational Women's Movements], [[European History Online]], Mainz: [[Institute of European History]], retrieved: June 22, 2011.
* [http://www.historyguide.org/intellect/wollstonecraft.html Biography of Mary Wollstonecraft with links to works].
* ''[http://www.victoria-woodhull.com/ Woodhull &amp; Claflin's Weekly]''
* [http://www.class.csupomona.edu/his/skpuz/hst202/Woodhull/WQart.html Woodhull's attempt to run for President].
{{refend}}

{{Feminism}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:First-Wave Feminism}}
[[Category:Feminist movements and ideologies]]
[[Category:Feminism and history]]
[[Category:First-wave feminism| ]]
[[Category:History of women in the United States]]
[[Category:History of women's rights in the United States]]
[[Category:Women's rights]]

[[de:Feminismus#Erste Welle des Feminismus]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>