<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20051014230101|25541453" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1271947" pageid="1271947" ns="0" title="First-wave feminism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-10-14T23:13:21Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''First-wave feminism''' was the [[feminist]] movement in the [[nineteenth century]] and early [[twentieth century]], which primarily focused on gaining the right of women's [[suffrage]]. The term was not used during the time of the movement and was instead coined retroactively after the term ''[[second-wave feminism]]'' began to be used to describe a newer feminist movement.

Prominent leaders of the movement in the US included [[Elizabeth Cady Stanton]] and [[Susan B. Anthony]], who campaigned for the abolition of slavery prior to championing women's right to vote. Anthony and other activists (such as [[Victoria Woodhull]] and [[Matilda Joslyn Gage]]) made attempts to cast votes prior to their legal entitlement to do so, for which many of them faced charges. First-wave feminism involved a wide range of women, some conservative Christian groups (such as [[Frances Willard]] and the [[Womens Christian Temperance Union]]), others resembling the diversity and radicalism of much of [[second-wave feminism]] (such as [[Matilda Joslyn Gage]] and the [[National Woman Suffrage Association]]).

Both Stanton and Anthony believed that abortion was an imposition of the patriarchy upon women, that it robbed the unborn child of its life, and that if decisions about abortion were placed into the hands of women, it would happen far less often (or cease entirely).  Anthony believed abortion to be "child-murder", but did not believe that outlawing the practice would help women:&lt;blockquote&gt;Much as I deplore the horrible crime of child-murder, earnestly as I desire its suppression, I cannot believe that such a law would have the desired effect. It seems to me to be only mowing off the top of the noxious weed, while the root remains. We want prevention, not merely punishment. We must reach the root of the evil, and destroy it.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&amp;minus; Susan B. Anthony, ''The Revolution'', 1869.



In the [[United States]], the end of first-wave feminism may be regarded as the passage of the [[Nineteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution]], which was the major victory of the movement.

In the UK, [[Mary Wollstonecraft]] published the first feminist treatise ''A [[Vindication of the Rights of Women]]'', in which she advocated the social and moral equality of the sexes.  Her later unfinished work ''[[Maria, or the Wrongs of Women]]'' earned her considerable criticism as she dared to acknowledge the existance of women's sexual desires, almost certainly becoming the first published woman writer to do so.  Wollstonecraft is regarded as the grandmother of British feminism and her ideas shaped the thinking of the [[Suffragette]]s.  The Suffragettes campaigned for the women's vote, which was eventually granted &amp;minus; to some women in 1918 and to all in 1928 &amp;minus; as much because of the part played by British women during the [[World War I | First World War]], as of the efforts of the Suffragettes.

==See also==
* [[second-wave feminism]]
* [[third-wave feminism]]

[[Category:Feminism]]

[[el:Φεμινισμός πρώτου κύματος]]
[[nl:Eerste feministische golf]]

==Sources==
* http://www.historyguide.org/intellect/wollstonecraft.html, which includes links to the texts ''Vindication&amp;hellip;'' and ''Maria&amp;hellip;''.
* The ''Woodhull &amp; Claflin's Weekly'' archives at http://www.victoria-woodhull.com/
* http://www.class.csupomona.edu/his/skpuz/hst202/Woodhull/WQart.html, about Woodhull's attempt to run for President.




{{fem-stub}}</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>