<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20110719043047|440249359" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1271947" pageid="1271947" ns="0" title="First-wave feminism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2011-10-21T13:44:22Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Feminism sidebar |expanded=Waves}}

'''First-wave feminism''' refers to a period of [[feminist]] activity during the 19th and early twentieth century in the [[United Kingdom]], [[Canada]], and the [[United States]]. It focused on ''[[de jure]]'' (officially mandated) inequalities, primarily on gaining [[women's suffrage]] (the right to vote).

The term ''first-wave'' was [[retronym|coined retroactively]] in the 1970s. The women's movement then, focusing as much on fighting ''[[de facto]]'' (unofficial) inequalities as ''de jure'' ones, acknowledged its predecessors by calling itself ''[[second-wave feminism]]''.

==Origins==
{{Main|History of feminism|Protofeminism}}
According to Miriam Schneir, [[Simone de Beauvoir]] wrote that the first woman to "take up her pen in defense of her sex" was [[Christine de Pizan]] in the 15th century.&lt;ref name=Schneir-1994&gt;{{cite book|author=Schneir, Miram|title=Feminism: The Essential Historical Writings|year=1994|first=1972|publisher=Vintage Books|page=xiv|isbn=0-679-75381-8}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Heinrich Cornelius Agrippa]] and [[Modesta di Pozzo di Forzi]] worked in the 16th century.&lt;ref name=Schneir-1994 /&gt; [[Marie de Gournay|Marie Le Jars de Gournay]], [[Anne Bradstreet]] and [[François Poullain de la Barre]] wrote in the 17th.&lt;ref name=Schneir-1994 /&gt;

[[File:8marta.jpg|thumb|upright|right|A 1932 Soviet poster for [[International Women's Day]].]]

[[File:Louise Weiss.jpg|thumb|right|[[Louise Weiss]] along with other Parisian suffragettes in 1935. The newspaper headline reads, in translation, "THE FRENCHWOMAN MUST VOTE".]]

== United Kingdom ==

[[Mary Wollstonecraft]] published one of the first feminist treatises, ''[[A Vindication of the Rights of Woman]]'' (1792), in which she advocated the social and moral equality of the sexes, extending the work of her 1790 pamphlet, ''[[A Vindication of the Rights of Men]]''. Her later unfinished novel, ''[[Maria: or, The Wrongs of Woman|Maria, or the Wrongs of Woman]]'', earned her considerable criticism as she discussed women's sexual desires. She died young, and her widower, the philosopher [[William Godwin]], quickly wrote a memoir of her that, contrary to his intentions, destroyed her reputation for generations.

Wollstonecraft is regarded as the [[Feminist history in the United Kingdom|grandmother of British feminism]] and her ideas shaped the thinking of the [[suffragette]]s, who campaigned for the women's vote. After generations of work, this was eventually granted − to some women in 1918, and equally with men in 1928.

In 1918 [[Marie Stopes]], who believed in equality in marriage and the importance of women's sexual desire, published ''[[Married Love]]'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Stopes, Marie Carmichael and McKibbin, Ross (ed.)|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=M13Q0aymFJoC|title=Married love|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=0192804324|year=2004|first=1918}}&lt;/ref&gt; a sex manual that, according to a survey of American academics in 1935, was one of the 25 most influential books of the previous 50 years, ahead of ''[[Special relativity|Relativity]]'' by [[Albert Einstein]] and ''[[Interpretation of Dreams]]'' by [[Sigmund Freud]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|doi=10.1098/rstb.2005.1781|author=Short, R.V.|date=August 23, 2005|title=New ways of preventing HIV infection: thinking simply, simply thinking|journal=Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences|volume=361|issue=1469|pages=811–20|publisher=The Royal Society via PubMed (U.S. National Institutes of Health)|pmid=16627296|pmc=1609406}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Early 20th century===

During the early 20th century, English women achieved civil equality, in theory. [[World War I]] saw more women go to work outside the home. In the beginning of the 20th century, women were limited to factory labor and domestic work. Women gained the right to sit in parliament, although it was only slowly that women were actually elected. Women started serving on school boards and local bodies, and numbers kept increasing after the war. This period also saw more women starting to become more educated. In 1910, "women were attending many leading medical schools, and in 1915 the American Medical Association began to admit women members."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wic.org/misc/history.htm, "Women's History in America"], Excerpted from Compton's Interactive Encyclopedia, 1995&lt;/ref&gt; Bills such as the Women's Emancipation Bill passed which aided the women's movement. [[Representation of the People Act 1918]] had given women the right to vote if they were property holders and older than 29. In 1928, this was extended to all women over 21.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Phillips, Melanie |title=The Ascent of Woman: A History of the Suffragette Movement and the Ideas Behind It |year=2004 |publisher=Abacus |location=London |isbn=978-0-349-11660-0}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Sex Disqualification (removal) Act 1919 opened professions and the Civil Service to women, and marriage was no longer seen to legally stop women from working outside the home. A Matrimonial Causes Act in 1923 gave women the right to the same grounds for divorce as men. However, the recession which started in the 1920s meant unemployment rose, which women were the first to face. Many women served in the armed forces during the war. In World War II, around 300,000 American women served in the Navy and Army performing jobs such as secretaries, typists and nurses. Many feminist writers and women's rights activists argued that it was not equality to men which they needed but a recognition of what women need to fulfil their potential of their own natures, not only within the aspect of work but society and home life too. [[Virginia Woolf]] produced her essay ''[[A Room of One's Own]]'' based on the ideas of women as writers and characters in fiction. Woolf said that a woman must have money and a room of her own to be able to write.

== United States ==
[[Image:Suffragette banner carried in picket of the White House.jpg|thumb|Suffragist with banner, Washington DC, 1918]]
''[[The Great Lawsuit|Woman in the Nineteenth Century]]'' by [[Margaret Fuller]] has been considered the first major feminist work in the United States and is often compared to Wollstonecraft's ''A Vindication of the Rights of Woman''.&lt;ref&gt;Slater, Abby. ''In Search of Margaret Fuller''. New York: Delacorte Press, 1978: 89–90. ISBN 0-440-03944-4&lt;/ref&gt; Prominent leaders of the feminist movement in the United States include [[Lucretia Coffin Mott]], [[Elizabeth Cady Stanton]], [[Lucy Stone]], and [[Susan B. Anthony]];  Anthony and other activists such as [[Victoria Woodhull]] and [[Matilda Joslyn Gage]] made attempts to cast votes prior to their legal entitlement to do so, for which many of them faced charges. Other important leaders included several women who dissented against the law in order to have their voices heard,([[Grimké sisters|Sarah and Angelina Grimké]]), in addition to other activists such as [[Carrie Chapman Catt]], [[Alice Paul]], [[Sojourner Truth]], [[Ida B. Wells]], [[Margaret Sanger]] and [[Lucy Burns]].&lt;ref&gt;Dicker, 2008. pp. 28, 47–48.&lt;/ref&gt;

First-wave feminism involved a wide range of women, some belonging to [[conservative Christian]] groups (such as [[Frances Willard (suffragist)|Frances Willard]] and the [[Woman's Christian Temperance Union]]), others such as [[Matilda Joslyn Gage]] of the [[National Woman Suffrage Association]] (NWSA) resembling the radicalism of much of [[second-wave feminism]]. The majority of first-wave feminists were more moderate and conservative than radical or revolutionary—like the members of the [[American Woman Suffrage Association]] (AWSA) they were willing to work within the political system and they understood the clout of joining with sympathetic men in power to promote the cause of suffrage. The limited membership of the NWSA was narrowly focused on gaining a federal amendment for women's suffrage, whereas the AWSA, with ten times as many members, worked to gain suffrage on a state-by-state level as a necessary precursor to federal suffrage. The NWSA had broad goals, hoping to achieve a more equal social role for women, but the AWSA was aware of the divisive nature of many of those goals and instead chose to focus solely on suffrage. The NWSA was known for having more publicly aggressive tactics (such as picketing and hunger strikes) whereas the AWSA used more traditional strategies like lobbying, delivering speeches, applying political pressure and gathering signatures for petitions.&lt;ref&gt;Dicker, 2008, pp. 40–43.&lt;/ref&gt;

The first wave of feminists, in contrast to the second wave, focused very little on the subjects of abortion, birth control, and overall reproductive rights of women. Though she never married, Anthony published her views about marriage, holding that a woman should be allowed to refuse sex with her husband; the American woman had no legal recourse at that time against [[Spousal rape|rape by her husband]].

In 1860, New York passed a revised Married Women's Property Act which gave women shared ownership of their children, allowing them to have a say in their children's wills, wages, and granting them the right to inherit property.&lt;ref&gt;Dicker, 2008, pp. 30, 38.&lt;/ref&gt; Further advances and setbacks were experienced in New York and other states, but with each new win the feminists were able to use it as an example to apply more leverage on unyielding legislative bodies. The end of the first wave is often linked with the passage of the [[Nineteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution]] (1920), granting women the right to vote. This was the major victory of the movement, which also included reforms in [[higher education]], in the workplace and professions, and in health care.

Many white women excluded black women from their organizations and denied them the right to participate in events because they feared that the racist attitudes of Southern voters would affect their support of the women's movement. One notable instance of black exclusion was at a Washington parade in 1913, when activist Alice Paul did not allow the black feminist Ida Wells-Barnett to march with the other white women; instead, Paul told her that she could march at the back of the procession with the other black women. {{Citation needed|date=June 2010}}

== See also ==
* [[Second-wave feminism]]
* [[Third-wave feminism]]
* ''[[The Subjection of Women]]'' by John Stuart Mill
* [[Timeline of women's rights (other than voting)]]

==References==
;Notes
{{Reflist}}
;Bibliography
{{refbegin}}
* Dicker, Rory Cooke. (2008) ''A History of U.S. Feminisms''. Berkeley: Seal Press. ISBN 1580052347
* Rupp, Leila J. (2011): [http://nbn-resolving.de/urn:nbn:de:0159-2011051243 Transnational Women's Movements], [[European History Online]], Mainz: [[Institute of European History]], retrieved: June 22, 2011.
* [http://www.historyguide.org/intellect/wollstonecraft.html Biography of Mary Wollstonecraft with links to works].
* ''[http://www.victoria-woodhull.com/ Woodhull &amp; Claflin's Weekly]''
* [http://www.class.csupomona.edu/his/skpuz/hst202/Woodhull/WQart.html Woodhull's attempt to run for President].
{{refend}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:First-Wave Feminism}}
[[Category:Feminism and history]]
[[Category:Women's rights]]

[[de:Feminismus#Erste_Welle_des_Feminismus]]
[[et:Esimese laine feminism]]
[[el:Φεμινισμός πρώτου κύματος]]
[[es:Primera ola del feminismo]]
[[nl:Eerste feministische golf]]
[[pl:Feminizm pierwszej fali]]
[[sr:Феминизам првог таласа]]
[[sh:Feminizam prvog vala]]
[[ta:முதல் அலை பெண்ணியம்]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>