<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20201125211707|990671840" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="2002497" pageid="2002497" ns="0" title="Critical race theory"><revisions><rev timestamp="2020-11-27T02:40:47Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Theory analyzing society and culture's relation to race}}

{{Over coverage|date=September 2020}}

'''Critical race theory''' ('''CRT'''){{sfn|Delgado Bernal|2002}} is a [[theoretical framework]] in the [[social science]]s that examines society and culture as they relate to [[Race (human categorization)|categorizations of race]], [[law]], and [[power (social and political)|power.]]{{sfn|Yosso|2005}}&lt;ref name="habermas.org"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Gordon|first=Lewis R.|date=Spring 1999|title=A Short History of the 'Critical' in Critical Race Theory|url=http://www.apa.udel.edu/apa/archive/newsletters/v98n2/lawblack/gordon.asp|url-status=dead|journal=American Philosophy Association Newsletter|volume=98|issue=2|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20030502193950/http://www.apa.udel.edu/apa/archive/newsletters/v98n2/lawblack/gordon.asp|archivedate=2 May 2003}}&lt;/ref&gt; It began as a theoretical movement within American law schools in the mid- to late 1980s as a reworking of [[critical legal studies|critical legal theory]] on race issues{{sfn|Cole|2007}} – which itself was introducing new frameworks to the legal field, such as [[postmodernism]], [[queer theory]], and [[post-colonialism]]. As the word "critical" suggests, both theoretical fameworks are rooted in [[critical theory|Critical Theory]], a [[social philosophy]] which argues that [[social problems]] are influenced and created more by [[Social structure|societal structures]] and [[cultural assumptions]] than by individual and psychological factors. &lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Crenshaw|Gotanda|Peller|Thomas|1995|p=19 in "Introduction"}}: "Critical Race Theory thus represents an attempt to inhabit and expand the space between two very different intellectual and ideological formations…[i.e. Civil Rights reform and Critical Legal Studies]"&lt;/ref&gt;

It is loosely unified by two common themes: 

* Firstly, that [[White supremacy#Academic use of the term|white supremacy]] exists and exhibits power maintained over time, and, in particular, that the law plays a role in this process. 

* Secondly, that transforming the relationship between law and racial power, as well as achieving racial [[emancipation]] and [[Sex segregation#Anti-subordination|anti-subordination]] more broadly, are possible.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Critical Race Theory: The Key Writings that Formed the Movement|date=1996|publisher=[[The New Press]]|isbn=978-1-56584-271-7|editor-last1=Crenshaw|editor-first1=Kimberlé Williams|editor-link1=Kimberlé Williams Crenshaw|location=New York City|chapter=Introduction|editor-last2=Gotanda|editor-first2=Neil|editor-last3=Peller|editor-first3=Gary|editor-link3=Gary Peller|editor-last4=Thomas|editor-first4=Kendall|editor-link4=Kendall Thomas}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

By 2002, over 20 [[Law school in the United States|American law schools]], and at least 3 [[Law school|law schools]] in other countries, offered critical race theory courses or classes which covered the issue centrally.{{sfn|Harris|2002}} In addition to [[Law (academic)|law]], critical race theory is taught and innovated in the fields of [[Education Studies|education]], [[political science]], [[women's studies]], [[ethnic studies]], [[Communication studies|communication]], [[Sociology of race and ethnic relations|sociology]], and [[American studies]].{{sfn|Delgado|Stefancic|2012|pp=6–7}} Important scholars to the theory include [[Derrick Bell]], [[Patricia Williams]], [[Richard Delgado]], [[Kimberlé Williams Crenshaw]], [[Camara Phyllis Jones]], and [[Mari Matsuda]].

Critics, including [[Richard Posner]] and [[Alex Kozinski]], take issue with the theory's foundation in [[postmodernism]] and its reliance on [[moral relativism]], [[social constructionism]], and other tenets allegedly contrary to individual freedom and [[classical liberalism]].

==Definition==
According to the [[UCLA Luskin School of Public Affairs|UCLA School of Public Affairs]]:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://spacrs.wordpress.com/what-is-critical-race-theory/ |title=What Is Critical Race Theory? |accessdate=11 March 2012 |publisher=[[UCLA School of Public Affairs]]|date=November 4, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{quote|CRT recognizes that racism is engrained in the fabric and system of the American society. The individual racist need not exist to note that institutional racism is pervasive in the dominant culture. This is the analytical lens that CRT uses in examining existing power structures. CRT identifies that these power structures are based on white privilege and white supremacy, which perpetuates the marginalization of people of color.}}

Legal scholar Roy L. Brooks has defined CRT as "a collection of critical stances against the existing legal order from a race-based point of view", adding that:{{sfn|Brooks|1994|p=85}}

{{quote|[I]t focuses on the various ways in which the received tradition in law adversely affects people of color not as individuals but as a group. Thus, CRT attempts to analyze law and legal traditions through the history, contemporary experiences, and racial sensibilities of racial minorities in this country. The question always lurking in the background of CRT is this: What would the legal landscape look like today if people of color were the decision-makers?|author=|title=|source=}}

==Origins==
In the early 1980s, [[students of color]] at [[Harvard Law School]] organized protests in various forms to [[Problematization|problematize]] the lack of [[racial diversity]] in the [[curriculum]], as well as among students and faculty. These students supported Professor [[Derrick Bell]], who left Harvard Law in 1980 to become the dean at [[University of Oregon School of Law]]. During his time at Harvard, Bell had developed new courses that studied American law through a racial lens that students of color wanted faculty of color to teach in his absence. However, the university, ignoring student requests created a significant conflict with the administration. The conflict arose with a Harvard law course on race relations taught by the Director of the NAACP Legal Defense Fund (LDF) a well-respected, white civil rights attorney along with the nation’s leading black civil rights attorney who served as both President and Director of LDF. The boycott was based in part on Harvard’s failure to add minority faculty to its faculty. Harvard denied their request to have the course taught only by Black law professors. Legal scholar Randall Kennedy noted that some students felt affronted by using an “archetypal white liberal...in a way that precludes the development of black leadership”. (See “Racial Critiques of the Legal Academia”, Randall Kennedy, Harvard Law Review Vol 102:1745 at p. 1757). In response, numerous students, including [[Kimberlé Williams Crenshaw|Kimberlé Crenshaw]] and [[Mari Matsuda]], [[Boycott|boycotted]] and organized to develop an "Alternative Course" using Bell's ''Race, Racism, and American Law'' (1973, 1st edition) as a core text and included guest speakers [[Richard Delgado]] and Neil Gotanda.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite book|last=Gottesman|first=Isaac|title=The Critical Turn in Education: From Marxist Critique to Poststructuralist Feminism to Critical Theories of Race|publisher=[[Taylor &amp; Francis]]|location=London, England|year=2016|isbn=978-1317670957|pages=|chapter=Critical Race Theory and Legal Studies}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Crenshaw|Gotanda|Peller|Thomas|1995|pp=xix–xxvii}} 

The repeated refusals of Harvard Law to acknowledge the requests of students of color led to the self-declaration of critical race theory as an offshoot of critical legal studies in 1987. Crenshaw sent out a call to attend a retreat entitled "New Developments in Critical Race Theory" that effectively created the field under the name CRT. As Crenshaw states, only herself, Matsuda, Gotanda, Chuck Lawrence, and a handful of others knew "that there were no ''new'' developments in critical race theory, because CRT hadn't had any old ones{{snd}}it didn't exist, it was made up as a name. Sometimes you gotta fake it until you make it." Crenshaw states that critical race theorists had "discovered ourselves to be critical theorists who did race and racial justice advocates who did critical theory."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Presidential Session: Intersectionality and Critical Race Theory|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=elaIUgX-zZE|last1=Crenshaw|first1=Kimberlé|last2=Matsuda|first2=Mari|date=17 January 2020|website=YouTube|publisher=American Studies Association|url-status=live|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Crenshaw|Gotanda|Peller|Thomas|1995|pp=xix–xxvii}} Crenshaw writes, "one might say that CRT was the offspring of a post-civil rights institutional activism that was generated and informed by an oppositionalist orientation toward racial power."&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

==Theoretical positions==
In regard to CRT as being 'radical', Will Oremus argues:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine|last=Oremus|first=Will|title=Did Obama Hug a Radical?|url=http://www.slate.com/articles/news_and_politics/explainer/2012/03/derrick_bell_controversy_what_s_critical_race_theory_and_is_it_radical_.html|magazine=[[Slate (magazine)|Slate]]|date=March 9, 2012|access-date=September 18, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;[T]he theory [is] radical…in the sense that it questions fundamental assumptions.… And unlike some strands of academic and legal thought, critical race theory has an open and activist agenda, with an emphasis on storytelling and personal experience. It's about righting wrongs, not just questing after knowledge.… [M]any of their ideas are not radical today in the sense of being outside the mainstream: Critical race theory is widely taught and studied.&lt;/blockquote&gt;Recent developments in critical race theory include work relying on updated [[social psychology|social psychological]] research on [[unconscious bias]] in order to justify [[affirmative action]]; and work relying on law and [[economic methodology]] to examine [[structural inequality]] and [[employment discrimination|discrimination in the workplace]].{{sfnm |1a1=Carbado |1a2=Gulati |1y=2003 |2a1=Kang |2a2=Banaji |2y=2006}}

=== Influence of critical legal studies ===
As a movement that draws heavily from [[critical theory]], critical race theory shares many intellectual commitments with critical theory, [[critical legal studies]], [[feminist legal theory|feminist jurisprudence]], and [[postcolonial theory]]. However, some authors like [[Tommy Curry (professor)|Tommy J. Curry]] have pointed out that the [[epistemic]] convergences with such approaches are emphasized due to the [[Idealism|idealist]] turn in critical race theory. The latter, as Curry explains, is interested in [[discourse]] (i.e., how we speak about race) and the theories of white [[Continental philosophy|Continental philosophers]], over and against the structural and institutional accounts of [[White supremacy#Academic use of the term|white supremacy]] which were at the heart of the [[Realistic conflict theory|realist]] analysis of racism introduced in [[Derrick Bell]]'s early works,{{sfn|Curry|2012}}{{page needed|date=September 2016}} and articulated through such Black thinkers as [[W. E. B. Du Bois]], [[Paul Robeson]], and Judge [[Robert L. Carter]].{{sfn|Curry|2009}}{{page needed|date=September 2016}}

Critical race theory draws on the priorities and perspectives of both critical legal studies and conventional [[Civil and political rights|civil rights]] scholarship, while also sharply contesting both of these fields. CRT's theoretical elements are provided by a variety of sources. [[Angela P. Harris]] describes CRT as sharing "a commitment to a vision of liberation from racism through right reason" with the civil rights tradition.{{sfn|Harris|1994|pp=741–743}} It [[deconstruction|deconstructs]] some premises and arguments of [[legal theory]] and simultaneously holds that legally-constructed rights are incredibly important.{{sfnm |1a1=Crenshaw |1a2=Gotanda |1a3=Peller |1a4=Thomas |1y=1995 |1p=xxiv |1ps=: "To the emerging race crits, rights discourse held a social and transformative value in the context of racial subordination that transcended the narrower question of whether reliance on rights alone could bring about any determinate results" |2a1=Harris |2y=1994}}{{page needed|date=September 2016}} As described by [[Derrick Bell]], critical race theory in Harris' view is committed to "radical [[critique]] of the law (which is [[Normative legal thought|normatively]] [[Deconstruction|deconstructionist]]) and…radical emancipation by the law (which is normatively reconstructionist)."{{sfn|Bell|1995|p=899}}

=== Major themes ===
[[Richard Delgado]] and Jean Stefancic have documented the following major themes as characteristic of work in critical race theory:
*'''Critique of [[liberalism]]''': CRT scholars favor a more aggressive approach to [[social transformation]], as opposed to liberalism's more cautious approach;{{Citation needed|date=July 2020}} a [[Race-conscious policy|race-conscious]] approach to transformation rejecting liberal embrace of [[affirmative action]], [[color blindness (race)|color blindness]], [[Role model|role modeling]], or the [[Meritocracy|merit principle]];{{sfn|Delgado|Stefancic|1993|p=462}} and an approach that relies more on [[Political organisation|political organizing]], in contrast to liberalism's reliance on [[Rights-based approach to development|rights-based remedies]].{{Citation needed|date=July 2020}}
*'''[[Storytelling]]''', '''counter-storytelling''', and "'''naming one's own reality'''": The use of [[narrative]] to illuminate and [[Experiential learning|explore experiences]] of [[racial oppression]].{{sfn|Delgado|Stefancic|1993}} Bryan Brayboy has emphasized the [[Epistemology|epistemic]] importance of storytelling in [[Indigenous peoples of the Americas|Indigenous-American]] communities as superseding that of theory, and has proposed a '''Tribal Critical Race Theory''' (TribCrit).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Brayboy|first=Bryan McKinley Jones|date=December 2005|title=Toward a Tribal Critical Race Theory in Education|journal=The Urban Review|volume=37|issue=5|pages=425–446|doi=10.1007/s11256-005-0018-y|s2cid=145515195|issn=0042-0972}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''[[Historical revisionism|Revisionist]] interpretations''' of American [[civil rights]] [[law]] and progress: Criticism of civil-rights scholarship and [[anti-discrimination law]], such as ''[[Brown v. Board of Education]]''. [[Derrick Bell]], one of CRT's founders, argued that civil rights advances for black people coincided with the self-interest of white [[Elitism|elitists]]. Likewise, [[Mary L. Dudziak]] performed extensive [[archival research]] in the [[United States Department of State|U.S. Department of State]] and [[United States Department of Justice|Department of Justice]], including the correspondence by [[Ambassadors of the United States|U.S. ambassadors]] abroad,  and found that U.S. civil rights legislation was not passed because people of color were discriminated against. Rather, it was enacted in order to improve the image of the United States in the eyes of [[Third World|third-world countries]] that the US needed as allies during the [[Cold War]].{{sfnm |1a1=Delgado |1a2=Stefancic |1y=1993 |2a1=Delgado |2a2=Stefancic |2y=2012 |2pp=18–21 |3a1=Dudziak |3y=1993}}
*'''Applying insights''' from [[social science]] writing on race and [[racism]] to legal problems.{{sfn|Delgado|Stefancic|1993}}
*'''[[intersectionality|Intersectional]] theory''': The examination of race, sex, class, [[national origin]], and [[sexual orientation]], and how their combination plays out in various settings, e.g., how the needs of a Latina person are different from those of a black male person and whose needs are the ones promoted.{{sfnm |1a1=Delgado |1a2=Stefancic |1y=1993 |2a1=Delgado |2a2=Stefancic |2y=2012 |2pp=51–55}}
*'''[[Essentialism]] vs. anti-essentialism''': Delgado and Stefancic write, "Scholars who write about these issues are concerned with the appropriate unit for analysis: Is the black community one, or many, communities? Do middle- and working-class African-Americans have different interests and needs? Do All oppressed peoples have something in common?". This is a look at the ways that oppressed groups may share in their oppression but also have different needs and values that need to be looked at differently. It is a question of how groups can be essentialized or are unable to be essentialized{{sfnm |1a1=Delgado |1a2=Stefancic |1y=1993 |2a1=Delgado |2a2=Stefancic |2y=2017 |2pp=63–66}}
*'''Non-white cultural [[nationalism]]''' and '''[[separatism]]''' (incl. [[black nationalism]]): The exploration of more radical views that argue for separation and [[Reparations (transitional justice)|reparations]] as a form of [[foreign aid]].{{sfn|Delgado|Stefancic|1993}}
* Legal institutions, '''[[critical pedagogy]]''', and minority lawyers in the bar.{{sfn|Delgado|Stefancic|1993}}
*'''Structural [[determinism]]''': Exploration of how "the structure of legal thought or culture influences its content," whereby a particular mode of thought or widely shared practice determines significant social outcomes, usually occurring without conscious knowledge. As such, theorists posit that our system cannot redress certain kinds of wrongs.{{sfnm |1a1=Delgado |1a2=Stefancic |1y=1993 |2a1=Delgado |2a2=Stefancic |2y=2012 |2pp=26, 155}}
*'''[[White privilege]]''': Belief in the notion of a myriad of social advantages, benefits, and courtesies that come with being a member of the dominant race (i.e. white people). A clerk not following you around in a store or not having people cross the street at night to avoid you, are two examples of white privilege.{{sfn|Delgado|Stefancic|2012|pp=78–80}}
*'''[[Microaggression]]''': Belief in the notion that sudden, stunning, or dispiriting transactions have the power to mar the everyday of oppressed individuals. These include small acts of racism consciously or unconsciously perpetrated, whereby an analogy could be that of water dripping on a rock wearing away at it slowly. Microaggressions are based on the assumptions about racial matters that are absorbed from [[cultural heritage]].{{sfn|Delgado|Stefancic|2012|pp=1–2}}
*'''Empathetic fallacy''': Believing that one can change a narrative by offering an alternative narrative in hopes that the listener's empathy will quickly and reliably take over. Empathy is not enough to change racism as most people are not exposed to many people different from themselves and people mostly seek out information about their own culture and group.{{sfn|Delgado|Stefancic|2012|pp=27–29}}

=== Whiteness as property ===
From the CRT perspective, the white skin that some Americans possess is akin to owning a piece of property, in that it grants privileges to the owner that a renter (in this case, a person of color) would not be afforded.{{sfnm |1a1=Harris |1y=1993 |2a1=Ladson-Billings |2y=1999 |2p=15}} [[Cheryl Harris|Cheryl I. Harris]] and [[Gloria Ladson-Billings]] describe this notion of ''whiteness as property'', whereby [[Whiteness studies|whiteness]] is the ultimate property that whites alone can possess; valuable just like property. The property functions of whiteness{{snd}}i.e., rights to [[disposition]]; rights to use and enjoyment, [[reputation]], and status property; and the absolute [[Right to property|right to exclude]]{{snd}}make the [[American Dream|American dream]] more likely and attainable for whites.

=== Internalization ===
Karen Pyke documents the theoretical element of [[internalized racism]] or [[Internalized oppression|internalized racial oppression]], whereby victims of racism begin to believe in the ideology that they are inferior to whites and white culture, who are superior. The [[Internalization|internalizing]] of racism is not due to any weakness, ignorance, inferiority, psychological defect, gullibility, or other shortcomings of the oppressed. Instead, it is how authority and [[power (social and political)|power]] in all aspects of society contributes to feelings of inequality.{{sfn|Pyke|2010|p=552}}

=== Institutional racism ===
[[Camara Phyllis Jones]] defines [[institutionalized racism]] as the structures, policies, practices, and norms resulting in differential access to the goods, services, and opportunities of society by race. ''Institutionalized racism'' is [[normative]], sometimes [[Legalization (international law)|legalized]] and often manifests as inherited disadvantage. It is [[Structuralism|structural]], having been absorbed into our [[Institution|institutions]] of custom, practice, and law, so there need not be an identifiable offender. Indeed, ''institutionalized racism'' is often evident as inaction in the face of need, manifesting itself both in material conditions and in access to power. With regard to the former, examples include differential access to quality education, sound [[housing]], [[gainful employment]], appropriate medical facilities, and a clean environment.{{sfn|Jones|2002|pp=9–10}}

Solid Ground, an organization that works to combat poverty, describes ''institutionalized racism'' as the systematic distribution of resources, power
and opportunity in society to the benefit of people who are white and the exclusion of people of color. Institutional racism dates back to [[slavery]], [[Racial segregation|segregation]], [[Internment Camps|internment camps]], and [[Indian reservation|Indian reservations]]. Such form of racism can be present in institutions mainly designed to benefit and cater to the lives of whites, such as bank [[lending]] policies and different housing contracts, which both deny people of color from living in certain neighborhoods or areas. Many people of color are also [[Racial profiling|racially profiled]] by law enforcement, and many groups are misrepresented in [[News media|news]] and other media. There are also restrictions to certain types of employment, as well as advancements in the workplace, which are strictly based on one's race.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.racialequitytools.org/resourcefiles/institutionalracism.pdf|title=Definition &amp; Analysis of Institutional Racism|last=Ground|first=Solid|date=|website=|url-status=live|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Applications ==
Scholars in critical race theory have focused, with some particularity, on the issues of [[hate crime]] and [[hate speech]]. In response to the opinion of the [[US Supreme Court|U.S. Supreme Court]] in the hate speech case of ''[[R.A.V. v. City of St. Paul]]'' (1992), in which the Court struck down an anti-[[bias]] ordinance as applied to a teenager who had burned a cross, [[Mari Matsuda]] and Charles Lawrence argued that the Court had paid insufficient attention to the history of racist speech and the actual injury produced by such speech.&lt;ref&gt;[[Mari Matsuda|Matsuda, Mari J.]], and Charles R. Lawrence. 1993. "Epilogue: Burning Crosses and the R.A.V. Case." In ''Words That Wound: Critical Race Theory, Assaultive Speech and the First Amendment'', edited by M. J. Matsuda ''et al.''&lt;/ref&gt;

Critical race theorists have also paid particular attention to the issue of [[affirmative action]], whereby scholars have argued in favor of such on the argument that so-called [[Meritocracy|merit standards]] for hiring and educational admissions are not race-neutral for a variety of reasons, and that such standards are part of the rhetoric of [[Neutrality (philosophy)|neutrality]] through which whites justify their disproportionate share of resources and social benefits.{{sfnm |1a1=Delgado |1y=1995 |2a1=Kennedy |2y=1990 |3a1=Williams |3y=1991}}

== Criticism and controversy ==

=== Criticism ===

==== United States of America ====
Some legal scholars have criticized CRT on a number of grounds, such as CRT scholars' reliance on narrative and storytelling, or CRT's critique of objectivity. Judge [[Richard Posner]] of the [[United States Court of Appeals for the Seventh Circuit|U.S. Seventh Circuit Court of Appeals]] has "label[ed] critical race theorists and [[Postmodernism|postmodernists]] the 'lunatic core' of 'radical [[legal egalitarianism]].'"&lt;ref name="Posner"&gt;{{cite journal |author1link=Richard Posner |last1=Posner |first1=Richard A. |date=13 October 1997 |url=http://www.dariaroithmayr.com/pdfs/Posner-The%20Skin%20Trade-The%20New%20Republic.pdf |title=The Skin Trade |journal=The New Republic |volume=217 |issue=15 |pages=40–43 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20161005230322/http://www.dariaroithmayr.com/pdfs/Posner-The%20Skin%20Trade-The%20New%20Republic.pdf |archivedate=5 October 2016 }}&lt;/ref&gt; He wrote:&lt;ref name=Posner /&gt;
{{quote|What is most arresting about critical race theory is that…it turns its back on the Western tradition of rational inquiry, forswearing analysis for narrative. Rather than marshal logical arguments and empirical data, critical race theorists tell stories&amp;nbsp;– fictional, science-fictional, quasi-fictional, autobiographical, anecdotal&amp;nbsp;– designed to expose the pervasive and debilitating racism of America today. By repudiating reasoned argumentation, the storytellers reinforce stereotypes about the [[Race and intelligence|intellectual capacities of nonwhites]].|author=|title=|source=}}

Judge [[Alex Kozinski]] of the [[United States Court of Appeals for the Ninth Circuit|Ninth Circuit Court of Appeals]] wrote that critical race theorists have constructed a philosophy which makes a valid exchange of ideas between the various disciplines unattainable:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Kozinski |first=Alex |author-link=Alex Kozinski |date=November 2, 1997 |title=Bending the Law |url=https://www.nytimes.com/books/97/11/02/reviews/971102.02kosinst.html |work=[[The New York Times]] |access-date=September 17, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{quote|The radical multiculturalists' views raise insuperable barriers to mutual understanding. Consider the "[[The Space Traders|Space Traders]]" story. How does one have a meaningful dialogue with Derrick Bell? Because his thesis is utterly untestable, one quickly reaches a dead end after either accepting or rejecting his assertion that white Americans would cheerfully sell all blacks to the aliens. The story is also a poke in the eye of American Jews, particularly those who risked life and limb by actively participating in the civil rights protests of the 1960s. Bell clearly implies that this was done out of tawdry self-interest. Perhaps most galling is Bell's insensitivity in making the symbol of Jewish hypocrisy the little girl who perished in the Holocaust&amp;nbsp;– as close to a saint as Jews have. A Jewish professor who invoked the name of Rosa Parks so derisively would be bitterly condemned&amp;nbsp;– and rightly so.}}

Daniel Farber and Suzanna Sherry have argued that critical race theory, along with critical feminism and critical legal studies, has [[antisemitism|anti-Semitic]] and anti-Asian implications, has worked to undermine notions of democratic community, and has impeded dialogue.{{sfn|Farber|Sherry|1997|pp=9–11}}

Jeffrey J. Pyle wrote in the ''[[Boston College Law Review]]'':{{sfn|Pyle|1999|p=788}}
{{quote|Critical race theorists attack the very foundations of the [classical] liberal legal order, including equality theory, legal reasoning, Enlightenment rationalism and neutral principles of constitutional law. These liberal values, they allege, have no enduring basis in principle, but are mere social constructs calculated to legitimate white supremacy. The rule of law, according to critical race theorists, is a false promise of principled government, and they have lost patience with false promises.}}

However, notions of anti-Semitism and anti-Asian implications has been contested as there are divisions within CRT specifically HebCrit and AsianCrit, that address issues of equity and marginalization for both Jewish and Asian Communities. "HebCrit specifically addresses the needs of the Jewish people. Often overlooked and ignored in multicultural, diversity, and ethnic studies, Jews continue to face specific concerns and obstacles in both the United States and around the world."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|url=https://doi.org/10.1080/13504630.2020.1773778|title=Hebcrit: a new dimension of critical race theory|first=Daniel Ian|last=Rubin|date=July 3, 2020|journal=Social Identities|volume=26|issue=4|pages=499–514|via=Taylor and Francis+NEJM|doi=10.1080/13504630.2020.1773778|s2cid=219923352}}&lt;/ref&gt; Asian Crit looks at the influence of race and racism on the experiences and outcomes of Asian Americans in US education." Asian Crit provides a foundation for discourse around the racialized experiences of Asian Americans and other racially marginalized groups in education.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|url=https://doi.org/10.1080/09518398.2018.1522008|title=On the utility of Asian critical (AsianCrit) theory in the field of education|first1=Jon S.|last1=Iftikar|first2=Samuel D.|last2=Museus|date=November 26, 2018|journal=International Journal of Qualitative Studies in Education|volume=31|issue=10|pages=935–949|via=Taylor and Francis+NEJM|doi=10.1080/09518398.2018.1522008|s2cid=149949621}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Peter Wood, president of the [[National Association of Scholars]], considers CRT a "grievance ideology" and an "absurdity". He sees the central tenet of "white racism in the American legal system" to be shown false because of items such as the [[Fourteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|14th Amendment]], the [[Voting Rights Act]]s, and ''[[Brown v. Board of Education]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Wood|first=Peter|date=2012-03-17|title=Bell Epoque - Innovations - The Chronicle of Higher Education|url=http://chronicle.com/blogs/innovations/bell-epoque/31897|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120317235755/http://chronicle.com/blogs/innovations/bell-epoque/31897|archive-date=2012-03-17|access-date=2020-09-18|website=chronicle.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; Critics including [[George Will]] saw resonances between critical race theory's use of storytelling and insistence that race poses challenges to objective judgments in the US, as exemplified by the [[O. J. Simpson murder case|acquittal of O. J. Simpson]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|last=Will|first=George|author-link=George Will|date=November 28, 1996|title=Good News? Don't Want To Hear About It|work=[[The Washington Post]]|url=http://www.lexisnexis.com/hottopics/lnacademic/|accessdate=March 23, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Ansell"&gt;{{Cite book|last=Ansell|first=Amy|url=https://archive.org/details/encyclopediarace00scha|title=Encyclopedia of Race, Ethnicity, and Society|publisher=Sage|year=2008|isbn=978-1-4129-2694-2|editor=Richard T. Schaefer|pages=[https://archive.org/details/encyclopediarace00scha/page/n396 344]–46|chapter=Critical Race Theory|url-access=limited}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In September 2020, the [[White House Office of Management and Budget]] took steps to cancel funding for training in critical race theory among federal agencies on the basis that it constituted "divisive, un-American propaganda".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last1=Dawsey |first1=Josh|last2=Stein|first2=Jeff |title=White House directs federal agencies to cancel race-related training sessions it calls 'un-American propaganda' |url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2020/09/04/white-house-racial-sensitivity-training/ |accessdate=5 September 2020 |work=[[Washington Post]] |date=5 September 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;https://www.whitehouse.gov/wp-content/uploads/2020/09/M-20-34.pdf{{full|date=September 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Controversies ===
==== United States of America ====
Critical race theory has stirred controversy since the 1980s over such issues as its:

* deviation from the ideal of [[Color blindness (race)|color blindness]];
* promotion of the use of [[narrative]] in [[Legal Studies|legal studies]];
* advocacy of "legal [[instrumentalism]]" as opposed to ideal-driven uses of the law;
* analysis of the [[Constitution of the United States|U.S. Constitution]] and existing law as constructed according to and perpetuating racial power; and 
* encouragement of [[Legal scholar|legal scholars]] to be partial on the side of promoting racial equity.&lt;ref name="Ansell" /&gt;

===== 2010 =====
In 2010, the [[Mexican American Studies Department Programs, Tucson Unified School District|Mexican American Studies Department Programs]] in [[Tucson, Arizona]] were effectively banned due to their connection to CRT, which was seen to be in violation of a recently passed state law that "prohibits schools from offering courses that 'advocate ethnic [[solidarity]] instead of the treatment of pupils as individuals.'"&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Alex Seitz-Wald|date=March 21, 2012|title=How Breitbart and Arizona seized on "critical race theory"|url=http://www.salon.com/2012/03/21/how_breitbart_and_arizona_seized_on_critical_race_theory/singleton/|work=Salon}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ban included the confiscation of books, in some cases in front of students, by the [[Tucson Unified School District]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Rodriguez|first=Roberto Cintli|date=18 January 2012|title=Arizona's 'banned' Mexican American books|url=https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/cifamerica/2012/jan/18/arizona-banned-mexican-american-books|url-status=live|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=|website=The Guardian}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Matt de la Peña]]'s [[Young-Adult Novel|young-adult novel]] ''[[Mexican WhiteBoy]]'' was banned for containing CRT.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Winerip|first=Michael|date=March 19, 2012|title=Racial Lens Used to Cull Curriculum in Arizona|work=The New York Times|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2012/03/19/education/racial-lens-used-to-cull-curriculum-in-arizona.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, this ban was later deemed unconstitutional on the grounds that the state showed discriminatory intent. "Both enactment and enforcement were motivated by racial animus," federal Judge [[A. Wallace Tashima]] said in the ruling.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.npr.org/sections/ed/2017/08/22/545402866/federal-judge-finds-racism-behind-arizona-law-banning-ethnic-studies|title=Federal Judge Finds Racism Behind Arizona Law Banning Ethnic Studies|website=NPR.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== United Kingdom ==== 
===== 2020 ===== 
On the 20 October 2020 the [[Conservative Party (UK)|Conservative]] UK Equalities Minister [[Kemi Badenoch]] stated that, in regard to teaching Critical Race Theory in primary and secondary school (see [[Education in the United Kingdom]]), "we do not want to see teachers teaching their pupils about white privilege and inherited racial guilt ... any school which teaches these elements of critical race theory, or which promotes partisan political views such as defunding the police without offering a balanced treatment of opposing views, is breaking the law".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Trilling |first1=Daniel |title=Why is the UK government suddenly targeting 'critical race theory'? |url=https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2020/oct/23/uk-critical-race-theory-trump-conservatives-structural-inequality |website=The Guardian |accessdate=23 October 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt; Badenoch's remarks have been countered in an open letter, signed by hundreds of academics nationwide, which highlights Badenoch's alleged misapprehensions about critical race theory.&lt;ref&gt;https://docs.google.com/document/d/1lgv5BrTcSwp7bFtqYRMqqkY8hWOHlQxH1Gl_-UzSYfo/edit?ts=5f980965&lt;/ref&gt; On the 30 October 2020 an open letter signed by 101 writers of the [[Black Writers' Guild]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|date=2020-10-30|title=Writers protest after minister suggests anti-racism books support segregation|url=http://www.theguardian.com/books/2020/oct/30/writers-protest-after-minister-suggests-anti-racism-books-support-segregation|access-date=2020-10-30|website=the Guardian|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; condemned Badenoch for saying some authors want racial division, including her criticisms of books such as ''[[White Fragility]]'' and ''[[Why I'm No Longer Talking to White People About Race]]'', saying that: "many of these books - and, in fact, some of the authors and proponents of critical race theory - actually want a segregated society".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Nelson|first=Fraser|date=|title=Kemi Badenoch: The problem with critical race theory|url=https://www.spectator.co.uk/article/kemi-badenoch-the-problem-with-critical-race-theory|url-status=live|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=2020-10-30|website=www.spectator.co.uk}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Subfields ==
Within critical race theory, various sub-groupings have emerged to focus on issues that fall outside the black-white paradigm of race relations as well as issues that relate to the intersection of race with issues of gender, sexuality, class and other social structures. For example, critical race feminism (CRF), Hebrew Crit (HebCrit), Latino critical race studies (LatCrit),{{sfn|Delgado|Stefancic|1998}} Asian American critical race studies (AsianCrit), South Asian American critical race studies (DesiCrit),{{sfn|Harpalani|2013}} and American Indian critical race studies (sometimes called TribalCrit). CRT [[methodology]] and analytical framework have also been applied to the study of white immigrant groups.{{sfn|Myslinska|2014a|pp=559–560}} CRT has spurred some scholars to call for a second wave of [[whiteness studies]], which is now a small offshoot known as Second Wave Whiteness (SWW).{{sfn|Jupp|Berry|Lensmire|2016}} Critical race theory has also begun to spawn research that looks at understandings of race outside the United States.{{sfn|Myslinska|2014b}}&lt;ref&gt;See, e.g., {{harvnb|Levin|2008}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Disability critical race theory ===
Another offshoot field is that of ''[[Disability studies#Race|disability critical race studies]]'' (DisCrit), which combines [[Disability Studies]] and Critical Race Theory to focus on the [[Intersectionality|intersection]] of disability and race.{{sfn|Annamma|Connor|Ferri|2012}}

=== Latino critical race theory ===
{{jargon|date=September 2020}}
Latino critical race theory (LatCRT) is a [[research]] framework, a scheme that illustrates and explains a research plan in helping to formulate [[Research question|research questions]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|title=Research Framework|date=2010|url=http://methods.sagepub.com/reference/encyc-of-case-study-research/n299.xml|encyclopedia=Encyclopedia of Case Study Research|place=2455 Teller Road, Thousand Oaks California 91320 United States|publisher=SAGE Publications, Inc.|doi=10.4135/9781412957397.n299|isbn=978-1-4129-5670-3|access-date=2020-10-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; that outlines the [[Social constructionism|social construction]] of race is central to how people of color are constrained and oppressed in society.{{sfn|Treviño|Harris|Wallace|2008}} Race scholars developed LatCRT as a critical response to the "problem of the [[Color line (racism)|color line]]" first explained by [[W. E. B. Du Bois]].{{sfn|Treviño|Harris|Wallace|2008}} 

While CRT focuses on the Black–White paradigm, LatCRT has moved to consider other racial groups, mainly [[Chicana/o studies|Chicana/Chicanos]], as well as [[Latinos/as]], [[Asian people|Asians]], [[Native Americans in the United States|Native Americans]]/[[First Nations]], and [[women of color]]. In ''Critical Race Counterstories along the Chicana/Chicano Educational Pipeline'', [[Tara J. Yosso]] discusses how the constraint of [[Person of color|people of color]] (PoC) can be defined.{{sfn|Yosso|2006}} Looking at the differences between [[Chicano|Chicana/o]] students, the tenets that separate such individuals are:{{sfn|Yosso|2006|p=7}}

* the intercentricity of race and racism; 
* the challenge of [[dominant ideology]]; 
* the commitment to [[social justice]]; 
* the centrality of [[Experiential knowledge|experience knowledge]]; and 
* the [[Interdisciplinarity|interdisciplinary]] perspective.

LatCRTs main focus is to advocate [[social justice]] for those living in [[social exclusion|marginalized communities]]{{sfn|Treviño|Harris|Wallace|2008}} (specifically Chicana/os), which are guided by structural arrangements that disadvantage people of color. [[Institution|Social institutions]] function as [[Dispossession, oppression and depression|dispossessions]], [[Disfranchisement|disenfranchisement]], and discrimination over minority groups, while LatCRT seeks to give voice to those who are [[Victimisation|victimized]].{{sfn|Treviño|Harris|Wallace|2008}} In order to do so, LatCRT has created two common themes.

First, CRT proposes that white supremacy and racial power are maintained over time, a process that the law plays a central role in. Different racial groups lack the voice to speak in this [[civil society]], and, as such, CRT has introduced a new critical form of expressions, called the '''voice of color'''.{{sfn|Treviño|Harris|Wallace|2008}} The ''voice of color'' is [[Narrative|narratives]] and storytelling [[Monologue|monologues]] used as devices for conveying personal racial experiences. These are also used to counter [[metanarrative]]s that continue to maintain [[racial inequality]]. Therefore, the experiences of the oppressed are important aspects for developing a LatCRT analytical approach, and it has not been since the rise of slavery that an institution has so fundamentally shaped the life opportunities of those who bear the label of criminal.

Secondly, LatCRT work has investigated the possibility of transforming the relationship between [[law enforcement]] and racial power, as well as pursuing a project of achieving racial emancipation and anti-subordination more broadly.{{sfn|Yosso|2005}} CRT finds the experiential knowledge of people of color and draws explicitly from these lived experiences as data, presenting research findings through storytelling, chronicles, scenarios, narratives, and parables.{{sfn|Yosso|2006}}

== References ==
{{Reflist|30em}}

=== Bibliography ===
{{refbegin|35em|indent=yes}}
: {{cite journal|last=Annamma|first=Subini Ancy|year=2012|title=Dis/ability critical race studies (DisCrit): theorizing at the intersections of race and dis/ability|journal=Race Ethnicity and Education|volume=16|pages=1–31|number=1|doi=10.1080/13613324.2012.730511|s2cid=145739550}}
: {{cite journal|last=Bell|first=Derrick A, Jr.|author-link=Derrick Bell|year=1980|title=''Brown v. Board of Education'' and the Interest-Convergence Dilemma|url=http://www.hartfordschools.org/files/Equity%20Page/Interest_Convergence_by_Bell.pdf|journal=[[Harvard Law Review]]|volume=93|issue=3|pages=518–533|access-date=September 18, 2016|ref=harv|via=|doi=10.2307/1340546|jstor=1340546}}
: {{cite journal|last=Bell|first=Derrick A.|author-link=Derrick Bell|author-mask={{long dash}}|year=1995|title=Who's Afraid of Critical Race Theory?|url=|journal=University of Illinois Law Review|volume=1995|issue=4|pages=893ff|ref=harv|via=}}
: {{cite journal|last=Brooks|first=Roy|year=1994|title=Critical Race Theory: A Proposed Structure and Application to Federal Pleading|url=|journal=Harvard BlackLetter Law Journal|volume=11|pages=85ff|issn=0897-2761|ref=harv}}
: {{cite journal |last1=Carbado |first1=Devon W. |last2=Gulati |first2=Mitu |last3=Valdes |first3=Francisco |last4=Culp |first4=Jerome McCristal |last5=Harris |first5=Angela P. |title=The Law and Economics of Critical Race Theory |journal=The Yale Law Journal |date=May 2003 |volume=112 |issue=7 |pages=1757 |jstor=3657500 |doi=10.2307/3657500 |url=http://www.yalelawjournal.org/pdf/190_fhmiem8p.pdf |ref=harv }}
: {{cite book|last=Cole|first=Mike|year=2007|title=Marxism and Educational Theory: Origins and Issues|publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis|isbn=978-0-203-39732-9|location=|pages=|ref=harv}}
: {{cite journal|last=Crenshaw|first=Kimberlé|year=1988|title=Race, Reform and Retrenchment: Transformation and Legitimation in Anti-Discrimination Law|url=|journal=[[Harvard Law Review]]|volume=101|issue=7|pages=1331–1387|doi=10.2307/1341398|issn=0017-811X|ref=harv|jstor=1341398}}
: {{cite book|year=1995|editor1-last=Crenshaw|editor1-first=Kimberlé|editor1-link=Kimberlé Williams Crenshaw|editor2-last=Gotanda|editor2-first=Neil|editor3-last=Peller|editor3-first=Gary|editor3-link=Gary Peller|editor4-last=Thomas|editor4-first=Kendall|editor4-link=Kendall Thomas|title=Critical Race Theory: The Key Writings that Formed the Movement|last=|first=|location=New York|pages=|publisher=The New Press|isbn=978-1-56584-271-7|ref=harv|url-access=registration|url=https://archive.org/details/critica_xxx_1995_00_1144}}
: {{cite journal|last=Curry|first=Tommy J.|year=2009|title=Will the Real CRT Please Stand Up: The Dangers of Philosophical Contributions to CRT|url=https://www.academia.edu/2635853|journal=The Crit: A Critical Legal Studies Journal|volume=2|issue=1|pages=1–47|access-date=September 17, 2016|ref=harv|via=}}
: {{cite journal|last=Curry|first=Tommy J.|author-mask={{long dash}}|year=2012|title=Shut Your Mouth when You're Talking to Me: Silencing the Idealist School of Critical Race Theory through a Culturalogic Turn in Jurisprudence|url=https://www.academia.edu/2635852|journal=Georgetown Journal of Law and Modern Critical Race Studies|volume=3|issue=1|pages=1–38|issn=1946-3154|access-date=September 17, 2016|ref=harv|via=}}
: {{cite journal|last1=Delgado|first1=Richard|author1-link=Richard Delgado|year=1995|title=Rodrigo's Tenth Chronicle: Merit and Affirmative Action|url=|journal=[[Georgetown Law Journal]]|volume=83|issue=4|pages=1711–1748|issn=0016-8092|ssrn=2094599|ref=harv}}
: {{cite journal|last1=Delgado|first1=Richard|author1-link=Richard Delgado|last2=Stefancic|first2=Jean|year=1993|title=Critical Race Theory: An Annotated Bibliography|url=|journal=[[Virginia Law Review]]|volume=79|issue=2|pages=461–516|doi=10.2307/1073418|issn=0042-6601|ref=harv|jstor=1073418}}
: {{cite book|last1=Delgado|first1=Richard|author1-link=Richard Delgado|author1-mask={{long dash}}|last2=Stefancic|first2=Jean|author2-mask=&amp;#32;|year=1998|title=The Latino/a Condition: A Critical Reader|publisher=New York University Press|isbn=978-0-8147-1894-0|location=|pages=|ref=harv}}
: {{cite book|last1=Delgado|first1=Richard|author1-link=Richard Delgado|author1-mask={{long dash}}|last2=Stefancic|first2=Jean|author2-mask=&amp;#32;|year=2012|title=Critical Race Theory: An Introduction|edition=2nd|series=Critical America|location=|pages=|publisher=New York University Press|isbn=978-0-8147-2136-0|ref=harv}}
: {{cite journal |last1=Bernal |first1=Dolores Delgado |title=Critical Race Theory, Latino Critical Theory, and Critical Raced-Gendered Epistemologies: Recognizing Students of Color as Holders and Creators of Knowledge |journal=Qualitative Inquiry |date=February 2002 |volume=8 |issue=1 |pages=105–126 |doi=10.1177/107780040200800107 |s2cid=146643087 |ref=harv }}
: {{cite journal |last1=Dudziak |first1=Mary L. |title=Desegregation as a Cold War Imperative |journal=Stanford Law Review |date=November 1988 |volume=41 |issue=1 |pages=61–120 |doi=10.2307/1228836 |jstor=1228836 |ref=harv }}
: {{cite book|last1=Farber|first1=Daniel A.|author1-link=Daniel A. Farber|last2=Sherry|first2=Suzanna|author2-link=Suzanna Sherry|year=1997|title=Beyond All Reason: The Radical Assault on Truth in American Law|url=https://archive.org/details/beyondallreasonr00farb|url-access=registration|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=978-0-19-535543-7|location=|pages=|ref=harv}}
: {{cite book|last=Gates|first=Henry Louis, Jr.|year=1996|author-link=Henry Louis Gates Jr.|chapter=Critical Race Theory and Freedom of Speech|editor-last=Menand|editor-first=Louis|editor-link=Louis Menand|title=The Future of Academic Freedom|publisher=University of Chicago Press|location=|pages=119–159|isbn=978-0-226-52004-9|ref=harv}}
: {{cite journal |last1=Harpalani |first1=Vinay |title=DesiCrit: Theorizing the Racial Ambiguity of South Asian Americans |date=12 August 2013 |journal=New York University Annual Survey of American Law |volume=69 |issue=1 |pages=77–183 |ssrn=2308892 |url=https://annualsurveyofamericanlaw.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/69-1_harpalani.pdf |ref=harv }}
: {{cite journal |last1=Harris |first1=Angela P. |title=Foreword: The Jurisprudence of Reconstruction |journal=California Law Review |date=July 1994 |volume=82 |issue=4 |pages=741–785 |jstor=3480931 |doi=10.2307/3480931 |ref=harv }}
: {{cite journal |last1=Harris |first1=Cheryl I. |title=Whiteness as Property |journal=Harvard Law Review |date=June 1993 |volume=106 |issue=8 |pages=1707–1791 |jstor=1341787 |doi=10.2307/1341787 |ref=harv }}
: {{Cite journal|last=Harris|first=Cheryl|author-mask={{long dash}}|year=2002|title=Critical Race Studies: An Introduction|url=|journal=[[UCLA Law Review]]|volume=49|issue=5|pages=1215ff|issn=1943-1724|ref=harv}}
: {{cite journal|last=Jones|first=Camara Phyllis|s2cid=158126244|year=2002|title=Confronting Institutionalized Racism|journal=[[Phylon (journal)|Phylon]]|volume=50|issue=1/2|pages=7–22|doi=10.2307/4149999|issn=0031-8906|ref=harv|jstor=4149999}}
: {{cite journal |last1=Jupp |first1=James C. |last2=Berry |first2=Theodorea Regina |last3=Lensmire |first3=Timothy J. |title=Second-Wave White Teacher Identity Studies: A Review of White Teacher Identity Literatures From 2004 Through 2014 |journal=Review of Educational Research |date=December 2016 |volume=86 |issue=4 |pages=1151–1191 |doi=10.3102/0034654316629798 |s2cid=147354763 |ref=harv }}
: {{cite journal |last1=Kang |first1=Jerry |last2=Banaji |first2=Mahzarin R. |title=Fair Measures: A Behavioral Realist Revision of Affirmative Action |journal=California Law Review |date=2006 |volume=94 |issue=4 |pages=1063–1118 |doi=10.15779/Z38370Q |ssrn=873907 |ref=harv }}
: {{cite journal |last1=Kennedy |first1=Duncan |title=A Cultural Pluralist Case for Affirmative Action in Legal Academia |journal=Duke Law Journal |date=September 1990 |volume=1990 |issue=4 |pages=705–757 |jstor=1372722 |doi=10.2307/1372722 |url=http://nrs.harvard.edu/urn-3:HUL.InstRepos:13548460 |ref=harv }}
: {{cite journal |last1=Ladson-Billings |first1=Gloria |title=Just what is critical race theory and what's it doing in a nice field like education? |journal=International Journal of Qualitative Studies in Education |date=January 1998 |volume=11 |issue=1 |pages=7–24 |doi=10.1080/095183998236863 |ref=harv }}
: {{cite journal|last=Levin|first=Mark|title=The Wajin's Whiteness: Law and Race Privilege in Japan|url=|year=2008|journal=Hōritsu Jihō|volume=80|number=2|pages=80–91|ssrn=1551462|ref=harv|via=}}
: {{cite journal|last=Matsuda|first=Mari|author-link=Mari Matsuda|year=1987|title=Looking to the Bottom: Critical Legal Studies and Reparations|url=|journal=[[Harvard Civil Rights-Civil Liberties Law Review]]|volume=22|issue=2|pages=323ff|issn=2153-2389|ref=harv}}
: {{cite journal|last=Myslinska|first=Dagmar|year=2014a|title=Contemporary First-Generation European-Americans: The Unbearable 'Whiteness' of Being|url=|journal=[[Tulane Law Review]]|volume=88|issue=3|pages=559–625|issn=0041-3992|ssrn=2222267|ref=harv}}
: {{cite journal|last=Myslinska|first=Dagmar|author-mask={{long dash}}|year=2014b|title=Racist Racism: Complicating Whiteness Through the Privilege and Discrimination of Westerners in Japan|journal=UMKC Law Review|volume=83|issue=1|pages=1–55|issn=0047-7575|ref=harv|ssrn=2399984}}
: {{cite journal|last=Pyke|first=Karen D.|s2cid=43997467|year=2010|title=What is Internalized Racial Oppression and Why Don't We Study it? Acknowledging Racism's Hidden Injuries|journal=[[Sociological Perspectives]]|volume=53|issue=4|pages=551–572|doi=10.1525/sop.2010.53.4.551|issn=1533-8673|jstor=10.1525/sop.2010.53.4.551|ref=harv}}
: {{cite journal |last1=Pyle |first1=Jeffrey |title=Race, Equality and the Rule of Law: Critical Race Theory's Attack on the Promises of Liberalism |journal=Boston College Law Review |date=1 May 1999 |volume=40 |issue=3 |pages=787–827 |url=https://lawdigitalcommons.bc.edu/bclr/vol40/iss3/6/ |ref=harv }}
: {{cite journal |last1=Treviño |first1=A. Javier |last2=Harris |first2=Michelle A. |last3=Wallace |first3=Derron |title=What's so critical about critical race theory? |journal=Contemporary Justice Review |date=March 2008 |volume=11 |issue=1 |pages=7–10 |doi=10.1080/10282580701850330 |s2cid=145399733 |ref=harv }}
: {{cite book|last=Williams|first=Patricia J.|author-link=Patricia J. Williams|year=1991|title=The Alchemy of Race and Rights: Diary of a Law Professor|location=Cambridge, Massachusetts|pages=|publisher=Harvard University Press|isbn=978-0-674-01470-1|ref=harv|title-link=The Alchemy of Race and Rights}}
: {{cite journal |last1=Yosso |first1=Tara J. |title=Whose culture has capital? A critical race theory discussion of community cultural wealth |journal=Race Ethnicity and Education |date=March 2005 |volume=8 |issue=1 |pages=69–91 |doi=10.1080/1361332052000341006 |ref=harv }}
: {{cite book|last=Yosso|first=Tara J.|author-link=Tara J. Yosso|author-mask={{long dash}}|year=2006|title=Critical Race Counterstories along the Chicana/Chicano Educational Pipeline|series=Teaching/Learning Social Justice|location=New York|pages=|publisher=Routledge|isbn=978-0-415-95195-1|ref=harv|url-access=registration|url=https://archive.org/details/criticalracecoun0000yoss}}
{{refend}}

== Further reading ==
{{refbegin|35em|indent=yes}}
: {{cite book
|last=Brewer
|first=Mary
|year=2005
|title=Staging Whiteness
|location=Middletown, Connecticut
|publisher=Wesleyan University Press
|isbn=978-0-8195-6769-7
}}
: {{cite book |last1=Curran |first1=Andrew |title=The Anatomy of Blackness: Science and Slavery in an Age of Enlightenment |publisher=Johns Hopkins University Press |location=Baltimore |isbn=9781421409658 |url=https://jhupbooks.press.jhu.edu/content/anatomy-blackness |year=2011}}
: {{cite book
|editor-last=Delgado
|editor-first=Richard
|editor-link=Richard Delgado
|year=1995
|title=Critical Race Theory: The Cutting Edge
|location=Philadelphia
|publisher=Temple University Press
|isbn=978-1-56639-347-8
}}
: {{cite book
|year=2006
|editor1-last=Dixson
|editor1-first=Adrienne D.
|editor2-last=Rousseau
|editor2-first=Celia K.
|title=Critical Race Theory in Education: All God's Children Got a Song
|location=New York
|publisher=Routledge
|isbn=978-0-415-95292-7
}}
: {{cite book |last1=Epstein |first1=Kitty Kelly |title=A Different View of Urban Schools: Civil Rights, Critical Race Theory, and Unexplored Realities |date=2006 |publisher=Peter Lang |isbn=978-0-8204-7879-1 |ref=harv }}
: {{cite journal
|last1=Ladson-Billings
|first1=Gloria
|author1-link=Gloria Ladson-Billings
|last2=Tate
|first2=William F, IV
|year=1994
|title=Toward a Critical Race Theory of Education
|url=http://hs.iastate.edu/wp-content/uploads/2011/01/Toward_a_Critical_Race_Theory_of_Education.pdf
|journal=[[Teachers College Record]]
|volume=97
|issue=1
|pages=47–68
|issn=0161-4681
|access-date=September 18, 2016
}}
: {{cite journal |last1=Solorzano |first1=Daniel G. |title=Images and Words that Wound: Critical Race Theory, Racial Stereotyping, and Teacher Education |journal=Teacher Education Quarterly |date=1997 |volume=24 |issue=3 |pages=5–19 |jstor=23478088 |url=http://www.teqjournal.org/backvols/1997/24_3/1997v24n302.PDF }}
: {{cite journal |last1=Solórzano |first1=Daniel |last2=Ceja |first2=Miguel |last3=Yosso |first3=Tara |title=Critical Race Theory, Racial Microaggressions, and Campus Racial Climate: The Experiences of African American College Students |journal=The Journal of Negro Education |date=2000 |volume=69 |issue=1/2 |pages=60–73 |id={{ProQuest|222072305}} |jstor=2696265 }}
: {{cite journal |last1=Solorzano |first1=Daniel G. |last2=Bernal |first2=Dolores Delgado |title=Examining Transformational Resistance Through a Critical Race and Latcrit Theory Framework: Chicana and Chicano Students in an Urban Context |journal=Urban Education |date=May 2001 |volume=36 |issue=3 |pages=308–342 |doi=10.1177/0042085901363002 |s2cid=144784134 |ref=harv }}
: {{cite journal |last1=Solorzano |first1=Daniel G. |last2=Yosso |first2=Tara J. |title=Critical race and LatCrit theory and method: Counter-storytelling |journal=International Journal of Qualitative Studies in Education |date=July 2001 |volume=14 |issue=4 |pages=471–495 |doi=10.1080/09518390110063365 |s2cid=144999298 |ref=harv }}
: {{cite journal |last1=Solórzano |first1=Daniel G. |last2=Yosso |first2=Tara J. |title=A Critical Race Counterstory of Race, Racism, and Affirmative Action |journal=Equity &amp; Excellence in Education |date=May 2002 |volume=35 |issue=2 |pages=155–168 |doi=10.1080/713845284 |s2cid=146680966 }}
: {{cite journal |last1=Tate |first1=William F. |title=Chapter 4: Critical Race Theory and Education: History, Theory, and Implications |journal=Review of Research in Education |date=January 1997 |volume=22 |issue=1 |pages=195–247 |doi=10.3102/0091732X022001195 |s2cid=53626156 |jstor=1167376 }}

: {{cite book
|last=Tuitt
|first=Patricia
|year=2004
|title=Race, Law, Resistance
|location=London
|publisher=Glasshouse Press
|isbn=978-1-904385-06-6
}}

: {{cite book
|last=Tyson
|first=Lois
|year=2006
|title=Critical Theory Today: A User-Friendly Guide 2nd Edition
|location=New York-London
|publisher=Routledge, Taylor &amp; Francis Group
|isbn=978-0415974103
}}

: {{cite journal |last1=Vélez |first1=Veronica |last2=Huber |first2=Lindsay Perez |last3=Lopez |first3=Corina Benavides |last4=de la Luz |first4=Ariana |last5=Solórzano |first5=Daniel G. |title=Battling for Human Rights and Social Justice: A Latina/o Critical Race Media Analysis of Latina/o Student Youth Activism in the Wake of 2006 Anti-Immigrant Sentiment |journal=Social Justice |date=2008 |volume=35 |issue=1 |pages=7–27 |jstor=29768477 }}

{{refend}}

{{Critical theory}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Critical Race Theory}}
[[Category:Critical race theory| ]]
[[Category:Critical theory]]
[[Category:Politics and race]]
[[Category:Postmodernism]]
[[Category:Social constructionism]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>