<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061108134039|86486987" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="2002497" pageid="2002497" ns="0" title="Critical race theory"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-11-09T09:05:37Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{unreferenced}}
{{cleanup|November 2006}}

The notions of the social construction of race and discrimination are present in the writings of known contemporary critical race theorists, such as [[Derrick Bell]], [[Mari Matsuda]], [[Richard Delgado]], [[Kimberle Crenshaw]], Gloria Ladson-Billings, &amp; William Tate, newly emerging CRT scholars Adrienne Dixson, Celia Rousseau, Thandeka Chpaman, as well as in the writings of pioneers in the field, including [[W.E.B. DuBois]] and [[Max Weber]].

==History &amp; Origins==
The historical origins of Critical Race Theory provide a contextual understanding to contemporary legal debates concerning the effectiveness of past civil rights strategies in the current political climate. The earliest writings on Critical Race Theory can be traced to [[Derrick Bell]] and [[Alan Freeman]] in the mid-1970s. According to Delgado, both Bell and Freeman were deeply concerned with the ‘snail's pace’ progress of [[racial reform]] in the [[United States]]. Concerned and dismayed that any gains made by civil rights laws of the 1960s were quickly being eroded in the 1970s, Derrick Bell, a lawyer who served as the executive director of an [[NAACP]] branch, began to fashion arguments that were designed to change existing laws.

CRT is a body of legal theory (stemming from Critical Legal Studies) which is based on at least six premises: 

# Storytelling is a significant part of the law, and disenfranchised people(s) have different stories and different ways of telling them than enfranchised people(s).
# Racist behavior is not an aberration; it is normal practice.
# Elites act against racist behavior in society only when it serves them.
# Race is a social construct, not a biological one.
# Characteristics ascribed to a particular race will change. (For example, African American people were most commonly called "happy-go-lucky and childlike" in the slavery era to rationalize slavery, but now are most commonly called "threatening and criminal" to rationalize increased police intervention.) 
# People have intersecting identities; i.e., they belong to more than one demographic group and are consequently affected by disenfranchisement or inequality in more than one way. We all have multiple lenses through which we experience the world (and through which we are experienced by others).

==Major Contributors==
Bell is arguably the most influential source of thoughts critical of traditional [[civil rights]] discourse. Bell’s critique represented a challenge on the dominant [[liberal]] and [[American conservatism|conservative]] position on civil rights, [[race]], and the law.  Derrick Bell employed three major arguments in his analyses of racial patterns in American law: Constitutional contradiction, the interest convergence principle, and the price of racial remedies.  

For instance, in ''The Constitutional Contradiction,'' Bell argued that the framers of the Constitution chose the rewards of property over justice. With regard to the interest convergence, he maintains that ''whites will promote racial advances for blacks only when they also promote white self-interest.'' Finally, in ''The Price of Racial Remedies,'' Bell argues that whites will not support civil rights policies that may threaten white social status. Each of the arguments presented sheds a different light to the traditional racial discourse.

Critical Race Theory is philosophically connected to two other movements which share overlapping literature: Critical Legal Studies and Critical Theory.

==Other Contributors==
Other significant contributors to the Critical Race Theory discourse in the 1980s to the present are Delgado and Crenshaw. Delgado, in defense of Bell’s storytelling or narrative style, argues that people of color speak from an experience framed by [[racism]]. Delgado argues that the stories of people of color come from a different frame of reference, and therefore give them a voice that is different from the dominant culture and deserves to be heard. Critical race theorists believe that in order to appreciate their perspective, the voice of a particular contributor must be understood. 

Crenshaw argued that little difference existed between conservative and liberal discourse on race-related law and policy. Crenshaw identified two distinct properties in [[anti-discrimination law]]: expansive properties and restrictive properties. The former stresses equality as outcome relying on the courts to eliminate effects of racism. The latter treats equality as a process. Its focus is to prevent any future wrongdoing. Crenshaw argues that expansive and restrictive properties coexist in anti-discrimination law. The implication of Crenshaw's argument is that the failure of the restrictive property to address or correct the racial injustices of the past simply perpetuates the status quo.

CRT has been explored in education most notably from Ladson-Billings, Tate, Lynn, Parker, Solorzano, Yosso, Dixson, Rousseau, and Chapman. Critical race scholarship in education has occurred in three waves. The first wave of studies emanated in the mid 1990s with the introduction of CRT to the field by Ladson-Billings and Tate. Parker and Solorzano's contributions followed soon thereafter. The second wave of scholarship occurred in the late 1990s and continued through about 2004. Younger scholars like Lynn, Duncan, Yosso became key players.  Dixson and Rousseau represent the third wave of new scholars who are attempting to re-introduce CRT to the field and also create stricter standards for how CRT in Education is defined.

== Offshoot Fields ==

No longer content with accepting whiteness as the norm, critical scholars have turned their attention to whiteness itself. In the field of '''[[Critical White Studies]]''', numerous thinkers, including [[Toni Morrison]], [[Eric Foner]], [[Peggy McIntosh]], [[Andrew Hacker]], [[Ruth Frankenberg]], [[John Howard Griffin]], [[David Roediger]], [[Kathleen Neal Cleaver]], [[Noel Ignatiev]], [[Cherríe Moraga]], [[Maurice Berger]], and [[Reginald Horsman]], attack such questions as: 

* How was whiteness invented, and why? 
* How has the category of whiteness changed over time? 
* Why did some immigrant groups, such as the Irish and Jews, start out as nonwhite and later become white? 
* Can some individual people be both white and nonwhite at different times, and what does it mean to "pass for white"? 
* At what point does pride in being white cross the line into white power or white supremacy? 
* What can whites concerned over racial inequity or white privilege do about it? 

Within Critical Race Theory, culturally specific subdivisions began to develop, including:
* Latino Critical Race Studies or [[LatCrit]].
* Asian American Critical Race Studies or [[AsiaCrit]].
* American Indian Critical Race Studies or [[TribalCrit]].



== Bibliography ==
*Bell, D.A. (1993) Remembrance of Racism Past: The Civil Rights Decline. In Hill &amp; J. E Jones (Eds.) Race in America: The Struggle for Equality (pp. 73-82). Madison: [[University of Wisconsin]] Press. 
*Crenshaw, K.W. (1988) Race Reform, Retrenchment: Transformation and Legitimation in Anti-Discrimination Law. [[Harvard Law]] Review, 101. 1331-1387. 
*Crenshaw, K.W. et al (1995). Introduction. In K. Crenshaw, N. Gotanda, G. Peller, &amp; K. Thomas (Eds.) Critical Race Theory: The Key Writings that Formed the Movement. [[New York]]: New Press 
*Delgado, R (1995) Legal Storytelling: Storytelling for Oppositionists and Others: A Plea for Narrative. In R. Delgado (Ed.) Critical Race Theory: The Cutting Edge. [[Philadelphia]]: [[Temple University]] Press. 
*Delgado, R (1995) The Imperial Scholar Revisited: How to Marginalize Outsider Writing, Ten Years Later.  In R. Delgado (Ed.) Critical Race Theory: The Cutting Edge. [[Philadelphia]]: [[Temple University]] Press. 
*Delgado, R (1995) [[Affirmative Action]] as a Majoritarian Device: Or, Do You Really Want to Be A Role Model? In R. Delgado (Ed.) Critical Race Theory: The Cutting Edge. [[Philadelphia]]: [[Temple University]] Press 
*Dixson, A. D. &amp; Rousseau, C. K. (2006). Critical race theory and education. New York, NY: Routledge.
*Dixson, A. D. &amp; Rousseau, C. K. (2005) 'And We Are Still Not Saved: Critical Race Theory in Education Ten Years Later', Race, Ethnicity and Education, 8 (1) pp. 7-27.
*Ladson-Billings, G.J. &amp; Tate, W.F. (1995). Toward a critical theory of race in education. Teachers College Record, 47-68.
*Lynn, M. (1999). Toward a critical race pedagogy: a research note. Urban Education, 33(5), pp. 606-626.
*Lynn, M. (2002). [Special Issue]. Critical Race Theory in Education: Recent Developments in the Field. Equity &amp; Excellence in Education. 35(2).
*Tate, W. F. (1996) Critical Race Theory: Review of Research in Education, 22, 201-247.

== Further reading ==
*[http://cdms.ds.uiuc.edu/Critical%20Whiteness/Introduction.htm Toward a Discipline Specific Bibliography of Critical Whiteness Studies]

[[Category:Critical theory]]
[[Category:Postmodernism]]
[[Category:Racism]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>