<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061110042234|86874367" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="249623" pageid="249623" ns="0" title="Same-sex marriage in the United States"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-11-11T03:59:36Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{SSM}}
{{current}}
'''[[Same-sex marriage]]''', often called '''gay marriage''', is a [[marriage]] between two persons of the same gender. The issue is a divisive [[politics|political issue]] in the [[United States]] and elsewhere. The social movement to obtain the [[rights and responsibilities of marriages in the United States|legal protections of civil marriage]] for same-sex couples began in the early [[1970s]], and the issue became a prominent one in U.S. politics in the [[1990s]].

The legal issues surrounding same-sex marriage in the United States are complicated by the nation's [[federalism|federal]] system of government. Traditionally, the federal government did not attempt to establish its own definition of marriage; any marriage recognized by a [[U.S. state|state]] was recognized by the federal government. With the passage of the [[Defense of Marriage Act]] in 1996, however, a marriage was explicitly defined as a union of one man and one woman for the purposes of federal law. Thus, no act or agency of the U.S. federal government currently recognizes same-sex marriage.

However, many aspects of marriage law affecting the day to day lives of inhabitants of the United States are determined by the states, not the federal government, and the Defense of Marriage Act does not prevent individual states from defining marriage as they see fit; indeed, most legal scholars believe that the federal government cannot impose a definition of marriage onto the laws of the various states by statute. [[Massachusetts]] has recognized same-sex marriage since 2004. [[Connecticut]], [[Vermont]], and [[California]] have created legal unions that, while not called marriages, are explicitly defined as offering all the rights and responsibilities of marriage under state law to same-sex couples. [[Maine]], [[New Jersey]], the [[District of Columbia]], and [[Hawaii]] have created legal unions for same-sex couples that offer varying subsets of the rights and responsibilites of marriage under the laws of those jurisdictions.

In contrast, nineteen states have constitutional amendments explicitly barring the recognition of same-sex marriage, confining civil marriage to a legal union between a [[man]] and a [[woman]]. Forty-three states have statutes defining marriage to two persons of the opposite-sex, including some of those that have created legal recognition for same-sex unions under a name other than "marriage." 

On October 25, 2006, the New Jersey Supreme Court ruled that gay couples have the same rights as heterosexual couples. It left it to the legislature, however, to decide if this would be in the form of marriages or some other type of civil union. This is of particular significance because, unlike Massachusetts, New Jersey does not have a law preventing non-residents from marrying if the marriage would not be recognized in their home state.

Opponents of same-sex marriage have attempted to prevent individual states from recognizing such unions by amending the [[United States Constitution]] to define marriage as a union between one man and one woman. In 2006, the [[Federal Marriage Amendment]], which would prohibit states from recognizing same-sex marriages, was approved by the [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican]]-controlled [[United States Senate Committee on the Judiciary|Senate Judiciary Committee]], on a party line vote, and was debated by the full United States Senate, but was ultimately defeated in both houses of Congress.&lt;ref&gt;''[http://www.cnn.com/2006/POLITICS/06/07/same.sex.marriage/index.html Senate blocks same-sex marriage ban]'', [[CNN]], [[June 7]], 2006, (Accessed [[July 5]], 2006) &lt;/ref&gt;

== The debate ==
=== Gay rights organizations ===

Evan Wolfson, the director of the ''[[Freedom to Marry]]'' coalition, contends that banning gay and bisexual Americans from legally marrying the one they romantically love constitutes "discrimination." He states that same-sex marriage would promote equality and fairness among all Americans by allowing same-sex couples to have the same legal protections as afforded to married, opposite-sex couples. {{fact}}	

::Gay families also deserve health care, retirement protections, the ability to use scarcely needed funds to afford education or a home and the ability to give kids the security to openly and proudly describe their families. This would make our nation stronger.

=== Conservative publications ===

A writer of ''[[The Weekly Standard]]'', Stanley Kurtz, a fellow at the Hudson Institute, blames same-sex marriage in the [[Netherlands]] for an increase in parental cohabitation contracts. He asserts that same-sex marriage has detached [[procreation]] from marriage in the Dutch mind and would likely do the same in the [[United States]]. 

Using [[anecdotal]] evidence, such as a Dutch man and two women who entered a cohabitation agreement together, and a small [[Unitarian Church]] group that advocates polygamy, Stanley states that allowing a monogamous same-sex marriage will create a social disorder that will eventually lead to [[polygamy]].

::...the American media are correct to report that the majority of Dutch citizens have accepted the innovation (same-sex marriage). The press has simply missed the meaning of that public shift. Broad Dutch acceptance of same-sex marriage means that marriage as an institution has been detached from parenthood in the public mind. That is why the practice of parental cohabitation has grown so quickly in the Netherlands. By the same token, the shoulder shrug that followed the triple wedding (cohabitation) story shows that legalized group marriage in the Netherlands is now a real possibility.

=== Liberal publications ===

Christopher Ott, a reporter for ''[[The Progressive]]'', has characterized the social conservatives' predictions of legalized polygamy in states such as Massachusetts that have same-sex marriage as false. He confronts the common argument that same-sex marriage would devalue [[marriage]] as a whole by referencing other historical events such as [[sufferage|allowing women to vote]] and stating that it did not devalue the electoral process. Ott describes the prohibition of same-sex marriage as devaluing the American principle of [[equal treatment]].

::...you also have to wonder if he and other opponents to equal rights really understand the consequences of the amendments they support. Do they really want gay and lesbian couples separated at the emergency room door in the event of an accident or illness? Do they really think long-term couples should be denied the right to make medical or end-of-life decisions, which married couples take for granted? Do they really think that kids should be denied health coverage by one parent's health insurance because the law treats them as strangers? Do they really think it's fair for gay and lesbian people to pay the same taxes as everyone else, but to be denied the hundreds of rights, benefits and protections of marriage? Do they really think that a gay and lesbian couple that has been together for 50 years does not deserve the protections that non-gay newlyweds enjoy from day one?

===Groups supporting and opposing same-sex marriage===
{{seealso|Blessing of same-sex unions in Christian churches}}
It is supported by an assortment of groups and individuals. Those supporting same-sex marriage include the [[Human Rights Campaign]]; the late [[Coretta Scott King]]; the mayors of several large cities such as [[Boston]], [[Los Angeles]], [[San Francisco]], [[Salt Lake City, Utah|Salt Lake City]], [[Chicago]], [[Seattle]], and [[New York]]; the [[American Civil Liberties Union]]; the [[American Psychiatric Association]]; [[Reform Judaism]]; the [[United Church of Christ]]; and the [[Unitarian|Unitarian Universalist]] religion. Several political parties such as the [[Communist Party USA]],&lt;ref&gt; ''[http://www.cpusa.org/article/articleview/589/1/3 ELECTION PLATFORM 2004]'', Communist Party USA, 2004. (Accessed [[July 5]], 2006)&lt;/ref&gt; the Socialist Party USA,&lt;ref&gt; ''[http://sp-usa.org/platform/humanrights.html Socialist Party Platform: Human Rights]'', Socialist Party USA, 2004. (Accessed [[July 5]], 2006)&lt;/ref&gt; U.S. [[Green Party]], the [[United States Libertarian Party]] and several state [[Democratic Party|Democratic Parties]] also support gay marriage.

Those supporting the creation of a separate but equal legal status for same-sex couples in the form of civil union or domestic partnership legislation include some state governors such as those of [[Washington]], [[Oregon]], [[California]], [[New Mexico]], and [[Connecticut]], the national [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democratic Party]].&lt;ref&gt;''[http://www.democrats.org/pdfs/2004platform.pdf Democratic Party 2004 Platform]'' &lt;/ref&gt; Some also support enacting reciprocal beneficiary legislation that would give some of the same legal rights as marriage but not all. They include the state governor of [[Utah]], and [[Focus on the Family]].

Groups that oppose giving a legal status to same-sex marriages include the [[American Family Association]], [[Family Research Council]], [[Southern Baptist Convention]],&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/news/archive/2004/06/15/national1654EDT0681.DTL]&lt;/ref&gt; the [[Presbyterian Church USA]],&lt;ref&gt; ''[http://www.pcusa.org/101/101-homosexual.htm Homosexuality]'', Presbyterian General Assemblies. (Accessed [[July 5]], 2006)&lt;/ref&gt; the [[Seventh-day Adventist Church]],&lt;ref&gt; ''[http://www.religioustolerance.org/hom_sda.htm THE SEVENTH-DAY ADVENTIST CHURCH AND HOMOSEXUALITY]'', ReligiousTolerance.org (Accessed [[July 5]], 2006) &lt;/ref&gt; the Southern Baptist Convention,&lt;ref&gt;Kastensmidt, Sam, ''[http://www.reclaimamerica.org/PAGES/NEWS/news.aspx?story=1264 SBC Officially Opposes “Homosexual Marriage”]'' The Southern Baptist Convention, [[June 26]], 2003. (Accessed [[July 5]], 2006) &lt;/ref&gt; the [[Hutterite]] Brethren,&lt;ref&gt; ''[http://www.cbc.ca/story/canada/national/2005/02/17/hutterite-050217.html Hutterites take rare political stand against gay marriage]'', CBC News, [[February 18]], 2005. (Accessed [[July 5]], 2006)&lt;/ref&gt; the [[Conservative Mennonite Conference]]&lt;ref&gt; ''[http://cmcrosedale.org/about/homosexuality.shtml CMC Statement on Homosexuality], Comservative Mennonite Conference. (Accessed [[July 5]], 2006)&lt;/ref&gt; the Evangelical Methodist Church,&lt;ref&gt; Williamon, Edward W., ''[http://www.emchurch.org/news.htm Is America witnessing the end of marriage?], The Evangelical Methodist Church. (Accessed [[July 5]], 2006)&lt;/ref&gt; [[Unification Church]], the [[Moral Majority]], the [[Christian Voice]], the [[Christian Coalition]], [[Focus on the Family]], [[The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]], the [[Orthodox Church in America]],&lt;ref&gt; ''[http://www.oca.org/DOCmarriage.asp?SID=12&amp;ID=26 On Marriage, Family, Sexuality, and the Sanctity of Life]'', Orthodox Church in America. (Accessed [[July 5]], 2006)&lt;/ref&gt; the [[Rabbinical Council of America]],&lt;ref name=orthjew&gt; ''[http://www.rabbis.org/news/article.cfm?id=100556 Same-Sex Marriage]'', Rabbinical Council of America. (Accessed [[July 5]], 2006)&lt;/ref&gt; the [[Union of Orthodox Jewish Congregations of America]] (OU),&lt;ref name=orthjew/&gt; the Church of God (Anderson, IN),&lt;ref&gt; ''[http://www.chog.org/ME2/Audiences/dirmod.asp?nm=Core+Pages&amp;type=gen&amp;mod=Core+Pages&amp;tier=3&amp;gid=9B410103A4034AF9930C4CFAC4474E93&amp;AudID=E5E87D912B4A4358915D489F4BF9B6F6 Resolution Regarding Same-Sex Marriage]'', The Church of God General Assembly Resolution, 2004. (Accessed [[July 5]], 2006)&lt;/ref&gt; a majority of the [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican Party]], and the [[Roman Catholic Church]].

== Popular opinion ==
:''See [[Same-sex marriage in the United States public opinion]]

== Legal issues ==
=== Federal level ===

In the [[United States]], proponents of equal marriage rights for same-sex couples observe that there are over 1,049 federal laws in which marital status is a factor, as well as state and private benefits (family memberships, discounts, etc) denied same-sex couples by excluding them from participating in marriage. A legal denial of federal rights or benefits, they say, directly contradicts the [[Fourteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|14th Amendment of the US Constitution]] which provides for [[Equal Protection Clause|equal protection]] and substantive [[due process]] under the law: rights conferred to one person cannot be denied to another.

In the 2003 case before the [[Supreme Court of the United States]] titled ''[[Lawrence v. Texas]]'', the court held that intimate consensual sexual conduct was part of the liberty protected by substantive due process under the Fourteenth Amendment. Many proponents of same-sex marriage believe that this ruling, especially when combined with the 1967 ruling in ''[[Loving v. Virginia]]'' that eliminated anti-[[miscegenation]] laws, paves the way for a subsequent decision invalidating state laws prohibiting same-sex marriage. However, these proponents often do not mention, or are not aware, of the United States Supreme Court's summary affirmance in the case of ''[[Baker v. Nelson]]'' [[Case citation|409 U.S. 810]]. This decision, binding on all lower federal courts, clearly distinguishes ''Loving'', and establishes the right of the individual States to uphold traditional opposite-sex marriage. 

Challenges to DOMA have already been rejected by several federal courts, including a decision by Judge James S. Moody in the case of ''[[Wilson v. Ake]]''. Most legal experts expect these challenges to fail.

Some opponents of same-sex marriage, wanting to ensure that the constitutionality of such laws cannot be challenged in the courts under the [[Full Faith and Credit clause]], [[Equal Protection Clause]] or [[Due process clause]] of the [[United States Constitution]], have proposed a [[Federal Marriage Amendment]] to the constitution that would prevent the federal government or any state from providing a marriage or the legal incidents thereof to a same-sex couple, whether through the legislature or the courts.

The amendment was debated in the [[United States Senate]], but on [[July 14]], [[2004]], a procedural motion to end debate failed by a wider-than-expected margin of 48 votes to 50. [http://www.nytimes.com/2004/07/14/politics/14CND-GAYS.html] This effectively prevented the amendment from facing a full Senate vote.

Also in 2003, lesbian comedian [[Rosie O'Donnell]]'s court case with ex-colleagues raised another new issue when O'Donnell's life partner, Kelli, was forced to testify against O'Donnell. Under United States law, spouses cannot be forced to testify against each other; but because same-sex couples are not allowed to marry, they are denied this courtroom right, part of a long [[Rights and responsibilities of marriages in the United States|list of benefits of marriage in the United States]]. They married on [[February 26]], [[2004]] in San Francisco, but this was later nullified by the California Supreme Court.

As of April, 2006, California same-sex couple Arthur Smelt and Christopher Hammer had a marriage-rights case pending in the federal [[United States Court of Appeals for the Ninth Circuit|Ninth Circuit Court of Appeals]]. Gay-rights groups including the [[Lambda Legal Defense and Education Fund]] and the [[American Civil Liberties Union]] did not support the lawsuit, on the grounds that it is likely to lose in the Supreme Court and set an unfavorable precedent. The Court eventually tossed out the suit in the spring of 2006, saying that the couples must wait for a ruling by the Appeals Court in California.&lt;ref&gt; Kravets, David, ''[http://www.boston.com/news/local/connecticut/articles/2006/04/02/two_paths_toward_one_goal_same_sex_marriage Two paths toward one goal: same-sex marriage]'', Associated Press, [[April 2]], 2006. &lt;/ref&gt;

=== State level ===
:''See [[Same-sex marriage in the United States by state]] for information on individual states''
[[Image:SSM NorthAm 2006.PNG|right|300px|thumb|Status of same-sex union laws in North America.]]

Outside of [[Massachusetts]], where same-sex marriage is legal, [[Vermont]], [[California]], [[District of Columbia]] and [[Connecticut]] are the only U.S. states to offer same-sex couples all or some of the state-level rights and benefits of marriage. They do not use the word "marriage", however, but call such unions ''[[civil union]]'' or ''[[domestic partnership]]''. 

[[Hawaii]], [[Maine]], and [[New Jersey]] have [[domestic partnership]] and reciprocal benefit laws provide similar benefits, but stop short of full equality on a state level. On October 25, 2006 the NJ Supreme Court ruled this inequality unconstitutional, and gave the legislature 180 days to correct it. 

There are also bills in both chambers of the [[New York State]] legislature that would extend marriage rights to same-sex couples. These bills were introduced in early [[2003]] and are currently still in committee.

In all cases, no rights that originate with the federal government attach to civil union, domestic partnership, etc., because the several states do not have jurisdiction over the Government of the United States.

=== Impact of foreign laws ===
The legalization of same sex-marriages across all of Canada (see [[same-sex marriage in Canada]]) has raised questions about U.S. law, due to Canada's proximity to the U.S. and the fact that Canada has no citizenship or residency requirement to receive a marriage certificate (unlike the [[same-sex marriage in the Netherlands|Netherlands]] and [[same-sex marriage in Belgium|Belgium]]). Canada and the U.S. have a history of respecting marriages contracted in either country. 

Immediately after the June 2003 ruling legalizing [[same-sex marriage in Ontario]], a number of American couples headed or planned to head to the province in order to get married. A coalition of American national [[gay rights]] groups issued a statement asking couples to contact them before attempting legal challenges, so that they might be coordinated as part of the same-sex marriage movement in the United States.

At present, same-sex marriages are recognized nationwide in the [[Same-sex marriage in the Netherlands|Netherlands]] (and possibly [[Same-sex marriage in Aruba|Aruba]]), [[Same-sex marriage in Belgium|Belgium]], [[Same-sex marriage in Spain|Spain]], New Zealand (Civil Unions with essentially all marriage rights) and [[Same-sex marriage in Canada|Canada]]. On [[1 December]], 2005, [[Same-sex marriage in South Africa|South Africa]]’s Constitutional Court extended marriage to include same-sex couples which will go into effect by December 2006. Same-sex marriages are also recognized in parts of other countries.

[[Same-sex marriage in Latvia|Latvia]] and [[Uganda]][http://hrw.org/english/docs/2005/07/12/uganda11307.htm] have amended their constitutions to prohibit same-sex marriage, and [[Gay rights in Nigeria|Nigeria]] is planning to do the same.

== Legislative action on same-sex unions ==
:''See [[Same-sex marriage legislation in the United States]]''

== 2004 presidential election ==
In the [[U.S. presidential election, 2004|2004 presidential election]] campaign, legal recognition of same-sex unions became a campaign issue. Incumbent [[George W. Bush]], the [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican Party]] candidate supported creating a federal "one man and one woman" definition of marriage, through the [[Federal Marriage Amendment]] (FMA), while supporting state-sanctioned [[civil unions]], [[reciprocal benefits]], or [[domestic partnerships]]. Challenger [[John F. Kerry]], the Democratic Party candidate took a similar position supporting the ban of [[marriages]] between [[same-sex couples]] on a state level while supporting [[civil unions]], [[reciprocal benefits]], and [[domestic partnerships]]. However, Kerry opposed the FMA.

During the [[2004 Republican National Convention]] GOP platform called for "a Constitutional amendment that fully protects marriage" [http://www.gop.com/media/2004platform.pdf]. After his re-election, President Bush indicated to the [[Washington Post]] that he saw little prospect for Congressional passage of the Federal Marriage Amendment to the federal [[Constitution]] unless the [[Defense of Marriage Act]] were ruled [[Constitutionality|unconstitutional]].

Strong opposition to gay marriage was arguably a significant factor in helping Bush get re-elected, particularly because Kerry was from Massachusetts, the state where gay marriage had just been legalized. Several states passed constitutional amendments defining marriage on election day, including [[Ohio]]. Nevertheless, in some states Bush received more votes than the ban on same-sex marriage, indicating some of those who voted for him also voted against defining marriage. The number of voters citing moral values as a deciding issue in their vote remained the same as in the [[2000]] according to exit polls.

== Case law ==
United States case law regarding the rights of homosexual persons:

*''Adams v. Howerton'', 673 F.2d 1036 (9th Cir. 1982), ''cert. denied'', 458 U.S. 1111 (affirming that same-sex marriage does not make one a "spouse" under the Immigration and Nationality Act)
*''Standhardt v. Superior Court ex rel. County of Maricopa'', 77 P.3d 451 (Ariz. Ct. App. 2003) (no state constitution right to same-sex marriage)
*''Rosengarten v. Downes'', 806 A.2d 1066 (Conn. 2002) (state will not recognize Vermont civil union)
*''Burns v. Burns'', 560 S.E.2d 47 (Ga. Ct. App. 2002) (recognizing marriage as between one man and one woman)
*''In re Estate of Hall'', 707 N.E.2d 201, 206 (Ill. App. Ct. 1998) (no same sex marriage will be recognized; petitoner claiming existing same-sex marriage was not in a marriage recognized by law)
*''Morrison v. Sadler'', 2003 WL 23119998 (Ind. Super. Ct. 2003) (Indiana's Defense of Marriage Act is found valid)
*''Frandsen v. County of Brevard'', 828 So. 2d 386 (Fla. 2002) (State constitution will not be construed to recognize same-sex marriage; sex classifications not subject to strict scrutiny under Florida constitution)
*''In re Estate of Gardiner'', 42 P.3d 120 (Kan. 2002) (a post-op male-to-female transgendered person may not marry a male, because this person is still a male in the eyes of the law, and marriage in Kansas is recognized only between a man and a woman)
*''Jones v. Hallahan'', 501 S.W.2d 588 (Ky. 1973) (upholding a Kentucky law defining marriage)
*''Jennings v. Jennings'', 315 A.2d 816, 820 n.7 (Md. Ct. App. 1974) ("marriage is between only one man and one woman.")
*''[[Baker v. Nelson]]'', 191 N.W.2d 185 (Minn. 1971) (upholding a Minnesota law defining marriage)
*''[[Lewis v. Harris]]'', (New Jersey Supreme Court) (New Jersey is required to extend all rights and responsibilities of marriage to same-sex couples, but prohibiting same-sex marriage does not violate the state constitution; legislature has 180 days from October 25, 2006 to amend the marriage laws or create a "parallel structure.")
*''Storrs v. Holcomb'', 645 N.Y.S.2d 286 (N.Y. App. Div. 1996) (New York does not recognize or authorize same-sex marriage) (this ruling has since been changed, New York does recognize same-sex marriages performed in other states)
*''In re Estate of Cooper'', 564 N.Y.S.2d 684 (N.Y. Fam. Ct. 1990)
*''De Santo v. Barnsley'', 476 A.2d 952 (Pa. Super. Ct. 1984)
*''Singer v. Hara'', 522 P.2d 1187 (Wash. App. 1974)
*''[[Andersen v. King County]]'', 2006 (Washington Supreme Court) (Washington's Defense of Marriage Act does not violate the state constitution)
*''Dean v. District of Columbia'', 653 A.2d 307 (D.C. 1995)

==Notes==
&lt;references/&gt;

==References==
* [http://www.pollingreport.com/civil.htm PollingReport.com Law and Civil Rights] compendium

==Bibliography==
*{{cite book | last = Wolfson | first = Evan | authorlink = Evan Wolfson | year = 2004 | title = Why Marriage Matters: America, Equality, and Gay People's Right to Marry | publisher = Simon &amp; Schuster | location = New York | id = ISBN 0-7432-6459-2}}
*{{cite book | last = Chauncey | first = George | authorlink = George Chauncey | year = 2004 | title = Why Marriage?: The History Shaping Today's Debate over Gay Equality | publisher = Basic Books | location = New York | id = ISBN 0-465-00957-3}}
*{{cite book | last = Dobson | first = James C. | authorlink = James Dobson | year = 2004 | title = [[Marriage Under Fire|Marriage under Fire: Why We Must Win This War]] | publisher = Multnomah | location = Sisters, Or. | id = ISBN 1-59052-431-4}}

{{Same-sex marriage in the United States}}

== See also ==
{{gay rights}}
* [[List of U.S. state laws on same-sex unions]]
* [[List of benefits of marriage in the United States]]
* [[Rights and responsibilities of marriages in the United States]]
* [[Defense of Marriage Act]]
*[[Marriage Protection Act]]
*[[Defense of marriage amendment]]
* [[Federal Marriage Amendment]]
* [[Domestic partnerships in the United States]]
*''[[Marriage Under Fire]]''
*[[Freedom to Marry Coalition]]
* [[Gay rights in the United States]]
* [[2004 in gay rights]]

==External links==
{{ cleanup-spam }}
===Supporting Same-sex Marriage===
* [http://www.democrats.org/a/communities/glbt_community/ The Democratic Party GLBT Community]
* [http://hawaiigaymarriage.com Hawai`i Gay Marriage Bureau]
* [http://www.freedomtomarry.org Freedom to Marry]
* [http://www.indegayforum.org/library/marriage.html Independent Gay Forum: Marriage]
*[http://www.marriageequality.org/main_home.php Marriage Equality USA]
*[http://www.eqca.org Equality California]
*[http://www.stateaction.org/issues/issue.cfm/issue/marriageequality.xml Center for Policy Alternatives Marriage Equality Policy Model]
*[http://www.lmfct.org Connecticut Same-Sex Marriage Organization: Love Makes a Family]
*[http://www.lgbtcaucus.com LGBT Political Investment Caucus]
*[http://www.GardenStateEquality.org Garden State Equality]
*[http://www.hrc.org Human Rights Campaign]
*[http://www.now.org/issues/lgbi/marr-rep.html National Organization for Women: Same-Sex Marriage is a Feminist Issue]
*[http://aclu.org ACLU: Oppose Writing Intolerance into the Constitution]
*[http://web.archive.org/web/20040402075348/http://www.365gay.com/newscon04/03/030204arnoldAmend.htm Arnold Splits From Bush, Would Support Gay Marriage]
*[http://www.psych.org/edu/other_res/lib_archives/archives/200502.pdf The American Psychiatric Association: Support of Legal Recognition of Same-Sex Civil Marriage]
*[http://www.apa.org/releases/gaymarriage.html American Psychological Association]
*[http://uk.gay.com/headlines/6384 Same-sex marriage gets New York support]
*[http://www.nesl.edu/lawrev/vol38/3/5-Lerner-PDF.pdf New England Law Review: Why We Support Same-Sex Marriage: A Response From Over 450 Clergy]
*[http://www.eqca.org/site/pp.asp?c=9oINKWMCF&amp;b=40383 Equality California: EQCA MARRIAGE CENTER]
*[http://socialism.com/fsarticles/vol25no1/gaymarriage.html Lesbian and gay marriage: for better or for worse]
*[https://www.dialoguejournal.com/excerpts/33-3a.asp D Michael Quinn article; In defense of marriage.]

===Against Same-sex Marriage===
* [http://www.domawatch.org DOMA Watch]
* [http://www.allianceformarriage.org Alliance for Marriage]
* [http://www.rcm.org Religious Coalition for Marriage]
* [http://www.va4marriage.org Virginia for Marriage]
* [http://www.nogaymarriage.com No Gay Marriage]
* [http://www.mnmarriage.com Minnesota Citizens in Defense of Marriage]
* [http://realmarriage.org/ A Coalition to Protect Tennessee Marriage]
* [http://www.defenseofmarriagecoalition.org Oregon Defense of Marriage Coalition]
* [http://www.formarriage.org The Marriage Amendment Project]
* [http://www.marriagedebate.com Institute for Marriage and Public Policy]
* [http://www.findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m0377/is_156/ai_n6143562 The Liberal Case Against Gay Marriage]
* [http://www-tech.mit.edu/V124/N5/kolasinski.5c.html The Secular Case Against Gay Marriage]
* [http://web.archive.org/web/20040712233407/http://www.family.org/cforum/extras/a0032427.cfm Eleven Arguments Against Same-Sex Marriage, by. Dr. James Dobson]
* [http://www.lds.org/newsroom/showrelease/0,15503,3881-1-20336,00.html LDS First Presidency Statement on Same-Gender Marriage]
* [http://www.voteonmarriage.org/ Vote Against Same Sex Marriage in Mass.]
* [http://www.lds.org/library/display/0,4945,161-1-11-1,00.html The Family: A Proclamation to the World (LDS)]
* [http://www.sbc.net/aboutus/pssexuality.asp Southern Baptist Position Statement]
* [http://www.voteyesmarriage.com VoteYesMarriage.com: California Marriage Amendment]
* [http://www.whitehouse.gov/news/releases/2004/02/20040224-2.html President Calls for Constitutional Amendment Protecting Marriage]
* [http://www.florida4marriage.org Florida Coalition to Protect Marriage]
* [http://www.mafamily.org/ Massachusetts Family Institute]
* [http://www.maydayformarriage.com/ MayDay for Marriage]
* [http://www.frc.org/file.cfm?f=KEYWORD&amp;key=DP Family Research Council: Policy Publications on Same-sex Marriage]
* [http://www.weeklystandard.com/Content/Public/Articles/000/000/012/285fhdqe.asp?pg=1 Same-Sex Marriage: Hijacking the Civil Rights Legacy]
* [http://headlines.agapepress.org/archive/7/afa/282006a.asp Do Homosexuals Really Want to Get Married?]

===Informational===
* [http://www.nhhousegop.com/Reports/ExecSumm-p1-25.pdf Conclusions of a New Hampshire Legislative Panel on Same-Sex Marriage]

[[Category:Marriage, unions and partnerships by country|United States]]
[[Category:Same-sex marriage in the United States| ]]

{{link FA|nl}}

[[es:Matrimonio entre personas del mismo sexo en los Estados Unidos]]
[[nl:Homohuwelijk in de Verenigde Staten]]
[[zh:美国同性婚姻]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>