<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20101115001637|396806306" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="249623" pageid="249623" ns="0" title="Same-sex marriage in the United States"><revisions><rev timestamp="2010-11-15T13:13:45Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[Image:Samesexmarriage.jpg|thumb|thumb|250px|right|Same-sex marriage ceremony]]
'''Same-sex marriage''', also referred to as '''gay marriage''', is [[marriage]] between two persons of the same sex.  The [[federal government of the United States]] does not recognize the [[marriage]]s of same-sex couples and is prohibited from doing so by the [[Defense of Marriage Act]]. Nationwide, same-sex marriage is legal in three states as a result of a court ruling and in two others plus a district through a vote in their respective legislatures.

Same-sex marriages are currently granted by five of the 50  [[U.S. states|states]], one [[federal district]], and one [[Indian tribe]]:
* In [[Same-sex marriage in Connecticut|Connecticut]], [[Same-sex marriage in Iowa|Iowa]], [[Same-sex marriage in Massachusetts|Massachusetts]], [[Same-sex marriage in New Hampshire|New Hampshire]], [[Same-sex marriage in Vermont|Vermont]], and [[Same-sex marriage in the District of Columbia|Washington, D.C.]], marriages for same-sex couples are legal and currently performed.&lt;!--DO NOT ADD CALIFORNIA!! THE JUDGE STAYED HIS OWN RULING! http://www.nytimes.com/2010/08/05/us/05prop.html?_r=1--&gt;
* The [[Same-sex marriage under United States tribal jurisdictions#Coquille Tribe|Coquille Indian Tribe]] in [[Oregon]] also grants same-sex marriage.

State which previously granted same-sex marriage licenses:
* In [[Same-sex marriage in California|California]], same-sex marriages were performed between June 16, 2008, and November 4, 2008, after the [[California Supreme Court]] held the statutes limiting marriage to opposite-sex couples violated the [[California Constitution|state constitution]]; however, the California electorate then approved [[California Proposition 8 (2008)|California Proposition 8]], a voter initiative that made the ban part of California's constitution. The California Supreme Court upheld the voter-approved constitutional ban in ''[[Strauss v. Horton]]'', 207 P.3d 48 (Cal. 2009), holding that same-sex couples have all the rights of heterosexual couples, except the right to the "designation" of marriage and that such a holding does not violate California's privacy, equal protection, or due process laws.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.courtinfo.ca.gov/opinions/archive/S168047.PDF -- For a review see: Thomas Kupka, Names and Designations in Law, in: [http://www.jurisprudence.com.au/juris6/kupka.pdf ''The Journal Jurisprudence'' 6 (2010) 121-130].&lt;/ref&gt; Proposition 8 then was challenged in federal court in ''[[Perry v. Schwarzenegger]]''. On August 4, 2010, a federal judge ruled that California's ban on same-sex marriage was unconstitutional,&lt;ref&gt;[https://ecf.cand.uscourts.gov/cand/09cv2292/files/09cv2292-ORDER.pdf ''Perry et al v. Schwarzenegger et al'', No C 09-2292 VRW] ([[United States District Court for the Northern District of California]])&lt;/ref&gt; and stayed his ruling.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mercurynews.com/breaking-news/ci_15677141?nclick_check=1]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.nytimes.com/2010/08/05/us/05prop.html?_r=1 | work=The New York Times | title=U.S. Court Overturns Calif. Same-Sex Marriage Ban | first1=Jesse | last1=McKinley | first2=John | last2=Schwartz | date=August 4, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; On August 12, 2010, he ruled that marriages could resume on August 18, 2010, but the [[United States Court of Appeals for the Ninth Circuit]] stayed the ruling pending appeal.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/38671236/ns/us_news-life/&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.reuters.com/article/idUSTRE67G4Y820100817 | work=Reuters | title=California gay marriage case hangs on technicality | date=August 17, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

States which recognize same-sex marriage but have not granted same-sex marriage licenses:
* In [[Same-sex marriage in New York|New York]], [[Same-sex marriage in Rhode Island|Rhode Island]], and [[Recognition of same-sex unions in Maryland|Maryland]], same-sex marriages are recognized, but not performed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.freedomtomarry.org/states/ |title=States |publisher=Freedom to Marry |date=2010-04-16 |accessdate=2010-06-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=GET ON BOARD – MERI Announces Launch of Call For MERI |url=http://www.marriageequalityri.org/www/learn/marriage_faq/ |title=Marriage Equality Rhode Island: Marriage FAQ |publisher=Marriageequalityri.org |date= |accessdate=2010-06-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.glad.org/uploads/docs/publications/ri-marriage-guide.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

The movement to obtain [[Rights and responsibilities of marriages in the United States|marriage rights]] and benefits for same-sex couples in the [[United States]] began in the early 1970s. The issue became even more prominent in [[U.S. politics]] in the mid-1990s with a public backlash toward the idea evidenced by [[United States Congress|Congress]]' passage of the 1996 [[Defense of Marriage Act]]. However, in the opening decade of the 21st century, public support for its legalization has grown considerably.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.columbia.edu/~jrl2124/Lax_Phillips_Gay_Policy_Responsiveness_2009.pdf Gay Rights in the States: Public Opinion and Policy Responsiveness]&lt;/ref&gt; A poll taken between August 6–10, 2010 found support for allowing [[same-sex marriage]] in the [[United States]] over 50% for the first time. 52% of respondents answered the federal government should give legal recognition to marriages between couples of the same sex (46% in 2009), 46% were against (53% in 2009).&lt;ref name="AP 1"&gt;[http://surveys.ap.org/data%5CGfK%5CAP-GfK%20Poll%20August%20NCC%20topline.pdf The AP-National Constitution Center Poll]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="CNN 1"&gt;[http://i2.cdn.turner.com/cnn/2010/images/08/11/rel11a.pdf CNN Opinion Research]&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;!-- DO NOT ADD MORE POLL RESULTS HERE, SEEING THIS ONE POLL TAKES HAS SUPPORT OVER 50% FOR THE FIRST TIME THAT IS WHY IT IS HERE --&gt; [[New England]] has since became the center of an [[Gay &amp; Lesbian Advocates &amp; Defenders|organized push]] to legalize [[same-sex marriage]] in the U.S., with four of the six states comprising that region granting same-sex couples the legal right to marry. The issue remains politically divisive in the United States.

{{SSM}}

==Legal issues==
{{See also|Same-sex marriage legislation in the United States}}

===Federal law===
The legal issues surrounding same-sex marriage in the United States are complicated by the nation's [[federalism|federal]] system of government. Traditionally, the federal government did not attempt to establish its own definition of marriage; any marriage recognized by a [[U.S. state|state]] was recognized by the federal government, even if that marriage was not recognized by one or more other states (as was the case with [[Anti-miscegenation laws|interracial marriage]] before 1967 due to [[anti-miscegenation laws]]). With the passage of the [[Defense of Marriage Act]] ("DOMA") in 1996, however, a marriage was explicitly defined as a union of one man and one woman for the purposes of federal law. (See {{usc|1|7}}.)

DOMA has been under challenge in the federal courts, and on July 8, 2010, Judge [[Joseph Louis Tauro|Joseph Tauro]] of the [[United States District Court for the District of Massachusetts|District Court of Massachusetts]] held that the denial of federal rights and benefits to lawfully married Massachusetts same-sex couples under the [[Defense of Marriage Act|DOMA]] is unconstitutional, under the [[Tenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Tenth Amendment]] to the [[United States Constitution|US Constitution]].&lt;ref name="hrc.org"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.hrc.org/14624.htm|title=Federal Court Declares Part of Defense of Marriage Act Unconstitutional|date=July 8, 2010|accessdate=July 9, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="politicalticker.blogs.cnn.com"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://politicalticker.blogs.cnn.com/2010/07/09/judge-rules-federal-same-sex-marriage-ban-unconstitutional/?iref=allsearch&amp;fbid=2-HnSdp2S6g|title=Judge rules federal same-sex marriage ban unconstitutional|work=CNN|date=July 9, 2010|accessdate=July 9, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; This ruling is currently under a [[Stay of proceedings|stay]], but would affect residents residing within the federal district that covers Massachusetts if the stay is lifted.  If this decision is appealed and affirmed, the ruling could apply elsewhere in the U.S.  For now, no act or agency of the federal government—except within the state of Massachusetts if the stay is lifted—may recognize same-sex marriage.

According to the federal government's [[Government Accountability Office]] (GAO), [[Rights and responsibilities of marriages in the United States|more than 1,138 rights and protections]] are conferred to U.S. citizens upon marriage by the federal government; areas affected include Social Security benefits, veterans' benefits, health insurance, Medicaid, hospital visitation, estate taxes, retirement savings, pensions, family leave, and immigration law.

However, many aspects of marriage law affecting the day to day lives of inhabitants of the United States are determined by the states, not the federal government, and the Defense of Marriage Act does not prevent individual states from defining marriage as they see fit.

The United States Supreme Court in 1972 dismissed ''[[Baker v. Nelson]]'', a case originating in Minnesota, "for want of a substantial federal question".  The [[Defense of Marriage Act]], as well as marriage laws in 45 states, could be affected by the outcome of ''[[Perry v. Schwarzenegger]]'', a case challenging the validity of [[California Proposition 8 (2008)|California's Proposition 8]] under the [[United States Constitution]].&lt;ref name="protectmarriage.com"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.protectmarriage.com/trial |title=Yes on 8 » Perry v. Schwarzenegger |publisher=Protect Marriage |date=2010-06-16 |accessdate=2010-06-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===State law===
{{further|[[Same-sex legal relationships in USA]]}}
{{See|Same-sex marriage law in the United States by state}}
{{Samesex marriage in USA map|align=left|size=350px}}

Five state governments offer same-sex marriage: [[Massachusetts]], [[Connecticut]], [[Iowa]], [[Vermont]], and [[New Hampshire]].&lt;ref name="Adams &amp; Crary 11-03-2009"&gt;Glenn Adams and David Crary, [http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/feedarticle/8789627 "Maine voters reject gay-marriage law"], November 4, 2009&lt;/ref&gt; In all five cases this has been achieved through legislation or court ruling.&lt;ref name="Adams &amp; Crary 11-03-2009"/&gt; As of November 2009, when legislation legalizing same-sex marriage in Maine was defeated by referendum, same-sex marriage had been defeated in all 31 states in which it had been directly put to a popular vote.&lt;ref name="Adams &amp; Crary 11-03-2009"/&gt;  Thirty states have passed constitutional amendments prohibiting same-sex marriage.&lt;ref name="Adams &amp; Crary 11-03-2009"/&gt;

Same-sex marriage has been legal in [[Same-sex marriage in Massachusetts|Massachusetts]] since November 18, 2003; in [[Same-sex marriage in Connecticut|Connecticut]] since October 10, 2008 (having previously legalized civil unions in October 2005);&lt;ref&gt;"[http://www.courant.com/news/politics/hc-gaymarriage1011.artoct11,0,5399554.story State Supreme Court Legalizes Same-Sex Marriage]", ''[[Hartford Courant]]''&lt;/ref&gt; in [[Same-sex marriage in Iowa|Iowa]] since April 27, 2009;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.365gay.com/news/iowa-supreme-court-strikes-down-gay-marriage-ban/ |title=Iowa Supreme Court strikes down gay marriage ban &amp;#124; News Story on |publisher=365gay.com |date= |accessdate=2010-06-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="365gay.com"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.365gay.com/news/iowa-gay-marriages-delayed/ |title=Iowa gay marriages delayed &amp;#124; News Story on |publisher=365gay.com |date= |accessdate=2010-06-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; in [[Same-sex marriage in Vermont|Vermont]] since September 1, 2009; and in [[Same-sex marriage in New Hampshire|New Hampshire]] since January 1, 2010.

Same-sex marriage is recognized only at the state level, as the federal [[Defense of Marriage Act]] explicitly bars federal recognition of such marriages.

Opponents of same-sex marriage have attempted to prevent individual states from recognizing same-sex unions by attempting to amend the [[United States Constitution]] to define marriage as a union between one man and one woman. In 2006, the [[Federal Marriage Amendment]], which would prohibit states from recognizing same-sex marriages, was approved by the [[United States Senate Committee on the Judiciary|Senate Judiciary Committee]], on a party-line vote, and was debated by the full United States Senate, but was ultimately defeated in both houses of Congress.&lt;ref&gt;"[http://www.cnn.com/2006/POLITICS/06/07/same.sex.marriage/index.html Senate blocks same-sex marriage ban]", [[CNN]], June 7, 2006, . Retrieved July 5, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

The right to marry was first extended to same-sex couples by a United States jurisdiction on November 18, 2003, in Massachusetts by a state Supreme Judicial Court ruling.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.boston.com/news/local/massachusetts/articles/2003/11/18/sjc_gay_marriage_legal_in_mass/ |title=/ News / Local / Mass. / SJC: Gay marriage legal in Mass |publisher=Boston.com |date=2003-11-18 |accessdate=2010-06-27 | first1=Kathleen | last1=Burge}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On May 15, 2008, the [[Supreme Court of California]] issued a decision in which it effectively legalized same-sex marriage in [[California]], holding that California's existing opposite-sex definition of marriage violated the constitutional rights of same-sex couples.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.cnn.com/2008/US/05/15/same.sex.marriage/index.html |title=California same-sex marriage ban struck down |publisher=Cnn.com |date= May 16, 2008|accessdate=2010-06-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="mercury_mintz"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.mercurynews.com/breakingnews/ci_9269719|title=California Supreme Court legalizes same-sex marriage|last=Mintz|first=Howard|date=May 15, 2008|publisher=Mercury News|language=en|accessdate=2008-05-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; Same-sex marriage opponents in California placed a state constitutional amendment known as [[California Proposition 8 (2008)|Proposition 8]] on the November ballot for the purpose of restoring an opposite-sex definition of marriage;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2008/05/16/us/15cnd-scene.html?bl&amp;ex=1210996800&amp;en=184fe9e64c13a342&amp;ei=5087%0A nytimes.com, Gay Couples Rejoice at Ruling]&lt;/ref&gt;  Proposition 8 was passed on Election Day 2008, as were proposed marriage-limiting amendments in Florida and Arizona.&lt;ref&gt;"[http://www.nytimes.com/2008/11/06/us/politics/06marriage.html Bans in 3 States on Gay Marriage]"&lt;/ref&gt;  The [[California Proposition 8 (2008)#Legal challenges|California amendment was challenged]] in a court proceeding, but was upheld by the state supreme court, in a 6–1 vote, on May 26, 2009.  The court ruled, however, that the approximately 18,000 same-sex marriages that took place in 2008 would remain valid. On October 12, 2009, [[Arnold Schwarzenegger|Governor Schwarzenegger]] signed SB 54, which allowed all out-of-state same-sex marriages to be given the benefits of marriage under California law, although only those performed before November 5, 2008 will be granted the designation "marriage". On October 10, 2008, the Connecticut Supreme Court overturned the state's civil-unions statute (2005), as unconstitutionally discriminating against same-sex couples, and required the state to recognize same-sex marriages.

Same-sex marriage was legalized in [[Iowa]] following the unanimous ruling of the [[Iowa Supreme Court]] in ''[[Varnum v. Brien]]'' on April 3, 2009.&lt;ref&gt;''[http://www.desmoinesregister.com/article/20090403/NEWS/90403010 Unanimous ruling: Iowa marriage no longer limited to one man, one woman]'', ''[[Des Moines Register]]'', April 3, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;  This was initially to take effect on April 24, but the date was changed to April 27 for administrative reasons.&lt;ref name="365gay.com"/&gt;

On April 7, 2009, [[Vermont]] legalized same-sex marriage through legislation. The Governor had previously vetoed the measure, but the veto was overridden by the Legislature. Vermont became the first state in the United States to legalize same-sex marriage through legislation, as opposed to litigation, albeit without the governor's signature. On the same day, the City Council of the federal District of Columbia passed a bill by a 12–1 vote that recognizes same-sex marriages performed elsewhere.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://voices.washingtonpost.com/dc/2009/05/dc_council_votes_to_recognize.html | work=The Washington Post | title=D.C. Council Votes 12–1 to Recognize Other States' Gay Marriages | accessdate=May 23, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On May 6, 2009, Maine became the fifth state to legalize same-sex marriage.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.maine.gov/tools/whatsnew/index.php?topic=Gov+News&amp;id=72146&amp;v=Article-2006 |title=Office of the Governor: News &amp; Events: News Releases |publisher=Maine.gov |date=2009-05-06 |accessdate=2010-06-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; The legislation was overturned by referendum in November 2009.&lt;ref name="Adams &amp; Crary 11-03-2009"/&gt;

On June 3, 2009, New Hampshire became the sixth state to legalize same-sex marriage.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gencourt.state.nh.us/legislation/2009/HB0436.html |title=hb 0436 |publisher=Gencourt.state.nh.us |date= |accessdate=2010-06-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As of June 1, 2009, [[Recognition of same-sex unions in New Jersey|New Jersey]] has created legal unions that, while not called marriages, are explicitly defined as offering all the rights and responsibilities of marriage under state (though not federal) law to same-sex couples. [[Domestic partnership in California|California]], [[Recognition of same-sex unions in Colorado|Colorado]], [[Recognition of same-sex unions in Hawaii|Hawaii]], [[Domestic partnership in Maine|Maine]], [[Recognition of same-sex unions in Maryland|Maryland]], [[Recognition of same-sex unions in Nevada|Nevada]], [[Domestic partnership in Oregon|Oregon]], [[Same-sex marriage in Rhode Island|Rhode Island]], [[Recognition of same-sex unions in Wisconsin|Wisconsin]] and [[Domestic partnership in Washington|Washington]] have created legal unions for same-sex couples that offer varying subsets of the rights and responsibilities of marriage under the laws of those jurisdictions.

On December 7, 2009, the New Jersey Senate Judiciary Committee narrowly approved a bill to allow same-sex marriage, on a vote of 7 to 6.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2009/12/08/nyregion/08marriage.html?_r=1&amp;hp|title=Senate Panel in N.J. Approves Gay Marriage Bill |date=2009-12-07 | work=The New York Times | first=David | last=Kocieniewski}}&lt;/ref&gt; The full Senate rejected the bill a month later, on January 7, 2010, on a vote of 20 to 14.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nj.com/news/index.ssf/2010/01/nj_senate_rejects_bill_legaliz.html|title=N.J. Senate rejects bill legalizing gay marriage|date=2010-01-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As of January 1, 2009, thirty states have constitutional amendments explicitly barring the recognition of same-sex marriage, defining civil marriage as a legal union between a man and a woman.&lt;ref&gt;"[http://www.nytimes.com/2008/11/06/us/politics/06marriage.html Number of states]", [[NYTimes.com]]&lt;/ref&gt;  More than forty states explicitly restrict marriage to two persons of the opposite sex, including some of those that have created legal recognition for same-sex unions under a name other than "marriage", e.g., civil unions and domestic partnerships.{{Citation needed|date=January 2009}}  Nineteen states ban any legal recognition of same-sex unions that would be equivalent to civil marriage.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hrc.org/documents/marriage_prohibitions_2009.pdf Statewide Marriage Prohibitions] plus Kansas http://www.kslib.info/constitution/art15.html&lt;/ref&gt;  New York courts have ruled that same-sex marriages conducted in states where they are legal must be recognized by those states, but that the state statutes do not allow the issuance of same-sex marriage licenses&amp;nbsp;— as a result New York now has same-sex divorces without allowing same-sex weddings.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.nycourts.gov/ad4/court/Decisions/2008/02-01-08/PDF/1562.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; New Jersey only recognized same-sex marriages for the purpose of divorce, otherwise they are converted to Civil Unions.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.aclu-nj.org/news/aclunjwinscaseallowingsame.htm|title=ACLU-NJ Wins Case Allowing Same-Sex Couple To Divorce in NJ|date=2009-02-06|accessdate=2009-08-03|publisher=[[American Civil Liberties Union]]}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On August 4, 2010, a decision by the US District Court in ''[[Perry v. Schwarzenegger]]'' ruled Proposition 8 unconstitutional.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite court |litigants=Perry v. Schwarzenegger  |court=US District Court, Northern California |date=August 4, 2010 |url=http://www.scribd.com/doc/35374462/Prop-8-Ruling-FINAL }}&lt;/ref&gt; This ruling is expected to affect all same-sex marriage bans in the United States. An appeal will be heard by the [[United States Court of Appeals for the Ninth Circuit]] the week of December 6,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news
  | last = Advocate.com editors
  | title = Ninth Circuit: Marriages on Hold
  | publisher = Advocate.com
  | date = 2010-08-16
  | url = http://advocate.com/News/Daily_News/2010/08/16/9th_Circuit_Blocks_Calif__Marriages/
  | accessdate = 2010-08-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; with the case anticipated to be ultimately decided by the US Supreme Court.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.cnn.com/2010/US/08/04/california.same.sex.ruling/index.html?hpt=T1 | work=CNN | title=Judge strikes down California's ban on same-sex marriage | accessdate=August 4, 2010 | date=August 5, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Pennsylvania state senator [[John Eichelberger]] plans to introduce a constitutional amendment banning same-sex marriage in Pennsylvania. However, Senator [[Daylin Leach]] has introduced a bill that would legalize same-sex marriage.&lt;ref name="advocate-pa-ban"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.advocate.com/news_detail_ektid84636.asp|title=Pa. Senator Introduces Gay Marriage Ban|date=May 19, 2009|work=[[The Advocate]]|accessdate=2009-05-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="pdn-pa-ban"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.philly.com/dailynews/local/20090519_Polls_show_Pa__resisting_tide_favoring_gay_marriage.html|title=Polls show Pa. resisting tide favoring gay marriage|last=Bunch|first=Will|date=Tue, May. 19, 2009|work=Philadelphia Daily News|accessdate=2009-05-19}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===International recognition of marriages===
{{Unreferenced section|date=September 2010}}

Same-sex marriage conducted abroad is recognized in the U.S. States of [[Same-sex marriage in New York|New York]], [[Same-sex marriage in California|California]], [[Same-sex marriage in Rhode Island|Rhode Island]], and [[Recognition of same-sex unions in Maryland|Maryland]], and in [[Recognition of same-sex unions in the District of Columbia|Washington, D.C.]].

The nationwide legalization of [[same-sex marriage in Canada]] has raised questions about U.S. law, because of Canada's proximity to the U.S. and the fact that Canada has no citizenship or residency requirement to receive a marriage certificate (unlike [[same-sex marriage in Belgium|Belgium]] and the [[same-sex marriage in the Netherlands|Netherlands]]). Canada and the U.S. have a history of respecting marriages contracted in either country.

Immediately after the June 2003 ruling legalizing [[same-sex marriage in Ontario]], a number of American couples went or planned to go to the province in order to get married. A coalition of American national [[gay rights]] groups issued a statement asking couples to contact them before attempting legal challenges, so that they might be coordinated as part of the same-sex marriage movement in the United States.{{Citation needed|date=February 2007}}

==Debate==

{{Undue|date=July 2010}}

President Barack Obama has stated that he is against same-sex marriage&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
  | last =
  | first =
  | title = ElectionCenter2008
  | publisher = CNN
  | date =
  | url = http://www.cnn.com/ELECTION/2008/issues/issues.samesexmarriage.html
  | accessdate = October 3, 2009}}
&lt;/ref&gt; while remaining sympathetic to human-rights.&lt;ref name="whitehouse"&gt;{{cite web |author= |title= ''the'' WHITE HOUSE ''PRESIDENT BARACK OBAMA'': Civil Rights|url= http://www.whitehouse.gov/issues/CIVIL_RIGHTS/|work= |publisher= |date= |accessdate=October 3, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; The president "supports full civil unions and federal rights for LGBT couples and opposes a constitutional ban on same-sex marriage."&lt;ref name="whitehouse" /&gt; He opposes a federal mandate for same-sex marriage, and also opposes the [[Defense of Marriage Act|proposed federal ban]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.independent.com/news/2009/jan/13/gay-supporters-petition-obama-repeal-doma/|title=Gay Supporters Petition Obama to Repeal DOMA|date=2009-01-13|accessdate=2009-06-24|first=Penny|last=Paterson|publisher=[[Santa Barbara Independent]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; on gay marriage, arguing that the individual states should decide.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
  | last = Eleveld
  | first = Kerry
  | title = White House Responds to Iowa
  | publisher = [[The Advocate]]
  | date = 2009-04-03
  | url = http://www.advocate.com/news_detail_ektid77464.asp
  | accessdate = 2009-06-17}}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.cnn.com/ELECTION/2008/issues/issues.samesexmarriage.html | work=CNN | title=Same-sex Marriage - Issues - Election Center 2008 - CNN.com | accessdate=May 23, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Obama opposed Proposition 8—California's constitutional ban on gay marriage—in 2008, and may have made comments in support of same-sex marriage during his Illinois Senate race in the 1990s,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.foxnews.com/politics/2009/01/15/report-obama-changed-view-gay-marriage/ |title=Report: Obama Changed His View on Gay Marriage |publisher=FOXNews.com |date=2010-04-07 |accessdate=2010-06-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; while he subsequently opposed same-sex marriage in the 2008 presidential election.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title= Same sex marriage issues-election center 2008-CNN.com|url= http://www.cnn.com/ELECTION/2008/issues/issues.samesexmarriage.html|date= |work= |publisher= |accessdate=14 September 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Support===
{{See also|List of supporters of same-sex marriage in the United States}}
[[File:Prop 8 Rally in Market St.jpg|thumb|250px|Rally for same-sex marriage (May 2009, San Francisco, California)]]

Same-sex marriage supporters make several arguments in support of their position. [[Mark Mathabane|Gail Mathabane]] likens prohibitions on same-sex marriage to past prohibitions on interracial marriage.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.usatoday.com/news/opinion/editorials/2004-01-25-couples_x.htm | work=USA Today | title=Gays face same battle interracial couples fought | first=Gail | last=Mathabane | date=January 25, 2004 | accessdate=May 23, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Fernando Espuelas argues that same-sex marriage should be allowed because same-sex marriage extends a civil right to a minority group.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.cnn.com/2008/POLITICS/11/06/espuelas.prop.eight/ | work=CNN | title=Commentary: Latinos should see gay marriage a civil right - CNN.com | date=November 7, 2008 | accessdate=May 23, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to an American history scholar Nancy Cott "there really is no comparison, because there is nothing that is like marriage except marriage."&lt;ref name="cott"&gt;[http://www.equalrightsfoundation.org/wp-content/uploads/2010/01/Perry-Vol-1-1-11-10.pdf]&lt;/ref&gt;

Supports argue that there is no scientific basis for distinguishing between heterosexual couples and same-sex couples with respect to the legal rights, obligations, benefits and burdens conferred by civil marriage. Gay men and lesbians form stable, committed relationships that are equivalent to heterosexual relationships in essential aspects. Lesbian and gay parents are as fit and capable as heterosexual parents, and their children are as psychologically healthy and well-adjusted as children reared by heterosexual parents.&lt;ref name="amici"&gt;[http://www.ca9.uscourts.gov/datastore/general/2010/10/27/amicus29.pdf Brief of the American Psychological Association, The California Psychological Association, the American Psychiatric Association, and the American Association for Marriage and Family Therapy as amici curiae in support of plaintiff-appellees - Appeal from United States District Court for the Northern District of California Civil Case No. 09-CV-2292 VRW (Honorable Vaughn R. Walker)]&lt;/ref&gt; Financial, psychological and physical well-being are enhanced by marriage, and [[LGBT parenting|children of same-sex couples]] benefit from being raised by two parents within a legally-recognized union supported by society’s institutions.&lt;ref name="amici"/&gt;&lt;ref name=cpa2006&gt;[http://www.cpa.ca/cpasite/userfiles/Documents/Marriage%20of%20Same-Sex%20Couples%20Position%20Statement%20-%20October%202006%20(1).pdf Marriage of Same-Sex Couples – 2006 Position Statement Canadian Psychological Association]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=pediatrics&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Pawelski JG, Perrin EC, Foy JM, ''et al.'' |title=The effects of marriage, civil union, and domestic partnership laws on the health and well-being of children |journal=Pediatrics |volume=118 |issue=1 |pages=349–64 |year=2006 |month=July |pmid=16818585 |doi=10.1542/peds.2006-1279}} available online: http://pediatrics.aappublications.org/cgi/content/full/118/1/349&lt;/ref&gt; The stigma created by states differential treatment of gay men
and women has severe psychological and social impacts. Singling out gay men and women as ineligible for the institution of
marriage invites the public to discriminate against them. Depriving same-sex couples of the ability to marry has adverse
effects on their children.&lt;ref name="amici2"&gt;[http://www.ca9.uscourts.gov/datastore/general/2010/10/27/amicus39.pdf Brief of Amici Curiae American Anthropological Association, American Psychoanalytic Association, National Association of Social Workers, National Association of Social Workers, California Chapter, American Sociological Association, and American Academy of Pediatrics, California, supporting plaintiffs-appellees and urging affirmance - Appeal from United States District Court for the Northern District of California Civil Case No. 09-CV-2292 VRW (Honorable Vaughn R. Walker)]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Opposition===

{{See also|Opponents of same-sex marriage in the United States}}

[[File:Fresno - Prop 8 Rally.jpg|thumb|250px|Rally for Prop 8 in Fresno, California (October 2008)]]

[[Vaughn R. Walker]] found in ''[[Perry v. Schwarzenegger]]'' political scientist Gary Segura to be an amply qualified expert witness as his education and experience show to offer testimony that religion is "the chief obstacle to gay and lesbian political advances".&lt;ref name="ORDER"&gt;[https://ecf.cand.uscourts.gov/cand/09cv2292/files/09cv2292-ORDER.pdf United States District Court for the Northern District of California]&lt;/ref&gt; He noted that political scientist Kenneth Miller disagreed that gays and lesbians lack political power. Having considered Miller’s background, experience and testimony, the court concluded that, Miller is not sufficiently familiar with gay and lesbian politics specifically to offer opinions on gay and lesbian political power.&lt;ref name="ORDER" /&gt;

===Marriage privatization===
{{Main|Marriage privatization}}

A libertarian argument for [[marriage privatization]] holds that government has no role in defining the terms whereby individuals contract to arrange their personal relationships, regardless of sexual orientation.&lt;ref name=Lindenberger&gt;Lindenberger, M., [http://www.time.com/time/nation/article/0,8599,1885190,00.html?xid=rss-topstories "A Gay-Marriage Solution: End Marriage?"] in ''Newsweek'', Mar. 16, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Kinsella&gt;Kinsella, S. [http://www.lewrockwell.com/blog/lewrw/archives/010707.html "Libertarian View on Gay Marriage"] in ''LewRockwell.com'', June 6, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Boaz&gt;{{cite web|author=&amp;ldquo;&amp;rdquo; |url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=aXrUdgTMG4E |title=Boaz, D., speech to Commonwealth Club of California |publisher=Youtube.com |date= |accessdate=2010-11-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; People holding this viewpoint argue that government should have a limited role or no role in defining marriage, only in enforcing those contracts people construct themselves and willfully enter.  The rights granted to a married couple exceed those that can be mutually granted by two people to each other contractually, and also involve rights granted by government.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.theatlantic.com/doc/200404u/int2004-04-23 |title=A Modest (Marriage) Proposal |publisher=Theatlantic.com |date=2004-04-09 |accessdate=2010-11-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://meganmcardle.theatlantic.com/archives/2008/05/the_libertarian_argument_for_g.php |title=The Libertarian Argument For Gay Marriage |publisher=Meganmcardle.theatlantic.com |date=2008-05-28 |accessdate=2010-11-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Boaz |first=David |url=http://www.slate.com/id/2440/ |title=Privatize Marriage |publisher=Slate.com |date=1997-04-25 |accessdate=2010-11-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Public opinion==
{{Main|Public opinion of same-sex marriage in the United States }}
Public support for same-sex marriage has grown. In 1996, 25% of Americans supported legalization. 

A May, 2010 [[Gallup Poll]] found opponents of legalizing same-sex marriage outnumbered supporters in the United States, by 53% to 44% (59% to 37% in 2005). Opposition was tied for the lowest Gallup has measured.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gallup.com/poll/128291/americans-opposition-gay-marriage-eases-slightly.aspx Americans' Opposition to Gay Marriage Eases Slightly]&lt;/ref&gt;

A poll taken between August 6–10, 2010 found growing support for allowing [[same-sex marriage]] in the [[United States]]. 52% of respondents answered the federal government should give legal recognition to marriages between couples of the same sex (46% in 2009), 46% were against (53% in 2009).&lt;ref name="AP 1"/&gt;&lt;ref name="CNN 1"/&gt;

==Effects of same-sex marriage==
===Economic impact on same-sex couples===
Dr. M. V. Lee Badgett, an economist and associate professor at the [[University of Massachusetts Amherst]], has studied the impact of same-sex legal marriage on same-sex couples.  According to a 1997 [[General Accounting Office]] study requested by Rep. [[Henry Hyde]] (R), at least 1,049 U.S. Federal laws and regulations include reference to marital status.&lt;ref&gt;Dang, Alain, and M. Somjen Frazer.. "Black Same-Sex Couple Households in the 2000 U.S. Census: Implications in the Debate Over Same-Sex Marriage." Western Journal of Black Studies 29.1 (Spring2005 2005): 521–530. Academic Search Premier. EBSCO. 30 Sep. 2009&lt;/ref&gt; A later 2004 study by the [[Congressional Budget Office]] finds 1,138 statutory provisions "in which marital status is a factor in determining or receiving 'benefits, rights, and privileges.'"&lt;ref name=cbo1&gt;{{cite journal
|url=http://www.cbo.gov/doc.cfm?index=5559
|title=The Potential Budgetary Impact of Recognizing Same-Sex Marriages
|publisher=Congressional Budget Office
|date=21 June 2004
|accessdate=8 March 2007
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many of these laws govern property rights, benefits, and taxation. Same-sex couples are ineligible for spousal and survivor [[Social Security (United States)|Social Security]] benefits.&lt;ref name=cbo1 /&gt; Badgett's research finds the resulting difference in Social Security income for same-sex couples compared to opposite-sex married couples is US$5,588 per year. The federal ban on same-sex marriage and benefits through the 1996 [[Defense of Marriage Act]] (DOMA) extends to federal government employee benefits.&lt;ref name=cbo1 /&gt; According to Badgett's work, same-sex couples face other financial challenges against which legal marriage at least partially shields opposite-sex couples.&lt;ref name="Badgett"&gt;{{cite book|last=Badgett|first=M.V. Lee|title=Money, Myths, and Change: The Economic Lives of Lesbians and Gay Men|publisher=University Of Chicago Press|location=Chicago|year=2003|isbn=0226034011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* potential loss of couple's home from medical expenses of one partner caring for another gravely ill one&lt;ref name="Badgett" /&gt;
* costs of supporting two households, travel, or emigration out of the U.S. for an American citizen unable to legally marry a non-U.S. citizen&lt;ref name="Badgett" /&gt;
* higher cost of purchasing private insurance for partner and children if company is not one of 18% that offer domestic partner benefits&lt;ref name="Badgett" /&gt;
* higher taxes: unlike a company's contribution to an employee's spouse's health insurance, domestic partner benefits are taxed as additional compensation&lt;ref name=cbo1 /&gt;
* legal costs associated with obtaining domestic partner documents to gain some of the power of attorney, health care decision-making, and inheritance rights granted through legal marriage&lt;ref name="Badgett" /&gt;
* higher health costs associated with lack of insurance and preventative care: 20% of same-sex couples have a member who is uninsured compared to 10% of married opposite-sex couples&lt;ref name="Badgett" /&gt;
* current tax law allows a spouse to inherit an unlimited amount from the deceased without incurring an estate tax but an unmarried partner would have to pay the estate tax on the inheritance from her/his partner&lt;ref name=cbo1 /&gt;
* same-sex couples are not eligible to file jointly or separately as a married couple and thus cannot take the advantages of lower tax rates when the individual income of the partners differs significantly&lt;ref name=cbo1 /&gt;

While state laws grant full marriage rights ([[Connecticut]], [[Iowa]], [[Massachusetts]], [[New Hampshire]] and [[Vermont]]) or some or all of the benefits under another name ([[New Jersey]], [[Washington (U.S. state)|Washington]], [[California]], etc.), these state laws do not extend the benefits of marriage on the Federal level, and most states do not currently recognize same-sex marriages, domestic partnerships, or civil unions from other states.

One often overlooked aspect of same-sex marriage are the potential ''negative'' effects on same-sex couples. While the legal benefits of marriage are numerous, same-sex couples would face the same financial constraints of legal marriage as opposite-sex married couples. Such potential effects include the [[marriage penalty]] in taxation.&lt;ref name=cbo1 /&gt; Similarly, while social service providers usually do not count one partner's assets toward the income means test for welfare and disability assistance for the other partner, a legally married couple's joint assets are normally used in calculating whether a married individual qualifies for assistance.&lt;ref name=cbo1 /&gt;

===Economic impact on the federal government===
The 2004 Congressional Budget Office] study, working from an assumption "that about 0.6 percent of adults would enter into same-sex marriages if they had the opportunity" (an assumption in which they admitted "significant uncertainty") estimated that legalizing same-sex marriage throughout the United States "would improve the budget's bottom line to a small extent: by less than $1 billion in each of the next 10 years". This result reflects an increase in net government revenues (increased income taxes due to marriage penalties more than offsetting decreased tax revenues arising from postponed estate taxes). Marriage recognition would increase the government expenses for Social Security and Federal Employee Health Benefits but that increase would be more than made up for by decreased expenses for Medicaid, Medicare, and Supplemental Security Income.&lt;ref name=cbo1 /&gt;

===Mental health===

Decades of research have confirmed that stigmatized people are ostracized, devalued, rejected, scorned, and shunned, experiencing discrimination, insults, attacks, and even murder. This is particularly true for gay men and women, a stigmatized group that has suffered a well-documented history of ostracization, discrimination, and violence. Based in part on the sound and comprehensive empirical research that has been conducted on the adverse effects of stigmatization, numerous prominent social sciences organizations, have issued position statements supporting same-sex marriage and opposing discrimination on the basis of sexual orientation, including the the American Psychoanalytic Association and the American Psychological Association.&lt;ref name="amici2"/&gt;

Several psychological studies&lt;ref name=autogenerated5&gt;Price, M. "UPFRONT&amp;nbsp;— Research uncovers the stress created by same-sex marriage bans" in ''Monitor on Psychology'', Volume 40, No. 1, page 10, January 2009. Washington DC: American Psychological Association. [http://www.apa.org/monitor/2009/01/marriage-bans.html]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Potoczniak, Daniel J.; Aldea, Mirela A.; DeBlaere, Cirleen "Ego identity, social anxiety, social support, and self-concealment in lesbian, gay, and bisexual individuals." ''Journal of Counseling Psychology,'' Vol 54(4), Oct 2007, 447–457.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
Balsam, Kimberly F.; Mohr, Jonathan J. "Adaptation to sexual orientation stigma: A comparison of bisexual and lesbian/gay adults." ''Journal of Counseling Psychology,'' Vol 54(3), Jul 2007, 306–319.
&lt;/ref&gt; have shown that an increase in exposure to negative conversations and media messages about same-sex marriage creates a harmful environment for the LGBT population that may affect their health and well-being.

One study surveyed more than 1,500 lesbian, gay and bisexual adults across the nation and found that respondents from the 25 states that have outlawed same-sex marriage had the highest reports of "minority stress"&amp;nbsp;— the chronic social stress that results from minority-group stigmatization&amp;nbsp;— as well as general psychological distress. According to the study, the negative campaigning that comes with a ban is directly responsible for the increased stress. Past research has shown that minority stress is linked to health risks such as risky sexual behavior and substance abuse.&lt;ref name=autogenerated4&gt;Rostosky, Sharon Scales; Riggle, Ellen D. B.; Gray, Barry E.; Hatton, Roxanna L. "Minority stress experiences in committed same-sex couple relationships." ''Professional Psychology: Research and Practice,'' Vol 38(4), Aug 2007, 392–400.&lt;/ref&gt;

Two other studies examined personal reports from LGBT adults and their families living in [[Memphis, Tennessee]], immediately after a successful 2006 ballot campaign banned same-sex marriage. Most respondents reported feeling alienated from their communities, afraid that they would lose custody of their children and that they might become victims of violence. The studies also found that families experienced a kind of secondary minority stress, says Jennifer Arm, a counseling graduate student at the [[University of Memphis]].&lt;ref&gt;Szymanski, Dawn M.; Carr, Erika R. "The roles of gender role conflict and internalized heterosexism in gay and bisexual men's psychological distress: Testing two mediation models." ''Psychology of Men &amp; Masculinity,'' Vol 9(1), Jan 2008, 40–54.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Physical health===

In 2009, a pair of economists at [[Emory University]] tied the passage of state bans on same-sex marriage in the US to an increase in the rates of [[HIV]] infection.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sovo.com/2009/6-12/news/localnews/10213.cfm Emory researchers: Gay marriage bans increase HIV infections]{{Dead link|date=June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Contact:&amp;#160; Elaine Justice: 404.727.0643 |url=http://www.emory.edu/home/news/releases/2009/06/study-links-gay-marriage-bans-to-rise-in-hiv-rate.html |title=Study Links Gay Marriage Bans to Rise in HIV infections |publisher=Emory.edu |date= |accessdate=2010-06-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; The study linked the passage of same-sex marriage ban in a state to an increase in the annual HIV rate within that state of roughly 4 cases per 100,000 population.

==Timeline of major events==
* October 10, 1972: The [[United States Supreme Court]] dismisses appeal in ''[[Baker v. Nelson]]'' "for want of a substantial federal question".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite court
  |litigants = Baker v. Nelson
  |vol = 409
  |reporter = U.S.
  |opinion = 810
  |court = Supreme Court of the United States
  |date = 1972-10-10
  |url= }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* May 5, 1993: The [[Supreme Court of Hawaii]] rules that statute limiting marriage to opposite-sex couples is presumed to be unconstitutional unless the state can show that it is (1) justified by compelling state interests and (2) narrowly drawn to avoid unnecessary abridgements of rights under the [[Constitution of Hawaii|Hawaii Constitution]]. The case is sent back to the lower courts for a trial on these two issues.&lt;ref&gt;Baehr v. Lewin 74 Haw. 530, 852 P.2d 44 (1993), reconsideration and clarification granted in part, 74 Haw. 645, 852 P.2d 74 (1993)&lt;/ref&gt;
* September 21, 1996: [[Bill Clinton|President Bill Clinton]] signs into law the [[Defense of Marriage Act]], denying federal recognition of same-sex marriages.
* December 3, 1996: A Hawaii trial court judge holds that no compelling interests support Hawaii's statute limiting marriage to opposite-sex couples. He stays the decision pending review by the Supreme Court of Hawaii.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://data.lambdalegal.org/pdf/legal/baehr/baehr-v-miike-decision.pdf |format=PDF |title=Trial-court decision in ''Baehr v. Miike''|date=1996-12-03 |publisher=First Circuit Court, State of Hawaii |accessdate=2009-06-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://archives.starbulletin.com/specials/samesex.html |title=Coverage of Hawaii same-sex marriage cases |publisher=Honolulu Star-Bulletin |accessdate=2009-06-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* November 3, 1998: Hawaii voters pass a [[Hawaii Constitutional Amendment 2 (1998)|constitutional amendment]] to give the [[Hawaii State Legislature]] the power to reserve marriage to opposite-sex couples.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite document|publisher=Hawaii Office of Elections|title=General Election 1998|url=http://hawaii.gov/elections/results/1998/general/98swgen.htm|date=1998-11-03|accessdate=2010-07-06|postscript=&lt;!-- Bot inserted parameter. Either remove it; or change its value to "." for the cite to end in a ".", as necessary. --&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* December 9, 1999: In light of the constitutional amendment, the Supreme Court of Hawaii in ''[[Baehr v. Miike]]'' reverses the decision of the trial court and remands the case with instructions to enter judgment for the state.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite court
  |litigants = Baehr v. Miike
  |opinion = No. 20371
  |court = Supreme Court of Hawaii
  |date = 1999-12-09 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* December 20, 1999: The [[Vermont Supreme Court]] holds that exclusion of same-sex couples from benefits and protections incident to marriage under state law violated the common-benefits clause of the [[Constitution of Vermont|Vermont Constitution]].
* November 18, 2003: The [[Massachusetts Supreme Judicial Court]] gives the state legislature 180 days to enact same-sex marriage.
* February 11, 2004: The [[Massachusetts General Court]] (legislature) completes the first step in a process that would ban same-sex marriage. The process is not continued.
* February 12&amp;nbsp;– March 11, 2004: [[San Francisco 2004 same-sex weddings|San Francisco issues same-sex marriage licenses]].
* May 17, 2004: Same-sex marriage starts in Massachusetts.
* August 12, 2004: The [[California Supreme Court]] rules that the San Francisco marriages are void.
* May 12, 2005: [[Nebraska Initiative Measure 416 (2000)|Nebraska Initiative Measure 416]] overturned by [[United States District Judge]] [[Joseph F. Bataillon]] as a unconstitutional violation of the [[14th Amendment to the United States Constitution|Fourteenth Amendment's]] [[Equal Protection]] clause, and a [[bill of attainder]] in violation of [[Article One of the United States Constitution|Article I]]'s [[Contract Clause]].
* September 29, 2005: California Governor [[Arnold Schwarzenegger]] vetoes a same-sex marriage bill.
* July 14, 2006: [[United States Court of Appeals for the Eighth Circuit]] rules that [[Nebraska Initiative Measure 416 (2000)|Nebraska Initiative Measure 416]]'s limiting marriage to one man and one woman does not violate the [[14th Amendment to the United States Constitution|Fourteenth Amendment's]] [[Equal Protection]] clause, and was not a [[bill of attainder]] in violation of [[Article One of the United States Constitution|Article I]]'s [[Contract Clause]], reversing Judge [[Joseph F. Bataillon]]'s 2005 decision.
* October 12, 2007: California Governor Arnold Schwarzenegger vetoes same-sex marriage bill.
* May 15, 2008: The [[Supreme Court of California]] overturns the state's ban on same-sex marriage.
* June 16, 2008: Same-sex marriage starts in California.
* September 10, 2008: HB436, a bill that seeks to "eliminates the exclusion of same gender couples from marriage", is submitted to the New Hampshire House of Representatives.
* October 10, 2008: The [[Supreme Court of Connecticut]] orders same-sex marriage legalized.
* November 4, 2008: California voters pass [[California Proposition 8 (2008)|Proposition 8]], amending the state constitution to ban same-sex marriage.
* November 5, 2008: Proposition 8 takes effect in California, stopping new same-sex marriage licenses from being issued after this date.
* November 12, 2008: Same-sex marriage starts in Connecticut.
* March 26, 2009: HB436 supporting same-sex marriage passes the New Hampshire House of Representatives.
* April 3, 2009: The [[Iowa Supreme Court]] legalizes same-sex marriage.
* April 6, 2009: A same-sex marriage bill is passed by the [[Vermont General Assembly]] and then vetoed by the governor.
* April 7, 2009: The [[Vermont General Assembly]] overrides the governor's veto of the same-sex marriage bill.
* April 23, 2009: Connecticut governor signs legislation which ''statutorily'' legalizes same-sex marriage (see Oct. 10 and Nov. 12, 2008), and also converts any existing civil unions into marriages as of October 1, 2010.
* April 27, 2009: Same-sex marriage starts in Iowa.
* April 29, 2009: HB436 supporting same-sex marriage passes the [[New Hampshire Senate]] with minor amendments.
* May 6, 2009: Maine Governor Baldacci signs Marriage Equality Bill. The [[New Hampshire House of Representatives]] concurs with the Senate's amendments to HB436, and the bill supporting same-sex marriage advances to Governor [[John Lynch (New Hampshire)|John Lynch]].
* May 12, 2009: A same-sex marriage bill passes in the lower house [[New York Assembly]].
* May 26, 2009: The California Supreme Court upholds [[California Proposition 8 (2008)|Proposition 8]], but also upholds the marriage rights of the 18,000 same-sex couples married while same-sex marriage had been briefly legalized.
* June 3, 2009: The [[New Hampshire General Court]] passes new HB73, which includes protections for religious institutions, as required by Gov. [[John Lynch (New Hampshire)|John Lynch]] to secure his signature on HB436, a bill legalizing same-sex marriage. Gov. Lynch signs both bills the same day.
* September 1, 2009: Same-sex marriage starts in Vermont.
* September 11, 2009: Same-sex marriage was supposed to start on this day in Maine, but is subject to a People's Veto.
* October 2, 2009: A Texas judge rules the state's same-sex marriage ban unconstitutional while presiding over the divorce proceedings for two gay Texans married in Massachusetts, clearing the way for both Texas's first same-sex divorce and a legal challenge to the same-sex marriage ban.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dallasnews.com/sharedcontent/dws/news/politics/state/stories/DN-gaydivorce_02met.ART.State.Edition2.4bcd80d.html Dallas Morning News], October 2, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;
* October 11, 2009: California Governor Arnold Schwarzenegger signs into law recognition of out-of-state same-sex marriage.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.commondreams.org/newswire/2009/10/12-1|title=Governor Signs Harvey Milk Day and Marriage Recognition Bills|publisher=[[Common Dreams NewsCenter]]|first=Vaishalee|last=Raja|date=2009-10-12|accessdate=2009-10-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.eqca.org/site/pp.asp?c=kuLRJ9MRKrH&amp;b=5305359|title=Marriage Recognition and Family Protection|publisher=[[Equality California]]|accessdate=2009-10-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* November 3, 2009: The same-sex marriage law passed in Maine is repealed by a People's Veto referendum.&lt;ref name="Adams &amp; Crary 11-03-2009"/&gt;
* December 1, 2009: The [[Council of the District of Columbia]] passes same-sex marriage bill 11-2 in its first vote. The bill must pass a second vote on December 15 before it can go to Mayor Adrian Fenty for signature. Barring interference by the United States Congress within thirty legislative days after Mayor Fenty signs the bill, DC will allow same-sex marriage.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2009/12/01/AR2009120101265.html|title=District approves same-sex marriage|publisher=Washington Post|first=Tim|last=Craig|date=2009-12-01|accessdate=2009-12-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* December 2, 2009: Same-sex marriage is defeated 38–24 in the [[New York State Senate]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2009/12/02/AR2009120203910.html | work=The Washington Post | title=N.Y. State Senate votes down gay marriage bill by wide margin | first=Karl | last=Vick | date=December 3, 2009 | accessdate=May 23, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* December 15, 2009: District of Columbia City Council passes same-sex marriage bill 11-2 in its second vote. The bill was signed by Mayor Fenty on December 18, 2009.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.google.com/hostednews/ap/article/ALeqM5gftV6RnfBC8iPPWGM0SGQeNLiC6QD9CJUE8O1 ]{{Dead link|date=June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* January 1, 2010: Same-sex marriage starts in New Hampshire and all out-of-state same-sex marriages are given the benefits of marriage under California law, although only those performed before November 5, 2008  are granted the designation "marriage".&lt;ref name="eqca.org"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.eqca.org/site/apps/nlnet/content2.aspx?c=kuLRJ9MRKrH&amp;b=5609563&amp;content_id={913FF32C-BE83-428B-9DBE-82D429183E7E}&amp;notoc=1 |title=Historic Bills Expanding LGBT Rights and Resources Become Law – Equality California |publisher=Eqca.org |date= |accessdate=2010-06-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* February 24, 2010: Maryland's attorney general issues an opinion requiring the state to recognize same-sex marriages performed in other states.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2010/02/24/AR2010022403630.html?hpid=topnews | work=The Washington Post | title=Md. attorney general: State to recognize same-sex marriages performed elsewhere | first1=Aaron C. | last1=Davis | first2=John | last2=Wagner | date=February 24, 2010 | accessdate=May 23, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* March 3, 2010: Same-sex marriage starts in Washington, D.C.&lt;ref name="dcagenda"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://dcagenda.com/2010/02/couples-plan-courthouse-visits-to-celebrate-d-c-marriage-law/|title=Couples plan courthouse visits to celebrate D.C. marriage law|last=Chibbaro|first=Lou|date=February 24, 2010|publisher=dcagenda|accessdate=April 24, 2010}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* July 8, 2010: Judge [[Joseph Louis Tauro|Joseph Tauro]] of the [[United States District Court for the District of Massachusetts|District Court of Massachusetts]] held in two related cases ([[Gill v. Office of Personnel Management]] and [[Massachusetts v. United States Department of Health and Human Services]]) that the denial of federal rights and benefits to lawfully married same-sex couples in Massachusetts under the [[Defense of Marriage Act]] is unconstitutional under the [[Fifth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Fifth]] and [[Tenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Tenth Amendments]] to the [[United States Constitution|U.S. Constitution]].&lt;ref name="hrc.org"/&gt;&lt;ref name="politicalticker.blogs.cnn.com"/&gt;
* August 4, 2010: California's Proposition 8 is overturned by [[United States District Judge]] [[Vaughn R. Walker]] as an unconstitutional violation of the [[14th Amendment to the United States Constitution|Fourteenth Amendment's]] [[Due Process]] and [[Equal Protection]] clauses.
* August 31, 2010: The [[Texas Courts of Appeals|Fifth Court of Appeals]] in [[Dallas, Texas]] reverses a 2009 ruling in a same-sex divorce case, ruling that the Texas constitutional ban on same-sex marriage does not violate the [[Equal Protection Clause]] of the [[Amendment Fourteen to the United States Constitution|Fourteenth Amendment]]. The court further rules that district courts in Texas do not have [[subject-matter jurisdiction]] to hear a same-sex divorce case.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web
  | last = Appleton
  | first = Roy
  | title = Dallas judge's ruling saying gay couple could divorce in Texas rejected on appeal
  | work = The Dallas Morning News
  | date = 2010-08-31
  | url = http://www.dallasnews.com/sharedcontent/dws/news/localnews/stories/090110dnmetgaydivorce.aa8079fa.html
  | accessdate = 2010-08-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* October 12, 2010: The Department of Justice appealed against Tauro's July 8 decision (see above).&lt;ref&gt;''Boston Globe'': [http://www.boston.com/news/local/massachusetts/articles/2010/10/12/feds_appeal_mass_rulings_against_us_marriage_law/ "Feds Appeal Mass Rulings against U.S. Marriage Law," October 12, 2010], accessed October 13, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

==Case law==
United States case law regarding same-sex marriage:
*''[[Baker v. Nelson]]'', 191 N.W.2d 185 ('''Minn. 1971''') (upholding a Minnesota law defining marriage)
*''Jones v. Hallahan'', 501 S.W.2d 588 ('''Ky. 1973''') (upholding a Kentucky law defining marriage)
*''Singer v. Hara'', 522 P.2d 1187 ('''Wash. App. 1974''') (ban on same-sex marriage was constitutional on the basis of ''gender discrimination''; because the historical definition of marriage is between one man and one woman, same-sex couples are inherently ineligible to marry)
*''Adams v. Howerton'', 673 F.2d 1036 ('''9th Cir. 1982'''), ''cert. denied'', 458 U.S. 1111 (affirming that same-sex marriage does not make one a "spouse" under the Immigration and Nationality Act)
*''De Santo v. Barnsley'', 476 A.2d 952 ('''Pa. Super. Ct. 1984''')(same-sex couples cannot undergo divorce proceedings because they cannot enter a common law marriage)
*''In re Estate of Cooper'', 564 N.Y.S.2d 684 ('''N.Y. Fam. Ct. 1990''')
*''Baehr v. Lewin'', 852 P.2d 44 (Haw. 1993) (holding that statute limiting marriage to opposite-sex couples violates the Hawaii constitution's equal-protection clause unless the state can show that the statute is (1) justified by compelling state interests and (2) narrowly tailored, prompting a [[Hawaii Constitutional Amendment 2 (1998)|state constitutional amendment]] and the federal [[Defense of Marriage Act]])
*''Dean v. District of Columbia'', 653 A.2d 307 ('''D.C. 1995''')
*''Storrs v. Holcomb'', 645 N.Y.S.2d 286 ('''N.Y. App. Div. 1996''') (New York does not recognize or authorize same-sex marriage) (this ruling has since been changed, New York does recognize same-sex marriages performed in other states)
*''In re Estate of Hall'', 707 N.E.2d 201, 206 ('''Ill. App. Ct. 1998''') (no same-sex marriage will be recognized; petitioner claiming existing same-sex marriage was not in a marriage recognized by law)
*''Baker v. State'', 170 Vt. 194; 744 A.2d 864 ('''Vt. 1999''') (Common Benefits Clause of the state constitution requires that same-sex couples be granted the same legal rights as married persons)
*''Rosengarten v. Downes'', 806 A.2d 1066 ('''Conn. Ct. App. 2002''') (Vermont civil union cannot be dissolved in Connecticut)
*''Burns v. Burns'', 560 S.E.2d 47 ('''Ga. Ct. App. 2002''') (recognizing marriage as between one man and one woman)
*''Frandsen v. County of Brevard'', 828 So. 2d 386 ('''Fla. 2002''') (State constitution will not be construed to recognize same-sex marriage; sex classifications not subject to strict scrutiny under Florida constitution)
*''In re Estate of Gardiner'', 42 P.3d 120 ('''Kan. 2002''') (a post-op male-to-female transgendered person may not marry a male, because this person is still a male in the eyes of the law, and marriage in Kansas is recognized only between a man and a woman)
*''Standhardt v. Superior Court ex rel. County of Maricopa'', 77 P.3d 451 ('''Ariz. Ct. App. 2003''') (no state constitution right to same-sex marriage)
*''Morrison v. Sadler'', 2003 WL 23119998 ('''Ind. Super. Ct. 2003''') (Indiana's Defense of Marriage Act is found valid)
*''[[Goodridge v. Dept. of Public Health]]'', 798 N.E.2d 941 ('''Mass. 2003''') (denial of marriage licenses to same-sex couples violated provisions of the state constitution guaranteeing individual liberty and equality, and was not rationally related to a legitimate state interest.)
*''[[Citizens for Equal Protection v. Bruning]]'', 455 F.3d 859 ('''8th Cir. 2006''') (reversing 368 F. Supp. 2d 980 ('''D. Neb. 2005''')) (Nebraska's [[Nebraska Initiative Measure 416 (2000)|Initiative Measure 416]] does not violate Fourteenth Amendment's Equal Protection Clause, was not a bill of attainder, and does not violate the First Amendment; "laws limiting the state-recognized institution of marriage to heterosexual couples ... do not violate the Constitution of the United States")&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ca8.uscourts.gov/opndir/06/07/052604P.pdf ''Citizens for Equal Protection v. Bruning'', 455 F.3d 859 (8th Cir. 2006)]&lt;/ref&gt;
*''[[Lewis v. Harris]]'', 908 A.2d 196 ('''N.J. 2006''') (New Jersey is required to extend all rights and responsibilities of marriage to same-sex couples, but prohibiting same-sex marriage does not violate the state constitution; legislature given 180 days from October 25, 2006 to amend the marriage laws or create a "parallel structure.")
*''[[Andersen v. King County]]'', 138 P.3d 963 ('''Wash. 2006''') (Washington's Defense of Marriage Act does not violate the state constitution)
*[http://www.courts.state.ny.us/reporter/3dseries/2006/2006_05239.htm ''Hernandez v. Robles''], 855 N.E.2d 1 ('''N.Y. 2006''') (New York State Constitution does not require that marriage be extended to same-sex couples).
*''[[Langan v. St. Vincent's Hospital]]'', 25 A.D.3d 90, 802 N.Y.S.2d 476 (N.Y. App. Div. 2005), review denied, 850 N.E.2d 672 (N.Y. 2006) (denying survivor partner in Vermont officiated Civil Union standing as a "spouse" for purposes of New York's wrongful death statute).
*''[[Same-sex marriage in Maryland#Conaway v. Deane &amp; Polyak|Conaway v. Deane]]'', 932 A.2d 571 ('''Md. 2007''') (upholding state law defining marriage as between a "man" and a "woman,")
*''[[Martinez v. County of Monroe]]'', 850 N.Y.S.2d 740 ('''N.Y. App. Div. 2008''') (The court ruled unanimously that because New York legally recognizes out-of-state marriages of opposite-sex couples, it must do the same for same-sex couples. The county was refused leave to appeal on a technicality.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Louis |first=Tim |url=http://www.rochestercitynewspaper.com/news/articles/2008/05/GAY-MARRIAGE-Technicality-delays |title=GAY MARRIAGE: Technicality delays county's appeal |publisher=Rochestercitynewspaper.com |date= |accessdate=2010-06-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;)
*''[[In re Marriage Cases]]'', 183 P.3d 384 ('''Cal. 2008''') (The court ruled that limiting marriage to opposite-sex couples is invalid under the equal protection clause of the California Constitution, and that full marriage rights, not merely domestic partnership, must be offered to same-sex couples.);&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.courtinfo.ca.gov/opinions/archive/S147999.PDF ]{{Dead link|date=June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; overruled by ''[[Strauss v. Horton]]'', 207 P.3d 48 ('''Cal. 2009''') (holding that same-sex couples have all the rights of heterosexual couples, except the right to the "designation" of marriage and that such a holding does not violate California's privacy, equal protection, or due process laws)&lt;ref&gt;http://www.courtinfo.ca.gov/opinions/archive/S168047.PDF&lt;/ref&gt; For a review see: Thomas Kupka, Names and Designations in Law, in: [http://www.jurisprudence.com.au/juris6/kupka.pdf ''The Journal Jurisprudence'' 6 (2010) 121-130].
*''[[Varnum v. Brien]]'', 763 N.W.2d 862, ('''Ia. 2009''') (Barring same-sex couples from marriage, the court unanimously ruled, violates the equal protection provisions of the [[Iowa Constitution]]. Equal protection requires full marriage, rather than civil unions or some other substitute, for same-sex couples.)
*''[[Perry v. Schwarzenegger]]'', No C 09-2292 VRW, (California's [[Proposition 8]] (2008) violates fundamental right to marry under ''Loving v. Virginia'', violates Due Process and Equal Protection Causes of the Fourteenth Amendment, and illegally discriminates on the basis of sexual orientation. Prop 8 is driven only by animus against same-sex couples; therefore, does not survive [[rational basis review]]. Permanently enjoins CA from enforcing Prop 8; order stayed pending appeal to the US [[Ninth Circuit Court of Appeals]].)

==See also==
{{Portal box|LGBT|United States}}
* ''[[A Union In Wait]]'' (documentary)
* [[Same-sex marriage]]
* [[Timeline of same-sex marriage]]
* [[Status of same-sex marriage]]
* [[Public opinion of same-sex marriage in the United States]]
* [[Same-sex marriage under United States tribal jurisdictions]]

===Legislation===
* [[Same-sex marriage status in the United States by state]]
* [[Same-sex marriage legislation in the United States]]
* [[Same-sex marriage law in the United States by state]]
* [[Same-sex unions in the United States]]
* [[Rights and responsibilities of marriages in the United States]]
* [[Defense of Marriage Act]]
* [[Marriage Protection Act of 2007]]
* [[Defense of marriage amendment]]
* [[Federal Marriage Amendment]]
* [[Domestic partnership in the United States]]

===Supporting organizations===
* [[American Civil Liberties Union]]
* [[American Foundation for Equal Rights]]
* [[Americans United for Separation of Church and State]]
* [[Courage Campaign]]
* [[Empowering Spirits Foundation]]
* [http://faithinamerica.info/ Faith in America]
* [[Freedom to Marry]]
* [[Gay and Lesbian Advocates and Defenders]]
* [[Gay and Lesbian Alliance Against Defamation]]
* [[Human Rights Campaign]]
* [[Log Cabin Republicans]]
* [[Marriage Equality USA]]
* [[National Gay and Lesbian Task Force]]
* [[National Organization for Women]]
* [[National Stonewall Democrats]]
* [[People For the American Way]]
* [[Soulforce (organization)]]

===Opposing organizations===
* [[Alliance Defense Fund]]
* [[Alliance for Marriage]]
* [[American Family Association]]
* [[Concerned Women for America]]
* [[Family Research Council]]
* [[Focus on the Family]]
* [[Liberty Counsel]]
* [[Knights of Columbus]]
* [[National Organization for Marriage]]
* [[Renew America]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Bibliography==
*{{cite book | last = Chauncey | first = George | authorlink = George Chauncey | year = 2004 | title = Why Marriage?: The History Shaping Today's Debate over Gay Equality | publisher = Basic Books | location = New York | isbn = 0-465-00957-3}}
* Murdoch, Joyce and Deb Price (2001). ''Courting Justice: Gay Men and Lesbians v. the Supreme Court''. New York, Basic Books. ISBN 0-465-01513-1.
*{{cite book | last = Dobson | first = James C. | authorlink = James Dobson | year = 2004 | title = Marriage Under Fire | publisher = Multnomah | location = Sisters, Or. | isbn = 1-59052-431-4 | unused_data = Marriage under Fire: Why We Must Win This War}}
*{{cite book | last = Wolfson | first = Evan | authorlink = Evan Wolfson | year = 2004 | title = Why Marriage Matters: America, Equality, and Gay People's Right to Marry | publisher = Simon &amp; Schuster | location = New York | isbn = 0-7432-6459-2}}

==External links==
*[http://www.newsweek.com/id/142307 Where Can Gays Wed? ''Newsweek's'' Interactive Map on same-sex marriage legislation in the United States, June 2008] by Marc Bain, Alicia Parlapiano and Xaquín G.V.
*[http://www.laweekly.com/news/news/california-supreme-court-set-to-consider-gay-marriage/18429/ ''LA Weekly'' feature, "California Supreme Court Set to Consider Gay Marriage," Feb. 2008 by Matthew Fleischer]
* [http://www.pollingreport.com/civil.htm PollingReport.com Law and Civil Rights] compendium
*[http://www.marriagedebate.com/pdf/iMAPP.May2008.pdf American Courts on Marriage: Is Marriage Discriminatory? 1998–2008], Joshua Baker, [[Institute for Marriage and Public Policy]], May 2008.

{{Status of same-sex unions}}
{{Same-sex marriage in the United States}}
{{United States topics}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Same-Sex Marriage In The United States}}
[[Category:Articles with inconsistent citation formats]]
[[Category:Same-sex marriage in the United States| ]]
[[Category:Article Feedback Pilot]]

[[es:Matrimonio entre personas del mismo sexo en los Estados Unidos]]
[[nl:Homohuwelijk in de Verenigde Staten]]
[[ru:Однополые браки в США]]
[[zh:美国同性婚姻]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>