<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20071104023715|169076806" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="249623" pageid="249623" ns="0" title="Same-sex marriage in the United States"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-11-04T02:38:39Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{SSM}}
[[Image:Samesexmarriage.gif|thumb|Same-sex marriage ceremony]]'''[[Same-sex marriage]]''', also known as '''gay marriage''', is a [[marriage]] between two persons of the same sex. The issue is a divisive [[politics|political issue]] in the [[United States]] and elsewhere. The social movement to obtain the [[rights and responsibilities of marriages in the United States]] for same-sex couples began in the early [[1970s]], and the issue became a prominent one in U.S. politics in the [[1990s]].

The legal issues surrounding same-sex marriage in the United States are complicated by the nation's [[federalism|federal]] system of government. Traditionally, the federal government did not attempt to establish its own definition of marriage; any marriage recognized by a [[U.S. state|state]] was recognized by the federal government, even if that marriage was not recognized by one or more other states (as was the case with [[Anti-miscegenation laws|interracial marriage]] before 1967). With the passage of the [[Defense of Marriage Act]] in 1996, however, a marriage was explicitly defined as a union of one man and one woman for the purposes of federal law.  (See {{usc|1|7}}.) Thus, no act or agency of the U.S. federal government currently recognizes same-sex marriage.

However, many aspects of marriage law affecting the day to day lives of inhabitants of the United States are determined by the states, not the federal government, and the Defense of Marriage Act does not prevent individual states from defining marriage as they see fit; indeed, most legal scholars believe that the federal government cannot impose a definition of marriage onto the laws of the various states by statute. [[Same-sex marriage in Massachusetts|Massachusetts]] has recognized same-sex marriage since 2004. [[Connecticut]], [[Vermont]], [[New Jersey]], [[California]], and [[New Hampshire]] (from 1 January 2008) have created legal unions that, while not called marriages, are explicitly defined as offering all the rights and responsibilities of marriage under state law to same-sex couples. [[Maine]], [[Hawaii]], the [[District of Columbia]], [[Oregon]] (from 1 January 2008) and [[Washington]] have created legal unions for same-sex couples that offer varying subsets of the rights and responsibilities of marriage under the laws of those jurisdictions.

In contrast, twenty-six states have constitutional amendments explicitly barring the recognition of same-sex marriage, confining civil marriage to a legal union between a [[man]] and a [[woman]]. Forty-three states have statutes restricting marriage to two persons of the opposite sex, including some of those that have created legal recognition for same-sex unions under a name other than "marriage." A small number of states ban any legal recognition of same-sex unions that would be equivalent to civil marriage.

Opponents of same-sex marriage have attempted to prevent individual states from recognizing such unions by amending the [[United States Constitution]] to define marriage as a union between one man and one woman. In 2006, the [[Federal Marriage Amendment]], which would prohibit states from recognizing same-sex marriages, was approved by the [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican]]-controlled [[United States Senate Committee on the Judiciary|Senate Judiciary Committee]], on a party line vote, and was debated by the full United States Senate, but was ultimately defeated in both houses of Congress.&lt;ref&gt;''[http://www.cnn.com/2006/POLITICS/06/07/same.sex.marriage/index.html Senate blocks same-sex marriage ban]'', [[CNN]], [[June 7]], 2006, (Accessed [[July 5]], 2006) &lt;/ref&gt;

On August 30, 2007, [[Iowa]] [[Judge]] [[Robert Hanson]] temporarily annulled a [[law]] allowing [[marriage]] only between men and women before placing a [[stay]] the following day on his own ruling.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/americas/6971696.stm  BBC NEWS, Iowa judge approves gay weddings]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Debate ==
=== Conservative publications ===

A writer of ''[[The Weekly Standard]]'', Stanley Kurtz, adjunct fellow at the [[Hudson Institute]], blames same-sex marriage in the [[Netherlands]] for an increase in parental cohabitation contracts. He asserts that same-sex marriage has detached [[procreation]] from marriage in the Dutch mind and would likely do the same in the [[United States]]. 

Using [[anecdotal]] evidence, such as a Dutch man and two women who entered a cohabitation agreement together, and a small [[Unitarian Church]] group that advocates polygamy, Kurtz states that allowing a monogamous same-sex marriage will create a social disorder that will eventually lead to [[group marriage]].

{{quotation|...the American media are correct to report that the majority of Dutch citizens have accepted the innovation [same-sex marriage]. The press has simply missed the meaning of that public shift. Broad Dutch acceptance of same-sex marriage means that marriage as an institution has been detached from the public mind. That is why the practice of parental cohabitation has grown so quickly in the Netherlands. By the same token, the shoulder shrug that followed the triple wedding [polyamory] story shows that legalized group marriage in the Netherlands is a real possibility.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.polygreens.org/?p=59 ''Stanley Kurtz Bangs Drum About Polyamory and Bisexuality''. Poly Greens News, January 7th, 2006.]&lt;/ref&gt;
|}}

=== Liberal publications ===

Christopher Ott, a reporter for ''[[The Progressive]]'', has characterized the social conservatives' predictions of legalized polygamy in states such as Massachusetts that have same-sex marriage as false. He confronts the common argument that same-sex marriage would devalue [[marriage]] as a whole by referencing other historical events such as [[suffrage|allowing women to vote]] and stating that it did not devalue the electoral process. Ott describes the prohibition of same-sex marriage as devaluing the American principle of [[equal treatment]].

{{quotation|...you also have to wonder if he and other opponents to equal rights really understand the consequences of the amendments they support. Do they really want gay and lesbian couples separated at the emergency room door in the event of an accident or illness? Do they really think long-term couples should be denied the right to make medical or end-of-life decisions, which married couples take for granted? Do they really think that kids should be denied health coverage by one parent's health insurance because the law treats them as strangers? Do they really think it's fair for gay and lesbian people to pay the same taxes as everyone else, but to be denied the hundreds of rights, benefits and protections of marriage? Do they really think that a gay and lesbian couple that has been together for 50 years does not deserve the protections that non-gay newlyweds enjoy from day one?&lt;ref&gt;Ott, Christopher, ''[http://www.progressive.org/media_324]'', The Progressive, [[February 8]], 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

===Groups supporting and opposing same-sex marriage===
{{seealso|Blessing of same-sex unions in Christian churches}}
{{wikinews|Interview with gay marriage movement founder Evan Wolfson}}
It is supported by an assortment of groups and individuals. Those supporting same-sex marriage include
[[Alternatives to marriage project]]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.unmarried.org/pressreleases/ssm-press-release.html&lt;/ref&gt;, the [[American Civil Liberties Union]],&lt;ref name="glaad"&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.glaad.org/media/resource_kit_detail.php?id=3457 |title=Marriage Equality for Same-Sex Couples|date=[[2004-05-14]]|accessdate=2007-01-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;
the [[American Psychiatric Association]],{{Fact|date=February 2007}}
the [[American Psychological Association]],{{Fact|date=February 2007}}
[[Freedom to Marry]],&lt;ref name="glaad" /&gt;
the Gay &amp; Lesbian Advocates &amp; Defenders,&lt;ref name="glaad" /&gt;
[[Gay &amp; Lesbian Alliance Against Defamation]],&lt;ref name="glaad" /&gt;
the [[Human Rights Campaign]],&lt;ref name="glaad" /&gt;
[[Coretta Scott King]] [http://www.usatoday.com/news/nation/2004-03-24-king-marriage_x.htm], [[Tucker Carlson]],
[[Lambda Legal]],&lt;ref name="glaad" /&gt;
[[Marriage Equality USA]] [http://www.marriageequality.org/meusa/about-us.shtml], [[MassEquality]],&lt;ref name="glaad" /&gt;
the [[Metropolitan Community Church]], [[Stonewall Democrats]], [[PFLAG]], [[Family Pride]], [[Log Cabin Republicans]], [[Gay and Lesbian Advocates and Defenders]], [[Basic Rights Oregon]], [[Equal Rights Washington]], [[Equality California]], [[Equality Maryland]], [[Equality Mississippi]], [[Equality North Dakota]], [[OutFront Minnesota]], [[Outright Libertarians]], [[Kentucky Equality Federation]], [[Stonewall Democrats]], [[Leadership Conference on Civil Rights]], [[Stonewall Young Democrats]], [[Kentucky Fairness Alliance]], [[Human Rights Watch]], [[Lavender Greens]], [[Human Rights Watch]], [[Gay and Lesbian Victory Fund]], [[People for the American Way]], [[Soulforce]], [[COLAGE]], National Black Justice Coalition, {{Fact|date=February 2007}}
National Center for Lesbian Rights,&lt;ref name="glaad" /&gt;
[[National Gay and Lesbian Task Force]],&lt;ref name="glaad" /&gt;
[[National Organization for Women]][http://www.now.org/issues/marriage/index.html], [[Reform Judaism]],{{Fact|date=February 2007}}
the [[Unitarian|Unitarian Universalist Association]],&lt;ref&gt;"Bisexual, Gay, Lesbian, and Transgender Community", [http://www.uua.org/visitors/justicediversity/6252.shtml] (accessed July 2007)&lt;/ref&gt;
the [[United Church of Christ]],[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/americas/4651803.stm], and
[[United Farm Workers]].{{Fact|date=February 2007}}

Additionally, the mayors [[As of 2006|in 2006]] of several large cities such as [[Shirley Franklin|Atlanta]], [[Thomas Menino|Boston]], [[Richard M. Daley|Chicago]], [[Antonio Villaraigosa|Los Angeles]], [[Michael Bloomberg|New York City]], [[Rocky Anderson|Salt Lake City]], [[Gavin Newsom|San Francisco]], and [[Greg Nickels|Seattle]]&lt;!-- this list should be re-written by mayor's name and give citations, since there are elections every so often and the current mayor of a city may not have the same position as the previous one--&gt; support same-sex marriage as well as politicians such as [[Deval Patrick]], [[Mike Gravel]], [[Eliot Spitzer]], and [[Dennis Kucinich]].   Several political parties such as the [[Communist Party USA]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.cpusa.org/article/articleview/589/1/3 |title=Election Platform 2004|work=Communist Party USA|accessdate=2006-07-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; U.S. [[Green Party (United States)|Green Party]], the Socialist Party USA,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://sp-usa.org/platform/humanrights.html |title=Socialist Party Platform: Human Rights|work=Socialist Party USA|accessdate=2006-07-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; and several state [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democratic Parties]] also support gay marriage.

Those supporting the creation of a separate but equal legal status for same-sex couples in the form of civil union or domestic partnership legislation include some state governors such as those of [[California]], [[Connecticut]], [[New Mexico]], [[Oregon]], and [[Washington]],&lt;!-- this list should be re-written by name and give citations, since there are elections every so often and the current governor of a state may not have the same position as the previous one--&gt; the national [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democratic Party]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.democrats.org/pdfs/2004platform.pdf |title=Democratic Party 2004 Platform}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[President of the United States|President]] [[George W. Bush]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.cnsnews.com/ViewCulture.asp?Page=%5CCulture%5Carchive%5C200410%5CCUL20041027b.html |title=Bush Tolerates Civil Unions, Thinks States Should Decide}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Groups that oppose giving a legal status to same-sex marriages include the [[American Family Association]],{{Fact|date=February 2007}}
the [[Christian Coalition of America|Christian Coalition]],{{Fact|date=February 2007}}
the [[Christian Voice]],{{Fact|date=February 2007}}
the Church of God (Anderson, IN),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.chog.org/ME2/Audiences/dirmod.asp?nm=Core+Pages&amp;type=gen&amp;mod=Core+Pages&amp;tier=3&amp;gid=9B410103A4034AF9930C4CFAC4474E93&amp;AudID=E5E87D912B4A4358915D489F4BF9B6F6 |title=Resolution Regarding Same-Sex Marriage|work=The Church of God General Assembly Resolution, 2004|accessdate=2006-07-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]],{{Fact|date=February 2007}}
the [[Conservative Mennonite Conference]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://cmcrosedale.org/about/homosexuality.shtml |title=CMC Statement on Homosexuality|publisher=Conservative Mennonite Conference|accessdate=2006-07-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;
the Evangelical Methodist Church,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Williamson|first=Edward W.|url= http://www.emchurch.org/news.htm |title=Is America witnessing the end of marriage?|publisher=The Evangelical Methodist Church|accessdate=2006-07-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Family Research Council]],{{Fact|date=February 2007}}
[[Focus on the Family]],{{Fact|date=February 2007}}
the [[Hutterite]] Brethren,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.cbc.ca/story/canada/national/2005/02/17/hutterite-050217.html |title=Hutterites take rare political stand against gay marriage|publisher=CBC News|date=[[2005-02-18]]|accessdate=2006-07-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;,
the [[Moral Majority]],{{Fact|date=February 2007}}
[[NARTH]],{{Fact|date=February 2007}}
the [[Orthodox Church in America]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.oca.org/DOCmarriage.asp?SID=12&amp;ID=26 |title=On Marriage, Family, Sexuality, and the Sanctity of Life|publisher=Orthodox Church in America|accessdate=2006-07-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;
the [[Rabbinical Council of America]],&lt;ref name="orthjew"&gt;''[http://www.rabbis.org/news/article.cfm?id=100556 Same-Sex Marriage]'', Rabbinical Council of America. (Accessed [[July 5]], 2006)&lt;/ref&gt; the national and most state [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican Parties]],{{Fact|date=February 2007}}
the [[Roman Catholic Church]],{{Fact|date=February 2007}}
the [[Southern Baptist Convention]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.reclaimamerica.org/PAGES/NEWS/news.aspx?story=1264 |title=SBC Officially Opposes "Homosexual Marriage|publisher=The Southern Baptist Convention|date=[[2003-07-26]]|accessdate=2006-07-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;
the [[Seventh-day Adventist Church]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.religioustolerance.org/hom_sda.htm |title=The Seventh-Day Adventist Church and Homosexuality}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Southern Baptist Convention]],&lt;ref&gt;http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/news/archive/2004/06/15/national1654EDT0681.DTL&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Unification Church]],{{Fact|date=February 2007}}
and
the [[Union of Orthodox Jewish Congregations of America]] (OU).&lt;ref name="orthjew" /&gt;

== Popular opinion ==
:''See [[Same-sex marriage in the United States public opinion]]

== Legal issues ==
:''See [[Same-sex marriage legislation in the United States]]''

=== State level ===
:''See [[Same-sex marriage legislation in the United States by state]]''
[[Image:US SSM Laws.png|right|300px|thumb|U.S. same-sex union laws (accuracy disputed).]]

=== Impact of foreign laws ===
The legalization of same-sex marriages across all of Canada (see [[same-sex marriage in Canada]]) has raised questions about U.S. law, due to Canada's proximity to the U.S. and the fact that Canada has no citizenship or residency requirement to receive a marriage certificate (unlike the [[same-sex marriage in the Netherlands|Netherlands]] and [[same-sex marriage in Belgium|Belgium]]). Canada and the U.S. have a history of respecting marriages contracted in either country. 

Immediately after the June 2003 ruling legalizing [[same-sex marriage in Ontario]], a number of American couples headed or planned to head to the province in order to get married. A coalition of American national [[gay rights]] groups issued a statement asking couples to contact them before attempting legal challenges, so that they might be coordinated as part of the same-sex marriage movement in the United States.{{Fact|date=February 2007}}

At present, same-sex marriages are recognized nationwide in the [[Same-sex marriage in the Netherlands|Netherlands]], [[Same-sex marriage in Belgium|Belgium]], [[Same-sex marriage in Spain|Spain]], [[Same-sex marriage in Canada|Canada]] and [[Same-sex marriage in South Africa|South Africa]]. Same-sex marriage conducted abroad is recognized in [[Same-sex marriage in Israel|Israel]], [[Same-sex marriage in Aruba|Aruba]] and the [[Same-sex marriage in Netherlands Antilles|Netherlands Antilles]].

== Case law ==
United States case law regarding the rights of gay or bisexual persons:

*''[[Baker v. Nelson]]'', 191 N.W.2d 185 ('''Minn. 1971''') (upholding a Minnesota law defining marriage)
*''Jones v. Hallahan'', 501 S.W.2d 588 ('''Ky. 1973''') (upholding a Kentucky law defining marriage)
*''Conaway v. Deane'', ___ A.2d. ___ ('''Md. 2007''') (upholding state law defining marriage as between a "man" and a "woman," stemming from No. 44, Sept. Term 2006)
*''Singer v. Hara'', 522 P.2d 1187 ('''Wash. App. 1974''')
*''Adams v. Howerton'', 673 F.2d 1036 ('''9th Cir. 1982'''), ''cert. denied'', 458 U.S. 1111 (affirming that same-sex marriage does not make one a "spouse" under the Immigration and Nationality Act)
*''De Santo v. Barnsley'', 476 A.2d 952 ('''Pa. Super. Ct. 1984''')
*''In re Estate of Cooper'', 564 N.Y.S.2d 684 ('''N.Y. Fam. Ct. 1990''')
*''Dean v. District of Columbia'', 653 A.2d 307 ('''D.C. 1995''')
*''Storrs v. Holcomb'', 645 N.Y.S.2d 286 ('''N.Y. App. Div. 1996''') (New York does not recognize or authorize same-sex marriage) (this ruling has since been changed, New York does recognize same-sex marriages performed in other states)
*''In re Estate of Hall'', 707 N.E.2d 201, 206 ('''Ill. App. Ct. 1998''') (no same sex marriage will be recognized; petitioner claiming existing same-sex marriage was not in a marriage recognized by law)
*''Baker v. State'', 170 Vt. 194; 744 A.2d 864 ('''Vt. 1999''') (Common Benefits Clause of the state constitution requires that same-sex couples be granted the same legal rights as married persons)
*''Rosengarten v. Downes'', 806 A.2d 1066 ('''Conn. 2002''') (state will not recognize Vermont civil union)
*''Burns v. Burns'', 560 S.E.2d 47 ('''Ga. Ct. App. 2002''') (recognizing marriage as between one man and one woman)
*''Frandsen v. County of Brevard'', 828 So. 2d 386 ('''Fla. 2002''') (State constitution will not be construed to recognize same-sex marriage; sex classifications not subject to strict scrutiny under Florida constitution)
*''In re Estate of Gardiner'', 42 P.3d 120 ('''Kan. 2002''') (a post-op male-to-female transgendered person may not marry a male, because this person is still a male in the eyes of the law, and marriage in Kansas is recognized only between a man and a woman)
*''Standhardt v. Superior Court ex rel. County of Maricopa'', 77 P.3d 451 ('''Ariz. Ct. App. 2003''') (no state constitution right to same-sex marriage)
*''Morrison v. Sadler'', 2003 WL 23119998 ('''Ind. Super. Ct. 2003''') (Indiana's Defense of Marriage Act is found valid)
*''[[Goodridge v. Dept. of Public Health]]'' ('''Massachusets Supreme Judicial Court, 2003''') (denial of marriage licenses to same-sex couples violated provisions of the state constitution guaranteeing individual liberty and equality, and was not rationally related to a legitimate state interest.)
*''[[Lewis v. Harris]]'' ('''New Jersey Supreme Court, 2006''') (New Jersey is required to extend all rights and responsibilities of marriage to same-sex couples, but prohibiting same-sex marriage does not violate the state constitution; legislature has 180 days from [[October 25]], [[2006]] to amend the marriage laws or create a "parallel structure.")
*''[[Andersen v. King County]]'' ('''Washington Supreme Court, 2006''') (Washington's Defense of Marriage Act does not violate the state constitution)

==References==
&lt;!--See http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Footnotes for an explanation of how to generate footnotes using the &lt;ref(erences/)&gt; tags--&gt; 
&lt;div class="references-small" style="-moz-column-count:2; column-count:2;"&gt;
&lt;references/&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

==Bibliography==
*{{cite book | last = Wolfson | first = Evan | authorlink = Evan Wolfson | year = 2004 | title = Why Marriage Matters: America, Equality, and Gay People's Right to Marry | publisher = Simon &amp; Schuster | location = New York | id = ISBN 0-7432-6459-2}}
*{{cite book | last = Chauncey | first = George | authorlink = George Chauncey | year = 2004 | title = Why Marriage?: The History Shaping Today's Debate over Gay Equality | publisher = Basic Books | location = New York | id = ISBN 0-465-00957-3}}
*{{cite book | last = Dobson | first = James C. | authorlink = James Dobson | year = 2004 | title = Marriage Under Fire|Marriage under Fire: Why We Must Win This War | publisher = Multnomah | location = Sisters, Or. | id = ISBN 1-59052-431-4}}

{{Same-sex marriage in the United States}}

== See also ==
{{gay rights}}

=== In General ===
* [[Same-sex marriage]]
* [[Timeline of same-sex marriage]]
=== In USA ===
* [[Same-sex marriage in the United States public opinion]]
* [[Same-sex marriage status in the United States by state]]
* [[Same-sex marriage legislation in the United States]]
* [[Same-sex marriage legislation in the United States by state]]
* [[List of benefits of marriage in the United States]]
* [[Defense of Marriage Act]]
* [[Marriage Protection Act]]
* [[Defense of marriage amendment]]
* [[Federal Marriage Amendment]]
* [[Domestic partnerships in the United States]]
* [[Freedom to Marry Coalition]]

==External links==
* [http://www.pollingreport.com/civil.htm PollingReport.com Law and Civil Rights] compendium

===Supporting same-sex marriage===
*[http://www.hrc.org Human Rights Campaign]
*[http://www.marriageequality.org/ Marriage Equality USA]
*[http://www.freedomtomarry.org Freedom to Marry]
*[http://www.now.org/issues/lgbi/marr-rep.html National Organization for Women: Same-Sex Marriage is a Feminist Issue]
*[http://www.aclu.org American Civil Liberties Union]
*[http://www.democrats.org/a/communities/glbt_community/ The Democratic Party GLBT Community]
*[http://www.glad.org/ Gay and Lesbian Advocates and Defenders (GLAD)]
[[es:Matrimonio entre personas del mismo sexo en los Estados Unidos]]
[[nl:Homohuwelijk in de Verenigde Staten]]
[[zh:美国同性婚姻]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>