<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20031007021234|1662083" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="249623" pageid="249623" ns="0" title="Same-sex marriage in the United States"><revisions><rev timestamp="2003-11-02T07:02:19Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[zh:&amp;#32654;&amp;#22269;&amp;#21516;&amp;#24615;&amp;#23130;&amp;#23035;]]

In the United States, [[same-sex marriage]] is not legally permitted, although one state provides "[[civil union]]s". Various groups have battled over the legal issue since the late 20th Century.

Opposition to same-sex marriage has dwindled from a two-thirds majority to a 53 percent of respondents saying that they opposed gay marriages, while 38 percent saying that they backed them; fiercest opposition still comes from religious groups. [http://www.washtimes.com/upi-breaking/20030725-081931-4103r.htm] A [[2003]] poll found that 52 percent of Americans favor a law banning same-sex marriages, while 41 percent of Americans oppose such a law.[http://story.news.yahoo.com/news?tmpl=story&amp;u=/ap/20030819/ap_on_re_us/gay_marriage_ap_poll_5]

In 1996, the federal [[Defense of Marriage Act]] (DOMA) was signed into law; it allows [[U.S. state]]s to not recognize same-sex marriages performed in other U.S. states (although no state currently offers same-sex marriage as an option) or other countries. Since then, various states have passed a law or changed their constitution to assert that they do not recognize same-sex unions, nor will they recognize such unions legally recognized in other states. These laws are sometimes referred to as "Mini-DOMAs".
Some opponents of same-sex marriage, fearing that such laws might be invalidated by the courts because of the [[Full_Faith_and_Credit_clause|"full faith and credit" clause]], have proposed a [[Federal Marriage Amendment]] to the [[United States Constitution]] that would explicitly define marriages as joining "one man and one woman".

There are also many groups actively fighting for legal recognition of same-sex marriage, among them traditional [[LGBT]] groups such as [[Human Rights Campaign|HRC]], [[Lambda Legal]] and [[NGLTF]], as well as groups that have been created around this single issue, such as [[Marriage Equality]] and [[Freedom to Marry]]. 

[[Vermont]] is the only US state to offer same-sex couples all of the rights and benefits of heterosexual couples. Vermont does not use the word marriage, but calls such unions ''civil unions''. The history of the civil union law in Vermont is given in the [[civil union]] article.

[[California]]'s domestic partnership law provides similar benefits, but again stops short of full same-sex marriage.

There are also bills in both chambers of the [[New York State]] legislature that would extend marriage rights to same-sex couples. These bills were introduced in early 2003 and are currently still in committee.

The legalization of [[same-sex marriage in Canada]] has raised questions about US law, due to Canada's proximity to the US and the fact that Canada has no citizenship or residency requirement to receive a marriage certificate (unlike the [[same-sex marriage in the Netherlands|Netherlands]] and [[same-sex marriage in Belgium|Belgium]]). Canada and the US have a history of respecting marriages contracted in either country.

A number of American couples immediately headed or planned to head to [[Ontario]] in order to get married. A coalition of American national gay rights groups has issued a statement asking couples to contact them before attempting legal challenges, so that they might be coordinated as part of the same-sex marriage movement in the United States.

==External Links==
* [http://www.washtimes.com/upi-breaking/20030725-081931-4103r.htm Gay wedding opposition said dwindling - UPI]
* [http://www.marriagewatch.org/stateinf.htm A state-by-state guide to same-sex marriage issues]
* [http://www.sbcbaptistpress.org/bpnews.asp?ID=16590 Same-sex 'marriage' issue percolates in 4 state courts, 1 federal court - Baptist Press News]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>