<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061107061206|86221002" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="2406648" pageid="2406648" ns="0" title="Violence Against Women Act"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-11-13T22:42:38Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">The '''Violence Against Women Act of 1994''' (VAWA) is a [[United States federal law]]. It was passed as Title IV, sec. 40001-40703 of the [[Violent Crime Control and Law Enforcement Act of 1994]] HR 3355 and signed as Public Law 103-322 by [[President Bill Clinton]] on [[September 13]] [[1994]].  It provided $1.6 billion to enhance investigation and prosecution of the violent crime perpetrated against women, increased pre-trial detention of the accused, provided for automatic and mandatory restitution of those convicted, and allowed civil redress in cases prosecutors chose to leave unprosecuted.

The [[National Organization of Women]] heralded the bill as "the greatest breakthrough in civil rights for women in nearly two decades."   The [[American Civil Liberties Union]] derided the Act as "troubling", saying that the increased penalties were rash, the increased pretrial detention was "repugnant" to the US Constitution, the mandatory HIV testing of those only charged but not convicted is an infringement of a citizen’s  [[right to privacy]] and the edict for automatic payment of full restitution was non-judicious in their paper "Analysis of Major Civil Liberties Abuses in the Crime Bill Conference Report as Passed by the House and the Senate, dated [[September 29]] [[1994]].  However, the ACLU has supported its reauthorization on the condition that the "unconstitutional DNA provision" be removed.&lt;ref&gt;[https://secure.aclu.org/site/Advocacy?pagename=homepage&amp;id=251&amp;page=UserAction Tell Congress to Support the Violence Against Women Act] &lt;/ref&gt;

VAWA and the 1994 Crime Bill in general was supported by Congressional [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democrats]] and President Clinton and opposed by then minority Congressional [[Republican Party (United States)|Republicans]] with a few exceptions. http://www.senate.gov/legislative/LIS/roll_call_lists/roll_call_vote_cfm.cfm?congress=103&amp;session=2&amp;vote=00295

Ironically, [[Paula Jones]]' attorneys Susan Carpenter-McMillan, Gilbert Davis and Joseph Cammarata would use VAWA in winning arguments one year later to allow a civil suit against President Clinton for sexual harassment to proceed.  Eventually  President Clinton paid an out of court settlement of $850,000 for the harassment.

In 2000, the [[Supreme Court of the United States]] held part of VAWA unconstitutional in [[United States v. Morrison]].  Only the civil rights remedy of VAWA was struck down.  The provisions providing program funding were unaffected.

VAWA was reauthorized by [[U.S. Congress|Congress]] in 2000, and again in October 2005, when it passed the [[U.S. Senate|Senate]] unanimously.  It is due for further reauthorization in 2010.

==World Health Organisation Multi-country Study on Women's Health and Domestic Violence against Women 2005==

The World Conference on [[Human Rights]], held in Vienna in 1993, and the [[Declaration on the Elimination of Violence against Women]] in the same year, concluded that civil society and governments have acknowledged that violence against women is a public health policy and human rights concern. Work in this area has resulted in the establishment of international standards, but the task of documenting the magnitude of violence against women and producing reliable, comparative data to guide policy and monitor implementation has been exceedingly difficult. The [[World Health Organisation]] [[Multi-country Study on Women’s Health and Domestic Violence against Women]] is a response to this difficulty. Published in [[2005]] it is a groundbreaking study which analysed data from 10 countries and sheds new light on the prevalence of violence against women. It seeks to look at violence against women from a public health policy perspective. The findings will be used to inform a more effective response from [[government]], including the health, justice and social service sectors, as a step towards fulfilling the state’s obligation to eliminate violence against women under international human rights laws.

==Criticisms==

Critics of VAWA cite the vast body of studies, such as the analysis by Martin S. Fiebert of the Department of Psychology at [[California State University]], Long Beach, who compliled 195 scholarly investigations: 152 empirical studies and 43 analyses, which demonstrate women are as physically aggressive, or more aggressive, than men &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.csulb.edu/~mfiebert/assault.htm]&lt;/ref&gt; . That aggregate sample size exceeds 175,700. Critics of VAWA reject inferences that instill gender politics by portrayal of women as victims and men as perpetrators. 

Failure of the courts to prosecute false domestic violence allegations in divorce and custody battles is viewed as advocating false domestic violence accusations in the same manner that claims of maritial infidelity were exagerated before [[no fault divorce]] legislature was enacted to curb this disturbing trend. Thomas Kasper writes in the Illinois Bar Journal, domestic violence measures funded by VAWA readily “become part of the gamesmanship of divorce.” 

Kathleen Blee, in her book "Women of the Klan" analyzes how racists such as the [[WKKK]] used demogoguery and lurid sexual imagry to advocate violence and discrimination against black men was adopted by later [[Radical Feminist]] movements who dropped 'black' from the old WKKK jargon to fuel profiling and demoguery of all men. Some [[Father's Rights]] and [[men's movement|men's rights]] activists decry the VAWA as funding similar discrimination against men, that it is as prejudiced to men as a 'Violence Against Whites Act' would be to blacks, and fuels villification of men. &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dvmen.org/ Domestic Violence Against Men In Colorado] &lt;/ref&gt; 

The 1999 book by University of Massachusetts Professor Daphne Patai, "Heterophobia: Sexual Harassment and the Future of Feminism," exposes what she labels the "Sexual Harassment Industry" of feminists who have created a judicial world in which accusation equals guilt, and the distinction between severe offenses and trivial annoyances is erased. 

===External Links===

*[http://www.epic.org/privacy/dv/vawa.html Privacy Provisions of the Violence Against Women Act]
*[http://www.who.int/gender/violence/who_multicountry_study/en/ World Health Organisation Multi-country Study on Women's Health and Domestic Violence against Women 2005]
*[http://www.csulb.edu/~mfiebert/assault.htm REFERENCES EXAMINING ASSAULTS BY WOMEN ON THEIR SPOUSES OR MALE PARTNERS: AN ANNOTATED BIBLIOGRAPHY by Martin S. Fiebert, Department of Psychology, California State University]
*[http://www.eagleforum.org/column/2006/sept06/06-09-13.html Laughing at Restraining Orders]
*[http://www.endabuse.org Family Violence Prevention Fund]
*[http://www.vawa2005.org Violence Against Women Act Reauthorization]
*[http://digital.library.unt.edu/govdocs/crs/search.tkl?q=vawa&amp;search_crit=fulltext&amp;search=Search&amp;date1=Anytime&amp;date2=Anytime&amp;type=form Read Congressional Research Service (CRS) Reports regarding the Violence Against Women Act]
*[http://www.acluprocon.org/bin/procon/procon.cgi?database=5-H-Sub-2Q.db&amp;command=viewone&amp;op=t&amp;id=3&amp;rnd=135.9087785266324 Is the Violence Against Women Act (VAWA) a good law?]
*[http://www.vawa2005.org Violence Against Women Act Reauthorization]
*[http://men.typepad.com/mens_hour/2005/07/vawa_open_lette.html VAWA - OPEN LETTER to Congress]
*[http://www.mediaradar.org/ RADAR]
*[http://www.eagleforum.org/psr/2005/oct05/psroct05.html Time to Defund Feminist Pork — the Hate-Men Law]

[[Category:1994 in law]]
[[Category:United States federal criminal legislation]]
[[Category:1994 in law]]  	 
[[Category:United States federal criminal legislation]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>