<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20121025042548|519698375" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="2406648" pageid="2406648" ns="0" title="Violence Against Women Act"><revisions><rev timestamp="2012-10-25T04:40:44Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Violence against women}}
{{About|United States federal law|other related topics|Outline of domestic violence}}

The '''Violence Against Women Act of 1994''' ('''VAWA''') is a [[United States federal law]] (Title IV, sec. 40001-40703 of the [[Violent Crime Control and Law Enforcement Act of 1994]], {{USBill|103|hr|3355}}) signed as {{USPL|103|322}} by [[US President|President]] [[Bill Clinton]] on September 13, 1994.  The Act provided $1.6 billion toward investigation and prosecution of violent crimes against women, imposed automatic and mandatory restitution on those convicted, and allowed civil redress in cases prosecutors chose to leave unprosecuted. The Act also established the [[Office on Violence Against Women]] within the [[United States Department of Justice|Department of Justice]].

VAWA was drafted by the office of [[U.S. Senator|Senator]] [[Joe Biden]] ([[Democratic Party (United States)|D]]-[[Delaware|DE]]), with support from a broad coalition of advocacy groups. The Act passed through [[U.S. Congress|Congress]] with bipartisan support in 1994, clearing the [[United States House of Representatives|House]] by a vote of 235&amp;ndash;195 and the [[United States Senate|Senate]] by a vote of 61&amp;ndash;38, although the following year House [[Republican Party (United States)|Republicans]] attempted to cut the Act's funding.&lt;ref name="wp-funding"&gt;{{cite news | work = [[Washington Post]] | title = House GOP Budget Cutters Try to Limit Domestic Violence Programs | url = http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/washingtonpost/access/18605326.html?dids=18605326:18605326&amp;FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS=ABS:FT&amp;type=current&amp;date=Jul+15%2C+1995&amp;author=Kenneth+J.+Cooper&amp;pub=The+Washington+Post+%28pre-1997+Fulltext%29&amp;desc=House+GOP+Budget+Cutters+Try+to+Limit+Domestic+Violence+Programs | first = Kenneth | last = Cooper | accessdate = April 19, 2012 | date = July 15, 1995}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the 2000 [[United States Supreme Court|Supreme Court]] case ''[[United States v. Morrison]]'', a sharply divided Court struck down the VAWA provision allowing women the right to sue their attackers in federal court. By a 5&amp;ndash;4 majority, the Court's conservative wing overturned the provision as an intrusion on [[states' rights]].&lt;ref name="cnn-scotus"&gt;{{cite news | publisher = [[CNN]] | title = Supreme Court strikes down Violence Against Women Act | url = http://articles.cnn.com/2000-05-15/justice/scotus.violence_1_supreme-court-strikes-christy-brzonkala-civilized-system?_s=PM:LAW | first = Charles | last = Bierbauer | date = May 18, 2000 | accessdate = April 19, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | work = [[New York Times]] | first = Linda | last = Greenhouse | authorlink = Linda Greenhouse | title = Women lose right to sue attackers in federal court | url = http://www.nytimes.com/2000/05/16/us/supreme-court-court-federalism-women-lose-right-sue-attackers-federal-court.html | date = May 16, 2000 | accessdate=April 19, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

VAWA was reauthorized by Congress in 2000, and again in December 2005.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release|date=January 5, 2006|title=President Signs H.R. 3402, the "Violence Against Women and Department of Justice Reauthorization Act of 2005" |url=http://georgewbush-whitehouse.archives.gov/news/releases/2006/01/20060105-3.html |publisher=George W. Bush White House archives}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Act's 2012 renewal was fiercely opposed by [[conservatism in the United States|conservative]] Republicans, who objected to extending the Act's protections to [[same-sex relationship|same-sex couples]] and to provisions allowing battered [[illegal immigration to the United States|illegal immigrants]] to claim [[visa (document)|temporary visas]].&lt;Ref name="vawa-2012"&gt;{{cite news | work = [[New York Times]] | title = Women Figure Anew in Senate’s Latest Battle | accessdate = April 19, 2012 | date = March 14, 2012 | first = Jonathan | last = Weisman | url = http://www.nytimes.com/2012/03/15/us/politics/violence-against-women-act-divides-senate.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; In April 2012, the Senate voted to reauthorize the Violence Against Women Act, and the House subsequently passed its own measure (omitting provisions of the Senate bill that would protect gay men, lesbians, American Indians, and illegal immigrants who were victims of domestic violence). Reconciliation of the two bills has been stymied by procedural measures, leaving the reauthorization in question.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | work = [[New York Times]] | first = Jennifer | last = Steinhauer | title = THE CAUCUS; G.O.P. Push on Domestic Violence Act | url = http://nyti.ms/ThdlgP | date = July 31, 2012 | accessdate=October 13, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Background==
The [[World Conference on Human Rights]], held in Vienna in 1993, and the [[Declaration on the Elimination of Violence Against Women]] in the same year, concluded that civil society and governments have acknowledged that domestic violence is a public health policy and [[human rights]] concern. 

The Violence Against Women Act was developed and passed as a result of extensive grassroots efforts in the late 80's and early 1990s, with advocates and professionals from the battered women's movement, sexual assault advocates, victim services field, law enforcement agencies, prosecutors' offices, the courts, and the private bar urging Congress to adopt significant legislation to address domestic and sexual violence. Since its original passage in 1994, VAWA's focus has expanded from domestic violence and sexual assault to also include dating violence and stalking.  It funds services to protect adult and teen victims of these crimes, and supports training on these issues, to ensure consistent responses across the country.  One of the greatest successes of VAWA is its emphasis on a coordinated community response to domestic violence, sex dating violence, sexual assault, and stalking; courts, law enforcement, prosecutors, victim services, and the private bar currently work together in a coordinated effort that had not heretofore existed on the state and local levels.  VAWA also supports the work of community-based organizations that are engaged in work to end domestic violence, dating violence, sexual assault, and stalking, particularly those groups that provide culturally and linguistically specific services. Additionally, VAWA provides specific support for work with tribes and tribal organizations to end domestic violence, dating violence, sexual assault, and stalking against Indian women.

Many grant programs authorized in VAWA have been funded by the U.S. Congress.  The following grant programs, which are administered primarily through the Office on Violence Against Women in the U.S. Department of Justice have received appropriations from Congress:

STOP Grants (State Formula Grants); Transitional Housing Grants; Grants to Encourage Arrest and Enforce Protection Orders; Court Training and Improvement Grants; Research on Violence Against Indian Women; National Tribal Sex Offender Registry; Stalker Reduction Database; Federal Victim Assistants; Sexual Assault Services Program; Services for Rural Victims; Civil Legal Assistance for Victims; Elder Abuse Grant Program; Protections and Services for Disabled Victims; Combating Abuse in Public Housing; National Resource Center on Workplace Responses; Violence on College Campuses Grants; Safe Havens Project; Engaging Men and Youth in Prevention.

==Debate and legal standing==
The [[American Civil Liberties Union]] had originally expressed concerns about the Act, saying that the increased penalties were rash, the increased pretrial detention was "repugnant" to the US Constitution, the mandatory HIV testing of those only charged but not convicted is an infringement of a citizen’s  [[right to privacy]] and the edict for automatic payment of full restitution was non-judicious (see their paper: "Analysis of Major Civil Liberties Abuses in the Crime Bill Conference Report as Passed by the House and the Senate", dated September 29, 1994).  However, the ACLU has supported reauthorization of VAWA on the condition that the "unconstitutional DNA provision" be removed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|publisher=American Civil Liberties Union|url=https://secure.aclu.org/site/Advocacy?pagename=homepage&amp;id=251&amp;page=UserAction |title=Tell Congress to Support the Violence Against Women Act}}&lt;/ref&gt;  

The ACLU, in their July 27, 2005 'Letter to the Senate Judiciary Committee Regarding the Violence Against Women Act of 2005, S. 1197' stated that "VAWA is one of the most effective pieces of legislation enacted to end domestic violence, dating violence, sexual assault, and stalking. It has dramatically improved the law enforcement response to violence against women and has provided critical services necessary to support women in their struggle to overcome abusive situations."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=ACLU Letter to the Senate Judiciary Committee Regarding the Violence Against Women Act of 2005, S. 1197|publisher=ACLU|date=July 27, 2005|url=http://www.aclu.org/womensrights/violence/19921leg20050727.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some [[conservatism in the United States|conservative]] activists opposed the bill. A spokeswoman for [[Concerned Women for America]] called the Act a "boondoggle" which "creates an ideology that all men are guilty and all women are victims." Conservative activist [[Phyllis Schlafly]] denounced VAWA as a tool to "fill feminist coffers" and argued that the Act promoted "divorce, breakup of marriage and hatred of men."&lt;ref name="vawa-2012"/&gt;  

In 2000 the [[Supreme Court of the United States]] held part of VAWA unconstitutional in ''[[United States v. Morrison]]'' on federalism grounds.  Only the civil rights remedy of VAWA was struck down.  The provisions providing program funding were unaffected.&lt;ref&gt;[http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/scripts/getcase.pl?court=US&amp;vol=529&amp;invol=598 United States v. Morrison], 529 U.S. 598, 627;  "For these reasons, we conclude that Congress' power under § 5 does not extend to the enactment of § 13981.... The judgment of the Court of Appeals is Affirmed." (at end of opinion section III)&lt;/ref&gt;

As of April 2012, the law is currently up for reauthorization in Congress.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Bolduan|first=Kate|title=House passes GOP version of Violence Against Women Act renewal|newspaper=CNN|location=Washington|language=English|date=16 May 2012| url=http://www.cnn.com/2012/05/16/politics/gop-violence-against-women/index.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; Different versions of the legislation have been passed along party lines in the Senate and House, with the Republican-sponsored House version favoring the reduction of services to illegal immigrants and LGBT individuals. The two bills are currently pending [[Reconciliation (United States Congress)|reconciliation]], and with November elections approaching it is unclear whether a final bill will reach the President's desk before the end of the year.

==Programs and services==
The Violence Against Women laws provide programs and services, including:
* Community violence prevention programs 
* Protections for victims who are evicted from their homes because of events related to domestic violence or stalking 
* Funding for victim assistance services, like rape crisis centers and hotlines 
* Programs to meet the needs of immigrant women and women of different races or ethnicities
* Programs and services for victims with disabilities
* Legal aid for survivors of violence

==See also==
*[[Domestic violence]]
*[[Violence against women]]
*[[International Violence Against Women Act]]

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
*[http://frwebgate.access.gpo.gov/cgi-bin/getdoc.cgi?dbname=109_cong_bills&amp;docid=f:h3402enr.txt.pdf Violence Against Women Act]
*[http://www.ovw.usdoj.gov Office on Violence Against Women]
*[http://www.epic.org/privacy/dv/vawa.html Privacy Provisions of the Violence Against Women Act]
*[http://www.who.int/gender/violence/who_multicountry_study/en/ World Health Organization Multi-country Study on Women's Health and Domestic Violence against Women 2005]
*[http://nnedv.org/docs/Policy/VAWA2005FactSheet.pdf VAWA 2005 Fact Sheet]

[[Category:1994 in law]]
[[Category:United States federal criminal legislation]]
[[Category:Joe Biden]]
[[Category:Violence against women in the United States]]
[[Category:1994 in the United States]]
[[Category:Women's rights legislation]]
[[Category:Women's rights in the United States]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>