<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20051031011421|26931607" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="2406648" pageid="2406648" ns="0" title="Violence Against Women Act"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-11-06T00:06:03Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">The '''Violence Against Women Act of 1994''' (VAWA) was passed as Title IV, sec. 40001-40703 of the [[Violent Crime Control and Law Enforcement Act of 1994]] HR 3355 and signed as Public Law 103-322 by [[President Bill Clinton]] [[September 13]] [[1994]].  It provided $1.6 Billion to enhance investigation and prosecution of violent crime perpetrated against women, increased pre-trial detention of the accused, provided for automatic and mandatory restitution of those convicted, and allowed civil redress in cases prosecutors chose to leave unprosecuted.
 
The [[National Organization of Women]] heralded the bill as "the greatest breakthrough in civil rights for women in nearly two decades."   The [[American Civil Liberties Union]] derided the Act as "troubling" complaining that the increased penalties were rash, the increased pretrial detention was "repugnant" to the US Constitution, the mandatory HIV testing of those only charged but not convicted is an infringement of a citizen’s  [[right to privacy]] and the edict for automatic payment of full restitution was non-judicious in their paper "Analysis of Major Civil Liberties Abuses in the Crime Bill Conference Report as Passed by the House and the Senate, dated [[September 29]] [[1994]].  However, the ACLU has supported its reauthorization. [https://secure.aclu.org/site/Advocacy?JServSessionIdr011=8t6xwr9p52.app26a&amp;pagename=homepage&amp;id=251&amp;page=UserAction] [https://secure.aclu.org/site/Advocacy?JServSessionIdr011=8t6xwr9p52.app26a&amp;pagename=homepage&amp;id=251&amp;page=UserAction]

VAWA and the 1994 Crime Bill in general was supported by Congressional [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democrats]] and President Clinton and opposed by then minority Congressional [[Republican Party (United States)|Republicans]] with a few exceptions.[http://www.senate.gov/legislative/LIS/roll_call_lists/roll_call_vote_cfm.cfm?congress=103&amp;session=2&amp;vote=00295]  Ironically, [[Paula Jones]]' attorneys Susan Carpenter-McMillan, Gilbert Davis and Joseph Cammarata would use VAWA in winning arguments one year later to allow a civil suit against President Clinton for sexual harassment to proceed.  Eventually  President Clinton paid an out of court settlement of $850,000 for the harassment.

In 2000, the [[Supreme Court of the United States]] held part of VAWA unconstitutional in [[United States v. Morrison]].  Only the civil rights remedy of VAWA was struck down.  The provisions providing program funding were unaffected.

VAWA was reauthorized by [[U.S. Congress|Congress]] in 2000, and again in October 2005, when it passed the [[U.S. Senate|Senate]] unanimously.  It is due for further reauthorization in 2010.

== External links ==
[http://www.vawa2005.org vawa.org]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>