<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20081115050348|251909991" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="361024" pageid="361024" ns="0" title="Men&#039;s rights movement"><revisions><rev timestamp="2008-11-15T05:11:13Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Articleissues|OR=August 2007|refimprove=May 2007}}
{{Rights}}
'''Men’s rights''' are the [[Freedom (political)|freedoms]] inherently possessed by men and boys of all ages, which may be institutionalized, ignored or suppressed by law, custom, and behavior in a particular society. The term may also refer to an activist movement advancing these rights. Supporters of men's rights aim to promote the physical, economic and emotional well-being of all men and boys, viewing this as part of [[human rights]], [[civil rights]], or [[equal rights]].  They are particularly concerned with issues involving family life such as [[family law]], [[child custody]], [[paternity fraud]], and [[domestic violence]]. There is no single unifying manifesto or organization which can claim to speak for the entire movement and the term is used in various ways.

Related areas of the [[men's movement]] include: 
*[[Fathers' rights]] focus on the relationship between fathers and their children and in particular [[family law]].
*[[Masculism]] provides a counterpart to [[feminism]] and argues against legal constructs, reforms, or entitlements which deny men equal rights under the law on the basis of gender; there are conservative "traditionalist", "liberal", and libertarian strands. {{Fact|date=May 2007}}

==Men's rights movement==

In the 2000s men and concerned women began to share their concerns on the Internet, often bringing forward unheard statistics or viewpoints. Its supporters are considered part of the [[Men's Movement]], and often call themselves Men's Rights Activists, or MRAs. [[Father's rights]] and misuse of [[Domestic violence]] laws are areas central to the men's rights movement. Its concerns include  health, education, employment, civil rights, legal equality and representation, and [[Constitutional rights]].{{Fact|date=May 2007}} Many supporters are particularly concerned with the effect of Sexual Harassment, Divorce, Custody, Rape and Violence Against Women Act-type laws, on men's rights and freedoms. It is argued that these laws cause violation of Constitutional rights such as the right to a fair trial and the right to [[due process]].{{Fact|date=May 2007}}{{Who|date=August 2007}}

[[Affirmative Action]] programmes, and [[Title IX]] of the Education Amendments of 1972 are also areas of prime concern. One group, S.P.A.R.C., argues that these policies have a far more discriminatory effect than is widely reported or acknowledged.  &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.deltabravo.net/custody/waronboys.php The War Against Boys by Christina Hoff Sommers&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

Being a relatively new phenomenon, most people are still ''unaware'' of Men's rights, or do not come forward for social reasons. In many places, Men's Rights movements are despised, particularly by powerful feminist groups which see in it, a threat to its own ideology. 

Men's Rights Advocacy and [[Masculism]] also promote the concept of "defending male identity".  Typically MRAs would subscribe to masculinity as strength, honor and honesty.{{Fact|date=May 2007}}{{Who|date=August 2007}}

==History==

Prior to 1995 the men's movement was predominantly a reactive and disorganized movement that received little attention or recognition. The American Coalition for Fathers and Children was founded in 1995 by mature activists such as Stuart A. Miller, and Dianna Thompson. ACFC founded the [[shared parenting]] movement and organized the largest protests in the history of the men's movement, the largest held in over 225 cities around the world on father's day, 2001 in the "Bridges for Children" campaign.{{Fact|date=February 2007}}The Coalition of Free Men, commonly known as the National Coalition of Free Men (NCFM), was founded in 1977 and is the oldest active men's rights organization in existence. NCFM has chapters and members throughout the United States and in several countries. In 2008 the NCFM started doing business as the National Coalition for Men since people often struggled understanding the significance of the word "Free".{{Fact|date=September 2008}}

==Structure==

Like most [[social movement]]s, those concerned with men's rights comprise a wide variety of individuals and organizations, both united and divided in various ways on specific issues including the mistreatment of men in the [[Mass media|media]], the [[abortion debate]], [[family law]] and false rape allegations. Some groups are formally organized or incorporated, while others are casual alliances or the work of a few individuals.{{Fact|date=May 2007}}

Although the vast majority of men's rights leaders and activists are men, there are many  women, including those in significant positions within the movement. For example, Sue Price in the Australian [[Men's Rights Agency]] has been at the forefront of activism there. Naomi Penner was a women's rights activist in the 1960s who later helped to create the [[National Coalition of Free Men]] in America in 1981. B.N. Saraswati founded one of the earliest Men's right group in India.

Although most men's rights advocates are from the developed world, they form a diverse group, which include both singularly religious and atheistic individuals, as well as those from the left, right, and center of politics and every echelon of society.  Significantly, however, the Men's right movement caught strength in India with Purush Hakka Sanraskhshan Samsta, of "Save Indian Family".{{Fact|date=May 2007}}


==Issues==


{{Refimprove|date=December 2007}}
Within the larger context of human rights, men's rights advocates are concerned with many of the same general issues as proponents of [[women's rights]], only with special attention and consideration to the less recognised role of men and boys.{{Fact|date=May 2007}}. There are however radical Men's rights proponents who see Women's rights as the '[[enemy]]' ( and vice versa ), rather than as allies in a fight against gender based discrimination of various kinds.


=== Conscription === 

Male-only military [[conscription]] : The risks to life and limb in male-only military conscription, is not compensated and hence is gender biased against males.

=== Divorce ===

Women currently file slightly more than two-thirds of divorce cases in the US[http://paa2005.princeton.edu/download.aspx?submissionId=51210].  Proponents of men's rights are particularly concerned about cases where unfair divorce laws are exploited by women for financial gain.  The concept of [[alimony]] is perceived to encourage women to encourage divorce, and also argued to violate men's rights. The origins of [[alimony]] can be traced back to the ecclesiastical courts in England,[http://www.divorcenet.com/states/nevada/alimony_weakest_link] but more recently has reached huge proportions [http://www.cnn.com/2008/SHOWBIZ/03/17/mccartney.mills/index.html].  There is a movement for "no fault" and "no compensation" divorce legislation around the world.{{Fact|date=November 2008}} 

=== Marriage Strike ===

Marriage strike is the name given to the phenomenon of males refusing to give in to marriage for fear of unfair legislations and financial ramifications of divorce for the male. Divorce has been described as 'slavery for men'.[http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,94415,00.html] The Rutgers report — though based on a small sample — found ten prevalent reasons for declining preference for marriage among males. The first three : They can get sex without marriage; they can enjoy "a wife" through cohabitation; and, they want to avoid divorce and its financial risks.

=== Education ===

In recent years, girls in the United States are performing much better than boys in the same age group, in most schools and colleges. &lt;ref&gt;Yupin Bae, Susan Choy, Claire Geddes, Jennifer Sable, and Thomas Snyder, [http://165.224.221.98/programs/quarterly/vol_2/2_2/q6-1.asp "Trends in Educational Equity of Girls and Women"], Education Statistics Quarterly, U.S. Department of Education, 2000&lt;/ref&gt; In the United States, 57% of college students are women, and the number is growing. &lt;ref&gt;USA Today [http://www.usatoday.com/news/education/2005-10-19-male-college-cover_x.htm "College gender gap widens: 57% are women"]&lt;/ref&gt; The numbers of male teachers is even more alarming [http://www.guardian.co.uk/education/2008/aug/07/primaryschools.educationsgendergap]. Medical schools in the UK currently admit 2 females for each male. The trend is similar in other industrialized countries. Male rights protagonists claim that there is no comprehensive action yet. And powerful feminist groups may not allow recognition, on the need to narrow this divide. They feel that such apathy may lead to future generations of males becoming less educated, and hence less gainfully employed.

===Employment===

[[Employment law]] is another area of concern, with such problems as unequal treatment around [[parental leave]], [[retirement age]], and [[pension]] entitlements. They also assert [[sexual harassment]] policies are [[de facto]] directed against the male style of inappropriate sexual behavior in the workplace, while ignoring the female style of inappropriate behavior in the workplace. They express anguish towards the fact that a man telling a joke or simply referring to a co-worker by a nickname is grounds for dismissal or lawsuits.  Spain's recent 40% requirement on boardroom members has come under harsh criticism from the movement, while a company with 100% female board members would be acceptable under [[Jose Luis Rodriguez Zapatero|Zapatero's]] new law.{{Fact|date=May 2007}}{{Who|date=August 2007}}

Males are given less preference in employment both at recruitment and at career progression. Equal Opportunity laws refer only to females, while males are not given the same priority in areas such as nursing or secretaries, which are predominantly female, for example. There is also a tendency, in the absence of disincentives, to recruit attractive females, instead of males to jobs.


===Family===

{{seealso|Fathers' rights movement}}
[[Family law]] is an area of deep concern among men's rights groups. Men's rights enthusiasts point to a systematic bias against men by family courts regarding issues related to [[child custody]].  &lt;ref&gt;[http://menshealth.uws.edu.au/documents/NONRES%20FATHERS.html Nonresident Fathers’ Struggle With The System&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;


===Health===

Health disparity concerns of men's rights movements include:

*The disparity in the spending on men and women in the healthcare system.  As another example, in the [[United Kingdom]] significantly more money is spent on [[breast cancer]] research than [[prostate cancer]] research. &lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/low/health/663688.stm BBC News | HEALTH | £1m for prostate cancer research&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; 40,000 cases of breast cancer were detected in the UK in 2000 and claimed the lives of 13,000 women in 2002.  In 2000, about 27,200 cases of [[prostate cancer]] were detected and claimed nearly 10,000 lives in 2002 in the UK. Funding for prostrate cancer, however, is only about a fourth of breast cancer. Awareness for breast cancer is very prevalent in society today, with October being Breast Cancer Awareness Month in the United States. There is no proportionate funding for male cancer awareness or treatment.

*Increasing [[suicide]] rate amongst young men, four times higher than amongst young women in the United Kingdom[http://www.statistics.gov.uk/statbase/ssdataset.asp?vlnk=5228]; (73% of all suicide deaths in the United States are white males.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.policyalmanac.org/health/archive/suicide.shtml Suicide in the United States&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;)

*Workplace deaths and injuries occurs at a higher rate for men in the [[United Kingdom]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hse.gov.uk/statistics/tables/table11e.htm HSE - STATISTICS: Table 11e&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.springerlink.com/content/l0h5l77h16395wpv/ SpringerLink - Journal Article&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

*For [[domestic violence]], advocates cite government statistics that show that in 15% to 38% of the cases of intimate partner violence the victim is male. {{Fact|date=March 2007}}  They argue that the real number is likely to be higher, since male victims may be less likely to report abuse than female victims due to social stigmatization &lt;ref&gt;http://pandora.nla.gov.au/pan/13076/20021019-0000/www.nuancejournal.com.au/documents/three/saran.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;. They also assert that the percentage of shelters for battered men should make up a respective percentage of all shelters. The National Coalition of Free Men has sued several women's shelters with the goal of allowing battered men and their children to be admitted and to receive assistance from shelters (see [[domestic violence#Violence against men|Violence against men]]).

*Male [[Circumcision]] Unlike female circumcision, this evokes very little protest from the media


===Media portrayal===

Another issue of concern is the anti-male bias in the media. Men's rights activists claim that men are portrayed unfairly on television, radio and in newspapers and magazines.  They claim that not only does the media not pay serious attention to men's rights issues but that men are portrayed in a negative light, particularly in [[advertising]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|title =Standyourground.com boycott list of companies bashing men particularly in media
|url =http://www.standyourground.com/boyc.php 
 |accessdate=2008-05-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The lack of concern over men's issues such as higher rates of [[suicide]] by men, decline in academic achievement among boys, and a willingness of the press to print feminist statistics such as the "wage gap" has led to the term "Lace Curtain" being used.


===Politics and law===

In [[South Australia]]n Parliament, one MP stated "tongue-in-cheek" that men would need signed consent from women to protect themselves from false rape allegations, should a proposed law come into effect.  She described the proposed law as making men who are accused of rape guilty until proven innocent, and stated, "Having to have a consensual sex contract is ridiculous but having these laws that don't protect men's rights are also ridiculous."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news 
  |last=
  |first=
  | coauthors = 
  |title=''MP backs off on sex 'contracts' ''
  |work=
  |pages=
  |language=
  |publisher=
  |date=2008-04-03
  |url=http://www.abc.net.au/news/stories/2008/04/03/2207242.htm
  |accessdate=2008-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[VAWA]] in America are being vehemently opposed by rights groups. Similarly, laws such as [[498a]] in India are being fought by groups such as [[Save Indian Family]] Foundation.

===Rape Laws===

Allegations of rape can devastate a males life. However, studies show that about one fourth of convictions for rape, are false [http://www.ncjrs.gov/txtfiles/dnaevid.txt]. The researchers found that the three main motivations for reporting false rape are to provide an alibi where the accuser believes she may be pregnant or has had illicit consensual sex, revenge against a partner, and a desperate attempt to seek sympathy or attention [http://www.independent.co.uk/news/uk/home-news/truth-test-to-uncover-false-rape-allegations-634512.html]. A study by Kanin,[http://www.anandaanswers.com/pages/naaFalse.html] shows that 41% of rape cases are false. However, there is no punishment recorded, for false accusations of rape.

In India, pre-marital sex is considered rape, if a promise to marry is not kept. [http://ibnlive.in.com/news/sex-after-false-promise-of-marriage-is-rape-court/56328-3.html?xml]. There is no corresponding provision for girls making such 'false promises'. There is considerable apprehension about the rights of young men subjected to these laws.

===Refugees===

In Australian immigration policy a distinction is regularly made between ''women and children'' (often treated erroneously as equivalent to "family groups") and ''single men''. The details are subject to current debate and recently failed legislation (August 2006) in the Australian Parliament. But for example in one recent case, the Minister for Immigration, Senator Amanda Vanstone, determined as follows concerning Papuan asylum seekers: "The single men on the boat would be sent to an immigration detention centre, but families would not be split up and would be housed in facilities in the community".&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.smh.com.au/news/national/vanstone-refuses-to-return-papuans/2006/01/19/1137553712890.html "Vanstone refuses to return Papuans", ''Sydney Morning Herald'', 26 January 2006]&lt;/ref&gt; The discriminatory treatment of single women (routinely assumed to be members of some ''family'') and single men evident in such a practice is rarely examined in the Australian media.{{Fact|date=April 2008}}


===Reproductive rights and equality===
{{seealso|reproductive rights}}

The term [[Male abortion]] was coined by Melanie McCulley, a South Carolina attorney, in her 1998 article, "The Male Abortion: The Putative Father's Right to Terminate His Interests in and Obligations to the Unborn Child," which was published in The Journal of Law and Policy.&lt;ref&gt;McCulley, Melanie G. (1998). The male abortion: the putative father's right to terminate his interests in and obligations to the unborn child. The Journal of Law and Policy, Vol. VII, No. 1.&lt;/ref&gt;  The theory is that when an unwed female becomes pregnant she has the option of abortion, adoption, or parenthood; and argues, in the context of legally recognized [[gender equality]], that in the earliest stages of pregnancy the father should have the right to relinquish all future parental rights and financial responsibility -- leaving the informed mother with the same three options.

In 2006, the National Center for Men brought a case in the US, [[Dubay v. Wells]] (dubbed by some [[Roe v. Wade]] for men), that argued that in the event of an unplanned pregnancy, when an unmarried woman informs a man that she is pregnant by him, he should have an opportunity to give up all paternity rights and responsibilities.  Supporters argue that this would allow the woman time to make an informed decision and give men the same reproductive rights as women.&lt;ref&gt;Traister, Rebecca. (March 13, 2006). "[http://www.salon.com/mwt/feature/2006/03/13/roe_for_men/ Roe for men?]." ''Salon.com.'' Retrieved December 17, 2007. &lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nationalcenterformen.org/page7.shtml The National Center For Men, men's rights counseling divorce paternity false accusation men's equal right&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;  In its dismissal of the case, the U.S. Court of Appeals (Sixth Circuit) stated that "the Fourteenth Amendment does not deny to [the] State the power to treat different classes of persons in different ways."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ca6.uscourts.gov/opinions.pdf/07a0442p-06.pdf |format=PDF|title=U.S. Court of Appeals for the Sixth Circuit, case No. 06-11016}}&lt;/ref&gt;


===Social security and retirement===

In some societies there is legislated discrimination against males in provision of social security. In [[Australia]], for example, a woman over 50 years of age may obtain a ''Widow Allowance''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.centrelink.gov.au/internet/internet.nsf/payments/qual_how_wid.htm Who can get Widow Allowance?&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; approximately equal to a pension if, after turning 40, she becomes widowed, divorced, or merely separated from a spouse (who may be a de facto spouse). She must have "no recent workforce experience", but she can easily qualify for this well after the loss of her partner by going through a period of underemployment. There is no similar allowance for men. In Australia and the [[UK]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thepensionservice.gov.uk/atoz/atozdetailed/retirement.asp#state The Pension Service - A to Z - State Pension&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;, ''some'' of these discriminatory arrangements (including also women's earlier qualification for Age Pension, etc.) are being legally phased out.  The policy of "age 65 for men, age 60 for women" remains in place in most Western countries, however.


===Wages===

{{seealso|Male-female income disparity in the USA}}


===Biased Violence Laws===
{{seealso|Domestic violence}}

Members of the fathers' rights movement state that feminist organizations invoke the specter of domestic violence as propaganda directed against fathers and fathers' rights groups.&lt;ref name="Taken Into Custody 303"&gt;{{cite book
  | last =Baskerville
  | first =Stephen
  |title=Taken Into Custody - The War Against Fathers, Marriage and the Family
  |publisher=Cumberland House
  | comment =page 21
  |date=2007
  | accessdate =2007-10-22  }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Male Rights protagonists point to domestic violence studies based on the [[Conflict Tactics Scale]] (CTS), which suggest that men and women act violently toward their partners in about equal percentages.&lt;ref name = "Controlling DV Against Men"&gt;{{cite web 
  | title =Controlling Domestic Violence Against Men
  | coauthors =Charles E. Corry, Ph.D., Martin S. Fiebert, Ph.D., and Erin Pizzey  
  | publisher =Equal Justice Foundation  
  |date=2002  
  | url =http://www.ejfi.org/DV/dv-9.htm
  | accessdate =2007-10-04 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = "Men need help too"&gt;{{cite web
  | coauthors = McCormick, Mike and Sacks, Glenn J
  |title=October’s Domestic Violence Awareness Month Ignores Many Victims
  |publisher=American Coalition of Fathers and Children also Omaha World Herald, Daytona
  |             Beach News-Journal and the Louisville Courier-Journal
  |date=October 2006
  | url =http://www.acfc.org/site/PageServer?pagename=octobers_dv_awareness
  | accessdate =2007-03-15  }}&lt;/ref&gt;  They claim that men comprise a "significant portion" of the victims of domestic violence,&lt;ref name = "Equal Rights"&gt;{{cite web
  | coauthors = McCormick, Mike and Sacks, Glenn J
  |title=Equal Rights Amendment Yes, ‘Women’s Equality Amendment’ No
  |publisher=GlennSacks.Com, also the Louisville Courier
  |date=October 2006
  | url =http://www.glennsacks.com/equal_rights_amendment.htm
  | accessdate =2007-04-15  }}&lt;/ref&gt; and they call for more services to be provided for male victims of domestic violence.&lt;ref name = "Men need help too"/&gt; The controversial [[VAWA]] in the USA punishes males for violence against females [http://www.aavreform.org/], but radical Men's groups accuse politicians of giving legitimacy to feminine [[hysteria]]. The misuse of [[Domestic Violence]] laws at divorce, is one more factor that binds male groups around the world.

Opponents accuse men's right enthusiasts of ignoring and/or 'defending' male violence. Michael Flood claims that studies based on the [[Conflict Tactics Scale]]s (CTS) are unreliable and that men's rights advocates ignore this when they cite statistics based on CTS studies.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.xyonline.net/husbandbattering.shtml Claims about Husband Battering&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; 

While the media awareness group [[Fairness and Accuracy in Reporting]] acknowledges that violence against men by women takes place, it also suggests that a misreading of the Straus/Gelles studies accounts for the difference in numbers observed by some men's rights advocates and those from the [[US Government|American government's]] [http://www.ojp.usdoj.gov/bjs/abstract/vrithed.htm Bureau of Justice Statistics].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fair.org/index.php?page=1247 Battered Men? Battered Facts&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Save Indian Family]] Foundation, is a group of volunteers in India, fighting wide spread extra-judicial [[extortion]] and the other misuse of tough divorce laws such as [[498a]], in troubled marriages [http://www.merinews.com/catFull.jsp?articleID=144381]. Media and feminist [[vigilantism]] against allegedly cruel husbands, is currently encouraged in India [http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/articleshow/899182.cms].

==See also==
*[[Fathers 4 Justice]]
*[[Father's Rights]]
*[[Human rights]]
*[[Male abortion]]
*[[Masculinity]]
*[[Masculism]]
*[[Paternal rights and abortion]]
*[[Parental leave]]
*[[Paternity fraud]]
*[[Pro-feminism]]
*[[Feminism]]
*[[Radical Feminism]]
*[[Save Indian Family]]
*[[Shared parenting]]

===Significant writers===
*[[Michael Green]]
*[[Warren Farrell]]
*[[Christina Hoff Sommers]]
*[[Glenn Sacks]]
*[[Herb Goldberg]]

==References==
&lt;!-- this 'empty' section displays references defined elsewhere --&gt;
{{reflist|2}}

== Bibliography ==
*''Save the Males'' by Richard Doyle, 2006, ISBN 978-1411696334
*''The Myth of Male Power'' by [[Warren Farrell]], 1993.
*''Women Can’t Hear what Men Don’t Say: The myths that divide couples and poison love'' by [[Warren Farrell]], 1999.
*''The War against Boys: How misguided feminism is harming our young men'' by Christina Hoff-Sommers, 2000.
*''Who Stole Feminism: How women have betrayed women'' by Christina Hoff-Sommers, 1994.
*''Spreading Misandry: The teaching of contempt for men in popular culture'' by Paul Nathanson and Katherine K. Young, 2001.
*''The Hazards of Being Male: Surviving the Myth of Masculine Privilege'' by [[Herb Goldberg]], 1987.
*''Refusing to be a Man: Essays on Sex and Justice'' by John Stoltenberg, 1989.
*''Iron John: A Book About Men'' by [[Robert Bly]], 1990.
*''Stiffed: The Betrayal of the American Man'' by [[Susan Faludi]], 1999.
*''Men Freeing Men: Exploding the myth of the traditional male'' by Francis Baumli, 1985.
* ''Flood, Michael: Backlash: Angry men's movements'' in: Rossi, Staceay E.: ''The Battle and Backlash rage on.'' 2004, XLibris Corp., ISBN 1-4134-5934-X, S. 261-287 [http://www.xyonline.net/downloads/backlash.pdf]
* ''Flood, Michael: Men's movements'' in: XY magazine, vol. 6. 1996 [http://www.xyonline.net/downloads/Mensmovements.pdf]

==External links==
'''Bibliographic'''
*[http://mensbiblio.xyonline.net/ The Men's Bibliography], a comprehensive bibliography of writing on men, masculinities, gender and sexualities, listing over 16,700 works. (mainly from a constructionist perspective)
*[http://www.mensstudies.info/RMBP.html Regional Masculinities Bibliography Project] comprehensive guide to worldwide scholarly literature on masculinity
*[http://www.boyhoodstudies.com Boyhood Studies], features a 2200+ bibliography of young masculinities.

'''Other'''
*[http://www.xyonline.net XYonline], on men and gender issues. Includes over 180 articles on men, gender, masculinity and sexuality, and categorised links to 560 websites.
*[http://menanddepression.nimh.nih.gov/ NIMH Web Pages on Men and Depression], talks about men and their depression and how to get help.
* [http://howellgroup.org/parsifal.html Article entitled "Wounded Masculinity: Parsifal and The Fisher King Wound"] The symbolism of the story as it relates to the Wounded Masculinity of Men by Richard Sanderson M.Ed., B.A.

{{Discrimination}}

[[Category:Anthropology]]
[[Category:Gender]]
[[Category:Sociology]]
[[Category:Rights]]
[[Category:Men|Rights]]
[[Category:Men's rights| ]]

[[de:Männerrecht]]
[[fr:Virilité]]
[[pl:Maskulinizm]]
[[ru:Мужество]]
[[sv:Mansforskning]]
[[uk:Мужність]]
[[tr:Erkek hakları]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>