<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20040917154337|6228905" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="361024" pageid="361024" ns="0" title="Men&#039;s rights movement"><revisions><rev timestamp="2004-09-29T04:15:58Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Men's rights''' began as a recognisable movement in the 1980s, largely in response to the women's rights or [[feminist]] movement. It aims to address issues of concern to men and to remove institutional and societal [[discrimination]] against males. 

Those in the men's rights movement often do not consider themselves to be [[masculist]], and quite often do not subscribe to a recognisable orthodoxy or gender [[ideology]]. One conventional strand of opinion recognises the need for parity between people irrespective of their gender. To achieve this inevitably requires some measures that improve the position of men. This can lead to the mistaken perception that such measures are anti-women.

Amongst men's rights advocates there are a number of women, including those in significant positions in the movement. For example, Sue Price in the [[Men's Rights Agency]] has been at the forefront of activism to eliminate discrimination against men in Australia. Men's rights advocates are not a uniform group: they include both singularly religious and atheistic individuals, as well as those from the left and right of politics. Most supporters of men's rights are from western nations, where gender equity has for some time been advocated mainly from a woman's perspective. At present the main engine for change for men's rights derives from men's role as [[father|fathers]].

Some typical discrimination against men which the men's rights movement has identified are:

*[[Family law]]
**[[divorce]] and [[separation]]
**[[Child custody|custody over children]]
*[[Employment]]
**[[parental leave]]
**[[retirement age]]
**[[pension]] entitlement
**[[sexual harassment]] policies
*[[Education]]
**Practices which discriminate against boys 
*[[Law | Legal]] and [[Judiciary |judicial]] [[bias]]es and [[discrimination]]
**Males are more likely to be charged and convicted on the basis of [[Innocence project | false allegations]] of violent or sexual abuses
*[[Military]] 
**Conscription for males only (though women are also conscripted to military service in [[Israel]])
*[[Domestic Violence]]
**Lack of help for male victims and female perpetrators
**Female [[spousal abuse]] of husbands and male partners
**[[Bias]]ed information
*[[Media]]
**Depiction of men vs. depiction of women
**[[Violence]] against men as "[[humor]]"
**Coverage of men's issues vs. women's issues

In the [[US]], high rates of [[circumcision]] by the medical profession continue in many areas.  Many circumcised men are subjects of victim blaming by those who strive to maintain the [[status quo]] concerning alteration of male genitalia.

The men's rights movement has grown and changed in character since the 1980s.  Just as the women's rights movement was small and lacked political power during its early beginnings in the 1800s, so the much younger men's rights movement is small and lacking in significant organisation or influence.

See also: [[Fathers' rights]] , [[Shared parenting]] 

==See also==
*[[List of family separation research articles]]

== External links ==
*[http://www.mensrights.com.au/ Men's Rights Agency Australia]
*[http://www.ukmm.org.uk United Kingdom Men's Movement]
*[http://www.parity-uk.org Parity UK]
*[http://www.ncfm.org/ National Coalition of Free Men]
*[http://www.mensactivism.org/activism_files/what_are_mens_issues.pdf What are Men's Issues?] (PDF document)
*[http://www.menweb.org/throop/ Men's Issues]
*[http://www.fathersforlife.org/ Fathers for Life]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>