<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20111113170040|460462489" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="361024" pageid="361024" ns="0" title="Men&#039;s rights movement"><revisions><rev timestamp="2011-11-13T17:54:34Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{POV|date=March 2011}}
{{Globalize|date=September 2011}}
{{Rights}}
'''Men's rights''' is an umbrella term, encompassing the political [[rights]], [[entitlements]], and [[freedoms]] of males within a nation or culture. Men's rights is a relatively recent concept—stemming from the late 20th century, as opposed to the 18th century roots of the [[women's rights]] movements—and is still underdeveloped as a theory.{{citation needed|date=October 2011}}

The '''men's rights movement''' is concerned with topics such as inequities in reproductive rights, divorce settlements, domestic violence laws, and sexual harassment laws. It has also been expanded to include things such as education and health care.{{citation needed|date=October 2011}}
[[File:SIF-Picture.jpg|thumb|250px|Protest in New Delhi for men's rights organized by [[Save Indian Family]]]]

==Movements==
The men's rights movement is part of the [[men's movement]],&lt;ref name="Chapman2010"&gt;{{cite book|author=Roger Chapman|title=Culture wars: an encyclopedia of issues, viewpoints, and voices|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=vRY27FkGJAUC&amp;pg=PA355|accessdate=6 November 2011|year=2010|publisher=M.E. Sharpe|isbn=978-0-7656-1761-3|page=355}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Bank2011"&gt;{{cite book|author=Barbara J. Bank|title=Gender and Higher Education|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=jK6WOme5yaQC&amp;pg=PA237|accessdate=6 November 2011|date=1 February 2011|publisher=JHU Press|isbn=978-0-8018-9782-5|page=237}}&lt;/ref&gt; and advocates are known as "men's rights activists," or MRAs.{{cn|date=November 2011}} The men's rights movement is concerned with a wide variety of issues, some of which have spawned their own groups or movements. For example, the [[fathers' rights movement]] is concerned specifically with divorce and child custody issues.

===History===
The men's rights movement emerged in the [[United States]] during the late 1970s from the [[antifeminism|antifeminist]] branch of the [[men's liberation movement]].&lt;ref name=Chafetz&gt;{{cite book|last=Chafetz|first=Janet Saltzman|title=Handbook of the sociology of gender|year=2006|publisher=Springer Science|location=New York|isbn=0387324607|page=168}}&lt;/ref&gt; The men's rights movement also helped create the [[father's rights movement]] during this time period.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Men and masculinities: a social, cultural, and historical encyclopedia|last=Kimmel|first=Michael|page=289}}&lt;/ref&gt; Early men's rights organizations include [[Men's Rights, Inc.]] and [[Free Men, Inc.]], both formed in 1977.&lt;ref name=Chafetz/&gt;&lt;ref name=Ashe&gt;{{cite book|last=Ashe|first=Fidelma|title=The new politics of masculinity: men, power and resistance|year=2007|publisher=Routledge|location=London|isbn=0415302757|page=63}}&lt;/ref&gt; During the 1980s, several men's rights organizations from different parts of the United States joined to form the National Coalition of Free Men (now the [[National Coalition for Men]]).&lt;ref name=Ashe/&gt;

===Structure===
Like participants in most [[social movement]]s, those concerned with men's rights comprise a wide variety of individuals and organizations, both united and divided in various ways on specific issues.&lt;ref&gt;Farrell, W. &amp; Sterba, J. (2008) Does feminism discriminate against men? A Debate, New York: Oxford University Press&lt;/ref&gt; Some groups are formally organized or incorporated, while others are casual alliances or the work of a few individuals.&lt;ref name=farrell01&gt;Farrell, W. (2001) ''Father and Child Reunion'', New York: Finch.&lt;/ref&gt;

Major men's rights organizations include the [[National Coalition for Men]] and the [[American Coalition for Fathers and Children]]. The National Coalition for Men has 22 chapters in the United States and chapters in 5 other countries.&lt;ref&gt;[http://ncfm.org/lead-with-us/chapters/]&lt;/ref&gt; The American Coalition for Fathers and Children was founded in 1995 by Stuart A. Miller and Dianna Thompson in an effort to provide a forum for discussion of male rights.&lt;ref name=ACFC&gt;http://www.acfc.us/advisors.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

Although the vast majority of men's rights leaders and activists are men{{Citation needed|date=October 2011}}, there are some women, including those in significant positions within the movement. For example, Sue Price and her husband, Reg Price, are co-directors of the Australian Men's Rights Agency.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.mensrights.com.au/Contact_Us-Mens_Rights_Agency-Australia.aspx&lt;/ref&gt; Naomi Penner was a women's rights activist in the 1960s who later helped to create the [[National Coalition of Free Men]] in America in 1981. [[Christina Hoff Sommers]] has written two books highlighting a perceived disparity in the feminist movement's level of support for issues that disadvantage women compared to the feminist movement's level of support for issues that disadvantage men.&lt;ref name="Hoff-Sommers, C.2000"&gt;Hoff Sommers, C. (2000) The War Against Boys: How Misguided Feminism is Harming Our Young, Men, New York: Simon &amp; Schuster.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Hoff-Sommers, C. 1995"&gt;Hoff-Sommers, C. (1995) Who Stole Feminism?  How women have betrayed women, New York: Simon &amp; Schuster.&lt;/ref&gt;

There are a number of men's rights organizations active in India, many of whom focus around the perceived abuse of anti-dowry laws against men.&lt;ref name=TNN&gt;{{cite news|title=Men demand fair play|url=http://articles.timesofindia.indiatimes.com/2009-11-20/chandigarh/28100670_1_law-ministry-men-demand-awareness-programme|accessdate=20 October 2011|newspaper=Times of India|date=20 November 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;  One such organization is [[Save Indian Family|The Save Indian Family Foundation]] (SIFF) a registered non-profit headquartered in Bangalore, that claims more than 30,000 members.&lt;ref&gt;http://saveindianfamily.org/about-us.html&lt;/ref&gt; SIFF has stated that they feel that anti-dowry laws have regularly been used in efforts to settle petty disputes in marriage,&lt;ref name=DT&gt;{{cite news|last=Gilani|first=Iftikhar|title=Shoaib Malik controversy to hit Pakistan-India relations|url=http://www.dailytimes.com.pk/default.asp?page=2010%5C04%5C06%5Cstory_6-4-2010_pg2_6|accessdate=20 October 2011|newspaper=Daily Times|date=6 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; and have said that their helplines receive calls from many men who say that their wives have used false dowry claims to get them jailed.&lt;ref name=TA&gt;{{cite news|last=Dhillon|first=Amrit|title=Men say wives use India's pro-women laws to torment them|url=http://www.theage.com.au/news/world/men-say-wives-use-indias-prowomen-laws-to-torment-them/2007/12/23/1198344884127.html|accessdate=20 October 2011|newspaper=The Age|date=24 December 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Men's rights in social context==
===Marriage and divorce===
&lt;!-- Does not relate to Men's Rights
Legal and religious traditions have often dictated that rights to make decisions and take actions that influence both partners have lain with the male.&lt;ref&gt;OPSI, [http://www.opsi.gov.uk/RevisedStatutes/Acts/ukpga/1882/cukpga_18820075_en_1 Married Women's Property Act 1882]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="google114"&gt;{{Cite book| last = Blundell| first =Sue| title = Women in ancient Greece, Volume 1995, Part 2| publisher = Harvard University Press| year = 1995| page = 114| url = http://books.google.com/?id=Xfx1VaSIOgQC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=women+ancient+greece#v=onepage&amp;q=women%20athens&amp;f=false| isbn = 9780674954731}}&lt;/ref&gt;
--&gt;

====Divorce====
{{Main|Divorce}}

Conservative men's rights groups began organizing in opposition of divorce reform and custody issues around the 1960s. The men involved in the early organization believed that family and divorce law discriminated against them and favored their wives.&lt;ref&gt;ref name = Politics of Masculinity| title = The New Politics of Masculinity: Men, Power and Resistance |author = Christopher P. Mason| page = P57|&lt;/ref&gt;

====Child support====
{{main|child support}}

====Alimony====
{{Main|alimony}}
&lt;!--- Source is incorrect, please fix source and repost
Muslim men in India do not have to pay spousal support beyond three months, regardless of the financial situation of the former wife.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vakilno1.com/bareacts/hinduadoptionsact/s18.htm]&lt;/ref&gt;
----&gt;
In the US, spousal support may be awarded regardless of gender.  A legal precedent for gender-blind spousal support in the United States was made in ''[[Orr v. Orr]]'',&lt;ref&gt;http://supreme.justia.com/us/440/268/&lt;/ref&gt; where the Supreme Court invalidated Alabama's statutes by which husbands, but not wives, were required to pay alimony upon divorce. This statute was considered a violation of the Equal Protection Clause of the 14th Amendment. The percentage of alimony recipients in the US who were male rose from 2.4% in (1996–2001) to 3.6% in (2002–2006) and is expected to increase as more marriages feature a female primary earner.&lt;ref name=WSJMenAlimony&gt;{{cite news |url=http://online.wsj.com/article/SB120700651883978623.html |title=Men Receiving Alimony Want A Little Respect | accessdate=2009-02-03 | work=The Wall Street Journal | first=Anita | last=Raghavan | date=2008-04-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!--where is the link to rights?
====Child Support and Custody====
In the United States, Fathers were awarded custody in 17.4 percent of the time, a percentage that has statistically not changed since 1994. &lt;ref&gt;http://www.census.gov/prod/2009pubs/p60-237.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
--&gt;
&lt;!-- no citations
===Family===
{{See also|Fathers' rights movement}}
[[Family law]] is an area of deep concern among men's rights groups. These issues vary from state to state and country to country.
--&gt;

===Military Conscription===
{{See also|conscription}}
From the late 1970s on, the men's rights movement has argued that military conscription of men only is evidence of men's oppression.&lt;ref name="Messner199741-44"&gt;{{cite book|author=Michael A. Messner|title=Politics of masculinities: men in movements|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=nG8MGcopgWQC&amp;pg=PA41|year=1997|publisher=Rowman &amp; Littlefield|isbn=978-0-8039-5577-6|pages=41–44}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="BoydLongwood1996"&gt;{{cite book|author1=Stephen Blake Boyd|author2=W. Merle Longwood|author3=Mark William Muesse|title=Redeeming men: religion and masculinities|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=VSrhNzWb6sIC&amp;pg=PR17||date=6 November 1996|publisher=Westminster John Knox Press|isbn=978-0-664-25544-2|page=17}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

In 1971 in the United States, draft resisters initiated a class-action suit alleging that male only conscription violated men's rights to equal protection under the US constitution.&lt;ref name=tb/&gt;&lt;ref name="Binkin1993"/&gt; When the case reached the Supreme Court in 1981, they  were supported by a men's rights group and the multiple women's groups, including the [[National Organization for Women]].&lt;ref name=tb&gt;{{cite news |url= http://news.google.com/newspapers?id=UDFPAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=nwIEAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=6777,7767318&amp;dq=men%27s-rights+conscription&amp;hl=en |title=Supreme Court to begin hearing male-only military draft case |first= Richard  |last= Carelli|work=Toledo Blade|date= March 23, 1981|accessdate=12 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the Supreme Court upheld the Military Selective Service Act, stating that "the argument for registering women was based on considerations of equity, but Congress was entitled, in the exercise of its constitutional powers, to focus on the question of military need, rather than equity.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.law.cornell.edu/supct/html/historics/USSC_CR_0453_0057_ZS.html Cornell University Law School: Rostker v. Goldberg]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Binkin1993"&gt;{{cite book|author=Martin Binkin|title=Who will fight the next war?: the changing face of the American military|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=AOHD6sbzNysC&amp;pg=PA53|accessdate=12 November 2011|year=1993|publisher=Brookings Institution Press|isbn=978-0-8157-0955-8|page=53}}&lt;/ref&gt;  
&lt;!-- Until we find some adequate sources to balance this section ([[WP:UNDUE]] and [[WP:FRINGE]]) then it should remain commented out
===Media portrayal===
[[File:Carlsons.jpg|thumb|right|Many believe idealized portrayals of the masculine physique set an unrealistic standard for male beauty. Here, the [[Carlson Twins]] model clothing.]]

Another issue of concern to men's rights advocates is an alleged anti-male bias in the media. Men's rights activists argue that men are portrayed unfairly on television, radio, and in newspapers and magazines.  Drs Katherine K. Young and Paul Nathanson have published an extensive volume of literature on the issue including ''Spreading Misandry: The Teaching of Contempt for Men in Popular Culture'' (McGill-Queen's Native and Northern press); the first in what has become a four book publication on discrimination against males.{{Citation needed|date=March 2011}} They argue that not only does the media not pay serious attention to men's rights issues but that men are portrayed in a negative light, particularly in [[advertising]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|title =Standyourground.com boycott list of companies bashing men particularly in media
|url =http://www.standyourground.com/boyc.php
 |accessdate=2008-05-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The lack of concern over men's issues&lt;ref&gt;Farrell, W. &amp; Sterba, J. P. (2008) Does Feminism Discriminate Against Men: A Debate (Point and Counterpoint), New York: Oxford University Press.&lt;/ref&gt; such as higher rates of [[suicide]] by men, decline in academic achievement among boys, and a willingness of the press to print feminist statistics distorting the size of the "wage gap"&lt;ref name="Hoff-Sommers, C. 1995"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://digitalcommons.shu.ac.uk/ciod_papers/54/ Ridley-Duff, R. J. (2008) "Gendering, Courtship and Pay Equity: Developing Attraction Theory to Understand Work-Life Balance and Entrepreneurial Behaviour", paper to the ''31st ISBE Conference'', 5th–7th November, Belfast]&lt;/ref&gt; has led to the term "Lace Curtain" to describe feminist control over publishing and media representation of gender issues.&lt;ref&gt;Farrell, W. (2000) Women Can’t Hear What Men Don’t Say, New York: Tarcher/Putnam.&lt;/ref&gt;
--&gt;

===Refugees===
In Australian immigration policy a distinction is regularly made between ''women and children'' (often treated erroneously as equivalent to "family groups"{{Citation needed|date=September 2011}}) and ''single men''.{{Citation needed|date=September 2011}} The details are subject to current debate and recently failed legislation (August 2006) in the Australian Parliament. But for example in one recent case, former Minister for Immigration, Senator Amanda Vanstone, determined as follows concerning Papuan asylum seekers: "The single men on the boat would be sent to an immigration detention centre, but families would not be split up and would be housed in facilities in the community".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.smh.com.au/news/national/vanstone-refuses-to-return-papuans/2006/01/19/1137553712890.html "Vanstone refuses to return Papuans", ''Sydney Morning Herald'', 26 January 2006]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Paternity leave===

{{See also|parental leave}}

In the countries where parental leave is available, it is often not distributed equally between parents. This can lead to fathers not being able to spend enough time with their children after birth.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1&gt;{{cite web |work=Department of Business Enterprise &amp; Regulation (2007) (ed.): Internal Review of Leave Policies and Related Research 2007 |title= Employment Relations Research Series No. 80, p. 96, |url=http://www.berr.gov.uk/files/file40677.pdf |publisher=berr.gov.uk}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Social security and retirement===

Previously, in some countries that award some form of social security or pension, women qualified for benefits earlier in life than men. However, this is currently being phased out.

"Widow Allowance" in Australia is awarded to a woman born before 1 June 1955, with no recent workforce experience and with low income if she becomes widowed, divorced, or separated from a spouse or de facto partner (of either sex&lt;ref&gt;http://www.centrelink.gov.au/internet/internet.nsf/individuals/member_couple.htm "You will be regarded as a member of a couple if you usually live with your partner and are: married[,] in a registered relationship (opposite-sex or same-sex), or in a de facto relationship (opposite-sex or same-sex)."&lt;/ref&gt;). The provision is available to women only; not to men in identical circumstances.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.centrelink.gov.au/internet/internet.nsf/payments/widowa_eligible.htm] "You may be eligible for Widow Allowance if you are a woman and you [...] have become widowed, divorced or separated (including separated de facto) since turning 40 years of age".&lt;/ref&gt;

In the United Kingdom, women's earlier qualification for State Pension has ended for anyone born after 1955.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.advicenow.org.uk/living-together/pensions/state-pensions,10179,FP.html]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Equal treatment and protection under the law==
====Sentencing disparities====

In 2011, California lawmakers, headed by state senator [[Carol Liu]], implemented a policy to release female inmates who are parents, convicted of non-violent, non-sexual and non-child related crimes, which they have deemed “primary caregivers" despite not having custody due to being in jail. Robert Oakes, legislative director for Liu, stated about Liu's goal: “In crafting the bill, her intent was to single out female inmates with children...But that could not be done because of a constitutional ban against gender-based discrimination. So the phrase ‘primary caregiver’ was added to the bill.” The program is currently only being offered to women. It is believed that similar actions will be extended to men at some point in the future, although no date has been set.&lt;ref&gt;"[http://www.newsytype.com/11335-california-mothers-in-jail/ California releasing thousands of mothers from jail]", ''NewsyType.com''.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.youtube.com/user/kcratv#p/search/4/VuEcZsIRJP0&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.latimes.com/news/local/la-me-prison-home-20110913,0,6210913.story&lt;/ref&gt;

====Rape laws====

{{See also|false accusation of rape}}

In most states in the [[United States]] it is possible to get a conviction for rape without corroborating evidence. Thus the issue of false accusations of rape is very serious.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Anderson |first1=Michelle |year=2004 |title=The Legacy of the Prompt Complaint Requirement, Corroboration Requirement, and Cautionary Instructions on Campus Sexual Assault |journal=Boston University Law Review |volume= 84|issue= }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Studies that review the evidence and report those that they can determine are conclusively false tend to find lower numbers while studies that ask the claimants to indicate if they have lied find higher numbers. More than half report a prevalence greater than fifteen percent.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Rumney |first1=Philip |last2= |first2= |year=2006 |title=False Allegations of Rape |journal=[[Cambridge Law Journal]] |volume=65 |issue= |pages=128–158 |publisher= |doi= |url= |accessdate= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Sentencing for those convicted of making such allegations are often perceived as being too lenient in comparison to the severe penalties imposed upon rapists.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.guardian.co.uk/society/2011/jan/28/false-rape-complaint-prosecution&lt;/ref&gt;

In many jurisdictions, alleged victims of [[Rape shield law|rape are given anonymity]] while this is not extended to the accused. The British government announced plans to grant anonymity to the accused but withdrew plans after criticism from campaign groups such as "Women Against Rape."&lt;ref&gt;http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-politics-10760239&lt;/ref&gt;

==Reproductive rights==
{{See also|reproductive rights}}

=====Spousal notification laws=====
In China the law states that a woman has no overriding priority over her spouse in deciding whether to have a child.&lt;ref&gt;Maximova, Vickie.  "[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/asia-pacific/1883709.stm Chinese man sues wife over abortion]."  (March 20, 2002). ''BBC News.'' Retrieved May 26, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Egypt]], [[Guinea-Bissau]], [[Abortion in Iran|Iran]], [[Iraq]], [[Abortion in Japan|Japan]], [[Republic of Korea]], [[Kuwait]], [[Malawi]], [[Morocco]], [[Abortion in Nicaragua|Nicaragua]], [[Saudi Arabia]], [[Syria]], [[Abortion in Turkey|Turkey]], and the [[United Arab Emirates]] all legally require that an abortion must be authorized by the woman's husband. However, in some countries, this authorization law can be overridden if there is genuine concern for maternal health.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Rahman, Anika; Katzive, Laura; Henshaw, Stanley K. |title=A Global Review of Laws on Induced Abortion, 1985–1997 |journal=International Family Planning Perspectives |volume=24 |issue=2 |pages= |year=1998 |doi= |url=http://www.guttmacher.org/pubs/journals/2405698.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=====Adoption=====
 
In [[Oregon]] an adoption may be granted without the consent of a married woman's husband if it has been determined that her husband at such time was not the father of the child; in this case, consent of the husband (or father) is not required.&lt;ref&gt;http://laws.adoption.com/statutes/oregon-laws,3.html)&lt;/ref&gt;

=====Abortion=====
The [[male abortion]], sometimes called a "financial abortion", describes a putative father's right to terminate his interests in and obligations to the unborn child.&lt;ref&gt;Savali (2011).&lt;/ref&gt;

In the US in 2006, ''[[Dubay v. Wells]]'' argued that in the event of an unplanned pregnancy, the male should have an opportunity to decline all paternity rights and responsibilities. Supporters said that this would allow the woman time to make an informed decision and give men the same reproductive rights as women.&lt;ref&gt;Traister, Rebecca. (March 13, 2006). "[http://www.salon.com/mwt/feature/2006/03/13/roe_for_men/ Roe for men?]." ''Salon.com.'' Retrieved December 17, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nationalcenterformen.org/page7.shtml The National Center For Men, men's rights counseling divorce paternity false accusation men's equal right&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; In its dismissal of the case, the U.S. Court of Appeals (Sixth Circuit) stated that "the Fourteenth Amendment does not deny to [the] State the power to treat different classes of persons in different ways."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ca6.uscourts.gov/opinions.pdf/07a0442p-06.pdf |format=PDF|title=U.S. Court of Appeals for the Sixth Circuit, case No. 06-11016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=====Reproductive rights after divorce=====

In 2003, a British woman lost her challenge against the 1990 Human Fertilization and Embryology Act which specifically states that both partners must consent to the use of their genetic material. She was attempting to gain access to fertilized embryos, frozen prior to her divorce from her ex-husband who had since withdrawn his consent.&lt;ref&gt;http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/3212677.stm&lt;/ref&gt; However, another British man was forced to pay child support for children conceived artificially after his ex-wife used sperm frozen during their marriage. In this case, the woman had falsely claimed his consent when undergoing the procedure.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-1392045/Man-ordered-pay-100-000-children-ex-wife-tricks-clinic-using-frozen-sperm.html&lt;/ref&gt;

=====Paternity fraud=====
{{See also|paternity fraud}}

Estimates have ranged that there might be as many as 800,000 incorrect paternity judgement in [[California]] alone (because of defaults). Once so judged, it is extremely difficult or even impossible to get liability for child support removed.&lt;ref&gt;Henry (2006).&lt;/ref&gt; In some cases a husband is responsible for his wife's children no matter what, even if the child is not his own.&lt;ref&gt;Holstein and Sacks (2011). "Currently the only person who can be held legally responsible to support the child is the mother's then-husband, who is presumed to be the father because the child was born into the marriage. Judges routinely (and at times apologetically) saddle such "duped dads" with stiff child support orders."&lt;/ref&gt;

==Male parental rights==

{{See also|Father's rights movement}}

In many industrialized nations where divorce is common, father's rights activists hold the belief that men are unfairly discriminated against in family courts when deciding issues of child custody.&lt;ref name =collier&gt;{{cite news | last =Collier | first =R   | coauthors =Sheldon S| title =Unfamiliar territory: The issue of a father's rights and responsibilities covers more than just the media-highlighted subject of access to his children |publisher= [[The Guardian]]  | date =2006-11-01  | url =http://society.guardian.co.uk/children/story/0,,1935970,00.html  |accessdate=2007-10-17 | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!--commenting out for now, there is nothing that links this to men's rights in the original source. 
===Paternity fraud==

{{See also|Paternity fraud}}

Paternity fraud refers to a paternal discrepancy or a non-paternity event, in which a mother names a man to be the biological father of a child, particularly for self-interest, when she knows or suspects that he is not the biological father. This has led to a number of cases of victims seeking compensation from mothers or, in some cases, being forced by the courts to continue payment even while in possession of a negative paternity test.&lt;ref&gt;http://jme.bmj.com/content/33/8/475.full&lt;/ref&gt; --&gt;

==Political representation==
In the United Kingdom, where there is a [[Minister for Women]], there have been calls for an analogous "Minister for Men". [[Lord Northbourne]], who made the first parliamentary call for such in 2004,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/uknews/1343276/Yesterday-in-Parliament.html | work=The Daily Telegraph | location=London | title=Yesterday in Parliament | first=Michael | last=Kallenbach | date=2000-06-16 | accessdate=2010-05-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; told the BBC that "if the government feels they need a minister to address women's issues, it should be the same for men."&lt;ref name="Northbourne"&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/programmes/bbc_parliament/3522631.stm | work=BBC News | title=FHM: For Him Minister? | date=2004-03-03 | accessdate=2010-05-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; Northbourne's proposal was presented to the prime minister during [[prime minister's questions]] the same year.&lt;ref&gt;http://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_answers/2004/mar/08/minister-for-men#S6CV0418P2_20040308_CWA_745&lt;/ref&gt; The proposal was rejected and Northbourne and others{{Who|date=September 2011}} argue that such a minister is needed, pointing to a relatively poor standard of health for men, [[Fathers' rights]], male suicide rates, and males under-performing in education compared to females.&lt;ref name="Northbourne"/&gt;

==Domestic violence==
{{See also|Domestic violence}}

Since the late 1970s and 1980s men's rights activists have asserted that a combination of feminist ideology and men's reluctance to admit being victims has covered up the large amount of domestic violence and murders committed by women.&lt;ref name="Messner1997"&gt;{{cite book|author=Michael A. Messner|title=Politics of masculinities: men in movements|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=nG8MGcopgWQC&amp;pg=PA84|accessdate=22 October 2011|year=1997|publisher=Rowman &amp; Littlefield|isbn=978-0-8039-5577-6|pages=84–85}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Miller2005"/&gt;&lt;ref name=observer&gt;{{cite news |url= http://www.guardian.co.uk/society/2003/dec/21/socialcare.uknews |title=Battered men get their own refuge &amp;#124; Society &amp;#124; The Observer |first= Jamie |last= Doward |work=[[The Observer]] |date=21 December 2003|publisher=[[Guardian Media Group|GMG]] |location=[[London, England|London]] |issn=0261-3077 |oclc=60623878 |accessdate=22 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; They state that women are as violent as men and that domestic violence is sex-symmetrical.&lt;ref name="Dragiewicz2011a"&gt;{{cite book|author=Molly Dragiewicz|title=Equality with a Vengeance: Men's Rights Groups, Battered Women, and Antifeminist Backlash|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=OHr7yWfEjQYC&amp;pg=PA84|accessdate=22 October 2011|date=12 April 2011|publisher=UPNE|isbn=978-1-55553-739-5|pages=84–5}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="LosekeGelles2005"&gt;{{cite book|author1=Donileen R. Loseke|author2=Richard J. Gelles|author3=Mary M. Cavanaugh|title=Current controversies on family violence|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=YBVGswoPYqMC&amp;pg=PA92|accessdate=22 October 2011|year=2005|publisher=SAGE|isbn=978-0-7619-2106-6|page=92}}&lt;/ref&gt; They argue that the judicial system too easily accepts false allegations of domestic violence made by women against their male partner.&lt;ref name="Boyd2007"&gt;{{cite book|author=Susan B. Boyd|title=Reaction and resistance: feminism, law, and social change|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=ASc568aunFoC&amp;pg=PA85|accessdate=22 October 2011|date=1 October 2007|publisher=UBC Press|isbn=978-0-7748-1411-9|page=85}}&lt;/ref&gt; Men's rights writer [[Christina Hoff Sommers]] has commented that "false claims about male domestic violence are ubiquitous and immune to refutation".&lt;ref&gt;Sommers (2011).&lt;/ref&gt;  In Western countries, men's rights activists have been vocal critics of legal and policy protection for abused women.&lt;ref name="Dragiewicz2011 b"&gt;{{cite book|author=Molly Dragiewicz|title=Equality with a Vengeance: Men's Rights Groups, Battered Women, and Antifeminist Backlash|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=OHr7yWfEjQYC&amp;pg=PA84|accessdate=22 October 2011|date=12 April 2011|publisher=UPNE|isbn=978-1-55553-739-5|pages=84–5}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="LosekeGelles2005"&gt;{{cite book|author1=Donileen R. Loseke|author2=Richard J. Gelles|author3=Mary M. Cavanaugh|title=Current controversies on family violence|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=YBVGswoPYqMC&amp;pg=PA92|accessdate=22 October 2011|year=2005|publisher=SAGE|isbn=978-0-7619-2106-6|page=92}}&lt;/ref&gt; They have campaigned for domestic violence shelters for battered men,&lt;ref name=observer/&gt;&lt;ref name="Miller2005"&gt;{{cite book|author=Susan L. Miller|title=Victims as offenders: the paradox of women's violence in relationships|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=7CsgywvFH-EC&amp;pg=PA16|accessdate=22 October 2011|date=October 2005|publisher=Rutgers University Press|isbn=978-0-8135-3671-2|page=16}}&lt;/ref&gt; and for the legal system to be educated about women's violence.&lt;ref name="Miller2005"/&gt;&lt;!--

commented out for now, WP:FRINGE it also restates the above Glenn Sacks and Mike McDormick, a fathers rights advocates, argues that using the data from The National Family Violence Survey, men comprise a "significant portion" of the victims of domestic violence,&lt;ref name = "Equal Rights"&gt;{{cite web
  | coauthors = McCormick, Mike and Sacks, Glenn J
  |title=Equal Rights Amendment Yes, ‘Women's Equality Amendment’ No
  |publisher=GlennSacks.Com, also the Louisville Courier
  |date=October 2006
  | url =http://www.glennsacks.com/equal_rights_amendment.htm
  | accessdate =2007-04-15  }}&lt;/ref&gt; and call for more services to be provided for male victims of domestic violence.  
--&gt;&lt;!-- this just seems to be a discussion of statistics, not related to rights.
Advocates cite{{Citation needed|date=September 2011}} government statistics that show that in 15% to 31.5% of the cases of intimate partner violence the victim is male.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ncjrs.gov/pdffiles1/nij/181867.pdf |format=PDF|title=Extent, Nature, and Consequences of Intimate Partner Violence}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Furthermore, according to a 2000 CDC/Justice study, "Approximately 23% of the men who had lived with a man as a couple reported being raped, physically assaulted, and/or stalked by a male cohabitant, while 7.4% of the men who had married or lived with a woman as a couple reported such violence by a wife or female cohabitant."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ncjrs.gov/txtfiles1/nij/181867.txt]&lt;/ref&gt;  Researchers from [[Charles Sturt University]] argue that the real numbers for violence against men are likely to be higher, since male victims may be less likely to report abuse than female victims due to social stigmatization.&lt;ref&gt;http://pandora.nla.gov.au/pan/13076/20021019-0000/www.nuancejournal.com.au/documents/three/saran.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

Critics such as Michael Flood accuse men's right enthusiasts of misrepresenting male violence or statistics about domestic violence. Michael Flood and Michael Kimmel criticize the methodology of the [[Conflict Tactics Scale]]s (CTS) arguing it excludes information about "intensity, context, consequences or meaning" noting that women are more likely to sustain injuries, fear for their lives, and experience sexual abuse and that the study omits data on intimate homicide, sexual abuse, and violence as self-defense. He concludes "[CTS] relies on only one partner's reports despite poor interspousal reliability" and agrees that while studies do show men are likely to under-report subjection to domestic violence, there is no evidence men are "more likely to under-report than female victims". He further notes that men under report their own violence committed against women and women do the reverse (Kimmel 2001, 10–11).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.xyonline.net/sites/default/files/Flood_Mythsmisconceptions.doc Father's Rights and Violence Against Women]&lt;/ref&gt; He states "crime victimization studies based on large-scale aggregate data, household and crime surveys, police statistics, and hospital data all show that men assault their partners and ex-partners at rates several times the rate at which women assault theirs and that female victims greatly outnumber male victims (Tjaden &amp; Thoennes 2000, pp. 25–26)".

In response to criticism about the influence of former (rather than current) partners – further studies based on the CTS 2 scale continue to show that women initiate violence at least as often as men, and perpetrate serious violence as often as men.&lt;ref&gt;Farrell, W. (2000) Women Can't Here What Men Don't Say, New York: Tarcher/Putnam&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.csulb.edu/~mfiebert/assault.htm Fiebert, M. (2005) References examining assaults by women on their spouses or male partners: An annotated bibliography], California State University, accessed 08 May 2006. Previously published in Sexuality and Culture, 1997, 1, 273–286 and also Sexuality and Culture, 2004, 8(3–4), 140–177.&lt;/ref&gt; In a study specifically examining the behaviour of former partners, Dutton &amp; Winstead (2006) found that women initiate revenge behaviours more frequently than men.&lt;ref&gt;Dutton, L. B., Winstead, B. A (2006) "Predicting unwanted pursuit: attachment, relationship satisfaction, relationship alternatives, and break-up distress", ''Journal of Social and Personal Relationships'', 23(4): 565–586.&lt;/ref&gt; 
--&gt;&lt;!-- Although we probably need a section on DV in this article, it shouldn't be a single set of lines without a perfect source about women's shelters.

A few women's shelters will assist male victims of domestic abuse &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.safe4all.org/resource-list/index?category=1] http://www.safe4all.org/resource-list/index?category=1  Resource List for Abused Men.  S.A.F.E. last accessed October 14, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;, but do not house men. Some may offer hotel vouchers, counseling, case management, legal services and other support services.{{Citation needed|date=October 2011}} 
--&gt;&lt;!--
[[498a]] in India, outlawing cruelty to women by their husband or his relatives, are being fought by groups such as [[Save Indian Family]] Foundation.
--&gt;

==Health==

The men's rights movement claims that men suffer shorter lives, higher successful suicide rates and higher incidents of most stress-related diseases than women do.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Men and masculinities: a social, cultural, and historical encyclopedia|last=Kimmel|first=Michael|page=531}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Circumcision===
Some authors have argued that [[circumcision]] is a violation of men's right to health and bodily integrity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=El-Salam|first=Seham Abd|title=The Importance of Genital Mutilations to Gender Power Politics|journal=Al-Raida|year=2002/2003|volume=20|issue=99|page=42|publisher=Institute for Women’s Studies in the Arab World|quote=Women’s defense of men’s right to bodily integrity and their work against MGM will not have a negative impact on their struggle against FGM.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Green|first=James|title=The Male Herbal: The Definitive Health Care Book for Men &amp; Boys|year=2007|publisher=Crossing Press|location=Berkeley, Calif.|isbn=1580911757|edition=2nd|quote=Circumcision: A Common Form of Disregard for Men's Rights… Glick emphasizes that infants are persons with full civil rights, and therefore no one has the right to impose circumcision on them—not even parents.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Denniston|first=George C.|title=Male and female circumcision medical, legal, and ethical considerations in pediatric practice|year=1999|publisher=Kluwer Academic/Plenum Publishers|location=New York|isbn=0306461315|page=348}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Men's rights}}

*[[Feminism]]
*[[Human rights]]
*[[Paternal rights and abortion]]
*[[Parental leave]]
*[[Sexism]]
*[[Women's rights]]

==References==
&lt;!-- this 'empty' section displays references defined elsewhere --&gt;
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

== Bibliography ==
*{{cite journal |last1=Archer |first1=John |last2= |first2= |year=2000|title=Sex differences in aggression between heterosexual partners: A meta-analytic review |journal=Psychological Bulletin |volume=126 |issue=5 |pages=651–680 |publisher= |doi=10.1037/0033-2909.126.5.651 |url= |accessdate=|quote=}}
*{{cite journal |last1=Basu|first1=Alaka |last2= |first2= |year=1995|title=ICPD: What about men's rights and women’s responsibilities? |journal= Health Transition Review |volume=6|issue= |pages=95-9 |publisher= |doi= |url= |accessdate=|quote=}}
*{{cite news |title=A licence to indoctrinate |first=Jennie|last=Bristow |url=http://www.spiked-online.com/index.php/site/article/6769/ |newspaper=[[Spiked (magazine)|Spiked]] |date=12 February 2003 |accessdate=17 October 2011}}
*{{cite journal |last1=Frieze |first1=Irene |last2= |first2= |year=2000 |title=Violence in close relationships—development of a research area: Comment on Archer (2000) |journal=[[Psychological Bulletin]] |volume=126 |issue=5 |pages=681–684 |publisher= |doi= |url= |accessdate=}}
*{{cite journal |last1=Henry|first1=Ronald K.|last2= |first2= |year=2006|title=The Innocent Third Party: Victims of Paternity Fraud |journal= Family Law Quarterly |volume=40|issue=1 |pages= |publisher= |doi= |url= |accessdate=|quote=}}
*{{cite news |title=Bill would give 'duped dads' some fairness under the law |last1=Holstein|first1=Ned |last2=Sacks|first2=Glenn |url=http://www.dailynews.com/opinions/ci_18185434 |newspaper=Los Angeles Daily News |date=1 June 2011 |accessdate=29 October 2011}}
*{{cite news |title=Manhattan Moment: What America really needs is a White House Council on Men and Boys |first=Kay|last=Hymowitz |url=http://washingtonexaminer.com/opinion/columnists/2011/03/manhattan-moment-what-america-really-needs-white-house-council-men-and-bo |newspaper=Washington Examiner |date=22 March 2011 |accessdate=17 October 2011}}
*{{cite journal |last1=Kelly |first1=Linda |last2= |first2= |year=2003 |title=Disabusing the definition of domestic abuse: How women batter men and the role of the feminist state |journal=[[Florida State University Law Review]] |volume=30 |issue= |pages=792–793 |publisher= |doi= |url= |accessdate=|quote=}}
*{{cite news |title=Battered Men Sounding Equal-Rights Battle Cry |first=Tamar |last=Lewin |url=http://www.nytimes.com/1992/04/20/us/battered-men-sounding-equal-rights-battle-cry.html?pagewanted=all&amp;src=pm |newspaper=New York Times |date=20 April 1992 |accessdate=17 October 2011}}
*{{Cite report |last1=Mead|first1=Sara  |authorlink= |coauthors= |date=June 2006 |title=The Truth About Boys and Girls |url= |publisher=
Education Sector |page= |docket= |accessdate= |quote= }}
*{{cite journal |last1=Mills|first1=Michael |last2= |first2= |year=1990|title=The  New Heretics: Men |journal=American Psychologist |volume=45|issue=5 |pages=675–678 |publisher= |doi= |url= |accessdate=|quote=}}
*{{cite book |title=The psychology of female violence: Crimes against the body |last=Motz |first=Anna |authorlink= |coauthors= |year=2008 |publisher=[[Routledge]] |location=[[New York]] |isbn=0-203-93091-6 |page= |pages= |url= |accessdate=}}
*{{cite book |title=A man's world?: changing men's practices in a globalized world |last1=Pease|first1=Bob|last2=Pringle|first2=Keith|authorlink= |coauthors= |year=2001 |publisher=[[Zed Books]] |location=London |isbn=9781856499125|page= |pages= |url= |accessdate=}}
*{{cite news |title=Respecting Accuracy In Domestic Abuse Reporting (radar) |last=Rosenthal|first=Mark |url= |newspaper=Bulverde Standard |date=29 March 2006 |accessdate=17 October 2011}}
*{{cite news |title=Should Men Have the Right to 'Financial Abortions'? |last=Savali|first=Kirsten West |url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/kirsten-west-savali/fathers-financial-abortion_b_1015286.html |newspaper=The Huffington Post |date=20 October 2011 |accessdate=17 October 2011}}
*{{cite news |title=Domestic violence myths help no one |first=Christina Hoff|last=Sommers |url=http://www.usatoday.com/news/opinion/forum/2011-02-03-sommers04_st_N.htm |newspaper=USA Today |date=4 February 2011 |accessdate=17 October 2011}}
*{{cite book |title=Legalizing misandry: from public shame to systemic discrimination against men |last1=Young |first1= Katherine |last2=Nathanson|first2=Paul|authorlink= |coauthors= |year=2006 |publisher=[[McGill-Queen's University Press]] |location= |isbn=9780773528628 |page= |pages= |url= |accessdate=}}
*{{cite news |title=Men's Rights |first=Kathy|last=Young|url=http://www.forbes.com/2009/11/19/mens-rights-feminism-equality-violence-opinions-contributors-cathy-young.html |newspaper=Forbes |date=4 February 2011 |accessdate=22 October 2011}}
*{{cite news |title=License to kill: men and women, crime and punishment |first=Kathy|last=Young|url= |newspaper=Reason Magazine |date=July 2011 |accessdate=22 October 2011}}

*''The Myth of Male Power'' by [[Warren Farrell]], 1993.
* ''Flood, Michael: Backlash: Angry men's movements'' in: Rossi, Staceay E.: ''The Battle and Backlash rage on.'' 2004, XLibris Corp., ISBN 1-4134-5934-X, S. 261–287 [http://www.xyonline.net/downloads/backlash.pdf]
* ''Flood, Michael: Men's movements'' in: XY magazine, vol. 6. 1996 [http://www.xyonline.net/downloads/Mensmovements.pdf]
* ''Emotion, Seduction and Intimacy: Alternative Perspectives on Human Behaviour'' (Third Edition) by Rory Ridley-Duff, Seattle, OR: Libertary Editions, ISBN 978-1-935961-00-0, http://www.libertary.com/book/emotion-seduction-intimacy

==External links==
'''Bibliographic'''
*[http://mensbiblio.xyonline.net/ The Men's Bibliography], a bibliography of writing on men, masculinities, gender and sexualities, listing over 16,700 works - primarily from a constructionist perspective
*[http://www.boyhoodstudies.com Boyhood Studies], features a 2200+ bibliography of young masculinities.

{{Discrimination}}
{{Masculism}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Men's Rights}}
[[Category:Anthropology]]
[[Category:Gender]]
[[Category:Sociology]]
[[Category:Men|Rights]]
[[Category:Men's rights| ]]

[[ja:男性差別]]
[[pl:Maskulinizm]]
[[sv:Mansforskning]]
[[tr:Erkek hakları]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>