<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20121116170658|523351047" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="361024" pageid="361024" ns="0" title="Men&#039;s rights movement"><revisions><rev timestamp="2012-11-16T18:14:52Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Rights}}

The '''men's rights movement''' (MRM), a subset of the larger [[men's movement]], is focused on addressing discrimination against men in areas such as [[reproductive rights]], [[divorce]] settlements, [[domestic violence]] laws, and [[sexual harassment]] laws.{{sfn|Newton|2004|p = [http://books.google.ca/books?id=bXZkmNTSQUAC&amp;pg=PA190 190-200]}}  It branched off from the [[men's liberation]] movement in the early 1970s, differing from that movement in its focus and rejection of pro-feminist principles.{{sfn|Newton|2004}}{{sfn |Messner | 1997 |p = [http://books.google.com/books?id=nG8MGcopgWQC&amp;pg=PA41#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false 41-48] }}
 
Issues commonly associated with the men's rights movement include marriage, cohabitation, parentage, job discrimination, divorce, support agreements, and child support.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Wishard  | first = RW | coauthors = Wishard L | year = 1980 | isbn = 978-0-89666-012-0 | publisher = Cragmont Publications | title = Men's rights: a handbook for the 80's }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
[[File:SIF-Picture.jpg|thumb|250px|Protest in New Delhi for men's rights organised by the [[Save Indian Family Foundation]]]]
The men's rights movement emerged from the [[men's liberation]] movement which appeared in the first half of the 1970s when some men began to study feminist ideas and politics.&lt;ref name="Messner 1"&gt;{{cite journal |last= Messner |first= Michael A. |authorlink= Michael Messner |year= 1998 |title= The Limits of the "Male Sex Role": An Analysis of the Men's Liberation and Men's Rights Movement's Discourse |journal= [[Gender &amp; Society]] |volume= 12 |issue= 3 |pages= 255&amp;ndash;276 |publisher= |doi= 10.1177/0891243298012003002  |pmid= |pmc= |url= |accessdate= }}&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Newton|2004|p = [http://books.google.ca/books?id=bXZkmNTSQUAC&amp;pg=PA190 190-200]}} Early men's liberationists acknowledged men's institutional power and saw feminism as a necessary movement to address women's unequal status. At the same time they stressed the costs of traditional masculinity and the harm of the male [[gender role]]. In the mid- to late 1970s the men's liberation movement split into two separate strands with opposing views: The [[Pro-feminism|pro-feminist men's movement]] and an [[Antifeminism|antifeminist]] men's rights movement.&lt;ref name="Messner 1"/&gt; Men's rights activists have since then rejected feminist principles and focused on perceived disadvantages of men and what they saw as evidence of men's oppression.&lt;ref name="Messner 1"/&gt;{{sfn|Newton|2004|p = [http://books.google.ca/books?id=bXZkmNTSQUAC&amp;pg=PA190 190-200]}}

The men's rights movement is generally understood as a [[Backlash (sociology)|backlash]] or [[countermovement]] to feminism.&lt;ref name="maddison"&gt;{{cite journal |last= Maddison |first= Sarah |authorlink= |year= 1999 |title= Private Men, Public Anger: The Men's Rights Movement in Australia |journal= Journal of Interdisciplinary Gender Studies |volume= 4 |issue= 2 |pages= 39&amp;ndash;52 |publisher= |doi= |pmid= |pmc= |url= http://newcastle.edu.au/Resources/Schools/Humanities%20and%20Social%20Science/JIGS/JIGSV4N2_039.pdf |accessdate= }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1= Doyle |first1= Ciara |authorlink1= |last2= |first2= |authorlink2= |editor1-first= Peter |editor1-last= Herrman |editor1-link= |others= |title= Citizenship Revisited: Threats or Opportunities of Shifting Boundaries |url= |edition= |volume= |year= 2004 |publisher= [[Nova Publishers]] |location= New York |isbn= 978-1-59033-900-8 | pages = [http://books.google.ca/books?id=HdLVGgJQ0mUC&amp;pg=PA61#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false 61–62] |chapter= The Fathers' Rights Movement: Extending Patriarchal Control Beyond the Marital Family |chapterurl= }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1= Flood |first1= Michael |authorlink1= Michael Flood |last2= |first2= |authorlink2= |editor1-first= Michael S. |editor1-last= Kimmel |editor1-link= Michael Kimmel |editor2-last= Hearn |editor2-first= Jeff |editor3-last= Connell |editor3-first= Raewyn |title= Handbook of Studies on Men and Masculinities |url= |edition= |volume= |year= 2005 |publisher= [[SAGE Publications]] |location= Thousand Oaks |isbn= 978-0-7619-2369-5 |page= 459 |pages= |chapter= Men's Collective Struggles for Gender Justice: The Case of Antiviolence Activism |chapterurl= http://books.google.com/books?id=UvAZD45BMDoC&amp;pg=PA459 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="RH Williams"&gt;{{cite journal |last= Williams |first= Rhys H. |authorlink= Rhys H. Williams (sociologist) |year= 1995 |title= Constructing the Public Good: Social Movements and Cultural Resources |journal= Social Problems |volume= 42 |issue= 1 |pages= 124&amp;ndash;144 |publisher= |doi= 10.2307/3097008   |pmid= |pmc= |url= |accessdate= }}&lt;/ref&gt; The men's rights movement consists of diverse points of view which are hostile toward feminist and profeminist ideas.{{sfn|Flood|2007| p = [http://books.google.com/books?id=jh7y6ELc90YC&amp;pg=PA430#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false 430-433]}} Men's rights activists believe that feminism has overshot its objective and harmed men.&lt;ref name="maddison"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Cahill"&gt;{{cite book |last1= Cahill |first1= Charlotte |authorlink1= |last2= |first2= |authorlink2= |editor1-first= Roger |editor1-last= Chapman |editor1-link= |others= |title= Culture Wars: An Encyclopedia of Issues, Viewpoints, and Voices |url= |edition= |volume= |year= 2010 |publisher= [[M.E. Sharpe]] |location= Armonk |isbn= 978-1-84972-713-6 |page= |pages= 354–356 |chapter= Men's movement |chapterurl= http://books.google.com/books?id=vRY27FkGJAUC&amp;pg=PA355 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Messner 1"/&gt; They dispute that men as a group have institutional power and [[Male privilege|privilege]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last = Kimmel |first = Michael S. |year= 1987 |title= Men's Responses to Feminism at the Turn of the Century |journal= Gender &amp; Society |volume= 1 |issue= 3 |pages= 261&amp;ndash;283 |publisher= |doi= 10.1177/089124387001003003 |pmid= |pmc= |url= |accessdate= }}&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Flood|2007| p = [http://books.google.com/books?id=jh7y6ELc90YC&amp;pg=PA430#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false 430-433]}} and instead see men as the real victims,{{sfn|Flood|2007|p = [http://www.xyonline.net/sites/default/files/Flood,%20Men's%20Movements,%20IEMM%202007.pdf 418–422] }}&lt;ref name="Messner 1"/&gt; arguing that men are disadvantaged relative to women.{{sfn|Flood|2007| p = [http://books.google.com/books?id=jh7y6ELc90YC&amp;pg=PA21#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false 21]}} Men's rights activists see men as an oppressed collective and agree that society and state have been "feminized" by the women's movement.&lt;ref name="maddison"/&gt; [[Warren Farrell]] and [[Herb Goldberg]], for instance, believe that all men are disadvantaged, discriminated against and oppressed and argue that power is an illusion for most men since women are the actual bearers of power.&lt;ref name="maddison"/&gt; Men's rights groups generally reject the notion that feminism is interested in men's problems{{sfn|Flood|2007| p = [http://books.google.com/books?id=jh7y6ELc90YC&amp;pg=PA430#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false 430-433]}} and some activists view the women's movement as a conspiracy which aims at concealing discrimination against men.&lt;ref name="Messner 1"/&gt;{{sfn|Flood|2007|p = [http://www.xyonline.net/sites/default/files/Flood,%20Men's%20Movements,%20IEMM%202007.pdf 418–422] }} Men's rights activists co-opted the feminist rhetoric of "rights" and "equality" in their discourse, framing custody issues, for instance, as a matter of basic civil rights.&lt;ref name="RH Williams"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Messner 1"/&gt; The plea for "equal rights for fathers" is frequently accompanied by a rhetoric of children's "needs" which helps deflect criticism that the rhetoric is motivated by self-interest.&lt;ref name="RH Williams"/&gt;

The men's rights movement includes a wide variety of individuals and organizations, both united and divided in various ways on specific issues.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1= Farrell |first1= Warren |authorlink1= |last2= Svoboda |first2= Steven| last3= Sterba |first3= James P. |authorlink2= |editor1-first= |editor1-last= |editor1-link= |others= |title= Does feminism discriminate against men? A Debate |url= |edition= |series= |volume= |year= 2008 |publisher= Oxford University Press |location= New York |isbn= 978-0-19-531282-9 |page= |pages= |chapter= |chapterurl= }}&lt;/ref&gt; Some groups are formally organized or incorporated, while others are casual alliances or the work of a few individuals.&lt;ref name=farrell01&gt;{{cite book |title= Father and Child Reunion:How to Bring the Dads We Need to the Children We Love |first= Warren |last= Farrell |authorlink= |publisher= [[G. P. Putnam's Sons|Putnam]] |location= New York|year= 2001 |isbn= 1585420751}}&lt;/ref&gt;

One of the first major men's rights organizations was the Coalition of American Divorce Reform Elements, founded in 1971, from which the Men's Rights Association spun off in 1973.{{sfn|Newton|2004|p = [http://books.google.ca/books?id=bXZkmNTSQUAC&amp;pg=PA190 190-200]}} ''Free Men Inc.'' was founded in 1977 in [[Columbia, Maryland]], spawning several chapters over the following years, which eventually merged to form the National Coalition of Free Men{{sfn|Ashe|2007|p = [http://books.google.com/books?id=nXDbiPA9IuQC&amp;pg=PA63#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false 63]}} (now known as the [[National Coalition for Men]]). Men's Rights, Inc. was also formed in 1977.&lt;ref name="Chafetz"&gt;{{cite book|last= Chafetz |first= Janet Saltzman |title= Handbook of the sociology of gender | year = 2006 | publisher = [[Springer Science+Business Media]] |location= New York |isbn= 0-387-32460-7 |page= 168 }}&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Ashe|2007|p = [http://books.google.com/books?id=nXDbiPA9IuQC&amp;pg=PA63#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false 63]}} In [[Israel]], the [[Man's Rights in the Family Party]] is headed by Yaakov Schlusser, who argues against equality of the sexes for fear boys will become [[Homosexuality|homosexuals]] and that custody should automatically be given to fathers before being examined by courts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url = http://www.ynetnews.com/articles/0,7340,L-3637253,00.html | title = Men's Rights Party vies for votes | last = Edelson | first = D | date = 2008-12-11 | work = [[Ynet]] | accessdate = 2012-11-03 }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Save Indian Family Foundation]] (SIFF) was founded in 2005 that in 2011 claimed to have approximately 4,000 registered members.&lt;ref name=Kumar&gt;{{cite conference | last = Kumar | first = A | url = http://www.malestudies.org/pdf/kumar.pdf | format = pdf | title = Men’s Movement in India: Story of Save Indian Family Movement | conference = Second Annual Male Studies Conference | location = New York | publisher = Foundation for Male Studies }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Issues==
The men's rights movement is concerned with a wide variety of issues, some of which have spawned their own groups or movements, such as the [[fathers' rights movement]], concerned specifically with [[divorce]] and [[child custody]] issues.{{sfn |Messner | 1997 |p = [http://books.google.com/books?id=nG8MGcopgWQC&amp;pg=PA41#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false 41-48] }}

===Adoption===
Fathers' rights activists seek a gender-neutral approach in which unwed men and women would have equal rights in [[adoption]] issues.&lt;ref name="shanley"&gt;{{cite book |author=Shanley, Mary Lyndon |title=Making babies, making families: what matters most in an age of reproductive technologies, surrogacy, adoption, and same-sex and unwed parents|publisher=Beacon Press |year=2002 |pages=46–47 | url=http://books.google.com/?id=3GnloZRnWOAC&amp;pg=PA44 |isbn=0-8070-4409-1  }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Anti-dowry laws===
Men's rights organizations such as [[Save Indian Family Foundation]] (SIFF) state that men are subject to [[dowry]] harassment when women misuse legislation meant to protect them from [[dowry death]] and [[bride burning]]s.&lt;ref name="Kumar"/&gt;  SIFF is one of the many men's rights organizations in India that focus on the perceived abuse of anti-[[dowry]] laws against men.&lt;ref name=TNN&gt;{{cite news|title=Men demand fair play|url=http://articles.timesofindia.indiatimes.com/2009-11-20/chandigarh/28100670_1_law-ministry-men-demand-awareness-programme|accessdate=20 October 2011|newspaper=Times of India|date=20 November 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;  SIFF has stated that they feel that anti-dowry laws have regularly been used in efforts to settle petty disputes in marriage,&lt;ref name=DT&gt;{{cite news|last=Gilani|first=Iftikhar|title=Shoaib Malik controversy to hit Pakistan-India relations|url=http://www.dailytimes.com.pk/default.asp?page=2010%5C04%5C06%5Cstory_6-4-2010_pg2_6|accessdate=20 October 2011|newspaper=Daily Times|date=6 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; and that their helplines receive calls from many men who say that their wives have used false dowry claims to get them jailed.&lt;ref name=TA&gt;{{cite news|last=Dhillon|first=Amrit|title=Men say wives use India's pro-women laws to torment them|url=http://www.theage.com.au/news/world/men-say-wives-use-indias-prowomen-laws-to-torment-them/2007/12/23/1198344884127.html|accessdate=20 October 2011|newspaper=The Age|date=24 December 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Child custody===
[[File:Fathers 4 Justice in Peterborough.jpg|thumb|right|Two protestors from UK-based father's rights group Fathers 4 Justice protesting in Peterborough in 2010.]]
[[Family law]] is an area of deep concern among men's rights groups. These issues vary from state to state and country to country. In India, father's rights have been a concern since 2000.&lt;ref name=Kumar/&gt; Many men feel that they are discriminated against and that they do not have the same contact rights or equitable [[shared parenting]] rights as their ex-spouse.{{sfn |Messner | 1997 |p = [http://books.google.com/books?id=nG8MGcopgWQC&amp;pg=PA41#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false 41-48] }}&lt;ref name=collier&gt;{{cite news | last = Collier | first = R | coauthors = Sheldon S | date = 2006-11-01 | url = http://society.guardian.co.uk/children/story/0,,1935970,00.html | title = Unfamiliar territory: The issue of a father's rights and responsibilities covers more than just the media-highlighted subject of access to his children | location = London | work = [[The Guardian]] | accessdate = 2011-11-24 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The United Kingdom and United States were cited, with several other unnamed countries, as affected regions where [[child custody]] issues have become complicated by higher divorce rates, less father-child time, while there has been greater expectations for fatherly involvement in their children's lives. Authors of ''Unfamiliar territory'' write, "The current struggles of the fathers' rights movement can be understood as part of this complex and painful renegotiation of intimate relations against a backdrop of changing lifestyles and expectations."&lt;ref name=collier/&gt; Father's rights activists seek to change the legal climate for men through changes in family law.{{sfn |Messner | 1997 |p = [http://books.google.com/books?id=nG8MGcopgWQC&amp;pg=PA41#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false 41-48] }} See [[Fathers' rights movement by country]] for more information about custody concerns. 

Men's rights activists state that the divorce rate in India has sharply risen from less than 5% in 2000, which has over-burdened the Indian court system's abilities to keep pace with the number of child custody cases. They argue that men have been parted from their children, with some only allowed to visit their children at the court once a month for 30 minutes during the to several years that it can take to resolve the custody case. To provide support services to men for shared parenting rights and father's rights, SIFF created several [[non-governmental organization]]s (NGOs).&lt;ref name=Kumar/&gt;

In the United States, fathers accounted for 17.4 percent custodial parents in 2007, a percentage that has statistically not changed since 1994.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.census.gov/prod/2009pubs/p60-237.pdf |title = Custodial Mothers and Fathers and their Child Support | year = 2007 | publisher = [[United States Department of Commerce]] | accessdate = 2011-11-24 | format = pdf }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Divorce===
Men's rights groups in the United States began organizing in opposition of divorce reform and custody issues around the 1960s. The men involved in the early organization claimed that family and divorce law discriminated against them and favored their wives.{{sfn|Ashe|2007|p = [http://books.google.com/books?id=nXDbiPA9IuQC&amp;pg=PA57#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false 57]}}  Rich Doyle wrote of the view of the men's rights movement concerning the court handling of divorces and child custody processes:
&lt;blockquote&gt;Divorce courts are frequently like slaughter-houses, with about as much compassion and talent. They function as collection agencies for lawyer fees, however outrageous, stealing children and extorting money from men in ways blatantly unconstitutional... Men are regarded as mere guests in their own homes, evictable any time at the whims of wives and judges.  Men are driven from home and children against their wills; then when unable to stretch paychecks far enough to support two households are termed "runaway fathers." Contrary to all principles of justice, men are thrown into prison for inability to pay alimony and support, however unreasonable or unfair the "obligation."{{sfn |Messner | 1997 |p = [http://books.google.com/books?id=nG8MGcopgWQC&amp;pg=PA41#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false 41-48] }}&lt;/blockquote&gt;
Laws and practices regarding spousal support, maintenance or [[alimony]] vary considerably by country and culture.  On one end of the spectrum are Nordic countries, like Sweden, that by 1978 assumed that divorced spouses were not responsible for one another.  Support might be provided for a transitionary period for the lower-wage earner or primarily care-givers, but only in about 6-8% of the cases and only for a limited time.  In most western countries alimony is provided on an ever decreasing basis due to shorter marriages and women more likely to be wage-earners.{{sfn|Goode|1993|p = [http://books.google.ca/books?id=FAK64L2tpKAC&amp;pg=PA40#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false 40], [http://books.google.ca/books?id=FAK64L2tpKAC&amp;pg=PA44#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false 44], [http://books.google.ca/books?id=FAK64L2tpKAC&amp;pg=PA64#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false 64], [http://books.google.ca/books?id=FAK64L2tpKAC&amp;pg=PA90#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false 90-92]}} Italy and many countries in Latin America, are on the other end.  Women may be supported during legal separation, which is a state in which they wish to remain because of low chance of remarriage, religious reasons or to retain inheritance rights to their husband's property.  Such women may be wives to husbands of privileged class.  However, the rate of support is declining in Italy, as well.{{sfn|Goode|1997|p = [http://books.google.ca/books?id=FAK64L2tpKAC&amp;pg=PA62#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false 62-64]}}

Although the rate of payments of spousal support is declining, both due to the reduced rates at which alimony is granted and low rates at which alimony is generally paid, there are concerns regarding men's rights when women continue to receive support after they enter into new relationships and women are supported by men who are "financially strapped".{{sfn | Goode | 1997 | p = [http://books.google.ca/books?id=FAK64L2tpKAC&amp;pg=PA164#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false 164-165] }} In the United States, the current alimony laws are challenged for constitutionality, assignment of temporary vs. permanent financial support paid to a spouse, and fair and equitable treatment under family law; There are several men's rights crusades to reform alimony at a state and federal level, including [[Arizona]], [[Florida]], [[Georgia (United States)|Georgia]], [[Massachusetts]], [[New Jersey]], [[North Carolina]], [[Ohio]], [[Pennsylvania]], and [[Tennessee]].&lt;ref name=Levitz&gt;{{cite news | last = Levitz | first = J | date = 2009-10-31 | url = http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052748703399204574505700448957522.html | title = The New Art of Alimony | work = [[The Wall Street Journal]] | accessdate = 2011-11-25 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Now that women make up a large percentage of the workforce, existing laws regarding alimony in the United States have come into question.&lt;ref name=Levitz/&gt; A legal precedent for gender-blind spousal support, granting men's rights to alimony, in the United States was made in ''[[Orr v. Orr]]'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite court |litigants= [[Orr v. Orr]] |vol= 440 |reporter= US 268 |opinion= |pinpoint= |court= [[Supreme Court of the United States]] |date= 1979|url= http://supreme.justia.com/us/440/268/ |accessdate= 2011-11-24 |quote=}}&lt;/ref&gt; where the Supreme Court invalidated Alabama's statutes by which husbands, but not wives, were required to pay alimony upon divorce. This statute was considered a violation of the Equal Protection Clause of the 14th Amendment. The percentage of alimony recipients in the US who were male rose from 2.4% in (1996–2001) to 3.6% in (2002–2006) and is expected to increase as more marriages feature a female primary earner.&lt;ref name=WSJMenAlimony&gt;{{cite news |url=http://online.wsj.com/article/SB120700651883978623.html |title=Men Receiving Alimony Want A Little Respect | accessdate=2009-02-03 | work=The Wall Street Journal | first=Anita | last=Raghavan | date=2008-04-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Domestic violence===
Men's rights activists assert that domestic violence by women is ignored and under-reported,&lt;ref name="Miller2005"/&gt;&lt;ref name=observer/&gt; because men are reluctant to describe themselves as victims.&lt;ref name=observer&gt;{{cite news |url= http://www.guardian.co.uk/society/2003/dec/21/socialcare.uknews |title=Battered men get their own refuge |first= Jamie |last= Doward |work=[[The Observer]] |date=21 December 2003|publisher=[[Guardian Media Group|GMG]] |location=[[London, England|London]] |issn=0261-3077 |oclc=60623878 |accessdate=October 22, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; They state that women are as aggressive or more aggressive than men in relationships,&lt;ref name="RenzettiEdleson2008"/&gt; that domestic violence is sex-symmetrical,&lt;ref name="Dragiewicz2011 b"&gt;{{cite book|author=Molly Dragiewicz|title=Equality with a Vengeance: Men's Rights Groups, Battered Women, and Antifeminist Backlash|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=OHr7yWfEjQYC&amp;pg=PA84|accessdate=October 22, 2011|date=12 April 2011|publisher= [[University Press of New England]] |isbn=978-1-55553-739-5|pages=84–5}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="LosekeGelles2005"&gt;{{cite book|author1=Donileen R. Loseke|author2=Richard J. Gelles|author3=Mary M. Cavanaugh|title=Current controversies on family violence|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=YBVGswoPYqMC&amp;pg=PA92|accessdate=October 22, 2011|year=2005|publisher= [[SAGE Publications]] |isbn=978-0-7619-2106-6|page=92}}&lt;/ref&gt; and that judicial systems too easily accept false allegations of domestic violence by women against their male partners.&lt;ref name="Boyd2007"&gt;{{cite book|author=Susan B. Boyd|title=Reaction and resistance: feminism, law, and social change|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=ASc568aunFoC&amp;pg=PA85|accessdate=October 22, 2011|date=1 October 2007|publisher= [[University of British Columbia Press]] |isbn=978-0-7748-1411-9|page=85}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Men's rights writer [[Christina Hoff Sommers]] has commented that "false claims about male domestic violence are ubiquitous and immune to refutation."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Domestic violence myths help no one |first=Christina Hoff|last=Sommers |url=http://www.usatoday.com/news/opinion/forum/2011-02-03-sommers04_st_N.htm |newspaper=USA Today |date= February 4, 2011 |accessdate=17 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Men's rights advocates have been critics of legal, policy and practical protections for abused women,&lt;ref name="Dragiewicz2011c"&gt;{{cite book|author=Molly Dragiewicz|title=Equality with a Vengeance: Men's Rights Groups, Battered Women, and Antifeminist Backlash|http://books.google.ca/books?id=OHr7yWfEjQYC&amp;pg=PA3|accessdate=October 22, 2011|date=12 April 2011|publisher= [[University Press of New England]] |isbn=978-1-55553-739-5|pages=3=4, 29}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="LosekeGelles2005"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Kimmel2010"&gt;{{cite book|author=Michael Kimmel|title=Misframing Men: The Politics of Contemporary Masculinities|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=wC9_3wBJX6QC&amp;pg=PA1|accessdate=3 November 2012|date=15 June 2010|publisher=Rutgers University Press|isbn=978-0-8135-4762-6|pages=1–}}&lt;/ref&gt; campaigning for domestic violence shelters for battered men&lt;ref name="Miller2005"&gt;{{cite book|author=Susan L. Miller|title=Victims as offenders: the paradox of women's violence in relationships|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=7CsgywvFH-EC&amp;pg=PA16|accessdate=October 22, 2011|date=October 2005|publisher= [[Rutgers University Press]] |isbn=978-0-8135-3671-2|page=16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=observer/&gt; and for the legal system to be educated about women's violence against men.&lt;ref name="Miller2005"/&gt;

Academics criticize the research cited by activists, and while acknowledging that men are victims of domestic violence, dispute their claims that such violence is gender symmetrical,&lt;ref name="Flood2004"&gt;{{cite book|author=Flood, Michael|editor=Stacey Elin Rossi|title=The Battle and Backlash Rage on|chapter= Backlash: Angry men’s movements|url=http://www.xyonline.net/sites/default/files/Flood,%20Backlash%20-%20Angry%20men_0.pdf|accessdate=29 December 2011|date=7 July 2004|publisher=Xlibris Corporation|isbn=978-1-4134-5934-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="RenzettiEdleson2008"&gt;{{cite book|author1=Susan L. Miller|author2=Terry G. Lilley|editor=Claire M. Renzetti and Jeffrey L. Edleson|title=Encyclopedia of interpersonal violence|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=BOKAMXEA_jQC&amp;pg=PT257|year=2008|publisher= [[SAGE Publications]] | isbn = 978-1-4129-1800-8| pages = 257–58 | chapter = Female perpetrators of intimate partner violence}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Dobash&gt;{{cite journal | last = Dobash | first = Russell P.| coauthors = R. Emerson Dobash, Margo Wilson, Martin Daly | title=The Myth of Sexual Symmetry in Marital Violence | journal = Social Problems | date = February 1992 | volume= 39 | issue=1 | doi = 10.1177/107780102237407 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Messner 1"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Kimmel2002"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Kimmel|first1=M. S.|title="Gender Symmetry" in Domestic Violence: A Substantive and Methodological Research Review|journal=Violence Against Women|volume=8|issue=11|year=2002|pages=1332–1363|issn=1077-8012|doi=10.1177/107780102237407}}&lt;/ref&gt; arguing that the focus on women's violence stems from a political agenda to minimize the issue of men's violence against women&lt;ref name="Flood2004"/&gt; and to undermine services to abused women.&lt;ref name="RenzettiEdleson2008"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Kimmel2002"/&gt;  Donileen Loseke, Mary Cavanaugh and Richard Gelles cite as an example the challenge to the [[Minnesota]] Battered Woman's Act by the Men's Defense Association claiming that it was discriminatory because it protected women but not men.  The lawsuit did not intend to shift resources to equally protecting men in situations of violence, but rather sought to "roll back protections for battered women".&lt;ref name="LosekeGelles2005"/&gt;

===Education===
Men's rights activists describe the education of boys as being in crisis, with boys having reduced educational achievement and motivation as compared to girls.&lt;ref name=forbes/&gt;  
Advocates blame the influence of feminism on education for discrimination against and systematic oppression of boys in the education system.&lt;ref name="MartinoKehler2009"&gt;{{cite book|author1=Mills, Martin|author2=Francis, Becky|author3=Skelton, Christine|editor=Wayne Martino, Michael Kehler, and Marcus B. Weaver-Hightower|title=The problem with boys' education: beyond the backlash|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=ouWMouuNuWAC&amp;pg=PA38|date=8 June 2009|publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis|isbn=978-1-56023-683-2|pages=38–55|chapter=Gender policies in Australia and the United Kingdom}}&lt;/ref&gt;  They critique what they describe as the "feminization" of education, stating that the predominance of female teachers, a focus on girls' needs as well as a curricula and assessment methods that favour girls have proved repressive and restrictive to men and boys.&lt;ref name=forbes/&gt;&lt;ref name="FrancisSkelton2005"&gt;{{cite book|author1=Becky Francis|author2=Christine Skelton|title=Reassessing gender and achievement: questioning contemporary key debates|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=XkkfekXzkZMC&amp;pg=PA18|accessdate=26 December 2011|date=27 September 2005|publisher=Psychology Press|isbn=978-0-415-33324-5|pages=18–19, 141 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  

Men's rights groups call for increased recognition of masculinity, greater numbers of male role models, more competitive sports, and the increased responsibilities for boys in the school setting. They have also advocated clearer school routines, more traditional school structures, including single-sex classes, and stricter discipline.&lt;ref name="FrancisSkelton2005"/&gt; 

Critics suggest that men's rights groups view boys as a homogeneous group sharing common experiences of schooling and that they do not take sufficient account in their analysis of how responses to educational approaches may differ by age, culture, ethnicity, sexuality, religion, and class.&lt;ref name="FrancisSkelton2005"/&gt;

In Australia, men's rights discourse has influenced government policy documents; less impact has been noted in the United Kingdom, where feminists have historically had less influence on educational policy.&lt;ref name="MartinoKehler2009"/&gt;

===Female privilege===
{{See also|Male privilege#Against the notion of male privilege}}
The men's rights movement asserts that males no longer hold [[male privilege]] to the exclusion of females, with two variations: those who argue that [[sexism]] harms men and women equally as both genders have different privileges and those who believe that female privilege has become the norm to the detriment of men.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Clatterbaugh | first = Kenneth | title = Contemporary Perspectives on Masculinity | year = 1997 | publisher = WestviewPress | isbn=0-8133-2700-8 | pages = 11 | url = http://digilib.bc.edu/reserves/en125/grif/en125105.pdf | format = pdf }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Governmental structures===
Men's rights groups have called for male-focused governmental structures to address issues specific to men and boys including education, health, work and marriage.&lt;ref name=toi&gt;{{cite news |url= http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/city/bangalore/What-about-tax-and-fathers-custody-rights/articleshow/5244920.cms |title=What about tax, and father's custody rights? |work=The Times of India|date=May 17, 2011|accessdate=22 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Northbourne"/&gt;&lt;ref name=wt&gt;{{cite news |url= http://www.washingtontimes.com/news/2011/may/17/guys-got-it-made-think-again-say-advocates/ |title=Guys got it made? Think again, say advocates |first= Wetzstein|last= Cheryl |work=Washington Times |date= |accessdate=22 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Men's rights groups in India have called for the creation of a Men's Welfare Ministry and a National Commission for Men, as well as the abolition of the National Commission for Women.&lt;ref name=toi/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url= http://uk.reuters.com/article/2009/11/20/us-india-husbands-idUKTRE5AJ0TZ20091120 |title=Indian husbands want protection from nagging wives &amp;#124; |work= Reuters |date= November 20, 2009|accessdate=22 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://articles.timesofindia.indiatimes.com/2009-08-09/man-woman/28177085_1_indian-law-law-minister-siff |title=Boys fight for freedom!|author=Manigandan KR |work=Times Of India|date=Aug 9, 2009 |accessdate=22 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In the United Kingdom, the creation of a Minister for Men analogous to the existing [[Minister for Women]], have been proposed by [[David Amess]], MP and [[Lord Northbourne]], but were rejected by the government of [[Tony Blair]].&lt;ref name="Northbourne"&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/programmes/bbc_parliament/3522631.stm | work=BBC News | title=FHM: For Him Minister? | date=2004-03-03 | accessdate=22 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/uknews/1343276/Yesterday-in-Parliament.html | work=The Daily Telegraph | location=London | title=Yesterday in Parliament | first=Michael | last=Kallenbach | date=2000-06-16 | accessdate=May 5, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_answers/2004/mar/08/minister-for-men#S6CV0418P2_20040308_CWA_745 ''Minister for Men.''] Hansard, UK Parliament. Retrieved November 24, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; In the United States, [[Warren Farrell]] heads a commission focused on the creation of a "White House Council on Boys and Men" as a counterpart to the "White House Council on Women and Girls" which was formed in March 2009.&lt;ref name=forbes&gt;{{cite news |url= http://www.forbes.com/sites/rahimkanani/2011/09/05/the-need-to-create-a-white-house-council-on-boys-to-men/ |title=The Need to Create a White House Council on Boys to Men |author=Rahim Kanani|work=Forbes|date=May 9, 2011 |accessdate=22 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=wt/&gt;

===Health===
Men's rights activists view the health issues faced by men and their shorter life spans as compared to women as evidence of discrimination and oppression.{{sfn |Messner | 1997 |p = [http://books.google.com/books?id=nG8MGcopgWQC&amp;pg=PA41#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false 41-48] }}&lt;ref name="HaywoodGhaill2003"/&gt;  They state that feminism has led to women's health issues being privileged at the expense of men's.&lt;ref name="Boyd2007"&gt;{{cite book|author=Menzies, Robert|editor=Susan B. Boyd|title=Reaction and resistance: feminism, law, and social change|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=ASc568aunFoC&amp;pg=PA86|accessdate=30 December 2011|date=30 November 2007|publisher=UBC Press|isbn=978-0-7748-1411-9|pages=65–97|chapter=Virtual Backlash: Representations of men's "rights" and feminist "wrongs" in cyberspace}}&lt;/ref&gt; They point to higher suicide rates in men compared to women,&lt;ref name="HaywoodGhaill2003"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Boyd2007"/&gt; and complain about the funding of men's health issues as compared to women's, including noting that prostate cancer research receives less funding than breast-cancer research.&lt;ref name="HaywoodGhaill2003"&gt;{{cite book|author1=Christian Haywood|author2=Máirtín Mac an Ghaill|title=Men and masculinities: theory, research, and social practice|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=d-vtAAAAMAAJ|accessdate=30 December 2011|date=1 January 2003|publisher= [[McGraw-Hill|Open University Press]] |pages=134–5|isbn=978-0-335-20892-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url= http://articles.chicagotribune.com/1998-06-21/features/9806210422_1_men-and-masculinity-dads-million-man-march |title=Feminism Has Created Progress, But Man, Oh, Man, Look What Else  |first=Kate |last=Zernike  |work= [[Chicago Tribune]] |date=1998-06-21 |accessdate=2011-12-30 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  [[David Benatar]] has suggested more money should be put into health research on males in order to reduce the disparity between men's and women's [[life expectancy]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Benatar | first = D | authorlink = David Benatar | title = The Second Sexism: Discrimination Against Men and Boys | isbn = 1118192303 | publisher = [[John Wiley &amp; Sons]] | pages = [http://books.google.ca/books?id=iGZ0dhvvVN8C&amp;pg=PA190#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false 190] | year = 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Some doctors and academics have argued [[circumcision]] is a violation of men's right to health and bodily integrity,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Denniston|first=George C.|title=Male and female circumcision medical, legal, and ethical considerations in pediatric practice|year=1999|publisher=Kluwer Academic/Plenum Publishers|location=New York|isbn=0-306-46131-5|page=348}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=El-Salam|first=Seham Abd|title=The Importance of Genital Mutilations to Gender Power Politics|journal=Al-Raida|year=2002/2003|volume=20|issue=99|page=42|publisher=Institute for Women’s Studies in the Arab World|quote=Women’s defense of men’s right to bodily integrity and their work against MGM will not have a negative impact on their struggle against FGM.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Somerville | first = M | chapter = Altering baby boys' bodies: the ethics of infant male circumcision | title = The Ethical Canary: Science, Society and the Human Spirit | location = Toronto | publisher = [[Viking Press]] | isbn = 0-670-89302-1 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Green|first=James|title=The Male Herbal: The Definitive Health Care Book for Men &amp; Boys|year=2007|publisher=Crossing Press|location=Berkeley, Calif.|isbn=1-58091-175-7|edition=2nd|quote=Circumcision: A Common Form of Disregard for Men's Rights… Glick emphasizes that infants are persons with full civil rights, and therefore no one has the right to impose circumcision on them—not even parents.}}&lt;/ref&gt; while others have disagreed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Benatar M, Benatar D |title=Between prophylaxis and child abuse: the ethics of neonatal male circumcision |journal=Am J Bioeth |volume=3 |issue=2 |pages=35–48 |year=2003 |pmid=12859815 |doi=10.1162/152651603766436216 |url=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Clark PA, Eisenman J, Szapor S |title=Mandatory neonatal male circumcision in Sub-Saharan Africa: medical and ethical analysis |journal=Med. Sci. Monit. |volume=13 |issue=12 |pages=RA205–13 |year=2007 |month=December |pmid=18049444 |doi= |url=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Patrick K |title=Is infant male circumcision an abuse of the rights of the child? No |journal=BMJ |volume=335 |issue=7631 |pages=1181 |year=2007 |month=December |pmid=18063641 |pmc=2128676 |doi=10.1136/bmj.39406.523762.AD |url=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Brusa M, Barilan YM |title=Cultural circumcision in EU public hospitals--an ethical discussion |journal=Bioethics |volume=23 |issue=8 |pages=470–82 |year=2009 |month=October |pmid=19076127 |doi=10.1111/j.1467-8519.2008.00683.x |url=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Academics critique the claims,&lt;ref name="HaywoodGhaill2003"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Flood2004"/&gt;{{sfn|Messner|1997|p = [http://books.google.ca/books?id=nG8MGcopgWQC&amp;pg=PA6#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false 6-7]}} stating, as [[Michael Messner]] puts it, that the poorer health outcomes are the heavy costs paid by men "for conformity with the narrow definitions of masculinity that promise to bring them status and privilege"{{sfn|Messner|1997|p = [http://books.google.ca/books?id=nG8MGcopgWQC&amp;pg=PA6#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false 6-7]}} and that these costs fall disproportionately on men who are marginalized socially and economically.{{sfn|Messner|1997|p = [http://books.google.ca/books?id=nG8MGcopgWQC&amp;pg=PA6#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false 6-7]}}  In this view, and according to [[Michael Flood]], men's health would best be improved by "tackling destructive notions of manhood, an economic system which values profit and productivity over workers’ health, and the ignorance of service providers" instead of blaming a feminist health movement.&lt;ref name="Flood2004"/&gt;

===Military conscription===
Men's rights activists have argued that military [[conscription]] of men is an example of oppression of men.{{sfn |Messner | 1997 |p = [http://books.google.com/books?id=nG8MGcopgWQC&amp;pg=PA41#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false 41-48] }}&lt;ref name="BoydLongwood1996"&gt;{{cite book|author1=Stephen Blake Boyd|author2=W. Merle Longwood|author3=Mark William Muesse|title=Redeeming men: religion and masculinities|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=VSrhNzWb6sIC&amp;pg=PR17|date=November 6, 1996|publisher=Westminster John Knox Press|isbn=978-0-664-25544-2|page=17}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

In 1971 in the United States, draft resisters initiated a class-action suit alleging that male only conscription violated men's rights to equal protection under the US constitution.&lt;ref name=tb/&gt;&lt;ref name="Binkin1993"/&gt; When the case, ''[[Rostker v. Goldberg]]'', reached the Supreme Court in 1981, they  were supported by a men's rights group and multiple women's groups, including the [[National Organization for Women]].&lt;ref name=tb&gt;{{cite news |url= http://news.google.com/newspapers?id=UDFPAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=nwIEAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=6777,7767318&amp;dq=men%27s-rights+conscription&amp;hl=en |title=Supreme Court to begin hearing male-only military draft case |first= Richard  |last= Carelli|work=Toledo Blade|date= March 23, 1981|accessdate=12 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the Supreme Court upheld the Military Selective Service Act, stating that "the argument for registering women was based on considerations of equity, but Congress was entitled, in the exercise of its constitutional powers, to focus on the question of military need, rather than equity.&lt;ref name="Binkin1993"&gt;{{cite book|author=Martin Binkin|title=Who will fight the next war?: the changing face of the American military|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=AOHD6sbzNysC&amp;pg=PA53|accessdate=12 November 2011|year=1993|publisher=Brookings Institution Press|isbn=978-0-8157-0955-8|page=53}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.law.cornell.edu/supct/html/historics/USSC_CR_0453_0057_ZS.html Cornell University Law School: Rostker v. Goldberg]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Parental abduction===
Men's rights activists state that children of men of Indian descent have been [[Child abduction|abducted]] from their homes in Canada, the United States and Europe, and moved to India where the national courts do not recognize foreign child custody orders. The country is not subject to the Hague Convention and men accused of dowry harassment may be arrested at Indian airports.&lt;ref name="Kumar"/&gt;

===Parental leave===
There is wide variance in [[parental leave]] provisions across 24 western countries, which are primarily European countries, Australia, Canada and the United States.  The most liberal allows the couple to choose how to split the family leave time between mother and father.  In the countries where parental leave is available and defined, it is generally for 2 to 12 days. Where maternal leave is available and defined, all but the United States and Australia, the period of time is generally 14–20 weeks, but four countries have extended leave periods.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | publisher = [[Department for Business, Innovation and Skills]] | year = 2007 | title = Internal Review of Leave Policies and Related Research | work = Employment Relations Research Series No. 80 | pages = 12-13 |url=http://www.berr.gov.uk/files/file40677.pdf | format = pdf }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Paternity fraud===
{{Main|Misattributed paternity|paternity fraud}}
Men's and fathers' rights groups have stated that there are high levels of misattributed paternity or "paternity fraud", where men are parenting and/or supporting financially children who are not biologically their own.&lt;ref name=cannold/&gt; They hold biological views of fatherhood, emphasizing the imperative of the genetic foundation of paternity rather than social aspects of fatherhood.&lt;ref name="RothsteinMurray2005"&gt;{{cite book|author=Majumber, Mary Anderlik |editor1=Mark A. Rothstein|editor2=Thomas H. Murray|editor3=Gregory E. Kaebnick|chapter=Disestablishment Suits|title=Genetic Ties and the Family: The Impact of Paternity Testing on Parents and Children|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=Q_FN-L-VZGYC&amp;pg=PA173date=12 September 2005|publisher=JHU Press|isbn=978-0-8018-8193-0|pages=172–79}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=cannold/&gt; They state that men should not have to support children fathered by another man,&lt;ref name=salah/&gt; and that men are harmed because a relationship is created between a man and non-biological children while denying the children and their biological father of that experience and knowledge of their genetic history. In addition, non-biological fathers are denied the resources to have their own biological children in another relationship.&lt;ref name=cannold/&gt;  Men's rights activists support the use of [[paternity testing]] to reassure presumed fathers about the child's paternity;&lt;ref name=salah/&gt; men's and fathers' rights groups have called for compulsory paternity testing of all children.&lt;ref name=shepherd&gt;{{cite news |url= http://www.news.com.au/technology/men-flock-online-for-peace-of-mind-paternity-tests/story-e6frfro0-1226385528162 |title=Men flock online for 'peace of mind' paternity tests |first= Tory |last= Shepherd|work=news.com.au |date= 6 June 2012|accessdate=27 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=cannold/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Who's your daddy?|newspaper=Philadelphia Daily News|date=5 October 2005|quote="I think the best solution is DNA testing at birth," said Glenn Sacks, a syndicated radio talk-show host who focuses on men's issues}}&lt;/ref&gt;  They have campaigned vigorously in support of men who have been shown by genetic testing not to be the biological father, but who are nevertheless required to be financially responsible for them.&lt;ref name="RothsteinMurray2005"/&gt;  Prompted by these concerns, legislators in certain jurisdictions have supported this biological view and have passed laws providing relief from child support payments when a man is proved not to be the father.&lt;ref name="RothsteinMurray2005"/&gt;&lt;ref name=cannold&gt;{{cite journal|last=Cannold|first=Leslie|journal=Women's Studies International Forum|title= Who's the father? Rethinking the moral 'crime' of 'paternity fraud'|date=July–August 2008|volume=31|issue=4|pages=249-256|doi=10.1016/j.wsif.2008.05.011|url=http://cannold.com/static/files/assets/aa358dd8/rethinking-the-moral-crime-of-paternity-fraud.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Australian men's rights groups have opposed the recommendations of a report by the [[Australian Law Reform Commission]] and the [[National Health and Medical Research Council]] that would require the consent of both parents for paternity testing of young children,&lt;ref name=salah&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.abc.net.au/science/articles/2005/12/14/1530514.htm |title=Teens may be forced to have paternity test|first= Anna|last=Salah|work=abc.net.au |date= 14 December 2005 |accessdate=27 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; and laws that would make it illegal to a sample for DNA testing without the individual's consent.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url= http://www.theaustralian.com.au/business/legal-affairs/fathers-disrupt-debate-on-dna/story-e6frg97x-1111118010434 |title=Fathers 'disrupt debate on DNA'|work= The Australian |first=Leigh |last=Dayton |date=12 November 2008|accessdate=27 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Sociologist Michael Gilding asserts that men's rights activists have exaggerated the rate and extent of misattributed paternity, which he estimates at about 1-3%.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url= http://www.smh.com.au/news/national/the-myth-behind-paternity-fraud/2005/06/29/1119724699885.html |title=The myth behind paternity fraud|first= Adele |last=Horrin |work=[[Sydney Morning Herald]] |date= 30 June 2005|accessdate=27 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=shepherd/&gt; He opposed as unnecessary calls for mandatory paternity testing of all children.&lt;ref name=shepherd/&gt;

===Rape===
Men's rights activists are concerned with false accusations of rape and sexual assault&lt;ref name=telher&gt;{{cite news |url= http://articles.chicagotribune.com/1992-10-30/features/9204080516_1_consensual-sex-contract-accusations-mel-feit |title= Sex Contract Shares Intimate Knowledge |first=Barbara |last=Brotman |work=The Chicago Tribune |date= October 30, 1992 |accessdate=1 November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; and desire to protect men from the negative consequences of false accusations.&lt;ref name="Kimmel"&gt;{{citation |title=Men and Masculinities: A Social, Cultural and Historical Encyclopedia |author=Michael Kimmel |year=1992 |contribution=Anti-Feminism |pages=35–37 |publisher=ABC-CLIO |isbn=978-1-57607-774-0 |editor= Michael S. Kimmel and Amy Aronson |publication-date=2003 |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=jWj5OBvTh1IC&amp;pg=PA37 |accessdate=23 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; They assert that the naming of the accused while providing the accuser with anonymity encourages abuse.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,158869,00.html |title=Privacy Rights Eroding Down Slippery Slope &amp;#124|first= McElroy |last=Wendy |work=foxnews.com |year=2011 [last update] |accessdate=23 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Farrell|1994|p = 161}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url= http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/scotland/3374319.stm |title=Rape case protection bid rejected |work=[[BBC News]] |date=7 January 2004, |publisher=[[British Broadcasting Corporation|BBC]]|accessdate=3 November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Men's rights activists in the United Kingdom, the United States and India have opposed [[marital rape]] legislation and legal decisions.&lt;ref name="LosekeGelles2005"&gt;{{cite book|author1=Donileen R. Loseke|author2=Richard J. Gelles|author3=Mary M. Cavanaugh|title=Current controversies on family violence|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=YBVGswoPYqMC&amp;pg=PA92|accessdate=6 February 2012|year=2005|publisher=SAGE|isbn=978-0-7619-2106-6|page=92}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Dunphy2000"&gt;{{cite book|author=Richard Dunphy|title=Sexual Politics: An Introduction|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=NVPQkt0bVpAC&amp;pg=PA142|accessdate=11 October 2012|year=2000|publisher=Edinburgh University Press|isbn=978-0-7486-1247-5|page=142}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=dhillon/&gt; The reasons for opposition include concerns about false allegations related to divorce proceedings,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://web.archive.org/web/20080706190837/http://www.strike-the-root.com/columns/Miller/miller1.html |title=Marital Rape - What a Can of Worms! |first= Stuart A|last=Millar |work=Strike at the Root |year=2002|accessdate=11 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Farrell|1994|p = 338|ps=:"Spousal rape legislation is blackmail waiting to happen. If a man feels he needs to file for divorce, his wife can say 'If you do, I'll accuse you of spousal rape.' Spousal rape legislation is worse than government-as-substitute-husband. It's government in the bedroom"}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Spousal Rape Laws|accessdate=2012/11/03.|newspaper=[[CNN]]|date=July 31, 1992|quote=Tom Williamson, President [[National Coalition of Free Men]]: "I don't think that there should be anything called marital rape laws.  I don't deny that the elements involved with rape can occur in a marriage.  They certainly do.  But the problem with the concept of having something called marital rape is that it makes every man vulnerable in a bad situation to blackmail.  It makes them vulnerable to false accusations for a variety of motivations that we know exists"}}&lt;/ref&gt; and in India anxiety about relationships&lt;ref name="Pandey2010"&gt;{{cite news|last=Pandey|first=Vineeta|title=Husbands can't get away with marital rape: Government|url=http://www.dnaindia.com/india/report_husbands-can-t-get-away-with-marital-rape-government_1356512|newspaper=DNA|accessdate=30 September 2012|quote="no relationship will work if these rules are enforced."|date=8 March 2010|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20100331132152/http://www.dnaindia.com/india/report_husbands-can-t-get-away-with-marital-rape-government_1356512|archivedate=31 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the future of marriage as such laws give women "grossly disproportional rights".&lt;ref name=dhillon&gt;{{cite news |title=Women confident law will end culture of abuse |newspaper=[[South China Morning Post]] |url=http://www.scmp.com/node/569778|first= Amrit |last=Dhillon  |date=01 November, 2006 |accessdate=11 October 2012|quote="The All India Harassed Husbands Association protested last week at the law. 'It gives such grossly disproportionate rights to women that men won't want to get married,' said member Akhil Gupta"}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Reproductive rights===
In the US in 2006, the court case ''[[Dubay v. Wells]]'' concerned whether men should have an opportunity to decline all paternity rights and responsibilities in the event of an unplanned pregnancy. Supporters said that this would allow the woman time to make an informed decision and give men the same reproductive rights as women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last = Traister | first = R | date = 2006-03-13 | url = http://www.salon.com/mwt/feature/2006/03/13/roe_for_men/ | title = Roe for men? | publisher = [[Salon (website)|Salon]] | accessdate = 2007-12-17 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In its dismissal of the case, the U.S. Court of Appeals (Sixth Circuit) stated that "Dubay’s claim that a man’s right to disclaim fatherhood would be analogous to a woman’s right to abortion rests upon a false analogy. In the case of a father seeking to opt out of fatherhood and thereby avoid child support obligations, the child is already in existence and the state therefore has an important interest in providing for his or her support."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ca6.uscourts.gov/opinions.pdf/07a0442p-06.pdf |format=PDF|title=U.S. Court of Appeals for the Sixth Circuit, case No. 06-11016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Social security and insurance===
Men's rights groups argue that women are given superior social security and tax benefits than men.{{sfn|Flood|2007| p = [http://books.google.com/books?id=jh7y6ELc90YC&amp;pg=PA430#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false 430-433]}}&lt;ref name="Honderich2005"&gt;{{cite book|author=Ferrell Christensen|editor=Ted Honderich|title=The Oxford companion to philosophy|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=F9oAomj2IIwC&amp;pg=PA563|accessdate=10 December 2011|date=26 May 2005|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=978-0-19-926479-7|pages=562–63|chapter=Masculism}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Warren Farrell]] states that men in the United States pay more into social security, but in total women receive more in benefits, and that discrimination against men in insurance and pensions have gone unrecognized.{{sfn|Farrell|1994|p=350}}

== Organizations ==
* [[National Coalition for Men]]
* [[Save Indian Family Foundation]]
* [[The Good Men Project]]

==Prominent authors and activists==
* [[Roy Baumeister]]
* [[Warren Farrell]]&lt;ref name=npost&gt;{{cite news|title=An Embattled Champion Of Male Values|url=http://www.nationalpost.com/story.html?id=afa74692-d935-4240-8a37-5c325ddc62be&amp;k=17056|accessdate=29 October 2012|newspaper=National Post}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
* [[Paul Nathanson]]
* [[Kathleen Parker]]
* [[Cathy Young]]
* [[Glenn Sacks]]&lt;ref name=salonsacks&gt;{{cite news|last=Berman|first=Judy|title="Men’s rights” groups go mainstream|url=http://www.salon.com/2009/11/05/mens_rights/|accessdate=29 October 2012|newspaper=Salon|date=5 November 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
* [[Christina Hoff Sommers]]

==See also==
{{Portal|Men's rights}}
*[[Feminism]]
*[[Men's studies]]
*[[Parental leave]]
*[[Paternal rights and abortion]]
*[[Sexism]]

==Footnotes==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==References==
* {{cite book | last = Ashe | first = F | year = 2007 | url = http://books.google.com/books?id=nXDbiPA9IuQC | title = The New Politics of Masculinity: Men, Power and Resistance | publisher = [[Routledge]] | location= London |isbn= 978-0-415-30275-3 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{cite book |last = Farrell | first = W | title = The Myth of Male Power | year = 1994 | publisher = [[Berkley Books]] | isbn = 978-0-425-14381-0 }}
* {{cite book |last = Flood | first = M | authorlink = Michael Flood |title= International Encyclopedia of Men and Masculinities | year = 2007 |publisher= [[Taylor &amp; Francis|Psychology Press]]  |location= London |isbn= 978-0-415-33343-6 | url=http://books.google.ca/books?id=jh7y6ELc90YC&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false | coauthors = Gardiner JK; Pease B; Pringle K}}
* {{cite book | last = Goode | first = WJ | year = 1993 | title = World Changes in Divorce Patterns | publisher = [[Yale University Press]] | url = http://books.google.com/books?id=FAK64L2tpKAC | isbn = 0-300-05537-4 }}
* {{cite book | last = Messner | first = MA | year = 1997 | title = Politics of Masculinities: Men in Movements | location = Lanham | publisher = [[Rowman &amp; Littlefield]] | url = http://books.google.ca/books?id=nG8MGcopgWQC | isbn = 0-8039-5577-4 }}
* {{cite book | last = Newton | first = J | title = From Panthers to Promise Keepers: rethinking the men's movement | year = 2004 | publisher = [[Rowman &amp; Littlefield]] | location = Lanham, MD | isbn = 9780847691302 | url = http://books.google.ca/books?id=bXZkmNTSQUAC&amp;printsec=frontcover }}

==Further reading==
* {{cite book | title = The Second Sexism: Discrimination Against Men and Boys | publisher = [[John Wiley &amp; Sons]] | isbn= 0470674512 | year = 2012 | last = Benatar | first = D | authorlink = David Benatar }}
* {{cite book | title = Is There Anything Good About Men?: How Cultures Flourish by Exploiting Men | publisher = [[Oxford University Press]] | year = 2010 | last = Baumeister | first = RF | authorlink = Roy Baumeister | isbn = 019537410X }}
* {{cite book | title = Save the Males: Why Men Matter Why Women Should Care | year = 2008 | isbn = 1400065798 | publisher = [[Random House#Digital Publishing Group|Random House Digital]] | isbn = 1400065798 | last = Parker | first = K | authorlink = Kathleen Parker}}
* {{cite book | title = Legalizing Misandry: From Public Shame to Systemic Discrimination Against Men | year = 2006 | isbn = 0773577890 | publisher = [[McGill-Queen's University Press]] | last = Nathanson | first = P | authorlink = Paul Nathanson | coauthors = Young KK }}
* {{cite book | title = Spreading Misandry: The Teaching of Contempt for Men in Popular Culture | year = 2001 |isbn =0773522727  | publisher = [[McGill-Queen's University Press]] | last = Nathanson | first = P | authorlink = Paul Nathanson | coauthors = Young KK }}
* {{cite book | title = The War Against Boys: How Misguided Feminism Is Harming Our Young Men | year = 2001 | isbn = 0684849577 | publisher = [[Simon &amp; Schuster]] | last = Summers | first = CH | authorlink = Christina Hoff Sommers }}

==External links==
* {{dmoz|Society/People/Men/Issues/Organizations/|Men's issues organizations}}

{{Discrimination}}
{{Masculism}}
{{Domestic violence}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Men's Rights}}
[[Category:Anthropology]]
[[Category:Gender]]
[[Category:Men's rights| ]]
[[Category:Human rights]]

[[ja:男性差別]]
[[pl:Maskulinizm]]
[[sv:Mansforskning]]
[[tr:Erkek hakları]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>