<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20091115072027|325940236" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="43797" pageid="43797" ns="0" title="Violence against LGBTQ people"><revisions><rev timestamp="2009-11-16T18:58:35Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Discrimination sidebar}}
'''[[Violence]] against [[lesbian]], [[gay]], [[bisexual]], [[transgender]], and [[queer]] ([[LGBTQ]]) people''' are actions which may occur either at the hands of individuals or groups, or as part of governmental enforcement of laws targeting people who are perceived to violate [[Heteronormativity|heteronormative]] rules and who contravene perceived protocols of [[gender role|gender]] and sexual roles. People who are perceived to be LGBTQ may also be targeted.

A [[hate crime]] is when individuals become victimized because of their race, ethnicity, religion, gender or sexual orientation (Conklin,1992)(CSVR). Hate crimes against LGBTQ people often occur because the perpetrators are [[Homophobia|homophobic]]. The attacks can also be blamed on society itself. A variety of religious groups as well as proponents of extremist political ideologies condemn homosexuality and relate it to being weak, ill, feminine, and morally wrong.&lt;ref&gt;Joanna Sugden, [http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/comment/faith/article3545414.ece Bishop accuses gays of 'conspiracy' against the Catholic Church], ''Times Online'' 13 March 2008&lt;/ref&gt;  Violence targeted at people because of their perceived sexuality can be psychological and physical including [[murder]]. These actions may be caused by cultural, [[religion and sexual orientation|religious]], or political [[mores]] and biases.

==An early example of persecution==

An early example of persecution was in the year 342 when the Christian emperors [[Constantius II|Constantius]] and [[Constans]] declared same-sex marriage to be illegal.&lt;ref&gt; [[Theodosian Code]] 9.8.3: ''"When a man marries and is about to offer himself to men in womanly fashion (quum vir nubit in feminam viris porrecturam), what does he wish, when sex has lost all its significance; when the crime is one which it is not profitable to know; when Venus is changed to another form; when love is sought and not found? We order the statutes to arise, the laws to be armed with an avenging sword, that those infamous persons who are now, or who hereafter may be, guilty may be subjected to exquisite punishment.''&lt;/ref&gt; In the year 390, the Christian emperors [[Valentinian II]], [[Theodosius I]] and [[Arcadius]] declared homosexual sex to be illegal and those who were guilty of it were condemned to be publicly burned alive.&lt;ref name = THEOD&gt; (Theodosian Code 9.7.6): All persons who have the shameful custom of condemning a man's body, acting the part of a woman's to the sufferance of alien sex (for they appear not to be different from women), shall expiate a crime of this kind in avenging flames in the sight of the people.&lt;/ref&gt; The Christian emperor [[Justinian I]] (527-565) made homosexuals a scapegoat for problems such as "famines, earthquakes, and pestilences." &lt;ref&gt; Justinian ''Novels'' 77, 144 &lt;/ref&gt;

==State-sanctioned violence==
===Historic===
{{main|LGBT rights by country or territory}}
[[Image:Burning of Sodomites.jpg|thumb|The knight von Hohenberg and his squire, being burned at the stake for sodomy, Zurich 1482 (Zurich Central Library)]]
The first recorded [[Abrahamic religions|Abrahamic]] laws  against sexual intercourse between men are dated  to circa [[550 BC]], during the [[Babylonian captivity]] of the [[Jews|Jewish people]]; they are recorded in [[Leviticus]], and they prescribe the death penalty. Similar laws are found   across [[Indo-European]] cultures in ''[[Lex Scantinia]]'' in Ancient Rome and ''[[nith]]'' in protohistoric Germanic culture, or the [[Assyrian_Empire#Middle_Assyrian_period|Middle Assyrian]] Law Codes dating 1075 BCE&lt;ref&gt;The Middle [[Assyrian law|Assyrian Law Codes]] (1075 BC) states: ''"If a man have intercourse with his brother-in-arms, they shall turn him into a eunuch"'', see [[Sodomy_law#History]]&lt;/ref&gt;.

After Constantine established Christianity as the state religion of the Roman Empire, male homosexual activity became repressed, specifically for the passive role, often sanctioned with mutilation or death and [[social ostracism]].&lt;ref name = THEOD/&gt; Laws and codes prohibiting homosexual practice were in force in [[Europe]] from the fourth century &lt;ref name = THEOD/&gt; to the twentieth centuries, and Muslim countries have had similar laws from the beginnings of Islam in the seventh century up to and including the present day. Among the states that have historically punished homosexuality with death are:

*[[Abbasid]] [[Baghdad]] under the Caliph [[Al-Hadi]] (785-786)
* The [[Florence|City of Florence]] during the [[Middle Ages]] and the [[Renaissance]];
** Illustrative victims: [[Giovanni di Giovanni]] (1350{{ndash}} 1365?), [[Florence|Florentine]] boy, castrated and "burned between the thighs with a red-hot iron" by court order;
* The [[Swiss]] [[canton of Zürich]] in the [[Renaissance]]
** Illustrative victims: Knight von Hohenberg (d. 1482), [[Swiss]] knight, burned at the stake together with his lover, his young squire;
* The kingdom of [[France]] during the [[Middle Ages]] and the [[Renaissance]]
** Illustrative victims: [[Jacques Chausson]] (1618{{ndash}} 1661), [[France|French]] writer, burned alive for attempting to seduce the son of a nobleman;
* [[England]] from 1533 until 1861 (see [[Buggery Act 1533]]);
* [[Nazi Germany]] (see [[History of homosexual people in Nazi Germany and the Holocaust]]);

===Contemporary===
{{See also|LGBT topics and Islam}}
* Death penalty in [[Afghanistan]] under the rule of the [[Taliban]] (1996-2001);
* [[Iraq]], post war (2003–)
**In January 2007, a [[United Nations]] report described the increased persecution, torture and extrajudicial killing of Iraqi lesbians and gay men by the Shia [[death squads]] of the [[Badr Organization|Badr]] and [[Sadr]] militias (the armed wings of the two main Shia parties that control the government of Iraq). In 2005, the [[Grand Ayatollah Ali al-Sistani]] issued a fatwa on his website calling for the execution of gays in the "worst, most severe way". Following protests from UK based Iraqi gay rights group, Sistani agreed to remove the fatwa from his website except for the section calling for the punishment of lesbianism.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/middle-east/iraqi-police-killed-14yearold-boy-for-being-homosexual-476917.html Iraqi police 'killed 14-year-old boy for being homosexual'] - ''The Independent''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.nytimes.com/2007/12/18/world/middleeast/18baghdad.html?_r=1&amp;oref=slogin Gays Living in Shadows of New Iraq] New York Times&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.pinknews.co.uk/news/politics/2005-1476.html Iraqi Ayatollah removes gay fatwa] Pink News&lt;/ref&gt;

{{As of|2007|10}}, homosexual acts are punishable by death in seven countries through Sharia Law:&lt;ref&gt; [http://ilga.org/news_results.asp?LanguageID=1&amp;FileCategoryID=50&amp;FileID=1111&amp;ZoneID=7 World Day against Death Penalty] Seven countries still put people to death for same-sex acts&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = FOXDEATH&gt;[http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,311025,00.html Gays Deserve Torture, Death Penalty, Iranian Minister Says]&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Iran]]
* [[Mauritania]]
* [[Nigeria]]
* [[Saudi Arabia]]
* [[Sudan]]
* [[United Arab Emirates]]
* [[Yemen]]

In Saudi Arabia, the maximum punishment for homosexuality is public execution, but the government will use other punishments—e.g., fines, jail time, and [[whipping]]—as alternatives, unless it feels that homosexuals are challenging state authority by engaging in [[LGBT social movements]].&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.sodomylaws.org/world/saudi_arabia/saudinews19.htm Is Beheading Really the Punishment for Homosexuality in Saudi Arabia?]&lt;/ref&gt;  

Iran is perhaps the nation to execute the largest number of its citizens for homosexuality.  Since the 1979 [[Iranian Revolution|Islamic revolution]] in Iran, the Iranian government has executed more than 4,000 people charged with homosexual acts.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation |url=http://www.vexen.co.uk/religion/homosexuality.html#Islam |title=Homosexuality and Religion}}&lt;/ref&gt; In Afghanistan after the fall of the Taliban, homosexuality went from a capital crime to one that it punished with fines and prison sentence.

International human rights organizations such as [[Human Rights Watch]] and [[Amnesty International]] condemn laws that make homosexual relations between consenting adults a crime.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.amnesty.org/en/library/asset/POL30/003/2008/en/d77d0d58-4cd3-11dd-bca2-bb9d43f3e059/pol300032008eng.html Love, Hate and the Law: Decriminalizing Homosexuality; Amnesty International (2008)]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hrw.org/en/news/2009/04/24/burundi-repeal-law-criminalizing-homosexual-conduct Burundi: Repeal Law Criminalizing Homosexuality; Human Rights Watch (24th April 2009)]&lt;/ref&gt;  Since 1994,  the [[United Nations]] [[Human Rights Committee]] has also ruled that such laws violated the right to privacy guaranteed in the [[Universal Declaration of Human Rights]] and the [[International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights]].&lt;ref name="ai-usa"&gt;{{cite press release |title=United Nations: General assembly to address sexual orientation and gender identity - Statement affirms promise of Universal Declaration of Human Rights |publisher=[[Amnesty International]] |date={{Date|2008-12-12|mdy}} |url=http://www.amnestyusa.org/document.php?id=ENGIOR410452008 |accessdate={{Date|2009-03-20|mdy}}}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=prai&gt;{{cite press release |title=UN: General Assembly statement affirms rights for all |publisher=[[Amnesty International]] |date={{Date|2008-12-12|mdy}} |url=http://www.amnesty.org/es/library/asset/IOR40/024/2008/en/269de167-d107-11dd-984e-fdc7ffcd27a6/ior400242008en.pdf |accessdate={{Date|2009-03-20|mdy}}}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=Sue |last=Pleming |date={{Date|2009-03-18|mdy}} |title=In turnaround, U.S. signs U.N. gay rights document |publisher=[[Reuters]] |url=http://www.reuters.com/article/domesticNews/idUSTRE52H5CK20090318 |accessdate={{Date|2009-03-20|mdy}}}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''See also: [[Mahmoud Asgari and Ayaz Marhoni]]''

==Relationship between religious condemnation and violence==
Several media articles discuss the role of religion plays, or has played, in fostering cultures that give rise to homophobic violence.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pinknews.co.uk/news/articles/2005-8869.html Violence against gays preached in British mosques claims new documentary]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://static.rnw.nl/migratie/www.radionetherlands.nl/currentaffairs/ned070727-redirected Homophobic attacks in Amsterdam: the perpetrators]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.spiegel.de/international/germany/0,1518,562638,00.html Does Germany Have a Problem With Gay Hate Crime?]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.freemuse.org/sw20860.asp Dancehall star signs Reggae Compassionate Act]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/comment/faith/article5387858.ece Pope accused of stoking homophobia after he equates homosexuality to climate change]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ekklesia.co.uk/node/7382 Evangelical leader criticises failure to condemn violence against gays]&lt;/ref&gt; However, some Christian leaders in the west tend to denounce such violence.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.catholicnewsagency.com/new.php?n=14672 Vatican U.N. delegation calls for end to unjust discrimination against homosexuals]&lt;/ref&gt;  Some religious leaders and followers believe that the Bible, the Koran, or the Torah say that homosexuality is wrong, while others have dismissed as exaggeration and misinterpretation such interpretations of the Bible.&lt;ref&gt;A church's struggle over gay marriage, The United Church of Christ&amp;nbsp;— famous for setting precedent&amp;nbsp;— considers backing same-sex marriage at its national synod, by Jane Lampman | Staff writer of The Christian Science Monitor &lt;/ref&gt;

==Criminal violence, legal and police responses==
Otherwise law-abiding citizens have at times been prepared to break the law, either out of prejudice or in order to repress people they perceive as having LGBT identities or engaging in LGBT activity.  In many parts of the world, including much of the [[EU]] and United States, acts of violence are legally classified as [[hate crime]]s, which entails a harsher sentence if convicted. In some countries this form of legislation extends to verbal abuse as well as physical violence. Sometimes, people have been the target of anti-LGBT violence because they were perceived to be LGBT, whether they were or not.

Violent hate crimes against LGBT people are notable because they tend to be especially brutal, "an intense rage is present in nearly all homicide cases involving gay male victims".  It is rare for a victim to just be shot, he is more likelely to be stabbed multiple times, mutilated, and strangled. "They frequently involved torture, cutting, mutilation... showing the absolute intent to rub out the human being because of his (sexual) preference".&lt;ref name = ALTS&gt;{{citation | title= Hate Crimes: a reference handbook | last= Altschiller | first= Donald | publisher= ABC-CLIO | year= 2005 | pages= 26–28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Acts of violence considered to have been inspired by hatred of LGBT people, legislative changes, police and judicial responses, by country.

==Violence and legal responses by country==
===Australia===
* On December 3, 2007, Craig Gee was attacked by four men whilst holding his boyfriend's hand walking down Crown Street in [[Surry Hills]], [[Sydney, Australia]]. Part of his skull was reduced to powder and his leg was broken during the attack.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.ssonet.com.au/display.asp?ArticleID=7569 'Sorry, we can't help you'] - Sydney Star Observer&lt;/ref&gt; This incident prompted a vigil against the rising level of [[homophobia]] in the city and alleged apathy from police,&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.ssonet.com.au/display.asp?ArticleID=7699 Vigil Attracts Huge Crowd&amp;nbsp;]— Sydney Star Observer&lt;/ref&gt;, and despite the attack, Gee and his boyfriend joined the Chief of Parade [[Margaret Cho]] to lead the 2008 [[Sydney Gay and Lesbian Mardi Gras]] parade.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.ssonet.com.au/display.asp?ArticleID=7885 Bashing Victims to Lead Parade]&amp;nbsp;— Sydney Star Observer&lt;/ref&gt;

===Brazil===
* In September 2007, Osvan Inacio dos Santos, 19, was attacked and murdered in a street near a bar where he had just won the local "Miss Gay" competition in the town of Batingas in northeast [[Brazil]]. dos Santos' naked body was found on Sunday morning and forensic examination found his skull had been fractured and indicated sexual assault.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.pinknews.co.uk/news/articles/2005-5494.html Gay beauty contest winner murdered- from Pink News- all the latest gay news from the gay community - Pink News&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
* In February 2008, Brazilian gay rights activist Alexandre Peixe dos Santos was attacked and beaten at the ''[[Sao Paulo]]'s Gay Pride Association offices'' in [[Brazil]]. Activists estimate that more than 2,680 gay people were murdered in [[Brazil]] between 1980 and 2006.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.pinknews.co.uk/news/articles/2005-6830.html Gay rights leader attacked in Brazil- from Pink News- all the latest gay news from the gay community - Pink News&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Canada===
* On November 17, 2001, in [[Vancouver, British Columbia]], [[Aaron Webster]], a gay man, was beaten to death with baseball bats and pool cues in a part of [[Stanley Park]] known for [[Cruising for sex|cruising]]. Ryan Cran, along with two unidentified youths, was convicted of manslaughter in Webster's death. Cran was paroled in February 2009 after serving four years of a six-year sentence.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cbc.ca/canada/british-columbia/story/2009/02/05/bc-arron-webster-ryan-cran-released.html Gay community troubled by release of killer in Stanley Park death]&lt;/ref&gt;
*On May 29, 2007, Michael Marcil, better known as [[drag queen]] Dixie Landers was beaten outside of an [[Ottawa]], [[Ontario]] gay pub.  Andrew Lefebvre and Sheri-Lee Rand have been charged for the attack.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.xtra.ca/public/viewstory.aspx?AFF_TYPE=2&amp;STORY_ID=3248&amp;PUB_TEMPLATE_ID=5 Dixie out of hospital; two people charged&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
* November 3, 2008 - Anji Dimitriou and Jane Currie were physically assaulted at an Oshawa, Ontario public school, while waiting to pick up their children.  Mark Scott, the attacker, punched both women in the face, referring to them as "men," "fucking dyke bitches" and spitting in Dimitriou's face.  He is in court in Jan. 2009, for two counts of assault causing bodily harm.&lt;ref&gt; [http://network.nationalpost.com/np/blogs/toronto/archive/2008/12/09/no-hate-charges-in-attack-on-oshawa-lesbians.aspx No hate charges in attack on Oshawa lesbians]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ctv.ca/servlet/ArticleNews/story/CTVNews/20081112/oshawa_attack_081112/20081112/ Lesbians seek hate crime charges after attack]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Croatia===
*On July 7, 2007, 30 participants at a gay pride event in [[Croatia]] were attacked by multiple assailants. The attackers had also prepared [[Molotov cocktail]]s but were stopped by the police before using them. Many people taking part in Gay Pride marches in Eastern Europe (e.g: [[Romania]], [[Russia]], [[Serbia]]) have been beaten after leaving the marches.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.iht.com/articles/ap/2007/10/30/europe/EU-GEN-Croatia-Hate-Crime.php Croat charged with hate crime for attempting to attack gay parade - International Herald Tribune&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.mywire.com/pubs/AFP/2007/07/07/3921947?extID=10051 MyWire | AFP: Violence at Croatian Gay Pride march]&lt;/ref&gt;

===France===
* The non-fatal stabbing of [[Bertrand Delanoë]], the openly gay mayor of [[Paris]], in October 2002.

===Israel===
* On June 30, 2005, Yishai Shlisel, a [[Haredi Judaism|Haredi Jew]], was charged with attempted murder after allegedly stabbing three marchers in a [[gay pride]] parade in [[Jerusalem]], [[Israel]], claiming he acted "in the name of God".&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/4653655.stm]&lt;/ref&gt;

* On August 1, 2009, [[2009 Tel Aviv gay centre shooting|a gunman entered a gay youth club]] in [[Tel Aviv]] and shot at patrons with automatic rifle fire, killing 24-year-old Nir Katz and 16-year-old Liz Tarbushi, and injuring fifteen others.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.haaretz.com/hasen/spages/1104611.html Livni to gay Israelis: Don't let hate crime stop you living your lives]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.haaretz.com/hasen/spages/1104659.html Hundreds mourn as Tel Aviv gay center attack victims laid to rest ]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cnn.com/2009/WORLD/meast/08/01/israel.club.shooting/ 2 dead, 11 hurt in shooting at gay club in Israel]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Ireland===
* The beating to death of Declan Flynn in [[Fairview, Dublin|Fairview Park]], [[Dublin]], in 1983. The murder and subsequent suspended sentences of the perpetrators who pleaded guilty to murder saw the emergence of a more vocal gay community in the aftermath.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation
  |title=Out at last
  | newspaper = Sunday Business Post
  |date=June 8, 2008
  |url=http://archives.tcm.ie/businesspost/2008/06/08/story33417.asp
  |format=
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Jamaica===
* On June 5, 2004, Jamaican gay rights activist [[Brian Williamson]] was murdered in [[Kingston, Jamaica|Kingston]]. His killer, Dwight Hayden, who used a [[machete]] to stab and chop him some 70 times, pleaded guilty&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jamaica-gleaner.com/gleaner/20060504/news/news2.html Man pleads guilty to murdering gay activist]&lt;/ref&gt; and received a life sentence.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.asylumlaw.org/docs/sexualminorities/JamaicaUSCountRep030607.pdf Country Reports on Human Rights Practices - 2006] Released by the Bureau of Democracy, Human Rights, and Labor March 6, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;
* In December 2005, a Jamaican mob chased an alleged gay man who, fearful of the crowd, jumped into the water and drowned.&lt;ref name="jamaica"&gt;[http://www.gaywired.com/article.cfm?section=66&amp;id=18055 Gay Men in Jamaica Attacked by Mob]&lt;/ref&gt;
* In April 2006, students rioted at the [[University of the West Indies]] in Jamaica and attacked an alleged gay student.&lt;ref name="jamaica"/&gt;
* On February 14, 2007, a group of gay men, including gay-rights activist Gareth Williams, were stoned by a mob in [[Mandeville, Jamaica]]. Their attackers reportedly had earlier demanded that the men leave the community.&lt;ref&gt; [http://direland.typepad.com/direland/2007/02/jamaica_gay_lea.html Direland: Jamaica: Gay Leader Escapes St. Valentine'S Day Lynch Mob&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="autogenerated1"&gt; [http://www.pinknews.co.uk/news/law/2005-6735.html Homophobic mob attack Jamaican gay men]&lt;/ref&gt;
* On April 8, 2007, approximately 100 men gathered outside a church where 150 people were attending the funeral of a gay man in Mandeville, [[Jamaica]]. According to mourners, the crowd broke the windows with bottles and shouted, "We want no battyman [gay] funeral here. Leave or else we’re going to kill you. We don’t want no battyman buried here in Mandeville." &lt;ref name="jamaica"/&gt;
* In January, 2008, three gay men were attacked in the privacy of their dwelling by an angry mob who had days before threatened them if they did not leave the community in Mandeville, [[Jamaica]]. According to reports, two men were hospitalised, one with serious injuries, while another man is still missing and feared dead.&lt;ref name="jamaica"/&gt;&lt;ref name="autogenerated1" /&gt;

===New Zealand===
* The murder in [[Wellington]], [[New Zealand]], on May 8, 1999, of supposedly gay teenager [[Jeff Whittington]], who was beaten, kicked, and stomped to death by two men who reportedly later boasted of beating up a "[[faggot]]." Whittington's attackers, Jason Morris Meads and Stephen James Smith, were sentenced to life in prison.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.stuff.co.nz/national/20087 Tax scam run from Rimutaka Prison]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Norway===
* The killing of Magne Andreassen in [[Lillehammer]], on August 21, 1992. The police investigation took about a year before [[Faust (musician)|Bård Faust]], the drummer of the band [[Emperor (band)|Emperor]], was tried and convicted of the killing. He was released from prison in 2002.&lt;ref name="decibel"&gt;{{citation |url=http://decibelmagazine.com/Content.aspx?ncid=103042 |title=Emperor – In the Nightside Eclipse |periodical=Decibel Magazine |accessdate=2009-01-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
{{Citation  | last = Kahn-Harris  | first = Keith  | title = Extreme metal: music and culture on the edge  | volume = 1  | pages = 45–46  | publisher = Berg Publishers  | publication-date = 2007  | isbn=1-84520-399-2  | contribution-url = http://books.google.com/books?id=9--qAVrfxukC  | year = 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Portugal===
* In February 2006, Gisberta Salce Júnior, a Brazilian transsexual living in  [[Oporto]], Portugal, was tortured and raped with sticks over a period of three days, then tossed into a water-filled pit and left to die. A group of adolescent boys admitted to the attack&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ilga.org/news_results.asp?LanguageID=1&amp;FileCategory=6&amp;FileID=823 Transexual Murdered in Portugal]&lt;/ref&gt; and received suspended sentences.

===Serbia===
* On June 30, 2001, hundreds of Serbian nationalists, skinheads, and soccer hooligans attacked participants of the first [[Gay pride parade#Belgrade|Serbian Pride Parade]] in [[Belgrade]].&lt;ref name="Serbia"&gt;{{citation |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/1415789.stm|title=In pictures: Belgrade gay march clashes |periodical=BBC News |accessdate=2009-01-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Sierra Leone===
* [[FannyAnn Eddy]] was the most prominent [[Sierra Leone]]an gay and lesbian rights activist, working for Sierra Leone Lesbian and Gay Association (SLLGA), and had addressed the [[United Nations]] on lesbian and gay issues in her country during the discussion on the [[Brazilian Resolution]]. Eddy founded SLLAGA in 2002. On September 28, 2004 Eddy was murdered while working alone in the [[Freetown]] SLLGA office, it is believed up to three men took part in the attack.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.hrw.org/legacy/english/docs/2004/10/04/sierra9440_txt.htm Sierra Leone: Lesbian Rights Activist Brutally Murdered]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/africa/3716768.stm Sierra Leone gay activist killed]&lt;/ref&gt;  Sierra Leone Police Force said that the murder could not be blamed on homophobia, and dismissed the claim that she had been raped, or that there was more than one attacker; Outrage expressed caution in accepting this statement by the police.  The one suspect escaped from police custody before his trial and has not been recaptured or prosecuted.  Human rights activists are unclear whether this was a hate crime or not, but regard her attack by one or more men in the offices of SLLGA as significant.  They have asked why only one suspected attacker was captured, expressed concern over repeated delays in prosecution, and how he was able to escape custody.&lt;ref name = EDDY&gt;{{web cite | url= http://www.iglhrc.org/cgi-bin/iowa/article/takeaction/resourcecenter/374.html | title= Alleged Fannyann Eddy Murderer Reportedly Escapes Police Detention in Sierra Leone | publisher= IGLHRC | date= 4 Oct 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.iglhrc.org/cgi-bin/iowa/article/takeaction/resourcecenter/388.html]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.afrol.com/articles/15308]&lt;/ref&gt;  In 2007 the [[Hirschfeld Eddy Foundation]] for the human rights of lesbian, gay, bisexual and transgender (LGBT) people was established in Berlin; the name is a combination of Eddy and [[Magnus Hirschfeld|Magnus Hirschfeld's]] names.

===South Africa===
{{See also|Corrective rape}}
* In November 1999, Blah Bar, a gay bar in [[Cape Town]], [[South Africa]], was bombed, injuring two people.&lt;ref&gt; [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/africa/507805.stm BBC News] | Africa | Bomb blast in gay clubland&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;

===Spain===
* On January 13, 2006, Julio Anderson Luciano and his fiancé, Isaac Ali Dani Peréz Triviño, were killed in the home they shared with Peréz Triviño's mother in the Spanish city of [[Vigo]]. Jacobo Piñeiro Rial, who stabbed them 22 and 35 times, respectively, then set fire to the home, was sentenced to 20 years imprisonment for arson after being acquitted by a jury of murder charges on a "gay panic" defence.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.typicallyspanish.com/news/publish/article_20321.shtml Self confessed killer of two gay men gets 20 years for starting a fire]&lt;/ref&gt;

===St. Maarten===
*On April 6, 2006, two American television producers, ''[[CBS Evening News]]'' senior producer Richard Jefferson and ''[[48 Hours (TV series)|48 Hours]]'' producer-researcher Ryan Smith, were severely beaten with a tire iron outside the Sunset Beach Bar on the [[Caribbean]] island of [[St. Maarten]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sfbaytimes.com/index.php?sec=article&amp;article_id=4911 San Francisco Bay Times&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Three men and one woman were convicted and sentenced to prison for the attack, which was ruled a hate crime.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.iglhrc.org/cgi-bin/iowa/article/takeaction/resourcecenter/302.html]&lt;/ref&gt;

===UK: England and Wales===
====1950-1959====
* On July 31 1950, in Rotherham, an English schoolteacher, Kenneth Crowe, aged 37, was found dead wearing his wife's clothes and a wig.  He had approached a miner on his way home from the pub, who upon discovering Crowe was male, beat and strangled him.&lt;ref name= MINER1&gt;{{citation | title= 'Thought Man Was Woman' Story: Charge Is Now Murder | newspaper= News of the World | date= 5 Nov 1950}}&lt;/ref&gt;  John Cooney was found not guilty of murder and sentenced to five years for manslaughter.&lt;ref name= MINER2&gt;{{citation | title= He Killed Man Who Dressed As a Woman | newspaper= News of the World | date=26 Nov 1950}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====1989-1990: West London murders====
[[Image:AdmiralDuncan.jpg|thumb|upright|London gay pub bombing in 1999 killed three and injured 70]]
Towards the end of 1989 and the start of 1990, there were a series of unsolved murders in west London over a period of six months.
* In September 1989, Christopher Schliach, a barrister who was gay, was murdered in his home; he was stabbed more than 40 times.&lt;ref name = LONUNS2/&gt;
* Three months later, Henry Bright, a hotelier who was gay, was also stabbed to death at his home.&lt;ref name = LONUNS2/&gt;.
* A month later, William Dalziel, a hotel porter who was gay, was found unconscious on a roadside in Acton, west London. He died from severe head injuries.&lt;ref name = LONUNS2/&gt;
* Three months after this, actor Michael Boothe was murdered in west London (see below [[#2007: Metropolitan Police review|2007 Met review]])
In July 1990, following these murders, hundreds of lesbians and gay men marched from the park where Boothe had been killed to Ealing town hall and held a candlelit vigil.&lt;ref name = LONUNS2/&gt;  The demonstration led to the formation of [[OutRage]], who called for the police to start protecting gay men instead of arresting them.&lt;ref name = LONUNS2/&gt; In September 1990, lesbian and gay police officers established the [[Gay Police Association|Lesbian and Gay Police Association]] (Lagpa/GPA).&lt;ref name = LONUNS2/&gt;

====1999: The Admiral Duncan pub bombing====
* In May 1999, the [[Admiral Duncan pub|Admiral Duncan]], a gay [[pub]] in [[Soho]] was bombed by former British National Party member [[David Copeland]], killing three people and wounding at least 70.&lt;ref&gt;{{web cite | url= http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/special_report/1999/05/99/the_nail_bomb_terror/333913.stm | title= Thousands remember Soho dead  | publisher= BBC | date= 02 May 1999}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{web cite | url= http://www.lgf.org.uk/news/1092/590/The-Admiral-Duncan-Bombing---10-years-on/ | title= The Admiral Duncan Bombing - 10 years on | publisher= The Lesbian and Gay Foundation (UK) | date= 30 April 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====2002: CPS 'zero tolerance'====
On the 27 Nov. 2002, the [[Crown Prosecution Service]] announced a 'zero tolerance' approach towards perpetrators of anti-gay offenses; this also covers transsexuals.  Crimes considered 'homophobic' or 'transphobic' are to be assessed in a similar way to those considered racist (e.g. the victim regarding them as such).&lt;ref name = GUACPS&gt;{{citation | title= Crackdown on homophobic crime | last= Dyer | first= Clare | newspaper= Guardian | date= 28 Nov 2002 | url= http://www.guardian.co.uk/uk/2002/nov/28/gayrights.ukcrime}}&lt;/ref&gt;"There is no statutory definition of a homophobic or transphobic incident. However, when prosecuting such cases, and to help us to apply our policy on dealing with cases with a homophobic or transphobic element, we adopt the following definition: 'Any incident which is perceived to be homophobic or transphobic by the victim or by any other person.'”&lt;ref name= CPS&gt;{{citation | title= CPS: Policy for prosecuting cases of homophobic and transphobic cime | publisher=  Crown Copyright; Crown Prosecution Service | date= Nov 2007 | page= 5 | url= http://www.cps.gov.uk/publications/docs/htc_policy.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====2003: Criminal Justice Act====
The [[Criminal Justice Act]] 2003 is passed, in which section 146 empowers courts in England and Wales to impose tougher sentences for offenses motivated or aggravated by the victim's sexual orientation.&lt;ref name = CJA&gt;[http://www.opsi.gov.uk/acts/acts2003/30044--o.htm#146 Section 146 of the Criminal Justice Act 2003]&lt;/ref&gt;

====2006: first prosecution for homophobic murder====
* On the 14th October 2005, London, [[Jody Dobrowski]] was beaten to death on Clapham Common by two men who perceived him as being gay; Dobrowski was beaten so badly he had to be identified by his fingerprints.  Thomas Pickford and Scott Walker were given life sentences in what was described as a 'homophobic murder' in June 2006.&lt;ref name = DOB&gt;{{web cite | title= Men jailed for gay barman murder | publisher= BBC | url= http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/london/5087286.stm | date =16 June 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;  This was the first prosecution in England and Wales where Section 146 of the Criminal Justice Act 2003 was used in sentencing the killers; this enabled the courts to impose a tougher sentence for offenses motivated or aggravated by the victim's sexual orientation, in this case a minimum of 30 years in prison.&lt;ref name = SOBCJA&gt;{{citation | title= Two face 30 years in jail for homophobic murder | newspaper= Times | date= 13 May 2006 | url= http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/uk/crime/article717120.ece}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====2007: Metropolitan Police review====
[[Image:Atherton, John (1598-1640) &amp; Childe, John (16 -1640) - 1641.jpg|thumb|250px|[[John Atherton]], Bishop of Waterford and Lismore, was hanged for [[sodomy]] under a law that he had helped to institute. His lover was John Childe, his steward and tithe proctor, also hanged. Anonymous pamphlet, 1641.]]
In July 2004 an independent inquiry into police procedures carried out by the independent Lesbian Gay Bisexual Transgender Advisory Group for the Metropolitan Police was announced.&lt;ref name = LONUNS1/&gt;  In May 2007 the report for the independent review was relased; it had examined how detectives had handled 10 murders of gay men or transsexuals.  The report found that some police inquiries were hampered by lack of knowledge, reliance on unfounded stereotypes and personal prejudices; these problems were mirrored and exacerbated by media coverage.  The review recognised that Scotland Yard's work with the gay, lesbian and transsexual communities and its investigative processes had improved significantly since the 1990s, but warned that more radical steps were needed.  The cases reviewed, and the findings, included:
* Actor Michael Boothe, in west London died in April 1990, beaten to death by a gang of up to six men close to a public lavatory.&lt;ref name = LONUNS1/&gt; the police said he had been the victim of "an extraordinarily severe beating, of a merciless and savage nature".  He managed to give a description of his attackers before he died, and a reward of £15,000 was offered, but nobody was caught,&lt;ref name = LONUNS2&gt;{{citation | title= The worst of times | last= Richardson | first= Colin | newspaper= Guardian | date= 14 August 2002 | url= http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2002/aug/14/gayrights.comment}}&lt;/ref&gt;  and the crime was not solved.  The police review identified institutional homophobia within the Metropolitan Police as a factor.&lt;ref name = LONUNS3&gt;{{citation | title= Officers' homophobia hampered murder investigations, says review | last= Muir | first= Hugh | newspaper= Guardian | date= 15 May 2007 | url= http://www.guardian.co.uk/uk/2007/may/15/gayrights.ukcrime}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Colin Ireland, age 43, who in 1993 was jailed for life for murdering five gay men.  Ireland picked up the men at pubs in London, and then killed them in their own homes.&lt;ref name = LONUNS1&gt;{{citation | title= Gay Rights: A matter of pride for the Metropolitan Police? | newspaper= Independent | url= http://www.independent.co.uk/news/uk/crime/gay-rights-a-matter-of-pride-for-the-metropolitan-police-552104.html | unused_data= |5 July 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt;  A Scotland Yard review showed that Ireland's capture was hampered by institutional homophobia within the Metropolitan Police.&lt;ref name = LONUNS3/&gt;
* Andrew Collier, a housing warden, aged 33, was one of Ireland's victims; the murder was classified as homophobic and linked with the death of Peter Walker, Ireland's first victim.  The report said the police could have done more to warn the community of the links between the murders.&lt;ref name = LONUNS3/&gt;
* Emanuel Spiteri, age 41, who was strangled to death in his flat in Catford by Ireland, after meeting in a pub in Earls Court, west London.&lt;ref name = LONUNS3/&gt;
* Robyn Brown, a 23-year-old transsexual prostitute, was found stabbed to death in her flat in London on February 28, 1997.  The original report described her as being 23-year-old Gemma Browne, formerly James Darwin Browne.&lt;ref name = GEMMA&gt;{{citation | last= Graham | first= Polly | newspaper= Sunday Mirror | page= 19 | date=  27 April 2003 | unused_data= TV Nicky's DNA tested in hunt for tranny-killer; Watchdog start to help probe over stab death}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The case went cold for over ten years, but her killer, James Hopkins, was eventually caught; in January 2009 he was jailed for life.&lt;ref name = YPROB&gt;[http://www.yorkshireeveningpost.co.uk/news/Transsexual-39was-killed-by-.4867222.jp Transsexual 'was killed by a Jamaican'] ''Yorkshire Evening Post'' 13 January 2009&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = METROB&gt;[http://www.metro.co.uk/news/article.html?Killer_of_transexual_prostitute_jailed_for_life&amp;in_article_id=498266&amp;in_page_id=34 'Killer of transexual prostitute jailed for life']&lt;/ref&gt;  The report found that identifying her to the public using different names may have hampered attempts to connect with relevant communities.&lt;ref name = LONUNS3/&gt;
* June 2000, south-east London, UK. Jaap Bornkamp, a 52 year old florist, was knifed in a homophobic attack; the murder remains unsolved despite the police displaying 20&amp;nbsp;ft by 10&amp;nbsp;ft images of CCTV footage taken near the murder scene.  He was attacked after leaving a night club, and the police are reported as saying there was no confrontation or argument, but that the attack was homophobic and unprovoked.&lt;ref name = LONUNS1/&gt;  The report found this case to have been a model of police good practice.&lt;ref name = LONUNS3/&gt;
* Geoffrey Windsor, 57, in south London died in June 2002 from head injuries in a park after he was beaten and robbed.  The police said the murder was motivated by homophobia.&lt;ref name = LONUNS1/&gt;  A review of this and similar cases in the area highlighted poor policing due to institutional homophobia within the police, particularly in not taking previous attacks in the area more seriously.&lt;ref name = LONUNS3/&gt;

====2000-2009: Recent cases====

* The name of [[Damilola Taylor]] is well known in the UK since his death on 27 November 2000 in Peckham, south London; he bled to death after being stabbed with a broken bottle in the thigh, which severed the femoral artery; he was attacked by a local gang of youths.  The BBC, Telegraph, Guardian and Independent newspapers reported at the time that during the weeks between arriving in the UK from Nigeria and the attack he had been subjected to bullying and beating, which included homophobic remarks, by a group of boys at his school, "The bullies told him that he was gay."&lt;ref name = BBCDAM&gt;{{web cite | title= Damilola's grieving father speaks out | publisher | BBC | date= 30 Nov 2000 | url= http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/africa/1048449.stm}}&lt;/ref&gt;  He "may not have understood why he was being bullied at school, or why some other children taunted him about being 'gay' - the word meant nothing to him."&lt;ref name = GUADAM/&gt;  He had to ask his mother what 'gay' meant, she said "Boys were swearing at him, saying lots of horrible words. They were calling him names."&lt;ref name = GUADAM&gt;{{citation | title= Death of a schoolboy | last= Hopkins | first= Nick | newspaper= Guardian | date= 29 Nov 2000 | url= http://www.guardian.co.uk/uk/2000/nov/29/ukcrime.nickhopkins}}&lt;/ref&gt;  His mother had spoken about this bullying, but the teachers failed to take it seriously "She said pupils had accused her son of being gay and had beaten him last Friday."&lt;ref name = INDAM&gt;{{citation | title= His mother told teachers he was being bullied. Now she must bury him | last= Bennetto | first= Jason | newspaper= Independent | date= 29 Nov 2000 | url= http://www.independent.co.uk/news/uk/home-news/his-mother-told-teachers-he-was-being-bullied-now-she-must-bury-him-622144.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Six months after the murder, his father said, "I spoke to him and he was crying that he was being bullied and being called names. He was being called 'gay'."&lt;ref name = "TELDAM"&gt;{{citation | title= Damilola's father attacks loss of values | last= Steele | first= John | newspaper= Telegraph | date= 19 June 2001 | url= http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/uknews/1377304/Damilolas-father-attacks-loss-of-values.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In the New Statesman two years later, when there had still been no convictions for the crime, Peter Tatchell, gay human rights campaigner, said, "In the days leading up to his murder in south London in November 2000, he was subjected to vicious homophobic abuse and assaults,"&lt;ref name = NSDAM&gt;{{citation | title= A victim of homophobia? | last= Tatchell | first= Peter | journal= New Statesman | date= 13 Jan 2003 | url= http://www.newstatesman.com/200301130014}}&lt;/ref&gt; and asked why the authorities had ignored this before and after his death.
* In July 2005, [[Lauren Harries]], a transwoman, was attacked along with her father and brother in their home in [[Cardiff]] by eight youths who shouted the word "tranny" (transphobic abuse) while beating their victims. One youth pleaded guilty to inflicting grievous bodily harm and was sentenced to two years probation; his accomplices were not formally identified or charged.&lt;ref&gt; [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/wales/4216786.stm BBC NEWS] | Wales | Transsexual and family attacked&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.walesonline.co.uk/news/wales-news/tm_objectid=16149951&amp;method=full&amp;siteid=50082&amp;headline=youth-who-attacked-transsexual-spared-jail--name_page.html]&lt;/ref&gt;
* In April 2006 a man was jailed for a homophobic attack on an openly gay Anglican priest.  Rev Dr Barry Rathbone was sitting in a park in Bournemouth, Dorset when Martin Powell and his girlfriend approached and spoke to him. Rathbone informed them that it was a cruising area, then Powell produced a three-foot long metal baseball bat, called him a 'queer', and started to hit him.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/dorset/4895796.stm Man jailed for priest attack]&lt;/ref&gt;
* 25 July 2008, 18 year old [[Michael Causer]] was attacked by a group of men at a party in [[Liverpool]], and died from his injuries. It is alleged that he was killed because he was gay.&lt;ref&gt; [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/merseyside/7868151.stm]&lt;/ref&gt;
* October 23, 2008 - 23 year-old gay [[hairdresser]], Daniel Jenkinson, was the victim of a homophobic attack in a [[Preston]] club. His attacker, Neil Bibby, 22, also from [[Preston]], was sentenced to 200 hours' unpaid work, a three-month weekend [[curfew]], and ordered to pay £2,000 [[compensation]] after he pleaded guilty to [[assault]]. Daniel needed facial reconstruction surgery after the attack, and says he is too scared to go out in the city.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.lep.co.uk/news/Gay-man-suffers-homophobic-attack.4824255.jp]&lt;/ref&gt;
* On March 3, 2009 in [[London Borough of Bromley|Bromley]], south [[London]], UK.  59 year old Gerry Edwards was stabbed to death by an assailant shouting homophobic abuse. His partner of over twenty years, 56 year old Chris Bevan, was also stabbed and admitted to hospital in a critical condition.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.newsshopper.co.uk/news/4175826.BICKLEY__Police_name_59_year_old_murder_victim/]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-1159685/Man-stabbed-death-partner-seriously-wounded-homophobic-attack.html]&lt;/ref&gt;  The police dealing with the case said they had an open mind, but were treating it as a homophobic murder; two men were subsequently arrested.&lt;ref name = BROMLEY&gt;{{citation | title= Two held over suspected homophobic murder | last= Taylor | first= Matthew | newspaper= Guardian | date= 6 March 2009 | url= http://www.guardian.co.uk/uk/2009/mar/06/fatal-stabbing-bromley-arrests}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====2009: Prosecution for verbal violence====
* On the 15 May, 2009, An English court found two football fans guilty of shouting homophobic chants at footballer [[Sol Campbell]] during a match.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|url=http://news.sky.com/skynews/Home/UK-News/Sol-Campbell-Two-Guilty-Of-Chanting-Gay-Boy-At-Portsmouth-Footballer-At-Match-Against-Tottenham/Article/200905315282355?lpos=UK_News_News_Your_Way_Region_6&amp;lid=NewsYourWay_ARTICLE_15282355_Sol_Campbell%3A_Two_Guilty_Of_Chanting_Gay_Boy_At_Portsmouth_Footballer_At_Match_Against_Tottenham|title=Pair Guilty Of Sol Campbell 'Gay Boy' Chants |publisher=sky.com|accessdate=2009-05-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; This was the first prosecution for indecent chanting in the UK.&lt;ref name = SOL/&gt; The police reported that up to 2,500 fans shouted chants at the match that included "Sol, Sol, wherever you may be, Not long now until lunacy, We won't give a fuck if you are hanging from a tree," the footballer commented "I felt totally victimised and helpless by the abuse I received on this day. It has had an effect on me personally".&lt;ref name = SOL&gt;{{citation | title = Pair guilty of homophobic chants at footballer Sol Campbell | newspaper= Guardian | date= 15 May 2009 | url= http://www.guardian.co.uk/uk/2009/may/15/sol-campbell-chant-guilty-portsmouth}}&lt;/ref&gt; Three men and two boys were given cautions after the match.&lt;ref name = SOL/&gt;

===UK: Scotland===
In 2009, the [[Scottish parliament]] unanimously passed legislation that means that crimes motivated by hatred of gay or disabled people will now be considered as 'aggravated offences'.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/scotland/8078988.stm MSPs approve new hate crime laws] BBC News 3 June 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

===USA===
In the [[United States]], the [[Federal Bureau of Investigation|FBI]] reported that 15.6% of hate crimes reported to police in 2004 were founded on perceived [[sexual orientation]]. Sixty-one percent of those attacks were against gay men, 14% against lesbians, 2% against heterosexuals and 1% against bisexuals, while attacks against LGBT people at large made up 20%.&lt;ref name=autogenerated2&gt; [http://www.fbi.gov/ucr/cius_04/offenses_reported/hate_crime/index.html Hate Crime - Crime in the United States 2004&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Violence based on perceived gender identity was not recorded in the report.

The FBI reported that for 2006, hate crimes against gays increased to 16%, from 14% in 2005, as percentage of total documented hate crimes across the U.S.&lt;ref name=ADVOCATE1120&gt;{{cite paper |last= |first= |authorlink= |title=FBI Shows Gay-Bashing Increase in 2006 |version= |publisher=''The Advocate'' |date=2007-11-20 |url=http://www.advocate.com/news_detail_ektid50559.asp |format= |id= |accessdate=2007-11-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The 2006 annual report, released on [[November 19]], [[2007]], also said that hate crimes based on sexual orientation are the third most common type, behind race and religion.&lt;ref name=ADVOCATE1120 /&gt;

[[Santa Clara County, California|Santa Clara County]] Deputy District Attorney (DDA) Jay Boyarsky attributed a surge in anti-gay hate crimes, from 3 in 2007 to 14 in 2008, to controversy over [[California Proposition 8 (2008)|Proposition 8]]. However, the DDA cautioned against reading too much from small statistical samples, pointing out that the vast majority of hate incidents don't get referred to the DA's office.&lt;ref name="hcspike"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mercurynews.com/ci_11921999|title=Surge in anti-gay hate crime cases|publisher=San Jose Mercury News|date=2009-03-16|accessdate=2009-03-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Legal responses to homophobic and transphobic hate crime====
In 1988 a Florida judge, trying a case concerning the beating to death of a gay man asked the prosecutor, "That's a crime now, to beat up a homosexual?"  The prosecutor responded, "Yes, sir. And it's also a crime to kill them."  "Times have really changed," the judge replied.&lt;ref name = ALTS/&gt;

On the 29 April, 2009, The U.S. House of Representatives voted to extend federal laws to classify as "hate crimes" attacks based on a victim's sexual orientation or gender identity (as well as mental or physical disability).&lt;ref name = REUT&gt;{{Citation | title= U.S. House passes "hate crime" bill that Bush opposed | publisher= Reuters(UK) | date =29 April 2009 | url= http://uk.reuters.com/article/usTopNews/idUKTRE53S8IM20090429}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====1970-1979====
* The beating death of gay man Howard Efland, who had checked into the Dover Hotel under the pseudonym of J. McCann, by officers of the [[Los Angeles Police Department]] in March 1970.&lt;ref&gt;[http://content.cdlib.org/view?docId=kt309nd9tq&amp;doc.view=entire_text&amp;brand=oac ONE National Gay and Lesbian Archives via Online Archive of California: Homophile Effort for Legal Protection, Incorporated (HELP, Inc.) Records]&lt;/ref&gt;
* The arson of the The Upstairs Lounge in [[New Orleans, Louisiana|New Orleans]] on June 24, 1973, killing 32 people.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cvvRJNQolYM]&lt;/ref&gt;
* The stabbing death of Robert Hillsborough in [[San Francisco, California|San Francisco]] on June 21, 1977 by a man shouting "faggot".&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation |title=''Gay &amp; Lesbian Rights'' |last=Peddicord |first=Richard |year=1996 |publisher=Rowman &amp; Littlefield |page=85 |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=GaDXSkJX-3EC |accessdate=2009-05-07 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* On November 27, 1978, openly gay [[San Francisco]] city supervisor [[Harvey Milk]], along with Mayor [[George Moscone]], was assassinated by political rival [[Dan White]] at San Francisco City Hall. Outrage over the assassinations and the short sentence given to White (seven years) prompted the [[White Night Riots]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation
  |title=The Mayor of Castro Street: The Life and Times of Harvey Milk
  |author=Randy Shilts
  |date=1988
  |isbn=0312019009
  |publisher=MacMillan}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Tennessee Williams]] was the victim of an assault in January 1979 in [[Key West]], being beaten by five teenage boys.  He escaped serious injury.  The episode was part of a spate of anti-gay violence inspired by an anti-gay newspaper ad run by a local [[Baptist]] minister.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation
  |title=Key West: The Last Resort
  | newspaper = Time Magazine
  |date=February 19, 1979
  |url=http://www.time.com/time/printout/0,8816,912357,00.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The beating death of Terry Knudsen by three men in Loring Park in [[Minneapolis, Minnesota|Minneapolis]] on June 5, 1979&lt;ref name = LORING&gt;[http://www.google.co.uk/url?sa=t&amp;source=web&amp;ct=res&amp;cd=13&amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.tucsonobserver.com%2Farchives%2Fpdf%2F1979%2F08%2FAUG%252024.pdf&amp;ei=5ZUESpDjD962jAfrio3tBA&amp;usg=AFQjCNHCXK-cREYYGqHWsUWlHENbu5ZysA&amp;sig2=MRO8XEb4rCHzIMLvOdYnLA]&lt;/ref&gt;.
* The stabbing death of Robert Allen Taylor on September 7, 1979, near Loring Park in [[Minneapolis, Minnesota]]. A local reporter interviewed the murderer from jail and was told, "I don't like gays. Okay?"&lt;ref name = LORING/&gt;
* The beating death in [[New York City]] on October 7, 1979, of 17 year old Steven Charles of [[Newark, New Jersey|Newark]] by [[Costabile Farace|Costabile "Gus" Farace]], Robert DeLicio, David Spoto and Farace's cousin Mark Granato. They also beat Charles' friend, 16 year old Thomas Moore of Brooklyn. Moore was critically injured but managed to get help at a nearby residence. It was Moore that identified the four men via a lineup four days after the incident. Farace, the leader of the attack, plead guilty to first-degree manslaughter. He was paroled after 8 years, in 1988. He himself was murdered on November 17, 1989.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | last = Raab | first = Selwyn | title = Five Families: The Rise, Decline, and Resurgence of America's Most Powerful Mafia Empires | volume = 1 | publisher = St. Martin's Press | publication-date = 2005 | isbn=0-312-30094-8 | year = 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====1980-1989====
* The drowning death of [[Charlie Howard (murder victim)|Charlie Howard]] in [[Bangor, Maine]], in 1984.&lt;ref&gt;[http://archive.seacoastonline.com/news/06202006/maine/108334.htm]&lt;/ref&gt;
* On May 13, 1988, [[Rebecca Wight]] was killed when she and her partner, [[Claudia Brenner]], were shot by Stephen Roy Carr while hiking and camping along the [[Appalachian Trail]]. Carr later claimed that he became enraged by the couple's lesbianism when he saw them having sex &lt;ref&gt;{{citation | last1=Brenna | first1= Claudia | last2= Ashley | first2= Hannah | title= Eight Bullets: One Woman's Story of Surviving Anti-Gay Violence | publisher= Firebrand Books | year= 1995}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====1990-1999====
[[Image:Matthew Shepard.jpg|thumb|upright|Matthew Shepard]]
* The fatal stabbing of [[James Zappalorti]] (1945{{ndash}}1990), a gay [[Vietnam]] veteran.&lt;ref name=nytimes&gt;{{Citation |work=[[The New York Times]] |title= S.I. Man, 44 Stabbed Dead On His Beach |first=James C. |last=McKinley, Jr. |date=1990-01-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The murder of Julio Rivera in [[New York City]] on July 2, 1990, by two men who beat him with a hammer and stabbed him with a knife because he was gay.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.nytimes.com/2001/09/02/nyregion/neighborhood-report-jackson-heights-antigay-attack-rekindles-ever-present-fears.html]&lt;/ref&gt;
* The killing of [[Paul Broussard]] (1968–1991), a Houston-area banker.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.outsmartmagazine.com/issue/i07-01/broussard.html]&lt;/ref&gt;
* The murder of U.S. Navy Petty Officer [[Allen R. Schindler, Jr.|Allen Schindler]] by a shipmate who stomped him to death in a public restroom in Japan on October 27, 1992.&lt;ref name="Jameson"/&gt; Schindler had complained repeatedly about anti-gay harassment aboard ship.&lt;ref name="Jameson"&gt;{{citation |last=Jameson |first=Sam |title=U.S. Sailor Sentenced to Life Imprisonment in Murder |periodical=[[Los Angeles Times]] |date=[[28 May]], [[1993]] |url=http://tech.mit.edu/V113/N28/sailor.28w.txt.html |accessdate=2008-03-21 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The case became synonymous with the [[gays]] in the military debate that had been brewing in the United States culminating in the [[Don't ask, don't tell|"Don't ask, don't tell"]] bill.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation
 | title = Any Mother's Son - About the Movie
 | publisher = [[Lifetime Television]]
 | url = http://www.mylifetime.com/on-tv/movies/any-mothers-son
 | accessdate =2008-01-12 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The 1993 rape and later murder of [[Brandon Teena]], a [[transman]] who was killed when his birth gender was revealed by police to male friends of his.&lt;ref name = bbio&gt;{{citation | last= Jones | first= Aphrodite | title= All She Wanted | publisher= Pocket Books | year= 1996}}&lt;/ref&gt;   The events leading to Mr. Teena's death were depicted in the movie ''[[Boys Don't Cry (film)|Boys Don't Cry]]''.&lt;ref name = bfilm&gt; [http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0171804/ Boys Don't Cry]&lt;/ref&gt;
* On March 9, 1995, [[Scott Amedure]] was murdered after revealing his attraction to his friend Jonathan Schmitz on a ''[[The Jenny Jones Show#The "Same Sex Crushes" Controversy|The Jenny Jones Show]]'' episode about secret crushes. Schmidtz purchased a shotgun to kill Amedure and did so after Amedure implied he still was attracted to him; Schmitz then turned himself in to police.&lt;ref name="urlTalk-Show Guest Is Guilty Of Second-Degree Murder - New York Times"&gt;{{Citation |url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E5DE113BF930A25752C1A960958260 |title=Talk-Show Guest Is Guilty Of Second-Degree Murder - New York Times |author= Bradsher, Keith|date= 1996-11-13|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5Z9xEOmO3 |archivedate= 2008-07-08|accessdate=2008-07-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|last=Jennings|first=Marianne M. |title=Business: Its Legal, Ethical, and Global Environment|publisher=Thomson West|year=2005|pages=388|isbn=0-324-20488-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The murders of [[Roxanne Ellis and Michelle Abdill]], a [[lesbian]] couple in [[Medford, Oregon]], on December 4, 1995, by a man who said he had "no compassion" for bisexual or homosexual people.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/1996/08/22/MN50950.DTL]&lt;/ref&gt; Robert Acremant was convicted and [[Capital punishment|sentenced to death]] by [[lethal injection]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://archive.mailtribune.com/archive/2005/0318/local/stories/12local.htm]&lt;/ref&gt;
* The bombing of the Otherside Lounge, a lesbian nightclub in Atlanta, by [[Eric Robert Rudolph]], the "[[Centennial Olympic Park bombing|Olympic Park]] Bomber," on February 21, 1997; five bar patrons were injured. In a statement released after he was sentenced to five consecutive life terms for his several bombings, Rudolph called homosexuality an "aberrant lifestyle".&lt;ref&gt;[http://washblade.com/2005/8-26/news/national/rudolph.cfm]&lt;/ref&gt;
* The October 7, 1998, fatal attack on [[Matthew Shepard]] (1976{{ndash}}1998), a gay student, in [[Laramie, Wyoming]]. Shepard was tortured, beaten severely, tied to a fence, and abandoned; he was found 18 hours after the attack and succumbed to his injuries less than a week later, on October 12. His attackers, Russell Arthur Henderson and Aaron James McKinney, are both serving two consecutive life sentences in prison.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/1999/11/05/us/parents-of-gay-obtain-mercy-for-his-killer.html]&lt;/ref&gt;
* The July 1, 1999, murders of gay couple [[Gary Matson]] and [[Winfield Mowder]] by [[white supremacist]] brothers Matthew and Tyler Williams in [[Redding, California]]. Tyler Williams was sentenced to a minimum of 33 years in prison, to be served after his completion of a 21-year sentence for firebombing synagogues and an abortion clinic.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pbs.org/niot/citizens_respond/redding.html]&lt;/ref&gt; Benjamin Williams claimed that by killing the couple he was "obeying the laws of the Creator".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gaypeopleschronicle.com/stories/99nov12.htm]&lt;/ref&gt; He committed suicide in 2003 while awaiting trial. Their former pastor described the brothers as "zealous in their faith" but "far from kooks".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.salon.com/news/feature/1999/10/06/redding/print.html]&lt;/ref&gt;
* The murder of U.S. Army Pfc. [[Barry Winchell]] on July 6, 1999, in [[Fort Campbell]], Kentucky by fellow soldier Calvin Glover. Winchell was beaten to death with a baseball bat after rumors spread on base of his relationship with transgendered author [[Calpernia Addams]]. Glover was sentenced to life in prison.&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20060213230320/www.davidclemens.com/gaymilitary/rolstobarry.htm]&lt;/ref&gt;
* The September 1999 murder of [[Steen Fenrich]], apparently by his stepfather, john D. Fenrich, in [[Queens]], New York. His dismembered remains were found in March 2001, with the phrase "gay nigger number one" scrawled on his skull along with his social security number. His stepfather fled from police while being interviewed, then committed suicide.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2000/03/24/nyregion/signs-in-grisly-killing-point-to-bias-and-stepfather-who-killed-himself.html?sec=health&amp;spon=&amp;pagewanted=all]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Oct 15th, 1999: Sissy "Charles" Bolden, Savannah, Georgia. Found shot to death.  Police arrested Charles E. Wilkins, Jr., in July 2003; he admitted the killing, and was charged in two other homicides, according to the Savannah Police Department.&lt;ref name = SISSY&gt;http://www.sovo.com/2004/11-12/news/localnews/gakillings.cfm&lt;/ref&gt;

====2000-2009====
* On July 3, 2000, in [[Grant Town, West Virginia]], [[Arthur Warren|Arthur "J.R." Warren]] was punched and kicked to death by two teenage boys who reportedly believed Warren had spread a rumor that he and one of the boys, David Allen Parker, had a sexual relationship. Warren's killers ran over his body to disguise the murder as a [[hit-and-run]]. Parker pleaded guilty and was sentenced to "life in prison with mercy", making him eligible for parole after 15 years.&lt;ref&gt; [http://abcnews.go.com/print?id=92841]&lt;/ref&gt; His accomplice, Jared Wilson, was sentenced to 20 years.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gaypeopleschronicle.com/stories/01aug24.htm]&lt;/ref&gt;
* On September 22, 2000, Ronald Gay entered a gay bar in [[Roanoke, Virginia]] and opened fire on the patrons, killing Danny Overstreet, 43 years old, and severely injuring six others. Ronald said he was angry over what his name now meant, and deeply upset that three of his sons had changed their surname. He claimed that he had been told by [[God]] to find and kill lesbians and gay men, describing himself as a "Christian Soldier working for my Lord;" Gay testified in court that "he wished he could have killed more fags," before several of the shooting victims as well as Danny Overstreet's family and friends.&lt;ref&gt; [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/americas/942255.stm BBC News] | AMERICAS | Murder charge for gay-bar gunman&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
* On June 16, 2001, [[Fred Martinez]], a transgender and [[two-spirit]] student was bludgeoned to death near [[Cortez, Colorado]] by 18-year-old Shaun Murphy, who reportedly bragged about attacking a "fag".&lt;ref&gt; [http://denver.rockymountainnews.com/cortez/]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Hate Crimes: Causes, Controls, and Controversies |lastGerstenfeld |firstPhyllis |year=2004 |publisher=SAGE |isbn=0761928146, 9780761928140 |page=1 |pages=293}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* On June 12, 2002, Philip Walsted, a gay man, was fatally beaten with a baseball bat. According to prosecutors, the neo-Nazi views of Walsted's assailant's, David Higdon, led to what was originally a robbery escalating to murder. Higdon was sentenced to life in prison, plus an additional sentence for robbery.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.houstonvoice.com/print.cfm?cid=2012]&lt;/ref&gt;
* The December 2002 homicide of [[Nizah Morris]], a [[trans woman]] in [[Philadelphia|Philadelphia, Pennsylvania]].
* The killing of [[Gwen Araujo]](1985{{ndash}}  2002), a [[trans woman]], by at least three men who were charged with committing a hate crime. Two were convicted of murder, the third manslaughter; however, the jury rejected the hate crime enhancement.
* On May 11, 2003, [[Sakia Gunn]], a 15-year-old lesbian, was murdered in a hate crime in [[Newark, New Jersey]]. While waiting for a bus, Gunn and her friends were propositioned by two men. When the girls rejected their advances, declaring themselves to be lesbians, the men attacked them. One of the men, Richard McCullough, fatally stabbed Gunn. In exchange for his pleading guilty to several lesser crimes including aggravated manslaughter, prosecutors dropped murder charges against McCullough, who was sentenced to 20 years.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.nytimes.com/2004/05/12/nyregion/newark-preaches-tolerance-of-gays-year-after-killing.html]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation |title=News and Sexuality: Media Portraits of Diversity |last=Castañeda |first= Laura |coauthors=Shannon B. Campbell |year=2004 |publisher=SAGE |isbn=0761928146, 9780761928140 |page=161–165 |pages=293}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* On June 17, 2003, [[Guin Richie Phillips|Richie Phillips]] of [[Elizabethtown, Kentucky]] was killed by Joseph Cottrell. His body was later found in a suitcase in [[Rough River Lake]]. During his trial, two of Cottrell's relatives testified that he lured Phillips to his death, and killed him because he was gay.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.enquirer.com/editions/2003/08/27/loc_kysuitcasebody27.html]&lt;/ref&gt; Cottrell was convicted of manslaughter and sentenced to 20 years in prison.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | title= Cottrell, appeal | work=Kentucky Supreme Court | url=http://162.114.92.72/Opinions/2005-SC-000181-MR.pdf  | accessdate=2009-05-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* On July 23, 2003, [[Nireah Johnson]] and Brandie Coleman were shot to death by Paul Moore, when Moore learned after a sexual encounter that Johnson was [[transgender]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gaywired.com/print_this_article.cfm?section=9&amp;id=2678]&lt;/ref&gt; Moore then burned his victims' bodies. He was convicted of murder and sentenced to 120 years in prison.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.in.gov/judiciary/opinions/archive/05230502.tac.html]&lt;/ref&gt;
* On July 31, 2003, 37-year-old [[Murder of Glenn Kopitske|Glenn Kopitske]] was shot and stabbed in the back by 17-year-old Gary Hirte, a straight-A student, star athlete&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.sovo.com/2006/11-10/news/police/police.cfm]&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Eagle Scout (Boy Scouts of America)|Eagle Scout]],&lt;ref&gt; [http://www3.jsonline.com/story/index.aspx?id=19381]&lt;/ref&gt; in [[Winnebago County, Wisconsin]]. Prosecutors contended that Hirte murdered Kopitske to see if he could get away with it.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.wisn.com/news/4146869/detail.html]&lt;/ref&gt; Hirte pleaded insanity, claiming he killed [[Glenn Kopitske|Kopitske]] in a murderous rage after a consensual sexual encounter with the victim, because he felt a [[homosexual]] act was "worse than murder". The 'temporary insanity' mitigation plea was not upheld, he was found guilty, and received a [[Life imprisonment|life sentence]].
* On October 2, 2004, multiple assailants in [[Waverly, Ohio]], attacked Daniel Fetty, a gay man who was hearing-impaired and homeless. Fetty was beaten, stomped, shoved nude into a garbage bin, impaled with a stick, and left for dead; he succumbed to his injuries the next day. Prosecuters alleged a hate crime. Three men received sentences ranging from seven years to life.
* On January 28, 2005, [[Ronnie Paris|Ronnie Antonio Paris]], a three-year-old boy living in [[Tampa, Florida]], died due to brain injuries inflicted by his father, Ronnie Paris, Jr. According to his mother and other relatives, Ronnie Paris, Jr., repeatedly slammed his son into walls, slapped the child's head, and "[[Boxing|boxed]]" him because he was concerned the child was gay and feared his son would grow up a [[sissy]]. Paris, Jr., was sentenced to thirty years in prison.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.advocate.com/news_detail_ektid18908.asp]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sptimes.com/2005/08/20/Hillsborough/Dad_sentenced_to_30_y.shtml]&lt;/ref&gt;
* On February 27, 2005, in [[Santa Fe, New Mexico]], 21-year-old James Maestas was assaulted outside a restaurant, then followed to a hotel and beaten unconscious by men who called him "faggot" during the attack. Although all of his attackers were charged with committing a hate crime, none was sentenced to prison.
* On March 11, 2005, [[Jason Gage]], an openly [[gay]] man, was murdered in his [[Waterloo, Iowa]], apartment by an assailant, Joseph Lawrence, who claimed [[Jason Gage|Gage]] had made sexual advance to him. Gage was [[bludgeon]]ed to death with a bottle, and stabbed in the neck, probably post-mortem, with a shard of glass.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.wcfcourier.com/articles/2005/03/31/news/metro/dc7e7d835fa746af86256fd5004ca40a.txt]&lt;/ref&gt; Lawrence was sentenced to fifty years in prison.
* On February 2, 2006, 18-year-old [[Jacob D. Robida]] entered a bar in [[New Bedford, Massachusetts]], confirmed that it was a [[gay bar]], and then attacked patrons with a hatchet and a handgun, wounding three.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.cnn.com/2006/US/02/02/gay.shooting/index.html CNN.com - Man, 18, sought after gun, hatchet attack at gay bar] - Feb 2, 2006&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; He fatally shot himself three days later.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.boston.com/news/local/massachusetts/articles/2006/02/07/autopsy_robida_shot_himself]&lt;/ref&gt;
* On June 10, 2006, [[Kevin Aviance]], a female impressionist, musician, and fashion designer, was robbed and beaten in [[Manhattan]] by a group of men who yelled anti-gay slurs at him. Four assailants pleaded guilty and received prison sentences.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.usatoday.com/life/people/2006-06-11-singer-hate-crime_x.htm]&lt;/ref&gt;
* On July 30, 2006, six men were attacked with [[baseball bat]]s and knives after leaving the [[San Diego, California]] [[Gay Pride]] festival. One victim was injured so severely that he had to undergo extensive facial reconstructive surgery. Three men pleaded guilty in connection with the attacks and received prison sentences. A 15-year-old juvenile also pleaded guilty.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.sfbaytimes.com/index.php?article_id=5335&amp;sec=article]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sgn.org/sgnnews34_39/page4.cfm]&lt;/ref&gt;
* On August 18, 2006, an [[2006 Greenwich Village assault case|altercation]] occurred in Manhattan between a man and seven black lesbians from Newark, New Jersey. During the altercation, the man was stabbed. The women claim that they acted in self-defense after he screamed homophobic epithets, spit on them, and pulled one of their weaves off,&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/14/nyregion/14assault.html?ex=1177128000&amp;en=a1ea123367fd1a57&amp;ei=5099&amp;partner=TOPIXNEWS|title=Woman in Gang Assault Trial Says Man Started the Fight|last=Hartocollis|first=Anemona|date=2007-04-14|publisher=New York Times|accessdate=2009-03-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; while he has described the attack as "a hate crime against a straight man."&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|url=http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/19233888/|title=Four women sentenced over attack on man|last=Associated Press|date=2007-06-15|publisher=MSNBC|accessdate=2009-01-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
* On October 8, 2006, [[Michael Sandy]] was attacked by four young [[heterosexual]] men who lured him into meeting after chatting online, while they were looking for gay men to rob. He was struck by a car while trying to escape his attackers, and died five days later without regaining consciousness.&lt;ref name="NYT1121"&gt;{{Citation | first=Michael | last=Brick | coauthors= | title=Three Sentenced in Death of Gay Man | date=2007-11-21 | publisher= The New York Times| url =http://www.nytimes.com/2007/11/21/nyregion/21plumb.html | work = | pages = | accessdate = 2007-11-21 | language = }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="DAILYNEWS1121"&gt;{{Citation | first=Scott | last=Shifrel | coauthors= | title=Three who killed Michael Sandy get near-maximum sentence for hate crime | date=2007-11-21 | publisher= The Daily News| url =http://www.nydailynews.com/news/ny_crime/2007/11/21/2007-11-21_three_who_killed_michael_sandy_get_nearm-2.html | work = | pages = | accessdate = 2007-11-21 | language = }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* On February 27, 2007 in [[Detroit, Michigan]] Andrew Anthos, a 72-year-old disabled gay man was beaten with a lead pipe by a man who was shouting anti-gay names at him. Anthos died 10 days later in the hospital.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.advocate.com/news_detail_ektid42467.asp]&lt;/ref&gt;
* On March 15, 2007 in [[Wahneta, Florida]], Ryan Keith Skipper, a 25 year old gay man was stabbed to death. Four suspects were arrested for the crime. The Sheriff is calling it a hate crime.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.theledger.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20070329/NEWS/703290493/0/FRONTPAGE]&lt;/ref&gt;
* On May 12, 2007, [[Roberto Duncanson]] was murdered in [[Brooklyn, New York]].  He was stabbed to death by Omar Willock, who claimed Duncanson had flirted with him.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.365gay.com/news/murderer-of-gay-man-not-to-be-charged-with-hate-crime/]&lt;/ref&gt;
*May 16, 2007, Sean William Kennedy, 20, was walking to his car from Brew's Bar in [[Greenville, SC]] when Andrew Moller, 18, got out of another car and approached Kennedy. Investigators said that Moller made a comment about Kennedy's sexual orientation, and threw a fatal punch because he didn't like the other man's sexual preference.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.wyff4.com/news/13345546/detail.html Deputies: Man Punched, Killed Because He Was Gay - Greenville News Story - WYFF Greenville&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
* On December 8, 2007 25 year old gay man Nathaniel Salerno was attacked by four men on a Metro train in [[Washington, DC]]. The men called him faggot while they beat him.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.washblade.com/2007/12-14/news/localnews/11725.cfm]&lt;/ref&gt;
* In February 2008, Duanna Johnson, a transsexual woman, was beaten by a police officer while she was held in the Shelby County Criminal Justice Center in Tennessee. Johnson said the officers reportedly called her a “faggot” and “he-she,” before and during the incident.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.kctv5.com/news/16654585/detail.html Transsexual Beaten; Officer Fired - Kansas City News Story - KCTV Kansas City&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.365gay.com/Newscon08/06/061808memph.htm]&lt;/ref&gt; In November 2008, she was found dead in the street, reportedly gunned down by three unknown individuals.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.myeyewitnessnews.com/news/local/story.aspx?content_id=f3bb7d09-2602-4c9f-a033-2b9f8fca3018 Homicide Victim Identified as Transgendered Person, Duanna Johnson]&lt;/ref&gt;
* On February 12, 2008, [[Lawrence "Larry" King]], a 15 year old junior highschool student was shot twice by a classmate at E.O. Green School in [[Oxnard, California]]. He was taken off life support after doctors declared him [[Brain death|brain dead]] on February 15.&lt;ref name="Newsweek"&gt;{{Citation | last = Setoodeh | first = Ramin | title = Young, Gay and Murdered | url = http://www.newsweek.com/id/147790&amp;GT1=43002 | publisher = ''Newsweek'' | date = 2008-07-19 | accessdate = 2008-07-23 }}&lt;/ref&gt; According to [[Associated Press]] reports, ''"prosecutors have charged a 14-year-old classmate with premeditated murder with hate-crime and firearm-use enhancements"''.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.ebar.com/news/article.php?sec=news&amp;article=2715 The Bay Area Reporter] Online | Breaking news: &lt;br&gt;Vigil Tues. for slain Oxnard teen&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.ksby.com/Global/story.asp?S=7881176 KSBY 6 Action News, Weather, Sports: Covering California's Central Coast | Organs harvested from Oxnard school shooting victim&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.venturacountystar.com/news/2008/feb/15/no-headline---na1fcvictimfamily15/ Victim's family members say they will donate teen's organs : Oxnard : Ventura County Star&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
* In [[Rochester, New York]] on March 16, 2008 police say Lance Neve was beaten unconscious because Neve was gay. A man attacked Neve at a bar leaving him with a fractured skull, and a broken nose.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.whec.com/article/stories/S379266.shtml?cat=566]&lt;/ref&gt; Jesse Parsons was sentenced to more than five years in prison for the assault.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.whec.com/article/stories/S556593.shtml&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://rnews.com/story_2004.cfm?story_type=2&amp;rnews_story_type=18&amp;id=67981&lt;/ref&gt;
* In [[Baltimore County, Maryland]] on May 29, 2008 eighteen year old Steven Parrish—a member of the Young Swans subgroup of the [[Bloods (gang)|Bloods]]—was murdered by Steven T. Hollis III and Juan L. Flythe after they found "gay messages" on his cell phone. They felt having a gay member would make their gang appear weak and that by killing Parrish they could prevent that perception.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.baltimoresun.com/news/local/baltimore_county/bal-md.co.gang19aug19,0,6897709.story?track=rss]&lt;/ref&gt;
* 17 July 2008, In Colorado, 18 year old [[Angie Zapata]], a trans woman, was beaten to death two days after meeting Allen Ray Andrade. The case was prosecuted as a hate crime, and Andrade was found guilty of first degree murder on April 22 2009.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.greeleytribune.com/article/20090423/NEWS/904229934/1002/NONE&amp;parentprofile=1001]&lt;/ref&gt;
* September 7, 2008 - Tony Randolph Hunter, 27, and his partner were attacked and beaten near a gay bar in [[Washington DC]]. Hunter later died from his injuries on September 18. Police are investigating it as a possible hate crime.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.metroweekly.com/gauge/?ak=3787]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.washingtonblade.com/blog/index.cfm?blog_id=21104]&lt;/ref&gt;
* September 13, 2008 in [[Denver, Colorado]] 26 year old Nima Daivari was attacked by a man who called him faggot. The police that arrived on the scene refused to make a report of the attack.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.denverpost.com/news/ci_10459273]&lt;/ref&gt;
* September 15, 2008 - A [[Bourbonnais, Illinois]] [[elementary school]] [[bus driver]] was charged with leading a homophobic attack on a 10-year old student passenger. The boy was taunted by the driver who then encouraged other students to [[chase]] and [[beat]] the child.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.365gay.com/news/school-bus-driver-charged-in-homophobic-attack-on-student/]&lt;/ref&gt;
* On November 7, 2008 in Newton, NC the home of openly gay Melvin Whistlehunt was destroyed by arsonists. Investigators found homophobic graffiti spray painted on the back of the house.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.observernewsonline.com/content/view/73644/1/]&lt;/ref&gt;
* On November 14, 2008, a 22 year old transgender woman, Lateisha Green, was shot and killed by Dwight DeLee in [[Syracuse, New York|Syracuse]], [[NY]] because he thought she was gay.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.californiachronicle.com/articles/82102]&lt;/ref&gt; Local news media reported the incident with her legal name, Moses "Teish" Cannon.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.syracuse.com/news/index.ssf/2008/11/syracuse_man_was_killed_for_be.html]&lt;/ref&gt;  DeLee was convicted of first-degree manslaughter as a hate crime on July 17, 2009 and received the maximum sentence of 25 years in state prison.  This was only the second time in the nation’s history that a person was prosecuted for a hate crime against a transgender person and the first hate crime conviction in New York state.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.advocate.com/news_detail_ektid99146.asp]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.advocate.com/News/Daily_News/2009/08/18/Lateisha_Green_Murderer_Sentenced]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.syracuse.com/news/index.ssf/2009/08/dwight_delee_to_be_sentenced_i.html]&lt;/ref&gt;
* On December 7, 2008 Romel Sucuzhanya, a 31 year old straight [[Ecuador]]ean and his brother Jose, were attacked on a [[Brooklyn]], [[New York City|New York]] street for appearing to be gay and for being [[Latino]]; they were walking arm-in-arm, which is normal for brothers in their culture. Romel later died from his injuries.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.pridedepot.com/modules/wordpress/?tag=romel-sucuzhanya]&lt;/ref&gt;
* On December 12, 2008 in [[Richmond, California]] a 28 year old lesbian was kidnapped and gang raped by four men who made homophobic remarks during the attack.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.365gay.com/news/4-sought-in-gang-rape-of-lesbian/]&lt;/ref&gt;
* On December 27, 2008 in [[Dayton, Ohio]] 24 year old Nathan Runkle was brutally assaulted outside a gay nightclub.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.huffingtonpost.com/mikko-alanne/a-hate-crime-you-wont-see_b_155665.html]&lt;/ref&gt;
* On February 15, 2009 in [[New York City]] Efosa Agbontaen and Branden McGillvery-Dummett were attacked by four young men with glass bottles and box cutters who used anti-gay slurs during the attack. Agbontaen and McGillvery-Dummett both required emergency room treatment for their injuries.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.advocate.com/exclusive_detail_ektid73933.asp]&lt;/ref&gt;
* On February 18, 2009 two men were arrested in [[Stroudsburg, PA]] for the stabbing death of gay veteran Michael Goucher.&lt;ref&gt; [http://regator.com/p/134567831/second_man_arrested_in_murder_of_gay_pennsylvania/]&lt;/ref&gt;
* On March 1, 2009 in [[Galveston, Texas]] three men entered Roberts Lafitte bar and attacked patrons with rocks. One of the victims, Marc Bosaw, was sent to the emergency room to have twelve staples in his head.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.chron.com/disp/story.mpl/ap/tx/6291167.html]&lt;/ref&gt;
* On March 14, 2009 a gay couple leaving a concert in [[Newark, New Jersey]] were attacked by 15 teens. Josh Kehoe and Bobby Daniel Caldwell were called "faggots" and beaten. Caldwell suffered a broken jaw.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.nj.com/news/index.ssf/2009/03/gay_couple_claim_that_brtiney.html]&lt;/ref&gt;
* On March 23, 2009 in [[Seaside, Oregon]] two gay men were attacked and left lying unconscious on a local beach. The men regained consciousness and were treated at a nearby hospital.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.365gay.com/news/gay-men-attacked-on-ore-beach/]&lt;/ref&gt;
* On April 6, 2009, Carl Joseph Walker-Hoover, an 11 year old child in [[Springfield, Massachusetts]], hung themself with an extension cord after being bullied all school year by peers who said "he acted feminine" and was gay.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.thebostonchannel.com/cnn-news/19141470/detail.html]&lt;/ref&gt;
* On April 11, 2009 a gay man in [[Gloucester, Massachusetts]] was attacked and beaten by as many as six people outside a bar. Justin Goodwin, 36, of Salem suffered a shattered jaw, broken eye socket, broken nose and broken cheek bone.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.365gay.com/news/brothers-charged-in-gay-mans-brutal-beating]&lt;/ref&gt;
* On June 30, 2009, Seaman [[August Provost]] was found shot to death and his body burned at his guard post on [[Camp Pendleton]]. LGBT community leaders "citing military sources initially said that Provost’s death was a [[hate crime]]."&lt;ref name=GLTP&gt; [http://www.gaylesbiantimes.com/?id=15098 GLBT community honors life of murdered seaman: Veterans use tragic death as rallying cry against ‘DADT’] Rick Braatz, Gay and Lesbian Times; 16 July 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; Provost had been harassed because of his sexual orientation.&lt;ref name=GLTP/&gt; Military leaders have since explained that "whatever the investigation concludes, the military’s “[[Don’t Ask, Don’t Tell]]” policy prevented Provost from seeking help."&lt;ref name=GLTP/&gt; Family and friends believe he was murdered because he was openly gay; the killer committed suicide a week later after admitting the murder, the Navy have not concluded if this was a hate crime.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.sandiego6.com/news/local/story/Suspect-in-Camp-Pendleton-murder-suicide-Campos/IQBbCHMiw02AFACT2PkbeA.cspx]&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Anti-gay slogan]]
* [[Biphobia]]
* [[Gay bashing]]
* [[Gay panic defense]]
* [[Hate crime]]
* [[Hate speech]]
* [[Heterosexism]]
* [[Lesbophobia]]
* [[Murder Music]]
* [[Pink Pistols]]
* [[Transphobia]]
* [[List of unlawfully killed transgender people]]

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
* Barry Yeoman, [http://www.barryyeoman.com/articles/murderonmountain.html Murder on the Mountain, ''Out'' Magazine]
* Gay Bashings In Schools- [http://365gay.com/Newscon06/04/042606schools.htm A survey released in 2006 shows that gay teens still experience homophobic attacks in their schools]
* [http://www.queeria.com/aktivizam.aspx?id=3218 Pictures from Belgrade (Serbian) Pride Parade] 30 June 2001

{{LGBT |social=expanded}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Violence Against Lgbt People}}
[[Category:Homophobic violence| ]]
[[Category:LGBT rights]]
[[Category:Sexual orientation and society]]
[[Category:Transgender]]
[[Category:Victims of anti-LGBT hate crimes| ]]

[[de:Antischwule Gewalt]]
[[it:Violenza contro le persone LGBT]]
[[nl:Potenrammen]]
[[ru:Преследование гомосексуалистов, лесбиянок, бисексуалов и транссексуалов]]
[[vi:Bạo lực LGBT]]
[[zh:同性戀、雙性戀與跨性別迫害]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>