<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20021012193348|353415" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="43797" pageid="43797" ns="0" title="Violence against LGBTQ people"><revisions><rev timestamp="2002-10-12T19:34:28Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Gay-bashing''' is literally the practice of attacking, usually beating up, a person believed to be homosexual, because of their [[homosexuality]] (see [[hate crime]]).

When directed towards other [[Queer]] people, hatred assaults can be called Queer-bashing or simply bashing.

Some notable Queer victims of hatred assaults include:

* [[Harvey Milk]]
* [[Matthew Shepard]]
* [[Brandon Teena]]
* [[Bertrand Delanoe|Bertrand Delano&amp;euml;]]

The term is often used in the metaphorical sense of denigrating homosexual people or opposing homosexual practices (see [[hate speech]]).

Gay-bashing is often committed against heterosexuals who are only ''perceived'' to be gay. Two prominent incidents:

* Actor and comedian [[Norm McDonald]] (of [[Saturday Night Live]]) was attacked by two men in [[New York City]]. They thought he was homosexual because he was well dressed, with styled hair, and lanky; he was walking through [[Greenwich Village]], an [[gay village|area popular amongst homosexuals]]. He suffered a concussion.
* A man was shot to death in an Iowa bar because he was standing quietly in a corner holding a purse. He was perceived as an unwelcome homosexual; in actuality, he was holding the purse for his wife, who was in the restroom.</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>