<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20031027085816|1632829" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="43797" pageid="43797" ns="0" title="Violence against LGBTQ people"><revisions><rev timestamp="2003-10-27T09:01:25Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[fr:Agression homophobe]][[zh:%E5%90%8C%E6%80%A7%E6%81%8B%E6%89%93%E5%8E%8B]]

'''Gay-bashing''' is the practice of attacking a person, usually physically, because they are or are perceived to be [[gay]], [[lesbian]], [[bisexual]], or [[transgender]]ed.

Although gay-bashing is often thought of relating to gay men, all [[Queer]] groups - including gay men, [[lesbian]]s, [[bisexual]]s and [[transgender]]ed people - can be targeted. The term can be modified into dyke-bashing, trans-bashing, Queer-bashing, or simply bashing. 

Bashing can include uttering threats, physical [[assault]] and [[battery (crime)|battery]], [[sexual assault]] and [[rape]], [[torture]], [[attempted murder]], and [[murder]]. In some districts, bashing may be treated legally as a [[hate crime]].

Some notable Queer victims of hatred assaults include:

* [[Harvey Milk]], gay [[politician]] ([[1930]] - [[1978]])
* [[Brandon Teena]], female-to-male [[transsexual]] ([[1972]] - [[1993]])
* [[Matthew Shepard]], gay [[student]] ([[1976]] - [[1998]])
* [[Bertrand Delanoe|Bertrand Delano&amp;euml;]], gay [[politician]] (stabbed nonfatally in [[2002]])
* [[Gwen Araujo]], male-to-female [[transsexual]] ([[1985]] - [[2002]])

A unique but tragic example of gay-bashing occurred on [[September 22]], [[2001]]. Ronald Gay entered a gay bar in [[Roanoke, Virginia]], opened fire on the patrons, killing Danny Overstreet and injuring six others. Ronald said he was angry over what his name now meant, and deeply upset that three of his sons had changed their surname. He claimed that had been told by [[God]] to find and kill homosexuals, describing himself as a "[[Christian]] Soldier working for my Lord".

The term "gay-bashing" is often taken to include, in addition to random assaults, attacks on gay people who made sexual overtures to attackers, with the argument being that such a disproportionate response must be occasioned by [[homophobia]] on the part of the assaulter. See [[gay panic defense]]. 

The term is often used in the metaphorical sense of denigrating homosexual people or opposing homosexual practices (see [[hate speech]]).

Gay-bashing is occasionally committed against heterosexuals who are only ''perceived'' to be gay. Two prominent incidents include:

* Actor and comedian [[Norm MacDonald]] (of [[Saturday Night Live]]) was attacked by two men in [[New York City]]. They thought he was homosexual because he was well dressed, with styled hair, and lanky; he was walking through [[Greenwich Village]], an [[gay village|area popular amongst homosexuals]]. He suffered a concussion.
* A man was shot to death in an [[Iowa]] bar because he was standing quietly in a corner holding a purse. He was perceived as an unwelcome homosexual; in actuality, he was holding the purse for his wife, who was in the restroom.

Gay-bashing as a practice may be on the decline as homosexuality eases into the protection of [[political correctness]], but to those it affects it is still a fearful and factual phenomenom born from their society's [[intolerance]].</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>