<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20071101165013|168535685" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="43797" pageid="43797" ns="0" title="Violence against LGBTQ people"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-11-04T20:07:10Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{LGBT}}
'''[[Violence]] against LGBT people, queer identifying and the same-sex attracted''' are [[hate crimes]] which may occur either at the hands of individuals or groups, or as part of governmental enforcement of laws targeting people who are perceived to violate [[Heteronormativity|heteronormative]] rules and who contravene protocols of [[gender role]]s. People who are mistakenly perceived to be LGBT may also be targeted.

Violence targeted at people because of their perceived sexuality may include threats, physical [[assault]], [[battery (crime)|battery]], [[sexual assault]], [[rape]], [[torture]], [[attempted murder]] and [[murder]]. These actions may be caused by cultural, [[religion and sexual orientation|religious]], or political [[mores]] and [[homophobia|biases]], though the extent to which these groups influence violence against lesbian, gay and bisexual individuals is debated.

In the [[United States]], the [[Federal Bureau of Investigation|FBI]] reported that 15.6% of hate crimes reported to police in 2004 were founded on perceived [[sexual orientation]]. 61% of these attacks were against gay men, 14% against lesbians, 2% against heterosexuals and 1% against bisexuals, while attacks against GLBT people at large made up 20%.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.fbi.gov/ucr/cius_04/offenses_reported/hate_crime/index.html&lt;/ref&gt; Violence based on perceived gender identity was not recorded in the report.

==State-sponsored violence==
{{main|Homosexuality laws of the world}}
Throughout [[recorded History]], homosexual activity has been repressed by certain governing bodies and members of society under pains of mutilation, death and [[social ostracism]]. Such laws and codes (in English-speaking societies, usually describing male homosexuality as ''[[buggery]]'' or ''[[sodomy]]''), were in force in [[Europe]] from the fifth to the twentieth centuries, and in Muslim countries from the beginning of the Muslim era up to and including the present day. Among the states that have historically punished homosexuality with death are:

*[[Abbasid]] [[Baghdad]] under the Caliph [[Al-Hadi]] (785-786)
* The [[Florence|City of Florence]] during the [[Middle Ages]] and the [[Renaissance]]
** Illustrative victims: [[Giovanni di Giovanni]] ([[1350]] &amp;ndash; [[1365]]?), [[Florence|Florentine]] boy, castrated and "burned between the thighs with a red-hot iron" by court order;
* The [[Swiss]] [[canton of Zürich]] in the [[Renaissance]]
** Illustrative victims: Knight von Hohenberg d. [[1482]], [[Swiss]] knight, burned at the stake together with his lover, his young squire;[[Image:Burning of Sodomites.jpg|thumb|250px|right|The knight von Hohenberg and his squire, being burned at the stake for sodomy, Zurich 1482 (Zurich Central Library)]]
* The kingdom of [[France]] during the [[Middle Ages]] and the [[Renaissance]]
** Illustrative victims: [[Jacques Chausson]] ([[1618]] &amp;ndash; [[1661]]), [[France|French]] minor writer, burned alive for attempting to seduce the son of a nobleman;
* [[England]] from from 1533 until [[1861]]; see [[Buggery Act 1533]]
* [[Nazi Germany]]; see [[History of homosexual people in Nazi Germany and the Holocaust]]
* [[Afghanistan]] under the rule of the [[Taliban]] (1996-2001)

Present-day countries where homosexuality is still punishable by death:
* [[Iran]]
* [[Mauritania]]
* [[Nigeria]]
* [[Pakistan]]
* [[Saudi Arabia]]
* [[Sudan]]
* [[Yemen]]

== Extralegal violence ==
{{proseline}}
Private citizens have at times taken extralegal action to repress those alleged to manifest variant sexual behavior.  In some jurisdictions in the [[United States]], these acts may be legally classified as [[hate crime]]s, which increases the resulting penalty if convicted.
[[Image:harvey milk.jpg|thumb|right|'''[[Harvey Milk]] ([[1930]]-[[1978]])'''&lt;br&gt;American politician and gay-rights activist, [[assassinate]]d by [[Dan White]].]]  Sometimes, people have been the target of anti-LGBT violence because they were perceived to be LGBT, whether they were or not.
Some notable acts of violence alleged or proven to have been inspired by hatred of their LGBT victims include:
* [[Tennessee Williams]] was the victim of an assault in January 1979 in [[Key West]], being beaten by five teenage boys.  He escaped serious injury.  The episode was part of a spate of anti-gay violence inspired by an anti-gay newspaper ad run by a local [[Baptist]] minister.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation
  | title = Key West: The Last Resort
  | newspaper = Time Magazine
  | date = February 19, 1979
  | url = http://www.time.com/time/printout/0,8816,912357,00.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* On [[May 13]], [[1988]], [[Rebecca Wight]] was killed when she and her partner, [[Claudia Brenner]], were shot by Stephen Roy Carr while hiking and camping along the [[Appalachian Trail]]. Carr later claimed that he became enraged by the couple's [[lesbianism]] when he saw them having sex.  Carr claimed the woman taunted him by having sex in front of him.
* The fatal stabbing of [[James Zappalorti]], a gay [[Vietnam]] veteran ([[1945]] &amp;ndash;  [[1990]])
* The rape and later murder of [[Brandon Teena]], a [[transsexual]] man ([[1972]] &amp;ndash;  [[1993]]).  The events leading to Mr. Teena's death were made into the movie ''[[Boys Don't Cry (film)|Boys Don't Cry]]''.
* The murders of [[Roxanne Ellis]] and [[Michelle Abdill]], a [[lesbian]] couple in [[Medford, Oregon]] in [[1995]], by a man who said he thought their "lifestyle" was "sick."
* The bombing of the Otherside Lounge, a lesbian nightclub in Atlanta, by [[Eric Robert Rudolph]], the "[[Centennial Olympic Park bombing|Olympic Park]] Bomber," on February 21, 1997; five bar patrons were injured.
* The death by beating and exposure of [[Matthew Shepard]], a gay [[student]] ([[1976]] &amp;ndash;  [[1998]])
* The murder of Pfc [[Barry Winchell]] on July 6, 1999. He was dating [[Calpernia Addams]], a transgendered author.
* The bombing of the [[Admiral Duncan pub]] by [[David Copeland]] in [[1999]]
[[Image:Atherton, John (1598-1640) &amp; Childe, John (16 -1640) - 1641.jpg|thumb|250px|[[John Atherton]], Bishop of Waterford and Lismore, was hanged for [[sodomy]] under a law that he had helped to institute. His lover was John Childe, his steward and tithe proctor, also hanged. Anonymous pamphlet, 1641.]]
* The [[July 1]], [[1999]], murders of gay couple [[Gary Matson]] and [[Winfield Mowder]] by [[white supremacist]] brothers Matthew and Tyler Williams. Matthew Williams claimed that by killing the couple he was following "obeying the law of God," because he believed [[homosexuality]] violated God's laws. Williams said he hoped his actions would inspire further violence against [[homosexual]]s and ethnic minorities.
* The murder of [[Steen Fenrich]] by his stepfather, in September [[1999]]. His dismembered remains were found in March [[2001]], with the phrase "gay nigger number one" scrawled on his skull along with his social security number.
* The murder of [[Arthur Warren|Arthur "J.R." Warren]] by three teenage boys on [[July 3]], [[2000]], who believed Warren spread a rumor that he and one of the boys had a sexual relationship. Warren's killers ran over his body to disguise the murder as a [[hit-and-run]]. 
* The gang-rape and murder of [[Fannyann Eddy]] in 2004, shortly after giving a speech about the threats of violence faced by lesbians and gays in Sierra Leone.
* The fatal beating of supposedly gay teenager [[Jeff Whittington]] in [[Wellington]], [[New Zealand]] on [[May 8]], [[1999]].
* One notorious incident of gay-bashing occurred on [[September 22]], [[2000]]. Ronald Gay entered a gay bar in [[Roanoke, Virginia]] and opened fire on the patrons, killing [[Danny Overstreet]] and injuring six others. Ronald said he was angry over what his name now meant, and deeply upset that three of his sons had changed their surname. He claimed that he had been told by [[God]] to find and kill lesbians and gay men, describing himself as a "Christian Soldier working for my Lord".&lt;ref&gt;http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/americas/942255.stm&lt;/ref&gt;
* The 2002 homicide of [[Nizah Morris]], a [[transgender]] in [[Philadelphia|Philadelphia, Pennsylvania]], and the mishandling of the case by the [[Philadelphia Police Department]].
* The non-fatal stabbing of [[Bertrand Delanoë]], a gay [[politician]], Mayor of Paris, France, in [[2002]]
* The killing of [[Gwen Araujo]], a [[transsexual]] woman ([[1985]] &amp;ndash;  [[2002]]).  Michael Magidson, Jaron Nabors, and José Merél were charged with the murder as a hate crime, with Jason Cazares charged as an accomplice.  Nabors made a deal with prosecution, receiving a manslaughter conviction in exchange for testimony, but his testimony was largely considered unreliable.  The jury hung on Cazares, who then pled guilty to voluntary manslaughter to avoid a retrial.  Magidson and Merél were convicted of second-degree murder, but the hate crime enhancement was not accepted by the jury.
* The killing of [[Paul Broussard]], a Houston-area banker (1968-1991)
* The beating death of [[Charlie Howard (murder victim)|Charlie Howard]] in [[Bangor, Maine]] in [[1984]].
* [[Aaron Webster]], a gay man in [[Vancouver, British Columbia]], was beaten to death in [[Stanley Park]] in [[2001]].
* On June 30, 2001, [http://www.queeria.com/aktivizam.aspx?id=3218 hundreds of soccer hooligans] attacked participants of the first Serbian Pride Parade in Belgrade.
* On [[June 17]], [[2003]], [[Guin Richie Phillips|Richie Phillips]] was murdered by Joseph Cottrell. His body was later found in a suitcase, in [[Rough River Lake]]. During his trial, Cottrell's relatives testified that he lured Phillips to his death, and killed him because he was gay.
* On [[July 23]], [[2003]], [[Nireah Johnson]] and Brandie Coleman were murdered by Paul Moore, when Moore learned after a sexual encounter that Johnson was [[transgender]].
* On [[July 31]], [[2003]], 37-year-old [[Glenn Kopitske]] was killed by 17-year-old Gary Hirte. Hirte pleaded insanity, claiming he killed [[Glenn Kopitske|Kopitske]] in a murderous rage after a consensual sexual encounter with the victim, because he felt a [[homosexual]] act was "worse than murder."
* On [[January 28]], [[2005]], [[Ronnie Paris]], a three-year-old African American child died due to brain injuries resulting from abuse by his father. According to his mother and other relatives, Ronnie Paris, Jr., would slam his son into walls and force him to "slap-box" because he was concerned the child was [[gay]] and feared his son would grow up a [[sissy]].
* On [[March 11]], [[2005]], [[Jason Gage]] -- an openly [[gay]] man -- was murdered in his [[Waterloo, Iowa]] apartment by an assailant who claimed [[Jason Gage|Gage]] had made advances and was killed when he fought with the victim. The district attorney in the case noted neither the victim or the perpetrator, or the apartment bore any signs of struggle. Gage was [[bludgeon]]ed to death with a bottle, and stabbed in the neck with a shard of glass.
* On June 30, 2005, Yishai Shlisel, a [[Haredi Judaism|Haredi Jew]] stabbed three marchers in a [[gay pride]] parade in [[Jerusalem]], [[Israel]], claiming he acted on behalf of God.&lt;ref&gt;http://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Israeli_man_faces_attempted_murder_charges_for_stabbing_three_gay_pride_marchers&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Jody Dobrowski]], murdered in [[2005]] in [[London]].
* On [[February 2]], [[2006]], 18 year-old [[Jacob D. Robida]] entered a bar in [[New Bedford, Massachusetts]], confirmed that it was a [[gay bar]], and then attacked patrons with a gun and a hatchet, wounding at least three.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.cnn.com/2006/US/02/02/gay.shooting/index.html&lt;/ref&gt;
*On [[April 6]], [[2006]], two American television producers, [[CBS Evening News]] senior producer Richard Jefferson and [[48 Hours]] producer-researcher Ryan Smith, were beaten with a tire iron outside the Sunset Beach Bar on the [[Caribbean]] island of [[St. Maarten]] by a group of four men and two women.  The attack left Smith unable to speak properly, having suffered a skull fracture and brain damage.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.sfbaytimes.com/index.php?sec=article&amp;article_id=4911&lt;/ref&gt;
* On [[July 30]], [[2006]], six men were brutally beaten after leaving the [[San Diego, California]] [[Gay Pride]] festival. One of the gay men was beaten so badly that he had to undergo extensive facial reconstructive surgery. All but one of the attackers were adults the exception being a 15-year-old.  The attackers were charged with [[hate crimes]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.signonsandiego.com/news/metro/20060921-1257-bn21attacks2.html&amp;cid=0&amp;sig2=5j6BFSRc0TOf8Nsuf9cy4w&lt;/ref&gt;
* On [[October 8]], [[2006]], [[Michael Sandy]] was attacked by four [[heterosexual]] young men who lured him into meeting after chatting with him online, while they were looking for gay men to rob. Sandy was hit by a car while trying to escape his attackers. He died five days later, never having regained consciousness.
* On [[May 12]], [[2007]], [[Roberto Duncanson]] was murdered in [[Brooklyn, New York]].  He was stabbed to death by Omar Willock, who claimed Duncanson had flirted with him.
*On [[July 7]], [[2007]], 30 participants at a gay pride event in [[Croatia]] were attacked by multiple assailants. The attackers had also prepared molotov cocktails but were stopped by the police before using them. Many people taking part in Gay Pride marches in Eastern Europe (e.g: [[Romania]], [[Russia]], [[Serbia]]) have been beaten after leaving the marches.{{Fact|date=September 2007}}
*[[May 16]],[[2007]], Sean William Kennedy 20, was walking to his car from Brew's Bar in [[Greenville, SC]] when Andrew Moller, 18 got out of another car and approached Kennedy. Investigators said that Moller made a comment about Kennedy's sexual orientation, and threw a fatal punch because he didn't like another man's sexual preference.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.wyff4.com/news/13345546/detail.html&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{gay rights}}

* [[Pink Pistols]]
* [[Heterosexism]]
* [[Homophobia]]
* [[Lesbophobia]]
* [[Biphobia]]
* [[Transphobia]]
* [[Gay panic defense]]
* [[Hate speech]]
* [[Anti-gay slogan]]
* [[Murder Music]]
* [[Hate crime]]

==References==
&lt;div class="references-small"&gt;&lt;references/&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

== External links==
* [http://www.rememberingourdead.org Remembering our Dead], a site which memorializes transgender victims of violence.
* Barry Yeoman, [http://www.barryyeoman.com/articles/murderonmountain.html Murder on the Mountain, ''Out'' Magazine]
* Gay Bashings In Schools- [http://365gay.com/Newscon06/04/042606schools.htm A survey released in 2006 shows that gay teens still experience homophobic attacks in their schools]
* [http://www.queeria.com/aktivizam.aspx?id=3218 Pictures from Belgrade (Serbian) Pride Parade] 30 June 2001
*Rictor Norton (Ed.), [http://www.infodpt.demon.co.uk/eighteen.htm Homosexuality in Eighteenth-Century England: A Sourcebook.] Updated 29 April 2007.

[[Category:LGBT civil rights]]
[[Category:Transgender]]
[[Category:Sexual orientation and society]]
[[Category:Homophobic violence]]

[[de:Antischwule Gewalt]]
[[fr:Aggression homophobe]]
[[nl:Potenrammen]]
[[ru:Преследование гомосексуалистов, лесбиянок, бисексуалов и транссексуалов]]
[[zh:同性戀、雙性戀與跨性別迫害]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>