<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20041011221934|7045610" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="43797" pageid="43797" ns="0" title="Violence against LGBTQ people"><revisions><rev timestamp="2004-11-02T01:55:25Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">The '''persecution of gays, lesbians, bisexuals,  and [[transgender]]ed''' individuals is the practice of [[persecution|persecuting]] a person, usually through physical attack, because they are or are perceived to be [[gay]], [[lesbian]], [[bisexual]], or [[transgender]]ed. In some circumstances, this is referred to as "'''gay-bashing'''", but it is somewhat a misnomer &amp;mdash; all [[Queer]] groups, including gay men, [[lesbian]]s, [[bisexual]]s and [[transgender]]ed people &amp;mdash; can be targeted. The term "gay-bashing" is rarely modified into '''dyke-bashing''', '''trans-bashing''', '''queer-bashing''', or simply '''bashing'''. 

Bashing can include uttering threats, physical [[assault]] and [[battery (crime)|battery]], [[sexual assault]] and [[rape]], [[torture]], [[attempted murder]], and [[murder]]. In some districts, bashing may be treated legally as a [[hate crime]]. Bashing also includes attacks on gay people who may have made sexual overtures to their attackers, with the argument being that such a disproportionate response must be occasioned by [[homophobia]] on the part of the assaulter. The term is often used in the metaphorical or exaggerative sense of criticising or denigrating homosexual people ''per se'' or opposing homosexual practices. (See also [[gay panic defense]], [[hate speech]] in these instances)

==Instances==
Some notable victims of hate-related assaults include:

* [[Harvey Milk]], gay [[politician]] ([[1930]] &amp;ndash; [[1978]])
* [[James Zappalorti]], gay [[Vietnam]] veteran ([[1945]] &amp;ndash;  [[1990]])
* [[Brandon Teena]], [[transsexual]] man ([[1972]] &amp;ndash;  [[1993]])
* [[Matthew Shepard]], gay [[student]] ([[1976]] &amp;ndash;  [[1998]])
* Patrons of the [[Admiral Duncan pub]], bombed by [[David Copeland]] in [[1999]]
* [[Bertrand Delano&amp;euml;]], gay [[politician]] (stabbed nonfatally in [[2002]])
* [[Gwen Araujo]], [[transsexual]] woman ([[1985]] &amp;ndash;  [[2002]])

A tragic example of gay-bashing occurred on [[September 22]], [[2000]]. Ronald Gay entered a gay bar in [[Roanoke, Virginia]] and opened fire on the patrons, killing [[Danny Overstreet]] and injuring six others. Ronald said he was angry over what his name now meant, and deeply upset that three of his sons had changed their surname. He claimed that he had been told by [[God]] to find and kill homosexuals, describing himself as a "Christian Soldier working for my Lord". [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/americas/942255.stm]

[[Tennessee Williams]] was the victim of a gay-bashing in January 1979 in [[Key West]], being beaten by five teenaged boys, but he was not seriously injured. The episode was part of a spate of anti-gay violence that had occurred after a local [[Baptist]] minister ran an anti-gay newspaper ad. Some of his literary critics spoke ill of the "excesses" present in his work, but these were, for the most part, merely attacks on Williams' sexuality.

Gay-bashing is occasionally committed against heterosexuals who are only ''perceived'' to be gay. Prominent incidents include:

* Actor and comedian [[Norm MacDonald]] (of [[Saturday Night Live]]) was attacked by two men in [[New York City]]. They thought he was homosexual because he was well-dressed, with styled hair, and lanky; he was walking through [[Greenwich Village]], an [[gay village|area popular amongst homosexuals]]. He suffered a concussion.

There are also [[urban myths]] and unconfirmed stories told about gay-bashing, often devised to make a point. For instance:

:'' A man was shot to death in an [[Iowa]] bar because he was standing quietly in a corner holding a purse. He was perceived as an unwelcome homosexual; in actuality, he was holding the purse for his wife, who was in the restroom.''

'''See also:''' [[Transphobia]], [[Homophobia]]

== External links==
* [http://www.rememberingourdead.org Remembering our Dead], a site which remembers transgender victims of violence.

[[Category:LGBT_civil_rights]]

[[fr:Agression homophobe]]
[[zh:&amp;#23545;&amp;#21516;&amp;#24615;&amp;#24651;&amp;#30340;&amp;#36843;&amp;#23475;]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>