<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20121108192807|522049753" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="11543449" pageid="11543449" ns="0" title="Sizeism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2012-11-10T00:41:39Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Discrimination sidebar}}
'''Size discrimination''' or '''sizeism''' is a form of [[discrimination]] based upon a person's physical size, including but not limited to height and/or weight.&lt;ref name="OEDdef"&gt;[http://oed.com/view/Entry/246660?redirectedFrom=sizeism#eid "sizeism."], The Oxford English Dictionary. 3rd ed. 2012. Web. 26 April 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; Sizeism usually refers to extremes in physical size, as in an extremely tall person or an extremely skinny person. 

==Discrimination==
This type of discrimination can take a number of forms, ranging from refusing to hire someone because he or she is too short or too tall, to treating [[overweight]]  and [[underweight]] individuals with [[disdain]]. In some regions, anti-discrimination [[law]]s are in place to prohibit sizeism, along with other forms of discrimination, but sizeist [[stereotypes]] (such as "overweight people are lazy", "skinny people are mean" or "tall people can play basketball") are often ingrained in modern society. 

In the USA, the [[list of anti-discrimination acts]] do not include sizeism specifically as an offense.&lt;ref name="DescriminationLaw"&gt;[http://www.sec.gov/eeoinfo/antidiscrimination.htm Antidiscrimination (EEO) Law Information], U.S. Securities and Exchange Commission. June 15 2011. Web. 26 April 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Characteristics==
Sizeism can be based on [[height]], [[weight]] or both, and so is often related to [[heightism|height-]] and [[weightism|weight-based discrimination]] but is not synonymous with either. Depending on where in the world one is and how one chooses to live his/her life, people may have a tendency to be especially tall, slender, short, or plump, and many societies have [[Internalization|internalized]] attitudes about size. As a general rule, sizeist attitudes imply that someone believes that his or her size is superior to that of other people and treat people of other sizes negatively.

Examples of sizeist discrimination might include a person being fired from a job for being overweight or exceptionally short though their work was unaffected.

==Sizeism and stereotypes==
Like other forms of discrimination, sizeism isn't always explicit. It involves the perpetuation of [[stereotype]]s and [[Attitude (psychology)|attitude]]s which support those stereotypes, such as the idea that fat people are lazy, fat people eat too much and don't exercise enough, tall people are good [[basketball]] players, that overweight people often contract diseases which render some jobs dangerous for themselves and others, that skinny women will be mean behind people's back and steal someone's boyfriend or, a skinny man isn't masculine due to lack of musculature. Sizeist attitudes can also take the form of expressions of physical [[disgust]] when confronted with people of differing sizes and can even manifest into phobias such as cacomorphobia (the fear of fat people), gigantasophobia (the fear of tall people), or zambianoliangioticaloigisticologphobia (the fear of short people). Sizeism, being a newly realized discriminatory belief, is usually observed by those who are sufferers.

==See also==
*[[Height discrimination]]
*[[Weight stigma]]

==References==
&lt;references /&gt; 
* Yofi Tirosh, [http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2145577 The Right to Be Fat], 12 Yale Journal of Health Policy, Law, and Ethics 264-335 (2012). 

[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Body shape]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>