<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20170911230046|800177254" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="11543449" pageid="11543449" ns="0" title="Sizeism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2017-10-15T02:49:28Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Refimprove|date=May 2016}}
{{Merge|Social stigma of obesity|date=January 2017}}
{{Merge|Weight stigma|date=January 2017}}
{{Merge|Anti-fat bias|date=January 2017}}
{{Discrimination sidebar}}
'''Sizeism''' or '''size discrimination''' is discrimination based on a person's size.&lt;ref name="OEDdef"&gt;[http://oed.com/view/Entry/246660?redirectedFrom=sizeism#eid "sizeism."], The Oxford English Dictionary. 3rd ed. 2012. Web. 26 April 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; Size discrimination usually refers to extremes in physical size, such as very tall or short; extremely thin or fat.

==Discrimination==
This type of discrimination can take a number of forms, ranging from [[employment discrimination|refusing to hire someone]] because they are considered to be too short or too tall, to treating [[overweight]] and [[underweight]] individuals with [[disdain]].

There aren't currently any specific [[anti-discrimination law]]s that have been put in place to prohibit sizeism, despite the issue being extremely prevalent.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2008/03/080327172129.htm|title=Weight Bias Is As Prevalent As Racial Discrimination, Study Suggests|last=|first=|date=March 28, 2008|website=www.sciencedaily.com|publisher=Yale University|access-date=2016-08-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sizeist [[stereotypes]] (such as "overweight people are lazy" or "tall people can play basketball") are often ingrained in modern society.

In the US, the [[list of anti-discrimination acts]] does not specifically include sizeism as an offense.&lt;ref name="DescriminationLaw"&gt;[https://www.sec.gov/eeoinfo/antidiscrimination.htm Antidiscrimination (EEO) Law Information], U.S. Securities and Exchange Commission. June 15, 2011. Web. 26 April 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Characteristics==
Sizeism can be based on [[height]], [[weight]] or both, and so is often related to [[heightism|height]] and [[weightism|weight-based discrimination]] but is not synonymous with either. Depending on where in the world one is and how one lives his/her life, people may have a tendency to be especially tall, slender, short, or plump, and many societies have [[Internalization|internalized]] attitudes about size. Another manifestation of body variance is muscle mass and skeletal size, often with associations of degree of compliance to one's born sex, but do not necessarily affect gender to deviate from sex. As a general rule, sizeist attitudes imply that someone believes that his or her size is superior to that of other people and treat people of other sizes negatively.{{Citation needed|date=October 2017}}

Examples of sizeist discrimination might include a person being fired from a job for being overweight or exceptionally short though their work was unaffected.{{Citation needed|date=October 2017}}

Sizeism often takes the form of a number of [[stereotypes]] about people of particular heights and weights.{{Citation needed|date=October 2017}}

Sizeist attitudes can also take the form of expressions of physical [[disgust]] when confronted with people of differing sizes and can even manifest into specific phobias such as cacomorphobia (the fear of fat people), or a fear of tall or short people. Sizeism, being a newly recognized discriminatory stance, is usually observed by those who are its targets.{{Citation needed|date=October 2017}}

==See also==
*[[Anti-fat bias]]
*[[Height discrimination]]

==Notes==
&lt;references /&gt;

==References==
* Yofi Tirosh, [http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2145577 The Right to Be Fat], ''Yale Journal of Health Policy, Law, and Ethics'', 264–335 (2012).

{{Discrimination}}

[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Body shape]]
[[Category:Fat acceptance movement]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>