<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20101101145301|394180087" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="11543449" pageid="11543449" ns="0" title="Sizeism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2010-11-02T18:49:10Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{neologism}}
{{expand|date=June 2010}}
{{one source|date=June 2010}}
{{sections|date=April 2010}}
{{Discrimination sidebar}}
'''Size discrimination''' or '''sizeism''' is a form of [[discrimination]] based upon the size of a person's body. This type of discrimination can take a number of forms, ranging from refusing to hire someone because he or she is too short, to treating [[overweight]] individuals with [[disdain]]. In some regions, [[law]]s are in place to prohibit sizeism, but sizeist attitudes (such as "skinny people are underweight" and other such attitudes) are often ingrained in modern society.

Sizeism can be based on [[height]], [[weight]] or both, and so is often related to [[heightism|height-]] and [[weightism|weight-based discrimination]]. Depending on where in the world one is and how one chooses to live his/her life, people may have a tendency to be especially tall, slender, short, or plump, and many societies have [[Internalization|internalized]] attitudes about size. As a general rule, sizwist attitudes imply that someone believes that his or her size is superior to that of other people.

Like other forms of discrimination, sizeism isn't always explicit. It involves the perpetuation of [[stereotype]]s and [[attitude]]s which support those stereotypes, such as the idea that fat people are lazy, that fat people eat too much and don't exercise enough, that tall people are good [[basketball]] players or that overweight people often contract diseases which render some jobs dangerous for themselves and others.&lt;ref name="drh"&gt;[http://www.drhoffman.com/page.cfm/193 Correlation between Obesity and Disease]&lt;/ref&gt; Sizeist attitudes can also take the form of expressions of physical [[disgust]] when confronted with people of differing sizes. Sizeism, being a newly realized discriminatory belief, is usually observed by those who are sufferers.

Any time someone makes a [[judgment]] about someone else on the basis of his or her size, such as inexplicably not letting one be a marathon runner due to weight, this is an example of sizeism. When a decision is made not to hire someone because of size, this is also sizeist.

==See also==
*[[Height discrimination]]
*[[Weight stigma]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Body shape]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>