<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20071107010624|169739444" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="61098" pageid="61098" ns="0" title="Ethnic cleansing"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-11-07T20:58:23Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{For|the video game|Ethnic Cleansing (computer game)}}
{{Discrimination}}
'''Ethnic cleansing''' refers to various policies or practices aimed at the displacement of an [[ethnic group]] from a particular territory in order to create a supposedly ethnically "pure" society. The term entered English and international usage in the early 1990s to describe certain events in the former [[ex-Yugoslavia|Yugoslavia]]. Its typical usage was developed in the Balkans, to be a less objectionable code-word meaning [[genocide]], but its intent was to best avoid the obvious pitfalls of longstanding international treaty laws prohibiting war crimes. This [[Orwellian]] term has since become still more Orwellian, because it is occasionally used as a claim of [[war crimes]], when no war crimes actually exist.  For example, ethnic cleansing has become improperly used to describe a situation wherein poorer ethnic groups are being displaced economically, by other, generally more affluent ethnic groups.

Synonyms include ''sectarian revenge''{{Fact|date=February 2007}} and ''ethnic purification'' and (in the French versions of some UN documents) ''nettoyage ethnique''  and ''épuration ethnique''.&lt;ref&gt;Drazen Petrovic, [http://www.ejil.org/journal/Vol5/No3/art3.html "Ethnic Cleansing - An Attempt at Methodology"], ''European Journal of International Law'', Vol. No. 3. Retrieved 20 May 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Definitions==
The term ethnic cleansing has been variously defined. In the many words of Andrew Bell-Fialkoff:

:[E]thnic cleansing [...] defies easy definition. At one end it is virtually indistinguishable from forced emigration and population exchange while at the other it merges with deportation and genocide. At the most general level, however, ethnic cleansing can be understood as the expulsion of an "undesirable" population from a given territory due to religious or ethnic discrimination, political, strategic or ideological considerations, or a combination of these.&lt;ref&gt;Andrew  Bell-Fialkoff, "[http://www.foreignaffairs.org/19930601faessay5199/andrew-bell-fialkoff/a-brief-history-of-ethnic-cleansing.html A Brief History of Ethnic Cleansing]", Foreign Affairs 72 (3): 110, Summer 1993. Retrieved 20 May 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

Drazen Petrovic has distinguished between broad and narrow definitions. Broader definitions focus on the fact of expulsion based on ethnic criteria, while narrower definitions include additional criteria:  for example, that expulsions are systematic, illegal, involve gross human-rights abuses, or are connected with an ongoing internal or international war. According to Petrovic:

:[E]thnic cleansing is a well-defined policy of a particular group of persons to systematically eliminate another group from a given territory on the basis of religious, ethnic or national origin. Such a policy involves violence and is very often connected with military operations. It is to be achieved by all possible means, from discrimination to extermination, and entails violations of human rights and international humanitarian law."&lt;ref&gt;Petrovic, "Ethnic Cleansing - An Attempt at Methodology" p.11 [http://www.ejil.org/journal/Vol5/No3/art3.pdf] and quoted by Ilan Pappe "The Ethnic cleansing of Palestine" 2006, p.1&lt;/ref&gt;

The official [[United Nations]] definition of ethnic cleansing is "rendering an area ethnically homogeneous by using force or intimidation to remove from a given area persons of another ethnic or religious group"&lt;ref&gt;Hayden, Robert M. (1996) [http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0037-6779(199624)55%3A4%3C727%3ASFGECA%3E2.0.CO;2-Y Schindler's Fate: Genocide, Ethnic Cleansing, and Population Transfers]. ''[[Slavic Review]]'' 55 (4), 727-48.&lt;/ref&gt;

However, ethnic cleansing rarely aims at complete ethnic homogeneity. The common practice is the removal of stigmatized ethnic groups, and thus can be defined as "the forcible removal of an ethnically defined population from a given territory", occupying the middle part of a somewhat fuzzy continuum between nonviolet pressured ethnic emigration and [[genocide]].&lt;ref name="martin"&gt;Martin, Terry (1998). [http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0022-2801%28199812%2970%3A4%3C813%3ATOOSEC%3E2.0.CO%3B2-A The Origins of Soviet Ethnic Cleansing]. ''[[The Journal of Modern History]]'' 70 (4), 813-861.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Origins of the term==
The term "ethnic cleansing" entered the English lexicon as a [[loan translation]] of the [[Bosnian language|Bosnian]]/[[Serbian language|Serbian]]/[[Croatian language|Croatian]] phrase ''etničko čišćenje'' ([[International Phonetic Alphabet|IPA]] {{IPA|/etnitʃko tʃiʃtʃʲeɲe/}}). {{Dubious}} 
During the [[1990s]] it was used extensively by the media in the former [[Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia|Yugoslavia]] in relation to the [[Yugoslav wars]], and appears to have been popularised by the international media some time around [[1992]]. The term may have originated some time before the [[1990s]] in the military doctrine of the former [[Yugoslav People's Army]], which spoke of "cleansing the field" (''čišćenje terena'', [[International Phonetic Alphabet|IPA]] {{IPA|/tʃiʃtʃʲeɲe terena/}}) of enemies to take total control of a conquered area. The origins of this doctrine are unclear, but may have been a legacy of the [[Partisans (Yugoslavia)|Partizan]] era.

This originally applied purely to military enemies, but came to be applied to ethnic groups as well. It was used in this context in Yugoslavia as early as [[1982]], in relation to the policies of the [[Kosovo]] Albanian administration creating an "ethnically clean" territory (i.e. "cleanly" Albanian) in the province.&lt;ref&gt;Marvine Howe in the New York Times (July 12, 1982), quoting an Albanian official in Kosovo&lt;/ref&gt; However, this usage had antecedents.

One of the earliest usages of the term ''cleansing'' can be found on [[May 16]], [[1941]], during the [[World War II|Second World War]], by one [[Viktor Gutic|Viktor Gutić]], a commander in the [[Croatia]]n fascist faction, the [[Ustase|Ustaše]]: ''Every Croat who today solicits for our enemies not only is not a good Croat, but also an opponent and disrupter of the prearranged, well-calculated plan for cleansing ''[čišćenje]'' our [[Independent State of Croatia|Croatia]] of unwanted elements [...].''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pavelicpapers.com/documents/ndhnews/ndhn0004.html Pavelicpapers.com]&lt;/ref&gt; The Ustaše did carry out large-scale ethnic cleansing and [[genocide]] of [[Serbs of Croatia|Serbs in Croatia]] during the [[World War II|Second World War]] and sometimes used the term "cleansing" to describe it.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pavelicpapers.com/documents/ndh/ndh002.html Pavelicpapers.com]&lt;/ref&gt; 

Some time later, on [[30 June]], [[1941]], [[Stevan Moljević]], a lawyer from [[Banja Luka]] who was an ideologue of the [[Chetnik]]s, published a booklet with the title ''On Our State and Its Borders''. Moljević assessed the circumstances in the following manner: ''One must take the opportunity of the war conditions and at a suitable moment take hold of the territory marked on the map, cleanse ''[očistiti]'' it before anybody notices and with strong battalions occupy the key places (...) and the territory surrounding these cities, freed of non-[[Serbs|Serb]] elements. The guilty must be promptly punished and the others deported - the [[Croats]] to [[Croatia]], the [[Muslims]] to [[Turkey]] or perhaps [[Albania]] - while the vacated territory is settled with Serb refugees now located in Serbia.''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bosnia.org.uk/bosrep/report_format.cfm?articleid=3025&amp;reportid=169 The Moljevic Memorandum]&lt;/ref&gt;

The term "cleansing" ("cleansing of borders", очистка границ) was used in Soviet documents of early 1930s in reference to the resettlement of [[Poles]] from the 22-km [[Border Security Zone of Russia|border zone]] in [[Byelorussian SSR]] and [[Ukrainian SSR]]. The process was repeated on a larger and wider scale in 1939-1941, involving many other ethnicities with cross-border ties to foreign [[nation-states]], see [[Involuntary settlements in the Soviet Union]] and [[Population transfer in the Soviet Union]].&lt;ref name="martin"/&gt; 

A similar term with the same intent was used by the [[Nazism|Nazi]] administration in [[Germany]] under [[Adolf Hitler]]. When an area under Nazi control had its entire [[Jew]]ish population removed, whether by driving the population out, by deportation to [[Concentration Camp]]s, and/or [[murder]], the area was declared ''[[judenrein]]'', (lit. "Jew Clean"): "cleansed of Jews".(cf. [[racial hygiene]]). (refer to Robert Brinkman aka b dub's novel "ethnic cleansing"

==Ethnic cleansing as a military and political tactic==
[[Image:Gagra massacre5467.jpg|200px|thumb|Massacre of Georgian civilians in Gagra during the war in Abkhazia, 1992]]
The purpose of ethnic cleansing is to remove the conditions for potential and actual opposition, whether political, terrorist, guerrilla or military, by physically removing any potentially or actually hostile ethnic communities. Although it has sometimes been motivated by a doctrine that claim an ethnic group is literally "unclean" (as in the case of the [[Jews in the Middle Ages|Jews of medieval Europe]]), more usually it has been a rational (if brutal) way of ensuring that total control can be asserted over an area. The campaign in Bosnia in early 1992 was a case in point. The tactic was used by [[Bosnian Croat]], [[Bosnian Muslim]] and [[Bosnian Serb]] forces. Ethnic cleansing is often also accompanied by efforts to eradicate all physical traces of the expelled ethnic group, such as by the destruction of cultural artifacts, religious sites and physical records.{{Fact|date=February 2007}}

In 1993, during the [[War in Abkhazia|Georgian-Abkhaz conflict]], armed Abkhaz separatist insurgency confronted with large population of ethnic [[Georgians]] implemented the tactic of [[Ethnic cleansing of Georgians in Abkhazia|ethnic cleansing]] directed against ethnic Georgians (which made the majority of the population) of [[Abkhazia]]. &lt;ref&gt;US State Department, Country Reports on Human Rights Practices for 1993, Abkhazia case &lt;/ref&gt; As the results, more than 250,000 ethnic Georgians were forced to flee and approximately 30,000 people were killed during separate incidents involving massacres and expulsion. (see [[Ethnic cleansing of Georgians in Abkhazia]]) &lt;ref&gt; Chervonnaia, Svetlana Mikhailovna. ''Conflict in the Caucasus: Georgia, Abkhazia, and the Russian Shadow.'' Gothic Image Publications, 1994. &lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt; ''S State Department, Country Reports on Human Rights Practices for 1993, February 1994, Chapter 17. &lt;/ref&gt;

As a tactic, ethnic cleansing has a number of significant advantages and disadvantages. It enables a force to eliminate civilian support for resistance by eliminating the civilians &amp;mdash; recognizing [[Mao Zedong]]'s dictum that guerrillas among a civilian population are fish in water, it disables the fish by draining the water. When enforced as part of a political settlement, as happened with the forced resettlement of ethnic Germans to Germany after [[1945]], it can contribute to long-term stability{{Fact|date=February 2007}}. Some individuals of the large German population in [[Czechoslovakia]] and prewar [[Poland]] had been sources of friction before the Second World War, but this was forcibly resolved{{Fact|date=February 2007}}. It thus establishes "facts on the ground" - radical demographic changes which can be very hard to reverse{{Fact|date=February 2007}}. But this does not concern the treatment of the inhabitants of [[Historical Eastern Germany]].{{Fact|date=February 2007}}

On the other hand, ethnic cleansing is such a brutal tactic and so often accompanied by large-scale bloodshed that it is widely reviled. It is generally regarded as lying somewhere between [[population transfer]]s and [[genocide]] on a scale of odiousness, and is treated by international law as a [[war crime]].

[[Image:Marcharmenians.jpg|right|thumb|300px|Armenian civilians, being cleansed from their homeland during the [[Armenian Genocide]].]]

==Ethnic cleansing as a crime under international law==
There is no formal legal definition of ethnic cleansing.&lt;ref&gt; Ward Ferdinandusse, [http://www.ejil.org/journal/Vol15/No5/9.pdf The Interaction of National and
International Approaches in the Repression of International Crimes], The European Journal of International Law Vol. 15 no.5 (2004), p. 1042, note 7.&lt;/ref&gt; However, ethnic cleansing in the broad sense - the forcible deportation of a population - is defined as a crime against humanity under the statutes of both [[International Criminal Court]] (ICC) and the [[International Criminal Tribunal for the Former Yugoslavia]] (ICTY).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.un.org/law/icc/statute/99_corr/2.htm ''Rome Statute of the International Criminal Court''], Article 7; [http://www.un.org/icty/legaldoc-e/index.htm ''Updated Statute of the International Criminal Tribunal for the Former Yugoslavia''], Article 5.&lt;/ref&gt; The gross human-rights violations integral to stricter definitions of ethnic cleansing are treated as separate crimes falling under the definitions for genocide or crimes against humanity of the statutes.&lt;ref&gt;Daphna Shraga and Ralph Zacklin [http://www.ejil.org/journal/Vol5/No3/art4-01.html "The International Criminal Tribunal for the Former Yugoslavia"], The European Journal of International Law Vol. 15 no.3 (2004).&lt;/ref&gt;

The UN Commission of Experts (established pursuant to Security Council Resolution 780) held that the practices associated with ethnic cleansing "constitute crimes against humanity and can be assimilated to specific war crimes. Furthermore ... such acts could also fall within the meaning of the Genocide Convention." The UN General Assembly condemned "ethnic cleansing" and racial hatred in a [[1992]] resolution.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.un.org/documents/ga/res/47/a47r080.htm A/RES/47/80] ""Ethnic cleansing" and racial hatred" United Nations. 12/16/1992. Retrieved on [[2006]], [[July 3|09-03]]&lt;/ref&gt;

There are however situations, such as the [[Expulsion of Germans after World War II]], where ethnic cleansing has taken place without legal redress. [[Timothy V. Waters]] argues that if similar circumstances arise in the future, this precedent would allow the ethnic cleansing of other populations under international law.&lt;ref&gt;[http://law.bepress.com/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4600&amp;context=expresso Timothy V. Waters, ''On the Legal Construction of Ethnic Cleansing''], Paper 951, 2006, [[University of Mississippi]] School of Law. Retrieved on [[2006]], [[December 13|12-13]]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!--The emergence of ethnic cleansing as a distinct category of war crime has been a somewhat complex process. Each individual element of a programme of ethnic cleansing could be considered as an individual violation of humanitarian law - a killing here, a house-burning there - thus missing the systematic way in which such violations were perpetrated with a single aim in mind. International courts therefore consider individual incidents in the light of a possible pattern of ethnic cleansing. In the Yugoslav case, for instance, the ICTY considers the widespread massacres and abuses of human rights in Bosnia and Kosovo as part of an overall "joint criminal enterprise" to carve out ethnically pure states in the region.

However, many alleged "ethnic cleansings" in the past do not fit the modern definition of "crimes against humanity."  For example, the post-WW2 [[German expulsions]] were sanctioned by the international agreement at [[Potsdam conference]], requiring that the actions proceed humanely.--&gt;

==Silent ethnic cleansing==

'''Silent ethnic cleansing''' is a term coined in the mid-[[1990s]] by some observers of the [[Yugoslav wars]].  Apparently concerned with Western-media representations of atrocities committed in the conflict &amp;mdash; which generally focused on those perpetrated by the [[Serbs]] &amp;mdash; atrocities committed against Serbs were dubbed "silent", on the grounds that they were not receiving adequate coverage. &lt;ref&gt;Krauthammer, Charles: "When Serbs Are 'Cleansed,' Moralists Stay Silent", ''International Herald Tribune'', 12 August 1995&lt;/ref&gt;

Since that time, the term has been used by other ethnically oriented groups for situations that they perceive to be similar &amp;mdash; examples include both sides in [[Northern Ireland]]'s continuing [[The Troubles|troubles]], and those who object to the expulsion of [[Volksdeutsche|ethnic Germans]] from former German territories during and after [[World War II]].

Some observers, however, assert that the term should only be used to denote population changes that do not occur as the result of overt violent action, or at least not from more or less organized aggression - the absence of such stressors being the very factor that makes it "silent" (although some form of coercion must logically exist).

==Instances of ethnic cleansing ==
This section lists incidents that have been termed "ethnic cleansing" by some academic or legal experts. Not all experts agree on every case; nor do all the claims necessarily follow definitions given in this article. Where claims of ethnic cleansing originate from non-experts (e.g., journalists or politicians) this is noted.

===Early instances===
*Most of the Old Testament contains passages of genocidal intent and ethnic cleansing ordered by God such as 1 SAMUEL 15.19
* The ancient [[Assyria]] began to utilize [[Military history of the Assyrian Empire#Deportations|mass-deportation]] as a punishment for [[List of revolutions and rebellions|rebellions]] since the 13th century BC. By the 9th century BC the Assyrians made it a habit of regularly deporting thousands of restless subjects to other lands.

* The [[Carthage]] was completely destroyed by [[Roman Republic|Rome]] in the [[Third Punic War]] (149-146 BC). 50,000 Carthaginians (perhaps a tenth of the original pre-[[war]] population) were sold into [[slavery in ancient Rome|slavery]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.infoplease.com/ipa/A0001198.html Ancient History]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.crystalinks.com/punicwars.html Punic Wars]&lt;/ref&gt;

* After conquering western [[Anatolia]] in 88 BC, [[Mithridates VI]] reportedly ordered the [[murder|killing]] of all [[Roman republic|Romans]] living there. The [[List of massacres|massacre]] of Roman men, women and children is known as the [[Asiatic Vespers]].

* [[Julius Caesar]]'s campaign against the [[Helvetii]], the [[Celt]]ic inhabitants of modern [[Switzerland]]: approximately 60% of the tribe was killed, and another 20% was taken into [[slavery]]. The remainder of the Helvetii were driven back into their old lands.

* The ethnic cleansing and massacres of [[Roman Empire|Roman]] population of [[Roman Britain]] by [[Celt]]ic Britons during the [[Boudica]]'s revolt, in 60-61 AD.&lt;ref&gt;[http://observer.guardian.co.uk/uk_news/story/0,6903,406152,00.html Dig uncovers Boudicca's brutal streak]&lt;/ref&gt; 

* The Germanic [[Vandals]] were enslaved and deported from [[North Africa]] after the Vandal kingdom in North Africa was defeated by a [[Byzantine]] army during a [[Vandalic War]] in 533 and 534.&lt;ref&gt;[http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/secondary/BURLAT/17*.html J. B. Bury: History of the Later Roman Empire • Vol. II Chap. XVII]&lt;/ref&gt;

*[[St. Brice's Day massacre]] of [[1002]]. The [[Anglo-Saxons|Anglo-Saxon]] King [[Ethelred the Unready]] ordered the death of all the [[Danish people|Danes]] living in the [[Kingdom of England]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/radio4/history/making_history/making_history_winter2002.shtml BBC Making History]&lt;/ref&gt;

* The ethnic cleansing of sedentary [[Greeks|Greek]] population of [[Anatolia]] by nomadic [[Seljuk Turks]] after the [[Battle of Manzikert]] in [[1071]].&lt;Ref&gt;[http://www.thelatinlibrary.com/imperialism/notes/manzikert.html Battle of Manzikert (1071 A.D.)]&lt;/Ref&gt;

* The [[Pechenegs]], nomadic [[Turkic people]] from the [[steppe]], were nearly annihilated at the [[Battle of Levounion]] by a combined [[Byzantine]] and [[Cuman]] army in [[1091]]. Attacked again in [[1094]] by the Cumans, many Pechenegs were slain or absorbed.

* [[Jews]] were frequently [[massacred]] and exiled from various European countries.  The persecution hit its first peak during the [[Crusades]]. In the [[First Crusade]] (1096) flourishing communities on the Rhine and the Danube were utterly destroyed; see [[German Crusade, 1096]]. In the [[Second Crusade]] ([[1147]]) the [[Jews in France]] were subject to frequent massacres.  The Crusades were followed by expulsions, including in, [[1290]], the banishing of all English Jews; in [[1396]], 100,000 Jews were expelled from France. According to [[James P. Carroll|James Carroll]], "Jews accounted for 10% of the total population of the [[Roman Empire]]. By that ratio, if other factors had not intervened, there would be 200 million Jews in the world today, instead of something like 13 million."&lt;ref&gt;Carroll, James. ''[[Constantine's Sword]]'' (Houghton Mifflin, 2001) ISBN 0-395-77927-8 p.26&lt;/ref&gt; 

* [[History of the Jews under Muslim rule|Jews]] and [[Christians]] expelled from [[Morocco]] and [[Islamic Spain]] during the reign of [[Berber people|Berber]] dynasty of [[Almohads]] in the [[12th century]]. Almohads gave a choice of either death or conversion to [[Islam]], or exile. Some, such the family of [[Maimonides]], fled east to the more tolerant [[Islam by country|Muslim lands]], while others went northward to settle in the growing Christian kingdoms.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.theforgottenrefugees.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=66&amp;Itemid=39 The Forgotten Refugees]&lt;/ref&gt;

* At the beginning of the [[13th century]] the eastern part of the [[Islamic world]] experienced the terrifying holocaust of the [[Mongol invasion]], which turned northern and eastern [[Iran]] into a desert. Over much of [[Central Asia]] speakers of [[Iranian languages]] were replaced by speakers of [[Turkic languages]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sfusd.k12.ca.us/schwww/sch618/Ibn_Battuta/Battuta's_Trip_Three.html Battuta's Travels: Part Three - Persia and Iraq]&lt;/ref&gt; 

* In [[1270]], the Jews of [[Tunisia]] were required either to leave or to embrace Islam.

* The ethnic cleansing of the [[French people|French]] from [[Sicily]] during the [[Sicilian Vespers]] in [[1282]].

* The [[Crow Creek Massacre]] in [[1325]] was part of the ethnic cleansing of the Initial Coalescent people by the Middle Missouri villagers.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usd.edu/anth/crow/crow1.html Crow Creek Massacre]&lt;/ref&gt;

* Northern [[Iraq]] remained predominantly [[Assyrian Christian]] until the destructions of [[Tamerlane]], an Islamic conqueror of [[Turco-Mongol]] descent, at the end of the 14th century.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.geocities.com/somasushma/Timur4.html The annihilation of Iraq]&lt;/ref&gt;

*  Between the [[11th century|11th]] and [[18th century|18th]] centuries, the [[Vietnamese|Vietnamese]] expanded southward in a process known as {{lang|vi|nam tiến}} (''southward expansion''). In 1471 the kingdom of [[Champa]] suffered a massive defeat by the Vietnamese, in which 120,000 [[Cham people]] were either captured or killed, and the kingdom was reduced to a small enclave near [[Nha Trang]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cpamedia.com/history/cham_survivors/ The Chams: Survivors of a Lost Civilisation]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://countrystudies.us/vietnam/11.htm The Le Dynasty and Southward Expansion]&lt;/ref&gt;

*[[Spain]]'s large [[Islam|Muslim]] and [[Judaism|Jewish]] minorities, inherited from that country's former [[Islamic Spain|Islamic kingdoms]], were expelled following a [[Alhambra decree]] in [[1492]], while [[Converso|converts to Catholicism]], called [[Morisco]]s or [[Marrano]]s, were expelled between [[1609]] and [[1614]].&lt;ref&gt; Rezun, Miron, "Europe's Nightmare: The Struggle for Kosovo", (p. 6), Praeger/Greenwood (2001) ISBN 0-275-97072-8; Parker, Geoffrey, "Europe in Crisis", (p. 18), Blackwell Publishing (1979, 2000) ISBN 0-631-22028-3; Gadalla, Moustafa, "Egyptian Romany: The Essence of Hispania" (pp. 28-9), Tehuti Research Foundation (2004) ISBN 1-931446-19-9 &lt;/ref&gt;

* The deportations of the [[Armenians]] by Persian [[Safavids]], which begun in the 1530s under [[Tahmasp I]]. Between [[1604]] and [[1605]] [[Abbas I of Persia|Shah Abbas]] relocated some 150,000 Armenians to an area of [[Isfahan]] called [[New Julfa]].

* In [[1622]], the tribal chief of the Powhatan Confederacy of what is now [[Virginia]] in the [[United States]] planned the destruction of the English settlers. During the [[Jamestown Massacre]], the [[Powhatans]] killed 347 [[English people|English]] settlers throughout the Virginia colony, almost one-third of the English population of first permanent English colony in the New World.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bookrags.com/Indian_massacre_of_1622 Around 347 people were massacred in the attack]&lt;/ref&gt;

* Hundreds of thousands of [[Poles]] and [[Jews in Poland|Jews]] had been wiped out or driven from the lands of present-day Ukraine by [[Zaporozhian Cossacks]] during the [[Khmelnytsky Uprising]] (1648-1654).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?artid=808&amp;letter=C JewishEncyclopedia.com - "Cossacks' Uprising", by Herman Rosenthal]&lt;/ref&gt; As a result of events during [[Deluge (history)|The Deluge]], population of [[Polish-Lithuanian Commonwealth]] dropped by one-third.

* After the [[Cromwellian conquest of Ireland#Guerrilla warfare, famine and plague|Cromwellian conquest of Ireland]] and [[Act for the Settlement of Ireland 1652|Act of Settlement]] in 1652, [[Irish Catholics]] had most of their lands confiscated and were banned from living in towns for a short period. As many as 100,000 [[Irish people|Irish]] men, women and children were forcibly taken to the colonies in the [[West Indies]] and [[North America]] as [[indentured servants]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/northernireland/ashorthistory/archive/intro99.shtml BBC The curse of Cromwell]&lt;/ref&gt;

* On [[August 10]], 1680, the [[Pueblo people|Pueblo]] Indians rose in revolt against Spanish rule. By the time the [[Pueblo Revolt]] succeeded, the Pueblo warriors killed 380 [[Spaniards|Spanish]] settlers and drove the surviving Europeans from [[New Mexico]]. By 1690s, certain Pueblo groups wanted the Spanish to come back to protect them against [[Apache]] and [[Navajo people|Navajo]] raiders.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hfac.uh.edu/gl/mav1.htm Resistance and Accommodation in New Mexico]&lt;/ref&gt;  

*[[Kosovo]] was taken temporarily by the [[Habsburg Monarchy|Austrian]] forces during the [[Great Turkish War]] with help of [[Serbs]]. After the Austrians retreated in 1690, hundreds of thousands of Serbs had to flee from Kosovo and [[Serbia]] to [[Bosnia and Herzegovina|Bosnia]] and [[Vojvodina]] to evade [[Ottoman]] reprisals.

===Colonial period===

* Conflict between [[Miao people|Miao]] groups and newly arrived [[Han Chinese|Han]] settlers increased during the [[18th century]] under repressive economic and cultural reforms imposed by the [[Qing Dynasty]]. This led to armed conflict and large-scale migrations continuing into the late 19th century, the period during which most [[Hmong people]] emigrated to [[Southeast Asia]].&lt;ref&gt;Culas &amp; Michaud, 68–74.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.north-by-north-east.com/articles/04_04_1.asp The Hmong]&lt;/ref&gt;

* In the [[Great Expulsion]] of 1755, around 4000 to 5000 French [[Acadians]] were deported from Acadia by the British; many later settled in [[Acadiana|Louisiana]], where they became known as [[Cajuns]].

* Expulsion and ethnic cleansing of the [[St. Domingue]]’s 40,000 white [[French people|French]] settlers during the [[Haitian Revolution]] from 1791 to 1804. [[Jean-Jacques Dessalines]], first ruler of an independent [[Haiti]], declared Haiti an all black nation, slaughtered all the remaining whites on the island and forbade [[Caucasian race|Caucasians]] from ever again owning property or land there.[http://www.fsmitha.com/h3/h34-np2.html] 

* Expulsion of more than a million [[Crimean Tatars]], [[Crimean Goths]] and [[Nogais]] of the [[Kuban]] and [[Budjak]] steppes to [[Ottoman Empire]] after the [[Crimean Khanate]] was annexed by Russia in [[1783]].

* During the [[Chios Massacre]]  in 1822 about 42,000 [[Greeks|Greek]] islanders of [[Chios]] were [[list of massacres|massacred]]; 45,000 were [[slavery|enslaved]]; and 23,000 were exiled. Less than 2,000 Greeks managed to survive on the island.

* On November 19, 1835, the [[Chatham Islands]] were [[invasion|invaded]] by mainland [[Māori]]. Some 300 [[Moriori]] men, women and children were [[massacred]] and the remaining 1,300 survivors were [[slavery|enslaved]]. By 1862, only 101 Morioris were left alive. Modern inhabitants are descendants of those who invaded and conquered the archipelago in 1835.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newzealandatoz.com/index.php?pageid=607&amp;PHPSESSID=1c2fab7979e45ccc7c3e7336e8636142 New Zealand A to Z | Chatham Islands]&lt;/ref&gt;   

* The ethnic cleansing of the light-skinned [[Spaniard|Spanish]] and [[Mestizo]] people by the [[Maya people|Mayas]] from the eastern [[Yucatan]] and the territory of [[Quintana Roo]] during the [[Caste War of Yucatán]].  The greatest success of the Maya revolt was reached in the spring of [[1848]], with the Europeans and Mestizos driven from most of the peninsula other than the walled cities of [[Campeche, Campeche|Campeche]] and [[Mérida, Yucatán|Mérida]] and the south-west coast.

* In the United States in the 19th century there were numerous instances of relocation of Native American peoples from their traditional areas to often remote reservations elsewhere in the country, particularly in the [[Indian Removal]] policy of the 1830s. The [[Trail of Tears]], which led to the deaths of about 2,000 to 8,000 [[Cherokees]] from disease, and the [[Long Walk of the Navajo]] are well-known examples.&lt;ref&gt;Perdue, Theda, ''Cherokee Women and the Trail of Tears'' in ''American Encounters: Natives and Newcomers from European Contact to Indian Removal, 1500-1850'', p. 526, (Routledge (UK), 2000)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Committee on Indian Affairs, US Senate, ''Cherokee Settlement and Accommodation Agreements Concerning the Navajo and Hopi Land Dispute'', (US General Printing Office, 1996)&lt;/ref&gt;[http://www.marionkentucky.us/Marion-Kentucky-trailoftears.htm]

* The [[Tasmanian aborigines|Tasmanians]], estimated at 8,000 people in 1803, were reduced to a population of around 300 by 1833, although much of this has been attributed to the effect of [[disease]]s to which they had no natural immunity (including [[smallpox]] and [[syphilis]]) and [[alcoholism]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.abc.net.au/pm/stories/s746130.htm Historian dismisses Tasmanian aboriginal genocide "myth"]&lt;/ref&gt; Estimates of the total number of Tasmanian deaths at the hands of European settlers vary, with some controversial estimates ranging as low as 118 in the period from [[1803]] until [[1847]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.adelaideinstitute.org/Dissenters/windschuttle.htm Our history not rewritten but put right. Accusations of genocide have been based on guesswork and blatant ideology. SMH, 24 November 2002]&lt;/ref&gt;  This conflict is a subject of the [[Australia]]n [[history wars]]. 

* [[Ainu people]] are an ethnic group indigenous to [[Hokkaidō]], northern [[Honshū]], the [[Kuril Islands]], much of [[Sakhalin]], and the southernmost third of the [[Kamchatka peninsula]]. As Japanese settlement expanded, the Ainu were pushed northward, until by the [[Meiji period]] they were confined by the government to a small area in Hokkaidō, in a manner similar to the placing of Native Americans on reservations. 

* The ethnic cleansing of the [[Assyrian people|Assyrian]] Christian population from Eastern [[Anatolia]] by [[Kurdish people|Kurdish]] tribes, in [[1842]]-[[1847]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://debate.org.uk/topics/history/xstnc-6.html The Massacres of the Khilafah]&lt;/ref&gt; 

* Expulsion of Turkish, Muslim, and Jewish populations from [[Balkan]]s following the independence of Balkan countries (e.g., [[Serbia]], [[Greece]], [[Bulgaria]]) from [[Ottoman Empire]] from early 1800s to early 1900.&lt;ref&gt;Justin McCarthy, ''Death and Exile: The Ethnic Cleansing of Ottoman Muslims, 1821-1922'', (Princeton, N.J: Darwin Press, c1995&lt;/ref&gt;
*Expulsion of Muslim populations in [[Northern Caucasus]] by imperial [[Russia]] throughout 19th century. Particularly, expulsion of [[Adyghe people|Circassians]] to [[Anatolia]] in [[1864]].&lt;ref&gt;McCarthy, ''ibid.''&lt;/ref&gt; (see [[Muhajir (Caucasus)]] for more details)

===20th century===
* The ethnic cleansing of the [[The Destruction of Thracian Bulgarians in 1913|Thracian Bulgarians]] by the [[Young Turks]] in the [[Ottoman Empire|Ottoman]] portion of [[Thrace]] in 1913. 
* The [[Armenian Genocide|Armenian]]/[[Assyrian Genocide]], under the [[Three Pashas]] of the late Ottoman empire and the later [[Pontian Greek Genocide]], both perpetrated by the [[Young Turks]] during [[1914]]&amp;ndash;[[1922]].&lt;ref&gt;Norman M. Naimark. ''Fires of Hatred: Ethnic Cleansing in Twentieth-Century Europe.'' Cambridge and London: Harvard University Press, 2001. ISBN. See also [http://www.h-net.org/reviews/showrev.cgi?path=84591082031333 review] by Nick Baron, H-Genocide, March 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Greco-Turkish War (1919-1922)#Greek massacres of Turks|Massacres of the Turkish population by the Greek army of occupation]] and [[Greco-Turkish War (1919-1922)#Greek scorched earth policy|Greek scorched earth policy]] by Greek troops after their defeat in the Greco Turkish War. [[Greco-Turkish War (1919-1922)#Re-Capture of Smyrna.2C September 1922|Massacre of Greek population]] and sack of [[İzmir|Smyrna]] by Turkish troops. 
* The [[Population exchange between Greece and Turkey]] of Greeks from Turkey and of Turks from Greece after the [[Greco-Turkish War (1919-1922)]] as a consequence of the [[Treaty of Lausanne]] in 1923. 
* The [[Bolshevik]] regime killed or deported an estimated 300,000 to 500,000 [[Don Cossacks]] during the [[Russian Civil War]], in 1919-1920.&lt;ref&gt;Kort, Michael (2001). ''The Soviet Colossus: History and Aftermath'', p. 133. Armonk, NY: M.E. Sharpe. ISBN 0-7656-0396-9.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Polish minority in the Soviet Union|Deportation of Poles]] by the [[Soviet Union]] from [[Belarus]], [[Ukraine]] and European Russia to [[Kazakhstan]] in 1934-1938.
* [[Deportation of Koreans in the Soviet Union|Deportation of Koreans]] by the [[Soviet Union]] from [[Russian Far East]] to [[Soviet Central Asia]] from September to October of 1937. More than 172,000 Koreans were deported.
* The persecutions and expulsions of [[Jews]] in [[Germany]], [[Austria]] and other [[Nazi]]-controlled areas prior to the initiation of [[the Holocaust|mass genocide]] in which 6 million Jews were killed.&lt;ref&gt;Naimark, ''op. cit.''&lt;/ref&gt;
* During the [[Finland|Finnish]] occupation of [[East Karelia]] during [[World War II]] the Russian speaking population of the city of [[Petrozavodsk]] was held in an [[concentration camp]].
* [[Expulsion of Poles by Germany]]. During World War II, Nazis planned to ethnicly cleanse the whole Polish population. Eventually during [[Consequences of German Nazism|Nazi occupation]] up to 1.6 to 2 million [[Poles]] were expelled, not counting milions of [[slavery|slave labourers]] deported from Poland.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ushmm.org/education/resource/poles/poles.php?menu=/export/home/www/doc_root/education/foreducators/include/menu.txt&amp;bgcolor=CD9544 Poles: Victims of the Nazi Era]&lt;/ref&gt;
* More than 250,000 [[Serbs]] were expelled from [[Croatia]] by the extreme nationalist [[Ustashe]] regime during the [[Serbian Genocide]], in 1941-1945.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www1.yadvashem.org/about_yad/press_room/press_releases/croatian_president.html Ustasa, Croatian nationalist, fascist, terrorist movement created in 1930.]&lt;/ref&gt;
* During WWII, in [[Kosovo &amp; Metohija]], some 10,000 Serbs lost their lives&lt;ref name=Krizman&gt;Serge Krizman, Maps of Yugoslavia at War, Washington 1943.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Istorija&gt;ISBN 86-17-09287-4: Kosta Nikolić, Nikola Žutić, Momčilo Pavlović, Zorica Špadijer: Историја за трећи разред гимназије природно-математичког смера и четврти разред гимназије општег и друштвено-језичког смера, Belgrade, 2002, pg. 182&lt;/ref&gt;, and about 80&lt;ref name=Krizman/&gt; to 100,000&lt;ref name=Krizman/&gt;&lt;ref name=Annexe&gt;[http://www.parliament.the-stationery-office.co.uk/pa/cm199900/cmselect/cmfaff/28/28ap42.htm Annexe I], by the Serbian Information Centre-London to a report of the Select Committee on Foreign Affairs of the [[British House of Commons|House of Commons]] of the [[Parliament of the United Kingdom]].&lt;/ref&gt; or more&lt;ref name=Istorija/&gt; were ethnically cleansed. Hundreds of thousands more would leave in the following decades, following the shift of power in Kosovo, resulting in non-violent ethnic cleansing of Serbs between 1945 and 1991.
* Deportation of [[Volga German]]s by [[Soviet Union]] to [[Kazakhstan]], [[Altai Krai]], [[Siberia]], and other remote areas, in 1941-1942.
* [[Population transfer in the Soviet Union|Deportation]] of [[Crimean Tatars]], [[Kalmykia|Kalmyks]], [[Chechnya|Chechens]], [[Ingushetia|Ingush]], [[Balkars]], [[Karachay-Cherkessia|Karachay]]s, and [[Meskhetian Turks]] by [[Soviet Union]] to [[Central Asia]] and [[Siberia]], 1943-1944.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rferl.org/featuresarticle/2005/05/1350f316-420a-4a90-b42e-b59fe9fcc8e5.html 60 Years After: For Victims Of Stalin's Deportations, War Lives On]&lt;/ref&gt; 
* The ethnic cleansing and [[massacres of Poles in Volhynia]] by nationalist [[Ukrainian Insurgent Army|UPA]] which took place in 1943 and 1944, with the bulk of victims reported for summer and autumn 1944.
* [[Expulsion of Germans after World War II]]. From 1944 until 1948, between 13.5 and 16.5 million [[Germans]] were expelled, [[East Prussia#Evacuation of East Prussia|evacuated]] or fled from Central and Eastern Europe. Estimated number of those who died in the process is being debated by historians and estimated between 500,000 and 3,000,000.&lt;ref&gt;''[http://cadmus.iue.it/dspace/bitstream/1814/2599/1/HEC04-01.pdf The Expulsion of 'German' Communities from Eastern Europe at the end of the Second World War]'', European University Institute, Florense. EUI Working Paper HEC No. 2004/1, Edited by Steffen Prauser and Arfon Rees pp. 4&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Istrian exodus]] during and after World War II. The [[diaspora]] of ethnic [[Italy|Italians]] from [[Istria]], [[Rijeka|Fiume]] and dalmatian [[Zadar|Zara]] lands, after the collapse of Italian [[fascism|fascist]] regime.
* The mass deportation of [[Ukrainians|Ukrainian]] speaking ethnic minorities from the territory of [[Poland]] after [[World War II]], culminating in [[1947]] with the start of [[Operation Wisla]]. Millions of [[Poles]] were simultaneously deported from [[Kresy|the eastern territories annexed by the Soviet Union]] into the western territories, which Soviets transferred from Germany to Poland. By 1950, 5 million Poles had been settled in what the government called the [[Regained Territories]].
* Mass expulsions of [[Hindu]]s and [[Sikh]]s from [[Pakistan]] to [[India]], and of [[Muslims]] from India to Pakistan. The controversy surrounding this move resulted in the killings of [[Hindu]]s, [[Muslims]]s and [[Sikh]]s in riots. This was known as the [[partition of India|partition of British India]] in [[1947]].&lt;ref&gt; Talbot, Ian:  "India and Pakistan", (pp. 198-99), Oxford University Press (2000) ISBN 0-340-70632-5 &lt;/ref&gt;  Well over 10 million people were violently displaced, making it the ''largest single instance of ethnic cleansing in recorded history''.
* After the annexation of the [[Muslim culture of Hyderabad|Muslim-ruled]] state of [[Hyderabad State|Hyderabad]] by India in 1948, about 7,000 Hadrami [[Arabs]] were interned and deported from [[India]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.al-bab.com/bys/articles/freitag99.htm British-Yemeni Society: Hadhrami migration in the 19th and 20th centuries]&lt;/ref&gt; 
* The [[Palestinian exodus]], in which the substantial majority of Arab [[Palestinians]] (approximately 700,000) in the areas of [[British Mandate of Palestine]] that became part of [[Israel]] fled or were deported by Israeli forces following the [[1948 Arab-Israeli War]].&lt;ref&gt; [[Benny Morris]], The Birth of the Palestinian Refugee Problem Revisited. Cambridge University Press. (2004) ISBN 0-521-00967-7 &lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Yoav Gelber, Palestine 1948: War, Escape and the Emergence of the Palestinian Refugee Problem. Sussex Academic Press. (2005) ISBN 1-84519-075-0 &lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt; [[Ilan Pappe]], Ethnic Cleansing of Palestine. Oxford: Oneworld. (2006) ISBN 1-85168-467-0 &lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Jewish exodus from Arab lands]], in which 99 percent of [[Jews]] (approximately 800,000) from Arab countries were deported by Arab governments, or fled oppression and discrimination, between the [[1948 Arab-Israeli War]] and the [[Six Day War]] in 1967. The major populations affected were in [[History of the Jews in Iraq|Iraq]], [[History of the Jews in Syria|Syria]], [[History of the Jews in Yemen]], [[History of the Jews in Egypt]], [[History of the Jews in Libya]], [[History of the Jews in Algeria]], [[History of the Jews in Tunisia|Tunisia]] and [[History of the Jews in Morocco|Morocco]].&lt;ref&gt; Itamar Levin, Locked Doors: The Seizure of Jewish Property in Arab Countries. Praeger/Greenwood. (2001) ISBN 0-275-97134-1 &lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt; Maurice Roumani, The Case of the Jews from Arab Countries: A Neglected Issue, Tel Aviv: World Organization of Jews from Arab Countries. (1977) ASIN B0006EGL5I&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt; Malka Hillel Schulewitz, The Forgotten Millions: The Modern Jewish Exodus from Arab Lands. London. (2001) ISBN 0-8264-4764-3&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Ran HaCohen, [http://www.antiwar.com/hacohen/h011303.html "Ethnic Cleansing: Some Common Reactions"]&lt;/ref&gt;
* After [[Indonesia]] received independence from the [[Netherlands]] in 1949, around 300.000 people, predominantly [[Indo people|Indo]]s or Dutch Indonesians (people of mixed Indonesian and European descent), fled or were expulsed from Indonesia.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dutchmalaysia.net/press/Easternization.html Easternization of the West: Children of the VOC]&lt;/ref&gt;
* The mass deportation of ethnic minorities from their homelands, including [[East Timor]] and [[Western New Guinea|Papua]], by the [[Indonesia]]n government, beginning with Indonesian independence in [[1949]] (and subsequent occupation and annexation of Papua until the present day and of East Timor until 1999).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.etan.org/et99b/september/19-25/23unrigh.htm UN rights chief calls for intl probe into East Timor massacres]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hrw.org/backgrounder/asia/timor/etimor1202bg.htm Justice Denied for East Timor]&lt;/ref&gt; 
* Displacement of [[Kashmiri Pandits|Kashmiri Hindus]] living in [[Kashmir]] due to the ongoing and anti-[[Republic of India|Indian]] insurgency. Some 300,000 Hindus have been internally displaced from Kashmir due to the violence.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/in.html India], ''The World Factbook''. Retrieved 20 May 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;
* On 5 July [[1960]], five days after the [[Democratic Republic of the Congo|Congo]] gained independence from Belgium, the [[Force Publique]] garrison near [[Léopoldville]] mutinied against its white officers and attacked numerous European targets. This caused the fear amongst the approximately 100,000 [[white African|whites]] still resident in the Congo and mass exodus from the country.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.historylearningsite.co.uk/united_nations_congo.htm ::UN:: History Learning Site]&lt;/ref&gt;  
* Mass expulsion of the [[pied-noir]] population of European descent and [[History of the Jews in Algeria|Jews]] from [[Algeria]] to [[France]]. In just a few months in [[1962]], 900,000 of these Europeans and native Jewish people left the country.&lt;ref&gt;[http://marketplace.publicradio.org/shows/2006/08/01/PM200608016.html Marketplace: Pied-noirs breathe life back into Algerian tourism]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://lexicorient.com/e.o/pied-noir.htm Pied-Noir]&lt;/ref&gt;
* The ethnic cleansing of the [[Arabs]] and [[Demographics of India|Indians]] from [[Zanzibar]] in [[1964]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://whosfaultisit.blogspot.com/2006/09/homemade-genocide-arab-world-is.html Who's Fault Is It?]&lt;/ref&gt;
* During the [[Bangladesh War of Independence]] of [[1971]] around 10 million [[Bengalis]] fled the country to escape the killings and [[1971 Bangladesh atrocities|atrocites]] committed by the [[Pakistan]] Army.
* The forced expulsion of [[Uganda]]'s entire [[Non-resident Indian and Person of Indian Origin|Asian]] population by [[Idi Amin]]'s regime.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/onthisday/hi/dates/stories/august/7/newsid_2492000/2492333.stm 1972: Asians given 90 days to leave Uganda]&lt;/ref&gt;
*The ethnic cleansing between 1963-1974 of Turkish Cypriots by Greek Cypriots and Greek military forces.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.mediaprof.org/tcvoices/trnchist/trnccr74.html&lt;/ref&gt;
* The ethnic cleansing in 1974-76 of the entire Greek population of the areas under Turkish military occupation in [[Cyprus]] during and after the [[Turkish Invasion of Cyprus]]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.lobbyforcyprus.org/press/press1998-1940/suntimes230177.htm&lt;/ref&gt;.
* [[Apartheid#Forced removals|Forced removals]] of non-white populations in South Africa under [[Apartheid]].&lt;ref&gt; Bell, Terry: "Unfinished Business: South Africa, Apartheid and Truth", (pp. 63-4), Verso, (2001, 2003) ISBN 1-85984-545-2 &lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt; Valentino, Benjamin A., "Final Solutions: Mass Killing and Genocide in the Twentieth Century", (p. 189), Cornell University Press, (2004) ISBN 0-8014-3965-5. &lt;/ref&gt;
*  At least one million Iraqi [[Kurds]] were displaced during the [[Al-Anfal Campaign]] ([[1986]]-[[1989]]). 
* The forced assimilation campaign of the late 80s directed against ethnic [[Turkish people|Turks]] resulted in the emigration of some 300,000 [[Turks in Bulgaria|Bulgarian Turks]] to Turkey.
* The [[Nagorno Karabakh]] conflict has resulted in the displacement of 528,000 (this figure does not include new born children of these [[Internally displaced person|IDP]]s) [[Azerbaijanis]] from Armenian occupied territories including Nagorno Karabakh, and 220,000 Azeris, 18,000 Kurds and 3,500 Russians fled from [[Armenia]] to Azerbaijan from 1988 to 1989.&lt;ref&gt;De Waal, ''Black Garden'', p. 285&lt;/ref&gt; 280,000 persons&amp;mdash;virtually all ethnic [[Armenians]]&amp;mdash;fled [[Azerbaijan]] during the [[1988]]–[[1993]] war over the disputed region of Nagorno-Karabakh.&lt;ref&gt;[http://ourworld.compuserve.com/homepages/usazerb/refugees.htm Refugees and displaced persons in Azerbaijan]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Since April 1989, some 70,000 black Mauritanians -- members of the [[Peul]], [[Wolof]], [[Soninke]] and [[Bambara]] ethnic groups -- had been expelled from [[Mauritania]] by the Mauritanian government.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.irinnews.org/report.aspx?ReportId=70522 Fair elections haunted by racial imbalance]&lt;/ref&gt; 
* In 1989, after bloody pogroms against the [[Meskhetian Turks]] by [[Uzbeks]] in Central Asia's [[Ferghana Valley]], nearly 90,000 Meskhetian Turks left [[Uzbekistan]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.irinnews.org/report.aspx?reportid=28663 Focus on Mesketian Turks]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cal.org/co/pdffiles/mturks.pdf Meskhetian Turk Communities around the World]&lt;/ref&gt;
*The [[Expulsion of Muslims from Jaffna by LTTE|expulsion of the Muslims from Jaffna]] was an act of ethnic cleansing carried out by the [[Tamil militant]] [[Liberation Tigers of Tamil Eelam]] (LTTE) organization in [[October]] [[1990]]. In order to achieve their goal of creating an ethnically "pure" [[Tamil people|Tamil]] state in the North and East of [[Sri Lanka]], the LTTE forcibly expelled the entire Muslim community - numbered at around 80,000 - from the northern [[Jaffna]] peninsular of the island. They were forced to leave within 48 hours of an LTTE warning and not permitted to take any of their belongings, which were subsequently looted by the LTTE.
* The widespread ethnic cleansing accompanying the [[Yugoslav wars]] from [[1991]] to [[1999]], of which the most significant examples occurred in eastern [[ethnic cleansing in Croatia|Croatia]] and self-proclaimed [[Republic of Serbian Krajina]] ([[1991]]-[[1995]]), in most of [[Bosnia and Herzegovina|Bosnia]] ([[1992]]-[[1995]]), and in the [[Albanians|Albanian]]-dominated breakaway [[Kosovo]] province (of [[Serbia]]) ([[1999]]). Large numbers of [[Serbs]], [[Croats]], [[Bosniaks]] and [[Albanians]] were forced to flee their homes and expelled.&lt;ref&gt;Committee on Foreign Relations, US Senate, ''The Ethnic Cleansing of Bosnia-Hercegovina'', (US General Printing Office, 1992)&lt;/ref&gt;  
* The forced displacement and [[Ethnic cleansing of Georgians in Abkhazia|ethnic-cleansing]] of more than 250,000 people, mostly [[Georgians]] but some others too, from [[Abkhazia]] during the conflict and after in [[1993]] and [[1998]].&lt;ref&gt; Bookman, Milica Zarkovic, "The Demographic Struggle for Power", (p. 131), Frank Cass and Co. Ltd. (UK), (1997) ISBN 0-7146-4732-2 &lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[1994]] massacres of nearly one million [[Tutsis]] by [[Hutus]], known as the [[Rwandan Genocide]]&lt;ref&gt; Leeder, Elaine J., "The Family in Global Perspective: A Gendered Journey", (p. 164-65), Sage Publications, (2004) ISBN 0-7619-2837-5 &lt;/ref&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[better citation needed]&lt;/sup&gt;
* The mass expulsion of southern [[Lhotshampa]]s (Bhutanese of Nepalese origin) by the northern [[Druk]] majority of [[Bhutan]] in [[1990]].&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.voanews.com/uspolicy/2006-10-19-voa1.cfm Voice of America (18 October 2006)] &lt;/ref&gt; The number of refugees is approximately 103,000.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unhcr.org/cgi-bin/texis/vtx/publ/opendoc.htm?tbl=PUBL&amp;id=4444d3c93e UNHCR Publication (State of the world refugees)]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Displacement of more than 500,000 [[Chechen people|Chechen]] and ethnic [[Russians|Russian]] civilians living in [[Chechnya]] during the [[First Chechen War]] in [[1994]]-[[1996]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.globalsecurity.org/military/world/war/chechnya1.htm First Chechnya War]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jamestown.org/edm/article.php?article_id=2369902 Ethnic Russians in the North of Caucasus - Eurasia Daily Monitor]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.reliefweb.int/rw/rwb.nsf/0/bb82d320aa527436c1256c560037d0a6?OpenDocument&amp;Click= Chechen census fiasco]&lt;/ref&gt;
* More than 800,000 Kosovo [[Albanians]] fled their homes in [[Kosovo]] during the [[Kosovo War]] in 1999. By November 1999, most of the Albanians had returned to Kosovo. Over 200,000 [[Serbs]] and other non-Albanian minorities fled or were expelled from Kosovo after the war.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/serbia/article/0,,1713498,00.html Serbia threatens to resist Kosovo independence plan]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://hrw.org/english/docs/2004/03/18/serbia8129.htm Kosovo/Serbia: Protect Minorities from Ethnic Violence (Human Rights Watch)]&lt;/ref&gt;

===21st century===

* Since the mid-1990s the central government of [[Botswana]] has been trying to move [[Bushmen]] out of the [[Central Kalahari Game Reserve]]. As of October 2005, the government has resumed its policy of forcing all Bushmen off their lands in the Game Reserve, using armed police and threats of violence or death.&lt;ref name="Daily Telegraph"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/main.jhtml?xml=/news/2005/10/29/wbot29.xml&amp;sSheet=/news/2005/10/29/ixworld.html
|title=Bushmen forced out of desert after living off land for thousands of years |publisher=The Daily Telegraph |accessdate=2005-10-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many of the involuntarily displaced Bushmen live in squalid resettlement camps and some have resorted to [[prostitution]] and [[alcoholism]], while about 250 others remain or have surreptitiously returned to the [[Kalahari]] to resume their independent lifestyle.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.nationalgeographic.com/news/2004/09/0914_040914_labushmen_2.html African Bushmen Tour U.S. to Fund Fight for Land]&lt;/ref&gt; “How can you have a [[Stone Age]] creatures continue to exist in the age of computers?“ asked Botswana’s president [[Festus Mogae]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.motherjones.com/news/dispatch/2005/01/01_800.html Exiles of the Kalahari]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.survival-international.org/news/1454 UN condemns Botswana government over Bushman evictions]&lt;/ref&gt;

* Expulsion of [[white people|white]] farmers by the [[Robert Mugabe|Mugabe]] regime in [[Zimbabwe]] in 2000. There were 270,000 [[whites in Zimbabwe]] (when the country was known as [[Rhodesia]]) in 1970. There are only a few thousand whites left in Zimbabwe today. 

* The removal of around 8,500 Jews (including the forced removal of about half of them)&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/middle_east/4159958.stm 'Israel evicts Gaza Strip settlers'], BBC News Online, [[17 August]], 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; from the [[Gaza Strip]], and around 660 from four small settlements in the [[West Bank]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/middle_east/4172694.stm 'Settlers and army clash in W Bank'], BBC News Online, [[22 August]], 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; in 2005 through the implementation of [[Israel's unilateral disengagement plan]].&lt;ref&gt;Robinson, Eugene. [http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2005/08/18/AR2005081801642.html "Betrayed in Gaza"], ''[[Washington Post]]'', August 19, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Klein, Morton A. [http://www.jewishjournal.com/home/preview.php?id=11876 "Gaza Withdrawal Rewards Terrorism"], ''[[The Jewish Journal of Greater Los Angeles]]'' February 27, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Jeff Jacoby|Jacoby, Jeff]]. [http://www.jewishworldreview.com/jeff/jacoby_2005_04_01.php3 "Sharon's retreat is a victory for terrorists"], ''Jewish World Review'', April 1, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Gross, Tom. [http://www.tomgrossmedia.com/ExodusFromGaza.html Exodus From Gaza] Tom Gross Mid-East Media Analysis. Retrieved November 4, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

* Attacks by the [[Janjaweed]] [[Arabs]], [[Muslim]] militias of [[Sudan]] on the [[African]] population of [[Darfur]], a region of western Sudan.&lt;ref&gt; Collins, Robert O., "Civil Wars and Revolution in the Sudan: Essays on the Sudan, Southern Sudan, and Darfur, 1962-2004
", (p. 156), Tsehai Publishers (US), (2005) ISBN 0-9748198-7-5 .&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Power, Samantha  "Dying in Darfur: 
Can the ethnic cleansing in Sudan be stopped?"[http://www.newyorker.com/fact/content/?040830fa_fact1], ''The New Yorker'', [[30 August]] [[2004]].
Human Rights Watch, [http://hrw.org/english/docs/2004/05/05/darfur8536.htm "Q &amp; A: Crisis in Darfur"] (web site, retrieved [[24 May]] [[2006]]).
Hilary Andersson, [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/programmes/from_our_own_correspondent/3752871.stm "Ethnic cleansing blights Sudan"], ''BBC News'', 27 May 2004.&lt;/ref&gt; A July 14, 2007 article notes that in the past two months up to 75,000 Arabs from [[Chad]] and [[Niger]] crossed the border into Darfur. Most have been relocated by the Sudanese government to former villages of displaced non-Arab people. Some 2.5 million have now been forced to flee their homes after attacks by Sudanese troops and Janjaweed militia.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.independent.co.uk/world/africa/article2768232.ece Arabs pile into Darfur to take land 'cleansed' by janjaweed]&lt;/ref&gt;  

*Currently in the [[Iraq Civil War]] (2003 to present), entire neighborhoods in [[Baghdad]] are being ethnically cleansed by [[Shia]] and [[Sunni]] Militias. Some areas are being evacuated by every member of a particular secular group due to lack of security, moving into new areas because of fear of reprisal killings. As of June 21, 2007, the [[United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees]] estimated that 2.2 million Iraqis had been displaced to neighboring countries, and 2 million were displaced internally, with nearly 100,000 Iraqis fleeing to Syria and Jordan each month.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cnn.com/2007/WORLD/meast/06/20/damon.iraqrefugees/index.html Iraq refugees chased from home, struggle to cope]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.boston.com/news/world/middleeast/articles/2006/11/03/un_nearly_100000_flee_iraq_monthly/ U.N.: 100,000 Iraq refugees flee monthly]. Alexander G. Higgins, ''[[Boston Globe]],'' [[November 3]], [[2006]]&lt;/ref&gt; 

*Although [[Iraqi Christians]] represent less than 5% of the total Iraqi population, they make up 40% of the [[refugees]] now living in nearby countries, according to [[UNHCR]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usatoday.com/news/world/iraq/2007-03-22-christians-iraq_N.htm Christians, targeted and suffering, flee Iraq]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.asianews.it/index.php?l=en&amp;art=7410&lt;/ref&gt; In the [[16th century]], Christians constituted half of Iraq's population.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unhcr.org/cgi-bin/texis/vtx/iraq?page=news&amp;id=461e5a644 UNHCR | Iraq]&lt;/ref&gt; In 1987, the last Iraqi census counted 1.4 million Christians.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.irinnews.org/report.aspx?reportid=61897 Christians live in fear of death squads]&lt;/ref&gt; But as the [[2003 invasion of Iraq|2003 invasion]] has radicalized Islamic sensibilities, Christians' total numbers slumped to about 500,000, of whom 250,000 live in Baghdad.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.guardian.co.uk/pope/story/0,,1961207,00.html&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, the [[Mandaeans|Mandaean]] and [[Yazidi]] communities are at the risk of elimination due to the ongoing [[atrocities]] by [[Islamism|Islamic]] extremists.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/6412453.stm Iraq's Mandaeans 'face extinction']&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/20294868/ Iraq's Yazidis fear annihilation]&lt;/ref&gt; A May 25, 2007 article notes that in the past 7 months only 69 people from Iraq have been granted [[Immigration to the United States#Asylum for refugees|refugee status]] in the [[United States]].&lt;ref&gt;Ann McFeatters: [http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/opinion/317322_mcfeatters27.html Iraq refugees find no refuge in America]. ''[[Seattle Post-Intelligencer]]'' May 25, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

* The ethnic cleansing of [[African American]] population of some racially mixed [[Los Angeles]] neighborhoods by [[Mexican American|Mexican]] [[gangs in the United States|street gangs]]. According to gang experts and law enforcement agents the [[Mexican Mafia]] leaders, or shot callers, have issued a "green light" on all blacks.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.latimes.com/news/printedition/opinion/la-op-hernandez7jan07,1,414328.story?coll=la-news-comment&amp;ctrack=1&amp;cset=true Roots of Latino/black anger]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.alternet.org/story/46855/ Ethnic Cleansing in L.A.]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.blackamericaweb.com/site.aspx/bawnews/stateof/hutchinson105 Thanks to Latino Gangs, There’s a Zone in L.A. Where Blacks Risk Death if They Enter]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/main.jhtml?xml=/news/2007/01/23/wgangs23.xml FBI called to deal with 'race' gang violence]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://observer.guardian.co.uk/world/story/0,,2036580,00.html A bloody conflict between Hispanic and black gangs is spreading across Los Angeles]&lt;/ref&gt;

*In October 2006, [[Niger]] announced that it would deport the [[Arabs]] living in the Diffa region of eastern Niger to Chad.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/6087048.stm Niger starts mass Arab expulsions]&lt;/ref&gt; This population numbered about 150,000.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.alertnet.org/thenews/newsdesk/L25138454.htm Reuters Niger's Arabs say expulsions will fuel race hate]&lt;/ref&gt; While the government was rounding Arabs in preparation for the [[deportation]], two girls died, reportedly after fleeing government forces, and three women suffered miscarriages. Niger's government had eventually suspended a controversial decision to deport Arabs.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/6081416.stm Niger's Arabs to fight expulsion]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unhcr.org/cgi-bin/texis/vtx/refworld/rwmain?docid=469638881e UNHCR | Refworld - The Leader in Refugee Decision Support]&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Genocide|GenocidePortalLogo(ESR)2.JPG}}
* [[Ethnocide]]
* [[Population transfer]]
* [[Involuntary settlements in the Soviet Union]]
* [[Civilian casualties]], civilian, non-combatant persons killed or injured by direct military action
* [[Command responsibility]]
* [[Crime against humanity]]
* [[Ethnic Cleansing (computer game)|Ethnic Cleansing]], a computer game.
* [[German exodus from Eastern Europe]]
* [[List of massacres]]
* [[List of wars and disasters by death toll]]
* [[Caste War of Yucatán]]
* [[1989 events in Mauritania and Senegal|1989 events]] 
* [[Partition of India#Independence and population exchanges|Partition of India]]
* [[1971 Bangladesh atrocities]]
* [[Persecution of Hindus]]
* [[Generalplan Ost]]
* [[Population transfer in the Soviet Union]]
* [[Polish minority in the Soviet Union]]
* [[Transmigration program]]
* [[Refugees of Iraq]]

==Notes==
&lt;div class="references-small"&gt;
&lt;references /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

==References ==
* {{cite journal | author=Bell-Fialkoff, Andrew | title=A Brief History of Ethnic Cleansing | journal=Foreign Affairs | volume=72 | issue=3 | year=1993 | pages=110}}  [http://www.foreignaffairs.org/19930601faessay5199/andrew-bell-fialkoff/a-brief-history-of-ethnic-cleansing.html]
* {{cite journal | author=Petrovic, Drazen | title=Ethnic Cleansing - An Attempt at Methodology | journal=European Journal of International Law | volume=5 | issue=1 | year=1994 | pages=359}}  [http://www.ejil.org/journal/Vol5/No3/art3.pdf]

== External links ==
* [http://www.warcrimes.info/ Documents and Resources on War, War Crimes and Genocide]
* [http://www.ryanspencerreed.com/ Photojournalist's Account] - Images of ethnic cleansing in Sudan
* [http://law.bepress.com/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4600&amp;context=expresso Timothy V. Waters, ''On the Legal Construction of Ethnic Cleansing''], Paper 951, 2006, [[University of Mississippi]] School of Law (PDF)
* [http://learning.lib.vt.edu/slav/genocide.html Genocides and Ethnic Cleansings of Central and East Europe, the Former USSR, the Caucasus and Adjacent Middle East -- 1890 - 2007]
*[http://www.world-science.net/exclusives/070525_ethnic-cleansing.htm ''Dump the “ethnic cleansing” jargon, group implores''] May 31, 2007, World Science

{{Racism topics|state=collapsed}}

[[Category:Ethnic cleansing|*]]
[[Category:Forced migration]]
[[Category:Human rights abuses]]
[[Category:Persecution]]
[[Category:Violence]]
[[Category:Racism]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]

[[bg:Етническо прочистване]]
[[bs:Etničko čišćenje]]
[[ca:Neteja ètnica]]
[[da:Etnisk udrensning]]
[[de:Ethnische Säuberung]]
[[et:Etniline puhastus]]
[[es:Limpieza étnica]]
[[fr:Nettoyage ethnique]]
[[ko:민족청소]]
[[it:Pulizia etnica]]
[[he:טיהור אתני]]
[[nl:Etnische zuivering]]
[[ja:民族浄化]]
[[no:Etnisk rensning]]
[[pl:Czystka etniczna]]
[[ru:Этнические чистки]]
[[sr:Етничко чишћење]]
[[fi:Etninen puhdistus]]
[[sv:Etnisk rensning]]
[[tr:Etnik temizlik]]
[[uk:Етнічна чистка]]
[[zh:种族清洗]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>