<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20041107222931|7325834" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="61098" pageid="61098" ns="0" title="Ethnic cleansing"><revisions><rev timestamp="2004-11-11T04:01:58Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[Category:Human rights abuses]] [[Category:Violence]]
The term '''ethnic cleansing''' refers to various policies of forcibly removing people of another [[ethnic group]].  At one end of the [[political spectrum|spectrum]], it is virtually indistinguishable from forced emigration and [[population transfer]], while at the other it merges with [[deportation]] and [[genocide]].

At the most general level, however, ethnic cleansing can be understood as the expulsion of an "undesirable" population from a given territory due to religious or ethnic discrimination, political, strategic or ideological considerations, or a combination of these.

Some political commentators avoid use of the term, which they see as a political [[euphemism]] which attempts to apply a word with positive connotations (cleansing) to a morally objectionable act (forced population movement usually achieved through violence).

==Origins of the term==
The term "ethnic cleansing" entered the English lexicon as a [[loan translation]] of the Serbian/Croatian phrase ''etni&amp;#269;ko &amp;#269;i&amp;#353;&amp;#263;enje'' ([[SAMPA]] /etnitSko tSiStS'eJe/) (notice that literal translation of the phrase is "ethnic cleaning"). During the [[1990s]] it was used extensively by the media in the former [[Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia|Yugoslavia]] in relation to the [[Yugoslav wars]], and appears to have been popularised by the international media some time around [[1992]]. The term may have originated some time before the [[1990s]] in the military doctrine of the former [[Yugoslav People's Army]], which spoke of "cleansing the territory" (''&amp;#269;i&amp;#353;&amp;#263;enje terena'', [[SAMPA]] "tSiStS'eJe terena") of enemies to take total control of a conquered area. The origins of this doctrine are unclear, but may have been a legacy of the [[Partisans (Yugoslavia)|Partizan]] era.

This originally applied purely to military enemies, but came to be applied to other ethnic groups as well. It was used in this context by the Yugoslav media as early as [[1981]], in relation to the policies of the [[Kosovo]] Albanian administration allegedly creating an "ethnically clean territory" (i.e. "cleanly" Albanian) in the province. However, this usage had antecedents.

The earliest known usage of it appears to have been in [[May 16]] [[1941]], in an article in the ''Hrvatska Krajina'' newspapers describing the visit of [[Ustase]] commander [[Viktor Gutic|Viktor Guti&amp;#263;]] to the [[Franciscans|Franciscan]] [[monastery]] [[Petricevac|Petri&amp;#263;evac]][http://www.pavelicpapers.com/documents/ndhnews/ndhn0004.html]. In the article, Guti&amp;#263; is quoted as saying:

: Every Croat who today solicits for our enemies not only is not a good Croat, but also an opponent and disrupter of the prearranged, well-calculated plan for cleansing [&amp;#269;i&amp;#353;&amp;#263;enje] our Croatia of unwanted elements...

It is possible that the revival of nationalism in the [[1980s]] reintroduced ethnic cleansing - which was practiced by all sides in the [[Second World War]] - into Yugoslavia's political debate and language.

A similar term with the same intent was used by the [[Nazi]] administration in [[Germany]] under [[Adolf Hitler]] 50 years earlier. When an area under Nazi control had its entire [[Jew]]ish population removed, whether by driving the population out, by deportation to [[Concentration Camp]]s, and/or [[murder]], the area was declared ''judenrein'' (lit. ''Jew Clean''): ''cleansed of jews''. (cf. [[racial hygiene]].)

==Ethnic cleansing in history==
Some narratives in the [[Torah]] and other books of the [[Old Testament]]  in the [[Bible]] (also known as the [[Hebrew Bible]] or Tenakh) describing the [[Hebrews|Hebrew]] (or [[Israelite]]) conquest of [[Canaan]] (in ca. 13th century B.C.E. or before) would now be considered descriptions of ethnic cleansing or even [[genocide]]. In several places the Hebrew [[God]], Yahweh commands the Hebrews to kill every man, woman and child after capturing a city, and sometimes cities also had to be burnt to the ground. It was also standard practice at the time to murder or enslave prisoners of war and their families.

For example, according to the biblical narative, the people of the Caananite village of Ai are massascred by [[Joshua]]'s troops in Joshua 8:20-25. In one passage detailing "the holy war against Midian" (Numbers 31:1-24). In verses 13-24 [[Moses]] asks the victorious Hebrew troops why they have spared the lives of all the women who had "perverted the sons of Israel" into rejecting God. Moses then orders the Hebrew troops to kill all the male children and women who are not virgins. Today, since Midian was most likely a city-state, this act would constitute [[genocide]] and many [[war crimes]].

The [[Assyria]]n Empire regularly deported entire ethnic groups, as did the [[Babylonia]]ns; victims of this policy most famously include the [[Jew]]s of [[Judah]] (see [[Babylonian captivity of Judah]]), and before them the Jews of [[Israel]] in [[-722|722 BC]].

In ancient times, the [[Roman Empire]] would often enslave or exile entire peoples, most famously the [[Jew]]s following the revolt of [[70 AD]] in [[Judea]]. After the expulsion, Jews became a nomadic nation without a homeland. During the [[Middle Ages]], every country that hosted them felt entitled to expel them, if conditions changed.

However, sometimes the expulsion of Jews had some features of ethnic cleansing, especially if it were accompanied by the violence and were enacted on the whole territory of the state. I.e. Jews were expelled from [[England]] ([[1290]]), [[France]] ([[1306]]), [[Hungary]] ([[1349]]&amp;ndash;[[1360]]), [[Provence]] ([[1394]] and [[1490]]), [[Austria]] ([[1421]]), [[Spain]] after the [[Reconquista]], [[Portugal]] (1497), [[Russia]] in [[1724]], and various parts of [[Germany]] at various times. Not all deportations of Jews affected an entire country or lasted for extended periods of time: Jews from [[Krakow]] ([[1494]]) were expelled to suburbs of the city, and Jews were expelled from [[Lithuania]] ([[1491]]) and allowed to return 10 years later. Expulsion of Jews in some cases can be compared to the expulsion of illegal immigrants, as is practised by modern countries from time to time.

Spain's large [[Muslim]] minority, inherited from that country's former Islamic kingdoms, was expelled in [[1502]] and [[1609]]&amp;ndash;[[1614]].

[[England]] expelled Gypsies, [[France]] expelled [[Huguenot]]s.

==Colonization-related ethnic cleansing==

During more recent times, ethnic cleansing has often been used during colonisation projects. In [[North America]], [[United Kingdom|British]] and [[United States|American]] settlers ethnically cleansed dozens of [[Native American]] tribes, forcibly relocating them to remote and often inhospitable reservation land.  In southern Africa and [[Australia]], [[Indigenous people|native]] tribes were removed from their lands so that they could be replaced by white farmers and settlers.

* The colonization of the [[Americas]] by European powers, particularly [[Spain]] and [[Britain]]. This led to population removals and massacres of the indigenous population, starting in the 15th century and continuing into the 20th.
* The colonization of [[Australia]] by Britain. This led to population removals and massacres of the indigenous population, starting in 1788.  It is important to note that the [[Maori]] were not ethnically cleansed in [[New Zealand]].  Many Maori were dispossessed of ownership of their land, but few were ever forcibly removed, and when this did happen it was mostly as a result of punishment for fighting and losing against colonial troops during the [[New Zealand Land Wars|Land Wars]].
* The removals and massacres of native populations in the [[African]] colonies of various European powers.
* The concentration of [[Boers]] by Britain during the Second [[Boer War]]

The American and South Pacific instances were disastrous. The native populations fell from from millions to thousands in only a few centuries, a combined result of colonization policies and [[epidemic]]s of foreign disease.

==Modern age ethnic cleansing==

The term "ethnic cleansing" has come to mean the displacement or expulsion from a territory of one ethnic group by another. The displacement is usually forcible, though there are examples of voluntary or compensated ethnic cleansing.  

The [[20th century]] has seen numerous cases, particularly in Europe and the Middle East.   

===Older examples===

* [[Great Upheaval|Expulsion]] of the [[Acadians]] in [[1755]].
* In the United States in the 19th Century there were numerous instances of relocation of Native American peoples from their traditional areas to often remote reservations elsewhere in the country.  See [[Long Walk of the Navajo]].
**The forced removal of the [[Cherokee]] Amerindian tribe at the behest of Presidents [[Andrew Jackson]] and [[Martin van Buren]], in violation of the ruling of [[John Marshall]]'s Supreme Court, led to the deaths of 1/4&amp;mdash;or about 4,000 to 8,000&amp;mdash;of said tribe during the march from Georgia to Oklahoma. See [[Trail of Tears]].

===Alleged 20th Century instances===

* The [[1913]] [[Convention of Adrianople]], annexed to the Peace Treaty between [[Bulgaria]] and Turkey, provided for an exchange of ethnic Turks and Bulgarians in a 15 kilometer strip.  
* The [[1919]] [[Treaty of Neuilly-Sur-Seine]] provided for the reciprocal emigration of ethnic minorities between [[Greece]] and [[Bulgaria]].
* In [[1923]] the [[Treaty of Lausanne]] between the [[British Empire]], [[France]], [[Italy]], [[Japan]], [[Greece]], [[Romania]] and the [[Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenes]], on the one part and [[Turkey]] on the other, which ended the [[First World War]] in the East, as well as post-War hostilities between [[Greece]] and the newly-formed [[Republic of Turkey]].  The treaty provided for a compulsory exchange of populations between Greece and Turkey.
* The [[Armenian Genocide]] and the [[Greco-Turkish relations#The First World War and after|expulsion of Pontian Greeks]] perpetrated by the [[Young Turks]] during 1914&amp;ndash;1922.
* The expulsion of Poles from [[Polish minority in Soviet Union|Belorussia and Ukraine]] 1932&amp;ndash;1936 to Kazakhstan.
* The term includes the German Nazi government's treatment of the Jews (the [[Holocaust]]) and the [[Gypsies]], in which the Nazis forcibly moved whole populations to death camps.  
* The expulsions of Jews from Austria after the Anschluss, and deportations of Poles and Jews from [[Polish areas annexed by Nazi Germany]].
* [[Generalplan Ost]], in which the Nazis planned to kill or expel most or all ethnic Slavs from large regions of Eastern Europe and replace them with German settlers. 
* The [[German exodus from Eastern Europe]].
* The deportations of [[Poles]], Lithuanians, Latvians and Estonians from areas occupied by Soviet Union 1939&amp;ndash;1941.
* The [[Massacres of Poles in Volhynia| ethnic cleansing of Volhynia]] by [[Ukrainians|Ukrainian]] guerrilla groups.
* The mass deportation and exile of the [[Chechens]], [[Ingush]], [[Volga German]]s, [[Balkars]], [[Kalmyks]], [[Crimean]] [[Tatars]], and other minorities living in the [[Soviet Union]] by [[Stalin]] in [[1943]]&amp;ndash;[[1944]], under the pretext that they were collaborating with [[Nazi Germany]]
* The expulsion of Poles from [[Zamosc Voivodship]] by Germans in 1944.
* The expulsions of 800,000 Poles from [[Warsaw]] to [[concentration camp]]s after defeat of [[Warsaw Uprising]] [[1944]], caused 200,000 deaths. The city of Warsaw, population of one million, was ordered to be completely demolished on the personal order of [[Hitler]]. Approximately 80% of the city was demolished. [[Heinrich Himmler|Himmler]] stated, that the aim, was to remove permanently the Polish population which the [[Nazi]]s viewed as an obstacle to [[Drang nach Osten|German Eastern expansion]] for the last 700 years.
* The [[World War II evacuation and expulsion|evacuation and expulsion of ethnic Germans]] from eastern Europe at the end of the [[Second World War]], notably from the [[Sudetenland]] and [[East Prussia]]. Begun as an evacuation by the German authorities, hastened by revenge attacks by Soviet troops and ultimately completed by [[USSR]] and its satellite states following the decisions at the [[Potsdam conference]].
* The mass deportation of ethnic minorities from their homelands, including [[East Timor]] and [[Papua (Indonesia)|Papua]], by the [[Indonesia]]n government, beginning with Indonesian independence in [[1949]] (and subsequent occupation and annexation of Papua until the present day and of East Timor until 1999).
* The [[Nakba]], or so-called [[Palestinian exodus]], in which the substantial majority of [[Palestinian]]s in the areas of Arab Palestine that became part of [[Israel]] fled prior to the [[1948]] [[Israeli War of Independence]].
* The mass flight of large [[Jew]]ish communities from [[Yemen]] and [[Iraq]], and small ones from the [[West Bank]] during 1948&amp;ndash;1950, as well as flights which took place later from [[Egypt]] and [[Libya]].
* The mass expulsion of Turks and Greeks from each other's respective sections of the divided island of [[Cyprus]] during the [[1974]] civil war and Turkish invasion.
* The widespread ethnic cleansing accompanying the [[Yugoslav wars]] from [[1991]] to [[1999]], of which the most significant examples occurred in eastern Croatia and Krajina ([[1991]]-[[1995]]), in most of Bosnia ([[1992]]-[[1995]]), and in the [[Albanian]]-dominated breakaway province of [[Serbia]] called [[Kosovo]] ([[1999]]). Large numbers of [[Serbs]], [[Croats]], [[Bosniaks]] and [[Albanians]] were forced to flee their homes and expelled. In [[2004]], following an upsurge in violence, Serbs were forced to flee their homes in the province (now [[United Nations]] administered) by Albanian rioters.
* The forced exclusion since [[1989]] of [[Hindus]] from the [[Pakistan]]i occupied region of the disputed territory of [[Kashmir]] by [[Islamic]] paramilitary groups, which the Indian government accuses the Pakistani governmnent of assisting.
*After the [[collapse of the Soviet Union]], a number of post-Soviet independent states witnessed out-migration of Russians, perceived as "colonizers" there because of the [[Soviet Union]]'s politics of [[Russification]]. For example, after the inclusion of [[Latvia]] in the [[USSR]], [[Latvians]] became a minority in their own country.
* Forced conversions and killings of [[Hindus]] and tribals in [[India]]'s northeast by [[National Liberation Front of Tripura|Christian militants]] since 1989.
* The 1994 massacres of [[Tutsis]] by [[Hutus]] known as the [[Rwandan Genocide]]
* Attacks by the [[Janjaweed]] [[Arab]] [[Muslim]] militias of [[Sudan]] on the non-[[Arab]] [[African]] [[Muslim]] population of [[Darfur]], a region in western Sudan.

==Ethnic cleansing as a military and political tactic==

The purpose of ethnic cleansing is to remove the conditions for potential and actual opposition, whether political, terrorist, guerrilla or military, by physically removing any potentially or actually hostile ethnic communities. Although it has sometimes been motivated by a doctrine that claim an ethnic group is literally "unclean" (as in the case of the Jews of medieval Europe), more usually it has been a rational (if brutal) way of ensuring that total control can be asserted over an area. The Serbian campaign in Bosnia in early 1992 was a case in point. As well as fighting a traditional war with the Bosnian Army, the Serbian forces sought to eradicate the entire non-Serb population of the areas they controlled, either through massacres (as the [[Srebrenica massacre]]) or more usually through terrorization of the civilian population to encourage them to flee to territory controlled by government forces. The tactic was also used by Croatian and Bosnian forces, and was repeated on a large scale during the [[Kosovo War]] in [[1999]]. Ethnic cleansing is often also accompanied by efforts to eradicate all physical traces of the expelled ethnic group, such as by the destruction of cultural artifacts, religious sites and physical records.

As a tactic, ethnic cleansing has a number of significant advantages and disadvantages. It enables a force to eliminate civilian support for resistance by eliminating the civilians &amp;#8212; in a reversal of [[Mao Tse Tung]]'s dictum that guerrillas among a civilian population are fish in water, it drains the water. When enforced as part of a political settlement, as happened with the forced resettlement of Germans from outside of Germans border after [[1945]], it can contribute to long-term stability. The large German populations in [[Czechoslovakia]] and [[Poland]] had been sources of friction before the Second World War, but this was forcibly resolved. It thus establishes "facts on the ground" &amp;#8212; radical demographic changes which can be very hard to reverse.

On the other hand, ethnic cleansing is such a brutal tactic and so often accompanied by large-scale bloodshed that it is very widely reviled. It is generally regarded as lying somewhere between [[population transfer]]s and [[genocide]] on a scale of odiousness, and is treated by international law as a [[war crime]]. It can also create political problems in the long term as "cleansed" communities campaign to be allowed to return home, as in the case of the [[Israel-Palestinian conflict]].

==Ethnic cleansing as international law crime==

Ethnic cleansing is designated a [[crime against humanity]] in international treaties, such as that which created the [[International Criminal Court]] (ICC). The [[International Criminal Tribunal for the Former Yugoslavia]] (ICTY) was set up in a similar spirit, and prosecutes these crimes under more generic names. 

The emergence of ethnic cleansing as a distinct category of war crime has been a somewhat complex process. Each individual element of a programme of ethnic cleansing could be considered as an individual violation of humanitarian law &amp;#8212; a killing here, a house-burning there &amp;#8212; thus missing the systematic way in which such violations were perpetrated with a single aim in mind. International courts therefore consider individual incidents in the light of a possible pattern of ethnic cleansing. In the Yugoslav case, for instance, the ICTY considers the widespread massacres and abuses of human rights in Bosnia and Kosovo as part of an overall "joint criminal enterprise" to carve out ethnically pure states in the region.

However, many alleged "ethnic cleansing" in the past doesn't fit in the modern definition of the crime against humanity. For example [[German expulsions]] were sanctioned by the international agreement at [[Potsdam conference]]. The agreement required the action to proceed in humane way.

==References and Links==

* "[http://www.foreignaffairs.org/19930601faessay5199/andrew-bell-fialkoff/a-brief-history-of-ethnic-cleansing.html A Brief History of Ethnic Cleansing]", Andrew Bell-Fialkoff, ''Foreign Affairs'', Vol. 72, No. 3 (1993) 110 
* "[http://www.ejil.org/journal/Vol5/No3/art3.html Ethnic Cleansing &amp;#8212; An Attempt at Methodology]", Drazen Petrovic, ''European Journal of International Law'', 5 EJIL (1994) 1-359

[[de:Ethnische Säuberung]]
[[fr:Nettoyage ethnique]]
[[ko:&amp;#48124;&amp;#51313;&amp;#52397;&amp;#49548;]]
[[nl:Etnische zuiveringen]]
[[ja:&amp;#27665;&amp;#26063;&amp;#27972;&amp;#21270;]]
[[zh:&amp;#31181;&amp;#26063;&amp;#28165;&amp;#27927;]]

:''See also: [[Ethnic Cleansing (computer game)]]''</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>