<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20081104073550|249601367" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="61098" pageid="61098" ns="0" title="Ethnic cleansing"><revisions><rev timestamp="2008-11-04T10:39:03Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{For|the video game|Ethnic Cleansing (video game)}}
{{Discrimination sidebar}}
'''Ethnic cleansing''' is a [[euphemism]] referring to the persecution through imprisonment, expulsion, or killing of members of an ethnic minority by a majority to achieve ethnic homogeneity in majority-controlled territory.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/ethnic%20cleansing ethnic cleansing - Definition from the Merriam-Webster Online Dictionary&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; It is sometimes used interchangeably with the more connotatively severe term [[genocide]]. The term entered English and international media in the early 1990s to describe [[Yugoslav wars|war events]] in the former [[ex-Yugoslavia|Yugoslavia]].

Synonyms include ''sectarian revenge''{{Fact|date=February 2007}} and ''ethnic purification'' and (in the French versions of some UN documents) ''nettoyage ethnique''  and ''épuration ethnique''.&lt;ref&gt;Drazen Petrovic, [http://www.ejil.org/journal/Vol5/No3/art3.html "Ethnic Cleansing - An Attempt at Methodology"], ''European Journal of International Law'', Vol. No. 3. Retrieved 20 May 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Definitions==
The term ethnic cleansing has been variously defined. In the words of Andrew Bell-Fialkoff:

:[E]thnic cleansing [...] defies easy definition. At one end it is virtually indistinguishable from forced emigration and population exchange while at the other it merges with deportation and genocide. At the most general level, however, ethnic cleansing can be understood as the expulsion of a population from a given territory.&lt;ref&gt;Andrew  Bell-Fialkoff, "[http://www.foreignaffairs.org/19930601faessay5199/andrew-bell-fialkoff/a-brief-history-of-ethnic-cleansing.html A Brief History of Ethnic Cleansing]", Foreign Affairs 72 (3): 110, Summer 1993. Retrieved 20 May 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

Drazen Petrovic has distinguished between broad and narrow definitions. Broader definitions focus on the fact of expulsion based on ethnic criteria, while narrower definitions include additional criteria:  for example, that expulsions are systematic, illegal, involve gross human-rights abuses, or are connected with an ongoing internal or international war. According to Petrovic:

:[E]thnic cleansing is a well-defined policy of a particular group of persons to systematically eliminate another group from a given territory, often based on economic principles, or nationalist claims to the land. Such a policy often involves violence and is very often connected with military operations. Unlike the U.S. Indian Removal program, which purchased the land from the natives, Ethnic Cleansing is to be achieved by all possible means, from discrimination to extermination, and entails violations of human rights and international humanitarian law."&lt;ref&gt;Petrovic, "Ethnic Cleansing - An Attempt at Methodology" p.11 [http://www.ejil.org/journal/Vol5/No3/art3.pdf] and quoted by Ilan Pappe "The Ethnic cleansing of Palestine" 2006, p.1&lt;/ref&gt;

The official [[United Nations]] definition of ethnic cleansing is "rendering an area ethnically homogeneous by using force or intimidation to remove from a given area persons of another ethnic or religious group"&lt;ref&gt;Hayden, Robert M. (1996) [http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0037-6779(199624)55%3A4%3C727%3ASFGECA%3E2.0.CO;2-Y Schindler's Fate: Genocide, Ethnic Cleansing, and Population Transfers]. ''[[Slavic Review]]'' 55 (4), 727-48.&lt;/ref&gt;

However, ethnic cleansing rarely aims at complete ethnic homogeneity. The common practice is the removal of stigmatized ethnic groups, and thus can be defined as "the forcible removal of an ethnically defined population from a given territory", occupying the middle part of a somewhat fuzzy continuum between nonviolent pressured ethnic emigration and [[genocide]].&lt;ref name="martin"&gt;Martin, Terry (1998). [http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0022-2801%28199812%2970%3A4%3C813%3ATOOSEC%3E2.0.CO%3B2-A The Origins of Soviet Ethnic Cleansing]. ''[[The Journal of Modern History]]'' 70 (4), 813-861.&lt;/ref&gt;

In reviewing the [[International Court of Justice]] (ICJ) [[Bosnian Genocide Case]] in the judgement of [[Jorgic v. Germany]] on [[12 July]] 2007 the [[European Court of Human Rights]] selectively quoted from the ICJ ruling on the ''Bosnian Genocide Case'' to explain that ''ethnic cleansing'' was not enough on its own to establish that a genocide had occurred:

{{quotation|The term 'ethnic cleansing' has frequently been employed to refer to the events in Bosnia and Herzegovina which are the subject of this case ... [[UN General Assembly|General Assembly]] resolution 47/121 referred in its Preamble to 'the abhorrent policy of 'ethnic cleansing', which is a form of genocide', as being carried on in Bosnia and Herzegovina. ... It [''i.e. ethnic cleansing''] can only be a form of genocide within the meaning of the [[Convention on the Prevention and Punishment of the Crime of Genocide|[Genocide] Convention]], if it corresponds to or falls within one of the categories of acts prohibited by Article II of the Convention. Neither the intent, as a matter of policy, to render an area “ethnically homogeneous”, nor the operations that may be carried out to implement such policy, can as such be designated as genocide: the intent that characterizes genocide is “to destroy, in whole or in part” a particular group, and deportation or displacement of the members of a group, even if effected by force, is not necessarily equivalent to destruction of that group, nor is such destruction an automatic consequence of the displacement. This is not to say that acts described as 'ethnic cleansing' may never constitute genocide, if they are such as to be characterized as, for example, 'deliberately inflicting on the group conditions of life calculated to bring about its physical destruction in whole or in part', contrary to Article II, paragraph (c), of the Convention, provided such action is carried out with the necessary specific intent (''[[dolus specialis]]''), that is to say with a view to the destruction of the group, as distinct from its removal from the region. As the [[ICTY]] has observed, while 'there are obvious similarities between a genocidal policy and the policy commonly known as 'ethnic cleansing' ' (''Krstić,'' IT-98-33-T, Trial Chamber Judgment, 2 August 2001, para. 562), yet '[a] clear distinction must be drawn between physical destruction and mere dissolution of a group. The expulsion of a group or part of a group does not in itself suffice for genocide. |ECHR quoting the ICJ&lt;ref&gt;[[European Court of Human Rights|ECHR]] [http://cmiskp.echr.coe.int/tkp197/view.asp?item=54&amp;portal=hbkm&amp;action=html&amp;highlight=&amp;sessionid=1448788&amp;skin=hudoc-en Jorgic v. Germany] §45 citing Bosnia and Herzegovina v. Serbia and Montenegro (“Case concerning the application of the Convention on the Prevention and Punishment of the Crime of Genocide”) the International Court of Justice (ICJ) found under the heading of “intent and 'ethnic cleansing'” § 190&lt;/ref&gt;}}

==Origins of the term==
The term "ethnic cleansing" entered the English lexicon as a [[Calque|loan translation]] of the [[Bosnian language|Bosnian]]/[[Serbian language|Serbian]]/[[Croatian language|Croatian]]/[[Montenegrin language|Montenegrin]] phrase ''etničko čišćenje'' ({{IPA2|ětnitʃkoː tʃîʃʨeːɲe}}). {{Dubious|date=March 2008}} 
During the 1990s it was used extensively by the media in the former [[Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia|Yugoslavia]] in relation to the [[Yugoslav wars]], and appears to have been popularised by the international media some time around 1992. The term may have originated some time before the 1990s in the military doctrine of the former [[Yugoslav People's Army]], which spoke of "cleansing the field" (''čišćenje terena'', {{IPA2|tʃîʃʨeːɲe terěːna}}) of enemies to take total control of a conquered area. The origins of this doctrine are unclear, but may have been a legacy of the [[Partisans (Yugoslavia)|Partizan]] era.

This originally applied purely to military enemies, but came to be applied to ethnic groups as well. It was used in this context in Yugoslavia as early as 1982, in relation to the policies of the [[Kosovo]] Albanian administration creating an "ethnically clean" territory (i.e. "cleanly" Albanian) in the province.&lt;ref&gt;Marvine Howe in the New York Times (July 12, 1982), quoting an Albanian official in Kosovo&lt;/ref&gt; However, this usage had antecedents.

Carnegie Endowment report for the Balkan Wars in 1914 points out that village-burning and ethnic cleansing have traditionally accompanied Balkan wars, regardless of ethnicities involved. In probably the earliest attestation of the term, [[Vuk Karadžić]] makes use of the word ''cleanse'' to describe what happened to the Turks in the [[Belgrade]] when the city was captured by the [[Karadjordje]]'s forces in 1806&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Judah, Tim |title=The Serbs: History, Myth and the Destruction of Yugoslavia |year=1997 |location=New Haven and London |publisher=Yale University Press|pages=pp. 75}}&lt;/ref&gt;. [[Konstantin Nenadović]] wrote in his biography of famous Serbian leader published in 1883 that after the fighting "the Serbs, in their bitterness, slit the throats of the Turks everywhere they found them, sparing neither the wounded, nor the woman, nor the Turkish children".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Mirko Grmek, Marc Gjidara, Neven Simac|title=Le Nettoyage ethnique: Documents historiques sur une idéologie serbe |year=1993 |location=Paris |language=French|pages=pp. 24}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Later attestation of the term ''cleansing'' can be found on [[May 16]], [[1941]], during the [[World War II|Second World War]], by one [[Viktor Gutic|Viktor Gutić]], a commander in the [[Croatia]]n fascist faction, the [[Ustase|Ustaše]]: ''Every Croat who today solicits for our enemies not only is not a good Croat, but also an opponent and disrupter of the prearranged, well-calculated plan for cleansing ''[čišćenje]'' our [[Independent State of Croatia|Croatia]] of unwanted elements [...].''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pavelicpapers.com/documents/ndhnews/ndhn0004.html Pavelicpapers.com]&lt;/ref&gt;{{Verify credibility|date=June 2008}} The Ustaše did carry out large-scale ethnic cleansing and [[genocide]] of [[Serbs of Croatia|Serbs in Croatia]] during the [[World War II|Second World War]] and sometimes used the term "cleansing" to describe it.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pavelicpapers.com/documents/ndh/ndh002.html Pavelicpapers.com]&lt;/ref&gt;.

Some time later, on 30 June, 1941, [[Stevan Moljević]], a lawyer from [[Banja Luka]] who was an ideologue of the [[Chetnik]]s, published a booklet with the title ''On Our State and Its Borders''. Moljević assessed the circumstances in the following manner: ''One must take the opportunity of the war conditions and at a suitable moment take hold of the territory marked on the map, cleanse ''[očistiti]'' it before anybody notices and with strong battalions occupy the key places (...) and the territory surrounding these cities, freed of non-[[Serbs|Serb]] elements. The guilty must be promptly punished and the others deported - the [[Croats]] to [[Croatia]], the [[Muslims]] to [[Turkey]] or perhaps [[Albania]] - while the vacated territory is settled with Serb refugees now located in Serbia.''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bosnia.org.uk/bosrep/report_format.cfm?articleid=3025&amp;reportid=169 The Moljevic Memorandum]&lt;/ref&gt;

The term "cleansing", more specifically the Russian term "cleansing of borders", ''ochistka granits'' (очистка границ), was used in Soviet documents of early 1930s in reference to the resettlement of [[Poles]] from the 22-km [[Border Security Zone of Russia|border zone]] in [[Byelorussian SSR]] and [[Ukrainian SSR]]. The process was repeated on a larger and wider scale in 1939–1941, involving many other ethnicities with cross-border ties to foreign [[nation-states]], see [[Involuntary settlements in the Soviet Union]] and [[Population transfer in the Soviet Union]].&lt;ref name="martin"/&gt; 

A similar term with the same intent was used by the [[Nazism|Nazi]] administration in [[Germany]] under [[Adolf Hitler]]. When an area under Nazi control had its entire [[Jew]]ish population removed, whether by driving the population out, by deportation to [[Concentration Camp]]s, and/or [[murder]], the area was declared ''[[judenrein]]'', (lit. "Jew Clean"): "cleansed of Jews".(cf. [[racial hygiene]]).

==Ethnic cleansing as a military and political tactic==
[[Image:Abkhazia genocidememorial2005.jpg|200px|thumb|The 12th anniversary of ethnic cleansing in Abkhazia which was held in Tbilisi in 2005. One of the visitors of the gallery recognized her dead son on the photograph.]]
The purpose of ethnic cleansing is to remove the conditions for potential and actual opposition, whether political, terrorist, guerrilla or military, by physically removing any potentially or actually hostile ethnic communities. Although it has sometimes been motivated by a doctrine that claim an ethnic group is literally "unclean" (as in the case of the [[Jews in the Middle Ages|Jews of medieval Europe]]), more usually it has been a rational (if brutal) way of ensuring that total control can be asserted over an area. 

Ethnic cleansing was a common phenomenon in the [[Bosnian war]]. This typically entailed intimidation, forced expulsion and/or killing of the undesired ethnic group as well as the destruction or removal of the physical vestiges of the ethnic group, such as places of worship, cemeteries and cultural and historical buildings. According to numerous ICTY verdicts, Serb&lt;ref name="ICTY: Radoslav Brđanin judgement"&gt;{{cite  web|url=http://www.un.org/icty/brdjanin/trialc/judgement/index.htm|title=ICTY: Radoslav Brđanin judgement|}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Croat&lt;ref name="ICTY: Kordić and Čerkez verdict"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.un.org/icty/kordic/trialc/judgement/index.htm|title=ICTY: Kordić and Čerkez verdict|}}&lt;/ref&gt; forces performed ethnic cleansing of their territories planned by their political leadership in order to create ethnically pure states ([[Republika Srpska]] and [[Herzeg-Bosnia]]). Furthermore, Serb forces committed [[Srebrenica genocide|genocide in Srebrenica]] at the end of the war.&lt;ref&gt;ICTY; "Address by ICTY President Theodor Meron, at Potočari Memorial Cemetery" The Hague, 23 June 2004 [http://www.un.org/icty/pressreal/2004/p860-e.htm]&lt;/ref&gt;

Based on the evidence of numerous Croat forces attacks against Bosnian Muslims (Bosniaks), the ICTY Trial Chamber concluded in the ''Kordić and Čerkez case'' that by April 1993 Croat leadership from Bosnia and Herzegovina had a common design or plan conceived and executed to [[Lašva Valley ethnic cleansing|ethnically cleanse Bosniaks from the Lašva Valley]] in Central Bosnia. [[Dario Kordić]], as the local political leader, was found to be the planner and [[wikt:instigator|instigator]] of this plan. &lt;ref name="ICTY: Kordić and Čerkez verdict - IV. Attacks on towns and villages: killings - C. The April 1993 Conflagration in Vitez and the Lašva Valley - 3. The Attack on Ahmići (Paragraph 642)"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.un.org/icty/kordic/trialc/judgement/kor-tj010226e-5.htm#IVC3|title=ICTY: Kordić and Čerkez verdict - IV. Attacks on towns and villages: killings - C. The April 1993 Conflagration in Vitez and the Lašva Valley - 3. The Attack on Ahmići (Paragraph 642)|}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1993, during the [[War in Abkhazia|Georgian-Abkhaz conflict]], armed Abkhaz separatist insurgency confronted with large population of ethnic [[Georgians]] implemented the campaign of [[Ethnic cleansing of Georgians in Abkhazia|ethnic cleansing]] directed against ethnic Georgians (Georgians formed the single largest ethnic group in pre-war Abkhazia, with a 45.7% plurality as of 1989) of [[Abkhazia]]. &lt;ref&gt;US State Department, Country Reports on Human Rights Practices for 1993, Abkhazia case &lt;/ref&gt; As the results, more than 250,000 ethnic Georgians were forced to flee and approximately 30,000 people were killed during separate incidents involving massacres and expulsion. (see [[Ethnic cleansing of Georgians in Abkhazia]]) &lt;ref&gt; Chervonnaia, Svetlana Mikhailovna. ''Conflict in the Caucasus: Georgia, Abkhazia, and the Russian Shadow.'' Gothic Image Publications, 1994. &lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt; ''S State Department, Country Reports on Human Rights Practices for 1993, February 1994, Chapter 17. &lt;/ref&gt; The ethnic cleansing campaign against ethnic Georgians of Abkhazia was recognized by OSCE conventions in Budapest, Lisbon, Istanbul and was also mentioned in UN General Assembly Resolution GA/10708. &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.un.org/News/Press/docs//2008/ga10708.doc.htm General Assembly Adopts Resolution Recognizing Right Of Return By Refugees, Internally Displaced Persons To Abkhazia, Georgia&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; 

As a tactic, ethnic cleansing has a number of significant impact. It enables a force to eliminate civilian support for resistance by eliminating the civilians &amp;mdash; recognizing [[Mao Zedong]]'s dictum that guerrillas among a civilian population are fish in water, it disables the fish by draining the water. When enforced as part of a political settlement, as happened with the [[Expulsion of Germans after World War II|forced resettlement of ethnic Germans to Germany]] after 1945, it can contribute to long-term stability.&lt;ref&gt; Judt, Tony. ''Postwar: A History of Europe Since 1945'' Penguin Press, 2005&lt;/ref&gt; Some individuals of the large German population in [[Czechoslovakia]] and prewar [[Poland]] had been sources of friction before the Second World War, but this was forcibly resolved&lt;ref&gt; Judt, Tony. ''Postwar: A History of Europe Since 1945'' Penguin Press, 2005. &lt;/ref&gt;. It thus establishes "[[facts on the ground]]" - radical demographic changes which can be very hard to reverse. 

On the other hand, ethnic cleansing is such a brutal tactic and so often accompanied by large-scale bloodshed that it is widely reviled. It is generally regarded as lying somewhere between [[population transfer]]s and [[genocide]] on a scale of odiousness, and is treated by international law as a [[war crime]].

[[Image:Marcharmenians.jpg|right|thumb|300px|Armenian civilians, being cleansed from their homeland during the [[Armenian Genocide]].]]

==Ethnic cleansing as a crime under international law==
There is no formal legal definition of ethnic cleansing.&lt;ref&gt; Ward Ferdinandusse, [http://www.ejil.org/journal/Vol15/No5/9.pdf The Interaction of National and
International Approaches in the Repression of International Crimes], The European Journal of International Law Vol. 15 no.5 (2004), p. 1042, note 7.&lt;/ref&gt; However, ethnic cleansing in the broad sense - the forcible deportation of a population - is defined as a crime against humanity under the statutes of both [[International Criminal Court]] (ICC) and the [[International Criminal Tribunal for the Former Yugoslavia]] (ICTY).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.un.org/law/icc/statute/99_corr/2.htm ''Rome Statute of the International Criminal Court''], Article 7; [http://www.un.org/icty/legaldoc-e/index.htm ''Updated Statute of the International Criminal Tribunal for the Former Yugoslavia''], Article 5.&lt;/ref&gt; The gross human-rights violations integral to stricter definitions of ethnic cleansing are treated as separate crimes falling under the definitions for genocide or crimes against humanity of the statutes.&lt;ref&gt;Daphna Shraga and Ralph Zacklin [http://www.ejil.org/journal/Vol5/No3/art4-01.html "The International Criminal Tribunal for the Former Yugoslavia"], The European Journal of International Law Vol. 15 no.3 (2004).&lt;/ref&gt;

The UN Commission of Experts (established pursuant to Security Council Resolution 780) held that the practices associated with ethnic cleansing "constitute crimes against humanity and can be assimilated to specific war crimes. Furthermore ... such acts could also fall within the meaning of the Genocide Convention." The UN General Assembly condemned "ethnic cleansing" and racial hatred in a 1992 resolution.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.un.org/documents/ga/res/47/a47r080.htm A/RES/47/80] ""Ethnic cleansing" and racial hatred" United Nations. 12/16/1992. Retrieved on 2006, 09-03&lt;/ref&gt;

There are however situations, such as the [[Expulsion of Germans after World War II]], where ethnic cleansing has taken place without legal redress. [[Timothy V. Waters]] argues that if similar circumstances arise in the future, this precedent would allow the ethnic cleansing of other populations under international law.&lt;ref&gt;[http://law.bepress.com/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4600&amp;context=expresso Timothy V. Waters, ''On the Legal Construction of Ethnic Cleansing''], Paper 951, 2006, [[University of Mississippi]] School of Law. Retrieved on 2006, 12-13&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!--The emergence of ethnic cleansing as a distinct category of war crime has been a somewhat complex process. Each individual element of a programme of ethnic cleansing could be considered as an individual violation of humanitarian law - a killing here, a house-burning there - thus missing the systematic way in which such violations were perpetrated with a single aim in mind. International courts therefore consider individual incidents in the light of a possible pattern of ethnic cleansing. In the Yugoslav case, for instance, the ICTY considers the widespread massacres and abuses of human rights in Bosnia and Kosovo as part of an overall "joint criminal enterprise" to carve out ethnically pure states in the region.

However, many alleged "ethnic cleansings" in the past do not fit the modern definition of "crimes against humanity."  For example, the post-WW2 [[German expulsions]] were sanctioned by the international agreement at [[Potsdam conference]], requiring that the actions proceed humanely.--&gt; 

************************************
==Silent ethnic cleansing==

'''Silent ethnic cleansing''' is a term coined in the mid-1990s by some observers of the [[Yugoslav wars]].  Apparently concerned with Western-media representations of atrocities committed in the conflict &amp;mdash; which generally focused on those perpetrated by the [[Serbs]] &amp;mdash; atrocities committed against Serbs were dubbed "silent", on the grounds that they were not receiving adequate coverage. &lt;ref&gt;Krauthammer, Charles: "When Serbs Are 'Cleansed,' Moralists Stay Silent", ''International Herald Tribune'', 12 August 1995&lt;/ref&gt;

Since that time, the term has been used by other ethnically oriented groups for situations that they perceive to be similar &amp;mdash; examples include both sides in [[Northern Ireland]]'s continuing [[The Troubles|troubles]], and those who object to the expulsion of [[Volksdeutsche|ethnic Germans]] from former German territories during and after [[World War II]].

Some observers, however, assert that the term should only be used to denote population changes that do not occur as the result of overt violent action, or at least not from more or less organized aggression - the absence of such stressors being the very factor that makes it "silent" (although some form of coercion must logically exist).

==Instances of ethnic cleansing ==
This section lists incidents that have been termed "ethnic cleansing" by some academic or legal experts. Not all experts agree on every case; nor do all the claims necessarily follow definitions given in this article. Where claims of ethnic cleansing originate from non-experts (e.g., journalists or politicians) this is noted.

===Early instances===
*[[Neanderthal]]s were replaced by early modern [[human]]s traveling from Africa, with some experts believing that [[Cro-Magnon]]s committed a form of slow ethnic cleansing.&lt;ref&gt;[http://english.pravda.ru/science/mysteries/24-10-2007/99419-genocide-0 First genocide of human beings occurred 30,000 years ago]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qn4158/is_19990716/ai_n14258651 Science: The Neanderthal in all of us]&lt;/ref&gt;

* Ancient [[Assyria]] began to utilize [[Military history of the Assyrian Empire#Deportations|mass-deportation]] as a punishment for [[List of revolutions and rebellions|rebellions]] since the 13th century BC. By the 9th century BC the Assyrians made it a habit of regularly deporting thousands of restless subjects to other lands.

* [[Carthage]] was completely destroyed by [[Roman Republic|Rome]] in the [[Third Punic War]] (149-146 BC). 50,000 Carthaginians (perhaps a tenth of the original pre-[[war]] population) were sold into [[slavery in ancient Rome|slavery]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.infoplease.com/ipa/A0001198.html Ancient History]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.crystalinks.com/punicwars.html Punic Wars]&lt;/ref&gt;

* After conquering western [[Anatolia]] in 88 BC, [[Mithridates VI]] reportedly ordered the [[murder|killing]] of all [[Roman republic|Romans]] living there. The massacre of Roman men, women and children is known as the [[Asiatic Vespers]].&lt;ref&gt;Staff. [http://www.britannica.com/eb/topic-572893/Lucius-Cornelius-Sulla Mithradates VI Eupator], [[Encyclopaedia Britannica]]., Accessed [[26 December]] 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

* [[Julius Caesar]]'s campaign against the [[Helvetii]], the [[Celt]]ic inhabitants of modern [[Switzerland]]: approximately 60% of the tribe was killed, and another 20% was taken into [[slavery]]. The remainder of the Helvetii were driven back into their old lands.

* During the war against [[Cantabrian wars|tribes in northern Spain]] trying to resist the Romans, led by [[Roman emperor|emperor]] [[Augustus]], the latter is acknowledged for pursuing an extermination policy{{Fact|date=June 2008}} which included cleansing of the entire adult male population of [[Cantabria]] and [[Asturias]] and all of its culture were forcibly shattered and replaced by Roman or pro-Roman [[settler]]s.

* The ethnic cleansing and massacres of [[Roman Empire|Roman]] population of [[Roman Britain]] by [[Celt]]ic Britons during the [[Boudica]]'s revolt, in 60-61 AD.&lt;ref&gt;[http://observer.guardian.co.uk/uk_news/story/0,6903,406152,00.html Dig uncovers Boudicca's brutal streak]&lt;/ref&gt; 

* The Germanic [[Vandals]] were enslaved and deported from [[North Africa]] after the Vandal kingdom in North Africa was defeated by a [[Byzantine]] army during a [[Vandalic War]] in 533 and 534.&lt;ref&gt;[http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/secondary/BURLAT/17*.html J. B. Bury: History of the Later Roman Empire • Vol. II Chap. XVII]&lt;/ref&gt;

* The apartheid-like system existed in early [[Timeline of Anglo-Saxon England|Anglo-Saxon England]], which prevented the native [[Brython|British]] genes getting into the [[Anglo-Saxons|Anglo-Saxon]] population by restricting intermarriage and wiped out a majority of original British genes in favour of [[Germanic peoples|Germanic]] ones, according to a new study. According to research led by [[University College London]], Anglo-Saxon settlers enjoyed a substantial social and economic advantage over the native [[Celt|Celtic Britons]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/wales/2076470.stm English and Welsh are races apart]&lt;/ref&gt; who lived in what is now [[England]], for more than 300 years from the middle of the 5th century.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/articlerender.fcgi?artid=1635457 Evidence for an apartheid-like social structure in early Anglo-Saxon England]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.nationalgeographic.com/news/2006/07/060721-england.html Ancient Britain Had Apartheid-Like Society, Study Suggests]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newscientist.com/channel/life/genetics/dn9575-apartheid-slashed-celtic-genes-in-early-england.html 'Apartheid' slashed Celtic genes in early England]&lt;/ref&gt;

*[[St. Brice's Day massacre]] of 1002. The [[Anglo-Saxons|Anglo-Saxon]] King [[Ethelred the Unready]] ordered the death of all the [[Danish people|Danes]] living in the [[Kingdom of England]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ft.com/cms/s/0/e896f82e-871c-11dc-a3ff-0000779fd2ac,s01=1,stream=FTSynd.html?nclick_check=1 England’s massacre of the immigrants]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/radio4/history/making_history/making_history_winter2002.shtml BBC Making History]&lt;/ref&gt;

* The [[Pechenegs]], nomadic [[Turkic people]] from the [[steppe]], were nearly annihilated at the [[Battle of Levounion]] by a combined [[Byzantine]] and [[Cuman]] army in 1091. Attacked again in 1094 by the Cumans, many Pechenegs were slain or absorbed.

* [[Jews]] were frequently [[wiktionary:massacre|massacred]] and exiled from various European countries.  The persecution hit its first peak during the [[Crusades]]. In the [[First Crusade]] (1096) flourishing communities on the Rhine and the Danube were utterly destroyed; see [[German Crusade, 1096]]. In the [[Second Crusade]] (1147) the [[Jews in France]] were subject to frequent massacres.  The Crusades were followed by expulsions, including in, 1290, the banishing of all English Jews; in 1396, 100,000 Jews were expelled from France. 

* [[History of the Jews under Muslim rule|Jews]] and [[Christians]] expelled from [[Morocco]] and [[Islamic Spain]] during the reign of [[Berber people|Berber]] dynasty of [[Almohads]] in the 12th century. Almohads gave a choice of either death or conversion to [[Islam]], or exile. Some, such the family of [[Maimonides]], fled east to the more tolerant [[Islam by country|Muslim lands]], while others went northward to settle in the growing Christian kingdoms.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.theforgottenrefugees.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=66&amp;Itemid=39 The Forgotten Refugees]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.myjewishlearning.com/history_community/Medieval/IntergroupTO/JewishMuslim/Almohads.htm The Almohads]&lt;/ref&gt;

* At the beginning of the 13th century the eastern part of the [[Islamic world]] experienced the terrifying holocaust of the [[Mongol invasion]], which turned northern and eastern [[Iran]] into a desert. Over much of [[Central Asia]] speakers of [[Iranian languages]] were replaced by speakers of [[Turkic languages]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sfusd.k12.ca.us/schwww/sch618/Ibn_Battuta/Battuta's_Trip_Three.html Battuta's Travels: Part Three - Persia and Iraq]&lt;/ref&gt; 

* The [[conquest of Prussia]] was accomplished with much bloodshed over more than 50 years, during which native [[Prussians]] who remained unbaptised were subjugated, killed, or exiled. To replace the partially exterminated native population, the [[Teutonic Order]] encouraged the [[immigration]] of German colonists.

* In 1270, the Jews of [[Tunisia]] were required either to leave or to embrace Islam.

* The ethnic cleansing of the [[French people|French]] from [[Sicily]] during the [[Sicilian Vespers]] in 1282.

* The [[Crow Creek Massacre]] in 1325 was part of the ethnic cleansing of the Initial Coalescent people by the Middle Missouri villagers.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usd.edu/anth/crow/crow1.html Crow Creek Massacre]&lt;/ref&gt;

* Northern [[Iraq]] remained predominantly [[Assyrian Christian]] until the destructions of [[Tamerlane]], a [[Turco-Mongol]] conqueror, at the end of the 14th century.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.geocities.com/somasushma/Timur4.html The annihilation of Iraq]&lt;/ref&gt;

*  Between the 11th and 18th centuries, the [[Vietnamese people|Vietnamese]] expanded southward in a process known as {{lang|vi|nam tiến}} (''southward expansion''). In 1471 the kingdom of [[Champa]] suffered a massive defeat by the Vietnamese, in which 120,000 [[Cham people]] were either captured or killed, and the kingdom was reduced to a small enclave near [[Nha Trang]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cpamedia.com/history/cham_survivors/ The Chams: Survivors of a Lost Civilisation]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://countrystudies.us/vietnam/11.htm The Le Dynasty and Southward Expansion]&lt;/ref&gt;

*[[Spain]]'s large [[Islam|Muslim]] and [[Judaism|Jewish]] minorities, inherited from that country's former [[Islamic Spain|Islamic kingdoms]], were expelled following a [[Alhambra decree]] in 1492, while [[Converso|converts to Catholicism]], called [[Morisco]]s or [[Marrano]]s, were expelled between 1609 and 1614.&lt;ref&gt; Rezun, Miron, "Europe's Nightmare: The Struggle for Kosovo", (p. 6), Praeger/Greenwood (2001) ISBN 0-275-97072-8; Parker, Geoffrey, "Europe in Crisis", (p. 18), Blackwell Publishing (1979, 2000) ISBN 0-631-22028-3; Gadalla, Moustafa, "Egyptian Romany: The Essence of Hispania" (pp. 28-9), Tehuti Research Foundation (2004) ISBN 1-931446-19-9 &lt;/ref&gt;

* The deportations of the [[Armenians]] by Persian [[Safavids]], which begun in the 1530s under [[Tahmasp I]]. Between 1604 and 1605 [[Abbas I of Persia|Shah Abbas]] relocated some 150,000 Armenians to an area of [[Isfahan]] called [[New Julfa]].

* In 1622, the tribal chief of the Powhatan Confederacy of what is now [[Virginia]] in the [[United States]] planned the destruction of the English settlers. During the [[Jamestown Massacre]], the [[Powhatans]] killed 347 [[English people|English]] settlers throughout the Virginia colony, almost one-third of the English population of first permanent English colony in the New World.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bookrags.com/Indian_massacre_of_1622 Around 347 people were massacred in the attack]&lt;/ref&gt; However, according to international law this would not be ethnic cleansing but a legitimate attack on illegal settlers, since all civilians on occupied land are legitimate military targets, unless there was a treaty in place.

* Hundreds of thousands of [[Poles]] and [[Jews in Poland|Jews]] had been wiped out or driven from the lands of present-day Ukraine by [[Zaporozhian Cossacks]] during the [[Khmelnytsky Uprising]] (1648-1654).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?artid=808&amp;letter=C JewishEncyclopedia.com - "Cossacks' Uprising", by Herman Rosenthal]&lt;/ref&gt; As a result of events during [[Deluge (history)|The Deluge]], population of [[Polish-Lithuanian Commonwealth]] dropped by one-third.

* After the [[Cromwellian conquest of Ireland#Guerrilla warfare, famine and plague|Cromwellian conquest of Ireland]] and [[Act for the Settlement of Ireland 1652|Act of Settlement]] in 1652, [[Irish Catholics]] had most of their lands confiscated and were banned from living in towns for a short period. As many as 100,000 [[Irish people|Irish]] men, women and children were forcibly taken to the colonies in the [[West Indies]] and [[North America]] as [[indentured servants]] or [[slaves]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/northernireland/ashorthistory/archive/intro99.shtml BBC The curse of Cromwell]&lt;/ref&gt; The contemporary commentator Prendergast reported that four fifths of Ireland's population was removed or killed and that whole counties were empty. The remaining native Irish were confined to [[Connacht]] only and were immediately killed if found east of the River Shannon. Several thousand Irish soldiers were sold to the King of Spain, the Dutch and a Polish Privateer. The death toll could have been over 1 million.

* On [[August 10]], [[1680]], the [[Pueblo people|Pueblo]] Indians rose in revolt against Spanish rule. By the time the [[Pueblo Revolt]] succeeded, the Pueblo warriors killed 380 [[Spaniards|Spanish]] settlers and drove the surviving Europeans from [[New Mexico]]. By 1690s, certain Pueblo groups wanted the Spanish to come back to protect them against [[Apache]] and [[Navajo people|Navajo]] raiders.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hfac.uh.edu/gl/mav1.htm Resistance and Accommodation in New Mexico]&lt;/ref&gt;  

*[[Kosovo]] was taken temporarily by the [[Habsburg Monarchy|Austrian]] forces during the [[Great Turkish War]] with help of [[Serbian people|Serbian]] soldiers who lived in the Krajina within the Monarchy. After the Austrians retreated in 1690, hundreds of thousands of Serbs from Kosovo had to flee to [[Bosnia and Herzegovina|Bosnia]] and [[Vojvodina]] to evade [[Ottoman Empire|Ottoman]] reprisals.

===Colonial period===

* Conflict between [[Miao people|Miao]] groups and newly arrived [[Han Chinese|Han]] settlers increased during the 18th century under repressive economic and cultural reforms imposed by the [[Qing Dynasty]]. This led to armed conflict and large-scale migrations continuing into the late 19th century, the period during which most [[Hmong people]] emigrated to [[Southeast Asia]].&lt;ref&gt;Culas &amp; Michaud, 68–74.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.north-by-north-east.com/articles/04_04_1.asp The Hmong]&lt;/ref&gt;

* In the [[Great Expulsion]] of 1755, around 4000 to 5000 French [[Acadians]] were deported from Acadia by the British; many later settled in [[Acadiana|Louisiana]], where they became known as [[Cajuns]].

* In 18th century, the [[Dzungars]] were annihilated by [[Qianlong Emperor]] in several campaigns.  About 80% of the Dzungar population, or around 500.000 to 800.000 people, were killed during or after the Chinese conquest in 1755-1757.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www4.gu.edu.au:8080/adt-root/uploads/approved/adt-QGU20061121.163131/public/02Whole.pdf Michael Edmund Clarke, ''In the Eye of Power'' (doctoral thesis), Brisbane 2004, p37]&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Qing Dynasty]] filled in the depopulated area with immigrants from many parts of their empire, but a century later the [[Muslim Rebellion]] ravaged the same region.

* Expulsion and ethnic cleansing of the [[St. Domingue]]’s 40,000 white [[French people|French]] settlers during the [[Haitian Revolution]] from 1791 to 1804. [[Jean-Jacques Dessalines]], first ruler of an independent [[Haiti]], declared Haiti an all black nation, slaughtered all the remaining whites on the island and forbade [[Caucasian race|Caucasians]] from ever again owning property or land there. [http://www.fsmitha.com/h3/h34-np2.html] 

* Expulsion of more than a million [[Crimean Tatars]], [[Crimean Goths]] and [[Nogais]] of the [[Kuban]] and [[Budjak]] steppes to [[Ottoman Empire]] after the [[Crimean Khanate]] was annexed by Russia in 1783.

* When the [[Venezuelan War of Independence]] started, the Spanish enlisted the [[Llanero]]s, playing on their dislike of the ''[[Criollo (people)|criollo]]s'' of the independence movement. [[José Tomás Boves]] led an army of llaneros which routinely killed white Venezuelans. After several more years of war, which killed half of [[Venezuela]]'s white population, the country achieved independence from Spain in 1821.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.globalpr.org/knowledge/businessguides/prlandscape-venezuela.pdf Venezuela]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.venezuelanalysis.com/analysis/1491 A First-Hand Impression of the Venezuelan Opposition]&lt;/ref&gt;

* During the [[Chios Massacre]]  in 1822 about 42,000 [[Greeks|Greek]] islanders of [[Chios]] were massacred; 45,000 were [[slavery|enslaved]]; and 23,000 were exiled. Less than 2,000 Greeks managed to survive on the island.

* In the immediate aftermath of [[Pedro I of Brazil|Dom Pedro]]’s abdication in 1831, the poor people of color, including slaves, staged anti-[[Portuguese people|Portuguese]] riots in the streets of [[Brazil]]'s larger cities.&lt;ref&gt;[http://isc.temple.edu/evanson/brazilhistory/Bahia.htm Rebelions in Bahia]&lt;/ref&gt; 

* On [[November 19]] [[1835]], the [[Chatham Islands]] were [[invasion|invaded]] by mainland [[Māori]]. Some 300 [[Moriori]] men, women and children were massacred and the remaining 1,300 survivors were [[slavery|enslaved]]. By 1862, only 101 Morioris were left alive. Modern inhabitants are descendants of those who invaded and conquered the archipelago in 1835.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newzealandatoz.com/index.php?pageid=607&amp;PHPSESSID=1c2fab7979e45ccc7c3e7336e8636142 New Zealand A to Z | Chatham Islands]&lt;/ref&gt;   

* The ethnic cleansing of the light-skinned [[Spaniard|Spanish]] and [[Mestizo]] people by the [[Maya people|Mayas]] from the eastern [[Yucatan]] and the territory of [[Quintana Roo]] during the [[Caste War of Yucatán]].  The greatest success of the Maya revolt was reached in the spring of 1848, with the Europeans and Mestizos driven from most of the peninsula other than the walled cities of [[Campeche, Campeche|Campeche]] and [[Mérida, Yucatán|Mérida]] and the south-west coast.

* In the United States in the 19th century there were numerous instances of relocation of Native American peoples from their traditional areas to often remote reservations elsewhere in the country, particularly in the [[Indian Removal]] policy of the 1830s. The [[Trail of Tears]], which led to the deaths of about 2,000 to 8,000 [[Cherokees]] from disease, and the [[Long Walk of the Navajo]] are well-known examples.&lt;ref&gt;Perdue, Theda, ''Cherokee Women and the Trail of Tears'' in ''American Encounters: Natives and Newcomers from European Contact to Indian Removal, 1500-1850'', p. 526, (Routledge (UK), 2000)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Committee on Indian Affairs, US Senate, ''Cherokee Settlement and Accommodation Agreements Concerning the Navajo and Hopi Land Dispute'', (US General Printing Office, 1996)&lt;/ref&gt;[http://www.marionkentucky.us/Marion-Kentucky-trailoftears.htm]

* The [[Tasmanian aborigines|Tasmanians]], estimated at 8,000 people in 1803, were reduced to a population of around 300 by 1833, although much of this has been attributed to the effect of [[disease]]s to which they had no natural immunity (including [[smallpox]] and [[syphilis]]) and [[alcoholism]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.abc.net.au/pm/stories/s746130.htm Historian dismisses Tasmanian aboriginal genocide "myth"]&lt;/ref&gt; Estimates of the total number of Tasmanian deaths at the hands of European settlers vary, with some controversial estimates ranging as low as 118 in the period from 1803 until 1847.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.adelaideinstitute.org/Dissenters/windschuttle.htm Our history not rewritten but put right. Accusations of genocide have been based on guesswork and blatant ideology. SMH, 24 November 2002]&lt;/ref&gt;  This conflict is a subject of the [[Australia]]n [[history wars]]. 

* [[Ainu people]] are an ethnic group indigenous to [[Hokkaidō]], northern [[Honshū]], the [[Kuril Islands]], much of [[Sakhalin]], and the southernmost third of the [[Kamchatka peninsula]]. As Japanese settlement expanded, the Ainu were pushed northward, until by the [[Meiji period]] they were confined by the government to a small area in Hokkaidō, in a manner similar to the placing of Native Americans on reservations. 

* The ethnic cleansing of the [[Assyrian people|Assyrian]] Christian population from Eastern [[Anatolia]] by [[Kurdish people|Kurdish]] tribes, in 1842-1847.&lt;ref&gt;[http://debate.org.uk/topics/history/xstnc-6.html The Massacres of the Khilafah]&lt;/ref&gt; 

* Expulsion of Turkish, Muslim, and Jewish populations from [[Balkan]]s following the independence of Balkan countries (e.g., [[Serbia]], [[Greece]], [[Bulgaria]]) from [[Ottoman Empire]] from early 1800s to early 1900.&lt;ref&gt;Justin McCarthy, ''Death and Exile: The Ethnic Cleansing of Ottoman Muslims, 1821-1922'', (Princeton, N.J: Darwin Press, c1995&lt;/ref&gt;

*Expulsion of Muslim populations in [[Northern Caucasus]] by imperial [[Russia]] throughout 19th century. Particularly, expulsion of [[Adyghe people|Circassians]] to [[Anatolia]] in 1864.&lt;ref&gt;McCarthy, ''ibid.''&lt;/ref&gt; (see [[Muhajir (Caucasus)]] for more details)

* During the mid-19th century, the [[Muslim]]s of [[China]] revolted against the [[Qing Dynasty]], most notably in the [[Dungan revolt]] (1862-1877) and the [[Panthay rebellion]] 1856-1873) in [[Yunnan]]. The Manchu government committed genocide to suppress these little known revolts.&lt;ref&gt;Levene, Mark. Genocide in the Age of the Nation-State. I.B.Tauris, 2005. ISBN 1845110579, page 288&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Giersch, Charles Patterson. Asian Borderlands: The Transformation of Qing China's Yunnan Frontier. Harvard University Press, 2006. ISBN 1845110579, page 219&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Dillon, Michael. [http://www.hsais.org/2essay0405_4.htm China’s Muslim Hui Community]. Curzon, 1999. ISBN 0700710264, page xix&lt;/ref&gt; killing a million people in the [[Panthay rebellion]],&lt;ref&gt;Damsan Harper, Steve Fallon, Katja Gaskell, Julie Grundvig,
Carolyn Heller, Thomas Huhti, Bradley Maynew, Christopher Pitts. Lonely
Planet China. 9. 2005. ISBN 1740596870&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=chineseciv&gt;Gernet,
Jacques. A History of Chinese Civilization. 2. New York: Cambridge
University Press, 1996.ISBN 0521497124 &lt;/ref&gt; and several million in the [[Dungan revolt]].&lt;ref name=chineseciv/&gt; A ''"washing off the Muslims"''(洗回 (xi Hui)) policy had been long advocated by officials in the [[Qing Dynasty|Manchu]] government.&lt;ref&gt;Jonathan N. Lipman, "Familiar Strangers: A History of Muslims in Northwest China (Studies on Ethnic Groups in China)", University of Washington Press (February 1998), ISBN 0295976446.&lt;/ref&gt;

===20th century===
* [[Treaty of Neuilly]] (1919); Greece and Bulgaria exchange populations, with some exceptions.

* [[Greco-Turkish War (1919-1922)#Greek massacres of Turks|Massacres of the Turkish population by the Greek army of occupation]] and [[Greco-Turkish War (1919-1922)#Greek scorched earth policy|Greek scorched earth policy]] by Greek troops after their defeat in the Greco Turkish War. [[Greco-Turkish War (1919-1922)#Re-Capture of Smyrna.2C September 1922|Massacre of Greek population]] and sack of [[İzmir|Smyrna]] by Turkish troops. 

* The [[Population exchange between Greece and Turkey]] of Greeks from Turkey and of Turks from Greece after the [[Greco-Turkish War (1919-1922)]] as a consequence of the [[Treaty of Lausanne]] in 1923. 

* The [[Bolshevik]] regime killed or deported an estimated 300,000 to 500,000 [[Don Cossacks]] during the [[Russian Civil War]], in 1919-1920.&lt;ref&gt;Kort, Michael (2001). ''The Soviet Colossus: History and Aftermath'', p. 133. Armonk, NY: M.E. Sharpe. ISBN 0-7656-0396-9.&lt;/ref&gt;

* [[Polish minority in the Soviet Union|Deportation of Poles]] by the [[Soviet Union]] from [[Belarus]], [[Ukraine]] and European Russia to [[Kazakhstan]] in 1934-1938.

* [[Deportation of Koreans in the Soviet Union|Deportation of Koreans]] by the [[Soviet Union]] from the [[Russian Far East]] to [[Soviet Central Asia]] from September to October 1937. More than 172,000 Koreans were deported.

* The [[Mexican Repatriation|Great Repatriation]] of an estimated half million [[Mexican Americans]] from the [[Southwestern United States]] to [[Mexico]] by American [[Immigration and Naturalization Service|INS]] officials during the [[Great Depression]]. Approximately 60% of those hastenily deported are naturalized citizens who lived in the US for over 10 years, and their families, including US-born children of Mexican parents. Mexican-Americans whose ancestry dated back to the 19th century pre-annexation period are racially and ethnically harassed by INS officials out of [[nativism]] and fears of a "[[Reconquista (Mexico)|Mexican takeover]]" of the American Southwest.

* Forced displacement of 150,000 [[Czechs]] after October 1, 1938, when the German army entered the border regions of [[Czechoslovakia]] surrendered in accordance with the [[Munich Agreement]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.radio.cz/en/article/46238 Forced displacement of Czech population under Nazis in 1938 and 1943], Radio Prague&lt;/ref&gt;

* The persecutions and expulsions of [[Jews]] in [[Germany]], [[Austria]] and other [[Nazi]]-controlled areas prior to the initiation of [[the Holocaust|mass genocide]] in which 6 million Jews were killed.&lt;ref&gt;Naimark, ''op. cit.''&lt;/ref&gt;

* During the [[Finland|Finnish]] occupation of [[East Karelia]] during [[World War II]] the Russian speaking population of the city of [[Petrozavodsk]] was held in an [[concentration camp]].

* [[Expulsion of Poles by Germany]]. During World War II, Nazis planned to ethnically cleanse the whole Polish population. Eventually during [[Consequences of German Nazism|Nazi occupation]] up to 1.6 to 2 million [[Poles]] were expelled, not counting millions of [[slavery|slave labourers]] deported from Poland.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ushmm.org/education/resource/poles/poles.php?menu=/export/home/www/doc_root/education/foreducators/include/menu.txt&amp;bgcolor=CD9544 Poles: Victims of the Nazi Era]&lt;/ref&gt;

* More than 250,000 [[Serbs]] were expelled from [[Croatia]] by the extreme nationalist [[Ustashe]] regime during the [[Serbian Genocide]], in 1941-1945.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www1.yadvashem.org/about_yad/press_room/press_releases/croatian_president.html Ustasa, Croatian nationalist, fascist, terrorist movement created in 1930.]&lt;/ref&gt;

*During WWII, [[Japanese American internment|Japanese-Americans]] and [[Japanese Canadian internment|Japanese-Canadians were interned]] in camps due to fears that Japanese immigrants might be a [[fifth column]] supporting the [[Japanese Empire|enemy]].

* During WWII, in [[Kosovo &amp; Metohija]], some 10,000 Serbs lost their lives&lt;ref name=Krizman&gt;Serge Krizman, Maps of Yugoslavia at War, Washington 1943.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Istorija&gt;ISBN 86-17-09287-4: Kosta Nikolić, Nikola Žutić, Momčilo Pavlović, Zorica Špadijer: Историја за трећи разред гимназије природно-математичког смера и четврти разред гимназије општег и друштвено-језичког смера, Belgrade, 2002, pg. 182&lt;/ref&gt;, and about 80&lt;ref name=Krizman/&gt; to 100,000&lt;ref name=Krizman/&gt;&lt;ref name=Annexe&gt;[http://www.parliament.the-stationery-office.co.uk/pa/cm199900/cmselect/cmfaff/28/28ap42.htm Annexe I], by the Serbian Information Centre-London to a report of the Select Committee on Foreign Affairs of the [[British House of Commons|House of Commons]] of the [[Parliament of the United Kingdom]].&lt;/ref&gt; or more&lt;ref name=Istorija/&gt; were ethnically cleansed. Hundreds of thousands more Serbs would be ethnically cleansed from Kosovo by coercion in the decades from 1945 to 1991.

* Deportation of [[Volga German]]s by [[Soviet Union]] to [[Kazakhstan]], [[Altai Krai]], [[Siberia]], and other remote areas, in 1941-1942.

* [[Population transfer in the Soviet Union|Deportation]] of [[Crimean Tatars]], [[Kalmykia|Kalmyks]], [[Chechnya|Chechens]], [[Ingushetia|Ingush]], [[Balkars]], [[Karachay-Cherkessia|Karachay]]s, and [[Meskhetian Turks]] by [[Soviet Union]] to [[Central Asia]] and [[Siberia]], 1943-1944.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rferl.org/featuresarticle/2005/05/1350f316-420a-4a90-b42e-b59fe9fcc8e5.html 60 Years After: For Victims Of Stalin's Deportations, War Lives On]&lt;/ref&gt; 

* The ethnic cleansing of [[Hungarians]], or the [[1944-1945 Killings in Bačka|massacres in Bačka]] by [[titoist]] partisans during the winter of 1944-45, about 40.000 massacred.&lt;ref&gt;''[http://www.hungarian-history.hu/lib/cseres/ Tibor Cseres: Serbian vendetta in Bacska]&lt;/ref&gt; Afterwards, between 45-48, internation camps were set which led directly to the death of 70.000 more, of famine, frost, plagues, tortures and executions.

* The ethnic cleansing and [[massacres of Poles in Volhynia]] by nationalist [[Ukrainian Insurgent Army|UPA]] which took place in 1943 and 1944, with the bulk of victims reported for summer and autumn 1944.

* The ethnic cleansing of [[Cham Albanians]] from Southern [[Epirus]] by Greeks which took place in 1944 and 1945, circa 18,000-35000&lt;ref&gt; Victor Roudometof, Collective Memory, National Identity, and Ethnic Conflict Greece, Bulgaria, and the Macedonian Question, p.181-182 The figure of 30,000 is adopted from the Cham associations without checking the other sources used in the discussion in this chapter.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Chameria_issue#Muslim_Cham_Expulsion|fled]] to Albania, and from several hundred to 2,800  killed.

* [[Expulsion of Germans after World War II]]. From 1944 until 1948, between 13.5 and 16.5 million [[Germans]] were expelled, [[East Prussia#Evacuation of East Prussia|evacuated]] or fled from Central and Eastern Europe, making this the largest single instance of ethnic cleansing in recorded history. Estimated number of those who died in the process is being debated by historians and estimated between 500,000 and 3,000,000.&lt;ref&gt;''[http://cadmus.iue.it/dspace/bitstream/1814/2599/1/HEC04-01.pdf The Expulsion of 'German' Communities from Eastern Europe at the end of the Second World War]'', European University Institute, Florense. EUI Working Paper HEC No. 2004/1, Edited by Steffen Prauser and Arfon Rees pp. 4&lt;/ref&gt;

* [[Istrian exodus]] during and after World War II. The [[diaspora]] of 350,000 ethnic [[Italy|Italians]] from [[Istria]], [[Rijeka|Fiume]] and dalmatian [[Zadar|Zara]] lands, after the collapse of Italian [[fascism|fascist]] regime.

* [[Manchukuo|Manchuria]], under Soviet occupation following [[World War II]] and soon to become a battlefield between the [[People's Liberation Army|Chinese communist forces]] and the [[Republic of China Army|Nationalist forces]] was home to hundreds of thousands of [[Japanese people|Japanese]] citizens. [[Korea]] and [[Taiwan]], now free from Japanese rule, and [[Sakhalin]], under Soviet military occupation, were Japanese territories before World War II and had millions of [[Japanese people|Japanese]] residents. All these were now to be expelled. 

* The mass deportation of [[Ukrainians|Ukrainian]] speaking ethnic minorities from the territory of [[Poland]] after [[World War II]], culminating in 1947 with the start of [[Operation Wisla]]. Millions of [[Poles]] were simultaneously deported from [[Kresy|the eastern territories annexed by the Soviet Union]] into the western territories, which Soviets transferred from Germany to Poland. By 1950, 5 million Poles had been settled in what the government called the [[Regained Territories]].

* [[Communist]] regime in [[Romania]] begins evictions of the [[Greeks|Greek]] community, approx. 75,000 migrate.

* Mass expulsions of [[Hindu]]s and [[Sikh]]s from [[Pakistan]] to [[India]], and of [[Muslims]] from India to Pakistan. The controversy surrounding the [[partition of India|partition of British India]] in 1947&lt;ref&gt; Talbot, Ian:  "India and Pakistan", (pp. 198-99), Oxford University Press (2000) ISBN 0-340-70632-5 &lt;/ref&gt;,   resulted in the killings of [[Hindu]]s, [[Muslim]]s and [[Sikh]]s in riots. Well over 10 million people were violently displaced, and up to 500,000 lost their lives. However, unlike most other instances, ''no government agencies'' actively took part in the bloodshed, although reportedly a limited number of Indian and Pakistani troops and police posted along the border were partisan in their sympathies and abetted the rioters. Those that did not (as well as the last remaining British officers) were simply overwhelmed by the magnitude of the violence and could do little to stop it.

* After the annexation of the [[Muslim culture of Hyderabad|Muslim-ruled]] state of [[Hyderabad State|Hyderabad]] by India in 1948, about 7,000 Hadrami [[Arabs]] were interned and deported from [[India]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.al-bab.com/bys/articles/freitag99.htm British-Yemeni Society: Hadhrami migration in the 19th and 20th centuries]&lt;/ref&gt; 

* The [[Palestinian exodus]], in which the substantial majority of Arab [[Palestinians]] (approximately 700,000) in the areas of [[British Mandate of Palestine]] that became part of [[Israel]] left following the [[1948 Arab-Israeli War]]. In some instances they were forced to leave, in some they were encouraged to leave and in some they fled because of the war.&lt;ref&gt; [[Benny Morris]], The Birth of the Palestinian Refugee Problem Revisited. Cambridge University Press. (2004) ISBN 0-521-00967-7 &lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Yoav Gelber, Palestine 1948: War, Escape and the Emergence of the Palestinian Refugee Problem. Sussex Academic Press. (2005) ISBN 1-84519-075-0 &lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt; [[Ilan Pappe]], Ethnic Cleansing of Palestine. Oxford: Oneworld. (2006) ISBN 1-85168-467-0 &lt;/ref&gt;. Sixty years later there are still millions of Palestinian refugees living in refugee camps in neighboring countries.

* [[Jewish exodus from Arab lands]], in which 99 percent of [[Jews]] (approximately 800,000) from Arab countries left between the [[1948 Arab-Israeli War]] and the [[Six Day War]] in 1967. The major populations affected were in [[History of the Jews in Iraq|Iraq]], [[History of the Jews in Syria|Syria]], [[History of the Jews in Yemen|Yemen]], [[History of the Jews in Egypt|Egypt]], [[History of the Jews in Libya|Libya]], [[History of the Jews in Algeria|Algeria]], [[History of the Jews in Tunisia|Tunisia]] and [[History of the Jews in Morocco|Morocco]].&lt;ref&gt; Itamar Levin, Locked Doors: The Seizure of Jewish Property in Arab Countries. Praeger/Greenwood. (2001) ISBN 0-275-97134-1 &lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Shohat, Ella: "Sephardim in Israel: Zionism from the Standpoint of Its Jewish Victims", Social Text, No. 19/20, (Autumn, 1988), (pp. 1-35), Duke University Press&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt; Maurice Roumani, The Case of the Jews from Arab Countries: A Neglected Issue, Tel Aviv: World Organization of Jews from Arab Countries. (1977) ASIN B0006EGL5I&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt; Malka Hillel Schulewitz, The Forgotten Millions: The Modern Jewish Exodus from Arab Lands. London. (2001) ISBN 0-8264-4764-3&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Ran HaCohen, [http://www.antiwar.com/hacohen/h011303.html "Ethnic Cleansing: Some Common Reactions"]&lt;/ref&gt;

* After [[Indonesia]] received independence from the [[Netherlands]] in 1949, around 300.000 people, predominantly [[Indo people|Indo]]s or Dutch Indonesians (people of mixed Indonesian and European descent), fled or were expulsed from Indonesia.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dutchmalaysia.net/press/Easternization.html Easternization of the West: Children of the VOC]&lt;/ref&gt;

* Displacement of [[Kashmir]]i's who have fled the Indian military action in Kashmir, most have fled to Pakistan as well as to Britain, Canada and the USA.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jammu-kashmir.com/archives/archives2008/kashmir20080407b.html Kashmiri refugees denied property ownership rights in Pakistan]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Kashmiri Pandits|Kashmiri Hindus]] living in [[Kashmir]] due to the ongoing and anti-[[Republic of India|Indian]] insurgency. Some 300,000 Hindus have been internally displaced from Kashmir due to the violence.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/in.html India], ''The World Factbook''. Retrieved 20 May 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

*In the aftermath of the 1949 Durban Riots (an inter-racial conflict between [[Zulu]]s and [[Asians in South Africa]]), hundreds of Indians fled Cato Manor.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.theindianstar.com/index.php?uan=5786 Current Africa race riots like 1949 anti-Indian riots: minister], TheIndianStar.com&lt;/ref&gt;

* On 5 and 6 September 1955 the [[Istanbul Pogrom]] or "Septembrianá"/"Σεπτεμβριανά"  was launched against the Greek population of [[Constantinople]], it was secretly backed by the Turkish government ,some Jews and Armenians of the city were also attacked by the mob, the event contributed greatly to the gradual extinction of the Greek minority in the city and country which numbered 100,000 in 1924 after the Turko-Greek population exchange treaty and only 5000 in 2007 and was followed by the Turkish government planned expulsion of the Greek minority in the [[Imbros]] and [[Tenedos]] islands in the period 1923-1993 ([[source needed]]).

* On 5 July 1960, five days after the [[Democratic Republic of the Congo|Congo]] gained independence from Belgium, the [[Force Publique]] garrison near [[Léopoldville]] mutinied against its white officers and attacked numerous European targets. This caused the fear amongst the approximately 100,000 [[white African|whites]] still resident in the Congo and mass exodus from the country.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.historylearningsite.co.uk/united_nations_congo.htm ::UN:: History Learning Site]&lt;/ref&gt;  

*[[Ne Win|Ne Win's]] rise to power in 1962 and his relentless persecution of "resident aliens" (immigrant groups not recognised as citizens of the [[Union of Burma]]) led to an exodus of some 300,000 [[Burmese Indians]] from racial discrimination and particularly after wholesale nationalisation of private enterprise a few years later in 1964.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Martin Smith|year=1991|title=Burma - Insurgency and the Politics of Ethnicity|publisher=Zed Books|location=London,New Jersey|pages=43-44,98,56-57,176}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,875949,00.html Asians v. Asians], TIME&lt;/ref&gt;

*The creation of the [[apartheid]] system in South Africa, which began in 1948 but reached full flower in the 1960s and 1970s, involved some ethnic cleansing, including the separation of blacks, [[Coloureds]], and whites, as well as the creation of [[Bantustans]], which involved [[Apartheid#Forced removals|forced removals]] of non-white populations.&lt;ref&gt; Bell, Terry: "Unfinished Business: South Africa, Apartheid and Truth", (pp. 63-4), Verso, (2001, 2003) ISBN 1-85984-545-2 &lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt; Valentino, Benjamin A., "Final Solutions: Mass Killing and Genocide in the Twentieth Century", (p. 189), Cornell University Press, (2004) ISBN 0-8014-3965-5. &lt;/ref&gt;

* Mass expulsion of the [[pied-noir]] population of European descent and [[History of the Jews in Algeria|Jews]] from [[Algeria]] to [[France]]. In just a few months in 1962, 900,000 of these Europeans and native Jewish people left the country.&lt;ref&gt;[http://marketplace.publicradio.org/shows/2006/08/01/PM200608016.html Marketplace: Pied-noirs breathe life back into Algerian tourism]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://lexicorient.com/e.o/pied-noir.htm Pied-Noir]&lt;/ref&gt;

* The ethnic cleansing of the [[Arabs]] and [[Demographics of India|Indians]] from [[Zanzibar]] in 1964.&lt;ref&gt;[http://channel4.empireschildren.co.uk/category/chapters/index.php?chapter=472&amp;cat=3 Country Histories - Empire's Children]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://whosfaultisit.blogspot.com/2006/09/homemade-genocide-arab-world-is.html Who's Fault Is It?]&lt;/ref&gt;

* Some 150,000 Italians settled in [[Libya]], constituting about 18% of the total population.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.britannica.com/eb/article-46562/Libya Libya - Italian colonization]&lt;/ref&gt; All of Libya's [[Italians]] were expelled from the North African country in 1970, a year after [[Muammar al-Gaddafi]] seized power (a "day of vengeance" on 7 October, 1970).&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/4380360.stm Libya cuts ties to mark Italy era ]&lt;/ref&gt;

* By 1969, more than 350,000 [[Salvador]]ans were living in [[Honduras]]. In 1969, Honduras enacted a new land reform law. This law took land away from Salvadoran immigrants and redistributed this land to native-born Honduran peoples. Thousands of Salvadorans were displaced by this law (see [[Football War]]). 

* During the [[Bangladesh War of Independence]] of 1971 around 10 million [[Bengalis]] fled the country to escape the killings and [[1971 Bangladesh atrocities|atrocities]] committed by the [[Pakistan]] Army.

* The forced expulsion of [[Uganda]]'s entire [[Non-resident Indian and Person of Indian Origin|Asian]] population by [[Idi Amin]]'s regime.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/onthisday/hi/dates/stories/august/7/newsid_2492000/2492333.stm 1972: Asians given 90 days to leave Uganda]&lt;/ref&gt;

*The ethnic cleansing between 1963–1974 of [[Turkish Cypriots]] by Greek Cypriots and Greek military forces.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mediaprof.org/tcvoices/trnchist/trnccr74.html TRNC: Chronology - 1963-1974&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

* The ethnic cleansing in 1974-76 of the [[Greeks|Greek]] population of the areas under Turkish military occupation in [[Cyprus]] during and after the [[Turkish Invasion of Cyprus]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lobbyforcyprus.org/press/press1998-1940/suntimes230177.htm Turkish invasion of Cyprus&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;.

* Following the U.S. withdrawal from [[Vietnam]] in 1975, the Lao kingdom was overthrown by the communists and the [[Hmong people]] became targets of retaliation and persecution. Thousands made the trek to and across the [[Mekong River]] into [[Thailand]], often under attack. This marked the beginning of a [[Conflict in Laos involving the Hmong|mass exodus of Hmong people]] from [[Laos]].

* The [[Khmer Rouge]] regime in [[Cambodia]] disproportionately targeted ethnic minority groups. These included ethnic [[Overseas Chinese|Chinese]], [[Vietnamese people|Vietnamese]] and [[Thai people|Thai]]. In the late 1960s, an estimated 425,000 ethnic Chinese lived in Cambodia, but by 1984, as a result of Khmer Rouge [[genocide]] and emigration, only about 61,400 Chinese remained in the country. The [[Cham people|Cham]] Muslims suffered serious purges with as much as half of their population exterminated. A Khmer Rouge order stated that henceforth “The Cham nation no longer exists on Kampuchean soil belonging to the [[Khmer people|Khmers]]” (U.N. Doc. A.34/569 at 9).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ppu.org.uk/genocide/g_cambodia1.html Genocide - Cambodia]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.genocidewatch.org/aboutgenocide/stantoncambodianlaw.htm The Cambodian Genocide and International Law]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.country-studies.com/cambodia/the-chinese.html Cambodia the Chinese]&lt;/ref&gt; 

* Subsequent waves of hundreds of thousands of [[Rohingya people|Rohingya]] fled [[Burma]] and many refugees inundated neighbouring Bangladesh including 250,000 in 1978 as a result of the [[King Dragon operation in Arakan]]. 

* The [[Sino-Vietnamese War]] resulted in the discrimination and consequent migration of [[Vietnam]]'s [[Hoa|ethnic Chinese]]. Many of these people fled as "[[boat people]]". In 1978-79, some 450,000 ethnic Chinese left Vietnam by boat as refugees (many officially encouraged and assisted) or were expelled across the land border with China.

* Aftermath of [[Indira Gandhi]] assassination in 1984 Oct 31, the ruling party [[Indian National Congress]] supporters formed large mobs and killed around 3000 [[Sikhs]] around Delhi which is known as the [[Anti Sikh Riots]] during the next four days. The mobs using the support of ruling party leaders used the Election voting list to identify Sikhs and kill them.

*  At least one million Iraqi [[Kurds]] were displaced and an estimated 100,000-200,000 killed during the [[Al-Anfal Campaign]] (1986-1989). 

* The forced assimilation campaign of the late 80s directed against ethnic [[Turkish people|Turks]] resulted in the emigration of some 300,000 [[Turks in Bulgaria|Bulgarian Turks]] to Turkey.

* The [[Nagorno Karabakh]] conflict has resulted in the displacement of population from both sides. 528,000 [[Azerbaijanis]] from Nagorno Karabakh Armenian controlled territories including Nagorno-Karabakh, and 185,000&lt;ref name="autogenerated1"&gt;Building Security in Europe's New Borderlands, Renata Dwan, M.E. Sharpe (1999) p. 148&lt;/ref&gt; to 220,000 Azeris, 18,000 Kurds and 3,500 Russians fled from [[Armenia]] to Azerbaijan from 1988 to 1989.&lt;ref&gt;De Waal, ''Black Garden'', p. 285&lt;/ref&gt; 280,000 to 304,000&lt;ref name="autogenerated1" /&gt; persons&amp;mdash;virtually all ethnic [[Armenians]]&amp;mdash;fled [[Azerbaijan]] during the 1988–1993 war over the disputed region of Nagorno-Karabakh.&lt;ref&gt;[http://ourworld.compuserve.com/homepages/usazerb/refugees.htm Refugees and displaced persons in Azerbaijan]&lt;/ref&gt;

* Since April 1989, some 70,000 black Mauritanians -- members of the [[Peul]], [[Wolof]], [[Soninke]] and [[Bambara]] ethnic groups -- have been expelled from [[Mauritania]] by the Mauritanian government.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.irinnews.org/report.aspx?ReportId=70522 Fair elections haunted by racial imbalance]&lt;/ref&gt; 

* In 1989, after bloody pogroms against the [[Meskhetian Turks]] by [[Uzbeks]] in Central Asia's [[Ferghana Valley]], nearly 90,000 Meskhetian Turks left [[Uzbekistan]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.irinnews.org/report.aspx?reportid=28663 Focus on Mesketian Turks]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cal.org/co/pdffiles/mturks.pdf Meskhetian Turk Communities around the World]&lt;/ref&gt;

* In 1991, following a crackdown on [[Rohingya people|Rohingya]] Muslims in [[Myanmar]], 250,000 refugees took shelter in the [[Cox's Bazar]] district of neighbouring Bangladesh.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/asia-pacific/7019882.stm Burmese exiles in desperate conditions], BBC News&lt;/ref&gt;

* As a result of [[1991–1992 South Ossetia War]], about 100,000 ethnic [[Ossetians]] fled [[South Ossetia]] and Georgia proper, most across the border into North Ossetia. A further 23,000 ethnic [[Georgians]] fled South Ossetia and settled in other parts of [[Georgia (country)|Georgia]].&lt;ref&gt; Human Rights Watch/Helsinki, [http://hrw.org/reports/1996/Russia.htm RUSSIA. THE INGUSH-OSSETIAN CONFLICT IN THE PRIGORODNYI REGION], May 1996.&lt;/ref&gt; According to [[Helsinki Watch]], the campaign of ethnic-cleansing was orchestrated by the Ossetian militants, during the events of [[Ossetian–Ingush conflict]], which resulted in [[expulsion]] of approximately 60,000 [[Ingush]] inhabitants from Prigorodny District.&lt;ref&gt;Russia: The Ingush-Ossetian Conflict in the Prigorodnyi Region (Paperback) by Human Rights Watch Helsinki Human Rights Watch (April 1996) ISBN 1564321657&lt;/ref&gt;

* The widespread ethnic cleansing accompanying the [[Yugoslav wars]] from 1991 to 1999, of which the most significant examples occurred in eastern [[Croatia]] and self-proclaimed [[Republic of Serbian Krajina]] (1991-1995) (see [[Operation Storm]]), in most of [[Bosnia and Herzegovina|Bosnia]] (1992-1995), and in the [[Albanians|Albanian]]-dominated breakaway [[Kosovo]] province (of [[Serbia]]) (1999). Large numbers of [[Serbs]], [[Croats]], [[Bosniaks]] and [[Albanians]] were forced to flee their homes and expelled.&lt;ref&gt;Committee on Foreign Relations, US Senate, ''The Ethnic Cleansing of Bosnia-Hercegovina'', (US General Printing Office, 1992)&lt;/ref&gt; Beginning in 1991, political upheavals in the [[Balkans]] displaced about 2,700,000 people by mid-1992, of which over 700,000 of them sought asylum in [[Europe]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/specials/bosnia/context/dayton.html Bosnia: Dayton Accords]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E3D61339F937A15752C1A963958260&amp;n=Top/Reference/Times%20Topics/Subjects/I/Immigration%20and%20Refugees Resettling Refugees: U.N. Facing New Burden]&lt;/ref&gt; 

* The forced displacement and [[Ethnic cleansing of Georgians in Abkhazia|ethnic-cleansing]] of more than 250,000 people, mostly [[Georgians]] but some others too, from [[Abkhazia]] during the conflict and after in 1993 and 1998.&lt;ref&gt; Bookman, Milica Zarkovic, "The Demographic Struggle for Power", (p. 131), Frank Cass and Co. Ltd. (UK), (1997) ISBN 0-7146-4732-2 &lt;/ref&gt; 

* The 1994 massacres of nearly 1,000,000 [[Tutsis]] by [[Hutus]], known as the [[Rwandan Genocide]]&lt;ref&gt; Leeder, Elaine J., "The Family in Global Perspective: A Gendered Journey", (p. 164-65), Sage Publications, (2004) ISBN 0-7619-2837-5 &lt;/ref&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[better citation needed]&lt;/sup&gt;

* The mass expulsion of southern [[Lhotshampa]]s (Bhutanese of Nepalese origin) by the northern [[Druk]] majority of [[Bhutan]] in 1990.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.voanews.com/uspolicy/2006-10-19-voa1.cfm Voice of America (18 October 2006)] &lt;/ref&gt; The number of refugees is approximately 103,000.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unhcr.org/cgi-bin/texis/vtx/publ/opendoc.htm?tbl=PUBL&amp;id=4444d3c93e UNHCR Publication (State of the world refugees)]&lt;/ref&gt;

* An estimated 1,000 [[Tamil people]] were killed, tens of thousands of houses were destroyed by the [[Sinhala people|Sinhalese]]-dominated government of [[Sri Lanka]] in what is commonly known as [[Black July]].The murder, looting and general destruction of property was well organized. Mobs armed with petrol were seen stopping passing motorists at critical street junctions and, after ascertaining the ethnic identity of the driver and passengers, setting alight the vehicle with the driver and passengers trapped within it. Mobs were also seen stopping buses to identify Tamil passengers and subsequently these passengers were knifed, clubbed to death or burned alive.

* Displacement of more than 500,000 [[Chechen people|Chechen]] and ethnic [[Russians|Russian]] civilians living in [[Chechnya]] during the [[First Chechen War]] in 1994-1996.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.globalsecurity.org/military/world/war/chechnya1.htm First Chechnya War]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jamestown.org/edm/article.php?article_id=2369902 Ethnic Russians in the North of Caucasus - Eurasia Daily Monitor]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.reliefweb.int/rw/rwb.nsf/0/bb82d320aa527436c1256c560037d0a6?OpenDocument&amp;Click= Chechen census fiasco]&lt;/ref&gt;

* The [[Jakarta riots of May 1998]] targeted many [[Chinese Indonesian]]s. Suffering from lootings and arsons, many Chinese Indonesians fled from [[Indonesia]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://edition.cnn.com/WORLD/asiapcf/9808/29/indonesia.riot/ Anti-Chinese riots continue in Indonesia], August 29, 1998, CNN&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.businessweek.com/2000/00_41/b3702149.htm Wages of Hatred], Business Week&lt;/ref&gt;

* More than 800,000 Kosovar [[Albanians]] fled their homes in [[Kosovo]] during the [[Kosovo War]] in 1998-9, after being expelled. Although on the contrary over 200,000 [[Serbs]] and other non-Albanian minorities were forced out of Kosovo during and after the war while most [[Albanians]] returned.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/serbia/article/0,,1713498,00.html Serbia threatens to resist Kosovo independence plan]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://hrw.org/english/docs/2004/03/18/serbia8129.htm Kosovo/Serbia: Protect Minorities from Ethnic Violence (Human Rights Watch)]&lt;/ref&gt;

* There have been serious outbreaks of inter-ethnic [[violence]] on the island of Kalimantan since 1997, involving the indigenous [[Dayak people]]s and immigrants from the island of [[Madura]]. In 2001 in the Central [[Kalimantan]] town of Sampit, at least 500 [[Madurese people|Madurese]] were killed and up to 100,000 Madurese were forced to flee. Some Madurese bodies were decapitated in a ritual reminiscent of the [[headhunting]] tradition of the Dayaks of old.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.globalpolicy.org/security/natres/timber/2001/0301brno.htm Behind Ethnic War, Indonesia's Old Migration Policy]&lt;/ref&gt;

===21st century===
* In 2003, Sinafasi Makelo, a representative of [[Mbuti]] [[Pygmies]], told the UN's Indigenous People's Forum that during the [[Second Congo War|Congo Civil War]], his people were hunted down and eaten as though they were game animals. Both sides of the war regarded them as "subhuman" and some say their flesh can confer magical powers. Makelo asked the [[UN Security Council]] to recognise [[cannibalism]] as a crime against humanity and an act of [[genocide]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/3869489.stm DR Congo pygmies 'exterminated']&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/2933524.stm DR Congo Pygmies appeal to UN]&lt;/ref&gt;

* In the late-1990s and early 2000s, [[paramilitaries]] organized and armed by the [[Indonesia]]n military and police forces murdered large numbers of civilians in [[East Timor]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.iht.com/articles/1999/04/29/edjose.2.t.php Yes to Kosovo, No to East Timor? - International Herald Tribune&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.abc.net.au/7.30/stories/s50444.htm 7.30 Report - 8/9/1999: Ethnic cleansing will empty East Timor if no aid comes: Belo&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.alternet.org/columnists/story/1096/ U.S. Fiddles While East Timor Burns | AlterNet&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;James M. Lutz, Brenda J. Lutz, ''[http://books.google.com/books?id=1gW12Wdr1QsC&amp;pg=RA1-PA209&amp;lpg=RA1-PA209&amp;dq=east+timor+ethnic+cleansing&amp;source=web&amp;ots=H6lg4hL9Du&amp;sig=Ha2vDTPiYCdc2iNMl4oKGYjzoiI Global Terrorism]''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.globalsecurity.org/military/library/news/1999/09/990908-timor7.htm Outrage Over East Timor&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hoover.org/publications/digest/3476806.html Hoover Institution - Hoover Digest - Why East Timor Matters&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://media.www.westernherald.com/media/storage/paper881/news/2004/05/10/Opinion/We.Cannot.Look.The.Other.Way.On.Ethnic.Cleansing-2124595.shtml We cannot look the other way on ethnic cleansing - Opinion&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

* Since the mid-1990s the central government of [[Botswana]] has been trying to move [[Bushmen]] out of the [[Central Kalahari Game Reserve]]. As of October 2005, the government has resumed its policy of forcing all Bushmen off their lands in the Game Reserve, using armed police and threats of violence or death.&lt;ref name="Daily Telegraph"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/main.jhtml?xml=/news/2005/10/29/wbot29.xml&amp;sSheet=/news/2005/10/29/ixworld.html
|title=Bushmen forced out of desert after living off land for thousands of years |publisher=The Daily Telegraph |accessdate=2005-10-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many of the involuntarily displaced Bushmen live in squalid resettlement camps and some have resorted to [[prostitution]] and [[alcoholism]], while about 250 others remain or have surreptitiously returned to the [[Kalahari]] to resume their independent lifestyle.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.nationalgeographic.com/news/2004/09/0914_040914_labushmen_2.html African Bushmen Tour U.S. to Fund Fight for Land]&lt;/ref&gt; “How can we continue to have [[Stone Age]] creatures  in an age of computers?“ asked Botswana’s president [[Festus Mogae]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.motherjones.com/news/dispatch/2005/01/01_800.html Exiles of the Kalahari]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.survival-international.org/news/1454 UN condemns Botswana government over Bushman evictions]&lt;/ref&gt;

* Expulsion of [[white people|white]] farmers by the [[Robert Mugabe|Mugabe]] regime in [[Zimbabwe]] in 2000. There were 270,000 [[whites in Zimbabwe]] (when the country was known as [[Rhodesia]]) in 1970. There are only a few thousand whites left in Zimbabwe today. 

* The removal of around 8,500 Jews (including the forced removal of about half of them)&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/middle_east/4159958.stm 'Israel evicts Gaza Strip settlers'], BBC News Online, [[17 August]], 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; from the [[Gaza Strip]], and around 660 from four small settlements in the [[West Bank]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/middle_east/4172694.stm 'Settlers and army clash in W Bank'], BBC News Online, [[22 August]], 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; in 2005 through the implementation of [[Israel's unilateral disengagement plan]].&lt;ref&gt;Robinson, Eugene. [http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2005/08/18/AR2005081801642.html "Betrayed in Gaza"], ''[[Washington Post]]'', August 19, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Klein, Morton A. [http://www.jewishjournal.com/home/preview.php?id=11876 "Gaza Withdrawal Rewards Terrorism"], ''[[The Jewish Journal of Greater Los Angeles]]'' February 27, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Jeff Jacoby|Jacoby, Jeff]]. [http://www.jewishworldreview.com/jeff/jacoby_2005_04_01.php3 "Sharon's retreat is a victory for terrorists"], ''Jewish World Review'', April 1, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Gross, Tom. [http://www.tomgrossmedia.com/ExodusFromGaza.html Exodus From Gaza] Tom Gross Mid-East Media Analysis. Retrieved November 4, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

* Attacks by the [[Janjaweed]], militias of [[Sudan]] on the [[African]] population of [[Darfur]], a region of western Sudan.&lt;ref&gt; Collins, Robert O., "Civil Wars and Revolution in the Sudan: Essays on the Sudan, Southern Sudan, and Darfur, 1962-2004
", (p. 156), Tsehai Publishers (US), (2005) ISBN 0-9748198-7-5 .&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Power, Samantha  "Dying in Darfur: 
Can the ethnic cleansing in Sudan be stopped?"[http://www.newyorker.com/fact/content/?040830fa_fact1], ''The New Yorker'', [[30 August]] [[2004]].
Human Rights Watch, [http://hrw.org/english/docs/2004/05/05/darfur8536.htm "Q &amp; A: Crisis in Darfur"] (web site, retrieved [[24 May]] [[2006]]).
Hilary Andersson, [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/programmes/from_our_own_correspondent/3752871.stm "Ethnic cleansing blights Sudan"], ''BBC News'', 27 May 2004.&lt;/ref&gt; A [[July 14]] [[2007]] article notes that in the past two months up to 75,000 Arabs from [[Chad]] and [[Niger]] crossed the border into Darfur. Most have been relocated by the Sudanese government to former villages of displaced non-Arab people. Some 2.5 million have now been forced to flee their homes after attacks by Sudanese troops and Janjaweed militia.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.independent.co.uk/world/africa/article2768232.ece Arabs pile into Darfur to take land 'cleansed' by janjaweed]&lt;/ref&gt;  

*Currently in the [[Iraq Civil War]] (2003 to present), entire neighborhoods in [[Baghdad]] are being ethnically cleansed by [[Shia]] and [[Sunni]] Militias.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/middle-east/iraq-is-disintegrating-as-ethnic-cleansing-takes-hold-478937.html Iraq is disintegrating as ethnic cleansing takes hold]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://weekly.ahram.org.eg/2006/784/sc4.htm "There is ethnic cleansing"]&lt;/ref&gt; Some areas are being evacuated by every member of a particular secular group due to lack of security, moving into new areas because of fear of reprisal killings. As of [[June 21]] [[2007]], the [[United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees]] estimated that 2.2 million Iraqis had been displaced to neighboring countries, and 2 million were displaced internally, with nearly 100,000 Iraqis fleeing to Syria and Jordan each month.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cnn.com/2007/WORLD/meast/06/20/damon.iraqrefugees/index.html Iraq refugees chased from home, struggle to cope]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.boston.com/news/world/middleeast/articles/2006/11/03/un_nearly_100000_flee_iraq_monthly/ U.N.: 100,000 Iraq refugees flee monthly]. Alexander G. Higgins, ''[[Boston Globe]],'' [[November 3]], [[2006]]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/30/world/middleeast/30mosul.html?hp In North Iraq, Sunni Arabs Drive Out Kurds]&lt;/ref&gt; 

*Although [[Iraqi Christians]] represent less than 5% of the total Iraqi population, they make up 40% of the [[refugees]] now living in nearby countries, according to [[UNHCR]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usatoday.com/news/world/iraq/2007-03-22-christians-iraq_N.htm Christians, targeted and suffering, flee Iraq]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.asianews.it/index.php?l=en&amp;art=7410 IRAQ Terror campaign targets Chaldean church in Iraq - Asia News&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; In the 16th century, Christians constituted half of Iraq's population.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unhcr.org/cgi-bin/texis/vtx/iraq?page=news&amp;id=461e5a644 UNHCR | Iraq]&lt;/ref&gt; In 1987, the last Iraqi census counted 1.4 million Christians.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.irinnews.org/report.aspx?reportid=61897 Christians live in fear of death squads]&lt;/ref&gt; But as the [[2003 invasion of Iraq|2003 invasion]] has reawakened Islamic sensibilities, Christians' total numbers slumped to about 500,000, of whom 250,000 live in Baghdad.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/pope/story/0,,1961207,00.html Jonathan Steele: While the Pope tries to build bridges in Turkey, the precarious plight of Iraq's Christians gets only worse | World news | guardian.co.uk&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, the [[Mandaeans|Mandaean]] and [[Yazidi]] communities are at the risk of elimination due to the ongoing atrocities by [[Islamism|Islamic]] extremists.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/6412453.stm Iraq's Mandaeans 'face extinction']&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/20294868/ Iraq's Yazidis fear annihilation]&lt;/ref&gt; A [[May 25]] [[2007]] article notes that in the past 7 months only 69 people from Iraq have been granted [[Immigration to the United States#Asylum for refugees|refugee status]] in the [[United States]].&lt;ref&gt;Ann McFeatters: [http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/opinion/317322_mcfeatters27.html Iraq refugees find no refuge in America]. ''[[Seattle Post-Intelligencer]]'' May 25, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

* The ethnic cleansing of [[African American]] population of some racially mixed [[Los Angeles]] neighborhoods by [[Mexican American|Mexican]] [[gangs in the United States|street gangs]]. According to gang experts and law enforcement agents the [[Mexican Mafia]] leaders, or shot callers, have issued a "green light" on all blacks.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.latimes.com/news/printedition/opinion/la-op-hernandez7jan07,1,414328.story?coll=la-news-comment&amp;ctrack=1&amp;cset=true Roots of Latino/black anger]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.alternet.org/story/46855/ Ethnic Cleansing in L.A.]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.blackamericaweb.com/site.aspx/bawnews/stateof/hutchinson105 Thanks to Latino Gangs, There’s a Zone in L.A. Where Blacks Risk Death if They Enter]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/main.jhtml?xml=/news/2007/01/23/wgangs23.xml FBI called to deal with 'race' gang violence]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://observer.guardian.co.uk/world/story/0,,2036580,00.html A bloody conflict between Hispanic and black gangs is spreading across Los Angeles]&lt;/ref&gt;

*In October 2006, [[Niger]] announced that it would deport the [[Arabs]] living in the Diffa region of eastern Niger to Chad.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/6087048.stm Niger starts mass Arab expulsions]&lt;/ref&gt; This population numbered about 150,000.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.alertnet.org/thenews/newsdesk/L25138454.htm Reuters Niger's Arabs say expulsions will fuel race hate]&lt;/ref&gt; While the government was rounding Arabs in preparation for the [[deportation]], two girls died, reportedly after fleeing government forces, and three women suffered miscarriages. Niger's government had eventually suspended a controversial decision to deport Arabs.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/6081416.stm Niger's Arabs to fight expulsion]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unhcr.org/cgi-bin/texis/vtx/refworld/rwmain?docid=469638881e UNHCR | Refworld - The Leader in Refugee Decision Support]&lt;/ref&gt;

*In 1950, the [[Karen people|Karen]] had become the largest of 20 minority groups participating in an insurgency against the [[military dictatorship]] in [[Burma]]. The conflict continues as of 2008. In 2004, the BBC, citing [[aid agencies]], estimates that up to 200,000 Karen have been driven from their homes during decades of war, with 120,000 more refugees from Burma, mostly Karen, living in [[refugee camp]]s on the Thai side of the border. Many accuse the military government of Burma of ethnic cleansing.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/asia-pacific/4987224.stm Burma Karen families 'on the run'], BBC News&lt;/ref&gt; As a result of the [[Internal conflict in Burma|ongoing war]] in minority group areas more than two million people have fled Burma to [[Thailand]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.refugeesinternational.org/content/article/detail/1142/?PHPSESSID=3fc64258eda9d44c2 " Human Rights in Burma: Fifteen Years Post Military Coup "], Refugees International&lt;/ref&gt;

*[[Civil unrest in Kenya (2007–present)|Civil unrest in Kenya]] erupted in December 2007.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usatoday.com/news/world/2008-01-30-kenya-violence_N.htm U.S. envoy calls violence in Kenya 'ethnic cleansing']&lt;/ref&gt; By [[January 28]], [[2008]], the death toll from the violence was at around 800.&lt;ref&gt;[http://english.aljazeera.net/NR/exeres/CA34AA32-041D-497D-BE2B-A463562C6FFF.htm Al Jazeera English - News - Kenya Ethnic Clashes Intensify&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; The United Nations estimated that as many as 600,000 people have been displaced.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2008/02/11/world/main3815702.shtml U.N.: 600,000 Displaced In Kenya Unrest]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/7174670.stm BBC NEWS | Africa | Kenya opposition cancels protests&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; A government spokesman claimed that Odinga's supporters were "engaging in ethnic cleansing".&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/7167363.stm BBC NEWS | Africa | Kenya diplomatic push for peace&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

*The [[2008 attacks on North Indians in Maharashtra]] began on February 3, 2008. Incidences of violence against [[North India]]ns and their property were reported in [[Bombay]], [[Pune]], [[Aurangabad district, Maharashtra|Aurangabad]], [[Beed]], [[Nashik]], [[Amravati]], [[Jalna district|Jalna]] and [[Latur]]. Nearly 25,000 North Indian workers fled Pune,&lt;ref name="IE_Pune_flee"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.expressindia.com/latest-news/25-000-North-Indian-workers-leave-Pune/276576/3/|accessdate=2008-04-06|title=25000 North Indian workers leave Pune|publisher=''[[Indian Express]]''}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="TOI_Pune_flee"&gt;{{cite news|title=25000 North Indians leave, Pune realty projects hit|url=http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/25000_North_Indians_leave_Pune_realty_projects_hit_/articleshow/2809937.cms|accessdate=2008-04-04|publisher=''[[Times of India]]''}}&lt;/ref&gt; and another 15,000 fled Nashik in the wake of the attacks.&lt;ref name="TOI_Nashik_flee"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/articleshow/2780795.cms|accessdate=2008-04-06|publisher=''[[Times of India]]''|date=2008-02-14|title=Maha exodus: 10,000 north Indians flee in fear}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Red_Nashik_flee"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.rediff.com/news/2008/feb/13nasik1.htm|accessdate=2008-04-06|title=MNS violence: North Indians flee Nashik, industries hit|date=2008-02-13|publisher=[[Rediff]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*[[2008 South Africa riots|South Africa Ethnic Cleansing]] erupted on 11 May 2008 within three weeks [http://www.irinnews.org/Report.aspx?ReportId=78458 80 000 were displaced] the death toll was [http://www.news24.com/News24/South_Africa/Xenophobia/0,,2-7-2382_2332419,00.html 62,] with 670 injured by the violence when South Africans ejected non-nationals in a nationwide ethnic cleansing / Xenophobic outburst ejecting the "makwerekwere" [http://www.thoughtleader.co.za/mandelarhodesscholars/2008/05/15/on-makwerekwere/ BLACKer Africans]. The most affected have been Zimbabweans (30 000), Mozambiqueans (20 000 have returned to Mozambique), Somalians, Ethiopians, Congolese, Angolans.  Local South Africans have also been caught up in the violence and so have other non-African nationals. [http://www.iol.co.za/index.php?set_id=1&amp;click_id=13&amp;art_id=vn20080528060919101C395802 Refugee camps a mistake] Arvin Gupta, a senior UNHCR protection officer, said the UNHCR did not agree with the City of Cape Town that those displaced by the violence should be held at camps across the city.

==In Fiction==

In the book, [[The Chronicles of Narnia: Prince Caspian]] the [[Telmarines]] trying to wipe out the [[Narnians]] is a form of ethnic cleansing.

==See also==
{{Portal|Genocide|GenocidePortalLogo(ESR)2.JPG}}
* [[Violence]]
* [[Ethnocide]]
* [[Population transfer]]
* [[Forced settlements in the Soviet Union]]
* [[Civilian casualties]], civilian, non-combatant persons killed or injured by direct military action
* [[Command responsibility]]
* [[Crime against humanity]]
* [[Cultural assimilation]]
* [[Ethnic Cleansing (computer game)|Ethnic Cleansing]], a computer game.
* [[German exodus from Eastern Europe]]
* [[World War II evacuation and expulsion]]
* [[Germanisation]]
* [[List of events named massacres]]
* [[List of wars and disasters by death toll]]
* [[Caste War of Yucatán]]
* [[1989 events in Mauritania and Senegal|1989 events]] 
* [[Partition of India#Independence and population exchanges|Partition of India]]
* [[1971 Bangladesh atrocities]]
* [[Persecution of Hindus]]
* [[Persecution of Muslims]]
* [[Expulsion of Asians in Uganda in 1972]]
* [[Generalplan Ost]]
* [[Population transfer in the Soviet Union]]
* [[Polish minority in the Soviet Union]]
* [[Transmigration program]]
* [[Refugees of Iraq]]
* [[Sinophobia]]
* [[The Holocaust]]

==Notes==
{{reflist|2}}

==References ==
* {{cite journal |author=Bell-Fialkoff, Andrew |title=A Brief History of Ethnic Cleansing |journal=Foreign Affairs |volume=72 |issue=3 |year=1993 |pages=110}}  [http://www.foreignaffairs.org/19930601faessay5199/andrew-bell-fialkoff/a-brief-history-of-ethnic-cleansing.html]
* {{cite journal |author=Jackson Preece, Jennifer |title=Ethnic Cleansing As An Instrument of Nation-State Creation |journal=Human Rights Quarterly |volume=20 |issue=4 |year=1998 |pages=359 |doi=10.1353/hrq.1998.0039}}  
* {{cite journal |author=Petrovic, Drazen |title=Ethnic Cleansing - An Attempt at Methodology |journal=European Journal of International Law |volume=5 |issue=4 |year=1998 |pages=817}}  [http://www.ejil.org/journal/Vol5/No3/art3.pdf]

== External links ==
* [http://www.warcrimes.info/ Documents and Resources on War, War Crimes and Genocide]
* [http://www.ryanspencerreed.com/ Photojournalist's Account] - Images of ethnic cleansing in Sudan
* [http://law.bepress.com/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4600&amp;context=expresso Timothy V. Waters, ''On the Legal Construction of Ethnic Cleansing''], Paper 951, 2006, [[University of Mississippi]] School of Law (PDF)
* [http://learning.lib.vt.edu/slav/genocide.html Genocides and Ethnic Cleansings of Central and East Europe, the Former USSR, the Caucasus and Adjacent Middle East -- 1890 - 2007]
* [http://www.koteka.net/ Ethnic Cleansing in West Papua]
*[http://www.world-science.net/exclusives/070525_ethnic-cleansing.htm ''Dump the “ethnic cleansing” jargon, group implores''] [[May 31]] [[2007]], World Science

{{Racism topics|state=collapsed}}

[[Category:Ethnic cleansing| ]]
[[Category:Forced migration]]
[[Category:Human rights abuses]]
[[Category:Persecution]]
[[Category:Racism]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]

[[ar:تطهير عرقي]]
[[bs:Etničko čišćenje]]
[[bg:Етническо прочистване]]
[[ca:Neteja ètnica]]
[[da:Etnisk udrensning]]
[[de:Ethnische Säuberung]]
[[el:Εθνοκάθαρση]]
[[et:Etniline puhastus]]
[[es:Limpieza étnica]]
[[eo:Etna purigado]]
[[fr:Nettoyage ethnique]]
[[ko:민족청소]]
[[it:Pulizia etnica]]
[[he:טיהור אתני]]
[[nl:Etnische zuivering]]
[[ja:民族浄化]]
[[no:Etnisk rensning]]
[[nn:Etnisk reinsing]]
[[pl:Czystka etniczna]]
[[ro:Purificare etnică]]
[[ru:Этнические чистки]]
[[sr:Етничко чишћење]]
[[fi:Etninen puhdistus]]
[[sv:Etnisk rensning]]
[[tr:Etnik temizlik]]
[[uk:Етнічна чистка]]
[[zh:种族清洗]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>