<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20031108174502|1697718" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="61098" pageid="61098" ns="0" title="Ethnic cleansing"><revisions><rev timestamp="2003-11-09T04:46:11Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Ethnic cleansing''' is a general term (considered by some to be a [[euphemism]]) used to describe the forced removal of an [[ethnic group]] from an area, in order to create an ethnically homogenous state. The term became popularized in the war in the former [[Yugoslavia]] during the [[1990s]], to describe actions done by Serb forces, later applying the same to the acts of [[Croatia]]n, [[Bosniak]] and ethnic [[Albanian]] forces. Often, the term is used in cases where [[genocide]] (or [[democide]]) is not appropriate by the number of people killed. Still, campaigns of "ethnic cleansing" tend to carry atrocities with them.

"Ethnic cleansing" is designated a [[crime against humanity]] in international treaties, such as that which created the [[International Criminal Court]].
The [[International Criminal Tribunal for the Former Yugoslavia]] was set up in asimilar spirit, and prosecutes these crimes under more generic names. 

==Transfer==

Some argue that mass population "transfers" can create political situations which are more stable than those involving multi-ethnic states, citing the [[partition of India]] and the post-World War II political situation in Eastern Europe. Others raise disturbing questions about historical events such as the [[German expulsion after World War II]].</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>