<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20091114101803|325775577" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="61098" pageid="61098" ns="0" title="Ethnic cleansing"><revisions><rev timestamp="2009-11-16T17:42:18Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{distinguish|Genocide}}
{{For|the video game|Ethnic Cleansing (video game)}}
{{Discrimination sidebar}}

'''Ethnic cleansing''' is a term that has come to be used broadly to describe all forms of ethnically-motivated violence, ranging from murder, rape, and torture to the [[population transfer|forcible removal of populations]].&lt;ref name=Carmichaelp2&gt;Carmichael, 2002, [http://books.google.ca/books?id=wN4A0FMweQoC&amp;pg=PA1&amp;dq=%22ethnic+cleansing%22+UN+definition#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false p. 2].&lt;/ref&gt; A 1993 [[United Nations]] Commission defined it more specifically as, "the planned deliberate removal from a specific territory, persons of a particular [[ethnic group]], by force or intimidation, in order to render that area ethnically homogenous."&lt;ref name=Carmichaelp2/&gt; The term entered English and international media usage in the early 1990s to describe [[Yugoslav wars|war events]] in the former [[ex-Yugoslavia|Yugoslavia]]. 

The term ethnic cleansing is not to be confused with genocide. These terms are not synonymous, yet the academic discourse considers both as existing in a spectrum of assaults on nations or religio-ethnic groups. Simply put, ethnic cleansing is similar to forced deportation or 'population transfer' whereas genocide is the "intentional murder of part or all of a particular ethnic, religious, or national group." &lt;ref name=Schabas&gt;[Schabas W. A., 2000, Genocide in International Law, Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.][http://books.google.com/books?id=pYptuRHDQPgC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=genocide+in+international+law#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false]&lt;/ref&gt; The idea in ethnic cleansing is "to get people to move, and the means used to this end range from the legal to the semi-legal."&lt;ref name=Naimark&gt; Naimark, 2001 [Naimark N. M., 2001, Fires of Hatred: Ethnic Cleansing in 20th Century Europe, Cambridge: Harvard University Press.][http://books.google.com/books?id=L-QLXnX16kAC&amp;dq=naimark+2001&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s] &lt;/ref&gt;Some academics consider genocide as a subset of "murderous ethnic cleansing." &lt;ref name=Mann&gt; [Mann M., 2005,The Dark Side of Democracy: Explaining Ethnic Cleansing, Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.][http://books.google.com/books?id=cGHGPgj1_tIC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=The+Dark+Side+of+Democracy#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false]&lt;/ref&gt; Thus, these concepts are different, but related,
"literally and figuratively, ethnic cleansing bleeds into genocide, as mass murder is committed in order to rid the land of a people."&lt;ref name=MassVio&gt;[Naimark, N. 2007, Theoretical Paper: 
Ethnic Cleansing, Online Encyclopedia of Mass Violence][http://www.massviolence.org/Ethnic-Cleansing]&lt;/ref&gt;

Synonyms include ''ethnic purification''.&lt;ref&gt;Drazen Petrovic, [http://www.ejil.org/journal/Vol5/No3/art3.html "Ethnic Cleansing - An Attempt at Methodology"], ''European Journal of International Law'', Vol. No. 3. Retrieved 20 May 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Definitions==
The official [[United Nations]] definition of ethnic cleansing is "rendering an area ethnically homogeneous by using force or [[intimidation]] to remove from a given area persons of another ethnic or religious group"&lt;ref&gt;Hayden, Robert M. (1996) [http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0037-6779(199624)55%3A4%3C727%3ASFGECA%3E2.0.CO;2-Y Schindler's Fate: Genocide, Ethnic Cleansing, and Population Transfers]. ''[[Slavic Review]]'' 55 (4), 727-48.&lt;/ref&gt;

The term ethnic cleansing has been defined as a spectrum, or continuum by some historians. In the words of [[Andrew Bell-Fialkoff]]:

:''[E]thnic cleansing [...] defies easy definition. At one end it is virtually indistinguishable from forced emigration and population exchange while at the other it merges with [[deportation]] and [[genocide]]. At the most general level, however, ethnic cleansing can be understood as the expulsion of a population from a given territory''.&lt;ref&gt;Andrew  Bell-Fialkoff, "[http://www.foreignaffairs.org/19930601faessay5199/andrew-bell-fialkoff/a-brief-history-of-ethnic-cleansing.html A Brief History of Ethnic Cleansing]", Foreign Affairs 72 (3): 110, Summer 1993. Retrieved 20 May 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

Terry Martin has defined ethnic cleansing as ''"the forcible removal of an ethnically defined population from a given territory"'' and as ''"occupying the central part of a continuum between genocide on one end and nonviolent pressured ethnic emigration on the other end."''&lt;ref name="martin"&gt;Martin, Terry (1998). [http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0022-2801%28199812%2970%3A4%3C813%3ATOOSEC%3E2.0.CO%3B2-A The Origins of Soviet Ethnic Cleansing]. ''[[The Journal of Modern History]]'' 70 (4), 813-861. pg. 822 &lt;/ref&gt;

In reviewing the [[International Court of Justice]] (ICJ) [[Bosnian Genocide Case]] in the judgement of [[Jorgic v. Germany]] on 12 July 2007 the [[European Court of Human Rights]] quoted from the ICJ ruling on the ''Bosnian Genocide Case'' to draw a distinction between ''ethnic cleansing'' and ''genocide''.

{{quotation|The term 'ethnic cleansing' has frequently been employed to refer to the events in [[Bosnia and Herzegovina]] which are the subject of this case ... [[UN General Assembly|General Assembly]] resolution 47/121 referred in its Preamble to 'the abhorrent policy of 'ethnic cleansing', which is a form of genocide', as being carried on in Bosnia and Herzegovina. ... It [''i.e. ethnic cleansing''] can only be a form of genocide within the meaning of the [[Convention on the Prevention and Punishment of the Crime of Genocide|[Genocide] Convention]], if it corresponds to or falls within one of the categories of acts prohibited by Article II of the Convention. Neither the intent, as a matter of policy, to render an area “ethnically homogeneous”, nor the operations that may be carried out to implement such policy, can as such be designated as genocide: the intent that characterizes genocide is “to destroy, in whole or in part” a particular group, and deportation or displacement of the members of a group, even if effected by force, is not necessarily equivalent to destruction of that group, nor is such destruction an automatic consequence of the displacement. This is not to say that acts described as 'ethnic cleansing' may never constitute genocide, if they are such as to be characterized as, for example, 'deliberately inflicting on the group conditions of life calculated to bring about its physical destruction in whole or in part', contrary to Article II, paragraph (c), of the Convention, provided such action is carried out with the necessary specific intent (''[[dolus specialis]]''), that is to say with a view to the destruction of the group, as distinct from its removal from the region. As the [[ICTY]] has observed, while 'there are obvious similarities between a genocidal policy and the policy commonly known as 'ethnic cleansing' ' (''Krstić,'' IT-98-33-T, Trial Chamber Judgment, 2 August 2001, para. 562), yet '[a] clear distinction must be drawn between physical destruction and mere dissolution of a group. The expulsion of a group or part of a group does not in itself suffice for genocide. |ECHR quoting the ICJ&lt;ref&gt;[[European Court of Human Rights|ECHR]] [http://cmiskp.echr.coe.int/tkp197/view.asp?item=54&amp;portal=hbkm&amp;action=html&amp;highlight=&amp;sessionid=1448788&amp;skin=hudoc-en Jorgic v. Germany] §45 citing Bosnia and Herzegovina v. Serbia and Montenegro (“Case concerning the application of the Convention on the Prevention and Punishment of the Crime of Genocide”) the International Court of Justice (ICJ) found under the heading of “intent and 'ethnic cleansing'” § 190&lt;/ref&gt;}}

==Origins of the term==

The term, ''ethnic cleansing'',  appears to have been popularised by the international media some time around 1992. It may have originated some time before the 1990s in the military doctrine of the former [[Yugoslav People's Army]], which spoke of "cleansing the field" (''čišćenje terena'', {{IPA-sh|tʃîʃtɕeːɲe terěːna|}}) of enemies to take total control of a conquered area. The origins of this doctrine are unclear.

During the 1990s the term  was used extensively by the media in the former [[Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia|Yugoslavia]] in relation to the [[Croatian War of Independence]], since Serb paramilitary forces and JNA engaged in forcible removal of Croats and other non-Serbs from areas of Croatia occupied by rebel Serbs. Rebel Serbs and JNA have committed widespread and systematic acts of persecution (murder, violence, detention, intimidation) against non-Serb population creating a such coercive atmosphere, atmosphere of fear, that targeted population had no option but to flee or to be deported by force. These acts were carried out from at least August 1991. The displacement of non-Serb population which followed these attacks was not merely the consequence of military action, but in fact its primary objective.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.un.org/icty/pressreal/2007/pr1162e-summary.htm ICTY] Summary of judgement for Milan Martić.&lt;/ref&gt;

A [[Carnegie Endowment]] report on the [[Balkan Wars]] in 1914 points out that village-burning and ethnic cleansing have traditionally accompanied [[Balkan]] wars, regardless of ethnicities involved. In probably the earliest attestation of the term, [[Vuk Karadžić]] makes use of the word ''cleanse'' to describe what happened to the [[Turkish people|Turks]] in [[Belgrade]] when the city was captured by the [[Karadjordje]]'s forces in 1806.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Judah, Tim |title=The Serbs: History, Myth and the Destruction of Yugoslavia |year=1997 |location=New Haven and London |publisher=Yale University Press|pages=75}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Konstantin Nenadović]] wrote in his biography of famous Serbian leader published in 1883 that after the fighting ''"the [[Serbs]], in their bitterness (after 500 years of Turkish occupation), slit the throats of the Turks everywhere they found them, sparing neither the wounded, nor the woman, nor the Turkish children"''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Mirko Grmek, Marc Gjidara, Neven Simac|title=Le Nettoyage ethnique: Documents historiques sur une idéologie serbe |year=1993 |location=Paris |language=French|pages=24}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Later attestation of the term ''cleansing'' can be found on 16 May 1941, during the [[World War II|Second World War]], by one [[Viktor Gutic|Viktor Gutić]], a commander in the Croatian [[extremist]] faction, the [[Ustase|Ustaše]]: ''Every Croat who today solicits for our enemies not only is not a good Croat, but also an opponent and disrupter of the prearranged, well-calculated plan for cleansing ''[čišćenje]'' our [[Independent State of Croatia|Croatia]] of unwanted elements [...].''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pavelicpapers.com/documents/ndhnews/ndhn0004.html Pavelicpapers.com]&lt;/ref&gt;{{Verify credibility|date=June 2008}} The Ustaše carried out large-scale ethnic cleansing and genocide of [[Serbs of Croatia|Serbs in Croatia]] during the [[World War II|Second World War]] and sometimes used the term "cleansing" to describe it.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pavelicpapers.com/documents/ndh/ndh002.html Pavelicpapers.com]&lt;/ref&gt;.

Some time later, on 30 June 1941, [[Stevan Moljević]], a lawyer from [[Banja Luka]] who was an ideologue of the [[Chetnik]]s, published a booklet with the title ''On Our State and Its Borders''. Moljević assessed the circumstances in the following manner: ''"One must take the opportunity of the war conditions and at a suitable moment take hold of the territory marked on the map, cleanse ''[očistiti]'' it before anybody notices and with strong battalions occupy the key places (...) and the territory surrounding these cities, freed of non-[[Serbs|Serb]] elements. The guilty must be promptly punished and the others deported - the [[Croats]] to (significantly amputated) Croatia, the [[Muslims]] to [[Turkey]] or perhaps [[Albania]] - while the vacated territory is settled with Serb refugees now located in Serbia.''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bosnia.org.uk/bosrep/report_format.cfm?articleid=3025&amp;reportid=169 The Moljevic Memorandum]&lt;/ref&gt;{{Verify credibility|date=May 2009}}

The term "cleansing", more specifically the [[Russian language|Russian]] term "cleansing of borders", ''ochistka granits'' (очистка границ), was used in [[Soviet Union]] documents of the early 1930s in reference to the resettlement of [[Poles]] from the 22-km [[Border Security Zone of Russia|border zone]] in [[Byelorussian SSR]] and [[Ukrainian SSR]]. The process was repeated on a larger and wider scale in 1939–1941, involving many other ethnicities with cross-border ties to foreign [[nation-states]], see [[Involuntary settlements in the Soviet Union]] and [[Population transfer in the Soviet Union]].&lt;ref name="martin"/&gt; 

A similar term with the same intent was used by the [[Nazism|Nazi]] administration in [[Germany]] under [[Adolf Hitler]]. When an area under Nazi control had its entire [[Jew]]ish population removed, whether by driving the population out, by deportation to [[Concentration Camp]]s, and/or [[murder]], the area was declared ''[[judenrein]]'', (lit. "Jew Clean"): "cleansed of Jews".(cf. [[racial hygiene]]).

==Ethnic cleansing as a military and political tactic==
[[Image:Abkhazia genocidememorial2005.jpg|200px|thumb|The 12th anniversary of ethnic cleansing in [[Abkhazia]] which was held in [[Tbilisi]] in 2005. One of the visitors of the gallery recognized her dead son on the photograph]]
The purpose of ethnic cleansing is to remove the conditions for potential and actual opposition, whether political, guerrilla or military, by physically removing any potentially or actually hostile ethnic communities. Although it has sometimes been motivated by a doctrine that claim an ethnic group is literally "unclean" (as in the case of the [[Jews in the Middle Ages|Jews of medieval Europe]]), more usually it has been a rational (if brutal) way of ensuring that total control can be asserted over an area. 

Ethnic cleansing was a common phenomenon in the [[Bosnian war]]. This typically entailed intimidation, forced expulsion and/or killing of the undesired ethnic group as well as the destruction or removal of the physical vestiges of the ethnic group, such as places of worship, cemeteries and cultural and historical buildings. According to numerous ICTY verdicts, Serb&lt;ref name="ICTY: Radoslav Brđanin judgement"&gt;{{cite  web|url=http://www.un.org/icty/brdjanin/trialc/judgement/index.htm|title=ICTY: Radoslav Brđanin judgement}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Croat&lt;ref name="ICTY: Kordić and Čerkez verdict"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.un.org/icty/kordic/trialc/judgement/index.htm|title=ICTY: Kordić and Čerkez verdict}}&lt;/ref&gt; forces performed ethnic cleansing of their territories planned by their political leadership in order to create ethnically pure states ([[Republika Srpska]] and [[Herzeg-Bosnia]]). Furthermore, Serb forces committed [[Srebrenica genocide|genocide in Srebrenica]] at the end of the war.&lt;ref&gt;ICTY; "Address by ICTY President Theodor Meron, at Potočari Memorial Cemetery" The Hague, 23 June 2004 [http://www.un.org/icty/pressreal/2004/p860-e.htm]&lt;/ref&gt;

Based on the evidence of numerous Croat forces attacks against Bosnian Muslims (Bosniaks), the ICTY Trial Chamber concluded in the ''Kordić and Čerkez case'' that by April 1993 Croat leadership from Bosnia and Herzegovina had a common design or plan conceived and executed to [[Lašva Valley ethnic cleansing|ethnically cleanse Bosniaks from the Lašva Valley]] in Central Bosnia. [[Dario Kordić]], as the local political leader, was found to be the planner and [[wikt:instigator|instigator]] of this plan.&lt;ref name="ICTY: Kordić and Čerkez verdict - IV. Attacks on towns and villages: killings - C. The April 1993 Conflagration in Vitez and the Lašva Valley - 3. The Attack on Ahmići (Paragraph 642)"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.un.org/icty/kordic/trialc/judgement/kor-tj010226e-5.htm#IVC3|title=ICTY: Kordić and Čerkez verdict - IV. Attacks on towns and villages: killings - C. The April 1993 Conflagration in Vitez and the Lašva Valley - 3. The Attack on Ahmići (Paragraph 642)}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1993, during the [[War in Abkhazia|Georgian-Abkhaz conflict]], armed [[Abkhaz]] [[separatist]] insurgency, confronted with large population of ethnic [[Georgians]], implemented a campaign of [[Ethnic cleansing of Georgians in Abkhazia|ethnic cleansing]] against the ethnic Georgians (Georgians formed the single largest ethnic group in pre-war Abkhazia, with a 45.7% plurality as of 1989) of [[Abkhazia]].&lt;ref&gt;US State Department, Country Reports on Human Rights Practices for 1993, Abkhazia case.&lt;/ref&gt; As the results, more than 250,000 ethnic Georgians were forced to flee and approximately 30,000 people were killed during separate incidents involving massacres and expulsion. (See [[Ethnic cleansing of Georgians in Abkhazia]])&lt;ref&gt; Chervonnaia, Svetlana Mikhailovna. ''Conflict in the Caucasus: Georgia, Abkhazia, and the Russian Shadow.'' Gothic Image Publications, 1994. &lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt; ''S State Department, Country Reports on Human Rights Practices for 1993, February 1994, Chapter 17. &lt;/ref&gt; This was recognized as ethnic cleansing by [[OSCE]] conventions and was also mentioned in [[UN General Assembly Resolution]] GA/10708.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.un.org/News/Press/docs//2008/ga10708.doc.htm General Assembly Adopts Resolution Recognizing Right Of Return By Refugees, Internally Displaced Persons To Abkhazia, Georgia&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; 

As a tactic, ethnic cleansing has a number of significant impacts. It enables a force to eliminate civilian support for resistance by eliminating the civilians &amp;mdash; recognizing [[Mao Zedong]]'s dictum that guerrillas among a civilian population are fish in water, it removes the fish by draining the water. When enforced as part of a political settlement, as happened with the [[Expulsion of Germans after World War II|forced resettlement of ethnic Germans to the new Germany]] after 1945, it can contribute to long-term stability.&lt;ref&gt; Judt, Tony. ''Postwar: A History of Europe Since 1945'' Penguin Press, 2005&lt;/ref&gt; Some individuals of the large German population in [[Czechoslovakia]] and prewar [[Poland]] had encouraged Nazi [[jingoism]] before the Second World War, but this was forcibly resolved&lt;ref&gt; Judt, Tony. ''Postwar: A History of Europe Since 1945'' Penguin Press, 2005. &lt;/ref&gt;. It thus establishes "[[facts on the ground]]" - radical demographic changes which can be very hard to reverse. 

For the most part, ethnic cleansing is such a brutal tactic and so often accompanied by large-scale bloodshed that it is widely reviled. It is generally regarded as lying somewhere between [[population transfer]]s and [[genocide]] on a scale of odiousness, and is treated by [[international law]] as a [[war crime]].

[[Image:Marcharmenians.jpg|right|thumb|300px|[[Armenia]]n civilians, being cleansed from their homeland during the [[Armenian Genocide]]]]

==Ethnic cleansing as a crime under international law==
There is no formal legal definition of ethnic cleansing.&lt;ref&gt; Ward Ferdinandusse, [http://www.ejil.org/journal/Vol15/No5/9.pdf The Interaction of National and International Approaches in the Repression of International Crimes], The European Journal of International Law Vol. 15 no.5 (2004), p. 1042, note 7.&lt;/ref&gt; However, ethnic cleansing in the broad sense - the forcible deportation of a population - is defined as a crime against humanity under the statutes of both [[International Criminal Court]] (ICC) and the [[International Criminal Tribunal for the Former Yugoslavia]] (ICTY).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.un.org/law/icc/statute/99_corr/2.htm ''Rome Statute of the International Criminal Court''], Article 7; [http://www.un.org/icty/legaldoc-e/index.htm ''Updated Statute of the International Criminal Tribunal for the Former Yugoslavia''], Article 5.&lt;/ref&gt; The gross human-rights violations integral to stricter definitions of ethnic cleansing are treated as separate crimes falling under the definitions for genocide or crimes against humanity of the statutes.&lt;ref&gt;Daphna Shraga and Ralph Zacklin [http://www.ejil.org/journal/Vol5/No3/art4-01.html "The International Criminal Tribunal for the Former Yugoslavia"], The European Journal of International Law Vol. 15 no.3 (2004).&lt;/ref&gt;

The UN Commission of Experts (established pursuant to Security Council Resolution 780) held that the practices associated with ethnic cleansing "constitute crimes against humanity and can be assimilated to specific war crimes. Furthermore ... such acts could also fall within the meaning of the Genocide Convention." The UN General Assembly condemned "ethnic cleansing" and racial hatred in a 1992 resolution.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.un.org/documents/ga/res/47/a47r080.htm A/RES/47/80] ""Ethnic cleansing" and racial hatred" United Nations. 12/16/1992. Retrieved on 2006, 09-03&lt;/ref&gt;

There are however situations, such as the [[expulsion of Germans after World War II]], where ethnic cleansing has taken place without legal redress. [[Timothy V. Waters]] argues that if similar circumstances arise in the future, this precedent would allow the ethnic cleansing of other populations under international law.&lt;ref&gt;[http://law.bepress.com/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4600&amp;context=expresso Timothy V. Waters, ''On the Legal Construction of Ethnic Cleansing''], Paper 951, 2006, [[University of Mississippi]] School of Law. Retrieved on 2006, 12-13&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!--The emergence of ethnic cleansing as a distinct category of war crime has been a somewhat complex process. Each individual element of a programme of ethnic cleansing could be considered as an individual violation of humanitarian law - a killing here, a house-burning there - thus missing the systematic way in which such violations were perpetrated with a single aim in mind. International courts therefore consider individual incidents in the light of a possible pattern of ethnic cleansing. In the Yugoslav case, for instance, the ICTY considers the widespread massacres and abuses of human rights in Bosnia and Kosovo as part of an overall "joint criminal enterprise" to carve out ethnically pure states in the region.

However, many alleged "ethnic cleansings" in the past do not fit the modern definition of "crimes against humanity."  For example, the post-WW2 [[German expulsions]] were sanctioned by the international agreement at [[Potsdam conference]], requiring that the actions proceed humanely.--&gt; 
==Silent ethnic cleansing==

'''Silent ethnic cleansing''' is a term coined in the mid-1990s by some observers of the [[Yugoslav wars]].  Apparently concerned with [[Western world|Western]] media representations of atrocities committed in the conflict &amp;mdash; which generally focused on those perpetrated by the [[Serbs]] &amp;mdash; atrocities committed against Serbs were dubbed "silent", on the grounds that they were not receiving adequate coverage.&lt;ref&gt;Krauthammer, Charles: "When Serbs Are 'Cleansed,' Moralists Stay Silent", ''International Herald Tribune'', 12 August 1995.&lt;/ref&gt;

Since that time, the term has been used by other ethnically oriented groups for situations that they perceive to be similar &amp;mdash; examples include both sides in [[Ireland]]'s [[The Troubles|recent conflict]], and the expulsion of [[Volksdeutsche|ethnic Germans]] from former German territories during and after [[World War II]].{{citation needed|date=November 2009|needs sources for both alleged examples}}

Some observers{{Who|date=August 2009}}, however, assert that the term should only be used to denote population changes that do not occur as the result of overt violent action, or at least not from more or less organized aggression - the absence of such stressors being the very factor that makes it "silent", although some form of coercion is still used.

==Instances of ethnic cleansing ==
{{Section OR|date=May 2009}}
This section lists incidents that have been termed "ethnic cleansing" by some academic or legal experts. Not all experts agree on every case; nor do all the claims necessarily follow definitions given in this article. Where claims of ethnic cleansing originate from non-experts (e.g., journalists or politicians) this is noted.

===In early modern history===
* After the [[Cromwellian conquest of Ireland]] and [[Act for the Settlement of Ireland 1652|Act of Settlement]] in 1652, the whole post-war Cromwellian settlement of Ireland has been characterised by historians such as Mark Levene and [[Alan Axelrod]] as ethnic cleansing, in that it sought to remove Irish Catholics from the eastern part of the country, others such as the historical writer [[Tim Pat Coogan]] have describe the actions of Cromwell and his subordinates as genocide.&lt;!-- GENOCIDE RFF TAG START--&gt;&lt;ref name=genocide&gt;
* Albert Breton (Editor, 1995). ''Nationalism and Rationality''. Cambridge University Press 1995.  Page 248. "Oliver Cromwell offered Irish Catholics a choice between genocide and forced mass population transfer"
* ''Ukrainian Quarterly''. Ukrainian Society of America 1944. "Therefore, we are entitled to accuse the England of Oliver Cromwell of the genocide of the Irish civilian population.."
*David Norbrook (2000).''Writing the English Republic: Poetry, Rhetoric and Politics, 1627-1660''. Cambridge University Press.  2000. In interpreting Andrew Marvell's contemporarily expressed views on Cromwell Norbrook says; "He (Cromwell) laid the foundation for a ruthless programme of resettling the Irish Catholics which amounted to large scale ethnic cleansing.."
*[http://www.economics.ox.ac.uk/index.php/staff/stewart/ Frances Stewart] (2000). ''War and Underdevelopment: Economic and Social Consequences of Conflict v. 1'' (Queen Elizabeth House Series in Development Studies), Oxford University Press. 2000. p. 51 "Faced with the prospect of an Irish alliance with Charles II, Cromwell carried out a series of massacres to subdue the Irish. Then, once Cromwell had returned to England, the English Commissary, General Henry Ireton, adopted a deliberate policy of crop burning and starvation, which was responsible for the majority of an estimated 600,000 deaths out of a total Irish population of 1,400,000."
*[http://www.electricscotland.com/familytree/frank/axelrod.htm Alan Axelrod] (2002). ''Profiles in Leadership'', Prentice-Hall. 2002. Page 122. "As a leader Cromwell was entirely unyielding. He was willing to act on his beliefs, even if this meant killing the king and perpetrating, against the Irish, something very nearly approaching genocide"
* [[Tim Pat Coogan]] (2002). ''The Troubles: Ireland's Ordeal and the Search for Peace''. ISBN 9780312294182. p 6. "The massacres by Catholics of Protestants, which occurred in the religious wars of the 1640s, were magnified for propagandist purposes to justify Cromwell's subsequent genocide."
*Peter Berresford Ellis (2002). ''Eyewitness to Irish History'', John Wiley &amp; Sons Inc. ISBN 9780471266334. p. 108 "It was to be the justification for Cromwell's genocidal campaign and settlement."
*[[John Morrill (historian)|John Morrill]] (2003). ''Rewriting Cromwell - A Case of Deafening Silences'',  Canadian Journal of History.  Dec 2003. "Of course, this has never been the Irish view of Cromwell.&lt;br&gt; Most Irish remember him as the man responsible for the mass slaughter of civilians at Drogheda and Wexford and as the agent of the greatest episode of ethnic cleansing ever attempted in Western Europe as, within a decade, the percentage of land possessed by Catholics born in Ireland dropped from sixty to twenty. In a decade, the ownership of two-fifths of the land mass was transferred from several thousand Irish Catholic landowners to British Protestants. The gap between Irish and the English views of the seventeenth-century conquest remains unbridgeable and is governed by G.K. Chesterton's mirthless epigram of 1917, that "it was a tragic necessity that the Irish should remember it; but it was far more tragic that the English forgot it."
*[http://feature.ipfw.edu/faculty/profiles/lutz.html James M Lutz], Brenda J Lutz, (2004). ''Global Terrorism'', Routledge:London, p.193: "The draconian laws applied by Oliver Cromwell in Ireland were an early version of ethnic cleansing. The Catholic Irish were to be expelled to the northwestern areas of the island. Relocation rather than extermination was the goal."
*[http://www.soton.ac.uk/history/profiles/levene1.html Mark Levene] (2005). ''Genocide in the Age of the Nation State: Volume 2''. ISBN 978-1845110574 Page 55, 56 &amp; 57. A sample quote describes the Cromwellian campaign and settlement as "a conscious attempt to reduce a distinct ethnic population".
*Mark Levene (2005). ''Genocide in the Age of the Nation-State'', I.B.Tauris: London: &lt;blockquote&gt;[The Act of Settlement of Ireland], and the parliamentary legislation which succeeded it the following year, is the nearest thing on paper in the English, and more broadly British, domestic record, to a programme of state-sanctioned and systematic ethnic cleansing of another people. The fact that it did not include 'total' genocide in its remit, or that it failed to put into practice the vast majority of its proposed expulsions, ultimately, however, says less about the lethal determination of its makers and more about the political, structural and financial weakness of the early modern English state.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!-- GENOCIDE REF TAG END--&gt;

*Michael Mann, basing his figures on those provided by [[Justin McCarthy (American historian)|Justin McCarthy]], states that between 1821 and 1922, around 5.5 million Muslims were expelled from south-eastern Europe as Bulgaria, Greece and Serbia gained their independence from the [[Ottoman Empire]].  These countries sought to expand their territory against the remaining Muslim areas, which culminated in the Balkan wars of the early 20th century.&lt;ref&gt;Michael Mann, ''The dark side of democracy: explaining ethnic cleansing'', [http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=cGHGPgj1_tIC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=The+dark+side+of+democracy:+explaining+ethnic+cleansing,&amp;as_brr=3#v=onepage&amp;q=derive%20from%20McCarthy&amp;f=false pp. 112-4], Cambridge, 2005 "... figures are derive[d] from McCarthy (1995: I 91, 162-4, 339), who is often viewed as a scholar on the Turkish side of the debate. Yet even if we reduce his figures by 50 percent, the would still horrify. He estimates between 1812 and 1922 somewhere around 5 1/2 million Muslims were driven out of Europe and 5 million more were killed or died of disease or starvation while fleeing. ... In the final Balkan wars of 1912-13 he estimates that 62 percent of Muslims (27 percent dead, 35 percent refugees) disappeared from the lands conquered by Greece, Serbia, and Bulgaria. This was murderous ethnic cleansing on a stupendous scale not previously seen in Europe, ..."

&lt;/ref&gt;

===20th century===

* The [[Bolshevik]] regime killed or deported an estimated 300,000 to 500,000 [[Don Cossacks]] during the [[Russian Civil War]], in 1919-1920.&lt;ref&gt;Kort, Michael (2001). ''The Soviet Colossus: History and Aftermath'', p. 133. Armonk, NY: M.E. Sharpe. ISBN 0-7656-0396-9.&lt;/ref&gt;{{Request quotation|date=July 2009}} &lt;!-- where does the author claim it was ethnic cleansing--&gt;

* The German government's persecutions and expulsions of [[Jews]] in [[Germany]], [[Austria]] and other [[Nazi]]-controlled areas prior to the initiation of [[the Holocaust|mass genocide]]. Estimated number of those who died in the process is approximately 6 million Jews.&lt;ref&gt;Naimark, ''op. cit.''&lt;/ref&gt;{{Request quotation|date=July 2009}} &lt;!-- where does the author claim it was ethnic cleansing--&gt;

[[Image:Ustasaguard.jpg|thumb|[[Ustashe|Ustaše]] guard in a mass grave at [[Jasenovac]] concentration camp.]]

* At least 330,000 Serbs, 30,000 Jews and 30,000 Roma were killed during the [[NDH]] (see [[Jasenovac]]) (today Croatia and Bosna and Herzegovina) &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ushmm.org/wlc/article.php?lang=en&amp;ModuleId=10005449 United States Holocaust Memorial Museum about Jasenovac and Independent State of Croatia]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Genocide and Resistance in Hitler’s Bosnia: The Partisans and the Chetniks, 1941-1943 pp20&lt;/ref&gt; and the same number of Serbs were forced out of the NDH , in may 1941 - may 1945. Estimates of the total numbers of men, women and children killed there goes up to 700,000. &lt;ref&gt;http://www.jasenovac.org/whatwasjasenovac.php&lt;/ref&gt;

* During WWII, in [[Kosovo &amp; Metohija]], some 10,000 Serbs lost their lives&lt;ref name=Krizman&gt;Serge Krizman, Maps of Yugoslavia at War, Washington 1943.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Istorija&gt;ISBN 86-17-09287-4: Kosta Nikolić, Nikola Žutić, Momčilo Pavlović, Zorica Špadijer: Историја за трећи разред гимназије природно-математичког смера и четврти разред гимназије општег и друштвено-језичког смера, Belgrade, 2002, p. 182.&lt;/ref&gt;, and about 80&lt;ref name=Krizman/&gt; to 100,000&lt;ref name=Krizman/&gt;&lt;ref name=Annexe&gt;[http://www.parliament.the-stationery-office.co.uk/pa/cm199900/cmselect/cmfaff/28/28ap42.htm Annexe I], by the Serbian Information Centre-London to a report of the Select Committee on Foreign Affairs of the [[British House of Commons|House of Commons]] of the [[Parliament of the United Kingdom]].&lt;/ref&gt; or more&lt;ref name=Istorija/&gt; were ethnically cleansed.&lt;ref name=Annexe/&gt;

* [[Population transfer in the Soviet Union|Deportation]] of [[Crimean Tatars]], [[Kalmykia|Kalmyks]], [[Chechnya|Chechens]], [[Ingushetia|Ingush]], [[Balkars]], [[Karachay-Cherkessia|Karachay]]s and [[Meskhetian Turks]] by [[Soviet Union]] to [[Central Asia]] and [[Siberia]], 1943-1944.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rferl.org/featuresarticle/2005/05/1350f316-420a-4a90-b42e-b59fe9fcc8e5.html 60 Years After: For Victims Of Stalin's Deportations, War Lives On]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!-- This source says religious cleansing was the motive not ethic cleansing--&gt; 

*The [[Population exchange between Greece and Turkey]] has been described as an ethnic cleansing.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.huffingtonpost.com/harut-sassounian/turkish-prime-minister-ad_b_208246.html&lt;/ref&gt;

* During the four years of occupation 1941 - 1944, the Axis (German, Hungarian and Croatian) forces committed numerous war crimes against civilian population (Serbs, Roma and Jews): about 50,000 people in [[Vojvodina]] (north [[Serbia]]) (see [[Occupation of Vojvodina, 1941-1944]]) were murdered and about 280,000 were arrested, raped or tortured.&lt;ref&gt;''Enciklopedija Novog Sada'', Sveska 5, Novi Sad, 1996 (page 196).&lt;/ref&gt; The total number of the killed people in Bačka was 19,573 (under Hungarian occupation), in Banat 7,513 (under German occupation) and in Syrmia 28,199 (under Croatian occupation). &lt;ref name="Ćurčić"&gt;Slobodan Ćurčić, ''Broj stanovnika Vojvodine'', Novi Sad, 1996 (pages 42, 43).&lt;/ref&gt;

* The ethnic cleansing of [[Hungarians]], or the [[1944-1945 killings in Bačka|massacres in Bačka]] by [[Titoist]] partisans during the winter of 1944-45, about 40.000 massacred.&lt;ref&gt;''[http://www.hungarian-history.hu/lib/cseres/ Tibor Cseres: Serbian vendetta in Bacska]&lt;/ref&gt;{{Request quotation|date=July 2009}}&lt;!-- where does the author claim it was ethnic cleansing--&gt;

*During Axis occupation in Albania (1943-1944), Albanian collaborationist organization [[Balli Kombëtar]] with [[Nazi Germany|Nazi German]] support mounted a major offensive in southern Albania ([[Northern Epirus]]) with devastating results: over 200 Greek populated towns and villages were burned or destroyed, 2,000 [[Greeks in Albania|ethnic Greeks]] were killed, 5,000 imprisoned and 2,000 taken hostages to concentration camps. Moreover, 30,000 people had to find refuge in nearby Greece during and after that period.&lt;ref&gt;Albania in the Twentieth Century, A History: Volume II: Albania in Occupation and War, 1939-45. Owen Pearson. I.B.Tauris, 2006. ISBN 1845111044.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;.Pyrrhus J. Ruches.  [http://books.google.com/books?id=2k9pAAAAMAAJ&amp;q=albania%27s+captives&amp;dq=albania%27s+captives&amp;lr=&amp;as_brr=0&amp;hl=el&amp;pgis=1 Albania's captivesArgonaut, 1965, p. 172 "The entire carnage, arson and imprisonment suffered by the hands of Balli Kombetar...schools burned".]&lt;/ref&gt;{{Request quotation|date=July 2009}}&lt;!-- where does the author claim it was ethnic cleansing--&gt;

* At the end of World War II many [[Expulsion of Germans after World War II|Germans were expelled from eastern Europe]], it is described as ethic cleansing by Thomas Kamusella, which he links to the development of ethnic nationalism in central and eastern Europe. Piotr Pikle describes the expulsion of Germans at the end of World War II from Czechoslovakia as ethnic cleansing, and Steffen Prauser and Arfon Rees describe the simultaneous expulsion of Germans from Poland as ethnic cleansing.&lt;ref&gt;''[http://cadmus.iue.it/dspace/bitstream/1814/2599/1/HEC04-01.pdf The Expulsion of 'German' Communities from Eastern Europe at the end of the Second World War]'', European University Institute, Florense. EUI Working Paper HEC No. 2004/1, Edited by Steffen Prauser and Arfon Rees pp. 24,20,29&lt;/ref&gt;

*During the [[Partition of India]] 5 million Hindus and Sikhs fled from what became Pakistan into India and more than 6 million Muslims fled from what became India into Pakistan. The events which occurred during this time period have been described as ethnic cleansing. &lt;ref&gt;http://cambridge.org/us/catalogue/catalogue.asp?isbn=9780521856614&amp;ss=exc&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://74.125.47.132/search?q=cache:EPiGNBHDvxMJ:www.sasnet.lu.se/partition.doc+Ethnic+cleansing+partition+of+India&amp;cd=8&amp;hl=en&amp;ct=clnk&amp;gl=us&amp;client=firefox-a&lt;/ref&gt; 

* The [[1948 Palestinian exodus]] that accompanied the establishment of the [[State of Israel]] has been described as an "ethnic cleansing."&lt;ref&gt;Michael Mann, ''The dark side of democracy: explaining ethnic cleansing'', Cambridge University Press, 2005, page 109, 519&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Nur-eldeen Masalha|Masalha, Nur]] (1992). ''Expulsion of the Palestinians''. Institute for Palestine Studies, this edition 2001, p. 175.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Morris, Benny. ''The Birth of the Palestinian Refugee Problem Revisited'', Cambridge University Press, 2004, pp. 239&amp;ndash;240.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.crimesofwar.org/thebook/arab-israeli-war.html Benny Morris, ''Arab-Israeli War''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Rosemarie Esber]], ''Under the Cover of War: The Zionist Expulsion of the Palestinians'', 2009, p.23.&lt;/ref&gt; 

* Between the [[1948 Arab-Israeli War]] and the [[Six Day War]] in 1967, there was a [[Jewish exodus from Arab lands]], that has been described as an "ethnic cleansing".&lt;ref name=JCPA&gt;http://www.jcpa.org/JCPA/Templates/ShowPage.asp?DRIT=5&amp;DBID=1&amp;LNGID=1&amp;TMID=111&amp;FID=625&amp;PID=861&amp;IID=1020&amp;TTL=The_Forgotten_Narrative:_Jewish_Refugees_from_Arab_Countries&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.jpost.com/servlet/Satellite?cid=1214132663726&amp;pagename=JPost%2FJPArticle%2FShowFull&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Ran HaCohen, [http://www.antiwar.com/hacohen/h011303.html "Ethnic Cleansing: Some Common Reactions"]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Footnotea&gt;A bipartisan resolution passed by the UN Congress in October 2003 noted that that Jews in Arab countries, "were forced to flee and in some cases brutally expelled amid coordinated violence and anti-Semitic incitement that amounted to ethnic cleansing." ([http://www.jcpa.org/JCPA/Templates/ShowPage.asp?DRIT=5&amp;DBID=1&amp;LNGID=1&amp;TMID=111&amp;FID=625&amp;PID=861&amp;IID=1020&amp;TTL=The_Forgotten_Narrative:_Jewish_Refugees_from_Arab_Countries The Forgotten Narrative]) [[Ran HaCohen]], while conceding that Jews faced harassment in Arab countries following the 1948 war, whether from the people and/or regimes, finds this characterization to be, "shamefully cynical when it is imputed by the very [[Zionist]]s who demanded 'let my people go', or by the same Israel that did all it could to force those very countries to let their Jews leave." ([http://www.antiwar.com/hacohen/h011303.html "Ethnic Cleansing: Some Common Reactions"])&lt;/ref&gt; 

* After the [[Republic of Indonesia]] achieved independence from [[the Netherlands]] in 1949, around 300.000 people, predominantly [[Indo people|Indo]]s or Dutch Indonesians (people of mixed Indonesian and European descent), fled or were expelled.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.zum.de/whkmla/region/seasia/indonesia19451949.html Struggle for Independence : 1945-1949]&lt;/ref&gt;

* [[Kashmir]]is who have fled the Indian military action in Kashmir, have migrated to Pakistan, as well as to Great Britain, Canada and the USA.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jammu-kashmir.com/archives/archives2008/kashmir20080407b.html "Kashmiri refugees denied property ownership rights in Pakistan"]&lt;/ref&gt; 

*In the aftermath of the 1949 Durban Riots (an inter-racial conflict between [[Zulu]]s and [[Asians in South Africa]]), hundreds of Indians fled Cato Manor.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.theindianstar.com/index.php?uan=5786 "Current Africa race riots like 1949 anti-Indian riots: minister"], TheIndianStar.com&lt;/ref&gt;

* On 5 and 6 September 1955 the [[Istanbul Pogrom]] or "Septembrianá"/"Σεπτεμβριανά", secretly backed by the Turkish government, was launched against the Greek population of [[Constantinople]]. The mob also attacked some Jews and Armenians of the city.  The event contributed greatly to the gradual extinction of the Greek minority in the city and country, which numbered 100,000 in 1924 after the Turko-Greek population exchange treaty.  By 2007 there were only 5000 Greeks. The Turkish government further forced expulsion of the Greek minority in the [[Imbros]] and [[Tenedos]] islands in the period 1923-1993.{{Citation needed|date=May 2009}} 

* Between 1957-1962 President [[Nasser]] of Egypt carried out an Anti-European policy, which resulted in the expulsion of 100-200,000 [[Greeks]] from [[Alexandria]] and the rest of [[Egypt]]. Many other [[Ethnic groups in Europe|Europeans]] were expelled, such as [[Italians]] and [[French people|French]].{{Citation needed|date=May 2009}}

* On 5 July 1960, five days after the [[Democratic Republic of the Congo|Congo]] gained independence from Belgium, the [[Force Publique]] garrison near [[Léopoldville]] mutinied against its white officers and attacked numerous European targets. This caused the fear amongst the approximately 100,000 [[white African|whites]] still resident in the Congo and led to their mass exodus from the country.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.historylearningsite.co.uk/united_nations_congo.htm ::UN:: History Learning Site]&lt;/ref&gt;  

*[[Ne Win|Ne Win's]] rise to power in 1962 and his relentless persecution of "resident aliens" (immigrant groups not recognised as citizens of the [[Union of Burma]]) led to an exodus of some 300,000 [[Burmese Indians]].  They migrated to escape racial discrimination and wholesale nationalisation of private enterprise a few years later in 1964.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Martin Smith|year=1991|title=Burma - Insurgency and the Politics of Ethnicity|publisher=Zed Books|location=London,New Jersey|pages=43–44,98,56–57,176}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,875949,00.html Asians v. Asians], TIME&lt;/ref&gt;

*The creation of the [[apartheid]] system in South Africa, which began in 1948 but reached full flower in the 1960s and 1970s, involved some ethnic cleansing, including the separation of blacks, [[Coloureds]], and whites into separate residential areas and private spheres.  The government created [[Bantustans]], which involved [[Apartheid#Forced removals|forced removals]] of non-white populations to reserved lands.&lt;ref&gt; Bell, Terry: ''Unfinished Business: South Africa, Apartheid and Truth'', (pp. 63-4), Verso, (2001, 2003) ISBN 1-85984-545-2 &lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt; Valentino, Benjamin A., ''Final Solutions: Mass Killing and Genocide in the Twentieth Century'', (p. 189), Cornell University Press, (2004) ISBN 0-8014-3965-5. &lt;/ref&gt;  The governing minority forced relocation of the majority to different areas, as well as restricting their movement, education and social activities.{{Citation needed|date=May 2009|citation needed that claims that this was ethnic cleansing.}} 

* As Algeria fought for independence, it expelled the ''[[pied-noir]]'' population of European descent and [[History of the Jews in Algeria|Jews]]; most fled to [[France]], where they had citizenship. In just a few months in 1962, 900,000 of these European descendants and native Jewish people left the country.&lt;ref&gt;[http://marketplace.publicradio.org/shows/2006/08/01/PM200608016.html "Marketplace: Pied-noirs breathe life back into Algerian tourism"]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://lexicorient.com/e.o/pied-noir.htm Pied-Noir]&lt;/ref&gt;

* [[Zanzibar]] forced ethnic cleansing of [[Arabs]] and [[Demographics of India|Indians]] from the nation in 1964.&lt;ref&gt;[http://channel4.empireschildren.co.uk/category/chapters/index.php?chapter=472&amp;cat=3 Country Histories - Empire's Children]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://whosfaultisit.blogspot.com/2006/09/homemade-genocide-arab-world-is.html Who's Fault Is It?]&lt;/ref&gt;

* Some 150,000 Italians settled in [[Libya]], constituting about 18% of the total population.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.britannica.com/eb/article-46562/Libya Libya - Italian colonization]&lt;/ref&gt; In 1970, the government expelled all of Libya's ethnic [[Italians]], a year after [[Muammar al-Gaddafi]] seized power (a "day of vengeance" on 7 October, 1970).&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/4380360.stm Libya cuts ties to mark Italy era ]&lt;/ref&gt;

* Between 1967 and 1973, the British government expelled the entire population of [[Diego Garcia]], a small island in the Indian Ocean.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.economicexpert.com/a/Diego:Garcia.html&lt;/ref&gt;  There are ongoing court cases as regards the rights of the population to return to the island.&lt;ref&gt;http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/africa/2380013.stm&lt;/ref&gt;

* By 1969, more than 350,000 [[Salvador]]ans were living in [[Honduras]]. In 1969, Honduras enacted a new land reform law. This law took land away from Salvadoran immigrants and redistributed this land to native-born Honduran peoples. Thousands of Salvadorans were displaced by this law (see [[Football War]]).{{Citation needed|date=May 2009|citation needed that caims that this was ethnic cleansing.}} 

* During the [[Bangladesh War of Independence]] of 1971 around 10 million [[Bengalis]], mainly [[Hindus]], fled the country to escape the killings and [[1971 Bangladesh atrocities|atrocities]] committed by the [[Pakistan]] Army. Furthermore, many intellectuals and other religious minorities were targeted by death squads and ''[[razakars]]''. {{Citation needed|date=May 2009|citation needed that claims that this was ethnic cleansing.}} 

* [[Idi Amin]]'s regime forced the expulsion in 1972 of [[Uganda]]'s entire ethnic [[Non-resident Indian and Person of Indian Origin|Asian]] population, mostly of Indian descent.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/onthisday/hi/dates/stories/august/7/newsid_2492000/2492333.stm 1972: Asians given 90 days to leave Uganda]&lt;/ref&gt;

* The ethnic cleansing in 1974-76 of the [[Greeks|Greek]] population of the areas under Turkish military occupation in [[Cyprus]] during and after the [[Turkish Invasion of Cyprus]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7D6143AF936A3575AC0A964958260|title='Ethnic cleansing', Cypriot style|date=1992-09-05|work=New York Times|accessdate=2008-12-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* Following the U.S. withdrawal from [[Vietnam]] in 1975, the Lao kingdom was overthrown by the communists and the [[Hmong people]] became targets of retaliation and persecution. Thousands made the trek to and across the [[Mekong River]] into [[Thailand]], often under attack. This marked the beginning of a [[Conflict in Laos involving the Hmong|mass exodus of Hmong people]] from [[Laos]].{{Citation needed|date=May 2009|citation needed that claims that this was ethnic cleansing.}}

* The [[Khmer Rouge]] regime in [[Cambodia]] disproportionately targeted ethnic minority groups. These included ethnic [[Overseas Chinese|Chinese]], [[Vietnamese people|Vietnamese]] and [[Thai people|Thai]]. In the late 1960s, an estimated 425,000 ethnic Chinese lived in Cambodia, but by 1984, as a result of Khmer Rouge [[genocide]] and emigration, only about 61,400 Chinese remained in the country. The [[Cham people|Cham]] Muslims suffered serious purges with as much as half of their population exterminated. A Khmer Rouge order stated that henceforth “The Cham nation no longer exists on Kampuchean soil belonging to the [[Khmer people|Khmers]]” (U.N. Doc. A.34/569 at 9).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ppu.org.uk/genocide/g_cambodia1.html Genocide - Cambodia]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.genocidewatch.org/aboutgenocide/stantoncambodianlaw.htm The Cambodian Genocide and International Law]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.country-studies.com/cambodia/the-chinese.html Cambodia the Chinese]&lt;/ref&gt; 

* Subsequent waves of hundreds of thousands of [[Rohingya people|Rohingya]] fled [[Burma]] and many refugees inundated neighbouring Bangladesh including 250,000 in 1978 as a result of the [[King Dragon operation in Arakan]].{{Citation needed|date=May 2009|citation needed that claims that this was ethnic cleansing.}} 

* The [[Sino-Vietnamese War]] resulted in the discrimination and consequent migration of [[Vietnam]]'s [[Hoa|ethnic Chinese]]. Many of these people fled as "[[boat people]]". In 1978-79, some 450,000 ethnic Chinese left Vietnam by boat as refugees (many officially encouraged and assisted) or were expelled across the land border with China.{{Citation needed|date=May 2009|citation needed that claims that this was ethnic cleansing.}} 

* Aftermath of [[Indira Gandhi]] assassination in 1984, the ruling party [[Indian National Congress]] supporters formed large mobs and killed around 3000 [[Sikhs]] around Delhi which is known as the [[Anti Sikh Riots]] during the next four days. The mobs using the support of ruling party leaders used the Election voting list to identify Sikhs and kill them.
 [[Image:Chemical weapon2.jpg|250px|thumb|Aftermath of the [[Halabja poison gas attack]].]] 
* The forced assimilation campaign of the late 80s directed against ethnic [[Turkish people|Turks]] resulted in the emigration of some 300,000 [[Turks in Bulgaria|Bulgarian Turks]] to Turkey.{{Citation needed|date=May 2009|citation needed that claims that this was ethnic cleansing.}}

* The [[Nagorno Karabakh]] conflict has resulted in the displacement of population from both sides. 528,000 [[Azerbaijanis]] from Nagorno Karabakh Armenian controlled territories including Nagorno-Karabakh, and 185,000&lt;ref name="autogenerated1"&gt;Building Security in Europe's New Borderlands, Renata Dwan, M.E. Sharpe (1999) p. 148&lt;/ref&gt; to 220,000 Azeris, 18,000 [[Kurds]] and 3,500 Russians fled from [[Armenia]] to Azerbaijan from 1988 to 1989.&lt;ref&gt;De Waal, ''Black Garden'', p. 285&lt;/ref&gt; 280,000 to 304,000&lt;ref name="autogenerated1" /&gt; persons&amp;mdash;virtually all ethnic [[Armenians]]&amp;mdash;fled [[Azerbaijan]] during the 1988–1993 war over the disputed region of Nagorno-Karabakh.&lt;ref&gt;[http://ourworld.compuserve.com/homepages/usazerb/refugees.htm Refugees and displaced persons in Azerbaijan]&lt;/ref&gt;

* Since April 1989, some 70,000 black Mauritanians—members of the [[Peul]], [[Wolof people|Wolof]], [[Soninke people|Soninke]] and [[Bambara people|Bambara]] ethnic groups—have been expelled from [[Mauritania]] by the Mauritanian government.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.irinnews.org/report.aspx?ReportId=70522 Fair elections haunted by racial imbalance]&lt;/ref&gt; 

* In 1989, after bloody pogroms against the [[Meskhetian Turks]] by [[Uzbeks]] in Central Asia's [[Ferghana Valley]], nearly 90,000 Meskhetian Turks left [[Uzbekistan]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.irinnews.org/report.aspx?reportid=28663 Focus on Meskhetian Turks]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cal.org/co/pdffiles/mturks.pdf Meskhetian Turk Communities around the World]&lt;/ref&gt;

* In 1991, following a crackdown on [[Rohingya people|Rohingya]] Muslims in [[Myanmar]], 250,000 refugees took shelter in the [[Cox's Bazar]] district of neighbouring Bangladesh.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/asia-pacific/7019882.stm Burmese exiles in desperate conditions], BBC News&lt;/ref&gt;

*In 1991, in retribution for supporting [[Saddam Hussein]] against Kuwait during the 1990 [[Invasion of Kuwait]], Kuwait carried out the [[Palestinian Expulsion from Kuwait|expulsion of 400,000 Palestinians]].&lt;ref&gt;http://newsvote.bbc.co.uk/mpapps/pagetools/print/news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/4089961.stm&lt;/ref&gt; 

* As a result of [[1991–1992 South Ossetia War]], about 100,000 ethnic [[Ossetians]] fled [[South Ossetia]] and Georgia proper, most across the border into North Ossetia. A further 23,000 ethnic [[Georgians]] fled South Ossetia and settled in other parts of [[Georgia (country)|Georgia]].&lt;ref&gt; Human Rights Watch/Helsinki, [http://hrw.org/reports/1996/Russia.htm RUSSIA. THE INGUSH-OSSETIAN CONFLICT IN THE PRIGORODNYI REGION], May 1996.&lt;/ref&gt; According to [[Helsinki Watch]], the campaign of ethnic-cleansing was orchestrated by the Ossetian militants, during the events of [[Ossetian–Ingush conflict]], which resulted in [[expulsion]] of approximately 60,000 [[Ingush]] inhabitants from Prigorodny District.&lt;ref&gt;Russia: The Ingush-Ossetian Conflict in the Prigorodnyi Region (Paperback) by Human Rights Watch Helsinki Human Rights Watch (April 1996) ISBN 1564321657&lt;/ref&gt;

* The widespread ethnic cleansing accompanying the [[Croatian War of Independence]] that was committed by rebel Serbs and Serb-led JNA on the occupied areas of Croatia (self-proclaimed [[Republic of Serbian Krajina]]) (1991-1995). Large number of Croats and non-Serbs were removed, either by murder, deportation or being forced to flee. The majority of Croatia's Serb population was ethnically cleansed by the Croatian army at the end of the war in [[Operation Storm]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://uk.reuters.com/article/worldNews/idUKL1187232120080311 FACTBOX - Brief history of Croatia's rebel Serb Krajina region | World | Reuters&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; In few last days of august 1995, more than 250.000 Serb refugees&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.de/books?id=UAl_w322vWQC&amp;pg=PA247&amp;lpg=PA247&amp;dq=serbian+refugies+from+croatia+250.000&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=lKzPnzVSn8&amp;sig=UB57DPz_VeAPtTb92wBFMxwF-_U&amp;hl=de&amp;ei=pqrUSrqFBaKYmwOLzrmMAw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=6&amp;ved=0CCEQ6AEwBQ#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false]&lt;/ref&gt; fled out of Croatia. 

* The widespread ethnic cleansing accompanying the [[war in Bosnia|Bosnia and Herzegovina]] (1992-1995), Large numbers of [[Serbs]], [[Croats]], [[Bosniaks]] were forced to flee their homes and expelled.&lt;ref name="Foreign Relations 1992"&gt;Committee on Foreign Relations, US Senate, ''The Ethnic Cleansing of Bosnia-Hercegovina'', (US Government Printing Office, 1992)&lt;/ref&gt; Beginning in 1991, political upheavals in the [[Balkans]] displaced about 2,700,000 people by mid-1992, of which over 700,000 of them sought asylum in [[Europe]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/specials/bosnia/context/dayton.html Bosnia: Dayton Accords]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E3D61339F937A15752C1A963958260&amp;n=Top/Reference/Times%20Topics/Subjects/I/Immigration%20and%20Refugees Resettling Refugees: U.N. Facing New Burden]&lt;/ref&gt; 

* The widespread ethnic cleansing committed against Albanians on the [[Albanians|Albanian]]-dominated breakaway [[Kosovo]] province (of [[Serbia]]) (1999). Large numbers of [[Albanians]] were forced to flee their homes and expelled.&lt;ref name="Foreign Relations 1992"/&gt; 

* The forced displacement and [[Ethnic cleansing of Georgians in Abkhazia|ethnic-cleansing]] of more than 250,000 people, mostly [[Georgians]] but some others too, from [[Abkhazia]] during the conflict and after in 1993 and 1998.&lt;ref&gt; Bookman, Milica Zarkovic, "The Demographic Struggle for Power", (p. 131), Frank Cass and Co. Ltd. (UK), (1997) ISBN 0-7146-4732-2 &lt;/ref&gt; 

* The 1994 massacres of nearly 1,000,000 [[Tutsis]] by [[Hutus]], known as the [[Rwandan Genocide]]&lt;ref&gt; Leeder, Elaine J., "The Family in Global Perspective: A Gendered Journey", (p. 164-65), Sage Publications, (2004) ISBN 0-7619-2837-5 &lt;/ref&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[better citation needed]&lt;/sup&gt;{{Citation needed|date=May 2009|citation needed that claims that this was ethnic cleansing.}} 

* The mass expulsion of southern [[Lhotshampa]]s (Bhutanese of Nepalese origin) by the northern [[Druk]] majority of [[Bhutan]] in 1990.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.voanews.com/uspolicy/2006-10-19-voa1.cfm Voice of America (18 October 2006)] &lt;/ref&gt; The number of refugees is approximately 103,000.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unhcr.org/cgi-bin/texis/vtx/publ/opendoc.htm?tbl=PUBL&amp;id=4444d3c93e UNHCR Publication (State of the world refugees)]&lt;/ref&gt;

* An estimated 1,000 [[Tamil people]] were killed, tens of thousands of houses were destroyed by the [[Sinhala people|Sinhalese]]-dominated government of [[Sri Lanka]] in what is commonly known as [[Black July]].The murder, looting and general destruction of property was well organized. Mobs armed with petrol were seen stopping passing motorists at critical street junctions and, after ascertaining the ethnic identity of the driver and passengers, setting alight the vehicle with the driver and passengers trapped within it. Mobs were also seen stopping buses to identify Tamil passengers and subsequently these passengers were knifed, clubbed to death or burned alive.{{Citation needed|date=May 2009|citation needed that claims that this was ethnic cleansing.}} 

* In October 1990, the militant [[Liberation Tigers of Tamil Eelam]] (LTTE), forcibly [[Expulsion of Muslims from the Northern province by LTTE|expelled]] the entire ethnic [[Islam in Sri Lanka|Muslim]] population (approx 75,000) from the Northern Province of [[Sri Lanka]]. The Muslims were given 48 hours to vacate the premises of their homes while their properties were subsequently looted by [[LTTE]]. Those who refused to leave were killed. This act of ethnic cleansing was carried out so the [[LTTE]] could facilitate their goal of creating a mono-ethnic Tamil state in Northern Sri Lanka.{{Citation needed|date=May 2009|citation needed that claims that this was ethnic cleansing.}} 

* Displacement of more than 500,000 [[Chechen people|Chechen]] and ethnic [[Russians|Russian]] civilians living in [[Chechnya]] during the [[First Chechen War]] in 1994-1996.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.globalsecurity.org/military/world/war/chechnya1.htm First Chechnya War]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jamestown.org/edm/article.php?article_id=2369902 Ethnic Russians in the North of Caucasus - Eurasia Daily Monitor]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.reliefweb.int/rw/rwb.nsf/0/bb82d320aa527436c1256c560037d0a6?OpenDocument&amp;Click= Chechen census fiasco]&lt;/ref&gt;

* The [[Jakarta riots of May 1998]] targeted many [[Chinese Indonesian]]s. Suffering from looting and arson many Chinese Indonesians fled from [[Indonesia]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://edition.cnn.com/WORLD/asiapcf/9808/29/indonesia.riot/ Anti-Chinese riots continue in Indonesia], August 29, 1998, CNN&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.businessweek.com/2000/00_41/b3702149.htm Wages of Hatred], Business Week&lt;/ref&gt;

* More than 800,000 Kosovar [[Albanians]] fled their homes in [[Kosovo]] during the [[Kosovo War]] in 1998-9, after being expelled. Although on the contrary over 200,000 [[Serbs]] and other non-Albanian minorities were forced out of Kosovo during and after the war while most [[Albanians]] returned.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/serbia/article/0,,1713498,00.html Serbia threatens to resist Kosovo independence plan]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://hrw.org/english/docs/2004/03/18/serbia8129.htm Kosovo/Serbia: Protect Minorities from Ethnic Violence (Human Rights Watch)]&lt;/ref&gt;

* There have been serious outbreaks of inter-ethnic [[violence]] on the island of Kalimantan since 1997, involving the indigenous [[Dayak people]]s and immigrants from the island of [[Madura]]. In 2001 in the Central [[Kalimantan]] town of Sampit, at least 500 [[Madurese people|Madurese]] were killed and up to 100,000 Madurese were forced to flee. Some Madurese bodies were decapitated in a ritual reminiscent of the [[headhunting]] tradition of the Dayaks of old.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.globalpolicy.org/security/natres/timber/2001/0301brno.htm Behind Ethnic War, Indonesia's Old Migration Policy]&lt;/ref&gt;

===21st century===

* In [[Jammu and Kashmir]], [[India]], the violent Islamic insurgency has specifically targeted the Hindu [[Kashmiri Pandit]] minority and 400,000 have either been murdered or displaced.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.house.gov/list/press/nj06_pallone/pr_feb15_kashmir.html Pallone introduces resolution condemning Human rights violation against Kashmiri Pandits], [[United States House of Representatives]], 2006-02-15&lt;/ref&gt; This has been condemned and labeled as ethnic cleansing in a 2006 resolution passed by the [[United States Congress]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://thomas.loc.gov/cgi-bin/query/z?c109:H.CON.RES.344: Expressing the sense of Congress that the Government of the Republic of India and the State Government of Jammu and Kashmir should take immediate steps to remedy the situation of the Kashmiri Pandits and should act to ensure the physical, political, and economic security of this embattled community. HR Resolution 344],[[United States House of Representatives]], 2006-02-15&lt;/ref&gt;  Also in 2009 [[Oregon Legislative Assembly]] passed a resolution to recognize September 14, 2007, as Martyrs Day to acknowledge ethnic cleansing and campaigns of terror inflicted on non-Muslim minorities of [[Jammu and Kashmir]] by militants seeking to establish an [[Islamic state]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.leg.state.or.us/09reg/measpdf/sjr1.dir/sjr0023.intro.pdf Senate Joint Resolution 23, 75th OREGON LEGISLATIVE ASSEMBLY--2009 Regular Session]&lt;/ref&gt;

* In 2003, Sinafasi Makelo, a representative of [[Mbuti]] [[Pygmies]], told the UN's Indigenous People's Forum that during the [[Second Congo War|Congo Civil War]], his people were hunted down and eaten as though they were game animals. Both sides of the war regarded them as "subhuman" and some say their flesh can confer magical powers. Makelo asked the [[UN Security Council]] to recognise [[cannibalism]] as a crime against humanity and an act of [[genocide]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/3869489.stm DR Congo pygmies 'exterminated']&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/2933524.stm DR Congo Pygmies appeal to UN]&lt;/ref&gt;

* In the late-1990s and early 2000s, [[paramilitaries]] organized and armed by the [[Indonesia]]n military and police forces murdered large numbers of civilians in [[East Timor]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.iht.com/articles/1999/04/29/edjose.2.t.php Yes to Kosovo, No to East Timor? - International Herald Tribune&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.abc.net.au/7.30/stories/s50444.htm 7.30 Report - 8/9/1999: Ethnic cleansing will empty East Timor if no aid comes: Belo&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.alternet.org/columnists/story/1096/ U.S. Fiddles While East Timor Burns | AlterNet&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;James M. Lutz, Brenda J. Lutz, ''[http://books.google.com/books?id=1gW12Wdr1QsC&amp;pg=RA1-PA209&amp;lpg=RA1-PA209&amp;dq=east+timor+ethnic+cleansing&amp;source=web&amp;ots=H6lg4hL9Du&amp;sig=Ha2vDTPiYCdc2iNMl4oKGYjzoiI Global Terrorism]''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.globalsecurity.org/military/library/news/1999/09/990908-timor7.htm Outrage Over East Timor&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hoover.org/publications/digest/3476806.html Hoover Institution - Hoover Digest - Why East Timor Matters&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://media.www.westernherald.com/media/storage/paper881/news/2004/05/10/Opinion/We.Cannot.Look.The.Other.Way.On.Ethnic.Cleansing-2124595.shtml We cannot look the other way on ethnic cleansing - Opinion&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

* Since the mid-1990s the central government of [[Botswana]] has been trying to move [[Bushmen]] out of the [[Central Kalahari Game Reserve]]. As of October 2005, the government has resumed its policy of forcing all Bushmen off their lands in the Game Reserve, using armed police and threats of violence or death.&lt;ref name="Daily Telegraph"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/main.jhtml?xml=/news/2005/10/29/wbot29.xml&amp;sSheet=/news/2005/10/29/ixworld.html
|title=Bushmen forced out of desert after living off land for thousands of years |publisher=The Daily Telegraph |accessdate=2005-10-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many of the involuntarily displaced Bushmen live in squalid resettlement camps and some have resorted to [[prostitution]] and [[alcoholism]], while about 250 others remain or have surreptitiously returned to the [[Kalahari]] to resume their independent lifestyle.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.nationalgeographic.com/news/2004/09/0914_040914_labushmen_2.html African Bushmen Tour U.S. to Fund Fight for Land]&lt;/ref&gt; “How can we continue to have [[Stone Age]] creatures  in an age of computers?“ asked Botswana’s president [[Festus Mogae]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.motherjones.com/news/dispatch/2005/01/01_800.html Exiles of the Kalahari]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.survival-international.org/news/1454 UN condemns Botswana government over Bushman evictions]&lt;/ref&gt;

* Attacks by the [[Janjaweed]], militias of [[Sudan]] on the [[African]] population of [[Darfur]], a region of western Sudan.&lt;ref&gt; Collins, Robert O., "Civil Wars and Revolution in the Sudan: Essays on the Sudan, Southern Sudan, and Darfur, 1962-2004
", (p. 156), Tsehai Publishers (US), (2005) ISBN 0-9748198-7-5 .&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Power, Samantha  "Dying in Darfur: 
Can the ethnic cleansing in Sudan be stopped?"[http://www.newyorker.com/fact/content/?040830fa_fact1], ''The New Yorker'', 30 August 2004.
Human Rights Watch, [http://hrw.org/english/docs/2004/05/05/darfur8536.htm "Q &amp; A: Crisis in Darfur"] (web site, retrieved 24 May 2006).
Hilary Andersson, [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/programmes/from_our_own_correspondent/3752871.stm "Ethnic cleansing blights Sudan"], ''BBC News'', 27 May 2004.&lt;/ref&gt; A 14 July 2007 article notes that in the past two months up to 75,000 Arabs from [[Chad]] and [[Niger]] crossed the border into Darfur. Most have been relocated by the Sudanese government to former villages of displaced non-Arab people. Some 2.5 million have now been forced to flee their homes after attacks by Sudanese troops and Janjaweed militia.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.independent.co.uk/world/africa/article2768232.ece Arabs pile into Darfur to take land 'cleansed' by janjaweed]&lt;/ref&gt;  

*Currently in the [[Iraq Civil War]] (2003 to present), entire neighborhoods in [[Baghdad]] are being ethnically cleansed by [[Shia]] and [[Sunni]] militias.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/middle-east/iraq-is-disintegrating-as-ethnic-cleansing-takes-hold-478937.html Iraq is disintegrating as ethnic cleansing takes hold]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://weekly.ahram.org.eg/2006/784/sc4.htm "There is ethnic cleansing"]&lt;/ref&gt; Some areas are being evacuated by every member of a particular group due to lack of security, moving into new areas because of fear of reprisal killings. As of 21 June 2007, the [[United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees]] estimated that 2.2 million Iraqis had been displaced to neighboring countries, and 2 million were displaced internally, with nearly 100,000 Iraqis fleeing to Syria and Jordan each month.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cnn.com/2007/WORLD/meast/06/20/damon.iraqrefugees/index.html Iraq refugees chased from home, struggle to cope]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.boston.com/news/world/middleeast/articles/2006/11/03/un_nearly_100000_flee_iraq_monthly/ U.N.: 100,000 Iraq refugees flee monthly]. Alexander G. Higgins, ''[[Boston Globe]],'' 3 November 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/30/world/middleeast/30mosul.html?hp In North Iraq, Sunni Arabs Drive Out Kurds]&lt;/ref&gt;

* The removal of around 8,500 Jews (including the forced removal of about half of them)&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/middle_east/4159958.stm 'Israel evicts Gaza Strip settlers'], BBC News Online, [[17 August]], 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; from the [[Gaza Strip]], and around 660 from four small settlements in the [[West Bank]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/middle_east/4172694.stm 'Settlers and army clash in W Bank'], BBC News Online, [[22 August]], 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; in 2005 through the implementation of [[Israel's unilateral disengagement plan]].&lt;ref&gt;Robinson, Eugene. [http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2005/08/18/AR2005081801642.html "Betrayed in Gaza"], ''[[Washington Post]]'', August 19, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Klein, Morton A. [http://www.jewishjournal.com/home/preview.php?id=11876 "Gaza Withdrawal Rewards Terrorism"], ''[[The Jewish Journal of Greater Los Angeles]]'' February 27, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Jeff Jacoby|Jacoby, Jeff]]. [http://www.jewishworldreview.com/jeff/jacoby_2005_04_01.php3 "Sharon's retreat is a victory for terrorists"], ''Jewish World Review'', April 1, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Gross, Tom. [http://www.tomgrossmedia.com/ExodusFromGaza.html Exodus From Gaza] Tom Gross Mid-East Media Analysis. Retrieved November 4, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; This was the first instance in history of Jews forcibly resettling other Jews.

*Although [[Iraqi Christians]] represent less than 5% of the total Iraqi population, they make up 40% of the [[refugees]] now living in nearby countries, according to [[UNHCR]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usatoday.com/news/world/iraq/2007-03-22-christians-iraq_N.htm Christians, targeted and suffering, flee Iraq]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.asianews.it/index.php?l=en&amp;art=7410 IRAQ Terror campaign targets Chaldean church in Iraq - Asia News&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; In the 16th century, Christians constituted half of Iraq's population.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unhcr.org/cgi-bin/texis/vtx/iraq?page=news&amp;id=461e5a644 UNHCR | Iraq]&lt;/ref&gt; In 1987, the last Iraqi census counted 1.4 million Christians.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.irinnews.org/report.aspx?reportid=61897 Christians live in fear of death squads]&lt;/ref&gt; But as the [[2003 invasion of Iraq|2003 invasion]] has allowed the growth of militant [[Islamism]], Christians' total numbers slumped to about 500,000, of whom 250,000 live in Baghdad.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/pope/story/0,,1961207,00.html Jonathan Steele: While the Pope tries to build bridges in Turkey, the precarious plight of Iraq's Christians gets only worse | World news | guardian.co.uk&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, the [[Mandaeans|Mandaean]] and [[Yazidi]] communities are at the risk of elimination due to the ongoing atrocities by [[Islamism|Islamic]] extremists.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/6412453.stm Iraq's Mandaeans 'face extinction']&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/20294868/ Iraq's Yazidis fear annihilation]&lt;/ref&gt; A 25 May 2007 article notes that in the past 7 months only 69 people from Iraq have been granted [[Immigration to the United States#Asylum for refugees|refugee status]] in the [[United States]].&lt;ref&gt;Ann McFeatters: [http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/opinion/317322_mcfeatters27.html Iraq refugees find no refuge in America]. ''[[Seattle Post-Intelligencer]]'' May 25, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

* The ethnic cleansing of [[African American]] population of some racially mixed [[Los Angeles]] neighborhoods by [[Mexican American|Mexican]] [[gangs in the United States|street gangs]]. According to gang experts and law enforcement agents the [[Mexican Mafia]] leaders, or shot callers, have issued a "green light" on all blacks.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.latimes.com/news/printedition/opinion/la-op-hernandez7jan07,1,414328.story?coll=la-news-comment&amp;ctrack=1&amp;cset=true Roots of Latino/black anger]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.alternet.org/story/46855/ Ethnic Cleansing in L.A.]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.blackamericaweb.com/site.aspx/bawnews/stateof/hutchinson105 Thanks to Latino Gangs, There’s a Zone in L.A. Where Blacks Risk Death if They Enter]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/main.jhtml?xml=/news/2007/01/23/wgangs23.xml FBI called to deal with 'race' gang violence]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://observer.guardian.co.uk/world/story/0,,2036580,00.html A bloody conflict between Hispanic and black gangs is spreading across Los Angeles]&lt;/ref&gt;

*In October 2006, [[Niger]] announced that it would deport the [[Arabs]] living in the Diffa region of eastern Niger to Chad.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/6087048.stm Niger starts mass Arab expulsions]&lt;/ref&gt; This population numbered about 150,000.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.alertnet.org/thenews/newsdesk/L25138454.htm Reuters Niger's Arabs say expulsions will fuel race hate]&lt;/ref&gt; While the government was rounding Arabs in preparation for the [[deportation]], two girls died, reportedly after fleeing government forces, and three women suffered miscarriages. Niger's government had eventually suspended a controversial decision to deport Arabs.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/6081416.stm Niger's Arabs to fight expulsion]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unhcr.org/cgi-bin/texis/vtx/refworld/rwmain?docid=469638881e UNHCR | Refworld - The Leader in Refugee Decision Support]&lt;/ref&gt;

*In 1950, the [[Karen people|Karen]] had become the largest of 20 minority groups participating in an insurgency against the [[military dictatorship]] in [[Burma]]. The conflict continues as of 2008. In 2004, the BBC, citing [[aid agencies]], estimates that up to 200,000 Karen have been driven from their homes during decades of war, with 120,000 more refugees from Burma, mostly Karen, living in [[refugee camp]]s on the Thai side of the border. Many accuse the military government of Burma of ethnic cleansing.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/asia-pacific/4987224.stm Burma Karen families 'on the run'], BBC News&lt;/ref&gt; As a result of the [[Internal conflict in Burma|ongoing war]] in minority group areas more than two million people have fled Burma to [[Thailand]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.refugeesinternational.org/content/article/detail/1142/?PHPSESSID=3fc64258eda9d44c2 " Human Rights in Burma: Fifteen Years Post Military Coup "], Refugees International&lt;/ref&gt;

*[[Civil unrest in Kenya (2007–present)|Civil unrest in Kenya]] erupted in December 2007.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usatoday.com/news/world/2008-01-30-kenya-violence_N.htm U.S. envoy calls violence in Kenya 'ethnic cleansing']&lt;/ref&gt; By 28 January 2008, the death toll from the violence was at around 800.&lt;ref&gt;[http://english.aljazeera.net/NR/exeres/CA34AA32-041D-497D-BE2B-A463562C6FFF.htm Al Jazeera English - News - Kenya Ethnic Clashes Intensify&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; The United Nations estimated that as many as 600,000 people have been displaced.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2008/02/11/world/main3815702.shtml U.N.: 600,000 Displaced In Kenya Unrest]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/7174670.stm BBC NEWS | Africa | Kenya opposition cancels protests&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; A government spokesman claimed that Odinga's supporters were "engaging in ethnic cleansing".&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/7167363.stm BBC NEWS | Africa | Kenya diplomatic push for peace&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

*The [[2008 attacks on North Indians in Maharashtra]] began on 3 February 2008. Incidences of violence against [[North India]]ns and their property were reported in [[Bombay]], [[Pune]], [[Aurangabad district, Maharashtra|Aurangabad]], [[Beed]], [[Nashik]], [[Amravati]], [[Jalna district|Jalna]] and [[Latur]]. Nearly 25,000 North Indian workers fled Pune,&lt;ref name="IE_Pune_flee"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.expressindia.com/latest-news/25-000-North-Indian-workers-leave-Pune/276576/3/|accessdate=2008-04-06|title=25000 North Indian workers leave Pune|publisher=''[[Indian Express]]''}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="TOI_Pune_flee"&gt;{{cite news|title=25000 North Indians leave, Pune realty projects hit|url=http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/25000_North_Indians_leave_Pune_realty_projects_hit_/articleshow/2809937.cms|accessdate=2008-04-04|publisher=''[[Times of India]]''}}&lt;/ref&gt; and another 15,000 fled Nashik in the wake of the attacks.&lt;ref name="TOI_Nashik_flee"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/articleshow/2780795.cms|accessdate=2008-04-06|publisher=''[[Times of India]]''|date=2008-02-14|title=Maha exodus: 10,000 north Indians flee in fear}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Red_Nashik_flee"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.rediff.com/news/2008/feb/13nasik1.htm|accessdate=2008-04-06|title=MNS violence: North Indians flee Nashik, industries hit|date=2008-02-13|publisher=[[Rediff]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*[[2008 South Africa riots|South Africa Ethnic Cleansing]] erupted on 11 May 2008 within three weeks [http://www.irinnews.org/Report.aspx?ReportId=78458 80 000 were displaced] the death toll was [http://www.news24.com/News24/South_Africa/Xenophobia/0,,2-7-2382_2332419,00.html 62,] with 670 injured by the violence when South Africans ejected non-nationals in a nationwide ethnic cleansing/xenophobic outburst. The most affected foreigners have been [[Somali people|Somalis]], [[People of Ethiopia|Ethiopians]], [[Non-resident Indian and Person of Indian Origin|Indians]], [[Pakistani people|Pakistanis]], [[Zimbabwe]]ans and [[Mozambique]]ans. Local South Africans have also been caught up in the violence. [http://www.iol.co.za/index.php?set_id=1&amp;click_id=13&amp;art_id=vn20080528060919101C395802 Refugee camps a mistake] Arvin Gupta, a senior UNHCR protection officer, said the UNHCR did not agree with the City of Cape Town that those displaced by the violence should be held at camps across the city.{{Citation needed|date=May 2009|citation needed that claims that this was ethnic cleansing.}}

==Criticism of the term==
[[Gregory Stanton]], the founder of [[Genocide Watch]], has criticised the rise of the term and its use for events that he feels should be called "genocide": as "ethnic cleansing" is not a legal term, its media use can detract attention from events that should be prosecuted as genocide.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.genocidewatch.org/images/AboutGen_Ethnic_CleansingBleachesTheAtrocitiesOfGenocide.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;  

==See also==
{{Portal|Genocide|GenocidePortalLogo(ESR)2.JPG}}
{{multicol}}
* [[Aegis Students]], an international student-based genocide prevention movement
* [[1971 Bangladesh atrocities]]
* [[1989 events in Mauritania and Senegal|1989 events]] 
* [[Caste War of Yucatán]]
* [[Communal violence]]
* [[Crime against humanity]]
* [[Ethnic Cleansing (computer game)|Ethnic Cleansing]], a computer game.
* [[Ethnocide]]
* [[Expulsion of Asians in Uganda in 1972]]
* [[Forced settlements in the Soviet Union]]
* [[Generalplan Ost]]
* [[German exodus from Eastern Europe]]
* [[Germanisation]]
* [[Iraqi Turkmen]]
* [[Jasenovac]]
* [[List of events named massacres]]
{{multicol-break}}
* [[Occupation of Vojvodina, 1941-1944]]
* [[Partition of India#Independence and population exchanges|Partition of India]]
* [[Persecution of Hindus]]
* [[Persecution of Muslims]]
* [[Polish minority in the Soviet Union]]
* [[Population transfer]]
* [[Population transfer in the Soviet Union]]
* [[Refugees of Iraq]]
* [[Religious cleansing]]
* [[Rule of Law in Armed Conflicts Project (RULAC)]]
* [[Sinophobia]]
* [[Social cleansing]]
* [[The Holocaust]]
* [[Transmigration program]]
* [[World War II evacuation and expulsion]]
* [[World War II persecution of Serbs]]
{{multicol-end}}

==References==
===Notes===
{{reflist|2}}
===Bibliography===
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite journal |author=Bell-Fialkoff, Andrew |title=A Brief History of Ethnic Cleansing |journal=Foreign Affairs |volume=72 |issue=3 |year=1993 |pages=110|url=http://www.foreignaffairs.org/19930601faessay5199/andrew-bell-fialkoff/a-brief-history-of-ethnic-cleansing.html}}
* {{cite book|author=Bowker, Robert P. G.|year=2003|title=Palestinian Refugees: Mythology, Identity, and the Search for Peace|publisher=Lynne Rienner Publishers|ISBN=1588262022}}
*{{cite book|title=Ethnic cleansing in the Balkans: nationalism and the destruction of tradition|first1=Cathie|last1=Carmichael|edition=Illustrated|publisher=Routledge|year=2002|ISBN=0415274168, 9780415274166}}
* {{cite book|title=The Israeli-Palestinian Conflict: A People's War|first1=Beverley|last1=Milton-Edwards|edition=Illustrated|publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis|year=2008|ISBN=0415410436, 9780415410434}}
* {{cite book|title=The terrorist conjunction: the United States, the Israeli-Palestinian conflict, and al-Qā'ida|first1=Alfred G.|last2=Gerteiny|publisher=Greenwood Publishing Group|year=2007|ISBN=0275996433, 9780275996437|url=http://books.google.ca/books?id=yXCkz5OZ7-AC&amp;pg=PA71&amp;dq=%22ethnic+cleansing%22+palestinians&amp;lr=&amp;as_brr=3#v=onepage&amp;q=%22ethnic%20cleansing%22%20palestinians&amp;f=false}}
*{{cite book|title=Right and Wrong, and Palestine, 9-11, Iraq, 7-7 ...|first1=Ted|last1=Honderich|authorlink1=Ted Honderich|publisher=Seven Stories Press|year=2006|ISBN=1583227369, 9781583227367}}
* {{cite journal |author=Jackson Preece, Jennifer |title=Ethnic Cleansing As An Instrument of Nation-State Creation |journal=Human Rights Quarterly |volume=20 |issue=4 |year=1998 |pages=359 |doi=10.1353/hrq.1998.0039}}  
*{{cite book|title=Bridging the barrier: Israeli unilateral disengagement|first1=Tami Amanda|last1=Jacoby|edition=Illustrated|publisher=Ashgate Publishing, Ltd.|year=2007|ISBN=754649695, 9780754649694}}
*{{cite book|title=Politicide: Ariel Sharon's war against the Palestinians|first1=Baruch|last1=Kimmerling|authorlink1=Baruch Kimmerling|publisher=Verso|year=2003|ISBN=1859845177, 9781859845172}}
* {{cite book|author=McDowall, David|year=1989|title=Palestine and Israel: The Uprising and Beyond|publisher=I.B. Tauris|ISBN=1850432899}}
* {{cite journal |author=Petrovic, Drazen |title=Ethnic Cleansing - An Attempt at Methodology |journal=European Journal of International Law |volume=5 |issue=4 |year=1998 |pages=817 |url=http://www.ejil.org/journal/Vol5/No3/art3.pdf}}
*{{cite book|title=Domicide: the global destruction of home: "Top 250" Red Series Maps Series|first1=John Douglas|last1=Porteous|first2=Sandra Eileen|last2=Smith|edition=Illustrated|publisher=McGill-Queen's Press - MQUP|year=2001|ISBN=0773522581, 9780773522589|url=http://books.google.ca/books?id=6t_KSirfEnsC&amp;pg=PA89&amp;dq=%22ethnic+cleansing%22+palestinians&amp;lr=&amp;as_brr=3#v=onepage&amp;q=%22ethnic%20cleansing%22%20palestinians&amp;f=false}}
*{{cite book|title=Ethnocracy: land and identity politics in Israel/Palestine, Part 797|edition=Illustrated|first1=Oren|last1=Yiftachel|authorlink1=Oren Yiftachel|publisher=University of Pennsylvania Press|year=2006|ISBN=081223927X, 9780812239270}}
{{refend}}

== External links ==
* [http://www.hungarian-history.hu/lib/cseres/index.htm Totoist Atrocities in Vojvodina 1944-1945]
* [http://www.read-all-about-it.org/genocide/table_of_contents.html Genocide of The Ethnic Germans in Yugoslavia 1944-1948]
* [http://www.warcrimes.info/ Documents and Resources on War, War Crimes and Genocide]
* [http://www.ryanspencerreed.com/ Photojournalist's Account] - Images of ethnic cleansing in Sudan
* [http://law.bepress.com/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4600&amp;context=expresso Timothy V. Waters, ''On the Legal Construction of Ethnic Cleansing''], Paper 951, 2006, [[University of Mississippi]] School of Law (PDF)
* [http://learning.lib.vt.edu/slav/genocide.html Genocides and Ethnic Cleansings of Central and East Europe, the Former USSR, the Caucasus and Adjacent Middle East -- 1890 - 2007]
* [http://www.koteka.net/ Ethnic Cleansing in West Papua]
*[http://www.world-science.net/exclusives/070525_ethnic-cleansing.htm ''Dump the “ethnic cleansing” jargon, group implores''] [[May 31]] [[2007]], World Science
*[http://genocideinvisegrad.wordpress.com/ Visegrad Genocide Memories]
*[http://srebrenica-genocide.blogspot.com/ Srebrenica Genocide Blog]
*[http://www.institut-genocid.ba/eng_index.php Institute for Research of Crimes Against Humanity and International Law of the Sarajevo University]

{{Racism topics|state=collapsed}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Ethnic Cleansing}}
[[Category:Ethnic cleansing| ]]
[[Category:Forced migration]]
[[Category:Human rights abuses]]
[[Category:Persecution]]
[[Category:Racism]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]

[[ar:تطهير عرقي]]
[[bs:Etničko čišćenje]]
[[bg:Етническо прочистване]]
[[ca:Neteja ètnica]]
[[da:Etnisk udrensning]]
[[de:Ethnische Säuberung]]
[[et:Etniline puhastus]]
[[el:Εθνοκάθαρση]]
[[es:Limpieza étnica]]
[[eo:Etna purigado]]
[[fr:Nettoyage ethnique]]
[[ko:민족청소]]
[[hr:Etničko čišćenje]]
[[it:Pulizia etnica]]
[[he:טיהור אתני]]
[[nl:Etnische zuivering]]
[[ja:民族浄化]]
[[no:Etnisk rensning]]
[[nn:Etnisk reinsing]]
[[pl:Czystka etniczna]]
[[ro:Purificare etnică]]
[[ru:Этнические чистки]]
[[sr:Етничко чишћење]]
[[fi:Etninen puhdistus]]
[[sv:Etnisk rensning]]
[[tr:Etnik temizlik]]
[[uk:Етнічна чистка]]
[[zh:种族清洗]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>