<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20081026112022|247752465" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="19823600" pageid="19823600" ns="0" title="Discrimination against homeless people"><revisions><rev timestamp="2008-10-26T11:21:35Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[Image:Man sleeping on Canadian sidewalk.jpg|thumb|300px|right|Discrimination against the homeless often takes the form of laws which prohibit sleeping in public.]]
'''Discrimination against the [[homeless]]''' is wide-spread and takes on many forms, ranging from difficulty finding employment or new housing, to criminalization of their activities, to direct physical and verbal abuse.

__TOC__
==Violent crime==
{{Discrimination sidebar}}
There have been many violent crimes committed against the homeless. &lt;ref&gt;Fantz, Ashley, [http://www.cnn.com/2007/US/02/19/homeless.attacks/index.html?iref=newssearch "Teen 'sport killings' of homeless on the rise"], [[CNN]], February 20, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; A recent study in 2007 found that this number is increasing.&lt;ref&gt;Lewan, Todd, [http://www.usatoday.com/news/nation/2007-04-08-homelessattacks_N.htm "Unprovoked Beatings of Homeless Soaring"], [[Associated Press]], April 8, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[National Coalition for the Homeless]], [http://www.nationalhomeless.org/getinvolved/projects/hatecrimes/pressrelease.html Hate, "Violence, and Death on Main Street USA: A report on Hate Crimes and Violence Against People Experiencing Homelessness, 2006"], February 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Housing and employment discrimination==
{{Expand-section|date=October 2008}}
Homeless people are often discriminated against when attempting to obtain employment or new housing.

== Use of the law to discriminate against the homeless ==
{{main|Anti-homelessness legislation}}
Use of the law to discriminate against the homeless generally takes on one of four forms: restricting the [[public]] areas in which sitting or sleeping are allowed, prohibiting [[begging]], removing the homeless from particular areas, or enforcing laws on the homeless and not on those who are not homeless.&lt;ref name=Cunningham&gt;{{cite book |title= Out of Sight--Out of Mind? |last= Cunningham |first= Kelly |coauthors= |year= 1999 |publisher= DIANE Publishing |location= |isbn= 0788182765 |pages= p.90 |url= }}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[French literature|French]] [[novel]]ist [[Anatole France]] noted this phenomenon as long ago as 1894, famously observing that "the law, in its majestic equality, forbids the rich as well as the poor to sleep under bridges".&lt;ref name="Anatole France"&gt;{{cite book |title=Le lys rouge |last=France |first=Anatole |authorlink=Anatole France |coauthors= |year=1894 |publisher= |location= |language=[[French language|French]]|isbn= |pages= |chapter=VII |chapterurl=http://fr.wikisource.org/wiki/Le_Lys_rouge_-_VII |quote=Ils y doivent travailler devant la majestueuse égalité des lois, qui interdit au riche comme au pauvre de coucher sous les ponts}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Homeless criminalization in the United States ===

There is a growing trend in the United States towards criminalizing the state of being homeless.&lt;ref&gt;National Coalition for the Homeless: [http://www.nationalhomeless.org/publications/crimreport/report.pdf A Dream Denied].&lt;/ref&gt; Proponents of this approach believe that punitive measures will deter people from "choosing" to be homeless. To this end, cities across the country increasingly outlaw life-sustaining activities—such as sleeping, eating, sitting, and begging—in public spaces, and selectively enforce more neutral laws—such as those prohibiting open containers or [[loitering]]—against homeless populations.&lt;ref&gt;National Coalition for the Homeless: [http://www.nationalhomeless.org/publications/crimreport/report.pdf A Dream Denied].&lt;/ref&gt; Violators of such laws typically incur criminal penalties, which result in fines and/or incarceration. 
Homeless people with new "criminal charges" have very restrictive housing and employment options, if either, for years.

In April, 2006 the United States Court of Appeals for the Ninth Circuit ruled that "making it a crime to be homeless by charging them with a crime is in violation of the 8th and 14th Amendments." [http://www.ca9.uscourts.gov/ca9/newopinions.nsf/8138B5E4723C6FE988257150005B327E/$file/0455324.pdf?openelement]

==References==
{{reflist}}

== See also ==
* [[Anti-homelessness legislation]]
* [[List of organizations opposing homelessness]]

{{Discrimination}}

[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Homelessness]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>