<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20211020051036|1050833915" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="19823600" pageid="19823600" ns="0" title="Discrimination against homeless people"><revisions><rev timestamp="2021-11-04T16:19:50Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Globalize|date=December 2010}}
{{Discrimination sidebar}}
[[File:Anti-homeless Architecture.jpg|thumb|Anti-homeless Architecture]]
'''Discrimination against homeless people''' is the act of treating [[homeless]] people, or people perceived to be homeless, unfavourably. As with most types of [[discrimination]], it can manifest in numerous forms.

==Discriminatory legislation regarding homelessness==
{{Main|Criminalization of homelessness}}
Use of the law to discriminate against homeless people takes on disparate forms: restricting the [[General public|public]] areas in which sitting or sleeping are allowed, ordinances restricting [[aggressive panhandling]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite report |title=Criminalizing Crisis: The Criminalization of Homelessness in U.S. Cities |publisher=National Law Center on Homelessness &amp; Poverty |date=November 2011 |url=http://www.nlchp.org/documents/Criminalizing_Crisis |access-date=2014-04-30 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170914033003/https://www.nlchp.org/documents/Criminalizing_Crisis |archive-date=2017-09-14 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; actions intended to divert homeless people from particular areas, penalizing loitering or anti-social behavior,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title=Britain: Where have all the homeless gone? |journal=[[The Economist]] |volume=372 |issue=8388 |pages=21–49 |url=http://www.economist.com/node/3084301}}&lt;/ref&gt; or enforcing laws on homeless people and not on those who are not homeless.&lt;ref name=Cunningham&gt;{{cite book |title=Out of Sight - Out of Mind? |publisher=National Law Center on Homelessness &amp; Poverty |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=2ESQoVYYWN4C&amp;pg=PA90 |year=1999 |isbn=978-0-7881-8276-1 |page=90}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There are at least 5 states which consider crimes against homeless people with the reason being due to their homelessness to be a hate crime, which include [[Florida]], [[Maine]], [[Washington state|Washington]] and [[Rhode Island]]. It is also a hate crime stature in [[Washington, DC]].

The [[French literature|French]] [[novelist]] [[Anatole France]] noted this phenomenon as long ago as 1894, famously observing that "the law, in its majestic equality, forbids the rich as well as the poor to sleep under bridges".&lt;ref name="Anatole France"&gt;{{cite book |title=Le lys rouge |last=France |first=Anatole |author-link=Anatole France |year=1894 |language=fr |chapter=VII |chapter-url=http://fr.wikisource.org/wiki/Le_Lys_rouge_-_VII |quote=Ils y doivent travailler devant la majestueuse égalité des lois, qui interdit au riche comme au pauvre de coucher sous les ponts}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Criminal victimization==
{{see also|Homelessness in the United States#Crimes against homeless people}}
Precise factors associated with victimization and injury to homeless people are not clearly understood. Nearly one-half of homeless people are victims of violence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Meinbresse |first1=M |last2=Brinkley-Rubinstein |first2=L |last3=Grassette |first3=A |last4=Benson |first4=J |last5=Hamilton |first5=R |last6=Malott |first6=M |last7=Jenkins |first7=D |s2cid=36463124 |title=Exploring the Experiences of Violence Among Individuals Who Are Homeless Using a Consumer-Led Approach |journal=Violence &amp; Victims |date=2014 |volume=29 |issue=1 |pages=122–136 |pmid=24672998 |doi=10.1891/0886-6708.vv-d-12-00069}}&lt;/ref&gt; There have been many violent crimes committed against homeless people due to their being homeless.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Fantz |first=Ashley |url=http://www.cnn.com/2007/US/02/19/homeless.attacks/index.html |title=Teen 'sport killings' of homeless on the rise |publisher=[[CNN]] |date=February 20, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; A study in 2007 found that this number is increasing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Lewan |first=Todd |work=[[USA Today]] |url=https://www.usatoday.com/news/nation/2007-04-08-homelessattacks_N.htm |title=Unprovoked Beatings of Homeless Soaring |agency=[[Associated Press]] |date=April 8, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Lack of access to public restrooms ==

Per the [[National Alliance to End Homelessness]],&lt;ref&gt;National Alliance to End Homelessness. (2018). State of homelessness. National Alliance to End Homelessness, retrieved from https://endhomelessness.org/homelessness-in-america/homelessness-statistics/state-of-homelessness-report/&lt;/ref&gt; in January 2017, there were a total of 553,742 homeless people accounted for across the United States, including territories. Of those accounted for, 192,875 of them were unsheltered and "lived in a place not meant for human habitation, such as the street or an abandoned building". Many unsheltered homeless camps are located in industrial districts and along highways, far away from public parks facilities where traditional public bathrooms are located. If local municipalities do not provide bathroom access, homeless people are left to urinate and defecate in the streets and waterways near their camps.

Robinson and Sickels with the University of Colorado Denver&lt;ref&gt;Robinson and Sickels (2015). No right to rest criminalizing homelessness in Colorado. University of Colorado Denver and Denver Homeless Outloud, retrieved from http://www.cpr.org/sites/default/files/homelessness-study.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; released a report highlighting the criminalization of homelessness across the State of Colorado. During their research, they found that 83% of the people they interviewed said they were denied bathroom access because they were homeless. Without access to bathrooms, unsheltered homeless populations across the country are living in third-world conditions. This, in turn, leads to public health concerns such as the hepatitis A outbreak seen in California. As reported by Kushel with ''[[The New England Journal of Medicine]]'',&lt;ref&gt;Dr. Kushel, M. (2018). Hepatitis A outbreaks in California – addressing the root cause. The New England Journal of Medicine, retrieved from https://www.nejm.org/doi/full/10.1056/NEJMp1714134&lt;/ref&gt; in 2017 alone 649 people in California were infected with hepatitis A; this outbreak began in the homeless population.

== Anti-homeless architecture ==

City and town plans may incorporate [[hostile architecture]], also known as anti-homeless or defensive architecture, to deter homeless people from camping or sleeping in problematic areas.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=McFadden|first=Christopher|date=2020-11-22|title=15 Examples of 'Anti-Homeless' Hostile Architecture That You Probably Never Noticed Before|url=https://interestingengineering.com/15-examples-of-anti-homeless-hostile-architecture-that-you-probably-never-noticed-before|url-status=live|access-date=2021-10-04|website=Interesting Engineering|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt; Research conducted by [[Crisis (charity)|Crisis]] (based in the UK) recorded that 35% said they were unable to find a free place to sleep as a result of the designs. The named hostile architectures include; anti-homeless spikes, segregated benches and gated doorways.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=New research from Crisis uncovers dehumanising effects of defensive architecture |url=https://www.crisis.org.uk/about-us/latest-news/new-research-from-crisis-uncovers-dehumanising-effects-of-defensive-architecture/ |website=Crisis}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==

{{div col|colwidth=30em}}
* [[Aporophobia]]
* [[Anti-homelessness legislation]]
* [[List of homelessness organizations]]
* [[Hostile architecture]]
* [[Camden bench]]
* [[Homeless dumping]]
* [[Skid row]]
* [[Black triangle (badge)]]
* [[Social cleansing]]
* [[Vagrancy laws]]
{{div col end}}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

{{Homelessness|state=expanded}}

{{Discrimination}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Discrimination Against The Homeless}}
[[Category:Discrimination against the homeless| ]]
[[Category:All articles with unsourced statements]]
[[Category:Class discrimination]]
[[Category:Homelessness]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>