<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20161117025143|749963409" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="36859663" pageid="36859663" ns="0" title="Discrimination against non-binary people"><revisions><rev timestamp="2016-11-17T02:53:37Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{multiple issues|
{{globalize|date=June 2016}}
{{Refimprove|date=September 2012}}
}}
{{Discrimination sidebar}}
{{Transgender sidebar}}

[[Discrimination]] towards [[gender variant]] persons who fall outside of the [[gender binary]] is [[prejudice]] towards individuals whose [[gender identity]] does not fit the [[gender binary]] as strictly [[male]] or [[female]]. It can be identified as a type of [[transphobia]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Norton|first=Jody|title="Brain Says You're a Girl, But I Think You're a Sissy Boy": Cultural Origins of Transphobia|journal=International Journal of Sexuality and Gender Studies|year=1997|volume=2, Number 2|pages=139–164|doi=10.1023/A:1026320611878|issue=2}}&lt;/ref&gt;and [[sexism]].&lt;ref name="Levesque2011"&gt;{{cite book | author = Roger J.R. Levesque | title = Encyclopedia of Adolescence | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=VdPGF1tfDJsC&amp;pg=PA2641 | accessdate = 20 September 2012 | date = 5 September 2011 | publisher = Springer | isbn = 978-1-4419-1694-5 | page = 2641}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="LeongPickren2011"&gt;{{cite book | author1 = Frederick T.L. Leong | author2 = Wade E. Pickren | author3 = Mark M. Leach |author4=Anthony J. Marsella | title = Internationalizing the Psychology Curriculum in the United States | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=RrATt7OYuP0C&amp;pg=PA163 | accessdate = 20 September 2012 | date = 1 November 2011 | publisher = Springer | isbn = 978-1-4614-0072-1 | page = 163}}&lt;/ref&gt;It affects [[third gender]], [[genderqueer]], [[agender]], and other non-binary identified people. [[Cisgender]] and binary [[transgender]] people can both display prejudice against non-binary people, and discrimination of this sort can be found in the transgender community. Much discrimination towards non-binary identifying individuals can be found in the [[lesbian]], [[gay]], [[bisexual]], and transgender ([[LGBT]]) communities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/kelsie-brynn-jones/when-being-trans-is-not-t_b_6340728.html | title=When Being Trans Is Not Trans Enough | work=Huffington Post | date=February 2, 2016 | accessdate=June 4, 2016 | author=Kelsie Brynn Jones}}&lt;/ref&gt; Discrimination towards non-binary persons demonstrates the existence of a gender hierarchy, since genders outside the binary are considered "other" and are often not widely accepted in society.

In the binary sex/gender system, genderqueerness is unintelligible and abjected.&lt;ref name="ftmborderlands"&gt;Hale, J.C. (1998) "...[O]ur embodiments and our subjectivities are abjected from social ontology: we cannot fit ourselves into extant categories without denying, eliding, erasing, or otherwise abjecting personally significant aspects of ourselves ... When we choose to live with and in our dislocatedness, fractured from social ontology, we choose to forgo intelligibility: lost in language and in social life, we become virtually unintelligible, even to ourselves..." from ''Consuming the Living, Dis(Re)Membering the Dead in the Butch/FtM Borderlands'' in the ''Gay and Lesbian Quarterly'' 4:311, 336 (1998). Retrieved on 2007-04-07.&lt;/ref&gt; A 2008 study in the ''National Transgender Discrimination Survey'' showed that genderqueer and other non-binary individuals were more likely to suffer physical assaults (32% vs. 25%), experience police brutality and harassment (31% vs. 21%), and opt out of medical treatment due to discrimination (36% vs. 27%) compared to transgender individuals who identified within the gender binary (i.e., [[trans man|trans men]] and [[trans woman|trans women]]). This study also found that they were more likely to be [[people of color]] (30% vs. 23%) and younger (under 45) than binary transgender people (89% vs. 68%).&lt;ref name="Harrison2011"&gt;{{cite journal |author1=Jack Harrison |author2=Jaime Grant |author3=Jody L. Herman | title = A Gender Not Listed Here: Genderqueers, Gender Rebels, and Otherwise in the National Transgender Discrimination Survey | publisher = Harvard Kennedy School | journal = LGBTQ Policy Journal | volume = 2 | issue = | page = 22 | year = 2011–2012 | doi = | url = http://www.thetaskforce.org/downloads/release_materials/agendernotlistedhere.pdf | format = PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt; In another study conducted by the [[National LGBTQ Task Force]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | url=http://www.thetaskforce.org/gender-listed-genderqueers-gender-rebels-otherwise-national-transgender-discrimination-survey/ | title=A Gender Not Listed Here: Genderqueers, Gender Rebels, and Otherwise in the National Transgender Discrimination Survey | authors=Jack Harrison, Jaime Grant, and Jody L. Herman | journal=LGBTQ Policy Journal | volume=2 | publisher=Harvard Kennedy School | date=April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; responders who identified as neither male nor female were less likely to be white and more likely to be multi racial, Black, or Asian, but less likely to be [[Hispanic and Latino Americans|Latin-American/Spanish in origin]] compared to those who identified as male or female. 20% of non-binary individuals lived in the lowest household income category.&lt;ref name="taskforce" /&gt;

==Legal discrimination==

===United States===
Despite being more likely to receive higher levels of education when compared to the general public, 90% of non-binary individuals face discrimination, often in the form of harassment in the workplace. 19% of genderqueer individuals report job loss as a result of their identities.&lt;ref name="transgenderlawcenter"&gt;{{Cite web|title = Non-Binary Identities &amp; the Law {{!}} Transgender Law Center|url = http://transgenderlawcenter.org/archives/10208|website = transgenderlawcenter.org|accessdate = 2015-10-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; Because identifying as non binary is an emergent and lesser-known identity, anti-discrimination laws that outline prohibition of discrimination for non binary individuals specifically does not exist. However, [[Title VII]] and the current proposed version of the federal [[Employment Non-Discrimination Act]] use such terms as "gender identity" and "gender expression," categories under which non binary individuals fall due to the fact that their gender expression cannot be defined as male or female.&lt;ref name="transgenderlawcenter" /&gt;

Twelve states currently have legislation which bars discrimination based on gender identity.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title = State Laws That Prohibit Discrimination Against Transgender People - National Center for Lesbian Rights|url = http://www.nclrights.org/legal-help-resources/resource/state-laws-that-prohibit-discrimination-against-transgender-people/|website = www.nclrights.org|accessdate = 2015-10-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; Despite these efforts, non-binary individuals have higher rates of physical and sexual assault and police harassment than those who identify as men or women, likely due to their gender expression or presentation.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title = 10 Myths About Non-Binary People It's Time to Unlearn|url = http://everydayfeminism.com/2014/12/myths-non-binary-people/|website = [[Everyday Feminism]]|accessdate = 2015-10-21|language = en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There is currently no way to acquire a federal license with a nonbinary designation, as the only options are currently male or female. The origin of these legal restrictions is the classification of gender identity into only two distinct genders, male and female, is known as the [[gender binary]]. 

=== United Kingdom ===
Non-binary is not recognized as a legal gender in the United Kingdom.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://nonbinary.org/wiki/Legal_gender#UK|title=Legal gender - Nonbinary.org|website=nonbinary.org|access-date=2016-10-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Gender Recognition Act 2004]] allowed people to apply to the [https://www.gov.uk/apply-gender-recognition-certificate Gender Recognition Panel] for a change of gender after living as the gender you wish to show on all your legal documents and being given a diagnosis of [[gender dysphoria]] by at least two health professionals. However, this change of gender only allowed for a change from male to female or vice versa. 

In 2006 the [[Identity Cards Act 2006]] was introduced, which issued documents to UK residents and linked them back to the National Identity Register database. When the issue of transgender people and their assigned vs. inner gender came up, it was said that transgender people would be issued two cards, each with a separate male and female gender marker.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201011/cmpublic/identity/100706/am/100706s01.htm|title=House of Commons Public Bill Committee : Identity Documents Bill|website=www.publications.parliament.uk|access-date=2016-10-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was also said that eventually the hope for some was that the identity cards would get rid of the gender markers all together. The [[Identity Documents Act 2010]] made all these cards invalid and called for their immediate destruction. 

== Health discrimination  ==

===United States===
14% reported discrimination in medical care, but were "more likely to avoid care altogether when sick or injured because of the fear of discrimination."&lt;ref name="taskforce"&gt;{{Cite web|title = A Gender Not Listed Here: Genderqueers, Gender Rebels, and OtherWise in the National Transgender Discrimination Survey - The Task Force|url = http://www.thetaskforce.org/gender-listed-genderqueers-gender-rebels-otherwise-national-transgender-discrimination-survey/|website = The Task Force|accessdate = 2015-10-21|language = en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===United Kingdom===
In a similar survey conducted by UK Trans Info, the vast majority of non-binary responders reported "fear of treatment being denied" as the main deterrent for not seeking healthcare. Many reported anxiety over having to deny their identities or  "pretend to be someone [they are] not" in order to receive treatment. As a result, 20% reported self-medicating as an alternative to seeking healthcare.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title = Experiences of non-binary people accessing healthcare|url = http://uktrans.info/research/45-medical-research/378-experiences-of-non-binary-people-accessing-healthcare|website = UK Trans Info|accessdate = 2015-10-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{distinguish|Discrimination against intersex people}}
{{Portal|Transgender|Discrimination}}
* [[Cissexism]]
* [[Gender binary]]
* [[Gender variance]]
* [[Genderism]]
* [[List of people with non-binary gender identities]]
* [[List of transgender-related topics]]
* [[Transphobia]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{LGBT}}
{{Discrimination}}

[[Category:Discrimination against LGBT people]]
[[Category:Genderqueer]]
[[Category:Gender studies]]
[[Category:Sexuality and gender-related prejudices]]
[[Category:Transgender]]
[[Category:Transphobia]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>