<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20191120102616|927104392" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="36859663" pageid="36859663" ns="0" title="Discrimination against non-binary people"><revisions><rev timestamp="2019-11-20T10:30:51Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{distinguish|Discrimination against intersex people}}
{{short description|Prejudicial treatment of people who do not identify as exclusively male or female}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=June 2019}}
{{Discrimination sidebar}}
{{Transgender sidebar}}
[[Discrimination]] or prejudice against [[non-binary]] people, people who do not [[Gender identity|identify]] as exclusively male or female, may occur in social, legal, or medical contexts. Both [[cisgender]] and binary [[transgender]] people (men and women), including members of the [[lesbian]], [[gay]], and [[bisexual]] communities, can display such prejudice.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/kelsie-brynn-jones/when-being-trans-is-not-t_b_6340728.html | title=When Being Trans Is Not Trans Enough | work=Huffington Post | date=February 2, 2016 | accessdate=June 4, 2016 | author=Kelsie Brynn Jones}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{unreliable source|sure=y|reason=HuffPo contributor blog|date=October 2019}}

==Social discrimination==
In the [[binary gender]] system, genderqueerness is unintelligible and abjected.&lt;ref name="ftmborderlands"&gt;Hale, J.C. (1998) "...[O]ur embodiments and our subjectivities are abjected from social ontology: we cannot fit ourselves into extant categories without denying, eliding, erasing, or otherwise abjecting personally significant aspects of ourselves ... When we choose to live with and in our dislocatedness, fractured from social ontology, we choose to forgo intelligibility: lost in language and in social life, we become virtually unintelligible, even to ourselves..." from ''Consuming the Living, Dis(Re)Membering the Dead in the Butch/FtM Borderlands'' in the ''Gay and Lesbian Quarterly'' 4:311, 336 (1998). Retrieved on April 7, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Discrimination|Social discrimination]] in the context of discrimination against non-binary and gender non-conforming people includes hate-motivated violence and excusing of such. According to a 2016 study from ''[[Journal of Sex Research|The Journal of Sex Research]],'' one of the most common themes of discrimination for genderqueer people is the incorrect use of preferred gender pronouns. The study labeled this as 'nonaffirmation', and it occurs when others do not affirm one's sense of gender identity. Participants within this study also reported experiencing [[gender policing]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Nadal|first=Kevin L.|last2=Whitman|first2=Chassitty N.|last3=Davis|first3=Lindsey S.|last4=Erazo|first4=Tanya|last5=Davidoff|first5=Kristin C.|date=2016-03-11|title=Microaggressions Toward Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, Transgender, Queer, and Genderqueer People: A Review of the Literature|journal=The Journal of Sex Research|language=en|volume=53|issue=4–5|pages=488–508|doi=10.1080/00224499.2016.1142495|pmid=26966779|issn=0022-4499}}&lt;/ref&gt; An article from the book ''Violence and Gender'', states that this experienced violence and discrimination leads to high levels of stress. This article stated that non-binary participants are less likely to experience hate speech (24.4% vs. 50%) compared to trans men and equally as likely (24.4% vs. 24.4%) as trans women, yet genderqueer/nonbinary participants, along with trans women are more likely than trans men individuals to be concerned about the safety of themselves and others.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Veldhuis|first=Cindy B.|last2=Drabble|first2=Laurie|last3=Riggle|first3=Ellen D.B.|last4=Wootton|first4=Angie R.|last5=Hughes|first5=Tonda L.|date=March 2018|title="I Fear for My Safety, but Want to Show Bravery for Others": Violence and Discrimination Concerns Among Transgender and Gender-Nonconforming Individuals After the 2016 Presidential Election|journal=Violence and Gender|volume=5|issue=1|pages=26–36|doi=10.1089/vio.2017.0032|issn=2326-7836}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Workplace discrimination==
{{Globalize|section|USA|2name=the United States|date=October 2018}}

===United States===
In the United States of America, unemployment rates for transgender people are approximately twice as high as those for cisgender people.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.thetaskforce.org/static_html/downloads/reports/reports/ntds_full.pdf|title=Injustice At Every Turn: A Report Of The National Transgender Discrimination Survey|last=Grant, Jaime M., Mottet, Lisa A., &amp; Tanis, Justin|date=April 26, 2017|website=thetaskforce.org|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150506162958/http://www.thetaskforce.org/static_html/downloads/reports/reports/ntds_full.pdf|archive-date=May 6, 2015|url-status=dead|access-date=April 26, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the National Transgender Discrimination Survey&lt;ref name="ncte-ntds"&gt;{{cite web|title=National Transgender Discrimination Survey|url=https://transequality.org/sites/default/files/docs/resources/NTDS_Report.pdf|website=National Center for Transgender Equality|accessdate=April 26, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; conducted by the LGBTQ+ Task Force, 90% of transgender employees said they have experienced discrimination of some form in the workplace; 50% of participants reported being harassed at work and 47% reported an adverse job outcome. That includes being fired or denied a promotion. In addition, 32% felt forced to act “traditionally gendered” to keep their jobs and 22% were denied access to bathrooms of choice based in gender identity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Thoroughgood |first1=Christian N. |last2=Sawyer |first2=Katina B. |last3=Webster |first3=Jennica R. |title=What lies beneath: How paranoid cognition explains the relations between transgender employees' perceptions of discrimination at work and their job attitudes and wellbeing |journal=Journal of Vocational Behavior |date=December 2017 |volume=103 |pages=99–112 |doi=10.1016/j.jvb.2017.07.009}}&lt;/ref&gt; 78% of those who had transitioned during their time at the workplace were happy with their choice to do so, and reported feeling more comfortable at work, although they experienced more discrimination.&lt;ref name="ncte-ntds"/&gt;

Not only does discrimination against transgender people in the workplace affect transgender employees, but it also affects the entire workplace team, distracting the victim and the perpetrator from the job itself.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Barclay |first1=J.M. |last2=Scott |first2=L.J. |title=Transsexuals and workplace diversity |journal=Personnel Review |date=July 2006 |volume=35 |issue=4 |pages=487–502 |doi=10.1108/00483480610670625}}&lt;/ref&gt; Transgender individuals in the U.S. often face workplace discrimination like conflicts related to their bathroom usage, backlash over transitioning genders and being “misgendered” by coworkers. The Center of American Progress in 2012 also found that there is also a substantial amount of public ignorance towards transgender communities, in comparison to LGB community peers. Because of that, negative psychological consequences occur as a result like mental health disparities, higher rates in attempted suicide, and paranoid thinking in public spaces.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Haas |first1=Ann P. |last2=Eliason |first2=Mickey |last3=Mays |first3=Vickie M. |last4=Mathy |first4=Robin M. |last5=Cochran |first5=Susan D. |last6=D'Augelli |first6=Anthony R. |last7=Silverman |first7=Morton M. |last8=Fisher |first8=Prudence W. |last9=Hughes |first9=Tonda |last10=Rosario |first10=Margaret |last11=Russell |first11=Stephen T. |last12=Malley |first12=Effie |last13=Reed |first13=Jerry |last14=Litts |first14=David A. |last15=Haller |first15=Ellen |last16=Sell |first16=Randall L. |last17=Remafedi |first17=Gary |last18=Bradford |first18=Judith |last19=Beautrais |first19=Annette L. |last20=Brown |first20=Gregory K. |last21=Diamond |first21=Gary M. |last22=Friedman |first22=Mark S. |last23=Garofalo |first23=Robert |last24=Turner |first24=Mason S. |last25=Hollibaugh |first25=Amber |last26=Clayton |first26=Paula J. |title=Suicide and Suicide Risk in Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, and Transgender Populations: Review and Recommendations |journal=Journal of Homosexuality |date=30 December 2010 |volume=58 |issue=1 |pages=10–51 |doi=10.1080/00918369.2011.534038 |doi-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the NTDS, almost all non-binary persons had experienced discrimination in the workplace. Their findings show that being out as a non-binary person negatively affects that person's employment outcomes. Though non-binary persons have higher unemployment rates than those who identify with a specified gender, masculine non-binary persons who still appear male, or are not "passing as female" generally have a harder time in the work environment.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://scholarworks.umass.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1331&amp;context=masters_theses_2|title=Gender Inequality: Nonbinary Transgender People in the Workplace|last=Davidson|first=Skylar|date=April 26, 2017|website=umass.edu|archive-url=http://scholarworks.umass.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1331&amp;context=masters_theses_2|archive-date=April 26, 2017|url-status=}}&lt;/ref&gt; 19% of non-binary trans persons reported job loss due to anti-transgender bias, a smaller proportion than for other respondents (27%).&lt;ref name="transgenderlawcenter" /&gt;{{rp|8}}

==Health discrimination==

===United States===
A survey conducted among rural U.S. LGBT populations suggested that transgender and non-binary patients were three times more likely to find health care providers that have other LGBT patients. They were also three times more likely to drive over an hour out of the way to visit their health care provider due "to the fact that in the last year, one in ten had visited an LGBT-specific health care clinic, which are often located in urban areas."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Whitehead|first=J.|last2=Shaver|first2=John|last3=Stephenson|first3=Rob|date=January 5, 2016|title=Outness, Stigma, and Primary Health Care Utilization among Rural LGBT Populations|journal=PLoS ONE|volume=11|issue=1|pages=e0146139|doi=10.1371/journal.pone.0146139|issn=1932-6203|pmc=4701471|pmid=26731405}}&lt;/ref&gt; With that being said, non-binary individuals, and members of the LGBTQ community are very tentative when sharing their sexual identities to health care providers in fear of receiving inadequate/unfair treatment.

20.4% of transgender and gender-nonconforming respondents to the NTDS reported having experienced discrimination when trying to access doctors and hospitals, 11.9% when attempting to access emergency rooms, and 4.6% when attempting to access the service of an ambulance.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Kattari|first=Shanna K.|last2=Walls|first2=N. Eugene|last3=Whitfield|first3=Darren L.|last4=Langenderfer-Magruder|first4=Lisa|date=2015-04-03|title=Racial and Ethnic Differences in Experiences of Discrimination in Accessing Health Services Among Transgender People in the United States|journal=International Journal of Transgenderism|language=en|volume=16|issue=2|pages=68–79|doi=10.1080/15532739.2015.1064336|issn=1553-2739}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===United Kingdom===
In the UK, non-binary individuals also experience health discrimination. Under the law of the United Kingdom, individuals are considered by the state to be either male or female, the gender that is stated on their birth certificate. This means that non-binary gender is not recognized in UK law. In a 2015 survey conducted by the Scottish Trans Alliance, three main areas were focused on including, non-binary individuals' experiences of medical services. When asked if they had ever experienced problems getting the help that was needed because of their non-binary identity, 56% said that they had. Some examples of this discrimination included refusal of surgery, withholding of treatment, discharging from clinics for being "untreatable," and no treatment due to not having protocol for non-binary individuals. In addition, more than half of the respondents answered that they experienced a delay in their treatment after being honest and open about their non-binary gender identities.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.scottishtrans.org/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/Non-binary-GIC-mini-report.pdf|title=Non-binary people's experiences of using UK gender identity clinics}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legal discrimination==
{{distinguish|Legal recognition of non-binary gender}}

===United States===
Despite being more likely to achieve higher levels of education when compared to the general public,&lt;ref name="transgenderlawcenter"&gt;{{Cite web|title = Non-Binary Identities &amp; the Law|url=http://transgenderlawcenter.org/archives/10208|website = transgenderlawcenter.org|accessdate=October 21, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|11}} 90% of non-binary individuals face discrimination, often in the form of harassment in the workplace. Nineteen percent of genderqueer individuals report job loss as a result of their identities.&lt;ref name="transgenderlawcenter"/&gt; Anti-discrimination laws that prohibit discrimination specifically against non-binary individuals do not exist.{{citation needed|date=October 2017}} However, [[Title VII]] and the current proposed version of the federal [[Employment Non-Discrimination Act]] use such terms as "gender identity" and "gender expression", categories under which non-binary individuals fall due to the fact that their gender expression cannot be defined as male or female.&lt;ref name="transgenderlawcenter" /&gt;

In 2004, Jimmie Smith was terminated from the fire department in Salem, Ohio after revealing their diagnosis with Gender Identity Disorder and intentions to undergo a male to female transition. The district court determined the reason for termination was because of their "transexuality" and not their gender non-conformity. The case was appealed to the Sixth Circuit, which overturned that decision and clarified to courts that under Title VII, sex discrimination was to be considered broader than only the traditional assumptions of sex.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Reineck|first=Katie|date=2017|title=RUNNING FROM THE GENDER POLICE: RECONCEPTUALIZING GENDER TO ENSURE PROTECTION FOR NON-BINARY PEOPLE.|url=|journal=Michigan Journal of Gender &amp; Law|volume=24|pages=265–322|via=OmniFile Full Text Mega (H.W. Wilson)}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Twelve states currently have legislation which bars discrimination based on gender identity.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title = State Laws That Prohibit Discrimination Against Transgender People - National Center for Lesbian Rights|url = http://www.nclrights.org/legal-help-resources/resource/state-laws-that-prohibit-discrimination-against-transgender-people/|website = www.nclrights.org|accessdate = 2015-10-21|date = 2013-07-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; Despite these efforts, non-binary individuals are subject to higher rates of physical and sexual assault and police harassment than those who identify as men or women, likely due to their gender expression or presentation.&lt;ref name="Harrison2011"&gt;{{cite journal|author1=Jack Harrison|author2=Jaime Grant|author3=Jody L. Herman|year=2011–2012|title=A Gender Not Listed Here: Genderqueers, Gender Rebels, and Otherwise in the National Transgender Discrimination Survey|url=http://www.thetaskforce.org/downloads/release_materials/agendernotlistedhere.pdf|format=PDF|journal=LGBTQ Policy Journal|volume=2|access-date=March 4, 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120725182217/http://www.thetaskforce.org/downloads/release_materials/agendernotlistedhere.pdf|archive-date=July 25, 2012|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title = 10 Myths About Non-Binary People It's Time to Unlearn|url = http://everydayfeminism.com/2014/12/myths-non-binary-people/|website = [[Everyday Feminism]]|accessdate = 2015-10-21|language = en-US|date = 2014-12-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Identity documents====
According to the Transgender Law Center, 70% of transgender people are not able to update their identity documents and one-third of have been harassed, assaulted or turned away when seeking basic services,&lt;ref name=osf-2017&gt;{{cite web |title=Gender Identity Recognition at the Border and Beyond |last1=Skeen |first1=Lisa |url=https://www.opensocietyfoundations.org/voices/gender-identity-recognition-border-and-beyond |date=April 5, 2017 |website=Open Society Foundations |publisher= |accessdate=October 26, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
and one third are not able to update their documents post-transition.
&lt;ref name=hrc-2017&gt;{{cite web |title=Understanding the Transgender Community |author=&lt;!--staff writers, no byline--&gt; |url=https://www.hrc.org/resources/understanding-the-transgender-community |date= |website=Human Rights Campaign |publisher= |accessdate=October 26, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2016, the U.S. State Department was sued for denying a passport to [[Dana Zzyym]], who is a veteran, an intersex person and then also identified as a non-binary person. Zzyym wrote "intersex" on their passport form instead of male or female, which were the only two available gender fields on the form. Zzyym was denied the passport, which led to LGBTQ advocacy organizations filing a lawsuit against the U.S. State Department on Zzyym's behalf. The advocacy group [[Lambda Legal]] argued for gender-neutral terms and a third option on U.S. passports, arguing that the existing passport fields violated the [[Due Process Clause]] and [[Equal Protection Clause]] of the U.S. Constitution. The State Department argued that adding additional gender fields to the passport form would prevent the agency's efforts to combat identity theft and passport fraud. The Tenth Circuit Court ruled in favor of Zzyym, the first time in U.S. history that the federal government recognized non-binary people.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.pbs.org/newshour/rundown/intersex-dana-zzyym-passport-decision/|title=Judge rules in favor of intersex veteran who was denied passport|website=PBS NewsHour|date=November 23, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

California, the District of Columbia, New York City, New York State, Iowa, Vermont, Oregon and Washington State have currently removed the surgical requirement to complete a change on a birth certificate. In these states, to change the gender on a birth certificate, one must fill out a standardized form but legal or medical approvals are not required. In Washington D.C., the applicant fills out the top half of the form and a health or social service professional must fill out the bottom half. A person may face obstacles obtaining a court order in order to make a change to documents in other states. Tennessee is the only state that has a specific statute that forbids altering the gender designation on a birth certificate due to gender surgery, while Idaho and Ohio have the same prohibition, but via court decision rather than by statute; and in Puerto Rico, a U.S. territory, a court ruled that gender markers could not be changed on identity documents under any circumstances.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lambdalegal.org/know-your-rights/article/trans-identity-document-faq|title=FAQ About Identity Documents|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=lambda-state&gt;{{cite web |title=Changing Birth Certificate Sex Designations: State-By-State Guidelines |author=&lt;!--staff writers, no byline--&gt; |url=https://www.lambdalegal.org/know-your-rights/article/trans-changing-birth-certificate-sex-designations |date=February 3, 2015 |website=Lambda Legal |publisher= |accessdate=October 26, 2017 |quote= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In California, the Gender Recognition Act of 2017 was introduced in the State Senate in Sacramento in January 2017, and signed into law by governor [[Jerry Brown]] on October 19.  The law recognizes a [[third gender]] option known as "non-binary" which may be used on state-issued documents such as driver's licenses to more accurately reflect a person's gender. Senate bill SB179 was originally drafted by State Senators [[Toni Atkins]] and [[Scott Wiener]].  The law also makes it easier for existing documents to be changed, by removing requirements for sworn statements by physicians and replacing it with a sworn attestation by the person seeking to make the change to their documents.  The Executive Director of Equality California commented, "It is up to an individual—not a judge or even a doctor—to define a person's gender identity."&lt;ref name="Gutierrez-2017"&gt;{{cite web |title=Bill seeks 3rd gender option on licenses, birth certificates |last1=Gutierrez |first1=Melody |url=http://www.sfgate.com/news/article/Calif-lawmakers-seek-nonbinary-gender-10886782.php |date=January 26, 2017 |website=SFGate |publisher=[[Hearst Communications|Hearst]] |accessdate=October 26, 2017 |quote= }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Bowerman-2017"&gt;{{cite web |title=Female, male or non-binary: California legally recognizes a third gender on identification documents |last1=Bowerman |first1=Mary |url=https://www.usatoday.com/story/news/nation-now/2017/10/19/female-male-non-binary-california-legally-recognizes-third-gender-identification-documents/779188001/ |date=January 26, 2017 |website=USA Today |publisher=[[Gannett]] |accessdate=October 26, 2017 |quote= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The first two U.S. citizens to receive a court decreed gender of non-binary were in Oregon and California. In [[Oregon]], [[Jamie Shupe]] was able to obtain a non-binary designation in June 2016 after a brief legal battle.&lt;!--don't use a gender-neutral pronoun here: Shupe now identifies as male. See https://jamieshupe.wordpress.com/2019/01/26/public-announcement-i-have-returned-to-my-male-birth-sex/--&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.portlandmercury.com/images/blogimages/2016/06/15/1466024211-shupe_ruling.pdf|title=Case No.: 16CV13991: In The Matter Of The Sex Change Of Jamie Shupe, Petitioner|last=Holmes Hehn|first=Amy|date=June 10, 2016|work=Portland Mercury|access-date=November 30, 2018|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160626085558/https://www.portlandmercury.com/images/blogimages/2016/06/15/1466024211-shupe_ruling.pdf|archive-date=June 20, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2016/jun/16/jamie-shupe-first-non-binary-person-oregon|title=Jamie Shupe becomes first legally non-binary person in the US|first=Lauren|last=Dake|date=June 16, 2016|publisher=|via=The Guardian|newspaper=The Guardian}}&lt;/ref&gt; Following in Shupe's footsteps, [[California]] resident Sarah Kelly Keenan was also able to legally change her gender marker to non-binary in September 2016.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.nbcnews.com/feature/nbc-out/californian-becomes-second-us-citizen-granted-non-binary-gender-status-n654611|title=Californian becomes second US citizen granted 'non-binary' gender status|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; After both Shupe and Keenan had success with their cases, more people have been inspired to take on the legal battle of changing their gender to a non-binary marker. With the help of organizations such as [https://www.intersexrecognition.org/ Intersex &amp; Genderqueer Recognition Project] dozens of these petitions have been granted and additional states have changed regulations to provide a third gender option on state ID, birth certificates, and/or court orders.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.intersexrecognition.org/resources|title=Resources|website=www.intersexrecognition.org|access-date=July 31, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===United Kingdom===

Non-binary is not recognized as a legal gender in the United Kingdom.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://nonbinary.org/wiki/Legal_gender#UK|title=Legal gender - Nonbinary.org|website=nonbinary.org|access-date=2016-10-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Gender Recognition Act 2004]] allowed people to apply to the [https://www.gov.uk/apply-gender-recognition-certificate Gender Recognition Panel] for a change of gender after living as the gender they wished to show on all their legal documents and being given a diagnosis of [[gender dysphoria]] by at least two health professionals. However, this change of gender only allowed for a change from male to female or vice versa.

In 2006 the [[Identity Cards Act 2006]] was introduced, which issued documents with binary gender markers to UK residents and linked them back to the National Identity Register database. The [[Identity Documents Act 2010]] made all these cards invalid and called for their immediate destruction.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201011/cmpublic/identity/100706/am/100706s01.htm|title=House of Commons Public Bill Committee : Identity Documents Bill|website=www.publications.parliament.uk|access-date=2016-10-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Canada ===
In 2002, the [[Northwest Territories]] was the first of [[Canada]]’s provinces to explicitly include gender identity as a protected group from discrimination under the law, followed by [[Manitoba]] in 2012.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Cossman|first=Brenda|date=January 2018|title=Gender identity, gender pronouns, and freedom of expression: Bill C-16 and the traction of specious legal claims|journal=University of Toronto Law Journal|volume=68|issue=1|pages=37–79|doi=10.3138/utlj.2017-0073|issn=0042-0220}}&lt;/ref&gt; By 2015, every Canadian province and territory had included similar changes to their discrimination laws.

In 2017, Canada passed [[An Act to amend the Canadian Human Rights Act and the Criminal Code|Bill C-16]] which formally recognized non-binary gender people and granted them protection under the law towards discrimination on the grounds of “gender identity” and “gender expression.”

===Australia===
The Sex Discrimination Act of 1984 did not explicitly protect non-binary persons from discrimination until the Sex Discrimination Amendment (Sexual Orientation, Gender Identity and Intersex Status) Act of 2013, which prohibited any discrimination on the grounds of "gender identity" and "intersex status". This amendment also removed the use of "other" and "opposite sex" in exchange for broader terms like "different sex".&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Bennett|first=Theodore|date=2014|title='No man's land': Non-binary sex identification in Australian law and policy|url=http://www.unswlawjournal.unsw.edu.au/wp-content/uploads/2017/09/37-3-14.pdf|journal=University of New South Wales Law Journal|volume=37|pages=847–873}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2014, the [[Australian High Court]] legally recognized non-binary as a category for people to identify with on legal documents. After [[Norrie May-Welby]] made a request for a third gender identity on legal documents and was eventually denied, Norrie chose to take the matter up with Australia's [[Human Rights Commission]] and their [[Court of Appeal]]. After a four-year long legal battle beginning in 2010, Norrie finally won the case. From this and the legalizing of the matter in [[New South Wales]], the [[Australian Capital Territory]] made the decision to pass a law which recognized non-binary identities. Several other states and territories followed suit afterwards.

==See also==
{{Portal|Transgender}}
* [[Androgyny]]
* [[Drop the T]]
* [[Gender polarization]]
* [[Gender variance]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{Discrimination}}
{{LGBT}}

[[Category:Discrimination against LGBT people]]
[[Category:Non-binary gender]]
[[Category:Gender studies]]
[[Category:Transphobia]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>