<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20170401153510|773297040" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="53659078" pageid="53659078" ns="0" title="Structural discrimination"><revisions><rev timestamp="2017-04-01T15:35:49Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Discrimination sidebar|state=collapsed}}
'''Structural discrimination''' is an unintentional form of [[discrimination]] resulting from policies that were enacted with the intent to be neutral with regard to characteristics such as race and gender.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Lee|first1=S|last2=Chiu|first2=MY|last3=Tsang|first3=A|last4=Chui|first4=H|last5=Kleinman|first5=A|title=Stigmatizing experience and structural discrimination associated with the treatment of schizophrenia in Hong Kong.|journal=Social Science &amp; Medicine (1982)|date=April 2006|volume=62|issue=7|pages=1685-96|pmid=16174547}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|1693}}&lt;ref name=pincus/&gt; Such discrimination occurs when these policies, despite apparently being neutral, nevertheless have disproportionately negative effects on certain societal groups.&lt;ref name=pincus&gt;{{cite journal|last1=PINCUS|first1=F. L.|title=Discrimination Comes in Many Forms: Individual, Institutional, and Structural|journal=American Behavioral Scientist|date=1 November 1996|volume=40|issue=2|pages=186–194|doi=10.1177/0002764296040002009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |url=https://www.nap.edu/read/10887/chapter/7#63 |title=Measuring Racial Discrimination |publisher=National Academy of Sciences |year=2004 |editor-last=Blank |editor-first=Rebecca M. |page=63}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some conceptualizations of structural discrimination focus on past forms of discrimination that have resulted in present-day inequality, while others focus on policies that still exist today and can have disproportionately negative effects on minority groups.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Pager|first1=D|last2=Shepherd|first2=H|title=The Sociology of Discrimination: Racial Discrimination in Employment, Housing, Credit, and Consumer Markets.|journal=Annual Review of Sociology|date=1 January 2008|volume=34|pages=181-209|pmid=20689680|pmc=2915460}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
==See also==
*[[Structural discrimination in New Zealand]]
==References==
{{Reflist}}

[[Category:Discrimination]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>