<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20051111091531|28011229" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="56285" pageid="56285" ns="0" title="Disability"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-11-11T12:25:21Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">The term "'''disability'''", as it is applied to [[human]]s, refers to any condition that impedes the completion of daily tasks using traditional methods. National [[government]]s and global [[humanitarian]] agencies have narrowed this definition for their own purposes, only pledging aid to those with specific disabilities of a certain severity. 

== Demographics of disability ==
Many books on disability and [[disability rights]] point out that the disabled community is one of very few groups of people that one doesn't have to be born into, as disability can develop later in life as well. Some disability rights activists use an acronym, TAB, humorously to point this out: TAB stands for "temporarily able-bodied" as a reminder that many become disabled as they join the ranks of the elderly.

In most areas of the world, but especially in developed countries, the number of people with disabilities is growing and becoming a more significant percentage of the population because medicine is allowing more people to live who might have otherwise died in less advanced times.

==Types of disability==

"Disability" can be broken down into a number of broad sub-categories, which can include the following:   

* Physical impairments affecting movement, such as [[muscular dystrophy]], [[post-polio syndrome]], [[spina bifida]] and [[cerebral palsy]].
* Sensory impairments, such as visual or hearing impairments.
* Neurological impairments, such as [[epilepsy]] or [[dysautonomia]].
* Cognitive impairments such as [[Autism]] or [[Down Syndrome]].
* Psychiatric conditions such as [[clinical depression|depression]] and [[Schizophrenia]].

Some disabilities are not obvious to outside observers; these are termed [[Invisible disability|invisible disabilities]].

A person may be impaired either by a correctable condition such as [[myopia]], or by an unchangeable one such as [[cerebral palsy]]. For those with mild conditions, related impairments can improve or disappear with the application of corrective devices. More serious impairments call for adaptive equipment.

A [[List_of_disabilities|list of disabilities]] can never be complete or finalized because individuals, organizations, and governments define disabilities differently.

==The evolution of a movement==

Historically, disabilities have often been cast in a negative light. An individual thus affected was seen as being a “patient” subject either to cure or to ongoing medical care. His condition is seen as disabling; the social reactions to it are justified, and the barriers unavoidable. This position is known as the [[medical model of disability]].

Over the past 20 years, a competing view known as the [[social model of disability]] has come to the fore.  In this model, disability is seen more as a social construction than a medical reality. Disabled activists, such as [[Tom Shakespeare]] (2002), argue that although their impairments may cause them pain or discomfort, what really ''dis''-ables people as members of society is a socio-cultural system which does not recognise their right to genuine [[equality]].

Both the medical and social models agree, to a point, that facilities and opportunities should be made as accessible as possible to individuals who require adaptations. Dismantling physical barriers, or setting up adaptations such as wheelchair ramps, is known as "fostering [[accessibility]]".

A human rights based approach has been adopted by many organizations of and for people with disabilities. In 2000, for example, the United Nations Assembly decided to start working on a comprehensive convention for the rights of people with disabilities. Since 2002 the "UN Ad-Hoc meeting" gathers every six months to discuss the content of this UN convention. These meetings are open for Non-Government-Organisations and Disabled Peoples' Organisations.

An approach that has led to tangible improvements in the lives of people with disabilities in many countries has been the [[Independent Living]] Movement. The term "Independent Living" was taken from 1959 California legislation that enabled people disabled by polio to leave hospital wards and move back into the community with the help of cash benefits for the purchase of personal assistance with the activities of daily living. With its origins in the US civil rights and consumer movements of the late 1960s, the movement and its philosophy have since spread to other continents influencing disabled people's self-perception, their ways of organizing themselves and their countries' social policy.

The [[disability rights movement]] began in the [[1970s]] and is largely responsible for the shift toward [[Independent_Living|independent living]] and accessibility.

==The language and terminology of disability==

Many people use the term ''disability'' to replace the designation [[handicapped]]. While these two designations are often used interchangeably, proponents of the social model of disability use the latter term to describe the social and economic consequences of the former; i.e., an individual with a physical or intellectual disability is said to be "handicapped" by the bias of society towards ability (e.g., a building without an elevator handicaps a person who uses a wheelchair).  Similarly, in the United Kingdom, people within the [[disability rights movement]] commonly use the term "disabled" to denote someone who is "disabled by society's inability to accommodate all of its inhabitants."

The Person First Movement has added another layer to this discourse by asking that people with disabilities be identified first as individuals. "Person First Language" -- referring, for example, to a “woman who is blind,” rather than to "a blind woman" - is a form of [[political correctness]] designed to further the aims of the social model by removing attitudinal barriers.

Some people with disabilities support the Person First Movement, while others do not. People who are [[Deaf]] in particular may see themselves as members of a specific community, properly called the [[Deaf culture]], and so will reject efforts designed to distance them from the central fact of their identity. This is a view that is becoming increasingly prevalent within other disabled communities, that are becoming self-aware and self defining by seeing their impairments as a central part of their upbringing, education, personality &amp; Lifestyle.

The [[American Psychological Association]] [[APA_style|style guide]] devotes a large section to the discussion of individuals with disabilities, and states that in professional writing following this style, the person should come first, and nominal forms describing the disability should be used so that the disability is being described, but is not modifying the person. For instance, "people with autism," "man with schizophrenia," "girl with paraplegia." Similarly, a person's adaptive equipment should be described functionally as something that assists a person, not as something that limits a person. "A woman who uses a wheelchair" -- she is not "in" it or "confined" to it, and she leaves it at the very least for sleeping and bathing. "A communication aid user." "A girl who uses a ventilator." "A man who takes antipsychotic medications to optimize his daily functioning."

Many people with disabilities especially dislike "disabled person" or "the disabled," as this implies that one's overall "personness" is defective, while "person with a disability" acknowledges the disability without implying anything about the overall person. However, according to the "social model", as it is society that disables a person, the reality of being a "person with a disability" is not really possible because it is impossible for an individual to "have" a society, therefore the term "disabled person" does not signify the lack of one's own "person-ness" but points an accusing finger at society for excluding those with impairments.

See also [[List of disability-related terms with negative connotations]]

==Well-known people with disabilities==

Many people with disabilities have contributed to society. These include:

* American president [[Franklin Delano Roosevelt|Franklin Roosevelt]] (impaired movement as the result of [[polio]]),
* classical composer [[Ludwig von Beethoven]] (deaf in later years),
* [[King Richard III]] of [[England]] (childhood sickness allowed bones to malform, resulting in severe curvature of the back and extremely uneven legs)
* musician [[Stevie Wonder]] (blind)
* jazz pianist [[Marcus Roberts]] (blind)
* musician [[Ray Charles]] (blind)
* [[Def Leppard]] drummer [[Rick Allen (drummer)|Rick Allen]] (lost left arm in a car accident),
* comedian, actor, author, and monologist [[Greg Walloch]] ([[cerebral palsy]]),
* civil rights activist [[Helen Keller]] (deaf and blind), 
* [[Cole Porter]], musical theater composer (lost legs after riding accident)
* Classical actress [[Sarah Bernhardt]] (lost leg after a nasty fall)
* [[Stephen Hawking]] (who has [[Motor Neurone Disease]] and uses a wheelchair and [[speech synthesizer]]),
* [[Deng Pufang]] - has [[paraplegia]] 
* British rock and roll singer/songwriter [[Ian Dury]]
* Nicaraguan guitar player, singer and songwriter [[Tony Melendez]] (born without arms)
* [[Major League Baseball|Major league]] [[pitcher]] [[Jim Abbott]] (born without a right hand)
*Actress [[Marlee Matlin]] (deaf)
*[[Joseph Merrick]] ("the Elephant Man", severe [[neurofibromatosis]])
*[[Christopher Reeve]], actor famous for portraying [[Superman]] who became a [[Quadriplegia|quadriplegic]] after a horse-riding accident,
* for others see [[list of people with disabilities]].

== See also ==
{{wikiquote}}
*[[List of disabilities]]
*[[Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990]]
*[[Assistive technology]]
*[[Disability etiquette]]
*[[Disability Discrimination Act]]
*[[Disabled robotics]]
*[[Human variability]]
*[[Independent Living]]
*[[International Classification of Functioning, Disability and Health]]
*[[Learning disability]]
*[[Inclusive development]]
*[[Invisible disability]]

== References ==
* Tom Shakespeare, ''Genetic Politics: from Eugenics to Genome'', with Anne Kerr (New Clarion Press, 2002).

== External links ==
*[http://www.aapd.com/ American Association of People With Disabilities] 
*[http://www.wapd.org/ World Association of Persons with Disabilities]
*[http://www.disabilityhistory.org/ The Disability Social History Project]
*[http://www.independentliving.org/ Independent Living Institute]
*[http://www.un.org/esa/socdev/enable/rights/adhoccom.htm UN Enable]
*[http://www.nad.org/ National Association of the Deaf (United States)]
*[http://www.icdri.org/ The International Center for Disability Resources on the Internet]
*[http://www.disabledcommunity.org/ DisabledCommunity.Org (United States)]
*[http://www.disabilitysecrets.com/questions.html Social Security Disability FAQ (United States)]
*[http://www.disabled-world.com/ Disabled World Disability news and articles]
*[http://www.officecentralcardiff.co.uk/index.php?action=disability_act OfficeCentral: Disability In The Workplace]
*[http://www.dlf.org.uk/ Disabled Living Foundation (UK)] 
[[Category:Disability]]
*[http://www.asksource.info/res_library/disability.htm Source - International Information Support Centre [Category:Inclusive Development]
*[http://www.iddc.org.uk International Disability and Development Consortium]

[[de:Behinderung]]
[[es:Discapacidad]]
[[he:נכות]]
[[ja:&amp;#38556;&amp;#23475;&amp;#32773;]]
[[nl:Handicap]]
[[no:Funksjonshemning]]
[[th:คนพิการ]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>