<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061113201653|87600502" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="56285" pageid="56285" ns="0" title="Disability"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-11-13T20:57:51Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Mergeto|Disabilities|date=October 2006}} - definition seems different but really should be one article, or the diff  properly explained

:''This article is about the condition of being physically, emotionally or mentally impaired. For the poem by Wilfred Owen, see [[Disabled (poem)]]. For the United States government financial assistance program, see [[Social Security Disability Insurance]].''

[[Image:Handicapped.jpg|thumb|200px|A parking zone for the disabled.]]
'''Disability''' refers to the social effects of physical, emotional or mental impairment. This definition, known as the 'social model' of disability, makes a clear distinction between the impairment itself (such as a medical condition that makes a person unable to walk or unable to sit) and the disabling effects of society in relation to that impairment. As Frank Bowe put it in ''Handicapping America'' (1978), the real issue is the societal response to disability: if a community allows physical, architectural, transportation, and other barriers to remain in place, society is creating handicaps that oppress individuals with disabilities. If, on the other hand, a community removes those barriers, persons with disabilities can function at much higher levels.  In simple terms, it is not the inability to walk or inability to sit that prevents a person entering a building unaided but the existence of stairs or the lack of benches to lie down, that are inaccessible to a wheelchair-user or a person with [[sitting disability]]. In other words, 'disability' is [[socially constructed]]. The 'social model' is often contrasted with the 'medical model' which sees 'disability' as synonymous with 'impairment.'[http://www.la-articles.org.uk/dsi.pdf]

== Demographics of disability ==
Many books on disability and [[disability rights]] point out that 'disabled' is an identity that one is not necessarily born with, as disabilities are more often acquired than congenital. Some disability rights activists use an acronym TAB, [[Temporarily Able-Bodied]], as a reminder that many people will develop disabilities at some point in their lives, due to accidents, [[illness]] (physical, mental or emotional), or late-emerging effects of genetics. 

Current issues and debates surrounding 'disability' include social and political [[rights]], societal inclusivity and [[citizenship]]. In developed countries the debate has moved beyond a concern about the perceived cost of maintaining dependent people with a disability to the struggle to find effective ways of ensuring people with a disability can participate in and contribute to society in all spheres of life. 

An approach that has led to tangible improvements in the lives of people with disabilities in some regions has been the [[Independent Living]] Movement. The term "Independent Living" was taken from 1959 California legislation that enabled people who had acquired a disability due to polio to leave hospital wards and move back into the community with the help of cash benefits for the purchase of personal assistance with the activities of daily living. With its origins in the US [[civil rights movements|civil rights]] and consumer movements of the late 1960s, the movement and its philosophy have since spread to other continents influencing people's self-perception, their ways of organizing themselves and their countries' social policy.

The [[disability rights movement]], led by end-users rather than families and other carers, began in the [[1970s]].  This self-advocacy is largely responsible for the shift toward [[Independent Living|independent living]] and accessibility.

==Language and terminology==
[[Image:Handicapped.svg|thumb|150px|Handicapped Accessible sign.]]

The [[American Psychological Association]] [[APA style|style guide]] devotes a large section to the discussion of individuals with disabilities, and states that in professional writing following this style, the person should come first, and nominal forms describing the disability should be used so that the disability is being described, but is not modifying the person. For instance: people with Down syndrome, a man with schizophrenia, and a girl with paraplegia. (This applies only to [[English language|English]] and possibly other [[preposition]]al languages, not [[postposition]]al languages.) It also states that a person's adaptive equipment should be described functionally as something that assists a person, not as something that limits a person (e.g., "A woman who uses a wheelchair" rather than "in" it or "confined" to it - she leaves it at the very least for sleeping and bathing). 

==Famous people with disabilities==

Many people with disabilities have contributed to society. These include:

* Self Advocate Singer-Composer [[Ian Dury]] (UK, 1942-2000)man

* USA president [[Franklin Delano Roosevelt|Franklin Roosevelt]] (impaired movement as the result of [[Guillain-Barré syndrome]] or [[polio]]),
* classical composer [[Ludwig van Beethoven]] (deaf in later years),
* [[King Richard III]] of [[England]] (childhood sickness allowed bones to malform, resulting in severe curvature of the back and extremely uneven legs)
* musician [[Stevie Wonder]] (USA, blind)
* jazz pianist [[Marcus Roberts]] (blind)
* [[Herbert Everest]] (USA, co-invented the wheelchair with [[Peter Jennings (Inventor)|Peter Jennings]])
* musician [[Ray Charles]] (USA, blind)
* [[Def Leppard]] drummer [[Rick Allen (drummer)|Rick Allen]] (lost left arm in a car accident),
* comedian, actor, author, and monologist [[Greg Walloch]] ([[cerebral palsy]]),
* civil rights activist [[Helen Keller]] (deaf and blind), 
* Chilean civil rights activist persons with disabilities  [[Carlos Kaiser]] (was born with incomplete upper and lower limbs)
* [[Cole Porter]], musical theater composer (lost legs after riding accident)
* Classical actress [[Sarah Bernhardt]] (lost leg after a nasty fall)
* [[Stephen Hawking]] (UK, has [[motor neurone disease]] and uses a wheelchair and [[speech synthesizer]])
* [[Deng Pufang]] - (China, has [[paraplegia]]) 
* Nicaraguan guitar player, singer and songwriter [[Tony Melendez]] (born without arms)
* [[Major League Baseball|Major league]] [[pitcher]] [[Jim Abbott]] (USA, born without a right hand)
* Actress [[Marlee Matlin]] (deaf)
* [[NFL]] [[placekicker]] [[Tom Dempsey]] (USA, born with only half a right foot)
*[[Joseph Merrick]] ("the Elephant Man", severe [[neurofibromatosis]])
*[[Christopher Reeve]], USA actor famous for portraying [[Superman]] who became a [[Quadriplegia|quadriplegic]] after a horse-riding accident,
* for others see [[list of people with disabilities]].
*Michael J. Fox (Parkinson's disease)

== See also ==
{{wikiquote}}
*[[List of disabilities]]


*[[Adaptive recreation]]
*[[Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990]]
*[[Assistive technology]]
*[[Bathing]]
*[[Developmental disability]]
*[[Disability etiquette]]
*[[Disability Discrimination Act]]
*[[Disabled robotics]]
*[[Disability studies]]
*[[Ergonomy]]
*[[Easter Seals]]
*[[Friendship Industries]]
*[[Human variability]]
*[[Ian Dury]]
*[[Inclusive development]]
*[[Independent Living]]
*[[International Classification of Functioning, Disability and Health]]
*[[Invisible disability]]
*[[Learning disability]]
*[[Orthopedics]]
*[[Post Secondary Transition For High School Students with Disabilities]]
*[[Passing (disability)|Passing]]

== References ==
* Frank Bowe, ''Handicapping America:Barriers to disabled people'', Harper &amp; Row, 1978 ISBN 0-06-010422-8
* ''Encyclopedia of disability'', general ed. Gary L. Albrecht, Thousand Oaks, Calif. [u.a.] : SAGE Publ., 2005
* David Johnstone, ''An Introduction to Disability Studies'', 2001, 2nd edition, ISBN 1-85346-726-X
* Michael Oliver, ''The Politics of Disablement'', St. Martin's Press 1997, ISBN 0-333-43293-2
* Tom Shakespeare, ''Genetic Politics: from Eugenics to Genome'', with Anne Kerr , New Clarion Press, 1999, ISBN 1-873797-25-7
* Kaushik, R.,1999, " Access Denied: Can we overcome disabling attitudes ," Museum International (UNESCO) , Vol. 51, No. 3, p. 48-52.

== External links ==
* [http://www.kidsonwheels.us Kids on Wheels magazine] - for young wheelchair users and their families
* [http://www.newmobility.com New Mobility magazine] - a lifestyle magazine for active adult wheelchair users
* [http://www.spinalnetwork.net Spinal Network: The Total Wheelchair Resource Book] - wheelchair bible
* [http://atwiki.assistivetech.net AT Wiki on Assistivetech.net]
* [http://www.mobilityrerc.gatech.edu Rehabilitation Engineering Research Center on Wheeled Mobility]
* [http://www.workrerc.org Rehabilitation Engineering Research Center on Workplace Accommodations]
*[http://www.scope.org.uk Scope - About cerebral palsy. For disabled people achieving equality. (UK)]
*[http://www.aapd.com/ American Association of People With Disabilities]
*[http://assistech.com/ Assistive Technologies for Special Needs] 
*[http://www.disabilityhistory.org/ The Disability Social History Project]
*[http://www.disabled-help.org/ Philips Disabled Help]
*[http://www.independentliving.org/ Independent Living Institute]
*[http://www.un.org/esa/socdev/enable/rights/adhoccom.htm UN Enable]
*[http://www.nad.org/ National Association of the Deaf (United States)]
*[http://www.disabledcommunity.org/ DisabledCommunity.Org (United States)]
*[http://www.disabled-world.com/ Disabled World Disability news and articles]
*[http://www.socialservicessluts.com/ Examples of Disabled Sexuality &amp; the Mainstream]
*[http://www.ssdrc.com/ Social Security, Medicare, and Disability news and articles]
*[http://www.humanics-es.com/recc-disabled.htm Ergonomics and design resources for people with disabilities]
*[http://www.asksource.info/res_library/disability.htm Source - International Information Support Centre]
*[http://www.iddc.org.uk International Disability and Development Consortium]
*[http://disability.wikia.com Wiki about disability] (To be completed)

&lt;!-- [[Category:Inclusive Development]] --&gt;

[[Category:Disability|*]]
[[Category:Educational psychology]]

&lt;!--interwiki--&gt;
[[ca:Discapacitat]]
[[de:Behinderung]]
[[es:Discapacidad]]
[[fr:Handicap]]
[[io:Handikapo]]
[[it:Handicap (medicina)]]
[[he:נכות]]
[[nl:Handicap]]
[[ja:障害者]]
[[no:Funksjonshemning]]
[[pl:Niepełnosprawność]]
[[pt:Deficiente]]
[[ru:Инвалидность]]
[[simple:Disability]]
[[sv:Funktionshinder]]
[[th:คนพิการ]]
[[tr:Engelli]]
[[uk:Інвалідність]]
[[zh:残疾]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>