<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20030830003505|1366865" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="56285" pageid="56285" ns="0" title="Disability"><revisions><rev timestamp="2003-08-30T12:23:34Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[ja:&amp;#38556;&amp;#23475;&amp;#32773;]]

A person is said to have a '''disability''' if they find it difficult or impossible to perform one or more activities of everyday living. 

Until recently, little distinction was made between the physical or mental condition of a person and the difficulties they faced. In the past 20 years, the '''social model of disability''' has been developed, which alters this perception. It distinguishes between an impairment (some ability is objectively less than average) and a deviation from the average that by itself is not better or worse, but that is a problem due to the attitude of society or the fact that standard facilities are based on the average, and that there is a the lack of tools. 

For example, as recently as the [[1960s]], [[left-handed]]ness was seen as an abnormality. In schools in the Western world, left-handed children were forced to write with their right hand and punished if they did not comply. By the 1980s, left-handedness was accepted as simply a difference; a physical characteristic. Yet if tools such as [[scissors]] and [[corkscrew]]s are only available in their right-handed forms, a left-handed person finds themselves disabled: they are unable to perform certain tasks and must be assisted by another person.

Thus, in the social model of disability, the disability is caused by society and the physical environment. Someone who is unable to [[walk]] and needs a [[wheelchair]] has an impairment; however, the social exclusion they may experience (lack of accessible [[transport]], no adapted public [[toilet]]s, [[building]]s which are innaccessible) is caused by their environment, not their physical condition. 

[[Discrimination]] of those disabled is sometimes termed '''able[[ism]]'''.

The term '''handicapped''', in its origin, meant ''hand in cap'', and had its origins in sport and gambling.

Some disabled persons apply the term '''tab''' for the "nondisabled", meaning "temporarily able-bodied".

Various '''attributive''' forms, such as "the disabled", "the blind", "the deaf", etc. -- rather than "disabled persons", "blind persons", "deaf persons", etc. -- are considered objectionable by many persons, since the former labeling seems to characterize a person by a single '''attribute'''.

Many of the most famous or creative persons in history have been disabled persons [http://members.fortunecity.com/jonhays/christinapage.htm].

== See also ==
* [[List of disabilities]]
* [[Disability etiquette]]
* [[Architectonic barrier]]
* [[Disability Discrimination Act]]
* [[Learning disability]]

==Further reading==
* "U. S. Counts One in 12 Children as Disabled", ''Washington Post'', July 5, 2002</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>