<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20181121082713|869931303" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="56285" pageid="56285" ns="0" title="Disability"><revisions><rev timestamp="2018-11-21T08:29:13Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{About||the poem by Wilfred Owen|Disabled (poem)|the Middle Age restrictions|Disabilities (Jewish)}}
{{Redirect|Impaired||Impairment (disambiguation){{!}}Impairment}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=August 2012}}
[[File:Handicapped Accessible sign.svg|alt=white line figure of a person seated over the axis of a wheel, blue background|thumb|[[International Symbol of Access]]]]
{{Disability}}

A '''disability''' is an impairment that may be [[Cognitive disability|cognitive]], [[Developmental disability|developmental]], [[Intellectual disability|intellectual]], [[mental disorder#Disability|mental]], [[physical disability|physical]], [[Sense|sensory]], or some combination of these. It substantially affects a person's life activities and may be present from birth or occur during a person's lifetime.&lt;ref name="Journal of Applied Physiology"&gt;[http://jap.physiology.org/content/95/5/2152 Journal of Applied Physiology]&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Quote|Disabilities is an umbrella term, covering impairments, activity limitations, and participation restrictions. An impairment is a problem in body function or structure; an activity limitation is a difficulty encountered by an individual in executing a task or action; while a participation restriction is a problem experienced by an individual in involvement in life situations. Disability is thus not just a health problem. It is a complex phenomenon, reflecting the interaction between features of a person’s body and features of the society in which he or she lives.|author=[[World Health Organization]]|source=Disabilities&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Disabilities |url=http://www.who.int/topics/disabilities/en/ |publisher=World Health Organization |accessdate=2016-10-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
Disability is a contested concept, with different meanings in different communities.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Claiming Disability: Knowledge and Identity|last = Linton|first = Simi|publisher = New York University Press|year = 1998|isbn = |location = New York|pages = }}&lt;/ref&gt; It may be used to refer to physical or mental attributes that some institutions, particularly medicine, view as needing to be fixed (the [[Medical model of disability|medical model]]). It may refer to limitations imposed on people by the constraints of an [[ableism|ableist]] society (the [[Social model of disability|social model]]). Or the term may serve to refer to the identity of disabled people. [[Physiological functional capacity]] (PFC) is a related term that describes an individual's performance level. It gauges one's ability to perform the physical tasks of daily life and the ease with which these tasks are performed. PFC declines with advancing [[aging|age]] to result in [[Frailty syndrome|frailty]], cognitive disorders or physical disorders, all of which may lead to labeling individuals as disabled.&lt;ref name="Journal of Applied Physiology"/&gt;&lt;ref name="pmid28400984"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Mugueta-Aguinaga I, Garcia-Zapirain B | title = Is Technology Present in Frailty? Technology a Back-up Tool for Dealing with Frailty in the Elderly: A Systematic Review | journal = [[Aging and Disease]] | volume = 8 | issue = 2 | pages = 176–195 | year = 2017 | pmid = 28400984 | pmc = 5362177 | doi = 10.14336/AD.2016.0901 | url = }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The discussion over disability's definition arose out of [[Disability rights movement|disability activism]] in the United States and the United Kingdom in the 1970s, which challenged how the medical concept of disability dominated perception and discourse about disabilities. Debates about proper terminology and their implied politics continue in disability communities and the academic field of [[disability studies]]. In some countries, the law requires that disabilities are documented by a healthcare provider in order to assess qualifications for [[disability benefits]].{{citation needed|date=June 2018}}

== History ==
{{Refimprove section|date=February 2016}}
Contemporary understandings of disability derive from concepts that arose during the West's scientific [[Age of Enlightenment|Enlightenment]]; prior to the Enlightenment, physical differences were viewed through a different lens.

During the [[Middle Ages]], madness and other conditions were thought to be caused by demons. They were also thought to be part of the natural order, especially during and in the fallout of the [[Black Death|Plague]], which wrought impairments throughout the general population.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;Braddock, David, and Susan Parrish, "An Institutional History of Disability," in ''Handbook of Disability Studies'', ed. Gary Albrecht, Katherine Seelman, and Michael Bury (Thousand Oaks, Calif.: Sage, 2001).&lt;/ref&gt; In the [[early modern period]] there was a shift to seeking biological causes for physical and mental differences, as well as heightened interest in demarcating categories: for example, Ambroise Pare, in the sixteenth century, wrote of "monsters", "prodigies", and "the maimed".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book
| title = A History of Disability
| last = Stiker
| first = Henri
| publisher = University of Michigan Press
| year = 2000
| isbn = 
| location = Ann Arbor, Michigan
| page = 91
}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[European Enlightenment]]'s emphases on knowledge derived from reason and on the value of natural science to human progress helped spawn the birth of institutions and associated knowledge systems that observed and categorized human beings; among these, the ones significant to the development of today's concepts of disability were [[Psychiatric hospital|asylums]], [[clinic]]s, and, [[prison]]s.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

Contemporary concepts of disability are rooted in eighteenth- and nineteenth-century developments. Foremost among these was the development of clinical medical discourse, which made the human body visible as a thing to be manipulated, studied, and transformed. These worked in tandem with scientific discourses that sought to classify and categorize and, in so doing, became methods of normalization.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = The History of Sexuality, vol. 1|last = Foucault|first = Michel|publisher = Vintage|year = 1980|isbn = |location = New York|pages = }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The concept of the "norm" developed in this time period, and is signaled in the work of the [[Belgian]] [[statistician]], [[Sociology|sociologist]], [[mathematician]], and [[astronomer]] [[Adolphe Quetelet]], who wrote in the 1830s of l'homme moyen – the average man. Quetelet postulated that one could take the sum of all people's attributes in a given population (such as their height or weight) and find their average, and that this figure should serve as a norm toward which all should aspire.

This idea of a statistical norm threads through the rapid take up of statistics gathering by Britain, United States, and the Western European states during this time period, and it is tied to the rise of [[eugenics]]. Disability, as well as other concepts including: abnormal, non-normal, and normalcy came from this.&lt;ref&gt;Davis, Lennard. "Constructing Normalcy." In his ''Enforcing Normalcy: Disability, Deafness, and the Body'' (New York: Verso, 1995), pp. 23–49.&lt;/ref&gt; The circulation of these concepts is evident in the popularity of the [[freak show]], where showmen profited from exhibiting people who deviated from those norms.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Freak Show: Presenting Human Oddities for Amusement and Profit|last = Bogdan|first = Robert|publisher = |year = 1998|isbn = |location = |pages = }}&lt;/ref&gt;

With the rise of eugenics in the latter part of the nineteenth century, such deviations were viewed as dangerous to the health of entire populations. With disability viewed as part of a person's biological make-up and thus their genetic inheritance, scientists turned their attention to notions of weeding such "deviations" out of the gene pool. Various metrics for assessing a person's genetic fitness, which were then used to deport, sterilize, or institutionalize those deemed unfit. At the end of the Second World War, with the example of Nazi eugenics, eugenics faded from public discourse, and increasingly disability cohered into a set of attributes that medicine could attend to – whether through augmentation, rehabilitation, or treatment. In both contemporary and modern history, disability was often viewed as a by-product of [[incest]] between [[first-degree relatives]] or [[second-degree relatives]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author = Barlow, Kathleen | year = 2006 | title = Inbreeding, Incest, and the Incest Taboo: The State of Knowledge at the Turn of the Century | doi = 10.1525/aa.2006.108.2.447| journal = American Anthropologist | volume = 108 | issue = 2| pages = 447–448 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the early 1970s, disability activists began to challenge how society treated disabled people and the medical approach to disability. Due to this work, physical [[Accessibility|barriers to access]] were identified. These conditions functionally disabled them, and what is now known as the [[social model of disability]] emerged. Coined by Mike Oliver in 1983, this phrase distinguishes between the [[medical model of disability]] – under which an impairment needs to be fixed – and the social model of disability – under which the society that limits a person needs to be fixed.&lt;ref&gt;Shakespeare, Tom. "The Social Model of Disability." In ''The Disability Studies Reader'', ed. Lennard Davis (New York: Routledge, 2006, 2d ed.), 197–204.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Sociology ==
{{Main|Disability studies}}
[[File:Museum of disABILITY History Buffalo NY.jpg|alt=crutches, braces, photographs, and other exhibits|thumb|Museum of disABILITY History, [[Buffalo, New York]].]]

=== Terminology ===
Different terms have been used for disabled people in different times and places.  ''Disability'' or ''impairment'' are commonly used, as are more specific terms, such as ''blind'' (to describe having no vision at all) or ''visually impaired'' (to describe having limited vision).

''Handicap'' has been disparaged as a result of [[List of common false etymologies#Other|false folk etymology]] that says it is a reference to begging.  It is actually derived from an old game, [[Hand-i'-cap]], in which two players trade possessions and a third, neutral person judges the difference of value between the possessions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://oxforddictionaries.com/definition/english/handicap|title=Definition of handicap in Oxford Dictionaries (British &amp; World English)|accessdate=April 12, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The concept of a neutral person evening up the odds was extended to [[Handicap (horse racing)|handicap racing]] in the mid-18th century.  In handicap racing, horses carry different weights based on the umpire's estimation of what would make them run equally.  The use of the term to describe a person with a disability—by extension from handicap racing, a person carrying a heavier burden than normal—appeared in the early 20th century.&lt;ref name=ety&gt;{{cite web|url=http://etymonline.com/?term=handicap|title=Online Etymology Dictionary|work=[[Online Etymology Dictionary]]|accessdate=April 12, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== People-first language ===
{{Main|People-first language}}
People-first language is one way to talk about disability that some people prefer. Using people-first language is said to put the person before the disability, so those individuals who prefer people-first language, prefer to be called, "a person with a disability". Some people prefer person-first phrasing, while others prefer identity-first phrasing.

For people-first guidelines, check out, "Cerebral Palsy: A Guide for Care" at the [[University of Delaware]]:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Cerebral Palsy: a Guide for Care |url=http://gait.aidi.udel.edu/res695/homepage/pd_ortho/clinics/c_palsy/cpweb.htm |publisher=The Nemours Foundation |accessdate=July 29, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;"The [[American Psychological Association]] [[APA style|style guide]] states that, when identifying a person with a disability, the person's name or pronoun should come first, and descriptions of the disability should be used so that the disability is identified, but is not modifying the person. Acceptable examples included "a woman with [[Down syndrome]]" or "a man who has [[schizophrenia]]". It also states that a person's adaptive equipment should be described functionally as something that assists a person, not as something that limits a person, for example, "a woman who uses a wheelchair" rather than "a woman in/confined to a wheelchair".&lt;/blockquote&gt;A similar kind of "people-first" terminology is also used in the UK, but more often in the form "people with impairments" (such as "people with visual impairments"). However, in the UK, the term "disabled people" is generally preferred to "people with disabilities". It is argued under the [[Social model of disability|social model]] that while someone's impairment (for example, having a spinal cord injury) is an individual property, "disability" is something created by external societal factors such as a lack of accessibility.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gcil.org.uk/FileAccess.aspx?id=59 Glasgow Centre for Inclusive Living: The Social Model of Disability] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090103084307/http://www.gcil.org.uk/FileAccess.aspx?id=59 |date=January 3, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; This distinction between the individual property of impairment and the social property of disability is central to the [[Social model of disability|social model]]. The term "disabled people" as a political construction is also widely used by international organisations of disabled people, such as [[Disabled Peoples' International]] (DPI).

The use of “people-first” terminology has given rise to the use of the acronym PWD to refer to person(s) (or people) with disabilities (or disability).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Meyers |first=Stephen |year=2014 |chapter=Chapter 23. The past dividing the present |title=Crises, Conflict and Disability: Ensuring Equality |page=195 |editor1-first=David |editor1-last=Mitchell |editor2-first=Valerie |editor2-last=Karr |publisher=[[Routledge]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.manilatimes.net/groups-and-individuals-honored-at-pwd-day/97928/ |title=Groups and individuals honored at PWD Day |date=May 20, 2014 |newspaper=[[The Manila Times]] |accessdate=July 15, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://devtracker.dfid.gov.uk/projects/GB-1-114000/ |title=Recognising &amp; Implementing Housing Rights CSCF449 |author=[[Department for International Development]] |accessdate=July 15, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; However other individuals and groups prefer identity-first language to emphasize how a disability can impact peoples identities. Which style of language used varies between different countries, groups and individuals.

=== Aging ===
To a certain degree, physical impairments and changing mental states are almost ubiquitously experienced by people as they age. Aging populations are often stigmatized for having a high prevalence of disability. [[Kathleen Woodward]], writing in ''Key Words for Disability Studies'', explains the phenomenon as follows:
{{Quote|Aging is invoked rhetorically—at times ominously—as a pressing reason why disability should be of crucial interest to all of us (we are all getting older, we will all be disabled eventually), thereby inadvertently reinforcing the damaging and dominant stereotype of aging as solely an experience of decline and deterioration. But little attention has been given to the imbrication of aging and disability.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Woodward|first1=Kathleen|editor1-last=Adams|editor1-first=Rachel|editor2-last=Reiss|editor2-first=Benjamin|editor3-last=Serlin|editor3-first=David|title=Key Words for Disability Studies|date=2015|publisher=New York University Press|location=Washington Square New York NY 10003|isbn=978-1-4798-4115-8|pages=33–34|chapter=9}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

== The workforce ==
As stated above, studies have illustrated a correlation between disabilities and poverty. Notably, jobs offered to disabled people are scarce. ''For global demographic data on unemployment rates for the disabled, see [[Disability and poverty]].'' However, there are current programs in place that aid intellectually disabled (ID) people to acquire skills they need in the workforce.&lt;ref name=":0x"&gt;Blick, R. N., Litz, K. S., Thornhill, M. G., &amp; Goreczny, A. J. (2016). Do inclusive work environments matter? Effects of community-integrated employment on quality of life for individuals with intellectual disabilities. Research In Developmental Disabilities, 53358-366. doi:10.1016/j.ridd.2016.02.015&lt;/ref&gt;  Such programs include sheltered workshops and adult day care programs. Sheltered programs consist of daytime activities such as, gardening, manufacturing, and assembling. These activities facilitate routine-oriented tasks that in turn allow intellectually disabled people to gain experience before entering the workforce. Similarly, adult day care programs also include day time activities. However, these activities are based in an educational environment where intellectually disabled are able to engage in educational, physical, and communication based tasks. This educational based environment helps facilitate communication, memory, and general living skills. In addition, adult day care programs arrange opportunities for their students to engage in community activities. Such opportunities are arranged by scheduling field trips to public places (e.g. Disneyland, Zoo, and Movie Theater). Despite, both programs providing essential skills for intellectually disabled prior to entering the workforce researchers have found that intellectually disabled people prefer to be involved with community-integrated employment.&lt;ref name=":0x" /&gt; Community-integrated employment are job opportunities offered to intellectually disabled people at minimum wage or a higher rate depending on the position. Community-integrated employment comes in a variety of occupations ranging from customer service, clerical, janitorial, hospitality and manufacturing positions. Within their daily tasks community-integrated employees work alongside employees who do not have disabilities, but who are able to assist them with training. All three options allow intellectually disabled people to develop and exercise social skills that are vital to everyday life. However, it is not guaranteed that community-integrated employees receive the same treatment as employees that do not have ID. According to Lindstrom, Hirano, McCarthy, and Alverson, community-integrated employees are less likely to receive  raises. In addition, studies conducted in 2013 illustrated only 26% of employees with ID retained full-time status.&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;L. Lindstrom, K.A. Hirano, C. McCarthy, C.Y. Alverson
“Just having a job”: Career advancement for low-wage workers with intellectual and developmental disabilities
Career Development and Transition for Exceptional Individuals, 37 (1) (2014), pp. 1–10&lt;/ref&gt;

Furthermore, many with disabilities, intellectual and (or) psychical, finding a stable workforce poses many challenges. According to a study conducted by JARID (Journal of Applied Research and Intellectual Disability, indicates that although finding a job may be difficult for an intellectually disabled individual, stabilizing a job is even harder.&lt;ref name=":2"&gt;Banks, P., Jahoda, A., Dagnan, D., Kemp, J., &amp; Williams, V. (2010). Supported Employment for People with Intellectual Disability: The Effects of Job Breakdown on Psychological Well-Being. Journal of Applied Research in Intellectual Disabilities, 23(4), 344-354. doi:10.1111/j.1468-3148.2009.00541.x
&lt;/ref&gt; This is largely due to two main factors: production skills and effective social skills. This idea is supported by Chadsey-Rusch, who claims that securing employment for the intellectually disabled, requires adequate production skills and effective social skills.&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt; However, other underlying factors for job loss include, structural factors and the integration between worker and workplace. As stated by Kilsby, limited structural factors can effect a multitude of factors in a job. Factors such as a restricted number of hours an intellectually disabled person is allowed to work. This in return, according to Fabian, Wistow, and Schneider leads to a lack of opportunity to develop relationships with coworkers and a chance to better integrate within the workplace. Nevertheless, those who are unable to stabilize a job often are left discouraged. According to the same study conducted by JARED, many who had participated, found that they had made smaller incomes when compared to their co-workers, had an excess of time throughout their days, because they did not have work. They,also, had feelings of hopelessness and failure. According to the NOD ( National Organization On Disability), not only do the (ID) face constant discouragement, but many live below the poverty line, because they are unable to find or stabilize employment and (or) because of employee restricting factors placed on ID workers.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt; This then causes the (ID) the incapacity to provide for themselves basic necessities one needs. Items such as, food, medical care, transportation, and housing.

=== Poverty ===
[[File:Pieter Bruegel d. Ä. 024.jpg|alt=painting of a group of people, some missing feet, hunched over crutches as a beggar walks past|thumb|upright|''[[The Beggars|The Cripples]]'', [[Pieter Bruegel the Elder|Pieter Bruegel]], 1568]]
There is a global correlation between [[disability and poverty]], produced by a variety of factors. Disability and poverty may form a vicious circle, in which physical barriers and stigma of disability make it more difficult to get income, which in turn diminishes access to health care and other necessities for a healthy life.{{sfn|Yeo|2005}} The [[World report on disability]] indicates that half of all disabled people cannot afford health care, compared to a third of abled people.&lt;ref&gt;World Health Organization, ''World report on disability'', 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; In countries without public services for adults with disabilities, their families may be impoverished.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://centrodiba.org|title=Centro DÍBÁ|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Disasters ===
{{Main|Disability and disasters}}
There is limited research knowledge, but many anecdotal reports, on what happens when disasters impact disabled people.&lt;ref name="cdra.colostate"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://cdra.colostate.edu/Data/Sites/1/cdra-research/peek-stough2010.pdf |title=Children With Disabilities in the Context of Disaster: A Social Vulnerability Perspective |publisher=Child Development |date= |accessdate=January 31, 2013 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130512111637/http://cdra.colostate.edu/Data/Sites/1/cdra-research/peek-stough2010.pdf |archivedate=May 12, 2013 |df=mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.apa.org/pubs/journals/releases/rep-55-3-211.pdf |title=Disaster Case Management and Individuals With Disabilities |date= |accessdate=January 31, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Individuals with disabilities are greatly affected by disasters.&lt;ref name="cdra.colostate" /&gt;{{sfn|Stough|2009}} Those with physical disabilities can be at risk when evacuating if assistance is not available. Individuals with [[cognitive impairments]] may struggle with understanding instructions that must be followed in the event a disaster occurs.{{sfn|Stough|2009}}{{sfn|Ducy|Stough|Clark|2012}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://jfi.sagepub.com/content/32/10/1325.full.pdf+html |title=Exploring the support role of special education teachers after Hurricane Ike: Children with significant disabilities |date=July 29, 2011 |accessdate=February 1, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; All of these factors can increase the degree of variation of risk in disaster situations with disabled individuals.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ncd.gov/publications/2009/Aug122009 |title=Effective Emergency Management: Making Improvements for Communities and People with Disabilities: National Council on Disability |publisher=Ncd.gov |date= |accessdate=January 29, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Research studies have consistently found discrimination against individuals with disabilities during all phases of a disaster cycle.&lt;ref name="cdra.colostate" /&gt; The most common limitation is that people cannot physically access buildings or [[transportation]], as well as access disaster-related services.&lt;ref name="cdra.colostate" /&gt; The exclusion of these individuals is caused in part by the lack of disability-related training provided to emergency planners and [[disaster relief]] personnel.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.un.org/disabilities/default.asp?id=1546 |title=UN Enable&amp;nbsp;– Disability, natural disasters and emergency situations |publisher=Un.org |date=May 31, 2011 |accessdate=January 29, 2013 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130202131058/http://www.un.org/disabilities/default.asp?id=1546 |archivedate=February 2, 2013 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Theory ==
The [[International Classification of Functioning, Disability and Health]] (ICF), produced by the [[World Health Organization]], distinguishes between body functions (physiological or psychological, such as vision) and body structures (anatomical parts, such as the eye and related structures). Impairment in bodily structure or function is defined as involving an anomaly, defect, loss or other significant deviation from certain generally accepted population standards, which may fluctuate over time. Activity is defined as the execution of a task or action. The ICF lists 9 broad domains of functioning which can be affected:
* Learning and applying knowledge
* General tasks and demands
* Communication
* Basic physical mobility, Domestic life, and Self-care (for example, [[activities of daily living]])
* Interpersonal interactions and relationships
* Community, social and civic life, including [[employment]]
* Other major life areas
In concert with disability scholars, the introduction to the ICF states that a variety of conceptual models have been proposed to understand and explain disability and functioning, which it seeks to integrate. These models include the following:

=== Medical model ===
{{Main|Medical model of disability}}

The [[medical model]] views disability as a problem of the person, directly caused by disease, trauma, or other health conditions which therefore requires sustained medical care in the form of individual treatment by professionals. In the medical model, management of the disability is aimed at a "cure", or the individual's adjustment and behavioral change that would lead to an "almost-cure" or effective cure. In the medical model, medical care is viewed as the main issue, and at the political level, the principal response is that of modifying or reforming [[healthcare]] policy.{{sfn|Nikora|Karapu|Hickey|Te Awekotuku|2004|p=5}}{{sfn|Donovan|2012|p=12}}

=== Social model ===
{{Main|Social model of disability}}
The social model of disability sees "disability" as a socially created problem and a matter of the full [[Inclusion (disability rights)|integration of individuals into society]]. In this model, disability is not an attribute of an individual, but rather a complex collection of conditions, created by the social environment. The management of the problem requires [[social activist|social action]] and it is the collective responsibility of society to create a society in which limitations for disabled people are minimal. Disability is both [[cultural]] and [[ideological]] in creation. According to the social model, equal access for someone with an impairment/disability is a human rights concern.{{sfn|Nikora|Karapu|Hickey|Te Awekotuku|2004|p=6–7}}{{sfn|Donovan|2012|p=12}} The social model of disability has come under criticism. While recognizing the importance played by the social model in stressing the responsibility of society, scholars, including [[Tom Shakespeare]], point out the limits of the model, and urge the need for a new model that will overcome the "medical vs. social" dichotomy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author = Shakespeare T | title = The social model of disability: An outdated ideology? | journal = Research in Social Science and Disability | volume = 2 | pages = 9–28 | year = 2001 | doi = 10.1016/S1479-3547(01)80018-X }}&lt;/ref&gt; The limitations of this model mean that often the vital services and information persons with disabilities face are simply not available, often due to limited economic returns in supporting them.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Parker|first1=Christopher J.|last2=May|first2=Andrew|last3=Mitchell|first3=Val|last4=Burrows|first4=Alison|title=Capturing Volunteered Information for Inclusive Service Design: Potential Benefits and Challenges|journal=The Design Journal|date=2015|volume=16|issue=11|pages=197–218|doi=10.2752/175630613X13584367984947|url=https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.2752/175630613X13584367984947}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some say [[medical humanities]] is a fruitful field where the gap between the medical and the social model of disability might be bridged.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author = Garden R | title = Disability and narrative: new directions for medicine and the medical humanities | journal = Med. Humanit. | volume = 36 | issue = 2 | pages = 70–4 | year = 2010 | pmid = 21393285 | doi = 10.1136/jmh.2010.004143 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Social construction ====
The social construction of disability is the idea that disability is constructed by social expectations and institutions rather than biological differences. Highlighting the ways society and institutions construct disability is one of the main focuses of this idea.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|edition = Winter 2014|title = Naturalistic Approaches to Social Construction|url = http://plato.stanford.edu/archives/win2014/entries/social-construction-naturalistic/|date = 2014-01-01|first = Ron|last = Mallon|editor-first = Edward N.|editor-last = Zalta}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the same way that race and gender are not biologically fixed, neither is disability.

Around the early 1970s, sociologists, notably Eliot Friedson, began to argue that [[labeling theory]] and [[social deviance]] could be applied to disability studies. This led to the creation of the [[social construction of disability]] theory. The social construction of disability is the idea that disability is constructed as the social response to a deviance from the norm. The medical industry is the creator of the ill and disabled social role. Medical professionals and institutions, who wield expertise over health, have the ability to define health and physical and mental norms. When an individual has a feature that creates an impairment, restriction, or limitation from reaching the social definition of health, the individual is labeled as disabled. Under this idea, disability is not defined by the physical features of the body but by a deviance from the social convention of health.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Profession of Medicine: A Study of the Sociology of Applied Knowledge |last=Freidson |first=Eliot |publisher=Harper and Row Inc |year=1970 |isbn=0-06-042205-X |location= |pages=205–210}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Social construction of disability would argue that the [[medical model of disability]]'s view that a disability is an impairment, restriction, or limitation is wrong. Instead what is seen as a disability is just a difference in the individual from what is considered "normal" in society.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Encyclopedia of American Disability History Vol. 2 |last=Burch |first=Susan |publisher=Facts on File |year=2009 |isbn=978-0-8160-7030-5 |location= |pages=543–544}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Other models ===
* The '''spectrum model''' refers to the range of audibility, sensibility, and visibility under which people function. The model asserts that disability does not necessarily mean reduced spectrum of operations. Rather, disability is often defined according to thresholds set on a continuum of disability.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Bites August 2011 - International organisations report on disability |url=http://www.dpa.org.nz/news/bites-newsletter/55-bites-august-2011 |publisher=Disabled Persons Assembly New Zealand |accessdate=March 6, 2013 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130205123349/http://dpa.org.nz/news/bites-newsletter/55-bites-august-2011 |archivedate=February 5, 2013 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The '''moral model''' refers to the attitude that people are ''morally responsible'' for their own disability.&lt;ref name="Disability Model"&gt;{{cite web |last=Kaplan |first=Deborah |title=Disability Model |url=http://www.peoplewho.org/debate/kaplan.htm |publisher=World Institute on Disability |accessdate=October 30, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; For example, disability may be seen as a result of bad actions of parents if [[congenital]], or as a result of practicing witchcraft if not.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Lum|first=Doman|title=Culturally Competent Practice: A Framework for Understanding Diverse Groups and Justice Issues|year=2010|publisher=Cengage Learning|isbn=9780840034434|page=449}}&lt;/ref&gt; Echoes of this can be seen in the doctrine of [[karma]] in Indian religions. It also includes notions that a disability gives a person "special abilities to perceive, reflect, transcend, be spiritual".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Olkin|first=Rhoda|title=What Psychotherapists Should Know About Disability|year=2012|publisher=Guilford Press|isbn=9781462506132|page=26}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The '''expert/professional model''' has provided a traditional response to disability issues and can be seen as an offshoot of the medical model. Within its framework, professionals follow a process of identifying the impairment and its limitations (using the medical model), and taking the necessary action to improve the position of the disabled person. This has tended to produce a system in which an authoritarian, over-active service provider prescribes and acts for a passive client.{{sfn|Nikora|Karapu|Hickey|Te Awekotuku|2004|p=5–6}}
* The '''tragedy/charity model''' depicts disabled people as victims of circumstance who are deserving of [[pity]]. This, along with the medical model, are the models most used by non-disabled people to define and explain disability.{{sfn|Nikora|Karapu|Hickey|Te Awekotuku|2004|p=6}}
* The '''legitimacy model''' views disability as a value-based determination about which explanations for the atypical are legitimate for membership in the disability category. This viewpoint allows for multiple explanations and models to be considered as purposive and viable.{{sfn|DePoy|Gilson|2004}}
* The '''social adapted model''' states although a person's disability poses some limitations in an able-bodied society, often the surrounding society and environment are more limiting than the disability itself.{{sfn|Nikora|Karapu|Hickey|Te Awekotuku|2004|p=7}}
* The '''economic model''' defines disability in terms of reduced ability to work, the related loss of productivity and economic effects on the individual, employer and society in general.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Economic Model of Disability |url=http://www.copower.org/models-of-disability/176-economic-model-of-disability.html |publisher=Michigan Disability Rights Coalition |accessdate=August 11, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The '''empowering model''' (also, '''customer model''') allows for the person with a disability and his/her family to decide the course of his/her treatment. This turns the professional into a service provider whose role is to offer guidance and carry out the client's decisions. This model "empowers" the individual to pursue his/her own goals.{{sfn|Nikora|Karapu|Hickey|Te Awekotuku|2004|p=7}}
*The '''market model''' of disability is minority rights and consumerist model of disability that recognizing disabled people and their stakeholders as representing a large group of consumers, employees and voters.  This model looks to personal identity to define disability and empowers people to chart their own destiny in everyday life, with a particular focus on economic empowerment.  By this model, based on US Census data, there are 1.2 billion people in the world who consider themselves to have a disability. "This model states that, due to the size of the demographic, companies and governments will serve the desires, pushed by demand as the message becomes prevalent in the cultural mainstream."{{sfn|Donovan|2012|p=12}}
*The '''consumer model''' of disability is based upon the “rights-based" model and claims that disabled people should have equal rights and access to products, goods and services offered by businesses.  The consumer model extends the rights-based model by proposing that businesses, not only accommodate customers with disabilities under the requirements of legislation, but that businesses actively seek, market to, welcome and fully engage disabled people in all aspects of business service activities.  The model suggests that all business operations, for example websites, policies and procedures, mission statements, emergency plans, programs and services, should integrate access and inclusion practices.  Furthermore, these access and inclusion practices should be based on established customer service access and inclusion standards that embrace and support the active engagement of people of all abilities in business offerings.&lt;ref&gt;Smith, T.B. (2012). A New and Emerging Model of Disability:  The Consumer Model.  White Paper. The Pennsylvania State University&lt;/ref&gt;
*Different theories revolve around prejudice, stereotyping, discrimination, and stigma related to disability. One of the more popular ones, as put by Weiner, Perry, and Magnusson 's (1988) work with '''attribution theory''', physical stigmas are perceived as to be un-controllable and elicit pity and desire to help, whereas, mental-behavioral stigmas are considered to be controllable and therefore elicit anger and desire to neglect the individuals with disabilities.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|url = |title = An attributional analysis of reactions to stigmas|author1=Weiner, B. |author2=Perry, R. P. |author3= Magnusson, J. |last-author-amp=yes |date = 1988|journal = Journal of Personality and Social Psychology|doi = 10.1037/0022-3514.55.5.738 |pmid = }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*The '''‘just world hypothesis'''’ talks about how a person is viewed as deserving the disability. And because it is the fault of that person, an observer does not feel obligated to feel bad for him or to help him.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = The belief in a just world: A fundamental delusion.|last = Lerner|first = M. J.|publisher = Plenum Press|year = 1980|isbn = |location = New York|pages = }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Identity ==
In contexts where their differences are visible, persons with disabilities often face stigma. People frequently react to disabled presence with fear, pity, patronization, intrusive gazes, revulsion, or disregard. These reactions can, and often do, exclude persons with disabilities from accessing social spaces along with the benefits and resources these spaces provide.&lt;ref name=":1x"&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://donnareeve.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/ReeveChapter2004b.pdf|title=Reeve Chapter 2004|format=PDF|last=Reeve|first=Donna|publisher=The Disability Press|year=2004|isbn=0-9528450-8-3|editor-last=Barnes|editor-first=Colin|location=Leeds, U.K.|pages=83–100|chapter=Psycho-emotional dimensions of disability and the social model|editor-last2=Mercer|editor-first2=Geof}}&lt;/ref&gt; Disabled writer/researcher Jenny Morris describes how stigma functions to marginalize persons with disabilities:&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://repositoriocdpd.net:8080/bitstream/handle/123456789/605/L_MorrisJ_PrideAgainstPrejudice_1991.pdf?sequence=1|title=Pride Against Prejudice Transforming Attitudes to Disability|last=Morris|first=Jenny|publisher=The Women's Press|year=1991|isbn=|location=Aylesbury, Bucks, England|pages=21, 22}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{Quote|“Going out in public so often takes courage. How many of us find that we can't dredge up the strength to do it day after day, week after week, year after year, a lifetime of rejection and revulsion? It is not only physical limitations that restrict us to our homes and those whom we know. It is the knowledge that each entry into the public world will be dominated by stares, by condescension, by pity and by hostility.”}}
Additionally, facing stigma can cause harm to psycho-emotional well-being of the person being stigmatized. One of the ways in which the psycho-emotional health of persons with disabilities is adversely affected is through the internalization of the oppression they experience, which can lead to feeling that they are weak, crazy, worthless, or any number of other negative attributes that may be associated with their conditions. Internalization of oppression damages the self-esteem of the person affected and shapes their behaviors in ways that are compliant with nondisabled dominance.&lt;ref name=":1x" /&gt; Ableist ideas are frequently internalized when disabled people are pressured by the people and institutions around them to hide and downplay their disabled difference, or, "pass". According to writer Simi Linton, the act of passing takes a deep emotional toll by causing disabled individuals to experience loss of community, anxiety and self-doubt.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Linton|first1=Semi|title=Claiming Disability: Knowledge and Identity|date=1998|publisher=NYU Press|location=New York|isbn=9780814751343|pages=19–21|url=http://web.b.ebscohost.com/ehost/detail/detail/bmxlYmtfXzQ3ODY0X19BTg2?sid=edb39fe1-bae0-4c9c-9dc5-d0c2903f2346@sessionmgr106&amp;vid=0&amp;detailAuthError=true#AN=47864&amp;db=nlebk|accessdate=3 May 2016}}{{Dead link|date=September 2018 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt; The media play a significant role in creating and reinforcing stigma associated with disability. Media portrayals of disability usually cast disabled presence as necessarily marginal within society at large. These portrayals simultaneously reflect and influence the popular perception of disabled difference.

=== Tropes ===
{{Further|Disability in the media}}
There are distinct tactics that the media frequently employ in representing disabled presence. These common ways of framing disability are heavily criticized for being dehumanizing and failing to place importance on the perspectives of persons with disabilities.

==== Inspiration porn ====
[[Inspiration porn]] refers to portrayals of persons with disabilities in which they are presented as being inspiring simply because the person has a disability. These portrayals are criticized because they are created with the intent of making able-bodied viewers feel better about themselves in comparison to the individual portrayed. Rather than recognizing the humanity of persons with disabilities, inspiration porn turns them into objects of inspiration for a nondisabled audience.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.abc.net.au/rampup/articles/2012/07/02/3537035.htm|title=We're not here for your inspiration|website=www.abc.net.au|language=en-AU|access-date=2016-04-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Supercrip ====
The supercrip trope refers to instances when media reports on or portray a disabled person who has made a noteworthy achievement; but center on their disability rather than what they actually did. They are portrayed as awe-inspiring for being exceptional compared to others with the same or similar conditions. This trope is widely used in reporting on disabled athletes as well as in portrayals of autistic savants.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Representing Autism Culture, Narrative, Fascination|last=Murray|first=Stuart|publisher=Liverpool University Press|year=2008|isbn=978-1-84631-092-8|location=Liverpool, U.K.|pages=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://physed.otago.ac.nz/sosol/v7i1/v7i1_1.html|title=sosol - Volume 7 Issue 1|website=physed.otago.ac.nz|access-date=2016-04-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Many disabled people denounce these representations as reducing people to their condition rather than viewing them as full people. Furthermore, supercrip portrayals are criticized for creating the unrealistic expectation that disability should be accompanied by some type of special talent, genius, or insight.

==== Disabled villain ====
Characters in fiction that bear physical or mental markers of difference from perceived societal norms are frequently positioned as villains within a text. Lindsey Row-Heyveld notes, for instance, “that villainous pirates are scraggly, wizened, and inevitably kitted out with a peg leg, eye patch, or hook hand whereas heroic pirates look like Johnny Depp's [[Jack Sparrow]].”&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Row-Heyveld|first=Lindsey|date=2015|title=Reading Batman, Writing X-Men Superpowers and Disabilities in the First-Year Seminar|url=http://pedagogy.dukejournals.org/content/15/3/519.full.pdf|journal=Pedagogy: Critical Approaches to Teaching Literature, Language, Composition, and Culture| volume = 15 |number =3|doi=10.1215/15314200-2917105|pmid=|access-date=April 19, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Disabled people's visible differences from the abled majority are  meant to evoke fear in audiences that can perpetuate the mindset of disabled people being a threat to individual or public interests and well-being.

=== Self advocacy ===
Some disabled people have attempted to resist [[marginalisation]] through the use of the social model in opposition to the medical model; with the aim of shifting criticism away from their bodies and impairments and towards the social institutions that oppress them relative to their abled peers. Disability activism that demands many grievances be addressed, such as lack of [[accessibility]], poor representation in media, general disrespect, and [[ignorance|lack of recognition]], originates from a social model framework.

Embracing disability as a positive identity by becoming involved in disabled communities and participating in disabled culture can be an effective way to combat internalised prejudice; and can challenge dominant narratives about disability.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Reeve|first=Donna|date=2002|title=Negotiating Psycho-Emotional Dimensions of Disability and their Influence on Identity Constructions|url=http://eprints.lancs.ac.uk/69654/1/ReeveArticle2002.pdf|journal=Disability &amp; Society|volume=17|issue=5|doi=10.1080/09687590220148487|pmid=|access-date=April 19, 2016|pages=493–508}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Intersections ===

{{expand section|date=February 2018}}

The experiences that disabled people have navigating social institutions vary greatly as a function of what other social categories they may belong to. The categories that intersect with disability to create unique experiences of ableism include, but aren't limited to, race and gender. The United Nations Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities differentiates two kinds of disability intersection, race disability intersection and gender disability intersection.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Lawson|first=Anna|title=European Union Non-Discrimination Law and Intersectionality:|publisher=Routledge|date=2016|url=https://books.google.am/books?id=-iu3DAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA47&amp;lpg=PA47&amp;q=disability%20intersections}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Race ====
Disabled people who are also racial [[minority group|minorities]] generally have less access to support and are more vulnerable to violent discrimination. For example, in the United States people of color who are mentally ill are more frequently victims of police brutality than their white counterparts. Camille A. Nelson, writing for the ''Berkeley Journal of Criminal Law'', notes that for “people who are negatively racialized, that is people who are perceived as being non-white, and for whom mental illness is either known or assumed, interaction with police is precarious and potentially dangerous.”&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Nelson|first1=Camille|title=Racializing Disability, Disabling Race: Policing Race and Mental Status|journal=Berkley Journal of Criminal Law|date=Spring 2010|volume=15|issue=1|url=http://www.bjcl.org/articles/15_1%20Nelson%20(1-64).pdf|accessdate=3 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Gender ====
The marginalization of disabled people can leave persons with disabilities unable to actualize what society expects of gendered existence. This lack of recognition for their gender identity can leave persons with disabilities with feelings of inadequacy. Thomas J. Gerschick of Illinois State University describes why this denial of gendered identity occurs:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Gerschick|first1=Thomas|title=Towards a Theory of Disability and Gender|journal=Signs|date=Summer 2000|volume=25|pages=1263–1268|jstor=3175525|doi=10.1086/495558}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{Quote|text="Bodies operate socially as canvases on which gender is displayed and kinesthetically as the mechanisms by which it is physically enacted. Thus, the bodies of disabled people make them vulnerable to being denied recognition as women and men."}}
To the extent that women and men with disabilities are gendered, the interactions of these two identities lead to different experiences. Disabled women face a sort of “double [[social stigma|stigmatization]]” in which their membership to both of these marginalized categories simultaneously exacerbates the negative stereotypes associated with each as they are ascribed to them. According to The UN Woman Watch, "Persistence of certain cultural, legal and institutional barriers makes women and girls with disabilities the victims of two-fold discrimination: as women and as persons with disabilities."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.un.org/womenwatch/enable/|title=WomenWatch: Feature on Women with Disabilities|last=WomenWatch|first=UN|website=www.un.org|access-date=2017-10-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; As Rosemarie Garland-Thomson puts it, “Women with disabilities, even more intensely than women in general, have been cast in the collective cultural imagination as inferior, lacking, excessive, incapable, unfit, and useless.”&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|date=Winter 2005|title=Feminist Disability Studies|doi=10.1086/423352|journal=Signs|volume=30|pages=1557–1587|last1=Garland-Thomson|first1=Rosemarie}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Assistive technology==
{{Main|Assistive technology}}
[[Assistive Technology]] is a generic term for devices and modifications (for a person or within a society) that help overcome or remove a disability. The first recorded example of the use of a [[prosthesis]] dates to at least 1800 BC.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Disability Social History Project&amp;nbsp;– Timeline |url=http://www.disabilityhistory.org/timeline_new.html |publisher=Disabilityhistory.org |accessdate=August 11, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[wheelchair]] dates from the 17th century.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Cooper, Rory A |author2=Hisaichi Ohnabe |author3=Douglas A. Hobson |title=An Introduction to Rehabilitation Engineering|year=2006|publisher=CRC Press|isbn=9781420012491|page=131}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[curb cut]] is a related structural innovation. Other examples are [[standing frames]], text [[telephones]], accessible [[Keyboard (computing)|keyboards]], [[large print]], [[Braille]], &amp; [[speech recognition]] [[software]]. Disabled people often develop personal or community adaptations, such as strategies to suppress tics in public (for example in [[Tourette's syndrome]]), or [[sign language]] in [[deaf]] communities.

As the [[personal computer]] has become more ubiquitous, various organizations have formed to [[software development|develop software]] and [[computer hardware|hardware]] to make computers more accessible for disabled people. Some software and hardware, such as [[Voice Finger]], [[Freedom Scientific]]'s ''[[JAWS (screen reader)|JAWS]]'', the Free and Open Source alternative ''[[Orca (assistive technology)|Orca]]'' etc. have been specifically designed for disabled people while other software and hardware, such as [[Nuance Communications|Nuance]]'s [[Dragon NaturallySpeaking]], were not developed specifically for disabled people, but can be used to increase accessibility.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unh.edu/disabilityservices/dragon-naturally-speaking Dragon Naturally Speaking] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150408025058/http://www.unh.edu/disabilityservices/dragon-naturally-speaking |date=April 8, 2015 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[LOMAK]] keyboard was designed in [[New Zealand]] specifically for persons with disabilities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Sobh|first=Tarek|title=Innovations and Advanced Techniques in Computer and Information Sciences and Engineering|year=2007|publisher=Springer|isbn=9781402062681|page=176}}&lt;/ref&gt;
The World Wide Web consortium recognised a need for International Standards for Web Accessibility for persons with disabilities and created the Web Accessibility Initiative (WAI).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.w3.org/WAI/ |title=Web Accessibility Initiative (WAI) - home page |publisher=W3.org |date= |accessdate=January 29, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; As at Dec 2012 the standard is WCAG 2.0 (WCAG = Web Content Accessibility Guidelines).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.w3.org/TR/WCAG20/ |title=Web Content Accessibility Guidelines (WCAG) 2.0 |publisher=W3.org |date= |accessdate=January 29, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Adapted sports==
{{Main|Disabled sports}}

[[File:Wheelchair basketball at the 2008 Summer Paralympics.jpg|alt=an athlete tilts his wheelchair and raises an arm to block his opponent's shot|thumb|upright|[[Wheelchair basketball]] match between South Africa and Iran at the [[Wheelchair basketball at the 2008 Summer Paralympics|2008 Summer Paralympics]]]]
The [[Paralympic Games]] (meaning "alongside the Olympics") are held after the (Summer and Winter) [[Olympics]]. The Paralympic Games include athletes with a wide range of physical disabilities. In member countries, organizations exist to organize competition in the Paralympic sports on levels ranging from recreational to elite (for example, [[Disabled Sports USA]] and [[BlazeSports America]] in the United States).

The Paralympics developed from a rehabilitation programme for British war veterans with spinal injuries. In 1948, Sir Ludwig Guttman, a neurologist working with World War II veterans with spinal injuries at [[Stoke Mandeville Hospital]] in [[Aylesbury]] in the UK, began using sport as part of the rehabilitation programmes of his patients.

In 2006, the [[Extremity Games]] were formed for physically disabled people, specifically limb loss or limb difference, to be able to compete in [[extreme sports]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=First Extremity Games was first class success|url=http://www.oandp.com/articles/2006-08_12.asp|publisher=oandp.com|accessdate=March 6, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Rights and government policies==
{{Main|Ableism}}

===Rights movement===
{{main|Disability rights movement}}
The disability rights movement aims to secure equal opportunities and equal rights for disabled people. The specific goals and demands of the movement are [[accessibility]] and [[safety]] in transportation, architecture, and the physical environment; equal opportunities in independent living, employment, education, and housing; and freedom from abuse, neglect, and violations of patients' rights.&lt;ref name="disabilityrightswi.org"&gt;{{cite web |title=Disability Rights Wisconsin |url=http://www.disabilityrightswi.org/priority-issues/abuse-neglect-and-patient-rights |publisher=Disabilityrightswi.org |accessdate=August 11, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Effective civil rights legislation is sought to secure these opportunities and rights.&lt;ref name="disabilityrightswi.org"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Law"&gt;{{cite book | last = Bagenstos | first = Samuel | title = Law and the Contradictions of the Disability Rights Movement | publisher = Yale University Press | location = New Haven | year = 2009 | isbn = 978-0-300-12449-1 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Löve |first1=Laufey |last2=Traustadóttir |first2=Rannveig |last3=Rice |first3=James |title=Achieving disability equality: Empowering disabled people to take the lead |journal=Social Inclusion |date=26 March 2018 |volume=6 |issue=1 |pages=1–8 |doi=10.17645/si.v6i1.1180 |url=https://www.cogitatiopress.com/socialinclusion/article/view/1180 |accessdate=4 September 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The early disability rights movement was dominated by the medical model of disability, where emphasis was placed on curing or treating disabled people so that they would adhere to the social norm, but starting in the 1960s, rights groups began shifting to the social model of disability, where disability is interpreted as an issue of discrimination, thereby paving the way for rights groups to achieve equality through legal means.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Kemple|first1=Miriam|last2=Ahmad|first2=Fatima|last3=Girijashanker|first3=Suraj|title=Shaping Disability Rights through Shaping the Disability Movement|journal=Journal of Human Rights Practices|date=2011|volume=3|issue=3|pages=355–363|doi=10.1093/jhuman/hur019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Policies and actions===

====Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities====
On December 13, 2006, the [[United Nations]] formally agreed on the [[Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities]], the first human rights treaty of the 21st century, to protect and enhance the rights and opportunities of the world's estimated 650 million disabled people.&lt;ref name="ReferenceA"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Kayess|first1=Rosemary|last2=French|first2=Phillip|title=Out of darkness into light? Introducing the Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities.|journal=Human rights law review|date=2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;  {{as of|2011|April}}, 99 of the 147 signatories had ratified the Convention.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=UN Enable&amp;nbsp;– Promoting the Rights of Persons with Disabilities |url=https://www.un.org/esa/socdev/enable/ |publisher=United Nations |accessdate=August 11, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Countries that sign the convention are required to adopt national laws, and remove old ones, so that persons with disabilities will, for example, have equal rights to education, employment, and cultural life; to the right to own and inherit property; to not be discriminated against in marriage, etc.; and to not be unwilling subjects in medical experiments. UN officials, including the High Commissioner for Human Rights, have characterized the bill as representing a paradigm shift in attitudes toward a more rights-based view of disability in line with the social model.&lt;ref name="ReferenceA"/&gt;

====International Year of Disabled Persons====
In 1976, the [[United Nations]] began planning for its [[International Year of Disabled Persons]] (1981),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=International Year for Disabled Persons|journal=Public Health Reports|date=1981|volume=95|issue=5|pages=498–499}}&lt;/ref&gt; later renamed the [[International Year of Disabled Persons]]. The UN Decade of Disabled Persons (1983–1993) featured a World Programme of Action Concerning Disabled Persons. In 1979, [[Frank Bowe]] was the only person with a disability representing any country in the planning of IYDP-1981. Today, many countries have named representatives who are themselves individuals with disabilities. The decade was closed in an address before the General Assembly by [[Robert Davila]]. Both Bowe and Davila are [[deaf]]. In 1984, [[UNESCO]] accepted [[sign language]] for use in education of deaf children and youth.

====Policies in the United States====
In the United States, the Department of Labor's 2014 rules for federal contractors, defined as companies that make more than $50,000/year from the federal government, required them to have as a goal that 7% of their workforce must be disabled people.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=US Labor Department announces final rules to improve employment of veterans, disabled people|url=https://www.dol.gov/newsroom/releases/ofccp/ofccp20131578|website=U.S. Department of Labor|accessdate=18 December 2017|date=27 August 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; In schools, the ADA says that all classrooms must be wheelchair accessible.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://law.freeadvice.com/government_law/education_law/accommodations-for-children-with-disabilities.htm|title=Accommodations for Children with Disabilities &amp; the ADA|work=FreeAdvice}}&lt;/ref&gt; The U.S. Architectural and Transportation Barriers Compliance Board, commonly known as the Access Board, created the Rehabilitation Act of 1973 to help offer guidelines for transportation and accessibility for the physically disabled.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Ansley |first=James |date=2000 |title=Creating Accessible Schools |website=National Clearinghouse for Educational Facilities |publisher=National Institute of Building Sciences |url=http://www.ncef.org/pubs/accessibility.pdf }}&lt;/ref&gt;

About 12.6% of the U.S. population are individuals who suffer from a mental or physical disability. Many are unemployed because of prejudiced assumptions that a person with disabilities is unable to complete tasks that are commonly required in the workforce. This became a major [[Human rights]] issue because of the discrimination that this group faced when trying to apply for jobs in the U.S. Many advocacy groups protested against such discrimination, asking the [[Federation|federal government]] to implement laws and policies that would help individuals with disabilities.

=====Rehabilitation Act of 1973=====

The [[Rehabilitation Act of 1973]] was enacted with the purpose of protecting individuals with disabilities from prejudicial treatment by government funded programs, employers, and agencies. The Rehabilitation Act of 1973 has not only helped protect U.S. citizens from being discriminated against but it has also created confidence amongst individuals to feel more comfortable with their disability. There are many sections within The Rehabilitation Act of 1973, that contains detailed information about what is covered in this policy.

; Section 501
:   An employer must hire an individual who meets the qualifications of a job description despite any preexisting disabilities.
; Section 503
:   Requires contractors or subcontractors, who receive more than $10,000 from the government to hire people with disabilities and to accommodate them with the needs that they need to achieve in the work force.
; [[Section 504 of the Rehabilitation Act|Section 504]]
:   States that receive federal money may not discriminate against any person with disabilities who qualifies for a program or job.

=====The Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990=====

The federal government enacted The Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990, which was created to allow equal opportunity for jobs, access to private and government funded facilities, and transportation for disabled people. This act was created with the purpose to ensure that employers would not discriminate against any individual despite their disability. In 1990, data was gathered to show the percentage of disabled people who worked in the U.S. Out of the 13% who filled out the survey, only 53% percent of individuals with disabilities worked while 90% of this group population did not, the government wanted to change this, they wanted Americans with disabilities to have the same opportunities as those who did not have a disability. The [[Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990|ADA]] not only required corporations to hire disabled people but that they also accommodate them and their needs.

; Title I: Employment
:   An employer must give a qualified individual with disabilities the same opportunities as any other employee despite their disability. The employer must offer equal work privileges to someone who has a disability including but not limited to pay, work hours, training, etc. The employer must also create accommodations suitable for the person and their physical or mental disabilities.
; Title II: State and Local Government Activities
:   Requires that the government give disabled people the same opportunities involving work, programs, building access, and services. Title II also requires that buildings create easy access for disabled people and provide communicators who will be able to help those with [[Hearing loss|hearing]] or speaking impairments. Public spaces are however not required to create accommodations that would in turn alter their services as long as the services proved that they did all they could to prevent discrimination against disabled people.f
; Title II: Transportation
:   [[Public transport]]ation should be customized so that disabled people may have easy access to public transit. [[Paratransit]] is a service that provides transportation to people who are unable to get from one destination to another due to their mental or physical disability.
; Title II: Public Accommodations
:   Public accommodations require that private businesses create accommodations that will allow disabled people easy access to buildings. Private businesses may not discriminate against disabled people and must provide accommodations that are reasonable, alterations may be made so that a person with disabilities can have equal access to facilities that are provided, communicators for the [[hearing impaired]], devices for the visually impaired, and wheelchair access. Facilities must regulate with the [[Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990|ADA]], when regulating the buildings infrastructure so it meets the [[Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990|ADA]] regulations.
; Title IV: Telecommunication Relay Services
:   Requires telephone companies to have [[Telecommunications relay service|TRS]] seven days a week, twenty four hours a day. It requires telephone companies to create accommodations for deaf/hard of hearing people by providing a third party that will be able to assistant both parties in communicating with one another.

====Policies in the United Kingdom====
In the UK, the Department for Work and Pension is a government department responsible for promoting disability awareness and among its aims is to increase the understanding of disability and removal of barriers for disabled people in the workplace. According to a news report, a people survey conducted in the UK shows a 23% increase in reported discrimination and harassment in the workplace at The Department for Work and Pension. The survey shows the number of reports for discrimination due to disability was in majority compared to discrimination due to gender, ethnicity or age. DWP received criticism for the survey results. As a department responsible for tackling discrimination at work, the DWP results may indicate room for improvement from within. A DWP spokesperson said the survey results do not necessarily indicate an increase in the number of reports, but rather reflecting the outcomes of efforts to encourage people to come forward.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title = Disabled staff at the DWP are reporting increased discrimination|url = https://www.independent.co.uk/news/uk/politics/disabled-dwp-staff-report-increased-discrimination-in-the-workplace-a6856191.html|website = The Independent|access-date = 2016-02-07|language = en-GB}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Policies in Japan====
{{main|Disability policy in Japan}}

====Policies in Sweden====
{{main|Disability policy in Sweden}}

===Political issues===
{{refimprove section|date=February 2010}}
[[File:USMC-00772.jpg|alt=woman seated in a wheelchair with military personnel in background|thumb|left|upright|A 28-year-old Iraqi woman who lost both of her legs during the [[Iraq War]] in 2005]]
Political [[rights]], [[social inclusion]] and [[citizenship]] have come to the fore in developed and some developing countries. The debate has moved beyond a concern about the perceived cost of maintaining dependent disabled people to finding effective ways to ensure that disabled people can participate in and contribute to society in all spheres of life.

In developing nations, where the vast bulk of the estimated 650 million disabled people reside, a great deal of work is needed to address concerns ranging from accessibility and education to self-empowerment, self-supporting employment, and beyond.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.un.org/disabilities/documents/toolaction/pwdfs.pdf|title=Fact Sheet on Persons with Disabilities, by United Nation|last=|first=|date=|website=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the past few years, disability rights activists have focused on obtaining full citizenship for the disabled.

There are obstacles in some countries in getting full employment; public perception of disabled people may vary.

====Abuse====
{{main|Disability abuse}}
Disability abuse happens when a person is abused physically, financially, verbally or mentally due to the person having a disability. As many disabilities are not visible (for example, asthma, learning disabilities) some abusers cannot rationalize the non-physical disability with a need for understanding, support, and so on.

As the prevalence of disability and the cost of supporting disability increases with medical advancement and longevity in general, this aspect of society becomes of greater political importance. How political parties treat their disabled constituents may become a measure of a political party's understanding of disability, particularly in the social model of disability.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Hough |first=Andrew |url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/uknews/crime/9626664/Disability-hate-crimes-rise-by-a-quarter-in-a-year.html |title='Disability hate crimes' rise by a quarter in a year |publisher=Telegraph |date=October 23, 2012 |accessdate=January 29, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Insurance====
Disability benefit, or [[disability pension]], is a major kind of [[disability insurance]] that is provided by government agencies to people who are temporarily or permanently unable to work due to a disability. In the U.S., disability benefit is provided in the category of [[Supplemental Security Income]]. In Canada, it is within the [[Canada Pension Plan]]. In other countries, disability benefit may be provided under [[social security]] systems.

Costs of disability pensions are steadily growing in Western countries, mainly in Europe and the United States. It was reported that, in the UK, expenditure on disability pensions accounted for 0.9% of gross domestic product (GDP) in 1980; two decades later it had reached 2.6% of GDP.&lt;ref&gt;OECD. Transforming disability into ability: Policies to promote work and income security for disabled people. Paris: OECD Publication Offices. 2003&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Labriola-Lund-2007"&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Labriola M, Lund T | title = Self-reported sickness absence as a risk marker of future disability pension. Prospective findings from the DWECS/DREAM study 1990-2004 | journal = Int J Med Sci | volume = 4 | issue = 3 | pages = 153–8 | year = 2007 | pmid = 17554400 | pmc = 1885553 | doi = 10.7150/ijms.4.153 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Several studies have reported a link between increased absence from work due to sickness and elevated risk of future disability pension.&lt;ref name="pmid16497865"&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Virtanen M, Kivimäki M, Vahtera J, Elovainio M, Sund R, Virtanen P, Ferrie JE | title = Sickness absence as a risk factor for job termination, unemployment, and disability pension among temporary and permanent employees | journal = Occup Environ Med | volume = 63 | issue = 3 | pages = 212–7 | year = 2006 | pmid = 16497865 | pmc = 2078149 | doi = 10.1136/oem.2005.020297 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

A study by researchers in Denmark suggests that information on self-reported days of absence due to sickness can be used to effectively identify future potential groups for disability pension.&lt;ref name="Labriola-Lund-2007"/&gt; These studies may provide useful information for policy makers, case managing authorities, employers, and physicians.

Private, for-profit disability insurance plays a role in providing incomes to disabled people, but the nationalized programs are the safety net that catch most claimants.

==Demographics==

Estimates of worldwide and country-wide numbers of individuals with disabilities are problematic. The varying approaches taken to defining disability notwithstanding, demographers agree that the world population of individuals with disabilities is very large. For example, in 2012, the [[World Health Organization]] estimated a world population of 6.5 billion people. Of those, nearly 650 million people, or 10%, were estimated to be moderately or severely disabled.&lt;ref name="World Health Organization"&gt;{{cite web |title=Disability World Report 2011 |url=http://www.who.int/disabilities/world_report/2011/report/en/ |publisher=World Health Organization |year=2011 |accessdate=January 8, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In 2018 the [[International Labour Organization]] estimated that about a billion people, one seventh of the world population, had disabilities, 80% of them in developing countries, and 80% of working age.  Excluding disabled people from the workforce was reckoned to cost up to 7% of [[gross domestic product]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=For many, disability is part of what it means to be human |url=https://www.ft.com/content/f4e2dc50-3dab-11e8-bcc8-cebcb81f1f90 |accessdate=14 August 2018 |publisher=Financial Times |date=11 May 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Afghanistan===
After years of war in Afghanistan, there are more than 1 million disabled people.&lt;ref&gt;"[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/south_asia/8073447.stm Homes for disabled in Afghanistan]". BBC News. May 29, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; Afghanistan has one of the highest incidences of disabled people in the world.&lt;ref&gt;"[http://www.irinnews.org/report.aspx?reportid=26520 Afghanistan: People living with disabilities call for integration]". [[IRIN]] Asia. December 2, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt; An estimated 80,000 Afghans are missing limbs, usually from landmine explosions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Norton-Taylor |first=Richard |date=February 13, 2008 |title=Afghanistan's refugee crisis 'ignored' |url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2008/feb/13/afghanistan |location=London |publisher=The Guardian |accessdate=August 11, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Australia===
In [[disability in Australia|Australia]], 18.5% of the population reported having a disability in a 2009 survey.&lt;ref name=ABS2009&gt;{{cite report|publisher=[[Australian Bureau of Statistics]] |year=2009 |url=http://www.ausstats.abs.gov.au/ausstats/subscriber.nsf/0/9C2B94626F0FAC62CA2577FA0011C431/$File/44300_2009.pdf |title=Disability, Ageing and Carers, Australia: Summary of Findings, cat. no. 4430.0, |place=Canberra |format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===United States===
According to the [[United States Census Bureau|U.S. Census Bureau]], {{as of|2010|lc=y}}, there were some 56.7 million disabled people, or 19% (by comparison, African Americans are the largest racial minority in the U.S., but only constitute 12.6% of the U.S. population).&lt;ref name="U.S. Bureau of the Census"&gt;{{cite web |title=American FactFinder |url=http://factfinder.census.gov/servlet/STTable?_bm=y&amp;-geo_id=01000US&amp;-qr_name=ACS_2007_3YR_G00_S1801&amp;-ds_name=ACS_2007_3YR_G00_ |publisher=Factfinder.census.gov |accessdate=August 11, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Disabled individuals make up one of the most inclusive minority groups in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=LaPlante|first=P. Mitchell|year=1991|title=The Demographics of Disability|url=|journal=The Milbank Quarterly|volume=69|pages=55–77|doi=10.2307/3350158}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to the 2014 Disability status report of the Cornell University Yang Tan Institute the prevalence rate of individuals with disabilities in the United States was 12.6% in that year. {{as of|2014}} ambulatory disability had the highest prevalence (7.1%) in the United States. By contrast, visual disability had the lowest prevalence (2.3%). Additionally, 3.6% of people in the United States were reported to have had an auditory disability in the same year.&lt;ref name=":3"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Erickson|first=W.|year=2014|title=2014 Disability Status Report: United States|url=|journal=Cornell University Yang Tan Institute on Employment and Disability|volume=|pages=1–65|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

5.8% of individuals ages 16–20 reported having any disability, physical and/ or cognitive. Adults 21 to 64 had a prevalence of 10.8% with over half of these (5.5%) being ambulatory disabilities. Ambulatory disability prevalence raised to 15.8% in adults 65–74 years of age. Adults 75 years and older comprised the highest prevalence with any disability at 50.3%.

Female individuals across all ages reported a total 0.4% higher prevalence rate than males who reported 12.4%.

In the U.S. 17.9% of Native American peoples reported having a disability while 4.5% reporting were of Asian descent, these were the two opposing poles of the prevalence rate within race {{as of|2014|lc=y}}.&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt;

Although there are acts that have been imposed in order to prevent the discrimination of individuals with disabilities in the workplace, there is still an employment gap that can be seen between those with and without disabilities. In regards to employment, the institute's status report accounts that 34.6% of people with any disability reported being employed. By comparison; 77.6% of individuals, who did not report having a disability, reported having a full-time job in 2014.&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt;

For those employed full-time, individuals with disabilities on average earned $5,100 less than employees without a disability who were also employed full-time. Those affected the most by these differences were intellectually disabled people.&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt;

===Europe===
Nearly 8 million European men were permanently disabled in [[World War I]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Kitchen |first=Martin |year=2000 |origyear=1980 |title=Europe Between the Wars |location=New York |publisher=Longman |isbn=0-582-41869-0 |oclc=247285240}}&lt;/ref&gt; About 150,000 [[Vietnam veteran]]s came home wounded, and at least 21,000 were permanently disabled.&lt;ref&gt;"[http://www.digitalhistory.uh.edu/database/article_display.cfm?HHID=513 The War's Costs] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20030907033319/http://www.digitalhistory.uh.edu/database/article_display.cfm?HHID=513 |date=September 7, 2003 }}". Digital History.&lt;/ref&gt; As of 2008, there were 2.9 million disabled veterans in the United States, an increase of 25 percent over 2001.&lt;ref&gt;"[http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,354985,00.html VA: Number of Disabled Veterans Rising]". FOXNews.com. May 11, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Developing nations===
There is widespread agreement among experts{{who|date=May 2014}} in the field, that disability is more common in developing than in developed nations. The connection between [[disability and poverty]] is thought to be part of a "vicious cycle" in which these constructs are mutually reinforcing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author = Yeo R., Moore K. | year = 2003 | title = Including disabled people in poverty reduction work: "Nothing about us, without us" | doi = 10.1016/S0305-750X(02)00218-8 | journal = World Development | volume = 31 | issue = | pages = 571–590 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
{{Portal|Disability}}
* [[Disability hate crime]]
* [[Disadvantaged]]
* [[Frailty syndrome]]
* [[Physiological functional capacity]]

==References==
===Citations===
{{Reflist}}

===Sources===
* {{cite book |last1=DePoy |first1=Elizabeth |last2=Gilson |first2=Stephen French |year=2004 |title=Rethinking Disability: Principles for Professional and Social Change |location=Pacific Grove, CA |publisher=Brooks Cole |isbn=978-0-534-54929-9 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite web |last=Donovan |first=Rich |date=March 1, 2012 |title=The Global Economics of Disability |url=http://www.returnondisability.com/pdf-docs/The_Global_Economics_of_Disability_2012.pdf |publisher=Return on Disability |accessdate=August 11, 2012 |ref=harv |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120913222254/http://www.returnondisability.com/pdf-docs/The_Global_Economics_of_Disability_2012.pdf |archive-date=September 13, 2012 |dead-url=yes |df=mdy-all }}
* {{cite encyclopedia |last1=Ducy |first1=Elizabeth McAdams |last2=Stough |first2=Laura M. |last3=Clark |first3=M. Carolyn |year=2012 |title=Choosing Agency in the Midst of Vulnerability: Using Critical Disability Theory to Examine a Disaster Narrative |work=Critical Qualitative Research Reader |editor1-last=Steinberg |editor1-first=Shirley R. |editor2-last=Cannella |editor2-first=Gaile S. |location=New York |publisher=Peter Lang |isbn=978-1-4331-0688-0 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite web |last1=Nikora |first1=Linda Waimari |last2=Karapu |first2=Rolinda |last3=Hickey |first3=Huhana |last4=Te Awekotuku |first4=Ngahuia |year=2004 |title=Disabled Maori and Disability Support Options |url=http://waikato.researchgateway.ac.nz/bitstream/10289/460/1/content.pdf |publisher=Maori&amp;nbsp;&amp; Psychology Research Unit, University of Waikato |accessdate=August 11, 2012 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite encyclopedia |last=Stough |first=Laura M. |year=2009 |title=The Effects of Disaster on the Mental Health of Individuals With Disabilities |work=Mental Health and Disasters |editor1-last=Neria |editor1-first=Yuval |editor2-last=Galea |editor2-first=Sandro |editor3-last=Norris |editor3-first=Fran H. |publisher=Cambridge University Press |isbn=978-1-107-41282-8 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite web |last=Yeo |first=Rebecca |year=2005 |title=Disability, poverty, and the new development agenda |publisher=Disability Knowledge and Research Programme |url=http://www.dfid.gov.uk/r4d/PDF/Outputs/Disability/RedPov_agenda.pdf |accessdate=June 19, 2013 |ref=harv}}

==Further reading==
* {{cite book |editor-last=Albrecht |editor-first=Gary L. |year=2005 |title=Encyclopedia of disability |location=Thousand Oaks, CA |publisher=[[SAGE Publications]] |isbn=978-0-7619-2565-1}}
* {{cite conference |last1=Arditi |first1=A. |last2=Rosenthal |first2=B. |year=1998 |title=Developing an objective definition of visual impairment |conference=Vision '96: Proceedings of the International Low Vision Conference |pages=331–334 |location=Madrid, Spain: [[ONCE]] |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Bowe |first=Frank |year=1978 |title=Handicapping America: Barriers to disabled people |location=New York |publisher=Harper &amp; Row |isbn=978-0-06-010422-1}}
* {{cite book |last=Charlton |first=James I. |title=Nothing about us without us : disability oppression and empowerment |year=2004 |publisher=Univ. of California Press |location=Berkeley, Calif. [u.a.] |isbn=9780520224810 |edition=[3. Dr]}}
* {{cite journal |last=Burch |first=Susan |date=July 2009 |title=(Extraordinary) Bodies of Knowledge: Recent Scholarship in American Disability History |journal=OAH Magazine of History |volume=23 |pages=29–34 |issn=0882-228X |doi=10.1093/maghis/23.3.29 |issue=3}}
* {{cite journal |last1=Burkhauser |first1=Richard V. |last2=Schmeiser |first2=Maximilian D.|last3=Weathers II |first3=Robert R.|date=Jan 2012 |title=The Importance of Anti-Discrimination and Workers' Compensation Laws on the Provision of Workplace Accommodations Following the Onset of a Disability |journal=Industrial &amp; Labor Relations Review |volume=65 |issue=1 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite journal |last=Darling |first=Peter |date=Aug 2007 |title=Disabilities and the Workplace |journal=Business NH Magazine |volume=24 |issue=8 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite encyclopedia |last=Glenn |first=Eddie |year=1995 |title=African American Women with Disabilities: An Overview |url=http://www.dinf.ne.jp/doc/english/Us_Eu/ada_e/pres_com/pres-dd/glenn.html}}
* {{cite journal |last=Miles |first=Albert S |year=1994 |title=Brown v. Board of Education and the American with Disabilities Act: Vistas of equal educational opportunities for African  Americans |journal=Journal of Negro Education |volume=63 |issue=3 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Johnstone |first=David |year=2001 |edition=2nd |title=An Introduction to Disability Studies |location= |publisher=Fulton |isbn=978-1-85346-726-4}}
* {{cite book |last1=Masala |first1=Carmelo |last2=Petretto |first2=Donatella Rita |year=2008 |title=Psicologia dell'Handicap e della Riabilitazione |trans-title=The Psychology of Handicap and Rehabilitation |language=Italian |location=Rome |publisher=Kappa |isbn=978-88-15-06226-0}}
* {{cite book |last=Oliver |first=Michael |year=1997 |title=The Politics of Disablement |location=London |publisher=[[St. Martin's Press]] |isbn=978-0-333-43293-8}}
* {{cite book |last=Pearson |first=Charlotte |year=2006 |title=Direct Payments and Personalisation of Care |location=Edinburgh |publisher=Dunedin Academic Press |isbn=978-1-903765-62-3}}
* {{cite book |last=Shakespeare |first=Tom |author2=with Anne Kerr |year=1999 |title=Genetic Politics: from Eugenics to Genome |location=Cheltenham |publisher=New Clarion Press |isbn=978-1-873797-25-9}}
* {{cite journal |last=Kaushik |first=R. |year=1999 |title=Access Denied: Can we overcome disabling attitudes |journal=Museum International |volume=51 |issue=3 |pages=48–52 |publisher=UNESCO |issn=1468-0033 |doi=10.1111/1468-0033.00217}}
* {{cite journal |last=Lansing |first=Michael J. |date=January 2009 |title='Salvaging the Man Power of America': Conservation, Manhood, and Disabled Veterans during World War I |pages=32–57 |journal=Environmental History |volume=14 |location= |publisher= |issn=1084-5453 |doi=10.1093/envhis/14.1.32}}
* {{cite journal |last=Longmore |first=Paul |date=July 2009 |title=Making Disability an Essential Part of American History |journal=OAH Magazine of History |volume=23 |pages=11–15 |isbn=  |issn=0882-228X |doi=10.1093/maghis/23.3.11 |issue=3}}
* {{cite journal |authors=Masala C. Petretto | title = From disablement to enablement: conceptual models of disability in the 20th century | journal = Disability and Rehabilitation | volume = 30 | issue = 17 | pages = 1233–44 | year = 2008 | pmid = 18821191 | doi = 10.1080/09638280701602418 | issn = 0963-8288 }}
* {{cite book|last=Rose |first=Sarah F. |title=No Right to Be Idle: The Invention of Disability, 1840s–1930s |publisher=University of North Carolina Press |year=2017 |pages=xvi, 382 |isbn=978-1469624891}}

==External links==
{{Spoken Wikipedia|Disability.ogg|2009-04-20|18.3 mega}}
* {{dmoz|Society/Disabled}}
* {{Wiktionary-inline|disability}}
* {{Wikiquote-inline}}
* {{Commons category-inline|Disabled people}}
&lt;!-- Please do not add any additional external links here, add them to the DMOZ directory --&gt;

{{Disability navbox}}
{{Disability by country}}
{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Disability| Disability]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>