<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20171111012927|809732976" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="30170774" pageid="30170774" ns="0" title="Social privilege"><revisions><rev timestamp="2017-11-11T01:29:32Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{other uses|Privilege (disambiguation)}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=May 2016}}
'''Privilege''' is a social theory that special rights or advantages are available only to a particular person or group of people.  The term is commonly used in the context of [[social inequality]], particularly in regard to [[ageism|age]], [[disability]], [[Race (human classification)|ethnic or racial category]], [[gender]], [[gender identity]], [[sexual orientation]], [[religion]] and/or [[social class]].&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite book|title = Geographies of Privilege|last = Twine|first = France Winddance|publisher = Routledge|year = 2013|isbn = 0415519616|location = |pages = 8–10}}&lt;/ref&gt; Two common examples may include having access to a higher education and housing.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; Under a newer usage of the term, privilege can also be emotional or psychological, regarding comfort and personal self-confidence, or having a sense of belonging or worth in society.&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{Cite book|title = Privilege: A Reader|last = Kimmel|first = Michael S.|publisher = Westview Press|year = 2009|isbn = 0813344263|location = |pages = 1, 5, 13–26}}&lt;/ref&gt; It began as an academic concept, but has since become popular outside of academia.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.theguardian.com/society/2013/jun/05/check-your-privilege-means |title=Check your privilege! Whatever that means |first=Hadley |last=Freeman |date=4 June 2013 |work=The Guardian |accessdate=23 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Substantial analysis of privilege and specific social groups have been published and have included a variety of perspectives. Some commentators have addressed limitations in the term, such as its inability to distinguish between concepts of "spared injustice" and "unjust enrichment", and its tendency to conflate disparate groups.&lt;ref name=":4"&gt;{{Cite journal |url=http://www.faculty.umb.edu/lawrence_blum/publications/publications/A57.pdf |title='White privilege': A mild critique |first=Lawrence |last=Blum |date=2008 |journal=Theory and Research in Education |volume=6 |doi = 10.1177/1477878508095586 |publisher = SAGE Publications |issue = 6(3) |pages=309 |accessdate=23 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==
[[File:Du Bois, W. E. B..jpg|thumb|W. E. B. Du Bois, author of the essay ''[[The Souls of Black Folk]].'']]
The concept of privilege dates back to 1903 when American [[sociologist]] and [[historian]] [[W. E. B. Du Bois]] published the essay ''[[The Souls of Black Folk]]'', in which he wrote that although [[African American]]s were observant about [[white Americans]] and conscious of [[Racial Discrimination Act 1975|racial discrimination]], white Americans did not think much about African Americans, nor about the effects of racial discrimination.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Revealing Whiteness: The Unconscious Habits of Racial Privilege|last = Sullivan|first = Shannon|publisher = Indiana University Press|year = 2006|isbn = 0253218489|location = |pages = 121–123}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = W.E.B. Du Bois and the Problems of the Twenty-First Century: An Essay on Africana Critical Theory|last = Reiland|first = Rabaka|publisher = Lexington Books|year = 2007|isbn = 0739116827|location = |pages = 3}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Classical and Contemporary Sociological Theory: Text and Readings|last = Appelrouth|first = Scott|publisher = SAGE Publications|year = 2007|isbn = 076192793X|location = 304-305|pages = }}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1935, Du Bois wrote about what he called the "wages of whiteness", which he described as including courtesy and deference, unimpeded admittance to all public functions, lenient treatment in court, and access to the best schools.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Critical Pedagogy Primer|last = Kincheloe|first = Joe L.|publisher = Peter Lang International Academic Publishers|year = 2008|isbn = 1433101823|location = |pages = 60–62}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1988, American [[feminism|feminist]] and anti-racism activist [[Peggy McIntosh]] published the essay ''White Privilege and Male Privilege: A Personal Account of Coming to See Correspondences through Work in Women’s Studies'', in which she documented forty-six privileges which she, as a white person, experienced in the United States. For example: "I can be sure that if I need legal or medical help, my race will not work against me", and "I do not have to educate my children to be aware of [[systemic racism]] for their own daily physical protection". McIntosh described [[white privilege]] as an "invisible package of unearned assets" which white people do not want to acknowledge, and which leads to them being confident, comfortable and oblivious about racial issues, while non-white people become unconfident, uncomfortable and alienated.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt; McIntosh's essay has been credited for stimulating academic interest in privilege, which has been extensively studied in the decades since.&lt;ref name=":7"&gt;{{Cite book|title = Encyclopedia of Gender and Society|last = O'Brien|first = Jodi A.|publisher = SAGE Publications|year = 2008|isbn = 1412909163|location = |pages = 418}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2014, [[Princeton University]] first-year student Tal Fortgang wrote ''Checking My Privilege'', a widely debated article in which he condemned classmates who told him to "check his privilege" for attributing his success in life to "some invisible patron saint of white maleness", and "for casting the equal protection clause, indeed the very idea of a meritocracy, as a myth".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://theprincetontory.com/main/checking-my-privilege-character-as-the-basis-of-privilege/|title=Checking My Privilege: Character as the Basis of Privilege|last=Fortgang|first=Tal|date=2 April 2014|work=The Princeton Tory|accessdate=24 June 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; McIntosh afterwards told the ''[[New Yorker Magazine|New Yorker]]'' that Fortgang was resisting seeing himself systemically. She argued that everybody has a combination of unearned advantage and unearned disadvantage, and should aim to try to see themselves in the context of societal patterns of discrimination and oppression.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.newyorker.com/online/blogs/books/2014/05/the-woman-who-coined-the-term-white-privilege.html|title=The Origins of Privilege|last=Rothman|first=Joshua|date=13 May 2014|work=The New Yorker|accessdate=24 June 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Overview ==
Historically, academic study of social inequality focused mainly on the ways in which minority groups were discriminated against, and ignored the privileges accorded to dominant social groups. That changed in the late 1980s, when researchers began studying the concept of privilege.&lt;ref name=":7" /&gt;

Privilege, as understood and described by researchers, is a function of multiple variables of varying importance, such as [[racism|race]], [[ageism|age]], [[genderism|gender]], [[heteronormativity|sexual orientation]], [[gender identity]], [[citizenship]], [[religion]], [[physical ability]], health, level of education, and others. Race, gender and social class are generally felt by sociologists to be the most determinative of a person's overall level of privilege.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = The Archaeology of Plural and Changing Identities: Beyond Identification|last = Casella|first = Eleanor C.|publisher = Springer|year = 2005|isbn = |location = |pages = 217}}&lt;/ref&gt; Privilege theory argues that each individual is embedded in a matrix of categories and contexts, and will be in some ways privileged and other ways disadvantaged, with privileged attributes lessening disadvantage and membership in a disadvantaged group lessening the benefits of privilege.&lt;ref name=":2"&gt;{{Cite book|title = Psychological Perspectives on Lesbian, Gay, and Bisexual Experiences|last = Garnets|first = Linda|publisher = Columbia University Press|year = 2002|isbn = 0231124139|location = |pages = 391}}&lt;/ref&gt; For example, a white [[lesbian]] [[Professor|university professor]] benefits from racial and educational privilege, but is disadvantaged due to her gender and sexual orientation.&lt;ref name=":6" /&gt; Some attributes of privilege are ordinarily fairly visible, such as race and gender, and others, such as citizenship status and birth order, are not. Some such as social class are relatively stable and others, such as age, wealth, religion and attractiveness, will or may change over time.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Gender in the Therapy Hour: Voices of Female Clinicians Working with Men (The Routledge Series on Counseling and Psychotherapy with Boys and Men)|last = Sweet|first = Holly Barlow|publisher = Routledge|year = 2012|isbn = 0415885515|location = |pages = 71}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some attributes of privilege are at least partly determined by the individual, such as level of education, whereas others such as race or class background are entirely involuntary.

In the context of the theory, privileged people are considered to be "the norm", and, as such, gain invisibility and ease in society, with others being cast as inferior variants.&lt;ref name=":6" /&gt; Privileged people see themselves reflected throughout society both in mass media and face-to-face in their encounters with teachers, workplace managers and other authorities, which researchers argue leads to a sense of entitlement and the assumption that the privileged person will succeed in life, as well as protecting the privileged person from worry that they may face discrimination from people in positions of authority.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Intercultural Communication: Globalization and Social Justice|last = Sorrells|first = Kathryn|publisher = SAGE Publications|year = 2012|isbn = 1412927447|location = |pages = 63}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Awareness of privilege ===
Some academics highlight a pattern where those who benefit from a type of privilege are unwilling to acknowledge it.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Handbook of Racial-Cultural Psychology and Counseling, Training and Practice|last = Carter|first = Robert T.|publisher = Wiley|year = 2004|isbn = 0471386294|location = |pages = 432}}&lt;/ref&gt; American sociologist [[Michael Kimmel]] describes the state of having privilege as being "like running with the wind at your back", unaware of invisible sustenance, support and propulsion.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt; The argument may follow that such a denial constitutes a further injustice against those who do not benefit from the same form of privilege.  One writer has referred to such denial as a form of "[[microaggression]]" or microinvalidation that negates the experiences of people who don't have privilege and minimizes the impediments they face.&lt;ref name=":3"&gt;{{Cite book|title = Microaggressions in Everyday Life: Race, Gender, and Sexual Orientation|last = Sue|first = Derald Wing|publisher = Wiley|year = 2010|isbn = 047049140X|location = |pages = 37–39}}&lt;/ref&gt;

McIntosh wrote that most people are reluctant to acknowledge their privilege, and instead look for ways to justify or minimize the effects of privilege stating that their privilege was fully earned. They justify this by acknowledging the acts of individuals of unearned dominance, but deny that privilege is institutionalized as well as embedded throughout our society. She wrote that those who believe privilege is systemic may nonetheless deny having personally benefited from it, and may oppose efforts to dismantle it.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt; According to researchers, privileged individuals resist acknowledging their privileges because doing so would require them to acknowledge that whatever success they have achieved did not result solely through their own efforts. Instead it was partly due to a system that has developed to support them.&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt; The concept of privilege calls into question the idea that society is a [[meritocracy]], which researchers have argued is particularly unsettling for Americans for whom belief that they live in a meritocracy is a deeply held cultural value, and one that researchers commonly characterize as a [[Meritocracy#Criticism|myth]].&lt;ref name=":6"&gt;{{Cite book|title = Deconstructing Privilege: Teaching and Learning as Allies in the Classroom|last = Case|first = Kim|publisher = Routledge|year = 2013|isbn = 0415641462|location = |pages =63–64 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Privilege: The Making of an Adolescent Elite at St. Paul's School (Princeton Studies in Cultural Sociology)|last = Khan|first = Shamus Rahman|publisher = Princeton University Press|year = 2012|isbn = 0691156239|location = |pages = 107–108}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":5" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Encyclopedia of Multicultural Psychology|last = Jackson|first = Yolanda Kaye|publisher = SAGE Publications|location = |pages = 471 |isbn=9781452265568 |url=https://books.google.com/?id=AP1yAwAAQBAJ |year=2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In ''The Gendered Society'', Michael Kimmel wrote that when privileged people do not feel personally powerful, arguments that they have benefited from unearned advantages seem unpersuasive.&lt;ref name=":5"&gt;{{Cite book|title = Seeing White: An Introduction to White Privilege and Race|last = Halley|first = Jean|publisher = Rowman &amp; Littlefield Publishers|year = 2011|isbn = 1442203072|location = |pages = 67, 191}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Criticism ==
The concept of privilege has been criticized for ignoring relative differences among groups. For example, researchers{{Who|date=August 2017}} have argued that in American culture there are status differences among [[Indian people|Asian Indians]], [[Chinese American|Chinese]], [[Japanese American|Japanese]], [[Korean American|Koreans]], and [[Cambodian American|Cambodians]], and among [[African American]]s, black immigrants from the [[Caribbean American|Caribbean]] and black immigrants from [[Africa]].&lt;ref name=":4" /&gt;

Some scholars{{Who|date=August 2017}} who believe that privilege exists and is systemic nonetheless criticize the label itself, saying that the word privilege implies luxuries rather than rights, and arguing that some benefits of privilege such as unimpeded access to [[education]] and [[housing]] would be better understood as rights.&lt;ref name=":4" /&gt; "White privilege", some{{Who|date=August 2017}} have argued, would be more accurately described as the advantages gained by whites through historical disenfranchisement of non-whites rather than something that gives whites privilege above and beyond normal human status.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Monahan, Michael J.|year=2014|title=The concept of privilege: a critical appraisal|journal=South African Journal of Philosophy|volume=3|issue=1|pages=73–83|doi=10.1080/02580136.2014.892681|issn=0258-0136|eissn=2073-4867}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Ableism]]
*[[Body privilege]]
*[[Christian privilege]]
*[[Cisgender privilege]]
*[[First World privilege]]
*[[Horizontal inequality]]
*[[Ingroups and outgroups]]
*[[Intersectionality]]
*[[Male privilege]]
*[[White privilege]]

==Further reading==
* {{cite book |last1=Rohlinger |first1=Deana A. |editor1-last=Ritzer |editor1-first=G. |editor2-last=Ryan |editor2-first=J.M. |title=The Concise Encyclopedia of Sociology |date=2010 |publisher=John Wiley &amp; Sons |isbn=978-1-44-439264-7 |pages=473–474 |chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Dz4wU64f_JYC&amp;q=%22male+privilege%22 |language=en |chapter=Privilege}}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

[[Category:Privilege (social inequality)| ]]
[[Category:Social inequality|*]]
[[Category:Critical theory]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Egalitarianism]]
[[Category:Feminist terminology]]
[[Category:Feminist theory]]
[[Category:Gender studies]]
[[Category:Identity politics]]
[[Category:Post-structuralism]]
[[Category:Queer theory]]
[[Category:Social philosophy]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>