<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20241112201522|1257021648" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="30170774" pageid="30170774" ns="0" title="Social privilege"><revisions><rev timestamp="2024-11-12T20:16:16Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|Theory of special advantage or entitlement}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=May 2016}}
'''Social privilege''' is an advantage or entitlement that benefits individuals belonging to certain groups, often to the detriment of others. Privileged groups can be advantaged based on [[social class]], [[wealth]], [[education]], [[caste]], [[ageism|age]], [[heightism|height]], [[Discrimination based on skin color|skin color]], [[physical fitness]], [[nationality]], [[Location|geographic location]], [[Cultural capital|cultural differences]], [[Ethnic group|ethnic]] or [[Race (human classification)|racial]] category, [[gender]], [[gender identity]], [[neurodiversity]], [[Disability|physical disability]], [[sexual orientation]], [[religion]], and other differentiating factors.&lt;ref name="black" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite book |title = Geographies of Privilege |last = Twine |first = France Winddance |publisher = Routledge |year = 2013 |isbn = 978-0415519618 |pages = 8–10}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Individuals can be privileged in one area, such as education, and not privileged in another area, such as health.  The amount of privilege any individual has may change over time, such as when a person becomes disabled, or when a child becomes a young adult. 

The concept of privilege is generally considered to be a theoretical concept used in a variety of subjects and often linked to social inequality.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; Privilege is also linked to social and cultural forms of power.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; It began as an academic concept, but has since been invoked more widely, outside of academia.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url= https://www.theguardian.com/society/2013/jun/05/check-your-privilege-means |title= Check your privilege! Whatever that means |first= Hadley |last= Freeman |author-link=Hadley Freeman |date=2013-06-05 |work= [[The Guardian]] |access-date=2018-11-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;  This subject is based on the interactions of different forms of privilege within certain situations.&lt;ref name=":8"&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://www.taylorfrancis.com/books/9780429494802|title=privilege: A Reader|last=S. Kimmel|first=Michael|editor2-first=Abby L|editor2-last=Ferber|editor1-first=Michael S|editor1-last=Kimmel|date=2018-04-17|publisher=Routledge|isbn=9780429494802|edition=4|location=Fourth Edition. Boulder, CO: Westview Press, 2016. Revised edition of Privilege, 2014.|pages=1–11|language=en|doi=10.4324/9780429494802}}&lt;/ref&gt; It can be understood as the inverse of [[social inequality]], in that it focuses on how power structures in society aid societally privileged people, as opposed to how those structures oppress others.&lt;ref name=":8" /&gt;

== History ==
===Writings of W. E. B. Du Bois===
[[File:Du Bois, W. E. B..jpg|thumb|[[W. E. B. Du Bois]], the author of  ''[[The Souls of Black Folk]]'' (1903)]]
Arguably{{explain|date=January 2024}}, the history of privilege as a concept dates back to American [[sociologist]] and [[historian]] [[W. E. B. Du Bois]]'s 1903 book ''[[The Souls of Black Folk]]''. Here, he wrote that although [[African American]]s were observant of [[white Americans]] and conscious of [[racial discrimination]], white Americans did not think much about African-Americans, nor about the effects of racial discrimination.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Revealing Whiteness: The Unconscious Habits of Racial Privilege|last = Sullivan|first = Shannon|publisher = Indiana University Press|year = 2006|isbn = 978-0253218483|pages = 121–123}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = W.E.B. Du Bois and the Problems of the Twenty-First Century: An Essay on Africana Critical Theory|last = Reiland|first = Rabaka|publisher = Lexington Books|year = 2007|isbn = 978-0739116821|pages = 3}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Classical and Contemporary Sociological Theory: Text and Readings|last = Appelrouth|first = Scott|publisher = SAGE Publications|year = 2007|isbn = 978-0761927938|location = 304-305|url-access = registration|url = https://archive.org/details/classicalcontemp0000appe}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1935, Du Bois wrote about what he called the "wages of whiteness" held by white Americans. He wrote that these included courtesy and deference, unimpeded admittance to all public functions, lenient treatment in court, and access to the best schools.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Critical Pedagogy Primer|last = Kincheloe|first = Joe L.|publisher = Peter Lang International Academic Publishers|year = 2008|isbn = 978-1433101823|pages = 60–62}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Codification of the concept===
Early concepts that would lead to the term White Privilege were developed by the Weather Underground in the 1960s.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Christensen |first=Mark |title=Acid Christ: Ken Kesey, LSD, and the Politics of Ecstasy |publisher=IPG |year=2010 |pages=264}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Sine |first=Peter |title=The Sixties |publisher=Wayne State University Press |year=1995 |pages=222}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1988, American [[feminism|feminist]] and anti-racism activist [[Peggy McIntosh]] published "White Privilege and Male Privilege: A Personal Account of Coming to See Correspondences through Work in Women's Studies". Here, McIntosh documented forty-six privileges which she, as a white person, experienced in the United States. As an example, "I can be sure that if I need legal or medical help, my race will not work against me", and "I do not have to educate my children to be aware of [[systemic racism]] for their own daily physical protection". McIntosh described [[white privilege]] as an "invisible package of unearned assets" which [[white people]] do not want to acknowledge, and which leads to them being confident, comfortable, and oblivious about racial issues, while non-white people become unconfident, uncomfortable, and alienated.&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{Cite book|title=Privilege: A Reader|last=Kimmel|first=Michael S.|publisher=Westview Press|year=2009|isbn=978-0813344263|pages=1, 5, 13–26}}&lt;/ref&gt; McIntosh's essay has been credited for stimulating academic interest in privilege, which has been extensively studied in the decades since.&lt;ref name=":7"&gt;{{Cite book|title = Encyclopedia of Gender and Society|last = O'Brien|first = Jodi A.|publisher = SAGE Publications|year = 2008|isbn = 978-1412909167|pages = 418}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Overview ==
Historically, academic study of social inequality focused mainly on the ways in which minority groups were discriminated against, and ignored the privileges accorded to dominant social groups. That changed in the late 1980s, when researchers began studying the concept of privilege.&lt;ref name=":7" /&gt;

Privilege, as understood and described by researchers, is a function of multiple variables of varying importance, such as [[racism|race]], [[ageism|age]], [[gender binary|gender]], [[heteronormativity|sexual orientation]], [[gender identity]], [[Neurodiversity|neurology]], [[citizenship]], [[religion]], [[physical ability]], [[health]], [[Education|level of education]], and others. Race and gender tend to have the highest impacts given that one is born with these characteristics and they are immediately visible. However, religion, sexuality and physical ability are also highly relevant.&lt;ref name=":8" /&gt;  Some such as social class are relatively stable and others, such as age, wealth, religion and attractiveness, will or may change over time.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Gender in the Therapy Hour: Voices of Female Clinicians Working with Men (The Routledge Series on Counseling and Psychotherapy with Boys and Men)|last=Sweet|first=Holly Barlow|publisher=Routledge|year=2012|isbn=978-0415885515|pages=71}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some attributes of privilege are at least partly determined by the individual, such as level of education, whereas others such as race or class background are entirely involuntary.

American sociologist [[Michael Kimmel|Michael S. Kimmel]] uses the metaphor of a wind to explain the concept. He explains that when you walk into the wind you have to struggle for each step that you take. When you walk with the wind, you do not feel the wind at all but you still move faster than you would otherwise. The wind is social privilege and if it flows with you, it simply propels you forward with little effort of your own.&lt;ref name=":8" /&gt;

In the context of the theory, privileged people are considered to be "the norm", and, as such, gain invisibility and ease in society, with others being cast as inferior variants.&lt;ref name=":6" /&gt; Privileged people see themselves reflected throughout society both in mass media and face-to-face in their encounters with teachers, workplace managers and other authorities, which researchers argue leads to a sense of entitlement and the assumption that the privileged person will succeed in life, as well as protecting the privileged person from worry that they may face discrimination from people in positions of authority.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Intercultural Communication: Globalization and Social Justice|last = Sorrells|first = Kathryn|publisher = SAGE Publications|year = 2012|isbn = 978-1412927444|pages = [https://archive.org/details/interculturalcom0000sorr/page/63 63]|url = https://archive.org/details/interculturalcom0000sorr/page/63}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Awareness of privilege ==
Some academics, such as Peggy McIntosh, highlight a pattern where those who benefit from a type of privilege are unwilling to acknowledge it.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|last=McIntosh|first=Peggy|chapter=White Privilege: Unpacking the Invisible Knapsack (1989) 1|date=2019-07-04|pages=29–34|publisher=Routledge|isbn=9781351133791|doi=10.4324/9781351133791-4|title=On Privilege, Fraudulence, and Teaching as Learning|s2cid=199169416}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":2"&gt;{{Cite book|title=Psychological Perspectives on Lesbian, Gay, and Bisexual Experiences|last=Garnets|first=Linda|publisher=Columbia University Press|year=2002|isbn=978-0231124133|pages=391}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Handbook of Racial-Cultural Psychology and Counseling, Training and Practice|last = Carter|first = Robert T.|publisher = Wiley|year = 2004|isbn = 978-0471386292|pages = 432}}&lt;/ref&gt; The argument may follow that such a denial constitutes a further injustice against those who do not benefit from the same form of privilege. [[Derald Wing Sue]] has referred to such denial as a form of "[[microaggression]]" or microinvalidation that negates the experiences of people who do not have privilege and minimizes the impediments they face.&lt;ref name=":3"&gt;{{Cite book|title = Microaggressions in Everyday Life: Race, Gender, and Sexual Orientation|last = Sue|first = Derald Wing|publisher = Wiley|year = 2010|isbn = 978-0470491409|pages = 37–39}}&lt;/ref&gt;

McIntosh wrote that most people are reluctant to acknowledge their privilege, and instead look for ways to justify or minimize the effects of privilege stating that their privilege was fully earned. They justify this by acknowledging the acts of individuals of unearned dominance, but deny that privilege is institutionalized as well as embedded throughout our society. She wrote that those who believe privilege is systemic may nonetheless deny having personally benefited from it, and may oppose efforts to dismantle it.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt; According to researchers{{who|date=October 2018}}, privileged individuals resist acknowledging their privileges because doing so would require them to acknowledge that whatever success they have achieved did not result solely through their own efforts. Instead it was partly due to a system that has developed to support them.&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt; The concept of privilege calls into question the idea that society is a [[meritocracy]], which researchers{{who|date=October 2018}} have argued is particularly unsettling for Americans for whom belief that they live in a meritocracy is a deeply held cultural value, and one that researchers commonly characterize as a [[Meritocracy#Critique|myth]].&lt;ref name=":6"&gt;{{Cite book|title = Deconstructing Privilege: Teaching and Learning as Allies in the Classroom|last = Case|first = Kim|publisher = Routledge|year = 2013|isbn = 978-0415641463|pages =63–64 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Privilege: The Making of an Adolescent Elite at St. Paul's School (Princeton Studies in Cultural Sociology)|last = Khan|first = Shamus Rahman|publisher = Princeton University Press|year = 2012|isbn = 978-0691156231|pages = 107–108}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":5" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Encyclopedia of Multicultural Psychology|last = Jackson|first = Yolanda Kaye|publisher = SAGE Publications|pages = 471 |isbn=9781452265568 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=AP1yAwAAQBAJ |year=2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In ''The Gendered Society'', Michael Kimmel wrote that when people at all levels of privilege do not feel personally powerful, arguments that they have benefited from unearned advantages seem unpersuasive.&lt;ref name=":5"&gt;{{Cite book|title = Seeing White: An Introduction to White Privilege and Race|last = Halley|first = Jean|publisher = Rowman &amp; Littlefield Publishers|year = 2011|isbn = 978-1442203075|pages = 67, 191}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Explain|date=January 2018}}

[[Catherine D'Ignazio]] and [[Lauren Klein]] in their book ''[[Data Feminism]]''&lt;ref name=":0a"&gt;{{Cite book |last1=Klein |first1=Lauren |title=Data Feminism |last2=D'Ignazio |first2=Catherine |publisher=The MIT Press |date=2020-03-17 |isbn=978-0262044004 |edition=1st |pages=28–29 |language=English}}&lt;/ref&gt; used the term '''privilege hazard''' when referring to the phenomenon where individuals in privileged positions remain unaware of their inherent advantages. This lack of awareness perpetuates societal inequalities and obstructs efforts to advocate for marginalized groups.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Guyan |first=Kevin |title=Queer data: using gender, sex and sexuality data for action |date=2022 |publisher=Bloomsbury Academic |isbn=978-1-350-23072-9 |series=Bloomsbury studies in digital cultures |location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; Privilege hazard is cited by other authors to acknowledge their positionality and risk of misinterpretating others' experiences.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Smith |first=Julia |title=Conscripted to Care: Women on the Frontlines of the COVID-19 Response |date=September 15, 2023 |publisher=McGill-Queen's University Press |year=2023 |isbn=9780228019329}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Authors such as [[Felicia Pratto]], Andrew Stewart, [[Peggy McIntosh]] and Taylor Phillips have contributed to this discourse by examining various forms of privilege hazards, including group dominance, white, male and class privilege. This exploration sheds light on how privilege manifests in different societal spheres and its implications for marginalized communities.

In their exploration of Data Feminism,&lt;ref name=":0a" /&gt; [[Catherine D'Ignazio]] and [[Lauren Klein]] define "privilege hazard" as the potential risks arising when privileged individuals, equipped with access to resources and data, attempt to address issues faced by marginalized groups. Relying solely on data may reinforce existing power dynamics. Software and data developers with privilege hazard may misinterpret data from contexts they don't understand.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Tanqueray |first1=Laetitia |last2=Larsson |first2=Stefan |date=2022 |title=What norms are social robots reflecting? A socio-legal exploration on HRI developers |journal=Social Robots in Social Institutions |series=Frontiers in Artificial Intelligence and Applications |volume=366 |pages=305–314 |doi=10.3233/FAIA366 |isbn=978-1-64368-374-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; The consequences may further marginalizing disadvantaged communities. To counter this, they advocate for an inclusive approach to data practices that centers on marginalized voices, aiming for a more equitable and just data ecosystem.

The continuous presence of privilege hazard is evident in the concept of group dominance, wherein one social group holds significant advantages over others, leading to the consolidation of power and resources. [[Felicia Pratto|Pratto]] and Stewart's research emphasizes that dominant groups often lack awareness of their privileged identities, viewing them as normal rather than as privileges.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Pratto |first1=Felicia |last2=Stewart |first2=Andrew L. |date=2012-03-19 |title=Group Dominance and the Half-Blindness of Privilege |url=https://spssi.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/j.1540-4560.2011.01734.x |journal=Journal of Social Issues |language=en |volume=68 |issue=1 |pages=28–45 |doi=10.1111/j.1540-4560.2011.01734.x |issn=0022-4537}}&lt;/ref&gt; Kaidi Wu and [[David Dunning]] delve into [[hypocognition]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Wu |first1=Kaidi |last2=Dunning |first2=David Alan |date=2020-02-16 |title=Hypocognition and the Invisibility of Social Privilege |url=http://dx.doi.org/10.31234/osf.io/5ge79 |access-date=2023-11-29 |doi=10.31234/osf.io/5ge79 }}&lt;/ref&gt; within group dominance privilege, highlighting how individuals from dominant groups may struggle to grasp the difficulties faced by minorities due to lack of exposure.

== Examples ==

===Educational racism===
[[Racism]] is the belief that groups of humans possess different behavioral traits corresponding to physical appearance and can be divided based on the superiority of one race over another. This can result in particular ethnic and cultural groups having privileged access to a multitude of resources and opportunities, including education and work positions.

Educational racism has been entrenched in American society since the creation of the United States of America. A system of laws in the 18th and 19th century known as the [[Black Codes (United States)|Black Codes]], criminalized the access to education for black people. Until the introduction of the [[Thirteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution]], the [[Fourteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution]] and the [[Civil Rights Act of 1866]], seeking out an education was punishable by the law for them. This thus served to keep African Americans illiterate and only value them as a workforce. However, even after these institutional and legal changes, African Americans were still targeted by educational racism in the form of [[school segregation in the United States]]. In the 20th century the fight against educational racism reached its climax with the landmark Supreme Court case [[Brown v. Board of Education]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|last=Bond|first=Helen|title=Racism in Education|date=2013|url=http://sk.sagepub.com/reference/sociology-of-education/n336.xml|work=Sociology of Education: An A-to-Z Guide|pages=640–643|publisher=SAGE Publications, Inc.|doi=10.4135/9781452276151|isbn=9781452205052|access-date=2019-08-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Educational racism also took other forms throughout history such as the creation of [[Canadian Indian residential school system]] in 1831, which forcefully integrated indigenous children into schools aimed at erasing their ethnic, linguistic and cultural specificities in order to assimilate them into a white settler society. Until the last residential school closed in 1996, Canada had an educational system which specifically harmed and targeted indigenous children. An estimated 6,000 children died under that system.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.thecanadianencyclopedia.ca/en/article/residential-schools|title=Residential Schools in Canada {{!}} The Canadian Encyclopedia|website=www.thecanadianencyclopedia.ca|access-date=2019-08-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Nowadays the opportunity gap pinpoints how educational racism is present in societies. The term refers to "the ways in which race, ethnicity, socioeconomic status, English proficiency, community wealth, familial situations, or other factors contribute to or perpetuate lower educational aspirations, achievement, and attainment for certain groups of students."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.edglossary.org/opportunity-gap/|title=Opportunity Gap Definition|last=Partnership|first=Great Schools|date=2013-05-15|website=The Glossary of Education Reform|access-date=2019-08-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; In other words, it is "the disparity in access to quality schools and the resources needed for all children to be academically successful."&lt;ref name=":02"&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://schottfoundation.org/issues/opportunity-gap/talking-points|title=Opportunity Gap - Talking Points {{!}} Schott Foundation for Public Education|website=schottfoundation.org|access-date=2019-08-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; Concretely this can be seen in the United States by considering how, according to the Schott Foundation's Opportunity to Learn Index, "students from historically disadvantaged families have just a 51 percent Opportunity to Learn when compared to White, non-Latino students."&lt;ref name=":02" /&gt;

According to McKinley et al.
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Students of color are pushed toward academic failure and continued social disenfranchisement. Racist policies and beliefs, in part, explain why children and young adults from racially marginalized groups fail to achieve academically at the same rate as their White peers.&lt;ref&gt;Bryan McKinley Jones Brayboy, Angelina E. Castagno and Emma Maughan. ''Review of Research in Education Vol. 31, Difference, Diversity, and Distinctiveness in Education and Learning'' (2007), pp. 159-194&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

=== Heterosexual privilege ===
[[Heterosexual privilege]] can be defined as "the rights and unearned advantages bestowed on heterosexuals in society".&lt;ref name=":9"&gt;{{Citation|last=Williford|first=Beth|chapter=Heterosexual Privilege|date=2009|chapter-url=http://sk.sagepub.com/reference/gender/n208.xml|publisher=SAGE Publications, Inc.|doi=10.4135/9781412964517.n208|isbn=9781412909167|access-date=2019-08-20|title=Encyclopedia of Gender and Society}}&lt;/ref&gt; There are both institutional and cultural forces encouraging heterosexuality in society.&lt;ref name=":9" /&gt; [[Sexual orientation]] is a repeated romantic, sexual or emotional attraction to one or multiple genders. There are a variety of categories including [[Heterosexuality|heterosexual]], [[gay]], [[lesbian]], and [[Bisexuality|bisexual]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.apa.org/topics/lgbt/orientation|title=Answers to Your Questions For a Better Understanding of Sexual Orientation and Homosexuality|website=American Psychological Association|language=en|access-date=2019-08-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; Heterosexual is considered the normative form of sexual orientation.&lt;ref name="black"&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Black|first1=Linda L.|last2=Stone|first2=David|date=2005|title=Expanding the Definition of Privilege: The Concept of Social Privilege|journal=Journal of Multicultural Counseling and Development|language=en|volume=33|issue=4|pages=243–255|doi=10.1002/j.2161-1912.2005.tb00020.x}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Heterosexual privilege is based in the existence of [[homophobia]] in society, particularly at the individual level. Between 2014 and 2018, 849 sexual orientation related hate crimes were committed in [[Canada]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www150.statcan.gc.ca/t1/tbl1/en/tv.action?pid=3510006601|title=Police-reported hate crime, by type of motivation, Canada (selected police services)|website=Statistics Canada|date=8 December 2014|access-date=2019-08-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; Despite the fact that [[Same-sex marriage in Canada|Canada]] legalized [[same-sex marriage]] in 2005 and has enshrined the protection of the human rights of all people of all sexual orientations, there is still societal bias against those who do not conform to heterosexuality.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/c-31.5/page-1.html|title=Civil Marriage Act|last=Branch|first=Legislative Services|date=2005-07-20|website=Justice Laws Act|access-date=2019-08-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/H-6/page-1.html?txthl=sexual#s-3|title=Canadian Human Rights Act|last=Branch|first=Legislative Services|date=1985|website=Justice Laws Website|access-date=2019-08-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Beyond this, institutions such as marriage stop homosexual partners from accessing each other's health insurance, tax benefits or adopting a child together.&lt;ref name=":9" /&gt; Same sex marriage is legal in only 27 countries, mostly in the northern hemisphere.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.pewforum.org/fact-sheet/gay-marriage-around-the-world/|title=Gay Marriage Around the World|website=Pew Research Center's Religion &amp; Public Life Project|language=en-US|access-date=2019-05-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; This results in an inability for non-heterosexual couples to benefit from the institutional structures that are based on heterosexuality, resulting in privilege for those who are heterosexual.

=== White privilege ===
Peggy McIntosh and scholars like [[Brian Lowery]] and Taylor Phillips discuss white privilege, highlighting the unseen benefits white individuals enjoy due to their race. McIntosh describes it as an ''invisible knapsack'' of unearned advantages, leading to limited perspectives and empathy towards marginalized groups.&lt;ref name=":1a"&gt;{{Citation |last=McIntosh |first=Peggy |title=White Privilege: Unpacking the Invisible Knapsack (1989) 1 |date=2019-07-04 |url=http://dx.doi.org/10.4324/9781351133791-4 |work=On Privilege, Fraudulence, and Teaching As Learning |pages=29–34 |access-date=2023-11-29 |publisher=Routledge |doi=10.4324/9781351133791-4 |isbn=978-1-351-13379-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; Taylor Phillips and Brian Lowery's research further elaborates on how whites tend to hide their privilege from themselves, maintaining the [[status quo]] and hindering progress toward [[Equity (economics)|equity.]]

=== Male privilege ===
Male privilege encompasses the advantages men experience solely due to their gender. [[Peggy McIntosh]] notes that males are conditioned not to recognize their privilege, leading to obliviousness and perpetuation of the privilege hazard.&lt;ref name=":1a" /&gt; Real-life examples, such as unequal distribution of household chores, illustrate how [[male privilege]] remains invisible to men due to societal norms.Tal Peretz expands on McIntosh's concept, questioning if men tend to overlook or critically examine their privilege.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Peretz |first=Tal |date=2018-07-08 |title=Seeing the Invisible Knapsack: Feminist Men's Strategic Responses to the Continuation of Male Privilege in Feminist Spaces |journal=Men and Masculinities |volume=23 |issue=3–4 |pages=447–475 |doi=10.1177/1097184x18784990 |issn=1097-184X|doi-access=free }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Class privilege ===
[[Class privilege]] refers to the benefits individuals enjoy based on their social or economic status. Taylor Phillips and [[Brian Lowery]]'s study&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Phillips |first=L Taylor |date=2015-02-25 |title=I Ain't No Fortunate One: On the Motivated Denial of Class and Race Privilege |url=http://dx.doi.org/10.5465/ambpp.2015.19158abstract |journal=Academy of Management Proceedings |volume=2015 |issue=1 |pages=19158 |doi=10.5465/ambpp.2015.19158abstract |issn=0065-0668}}&lt;/ref&gt; reveals that when confronted with their privilege, individuals tend to defend themselves, attributing success to personal efforts rather than acknowledging systemic advantages. This defensive response shields individuals from accepting their unearned advantages, representing a form of '''privilege hazard'''. Shai Davaidai and Jacklyn Stein's works delve into perceptions of wealth and poverty, highlighting the impact of environments on individuals' views of their circumstances.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Davidai |first=Shai |date=2022-02-01 |title=How do people make sense of wealth and poverty? |url=http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.copsyc.2021.06.010 |journal=Current Opinion in Psychology |volume=43 |pages=42–47 |doi=10.1016/j.copsyc.2021.06.010 |pmid=34284254 |issn=2352-250X}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Stein |first=Jacklyn |title=American Understandings of U.S. Economic Inequality: Redistribution and Resistance |publisher=University of Massachusetts Amherst |date=2021-10-01 |language=English}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Intersectionality ==
Privilege theory argues that each individual is embedded in a matrix of categories and contexts, and will be in some ways privileged and other ways disadvantaged, with privileged attributes lessening disadvantage and membership in a disadvantaged group lessening the benefits of privilege.&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt; This can be further supported by the idea of [[intersectionality]], which was coined by Kimberle Crenshaw in 1989.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Crenshaw|first=Kimberle|date=1989|title=Demarginalizing the Intersection of Race and Sex: A Black Feminist Critique of Antidiscrimination Doctrine, Feminist Theory and Antiracist Politics|url=http://chicagounbound.uchicago.edu/uclf/vol1989/iss1/8|journal=University of Chicago Legal Forum|volume=1989|issue=1|pages=139–167}}&lt;/ref&gt; When applying intersectionality to the concept of social privilege, it can be understood as the way one form of privilege can be mitigated by other areas in which a person lacks privilege, for example, a black man who has [[male privilege]] but no white privilege.&lt;ref name=":10"&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Coston|first1=Bethany M.|last2=Kimmel|first2=Michael|date=2012-03-19|title=Seeing Privilege Where It Isn't: Marginalized Masculinities and the Intersectionality of Privilege|journal=Journal of Social Issues|language=en|volume=68|issue=1|pages=97–111|doi=10.1111/j.1540-4560.2011.01738.x}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is also argued that members of privileged social identity groups often do not recognize their advantages.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Allen |first=Brenda |title=Difference Matters |page=15|edition=2nd|isbn=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Intersections of forms of identity can either enhance privilege or decrease its effects.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Presumed Incompetent : the Intersections of Race and Class for Women in Academia.|last=Gutiérrez y Muhs, Gabriella.|date=2012|publisher=Utah State University Press|others=Niemann, Yolanda Flores., González, Carmen G., Harris, Angela P.|isbn=9780874218701|location=Utah|pages=29–39|oclc=843635973}}&lt;/ref&gt; Psychological analysis has found that people tend to frame their lives on different elements of their identity and therefore frame their lives through the privilege they do or do not have.&lt;ref name=":11"&gt;{{Cite book |last=Voltmer |first=Amy |title=Understanding Intersectionality through Subjective Experiences of Privilege and Oppression |isbn=9780438047501 |oclc=1089398027}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, this analysis also found that this framing was stronger amongst certain nationalities, suggesting that identity and privilege may be more central in certain countries.&lt;ref name=":11" /&gt; Often people construct themselves in relation to the majority, so ties to identity and therefore degrees of privilege can be stronger for more marginalized groups.

Forms of privilege one might have can actually be decreased by the presence of other factors. For example, the feminization of a gay man may reduce his male privilege in addition to already lacking heterosexual privilege.&lt;ref name=":10" /&gt; When acknowledging privilege, multifaceted situations must be understood individually. Privilege is a nuanced notion and an intersectional understanding helps bridge gaps in the original analysis.

== Criticism ==
The concept of privilege has been criticized for ignoring relative differences among groups. For example, Lawrence Blum argued that in American culture there are status differences among [[Chinese American|Chinese]], [[Japanese American|Japanese]], [[Indian American|Indians]], [[Korean American|Koreans]], and [[Cambodian American|Cambodians]], and among [[African American]]s, black immigrants from the [[Caribbean American|Caribbean]], and black immigrants from [[Africa]].&lt;ref name=":4"&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.faculty.umb.edu/lawrence_blum/publications/publications/A57.pdf|title='White privilege': A mild critique|first=Lawrence|last=Blum|date=2008|journal=Theory and Research in Education|volume=6|doi=10.1177/1477878508095586|issue=3 |pages=309–321|s2cid=144471761|access-date=23 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Blum agreed that privilege exists and is systemic yet nonetheless criticized the label itself, saying that the word "privilege" implies luxuries rather than rights, and arguing that some benefits of privilege such as unimpeded access to [[education]] and [[housing]] would be better understood as rights; Blum suggested that privilege theory should distinguish between "spared injustice" and "unjust enrichment" as some effects of being privileged are the former and others the latter. Blum also argued that privilege can end up homogenising both privileged and non-privileged groups when in fact it needs to take account the role of interacting effects and an individual's multiple group identities.&lt;ref name=":4"/&gt; "White privilege", Michael Monahan argued, would be more accurately described as the advantages gained by whites through historical disenfranchisement of non-whites rather than something that gives whites privilege above and beyond normal human status.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Monahan, Michael J.|year=2014|title=The concept of privilege: a critical appraisal|journal=South African Journal of Philosophy|volume=3|issue=1|pages=73–83|doi=10.1080/02580136.2014.892681|s2cid=145358447|issn=0258-0136|url=https://philpapers.org/rec/MONTCO-21 |eissn=2073-4867}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Psychologist Erin Cooley reported in a study published in 2019 that reading about white privilege decreased social liberals' sympathy for poor whites and increased their will to punish/blame but did not increase their sympathy for poor blacks.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Cooley |first1=Erin |last2=Brown-Iannuzzi |first2=Jazmin |date=2019-04-29 |title=Complex intersections of race and class: Among social liberals, learning about White privilege reduces sympathy, increases blame, and decreases external attributions for White people struggling with poverty. |journal=Journal of Experimental Psychology: General |volume= 148|issue= 12|pages= 2218–2228|doi=10.1037/xge0000605 |pmid=31033321 |s2cid=139104272 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The existence of privilege across various categories leads to variation in experiences within specific privileged groups, raising concerns about the legitimacy of privilege hazard. Jamie Abrams' article&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Abrams |first=Jamie |date=2016 |title=Debunking the Myth of Universal Male Privilege |journal=University of Michigan Journal of Law Reform |volume=49 |issue=2 |pages=303 |doi=10.36646/mjlr.49.2.debunking |issn=2688-4933|doi-access=free }}&lt;/ref&gt; challenges the notion of privilege, discussing how efforts solely focused on highlighting male privilege may inadvertently reinforce existing cultural norms and fail to foster inclusivity. This perspective underscores the complexity of addressing systemic privilege, emphasizing the need to reshape [[Social norm|societal norms]] and institutional structures. [[Herb Goldberg|Herb Goldberg's]] book sheds light on how the idea of [[male privilege]] and power has hurt men's personal [[self-realization]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Goldberg |first=Herb |title=The Hazards of Being Male: Surviving the Myth of Masculine Privilege |publisher=Iconoclassic |date=2009-07-15 |isbn=978-0965762878 |edition=2009th |pages=352 |language=English}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Ableism]]
*[[Attention inequality]]
*[[Body privilege]]
*[[Caste]]
*[[Christian privilege]]
*[[Decadence]]
*[[Dominant culture]]
*[[First World privilege]]
*[[Horizontal inequality]]
*[[Ingroups and outgroups]]
*[[Male privilege]]
*[[Nobility]]
*[[Privilege (social inequality)]]
*[[Privilege hazard]]
*[[Social justice]]
*[[Social Stratification]]
*[[Structural abuse]]
*[[Structural discrimination]]
*[[Structural violence]]
*[[White privilege]]

==Further reading==
* {{cite journal |doi=10.1037/pspi0000240|title=I ain't no fortunate one: On the motivated denial of class privilege|year=2020|last1=Phillips|first1=L. Taylor|last2=Lowery|first2=Brian S.|journal=Journal of Personality and Social Psychology|volume=119|issue=6|pages=1403–1422|pmid=32551742|doi-access=free}}
* {{cite book |last1=Rohlinger |first1=Deana A. |editor1-last=Ritzer |editor1-first=G. |editor2-last=Ryan |editor2-first=J.M. |title=The Concise Encyclopedia of Sociology |date=2010 |publisher=John Wiley &amp; Sons |isbn=978-1-44-439264-7 |pages=473–474 |chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Dz4wU64f_JYC&amp;q=%22privilege%22 |language=en |chapter=Privilege}}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==
*{{Commonscatinline|Social privilege}}

{{Social class|state=expanded}}
{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Social privilege| ]]
[[Category:Critical theory]]
[[Category:Feminist terminology]]
[[Category:Feminist theory]]
[[Category:Gender equality]]
[[Category:Identity politics]]
[[Category:Post-structuralism]]
[[Category:Social justice terminology]]
[[Category:Majority–minority relations]]
[[Category:Concepts in social philosophy]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>