<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20051106193846|27552214" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="929970" pageid="929970" ns="0" title="Controversies in autism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-11-06T19:43:59Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{cleanup-date|November 2005}}
{{npov}}

There is considerable disagreement over the exact nature of '''[[autism]]'''. It is generally believed to be a spectrum or cluster of physical, mental and emotional conditions, of varying severity, none of which are well understood.  Despite the many physical [[conditions comorbid to autism spectrum disorders]], diagnostic criteria is as of [[2005]] still limited to [[psychiatric]] evaluation methods.  

The causes of autism are poorly understood, as are the prognoses, or treatment options.  There is, however, widespread agreement that early diagnosis and intervention can often make a significant difference for an autistic person's long-term prospects.  The human mind and [[nervous system]] are more plastic at a younger age, and there is a great urgency in the search for possible therapies and treatments. However, many autistic people, and some non-autistic supporters, believe that this natural emphasis on the problems facing children has often left support for adults neglected.

The medical community considers autistic disorders to be essentially incurable, or at least to have life-long effects.  Meanwhile, judging by the plethora of matieral on the [[internet]] and elsewhere, many [[autistic spectrum]] adults and [[neurotypical]] (non-autistic) allies in the [[autism rights movement]] do not consider autism to be a disorder, but simply a different way of perceiving and behaving. These people believe that at least some of the difficulties encoutered by people with autism may result from [[prejudice]] and lack of accommodation from society. 

With knowledge being so limited, and scientific progress slow, nearly all aspects of dealing with autism are hotly debated.  Parents of autistic kids face a bewildering set of choices, and attendant uncertainty about their merits.  

Some of these controversies are described below.   

==The usefulness and accuracy of autism as a diagnosis==

The 1994 [[DSM-IV]] criteria for the diagnosis of autism is the result of several drastic revisions, and the psychiatric community differs on whether the condition should be "clumped" along a spectrum or "split" into multiple distinct disorders that have similar symptoms.  Research and clinical experience further suggests that while autism may appear to manifest as a psychiatric disorder, its underlying causes are neurological.  [[Pervasive developmental disorder]] has emerged as an overarching descriptive term for the cluster of disorders that includes autism.

Autism is complicated by the fact that there is no defining test, and there is significant variation among people with autistic traits.  Those with [[Asperger's syndrome|Asperger syndrome]] may be highly functional, apparently merely lacking "social" skills, whereas others with "profound autism" may be non-verbal and deficient in elementary skills.  Some autistic people are "mentally retarded" (low IQ individuals); others have average or above average intelligence; and a minority have narrow, but exceptional [[autistic savant]] abilities; some have specific talents. A wide range of [[conditions comorbid to autism spectrum disorders]] strengthen the impression that what we call autism is a similarly-appearing set of symptoms for a wide range of underlying disorders.

This is not just an academic issue.  Treatment strategies and choices are based on a conviction of what needs to be changed.  Different parents have had hugely divergent experience with different treatment approaches.  Some claim their children have "grown out of it." Others claim their children recovered with only behavioral approaches. Some parents claim to have "cured" their children with biomedical intervention; others report little or no progress after trying many different approaches.  

Finally, there are also those (mainly autistics themselves) who reject the premise that autism is necessarily a disorder that requires fixing.  In their view, a diagnosis can sometimes amount to a judgment of non-conformity that is followed by efforts to correct what are essentially traits of personality.

===Asperger's and autism===

Currently, [[Asperger_syndrome|Asperger's]] is classified as a separate diagnosis in the [[DSM-IV]] but [[Asperger_syndrome|Asperger's]] is considered an [[autism spectrum disorder]]. The main difference between the definitions for autistic disorder and Asperger's syndrome in the DSM is that autism involves a speech delay and [[Asperger_syndrome|Asperger's syndrome]] does not. There are many people who believe [[autism]] and [[Asperger_syndrome|Asperger's]] should not be given separate labels in the DSM only because of a language delay, and there are some who believe autism and Asperger's have no defining differences.
It is also unclear if an autistic child who learns to speak and is high functioning should have his or her diagnosis changed to that of Asperger's Syndrome.

===Geeks and nerds===

It has been suggested that so-called [[geeks]] and [[nerd|nerds]] are undiagnosed persons with Asperger's syndrome. This has been disputed by professionals who indicate that geeks and nerds simply exhibit normal variant behavior, not pathological behavior. It should be noted, however, that many persons diagnosed with Asperger's syndrome also believe their behavior is not "abnormal" per se, and reject the notion that any divergence from a supposed ideal should be considered pathological. There are cases of persons who considered themselves simply geeks or nerds but later realize a diagnosis of Asperger's may apply to them, for example after having a child diagnosed autistic.

Whether Asperger's syndrome has any actual relation to being a geek or a nerd may only be determined genetically, so this issue has not been resolved either way at this point.
But there exists an apparent trend to pathologize almost any human variant behavior (e.g. [[ADHD]]) which could be interpreted as a trend to phase out [[ad hoc]] terms such as "geek".

=='Autistic' vs. 'Has autism'==

Individuals who describe themselves as autistic on the [[internet]] have
repeatedly stated their preference for the word ''autistic'' to be used
as an adjective as opposed to a noun. (In fact, it appears that the vast
majority of persons diagnosed autistic who express their views
verbally or in writing hold this position, across the spectrum.) They claim 
that autism is part of their very being, not something that could potentially
go away. Even if autism could be removed, they say that would be akin
to ceasing to exist.

As with other such arguments involving the [[autism rights movement]],
many parents of autistic children disagree. They claim that their children,
in fact, "''have autism''". The implication of this view is that 
autism is and should be removable/curable. They often cite [[regressive autism]], mercury
poisoning and other arguments as support for this position.

The more common usage today appears to be as a noun, but
people who are not emotionally involved in these arguments are 
generally not bothered by either usage.

==Epidemiology of autism==

{{details|Autism epidemic}}

There is uncertainty and controversy whether the incidence of autism is actually increasing, or if there simply is an increase in the number of reported cases.  Some argue that 
if the incidence is rising, then environmental factors play a greater role; while if it's being reported more often, genetics deserves more attention. Others argue that rising incidence can be explained using genetics. One theory, particularly associated with [[Simon Baron-Cohen]], suggests that increased social mobility may lead to the genetic amplification of autistic traits. Natural selection of traits useful in the information age has also been noted.

Anecdotal reports from school districts and physicians supports the impression that the incidence is rising, and some studies appear to support this as well.  Some believe the incidence has grown from about 1 in 5000 to 1 in 150 to 400 in the last few years and believe we are facing a major societal problem.

Others point out that several factors are likely to cause increased reporting.  First, the broadening definition of autism, which began most markedly with revised classifications in DSM-III-R in 1987, and the greater availability of services for autistic individuals creates an incentive to be inclusive in the diagnosis. Second, the last few decades have seen a greater awareness of autistic traits among pediatricians and other medical specialties.  It is surmised that some children who were previously diagnosed as retarded, or as having a psychotic disorder, are now diagnosed as autistic, or with pervasive developmental delay. Autism was once believed to be a type of childhood schizophrenia.

It will take time to resolve this issue.  As noted above, there is no definitive, standardized way to diagnose autism. This problem applies both for purposes of measuring past, present and future incidence.  There are important implications from this controversy, because the answer will guide both the allocation and magnitude of research, legal action, and therapy.

==Genetics and autism==

There is evidence that autism has a genetic component, and ongoing research focuses on finding the markers that determine autistic phenotypes. But there is significant disagreement whether genetics are a contributing or a decisive factor. For example, recent studies on twins by Greenberg ([[2001]]) and Betancur ([[2002]]) do not support twinning as a substantial risk factor in the etiology of autism. 

There is a trend toward viewing genetics as an underlying factor, although most autistic children have apparently [[neurotypical]] parents, which suggests
that a single rare gene cannot be the cause. This group of disorders is notable for its significant gender disparity, with the incidence of autism in males greatly exceeding the incidence in females. A [[1994]] study estimated the male-female ratio at 3:1 while a [[1982]] Japanese study indicated a ratio of 9:1. There are some, however, who speculate that autism occurs equally in both sexes, and that males are simply more likely to be diagnosed than females.

Scientists have recently (July 2005) shown that variations in the gene for protein kinase C beta 1 (PRKCB1), a protein with an important role in brain function, are strongly associated with autism. This exciting finding suggests some answers to a number of previous, but unexplained, observations about autism and provides the potential for a mechanistic explanation for some of the characteristics of the condition.

===Implications of genetic testing===

If and when genetic testing for autism becomes available, it is believed that
many women pregnant with an autistic child will decide to abort the pregnancy.
There is some precedent from [[Down's Syndrome]] which points in this direction.
[[Autism rights]] advocates believe this will be akin to [[genocide]].
Furthermore, the impact of such an event on the human species as a whole
could be very significant. Assuming that it is true that people such as
[[Albert Einstein]] and [[Isaac Newton]] were autistic, as some speculate,
common [[pro-life]] arguments such as "What if the next Einstein were to be aborted?"
would potentially be more biologically persuasive.

==Vaccines and autism==
In the late [[1990s]], controversial theories arose linking childhood vaccinations to autism.  

=== Thimerosal ===
{{main|Vaccine controversy}}
One theory states that early childhood [[vaccination]]s cause a shock to a child's immunological, neurological, and gastrointestinal systems.  These claims are based on several factors, including the presence of [[thimerosal]] in some vaccines, as well as the [[immunogen]]s themselves.

Until a few years ago, some formulations of [[vaccine]]s contained thimerosal, a mercury-based compound for purposes of preserving multi-use vaccine containers.  In sufficient quantities, mercury is [[neurotoxic]], and thus it is tightly regulated by the [[Environmental Protection Agency|EPA]].  The vaccines for [[Hepatitis B]], [[diphtheria]], [[tetanus]] and [[pertussis]] (DTP/DTaP) in particular are typically administered to children under the age of 2, and several formulations of this vaccine also contained thimerosal, although this has now been phased out. One recent theory is that children who became autistic subsequent to vaccination lacked sufficient quantities of an enzyme necessary to process thimerosal.

While denying the link between autism and thimerosal, vaccine manufacturers have discontinued the use of thimerosal in childhood vaccines, though physicians continued to use existing stock of vaccines with thimerosal for some years afterwards.  No reduction in autism diagnoses has been recorded as a result of this change.

=== MMR triple vaccine ===
{{main|MMR vaccine}}

A possible link between the measles, mumps and rubella ([[MMR vaccine|MMR]]) triple vaccine (which, containing live viruses, cannot be preserved by thimerosal) and autism was suggested in [[1998]], when [http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=9500320 Wakefield and colleagues] described a novel syndrome, [[autistic enterocolitis]], in a study published in the ''[[Lancet]]''.  The study of twelve children with bowel symptoms and regressive developmental disorders, mostly autism, has been strongly criticised for a number of weaknesses such as small sample size (albeit typical of such studies), funding sources and particularly subject selection: according to at least one source ([http://briandeer.com/mmr-lancet.htm report]) all subjects were already litigants and some were recruited before clincal approval was granted.

Further epidemiological studies were conducted with larger sample sizes (using medical records rather than clinical study) in a number of countries nations.  These report that there is no evidence of correlation or causality between thimerosal or MMR, and autism,[http://www.iom.edu/report.asp?id=20155].  It should be noted that it is not uncommon for early, widely-publicised studies to be contradicted by subsequent, more detailed research; one review, by Dr. John Ioannidis, found that a third of such studies are subsequently contradicted or seriously weakened by later research.

In [[2004]], 10 of the 13 authors of the original Wakefield study retracted the paper's interpretation, stating that the data were insufficient to establish a causal link between MMR vaccine and autism [http://briandeer.com/mmr/lancet-retraction.htm]. However failing to prove that link exists is not the same as proving that there is no link (since it is impossible to prove a negative) and the controversy continues.

==Intelligence and autism==
{{details|Intelligence tests and autism}}

Until recently, a majority of children diagnosed autistic were also believed to be mentally retarded. The term "mentally retarded" itself is debatable because this determination is based on [[IQ]] testing, which has its own set of controversies and detractors. A more accurate characterization would be to say that children who are diagnosed autistic may also have low IQ scores, which may or may not be meaningful in itself.

Autistic persons who have normal or high intelligence are often not diagnosed with autism, so the average IQ of the autistic community as a whole cannot be determined. Furthermore, anecdotal accounts of autistic children whose IQs have increased dozens of points over a relatively short period of time are not uncommon. It is unlikely that these increases correspond to an actual increase in intelligence. Instead, it has been suggested that like any children, the autistics may simply get better at taking IQ tests (the so-called practice effect). 

The view that mental retardation and autism go hand in hand is at odds with other findings, particularly the increasing recognition of so-called high functioning autistics and the recognition of [[Asperger]] syndrome as a type of autism.

Characteristics observed by some studies as being associated with [[gifted children]] at least appear to be analogous to those of autistic children:

* Some studies suggest that gifted children are more than twice as introverted as their peers [http://www.a-gifted-child.com/emotional.html].
* Gifted children have been characterized as having obsessive interests, as playing alone and enjoying solitude. They are also said to have prodigious memories and show intense reactions to noise, pain and frustration [http://www.jewishworldreview.com/cols/sowell110599.asp].
* According to some reports, gifted children have a higher than average propensity to allergies [http://www.sengifted.org/articles_counseling/Webb_MisdiagnosisAndDualDiagnosisOfGiftedChildren.shtml].

These findings have led to speculation that high intelligence and autism are related. Autistic author [[Temple Grandin]] speculates that [[genius]] itself "may be an abnormality" [http://www.onlineparadigm.com/archives/230-SP03_MH.pdf]

An alternative view is that autism and intelligence are unrelated; autistics with all levels of intelligence have been observed. According to this view, autistics with low intelligence would be more likely to be recognized and diagnosed as autistic. Those with normal to high intelligence might be better able to articulate their experiences (either verbally or through writing). These autistics might be labeled as high functioning regardless of their other neurological deficits.

==Prognosis for autistic children==

Children who are diagnosed with autism face a great range of outcomes.  Some are reported to have learned speech and/or writing, self-care, and social skills on their own.  Others experience an apparently miraculous "recovery" and begin behaving in a way that is generally indistinguishable from the way non-autistics behave, either for no apparent reason or, apparently, from a few simple alterations in diet.  Some become mainstreamed after years of hard work and intensive training.  Some develop slowly, but never become typical.  There are a few who never move beyond a level of functioning that society perceives as "low". Yet others are fairly typical during childhood and report becoming "more autistic" in adulthood.

It seems paradoxical that while some people see early intervention as crucial for autism, the prognosis is also most uncertain the younger the child is.  An idiosyncratic development path may be confused with a more severe disorder, and the child may "catch up" on his/her own.  Research indicates that the human mind and nervous system remains plastic for longer than originally thought, and autistic persons, like those with learning disabilities, have been known to develop all their lives.

There is broad concensus in the medical community to the effect that autistic behaviors can be improved through training, medical or educational interventions, though there is wide disagreement on what the right kinds of treatment are and what the appropriate objectives should be.

==Treatment choices==

It follows that there are a number of issues about the right way to deal with autism.  These issues complicate the choices that confront parents with children who have developmental delays and/or diagnosed as being on the "spectrum."  

It is particularly problematic that almost all approaches tried by parents have not been
validated by [[double-blind]] studies. Scientific rigor is of particular significance in studying a disorder such as autism given that its diagnosis is based on the subjective observation of certain behaviors, not on objective metrics such as genetic tests.

In many cases any long-term consequences and
risks are unknown or have not been studied in depth. It is also believed that no approach
will work equally well for all autistic children.

===Discredited approaches===

The [[Bruno Bettelheim]] hypothesis that autistic children are the product of emotional abuse -- specifically, unsympathetic, emotionally distant "refrigerator mothers" -- has been discredited.  There is no evidence to support the idea that autistic children - as a group - have shut themselves in because their parents didn't give them enough love and attention. Bettelheim prescribed "parendectomy", i.e. removal of the parents. Given how sensitive and easily frustrated autistic children are, the potential damage caused by this approach cannot be understated.

===Behavioral interventions===

Several schools of thought exist about behavioral interventions to treat autism.  

The most prominent is Lovaas/[[Applied Behavioral Analysis]] (ABA), which involves training autistic children through intensive trials (40 hours a week is often recommended) and reinforcement of limited tasks that grow more complex over time.  A common method of [[conditioning]] used in ABA is that
of offering some food or a drink after successful completion of a request.
While this is a proven method for developing specific skills in children who do not respond to conventional reinforcement (e.g., parental approval), it is often criticized for being harsh, stringent, and not conducive to general skill-building. Its long-term
outcome is questioned, and it has been suggested that full-time pressure of this kind
can lead to [[posttraumatic stress disorder]], [[anxiety]] and [[depression]]. There is also
some controversy about its effectiveness. Original ABA studies looked promising,
but subsequent ones have not replicated their success fully. Furthermore, no [[double-blind]]
ABA studies have been conducted. Studies on ABA are often conducted by ABA advocates.

The Greenspan/DIR approach seeks to stabilize the child's environment and then taking his/her lead to create learning opportunities through "floor time" and related approaches.  While this has proven effective for children with strong sensory needs, the approach is often criticized for catering to the child's limitations rather than building strengths.

Other approaches pioneered by Marion Blank, Barry Kaufman, Arnold Miller, and others are less popular and known but have similar supporters and detractors.

===Drug therapy===

The benefits of drugs is widely disputed.  While anti-seizure medication is indicated for some children with seizures, many parents are opposed to using psychopharmacology to treat their children.  They point out that autistic people are not necessarily psychotic, particularly anxious, or depressed.  Many autistic people themselves are against the overprescription of [[neuroleptic]] drugs in autistic people to control behavior.  They have formed an organization called 
[http://www.dinahm.pwp.blueyonder.co.uk/  Autistic People Against Neuroleptic Abuse] to counter this phenomenon.

===Occupational, auditory, visual therapy===

&lt;!-- The controversy about these needs to be stated --&gt;

Developmental neurologists have noted that autistic children tend to be hyposensitive and/or hypersensitive to one or several sensory impressions, and that their gross and fine motor skills are usually impaired to varying degrees.  These are symptoms consistent with [[Sensory Integration Dysfunction]].

Pediatric [[occupational therapy]] has proven successful in helping autistic children deal more effectively with sensory impressions, use their senses more productively, and become more aware of their bodies.

Auditory therapies include the [[Tomatis]] and [[Berard]] schools and focus on training the child to use his/her sense of hearing more effectively.

Visual therapy, pioneered by Melvin Kaplan and others, employs prism lenses that distort the child's vision, forcing him/her to use his/her focal vision more productively.

===Biomedical intervention===

Some parents and medical professionals report improvements in the behavior of autistic children enrolled in restrictive diets, detoxification therapies, and a range of treatments, collectively known as [[biomedical intervention for autism biomedical intervention]].  These claims are hotly contested by most specialists doctors, some of whom believe that the failure of conventional medicine to address parental concerns, and the meager resources committed to scientific research, has led to autism becoming a magnet for [[quacks]] and [[charlatans]].

The premise for biomedical intervention is that certain neurological disorders are caused by environmental shocks that in turn compromise the children's gastrointestinal, immunological and neurological systems.  Based on this premise, what is often diagnosed as autism or PDD is a physiological syndrome that can and should be treated.  

This point of view is consistent with wider evidence that diet and nutrition can affect behavior generally, but there is no medical literature evidencing claims that autism can be cured. Some of the most prominent advocates of various therapies have autistic children who manifestly display serious behavioral difficulties.

There is plenty of anecdotal evidence to support biomedical intervention - most parents who try one or several therapies report some progress, and there are stories of children who have undergone these programs and become seemingly completely neurotypical, able to return to mainstream education. However, this evidence may be confounded by the dramatic improvements often seen in autistic children as they grow up, with or without such interventions. Hence the need for [[double-blind]] studies regarding treatments.

The use of high doses of [[vitamin B6]] with or without [[magnesium]] is very popular among parents. Some studies do validate its effectiveness; including some [[double-blind]] ones [http://www.autismwebsite.com/ari/treatment/b6studies.htm]. However, there appear to be some significant risks associated with high doses of vitamin B6, including [[peripheral neuropathy]]. Some people argue that vitamin B6 only helps children in the following groups:

* Those with nutritional deficiencies, which can benefit from [[multivitamins]] in general. (Autistic children are notoriously fussy eaters.)

* Those with [[vitamin B6 deficiency]] (related to [[seizures]].)

===Non-coercive approaches===

The [[autism rights movement]] has been criticized for promoting "doing nothing" 
about autism. While clearly anti-cure, autistic advocates have pointed out that
not forcing children to be something they are not is not equivalent to "letting
them do whatever they want" or not educating them.

Given how much autistic individuals appear to be prone to [[stress]], 
[[anxiety]], nervousness and self-doubt, a number of non-coercive approaches
have been proposed.

The Son-Rise program falls into this category, but it has a number of retractors.
For one, there is no scientific evidence to validate it, and it is promoted in
a way that seems to give a lot of unsubstantiated hope to parents. For example,
proponents of the Son-Rise program claim that children will "decide" to become 
non-autistic after accepting them for who they are and engaging them in play.
The program was started by the parents of Raun Kaufman, who is claimed to have
gone from being autistic to totally non-autistic. There are questions as to whether
it is true that Raun Kaufman was autistic as a child, and also about the claim
that "there is no trace" of his autism now. Overall, the goals of the Son-Rise
program (i.e. removing the autism completely) are questioned, as well as the
use of locked doors in order to keep children in the play area.

Economist [[Thomas Sowell]], author of ''The Einstein Syndrome'', is a major 
opponent of any form of "early intervention" for children with certain 
characteristics (whom he considers wrongly labeled autistic), i.e. those who appear to be intelligent, are able to understand spoken language, and have several engineers or musicians
as close family members. His observations are based on experiences with his
own son (a late talker) and various anecdotal accounts.
Sowell has been criticized for providing false hope, and there
are cases he himself documents in his book of parents who followed his advise
only to later find out that their children were not simply late talkers.

An approach for dealing with autism which involves reducing stressful sitations, and not trying
to force the autistic child to change into someone he is not, is proposed in ''The Self-Help Guide for Special Kids and Their Parents'' by Joan Matthews and James Williams. 
(James Williams is an autistic child who, with his mother's help, recounts much of his
experiences through examples of possible problems encountered by parents of autistic
children.) The approach recommends, for example, not forcing the child into a mainstreamed schooling situation too early; trying to understand the problems caused by hypersensitivity and
adapting to them; allowing the child to cope with stress by stimming; helping the child 
develop left-brain thinking; and so on. Joan Matthews is also very much opposed to ABA therapy. This approach is close to something that would be acceptable to autistic advocates. But it also has the danger of giving false hope to parents. What worked well for James Williams may not work equally well for everyone.

==The autism rights movement==

{{Details|Autism rights movement}}

Some autistic people have started to speak and/or write about their experience.  The use of the Internet has made it possible for autistics to present their perspective when they do not have the communication skills to do so offline. Even some mute autistics, such as [http://greg.quuxuum.org/journal/o_neill.html Jasmine O'Neill], and [http://www.autistics.us/library/ Amanda Baggs], write well and present a case for greater acceptance of autism.  These autistics sometimes say they do not desire a cure, but want more opportunities to use their skills and perceptions. The opinions expressed within the autism rights movement are often very controversial.

The position this movement considers most fundamental is the position that autism is not a disorder at all but simply a different way of being. They believe a cure for autism could destroy the original personality of the autistic person and replace them with a different ([[neurotypical]]) person. Websites such as [http://www.autistics.org Autistics.org], [http://www.aspiesforfreedom.com/ Aspies for freedom] and [http://www.graphictruth.com/ Graphic Truth] present this view. 

This movement has made ethical challenges to applied behavioral analysis (ABA) and [[Institutional Damage|mental institutions]]. In particular, heated controversy was sparked when [[Michelle Dawson]], an autistic person, autism researcher, and autism rights activist challenged ABA in Canada's supreme court. The movement strives to include autistic adults in autism societies and provide services for autistic adults. They also wish to challenge descriptions of autism that they consider to be pitiful, insulting, and/or incorrect.

==See also==

* [[List of autism-related topics]]
* [[A-CHAMP]]
* [[Autism]]
* [[Autism rights movement]]
* [[Aspies For Freedom]]
* [[Asperger's syndrome]]
* [[Autistic culture]]
* [[Chelation therapy]]
* [[Generation Rescue]]
* [[Mark Geier]]
* [[Neurodiversity]]
* [[Refrigerator mother]]
* [[Richard Deth]]

==External links==

===Autism rights movement===

* [http://users.1st.net/cibra/ 1st.net] - 'CIBRA: [[Children Injured by Restraints and Aversives]]'
* [http://www.ani.ac/ ANI.ac] - '[[Autism Network International]], an autistic-run self-help and advocacy organization for autistic people' 
* [http://home.att.net/~ascaris1/ ATT.net] - 'Autistic Advocacy: A repository for my articles, editorials, and questionable attempts at humor', Frank Klein
* [http://www.autcom.org/ AutCom.org] - [[Autism National Committee]]
* [http://www.autistics.org Autistics.org] - 'Autistics.org: The Real Voice of Autism' (esources by and for persons on the autistic spectrum)
* [http://www.gettingthetruthout.org/page001.html GettingTheTruthOut.org] (photographs and first-person writing, presenting the appearance and subjective experience of an autistic person, discussing ways in which her self-perception differs from what other see of her apparent condition)
* [http://www.isn.net/~jypsy/ ISN.net] - 'Oops.. Wrong Planet Syndrome'
:* [http://www.isn.net/~jypsy/AuSpin/ournames.htm ISN.net] - 'Our Names are Autism, Too', Janet Norman-Bain (September 11, 2004) 
* [http://www.jimsinclair.org/ JimSinclair.org] - [[Jim Sinclair]]* [http://home.netcom.com/~plimchoy/ NetCom.com] - 'Less Frustration -- the thing we all strive for'
* [http://neurodiversity.com NeuroDiversity.com] - 'neurodiversity.com: honoring the variety of human wiring'
* [http://www.sentex.net/~nexus23/naa_03.html Sentex.net] - 'No Autistics Allowed:  Explorations in Discrimination Against Autistics', [[Michelle Dawson]]
* [http://www.simplecomplexities.org/ SimpleComplexities.org] - 'Asperger's Syndrome World Community: The Nation of Asperocria' (autism rights community)
* [http://mjane.zolaweb.com ZolaWeb.com] - 'Feeling Stressed? For therapy, try making Teddy Bears!' Jane Meyerding

===Internet "autism rights movement" campaigns===

In the early [[2000s]], activist campaigns started over the Internet.
* In April 2000, [http://www.autistics.org Autistics.org] hosted an online counter-rally called [http://www.autistics.org/library/reply.html "Hear Our Voices"] to protest an autism rally in Washington D.C. called "Hear Their Silence" that they disagreed with.
* In [[2004]], a [http://www.isn.net/~jypsy/AuSpin/a2p2.htm Autistic Adults Picture Project] was started in response to similar projects started by parents that only include pictures of children.
* In September 2004, the [http://www.isn.net/~jypsy/AuSpin/ournames.htm "Our Names are Autism Too"] is a campaign that protested an article titled [http://www.asohalton.org/My%20Name%20is%20Autism.pdf "My Name is Autism"] that presented a view autism rights activists found insulting.
* In October 2004, the [http://www.isn.net/~jypsy/AuSpin/sig.html Signatures of Intolerance] campaign was started over controversy surrounding ABA in Canada.
* In 2004, the [http://www.neurodiversity.com/mothers_for_dignity.html Petition to Defend the Dignity of Autistic Citizens] was started to protest the use of insults to describe autism (such as "mad child disease").

===Groups for parents of autistic people===

* [http://maapservices.org/ MAAPServices.org] - 'The Source', MAAP Services for Autism and Asperger's Syndrome

===Research organizations on autism===

* [http://info.med.yale.edu/chldstdy/autism/pddinfo.html/ Yale.edu] - 
'Information About Pervasive Developmental Disorders' ([[Yale]]'s Pervasive Developmental Delay Clinic)
* [http://osiris.sunderland.ac.uk/autism/index.html Sunderland.ac.uk] - The Autism Research Unit at the [[University of Sunderland]], UK

===Behavioral therapies for autism===

* [http://www.lovaas.com/ Lovaas.com] - 'Lovaas Center for Early Intervention' (Dr. O. Ivar Lovaas, founder of [[Applied Behavioral Analysis]])
* [http://www.millermethod.org/ MillerMethod.com] - 'The Miller Method: for children with autism spectrum and severe learning disorderss', [[Arnold Miller]]
* [http://neurodiversity.com/library_index.html NeuroDiversity.com] - 'Library of the History of Autism Research, Behaviorism &amp; Psychiatry' (complete articles in html and pdf)
* [http://www.son-rise.org/ Son-Rise.org] - 'Autism Treatment Center of America', (founded by [[Barry Kaufman]])
* [http://www.stanleygreenspan.com/ StanleyGreenspan.com] - '[[Stanley I. Greenspan]], M.D.' (developer of the developmental, individual-difference, relationship-based model (DIR))

===Biomedical intervention resources===

* [http://www.autism.org/ Autism.org] - '[[Center for the Study of Autism]]' (founded by Bernard Rimland)
* [http://www.autismndi.com/ AutismNDI.com] - 'AutismNDI: [[Autism Network for Dietary Intervention]]'
* [http://www.autismwebsite.com/ari/index.htm/ AutismWebsite.com] - [[Autism Research Institute]] (founded by [[Bernard Rimland]])
* [http://www.cureautismnow.org/ CANFoundation] - [[Cure Autism Now]]

[[Category:Autism]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>