<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20080908085435|237029997" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="929970" pageid="929970" ns="0" title="Controversies in autism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2008-09-19T03:29:17Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Controversies in autism''' encompass the disagreement over the exact nature of [[autism]], its [[causes of autism|causes]] and manifestations.  Autism is considered to be a neurodevelopmental condition which manifests itself in markedly abnormal [[social interaction]], communication ability, and patterns of interests.  

The cause(s) of autism and the [[spectrum disorder|spectrum]] of [[pervasive developmental disorder]]s (PDDs) are either unknown or unclear.

==Epidemiology ==
{{details|Epidemiology of autism}}

There is uncertainty and controversy over whether the [[Incidence (epidemiology)|incidence]] of [[autism spectrum]] disorders (ASD) is actually increasing or if there simply is an increase in the number of reported cases and better diagnosis.

==Genetics==
{{details|Heritability of autism}}

There is evidence that autism has a genetic component,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | author = Dunham, Will | url = http://www.reuters.com/article/scienceNews/idUSN1623067120070219 | title = International study finds new autism genetic links |publisher = Reuters | date = 2007-02-19 | accessdate = 2008-02-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; and ongoing research focuses on finding the biomarkers that determine autistic [[phenotype]]s. One, as yet unproven theory is that there may be genes which contribute to a vulnerability to environmental triggers or have another role in the etiology of autism. 

Genetics is viewed as an underlying factor. However, while some parents of those with autism are progressively also being diagnosed on the autism spectrum, at least some autistic children have apparently [[neurotypical]] parents. This suggests to some that genetics are either not a necessary cause or that they don't play a part in all cases of ASD, although it could also mean that the gene(s) responsible may be recessive or a [[Mutation|spontaneous mutation]]. The spectrum of autistic disorders is notable for its significant [[gender]] disparity, with the incidence of autism in males greatly exceeding the incidence in females. Whilst this could argue against a genetic theory, it has also been argued that male brains may be more vulnerable during early development.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | author = Kimura, Doreen | date = 2002-05-13 | url = http://www.sciam.com/article.cfm?articleID=00018E9D-879D-1D06-8E49809EC588EEDF | title = Sex Differences in the Brain | publisher = Scientific American | accessdate = 2008-02-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Variations in the gene for [[Protein kinase|protein kinase C]] beta 1 (PRKCB1), a protein with an important role in [[brain]] function, may be associated with autism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release | url = http://www.news-medical.net/?id=11761 |title = Variations in the gene for protein kinase C beta 1 (PRKCB1) strongly associated with autism |date = 2005-07-18 | publisher = Medical Research News | accessdate = 2008-02-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Vaccines==
Several controversial claims have been made with regard to [[autism]] and [[vaccinations]], leading notably to the [[MMR vaccine controversy]] and the [[thiomersal controversy]]. None of these claims have been verified.

==Intelligence==
[[Scientific literature]] suggests that mainstream [[Intelligence quotient|intelligence tests]] do not accurately measure the cognitive abilities of autistics because autistic cognition differs from typical [[human cognition]]. According to the [[Association for Psychological Science]], a 2007 study by Dawson et al. suggested that [[Raven's Progressive Matrices]] (RPM), a test of abstract reasoning, may be a better indicator of intelligence for autistic children than the more commonly used [[Wechsler Intelligence Scale for Children]] (WISC).  Researchers suspected that the WISC relied too heavily on language to be an accurate measure of intelligence for autistics.  They administered both tests to neurotypical and autistic children.  The neurotypical children scored similarly on both tests, but the autistic children fared far better on the RPM than on the WISC.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url =http://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2007/08/070803151245.htm | title = The Matrix of Autism | publisher = Science Daily | date = 2007-08-05| accssdate = 2008-01-07 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

This study contradicts the widely held assumption that autistics suffer from cognitive deficits in high-level [[Abstraction|abstract thinking]].  The RPM is considered a "paradigmatic measure" of abstract, general and fluid reasoning, which is precisely the ability autistics have been presumed to lack. This theory would predict that autistics fare dramatically worse on the RPM than on other measures of intelligence, whereas Dawson et al. showed that the opposite is true.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url =http://sciencenow.sciencemag.org/cgi/content/full/2006/220/1?eaf | title = The Case of Mistaken IQ | publisher = ScienceNow| date=  2006-02-20| accessdate = 2007-10-24 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Dawson M, Soulières I, Gernsbacher MA, Mottron L (2007).
"The Level and Nature of Autistic Intelligence". ''Psychological Science'' 18 (8), 657–662. &lt;/ref&gt;

A recent review questioned the validity of IQ testing of autistic people.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author= Edelson, MG |year=2006 |title= Are the majority of children with autism mentally retarded? a systematic evaluation of the data |journal= Focus Autism Other Dev Disabl |volume=21 |issue=2 |pages=66–83 |url=http://www.willamette.edu/dept/comm/reprint/edelson/ |accessdate=2007-04-15 |doi= 10.1177/10883576060210020301}}&lt;/ref&gt; As those with normal or [[Genius|high intelligence]] are less likely to be diagnosed with autism, the average IQ of the [[autistic community]] as a whole may not be able to be reliably determined. Furthermore, anecdotal accounts of autistic children whose IQ scores have increased dozens of points over a relatively short period of time are not uncommon. Some of these cases, however, may not correspond to an increase in actual intelligence; perhaps, as with neurotypical children, children with autism may simply get better at taking IQ tests (the so-called practice effect).

== Joint attention ==
Joint attention refers to a cluster of behaviors in one of two classes: a child's response to someone else pointing or shifting eye gaze, and a child seeking another's attention. Many joint-attention behaviors differ in children with autism: for example, [[eye contact]] is relatively absent or atypical.&lt;ref name=Bruinsma&gt;{{cite journal |journal= Ment Retard Dev Disabil Res Rev |date=2004 |volume=10 |issue=3 |pages=169–75 |title= Joint attention and children with autism: a review of the literature |author= Bruinsma Y, Koegel RL, Koegel LK |doi=10.1002/mrdd.20036 |pmid=15611988}}&lt;/ref&gt; These joint attention skills seem to be prerequisites for functional language development.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |journal=Pediatrics |date=2007 |volume=120 |issue=5 |pages=1183–215 |title= Identification and evaluation of children with autism spectrum disorders |author= Johnson CP, Myers SM, Council on Children with Disabilities |doi=10.1542/peds.2007-2361 |pmid=17967920 |url=http://pediatrics.aappublications.org/cgi/content/full/120/5/1183 |laysummary=http://aap.org/advocacy/releases/oct07autism.htm |laysource=AAP |laydate=2007-10-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; It has also been hypothesized that autistic children initiate joint attention perhaps even as often as their neurotypical peers, albeit in atypical ways, and that a parent should join an autistic child's focus of attention and try harder to notice the child's atypical requests for attention rather than insist on typical behavior from the child. The empirical data supporting the latter hypothesis has been questioned.&lt;ref&gt;Joint attention controversy:
* {{cite journal |journal= Child Dev Perspect |date=2008 |volume=2 |issue=1 |pages=38–45 |title= Why does joint attention look atypical in autism? |author= Gernsbacher MA, Stevenson JL, Khandakar S, Goldsmith HH |doi=10.1111/j.1750-8606.2008.00039.x}}
* {{cite journal |journal= Child Dev Perspect |date=2008 |volume=2 |issue=1 |pages=46–8 |title= On why joint attention  might look atypical in autism: a case for a strong policy statement but more nuanced empirical story |author= Burack JA, Russo N |doi=10.1111/j.1750-8606.2008.00040.x}}
* {{cite journal |journal= Child Dev Perspect |date=2008 |volume=2 |issue=1 |pages=49–52 |title= Autistics’ atypical joint attention: policy implications and empirical nuance |author= Gernsbacher MA, Stevenson JL, Khandakar S, Goldsmith HH |doi=10.1111/j.1750-8606.2008.00041.x}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

== References ==
{{reflist}}

{{pervasive developmental disorders}}

[[Category:Autism]]
[[Category:Medical controversies]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>