<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20091021155157|321210804" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="929970" pageid="929970" ns="0" title="Controversies in autism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2009-10-21T16:19:17Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Controversies in autism''' encompass the disagreement over the exact nature of [[autism]], its [[causes of autism|causes]] and manifestations.  Autism is considered to be a neurodevelopmental condition which manifests itself in markedly abnormal [[social interaction]], communication ability, and patterns of interests.  

The cause(s) of autism and the [[spectrum disorder|spectrum]] of [[pervasive developmental disorder]]s (PDDs) are either unknown or unclear.

==Epidemiology ==
{{details|Epidemiology of autism}}

There is uncertainty and controversy over whether the [[Incidence (epidemiology)|incidence]] of [[autism spectrum]] disorders (ASD) is actually increasing or if there simply is an increase in the number of reported cases and better diagnosis.

==Genetics==
{{details|Heritability of autism}}

There is evidence that autism has a genetic component,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | author = Dunham, Will | url = http://www.reuters.com/article/scienceNews/idUSN1623067120070219 | title = International study finds new autism genetic links |publisher = Reuters | date = 2007-02-19 | accessdate = 2008-02-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; and ongoing research focuses on finding the biomarkers that determine autistic [[phenotype]]s. One, as yet unproven theory is that there may be genes which contribute to a vulnerability to environmental triggers or have another role in the etiology of autism. 

Genetics is viewed as an underlying factor. However, while some parents of those with autism are progressively also being diagnosed on the autism spectrum, at least some autistic children have apparently [[neurotypical]] parents. This suggests to some that genetics are either not a necessary cause or that they don't play a part in all cases of ASD, although it could also mean that the gene(s) responsible may be recessive or a [[Mutation|spontaneous mutation]]. The spectrum of autistic disorders is notable for its significant [[gender]] disparity, with the incidence of autism in males greatly exceeding the incidence in females. Whilst this could be evidence for a genetic theory, it has also been argued that male brains may be more vulnerable during early development.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | author = Kimura, Doreen | date = 2002-05-13 | url = http://www.sciam.com/article.cfm?articleID=00018E9D-879D-1D06-8E49809EC588EEDF | title = Sex Differences in the Brain | publisher = Scientific American | accessdate = 2008-02-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Vaccines==
Several controversial claims have been made with regard to [[autism]] and [[vaccinations]], leading notably to the [[MMR vaccine controversy]], the [[thiomersal controversy]], and the theory of [[vaccine overload]]. These theories lack scientific evidence and are biologically implausible.&lt;ref&gt;Vaccines and autism:
*{{cite journal |author= Gerber JS, Offit PA |title= Vaccines and autism: a tale of shifting hypotheses |journal= Clin Infect Dis |volume=48 |issue=4 |pages=456–61 |year=2009 |pmid=19128068 |doi=10.1086/596476 |url=http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/doi/full/10.1086/596476 |laysummary=http://www.idsociety.org/Content.aspx?id=13336 |laysource=IDSA |laydate=2009-01-30}}
*{{cite journal |author=Gross L |title=A broken trust: lessons from the vaccine–autism wars |journal=PLoS Biol |volume=7 |issue=5 |pages=e1000114 |year=2009 |pmid=19478850 |doi=10.1371/journal.pbio.1000114 |url=http://www.plosbiology.org/article/info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.1000114 |pmc=2682483 }}
&lt;/ref&gt;

==Intelligence==

The fraction of autistic individuals who also meet criteria for mental retardation has been reported as anywhere from 25% to 70%, a wide variation illustrating the difficulty of assessing autistic intelligence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |chapter= Learning in autism |author= Dawson M, Mottron L, Gernsbacher MA |title= Learning and Memory: A Comprehensive Reference |volume=2 |pages=759–72 |editor= Byrne JH (ed.-in-chief), Roediger HL III (vol. ed.) |publisher= Academic Press |year=2008 |doi=10.1016/B978-012370509-9.00152-2 |isbn=0-12-370504-5 |chapterurl=http://psych.wisc.edu/lang/pdf/Dawson_AutisticLearning.pdf |accessdate=2008-07-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; For ASD other than autism, the association with mental retardation is much weaker.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author= Chakrabarti S, Fombonne E |title= Pervasive developmental disorders in preschool children |journal=JAMA |year=2001 |volume=285 |issue=24 |pages=3093–9 |pmid=11427137 |url=http://jama.ama-assn.org/cgi/content/full/285/24/3093 |doi= 10.1001/jama.285.24.3093}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A 2007 study suggested that [[Raven's Progressive Matrices]] (RPM), a test of abstract reasoning, may be a better indicator of intelligence for autistic children than the more commonly used [[Wechsler Intelligence Scale for Children]] (WISC). Researchers suspected that the WISC relied too heavily on language to be an accurate measure of intelligence for autistics. The neurotypical children scored similarly on both tests, but the autistic children fared far better on the RPM than on the WISC. The RPM measures abstract, general and fluid reasoning, an ability autistics have been presumed to lack.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author= Dawson M, Soulières I, Gernsbacher MA, Mottron L |title= The level and nature of autistic intelligence |journal= Psychol Sci |volume=18 |issue=8 |pages=657–62 |year=2007 |pmid=17680932 |doi=10.1111/j.1467-9280.2007.01954.x |laysummary=http://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2007/08/070803151245.htm |laysource=ScienceDaily |laydate=2007-08-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; A 2008 study found a similar effect, but to a much lesser degree and only for individuals with Wechsler IQs less than 85.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author= Bölte S, Dziobek I, Poustka F |title= Brief report: the level and nature of autistic intelligence revisited |journal= J Autism Dev Disord |volume= |issue= |pages= |year=2008 |pmid=19052857 |doi=10.1007/s10803-008-0667-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A 2006 review questioned the common assumption that most children with autism are mentally retarded.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author= Edelson, MG |year=2006 |title= Are the majority of children with autism mentally retarded? a systematic evaluation of the data |journal= Focus Autism Other Dev Disabl |volume=21 |issue=2 |pages=66–83 |url=http://www.willamette.edu/dept/comm/reprint/edelson/ |accessdate=2007-04-15 |doi= 10.1177/10883576060210020301}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Joint attention ==
Joint attention refers to a cluster of behaviors in one of two classes: a child's response to someone else pointing or shifting eye gaze, and a child seeking another's attention. Many joint-attention behaviors differ in children with autism: for example, [[eye contact]] is relatively absent or atypical.&lt;ref name=Bruinsma&gt;{{cite journal |journal= Ment Retard Dev Disabil Res Rev |date=2004 |volume=10 |issue=3 |pages=169–75 |title= Joint attention and children with autism: a review of the literature |author= Bruinsma Y, Koegel RL, Koegel LK |doi=10.1002/mrdd.20036 |pmid=15611988}}&lt;/ref&gt; These joint attention skills seem to be prerequisites for functional language development.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |journal=Pediatrics |date=2007 |volume=120 |issue=5 |pages=1183–215 |title= Identification and evaluation of children with autism spectrum disorders |author= Johnson CP, Myers SM, Council on Children with Disabilities |doi=10.1542/peds.2007-2361 |pmid=17967920 |url=http://pediatrics.aappublications.org/cgi/content/full/120/5/1183 |laysummary=http://aap.org/advocacy/releases/oct07autism.htm |laysource=AAP |laydate=2007-10-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; It has also been hypothesized that autistic children initiate joint attention perhaps even as often as their neurotypical peers, albeit in atypical ways, and that a parent should join an autistic child's focus of attention and try harder to notice the child's atypical requests for attention rather than insist on typical behavior from the child. The empirical data supporting the latter hypothesis has been questioned.&lt;ref&gt;Joint attention controversy:
* {{cite journal |journal= Child Dev Perspect |date=2008 |volume=2 |issue=1 |pages=38–45 |title= Why does joint attention look atypical in autism? |author= Gernsbacher MA, Stevenson JL, Khandakar S, Goldsmith HH |doi=10.1111/j.1750-8606.2008.00039.x}}
* {{cite journal |journal= Child Dev Perspect |date=2008 |volume=2 |issue=1 |pages=46–8 |title= On why joint attention  might look atypical in autism: a case for a strong policy statement but more nuanced empirical story |author= Burack JA, Russo N |doi=10.1111/j.1750-8606.2008.00040.x}}
* {{cite journal |journal= Child Dev Perspect |date=2008 |volume=2 |issue=1 |pages=49–52 |title= Autistics’ atypical joint attention: policy implications and empirical nuance |author= Gernsbacher MA, Stevenson JL, Khandakar S, Goldsmith HH |doi=10.1111/j.1750-8606.2008.00041.x}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

== References ==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

{{pervasive developmental disorders}}

[[Category:Autism]]
[[Category:Medical controversies]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>