<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20140719051035|617542325" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="5312771" pageid="5312771" ns="0" title="Social integration"><revisions><rev timestamp="2014-10-07T10:52:30Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{multiple issues|
{{Expert-subject|Sociology|reason=contains almost no relevant research|date=April 2013}}
{{Refimprove|date=July 2010}}
{{essay-like|date=May 2011}}
}}
'''Social integration '''is the set of arrangements adopted by the society and the group to accept a new member among them, and to facilitate this acceptance process. These arrangements are taken on different levels since social integration cannot succeed on one level and fail on another level. Example: education cannot be ensured without ensuring mechanism for social promotion. And neither education, nor work can be ensured without ensuring in front of the law, etc.   In tolerant and open societies, members of minority groups can often use social integration to gain full access to the opportunities, rights and services available to the members of the [[mainstream]] of society. Major agents of social integration are cultural institutions such as churches and civic organizations. Mass media content also performs a social integration function in mass societies.

==Definition==
The term "social integration" first came into use in the work of French sociologist [[Émile Durkheim|Emile Durkheim]]. He wanted to understand why rates of suicide were higher in some social classes than others. Durkhiem believed that [[society]] exerted a powerful force on individuals. He concluded that a people's beliefs, values, and norms make up a collective consciousnesss, a shared way of understanding each other and the world.

==Uses==
In the emerging world of [[social networking]] applications on the internet, social integration is a term that can be considered when members are being transparent in all of their various work, personal, faith and local community interactions.{{Citation needed|date=November 2009}}

A 2012 research review found that [[Working class|working-class]] students were less socially integrated than middle-class students at university.&lt;ref&gt;Rubin, M. (2012). Social class differences in social integration among students in higher education: A meta-analysis and recommendations for future research. ''Journal of Diversity in Higher Education, 5, 22-38.''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://sites.google.com/site/markrubinsocialpsychresearch/working-class-students-are-left-out-at-university Working-Class Students are Left Out at University] Mark Rubin's Social Psychology Research, retrieved 29 March 2013&lt;/ref&gt;

Recent research also shows that immigrants should be independent and proactive in order to achieve better social integration in their host countries.&lt;ref&gt;Rubin, M., Watt, S. E., &amp; Ramelli, M. (2012). Immigrants’ social integration as a function of approach-avoidance orientation and problem-solving style. International Journal of Intercultural Relations, 36, 498-505. http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ijintrel.2011.12.009&lt;/ref&gt; For further information, see here.&lt;ref&gt;https://sites.google.com/site/markrubinsocialpsychresearch/immigrants-should-be-independent-and-proactive-to-achieve-better-social-integration&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Sami,N.,Habib, S.E.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[United Nations]] has a Social Integration Branch, which is a part of the [[Division for Social Policy and Development]] (Department of Economic and Social Affairs). It also issues a quarterly publication named ''Bulletin on Social Integration Policies''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.un.org/esa/socdev/sib/ |title=UNDESA - Division for Social Policy and Development (DSPD) |publisher=Un.org |date= |accessdate=2014-06-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; The UN Alliance of Civilizations&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unaoc.org/%20Official%20Webpage%20 ]{{dead link|date=June 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; initiative works on Migration and Integration as a key for intercultural understanding. An Online Community on Migration and Integration&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.unaoc.org/communities/migrationintegration%20 |title=Migration &amp; Integration &amp;#124; Building Inclusive Societies |publisher=Unaoc.org |date=2012-03-15 |accessdate=2014-06-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; shows Good Practices from around the world.

==See also==
*[[Acculturation]]
*[[Cultural assimilation]]
*[[Cultural diversity]]
*[[Jim Crow laws|Jim Crow Laws (Racial Segregation and Discrimination)]]
*[[Suffrage]]
*[[TPI-theory]]
*''[[Menace in Europe: Why the Continent's Crisis Is America's, Too]]'', a book by [[Claire Berlinski]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}
{{Discrimination}}
[[Category:Cultural assimilation]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>