<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20151019112347|686483169" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="5312771" pageid="5312771" ns="0" title="Social integration"><revisions><rev timestamp="2015-11-09T02:58:28Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Expert-subject|Sociology|reason=needs more relevant research|date=April 2013}}

'''Social integration''' can be seen as a dynamic and structured process in which all members participate in dialogue to achieve and maintain peaceful social relations. Social integration does not mean [[forced assimilation]].

Social integration is focused on the need to move toward a safe, stable and [[just society]] by mending conditions of [[social disintegration]] and [[social exclusion]] - social fragmentation, exclusion and [[Polarization (politics)|polarization]]; and by expanding and strengthening conditions of social integration - towards peaceful social relations of coexistence, collaboration and [[Group cohesiveness|cohesion]].&lt;ref&gt;"PeaceDialogue." UN News Center. UN, n.d. Web. 02 Jan. 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Examples==

In many instances education is used as a mechanism for social promotion. Neither education nor work can be ensured without a form of law. In relation to tolerant and open societies, members of minority groups  often use social integration to gain full access to the opportunities, rights and services available to the members of the [[mainstream]] of society with cultural institutions such as churches and civic organizations. Mass media content also performs a social integration function in mass societies.

The term "social integration" first came into use in the work of French sociologist [[Émile Durkheim]]. He wanted to understand why rates of suicide were higher in some social classes than others. Durkheim believed that [[society]] exerted a powerful force on individuals. He concluded that a people's beliefs, values, and norms make up a collective consciousness, a shared way of understanding each other and the world.

==Uses==
In the emerging world of [[social networking]] applications on the internet, social integration is a term that can be considered when members are being transparent in all of their various work, personal, faith and local community interactions.{{Citation needed|date=November 2009}}

A 2012 research review found that [[Working class|working-class]] students were less socially integrated than middle-class students at university.&lt;ref&gt;Rubin, M. (2012). Social class differences in social integration among students in higher education: A meta-analysis and recommendations for future research. ''Journal of Diversity in Higher Education, 5, 22-38.''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://sites.google.com/site/markrubinsocialpsychresearch/working-class-students-are-left-out-at-university Working-Class Students are Left Out at University] Mark Rubin's Social Psychology Research, retrieved 29 March 2013&lt;/ref&gt;

Recent research also shows that immigrants should be independent and proactive in order to achieve better social integration in their host countries.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Rubin | first1 = M. | last2 = Watt | first2 = S. E. | last3 = Ramelli | first3 = M. | year = 2012 | title = Immigrants' social integration as a function of approach-avoidance orientation and problem-solving style | url = | journal = International Journal of Intercultural Relations | volume = 36 | issue = | pages = 498–505 | doi = 10.1016/j.ijintrel.2011.12.009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; For further information, see here.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://sites.google.com/site/markrubinsocialpsychresearch/immigrants-should-be-independent-and-proactive-to-achieve-better-social-integration|title=Immigrants Should Be Independent and Proactive to Achieve Better Social Integration - Mark Rubin's Social Psychology Research|work=google.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Sami,N.,Habib, S.E.&lt;/ref&gt;

from a demographic and cultural standpoint, recent longitudinal studies suggest that social isolation or integration has shown to increase in older Spanish individuals, especially those whom may be suffering from neurocognitive disorders such as dementia and overall cognitive decline.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Zunzunegui|first1=et, al.|title=Social Networks, Social Integration, and Social Engagement Determine Cognitive Decline in Community-dwelling Spanish Older Adults|url=http://psychsocgerontology.oxfordjournals.org/content/58/2/S93.full.pdf+html|website=www.psychcgerontology.oxfordjournals.org|accessdate=2015-07-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[United Nations]] has a Social Integration Branch, which is a part of the [[Division for Social Policy and Development]] (Department of Economic and Social Affairs). It also issues a quarterly publication named ''Bulletin on Social Integration Policies''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.un.org/esa/socdev/sib/ |title=UNDESA - Division for Social Policy and Development (DSPD) |publisher=Un.org |date= |accessdate=2014-06-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; The UN Alliance of Civilizations&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unaoc.org/%20Official%20Webpage%20 ]{{dead link|date=June 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; initiative works on Migration and Integration as a key for intercultural understanding. An Online Community on Migration and Integration&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.unaoc.org/communities/migrationintegration%20 |title=Migration &amp; Integration &amp;#124; Building Inclusive Societies |publisher=Unaoc.org |date=2012-03-15 |accessdate=2014-06-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; shows Good Practices from around the world.

==See also==
*[[Acculturation]]
*[[Cultural assimilation]]
*[[Cultural diversity]]
*[[Jim Crow laws|Jim Crow Laws (Racial Segregation and Discrimination)]]
*[[Social exclusion]]
*[[Suffrage]]
*[[TPI-theory]]
*''[[Menace in Europe: Why the Continent's Crisis Is America's, Too]]'', a book by [[Claire Berlinski]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{Discrimination}}
{{Émile Durkheim}}

[[Category:Cultural assimilation]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>