<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20120923154239|514176571" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="5312771" pageid="5312771" ns="0" title="Social integration"><revisions><rev timestamp="2012-11-12T21:12:39Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Ref improve|date=July 2010}}
  {{essay-like|date=May 2011}}
'''Social integration''', in [[sociology]] and other [[social sciences]], is the movement of minority groups such as [[ethnic minorities]], refugees and underprivileged sections of a [[society]] into the mainstream of societies. Social integration requires proficiency in an accepted common language of the society, acceptance of the laws of the society and adoption of a common set of values of the society. It does not require assimilation and it does not require persons to give up all of their culture, but it may require to forgo some aspects of their culture which are inconsistent with the laws and values of the society. In tolerant and open societies, members of minority groups can often use social integration to gain full access to the opportunities, rights and services available to the members of the mainstream of society.

In the emerging world of [[social networking]] applications on the internet, social integration is a term that can be considered when members are being transparent in all of their various work, personal, faith and local community interactions.{{Citation needed|date=November 2009}}

Recent research has shown that working-class students are less socially integrated than middle-class students at university.&lt;ref&gt;Rubin, M. (2012). Social class differences in social integration among students in higher education: A meta-analysis and recommendations for future research. ''Journal of Diversity in Higher Education, 5, 22-38.''&lt;/ref&gt; For further information, see [http://sites.google.com/site/markrubinsocialpsychresearch/working-class-students-are-left-out-at-university here].

Recent research also shows that immigrants should be independent and proactive in order to achieve better social integration in their host countries.&lt;ref&gt;Rubin, M., Watt, S. E., &amp; Ramelli, M. (in press). Immigrants’ social integration as a function of approach-avoidance orientation and problem-solving style. International Journal of Intercultural Relations. http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ijintrel.2011.12.009&lt;/ref&gt; For further information, see [https://sites.google.com/site/markrubinsocialpsychresearch/immigrants-should-be-independent-and-proactive-to-achieve-better-social-integration here].

The [[United Nations]] has a Social Integration Branch, which is a part of the [[Division for Social Policy and Development]] (Department of Economic and Social Affairs). It also issues a quarterly publication named ''Bulletin on Social Integration Policies''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.un.org/esa/socdev/sib/]&lt;/ref&gt; The UN Alliance of Civilizations&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unaoc.org/%20Official%20Webpage%20]&lt;/ref&gt; initiative works on Migration and Integration as a key for intercultural understanding. An Online Community on Migration and Integration&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unaoc.org/communities/migrationintegration%20]&lt;/ref&gt; shows Good Practices from around the world.

Examples for socially integrated societies will be [[United States]], [[Canada]], [[Singapore]], [[Israel]], and others.{{fact|date=September 2012}}
==References==
{{Reflist}}

==See also==
*[[Cultural assimilation]]
*[[Acculturation]]
*[[TPI-theory]]

[[Category:Cultural assimilation]]

[[da:Social integration]]
[[de:Integration (Soziologie)]]
[[fr:Intégration (sociologie)]]
[[it:Integrazione (scienze sociali)]]
[[nl:Integratie (sociologie)]]
[[no:Sosial integrering]]
[[pl:Integracja społeczna]]
[[ru:Социальная интеграция]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>