<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20161118211532|750286248" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="200977" pageid="200977" ns="0" title="Sexual objectification"><revisions><rev timestamp="2016-11-18T21:36:11Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Redirect|Sex object}}
'''Sexual objectification''' is the act of treating a person as an instrument of [[sexual pleasure]]. [[Objectification]] more broadly means treating a person as a [[commodity]] or an object without regard to their personality or [[dignity]]. Objectification is most commonly examined at the level of a society, but can also refer to the behavior of individuals.

The concept of sexual objectification and, in particular, the objectification of women, is an important idea in feminist theory and psychological theories derived from feminism. Many feminists regard sexual objectification as deplorable and as playing an important role in gender inequality. However, some social commentators argue that some modern women objectify themselves as an expression of their empowerment.{{citation needed|date=July 2016}}

==Sexual objectification of women==
Female sexual objectification by a male involves a woman being viewed primarily as an object of male sexual desire, rather than as a whole person.&lt;ref name=Barry&gt;{{cite book |last=Barry |first=Kathleen |contribution=Pornography: the ideoloy of cultural sadism |editor-last=Barry |editor-first=Kathleen |title=Female sexual slavery |page=247 |publisher=NYU Press |location=New York London |year=1984 |isbn=978-0-8147-1069-2 |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=LeMoncheck&gt;{{cite book |last=LeMoncheck |first=Linda |contribution=I only do it for the money: pornography, prostitution, and the business of sex |editor-last=LeMoncheck |editor-first=Linda |title=Loose women, lecherous men a feminist philosophy of sex |page=133 |publisher=Oxford University Press |location=New York, New York |year=1997 |isbn=978-0-19-510556-8 |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Szymanski |first1=Dawn M. |last2=Moffitt |first2=Lauren B. |last3=Carr |first3=Erika R. |title=Sexual objectification of women: advances to theory and research |journal=[[The Counseling Psychologist]] |volume=39 |issue=1 |pages=6–38 |publisher=[[SAGE Publications|Sage]] |doi=10.1177/0011000010378402 |date=January 2011 |url=http://dx.doi.org/10.1177/0011000010378402 |ref=harv |postscript=.}} [http://www.apa.org/education/ce/sexual-objectification.pdf Pdf.]&lt;/ref&gt;  Although opinions differ as to which situations are objectionable, some feminists&lt;ref name=Jhally&gt;{{cite AV media |last=Jhally |first=Sut (director) |author-link=Sut Jhally |date=1997 |title=Dreamworlds II: desire, sex, power in music |medium=Documentary |location=USA |publisher=[[Media Education Foundation]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; see objectification of women taking place in the sexually oriented depictions of women in advertising and media, women being portrayed as weak or submissive through [[pornography]], images in more mainstream [[Published media|media]] such as [[advertising]] and [[art]], [[Striptease|stripping]] and [[prostitution]], men brazenly evaluating or judging women sexually or aesthetically in public spaces and events, such as beauty contests, and the presumed need for [[cosmetic surgery]], particularly breast enlargement and [[labiaplasty]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Yeung |first=Peter |title=The female artists reclaiming their bodies |url=http://www.dazeddigital.com/artsandculture/article/22316/1/the-female-artists-reclaiming-their-bodies |work=Dazed |publisher=Dazed Digital |date=December 2014 |quote=It is through this prism of patriarchal control that much exploitation of women has been enacted: commonly phallocentric portraiture has been used to permeate the rest of society...The fetishisation of womens’ bodies and their regular reduction to breasts is something that New York artist Cindy Hinant is acutely aware of.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Objectification in the media can range from subtle forms, such as the lack of main female characters, to very explicit forms such as highly [[Sexualization|sexualized]] dialogue and provocatively dressed female characters.

Some feminists and psychologists&lt;ref name=fredrickson2&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Fredrickson |first1=Barbara L. |last2=Roberts |first2=Tomi-Ann |title=Objectification theory: toward understanding women's lived experiences and mental health risks |journal=[[Psychology of Women Quarterly]] |volume=21 |issue=2 |pages=173–206 |publisher=[[SAGE Publications|Sage]] |doi=10.1111/j.1471-6402.1997.tb00108.x |date=June 1997 |url=http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1471-6402.1997.tb00108.x |ref=harv |postscript=.}}&lt;/ref&gt; argue that sexual objectification can lead to negative psychological effects including [[eating disorder]]s, [[depression (mood)|depression]] and [[sexual dysfunction]], and can give women negative [[self-image]]s because of the belief that their intelligence and competence are currently not being, nor will ever be, acknowledged by society.&lt;ref name=:0 /&gt; Some have argued that the feminist movement itself has contributed to the problem of the sexual objectification of women by pushing for an end to the so-called oppressive patriarchal marriage and promoting "free" love (i.e. women choosing to have non-reproductive sex outside of marriage and for their own pleasure).&lt;ref name=fredrickson2 /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Abrams |first1=Dominic |last2=Hogg |first2=Michael A. |contribution=Collective identity: group membership and self-conception |editor-last1=Brewer |editor-first1=Marilynn B. |editor-last2=Hewstone |editor-first2=Miles |editor-link1=Marilynn B. Brewer |title=Self and social identity |page=167 |publisher=Blackwell Publishing |location=Malden, Massachusetts |series=Perspectives on Social Psychology |year=2004 |isbn=978-1-4051-1069-3 |ref=harv |postscript=.}} [https://books.google.com/?id=aGhvm-QH1yEC&amp;pg=RA1-PA136&amp;lpg=RA1-PA136&amp;dq=Fredrickson+and+Roberts Pdf.]&lt;/ref&gt; Such promotion has increased the average number of lifetime sexual partners for men, which in turn has caused some men to devalue sex, which in turn has caused men who objectify women to devalue women.{{dubious|date=February 2013}} One study found that men exposed to media content in which women were objectified were more likely to accept those behaviors than men who were exposed to content where women were not objectified.&lt;ref&gt;Galdi, Silvia, Anne Maass, and Mara Cadinu. "Objectifying Media: Their Effect On Gender Role Norms And Sexual Harassment Of Women." ''Psychology Of Women Quarterly'' 38.3 (2014): 398-413. ''SocINDEX with Full Text''. Web. 19 Apr. 2016.&lt;/ref&gt; How objectification has affected women and society in general is a topic of academic debate, with some saying girls' understanding of the importance of appearance in society may contribute to feelings of [[fear]], [[shame]], and [[disgust]] during the transition to womanhood,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Lee |first=Janet |title=Menarche and the (hetero)sexualization of the female body |journal=[[Gender &amp; Society]] |volume=8 |issue=3 |pages=343–362 |publisher=[[SAGE Publications|Sage]] |doi=10.1177/089124394008003004 |date=September 1994 |url=http://dx.doi.org/10.1177/089124394008003004 |ref=harv |postscript=.}}&lt;/ref&gt; and others saying that young women are especially susceptible to objectification, as they are often taught that [[Power (sociology)|power]], [[respect]], and [[wealth]] can be derived from one's outward appearance.&lt;ref name=apareport&gt;{{Cite report |last1=American Psychological Association |first1=(APA) |title=Report of the American Psychological Association task force on the sexualization of girls, executive summary |journal=[[American Psychological Association]] |location=Washington, DC |year=2010 |url=http://www.apa.org/pi/women/programs/girls/report-full.pdf |access-date=19 February 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Pro-feminist cultural critics such as [[Robert Jensen]] and [[Sut Jhally]] accuse [[mass media]] and advertising of promoting the objectification of women to help promote goods and services.&lt;ref name=Jhally /&gt;&lt;ref name=Jensen&gt;{{cite book |last=Jensen |first=Robert |author-link=Robert Jensen |contribution=Using pornography |editor-last1=Dines |editor-first1=Gail |editor-last2=Jensen |editor-first2=Robert |editor-last3=Russo |editor-first3=Ann |editor-link1=Gail Dines |editor-link2=Robert Jensen |title=Pornography: the production and consumption of inequality |page=133 |publisher=Oxford University Press |location=New York, New York |year=1997 |isbn=978-0-19-510556-8 |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Frith&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Frith |first1=Katherine |last2=Shaw |first2=Ping |last3=Cheng |first3=Hong |title=The construction of beauty: a cross-cultural analysis of women's magazine advertising |journal=[[Journal of Communication]] |volume=55 |issue=1 |pages=56–70 |publisher=[[Wiley-Blackwell|Wiley]] |doi=10.1111/j.1460-2466.2005.tb02658.x |date=March 2005 |url=http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1460-2466.2005.tb02658.x |ref=harv |postscript=.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The objection to the objectification of women is not a recent phenomenon. In the French [[Age of Enlightenment|Enlightenment]], for example, there was a debate as to whether a woman's breasts were merely a sensual enticement or rather a natural gift. In [[Alexandre Guillaume Mouslier de Moissy]]'s 1771 play ''The True Mother'' (''La Vraie Mère''), the title character rebukes her husband for treating her as merely an object for his sexual gratification: "Are your senses so gross as to look on these breasts &amp;ndash; the respectable treasures of nature &amp;ndash; as merely an embellishment, destined to ornament the chest of women?"&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Schama |first=Simon |author-link=Simon Schama |contribution=The cultural construction of a citizen: II Casting roles: children of nature |editor-last=Schama |editor-first=Simon |editor-link=Simon Schama |title=[[Citizens. A Chronicle of the French Revolution|Citizens: a chronicle of the French Revolution]] |publisher=Knopf Distributed by Random House |location=New York |year=1989 |isbn=978-0-394-55948-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The issues concerning sexual objectification became first [[problematization|problemized]] during the 1970s by feminist groups. Since then, it has been argued that the phenomenon of female sexual objectification has increased drastically since its problematization in all levels of life, and has resulted in negative consequences for women, especially in the political sphere. However, a rising form of new third-waver feminist groups have also taken the increased objectification of women as an opportunity to use the female body as a mode of power.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Heldman|first=Caroline|title=Sexualizing Sarah Palin|url=http://download.springer.com/static/pdf/634/art%253A10.1007%252Fs11199-011-9984-6.pdf?originUrl=http%3A%2F%2Flink.springer.com%2Farticle%2F10.1007%2Fs11199-011-9984-6&amp;token2=exp=1475121445~acl=%2Fstatic%2Fpdf%2F634%2Fart%25253A10.1007%25252Fs11199-011-9984-6.pdf%3ForiginUrl%3Dhttp%253A%252F%252Flink.springer.com%252Farticle%252F10.1007%252Fs11199-011-9984-6*~hmac=8b67612fbecfdda5ea221e5b332d6e44c78793f657c1d6f6cc22b27e6568ee32|journal=Springer Science+Business Media|volume=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Female self-objectification===
{{further information|sex-positive feminism|feminist sex wars}}

[[Ariel Levy]] contends that Western women who exploit their sexuality by, for example, wearing revealing clothing and engaging in lewd behavior, engage in female self-objectification, meaning they objectify themselves. While some women see such behaviour as a form of [[empowerment]], Levy contends that it has led to greater emphasis on a physical criterion or [[sexualization]] for women's perceived self-worth, which Levy calls "[[Raunch aesthetics|raunch culture]]".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Levy |first=Ariel |author-link=Ariel Levy |title=[[Female Chauvinist Pigs|Female chauvinist pigs: women and the rise of raunch culture]] |publisher=Pocket Books |location=London |year=2006 |isbn=978-1-4165-2638-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Levy discusses this phenomenon in ''[[Female Chauvinist Pigs]]: Women and the Rise of Raunch Culture''. Levy followed the camera crew from the ''[[Girls Gone Wild (franchise)|Girls Gone Wild]]'' video series, and argues that contemporary America's sexualized culture not only objectifies women, it encourages women to objectify themselves.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://women.timesonline.co.uk/tol/life_and_style/women/article2523264.ece |work=The Times |location=London |title=Yes we are bovvered |first=Ginny |last=Dougary |date=25 September 2007 |accessdate=23 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; In today's culture, Levy writes, the idea of a woman participating in a wet T-shirt contest or being comfortable watching explicit [[pornography]] has become a symbol of feminist strength.

==Sexual objectification of men==
[[Feminist]] authors [[Christina Hoff Sommers]] and [[Naomi Wolf]] write that women's sexual liberation led women to a [[role reversal]], whereby they viewed men as sex objects,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book  |last=Sommers |first=Christina |author-link=Sommers, Christina Hoff |contribution=The gender wardens |title-link=Who Stole Feminism? How Women Have Betrayed Women |title=Who stole feminism?: how women have betrayed women |pages=264–265 |publisher=Touchstone/Simon &amp; Schuster |location=New York |year=1995 |isbn=978-0-684-80156-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Wolf |first=Naomi |author-link=Naomi Wolf |title=Fire with fire: the new female power and how to use it |pages=225–228 |publisher=Fawcett Columbine |location=New York |year=1994 |isbn=978-0-449-90951-5}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Friend |first=Tad |author-link=Tad Friend |title=Yes: Feminist women who like sex |pages=48–56 |url=http://www.esquire.com/ |date=February 1994}}&lt;/ref&gt; in a manner similar to what they criticize about men's treatment of women. Psychologist [[Harold Lyon]] suggests that men's liberation is a necessary step toward woman's liberation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Lyon|first1=Harold C.|title=Tenderness Is Strength|date=1977|publisher=Harper &amp; Row|location=New York|isbn=978-0060127138|edition=first}}&lt;/ref&gt; This was especially apparent during the [[girl power]] era of the 1990s and early 2000s. Men are often objectified by other men.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Teunis |first=Niels |title=Sexual objectification and the construction of whiteness in the gay male community |journal=[[Culture, Health &amp; Sexuality]] |volume=9 |issue=3 |pages=263–275 |publisher=[[Taylor &amp; Francis]] |jstor=20460929 |doi=10.1080/13691050601035597 |date=May 2007 |url=https://dx.doi.org/10.1080/13691050601035597 |ref=harv |postscript=.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Research has suggested that the psychological effects of objectification on men are similar to those of women, leading to negative [[body image]] among men.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Neimark |first=Jill |url=http://www.psychologytoday.com/articles/200910/the-beefcaking-america |title=The beefcaking of America |work=[[Psychology Today]] |publisher=Sussex Publishers |date=1 November 1994 |accessdate=1 August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Instances where men may be viewed as sex objects by women include advertisements, [[sexuality in music videos|music videos]], films, television shows, [[beefcake]] calendars, [[women's magazine]]s, male [[striptease|strip shows]], and [[clothed female, naked male|clothed female/nude male]] (CFNM) events.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.sensations4women.com/sportsIni/index.html |title=Sports, gym classes, team initiations and events |work=Sensations4women.com |date=26 January 1998 |accessdate=1 August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Women also purchase and consume [[pornography]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=McElroy |first=Wendy |author-link=Wendy McElroy |title=XXX: a woman's right to pornography |page=36 |publisher=St. Martin's Press |location=New York |year=1995 |isbn=978-0-312-13626-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Pearce |first=Dulcie |url=http://www.thesun.co.uk/sol/homepage/features/article2355510.ece |title=Shock Sun sex survey reveals 66% of women watch porn |work=''[[The Sun (United Kingdom)|The Sun]]'' |publisher=[[News UK|News Corp]] |date=1 April 2009 |accessdate=1 August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.multichannel.com/article/79434-A_Playgirl_for_Adult_TV.php |title=A 'Playgirl" for adult TV |work=[[Multichannel News]] |publisher=[[NewBay Media]] |accessdate=1 August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Taormino |first=Tristan |url=http://www.villagevoice.com/2008-05-13/coulumns/girls-love-gay-male-porn |title=Girls love gay male porn |work=[[The Village Voice]] |publisher=Josh Fromson |date=13 May 2008 |accessdate=16 August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Scott |first=Lisa |url=http://www.metro.co.uk/lifestyle/356386-women-who-like-to-watch-gay-porn |title=Women who like to watch gay porn |work=[[Metro (British newspaper)|Metro]] |publisher=[[DMG Media]] |date=15 October 2008 |accessdate=17 August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Murphy |first=Chris |title=Women's porn tastes: You'll never guess what ladies prefer |url=http://www.mirror.co.uk/news/weird-news/womens-porn-tastes-youll-never-5686920 |work=[[Daily Mirror]] |publisher=[[Trinity Mirror]]  |date=12 May 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; {{Overcite}}

=== Media ===
Men's bodies have become more objectified than they previously were. It is known as "Six-pack Advertising," where men are seen as sexual objects. Because of society's established gaze on the objectification of women, the newfound objectification of men is not as widespread. Even with this increase of male objectification, males are still seen as the dominant figures and so the focus is still primarily on women.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Tortajada|first=I.|last2=Arauna|first2=A.|date=2013|title=Advertising Stereotypes and Gender Representation in Social Networking Sites|url=|journal=Comunar|doi=|pmid=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Male sexual objectification has been found in 37% of advertisements featuring men's body parts to showcase a product.&lt;ref name=":02"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Davidson|first=M.|last2=Gervais|first2=S.|date=2013|title=A psychometric examination of the interpersonal sexual objectification scale among college men|url=|journal=Journal Of Counseling Psychology|doi=|pmid=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt; These advertisements are a form of sexual objectification. Similar to the issues of sexual objectification in women, it is common for said objectification to lead men to body shaming, eating disorders, and a drive for perfection. Men in the media are especially pressured to take part in steroid use in order to meet the standard of beauty set by body evaluation. The continued exposure of these "ideal" men subject society to expect all men to fit this role.

Male actors featured in TV shows and movies are oftentimes in excellent shape and have the "ideal" bodies. These men often fill the leading roles. When society is subjected to men who do not have ideal bodies, we typically see them as the comic relief. It is rare to see an out of shape man have a leading role. "There are temporal, cultural and geographical ‘norms’ of gender and other aspects of identity, which are often incorrectly considered to be inherent or natural."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Dawson|first=L.|date=2015|title=Passing and policing: controlling compassion, bodies and boundaries in Boys Don’t Cry and Unveiled/Fremde Haut|url=|journal=Studies In European Cinema|doi=|pmid=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the media, the ideal version of a man is seen as a strong, toned man. The idealized version of a woman is thin (Aubrey, pg. 7). The concept of body evaluation is more common in criticizing women. However, body evaluation revolves more towards nonverbal cues for men. It is more common in women because sexual, sometimes offensive, verbal remarks are directed towards women. Men, on the other hand, experience more body evaluation through gazing and other nonverbal cues. Gazing is simply the way in which depict men from an idealized perspective. Men tend to experience this from other men, whereas women experience it from both sexes.&lt;ref name=":02" /&gt; The Interpersonal Sexual Objectification Scale (ISOS) is a scale that shows sexual objectification of respondents, both men and women. While experiencing sexual objectification it creates the need to constantly maintain and critique one’s physical appearance. This leads to other things like eating disorders, body shaming, and anxiety. The ISOS scale can be related to objectification theory and sexism.&lt;ref name=":02" /&gt; Self-objectification is concentrated more on women, which is the way in which we evaluate ourselves. Men typically experience it through media display, but the difference is men do not experience the negative effects at the extent to which women do.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Aubrey|first=S.|date=2003|title=Investigating the Role of Self-Objectification in the Relationship between Media Exposure and Sexual Self-Perceptions|url=|journal=International Communication Association|doi=|pmid=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Views on sexual objectification==
{{see also|Gaze}}
While the concept of sexual objectification is important within feminist theory, ideas vary widely on what constitutes sexual objectification and what are the ethical implications of such objectification. Some feminists such as [[Naomi Wolf]] find the concept of [[physical attractiveness]] itself to be problematic,&lt;ref name=beautymyth&gt;{{cite book |last=Wolf |first=Naomi |author-link=Naomi Wolf |title=The beauty myth: how images of beauty are used against women |publisher=Perennial |location=New York |year=2002 |origyear=1992 |isbn=978-0-06-051218-7}}&lt;/ref&gt; with some [[radical feminists]]  being opposed to any evaluation of another person's sexual attractiveness based on physical characteristics.{{Citation needed|reason=This claim needs references to reliable sources|date=September 2015}} [[John Stoltenberg]] goes so far as to condemn as wrongfully objectifying any sexual fantasy that involves the visualization of a woman.&lt;ref name=stoltenberg&gt;{{cite book |last=Stoltenberg |first=John |author-link=John Stoltenberg |title=Refusing to be a man: essays on sex and justice |publisher=UCL Press |location=London New York|url=http://www.feministes-radicales.org/wp-content/uploads/2010/11/Stoltenberg-Refusing-to-be-a-Man.pdf |year=2000 |isbn=978-1-84142-041-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{page needed|date=November 2016}}

Radical feminists view objectification as playing a central role in reducing women to what they refer to as the "oppressed sex [[Social class|class]]".{{Cite quote|date=September 2015}} While some feminists view mass media in societies that they argue are [[patriarchal]] to be objectifying, they often focus on [[pornography]] as playing an egregious role in habituating men to objectify women.&lt;ref name='MacKinnon "Only Words"'&gt;{{cite book |last=MacKinnon |first=Catharine |author-link=Catharine MacKinnon |title=Only words |publisher=Harvard University Press |location=Cambridge, Massachusetts |year=1993 |isbn=978-0-674-63934-8}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Some [[social conservatives]] have taken up aspects of the [[feminist]] critique of sexual objectification. In their view however, the increase in the sexual objectification of both sexes in Western culture is one of the negative legacies of the [[sexual revolution]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Dr. James Dobson |url=http://www.theinterim.com/issues/society-culture/dr-james-dobson-6 |work=The Interim: Canada's life and family newspaper |location=[[Toronto|Toronto, Canada]] |publisher=via [[True Media]] |date=12 January 1997 |accessdate=1 August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=shalit1&gt;{{cite book |last=Shalit |first=Wendy |author-link=Wendy Shalit |title=A return to modesty: discovering the lost virtue |publisher=Touchstone |location=New York |year=2000 |isbn=978-0-684-86317-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Reisman |first=Judith A. |author-link=Judith Reisman |title="Soft porn" plays hardball: its tragic effects on women, children, and the family |publisher=Huntington House Publishers |location=[[Lafayette, Louisiana]] |year=1991 |isbn=978-0-910311-92-2 |pages=32–46, 173}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Holz |first=Adam R. |title=Is average the new ugly? |url=http://www.pluggedin.com/familyroom/articles/2007/isaveragethenewugly.aspx |work=[[Plugged In|Plugged In Online]] |publisher=[[Focus on the Family]] |date=2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=National Coalition for the Protection of Children &amp; Families |url=http://pureintimacy.org/piArticles/A000000551.cfm |title=Subtle Dangers of Pornography (special report by the National Coalition for the Protection of Children &amp; Families) |work=Pure Intimacy (website) |publisher=[[Focus on the Family]] |date=July 1997 |accessdate=1 August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; These critics, notably [[Wendy Shalit]], advocate a return to pre-sexual revolution standards of [[sexual morality]], which Shalit refers to as a "return to [[modesty]]", as an antidote to sexual objectification.&lt;ref name=shalit1/&gt;&lt;ref name=shalit2&gt;{{cite web |last=Shalit |first=Wendy |author-link=Wendy Shalit |title=Modesty revisited |url=http://www.orthodoxytoday.org/articles/ShalitModesty.php |website=orthodoxytoday.org |publisher=[[Antiochian Orthodox Christian Archdiocese of North America|Fr. Johannes Jacobse]] |date=2000}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Others contest feminist claims about the objectification of women. [[Camille Paglia]] holds that "Turning people into sex objects is one of the specialties of our species." In her view, objectification is closely tied to (and may even be identical with) the highest human faculties toward conceptualization and [[aesthetics]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Paglia |first=Camille |author-link=Camille Paglia |title=[[Sexual Personae: Art and Decadence from Nefertiti to Emily Dickinson|Sexual personae: art and decadence from Nefertiti to Emily Dickinson]] |publisher=Vintage Books |location=New York |year=1991 |isbn=978-0-679-73579-3}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Individualist feminist]] [[Wendy McElroy]] says, given that  'objectification' of women means to make women into sexual objects; it is meaningless because, 'sexual objects', taken literally, means nothing because inanimate objects do not have sexuality. She continues that women are their bodies as well as their minds and souls, and so focusing on a single aspect should not be "degrading".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=McElroy |first=Wendy |author-link=Wendy McElroy |title=A feminist overview of pornography, ending in a defense thereof |url=http://www.wendymcelroy.com/freeinqu.htm |website=WendyMcElroy.com |date=2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Objectification theory==
{{expert needed|Feminism|ex2=Gender Studies|section|reason=The prose is jargon-filled, repetitive and nearly impenetrable to laypeople. The structure needs improvement|date=January 2015}}
Sexual objectification has been studied based on the proposition that girls and women develop their primary view of their physical selves from observing others. These observations can take place in the media or through personal experience.&lt;ref name=bartky&gt;{{cite book |last=Bartky |first=Sandra Lee |author-link=Sandra Bartky |contribution=On psychological oppression |editor-last=Bartky |editor-first=Sandra Lee |editor-link=Sandra Bartky |title=Femininity and domination: studies in the phenomenology of oppression |page=26 |publisher=Routledge |location=New York |year=1990 |isbn=978-0-415-90186-4 |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt; Through a blend of expected and actual exposure, women are socialized to objectify their own physical characteristics from a [[Grammatical person|third person]] perception, which is identified as self-objectification.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Kaschak |first=Ellyn |author-link=Ellyn Kaschak |title=Engendered lives: a new psychology of women's experience |page=12 |publisher=Basic Books |location=New York, New York |year=1992 |isbn=978-0-465-01349-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; Women and girls develop an expected physical appearance for themselves, based on observations of others; and are aware that others are likely to observe as well. The sexual objectification and self-objectification of women is believed to influence social [[gender roles]] and inequalities between the sexes.&lt;ref name=Goldenberg&gt;{{cite book |last1=Goldenberg |first1=Jamie L. |last2=Roberts |first2=Tomi-Ann |contribution=The beast within the beauty: an existential perspective on the objectification and condemnation of women |editor-last1=Greenberg |editor-first1=Jeff |editor-last2=Koole |editor-first2=Sander L. |editor-last3=Pyszczynski |editor-first3=Tom |title=Handbook of experimental existential psychology |pages=71–85 |publisher=Guilford Press |location=New York |year=2004 |isbn=978-1-59385-040-1 |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Self-objectification===
Self-objectification can increase in situations which heighten the awareness of an individual’s physical appearance.&lt;ref name=frederickson1.82&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Fredrickson |first1=Barbara L. |last2=Harrison |first2=Kristen |author-link1=Barbara Fredrickson |title=Throwing like a girl: self-objectification predicts adolescent girls’ motor performance |journal=[[Journal of Sport and Social Issues]] |volume=29 |issue=1 |pages=79–101 |publisher=[[SAGE Publications|Sage]] |doi=10.1177/0193723504269878 |date=February 2005 |url=http://dx.doi.org/10.1177/0193723504269878 |ref=harv |postscript=.}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|82}} Here, the presence of a [[third person (video games)|third person]] observer is enhanced. Therefore, when individuals know others are looking at them, or will be looking at them, they are more likely to care about their physical appearance. Examples of the enhanced presence of an observer include the presence of an audience, camera, or other known observer.

===Women, girls, and self-objectification===
Primarily, objectification theory describes how women and girls are influenced as a result of expected social and [[gender roles]].&lt;ref name=bartky/&gt; Research indicates not all women are influenced equally, due to the [[anatomical]], [[hormonal]], and [[Genetics|genetic]] differences of the female body; however, women’s bodies are often objectified and evaluated more frequently.&lt;ref name=frederickson1.82 /&gt;{{rp|90–95}} Self-objectification in girls tends to stem from two main causes: the internalization of traditional beauty standards as translated through media as well as any instances of sexual objectification that they might encounter in their daily lives.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=McKay |first=Tajare' |title=Female self-objectification: causes, consequences and prevention |journal=McNair Scholars Research Journal |volume=6 |issue=1 |pages=53–70 |publisher=[[Ronald E. McNair Post-Baccalaureate Achievement Program|McNair Scholars Program]] |date=30 September 2013 |url=http://commons.emich.edu/mcnair/vol6/iss1/7/ |ref=harv |postscript=.}} [http://commons.emich.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1065&amp;context=mcnair Pdf.]&lt;/ref&gt; It is not uncommon for women to translate their anxieties over their constant sense of objectification into obsessive self-surveillance. This, in turn, can lead to many serious problems in women and girls, including "body shame, anxiety, negative attitudes toward menstruation, a disrupted flow of consciousness, diminished awareness of internal bodily states, depression, sexual dysfunction, and disordered eating."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Calogero |first1=Rachel M. |last2=Davis |first2=William N. |last3=Thompson |first3=J. Kevin |title=The role of self-objectification in the experience of women with eating disorders |journal=[[Sex Roles (journal)|Sex Roles]] |volume=52 |issue=1 |pages=43–50 |publisher=[[Springer Science+Business Media|Springer]] |doi=10.1007/s11199-005-1192-9 |date=January 2005 |url=http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s11199-005-1192-9 |ref=harv |postscript=.}} [http://brown.uk.com/eatingdisorders/calogero.pdf Pdf.]&lt;/ref&gt;

Sexual objectification occurs when a person is identified by their sexual body parts or sexual function. In essence, an individual loses their identity, and is recognized solely by the physical characteristics of their body.&lt;ref name=bartky/&gt; The purpose of this recognition is to bring enjoyment to others, or to serve as a sexual object for society.&lt;ref name=LeMoncheck /&gt; Sexual objectification can occur as a [[social construct]] among individuals.

===Psychological consequences===
Objectification theory suggests both direct and indirect consequences of objectification to women. Indirect consequences include [[self consciousness]] in terms that a woman is consistently checking or rearranging her clothes or appearance to ensure that she is presentable. More direct consequences are related to sexual victimization. Rape and sexual harassment are examples of this.&lt;ref name=fredrickson2 /&gt; Doob (2012) states that sexual harassment is one of the challenges faced by women in workplace. This may constitute sexual jokes or comments, most of which are degrading.&lt;ref name="Doob"&gt;{{cite book |last=Doob |first=Christopher B. |title=Social inequality and social stratification in US society |publisher=Pearson Education, Inc. |location=Upper Saddle River, New Jersey |year=2013 |isbn=978-0-205-79241-2}}&lt;/ref&gt; Research indicates that objectification theory is valuable to understanding how repeated visual images in the media are socialized and translated into [[mental health]] problems, including psychological consequences on the individual and societal level.&lt;ref name=fredrickson2 /&gt; These include increased self-consciousness, increased body anxiety, heightened mental health threats ([[Clinical depression|depression]], [[anorexia nervosa]], [[bulimia]], and [[sexual dysfunction]]), and increased body shame.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Moradi |first1=Bonnie |last2=Huang |first2=Yu-Ping |title=Objectification theory and psychology of women: a decade of advances and future directions |journal=[[Psychology of Women Quarterly]] |volume=32 |issue=4 |pages=377–398 |publisher=[[SAGE Publications|Sage]] |doi=10.1111/j.1471-6402.2008.00452.x |date=December 2008 |url=http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1471-6402.2008.00452.x |ref=harv |postscript=.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Therefore, the theory has been used to explore an array of dependent variables including [[disordered eating]], [[mental health]], [[Clinical depression|depression]], motor performance, [[body image]], idealized body type, [[stereotype]] formation, sexual perception and sexual typing.&lt;ref name=fredrickson2/&gt;&lt;ref name=frederickson1.82/&gt; Body shame is a byproduct of the concept of an idealized body type adopted by most Western cultures that depicts a thin, model-type figure. Thus, women will engage in actions meant to change their body such as dieting, exercise, eating disorders, [[cosmetic surgery]], etc.&lt;ref name=fredrickson2 /&gt; Effects of objectification theory are identified on both the individual and societal levels.

===Causes of depression===
[[Learned helplessness]] theory posits that because human bodies are only alterable to a certain point, people develop a sense of body shame and anxiety from which they create a feeling of helplessness in relation to correcting their physical appearance and helplessness in being able to control the way in which others perceive their appearance. This lack of control often results in depression.&lt;ref name=fredrickson2 /&gt; In relating to a lack of motivation, objectification theory states that women have less control in relationships and the work environment because they have to depend on the evaluation of another who is typically basing their evaluation on physical appearance. Since the dependence on another's evaluation limits a woman's ability to create her own positive experiences and motivation, it adversely increases her likelihood for depression.&lt;ref name=fredrickson2 /&gt; Furthermore, sexual victimization may be a cause. Specifically, victimization within the workplace degrades women. Harassment experienced every day wears on a woman, and sometimes results in a state of depression.&lt;ref name=fredrickson2 /&gt;&lt;ref name="Doob"/&gt;

==Sexual fetishism==
[[Sexual fetishism]] can be considered sexual objectification when a person is assigned or adopts the status of the fetish object. In [[BDSM]] activities, even though it is consensual, subjecting a submissive to [[erotic humiliation]] can be regarded as sexual objectification.{{Citation needed|reason=Very conflicting statement.|date=June 2014}} [[Human furniture]] is a form of fetishism and sexual objectification. [[Allen Jones (sculptor)|Allen Jones]]' [[Hatstand, Table and Chair|''Hatstand'', ''Table'' and ''Chair'']] sculptures incorporates semi-naked women into furniture, in a show of exaggerated sexual objectification.

==See also==
{{Commons category}}
*[[Dehumanization]]
*[[Exploitation of women in mass media]]
*[[Forniphilia]] or Human furniture
*[[Rape culture]]
*[[Sex in advertising]]
*[[Sexuality in music videos]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
* {{cite book |last=Bartky |first=Sandra Lee |author-link=Sandra Bartky |title=Femininity and domination: studies in the phenomenology of oppression |publisher=Routledge |location=New York |year=1990 |isbn=978-0-415-90186-4}}
* {{cite book |last=Berger |first=John |author-link=John Berger |title=[[Ways of Seeing]] |publisher=BBC and Penguin Books |year=1972 |location=London}} ISBN 0-563-12244-7 (BBC), ISBN 0-14-021631-6, ISBN 0-14-013515-4 (pbk).
* {{Cite journal |last1=Bridges |first1=Ana J. |last2=Johnson |first2=Jennifer A. |last3=Dines |first3=Gail |last4=Condit |first4=Deirdre M. |last5=West |first5=Carolyn M. |author-link1=Ana J. Bridges |author-link2=Jennifer A. Johnson |author-link3=Gail Dines |author-link5=Carolyn M. West |title=Introducing ''Sexualization, Media &amp; Society'' |journal=[[Sexualization, Media, &amp; Society]] |volume=1 |issue=1 |pages=487–515 |publisher=[[SAGE Publications|Sage]] |doi=10.1177/2374623815588763 |date=April 2015 |url=http://dx.doi.org/10.1177/2374623815588763 |ref=harv |postscript=.}}
* {{cite book |last=Brooks |first=Gary R. |title=The centerfold syndrome: how men can overcome objectification and achieve intimacy with women |publisher=Jossey-Bass |year=1995 |location=San Francisco |isbn=978-0-7879-0104-2}} 
* {{Cite journal |last1=Coy |first1=Maddy |last2=Garner |first2=Maria |author-link1=Maddy Coy |title=Glamour modelling and the marketing of self-sexualization: critical reflections |journal=[[International Journal of Cultural Studies]] |volume=13 |issue=6 |pages=657–675 |publisher=[[SAGE Publications|Sage]] |doi=10.1177/1367877910376576 |date=November 2010 |url=http://dx.doi.org/10.1177/1367877910376576 |ref=harv |postscript=.}}
* {{Cite journal |last=Eames |first=Elizabeth R. |title=Sexism and woman as sex object |journal=Journal of Thought |volume=11 |issue=2 |pages=140–143 |publisher=Caddo Gap Press |date=1976 |url=http://journalofthought.com/?page_id=66 |ref=harv |postscript=.}} [http://eric.ed.gov/?id=EJ147519 Preview.]
* {{cite conference |last=Holroyd |first=Julia |title=Sexual objectification: The unlikely alliance of feminism and Kant |format=pdf |conference=Society for Applied Philosophy International Congress |date=2005 |location=Oxford, UK |url=http://www.brown.edu/Departments/Philosophy/conferencepapers/objectification.pdf}} (conference paper)
* {{cite book |last=LeMoncheck |first=Linda |title=Dehumanizing Women: Treating Persons as Sex Objects |publisher=Rowman &amp; Littlefield |year=1985 |location=New York |isbn=978-0-8476-7386-5}}
* {{Cite journal |last=Nussbaum |first=Martha C. |title=Objectification |author-link=Martha Nussbaum |journal=[[Philosophy &amp; Public Affairs]] |volume=24 |issue=4 |pages=249–291 |publisher=[[Wiley-Blackwell|Wiley]] |doi=10.1111/j.1088-4963.1995.tb00032.x |jstor=2961930 |date=October 1995 |url=http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1088-4963.1995.tb00032.x |ref=harv |postscript=.}}
* {{Cite journal |last=Papadaki |first=Evangelia (Lina) |title=Sexual objectification: From Kant to contemporary feminism |journal=[[Contemporary Political Theory]] |volume=6 |issue=3 |pages=330–348 |publisher=[[Palgrave Macmillan]] |doi=10.1057/palgrave.cpt.9300282 |date=August 2007 |url=http://dx.doi.org/10.1057/palgrave.cpt.9300282 |ref=harv |postscript=.}} [http://www.palgrave-journals.com/cpt/journal/v6/n3/pdf/9300282a.pdf Pdf.]
* {{cite news |last=Parker |first=Kathleen |author-link=Kathleen Parker |title='Save the males': Ho culture lights fuses, but confuses |url=http://www.nydailynews.com/lifestyle/2008/06/30/2008-06-30_save_the_males_ho_culture_lights_fuses_b.html |work=[[Daily News (New York)|Daily News]] |location=New York |date=30 June 2008}} 
* {{cite book |last=Paul |first=Pamela |authorlink=Pamela Paul |title=Pornified: how pornography is transforming our lives, our relationships, and our families |publisher=Times Books |location=New York |year=2005 |isbn=978-0-8050-8132-9}}
* {{Cite journal |last=Sharge |first=Laurie |title=Exposing the fallacies of anti-porn feminism |journal=[[Feminist Theory (journal)|Feminist Theory]] |volume=6 |issue=1 |pages=45–65 |publisher=[[Sage Publications|Sage]] |doi=10.1177/1464700105050226 |date=April 2005 |url=http://dx.doi.org/10.1177/1464700105050226 |ref=harv |postscript=.}}
* {{cite book |last=Soble |first=Alan |title=Pornography, Sex, and Feminism |publisher=[[Prometheus Books]] |year=2002 |location=Amherst, New York}} ISBN 1-57392-944-1 (pb).

==External links==
* [http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/feminism-objectification/ "Feminist Perspectives on Objectification"] by Evangelia Papadaki, ''[[Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy]]'', March 10, 2010.
* [http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/feminist-sex-markets/#SexObj "Feminist Perspectives on Sex Markets: 1.3 Sexual Objectification"] by Laurie Shrage, ''[[Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy]]'', July 13, 2007.
* [http://finallyfeminism101.wordpress.com/2007/03/23/faq-what-is-sexual-objectification/ "FAQ: What is sexual objectification?"] by Tigtog, ''Finally, A Feminism 101 Blog'', March 23, 2007.
* [http://www.nearbycafe.com/loveandlust/steinberg/erotic/cn/cn5.html "Comes Naturally #5: On Sexual Objectification"] by David Steinberg, ''[[Spectator Magazine]]'', March 5, 1993. – Sex-positive feminist perspective on sexual objectification.
* [http://www.telegraph.co.uk/htmlContent.jhtml;?html=/archive/1996/10/05/tlpet05.html "Women Like Seeing Men as Sex Objects"]. Interview with [[Janet Anderson]] by [[Petronella Wyatt]], ''[[Daily Telegraph]]'', October 5, 1996.
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20080208172715/http://www.psu.edu/dept/medialab/research/objectification.html "Sexual Suggestiveness in Online Ads: Effects of Objectification on Opposite Genders"] by Sriram Kalyanaraman, Michael Redding, and Jason Steele, ''Media Effects Research Laboratory, [[Pennsylvania State University]]'', 2000.
* [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=d-N9daqANcw "I'm a sexy woman, so stop objectifying me!"] by Karen Straughan, March 28, 2012.

{{Sexual ethics|state=expand}}
{{Nudity|state=expand}}

[[Category:Sexualization]]
[[Category:Sexuality and society]]
[[Category:Feminist theory]]
[[Category:Philosophy of sexuality]]
[[Category:Postmodern theory]]
[[Category:Sexual attraction]]
[[Category:Human sexuality]]
[[Category:Sexual fetishism]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>