<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20071110003218|170447117" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="200977" pageid="200977" ns="0" title="Sexual objectification"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-11-14T18:13:18Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Refimprove|date=April 2007}}

'''Sexual objectification''' is [[objectification]] of a person. That is, seeing them as a sexual object, and emphasizing their sexual attributes and [[physical attractiveness]], while de-emphasizing their existence as a living person with [[emotion]]s and [[feeling]]s of their own. The concept of sexual objectification and, in particular, the objectification of [[women]], is an important idea in [[feminist]] theory and psychological theories derived from feminism. Many [[feminists]] regard sexual objectification as objectionable and as playing an important role in the way that [[men]] subjugate [[women]]. Increased sexual freedom and media visibility for women and [[gay men]] has also led to an increased sexual objectification of men.

== Objectification of women ==
Many feminists (as well as some non-feminists) view the sexual objectification of women as one of the main ways in which women are subordinated in a sexist society. In their view, the objectification of women involves disregarding personal abilities and capabilities, and focusing instead on attributes relevant to women's role as sexual partners, such as [[physical attractiveness]], sex appeal, and submissiveness. 

Examples of phenomena seen by some feminists as objectifying women include depictions of women in advertising and media, images of women in [[pornography]], as well as images in more mainstream [[media]] such as [[advertising]] and [[art]], [[stripping]] and [[prostitution]], men evaluating women sexually in public spaces, and [[cosmetic surgery]], particularly [[breast enlargement]].

&lt;!-- The following section needs concrete references given in the correct format --&gt;
Historically, feminists believe women have often been valued for their physical attributes. Some feminists and psychologists argue that such sexual objectification can lead to negative psychological effects include [[depression (mood)|depression]] and [[hope]]lessness, and can give women negative [[self-image]]s because of the belief that their intelligence and competence are not being acknowledged.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
  | last =[[Miles Hewstone|Hewstone]]
  | first =Miles
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors = [[Marilynn B. Brewer]]
  | title =Self and Social Identity 
  | publisher =Blackwell Publishing Professional
  | date = 2004-01-01
  | location =
  | pages =167
  | url =http://books.google.com/books?vid=ISBN1405110694&amp;id=aGhvm-QH1yEC&amp;pg=RA1-PA136&amp;lpg=RA1-PA136&amp;ots=ai3jNO8_Ks&amp;dq=Fredrickson+and+Roberts&amp;sig=-Ii-Dd49gSgcbZT3O0s4_bzDju8
  | doi =
  | id = ISBN 978-1-4051-1069-3  ISBN 1-4051-1069-4  }}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal
  | last = [[Barbara Fredrickson|Fredrickson]]
  | first =Barbara L.
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =Tomi-Ann Roberts
  | title =Objectification Theory: Toward understanding women's lived experiences and mental health risks
  | journal =Psychology of Women Quarterly
  | volume =21
  | issue =
  | pages =172-206
  | publisher =
  | date =
  | url =
  | doi = 10.1111/j.1471-6402.1997.tb00108.x.
  | id =
  | accessdate =  }}&lt;/ref&gt; The precise degree to how objectification has affected women and society in general is a topic of academic debate. Such claims include:

*Girls' understanding of the importance of appearance in society may contribute to feelings of [[fear]], [[shame]], and [[disgust]] that some experience during the transition from girlhood to womanhood because they sense that they are becoming more visible to society as sexual objects.&lt;ref&gt;Lee, Janet. 1994. Menarche and the (hetero)sexualization of the female body. ''Gender &amp; Society'' 8(3):343–362. {{DOI|10.1177/089124394008003004}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Young women are especially susceptible to objectification, as they are often taught that [[power]], [[respect]], and [[wealth]] can be derived from one's outwardly appearance.&lt;ref name-apareport&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.apa.org/pi/wpo/sexualizationsum.html
|title=Report of the APA Task Force on the Sexualization of Girls, Executive Summary
|accessmonthday=November 2
|accessyear=2007
|author=APA Task Force on the Sexualization of Girls
|date=2007-02-19
|publisher=[[American Psychological Association]]
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Pro-feminist cultural critics such as [[Robert Jensen]] and [[Sut Jhally]] accuse [[mass media]] and advertising of promoting the objectification of women to help promote goods and services.

== Objectification of men ==
[[Feminist]] authors [[Christina Hoff Sommers]] and [[Naomi Wolf]] maintain that women's sexual liberation has led some women to make men into sex objects. Research has suggested that the psychological effects of objectification on men are similar to those of women, leading to negative [[body image]] among men, as well as fears of inadequate sexual performance, leading to increased use of drugs like [[Viagra]].

Examples of the increasing trend of the objectification of men in contemporary media include increasing exposure of the male body in movies, television, advertising, and women's magazines; the popularity of male [[striptease]] performances; advertisements for drugs to increase [[penis size]] or improve sexual performance; and increasingly prominent media portrayals of men with unrealistic body types (e.g., hairlessness, perfectly toned muscles, an absence of blemishes or body fat, etc.) on billboards, in calendars, in magazine advertisements, etc. In addition, [[clothed female, nude male]] (cfnm) events have gained more popularity and/or media visibility.

== Views on sexual objectification ==
While the concept of sexual objectification is important within feminist theory, ideas on what constitutes objectification and what the ethical implications of objectification are vary widely. Some feminists such as [[Naomi Wolf]] find the concept of physical [[attractiveness]] itself to be problematic,&lt;ref name=beautymyth&gt;Wolf, Naomi. (1992). ''The Beauty Myth: How Images of Beauty Are Used Against Women''. New York: William Morrow and Co. (Reprinted, 2002. New York: Harper Perennial) ISBN 0060512180&lt;/ref&gt; with some [[radical feminists]] being opposed to any evaluation of another person's sexual attractiveness based on physical characteristics. [[John Stoltenberg]] goes so far as to condemn any sexual fantasy that involves visualization of a woman as wrongfully objectifying.&lt;ref name=stoltenberg&gt; Stoltenberg, John. 1989. Refusing to be a man: Essays on sex and justice. Portland, OR: Breitenbush Books. (Reprinted, 2000. Oxford: Routledge) ISBN 1841420417&lt;/ref&gt;

Radical feminists view objectification as playing a central role in reducing women to what they refer to as the "sex [[Social class|class]]". While radical feminists view all mass media in a [[patriarchal]] society to be objectifying, they most often focus on [[pornography]] as playing an egregious role in habituating men to objectify women.

Other feminists, particularly those identified with [[sex-positive feminism]], take a more nuanced view of sexual objectification, seeing sexual objectification as mainly a problem when not counterbalanced by women's sense of their own sexual subjectivity. Sex-positive feminist activism therefore emphasizes developing greater sexual subjectivity in women, rather than attacking sexual objectification.

Some [[social conservatives]] have taken up aspects of the [[feminist]] critique of sexual objectification. In their view however, the increase of sexual objectification in Western culture is one of the negative legacies of the [[sexual revolution]].&lt;ref&gt;National Coalition for the Protection of Children and Families. 1997. [http://www.pureintimacy.org/gr/intimacy/understanding/a0000121.cfm Subtle dangers of pornography]. ''NCPCF in Action Special Report'', July 1997. (Archived at ''Pure Intimacy'' (website).)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=shalit1&gt;Shalit, Wendy. 1999. ''A Return To Modesty: Discovering the Lost Virtue''. New York: Free Press. ISBN 0684843161 (hc), ISBN 0684863170 (pb).&lt;/ref&gt; These critics, notably [[Wendy Shalit]], advocate a return to pre-sexual revolution standards of [[sexual morality]], which Shalit refers to as a "return to modesty", as an antidote to sexual objectification.&lt;ref name=shalit1/&gt;&lt;ref name=shalit2&gt;Shalit, Wendy. 2000. [http://www.boundless.org/2000/features/a0000413.html Modesty revisited]. ''[[Boundless webzine]]''.&lt;/ref&gt;                    

Many critics of feminism contest feminist claims about the objectification of women. [[Camille Paglia]] holds that "Turning people into sex objects is one of the specialties of our species." In her view, objectification is closely tied to (and may even be identical with) the highest human faculties toward conceptualization and [[aesthetics]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
  | last =Paglia 
  | first =Camille 
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | title =Sexual Personae: Art &amp; Decadence from Nefertiti to Emily Dickinson 
  | publisher =Vintage
  |date=August 20, 1991
  | location =
  | pages =
  | url =
  | doi =
  | id = ISBN 0-6797-3579-8 ISBN 978-0-6797-3579-3  }}
&lt;/ref&gt; [[Individualist feminist]] [[Wendy McElroy]] holds that the label "sex object" means nothing because inantimate objects are not sexual. She continues that women are thier bodies and sexuality as well as thier minds and souls.&lt;ref&gt;McElroy, Wendy. 2006. [http://www.wendymcelroy.com/freeinqu.htm A feminist overview of pornography, ending in a defense thereof.] ''WendyMcElroy.com''.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Libertarian]] economist and social critic [[Murray Rothbard]] wrote that women are and always will be sex objects to men and men are and always will be sex objects to women.&lt;ref&gt;Rothbard, Murray N. 1970. [http://www.lewrockwell.com/rothbard/rothbard4.html "The great women's liberation issue: Setting it straight"]. ''The Individualist'', May 1970. (Archived at ''LewRockwell.com''.)&lt;/ref&gt;

A related concept often used by [[postmodernist]] feminist theorists, is that of [[gaze]].

== Objectification as a sexual fetish ==
Sexual objectification also describes a specific [[sexual fetish]] involving the act of treating a person as an object for erotic purposes. This may provide [[erotic humiliation]] for the person so regarded. As with most [[BDSM]]-related activities, it is not considered abusive when engaged in consensually. [[Allen Jones (sculptor)|Allen Jones]]' ''Hat Stand and Table Sculpture'', which show semi-naked women in the roles of furniture, are clear examples of the depiction of the fantasy of sexual objectification.

==References==
{{reflist}}

==Further reading==
* Bartky, Sandra Lee. 1990. ''Femininity and Domination: Studies in the Phenomenology of Oppression''. New York: Routledge. ISBN 0-415-90185-5 (hc), ISBN 0-415-90186-3 (pb).
* Brooks, Gary R. 1995. ''The Centerfold Syndrome: How Men Can Overcome Objectification and Achieve Intimacy with Women''. San Francisco: Jossey-Bass. ISBN 0787901040.
* Eames, Elizabeth. 1976. Sexism and woman as sex object. ''Journal of Thought'' 11(2):140–143.
* Holroyd, Julia. 2005. [http://www.brown.edu/Departments/Philosophy/conferencepapers/objectification.pdf Sexual objectification: The unlikely alliance of feminism and Kant] (conference paper). Society for Applied Philosophy International Congress 2005, Oxford, UK.
* LeMoncheck, Linda. 1985. ''Dehumanizing Women: Treating Persons as Sex Objects''. New York: Rowman &amp; Littlefield Publishers. ISBN 0847673316 (hc).
* [[Martha Nussbaum|Nussbaum, Martha C.]] 1995. Objectification. ''Philosophy and Public Affairs'' 24(4): 249–291. {{DOI|10.1111/j.1088-4963.1995.tb00032.x}}. ([http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0048-3915(199523)24%3A4%3C249%3AO%3E2.0.CO%3B2-U JSTOR link].)
* Papadaki, Evangelia. 2007. Sexual objectification: From Kant to contemporary feminism. ''Contemporary Political Theory'' 6(3):330–348. {{DOI|10.1057/palgrave.cpt.9300282}}.
* Shrage, Laurie. 2005. Exposing the fallacies of anti-porn feminism. ''Feminist Theory'' 6:45–65. {{DOI|10.1177/1464700105050226}}.
* [[Alan Soble|Soble, Alan]] (ed). 1997. ''Sex, Love and Friendship: Studies of the Society for the Philosophy of Sex and Love 1977–1992''. Amsterdam: Rodopi. ISBN 9042002271. Chapters 13–16.
* Soble, Alan. 2002. ''Pornography, Sex, and Feminism''. Amherst, NY: [[Prometheus Books]]. ISBN 1-57392-944-1 (pb).

==See also==
*[[Sexualization]]
*[[Lookism]]
*[[Gynophagia]]

==External links==
* [http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/feminist-sex-markets/#SexObj "Feminist Perspectives on Sex Markets: 1.3 Sexual Objectification"] by Laurie Shrage, ''[[Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy]]'' (online encyclopedia), July 13, 2007.
* [http://fetchmemyaxe.blogspot.com/2006/06/objectification.html  "Objectification"] by Belledame, ''Fetch my Axe'', June 5, 2006.
* [http://www.nearbycafe.com/loveandlust/steinberg/erotic/cn/cn5.html "Comes Naturally #5: On Sexual Objectification"] by David Steinberg, ''[[Spectator (magazine)|Spectator]]'', March 5, 1993. – Sex-positive feminist perspective on sexual objectification.
* [http://www.telegraph.co.uk/htmlContent.jhtml;?html=/archive/1996/10/05/tlpet05.html "Women Like Seeing Men as Sex Objects"]. Interview with [[Janet Anderson]] by [[Petronella Wyatt]], ''[[Daily Telegraph]]'', October 5, 1996.
* [http://www.psu.edu/dept/medialab/research/objectification.html Sexual Suggestiveness in Online Ads: Effects of Objectification on Opposite Genders] by Sriram Kalyanaraman, Michael Redding, and Jason Steele, ''Media Effects Research Laboratory, [[Pennsylvania State University]]'', 2000.</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>