<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20211128135716|1057584950" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="200977" pageid="200977" ns="0" title="Sexual objectification"><revisions><rev timestamp="2021-11-28T16:02:18Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Disregarding personality or dignity; reducing a person to a commodity or sex object}}
{{Redirect|Sex object}}
[[File:Hot Import Nights bikini contest 35.jpg|thumb|260x260px|Women in a [[bikini contest]] are valued for their bodies and sexual appeal over other attributes.]]
'''Sexual objectification''' is the act of treating a person solely as an [[Object (philosophy)|object]] of [[sexual desire]]. [[Objectification]] more broadly means treating a person as a [[commodity]] or an object without regard to their [[personality]] or [[dignity]]. Objectification is most commonly examined at the level of a society, but can also refer to the behavior of individuals and is a type of [[dehumanization]].

Although both males and females can be sexually objectified, the concept is mainly associated with the objectification of [[woman|women]], and is an important idea in many [[feminism|feminist]] theories and psychological theories derived from them. Many psychologists associate objectification with a range of physical and mental health risks in women.
{{Feminism sidebar}}

==Sexual objectification of women==
===General===
The sexual objectification of women involves them being viewed primarily as an object of male sexual desire, rather than as a whole person.&lt;ref name=Barry&gt;{{cite book |last=Barry |first=Kathleen |contribution=Pornography: the ideoloy of cultural sadism |editor-last=Barry |editor-first=Kathleen |title=Female sexual slavery |page=247 |publisher=NYU Press |location=New York London |year=1984 |isbn=978-0-8147-1069-2 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=LeMoncheck&gt;{{cite book |last=LeMoncheck |first=Linda |contribution=I only do it for the money: pornography, prostitution, and the business of sex |editor-last=LeMoncheck |editor-first=Linda |title=Loose women, lecherous men a feminist philosophy of sex |page=[https://archive.org/details/loosewomenlecher00lemo/page/133 133] |publisher=Oxford University Press |location=New York, New York |year=1997 |isbn=978-0-19-510556-8 |url=https://archive.org/details/loosewomenlecher00lemo/page/133 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Szymanski |first1=Dawn M. |last2=Moffitt |first2=Lauren B. |last3=Carr |first3=Erika R. |title=Sexual objectification of women: advances to theory and research |journal=[[The Counseling Psychologist]] |volume=39 |issue=1 |pages=6–38 |doi=10.1177/0011000010378402 |date=January 2011  |s2cid=17954950 |url=http://www.apa.org/education/ce/sexual-objectification.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Although opinions differ as to which situations are objectionable, many see the objectification of women taking place in the sexually oriented depictions of women in advertising, art and media, [[pornography]], the occupations of [[Striptease|stripping]] and [[prostitution]], and women being brazenly evaluated or judged sexually or aesthetically in public spaces and events, such as [[beauty contest]]s.&lt;ref name=Jhally&gt;{{cite AV media |last=Jhally |first=Sut (director) |author-link=Sut Jhally |date=1997 |title=Dreamworlds II: desire, sex, power in music |medium=Documentary |location=USA |publisher=[[Media Education Foundation]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Some feminists and psychologists&lt;ref name=fredrickson2&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Fredrickson |first1=Barbara L. |last2=Roberts |first2=Tomi-Ann |title=Objectification theory: toward understanding women's lived experiences and mental health risks |journal=[[Psychology of Women Quarterly]] |volume=21 |issue=2 |pages=173–206 |doi=10.1111/j.1471-6402.1997.tb00108.x |date=June 1997|s2cid=145272074 }}&lt;/ref&gt; argue that sexual objectification can lead to negative psychological effects including [[eating disorder]]s, [[depression (mood)|depression]] and [[sexual dysfunction]], and can give women negative [[self-image]]s because of the belief that their intelligence and competence are currently not being, nor will ever be, acknowledged by society.&lt;ref name=:0 /&gt; Sexual objectification of women has also been found to negatively affect women's performance, confidence, and level of position in the workplace.{{Citation Needed|date=June 2019}} How objectification has affected women and society in general is a topic of academic debate, with some saying girls' understanding of the importance of appearance in society may contribute to feelings of [[fear]], [[shame]], and [[disgust]] during the transition to womanhood,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Lee |first=Janet |title=Menarche and the (hetero)sexualization of the female body |journal=[[Gender &amp; Society]] |volume=8 |issue=3 |pages=343–362 |doi=10.1177/089124394008003004 |date=September 1994|s2cid=144282688 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and others saying that young women are especially susceptible to objectification, as they are often taught that [[Power (sociology)|power]], [[respect]], and [[wealth]] can be derived from one's outward appearance.&lt;ref name=apareport&gt;{{Cite report |title=Report of the American Psychological Association task force on the sexualization of girls, executive summary |publisher=[[American Psychological Association]] |location=Washington, DC |year=2010 |url=http://www.apa.org/pi/women/programs/girls/report-full.pdf |access-date=19 February 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{multiple_images
| perrow = 1
| total_width = 250
| image1 = Three's Company.jpg
| image2 = Show girls at motorcycle show 2012.jpg
| footer = Sexual objectification in advertisements occurs when the women shown have no relationship to the object being sold. Here, U.S. [[promotional models]] in bikinis and crop tops advertise a car battery brand (''top image''), and female models attract male customers to a motorcycle brand (''bottom image'').
}}

Pro-feminist cultural critics such as [[Robert W. Jensen|Robert Jensen]] and [[Sut Jhally]] accuse [[mass media]] and advertising of promoting the objectification of women to help promote goods and services,&lt;ref name=Jhally /&gt;&lt;ref name=Jensen&gt;{{cite book |last=Jensen |first=Robert |author-link=Robert Jensen |contribution=Using pornography |editor-last1=Dines |editor-first1=Gail |editor-last2=Jensen |editor-first2=Robert |editor-last3=Russo |editor-first3=Ann |editor-link1=Gail Dines |editor-link2=Robert Jensen |title=Pornography: the production and consumption of inequality |page=[https://archive.org/details/loosewomenlecher00lemo/page/133 133] |publisher=Oxford University Press |location=New York, New York |year=1997 |isbn=978-0-19-510556-8 |url=https://archive.org/details/loosewomenlecher00lemo/page/133 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Frith&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Frith |first1=Katherine |last2=Shaw |first2=Ping |last3=Cheng |first3=Hong |title=The construction of beauty: a cross-cultural analysis of women's magazine advertising |journal=[[Journal of Communication]] |volume=55 |issue=1 |pages=56–70 |doi=10.1111/j.1460-2466.2005.tb02658.x |date=March 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the television and film industries are commonly accused of normalizing the sexual objectification of women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://my.vanderbilt.edu/wgs272/2013/04/representations-of-women-in-reality-tv/|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190414044502/https://my.vanderbilt.edu/wgs272/2013/04/representations-of-women-in-reality-tv/|archive-date=14 April 2019|title=Representations of Women in Reality TV|date=15 April 2013|author=balembbn|website=Feminism and Film (blog)|via=Vanderbilt University}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The objection to the objectification of women is not a recent phenomenon. In the French [[Age of Enlightenment|Enlightenment]], for example, there was a debate as to whether a woman's breasts were merely a sensual enticement or rather a natural gift. In [[Alexandre Guillaume Mouslier de Moissy]]'s 1771 play ''The True Mother'' (''La Vraie Mère''), the title character rebukes her husband for treating her as merely an object for his sexual gratification: "Are your senses so gross as to look on these breasts &amp;ndash; the respectable treasures of nature &amp;ndash; as merely an embellishment, destined to ornament the chest of women?"&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Schama |first=Simon |author-link=Simon Schama |contribution=The cultural construction of a citizen: II Casting roles: children of nature |editor-last=Schama |editor-first=Simon |editor-link=Simon Schama |title=Citizens: a chronicle of the French Revolution |publisher=Knopf Distributed by Random House |location=New York |year=1989 |isbn=978-0-394-55948-3|title-link=Citizens. A Chronicle of the French Revolution }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The issues concerning sexual objectification became first [[problematization|problemized]] during the 1970s by feminist groups. Since then, it has been argued that the phenomenon of female sexual objectification has increased drastically since its problematization in all levels of life, and has resulted in negative consequences for women, especially in the political sphere. However, a rising form of new third-waver feminist groups have also taken the increased objectification of women as an opportunity to use the female body as a mode of power.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last = Heldman | first = Caroline | title = Sexualizing Sarah Palin: the social and political context of the sexual objectification of female candidates | journal = [[Sex Roles (journal)|Sex Roles]] | volume = 65 | issue = 3 | pages = 156&amp;ndash;164 | doi = 10.1007/s11199-011-9984-6 | date = August 2011 | s2cid = 141197696 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some have argued that the feminist movement itself has contributed to the problem of the sexual objectification of women by promoting  "free" love (i.e. men and women choosing to have non-reproductive sex outside of marriage and for their own pleasure).&lt;ref name=fredrickson2 /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Abrams |first1=Dominic |last2=Hogg |first2=Michael A. |contribution=Collective identity: group membership and self-conception |editor-last1=Brewer |editor-first1=Marilynn B. |editor-last2=Hewstone |editor-first2=Miles |editor-link1=Marilynn B. Brewer |title=Self and social identity |page=167 |publisher=Blackwell Publishing |location=Malden, Massachusetts |series=Perspectives on Social Psychology |year=2004 |isbn=978-1-4051-1069-3 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=aGhvm-QH1yEC&amp;q=Fredrickson+and+Roberts&amp;pg=RA1-PA136}}&lt;/ref&gt; One study found that men exposed to media content in which women were objectified were more likely to accept those behaviors than men who were exposed to content where women were not objectified.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1= Galdi |first1= Silvia |last2= Maass |first2= Anne | last3 = Cadinu | first3 = Mara | title = Objectifying media: their effect on gender role norms and sexual harassment of women | journal = [[Psychology of Women Quarterly]] | volume = 38 | issue = 3 | pages = 393&amp;ndash;413 | doi = 10.1177/0361684313515185 | date = September 2014 |s2cid= 145614917 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Latina women ===
Latina women face a particular form of sexual objectification based on [[Stereotypes of Latinos|stereotypes relating to Latina women.]] American media often portrays Latina women as being sexually promiscuous and curvaceous, having large breasts and butt, being melodramatic, or having a feisty attitude.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=McLaughlin|first1=Bryan|last2=Rodriguez|first2=Nathian S.|last3=Dunn|first3=Joshua A.|last4=Martinez|first4=Jobi|date=2018-09-03|title=Stereotyped Identification: How Identifying with Fictional Latina Characters Increases Acceptance and Stereotyping|url=https://doi.org/10.1080/15205436.2018.1457699|journal=Mass Communication and Society|volume=21|issue=5|pages=585–605|doi=10.1080/15205436.2018.1457699|s2cid=149715074|issn=1520-5436}}&lt;/ref&gt; Keller identifies three main stereotypes that contribute to the objectification of Latinas. (Cantina Girl, Suffering Senorita, and Vamp). The “Cantina Girl” is characterized as being an alluring sexual presence. The “Suffering Senorita” is the Latina who goes “bad” due to her love of the (usually Anglo) love interest. Lastly, the “Vamp” is seen as beautiful but devious, and a psychological threat for her wit or charm.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Merskin|first=Debra|date=2007-05-29|title=Three Faces of Eva: Perpetuation of The Hot-Latina Stereotype in Desperate Housewives|url=https://doi.org/10.1080/10646170701309890|journal=Howard Journal of Communications|volume=18|issue=2|pages=133–151|doi=10.1080/10646170701309890|s2cid=144571909|issn=1064-6175}}&lt;/ref&gt; All three of these categorizations stem from the sexual objectification of Latina women’s bodies and identities. 

Such sexual objectifications hold real world consequences for Latina women and [[Latinx|LatinX communities]]. For instance, the prevalence of negative Latina stereotypes (such as [[Sexualization|hypersexualization]]) has led to a decrease in positive [[Social identity theory|in-group attitudes]] among the LatinX community.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Tukachinsky|first1=Riva|last2=Mastro|first2=Dana|last3=Yarchi|first3=Moran|date=2017-07-03|title=The Effect of Prime Time Television Ethnic/Racial Stereotypes on Latino and Black Americans: A Longitudinal National Level Study|url=https://doi.org/10.1080/08838151.2017.1344669|journal=Journal of Broadcasting &amp; Electronic Media|volume=61|issue=3|pages=538–556|doi=10.1080/08838151.2017.1344669|s2cid=148590923|issn=0883-8151}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Sexual objectification of men==
===General===
Male sexual objectification involves a man being viewed primarily as an object of sexual desire, rather than as a whole person. Psychologist [[Harold Lyon]] suggests that men's liberation is a necessary step toward woman's liberation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Lyon|first1=Harold C.|title=Tenderness Is Strength|date=1977|publisher=Harper &amp; Row|location=New York|isbn=978-0060127138|edition=first}}&lt;/ref&gt;  

Instances where men may be viewed as sex objects by women include advertisements, [[sexuality in music videos|music videos]], films, television shows, [[beefcake]] calendars, [[women's magazine]]s, male [[striptease|strip shows]], and clothed female/nude male (CFNM) events.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.sensations4women.com/sportsIni/index.html |title=Sports, gym classes, team initiations and events |work=Sensations4women.com |date=26 January 1998 |access-date=1 August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Women also purchase and consume [[pornography]].&lt;ref&gt;''Citations'':
* {{cite book |last=McElroy |first=Wendy |author-link=Wendy McElroy |title=XXX: a woman's right to pornography |page=[https://archive.org/details/xxxwomansrightto00mcel/page/36 36] |publisher=St. Martin's Press |location=New York |year=1995 |isbn=978-0-312-13626-0 |url=https://archive.org/details/xxxwomansrightto00mcel/page/36 }}
* {{cite news |url=http://www.multichannel.com/article/79434-A_Playgirl_for_Adult_TV.php |title=A 'Playgirl" for adult TV |work=[[Multichannel News]] |publisher=[[NewBay Media]] |access-date=1 August 2012}}
* {{cite news |last=Taormino |first=Tristan |url=http://www.villagevoice.com/2008-05-13/coulumns/girls-love-gay-male-porn |title=Girls love gay male porn |work=[[The Village Voice]] |publisher=Josh Fromson |date=13 May 2008 |access-date=16 August 2012}}
* {{cite news |last=Scott |first=Lisa |url=http://www.metro.co.uk/lifestyle/356386-women-who-like-to-watch-gay-porn |title=Women who like to watch gay porn |work=[[Metro (British newspaper)|Metro]] |publisher=[[DMG Media]] |date=15 October 2008 |access-date=17 August 2012}}
* {{cite news |last=Murphy |first=Chris |title=Women's porn tastes: You'll never guess what ladies prefer |url=https://www.mirror.co.uk/news/weird-news/womens-porn-tastes-youll-never-5686920 |work=[[Daily Mirror]] |publisher=[[Trinity Mirror]]  |date=12 May 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Within gay male communities, men are often objectified by other men.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Teunis |first=Niels |title=Sexual objectification and the construction of whiteness in the gay male community |journal=[[Culture, Health &amp; Sexuality]] |volume=9 |issue=3 |pages=263–275 |jstor=20460929 |doi=10.1080/13691050601035597 |pmid=17457730 |date=May 2007 |s2cid=8287617 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Discussing negative effects of objectification is met with considerable resistance in the community. The sexual objectification of [[person of color|men of color]] may force them to play specific roles in sexual encounters that are not necessarily of their own choosing.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | doi=10.1080/13691050601035597| pmid=17457730|title = Sexual objectification and the construction of whiteness in the gay male community| journal=Culture, Health &amp; Sexuality| volume=9| issue=3| pages=263–275|year = 2007|last1 = Teunis|first1 = Niels| s2cid=8287617}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Research suggests that the psychological effects of objectification on men are similar to those of women, leading to negative [[body image]] among men.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Neimark |first=Jill |url=http://www.psychologytoday.com/articles/200910/the-beefcaking-america |title=The beefcaking of America |work=[[Psychology Today]] |publisher=Sussex Publishers |date=1 November 1994 |access-date=1 August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Media ===
Men's bodies have become more objectified than they previously were, though because of society's established gaze on the objectification of women, the newfound objectification of men is not as widespread.{{fact|date=April 2021}} Even with this increase of male objectification, males are still seen as the dominant figures and so the focus is still primarily on women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1= Tortajada-Giménez |first1= Iolanda |last2= Araüna-Baró |first2= Núria | last3 = Martínez-Martínez | first3 = Inmaculada José | title = Advertising stereotypes and gender representation in social networking sites | journal = Comunicar | volume = 21 | issue = 41 | pages = 177&amp;ndash;186 | date = 2013 | url = https://www.revistacomunicar.com/indice-en/articulo.php?numero=41-2013-17 |doi= 10.3916/C41-2013-17 | doi-access = free }} [https://doi.org/10.3916/C41-2013-17 Original Spanish article.]&lt;/ref&gt;

Male sexual objectification has been found in 37% of advertisements featuring men's body parts to showcase a product.&lt;ref name=":02"&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Davidson | first1 = M. Meghan | last2 = Gervais | first2 = Sarah J. | last3 = Canivez | first3 = Gary L. | last4 = Cole | first4 = Brian P. | title = A psychometric examination of the Interpersonal Sexual Objectification Scale among college men | journal = [[Journal of Counseling Psychology]] | volume = 60 | issue = 2 | pages = 239&amp;ndash;250 | doi = 10.1037/a0032075 | pmid = 23458607 | date = April 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Similar to the issues of sexual objectification in women, it is common for said objectification to lead men to body shaming, eating disorders, and a drive for perfection. The continued exposure of these "ideal" men subject society to expect all men to fit this role.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last = Buchbinder | first = David | author-link = David Buchbinder | title = Object or ground? The male body as fashion accessory | journal = [[Canadian Review of American Studies]] | volume = 34 | issue = 3 | pages = 221&amp;ndash;232 | doi = 10.1353/crv.2006.0030 | date = Winter 2004 | s2cid = 161493223 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Male actors featured in TV shows and movies are oftentimes in excellent shape and have the "ideal" bodies. These men often fill the leading roles. When society is subjected to men who do not have ideal bodies, we typically see them as the comic relief. It is rare to see an out of shape man have a leading role. Leanne  Dawson writes that "There are temporal, cultural and geographical ‘norms’ of gender and other aspects of identity, which are often incorrectly considered to be inherent or natural."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last = Dawson | first = Leanne | title = Passing and policing: controlling compassion, bodies and boundaries in ''Boys Don't Cry'' and ''Unveiled/Fremde Haut'' | journal = Studies in European Cinema | volume = 12 | issue = 3 | pages = 205&amp;ndash;228 | doi = 10.1080/17411548.2015.1094258 | date = 2015 | s2cid = 147349266 | url = https://www.pure.ed.ac.uk/ws/files/22121834/Dawson_SEC_2015_Passing_and_Policing.pdf | hdl = 20.500.11820/8f102aab-aa8c-4524-8cc1-18ff25ed0467 | hdl-access = free }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the media, the ideal version of a man is seen as a strong, toned man. The idealized version of a woman is thin.&lt;ref name="Aubrey" /&gt; Body evaluation is more commonly used to criticize women than men, and it can take different forms for men. For example, body evaluation is often directed at men's nonverbal cues. By contrast, women more often are subject to body evaluation in the form of sexual, sometimes offensive, verbal remarks. Men tend to experience this from other men, whereas women experience it from both sexes.&lt;ref name=":02" /&gt; The Interpersonal Sexual Objectification Scale (ISOS) is a scale that shows sexual objectification of respondents, both men and women. While experiencing sexual objectification it creates the need to constantly maintain and critique one's physical appearance. This leads to other things like eating disorders, body shaming, and anxiety. The ISOS scale can be related to objectification theory and sexism.&lt;ref name=":02" /&gt; Self-objectification, which is the way in which people evaluate themselves, is concentrated more on women.  Men typically experience it through media display.  To the extent that men do experience self-objectification, studies have shown that men typically do not experience its negative effects to the extent that women do.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|first1=Tomi-Ann|last1=Roberts|first2=Jennifer Y.|last2=Gettman|title=Mere Exposure: Gender Differences in the Negative Effects of Priming a State of Self-Objectification|url=https://doi.org/10.1023/B:SERS.0000032306.20462.22|journal=Sex Roles|date=1 July 2004|issn=1573-2762|pages=17–27|volume=51|issue=1|doi=10.1023/B:SERS.0000032306.20462.22|s2cid=55703429}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Aubrey"&gt;{{cite book | last = Stevens Aubrey | first = Jennifer |title=Investigating the role of self-objectification in the relationship between media exposure and sexual self-perceptions | url = http://www.icahdq.org/page/PastFuture | date = 27 May 2003 }} Paper presented at the annual meeting of the [[International Communication Association]], Marriott Hotel, San Diego, CA, May 27, 2003.
:''See also'': {{cite journal | last = Stevens Aubrey | first = Jennifer | title = Effects of sexually objectifying media on self-objectification and body surveillance in undergraduates: results of a 2-year panel study | journal = [[Journal of Communication]] | volume = 56 | issue = 2 | pages = 366&amp;ndash;386 | doi = 10.1111/j.1460-2466.2006.00024.x | date = June 2006 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the media, sexual objectification has been used as a way to sell products to the general public.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|first1=Amanda|last1=Zimmerman|first2=John|last2=Dahlberg|title=The Sexual Objectification of Women in Advertising: A Contemporary Cultural Perspective|url=http://www.journalofadvertisingresearch.com/content/48/1/71|journal=Journal of Advertising Research|date=1 March 2008|issn=0021-8499|pages=71–79|volume=48|issue=1|doi=10.2501/S0021849908080094|s2cid=30977582}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|first1=Lizardo|last1=Vargas-Bianchi|first2=Marta|last2=Mensa|title=Do you remember me? Women sexual objectification in advertising among young consumers|url=https://doi.org/10.1108/YC-04-2019-0994|journal=Young Consumers|date=1 January 2020|issn=1747-3616|pages=77–90|volume=21|issue=1|doi=10.1108/YC-04-2019-0994|s2cid=216353566}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sexual objectification has been used as a marketing strategy for many decades according to the Journal of Advertising. This specific strategy targets the public in selling products that will make them look and feel desirable and attractive. It is stated that this strategy sells well by grabbing the attention of the public. The journal states that explicit advertisements do better in marketing than other non-explicit ads.{{fact|date=April 2021}}

==Views on sexual objectification==
{{see also|Gaze}}
While the concept of sexual objectification is important within feminist theory, ideas vary widely on what constitutes sexual objectification and what are the ethical implications of such objectification. Some feminists such as [[Naomi Wolf]] find the concept of [[physical attractiveness]] itself to be problematic,&lt;ref name=beautymyth&gt;{{cite book |last=Wolf |first=Naomi |author-link=Naomi Wolf |title=The beauty myth: how images of beauty are used against women |publisher=Perennial |location=New York |year=2002 |orig-year=1992 |isbn=978-0-06-051218-7 |url=https://archive.org/details/beautymyth00naom }}&lt;/ref&gt; with some [[radical feminists]]  being opposed to any evaluation of another person's sexual attractiveness based on physical characteristics.{{Citation needed|reason=This claim needs references to reliable sources|date=September 2015}} [[John Stoltenberg]] goes so far as to condemn as wrongfully objectifying any sexual fantasy that involves the visualization of a woman.&lt;ref name=stoltenberg&gt;{{cite book |last=Stoltenberg |first=John |author-link=John Stoltenberg | chapter = Sexual objectification and male supremacy |chapter-url=http://www.feministes-radicales.org/wp-content/uploads/2010/11/Stoltenberg-Refusing-to-be-a-Man.pdf |title=Refusing to be a man: essays on sex and justice |publisher=UCL Press |location=London New York | page = 38 |year=2000 |isbn=978-1-84142-041-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Radical feminists view objectification as playing a central role in reducing women to what they refer to as the "oppressed sex [[Social class|class]]".{{Cite quote|date=September 2015}} While some feminists view mass media in societies that they argue are [[patriarchal]] to be objectifying, they often focus on [[pornography]] as playing an egregious role in habituating men to objectify women.&lt;ref name='MacKinnon "Only Words"'&gt;{{cite book |last=MacKinnon |first=Catharine |author-link=Catharine MacKinnon |title=Only words |url=https://archive.org/details/onlywords00mack |url-access=registration |publisher=Harvard University Press |location=Cambridge, Massachusetts |year=1993 |isbn=978-0-674-63934-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some [[social conservatives]] have taken up aspects of the [[feminist]] critique of sexual objectification. In their view however, the increase in the sexual objectification of both sexes in Western culture is one of the negative legacies of the [[sexual revolution]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Dr. James Dobson |url=http://www.theinterim.com/issues/society-culture/dr-james-dobson-6 |work=The Interim: Canada's life and family newspaper |location=[[Toronto, Ontario]], Canada |publisher=via [[True Media]] |date=12 January 1997 |access-date=1 August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=shalit1&gt;{{cite book |last=Shalit |first=Wendy |author-link=Wendy Shalit |title=A return to modesty: discovering the lost virtue |publisher=Touchstone |location=New York |year=2000 |isbn=978-0-684-86317-7 |url=https://archive.org/details/returntomodestyd00shal }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Reisman |first=Judith A. |author-link=Judith Reisman |title="Soft porn" plays hardball: its tragic effects on women, children, and the family |url=https://archive.org/details/softpornplayshar00reis/page/32 |url-access=registration |publisher=Huntington House Publishers |location=[[Lafayette, Louisiana]] |year=1991 |isbn=978-0-910311-92-2 |pages=[https://archive.org/details/softpornplayshar00reis/page/32 32–46, 173] }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Holz |first=Adam R. |title=Is average the new ugly? |url=http://www.pluggedin.com/familyroom/articles/2007/isaveragethenewugly.aspx |work=[[Plugged In|Plugged In Online]] |publisher=[[Focus on the Family]] |date=2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=National Coalition for the Protection of Children &amp; Families |url=http://pureintimacy.org/piArticles/A000000551.cfm |title=Subtle Dangers of Pornography (special report by the National Coalition for the Protection of Children &amp; Families) |work=Pure Intimacy (website) |publisher=[[Focus on the Family]] |date=July 1997 |access-date=1 August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; These critics, notably [[Wendy Shalit]], advocate a return to pre-sexual revolution standards of [[sexual morality]], which Shalit refers to as a "return to [[modesty]]", as an antidote to sexual objectification.&lt;ref name=shalit1/&gt;&lt;ref name=shalit2&gt;{{cite web |last=Shalit |first=Wendy |author-link=Wendy Shalit |title=Modesty revisited |url=http://www.orthodoxytoday.org/articles/ShalitModesty.php |website=orthodoxytoday.org |publisher=[[Antiochian Orthodox Christian Archdiocese of North America|Fr. Johannes Jacobse]] |date=2000}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Others contest feminist claims about the objectification of women. [[Camille Paglia]] holds that "[t]urning people into sex objects is one of the specialties of our species." In her view, objectification is closely tied to (and may even be identical with) the highest human faculties toward conceptualization and [[aesthetics]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Paglia |first=Camille |author-link=Camille Paglia |title=Sexual personae: art and decadence from Nefertiti to Emily Dickinson |publisher=Vintage Books |location=New York |year=1991 |isbn=978-0-679-73579-3|title-link=Sexual Personae: Art and Decadence from Nefertiti to Emily Dickinson }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Individualist feminist]] [[Wendy McElroy]] says, given that  'objectification' of women means to make women into sexual objects; it is meaningless because, 'sexual objects', taken literally, means nothing because inanimate objects do not have sexuality. She continues that women are their bodies as well as their minds and souls, and so focusing on a single aspect should not be "degrading".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=McElroy |first=Wendy |author-link=Wendy McElroy |title=A feminist overview of pornography, ending in a defense thereof |url=http://www.wendymcelroy.com/freeinqu.htm |website=WendyMcElroy.com |date=2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Objectification theory==
{{expert needed|Feminism|ex2=Gender Studies|section|reason=The prose is jargon-filled, repetitive and nearly impenetrable to laypeople. The structure needs improvement|date=January 2015}}
Objectification theory is a framework for understanding the experiences of women in cultures that sexual objectify them, proposed by [[Barbara Fredrickson]] and Tomi-Ann Roberts in 1997.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1 = Fredrickson|first1 = B. L.|author-link1 = Barbara Fredrickson|last2 = Roberts|first2 = T.-A.|year = 1997|title = Objectification Theory|journal = [[Psychology of Women Quarterly]]|volume = 21|issue = 2|pages = 173–206|doi = 10.1111/j.1471-6402.1997.tb00108.x|s2cid = 145272074}}&lt;/ref&gt; Within this framework, Fredrickson and Roberts draw conclusions about women's experiences. This theory states that, because of sexual objectification, women learn to internalize an outsider's view of their bodies as the primary view of themselves. Women, they explain, begin to view their bodies as objects separate from their person. This internalization has been termed self-objectification. This theory does not seek to prove the existence of sexual objectification; the theory assumes its existence in culture. This self-objectification then, according to objectification theory, leads to increased habitual body monitoring. With this framework in mind, Fredrickson and Roberts suggest explanations for consequences they believe are the result of sexual objectification. The consequences suggested are: increased feelings of shame, increased feelings of anxiety, decreased peak motivational state, and decreased awareness of internal bodily states.

Sexual objectification has been studied based on the proposition that girls and women develop their primary view of their physical selves from observing others. These observations can take place in the media or through personal experience.&lt;ref name=bartky&gt;{{cite book |last=Bartky |first=Sandra Lee |author-link=Sandra Bartky |chapter=On Psychological Oppression |title=Femininity and Domination: Studies in the Phenomenology of Oppression |page=[https://archive.org/details/femininitydomina00bart/page/22 22]-32 |publisher=[[Routledge]] |location=New York |year=1990 |isbn=978-0-415-90186-4 |url=https://archive.org/details/femininitydomina00bart |url-access=registration }}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|26}} Through a blend of expected and actual exposure, women are socialized to objectify their own physical characteristics from a [[Grammatical person|third-person]] perception, which is identified as self-objectification.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Kaschak |first=Ellyn |author-link=Ellyn Kaschak |title=Engendered Lives: A New Psychology of Women's Experience |url=https://archive.org/details/engenderedlivesn00kascrich |url-access=registration |page=[https://archive.org/details/engenderedlivesn00kascrich/page/12 12] |publisher=[[Basic Books]] |location=New York, New York |year=1992 |isbn=978-0-465-01349-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; Women and girls develop an expected physical appearance for themselves, based on observations of others; and are aware that others are likely to observe as well. The sexual objectification and self-objectification of women is believed to influence social [[gender roles]] and inequalities between the sexes.&lt;ref name=Goldenberg&gt;{{cite book |last1=Goldenberg |first1=Jamie L. |last2=Roberts |first2=Tomi-Ann |chapter=The Beast within the Beauty: An Existential Perspective on the Objectification and Condemnation of Women |editor-last1=Greenberg |editor-first1=Jeff |editor-link1=Jeff Greenberg |editor-last2=Koole |editor-first2=Sander L. |editor-last3=Pyszczynski |editor-first3=Thomas A. |editor-link3=Tom Pyszczynski |title=Handbook of Experimental Existential Psychology |pages=71–85 |publisher=[[Guilford Press]] |location=New York |year=2004 |isbn=978-1-59385-040-1 |chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=j_KMRe9wK2MC&amp;pg=PA71 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Psychological consequences===
Objectification theory suggests both direct and indirect consequences of objectification to women. Indirect consequences include [[self consciousness]] in terms that a woman is consistently checking or rearranging her clothes or appearance to ensure that she is presentable. More direct consequences are related to sexual victimization. Rape and sexual harassment are examples of this.&lt;ref name=fredrickson2 /&gt; Doob (2012) states that sexual harassment is one of the challenges faced by women in workplace. This may constitute sexual jokes or comments, most of which are degrading.&lt;ref name="Doob"&gt;{{cite book |last=Doob |first=Christopher B. |title=Social Inequality and Social Stratification in US Society |publisher=[[Pearson Education, Inc.]] |location=Upper Saddle River, New Jersey |year=2013 |isbn=978-0-205-79241-2}}&lt;/ref&gt; Research indicates that objectification theory is valuable to understanding how repeated visual images in the media are socialized and translated into [[mental health]] problems, including psychological consequences on the individual and societal level.&lt;ref name=fredrickson2 /&gt; These include increased self-consciousness, increased body anxiety, heightened mental health threats ([[Clinical depression|depression]], [[anorexia nervosa]], [[bulimia]], and [[sexual dysfunction]]), and increased body shame.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Moradi |first1=Bonnie |last2=Huang |first2=Yu-Ping |title=Objectification Theory and Psychology of Women: A Decade of Advances and Future Directions |journal=[[Psychology of Women Quarterly]] |volume=32 |issue=4 |pages=377–398 |doi=10.1111/j.1471-6402.2008.00452.x |year=2008 |s2cid=144389646 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Therefore, the theory has been used to explore an array of dependent variables including [[disordered eating]], [[mental health]], [[Clinical depression|depression]], motor performance, [[body image]], idealized body type, [[stereotype]] formation, sexual perception and sexual typing.&lt;ref name=fredrickson2/&gt;&lt;ref name=frederickson1.82&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Fredrickson |first1=Barbara L. |last2=Harrison |first2=Kristen |author-link1=Barbara Fredrickson |title=Throwing like a Girl: Self-Objectification Predicts Adolescent Girls' Motor Performance |journal=[[Journal of Sport and Social Issues]] |volume=29 |issue=1 |pages=79–101 |doi=10.1177/0193723504269878 |year=2005 |s2cid=146312527 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Body shame is a byproduct of the concept of an idealized body type adopted by most Western cultures that depicts a thin, model-type figure. Thus, women will engage in actions meant to change their body such as dieting, exercise, eating disorders, [[cosmetic surgery]], etc.&lt;ref name=fredrickson2 /&gt; Effects of objectification theory are identified on both the individual and societal levels.

===Causes of depression===
[[Learned helplessness]] theory posits that because human bodies are only alterable to a certain point, people develop a sense of body shame and anxiety from which they create a feeling of helplessness in relation to correcting their physical appearance and helplessness in being able to control the way in which others perceive their appearance. This lack of control often results in depression.&lt;ref name=fredrickson2 /&gt; In relating to a lack of motivation, objectification theory states that women have less control in relationships and the work environment because they have to depend on the evaluation of another who is typically basing their evaluation on physical appearance. Since the dependence on another's evaluation limits a woman's ability to create her own positive experiences and motivation, it adversely increases her likelihood for depression.&lt;ref name=fredrickson2 /&gt; Furthermore, sexual victimization may be a cause. Specifically, victimization within the workplace degrades women. Harassment experienced every day wears on a woman, and sometimes this results in a state of depression.&lt;ref name=fredrickson2 /&gt;&lt;ref name="Doob"/&gt;

==See also==
{{Commons category}}
{{Div col|colwidth=22em}}

*[[Dehumanization]]
*[[Exploitation of women in mass media]]
*[[Human furniture]]
*[[Male gaze]]
*[[Pornographication]]
*[[Rape culture]]
*[[Sex in advertising]]
*[[Sexuality in music videos]]
*[[Sex in film]]

{{div col end}}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
* {{cite book |last=Bartky |first=Sandra Lee |author-link=Sandra Bartky |title=Femininity and domination: studies in the phenomenology of oppression |url=https://archive.org/details/femininitydomina00bart |url-access=registration |publisher=Routledge |location=New York |year=1990 |isbn=978-0-415-90186-4}}
* {{cite book |last=Berger |first=John |author-link=John Berger |title=Ways of Seeing |publisher=BBC and Penguin Books |year=1972 |location=London|title-link=Ways of Seeing }} {{ISBN|0-563-12244-7}} (BBC), {{ISBN|0-14-021631-6}}, {{ISBN|0-14-013515-4}} (pbk).
* {{Cite journal |last1=Bridges |first1=Ana J. |last2=Johnson |first2=Jennifer A. |last3=Dines |first3=Gail |last4=Condit |first4=Deirdre M. |last5=West |first5=Carolyn M. |author-link1=Ana J. Bridges |author-link2=Jennifer A. Johnson |author-link3=Gail Dines |author-link5=Carolyn M. West |title=Introducing ''Sexualization, Media &amp; Society'' |journal=[[Sexualization, Media, &amp; Society]] |volume=1 |issue=1 |pages=487–515 |doi=10.1177/2374623815588763 |date=April 2015  |doi-access=free }}
* {{cite book |last=Brooks |first=Gary R. |title=The centerfold syndrome: how men can overcome objectification and achieve intimacy with women |publisher=Jossey-Bass |year=1995 |location=San Francisco |isbn=978-0-7879-0104-2}} 
* {{Cite journal |last1=Coy |first1=Maddy |last2=Garner |first2=Maria |author-link1=Maddy Coy |title=Glamour modelling and the marketing of self-sexualization: critical reflections |journal=[[International Journal of Cultural Studies]] |volume=13 |issue=6 |pages=657–675 |doi=10.1177/1367877910376576 |date=November 2010 |s2cid=145230875 }}
* {{Cite journal |last=Eames |first=Elizabeth R. |title=Sexism and woman as sex object |journal=Journal of Thought |volume=11 |issue=2 |pages=140–143 |date=1976 |url= http://journalofthought.com/?page_id=66 }} [http://eric.ed.gov/?id=EJ147519 Preview.] [Link Broken]
* {{cite conference |last=Holroyd |first=Julia |title=Sexual objectification: The unlikely alliance of feminism and Kant |conference=Society for Applied Philosophy International Congress |date=2005 |location=Oxford, UK |url=http://www.brown.edu/Departments/Philosophy/conferencepapers/objectification.pdf |url-status=bot: unknown |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20050521221242/http://www.brown.edu/Departments/Philosophy/conferencepapers/objectification.pdf |archive-date=2005-05-21 }} (conference paper)
* {{cite book |last=LeMoncheck |first=Linda |title=Dehumanizing Women: Treating Persons as Sex Objects |publisher=Rowman &amp; Littlefield |year=1985 |location=New York |isbn=978-0-8476-7386-5 |url-access=registration |url=https://archive.org/details/dehumanizingwome0000lemo }}
* {{Cite journal |last=Nussbaum |first=Martha C. |title=Objectification |author-link=Martha Nussbaum |journal=[[Philosophy &amp; Public Affairs]] |volume=24 |issue=4 |pages=249–291 |doi=10.1111/j.1088-4963.1995.tb00032.x |jstor=2961930 |date=October 1995}}
* {{Cite journal |last=Papadaki |first=Evangelia (Lina) |title=Sexual objectification: From Kant to contemporary feminism |journal=[[Contemporary Political Theory]] |volume=6 |issue=3 |pages=330–348 |doi=10.1057/palgrave.cpt.9300282 |date=August 2007  |s2cid=144197352 |url=http://www.palgrave-journals.com/cpt/journal/v6/n3/pdf/9300282a.pdf}}
* {{cite news |last=Parker |first=Kathleen |author-link=Kathleen Parker |title='Save the males': Ho culture lights fuses, but confuses |url=http://www.nydailynews.com/lifestyle/2008/06/30/2008-06-30_save_the_males_ho_culture_lights_fuses_b.html |work=[[Daily News (New York)|Daily News]] |location=New York |date=30 June 2008}} 
* {{cite book |last=Paul |first=Pamela |author-link=Pamela Paul |title=Pornified: how pornography is transforming our lives, our relationships, and our families |publisher=Times Books |location=New York |year=2005 |isbn=978-0-8050-8132-9}}
* [[Mario Perniola]], ''The Sex-appeal of the inorganic'', translated by Massimo Verdicchio, London-New York, [[Continuum International Publishing Group|Continuum]], 2004.
* {{Cite journal |last=Sharge |first=Laurie |title=Exposing the fallacies of anti-porn feminism |journal=[[Feminist Theory (journal)|Feminist Theory]] |volume=6 |issue=1 |pages=45–65 |doi=10.1177/1464700105050226 |date=April 2005 |s2cid=145194517 }}
* {{cite book |last=Soble |first=Alan |title=Pornography, Sex, and Feminism |publisher=[[Prometheus Books]] |year=2002 |location=Amherst, New York|isbn= 978-1-57392-944-8}}

==External links==
* Papadaki, Evangelia (March 10, 2010), "[http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/feminism-objectification/ Feminist perspectives on objectification]", in {{cite book | editor-last = Zalta | editor-first = Edward N. | editor-link = Edward N. Zalta | title = Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy | title-link = Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy }}
* Shrage, Laurie (July 13, 2007), "[http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/feminist-sex-markets/#SexObj Feminist perspectives on sex markets: 1.3 sexual objectification]", in {{cite book | editor-last = Zalta | editor-first = Edward N. | editor-link = Edward N. Zalta | title = Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy  | title-link = Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy }}
* {{cite web | last = Steinberg | first = David | title = On Sexual Objectification | url = http://www.nearbycafe.com/loveandlust/steinberg/erotic/cn/cn5.html | work = [[Spectator Magazine]] &amp;#124; Comes Naturally column #5 | date = March 5, 1993 }} – Sex-positive feminist perspective on sexual objectification.
* {{cite news | last = Wyatt | first = Petronella | author-link = Petronella Wyatt | title = Women like seeing men as sex objects | url = https://www.telegraph.co.uk/htmlContent.jhtml;?html=%2Farchive%2F1996%2F10%2F05%2Ftlpet05.html | work = [[Daily Telegraph]] | date = October 5, 1996 | url-status = bot: unknown | archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20080530044627/http://www.telegraph.co.uk/htmlContent.jhtml;?html=%2Farchive%2F1996%2F10%2F05%2Ftlpet05.html | archive-date = May 30, 2008 }} Interview with [[Janet Anderson]].
* {{cite web | last1 = Kalyanaraman | first1 = Sriram | last2 = Redding | first2 = Michael | last3 = Steele | first3 = Jason | title = Sexual suggestiveness in online ads: effects of objectification on opposite genders | archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20080208172715/http://www.psu.edu/dept/medialab/research/objectification.html | archive-date = February 8, 2008 | url = http://www.psu.edu/dept/medialab/research/objectification.html | website = psu.edu/dept/medialab | publisher = Media Effects Research Laboratory, [[Pennsylvania State University]] | date = 2000 }}
*Davis, Stefanie E (July 13, 2018) [https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/full/10.1177/2056305118786727 "Objectification, Sexualization and Misrepresentation: Social Media and the College Experience"]  Sage Journals 
*Bello, D. C., Pitts, R. E., &amp; Etzel, M. J. (1983). The communication effects of controversial sexual content in television programs and commercials. ''Journal of Advertising'', ''12''(3), 32-42.  
*Hill, M. S., &amp; Fischer, A. R. (2008). Examining objectification theory: Lesbian and heterosexual women's experiences with sexual-and self-objectification. The Counseling Psychologist, 36(5), 745-776. https://doi.org/10.1177/0011000007301669   

;[[WP:UGC|User generated content]]
* {{cite web | last = Tigtog | title = FAQ: What is sexual objectification? | url = http://finallyfeminism101.wordpress.com/2007/03/23/faq-what-is-sexual-objectification/ | website = finallyfeminism101.wordpress.com | publisher = Finally, A Feminism 101 Blog via [[WordPress]] | date = March 23, 2007}}
* {{cite AV media | people= [[Karen Straughan]] | date= March 28, 2012 |access-date= June 7, 2017 | title= I'm a sexy woman, so stop objectifying me! | medium= Video | publisher= [[Karen Straughan]] via [[YouTube]] | url = https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=d-N9daqANcw }}

{{Sexual ethics|state=expand}}
{{Nudity|state=expand}}
{{Authority control}}
[[Category:Sexualization]]
[[Category:Sexuality and society]]
[[Category:Feminist terminology]]
[[Category:Feminist theory]]
[[Category:Philosophy of sexuality]]
[[Category:Postmodern theory]]
[[Category:Sexual attraction]]
[[Category:Human sexuality]]
[[Category:Sexual fetishism]]
[[Category:Sexual ethics]]
[[Category:Pornography]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>