<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20121114042738|522942363" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="200977" pageid="200977" ns="0" title="Sexual objectification"><revisions><rev timestamp="2012-11-14T04:29:20Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">:''"Sex object" redirects here. For other uses, see [[Sex object (disambiguation)]]''
'''Sexual objectification''' refers to the practice of regarding or treating another person merely as an instrument (object) towards one's sexual pleasure, and a sex object is a person who is regarded simply as an object of sexual gratification. [[Objectification]] more broadly is an attitude that regards a person as a commodity or as an object for use, with little or no regard for a person's [[Personality type|personality]] or [[sentience]].&lt;ref name=Bartky/&gt;&lt;ref name=LeMoncheck&gt;LeMoncheck, Linda, ''Loose Women, Lecherous Men: A Feminist Philosophy of Sex'' (Oxford University press, 1997), ISBN 978-0-19-510556-8, p. 133&lt;/ref&gt; Objectification is most commonly examined at a societal level, but can also arise at an individual level.

The concept of sexual [[objectification]] and, in particular, the objectification of [[women]], is an important idea in [[feminist]] theory and psychological theories derived from feminism.&lt;ref name=Barry&gt;Barry, Kathleen, ''Female Sexual Slavery'' (NYU Press, 1994), ISBN 978-0-8147-1069-2, p.247&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Goldenberg&gt;Goldenberg, Jamie L., and Tomi-Ann Roberts, 'The Beast within the Beauty: An Existential Perspective on the Objectification and Condemnation of Women' in Jeff Greenberg, Sander Leon Koole, Thomas A. Pyszczynski and Tom Pyszczynski (eds) ''Handbook of Experimental Existential Psychology'' (Guilford Press, 2004), ISBN 978-1-59385-040-1&lt;/ref&gt; Many [[feminists]] regard sexual objectification as objectionable and as playing an important role in [[gender inequality]].&lt;ref name=Bartky&gt;Bartky, Sandra Lee, ''Femininity and Domination: Studies in the Phenomenology of Oppression'' (Routledge, 1990), ISBN 0-415-90186-3, p. 26&lt;/ref&gt; Some social commentators, however, argue that some modern women objectify themselves as an expression of their [[empowerment]] over men, while others argue that increased sexual freedom for women, [[gay]], and [[bisexual]] men has led to an increase of the objectification of men.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://yoyo.cc.monash.edu.au/~farmboy/dis.html |title=Men As Sex Objects (turnin' the tables) |publisher=Yoyo.cc.monash.edu.au |date= |accessdate=2012-08-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.haaretz.com/hasen/spages/958248.html Study: For Israeli women, going on vacation means more sex] Irit Rosenblum, Haaretz, 26/02/2008.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Botting, Kate and Botting, Douglas. "Men Can Be Sex Objects Too". Cosmopolitan. August 1996.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2006/may/15/gender.features11 No more faking:] "Sex isn't over until we've had an orgasm...," say Melinda Gallagher and Emily Kramer, founders of the outrageous Cake sex empire for women. But is their love of porn and lapdancing breaking new ground, or is so-called 'raunch feminism' setting the cause back?
Sharon Krum The Guardian, Monday May 15, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Simpson|first=Mark |url=http://www.marksimpson.com/blog/2007/02/11/speedophobia |title= Speedophobia: America's Fear and Loathing of Budgie Smuggling |publisher=Marksimpson.com |date= |accessdate=2012-08-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; The idea of sexual objectification has also been an important area of discussion and debate in the area of [[sexual ethics]] and the [[philosophy of sex]].&lt;ref&gt;See, for example – [[Alan Soble|Soble, Alan]] (ed). 1997. ''Sex, Love and Friendship: Studies of the Society for the Philosophy of Sex and Love 1977–1992''. Amsterdam: Rodopi. ISBN 90-420-0227-1. Chapters 13–16.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Sexual objectification of women==
Feminist scholars say that the objectification of women involves the act of disregarding the personal and intellectual abilities and capabilities of a female; and reducing a woman's worth or role in society to that of an instrument for the sexual pleasure that she can produce in the mind of another.&lt;ref name=LeMoncheck/&gt;&lt;ref name=Barry/&gt;  Although opinions differ as to which situations are objectionable, some feminists see objectification of women taking place in the sexually oriented depictions of women in advertising and media, women being portrayed as weak or submissive through [[pornography]], images in more mainstream [[Published media|media]] such as [[advertising]] and [[art]], [[Striptease|stripping]] and [[prostitution]], men brazenly evaluating or judging women sexually or aesthetically in public spaces, and the presumed need for [[cosmetic surgery]], particularly [[breast enlargement]] and [[labiaplasty]].{{Citation needed|date=April 2008}}

Feminists argue {{who|date=October 2012}} that women have historically been valued mainly for their physical attributes. Some feminists and psychologists argue that such objectification can lead to negative psychological effects including [[depression (mood)|depression]] and [[hope]]lessness, and can give women negative [[self-image]]s because of the belief that their intelligence and competence are currently not being, or will never be, acknowledged by society. Some would argue that the feminist movement itself has contributed to the problem of the sexual objectification of women. By pushing for an end to the so-called oppressive patriarchal marriage, thinking that it would be best if the newly liberated women could just be freelovers and have sex with random  partners outside the so-called oppressive patriarchal marriage system.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
  | last =Hewstone
  | first =Miles
  | authorlink =Miles Hewstone
  | coauthors = [[Marilynn B. Brewer]]
  | title =Self and Social Identity
  | publisher =Blackwell Publishing Professional
  | date = 2004-01-01
  | location =
  | page =167
  | url =http://books.google.com/?id=aGhvm-QH1yEC&amp;pg=RA1-PA136&amp;lpg=RA1-PA136&amp;dq=Fredrickson+and+Roberts
  | doi =
  | isbn = 978-1-4051-1069-3  ISBN 1-4051-1069-4  }}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal
  | last = Fredrickson
  | first =Barbara L.
  | authorlink =Barbara Fredrickson
  | coauthors =Tomi-Ann Roberts
  | title =Objectification Theory: Toward understanding women's lived experiences and mental health risks
  | journal =Psychology of Women Quarterly
  | volume =21
  | issue =2
  | pages =172–206
  | publisher =
  | date =
  | url = http://www3.interscience.wiley.com/journal/119947167/abstract?CRETRY=1&amp;SRETRY=0
  | doi = 10.1111/j.1471-6402.1997.tb00108.x
  | id =
  | accessdate = 2008-12-11 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The precise degree to how objectification has affected women and society in general is a topic of academic debate. Such claims include: girls' understanding of the importance of appearance in society may contribute to feelings of [[fear]], [[shame]], and [[disgust]] that some experience during the transition from girlhood to womanhood because they sense that they are becoming more visible to society as sexual objects;&lt;ref&gt;Lee, Janet. 1994. Menarche and the (hetero)sexualization of the female body. ''Gender &amp; Society'' 8(3):343–362. {{DOI|10.1177/089124394008003004}}&lt;/ref&gt; and that young women are especially susceptible to objectification, as they are often taught that [[Power (sociology)|power]], [[respect]], and [[wealth]] can be derived from one's outward appearance.&lt;ref name=apareport&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.apa.org/pi/wpo/sexualizationsum.html
|title=Report of the APA Task Force on the Sexualization of Girls, Executive Summary
|accessdate=November 2, 2007
|author=APA Task Force on the Sexualization of Girls
|date=2007-02-19
|publisher=[[American Psychological Association]]
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Pro-feminist cultural critics such as [[Robert Jensen]] and [[Sut Jhally]] accuse [[mass media]] and advertising of promoting the objectification of women to help promote goods and services.&lt;ref name= Jensen&gt;Jensen, Robert, 'Using Pornography' in Dines, Gail, Robert Jensen and Ann Russo (eds) ''Pornography: The Production and Consumption of Inequality'' (Routledge, 1998), ISBN 978-0-415-91813-8&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Jhally&gt;Jhally, Sut (dir) ''Dreamworlds II: Desire, Sex, Power in Music'' (Media Education Foundation, USA, 1997)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Frith&gt;Frith, Katherine, Ping Shaw and Hong Cheng 'The Construction of Beauty: A Cross-Cultural Analysis of Women's Magazine Advertising' in ''Journal of Communication'' 55 (1), 2005, pp.56–70&lt;/ref&gt;

The objection to the objectification of women is not a recent phenomenon. In the French [[Age of Enlightenment|Enlightenment]], for example, there was a debate as to whether a woman's breasts were merely a sensual enticement or rather a natural gift. In [[Alexandre Guillaume Mouslier de Moissy]]'s 1771 play ''The True Mother'' (''La Vraie Mère''), the title character rebukes her husband for treating her as merely an object for his sexual gratification: "Are your senses so gross as to look on these breasts &amp;ndash; the respectable treasures of nature &amp;ndash; as merely an embellishment, destined to ornament the chest of women?"&lt;ref&gt;Simon Schama. ''Citizens. A Chronicle of the French Revolution'', p. 147. New York: Alfred A. Knopf, Inc., 1989. ISBN 0-394-55948-7.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Female self-objectification===
Feminists such as [[Ariel Levy]] contend that exploitation by Western women of their sexuality  by, for example, wearing revealing clothing and engaging in lewd behavior, are forms of female self-objectification. While some women see such behaviour as a form of [[empowerment]], critics contend that it has led to greater emphasis on a physical criterion or [[sexualization]] for women's perceived self-worth, which Levy calls "raunch culture".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nydailynews.com/lifestyle/2008/06/30/2008-06-30_save_the_males_ho_culture_lights_fuses_b.html 'Save the males': Ho culture lights fuses, but confuses], By KATHLEEN PARKER, NY Daily News, June 30th 2008. Based on "Save the Males" by Kathleen Parker, Copyright  2008, Random House, an imprint of Random House Publishing Group.&lt;/ref&gt;

Levy discusses this phenomenon in ''[[Female Chauvinist Pigs|Female Chauvinist Pigs: Women and the Rise of Raunch Culture]]''. Levy followed the camera crew from the ''[[Girls Gone Wild (franchise)|Girls Gone Wild]]'' video series, and argues that contemporary America's sexualized culture not only objectifies women, it encourages women to objectify themselves.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://women.timesonline.co.uk/tol/life_and_style/women/article2523264.ece | work=The Times | location=London | title=Yes we are bovvered | first=Ginny | last=Dougary | date=September 25, 2007 | accessdate=May 23, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; In today's culture, Levy writes, the idea of a woman participating in a wet T-shirt contest or being comfortable watching explicit [[pornography]] has become a symbol of feminist strength; she says that she was surprised at how many people, both men and women, working for programs such as ''Girls Gone Wild'' told her that this new "raunchy" culture marked not the ''downfall'' of feminism but its ''triumph'', because it proved that U.S. women have become strong enough to express their sexuality publicly.

== Sexual objectification of men ==
[[Feminist]] authors [[Christina Hoff Sommers]] and [[Naomi Wolf]] write that women's sexual liberation has led many women to a [[role reversal]], whereby they view men as sex objects,&lt;ref&gt;Sommers, Christina Hoff. 1994. ''Who Stole Feminism: How Women Have Betrayed Women''. New York. Simon and Schuster (pp.264-265), ISBN 0-671-7924-8 (hc), ISBN 0-684-80156-6 (pb)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Wolf, Naomi. 1994. ''Fire With Fire: The New Female Power and How to Use It''. New York: Fawcett Columbine (pp.225-228), ISBN 0-449-90951-4.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Friend,Tad. ''Yes (feminist women who like sex)'' Esquire. February 1994&lt;/ref&gt; in a manner similar to what they criticize men's treatment of women. Research has suggested that the psychological effects of objectification on men are similar to those of women, leading to negative [[body image]] among men.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Neimark |first=Jill |url=http://www.psychologytoday.com/articles/200910/the-beefcaking-america |title=The Beefcaking of America |publisher=Psychologytoday.com |date= |accessdate=2012-08-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Instances where men are viewed as sex objects by women include [[advertising]], [[sexuality in music videos|music videos]], [[movies]] and [[television shows]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/EatingTheEyeCandy |title=Eating the Eye Candy |publisher=Tvtropes.org |date= |accessdate=2012-08-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/FemaleGaze |title=Female Gaze |publisher=Tvtropes.org |date=2004-06-21 |accessdate=2012-08-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/ShirtlessScene |title=Shirtless Scene |publisher=Tvtropes.org |date= |accessdate=2012-08-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://archive.is/qmfN|title=Female Friendly Advertising |publisher=Mankinirevolution.com |date= |accessdate=2012-08-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[beefcake calendars]],  women's magazines, male [[striptease|strip shows]], and [[clothed female nude male]] (CFNM) events.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sensations4women.com/sportsIni/index.html |title=Sports, Gym Classes, Team Initiations and Events |publisher=Sensations4women.com |date=1998-01-26 |accessdate=2012-08-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dancingbear.com |title=Tale of the Dancing Bear |publisher=Dancingbear.com |date= |accessdate=2012-08-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; Also, more women are purchasing and consuming [[pornography]].&lt;ref&gt;McElroy, Wendy. 1995. ''XXX: A Woman's Right to Pornography''. New York: St. Martin's Press (p.36)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Dulcie Pearce |url=http://www.thesun.co.uk/sol/homepage/features/article2355510.ece |title=66% of women watch porn |publisher=Thesun.co.uk |date=2009-04-01 |accessdate=2012-08-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.multichannel.com/article/79434-A_Playgirl_for_Adult_TV.php |title=A 'Playgirl" for Adult TV |publisher=Multichannel.com |date= |accessdate=2012-08-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Taormino |first=Tristan |url=http://www.villagevoice.com/2008-05-13/coulumns/girls-love-gay-male-porn |title=Girls Love Gay Male Porn |publisher=Villagevoice.com |date=2008-05-13 |accessdate=2012-08-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Scott |first=Lisa |url=http://www.metro.co.uk/lifestyle/356386-women-who-like-to-watch-gay-porn |title=Women who like to watch gay porn |publisher=Metro,co.uk |date=2008-10-15 |accessdate=2012-08-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Views on sexual objectification ==
{{related|[[Gaze#The "male gaze" in feminist theory|The gaze]]}}
While the concept of sexual objectification is important within feminist theory, ideas vary widely on what constitutes sexual objectification and what are the ethical implications of such objectification. Some feminists such as [[Naomi Wolf]] find the concept of [[physical attractiveness]] itself to be problematic,&lt;ref name=beautymyth&gt;Wolf, Naomi. (1992). ''The Beauty Myth: How Images of Beauty Are Used Against Women''. New York: William Morrow and Co. (Reprinted, 2002. New York: Harper Perennial) ISBN 0-06-051218-0&lt;/ref&gt; with some [[radical feminists]] being opposed to any evaluation of another person's sexual attractiveness based on physical characteristics. [[John Stoltenberg]] goes so far as to condemn as wrongfully objectifying any sexual fantasy that involves visualization of a woman.&lt;ref name=stoltenberg&gt;Stoltenberg, John. 1989. Refusing to be a man: Essays on sex and justice. Portland, OR: Breitenbush Books. (Reprinted, 2000. Oxford: Routledge) ISBN 1-84142-041-7&lt;/ref&gt;

Radical feminists view objectification as playing a central role in reducing women to what they refer to as the "sex [[Social class|class]]". While some feminists view mass media in societies that they argue are [[patriarchal]] to be objectifying, they often focus on [[pornography]] as playing an egregious role in habituating men to objectify women.&lt;ref name='MacKinnon "Only Words"'&gt;{{cite book|last=MacKinnon|first=Catharine|title=Only Words|year=1992|publisher=Harvard University Press|isbn=978-0-674-63934-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Other feminists, particularly those identified with [[sex-positive feminism]], take a different view of sexual objectification and see it as a problem when it is not counterbalanced by women's sense of their own sexual subjectivity.{{Citation needed|date=April 2008}}

Some [[social conservatives]] have taken up aspects of the [[feminist]] critique of sexual objectification. In their view however, the increase in the sexual objectification of both sexes in Western culture is one of the negative legacies of the [[sexual revolution]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.theinterim.com/issues/society-culture/dr-james-dobson-6 |title=Dr. James Dobson |publisher=Theinterim.com |date=1997-01-12 |accessdate=2012-08-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=shalit1&gt;Shalit, Wendy. 1999. ''A Return To Modesty: Discovering the Lost Virtue''. New York: Free Press. ISBN 0-684-84316-1 (hc), ISBN 0-684-86317-0 (pb).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Riesman, Judith A. 1991. ''Soft Porn Plays Hardball: Its Tragic Effects on Women, Children and the Family.'' Lafayette, LA.  Huntington House Publishers. ( pp.32-46, p.173) ISBN 0-910311-92-7&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Holz, Adam R. 2007.   [http://www.pluggedin.com/familyroom/articles/2007/isaveragethenewugly.aspx Is Average the New Ugly?] ''[[Plugged In Online]]''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Coalition |first=National |url=http://pureintimacy.org/piArticles/A000000551.cfm |title=Subtle Dangers of Pornogaphy |publisher=Pureintimacy.org |date= |accessdate=2012-08-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; These critics, notably [[Wendy Shalit]], advocate a return to pre-sexual revolution standards of [[sexual morality]], which Shalit refers to as a "return to [[modesty]]", as an antidote to sexual objectification.&lt;ref name=shalit1/&gt;&lt;ref name=shalit2&gt;Shalit, Wendy. 2000. [http://www.boundless.org/2005/articles/a0001513.cfm Modesty revisited]. ''[[Boundless webzine]]''.&lt;/ref&gt;

Other feminists contest feminist claims about the objectification of women. [[Camille Paglia]] holds that "Turning people into sex objects is one of the specialties of our species." In her view, objectification is closely tied to (and may even be identical with) the highest human faculties toward conceptualization and [[aesthetics]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
  | last =Paglia
  | first =Camille
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | title =Sexual Personae: Art &amp; Decadence from Nefertiti to Emily Dickinson
  | publisher =Vintage
  |date=August 20, 1991
  | location =
  | pages =
  | url =
  | doi =
  | isbn = 0-679-73579-8 ISBN 978-0-6797-3579-3  }}
&lt;/ref&gt; [[Individualist feminist]] [[Wendy McElroy]] holds that the label "sex object" means nothing because inanimate objects are not sexual. She continues that women are their bodies as well as their minds and souls.&lt;ref&gt;McElroy, Wendy. 2006. [http://www.wendymcelroy.com/freeinqu.htm A feminist overview of pornography, ending in a defense thereof.] ''WendyMcElroy.com''.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Objectification theory ==
'''Objectification Theory''' is based on the principle that girls and women develop their primary view of their physical selves from observations of others. These observations can take place in the media or through personal experience.&lt;ref name=bartky&gt;Bartky, Sandra Lee. (1990). ''Femininity and Domination: Studies in the Phenomenology of Oppression''. Routledge. ISBN 978-0-415-90186-4. p 26.&lt;/ref&gt; Through a blend of expected and actual exposure, females are socialized to objectify their own physical characteristics from a [[Grammatical person|third person]] perception, which is identified as self-objectification.&lt;ref&gt;Kaschak, Edward. (1992). ''Engendered Lives: A new Psychology of Women's Experience'' (Basic Books). ISBN 0-465-01349-X. p 12.&lt;/ref&gt; Women and girls develop an expected physical appearance for themselves, based on observations of others; and are aware that others are likely to observe as well. The sexual objectification and self objectification of women is believed to influence social [[gender roles]] and inequalities between the sexes.&lt;ref&gt;Goldenberg, Jamie L., and Tomi-Ann Roberts. (2004). The beast within the beauty: An existential perspective on the objectification and condemnation of women. In: J Greenberg, SL Koole, T Pyszczynski (eds), ''Handbook of experimental existential psychology''; p 71–85. (Guilford Press). ISBN 978-1-59385-040-1.&lt;/ref&gt; Some research questions the existence of sexual objectification. Some research shows that people do not so much objectify others but redistributes mental states in others&lt;ref&gt;http://pantheon.yale.edu/~jk762/mind-body.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Self-objectification ===
Self-objectification can increase in elicit situations which heightens the awareness of an individual’s physical appearance.&lt;ref name=frederickson1.82&gt;[[Barbara Fredrickson|Fredrickson, Barbara L]]. and Kristen Harrison. (2005). Throwing like a girl: Self-objectification predicts adolescent girl's motor performance. ''Journal of Sport and Social Issues'' 29(1):79–101. {{DOI|10.1177/0193723504269878}}. p 82.&lt;/ref&gt; Here, the presence of a [[third person (video games)|third person]] observer is enhanced. Therefore, when individuals know others are looking at them, or will be looking at them, they are more likely to care about their physical appearance. Examples of enhanced presence of an observer include the presence of an audience, camera, or other known observer.

=== Women, girls, and self-objectification ===
Primarily, objectification theory describes how women and girls are influenced as a result of expected social and [[gender roles]].&lt;ref name=bartky/&gt; Research indicates not all women are influenced equally, due to the [[anatomical]], [[hormonal]], and [[Genetics|genetic]] differences of the female body; however, women’s bodies are often objectified and evaluated more frequently.&lt;ref&gt;Fredrickson and Harrison (2005), p 90–95.&lt;/ref&gt; Females learn that their physical appearance is important to themselves and society. As a result, females consider their physical appearance often, expecting that others will also.

Sexual objectification occurs when a person is identified by their sexual body parts or sexual function. In essence, an individual loses their identity, and is recognized solely by the physical characteristics of their body.&lt;ref name=bartky/&gt; The purpose of this recognition is to bring enjoyment to others, or to serve as a sexual object for society.&lt;ref&gt;LeMoncheck, Linda. (1997). ''Loose Women, Lecherous Men: A Feminist Philosophy of Sex'' (Oxford University Press). ISBN 978-0-19-510556-8. p 133.&lt;/ref&gt; Sexual objectification can occur as a social construct among individuals.

=== Psychological consequences ===
Research indicates that objectification theory is valuable to understanding how repeated visual images in the media are socialized and translated into [[mental health]] problems, including psychological consequences on the individual and societal level.&lt;ref name=fredrickson2&gt;Fredrickson, Barbara L.; Tomi-Ann Roberts. (1997). "Objectification Theory: Toward understanding women's lived experiences and mental health risks". ''Psychology of Women Quarterly'' 21(2):173–206. {{doi|10.1111/j.1471-6402.1997.tb00108.x}}. Retrieved on 2009-4-11.&lt;/ref&gt; These include increased [[self consciousness]], increased body anxiety, heightened mental health threats ([[Clinical depression|depression]], [[anorexia nervosa]], [[bulimia]], and [[sexual dysfunction]]), and increased body shame. Therefore, the theory has been used to explore an array of dependent variables including [[disordered eating]], [[mental health]], [[Clinical depression|depression]], motor performance, [[body image]], idealized body type, [[stereotype]] formation, sexual perception and sexual typing.&lt;ref name=frederickson1.82/&gt;&lt;ref name=fredrickson2/&gt; Effects of objectification theory are identified on both the individual and societal levels.

== Sexual fetishism ==
[[Sexual fetishism]] can be considered sexual objectification when a person is assigned or adopts the status of the fetish object. In [[BDSM]] activities, even though it is consensual, subjecting a submissive to [[erotic humiliation]] can be regarded as sexual objectification. [[Human furniture]] is a form of fetishism and sexual objectification. [[Allen Jones (sculptor)|Allen Jones]]' "Hat Stand and Table Sculpture" incorporates semi-naked women into furniture, and are regarded as sexual objectification.

==See also==
{{Commons category}}
*[[Dehumanization]]
*[[Exploitation of women in mass media]]
*[[Gender role]]
*[[Objectification]]
*[[Sex in advertising]]
*[[Sexuality in music videos]]
*[[Sexualization]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
* Bartky, Sandra Lee. 1990. ''Femininity and Domination: Studies in the Phenomenology of Oppression''. New York: Routledge. ISBN 0-415-90185-5 (hc), ISBN 0-415-90186-3 (pb).
* [[John Berger|Berger, John]]. 1972. ''[[Ways of Seeing]]''. London: British Broadcasting Corporation and Penguin Books. ISBN 0-563-12244-7 (BBC), ISBN 0-14-021631-6, ISBN 0-14-013515-4 (pbk).
* Brooks, Gary R. 1995. ''The Centerfold Syndrome: How Men Can Overcome Objectification and Achieve Intimacy with Women''. San Francisco: Jossey-Bass. ISBN 0-7879-0104-0.
* Eames, Elizabeth. 1976. Sexism and woman as sex object. ''Journal of Thought'' 11(2):140–143.
* Holroyd, Julia. 2005. [http://www.brown.edu/Departments/Philosophy/conferencepapers/objectification.pdf Sexual objectification: The unlikely alliance of feminism and Kant] (conference paper). Society for Applied Philosophy International Congress 2005, Oxford, UK.
* LeMoncheck, Linda. 1985. ''Dehumanizing Women: Treating Persons as Sex Objects''. New York: Rowman &amp; Littlefield Publishers. ISBN 0-8476-7331-6 (hc).
* [[Martha Nussbaum|Nussbaum, Martha C.]] 1995. Objectification. ''Philosophy and Public Affairs'' 24(4): 249–291. {{DOI|10.1111/j.1088-4963.1995.tb00032.x}}. ([http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0048-3915(199523)24%3A4%3C249%3AO%3E2.0.CO%3B2-U JSTOR link].)
* Papadaki, Evangelia. 2007. [http://www.palgrave-journals.com/cpt/journal/v6/n3/full/9300282a.html Sexual objectification: From Kant to contemporary feminism.] ''Contemporary Political Theory'' 6(3):330–348. {{DOI|10.1057/palgrave.cpt.9300282}}. ([http://www.palgrave-journals.com/cpt/journal/v6/n3/pdf/9300282a.pdf PDF])
* Shrage, Laurie. 2005. Exposing the fallacies of anti-porn feminism. ''Feminist Theory'' 6:45–65. {{DOI|10.1177/1464700105050226}}.
* Soble, Alan. 2002. ''Pornography, Sex, and Feminism''. Amherst, NY: [[Prometheus Books]]. ISBN 1-57392-944-1 (pb).
* Paul, Pamela. 2005. ''Pornified: How Pornography Is Damaging Our Lives, Our Relationships, and Our Families''. New York, NY: [[Henry Holt and Company]]. ISBN  	0-8050-7745-6 (hc).

==External links==
* [http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/feminism-objectification/ "Feminist Perspectives on Objectification"] by Evangelia Papadaki, ''[[Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy]]'', March 10, 2010.
* [http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/feminist-sex-markets/#SexObj "Feminist Perspectives on Sex Markets: 1.3 Sexual Objectification"] by Laurie Shrage, ''[[Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy]]'', July 13, 2007.
* [http://finallyfeminism101.wordpress.com/2007/03/23/faq-what-is-sexual-objectification/ "FAQ: What is sexual objectification?"] by Tigtog, ''Finally, A Feminism 101 Blog'', March 23, 2007.
* [http://www.nearbycafe.com/loveandlust/steinberg/erotic/cn/cn5.html "Comes Naturally #5: On Sexual Objectification"] by David Steinberg, ''[[Spectator Magazine]]'', March 5, 1993. – Sex-positive feminist perspective on sexual objectification.
* [http://www.telegraph.co.uk/htmlContent.jhtml;?html=/archive/1996/10/05/tlpet05.html "Women Like Seeing Men as Sex Objects"]. Interview with [[Janet Anderson]] by [[Petronella Wyatt]], ''[[Daily Telegraph]]'', October 5, 1996.
* John Berger's ''Ways of Seeing, Episode 2: The Female Nude''. [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=u72AIab-Gdc Part 1], [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=aHsV7ljusCs Part 2], [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=h1yvciNEuAs Part 3], [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hNZNB-SfC7w Part 4]. (Archived on [[YouTube]].)
* [http://web.archive.org/web/20080208172715/http://www.psu.edu/dept/medialab/research/objectification.html "Sexual Suggestiveness in Online Ads: Effects of Objectification on Opposite Genders"] by Sriram Kalyanaraman, Michael Redding, and Jason Steele, ''Media Effects Research Laboratory, [[Pennsylvania State University]]'', 2000.
* [http://econshp2.econ.kuleuven.ac.be/consumerscience/Lists/Posts/Post.aspx?ID=181 "Bikini-Clad Women Make Men Impatient"] by Bram Van den Bergh, ''Katholieke Universiteit Leuven Marketing &amp; Consumer Science Blog'', June 11, 2008.

{{Sexual ethics|state=expand}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Sexual Objectification}}
[[Category:Sexualization]]
[[Category:Sexuality and society]]
[[Category:Feminist theory]]
[[Category:Philosophy of sexuality]]

[[es:Deshumanización sexual]]
[[fr:Objectification sexuelle]]
[[lt:Seksualinis objektifikavimas]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>