<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20041008193418|6434514" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="195306" pageid="195306" ns="0" title="Harvey Milk"><revisions><rev timestamp="2004-10-08T19:35:08Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">&lt;table align=right&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;[[image:harvey_milk.jpg]]&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
'''Harvey Milk''' ([[May 22]], [[1930]] - [[November 27]], [[1978]]) an [[United States|American]] politician and [[gay rights]] activist, was the first openly [[gay]] city supervisor of [[San Francisco, California]]. He and the mayor were [[assassin]]ated in 1978.

Of [[Lithuania]]n ancestry, Harvey Milk was born '''Glimpy Milch''' in [[Long Island, New York]]. He graduated from Albany State College in 1951 and joined the [[United States Navy]]; he was dishonorably discharged for homosexuality.

Like many gay people of the time, Milk later moved to San Francisco in [[1972]], where he settled with his lover Scott Smith and opened a camera store in [[the Castro]] [[gay village]]. He emerged as a community leader, founding the Castro Valley Association of local merchants, and represented the neighborhood businesses in dealing with the city government.

Despite a national climate of hostility against gay people, he ran for office several times. He emerged as a figurehead for San Francisco's large [[gay community]], and was called the "Mayor of Castro Street." He was elected city supervisor in [[1977]], the first openly gay elected official of any large city in the US.

He was assassinated on November 27, 1978 at City Hall, together with mayor [[George Moscone]], by former city supervisor [[Dan White]]. White had resigned previously following the enactment of a gay rights bill which he had opposed. 

A huge throng turned out for Milk's and Moscone's funeral cort&amp;egrave;ge, along a route decorated with [[rainbow flag]]s.

White was convicted of [[manslaughter]] on the grounds of [[diminished responsibility]] and sentenced to seven years and eight months, a sentence widely denounced as lenient and motivated by [[homophobia]]. Lawyers had prevented anyone pro-gay from serving on the jury, and had brought in a psychologist to show evidence of the depression - namely that the consumption of junk food was out of character for the normally health-conscious White (leading to a common misunderstanding that junk food was ''blamed'' &amp;mdash; see [[Twinkie defense]]).  White later committed suicide while on parole. 

Milk had foreseen his risk of assassination and had recorded several audio tapes to be played in that event. On one of the tapes, he made his famous quotation, "If a bullet should enter my brain, let that bullet destroy every closet door in the country."

After the sentence, the gay community erupted into the [[White Night Riots]]; more than 160 people ended up in hospital.

Harvey Milk is widely regarded as a [[martyr]] for the gay community and the gay rights movement. Many [[Queer]] community institutions are named for Milk, including the Harvey Milk Institute and the Harvey Milk Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, and Transgender [[United States Democratic Party|Democratic]] Club in San Francisco, as well as a number of Queer-positive alternative schools in the United States, including [[Harvey Milk School]] in New York City.

A number of pieces of music have taken Harvey Milk as their subject. [[Blue Gene Tyranny]]'s ''Harvey Milk (Portrait)'' (1978) is a piece for [[magnetic tape]] which manipulates a recording of a speech Milk gave in 1978. In 1995 the [[opera]] ''Harvey Milk'' by composer [[Stewart Wallace]] and [[librettist]] [[ Michael Korie]] was premiered.

The life of this politician is depicted in the [[Academy Award]] winning [[documentary film]], ''The Times of Harvey Milk''.

See [[List of famous gay, lesbian, and bisexual people]] and [[list of assassinated persons]].

==References==
*[[Randy Shilts]].  ''The Mayor of Castro Street''.  [[1982]].
*Wallace Turner.  "San Francisco Mayor is Slain; City Supervisor Also Killed; Ex-Official Gives Up to Police." '' The New York Times''.  [[November 28]], [[1978]].  A1.

== External links ==
*[http://www.glbthistory.org The GLBT Historical Society of Northern California] holds Harvey Milk's archives.
*[http://www.time.com/time/time100/heroes/profile/milk01.html &lt;i&gt;Time&lt;/i&gt; 100 Persons and Icons - Harvey Milk]
*[http://www.harveymilk.org/ Harvey Milk Institute]
*[http://www.shapingsf.org/ezine/gay/files/whitengt.htm Account of the White Night riots]
*[http://www.milkclub.org/ Harvey Milk Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, and Transgender Democratic Club]
*[http://www.stewartwallace.com/harvey_milk.htm Harvey Milk Opera]
*[http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0176705/ ''Execution of Justice''] [[Showtime]] original movie about the events leading up to the [[November 27]] assassinations.
*[http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0088275/ ''The Times of Harvey Milk'' - IMDB Entry]

[[Category:1930 births|Milk, Harvey]]
[[Category:1978 deaths|Milk, Harvey]]
[[Category:Assassinated people|Milk, Harvey]]
[[Category:LGBT rights activists|Milk, Harvey]]
[[Category:San Francisco history|Milk, Harvey]]
[[Category:U.S. history of LGBT rights|Milk, Harvey]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>