<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20071110143332|170547589" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="195306" pageid="195306" ns="0" title="Harvey Milk"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-11-13T08:20:11Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{otheruses}}
{{Infobox revolution biography
|name= Harvey Milk
|lived=
|dateofbirth= {{birth date|1930|5|22|mf=y}}
|placeofbirth= [[Woodmere, New York]]
|dateofdeath= {{death date and age|1978|11|27|1930|5|22|mf=y}}
|placeofdeath= [[San Francisco, California]]
|image= [[Image:harvey milk.jpg|190px]]
|caption= American politician and gay-rights activist
|alternate name=
|movement= [[LGBT social movements]]
|organizations=
}}
'''Harvey Bernard Milk''' ([[May 22]], [[1930]] – [[November 27]], [[1978]]), an [[United States|American]] politician and [[gay rights]] activist, was the first openly [[gay]] [[city supervisor]] of [[San Francisco, California]]. He and Mayor [[George Moscone]] were [[Moscone-Milk Assassinations|assassinated]] in 1978.  His assassin, [[Dan White]], was sentenced to seven years in prison.  Outrage over the verdict led to the [[White Night Riots]] in San Francisco by enraged citizens.  Milk is seen by some to be a martyr to the [[LGBT]] community.

==Biography==
===Early life===
Milk's given name was '''Harvey Bernard Milk'''. His grandfather, Morris Milk was the owner and namesake of Milk's Department Store in [[Woodmere, New York]]; "Glimpy" was Harvey's nickname because as a child and adolescent, he was considered odd-looking because of his large ears, nose, and feet. He was born in Woodmere. He graduated from Bay Shore High School, [[Bay Shore, NY]] in [[1947]], graduated from [[University at Albany]] in [[1951]] and joined the [[United States Navy]]; he was [[Military discharge#Honorable|honorably discharged]], although he later told voters in campaigns that he was a victim of one of the many anti-gay purges of the armed services.

Following his service in the Navy, Milk lived for a time in [[Dallas, Texas]]. Eventually he relocated to [[New York City]] and took a job on [[Wall Street]]. He also became involved with theater, serving as [[Assistant Director]] along side Tom O'Horgan for a number of plays including ''[[Lenny theatre play|Lenny]]'' and the [[musical theatre|musical]] ''[[Jesus Christ Superstar]]''.

In 1972, Milk moved to San Francisco. He settled with his [[significant other|partner]] Scott Smith and opened a camera store, Castro Camera, in [[the Castro]] [[gay village]]. He emerged as a community leader, founding the Castro Valley Association of local merchants, and represented the neighborhood businesses in dealing with the city government.

===Public office===
Milk ran for the [[San Francisco Board of Supervisors]] unsuccessfully twice, in [[1973]] and [[1975]]. He emerged as a figurehead for San Francisco's large [[gay community]], and was known as the "[[Castro Street|Mayor of Castro Street]]," a title which he himself coined. With each campaign, he garnered a larger number of supporters.

 Milk's opponent in that race was [[Art Agnos]], who would win the assembly seat by 3,600 votes out of 33,000 ballots cast.

After San Francisco switched from at-large to district elections, Milk was elected to the Board of Supervisors on his third attempt in [[1977]], the first openly gay elected official of any large city in the United States, and only the third openly gay elected official in all of the US, after [[Kathy Kozachenko]] and [[Elaine Noble]]. Milk represented District 5, which included the Castro.

In his eleven months as a Supervisor, he sponsored a gay rights bill for the City as well as – famously – a [[pooper-scooper]] ordinance.  He was also instrumental in defeating Proposition 6, [[The Briggs Initiative]], backed by State Senator Briggs, which would have allowed openly gay men and lesbians who were teachers to be fired based on their sexuality. In November 1978, Proposition 6 was soundly voted down by Californians.

Milk was also successful in reaching out and making alliances among the city's ethnic populations and among labor union leaders but not among the rank and file members.

===The outing of Sipple===
On [[September 22]] [[1975]] former marine [[Oliver Sipple]] saved the life of President [[Gerald Ford]] for which he was highly praised by law enforcement in the media as well as in a personal letter from the President. Milk [[coming out|outed]] Sipple despite Sipple's insistence to reporters that his sexuality was to be kept confidential proclaiming Sipple a "gay hero," and stating (this) "will help break the stereotype of homosexuals." [[Gay liberation]] groups petitioned local media to give Sipple his due as a gay hero. ''[[San Francisco Chronicle]]'' columnist [[Herb Caen]] published the private side of the former Marine's story as did a handful of other publications. Sipple's mother disowned him when she learned his secret but according to a 2006 ''Washington Post'' article later reconciled with his sexual orientation."&lt;ref name="WaPo"&gt; [http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2006/12/30/AR2006123000160.html Caught in Fate's Trajectory, Along With Gerald Ford], Lynne Duke, ''Washington Post'', December 30, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; Still the damage to Sipple was done.  His mental and physical health sharply declined over the years. He drank heavily, gained weight to 300 lbs, was fitted with a pacemaker, became paranoid and suicidal. On February 2, 1989, he was found dead in his bed, at the age of forty-seven.

===Assassination===
{{main|Moscone-Milk Assassinations}}

Late in 1978, Supervisor [[Dan White]], an acrimonious political opponent of Milk's, resigned from the Board of Supervisors.  His resignation meant that Moscone would choose White's successor, and thus could tip the Board's balance of power in Moscone's favor.  Recognizing this, those who supported a more [[conservative (politics)|conservative]] agenda, including board ally [[Dianne Feinstein]], talked White into changing his mind.  White requested that Moscone re-appoint him to his former seat. Moscone originally indicated a willingness to do so, but more [[liberal (politics)|liberal]] city leaders, including Milk, lobbied him against the idea, and Moscone ultimately decided not to re-appoint White. On November 27, 1978, White went to San Francisco City Hall to meet with Moscone and make a final plea for re-appointment. When Moscone refused to yield, White shot Moscone to death, then went to Milk's office and also shot Milk to death.
White later turned himself in at the police station where he was formerly an officer. Even though he had carried a gun, 10 extra rounds, and crawled through a window to avoid metal detectors, White denied premeditation. Thousands attended a spontaneous candlelight memorial vigil the night of Milk's funeral. [http://www.archive.org/details/ssfHarveym1 Video of candlelight vigil], accompanied by a message Milk recorded preemptively "to be played only in the event of [his] death by assassination".  Milk had foreseen his risk of assassination and had recorded several audio tapes to be played in that event. One of the tapes included his now-famous quote, "If a bullet should enter my brain, let that bullet destroy every closet door."

==== Trial ====
{{See|Twinkie defense}}

Dan White's trial, which began four months after the killings, was one of the most closely watched trials in California at that time.  The prosecution claimed that White's motive was revenge.  But White's attorney, Douglas Schmidt, claimed that White was a victim of pressure and had been depressed, a state exacerbated by his consuming a large quantity of [[junk food ]] before the murders; this became known as the "[[Twinkie defense]]."  Schmidt also told the jury and the press that White carried all that ammunition on him not so much out of hatred but out of impulse from his experience as an ex-police officer.

Finally, the jury heard what the prosecution hoped it would be its most damaging piece of evidence&amp;mdash;Dan White's tape-recorded confession which was taped the day after the murders.  What was notable about this confession was that the police didn't seem to ask White any questions about the crime and just let him talk.  Instead, White tearfully talked of how Moscone and Milk refused to give him his supervisor's job back.

White was convicted of [[voluntary manslaughter]] on the grounds of [[diminished capacity]] and sentenced to seven years and eight months, a sentence widely denounced as lenient and motivated by [[homophobia]]. During [[Jury#Selection|jury selection]], defense attorneys had excluded candidates they deemed "pro-gay."

==== White Night Riots ====
{{See|White Night Riots}}
After the sentence, the gay community erupted into what became known as the [[White Night Riots]]. As soon as the sentence was announced, word ran through the [[gay community]] and groups of people began walking quickly to the Civic Center and by 8:00 PM, there was a sizable mob formed. According to the documentary, ''[[The Times of Harvey Milk]]'', the enraged crowd started by screaming at police officers calling for revenge and death. Then, riots began to break out with the mob setting ablaze a number of police vehicles, disrupting traffic, smashing windows of cars and stores, buses had their overhead wires ripped down, and physical violence resulted against the outnumbered police officers.

Many rioters were arrested but the Chief of Police, Charles Gain, was blamed for being too weak in his response and holding back his officers when he should have been more proactive and defended lives and property. He defended himself by pointing out that no one was dead and only a few had minor injuries. More than 160 people were hospitalized because of the rioting.

==Legacy==
[[Image:Harvey milk plaza.JPG|center|frame|An inscription at the Harvey Milk Plaza in San Francisco.]]
{{wikiquote}}
Harvey Milk is widely regarded as a [[martyr]] for the gay community and the gay rights movement. Many gay and lesbian community institutions are named for Milk, including the Harvey Milk Institute and the [[Harvey Milk Lesbian/Gay/Bisexual/Transgendered Democratic Club]] in San Francisco, as well as a number of alternative schools in the United States, including [[Harvey Milk High School]] in New York City. [[Oakes College]] at the [[University of California, Santa Cruz]] has an on-campus apartment building named Harvey Milk.  A diner at the [[University of Warwick]] in the [[United Kingdom|UK]] was named Harvey's in his honour, and the [[Leeds University Union]] named a nightclub the Harvey Milk Bar (although it has since been renamed).

===Bust in San Francisco city hall===
{{Expand|date=October 2007}}
In February 2007, the city of San Francisco agreed to erect a bust of Harvey Milk in City Hall in tribute to his service and memorialize his life's work. A lengthy process to chose a design took place and a gala installation event is planned for 2008.

==Depictions==
The life of this politician is depicted in the [[Academy Awards|Academy Award]]-winning [[documentary film]], ''[[The Times of Harvey Milk]]'' in 1984, narrated by [[Harvey Fierstein]].  A 20th anniversary digitally remastered DVD of the documentary was released in 2004 and includes interviews with the film's director, Rob Epstein and Harvey's openly gay nephew, Stuart Milk [http://thecastro.net/street/memoriespage/nicoletta/milk10.html] , among others.

{{Portal|LGBT|Portal LGBT.svg}}{{LGBT}}

In 1995 the [[opera]] ''[[Harvey Milk (Opera)|Harvey Milk]]'' by composer [[Stewart Wallace]] and [[librettist]] [[Michael Korie]] was premiered by the [[Houston Grand Opera]], and in 1996 it was recorded on CD under Donald Runnicles with the [[San Francisco Opera]] orchestra and chorus. 

The 1999 film ''[[Execution of Justice]]'' based on the 1983 play (of the same title) written by Emily Mann re-lives the assassination.

In 2000 a TV film, ''[[American Justice: It's Not My Fault - Strange Defenses]]'' examined the assassination with archival footage of Milk and White. 

In 2004, playwright and actor [[Jade Esteban Estrada]] portrays Milk in the solo musical comedy ''ICONS: The Lesbian and Gay History of the World, Vol. 2''. 

Director [[Gus Van Sant]] has long been attached to direct a biopic of Milk for over a decade.  Director [[Bryan Singer]] has also expressed interest in the project based on the [[Randy Shilts]] biography of the same name, scheduled for release in 2008. [[Sean Penn]] and [[Matt Damon]] are being considered for the roles of Milk and White in Van Sant's film.

Folk musician Zoe Lewis honors Milk with her song 'Harvey' on her 1998 album "Sheep".

In 1989 artist [[Félix González-Torres]] mentions Milk on an untitled billboard ("People With AIDS Coalition 1985 Police Harassment 1969 Oscar Wilde 1895 Supreme Court 1986 Harvey Milk 1977 March on Washington 1987 Stonewall Rebellion 1969")

==References==
*[[Randy Shilts|Shilts, Randy]],  ''The Mayor of Castro Street: The Life and Times of Harvey Milk''. New York: St. Martin's Press, [[1982]].  ISBN 0-312-01900-9
*[[Mike Weiss|Weiss, Mike]] ''Double Play--The San Francisco City Hall Killings'' [[1984]].
*[[Wallace Turner|Turner, Wallace]],  "San Francisco Mayor is Slain; City Supervisor Also Killed; Ex-Official Gives Up to Police." '' The New York Times''.  [[November 28]], [[1978]].  A1.

== See also ==
*[[List of assassinated American politicians]]

==External links==
{{gay rights}}
*[http://thecastro.net/milkpage.html]http://thecastro.net/milkpage.html  Significant collection of photographs and Milk history.
*[http://sfpl.org/librarylocations/main/glc/glcarchival.htm#glc35 The James C. Hormel Gay &amp; Lesbian Center at the San Francisco Public Library] holds the Harvey Milk Archives - Scott Smith Collection.
*[http://www.time.com/time/time100/heroes/profile/milk01.html ''Time'' 100 Persons and Icons - Harvey Milk]
*[http://www.milkmemorial.org Harvey Milk City Hall Memorial] Organization dedicated to placing a bust of Harvey Milk in San Francisco's City Hall.
*[http://www.harveymilk.org/ Harvey Milk Institute]
*[http://www.shapingsf.org/ezine/gay/files/whitengt.htm Account of the White Night riots]
*[http://www.milkclub.org/ Harvey Milk Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, and Transgender Democratic Club]
*[http://www.stewartwallace.com/harvey_milk.htm Harvey Milk Opera]
*[http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0176705/ ''Execution of Justice''] [[Showtime]] original movie about the events leading up to the [[November 27]] assassinations.
*[http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0088275/ ''The Times of Harvey Milk'' - IMDB Entry]
*[http://www.hicom.net/~oedipus/milk.html ''The Forgotten Populist, Harvey Milk''] an analysis of Milk's politics and political philosophy
* [http://www.glbthistory.org The Gay, Lesbian, Bisexual, Transgender Historical Society] Holds artifacts of Milk, including the suit he was wearing when shot by Dan White

*[http://thecastro.net/street/ewpage/ewpage.html"Uncle Donald's Castro Street"] A long time Castro resident gives his account of the Riot and Police Assault on Castro street afterward

[[de:Harvey Milk]]
[[es:Harvey Milk]]
[[fr:Harvey Milk]]
[[it:Harvey Milk]]
[[he:הארווי מילק]]
[[ja:ハーヴェイ・ミルク]]
[[pt:Harvey Milk]]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Milk, Harvey}}
[[Category:San Francisco Board of Supervisors]]
[[Category:California politicians]]
[[Category:Gay politicians]]
[[Category:Jewish American politicians]]
[[Category:LGBT rights activists from the United States]]
[[Category:People from San Francisco]]
[[Category:Assassinated activists]]
[[Category:Assassinated American politicians]]
[[Category:Deaths by firearm in the United States]]
[[Category:LGBT politicians from the United States]]
[[Category:1930 births]]
[[Category:1978 deaths]]
[[Category:LGBT Jews]]
[[Category:LGBT people from the United States]]
[[Category:Jewish biography stubs]]
[[Category:People from Long Island]]
[[Category:State University of New York at Albany alumni]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>