<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20041014235906|6834697" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="29269" pageid="29269" ns="0" title="Self-determination"><revisions><rev timestamp="2004-10-24T21:31:58Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Self-determination''' is a principle in [[international law]] that a people ought to be able to determine their own governmental forms and structure free from outside influence.

This principle was first articulated by [[Woodrow Wilson]] in his [[Fourteen Points]]; and was important in the [[Treaty of Versailles]] for drawing the boundaries of [[Eastern Europe]] and affecting [[decolonization]]. Many of the concepts embodied in the ideal of self-determination, however, can be found in earlier documents such as the [[Declaration of Independence of the United States]]. 

The right to self-determination has been used in recent decades by people all over the world. In most cases there is an ethnic or religious minority seeking independence from a majority to escape prejudice or persecution. 

The [[constitution of the Soviet Union]] acknowledged this right for its [[republic]]s, but it was not applied in practice until the [[perestroika]], when it led to the [[collapse of the Soviet Union|breakup of the Soviet Union]]

At the ratification of the [[UN Charter]] in [[1951]], the signatories introduced the right of all people to self-determination into the framework of international law and diplomacy. 

The purpose of the self determination clause was to allow the former [[colony|colonies]] that existed before [[World War II]] to have a say in their future.  However, after [[decolonization]] the right to self-determination became understood to apply only to states and not to peoples, and to be circumscribed by the principles of [[territorial integrity]] and [[non-interference in internal affairs]].  Many of the newly independent former colonies faced secessionist and [[irredentist]] movements and therefore there was an international consensus that self-determination did not apply to these movements.

The [[United Nations Declaration on Human Rights]] in [[1970]] committed the idea of the right for self-determination to the body of international protocol. In essence, all people reserve the right to seek self-determination to address a lack of proper representation or oppression from any given government. 

There is tension between the concept of self-determination and that of [[territorial integrity]].  This conflict has been resolved in practice by defining the notion of "people" entitled to self-determination as persons living in a particular nation-state rather than persons sharing a common culture or language.  Hence, self-determination as it is understood in the early [[21st century]] does not generally promote the political aspirations of oppressed [[ethnic minority|ethnic minorities]].

Wilson's ideas of self-determination originated in his [[U.S. Southern states|Southern]] heritage and sympathies. His favorite movie was [[The Birth of a Nation]], and his [[United States Democratic Party|Democratic Party]] beliefs and personal ties were steeped in Southern pride and resentment of [[U.S. Northern states|Northern]] power. Hence Southern interpretations of States-Rights directly led to Wilson's ideas of self-determination. Many have criticized both concepts, however, for promoting secession and division over unity. Further, they key question is at what level do populations have the right to self-determination and the formation or preservation of a state, the empowerment of a local majority, and the formation of a local minority. In the United States, southern states' rights to determine their own destiny during the [[American Civil War|Civil War]] and Civil Rights era were held to be not absolute, especially since significant minorities there were oppressed. In [[Europe]] after [[World War I]], many of the former Empires destroyed in that war were broken up into ethnic states which themselves were amalgamations of peoples containing their own minorities, in [[Yugoslavia]], the former Russian and Austro-Hungarian provinces, and in the Middle East. In [[History of Palestine|Palestine]], [[Zionism|zionist]] immigrants would claim self-determination to justify the creation of the state of [[Israel]] in the former lands of the [[Ottoman Empire]], just people in the [[West Bank]] would later claim independence as [[Palestine]].

Hence, self-determination has been held to be an example of [[democracy]] at work, but also as an example of an abstract theory that when implemented has sometimes led to and fed further ethnic, national, and regional civil conflict.

==See also==
*[[Emancipation]]
*[[Independence]]
*[[Separatism]]
*[[Sovereignty]]
*[[States' Rights]]

[[nl:Zelfbeschikkingsrecht]]

[[Category:International relations]]
[[Category:International law]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>