<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20071113105540|171177413" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="29269" pageid="29269" ns="0" title="Self-determination"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-11-13T10:56:37Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Refimprove|date=May 2007}}
{{expert-subject|Politics|article|date=November, 2006}}
{{otheruses4|self-determination in politics| the psychology theory|Self-Determination Theory}}

The principle of '''self-determination''', often seen as a moral and legal [[right]], is that every [[nation]] is entitled to a [[sovereignty|sovereign]] territorial [[state]], and that every specifically identifiable population should choose which state it belongs to, often by [[plebiscite]]. It is commonly used to justify the aspirations of an [[ethnic group]] that self-identifies as a nation toward forming an independent sovereign state, but it equally grants the right to reject sovereignty and join a larger multi-ethnic state.

Although there is a consensus that [[international law]] recognizes the principle of self-determination, the principle does not, by itself, define which group is a nation, which groups are entitled to sovereignty, or what territory they should get for that purpose.  Its application in international law creates a tension between this principle and the principles of [[territorial integrity]] and [[non-intervention]] in [[internal affairs]].

The principle of self-determination formally expresses a central claim of [[nationalism]], namely the entitlement of each nation to its own nation state. It has itself become a typical demand of nationalist movements. However, the formal expression of the principle came later than the nationalist movements, and the first [[nation-state]]s. In the 20th century the principle was central to the process of [[decolonisation]], but its use is not limited to contesting [[colonialism|colonialist]] or [[imperialism|imperialist]] rule.

Some interpretations of the principle in [[ethics]] treat it as a translation or extension of universal rights of [[individuals]] (''[[political freedom]], [[freedom of religion]], [[freedom of speech]]'') to a group. Sometimes it is treated as a specific [[Collective rights|collective right]], distinct from individual rights. It is a disputed principle in ethics, with some arguing that no such entitlement exists, other than perhaps the right to resist or secede from [[tyranny]]. 

== History and overview ==
The principle that a [[state]] should be sovereign and autonomous has long been associated with the idea of the state itself. The ideal of self-determination by a specific population (rather than their rulers) is of later origin. Early statements of the principle can be found in the [[Declaration of Independence (United States)|Declaration of Independence of the United States]]. In 1859 [[John Stuart Mill]] argued in [[On Liberty]] that political communities are entitled collectively to determine their own affairs. He argues that states should be seen as self-determining communities ''even if'' their internal political arrangements are not free; self-determination and political freedom are not equivalent terms.

===Wilsonianism===
{{Main|Wilsonian}}

This principle was first applied to the modern [[international relations]] context by [[Woodrow Wilson]] in his [[Fourteen Points]] of January 1918, in which he set out a blueprint for a just and lasting peace in Europe after [[World War I]]. The Wilsonian approach influenced the [[Idealism (international relations)|idealist tradition in International Relations]], which has at times supported military intervention in support of self-determination.

===The Soviet Union===
The 1918 [[1918 Soviet Constitution|Constitution of the Soviet Union]] acknowledged this right for its constituent [[republic]]s (although not for declared "[[autonomous oblast|autonomous" regions]]), but was not applied in practice until the [[Perestroika]], when it led to the [[collapse of the Soviet Union|breakup of the Soviet Union]].

[[Vladimir Lenin]] supported the concept of the right of a culturally distinct grouping to self-determination, albeit within the framework of [[proletarian internationalism]] and, as it turned out in the policy of the [[Soviet Union]]. The policy of [[Korenizatsiya]] seemed to indicate Lenin's sincere belief in national self-determination. However, Lenin also assumed that the populations of the ethnically diverse [[Republics of the Soviet Union|Soviet republics]] were voluntarily confederated with [[Russia]] in the form of the Soviet Union. The process of [[national delimitation in the Soviet Union]] established ethnic-national boundaries for national autonomies for non-Russian population where there was none during the times of the [[Russian Empire]]. 

During the [[Operation Barbarossa|German invasion in 1941]], some national minorities saw the invading forces as liberators, and some fought with [[Nazi Germany]]. After the Soviet victory, this was treated as collaboration: the issue is still contentious in the [[Baltic States]].

In regard to a long running argument going on between [[Rosa Luxembourg]], right-wing tendencies within the [[Russian Social Democratic Labour Party]], and the [[Bolsheviks]], Lenin said: 

&lt;blockquote&gt;...[T]he tendency of every national movement is towards the formation of national states, under which these requirements of modern capitalism are best satisfied. ...  [T]he national state is typical and normal for the capitalist period. Consequently, if we want to grasp the meaning of self-determination of nations ... by examining the historico-economic conditions of the national movements, we must inevitably reach the conclusion that the self-determination of nations means the [[separatism|political separation]] of these nations from alien national bodies, and the formation of an independent national state. ...[It] would be wrong to interpret the right to self-determination as meaning-anything but the right to existence as a separate state." -Lenin, [http://www.marxists.org/archive/lenin/works/1914/self-det/ch01.htm#v20pp72-395 What Is Meant By The Self-Determination of Nations?]&lt;/blockquote&gt;

===The UN Charter===

At the ratification of the [[UN Charter]] in post [[World War II]] [[1945]], the signatories introduced the right of all people to self-determination into the framework of international law and diplomacy. In addition, the right to self-determination holds the prestigious position of Article 1 in both the [[International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights]] (ICCPR) and the [[International Covenant on Economic, Social and Cultural Rights]] (ICESCR).  Its presence in the two covenants points to the right's complex nature and importance.

In the [[Universal Declaration of Human Rights]], the [[United Nations]] states that everyone has the right to a nationality and that no one should be arbitrarily deprived of a nationality or denied the right to change nationality. Self-determination is often invoked in national liberation struggles, [[secession]] of territories and constitutional disputes about how this right can be expressed to the satisfaction of opposing interest groups.

== Conflict with territorial integrity ==

At the time of the UN Charter, the focus was on the former [[colony|colonies]] of the Axis powers, and implicitly on all overseas colonies. There was no intention to support secessionist claims in, for instance, European states. However, the concept of self-determination is by definition in tension with that of [[territorial integrity]], which is an older principle of [[international law]]. Territorial integrity applies to integral parts of a state, and since the colonies were not seen as such (except by France), their independence was not seen as an attack on the principle. The importance attached to territorial integrity was exemplified by adherence to the principle of [[uti possidetis]] during the decolonization process. The colonial borders were retained at independence, even if they had little relevance to linguistic, ethnic and cultural boundaries. Once these new nation-states were established in Africa and Asia, some felt that the principle had been sufficiently applied, and that the principles of [[territorial integrity]] and [[Non-Intervention|non-intervention]] should again prevail. Certainly, the United Nations never supported any [[secession]] during the [[Cold War]], other than from a colonial power.

When some of the newly independent ex-colonies faced secessionist and [[irredentist]] movements, the international consensus was that self-determination did not apply to these movements. The consensus defined a "people" entitled to self-determination as persons living in a particular geographic area, rather than persons sharing a common culture or language (a nation). This did not generally promote the political aspirations of oppressed [[ethnic minority|ethnic minorities]]. Since the end of the Cold War, however, this consensus has eroded. Most notably, western powers gave covert and overt support to the [[Dissolution of Yugoslavia|serial secession]] of the constituent Republics of [[Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia|Yugoslavia]]. One of these conflicts, in [[Kosovo]] (an autonomous province within [[Serbia]]), is still unresolved.

Self-determination is a notoriously difficult principle to define and apply.  
A state is self-determining even if its citizens strive, and fail, to create free political institutions, however in turn, it is deprived of its self-determination if such institutions are established by an external power. [[John Stuart Mill|Mill]] argued that the members of a political community must seek their own freedom, just as they may seek to be virtuous, they cannot be 'set free' just as an individual cannot be made virtuous. In this way self-determination can be seen to be a parallel to state sovereignty.

Given the perceived risk of constant fragmentation, states have approached self-determination cautiously. Methods of self-determination range from sovereignty referendum, as in the case of the people of [[1995 Quebec referendum|Quebec]] in [[Canada]], or as an armed struggle in the case of the [[Tamil Tigers]] in [[Sri Lanka]]. The threat of fragmentation due to self-determination can be regarded as very dangerous to other communities in a country, especially if the groups striving for self-determination live in an area with the majority of a country's wealth.  On the other hand, supporters of self-determination argue that if the wealth is coming from the land they live in the local inhabitants deserve the wealth not the country as a whole.  This is an important dimension of the self-determination arguments in [[Iraq]] and [[Nigeria]] as well as many other countries.

==Twentieth Century issues==
===Vietnam===
{{main|Geneva Conference (1954)}}
{{See Also|First Indochina War}}

[[French Indochina]] came out of [[World War II]] having defeated the Japanese invasion, and yet was still a colony of the French Empire.  France was arguably too weak militarily and economically, and perhaps psychologically, to maintain control of the territory, especially during the First Indochina War in the early 1950s.  After the French defeat at the [[Battle of Dien Bien Phu]], a conference convened in Geneva, Switzerland to resolve the dispute.  The [[Geneva Conference (1954)]] divided the country into [[North Vietnam]] and [[South Vietnam]], and guaranteed the Vietnamese self-determination, through a plebiscite to be held in July of [[1956]].The committee was too weak to enforce the accord, and South Vietnam President [[Ngo Dinh Diem]] refused to allow free elections for determination. A [[Communist]] resistance was formed against Diem's government (the [[Viet Cong]]), sowing the seeds of the [[Vietnam War]].

===Scotland===
{{main|Scottish Parliament|Scottish independence}}
The [[Kingdom of Scotland]] was an independent state ([[Declaration of Arbroath]], 1320) from 843 until [[1707]], when the [[Acts of Union 1707|Acts of Union]] (despite widespread protest across Scotland)&lt;ref name="1707 protests"&gt; Devine, T.M (1999), ''The Scottish Nation 1700–2000'', P.9, ISBN 0-14-023004-1 ''"From that point on anti-union demonstrations were common in the capital.  In November rioting spread to the south west, that stranglehold of strict Calvinism and covenanting tradition.  The Glasgow mob rose against union sympathisers in disturbances which lasted intermittently for over a month"''&lt;/ref&gt; resulted in a [[political union]] with the [[Kingdom of England]] to create the [[Kingdom of Great Britain]].

In the 1980s and 1990s efforts began in earnest to create a [[devolved]] parliament in Scotland, deriving power from the British Parliament. Such a parliament was put into place in 1999, after a [[referendum]] in 1997. It grants Scotland specific powers, and some limited self-determination.

==Current issues==
===Australia===
{{main|Self-determination of Australian Aborigines}}
Recently (2003 onwards), self-determination has become a topic of some debate in Australia in relation to Aborigines (indigenous Australians). In the 1970s, the Aboriginal community approached the Federal Government and requested the right to administer their own communities. This encompassed basic local government functions, ranging from land dealings and management of community centres to road maintenance and garbage collection, as well as setting education programmes and standards in their local schools.

==Current issues==
===Chechnya===
Fighting for more than three centuries agaisnt russian colonial expansion and opression chechen resistance has reached the peak of its success in 1991, at the time of the fall of Soviet Empire. A referendum on constitution was held in 1992 and Chechnya has declared its full independence from Russian Socialist Federative Republic. Russian authorities started reconsolidation and centralization of their power by 1993. It began by attempting to force all of the former russian republics to rejoin Russia by signing bilateral Federative treaties with Moscow. Two republics: Tatarstan and Chechnya have refused russian demands. Already independent for more than 2 years Chechen Republic of Ichkeria refused all threats. First president of Chechen Republic - Djohar Dudayev, refused to attend Federal senate conventions, did not sign Federative treaty, and finally, chechnya did not participate in "Duma" (russian parliament) elections, thus did not have any representatives in Russian government. Eventually, Russia rejected any idea of negotiations, that might still solve the crisis, and invaded Chechnya in 1994. Russia has started war with unprecedented brutality against local population, thus outraging majority of chechen citizens, even those that might be loyal to Moscow. Warfare was mostly carried out in a guerilla style, and by 1996 chechen resistance overtook the initiative. 1996 was marked by russia's humiliating defeat, and peace treaty between Chechen Republic of Ichkeria and Russian Federation. After short lived peace marked by unceasing provokations from various sides, war started again in 1999. This time new Russian president Vladimir Putin based his argument on dubious explosions in Moscow and other major cities and invasion in Dagestan. War was raged on unprecedented scale, much more brutal than the first one. International organizations and observers were denied any access. Russian administration regime and death squadrons are constantly criticized for disapearances and murders of civilians and every day mass violations of basic human rights. The chechen capital city of Grozny was almost totally destroyed (94%), only 210,000 residents out of prewar 500-600,000 population, presently live in the city. The economy and infrustructure of chechen republic is destroyed and ceased to be, unemployment figures are to be somewhere around 60-70%. Some reconstruction efforts are being made by pro-moscow authorities but still remain at the levels of rebuilding residences and government buildings, mostly for the propaganda uses. Social, housing and infrastructure spheres remain barely satisfied. Figures of death toll at the present moment vary from 80,000 (russians) to 250,000 (Chechen) among chechen civilians, including 40,000 chechen kids, out of 1 million of prewar population; refugee numbers, estimated by international humanitarian organizations, around 300,000; 10,000 to 50,000 russian and chechen soldiers. War has totally shifted to an underground guerilla warfare, althogh some major assaults are being conducted by chechen resistance from time to time. The conflict is still present, although, lacks attention of international community, particularly by the western countries elites, which consider chechen question as an uncomfortable obstacle to having good relations with Russia, securing political benefits in war against terror (USA) and energy supply markets (EU).{{Fact|date=November 2007}}

=== Israel and Palestine ===
{{Main|Israel-Palestine conflict}}
The right to self-determination as outlined in the [[public international law]] is often referenced by both sides in the ongoing [[Israel-Palestinian conflict]]. [[Palestinian]]s assert a nationalist right to self-determination that they argue is hindered by Israeli policies in the West Bank and Gaza Strip.  [[Israel]] was, in turn, formed under the right to self-determination as outlined in the U.N. Charter. It's declaration of independence notes that "This recognition by the United Nations of the right of the Jewish people to establish their State is irrevocable," and that "This right is the natural right of the Jewish people to be masters of their own fate, like all other nations, in their own sovereign State."

[[Occupation of the West Bank and East Jerusalem by Jordan|Jordan occupied the West Bank and East Jerusalem]] (including the [[Jerusalem's Old City|Old City]]) and [[Occupation of the Gaza Strip by Egypt|Egypt occupied the Gaza Strip]] from 1949 through 1967. Throughout those years, the King of Jordan had annexed the West Bank, providing its residents with citizenship, but not with the right of mobility across the Jordan River{{Fact|date=October 2007}}. The king forbid the use of the word "Palestine" on official documents. The Jordanian position on this was that historically the East and West Bank had been one cultural entity and thus one nationality though Palestinians dispute this.  This led to open fighting between Palestinian refugees and the Jordanian government in 1970. However, in 1988, the Jordanian government relinquished its claim to the West Bank.  Egypt never annexed the Gaza, and denied its residents of citizenship and did not allow its residents to move into Egypt or anywhere else.  Despite this Egypt was not subject to a rebellion. In fact, the [[Palestine Liberation Organization]] was created in 1964 by the [[Arab League]] in [[Cairo]], [[Egypt]], and was controlled by and large by the Egyptian government.  Neither country attempted to relieve the refugee crisis (although Jordan did alleviate this somewhat by granting Palestinians citizenship) and neither allowed (to different extents) self-determination in these territories. 

The PLO stated its goal to be the destruction of the State of Israel through armed struggle, and replacing it with an "independent Palestinian state" between the [[Jordan River]] and the [[Mediterranean Sea]].  Israelis argue this would deny self-determination by the millions of Israelis now living there. Today, certain factions of the PLO, including some representatives from its dominant Fatah party, agree that Palestinian self-determination and Jewish self-determination need not be mutually exclusive. However, Hamas, which was elected to a majority of parliamentary seats in Palestinian elections and is the disputed but de facto government in the Gaza Strip, continues to call for the destruction of Israel.

=== Kosovo ===
{{see|Kosovo status process}}
The province is the subject of a long-running political and territorial dispute between the Serbian (and previously, the [[Yugoslavia|Yugoslav]]) government and Kosovo's largely ethnic-Albanian population. [[Kosovo Albanians]] are currently trying to seek [[independence]] from [[Serbia]] on the grounds of self-determination. In any officially-sanctioned referendum it is likely a majority of ethnic Albanians would favour independence, whilst the minority 200,000 non-Albanians (mostly Serbs) would oppose it. International negotiations began in [[2006]] to determine the final status of Kosovo.

=== Jammu and Kashmir ===
{{main|Kashmir Conflict|Terrorism in Kashmir}}
[[Terrorism in Kashmir|Insurgent groups]] in [[Indian-controlled Kashmir]] (the Indian state of [[Jammu and Kashmir]]) such as [[Lashkar-e-Toiba]] and [[Hizbul Mujahideen]] are currently trying to seek full [[Independence]] for the whole region from [[India]] on the claim of its right to self-determination as an [[Islamic State]]. Both the insurgents and the Indian Armed forces stand accused of Human rights violations, with some insurgent groups conducting a policy of [[ethnic cleansing]] of [[Hindu]]s in Kashmir, and the Indian army being accused of violating human rights of ordinary citizens of Kashmir.&lt;ref&gt;Alexander Evans, A departure from history: Kashmiri Pandits, 1990–2001, Contemporary South Asia (Volume 11, Number 1, 1 March 2002, pp. 19-37)&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Puerto Rico ===
{{main|Puerto Rican independence movement}}
Since 1972, the U.N. Decolonization Committee has called for [[Puerto Rico]]'s decolonization and for the U.S. to recognize the island's right to self-determination and independence. Most recently, the Decolonization Subcommittee called for the [[United Nations General Assembly]] to review the political status of Puerto Rico, a power reserved by the 1953 Resolution. &lt;ref&gt; [http://www.un.org/News/Press/docs/2007/gacol3160.doc.htm SPECIAL COMMITTEE ON DECOLONIZATION CALLS ON UNITED STATES TO EXPEDITE PUERTO RICO’S SELF-DETERMINATION PROCESS - General Assembly GA/COL/3160 - Department of Public Information - June 14, 2007] &lt;/ref&gt;

=== Sri Lanka ===

Tamil ethnic minority in [[Sri Lanka]] is seeking independence for their traditional homeland in Sri Lanka. Ongoing war between the Sri Lankan government and the [[Liberation Tigers of Tamil Eelam]] (LTTE) has claimed thousands of lives including civilians and political leaders. Norwegian peace talks have failed to achieve peace in this region, and the war continues. The LTTE governs a part of the traditonal homeland of ethnic Tamil minority as a de facto state of [[Tamil Eelam]].

=== Northern Ireland ===

[[Northern Ireland]] offers a complex demonstration of the problems of self-determanition. In this case it is establishing who is eligible to vote in any such referendum. A majority (54%) of the population of Northern Ireland still favours continued [[political union|union]] with [[Great Britain]]. However, there are claims by [[Irish nationalists]] that any vote should be taken by the whole of [[Ireland]]. This would most likely result in Northern Ireland joining the rest of Ireland in a 32-county [[Republic]]. 

A referendum in 1973 showed overwhelming support for the union with Great Britain, but this was [[boycotted]] by most nationalists.

=== Spain ===
Movements are pushing for independence amongst the [[Basques]], [[Catalans]] and [[Galicians]]

=== Somaliland ===
Declaring independence in 1991 after the collapse of central authority in [[Somalia]] and its descent into civil war. [[Somaliland]] claims to be the successor state of the briefly independent [[State of Somaliland]] which declared independence after the dissolvment of the colony of [[British Somaliland]] in 1960.

It has not yet been recognised by any states despite the establishment of a stable democracy in one of the most turbulent parts of the continent.

=== Taiwan ===

{{main|Political Status of Taiwan}}

Taiwan is still the focus of a self-determination dispute in the [[East Asia]] region.  The government of the [[People's Republic of China]] claims the entirety of Taiwan as its territory.  However, Taiwanese independence advocates argue that there no legal claim over Taiwan as no legally binding treaty ever transferred sovereignty to China following World War II. At the same time, the ''de facto'' government of Taiwan, the [[Republic of China]] still officially claims the mainland and several other areas and denies the legitimacy of the People's Republic.  However, in practice, this claim essentially died off through the 1990s and is no longer pressed by Taiwan's elected government.

=== Turkish Cypriots ===
{{main|Turkish Republic of Northern Cyprus}}
Since 1974, [[Turkish Republic of Northern Cyprus]] (a state recognized by [[Turkey]] only), has been governing the northern part of the Mediterranean island, Cyprus. The [[Turkish Cypriot]] community claimed a right of self-determination in ending their partnership with the [[Greek Cypriots]] in the [[Republic of Cyprus]].

=== United States ===
The colonisation of the North American continent and its [[Native Americans in the United States|Native American]] population has been the source of legal battles since the early 1800s. The Westward push of European-American settlers eventually brought about the destruction of most Native American cultures, and what few remained were reduced to living on [[Indian reservation|reservations]]. These had been given a certain degree of [[autonomy]], within the United States federal government, which allows for their exclusion from various national legal restrictions.
Another group of people affected by the westward expansion of the European-Americans are Mexicans and their present descendents the Chicanos. Majorally of Native American and Mestizo descent these people lay claim to the stolen territories of the U.S. Southwest most notably: California, Arizona, Texas, Colorado, New Mexico, parts of Utah and Wyoming. These movements name this land mass Aztlan after the original homeland of the Mexica (Aztec)and or refer to it as "Occupied Mexico." They hold that the U.S.-Mexico Border is an Apartheid Border and that recent migrants from Mexico and Latin America are only following ancient migratory patterns of their native american ancestors. 

There is an active [[Hawaiian sovereignty movement]] which aims at rectifying the overthrow of the Hawaiian monarchy in the late 19th century which resulted in the incorporation of Hawaii into the United States.  They hold that self-determination was never granted to native Hawaiians after the overthrow and thus a large measure of autonomy or independence should be granted to Hawaii.  Opponents allege that this would violate the self-determination rights of the non-Hawaiian majority living in Hawaii now.

Almost all historians agree that the South was fighting for self-determination during the [[American Civil War]].

Further, there have at times been calls for local self-determination by ethnic minority communities. For example, the [[Young Lords]], a [[Puerto Rico|Puerto Rican]] internationalist group founded in [[Lincoln Park, Chicago]] in 1968, called not only for independence for Puerto Rico but also for neighborhood empowerment within cities in the continental United States, which they characterized as self-determination in every ''barrio'' or neighborhood.

=== Western Sahara ===

Formerly [[Spanish Sahara]], after the withdrawal of [[Spain|Spanish]] rule in 1975 an invasion by [[Morocco]] and [[Mauritania]] defeated the wishes of the indigenous population who supported the [[Sahrawi Arab Democratic Republic]] (SADR).

Morocco continues to refuse to accept any kind of referendum, and has continually spoken of [[autonomy]], through it has never revealed concrete plans for this either. [[UN]] attempts to organise a [[plebicite]] to settle the situation have floundered in recent years. The SADR receives the backing of [[Algeria]], and is a member of the [[African Union]]. It is currently recognised by 43 states. 22 others have withdrawn recognition.

==See also==
*[[Nationalism]]
*[[Ethnic nationalism]]
*[[Identity politics]]
*[[International relations theory]]
*[[Nation-state]]
*[[Non-Intervention]]
*[[Sovereignty]]
*[[Anglo-French Declaration]], November 7, 1918
*[[Wars of national liberation]]
*[[Puerto Rican Independence Movement]]
*[[Self-ownership]]
*[[Individualist anarchism]]
*[[National delimitation in the Soviet Union]]

==References==
&lt;references/&gt;
==External links==
*[http://www.un.org/documents/ga/res/15/ares15.htm United Nations General Assembly Resolution 1514(XV). "Declaration on the Granting of Independence to Colonial Countries and Peoples"]
*[http://www.unpo.org/article.php?id=4957 Unrepresented Nations and Peoples Organization on Self-determination]
*[http://www.princeton.edu/lisd. Liechtenstein Institute on Self-Determination at Princeton University]
*[http://www.tamilnation.org/selfdetermination/ Self Determination - International Law and Practise] collated &amp; sequenced by Nadesan Satyendra
*[http://www.mahapunjab.org/PNSD/ Parliamentarians for National Self-Determination] Unofficial page for London based Parliamentary lobby group
* [http://www.marxists.org/archive/lenin/works/1914/self-det/index.htm The Right of Nations to Self-Determination] [[Lenin|V. I. Lenin]] February-May 1914

[[Category:Political theories]]
[[Category:International relations]]
[[Category:International law]]
[[Category:Communism]]
[[Category:Maoism]]
[[Category:Nationalism]]
[[Category:Anarchism]]
[[Category:Sovereignty movements]]
[[Category:Human rights]]
[[Category:Collective rights]]

[[ast:Drechu d'autodetermín]]
[[ca:Autodeterminació]]
[[de:Selbstbestimmungsrecht der Völker]]
[[es:Derecho de libre determinación]]
[[eo:Rajto de memdetermino]]
[[eu:Autodeterminazio]]
[[fr:Autodétermination]]
[[it:Autodeterminazione dei popoli]]
[[he:הגדרה עצמית]]
[[ms:Pemerintahan-sendiri]]
[[nl:Zelfbeschikkingsrecht]]
[[ja:民族自決]]
[[no:Nasjonal selvråderett]]
[[pt:Autodeterminação]]
[[ru:Право на самоопределение]]
[[scn:Autuditirminazzioni di li pòpuli]]
[[sr:Самоопредељење]]
[[zh:民族自決]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>