<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20091116212905|326227419" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="29269" pageid="29269" ns="0" title="Self-determination"><revisions><rev timestamp="2009-11-16T21:32:45Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{About|self-determination in politics|the psychology theory|Self-determination theory}}
'''Self-determination''' is the free choice of one’s own acts without external compulsion; and especially as the freedom of the people of a given territory to determine their own political status. It can also be defined as the ability or power to make decisions for yourself, especially the power of a [[nation]] to decide how it will be governed. In other words, it is the right of the people of a nation to decide how they want to be governed without the influence of any other country.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/self-determination Merriam-Webster online dictionary]; [http://wordnet.princeton.edu/perl/webwn?s=self-determination Wordnet.Princeton definition];   [http://www.answers.com/topic/self-determination Answers.com definition].&lt;/ref&gt; The latter is a complex concept with conflicting definitions and legal criteria for determining which groups may legitimately claim the right to self-determination.&lt;ref name="Unterberger"&gt;Betty Miller Unterberger, [http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_gx5215/is_2002/ai_n19132482 Self-Determination], Encyclopedia of American Foreign Policy, 2002.&lt;/ref&gt; This often coincides with various [[nationalist]] movements.

==History==
===Pre-20th century===
Just as [[colonisation]] and [[colonialism]] have been practiced throughout recorded history, political self-determination, on an individual level, has been documented similarly and cherished highly by collective peoples despite them; ancient [[Mesopotamia]] and the later [[Polis|Greek city-states]] are early examples of its practice.&lt;ref name="Unterberger"/&gt;

The revolt of [[New World]] British colonists in North America, during the mid-1770s, has been seen as the first assertion of the right of national and democratic self-determination, because of the explicit invocation of natural law, the natural rights of man, as well as the consent of, and sovereignty by, the people governed; these ideas were inspired particularly by [[John Locke]]’s [[Age of Enlightenment|enlightened]] writings of the previous century. [[Thomas Jefferson]] further promoted the notion that the will of the people was supreme, especially through authorship of the [[Declaration of Independence]] which inspired [[Europe]]ans throughout the 19th century.&lt;ref name="Unterberger"/&gt; The French Revolution was motivated similarly and legitimatized the ideas of self-determination on that [[Old World]] continent.&lt;ref&gt;Chimène Keitner, [[Oxford University]], [http://www.ciaonet.org/isa/woc01/National Self-Determination: The Legacy of the French Revolution], paper presented at International Studies Association Annual Meeting, March 2000.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F60B16FD3D5C147A93C2AB178CD85F4D8185F9 Self-Determination Not a New Expedient; First Plebiscite Was Held in Avignon During the French Revolution&amp;mdash;Forthcoming Book Traces History and Growth of the Movement], [[New York Times]],
July 20, 1919, 69.&lt;/ref&gt;

During the early 1800s most of the nations of [[South America]] achieved [[Hispanic American wars of independence|independence from Spain]]. The United States supported that status, as policy in the hemisphere relative to European colonialism, with the [[Monroe Doctrine]]. The American public, organized associated groups, and even Congressional resolutions, often supported such movements, particularly the [[Greek War of Independence]] (1821-29) and the [[12 points of the Hungarian Revolutionaries of 1848|demands of Hungarian revolutionaries in 1848]]. Such support, however, never became official government policy, due to balancing of other [[national interests]]. After the [[American Civil War]] and with increasing capability, the [[United States]] government opposed self-determination for the West Indian islands of [[Saint Thomas, U.S. Virgin Islands|Saint Thomas]] and [[St. John, U.S. Virgin Islands|Saint John]] in 1868, the [[Hawaii|Hawaiian Islands]] in 1868. With its victory in the [[Spanish-American War]] in 1899 and its growing stature in the world the United States supported annexation of the former Spanish colonies of [[Guam]], [[Puerto Rico]] and the [[Philippines]], without the consent of their peoples, and it retained “quasi-[[suzerainty]]” over Cuba, as well.&lt;ref name="Unterberger"/&gt;

===World War I and II===
[[Woodrow Wilson]] revived the American commitment to self-determination, at least for European states, during [[World War I]]. When the [[Bolsheviks]] came to power in [[Russia]] in November 1917, they called for Russia’s immediate withdrawal as a member of the [[Allies of World War I]]. They also supported the right of all nations, including colonies, to self-determination. (As early as 1914 Lenin wrote: “[It] would be wrong to interpret the right to self-determination as meaning anything but the right to existence as a separate state.”&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.marxists.org/archive/lenin/works/1914/self-det/ch01.htm#v20pp72-395 "What Is Meant By The Self-Determination of Nations?"]&lt;/ref&gt;) The 1918 [[1918 Soviet Constitution|Constitution of the Soviet Union]] acknowledged the right of [[secession]] for its constituent [[republic]]s.&lt;ref name="Unterberger"/&gt;

This presented a challenge to Wilson’s more limited demands. In January 1918 Wilson issued his [[Fourteen Points]] of January 1918 which, among other things, called for adjustment of colonial claims, as long as the interests of colonial powers had equal weight with the claims of subject peoples.&lt;ref name="Unterberger"/&gt; The [[Treaty of Brest-Litovsk]] in March 1918 led to Russia's exit from the war and the independence of [[Finland]], [[Estonia]], [[Latvia]], [[Ukraine]], [[Lithuania]] and [[Second Polish Republic|Poland]]. The end of the war led to the dissolution of the defeated [[Austro-Hungarian Empire]] and the creation by the Allies of [[Czechoslovakia]] and the union of the [[State of Slovenes, Croats and Serbs]] and the [[Kingdom of Serbia]] as new states. However, this imposition of states where some nationalities (especially Poles, Czechs, and Serbs and [[Romanians]]) were given power over nationalities who disliked and distrusted them eventually helped lead to [[World War II]]. The defeated [[Ottoman empire]] was dissolved into the [[Republic of Turkey]] and several smaller nations, including [[Yemen]], plus the new [[Middle east]] [[Allies of World War I|Allied]] “[[League of Nations mandate|mandate]]s” of [[French Mandate for Syria and the Lebanon|Syria and Lebanon]] (future [[Syria]], [[Lebanon]] and [[Hatay State]]), [[British Mandate of Palestine|Palestine]] (future [[Transjordan]] and [[Israel]]), [[British Mandate of Mesopotamia|Mesopotamia]] (future [[Iraq]]). The [[League of Nations]] was proposed as much as a means of consolidating these new states, as a path to [[peace]].&lt;ref name="Rothbard"&gt;[[Murray N. Rothbard]], [http://www.lewrockwell.com/rothbard/rothbard134.html National Self-Determination], Rothbard Archives at [[Lewrockwell.com]], August, 1990.&lt;/ref&gt;

During the 1920s and 1930s there were some successful movements for self-determination in the beginnings of the process of [[decolonization]]. In the [[Statute of Westminster 1931|Statute of Westminster]] the [[United Kingdom]] granted independence to [[Canada]], [[New Zealand]], [[Newfoundland and Labrador|Newfoundland]], the [[Irish Free State]], the Commonwealth of [[Australia]], and the [[Union of South Africa]] after the [[British parliament]] declared itself as incapable of passing laws over them without their consent. [[Egypt]], [[Afghanistan]] and [[Iraq]] also achieved [[independence]] from Britain and [[Lebanon]] from [[France]]. Other efforts were unsuccessful, like the [[Indian independence movement]]. And [[Italy]], [[Japan]] and [[Germany]] all initiated new efforts to bring certain territories under their control, leading to [[World War II]].

===The UN Charter===
In 1941 [[Allies of World War II]] signed the [[Atlantic Charter]] and accepted the principle of self-determination. In January 1942 twenty-six nations signed the [[Declaration by United Nations]], which accepted those principles. The ratification of the [[United Nations Charter]] in 1945 at then end of World War II placed the right of self-determination into the framework of international law and diplomacy.  
*Chapter 1, Article 1, part 2 states that purpose of the UN Charter is: “To develop friendly relations among nations based on respect for the principle of equal rights and self-determination of peoples, and to take other appropriate measures to strengthen universal peace.”&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.un.org/aboutun/charter/ United Nations Charter]&lt;/ref&gt;
*Article 1 in both the [[International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights]] (ICCPR)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unhchr.ch/html/menu3/b/a_ccpr.htm Text of International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights]&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[International Covenant on Economic, Social and Cultural Rights]] (ICESCR).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unhchr.ch/html/menu3/b/a_cescr.htm Text of International Covenant on Economic, Social and Cultural Rights]&lt;/ref&gt; Both read: “All peoples have the right of self-determination. By virtue of that right they freely determine their political status and freely pursue their economic, social and cultural development.” 
*The United Nations [[Universal Declaration of Human Rights]] article 15 states that everyone has the right to a nationality and that no one should be arbitrarily deprived of a nationality or denied the right to change nationality. 

However, the charter and other resolutions did not insist on full independence as the best way of obtaining [[self-government]], nor did they include an enforcement mechanism. Moreover, nations were recognized by the legal doctrine of [[uti possidetis juris]], meaning that old administrative boundaries would become international boundaries upon independence, even if they had little relevance to linguistic, ethnic, and cultural boundaries.&lt;ref name="Hensel"&gt;Paul R. Hensel and Michael E. Allison, Department of Political Science  [[Florida State University]] and Ahmed Khanani, Department of Political Science, [[Indiana University]], [http://garnet.acns.fsu.edu/~phensel/Research/io05.pdf The Colonial Legacy and Border Stability: Uti Possidetis and Territorial Claims in the Americas], research paper at Paul Hensel’s Florida State university web site.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Gudeleviciute"&gt;Vita Gudeleviciute, [http://www.ceeol.com/aspx/getdocument.aspx?logid=5&amp;id=3aa23ac1-66e8-4193-a3e1-a7286ee6bfd5 Does the Principle of Self-determination Prevail over the Principle of Territorial Integrity?], International Journal of Baltic Law, [[Vytautas Magnus University]] School of Law, Volume 2, No. 2 (April, 2005).&lt;/ref&gt; Nevertheless, justified by the language of self-determination, between 1946 and 1960, the peoples of thirty-seven new nations freed themselves from colonial status in [[Asia]], [[Africa]], and the [[Middle East]].&lt;ref name="Unterberger"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[:s:United Nations General Assembly Resolution 1514|Resolution 1514 (XV) "Declaration on the Granting of Independence to Colonial Countries and Peoples"]]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www2.ohchr.org/english/law/independence.htm Declaration on the Granting of Independence to Colonial Countries and Peoples], General Assembly resolution 1514 (XV) of 14 December 1960.&lt;/ref&gt;  The territoriality issue inevitably would lead to more conflicts and independence movements within many nations and challenges to the assumption that [[territorial integrity]] is as important as self-determination.&lt;ref name="Hensel"/&gt; 

The [[Soviet Union]]’s successful post-war efforts to turn [[East Germany|Eastern Germany]] and the countries of [[Eastern Europe]] into Soviet [[satellite states]] contrasted with decolonization. The additional success of communists in creating the [[People's Republic of China]] led to the [[Cold War]] with western nations. These nations became willing to support authoritarian governments as long as they remained [[anti-communist]] and began to suspect all self-determinations movements of being communist-inspired or controlled.&lt;ref name="Unterberger"/&gt;  Thus the United States entered into a 10 year war in [[Vietnam]], taking over from [[French colonial empire|French colonialists]],&lt;ref&gt;Elizabeth Chadwick, [http://books.google.com/books?id=NxP5y5guFu8C&amp;client= Self-determination, terrorism, and the international humanitarian law of armed conflict], Martinus Nijhoff Publishers, 1996, [http://books.google.com/books?id=NxP5y5guFu8C&amp;pg=PA193&amp;dq=united+states+self-determination+vietnam+war&amp;ei=Da4eSru8MpaQyATVmPW2Dw&amp;client=firefox-a#PPA192,M1 p. 192-193] ISBN 9041101225&lt;/ref&gt; and supported [[Portugal]] in its attempts to hold on to [[Angola]]. The [[Soviet Union]] also violated principles of self-determination by suppressing the [[Hungarian revolution of 1956]] and the [[Prague Spring]] Czechoslovak reforms of 1968.  [[Soviet war in Afghanistan|It invaded Afghanistan]] to support an increasingly unpopular communist government assailed by local tribal groups.&lt;ref name="Unterberger"/&gt;

The Cold War began to wind down after [[Mikhail Gorbachev]] assumed power in March 1985. With the cooperation of U.S. president [[Ronald Reagan]], Gorbachev wound down the size of the [[Soviet Armed Forces]] and reduced nuclear arms in Europe, while liberalizing the [[economy of the Soviet Union|economy]]. In 1989 in rapid succession, communist regimes collapsed in Poland, Hungary, Czechoslovakia, East Germany, and Romania. In December 1991, Gorbachev resigned as president and the [[Soviet_union#Reforms_of_Gorbachev_and_dissolution|Soviet Union dissolved]] relatively peacefully into fifteen sovereign republics, all of which rejected communism and most of which adopted democratic reforms and free-market economies. [[Yugoslavia#Breakup|Yugoslavia]] began a much more violent break up in 1990.&lt;ref name="Unterberger"/&gt;

==Current Issues==
Since the early 1990s, the legitimatization of the principle of national self-determination has led to an increase in the number of conflicts within states, as sub-groups seek greater self-determination and even full secession, and as their conflicts for leadership within groups and with other groups and with the dominant state become violent.&lt;ref&gt;Martin Griffiths, [http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/journals/MqLJ/2003/3.html Self-determination, International Society And World Order], [[Macquarie University]] Law Journal, 1, 2003.&lt;/ref&gt; The international reaction to these new movements has been uneven and often dictated more by politics than principle. The year 2000 United Nations Millennium Declaration failed to deal with these new demands, mentioning only “the right to self-determination of peoples which remain under colonial domination and foreign occupation.”&lt;ref name="Gudeleviciute"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.un.org/millennium/declaration/ares552e.pdf United Nations Millennium Declaration, adopted by the UN General Assembly Resolution 55/2 (08 09 2000), paragraph 4.]&lt;/ref&gt;

In an issue of [[Macquarie University]] Law Journal Associate professor Aleksandar Pavkovic and Senior Lecturer Peter Radan outlined current legal and political issues in self-determination.&lt;ref name="Pavkovic"&gt; Aleksandar Pavkovic and Peter Radan,  [http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/journals/MqLJ/2003/1.html In Pursuit of Sovereignty and Self-determination: Peoples, States and Secession in the International Order], [http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/journals/MqLJ/2003/index.html Index of papers], [[Macquerie University]] Law Journal, 1, 2003.&lt;/ref&gt; These include:

===Defining "peoples"===
There is not yet a recognized legal definition of "peoples" in international law. Vita Gudeleviciute of [[Vytautas Magnus University]] Law School, reviewing international law and UN resolutions, finds in cases of non-self-governing peoples (colonized and/or indigenous) and foreign military occupation "a people" is the entire population of the occupied territorial unit, no matter their other differences. In cases where people lack representation by a state’s government, the unrepresented become a separate people. Present international law does not recognize ethnic and other minorities as separate peoples.&lt;ref name="Gudeleviciute"/&gt; Other definitions offered are "peoples" being self-evident (from ethnicity, language, history, etc.), or defined by "ties of mutual affection or sentiment," i.e. "loyalty," or by mutual obligations among peoples. Or the definition may be simply that a people is a group of individuals who unanimously choose a separate state. If the “people” are unanimous in their desire for self-determination, it strengthens their claim. For example, the populations of federal units of the Yugoslav federation were considered a people in the breakup of Yugoslavia, even though some of those units had very diverse populations.&lt;ref name="Pavkovic"/&gt; Libertarians who argue for self-determination distinguish between the voluntary nation (the land, the culture, the terrain, the people) and the state, the coercive apparatus, which they have a right to choose or self-determine.&lt;ref name="Rothbard"/&gt;

===Self-determination versus territorial integrity===
National self-determination challenges the principle of territorial integrity (or [[sovereignty]]) of states because it is the will of the people that makes a state legitimate. This implies a people should be free to choose their own state and its territorial boundaries. However, there are far more self-identified nations than there are existing states and there is no legal process to redraw state boundaries according to the will of these peoples.&lt;ref name="Pavkovic"/&gt; 

Pavkovic and Radan describe three theories of international relations relevant to self-determination.
* The realist theory of international relations insists that territorial sovereignty is more important than national self-determination. This policy was pursued by the major powers during the Cold War.  
* Liberal internationalism has become an alternative since that time. It promotes the abolition of war among states as well as increased individual liberty within states, and holds the expansion of global markets and cross-border cooperation diminishes the significance of territorial integrity, allowing for somewhat greater recognition of greater self-determination of peoples. 
* Cosmopolitan liberalism calls for political power to shift to a world government which would make secession and change of boundaries a relatively easy administrative matter. However, also would mean the de facto end of self-determination of national groups.&lt;ref name="Pavkovic"/&gt; 

[[Allen Buchanan]], author of seven books on self-determination and secession, supports territorial integrity as a moral and legal aspect of constitutional democracy. However, he also advances a “Remedial Rights Only Theory”  where a group has “a general right to secede if and only if it has suffered certain injustices, for which secession is the appropriate remedy of last resort.” He also would recognize secession if the state grants, or the constitution includes, a right to secede.&lt;ref name="Gudeleviciute"/&gt; 

Vita Gudeleviciute holds that in cases of non-self-governing peoples and foreign military occupation the principle of self-determination trumps that of territorial integrity. In cases where people lack representation by a state’s government, they also may be considered a separate people, but under current law cannot claim the right to self-determination. On the other hand, he finds that secession within a single state is a domestic matter not covered by international law. Thus there are no on what groups may constitute a seceding people.&lt;ref name="Gudeleviciute"/&gt;

===Methods of increasing minority rights===
In order to accommodate demands for minority rights and avoid secession and the creation of a separate new state, many states [[decentralization|decentralize]] or [[devolution|devolve]] greater decision-making power to new or existing subunits or even [[autonomous areas]]. More limited measures might include restricting demands to the maintenance of national cultures or granting non-territorial autonomy in the form of national associations which would assume control over cultural matters. This would be available only to groups that abandoned secessionist demands and the territorial state would retain political and judicial control, but only if would remain with the territorially organized state.&lt;ref name="Pavkovic"/&gt;

===Self-determination versus majority rule/equal rights===
Pavković explores how national self-determination, in the form of creation of a new state through secession, could override the principles of [[majority rule]] and of [[equal rights]], which are primary liberal principles. This includes the question of how an unwanted state can be imposed upon a minority. He explores five contemporary theories of secession. In “anarcho-capitalist” theory only landowners have the right to secede. In communitarian theory, only those groups that desire direct or greater political participation have the right, including groups deprived of rights, per Allen Buchanan. In two nationalist theories, only national cultural groups have a right to secede. Australian professor Harry Beran’s democratic theory endorses the equality of the right of secession to all types of groups. Unilateral secession against majority rule is justified if the group allows secession of any other group within its territory.&lt;ref&gt;Aleksandar Pavković, [http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/journals/MqLJ/2003/5.html Majority Rule and Equal Rights: a Few Questions], [[Macquerie University]] Law Journal, 1, 2003.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Harry Beran, “A Democratic Theory of Political Self-Determination for a New World Order” in Percy Lehning (ed), Theories of Secession (1998) 36, 39, 42-43.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Constitutional law===
Most sovereign states do not recognize the right to self-determination through secession in their constitutions. Many expressly forbid it. However, there are several existing models of self-determination through greater autonomy and through secession.&lt;ref name="Kreptul"&gt;Andrei Kreptul, [http://mises.org/journals/jls/17_4/17_4_3.pdf The Constitutional Right of Secession in Political Theory and History], [[Journal of Libertarian Studies]], [[Ludwig von Mises Institute]], Volume 17, no. 4 (Fall 2003), pp. 39–100.&lt;/ref&gt;

In liberal constitutional democracies the principle of [[majority rule]] has dictated whether a minority can secede. In the United States [[Abraham Lincoln]] acknowledged that secession might be possible through [[List of amendments to the United States Constitution|amending]] the [[United States Constitution]]. The [[Supreme Court of the United States|Supreme Court]] in [[Texas v White]], held secession could occur "through revolution, or through consent of the States."&lt;ref&gt;Aleksandar Pavković, Peter Radan, [http://books.google.com/books?id=-IjHbPvp1W0C  Creating New States: Theory and Practice of Secession], p. 222, Ashgate Publishing, Ltd., 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.law.cornell.edu/supct/html/historics/USSC_CR_0074_0700_ZO.html ''Texas v. White''], 74 U.S. 700 (1868) at [[Cornell University Law School]] Supreme Court collection.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Parliament of the United Kingdom|British Parliament]] in 1933 held that [[Western Australia]] only could secede from Australia upon vote of a majority of the country as a whole; the previous two-thirds majority vote for secession via referendum in Western Australia was insufficient.&lt;ref name="Pavkovic"/&gt; 

The [[Communist Party of China|Chinese Communist Party]] followed the Soviet Union in including the right of secession in its 1931 constitution in order to entice ethnic nationalities and Tibet into joining. However, the Party eliminated the right to secession in later years, and had anti-secession clause written into the Constitution before and after the founding the People's Republic of China. The 1947 Constitution of the [[Burma|Union of Burma]] contained an express state right to secede from the union under a number of procedural conditions. It was eliminated in the 1974 constitution of the Socialist Republic of the Union of Burma (officially the “Union of Myanmar”). Burma still allows “local autonomy under central leadership.”&lt;ref name="Kreptul"/&gt;
 
As of 1996 the constitutions of Austria, [[Ethiopia]], France, [[Singapore]]{{Citation needed|date=October 2009}}, [[Federation of Saint Kitts and Nevis|Saint Kitts and Nevis Republics]] have express or implied rights to secession. [[Switzerland]] allows for the secession from current and the creation of new [[Cantons of Switzerland|cantons]]. In the case of proposed [[Quebec]] separation from Canada the [[Supreme Court of Canada]] in 1998 ruled that only both a clear majority of the province and a constitutional amendment confirmed by all participants in the Canadian federation could allow secession.&lt;ref name="Kreptul"/&gt;

The 2003 draft of the [[Treaty establishing a Constitution for Europe|European Union Constitution]] allowed for the voluntary withdrawal of member states from the union.&lt;ref name="Kreptul"/&gt; There was much discussion about such self-determination by minorities&lt;ref&gt;Xenophon Contiades, [http://www.inter-disciplinary.net/AUD/s6.htm Sixth Scholarly Panel: Cultural Identity in the New Europe], 1st Global Conference on Federalism and the Union of European Democracies, March 2004.&lt;/ref&gt; before the final document underwent the unsuccessful ratification process in 2005.

===Drawing new borders===
Once groups exercise self-determination through secession, the issue of the proposed borders may prove more controversial than the fact of secession. The bloody Yugoslav wars in the 1990s were related mostly to borders issues because the international community applied a version of [[uti possidetis juris]] in transforming existing internal borders of the various Yugoslav republics into international borders, despite the conflicts of ethnic groups within those boundaries. The northern two-thirds of Quebec already has made it clear it will resist by force being incorporated into a Quebec nation.&lt;ref name="Pavkovic"/&gt;

The border between [[Northern Ireland]] and the [[Irish Free State]] was based on the borders of existing counties and did not include all of historic [[Ulster]].  A Boundary Commission was established to consider re-drawing it. Its proposals, which amounted to a small net transfer to Northern Ireland, were leaked to the press and then not acted upon. In December 1925, the governments of the Irish Free State, Northern Ireland, and the United Kingdom agreed to accept the existing border. Most Irish Nationalists and Irish Republicans claim all of Northern Ireland and are not particularly interested in new borders.{{Citation needed|date=August 2008}}

==Current movements==
For past movements see [[list of historical autonomist and secessionist movements]] and [[Decolonization#Charts_of_the_independences|lists of decolonized nations]]. Also see [[list of autonomous areas by country]] and [[list of territorial autonomies]] and [[list of active autonomist and secessionist movements]].

===Abkhazia and South Ossetia===
{{Main|International recognition of Abkhazia and South Ossetia}}

===Australia===
{{Main|Self-determination of Australian Aborigines}}
Recently (2003 onwards), self-determination has become the topic of some debate in Australia in relation to Aborigines (indigenous Australians). In the 1970s, the Aboriginal community approached the Federal Government and requested the right to administer their own communities. This encompassed basic local government functions, ranging from land dealings and management of community centres to road maintenance and garbage collection, as well as setting education programmes and standards in their local schools.

===Balochistan province===
{{Main|Balochistan conflict}}
Since 1948, [[Baloch nationalist]]s in [[Pakistan]], [[Iran]], and [[Afghanistan]] have been seeking independence as a separate state for the [[Baloch people]] from elements outside the country. The movement has culminated in several armed uprisings in both Pakistan and Iran, that have been crushed, especially during the 1970s. The movement is strongest in [[Balochistan (Pakistan)]], where it is led by the [[Balochistan Liberation Army]] and the [[Baloch Students Organization]].

===Basque Country===
{{Main|Basque nationalism}}
The '''Basque Country''' ({{lang-eu|Euskal Herria}}, {{lang-es|País Vasco}}, {{lang-fr|Pays Basque}}) as a [[cultural region]] (not to be confused with the homonym [[Autonomous Community]] of the [[Basque Country (autonomous community)|Basque country]]) is a [[Europe]]an region in the western [[Pyrenees]] that spans the border between [[France]] and [[Spain]], on the [[Atlantic Ocean|Atlantic]] coast. It comprises the autonomous communities of the [[Basque Country (autonomous community)|Basque Country]] and [[Navarre]] in [[Spain]] and then the [[Northern Basque Country]] in [[France]].
Since the 19th century, [[Basque nationalism]] has demanded the right of some kind of self-determination{{Citation needed|date=January 2008}}. This desire for independence is particularly stressed among [[left-wing politics|leftist]] Basque nationalists. The right of self-determination was asserted by the [[Basque Parliament]] in 1990, 2002 and 2006.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.eitb24.com/portal/eitb24/noticia/en/politics/pp-and-pse-voted-against-basque-parliament-adopts-resolution-on-s?itemId=B24_18787&amp;cl=%2Feitb24%2Fpolitica&amp;idioma=en EITB: ''Basque parliament adopts resolution on self-determination'']&lt;/ref&gt; 
Since{{Citation needed|date=January 2008}} self-determination is not recognized in the [[Spanish Constitution of 1978]], some Basques abstained and some even voted against it in the referendum of December 6 of that year. However, it was approved by a clear [[majority]] at the Spanish level, and simple majority at Navarrese and Basque levels. The derived autonomous regimes for the BAC was approved in later referendum but the autonomy of Navarre (''amejoramiento del fuero'': "improvement of the charter") was never subject to referendum but just approved by the Navarrese Cortes (parliament).
There are not many sources on the issue for the French Basque country.

''[[Euskadi Ta Askatasuna]]'' (ETA) {{lang|eu|'''Euskadi Ta Askatasuna'''}} or '''ETA''' ({{lang-en|Basque Homeland and Freedom}}; {{pronounced|ˈɛːta}}), is an armed [[Basque nationalist]] and [[separatist]] organization.&lt;!-- Do not add "terrorist" here, that is covered in the very next paragraph --&gt; Founded in 1959, it evolved from a group advocating traditional cultural ways to a [[paramilitary]] group with the goal of [[Basque independence]]. Its ideology is Marxist-Leninist.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.goizargi.com/2003/queeselmlnv4.htm"What is the MNLV (4)"&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.goizargi.com/2003/queeselmlnv3.htm "What is the MNLV (3)"&lt;/ref&gt;

===Biafra===
{{Main|Biafra}}
Biafra Republic was first declared in 1967 by Lt. Col Chukwuemeka Odumegwu Ojukwu but the state could only survive for 30 months during which Nigerian government fought the break-away republic to annex it. Over 3 million Igbos lost their lives in the ensuing war.

In 1999, a new group of activists formed an organization Movement for the Actualization of the Sovereign Republic of Biafra (MASSOB). Various other other groups have been formed with similar agenda.

===Catalan Countries===
{{Main|Països Catalans|Catalan independentism}}
[[Països Catalans]] (in [[catalan]], often literally translated into English as ''Catalan Countries'') refers to the territories where [[Catalan language]] was historically spoken&lt;ref&gt;"[http://www.grec.cat/cgibin/hecangcl.pgm?NDCHEC=0048266&amp;PGMORI=E  The Catalan Countries]". ''Grup Enciclopèdia Catalana''. Accessed: 13 February 2008&lt;/ref&gt;.
These territories in the past were in the, talking in contemporary terms, Confederation of the [[Crown of Aragon]]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.questia.com/PM.qst?a=o&amp;d=59158729&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.enciclopedia.cat/fitxa_v2.jsp?NDCHEC=0225093 {{ca}}&lt;/ref&gt; (which included the [[Kingdom of Aragon]], the [[Kingdom of Valencia]], the [[Kingdom of Majorca]], [[Sicily]], [[Malta]] and [[Sardinia]], and for a brief period, [[Provence]], the [[Kingdom of Naples]], the [[Duchy of Neopatria]], and the [[Duchy of Athens]].)&lt;ref&gt;[http://libro.uca.edu/chaytor/empire.jpg Original Aragonese Empire extension map on "A History of Aragon and Catalonia" by H. J. Chaytor]&lt;/ref&gt;.

Nowadays there are a lot of movements which supports the [[independentism|independence]] of [[Catalan Countries]] from [[Spain]] and [[France]]. Some of the politic parties of Catalonia, Valencian community, and Balear islands that follow this idea are [[Republican Left of Catalonia]] and [[Republican Left of the Valencian Country]], [[Estat Català]], Partit Republicà Català, [[CUP|Popular Unity Candidates]], [[Valencian Nationalist Bloc]], Bloc per Mallorca, etc. Furthermore, there are some other Catalan groups and movements that want the independence of Catalan Countries, such as: Sobirania i Progrés&lt;ref&gt;http://www.sobiraniaiprogres.cat/ {{ca}}&lt;/ref&gt;, Deu Mil per l'autodeterminació&lt;ref&gt;http://deumil.cat/ {{ca}}&lt;/ref&gt;, Catalunya Estat Lliure &lt;ref&gt;http://www.catalunyaestatlliure.cat/ {{ca}}&lt;/ref&gt;, Sobirania Valenciana &lt;ref&gt;http://sobiraniavalenciana.org/Portada.htm&lt;/ref&gt;, etc.
All these political parties and movements follow a non-violence way to express their ideas.

===Chechnya===
Under Dzhokkar Dudayev, Chechnya declared independence as the [[Chechen Republic of Ichkeria]], using self-determination, Russia's history of bad treatment of Chechens, and a history of independence before invasion by Russia as main motives. Russia has now reinvaded Chechnya, but the separatist government functions still in exile, though it has been split into two entities: the Achmed Zakayev-run pro-Russian Chechen Republic (based in [[Poland]], the [[UK]] and the [[US]]), and the Islamic Caucasus Emirate.

===Germany===
Under conditions of peace and in democratic state the focus of German public addresses weaker topics, as especially the ''Rights of informational self determination''. This is a new topic in the context of surveillance of public areas and surveillance at work &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.heise.de/mobil/Personen-und-Geraete-per-GPS-Mobilfunk-oder-WLAN-lokalisieren--/artikel/121778/0 Personen und Geraete per GPS, Mobilfunk oder WLAN lokalisieren]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://beat.doebe.li/bibliothek/t05126.html Technische Basis zum Internet der Dinge]&lt;/ref&gt;. {{Clarify|date=July 2009}}

===Israel and Palestine===
{{Main|Israel-Palestine conflict}}
The right to self-determination as outlined in [[public international law]] is often referenced by both sides in the ongoing [[Israel-Palestinian conflict]].

===Jammu and Kashmir===
{{Main|Kashmir Conflict}}

There is a democratic movement for independence from [[India|Indian rule]] led by the [[Hurriyat Conference]] in [[Jammu and Kashmir|India Administered Kashmir]]. The pro-freedom groups demand that a free and impartial [[plebiscite]] under the aegis of the [[United Nation]] as per the [http://www.kashmiri-cc.ca/un/  United Nation resolutions on Kashmir] be applied.  And that, the [[UN Resolution]] can peacefully and permanently solve the [[Kashmir dispute|Kashmir conflict]] in order to restore peace in the region and put an end to nearly 60 years of mayhem in [[Kashmir]]. Some groups have even suggested that a third option of Independence be added in order to update the 'old' Resolution. [http://www.kashmiri-cc.ca/un/sc21apr48.htm UN Resolution 47] has only two options, namely union with [[India]] and union with [[Pakistan]].&lt;ref name="Right To Self-determination,   A Key To Kashmir Solution"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.countercurrents.org/kashmir-safvi240207.htm|title=Right To Self-determination, A Key To Kashmir Solution|first=Syed Ali Safvi|date=24 February, 2007|publisher=Countercurrents.org|accessdate=12 August 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

[[Jawaharlal Nehru]], the first [[Prime Minister of India]], on several occasions made it public that "...[[Kashmir]] should decide question of accession by [[plebiscite]] or [[referendum]] under international auspices such as those of the [[United Nations]]..." Ironically, [[India]] has refrained from granting the right of self-determination to the people of [[Kashmir]], which is their democratic right by all standards of [[International Law]].&lt;ref name="INDIA'S COMMITMENT OF PLEBISCITE FOR   THE PEOPLE OF KASHMIR"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.na.gov.pk/s_kashmir_india_comitment.html|title=INDIA'S COMMITMENT OF PLEBISCITE FOR THE PEOPLE OF KASHMIR|accessdate=2009-08-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Kosovo===
{{Main|Kosovo status process}}
[[Kosovo]] is a largely ethnic-[[Albania]]n nation (Albanians 88%, Serbs 6%, Bosniaks 3%, Roma 2%, Turks 1%),&lt;ref name="FCO"&gt;[http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/about-the-fco/country-profiles/europe/kosovo Background Brief : Kosovo], ''Foreign &amp; Commonwealth Office''.&lt;/ref&gt;  which seeks independence on territories long held by ethnic Serbs, including as part of [[Yugoslavia]]. Conflict between the two culminated in the 1996-1999 [[Kosovo War]] between the [[Kosovo Liberation Army]] (KLA) and the then [[Federal Republic of Yugoslavia]] led by [[Slobodan Milošević]]. This culminated in the 1999 [[United States]]/[[NATO]] [[1999 NATO bombing of the Federal Republic of Yugoslavia|attacks on Serbia]], withdrawal of Serbian troops and entry of the NATO [[Kosovo Force]]. International negotiations to determine the final status of Kosovo were unsuccessful. On 17 February 2008, 109 members (10 members including all Kosovo Serbs were absent) of the [[Kosovo Assembly]] voted unanimously for a unilateral declaration of independence.{{Citation needed|date=August 2009}} Serbia rejected the decision. Kosovo is independent, supervised by the international community following the conclusion of the political process to determine Kosovo’s final status envisaged in UN Security Council Resolution 1244.&lt;ref name="FCO"/&gt; See the [[2008 Kosovo declaration of independence]]. In February 2008 Europe's major powers and the United States recognised independence of Kosovo.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/country_profiles/3550401.stm Timeline : Kosovo], ''BBC News''.&lt;/ref&gt; As of November 2009, the independence of Kosovo has been recognized by {{kosovorecognition}} countries.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.kosovothanksyou.com/ Who Recognized Kosova? The Kosovar people thank you]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rks-gov.net/sq-AL/Pages/ShtetKaneNjohurKosoven.aspx Republic of Kosova Government]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Kurdistan===
[[Kurdistan]] is the land of the [[Kurdish people]] of the middle east. The territory is currently part of 4 states [[Turkey]], [[Iraq]], [[Syria]] and [[Iran]]. There are Kurdish self determination movements in each of the 4 states. Iraqi Kurdistan has to date achieved the largest degree of self-determination through the formation of the [[Kurdistan Regional Government]], an entity recognised by the Iraqi Federal Constitution. 

Although the right of the creation of a Kurdish state was recognized following [[World War I]] in the [[Treaty of Sèvres]], the treaty was then annulled by the [[Treaty of Lausanne]]. To date two separate Kurdish republics and one Kurdish Kingdom have declared sovereignty. The [[Republic of Ararat]] (Northern Kurdistan/Eastern Turkey), the [[Republic of Mehabad]] (Eastern Kurdistan/Iranian Kurdistan) and the [[Kingdom of Kurdistan]] (Southern Kurdistan/Northern Iraq), each of these fledgling states was crushed by military intervention. The [[Patriotic Union of Kurdistan]] which currently holds the [[President of Iraq|Iraqi presidency]] and the [[Kurdistan Democratic Party]] which governs the [[Kurdistan Regional Government]] both explicitly commit themselves to the development of Kurdish self-determination.

===New Zealand===
{{Main|South Island Independence}}

Secession movements have surfaced several times in the [[South Island]] of [[New Zealand]]. The [[Prime Minister of New Zealand]], Sir [[Julius Vogel]], was among the first people to make this call,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tkhome.net/de/referate/nz.php History of New Zealand]&lt;/ref&gt; which was voted on by the [[Parliament of New Zealand]] as early as 1865. The desire for South Island independence was one of the main factors in moving the capital of New Zealand from [[Auckland]] to [[Wellington]] that year.

The [[South Island Party]] with a pro-South agenda, fielded candidates in the [[New Zealand general election 1999|1999 General Election]] and a new [[South Island Party (2008)|South Island Party]] was formed before the [[New Zealand general election 2008|2008 General Election]].  Today, the question of South Island Independence remains publicly debated but is not a political issue.

===South Africa===
{{Main|Volkstaat}}

===Southern Cameroons/Ambazonia===
[[Southern Cameroons]] today makes up the two English-speaking regions of the [[Cameroon|Republic of Cameroun]], the North West and South West regions. The people of Southern Cameroons' claim to self-determination arises out of their allegations that the [[Cameroon|Republic of Cameroun]] forcefully annexed their territory by the 1961 take over of the territory and the 1972 dissolution of the federation in favor of a [[Cameroon|Unitary Republic of Cameroon]]. Southern Cameroons scored a victory in a legal battle against the Republic of Cameroon when the African Commission for Human and Peoples' Rights found that there were unresolved issues with the constitutional structure of the Republic of Cameroon vis-a-vis Southern Cameroons. More importantly, the African Commission found that contrary to the claims of the Republic of Cameroon, the people of Southern Cameroons are indeed a "people" under the African Charter and broad international law with the inalienable right to determine their destiny&lt;ref&gt;[http://docs.google.com/fileview?id=0B0uuvXdgDlroNmExNDdlNzUtMmEyZi00NTllLTgxOGMtYjE4OTRiODRjNDFm&amp;hl=en Google docs]&lt;/ref&gt;.

===Southern Sudan===
[[Southern Sudan]] reached a [[Comprehensive Peace Agreement|peace agreement]] with [[Sudan]] in 2005.  It contains [[Southern Sudanese independence referendum, 2011|a referendum]] for self-determination in 2011.

===Tamil Eelam and Sri Lanka===
{{Main|Tamil Eelam}}
The [[Sri Lankan Tamils]] people seek self determination due to ethnic pogroms and discrimination by the majority Sinhala government’s discrimination in language, education, jobs, and civil liberties.&lt;ref&gt;Vijay Sappani. (February 06, 2009). The crisis in Sri Lanka: Canada's role. [[National Post]].&lt;/ref&gt;  The early non violent protests developed into a violent confrontation with the state and eventual civil war. Tamil independence advocates argue that former sovereignty of Tamils in their north eastern homeland that was lost during colonialism should be re-instated to meet Tamil aspirations.

===Taiwan===
{{Unreferenced section|date=December 2007}}
{{Main|Political Status of Taiwan}}
Taiwan is the focus of a self-determination dispute in the [[East Asia]] region. The government of the [[People's Republic of China]] claims the entirety of Taiwan as its territory. However, Taiwanese independence advocates argue that there is no legal claim to Taiwan, as no legally binding treaty ever transferred sovereignty to China following World War II, an assertion that both the [[People's Republic of China]] and the [[Republic of China]] disagree with. At the same time, the ''de facto'' government of Taiwan, the [[Republic of China]] still has not formally withdrawn its claims to the mainland and several other areas. In practice, however, this claim essentially died off through the 1990s and is no longer pressed by Taiwan's elected government.{{Citation needed|date=November 2007}}{{citation is really not needed as this is common knowledge}}

===Tibet===
{{Main|Tibetan independence movement}}
There is a strong movement, especially from the Tibetan [[diaspora]], for self-determination of the Tibet region.  The movement is strongly opposed by the People's Republic of China.&lt;ref&gt;[[http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/india/The-burden-of-being-Dalai-Lama/articleshow/5183939.cms]]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Turkish Cypriots===
{{Main|Turkish Republic of Northern Cyprus}}
Since Turkey's invasion and continued occupation of Cyprus in 1974, following ethnic clashes and turmoil on the island, an administration recognized by [[Turkey]] only was declared in 1983 - the [[Turkish Republic of Northern Cyprus]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/country_profiles/1021835.stm BBC Timeline: Cyprus, accessed 2-26-2008.]&lt;/ref&gt; It is questionable whether it was the [[Turkish Cypriot]] community who claimed the right of self-determination in ending their partnership with the [[Republic of Cyprus]], given that they were greatly out-numbered by the Turkish settlers who were brought to the area by Turkey.&lt;ref&gt;[http://72.14.235.104/search?q=cache:Q0cRQ4qiyroJ:www.euractiv.com/en/enlargement/integrating-north-cyprus-eu/article-152509+self+determination+press+release+noth+cyprus&amp;hl=en&amp;ct=clnk&amp;cd=3 EurActiv.com:Integrating North Cyprus into the EU, accessed 2-26-2008]&lt;/ref&gt;

===United States===
The colonization of the North American continent and its [[Native Americans in the United States|Native American]] population has been the source of legal battles since the early 1800s. Surviving Native Americans have been resettled onto separate tracts of land ([[Indian reservation|reservations]]), which have been given a certain degree of [[autonomy]] within the United States federal government.

The [[Chicano Movement]] (or [[Chicano nationalism|Chicano nation]]) seeks to recreate [[Aztlán]], the legendary homeland of the [[Aztec]]s comprising the [[Southwestern United States]] which is home to the majority of [[Mexican Americans]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aztlan.net/homeland.htm Professor Predicts 'Hispanic Homeland'], Associated Press, 2000&lt;/ref&gt;

There is an active [[Hawaiian sovereignty movement]] which aims at reversing the overthrow of the Hawaiian monarchy in the late 19th century, which resulted in the incorporation of [[Hawai'i]] into the United States. 

Since 1972, the U.N. Decolonization Committee has called for [[Puerto Rico]]'s decolonization and for the U.S. to recognize the island's right to self-determination and independence. In 2007 the Decolonization Subcommittee called for the [[United Nations General Assembly]] to review the political status of Puerto Rico, a power reserved by the 1953 Resolution.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.un.org/News/Press/docs/2007/gacol3160.doc.htm Special Committee on Decolonization Calls on United States to Expedite Puerto Rico’s Self-determination Process - General Assembly GA/COL/3160 - Department of Public Information - [[June 14]], 2007]&lt;/ref&gt; This follows the 1967 passage of a [[plebiscite]] act that provided for a vote on the status of Puerto Rico with three status options: continued commonwealth, statehood, and independence. In the first plebscite the commonwealth option won with 60.4% of the votes but U.S. congressional committees failed to enact legislation to address the status issue. In subsequent plebiscites in 1993 and 1998, the status quo was upheld.&lt;ref&gt;For complete statistics of these plebiscites, see [http://electionspuertorico.org/cgi-bin/events.cgi Elections in Puerto Rico:Results].&lt;/ref&gt;

Many current U.S. [[Secession in the United States|state, regional and city secession groups]] use the language of self-determination. A 2008 [[Zogby International]] poll revealed that 22% of Americans believe that "any state or region has the right to peaceably secede and become an independent republic."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.zogby.com/news/ReadNews.dbm?ID=1531 Middlebury Institute/Zogby Poll: One in Five Americans Believe States Have the Right to Secede], [http://zogby.com Zogby International], July 23, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Alex  Mayer, [http://www.stltoday.com/blogzone/the-platform/editorial-writers-notebooks/2008/07/secession-still-a-popular-idea/ Secession: still a popular idea?], [[St. Louis Post-Dispatch]], July 25, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Ethnic nationalism]]
* [[Religious nationalism]]
* [[Identity politics]]
* [[Individualist anarchism]]
* [http://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Informationelle_Selbstbestimmung Informational self determination (German)]
* [[International relations theory]]
* [[National delimitation in the Soviet Union]]
* [[Nationalism]]
* [[Nation-state]]
* [[Non-Intervention]]
* [[Puerto Rican Independence Movement]]
* [[Right to exist]]
* [[Secession]]
* [[Self-ownership]]
* [[Sovereignty]]
* [[Special Committee on Decolonization]]
* [[Wars of national liberation]]
* [[Anglo-French Declaration|Anglo-French Declaration of November 7, 1918]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Books==
* Danspeckgruber, Wolfgang F., ed. ''The Self-Determination of Peoples: Community, Nation, and State in an Interdependent World'', Boulder: [[Lynne Rienner Publishers]], 2002.
* Danspeckgruber, Wolfgang F., and Arthur Watts, eds. ''Self-Determination and Self-Administration: A Sourcebook'', Boulder: [[Lynne Rienner Publishers]], 1997.
* Allen Buchanan, ''Justice, Legitimacy, and Self-Determination: Moral Foundations for International Law (Oxford Political Theory)'', [[Oxford University Press]], USA, 2007.
* Annalisa Zinn, ''Globalization and Self-Determination (Kindle Edition)'', [[Taylor &amp; Francis]], 2007.
* Marc Weller, ''Autonomy, Self Governance and Conflict Resolution (Kindle Edition)'', [[Taylor &amp; Francis]], 2007.
* Valpy Fitzgerald, Frances Stewart, Rajesh Venugopal (Editors), ''Globalization, Violent Conflict and Self-Determination,'' Palgrave Macmillan, 2006.
* Joanne Barker (Editor), ''Sovereignty Matters: Locations of Contestation and Possibility in Indigenous Struggles for Self-Determination'', [[University of Nebraska Press]], 2005.
* David Raic, ''Statehood and the Law of Self-Determination (Developments in International Law, V. 43) (Developments in International Law, V. 43)'', [[Springer Science+Business Media|Springer]], 2002.
* Y.N. Kly and D. Kly, ''In pursuit of The Right to Self-determination'', Collected Papers &amp; Proceedings of the First International Conference on the Right to Self-Determination &amp; the United Nations, Geneva 2000, G E N E V A 2000, preface by Richard Falk, Clarity Press, 2001.
* Antonio Cassese, ''Self-Determination of Peoples: A Legal Reappraisal (Hersch Lauterpacht Memorial Lectures)'', [[Cambridge University Press]], 1999.
* Percy Lehning, ''Theories of Secession,'' Routledge, 1998.
* Hurst Hannum, ''Autonomy, Sovereignty, and Self-Determination: The Accommodation of Conflicting Rights'', [[University of Pennsylvania Press]], 1996.

==External links==
* [http://www.selfdetermination.net/ The Liechtenstein Institute on Self-Determination, Princeton University]
*[http://www.un.org/documents/ga/res/15/ares15.htm United Nations General Assembly Resolution 1514(XV). "Declaration on the Granting of Independence to Colonial Countries and Peoples"] 
*[http://www.un.org/aboutun/charter/ United Nations Charter].
*[http://www.unhchr.ch/html/menu3/b/a_ccpr.htm Text of International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights].
*[http://www.unhchr.ch/html/menu3/b/a_cescr.htm Text of International Covenant on Economic, Social and Cultural Rights].
*[http://selfdetermine.irc-online.org/index.html Self Determination in Focus], [[Foreign Policy In Focus]] self-determination papers site.
*Andrei Kreptul, [http://mises.org/journals/jls/17_4/17_4_3.pdf The Constitutional Right of Secession in Political Theory and History], [[Journal of Libertarian Studies]], [[Ludwig von Mises Institute]], Volume 17, no. 4 (Fall 2003), pp.&amp;nbsp;39–100.
*Jacob T. Levy, [http://ssrn.com/abstract=1028374 Self-Determination, Non-Domination, and Federalism], published in Hypatia: A Journal of Feminist Philosophy.
*[http://www.marxists.org/archive/lenin/works/1914/self-det/index.htm The Right of Nations to Self-Determination] [[Lenin|V. I. Lenin]] February-May 1914.
*[http://www.mahapunjab.org/PNSD/ Parliamentarians for National Self-Determination] Unofficial page for London based Parliamentary lobby group.
*[http://www.tamilnation.org/selfdetermination/ Self Determination - International Law and Practise] collated and sequenced by Nadesan Satyendra.
*[http://www.cwis.org/index.php The Center for World Indigenous Studies].

{{DEFAULTSORT:Self-Determination}}
[[Category:Political theories]]
[[Category:International relations]]
[[Category:International law]]
[[Category:Nationalism]]
[[Category:Secession]]
[[Category:Independence movements]]
[[Category:Human rights]]
[[Category:Collective rights]]
[[Category:Anarchist theory]]
[[Category:Communist terminology]]
[[Category:Maoism]]
[[Category:Autonomy]]

[[ar:حق تقرير المصير]]
[[ast:Drechu d'autodetermín]]
[[ca:Autodeterminació]]
[[cs:Právo národů na sebeurčení]]
[[de:Selbstbestimmungsrecht der Völker]]
[[es:Derecho de autodeterminación]]
[[eo:Rajto de memdetermino]]
[[eu:Autodeterminazio]]
[[fr:Autodétermination]]
[[ko:민족 자결]]
[[hr:Pravo na samoodređenje naroda]]
[[it:Autodeterminazione dei popoli]]
[[he:הגדרה עצמית]]
[[nl:Zelfbeschikkingsrecht]]
[[ja:民族自決]]
[[no:Nasjonal selvråderett]]
[[pl:Samostanowienie narodów]]
[[pt:Autodeterminação]]
[[ru:Право на самоопределение]]
[[scn:Autuditirminazzioni di li pòpuli]]
[[sk:Právo na samourčenie národov]]
[[sr:Самоопредељење]]
[[fi:Itsemääräämisoikeus]]
[[ta:தன்னாட்சி உரிமை]]
[[tr:Öz belirtim]]
[[zh-yue:民族自決]]
[[zh:民族自決]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>