<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20131117203602|582097525" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="29269" pageid="29269" ns="0" title="Self-determination"><revisions><rev timestamp="2013-11-17T20:52:48Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{about|self-determination in international law|other uses|Self-determination (disambiguation)}}
{{lead rewrite|date=October 2012}}
The right of nations to '''self-determination''' (from {{Lang-de|Selbstbestimmungsrecht der Völker}}), or in short form, the [[Rights|right]] to self-determination is the cardinal principle in modern [[international law]] ([[jus cogens]]), binding, as such, on the [[United Nations]] as authoritative interpretation of the Charter’s norms.&lt;ref&gt;''See'': [[s:United Nations General Assembly Resolution 1514|United Nations General Assembly Resolution 1514]] in [[Wikisource]] states&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Self-Determination of Peoples and Plural-Ethnic States in Contemporary International Law: Failed States, Nation-Building and the Alternative, Federal Option |last=McWhinney |first=Edward |authorlink=Edward McWhinney |year=2007 |publisher=Martinus Nijhoff Publishers |location= |isbn=9004158359 |page=8 |accessdate=September 18, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; It states that nations based on respect for the principle of equal rights and fair [[equal opportunity|equality of opportunity]] have the right to freely choose their [[sovereignty]] and international [[political status]] with no external compulsion or interference&lt;ref&gt;''See'': [[Charter of the United Nations|Chapter I - Purposes and Principles of Charter of the United Nations]]&lt;/ref&gt; which can be traced back to the [[Atlantic Charter]], signed on 14 August 1941, by [[Franklin D. Roosevelt]], President of the United States of America, and [[Winston Churchill]], Prime Minister of the United Kingdom who pledged The Eight Principal points of the Charter.&lt;ref&gt;''See'': Clause 3 of the [[Atlantic Charter]] reads: "Third, they respect the right of all peoples to choose the form of government under which they will live; and they wish to see sovereign rights and self government restored to those who have been forcibly deprived of them" then became one of the eight cardinal principal points of the Charter all people had a right to self-determination.&lt;/ref&gt; The principle does not state how the decision is to be made, or what the outcome should be, whether it be [[independence]], [[federation]], [[protectorate|protection]], some form of [[autonomy]] or even full [[Cultural assimilation|assimilation]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.un.org/Depts/dpi/decolonization/trust4.htm |title=United Nations Trust Territories that have achieved self-determination |publisher=Un.org |date=1960-12-14 |accessdate=2012-03-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; Neither does it state what the [[boundary delimitation|delimitation]] between nations should be — or even what [[Nation-building|constitutes a nation]]. In fact, there are conflicting definitions and legal criteria for determining which groups may legitimately claim the right to self-determination.&lt;ref name="Unterberger"&gt;[[Betty Miller Unterberger]], [http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_gx5215/is_2002/ai_n19132482 Self-Determination], Encyclopedia of American Foreign Policy, 2002.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 14 December 1960, the [[United Nations General Assembly]] adopted [[United Nations General Assembly Resolution 1514 (XV)]] under titled [[Declaration on the Granting of Independence to Colonial Countries and Peoples]] provided for the granting of [[independence]] to [[Colonialism|colonial]] countries and peoples in providing an inevitable legal linkage between self-determination and its goal of decolonisation, and a postulated new international law-based right of [[Liberty|freedom]] also in economic self-determination. In Article 5 states: Immediate steps shall be taken in [[United Nations list of Non-Self-Governing Territories|Trust and Non-Self-Governing Territories]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.un.org/en/decolonization/nonselfgov.shtml Trust and Non-Self-Governing Territories listed by the United Nations General Assembly]&lt;/ref&gt; or all other territories which have not yet attained independence, to transfer all powers to the peoples of those territories, without any conditions or reservations, in accordance with their freely expressed will and desire, without any distinction as to race, creed or colour, in order to enable them to enjoy complete independence and freedom, moreover on 15 December 1960 the United Nations General Assembly adopted [[United Nations General Assembly Resolution 1541 (XV)]] under titled Principles which should guide members in determining whether or nor an obligation exists to transmit the information called for under [[Chapter XI of the United Nations Charter|Article 73e]] of the [[United Nations Charter]] in Article 3 provided that [i]nadequacy of political, economic, social or educational preparedness should never serve as a pretext for delaying independence. To monitor the implementation of [[United Nations General Assembly Resolution 1514 (XV)|Resolution 1514]] in 1961 the General Assembly created the Special Committee referred to popularly as the [[Special Committee on Decolonization]]&lt;ref&gt;''See'' : [[United Nations General Assembly Resolution 1654 (XVI)]]&lt;/ref&gt; to ensure [[decolonization]] complete compliance with the principle of self-determination in General Assembly Resolution 1541 (XV), 12 Principle of the Annex defining free association with an independent State, integration into an independent State, or independence as the three legitimate options of full [[self-government]]&lt;ref&gt;''See'': [http://unyearbook.un.org/1960YUN/1960_P1_SEC3_CH4.pdf General Assembly 15th Session - resolution 1541 (XV)] (pages:509-510)&lt;/ref&gt; compliance with the principle of self-determination.&lt;ref&gt;''See'':{{sourcetext|source=United Nations General Assembly Resolution 1514}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''See'':[http://unyearbook.un.org/1960YUN/1960_P1_SEC3_CH4.pdf United Nations General Assembly 15th Session - The Trusteeship System and Non-Self-Governing Territories (pages:509-510)]&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|"National aspirations must be respected; people may now be dominated and governed only by their own consent. ''Self determination'' is not a mere phrase; it is an imperative principle of action. . . . "|[[Woodrow Wilson]] with his famous ''self-determination'' speech on 11 February 1918 after he announced his [[Fourteen Points]] on 8 January 1918.}}

By extension the term self-determination has come to mean the [[Self-determination (philosophy)|free choice of one's own acts]] without external compulsion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/self-determination |title=Merriam-Webster online dictionary |publisher=Merriam-webster.com |date= |accessdate=2012-03-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.answers.com/topic/self-determination Answers.com definition].&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
{{Refimprove| section may contain original research or biased language and|date=March 2010}}

===Pre-20th century===

====Origins====
Just as [[colonisation]] and [[colonialism]] have been practiced throughout recorded history, political self-determination, on an individual level, has been documented similarly and cherished highly by collective peoples despite them; ancient [[Mesopotamia]] and the later [[Polis|Greek city-states]] are early examples of its practice.&lt;ref name="Unterberger"/&gt;  The employment of [[imperialism]], through the expansion of empires, and the concept of political sovereignty, as developed after the [[Treaty of Westphalia]], also explain the emergence of self-determination during the modern era.  During, and after, the [[Industrial Revolution]] many groups of people recognized their shared history, geography, language, and customs.  [[Nationalism]] emerged as a uniting ideology not only between competing powers, but also for groups that felt subordinated or disenfranchised inside larger states, in this situation self-determination can be seen as a reaction to imperialism.  Such groups often pursued independence and sovereignty over territory, but sometimes a different sense of autonomy has been pursued or achieved.

====Empires====
The world possessed several traditional, continental empires such as the [[Ottoman Empire|Ottoman]], [[Russian Empire|Russian]], [[Austrian Empire|Austrian/Habsburg]], and the [[Qing Empire]].  Political scientists often define competition in Europe during the [[Modern Era]] as a [[Balance of power in international relations|balance of power]] struggle, which also induced various European states to pursue colonial empires, beginning with the [[Spanish Empire|Spanish]] and [[Portuguese Empire|Portuguese]], and later including the [[British Empire|British]], [[French colonial empire|French]], [[Dutch Empire|Dutch]], and [[German colonial empire|German]].
During the early 19th century, competition in Europe produced multiple wars, most notably the [[Napoleonic Wars]].  After this conflict, the British Empire became dominant and entered its [[Britain's Imperial Century|"imperial century"]], while nationalism became a powerful political ideology in Europe.

Later, after the [[Franco-Prussian War]] in 1870, "[[New Imperialism]]" was unleashed with [[Second French colonial empire|France]] and later [[German colonial empire|Germany]] establishing colonies in Asia, the Pacific, and Africa.  Japan also emerged as a new power.  Multiple theaters of competition developed across the world:
* Africa:  multiple European states competed for colonies in the "[[Scramble for Africa]]";
* Central Asia:  [[Russian Empire|Russia]] and [[British Empire|Britain]] competed for domination in the "[[Great Game]]"
* Eastern Asia:  colonies and various [[spheres of influence]] were established, largely to the detriment of the [[Qing Empire]].

The Ottoman Empire, Austrian Empire, Russian Empire, Qing Empire and the new [[Empire of Japan]] maintained themselves, often expanding or contracting at the expense of another empire.  All ignored notions of self-determination for those governed.&lt;ref&gt;Jackson J. Spielvogel, ''Western Civilization: Since 1500 '', [http://books.google.com/books?id=fwxLkRmd-4QC&amp;pg=PT421&amp;dq=%22new+imperialism%22+france+germany+ottoman+russia+japan&amp;ei=W7AGS-i7BKe8zgSKuaGqDw#v=onepage&amp;q=%22new%20imperialism%22%20france%20germany%20ottoman%20russia%20japan&amp;f=false p. 767], Cengage Learning, 2008, ISBN 0-495-50287-1, ISBN 978-0-495-50287-6.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Rebellions and emergence of nationalism====
{{Nationalism sidebar |Core}}
The revolt of [[New World]] British colonists in North America, during the mid-1770s, has been seen as the first assertion of the right of national and democratic self-determination, because of the explicit invocation of natural law, the natural rights of man, as well as the consent of, and sovereignty by, the people governed; these ideas were inspired particularly by [[John Locke]]'s [[Age of Enlightenment|enlightened]] writings of the previous century. [[Thomas Jefferson]] further promoted the notion that the will of the people was supreme, especially through authorship of the [[United States Declaration of Independence]] which inspired Europeans throughout the 19th century.&lt;ref name="Unterberger"/&gt; The French Revolution was motivated similarly and legitimatized the ideas of self-determination on that [[Old World]] continent.&lt;ref&gt;Chimène Keitner, [[Oxford University]], [http://www.ciaonet.org/isa/woc01/National Self-Determination: The Legacy of the French Revolution], paper presented at International Studies Association Annual Meeting, March 2000.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F60B16FD3D5C147A93C2AB178CD85F4D8185F9 "Self-Determination Not a New Expedient; First Plebiscite Was Held in Avignon During the French Revolution—Forthcoming Book Traces History and Growth of the Movement"], ''[[New York Times]]'', July 20, 1919, 69.&lt;/ref&gt;

Within the New World during the early 19th century, most of the nations of [[Hispanic America|Spanish America]] achieved [[Spanish American wars of independence|independence from Spain]]. The United States supported that status, as policy in the hemisphere relative to European colonialism, with the [[Monroe Doctrine]]. The American public, organized associated groups, and even Congressional resolutions, often supported such movements, particularly the [[Greek War of Independence]] (1821–29) and the [[12 points of the Hungarian Revolutionaries of 1848|demands of Hungarian revolutionaries in 1848]]. Such support, however, never became official government policy, due to balancing of other [[national interests]]. After the [[American Civil War]] and with increasing capability, the United States government did not accept self-determination as a basis during its [[Purchase of Alaska]] and attempted purchase of the West Indian islands of [[Saint Thomas, U.S. Virgin Islands|Saint Thomas]] and [[St. John, U.S. Virgin Islands|Saint John]] in 1860s, or its growing influence in the [[Hawaii|Hawaiian Islands]], that led to annexation in 1898. With its victory in the [[Spanish-American War]] in 1899 and its growing stature in the world, the United States supported annexation of the former Spanish colonies of [[Guam]], [[Puerto Rico]] and the Philippines, without the consent of their peoples, and it retained "quasi-[[suzerainty]]" over Cuba, as well.&lt;ref name="Unterberger"/&gt;

Nationalist sentiments emerged inside the traditional empires including: [[Pan-Slavism]] in Russia; [[Ottomanism]], [[Kemalist ideology]] and [[Arab nationalism]] in the Ottoman Empire; [[State Shintoism]] and [[Japanese nationalism|Japanese identity]] in Japan; and [[Chinese nationalism|Han identity]] in juxtaposition to the [[Manchu people|Manchurian ruling class]] in China. Meanwhile in Europe itself there was a [[Rise of nationalism in Europe|rise of nationalism]], with nations such as [[Greek War of Independence|Greece]], [[Hungarian Revolution of 1848|Hungary]], [[Greater Poland Uprising (1848)|Poland]] and [[Bulgarian unification|Bulgaria]] seeking or winning their independence.

[[Karl Marx]] supported such nationalism, believing it might be a "prior condition" to social reform and international alliances.&lt;ref&gt;Erica Benner, ‘’Really existing nationalisms: a post-communist view from Marx and Engels’‘, [http://books.google.com/books?id=N-7Xc8WtCLgC&amp;pg=PA188&amp;dq=%22self-determination%22+of+colonies+marx&amp;ei=HLAGS6bRHafgyASj-_2_Dw#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false p. 188], Oxford University Press, 1995 ISBN 0-19-827959-0, ISBN 978-0-19-827959-4&lt;/ref&gt; In 1914 [[Vladimir Lenin]] wrote: "[It] would be wrong to interpret the right to self-determination as meaning anything but the right to existence as a separate state."&lt;ref name="Lenin"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.marxists.org/archive/lenin/works/1914/self-det/ch01.htm#v20pp72-395 |title=What Is Meant By The Self-Determination of Nations? |publisher=Marxists.org |date= |accessdate=2012-03-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===World Wars I and II===

====Europe, Asia and Africa====
[[File:Decolonization - World In 1945 en.svg|500px|thumb|Map of the world in 1945, showing [[United Nations Trusteeship Council]] territories in green&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.un.org/Depts/Cartographic/map/profile/world45.pdf |title=http://www.un.org/Depts/Cartographic/map/profile/world45.pdf |format=PDF |date= |accessdate=2012-03-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
[[Woodrow Wilson]] revived America's commitment to self-determination, at least for European states, during World War I. When the [[Bolsheviks]] came to power in Russia in November 1917, they called for Russia's immediate withdrawal as a member of the [[Allies of World War I]]. They also supported the right of all nations, including colonies, to self-determination."&lt;ref name="Lenin"/&gt; The 1918 [[1918 Soviet Constitution|Constitution of the Soviet Union]] acknowledged the right of [[secession]] for its constituent republics.&lt;ref name="Unterberger"/&gt;

This presented a challenge to Wilson's more limited demands. In January 1918 Wilson issued his [[Fourteen Points]] of January 1918 which, among other things, called for adjustment of colonial claims, as long as the interests of colonial powers had equal weight with the claims of subject peoples.&lt;ref name="Unterberger"/&gt; The [[Treaty of Brest-Litovsk]] in March 1918 led to Russia's exit from the war and the independence of Armenia, Finland, Estonia, Latvia, Ukraine, Lithuania, Georgia and [[Second Polish Republic|Poland]]. The end of the war led to the dissolution of the defeated [[Austro-Hungarian Empire]] and the creation by the Allies of [[Czechoslovakia]] and the union of the [[State of Slovenes, Croats and Serbs]] and the [[Kingdom of Serbia]] as new states. However, this imposition of states where some nationalities (especially Poles, Czechs, and Serbs and [[Romanians]]) were given power over nationalities who disliked and distrusted them eventually helped lead to World War II. The defeated [[Ottoman empire]] was dissolved into the [[Republic of Turkey]] and several smaller nations, including [[Yemen]], plus the new [[Middle East]] [[Allies of World War I|Allied]] "[[League of Nations mandate|mandates]]" of [[French Mandate for Syria and the Lebanon|Syria and Lebanon]] (future Syria, Lebanon and [[Hatay State]]), [[British Mandate of Palestine|Palestine]] (future [[Transjordan]] and Israel), [[British Mandate of Mesopotamia|Mesopotamia]] (future Iraq). The [[League of Nations]] was proposed as much as a means of consolidating these new states, as a path to peace.&lt;ref name="Rothbard"&gt;[[Murray N. Rothbard]], [http://www.lewrockwell.com/rothbard/rothbard134.html National Self-Determination], Rothbard Archives at [[Lewrockwell.com]], August 1990.&lt;/ref&gt;

During the 1920s and 1930s there were some successful movements for self-determination in the beginnings of the process of [[decolonization]]. In the [[Statute of Westminster 1931|Statute of Westminster]] the United Kingdom granted independence to Canada, New Zealand, [[Newfoundland and Labrador|Newfoundland]], the [[Irish Free State]], the Commonwealth of Australia, and the [[Union of South Africa]] after the [[British parliament]] declared itself as incapable of passing laws over them without their consent. Egypt, Afghanistan and Iraq also achieved independence from Britain and Lebanon from France. Other efforts were unsuccessful, like the [[Indian independence movement]]. And Italy, Japan and Germany all initiated new efforts to bring certain territories under their control, leading to World War II.

In Asia, Japan became a rising power and gained more respect from Western powers after its victory in the [[Russo-Japanese War]].  Japan joined the Allied Powers in World War I and [[Japan during World War I|attacked German colonial possessions]] in the Far East, adding former German possessions to its own empire.  In the 1930s, Japan gained significant influence in [[Inner Mongolia]] and [[Manchuria]] after it [[Mukden Incident|invaded Manchuria]].  It established [[Manchukuo]], a [[puppet state]] in Manchuria and eastern Inner Mongolia. This was essentially the model Japan followed as it invaded other areas in Asia and established the [[Greater East Asia Co-Prosperity Sphere]].

In 1912, the [[Republic of China]] officially [[successor state|succeeded]] the Qing Dynasty, while [[Outer Mongolia]], [[Tibet (1912–1951)|Tibet]] and [[Tannu Uriankhai|Tuva]] proclaimed their independence. Independence was not accepted by the government of China. By the [[Treaty of Kyakhta (1915)]] [[Outer Mongolia, 1911-1919|Outer Mongolia]] recognized China's sovereignty. However, the Soviet threat of seizing parts of Inner Mongolia induced China to recognize Outer Mongolia's independence, provided that a referendum was held. The referendum took place on October 20, 1945, with (according to official numbers) 100% of the electorate voting for independence.

Many of Eastern Asia's current disputes to sovereignty and self-determination stem from unresolved disputes from World War II.  After its fall, the [[Empire of Japan]] renounced control over many of its former possessions including Korea, [[Sakhalin Island]], and Taiwan].  In none of these areas were the opinions of affected people consulted, or given significant priority. Korea was specifically granted independence but the receiver of various other areas was not stated in the [[Treaty of San Francisco]], giving Taiwan ''de facto'' independence although its political status continues to be ambiguous.

===The Cold War world===

====The UN Charter====
In 1941 [[Allies of World War II]] signed the [[Atlantic Charter]] and accepted the principle of self-determination. In January 1942 twenty-six states signed the [[Declaration by United Nations]], which accepted those principles. The ratification of the United Nations Charter in 1945 at the end of World War II placed the right of self-determination into the framework of international law and diplomacy.
* Chapter 1, Article 1, part 2 states that purpose of the UN Charter is: "To develop friendly relations among nations based on respect for the principle of equal rights and self-determination of peoples, and to take other appropriate measures to strengthen universal peace."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.un.org/aboutun/charter/ |title=United Nations Charter |publisher=Un.org |date= |accessdate=2012-03-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Article 1 in both the [[International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights]] (ICCPR)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www2.ohchr.org/english/law/ccpr.htm |title=Text of International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights |publisher=.ohchr.org |date= |accessdate=2012-03-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[International Covenant on Economic, Social and Cultural Rights]] (ICESCR).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www2.ohchr.org/english/law/cescr.htm |title=Text of International Covenant on Economic, Social and Cultural Rights |publisher=.ohchr.org |date= |accessdate=2012-03-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; Both read: "All peoples have the right of self-determination. By virtue of that right they freely determine their political status and freely pursue their economic, social and cultural development."
* The United Nations [[Universal Declaration of Human Rights]] article 15 states that everyone has the right to a nationality and that no one should be arbitrarily deprived of a nationality or denied the right to change nationality.

However, the charter and other resolutions did not insist on full independence as the best way of obtaining [[self-government]], nor did they include an enforcement mechanism. Moreover, new states were recognized by the legal doctrine of [[uti possidetis juris]], meaning that old administrative boundaries would become international boundaries upon independence even if they had little relevance to linguistic, ethnic, and cultural boundaries.&lt;ref name="Hensel"&gt;Paul R. Hensel and Michael E. Allison, Department of Political Science  [[Florida State University]] and Ahmed Khanani, Department of Political Science, [[Indiana University]], [http://garnet.acns.fsu.edu/~phensel/Research/io05.pdf The Colonial Legacy and Border Stability: Uti Possidetis and Territorial Claims in the Americas], research paper at Paul Hensel's Florida State university web site.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Gudeleviciute"&gt;Vita Gudeleviciute, [http://www.ceeol.com/aspx/getdocument.aspx?logid=5&amp;id=3aa23ac1-66e8-4193-a3e1-a7286ee6bfd5 Does the Principle of Self-determination Prevail over the Principle of Territorial Integrity?], International Journal of Baltic Law, [[Vytautas Magnus University]] School of Law, Volume 2, No. 2 (April 2005).&lt;/ref&gt; Nevertheless, justified by the language of self-determination, between 1946 and 1960, the peoples of thirty-seven new nations freed themselves from colonial status in Asia, Africa, and the Middle East.&lt;ref name="Unterberger"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[:s:United Nations General Assembly Resolution 1514|Resolution 1514 (XV) "Declaration on the Granting of Independence to Colonial Countries and Peoples"]]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www2.ohchr.org/english/law/independence.htm Declaration on the Granting of Independence to Colonial Countries and Peoples], General Assembly resolution 1514 (XV) of 14 December 1960.&lt;/ref&gt;  The territoriality issue inevitably would lead to more conflicts and independence movements within many states and challenges to the assumption that [[territorial integrity]] is as important as self-determination.&lt;ref name="Hensel"/&gt;

====The communist versus capitalist worlds====
Decolonization in the world was contrasted by the Soviet Union's successful post-war expansionism. [[People's Republic of Tuva|Tuva]] and several regional states in [[Eastern Europe]], the Baltic, and Central Asia had been fully annexed by the Soviet Union during World War II.  Now, it extended its influence by establishing [[satellite states]] Eastern Germany and the countries of Eastern Europe, along with support for revolutionary movements in China and North Korea. Although satellite states were independent and possessed sovereignty, the Soviet Union often violated principles of self-determination by suppressing the [[Hungarian revolution of 1956]] and the [[Prague Spring]] Czechoslovak reforms of 1968. It [[Soviet war in Afghanistan|invaded Afghanistan]] to support an increasingly unpopular communist government assailed by local tribal groups.&lt;ref name="Unterberger"/&gt; However, [[Marxism-Leninism]] and its theory of imperialism were also strongs influences in the national emancipation movements of third world nations rebelling against colonial or puppet regimes. In many [[Third World]] countries, communism became an ideology that united groups to oppose imperialism or colonization.

Soviet actions were countered by the United States which saw communism as a menace to its interests. Throughout the cold war, the United States created, supported, and sponsored regimes with various success that served their economic and political interests, among them [[anti-communism]]. To achieve this, a variety of means was implemented, including the orchestration of coups, sponsoring of anti-communist countries and military interventions. Consequently, many self-determination movements, which spurned some type of anti-communist government, were accused of being Soviet-inspired or controlled.&lt;ref name="Unterberger"/&gt;

The [[Rhodesian Bush War]] of the 1960s and 1970s pitted the unrecognized, ardently anti-communist Rhodesian government, composed largely of the country's minority whites, against rival groups of black guerrillas, aligned respectively with Moscow and Beijing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
|title=Counter-Insurgency in Rhodesia
|last=Cilliers
|first=Jakkie
|location=London, Sydney &amp; Dover, New Hampshire
|publisher=Croom Helm
|year=1984
|month=December
|isbn=978-0-7099-3412-7
|pages=1–5}}, {{cite news
|title=Chimurenga war communiqué No. 8. Period from 30 Jan to 20 March 1974
|date=27 March 1974
|publisher=[[Zimbabwe African National Union]]
|location=Lusaka}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Chinese-backed [[Zimbabwe African National Union]] eventually took power [[Southern Rhodesian general election, 1980|in 1980]], when the internationally-recognised [[Zimbabwe|Republic of Zimbabwe]] was formed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://richardknight.homestead.com/files/zimletmarch80.htm |title=Letter by George M. Houser, Executive Director of the American Committee on Africa (ACOA), on the 1980 independence election in Rhodesia |author=George M. Houser |accessdate=2007-12-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Asia====
In Asia, the Soviet Union had already converted Mongolia into a satellite state but abandoned propping up the [[Second East Turkestan Republic]] and gave up its [[Soviet invasion of Manchuria (1945)|Manchurian claims]] to China. The new [[People's Republic of China]] had gained control of mainland China in the [[Chinese Civil War]]. The [[Korean War]] shifted the focus of the Cold War from Europe to Asia, where competing superpowers took advantage of [[decolonization]] to spread their influence.

In 1947, India gained independence from the [[British Empire]]. The empire was in decline but adapted to these circumstances by creating the British Commonwealth—since 1949 the [[Commonwealth of Nations]]—which is a free association of equal states.  As India obtained its independence, multiple ethnic conflicts emerged in relation to the formation of a statehood during the [[Partition of India]] which resulted in Islamic Pakistan and Secular India. Before the [[British Raj|advent of the British]], no empire based in mainland India had controlled any part of what now makes up the country's Northeast, part of the reason for the ongoing [[insurgency in Northeast India]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.apcss.org/Publications/Edited%20Volumes/ReligiousRadicalism/PagesfromReligiousRadicalismandSecurityinSouthAsiach10.pdf] p.220&lt;/ref&gt; In 1971 [[Bangladesh Liberation War|Bangladesh obtained independence]] from Pakistan.

Burma also gained independence from the British Empire, but declined membership in the Commonwealth. [[Internal conflict in Burma]] that challenge the ruling government persist.

Indonesia gained independence from the Netherlands in 1949 after the latter failed to restore colonial control.  As mentioned above, Indonesia also wanted a powerful position in the region that could be lessened by the creation of united [[Malaysia]]. The Netherlands retained [[Dutch New Guinea]], but Indonesia threatened to invade and annex it. A vote was supposedly taken under the UN sponsored [[Act of Free Choice]] to allow West New Guineans to decide their fate, although many dispute its veracity.  Later, Portugal relinquished control over [[East Timor]] in 1975, at which time Indonesia promptly invaded and annexed it.

====North Borneo and Sarawak====
Another controversial episode with perhaps more relevance was the British beginning their exit from [[British Malaya]]. An experience concerned the findings of a ''United Nations Assessment Team'' that led the British territories of [[North Borneo]] and [[Crown Colony of Sarawak|Sarawak]] in 1963 to determine whether or not the populations wished to become a part of the new Malaya Federation.&lt;ref name="am001"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://untreaty.un.org/unts/1_60000/21/36/00041791.pdf |title=United Nations Treaty Series Nr.10760: Agreement relating to Malaysia |accessdate=2010-07-29 |publisher=United Nations |work=United Nations Treaty Collection |format=PDF |year=1963 |month=July}}&lt;/ref&gt; The United Nation Team's mission followed on from an earlier assessment by the British-appointed [[Cobbold Commission]] which had arrived in the territories in 1962 and held hearings to determine public opinion. It also sifted through 1600 letters and memoranda submitted by individuals, organisations and political parties. Cobbold concluded that around two thirds of the population favoured joining Malaysia while the remaining third wanted either independence or continuing control by the United Kingdom. The United Nations team largely confirmed these findings, which were later accepted by the General Assembly, and both territories subsequently joined with the new formation of [[Malaysia]]. The conclusions of both the Cobbold Commission and the United Nations team were arrived at without any [[referendums]] self-determination being held.&lt;ref&gt;{{sourcetext|source=United Nations General Assembly Resolution 1514}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://unyearbook.un.org/1960YUN/1960_P1_SEC3_CH4.pdf |title=United Nations General Assembly 15th Session - The Trusteeship System and Non-Self-Governing Territories (pages:509-510) |format=PDF |date= |accessdate=2012-03-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://unyearbook.un.org/1963YUN/1963_P1_SEC1_CH3.pdf |title=United Nations General Assembly 18th Session - the Question of Malaysia (pages:41-44) |format=PDF |date= |accessdate=2012-03-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Singaporean national referendum, 1962|Unlike in Singapore]], however, no [[referendum]] was ever conducted in [[Crown Colony of Sarawak|Sarawak]] and [[North Borneo]] (now [[Sabah]] and [[Labuan]]).&lt;ref&gt;[[Jeffrey Kitingan]]: [http://www.freemalaysiatoday.com/category/nation/2013/03/08/there-was-no-sabah-referendum/ There was no Sabah referendum], published by [[Free Malaysia Today]], March 8, 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; they sought to consolidate several of the previous ruled entities then there was [[Manila Accord]], an agreement between the Philippines, [[Federation of Malaya]] and Indonesia on 31 July 1963&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://treaties.un.org/doc/Publication/UNTS/Volume%20550/volume-550-I-8029-English.pdf|title=United Nations Treaty Registered No. 8029, Manila Accord between Philippines, Federation of Malaya and Indonesia (31 JULY 1963)|publisher=Un.org |date= |accessdate=2012-05-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://treaties.un.org/doc/Publication/UNTS/Volume%20608/volume-608-I-8809-English.pdf|title=United Nations Treaty Series No. 8809, Agreement relating to the implementation of the Manila Accord|publisher=Un.org |date= |accessdate=2012-05-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; to abide by the wishes of the people of [[North Borneo]] (now [[Sabah]] and [[Labuan]]) and [[Crown Colony of Sarawak|Sarawak]] within the context of [[United Nations General Assembly Resolution 1541 (XV)]], Principle 9 of the Annex&lt;ref&gt;[http://unyearbook.un.org/1960YUN/1960_P1_SEC3_CH4.pdf General Assembly 15th Session – The Trusteeship System and Non-Self-Governing Territories (pages:509–510)]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://unyearbook.un.org/1963YUN/1963_P1_SEC1_CH3.pdf General Assembly 18th Session – the Question of Malaysia (pages:41–44)]&lt;/ref&gt; taking into account [[referendum]]s in North Borneo and Sarawak that would be free and without coercion.&lt;ref&gt;[http://treaties.un.org/doc/Publication/UNTS/Volume%20550/volume-550-I-8029-English.pdf United Nations Treaty Registered No. 8029, Manila Accord between Philippines, Federation of Malaya and Indonesia (31 JULY 1963)]&lt;/ref&gt; This also triggered the [[Indonesia–Malaysia confrontation]]  because Indonesia opposed the violation of the agreements.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.un.org/en/decolonization/nonselfgov.shtml |title=United Nations list of Trust and Non-Self-Governing Territories, North Borneo and Sarawak |publisher=Un.org |date= |accessdate=2012-03-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.un.org/News/Press/docs/2006/org1469.doc.htm |title=United Nations Member States |publisher=Un.org |date= |accessdate=2012-03-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===After the Cold War===
The Cold War began to wind down after [[Mikhail Gorbachev]] assumed power in March 1985. With the cooperation of the American president [[Ronald Reagan]], Gorbachev wound down the size of the [[Soviet Armed Forces]] and reduced nuclear arms in Europe, while liberalizing the [[economy of the Soviet Union|economy]].

In 1989–90, the communist regimes of Soviet satellite states collapsed in rapid succession in Poland, Hungary, Czechoslovakia, East Germany, Bulgaria, Romania, and Mongolia.  East and West Germany united, Czechoslovakia peacefully split into [[Czech Republic]] and [[Slovakia]], while in 1990 Yugoslavia began a [[Yugoslavia#Breakup|violent break up]] into its former 6 sub-unit republics. [[Kosovo]], which was previously an autonomous unit of Serbia declared independence in 2008, but has received less international recognition.&lt;ref name="Unterberger"/&gt;

In December 1991, Gorbachev resigned as president and the [[Soviet Union#Reforms of Gorbachev and dissolution|Soviet Union dissolved]] relatively peacefully into fifteen sovereign republics, all of which rejected communism and most of which adopted democratic reforms and free-market economies.  Inside those new republics, [[Commonwealth of Unrecognized States|four major areas]] have claimed their own independence, but not received widespread international recognition.

After decades of civil war, Indonesia finally recognized the independence of [[East Timor]] in 2002.

In 1949, the [[Communists]] won the civil war and established the [[People's Republic of China]] in Mainland China. The [[Kuomintang]]-led [[Republic of China]] government retreated to [[Taipei]], its jurisdiction now limited to [[Taiwan]] and several outlying islands. Since then, the People's Republic of China has been involved in disputes with the ROC over issues of sovereignty and the political status of Taiwan.

As noted, self-determination movements remain [[List of active autonomist and secessionist movements|strong in some areas of the world]].  Some areas possess ''de facto'' independence, such as Taiwan, [[North Cyprus]], [[Kosovo]], and [[South Ossetia]], but their independence is disputed by one or more major states. Significant movements for self-determination also persist for locations that lack ''de facto'' independence, such as [[Kurdistan]],[[ Balochistan ]],[[Chechnya]], and the [[State of Palestine]]

==Current issues==
Since the early 1990s, the legitimatization of the principle of national self-determination has led to an increase in the number of conflicts within states, as sub-groups seek greater self-determination and even full secession, and as their conflicts for leadership within groups and with other groups and with the dominant state become violent.&lt;ref&gt;Martin Griffiths, [http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/journals/MqLJ/2003/3.html Self-determination, International Society And World Order], [[Macquarie University]] Law Journal, 1, 2003.&lt;/ref&gt; The international reaction to these new movements has been uneven and often dictated more by politics than principle. The year 2000 United Nations Millennium Declaration failed to deal with these new demands, mentioning only "the right to self-determination of peoples which remain under colonial domination and foreign occupation."&lt;ref name="Gudeleviciute"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.un.org/millennium/declaration/ares552e.pdf |title=United Nations Millennium Declaration, adopted by the UN General Assembly Resolution 55/2 (08 09 2000), paragraph 4. |format=PDF |date= |accessdate=2012-03-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In an issue of ''[[Macquarie University]] Law Journal'' Associate Professor Aleksandar Pavkovic and Senior Lecturer Peter Radan outlined current legal and political issues in self-determination.&lt;ref name="Pavkovic"&gt;Aleksandar Pavkovic and Peter Radan,  [http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/journals/MqLJ/2003/1.html In Pursuit of Sovereignty and Self-determination: Peoples, States and Secession in the International Order], [http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/journals/MqLJ/2003/index.html Index of papers], [[Macquerie University]] Law Journal, 1, 2003.&lt;/ref&gt; These include:

===Defining "peoples"===
There is not yet a recognized legal definition of "peoples" in international law. Vita Gudeleviciute of [[Vytautas Magnus University]] Law School, reviewing international law and UN resolutions, finds in cases of non-self-governing peoples (colonized and/or indigenous) and foreign military occupation "a people" is the entire population of the occupied territorial unit, no matter their other differences. In cases where people lack representation by a state's government, the unrepresented become a separate people. Present international law does not recognize ethnic and other minorities as separate peoples, with the notable exception of cases in which such groups are systematically disenfranchised by the government of the state they live in.&lt;ref name="Gudeleviciute"/&gt; Other definitions offered are "peoples" being self-evident (from ethnicity, language, history, etc.), or defined by "ties of mutual affection or sentiment", i.e. "loyalty", or by mutual obligations among peoples. Or the definition may be simply that a people is a group of individuals who unanimously choose a separate state. If the "people" are unanimous in their desire for self-determination, it strengthens their claim. For example, the populations of federal units of the Yugoslav federation were considered a people in the breakup of Yugoslavia, even though some of those units had very diverse populations.&lt;ref name="Pavkovic"/&gt; Libertarians who argue for self-determination distinguish between the voluntary nation (the land, the culture, the terrain, the people) and the state, the coercive apparatus, which they have a right to choose or self-determine.&lt;ref name="Rothbard"/&gt;

===Self-determination versus territorial integrity===
National self-determination appears to challenge the principle of territorial integrity (or [[sovereignty]]) of states as it is the will of the people that makes a state legitimate. This implies a people should be free to choose their own state and its territorial boundaries. However, there are far more self-identified nations than there are existing states and there is no legal process to redraw state boundaries according to the will of these peoples.&lt;ref name="Pavkovic"/&gt; According to the Helsinki Final Act of 1975, the UN, ICJ and international law experts, there is no contradiction between the principles of self-determination and territorial integrity, with the latter taking precedence.
&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.un.int/azerbaijan/pdf/unrep1.pdf |title=Protracted conflicts in the GUAM area and their implications for international peace, security and development. The situation in the occupied territories of Azerbaijan, Security Council, Sixty-third year/ General Assembly, Sixty-third session, Agenda items 13 and 18, A/63/664–S/2008/823, 29 December 2008 |format=PDF |date= |accessdate=2012-03-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.law.fsu.edu/journals/transnational/vol101/vyver.pdf |title=Prof. Johan D. van der Vyver (Professor of International Law and Human Rights, Emory University School of Law), Self-Determination of the Peoples of Quebec Under International Law, Journal of TRANSNATIONAL LAW &amp; POLICY, Vol. 10:1, FALL 2000, USA |format=PDF |date= |accessdate=2012-03-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=CRIA |url=http://cria-online.org/1_2.html |title=M.Mammadov, Legal Aspects of the Nagorno-Garabagh Conflict, Caucasian Review of International Affairs, Vol. 1 (1) - Winter 2006, Germany, pp. 14-30 |publisher=Cria-online.org |date= |accessdate=2012-03-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ucss.ge/lecture%203%20-%20TI%20and%20NSD41.doc |title=S. Neil MacFarlane (Professor of International Relations and Fellow, St Anne's College, University of Oxford), Normative Conflict – Territorial Integrity and National Self-Determination, Centre for Social Sciences, December 14, 2010 |date= |accessdate=2012-03-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Pavkovic and Radan describe three theories of international relations relevant to self-determination.
* The realist theory of international relations insists that territorial sovereignty is more important than national self-determination. This policy was pursued by the major powers during the Cold War.
* Liberal internationalism has become an alternative since that time. It promotes the abolition of war among states as well as increased individual liberty within states, and holds the expansion of global markets and cross-border cooperation diminishes the significance of territorial integrity, allowing for somewhat greater recognition of greater self-determination of peoples.
* Cosmopolitan liberalism calls for political power to shift to a world government which would make secession and change of boundaries a relatively easy administrative matter. However, also would mean the de facto end of self-determination of national groups.&lt;ref name="Pavkovic"/&gt;

[[Allen Buchanan]], author of seven books on self-determination and secession, supports territorial integrity as a moral and legal aspect of constitutional democracy. However, he also advances a "Remedial Rights Only Theory"  where a group has "a general right to secede if and only if it has suffered certain injustices, for which secession is the appropriate remedy of last resort." He also would recognize secession if the state grants, or the constitution includes, a right to secede.&lt;ref name="Gudeleviciute"/&gt;

Vita Gudeleviciute holds that in cases of non-self-governing peoples and foreign military occupation the principle of self-determination trumps that of territorial integrity. In cases where people lack representation by a state's government, they also may be considered a separate people, but under current law cannot claim the right to self-determination. On the other hand, she finds that secession within a single state is a domestic matter not covered by international law. Thus there are no on what groups may constitute a seceding people.&lt;ref name="Gudeleviciute"/&gt;

A number of states have laid claim to territories, which they allege were removed from them as a result of colonialism.  This is justified by reference to Paragraph 6 of UN Resolution 1514(XV), which states that any attempt "aimed at partial or total disruption of the national unity and the territorial integrity of a country is incompatible with the purposes and principles of the Charter".  This, it is claimed, applies to situations where the territorial integrity of a state had been disrupted by colonisation, so that the people of a territory subject to a historic territorial claim are prevented from exercising a right to self-determination.  This interpretation is rejected by many states, who argue that Paragraph 2 of UN Resolution 1514(XV) states that "all peoples have the right to self-determination" and Paragraph 6 cannot be used to justify territorial claims.  The original purpose of Paragraph 6 was "to ensure that acts of self-determination occur within the established boundaries of colonies, rather than within sub-regions".  Further, the use of the word ''attempt'' in Paragraph 6 denotes future action and cannot be construed to justify territorial redress for past action.&lt;ref name="Musgrave2000"&gt;{{cite book|author=Thomas D. Musgrave|title=Self-Determination and National Minorities|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=BJg6T7SqJ1gC|accessdate=5 March 2012|year=2000|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=978-0-19-829898-4|page=239}}&lt;/ref&gt;  An attempt sponsored by Spain and Argentina to qualify the right to self-determination in cases where there was a territorial dispute was rejected by the UN General Assembly, which re-iterated the right to self-determination was a universal right.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.falklands.gov.fk/assembly/documents/The%20Challenge%20of%20Sovereignty%20in%20small%20states.pdf] Falkland Islands Government, Dick Sawle MLA, The Challenge of Sovereignty in small states ''As I mentioned previously, the UN itself, in 2008, rejected the claim that a dispute over sovereignty affected self-determination, affirming self-determination to be “a basic human right.”''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.un.org/News/Press/docs/2008/gaspd406.doc.htm | title=General Assembly GA/SPD/406 | publisher=UN Department of Public Information | date=20 October 2008 | accessdate=March 10, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Methods of increasing minority rights===
In order to accommodate demands for minority rights and avoid secession and the creation of a separate new state, many states [[decentralization|decentralize]] or [[devolution|devolve]] greater decision-making power to new or existing subunits or even [[autonomous area]]s. More limited measures might include restricting demands to the maintenance of national cultures or granting non-territorial autonomy in the form of national associations which would assume control over cultural matters. This would be available only to groups that abandoned secessionist demands and the territorial state would retain political and judicial control, but only if would remain with the territorially organized state.&lt;ref name="Pavkovic"/&gt;

===Self-determination versus majority rule/equal rights===
Pavković explores how national self-determination, in the form of creation of a new state through secession, could override the principles of [[majority rule]] and of [[Civil rights|equal rights]], which are primary liberal principles. This includes the question of how an unwanted state can be imposed upon a minority. He explores five contemporary theories of secession. In "anarcho-capitalist" theory only landowners have the right to secede. In communitarian theory, only those groups that desire direct or greater political participation have the right, including groups deprived of rights, per Allen Buchanan. In two nationalist theories, only national cultural groups have a right to secede. Australian professor Harry Beran's democratic theory endorses the equality of the right of secession to all types of groups. Unilateral secession against majority rule is justified if the group allows secession of any other group within its territory.&lt;ref&gt;Aleksandar Pavković, [http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/journals/MqLJ/2003/5.html Majority Rule and Equal Rights: a Few Questions], [[Macquarie University]] Law Journal, 1, 2003.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Harry Beran, "A Democratic Theory of Political Self-Determination for a New World Order" in Percy Lehning (ed), Theories of Secession (1998) 36, 39, 42–43.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Constitutional law===
Most [[sovereign state]]s do not recognize the right to self-determination through secession in their constitutions. Many expressly forbid it. However, there are several existing models of self-determination through greater autonomy and through secession.&lt;ref name="Kreptul"&gt;Andrei Kreptul, [http://mises.org/journals/jls/17_4/17_4_3.pdf The Constitutional Right of Secession in Political Theory and History], [[Journal of Libertarian Studies]], [[Ludwig von Mises Institute]], Volume 17, no. 4 (Fall 2003), pp. 39–100.&lt;/ref&gt;

In liberal constitutional democracies the principle of [[majority rule]] has dictated whether a minority can secede. In the United States [[Abraham Lincoln]] acknowledged that secession might be possible through [[List of amendments to the United States Constitution|amending]] the [[United States Constitution]]. The [[Supreme Court of the United States|Supreme Court]] in ''[[Texas v. White]]'', held secession could occur "through revolution, or through consent of the States."&lt;ref&gt;Aleksandar Pavković, Peter Radan, [http://books.google.com/books?id=-IjHbPvp1W0C Creating New States: Theory and Practice of Secession], p. 222, Ashgate Publishing, Ltd., 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.law.cornell.edu/supct/html/historics/USSC_CR_0074_0700_ZO.html ''Texas v. White''], 74 U.S. 700 (1868) at [[Cornell University Law School]] Supreme Court collection.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Parliament of the United Kingdom|British Parliament]] in 1933 held that [[Western Australia]] only could secede from Australia upon vote of a majority of the country as a whole; the previous two-thirds majority vote for secession via referendum in Western Australia was insufficient.&lt;ref name="Pavkovic"/&gt;

The [[Communist Party of China|Chinese Communist Party]] followed the Soviet Union in including the right of secession in its 1931 constitution in order to entice ethnic nationalities and Tibet into joining. However, the Party eliminated the right to secession in later years, and had anti-secession clause written into the Constitution before and after the founding the People's Republic of China. The 1947 Constitution of the [[Burma|Union of Burma]] contained an express state right to secede from the union under a number of procedural conditions. It was eliminated in the 1974 constitution of the Socialist Republic of the Union of Burma (officially the "Union of Myanmar"). Burma still allows "local autonomy under central leadership."&lt;ref name="Kreptul"/&gt;

As of 1996 the constitutions of Austria, Ethiopia, France, Singapore,{{citation needed|date=October 2009}} [[Federation of Saint Kitts and Nevis|Saint Kitts and Nevis Republics]] have express or implied rights to secession. Switzerland allows for the secession from current and the creation of new [[Cantons of Switzerland|cantons]]. In the case of proposed [[Quebec]] separation from Canada the [[Supreme Court of Canada]] in 1998 ruled that only both a clear majority of the province and a constitutional amendment confirmed by all participants in the Canadian federation could allow secession.&lt;ref name="Kreptul"/&gt;

The 2003 draft of the [[Treaty establishing a Constitution for Europe|European Union Constitution]] allowed for the voluntary withdrawal of member states from the union, although the State wanted to leave could not be involved in the vote deciding whether or not they can leave the Union.&lt;ref name="Kreptul"/&gt; There was much discussion about such self-determination by minorities&lt;ref&gt;Xenophon Contiades, [http://www.inter-disciplinary.net/AUD/s6.htm Sixth Scholarly Panel: Cultural Identity in the New Europe], 1st Global Conference on Federalism and the Union of European Democracies, March 2004.&lt;/ref&gt; before the final document underwent the unsuccessful ratification process in 2005.

===Drawing new borders===
In determining international borders between sovereign states, self-determination has yielded to a number of other principles.&lt;ref name="Anstis"&gt;Sebastian Anstis, [http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/09592296.2010.482477 The Normative Bases of the Global Territorial Order], [[Diplomacy &amp; Statecraft]], Volume 21, no. 2 (June 2010), pp. 306–323.&lt;/ref&gt; Once groups exercise self-determination through secession, the issue of the proposed borders may prove more controversial than the fact of secession. The bloody Yugoslav wars in the 1990s were related mostly to borders issues because the international community applied a version of [[uti possidetis juris]] in transforming existing internal borders of the various Yugoslav republics into international borders, despite the conflicts of ethnic groups within those boundaries. In the 1990s indigenous populations of the northern two-thirds of Quebec state opposed to being incorporated into a Quebec nation and even stated a determination to resist it by force.&lt;ref name="Pavkovic"/&gt;

The border between [[Northern Ireland]] and the [[Irish Free State]] was based on the borders of existing counties and did not include all of historic [[Ulster]].  A [[Irish Boundary Commission|Boundary Commission]] was established to consider re-drawing it. Its proposals, which amounted to a small net transfer to Northern Ireland, were leaked to the press and then not acted upon. In December 1925, the governments of the Irish Free State, Northern Ireland, and the United Kingdom agreed to accept the existing border. Most Irish Nationalists and Irish Republicans claim all of Northern Ireland and are not particularly interested in new borders.{{Citation needed|date=August 2008}}

==Individual cases of disputed self-determination==
For past movements see [[list of historical autonomist and secessionist movements]] and [[Decolonization#Charts of the independences|lists of decolonized nations]]. Also see [[list of autonomous areas by country]] and [[list of territorial autonomies]] and [[list of active autonomist and secessionist movements]].

===Australia===
{{Main|Self-determination of Australian Aborigines}}
Recently (2003 onwards), self-determination has become the topic of some debate in Australia in relation to Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander people. In the 1970s, the Indigenous community approached the Federal Government and requested the right to administer their own communities. This encompassed basic local government functions, ranging from land dealings and management of community centres to road maintenance and garbage collection, as well as setting education programmes and standards in their local schools.

===Basque Country===
{{Main|Basque nationalism}}
The Basque Country ({{lang-eu|Euskal Herria}}, {{lang-es|País Vasco}}, {{lang-fr|Pays Basque}}) as a [[cultural region]] (not to be confused with the homonym [[Autonomous Community]] of the [[Basque Country (autonomous community)|Basque country]]) is a European region in the western [[Pyrenees]] that spans the border between France and Spain, on the Atlantic coast. It comprises the autonomous communities of the Basque Country and [[Navarre]] in Spain and the [[Northern Basque Country]] in France.
Since the 19th century, [[Basque nationalism]] has demanded the right of some kind of self-determination.{{citation needed|date=January 2008}} This desire for independence is particularly stressed among [[left-wing politics|leftist]] Basque nationalists. The right of self-determination was asserted by the [[Basque Parliament]] in 1990, 2002 and 2006.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.eitb24.com/portal/eitb24/noticia/en/politics/pp-and-pse-voted-against-basque-parliament-adopts-resolution-on-s?itemId=B24_18787&amp;cl=%2Feitb24%2Fpolitica&amp;idioma=en |title=EITB: ''Basque parliament adopts resolution on self-determination'' |publisher=Eitb24.com |date= |accessdate=2012-03-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Since{{Citation needed|date=January 2008}} self-determination is not recognized in the [[Spanish Constitution of 1978]], some Basques abstained and some even voted against it in the referendum of December 6 of that year. However, it was approved by a clear majority at the Spanish level, and with 74.6% of the votes in the Basque Country.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www9.euskadi.net/q93TodoWar/q93Desplegar.jsp ]{{dead link|date=March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The derived autonomous regimes for the BAC was approved in later referendum but the autonomy of Navarre (''amejoramiento del fuero'': "improvement of the charter") was never subject to referendum but just approved by the Navarrese Cortes (parliament).&lt;!--There are not many sources on the issue for the French Basque country.--&gt;

''[[Euskadi Ta Askatasuna]]'' or ETA ({{lang-en|Basque Homeland and Freedom}}; pronounced {{IPA-eu|ˈeta|}}), is an armed [[Basque nationalist]], [[separatist]] and [[terrorist]] organization.&lt;!-- Do not add "terrorist" here, that is covered in the very next paragraph --&gt; &lt;!-- I've added "terrorist" here, because there is not a "very next paragraph" --&gt; Founded in 1959, it evolved from a group advocating traditional cultural ways to a [[paramilitary]] group with the goal of [[Basque independence]]. Its ideology is Marxist-Leninist.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.goizargi.com/2003/queeselmlnv4.htm"What is the MNLV (4)"&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.goizargi.com/2003/queeselmlnv3.htm |title=What is the MNLV (3) |language={{es icon}} |publisher=Goizargi.com |date=2002-01-27 |accessdate=2012-03-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Biafra===
{{main|Biafra}}

From 1999 to the present day, the indigenous people of Biafra have been agitating for independence to revive their country. They have registered a human rights organization known as Bilie Human Rights Initiative both in Nigeria and in the United Nations to advocate for their right to self-determination and achieve independence by the rule of law.&lt;ref name=BBCprofile&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-africa-13949550 | title=Nigeria profile | work=BBC Africa | date=May 1, 2012 | accessdate=May 19, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Canada===
{{main|Quebec sovereignty movement}}
In Canada, many in the province of Quebec have wanted the province to separate from [[Confederation]]. The [[Parti Québécois]] has asserted Quebec's "right to self-determination." There is debate on under which conditions would this right be realized.&lt;ref&gt;Guy Leblanc. [https://wsws.org/articles/2000/may2000/que-m06.shtml Canada: Parti Québécois convention meets as support for separation wanes]&lt;/ref&gt; [[French-speaking ]] Quebec nationalism and support for maintaining Québébois culture would inspire [[Quebec nationalism|Quebec nationalists]], many of whom were supporters of the [[Quebec sovereignty movement]] during the late-20th century.&lt;ref name="Clift1982"&gt;{{cite book|author=Dominique Clift|title=Quebec nationalism in crisis|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=ArsBP5Efqx4C&amp;pg=PA106|year=1982|publisher=McGill-Queen's Press - MQUP|isbn=978-0-7735-0383-0|pages=106–108}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Catalan Countries===
{{Main|Països Catalans|Catalan independentism}}

After the [[2012 Catalan march for independence]], in which more than 1.5 million citizens marched, the [[President of the Generalitat of Catalonia|President of Catalonia]], [[Artur Mas i Gavarró|Artur Mas]], called for new [[Catalonian parliamentary election, 2012|parliamentary elections on 25 November 2012]] to elect a new [[Parliament of Catalonia|parliament]] that would exercise the right of self-determination for Catalonia. The Parliament of Catalonia voted to hold a 'referendum or consultation' in the next four-year legislature in which the people of Catalonia would decide on becoming a new independent and sovereign state. The parliamentary decision was approved by a large majority of MPs: 84 voted for, 21 voted against, and 25 abstained.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Two thirds of the Catalan Parliament approve organising a self-determination citizen vote within the next 4 years|url=http://www.catalannewsagency.com/news/politics/two-thirds-catalan-parliament-approve-organising-self-determination-citizen-vote-withi|publisher=Catalan News Agency|date=28 September 2012|accessdate=29 September 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Chechnya===
Under [[Dzhokhar Dudayev]], Chechnya declared independence as the [[Chechen Republic of Ichkeria]], using self-determination, Russia's history of bad treatment of Chechens, and a history of independence before invasion by Russia as main motives. Russia has restored control over Chechnya, but the separatist government functions still in exile, though it has been split into two entities: the [[Akhmed Zakayev]]-run secular Chechen Republic (based in Poland, the UK and the USA), and the Islamic [[Caucasus Emirate]].

===Falkland Islands===
{{Main|Falkland Islands sovereignty dispute}}
Self-determination is referred to in the [[Falkland Islands Constitution]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2008/2846/contents/made |title=The Falkland Islands Constitution Order 2008 |publisher=Legislation.gov.uk |date=2011-07-04 |accessdate=2012-03-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; and is a factor in the [[Falkland Islands sovereignty dispute]]. The population has existed for over nine generations, continuously for over 175 years.&lt;ref name="Bulmer-Thomas1989"&gt;{{cite book|author=Victor Bulmer-Thomas|title=Britain and Latin America: A Changing Relationship|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=Kfk0AWSaHjoC&amp;pg=PA3|accessdate=11 September 2012|date=17 August 1989|publisher=Cambridge University Press|isbn=978-0-521-37205-3|pages=3–}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In a 1986 poll, 94.5% of the population voted to remain British.,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://en.mercopress.com/2012/09/08/falklands-1986-referendum-showed-94.5-favoured-british-sovereignty|title=Falklands’ 1986 referendum showed 94.5% favoured British sovereignty |publisher=En.mercopress.com |date= |accessdate=2012-08-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; a wish re-iterated in the [[Falkland Islands sovereignty referendum]]. As administering power, the British Government considers that, since the majority of inhabitants wish to remain British, transfer of sovereignty to Argentina would be counter to their right to self-determination.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://en.mercopress.com/2011/06/15/self-determination-and-self-sufficiency-falklands-message-to-the-world-on-liberation-day |title="Self determination and self sufficiency", Falklands message to the world on Liberation Day — MercoPress |publisher=En.mercopress.com |date= |accessdate=2012-03-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Argentina states the principle of self-determination is not applicable since the current inhabitants are not aboriginal and were brought to replace the Argentine population. Which was expelled by an 'act of force', forcing the Argentinian inhabitants to directly leave the occupied islands.  This refers to the [[Re-establishment of British rule on the Falkland Islands|re-establishment of British rule]] in the year 1833&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cancilleria.gov.ar/portal/seree/malvinas/homeing.html] Argentina’s Position on Different Aspects of the Question of the Malvinas Islands&lt;/ref&gt;

===Gibraltar===
{{Main|Disputed status of Gibraltar}}

The right to self-determination is referred to in the pre-amble of Chapter 1 of the [[Gibraltar Constitution Order 2006|Gibraltar constitution]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gibraltarlaws.gov.gi/constitution/Gibraltar_Constitution_Order_2006.pdf |title=The Gibraltar Constitution Order 2006 |publisher=Gibraltarlaws.gov.gi |date=2006-12-14 |accessdate=2013-07-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; and, since the United Kingdom also gave assurances that the right to self-determination of Gibraltarians would be respected in any transfer of sovereignty over the territority, is a factor in the dispute with Spain over the territory.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://law.uoregon.edu/org/oril/docs/9-1/Leathley.pdf |title=Gibraltar’s Quest for Self-Determination: A Critique of Gibraltar’s New Constitution |publisher=OREGON REVIEW OF INT’L LAW [Vol. 9, 2007] |year=2007 |accessdate=2013-07-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; The impact of the right to self-determination of Gibraltarians was seen in the [[Gibraltar sovereignty referendum, 2002|2002 Gibraltar sovereignty referendum]], where Gibraltarian voters overwhelmingly rejected a plan to share sovereignty over Gibraltar between the UK and Spain. However, the UK government differs with the Gibraltan government in that it considers Gibraltan self-determination to be limited by the [[Treaty of Utrecht]], which prevents Gibraltar achieving independence without the agreement of Spain, a position that the Gibraltan government does not accept.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gbc.gi/upload/pdf/NewGibraltarConstitution.pdf Despatch. Gibraltar Constitution Order 2006], section 5&lt;/ref&gt;

The Spanish government denies that Gibraltarians have the right to self-determination, considering them to be "an artificial population without any genuine autonomy"  and not "indigenous".&lt;ref name="Self-Determination of Peoples: A Legal Reappraisal"&gt;{{cite book|author=Antonio Cassese|title=Self-Determination of Peoples: A Legal Reappraisal|url=http://books.google.pl/books?id=IVDtjzY3r2gC&amp;pg=PA206&amp;lpg=PA206&amp;dq=Gibraltar+self-determination&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=Xhu_hxooDi&amp;sig=Hfzw3HE7pvecJ_N4Tjgn52zemvY&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=AaveUfa_IMzBswbZ-4HoDg&amp;ved=0CFIQ6AEwBQ#v=onepage&amp;q=Gibraltar%20self-determination&amp;f=false|year=1998|publisher=Cambridge University Press|isbn= 9780521637527|pages=209}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the [[Partido Andalucista]] has agreed to recognise the right to self-determination of Gibraltarians.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.chronicle.gi/headlines_details.php?id=30023 |title=Andalusian nationalists say ‘yes’ to Gibraltar’s self-determination |publisher=Gibraltar Chronicle  |date=11 July 2013 |accessdate=11 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Jammu and Kashmir===
{{Main|Kashmir conflict}}

[[United Nations Security Council Resolution 47]], adopted in 1948, called for a plebiscite to decide the fate of [[Kashmir]]. The [[All Parties Hurriyat Conference]] (APHC), an alliance of 26 organizations in Kashmir seeks self-determination according to the UN resolution.
Some groups have suggested that a third option of Independence be added to the resolutions two options of union with India or union with Pakistan.&lt;ref name="Right To Self-determination, A Key To Kashmir Solution"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.countercurrents.org/kashmir-safvi240207.htm|title=Right To Self-determination, A Key To Kashmir Solution|first=Syed Ali Safvi|date=24 February 2007|publisher=Countercurrents.org|accessdate=12 August 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Kashmiri-cc.ca on [http://www.kashmiri-cc.ca/un/sc21apr48.htm UN Resolution 47] and [http://www.kashmiri-cc.ca/un/ United Nation resolutions on Kashmir].&lt;/ref&gt;

===Kurdistan===

''Main articles'' [[Turkey-PKK conflict|Turkey-PKK Conflict]], [[Kurdish-Iraqi conflict|Kurdish-Iraqi Conflict]], [[Kurdish separatism in Iran|Kurdish Separatism In Iran]] and [[2012 Syrian Kurdistan rebellion|2012 Syrian Kurdistan Rebellion]]

[[Kurdistan]] is a historical region primarily inhabited by the [[Kurdish people]] of the middle east. The territory is currently part of 4 states Turkey, Iraq, Syria and Iran. There are Kurdish self-determination movements in each of the 4 states. Iraqi Kurdistan has to date achieved the largest degree of self-determination through the formation of the [[Kurdistan Regional Government]], an entity recognised by the Iraqi Federal Constitution.

Although the right of the creation of a Kurdish state was recognized following World War I in the [[Treaty of Sèvres]], the treaty was then annulled by the [[Treaty of Lausanne]]. To date two separate Kurdish republics and one Kurdish Kingdom have declared sovereignty. The [[Republic of Ararat]] ([[Ağrı Province]], Turkey), the [[Republic of Mehabad]] ([[West Azerbaijan Province]], Iran) and the [[Kingdom of Kurdistan]] ([[Sulaymaniyah Province]], [[Iraqi Kurdistan]], Iraq), each of these fledgling states was crushed by military intervention. The [[Patriotic Union of Kurdistan]] which currently holds the [[President of Iraq|Iraqi presidency]] and the [[Kurdistan Democratic Party]] which governs the [[Kurdistan Regional Government]] both explicitly commit themselves to the development of Kurdish self-determination, but opinions vary as to the question of self-determination sought within the current borders and countries.

===South Africa===
{{Main|Volkstaat}}

Section 235 of the [[South African Constitution]] allows for the right to self-determination of a community, within the framework of "the right of the South African people as a whole to self-determination", and pursuant to national legislation.&lt;ref name=section235&gt;{{cite web | title=Section 235 | url=http://www.info.gov.za/documents/constitution/1996/96cons14.htm#235 | work=South African Constitution | publisher= | year=1996 | accessdate=2009-05-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; This section of the constitution was one of the negotiated settlements during the handing over of political power in 1994. Supporters of an independent white homeland have argued that their goals are legitimate under this legislation.&lt;ref name=section235&gt;{{cite web | title=Minister Valli Moosa views volkstaat as legitimate ideal | url=http://152.111.1.88/argief/berigte/beeld/1998/06/5/4/12.html | work=Minister Valli Moosa views volkstaat as legitimate ideal | publisher= | year=1996 | accessdate=2009-05-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Turkish Cypriots===
{{Main|Turkish Republic of Northern Cyprus}}
Since Turkey's invasion and continued occupation of Cyprus in 1974, following ethnic clashes and turmoil on the island, an administration recognized by Turkey only was declared in 1983 – the [[Turkish Republic of Northern Cyprus]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/country_profiles/1021835.stm |title=BBC Timeline: Cyprus, accessed 2-26-2008 |publisher=BBC News |date=2011-12-13 |accessdate=2012-03-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; Turkish Cypriots and their former leader, [[Fazıl Küçük]] said that Turkish Cypriots had the right of self-determination, as well as Greek Cypriots.&lt;ref&gt;Küçük, Fazıl. ''Mücadelemizin Görkemli Günleri'', p.10&lt;/ref&gt;

===United States===
The colonization of the North American continent and its [[Native Americans in the United States|Native American]] population has been the source of legal battles since the early 19th century. Surviving Native Americans have been resettled onto separate tracts of land ([[Indian reservation|reservations]]), which have been given a certain degree of [[autonomy]] within the United States federal government.  The federal government recognizes [[Tribal sovereignty in the United States|Tribal Sovereignty]] and has established a number of laws attempting to clarify the relationship between the federal, state, and tribal governments. The Constitution and later federal laws grant local sovereignty to tribal nations, but do not grant full sovereignty equivalent to that of foreign nations, hence the term "domestic dependent nations".

Certain [[Chicano nationalism|Chicano nationalist]] groups seek to "recreate" an ethnic-based state called [[Aztlán]], the legendary homeland of the [[Aztec]]s comprising the [[Southwestern United States]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aztlan.net/homeland.htm Professor Predicts 'Hispanic Homeland'], Associated Press, 2000&lt;/ref&gt;

There are multiple active Hawaiian autonomy or independence movements each with their own distinct modality of realizing some level of political control over single or several islands. The groups range from those seeking territorial units similar to Indian reservations under the United States with the least amount of independent control to the [[Hawaiian sovereignty movement]] which would have the most amount of control, The Hawaiian Sovereignty movement aims at reviving the Hawaiian nation under the Hawaiian constitution, which supposedly has [http://www2.hawaii.edu/~anu/pdf/Dissertation(Sai).pdf retained its sovereignty] while under control of the United States.

Since 1972, the U.N. Decolonization Committee has called for [[Puerto Rico]]'s decolonization and for the U.S. to recognize the island's right to self-determination and independence. In 2007 the Decolonization Subcommittee called for the United Nations General Assembly to review the political status of Puerto Rico, a power reserved by the 1953 Resolution.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.un.org/News/Press/docs/2007/gacol3160.doc.htm |title=Special Committee on Decolonization Calls on United States to Expedite Puerto Rico’s Self-determination Process – General Assembly GA/COL/3160 – Department of Public Information – June 14, 2007 |publisher=Un.org |date= |accessdate=2012-03-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; This follows the 1967 passage of a [[plebiscite]] act that provided for a vote on the status of Puerto Rico with three status options: continued commonwealth, statehood, and independence. In the first plebscite the commonwealth option won with 60.4% of the votes but U.S. congressional committees failed to enact legislation to address the status issue. In subsequent plebiscites in 1993 and 1998, the status quo was upheld.&lt;ref&gt;For complete statistics of these plebiscites, see [http://electionspuertorico.org/cgi-bin/events.cgi Elections in Puerto Rico:Results].&lt;/ref&gt;  In 2012, a majority Puerto Rican residents voted to change the territory's relationship with the United States, with the Statehood option apparently being the preferred option.  As of January 2013, Washington has not taken action to address the results of this plebiscite.

Many current U.S. [[Secession in the United States|state, regional and city secession groups]] use the language of self-determination. A 2008 [[Zogby International]] poll revealed that 22% of Americans believe that "any state or region has the right to peaceably secede and become an independent republic."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.zogby.com/news/ReadNews.dbm?ID=1531 Middlebury Institute/Zogby Poll: One in Five Americans Believe States Have the Right to Secede], [http://zogby.com Zogby International], July 23, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Alex Mayer, [http://www.stltoday.com/blogzone/the-platform/editorial-writers-notebooks/2008/07/secession-still-a-popular-idea/ Secession: still a popular idea?], [[St. Louis Post-Dispatch]], July 25, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{colbegin}}
* [[Anglo-French Declaration|Anglo-French Declaration of November 7, 1918]]
* [[Ethnic nationalism]]
* [[Identity politics]]
* [[Individualist anarchism]]
* [[:de:Informationelle Selbstbestimmung|Informational self-determination (German)]]
* [[International relations theory]]
* [[List of historical unrecognized countries]]
* [[List of national liberation movements recognized by intergovernmental organizations]]
* [[National delimitation in the Soviet Union]]
* [[Nation-state]]
* [[Non-Intervention]]
* [[Puerto Rican Independence Movement]]
* [[Religious nationalism]]
* [[Right to exist]]
* [[Self-ownership]]
* [[Special Committee on Decolonization]]
* [[Territorial integrity]]
* [[United Nations list of Non-Self-Governing Territories]]
* [[Wars of national liberation]]
{{colend}}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Books==
{{refbegin}}
* Danspeckgruber, Wolfgang F., ed. ''The Self-Determination of Peoples: Community, Nation, and State in an Interdependent World'', Boulder: [[Lynne Rienner Publishers]], 2002.
* Danspeckgruber, Wolfgang F., and Arthur Watts, eds. ''Self-Determination and Self-Administration: A Sourcebook'', Boulder: [[Lynne Rienner Publishers]], 1997.
* Allen Buchanan, ''Justice, Legitimacy, and Self-Determination: Moral Foundations for International Law (Oxford Political Theory)'', [[Oxford University Press]], USA, 2007.
* Annalisa Zinn, ''Globalization and Self-Determination (Kindle Edition)'', [[Taylor &amp; Francis]], 2007.
* Marc Weller, ''Autonomy, Self Governance and Conflict Resolution (Kindle Edition)'', [[Taylor &amp; Francis]], 2007.
* Valpy Fitzgerald, Frances Stewart, Rajesh Venugopal (Editors), ''Globalization, Violent Conflict and Self-Determination'', Palgrave Macmillan, 2006.
* Joanne Barker (Editor), ''Sovereignty Matters: Locations of Contestation and Possibility in Indigenous Struggles for Self-Determination'', [[University of Nebraska Press]], 2005.
* David Raic, ''Statehood and the Law of Self-Determination (Developments in International Law, V. 43) (Developments in International Law, V. 43)'', [[Springer Science+Business Media|Springer]], 2002.
* Y.N. Kly and D. Kly, ''In pursuit of The Right to Self-determination'', Collected Papers &amp; Proceedings of the First International Conference on the Right to Self-Determination &amp; the United Nations, Geneva 2000, G E N E V A 2000, preface by Richard Falk, Clarity Press, 2001.
* Antonio Cassese, ''Self-Determination of Peoples: A Legal Reappraisal (Hersch Lauterpacht Memorial Lectures)'', [[Cambridge University Press]], 1999.
* Percy Lehning, ''Theories of Secession'', Routledge, 1998.
* Hurst Hannum, ''Autonomy, Sovereignty, and Self-Determination: The Accommodation of Conflicting Rights'', [[University of Pennsylvania Press]], 1996.
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{Commons category}}
* Thürer, Daniel, Burri, Thomas. [http://www.mpepil.com/sample_article?id=/epil/entries/law-9780199231690-e873&amp;recno=18&amp; Self-determination], ''Max Planck Encyclopedia of Public International Law''
* [http://www.selfdetermination.net/ The Liechtenstein Institute on Self-Determination, Princeton University]
* [http://undocs.org/A/Res/1514(XV) United Nations General Assembly Resolution 1514(XV). "Declaration on the Granting of Independence to Colonial Countries and Peoples"]
* [http://www.un.org/aboutun/charter/ United Nations Charter].
* [http://www.unhchr.ch/html/menu3/b/a_ccpr.htm Text of International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights].
* [http://www.unhchr.ch/html/menu3/b/a_cescr.htm Text of International Covenant on Economic, Social and Cultural Rights].
* [http://selfdetermine.irc-online.org/index.html Self Determination in Focus], [[Foreign Policy In Focus]] self-determination papers site.
* Andrei Kreptul, [http://mises.org/journals/jls/17_4/17_4_3.pdf The Constitutional Right of Secession in Political Theory and History], [[Journal of Libertarian Studies]], [[Ludwig von Mises Institute]], Volume 17, no. 4 (Fall 2003), pp.&amp;nbsp;39–100.
* [[Jacob T. Levy]], [http://ssrn.com/abstract=1028374 Self-Determination, Non-Domination, and Federalism], published in Hypatia: A Journal of Feminist Philosophy.
* [http://www.legalfrontiers.ca/2010/11/winds-of-change-or-hot-air-decolonization-and-the-salt-water-test/ "Winds of Change or Hot Air? Decolonization, Self-determination and the Salt Water Test,"] Legal Frontiers International Law Blog
* [http://www.marxists.org/archive/lenin/works/1914/self-det/index.htm The Right of Nations to Self-Determination] [[Vladimir Lenin]] February–May 1914.
* [http://www.mahapunjab.org/PNSD/ Parliamentarians for National Self-Determination] Unofficial page for London based Parliamentary lobby group.
* [http://www.tamilnation.org/selfdetermination/ Self Determination - International Law and Practise] collated and sequenced by Nadesan Satyendra.
* [http://www.cwis.org/index.php The Center for World Indigenous Studies].
* [http://www.iss.europa.eu/publications/detail/article/post-2011-scenarios-in-sudan-what-role-for-the-eu/ Post-2011 scenarios in Sudan: What role for the EU?], edited by Damien Helly, Report No.6, November 2009, [[European Union Institute for Security Studies]]
* [http://www.nationalyounglords.com/  self determination for Puerto Rico and all Latin American nations]

{{Indigenous rights footer}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Self-Determination}}
[[Category:Political theories]]
[[Category:International law]]
[[Category:Nationalism]]
[[Category:Secession]]
[[Category:Independence movements]]
[[Category:Collective rights]]
[[Category:Anarchist theory]]
[[Category:Communist terminology]]
[[Category:Maoism]]
[[Category:Autonomy]]
[[Category:Human rights by issue]]
[[Category:Sovereignty]]
[[Category:Decentralization]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>