<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20090926125722|316298192" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="11725949" pageid="11725949" ns="0" title="Feminization (sociology)"><revisions><rev timestamp="2009-10-13T19:06:00Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">The term '''feminization''' has been used to describe a shift in [[gender role]]s and [[sex role]]s in a society, group, or organisation towards a focus upon the [[feminine]]. This is the opposite of a cultural focus upon [[masculinity]].

Scholar Ann Douglas chronicled the rise of what she describes as sentimental "feminization" of American mass culture in the 19th century, in which writers of both sexes underscored popular convictions about women's weaknesses, desires, and proper place in the world. &lt;ref name="douglas"&gt;Ann Douglas (1977). ''The Feminization of American Culture''. Farrar, Straus and Giroux ISBN 0-374-52558-7&lt;/ref&gt; 

Such a figurative societal shift has also been remarked upon in more modern times. &lt;ref name="neutopia"&gt;Doctress Neutopia (1994). [http://feminism.eserver.org/feminization-of-cyberspace.txt The Feminization of Cyberspace.] Feminism and Women's Studies&lt;/ref&gt;  It can also mean the incorporation of women into a group or a profession that was once dominated only by men.

Potential examples of feminization in society can include: 
* The ''feminization of education'' - Majority female teachers, and a female majority of students in higher education.&lt;ref&gt;Carole Leathwood, Barbara Read, 'Gender and the Changing Face of Higher Education: A Feminized Future?', Open University Press, ISBN: 9780335227143, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;
* The ''feminization of television'' - Television network programming decisions.

==See also==
* [[Atypical gender role]]
* [[Emasculation]]
* [[Sociology of gender]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{socio-stub}}

[[Category:Gender studies]]
[[Category:Sociology of culture]]
[[Category:Cultural trends]]
[[Category:Sociological terms]]

[[ko:사회학적 여성화]]
[[nl:feminisering]]
[[pam:Peminisasyon]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>