<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20170628201654|787989116" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="11725949" pageid="11725949" ns="0" title="Feminization (sociology)"><revisions><rev timestamp="2017-08-09T05:35:10Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">In [[sociology]], '''feminization''' is the shift in [[gender role]]s and [[sex role]]s in a society, group, or organization towards a focus upon the [[feminine]]. This is the opposite of a cultural focus upon [[masculinity]].

Scholar Ann Douglas chronicled the rise of what she describes as sentimental "feminization" of [[Culture of the United States|American mass culture]] in the 19th century, in which writers of both sexes underscored popular convictions about women's weaknesses, desires, and proper place in the world.&lt;ref name="douglas"&gt;Ann Douglas (1977). ''The Feminization of American Culture''. Farrar, Straus and Giroux {{ISBN|0-374-52558-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;

It can also mean the incorporation of women into a group or a profession that was once dominated by men.{{Citation needed|date=April 2017}}

Potential examples of feminization in society can include:
* Feminization of education – Majority female teachers, a female majority of students in higher education and a curriculum which is better suited to the learning process of women.&lt;ref&gt;Carole Leathwood, Barbara Read, 'Gender and the Changing Face of Higher Education: A Feminized Future?', Open University Press, {{ISBN|978-0-335-22714-3}}, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;
* Feminisation of the workplace
* [[Feminization of migration]]

== Introduction of feminization ==
Defining the term "feminization" can be complicated due to its meaning being unstable, as it can be portrayed as either a social process or as a critique of a process. Feminization has two basic meanings. The first concerns a person who was not initially feminine but becomes feminine later in their life through the perceptions of both the individual and those around them. According to gender theorist [[Judith Butler]], a person's gender is not solely an act of will or self-description, as it is also shaped by the people who describe, categorize, and treat the person according to their own perceptions of their gender. The second meaning of the term feminization describes when a person who originally had feminine qualities begins to incorporate more feminine attributes into their personality in some way, shape, or form. 

The term has often been used to describe females, however over time it shifted to where the term can be used to describe the process of someone or something becoming more feminine by adopting feminine qualities.&lt;ref name="Myth"&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://eds.b.ebscohost.com/eds/detail/detail?vid=10&amp;sid=5e7f54a0-871f-4d64-8fe7-33669e98b355%40sessionmgr102&amp;hid=127&amp;bdata=JnNpdGU9ZWRzLWxpdmU%3d#AN=116834827&amp;db=edb|title=The Myth of Ameriican Jewish Feminization|last=|first=|date=|work=|page=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{full|date=April 2017}}

== Feminization of poverty ==
{{Main|Feminization of poverty}}
Women are more likely than men to live below the poverty line, a phenomenon known as the feminization of poverty. The 2015 poverty rates for men and women in the U.S. were 10% and 15% respectively. Women are less likely to pursue advanced degrees  and tend to have low paying jobs. It has been argued that even with the same level of education and occupational role, women earn much less than men,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.un.org/womenwatch/daw/followup/session/presskit/fs1.htm|title=Beijing +5 – Women 2000: Gender Equality, Development and Peace for the 21st Century Twenty-third special session of the General Assembly, 5-9 June 2000|website=www.un.org|access-date=2017-04-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; although other sources have disputed the idea of a wage gap in American society.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.washingtonexaminer.com/harvard-prof.-takes-down-gender-wage-gap-myth/article/2580405|title=Harvard prof. takes down gender wage gap myth|last=Schow|first=Ashe|website=The Washington Examiner|date=January 13, 2016|accessdate=May 9, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Feminization of the labor force ==
Feminization of the labor force in present day associations is inescapable in this day and age, in that females make up half of the labor force and the revelation of them as a potential profitable asset.In introductory set up, men were known to go to social crises like passing of a nearby relative, taking care of an ill parent, and this could mean being missing from the occupation for some days consequently this could mean less or no profitability and they too accommodated the family while women handled the household. Be that as it may, in spite of the outlook change in societal parts where work is no longer sex situated, men still could have more issues in the work put because of ladies characteristics which incorporate, less quantities of corruption or fraud, misappropriation of assets or slipping away of obligations furthermore, they are known for their adaptability, and meeting due dates.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.in/anisha-motwani/the-feminization-of-workp_b_8258716.html|title=Why The Feminisation Of The Workplace Is Good News For Everyone|work=Huffington Post India|access-date=2017-05-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

[[Category:Gender studies]]
[[Category:Sociology of culture]]
[[Category:Cultural trends]]
[[Category:Sociological terminology]]
[[Category:Femininity]]


{{gender-studies-stub}}</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>