<?xml version="1.0"?><api batchcomplete=""><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="11725949" pageid="11725949" ns="0" title="Feminization (sociology)"><revisions><rev timestamp="2014-04-02T16:12:01Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">In [[sociology]], '''feminization''' is the shift in [[gender role]]s and [[sex role]]s in a society, group, or organization towards a focus upon the [[feminine]]. This is the opposite of a cultural focus upon [[masculinity]].

Scholar Ann Douglas chronicled the rise of what she describes as sentimental "feminization" of American mass culture in the 19th century, in which writers of both sexes underscored popular convictions about women's weaknesses, desires, and proper place in the world.&lt;ref name="douglas"&gt;Ann Douglas (1977). ''The Feminization of American Culture''. Farrar, Straus and Giroux ISBN 0-374-52558-7&lt;/ref&gt; Strong male icons in American culture like [[Ward Cleaver]] and [[John Wayne]] have been replaced in recent years by strong female icons and weak male icons like [[Homer Simpson]].

It can also mean the incorporation of women into a group or a profession that was once dominated only by men.

Potential examples of feminization in society can include:
* The ''feminization of education'' – Majority female teachers, a female majority of students in higher education and a curriculum and pedology which is better suited to the learning process of women.&lt;ref&gt;Carole Leathwood, Barbara Read, 'Gender and the Changing Face of Higher Education: A Feminized Future?', Open University Press, ISBN 978-0-335-22714-3, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;
* The ''feminization of television'' – Television network programming decisions.
* The ''[[feminization of poverty]]'' – Less income for females than males in the labour market, and female single-headed households seem to face poverty more severely than other women.

==See also==
* [[Atypical gender role]]
* [[Emasculation]]
* [[Sociology of gender]]
* [[Kawaii|Cuteness in Japanese culture]]

'''Feminization:'''
* [[Feminisation of the workplace]]
* [[Feminization of migration]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Feminization (Sociology)}}
[[Category:Gender studies]]
[[Category:Sociology of culture]]
[[Category:Cultural trends]]
[[Category:Sociological terminology]]
[[Category:Femininity]]


{{gender-studies-stub}}</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>