<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20051030003404|26834836" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="14654024" pageid="14654024" ns="0" title="Elitism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-10-31T22:54:10Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Elitism''' is a belief or attitude that an [[elite]] &amp;mdash; a selected group of persons whose personal abilities, specialized training or other attributes place them at the top of any field (see below) &amp;mdash; are the people whose views on a matter are to be taken most seriously, or who are alone fit to govern.  Thus elitism sees an elite as occupying a special position of authority or [[privilege]] in a group, set apart from the majority of people who do not match up with their abilities or attributes. Thus this selected elite is treated with '''favouritism'''. Members of an ''inherited'' elite are [[aristocrat]]s.

For the converse of "elitism" see "[[anti-elitism]]" and "[[populism]]".

Attributes that identify an elite vary; personal achievement may not be essential. Attributes of elites include:

* High level of [[politics|political influence]] 
* Membership in powerful [[clique]]s and desirable clubs
* High level of [[Academic_degree|academic qualifications]]
* High level of [[experience]] in a given field ([[achieved status]])
* High [[Intelligence (trait)|intelligence]]
* High natural abilities such as [[Athletics|athletic]] abilities
* High [[creativity]]
* Good [[Taste#Taste_in_aesthetics|taste]], since "taste" is defined among the elite
* Claimed innate qualities, abilities, or other [[ascribed status]].

Commonly, large amount of personal [[wealth]], often assessed as the reward of elite qualities by those who are impressed by it, are insufficient on their own, as every [[nouveau riche]] can attest.

The term ''elitism'' is also used to refer to situations where a group of people who claim to possess high abilities or simple an [[in-group]] or [[cadre]] conspire to give themselves extra privileges at the expense of all other people. This form of elitism may be described as ''[[discrimination]]''.

Less commonly, ''elitism'' may also refer to situations where an elite is given both special privileges and special responsibilities, in the hope that this arrangement will benefit all people.

At times elitism is closely related to [[social class]] and stratification. People within a higher social class are usually known as the "social elite".

== Anti-elitism ==

: ''Main article: [[Anti-elitism]]''

The term "elitism" or the title "elitist" can be used resentfully by a person who is not a member of an elite, or is a member but resents their position or uses it in a condescending or cynical manner in order to ridicule or criticise practices which discriminate on the basis of ability or attributes. Often, accusing someone of being an "elit''ist''" is a [[pejorative]] remark meant to imply that the person in question does not in fact belong to an elite, but is merely a hanger-on. Elitism can be seen as encouraging the exclusion of large numbers of people from positions of privilege or power. Thus, many anti-elitists seek the social equality of [[Egalitarianism]], [[Populism]], [[Socialism]], or [[Communism]]. They may also support [[affirmative action]], [[social security]], [[luxury tax]], and increasingly high [[progressive tax]] for the wealthiest members of society. All of these measures seek to reduce the gap of power between the elites and non-elites.

== Elitism and education ==

: ''Main article: [[Academic elitism]]''

'''Elitism''' in the context of [[education]] is the practice of concentrating attention on or allocating funding to the [[student]]s who rank highest in a particular field of endeavour, the other students being deemed less worthy of attention.

Elitism in education could be based upon learning ability, knowledge, or other abilities.

== See also ==

* [[Aristocracy]]
* [[High culture]]
* [[Meritocracy]]
* [[Social class]]

[[Category:Social groups]]

[[fr:Élitisme]]
[[he:אליטיזם]]
[[nl:Elitarisme]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>