<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061108053520|86437533" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="14654024" pageid="14654024" ns="0" title="Elitism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-11-08T05:38:07Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Elitism''' is the belief or attitude that the people who are considered to be the [[elite]] &amp;mdash; a selected group of persons with outstanding personal abilities, [[wealth]], specialised training or experience, or other distinctive attributes &amp;mdash; are the people whose views on a matter are to be taken the most seriously, or that these are persons whose views should be regarded as carrying the most weight, or, more simply, these people are best fit to govern. Alternatively, the term '''elitism''' could be used to describe a situation in which power is in fact concentrated in the hands of an elite, whether rightly or not.

Elitism is often used [[pejorative|pejoratively]] to describe a general mindset of arrogance or disregard for the general non-elite public ([[Meritocracy]], a special kind of elitism, does not carry this connotation).

For the converse of "elitism" see "[[anti-elitism]]", "[[populism]]", and the [[political theory]] of [[Pluralism#Pluralism_in_politics|Pluralism]]. 

==Characteristics of the "elite"==
Attributes that identify an elite vary; personal achievement may not be essential. Elite attributes include:

* Commonly, large amounts of personal [[wealth]], often assessed as the reward of elite qualities by those who are impressed by it, are insufficient on their own, as every [[nouveau riche]] can attest.

* The term ''elitism'' is also used to refer to situations where a group of people who claim to possess high abilities or simply an [[in-group]] or [[cadre]] conspire to give themselves extra privileges at the expense of all other people. This form of elitism may be described as ''[[discrimination]]''.

* Less commonly, ''elitism'' may also refer to situations where an elite is given both special privileges and special responsibilities, in the hope that this arrangement will benefit all people.

* At times elitism is closely related to [[social class]] and what [[sociologist]]s call [[social stratification]]. People within a higher social class are usually known as the "social elite".

== Anti-elitism ==
{{main|Anti-elitism|Populism|Pluralism}}

===Elitism as a pejorative term===
The term "elitism" or the title "elitist" can be used resentfully by a person who is not a member of an elite, or is a member but resents the elite position or uses it in a condescending or [[cynicism|cynical]] manner in order to ridicule or criticize practices which discriminate on the basis of ability or attributes. Often, accusing someone of being an "elitist" is used as a  pejorative remark meant to imply that the person in question does not in fact belong to an elite, but is merely a hanger-on. 

===Elitism vs. Egalitarianism===
Elitism can be interpreted as encouraging the exclusion of large numbers of people from positions of privilege or power. Thus, many populists seek the social equality of [[Egalitarianism]], [[Populism]], [[Socialism]], or [[Communism]]. They may also support [[affirmative action]], [[social security]], [[luxury tax]]es, and increasingly high [[progressive tax]]es for the wealthiest members of society. All of these measures seek to reduce the gap of power between the elite and those who are not elite.

===Elitism vs. Pluralism===
[[Pluralism#Pluralism_in_politics|Pluralism]] is the belief that [[public policy]] decisions should be (or, descriptively, are) the result of the struggle of forces exerted by large populations (workers, consumers, retirees, parents, etc.) directly or indirectly in the policy-making process. This is contrasted with elitism which is the belief that decisions should be (or are) being made essentially according to the interests or ideas of elites.

== Elitism and education ==
{{main|Academic elitism}}

'''Elitism''' in the context of [[education]] is the practice of concentrating attention on or allocating funding to the [[student]]s who rank highest in a particular field of endeavour, the other students being deemed less worthy of attention.

Elitism in education could be based upon learning ability, knowledge, or other abilities.

== See also ==
* [[Aristocracy]]
* [[Classism]]
* [[Limousine liberal]]
* [[High culture]] and [[popular culture]]
* [[Meritocracy]]
* [[Champagne socialist]]
* [[Social class]]
* [[Tall poppy syndrome]]
* [[Oligarchy]] (political governance by "the few")
* [[Esotericism]]
* [[Thomas R. Dye]] (political scientist who has written widely on the subject of Elite theory)
* [[Pluralism#Pluralism_in_politics|Pluralism in politics]] (the polar opposite of Elitism)


[[Category:Social groups]]
[[Category:Political science theories]]
[[Category:Sociology]]

[[cs:Elitářství]]
[[de:Elitarismus]]
[[fr:Élitisme]]
[[he:אליטיזם]]
[[nl:Elitarisme]]
[[pl:Elitaryzm]]
[[ru:Элитизм]]
[[zh:精英主义]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>