<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20181112113011|868470382" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="14654024" pageid="14654024" ns="0" title="Elitism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2018-11-12T12:09:20Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{redirect|Elitist}}
{{refimprove|date=March 2011}}
{{Discrimination sidebar|expanded=Social}}

'''Elitism''' is the belief or attitude that individuals who form an [[elite]] — a select group of people with a certain [[ancestry]], intrinsic [[quality (philosophy)|quality]], high [[intellect]], [[wealth]], special skills, or experience — are more likely to be constructive to society as a whole, and therefore deserve influence or authority greater than that of others. In the United States, the term ''elitism'' often refers to the concentration of power in the [[Northeast megalopolis|Northeast Corridor]] and on the [[West Coast of the United States|West Coast]], where the typical American elite resides – journalists, lawyers, doctors, high-level civil servants, businesspeople, university lecturers, entrepreneurs, and financial advisors in the [[quaternary sector of the economy|quaternary sector]], often in established technological or political catchments of their [[higher education]] [[alma mater]].{{citation needed|date=May 2018}}

Alternatively, the term ''elitism'' may be used to describe a situation in which power is concentrated in the hands of a limited number of people. Oppositions of elitism include [[anti-elitism]], [[egalitarianism]], [[populism]] and [[political theory]] of [[Pluralism (political theory)|pluralism]].

[[Elite theory]] is the sociological or political science analysis of elite influence in society: elite theorists regard pluralism as a utopian ideal. Elitism is closely related to [[social class]] and what [[sociologist]]s call [[social stratification]], which in the [[Anglo Saxon]] tradition have long been anchored in the "blue blood" claims of hereditary [[nobility]]. Members of the upper classes are sometimes known as the social elite. The term ''elitism'' is also sometimes used to denote situations in which a group of people claiming to possess high abilities or simply an [[in-group]] or [[En cadre|cadre]] grant themselves extra privileges at the expense of others. This form of elitism may be described as ''[[discrimination]]''.

==Characteristics==
Attributes that identify an elite vary; personal achievement may not be essential. Elitist status ''can'' be based on personal achievement, such as degrees from top-rate universities or impressive internships and job offers, it can (in archaic societies) be based on lineage or passed-on fame from parents or grandparents. As a term, "elite" usually describes a person or group of people who are members of the uppermost class of society, and wealth can contribute to that class determination. Personal attributes commonly purported by elitist theorists to be characteristic of the elite include: rigorous study of, or great accomplishment within, a particular field; a long track record of competence in a demanding field; an extensive history of dedication and effort in service to a specific discipline (e.g., medicine or law) or a high degree of accomplishment, training or wisdom within a given field. Elitists tend to favor social systems such as [[meritocracy]], [[technocracy (bureaucratic)|technocracy]] and [[plutocracy]] as opposed to radical [[democracy]], political [[egalitarianism]] and [[populism]]. Elitists also believe only a few "shakers and movers" truly change society rather than society being changed by the majority of people who only vote and elect the elites into power. To elitists, the public is abjectly powerless and can be manipulated only by the top group of elites.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Elite (elitist) theory|url=http://www.auburn.edu/~johnspm/gloss/elite_theory|website=auburn.edu|publisher=Auburn University|accessdate=13 August 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some [[synonym]]s for "elite" might be "upper-class" or "[[aristocracy|aristocratic]]", indicating that the individual in question has a relatively large degree of control over a society's [[means of production]]. This includes those who gain this position due to socioeconomic means and not personal achievement. However, these terms are misleading when discussing elitism as a political theory, because they are often associated with negative "class" connotations and fail to appreciate a more unbiased exploration of the philosophy.

===Academic elitism===
{{anchor|Academic}}
{{see also|Ivory tower}}
{{unreferenced section|date=August 2014}}
Elitism in the context of [[education]] is the practice of concentrating attention on or allocating funding to the best students, or those [[student]]s who rank highest in a particular field of endeavour. For example, a politician who promotes advanced classes for students deemed to be highly intelligent might be accused of elitism, even if this were argued to promote an egalitarian goal, such as curing disease. Elitism in education could be based on conventional assessment of learning ability, knowledge, or other abilities. However, an "elite" school can also mean a school for the wealthy or one that is hard to enter.

==Anti-elitism&lt;!--'Antielitism' and 'Antielitism' redirect here--&gt;==
{{main|Populism|Pluralism (political theory)}}
The term ''elitism'' and the [[pejorative]] title ''elitist'' are sometimes used by people who are not (or, who claim not to be) members of elite organizations. In politics, such terms are often used to disparage a politician's views as out of touch with the interests of the "[[average Joe]]". The implication is that the alleged elitist person or group thinks they are better than everyone else, and put themselves before others as a result. The definition of ''elitist'' is similar to that of the word "[[snob]]".

An elitist is not always seen as truly elite, but only privileged. The definition may have different appreciations depending on the political contexts. Since elitism may be viewed as something necessary for creating patterns of good intellectual or professional performance, it can be used also for maintaining conditions of lack of competition and privilege.

An early proponent of '''anti-elitism'''&lt;!--boldface per WP:R#PLA--&gt; was [[Georges Sorel]].&lt;ref&gt;Daniel Woodley, ''Fascism and Political Theory: Critical Perspectives on Fascist Ideology'', Routledge, 2010, p. 125.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Egalitarianism===
{{further|Egalitarianism}}
Elitism endorses the exclusion of large numbers of people from positions of privilege or power. Thus, many populists seek the (perceived, if not present in practice) social equality of egalitarianism, [[populism]], [[socialism]], or [[communism]]. They may also support [[affirmative action]], [[social security]], [[luxury tax]]es, and highly [[progressive tax]]es for the wealthiest members of society. All of these measures seek to reduce the difference of power between the elite and the ordinary. However, these measures to reduce difference could be seen as anti-[[meritocracy|meritocratic]] in that they avoid rewarding or promoting those who are the most competitive or provide the most effort in their endeavors.

The terms ''elitism'' and ''meritocracy'' are not equivalent in meaning. Professor Kenneth Paul Tan at the Lee Kuan Yew School of Public Policy asserts that "Meritocracy, in trying to 'isolate' merit by treating people with fundamentally unequal backgrounds as superficially the same, can be a practice that ignores and even conceals the real advantages and disadvantages that are unevenly distributed to different segments of an inherently unequal society, a practice that in fact perpetuates this fundamental inequality. In this way, those who are picked by meritocracy as having merit may already have enjoyed unfair advantages from the very beginning, ignored according to the principle of nondiscrimination."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Tan|first1=Kenneth Paul|title=Meritocracy and Elitism in a Global City: Ideological Shifts in Singapore|journal=International Political Science Review|date=January 2008|volume=29|issue=7–27|pages=7|doi=10.1177/0192512107083445}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Discrimination}}
{{div col|colwidth=22em}}
* [[Classism]]
* [[Collective narcissism]]
* [[Exclusivism]]
* [[Global elite]]
* [[International Debutante Ball]]
* [[Ivory tower]]
* [[Meritocracy]]
* [[Narcissism]]
* [[Oligarchy]]
* [[Rankism]]
* [[Sectarianism]]
* [[Self-righteousness]]
* [[Snobbery]]
* [[Social Darwinism]]
* ''[[Social Evolution]]''
* [[Supremacism]]
{{div col end}}

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* {{Wiktionary-inline|elitism}}
* [[William Deresiewicz|Deresiewicz, William]] (June 2008). [https://theamericanscholar.org/the-disadvantages-of-an-elite-education/#.VSvVWfCtv-5 The Disadvantages of an Elite Education]. "Our best universities have forgotten that the reason they exist is to make minds, not careers." ''[[The American Scholar]].'' &amp;nbsp; [http://www.foreignaffairs.com/articles/143034/george-scialabba/class-and-the-classroom Review] of William Deresiewicz’s book ''[[Excellent Sheep]]'' (April 2015), ''[[Foreign Affairs]]'' 

[[Category:Social groups]]
[[Category:Political science]]
[[Category:Ideologies]]
[[Category:Oligarchy]]
[[Category:Social theories]]
[[Category:Narcissism]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Elite theory]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>