<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20081106214036|250107663" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="14654024" pageid="14654024" ns="0" title="Elitism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2008-11-13T04:41:04Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Elitism''' is the belief or attitude that those individuals who are considered members of the [[elite]] &amp;mdash; a select group of people with outstanding personal abilities, intellect, [[wealth]], specialized training or experience, or other distinctive attributes &amp;mdash; are those whose views on a matter are to be taken the most seriously or carry the most weight; whose views and/or actions are most likely to be constructive to society as a whole; or whose extraordinary skills, abilities or wisdom render them especially fit to govern &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.answers.com/topic/elitism#copyright elitism: Definition and Much More from Answers.com&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;. Alternatively, the term '''elitism''' may be used to describe a situation in which power is concentrated in the hands of the elite.

Those opposed to elitism are considered "anti-elitism", "[[populism]]," and the [[political theory]] of [[Pluralism (political theory)|pluralism]]. [[Elite theory]] is the sociological or political science analysis of elite influence in society - elite theorists regard pluralism as an utopian ideal. 

''Elitism'' may also refer to situations in which an elite individual assumes special privileges and responsibilities in the hope that this arrangement will benefit humanity.

At times, elitism is closely related to [[social class]] and what [[sociologist]]s call [[social stratification]]. Members of the upper classes are sometimes, though inaccurately, known as the "[[social elite]]."

The term ''elitism'' is also sometimes misused to denote situations in which a group of people claiming to possess high abilities or simply an [[in-group]] or [[cadre]] grant themselves extra privileges at the expense of others. This debased form of elitism may be described as ''[[discrimination]]''.

==Characteristics of the "elite"==

Attributes that identify an elite vary; personal achievement may not be essential. As a term "Elite" usually describes a person or group of people who are members of the uppermost class of society. Personal attributes commonly purported by elitist theorists to be characteristic of the elite include:

* Rigorous study of, or great accomplishment within, a particular field.
* A long track record of competence in a demanding field
* An extensive history of dedication and effort in service to a specific discipline (e.g., medicine or law)
* A high degree of accomplishment, training or wisdom within a given field


Some synonyms for elite might be "Upper-class," or "Aristocratic," indicating that the individual in question has a relatively large degree of control over a society's [[means of production]].

== Anti-elitism ==
{{main|Populism|Pluralism (political theory)}}

===Elitism as a pejorative term===
The term "elitism" or the title "elitist" can be used resentfully [http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m0354/is_2_45/ai_105401836/pg_3#] by a person who is not a member of an elite, or is a member but resents the elite position or uses it in a condescending or [[cynicism|cynical]] manner in order to ridicule or criticize practices which discriminate on the basis of ability or attributes. Often, such as in politics, it is used to describe persons as out of touch with the [[Average Joe]]. The implication is that the "elitist" person or group thinks they are better than everyone else, and therefore put themselves before others. It could be seen as a synonym for [[snob]]. An elitist is not always seen as truly elite, but only privileged. This use is often employed in politics in societies where social equality is valued and the middle and lower classes have political power.

===Elitism versus egalitarianism===
Elitism  endorses the exclusion of large numbers of people from positions of privilege or power. Thus, many populists seek the social equality of [[Egalitarianism]], [[Populism]], [[Socialism]], or [[Communism]]. They may also support [[affirmative action]], [[social security]], [[luxury tax]]es, and increasingly high [[progressive tax]]es for the wealthiest members of society. All of these measures seek to reduce the gap of power between "the elite" and "the ordinary".

===Elitism versus pluralism===
[[Pluralism (political theory)|Pluralism]] is the belief that [[public policy]] decisions should be (or, descriptively, are) the result of the struggle of forces exerted by large populations (workers, consumers, retirees, parents, etc.) directly or indirectly in the policy-making process. This is contrasted with elitism which is the belief that decisions should be (or are being) made essentially according to the interests or ideas of elites. There is a difference, however, between the idea of being more able to fulfill a political task and the actual knowing of the specialization and specifications of each corporation or other group among the general population and its particular hopes and needs, which suggests a way of cooperation which has been recently put into practice in some countries between politicians and groups of citizens which have some remote resemblances to [[Corporatism]].

== Elitism and education ==
{{main|Academic elitism}}

'''Elitism''' in the context of [[education]] is the practice of concentrating attention on or allocating funding to the [[student]]s who rank highest in a particular field of endeavour, with the other students being deemed less capable of achievement or as holding less promise for the society's future.  For example, a politician who promotes specialized biochemistry classes for highly intelligent students in an effort to cure diseases might be accused of elitism.

Elitism in education could be based upon learning ability, knowledge, or other abilities.  An elite school could merely be a wealthy school or an old school.

== See also ==
{{multicol}}
* [[Aristocracy]]
* [[Classism]]
* [[High culture]] and [[popular culture]]
* [[Limousine liberal]]
* [[Meritocracy]]
{{multicol-break}}
* [[Model minority]]
* [[Social class]]
* [[Tall poppy syndrome]]
* [[Oligarchy]] (political governance by "the few")
* [[Esotericism]]
{{multicol-break}}
* [[Misanthropy]]
* [[Thomas R. Dye]] (political scientist who has written widely on the subject of Elite theory)
* [[Pluralism (political theory)|Pluralism in politics]] (the polar opposite of elitism)
* [[Noble lie]] are lies told to maintain elitist societies
* [[Leet]], an [[internet slang]] term derived from "Elite"
{{multicol-end}}

==References==
{{reflist}}

== External links ==
{{Wiktionarypar|elitism}}

{{Discrimination}}

[[Category:Social groups]]
[[Category:Political science]]
[[Category:Sociology]]

[[cs:Elitářství]]
[[de:Elitarismus]]
[[es:Elitismo]]
[[fr:Élitisme]]
[[he:אליטיזם]]
[[nl:Elitarisme]]
[[pl:Elitaryzm]]
[[ru:Элитизм]]
[[fi:Elitismi]]
[[zh:精英主义]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>