<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20041110142203|7298777" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="14654024" pageid="14654024" ns="0" title="Elitism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2004-11-10T15:46:02Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Elitism''' is a belief or attitude that an ''[[elite]]'' (a selected group of persons whose personal abilities, specialized training or other attributes place them at the top of any field) are the people whose views on a matter are to be taken most seriously, or who are alone fit to govern.  Under elitism these people are seen as occupying a special position of authority or privilege in a group, as opposed to the majority of people who do not match up with their abilities or attributes. Members of an inherited elite are [[aristocrat]]s.

The abilities or attributes of a person that can be considered elite vary.  They include, but are not limited to:
* High level of [[Academic_degree|academic qualifications]]
* High level of [[experience]] in a given field
* High [[Intelligence (trait)|intelligence]]
* High natural abilities such as [[Athletics|athletic]] abilities
* High [[creativity]]
* [[taste#Taste_in_aesthetics|Good taste]]
Or more commonly,
* Large amount of personal [[wealth]], which are often assessed as the reward of elite qualities.

Elitism takes many forms, some of which are positive and some negative. 

Positive forms of elitism are formed in situations in which members of a community with special abilities or special qualifications are afforded greater respect in honour of their abilities or qualifications.  Their position in the top of their field is used in order to benefit everybody.

Negative forms of elitism are formed when a group of people with high abilities or attributes conspire to give themselves extra privilege at the expense of all other people.  This form of elitism may be described as ''[[discrimination]]''.

At times elitism is closely related to [[social class]] and straification. People with a higher social class is usually known as the "social elite".

==Anti-elitism==

The term "elitism" or the title "elitist" can be used resentfully by a person who is not a member of an elite, as a criticism against practices which discriminate on the basis of ability or attributes.  Elitism can be seen as encouraging the exclusion of large numbers of people from positions of privilege or power.

==Elitism and education==

'''Elitism''' in the context of [[education]] is the practice of concentrating attention on or allocating funding to the [[student]]s who rank highest in a particular field of endeavour, the other students being deemed less worthy of attention.

Elitism in education could be based upon learning ability, knowledge, or other abilities (such as [[Athletics|athletic]] ability).

==See also==

* [[Academic elitism]]
* [[Social Class]]
* [[Aristocracy]]
* [[Meritocracy]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>