<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20211019145152|1050725061" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="60115831" pageid="60115831" ns="0" title="Amatonormativity"><revisions><rev timestamp="2021-10-19T14:54:36Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|assumption that everyone prospers with an exclusive, romantic relationship}}
'''Amatonormativity''' is a term coined by [[Arizona State University]] professor of [[philosophy]] Elizabeth Brake to capture societal assumptions about [[Romance (love)|romance]].&lt;ref name="BBC"&gt;{{cite news |title=Do you feel under pressure to find The One? |url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/bitesize/articles/zfjx6v4 |access-date=15 July 2020 |publisher=BBC |date=2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="TWA"&gt;{{cite news |last1=Bonos |first1=Lisa |title=Bugging your friend to get into a relationship? How amatonormative of you. |url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/soloish/wp/2017/07/06/what-is-amatonormativity-the-belief-that-youre-always-better-off-in-a-romantic-relationship/ |access-date=14 July 2020 |work=The Washington Post |date=6 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Brake wanted a word to describe the pressure she received by many to prioritize [[marriage]] in her own life when she did not want to. The term does not necessarily only involve social pressures for marriage but general pressures involving romance.&lt;ref name="TWA"/&gt;&lt;ref name="EBA"&gt;{{cite web |last1=Brake |first1=Elizabeth |title=Amatonormativity |url=https://elizabethbrake.com/amatonormativity/ |website=Elizabeth Drake |publisher=Elizabeth Drake |access-date=14 July 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Derivation==
The word amatonormativity comes from ''amatus'', which is the [[Latin]] word for "beloved".&lt;ref name="TWP"&gt;{{cite news |last1=Baer |first1=Drake |title=There's a word for the assumption that everybody should be in a relationship |url=https://theweek.com/articles/688887/theres-word-assumption-that-everybody-should-relationship |access-date=14 July 2020 |publisher=The Week Publications Inc |date=31 March 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another word which is similarly related to the word Amatonormativity is amative. [[Merriam-Webster dictionary]] defines the word amative as: strongly moved by love and especially sexual love. Relating to or indicative of love. Amorous is a closely related word also derived from amatus.&lt;ref name="MW"&gt;{{cite web |title=Amative |url=https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/amative |website=merriam-webster |publisher=Merriam-Webster dictionaries |access-date=14 July 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{original research inline|date=October 2021}}

==Examples==
Elizabeth Brake describes the term as a pressure or desire for [[monogamy]], romance, and/or marriage.
The desire to find relationships that are romantic, sexual, monogamous, and lifelong has many social consequences. People who are [[Asexuality|asexual]], [[aromantic]], and/or [[nonmonogamy|nonmonogamous]] become social oddities. According to researcher Bella DePaulo it puts a stigma on [[Single person|single people]] as incomplete and re-enforces romantic partners to stay in unhealthy relationships because of a fear the partners may have of being single.&lt;ref name="cut"&gt;{{cite web |title=There's a Word for the Assumption That Everybody Should Be in a Relationship |publisher=The Cut |url=https://www.thecut.com/2017/03/amatonormativity-everybody-should-be-coupled-up.html |access-date=March 2, 2019 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Brake, one way in which this stigma is [[Institutional theory|institutionally]] applied is the law and morality surrounding marriage. Loving friendships and other relationships are not given the same legal protections romantic partners are given through marriage. This legality also de-legitimizes the love and care found in other non-marital relationships.&lt;ref name="psych"&gt;{{cite web |title=Should Marriage Be Abolished, Minimized, or Left Alone? |publisher=Psychology Today |url=https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/living-single/201207/should-marriage-be-abolished-minimized-or-left-alone |access-date=March 2, 2019 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Brake wrote a book, ''Minimizing Marriage'', in which she defines amatonormativity as "the widespread assumption is that everyone is better off in an exclusive, romantic, long-term coupled relationship, and that everyone is seeking such a relationship."&lt;ref name="HP"&gt;{{cite news |last1=Sharpe |first1=Brianna |title=Why These Families Want To Queer Valentine's Day |url=https://www.huffingtonpost.ca/entry/valentines-day-gender_ca_5e444684c5b61b84d3440f4f |access-date=14 July 2020 |publisher=Huffington Post |date=12 February 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Criticism of marriage]]
*[[Heteronormativity]]
*[[Polyamory]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{Discrimination}}

[[Category:Feminist terminology]]
[[Category:Neologisms]]
[[Category:Sexuality and gender-related prejudices]]
[[Category:Intimate relationships]]
[[Category:Romance]]
[[Category:Philosophy of love]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>