<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20041016083316|6630382" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="236331" pageid="236331" ns="0" title="Sexual harassment"><revisions><rev timestamp="2004-10-16T20:18:46Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[ja:&amp;#12475;&amp;#12463;&amp;#12471;&amp;#12515;&amp;#12523;&amp;#12495;&amp;#12521;&amp;#12473;&amp;#12513;&amp;#12531;&amp;#12488;]]
'''Sexual harassment''' is [[harassment]] of a sexual nature, typically in the workplace or other setting where raising objections or refusing may have negative consequences. In [[United States|American]] employment law, it is any ''unwelcome sexual advance or conduct'' on the job, having the effect of making the workplace [[intimidating]], hostile or offensive. Sexual harassment is considered a form of [[illegal]] [[discrimination]]. To be considered sexual harassment, the harassment must impact individuals of a specific [[sex]] in a [[discriminatory]] manner ([http://www.epexperts.com/news_index826.html see article]) (Article checked on [[August 15]], [[2004]].)

The definition of the phrase ''sexual harassment'' can be broad and controversial, depending on each individual's opinion of ''what'' sexual harassment is. While typical sexual harassment behaviour usually includes unwanted [[touching]] of a co-worker's [[private parts]], lewd comments, talk about gender superiority, sexual jokes, etc., some companies have reported that they have had to fire employees (after a co-worker had complained of ''sexual harassment'') for such actions as telling the complaining co-worker how good he or she looks for that co-worker's date with another person, or for simply handling what seemed, to the fired employee, to be just a harmless compliment.  Although not always meant to, such comments may sound rude or amount to sexual harassment, depending on context.

Probably the best definition of sexual harassment is sexual behaviour which the person doing it reasonably should have known was unwanted/likely to be unwanted and distressing.  Also sexual behaviour which the person doing it failed to stop after it became clear that the person on the receiving end did not like it.

Two forms of sexual harassment have been defined:
* ''[[quid pro quo]]'' ([[Latin]]: ''something for something'')
* [[hostile work environment]]

The concept of sexual harassment has both colloquial and legal meanings. Many more people believe they have experienced sexual harassment than have a solid legal case against the accuser.  Supreme Court Justice Clarence Thomas has pointed out that sexual harassment is not a freestanding tort, but is only, in its legal sense, a subcategory of employment discrimination.

For many businesses, preventing sexual harassment and defending its managerial employees from sexual harassment charges have become key goals of human resources and legal decision-making.  A Pennsylvania state legislator, attorney and MBA who was an early advocate of the illegality of sexual harassment, Rep. Mark B. Cohen of Philadelphia, said that "The best way to prevent sexual harassment is to prevent the sexualization of the work force.  No matter how friendly one's co-workers are in the course of the workday, everyone should understand that a job is not a series of dates and that the friendly easy informality created by working together does not in and of itself indicate a desire for emotional and/or sexual intimacy."
==See also==


*[[Feminism]]

== External links ==

* [http://www.nolo.com/lawcenter/ency/article.cfm/objectID/7440C7F8-0B89-46E4-A1DE73FE99AA61E0/catID/DE34C24C-9CBE-42EF-917012F2F6758F92 NOLO Law for All: Preventing Sexual Harassment in the Workplace]
* [http://www.ericdigests.org/1999-4/sexual.htm Sexual Harassment Interventions]
* [http://www.ericdigests.org/1994/sexual.htm Sexual Harassment in Higher Education from Conflict to Community]
* [http://www.ericdigests.org/1992-2/sexual.htm Getting Serious about Sexual Harassment]
* [http://www.ericdigests.org/2001-3/preventing.htm Preventing Student Sexual Harassment]
* [http://www.ericdigests.org/2000-3/sexual.htm Sexual Misconduct by School Employees]
* [http://www1.law.ucla.edu/~volokh/harass/ Freedom of Speech vs. Workplace Harassment Law]
[[Category:Feminism]]
[[Category:Sexology]]
[[Category:Crimes]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>