<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20141117025917|634171467" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="187923" pageid="187923" ns="0" title="Anti-LGBTQ rhetoric"><revisions><rev timestamp="2014-11-17T03:04:09Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[Image:Seattle gay parade-protesters.jpg|thumb|Anti-LGBT demonstration in [[Seattle]], [[Washington (state)|Washington]], [[United States]]]]
'''Anti-LGBT rhetoric''' and '''anti-gay slogans''' are themes, [[catchphrase]]s, and [[slogan]]s that have been used against [[homosexuality]] or other [[non-heterosexual]] [[sexual orientation]]s and to demean [[lesbian]], [[gay]], [[bisexual]], and [[transgender]] ([[LGBT]]) people. They range from the demeaning and pejorative to those expressing negativity on [[religion and homosexuality|religious]], medical, or moral grounds and can often be characterized as being [[hate speech]].

The rhetoric generally has an [[ideology|ideological]] basis in [[heterosexism]], and can be motivated by [[homophobia]], [[biphobia]], and [[transphobia]].

The slogans listed here are not just terms of [[invective]] but they represent [[argument]]s that are commonly used to convey opposition to [[LGBT rights]] or to the full acceptance of LGBT people.

==Themes==
Some concepts and arguments against same-sex desire and practices have been evident over the centuries, though the importance of specific arguments has varied from culture to culture. For example, preoccupation with [[child abuse]] is a largely modern concern.

Anti-gay rhetoric can come under the refrain that homosexuality goes against [[Traditional values]], or that homosexuality is a [[trojan horse]], or that it "destroys families" and humankind.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ctvnews.ca/sports/ahead-of-olympics-russia-raises-anti-lgbt-rhetoric-1.1562570 |title=Russia raises anti-LGBT rhetoric at home while softening message to West &amp;#124; CTV News |publisher=Ctvnews.ca |date=2013-11-27 |accessdate=2014-03-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Declaration that same-sex desire is unnatural===
{{See also|Homosexuality and psychology}}

This particular charge dates back to [[Plato]], who argued in the ''Laws'' I 636c and VIII 841d that homosexual sex was "out of nature" ''(para phusin).''

Though the psychiatric establishment once medicalized same-sex desire, homosexuality was later removed in 1974 as a [[mental disorder]] from the [[Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders]] (DSM) because it wasn't supported by sound scientific evidence and didn't meet the criteria for a mental disorder.&lt;ref&gt;JAMA: Gay Is Okay With APA (American Psychiatric Association); available online: http://wayback.archive.org/web/20100324080417/http://www.soulforce.org/article/642&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=amici&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.courts.ca.gov/documents/Amer_Psychological_Assn_Amicus_Curiae_Brief.pdf Page 30 |title=Case No. S147999 in the Supreme Court of the State of California, In re Marriage Cases Judicial Council Coordination Proceeding No. 4365(...) - APA California Amicus Brief&amp;nbsp;— As Filed |format=PDF |date= |accessdate=2010-12-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; There has been significant controversy over this decision.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aglp.org/gap/1_history/#declassification |title=The Declassification of Homosexuality by the American Psychiatric Association |publisher=Aglp.org |date= |accessdate=2014-03-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, according to another rebuttal of this argument, held by, among others, The [[American Society for the Defense of Tradition, Family and Property]], there are some behaviors exhibited by many animals that most would consider unnatural in humans, such as [[cannibalism]].&lt;ref&gt;The American Society for the Defense of Tradition, Family and Property. "Defending a Higher Law". [http://wayback.archive.org/web/20130509082154/http://www.tfp.org/TFPForum/online_library/Defending_A_Higher_Law.pdf], page 89&lt;/ref&gt; The counter argument to this claim is that it confuses "unnatural" with "wrong," and that this is therefore simply a restatement of the claim that homosexuality is ''morally'' wrong (like cannibalism), not unnatural.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lpva.com/Archives/Editorial/Hugman/20060415.shtml |title=The Liberarian Party of Virginia, Opponents of same-sex marriage use flawed arguments, by Michael Hugman |publisher=Lpva.com |date= |accessdate=2014-03-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; These issues are complicated by the [[polysemous]] character of the terms [[Appeal to nature|"natural" and "unnatural"]] which can be used in many equivocal ways.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://skepdic.com/natural.html |title=Skeptic's dictionary, "Natural" |publisher=Skepdic.com |date=2014-02-19 |accessdate=2014-03-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A modern [[Christian]] slogan expressing this view is "God made [[Adam and Eve]], not [[Adam and Steve]]".&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite news
|url=http://www.reuters.com/article/newsOne/idUSN1542579420070515?sp=true
|title=Evangelist Jerry Falwell dies at 73
|publisher=Reuters
|accessdate=13 April 2009
|date=15 May 2007
|author=Stuart Grudgings
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

===Conflation with child abuse===
{{See also|Child abuse|LGBT rights opposition}}
[[Societal_attitudes_toward_homosexuality#Association_with_child_abuse_and_pedophilia|The claim that homosexuals sexually abuse children]] predates the current era, as it was leveled against [[pederasty|pederasts]] even during [[Classical antiquity|antiquity]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Lucian]]. ''Erotes''&lt;/ref&gt; More recently, this charge has been phrased as "[[homosexual recruitment]]", implying that homosexuals are secretly steering children towards a homosexual lifestyle. A common slogan is "Homosexuals cannot reproduce — so they must recruit" or its variants.
In ''[[The Advocate]]''{{'}}s website, advocate.com, interview on his 2000 work, ''Outlaw Representation: Censorship and Homosexuality in 20th-Century American Art,'' [[Richard Meyer (academic)|Richard Meyer]] discusses this line of attack:

{{quote|text=...those who attacked [[Robert Mapplethorpe|Mapplethorpe]]'s work in the late 1980s used this photograph to reinforce long-standing stereotypes of gay men as [[pedophile]]s. Although no sexual activity is shown (or even suggested) in the portrait, and although the picture was commissioned by the child's mother who was in the room at the time of its taking, the very fact that Mapplethorpe had photographed a naked boy was enough, at least in the minds of [[Pat Robertson]] and [[Jesse Helms]], for the photographer to be accused of [[child molestation]].|sign=[[Tim Miller (performance artist)|Tim Miller]], ''The Advocate'', 2001&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.advocate.com/html/stories/857/857_outlaw.asp |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20050309010753/http://www.advocate.com/html/stories/857/857_outlaw.asp |archivedate=2005-03-09 |title=Miller, Tim. Taking on the Antigay Censors. advocate.com, 2001 |publisher=Web.archive.org |date= |accessdate=2014-03-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Anti-gay groups have often argued that more homosexual men are sexual abusers than heterosexuals, on the grounds that a third of abusers target boys rather than girls. This is far in excess of the proportion of gay men in the population. It is thus argued that gay men are disproportionately likely to offend.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.frc.org/get.cfm?i=IS02E3 |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20071218155700/http://www.frc.org/get.cfm?i=IS02E3 |archivedate=2007-12-18 |title=Timothy J. Dailey, '&amp;#39;Homosexuality and Child Sexual Abuse'&amp;#39; |publisher=Web.archive.org |date= |accessdate=2014-03-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|text=Homosexuality and homosexual pedophilia are not synonymous. In fact, it may be that these two orientations are mutually exclusive, the reason being that the homosexual male is sexually attracted to masculine qualities whereas the heterosexual male is sexually attracted to feminine characteristics, and the sexually immature child’s qualities are more feminine than masculine...The child offender who is attracted to and engaged in adult sexual relationships is heterosexual. It appears, therefore, that the adult heterosexual male constitutes a greater sexual risk to underage children than does the adult homosexual male.&lt;ref&gt;A. Nicholas Groth, William F. Hobson, and Thomas S. Gary, “The Child Molester: Clinical Observations,” in Social Work and Child Sexual Abuse, eds. Jon R. Conte and David A. Shore (New York: Haworth Press, 1982), p.136.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

===Homosexual sex acts as sin===
{{Main|Religion and homosexuality}}
[[File:Anti gay San Francisco.jpg|thumb|right|Religious protest of homosexuality in San Francisco]]
Many conservative denominations of [[Abrahamic religions|Abrahamic]] and other religions consider homosexual acts to be inherently sinful based on scripture (e.g., Leviticus 18:22 "Do not have sexual relations with a man as one does with a woman; that is detestable," and Leviticus 20:13 "If a man has sexual relations with a man as one does with a woman, both of them have done what is detestable. They are to be put to death; their blood will be on their own heads" as well as 1Corinthians 6:9 "Or do you not know that the unrighteous will not inherit the kingdom of God? Do not be deceived ; neither fornicators, nor idolaters, nor adulterers, nor effeminate, nor homosexuals...will inherit the kingdom of God.") Many [[Christian]] denominations and a number of [[Christian fundamentalism|Christian fundamentalists]] (e.g., [[Pat Robertson]] and [[Jerry Falwell]]) cite Biblical texts to advocate that same-sex sexual intercourse is [[sin]]ful. These individuals and congregations believe that such sexual acts as [[anal sex|anal]] and or [[oral sex]] (along with [[fornication]] of any kind) are forms of [[sexual immorality]] that should be advised against. One slogan is the commonly used phrase "love the sinner and not the sin." These churches tend to speak out against violence and hate towards those who are attracted to the same gender.&lt;ref name="lds.org"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://wayback.archive.org/web/20121015134103/http://lds.org/ldsorg/v/index.jsp?hideNav=1&amp;locale=0&amp;sourceId=bf10226fecfdb010VgnVCM1000004d82620a____&amp;vgnextoid=f318118dd536c010VgnVCM1000004d82620aRCRD |title=Internet Archive Wayback Machine |publisher=Wayback.archive.org |date=2012-10-20 |accessdate=2014-03-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2009/11/11/salt-lake-city-oks-gay-ri_n_353399.html | work=Huffington Post | title=Salt Lake OKs gay rights laws with Mormon backing | date=11 November 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Dallin H. Oaks of [[The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]] has said:

{{cquote|I desire now to say with emphasis that our concern for the bitter fruit of sin is coupled with Christlike sympathy for its victims, innocent or culpable. We advocate the example of the Lord, who condemned the sin, yet loved the sinner. We should reach out with kindness and comfort to the afflicted, ministering to their needs and assisting them with their problems.&lt;ref name="lds.org"/&gt;}}
Some conservative churches reject the idea of a homosexual orientation and view homosexuality as being an urge towards sinful homosexual behavior and thus something everyone may experience from time to time. Various inflammatory and controversial slogans, including some listed in the next section, have been used by opponent congregations and individuals, particularly by [[Fred Phelps]], founder of the website [[godhatesfags.com]] and the independent [[Westboro Baptist Church]]. These slogans have included "God Hates Fags", "Fear God Not Fags", and "[[Matthew Shepard]] Burns In Hell".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://portlandmercury.com/2000-09-14/city.html |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20050310064914/http://portlandmercury.com/2000-09-14/city.html |archivedate=2005-03-10 |title=Dunn, Katia. "What If God Were Gay?". Portland Mercury |publisher=Web.archive.org |date= |accessdate=2014-03-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other congregations, including the [[Metropolitan Community Church]]es, commonly affirm homosexuality and believe that neither homosexuality nor homosexual sex acts are a sin.&lt;ref&gt;MCC. "MCC's International Statement on Marriage Equality" Metropolitan Community Church. [http://wayback.archive.org/web/20130602164639/http://www.mccchurch.org/Content/NavigationMenu/ProgramsandInitiatives/HumanRightsSocialJustice/MarriageEquality/Marriage_Equality.htm]&lt;/ref&gt;

Homosexuality is also considered sinful in [[Islam]]. In Middle Eastern countries acts of Homosexuality is punishable by death.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|website=https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/LGBT_rights_by_country_or_territory#Middle_East}}&lt;/ref&gt; The only country that recognizes same sex relationship in the Middle East is Israel, however it is not an Islamic State. Along with Israel same-sex sexual activities have been legal in the Palestinian territories (West Bank) since 1951. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|website=https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/LGBT_rights_in_the_Palestinian_territories}}&lt;/ref&gt; Homosexuality between women however is legal in some Islamic countries, but it is illegal between men.

Based on this, the Rev. [[Jerry Falwell]] blamed homosexuals (among others) for indirectly causing the [[terrorist]] attacks on [[New York]] and [[Washington, D.C.]] on [[September 11, 2001]], by provoking the aggression of [[Islamic fundamentalism|Islamic fundamentalists]]. On the broadcast of the Christian television program ''[[The 700 Club]]'', Falwell made the following statement (for which he later apologized):
{{cquote|I really believe that the [[Paganism|pagans]] and the [[abortion]]ists and the [[feminist]]s and the gays and the [[lesbian]]s who are actively trying to make that an alternative lifestyle—the [[American Civil Liberties Union|ACLU]], [[People For the American Way]], all of them who have tried to [[secular]]ize America—I point the finger in their face and say, "You helped this happen."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://archives.cnn.com/2001/US/09/14/Falwell.apology/|archiveurl=http://wayback.archive.org/web/20130305091634/http://archives.cnn.com/2001/US/09/14/Falwell.apology/|archivedate=2013-03-05 |title=CNN report of Falwell's speech |publisher=Archives.cnn.com |date= |accessdate=2014-03-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

In 1997 the [[14th Dalai Lama]] Tenzin Gyatso said, "From a Buddhist point of view, men-to-men and women-to-women is generally considered sexual misconduct."&lt;ref&gt;San Francisco Chronicle, 06/11/1997, Dalai Lama Speaks on Gay Sex / He says it's wrong for Buddhists but not for society, http://www.sfgate.com/news/article/Dalai-Lama-Speaks-on-Gay-Sex-He-says-it-s-wrong-2836591.php&lt;/ref&gt;

===AIDS as a gay disease===
&lt;!-- Removed:[[Image:Anty LGBT.png|thumb|200px|Anti-gay flag{{citation needed|date=June 2009}}]] no evidence of usage--&gt;
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:AdParody-anti-gaySlogan.png|thumb|left|Anti-gay [[Advertising slogan|slogan]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;''c. 1990''&lt;/small&gt; (Parody of [[Raid (insecticide)|Raid]] advertisement)]] --&gt;

A common theme of anti-gay slogans is that [[AIDS]] is a "gay disease". One example is the slogan "AIDS Kills Fags Dead", a [[parody]] of the advertising slogan "[[Raid bug spray|Raid]]: [[Kills Bugs Dead]]", the tagline used in [[television advertising]] for the [[SC Johnson]] [[insecticide]].

The slogan appeared during the early years of AIDS in the United States, when the disease was mainly diagnosed among male homosexuals and was almost invariably fatal. The slogan caught on quickly as a catchy [[truism]], a [[chant]], or simply something written as [[graffiti]]. It is reported that the slogan first appeared in public in the early 1990s, when [[Sebastian Bach]], the former lead singer of the [[heavy metal music|heavy metal]] band [[Skid Row (American band)|Skid Row]], wore it on a [[t-shirt]] thrown to him by an audience member.&lt;ref&gt;Michael Musto. "La Dolce Musto", village voice, 2000. http://www.villagevoice.com/nyclife/0022,musto,15284,15.html&lt;/ref&gt; A variant of this is "AIDS cures fags."

The phrase has been used by religious opponents of homosexuality. It was for example seen in 1998 at the funeral of [[Matthew Shepard]], a victim of anti-gay violence, when Fred Phelps and his followers chanted it in front of the gathering.

According to the [[World Health Organization]], women comprise 50% of people living with HIV.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.who.int/gender/hiv_aids/en/ |title=WHO &amp;#124; Gender inequalities and HIV |publisher=Who.int |date= |accessdate=2014-03-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;
According to the [[Centers for Disease Control]], among male adults in the United States, MSM (men who have sex with men) accounted for "61% of new HIV infections in the US and 79% of infections among all newly infected men."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cdc.gov/hiv/topics/msm/], CDC: HIV among Gay and Bisexual Men. Revised May 2012&lt;/ref&gt;

The proportion of HIV cases that can be attributed to the result of homosexual relations varies according to geography.&lt;ref&gt;Joint United Nations Programme on HIV/AIDS (UNAIDS) and World Health Organization (WHO). AIDS epidemic update: December 2007. http://data.unaids.org/pub/EPISlides/2007/2007_epiupdate_en.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; In Russia, among newly registered HIV cases in 2006 where the mode of transmission was known, about one half was due to heterosexual intercourse, and this proportion has been steadily increasing.&lt;ref&gt;Ladnaya NN (2007) The national HIV and AIDS epidemic and HIV surveillance in the Russian Federation. Presentation to “Mapping the AIDS Pandemic” meeting. 30 June. Moscow.&lt;/ref&gt; Almost 60% of cases were attributed to unsafe sex between men.&lt;ref name=eurohiv.org&gt;EuroHIV (2007). ''HIV/AIDS surveillance in Europe: end-year report 2006, No 76''. Saint-Maurice, Institut de Veille Sanitaire. Available at http://www.eurohiv.org.&lt;/ref&gt; In the Caribbean, it is estimated that about 40% of reported HIV cases are the result of unsafe sex between men.&lt;ref&gt;Caribbean Commission on Health and Development (2005). ''Report of the Caribbean Commission on Health and Development for the 26th Meeting of the CARICOM Heads of Government: Overview.'' 3–6 July. Saint Lucia. Available at http://www.cpc-paho.org/publications/publication.aspx?id=59.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Inciardi JA, Syvertsen JL, Surratt HL (2005). HIV/AIDS in the Caribbean Basin. ''AIDS Care'', 17(Suppl. 1):S9–S25.&lt;/ref&gt; About 53% of newly diagnosed HIV infections in the United States, in 2005, were among men who have sex with men.&lt;ref&gt;Joint United Nations Programme on HIV/AIDS (UNAIDS) and World Health Organization (WHO). AIDS epidemic update: December 2007, page 39. http://data.unaids.org/pub/EPISlides/2007/2007_epiupdate_en.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; The largest proportion of new HIV infection in Canada, in 2002, was accounted for by unprotected sex between men,&lt;ref&gt;Public Health Agency of Canada (2006). ''HIV and AIDS in Canada: surveillance report to June 30, 2006''. Ottawa. Available at http://wayback.archive.org/web/20130117223520/http://www.phac-aspc.gc.ca/aids-sida/publication/index.html#surveillance.&lt;/ref&gt; whereas in Western Europe the highest proportion was accounted for by heterosexual intercourse.&lt;ref name=eurohiv.org/&gt;
{{Further|Misconceptions about HIV and AIDS|AIDS#Stigma}}

==See also==
{{portal|LGBT}}
* [[Biphobia]]
* [[Heterosexism]]
* [[Homophobic propaganda]]
* [[Homophobia]]
* [[LGBT rights]]
* [[LGBT rights opposition]]
* [[LGBT slogans]]
* [[List of organizations designated by the Southern Poverty Law Center as anti-gay hate groups]]
* [[Religion and homosexuality]]
* [[Transphobia]]

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

{{LGBT}}
{{Discrimination}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Anti-Lgbt Slogans}}
[[Category:Homophobia]]
[[Category:Transphobia]]
[[Category:Sexual orientation and society]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>