<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20030811212546|1286342" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="187923" pageid="187923" ns="0" title="Anti-LGBTQ rhetoric"><revisions><rev timestamp="2003-08-13T23:04:38Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[zh:&amp;#21453;&amp;#21516;&amp;#24615;&amp;#24651;&amp;#26631;&amp;#35821;]]

'''Anti-gay slogans''' are [[catchphrase]]s which oppose [[homosexuality]]. They have had an active history in the past two decades. These range from opposition on religious or moral grounds (see [[religion and homosexuality]]) to disrespectful, denigrating, and pejorative incarnations. The latter commonly use the pejorative term "[[fag]]" or "[[faggot]]".

In the political use, anti-gay slogans are commonly used to state the varied cases against homosexuality, and these reflect the spectrum of discourse among those who oppose homosexuality and [[gay rights]]. Many of these slogans are considered [[homophobic hate speech]] by those who accept the concept of [[hate speech]].

== Themes ==
The basic themes of anti-gay slogans are based on various claims:
* [[AIDS]] is a gay disease
* Homosexuality is a sin (see [[religion and homosexuality]])
* Homosexuals "recruit" children
* Homosexuality as a [[sexual perversion]]

=== AIDS as a gay disease ===

A common theme of anti-gay slogans is that [[AIDS]] is a [[gay disease]] which is somehow deserved.

The [[slogan 'AIDS Kills Fags Dead']] has been used in the [[United States]] to express both opposition to homosexuality and hatred towards homosexual persons. It is generally cited as a prime example of homophobic hate speech; refer to ''[[Slogan 'AIDS Kills Fags Dead']]'' for more information.

''See also: [[Homosexuality and medical science]]''

=== Homosexuality as a sin ===

Many slogans, including the above, have been used by [[religion and homosexuality|religious opponents of homosexuality]]. 

Fred Phelps is the leader and head [[minister]] of the Westboro Baptist Church in [[Topeka, Kansas]]. He is also owner of the web sites '''"godhatesfags.com"''' and "godhatesamerica.com" and a perpetrator of anti-homosexual [[propaganda]]. His group carries out daily picketing in Topeka, and travels nationally to picket the funerals of homosexual victims of murder, [[gay-bashing]] or death related to [[AIDS]]/HIV, as well as other events related or supposedly related to gay people.

Phelps and his supporters and members of his church (1) attend said gatherings, as well as other gay-related events, with signs bearing anti-homosexual slogans which some consider to be hate speech. These have also included "God Hates Fags," and "Matthew Shepard Rots In Hell".

* "Fear God Not Fags": see http://www.cnn.com/US/9810/16/shepard.funeral.03/ 

=== "Recruitment" ===

Another common theme is that homosexuals are somehow predatory on children, or are "recruiting" in secret. A common slogan is "Homosexuals cannot reproduce — so they must recruit" and its variants.

=== Homosexuality as a perversion ===

A final theme is that homosexuals perform terrifying and unnatural sex acts, the nature of which is so horrible that they must be referred to only in code, for example in the slogan "Save the Gerbils".

== External links ==

* [http://www.sebastianbach.com/ Sebastian Bach's official website]
* "[http://www.villagevoice.com/issues/0022/musto.php La Dolce Musto]" Michael Musto column discussing Sebastian Bach, dated May 31 - June 6, 2000</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>