<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20051107030455|27585229" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="187923" pageid="187923" ns="0" title="Anti-LGBTQ rhetoric"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-11-08T21:56:22Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Anti-gay slogans''' are [[catchphrase]]s or [[slogan]]s which express opposition to [[homosexuality]] in ways which [[gay rights activist]]s consider to be irrationally hostile or fearful (see [[homophobia]] and also [[anti-gay]]). Whether any particular formula is actually irrational is, of course, a matter of considerable controversy.

These slogans, along with moral or or scriptural prohibitions, have a long history, dating back at least as far as [[Classical Greece]] 2500 years ago. They range from the disrespectful, denigrating and pejorative to those expressing antipathy on [[religion and homosexuality|religious]] or moral grounds. They commonly use pejorative terms like "[[fag (slang)|fag]]" or "[[faggot (slang)|faggot]]". [[Westboro Baptist Church|Godhatesfags.com]] is a prime example.

In political use, they are commonly used to convey the varied cases against homosexuality. They reflect the spectrum of opinion among those who oppose homosexuality and [[gay rights]]. Many are considered [[homophobic hate speech]] by those who accept the concept of [[hate speech]].

== Themes ==

The stock phrases used against same-sex love have changed little over the centuries. They are one of the main vehicles for the propagation of anti-gay attitudes.

=== Declaration that same-sex love is unnatural ===

''Main article: [[Queer studies]]''

This particular charge dates back to Plato, who claimed that male love was "against nature" ''(para-physein).'' In recent times the discussion has been framed in psychiatric rather than philosophical terms, with the claim that it is a [[sexual perversion]].

Though the psychiatric establishment did medicalize same-sex love, that position has been revised and homosexuality was removed as a medical disorder from the DSM4 (Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders). Recent work in [[queer studies]] has shown the practice to be widespread in nature (see: [[Non-human animal sexuality]]) as well as in human society, leading gay right advocates to assert that opposition to same sex love would itself be against nature.

=== Blame for Biblical plagues and natural disasters ===

''Main article: [[Religion and homosexuality]]''

Since the middle ages, sodomites were blamed for "bringing down the wrath of God" upon the land, and their pleasures blamed for the periodic epidemics of disease which decimated the population. This "pollution" was thought to be cleansed by fire (modelled after the mythical destruction of [[Sodom]] and [[Gomorrah]]), as a result of which countless individuals were burned at the stake or run through with white-hot iron rods.

A modern example of this type of thinking was shown by the [[Jerry Falwell|Rev. Jerry Falwell]], who blamed gays and lesbians (among others) for indirectly causing the terrorist attacks on New York and Washington of September 11, 2001. On the broadcast of the Christian television program "The 700 Club," Falwell made the following statement (for which he later apologized):

*''I really believe that the pagans, and the abortionists, and the feminists, and the gays and the lesbians who are actively trying to make that an alternative lifestyle, the [[ACLU]], People For the American Way, all of them who have tried to secularize America. I point the finger in their face and say 'you helped this happen.'''

Since the [[1980]]'s, similar accusations have been made, inspired by the [[AIDS]] epidemic, labeling it a gay [[disease]] and divine retribution against homosexuals. The epidemic, however, has touched primarily people enagaged in opposite-sex behaviors, and medical evidence indicates the disease is propagated not because the sex of the partner is the same as one's own, but as a factor of unhygienic sexual behaviors (such as relations with multiple partners concurrent with an absence of protective techniques). ''See [[#AIDS as a gay disease|discussion below]]''

=== Conflation with child abuse ===

:''See also [[Gay rights counter-movement]]''

This is an accusation which predates the current era, as it was leveled against [[pederasty|pederasts]] even during [[Classical antiquity|Antiquity]] (See [[Lucian|Lucian's ''Erotes'']]). 
More recently, this charge has been phrased as "recruitment", implying that homosexuals are somehow predatory on children, or are "recruiting" in secret. A common slogan is "Homosexuals cannot reproduce &amp;#8212; so they must recruit" or its variants.

In an Advocate.com interview[http://www.advocate.com/html/stories/857/857_outlaw.asp] on his [[2000]] work, ''Outlaw Representation: Censorship and Homosexuality in 20th-Century American Art,'' [[Richard Meyer]] discusses this line of attack:
*''. . . those who attacked [[Robert Mapplethorpe|Mapplethorpe]]'s work in the late [[1980]]s used this photograph to reinforce long-standing stereotypes of gay men as pedophiles. Although no sexual activity is shown (or even suggested) in the portrait, and although the picture was commissioned by the child's mother who was in the room at the time of its taking, the very fact that Mapplethorpe had photographed a naked boy was enough, at least in the minds of [[Pat Robertson]] and [[Jesse Helms]], for the photographer to be accused of child molestation.''

Among the counterarguments used to refute the charge are that it is based on the denial of the comparable abuse of young girls by men who prefer the opposite sex, and on the infantilization of adolescents who in a different context would be considered to have come of age. The reports of young people discovering their attraction to others of the same sex at an early age contradict claims that those young people were subject to outside persuasion.

Writers who deconstruct the notion of a linkage between homosexuality and pedophilia, such as [[Gerald Hannon]], may even ''themselves'' find their work misrepresented as endorsing pedophilia and child abuse.

=== Dissipation of vital force ===

This argument has been phrased since antiquity in agricultural terms, as "casting one's seed on sterile rocks." It has been countered by pointing out that there are multiple examples of non-procreative heterosexual sex (as well as masturbation), such as relations between people past the age of conception, commercial sex, and sex in which birth-control measures are used. It has also been suggested that the insemination inherent in same-sex relations, while not producing actual offspring, yields spiritual and intellectual fruit.

=== Association with effeminacy in men, and masculinity in women ===

''Main article: [[Gender identity]]''

This accusation seems to be based on the generalization that all those who engage in same-sex relations are also gender variant, a contention which is not sustained by research in the field.

=== Homosexuality as a sin ===

''Main article: [[Religion and homosexuality]]''

Some Christians interpret Biblical texts to imply that same-sex sexual relationships are "sinful." Many [[mainline]] churches are very divided over the issue of [[same sex marriage]] and religious [[blessing of same sex unions]] where thy can bless the same sex love but not the same sex sex acts. These individuals and congregations believe that the sexual acts, i.e.,  [[anal sex]] and/or [[oral sex]],  are forms of [[sexual immorality]] that should be advised against.  One slogan commonly heard is "love the sinner and not the sin."   Other congregations, including the [[metropolitan Community Church]]es, commonly affirm homosexuality and believe that neither homosexuality or homosexual sex acts are a sin. Some conservative churches reject the idea of a homosexual "orientation" and view homosexuality as being an urge towards sinful homosexual behavior. Many slogans, including some listed in the next section, have been used by [[religion and homosexuality|religious opponents of homosexuality]], particularly by [[Fred Phelps|Rev. Fred Phelps]], founder of the [[westboro Baptist Church|godhatesfags.com]] website and [[Westboro Baptist Church]]. These controversial slogans have included "God Hates Fags", "Fear God Not Fags", and "[[Matthew Shepard]] Burns In Hell" [http://www.portlandmercury.com/2000-09-14/city.html]. Another slogan is "God made Adam and Eve, not Adam and Steve".

=== AIDS as a gay disease ===

''Related article: [[Homosexuality and medical science]]''

A common theme of anti-gay slogans is that [[AIDS]] is a gay disease which is somehow deserved. One example is the [[slogan]] "AIDS Kills Fags Dead" (''[[faggot (slang)|fag]]'' being a pejorative term for a male homosexual). The fact that the AIDS disease is much more prevalent in the homosexual community fuels the societal thinking in this regard. Actually, HIV, the disease which is believed to be the cause of AIDS, is much more attainable from a man than a woman.

&lt;div style="float: right; margin: 0 0 1em 1em; text-align: center;"&gt;[[Image:AdParody-anti-gaySlogan.png]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;''Anti-gay &lt;br&gt;[[Advertising slogan|slogan]] [[parody]] ''&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;''c. 1990''&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

The "AIDS Kills Fags Dead" slogan is a [[parody]] of the [[advertising slogan]] "[[Raid bug spray|Raid]]: [[Kills Bugs Dead]]", the tagline used in [[television advertising]] for the [[SC Johnson]] [[insecticide]]. It thus implicitly identifies gay men with vermin fit for extermination.

The slogan appeared during the early years of [[AIDS]] in the United States, when the disease was mainly diagnosed among male homosexuals and was almost invariably fatal. The slogan caught on quickly as a catchy [[truism]], a [[chant]], or simply something written as [[graffiti]].

It is reputed that the slogan first appeared in public in the early [[1990s]], when [[Sebastian Bach]], lead singer of the [[heavy metal music|heavy metal]] band [[Skid Row (band II)|Skid Row]], wore it on a [[t-shirt]].

The phrase has been used by [[religion and homosexuality|religious opponents of homosexuality]]. It was for example seen in [[1998]] at the funeral of [[Matthew Shepard]], a victim of anti-gay violence (who did not have AIDS), when a group led by [[Fred Phelps]] of the [[Westboro Baptist Church]] staged a protest.

A variant of this is "AIDS cures fags", a role reversal which makes homosexuality the disease and the inevitable death from AIDS the "cure".

==See also==

*[[Homophobic hate speech]]
*[[Homosexuality and medical science ]]
*[[Homosexuality and morality]]
*[[List of gay-related topics]]
*[[List of sexual slurs]]
*[[Hate speech]]
*[[Fred Phelps]]
*[[Skid Row (band II)|Skid Row]]

== External links and references==

* [http://www.cnn.com/US/9810/16/shepard.funeral.03/ Slain gay student remembered as 'angel with new wings']
* [http://www.sebastianbach.com/ Sebastian Bach's official website]
* "[http://www.villagevoice.com/issues/0022/musto.php La Dolce Musto]" Michael Musto column discussing Sebastian Bach, dated May 31 - June 6, 2000

[[zh:&amp;#21453;&amp;#21516;&amp;#24615;&amp;#24651;&amp;#26631;&amp;#35821;]]
[[Category:LGBT civil rights]]
[[Category:Sexual orientation and society]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>