<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20031006205555|1697454" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="18947899" pageid="18947899" ns="0" title="Anti-intellectualism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2003-11-09T03:41:19Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Anti-intellectualism''' is a term, which in one sense describes a hostility towards, or a mistrust of intellectuals, and their [[intellectual]] pursuits. This may be expressed in various ways, such as an attack on the merits [[science]], [[education]], or [[literature]], 

In a broader sense, the term 'anti-intellectualism' simply reflects an attitude that takes "intellectualism" with a [[grain of salt]]. Inasmuch as intellectuals may be [[vanity|vain]] or [[narcissism|narcissistic]] in their self-image, so too may they be understood by "common people" as simply another fallible [[human]] [[archetype]].

== Prevalence ==

Anti-intellectualism is found in every nation on earth, but has become associated in particular with the [[United States of America]].  It existed in the US before the nation itself; the [[New England]] [[Puritan]] writer [[John Cotton]] wrote in [[1642]] that "The more learned and witty you bee, the more fit to act for Satan will you bee."  In [[1843]], [[Bayard R. Hall]] wrote of frontier [[Indiana]], that "(w)e always preferred an ignorant bad man to a talented one, and hence attempts were usually made to ruin the moral character of a smart candidate; since unhappily smartness and wickedness were supposed to be generally coupled, and incompetence and goodness."   Anti-intellectual [[folklore]] values the self-reliant and &amp;quot;self-made man,&amp;quot; schooled by [[society]] and by experience, over the intellectual whose learning was acquired through [[book]]s and formal study.

== Causes ==

Anti-intellectual beliefs can come from a variety of factors.  These include:

=== Religion ===

Although most [[religion]]s have rich intellectual traditions, many often rely on arguments from authority and reject secular critical traditions.  [[Evangelical]] or [[fundamentalism|fundamentalist]] forms of religion are a frequent source of anti-intellectual statements.  [[Syncretism|Syncretistic]] or [[mysticism|mystical]] varieties of religion may also struggle with the definitions and distinctions of [[theology]].  Some religions have [[doctrine]]s that affirm statements about [[natural history|natural]] or human [[history]], the [[provenance]] of [[sacred text]]s, and other matters that may be investigated by outside [[scholarship]]; this can give rise to conflict.  In a different cultural field, when [[bohemian]]ism and [[romanticism]] become major factors in the arts, religious believers may believe these trends to be subversive of [[morality]] and call for [[censorship]].

=== Corporate culture ===

[[Corporation|Corporate]] culture, which sometimes calls itself "[[pragmatism]]," is an occasional source of hostility to learning. The idea here is that education is a costly and useless distraction from the more important business of making [[money]].  Reading is a sort of solitary vice, according to this viewpoint; it does little to make a person more affable or conventional, and does not foster an aptitude for [[marketing]].  It is feared that intellectuals may acquire [[ethics|ethical]] and [[politics|political]] ideas that may impede business or make its practices distasteful.  Scientific and [[technology|technological]] learning may be given a grudging respect; but the arts, literature, philosophy, and similar [[culture|cultural]] pursuits are all wastes of time.  Those who pursue them are supposed to inhabit an "ivory tower" of [[academy|academia]], full of grand plans whose practise is seen as impossibly flawed by practical people who know better. 

According to this view, education should be a sort of [[apprentice]]ship, rather than being done on the model of [[classical education]] based on [[Greek language|Greek]] and [[Latin]] [[grammar]] and literature.  The educational [[philosophy]] of [[John Dewey]], founded on these assumptions, has largely replaced classical education in the USA.

=== Populism ===

[[Populism]] is a third strain of anti-intellectualism.  Intellectuals are presented as [[elitism|elitists]] and tricksters whose knowledge and [[rhetoric]]al skills are feared, not because they are useless, but because they may be used to hoodwink the ordinary people, who are conceived of as the "salt of the earth" and the source of virtue.  In a similar vein, the curiosity and objectivity of intellectuals about foreign countries and beliefs is portrayed by populists as a lack of [[patriotism]] or [[moral clarity]], and intellectuals are often held to be suspect of holding dangerously foreign, possibly subversive, opinions.  This kind of anti-intellectualism is associated in the history of the United States with [[Joseph McCarthy]], the [[anti-Communism|anti-Communist]] [[U.S. senator|senator]] from [[Wisconsin]].   [[William F. Buckley, Jr.]] once remarked that he'd rather be governed by the first hundred names in the phone book than by the [[faculty]] of [[Harvard University]].  (Buckley went to [[Yale University|Yale]].)  When [[Richard Nixon]] evoked the virtues of a "silent majority," by implication he opposed them to a minority that talked too much.

== Reference ==
:''Anti-Intellectualism in American Life'', by [[Richard Hofstadter]]: ISBN 0394703170</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>