<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20051110183709|27944102" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="18947899" pageid="18947899" ns="0" title="Anti-intellectualism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-11-11T03:55:58Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Anti-intellectualism''' is a term that in one sense describes a hostility towards, or mistrust of, [[intellectuals]] and intellectual pursuits.  This may be expressed in various ways, such as an attack on the merits of [[science]], [[education]], or [[literature]].

Anti-intellectuals often seek to frame themselves as champions of the self-styled 'ordinary people', and as advocates of [[egalitarianism]] against [[elitism]], especially what they perceive as [[academic elitism]].  These critics argue from a perception that educated people form a [[social class]] by virtue of their education: that members of this social class tend to talk chiefly to one another, and as such are remote from other points of view, and also that members of this social class tend to dominate [[politics|political]] discourse about [[social issue|social]] and other issues.  

Anti-intellectualism can also be used as a term used to criticize an educational system if it seems to place minimal emphasis on academic and intellectual accomplishment or a [[government]]'s tendency to formulate policies without consultation with authoritative and [[scholarly method|scholarly]] study on the issues in question.

[[Image:nast-intellect.png|thumb|300px|[[Political cartoon]]ist [[Thomas Nast]] contrasts an intellectual with a [[boxing|prize-fighter]].]]

== Causes ==

Anti-intellectual beliefs can come from a variety of sources.  These include:

=== Religion ===

Although most [[religion]]s have rich intellectual traditions, many often rely on arguments from authorities that are not indepedently verifiable, along with a somewhat common tendency to reject secular critical traditions.  [[Evangelicalism|Evangelical]] or [[fundamentalism|fundamentalist]] forms of religious beliefs can be a source of anti-intellectual statements, though not all such groups are anti-intellectual and many pride themselves on their intellectual traditions.  [[Syncretism|Syncretistic]] or [[mysticism|mystical]] varieties of religious beliefs may also struggle with the definitions and distinctions of [[theology]].  Some religions have [[doctrine]]s that affirm statements about [[natural history|natural]] or human [[history]], the [[provenance]] of [[sacred text]]s, and other matters that may be investigated by outside [[scholarly method|scholarship]]; this can give rise to conflict.  In a different cultural field, when [[bohemianism]] and [[romanticism]] become major factors in the fine arts, religious believers may believe these trends to be subversive of [[morality]] and call for [[censorship]]. This has been a fairly common theme in socio-cultural trends in the Americas and Europe since the time of the [[Protestant Reformation|Reformation]], as an example. However this is not a sign of anti-intellecualism. It is a sign of moral conservatism, which is distinctly different from anti-intellectualism, though the two concepts may be allied in some cases.also its when people, moastly teens, find it "uncool" to be the smart person in their school or class.

=== Corporate culture ===

[[Corporation|Corporate]] culture in modern times has demonstrated a general preference for '[[pragmatism]]', and this is an occasional source of hostility toward learning.  The idea here is that education is a costly and useless distraction from the more important business of making [[money]]. Reading and writing are solitary ventures, and according to this viewpoint these activities do little to make a person more affable or conventional, and does not foster an aptitude for [[marketing]] or acumen for [[investment]] in profitable ventures.  It is feared that intellectuals may acquire [[ethics|ethical]] and [[politics|political]] ideas that may impede business or make its practices distasteful. This viewpoint tends to be commonly found in  populations that utilise [[capitalism]] as their form of economic activity.  Scientific and [[technology|technological]] learning may be given a grudging respect; but the [[art|arts]], [[literature]], [[philosophy]], and similar [[culture|cultural]] pursuits are all considered a waste of time.  Those who pursue them are supposed to inhabit an '[[ivory tower]]' of [[academy|academia]], full of grand plans whose practice is seen as impossibly flawed by their critics. 

According to this view, education should be a sort of [[apprentice]]ship, rather than being done on the model of [[classical education]] based on [[Greek language|Greek]] and [[Latin]] [[grammar]] and literature.  The educational [[philosophy]] of [[John Dewey]], founded on these assumptions, has had some influence on education in the USA.

===Educational system===

The educational system may serve as a powerful tool for forming the culture of a nation.  In the English speaking world, particularly in the [[United States|USA]] and [[England]], the schools and universities have often been criticized for being overtaken by overtly anti-intellectual trends and hence not preparing the youth properly to be members of society who would  be cultured, prepared for challenging jobs, and capable of independent thought.

====In schools====

In schools these may include lack of emphasis on effective teaching of mathematics and the sciences, which is by now somewhat proverbial, and the rewriting [[history]] curricula to de-emphasize facts in favor of political agendas of the editors, which may include political correctness or '[[minority]] narratives' or a [[nationalist]] agenda.  Such critics would say, for example, that not teaching kids [[multiplication table]]s in [[primary school]] and not making sure that they learn [[algebra]] by graduation is a blatant example of anti-intellectualism and malfeasance on the part of many schools.  They would similarly criticize allowing students to graduate without learning the key facts about their country's national [[history]], or without having read lots of [[William Shakespeare|Shakespeare]].

Many critics of anti-intellectualism would also suggest the push to teach [[creationism]] (or [[Intelligent Design]]) over [[evolution]] is an example of anti-intellectualism.

====In colleges====

In the realm of [[higher education]] concerns are generally twofold: 

One type of criticism of colleges being anti-intellectual has to do with perceived political biases within some branches of [[humanities]] and social science in university departments.  Some believe that humanities professors in American colleges tend toward political [[liberalism]].  [[Conservative]] critics contend the [[research]] and [[teaching]] done by perceived liberal professors lacks academic rigor and may amount to [[indoctrination]] of students, while [[liberalism|liberal]] critics charge that [[indoctrination]] is what [[conservatives]] have traditionally used in the humanities to support the status quo.  Among the fields most contested are [[Women's Studies]], culture studies, and history.  Conservative critics are sometimes called anti-intellectuals, while liberal reformers are often charged with 're-writing history'; the fairness or each party's assertion must be recognized to vary from case to case.

The other major concern deals with the perceived lack of general education in college curricula.  The critics would say, for example, that college students ought to take more [[humanities]] classes, such as history or literature, along with the requirements of their major.  Notably, the [[humanities]] requirements in [[United States|American]] colleges are actually much greater than in many other countries, such as [[Russia]] or [[India]] where [[college]] instruction is focused almost entirely on professional, often technical, preparation.  It may be argued that in these countries it is generally believed [[high school]] education has given a student sufficient exposure to general education topics.  No such confidence is usually shown by observers of the American school system.

====The demands of youth culture====

A major preserve of real, militant anti-intellectualism in today's America (as perhaps in many other countries) is a youth subculture often associated with those students who are more interested in social life and athletics than in their studies.  Such subcultures exist among students of all groups, although among [[Asian Americans]] it is reputedly much less pronounced.  On the other hand, there exists much anecdotal evidence of anti-intellectualism among [[African American]] youth who may consider focusing on school studies a 'white' thing.  Needless to say, there are plenty of loafers and anti-intellectuals among white students also.  

Commercial [[youth culture]] also generates a dizzying variety of [[fad]]s.  Keeping up with the trends is difficult, and their content is frequently criticised by cultural critics of many different persuasions for being simple-minded and pandering to unsophisticated appetites.  Playing the game of [[Why Nerds are Unpopular|popularity]] has been likened by [[blog]] writer [[Paul Graham]] to a full time job that leaves little time for intellectual interests.

[[Image:Astevenson.jpg|frame|[[Adlai Stevenson]] was called an "[[egghead]]" by [[Richard Nixon]] during the [[U.S. presidential election, 1952|1952 US presidential race]].]]

=== Populism ===

[[Populism]] is another major strain of anti-intellectualism.  Intellectuals are presented as [[elitism|elitists]] and tricksters whose knowledge and [[rhetoric|rhetorical]] skills are feared, not because they are useless, but because they may be used to hoodwink the ordinary people, who are conceived of as the 'salt of the earth' and the source of virtue.

In a similar vein, the curiosity and objectivity of intellectuals about foreign countries and beliefs is portrayed by populists as a lack of [[patriotism]] or [[moral clarity]], and intellectuals are often held to be suspect of holding dangerously foreign, possibly subversive, opinions.  This kind of anti-intellectualism is associated in the history of the United States with [[Joseph McCarthy]], the [[anti-Communism|anti-Communist]] [[U.S. senator|senator]] from [[Wisconsin]].  [[William F. Buckley, Jr.]] once remarked that he'd rather be governed by the first hundred names in the phone book than by the [[faculty]] of [[Harvard University]] since he believed that there were many Communists in the educational establishment (Buckley went to [[Yale University|Yale]]).

== Anti-intellectualism in the United States ==

Anti-intellectualism is found in every nation on earth.  Americans, among others, have been accused quite vocally of suffering from it, particularly by the [[American liberalism|liberal]] [[literati]] both in the [[United States|USA]] and in [[Europe]].  Such accusations are particularly fueled by the existence of the political schism between the [[United States Republican Party|Republican]] and [[United States Democratic Party|Democratic]] parties which prompts the less scrupulous contenders on both sides use it as a term of abuse for their opponents.  By comparison societies in [[Europe]] and [[Asia]] are much more politically homogenous.

In the U.S., the Republican Party is typically home to anti-intellectuals.  Many conservative activists have displayed utter disdain for [[academia]] and such reputable institutions as [[Harvard University|Harvard]], [[Princeton University|Princeton]], [[Yale University|Yale]], and various other colleges which many on the right-wing contend are hotbeds of political liberalism.

Historically, anti-intellectualism did play a prominent role in American culture. Some of it originated from the commonly held view among conservative [[Christianity|Christians]] of old that [[education]] subverts religious belief.  The validity of this view, in fact, was well substantiated by the spread of [[atheism]] and [[Deism]] among the educated during the [[The Age of Enlightenment|Enlightenment]]. Hence, for instance, the [[New England]] [[Puritan]] writer [[John Cotton]] wrote, in [[1642]], "The more learned and witty you bee, the more fit to act for [[Satan]] will you bee." 

A much more important historical source of anti-intellectualism has been the 19th century [[popular culture]].  At the time when the vast majority of the population was involved in [[manual labour|manual labor]], and most of the population was [[rural]] and engaged in [[agriculture]], bookish education, which at the time focused on [[classics]], was seen to have little value.  It should be noted that Americans of the era were generally very literate and, in fact, read [[William Shakespeare|Shakespeare]] much more than their present day counterparts. However, the ideal at the time was an individual skilled and successful in his trade and a productive member of society; studies of [[classics]] and [[Latin]] in colleges were generally derided in [[popular culture]]. 

Anti-intellectual [[folklore]] values the self-reliant and &amp;quot;self-made man,&amp;quot; schooled by [[society]] and by experience, over the [[intellectual]] whose learning was acquired through [[book]]s and formal study.  This folklore has a long history in the United States. In [[1843]], [[Bayard R. Hall]] wrote of frontier [[Indiana]], that "(w)e always preferred an ignorant bad man to a talented one, and hence attempts were usually made to ruin the moral character of a smart candidate; since unhappily smartness and wickedness were supposed to be generally coupled, and incompetence and goodness."  A character of [[O. Henry]] has noted that once a graduate of an [[East Coast of the United States|East Coast]] [[college]] gets over being vain, he makes just as good a [[cowboy]] as any other young man. The related stereotype of the slow-witted naïf with a heart of gold also frequently appears in American popular culture, recently and conspicuously in the [[1985]] novel and [[1994]] motion picture ''[[Forrest Gump]]''.  

In the United States, [[Robert Warshow]] has put forth the hypothesis that the [[Communist Party USA|Communist Party]] became central to American intellectual life during the [[1930s]]: 

:''For most American intellectuals, the Communist movement of the 1930s was a crucial experience.  In Europe, where the movement was at once more serious and more popular, it was still only one current in intellectual life; the Communists could never completely set the tone of thinking. . . . But in this country there was a time when virtually all intellectual vitality was derived in one way or another from the Communist party.  If you were not somewhere within the party’s wide orbit, then you were likely to be in the opposition, which meant that much of your thought and energy had to be devoted to maintaining yourself in opposition.''[http://www.fas.org/sgp/library/moynihan/appa7.html]&lt;!--Moynihan Commission Report, quoted from Robert Warshow, ''The Legacy of the 30’s: Middle-Class Mass Culture and the Intellectuals’ Problem,'' Commentary Magazine (December 1947): 538, footnote 103.--&gt;

Today, Christian thinkers, who have less influence in society, no longer consider [[education]] in general evil, although they may object to some of its specific un-Christian aspects, e.g. alleged anti-religious or pro-[[abortion]] propaganda in schools and colleges.  The once-plentiful industrial jobs have disappeared and have been replaced with low-wage service and specialty ones, which at most require a high school diploma.  Statistics indicate that in the United States half the population has at least some college experience, however only one-third of the population graduates from college.

Perceived lack of 'real life' usefulness, as well as, allegedly, [[academic rigor]] in humanities studies in the universities have contributed to much disdain for such studies, particularly among those who study, or have studied, [[technical]] subjects.  This may be considered anti-intellectualism, or perhaps a 'rival-intellectualism' inasmuch as people, who may think that intellectual pursuit of study of [[English literature]] is useless, may think that studying [[mechanical engineering]], which is an intellectual activity of great complexity, is useful and good.  A characteristic criticism, not necessarily valid by any means, of the study of humanities is that teaching students literature prepares them to become future professors of literature, and not much else.

The American educational system also serves as a significant wellspring of anti-intellectualism in its reputed failure to impart the necessary knowledge and skills to make informed decisions about the world to its students.

===Use of the term for political reasons===

In the English-speaking countries accusation of anti-intellectualism are often made in discourse between political opponents.  For example, in the [[United States|USA]] the [[American liberalism|liberals]] may claim that [[conservative]] beliefs about foreign affairs or [[economics]] stem from "ignorance," poor education, and "lack of awareness" of the substantive issues involved, and as such are anti-intellectual.  A quintessential example of this is the title of a book by [[Michael Moore]], a famous [[United States|American]] [[liberalism|liberal]] filmmaker: ''[[Stupid White Men]]'' (the book criticizes [[United States|American]] corporate and government leaders).  The conservatives generally counter by claiming exactly the same thing about the liberals. For example, in an argument about the Israeli-Palestinian conflict one may imagine the pro-[[Palestinian]] side accuses the opponent of ignorance of the great suffering of the Palestinians under Israeli [[occupation]].  Meanwhile, the pro-Israeli side would probably respond by calling the other ignorant of the long history of [[Palestinian]] [[terrorism]] constituting an existential threat to [[Israel]] which the Israelis may need to counteract by [[military]] means.  It should be appreciated, however, that political doctrines and policies, whether liberal or conservatives, are developed by highly educated individuals well-versed in their fields of inquiry. The divergent views usually come either from different interpretations of the same facts where there is no clear objective way to ascertain validity of a belief, e.g., will lower taxes help the [[Economics|economy]], or from a politically-motivated lack of desire to try to find out the truth about the situation, e.g., are teaching methods in school optimal.

==Anti-intellectualism in the former Soviet Union==

In the [[Soviet Union]], within the first decade after the Revolution of 1917, the [[Bolsheviks]] generally scorned and suspected the educated as potential traitors to the cause of the proletariat.  Whereas the core of the [[Communist]] Party was well-educated, the people who became local activists and officials in [[government]] and [[industry]] often lacked education and disdained those who had it.  [[Lenin]] once called the [[intelligentsia]], perhaps particularly those who opposed him, "rotten" and "shit".  The boast, roughly translated as "we haven&amp;rsquo;t completed any academies" ("&amp;#1084;&amp;#1099; &amp;#1072;&amp;#1082;&amp;#1072;&amp;#1076;&amp;#1077;&amp;#1084;&amp;#1080;&amp;#1077;&amp;#1074; &amp;#1085;&amp;#1077; &amp;#1082;&amp;#1086;&amp;#1085;&amp;#1095;&amp;#1072;&amp;#1083;&amp;#1080;") became a byword for the new ruling [[elite]].

Later on, the Soviet government came to see education as important and dedicated great resources to literacy, on the one hand, and higher and professional education, on the other.  However, as a matter of social policy, the government sought to promote the [[working class]] over an intellectual élite.  Accordingly, industrial workers often received greater salaries than university-trained professionals such as [[teacher]]s, [[medical doctor|doctor]]s, and [[engineer]]s.  Moreover, workers were covertly inculcated with the notion that only the manual labor creates real value in the economy, whereas the educated people just sit around writing papers.  Some critics have seen this policy as anti-intellectual.

The Soviet treatment of science is an example of anti-intellectualism - the triumph of [[Lysenkoism]] in Soviet Russia was a result of political bullying of scientists and the punishment of dissenters rather than the normal scientific process of publishing one's findings.

==Anti-intellectualism in Maoist China and Cambodia==

In [[Maoist]] [[China]] during the [[Cultural Revolution]], a revolutionary transformation of all aspects of life, including education, was attempted.  University education in particular was moved away from the generation of highly specialized experts, who were seen as constituting a self-interested [[social class|class]] divorced from the rest of society, and into the service of the masses.  Training programs were accelerated and connected to the practical needs of productive work and socialist development.  Some universities were closed for several years during the transformation.  At the same time, primary and secondary education were greatly expanded in rural China, and urban students were encouraged or required to spend some time in the countryside, both to teach the peasants and to learn from them.  Critics have charged that the practice of curtailing and transforming university education and sending students to the countryside was anti-intellectual.  In the view of the Chinese government, however, state-funded education should be made to serve first and foremost the needs of the society at large.  A poor country with a mostly rural population, it argued, had more need of general, practical education for many than of highly specialized education for a few.

In [[Cambodia]], a country in which few people have access to formal education (the literacy rate is about 50% as of [[2004]]), the [[Khmer Rouge]] regime (1975&amp;ndash;1979) was generally disdainful of intellectuals and saw many as enemies or traitors (see also: [[Khmer Rouge]] and [[Democratic Kampuchea]]).

==Historical anti-intellectualism==

The [[Roman Republic|Roman]] statesman [[Cato the Elder]]'s public career displayed many traits that today would be considered anti-intellectual.  He vehemently opposed the introduction of [[ancient Greece|Greek]] cultural ideals and models into the Roman republic, believing them to be subversive of traditional plainspokenness and rugged military values.  He urged the [[Roman Senate]] to pass its decree against the newly imported [[Bacchanalia]]n [[mystery religion|mysteries]], which it did in the ''Senatus consultum de Bacchanalibus'' in [[186 BC]].  He urged the deportation of three [[Athens|Athenian]] philosophers, [[Carneades]], [[Diogenes]], and [[Critolaus]], who had been sent to [[Rome]] as [[ambassador]]s from Athens, on the grounds that he found the opinions they expressed were dangerous.

==A loaded term?==

Not surprisingly, intellectuals commonly use allegations of anti-intellectualism as a charge against their critics.  Critics of certain intellectuals in turn argue that "anti-intellectualism" is itself a [[loaded term]].  The term 'intellectual' implies knowledge, wisdom, and intelligence, and thus to be called 'anti-intellectual' can often be perceived as meaning one favours ignorance or [[stupidity]].

Sometimes criticism of intellectuals can take the form of a specific critique of an intellectual's specific field of study or theory.  Not all 'intellectual' theories are correct, and thus an intellectual's beliefs can be disputed without necessarily being against the larger concept of intellectual study.

== See also ==
* [[Anti-science]]
* [[Boffins|Boffin]]
* [[Geek]]
* [[God complex]]
* [[Nerd]]
* [[Philistinism]]
* [[Post-Autistic Economics]]
* ''[[Why Nerds are Unpopular]]''

== References ==

*''Anti-Intellectualism in American Life'', by [[Richard Hofstadter]]: ISBN 0394703170
*Hinton, William. ''Hundred Day War: The Cultural Revolution at Tsinghua University''. New York: New York UP, 1972. ISBN 0853452814.
*[http://www.fas.org/sgp/library/moynihan/appa7.html Moynihan Commission Report, Appendix A, 7. The Cold War, footnote 103] quoted from Robert Warshow, ''The Legacy of the 30’s: Middle-Class Mass Culture and the Intellectuals’ Problem,'' Commentary Magazine (December 1947): 538.

[[Category:Academia]]
[[Category:criticisms|Intellectualism]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>