<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20131116221013|581969921" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="18947899" pageid="18947899" ns="0" title="Anti-intellectualism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2013-11-17T03:03:44Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{POV|date=March 2012}}
[[File:nast-intellect.png|thumb|300px|Intellectual and anti-intellectual: [[Political cartoon]]ist [[Thomas Nast]] contrasts the reedy [[scholar]] with the bovine [[boxing|boxer]], epitomizing the [[populism|populist]] view of reading and study as antithetical to sport and athleticism. Note the disproportionate heads/bodies, with the size of the head representing "mental" ability and intelligence, and the size of the body representing kinesthetic talent and "physical" ability.]]
{{Discrimination sidebar}}
'''Anti-intellectualism''' is hostility towards and mistrust of [[intellect]], [[intellectual]]s, and [[Intellectualism|intellectual pursuits]], usually expressed as the derision of [[education]], [[philosophy]], [[literature]], [[art]], and [[science]], as impractical and contemptible. Alternatively, self-described intellectuals who are alleged to fail to adhere to rigorous standards of scholarship may be described as anti-intellectuals although pseudo-intellectualism is a more commonly, and perhaps more accurately, used description for this phenomenon.

In public discourse, anti-intellectuals are usually perceived and publicly present themselves as champions of the common folk—[[populism|populists]] against political [[elitism]] and [[academic elitism]]—proposing that the educated are a social class detached from the everyday concerns of the majority, and that they dominate [[politics|political]] discourse and [[higher education]].

Because "anti-intellectual" can be [[pejorative]], defining specific cases of anti-intellectualism can be troublesome; one can object to specific facets of intellectualism or the application thereof without being dismissive of intellectual pursuits in general. Moreover, allegations of anti-intellectualism can constitute an [[appeal to authority]] or an [[appeal to ridicule]] that attempts to discredit an opponent rather than specifically addressing his or her arguments.&lt;ref&gt;"It is all too easy for people with more formal schooling to believe they know better than those directly involved [in a particular problem]."It is all too easy for people with more formal schooling to believe they know better than those directly involved [in a particular problem]," Sowell, 2001.&lt;/ref&gt;

Anti-intellectualism is a common facet of [[totalitarian]] dictatorships to oppress political dissent. The [[Nazi]] party's populist rhetoric featured anti-intellectualism as a common motif, including [[Adolf Hitler]]'s political [[polemic]], ''[[Mein Kampf]]''. Perhaps its most extreme political form was during the 1970s in [[Cambodia]] under the rule of [[Pol Pot]] and the [[Khmer Rouge]], when people were killed for being academics or even for merely wearing eyeglasses (as it suggested literacy) in the [[Killing Fields]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.woroni.com.au/articles/features/trial-khmer-rogue&lt;/ref&gt;

==Anti-intellectualism expressed==
===Intellectualism as a social divider===
Anti-intellectualism usually is expressed through declarations of [[other]]ness—the intellectual is "not one of ''us''" and may be dangerous, due to having little empathy for the common folk.&lt;ref name="dumbing of america"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2008/02/15/AR2008021502901.html|title=The Dumbing Of America|last=Jacoby|first=Susan|date=February 17, 2008|work=[[The Washington Post]]|accessdate=16 November 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Historically, this resulted in portrayals of intellectuals as an arrogant class, whom rural communities viewed as "city slickers" indifferent to country ways; such communities tended to [[stereotype]] intellectuals as foreigners or as racial and ethnic minorities who "think differently" than the natives. Religious critics{{who|date=August 2013}} describe intellectuals as prone to mental instability, proposing an organic, causal connection between [[genius]] and madness; they are unlike regular people because of their assumed [[atheism]], and are indecent given their [[sexual ethics|sexual mores]], [[homosexuality]], [[promiscuity|sexual promiscuity]], or [[celibacy]].{{citation needed|date=August 2013}}

===Distrust of intellectuals===
Economist [[Thomas Sowell]] argues for distinctions between unreasonable and reasonable wariness of intellectuals. Defining intellectuals as "people whose occupations deal primarily with ideas" as distinct from those who apply ideas practically, Sowell argues that there can be good cause for distrust of intellectuals. When working in their fields of expertise, intellectuals have increased knowledge. However, when compared to other careers, Sowell suggests intellectuals have few disincentives for speaking outside their expertise, and are less likely to face the consequences of their errors. For example, a physician is judged by effective treatment, yet might face [[malpractice]] lawsuits if he harms a patient. In contrast, a university professor with [[tenure]] is less likely to be judged by the effectiveness of his ideas and less likely to face repercussions for his errors:

&lt;blockquote&gt;By encouraging, or even requiring, students to take stands where they have neither the knowledge nor the intellectual training to seriously examine complex issues, teachers promote the expression of unsubstantiated opinions, the venting of uninformed emotions, and the habit of acting on those opinions and emotions, while ignoring or dismissing opposing views, without having either the intellectual equipment or the personal experience to weigh one view against another in any serious way.&lt;ref name="Sowell2009"&gt;{{cite book|last=Sowell|first=Thomas|title=Intellectuals and Society|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=r601nMi73RQC|accessdate=16 November 2013|year=2009|publisher=Basic Books|isbn=9780465019489}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The source, economist [[Thomas Sowell]], discusses intellectual influence, labeling schoolteachers as what he calls "intelligentsia" who recruit children, beginning in elementary school, to advocate for or against issues as part of "community service" projects, which will later assist them in the college application process. In this manner, intellectuals participate in other areas where they may possess no prior knowledge at all in order to influence public policy issues. The author argues that as a result, they encourage their students to formulate opinions "without any intellectual training or prior knowledge of those issues, making constraints against falsity few or non-existent."&lt;ref&gt;Sowell (2009), p. 296.&lt;/ref&gt;

Similar arguments have been made by others. Historian [[Paul Johnson (writer)|Paul Johnson]]&lt;ref name="Johnson2009"&gt;{{cite book|last=Johnson|first=Paul|title=Intellectuals|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=GTqHpZech0YC&amp;pg=PT1|accessdate=16 November 2013|date=2009-10-13|publisher=HarperCollins|isbn=9780061871474}}&lt;/ref&gt; argued that a close examination of 20th-century history reveals that intellectuals have championed innumerable disastrous public policies, writing, "beware intellectuals. Not merely should they be kept well away from the levers of power, they should also be objects of suspicion when they seek to offer collective advice." Journalist [[Tom Wolfe]]&lt;ref&gt;Wolfe, Tom. (2000). "In the Land of the Rococo Marxists," ''Harper's Monthly'', June 2000.&lt;/ref&gt; described an intellectual as "a person knowledgable in one field who speaks out only in others."

===Criticism of the ''intelligentsia''===
{{expand section|date=August 2013}}
Writer [[George Orwell]] was scathing of what he described as a "[[left-wing]] [[intelligentsia]]" that considered itself more "advanced"&lt;ref name="orwell1"&gt;From a review of Malcolm Muggeridge's ''The Thirties'', in ''New English Weekly'' (25 April 1940)&lt;/ref&gt; and "enlightened"&lt;ref name="orwell1" /&gt; than the ordinary man, and attacked their "shallow self-righteousness."&lt;ref name="orwell1" /&gt;

In his essay ''[[Notes on Nationalism]]'' in May 1945, responding what he considered to be a particularity outlandish claim that had gained currency in intellectual circles casting aspersions on the [[United States]]' motives for entering [[World War II]], he wrote:

&lt;blockquote&gt;I have heard it confidently stated, for instance, that the American troops had been brought to Europe not to fight the Germans but to crush an English revolution. One has to belong to the intelligentsia to believe things like that: no ordinary man could be such a fool.&lt;ref&gt;George Orwell, ''Notes on Nationalism'' (1945)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

===Anti-intellectualism expressed in popular culture===
{{expand section|date=August 2013}}
Intellectualism is portrayed in a highly critical light in an episode of the American [[animation]] series [[The Simpsons]], [[They Saved Lisa's Brain]], which revolves around one of the protagonists joining the local branch of [[Mensa]], and through a bizarre series of events finds itself in complete charge of the local town of [[Springfield (The Simpsons)|Springfield]].

Considering themselves to be intellectually superior to the rest of the townsfolk, they quickly implement a series of ostensibly logical but socially disruptive [[public policies]] that antagonize the rest of the town, with disastrous consequences, and are eventually rebuked by [[Stephen Hawking]], appearing as himself.{{citation needed|date=August 2013}}

==Sources==
===Authoritarianism===
[[File:Benito mussolini28.jpg|thumb|right|Benito Mussolini: ''Il Duce'' of Fascist Italy, a [[police state]].]]
[[Dictator]]s, and their [[dictatorship]] supporters, use anti-intellectualism to gain popular support, by accusing intellectuals of being a socially detached, politically dangerous class who question the extant social norms, who dissent from established opinion, and who reject [[nationalism]], hence they are [[patriotism|unpatriotic]], and thus subversive of the nation. Violent anti-intellectualism is common to the rise and rule of [[authoritarianism|authoritarian]] political movements, such as [[Italian Fascism]], [[Stalinism]] in Russia, [[Nazism]] in Germany, the [[Khmer Rouge]] in [[Cambodia]], and Iranian [[Iranian Revolution|theocracy]].{{citation needed|date=May 2010}}

In the 20th century, intellectuals were systematically demoted or expelled from the power structures, and, occasionally, [[assassination|assassinated]]. In Argentina in 1966, the [[military dictatorship]] of [[Juan Carlos Onganía]] intervened and dislodged many [[faculty (university)|faculties]], leading to a massive [[brain drain]] in an event which was called [[La Noche de los Bastones Largos|The Night of the Long Police Batons]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://fcis.oise.utoronto.ca/~dschugurensky/assignment1/1966uba.html Police repression at the Universidad de Buenos Aires] - [[University of Toronto]]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{es icon}} [http://www.elortiba.org/blargos.html La noche de los bastones largos]&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Biochemistry|biochemist]] [[César Milstein]] reports that when the military usurped Argentine government, they declared: "our country would be put in order, as soon as all the intellectuals who were meddling in the region were expelled". In Brazil, the educator [[Paulo Freire]] was banished for being ignorant, according to the organizers of the ''coup d’ État'' of the moment.&lt;ref name="politicalaffairs1"&gt;[http://www.politicalaffairs.net/article/articleview/4771/1/238 Political Affairs Magazine - Power and the Intellectuals&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Flag of Democratic Kampuchea.svg|thumb|left|Flag of [[Democratic Kampuchea]].]]

Extreme [[ideology|ideological]] dictatorships, such as the [[Khmer Rouge]] regime in [[Kampuchea]] (1975–79), killed potential opponents with more than elementary education. In achieving their Year Zero [[social engineering (political science)|social engineering]] of Cambodia, they assassinated anyone suspected of "involvement in free-market activities". The suspected Cambodian populace included professionals and almost every educated man and woman, city-dwellers, and people with connections to foreign governments. Doctrinally, the [[Maoism|Maoist]] Khmer Rouge designated the farmers as the true [[proletariat]], as the true representatives of the [[working class]], hence the anti-intellectual purge (cf. [[Cultural Revolution|Great Proletarian Cultural Revolution]], 1966–76).

Governmental anti-intellectualism ranges from closing [[Public library|public libraries]] and public schools, to segregating intellectuals in an [[Ivory Tower]] [[ghetto]], to official declarations that intellectuals tend to mental illness, thus facilitating [[psychiatry|psychiatric]] imprisonment, then scapegoating to divert popular discontent from the dictatorship (''[[List of Latin phrases (V)#vide|vide]]'' the [[Soviet Union|USSR]] and [[Kingdom of Italy|Fascist Italy]], cf. [[Antonio Gramsci]]).

Moreover, anti-intellectualism is neither always violent, nor oppressive, because most any social group can exercise contempt for [[intellect]], [[intellectualism]], and [[higher education|education]]. To wit, the [[Uruguay]]an writer [[Jorge Majfud]] said that "this contempt, that arises from a power installed in the social institutions and from the inferiority complex of its actors, is not a property of "underdeveloped" countries. In fact, it is always the critical intellectuals, writers, or artists who head the top-ten lists of 'The Most Stupid of the Stupid' in the country."&lt;ref name="politicalaffairs1"/&gt;

===Populism===
Some forms of populism portray intellectuals as [[elitism|elitists]] possessed of [[rhetoric]]al skills with which they deceive the common folk.&lt;ref&gt;''The New Fontana Dictionary of Modern Thought'', Third Edition (1999) p. 668.&lt;/ref&gt;{{citation needed|date=August 2012}}

[[File:Lysenko in field with wheat.jpg|thumb|left|[[Trofim Lysenko]]]]
'''Education''' – Populism also asserts that [[Academy|academic]] knowledge must be controlled, by "the people", because educators must work within the politics of the interested parties, such as the government, nationally, and with parents' groups, regionally, in establishing the content of the school [[curriculum]].{{citation needed|date=June 2010}} In the US, the common populist action is religiously supported education politics to introduce evangelical Protestant Christian religious interpretations of national history and natural science to school curricula—especially [[creationism]], or variant pseudosciences, such as [[Creation Science|Scientific Creationism]] and [[Intelligent Design]], as factually equal counters to [[evolution]].&lt;ref&gt;"How Christian Were the Founders", Russell Shorto, ''New York Times'' (14 February 2010)&lt;/ref&gt; (see: [[Discovery Institute]])

'''Government Policy''' – In the USSR, in 1948, the Stalinist Central Committee officially imposed the Soviet (national) science of [[Lysenkoism]] upon agriculture. A concept developed by [[Agronomy|Agronomist]] [[Trofim Lysenko]], Lysenkoism was promoted as the realization of Communist ideology: raised by farming parents and with limited formal education, he was lionized as the creator of innovative crop-growing methods based on the outdated concept of [[Lamarckism|Lamarckian inheritance]]. Soviet government suppressed non-Lysenkoist biology, including the dismissal and assassination of scientists such as [[Nikolai Vavilov]]. Ultimately, Lysenkoism yielded poor [[Agriculture|agricultural]] results for the USSR. Moreover, because Lysenkoism was more political than scientific, its fortunes waxed and waned amid Russian Communist Party politics, ending as an officially discredited [[pseudoscience]] upon the fall of [[Nikita Khrushchev]], in 1964.&lt;ref&gt;''The New Fontana Dictionary of Modern Thought'' (1999), A. Bullock and S. Trombley, eds., pp. 492–3&lt;/ref&gt;

==Educational anti-intellectualism==
[[Education]] is often associated with charges of anti-intellectualism from a variety of critics who disagree over the meaning, goals and [[curriculum|curricula]] of [[public education]]. Historically, such intellectual disagreements have manifested as ''[[Kulturkampf]]'' in Bismarck's Germany and [[Culture War]]s in the contemporary US.

===Grammar school===
In the 2004 ''[[New York Times]]'' newspaper article "When Every Child is Good Enough", [[John Tierney (journalist)|John Tierney]] reported that [[conservatism|conservative]] parents believe that US primary and secondary schools over-emphasize [[equality of outcome]]&lt;ref&gt;John Tierney, [http://www.nytimes.com/2004/11/21/weekinreview/21tier.html "When Every Child Is Good Enough"], ''The New York Times'', 21 November 2004&lt;/ref&gt; to the detriment of their children's individual (unequal) achievements. A literary example of that contention is the [[social science fiction|science fiction]] short story '[[Harrison Bergeron]]' (1961), by [[Kurt Vonnegut]], wherein the government's [[Harrison Bergeron|Handicapper General]] imposes equality upon the eponymous hero, lest his existence—as the smartest, handsomest, most athletic boy in the world—hurt the feelings of the mediocre [[populism|popular]] majority, (''viz.'' the over-simplification, the [[dumbing down]], of [[curriculum|curricula]]).

===University===
In the [[English-speaking world]], especially in the US, critics like [[David Horowitz]] (''viz.'' the [[David Horowitz Freedom Center]]), [[William John Bennett|William Bennett]], an ex-US secretary of education, and [[paleoconservatism|paleoconservative activist]] [[Patrick Buchanan]], criticize schools and universities as '[[Intellectualism|intellectualist]]'.{{citation needed|date=February 2010}}

In his book ''The Campus Wars''&lt;ref&gt;Searle, John R. (1971). [http://www.ditext.com/searle/campus/2.html The Campus Wars, Chapter 2: The Students], URL retrieved 14 June 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; about the widespread student protests of the late 1960s, philosopher [[John Searle]] wrote:

:the two most salient traits of the radical movement are its anti-intellectualism and its hostility to the university as an institution. [...] Intellectuals by definition are people who take ideas seriously for their own sake. Whether or not a theory is true or false is important to them independently of any practical applications it may have. [Intellectuals] have, as Richard Hofstadter has pointed out, an attitude to ideas that is at once playful and pious. But in the radical movement, the intellectual ideal of knowledge for its own sake is rejected. Knowledge is seen as valuable only as a basis for action, and it is not even very valuable there. Far more important than what one knows is how one feels.

In 1972, sociologist [[Stanislav Andreski]]&lt;ref&gt;Stanislav Andreski, ''The Social Sciences as Sorcery''. 1972, The University of California Press&lt;/ref&gt; warned readers of academic works to be wary of [[appeals to authority]] when academics make questionable claims, writing, "do not be impressed by the imprint of a famous publishing house or the volume of an author's publications. [...] Remember that the publishers want to keep the printing presses busy and do not object to nonsense if it can be sold."

Critics have alleged that much of the prevailing philosophy in American academia (i.e., postmodernism, poststructuralism, relativism) are anti-intellectual: "The displacement of the idea that facts and evidence matter by the idea that everything boils down to subjective interests and perspectives is—second only to American political campaigns—the most prominent and pernicious manifestation of anti-intellectualism in our time."&lt;ref&gt;[[Larry Laudan]], ''Science and Relativism: Some Key Controversies in the Philosophy of Science'' (1990), University of Chicago Press&lt;/ref&gt;

In the notorious [[Sokal Hoax]] of the 1990s, physicist [[Alan Sokal]] submitted a deliberately preposterous paper to Duke University's ''Social Texts'' journal to test if, as he later wrote, a leading "culture studies" periodical would "publish an article liberally salted with nonsense if (a) it sounded good and (b) it flattered the editors' ideological preconceptions."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.physics.nyu.edu/faculty/sokal/lingua_franca_v4/lingua_franca_v4.html|title=A Physicist Experiments With Cultural Studies|accessdate=April 3, 2007|last=Sokal|first=Alan D.|authorlink=Alan Sokal|work=[[Lingua Franca (magazine)|Lingua Franca]]|year=1996|month=May|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20070326152500/http://www.physics.nyu.edu/faculty/sokal/lingua_franca_v4/lingua_franca_v4.html|archivedate=26 March 2007 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;|deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Social Texts'' published the paper, seemingly without noting any of the paper's abundant mathematical and scientific errors, leading Sokal to declare that "my little experiment demonstrate[s], at the very least, that some fashionable sectors of the American academic Left have been getting intellectually lazy."

In a 1995 interview, social critic [[Camille Paglia]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://privat.ub.uib.no/BUBSY/playboy.htm privat.ub.uib.no]&lt;/ref&gt; described academics (including herself) as "a parasitic class," arguing that during widespread social disruption "the only thing holding this culture together will be masculine men of the working class. The cultural elite—women and men—will be pleading for the plumbers and the construction workers."

==Youth culture==
Critics have suggested that contemporary [[Youth subculture|youth culture]] is a [[commerce|commercial]] form of anti-intellectualism orienting adherents to [[consumerism]]. The ''[[Frontline (U.S. TV series)|Frontline]]'' public affairs television series documentary [http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/pages/frontline/shows/cool/etc/script.html ''The Merchants of Cool''](2001) describes how the [[advertising]] business transformed [[adolescence|adolescents']] language, thought, and action ([[clique]]s, [[fashion]], [[fads]]) into [[commodity|commodities]], and thus engendered a [[generation]] of intellectually disengaged Americans uninterested in progressing to [[adulthood]].

The US youth [[subculture]] originated from the post-[[World War II]] economic prosperity allowing adolescents to work and have a [[Disposable and discretionary income|discretionary income]]—whilst still dependent upon parents. In turn, scholars{{citation needed|date=June 2010}} argue that the newfound economic power of adolescents allowed business to sell them [[popularity]]—an [[Identity (social science)|identity]] as a ''young'' person—something that once was not for sale, but self-created; to wit, the computer programmer and [[blog]] writer [[Paul Graham (computer programmer)|Paul Graham]] likened youth culture to an occupation permitting little time for education and intellectual interests.&lt;ref&gt;Graham P (February 2003). [http://paulgraham.com/nerds.html "Why Nerds are Unpopular".]&lt;/ref&gt;

==American anti-intellectualism==
[[File:JohnCotton.jpg|right|thumb|[[John Cotton (puritan)|John Cotton]] (1585–1652)]]

===17th century===
In ''The Powring Out of the Seven Vials'' (1642), the [[Puritan]] [[John Cotton (puritan)|John Cotton]] wrote that 'the more learned and witty you bee, the more fit to act for [[Satan]] will you bee. ... Take off the fond doting ... upon the learning of the [[Society of Jesus|Jesuites]], and the glorie of the Episcopacy, and the brave estates of the Prelates. I say bee not deceived by these pompes, empty shewes, and faire representations of goodly condition before the eyes of flesh and blood, bee not taken with the applause of these persons.'&lt;ref name="Hofstadter, Richard 1962 p.46"&gt;Hofstadter, Richard ''Anti-intellectualism in American Life'' (1962), p. 46.&lt;/ref&gt; Not every Puritan concurred with Cotton's contempt for [[Secularism|secular]] education; some founded universities such as [[Harvard University|Harvard]], [[Yale University|Yale]], and [[Dartmouth College|Dartmouth]].

Economist Thomas Sowell&lt;ref&gt;Sowell, Thomas. (2001) ''The Quest for Cosmic Justice''. Simon and Schuster, 2001, ISBN 978-0-7432-1507-7, p. 187.&lt;/ref&gt; argues that American anti-intellectualism can be traced to the early Colonial era, and that wariness of the educated upper-classes is understandable given that America was built, in large part, by people fleeing persecution and brutality at the hands of the educated upper classes. Additionally, rather few intellectuals possessed the practical hands-on skills required to survive in the New World, leading to a deeply rooted suspicion of those who may appear to specialize in "verbal virtuosity" rather than tangible, measurable products or services:

&lt;blockquote&gt;From its colonial beginnings, American society was a "decapitated" society—largely lacking the topmost social layers of European society. The highest elites and the titled aristocracies had little reason to risk their lives crossing the Atlantic and then face the perils of pioneering. Most of the white population of colonial America arrived as [[indentured servant]]s and the black population as slaves. Later waves of immigrants were disproportionately [[peasant]]s and [[proletarian]]s, even when they came from Western Europe [...] The rise of American society to pre-eminence as an economic, political and military power was thus the triumph of the common man and a slap across the face to the presumptions of the arrogant, whether an elite of blood or books.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The source, Thomas Sowell, describes the effect the American Revolution had on the development of American government, as established by the Constitution and Bill of Rights. In his opinion, the tendency to "disregard" the impartiality of the law depending upon "who you are" rather than what the author describes as the impartiality of the "supremacy of the law" conflicts with the American creed of the common man. According to Sowell, this fundamental right uniquely distinguishes the American character, forged by "the beaten men of beaten races," from that of the arrogant and privileged elites of the European aristocracy.&lt;ref&gt;Sowell (2001), p. 187&lt;/ref&gt;

===19th century===
In the history of American anti-intellectualism, modern scholars{{citation needed|date=June 2010}} suggest that 19th-century [[popular culture]] is important, because, when most of the populace lived a [[rural]] life of [[manual labour]] and [[agriculture|agricultural]] work, a 'bookish' education, concerned with the Græco-Roman [[classics]], was perceived as of impractical value, ergo [[Profit (economics)|unprofitable]]—yet Americans, generally, were [[literacy|literate]] and read [[William Shakespeare|Shakespeare]] for pleasure—thus, the [[Ideal (ethics)|ideal]] "American" man was technically skilled and successful in his [[trade]], ergo a productive member of society.{{citation needed|date=November 2009}} Culturally, the ideal American was a self-made man whose knowledge derived from life-experience, not an intellectual man, whose knowledge derived from books, formal education, and academic study; thus, in ''The New Purchase, or Seven and a Half Years in the Far West'' (1843), the Reverend Bayard R. Hall, A.M., said about frontier [[Indiana]]:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
"We always preferred an ignorant bad man to a talented one, and, hence, attempts were usually made to ruin the [[morality|moral]] character of a smart candidate; since, unhappily, [[Intellectual giftedness|smartness]] and wickedness were supposed to be generally coupled, and [like-wise] incompetence and goodness."&lt;ref name="Hofstadter, Richard 1962 p.46"/&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Yet, the [[egghead]]'s worldly redemption was possible if he embraced [[mainstream]] [[mores]]; thus, in the fiction of [[O. Henry]], a character noted that once an East Coast [[university]] graduate 'gets over' his intellectual vanity—no longer thinks himself better than others—he makes just as good a [[cowboy]] as any other young man, despite his counterpart being the slow-witted naïf of good heart, a pop culture [[stereotype]] from stage shows.

===20th and 21st centuries===
Charges of anti-intellectualism have been made against a variety of movements and schools of thought:

[[File:Robert McNamara at a cabinet meeting, 22 Nov 1967.jpg|thumb|right|[[Robert McNamara]]]]
* '''Anti-war protests''' – The 1960s–70s anti-war movement protesting the ten-year US–[[Vietnam War]] (1963–1973), demonstrated its anti-intellectual leanings against US defence secretary [[Robert McNamara]]. They rallied against the war's increasing casualties, and the intellectual justification for the war, which was becoming seemingly impossible to win. McNamara's appearance as an intellectual, justifying warfare with an apparent disregard for the lives of American soldiers had become very unpopular. The anti-intellectualism in this movement may have been a counter to the perceived 'intellectual' rationalisation of the war by McNamara and others.

: Marxist intellectual [[Theodor Adorno]] criticised such [[left-wing]] anti-intellectualism as "actionism," a kind of ineffective "pseudo-activity" which serves to deflect attention from the difficulty of genuinely changing the world, a difficulty which critical thought would make clear.&lt;ref&gt;Adorno, Theodor W. "Resignation", in ''Critical Models: Interventions and Catchwords'', translated by Henry W. Pickford (New York: Columbia University Press, 1998)&lt;/ref&gt;

: However, publications such as ''[[The Pentagon Papers]]'' (1971) had made the war very unpopular with intellectuals and anti-intellectuals alike, and the movement gained much popular support, culminating in the [[Case Church Amendment]] and the eventual exit of American troops from the war in 1973.
* '''Political''' – The writer [[Robert Warshow]] proposed that the [[Communist Party USA|Communist Party of the USA]] was central to United States intellectual life during the 1930s:

: "For most American intellectuals, the [[Communism|Communist]] movement of the 1930s was a crucial experience. In Europe, where the [Communist] movement was at once more serious and more popular, it was still only one current in intellectual life; the Communists could never completely set the tone of thinking. ... But in this country there was a time when virtually all intellectual vitality was derived, in one way or another, from the Communist party. If you were not somewhere within the party's wide orbit, then you were likely to be in the opposition, which meant that much of your thought and energy had to be devoted to maintaining yourself in opposition."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fas.org/sgp/library/moynihan/appa7.html Report of the Commission on Protecting and Reducing Government Secrecy.] Moynihan Commission Report, quoted from Robert Warshow, "The Legacy of the 30's: Middle-Class Mass Culture and the Intellectuals' Problem", ''Commentary'' magazine (December 1947): 538, footnote 103.&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''Populist''' – While campaigning prior to [[United States presidential election, 2012|United States presidential election of 2012]], [[Republican Party presidential candidates, 2012|GOP candidate]] [[Rick Santorum]] was accused of populist anti-intellectualism by some critics after describing [[Barack Obama|President Obama]] as a "snob" for wanting all Americans to pursue higher education, and suggesting that institutions of higher learning were centers of [[Modern liberalism in the United States|liberal]] [[indoctrination]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://seattletimes.nwsource.com/html/opinion/2017651246_sirota03.html Opposite of snobbery: Challenging Santorum on funding college.]&lt;/ref&gt;

==European anti-intellectualism==
[[File:Marco Porcio Caton Major.jpg|thumb|[[Cato the Elder]]]]

===Greco–Roman world===
In the [[Roman Republic]] (509–27 BC), the public career of the statesman [[Cato the Elder]] displayed traits that some modern observers argue{{citation needed|date=June 2010}} would be considered anti-intellectual in the contemporary world. He vehemently opposed the introduction of [[ancient Greece|Greek]] culture to the Roman republic, believing them subversive of traditional Roman military values and plainspokenness. In 186 BC, he convinced the [[Roman Senate|Senate]] to decree against the [[Bacchanalia]], then a recently imported [[mystery religion]], they agreed with him via the ''Senatus consultum de Bacchanalibus''. He urged the deportation of three [[Athens|Athenian]] philosophers, [[Carneades]], [[Diogenes the Stoic]], and [[Critolaus]], in [[Rome]] as Athenian [[ambassador]]s, because he believed their opinions dangerous to the Republic.

===Soviet Union===
In the first decade after the [[Russian Revolution of 1917]], the [[Bolsheviks]] suspected the [[Tsarism|Tsarist]] [[intelligentsia]] as potentially traitorous of the [[proletariat]], thus, the initial [[Soviet Union|Soviet]] government comprised men and women without much formal education. [[Vladimir Lenin|Lenin]] derided the old intelligentsia with the expression (roughly translated): 'We ain't completed no academies' (мы академиев не кончали).&lt;ref&gt;[http://wwi.lib.byu.edu/index.php/Intelligentsia_/_Lenin_to_Gorky Intelligentsia / Lenin to Gorky]&lt;/ref&gt; Moreover, the deposed propertied classes were termed ''[[Lishentsy]]'' ("the disenfranchised"), whose children were excluded from education; eventually, some 200 Tsarist intellectuals were deported to Germany on [[Philosophers' ships]] in 1922; others were deported to Latvia and to Turkey in 1923.

During the [[revolution]]ary period, the pragmatic Bolsheviks employed "bourgeois experts" to manage the economy, industry, and agriculture, and so learn from them. After the [[Russian Civil War]] (1917–23), to achieve socialism, the [[Soviet Union|USSR]] (1922–91) emphasised literacy and education in service to modernising the country via an educated [[working class]] [[intelligentsia]], rather than an [[Ivory Tower]] intelligentsia. During the 1930s and the 1950s, [[Joseph Stalin]] replaced Lenin's intelligentsia with a "communist" intelligentsia, loyal to him and with a specifically Soviet world view, thereby producing the most egregious examples of Soviet anti-intellectualism—the [[pseudoscience|pseudoscientific]] theories of [[Lysenkoism]] and [[Japhetic theory]], most damaging to [[biology]] and [[linguistics]] in that country, by subordinating [[science]] to a dogmatic interpretation of [[Marxism]].

===Fascism===
[[File:Giovanni Gentile.png|thumb|left|Active philosopher: [[Giovanni Gentile]], intellectual father of [[Italian Fascism]].]]

The [[Actual Idealism|idealist]] philosopher [[Giovanni Gentile]] established the intellectual basis of [[Fascism|Fascist]] ideology with the ''autoctisi'' (self-realisation) via concrete thinking that distinguished between the good (active) intellectual and the bad (passive) intellectual:

{{quote|Fascism combats ... not intelligence, but intellectualism... which is... a sickness of the intellect... not a consequence of its abuse, because the intellect cannot be used too much... it derives from the false belief that one can segregate oneself from life.|Giovanni Gentile|addressing a Congress of Fascist Culture, Bologna, 30 March 1925}}

To counter the "passive intellectual" who used his or her intellect abstractly, and therefore was "decadent", he proposed the "concrete thinking" of the active intellectual who applied intellect as [[Praxis (process)|praxis]]—a "man of action", like Fascist [[Benito Mussolini]], versus the decadent [[Communism|Communist]] [[intellectual]] [[Antonio Gramsci]]. The passive intellectual stagnates intellect by objectifying ideas, thus establishing them as objects. Hence the [[Fascism|Fascist]] rejection of materialist [[logic]], because it relies upon ''[[a priori and a posteriori|a priori]]'' principles improperly counter-changed with ''a posteriori'' ones that are irrelevant to the matter-in-hand in deciding whether or not to act.

In the praxis of Gentile's concrete thinking criteria, such consideration of the ''a priori'' toward the properly ''a posteriori'' constitutes ''impractical'', decadent intellectualism. Moreover, this fascist philosophy occurred parallel to [[Actual Idealism]], his philosophic system; he opposed [[intellectualism]] for its being disconnected from the active intelligence that gets things done, i.e. thought is killed when its constituent parts are labelled, and thus rendered as discrete entities.&lt;ref&gt;Gentile, Giovanni, ''Origins and Doctrine of Fascism (with selections from other works)'', A. James Gregor, ed., pp. 22–23, 33, 65–66&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''The Oxford Guide to Philosophy'' (2005), Ted Honderich, ed., p. 332.&lt;/ref&gt;

Related to this, is the confrontation between the Spanish [[Franquism|franquist]] General, [[José Millán Astray#Confrontation with Unamuno|Millán Astray]], and the writer [[Miguel de Unamuno]] during the ''[[Dia de la Raza]]'' celebration at the [[University of Salamanca]], in 1936, during the [[Spanish Civil War]]. The General exclaimed: ''¡Muera la inteligencia! ¡Viva la Muerte!'' ("Death to intelligence! Long live death!"); the Falangists applauded.{{Citation needed|date=July 2013}}

==Asian anti-intellectualism==
[[File:Mao Zedong portrait.jpg|thumb|right|Chairman [[Mao Zedong]]]]

===China===
'''Imperial China''' – [[Qin Shi Huang]] (246–21 BC), the first Emperor of unified China, consolidated political thought, and power, by suppressing [[freedom of speech]] at the suggestion of Chancellor [[Li Si]], who justified such anti-intellectualism by accusing the [[intelligentsia]] of falsely praising the emperor, and of dissenting through libel. From 213 to 206 BC, the works of the [[Hundred Schools of Thought]] were incinerated, especially the ''Shi Jing'' ([[Classic of Poetry]], c. 1000 BC) and the ''Shujing'' ([[Classic of History]], c. 6th century BC). The exceptions were books by Qin historians, and books of [[Legalism (Chinese philosophy)|Legalism]], an early type of [[totalitarianism]]—and the Chancellor's philosophic school, (see the [[Burning of books and burying of scholars]]).

'''People's Republic of China''' – The [[Cultural Revolution]] was a politically violent decade (1966–76) of wide-ranging [[social engineering (political science)|social engineering]] of the [[People's Republic of China]] by its leader Chairman [[Mao Zedong|Mao]]. After several national policy failures, Mao, to regain public prestige and control of the [[Communist Party of China]] (CCP), on 16 May, announced that the Party and Chinese society were permeated with liberal bourgeois elements who meant to restore [[capitalism]] to China, and that said people could only be removed with post–[[Chinese Revolution (1949)|Revolutionary]] [[class struggle]]. To that effect, China's youth nationally organised into [[Red Guards (China)|Red Guards]], paramilitaries hunting the liberal bourgeois elements subverting the CCP and Chinese society. The Red Guards acted nationally, purging the country, the military, urban workers, and the leaders of the CCP, until there remained no one politically dangerous to Mao. Three years later, in 1969, Mao declared the Cultural Revolution ended; yet the political intrigues continued until 1976, concluding with the arrest of the [[Gang of Four]], the ''de facto'' end of the Cultural Revolution.

===Democratic Kampuchea===
When the Communist Party of Cambodia, the [[Khmer Rouge]] (1951–81), established their regime as [[Democratic Kampuchea]] (1975–1979) in [[Cambodia]], their anti-intellectualism idealised the country and demonised the cities to establish [[agrarian socialism]], thus, they emptied cities to purge the [[Khmer people|Khmer]] nation of every [[treason|traitor]], [[enemy of the state]], and [[intellectual]], often symbolised by eyeglasses (see the [[Killing Fields]]).

==See also==
* [[Elitism#Anti-elitism|Anti-elitism]]
* [[Antiscience]]
* [[Dumbing down]]
* [[Nerd]], an anti-intellectual stereotype
* [[Oblomov#Oblomovism|Oblomovism]], a term derived from the novel ''[[Oblomov]]'', written by Russian author [[Ivan Goncharov]]
* [[Obscurantism]]
* [[Philistinism]]
* [[Poshlost]]
* [[Postmodernism]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
* ''The Anti-Intellectual Presidency: The Decline of Presidential Rhetoric from George Washington to George W. Bush'', by Elvin T. Lim: New York: Oxford University Press. ISBN 978-0-19-534264-2.
* ''[[Anti-intellectualism in American Life]]'', by [[Richard Hofstadter]]: ISBN 978-0-394-70317-6
* ''Anti-Intellectualism in American Media,'' by Dane S. Claussen: New York: Peter Lang Publishing, 2004. ISBN 978-0-8204-5721-5
* ''Evening Chats in Beijing: Probing China's Predicament,'' by Perry Link: New York, London: W.W. Norton &amp; Company, 1991. ISBN 978-0-393-31065-8
* Hinton, William. ''Hundred Day War: The Cultural Revolution at Tsinghua University''. New York: New York UP, 1972. ISBN 978-0-85345-281-2.
* [http://www.fas.org/sgp/library/moynihan/appa7.html Moynihan Commission Report, Appendix A, 7. The Cold War, footnote 103] quoted from Robert Warshow, ''The Legacy of the 30's: Middle-Class Mass Culture and the Intellectuals' Problem,'' Commentary Magazine (December 1947): 538.
* [http://www.leftbusinessobserver.com/Action.html "Action Will be Taken" Left Anti-Intellectualism and its Discontents] by Liza Featherstone, Doug Henwood, and Christian Parenti (Left Business Observer)

{{DEFAULTSORT:Anti-Intellectualism}}
[[Category:Academia]]
[[Category:Anti-intellectualism| ]]
[[Category:Social theories]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>