<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20161114153258|749477698" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="18947899" pageid="18947899" ns="0" title="Anti-intellectualism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2016-11-23T02:40:14Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{refimprove|date=July 2014}}
[[File:nast-intellect.png|thumb|300px|Intellectual and anti-intellectual: [[Political cartoon]]ist [[Thomas Nast]] contrasts the reedy [[scholar]] with the bovine [[boxing|boxer]], epitomizing the [[populism|populist]] view of reading and study as antithetical to sport and athleticism. Note the disproportionate heads and bodies, with the size of the head representing "mental" ability and intelligence, and the size of the body representing kinesthetic talent and "physical" ability.]]
{{Discrimination sidebar}}
'''Anti-intellectualism''' is hostility towards and mistrust of [[intellect]], [[intellectual]]s, and [[Intellectualism|intellectual pursuits]], usually expressed as the derision of [[education]], [[philosophy]], [[literature]], [[art]], and [[science]], as impractical and contemptible. Alternatively, self-described intellectuals who are alleged to fail to adhere to rigorous standards of scholarship may be described as anti-intellectuals although pseudo-intellectualism is a more commonly, and perhaps more accurately, used description for this phenomenon.

In public discourse, anti-intellectuals are usually perceived and publicly present themselves as champions of the common folk—[[populism|populists]] against political [[elitism]] and [[academic elitism]]—proposing that the educated are a social class detached from the everyday concerns of the majority, and that they dominate [[politics|political]] discourse and [[higher education]].

Because "anti-intellectual" can be [[pejorative]], defining specific cases of anti-intellectualism can be troublesome; one can object to specific facets of intellectualism or the application thereof without being dismissive of intellectual pursuits in general. Moreover, allegations of anti-intellectualism can constitute an [[appeal to authority]] or an [[appeal to ridicule]] that attempts to discredit an opponent rather than specifically addressing his or her arguments.&lt;ref&gt;"It is all too easy for people with more formal schooling to believe they know better than those directly involved [in a particular problem]," Sowell, 2001.{{full citation needed|date=November 2016|reason=quote seems not to be contained in 2001 Cosmic Justice book}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Anti-intellectualism has been used by [[totalitarian]] [[Dictatorship|dictatorships]] to oppress [[political dissent]].{{citation needed|date=May 2015}} Perhaps its most extreme political form was during the 1970s in [[Cambodia]] under the rule of [[Pol Pot]] and the [[Khmer Rouge]], when people were killed for being academics or even for merely wearing eyeglasses (as it suggested literacy) in the [[Killing Fields]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.woroni.com.au/articles/features/trial-khmer-rogue |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120422004018/http://www.woroni.com.au/articles/features/trial-khmer-rogue |archivedate=2012-04-22 |title=Trial of the Khmer Rogue}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{citation needed|date=May 2015}}

During the [[Spanish Civil War]] and the following dictatorship, General [[Francisco Franco]]'s civilian repression, the [[White Terror (Spain)|White Terror]] campaign, killed an estimated 200,000 civilians, heavily targeting writers, artists, teachers and professors.

==Distrust of intellectuals==
Economist [[Thomas Sowell]] argues for distinctions between unreasonable and reasonable wariness of intellectuals. Defining intellectuals as "people whose occupations deal primarily with ideas" as distinct from those who apply ideas practically, Sowell argues that there can be good cause for distrust of intellectuals. When working in their fields of expertise, intellectuals have increased knowledge. However, when compared to other careers, Sowell suggests intellectuals have few disincentives for speaking outside their expertise, and are less likely to face the consequences of their errors. For example, a physician is judged by effective treatment, yet might face [[malpractice]] lawsuits if he harms a patient. In contrast, a university professor with [[tenure]] is less likely to be judged by the effectiveness of his ideas and less likely to face repercussions for his errors:

&lt;blockquote&gt;By encouraging, or even requiring, students to take stands where they have neither the knowledge nor the intellectual training to seriously examine complex issues, teachers promote the expression of unsubstantiated opinions, the venting of uninformed emotions, and the habit of acting on those opinions and emotions, while ignoring or dismissing opposing views, without having either the intellectual equipment or the personal experience to weigh one view against another in any serious way.&lt;ref name="Sowell2009"&gt;{{cite book|last=Sowell|first=Thomas|title=Intellectuals and Society|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=r601nMi73RQC|accessdate=16 November 2013|year=2009|publisher=Basic Books|isbn=9780465019489}}{{pages needed|date=November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Sowell discusses intellectual influence, labeling schoolteachers as what he calls "intelligentsia" who recruit children, beginning in elementary school, to advocate for or against issues as part of "community service" projects, which will later assist them in the college application process. In this manner, intellectuals participate in other areas where they may possess no prior knowledge at all in order to influence public policy issues. The author argues that as a result, they encourage their students to formulate opinions "without any intellectual training or prior knowledge of those issues, making constraints against falsity few or non-existent."&lt;ref&gt;Sowell (2009), p. 296.&lt;/ref&gt;

Similar arguments have been made by others. Historian [[Paul Johnson (writer)|Paul Johnson]]&lt;ref name="Johnson2009"&gt;{{cite book|last=Johnson|first=Paul|title=Intellectuals|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=GTqHpZech0YC&amp;pg=PT1|accessdate=16 November 2013|date=2009-10-13|publisher=HarperCollins|isbn=9780061871474}}&lt;/ref&gt; argued that a close examination of 20th-century history reveals that intellectuals have championed innumerable disastrous public policies, writing, "beware intellectuals. Not merely should they be kept well away from the levers of power, they should also be objects of suspicion when they seek to offer collective advice." Journalist [[Tom Wolfe]]&lt;ref&gt;Wolfe, Tom. (2000). "In the Land of the Rococo Marxists," ''Harper's Monthly'', June 2000.&lt;/ref&gt; described an intellectual as "a person knowledgeable in one field who speaks out only in others."

Such views form the basis of an episode of the American [[animation]] series ''[[The Simpsons]]'', "[[They Saved Lisa's Brain]]", in which one of the protagonists joins the local branch of [[Mensa International|Mensa]] that through a bizarre series of events, subsequently finds itself in complete charge of the local town of [[Springfield (The Simpsons)|Springfield]].  Considering themselves to be intellectually superior to the rest of the townsfolk, they high-handedly implement a series of ostensibly logical but socially disruptive public policies that antagonize the rest of the town, with disastrous consequences, and are eventually rebuked by [[Stephen Hawking]] who appeared as himself.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0701272/fullcredits?ref_=tt_ov_st_sm&lt;/ref&gt;

==Authoritarianism==
In the 20th century, intellectuals were systematically demoted or expelled from the power structures, and, occasionally, [[assassination|assassinated]]. {{Where|date=August 2015}} In Argentina in 1966, the [[military dictatorship]] of [[Juan Carlos Onganía]] intervened and dislodged many [[faculty (university)|faculties]], leading to a massive [[brain drain]] in an event which was called [[La Noche de los Bastones Largos|The Night of the Long Police Batons]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://fcis.oise.utoronto.ca/~dschugurensky/assignment1/1966uba.html Police repression at the Universidad de Buenos Aires] - [[University of Toronto]]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{es icon}} [http://www.elortiba.org/blargos.html La noche de los bastones largos] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100514124954/http://www.elortiba.org/blargos.html |date=May 14, 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Biochemistry|biochemist]] [[César Milstein]] reports that when the military usurped Argentine government, they declared: "our country would be put in order, as soon as all the intellectuals who were meddling in the region were expelled". In Brazil, the educator [[Paulo Freire]] was banished for being ignorant, according to the organizers of the ''coup d’ État'' of the moment.&lt;ref name="politicalaffairs1"&gt;[http://www.politicalaffairs.net/article/articleview/4771/1/238 Political Affairs Magazine - Power and the Intellectuals&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070927003056/http://www.politicalaffairs.net/article/articleview/4771/1/238 |date=September 27, 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Flag of Democratic Kampuchea.svg|thumb|left|Flag of [[Democratic Kampuchea]].]]

Extreme [[ideology|ideological]] dictatorships, such as the [[Khmer Rouge]] regime in [[Kampuchea]] (1975–79), killed potential opponents with more than elementary education. In achieving their [[Year Zero (political notion)|Year Zero]] [[social engineering (political science)|social engineering]] of Cambodia, they assassinated anyone suspected of "involvement in free-market activities". The suspected Cambodian populace included professionals and almost every educated man and woman, city-dwellers, and people with connections to foreign governments. Doctrinally, the Khmer Rouge designated the farmers as the true [[proletariat]], as the true representatives of the [[working class]], hence the anti-intellectual purge.

Governmental anti-intellectualism ranges from closing [[Public library|public libraries]] and public schools, to segregating intellectuals in an [[Ivory Tower]] [[ghetto]], to official declarations that intellectuals tend to mental illness, thus facilitating [[psychiatry|psychiatric]] imprisonment, then scapegoating to divert popular discontent from the dictatorship (see the [[Kingdom of Italy|Fascist Italy]], cf. [[Antonio Gramsci]]).

Moreover, anti-intellectualism is neither always violent, nor oppressive, because most any social group can exercise contempt for [[intellect]], [[intellectualism]], and [[higher education|education]]. To wit, the [[Uruguay]]an writer [[Jorge Majfud]] said that "this contempt, that arises from a power installed in the social institutions and from the inferiority complex of its actors, is not a property of "underdeveloped" countries. In fact, it is always the critical intellectuals, writers, or artists who head the top-ten lists of 'The Most Stupid of the Stupid' in the country."&lt;ref name="politicalaffairs1"/&gt;

==Educational anti-intellectualism==
In the [[English-speaking world]], especially in the US, critics like [[David Horowitz]] (''viz.'' the [[David Horowitz Freedom Center]]), [[William John Bennett|William Bennett]], an ex-US secretary of education, and [[paleoconservatism|paleoconservative activist]] [[Patrick Buchanan]], criticize schools and universities as '[[Intellectualism|intellectualist]]'.{{citation needed|date=February 2010}}

In his book ''The Campus Wars''&lt;ref&gt;Searle, John R. (1971). [http://www.ditext.com/searle/campus/2.html The Campus Wars, Chapter 2: The Students], URL retrieved 14 June 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; about the widespread student protests of the late 1960s, philosopher [[John Searle]] wrote:

:the two most salient traits of the radical movement are its anti-intellectualism and its hostility to the university as an institution. [...] Intellectuals by definition are people who take ideas seriously for their own sake. Whether or not a theory is true or false is important to them independently of any practical applications it may have. [Intellectuals] have, as Richard Hofstadter has pointed out, an attitude to ideas that is at once playful and pious. But in the radical movement, the intellectual ideal of knowledge for its own sake is rejected. Knowledge is seen as valuable only as a basis for action, and it is not even very valuable there. Far more important than what one knows is how one feels.

In 1972, sociologist [[Stanislav Andreski]]&lt;ref&gt;Stanislav Andreski, ''The Social Sciences as Sorcery''. 1972, The University of California Press&lt;/ref&gt; warned readers of academic works to be wary of [[appeals to authority]] when academics make questionable claims, writing, "do not be impressed by the imprint of a famous publishing house or the volume of an author's publications. [...] Remember that the publishers want to keep the printing presses busy and do not object to nonsense if it can be sold."

Critics have alleged that much of the prevailing philosophy in American academia (i.e., postmodernism and poststructuralism) are anti-intellectual: "The displacement of the idea that facts and evidence matter by the idea that everything boils down to subjective interests and perspectives is—second only to American political campaigns—the most prominent and pernicious manifestation of anti-intellectualism in our time."&lt;ref&gt;[[Larry Laudan]], ''Science and Relativism: Some Key Controversies in the Philosophy of Science'' (1990), University of Chicago Press&lt;/ref&gt;

In the notorious [[Sokal Hoax]] of the 1990s, physicist [[Alan Sokal]] submitted a deliberately preposterous paper to Duke University's ''Social Text'' journal to test if, as he later wrote, a leading "culture studies" periodical would "publish an article liberally salted with nonsense if (a) it sounded good and (b) it flattered the editors' ideological preconceptions."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.physics.nyu.edu/faculty/sokal/lingua_franca_v4/lingua_franca_v4.html|title=A Physicist Experiments With Cultural Studies|accessdate=April 3, 2007|last=Sokal|first=Alan D.|authorlink=Alan Sokal|work=[[Lingua Franca (magazine)|Lingua Franca]]|date=May 1996|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070326152500/http://www.physics.nyu.edu/faculty/sokal/lingua_franca_v4/lingua_franca_v4.html|archivedate=26 March 2007 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;|deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Social Text'' published the paper, seemingly without noting any of the paper's abundant mathematical and scientific errors, leading Sokal to declare that "my little experiment demonstrate[s], at the very least, that some fashionable sectors of the American academic Left have been getting intellectually lazy."

In a 1995 interview, social critic [[Camille Paglia]]&lt;ref&gt;http://endingmaleviolence.blogspot.co.nz/2010/02/playboy-interview-may-1995-camille.html&lt;/ref&gt; described the "cultural elite" (including herself) as "a parasitic class," arguing that during widespread social disruption "the only thing holding this culture together will be masculine men of the working class. The cultural elite—women and men—will be pleading for the plumbers and the construction workers."

==In the United States==
[[File:JohnCotton.jpg|right|thumb|[[John Cotton (puritan)|John Cotton]] (1585–1652)]]

===17th century===
In ''The Powring Out of the Seven Vials'' (1642), the [[Puritan]] [[John Cotton (puritan)|John Cotton]] wrote that 'the more learned and witty you bee, the more fit to act for [[Satan]] will you bee. ... Take off the fond doting ... upon the learning of the [[Society of Jesus|Jesuits]], and the glorie of the Episcopacy, and the brave estates of the Prelates. I say bee not deceived by these pompes, empty shewes, and faire representations of goodly condition before the eyes of flesh and blood, bee not taken with the applause of these persons.'&lt;ref name="Hofstadter, Richard 1962 p.46"&gt;Hofstadter, Richard ''Anti-intellectualism in American Life'' (1962), p. 46.&lt;/ref&gt; Not every Puritan concurred with Cotton's contempt for [[Secularism|secular]] education; some founded universities such as [[Harvard University|Harvard]], [[Yale University|Yale]], and [[Dartmouth College|Dartmouth]].

Economist Thomas Sowell&lt;ref&gt;Sowell, Thomas. (2001) ''The Quest for Cosmic Justice''. Simon and Schuster, 2001, ISBN 978-0-7432-1507-7, p. 187.&lt;/ref&gt; argues that American anti-intellectualism can be traced to the early Colonial era, and that wariness of the educated upper-classes is understandable given that America was built, in large part, by people fleeing persecution and brutality at the hands of the educated upper classes. Additionally, rather few intellectuals possessed the practical hands-on skills required to survive in the New World, leading to a deeply rooted suspicion of those who may appear to specialize in "verbal virtuosity" rather than tangible, measurable products or services:

&lt;blockquote&gt;From its colonial beginnings, American society was a "decapitated" society—largely lacking the topmost social layers of European society. The highest elites and the titled aristocracies had little reason to risk their lives crossing the Atlantic and then face the perils of pioneering. Most of the white population of colonial America arrived as [[indentured servant]]s and the black population as slaves. Later waves of immigrants were disproportionately [[peasant]]s and [[proletarian]]s, even when they came from Western Europe [...] The rise of American society to pre-eminence as an economic, political and military power was thus the triumph of the common man and a slap across the face to the presumptions of the arrogant, whether an elite of blood or books.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The source, Thomas Sowell, describes the effect the American Revolution had on the development of American government, as established by the Constitution and Bill of Rights. In his opinion, the tendency to "disregard" the impartiality of the law depending upon "who you are" rather than what the author describes as the impartiality of the "supremacy of the law" conflicts with the American creed of the common man. According to Sowell, this fundamental right uniquely distinguishes the American character, forged by "the beaten men of beaten races," from that of the arrogant and privileged elites of the European aristocracy.&lt;ref&gt;Sowell (2001), p. 187&lt;/ref&gt;

===19th century===
In the history of American anti-intellectualism, modern scholars{{citation needed|date=June 2010}} suggest that 19th-century [[popular culture]] is important, because, when most of the populace lived a [[rural]] life of [[manual labour]] and [[agriculture|agricultural]] work, a 'bookish' education, concerned with the Græco-Roman [[classics]], was perceived as of impractical value, ergo [[Profit (economics)|unprofitable]]—yet Americans, generally, were [[literacy|literate]] and read [[William Shakespeare|Shakespeare]] for pleasure—thus, the [[Ideal (ethics)|ideal]] "American" man was technically skilled and successful in his [[trade]], ergo a productive member of society.{{citation needed|date=November 2009}} Culturally, the ideal American was a self-made man whose knowledge derived from life-experience, not an intellectual man, whose knowledge derived from books, formal education, and academic study; thus, in ''The New Purchase, or Seven and a Half Years in the Far West'' (1843), the Reverend Bayard R. Hall, A.M., said about frontier [[Indiana]]:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
"We always preferred an ignorant bad man to a talented one, and, hence, attempts were usually made to ruin the [[morality|moral]] character of a smart candidate; since, unhappily, [[Intellectual giftedness|smartness]] and wickedness were supposed to be generally coupled, and [like-wise] incompetence and goodness."&lt;ref name="Hofstadter, Richard 1962 p.46"/&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Yet, the [[egghead]]'s worldly redemption was possible if he embraced [[mainstream]] [[mores]]; thus, in the fiction of [[O. Henry]], a character noted that once an East Coast [[university]] graduate 'gets over' his intellectual vanity—no longer thinks himself better than others—he makes just as good a [[cowboy]] as any other young man, despite his counterpart being the slow-witted naïf of good heart, a pop culture [[stereotype]] from stage shows.

==In Europe==

===Soviet Union===
In the first decade after the [[Russian Revolution]] of 1917, the [[Bolshevik]]s suspected the [[Tsarism|Tsarist]] [[intelligentsia]] as potentially traitorous of the [[proletariat]], thus, the initial [[Soviet Union|Soviet]] government comprised men and women without much formal education. [[Vladimir Lenin]] derided the old intelligentsia with the expression (roughly translated): 'We have completed no academies' (мы академиев не кончали).&lt;ref&gt;[http://wwi.lib.byu.edu/index.php/Intelligentsia_/_Lenin_to_Gorky Intelligentsia / Lenin to Gorky]&lt;/ref&gt; Moreover, the deposed propertied classes were termed ''[[Lishentsy]]'' ("the disenfranchised"), whose children were excluded from education; eventually, some 200 Tsarist intellectuals such as writers, philosophers, scientists, and engineers were deported to Germany on [[Philosophers' ships]] in 1922; others were deported to [[Latvia]] and to [[Turkey]] in 1923.

During the [[revolution]]ary period, the pragmatic Bolsheviks employed "bourgeois experts" to manage the economy, industry, and agriculture, and so learn from them. After the [[Russian Civil War]] (1917–22), to achieve socialism, the [[Soviet Union|USSR]] (1922–91) emphasised literacy and education in service to modernising the country via an educated [[working class]] [[intelligentsia]], rather than an [[Ivory Tower]] intelligentsia. During the 1930s and the 1950s, [[Joseph Stalin]] replaced Lenin's intelligentsia with a "communist" intelligentsia, loyal to him and with a specifically Soviet world view, thereby for a while producing the worst examples of Soviet anti-intellectualism — the [[Pseudoscience|pseudoscientific]] theories of [[Lysenkoism]] and [[Japhetic theory]], most damaging to [[biology]] and [[linguistics]] in that country.

===Fascism===
[[File:Giovanni Gentile.png|thumb|right|Active philosopher: [[Giovanni Gentile]], intellectual father of [[Italian Fascism]].]]

The [[Actual Idealism|idealist]] philosopher [[Giovanni Gentile]] established the intellectual basis of [[Fascism|Fascist]] ideology with the ''autoctisi'' (self-realisation) via concrete thinking that distinguished between the good (active) intellectual and the bad (passive) intellectual:

{{quote|Fascism combats ... not intelligence, but intellectualism... which is... a sickness of the intellect... not a consequence of its abuse, because the intellect cannot be used too much... it derives from the false belief that one can segregate oneself from life.|Giovanni Gentile|addressing a Congress of Fascist Culture, Bologna, 30 March 1925}}

To counter the "passive intellectual" who used his or her intellect abstractly, and therefore was "decadent", he proposed the "concrete thinking" of the active intellectual who applied intellect as [[Praxis (process)|praxis]]—a "man of action", like Fascist [[Benito Mussolini]], versus the decadent [[Communism|Communist]] [[intellectual]] [[Antonio Gramsci]]. The passive intellectual stagnates intellect by objectifying ideas, thus establishing them as objects. Hence the [[Fascism|Fascist]] rejection of materialist [[logic]], because it relies upon ''[[a priori and a posteriori|a priori]]'' principles improperly counter-changed with ''a posteriori'' ones that are irrelevant to the matter-in-hand in deciding whether or not to act.

In the praxis of Gentile's concrete thinking criteria, such consideration of the ''a priori'' toward the properly ''a posteriori'' constitutes ''impractical'', decadent intellectualism. Moreover, this fascist philosophy occurred parallel to [[Actual Idealism]], his philosophic system; he opposed [[intellectualism]] for its being disconnected from the active intelligence that gets things done, i.e. thought is killed when its constituent parts are labelled, and thus rendered as discrete entities.&lt;ref&gt;Gentile, Giovanni, ''Origins and Doctrine of Fascism (with selections from other works)'', A. James Gregor, ed., pp. 22–23, 33, 65–66&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''The Oxford Guide to Philosophy'' (2005), Ted Honderich, ed., p. 332.&lt;/ref&gt;

Related to this, is the confrontation between the Spanish [[Franquism|franquist]] General, [[José Millán Astray#Confrontation with Unamuno|Millán Astray]], and the writer [[Miguel de Unamuno]] during the ''[[Dia de la Raza]]'' celebration at the [[University of Salamanca]], in 1936, during the [[Spanish Civil War]]. The General exclaimed: ''¡Muera la inteligencia! ¡Viva la Muerte!'' ("Death to intelligence! Long live death!"); the Falangists applauded.{{Citation needed|date=July 2013}}

==In Asia==

===China===
====Imperial China====
[[Qin Shi Huang]] (246–210 BC), the first Emperor of unified China, consolidated political thought, and power, by suppressing [[freedom of speech]] at the suggestion of Chancellor [[Li Si]], who justified such anti-intellectualism by accusing the [[intelligentsia]] of falsely praising the emperor, and of dissenting through libel. From 213 to 206 BC, it was generally thought that the works of the [[Hundred Schools of Thought]] were incinerated, especially the ''Shi Jing'' ([[Classic of Poetry]], c. 1000 BC) and the ''Shujing'' ([[Classic of History]], c. 6th century BC). The exceptions were books by Qin historians, and books of [[Legalism (Chinese philosophy)|Legalism]], an early type of [[totalitarianism]]—and the Chancellor's philosophic school (see the [[Burning of books and burying of scholars]]).
However, upon further inspection of Chinese historical annals such as Shi Ji and Han Shu, this was found not to be the case. The Qin Empire privately kept one copy of each these books in the Imperial Library but publicly ordered that the books should be banned. Those who owned copies were ordered to surrender the books to be burned; those who refused were executed.  This eventually led to the loss of most ancient works of literature and philosophy when [[Xiang Yu]] burned down the Qin palace in 208BC.

====People's Republic of China====
[[File:Mao Zedong portrait.jpg|thumb|right|Chairman [[Mao Zedong]]]]

The [[Cultural Revolution]] was a politically violent decade (1966–76) of wide-ranging [[social engineering (political science)|social engineering]] of the [[People's Republic of China]] by its leader Chairman [[Mao Zedong|Mao]]. After several national policy crises, Mao, to regain public prestige and control of the [[Communist Party of China]] (CPC), on 16 May 1966, announced that the Party and Chinese society were permeated with liberal bourgeois elements who meant to restore [[capitalism]] to China, and that said people could only be removed with [[Aggravation of class struggle under socialism|post–revolutionary class struggle]]. To that effect, China's youth nationally organised into [[Red Guards (China)|Red Guards]], hunting the liberal bourgeois elements subverting the CCP and Chinese society. The Red Guards acted nationally, purging the country, the military, urban workers, and the leaders of the CCP. The Red Guards were particularly aggressive in attacking their teachers and professors, causing most schools and universities to be shut down once the Cultural Revolution began.  Three years later, in 1969, Mao declared the Cultural Revolution ended; yet the political intrigues continued until 1976, concluding with the arrest of the [[Gang of Four]], the ''de facto'' end of the Cultural Revolution.

===Democratic Kampuchea===
When the Communist Party of Cambodia, the [[Khmer Rouge]] (1951–81), established their regime as [[Democratic Kampuchea]] (1975–1979) in [[Cambodia]], their anti-intellectualism idealised the country and demonised the cities to establish [[agrarian socialism]], thus, they emptied cities to purge the [[Khmer people|Khmer]] nation of every [[treason|traitor]], [[enemy of the state]], and [[intellectual]], often symbolised by eyeglasses (see the [[Killing Fields]]).

===Ottoman Empire===
[[File:April24Victims.jpg|thumbnail|Some of the Armenian intellectuals who were detained, deported, and killed in the Armenian Genocide of 1915]]
In the early stages of the [[Armenian Genocide]] of 1915, around 2,300 Armenian intellectuals were [[Deportation of Armenian intellectuals on 24 April 1915|deported]] from Constantinople (Istanbul) and subsequently mostly murdered by the Ottoman government.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Dadrian|first=Vahakn N.|authorlink=Vahakn Dadrian|title=The history of the Armenian genocide: ethnic conflict from the Balkans to Anatolia to the Caucasus|year=2004|publisher=Berghahn Books|location=New York|isbn=1-57181-666-6|page=221|edition=6th rev.}}&lt;/ref&gt; The event has been described by historians as a [[decapitation strike]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Blinka|first=David S.|title=Re-creating Armenia: America and the memory of the Armenian genocide|date=2008|publisher=University of Wisconsin Press|location=Madison|page=31|quote=In what scholars commonly refer to as the decapitation strike on April 24, 1915...}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Bloxham|first1=Donald|authorlink1=Donald Bloxham|title=The Great Game of Genocide: Imperialism, Nationalism, and the Destruction of the Ottoman Armenians|date=2005|publisher=Oxford University Press|page=70|quote=...the decapitation of the Armenian nation with the series of mass arrests that began on 24 April...}}&lt;/ref&gt; which intended to deprive the Armenian population of an intellectual leadership and a chance of resistance.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Sahаkian|first=T. A.|title=Արևմտահայ մտավորականության սպանդի արտացոլումը հայ մամուլում 1915-1916 թթ. [The interpretation of the fact of extermination of the Armenian intelligentsia in the Armenian press in 1915-1916]|journal=[[Lraber Hasarakakan Gitutyunneri]]|date=2002|issue=1|page=89|url=http://lraber.asj-oa.am/770/|language=hy|quote=Դրանով թուրքական կառավարությունը ձգտում էր արևմտահայությանը գլխատել, նրան զրկել ղեկավար ուժից, բողոքի հնարավորությունից:}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Columns-list|3|
* [[Elitism#Anti-elitism|Anti-elitism]]
* [[Anarchism]]
* [[Anarcho-primitivism]]
* [[Antiscience]]
* [[Anti-technology]]
* [[Dumbing down]]
* [[Nerd]]
* [[Nihilism#Epistemological_nihilism|Epistemological nihilism]]
* [[Oblomov#Oblomovism|Oblomovism]], a term derived from the novel ''[[Oblomov]]'', written by Russian author [[Ivan Goncharov]]
* [[Obscurantism]]
* [[Philistinism]]
* [[Poshlost]]
* [[Postmodernism]]
* [[Relativism]]
}}

==Footnotes==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Further reading==

* {{cite book|author=Dane S. Claussen|title=Anti-Intellectualism in American Media|publisher=New York: Peter Lang Publishing|year=2004|isbn=978-0820457215}}
* Liza Featherstone, Doug Henwood, and Christian Parenti, [http://www.leftbusinessobserver.com/Action.html "'Action Will be Taken': Left Anti-Intellectualism and its Discontents,"] Left Business Observer.
* William Hinton, ''Hundred Day War: The Cultural Revolution at Tsinghua University''. New York: New York University Press, 1972.
* [[Richard Hofstadter]], ''[[Anti-intellectualism in American Life]].'' New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1963.
* {{cite book|author=Aaron Lecklider|title=Inventing the Egghead: The Battle over Brainpower in American Culture|publisher=Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Press|year=2013|isbn=978-0-8122-4486-1}}
* {{cite book|author=Elvin T. Lim|title=The Anti-Intellectual Presidency: The Decline of Presidential Rhetoric from George Washington to George W. Bush|publisher=New York: Oxford University Press|year=2008|isbn=978-0199898091}}
*{{cite web|title=Anti-Intellectualism and the "Dumbing Down" of America|year=2014|url=https://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/wired-success/201407/anti-intellectualism-and-the-dumbing-down-america|publisher=psychology today|quote=There is a growing and disturbing trend of anti-intellectual elitism in American culture. It’s the dismissal of science, the arts, and humanities and their replacement by entertainment, self-righteousness, ignorance, and deliberate gullibility.}}

==External links==
{{wiktionary}}

{{Discrimination}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Anti-Intellectualism}}
[[Category:Academia]]
[[Category:Anti-intellectualism| ]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Social theories]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>