<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20091115224327|326056443" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="18947899" pageid="18947899" ns="0" title="Anti-intellectualism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2009-11-16T19:50:24Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Refimprove|date=July 2009}}
'''Anti-intellectualism''' is the hostility towards and mistrust of intellect, [[intellectual]]s, and intellectual pursuits, usually expressed as the derision of [[education]], [[philosophy]], [[literature]], [[art]], and [[science]]. As political adjective, '''Anti-intellectual''' describes an education system emphasising minimal academic accomplishment, and a [[government]] who formulate [[public policy]] without the advice of [[Academia|academics]] and their [[scholarly method|scholarship]].

[[Image:nast-intellect.png|thumb|300px|[[Political cartoon]]ist [[Thomas Nast]] contrasts a reedy [[scholar]] with a bovine [[boxing|boxer]], epitomising the [[populism|popular]] view of reading and study as antithetical to sport and athleticism, note the disproportionate heads.]]

In [[public]] [[discourse]], '''Anti-intellectuals''' usually perceive and publicly present themselves as champions of the common folk — [[populism|populists]] against [[elitism|élitists]] and [[academic elitism|academic élitism]] — proposing that educated people are a social group detached from the quotidian concerns of the majority, and that they dominate [[politics|political]] discourse and [[higher education]]. 

== Anti-intellectualism expressed ==
Anti-intellectualism usually is expressed through declarations of [[Other]]ness — the intellectual is 'not one of us', he or she is dangerous to societal normality, for having little empathy for the common folk. Historically, this resulted in portrayals of [[intellectual]]s as an arrogant social group, whom rural communities viewed as ‘city slickers’ caring little for the country and country ways. It also is common for such communities to [[stereotype]] intellectuals as ‘foreigners’ or as ethnic minorities who ‘think differently’ than the natives; critics misrepresent them as prone to mental instability, because there is an organic, causal connection between [[genius]] and madness. Religion often portrays intellectuals as promoters of [[atheism]], and as indecent, either because of their [[sexual ethics|sexual mores]], [[homosexuality]], [[promiscuity|sexual promiscuity]], or [[celibacy]].

==Sources of anti-intellectualism ==
=== Religion ===
[[Image:Galileo before the Holy Office.jpg|thumb|275px|&lt;small&gt;'''Conflict theory:'''&lt;/small&gt; ''Galileo before the Holy Office'', by [[Joseph-Nicolas Robert-Fleury]], a 19th century depiction of the [[Galileo affair|Galileo Affair]], religion suppressing [[heliocentrism|heliocentric]] science.]]

In [[Classical antiquity]] and in the [[Modern history|modern]] era, religion tended to anti-intellectual sentiment — usually among [[fundamentalism|fundamentalist]]s who perceived [[doctrine|doctrinal]] contradictions allowing too much freedom. Yet, said sentiment was not universal, e.g. [[Judaism]]’s [[scholarly method|scholarly]] and [[theology|theologic]] traditions, and the [[History of European research universities|Western university system]] evolved from religious schools. Moreover, mediæval and modern [[philosophy|philosophers]] — [[Thomas Aquinas]], [[René Descartes]], [[John Locke]], [[Immanuel Kant]] — considered themselves religious without contradicting their [[intellectual]]ism; see the [[Conflict thesis|Conflict Thesis]] for further discussion of religious anti-intellectualism. 

When religious [[doctrine]] stipulates definitive statements about [[natural history|natural]] and human [[history]], the [[provenance]] of [[sacred text]]s, and other matters of [[faith]], intellectuals usually propose that such claims be substantiated via external [[scholarship]]. Therefore, a claim about the authenticity of the mediæval [[Turin shroud|Shroud of Turin]] (ca. 1260–1390) being a religious artefact from antiquity could be [[Turin shroud#Radiocarbon dating|scientifically tested]]; and a [[theodicy]] could be [[logic]]ally examined for consistency — although the results might provoke intellectual and [[existentialism|existential]] doubt either confirming or negating the faith of the believers. Furthermore, when [[bohemianism]], [[avant-gardism]], and [[romanticism]] became integral to the fine arts, religious anti-intellectuals perceived them as [[morality|immoral]], if not amoral — and demanded their [[censorship]]. Historically, this remains thematically common to the socio-cultural trends in the Americas and in Europe, since the [[Protestant Reformation]] (1517).

=== Authoritarian politics ===
[[Dictators]], and people seeking to establish [[dictatorships]], use anti-intellectualism to gain popular political support, because they perceive the educated as a politically dangerous social group who question extant social norms, dissent from established, popular opinion, and reject [[nationalism]], hence are [[patriotism|unpatriotic]], thus subversive. In the event, violent anti-intellectualism usually is common to the rise and rule of [[authoritarianism|authoritarian]] political movements, such as Italian [[Fascism]], Soviet [[Stalinism]], and Iranian [[Iranian Revolution|theocracy]].{{Citation needed|date=November 2009}}

[[ideology|Ideologically]] extreme dictatorships, such as the [[Khmer Rouge]] (1975–79), the Communist Party of Kampuchea, killed people with more than elementary educations. Other expressions of governmental anti-intellectualism range from closing public libraries and schools, to isolating intellectuals and [[scientist]]s in an [[Ivory Tower]], to official declarations that intellectuals are prone to mental illness, and, via mental health laws, imprison them in [[psychiatry|psychiatric]] hospitals, thereby rendering them scapegoats who divert popular discontent from the dictatorship.

Moreover, anti-intellectualism is neither always violent, nor oppressive, because most any social group can exercise contempt for [[intellect]], [[intellectualism]], and [[higher education|education]]. To wit, the Uruguayan writer, [[Jorge Majfud]] said that ‘this contempt, that arises from a power installed in the social institutions, and from the inferiority complex of its actors, is not a property of “underdeveloped” countries. In fact, it is always the critical intellectuals, writers, or artists who head the top-ten lists of “the most stupid of the stupid” in the country’.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.politicalaffairs.net/article/articleview/4771/1/238 Political Affairs Magazine - Power and the Intellectuals&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Populism ===
[[Populism]] posits intellectuals as [[elitism|elitists]] with fearful [[rhetoric]]al skills with which they deceive the common folk, the virtuous 'salt of the earth'. In the US, ex-president [[George W. Bush]] (2001–2009) used populism in gaining and retaining popular support for his government.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2006/04/01/AR2006040101004.html Baker, Peter; “The President as Average Joe: Trying to Boost Support, Bush Brings Banter to the People”; washingtonpost.com; 2 April 2006.]&lt;/ref&gt; For example, populists proposing such perceptions of intellectuals assert that knowledge needs to be regulated ‘by the people’, because educators need to work within the policies of the interested parties — such as parents’ groups — in matters of [[curriculum|curricular]] content, (''viz.'' including [[Creationism]] [[pseudoscience]] as academically analogous to [[evolution]]). Like-wise, the intellectual’s objectivity and curiosity towards and about foreign countries are misrepresented as unpatriotic, lacking in definitive [[moral clarity]] — hence subversive of the homeland’s social norms, popular opinion, and [[nationalism]].

==Education system anti-intellectualism==
Because the [[curriculum|curricula]] of a country’s education system determine the cultural formation of its nation — thereby, the real-world [[trade (occupation)|occupational]] and [[profession]]al destinies of its graduates, as either [[blue-collar worker|blue collar]] or [[white-collar worker|white collar]] workers — the intellectuals and the anti-intellectuals vie to control the content of [[public education|public]] and private [[education]]. This contest has been and is variously manifested as ''[[Kulturkampf]]'' in Bismarck’s Germany, [[culture war]] in the US, and [[cultural hegemony]] elsewhere. In the Anglophone world, especially in the US, anti-intellectuals such as the politicians [[David Horowitz]] (''viz.'' the [[David Horowitz Freedom Center]]), [[Patrick Buchanan]], and [[William John Bennett|William Bennett]], an ex-secretary of education, criticize schools and universities as '[[Intellectual]]ist', for teaching curricula emphasising ''impractical'', rather than ''practical'' education that would not yield graduates prepared for ‘real-world’ work.

====At school====
In the 2004 newspaper article ‘When Every Child is Good Enough’, John Tierney reported that [[conservatism|conservative]] parents believe that US primary and secondary schools over-emphasise [[equality of outcome]] &lt;ref&gt;John Tierney, “When Every Child Is Good Enough”, The New York Times, 21 November 2004&lt;/ref&gt; to the detriment of their childrens’ individual (unequal) achievements. A literary example of that contention is the [[social science fiction|science fiction]] short story ‘[[Harrison Bergeron]]’ (1961), by [[Kurt Vonnegut]], wherein the government’s [[Harrison Bergeron|Handicapper General]] imposes equality upon the eponymous hero, lest his existence — as the smartest, handsomest, most athletic boy in the world — hurt the feelings of the mediocre [[populism|popular]] majority, (''viz.'' the over-simplification, the [[dumbing down]], of [[curriculum|curricula]]).

====At university====
The “[[intellectual]]ist” accusations against [[higher education]], by such as [[David Horowitz]], [[Patrick Buchanan]] and [[William John Bennett|William Bennett]], are based upon three [[reactionary]] and [[conservative]] concerns about [[curriculum|curricular]] content: 

(i) '''Liberal political bias:''' That university professors, instructors, and lecturers inculcate [[secularism|secular]] and [[liberalism|liberal]] values to the students without ‘equal time’ for analogue views (''viz.'' [[Creationism]], etc.). That said political bias sacrifices objectivity and [[tradition]]al religious values in favour of [[political radicalism]] and [[left-wing politics|left-wing]] perspectives, especially in the [[Humanities]], and in the [[social sciences]] that challenge the cultural validity of [[white people|white]] [[patriarchy]], see [[Women's Studies]], [[Gender Studies]], [[Cultural Studies]], [[Ethnic Studies]], and [[race relations|Racial Studies]].

(ii) '''Deficient curricula:''' The lack of general education requirements (i.e. the Humanities) such as [[philosophy]], [[history]], [[literature]], [[music]], et cetera, in acquiring a balanced education.

(iii) '''Impracticality:''' That a [[humanism|humanistic]] education is not readily [[profit (economics)|profitable]] in ‘real life’ as opposed to a [[Vocational education|technical]] (computer science, engineering, etc.) or [[professional]] (law, medicine, etc.) education.

==Youth culture==
Contemporary [[Youth subculture|Youth Culture]] is a [[commerce|commercial]] form of anti-intellectualism orienting adherents to [[consumerism]]. The ''[[Frontline (U.S. TV series)|Frontline]]'' public affairs television series documentary [http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/pages/frontline/shows/cool/etc/script.html ''The Merchants of Cool''] (2001) describes how the [[advertising]] business transformed [[adolescence|adolescents’]] language, thought, and action ([[cliques]], [[fashion]], [[fads]]) into [[commodity|commodities]], and thus engendred a [[generation]] of intellectually disengaged Americans uninterested in progressing to [[adulthood]]. 

The US youth [[sub-culture]] originated from the post–Second World War economic prosperity allowing adolescents to work and have a [[Disposable/Discretionary income|discretionary income]] — whilst still dependant upon parents. In turn, their economic power allowed business to sell them [[popularity]] — an [[identity]] as a ''young'' person — something that once was not for sale, but self-created; to wit, the British [[blog]] writer [[Paul Graham]] likened youth culture to an occupation permitting little time for education and intellectual interests.&lt;ref&gt;Graham P (February 2003). [http://paulgraham.com/nerds.html Why Nerds are Unpopular.]&lt;/ref&gt;

== American anti-intellectualism ==
===17th Century===
In ''The Powring Out of the Seven Vials'' (1642), the [[Puritan]] [[John Cotton (puritan)|John Cotton]] wrote that ‘the more learned and witty you bee, the more fit to act for [[Satan]] will you bee. . . . Take off the fond doting . . . upon the learning of the [[Society of Jesus|Jesuites]], and the glorie of the Episcopacy, and the brave estates of the Prelates. I say bee not deceived by these pompes, empty shewes, and faire representations of goodly condition before the eyes of flesh and blood, bee not taken with the appause of these persons.’ &lt;ref name="Hofstadter, Richard 1962 p.46"&gt;Hofstadter, Richard ''Anti-intellectualism in American Life'' (1962), p.46.&lt;/ref&gt; Hence, the anti-intellectualism that [[Conservative Christianity|conservative Christians]] (Evangelicals and Fundamentalists) espouse proposes that contemporary education subverts religious belief and faith, arguing that the [[atheism]] and [[Deism]] characteristic to [[education|educated]] people during the [[The Age of Enlightenment]] in the eighteenth century, establishes the validity of their perspective. As such, they oppose ‘un-Christian elements’ in [[Education in the United States|public schools]], [[K–12 education|Kindergarten through 12th grade]] and [[Higher education|universities]], especially [[sex education|comprehensive sexual education]] and [[evolution]]. To wit, this anti-intellectual current is in the work of [[Fundamentalist Christianity|Fundamentalist]] Christian cartoonist [[Jack Chick]], who, in the [[anti-evolution]] [[tract (literature)|tract]] ''Big Daddy?'' (2002) depicts intellectuals, specifically university academics, as elitist and religiously intolerant for rejecting [[young earth creationism]], a literal interpretation of the [[Book of Genesis]] espoused by some fundamentalist Christians and Jews.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.chick.com/reading/tracts/0055/0055_01.asp Big Daddy?&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Zucker, David ''The Torah: An Introduction for Christians and Jews'' (2005), Paulist Press, ISBN 0809143496.&lt;/ref&gt;

===19th Century===
In the history of American anti-intellectualism, 19th century [[popular culture]] is important, because, in a time when most of the populace lived a [[rural]] life of [[manual labour]] and [[agriculture|agricultural]] work, a ‘bookish’ education, concerned with the Græco-Roman [[classics]], was perceived as of impractical value, ergo [[Profit (economics)|unprofitable]] — yet Americans, generally, were [[literacy|literate]] and read [[William Shakespeare|Shakespeare]] for pleasure — thus, the [[idealism|ideal]] ''American '' man was technically skilled, successful in his [[trade]], ergo a productive member of society.

Culturally, the ideal American was a self-made man whose knowledge derived from life-experience, not an [[intellectual]] man, whose knowledge derived from [[books]], formal [[education]], and [[academic]] study. To wit, in ''The New Purchase, or Seven and a Half Years in the Far West'' (1843), the Reverend Bayard R. Hall, A.M., about frontier [[Indiana]] said, ‘we always preferred an ignorant bad man to a talented one, and, hence, attempts were usually made to ruin the [[morality|moral]] character of a smart candidate; since, unhappily, [[Intellectual giftedness|smartness]] and wickedness were supposed to be generally coupled, and [like-wise] incompetence and goodness’.&lt;ref name="Hofstadter, Richard 1962 p.46"/&gt; Yet, the [[egghead]]’s worldly redemption was possible if he embraced [[mainstream]] [[mores]]; thus, in the fiction of [[O. Henry]], a character noted that once an East Coast [[university]] graduate ‘gets over’ his intellectual vanity — no longer thinks himself better than others — he makes just as good a [[cowboy]] as any other young man, despite his counterpart being the slow-witted naïf of good heart, a pop culture [[stereotype]] from stage shows, and current in US culture as the ‘Average Joe’ type of man portrayed in the novel ''[[Forrest Gump (novel)|Forrest Gump]]'' (1986), by [[Winston Groom]], and the film ''[[Forrest Gump]]'' (1994), by [[Robert Zemeckis]].

===20th and 21st centuries===
'''Rightist perspective'''

The writer [[Robert Warshow]] proposed that the [[Communist Party USA|Communist Party of the USA]] was central to US intellectual life during the 1930s: 

:For most American [[intellectual]]s, the [[Communism|Communist]] movement of the 1930s was a crucial experience. In Europe, where the movement was at once more serious and more popular, it was still only one current in intellectual life; the Communists could never completely set the tone of thinking. . . . But in this country there was a time when virtually all intellectual vitality was derived, in one way or another, from the Communist party. If you were not somewhere within the party’s wide orbit, then you were likely to be in the opposition, which meant that much of your thought and energy had to be devoted to maintaining yourself in opposition.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fas.org/sgp/library/moynihan/appa7.html Report of the Commission on Protecting and Reducing Government Secrecy&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!--Moynihan Commission Report, quoted from Robert Warshow, “The Legacy of the 30’s: Middle-Class Mass Culture and the Intellectuals’ Problem”, ''Commentary'' magazine (December 1947):538, footnote 103.--&gt;

A contemporary philosophic descendant of Warshow, is [[David Horowitz]], an ex-[[Marxism|Marxist]] advocating an ‘[[academic freedom]]’ movement, via the [[David Horowitz Freedom Center]] (1988), proposing that [[identity politics]] and left-wing academics [[doctrine|indoctrinate]] university students with anti-Americanism.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.frontpagemag.com FrontPage Magazine&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Feminism'''

In ''Spreading Misandry: The Teaching of Contempt for Men in Popular Culture'' (2001), the Canadian [[religious studies]] academics, [[Nathanson and Young]]&lt;ref&gt;Nathanson, Paul and Kathleen Young. 2001. Spreading misandry: the teaching of contempt for men in popular culture. McGill-Queen's Press, ISBN 0773522727.&lt;/ref&gt; propose that ‘[[ideology|ideological]] [[feminism]]’ — akin to the [[gender feminism]] proposed by [[Christina Hoff Summers]] — is ‘profoundly anti-intellectual’.

'''Leftist perspective'''

The 1960s anti-war movement protesting the thirty-year [[Vietnam War|US war against Vietnam]] (1945–75) manifested its anti-intellectualism against US defense secretary [[Robert McNamara]], whose [[business school]] intellectualism manifested itself in that war’s published [[body count]]s, a feature of [[attrition warfare]], a militarily strategy applied when conquest is infeasible. The Marxist [[Theodor Adorno]] criticised this left-wing anti-intellectualism as [[actionism]], philosophically-baseless action for its own sake, meant to effect political change. Furthermore, non-conformist students romanticized the [[poverty|poor]] people of [[Appalachia]] and the [[Mississippi Delta]], as an ideal wherein [[illiterate|illiteracy]] was freedom from the [[suburb]]an [[conformism]] of post–Second World War US society.

===News media===
[[intellectual|Public intellectuals]], such as Professor [[Noam Chomsky]], observe that the news media’s low-quality intellectual content is [[bread and circuses|spectacle]] in service to commerce (high viewership [[ratings]]) promoting [[The Establishment|Establishment]] perspectives with [[Manufacturing Consent|manufactured consent]]. 

In the [[2000 Presidential Election]], the [[mass media|mass communications media]], especially stand-up comedians on [[television]], portrayed the [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democratic Party]] candidate [[Al Gore]] as a boring ‘[[brainiac]]’ (a [[portmanteau]] word of ''brain'' + ''maniac'') who spoke in a monotone about abstruse facts and figures incomprehensible to ''hoi polloi''. His reported claim to ‘have invented the Internet’ &lt;ref&gt;[http://cnn.com/ALLPOLITICS/stories/1999/03/09/president.2000/transcript.gore/ Transcript: Vice President Gore on CNN's 'Late Edition' - 9 March 1999&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; was especially ridiculed by anti-intellectuals, thus stereotypically portraying him as an intellectual detached from the common folk. Like-wise, conservative political commentators, such as [[Ann Coulter]] (an attorney), [[Bill O'Reilly (political commentator)|Bill O’Reilly]] (MA, public administration), and radio personality [[Rush Limbaugh]], argue that the news media betray left-wing intellectual snobbery when they portray right-wing politicians, such as [[Ronald Reagan]], [[George W. Bush]], and [[Sarah Palin]], as illiterate incompetents. In particular, O’Reilly, a [[Harvard|Harvard University]] alumnus, is known for hostility towards the East Coast ‘liberal [[Ivy League]] élites’.

As talk programme hosts, O’Reilly, Limbaugh, [[Tucker Carlson]], and [[Joe Scarborough]] (an attorney) practise anti-intellectualism by habitually interrupting the guests’ presentations of complex arguments; about that behaviour, Scarborough said, ‘If my guest is allowed to speak uninterrupted for more than fifteen seconds, then I’m not doing my job’. {{Citation needed|date=October 2008}}

==European anti-intellectualism==
===The Græco-Roman world===
In the [[Roman Republic]] (509–27 BC), the public career of the statesman [[Cato the Elder]] displayed traits that would be considered anti-intellectual in the contemporary world. He vehemently opposed the introduction of [[ancient Greece|Greek]] culture to the Roman republic, believing them subversive of traditional Roman military values and plain-spokenness. In 186 BC, he convinced the [[Roman Senate|Senate]] to decree against the [[Bacchanalia]], then a recently imported [[mystery religion]], they agreed with him via the ''Senatus consultum de Bacchanalibus''. He urged the deportation of three [[Athens|Athenian]] philosophers, [[Carneades]], [[Diogenes the Stoic]], and [[Critolaus]], in [[Rome]] as Athenian [[ambassador]]s, because he believed their opinions dangerous to the Republic.

===The USSR===
In the first decade after the [[Russian Revolution of 1917]], the [[Bolsheviks]] suspected the [[Tsarism|Tsarist]] [[intelligentsia]] as potentially traitorous of the [[proletariat]], thus, the initial [[Soviet]] government comprised men and women without much formal education. [[Lenin]] derided the old intelligentsia with the expression (very roughly translated): ‘We ain’t completed no academies’, (мы академиев не кончали).&lt;ref&gt;[http://wwi.lib.byu.edu/index.php/Intelligentsia_/_Lenin_to_Gorky Intelligentsia / Lenin to Gorky]&lt;/ref&gt; Moreover, the deposed propertied classes were termed ''[[Lishentsy]]'' (‘the disenfranchised’), whose children were excluded from education; eventually, some 200 Tsarist intellectuals were deported to Germany on [[Philosophers' ships]] in 1922; others were deported to Latvia and to Turkey in 1923.

During the [[revolution]]ary period, the pragmatic Bolsheviks employed ‘bourgeois experts’ to manage the economy, industry, and agriculture, and so learn from them. After the [[Russian Civil War]] (1917–23), to achieve [[Socialism]], the [[Soviet Union|USSR]] (1922–91) emphasised literacy and education in service to modernising the country via an educated [[working class]] [[intelligentsia]], rather than an [[Ivory Tower]] intelligentsia. During the 1930s and the 1950s, [[Stalin]] replaced Lenin’s intelligentsia with a Communist intelligentsia, loyal to him and with a specifically Soviet world view, thereby producing the most egregious examples of Soviet anti-intellectualism — the [[pseudoscience|pseudoscientific]] theories of [[Lysenkoism]] and [[Japhetic theory]], most damaging to [[biology]] and [[linguistics]] in that country, by subordinating [[science]] to a [[fundamentalist]] interpretation of [[Marxism]].

===Fascist Italy===
The [[Actual Idealism|idealist]] philosopher [[Giovanni Gentile]] established the intellectual basis of [[Fascism|Fascist]] ideology with the ''autoctisi'' (self-realisation) via concrete thinking that distinguished between the good (active) intellectual and the bad (passive) intellectual:

{{cquote2|Fascism combats . . . not intelligence, but intellectualism . . . which is . . . a sickness of the intellect . . . not a consequence of its abuse, because the intellect cannot be used too much . . . it derives from the false belief that one can segregate oneself from life. . . .|Giovanni Gentile|addressing a Congress of Fascist Culture, Bologna, 30 March 1925}}

To counter the ‘passive intellectual’ who used his or her intellect abstractly, and therefore was ‘decadent’, he proposed the ‘concrete thinking’ of the active intellectual who applied intellect as [[Praxis (process)|praxis]] — a ‘Man of Action’, like Fascist [[Benito Mussolini]], versus the decadent [[Communism|Communist]] [[intellectual]] [[Antonio Gramsci]]. The passive intellectual stagnates intellect by objectifying ideas, thus establishing them as objects — hence the [[Fascism|Fascist]] rejection of [[logic]] — because it relies upon ''[[a priori and a posteriori]]'' facts that hold principles (external to the matter-in-hand) as considerable in effectin an action or not. In the praxis of Gentile's concrete thinking criteria, such consideration of the ''a priori'' constitutes ''impractical'', decadent intellectualism. Moreover, this fascist philosophy occurred parallel to [[Actual Idealism]], his philosophic system; he opposed [[intellectual]]ism for its being disconnected from the active intelligence that gets things done, i.e. thought is killed when its constituent parts are labelled, and thus rendered as discrete entities.&lt;ref&gt;Gentile, Giovanni, ''Origins and Doctrine of Fascism (with selections from other works)'', A. James Gregor, ed., pp. 22–23, 33, 65–66&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''The Oxford Guide to Philosophy'' (2005), Ted Honderich, ed., p. 332.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Asian anti-intellectualism==
===China===

The [[Tao Te Ching]] (ca. 6th c. BC) advises emperors to keep their subjects occupied and content with a ‘full belly and an empty mind’, {{Citation needed|date=September 2009}} and that for a people, ‘ignorance is better than knowledge’. {{Citation needed|date=September 2009}} [[Qin Shi Huang]] (246–21 BC), the first Emperor of unified China, consolidated political thought, and power, by suppressing [[freedom of speech]] at the suggestion of Chancellor [[Li Ssu]], who justified such anti-intellectualism by accusing the [[intelligentsia]] of falsely praising the emperor, and of dissenting through libel. From 213 to 206 BC, the works of the [[Hundred Schools of Thought]] were incinerated, especially the ''Shi Jing'' ([[Classic of Poetry]], ca. 1000 BC) and the ''Shujing'' ([[Classic of History]], ca. 6th c. BC); the exceptions were books by Qin historians, and books of [[Legalism (Chinese philosophy)|Legalism]], an early type of [[totalitarianism]] — and the Chancellor’s philosophic school, (see the [[Burning of books and burying of scholars]]).

===Democratic Kampuchea===

When the Communist Party of Cambodia, the [[Khmer Rouge]] (1951–81), established their régime as [[Democratic Kampuchea]] (1975–1979) in [[Cambodia]], their anti-intellectualism idealised the country and demonised the cities — which they emptied to purge the [[Khmer]] nation of every [[treason|traitor]], [[enemy of the state]], and [[intellectual]] (often symbolised by eyeglasses) — to establish [[agrarian socialism]], (see the [[Killing Fields]] and the [[Other]]).

===Iran===

The [[Islamic Republic of Iran]], a [[theocracy|theocratic]] régime established in 1979, effected its anti-intellectualism by replacing [[secularism|secular]] law with religion, thereby provoking the [[brain drain]]-emigration of most of Iran’s Western-educated and -trained [[intelligentsia]]. In 1980, the government closed the country’s universities until the [[curricula]] were ‘purified’ of the [[Pahlavi Dynasty]] (1925–1979) corruption. The assassination of the [[poetry|poet]] [[Saïd Soltanpour]], in 1981, was the theocracy’s most notorious anti-intellectual suppression; and secular education remained proscribed until 1982.

== See also ==
* [[Anti-science]]
* [[Appeal to emotion]]
* [[Obscurantism]]
* [[Pseudo-philosophy]]
* [[Dumbing down]]

==References==
{{reflist}}
{{refbegin}}

==Further reading==
*''[[Anti-intellectualism in American Life]]'', by [[Richard Hofstadter]]: ISBN 0-394-70317-0
*''Anti-Intellectualism in American Media,'' by Dane S. Claussen: New York: Peter Lang Publishing, 2004. ISBN 0-8204-5721-3
*''Evening Chats in Beijing: Probing China's Predicament,'' by Perry Link: New York, London: W.W. Norton &amp; Company, 1991. ISBN 0393310655 
*Hinton, William. ''Hundred Day War: The Cultural Revolution at Tsinghua University''. New York: New York UP, 1972. ISBN 0-85345-281-4.
*[http://www.fas.org/sgp/library/moynihan/appa7.html Moynihan Commission Report, Appendix A, 7. The Cold War, footnote 103] quoted from Robert Warshow, ''The Legacy of the 30’s: Middle-Class Mass Culture and the Intellectuals’ Problem,'' Commentary Magazine (December 1947): 538.
*[http://www.leftbusinessobserver.com/Action.html "Action Will be Taken" Left Anti-Intellectualism and its Discontents] by Liza Featherstone, Doug Henwood, and Christian Parenti (Left Business Observer)
{{refend}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Anti-Intellectualism}}
[[Category:Academia]]
[[Category:Anti-intellectualism|*]]
[[Category:Social theories]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]

[[cy:Gwrthddeallaeth]]
[[nl:Anti-intellectualisme]]
[[pt:Anti-intelectualismo]]
[[ru:Антиинтеллектуализм]]
[[sv:Antiintellektualism]]
[[zh:反智主义]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>