<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20081107181450|250278148" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="18947899" pageid="18947899" ns="0" title="Anti-intellectualism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2008-11-08T03:02:12Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Anti-intellectualism''' describes a sentiment of hostility towards, or mistrust of, [[intellectual]]s and [[intellect]]ual pursuits.  This may be expressed in various ways, such as attacks on the merits of [[science]], [[education]], [[art]], or [[literature]].

[[Image:nast-intellect.png|thumb|300px|[[Political cartoon]]ist [[Thomas Nast]] contrasts a scholar with a [[boxing|prize-fighter]]. His caricature encapsulates the popular view that sees reading and study as being in opposition to sport and athletic pursuits, although the bovine figure of the fighter is no less negative than that of the scholar.]]
Anti-intellectuals often perceive themselves as champions of the ordinary people and [[egalitarianism]] against [[elitism]], especially [[academic elitism]].  These critics argue that highly educated people form an isolated social group tend to dominate [[politics|political]] discourse and [[higher education]] ([[academia]]). 

Anti-intellectualism can also be used as a term to criticize an educational system if it seems to place minimal emphasis on academic and intellectual accomplishment, or if a [[government]] has a tendency to formulate policies without consulting academic and [[scholarly method|scholarly]] study.

== Expression ==
Anti-intellectualism will often be expressed within communities through declarations of [[Other]]ness, that is, intellectuals will be said to be 'not one of us'.  Those who mistrust intellectuals will represent them as a danger to normality, insisting that they are outsiders with little empathy for the common people.  This has historically resulted in intellectuals being painted as arrogant members of a different social grouping.  In rural communities, for example, intellectuals may be viewed as "city slickers" who know little of the country and its ways.  It is also common for communities to typecast intellectuals as foreigners or members of ethnic minorities, for instance as [[Asians]].  Along with this, intellectuals will often be said to be prone to mental instability, their critics insisting there is a medically proven connection between [[genius]] and madness.  Communities where religious [[faith]] is strong may endeavor to link intellectuals with the promotion of [[atheism]], while the sexual mores of intellectuals can be also placed in doubt in some cultures where they can be suspected of high promiscuity, [[Homophobia|homosexual]] tendencies, or lack of interest in sex at all.  Notably, those who disapprove of intellectuals often view them as exhibiting not one, but a combination of these character traits.

== Causes ==
Anti-intellectual beliefs may come from a variety of sources. These include:

=== Religion ===
Although a variety of [[religion]]s coexist with intellectual traditions, they rely on non-independently verifiable [[argument from authority|arguments from authority]], along with a somewhat common tendency to reject secular critical traditions. 

It is more common for [[fundamentalism|fundamentalist]] wings of a religion to harbor anti-intellectual sentiments, due to a tendency to reject that which runs contrary to their religious beliefs.  However, it is important to note that this is not necessarily the case with all religious groups, and that many religious groups pride themselves on their scholarly, as well as religious, traditions.
When religious [[doctrine]]s include statements about [[natural history|natural]] or human [[history]], the [[provenance]] of [[sacred text]]s (and other matters), such claims may be investigated by external [[scholarship]]. For example a claim about the age of a [[Turin shroud|religious artifact]] may be [[Turin shroud#Radiocarbon dating|scientifically tested]], or a [[theodicy]] may be logically examined. If such an investigation is instigated, the outcome may therefore create conflict in relation to how an adherent to the doctrine perceives it as confirming or denying their belief. 

However, religious anti-intellectualism is not confined to hostility against science: When movements such as [[bohemianism]], [[avant-gardism]] and [[romanticism]] become major factors in the fine arts, religious believers may perceive these trends to be subversive of [[morality]] and call for [[censorship]]. This has been a fairly common theme in socio-cultural trends in the Americas and Europe since the time of the [[Protestant Reformation|Reformation]]. Some would argue, however, that this is just moral conservatism, which is distinct from anti-intellectualism, though the two positions are allied in many cases.

=== Authoritarian politics ===
Anti-intellectualism is often used by [[dictators]] or those seeking to establish [[dictatorships]]. Educated people as a social group have often been seen by totalitarian elements as a threat because of the tendency of intellectuals to question existing social norms and to dissent from established opinion. Thus, often violent anti-intellectual backlashes are common during the rise and rule of authoritarian political movements, such as [[Fascism]], [[Stalinism]] and [[theocracy|Theocratic rule]]. Moreover, because many intellectuals refuse to embrace [[nationalism]], they are also commonly portrayed as [[patriotism|unpatriotic]] and subversive. 

The most extreme dictatorships, such as that of the [[Khmer Rouge]], simply murdered anyone with more than a rudimentary education. Other expressions of anti-intellectualism range from the closure of public libraries and places of learning, to keeping intellectuals and scientists isolated from the world in an "[[ivory tower]]", to official declarations that intellectuals are prone to mental illness and enacting laws to have them placed under psychiatric care.  In addition, intellectuals in countries ruled by authoritarian governments are often subject to popular condemnation and used as scapegoats to divert the anger of the public away from those in power. Anti-intellectualism is not necessarily violent, however, and not necessarily oppressive. Anti-intellectual attitudes can be held by any group, including non-violent ones, as well as by individuals who merely disfavor intellectualism and learning in general. According to [[Jorge Majfud]], "this contempt that arises from a power installed in the social institutions and from the inferiority complex of its actors, is not a property of 'underdeveloped' countries. In fact, it is always the critical intellectuals, writers or artists who head the top-ten lists of the most stupid of the stupid in the country."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.politicalaffairs.net/article/articleview/4771/1/238 Political Affairs Magazine - Power and the Intellectuals&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Populism ===
[[Populism]] can be another major strain of anti-intellectualism.  In this context, intellectuals are presented as [[elitism|elitists]] and tricksters whose knowledge and [[rhetoric]]al skills are feared, not because they are useless, but because they may be used to hoodwink the ordinary people, who are conceived of as the 'salt of the earth' and the source of virtue.  American President [[George W. Bush]] has been accused of appealing to this type of populism. &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2006/04/01/AR2006040101004.html Baker, Peter; "The President as Average Joe: Trying to Boost Support, Bush Brings Banter to the People"; washingtonpost.com; [[April 2]], [[2006]].]&lt;/ref&gt; Those who argue from populist ideals will often assert that knowledge needs to be regulated by the people, claiming that educators need to work in line with policies made by [[Stakeholder (general)|stakeholders]] such as parent groups.

In a similar vein, the curiosity and objectivity of intellectuals about foreign countries and beliefs is portrayed as a lack of [[patriotism]] or [[moral clarity]], and intellectuals are often held to be suspect of holding dangerously foreign, possibly subversive, opinions.  An extreme form was embodied by [[Joseph McCarthy]], the [[anti-Communism|anti-Communist]] [[U.S. senator|senator]] from [[Wisconsin]].

==Issues within the educational system==
The educational system may serve as a powerful tool for forming the culture of a nation.  In the English speaking world, particularly in the [[United States]] and [[United Kingdom]], the schools and universities have often been criticized for being overtaken by overtly 'Intellectualist' trends and hence not preparing the youth properly to be members of society who would  be cultured, prepared for challenging jobs, and capable of independent thought.

====In primary and secondary schools====
Some commentators&lt;ref&gt;John Tierney, "When Every Child Is Good Enough," ''[[The New York Times]],'' November 21, 2004&lt;/ref&gt; believe that primary and secondary schools, at least in the United States, place too much emphasis on [[equality of outcome]] at the expense of individual intellectual achievement.  In the view of such commentators, such emphasis leads to a [[Harrison Bergeron|Handicapper General]] mentality and the [[dumbing down]] of the curriculum.

=====The demands of youth culture=====
A major preserve of real, though hardly militant or even self-aware, anti-intellectualism in the contemporary world is a youth subculture often associated with those students who are more interested in social life or athletics than in their studies.  Such subcultures, often marked by [[cliques]], exist among students of all groups.  Commercial [[youth culture]] also generates a dizzying variety of [[fad]]s.  Keeping up with the trends is difficult, and their content is frequently criticised by cultural critics of many different persuasions for being simple-minded and pandering to unsophisticated appetites.  Pursuing [[popularity]] has been likened by [[blog]] writer [[Paul Graham]] to a full time job that leaves little time for intellectual interests.&lt;ref&gt;[http://paulgraham.com/nerds.html Why Nerds are Unpopular&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

The Frontline Special "Merchants of Cool(2/27/2001)" ([http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/pages/frontline/shows/cool/etc/script.html script]) suggests that advertising giants are creating an anti-intellectual, commodity-obsessed generation.

====In colleges====
In the realm of [[higher education]] concerns are generally threefold: 

=====Political bias=====
One type of criticism is based upon the perception that university professors and other academics have increasingly inculcated their own political ideologies into pedagogical interactions and professional research at the cost of the quality, objectivity, and appropriateness of each. In the [[United States]] this claim is more often made by those individuals on the conservative side of the  political spectrum against political [[liberals]], as understood in a contemporary sense of the term as well as [[Radicalization|radicals]] and [[leftists]]. Whether this focus on the proverbial "ivory tower left" is deserved is the subject of much intense debate both within the [[Academy]] and various political spheres.

Generally, these criticisms are brought up against persons working within the field of the [[Humanities]]-especially a set of the Humanities falling under the large subdivision of the [[Social Sciences]]. Among the fields most contested are [[Women's Studies]], [[Cultural Studies]], [[Ethnic Studies]] or [[race relations|Racial Studies]]. Whether such field-specific attention is deserved is, once again, the subject of much intense debate.

When the criticism of political bias is set in the context of American [[liberals]] vs. American [[Conservatism|conservatives]], as it often is, the dialogue between the two sides can become rapidly polemical. One finds conservative critics called "anti-intellectuals" as they attempt to bring the charge of political bias against various liberals even as the accused liberals are charged with such things as "re-writing history" ([[Historical revisionism]]); the validity of each party's assertion must be recognized to vary from case to case.

=====Deficient programs=====
Another major concern centers on the perceived lack of general education in college curricula. Critics claim{{Who|date=November 2007}} , for example, that college students ought to take more [[humanities]] classes, such as history or literature, along with the requirements of their major. Notably, the [[humanities]] requirements in [[United States|American]] colleges are actually much greater than in many other countries, such as [[Russia]] or [[India]] where [[college]] instruction is focused almost entirely on professional, often technical, preparation.

=====Lack of usefulness=====
A third line of criticism, sometimes seeming to contradict the second, is the absence of 'real life' usefulness from the study of humanities. This has also contributed to anti-intellectualism, particularly among those who study, or have studied, [[technical]] subjects.  This is sometimes considered more of a 'rival-intellectualism' rather than true anti-intellectualism, inasmuch as people who have received university-level technical training have themselves engaged in an intellectual activity of great complexity.  This sort of antagonism is often exacerbated in universities when it comes to apportioning limited budgets and providing funding for professors and graduate students.  While it is often more expensive to hire and fund technical and engineering departments (often due to demands for labs, resources, computers, etc.) a university's budget committee may see them as having greater practical importance over the liberal arts.  Furthermore, grants and endowments to universities may come with stipulations requiring that the money go to programs that the benefactor views as useful.

== Anti-intellectualism in the United States ==
===19th Century culture===
19th century [[popular culture]] is important in the history of American anti-intellectualism.  At the time when the vast majority of the population led a [[rural]] life, full of [[manual labour|manual labor]] and [[agriculture]], bookish education, which at the time focused on [[classics]], was seen to have little value.  It should be noted that Americans of the era were generally very literate and, in fact, read [[William Shakespeare|Shakespeare]] much more than their present-day counterparts. {{Fact|date=November 2008}} However, the ideal at the time was an individual skilled and successful in his trade and a productive member of society; studies of [[classics]] and [[Latin]] in colleges were generally derided.{{Fact|date=November 2008}}

The 19th century predominantly valued the self-reliant and "self-made man," schooled by [[society]] and by experience, over the [[intellectual]] whose learning was acquired through books and formal study.  In 1843, [[Bayard R. Hall]] wrote of frontier [[Indiana]], that "(w)e always preferred an ignorant bad man to a talented one, and hence attempts were usually made to ruin the moral character of a smart candidate; since unhappily smartness and wickedness were supposed to be generally coupled, and incompetence and goodness." Still, there was a possibility for redemption if the "egghead" embraced common mores. A character of [[O. Henry]] noted that once a graduate of an [[East Coast of the United States|East Coast]] [[college]] gets over being vain, he makes just as good a [[cowboy]] as any other young man.    

The related stereotype of the slow-witted naïf with a heart of gold, which became popular in 19th century stage shows, still reappears in American culture, recently in the 1985  novel and 1994  motion picture ''[[Forrest Gump (film)|Forrest Gump]]''.

===20th and 21st century culture===
====Right-wing currents====
=====Conservative critiques of academia=====

[[Robert Warshow]] has put forth the hypothesis that the [[Communist Party USA|Communist Party]] became central to American intellectual life during the 1930s: 

:''For most American intellectuals, the Communist movement of the 1930s was a crucial experience.  In Europe, where the movement was at once more serious and more popular, it was still only one current in intellectual life; the Communists could never completely set the tone of thinking. . . . But in this country there was a time when virtually all intellectual vitality was derived in one way or another from the Communist party.  If you were not somewhere within the party’s wide orbit, then you were likely to be in the opposition, which meant that much of your thought and energy had to be devoted to maintaining yourself in opposition.''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fas.org/sgp/library/moynihan/appa7.html Report of the Commission on Protecting and Reducing Government Secrecy&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!--Moynihan Commission Report, quoted from Robert Warshow, ''The Legacy of the 30’s: Middle-Class Mass Culture and the Intellectuals’ Problem,'' Commentary Magazine (December 1947): 538, footnote 103.--&gt;

A more recent variant on this tendency is the so-called "academic freedom" movement, led by [[David Horowitz]] and his [[David Horowitz Freedom Center|Center for the Study of Popular Culture]], which claims the identity politics and left-wing views of certain academics are a means of indoctrinating university students with anti-American views&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.frontpagemag.com FrontPage Magazine&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;.

=====Religious fundamentalism=====
Some modern American anti-intellectualism originates from the view held by some [[conservative Christian]]s that the current form of public education subverts religious belief. The validity of this view was substantiated by the spread of [[atheism]] and [[Deism]] among the educated during the [[The Age of Enlightenment|Enlightenment]], and was deep-rooted even before that time. For instance, the [[New England]] writer and [[Puritan]] [[John Cotton (puritan)|John Cotton]] wrote in 1642, "The more learned and witty you bee, the more fit to act for [[Satan]] will you bee."  More recently, an anti-intellectual current is claimed by some in the works of [[Fundamentalist Christianity|Fundamentalist]] Christian cartoonist [[Jack Chick]].  In his anti-[[evolution]] tract ''Big Daddy?'' for example, he depicts the academic establishment as intolerant and elitist in their rejection of [[young earth creationism]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.chick.com/reading/tracts/0055/0055_01.asp Big Daddy?&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!-- Unsourced image removed: [[Image:Cartoon.jpg|thumb|200px|[[Political cartoon]] criticizing rural attitudes towards Evolution]] --&gt;
Some Christians also object to what they perceive as "un-Christian" elements in [[Education in the United States|public schools]] ([[K–12 education|K-12]]) and [[Higher education|colleges and universities]]. Focal points for fundamentalist criticism are [[sex education|comprehensive sex education]] and [[evolution]]. &lt;!--unsourced info removed: anti-[[prejudice]] programs and even [[Humanism|Humanist]] values.--&gt;

====Left-wing currents====
=====1960s student culture=====
Especially in the 1960s many student demonstrators{{Who|date=October 2008}} romanticized the impoverished populations of [[Appalachia]] and the [[Mississippi Delta]].{{Fact|date=October 2008}} The lack of formal education in these regions was seen as a sort of freedom from "conformist" society that allowed one to lead a more genuine and worthy life.{{Fact|date=October 2008}} The sanitized version of [[folk music]] that became popular on campus around this time is a related trend.{{Fact|date=October 2008}} 

The anti-war movement also despised the highly educated and objective Washington technocrat, epitomized by [[Robert McNamara]], who was not moved by subjective, irrational emotions. McNamara was alleged to make decisions solely on numbers and probabilities and could not see individual lives or deaths as anything but statistics. The Vietnam [[body count]] was offered as an example of this objectivity.

[[Theodor Adorno]], himself a Marxist, sharply criticised this trend in the '60s Left, which he called "[[actionism]]," defined as the belief that actions such as protests and strikes could change the political structure by themselves without being supported by solid theory and an organized program or party.

=====The intellectual as paid apologist for the status quo=====
Many on the left{{Who|date=March 2008}} have claimed that the intellectual's status as a "professional thinker" requires the support of a member of the ruling class willing to fund them.{{Fact|date=February 2007}} Therefore, most intellectuals, in order to maintain their profession, must assume a subservient posture towards the current power structure even when their ideas are outwardly "radical." These critics point out that many a tenured professor has called for revolution, but few have ever taken concrete steps to promote one. This has the effect of discrediting the idea of social change by associating it with hypocritical academics, thereby serving the status quo.

In return for their rhetorical services, so this theory goes, intellectuals are rewarded with the power to set themselves up as the social betters of the proletariat and are given a measure of control over  how normal people live their lives. In addition, when government actions go awry, intellectuals provide rulers with a convenient scapegoat - those who were paid to promote the policy can easily be blamed for creating it. 

Although not a leftist thinker, [[Eric Hoffer]] is closely associated with this view of intellectuals. He compared them to the scribes that directed the construction of the [[Egyptian pyramid|pyramids]] - seemingly authoritative figures, who were in reality servants to the [[Pharaoh]]. &lt;!-- Doesn't seem like a very good analogy to me. The Pharaohs were divine, they didn't need to hide behind the scribes/priests. --&gt;

====In the media====
In the US [[2000 Presidential Election]], the media (particularly late night comics) portrayed Candidate [[Al Gore]] as a boring "[[brainiac]]" who spoke in a monotonous voice and jabbered on about numbers and figures that no one could understand. His supposed "claim to have invented the Internet"&lt;ref&gt;[http://cnn.com/ALLPOLITICS/stories/1999/03/09/president.2000/transcript.gore/ Transcript: Vice President Gore on CNN's 'Late Edition' - March 9, 1999&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; was widely ridiculed. It was the classic stereotype of a pompous, out-of-touch intellectual, and this perception arguably hurt Gore in the election. In the years since, debate between the left and right in America has often centered on the relation of the intellectual class to the public as a whole.

Conservative commentators such as [[Ann Coulter]], [[Bill O'Reilly (commentator)|Bill O'Reilly]], and [[Rush Limbaugh]] commonly argue that conservative politicians, particularly [[Ronald Reagan]] and [[George W. Bush]], have been attacked by media as being "incompetent" - this can be understood as an accusation of intellectual snobbery by the media. O'Reilly in particular is well known for having a hostile attitude towards what he calls the "[[Ivy League]] Elite." The word "intellectual" itself has been used as an insult by many on the right.

Both O'Reilly and Limbaugh, as well as other conservative hosts such as [[Tucker Carlson]] and [[Joe Scarborough]] are frequently accused of having anti-intellectual atmospheres on their shows, evidenced by their frequent interruption of guests who try to put forward complex arguments. Scarborough once commented that, "If my guest is allowed to speak uninterrupted for more than 15 seconds, then I'm not doing my job."{{Fact|date=October 2008}}

=====[[Sensationalism]]=====

Some analysts feel the lack of intellectual content is representative of the media's propensity, in the service of higher [[ratings]], to promote argument and spectacle rather than informed debate. Among those analysts, scholars such as [[Noam Chomsky]] believe that this [[soundbite]] atmosphere of the media inherently promotes pro-[[establishment]] views and aids in the [[Manufacturing Consent|manufacture of consent]].

There is a strong feeling on both sides of the political divide that corporate news focuses too much on soundbites and [[headlines]], and not enough on in-depth reporting. Researchers have noticed a trend in the amount of coverage newspapers and broadcast networks devote to various subjects: World events and political coverage are receiving a declining percentage of print space and airtime, while crimes, sex scandals, and celebrity intrigue take up more and more space.{{Fact|date=February 2007}}. ''See also:'' [[Junk food news]].

This trend is clearly visible on cable television as well. For example, [[The Learning Channel]] has shifted from airing purely documentary and informational content to devoting a large portion of its programming to makeover specials, home-remodeling shows, and programs focused on muscle cars and motorcycles.{{Fact|date=February 2007}}. ''See also:'' [[Oprah#Criticisms and controversies|Criticisms of Oprah Winfrey]].

==Anti-intellectualism in the Soviet Union==
{{Articleissues|OR=October 2008|weasel=October 2008|unreferenced=October 2008}}
In the [[Soviet Union]], within the first decade after the [[Russian Revolution of 1917|Revolution of 1917]], the [[Bolsheviks]] generally scorned and suspected the educated as potential traitors to the cause of the proletariat.{{Fact|date=October 2008}} Whereas the core of the [[Communist]] Party was well-educated, the people who became local activists and officials in [[government]] and [[industry]] often lacked at least formal education and disdained those who had it.{{Fact|date=October 2008}} [[Lenin]] once called the [[intelligentsia]], particularly those who opposed him, "rotten" and "shit".{{Fact|date=June 2007}} The boast, roughly translated as "we ain't completed no academies" ("мы академиев не кончали") became a byword for the new ruling [[elite]].{{Fact|date=June 2007}}

Later on, the Soviet government came to see education as important and dedicated great resources to literacy on the one hand, and higher and professional education on the other. However, as a matter of social policy, the government sought to promote the [[working class]] over an intellectual elite. Accordingly, industrial workers often received greater salaries than university-trained professionals such as [[teacher]]s, [[medical doctor|doctors]], and [[engineer]]s. Moreover, workers were covertly inculcated with the notion that only the manual labor creates real value in the economy, whereas the educated people just sit around writing papers.{{Fact|date=August 2007}}

It must be stressed, however, that the anti-intellectualism of the Soviet political elite was closely associated with the fact that the Russian academic milieu, as a part of the tsarist state apparatus, had been hostile to the 1917 Bolshevik takeover almost by definition; however, when dealing with practical issues such as economic and scientific management, the early Soviet regime had to resort to such "bourgeois experts", therefore the tense relationship between the Communist Party elite and non-Party educated people. It was only during the early 1930s that [[Stalin]] attempted to replace the old intelligentsia with a new, Party-approved group.{{Fact|date=October 2008}} Such favouring of ''partinost'' - that is to say, a partisan stance towards all matters intellectual - over formal scholarship, no matter how crude such partisan stance happened to be - in the end amounted to a clear anti-intellectual stance.{{Fact|date=October 2008}}   

The Soviet treatment of science is an example of anti-intellectualism - the triumph of [[Lysenkoism]] in Soviet Russia was a result of political bullying of scientists and the punishment of dissenters rather than the normal scientific process of publishing one's findings{{Fact|date=March 2008}}.

==Anti-intellectualism in Asia -  China, Cambodia and Iran==

Asian anti-intellectualism has deep roots. Even the [[Tao Te Ching]] advises rulers to keep their subjects with a "full belly and an empty mind" and that "ignorance is better than knowledge" among the people. Additionally, [[Qin Shi Huang]], the first emperor of China, even was one of the most prominent to show anti-intellectualism by distrusting scholars and forcing the educated into labor, and [[Burning of books and burying of scholars|burning texts]] written by historians or by Confucian scholars.

A number of Asian countries have experienced degrees of anti-intellectualism in the 20th century.

In [[Cambodia]], a country where few people have access to formal education (the literacy rate is about 50% as of 2004), the [[Khmer Rouge]] regime (1975&amp;ndash;1979) was generally disdainful of intellectuals and saw many as enemies or traitors (see also: [[Democratic Kampuchea]]). In some sectors, anyone who wore glasses was shot by Khmer guards, as glasses were seen as a mark of education and intellectualism.

The revolutionary regime in the newly established [[Islamic Republic of Iran]] also displayed a streak of anti-intellectualism in its policies. Besides the emigration of many well-educated, western-trained, intellectuals in the wake of the revolution ([[Brain drain]]), the government decreed in 1980 that all universities are to be closed until the curricula are "purified" from the corrupt Pahlavi legacy. The ban on secular high education persisted until 1982. Also, the repressive attitude of the regime toward Iranian intelligentsia is well known (a highly publicized case of intellectual repression was the execution of the poet [[Said Soltanpour]] in 1981).

==Anti-intellectualism in the classical world==
The [[Roman Republic|Roman]] statesman [[Cato the Elder]]'s public career displayed many traits that today would be considered anti-intellectual. He vehemently opposed the introduction of [[ancient Greece|Greek]] cultural ideals and models into the Roman republic, believing them to be subversive of traditional plainspokenness and rugged military values. He urged the [[Roman Senate]] to pass its decree against the newly imported [[Bacchanalia]]n [[mystery religion|mysteries]], which it did in the ''Senatus consultum de Bacchanalibus'' in 186 BC. He urged the deportation of three [[Athens|Athenian]] philosophers, [[Carneades]], [[Diogenes the Stoic]], and [[Critolaus]], who had been sent to [[Rome]] as [[ambassador]]s from Athens, on the grounds that he believed the opinions they expressed were dangerous. The Emperor [[Augustus]] also exiled many philosophers.

However, rulers in the ancient and classical worlds were generally intolerant of anyone who disagreed with them. Anti-intellectualism as hostility by self-identified "common" people, or those that claim to speak for them, against a ''perceived class'' of cultural elites is generally considered a modern phenomenon.

== See also ==
* [[Anti-globalization]]
* [[Anti-science]]
* [[Atheists in foxholes]]
* [[Appeal to emotion]]
* [[Boffin]]
* [[Burning of books and burying of scholars]]
* [[Creation-evolution controversy]]
* [[Cultural Cringe|Cultural Cringe (Colonial Anti-Intellectualism)]]
* [[Frugality]]
* [[God complex]]
* [[Handicapper General|Handicapper General (primarily associated with U.S. anti-intellectualism)]]
* [[Infidel]]s
* [[Keeping up with the Joneses]]
* [[Lysenkoism]]
* [[Luddite]]
* [[Nerd]]
* [[Obscurantism]]
* [[Philistinism]]
* [[Pseudo-philosophy]]
* [[Populism]]
* [[Pragmatism]] 
* [[Propaganda]]
* [[Tall Poppy Syndrome|Tall Poppy Syndrome (Australian anti-intellectualism)]]
* [[The Professors: The 101 Most Dangerous Academics in America]]
* [[Truthiness]]
* [[Dumbing down]]

==References==
{{reflist}}
{{refbegin}}
*''[[Anti-intellectualism in American Life]]'', by [[Richard Hofstadter]]: ISBN 0-394-70317-0
*''Anti-Intellectualism in American Media,'' by Dane S. Claussen: New York: Peter Lang Publishing, 2004. ISBN 0-8204-5721-3
*''Evening Chats in Beijing: Probing China's Predicament,'' by Perry Link: New York, London: W.W. Norton &amp; Company, 1991. ISBN 0393310655 
*Hinton, William. ''Hundred Day War: The Cultural Revolution at Tsinghua University''. New York: New York UP, 1972. ISBN 0-85345-281-4.
*[http://www.fas.org/sgp/library/moynihan/appa7.html Moynihan Commission Report, Appendix A, 7. The Cold War, footnote 103] quoted from Robert Warshow, ''The Legacy of the 30’s: Middle-Class Mass Culture and the Intellectuals’ Problem,'' Commentary Magazine (December 1947): 538.
*[http://www.leftbusinessobserver.com/Action.html "Action Will be Taken" Left Anti-Intelectualism and its Discontents] by Liza Featherstone, Doug Henwood, and Christian Parenti (Left Business Observer)
{{refend}}

[[Category:Academia]]
[[Category:Anti-intellectualism|*]]

[[cy:Gwrthddeallaeth]]
[[nl:Anti-intellectualisme]]
[[pt:Antiintelectualismo]]
[[ru:Антиинтеллектуализм]]
[[sv:Antiintellektualism]]
[[zh:反智主义]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>