<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20210917232004|1044954075" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1125781" pageid="1125781" ns="0" title="Voter suppression"><revisions><rev timestamp="2021-11-14T21:05:04Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Strategy designed to restrict specific groups of people from voting}}
[[File:Voters at the voting booths in 1945.jpg|thumb|[[Voting|Voters]] at [[voting booth]]s in the United States in 1945]]
[[File:Iraqi voters in Baghdad2.jpg|right|thumb|300px|Voters lining up outside a [[Baghdad]] polling station during the [[January 2005 Iraqi legislative election|2005 Iraqi election]]. Voter turnout was considered high despite widespread concerns of violence.]]
{{Discrimination sidebar|state=collapsed}}
'''Voter suppression''' is a strategy used to influence the outcome of an [[election]] by discouraging or preventing specific groups of people from [[voting]]. It is distinguished from [[political campaigning]] in that campaigning attempts to change likely voting behavior by changing the opinions of potential voters through persuasion and organization, activating otherwise inactive voters, or registering new supporters. Voter suppression, instead, attempts to reduce the number of voters who might vote against a candidate or proposition.

The tactics of voter suppression range from minor changes that make voting less convenient,  to physically intimidating and even physically attacking prospective voters, which is illegal. Voter suppression can be effective if a significant number of voters are intimidated or disenfranchised.&lt;ref name="Powers"&gt;{{cite news | last = Powers | first = Scott |author2=David Damron | title =Analysis: 201,000 in Florida didn't vote because of long lines | newspaper = [[Orlando Sentinel]] | location = Orlando, FL | date = January 29, 2013 | url =http://articles.orlandosentinel.com/2013-01-29/business/os-voter-lines-statewide-20130118_1_long-lines-sentinel-analysis-state-ken-detzner | access-date = 2016-02-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2013, the [[Supreme Court of the United States|United States Supreme Court]] ruled in ''[[Shelby v. Holder]]'' that voting laws had resulted in voter suppression and discrimination.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.politico.com/story/2013/06/voting-rights-act-harry-reid-senate-93344.html|title=Harry Reid: Senate 'will act' on Voting Rights Act|last=Van Dongen|first=Rachel|date=25 June 2013|access-date=5 July 2013|newspaper=Politico|author2=Everett, Burgess}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Examples==
===Australia===

In Australia citizens are expected to enroll to vote and it is their responsibility to update their enrollment when they change their address. Even so, it is estimated that about 6% of eligible Australian voters are not enrolled, or are enrolled incorrectly. These are disproportionately younger voters, many of whom might neglect to enroll when they attain [[voting age]].

In 2006, the [[Howard Government]] legislated to close the electoral roll much earlier once an election was called. While previously, voters had been allowed seven days of grace after an election had been called to arrange or update their enrollment, new voters were now allowed only until 8:00 pm on the day that the electoral [[Writ of election|writ]] was issued to lodge their enrollment form, while those who needed to update their addresses were allowed three days. In Australia, the [[Prime Minister of Australia|Prime Minister]] effectively has the right to determine the date of the election, so long as constitutional rules regarding the maximum term of the parliament are adhered to. This measure was therefore likely to result in many newer voters being precluded from voting in the first election for which they were eligible because the time to arrange their enrollment once an election is called had been greatly reduced.

The measure was widely seen as an attempt at voter suppression aimed at younger voters,&lt;ref&gt;Orr, Graeme [http://inside.org.au/court-by-surprise-the-high-court-upholds-voting-rights/ "Court by surprise: the High Court upholds voting rights"], 6 August 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; surveys had shown that younger voters are more likely than the general population to vote for the [[Australian Labor Party]] or the [[Australian Greens|Greens]] than the [[Liberal Party of Australia|Liberal Party]].&lt;ref&gt;Brooker, Ron [http://resources.news.com.au/files/2011/07/22/1226099/942923-aus-file-young-voters.pdf "Youth Federal Election Voting Intentions: A Statistical and Graphical Analysis of Newspoll Quarterly Data 1996–2010"], The Whitlam Institute, June 2011&lt;/ref&gt; The Government denied that they were trying to suppress some voters, insisting that the purpose of the reform was to smooth the administration of elections and to reduce the possibility of electoral fraud. This was in spite of the fact that the [[Australian Electoral Commission]] had requested no such reform, there was no evidence of significant electoral fraud and that the Australian Electoral Commission had been dealing with hundreds of thousands of late enrollments without significant problems for decades.

In July 2010, the [[Left-wing politics|left-leaning]] lobby group [[GetUp!]] launched a challenge to this law. The [[High Court of Australia]] expedited the hearing so that a ruling could be made in time for the [[2010 Australian federal election|2010 federal election]]. The majority ruling struck down early closing of the roll, reinstating the old rule allowing voters seven days grace to arrange or update their enrollment.

Australian citizens of the ages 16 or 17 can enroll online&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aec.gov.au/enrol/ enroll online]&lt;/ref&gt; so that when they turn 18 they are able to vote.

=== Canada ===

Shortly before the [[2011 Canadian federal election|Canadian 2011 Federal Election]], vote suppression tactics were [[2011 Canadian federal election voter suppression scandal|exercised by issuing robocalls and live calls to falsely advise voters]] that their polling station had changed. The locations offered by these messages were intentionally false, often to lead voters several hours from the correct stations, and often identified themselves illegally as coming from [[Elections Canada]].&lt;ref name="canconrobocall"&gt;{{cite news
  | title =Robocalls complaints came 3 days before 2011 election
  | publisher = CBC News
  | date =2012-11-19
  | url =http://www.cbc.ca/news/politics/story/2012/11/19/pol-elections-canada-emails-show-complaints-robocalls.html
  | access-date = 2012-11-19 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In litigation brought by [[The Council of Canadians]], a federal court found that such fraud had occurred and had probably been perpetrated by someone with access to the [[Conservative Party of Canada|Conservative Party]]'s voter database, including its information about voter preferences.&lt;ref name="MacCharles"&gt;{{cite news | last = MacCharles| first = Tonda| title = Robocalls: Widespread but ‘thinly scattered’ vote suppression didn’t affect election, judge rules| newspaper = [[Toronto Star]] | date = May 23, 2013 | url = https://www.thestar.com/news/canada/2013/05/23/robocalls_widespread_but_thinly_scattered_vote_suppression_didnt_affect_election_judge_rules.html | access-date = 2013-05-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The court stated that the evidence did not prove that the Conservative Party or its successful candidates were directly involved.&lt;ref name="MacCharles"/&gt;  It did, however, criticize the Conservative Party for making “little effort to assist with the investigation”.&lt;ref name="MacCharles"/&gt;  The court did not annul the result in any of six [[Electoral district (Canada)|ridings]] where the fraud had occurred, because it concluded that the number of votes affected had been too small to affect the outcome.&lt;ref name="MacCharles"/&gt;

=== France ===
In France being registered on voting lists is not systematical, neither arriving majority age, neither if changing of address, neither if having already been registering on lists.
The registration might still be done at times even without any demand to register voters without them asking, but it is not mandatory for authorities.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Listes électorales : nouvelle inscription|trans-title=Election lists: new registration|url=https://www.service-public.fr/particuliers/vosdroits/F1367|url-status=live|access-date=2021-05-15|website=www.service-public.fr|language=Fr}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Israel ===

In April 2019, during [[Israel]]'s general elections for the 21st [[Knesset]], [[Likud]] activists installed hidden cameras in polling stations in [[Arab citizens of Israel|Arab communities]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.ynetnews.com/articles/0,7340,L-5491778,00.html|title=Outrage as Likud activists secretly film voting in Arab communities|date=2019-09-04|website=Ynetnews|language=en|access-date=2019-04-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Election observers]] were seen wearing such cameras.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|last=ynet|title=משקיפים של הליכוד עם מצלמות נסתרות על מצביעים בקלפיות|date=2019-04-10|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Lr0pbIkoWuI|access-date=2019-04-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Hanan Melcer]], the Head of the General Elections Committee, said the cameras were illegal.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.i24news.tv/en/news/israel/society/1554799171-fears-of-meddling-mounts-as-numerous-complaints-are-registered|title=i24NEWS|website=www.i24news.tv|access-date=2019-04-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; The following day, PR agency Kaizler Inbar took credit for the operation and said it had been planned in collaboration with Likud. They additionally claimed that voter turnout in Arab communities had fallen under 50% thanks to the presence of the agency's observers in the polling stations,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.facebook.com/Kaizler.Inbar/posts/441952923292920|title=קייזלר ענבר|website=www.facebook.com|language=en|access-date=2019-04-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; though there is little evidence that the cameras had any effect on the voter turnout, as the Arab population had been promising to boycott the election well in advance.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Israel's young Arab citizens call for election boycott|url=https://www.jpost.com/israel-elections/israels-young-arab-citizens-call-for-election-boycott-585859|access-date=2020-07-05|website=The Jerusalem Post {{!}} JPost.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Taiwan ===
Political participation is crucial in a democratic country like Taiwan. The analysis of the voting turnout in Taiwan has been extremely high compared to other democratic countries. However, the voting suppression in this country focuses on two main factors of age and ethnicity. Thus, the voting suppression in Taiwan is individuals that are higher in age because of poor health. There are three voting groups that are in Taiwan- Pan-Blue supporters, Pan-Green, and independents. Voters that classified them to be independents are less likely to vote because of receiving less political information. Thus, the inadequate advertisement of political information for the people contributes to voting suppression as many people are not equally well-informed.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|last=Wu|first=Chung-li|title=Political Participation in Taiwan|date=2017|url=https://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctvndv9z7.14|work=The Taiwan Voter|pages=252–272|editor-last=Achen|editor-first=Christopher H.|publisher=University of Michigan Press|isbn=978-0-472-07353-5|access-date=2020-11-11|last2=Liu|first2=Tzu-Ping|editor2-last=Wang|editor2-first=T. Y.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another factor is understanding the difference in ethnic backgrounds between Minnan and mainlanders affect their participation in political life.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Batto|first=Nathan F.|date=2020-08-20|title=The Taiwan Voter, edited by Christopher H. Achen and T.Y. Wang (2017)|url=http://dx.doi.org/10.1163/24688800-00302010|journal=International Journal of Taiwan Studies|volume=3|issue=2|pages=363–366|doi=10.1163/24688800-00302010|issn=2468-8797}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===United Kingdom===

[[Lutfur Rahman (British politician)|Lutfur Rahman]] was the [[directly elected mayor of Tower Hamlets]] for the [[United Kingdom Labour Party|Labour Party]], in London until he was removed from office for breaching electoral rules.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Tower Hamlets election fraud mayor Lutfur Rahman removed from office|work=[[BBC News]]|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-england-london-32428648|date=23 April 2015|access-date=23 April 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; His supporters allegedly intimidated voters at polling stations.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|last=Syal|first=Rajeev|last2=Quinn|first2=Ben|date=2015-04-23|title=Met considers criminal inquiry into Tower Hamlets mayor Lutfur Rahman|language=en-GB|work=The Guardian|url=https://www.theguardian.com/politics/2015/apr/23/tower-hamlets-mayor-lutfur-rahman-found-guilty-of-electoral|access-date=2020-07-05|issn=0261-3077}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===United States===

{{main|Voter suppression in the United States}}
In the [[United States]], elections are administered locally, and forms of voter suppression vary among jurisdictions. At the founding of the country, the right to vote in most states was limited to property-owning white males.&lt;ref name="Carroll2003"&gt;Bret Carroll. ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=c5t2AwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA89 American Masculinities: A Historical Encyclopedia]''. SAGE Publications; 14 October 2003. {{ISBN|978-1-4522-6571-1}}. p. 89.&lt;/ref&gt; Over time, the right to vote was formally granted to racial minorities, women, and youth.&lt;ref name="Rivers2012"&gt;Christina Rivers. ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=q-666oIQaQUC&amp;pg=PA148 The Congressional Black Caucus, Minority Voting Rights, and the U.S. Supreme Court]''. University of Michigan Press; 17 July 2012. {{ISBN|0-472-11810-2}}. pp. 146–48.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Macbain-Stephens2006"&gt;Jennifer Macbain-Stephens. ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=eB6sDQIBUdoC Women's Suffrage: Giving the Right to Vote to All Americans]''. Rosen Classroom; January 2006. {{ISBN|978-1-4042-0869-8}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Amendments1970"&gt;United States. Congress. Senate. Committee on the Judiciary. Subcommittee on Constitutional Amendments. ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=-acTAAAAIAAJ Lowering the voting age to 18: Hearings, Ninety-first Congress, second session]''. U.S. Govt. Print. Off. 1970.&lt;/ref&gt; During the later 19th and early 20th centuries, Southern states passed [[Jim Crow laws]] to suppress poor and racial minority voters – such laws included [[Poll tax (United States)|poll taxes]], [[literacy test]]s, and [[grandfather clause]]s.&lt;ref name="Johnson2010"&gt;Kimberley Johnson. ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=dnfNBgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT97 Reforming Jim Crow: Southern Politics and State in the Age Before Brown]''. Oxford University Press; 16 April 2010. {{ISBN|978-0-19-988904-4}}. p. 97.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Klarman2004"&gt;Michael J. Klarman. ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=WWl0aWMSWSMC&amp;pg=PA70 From Jim Crow to Civil Rights: The Supreme Court and the Struggle for Racial Equality]''. Oxford University Press; 5 February 2004. {{ISBN|978-0-19-535167-5}}. p. 70.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Hazen2004"&gt;Walter Hazen. ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=64PxCgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA38 The Civil War to the Jim Crow Laws: American Black History]''. Milliken Publishing Company; 1 September 2004. {{ISBN|978-0-7877-2730-7}}. p. 38.&lt;/ref&gt; Most of these voter suppression tactics were made illegal after the enactment of the [[Voting Rights Act of 1965]]. Even after the repeal of the Jim Crow laws that were implemented by these statutes, there have been repetitive incidents of racial discrimination  against voters in Southern States. Specifically, in 2018, 87,000 people in Georgia were unable to vote because of late registration. Many of the states with the strictest voting regulations are swing states, which have been enacted primarily by politicians who represent the Republican party.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Kauffman|first=Angela Caputo, Geoff Hing, and Johnny|title=A Georgia law prevented 87,000 people from voting last year. And it could have a big impact in 2020|url=https://www.apmreports.org/story/2019/10/28/georgia-voting-deadlines-2020-election|access-date=2020-10-07|website=www.apmreports.org}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to AMP Reports, many people who were predicted to be in favor of voting for the Democratic party had their ballot dismissed, as the study showed in an analysis that "A disproportionate number of those potential voters were people of color or young voters, groups that typically favor Democrats."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Kauffman|first=Angela Caputo, Geoff Hing, and Johnny|title=A Georgia law prevented 87,000 people from voting last year. And it could have a big impact in 2020|url=https://www.apmreports.org/story/2019/10/28/georgia-voting-deadlines-2020-election|access-date=2020-10-07|website=www.apmreports.org}}&lt;/ref&gt; The history of the previous Jim Crow regulations in the southern states affects the voter suppression today because people that fall into the minority category often have their vote dismissed, due to manipulation of voting regulations.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Constitutional Rights Foundation|url=https://www.crf-usa.org/black-history-month/race-and-voting-in-the-segregated-south|access-date=2020-10-07|website=www.crf-usa.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2013, [[voter ID laws]] arose following the Supreme Court's decision to strike down Section 4 of the Voting Rights Act, which some argue amounts to voter suppression against African-Americans.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Childress|first1=Sarah|title=With Voting Rights Act Out, States Push Voter ID Laws|url=https://www.pbs.org/wgbh/frontline/article/with-voting-rights-act-out-states-push-voter-id-laws/|work=FRONTLINE|publisher=PBS|date=June 26, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Childress|first1=Sarah|title=Supreme Court Strikes Blow to Voting Rights Act: What's Next?|url=https://www.pbs.org/wgbh/frontline/article/supreme-court-strikes-blow-to-voting-rights-act-whats-next/|work=FRONTLINE|publisher=PBS|date=June 25, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Texas, a voter ID law requiring a driver's license, passport, military identification, or gun permit, was repeatedly found to be intentionally discriminatory. The state's election laws could be put back under the control of the U.S. Department of Justice (DOJ). Under Attorney General [[Jeff Sessions]], however, the DOJ has expressed support for Texas's ID law.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2017/08/a-court-strikes-down-texass-voter-id-law-for-the-fifth-time/537792/|title=A Court Strikes Down Texas's Voter ID Law For the Fifth Time|date=August 24, 2017|website=The Atlantic}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sessions was accused by [[Coretta Scott King]] in 1986 of trying to suppress the black vote.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |newspaper=The Washington Post |date=January 10, 2017 |title=Read the letter Coretta Scott King wrote opposing Sessions’s 1986 federal nomination |url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/powerpost/wp/2017/01/10/read-the-letter-coretta-scott-king-wrote-opposing-sessionss-1986-federal-nomination/}}&lt;/ref&gt; A similar ID law in North Dakota, which would have disenfranchised large numbers of Native Americans, was also overturned.&lt;ref name="nprvote"&gt;{{cite web |website=NPR |date=August 2, 2016 |title=As November Approaches, Courts Deal Series Of Blows To Voter ID Laws |url=https://www.npr.org/sections/thetwo-way/2016/08/02/488392765/as-november-approaches-courts-deal-series-of-blows-to-voter-id-laws}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Wisconsin, a federal judge found that the state's restrictive voter ID law led to "real incidents of disenfranchisement, which undermine rather than enhance confidence in elections, particularly in minority communities";&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://hyp.is/Mrc_rAC9EeiVTFMDt_YwQA/elections.wi.gov/sites/default/files/news/petersonruling_pdf_14890.pdf|title=Case: 3:15-cv-00324-jdp Document #: 234 In the United States District Court for the Western District of Wisconsin|access-date=January 23, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; and, given that there was no evidence of widespread voter impersonation in Wisconsin, found that the law was "a cure worse than the disease." In addition to imposing strict voter ID requirements, the law cut back on early voting, required people to live in a ward for at least 28 days before voting, and prohibited emailing absentee ballots to voters.&lt;ref name="nprvote" /&gt;

Other controversial measures include shutting down [[Department of Motor Vehicles]] (DMV) offices in minority neighborhoods, making it more difficult for residents to obtain voter IDs;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |website=CNN |title=DOT launches investigation in Alabama over DMV closures |date=December 9, 2015 |url=http://www.cnn.com/2015/12/09/politics/alabama-dmv-closures-voting-rights/index.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |website=Esquire |title=The State of Alabama Has Fully Lost Its Mind |date=April 12, 2017 |url=http://www.esquire.com/news-politics/politics/news/a54465/alabama-bentley-resign-church-police/}}&lt;/ref&gt; shutting down polling places in minority neighborhoods;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |website=The Nation |title=There Are 868 Fewer Places to Vote in 2016 Because the Supreme Court Gutted the Voting Rights Act |date=November 4, 2016 |url=https://www.thenation.com/article/there-are-868-fewer-places-to-vote-in-2016-because-the-supreme-court-gutted-the-voting-rights-act/}}&lt;/ref&gt; systematically depriving precincts in minority neighborhoods of the resources they need to operate efficiently, such as poll workers and voting machines;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |newspaper=The New York Times |title=Long Lines at Minority Polling Places |date=September 24, 2014 |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2014/09/25/opinion/long-lines-at-minority-polling-places.html?_r=1}}&lt;/ref&gt; and purging voters from the rolls shortly before an election.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |newspaper=The New York Times |title=Ruling Preserves Voting Rights for Thousands in North Carolina |date=November 4, 2016 |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2016/11/05/us/north-carolina-voting-rights.html?_r=0}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Often, voter fraud is cited as a justification for such laws even when the incidence of voter fraud is low. In Iowa, lawmakers passed a strict voter ID law with the potential to disenfranchise 260,000 voters. Out of 1.6 million votes cast in Iowa in 2016, there were only 10 allegations of voter fraud; none were cases of impersonation that a voter ID law could have prevented.  Iowa Secretary of State Paul Pate, the architect of the bill, admitted, "We've not experienced widespread voter fraud in Iowa."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |website=The Nation |title=Iowa’s New Voter-ID Law Would Have Disenfranchised My Grandmother |date=April 13, 2017 |url=https://www.thenation.com/article/iowas-new-voter-id-law-would-have-disenfranchised-my-grandmother/}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In May 2017, President Donald Trump established the [[Presidential Advisory Commission on Election Integrity]], for the purpose of preventing voter fraud. Critics have suggested its true purpose is voter suppression. The commission is led by Kansas secretary of state [[Kris Kobach]], a staunch advocate of strict voter ID laws and a proponent of the Crosscheck system. Crosscheck is a national database designed to check for voters who are registered in more than one state by comparing names and dates of birth. Researchers at Stanford University, the University of Pennsylvania, Harvard University, and Microsoft found that for every legitimate instance of double registration it finds, Crosscheck's algorithm returns approximately 200 false positives.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |newspaper=The Washington Post |date=June 30, 2017 |title=How Trump’s nationwide voter data request could lead to voter suppression |url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/wonk/wp/2017/06/30/how-trumps-nationwide-voter-data-request-could-lead-to-voter-suppression/}}&lt;/ref&gt; Kobach has been repeatedly sued by the [[American Civil Liberties Union]] (ACLU) for trying to restrict voting rights in Kansas.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |newspaper=The New York Times |date=June 13, 2017 |title=The Man Behind Trump’s Voter-Fraud Obsession |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2017/06/13/magazine/the-man-behind-trumps-voter-fraud-obsession.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url= https://theintercept.com/2016/10/27/voter-suppression-is-the-real-election-scandal/ |title=Voter Suppression is the Real Election Scandal| work=[[The Intercept]]|date= October 27, 2016| author=Speri, Alice}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Social media impact on voting suppression  ==
Social media platforms, specifically Facebook contains 2.4{{nbsp}}billion active users.&lt;ref name="Singh 2020 15–21"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Singh|first=Spandana|last2=Blase|first2=Margerite|date=2020|title=Facebook/Instagram|url=https://www.jstor.org/stable/resrep26363.6|pages=15–21}}&lt;/ref&gt; The content in regards to election voting on social media includes misinformation and disinformation which contribute to voter suppression. The [[Brennan Center for Justice]] identifies several kinds of "voter suppression messages" used by Russia-linked accounts in the 2016 US Presidential election: misinformation about the time or location for voting, promoting attacks against Clinton to discourage supporters, and urging voters to boycott the election or to cast a vote for a third-party candidate.&lt;ref name="BC2020"&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www.brennancenter.org/our-work/analysis-opinion/new-evidence-shows-how-russias-election-interference-has-gotten-more
|title=New Evidence Shows How Russia’s Election Interference Has Gotten More Brazen
|last=Kim
|first=Young Mie
|publisher=Brennan Center
|quote=Drawing upon the literature (e.g., Wang 2012), I define voter suppression as a strategy to break the coalition of the opposition. Accordingly, I identify four types of voter suppression messages: election boycott, deception (lying about time, location or manner of voting), third-party candidate promotion (e.g., the promotion of Jill Stein targeting likely Hillary Clinton voters), and same-side candidate attack (i.e., an in-kind candidate attack, such as an attack on Clinton targeting likely Clinton voters).
|date=March 5, 2020
|access-date=September 17, 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==

* [[American Center for Voting Rights]]
* [[Electoral fraud]]
* [[Gerrymandering]]
* [[Political corruption]]
* [[Voter caging]]
* [[Voter ID laws in the United States]]
* [[Voter registration]]
* [[Voter turnout]]

==Further reading==

* Rick L. Hasen. 2020. ''Election Meltdown: Dirty Tricks, Distrust, and the Threat to American Democracy''. Yale University Press.

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* {{citation |work=[[Core.ac.uk]] |quote= [[Open access]] research papers |url= https://core.ac.uk/search?q=%22voter%2Bsuppression%22 |title= Voter+suppression }} {{open access}}

{{Corruption}}
{{Discrimination}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Voter Suppression}}
[[Category:Voter suppression| ]]
[[Category:Political campaign techniques]]
[[Category:Political corruption]]
[[Category:Electoral fraud]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Injustice]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>