<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20070609025751|136966475" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1125781" pageid="1125781" ns="0" title="Voter suppression"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-10-22T06:39:39Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{globalize/USA}}
{{PoliticalCampaigns}}
'''Voter suppression''' is a form of [[electoral fraud]] and refers to the use of governmental power, political campaign strategy, and private resources aimed at suppressing (i.e. reducing) the total vote of opposition candidacies instead of attempting to change likely voting behavior by changing the opinions of potential voters. This method is particularly effective if a significant amount of voters are intimidated individually because the voter might not consider his single vote important. 

==Voter suppression by governmental power==
In the [[United States]], voter suppression was used extensively in some [[U.S. Southern states|Southern state]]s until the [[Voting Rights Act]] ([[1965]]) made most disenfranchisement and voting qualifications illegal.  Traditional voter suppression tactics included the institution of poll taxes and literacy tests, aimed at suppressing the votes of African Americans and working class white voters. 

Measures in place in seven U.S. states ban released [[felony|felon]]s from voting; some allege that this is a tactic aimed at suppressing voter turnout.  Occasionally, as in [[Florida]] in the [[U.S. presidential election, 2000|2000 presidential election]], some non-felons are banned due to [[Florida Central Voter File|record-keeping errors]] and are not warned of their disqualification before they have the right to contest it.

==Voter suppression by campaign organizations==
In the [[2002 New Hampshire Senate election phone jamming scandal]], Republican officials attempted to reduce the number of Democratic voters by paying professional telemarketers in Idaho to make repeated hang-up calls to block Democrats' ride-to-the-polls phone lines on election day.&lt;ref name="dojjamming"&gt;{{cite press release
  | title =Former RNC New England Regional Director Indicted in New Hampshire Phone Jamming Case
  | publisher = US DOJ
  | date =2004-12-01
  | url =http://www.usdoj.gov/opa/pr/2004/December/04_crm_768.htm
  | accessdate = 2007-05-25 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="jammerconvict"&gt;{{cite news
  | title =Former GOP Official Gets Prison Term for Phone Plot
  | publisher =AP
  | date =2006-05-17
  | url =http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,195914,00.html
  | accessdate = 2007-05-25 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[2006]], four employees of the [[John Kerry]] campaign&lt;ref name="slashcharged"&gt;{{cite news 
  | last =Ehlke
  | first =Gretchen
  | title =Congresswoman's son, four others charged with slashing Republican van tires on Election Day
  | publisher =AP
  | date =2005-01-24
  | url =http://web.archive.org/web/20050829020422/http://sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/news/a/2005/01/24/national1242EST0521.DTL
  | accessdate = 2007-05-25 }}&lt;/ref&gt; were convicted&lt;ref name="slashconvicted"&gt;{{cite news 
  | last =Ehlke
  | first =Gretchen
  | title =Men Get Jail Time In Milwaukee Tire-Slashing Case
  | publisher =AP
  | date =2006-04-26
  | url =http://web.archive.org/web/20060503003521/http://wfrv.com/topstories/local_story_116123954.html
  | accessdate = 2007-05-25 }}&lt;/ref&gt; of slashing the tires of 25 vans rented by the state [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican Party]].  The party planned to drive poll watchers to polling places by 7 a.m. the day of the [[United States general election, 2004|2004 general election]], and then deliver any voters who didn't have a ride.&lt;ref name="slashcharged"/&gt; At the campaign workers' sentencing, Judge Michael B. Brennan told the defendants, "Voter suppression has no place in our country. Your crime took away that right to vote for some citizens."&lt;ref name="slashconvicted"/&gt;

[[Caging list]]s have been used by political parties to eliminate potential voters from the other party's voting roll.  A political party sends registered mail to addresses of registered voters. If the mail is returned as undeliverable the party uses that fact to challenge the registration, arguing that because the voter could not be reached at the address, the registration is fraudulent.

==Voter suppression by front organizations==
During the [[United States presidential election, 2004|2004 election]] allegations surfaced in several states that the group called [[Voters Outreach of America]] had collected and submitted Republican voter registration forms while inappropriately disposing of Democratic registration forms.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
  |url=http://www.klas-tv.com/Global/story.asp?S=2421595&amp;nav=168XRvNe
  |title=Investigation into Trashed Voter Registrations
  |date=2004-10-13
  |publisher=KLAS-TV
  |author=George Knapp
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
  |url=http://edition.cnn.com/2004/ALLPOLITICS/10/14/nevada.registration/index.html
  |title=Nevada investigates voter registration, Probe also under way in Oregon on fraud allegations
  |date=2004-10-14
  |publisher=[[CNN]]
  |author=
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite news
  |url=http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2004/10/14/politics/main649380.shtml
  |title=Voter Fraud Charges Out West
  |date=2004-10-14
  |publisher=[[CBS News]]
  |author=David Paul Kuhn 
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite news
  |url=http://www.post-gazette.com/pg/04294/398767.stm
  |title=Campaign 2004: Voter registration workers cry foul
  |date=2004-10-20
  |publisher=[[Pittsburgh Post-Gazette]]
  |author=Dennis B. Roddy
}}&lt;/ref&gt;.

==Voter suppression by unknown activists==
In the [[U.S. presidential election, 2004|U.S. presidential election of 2004]], some voters got phone calls with false information intended to keep them from voting--saying that their voting place had been changed or that voting would take place on Wednesday as well as on Tuesday.&lt;ref name="pfaw"&gt;{{cite web
  | title =Intimidation and Deceptive Practices
  | publisher =Election Protection coalition/[[People For the American Way|PFAW]]
  | url =http://www.ep365.org/site/c.fnKGIMNtEoG/b.2052599/k.6FF4/Intimidation_and_Deceptive_Practices.htm
  | accessdate = 2007-05-25 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="acvr"&gt;{{cite web
  | title =Incidents Of Voter Intimidation &amp; Suppression
  | publisher =American Ctr for Voting Rights
  | url =http://web.archive.org/web/20060210111239/http://www.ac4vr.com/reports/072005/republicanincidents.html
  | accessdate = 2007-05-25 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Voter suppression distinct from other campaign tactics==
Unlike [[negative campaigning]], which ordinarily seeks reduce the likelihood of someone voting for a candidate through disparaging arguments directed at a candidate, voter suppression prevents people from voting altogether. Thus if as in the [[U.S. presidential election, 1964|U.S. presidential election of 1964]] in the United States the [[Lyndon Johnson]] campaign depicted [[Barry Goldwater]] as a "right-wing extremist," such a depiction does not constitute voter suppression. 

Negative campaigning, even if it goes as far as [[slander]] or [[libel]], is not generally considered to be a form of voter suppression. Research has shown, however, that negative campaigning does indirectly make people less likely to vote.&lt;ref name="goingnegative"&gt;{{cite web
  | title =Going Negative
  | publisher =Stanford University Political Communication Lab
  | url =http://pcl.stanford.edu/common/docs/research/iyengar/1996/goingneg.html
  | accessdate = 2007-05-25 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some kinds of [[vote fraud]]--such as bribery or intimidation of electors, or manipulation of voting results by tampering with the voting devices, paraphernalia, or tabulating machines with the result of falsifying, undercounting, or otherwise misrepresenting the vote--may result in depriving qualified electors of their legitimate voice in an election.  The term "voter suppression," however, is usually reserved for attempts to keep voters away from the polls, not for other kinds of vote manipulation.

==See also==
*[[2004 U.S. presidential election controversy, vote suppression]]
*[[Electoral fraud]]
*[[Caging list]]
*[[Voters Outreach of America]]
*[[American Center for Voting Rights]]
*[[Political corruption]]
*[[Voter turnout]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.ac4vr.com/reports/072005/default.html Vote Fraud, Intimidation &amp; Suppression In The 2004 Presidential Election] 
* [http://www.ac4vr.com/ American Center For Voting Rights], [[August 2]], [[2005]], report.
* [http://blackprof.com/stealingd.html Stealing democracy] Spencer Overton, Stealing Democracy, June 5, 2006

[[Category:Political campaign techniques]]
[[Category:Political corruption]]
[[Category:Election fraud]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>