<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20191102230354|924287197" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="392689" pageid="392689" ns="0" title="New queer cinema"><revisions><rev timestamp="2019-11-04T23:48:03Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Redirect|Queer cinema|LGBT films in general|List of LGBT films}}
{{More citations needed|date=March 2009}}

[[File:B. Ruby Rich.jpg|thumb|right|Film critic [[B. Ruby Rich]] coined the term "New Queer Cinema" in 1992.]]
"'''New Queer Cinema'''" is a term first coined by the academic [[B. Ruby Rich]] in ''[[Sight &amp; Sound]]'' magazine in 1992 to define and describe a movement in [[queer]]-themed [[independent film]]making in the early 1990s. The term developed from use of the word ''queer'' in academic writing in the 1980s and 1990s as an inclusive way of describing gay, lesbian, bisexual and transgender identity and experience, and also defining a form of sexuality that was fluid and subversive of traditional understandings of sexuality. Also, the major film studio to discuss these issues was aptly named [[New Line Cinema]] with its [[Fine Line Features]] division. Since 1992, the phenomenon has also been described by various other academics and has been used to describe several other films released since the 1990s. Films of the New Queer Cinema movement typically share certain themes, such as the rejection of [[heteronormativity]] and the lives of [[LGBT]] protagonists living on the fringe of society.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=New Queer Cinema|url=http://mubi.com/lists/new-queer-cinema|publisher=Mubi.com|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130316030642/http://mubi.com/lists/new-queer-cinema|archive-date=16 March 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=GLBTQ New Queer Cinema|url=http://www.glbtqarchive.com/arts/new_queer_cinema_A.pdf|publisher=Glbtq.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==

Susan Hayward states that Queer cinema existed for decades before it was given its official label, such as, with the films of French creators [[Jean Cocteau]] (''[[Le sang d'un poète]]'' in 1934) and [[Jean Genet]] (''[[Un chant d'amour]]'' in 1950).&lt;ref name="Hayward, Susan 2006. p. 329-333"&gt;Hayward, Susan. "Queer cinema" in ''Cinema Studies: The Key Concepts'' (Third Edition). Routledge, 2006. p. 329-333&lt;/ref&gt; Queer cinema is associated with avant-garde and underground film (e.g., [[Andy Warhol]]'s 1960s films).&lt;ref name="Hayward, Susan 2006. p. 329-333"/&gt; In avant-garde film, there are lesbian filmmakers, who laid the heritage for Queer cinema, notably [[Ulrike Ottinger]], [[Chantal Akerman]] and [[Pratibha Parmar]].&lt;ref name="Hayward, Susan 2006. p. 329-333"/&gt; An important influence on the development of Queer cinema was [[Rainer Werner Fassbinder]]'s 1970s and 1980s European [[art film]]s, which added a "gay and queer sensibility" to film (e.g., ''[[Querelle]]'' from 1982, based on Genet's novel).&lt;ref name="Hayward, Susan 2006. p. 329-333"/&gt; Another influence on Queer cinema was the Brazilian filmmaker [[Héctor Babenco]], whose film ''[[Kiss of the Spider Woman (film)|Kiss of the Spider Woman,]]'' from 1985, depicted a man in prison, who is seduced by his cellmate.&lt;ref name="Hayward, Susan 2006. p. 329-333"/&gt;

The identification of Queer cinema probably emerged in the mid-1980s through the influence of [[Queer theory]], which aims to "challenge and push further debates on gender and sexuality" developed by [[feminist theory]] and "confuse binary essentialisms around gender and sexual identity, expose their limitations", and depict the blurring of these roles and identities.&lt;ref name="Hayward, Susan 2006. p. 329-333"/&gt; Queer cinema filmmakers sometimes made films in genres that were typically considered mainstream, then subverting the conventions by depicting the "question of pleasure" and celebrating excess, or by re-adding homosexual themes or historical elements where they had been erased through [[straightwashing]] (e.g., in [[Derek Jarman]]'s historical film ''[[Edward II (film)|Edward II]]'' (1991)).&lt;ref name="Hayward, Susan 2006. p. 329-333"/&gt; Queer cinema filmmakers call for a "multiplicity of voices and sexualities" and, rather than having one unifying aesthetic, they have a "collection of different aesthetics."&lt;ref name="Hayward, Susan 2006. p. 329-333"/&gt; The issue of "lesbian invisibility" has been raised in Queer cinema, since more funding goes to gay male filmmakers than lesbian directors, as is the case with the heterosexual/mainstream film industry, and as such, much of queer cinema focuses on the "construction of male desire."&lt;ref name="Hayward, Susan 2006. p. 329-333"/&gt;

In her 1992 article, Rich commented on the strong gay and lesbian presence on the previous year's film festival circuit and coined the phrase "New Queer Cinema" to describe a growing movement of similarly themed films being made by gay and lesbian independent filmmakers, chiefly in North America and England.&lt;ref name="michelleaaron"&gt;{{Cite book|last=Aaron|first=Michelle|title=New Queer Cinema: A Critical Reader|publisher=[[Rutgers University Press]]|page=3|year=2004|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=PGd4-qtfyzIC&amp;pg=PA3| isbn=978-0-8135-3486-2|postscript= .}}&lt;/ref&gt; Rich developed her theory in the ''[[Village Voice]]'' newspaper, describing films that were radical in form and aggressive in their presentation of sexual identities, which challenged both the status quo of heterosexual definition and resisted promoting "positive" images of lesbians and gay men that had been advocated by the [[gay liberation movement]] of the 1970s and 1980s. In the films of New Queer Cinema, the protagonists and narratives were predominantly [[LGBT]], but were presented invariably as outsiders and renegades from the rules of conventional society, who embraced radical and unconventional gender roles and ways of life, frequently casting themselves as outlaws or fugitives.

[[File:River Phoenix.jpg|thumb|left|150px|[[River Phoenix]]'s critically acclaimed performance as gay hustler [[Mikey Waters]] in Gus Van Sant's 1991 film ''[[My Own Private Idaho]]'' helped bring queer cinema to a mainstream audience.]]

Drawing on [[postmodernist]] and [[poststructuralist]] academic theories of the 1980s, the New Queer Cinema presented human identity and sexuality as socially constructed, and therefore fluid and changeable, rather than fixed. In the world of New Queer Cinema, sexuality is often a chaotic and subversive force, which is alienating to and often brutally repressed by dominant heterosexual power structures. Films in the New Queer Cinema movement frequently featured explicit and unapologetic depictions of same-sex sexual activity, and presented same-sex relationships that reconfigured traditional heterosexual notions of family and marriage. While not all identifying with a specific political movement, New Queer Cinema films were invariably radical, as they sought to challenge and subvert assumptions about identity, gender, class, family and society.

The 1991 documentary ''[[Paris Is Burning (film)|Paris is Burning]]'' introduced audiences to yet another subcultural realm. Director [[Jennie Livingston]] captured the realities of New York's drag balls and houses, and of the non-white people who occupied these spaces. This was an arguably underground world with which many Americans were unfamiliar. Aesthetic excellence and flamboyance were crucial in drag performances and competitions. Stylized [[vogue (dance)|vogue]] dancing was also exhibited as central to the drag experience, notably influencing the artistry of pop icon [[Madonna (entertainer)|Madonna]]. New Queer Cinema figures like Livingston encouraged viewers to suspend their ignorance, and enjoy the diversity of humanity.

The films also frequently referenced the [[AIDS]] crisis of the 1980s, often commenting on the failure of the [[Ronald Reagan]] administration to respond to the AIDS epidemic and the social stigma experienced by the gay community. Given the relative invisibility of references to AIDS in mainstream Hollywood filmmaking, the work of New Queer Cinema was hailed by the gay community as a welcome correction to a history of under-representation and stereotyping of gay and lesbian people.

Among the films cited by Rich were [[Todd Haynes]]'s ''[[Poison (film)|Poison]]'' (1991),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://emanuellevy.com/review/featured-review/gay-pride-2015-celebrating-haynes-poison/|title=Gay Pride 2015: Celebrating Todd Haynes’ Poison|first=Emanuel|last=Levy|author-link=Emanuel Levy|website=EmmanuelLevy|date=June 27, 2015|accessdate=November 3, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.slantmagazine.com/house/article/hearth-of-darkness-rob-whites-todd-haynes|title=Hearth of Darkness: Rob White's Todd Haynes|work=[[Slant Magazine]]|first=Clayton|last=Dillard|date=April 3, 2013|accessdate=November 3, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Laurie Lynd]]'s ''[[RSVP (1991 film)|RSVP]]'' (1991), [[Isaac Julien]]'s ''[[Young Soul Rebels]]'' (1991), [[Derek Jarman]]'s ''[[Edward II (film)|Edward II]]'' (1991), [[Tom Kalin]]'s ''[[Swoon (film)|Swoon]]'' (1992), and [[Gregg Araki]]'s ''[[The Living End (film)|The Living End]]'' (1992). All the films feature explicitly gay and lesbian protagonists and subjects; explicit and unapologetic depictions of or references to gay sex; and a confrontational and often antagonistic approach towards [[heterosexual]] culture.

These directors were making their films at a time when the gay community was facing new challenges from the AIDS crisis in the 1980s and the [[conservatism|conservative]] political wave brought on by the presidency of [[Ronald Reagan]] in the United States and the government of [[Margaret Thatcher]] in the United Kingdom. Jarman himself was diagnosed with AIDS in 1986, and died in 1994 at the age of 52. Jarman's public promotion of [[gay rights]] and equality have established him as an influential activist within the [[LGBT]] community.

[[Queer theory]] and politics were emerging topics in academic circles, with proponents arguing that gender and sexual categories, such as ''homosexual'' and ''heterosexual,'' were historical social constructs, subject to change with cultural attitudes.  Rich noted that many films were beginning to represent sexualities which were unashamedly neither fixed nor conventional, and coined the phrase "New Queer Cinema".

==Evolution==
Beginning in the 2010s, a number of LGBT filmmakers, including [[Rose Troche]]&lt;ref name=concussion&gt;[http://blogs.indiewire.com/womenandhollywood/sundance-interview-concussion-directed-by-stacie-passon-produced-by-rose-troche-starring-robin-weigert "Sundance Interview: Concussion"]. ''Women and Hollywood'', February 1, 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Travis Mathews]],&lt;ref name=nightcharm&gt;[http://www.nightcharm.com/2013/03/09/cruising-with-travis-mathews-the-nightcharm-interview/ "Cruising With Travis Mathews: The Nightcharm Interview"]. ''Nightcharm'', March 9, 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; identified a newer trend in LGBT filmmaking, in which the influence of New Queer Cinema was evolving toward more universal audience appeal.

Rich, the originator of the phrase New Queer Cinema, has identified the emergence in the late 2000s of LGBT-themed mainstream films such as ''[[Brokeback Mountain]]'', ''[[Milk (film)|Milk]]'', and ''[[The Kids Are All Right (film)|The Kids Are All Right]]'' as a key moment in the evolution of the genre,&lt;ref&gt;''[[Q (radio show)|Q]]'', May 31, 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; while both Troche and Mathews singled out [[Stacie Passon]]'s 2013 ''[[Concussion (2013 film)|Concussion]]'', a film about [[marital infidelity]] in which the central characters' lesbianism is a relatively minor aspect of a story, in which the primary theme is how a long-term relationship can become troubled and unfulfilling regardless of its gender configuration, as a prominent example of the trend.&lt;ref name=concussion /&gt;&lt;ref name=nightcharm /&gt; The French film ''[[Blue Is the Warmest Colour]]'', which won the [[Palme d'Or]] at the [[2013 Cannes Film Festival]], has also been singled out as a notable example.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.xtra.ca/public/National/B_Ruby_Rich_on_this_years_queer_film_festival_circuit-13653.aspx "B Ruby Rich on this year's queer film festival circuit"]. ''[[Xtra!]]'', May 31, 2013. {{webarchive|url=https://archive.is/20130628063535/http://www.xtra.ca/public/National/B_Ruby_Rich_on_this_years_queer_film_festival_circuit-13653.aspx |date=June 28, 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Film|LGBT}}
* [[List of lesbian, gay, bisexual or transgender-related films]]
* [[History of homosexuality in American film]]
* [[New York Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, &amp; Transgender Film Festival]]
* [[Queer theory]]
* [[Straightwashing]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==Sources==
* [[B. Ruby Rich]]. “New Queer Cinema”: ''Sight &amp; Sound'', Volume 2, Issue 5 (September 1992)
* B. Ruby Rich. “Queer and present danger”: ''Sight &amp; Sound'', Volume 10, Issue 3 (March 2000): https://web.archive.org/web/20120603121621/http://www.bfi.org.uk/sightandsound/feature/80
* B. Ruby Rich, ''New Queer Cinema: The Director’s Cut'', Duke University Press, 2013.
* Pier Maria Bocchi, ''Mondo Queer. Cinema e militanza gay'', Lindau, Torino, 2005, {{ISBN|88-71-80-548-8}}.
* Joseph Bristow: ''Sexuality'' (1997), {{ISBN|0-415-08494-6}}
* {{cite book | last = Cante | first = Richard C. | title = Gay Men and the Forms of Contemporary US Culture | publisher = Ashgate Publishing. |isbn=0-7546-7230-1 |date=March 2009 | location = London}}
* [[Derek Jarman]]: ''Queer Edward II'' (1991), {{ISBN|0-85170-316-X}}
* Martin Frey. ''Derek Jarman - Bewegte Bilder eines Malers.'' BoD, 2008, {{ISBN|978-3-8370-1217-0}}
* Nick Rees-Roberts: ''French Queer Cinema'', Edinburgh University Press, 2008
* [[Mark Simpson (journalist)|Mark Simpson]] (ed.): ''Anti-Gay'' (1996), {{ISBN|0-304-33144-9}}
* Tamsin Spargo: ''[[Michel Foucault|Foucault]] and [[Queer theory]]'' (1999), {{ISBN|1-84046-092-X}}
* Colin Spencer: ''Homosexuality: A History'' (1995) {{ISBN|1-85702-447-8}}
* Pamela Demory, Christopher Pullen (ed.), ''Queer Love in Film and Television: Critical Essays'', Palgrave Macmillan, 2013.
* Robin Griffiths, ''Queer Cinema in Europe'', Intellect Books, 2008.
* [[Richard Dyer]]: ''The Culture of Queers'' (2002). {{ISBN|0-415-22376-8}}
* [[Axel Schock]] / [[Manuela Kay]]: ''[[Out im Kino]]. Das lesbisch-schwule Filmlexikon'' (2004). {{ISBN|978-3-89656-090-2}}
* Doan, Laura L. ''The Lesbian Postmodern''. New York: Columbia University Press, 1994.
* Aaron, Michele. ''New Queer Cinema: A Critical Reader''. New Jersey: Rutgers University Press, 2004.

==External links==
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20120211124350/http://www.greencine.com/static/primers/queer.jsp A Brief History of Queer Cinema at GreenCine] (archived version)

{{Film genres}}
{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Film genres]]
[[Category:Film theory]]
[[Category:LGBT-related film]]
[[Category:Movements in cinema]]
[[Category:Postmodern theory]]
[[Category:Queer culture]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>