<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20051111230100|28065421" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="399908" pageid="399908" ns="0" title="White flight"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-11-11T23:01:34Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''White flight''' is a colloquial term for the [[demographics|demographic]] trend of [[upper class|upper]] and [[middle class]] [[Whites|white people]] moving away from (predominantly non-white) [[Inner city|inner cities]], finding new homes in nearby [[suburb]]s or even moving to new locales entirely, e.g. from the [[Rust Belt]] to the [[Sun Belt]]. In some of the United States' largest cities, the trend reversed itself in the 1990s (see ''[[gentrification]]'').


==White flight in the United States==

White flight has been taking place in many American [[city|cities]] and regions, especially in the [[U.S. Northeast|Northeastern]], [[Midwest]]ern, and [[The West (U.S.)|Western]] sections of the [[United States]] since the [[1950s]]. 

The effects of white flight have been significant for the cities that have been hit by this phenomenon, especially [[Detroit, Michigan]] and [[Saint Louis, Missouri|St. Louis, Missouri]], which lost more than half of their peak populations largely due to white flight. In [[New York, New York|New York City]] many whites have moved from parts of [[The Bronx|the Bronx]] and [[Brooklyn]] to [[Staten Island]], suburban [[Long Island]], and suburban [[New Jersey]]. Other U.S. cities that have been noticeably affected by white flight include [[Philadelphia, Pennsylvania]], [[Cleveland, Ohio]], the West and South Sides of [[Chicago, Illinois]],  the [[Greater Los Angeles Area]] (in inner suburbs such as [[Compton, California|Compton]] and  [[Inglewood, California|Inglewood]] in the mid-20th century and in many other places since then - see "White flight in Southern California" below), [[Baltimore, Maryland]], [[Newark, New Jersey]], and numerous smaller cities. 

===History===

In the years after [[World War II]] [[whites]] began to move away from inner core cities to newer [[suburb]]an communities.  Major cities had experienced tight housing markets during the war years, and an influx of blacks seeking war work. Whites with the means to leave did so in some cases to escape the increasing [[crime]] and racial tension in inner cities throughout the country but, in other locations in the immediate postwar years, many whites left core cities because they believed that suburban communities, with their new housing stock, roads and schools, were more desirable places to live than  the inner cities. 

Prior to the [[Civil Rights Act of 1964]], due to racist real-estate covenants and other discriminatory practices, non-white people were almost never afforded the same opportunities to move away from the cities, even when they may have been economically able to do so.  

As wealthier white residents abandoned the [[Inner-city|inner city]] neighborhoods, they ultimately left behind increasingly poor non-white populations whose neighborhoods rapidly deteriorated, beginning in the 1950s and especially in the 1960s. Whites took their tax and investment dollars with them, abandoning the cities to the poorest Americans. Jobs and businesses disintegrated along with the neighborhoods and ultimately turned the increasingly poverty-stricken areas into crime-ridden slums with failing and dilapidated [[public school]]s.  

An important element of this migration of well-to-do whites was the availability of federally-subsidized home mortgages (VA, FHA, HOLC) which made it possible for families to buy cheap, new homes in suburbs--but not to buy apartments in cities. State and federal governments also subsidized white flight by paying for highways to carry suburbanites to work in cities (the National Defense and Interstate Highway Act and its successors) and by changing tax codes to benefit suburban "minimal cities" ("the Lakewood Plan").

Another important aspect of this migration was the phenomenon of "block-busting." Real estate agents would facilitate the sale of a house in a white neighborhood to a black family using a number of methods, such as buying the house themselves, or using a white proxy, and selling at perhaps a reduced price to the black family. A panic would ensue among some white homeowners, fanned by the real estate agents, who feared that their property values would drop, which of course they did as soon as they began selling in large numbers, often to the real estate agents, or their proxies. The real estate agents would then sell at higher prices to the incoming black families, reaping the profits of the price difference as well as the commissions on sales. It was not uncommon for a neighborhood to be completely changed in the space of a few years by this process.

It should be noted that several predominantly poorer white communities also face conditions similar to those of areas that have experienced white flight.  The cities of [[Buffalo, New York|Buffalo]] and [[Niagara Falls, New York|Niagara Falls]] in New York serve as prime examples. In these areas, manufacturing jobs were once dominant but have now largely disappeared, resulting in [[urban decay]].

===Schools and busing===
White flight has also affected education.  The landmark 1954 [[United States Supreme Court|Supreme Court]] decision of [[Brown v. Board of Education]] ordered the desegregation of schools.  American cities affected by white flight also witnessed growing disparities in the quality of education. Thus, to achieve racial balance and equality in schools, the Court subsequently mandated in the 1971 decision of [[Swann v. Charlotte-Mecklenburg Board of Education]] controversial school [[Forced busing|busing]] to mainly all-white schools in the suburbs.  From the mid 1970s, many minority students (especially blacks) were transported  long distances from poorer core cities to   newer affluent suburbs.  As [[Justice William Douglas]] observed in his dissent in [[Milliken v. Bradley]] (1974), "The inner core of Detroit is now rather solidly black; and the blacks, we know, in many instances are likely to be poorer ..."

In turn, busing and desegregation orders in education have in some cases led to a further, non-geographical white flight, one out of the public school systems which are subject to desegregation orders and into private schooling. For instance, in [[1970]] when a [[United States District Court|federal court]] ordered desegregation of the public schools in [[Pasadena, California]], the proportion of white students in those schools reflected the proportion of whites in the community, 54 percent and 53 percent, respectively. Although staying in place geographically, after the desegregation process began large numbers of whites in the upper and middle classes who could afford it pulled their children from the public schools and placed them into private schools instead. As a result, by [[2004]] Pasadena was home to sixty-three private schools, which educated one-third of all school-aged children in the city, and the proportion of white students in the public schools had fallen to 16 percent. The superintendent of Pasadena's public schools characterized them as being to whites "like the bogey-man," and mounted policy changes and a publicity drive to induce affluent whites to put their children back into the public schools.

===White flight in recent decades===

White flight continues in some areas to the present day but has taken on a new trend as some of the older suburbs have been experiencing urban decay similar to their parent cities, such as in some of the southern and western suburbs of Chicago adjacent to the city. [[East St. Louis, Illinois|East St. Louis]] and many of the neighboring communities on the Illinois side of the St. Louis metropolitan area have also long suffered from urban decay with the decline of the manufacturing industries that had once powered the economies of the region. 

In general, the only whites who tend to remain in cities and suburbs affected by white flight are low-income whites (though many low-income whites in East Coast cities have moved to close-in, working-class suburbs or other, more heavily white neighborhoods within the same city) and [[senior citizen]]s (especially "[[Empty nest syndrome|empty nesters]]"), who have often lived in a particular community for a very long time.  Usually, when these seniors die or move to retirement communities, the process of white flight is complete.  

It should also be noted that affluent and professional whites sometimes remain in specific parts of a city that has otherwise been affected by white flight.  For example, well-off whites continue to live in St. Louis neighborhoods around [[Forest Park (St. Louis)|Forest Park]] and the Central West End even as much of the rest of St. Louis has been utterly transformed due to the white flight that has been occurring there since the 1950s.  In general, whites who remain in such locations do not have children or, if they do, their children attend private schools.  Additionally, even though the demographic make-up of New York City has been dramatically altered due to white flight from the outer boroughs, parts of [[Manhattan]] have actually become more white during the past 20 years due to [[gentrification]] (see below).  

Moreover, the population decline of some Midwestern, Northeastern, and Western cities has either slowed down or has even been reversed (such as in parts of Chicago), while other areas remain economically devastated due to seemingly-permanent economic shifts and job losses (such as in Detroit). The future of this trend remains to be seen.

As well, a recent trend has been white flight due to large-scale immigration of Hispanics, and sometimes immigration from groups like East [[Asia]]ns, South and Southeast Asians, [[Middle East]]erners, [[North Africa]]ns, immigrants from the former [[USSR]], [[Eastern Europe]]ans and [[Southern Europe]]ans. This trend has been most pronounced in New York City, northern New Jersey, and southern California, where the most of these groups have immigrated. From [[Brooklyn]] neighborhoods like [[Bensonhurst]] and [[Bay Ridge]], most of the Italians have moved to [[Staten Island]], where they retain similar income and living style but are isolated from the urban environment and diversity. From [[Queens]], white residents first moved from the northern areas to a degree and then from the central and southern areas, mostly emptying out to [[Nassau County]] and [[Suffolk County]] in [[Long Island]]. However, both in Brooklyn and Queens, a percentage of white residents still resides in these neighborhoods. Neighborhoods in Queens dramatically affected by white flight to the point of total change include [[Flushing]] and the surrounding areas, [[Long Island City]], [[Jackson Heights]], [[Elmhurst]], and [[Corona]]. Neighborhoods currently being affected by a more casual white flight in which children move away include [[Ozone Park]], [[Rosedale]], and [[Briarwood]]. They largely move to Long Island. From working-class areas in [[Hudson County]], [[Passaic County]], and [[Essex County]], Italians have largely moved to the triangle formed by [[West Essex]], eastern [[Morris County]], and western [[Passaic County]]. This form of white flight usually rarely involves a drop in income, but involves more ethnic change with the community not being affected negatively, as it is a slower and more casual process of migration. In southern California, eastern [[Los Angeles County]], the eastern [[San Fernando Valley]], sections of the [[San Gabriel Valley]], and sections of [[Orange County]] and the [[Inland Empire]] have been affected by white flight due to Asian and Hispanic immigration.

===White flight in Southern California===

The forces and groups involved in white flight in Southern California are distinct from those in other areas due to the region's demography and history. 

Many whites once lived in urban neighborhoods in Los Angeles before departing the city in large numbers after the [[1965]] [[Watts Riots]] (a trend that actually began before the riots but accelerated after them).  The major [[12th Street Riot]] in Detroit in [[1967]] and during the following year, after the assassination of civil rights leader [[Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr.]], contributed to white flight in that city.  Now, the city of Detroit is over 80% black whereas a majority of its neighboring suburbs, such as [[Livonia, Michigan|Livonia]], [[Dearborn, Michigan|Dearborn]], and [[Warren, Michigan|Warren]], are overwhelmingly white.[http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2001/08/13/national/main306205.shtml]. Similarly, after the [[1992 Los Angeles riots]], large numbers of white Californians left Southern California or left the state entirely. The phenomenon has affected not only the central city basin, but also the suburban regions of the [[San Fernando Valley]] and the [[San Gabriel Valley]] in [[Southern California]], where many [[working class|working-class]] Hispanics and lower to upper-middle class [[Asian Americans]] have moved during much of the 1980s and 1990s.  

Some of the people leaving Los Angeles have moved to other states. Many of these ex-Californians ended up settling in the [[Rocky Mountain States]] of [[Arizona]], [[Colorado]], [[Idaho]] and [[Nevada]]. As these people have tended to be politically conservative, their departure from the state has helped to transform California into a stronghold of the [[U.S. Democratic Party|Democratic Party]], while making their new home states even more favorable to the [[U.S. Republican Party|Republicans]].  [http://www.usatoday.com/news/nation/2002-10-28-gop-west-1acover_x.htm]

==White flight elsewhere in the world==
The phenomenon is also to be found in [[South Africa]]n cities, most notably [[Johannesburg]] and [[Durban]], which saw a mass influx of African people into the inner cities during the final years of [[apartheid]], and from which white people fled in great numbers to the suburbs (or out of the country) before crime rates grew to what they are today. In some areas of [[New Zealand]], there has been a gradual process of white flight, with mass urbanisation of [[Maori]] and arrivals of [[Pacific Islands]] guest workers between the 1950s and 1970s, though in [[Auckland]] the process has largely been in reverse since the 1980s, with white (Pakeha) New Zealanders moving to previously Maori and Pacific Islander neighborhoods such as Ponsonby, Grey Lynn and Kingsland. Similar gentrification trends have occurred in [[Wellington, New Zealand|Wellington]] inner city suburbs like Thorndon, Newtown, and Aro Valley.

In [[Australia]], both [[Sydney]] and [[Melbourne]] have seen an out flux of [[Anglo-Celtic]] Australians to the rural and coastal areas following large scale [[Asian]] immigration during the 1980s and 1990s. This has declined to some extent following the high house prices on the early 2000s.

In [[France]] see [[2005 Paris suburb riots]].

==Gentrification: the opposite of white flight==
The opposing social trend of wealthy social groups moving into an inner city area and displacing the existing residents is called [[gentrification]].  In Cleveland, as reported on the ''[[Newshour with Jim Lehrer]]'' on [[PBS]] in 2003, several wealthy homosexual couples have purchased and restored homes in the predominantly black neighborhoods. This study echoed an earlier Ohio documentary titled Flag Wars [http://www.pbs.org/pov/pov2003/flagwars/special_gentrification.html], detailing similar Black vs. Gay (homophobia vs. racism) themes in the old silk stocking district of [[Columbus]]. In other cases, some inner city areas may witness a renaissance as a home for artists, which happens to be the case with the [[Silver Lake, Los Angeles, California|Silver Lake]] neighborhood of Los Angeles.  In [[Montreal]] and [[Toronto]], as with many [[Canada|Canadian]] cities, many inner city areas have been gentrified by the usual "[[yuppie]]" couples but also by "empty nesters," that is, couples in their late forties or fifties whose children have left their home, giving them an incentive to sell their large house in the suburbs and buy a condominium or townhouse in the inner city, close to the better parks, the leisure activities, the cultural attractions and the convenience of the [[Montreal metro]].

[[Category:Human migration]]
[[Category:Demographic history of the United States|*]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>