<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20151018213023|686390699" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="399908" pageid="399908" ns="0" title="White flight"><revisions><rev timestamp="2015-11-20T01:42:51Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{About|the social phenomenon|the musical band|White Flight (band)}}
{{pp-semi-indef}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=October 2012}}

{{Segregation}}

'''White flight''' is a term that originated in the United States, starting in the mid-20th century, and applied to the large-scale migration of [[European American|whites of various European ancestries]] from racially mixed urban regions to more racially homogeneous suburban or [[exurban]] regions. The term has more recently been applied to other migrations by whites, from older, inner suburbs to rural areas, as well as from the US Northeast and Midwest to the milder climate in the Southeast and Southwest.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The Encyclopedia of Race, Ethnicity, and Society|editor-first=Richard T.|editor-last=Schaefer|year=2008|publisher=SAGE publications}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite encyclopedia|encyclopedia=Merriam-Webster Dictionary|url=http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/white%20flight|title=white flight}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Armor, David J.|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=BJuAZpULzAsC&amp;pg=PA177&amp;dq=%22causes+white+flight%22+armor&amp;ei=f0eHSKGjEZOaigHsoaDnAQ&amp;sig=ACfU3U00umALO3lLCIR6zDA2GbLzKG0tAQ#PPA71,M1|title=Forced Justice: School Desegregation and the Law|publisher=Oxford University Press US|year=1986}}&lt;/ref&gt; The term has also been used for large-scale [[Decolonization|post-colonial]] emigration of [[White Africans of European ancestry|whites from Africa]], or parts of that continent,&lt;ref name=Hammer2010&gt;{{cite news|title=(Almost) Out of Africa: The White Tribes|work=World Affairs Journal|author=Joshua Hammer|date=May–June 2010|url=http://worldaffairsjournal.org/article/almost-out-africa-white-tribes}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Mosiuoa 'Terror' Lekota threatens to topple the ANC|author=Johnson, RW|date=October 19, 2008|work=The Times |url=http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/world/africa/article4969026.ece|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title= The atlas of changing South Africa|edition= 2nd|author=Christopher, A. J.|year=2000 |publisher=Routledge|page=213|isbn=9780203185902}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The uncertain promise of Southern Africa|editor1-first=York W.|editor1-last=Bradshaw|editor2-first=Stephen N.|editor2-last=Ndegwa|year=2001|publisher=Indiana University Press|page=6}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|editor1-last=Reinhardt|editor1-first=Steven G.|editor2-first=Dennis P.|editor2-last=Reinhartz|title=Transatlantic history|year=2006|publisher=Texas A&amp;M University Press|isbn=9781585444861|edition=1st|pages=149–150}}&lt;/ref&gt; driven by levels of violent crime and anti-colonial state policies.&lt;ref name="Economist 12295535"&gt;{{cite news|title=White flight from South Africa: Between staying and going|work=The Economist|date=September 25, 2008|url=http://www.economist.com/node/12295535}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Migration of middle-class white populations was observed during the 1950s and 1960s out of cities such as [[Detroit]], [[Oakland]], and [[Cleveland]], although racial segregation of public schools had ended there long before the U.S. Supreme Court's decision in ''[[Brown v. Board of Education]]''. In the 1970s, attempts to achieve effective [[desegregation]] by means of forced [[Desegregation busing in the United States|busing]] in some areas led to more families' moving out of former areas.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Clotfelter, Charles T.|title=After Brown: The Rise and Retreat of School Desegregation|publisher=Princeton University Press|year=2004}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Ravitch|first=Diane|title=The Troubled Crusade: American Education, 1945–1980|year=1983|publisher=Basic books|location=New York City|isbn=9780465087570|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=iH6jKXSgoRkC&amp;pg=PA177&amp;vq=white+flight&amp;dq=%22School+desegregation+and+White+Flight.%22&amp;source=gbs_search_r&amp;cad=1_1&amp;sig=ACfU3U1FzJ9tPXFyq9BsrJd2aYER_3UoUQ#PPA179,M1}}&lt;/ref&gt; More generally, some historians suggest that white flight occurred in response to population pressures, both from the large migration of blacks from the rural South to northern cities in the [[Great Migration (African American)|Great Migration]] and the waves of new immigrants from southern and eastern Europe.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | last1 = Boustan | first1 = L. P. | doi = 10.1162/qjec.2010.125.1.417 | title = Was Postwar Suburbanization "White Flight"? Evidence from the Black Migration* | journal = Quarterly Journal of Economics | volume = 125 | pages = 417–443 | year = 2010 | pmid =  | pmc = }}&lt;/ref&gt; However, some historians have challenged the phrase "white flight" as a misnomer whose use should be reconsidered. In her study of Chicago's West Side during the post-war era, historian Amanda Seligman argues that the phrase misleadingly suggests that whites immediately departed when blacks moved into the neighborhood, when in fact, many whites defended their space with violence, intimidation, or legal tactics.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Seligman|first=Amanda|title=Block by block : neighborhoods and public policy on Chicago's West Side|year=2005|publisher=University of Chicago Press|location=Chicago|isbn=978-0-226-74663-0|pages=213–14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The business practices of [[redlining]], [[mortgage discrimination]], and racially [[restrictive covenants]] contributed to the overcrowding and physical deterioration of areas where minorities chose to congregate. Such conditions are considered to have contributed to the emigration of other populations. The limited facilities for banking and insurance, due to a perceived lack of profitability, and other social services, and extra fees meant to hedge against perceived profit issues increased their cost to residents in predominantly non-white suburbs and city neighborhoods.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Kruse|first=Kevin M.|title=White Flight: Atlanta and the Making of Modern Conservatism|year=2007|publisher=Princeton University Press|location=Princeton, N.J.|isbn=978-0-691-13386-7|url=http://press.princeton.edu/chapters/i8043.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Thabit, Walter|title=How East New York Became a Ghetto|year=2003|publisher=New York University Press|location=New York|isbn=0-8147-8267-1|page=42}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to the environmental geographer Laura Pulido, the historical processes of suburbanization and urban decentralization contribute to contemporary [[environmental racism]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Pulido, Laura|title=Rethinking Environmental Racism: White Privilege and Urban Development in Southern California|journal=Annals of the Association of American Geographers|volume=90|number=1|date=Mar 2000|pages=12–40|url=http://www.geog.umn.edu/faculty/squires/courses/BSE3001/PulioEnvironmentalRacismWhitePrivilege.pdf|doi=10.1111/0004-5608.00182}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==United States==
In the United States during the 1940s, for the first time a powerful interaction between segregation laws and race differences in terms of socioeconomic status enabled white families to abandon inner cities in favor of suburban living. The eventual result was severe levels of urban decay that, by the 1960s, resulted in the crumbling urban "ghettos".  Prior to national data obtained by the 1950 U.S. census, the migration pattern of disproportionate numbers of whites moving from cities to suburban communities was merely anecdotal. Because urban populations in the United States were still substantially growing, a relative decrease in one racial or ethnic component remained very difficult to prove statistically to the satisfaction of national policy makers. Data on urban population changes had not been broken into what are now familiarly called its “components.” The first data set that potentially could prove “white flight” was the 1950 census data. But the original processing of this data, on older-style tabulation machine by the U.S. Census Bureau, failed to attain any such level of statistical proof. It was a rigorous reprocessing of the same mass of raw data, on a UNIVAC I by Donald J. Bogue of the Scripps Foundation, that scientifically proved the reality of white flight.&lt;ref&gt;Bogue, Donald J. (1957) ''Components of Population Change, 1940-1950'' published jointly by Scripps Foundation for Research in Population Problems: Miami University, and Population Research and Training Center: University of Chicago.&lt;/ref&gt;

During the later 20th century, [[industrial restructuring]] led to major losses of jobs, leaving formerly middle-class working populations suffering poverty, with some unable to move away and seek employment elsewhere.  Real estate prices often fall in areas of economic erosion, allowing persons with lower income to establish homes in such areas. Since the 1960s and changed immigration laws, the United States has received immigrants from Mexico, Central and South America, Asia, and Africa. Immigration has changed the [[Demographics of the United States|demographics]] of both cities and suburbs, and the US become a largely suburban nation, with the suburbs becoming more diverse. In addition, Latinos, the fastest growing minority group in the US, began to migrate away from traditional entry cities and to cities in the [[Southwestern United States|Southwest]], such as [[Phoenix, Arizona|Phoenix]] and [[Tucson, Arizona|Tucson]]. In 2006, the increased number of Latinos had made whites a minority group in some western cities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2006/08/20/AR2006082000629.html|first=Anushka|last= Asthana|author-link=Anushka Asthana|title=Changing Face of Western Cities: Migration Within U.S. Makes Whites a Minority in 3 More Areas|newspaper=Washington Post|date=August 21, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Catalysts===

====Legal exclusion====
In the 1930s, states outside the [[Southern United States|South]] (where racial segregation was legal) practiced unofficial segregation via [[Covenant (law)#Exclusionary covenants|exclusionary covenants]] in title deeds and real estate neighborhood [[redlining]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Crossney|first=Kristen|author2=Bartelt, David |title=Residential Security, Risk, and Race: The Home Owners' Loan Corporation and Mortgage Access in Two Cities|journal=Urban Geography|date=December 1, 2005|volume=26|issue=8|pages=707–736|doi=10.2747/0272-3638.26.8.707|url=http://bellwether.metapress.com/content/h128812346540080/}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mi.vt.edu/data/files/hpd+vol.16+issues+3+and+4/articles/hpd6%283,4%29+crossney.pdf |author1=Crossney |author2=Bartelt |title=2006 Housing Policy Debate |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/20080414023817/http://www.mi.vt.edu/data/files/hpd%20vol.16%20issues%203%20and%204/articles/hpd6(3,4)%20crossney.pdf |archivedate=April 14, 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&amp;nbsp;– explicit, legally sanctioned racial discrimination in real property ownership and lending practices. Blacks were effectively barred from pursuing homeownership, even when they were able to afford it.&lt;ref name="crabgrass" /&gt; Suburban expansion was reserved for middle-class and working-class white people, facilitated by their increased wages incurred by the war effort and by subsequent federally guaranteed mortgages (VA, FHA, HOLC) available only to whites to buy new houses, such as those created by the [[Federal Housing Administration]].&lt;ref&gt;''[http://wbhsi.net/~wendyplotkin/DeedsWeb/fha38.html "Racial" Provisions of FHA Underwriting Manual, 1938]'' &lt;br&gt;
:"Recommended restrictions should include provisions for: prohibition of the occupancy of properties except by the race for which they are intended...Schools should be appropriate to the needs of the new community, and they should not be attended in large numbers by inharmonious racial groups." —[[Federal Housing Administration]], Underwriting Manual: Underwriting and Valuation Procedure Under Title II of the [[National Housing Act of 1934|National Housing Act]] With Revisions to February, 1938 (Washington, D.C.), Part II, Section 9, Rating of Location.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Roads====
After World War II, aided by the construction of the [[interstate highway system]], many [[White American]]s began leaving industrial cities for new housing in suburbs.&lt;ref name=crabgrass&gt;{{cite crabgrass}}&lt;/ref&gt; The roads served to transport suburbanites to their city jobs, facilitating the development of suburbs, and shifting the tax base away from the city. This may have exacerbated [[urban decay]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Locational Dimensions of Urban Highway Impact: An Empirical Analysis|author=Wheeler, James O.|journal=Geografiska Annaler. Series-B, Human Geography|volume=58|number=2|year=1976|pages=67–78|jstor=490613}}&lt;/ref&gt; In some cases, such as in the Southern United States, local governments used highway road constructions to deliberately divide and isolate [[black neighborhood]]s from goods and services, often within industrial corridors. In [[Birmingham, Alabama]], the local government used the highway system to perpetuate the racial residence-boundaries the city established with a 1926 racial zoning law. Constructing interstate highways through majority-black neighborhoods eventually reduced the populations to the poorest proportion of people financially unable to leave their destroyed community.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Connerly|first=C. E.|title=From Racial Zoning to Community Empowerment: The Interstate Highway System and the African American Community in Birmingham, Alabama|journal=Journal of Planning Education and Research|date=December 1, 2002|volume=22|issue=2|pages=99–114|doi=10.1177/0739456X02238441}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Blockbusting====
{{Main|Blockbusting}}
The real estate business practice of "blockbusting" was a for-profit catalyst for white flight and a means to control non-white migration. By subterfuge, real estate agents would facilitate black people buying a house in a white neighborhood, either by buying the house themselves, or via a white proxy buyer, and then re-selling it to the black family. The remaining white inhabitants (alarmed by real estate agents and the local newsmedia),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Ford|first=Richard Thompson|title=The Race Card: How Bluffing about Bias Makes Race Relations Worse|year=2008|publisher=Farrar, Straus and Giroux|location=New York|isbn=9780374245757|edition=1st|pages=290–291}}&lt;/ref&gt; fearing devalued residential property, would quickly sell, usually at a loss. Losses happened when they sold ''en masse'', and would sell the properties to the incoming black families, profiting from price [[arbitrage]] and the sales commissions from both the blacks and the whites. By such tactics, the racial composition of a neighborhood population often changed completely in a few years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite encyclopedia|url=http://www.encyclopedia.chicagohistory.org/pages/147.html|title=Blockbusting|encyclopedia=Encyclopedia of Chicago History|author=Hirsch, Arnold R.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Urban decay====
{{Main|Urban decay}}
[[File:BrokenPromises JohnFekner.jpg|thumb|250px|right|Urban decay in the US: the South Bronx, New York City, was exemplar of the federal and local government's abandonment of the cities in the 1970s and 1980s; the Spanish sign reads "FALSAS PROMESAS", the English sign reads "BROKEN PROMISES".]]

Urban decay is the sociological process whereby a city, or part of a city, falls into disrepair and decrepitude. Its characteristics are [[depopulation]], [[economic restructuring]], abandoned buildings, high local unemployment (and thus poverty),&lt;ref name="power" /&gt; fragmented families, political [[disenfranchisement]], crime, and a desolate, inhospitable city landscape. White flight contributed to the draining of cities' tax bases when middle-class people left. Abandoned properties attracted criminals and [[street gangs]], contributing to crime.&lt;ref name="power"&gt;[[Robert Caro|Caro, Robert]]. ''[[The Power Broker: Robert Moses and the Fall of New York]]''. p.522. "The construction of the [[Gowanus Parkway]], laying a concrete slab on top of lively, bustling Third Avenue, buried the avenue in shadow, and when the parkway was completed, the avenue was cast forever into darkness and gloom, and its bustle and life were forever gone. ISBN 0-394-72024-5&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 1970s and 1980s, urban decay was associated with Western cities, especially in North America and parts of Europe. In that time, major structural changes in global economies, transportation, and government policy created the economic, then social, conditions resulting in urban decay.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Andersen|first=Hans Skifter|title=Urban Sores: On the Interaction Between Segregation, Urban Decay, and Deprived Neighbourhoods|year=2003|publisher=Ashgate|location=Burlington, VT|isbn=0-7546-3305-5}}&lt;/ref&gt;

White flight in North America started to reverse in the 1990s, when the rich suburbanites returned to cities, [[Gentrification|gentrifying]] the decayed urban neighborhoods.&lt;ref name="crabgrass"/&gt;&lt;ref name=comeback&gt;{{cite book|author=Proscio, Tony|author2=Grogan, Paul S.|title=Comeback Cities: A Blueprint for Urban Neighborhood Revival|year=2000|publisher=Westview Press|location=Boulder, CO|isbn=0-8133-3952-9|pages=139–145|quote=The 1965 law brought an end to the lengthy and destructive&amp;nbsp;– at least for cities&amp;nbsp;– period of tightly restricted immigration a spell born of the nationalism and [[xenophobia]] of the 1920s. [p.140]|postscript=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Government-aided white flight====
New municipalities were established beyond the abandoned city's jurisdiction to avoid the [[legacy costs]] of maintaining city infrastructures; instead new governments spent taxes to establish suburban infrastructures. The federal government contributed to white flight and the early decay of non-white city neighborhoods by withholding maintenance capital mortgages, thus making it difficult for the communities to either retain or attract middle-class residents.&lt;ref name=wilson&gt;{{cite book|last=Wilson|first=William Julius|title=[[When Work Disappears]]: The World of the New Urban Poor|year=1997|publisher=Vintage Books|location=New York City|isbn=0-679-72417-6}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The new suburban communities limited the emigration of poor and non-white residents from the city by restrictive [[zoning]]; thus, few lower-middle-class people could afford a house in the suburbs. Many all-white suburbs were eventually annexed to the cities their residents had left. For instance, [[Milwaukee|Milwaukee, Wisconsin]] partially annexed towns such as [[Granville, Wisconsin|Granville]]; the (then) mayor, [[Frank P. Zeidler]], complained about the socially destructive "Iron Ring" of new municipalities incorporated in the post–World War II decade.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.jsonline.com/story/index.aspx?id=459264|title=Mayor served 'the public welfare': Longtime city icon known for integrity, energy, principles]|author=Borsuk, by Alan J.|newspaper=Journal Sentinel|date=July 8, 2006|archivedate=July 11, 2006|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20060711031644/http://www.jsonline.com/story/index.aspx?id=459264}}&lt;/ref&gt; Analogously, semi-rural communities, such as [[Oak Creek, Wisconsin|Oak Creek]], [[South Milwaukee, Wisconsin|South Milwaukee]], and [[Franklin, Milwaukee County, Wisconsin|Franklin]], formally incorporated as discrete entities to escape urban annexation. Wisconsin state law had allowed Milwaukee's annexation of such rural and suburban regions that did not qualify for discrete incorporation per the legal incorporation standards.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Rast|first=J.|title=Governing the Regimeless City: The Frank Zeidler Administration in Milwaukee, 1948-1960|journal=Urban Affairs Review|date=1 September 2006|volume=42|issue=1|pages=81–112|doi=10.1177/1078087406289734}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Curran, Donald J. Curran|title=Infra-Metropolitan Competition|journal=Land Economics|volume=40|number=1|date=February 1964|pages=94–99|doi=10.2307/3144466}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Desegregation of schools====
{{Main|Desegregation busing}}
In some areas, the post–World War II racial desegregation of the public schools catalyzed white flight. In 1954, the US Supreme Court ordered the ''de jure'' termination of the "separate, but equal" legal racism established with the ''[[Plessy v. Ferguson]]'' (1896) case in the 19th century. It declared that segregation of public schools was unconstitutional. Many southern jurisdictions mounted [[massive resistance]] to the policy. In some cases, white parents withdrew their children from public schools and established private religious schools instead.

Upon desegregation in 1957 in [[Baltimore|Baltimore, Maryland]], the Clifton Park Junior High School had 2,023 white students and 34 black students; ten years later, it had twelve white students and 2,037 black students. In northwest Baltimore, Garrison Junior High School's student body declined from 2,504 whites and twelve blacks to 297 whites and 1,263 blacks in that period.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bcps.k12.md.us/About/History/From_the_Oldorder1.asp|title=From the Old Order to the New Order–Reasons and Results, 1957-1997|publisher=Baltimore City Public School System|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20040102085255/http://www.baltimorecityschools.org/About/History/From_the_oldorder1.asp|archivedate=January 4, 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the same time, the city's working class population declined because of the loss of industrial jobs as heavy industry restructured.

In ''[[Swann v. Charlotte-Mecklenburg Board of Education]]'' (1971), the Supreme Court ordered the [[desegregation busing in the United States|desegregation busing]] of poor black students to suburban white schools, and suburban white students to the city to try to integrate student populations. In ''[[Milliken v. Bradley]]'' (1974), the dissenting [[Justice William Douglas]] observed, "The inner core of Detroit is now rather solidly black; and the blacks, we know, in many instances are likely to be poorer." Likewise, in 1977, the Federal decision in ''Penick v. The Columbus Board of Education'' (1977) accelerated white flight from [[Columbus, Ohio]]. Although the racial desegregation of schools affected only public school districts, the most vehement opponents of racial desegregation have sometimes been whites whose children attended private schools.&lt;!-- Where? When? This covers more than 20 years and specifics are important. --&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Jacobson, Cardell K.|title=Desegregation Rulings and Public Attitude Changes: White Resistance or Resignation?|journal=[[American Journal of Sociology]]|volume=84|number=3|pages=698–705|jstor=2778261|doi=10.1086/226833}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.sfgate.com/bayarea/article/C-W-Nevius-Racism-alive-and-well-in-S-F-2504634.php|author=Nevius, C.W.|title=Racism alive and well in S.F. schools&amp;nbsp;– here's proof|newspaper=SF Gate|date=September 9, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A secondary, non-geographic consequence of school desegregation and busing was "cultural" white flight: withdrawing white children from the mixed-race public school system and sending them to private schools unaffected by US federal integration laws. In 1970, when the [[United States District Court for the Central District of California]] ordered the [[Pasadena Unified School District]] desegregated, the proportion of white students (54%) reflected the school district's proportion of whites (53%). Once the federally ordered school desegregation began, whites who could afford private schools withdrew their children from the racially diverse [[Pasadena, California|Pasadena]] public school system. By 2004, Pasadena had 63 private schools educating some 33% of schoolchildren, while white students made up only 16% of the public school populace. The Pasadena Unified School District superintendent characterized public schools as "like the bogey-man" to whites. He implemented policies to attract white parents to the racially diverse Pasadena public school district.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.penfamilies.org/documents/dailyjournal_5_17_04.pdf|author=Ryan, John|title=Tackling Local Resistance to Public Schools|work=Daily Journal}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Checkerboard and tipping models===
In studies in the 1980s and 1990s, blacks said they were willing to live in neighborhoods with 50/50 ethnic composition. Whites were also willing to live in integrated neighborhoods, but preferred proportions of more whites. Despite this willingness to live in integrated neighborhoods, most people live in segregated neighborhoods, which have continued to form.&lt;ref name=Zhang&gt;{{Cite journal | last1 = Zhang | first1 = J. | doi = 10.1111/j.1467-9787.2010.00671.x | title = Tipping and Residential Segregation: A Unified Schelling Model* | journal = Journal of Regional Science | volume = 51 | pages = 167–193 | year = 2011 | pmid =  | pmc = }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1969, Nobel Prize-winning economist [[Thomas Schelling]] published "Models of Segregation", a paper in which he demonstrated through a "checkerboard model" and mathematical analysis, that even when every agent prefers to live in a mixed-race neighborhood, almost complete segregation of neighborhoods emerges as individual decisions accumulate. In his "tipping model", he showed that members of an ethnic group do not move out of a neighborhood as long as the proportion of other ethnic groups is relatively low, but if a critical level of other ethnicities is exceeded, the original residents may make rapid decisions and take action to leave. This tipping point is viewed as simply the end-result of [[domino effect]] originating when the threshold of the majority ethnicity members with the highest sensitivity to sameness is exceeded. If these people leave and are either not replaced or replaced by other ethnicities, then this in turn raises the level of mixing of neighbors, exceeding the departure threshold for additional people.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Schelling, T.|year=1969|title=Models of segregation|journal=The American Economic Review|volume=59|issue=2|pages=488–493}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Africa==

===South Africa===
About 800,000 out of an earlier total population of 5.2 million whites have left [[South Africa]] since 1995, according to a report from 2009{{Citation needed|date=October 2014}}. ([[Apartheid]], a system of segregation of whites, blacks, and people of other races, had ended in 1994.) The country has suffered a high rate of violent crime, a primary stated reason for emigration{{Citation needed|date=October 2014}}. Other causes include [[South African farm attacks|attacks against white farmers]], concern about being excluded by [[affirmative action]] programs, rolling blackouts in electrical supplies, and worries about corruption and autocratic political tendencies among new leaders. Since many of those who leave are highly educated, there are shortages of skilled personnel in the government, teaching, and other professional areas{{Citation needed|date=October 2014}}. Some observers fear the long-term consequences, as South Africa's labor policies make it difficult to attract skilled immigrants. The migration of whites in South Africa was facilitated by the creation of immigration routes into European countries for people with European ancestry. For instance, the British government introduced the notion of patriality to ensure white people of British ancestry from Africa could settle in the UK{{Citation needed|date=October 2014}}. In the global economy, some professionals and skilled people have been attracted to work in the US and European nations.&lt;ref name="Economist 12295535"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.newsweek.com/2009/02/13/fleeing-from-south-africa.html |author=Johnson, Scott|title=Fleeing From South Africa|work=Newsweek|date=February 14, 2009|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110728021207/http://www.newsweek.com/2009/02/13/fleeing-from-south-africa.html|archivedate=July 28, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Zimbabwe (Rhodesia)===

Until 1980, the former British dependency of [[Rhodesia]] held a well-publicised image as being one of two nations in sub-Saharan Africa where a white minority of European descent and culture held political, economic, and social control over a preponderantly black African majority.&lt;ref name="Nelson"&gt;{{cite book|title=Zimbabwe, a Country Study|series=Area Handbook Series|editor-last=Nelson|editor-first=Harold D|year=1983|location=Washington, D.C.|publisher=Department of the Army, [[American University]]|edition=Second|oclc=227599708}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nevertheless, unlike white South Africans a significant percentage of [[White people in Zimbabwe|white Rhodesian]]s represented recent immigrants. Initially, about three-fourths of resident whites were of British origin, with those from England and Wales predominating.&lt;ref name="Nelson"/&gt; After [[World War II]] there was a substantial influx of the [[British diaspora]], including former colonials from [[India]], [[Pakistan]], and other British possessions in Africa. Also represented were working-class Englishmen responding to economic opportunities.&lt;ref name="Nelson"/&gt; In 1969 only 41% of Rhodesia's white community had been nationals since birth, or 93,600 persons. It was estimated that half of the remainder held British passports (approximately 67,000 persons), with a smaller number having South African passports.&lt;ref name="Nelson"/&gt;

During the [[Rhodesian Bush War]], almost the entire white male population between eighteen and fifty-eight was affected by various military commitments, and individuals spent up to five or six months of the year on combat duty away from their normal occupations in the civil service, commerce, industry, or agriculture.&lt;ref name="blackfire"&gt;{{cite book|last=Raeburn|first=Michael|title=We are everywhere: Narratives from Rhodesian guerillas|pages=200–209}}&lt;/ref&gt; These long periods of service in the field led to an increased emigration of men of military age. In November 1963, state media cited the chief reasons for emigration as uncertainty about the future, economic decline due to embargo and war, and the heavy commitments of national service, which was described as "the overriding factor causing people to leave".&lt;ref name="blackfire"/&gt; Of the male emigrants in 1976 about half fell into the 15 to 39 age bracket. Between 1960 and 1976 160,182 whites immigrated, while 157,724 departed. This dynamic turnover rate led to depressions in the property market, a slump in the construction industry, and a decline in retail sales.&lt;ref name="blackfire"/&gt; The number of white Rhodesians peaked in 1975 at 278,000 and rapidly declined as the bush war intensified. Disfavour with the biracial [[Zimbabwe Rhodesia]] administration in 1979 also contributed to a mass exodus.&lt;ref name="Nelson"/&gt;

The establishment of the new [[Republic of Zimbabwe]] in 1980 sounded the death knell for white political power and ushered in a new era of self-determination for the black majority.&lt;ref name="Nelson"/&gt; White emigration peaked between 1980 and 1982 at 53,000 persons, with the breakdown of law and order, an increase in crime in the rural areas, and the provocative attitude of Zimbabwean officials being cited as the main causes.&lt;ref name="SmithGB"&gt;{{cite book|author= Smith, Ian|title=The Great Betrayal|pages=368–409|publisher= Blake Publishing Ltd.|location=London|year=1997|isbn= 1-85782-176-9}}&lt;/ref&gt; Political conditions typically had a greater impact on the decision to migrate among white than black professionals.&lt;ref name="Driouchi"&gt;{{cite book|author= Driouchi, Ahmed|title=Labor and Health Economics in the Mediterranean Region: Migration and Mobility of Medical Doctors |pages=340–345|publisher= IGI Global|location=Hershey|year=2014|isbn= 978-1466647237}}&lt;/ref&gt; Between 1982 and 2000 Zimbabwe registered a net loss of 100,000 whites, or an average of 5,000 departures per year.&lt;ref name="Marrow"&gt;Helen Marrow, The new Americans: a guide to immigration since 1965 // Mary C. Waters, Reed Ueda, Helen B. Marrow (eds.), Harvard University Press, 2007, pp. 309-317&lt;/ref&gt; A second wave of white emigration was sparked by President [[Robert Mugabe]]'s violent [[Land reform in Zimbabwe|land reform]] programme after 2000.&lt;ref name="Driouchi"/&gt; Popular destinations included South Africa and Australia, which emigrants perceived to be geographically, culturally, or sociopolitically similar to their home country.&lt;ref name="Marrow"/&gt;

From a strictly economic point of view, the departure figures were not as significant as the loss of the skills of those leaving.&lt;ref name="Nelson"/&gt;  A disproportionate number of white Zimbabwean emigrants were well educated and highly skilled. Among those living in the United States, for example, 53.7% had a bachelor's degree, while only 2% had not completed secondary school.&lt;ref name="Marrow"/&gt; Most (52.4%) had occupied technical or supervisory positions of critical importance to the modern sector of the economy.&lt;ref name="Marrow"/&gt; Inasmuch as black workers did not begin making large inroads into apprenticeships and other training programs until the 1970s, few were in a position to replace their white colleagues in the 1980s.&lt;ref name="Nelson"/&gt;

==Europe==

===Denmark===
A study of school choice in [[Copenhagen]] found that an [[immigration to Denmark|immigrant]] proportion of below 35% in the local schools did not affect parental choice of schools. If the percentage of immigrant children rose above this level, native Danes are far more likely to choose other schools. Immigrants who speak Danish at home also opt out. Other immigrants, often more recent ones, stay with local schools.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | last1 = Rangvid | first1 = B. S. | title = School Choice, Universal Vouchers and Native Flight from Local Schools | doi = 10.1093/esr/jcp024 | journal = European Sociological Review | volume = 26 | issue = 3 | pages = 319–335 | year = 2009 | pmid =  | pmc = }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Ireland===
A 2007 government report stated that immigration in [[Dublin]] has caused "dramatic" white flight from elementary schools in a studied area (Dublin 15). 27% of residents were foreign-born immigrants. The report stated that Dublin was risking creating immigrant-dominated ''[[banlieues]]'', on the outskirts of a city, similar to such areas in France. The immigrants in the area included [[Eastern Europeans]] (such as those from [[Poland]]), Asians, and Africans (mainly [[political refugees]] from [[Nigeria]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20071024022221/http://www.iht.com/articles/ap/2007/10/19/europe/EU-GEN-Ireland-White-Flight.php|url=http://www.iht.com/articles/ap/2007/10/19/europe/EU-GEN-Ireland-White-Flight.php |title=Report finds evidence of 'white flight' from immigrants in northwest Dublin|work=International Herald Tribune|date=October 19, 2007|archivedate=October 27, 2007|accessdate=April 20, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===The Netherlands===
A rise in ethnic violence (crime committed by and against immigrants), and fear that social order is breaking down, are cited as motives for white flight (as well as over-crowding and traffic jams). A 2004 all-party report by the government concluded that the immigration policy had been a failure. There were concerns about "sink schools" and [[ethnic ghetto]]s. Half the prison population was composed of immigrant youths. More than 40% of immigrants received some form of government assistance. Immigrants said they were widely discriminated against.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/education/3348562/Dutch-desert-their-changing-country.html |author=Ambrose Evans-Pritchard |title=Dutch desert their changing country|work=The Telegraph|date=December 11, 2004|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2005/02/27/international/europe/27dutch.html |author=Simons, Marslie |title=More Dutch Plan to Emigrate as Muslim Influx Tips Scales|work=New York Times|date=February 27, 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Norway===
White flight in [[Norway]] has increased in the 1970s with the immigration of non-Scandinavians from (in numerical order, starting with the largest): Poland, [[Pakistan]], [[Iraq]], [[Somalia]], [[Vietnam]], [[Iran]], [[Turkey]], [[Bosnia and Herzegovina]], [[Russia]], [[Sri Lanka]], [[the Philippines]], [[the UK]], [[Kosovo]], [[Thailand]], [[Afghanistan]], and [[Lithuania]]. By June 2009, more than 40% of [[Oslo]] schools had an immigrant majority, with some schools having a 97% immigrant share.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.frie-ytringer.com/2009/06/09/40-prosent-av-osloskolene-har-innvandrerflertall/|title=40 prosent av Osloskolene har innvandrerflertall|language=no}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{unreliable source?|date=October 2013|reason=blog}} Schools in Oslo are increasingly divided by ethnicity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dagsavisen.no/samfunn/rommer-til-hvitere-skoler/|title=Rømmer til hvitere skoler|work=Dagsavisen|date=June 2, 2009|last=Bredeveien|first=Jo Moen|trans_title=Escaping the whiter schools|language=no}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aftenposten.no/nyheter/iriks/article3228559.ece|title=Foreldre flytter barna til 'hvitere' skoler|work=Aftenposten|date=August 22, 2009|last=Lundgaard|first=Hilde|trans_title=Parents moving kids to 'whiter' schools|language=no}}&lt;/ref&gt; For instance, in the [[Groruddalen]] (Grorud valley), four boroughs which currently has a population of around 165,000, the ethnic Norwegian population decreased by 1,500 in 2008, while the immigrant population increased by 1,600.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.osloby.no/nyheter/Ola-og-Kari-flytter-fra-innvandrerne-5313778.html|title=Ola og Kari flytter fra innvandrerne|work=Aftenposten|date=December 15, 2009|last=Slettholm|first=Andreas|language=no}}&lt;/ref&gt; In thirteen years, a total of 18,000 ethnic Norwegians have moved from the borough.&lt;ref name=nett15110&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nettavisen.no/nyheter/article2802878.ece|title=Noen barn er brune |work=Nettavisen|date=January 15, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In January 2010, a news feature from ''[[Dagsrevyen]]'' on the public [[Norwegian Broadcasting Corporation]] said, "Oslo has become a [[racially]] divided city. In some city districts the [[racial segregation]] starts already in kindergarten." Reporters said, "In the last years the brown schools have become browner, and the white schools whiter," a statement which caused some minor controversy.&lt;ref name=nett15110/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.dagbladet.no/2010/01/14/nyheter/dagsrevyen/nrk/tv/tv_og_medier/9914499/|title=Et stort flertall av barna er brune|work=Dagbladet|first1=Gunnar|last1=Ringheim|first2=Line|last2=Fransson|first3=Lars Molteberg|last3=Glomnes|date=January 14, 2010|language=no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Sweden===
After [[World War II]], immigration into Sweden occurred in three phases. The first was a direct result of the war, with refugees from [[concentration camp]]s and surrounding countries in Scandinavia and Northern Europe. The second, prior to 1970, involved immigrant workers, mainly from [[Finland]], [[Italy]], [[Greece]], and [[Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia|Yugoslavia]]. In the most recent phase, from the 1970s onwards, refugees immigrated from the [[Middle East]], Africa, and [[Latin America]], joined later by their relatives.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Andersson|2007|p=64}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A study which mapped patterns of segregation and congregation of incoming population groups&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Andersson|2007|p=68}}&lt;/ref&gt; found that, if a majority group is reluctant to accept a minority influx, they may leave the district, avoid the district, or use tactics to keep the minority out. The minority group in turn react by either dispersing or congregating, avoiding certain districts in turn. Detailed analysis of data from the 1990s onwards indicates that the concentration of immigrants in certain city districts, such as [[Husby, Stockholm|Husby]] in Stockholm and [[Rosengård]] in [[Malmö]], is in part due to immigration influx, but primarily due to white flight.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Andersson|2007|pp=74–75}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | last1 = Bråmå | first1 = Åsa | title = ‘White flight’? The production and reproduction of immigrant concentration areas in Swedish cities, 1990–2000 | doi = 10.1080/00420980500406736 | journal = Urban Studies | volume = 43 | issue = 7 | pages = 1127–1146 | year = 2006 | pmid =  | pmc = }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===United Kingdom===
For centuries, [[London]] was the destination for refugees and immigrants from continental Europe. Although all the immigrants were European, neighborhoods showed [[ethnic succession]] over time, as older residents (in some cases, ethnic British) moved out and new immigrants moved in, an early case of white flight (though the majority of London's population was still ethnic British).&lt;ref name="Porter"&gt;{{cite book|author=Porter, Roy|authorlink=Roy Porter|title=London: A Social History|location=Cambridge, MA|publisher=Harvard University Press|year=1994|pages=132, 140}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 2001 [[census in the United Kingdom|census]], the London boroughs of [[London Borough of Newham|Newham]] and [[London Borough of Brent|Brent]] were found to be the first areas to have non-white majorities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/shared/spl/hi/uk/03/census_2001/html/ethnicity.stm |work=BBC News|title=Census 2001: Ethnicity}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[United Kingdom Census 2011|2011 census]] found that, for the first time, less than 50% of London's population were white British, and that in some areas of London white British people make up less than 20% of the population. A 2005 report stated that white migration within the UK is mainly from areas of high ethnic minority population to those with predominantly white populations. White British families have moved out of London as many immigrants have settled in the capital. The report's writers expressed concern about British social cohesion and stated that different ethnic groups were living "parallel lives"; they were concerned that lack of contact between the groups could result in fear more readily exploited by extremists. The London School of Economics in a study found similar results.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Johnston, Philip|title=Whites 'leaving cities as migrants move in'|work=The Telegraph|date=February 10, 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Researcher Ludi Simpson says that the growth of ethnic minorities in Britain is due mostly to natural population growth (births outnumber deaths) rather than immigration. Both white and non-white Britons who can do so economically are equally likely to leave mixed-race inner-city areas. In his opinion, these trends indicate [[counter urbanisation]] rather than white flight.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Dominic Casciani|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/magazine/5304276.stm |title=So who's right over segregation?|work=[[BBC News]] Magazine|date=September 4, 2006|accessdate=September 21, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Finney|Simpson|2009|loc=Myths and counterarguments: a quick reference summary}}

==Oceania==

===Australia===
In [[Sydney]], the poorer suburbs that attracted migrants were in the [[Greater Western Sydney]] region, away from the city and the harbor. Those areas popular with European and Asian migrants experienced a degree of white flight, with a concentration of [[Anglo-Celtic Australian|Anglo-Celtic]] people in certain areas, such as [[Penrith, New South Wales|Penrith]] in far-western Sydney, the [[Sutherland Shire]] and the [[Gosford, New South Wales|Gosford]]–[[Wyong, New South Wales|Wyong]] area of the Central Coast, north of Sydney. These suburbs remain predominantly European-Australian.&lt;ref&gt;Birrell, Bob, and Seol, Byung-Soo. [http://elecpress.monash.edu.au/pnp/free/pnpv6n3/BirrSeol1.htm "Sydney's Ethnic Underclass"], ''People and Place'', vol. 6, no. 3, September 1998. {{wayback|url=http://elecpress.monash.edu.au/pnp/free/pnpv6n3/BirrSeol1.htm |date=20061002100113 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the [[New South Wales]] Secondary Principals Council and the [[University of Western Sydney]], public schools in that state have experienced white flight to private and Catholic schools wherever there is a large presence of [[Australian Aboriginal|Aboriginal]] and Middle Eastern students.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.stuff.co.nz/world/308634/White-flight-from-Aussie-public-schools|title='White flight' from Aussie public schools|work=Sydney Morning Herald|date=March 10, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===New Zealand===
[[File:New Zealand school decile vs roll ethnicity 2011.png|thumb|250px|alt=European/Pakeha students make up less than 10% of the student body in 1st-decile schools and over 70% in high-decile schools. Maori and Pasifica students make up 50 and around 42% respectively in 1st-decile schools, and less than 10% each in 10th-decile schools.|Percentages of New Zealand school rolls occupied by certain ethnic groups in 2011, broken down by socioeconomic decile. White flight is evident with low-decile schools have a disproportionately low number of European students and high numbers of Maori and Pacifika students, while the inverse is true for high-decile schools.]]
White flight has been observed in low [[Socio-Economic Decile|socioeconomic decile]] schools in New Zealand. Data from the [[Ministry of Education (New Zealand)|Ministry of Education]] found that 60,000 New Zealand European students attended low-decile schools (situated in the poorest areas) in 2000, and had fallen to half that number in 2010. The same data also found that high-decile schools (which are in the wealthiest areas) had a corresponding increase in New Zealand European students.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nzherald.co.nz/nz/news/article.cfm?c_id=1&amp;objectid=10813743|title=Claim of 'white flight' from low decile schools|work=The New Zealand Herald|author=Garret-Walker, Hana |date=June 18, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Ministry claimed demographic changes were behind the shifts, but teacher and principal associations have attributed white flight to racial and class stigmas of low-decile schools, which commonly have majority Maori and Pacific Islander rolls.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.radionz.co.nz/news/te-manu-korihi/108575/some-pakeha-parents-stereotyping-maori-pupils-principals|title=Some Pakeha parents stereotyping Maori pupils&amp;nbsp;– principals|publisher=Radio New Zealand|date=June 19, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In one specific case, white flight has significantly affected Sunset Junior High School in a suburb of the city of [[Rotorua]], with the total number of students reduced from 700 to 70 in the early 1980s. All but one of the 70 students are Maori. The area has a concentration of poor, low-skilled people, with struggling families, and many single mothers. Related to the social problems of the families, student educational achievement is low on the standard reading test.&lt;ref name="NZ_Herald_10392647"&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.nzherald.co.nz/warriors-still/news/article.cfm?c_id=1501094&amp;objectid=10392647 |title='White flight' threatens school |author=Collins, Simon |date=July 24, 2006 |work=[[The New Zealand Herald]] |accessdate=September 22, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{col-begin}}{{col-break}}
*[[Auto-segregation]]
*[[Black flight]]
*[[Ethnic succession theory]]
*[[Gentrification]]
*[[Planned shrinkage]]
{{col-break|gap=4em}}
*[[Political demography]]
*[[Residential segregation]]
*[[Urban decay]]
*[[Xenophobia]]
{{col-end}}

==References==
'''Notes'''
{{Reflist|30em}}

'''Bibliography'''
*{{cite journal|last=Andersson|first=Roger|title=Ethnic residential segregation and integration processes in Sweden|url=http://skylla.wz-berlin.de/pdf/2007/iv07-602.pdf#page=63|publisher=[[Social Science Research Center Berlin]]|year=2007|series=Residential Segregation and the Integration of Immigrants: Britain, the Netherlands and Sweden|editor-first=Karen|editor-last= Schönwälder|pages=61–90}}
*{{cite book |author=Avila, Eric |title=Popular Culture in the Age of White Flight: Fear and Fantasy in Suburban Los Angeles |publisher=University of California Press |location=Berkeley |year=2005 |isbn=978-0-520-24811-3 |oclc= }}
*{{cite book|last1=Finney|first1=Nissa|last2=Simpson|first2=Ludi|title='Sleepwalking to segregation'?: Challenging myths about race and migration|year=2009|location=Bristol|publisher=Policy Press|isbn=9781847420077|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|author=Gamm, Gerald|year=1999|title=Urban Exodus: Why the Jews Left Boston and the Catholics Stayed|publisher=Harvard University Press}}
*{{cite book|last=Kruse|first=Kevin M.|title=White Flight: Atlanta and the Making of Modern Conservatism|publisher=Princeton University Press|location=Princeton, N.J.|isbn=978-0691133867}}
*{{cite journal|author=Lupton, R.|author2=Power, A.|year=2004|title=Minority Ethnic Groups in Britain|journal=CASE-Brookings Census Brief|number=2|location=London|url=http://sticerd.lse.ac.uk/dps/case/CBCB/census2_part1.pdf}}
*{{cite book|last=Pietila|first=Antero|title=Not in My Neighborhood: How Bigotry Shaped a Great American City|year=2010|publisher=Ivan R. Dee|location=Chicago|isbn=978-1566638432}}
*{{cite journal|last=Schneider|first=J.|title=Escape From Los Angeles: White Flight from Los Angeles and Its Schools, 1960-1980|journal=Journal of Urban History|date=30 May 2008|volume=34|issue=6|pages=995–1012|doi=10.1177/0096144208317600}}
* Seligman, Amanda I. (2005), ''Block by Block: Neighborhoods and Public Policy on Chicago's West Side'' Chicago: University of Chicago Press.
*{{cite book |author=Sugrue, Thomas J. |title=[[The Origins of the Urban Crisis]]: Race and Inequality in Postwar Detroit |publisher=Princeton University Press |location=Princeton |year= 2005 |isbn=978-0-691-12186-4 |oclc= }}
*{{cite journal|author=Tarasawa, Beth|url=http://southernspaces.org/2009/new-patterns-segregation-latino-and-african-american-students-metro-atlanta-high-schools|title=New Patterns of Segregation: Latino and African American Students in Metro Atlanta High Schools]|journal=Southern Spaces|date=January 19, 2009}}
*{{cite journal|author=Wiese, Andrew|year=2006|url=http://southernspaces.org/2006/african-american-suburban-development-atlanta |title=African American Suburban Development in Atlanta|journal=Southern Spaces}}

{{White people}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:White Flight}}
[[Category:Human migration]]
[[Category:Forced migration]]
[[Category:Race and crime]]
[[Category:Urban decay]]
[[Category:Urban decay in the United States]]
[[Category:Urban studies and planning terminology]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>