<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20101117103923|397281643" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="399908" pageid="399908" ns="0" title="White flight"><revisions><rev timestamp="2010-11-17T10:40:22Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{About|the social phenomenon|the musical band|White Flight (band)}}
{{POV|date=November 2009}}
{{Segregation}}

"'''White flight'''" is the sociologic and [[Demographics|demographic]] term denoting a trend wherein [[white people|whites]] flee [[Urban area|urban]] communities as the minority population increases, and move to other places like [[commuter town]]s.&lt;ref&gt;David J. Armor. [http://books.google.com/books?id=BJuAZpULzAsC&amp;pg=PA177&amp;dq=%22causes+white+flight%22+armor&amp;ei=f0eHSKGjEZOaigHsoaDnAQ&amp;sig=ACfU3U00umALO3lLCIR6zDA2GbLzKG0tAQ#PPA71,M1 ''Forced Justice: School Desegregation and the Law.''] Oxford University Press US, 1986.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.poynter.org/column.asp?id=58&amp;aid=111344 The Best Story of Our Lives] By Bobbi Bowman&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''[http://abcnews.go.com/US/wireStory?id=3461488 ABC News: Increasing Diversity]''&lt;/ref&gt; In many mixed-race cities in the [[United States|U.S.]], the ''[[Brown v. Board of Education]]'' (1954) decision of the [[Supreme Court of the United States|Supreme Court]], ordering the ''[[de jure]]'' [[racial desegregation]] of public schools in the United States, and subsequent attempts to achieve effective desegregation by means of forced [[Desegregation busing in the United States|busing]], were major factors propelling white flight.&lt;ref&gt;Charles T. Clotfelter. ''After Brown: The Rise and Retreat of School Desegregation.'' Princeton University Press, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Diane Ravitch. [http://books.google.com/books?id=iH6jKXSgoRkC&amp;pg=PA177&amp;vq=white+flight&amp;dq=%22School+desegregation+and+White+Flight.%22&amp;source=gbs_search_r&amp;cad=1_1&amp;sig=ACfU3U1FzJ9tPXFyq9BsrJd2aYER_3UoUQ#PPA179,M1 ''The Troubled Crusade: American Education, 1945-1980'']. Basic Books, 1984.&lt;/ref&gt; However, white flight was observed during the 1950s and 1960s even in those cities (such as [[Detroit]] and [[Cleveland]]) where racial segregation of public schools was banned long before Brown.
Although an American coinage, the term “white flight” denotes like behavior in other countries. 

The business practices of [[redlining]], [[mortgage discrimination]], and racially-[[restrictive covenants]] have been credited with accelerated white flight to the suburbs. The denying of banking and insurance and other social services or the exorbitant prices of said services increased their cost to residents in predominantly non-white suburbs and city neighborhoods.&lt;ref&gt;[http://press.princeton.edu/chapters/i8043.html ''White Flight: Atlanta and the Making of Modern Conservatism''] by Kevin M. Kruse. ISBN 978-0-691-13386-7&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''[http://books.google.com/books?id=TWo8OFJpFtAC How East New York Became a Ghetto]'' by Walter Thabit. ISBN 0-8147-8267-1. Page 42.&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, according to Laura Pulido,{{Who|date|date=August 2010}} the historical processes of [[suburbanization]] and urban decentralization contribute to contemporary [[environmental racism]].&lt;ref&gt;''Rethinking Environmental Racism: White Privilege and Urban Development in Southern California'', by Laura Pulido ''Annals of the Association of American Geographers'', Vol. 90, No. 1 (Mar. 2000), pp.12-40&lt;/ref&gt;

==Europe==
===Ireland===
Non-white immigration to [[Republic of Ireland|Ireland]] at the [[20th century]]’s end provoked white flight from [[Dublin]] to the island's interior and peripheral suburbs, which an economist described as “unprecedented white flight”. In 2006, the Central Statistic Office forecast that white flight would continue.&lt;ref&gt;http://archives.tcm.ie/businesspost/2006/03/26/story12901.asp&lt;/ref&gt; Also, international and Irish news media reported an emerging pattern of indigenous Irish self-segregation centred upon Gaeilge ([[Irish language]]) schools in reaction against the increased percentages of non-white and foreign immigrant pupils matriculated to Dublin schools.&lt;ref&gt;http://web.archive.org/web/20071024022221/http://www.iht.com/articles/ap/2007/10/19/europe/EU-GEN-Ireland-White-Flight.php&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.time.com/time/world/article/0,8599,1853128,00.html | work=Time | title=Ireland's Language Dilemma | date=23 October 2008 | first=Don | last=Duncan}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Netherlands===
In recent years, and especially after the assassination of the artist [[Theo van Gogh (film director)|Theo van Gogh]] by a Dutch Muslim, some Dutch people have left the [[Netherlands]], emigrating to [[Australia]], [[New Zealand]] and [[Canada]]. Aggravating the high-population density stresses, the rise of inter-ethnic violence and crime between the indigenous Dutch people and Muslim immigrants are cited as motives for white flight.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.telegraph.co.uk/education/3348562/Dutch-desert-their-changing-country.html Dutch desert their changing country]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2005/02/27/international/europe/27dutch.html?_r=1&amp;ex=1110171600&amp;en=d6582f891be6b650&amp;ei=5070 More Dutch Plan to Emigrate as Muslim Influx Tips Scales]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Norway===
White flight in [[Norway]] is the result of mass immigration, starting in the 1960s, and increasing since. By June 2009, more than 40% of [[Oslo]] schools had a majority of people of immigrant backgrounds, with some schools having up to a 97% immigrant share.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.frie-ytringer.com/2009/06/09/40-prosent-av-osloskolene-har-innvandrerflertall/ 40 prosent av Osloskolene har innvandrerflertall]&lt;/ref&gt; Schools in Oslo are increasingly divided by ethnicity, with white flights segregating cities being widespread.&lt;ref&gt;{{citeweb|url=http://www.dagsavisen.no/innenriks/article418561.ece|title=Rømmer til hvitere skoler|work=Dagsavisen|date=2 June 2009|last=Bredeveien|first=Jo Moen}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{citeweb|url=http://www.aftenposten.no/nyheter/iriks/article3228559.ece|title=Foreldre flytter barna til "hvitere" skoler|work=Aftenposten|date=22 August 2009|last=Lundgaard|first=Hilde}}&lt;/ref&gt; For instance, in the Oslo borough of [[Groruddalen]], which currently has a population around 165,000, the ethnic Norwegian population decreased by 1,500 in 2008, while the immigrant population increased by 1,600,&lt;ref&gt;{{citeweb|url=http://www.aftenposten.no/nyheter/oslo/article3424942.ece|title=Ola og Kari flytter fra innvandrerne|work=Aftenposten|date=15 December 2009|last=Slettholm|first=Andreas}}&lt;/ref&gt; and in thirteen years, a total of 18,000 ethnic Norwegians had moved from the borough.&lt;ref name=nett15110&gt;{{citenews|url=http://www.nettavisen.no/nyheter/article2802878.ece|title=Noen barn er brune |work=Nettavisen|date=15 January 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After receiving an increasing amount of attention, in January 2010, on the news programme ''[[Dagsrevyen]]'' on the public [[Norwegian Broadcasting Corporation]], a feature story was introduced as "Oslo has become a racially divided city. In some city districts the [[racial segregation]] starts already in kindergarten." During the feature, it was also said that "in the last years the brown schools have become browner, and the white schools whiter", an outspokenness which caused some minor controversy.&lt;ref name=nett15110/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{citenews|url=http://www.dagbladet.no/2010/01/14/nyheter/dagsrevyen/nrk/tv/tv_og_medier/9914499/|title=«Et stort flertall av barna er brune»|work=Dagbladet|first1=Gunnar|last1=Ringheim|first2=Line|last2=Fransson|first3=Lars Molteberg|last3=Glomnes|date=14 January 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Sweden===
White flight in [[Sweden]] has followed the same pattern as white flight elsewhere. The triggering event was mass immigration starting in the 1990s, especially in larger cities. The white flight is more obvious in suburban areas. In particular, in the third largest city of Malmö, white flight is the most obvious. Infamous suburbs in [[Malmö]], such as [[Rosengård]] have as much as 86% immigrants&lt;ref&gt;http://www.dn.se/nyheter/sverige/herrgarden-varst-utsatta-omradet-i-rosengard-1.476220&lt;/ref&gt; and percentage gets higher with the descendents of immigrants, mostly originating from the [[Middle East]]/[[North Africa]]. In recent debates (2009) in Sweden, different parties argued for the necessity of breaking the social structure in nearby white segregated towns like [[Vellinge]] by moving newly arrived young male immigrants to those areas by law&lt;ref&gt;http://www.dn.se/nyheter/sverige/boende-for-flyktingbarn-i-vellinge-1.991729&lt;/ref&gt;.

===United Kingdom===
[[Trevor Phillips]], head of the UK [[Commission for Equalities and Human Rights]], and Mike Poulsen, an Australian academic, have claimed that [[White British|White Britons]] and non-white Britons are becoming more segregated. However, researchers Ceri Peach, Danny Dorling and Ludi Simpson have argued that segregation in the UK is either stable or declining.&lt;ref&gt;Dominic Casciani, [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/magazine/5304276.stm So who's right over segregation?], [[BBC News]] Magazine, 4 September 2006, accessed 21 September 2006&lt;/ref&gt; Demographic data indicate trends of simultaneous ethnic minority dispersal and segregation. In the 1980s and 1990s, ethnic minority populations increased in both white-majority suburbs and towns and the [[inner city]] districts of first [[Immigration to the United Kingdom since 1922|immigrant]] settlement.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/main.jhtml?xml=/news/2005/02/10/nmig10.xml Whites leaving cities]&lt;/ref&gt; In areas such as [[London Borough of Newham|Newham]] and [[London Borough of Brent|Brent]], White Britons have become a minority, though they remain the single largest ethnic group.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/shared/spl/hi/uk/03/census_2001/html/ethnicity.stm | work=BBC News}}&lt;/ref&gt; Unlike in the United States, all major British cities have white-majority populaces.&lt;ref&gt;'Minority White Cities?', chapter 7 in [https://www.policypress.org.uk/catalog/product_info.php?products_id=1370] Finney and Simpson (2009).&lt;/ref&gt; Researcher Ludi Simpson says that the growth of ethnic minorities in Britain is due mostly to natural population growth (births outnumber deaths) rather than immigration, and that both white and non-white Britons are equally likely to leave mixed-race inner-city areas. In his opinion, these trends indicate [[counter urbanisation]] rather than white flight.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ccsr.ac.uk/research/mrpd/RaceMigBook.html Simpson, L. ''Myths and counterarguments: a quick reference summary''.&lt;/ref&gt;

==North America==
===United States===
White flight has occurred, and occurs, in almost every large U.S. city,&lt;ref&gt;''[http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2006/08/20/AR2006082000629.html Growing diversity of American cities]'' By Anushka Asthana, Washington Post. Monday 21 August 2006&lt;/ref&gt; begun consequent to the post–World War II [[Post-World War II baby boom|baby]] and economic booms. Explosive suburban population growth, and racially integrated city populations were made feasible by the building of highways and parkways bypassing non-white neighborhoods to reduce travel time between town and the country.&lt;ref name="crabgrass"&gt;''Crabgrass Frontier: The Suburbanization of the United States'' by Kenneth T. Jackson. ISBN 0-19-503610-7&lt;/ref&gt;

====History====
{{See also|Great Migration (African American)|Second Great Migration (African American)}}
After World War II, aided by the construction of the [[interstate highway system]], many [[White American]]s began fleeing large cities to new [[suburb]]s. These suburbs often had racially-restrictive housing policies. In the cities, the post-war housing shortages - resulting from the influx of rural black African, and Latino workers for war-effort employment combined with the massive numbers of military white Europeans and Mexicans returning home from the war - aggravated pre-existing socio-economic inequalities between the races. Those social conditions precipitated white flight from urban downtown areas to outlying suburbs and subdivisions where the post-war housing boom was already well under way.  With the unprecedented influx of blacks and poor whites into the nation's cities during the war, middle-class and middle working-class whites considered these locales far preferable to the inner cities, many of whose infrastructures were already in serious decline. A practice further reinforcing unofficial segregation in states outside the old Confederate South was [[Covenant (law)#Exclusionary_covenants|exclusionary covenants]] in title deeds and real estate neighborhood redlining&lt;ref&gt;[http://bellwether.metapress.com/content/h128812346540080/ Crossney and Bartelt 2005 Urban Geography][http://web.archive.org/web/20080414023817/http://www.mi.vt.edu/data/files/hpd+vol.16+issues+3+and+4/articles/hpd6%283,4%29+crossney.pdf Crossney and Bartelt 2006 Housing Policy Debate]&lt;/ref&gt; — explicit, legally sanctioned racial discrimination in real property ownership and lending practices; thus Black Americans were effectively disbarred from pursuing the [[American Dream]] of homeownership, even when they were able to afford it.&lt;ref name="crabgrass" /&gt; Suburban expansion was reserved for middle-class and working-class white people, facilitated by their increased wages incurred by the war effort and by subsequent federally-guaranteed mortgages (VA, FHA, HOLC) available only to whites to buy new houses.  Blacks and other minorities were relegated to a state of permanent rentership.&lt;ref&gt;''[http://web.archive.org/web/20080504215500/http://www.public.asu.edu/~wplotkin/DeedsWeb/fha38.html "Racial" Provisions of FHA Underwriting Manual, 1938]'' &lt;blockquote&gt; Recommended restrictions should include provisions for: prohibition of the occupancy of properties '''except by the race for which they are intended''' . . . Schools should be appropriate to the needs of the new community, and they should not be attended in large numbers by '''inharmonious racial groups'''. [[Federal Housing Administration]], Underwriting Manual: Underwriting and Valuation Procedure Under Title II of the [[National Housing Act of 1934|National Housing Act]] With Revisions to February, 1938 (Washington, D.C.), Part II, Section 9, Rating of Location.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;

The roads built via the [[Federal Aid Highway Act of 1956|National Interstate and Defense Highways Act]] (1956) and its successors, built to transport suburbanites to their city jobs, much aided white flight, and proportionately reduced the city’s supporting tax base, thus, consequently, beginning [[urban decay]].&lt;ref&gt;''Locational Dimensions of Urban Highway Impact: An Empirical Analysis'', by James O. Wheeler, “Geografiska Annaler”. Series-B, Human Geography, Vol. 58, No. 2 (1976) pp.67-78&lt;/ref&gt; In some cases, such as in the [[Southern United States]], local governments used highway road constructions to deliberately divide and isolate [[black neighborhood]]s from goods and services, often within industrial corridors. In [[Birmingham, Alabama]], the local government used the post–World War II interstate highway system to perpetuate the racial residence-boundaries the city established with a 1926 racial zoning law. Constructing interstate highways through majority-black neighborhoods eventually reduced the populations to the poorest proportion of people financially unable to leave their destroyed community.&lt;ref&gt;''From Racial Zoning to Community Empowerment: The Interstate Highway System and the African American Community in Birmingham, Alabama'' Charles E. Connerly Journal of Planning Education and Research, Vol. 22, No. 2, pp.99-114 (2002)&lt;/ref&gt;

=====Blockbusting=====
{{Main|Blockbusting}}

The [[real estate]] business practice of “blockbusting” was a very important means of controlling non-white migration and aiding white flight for profit. By subterfuge, real estate agents would facilitate black people buying a house in a white neighborhood; either buying the house themselves, or via a white proxy buyer, and then re-selling it to the black family. The consequent panic among the remaining white inhabitants (aggravated by real estate agents and the local newsmedia)&lt;ref&gt;[Ford, Richard T. ''The race card : how bluffing about bias makes race relations worse''; New York: Farrar, Straus and Giroux, 2008; pp. 290-291]&lt;/ref&gt;, would psychologically coerce the remaining white inhabitants, fearing devalued residential property, to quickly sell, usually at a loss — realized when they began selling en masse — thus generating great sales commissions for the agents. In turn, the real estate agents would then sell at to the incoming black families, profiting from price [[arbitrage]] and the sales commissions from both the black and white victims of such schemes. Thereby, the racial composition of a neighborhood populace often changed completely in a few years.&lt;ref&gt;''[http://www.encyclopedia.chicagohistory.org/pages/147.html Blockbusting]'' - Encyclopedia of Chicago History&lt;/ref&gt;

=====Urban decay=====
{{Main|Urban decay}}
[[Image:BrokenPromises JohnFekner.jpg|thumb|250px|right|&lt;small&gt;'''Urban decay in the US:'''&lt;/small&gt; the South Bronx, New York City, was exemplar of the federal and local government’s abandonment of the cities in the 1970s and 1980s; the Spanish sign reads “FALSE PROMISES”, the English sign reads “BROKEN PROMISES”.]]

Urban decay is the sociological process whereby a city, or part of a city, falls into disrepair and decrepitude — [[depopulation]], [[economic restructuring]], abandoned buildings, high local [[unemployment]], fragmented families, political [[disenfranchisement]], [[crime]], and a desolate, inhospitable city landscape.  White flight’s draining of a city’s tax base is one cause.

In the 1970s and 1980s, urban decay was associated with Western cities, especially in [[North America]] and parts of [[Europe]]. In that time, major structural changes in global economies, [[transportation]], and government policy created the economic, then social, conditions resulting in urban decay.&lt;ref&gt;''[http://books.google.com/books?id=uf0vS1A-0dkC Urban Sores: On the Interaction Between Segregation, Urban Decay, and Deprived Neighbourhoods]'', by Hans Skifter Andersen. ISBN 0-7546-3305-5. 2003.&lt;/ref&gt; Urban decay contradicts the urban development of most of Europe and North America, in countries beyond, urban decay is manifest in the peripheral [[slum]]s at the outskirts of a metropolis, while the city center and the inner city retain high real estate values and sustain a steadily increasing population.&lt;ref name="crabgrass"&gt;''[http://books.google.com/books?vid=ISBN0195049837 Crabgrass Frontier: The Suburbanization of the United States]'' by Professor Kenneth T Jackson (1987)&lt;/ref&gt;

North American cities suffered white flight to the suburbs and exurb commuter towns, which &lt;ref name="crabgrass"/&gt; started to reverse in the 1990s, when the rich suburbanites returned to cities, [[Gentrification|gentrifying]] the decayed urban neighborhoods. [[Blight (urban)|Blight]] is another characteristic of urban decay — the visual, psychological, and physical effects of living among empty lots, and buildings and houses labelled “THIS PROPERTY IS CONDEMNED”. Such desolate properties are socially dangerous to the community because they attract criminals and [[street gang]]s, thus contributing to the volume of crime. Urban decay has no single cause; it results from combinations of inter-related socio-economic conditions — including the city’s [[urban planning]] decisions, strictly-enforced [[rent control]],{{Citation needed|date=March 2009}} the [[poverty]] of the local populace, the construction of neighborhood-excluding [[freeway#Effects and controversy|freeway]] roads and rail road lines,&lt;ref name="power"&gt;''[[The Power Broker]]: Robert Moses and the Fall of New York'', by [[Robert Caro]], p.522.&lt;blockquote&gt;The construction of the [[Gowanus Parkway]], laying a concrete slab on top of lively, bustling Third Avenue, buried the avenue in shadow, and when the parkway was completed, the avenue was cast forever into darkness and gloom, and its bustle and life were forever gone.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; depopulation by suburbanization of peripheral lands, real estate neighborhood redlining,&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=TWo8OFJpFtAC How East New York Became a Ghetto] by Walter Thabit. ISBN 0-8147-8267-1. Page 42.&lt;/ref&gt; immigration restrictions,&lt;ref name="comeback"&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?vid=ISBN0813339529 Comeback Cities: A Blueprint for Urban Neighborhood Revival] By Paul S. Grogan, Tony Proscio. ISBN 0-8133-3952-9. Published 2002. pp.139-145.&lt;blockquote&gt;"The 1965 law brought an end to the lengthy and destructive — at least for cities — period of tightly restricted immigration a spell born of the [[nationalism]] and [[xenophobia]] of the 1920s", p.140&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; and [[racial discrimination]].

====Government-aided white flight====
The organization of municipal government in the U.S. facilitated white flight from racially diverse cities by establishing new municipalities beyond the abandoned city’s jurisdiction to avoid the [[legacy costs]] of maintaining city infrastructures, instead spending said taxes establishing the suburban infrastructures. The federal government contributed to white flight and the early decay of non-white city neighborhoods by withholding maintenance capital mortgages, thus making it difficult for the communities to either retain or attract middle-class residents.&lt;ref name="wilson"&gt;''[[When Work Disappears]]: The World of the New Urban Poor'', by William Julius Wilson (1996) ISBN 0-679-72417-6&lt;/ref&gt;

The new suburban communities limited the emigration of poor and non-white residents from the city with restrictive [[zoning]], thus few lower middle-class people could afford a house in the suburbs. In the event, many all-white suburbs were incorporated to the cities they had fled. Milwaukee, Wisconsin, partially incorporated [[Political subdivisions of Wisconsin|towns]] such as [[Granville, Wisconsin]]; the (then) Mayor, [[Frank P. Zeidler]] complained about the socially destructive "Iron Ring" of new municipalities incorporated in the post–World War II decade.&lt;ref&gt;''[http://www.jsonline.com/story/index.aspx?id=459264 Mayor served 'the public welfare': Longtime city icon known for integrity, energy, principles]'', by Alan J. Borsuk. “Journal Sentinel”, 8 July 2006&lt;/ref&gt; Analogously, semi-rural communities, such as [[Oak Creek, Wisconsin|Oak Creek]], [[South Milwaukee, Wisconsin|South Milwaukee]], and [[Franklin, Milwaukee County, Wisconsin|Franklin]], formally incorporated as discrete entities, to escape urban incorporation when Wisconsin state law allowed Milwaukee’s incorporation of such rural and sub-urban regions, that did not qualify for discrete incorporation, per the legal incorporation standards.&lt;ref&gt;Joel Rast, "Governing the Regimeless City: The Frank Zeidler Administration in Milwaukee, 1948–1960", ''Urban Affairs Review'', Vol. 42, No. 1, 81-112 (2006)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Donald J. Curran, "Infra-Metropolitan Competition", ''Land Economics'', Vol. 40, No. 1 (Feb., 1964), pp. 94-99&lt;/ref&gt;

====Desegregation: public schools and student busing====
{{Main|Desegregation busing}}

The post–World War II racial desegregation of U.S. society — especially of the public schools — catalyzed white flight from the cities to the suburbs. In 1954, the US Supreme Court ordered the ''de jure'' termination of the “separate, but equal” legal racism established with the ''[[Plessy v. Ferguson]]'' (1896) case in the nineteenth century, thus, with the ''[[Brown v. Board of Education]]'' (1954) case, the Supreme Court ordered the racial desegregation of public schools, because the unequal funding of majority-black and majority-white public schools ensured that black people received an inferior public education despite paying taxes for it. In 1971, in the case of ''[[Swann v. Charlotte-Mecklenburg Board of Education]]'' (1971), the Supreme Court ordered the [[desegregation busing in the United States|forced busing]] of poor black students to suburban white schools, and wealthy white students to poor schools in the city. In the case of ''[[Milliken v. Bradley]]'' (1974), the dissenting [[Justice William Douglas]] observed that “the inner core of Detroit is now rather solidly black; and the blacks, we know, in many instances are likely to be poorer. . . .” Like-wise, in 1977, the Federal decision in ''Penick v. The Columbus Board of Education'' (1977) accelerated white flight from Columbus, Ohio. Though the racial desegregation of schools affected only public school districts, the most vehement opponents of racial desegregation were whites whose children attended private schools. &lt;ref&gt;Jacobson, Cardell K., “Desegregation Rulings and Public Attitude Changes: White Resistance or Resignation?”, ''[[American Journal of Sociology]]'', v.84 n.3, pp.698–705.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2007/09/09/BAIFS1GE4.DTL C.W. Nevius: Racism alive and well in S.F. schools - here's proof]&lt;/ref&gt;

A secondary, non-geographic consequence, of school desegregation and busing was ''cultural'' white flight: withdrawing white children from the mixed-race public school system and matriculating them to private schools unaffected by U.S. federal integration laws. In 1970, when the [[United States District Court for the Central District of California]] ordered the [[Pasadena Unified School District]] desegregated, the white-student proportion (54%) of the schools approximately reflected the school district’s proportional white populace (53%).

Once the federally-ordered school desegregation occurred, whites who could afford private schools withdrew their children from the racially diverse [[Pasadena, California|Pasadena]] public school system. In result, by 2004, Pasadena had 63 private schools educating some 33% of schoolchildren, while white students made up only 16% of the public school populace. The Pasadena Unified School District superintendent characterized public schools as “like the bogey-man” to whites and implemented policies meant to persuade white parents to matriculate their children to the racially diverse Pasadena public school district.&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20080414024327/http://www.penfamilies.org/www/pen/Files/LA+Daily+Journal+Article+on+Pasadena+School+Reform.doc Tackling Local Resistance to Public Schools] By John Ryan&lt;/ref&gt; In the event, white flight rapidly altered the racial composition of public school systems; upon desegregation, in Baltimore, Maryland, the Clifton Park Junior High School had 2,023 white students and 34 black students; 10 years later, it had 12 white students and 2,037 black students. In northwest Baltimore, Garrison Junior High School’s student body declined from 2,504 whites and 12 blacks to 297 whites and 1,263 blacks in that period.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bcps.k12.md.us/About/History/From_the_Oldorder1.asp Reasons and Results 1957-1997&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

====Recent decades====
In 1967, the [[12th Street Riot]] of Detroit, Michigan, contributed to white flight, leaving contemporary Detroit more than 80 percent black, and most of its suburbs, including [[Livonia, Michigan|Livonia]], [[Dearborn, Michigan|Dearborn]], and [[Warren, Michigan|Warren]], overwhelmingly white.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2001/08/13/national/main306205.shtml | work=CBS News | title=Most Racially Uniform Cities | date=13 August 2001}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A unique example of white flight in the United States took place in [[Miami]]: in 1980, the [[Mariel Boatlift]] brought 150,000 Cubans to Miami, the largest such migration in U.S. civilian history{{Citation needed|date=January 2010}}. During this time, many of the middle class non-Hispanic whites in the community left the city. As a consequence, while non-Hispanic whites made up about 90% of Miami's population in 1960, by 1990 they made up only about 10%.&lt;ref&gt;[[Miami, Florida]] Wikipedia article, retrieved January 29, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

=====California=====
{{Citations missing|section|date=February 2008}}

In [[Southern California]], white flight from [[Los Angeles]] began before the racial [[Watts Riots]] in 1965, but the riots appear to have increased the pace of flight. Likewise, the [[Los Angeles riots of 1992|1992 riots]] spurred both [[black flight]] and white flight from the  city. In [[California]] and in the rest of the [[Western United States|western U.S.]], Hispanic Americans are the greatest ethnic minority; as their communities increased in size in larger cities, so increased the white flight to the suburbs. During the 1990s and early 2000s, African Americans continued migrating from the historically black communities of [[Inglewood, California|Inglewood]] and [[Compton, California|Compton]], which now have mostly Latino populations, to [[Inland Empire, California]] communities such as [[Fontana, California|Fontana]], [[Rialto, California|Rialto]], [[Moreno Valley, California|Moreno Valley]], [[Palmdale, California|Palmdale]], as well as parts of [[Orange County, California|Orange]], and [[Ventura County|Ventura]] Counties.&lt;ref&gt;Pollard-Terry, Gayle. “Where It's Booming: Watts”, ''[[Los Angeles Times]]'', 16 October 2005. p.E-1.&lt;/ref&gt; (See [[black flight]].)

In [[San Diego]], white flight in the 1950s occurred in much of the southern parts of the city, such as [[South East San Diego]], as residents moved to neighborhoods in the more northern part of [[San Diego County]]. As a result of this the majority of the neighborhoods south of the [[Interstate 8]] highway are predominantly [[Hispanic]], [[African-American]], or [[Filipino American|Filipino]].

Since 1980, in the states west of Texas, [[San Francisco]] and [[Oakland, California|Oakland]] are the only major U.S. cities whose white populations have increased. After sixty years of having been a predominantly black city, [[gentrification]] begun in the 1990s has changed the demographic composition of Oakland. Most of the [[Asian-American]] population of the San Francisco Bay Area live in [[San Mateo County, California|San Mateo County]], [[San Jose]], [[Santa Clara]], the [[East Bay]], [[Sonoma County, California|Sonoma]], and [[Napa Valley]], not the city proper. The non-white proportions — 20 percent black and 40 percent Latino — of the [[Social conservative|socially conservative]] capital city of Sacramento (38% white) are greater than the comparable proportions of [[Social liberal|socially liberal]] San Francisco.

==Oceania==
===Australia===
In [[Australia]], white flight occurred in the cities where most immigrants, usually Asian, settled, especially in [[Sydney]], where white Australians have moved from the [[south-western Sydney]] suburbs and have moved to peripheral metropolitan suburbs, notably [[Penrith, New South Wales|Penrith]] in far-western Sydney and the [[Gosford]]–[[Wyong]] area of the Central Coast, north of Sydney. These suburbs remain predominantly white ([[Anglo-Celtic]]).&lt;ref&gt;Birrell, Bob, and Seol, Byung-Soo. [http://elecpress.monash.edu.au/pnp/free/pnpv6n3/BirrSeol1.htm 'Sydney's Ethnic Underclass'], ''People and Place'', vol. 6, no. 3, September 1998.&lt;/ref&gt;

===New Zealand===
From the 1950s to the 1970s, white flight in areas of [[New Zealand]] was a gradual reaction to the mass urbanisation of [[Māori]] natives and Pacific island guest workers. In [[Auckland]], white flight mostly has reversed since the 1980s, with [[European New Zealander]]s residing in neighbourhoods that previously had non-white (Māori and Pacific Islander) populaces such as Ponsonby, Grey Lynn and Kingsland. Contemporarily, those previously non-white city neighbourhoods and the CBD are amongst the most expensive, desirable real estate in Auckland and New Zealand. Similar [[gentrification]] has occurred in [[Wellington]] inner city neighbourhoods of Thorndon, Newtown and Aro Valley.{{Citation needed|date=July 2008}}

==See also==
*[[Auto-segregation]]
*[[Black flight]]
*[[Ethnic succession theory]]
*[[Planned shrinkage]]
*[[Residential segregation]]
*[[Urban decay]]
*[[Xenophobia]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist|2}}

==References==
*{{cite book |author=Avila, Eric |title=Popular Culture in the Age of White Flight: Fear and Fantasy in Suburban Los Angeles |publisher=University of California Press |location=Berkeley |year=2005 |pages= |isbn=9780520248113 |oclc= |doi= |accessdate=}}
* Finney, Nissa and Simpson, Ludi (2009) [https://www.policypress.org.uk/catalog/product_info.php?products_id=1370 'Sleepwalking to segregation'? Challenging myths about race and migration], Bristol: Policy Press.
* Gamm, Gerald (1999).  ''Urban Exodus: Why the Jews Left Boston and the Catholics Stayed''  Harvard University Press.
* Kruse, Kevin M. (2005), ''[http://southernspaces.org/2005/white-flight-strategies-ideology-and-legacy-segregationists-atlanta White Flight: The Strategies, Ideology, and Legacy of Segregationists in Atlanta]'' ''Southern Spaces.'' http://southernspaces.org/2005/white-flight-strategies-ideology-and-legacy-segregationists-atlanta
* Kruse, Kevin M. (2005), ''White Flight: Atlanta and the Making of Modern Conservatism.''  Princeton:  Princeton University Press.
* Lupton, R. and Power, A. (2004) 'Minority Ethnic Groups in Britain'. CASE-Brookings Census Brief No.2, London: LSE.
*Pietila, Antero.  (2010)  ''Not in My Neighborhood: How Bigotry Shaped a Great American City'' (Chicago: Ivan R. Dee).
* Schneider, Jack (2008), ''[http://juh.sagepub.com/cgi/content/abstract/34/6/995 Escape from Los Angeles: White Flight from Los Angeles and Its Schools, 1960-1980]''
* Seligman, Amanda I. (2005), ''Block by Block: Neighborhoods and Public Policy on Chicago's West Side'' Chicago: University of Chicago Press.
*{{cite book |author=Sugrue, Thomas J. |title=The Origins of the Urban Crisis: Race and Inequality in Postwar Detroit |publisher=Princeton University Press |location=Princeton |year= 2005 |pages= |isbn=9780691121864 |oclc= |doi= |accessdate=}}
*Wiese, Andrew. (2006) "[http://southernspaces.org/2006/african-american-suburban-development-atlanta African American Suburban Development in Atlanta]" ''Southern Spaces.''http://southernspaces.org/2006/african-american-suburban-development-atlanta
*Beth Tarasawa, "[http://southernspaces.org/2009/new-patterns-segregation-latino-and-african-american-students-metro-atlanta-high-schools New Patterns of Segregation: Latino and African American Students in Metro Atlanta High Schools]," ''Southern Spaces'', 19 January 2009. 
{{DEFAULTSORT:White Flight}}
[[Category:Human migration]]
[[Category:Forced migration]]
[[Category:Urban decay]]
[[Category:Urban studies and planning terminology]]

[[cs:Bílý útěk]]
[[fr:White flight]]
[[id:White flight]]
[[ja:ホワイト・フライト]]
[[ru:Бегство белых]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>