<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20121117190218|523536024" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="399908" pageid="399908" ns="0" title="White flight"><revisions><rev timestamp="2012-11-17T20:08:47Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Use mdy dates|date=October 2012}}
{{About|the social phenomenon|the musical band|White Flight (band)}}
{{Multiple issues|POV = November 2009|refimprove = January 2012|lead too long = September 2011}}

{{Segregation}}

'''White flight''' is a term that originated in the United States, starting in the mid-20th century, and applied to the large-scale migration of [[European American|whites of various European ancestries]] from racially mixed urban regions to more racially homogeneous suburban or [[exurban]] regions, originating from fear and anxiety about increasing minority populations{{citation needed|date=January 2012}}. The term has more recently been applied to other migrations by whites, from older, inner suburbs to rural areas, as well as from the US Northeast and Midwest to the milder climate in Southeast and Southwest, but this is a change from its original cause and meaning.&lt;ref&gt;''The Encyclopedia of Race, Ethnicity, and Society,'' editor Richard T. Schaefer, 2008, SAGE publications&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Merriam-Webster Dictionary, http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/white%20flight&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;David J. Armor. [http://books.google.com/books?id=BJuAZpULzAsC&amp;pg=PA177&amp;dq=%22causes+white+flight%22+armor&amp;ei=f0eHSKGjEZOaigHsoaDnAQ&amp;sig=ACfU3U00umALO3lLCIR6zDA2GbLzKG0tAQ#PPA71,M1 ''Forced Justice: School Desegregation and the Law.''] Oxford University Press US, 1986.&lt;/ref&gt;

The term has also been used for large scale [[Decolonization|post-colonial]] emigration of [[White Africans of European ancestry|whites from Africa]],&lt;ref name=Hammer2010&gt;{{cite news|title=(Almost) Out of Africa: The White Tribes|work=World Affairs Journal|author=Joshua Hammer|date=May/June 2010|url=http://www.worldaffairsjournal.org/articles/2010-MayJune/full-Hammer-MJ- 2010.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Mosiuoa 'Terror' Lekota threatens to topple the ANC|author=RW Johnson|date=October 19, 2008|work=The Times |url=http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/world/africa/article4969026.ece|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title= The atlas of changing South Africa|edition= 2nd Edition|author=A. J. Christopher|year=2000 |publisher=Routledge|page=213}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;The uncertain promise of Southern Africa, York W.  Bradshaw, Stephen N. Ndegwa, 2001, Indiana University Press, page  6&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Transatlantic history,  Steven G. Reinhardt, Dennis Reinhartz,  William Hardy McNeill, Texas A&amp;M University Press, 2006, pages 149–150&lt;/ref&gt; driven by levels of violent crime and other reasons.&lt;ref name= "Economist 12295535"&gt;{{cite news|title=White flight from South Africa: Between staying and going|work=The Economist|date=September 25, 2008|url=http://www.economist.com/node/12295535}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Following [[World War II]], there was pent-up housing demand in the US, and widespread suburban development took place. In addition, some working-class and middle-class white families felt pressure from increases in minority populations and overcrowding in cities.{{citation needed|date=January 2012}} They moved out to the suburbs, aided by [[G.I. Bill|GI loans]] for purchase, federally subsidized highway construction, and other facilities that made commuting to work easier. {{citation needed|date=January 2012}}

In the 1970s, attempts to achieve effective [[desegregation]] by means of forced [[Desegregation busing in the United States|busing]] in some areas led to more families' moving out of former areas.&lt;ref&gt;Charles T. Clotfelter. ''After Brown: The Rise and Retreat of School Desegregation.'' Princeton University Press, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Diane Ravitch. [http://books.google.com/books?id=iH6jKXSgoRkC&amp;pg=PA177&amp;vq=white+flight&amp;dq=%22School+desegregation+and+White+Flight.%22&amp;source=gbs_search_r&amp;cad=1_1&amp;sig=ACfU3U1FzJ9tPXFyq9BsrJd2aYER_3UoUQ#PPA179,M1 ''The Troubled Crusade: American Education, 1945–1980'']. Basic Books, 1984.&lt;/ref&gt; Migration of middle-class white populations was observed during the 1950s and 1960s out of cities such as Detroit and [[Cleveland]], although racial segregation of public schools had ended there long before the U.S. Supreme Court's decision in ''[[Brown v. Board of Education]]''. More generally, some historians suggest that white flight occurred in response to population pressures, both from the large migration of blacks from the rural South to northern cities in the [[Great Migration (African American)|Great Migration]] and the waves of new immigrants from southern and eastern Europe.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite doi|10.1162/qjec.2010.125.1.417}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, some historians have challenged the phrase "white flight" as a misnomer whose use should be reconsidered. In her study of Chicago's West Side during the post-war era, historian Amanda Seligman argues that the phrase misleadingly suggests that whites immediately departed when blacks moved into the neighborhood, when in fact, many whites defended their space with violence, intimidation, or legal tactics.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Seligman|first=Amanda|title=Block by block : neighborhoods and public policy on Chicago's West Side|year=2005|publisher=University of Chicago Press|location=Chicago|isbn=978-0-226-74663-0|pages=213–14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The business practices of [[redlining]], [[mortgage discrimination]], and racially [[restrictive covenants]] contributed to the overcrowding and physical deterioration of areas where minorities chose to congregate. Such conditions are considered to have contributed to the out-migration of other populations. The limited facilities for banking and insurance, due to a perceived lack of profitability, and other social services, and extra fees meant to hedge against perceived profit issues increased their cost to residents in predominantly non-white suburbs and city neighborhoods.&lt;ref&gt;[http://press.princeton.edu/chapters/i8043.html Kevin M. Kruse, ''White Flight: Atlanta and the Making of Modern Conservatism''] ISBN 978-0-691-13386-7&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=TWo8OFJpFtAC Walter Thabit, ''How East New York Became a Ghetto''] by . ISBN 0-8147-8267-1. p. 42.&lt;/ref&gt; According to the environmental geographer Laura Pulido, the historical processes of suburbanization and urban decentralization contribute to contemporary [[environmental racism]].&lt;ref&gt;Laura Pulido, "Rethinking Environmental Racism: White Privilege and Urban Development in Southern California", ''Annals of the Association of American Geographers'', Vol. 90, No. 1 (Mar. 2000), pp.12–40&lt;/ref&gt;

==United States==
{{Off-topic|date=April 2011}}
In its first centuries the US was settled primarily by immigrants from northern Europe, and it transported slaves from Africa in a forced migration. By the time of the Civil War, the overwhelming number of African Americans were located in the rural South.

Many of the 19th c. and later immigrants were from rural societies and relatively unskilled; they started working in entry-level jobs. By the post–World War II [[Post–World War II baby boom|baby]] and [[Post–World War II economic expansion|economic]] booms, their descendants were thriving and there was pent-up demand after the war for improved housing. The subsidized federal highway construction and real estate development of cheaper outlying lands led to suburban development and growth outside cities; commuting by highways and parkways allowed the wealthier residents to bypass older areas filled with newer, poorer immigrants.&lt;ref name="crabgrass"&gt;Kenneth T. Jackson, ''Crabgrass Frontier: The Suburbanization of the United States'', ISBN 0-19-503610-7&lt;/ref&gt;

During the later twentieth century, industrial restructuring led to major losses of jobs, leaving formerly middle-class working populations suffering poverty, with some unable to move away for new work. Since the 1960s and changed immigration laws, the United States has received immigrants from Mexico, Central and South America; Asian and African nations. Such immigrants have changed the demographics of both cities and suburbs, for at the same time, the US has become a suburban nation. The suburbs have become more diverse. In addition, Latinos, the fastest growing minority group in the US, have begun to migrate within the interior of the nation and away from the traditional entry cities. For instance, some are moving to such Southwest cities as Phoenix and Tucson, where their increasing numbers in 2006 made [[European American]]s a minority in additional cities of the West.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2006/08/20/AR2006082000629.html Anushka Asthana, "Changing Face of Western Cities: Migration Within U.S. Makes Whites a Minority in 3 More Areas"], ''Washington Post'', August 21, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

===Overview===
{{See also|Great Migration (African American)|Second Great Migration (African American)}}
After World War II, aided by the construction of the [[interstate highway system]], many [[White American]]s began leaving industrial cities for new housing in suburbs. These suburbs often had racially restrictive housing policies excluding African Americans, Hispanic Americans, Native Americans and/or Jews and Catholics. In the cities, the post-war housing shortages – resulting from the influx of rural black and Latino workers for war-effort employment, combined with the massive numbers of white military veterans returning home from the war, aggravated socio-economic inequalities between the races. Those social conditions precipitated white flight from urban downtown areas to outlying suburbs and subdivisions where the post-war housing boom was already well under way. With the unprecedented influx of blacks and poor whites into the nation's cities during the war, middle-class and middle working-class whites considered suburban locales preferable to the inner cities, many of whose infrastructures were already in serious decline.{{citation needed|date=January 2012}}

===Catalysts for white flight===

====Legal exclusion====
A practice further reinforcing unofficial segregation in states outside the South, where racial segregation was legal, were [[Covenant (law)#Exclusionary_covenants|exclusionary covenants]] in title deeds and real estate neighborhood redlining&lt;ref&gt;[http://bellwether.metapress.com/content/h128812346540080/ Crossney and Bartelt 2005 Urban Geography][http://web.archive.org/web/20080414023817/http://www.mi.vt.edu/data/files/hpd+vol.16+issues+3+and+4/articles/hpd6%283,4%29+crossney.pdf Crossney and Bartelt, "2006 Housing Policy Debate"]&lt;/ref&gt; — explicit, legally sanctioned racial discrimination in real property ownership and lending practices. Black Americans were effectively barred from pursuing homeownership, even when they were able to afford it.&lt;ref name="crabgrass" /&gt; Suburban expansion was reserved for middle-class and working-class white people, facilitated by their increased wages incurred by the war effort and by subsequent federally guaranteed mortgages (VA, FHA, HOLC) available only to whites to buy new houses. Blacks and other minorities were relegated to a state of permanent rentership.&lt;ref&gt;''[http://wbhsi.net/~wendyplotkin/DeedsWeb/fha38.html "Racial" Provisions of FHA Underwriting Manual, 1938]'' &lt;blockquote&gt; Recommended restrictions should include provisions for: prohibition of the occupancy of properties '''except by the race for which they are intended''' . . . Schools should be appropriate to the needs of the new community, and they should not be attended in large numbers by '''inharmonious racial groups'''. [[Federal Housing Administration]], Underwriting Manual: Underwriting and Valuation Procedure Under Title II of the [[National Housing Act of 1934|National Housing Act]] With Revisions to February, 1938 (Washington, D.C.), Part II, Section 9, Rating of Location.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;

====Roads====
The roads built via the [[Federal Aid Highway Act of 1956|National Interstate and Defense Highways Act]] (1956) and its successors served to transport suburbanites to their city jobs, thus facilitating the development of these suburbs, and shifting the tax base away from the city and out to the suburbs. This may have exacerbated  [[urban decay]].&lt;ref&gt;''Locational Dimensions of Urban Highway Impact: An Empirical Analysis'', by James O. Wheeler, “Geografiska Annaler”. Series-B, Human Geography, Vol. 58, No. 2 (1976) pp.67–78&lt;/ref&gt; In some cases, such as in the Southern United States, local governments used highway road constructions to deliberately divide and isolate [[black neighborhood]]s from goods and services, often within industrial corridors. In [[Birmingham, Alabama]], the local government used the post–World War II interstate highway system to perpetuate the racial residence-boundaries the city established with a 1926 racial zoning law. Constructing interstate highways through majority-black neighborhoods eventually reduced the populations to the poorest proportion of people financially unable to leave their destroyed community.&lt;ref&gt;''From Racial Zoning to Community Empowerment: The Interstate Highway System and the African American Community in Birmingham, Alabama'' Charles E. Connerly Journal of Planning Education and Research, Vol. 22, No. 2, pp.99–114 (2002)&lt;/ref&gt;

====Blockbusting====
{{Main|Blockbusting}}
The real estate business practice of “blockbusting” was a for-profit catalyst for white flight and a means to control non-white migration. By subterfuge, real estate agents would facilitate black people's buying a house in a white neighborhood; either buying the house themselves, or via a white proxy buyer, and then re-selling it to the black family. The remaining white inhabitants (alarmed by real estate agents and the local newsmedia),&lt;ref&gt;Ford, Richard T. ''The Race Card: How Bluffing about Bias Makes Race Relations Worse''; New York: Farrar, Straus and Giroux, 2008; pp. 290–291&lt;/ref&gt; fearing devalued residential property, would quickly sell, usually at a loss. Losses happened when they sold ''en masse'', but sales agents made good commissions anyway. They could sell the properties to the incoming black families, profiting from price [[arbitrage]] and the sales commissions from both the black and white victims of such schemes. By such tactics, the racial composition of a neighborhood population often changed completely in a few years.&lt;ref&gt;''[http://www.encyclopedia.chicagohistory.org/pages/147.html Blockbusting]'' – Encyclopedia of Chicago History&lt;/ref&gt;

====Urban decay====
{{Main|Urban decay}}
[[File:BrokenPromises JohnFekner.jpg|thumb|250px|right|'''Urban decay in the US:''' the South Bronx, New York City, was exemplar of the federal and local government’s abandonment of the cities in the 1970s and 1980s; the Spanish sign reads “FALSAS PROMESAS”, the English sign reads “BROKEN PROMISES”.]]

Urban decay is the sociological process whereby a city, or part of a city, falls into disrepair and decrepitude. Its characteristics are [[depopulation]], [[economic restructuring]], abandoned buildings, high local unemployment, fragmented families, political [[disenfranchisement]], crime, and a desolate, inhospitable city landscape.  White flight contributed to the draining of cities' tax bases when middle-class people left.

In the 1970s and 1980s, urban decay was associated with Western cities, especially in North America and parts of Europe. In that time, major structural changes in global economies, transportation, and government policy created the economic, then social, conditions resulting in urban decay.&lt;ref&gt;''[http://books.google.com/books?id=uf0vS1A-0dkC Urban Sores: On the Interaction Between Segregation, Urban Decay, and Deprived Neighbourhoods]'', by Hans Skifter Andersen. ISBN 0-7546-3305-5. 2003.&lt;/ref&gt; Urban decay contradicts the urban development of most of Europe and North America, in countries beyond, urban decay is manifest in the peripheral [[slum]]s at the outskirts of a metropolis, while the city center and the inner city retain high real estate values and sustain a steadily increasing population.&lt;ref name="crabgrass"&gt;''[http://books.google.com/books?vid=ISBN0195049837 Crabgrass Frontier: The Suburbanization of the United States]'' by Professor Kenneth T Jackson (1987)&lt;/ref&gt;

North American cities suffered white flight to the suburbs and exurb commuter towns, which&lt;ref name="crabgrass"/&gt; started to reverse in the 1990s, when the rich suburbanites returned to cities, [[Gentrification|gentrifying]] the decayed urban neighborhoods. [[Blight (urban)|Blight]] is another characteristic of urban decay. Abandoned properties attract criminals and [[street gang]]s, contributing to crime. Urban decay has no single cause; it results from combinations of inter-related socio-economic conditions – including the city’s [[urban planning]] decisions,  the poverty of the local populace, the construction of neighborhood-excluding [[freeway#Effects and controversy|freeway]] roads and rail road lines,&lt;ref name="power"&gt;''[[The Power Broker]]: Robert Moses and the Fall of New York'', by [[Robert Caro]], p. 522.&lt;blockquote&gt;The construction of the [[Gowanus Parkway]], laying a concrete slab on top of lively, bustling Third Avenue, buried the avenue in shadow, and when the parkway was completed, the avenue was cast forever into darkness and gloom, and its bustle and life were forever gone.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; depopulation by suburbanization of peripheral lands, real estate neighborhood redlining,&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=TWo8OFJpFtAC How East New York Became a Ghetto] by Walter Thabit. ISBN 0-8147-8267-1. Page 42.&lt;/ref&gt; immigration restrictions,&lt;ref name="comeback"&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?vid=ISBN0813339529 Comeback Cities: A Blueprint for Urban Neighborhood Revival] By Paul S. Grogan, Tony Proscio. ISBN 0-8133-3952-9. Published 2002. pp. 139–145."The 1965 law brought an end to the lengthy and destructive – at least for cities – period of tightly restricted immigration a spell born of the nationalism and [[xenophobia]] of the 1920s", p. 140&lt;/ref&gt; and [[racial discrimination]].

====Government-aided white flight====
New municipalities were established beyond the abandoned city’s jurisdiction to avoid the [[legacy costs]] of maintaining city infrastructures; instead new governments spent taxes to establish suburban infrastructures. The federal government contributed to white flight and the early decay of non-white city neighborhoods by withholding maintenance capital mortgages, thus making it difficult for the communities to either retain or attract middle-class residents.&lt;ref name="wilson"&gt;''[[When Work Disappears]]: The World of the New Urban Poor'', by William Julius Wilson (1996) ISBN 0-679-72417-6&lt;/ref&gt;

The new suburban communities limited the emigration of poor and non-white residents from the city by restrictive [[zoning]], thus few lower-middle-class people could afford a house in the suburbs. Many all-white suburbs were eventually annexed to the cities their residents had left. For instance, [[Milwaukee|Milwaukee, Wisconsin]], partially annexed [[Political subdivisions of Wisconsin|towns]] such as [[Granville, Wisconsin]]; the (then) Mayor, [[Frank P. Zeidler]] complained about the socially destructive "Iron Ring" of new municipalities incorporated in the post–World War II decade.&lt;ref&gt;''[http://www.jsonline.com/story/index.aspx?id=459264 Mayor served 'the public welfare': Longtime city icon known for integrity, energy, principles]'', by Alan J. Borsuk. “Journal Sentinel”, July 8, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; Analogously, semi-rural communities, such as [[Oak Creek, Wisconsin|Oak Creek]], [[South Milwaukee, Wisconsin|South Milwaukee]], and [[Franklin, Milwaukee County, Wisconsin|Franklin]], formally incorporated as discrete entities to escape urban annexation. Wisconsin state law had allowed Milwaukee’s annexation of such rural and suburban regions that did not qualify for discrete incorporation per the legal incorporation standards.&lt;ref&gt;Joel Rast, "Governing the Regimeless City: The Frank Zeidler Administration in Milwaukee, 1948–1960", ''Urban Affairs Review'', Vol. 42, No. 1, 81–112 (2006)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Donald J. Curran, "Infra-Metropolitan Competition", ''Land Economics'', Vol. 40, No. 1 (Feb. 1964), pp. 94–99&lt;/ref&gt;

====Desegregation: public schools and student busing====
{{Main|Desegregation busing}}
In some areas, the post–World War II racial desegregation of the public schools catalyzed white flight. In 1954, the US Supreme Court ordered the ''de jure'' termination of the “separate, but equal” legal racism established with the ''[[Plessy v. Ferguson]]'' (1896) case in the nineteenth century. It declared that segregation of public schools was unconstitutional.  Many southern jurisdictions mounted [[Massive resistance]] to the policy.  In some cases, white parents withdrew their children from public schools and established private religious schools instead.

In 1971, in the case of ''[[Swann v. Charlotte-Mecklenburg Board of Education]]'' (1971), the Supreme Court ordered the [[desegregation busing in the United States|desegregation busing]] of poor black students to suburban white schools, and suburban white students to the city to try to integrate student populations. In the case of ''[[Milliken v. Bradley]]'' (1974), the dissenting [[Justice William Douglas]] observed that “the inner core of Detroit is now rather solidly black; and the blacks, we know, in many instances are likely to be poorer. . . .” Likewise, in 1977, the Federal decision in ''Penick v. The Columbus Board of Education'' (1977) accelerated white flight from Columbus, Ohio. Although the racial desegregation of schools affected only public school districts, the most vehement opponents of racial desegregation have sometimes been whites whose children attended private schools.&lt;!-- Where? When? This covers more than 20 years and specifics are important. --&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Jacobson, Cardell K., “Desegregation Rulings and Public Attitude Changes: White Resistance or Resignation?”, ''[[American Journal of Sociology]]'', v.84 n.3, pp. 698–705.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2007/09/09/BAIFS1GE4.DTL C.W. Nevius: Racism alive and well in S.F. schools – here's proof]&lt;/ref&gt;

A secondary, non-geographic consequence of school desegregation and busing was "cultural" white flight: withdrawing white children from the mixed-race public school system and sending them to private schools unaffected by US federal integration laws. In 1970, when the [[United States District Court for the Central District of California]] ordered the [[Pasadena Unified School District]] desegregated, the white-student proportion (54%) of the schools approximately reflected the school district’s proportional white populace (53%). Once the federally ordered school desegregation began, whites who could afford private schools withdrew their children from the racially diverse [[Pasadena, California|Pasadena]] public school system. By 2004, Pasadena had 63 private schools educating some 33% of schoolchildren, while white students made up only 16% of the public school populace. The Pasadena Unified School District superintendent characterized public schools as “like the bogey-man” to whites. He implemented policies to attract white parents to the racially diverse Pasadena public school district.&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20080414024327/http://www.penfamilies.org/www/pen/Files/LA+Daily+Journal+Article+on+Pasadena+School+Reform.doc John Ryan, "Tackling Local Resistance to Public Schools"], Pen Families&lt;/ref&gt; In the event, white flight rapidly altered the racial composition of public school systems. For instance, upon desegregation in 1957 in [[Baltimore|Baltimore, Maryland]], the Clifton Park Junior High School had 2,023 white students and 34 black students; ten years later, it had twelve white students and 2,037 black students. In northwest Baltimore, Garrison Junior High School’s student body declined from 2,504 whites and twelve blacks to 297 whites and 1,263 blacks in that period.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bcps.k12.md.us/About/History/From_the_Oldorder1.asp Reasons and Results 1957–1997&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; At the same time, the city's working class population declined because of the loss of industrial jobs as heavy industry restructured.

===Specific examples===
In 1967, the [[12th Street Riot]] of Detroit, Michigan, contributed to white flight. The tremendous loss of jobs in the auto industry since then also contributed to depopulation of the city and region. Most of its suburbs, including [[Livonia, Michigan|Livonia]], and [[Warren, Michigan|Warren]], are predominantly white.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2001/08/13/national/main306205.shtml | work=CBS News | title=Most Racially Uniform Cities | date=August 13, 2001}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1980, the [[Mariel Boatlift]] brought 150,000 Cubans to Miami, Florida, in what was the largest such short-term migration in US civilian history{{Citation needed|date=January 2010}}. Miami had become a center of exiled Cuban refugees since the rise of [[Fidel Castro]] who ironically were part of the white flight from Cuba, since the majority of migrants leaving Cuba were white Cubans. After the new refugees arrived, many of the middle-class non-Hispanic whites in the community left the city. In 1960, non-Hispanic whites made up about 90% of Miami's population. Suburbanization trends and highway development affected Miami, too, as did an increase in the Haitian immigrant population. By 1990, non-Hispanic whites comprised only about 10% of the city's residents. In addition to having numerous residents of Cuban ancestry, the international city has attracted many new immigrants from Central and South America.
===Recent studies===

====Multi-ethnic responses to changes in neighborhoods====
With the increasing diversity of United States society, researchers are looking at multi-ethnic responses to changes in composition of residential neighborhoods to understand differences among groups. A 2008 study identified differences among some Latino nationalities, and between certain Latino ethnic groups and African Americans. It found that non-whites may leave neighborhoods as the proportion of other groups increases. In some cases, Latinos and blacks left neighborhoods with increasing white populations, both because of a fear of discrimination and sometimes because of rise in housing costs (the last according to a cited study). Cubans, especially foreign-born Cubans, have a tendency to leave neighborhoods with increasing black populations. Puerto Ricans have a lesser tendency to take such action. Neighborhood ethnic composition has little effect on African Americans' decisions to move. European Americans show a higher likelihood of moving when there are many neighbors from other minority groups, whether they were African American or Latino.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite doi|10.1007/s11113-008-9101-x}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Checkerboard and tipping models ====
In studies in the 1980s and 1990s, blacks said they were willing to live in neighborhoods with 50/50 ethnic composition. Whites were also willing to live in integrated neighborhoods but preferred proportions of more whites. Despite this willingness to live in integrated neighborhoods, most people live in segregated neighborhoods, which have continued to form.&lt;ref name=Zhang&gt;{{cite doi|10.1111/j.1467-9787.2010.00671.x}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1969, the Nobel Prize-winning economist [[Thomas Schelling]] published his "Models of Segregation", a paper in which he demonstrated through a "checkerboard model" and mathematical analysis, that even when every agent prefers to live in a mixed-race neighborhood, almost complete segregation of neighborhoods emerges as individual decisions accumulate. In his "tipping model", he demonstrated the effects which emerge when people have varying levels of perception as to acceptable levels for other ethnic groups in the neighborhood. The model shows that members of an ethnic group do not move out of a neighborhood as long as the proportion of other ethnic groups is relatively low, but if a critical level of other ethnicities is exceeded, the original residents may make rapid decisions and take action to leave. This tipping point is viewed as simply the end-result of [[domino effect]] originating when the threshold of the majority ethnicity members with the highest sensitivity to sameness is exceeded. If these people leave and are either not replaced or replaced by other ethnicities, then this in turn raises the level of mixing of neighbours, exceeding the departure threshold for additional people. Domino and tipping models were suggested to be explanatory factors for white flight in the 1960s US. Schelling also noted that in different societies, people have residential preferences, for factors other than ethnicity, such as age, gender, income levels.&lt;ref&gt;Schelling, T. (1969). "Models of segregation", ''The American Economic Review,'' 1969, 59(2), 488–493.&lt;/ref&gt; In 2010 Junfu Zhang found support for both the checkerboard model of residential segregation as the only stable spatial arrangement (arrangement not subject to tipping effects), and for tipping effects,  showing how these lead to integrated residential areas being irreversibly tipped into complete segregation.&lt;ref name=Zhang/&gt;

==Africa==

===South Africa===
About 800,000 out of an earlier total population of 5.2 million whites have left South Africa since 1995, according to a report from 2009. The country has suffered a high rate of violent crime, a primary stated reason for emigration. Other causes include attacks against white farmers, concern about being excluded by [[affirmative action]] programs, rolling blackouts in electrical supplies, and worries about corruption and autocratic political tendencies among new leaders. Since many of those who leave are highly educated, there are shortages of skilled personnel in the government, teaching and other professional areas. Some observers fear the long-term consequences, as South Africa's labor policies make it difficult to attract skilled immigrants. The migration of whites in South Africa was facilitated by the creation of immigration routes into European countries for people with European ancestry. For instance UK government introduced the notion of patriality to ensure white people of British ancestry from Africa could settle in the UK while restricting the extension of the same privilege to colonial citizens. In the global economy, some professionals and highly skilled people have been attracted to work in the US and European nations. In addition, many South African Indians have also emigrated to countries like Australia, New Zealand, Canada, United States, and United Kingdom to seek greater economic opportunities and safer living conditions. They also cite high crime and black economic empowerment (BEE) policies as reasons for leaving. Many South African Indians are highly educated and skilled. Some dispute these high numbers and argue that not all have emigrated permanently, and that a significant number return.&lt;ref name= "Economist 12295535"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.newsweek.com/2009/02/13/fleeing-from-south-africa.html |author=Scott Johnson|title=Fleeing From South Africa|work=Newsweek|date=February 14, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Europe==

===Denmark===
A study of school choice in [[Copenhagen]] found that an immigrant proportion of below 35% in the local schools did not affect parental choice of schools. If the percentage of immigrant children rose above this level, native Danes are far more likely to choose other schools. Immigrants who speak Danish at home (a measure of assimilation) also opt out. Other immigrants, likely more recent ones, stay with local schools.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite doi|10.1093/esr/jcp024}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Ireland===
A 2007 government report stated that immigration in [[Dublin]] has caused "dramatic" white flight from elementary schools in a studied area. 27% of residents were foreign born immigrants. The report stated that Dublin was risking creating immigrant-dominated ''[[banlieues]]'', on the outskirts of a city, similar to such areas in France. The immigrants in the area included Eastern Europeans, such as Polish; Asians and Africans, mainly political [[refugees]] from Nigeria. New immigrants resided in rental housing in the study area because they lacked the savings and credit history to buy into what was characterized as an expensive market.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20071024022221/http://www.iht.com/articles/ap/2007/10/19/europe/EU-GEN-Ireland-White-Flight.php|url=http://www.iht.com/articles/ap/2007/10/19/europe/EU-GEN-Ireland-White-Flight.php |title=Report finds evidence of 'white flight' from immigrants in northwest Dublin|work=International Herald Tribune|date=October 19, 2007|archivedate=October 27, 2007|accessdate=Retrieved April 20, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; On the other hand, as part of the new prosperity that Ireland was achieving for a while in the 1990s, many Irish returned from overseas.

===Netherlands===
The nation was shocked in 2004 by the assassination of the artist [[Theo van Gogh (film director)|Theo van Gogh]] by a Dutch Muslim. Many ethnic Dutch were emigrating from the Netherlands to nations such as Australia, New Zealand and Canada{{Citation needed|date=August 2012}}. Rising ethnic violence, crime committed by and against immigrants, and fear that social order is breaking down, are cited as motives, as well as over-crowding and traffic jams. An all-party report by the government concluded in 2004 that the immigration policy had been a failure. There were concerns about "sink schools" and [[ethnic]] [[ghettos]]. Half the prison population was composed of immigrant youths. More than 40% of immigrants received some form of government assistance. Immigrants said they were widely discriminated against.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/education/3348562/Dutch-desert-their-changing-country.html |author=Ambrose Evans-Pritchard |title=Dutch desert their changing country|work=The Telegraph|date=December 11, 2004|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2005/02/27/international/europe/27dutch.html |author=Marslie Simons |title=More Dutch Plan to Emigrate as Muslim Influx Tips Scales|work=New York Times|date=February 27, 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2010 between 40 and 45% of the population of [[Amsterdam]], [[Rotterdam]] and [[The Hague]] was of non-Dutch origin.

===Norway===
White flight has been seen in some neighborhoods as immigration of non-Scandinavians (in numerical order, starting with the largest group; migrants from Poland, Pakistan, Iraq, Somalia, Vietnam, Iran, Turkey, Bosnia and Herzegovina, Russia, Sri Lanka, The Philippines, UK, Kosovo, Thailand, Afghanistan, and Lithuania) has increased since the 1970s. By June 2009, more than 40% of [[Oslo]] schools had a majority of people of immigrant backgrounds, with some schools having a 97% immigrant share.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.frie-ytringer.com/2009/06/09/40-prosent-av-osloskolene-har-innvandrerflertall/ "40 prosent av Osloskolene har innvandrerflertall"]&lt;/ref&gt; Schools in Oslo are increasingly divided by ethnicity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dagsavisen.no/innenriks/article418561.ece|title=Rømmer til hvitere skoler|work=Dagsavisen|date=June 2, 2009|last=Bredeveien|first=Jo Moen}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aftenposten.no/nyheter/iriks/article3228559.ece|title=Foreldre flytter barna til "hvitere" skoler|work=Aftenposten|date=August 22, 2009|last=Lundgaard|first=Hilde}}&lt;/ref&gt; For instance, in the Oslo borough of [[Groruddalen]], which currently has a population of c. 165,000, the ethnic Norwegian population decreased by 1,500 in 2008, while the immigrant population increased by 1,600.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aftenposten.no/nyheter/oslo/article3424942.ece|title=Ola og Kari flytter fra innvandrerne|work=Aftenposten|date=December 15, 2009|last=Slettholm|first=Andreas}}&lt;/ref&gt; In thirteen years, a total of 18,000 ethnic Norwegians have moved from the borough.&lt;ref name=nett15110&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nettavisen.no/nyheter/article2802878.ece|title=Noen barn er brune |work=Nettavisen|date=January 15, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In January 2010, on the news programme ''[[Dagsrevyen]]'' on the public [[Norwegian Broadcasting Corporation]], a feature story said, "Oslo has become a [[racially]] divided city. In some city districts the [[racial segregation]] starts already in kindergarten". Reporters during the feature said, "in the last years the brown schools have become browner, and the white schools whiter", an outspokenness which caused some minor controversy.&lt;ref name=nett15110/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.dagbladet.no/2010/01/14/nyheter/dagsrevyen/nrk/tv/tv_og_medier/9914499/|title=Et stort flertall av barna er brune|work=Dagbladet|first1=Gunnar|last1=Ringheim|first2=Line|last2=Fransson|first3=Lars Molteberg|last3=Glomnes|date=January 14, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Sweden===
After [[World War II]], immigration into Sweden occurred in three phases. The first was a direct result of the war, with refugees from [[concentration camp]]s and surrounding countries in Scandinavia and Northern Europe. The second, prior to 1970, involved immigrant workers, mainly from Finland, Italy, Greece, and Yugoslavia. In the most recent phase, from the 1970s onwards, non-European refugees have immigrated there, joined later by their relatives, from countries in the Middle East, Africa and Latin America.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Andersson|2007|p=64}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Individuals in Sweden are identified by codes which include details of ethnicity and location. In exceptional circumstances, these are made available to researchers in political and social sciences; they have mapped patterns of segregation and congregation of incoming population groups over time in different parts of Sweden.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Andersson|2007|p=68}}&lt;/ref&gt; Data is analysed in terms of majority and minority population groups. If a majority group is reluctant to accept a minority influx, they may leave the district, avoid the district or use tactics to keep the minority out. The minority group in turn can react by either dispersing or congregating, avoiding certain districts in turn. In Sweden recent detailed analysis of data from the 1990s onwards indicates that the concentration of immigrants in certain city districts, such as [[Husby, Stockholm|Husby]] in Stockholm and [[Rosengård]] in [[Malmö]], is in part due to flight, but primarily due to avoidance.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Andersson|2007|pp=74–75}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite doi|10.1080/00420980500406736}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===United Kingdom===
{{Off-topic|date=April 2011}}
For centuries, London was the destination for refugees and immigrants from Europe. Although all the immigrants were European, neighborhoods showed [[ethnic succession]] over time, as older residents moved out (in some cases, ethnic British) and new immigrants moved in – often both movements at once. Although the majority of London's population was still ethnic English and British. This was similar to what is now described as "white flight" following arrival of non-white ethnicities. For instance, in the 17th and 18th century, the East End had many [[French Huguenot]] (Protestant) refugees, who managed the silk-weaving industry. At its peak in the mid-18th century, 12,000 silk weavers were employed in the [[Spitalfields]] area.&lt;ref name="Porter"&gt;Roy Porter, ''London: A Social History'', Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press, 1994, pp. 132, 140&lt;/ref&gt;  In 1742 they built a church, ''La Neuve Eglise''. Later it became used as a Methodist chapel to serve mostly poor East Enders from around England. Although in the 17th century, the East End also had [[Sephardi Jews|Sephardic Jewish]] immigrants, it was not until the concentration of 19th-century [[Ashkenazi Jews|Ashkenazi Jewish]] immigration from eastern Europe, that the Methodist chapel was adapted as the ''Machzikei HaDath'', or Spitalfields Great Synagogue; it was consecrated in 1898. By the 1870s, thousands of unskilled Jewish immigrants were garment workers in [[sweatshops]].&lt;ref&gt;Porter (1994), pp. 301–302&lt;/ref&gt; [[British Jews|Descendants of Jewish immigrants]] became educated, took better jobs, and gradually moved on to other parts of London and its suburbs, and new immigrants settled in the area. Since 1976, the synagogue was converted to the ''Jamme Masjid'' mosque, which serves the local ethnic Bangladeshi population, who are Muslim.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.portcities.org.uk/london/server/show/conMediaFile.6057/The-Great-London-Mosque-on-Brick-Lane.html "The Great London Mosque on Brick Lane"], Port Cities: London. Retrieved April 17, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 2001 Census, the London boroughs of [[London Borough of Newham|Newham]] and [[London Borough of Brent|Brent]] were the first areas to have non-white majorities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/shared/spl/hi/uk/03/census_2001/html/ethnicity.stm |work=BBC News|title=Census 2001: Ethnicity}}&lt;/ref&gt; All major British cities have white-majority populations.&lt;ref&gt;'Minority White Cities?', chapter 7 in [https://www.policypress.org.uk/catalog/product_info.php?products_id=1370] Finney and Simpson (2009).&lt;/ref&gt; Although not all were of ethnic British origin (English, Scots and Welsh). It has also been forecast that places like Birmingham and Leicester will have non-white majority populations in time.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/uknews/1377501/Midlands-communities-will-be-mostly-non-white-in-15-years.html | location=London | work=The Daily Telegraph | first1=Maurice | last1=Weaver | first2=Philip | last2=Johnston | title=Midlands communities will be mostly non-white 'in 15 years' | date=December 8, 2000}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A 2005 report stated that white migration within the UK is mainly from areas of high ethnic minority population to those with predominantly white populations. White British families have moved out of London as many immigrants have settled in the capital. The report's writers expressed concern about British social cohesion and stated that different ethnic groups were living "parallel lives"; they were concerned that lack of contact between the groups could result in fear more readily exploited by extremists. The London School of Economics in a study found similar results.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Philip Johnston|title=Whites 'leaving cities as migrants move in'|work=The Telegraph|date=February 10, 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A 2006 BBC article states that [[Trevor Phillips]], head of the UK [[Commission for Equalities and Human Rights]], and Mike Poulsen, an Australian academic, have argued that [[White British|White Britons]] and non-white Britons are becoming more ethnically segregated.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/uk/2005/sep/01/race.world | location=London |work=The Guardian | first=David | last=Adam | title=UK Asians isolated in city enclaves | date=September 1, 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; But, researchers [[Ceri Peach]], Danny Dorling and Ludi Simpson have argued that segregation in the UK is either stable or declining.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Dominic Casciani|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/magazine/5304276.stm |title=So who's right over segregation?|work=[[BBC News]] Magazine|date=September 4, 2006|accessdate=September 21, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; Simpson says that the growth of ethnic minorities in Britain is due mostly to natural population growth (births outnumber deaths) rather than immigration. Both white and non-white Britons who can do so economically are equally likely to leave mixed-race inner-city areas. In his opinion, these trends indicate [[counter urbanisation]] rather than white flight.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ccsr.ac.uk/research/mrpd/RaceMigBook.html Simpson, L. ''Myths and counterarguments: a quick reference summary''].&lt;/ref&gt;

==Oceania==

===Australia===
In Sydney, the attraction of Sydney Harbour which stretches through the middle of the city has meant the poorer suburbs that attracted migrants were in the [[Greater Western Sydney]] region, away from the city and the harbour. Those areas popular with European and Asian migrants experienced a degree of white flight, with a concentration of Anglo-Celtic people in certain areas, such as [[Penrith, New South Wales|Penrith]] in far-western Sydney, the [[Sutherland Shire]] and the [[Gosford, New South Wales|Gosford]]–[[Wyong, New South Wales|Wyong]] area of the Central Coast, north of Sydney. These suburbs remain predominantly European-Australian.&lt;ref&gt;Birrell, Bob, and Seol, Byung-Soo. [http://elecpress.monash.edu.au/pnp/free/pnpv6n3/BirrSeol1.htm "Sydney's Ethnic Underclass"], ''People and Place'', vol. 6, no. 3, September 1998.&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the NSW Secondary Principals Council and the [[University of Western Sydney]], public schools in Australia have experienced white flight to private and Catholic schools wherever there is a large presence of [[Australian Aboriginal|Aboriginal]] and Middle Eastern students.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.stuff.co.nz/world/308634/White-flight-from-Aussie-public-schools|title='White flight' from Aussie public schools|work=Sydney Morning Herald|date=March 10, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===New Zealand===
[[File:New Zealand school decile vs roll ethnicity 2011.png|thumb|250px|Percentages of New Zealand school rolls occupied by certain ethnic groups in 2011, broken down by socioeconomic decile. White flight is evident with low-decile schools have a disproprtionately low number of European students and high numbers of Maori and Pacifika students, while the inverse is true for high-decile schools.]]
White flight has been observed in low [[Socio Economic Decile|socioeconomic decile]] schools in New Zealand. Data from the [[Ministry of Education (New Zealand)|Ministry of Education]] found that 60,000 [[Pakeha]]/New Zealand European students attended low-decile schools (situated in the poorest areas) in 2000, and had fallen to half that number in 2010. The same data also found that high-decile schools (which are in the wealthiest areas) had a corresponding increase in NZ European students.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nzherald.co.nz/nz/news/article.cfm?c_id=1&amp;objectid=10813743|title=Claim of 'white flight' from low decile schools|work=The New Zealand Herald|author=Hana Garrett-Walker |date=June 18, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Ministry claimed demographic changes were behind the shifts, but teacher and principal associations have attributed white flight to racial and class stigmas of low-decile schools, which commonly have majority Maori and Pacific Islander rolls.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.radionz.co.nz/news/te-manu-korihi/108575/some-pakeha-parents-stereotyping-maori-pupils-principals|title=Some Pakeha parents stereotyping Maori pupils – principals|publisher=Radio New Zealand|date=June 19, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In one specific case, white flight has significantly affected Sunset Junior High School in a suburb of the city of [[Rotorua]], with the junior high school population of students reduced from 700 to 70 in the early 1980s. All but one of the 70 students are Maori. The area has a concentration of poor, low-skilled people, with struggling families, and many single mothers. Related to the social problems of the families, student educational achievement is low on the standard reading test.&lt;ref name="NZ_Herald_10392647"&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.nzherald.co.nz/warriors-still/news/article.cfm?c_id=1501094&amp;objectid=10392647 |title='White flight' threatens school |author=Collins, Simon |date=July 24, 2006 |work=[[The New Zealand Herald]] |accessdate=September 22, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Auto-segregation]]
*[[Black flight]]
*[[Ethnic succession theory]]
*[[Gentrification]]
*[[Planned shrinkage]]
*[[Political demography]]
*[[Residential segregation]]
*[[Urban decay]]
*[[Xenophobia]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist|2}}

==References==
*{{citation|first=Roger|last=Andersson|title=Ethnic residential segregation and integration processes in Sweden|url=http://skylla.wz-berlin.de/pdf/2007/iv07-602.pdf#page=63|publisher=[[Social Science Research Center Berlin]]|year=2007|series=Residential Segregation and the Integration of Immigrants: Britain, the Netherlands and Sweden|editor-first=Karen|editor-last= Schönwälder|pages=61–90}}
*{{cite book |author=Avila, Eric |title=Popular Culture in the Age of White Flight: Fear and Fantasy in Suburban Los Angeles |publisher=University of California Press |location=Berkeley |year=2005 |isbn=978-0-520-24811-3 |oclc= }}
* Finney, Nissa and Simpson, Ludi (2009) [https://www.policypress.org.uk/catalog/product_info.php?products_id=1370 'Sleepwalking to segregation'? Challenging myths about race and migration], Bristol: Policy Press.
* Gamm, Gerald (1999).  ''Urban Exodus: Why the Jews Left Boston and the Catholics Stayed''  Harvard University Press.
* Kruse, Kevin M. (2005), ''White Flight: Atlanta and the Making of Modern Conservatism.''  Princeton:  Princeton University Press.
* Lupton, R. and Power, A. (2004) 'Minority Ethnic Groups in Britain'. CASE-Brookings Census Brief No.2, London: LSE.
*Pietila, Antero.  (2010)  ''Not in My Neighborhood: How Bigotry Shaped a Great American City'' (Chicago: Ivan R. Dee).
* Schneider, Jack (2008), ''[http://juh.sagepub.com/cgi/content/abstract/34/6/995 Escape from Los Angeles: White Flight from Los Angeles and Its Schools, 1960–1980]''
* Seligman, Amanda I. (2005), ''Block by Block: Neighborhoods and Public Policy on Chicago's West Side'' Chicago: University of Chicago Press.
*{{cite book |author=Sugrue, Thomas J. |title=[[The Origins of the Urban Crisis]]: Race and Inequality in Postwar Detroit |publisher=Princeton University Press |location=Princeton |year= 2005 |isbn=978-0-691-12186-4 |oclc= }}
*Wiese, Andrew. (2006) [http://southernspaces.org/2006/african-american-suburban-development-atlanta "African American Suburban Development in Atlanta"], ''Southern Spaces''
*Beth Tarasawa, "[http://southernspaces.org/2009/new-patterns-segregation-latino-and-african-american-students-metro-atlanta-high-schools New Patterns of Segregation: Latino and African American Students in Metro Atlanta High Schools]," ''Southern Spaces'', January 19, 2009.
Jo Moen
{{White people}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:White Flight}}
[[Category:Human migration]]
[[Category:Forced migration]]
[[Category:Race and crime]]
[[Category:Urban decay]]
[[Category:Urban decay in the United States]]
[[Category:Urban studies and planning terminology]]

[[cs:Bílý útěk]]
[[fr:White flight]]
[[id:White flight]]
[[ja:ホワイト・フライト]]
[[ru:Бегство белых]]
[[fi:Valkoisten pako]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>