<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20091114202344|325851598" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="313538" pageid="313538" ns="0" title="Nepotism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2009-11-16T10:56:25Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Copyedit|date=March 2009}}
{{Wiktionary|nepotism}}
{{Discrimination sidebar}}
'''Nepotism''' is [[favouritism]] granted to [[relatives]] or friends, without regard to their [[merit]].&lt;ref name="dictionary"&gt;Modern Language Association (MLA):"nepotism." The American Heritage® New Dictionary of Cultural Literacy, Third Edition. Houghton Mifflin Company, 2005. 10 Aug. 2009. [http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/nepotism Dictionary.com].&lt;/ref&gt; The word ''nepotism'' is from the Latin word ''[[wikt:nepos#Latin|nepos]]'' (meaning "[[nephew]]" or "[[grandchild]]").

== Types of nepotism ==
=== Papal ===
{{Main|Cardinal-nephew}}   
Nepotism gained its name after the church practice in the [[Middle Ages]], when some [[Catholicism|Catholic]] [[pope]]s and [[bishop]]s, who had taken vows of [[chastity]], and therefore usually had no children of their own, gave their nephews such positions of preference as were often accorded by fathers to son.&lt;ref name="Article Nepotism"&gt;{{cite web
  |last=
  |first=
  |authorlink=
  |coauthors=
  |title=Article Nepotism 
  |work=New Catholic Dictionary
  |publisher=
  |date=
  |url=http://catholic-forum.com/saints/ncd05726.htm
  |doi=
  |accessdate=2007-07-12 }}
&lt;/ref&gt; 

Several popes elevated nephews and other relatives to the [[Cardinal (Catholicism)|cardinalate]]. Often, such appointments were a means of continuing a papal "dynasty". 

For instance, [[Pope Callixtus III]], head of the [[Borgia]] family, made two of his nephews Cardinals; one of them, Rodrigo, later used his position as a Cardinal as a stepping stone to the papacy, becoming [[Pope Alexander VI]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  |last=
  |first=
  |authorlink=
  |coauthors=
  |title=Article Pope Alexander VI
  |work=New Catholic Dictionary
  |publisher=
  |date=
  |url=http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/01289a.htm
  |doi=
  |accessdate=2007-07-12 }}
&lt;/ref&gt; Coincidentally, Alexander elevated Alessandro Farnese, his mistress's brother, to the cardinalate; Farnese would later go on to become [[Pope Paul III]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  |last=
  |first=
  |authorlink=
  |coauthors=
  |title=Article Pope Paul III
  |work=Catholic Encyclopedia
  |publisher=
  |date=
  |url=http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/11579a.htm
  |doi=
  |accessdate=2007-07-12 }}
&lt;/ref&gt; 

Paul also engaged in nepotism, appointing, for instance, two nephews, aged fourteen and sixteen, as cardinals. The practice was finally ended when [[Pope Innocent XII]] issued the [[Papal bull|bull]] ''[[Romanum decet Pontificem]]'', in 1692.&lt;ref name="Article Nepotism"/&gt; The papal bull prohibited popes in all times from bestowing estates, offices, or revenues on any relative, with the exception that one qualified relative (at most) could be made a Cardinal.

=== Political ===
Nepotism is a common accusation in politics when the relative of a powerful figure ascends to similar power seemingly without appropriate qualifications. The [[British English]] expression "[[Bob's your uncle]]" is thought to have originated when [[Robert Arthur Talbot Gascoyne-Cecil, 3rd Marquess of Salisbury]], promoted his nephew, [[Arthur Balfour]], to the esteemed post of [[Chief Secretary for Ireland]] in what was widely seen as an act of nepotism.{{Or|date=August 2009}}

==== Examples ====
{{Refimprove|date=October 2009}}
===== [[Australia]] =====
[[Anna Bligh]], who won the 2008 Queensland State election has been accused of nepotism by giving her husband Greg Withers a bureaucratic position.&lt;ref&gt;Des Houghton, June 28, 2008. [http://www.news.com.au/couriermail/story/0,23739,23931778-5012449,00.html "Anna Bligh's Labor in trouble in the polls"]. ''Couriermail'', Retrieved August 17, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

===== [[Azerbaijan]] =====
President [[Heydar Aliyev]] appointed his son [[Ilham Aliyev]] Prime Minister during the last months of his presidency in 2003. Prior to the election the elder Aliyev dropped out and put his son up as presidential candidate instead. Aliyev was elected to the presidency and his father died just two months later, having successfully sealed the transfer of power to his son. {{Citation needed|date=August 2009}}
===== [[Bangladesh]] =====
Former PM [[Khaleda Zia]] is accused of favouring her son [[Tareq Zia]] in political arena{{Citation needed|date=October 2009}}.

===== [[Fiji]] =====
In 2009, [[Voreqe Bainimarama]] appointed [[Francis Kean]], his brother-in-law, at the head of the naval forces (though Francis Kean had served a jail sentence){{Citation needed|date=August 2009}}.
===== [[France]] =====
* In [[2008]] [[Jean Sarkozy]], second son of President [[Nicolas Sarkozy]], stood for election in a [[Cantons of France|canton]] in the Parisian suburb of [[Neuilly-sur-Seine]], in a district of which his father used to be mayor. The original candidate (a loyal member of Sarkozy's UMP Party) stepped aside to allow Jean Sarkozy to run. This resulted in French commentators announcing "behold, the rise of the [[Dauphin of France|dauphin]]"{{Citation needed|date=October 2009}}.
* In [[October]] [[2009]] [[Jean Sarkozy]] is about to become [http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Epad EPAD]'s director despite lacking any real diploma yet and having no professional experience &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.reuters.com/article/worldNews/idUSTRE59F1AH20091016 Poll shows majority against job for Sarkozy's son]&lt;/ref&gt;.
* In [[September]] [[2009]] [[Pierre Sarkozy]], first son of President [[Nicolas Sarkozy]], asked [http://fr.wikipedia.org/SCPP SCPP] for a financial help (of around 10000€) towards an 80000€ artistic project. Pierre Sarkozy not being an SCPP member, financing was automatically rejected. Following the refusal, he went to the [[Élysée]] which lead to an Élysée counsel contacting the SCPP, and SCPP president [[Marc Guez]] assuring the issue would soon be favorably resolved&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.electronlibre.info/+Nepotisme-et-Sarkozysme-acte-II,02317+ Népotisme et Sarkozysme, acte II (màj)]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rue89.com/2009/11/07/apres-jean-un-coup-de-pouce-de-lelysee-pour-pierre-sarkozy-125100 Après Jean, un coup de pouce de l'Elysée pour Pierre Sarkozy]&lt;/ref&gt;. According to [http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abeille_Musique Abeille Music] president and SCPP member Yves Riesel, however, this will not happen as SCPP's financial helps have been restricted to members only for months&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.liberation.fr/politiques/0101601841-apres-jean-l-elysee-se-met-au-service-de-pierre-sarkozy Après Jean, l'Elysée se met au service de Pierre Sarkozy]&lt;/ref&gt;.

===== [[Greece]] =====
* Greek Prime Minister [[Kostas Karamanlis]] entered to the Parliament in 1989 after his election in the 1st District of Thessaloniki as a MP of New Democracy, a party founded by his uncle, [[Constantine Karamanlis]]. He has also included Michalis Liapis, his cousin, in two of his cabinets{{Citation needed|date=October 2009}}.
* [[George Papandreou]], Leader of the Official Opposition in Hellenic Parliament, was firstly elected MP in 1981 with PASOK, the party led by his father, Andreas, and has been included in numerous cabinets under either his father or [[Kostas Simitis]].
* [[Dora Bakoyannis]], Greek Foreign Minister, served as Minister for Culture under her father, [[Constantine Mitsotakis]], New Democracy Chairman for eight years. Her brother, Kyriakos, is also a MP.{{Citation needed|date=August 2009}}

===== [[India]] =====
* The [[Nehru-Gandhi Family]] has shown a strong tendency for nepotism, as manifested through ''dynastic politics''.  A recent example is the rise of [[Rahul Gandhi]].
* In the state of [[Tamilnadu]], politician [[Karunanidhi]] has promoted many of his family members in various leadership positions in his party [[DMK]]; his first son [[M. K. Azhagiri]] controls the party in southern areas, his second son [[M.K. Stalin]] is nominated for next party president and Chief ministerial candidate, his daughter [[Kanimozhi]] is Member of Parliament, and his nephew [[Murasoli Maran]] and grand nephew [[Dayanidhi Maran]] were central ministers{{Citation needed|date=October 2009}}.
* In the state of Punjab, the present Chief Minister Parkash Badal has appointed his son Sukhbir Badal as deputy CM, projecting him as a likely future Chief Minister.{{Citation needed|date=August 2009}}
===== [[Maldives]] =====
President Maumoon Abdul Gayyoom has had thirteen of his brothers, brothers-in-law, and classmates as members of his cabinet.{{Citation needed|date=August 2009}}
=====[[Mauritania]]=====
* The President of Mauritania is infamous for appointing his relatives into high positions{{fact}}.

===== [[North Korea]] =====
[[Kim Jong-il]] became [[Chairman of the National Defense Commission of North Korea|Chairman of the National Defense Commission]], [[Supreme Commander of the Korean People's Army]], and [[General Secretary of the Workers' Party of Korea]] (the ruling party since 1948), succeeding his father [[Kim Il-sung]], the founder of the [[Democratic People's Republic of Korea]], [[Kim_Il-sung#Death|who died in 1994]]. In turn, Kim Jong-un, his son is touted to succeed him.{{Citation needed|date=August 2009}}
===== [[Pakistan]] =====
* [[Benazir Bhutto]] was appointed the leader of the [[Pakistan Peoples Party]] without direct election because she was the daughter of former leader [[Zulfiqar Ali Bhutto]]. Upon Benazir's death her son [[Bilawal Bhutto Zardari]] was appointed co-chairman without election despite being only eighteen years old at the time and lacking any knowledge of politics or life in Pakistan. The other chairman of the PPP was Benazir's husband [[Asif Ali Zardari]] who was accused of widespread corruption during his wife's previous terms in office{{Citation needed|date=October 2009}}.
* [[Nawaz Sharif]] the leader of the [[Pakistan Muslim League]] has appointed his brother [[Shahbaz Sharif]] as an unelected vice-preseident of his party. Sharif had also appointed his son's father in law, [[Ishaq Dar]] as the finance minister during his tenure in office. {{Citation needed|date=August 2009}}
===== [[Romania]] =====
[[Elena Basescu]], the daughter of the current president [[Traian Basescu]], was elected president of the youth organization in the political party which was ruled by [[Traian Basescu]] before becoming president of Romania.{{Citation needed|date=August 2009}}
===== [[Sri Lanka]] =====
After winning the Presidential election in [[2005]] [[Mahinda Rajapaksa]] appointed 3 of his brothers to his government: [[Gotabhaya Rajapaksa]], a former army officer, as the secretary of defense{{Citation needed|date=October 2009}}; [[Basil Rajapaksa]] as Senior Adviser to President{{Citation needed|date=October 2009}} and [[Chamal Rajapaksa]] as Cabinet Minister of Ports &amp; Aviation and Irrigation &amp; Water Management{{Citation needed|date=October 2009}}. He also appointed several close friends and associates as presidential advisers{{Citation needed|date=October 2009}}, including [[Sajin Vass Gunawardene]] (CEO of the state owned Mihin Air, though he did not have any qualifications.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/sinhala/news/story/2007/09/070919_basil_mp.shtml BBCSinhala.com&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;). [[Mahinda Rajapaksa]] also made his son a cadet officer even though he did not meet certain requirements{{Citation needed|date=October 2009}}.

===== [[Syria]] =====
[[Bashar al-Assad]] was appointed as [[President of Syria|President]] after his father [[Hafez al-Assad|Hafez]]'s death, despite being too young for the post under the country's constitution as it then stood.{{Citation needed|date=August 2009}}
===== [[Trinidad and Tobago]] =====
Prime Minister Patrick Manning appointed his unelected wife Hazel Manning to the Cabinet for two consecutive terms, first as Minister of Education and currently as Minister of Local Government. {{Citation needed|date=August 2009}}
===== [[United States]] =====
* When [[United States Senator|U.S. Senator]] [[Frank Murkowski]] was elected [[Governor of Alaska]], he appointed his daughter, [[Alaska House of Representatives|State Representative]] [[Lisa Murkowski]], to fill the remaining two years of his seat and was accused by some of nepotism.
* [[John F. Kennedy]] was accused of nepotism for his appointment of his brother [[Robert Kennedy]] as [[Attorney General of the United States]].{{Citation needed|date=August 2009}}

===== [[Vietnam]] =====
After "winning" the first ever democratic election in South Vietnam in 1955, [[Ngo Dinh Diem]] appointed his brother Ngo Dinh Nhu in charge of the private armies and secret police. [[Ngô Đình Cẩn]], his younger brother, was put in charge of the former Imperial City of Huế.{{Citation needed|date=August 2009}}
===== [[Venezuela]] =====
President [[Hugo Chavez]] and [[Cilia Flores]], president of the Venezuela National Assembly, are also known for their influences to get family members in the government. Flores managed to place relatives in as many as nine of sixty permanent positions at the National Assembly- three siblings, two nephews, a cousin, the mother of that cousin, her mother-in-law and an aunt.&lt;ref&gt;http://buscador.eluniversal.com/2008/07/08/pol_ava_cilia-flores-niega-i_08A1777279.shtml&lt;/ref&gt; {{Citation needed|the article does not mention the particular family members only the accusation of general nepotism|date=October 2008}}

===== Remarks =====
At some point, nepotism at high levels of government might serve to create what are in effect monarchies in nominal republics. In Syria, the case of the al-Assads mentioned above is one example. In [[Egypt]], the likely similar succession of [[Gamal Mubarak]] to the [[President of Egypt|Presidency]] upon [[Hosni Mubarak]]'s death is equivalent.{{Or|date=August 2009}}

=== In entertainment ===
Outside of national politics, accusations of "nepotism" are made in instances of ''prima facie'' favouritism to relatives, such as:
* [[Peaches Geldof]]'s role as magazine editor in an [[MTV]] reality show - produced by a company owned by her father [[Bob Geldof]].&lt;ref&gt;
http://www.sundaymirror.co.uk/showbiz/showbiznews/2008/03/16/peaches-geldof-bags-tv-reality-show-as-magazine-editor-98487-20353319/  Peaches Geldof bags TV reality show as magazine editor&lt;/ref&gt; In a sketch of [[The Kevin Bishop Show]], which frequently has less-than-flattering fake perfume adverts for celebrities, Peaches Geldof got one - "Nepotism, the smell of Peaches Geldof". Before this, a mock voice said "I'm a fashion model, a TV presenter, and I'm a journalist as well...did I mention my dad's Bob Geldof?"{{Citation needed|date=October 2009}}
* One-time Guardian contributor Max Gogarty has also been accused of taking advantage of family contacts to achieve success disproportionate to his ability; his father Paul Gogarty is a frequent travel writer for the newspaper.{{Citation needed|date=October 2009}}
* [[Coppola family tree|The Coppola Family]] of Hollywood includes many distinguished filmmakers. The careers of both [[Sofia Coppola]] and [[Nicolas Cage]] are attributed to aid by director [[Francis Ford Coppola]] who cast his daughter Sofia in ''[[The Godfather Part III]]''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hollywood.com/news/EXTRA_Nepotism_in_the_Directors_Chair/312221 EXTRA: Nepotism in the Director's Chair at Hollywood.com&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://spiritof1976.livejournal.com/338603.html Nothing is true, everything is permitted - Coppola nepotism hate&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Nonetheless, both have subsequently established independent careers. Indeed Cage changed his last name in order to avoid such charges.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.imdb.com/name/nm0000115/bio Nicolas Cage - Biography&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Lily Allen]]'s career can be credited to her father [[Keith Allen]]'s connections and also the family name.{{Citation needed|date=November 2009}}

== Social and economic effects ==
{{Section OR|date=August 2009}}
Nepotism and cronyism can have short- and long-term effects on a society, depending on the extent of the takeup and social acceptability of these practices.

Areas in which, it is believed, nepotism has negative societal effects:
* the [[civil service]]
* intergovermental and intragovermental relations (ambassadors, civil-service attached personnel)

==See also==
{{multicol}}
*[[Cronyism]]
*[[Simony]]
*[[Ingroup bias]]
{{multicol-break}}
*[[Ethnic nepotism]]
*[[Professional courtesy]]
*[[List of cardinal-nephews]]
{{multicol-end}}

==References==
{{reflist}}
{{refbegin}}
*''[http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0003-0678(197310)25%3A4%3C493%3AAC%3E2.0.CO%3B2-U American Calendar]'' (Fall 1973) in ''American Quarterly'' 25.4 (Oct. 1973):493-96.
*''[http://dictionary.reference.com/search?q=nepotism Nepotism]'' - Dictionary.com
{{refend}}

== External links ==
{{wikiquote}}
* [http://www.Hollywoodnepotism.net Hollywoodnepotism.net]

[[Category:Corruption]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Ethically disputed political practices]]

[[ar:محسوبية]]
[[bg:Непотизъм]]
[[ca:Nepotisme]]
[[cs:Nepotismus]]
[[da:Nepotisme]]
[[de:Nepotismus]]
[[el:Νεποτισμός]]
[[es:Nepotismo]]
[[eo:Nepotismo]]
[[eu:Nepotismo]]
[[fa:پارتی‌بازی]]
[[fr:Népotisme]]
[[ko:네포티즘]]
[[hr:Nepotizam]]
[[id:Nepotisme]]
[[is:Frændhygli]]
[[it:Nepotismo]]
[[he:נפוטיזם]]
[[ka:ქართული]]
[[hu:Nepotizmus]]
[[ms:Nepotisme]]
[[nl:Nepotisme]]
[[ja:縁故主義]]
[[no:Nepotisme]]
[[pl:Nepotyzm]]
[[pt:Nepotismo]]
[[ru:Непотизм]]
[[simple:Nepotism]]
[[sk:Nepotizmus]]
[[ckb:خزمگەریەتى]]
[[sr:Непотизам]]
[[fi:Nepotismi]]
[[sv:Nepotism]]
[[th:คติเห็นแก่ญาติ]]
[[uk:Непотизм]]
[[zh:裙帶關係]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>