<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20071109142234|170328465" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="313538" pageid="313538" ns="0" title="Nepotism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-11-12T17:13:00Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{wiktionary|nepotism}}
{{Discrimination2}}
'''Nepotism''' is the showing of favoritism toward relatives, based upon that relationship,  rather than on an objective evaluation of ability or suitability.  For instance, offering employment to a relative, despite the fact that there are others who are better qualified and willing to perform the job, would be considered nepotism.  The word ''nepotism'' is from the Latin word 'nepos', meaning "[[nephew]]" or "[[grandchild]]".   

== Papal nepotism ==
{{main|Cardinal-nephew}}   
Nepotism gained its name after the church practice in the [[Middle Ages]], when some [[Catholicism|Catholic]] [[pope]]s and [[bishop]]s — who had taken vows of [[chastity]], and therefore usually had no children of their own — gave their nephews positions of preference such as were often accorded by fathers to sons&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | last =
  | first =
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | title = Article Nepotism 
  | work = New Catholic Dictionary
  | publisher =
  | date =
  | url = http://catholic-forum.com/saints/ncd05726.htm
  | format =
  | doi =
  | accessdate = 2007-07-12 }}
 &lt;/ref&gt;. Several popes are known to have elevated nephews and other relatives to the [[cardinal (Catholicism)|cardinalate]]. Often, such appointments were used as a means of continuing a papal "dynasty". For instance, [[Pope Callixtus III]], head of the [[Borgia]] family, made two of his nephews Cardinals; one of them, Rodrigo, later used his position as a Cardinal as a stepping stone to the papacy, becoming [[Pope Alexander VI]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | last =
  | first =
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | title = Article Pope Alexander VI
  | work = New Catholic Dictionary
  | publisher =
  | date =
  | url = http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/01289a.htm
  | format =
  | doi =
  | accessdate = 2007-07-12 }}
 &lt;/ref&gt;. Coincidentally, Alexander&amp;mdash;one of the most corrupt popes&amp;mdash;elevated Alessandro Farnese, his mistress's brother, to the cardinalate; Farnese would later go on to become [[Pope Paul III]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | last =
  | first =
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | title = Article Pope Paul III
  | work = Catholic Encyclopedia
  | publisher =
  | date =
  | url = http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/11579a.htm
  | format =
  | doi =
  | accessdate = 2007-07-12 }}
 &lt;/ref&gt;. Paul also engaged in nepotism, appointing, for instance, two nephews (aged fourteen and sixteen) Cardinals. The practice was finally ended when [[Pope Innocent XII]] issued a [[Papal bull|bull]] ''[[Romanum decet Pontificem]]'' in 1692&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | last =
  | first =
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | title = Article Nepotism 
  | work = New Catholic Dictionary
  | publisher =
  | date =
  | url = http://catholic-forum.com/saints/ncd05726.htm
  | format =
  | doi =
  | accessdate = 2007-07-12 }}
 &lt;/ref&gt;. The papal bull prohibited popes in all times from bestowing estates, offices, or revenues on any relative, with the exception that one qualified relative (at most) could be made a Cardinal.

== Examples ==
Nepotism is a common accusation in politics when the relative of a powerful figure ascends to similar power seemingly without appropriate qualifications. For example, the popular [[British English]] expression "[[Bob's your uncle]]" is often thought to have originated when [[Robert Arthur Talbot Gascoyne-Cecil, 3rd Marquess of Salisbury]], promoted his nephew, [[Arthur Balfour]], to the esteemed post of [[Chief Secretary for Ireland]] in what was widely seen as an act of nepotism.  More recently, when [[United States Senator|U.S. Senator]] [[Frank Murkowski]] was elected [[Governor of Alaska]], he appointed his daughter, [[Alaska House of Representatives|State Representative]] [[Lisa Murkowski]], to fill the remaining two years of his seat and was accused by some of nepotism. [[John F. Kennedy]] was accused of nepotism for his appointment of his brother [[Robert Kennedy]] as [[Attorney General]], and there have been many allegations that during the [[presidency of George W. Bush]] it became much more widespread&lt;ref&gt;See for example, [http://www.slate.com/id/2089156/][http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/opinion/35502_helen177.shtml][http://www.businessweek.com/magazine/content/04_06/b3869035_mz005.htm] in the [[US]].&lt;/ref&gt;

Many countries in the world have examples of this tilt towards dynastic rule, such as:
* [[Malaysia]]: [[Abdul Razak|Tun Abdul Razak]], the second [[Prime Minister of Malaysia|Prime Minister]], and his son, [[Najib Tun Razak]], the current [[Deputy Prime Minister of Malaysia|Deputy Prime Minister]]; [[Khairy Jamaluddin]] who won his position as Deputy Chief of [[UMNO]] Youth Wing with the influence of his father-in-law, [[Abdullah Ahmad Badawi]], the current Prime Minister. 
* [[Maldives]]: President Maumoon Abdul Gayyoom once had 13 of his brothers, brothers-in-law, and classmates as members of his cabinet. 
* [[Syria]]: [[Bashar al-Assad]] was appointed as [[President of Syria|President]] after his father [[Hafez al-Assad|Hafez]]'s death, despite being too young for the post under the country's constitution as it then stood.
* [[North Korea]]: [[Kim Jong-il]] became [[Chairman of the National Defense Commission of North Korea|Chairman of the National Defense Commission]], [[Supreme Commander of the Korean People's Army]], and [[General Secretary of the Workers' Party of Korea]] (the ruling party since 1948), succeeding his father [[Kim Il-sung]], the founder of the [[Democratic People's Republic of Korea]], [[Kim_Il-sung#Death|who died in 1994]].
* [[Trinidad and Tobago]]: Prime Minister Patrick Manning appointed his unelected wife Hazel Manning to the Cabinet for two consecutive terms, first as Minister of Education and currently as Minister of Local Government.


At some point, nepotism at high levels of government might serve to create what are in effect monarchies in nominal republics. In Syria, the case of the al-Assads mentioned above is one example. In [[Egypt]], the likely similar succession of [[Gamal Mubarak]] to the [[President of Egypt|Presidency]] upon [[Hosni Mubarak]]'s death is equivalent. In [[Iraq]], had there not been an overthrow of the government of [[Saddam Hussein]] with the [[2003 invasion of Iraq|US-led invasion]], it would have been highly likely that his younger son, [[Qusay Hussein]], would have succeeded to the presidency.

In Romania ''nepotism'' is very commonly used as a word describing a 'connection' (relationship) that allows a person to obtain a certain job. 'Nepot' in Romanian means "nephew" or "grandson". During communist rule, nepotism was often the only way of getting a good, well-paid or otherwise advantageous job.

==References==
&lt;references/&gt;
*''[http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0003-0678(197310)25%3A4%3C493%3AAC%3E2.0.CO%3B2-U American Calendar]'' (Fall 1973) in ''American Quarterly'' 25.4 (Oct. 1973):493-96.
*''[http://dictionary.reference.com/search?q=nepotism]'' Nepotism - Dictionary.com

==See also==
*[[Cronyism]]
*[[Simony]]
*[[Ingroup bias]]
*[[Ethnic nepotism]]
*[[List of cardinal-nephews]]

{{wikiquote}}

[[Category:Corruption]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]

[[ar:محسوبية]]
[[bg:Непотизъм]]
[[cs:Nepotismus]]
[[da:Nepotisme]]
[[de:Nepotismus]]
[[el:Νεποτισμός]]
[[es:Nepotismo]]
[[eo:Nepotismo]]
[[fr:Népotisme]]
[[it:Nepotismo]]
[[he:נפוטיזם]]
[[nl:Nepotisme]]
[[ja:縁故主義]]
[[no:Nepotisme]]
[[pl:Nepotyzm]]
[[pt:Nepotismo]]
[[ru:Непотизм]]
[[sk:Nepotizmus]]
[[sr:Непотизам]]
[[fi:Nepotismi]]
[[sv:Nepotism]]
[[zh:裙带关系]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>