<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061030192548|84675294" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="313538" pageid="313538" ns="0" title="Nepotism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-11-08T16:49:36Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{wikiquote}}
'''Nepotism''' means favoring relatives because of their relationship rather than because of their abilities. 

For example, if a manager employed or promoted a relative rather than a more qualified non-relative, that manager would be guilty of nepotism. Some biologists have suggested that a tendency towards nepotism is instinctive, a form of [[kin selection]].

The word ''nepotism'' comes from the Latin word 'nepos', meaning "nephew".  In the [[Middle Ages]], some [[Catholicism|Catholic]] [[pope]]s and [[bishop]]s, who had taken vows of [[chastity]], and therefore usually had no children of their own, gave their nephews positions of preference such as were often accorded by fathers to sons. Several popes are known to have elevated nephews and other relatives to the [[cardinal (Catholicism)|cardinalate]]. Often, such appointments were used as a means of continuing a papal "dynasty". For instance, [[Pope Callixtus III]], of the [[Borgia]] family, made two of his nephews Cardinals; one of them, Rodrigo, later used his position as a Cardinal as a stepping stone to the papacy, becoming [[Pope Alexander VI]]. Coincidentally, Alexander&amp;mdash;one of the most corrupt popes&amp;mdash;elevated Alessandro Farnese, his mistress's brother, to the cardinalate; Farnese would later go on to become [[Pope Paul III]]. Paul also engaged in nepotism, appointing, for instance, two nephews (aged fourteen and sixteen) Cardinals. The practice was finally ended when [[Pope Innocent XII]] issued a [[Papal bull|bull]] in [[1692]]. The papal bull prohibited popes in all times from bestowing estates, offices, or revenues on any relative, with the exception that one qualified relative (at most) could be made a Cardinal.

Nepotism is a common accusation in politics when the relative of a powerful figure ascends to similar power seemingly without appropriate qualifications. For example, when [[United States Senator|U.S. Senator]] [[Frank Murkowski]], was elected [[Governor of Alaska]], he appointed his daughter, [[Alaska House of Representatives|State Representative]] [[Lisa Murkowski]], to fill the remaining two years of his seat and was accused by some of nepotism. (Murkowski won reelection on her own in [[2004]].) [[John F. Kennedy]] was accused of nepotism for his appointment of his brother [[Robert Kennedy]] as [[Attorney General]].

Other US examples include [[Hillary_Rodham_Clinton|Hillary]] and [[Bill_Clinton|Bill]] Clinton, as well as [[George_H._W._Bush|George H.W. Bush]], [[George_W._Bush|George W. Bush]] and [[Jeb_Bush|Jeb Bush]].

Families elsewhere have also dominated politics of their homeland, such as [[Abdul Razak|Tun Abdul Razak]], the second [[Prime Minister of Malaysia]], and his son, [[Najib Tun Razak]], the current [[Deputy Prime Minister of Malaysia]]. Many countries in Asia have this tilt towards dynastic rule. In India, the [[Nehru-Gandhi dynasty]] has been ruling India for most part since Independence while other people in India have always given preference to their kith and kin in various states in India. In the Indian state of [[Bihar]], the former Chief Minister [[Laloo Prasad Yadav]], widely known as one of the most corrupt Indian politicians&lt;ref&gt;http://puggy.symonds.net/pipermail/corruption-issues/2003-January/000241.html&lt;/ref&gt;, elevated his nearly-illiterate wife [[Rabri Devi]] to the post of Chief Minister, after a court ruling sentenced him on a corruption case making him unfit for the post. President of Maldives Maumoon Abdul Gayyoom once had 13 of his brothers, brothers inlaw and his class mates as members of his cabinet.

In Romania ''nepotism'' is very commonly used as a word describing a 'connection' (relationship) that allows a person to obtain a certain job. 'Nepot' in Romanian means "nephew". During communist rule, nepotism was often the only way of getting a good, well-paid job. 

Nepotism has also been known humorously as ''payrola'', after [[payola]].

The popular [[British English]] expression "[[Bob's your uncle]]" is often thought to have originated when [[Robert Arthur Talbot Gascoyne-Cecil, 3rd Marquess of Salisbury]] promoted his nephew, [[Arthur Balfour]], to the esteemed post of [[Chief Secretary for Ireland]] in what was widely seen as an act of nepotism.

== Anti-nepotism laws ==
{{expandsection}}
Most European and North American countries have made nepotism a legal offense through anti-nepotism laws.

==References==
&lt;!-- ----------------------------------------------------------
  See http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Footnotes for a 
  discussion of different citation methods and how to generate 
  footnotes using the &lt;ref&gt;, &lt;/ref&gt; and  &lt;reference /&gt; tags
----------------------------------------------------------- --&gt;
&lt;div class="references-small"&gt;
&lt;references /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
* Francis Fitzgerald. 1972. '''Fire in the Lake: The Vietnamese and the Americans in Vietnam'''. Boston: Back Bay Books. ISBN 0-316-15919-0. pp. 94-97, 126-127.

==See also==
*[[Cronyism]]
*[[Simony]]
*[[Ingroup bias]]
*[[ethnic nepotism]]

[[Category:Corruption]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]

[[cs:Nepotismus]]
[[da:Nepotisme]]
[[de:Nepotismus]]
[[es:Nepotismo]]
[[eo:Nepotismo]]
[[fr:Népotisme]]
[[it:Nepotismo]]
[[he:נפוטיזם]]
[[nl:Nepotisme]]
[[no:Nepotisme]]
[[pl:Nepotyzm]]
[[pt:Nepotismo]]
[[ru:Непотизм]]
[[sk:Nepotizmus]]
[[fi:Nepotismi]]
[[sv:Nepotism]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>