<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20081113231058|251655195" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="313538" pageid="313538" ns="0" title="Nepotism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2008-11-14T10:20:54Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{wiktionary|nepotism}}
{{Discrimination sidebar}}
'''Nepotism''' is the showing of favoritism toward relatives and friends, based upon that relationship,  rather than on an objective evaluation of ability, [[meritocracy]] or suitability.  For instance, offering employment to a relative, despite the fact that there are others who are better qualified and willing to perform the job.  The word ''nepotism'' is from the Latin word 'nepos', meaning "[[nephew]]" or "[[grandchild]]".

== Papal nepotism ==
{{main|Cardinal-nephew}}   
Nepotism gained its name after the church practice in the [[Middle Ages]], when some [[Catholicism|Catholic]] [[pope]]s and [[bishop]]s — who had taken vows of [[chastity]], and therefore usually had no children of their own — gave their nephews positions of preference such as were often accorded by fathers to sons&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  |last=
  |first=
  |authorlink=
  |coauthors=
  |title=Article Nepotism 
  |work=New Catholic Dictionary
  |publisher=
  |date=
  |url=http://catholic-forum.com/saints/ncd05726.htm
  |format=
  |doi=
  |accessdate=2007-07-12 }}
 &lt;/ref&gt;. Several popes are known to have elevated nephews and other relatives to the [[cardinal (Catholicism)|cardinalate]]. Often, such appointments were used as a means of continuing a papal "dynasty". For instance, [[Pope Callixtus III]], head of the [[Borgia]] family, made two of his nephews Cardinals; one of them, Rodrigo, later used his position as a Cardinal as a stepping stone to the papacy, becoming [[Pope Alexander VI]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  |last=
  |first=
  |authorlink=
  |coauthors=
  |title=Article Pope Alexander VI
  |work=New Catholic Dictionary
  |publisher=
  |date=
  |url=http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/01289a.htm
  |format=
  |doi=
  |accessdate=2007-07-12 }}
 &lt;/ref&gt;. Coincidentally, Alexander elevated Alessandro Farnese, his mistress's brother, to the cardinalate; Farnese would later go on to become [[Pope Paul III]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  |last=
  |first=
  |authorlink=
  |coauthors=
  |title=Article Pope Paul III
  |work=Catholic Encyclopedia
  |publisher=
  |date=
  |url=http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/11579a.htm
  |format=
  |doi=
  |accessdate=2007-07-12 }}
 &lt;/ref&gt;. Paul also engaged in nepotism, appointing, for instance, two nephews (aged fourteen and sixteen) Cardinals. The practice was finally ended when [[Pope Innocent XII]] issued a [[Papal bull|bull]] ''[[Romanum decet Pontificem]]'' in 1692&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  |last=
  |first=
  |authorlink=
  |coauthors=
  |title=Article Nepotism 
  |work=New Catholic Dictionary
  |publisher=
  |date=
  |url=http://catholic-forum.com/saints/ncd05726.htm
  |format=
  |doi=
  |accessdate=2007-07-12 }}
 &lt;/ref&gt;. The papal bull prohibited popes in all times from bestowing estates, offices, or revenues on any relative, with the exception that one qualified relative (at most) could be made a Cardinal.

== Examples ==
Nepotism is a common accusation in politics when the relative of a powerful figure ascends to similar power seemingly without appropriate qualifications. For example, the popular [[British English]] expression "[[Bob's your uncle]]" is often thought to have originated when [[Robert Arthur Talbot Gascoyne-Cecil, 3rd Marquess of Salisbury]], promoted his nephew, [[Arthur Balfour]], to the esteemed post of [[Chief Secretary for Ireland]] in what was widely seen as an act of nepotism.  More recently, when [[United States Senator|U.S. Senator]] [[Frank Murkowski]] was elected [[Governor of Alaska]], he appointed his daughter, [[Alaska House of Representatives|State Representative]] [[Lisa Murkowski]], to fill the remaining two years of his seat and was accused by some of nepotism. [[John F. Kennedy]] was accused of nepotism for his appointment of his brother [[Robert Kennedy]] as [[Attorney General]].

Many countries in the world have examples of this tilt towards dynastic rule, such as:
* [[Azerbaijan]]: President [[Heydar Aliyev]], who was suffering from failing health, appointed his son [[Ilham Aliyev]] Prime Minister during the last months of his presidency in 2003. Then just prior to the election the elder Aliyev dropped out and put his son up as presidential candidate instead. Aliyev was elected to the presidency and his father died just two months later, having successfully sealed the transfer of power to his son. 
* [[Trinidad and Tobago]]: Prime Minister Patrick Manning appointed his unelected wife Hazel Manning to the Cabinet for two consecutive terms, first as Minister of Education and currently as Minister of Local Government. 
* [[India]]: The [[Nehru-Gandhi Family]], which has exercised enormous influence over Indian politics for the past century, has shown a strong tendency for nepotism, as manifested most starkly through "[[dynastic politics]]".  The most obvious recent example is the rise of [[Rahul Gandhi]], widely described as a "certain future Prime Minister", despite his lifelong lack of success in academic and professional life, including his failure to graduate from [[Harvard College]], his admission to Harvard also having been seen as a "non-merit exception".  
* [[Cuba]]: Former presidente Fidel Castro appointed his brother Raul as minister of defense during the 60s and during the 80s as his successor to the presidency which materialized in 2007. Fidel´s son "Fidelito" was in charge of the nuclear program in Cuba, which was eventually a failure and involved a loss of 800 million dollars. Fidel´s close family members have been living in big farms or "fincas" disguised as "agricultural research centers" or "army facilities", but in practice they are mansions for Fidel's relatives. {{Fact|date=September 2008}}
* [[Malaysia]]: [[Abdul Razak|Tun Abdul Razak]], the second [[Prime Minister of Malaysia|Prime Minister]], and his son, [[Najib Tun Razak]], the current [[Deputy Prime Minister of Malaysia|Deputy Prime Minister]]; [[Khairy Jamaluddin]] who won his position as Deputy Chief of [[UMNO]] Youth Wing with the influence of his father-in-law, [[Abdullah Ahmad Badawi]], the current Prime Minister. 
* [[Maldives]]: President Maumoon Abdul Gayyoom once had 13 of his brothers, brothers-in-law, and classmates as members of his cabinet.
* [[Singapore]]: [[Lee Hsien Loong]], the eldest son of [[Singapore]]'s first Prime Minister [[Lee Kuan Yew]], is the current [[Prime Minister of Singapore]]. Lee Hsien Loong was also the youngest Brigadier General in the [[Singapore Armed Forces]]. He joined the forces in 1971 and by 1983, he was the Chief of Staff of the Armed Forces. His wife (Lee Kuan Yew's daughter-in law), [[Ho Ching]], is the [[Chief Executive Officer]] of [[Temasek Holdings]], a government-controlled fund that owns assets over US$100 billion, including a large proportion of the largest Singaporean companies. These include [[SingTel]], the largest South-East Asian telecom company, which was headed by [[Lee Hsien Yang]] (Lee Kuan Yew's younger son) from 1995 to 2006. Lee Hsien Yang became CEO of Singtel at age 38, after a successful career in the Singapore Armed Forces which saw him reach the rank of Brigadier General as well.    
* [[Syria]]: [[Bashar al-Assad]] was appointed as [[President of Syria|President]] after his father [[Hafez al-Assad|Hafez]]'s death, despite being too young for the post under the country's constitution as it then stood.
* [[North Korea]]: [[Kim Jong-il]] became [[Chairman of the National Defense Commission of North Korea|Chairman of the National Defense Commission]], [[Supreme Commander of the Korean People's Army]], and [[General Secretary of the Workers' Party of Korea]] (the ruling party since 1948), succeeding his father [[Kim Il-sung]], the founder of the [[Democratic People's Republic of Korea]], [[Kim_Il-sung#Death|who died in 1994]].
* [[France]]: in 2008 [[Jean Sarkozy]], son of the French President [[Nicolas Sarkozy]], stood for election in a [[Cantons of France|canton]] in the affluent Parisian suburb of [[Neuilly-sur-Seine|Neuilly]], the same district in which his father was [[Mayor]]. The original candidate was a loyal member of Sakozy's UMP Party named [[Arnaud Teulle]]. He stepped aside to allow Jean Sarkozy to run. This resulted in French commentators announcing "behold, the rise of the [[dauphin]]".&lt;ref&gt;http://www.thefirstpost.co.uk/people,710,sarkos-farm-show-slanging-match,18503  Sarko loses cool with ‘dumb ass’ voter &lt;/ref&gt; 
* [[Sri Lanka]] after winning the Presidential election in 2005 Mahinda Rajapakse appointed younger brother Gotabhaya Rajapakse a former army officer as the secretary of defense, another younger brother Basil Rajapakse  as a minister, elder brother Chamal Rajapakse also as a minister he further went on to appoint several close friends and associates as presidential advisers including Sajin Vass Gunawardene who was also appointed CEO of the state owned Mihin Air, though he did not have any qualifications. &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/sinhala/news/story/2007/09/070919_basil_mp.shtml BBCSinhala.com&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[United States]] after becoming [[Secretary of the Treasury]], [[Henry Paulson]] appointed his protégé and former [[Goldman Sachs]] colleague [[Neel Kashkari]] to run the Office of Financial Stability in October 2008.
* [[Vietnam]] after "winning" the first ever democratic election in South Vietnam in 1955, [[Ngo Dinh Diem]] appointed his brother Ngo Dinh Nhu in charge of the private armies and secret police. [[Ngô Đình Cẩn]], his younger brother, was put in charge of the former Imperial City of Huế.
* [[Venezuela]]  President [[Hugo Chavez]]  and  [[Cilia Flores]], president of the Venezuela National Assembly, are also known for their influences to get family members in the government. Flores managed to place relatives in as many as nine of sixty permanent positions at the National Assembly- three siblings, two nephews, a cousin, the mother of that cousin, her mother-in-law and an aunt. &lt;ref&gt;http://buscador.eluniversal.com/2008/07/08/pol_ava_cilia-flores-niega-i_08A1777279.shtml&lt;/ref&gt; {{Fact|the article does not mention the particular family members only the accusation of general nepotism|date=October 2008}}
 

At some point, nepotism at high levels of government might serve to create what are in effect monarchies in nominal republics. In Syria, the case of the al-Assads mentioned above is one example. In [[Egypt]], the likely similar succession of [[Gamal Mubarak]] to the [[President of Egypt|Presidency]] upon [[Hosni Mubarak]]'s death is equivalent. In [[Iraq]], had there not been an overthrow of the government of [[Saddam Hussein]] with the [[2003 invasion of Iraq|US-led invasion]], it would have been highly likely that his younger son, [[Qusay Hussein]], would have succeeded to the presidency.

Outside of national politics, accusations of "nepotism" are made in instances of ''prima facie'' favouritism to relatives, such as:
* [[Peaches Geldof]]'s role as magazine editor in an [[MTV]] reality show - produced by a company owned by her father [[Bob Geldof]].&lt;ref&gt;
http://www.sundaymirror.co.uk/showbiz/showbiznews/2008/03/16/peaches-geldof-bags-tv-reality-show-as-magazine-editor-98487-20353319/  Peaches Geldof bags TV reality show as magazine editor &lt;/ref&gt; One-time Guardian contributor Max Gogarty has also been accused of taking advantage of family contacts to achieve success disproportionate to his ability; his father Paul Gogarty is a frequent travel writer for the newspaper.
* [[Coppola family tree|The Coppola Family]] of Hollywood includes many distinguished filmmakers. The careers of both [[Sofia Coppola]] and [[Nicolas Cage]] are attributed to aid by director [[Francis Ford Coppola]] who cast his daughter Sofia in [[The Godfather Part III]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hollywood.com/news/EXTRA_Nepotism_in_the_Directors_Chair/312221 EXTRA: Nepotism in the Director's Chair at Hollywood.com&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt;[http://spiritof1976.livejournal.com/338603.html Nothing is true, everything is permitted - Coppola nepotism hate&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Nonetheless, both have subsequently established independent careers. Indeed Cage changed his last name in order to avoid such charges.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.imdb.com/name/nm0000115/bio Nicolas Cage - Biography&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

* [[Cecelia Ahern]] had her first novel [[PS, I Love You]] published just days after finished college, despite her poor quality of writing and mediocre performance in college. Many Irish attribute this to her fathers role as the then [[Taoiseach]] of Ireland.

==See also==
{{multicol}}
*[[Cronyism]]
*[[Simony]]
*[[Ingroup bias]]
{{multicol-break}}
*[[Ethnic nepotism]]
*[[List of cardinal-nephews]]
{{multicol-end}}

==References==
{{reflist}}
{{refbegin}}
*''[http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0003-0678(197310)25%3A4%3C493%3AAC%3E2.0.CO%3B2-U American Calendar]'' (Fall 1973) in ''American Quarterly'' 25.4 (Oct. 1973):493-96.
*''[http://dictionary.reference.com/search?q=nepotism Nepotism]'' - Dictionary.com
{{refend}}

== External links ==
{{wikiquote}}


[[Category:Corruption]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]

[[ar:محسوبية]]
[[bg:Непотизъм]]
[[ca:Nepotisme]]
[[cs:Nepotismus]]
[[da:Nepotisme]]
[[de:Nepotismus]]
[[el:Νεποτισμός]]
[[es:Nepotismo]]
[[eo:Nepotismo]]
[[fa:پارتی‌بازی]]
[[fr:Népotisme]]
[[id:Nepotisme]]
[[it:Nepotismo]]
[[he:נפוטיזם]]
[[hu:Nepotizmus]]
[[nl:Nepotisme]]
[[ja:縁故主義]]
[[no:Nepotisme]]
[[pl:Nepotyzm]]
[[pt:Nepotismo]]
[[ru:Непотизм]]
[[sk:Nepotizmus]]
[[sr:Непотизам]]
[[fi:Nepotismi]]
[[sv:Nepotism]]
[[zh:裙帶關係]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>