<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20051103132203|27252511" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="313538" pageid="313538" ns="0" title="Nepotism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-11-03T14:30:53Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Nepotism''' means favoring relatives or personal friends because of their relationship rather than because of their abilities. The word is generally used derogatorily.

For example, if a manager hired or promoted a relative rather than a more qualified non-relative, that manager would be guilty of nepotism. Some biologists have suggested that a tendency towards nepotism is instinctual, a form of [[kin selection]].

The word ''nepotism'' comes from the Latin word ''nepos'', meaning "nephew".  In the [[Middle Ages]], some [[Catholicism|Catholic]] [[pope]]s and [[bishop]]s, who had taken vows of chastity, raised their illegitimate sons as "nephews" and gave them preferences. Several popes are known to have elevated nephews and other relatives to the [[cardinal (Catholicism)|cardinalate]]. Often, such appointments were used as a means of continuing a papal "dynasty". For instance, [[Pope Callixtus III]], of the [[Borgia]] family, made two of his nephews Cardinals; one of them, Rodrigo, later used his position as a Cardinal as a stepping stone to the papacy, becoming [[Pope Alexander VI]]. Coincidentally, Alexander&amp;mdash;one of the most corrupt popes&amp;mdash;elevated Alessandro Farnese, his mistress's brother, to the cardinalate; Farnese would later go on to become [[Pope Paul III]]. Paul also engaged in nepotism, appointing, for instance, two nephews (aged fourteen and sixteen) Cardinals. The practice was finally ended when [[Pope Innocent XII]] issued a [[Papal bull|bull]] in [[1692]]. The papal bull prohibited popes in all times from bestowing estates, offices, or revenues on any relative, with the exception that one qualified relative (at most) could be made a Cardinal.

Nepotism is a common accusation in politics when the relative of a powerful figure ascends to similar power seemingly without appropriate qualifications. For example, in [[America]], politically powerful families such as the [[Kennedy political family|Kennedy family]] and [[Bush family]] in American politics are sometimes accused of nepotism by critics. Recently, [[United States Senator|U.S. Senator]] [[Frank Murkowski]], when elected [[Governor of Alaska]], appointed his daughter [[Alaska House of Representatives|Representative]] [[Lisa Murkowski]] to fill the remaining two years of his seat and was accused of nepotism. (Murkowski won reelection on her own in [[2004]].) Families elsewhere have also dominated politics of their homeland, such as [[Abdul Razak|Tun Abdul Razak]], second [[Prime Minister of Malaysia]] and his son, [[Najib Tun Razak]], current [[Deputy Prime Minister of Malaysia]], or Minister Mentor [[Lee Kuan Yew]] (first [[Prime Minister of Singapore]]) and his son, [[Lee Hsien Loong]], who recently succeeded [[Goh Chok Tong]] as [[Prime Minister of Singapore]]. Many countries in Asia have this tilt towards relatives' rule. In India, the [[Nehru-Gandhi dynasty]] has been ruling India for most part since Independence while other people in India have always given preference to their kith and kin in various states in India.

In the [[U.K.]], the popular expression "And Bob's your uncle" originated when [[Robert Gascoyne-Cecil, 3rd Marquess of Salisbury|Robert Cecil, Marquess of Salisbury]], the [[Prime Minister]], appointed his nephew, [[Arthur Balfour]], to a prestigious position. The phrase was originally a sarcastic jibe at nepotism, but today simply means "no problem."   

In [[China]], nepotism is seen in a positive light and is seen as a legitimate reason to get hired. In fact, some citizens of the [[People's Republic of China]] (PRC) sued the government of the PRC because of the [[Great Leap Forward]]-forced migrations, claiming among other things that this separation from family impacted the possibilities of getting hired.

The current record for nepotism and [[cronyism]] amongst leaders of states is held by President [[Maumoon Abdul Gayoom]] of the [[Maldives]], who at the last count had at least eleven family members, in-laws and cronies in his cabinet, plus numerous close relatives and friends in the highest government posts.

Nepotism has also been known humorously as ''payrola'', after [[payola]].

==References==
* Francis Fitzgerald. 1972. '''Fire in the Lake: The Vietnamese and the Americans in Vietnam'''. Boston: Back Bay Books. ISBN 0316159190. pp. 94-97, 126-127.

==See also==
*[[Cronyism]]

[[Category:Corruption]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]

[[cs:Nepotismus]]
[[de:Nepotismus]]
[[eo:Nepotismo]]
[[fr:Népotisme]]
[[it:Nepotismo]]
[[nl:Nepotisme]]
[[no:Nepotisme]]
[[pl:Nepotyzm]]
[[pt:Nepotismo]]
[[fi:Nepotismi]]
[[ru:Непотизм]]
[[sk:Nepotizmus]]
[[sv:Svågerpolitik]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>