<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20231111072317|1184574326" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="990353" pageid="990353" ns="0" title="Polyculturalism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2023-11-11T07:27:01Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|Ideological approach}}
{{Distinguish|Multiculturalism}}
{{Discrimination sidebar|Related}}
'''Polyculturalism''' is an ideological approach to the consequences of intercultural engagements within a geographical area which emphasises similarities between, and the enduring interconnectedness of, groups which self-identify as distinct, thus blurring the boundaries which may be perceived by members of those groups.&lt;ref name="Rosenthal&amp;Levy2010"&gt;{{cite journal|doi=10.1111/j.1751-2409.2010.01022.x|title=The Colorblind, Multicultural, and Polycultural Ideological Approaches to Improving Intergroup Attitudes and Relations|journal=Social Issues and Policy Review|volume=4|pages=215–246|year=2010|last1=Rosenthal|first1=Lisa|last2=Levy|first2=Sheri R}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The concept of polyculturalism was first proposed by [[Robin Kelley]] and [[Vijay Prashad]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://theconversation.com/cultures-fuse-and-connect-so-we-should-embrace-polyculturalism-78876|title=Cultures fuse and connect, so we should embrace polyculturalism|last=Haslam|first=Nick}}&lt;/ref&gt; It differs from [[multiculturalism]] which instead emphasises the separateness of the identities of self-identifying cultural groups with an aim of preserving and celebrating their differences in spite of interactions between them. Supporters of polyculturalism oppose multiculturalism, arguing that the latter's emphasis on difference and separateness is divisive&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://hikevipadan.blogspot.com//%7B%7Bfull%7D%7D|title=Polyculturalism}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="sbs.com.au"&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.sbs.com.au/topics/life/culture/article/2017/06/07/if-multiculturalism-isnt-working-why-not-embrace-polyculturalism%7B%7Bfull%7D%7D|title=Latest News &amp; Opinion on Culture &amp; Social Affairs – SBS Life}}&lt;/ref&gt; and harmful to social cohesion.&lt;ref name="JP&amp;MA2003"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Podur|first1=Justin|last2=Albert|first2=Michael|date=15 July 2003|title=Revolutionizing Culture Part One|url=https://www.zmag.org/znet/viewArticle/10125|journal=Podur ZMag|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080611094904/https://www.zmag.org/znet/viewArticle/10125|archive-date=11 June 2008|access-date=17 Aug 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Polyculturalism was the subject of the 2001 book ''Everybody Was Kung Fu Fighting: Afro-Asian Connections and the Myth of Cultural Purity'' by [[Vijay Prashad]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.semcoop.com/detail/0807050105|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20040823095427/http://www.semcoop.com/detail/0807050105|url-status=dead|archive-date=23 August 2004|title=Everybody Was Kung Fu Fighting — Afro-Asian Connections and the Myth of Cultural Purity — Vijay Prashad|date=23 August 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Comparison of cultural ideologies==

{{More citations needed section|date=August 2018}}
{{Expand section|date=August 2018}}

Like advocates of [[multiculturalism]], proponents of polyculturalism encourage individuals to learn about different cultures, especially those they may come into contact with in their own areas.&lt;ref name="JK" /&gt; However whereas multiculturalism advocates for toleration&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.semcoop.com/detail/0807050105%7B%7Bfull%7D%7D|title=Wayback Machine|date=23 August 2004}}{{dead link|date=May 2020|bot=medic}}{{cbignore|bot=medic}}&lt;/ref&gt; between members of distinctly different cultures groups, polyculturalism is less rigid and acknowledges that individuals shape their own identities and may choose to change&lt;ref name="JP&amp;MA2003" /&gt; so as to express their culture in a different way to their own ancestors, either by adding elements of other cultures to it or by eliminating aspects of it.&lt;ref name="JK" /&gt;

Polyculturalism views the concept of race as a [[Social constructionism|social construct]] with no scientific basis,&lt;ref name="JK"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Korber |first1=John |title=Polyculturalism |url=http://members.aol.com/Jakajk/Oneworld.html |journal=One World One People |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20081014230838/http://members.aol.com/Jakajk/Oneworld.html |archive-date=14 October 2008 |access-date=17 Aug 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; however it recognises the concept of ethnicity,&lt;ref name="AG"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Gibbons |first1=Andrea |title=Vijay Prashad: Polyculturalism and Kung Fu |date=27 September 2016 |url=http://writingcities.com/2016/09/27/vijay-prashad-polyculturalism-kung-fu/ }}&lt;/ref&gt; considering ethno-nationalism a barrier which must be transcended in the pursuit of a dynamic community culture.

Critics of [[multiculturalism]] argue that it entrenches [[identity politics]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1037/a0026490 |pmid=22250894 |title=The relation between polyculturalism and intergroup attitudes among racially and ethnically diverse adults |journal=Cultural Diversity and Ethnic Minority Psychology |volume=18 |issue=1 |pages=1–16 |year=2012 |last1=Rosenthal |first1=Lisa |last2=Levy |first2=Sheri R }}&lt;/ref&gt; while polyculturalism aims to forge a common new identity&lt;ref name="sbs.com.au"/&gt;

Polyculturalism acknowledges that cultures are dynamic, interactive and impure while [[multiculturalism]] treats them as static, isolated and complete.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Haslam |first1=Nick |title=Cultures fuse and connect, so we should embrace polyculturalism |url=https://theconversation.com/cultures-fuse-and-connect-so-we-should-embrace-polyculturalism-78876 |website=The Conversation |access-date=25 August 2018 |language=en |date=6 June 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Examples of polycultural states ==

=== Revolutionary France=== 
The different successive [[polity|polities]] over the last two centuries in France has tried various policies in intercultural relations, creating much research material for Citizenship Studies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.migrationpolicy.org/article/french-government-revives-assimilation-policy|title=French Government Revives Assimilation Policy|date=1 October 2003|website=Migrationpolicy.org|access-date=27 April 2020|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150130222428/http://www.migrationpolicy.org/article/french-government-revives-assimilation-policy|archive-date=30 January 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The French Revolution was ground-breaking in its de-emphasis of religious and other cultural distinctions.  On the 27th August 1789, the National Constituent Assembly issued the [[Declaration of the Rights of Man and of the Citizen]]. On the 27th September 1791, the National Constituent Assembly voted to give France’s Jewish population equal rights under the law. That a long-scapegoated minority were to be recognised simply as citizens regardless of their religion was unprecedented in Modern Europe.&lt;ref name="''Haaretz''|2012"&gt;{{cite news |last1=Green |first1=David |title=This Day in Jewish History / Liberté and ÉGalité for France's Jews |url=https://www.haaretz.com/jewish/this-day-egalite-for-france-s-jews-1.5168453 |access-date=27 April 2020 |work=Haaretz |date=27 September 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Debates about citizenship, equality, and representative politics among intellectuals defined [[the Age of Enlightenment]], and played a role in the shaping of political thinking in early America and France on the eve of the Revolution in 1789.&lt;ref&gt;John G.A. Pocock, ''The Machiavellian Moment: Florentine Political Thought and the Atlantic Republican Tradition'' (1975); Bernard Bailyn, ''The Ideological Origins of the American Revolution''. Harvard University Press, 1967; Gordon S. Wood, ''The Radicalism of the American Revolution: How a Revolution Transformed a Monarchical Society into a Democratic One Unlike Any That Had Ever Existed'', (1992); Gordon S. Wood, ''The Creation of the American Republic 1776–1787'', (1969); Lance Banning, ''The Jeffersonian Persuasion: Evolution of a Party Ideology'', (1978); Drew R. McCoy, ''The Elusive Republic: Political Economy in Jeffersonian America'',(1980); Joyce Appleby, ''Capitalism and a New Social Order: The Republican Vision of the 1790s'', 1984; Joyce Appleby, ed., "Republicanism in the History and Historiography of the United States," special issue of ''American Quarterly'', Vol. 37, No. 4, (1985); Joyce Appleby, Liberalism and Republicanism in the Historical Imagination, (1992); Isaac Kramnick, ''Republicanism and Bourgeois Radicalism: Political Ideology in Late Eighteenth-Century England and America'', (1990); Robert E. Shalhope, "Toward a Republican Synthesis: The Emergence of an Understanding of Republicanism in American Historiography," ''William and Mary Quarterly'', 29 (Jan. 1972), 49–80; Robert E. Shalhope, "Republicanism and Early American Historiography," ''William and Mary Quarterly'', 39 (Apr. 1982), 334–356.&lt;/ref&gt;  Radical components of the Republican movement in France coalesced around the [[Jacobin Club]] in early 1790. One of their objectives was: 
To work for the establishment and strengthening of the constitution in accordance with the spirit of the preamble (that is, of respect for legally constituted authority and the Declaration of the Rights of Man and of the Citizen).&lt;ref&gt;The preceding sentences incorporate text from a publication now in the [[public domain]]: [[Walter Alison Phillips|Phillips, Walter Alison]] (1911). "Jacobins, The". In Chisholm, Hugh (ed.). ''[[Encyclopædia Britannica]]''. 15 (11th ed.). Cambridge University Press. pp. 117–119.&lt;/ref&gt;

The political views of the Jacobin Movement were rooted in Jean-Jacques Rousseau's notion of the [[social contract]].&lt;ref name=Schama1989&gt;{{cite book|last=Schama|first=Simon|title=[[Citizens: A Chronicle of the French Revolution]]|date=1989|publisher= Random House|page=475|isbn=0679726101}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The promotion and inculcation of civic values and the sense of nationhood became consolidated in France.&lt;ref name=Bosher1988&gt;{{cite book|last=Bosher|first=John F.|title=The French Revolution|date=1988|publisher=W. W. Norton|pages=191–208|isbn=9780393025880}}&lt;/ref&gt; A common identity for the peoples within France’s natural boundaries of the Alps, Jura mountains, Pyrenees, the river Rhine and the Atlantic coast was successfully cultivated and propagated. France’s regional identities were presented as parts of a wider whole in an effort to create common bonds across a much larger territorial area.

=== Socialist Yugoslavia=== 
In the new socialist countries that arose in the 20th century religious and other cultural distinctions were played down in an effort to promote a new shared common citizenship. The capacity to satisfactorily facilitate cultural autonomy in poly-ethnic societies without reinforcing divisions and thereby weaken the state had exorcised socialist intellectuals from as far back as [[Otto Bauer]] in his 1907 book “The Nationalities Question and Social Democracy”.

[[Edvard Kardelj]], the constitutional architect of [[Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia]], had set out to delicately de-escalate the often fractious '[[national question]]' in the Balkans. The [[1946 Yugoslav Constitution]] was heavily influenced by the [[1936 Constitution of the Soviet Union]], another poly-ethnic socialist state. Kardelj pointed out: “For us the model was the Soviet Constitution, since the Soviet federation is the most positive example of the solution of relations between peoples in the history of Mankind.”&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Hondius |first1=F.W. |title=The Yugoslav Community of Nations |date=1968 |publisher=Mouton |location=The Hague-Paris |isbn=3111188302 |page=137 |edition=1st |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=NTuOAAAAMAAJ |access-date=27 April 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The development of a Yugoslav socialist consciousness was further clarified in the [[1953 Yugoslav constitutional amendments|1953 Constitutional Law]]. The law referred to “all power in the FPRY belongs to the working people”. The emphasis on class was an obvious effort to supersede individual ethnic and religious differences. The constitutional changes were explained by the gathering development of new “unified Yugoslav community”.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Štiks |first1=Igor |title="Brothers Re-United! Federal Citizenship in Socialist Yugoslavia." Nations and Citizens in Yugoslavia and the Post-Yugoslav States: One Hundred Years of Citizenship |date=2015 |publisher=Bloomsbury Academic |location=London |isbn=978-1-4742-2152-8 |page=58 |url=http://library.oapen.org/bitstream/id/5686943a-aff2-4c78-84a8-1a7b294471e6/642972.pdf |access-date=27 April 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the practise of [[socialist self-management]] the establishment of a powerful body like the Council of Producers ({{lang-sh|Vijeće proizvođača}}) instead of a Council of Nationalities appeared to confirm the [[postnationalism|post-nationalist]] atmosphere the populations of Yugoslavia had entered.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Lampe |first1=John |title=Yugoslavia as History: Twice There Was a Country |date=2000 |publisher=Cambridge University Press |location=Cambridge |isbn=0-521-773571 |page=261 |edition=2nd |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=AZ1x7gvwx_8C |access-date=27 April 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The developing moves from a Yugoslav citizenship to a Yugoslav ethnicity was greatly aided by the mutual comprehensibility of many of the ethnic groups in the region. Even after Yugoslavia was dismantled there is much agreement about this shared linguistic heritage as can be seen in the [[Declaration on the Common Language]].{{citation needed|date=April 2023}}

== See also ==
{{Portal|Politics|Society}}
*[[Civic engagement]]
*[[Classical republicanism]]
*[[Consociationalism]]
*[[New Soviet man]]
*[[Soviet people]] 
*[[Social engineering (political science)]]
*[[Yugoslavs]]
*[[Czechoslovaks]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{Culture}}
{{Discrimination}}
{{Ethnicity}}

[[Category:Ethnicity]]
[[Category:Cultural geography]]
[[Category:Politics and race]]
[[Category:Sociology of culture]]
[[Category:Social theories]]
[[Category:Civil rights and liberties]]
[[Category:Citizenship]]
[[Category:Government and personhood]]
[[Category:National identity]]
[[Category:Political concepts]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>