<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20160731110024|732351011" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="48844349" pageid="48844349" ns="0" title="Discrimination against autistic people"><revisions><rev timestamp="2016-08-16T11:48:55Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Multiple issues|
{{refimprove|date=December 2015}}
{{original research|date=December 2015}}
{{primary sources|date=December 2015}}}}
{{Discrimination sidebar|Social}}
Although contemporary recognition of [[autism]] as a neurological state has only emerged in the 20th century, it is probable that autistic people have been subjected to persecution prior to its recognition by psychology, but were labelled as being, for example, "[[witchcraft|witches]]" or [[lunatic]]s.

==Modern examples==
It has been estimated that 63 percent of children in American schools who are bullied by other children, suffered from autistic spectrum disorders.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.iidc.indiana.edu/pages/Bullying-and-Students-on-the-Autism-Spectrum|title=Bullying and Students on the Autism Spectrum|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Children with autism are far more likely to be targeted for physical and/or sexual abuse than other children.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://nationalautismassociation.org/resources/autism-safety-facts/|title=Autism &amp; Safety Facts|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

This treatment continues into adulthood – one third of autistic people in the [[United Kingdom]] have reported being discriminated against in the workplace, and 81 percent said that they had either been bullied, experienced unfairness or a lack of support at work.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.learningdisabilitytoday.co.uk/third_of_adults_with_autism_experience_workplace_discrimination_4751.aspx|title=Third of adults with autism experience workplace discrimination|work=Learning Disability Today}}&lt;/ref&gt;

People with autism are as much as 28 times more likely to commit suicide than the general population,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/aspergers-diary/201303/new-research-autism-and-suicide|title=New Research on Autism and Suicide|work=Psychology Today}}&lt;/ref&gt; a rate that is arguably even higher than the rate for war veterans and rape survivors.

In contemporary [[Sub-Saharan Africa]], autistic children are commonly [[Witchcraft accusations against children in Africa|accused]] of [[witchcraft]] because of their eccentric behavior, and are often subject to torture and even death.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.icare4autism.org/news/2010/07/children-with-autism-branded-as-witches/|title=Children with Autism Branded as 'Witches' - ICare4Autism|work=ICare4Autism}}&lt;/ref&gt;

It's likely that many of the disabled children killed in [[Action T4]] had autism. Though the Nazis did not specifically target children with a diagnosis of autism, they did kill many children with various developmental disabilities, which were poorly understood in the 1930s and 1940s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cnn.com/2015/04/16/opinions/perry-kennedy-autism/|title=RFK Jr.'s strange remarks on autism - CNN.com|author=David M. Perry|date=16 April 2015|work=CNN}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Sociological and cultural aspects of autism]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>