<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20210708143827|1032611571" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="48844349" pageid="48844349" ns="0" title="Discrimination against autistic people"><revisions><rev timestamp="2021-09-28T00:38:20Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|none}}{{Discrimination sidebar|Social}}
'''Discrimination against autistic people''' is the [[discrimination]] and [[persecution]] that [[autism|autistic]] people have been subjected to. This is because they are seen as different and sometimes inferior.

==Prevalence==
Research published in 2013 reported the results of a survey taken of a national sample of American parents of [[autism spectrum disorder]] (ASD) children conducted by the [[Kennedy Krieger Institute]]. The study found that 38 percent of the Autistic children experienced [[bullying]] over a one-month period, and 28% were frequently bullied. Of those bullied, 69% experienced emotional trauma, 14% feared for their safety, and 8% suffered physical injury.&lt;ref name="pmid23275052"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Zablotsky B, Bradshaw CP, Anderson C, Law PA | title = The association between bullying and the psychological functioning of children with autism spectrum disorders | journal = Journal of Developmental and Behavioral Pediatrics | volume = 34 | issue = 1 | pages = 1–8 | date = January 2013 | pmid = 23275052 | doi = 10.1097/DBP.0b013e31827a7c3a | s2cid = 11295800 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Research published in 2019 used data from more than 8,000 children in the [[University of London]]'s [[Millennium Cohort Study]], which tracks the lives of about 19,000 people born in the [[United Kingdom]] starting in 2000. Out of the children selected, 231 have autism. The study from the ''Journal of Autism and Developmental Disorders'' found that these Autistic children were more likely to engage in "two-way sibling bullying", meaning being both a victim and perpetrator of bullying.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| vauthors = Krans B | date=2019-07-25|title=Kids with Autism at Increased Risk for Bullying|url=https://www.healthline.com/health-news/children-with-autism-are-at-increased-risk-for-bullying-even-from-siblings|url-status=live|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=2021-02-01|website=[[Healthline]]|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Toseeb U, McChesney G, Oldfield J, Wolke D | title = Sibling Bullying in Middle Childhood is Associated with Psychosocial Difficulties in Early Adolescence: The Case of Individuals with Autism Spectrum Disorder | journal = Journal of Autism and Developmental Disorders | volume = 50 | issue = 5 | pages = 1457–1469 | date = May 2020 | pmid = 31332675 | pmc = 7211196 | doi = 10.1007/s10803-019-04116-8 }}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Further research published in 2017, a meta-analysis of three studies, demonstrated that "first impressions of individuals with ASD made from thin slices of real-world social behavior by typically-developing observers are not only far less favorable across a range of trait judgments compared to controls, but also are associated with reduced intentions to pursue social interaction."&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; The meta-analysis continues, "These patterns are remarkably robust, occur within seconds, do not change with increased exposure, and persist across both child and adult age groups."&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; This may be why autistic people have "smaller social networks and fewer friendships, difficulty securing and retaining employment, high rates of loneliness, and an overall reduced quality of life."&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Sasson |first1=Noah J. |last2=Faso |first2=Daniel J. |last3=Nugent |first3=Jack |last4=Lovell |first4=Sarah |last5=Kennedy |first5=Daniel P. |last6=Grossman |first6=Ruth B. |title=Neurotypical Peers are Less Willing to Interact with Those with Autism based on Thin Slice Judgments |journal=Scientific Reports |date=1 February 2017 |volume=7 |page=40700 |doi=10.1038/srep40700 |pmid=28145411 |pmc=5286449 |bibcode=2017NatSR...740700S |issn=2045-2322|doi-access=free }}&lt;/ref&gt; Smaller social networks, fewer friendships, and loneliness correlate with severe health outcomes. According to a paper published in the ''[[Journal of Health and Social Behavior]]'', "Health risks associated with social isolation have been compared in magnitude to the well-known dangers of smoking cigarettes and obesity."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=CORNWELL |first1=ERIN YORK |last2=WAITE |first2=LINDA J. |title=Social Disconnectedness, Perceived Isolation, and Health among Older Adults |journal=Journal of Health and Social Behavior |date=2009 |volume=50 |issue=1 |pages=31–48 |doi=10.1177/002214650905000103 |pmid=19413133 |issn=0022-1465|pmc=2756979 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, according to the [[United Kingdom|UK]] [[Office for National Statistics]], the unemployment rate of Autistic people may reach 85%, the highest rate among all disabled groups studied.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Putz |first1=Catherine |last2=Sparkes |first2=Indiana |last3=Foubert |first3=Josephine |title=Outcomes for disabled people in the UK - Office for National Statistics |website=www.ons.gov.uk |date=18 February 2021 |url=https://www.ons.gov.uk/peoplepopulationandcommunity/healthandsocialcare/disability/articles/outcomesfordisabledpeopleintheuk/2020 |access-date=15 April 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt; These findings suggest that discrimination against Autistic people may cause social isolation, which cause worse health outcomes and lower employment rates for Autistic people.

In the [[United States]], people with disabilities are victims of violent crime three times as often as people without disabilities. The [[Bureau of Justice Statistics]] does not report separately on autistic victims, but it does note that the victimization rate is especially high among those whose disabilities are cognitive. A small-sample study of Americans and Canadians found that adults with autism face a greater risk of [[Sexual abuse|sexual victimization]] than their peers. Autistic respondents were more than twice as likely to say they had been the victim of [[rape]] and over three times as likely to report unwanted sexual contact.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| vauthors = Pitney Jr JJ |title=The politics of autism : navigating the contested spectrum|isbn=978-1-4422-4960-8|location=Lanham|oclc=907022313|year=2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2018, a large scale study found that autistic girls were almost three times more likely to be a victim of sexual abuse.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Ohlsson Gotby|first1=Vide|last2=Lichtenstein|first2=Paul|last3=Långström|first3=Niklas|last4=Pettersson|first4=Erik|date=September 2018|title=Childhood neurodevelopmental disorders and risk of coercive sexual victimization in childhood and adolescence - a population-based prospective twin study|url=https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/29570782/|journal=Journal of Child Psychology and Psychiatry, and Allied Disciplines|volume=59|issue=9|pages=957–965|doi=10.1111/jcpp.12884|issn=1469-7610|pmid=29570782|s2cid=4238219}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Examples ==

In 2011, a 10-year-old autistic boy from [[Pakistan]] was granted [[political asylum]] in the United States on the grounds that his autism-related behavior, which included [[Compulsive behavior|compulsions]] and violent episodes of [[self-harm]], placed him at risk of torture and persecution if returned to his native country. The boy's mother wrote in her asylum application that the majority of Pakistanis viewed the boy's condition as a curse from [[God]], and that the boy was forced to undergo various dangerous and degrading "treatments" such as drinking dirty water meant for crows.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| vauthors = Feinstein A |title=A history of autism : conversations with the pioneers|date=2010|publisher=Wiley-Blackwell|isbn=978-1-4051-8654-4|location=Chichester, West Sussex, U.K.|oclc=495597850}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2019, a 11-year-old [[Nonverbal autism|non-verbal autistic]] boy in the fifth grade received the "Bailly Preparatory Academy 2018-2019 Most Annoying Male" award from his [[special education]] teacher at Bailly Preparatory Academy, while other students were given positive awards, such as "most improved" or "funniest". The mother of the autistic boy, Estella Castejon, said she went to the [[school]] that gave her son the award and demanded an apology from the principal and the teacher who gave her son the award. Although Castejon did not receive an apology, Dr. Peter Morikis of the [[Gary Community School Corporation]] released a statement saying that the teacher would be disciplined.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| vauthors = Thomas E |date=2019-06-05|title=Parents outraged after son with autism was given 'most annoying' award|url=https://abcnews.go.com/US/parents-outraged-autistic-son-annoying-award/story?id=63502968|url-status=live|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=2021-02-01|website=[[ABC News]]|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| vauthors = O'Kane C |date=2019-06-04|title=Family outraged after boy with autism receives "Most Annoying" student award from school|url=https://www.cbsnews.com/news/indiana-boy-with-autism-receives-most-annoying-student-award-from-school/|url-status=live|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=2021-02-01|website=[[CBS News]]|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Autism friendly]]
* [[Autism rights movement]]
* [[Neurodiversity]]

== References ==
{{reflist}}

[[Category:Sociological and cultural aspects of autism]]
[[Category:discrimination by type|aut]]
[[Category:persecution|aut]]
[[Category:bullying|aut]]
[[Category:Ableism]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>