<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20241125164332|1259519259" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="48844349" pageid="48844349" ns="0" title="Discrimination against autistic people"><revisions><rev timestamp="2024-11-29T14:42:57Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|none}}
{{globalize|article|US|UK|Canada|date=January 2023}}
{{Discrimination sidebar|Social}}
'''Discrimination against autistic people''' involves any form of [[discrimination]], [[persecution]], or [[oppression]] against people who are [[autistic]]. Despite contention over its status as a disability, discrimination against autistic people is considered to be a form of [[ableism]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Billawalla |first1=Alshaba |last2=Wolbring |first2=Gregor |title=Analyzing the discourse surrounding Autism in the New York Times using an ableism lens |journal=Disability Studies Quarterly |date=2014 |volume=34 |issue=1 |doi=10.18061/dsq.v34i1.3348 |url=https://dsq-sds.org/article/view/3348/3524 |access-date=13 December 2021|doi-access=free }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Prevalence==
===Ireland===
Research published by charity AsIAm in 2022 showed that 6 in 10 Irish people associated autism with negative characteristics such as "not making eye contact", "difficulty making friends" and "no to little verbal communication".&lt;ref name=it-autistic-people-still-facing-barriers&gt;{{Cite news |title=Autistic people still facing barriers, new report finds |last=Kenny |first=Áine |date=2022-03-31 |url=https://www.irishtimes.com/news/ireland/irish-news/autistic-people-still-facing-barriers-new-report-finds-1.4841303 |access-date=2024-10-10 |newspaper=[[The Irish Times]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; People were less likely to know the positive traits associated with autism, such as logical thinking, honesty and being detail-oriented.&lt;ref name=it-autistic-people-still-facing-barriers/&gt; The survey found that ten percent of autistic people surveyed felt workplaces were inclusive.&lt;ref name=it-autistic-people-still-facing-barriers/&gt;

The Same Chance report was based on two surveys were conducted on behalf of AsIAm – the first, by Core Research assessed public attitudes to autistic people by surveying 1,000 members of the general public.&lt;ref name=it-autistic-people-still-facing-barriers/&gt; The second survey was of 944 parents, carers and autistic people over the age of 18.&lt;ref name=it-autistic-people-still-facing-barriers/&gt;

The issues raised in the second survey included accessing healthcare, education, employment and housing.&lt;ref name=it-autistic-people-still-facing-barriers/&gt; 
===United Kingdom===
Research published in 2019 used data from more than 8,000 children in the [[University of London]]'s [[Millennium Cohort Study]], which tracks the lives of about 19,000 people born in the [[United Kingdom]] starting in 2000. Out of the children selected, 231 were autistic. The study from the ''[[Journal of Autism and Developmental Disorders]]'' found that these autistic children were more likely to engage in "two-way sibling bullying", meaning being both a victim and perpetrator of bullying.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Toseeb U, McChesney G, Oldfield J, Wolke D | title = Sibling Bullying in Middle Childhood is Associated with Psychosocial Difficulties in Early Adolescence: The Case of Individuals with Autism Spectrum Disorder | journal = Journal of Autism and Developmental Disorders | volume = 50 | issue = 5 | pages = 1457–1469 | date = May 2020 | pmid = 31332675 | pmc = 7211196 | doi = 10.1007/s10803-019-04116-8 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Further research published in 2017, a meta-analysis of three studies, demonstrated that "first impressions of individuals with ASD made from thin slices of real-world social behavior by typically-developing observers are not only far less favorable across a range of trait judgments compared to controls, but also are associated with reduced intentions to pursue social interaction."&lt;ref name="Sasson-2017" /&gt; The meta-analysis continues, "These patterns are remarkably robust, occur within seconds, do not change with increased exposure, and persist across both child and adult age groups."&lt;ref name="Sasson-2017" /&gt; This may be why autistic people have "smaller social networks and fewer friendships, difficulty securing and retaining employment, high rates of loneliness, and an overall reduced quality of life."&lt;ref name="Sasson-2017"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Sasson |first1=Noah J. |last2=Faso |first2=Daniel J. |last3=Nugent |first3=Jack |last4=Lovell |first4=Sarah |last5=Kennedy |first5=Daniel P. |last6=Grossman |first6=Ruth B. |title=Neurotypical Peers are Less Willing to Interact with Those with Autism based on Thin Slice Judgments |journal=Scientific Reports |date=1 February 2017 |volume=7 |page=40700 |doi=10.1038/srep40700 |pmid=28145411 |pmc=5286449 |bibcode=2017NatSR...740700S |issn=2045-2322|doi-access=free }}&lt;/ref&gt; Smaller social networks, fewer friendships, and loneliness correlate with severe health outcomes. According to a paper published in the ''[[Journal of Health and Social Behavior]]'', "Health risks associated with social isolation have been compared in magnitude to the well-known dangers of smoking cigarettes and obesity."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=CORNWELL |first1=ERIN YORK |last2=WAITE |first2=LINDA J. |title=Social Disconnectedness, Perceived Isolation, and Health among Older Adults |journal=Journal of Health and Social Behavior |date=2009 |volume=50 |issue=1 |pages=31–48 |doi=10.1177/002214650905000103 |pmid=19413133 |issn=0022-1465|pmc=2756979 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, according to the [[UK]] [[Office for National Statistics]], the unemployment rate of autistic people may reach 85%, the highest rate among all disabled groups studied. It is noted that in many countries autism is not a disability protected by anti-discrimination employment laws, and this is due to many corporations lobbying against it.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Putz |first1=Catherine |last2=Sparkes |first2=Indiana |last3=Foubert |first3=Josephine |title=Outcomes for disabled people in the UK – Office for National Statistics |website=www.ons.gov.uk |date=18 February 2021 |url=https://www.ons.gov.uk/peoplepopulationandcommunity/healthandsocialcare/disability/articles/outcomesfordisabledpeopleintheuk/2020 |access-date=15 April 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt; Autistic adults are also more likely to face healthcare disparities, such as being [[Vaccines and autism|unvaccinated]] against common diseases like [[tetanus]] and being more likely to use emergency services.&lt;ref name="Nicolaidis Raymaker McDonald Dern pp. 761–769"&gt;{{cite journal | last1=Nicolaidis | first1=Christina | last2=Raymaker | first2=Dora | last3=McDonald | first3=Katherine | last4=Dern | first4=Sebastian | last5=Boisclair | first5=W. Cody | last6=Ashkenazy | first6=Elesia | last7=Baggs | first7=Amanda | title=Comparison of Healthcare Experiences in Autistic and Non-Autistic Adults: A Cross-Sectional Online Survey Facilitated by an Academic-Community Partnership | journal=Journal of General Internal Medicine | publisher=Springer Science and Business Media LLC | volume=28 | issue=6 | date=2012-11-21 | issn=0884-8734 | doi=10.1007/s11606-012-2262-7 | pages=761–769| pmid=23179969 | pmc=3663938 }}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Autistic people are also less likely to graduate from [[high school|secondary school]], college, or other forms of higher education, further contributing to high rates of unemployment and lower of quality of life.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://the61percentproject.com/attrition-issue-why-students-with-autism-drop-out.php | title=Attrition Issue: Why Students with Autism Drop Out – the 61% Project }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=https://www.autismspeaks.org/autism-statistics-asd | title=Autism Statistics and Facts}}&lt;/ref&gt; This failure to successfully complete education can be in part attributed to a lack of support from educational institutions. In the UK, only one quarter of autistic children in [[state school|state-funded schools]] feel happy and are thus able to achieve their maximum potential.&lt;ref name="NAS"&gt;{{cite web | title=Education Report 2023 | date=30 May 2023 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===United States===
In the [[United States]], people with disabilities are victims of violent crime three times as often as people without disabilities. The [[Bureau of Justice Statistics]] does not report separately on autistic victims, but it does note that the victimization rate is especially high among those whose disabilities are cognitive. A small-sample study of Americans and Canadians found that autistic adults face a greater risk of [[sexual victimization]] than their peers. Autistic respondents were more than twice as likely to say they had been the victim of [[rape]] and over three times as likely to report unwanted sexual contact.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| vauthors = Pitney Jr JJ |title=The politics of autism : navigating the contested spectrum|isbn=978-1-4422-4960-8|location=Lanham|oclc=907022313|year=2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2018, a large scale study found that autistic girls were almost three times more likely to be a victim of sexual abuse compared to non-autistic girls.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Ohlsson Gotby|first1=Vide|last2=Lichtenstein|first2=Paul|last3=Långström|first3=Niklas|last4=Pettersson|first4=Erik|date=September 2018|title=Childhood neurodevelopmental disorders and risk of coercive sexual victimization in childhood and adolescence – a population-based prospective twin study|url=https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/29570782/|journal=Journal of Child Psychology and Psychiatry, and Allied Disciplines|volume=59|issue=9|pages=957–965|doi=10.1111/jcpp.12884|issn=1469-7610|pmid=29570782|s2cid=4238219}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Discrimination in media and culture==
Representation of autistic people in media has perpetuated myths about autism, including characterizing autism as shameful and burdensome for family members, advertising fake cures for autism, and publicizing the long-disproven arguments surrounding [[vaccines and autism]]. These myths are perpetuated in [[mass media]] as well as [[news media]] and [[social media]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Holton |first1=Avery |last2=Farrell |first2=Laura C. |last3=Fudge |first3=Julie L. |title=A Threatening Space?: Stigmatization and the Framing of Autism in the News |journal=Communication Studies |date=March 28, 2014 |volume=65 |issue=2 |pages=189–207 |doi=10.1080/10510974.2013.855642 |s2cid=145668002 |url=https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/10510974.2013.855642 |access-date=23 December 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt; Stigmatization of autism can also be perpetuated by advertising from autism conversion organizations, such as [[Autism Speaks]]' advertising wherein a mother describes having considered [[murder-suicide]] in front of her autistic daughter or the NYU Child Study Center's advertisements where autism is personified as a kidnapper holding children for ransom.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Waltz |first1=Mitzi |title=Images and narratives of autism within charity discourses |journal=Disability &amp; Society |date=February 16, 2012 |volume=27 |issue=2 |pages=219–233 |doi=10.1080/09687599.2012.631796 |s2cid=143756605 |url=https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/10.1080/09687599.2012.631796 |access-date=23 December 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Moreover, the autistic behavior known as [[stimming]] is frequently referred to as "distracting" and the way autistic people naturally talk is often described as rude.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |date=2021-08-09 |title=Asperger's Doesn't Mean They're Rude |url=https://psychcentral.com/autism/myths-about-aspergers-and-rudeness |access-date=2023-02-21 |website=Psych Central |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; Stimming specifically is often targeted in therapies such as [[Applied Behavioral Analysis]], despite the fact that it is vital to self regulation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Taylor |first1=Elinor |title=Beyond 'bad' behaviors: A call for occupational scientists to rethink autism |journal=Journal of Occupational Science |date=2 October 2023 |volume=30 |issue=4 |pages=575–590 |doi=10.1080/14427591.2022.2136231 |s2cid=253503104 |url=https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/14427591.2022.2136231}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Physical health-related research ==
In the United States, recently published research&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=McDonald |first1=T. A. Meridian |last2=Scudder |first2=Audrey |date=2023-01-13 |title=Mind the NIH-Funding Gap: Structural Discrimination in Physical Health–Related Research for Cognitively Able Autistic Adults |journal=Journal of Autism and Developmental Disorders |volume=54 |issue=4 |pages=1411–1424 |language=en |doi=10.1007/s10803-022-05856-w |pmid=36635433 |pmc=10762646 |pmc-embargo-date=April 1, 2025 |s2cid=255773930 |issn=0162-3257}}&lt;/ref&gt; shows that the National Institutes of Health (NIH) has not funded grants focused on the treatment of physical health disparity conditions, such as insomnia, cardiovascular disease, and other conditions, in autistic adults across four decades of research funding.  McDonald and Scudder (2023) explicitly distinguish health disparity conditions that affect the lives of autistic people from research grants focused on the cause, cure, and prevention of autism.  Although their research focused on autistic adults without an intellectual disability, the research did not exclude this population and found a lack of funded grants focused on the treatment of health disparity conditions for autistic adults with intellectual disabilities.  The research describes several systemic discriminatory "nodes" of practices and policies that may contribute to the apparent discrimination in research grant funding.  These include the exclusion of disability populations from groups designated for physical health disparity research grants, the designation of autism as a "primary disease;" a designation used as a rationale for some National Institutes of Health (e.g., the National Heart Lung and Blood Institute) to exclude research focused on autistic populations from grant funding review, and the pressure on early career researchers by academic institutions (that receive NIH funding) to either change their research topic or their population for NIH grant applications and to avoid challenging NIH policies until they are at a more advanced stage in their career.

==Immigration==
In the United States, the [[first Trump administration]] supported restrictive immigration policies that discriminated against autistic people. Under these policies, autistic immigrants faced deportation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.inquirer.com/news/immigration-trump-deferred-action-medical-autism-mexico-guatemala-20190913.html |title=Immigrant families with severely ill or disabled children now face deportation by Trump administration |date=13 September 2019 |publisher=[[The Philadelphia Inquirer]] |accessdate=2022-05-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= https://www.disabilityscoop.com/2018/04/30/trump-bar-immigrants-disabilities/25032/ |title=Trump Administration Seeks To Bar Immigrants with Disabilities |date=30 April 2018 |publisher=Disability Scoop |accessdate=2022-05-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Disability in Canada|Canada]], autistic immigrants have been denied citizenship or they have faced deportation due to the perception that they are a "burden" upon the Canadian medical system. In 2018, reforms in Canadian immigration law were announced – these reforms are supposed to make it easier for autistic and disabled immigrants to migrate to Canada.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://globalnews.ca/news/4150860/disability-immigration-law-a-blessing-says-father-autistic-child/ |title=Father of son with autism calls Canada's new immigration policy a 'blessing for all of us' |publisher=Global News |accessdate=2022-05-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

New Zealand effectively prohibits the application for permanent residency for people with autism "where significant support is required".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title="Burdens" and Borders: Disability Discrimination in New Zealand Immigration Law |url=https://www.equaljusticeproject.co.nz/articles/burdens-and-borders-disability-discrimination-in-new-zealand-immigration-law2020 |access-date=2023-03-04 |website=Equal Justice Project |date=4 May 2020 |language=en-GB}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Operational Manual – Immigration New Zealand. Issue Date: 3 May 2024Operational Manual – Immigration New Zealand. Issue Date: 22 August 2016 |url=https://www.immigration.govt.nz/opsmanual/#46506.htm |access-date=2024-05-14 |website=www.immigration.govt.nz}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Australia's health criteria have prompted criticism about its immigration policies. Australia forbids the immigration of people who would be exceptionally costly for the nation's health care or social services. Autistic people are subject to this policy.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.theguardian.com/australia-news/2017/feb/23/outcry-after-sydney-doctor-faced-with-deportation-over-autistic-child/ |access-date=2024-03-15 |website=Guardian |language=en-GB |title=Outcry after Sydney doctor faced with deportation over autistic child |date=23 February 2017 |last1=Doherty |first1=Ben |last2=Knaus |first2=Christopher }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Autism-friendly]]
* [[Autism rights movement]]
* [[Neurodiversity]]
*[[Violence and autism]]

== References ==
{{reflist}}

{{Autism}}

[[Category:Sociological and cultural aspects of autism]]
[[Category:Discrimination by type|aut]]
[[Category:Persecution|aut]]
[[Category:Harassment and bullying|aut]]
[[Category:Ableism]]
[[Category:Discrimination in the United States|aut]]
[[Category:Discrimination in Canada|aut]]
[[Category:Discrimination in New Zealand|aut]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>