<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20101031182139|394015438" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="66935" pageid="66935" ns="0" title="Queer"><revisions><rev timestamp="2010-11-08T14:07:04Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Clear}}
{{Other uses}}
{{pp-semi-indef|small=yes|expiry=February 03, 2009}}

{{LGBT sidebar}}
'''''Queer''''' is an [[umbrella term]] for [[minority]] [[sexual orientation]]s and [[Gender identity|gender identities]]&lt;ref name=QUEER&gt;QUEER: "[http://www.algbtical.org/2A%20QUEER.htm Umbrella Term for Sexual Minorities]." Retrieved on September 02, 2010&lt;/ref&gt; that are not [[heterosexual]], [[heteronormative]] or [[Gender binary|gender-binary]]. In the context of Western [[identity politics]] the term also acts as a label setting queer-identifying people apart from [[discourse]], [[Ideology|ideologies]], and [[lifestyle (sociology)|lifestyle]]s that typify [[mainstream]] [[LGBT]] ([[lesbian]], [[gay]], [[bisexual]], and [[transsexual]]) [[LGBT community|communities]] as being [[Oppression|oppressive]] or [[Cultural assimilation|assimilationist]].

This term is controversial because it was [[Reappropriation|reappropriated]] only two decades ago from its use as an [[anti-gay]] [[Pejorative|epithet]]. Furthermore, some LGBT people disapprove of using ''queer'' as a catch-all because they consider it offensive, derisive or [[Self-deprecation|self-deprecating]] given its continuous use as a form of [[hate speech]].

__TOC__
== Background ==
===Origin===
Since its emergence in the English language in the 16th century (related to the German ''quer'', meaning "across, at right angle, diagonally or transverse"), ''queer'' has generally meant "strange", "unusual", or "out of alignment". It might refer to something suspicious or "not quite right", or to a person with mild derangement or who exhibits socially inappropriate behaviour.  The expression "in Queer Street" was used in the [[United Kingdom|UK]] as of the 1811 edition of [[Francis Grose]]'s ''[[A Classical Dictionary of the Vulgar Tongue]]'' for someone in financial trouble.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.telegraphindia.com/1050513/asp/opinion/story_4734803.asp The Telegraph] If one is bankrupt, one is in Queer Street. This originates from the word query which tradesmen and merchants would write against the names of persons who were late in paying. Another theory relates it to Carey Street off Chancery Lane in London which housed the bankruptcy courts.&lt;/ref&gt;

''Queer as Folk'' is a reference to the common expression unrelated to homosexuality "There's nowt so queer as folk".

In the 1904 [[Sherlock Holmes]] story "[[The Adventure of the Second Stain]]", the term is still used in a completely non-sexual context (Inspector Lestrade is threatening a misbehaving constable with "finding himself in Queer Street", i.e., in this context, being severely punished).

===Semantic shift===
By the time that story was published, however, the term was already starting to gain a connotation of sexual deviance (especially that of homosexual and/or effeminate males), which is already known in the late 19th century; an early recorded usage of the word in this sense was in a letter by [[John Sholto Douglas, 9th Marquess of Queensberry]] to his son [[Lord Alfred Douglas]].

Subsequently, for most of the 20th century, "queer" was frequently used as a derogatory term for effeminate gay males who were believed to engage in receptive or passive anal/oral sex with men, and others exhibiting untraditional (i.e. trans &lt;ref&gt;Jane Czyzselska, untitled, Pride 1996 Magazine (london: Pride Trust &amp; Gay Times, 1996) p15 &lt;/ref&gt;) gender behaviour. Furthermore, masculine males, who performed the role of the "penetrator" were considered "straights".&lt;ref&gt;[http://209.85.175.104/search?q=cache:rkrcYyzPin0J:www.anzasa.arts.usyd.edu.au/a.j.a.s/Articles/1_02/Robertson.pdf+ A TALE OF TWO SEXUAL REVOLUTIONS]; STEPHEN ROBERTSON AUSTRALASIAN JOURNAL OF AMERICAN STUDIES Quote: The most striking addition to the picture offered by D’Emilio and Freedman is a working-class sexual culture in which only those men who took the passive or feminine role were considered ‘queer.’ A man who took the ‘active role,’ who inserted his penis into another man, remained a ‘straight’ man, even when he had an on-going relationship with a man who took the passive role.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Linguistic reappropriation===
One of the first attempts by the LGBT community to re-claim the term "queer" was through an organisation called [[Queer Nation]], which was formed in March 1990; a few months later, an influential though anonymous flier was distributed at the [[Gay Pride Parade (New York City)|New York Gay Pride Parade]] in June 1990 entitled "Queers Read This".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.qrd.org/qrd/misc/text/queers.read.this Text of the "Queer Read This" flier]. Retrieved 4 February 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

Because of the context in which it was reclaimed, ''queer'' has sociopolitical connotations, and is often preferred by those who are activists, by those who strongly reject traditional gender identities, by those who reject distinct [[sexual identity|sexual identities]] such as gay, lesbian, bisexual, and straight, and by those who see themselves as oppressed by the [[heteronormativity]] of the larger culture. In this usage it retains the historical connotation of "outside the bounds of normal society" and can be construed as "breaking the rules for sex and gender". It can be preferred because of its ambiguity, which allows "queer"-identifying people to avoid the sometimes strict boundaries that surround other labels.  In this context, "queer" is not a synonym for [[LGBT]] as it creates a space for "queer" heterosexuals as well as "non-queer" homosexuals.

The term is sometimes capitalized when referring to an [[Identity (social science)|identity]] or community, rather than merely a sexual fact (cf. the capitalized use of [[Deaf]]).&lt;ref name=BI&gt;"Information About: [http://www.informationdelight.info/encyclopedia/entry/queer Queer]". Retrieved on September 2, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Inclusivity and scope==
The range of what "queer" includes varies. In addition to referring to LGBT-identifying people, it can also encompass: [[pansexual]], [[pomosexual]], [[intersexual]], [[genderqueer]], [[asexual]] and [[autosexual]] people, and even [[heteronormativity|gender normative heterosexuals]] whose sexual orientations or activities place them outside the heterosexual-defined mainstream, e.g. [[BDSM]] practitioners, or [[polyamory|polyamorous]] persons.

For some queer-identified people, part of the point of the term "queer" is that it simultaneously builds up and tears down boundaries of identity. For instance, among genderqueer people, who do not solidly identify with one particular gender, once solid gender roles have been torn down, it becomes difficult to situate sexual identity.  For some people, the non-specificity of the term is liberating. Queerness becomes a way to simultaneously make a political move against heteronormativity while simultaneously refusing to engage in traditional [[Essentialism|essentialist]] identity politics.&lt;ref name=LESBIAN&gt;"Alphabet Soup: [http://thinkingaboutnow.wordpress.com/2010/02/01/alphabet-soup-labels-and-empowerment/ Labels and Empowerment]". Retrieved on September 2, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Current examples==
===Academia===
{{Main|Queer studies|Queer theory|Queer theology}}

===Arts, entertainment, and publishing===
{{See also|Queer cinema}}
Some television shows that use "queer" in their titles include both the [[Queer as Folk (UK TV series)|British]] and [[Queer as Folk (North American TV series)|North American]] versions of ''Queer as Folk'', ''[[Queer Eye]]'', and the cartoon ''[[Queer Duck]]''. This commonplace usage has, especially in the American colloquial culture, recently led to the more hip and iconic abbreviation "Q".&lt;ref name=Q&gt;" Queerbook, [http://inventorspot.com/articles/queerbook_whats_name_31251 What's In A Name?]" Retrieved on September 2, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
{{Portal|LGBT}}
* [[Sexuality and gender identity-based cultures]]
* [[Sexual minority]]
* [[Queer nationalism]]
* [[Homophobia]]
* [[Heterosexism]]
* [[Bisexual/Fluid/Pansexual]]
* [[Gay shame]]
* [[Queercore]] (formerly "homocore")
* [[Queer Youth Alliance]]

==References==
=== Notes ===
{{Reflist}}

===Bibliography===
{{Refbegin}}
* Anon. "Queercore". ''i-D magazine'' No. 110; the sexuality issue. (1992).
* Crimp, D. ''AIDS DemoGraphics''. (1990).
* Katlin, T. "Slant: Queer Nation".  ''Artforum'', November 1990.  pp.&amp;nbsp;21–23.
* Tucker, S. "Gender, Fucking &amp; Utopia".  ''Social text'', Vol.9, No.1. (1992).
{{Refend}}

==External links==
{{Wiktionary|queer}}
* [http://www.glbthistory.org The Gay, Lesbian, Bisexual, Transgender Historical Society]

{{Template group
|list =
{{Sexual identities}}
{{LGBT |main=expanded}}
}}

[[Category:Queer theory| ]]
[[Category:LGBT terms|Queer culture]]
[[Category:LGBT|Queer culture]]
[[Category:Reclaimed words]]

[[bs:Queer]]
[[bg:Куиър]]
[[de:Queer]]
[[es:Queer]]
[[eo:Kviro]]
[[fr:Queer]]
[[gl:Queer]]
[[hr:Queer]]
[[it:Queer]]
[[he:קוויר]]
[[mk:Queer]]
[[nl:Queer]]
[[ja:クィア]]
[[pl:Queer]]
[[pt:Queer]]
[[ro:Queer]]
[[sh:Queer]]
[[sv:Queer]]
[[tr:Queer]]
[[zh:酷兒 (LGBT)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>