<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20021017142044|364462" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="66935" pageid="66935" ns="0" title="Queer"><revisions><rev timestamp="2002-10-17T15:56:16Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Queer''' is an inclusive term for people of an unorthodox sexual orientation or gender identity, such as [[gay]] men, [[lesbian]]s, [[bisexual]]s, and [[transgender]]ed people. In this usage, it is usually a synonym of such terms as LGBT or [[lesbigay]]. Often, it carries the connotatian of being oppressed merely for being who they are.

The term is often uppercased when referring to an identity or community, rather than merely a sexual fact (compare the capitalized use of [[Deaf]]).

Historically, the term was an epithet for gay men, bordering on [[profanity]]. Since the term originated as a [[homophobia|homophobic]] slur, many members of sexual minorities do not favour its use. On the other hand, many people identify primarily as Queer rather than gay, lesbian, bisexual, or transgendered.

The term first attained common usage during the [[1980s]], when it was popularized by the activist group [[Queer Nation]].

[[Queer studies]] as an academic discipline is now established at many universities. Like some branches of [[feminism]], scholars in Queer theory tend to view prostitition, pornography and [[BDSM]] as legitimate and valuable expressions of human sexuality; this places them in conflict with other branches of feminism that view them as mechanisms for the oppression of women.

See also [[Queer culture]], [[taboo]], [[profanity]], [[hate speech]].</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>