<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20170917124446|801063826" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="66935" pageid="66935" ns="0" title="Queer"><revisions><rev timestamp="2017-10-05T20:38:17Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Other uses}}
{{pp-semi-indef|small=yes}}

{{LGBT sidebar}}
'''''Queer''''' is an [[umbrella term]] for [[sexual minority|sexual]] and [[gender]] [[Minority group|minorities]] who are not [[heterosexual]] and/or not [[cisgender]]. Originally meaning "strange" or "peculiar", ''queer'' came to be used [[pejorative]]ly against those with same-sex desires or relationships in the late [[19th century]]. Beginning in the late 1980s, queer scholars and activists began to [[reappropriation|reclaim]] the word to establish community and assert an identity distinct from the [[gay]] identity. People who reject traditional gender identities and seek a broader and deliberately ambiguous alternative to the label ''[[LGBT]]'' may describe themselves as ''queer''.

''Queer'' is also increasingly used to describe non-normative&lt;ref group=note&gt;"Non-normative" does not mean "not normal", but rather refers to the privileging of "normal" genders and sexualities over the "non-normative". The term "normative" implies that "normal" does not exist in and of itself, but is created. See also [[heteronormativity]] for more context.&lt;/ref&gt; (i.e. anti-[[heteronormative]] and anti-[[Heteronormativity#Homonormativity|homonormative]]) identities and politics.&lt;ref name="oed"&gt;{{cite encyclopedia
 | year =2014
 | title = queer
 | encyclopedia = Oxford English Dictionary
 | publisher = Oxford University Press}}&lt;/ref&gt; Academic disciplines such as [[queer theory]]  and [[queer studies]] share a general opposition to [[Gender binary|binarism]], normativity, and a perceived lack of [[intersectionality]] within the mainstream LGBT movement. Queer arts, queer cultural groups, and queer political groups are examples of expressions of queer identities.

Critics of the use of the term include members of the LGBT community and others who associate the term more with its colloquial usage as a derogatory insult or who wish to dissociate themselves from queer radicalism.

== Etymology ==
Entering the English language in the [[{{ordinal|16}} century]], ''queer'' originally meant "strange", "odd", "peculiar", or "eccentric". It might refer to something suspicious or "not quite right", or to a person with mild derangement or who exhibits socially inappropriate behaviour.&lt;ref name="oed"/&gt;&lt;ref name="mw"&gt;{{cite encyclopedia| year =2014 | title = queer | encyclopedia = Merriam-Webster | publisher = Encyclopædia Britannica | url=http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/queer}}&lt;/ref&gt; A [[Northern England English|Northern English]] expression, "[[wikt:there's nowt so queer as folk|There's nowt so queer as folk]]," meaning, "There is nothing as strange as people," employs this meaning.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=there's nowt so queer as folk|url=http://dictionary.cambridge.org/dictionary/english/there-s-nowt-so-queer-as-folk|work=Cambridge Advanced Learner's Dictionary and Thesaurus (via Cambridge Dictionaries Online)|publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]]|accessdate=2 November 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Related meanings of queer include a feeling of unwellness or something that is questionable or suspicious.&lt;ref name="oed"/&gt;&lt;ref name="mw"/&gt; The expression "in [[Queer Street]]" was used in the [[United Kingdom]] for someone in financial trouble. In the 1904 [[Sherlock Holmes]] story "[[The Adventure of the Second Stain]]", [[Inspector Lestrade]] threatens that a misbehaving constable will "find [himself] in Queer Street" (i.e., lose his position).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Doyle |first=Arthur Conan |year=1904 |title= The Return of Sherlock Holmes|chapter=The Adventure of the Second Stain|url=http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/108 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===''Queer'' as a pejorative===
By the time "The Adventure of the Second Stain" was published, the term was starting to gain a connotation of sexual deviance, referring to feminine men or men who would engage in same-sex relationships. An early recorded usage of the word in this sense was in an 1894 letter by [[John Sholto Douglas, 9th Marquess of Queensberry]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last= Foldy|first= Michael S. |year= 1997|title= The Trials of Oscar Wilde: Deviance, Morality, and Late-Victorian Society |publisher= Yale University Press|isbn= 9780300071122|page=22}}&lt;/ref&gt; Usage of ''queer'' as a derogatory term for effeminate men become prominent in the [[{{ordinal|20}} century]].&lt;ref name="oed"/&gt; In the early-{{ordinal|20}} century, individuals with non-normative sexual or gender identities, including English poet and author [[Radclyffe Hall]], preferred the identity of ''[[Sexual inversion (sexology)|invert]]''. In the mid-{{ordinal|20}} century, the invert identity lost ground and shifted toward the [[homophile]] identity. In the 1960s and 1970s, the homophile identity was displaced by a more radicalized [[gay]] identity, which at the time included [[transgender|trans]] and [[gender variance|gender-nonconforming]] people.

During the [[endonym]]ic shifts from invert to homophile to gay, ''queer'' was pejoratively applied to men who were believed to engage in receptive or passive [[Anal sex|anal]] or [[Oral sex|oral]] [[Sexual intercourse|sex]] with other men&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last= Robertson|first= Stephen|year= 2002|title=A Tale of Two Sexual Revolutions |journal= Australasian Journal of American Studies|publisher= Australia and New Zealand American Studies Association |volume= 21 |issue= 1 |pages= 98–110}}&lt;/ref&gt;  as well as those who exhibited non-normative gender expressions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Czyzselska |first= Jane|year= 1996 |title= untitled |journal= Pride 1996 Magazine|publisher= Pride Trust &amp; Gay Times|location = London|page= 15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Reclamation===
Beginning in the late-1980s, the label ''queer'' began to be [[reappropriation|reclaimed]] from its pejorative use as a neutral or positive self-identifier by LGBT people.&lt;ref name="oed"/&gt; An early example of this usage by the LGBT community was by an organisation called [[Queer Nation]], which was formed in March 1990 and circulated an anonymous flier at the [[Gay Pride Parade (New York City)|New York Gay Pride Parade]] in June 1990 titled "Queers Read This".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.qrd.org/qrd/misc/text/queers.read.this|title= Queers Read This |last1= Queer Nation |date= June 1990}}&lt;/ref&gt; The flier included a passage explaining their adoption of the label queer:

{{quote|Ah, do we really have to use that word? It's trouble. Every gay person has his or her own take on it. For some it means strange and eccentric and kind of mysterious [...] And for others "queer" conjures up those awful memories of adolescent suffering [...] Well, yes, "gay" is great. It has its place. But when a lot of lesbians and gay men wake up in the morning we feel angry and disgusted, not gay. So we've chosen to call ourselves queer. Using "queer" is a way of reminding us how we are perceived by the rest of the world.}}

Queer people, particularly queer people of color, began to reclaim ''queer'' in response to a perceived shift in the gay community toward [[liberal conservatism]], catalyzed by [[Andrew Sullivan]]'s 1989 piece in ''[[The New Republic]]'', titled ''Here Comes the Groom: The Conservative Case for Gay Marriage''.&lt;ref name="duggan"&gt;{{cite book |last= Duggan|first= Lisa|date= 2003|title= The Twilight of Equality?: Neoliberalism, Cultural Politics, and the Attack on Democracy|url= |location= Boston|publisher= Beacon Press|page= 60|isbn= 9780807079553}}&lt;/ref&gt; The queer movement rejected causes viewed as [[cultural assimilation|assimilationist]], such as [[same-sex marriage|marriage]], [[sexual orientation and military service|military inclusion]] and adoption.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Sycamore|first1=Mattilda Bernstein|title=That's Revolting!: Queer Strategies for Resisting Assimilation|date=2008|publisher=Counterpoint Press|isbn=9781593761950|page=1|edition=illustrated, revised|url=https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=t_EK8GjtytMC|accessdate=11 March 2015|quote=Willful participation in U.S. imperialism is crucial to the larger goal of assimilation, as the holy trinity of marriage, military service and adoption has become the central preoccupation of a gay movement centered more on obtaining straight privilege than challenging power}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The term may be capitalized when referring to an [[Identity (social science)|identity]] or community, rather than as an objective fact describing a person's desires, in a construction similar to the capitalized use of [[Deaf culture|Deaf]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Deaf Culture|url=http://www.glbtq.com/social-sciences/deaf_culture.html|publisher=[[glbtq.com]]|accessdate=9 March 2015|date=2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The "hip and iconic abbreviation 'Q'" has developed from common usage of ''queer'', particularly in the United States.&lt;ref name=Q&gt;" Queerbook, [http://inventorspot.com/articles/queerbook_whats_name_31251 What's In A Name?]" Retrieved on September 2, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Inclusivity and scope==
Because of the context in which it was reclaimed, ''queer'' has sociopolitical connotations and is often preferred by those who are activists—namely, by those who strongly reject traditional gender identities; reject distinct [[sexual identity|sexual identities]] such as gay, lesbian, bisexual, or straight; or see themselves as oppressed by the [[Heteronormativity#Homonormativity|homonormativity]] of the politics of the broader gay or LGBT community. In this usage, ''queer'' retains its historical connotation of "outside the bounds of normal society" and can be construed as "breaking the rules for sex and gender". It can be preferred because of its ambiguity, which allows queer-identifying people to avoid the sometimes rigid boundaries that are associated with labels such as ''gay'', ''lesbian'', or even ''transgender''.

While initially used only to refer to radical homosexuals, opinions on the range of what queer includes can vary. For some people, the non-specificity of the term is liberating. Queerness thus becomes a path of political resistance against heteronormativity as well as homonormativity while simultaneously refusing to engage in traditional [[Essentialism|essentialist]] identity politics.&lt;ref name=LESBIAN&gt;"Alphabet Soup: [http://thinkingaboutnow.wordpress.com/2010/02/01/alphabet-soup-labels-and-empowerment/ Labels and Empowerment]". Retrieved on September 2, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Queer bodies==
{{further|Intersex and LGBT}}
[[Intersex]] activists have sometimes talked of intersex bodies as "queer bodies".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Carpenter |first=Morgan |date=18 June 2013 |title= Australia can lead the way for intersex people |url= https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2013/jun/18/intersex-people-australia |newspaper=[[The Guardian]] |location= |accessdate=2014-12-29 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Activists and scholars such as [[Morgan Holmes]] and [[Katrina Karkazis]] have documented a heteronormativity in medical rationales for the surgical normalization of infants and children born with atypical sex development.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal| last = Holmes| first = Morgan| authorlink=Morgan Holmes | date = May 1994| pages = 11–130|url=http://www.aissg.org/articles/HOLMES.HTM|title=Re-membering a Queer Body|publisher=Faculty of Environmental Studies, [[York University]], Ontario }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book| publisher = [[Duke University Press]]| last = Karkazis| first = Katrina| authorlink = Katrina Karkazis| title = [[Fixing Sex|Fixing Sex: Intersex, Medical Authority, and Lived Experience]]| location =| isbn = 978-0822343189| date = November 2009
}}&lt;/ref&gt; In "What Can Queer Theory Do for Intersex?" [[Iain Morland]] contrasts queer "hedonic activism" with an experience of insensate post-surgical intersex bodies to claim that "queerness is characterized by the sensory interrelation of pleasure and shame".&lt;ref name="after"&gt;{{cite journal |editor1-last=Morland |editor1-first=Iain | editor1-link=Iain Morland 
|date=2009 |title=Intersex and After |url=https://www.dukeupress.edu/Intersex-and-After/ |journal=[[GLQ: A Journal of Lesbian and Gay Studies]] |publisher= |volume=15 |issue=2 |isbn=978-0-8223-6705-5 |pages= |doi= |accessdate=2014-12-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

However, concerns have been raised among intersex activists that LGBT or ''queer'' groups including them could give the wrong impression that all or most intersex people are lesbian, gay, bisexual or transgender. Another concern is that the addition is only cosmetic, and that among groups that do this, LGBT goals are always prioritized over intersex ones. Emi Koyama states:&lt;ref name=LGBTI&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.intersexinitiative.org/articles/lgbti.html
|title= Adding the "I": Does Intersex Belong in the LGBT Movement? |first1= Emi |last1= Koyama |website=Intersex Initiative |accessdate=30 Sep 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
&lt;blockquote&gt;"To make it worse, the word 'intersex' began to attract individuals who are not necessarily intersex, but feel that they might be, because they are queer or trans. Many of these people felt that to be intersex meant a social and biological justification for being who they are, as in it's okay that you're queer or trans because they were literally 'born that way.' This obviously clashes with the majority of people born with intersex conditions, who despite their intersex bodies feel that they are perfectly ordinary heterosexual, non-trans men and women."&lt;ref name=DSD&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.intersexinitiative.org/articles/intersextodsd.html|title= From "Intersex" to "DSD": Toward a Queer Disability Politics of Gender |first1= Emi |last1= Koyama |website=Intersex Initiative |accessdate=30 Sep 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;

In 2016, [[Organisation Intersex International Australia]] wrote about the sponsorship of lesbian, gay, bisexual, transgender and intersex ([[LGBTI]]) events by [[In vitro fertilisation|IVF]] clinics in Australia, in a context where [[genetic diagnosis of intersex]] leads to the genetic de-selection of intersex traits, stating that, in addition to ethical issues raised by their de-selection, "sponsorship of "LGBTI" events by such businesses raises more ethical issues still, including the nature of community and comprehension of issues relating to intersex bodily diversity."&lt;ref name="oii2016"&gt;{{Cite web| last = Organisation Intersex International Australia | title = LGBTI sponsorship and the elimination of intersex traits| author-link = Organisation Intersex International Australia | accessdate = 2017-07-02| date = July 10, 2016 | url = https://oii.org.au/30555/sponsorship-elimination-intersex-traits/}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Queer academia==
{{Main|Queer studies|Queer theory}}
In academia, the term ''queer'' and the related verb ''[[queering]]'' broadly indicate the study of literature, discourse, academic fields, and other social and cultural areas from a non-heteronormative perspective. It often means studying a subject [[Resistant reading|against the grain]] from the perspective of [[gender studies]].

[[Queer studies]] is the study of issues relating to sexual orientation and gender identity usually focusing on LGBT people and cultures. Originally centered on [[LGBT history]] and [[literary theory]], the field has expanded to include the academic study of issues raised in [[biology]], [[sociology]],  [[anthropology]], [[history of science]], [[philosophy]], [[psychology]], [[sexology]], [[political science]], [[ethics]], and other fields by an examination of the identity, lives, history, and perception of queer people. Organizations such as the [[Irish Queer Archive]] attempt to collect and preserve history related to queer studies.

[[Queer theory]] is a field of [[post-structuralist]] [[critical theory]] that emerged in the early 1990s out of the fields of queer studies and [[women's studies]]. Applications of queer theory include [[queer theology]] and [[queer pedagogy]]. Queer theorists, including Rod Ferguson, Jasbir Puar, Lisa Duggan, and Chong-suk Han, critique the mainstream gay political movement as allied with [[neoliberal]] and [[imperialistic]] agendas, including gay tourism, gay and trans military inclusion, and state- and church-sanctioned marriages for monogamous gay couples. Puar, a queer theorist of color, coined the term ''[[homonationalism]]'', which refers to the rise of [[American exceptionalism]], [[nationalism]], [[white supremacy]], and [[patriarchy]] within the gay community catalyzed in response to the [[September 11 attacks]].&lt;ref name="puar"&gt;{{cite book |last= Puar|first= Jasbir|date= 2007|title= Terrorist Assemblages: Homonationalism in Queer Times|url= |location= |publisher= Duke University Press|page= |isbn= 9780822341147|access-date= }}&lt;/ref&gt; Many studies have acknowledged the problems that lie within the traditional theory and process of social studies, and so choose to utilise a queer theoretical approach instead. One such study was conducted in Melbourne in 2016 by Roffee and Waling. By using queer and feminist theories and approaches the researchers were better equipped to cater for the needs, and be accommodating for the vulnerabilities, of the LGBTIQ participants of the study. In this case, it was a specifically post-modern queer theory that enabled the researchers to approach the study with a fair perspective, acknowledging all the varieties of narratives and experiences within the LGBTIQ community.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.researchgate.net/publication/306325028_Resolving_ethical_challenges_when_researching_with_minority_and_vulnerable_populations_LGBTIQ_victims_of_violence_harassment_and_bullying]|title=James Roffee &amp; Andrea Waling Resolving ethical challenges when researching with minority and vulnerable populations: LGBTIQ victims of violence, harassment and bullying}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Queer art==
The label ''queer'' is often applied to art movements, particularly cinema. [[New Queer Cinema]] was a movement in queer-themed independent filmmaking in the early 1990s. Modern queer film festivals include the [[Melbourne Queer Film Festival]]  and [[Mardi Gras Film Festival]] (run by Queer Screen) in Australia, the [[Mumbai Queer Film Festival]] in India, the [[Asian Queer Film Festival]] in Japan, and [[Queersicht]] in Switzerland. Chinese film director [[Cui Zi'en]] titled his 2008 documentary about homosexuality in China ''[[Queer China]]'', which premiered at the 2009 Beijing Queer Film Festival after previous attempts to hold a queer film festival were shut down by the government.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2009/06/18/gays-in-china-beijing-que_n_217486.html|title= Gays In China: Beijing Queer Film Festival Goes Off Without A Hitch|last1= Tran|first1= Tini|date= June 18, 2009|website= The World Post|accessdate=30 January 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Multidisciplinary queer arts festivals include the [[Outburst Queer Arts Festival Belfast]] in Northern Ireland, the [[Queer Arts Festival]] in Canada, and the [[National Queer Arts Festival]] in the United States.

Television shows that use ''queer'' in their titles include the UK series ''[[Queer as Folk (UK TV series)|Queer as Folk]]'' and its American-Canadian [[Queer as Folk (North American TV series)|remake of the same name]], ''[[Queer Eye]]'', and the cartoon ''[[Queer Duck]]''.

==Queer culture and politics==
Several [[LGBT social movements]] around the world use the identifier ''queer'', such as the [[Queer Cyprus Association]] in Cyprus and the [[Queer Youth Network]] in the United Kingdom. In India, [[pride parade]]s include [[Queer Azaadi Mumbai]] and the [[Delhi Queer Pride Parade]]. The use of ''queer'' and ''Q'' is also widespread in Australia, including national counselling and support service Qlife&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.qlife.org.au |title=Archived copy |accessdate=January 31, 2014 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140202221819/https://www.qlife.org.au/ |archivedate=February 2, 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Q News (Australian magazine)|Q News]].

Other social movements exist as offshoots of queer culture or combinations of queer identity with other views. Adherents of [[queer nationalism]] support the notion that the LGBT community forms a distinct people due to their unique culture and customs. [[Queercore]] (originally ''homocore'') is a cultural and social movement that began in the mid-1980s as an offshoot of [[Punk subculture|punk]] expressed in a do-it-yourself style through zines, music, writing, art and film.

The term [[queer migration]] is used to describe the movement of LGBTQ people around the world often to escape discrimination or ill treatment due to their orientation or gender expression. Organizations such as the [[Iranian Railroad for Queer Refugees]] attempt to assist individuals in such relocations.

==Controversial nature of the term==
The use of the term ''queer'' is not  uncontroversial. Many people and organizations, both LGBT and non-LGBT, refuse to use the word.&lt;ref&gt;For example, see Drew Cordes [http://www.bilerico.com/2012/02/new_yorker_magazine_refuses_to_print_the_word_quee.php "New Yorker magazine refuses to use the word queer"]. Retrieved 29 January 2014.&lt;/ref&gt; There are several reasons for this.

* Some LGBT people disapprove of using ''queer'' as a catch-all because they consider it offensive, derisive or [[Self-deprecation|self-deprecating]], given its continuous use as a form of [[hate speech]] in English.&lt;ref&gt;Wisegeek, [http://www.wisegeek.org/is-queer-a-derogatory-word.htm "Is Queer a Derogatory Word?"] Retrieved 29 January 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;
* Other LGBT people resent the use of the word ''queer'' in this sense because they associate it with political radicalism. They also disagree with how the deliberate use of the epithet ''queer'' by political radicals has played a role in dividing the LGBT community by political opinion, class, gender, age, and so on. The controversy about the word also marks a social and political rift in the LGBT community between those (including civil-rights activists) who perceive themselves as "normal" and who wish to be seen as ordinary members of society and those who see themselves as separate, confrontational and not part of the ordinary social order.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Gamson|first1=Joshua|title=Must Identity Movements Self-Destruct? A Queer Dilemma|journal=Social Problems|date=August 1995|volume=42|issue=3|pages=390–407|doi=10.1525/sp.1995.42.3.03x0104z}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Some LGBT people avoid ''queer'' because they perceive it as faddish slang or academic jargon.&lt;ref name="AyoubPaternotte2014"&gt;{{cite book|author1=Phillip Ayoub|author2=David Paternotte|title=LGBT Activism and the Making of Europe: A Rainbow Europe?|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=7hlHBQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT137|date=28 October 2014|publisher=Palgrave Macmillan|isbn=978-1-137-39177-3|pages=137–138}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Gay Shame]]
* [[Heterosexism]]
* [[Homophobia]]
* [[Sexual minority]]
* [[Sexuality and gender identity-based cultures]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

=== Notes ===
{{reflist|group=note}}

===Bibliography===
{{Refbegin}}
* Anon. "Queercore". ''i-D magazine'' No. 110; the sexuality issue. (1992).
* Crimp, D. ''AIDS DemoGraphics''. (1990).
* Katlin, T. "Slant: Queer Nation".  ''Artforum'', November 1990.  pp.&amp;nbsp;21–23.
* Tucker, S. "Gender, Fucking &amp; Utopia".  ''Social text'', Vol.9, No.1. (1992).
{{Refend}}

==External links==
{{Wiktionary|queer}}
* [http://www.glbthistory.org The Gay, Lesbian, Bisexual, Transgender Historical Society]

{{Navboxes
|list =
{{Sexual identities}}
{{LGBT |main=expanded}}
}}

[[Category:Words coined in the 1980s]]
[[Category:Queer| ]]
[[Category:Queer theory| ]]
[[Category:LGBT terminology|Queer]]
[[Category:Reclaimed words]]
[[Category:Homophobic slurs]]
[[Category:Homophobia]]
[[Category:English words]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>