<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20141006162121|628496412" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="66935" pageid="66935" ns="0" title="Queer"><revisions><rev timestamp="2014-10-31T06:04:04Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Other uses}}
{{pp-semi-indef|small=yes}}

{{LGBT sidebar}}
'''''Queer''''' is an [[umbrella term]] for [[sexual minority|sexual]] and gender minorities that are not [[heterosexual]], or [[gender binary|gender-binary]]. Originally meaning ''strange'' or ''peculiar'', ''queer'' developed a usage as a [[pejorative]] term for ''homosexual'' in the late 19th century. Beginning in the late 1980s, some political and social [[LGBT]] groups began to [[reappropriation|reappropriate]] the word to establish community and assert a political identity, with it becoming the preferred term to describe some academic disciplines and gaining use as a descriptor of non-heterosexual identities.&lt;ref name="oed"&gt;{{cite encyclopedia
 | year =2014
 | title = queer
 | encyclopedia = Oxford English Dictionary
 | publisher = Oxford University Press}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Queer'' may be used by those who reject traditional gender identities as a broader, less conformist, and deliberately ambiguous alternative to ''LGBT''.

The term is now used in the name of some academic disciplines, such as [[queer theory]],  to denote a general opposition to binary thinking. Queer arts,  queer cultural groups, and queer political groups are examples of expressions of queer identities.

Criticisms of ''queer'' include those who associate the term with its pejorative usage and those who associate it with political radicalism.

== Etymology ==


===''Strange'' meaning===
Entering the English language in the 16th century, ''queer'' originally meant ''strange'', ''odd'', ''peculiar'', or ''eccentric''. It might refer to something suspicious or "not quite right", or to a person with mild derangement or who exhibits socially inappropriate behaviour.&lt;ref name="oed"/&gt;&lt;ref name="mw"&gt;{{cite encyclopedia
 | year =2014
 | title = queer
 | encyclopedia = Merriam-Webster
 | publisher = Encyclopædia Britannica
 | url=http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/queer}}&lt;/ref&gt; A [[Northern English]] expression, "There's nowt so queer as folk," meaning, "There is nothing as strange as people," employs this meaning.

Related meanings of ''queer'' include a feeling of unwellness or something that is questionable or suspicious.&lt;ref name="oed"/&gt;&lt;ref name="mw"/&gt; The expression "in [[Queer Street]]" was used in the [[United Kingdom]] for someone in financial trouble. In the 1904 [[Sherlock Holmes]] story "[[The Adventure of the Second Stain]]", [[Inspector Lestrade]] threatens that a misbehaving constable will "find [himself] in Queer Street", i.e., lose his position.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Doyle |first=Arthur Conan |year=1904 |title= The Return of Sherlock Holmes|chapter=The Adventure of the Second Stain|url=http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/108 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===''Homosexual'' meaning===
By the time "The Adventure of the Second Stain" was published, the term was starting to gain a denotation of sexual deviance, referring to homosexual and/or effeminate males. An early recorded usage of the word in this sense was in an 1894 letter by [[John Sholto Douglas, 9th Marquess of Queensberry]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last= Foldy|first= Michael S. |year= 1997|title= The Trials of Oscar Wilde: Deviance, Morality, and Late-Victorian Society |publisher= Yale University Press|isbn= 9780300071122|page=22}}&lt;/ref&gt; Usage of ''queer'' as a derogatory term for effeminate gay males become prominent in the 20th century.&lt;ref name="oed"/&gt; The term was particularly applied to men who were believed to engage in receptive or passive [[Anal sex|anal]] or [[Oral sex|oral]] [[Sexual intercourse|sex]] with other men,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last= Robertson|first= Stephen|year= 2002|title=A Tale of Two Sexual Revolutions |journal= Australasian Journal of American Studies|publisher= Australia and New Zealand American Studies Association |volume= 21 |issue= 1 |pages= 98–110}}&lt;/ref&gt;  and those exhibiting non-traditional (e.g., [[transgender]]) gender behaviour.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Czyzselska |first= Jane|year= 1996 |title= untitled |journal= Pride 1996 Magazine|publisher= Pride Trust &amp; Gay Times|location = London|page= 15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Reappropriation===
Beginning in the late 1980s, the label ''queer'' began to be [[reappropriation|reappropriated]] from its pejorative use as a neutral or positive self-identifier by LGBT people.&lt;ref name="oed"/&gt; An early example of this usage by the LGBT community was by an organisation called [[Queer Nation]], which was formed in March 1990 and circulated an anonymous flier at the [[Gay Pride Parade (New York City)|New York Gay Pride Parade]] in June 1990 titled "Queers Read This".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.qrd.org/qrd/misc/text/queers.read.this|title= Queers Read This |last1= Queer Nation |date= June 1990}}&lt;/ref&gt; The flier included a passage explaining their adoption of the label ''queer'':{{quote|Ah, do we really have to use that word?  It's trouble. Every gay person has his or her own take on it. For some it means strange and eccentric and kind of mysterious.... And for others "queer" conjures up those awful memories of adolescent suffering... Well, yes, "gay" is great.  It has its place.  But when a lot of lesbians and gay men wake up in the morning we feel angry and disgusted, not gay.  So we've chosen to call ourselves queer. Using "queer" is a way of reminding us how we are perceived by the rest of the world.}}

The term may be capitalized when referring to an [[Identity (social science)|identity]] or community, rather than as an objective fact describing a person's desires, in a construction akin to the capitalized use of [[Deaf]].

In the late 2000s (decade) and early 2010s, a number of communities started to use the term, to represent  inclusivity of forms of sexuality, gender identities and [[intersex]] status inadequately represented by the [[LGBT]] acronym.

The "hip and iconic abbreviation 'Q'" has developed from common usage of ''queer'', particularly in the United States.&lt;ref name=Q&gt;" Queerbook, [http://inventorspot.com/articles/queerbook_whats_name_31251 What's In A Name?]" Retrieved on September 2, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Inclusivity and scope==
Because of the context in which it was reclaimed, ''queer'' has sociopolitical connotations, and is often preferred by those who are activists; by those who strongly reject traditional gender identities; by those who reject distinct [[sexual identity|sexual identities]] such as gay, lesbian, bisexual, and straight; and by those who see themselves as oppressed by the [[heteronormativity]] of the larger culture. In this usage it retains the historical connotation of "outside the bounds of normal society" and can be construed as "breaking the rules for sex and gender". It can be preferred because of its ambiguity, which allows queer-identifying people to avoid the sometimes strict boundaries that surround other labels.  In this context, ''queer'' is not strictly a synonym for ''[[LGBT]]'' as it creates a space for [[queer heterosexuality|queer heterosexuals]] as well as non-queer homosexuals.

The range of what ''queer'' includes varies. In addition to referring to LGBT-identifying people, it can also encompass: [[pansexual]], pomosexual,&lt;ref&gt;[http://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/pomosexual pomosexual] at Wiktionary.org&lt;/ref&gt; [[intersex]], [[genderqueer]], [[asexuality|asexual]] and [[autosexual]] people, as well as [[heteronormativity|gender normative heterosexuals]] whose sexual orientations or activities place them outside the heterosexual-defined mainstream, e.g., [[BDSM]] practitioners, or [[polyamory|polyamorous]] persons.

For some queer-identified people, part of the point of the term ''queer'' is that it simultaneously builds up and tears down boundaries of identity. For instance, among genderqueer people, who do not solidly identify with one particular gender, once solid gender roles have been torn down, it becomes difficult to situate sexual identity.  For some people, the non-specificity of the term is liberating. Queerness becomes a way to make a political move against heteronormativity while simultaneously refusing to engage in traditional [[Essentialism|essentialist]] identity politics.&lt;ref name=LESBIAN&gt;"Alphabet Soup: [http://thinkingaboutnow.wordpress.com/2010/02/01/alphabet-soup-labels-and-empowerment/ Labels and Empowerment]". Retrieved on September 2, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Queer academia==
{{Main|Queer studies|Queer theory}}
In academia, the term ''queer'' and the related verb ''[[queering]]'' broadly indicate the study of literature, discourse, academic fields, and other social and cultural areas from a non-heteronormative perspective. It often means studying a subject [[Resistant reading|against the grain]] from the perspective of [[gender studies]].

[[Queer studies]] is the study of issues relating to sexual orientation and gender identity usually focusing on LGBT people and cultures. Originally centered on [[LGBT history]] and [[literary theory]], the field has expanded to include the academic study of issues raised in [[biology]], [[sociology]],  [[anthropology]], [[history of science]], [[philosophy]], [[psychology]], [[sexology]], [[political science]], [[ethics]], and other fields by an examination of the identity, lives, history, and perception of queer people. Organizations such as the [[Irish Queer Archive]] attempt to collect and preserve history related to queer studies.

[[Queer theory]] is a field of [[post-structuralist]] [[critical theory]] that emerged in the early 1990s out of the fields of queer studies and [[women's studies]]. Applications of queer theory include [[queer theology]] and [[queer pedagogy]].

==Queer art==
The label ''queer'' is often applied to art movements, particularly cinema. [[New Queer Cinema]] was a movement in queer-themed independent filmmaking in the early 1990s. Modern queer film festivals include the [[Melbourne Queer Film Festival]]  and [[Mardi Gras Film Festival]] (run by Queer Screen) in Australia, the [[Mumbai Queer Film Festival]] in India, the [[Asian Queer Film Festival]] in Japan, and [[Queersicht]] in Switzerland. Chinese film director [[Cui Zi'en]] titled his 2008 documentary about homosexuality in China ''[[Queer China]]'', which premiered at the 2009 Beijing Queer Film Festival after previous attempts to hold a queer film festival were shut down by the government.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2009/06/18/gays-in-china-beijing-que_n_217486.html|title= Gays In China: Beijing Queer Film Festival Goes Off Without A Hitch|last1= Tran|first1= Tini|date= June 18, 2009|website= The World Post|accessdate=30 January 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Multidisciplinary queer arts festivals include the [[Outburst Queer Arts Festival Belfast]] in Northern Ireland, the [[Queer Arts Festival]] in Canada, and the [[National Queer Arts Festival]] in the United States.

Television shows that use ''queer'' in their titles include the UK series ''[[Queer as Folk (UK TV series)|Queer as Folk]]'' and its American-Canadian [[Queer as Folk (North American TV series)|remake of the same name]], ''[[Queer Eye]]'', and the cartoon ''[[Queer Duck]]''.

==Queer culture and politics==
Several [[LGBT social movements]] around the world use the identifier ''queer'', such as the [[Queer Cyprus Association]] in Cyprus and the [[Queer Youth Network]] in the United Kingdom. In India, [[pride parade]]s include [[Queer Azaadi Mumbai]] and the [[Delhi Queer Pride Parade]]. The use of ''queer'' and ''Q'' is also widespread in Australia, including national counselling and support service Qlife&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.qlife.org.au]&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Q News (Australian magazine)|Q News]].

Other social movements exist as offshoots of queer culture or combinations of queer identity with other views. Adherents of [[queer nationalism]] support the notion that the LGBT community forms a distinct people due to their unique culture and customs. [[Queercore]] (originally ''homocore'') is a cultural and social movement that began in the mid-1980s as an offshoot of [[Punk subculture|punk]] expressed in a do-it-yourself style through zines, music, writing, art and film.

The term [[queer migration]] is used to describe the movement of LGBTQ people around the world often to escape discrimination or ill treatment due to their orientation or gender expression. Organizations such as the [[Iranian Railroad for Queer Refugees]] attempt to assist individuals in such relocations.

==Controversial nature of the term==
The use of the term ''queer'' is not  uncontroversial. Many LGBT people refuse to use the word, and there are others who also do not use it.&lt;ref&gt;For example, see Drew Cordes [http://www.bilerico.com/2012/02/new_yorker_magazine_refuses_to_print_the_word_quee.php "New Yorker magazine refuses to use the word queer"]. Retrieved 29 January 2014.&lt;/ref&gt; There are several reasons for this.

* Some LGBT people disapprove of using ''queer'' as a catch-all because they consider it offensive, derisive or [[Self-deprecation|self-deprecating]], given its continuous use as a form of [[hate speech]] in English.&lt;ref&gt;Wisegeek, [http://www.wisegeek.org/is-queer-a-derogatory-word.htm "Is Queer a Derogatory Word?"] Retrieved 29 January 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;

* Other LGBT people resent the use of the word ''queer'' in this sense because they associate it with political radicalism. They also disagree with how the deliberate use of the epithet ''queer'' by political radicals has played a role in dividing the LGBT community by political opinion, class, gender, age, and so on. The controversy about the word also marks a social and political rift in the LGBT community between those (including civil-rights activists) who perceive themselves as "normal" and who wish to be seen as ordinary members of society and those who see themselves as separate, confrontational and not part of the ordinary social order.&lt;ref&gt;Joshua Gamson, [http://freeskoool.wikispaces.com/file/view/Gamson+Identity+Movements+Self+Destruct.pdf Must Identity Movements Self-Destruct? A Queer Dilemma], Social Problems, Vol. 42, No. 3 (Aug., 1995), pp. 390-407, University of California Press on behalf of the Society for the Study of Social Problems. Retrieved on 29 January 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;

* Some LGBT people avoid ''queer'' because they perceive it as faddish slang or academic jargon.

* For a number of reasons, some LGBT people do not see themselves as being members of the ''queer'' community.

== See also ==
* [[Gay Shame]]
* [[Heterosexism]]
* [[Homophobia]]
* [[Sexual minority]]
* [[Sexuality and gender identity-based cultures]]

==References==

=== Notes ===
{{Reflist}}

===Bibliography===
{{Refbegin}}
* Anon. "Queercore". ''i-D magazine'' No. 110; the sexuality issue. (1992).
* Crimp, D. ''AIDS DemoGraphics''. (1990).
* Katlin, T. "Slant: Queer Nation".  ''Artforum'', November 1990.  pp.&amp;nbsp;21–23.
* Tucker, S. "Gender, Fucking &amp; Utopia".  ''Social text'', Vol.9, No.1. (1992).
{{Refend}}

==External links==
{{Wiktionary|queer}}
* [http://www.glbthistory.org The Gay, Lesbian, Bisexual, Transgender Historical Society]

{{Navboxes
|list =
{{Sexual identities}}
{{LGBT |main=expanded}}
}}

[[Category:Queer| ]]
[[Category:Queer theory| ]]
[[Category:LGBT terms|Queer]]
[[Category:Reclaimed words]]
[[Category:Sexuality and gender-related slurs]]
[[Category:Homophobia]]
[[Category:English words]]

[[simple:Queer]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>