<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20051107193841|27643576" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="13831" pageid="13831" ns="0" title="Human rights"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-11-09T16:10:04Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Rights}}

'''Human rights''' refers to the concept of [[human beings]] as having universal [[rights]], or status, regardless of legal [[jurisdiction]], and likewise other localizing factors, such as [[ethnicity]] and [[nationality]]. 

The existence, validity and the content of human rights continue to be the subject to debate in philosophy and political science. However human rights are defined in [[international law]] &amp; covenants,  and further, in the domestic laws of many states. There is, however, a great deal of variance between how human rights norms are defined in these multiple contexts and how they are upheld in different local jurisdictions. 

Within particular states, "human rights" refer to safeguards for the individual against arbitrary use of power by the government regarding 1) the well being of individuals, 2) the freedom and autonomy of individuals, and 3) the representation of the human interest in government.
These rights commonly include the [[right to life]], the right to an adequate [[standard of living]], freedom from [[torture]] and other mistreatment, [[freedom of expression]], [[freedom of movement]], the right to [[self-determination]], the right to [[education]], and the right to participation in cultural and political life. These norms are based on the legal and political traditions of [[United Nations member states]] and are incorporated into [[international human rights instruments]] (see below).

With the exception of so called non-derogable human rights (the four most important are the right to life, the right to be free from slavery and the right to be free from retroactive application of  penal laws), most human rights can be limited or even pushed aside during times of war.[http://www.un.org/esa/socdev/enable/comp210.htm] Conduct in war is governed by [[International Humanitarian Law]].

==Human Rights in international law==

The [[1948]], the  [[Universal Declaration of Human Rights]] resolution was adopted virtually unanimously by the [[United Nations]] [[General Assembly]]. While not legally binding, it urged member nations to promote a number of human, civil, economic and social rights, asserting these rights are part of the "foundation of freedom, justice and peace in the world". The declaration limits the behavior of the state, which now has duties to the citizen ([[rights-duty duality]]). Efforts to create a  legally binding form of the charter led to disagreements between various states over which rights were acceptable. Thus, two different covenents, the [[International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights]] (opened for signature 1966, entered into force March 23, 1976) [http://www.unhchr.ch/html/menu3/b/a_ccpr.htm] and the [[International Covenant on Economic, Social and Cultural Rights]] (opened for signature 1966, entered into force January 3, 1976) [http://www.unhchr.ch/html/menu3/b/a_cescr.htm] were created which bind those states that ratify them to protect the rights listed in the respective covenant. Together these three documents constitute the International Bill of Human Rights. There have also been a number of other conventions regarding particular rights, including the
*[[Convention on the Prevention and Punishment of the Crime of Genocide]] (entry into force: 1951) [http://www.unhchr.ch/html/menu3/b/p_genoci.htm]
*[[UN Convention Against Torture|Convention against Torture]] (entry into force: 1984) [http://www.unhchr.ch/html/menu3/b/h_cat39.htm]
*[[Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Racial Discrimination]] (entry into force: 1969) [http://www.unhchr.ch/html/menu3/b/d_icerd.htm]
*[[Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination Against Women]] (entry into force: 1981) [http://www.un.org/womenwatch/daw/cedaw/frame.htm]
*[[Convention on the Rights of the Child]] (entry into force: 1989) [http://www.unicef.org/crc/crc.htm]
*[[Rome Statute|Rome Statute of the International Criminal Court]] (entry into force: 2002)

A modern interpretation of the original Declaration of Human Rights was made in the [[Vienna Declaration and Programme of Action]][http://www.ohchr.org/english/law/vienna.htm], adopted by the World Conference on Human Rights in 1993. The degree of unanimity over these conventions, in terms of how many and which countries have ratified them vary, as does the degree to which they are respected by various states. The UN has set up a number of bodies to monitor and study human rights, under the leadership of the [[UN High Commissioner for Human Rights]] (HCHR). 

There are also many regional agreements and organisations governing human rights including the [[European Court of Human Rights]], the only international court with jurisdiction to deal with cases brought by individuals (not states). the [[African Commission on Human and Peoples' Rights]], [[Inter-American Commission on Human Rights]] and the [[Inter-American Court of Human Rights]].

==Types of human rights==

Human rights are typically divided into two categories: [[negative right|negative human rights]] (rights to be free from) and [[positive right|positive human rights]] (rights to), although other categorizations exist. Negative human rights, which follow mainly from the Anglo-American legal tradition, denote actions that a government should not take. These are codified in the [[United States Bill of Rights]], the [[English Bill of Rights]] and the [[Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms]] and include freedoms of [[freedom of speech|speech]], [[freedom of religion|religion]] and [[freedom of assembly|assembly]].

Positive human rights follow mainly from the [[Jean-Jacques Rousseau|Rousseauian]] Continental European legal tradition, denote rights that the state is obliged to protect and provide. Examples of such rights include: the rights to education, to a livelihood, and to legal equality. Positive rights have been codified in the Universal Declaration of Human Rights and in many 20th-century [[list of national constitutions|constitutions]].

A categorization offered by [[Karel Vasak]] is the three generations of human rights: first-generation civil and political rights (right to life and political participation), second-generation economic, social and cultural rights (right to subsistence) and third-generation solidarity rights (right to peace, right to clean environment). Out of these generations, the third generation is the most debated and lacks both legal and political recognition.

Some theorists discredit these divisions by claiming that rights are interconnected. Arguably, for example, basic education is necessary for the right to political participation.

==History of human rights==

The best-known histories of the human rights movement tend to begin with the ancient [[religion]]s and societies and show the evolution of concepts and institutions of human rights across civilizations. The roots of the notion of Human Rights can be drawn as far back as the [[ancient philosophy|Ancients]] (the role of the individual in the state) but the idea of civil and political rights stems from liberal freedoms advocated by [[John Stuart Mill]] in ''[[On Liberty]]''. The concepts of economic, social and cultural Rights can be traced back to [[Hegel]]'s ''[[Elements of the Philosophy of Right]]''.

The origin of modern positive rights in international law may be traced to the creation of the [[International Labour Organization]] in [[1919]] as a Western response to the [[socialism|socialist ideology]] of the [[Russian Revolution of 1917]].

==Philosophical basis of human rights==

Numerous theoretical approaches have been advanced to explain how human rights become part of social expectations. The biological theory considers the comparative reproductive advantage of human social behavior based on empathy and altruism in the context of natural selection. Other theories hold that human rights codify moral behavior, which is a human, social product developed by a process of biological and social evolution (associated with [[David Hume|Hume]]) or as a sociological pattern of rule setting (as in the sociological theory of law and the work of [[Max Weber|Weber]]). This approach includes the notion that individuals in a society accept rules from legitimate authority in exchange for security and economic advantage (as in [[John Rawls|Rawls]]).

[[Natural law|Natural law theories]] base human rights on the “natural” moral order based on religious precepts, the assumed common understandings of justice, or the belief that moral behavior is a set of objectively valid prescriptions. In legend, literature, religion and political thought, justice (and eventually the concept of human rights) became socially constructed over time into complex webs of social interaction striving toward a social order in which human beings are treated fairly. Religious societies tend to try to justify human rights through religious arguments. For example, [[liberal movements within Islam]] have tried to use the story of Adam in the [[Qur'an]] to support human rights in a Muslim context.

Other theories are based on human agency, positing such constructs for agreement to rules on the utilitarian principles mediated by public reasoning. The social evolution model is based on human needs and struggle that incorporates an analysis of the norm-creating process. Values become norms through the constitutive process of authoritative decision-making. Such norms may take the form of law through a particular form of authoritative decision making of institutions associated with a legal system. It is the process of public reasoning through human rights norm-creating that progressively weeds out the culturally bound behaviors that are inconsistent with contemporary human rights. In this sense, culturally particular norms adapt to evolving human rights standards as defined in [[list of national constitutions|national constitutions]] and [[international human rights instruments]].

Ultimately, the term "human rights" is often itself an appeal to a transcendent principle, without basing it on existing legal concepts. The term "[[humanism]]" refers to the developing doctrine of such [[universality|universally applicable]] values.

Some authors argue that nationalism and realism weaken human rights, while individualism and cosmopolitanism strengthen them.  This is argued by Klitou in his book "The Friends and Foes of Human Rights." Klitou also outlines the need for a "human identity" in order to empower human rights law.

==Western view of human rights==
In the [[Political philosophy|Western political tradition]], human rights are held to be "inalienable" and to belong to all humans. They are necessary for freedom and the maintenance of a "reasonable" quality of life. If a right is inalienable, that means it cannot be bestowed, granted, bartered, or sold away (e.g., one cannot sell oneself into [[slavery]]). Rights may also be [[non-derogable]] (not limited in times of national emergency); these often include the right to life, the right to be prosecuted only according to the laws that are in existence at the time of the offense, the right to be free from slavery, and the right to be free from torture.

==Human rights controversies==

There are a number of controversies regarding human rights including:
#Are human rights political, moral or legal entities (or all three at the same time)?
#Is there or should there be a hierarchy of human rights?
#Do human rights impede on [[sovereignty|state sovereignty]]? What if the state itself has ratified international conventions?
#Should human rights be used as a context for economic or military intervention? (Often leads to a worsening of the human rights situation in the target country)
#Questions of [[cultural relativism]]&amp;mdash;e.g. "Political participation is not a part of African culture. Who are you to say that we should have political participation?" These arguments can also be made on religious basis: e.g., "In our religion marriages have always been arranged; why should we not continue this practice?" Some arguments claim that human rights policies are a form of [[cultural imperialism]] in which powerful countries dictate which rights they consider most important to less powerful countries. The increasing number of third-world states that are party to international human rights treaties has made these arguments weaker, but they have not disappeared altogether.
#Who should hold the moral duty to uphold rights? For civil and political rights, many would answer 'the state'. But in practice, it is frequently one's fellow citizens and civil society who need to shoulder this responsibility. It is not quite so clear who should be responsible for promoting economic, social and cultural rights (do we have a global duty?). This debate mirrors debates between [[communitarianism]] and [[cosmopolitanism]].
#Which rights should be defined as fundamental human rights? Should all human rights be considered equal?

== See also ==

===Similar topics===
*[[Civil rights]]
*[[Inalienable rights]]
*[[Natural rights]]
*[[Rights]]

=== General ===
*[[International human rights instruments]]
*[[Human rights abuse]]
*[[Three generations of human rights]]
*[[Human rights education]]
*[[Social justice]]
*[[Slavery]]
*[[Democratic ideals]]
*[[International Day of the Disappeared]]

=== Human rights organizations ===

*[[Amnesty International]]
*[[ARTICLE 19]]
*[[Carter Center]]
*[[Forum 18]]
*[[Freedom House]]
*[[Human Rights Campaign]]
*[[Human Rights Watch]]
*[[International Freedom of Expression Exchange]]
*[[International Helsinki Federation for Human Rights]]
*[[Memorial (society)]]
*[[Montagnard Foundation]]
*[[Network Against Prohibition]]
*[[Office of the United Nations High Commissioner for Human Rights]]
*[[Southern Poverty Law Center]]
*[[Bahrain Centre for Human Rights]]

=== Country-specific articles ===
====Africa====
*[[South Africa]]: [[Human rights in South Africa]]
*[[Sudan]]: [[Human rights in Sudan]]
*[[Uganda]]: [[Human rights in Uganda]]
*[[Zimbabwe]]: [[Human rights in Zimbabwe]]
**Note: Citizens of the African nations are provided supranational human rights protection by the [[African Commission on Human and Peoples' Rights]].

====Americas====
*[[Brazil]]: [[Human rights in Brazil]]
*[[Canada]]: [[Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms]] makes mention of essential human rights
*[[Cuba]]: [[Human rights in Cuba]]
*[[Mexico]]: [[Human rights in Mexico]]
*[[Peru]]: [[APRODEH]]
*[[United States|USA]]: [[Human rights in the United States]]
**Note: Citizens of the American nations enjoy varying degrees of supranational human rights protection from the [[Inter-American Commission on Human Rights]] and the [[Inter-American Court of Human Rights]].
&lt;!-- *[[Canada]]: Canada attempts to resolve tension between international human rights norms and sovereignty by allowing legislative primacy on a temporary and renewable basis [[notwithstanding clause|notwithstanding]] that the law infringes the [[Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms]]. *** What does this sentence mean? Which law is it that is infringing on the charter?--The laws enacted under legislative primacy? --&gt;
&lt;!-- 
answer to above, and for further comments and edits
The notwithstanding clause is an "override" clause in principle. If the provinces want to make a law that conflict with the Charter, the provinces use the notwithstanding clause to override the Charter. This ensures that the law is active, although it conflicts with the Charter. You can try researching Quebec's (a province) 101 bill. Also Quebec's law that makes Quebec's only official language French, in contrast to English and French in all the other provinces in Canada.
--&gt;

====Asia====
*[[Cambodia]]: [[Human rights in Cambodia]]
*[[Iran]]: [[Human rights in Iran]]
*[[Iraq]]: [[Human rights in Iraq]]
*[[Japan]]: [[Human rights in Japan]]
*[[People's Republic of China|PRC]]: [[Human rights in the People's Republic of China]]
*[[Mongolia]]: [[Human rights in Mongolia]]
*[[Myanmar]] (Burma): [[Human rights in Myanmar]]
*[[North Korea]]: [[Human rights in North Korea]]
*[[Russia]]: [[Human rights in Russia]]
*[[Saudi Arabia]]: [[Human rights in Saudi Arabia]]
*[[Sri Lanka]]: [[Human rights in Sri Lanka]]
*[[Turkmenistan]]: [[Human rights in Turkmenistan]]

====Europe====
* ''See [[Human rights in Europe]]''
** Note: The most powerful human rights organization is the [[European Court of Human Rights]], which is the only international court with jurisdiction to deal with cases brought by individuals (not states).

====Oceania====
*[[Australia]]: [[Human rights in Australia]]

==References==
* Steiner, Henry J. &amp; Alston, Philip. (1996). ''International Human Rights in Context: Law, Politics, Morals.'' Oxford: Clarendon Press. ISBN 019825437X
* Donnelly, Jack. (2003). ''Universal Human Rights in Theory &amp; Practice.'' 2nd ed. Ithaca &amp; London: Cornell University Press.
* Forsythe, David P. (2000). ''Human Rights in International Relations.'' Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.
* Ignatieff, Michael. ''Human Rights as Politics and Idolatry.'' Princeton &amp; Oxford: Princeton University Press.
* Shute, Stephen &amp; Hurley, Susan (eds.). (1993). ''On Human Rights: The Oxford Amnesty Lectures.'' New York: BasicBooks.
* Sunga, Lyal S. (1992) Individual Responsibility in International Law for Serious Human Rights Violations, Nijhoff Publishers.

==External links==
=== Information ===
*[http://www.betterworldlinks.org/menschenrechte.htm Better World Links] Biggest Link List on Human Rights
*[http://www.rightsphilosophyforum.org/ Rights Philosophy Forum]
*[http://www.state.gov/g/drl/hr/c1470.htm Country reports on human rights] from the U.S. Department of State
*[http://www.ngochr.org/custom/index.php ngoCHR.org] &amp;ndash; Volunteer reporting on the United Nations Commission on Human Rights
*[http://www.le.ac.uk/library/hmb11/law/humanr.html University of Leicester, UK, list of sources and links.]
*[http://www.tamilnation.org/humanrights.htm Introduction to Human Rights &amp; Humanitarian Law]
*[http://www.detroitfocus.org/Issues/0410/CryForCompassion/index.html Photojournalist's approach to human rights in Sudan]
*[http://www.liberalislam.net/adam.html A Muslim approach to human rights] from LiberalIslam.net
*[http://www.missionandjustice.org Mission and Justice] &amp;ndash; Human Rights, Justice and Peace news from the Asia Pacific region.
*[http://www.tamilnation.org/humanrights/tamil.htm Sri Lanka &amp;ndash; Human Rights of the Tamil People]
*[http://www.childrensrights.ie/convention.php Children's Rights Alliance]
*[http://www.yihrc.org Human rights development in Asia]
*[http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/rights-human/ Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy entry]
*[http://www1.umn.edu/humanrts University of Minnesota Human Rights Library]
*[http://www.ifex.org International Freedom of Expression Exchange] - Monitoring censorship around the world
*[http://www.newsxs.com/en/preset/324 Human Rights, news headlines by NewsXS]. Aggregated news and rss-feed.

=== Human rights organizations ===
*[http://www.betterworldlinks.org/book20b.htm Better World Links on Human Rights Organizations]
*[http://www.antislavery.org Anti Slavery]
*[http://www.ahrchk.net Asian Human Rights Commission]
*[http://www.justicefortheworld.org Justice For The World]
*[http://www.globalrights.org Global Rights: Partners for Justice]
*[http://www.olympicwatch.org/ Olympic Watch: Human Rights in China and Beijing 2008]
*[http://www.humanrights.gov.au Australian Human Rights and Equal Opportunity Commission]
*[http://www.fian.org FoodFirst Information and Action Network]
*[http://www.ensaaf.org ENSAAF: Fighting Impunity in India]
*[http://www.punjabjustice.org Committee for Information and Initiative on Punjab]


[[Category:Human rights]]
[[Category:International relations]]
[[Category:Rights]]

[[ar:حقوق الإنسان]]
[[zh-min-nan:Jîn-kôan]]
[[cs:Lidská práva]]
[[da:Menneskerettighederne]]
[[de:Menschenrechte]]
[[es:Derechos humanos]]
[[fr:Droits de l'Homme]]
[[id:Hak Asasi Manusia]]
[[is:Mannréttindi]]
[[it:Diritti umani]]
[[he:זכויות האדם]]
[[lt:Žmogaus teisės]]
[[lv:Cilvēktiesības]]
[[nl:Rechten van de Mens]]
[[ja:人権]]
[[no:Menneskerettigheter]]
[[pl:Prawa człowieka]]
[[pt:Direitos humanos]]
[[ru:Права человека]]
[[sk:Ľudské práva]]
[[fi:Luonnonoikeusteoria]]
[[sv:De mänskliga rättigheterna]]
[[zh:人权]]
[[simple:Human rights]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>