<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20071114083924|171394250" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="13831" pageid="13831" ns="0" title="Human rights"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-11-14T09:02:34Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[Image:Magna Carta.jpg|200px|thumb|right|The ''[[Magna Carta]]'' or "Great Charter" was the world's first document containing commitments by a [[sovereign]] to his people to respect certain [[Law|legal]] rights]]
'''Human rights''' refers to "the basic rights and freedoms to which all humans are entitled, often held to include the right to life and liberty, freedom of thought and expression, and equality before the law."&lt;ref&gt;The American Heritage Dictionary of the English Language, Fourth Edition&lt;/ref&gt; The [[United Nations]] [[Universal Declaration of Human Rights]] states, "All human beings are born free and equal in dignity and rights. They are endowed with reason and conscience and should act towards one another in a spirit of brotherhood."&lt;ref&gt;UNIVERSAL DECLARATION OF HUMAN RIGHTS adopted by General Assembly resolution 217 A (III) of 10 December 1948. http://www.unhchr.ch/html/menu6/2/fs2.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

The idea of human rights descended from the philosophical idea of [[natural rights]] which are considered to exist even when trampled by governments or society;&lt;ref&gt;Natural rights, The Columbia Electronic Encyclopedia (2005) http://columbia.thefreedictionary.com/Natural+rights&lt;/ref&gt; some recognize virtually no difference between the two and regard both as labels for the same thing, while others choose to keep the terms separate to eliminate association with some features traditionally associated with natural rights.&lt;ref&gt;Peter Jones. Rights. Palgrave Macmillan, 1994, p. 73&lt;/ref&gt; Natural rights, in particular, are rights of the [[individual]], and are considered beyond the authority of a future government or [[Intergovernmental organizations|international body]] to dismiss. [[John Locke]] is perhaps the most prominent philosopher that developed this theory.&lt;ref&gt;Natural rights, The Columbia Electronic Encyclopedia (2005) http://columbia.thefreedictionary.com/Natural+rights&lt;/ref&gt; 

==Human rights sources==
===The United Nations===
{{main|United Nations|Universal Declaration on Human Rights|International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights|International Covenant on Economic, Social and Cultural Rights}}

[[Image:Unpicture.jpg|thumb|right|The UN General Assembly]]
The United Nations is the only international entity with [[jurisdiction]] for universal human rights legislation. All UN organs have advisory roles to the [[Security Council]]. Article 1-3 of the [[United Nations Charter]] states "To achieve international co-operation in solving international problems of an economic, social, cultural, or humanitarian character, and in promoting and encouraging respect for [[human rights]] and for fundamental freedoms for all without distinction as to race, sex, language, or religion."

The [[United Nations Human Rights Council]] is involved with the investigation into violations of human rights.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.un.org/apps/news/infocusRel.asp?infocusID=114&amp;Body=human%20rights%20council&amp;Body1= United Nations Rights Council Page]&lt;/ref&gt; The [[International Court of Justice]] (ICJ) is the principle judicial organ of the [[United Nations]].&lt;ref&gt;International Court of Justice homepage http://www.icj-cij.org/&lt;/ref&gt;

===Europe===
{{main|European Convention on Human Rights|European Social Charter|Charter of Fundamental Rights of the European Union}}
The [[European Convention on Human Rights]] defines and guarantees since 1950 human rights and fundamental freedoms in Europe. All 47 member states of the [[Council of Europe]] have signed this Convention and are therefore under the jurisdiction of the [[European Court of Human Rights]] in Strasbourg. In order to prevent torture and inhuman or degrading treatment (see Article 3 of the Convention), the [[European Committee for the Prevention of Torture]] has been set up. 

[[Image:European Court of Human Rights.jpg|333px|thumb|left|European Court of Human Rights in [[Strasbourg]]]]

Human rights commonly include:
*''[[right to life|security rights]]'' that prohibit crimes such as [[murder]]/"enforced" [[involuntary suicide]], [[massacre]], [[torture]] and [[rape]]
*''[[liberty]] rights'' that protect freedoms in areas such as [[freedom of conscience|belief]] and [[freedom of religion|religion]], [[freedom of association|association]], [[freedom of assembly|assembling]] and [[freedom of movement|movement]]
*''[[political]] rights'' that protect the liberty to participate in politics by [[freedom of expression|expressing themselves]], [[right to petition|protesting]], participating in a [[republic]]
*''[[due process]] rights'' that protect against abuses of the legal system such as [[arrest]] and [[imprisonment]] without [[trial]], secret trials and excessive punishments
*''[[Social equality|equality]] rights'' that guarantee equal [[citizenship]], equality before the [[law]] and [[discrimination|nondiscrimination]]
*''[[Social welfare provision|welfare]] rights'' (also known as economic rights) that require the provision of, e.g., [[education]], paid holidays, and protections against severe [[poverty]] and [[starvation]] 
*''[[collective rights|group rights]]''

==History of human rights==
===Human Rights in the ancient world===
[[Ur-Nammu]], king of [[Ur]] in ca. 2050 BC created the [[Code of Ur-Nammu]], the oldest legal codex that survives today. Several other sets of laws were created in [[Mesopotamia]] including the [[Code of Hammurabi]] (ca. 1780 BC), one of the best preserved examples of this type of document. It shows rules, and punishments if those rules are broken, on a variety of matters including [[Legal rights of women in history|women's rights]], [[children's rights]] and [[slavery|slave rights]].

The prefaces of these codes invoked the Mesopotamian gods for divine sanction. Societies have often derived the origins of human rights in religious documents. The [[Vedas]], the [[Bible]], the [[Qur'an]] and the [[Analects of Confucius]] are some of the oldest written sources that address questions of people's duties, rights, and responsibilities.

===Persian Empire===
{{see also|Persian Empire}}
[[Image:Cyrus cilinder.jpg|left|thumb|The [[Cyrus cylinder]] of [[Cyrus the Great]], founder of the [[Achaemenid Empire|Achaemenid]] [[Persian Empire]] ]]
The [[Achaemenid Empire|Achaemenid]] [[Persian Empire]] of [[History of Iran|ancient Iran]] established unprecedented principles of human rights in the [[6th century BC]] under [[Cyrus the Great]]. After his conquest of [[Babylon]] in [[539 BC]], the king issued the [[Cyrus cylinder]], discovered in [[1879]] and recognized by many today as the first human rights document. The cylinder declared that citizens of the empire would be allowed to practice their [[freedom of religion|religious beliefs freely]]. It also abolished [[slavery]], so all the palaces of the kings of Persia were built by paid workers in an era where slaves typically did such work.&lt;ref name="Engineering an Empire: Persian Empire"&gt; [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=eKN-gZuSH2o Engineering an Empire: Persian Empire]&lt;/ref&gt; These two reforms were reflected in the biblical books of [[Books of Chronicles|Chronicles]], [[Book of Nehemiah|Nehemiah]], and [[Book of Ezra|Ezra]], which state that Cyrus released the followers of [[Judaism]] from slavery and allowed them to migrate back to their land. The cylinder now lies in the [[British Museum]], and a replica is kept at the [[United Nations headquarters]].

In the Persian Empire, citizens of all religions and [[ethnic group]]s were also given the same rights, while women had the same rights as men. The Cyrus cylinder also documents the protection of the rights to [[liberty]] and [[security]], [[freedom of movement]], the right of [[property]], and [[economic rights|economic]] and [[social rights]].&lt;ref&gt;Arthur Henry Robertson, John Graham Merrills (1996). ''Human Rights in the World: An Introduction to the Study of the International Protection of Human Rights''. [[Manchester University Press]]. ISBN 0719049237.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Maurya Empire===
{{seealso|Maurya Empire}}
The [[Maurya Empire]] of [[History of India|ancient India]] established unprecedented principles of civil rights in the [[3rd century BC]] under [[Ashoka the Great]]. After his brutal conquest of [[Kalinga]] in circa [[265 BC]], he felt remorse for what he had done, and as a result, adopted [[Buddhism]]. From then, Ashoka, who had been described as "the cruel Ashoka" eventually came to be known as "the pious Ashoka". During his reign, he pursued an official policy of [[nonviolence]] (''[[ahimsa]]'') and the protection of human rights, as his chief concern was the happiness of his subjects.&lt;ref&gt;O. P. Chauhan (2004). ''Human Rights: Promotion and Protection''. Anmol Publications PVT. LTD. ISBN 812612119X.&lt;/ref&gt; The unnecessary slaughter or mutilation of animals was immediately abolished, such as [[sport]] [[hunting]] and [[livestock branding|branding]]. Ashoka also showed mercy to those imprisoned, allowing them outside one day each year, and offered common citizens free education at [[university|universities]]. He treated his subjects as equals regardless of their religion, politics or [[caste]], and constructed free [[hospital]]s for both humans and animals. Ashoka defined the main principles of nonviolence, [[tolerance]] of all [[sect]]s and opinions, [[obedience]] to parents, [[respect]] for teachers and [[priest]]s, being [[liberal]] towards friends, humane treatment of [[servant (domestic)|servant]]s, and [[generosity]] towards all. These reforms are described in the [[Edicts of Ashoka]].

In the Maurya Empire, citizens of all religions and ethnic groups also had rights to [[Freedom (political)|freedom]], [[tolerance]], and [[equality]]. The need for tolerance on an [[Egalitarianism|egalitarian]] basis can be found in the Edicts of Ashoka, which emphasize the importance of tolerance in public policy by the government. The slaughter or capture of [[Prisoner of war|prisoners of war]] was also condemned by Ashoka.&lt;ref&gt;[[Amartya Sen]] (1997). ''Human Rights and Asian Values''. ISBN 0-87641-151-0.&lt;/ref&gt; Slavery was also non-existent in ancient India.&lt;ref&gt;[[Arrian]], ''[[Indica (Arrian)|Indica]]'', "This also is remarkable in [[History of India|India]], that all Indians are free, and no Indian at all is a slave. In this the Indians agree with the [[Lacedaemonian]]s. Yet the Lacedaemonians have [[Helot]]s for slaves, who perform the duties of slaves; but the Indians have no slaves at all, much less is any Indian a whore."&lt;/ref&gt;

===Early Islamic Caliphate===
{{main|Early reforms under Islam}}

Many [[reform]]s in human rights took place under [[Islam]] between [[610]] and [[661]], including the period of [[Muhammad]]'s mission and the rule of the [[Rashidun|four immediate successors]] who established the [[Rashidun Empire|Rashidun Caliphate]]. Historians generally agree that Muhammad preached against what he saw as the social evils of his day,&lt;ref&gt; ''Encyclopedia of world history'' (1998), p.452, [[Oxford University Press]] &lt;/ref&gt; and that Islamic social reforms in areas such as [[social security]], [[family]] structure, [[slavery]], and the rights of [[women]] and [[Ethnic minority|ethnic minorities]] improved on what was present in existing [[Arab]] society at the time.&lt;ref name="LewisNYRB"&gt;{{cite news | last=Lewis | first=Bernard | title=Islamic Revolution |date=January 21, 1998 | publisher=The New York Review of Books | url=http://www.nybooks.com/articles/4557}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Watt (1974), p.234&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Robinson (2004) p.21&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Esposito (1998), p. 98&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;"Ak̲h̲lāḳ", ''Encyclopaedia of Islam Online''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Nancy"&gt;Nancy Gallagher, Encyclopedia of Women &amp; Islamic Cultures, Infanticide and Abandonment of Female Children &lt;/ref&gt; For example, according to [[Bernard Lewis]], Islam "from the first denounced [[Aristocracy|aristocratic]] privilege, rejected [[hierarchy]], and adopted a formula of the [[career]] open to the talents."&lt;ref name="LewisNYRB"/&gt; [[John Esposito]] sees Muhammad as a reformer who condemned practices of the pagan Arabs such as [[female infanticide]], [[exploitation]] of the poor, [[usury]], [[murder]], false [[contract]]s, and [[theft]].&lt;ref&gt;Esposito, Islam the Straight Path, p. 79, Oxford University Press &lt;/ref&gt; [[Bernard Lewis]] believes that the egalitarian nature of Islam "represented a very considerable advance on the practice of both the [[Greco-Roman]] and the [[Persian Empire|ancient Iranian]] world."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | last=Lewis | first=Bernard | title=Islamic Revolution | date=January 21, 1998 | publisher=The New York Review of Books | url=http://www.nybooks.com/articles/4557}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Muhammad made it the responsibility of the Islamic government to provide food and clothing, on a reasonable basis, to [[Prisoners of war|captives]], regardless of their religion. If the prisoners were in the custody of a person, then the responsibility was on the individual.&lt;ref&gt;Maududi (1967), Introduction of Ad-Dahr, "Period of revelation", pg. 159&lt;/ref&gt; Lewis states that Islam brought two major changes to ancient slavery which were to have far-reaching consequences. "One of these was the presumption of freedom; the other, the ban on the enslavement of free persons except in strictly defined circumstances," Lewis continues. The position of the Arabian slave was "enormously improved": the Arabian slave "was now no longer merely a chattel but was also a human being with a certain religious and hence a [[social status]] and with certain quasi-legal rights."&lt;ref name=Lewis&gt; Bernard Lewis, [[Race and Slavery in the Middle East]], Oxford Univ Press 1994, [http://www.fordham.edu/halsall/med/lewis1.html chapter 1] &lt;/ref&gt;

[[John Esposito|Esposito]] states that reforms in [[women's rights]] affected [[marriage]], [[divorce]], and [[inheritance]].&lt;ref name="Espos"&gt; John Esposito, ''Islam: The Straight Path'' p. 79 &lt;/ref&gt; Women were not accorded with such legal status in other cultures, including the West, until centuries later.&lt;ref&gt; Encyclopedia of religion, second edition, Lindsay Jones, p.6224, ISBN 0-02-865742-X &lt;/ref&gt; ''The Oxford Dictionary of Islam'' states that the general improvement of the status of Arab women included prohibition of [[female infanticide]] and recognizing women's full personhood.&lt;ref name="OxfordDicT"&gt;''The Oxford Dictionary of Islam'' (2003), p. 339&lt;/ref&gt; "The [[dowry]], previously regarded as a bride-price paid to the father, became a nuptial gift retained by the wife as part of her personal property."&lt;ref name="majid"&gt;[[Majid Khadduri]], ''Marriage in Islamic Law: The Modernist Viewpoints'', American Journal of [[Comparative law|Comparative Law]], Vol. 26, No. 2, pp. 213-218 &lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Espos"/&gt; Under Islamic law, marriage was no longer viewed as a "status" but rather as a "[[contract]]", in which the woman's consent was imperative.&lt;ref name="majid"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Espos"/&gt;&lt;ref name="OxfordDicT"/&gt; "Women were given inheritance rights in a [[patriarchal society]] that had previously restricted inheritance to male relatives."&lt;ref name="Espos"/&gt; [[Annemarie Schimmel]] states that "compared to the pre-Islamic position of women, Islamic legislation meant an enormous progress; the woman has the right, at least according to the letter of the law, to administer the wealth she has brought into the family or has earned by her own work."&lt;ref name = "Schimmel"&gt; Annemarie Schimmel, ''Islam-: An Introduction'', p.65, SUNY Press, 1992 &lt;/ref&gt; [[William Montgomery Watt]] states that Muhammad, in the historical context of his time, can be seen as a figure who testified on behalf of [[women’s rights]] and improved things considerably. Watt explains: "At the time Islam began, the conditions of women were terrible - they had no [[Property|right to own property]], were supposed to be the property of the man, and if the man died everything went to his sons." Muhammad, however, by "instituting rights of property ownership, inheritance, education and divorce, gave women certain basic safeguards."&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.alastairmcintosh.com/articles/2000_watt.htm Interview: William Montgomery Watt], by [[Bashir Mann|Bashir Maan]] &amp; [[Alastair McIntosh]] (1999). A paper using the material on this interview was published in The Coracle, [[Iona Community|the Iona Community]], summer 2000, issue 3:51, pp. 8-11.&lt;/ref&gt; Haddad and [[John Esposito|Esposito]] state that "Muhammad granted women rights and privileges in the sphere of [[Family Life|family life]], marriage, education, and economic endeavors, rights that help improve women's status in society."&lt;ref&gt; Yvonne Yazbeck Haddad, John L. Esposito, ''Islam, Gender, and Social Change'', Oxford University Press US, 2004, p.163 &lt;/ref&gt;

Sociologist [[Robert Bellah]] (''Beyond belief'') argues that Islam in its seventh-century origins was, for its time and place, "remarkably modern...in the high degree of commitment, involvement, and participation expected from the rank-and-file members of the community."  This because, he argues, that Islam emphasized on the equality of all Muslims, where leadership positions were open to all. Dale Eickelman writes that Bellah suggests "the early Islamic community placed a particular value on individuals, as opposed to collective or group responsibility."&lt;ref&gt; “Social Sciences and the Qur’an,” in Encyclopedia of the Qur’an, vol. 5, ed. Jane Dammen McAuliffe. Leiden: Brill, pp. 66-76. &lt;/ref&gt;

===Human rights in early modern era===
[[Image:Us declaration independence.jpg|right|thumb|200px|''U.S. Declaration of Independence'' ratified by the [[Continental Congress]] on [[July 4]], [[1776]]]]
The conquest of the Americas in the 16th century by the Spanish resulted in vigorous debate about human rights in Spain. The debate from 1550-51 between Las Casas and Juan Ginés de Sepúlveda at Valladolid was probably the first on the topic of human rights in European history. Several [[17th century|17th]] and [[18th century]] European philosophers, most notably [[John Locke]], developed the concept of ''[[natural rights]]'', the notion that people possess certain rights by virtue of being human. Though Locke believed natural rights were derived from divinity since [[human being|humans]] were creations of [[God]], his ideas were important in the development of the modern notion of rights. Lockean natural rights did not rely on citizenship nor any law of the state, nor were they necessarily limited to one particular ethnic, cultural or religious group.

Two major revolutions occurred that century in the [[United States]] (1776) and in [[France]] (1789). The [[Virginia Declaration of Rights]] of 1776 sets up a number of fundamental rights and freedoms. The later [[United States Declaration of Independence]] includes concepts of natural rights and famously states "that all men are created equal, that they are endowed by their creator with certain unalienable rights, that among these are life, liberty and the pursuit of happiness." Similarly, the [[Declaration of the Rights of Man and of the Citizen]] defines a set of individual and collective rights of the people. These are held to be universal - not only to French citizens but to ''all men without exception''.

===Modern Era===
[[Image:Declaration of Human Rights.jpg|left|thumb|200px|''Declaration of the Rights of Man and of the Citizen'' approved by the National Assembly of France, [[August 26]], [[1789]]]]
Philosophers such as [[Thomas Paine]], [[John Stuart Mill]] and [[Hegel]] expanded on the theme of [[Universality (philosophy)|universality]] during the 18th and [[19th century|19th]] centuries. In [[1831]] [[William Lloyd Garrison]] wrote in a newspaper called ''[[The Liberator]]'' that he was trying to enlist his readers in "the great cause of human rights"&lt;ref&gt;Mayer, Henry "All on Fire: William Lloyd Garrison and the Abolition of Slavery" St. Martin's Press, 1998, p. 110&lt;/ref&gt; so the term ''human rights'' probably came into use sometime between Paine's ''The Rights of Man'' and Garrison's publication. In 1849 a contemporary, [[Henry David Thoreau]], wrote about human rights in his treatise ''[[Civil Disobedience (Thoreau)|On the Duty of Civil Disobedience]]'' [http://www.cs.indiana.edu/statecraft/civ.dis.html] which was later influential on human rights and civil rights thinkers. United States [[David Davis (Supreme Court justice)|Supreme Court Justice David Davis]], in his [[1867]] opinion for [[Ex Parte Milligan]], wrote "By the protection of the law, human rights are secured; withdraw that protection and they are at the mercy of wicked rulers or the clamor of an excited people."&lt;ref&gt;''Ex Parte Milligan'', 71 U.S. 2, 119.&lt;/ref&gt;

Many groups and movements have managed to achieve profound social changes over the course of the [[20th century]] in the name of human rights. In [[Western Europe]] and [[North America]], [[trade union|labour union]]s brought about laws granting workers the right to strike, establishing minimum work conditions and forbidding or regulating [[child labor|child labour]]. The [[women's rights]] movement succeeded in gaining for many women the right to [[vote]]. [[National liberation]] movements in many countries succeeded in driving out [[colony|colonial]] powers. One of the most influential was [[Mahatma Gandhi]]'s movement to free his native [[India]] from [[United Kingdom|British]] rule. Movements by long-oppressed racial and religious minorities succeeded in many parts of the world, among them the [[civil rights movement]], and more recent diverse [[identity politics]] movements, on behalf of women and minorities in the United States. 

===After World War II===
[[Image:EleanorRooseveltHumanRights.gif|rightt|thumb|200px|"It is not a [[treaty]]...[In the future, it] may well become the international [[Magna Carta]]."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.americanrhetoric.com/speeches/eleanorrooseveltdeclarationhumanrights.htm Eleanor Roosevelt: Address to the United Nations General Assembly] [[10 December]] [[1948]] in Paris, France&lt;/ref&gt; [[Eleanor Roosevelt]] with the Spanish text of the Universal Declaration in 1949]] Appalled by the barbarism of the [[Second World War]], the [[United Nations General Assembly]] adopted the [[Universal Declaration of Human Rights]] in [[1948]]. While not legally binding, it urged member nations to promote a number of human, civil, economic and social rights, asserting these rights are part of the "foundation of freedom, justice and peace in the world". The declaration was the first international legal effort to limit the behavior of states and press upon them duties to their citizens following the model of the [[corelative|rights-duty duality]].

Many states wanted to go beyond the declaration of rights and create legal covenants which would put greater pressure on states to follow human rights norms. Because some states disagreed over whether this international covenant should contain economic and social rights (which usually require a greater effort to fulfill on the part of individual states), two treaties were prepared.

In [[1976]], the [[International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights]] was adopted by the United Nations. The [[International Covenant on Economic, Social and Cultural Rights]] came into force in 1976. It commits 155 state parties to work toward the granting of economic, social, and cultural rights (ESCR) to individuals. The Universal Declaration of Human Rights (abbreviated UDHR) is a non-binding declaration adopted by the United Nations General Assembly (A/RES/217, 1948-12-10 at Palais de Chaillot, Paris). 
{{clr}}
{{Cquote|...recognition of the inherent dignity and of the equal and [[inalienable rights]] of all members of the human family is the foundation of freedom, justice and peace in the world|30px|30px|Preamble to the Universal Declaration of Human Rights, 1948}}
Since then several other [[International human rights instruments|pieces of legislation]] have been introduced at the international level:

*[[Convention on the Prevention and Punishment of the Crime of Genocide]] (entry into force: 1951) [http://www.unhchr.ch/html/menu3/b/p_genoci.htm]
*[[UN Convention Against Torture|Convention against Torture]] (entry into force: 1984) [http://www.unhchr.ch/html/menu3/b/h_cat39.htm]
*[[Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Racial Discrimination]] (entry into force: 1969) [http://www.unhchr.ch/html/menu3/b/d_icerd.htm]
*[[Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination Against Women]] (entry into force: 1981) [http://www.un.org/womenwatch/daw/cedaw/index.html]
*[[Convention on the Rights of the Child]] (entry into force: 1989) [http://www.unicef.org/crc]
*[[Rome Statute|Rome Statute of the International Criminal Court]] (entry into force: 2002)

With the exception of the non-deformable human rights (the four most important are the right to life, the right to be free from slavery, the right to be free from torture and the right to be free from retroactive application of  penal laws), the UN recognises that human rights can be limited or even pushed aside during times of national emergency - although "the emergency must be actual, affect the whole population and the threat must be to the very existence of the nation. The declaration of emergency must also be a last resort and a temporary measure". [http://www.un.org/esa/socdev/enable/comp210.htm] Conduct in war is governed by [[International Humanitarian Law]].

===International bodies===
The [[International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights]] created an agency, the [[Human Rights Committee]] to promote participation with its standards. The eighteen members of the committee express opinions as to whether a particular practice is a human rights violation, although these reports are not legally binding.

A modern interpretation of the original Declaration of Human Rights was made in the [[Vienna Declaration and Programme of Action]] adopted by the World Conference on Human Rights in 1993. The degree of unanimity over these conventions, in terms of how many and which countries have ratified them varies, as does the degree to which they are respected by various states. The UN has set up a number of bodies to monitor and study human rights, under the leadership of the [[UN High Commissioner for Human Rights]] (UNHCHR).

===Regional legislation===
There are also many regional agreements and organisations governing human rights including the [[European Court of Human Rights]], which is the only international court with jurisdiction to deal with cases brought by individuals (rather than states); the [[African Commission on Human and Peoples' Rights]]; [[Inter-American Commission on Human Rights]]; [[Cairo Declaration on Human Rights in Islam]]; [[Inter-American Court of Human Rights]]; and Iran's [[Defenders of Human Rights Center]].

==Philosophy of human rights==
{{rights}}

===Theory of value and property===
{{seealso|Property}}
[[Henry of Ghent]] articulated the theory that every person has a property interest in their own body.&lt;ref&gt;The Idea of Natural Rights: Studies on Natural Rights, Natural Law, and Church Law 1150 ¿ 1625. Brian Tierney 1997. ISBN-10: 0802848540.&lt;/ref&gt; [[John Locke]] uses the word property in both broad and narrow senses. In a broad sense, it covers a wide range of human interests and aspirations; more narrowly, it refers to material goods. He argues that property is a natural right and it is derived from labour."&lt;ref&gt;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Locke&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, property precedes government and government cannot "dispose of the estates of the subjects arbitrarily." To deny valid [[property rights]] according to Locke is to deny [[human rights]]. The British philosopher had significant impacts upon the development of the Government of the UK and was central to the fundamental founding philosophy of the [[United States of America]].
Karl Marx later critiqued Locke's theory of property in his social theory.

===Types===
A few groups, such as  conceptually divide rights into '''[[negative and positive rights]]'''. By this distinction, "negative" human rights, which follow mainly from the Anglo-American legal tradition of [[natural rights]], are rights that a government and/or private entities may never take action to remove. For example, right to life and security of person; freedom from [[slavery]]; equality before the law and [[due process]] under the [[rule of law]]; freedom of movement; freedoms of [[freedom of speech|speech]], [[freedom of religion|religion]], [[freedom of assembly|assembly]]; the [[right to bear arms]]. These have been codified in documents including the Scottish [[Claim of Right]], the [[English Bill of Rights]] the [[Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms]] and the [[United States Bill of Rights]] and [[Fourteenth Amendment]].

This distinction holds that "Positive" human rights mainly follow from the [[Jean-Jacques Rousseau|Rousseauian]] [[Continental European]] legal tradition and denote human rights and entitlements that the state is obliged to protect and provide. Examples of such rights include: the rights to education, to health care, to a livelihood. Such 'positive rights' have been codified in the Universal Declaration of Human Rights (Articles 22-28) and in many 20th-century [[list of national constitutions|constitutions]].

Another categorization, offered by [[Karel Vasak]], is that there are '''[[three generations of human rights]]''': first-generation civil and political rights (right to life and political participation), second-generation economic, social and cultural rights (right to subsistence) and third-generation solidarity rights (right to peace, right to clean environment). Out of these generations, the third generation is the most debated and lacks both legal and political recognition. Some theorists discredit these divisions by claiming that rights are interconnected. Arguably, for example, basic education is necessary for the right to political participation.

Some human rights are said to be "[[inalienable rights]]."  The term inalienable rights (or unalienable rights) refers to "a set of human rights that are fundamental, are not awarded by human power, and cannot be surrendered."&lt;ref&gt;See Wikipedia article "[[inalienable rights]]"&lt;/ref&gt;

===Justification of human rights===
Several theoretical approaches have been advanced to explain how human rights become part of social expectations. The '''[[Biology|biological]] theory''' considers the comparative reproductive advantage of human social behavior based on empathy and [[altruism]] in the context of [[natural selection]]. Other theories hold that human rights codify moral behavior, which is a human, social product developed by a process of biological and social evolution (associated with [[David Hume|Hume]]) or as a sociological pattern of rule setting (as in the sociological theory of law and the work of [[Max Weber|Weber]]). This approach includes the notion that individuals in a society accept rules from legitimate authority in exchange for security and economic advantage (as in [[John Rawls|Rawls]]).

On the other hand, '''[[Natural law|natural law theories]]''' base human rights on the “natural” moral order that derives from religious precepts such as common understandings of justice and the belief that moral behavior is a set of objectively valid prescriptions. Some have used religious texts such as the [[Bible]] and [[Qur'an]] to support human rights arguments. However, there are also more secular forms of natural law theory that understand human rights as derivative of the notion of universal human dignity.&lt;ref&gt;Kohen, Ari (2007). ''In Defense of Human Rights: A Non-Religious Grounding in a Pluralistic World.'' Routledge.  ISBN 0415420156 , ISBN 978-0415420150&lt;/ref&gt;

Yet others have attempted to construct an "'''[[interests theory]]'''" defence of human rights. For example the philosopher [[John Finnis]] argues that human rights are justifiable on the grounds of their instrumental value in creating the necessary conditions for human well-being. Some interest-theorists also justify the duty to respect the rights of other individuals on grounds of self-interest (rather than altruism or benevolence). Reciprocal recognition and respect of rights ensures that one's own will be protected.

Ultimately, the term "human rights" is often itself an appeal to a transcendent principle, not based on existing legal concepts. The term "[[humanism]]" refers to the developing doctrine of such [[universality|universally applicable]] values. The term "human rights" has replaced the term "[[natural rights]]" in popularity, because the rights are less and less frequently seen as requiring [[natural law]] for their existence.&lt;ref&gt;Weston, Burns H. [http://www.britannica.com/eb/article-9106289?query=human%20rights&amp;ct=eb ''Human Rights''] in Encyclopedia Britannica Online, p. 2, Retrieved May 18, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

===Criticism of human rights===
One of the arguments made against the concept of human rights is that it suffers from [[cultural imperialism]]. In particular, the concept of human rights is fundamentally rooted in a politically [[liberalism|liberal]] outlook which, although generally accepted in [[Western Europe]], [[Japan]], [[India]] and [[North America]], is not necessarily taken as standard elsewhere. An appeal is often made to the fact that influential human rights thinkers, such as [[John Locke]] and [[John Stuart Mill]], have all been Western and indeed that some were involved in the running of [[Empire]]s themselves. The cultural imperialism argument achieves even greater potency when it is made on the basis of [[religion]]. Some histories of human rights emphasise the [[Christian]] influence on the agenda and then question whether this is in keeping with the tenets of other [[world religions]]. For example, in [[1981]], the Iranian representative to the [[United Nations]], [[Said Rajaie-Khorassani]], articulated the position of his country regarding the Universal Declaration of Human Rights by saying that the UDHR was "a [[Secularism|secular]] understanding of the [[Judeo-Christian]] tradition", which could not be implemented by Muslims without trespassing the Islamic law.&lt;ref name="Littman1999"&gt;Littman, David. "Universal Human Rights and 'Human Rights in Islam'". ''Midstream'', February/March 1999&lt;/ref&gt;

A final set of debating points revolves around the question of who has the duty to uphold human rights. Human rights have historically arisen from the need to protect citizens from abuse by the state and this might suggest that all mankind has a duty to intervene and protect people wherever they are. Divisive national loyalties, which emphasise differences between people rather than their similarities, can thus be seen as a destructive influence on the human rights movement because they deny people's innately similar human qualities.&lt;ref&gt;Klitou, Demetrius ''The Friends and Foes of Human Rights''&lt;/ref&gt; But others argue that [[state sovereignty]] is paramount, not least because it is often the state that has signed up to human rights treaties in the first place. Commentators' positions in the argument for and against [[interventionism (politics)|intervention]] and the [[use of force by states]] are influenced by whether they believe human rights are largely a legal or moral duty and whether they are of more [[cosmopolitanism|cosmopolitan]] or [[nationalism|nationalist]] persuasion.

==Human rights violations==
Human rights violations are abuses of people in ways that abuse any [[Fundamental right|fundamental human rights]]. It is a term used when a government violates national or international law related to the protection of human rights. According to the [[Universal Declaration of Human Rights]] fundamental human rights are violated when, among other things:

{{MultiCol}}
* A certain [[race]], [[creed]], or group is denied recognition as a "person". (Articles 2 &amp; 6)
* Men and women are not treated as equal. (Article 2)
* Different racial or religious groups are not treated as equal. (Article 2)
* Life, liberty or security of person is threatened. (Article 3)
* A person is sold as or used as a [[slavery|slave]]. (Article 4)
* [[Cruel and unusual punishment|Cruel, inhuman or degrading punishment]] is used on a person (such as [[torture]] or [[execution (legal)|execution]]). (Article 5) (See also [[Prisoners' rights]])
* Victims of abuse are denied an effective [[judicial]] remedy. (Article 8)
{{ColBreak}}
* Punishments are dealt arbitrarily or unilaterally, without a proper and [[right to a fair trial|fair trial]]. (Article 11)
* Arbitrary interference into personal, or private lives by agents of the state. (Article 12)
* Citizens are forbidden to leave or return to their country. (Article 13)
* [[Freedom of speech]] or [[freedom of religion|religion]] is denied. (Articles 18 &amp; 19)
* The right to join a [[trade union]] is denied. (Article 23)
* Education is denied. (Article 26)
{{EndMultiCol}}

Human rights violations and abuses include those alleged by [[non-governmental organizations]], such as [[Amnesty International]], [[Human Rights Watch]], [[World Organisation Against Torture]], [[Freedom House]], [[International Freedom of Expression Exchange]] and [[Anti-Slavery International]] that collect evidence and documentation. Only a very few countries do not commit significant human rights violations, according to Amnesty International. In their [[2004]] human rights report (covering [[2003]]) the [[Netherlands]], [[Norway]], [[Denmark]], [[Iceland]] and [[Costa Rica]] are the only (mappable) countries that did not violate at least some human rights significantly.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | title=Amnesty International Report 2004 | publisher=Amnesty International | date=2004 | isbn=0862103541 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some people believe human rights abuses are more common in [[dictatorship]]s or [[theocracy|theocracies]] than in [[democracy|democracies]] because [[freedom of speech]] and [[freedom of the press]] tend to uncover state orchestrated abuse and expose it. Nonetheless human rights abuses do also occur in democracies.

Many suggest the basic problem in dealing with Human Rights is the lack of understanding of the basic laws of [[fiduciary control]]. International [[equity]] expert [[Professor Paul Finn]] has underlined, “the most fundamental fiduciary relationship in our society is manifestly that which exists between the community (the people) and the state, its agencies and [[officials]. "

In [[equity]] a politician's fiduciary obligations not only comprise duties of good faith and loyalty, but also include duties of skill and [[competence]] in managing a country and it's people.

It is widely agreed Government is a 'trust structure' created by people to manage the needs of society. The relationship between government and the governed is clearly a [[fiduciary]] one. Yet rules such as [[Sovereign Immunity]] or [[Crown and Judicial Immunity]] are now being targeted as the very the tools of oppression that are preventing those being abused from taking action against the person controlling the laws of a country. Originating from within the [[Courts of Equity]], the fiduciary concept was partly designed to prevent those holding positions of power from abusing their authority.

Modern arguments suggest anyone accepting any judicial, political or government  control over the interests of people requires moral obligations of the highest responsibility and trust. Its conduct should therefore be judged by the most exacting fiduciary standards. The fiduciary relationship arises from the governments ability to control people with the exercise of that power. In effect, if a government staff have the power to abolish any rights they are burdened with the fiduciary duty to protect such an interest because the government would benefit from the exercise of its own discretion to extinguish rights which it alone had the power to dispose of.

[http://web.mac.com/christiandavenport/iWeb/Christian%20Davenport/Stop%20Our%20States%20(SOS).html Human Rights Violation/State Repression Data]

==National human rights institutions==

In over 110 countries [[National human rights institutions]] (NHRIs) have been set up to protect, promote or monitor human rights in a given country. There are now over 110 such bodies.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nhri.net National Human Rights Institutions Forum] is the official portal for the National Human Rights Institutions and show a list of 119 institutions that can be found at [http://www.nhri.net/nationaldatalist.asp]&lt;/ref&gt; Not all of them are compliant with the United Nations advisory standards as set out in the 1993 [[Paris Principles]], but the number and effect of these institutions is increasing.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.huridocs.org HURIDOCS] has developed extensive methodologies for monitoring and documenting human rights violations, and more resources can be found at [http://www.humanrightstools.org/dir/1__Monitoring_-_brown_Documentation_-_Advocacy/Monitoring_and_fact-finding_/ Human Rights Tools]&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{MultiCol}}
* [[Cairo Declaration on Human Rights in Islam]]
* [[Cyrus Cylinder]]
* [[Anti-terrorism legislation]]
* [[Ethic of reciprocity|The Golden Rule]]
* [[Global governance]]
* [[Human Responsibilities]]
* [[Human rights and the United States]]
* [[Portal:Human rights|Human rights portal]]
* [[Human rights in the Soviet Union]]

{{ColBreak}}

* [[Freedom of thought]]
* [[Police Brutality]]
* [[Prisoner rights in Islam]]
* [[Social rights in Islam]]
* [[Teaching for social justice]]
* [[United Nations Human Rights Council]]
* [[United Nations Parliamentary Assembly]]

{{EndMultiCol}}



;Multilateral organisations
{{MultiCol}}
*[http://docs.lib.duke.edu/igo/guides/ngo/db/rights.asp Duke University's library list]
*[http://www.youthforhumanrights.org Youth for Human Rights International]
*[http://www.ihra.co.in International Human rights Association]
*[http://www.pww.org.pk/ Peace WorldWide]
*[[Aga Khan Development Network]] (AKDN)
*[[Amnesty International]]
*[http://www.ansarburney.org/ Ansar Burney Trust]
*[[Bahrain Centre for Human Rights]]
*[[Carter Center]]
*[[DEMIRA Deutsche Minenraeumer e.V.]] - German Mine Clearer
*[[Forum 18]]
*[[Freedom House]]
*[[Human Rights Foundation]]
*[[Human Rights Watch]]
*[http://www.imagine-life.org/ Imagine-Life]
*[[International Freedom of Expression Exchange]]
*[[International Helsinki Federation for Human Rights]]
*[http://www.escr-net.org/ International Network for Economic, Social &amp; Cultural Rights (ESCR-Net)]
*[[International Progress Organization]]
*[[International Service for Human Rights]]
{{ColBreak}}
*[http://www.jhr.ca/ Journalists for Human Rights]
*[[Defenders of Human Rights Center]]
*[[Liberty (pressure group)]]
*[[Memorial (society)|Memorial]]
*[[Montagnard Foundation]]
*[[Network Against Prohibition]]
*[http://www.ihra.co.in International Human Rights Association]
*[[Office of the United Nations High Commissioner for Human Rights]]
*[[Peace Brigades International]]
*[[Prisoners Overseas]]
*[[Southern Poverty Law Center]]
*[[US Human Rights Network]]
*[[World Organisation Against Torture]]
*[http://www.speaktruth.org/ Speak Truth to Power]
*[http://www.rfkmemorial.org/ Robert F. Kennedy Memorial]
*[http://www.witness.org/ WITNESS]
{{EndMultiCol}}

==Notes==
{{reflist|2}}

==References==
* Pro.Dr.Tahir-ul-Qadri, Huquq al Insania fil Islam (Human Rights in Islam),Minhaj Publishers (2005) 365-M-Model Town Lahore,Pakistan 
* Steiner, J. &amp; Alston, Philip. (1996). ''International Human Rights in Context: Law, Politics, Morals.'' Oxford: Clarendon Press. ISBN 019825427X
* Barzilai, Gad. (2003). Communities and Law: Politics and Cultures of Legal Identities. Ann Arbor: University of Michigan Press. 
* Davenport, Christian (2007). [http://www.cambridge.org/catalogue/catalogue.asp?isbn=0521864909 ''State Repression and the Domestic Democratic Peace.'']  New York: Cambridge University Press.
* Davenport, Christian (2007). [http://www.bsos.umd.edu/gvpt/davenport/STATER%7e2.PDF ''State Repression and Political Order.''] Annual Review of Political Science.
* Donnelly, Jack. (2003). ''Universal Human Rights in Theory &amp; Practice.'' 2nd ed. Ithaca &amp; London: Cornell University Press.
* Ellerman, David (2005). ''Helping People Help Themselves: From the World Bank to an Alternative Philosophy of Development Assistance.'' Ann Arbor: University of Michigan Press.
* Forsythe, David P. (2000). ''Human Rights in International Relations.'' Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.
* [[Hans Köchler|Köchler, Hans]]. (1981). [http://hanskoechler.com/Filosofia-del-derecho.htm ''The Principles of International Law and Human Rights'']
* [[Hans Köchler|Köchler, Hans]]. (1990). ''Democracy and Human Rights''. (Studies in International Relations, XV.) Vienna: International Progress Organization. ISBN 3-900704-08-2  
* Ignatieff, Michael. ''Human Rights as Politics and Idolatry.'' Princeton &amp; Oxford: Princeton University Press.
*Landman, Todd (2006) ''Studying Human Rights'', Oxford and London: Routledge ISBN 0-415-32605-2
* Shute, Stephen &amp; Hurley, Susan (eds.). (1993). ''On Human Rights: The Oxford Amnesty Lectures.'' New York: BasicBooks.
* Hans-Georg Möller, How to Distinguish Friends from Enemies: Human Rights Rhetoric and Western Mass Media. In Peter D. Hershock, R.T. Ames and M. Stepaniants (eds.), Technology and Cultural Values on the Edge of the Third Millennium. (Selected papers from the 8 th East-West Philosophers Conference) Honolulu: U of Hawai’i Press, 2003. 209-221. 
* Sunga, Lyal S. (1992) Individual Responsibility in International Law for Serious Human Rights Violations, Nijhoff Publishers.
*  Donnelly, Jack.  Universal Human Rights in Theory and Practice.  Cornell University Press, 2003.
* McLagan, Meg ''[http://www.anthrosource.net/doi/abs/10.1525/aa.2003.105.3.605 Principles, Publicity, and Politics: Notes on Human Rights Media]'' American Anthropologist September 2003, Vol. 105, No. 3, pp. 605-612 
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{external links}}
{{MultiCol}}
*[http://tv.oneworld.net OneworldTV has a section of documentaries devoted to human rights.]
*[http://www.nhri.net National Human Rights Institutions Forum] - Official Portal for the Global network of National Human Rights Institutions.
*[http://www.un.org/Overview/rights.html United Nations- Universal Declaration of Human Rights]
*[http://www.un.org/rights/ United Nations- Human Rights]
*[http://www.coe.int Council of Europe - Convention for the Protection of Human Rights and Fundamental Freedoms]
*[http://www1.umn.edu/humanrts University of Minnesota Human Rights Library] - Over 23,000 documents and 4,000 links
*[http://www.hrusa.org University of Minnesota Human Rights Resource Center] - Creating and distributing Human Rights Education (HRE) resources, training activists, professionals, and students &amp; building advocacy networks
*[http://www.hrea.org Human Rights Education Associates (HREA)] - Over 3,000 downloadable training materials and on-line courses for human rights defenders, development workers and educators
{{ColBreak}}

*[http://www.globalautonomy.ca/global1/glossary_entry.jsp?id=CO.0044  Adam Sneyd, "The Right to Development"], in Globalization and Autonomy Online Compendium, edited by William D. Coleman and Nancy Johnson
*[http://www.universalhumanrightsindex.org/ The Universal Human Rights Index of United Nations documents]
*[http://www.projectworldview.org/wvtheme32.htm "Valuing Human Rights" from Project Worldview]

=== Human rights organizations ===
*[http://www.ihra.co.in International Human Rights Association]
*[http://www.amnesty.org Amnesty International]
*[http://www.international-council.org The International Council on Human Rights Policy]
*[http://www.mdri.org Mental Disability Rights International]

{{Africa_in_topic|Human rights in}}
{{North America in topic|Human rights in}}
{{South America in topic|Human rights in}}
{{Asia in topic|Human rights in}}
&lt;!-- {{Furtopia in topic|Human rights in}} --&gt;
{{Europe in topic|Human rights in}}
{{Oceania in topic|Human rights in}}
&lt;!-- {{Atlantis in topic|Human rights in}} --&gt;

{{Portal}}

[[Category:Human rights|*]]
[[Category:International relations]]
[[Category:Rights]]

[[ar:حقوق الإنسان]]
[[zh-min-nan:Jîn-kôan]]
[[ca:Drets humans]]
[[cs:Lidská práva]]
[[da:Menneskerettighederne]]
[[de:Menschenrechte]]
[[es:Derechos humanos]]
[[fa:حقوق بشر]]
[[fr:Droits de l'homme]]
[[ko:인권]]
[[hi:मानवाधिकार]]
[[hr:Ljudska prava]]
[[is:Mannréttindi]]
[[it:Diritti umani]]
[[he:זכויות האדם]]
[[ka:ადამიანის უფლებები]]
[[lv:Cilvēktiesības]]
[[lt:Žmogaus teisės]]
[[mk:Човекови права]]
[[nl:Rechten van de Mens]]
[[ja:人権]]
[[no:Menneskerettigheter]]
[[ps:بشري حقونه]]
[[pl:Prawa człowieka]]
[[pt:Direitos humanos]]
[[qu:Runapa kaqnin]]
[[ru:Права человека]]
[[sq:Të Drejtat e Njeriut]]
[[simple:Human rights]]
[[sk:Ľudské práva]]
[[fi:Ihmisoikeudet]]
[[sv:De mänskliga rättigheterna]]
[[th:สิทธิมนุษยชน]]
[[vi:Nhân quyền]]
[[tr:İnsan hakları]]
[[uk:Права людини]]
[[zh:人权]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>