<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20071105103554|169351942" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="31783" pageid="31783" ns="0" title="Uyghurs"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-11-14T04:12:06Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{For|the language spoken by this ethnic group|Uyghur language}}
{{Infobox Ethnic group
|group         = Uyghur&lt;br/&gt; ئۇيغۇر
|image         = [[Image:Uyghur_figures.jpg|250px]]
|image_capiton = Uyghur in the history
|population    = approx. 15,000,000
|regions       = {{flag|China}} ([[Xinjiang]])&lt;br /&gt;{{flag|Pakistan}}&lt;br /&gt;{{flag|Kazakhstan}}&lt;br /&gt; {{flag|Kyrgyzstan}} &lt;br /&gt;{{flag|Uzbekistan}} &lt;br /&gt;{{flag|Mongolia}}&lt;br /&gt; {{flag|Turkey}} &lt;br /&gt;{{flag|Russia}}
|languages     = [[Uyghur language|Uyghur]]
|religions     = [[Sunni Islam]]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.cnn.com/2005/WORLD/asiapcf/04/20/eyeonchina.xinjiang/index.html&lt;/ref&gt;
|related= Other [[Turkic peoples]], ancient [[Tocharians]]{{Fact|date=April 2007}}
}}

The '''Uyghur''' (also spelled '''Uygur''', '''Uighur''', '''Uigur'''; [[Uyghur language|Uyghur]]: ئۇيغۇر; {{zh-stp|s=维吾尔|t=維吾爾|p=Wéiwú'ěr}}) are a [[Turkic peoples|Turkic]] people of [[Central Asia]]. Today Uyghurs live primarily in the [[Xinjiang Uyghur Autonomous Region]] (also known by its controversial name [[East Turkistan]] or Uyghurstan). There are also existing Uyghur communities in [[Pakistan]], [[Kazakhstan]], [[Kyrgyzstan]], [[Mongolia]], [[Uzbekistan]], [[Germany]] and [[Turkey]] and a smaller one in [[Taoyuan County, Hunan|Taoyuan County]] of [[Hunan]] province in south-central China.&lt;ref&gt; http://english.people.com.cn/english/200012/28/eng20001228_59085.html&lt;/ref&gt; 

There are small but very active Uyghur communities in the [[United States]], mainly in [[Los Angeles]], [[San Francisco]], [[New York]] and [[Washington, DC]]. Uyghur neighborhoods can also be found in major cities like [[Beijing]] and [[Shanghai]],&lt;ref&gt; http://acc6.its.brooklyn.cuny.edu/~phalsall/texts/chinethn.html&lt;/ref&gt; as well as in [[Toronto]] and [[Vancouver]] in [[Canada]].

==Identity==

Historically the term "Uyghur" (meaning "united" or "allied") was applied to a group of Turkic-speaking tribes that lived in the [[Altay Mountains]].  Along with the [[Göktürks]] (Kokturks) the Uyghurs were one of the largest and most enduring [[Turkic peoples]] living in [[Central Asia]]. 

The earliest use of the term "Uyghur" (Weihu) was during the Northern [[Northern Wei Dynasty|Wei]] Dynasty (386-534 AD), in China.  At that time the Uyghur were part of the [[Gaoche]], a group of Turkic tribes, which were later called [[Tiele]] people (or possibly [[Turan]]). This group included tribes such as [[Syr-Tardush]] ([[Xueyantuo]]), Basmil (Baximi), [[Oguz]] (Wuhu), [[Khazar]] (Hesan), [[Alan]]s (A-lans), [[Kyrgyz]] (Hegu), [[Tuva]] (Duva)  and [[Yakut]] (Guligan) from the Lake Baikal Region. The forebears of the [[Tiele]] belonged to those of [[Hun]] ([[Xiongnu]]) descendants. According to Chinese Turkic scholars Ma Changshou and Cen Zhongmian, the Chinese word [[Tiele]] originates from the Turkic word "Türkler" (Turks), which is a plural form of "Türk" (Turk) and the Chinese word "Tujue" comes from the Turkic word "Türküt" which is a singular form of Türk.&lt;ref&gt;[A Historical Collection on the History of the Turks]. (Beijing: Zhonghua shuju, 1958): 6-7. &lt;/ref&gt;  The origin of [[Gaoche]] can be traced back to the [[Dingling]] peoples c. 200 BC, contemporary with the Chinese [[Han Dynasty]].&lt;ref&gt;Golden, Peter. ''An Introduction to the History of the Turkic Peoples'' (Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz, 1992), 94.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Sima Qian, Shiji [Records of the Historian] Vol. 110: Xiongnu; and Ban Gu, Han Shu [History of the Han Dynasty], Vol. 94: Xiongnu.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Book of Sui]], vol. 84 (c. 600 AD).&lt;/ref&gt; 

The first use of "Uyghur" as reference to a political nation occurred during the interim period between the First and Second Göktürk Kaganates (630-684 AD). After the collapse of the [[Uyghur Empire]] in 840 AD, Uyghur refugees resettled to the [[Tarim Basin]], intermarrying with the local people.  It is only after this resettlement, that "Uyghur" can be properly used as an ethnic designation. {{Fact|date=August 2007}} 

In modern usage, "Uyghur" refers to settled Turkic [[urban area|urban]]-dwellers and farmers who follow traditional Central Asian practice, distinguished from nomadic Turkic populations in [[Central Asia]] {{Fact|date=August 2007}}. The Chinese Communists reintroduced the term "Uyghur" to replace the previously used [[Turki]]. "Uyghur" is widely credited as having been used by Chinese Communists for the first time in 1921 with the establishment of the [[ Revolutionary Uyghur Union]] (Inqilawi Uyghur Itipaqi), a [[Communist]] [[nationalist]] group with intellectual and organizational ties to the [[Soviet Union]].  There is some evidence that Uyghur students and merchants living in [[Russia]] had already embraced the name prior to this date, drawing on Russian studies that claimed a linkage between the historical khanate and Xinjiang's current inhabitants.

Uyghurs live mainly in Xinjiang Uyghur Autonomous Region, China, where they are the largest ethnic group, together with [[Han Chinese]], [[Uzbeks]], [[Kazakhs]], [[Kyrgyz]] and [[Russians]]. Thousands of Uyghurs also live in [[Kazakhstan]] and [[Kyrgyzstan]].  "Xinjiang", meaning "New Frontier", is the official Chinese name of the [[Autonomous Region]]. Uyghurs still refer to "Xinjiang" as [[East Turkistan]].

== History ==
=== Orkhon Uyghur ===
Uyghur history can be divided into four distinct phases: Pre-Imperial (300 BCE-630 CE), Imperial (630-840 CE), Idiqut (840-1225 CE), and Mongol (1225-1600 CE), with perhaps a fifth modern phase running from the death of the Silk Road in 1600 CE until the present. Uyghur history is the story of an obscure nomadic tribe from the Altai Mountains rising to challenge the Chinese Empire and ultimately becoming the diplomatic arm of the Mongol invasion.

==== Pre-630 CE ====
[[Image:Gokturkut.png|right|thumb|250px|Map of the Western (purple) and Eastern (blue) [[Göktürks|Göktürk]] [[khagan]]ates at their height, c. 600 CE. Lighter areas show direct rule; darker areas show spheres of influence.]]

The ancestors of the Uyghur include the nomadic [[Gaoche]] people and possibly the [[Tocharian]] peoples of the [[Tarim]] Basin.  Gaoche, meaning 'High Cart', was a reference to the distinct high-wheeled, ox-drawn carts used to move [[yurt]]s. The Gaoche were Altaic nomads who lived in the valleys south of [[Lake Baikal]] and around the [[Yenisei River]](Yenisei = Ana Say, or "Mother River" in Turkic).  They practiced some minor agriculture and were highly developed metalsmiths due to the abundance of easily available iron ore in the Yenisei.  They became vassals of the [[Huns]] and provided them with manufactured arms.  After the Huns they were passed as vassals to the [[Rouran]] and [[Hepthalite]] States.  In [[450]] CE the Gaoche planned a revolt against the Rouran that was defeated by the [[Türk]]{{dn}} (another Rouran vassal tribe).  This incident marked the beginning of the historic Türk-Tiele animosity that plagued the [[Göktürk|Göktürk Khanate]].  When the Göktürk defeated the Rouran/Hepthalite state, they became the new masters of the Tiele (the name "Gaoche" was replaced by "Tiele" in historic records around this time).  It was also at this time that the Uyghur tribe was first mentioned in Chinese records as a small tribe of 10,000 yurts in the South [[Baikal]] region.

The Uyghur participated in a coalition of Tiele under the leadership of the [[Syr-Tardush]] tribe, who allied with the Chinese [[Sui Dynasty|Sui Empire]] in [[603]] to defeat Tardu Khan and win their independence.  This alliance existed with varying degrees of autonomy from 603 until [[630]] when the Göktürk Khanate was decisively defeated by the Emperor [[Tang Taizong]].  During this time the Uyghur occupied second position in the alliance after the [[Syr-Tardush]].  In the interregnum between the first and second Göktürk Khanates (630-[[683]]), the Uyghur toppled the Syr-Tardush and declared their independence.  When a second Göktürk Khanate was established during the reign of [[Empress Wu of Zhou|Empress Wu]], the Uyghurs, together with other nomadic Turkic tribes, participated in the [[Gokturk]] empire. the empire declined following [[Bilge Khan]]'s death in [[734]].  After a series of revolts coordinated with their Chinese allies, the Uyghur emerged as the leaders of a new coalition force called the "Toquz Oghuz".  In [[744]] the Uyghur, together with other related subject tribes (the Basmil and [[Qarluq]]), defeated the Göktürk Khanate and founded the [[Uyghur Empire]] at Mount [[Ötüken]], which lasted for about 100 years.

====745 CE-840 CE====
[[Image:Uyghur Khaganate.png|right|thumb|250px|Map of the Uyghur Khaganate and areas under its dominion (in yellow) at its height, c. 820 CE.]]

Properly called the On- Uyghur (ten Uyghurs) and Toquz-Oghuz (nine tribes) Orkhon Khanate, the [[Uyghur Empire]] stretched from the Caspian Sea{{Fact|date=May 2007}} to [[Manchuria]] and lasted from 745 to 840 CE. It was administered from the imperial capital [[Ordu Baliq]], the first city built in [[Mongolia]].  During the imperial phase "Uyghur" came to mean any citizen of the [[Uyghur Empire]], and not just a member of the Uyghur tribe.  After the [[An Shi Rebellion]], the [[Uyghur Empire]] considered conquering the [[Tang Dynasty|Tang Empire]],{{Fact|date=August 2007}} but chose instead to use an exploitative trade policy to drain off the wealth of China without actually destroying it.  In return, they policed the borders and quelled internal rebellions.  Large numbers of [[Sogdian]] refugees came to Ordu Baliq to escape the Islamic Jihad in their homeland.  It was from them the Uyghur were converted from Buddhism to [[Manichaeism|Manichaeanism]].  The Uyghurs thus inherited the legacy of [[Sogdian]] Culture. 

In 840, following a famine and a civil war, the [[Uyghur Empire]] was overrun by the [[Kyrgyz]], another Turkic people.  The result was that the majority of tribal groups formerly under the umbrella of the Uyghurs migrated to what is now northwestern China, especially the modern Xinjiang Uyghur Autonomous Region.

=== Modern Uyghur ===
==== 840 CE-1600 CE ====

[[Image:Museum für Indische Kunst Dahlem Berlin Mai 2006 063.jpg|200px|right|thumb|Wall painting of Uyghur Princes]]

The Uyghur refugees who fled southwest and west following the collapse of the [[Uyghur Empire]] established states in three areas: [[Gansu]], present day [[Xinjiang]], and the Valley of [[Chu River]] in the West [[Tian Shan]] ( Tengri-Tag) Mountains. 

Those who fled west, together with other Turkic tribal groups living in [[Dzungaria]] and the [[Tarim Basin]], established the [[Beshbalik]]-[[Turpan]]-[[Kucha]] state in the Tarim Basin, [[Turfan Depression]], and Dzungaria. In the process, they merged with the local populations of Tocharians (or Tokharians, whose language was Indo-European). It is probable that [[genetics|genetic]]ally and culturally, modern Uyghurs descended from the nomadic Turkic tribes and the Indo-European-speaking groups who preceded them in the [[Tarim Basin]] oasis-cities, as well as Uyghurs from Mongolia . Today one can still see Uyghurs with light-colored skin and hair. Modern studies have found that modern Uyghur populations represent an admixture of eastern and western Eurasian [[mtDNA]]&lt;ref&gt; http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/reprint/21/12/2265.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Y chromosome]]&lt;ref&gt; http://www.pnas.org/cgi/content/full/98/18/10244&lt;/ref&gt; lineages.  It is at this time "Uyghur" can be used as an ethnic designation.  

'''Yugor''' The eastern-most of the three Uyghur states was the Ganzhou Kingdom (870- 1036 CE), with its capital near present-day [[Zhangye]] in the [[Gansu]] province of China. There, the Uyghur converted from [[Manicheism]] to [[Lamaism]] (Tibetan and Mongol [[Buddhism]]). Unlike other Turkic peoples further west, they did not later convert to Islam. Their descendants are now known as [[Yugurs]] (or ''Yogir'', ''Yugor'', and ''Sary Uyghurs'', literally meaning "yellow Uyghurs" referring to their yellow hair) and are distinct from modern Uyghurs.  In 1028-1036 CE the Yugors were defeated in a bloody war and forcibly absorbed into the [[Tangut]] kingdom.

'''Karakhoja''' The central of the three Uyghur states was the Karakhoja kingdom (created during 856-866 CE), also called the "Idiqut" (" Holy Wealth, Glory ") state, and was based around the cities of [[Turfan]] (winter capital), [[Beshbalik]] (summer capital), [[Kumul]], and [[Kucha]].  A Buddhist state, with state-sponsored Buddhism and Manichaeism, it can be considered the epicentre of Uyghur culture. The Idiquts (title of the Karakhoja rulers) ruled independently until 1209, when they submitted to the Mongols under [[Genghis Khan]] and, as vassal rulers, existed until 1335. 

'''[[Kara-Khanid Khanate|Kara-Khanids]]''', or The Karahans (Great Khans Dynasty), was the westernmost of the three Uyghur states. The Karahans (Karakhanliks) originated from Uyghur tribes settled in the [[Chu River]] Valley after 840 and ruled between 940-1212 in [[Turkistan]] and Maveraünnehir. They converted to [[Islam]] in 934 under the rule of [[Sultan Satuq Bughra Khan]] (920-956) and, after taking power over [[Qarluks]] in 940, built a federation with Muslim institutions. Together with the [[Samanids]] of [[Samarkand]], they considered themselves the defenders of Islam against the Buddhist Uyghur Idiqut and the Buddhist [[Scythian]]-[[Tocharian]] kingdom of [[Khotan]]. The first capital of the Karahans was established in the city of [[Balasagun]] in the Chu River Valley and later was moved to [[Kashgar]].

The reign of the Karahans is especially significant from the point of view of Turkic culture and art history. It is during this period that mosques, schools, bridges, and caravansaries were constructed in the cities. Kashgar, [[Bukhara]] and [[Samarkand]] became centers of learning. During this period, Turkish literature developed. Among the most important works of the period is [[Kutadgu Bilig]] (translated as "The Knowledge That Gives Happiness"), written by [[Yusuf Balasaghuni]] between the years 1069-1070.

Both the Idiqut and the Kara-Khanid states eventually submitted to the [[KaraKhitans]]. After the rise of the [[Seljuk Turks]] in [[Iran]], the [[Kara-Khanid Khanate|Kara-Khanids]] became nominal vassals of the [[Seljuks]] as well. Later they would serve the dual-[[suzerainty]] of the [[Kara-Khitans]] to the north and the Seljuks to the south. Finally all three states became vassals to [[Genghis Khan]] in 1209.

Most inhabitants of the [[Ürümqi|Besh Balik]] and [[Turfan]] regions did not convert to Islam until the [[15th century]] expansion of the [[Yarkand]] Khanate, a Turko-Mongol [[successor state]] based in western Tarim. Before converting to Islam, Uyghurs were [[Manichaean]]s, [[Zoroastrian]]s, [[Buddhist]]s, or [[Nestorian]] [[Christianity|Christians]].

==== Post-1600 CE ====
The [[Manchus]], nomads from present-day northeast China, vastly expanded the Qing empire, which they founded in 1644, to include much of Mongolia, East Turkistan, and Tibet. The Manchus invaded [[East Turkistan]] in 1759 and dominated it until 1864. During this period the Uyghurs revolted 42 times against Manchu rule with the purpose of regaining their independence. In the revolt of 1864, the Uyghurs were successful in expelling the Manchus from [[East Turkistan]], and founded an independent [[Kashgaria]] kingdom under the leadership of [[Yakub Beg]]. This kingdom was recognized by the [[Ottoman]] Empire, Tsarist Russia, and Great Britain. 

Large Manchu forces under the overall command of General [[Zuo Zongtang]]  attacked [[East Turkestan]] in 1876. Fearing Tsarist expansion into East Turkestan, Great Britain supported the Manchu invasion forces through loans by British banks.  After this invasion, [[East Turkestan]] was renamed "Xinjiang" or "Sinkiang", which means "New Dominion" or "New Territory", and it was annexed by the Manchu empire on November 18, 1884.

In 1911, the Nationalist Chinese, under the leadership of Dr. Sun Yat Sen, overthrew Manchu rule and established a republic. Official recognition of the Uyghurs came under the rule of [[Sheng Shicai]] who deviated from the official [[Kuomintang]] ''five races of China'' stance in favor of a [[Stalinist]] policy of delineating fourteen distinct ethnic nationalities in [[Xinjiang]]. The Uyghurs staged several uprisings against Nationalist Chinese rule. Twice, in 1933 and 1944, the Uyghurs were successful in setting up an independent [[First East Turkestan Republic|Islamic Eastern Turkestan Republic]]. These independent Islamic Republics were subsequently overthrown by the Nationalist Chinese with the military assistance and political support of the Soviet Union, which opposed the Uyghur independence movement throughout this period. In 1949, the Nationalist Chinese were defeated by the Chinese communists and [[East Turkestan]] was annexed by the [[People's Republic of China]].

===Separatism===
{{main|East Turkestan independence movement}}
[[Image:Flag of Eastern Turkistan.svg|thumb||right|200px|The "Kokbayraq" flag. This flag is used by Uyghurs as a symbol of the [[East Turkestan independence movement]]. It is almost identical to the flag of Turkey except with a blue background. The [[People's Republic of China|Chinese government]] prohibits using the flag in the country.]]

Following [[9/11]], [[China]] voiced its support for the [[United States of America]] in the [[war on terror]]. The Chinese government has often referred to Uyghur nationalists as "terrorists" and received more global support for their own "war on terror" since [[9/11]]. Human rights organizations have become concerned that this "war on terror" is being used by the Chinese government as a pretext to repress ethnic Uyghurs. &lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/asia-pacific/4435135.stm China 'crushing Muslim Uighurs'] BBC News Online, [[2007-04-21]]. Retrieved [[2007-04-21]].&lt;/ref&gt; Uyghur exile groups also claim that the Chinese government is suppressing Uyghur culture and religion, and responding to demands for independence with human rights violations.  The Chinese government has not forced Uyghurs to adhere to the one-child policy of China, which points to some degree of autonomy and respect for their Islamic culture, which expects people to have multiple children.  

Many Uyghur in the [[diaspora]] support [[Pan-Turkism|Pan-Turkic groups]]. Several organizations, such as the East Turkestan Party, provide support for the Chinese Uyghurs. 

Though most Uyghur political groups support peaceful, secular Uyghur nationalism, there are some radical [[Islamist]] militant groups (such as the [[East Turkestan Islamic Movement]] and [[East Turkestan Liberation Organization]]) advocating independence from China. This has caused much confusion with regard to names and beliefs of Uyghur political groups. Often the Chinese government refers generally to [[East Turkestan]] nationalists as "[[Terrorism|terrorists]]".

The Chinese government often imprisons Uyghur nationalists and has executed some individuals. On February 9, 2007, [[Ismail Semed]] was executed by the [[Peoples Republic of China]] for "attempting to split the motherland"&lt;ref&gt;http://www.rfa.org/english/news/breaking_news/2007/02/08/uyghur_execute/&lt;/ref&gt;. In March 2006, Huseyin Celil, a Canadian Muslim religious leader was arrested and later convicted for “separatist activities” and sentenced to life imprisonment because of his alleged links to groups seeking independence for Xinjiang.

The name [[Xinjiang]], which means "new dominion" in Chinese, is considered offensive by many advocates of Uyghur independence who prefer to use historical or ethnic names such as Chinese Turkestan, East Turkestan (with Turkestan sometimes spelled as Turkistan), or Uyghurstan.

==Culture==
[[Image:Khotan-mercado-chicas-d01.jpg|thumb|right|200px|Three Uyghur girls at a Sunday market in the oasis city [[Khotan]] (Hotan / Hetian), in the [[Xinjiang]] Uyghur Autonomous Region of the People's Republic of [[China]].]]

The relics of the Uyghur culture constitute major collections in the museums of [[Berlin]], [[London]], [[Paris]], [[Tokyo]], [[St. Petersburg]], and [[New Delhi]]. During the late 19th and early 20th centuries, scientific and archaeological expeditions to the region of Eastern Turkestan’s [[Silk Road]] discovered numerous cave temples, monastery ruins, and wall paintings, as well as valuable miniatures, books, and documents. Explorers from Europe, America, and even Japan were amazed by the art treasures found there, and soon their reports caught the attention of an interested public around the world. The manuscripts and documents discovered in [[Xinjiang]] ([[Eastern Turkestan]]) reveal the very high degree of civilization attained by the Uyghurs.  This Uyghur power, prestige, and civilization, which dominated Central Asia for over a thousand years, went into a steep decline after the [[Manchu]] invasion of their homeland.

Currently, Turkic and Islamic cultural elements are dominant in the [[Tarim Basin]], which reflects a thousand years of Turkic rule in the region and resulted in the replacement of previous religious traditions.  

Both Uyghur and Han locals live by the unofficial "Xinjiang time", two hours removed from the official Beijing time. Businesses and government offices have modified hours to compensate for the difference from official Beijing time (e.g. opening at 10 am and closing at 8 pm).

===Literature===
Most of the early Uyghur literary works were translations of [[Buddhist]] and [[Manichean]] religious texts, but there were also narrative, poetic, and epic works. Some of these have been translated into German, English, Russian, and Turkish. After embracing Islam, world-renowned Uyghur scholars emerged, and Uyghur literature flourished. Among hundreds of important works surviving from that era are [[Qutatqu Bilik]] (Wisdom Of Royal Glory) by [[Yusuf Balasaghuni|Yüsüp Has Hajip]] (1069-70), [[Kashgarli Mehmud|Mähmut Qäşqäri]]'s ''Divan-i Lugat-it Türk''- A Dictionary of Turkic Dialects(1072), and [[Ähmät Yüknäki]]'s ''Atabetul Hakayik''. Perhaps the most famous and well loved pieces of modern Uyghur literature are [[Abdurehim Otkur]]'s ''Iz'', ''Oyghanghan Zimin'', [[Zordun Sabir]]'s ''Anayurt'' and [[Ziya Samedi]]'s (former minister of culture in Sinkiang Government in 50's) novels ''Mayimkhan'' and ''Mystery of the years'' .

===Holy Books===
Aside from the [[Quran]], [[Sufi]] verse, and a host of exegetical and legal texts of the Islamic tradition, all of which have long been the main religious texts in the Arabic, Persian, Chaghatai, and Uyghur languages, fragments of Buddhist and Christian texts dating from a very early time were also found in [[Turpan]]. In the beginning of the 1900's a Turkish Christian [[Johannes Avetaranian]] translated the New Testament and parts of the Old Testament into Uyghur. After he left Xinjiang, Swedish Christians revised and updated the text many times, as well as completed a translation of the Old Testament. [[George Hunter (missionary)|George Hunter]] in Urumqi, a Scottish Christian also translated some portions of the Scripture. Also many other text's about [[Jesus]] were translated. A complete modern revision of the Christians' holy books is in progress.

===Medicine===
The Uyghurs had an extensive knowledge of medicine and medical practice. Chinese [[Song Dynasty]] (906-960) sources indicate that a Uyghur physician named Nanto traveled to China and brought with him many kinds of medicine unknown to the Chinese. There were 103 different herbs for use in Uyghur medicine recorded in a medical compendium by [[Li Shizhen]] (1518-1593), a [[Traditional Chinese medicine|Chinese medical]] authority. Some scholars believe that [[acupuncture]] was originally a Uyghur discovery, not a Chinese discovery.&lt;ref&gt;Professor Rashid Rahmeti Arat, Zur Heilkunde der Uighuren (Medical Practices of the Uygurs), Berlin (1930 and 1932)&lt;/ref&gt; 

Today, traditional Uyghur medicine can still be found at street stands. Similar to other traditional medicine, diagnosis is usually made through checking the pulse, symptoms, and disease history, and then the pharmacist pounds up different dried herbs, making personalized medicines according to the prescription.  Modern Uyghur medical hospitals adopted the Western medical system and apply advanced Western pharmaceutical technologies to purify and produce traditional medicines that are effective for a few chronic and rare diseases.

===Art===
{{section-stub}}
The cave paintings at [[Bezeklik]] and Kizil.
[[Image:Turpan-bezeklik-pinturas-d02.jpg|thumb|left|Wall painting at [[Bezeklik Thousand Buddha Caves|Bezeklik caves]] in Flaming Mountains, Turpan Depression]]
[[Image:Wall painting from Kizil.jpg|thumb|middle|Wall painting from [[Kizil Caves|Kizil caves]] (Red caves) near Kucha, Tarim Basin]]

===Music===
{{section-stub}}
Uyghurs have over 62 different kinds of musical instruments; most Uyghur homes have a [[dutar]]. The 12 [[Muqam]]s is perhaps the Uyghurs' most well known music. Uyghur music has close ties with [[Persian music]].

==Orthography==
{{main|Uyghur alphabet}}
Throughout the centuries, the Uyghurs have used the following scripts: 
#Confederated with the [[Göktürks]] in the 6th and 7th centuries, they used the [[Orkhon script]].
#In the 5th century, they adopted [[Sogdian]] italic script which became known as the Uyghur script. This script was used for almost 800 years, not only by the Uyghurs, but also by other Turkic peoples, by the Mongols, and by the Manchus in the early stage of their rule in China.
#After embracing Islam in the 10th century, the Uyghurs adopted the Arabic alphabet, and its use became common in the 11th century.
#During a short period of time (1969-1987), Uyghurs in China used a Latin script (yengi yazik).
#Today the Uyghurs of the former Soviet Union use [[Cyrillic]], the Uyghurs of [[Xinjiang]] (Eastern Turkestan) use a modified Arabic script, and the Uyghurs of Turkey use the Latin alphabet.

==See also==
*[[List of Uyghurs]]
*[[Uyghur language]]
*[[East Turkestan|East Turkestan/Uyghurstan]]
*[[Kushan Empire]]
*[[Uyghur detainees in Guantanamo]]
*[[Uyghur timeline]]

==Notes==
&lt;div class="references-small"&gt;&lt;references /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

==References==
* http://acc6.its.brooklyn.cuny.edu/~phalsall/texts/chinethn.html 
* Anderson, Elise. 2006. ''The muqam in modern Uyghur Life''. Oklahoma Baptist University. Honors project. Shawnee, Oklahoma: Oklahoma Baptist University.
* Findley, Carter Vaughn. 2005. ''The Turks in World History''. Oxford University Press. ISBN 0-19-516770-8; 0-19-517726-6 (pbk.)
* Human Rights in China: ''China, Minority Exclusion, Marginalization and Rising Tensions'', London, Minority Rights Group International, 2007 
* Kamberi, Dolkun. 2005. ''Uyghurs and Uyghur identity''. Sino-Platonic papers, no. 150. Philadelphia, PA: Dept. of East Asian Languages and Civilizations, University of Pennsylvania.
* Mackerras, Colin. Ed. and trans. 1972. '''''The Uighur Empire''' according to the T'ang Dynastic Histories: a study in Sino-Uyghur relations 744–840''. University of South Carolina Press. ISBN 0-87249-279-6
* Millward, James A. and Nabijan Tursun, ''Political History and Strategies of Control, 1884–1978'' in ''Xinjiang: China's Muslim Borderland'' ISBN 0-7656-1318-2
* Rall, Ted. ''Silk Road to Ruin: Is Central Asia the New Middle East?'' New York: NBM Publishing, 2006.
* Rudelson, Justin Ben-Adam, ''Oasis identities: Uyghur nationalism along China's Silk Road'', New York: Columbia University Press, 1997.

== External links ==
{{sisterlinks|Uyghurs}}
*[http://www.forcedmigration.org/video/uyghur/ Lost Nation: Stories from the Uyghur diaspora] An introduction to the Uyghur Diaspora and links to resources 
*[http://www.forcedmigration.org/video/uyghur/media/ Lost Nation: Stories from the Uyghur diaspora] A documentary film in which five Uyghurs from five cities around the world tell their personal story of migration.
* [http://www.qub.ac.uk/cibr/talkingborders.htm Talking Borders] Queen's University Belfast online audio archive talk by Dr Michael Dillon
*[http://www.uyghurcongress.org/ The World Uyghur Congress]
*[http://baltimorechronicle.com/2007/061407Hickman.shtml Unintended Uiyghurs] 
*[http://depts.washington.edu/silkroad/texts/tangshu/tangshu.html The “New T’ang History” (''Hsin T’ang-shu'') on the History of the Uighurs] Translated and annotated by Colin Mackerras
*[http://www.uhrp.org/ The Uyghur Human Rights Project]
*[http://www.uyghuramerican.org/ The Uyghur American Association]
*[http://www.turkistanim.org/ East Turkistan Information]
*[http://homepages.utoledo.edu/nlight/uyghpg.htm  Introduction to Uyghur Culture and History] Links to cultural and historical background, current news, research materials and photographs.
*[http://www.stevegongphoto.com/gallery/707846/ Photos of Uyghur People]
*[http://www.gokbayrak.com/turkistan.asp?inc=&amp;dil=ingilizce East Turkestan Culture and Solidarity Association, Kayseri, Turkey] Information website by Uyghur diaspora in living in Turkey
*[http://the_uighurs.tripod.com/index.htm/ The Uighurs] Independent Tripod Site
*[http://www.uyghur1.com/ Uyghur News Site]
*[http://saveeastturk.org/en/index.php Save East Turkistan]
*[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZL56XQx5pvE&amp;mode=related&amp;search= Information Video]
*[http://www.uyghur.TV/ Uyghur | Uyghur Music | Uyghur Video | Uyghur TV]
===Language===
*[http://wiki.yulghun.com/ Online UyghurWikipedia]
*[http://www.uighurdictionary.com/ Online English-Uighur Dictionary]
*[http://www.uyghurdictionary.org/ An Uyghur-English Multiscript Dictionary]
*[http://www.uighurlanguage.com/ UighurLanguage.com]
*[http://dict.yulghun.com/ Online Uyghur-English Dictionary]
*[http://groups.yahoo.com/group/UyghurLanguage/ Uyghur Language Discussion Group]
*[http://kenjisoft.homelinux.com/lughet/ English-Uyghur Online Dictionary]
*[http://groups.yahoo.com/group/uygurlar/ Uyghur Email Groups]
*[http://injil.net]

===Guantanamo Uyghur FOIA Documents===
*[http://www.defenselink.mil/pubs/foi/detainees/csrt/Set_4_0320-0464.pdf Uyghur testimony before Combatant Status Review Tribunal in Guantanamo Bay, Cuba]

&lt;br/&gt;{{Ethnic groups in China}}

&lt;!--Categories--&gt;
&lt;!--Other languages--&gt;

[[Category:Uyghurs| ]]
[[Category:Languages of Pakistan]]
[[Category:Turkic peoples]]
[[Category:Central Asians]]
[[Category:Ethnic groups in Kazakhstan]]
[[Category:Ethnic groups in Kyrgyzstan]]
[[Category:Ethnic groups in Uzbekistan]]
[[Category:Muslim communities]]
[[Category:Islam in China]]

[[ar:يوغور]]
[[az:Uyğurlar]]
[[bg:Уйгури]]
[[ca:Uigurs]]
[[da:Uighur]]
[[de:Uiguren]]
[[es:Uigur]]
[[fr:Ouïgours]]
[[ko:위구르족]]
[[it:Uiguri]]
[[lt:Uigūrai]]
[[nl:Oejgoers]]
[[ja:ウイグル人]]
[[no:Uighurer]]
[[ug:Uyghur]]
[[pl:Ujgurzy]]
[[pt:Uigure (etnia)]]
[[ru:Уйгуры]]
[[fi:Uiguurit]]
[[vi:Người Uyghur]]
[[tr:Uygur]]
[[zh:维吾尔族]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>