<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20051111032152|27989380" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="31783" pageid="31783" ns="0" title="Uyghurs"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-11-11T16:30:20Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">The '''Uyghur''' (also called '''Uighur''', '''Uygur''', or '''Uigur''') [pronounced ''WEE-gurs''] ({{zh-stp| s=维吾尔 |t=維吾爾 |p=wéiwú'ěr}})  are a [[Turkic]]-speaking [[ethnic group]] living in northwestern [[China]] (mainly in the [[Xinjiang]] Uygur Autonomous Region, where they are the largest ethnic group together with [[Han Chinese|Han]] people), [[Uzbekistan]], [[Kazakhstan]], [[Kyrgyzstan]], [[Turkey]], and [[Russia]]. Another group of Uyghurs lives in [[Taoyuan County, Hunan|Taoyuan County]] of [[Hunan]] province in Southcentral [[China]]. Uyghurs form one of the [[List of Chinese ethnic groups|56 ethnic groups]] officially recognized by the [[People's Republic of China]].

[[Image:uighurchildren.jpg|thumb|right|300px|Uyghur children.]]

==Origins==
Historically the term "Uyghur" (meaning "united" or "allied") was applied to a group of Turkic-speaking tribes that lived in what is now Mongolia.  Along with the so-called Kokturks (a.k.a. [[Gokturks]]), the Uyghurs were one of the largest and most enduring [[Turkic]] peoples living in [[Central Asia]].  They existed as a tribal federation ruled by the [[Juan Juan]] from [[460]]–[[545]], and then by the [[Hephthalites]] from [[541]]–[[565]] before being taken over by the Gokturk empire ([[Khanate|Khaganate]]).

[[Image:Gokturkut.jpg|right|thumb|200px|Map of the Western (purple) and Eastern (blue) Gokturk [[khagan]]ates at their height, c. 600 AD. Lighter areas show direct rule; darker areas show spheres of influence.]]

Known as '''Huihe''' (回紇 huíhé) and Huihu in Chinese sources, Under  Khutlugh Bilge Kul [[Khagan]]'s leadership, they established an empire ([[Khagan]]ate) in the [[8th century]] and replaced the [[Gokturks]].  Their [[ethnonym]] Huihu is the origin of the term Huihui (回回) which came to be used for [[Muslim]]s in Chinese and which is now used for the [[Hui people|Hui]] nationality in China.

Their empire stretched from the [[Caspian Sea]] to [[Manchuria]], and lasted from [[745]]–[[840]], when they were overrun by the [[Kirghiz]], another Turkic people.  The result was that the majority of tribal groups formerly under the umbrella of the Uyghurs migrated to what is now modern [[Xinjiang]].  Joined by other [[Turkic]] tribal groups living in [[Zungaria]] and the [[Tarim Basin]], they established the Idiqut kingdom which lasted until [[1209]] when they submitted to the [[Mongols]] under [[Genghis Khan]]. Others, occupying western Tarim Basin, [[Fergana Valley]], and parts of Kazakhstan bordering the Muslim, Turco-Tajik [[Khwarezmia|Khwarazm]] Sultanate, converted to [[Islam]] no later than 10th century and built a federation with Muslim institutions called Kara-Khanlik, whose princely dynasties are called Kara-Khanids by historians.

After the rise of the [[Seljuk Turks|Seljuks]] in [[Iran]], the [[Kara-Khanid]]s became nominal vassals of the Seljuks. Later they would serve the dual [[suzerainty]] of both the Kara-Khitans to the north and the Seljuks to the south.

In his now dated book ''Empire Of The Steppes'', [[René Grousset]] reports that the Uyghurs took up a settled agricultural lifestyle in the Tarim.  They had an opportunity to resume [[nomad]]ism after the Kirghiz were driven out of Mongolia by other tribes, but the Uyghurs chose not to do so.

[[Image:Uyghurmap.jpg|right|thumb|200px|Map of the Uyghur Khaganate and areas under its dominion (in yellow) at its height, c. 820 AD.]]

A small number of Uyghurs also migrated to what is now [[Gansu]] province in China around the late [[9th century]], where they converted from [[Manicheism]] to [[Tibetan Buddhism]]. Unlike other Turkic peoples further west, they did not later convert to Islam; they are thus unusual amongst Turkic peoples.  Their descendants still live there to this day, where they are known as [[Yugur]]s (population approximately 10,000).  They are distinct from modern Uyghurs.

Most Uyghurs in the [[Besh Balik]] and [[Turfan]] regions did not convert until the [[15th century]] expansion of the [[Yarkand]] Khanate, a Turko-Mongol [[successor state]] based in the western Tarim. With conversion to Islam, the traditional ethnonym Uyghur was dropped and the population of what is now modern Xinjiang identified themselves by the terms [[Turki]] and Muslims.

Before converting to Islam, Uyghurs included [[Manichaean]]s, [[Buddhist]]s and even some [[Nestorian]] [[Christianity|Christians]]. Genetically and culturally, modern Uyghurs descend from the nomadic Turkic tribes from Mongolia as well as the many Indo-European speaking groups who preceded them in the Tarim Basin oasis cities.  Today, one can still see Uyghurs with light-coloured skin and hair. At the present time, the Turkic and Islamic cultural elements are dominant in the Tarim, reflecting Turkic emigration to the Tarim region, especially during the Mongol period, as well as the replacement of previous religious traditions by Islam. 

This has had an effect on modern politics, due to this very long, off-and-on relitionship, politically, militarily, and culturally, with China.  Chinese rule was in the remote past solid at times in these regions until the [[An Lu Shan]] Rebellion and the [[Battle of Talas]] both of which were in the 750s.  China ruled in the region existed at times as far back as 100 A.D. or so.  This history goes far to explain a troubled relationship with past and present Chinese institutions and with the dominant Chinese ethnic group, the [[Han]].

Modern usage of the Uyghur ethnonym is used to give an ethnic definition to a traditional Central Asian distinction between nomads and settled farmers.  It refers to the descendants of settled Turkic [[urban area|urban]] [[oasis]]-dwelling and agricultural populations of Xinjiang as opposed to those Turkic groups that remained nomadic.  It is widely credited as having been used for the first time in [[1921]] with the establishment of the [[Organization of Revolutionary Uyghur]] (Inqilawi Uyghur Itipaqi), a [[Communist]] [[nationalist]] group with intellectual and organizational ties to the [[Soviet Union]].

There is some evidence that Uyghur students and merchants living in [[Russia]] had already embraced the name prior this date, drawing on Russian studies that claimed a linkage between the historical khanate and Xinjiang's current inhabitants. Official recognition of the Uyghurs came under the rule of [[Sheng Shicai]], who deviated from the official [[Kuomintang]] "five races of China" stance in favor of a [[Stalinist]] policy of delineating fourteen distinct ethnic nationalities within Xinjiang. Despite the efforts of the Chinese government and Uyghur intellectuals it is not a particularly favored term in modern Xinjiang.  Most modern Uyghurs prefer to describe themselves as [[Muslim]]s (if they are farmers) or Turkic (if they are intellectuals).

==Notable Uyghurs==

Famous Uyghurs include [[Tumen]], [[Koltekin]], [[Bayanchur Khan]], [[Sultan Satuq Bughra Khan]], [[Kashgarli Mehmud]] (Mehmud Kashgari), [[Yusuf Balasaguni]] (Yusuf Has Hajip), Farabi ([[Muhammad ibn Muhammad ibn Tarkhan ibn Uzalagh al-Farabi]]), [[Sultan Said Khan]], [[Abdurashid Khan]], [[Amannisa Khan]], [[Yakubbeg(Bedewlet)]], [[Fragrant Concubine|Ipar Khan]] (Xiang Fei), [[Ehmetjan Qasimi]], [[Mehmet Emin Boghra]], [[Turghun Almas]], Alptekins ([[Isa Yusuf Alptekin]] &amp; [[Erkin Alptekin]]), [[Rebiya Kadeer]], and [[Ismail Tiliwaldi]].

==References==
* Mackerras, Colin. Ed. and trans. 1972. '''''The Uighur Empire''' according to the T'ang Dynastic Histories: a study in Sino-Uyghur relations 744&amp;ndash;840''. University of South Carolina Press.
* Millward, James A. and Nabijan Tursun, "Political History and Strategies of Control, 1884&amp;ndash;1978" in ''Xinjiang: China's Muslim Borderland'' (ISBN 0765613182).
*Rudelson, Justin Ben-Adam, ''Oasis identities: Uyghur nationalism along China's Silk Road'', New York: Columbia University Press, 1997.

==See also==
*[[Uyghur language]]
*[[East Turkestan|East Turkestan/Uyghuristan]]
*[[Kushan]]
*[[Muqam]]

== External links ==
*[http://www.uyghurinfo.com/ Uyghur Information Agency]
*[http://www.uhrp.org/ The Uyghur Human Rights Project]
*[http://www.uyghuramerican.org/ The Uyghur American Association]
*[http://homepages.utoledo.edu/nlight/uyghpg.htm Uyghur Culture and History]
*[http://www.uyghuronline.com/ Uyghur Health]
*[http://www.biliwal.com/ News, Discussions]
*[http://www.uyghurtili.org/ Uyghurtili.org]
*[http://www.anatilim.com/ Anatilim.com]
*[http://www.ukij.org/ UKIJ-Uyghur Computer Science Association ]
*[http://www.bilik.cn/ Discussions, Software (Uyghur Edition)]

===Language===
*[http://www.uyghurdictionary.org/ An Uyghur-English Multiscript Dictionary]
*[http://www.uighurlanguage.com/ UighurLanguage.com]
*[http://dict.yulghun.com/ Online Uyghur-English Dictionary]
*[http://groups.yahoo.com/group/UyghurLanguage/ Uyghur Language Discussion Group]
*[http://kenjisoft.homelinux.com/lughet/ English-Uyghur Online Dictionary]

{{CEG}}

[[Category:Turkic peoples]]
[[Category:Anthropology]]
[[Category:Muslim communities]]

[[bg:Уйгури]]
[[de:Uiguren]]
[[es:Uigur]]
[[fr:Ouïgours]]
[[ja:ウイグル人]]
[[nl:Oejgoers]]
[[no:Uighurer]]
[[fi:Uiguurit]]
[[ug:Uighurs]]
[[zh:维吾尔族]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>