<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061028004542|84153082" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="66936" pageid="66936" ns="0" title="LGBTQ"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-11-11T17:59:03Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Portal|LGBT|Gay flag.svg|50px}}
'''LGBT''' (or '''GLBT''') is an abbreviation used as a collective term to refer to [[lesbian|'''L'''esbian]], [[gay|'''G'''ay]], [[bisexuality|'''B'''isexual]], and [[transgender|'''T'''ransgender]] people. It is an adaptation of the abbreviation LGB. While still controversial (see [[LGBT#Controversy|Controversy]] below), it is considered less controversial than the terms ''[[queer]]'' or ''lesbigay'' and is more comprehensive than ''[[homosexual]]'' or simply ''[[gay]]''. The acronym '''GLBT''' is sometimes used in the [[United States]] and commonly in [[Australia]], but to a lesser extent elsewhere. 

Many variants exist. The most commonly used involve adding a '''''Q''''' for ''[[queer]]'' or ''[[Bi-curious|questioning]]'' (some variants, in fact, use ''two'' Qs to represent ''both'' of these groups), an '''''A''''' for [[asexual]] or allies (and sometimes ''''S'''' for ''[[straight ally]]''), an '''''I''''' for ''[[intersex]]'', or a '''''P''''' for ''[[pansexual]]'' or ''[[polyamory|polyamorous]]''. Some even add an '''''O''''' for ''[[omnisexual]]'' or ''other''.
{{LGBT}}
==Meaning of each term==
Each term in the acronym is used to refer to members of the specific group and to the ''community'' ([[subculture]]) that surrounds them. This can include rights advocates, artists, authors, etc.

===Lesbian===
{{see details|lesbian}}

In this context, lesbian refers to females with a [[sexual orientation]] towards females only.

===Gay===
{{see details|gay}}

In this context, ''gay'' refers specifically to males with a sexual orientation towards males only; and the gay male community, though the term can be used without respect to the gender of the person in question in wider contexts. Some aspects of stereotypical gay male culture are seen in, and sometimes said to be the basis of, [[metrosexual]] traits amongst some [[heterosexuality|straight]] males.

===Bisexual===
{{see details|bisexuality}}

Bisexual refers to persons who are attracted more than just one gender. While traditionally bisexuality has been defined as 'an attraction to both males and females', it commonly encompasses [[Pansexuality]], 'an attraction where the gender of the partner is of little or no relevance' (i.e. to male, female, and [[transgender|any other gender identity]]).  Bisexuality covers anywhere between the sexual orientations of [[asexuality]], homosexuality, and heterosexuality.

===Transgender===
{{see details|transgender}}

Transgender is generally used as a catch-all [[umbrella term]] for a variety of individuals, behaviors, and groups centered around the full or partial reversal of gender roles as well as physical sexual reassignment therapies (which can be just hormonal or involve various degrees of surgical alteration). A common definition is "People who feel that the gender they were assigned (usually at birth) is a false or incomplete description of themselves." Included in this definition are a number of well known sub-categories such as [[transsexual]], [[transvestism|transvestite]] and sometimes [[genderqueer]]s. (See also [[cross-dressing]].)

===Intersex===
{{see details|intersexuality}}

This term (represented by the letter "''I''" in the ''LGBTI'' and ''GLBTI'' initialisms) may or may not be included, and some intersex communities are not inclusive of non-intersex LGBT persons (while some are).

''Intersex'' refers to ambiguous or mismatching [[sexual characteristics]] (including levels of [[sex hormone]]s) and those people who have them. This is distinct from the older term [[hermaphrodite]], which is generally not accurate when referring to [[vertebrates]] (including humans). In many cases, the line between intersex and transgender is complex, and some individuals fit into both classifications.

==History==
{{Main|LGBT history}}

Up until the [[sexual revolution]] of the [[1960s]] there were no widely known terms for describing the people in these groups other than the derogatory terms used by the [[heterosexual|straight]] community; [[third gender]], in use before the second world war, fell out of use after it. As people began organizing for their sexual rights they needed a term that would say who they were in a positive way. (Compare [[heteronormativity]]) 

The first term used, ''[[homosexual]]'', carried too much negative baggage and was replaced by ''gay''. As lesbians forged their own identity, the term ''gay and lesbian'' became more common.  This was soon followed by bisexual and transgender people also asking for recognition as a legitimate categories within the larger community.  However, after the initial euphoria of the beginnings of the [[Stonewall Rebellion]] wore off, starting in the late  1970s and early 1980s, there was a change in perception and some gay men and lesbian women were not very accepting of bisexual or transgender people, and disparaged them. 

They accused transsexual people of as acting out [[stereotypes]]; and bisexual people of actually being gay men or lesbian women who were simply too afraid to "[[come out]]".  

Not until the 1990s did it become common for people to speak of "gay, lesbian, bisexual and transgender people" with equal respect within the movement.    

''LGBT'' became increasingly common from the mid [[1990s]] and [[as of 2005]], ''LGBT'' has become so mainstream that it has been adopted by the majority of [[List of lesbian, gay, bisexual and transgender community centers|lesbian, gay, bisexual, and transgender community centers]] and the LGBT press in most [[English language|English]]-speaking countries. Although still today it is often questionable as to whether someone or a group using the term is doing so in a tokenistic manner, and is actually only committed to lesbian &amp; gay issues (or even just gay mens' issues).

==Variants==
Many variants exist, including variations which merely change the order of the letters; but ''LGBT'' is the most common acronym and the one most accepted in current usage. When not inclusive of transgender people it is shortened to '''LGB'''. It may also include two additional ''Q''s for ''[[queer]]'' and ''questioning'' (sometimes abbreviated with a question mark) ('''LGBTQ''', '''LGBTQQ'''); a variant being '''LGBU''', where ''U'' stands for "unsure", an ''I'' for [[intersex]] ('''LGBTI'''), another ''T'' for ''[[transsexual]]'' ('''LGBTT'''), another ''T'' (or ''TS'' or the numeral 2) for ''[[Two-Spirit|two-spirited]]'' people, and an ''A'' for straight ''[[straight ally|allies]]'' or ''[[asexual]]'' ('''LGBTA'''). At its fullest, then, it is some permutation of '''LGBTTTIQQA''', though this is extremely rare. The order of the letters is also not standardized; in addition to the uses which reverse the initial L and G, the extended letters, if used, may appear in almost any order. 

The magazine ''[[Anything That Moves]]'' coined the acronym '''FABGLITTER''' (from [[Sexual fetishism|Fetish]], Allies, Bisexual, Gay, Lesbian, Intersexed, Transgender, Transsexual Engendering [[Revolution]]), although this term has not made its way into common usage.

The terms transsexual and intersex are regarded by some people as falling under the umbrella term ''transgender'', though many transsexual and intersex people object to this (both for different reasons). [[Gay-straight alliance]] (GSA) organizations often use '''LGBTQA''' for ''LBGT, questioning and allies''.

Some variants are local alterations that are used to the exclusion of others by virtue of being commonplace in a region. For example, in [[Minnesota]] the term ''GLBT'' is more prominent.

'''SGL''' (for ''same gender loving'') is often favored by [[African-American]] homosexuals as a way of distinguishing themselves from what they regard as [[white (people)|white]]-dominated LGBT communities.

'''LUG''' (for ''[[lesbian until graduation]]''), '''GUG''' (''gay until graduation'')  and '''BUG''' (''bisexual until graduation'') are facetious terms for young people (most commonly female) who experiment with same-sex relationships on a temporary basis, particularly while attending college or university.

==Controversy==
The term ''LGBT'' is controversial. For example, some transgender and transsexual people do not like the term because they do not believe their cause is the same as that of LGB people; they may also object when an organization adds a ''T'' to their acronym when the level of service they actually offer to trans people is questionable. There are also LGB people who don't like the ''T'' for the same or similar reasons. 

Many people also believe that a sharp distinction should be drawn between [[sexual orientation]] and [[gender identity]]. ''GLB'' concerns the former; ''TTI'' concerns the latter.

Similarly, some intersex people want to be included into LGBT groups and would prefer ''LGBTI''; others insist that they are not a part of the LGBT community and would rather not be included in the acronym.

A reverse to the above situations is evident in the belief of 'lesbian &amp; gay separatism' (not to be confused with the related, [[Lesbian Separatism]]) which holds that Lesbians and Gay men form (or should form) a community distinct and separate from other groups normally included in the LGBTQ sphere. While not always appearing of sufficient number or organisation to be called a '[[social movement|movement]]', this group persists as a significant, and often vocal/active, element within most part of the LGBT community. This is particularly noticeable in [[UK]] political and campaign organisations. People of this opinion will commonly also deny the existence or right-to-equality of non-[[monosexuality|monosexual]] orientations and of [[transexuality]]. This can extend to public [[biphobia]] and [[transphobia]].

Many people have looked for a generic term to replace acronyms. Words like "[[queer]]" and "rainbow" have been tried but most have not been widely adopted. "Queer" has many negative connotations to older people who remember the word as a taunt and insult, a usage of the term which has continued. Many younger people also understand "queer" to be more politically charged than "LGBT". "Rainbow" has connotations that recall the [[hippies]], [[New Age]] movements and politics ([[Jesse Jackson]]'s [[Rainbow Coalition]].)

Other gay people also do not care for the term as the lettering comes across as being overly [[Political correctness|Politically Correct]], or as an attempt to [[Categorization|categorize]] the various groups of people into one [[grey area]] word.

It is also worth noting that there are some Lesbian, Gay, and Bi people who are against an "LGBT community", or "LGB community", including the [[LGBT rights|political and social solidarity, and visability and human rights campaigning]] that normally goes with it (including [[gay pride|Pride]] marches and events). Some of them believe that grouping together people with non-hetero sexual orientations perpetuates the myth that being gay/lesbian/bi makes a person deficiently different than other people. This fraction of gay/lesbian/bi people are often not very visible compared to other LGBT people, as most of them blend into the general population showing few or zero external or social indicators as to their orientation, apart from interest in the same gender / when they are looking for a partner.

Since this fraction are difficult to distinguish from the heterosexual majority, it is common for people to assume all gay/lesbian/bi people support LGBT liberation and the visability of LGBT people in society, including the right to live your life in a different way to the majority.

==See also==

[[Portal:LGBT]]
*[[List of LGBT-related topics]]
*[[Asexual]]
*[[Gender]]
*[[Bisexual community]]
*[[Gay community]]
*[[Gay marketing]]
*[[List of transgender-related topics]]
*[[List of LGBT organizations]]
*[[List of LGBT publications]]
*[[List of LGBT blogs]]
*[[Queer theory]]
*[[Queer Theology]]
*[[Intersex]]


*[[Androphile]]
*[[bisexuality|Bisexual]]
*[[Ephebophile]]
*[[Gay]]
*[[Gynephile]]
*[[Homosexual]]
*[[Lesbian]]
*[[Pederast]]
*[[Queer]]
*[[Transgender]]

==External links==
{{wikiquotepar|Gay, lesbian, bisexual, and transgender}}
* [http://gayinfo.tripod.com/ Extensive set of short LGBT biographies]
* [http://www.glbt.ca/ GLBT.ca] A site containing GLBT profiles (mostly Canadian)
* [http://www.lgbtlink.co.uk/ LGBT Link] LGBT Community for UK University Students (UK Based)
* [http://www.glbtq.com/ GLBTQ] An Encyclopedia of GLBT &amp; Queer culture
* [http://www.queerfilter.com/ Queerfilter] A selection of blogs (or weblogs) by LGBT people and their friends
[[Category:LGBT| ]]
[[Category:LGBT terms]]

[[br:LGBT]]
[[bg:ЛГБТ]]
[[ca:LGBT]]
[[de:LGBT]]
[[es:LGBT]]
[[fr:LGBT]]
[[gl:LGBT]]
[[it:LGBT]]
[[he:להט"ב]]
[[mk:LGBTQ]]
[[nl:LGBT]]
[[no:LHB]]
[[pl:LGBT]]
[[pt:LGBT]]
[[ro:LGBT]]
[[simple:LGBT]]
[[sr:ЛГБТ]]
[[sh:LGBT]]
[[sv:HBT]]
[[zh:LGBT]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>