<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20071112180301|171000092" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="66936" pageid="66936" ns="0" title="LGBTQ"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-11-13T03:31:21Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Unreferenced|date=August 2007}}
{{Original research|date=October 2007}}
{{LGBT}}
The [[initialism]] '''LGBT''' (also '''GLBT''') is in use (since the 1990s) to refer collectively to [[lesbian|'''L'''esbian]], [[gay|'''G'''ay]], [[bisexuality|'''B'''isexual]], and [[transgender|'''T'''ransgender]] people. The acronym is an adaptation of the initial LGB. In modern use, the acronym relates the diversity of the [[Gay culture]].
Many variants exist. The most commonly used involve adding a '''''Q''''' for ''[[queer]]'' or ''[[Questioning (sexuality &amp; gender)|questioning]]'' (some variants, in fact, use ''two'' Qs to represent ''both'' of these groups), an '''''A''''' for [[asexual]] or allies (and sometimes ''''S'''' for ''[[straight ally]]''), a '''''T''''' or '''''2''''' for ''[[two spirit]]'', a '''''T''''' for ''[[transsexualism|transsexual]]'', an '''''I''''' for ''[[intersex]]'', or a '''''P''''' for ''[[pansexual]]'' or ''[[polyamory|polyamorous]]''. Some even add an '''''O''''' for ''[[omnisexual]]'' or ''other''.

==Meaning of each term==
Each term in the initialism is used to refer to members of the specific group and to the ''community'' ([[subculture]]) that surrounds them. This can include rights advocates, artists, authors, etc.

===Lesbian===
{{see details|lesbian}}

In this context, lesbian refers to females with a [[sexual orientation]] predominately (not necessarly exclusively) towards females.

===Gay===
{{see details|gay}}

In this context, ''gay'' refers specifically to males with a sexual orientation predominately (not necessarily exclusively) toward males.

===Bisexual===
{{see details|bisexuality}}

Bisexual refers to persons who are attracted to more than just one [[sex]]. While traditionally bisexuality has been defined as 'an attraction to both males and females', it commonly encompasses [[Pansexuality]], 'an attraction where the sex of the partner is of little or no relevance' (i.e. to male, female, and [[transgender|any other gender identity]]). Bisexuality covers anywhere between the sexual orientations of [[asexuality]], homosexuality, and heterosexuality.

===Transgender===
{{see details|transgender}}

Transgender is generally used as a catch-all [[umbrella term]] for a variety of individuals, behaviours, and groups centered around the full or partial reversal of gender roles as well as physical sexual reassignment therapies (which can be just hormonal or involve various degrees of surgical alteration). A common definition is "People who feel that the gender they were assigned (usually at birth) is a false or incomplete description of themselves." Included in this definition are a number of well known sub-categories such as [[transsexual]], [[transvestism|transvestite]] and sometimes [[genderqueer]]s. (See also [[cross-dressing]].)

==History==
{{Main|LGBT history}}

Up until the [[sexual revolution]] of the 1960s there were no widely known terms for describing the people in these groups other than the derogatory terms used by the [[heterosexual|straight]] community; [[third gender]], in use before the second world war, fell out of use after it. As people began organizing for their sexual rights they needed a term that would say who they were in a positive way. (Compare [[heteronormativity]])

The first term used, ''[[homosexual]]'', was thought to carry negative connotations and has tended to be replaced by ''gay''. As lesbians forged their own identity, the term ''gay and lesbian'' became more common. This was soon followed by bisexual and transgender people also asking for recognition as legitimate categories within the larger community. However, after the initial euphoria of the beginnings of the [[Stonewall Rebellion]] wore off, starting in the late 1970s and early 1980s, there was a change in perception and some gays and lesbians were not very accepting of bisexual or transgender people.

It was thought that transsexual people were acting out [[stereotypes]]; and bisexuals were simply gay men or lesbian women who were simply afraid to "[[come out]]" and be honest as to who their identity. Like may organisations, the movement underwent growing pains, and these are seen even today in the fact that there is no agreement as to whether the acronym should be GLBT or LGBT.

Not until the 1990s did it become common to speak of "gay, lesbian, bisexual and transgender people" with equal respect within the movement. Although the GLBT/LGBT community has seen some controversy regarding universal acceptance of different members (transgender individuals, in particular, have sometimes been marginalized by the larger GLBT/LGBT community), the term GLBT/LGBT has been a positive symbol of inclusion. Despite the fact that GLBT/LGBT does not nominally encompass all individuals in the queer communities (see Variants below), the term is generally accepted to include those not identified in the standard, four letter acronym. Overall, the use of the term GLBT/LGBT has, over time, largely aided in bringing otherwise marginalized individuals into the general community.

==Variants==
Many variants exist, including variations which merely change the order of the letters; but ''LGBT'' or ''GLBT'' are the most common terms and the ones most frequently seen in current usage.{{Fact|date=February 2007}} When not inclusive of transgender people it is shortened to '''LGB'''. It may also include two additional ''Q''s for ''[[queer]]'' and ''questioning'' (sometimes abbreviated with a question mark) ('''LGBTQ''', '''LGBTQQ''', '''GLBTQ2'''); a variant being '''LGBU''', where ''U'' stands for "unsure", an ''I'' for [[intersex]] ('''LGBTI'''), another ''T'' for ''[[transsexual]]'' ('''LGBTT'''), another ''T'' (or ''TS'' or the numeral 2) for ''[[Two-Spirit|two-spirited]]'' people, and an ''A'' for straight ''[[straight ally|allies]]'' or ''[[asexual]]'' ('''LGBTA'''). At its fullest, then, it is some permutation of '''LGBTTTIQQA''', though this is extremely rare. The order of the letters is also not standardized; in addition to the uses which reverse the initial L and G, the extended letters, if used, may appear in almost any order.

Variant terms do not typically represent political differences within the community, however, but arise simply from the usage preferences of individuals and groups.

The magazine ''[[Anything That Moves]]'' coined the acronym '''FABGLITTER''' (from [[Sexual fetishism|Fetish]], Allies, Bisexual, Gay, Lesbian, Intersexed, Transgender, Transsexual Engendering [[Revolution]]), although this term has not made its way into common usage.

The terms transsexual and intersex are regarded by some people as falling under the umbrella term ''transgender'', though many transsexual and intersex people object to this (both for different reasons). [[Gay-straight alliance]] (GSA) organizations often use '''LGBTQA''' for ''LBGT, questioning and allies''.

'''SGL''' (for ''[[same gender loving]]'') is often favored by [[African-American]] homosexuals as a way of distinguishing themselves from what they regard as [[white (people)|white]]-dominated LGBT communities.

'''LUG''' (for ''[[lesbian until graduation]]''), '''GUG''' (''gay until graduation'') and '''BUG''' (''bisexual until graduation'') are facetious terms for young people (most commonly female) who experiment with same-sex relationships on a temporary basis, particularly while attending college or university.

'''MSM''' (Men who have sex with men) is clinically used to describe men have sex with other men without referring to their sexual orientation.

==Controversy==
The terms ''LGBT'' or ''GLBT'' are not agreed upon by everyone. For example, it may be argued that the transgender and transsexual causes are not the same as that of LGB people: one has to do with sexual identity whilst the other is a matter of attraction. 

It may also be argued that a distinction should be drawn between [[sexual orientation]] and [[gender identity]] as orientation is to do with attraction whilst gender identity is a matter of a person's understanding of them being either male or female, irrespective of their sexual orientation. ''GLB'' concerns the former; ''TTI'' (Trangender Transexual Intersex) concerns the latter.

Similarly, some intersex people{{Fact|Weasel word|date=August 2007}} want to be included into LGBT groups and would prefer ''LGBTI''; others insist that they are not a part of the LGBT community and would rather not be included in the term.

A reverse to the above situations is evident in the belief of 'lesbian &amp; gay separatism' (not to be confused with the related, [[Lesbian Separatism]]) which holds that lesbians and gay men form (or should form) a community distinct and separate from other groups normally included in the LGBTQ sphere. While not always appearing of sufficient number or organization to be called a '[[social movement|movement']], this group persists as a significant, and often vocal and active, element within most parts of the LGBT community. This is particularly noticeable in [[United Kingdom|UK]] political and campaign organisations. People of this opinion will commonly also deny the existence or right-to-equality of non-[[monosexuality|monosexual]] orientations and of [[transsexualism|transsexuality]]. This can extend to public [[biphobia]] and [[transphobia]].

Many people have looked for a generic term to replace the initialisms, acronyms, and abbreviations. Words like "[[queer]]" and "rainbow" have been tried but most have not been widely adopted.{{Fact|date=November 2007}} "Queer" has many negative connotations to older people who remember the word as a taunt and insult, a usage of the term which has continued. Many younger people also understand "queer" to be more politically charged than "LGBT". "Rainbow" has connotations that recall the [[hippies]], [[New Age]] movements and politics ([[Jesse Jackson]]'s [[Rainbow Coalition]].)

Other gay people also do not care for the term as the lettering comes across as being overly "[[Political correctness|politically correct]]", or as an attempt to [[Categorization|categorize]] the various groups of people into one [[grey area]] word.

It is also worth noting that there are some lesbian, gay, and bi people who are against an "LGBT community", or "LGB community", including the [[LGBT rights|political and social solidarity, and visibility and human rights campaigning]] that normally goes with it (including [[gay pride|pride]] marches and events). Some of them believe that grouping together people with non-heterosexual orientations perpetuates the myth that being gay/lesbian/bi makes a person deficiently different than other people. This fraction of gay/lesbian/bi people are often not very visible compared to other LGBT people, as most of them blend into the general population showing few or zero external or social indicators as to their orientation, apart from interest in the same sex.

Since this fraction are difficult to distinguish from the heterosexual majority, it is common for people to assume all gay/lesbian/bi people support LGBT liberation and the visibility of LGBT people in society, including the right to live one's life in a different way to the majority.

==References==
* The LibraryThing Blog. [http://www.librarything.com/blog/2005/12/tags-again-glbt-vs-lgbt.php Tags again: GLBT vs. LGBT]. Published online.
* Safe Schools Coalition. [http://www.safeschoolscoalition.org/glossary.pdf Glossary]. Published online.
* Religious Institute. "Time to Seek" [http://www.religiousinstitute.org/documents/TimetoSeekdefinitions.pdf Definitions]. Published online.
* Stahl, S. [http://www.jewishlibraries.org/ajlweb/publications/proceedings/proceedings2004/stahl.pdf Sorting the Alphabet Soup of Sexual Orientation and Identity: a Guide to LBGT Sources]. Published online.
* Planned Parenthood (2002). Enhancing Cultural Competence. Welcoming the Lesbian, Gay, bisexual and Transgender Community. Published online.
* AVERT (1997). [http://www.avert.org/media/pdfs/homosexualityinschool.pdf Talking About Homosexuality in the Secondary School]. Published online.

==See also==
*[[Androphile]]
*[[Asexuality]]
*[[Bisexual community]]
*[[Gay community]]
*[[Gay marketing]]
*[[Gender]]
*[[Gynephile]]
*[[Homosexual]]
*[[Intersex]]
*[[LGBT rights opposition]]
*[[List of transgender-related topics]]
*[[List of LGBT publications]]
*[[List of LGBT-related organizations]]
*[[Queer theory]]
*[[Queer theology]]
*''[[Say Amen]]''
*[[Sex]]

==External links==
{{wikiquotepar|LGBT}}
{{wiktionary|GLBT}}

* [http://www.gaycityusa.com/ LGBT Web site directory]
* [http://gayinfo.tripod.com/ Extensive set of short LGBT biographies]
* [http://www.glbtq.com/ GLBTQ] An Encyclopedia of GLBT &amp; Queer culture
* [http://outwithcancer.com/ LGBT Cancer Research and Social Network - OutWithCancer]
* [http://lgbtfriends.meetup.com/138/ Atlanta LGBT Group] (Metro Atlanta Area, Georgia)

[[Category:LGBT|LGBT]]
[[Category:LGBT terms]]
[[Category:Acronyms]]
[[Category:Neologisms]]

[[br:LGBT]]
[[bg:ЛГБТ]]
[[ca:LGBT]]
[[cy:LHDT]]
[[de:LGBT]]
[[es:LGBT]]
[[eo:GLAT]]
[[fr:LGBT]]
[[gl:LGBT]]
[[ko:LGBT]]
[[it:LGBT]]
[[he:להט"ב]]
[[hu:LMBT]]
[[mk:LGBTQ]]
[[nl:LGBT]]
[[ja:LGBT]]
[[no:LHB]]
[[uz:LGBT]]
[[pl:LGBT]]
[[pt:GLBT]]
[[ro:LGBT]]
[[simple:LGBT]]
[[sr:ЛГБТ]]
[[sh:LGBT]]
[[sv:HBT]]
[[zh:LGBT]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>