<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20041011151620|6772887" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="66936" pageid="66936" ns="0" title="LGBTQ"><revisions><rev timestamp="2004-10-22T15:19:38Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[pl:LGBT]]
[[fr:LGBT]]
[[Category:LGBT]]
'''LGBT''' (or '''GLBT''') is an [[acronym]] used as a collective term to refer to [[lesbian]]s, [[gay]]s, [[bisexual]]s, and [[transgender]] people. It is considered less controversial than the terms "[[queer]]" or "[[lesbigay]]".

Many variants exist, including permutations which merely change the order of the letters. When not inclusive of transgender people it is LGB. It may also include two additional Qs for queer and questioning (LGBTQ, LGBTQQ), an I for [[intersexual]] (LGBTI), another T for [[transsexual]] (LGBTT), and an A for [[straight ally|straight allies]] (LGBTA). At its fullest, then, it is LGBTTIQQA, though this is exteremely rare. It can also be noted that the terms [[transsexual]] and [[intersex]] are regarded by some people as falling under the umbrella term ''transgender'', though many transsexual and intersex people object to this (both for different reasons). [[Gay-Straight Alliance]] (GSA) organizations often use LGBTQA for LGBT...questioning and allies.

As of 2004, LGBT had become so mainstream, it has been adoped by the majority of [[List of lesbian, gay, bisexual and transgender community centers|lesbian, gay, bisexual, and transgender community centers]] and the [[gay press]] in most English-speaking countries. 

===See also===
*[[Gay community]]
*[[Homosexuality]]
*[[Queer]]
*[[List of gay-related topics]]
*[[List of transgender-related topics]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>