<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20071002214634|161883131" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="355849" pageid="355849" ns="0" title="Equal opportunity"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-10-11T01:16:29Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{ redirect3|Equal opportunities|for the [[Yes Minister]] episode see [[Equal Opportunities (Yes Minister)]]}}

'''Equal opportunity''' is a descriptive term for an approach intended to provide a certain [[social environment]] in which people are not excluded from the activities of society, such as [[education]], [[employment]], or [[health care]], on the basis of [[immutable]] traits. Equal opportunity practices include measures taken by organizations to ensure fairness in the employment process.

In job advertisements and descriptions, the fact that the employer is an equal opportunity employer is sometimes indicated by the abbreviations EOE or MFDV which stands for Male, Female, Disabled, Veteran.

==Social Theory==
In the pursuit of a [[meritocracy]], equal opportunity is essential. 

Equal Opportunity is often considered separate from basic Freedoms. For example, Freedom of Speech is usually not within the realm of Equal Opportunity but rather within basic rights. Equal Opportunity consists of additional elements crucial to a meritocracy, such as:
*Consideration for employment, housing, and education free from immutable characteristics such as race, age, or disability;
*Equal access to goods and services from the government

In practice, methods for fulfilling equal opportunity can be less than complete or ineffective. Indeed, the means by which to measure the success or failure of equal opportunity policies is unclear. ''Opportunity'' itself is often difficult - if not impossible - to accurately measure. Thus, in practice, equal opportunity is said to exist when people with similar abilities reach similar results ([[equality of outcome]]) after doing a similar amount of work. Indeed, equal opportunity and equality of outcome are often seen as complementary. Other societal traditions interfere with equality of opportunity, however; for example, as long as wealth, and thus opportunities, can be passed from one [[generation]] to another through [[inheritance]], it is unclear how equality of outcome would come about for two children of similar ability, one born into the elite class and one born into the middle or lower class.

==See also==
* [[Asset-based egalitarianism]]
* [[Affirmative action]]
* [[Equal Opportunity Employment]]
* [[Universal access]]
* [[Centre for Equal Opportunities and Opposition to Racism]] (Belgium)
* [[Commission for Equality and Human Rights|Commission for Equality and Human Rights (UK)]]
* [[Commission for Racial Equality|Commission for Racial Equality (UK)]]
* [[Disability Rights Commission|Disability Rights Commission (UK)]]
* [[Equal Employment Opportunity Commission|Equal Employment Opportunity Commission (US)]]
* [[Equal Opportunities Commission|Equal Opportunities Commission (UK)]] - gender equality
* [[Human Rights and Equal Opportunity Commission|Human Rights and Equal Opportunity Commission (Australia)]]
* Office of [[Fair housing]] and Equal Opportunity
* [[New Brunswick Equal Opportunity program]]
* [[U.S. Commission on Civil Rights]]
* [[Directorate-General for Employment, Social Affairs and Equal Opportunities|Directorate-General for Employment, Social Affairs and Equal Opportunities (EU)]]
* [[Equality inclusion]]
* [[Equality of outcome]]

==External links==
*United Kingdom
**[http://www.womenandequalityunit.gov.uk/ UK Government Women &amp; Equality Unit]
**[http://www.scoutbase.org.uk/library/hqdocs/eqopps/index.htm The Scout Association of the UK]
*United States
**[http://www.eeoc.gov/ U.S. Equal Employment Opportunity Commission (EEOC) (US)] - the branch of the U.S. government that enforces equal opportunity laws in workplaces.
**[http://www.doi.gov/diversity/ Department of the Interior Office for Equal Opportunity (US)]
*[http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/equal-opportunity/ Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy entry on Equality of Opportunity]
[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Disability rights]]
[[Category:Anti-racism]]
[[Category:Civil rights]]
[[de:Chancengleichheit]]
[[es:Igualdad de oportunidades]]
[[fr:Égalité des chances]]
[[nl:Gelijkwaardige behandeling]]
[[ja:男女同権]]
[[fi:Mahdollisuuksien tasa-arvo]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>