<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20050831175109|22265359" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="355849" pageid="355849" ns="0" title="Equal opportunity"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-09-26T10:55:08Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Equal opportunity''' is a descriptive term for an approach intended to give equal access to an [[social environment|environment]] or benefits, such as [[education]], [[employment]], [[health_care|health care]], or [[social_welfare|social welfare]] to all, often with emphasis on members of various social groups which might have at some time suffered from [[discrimination]]. This can involve the hiring of workers and other such practices. Social groupings generally emphasized in such a way are those delineated by aspects of [[gender]], [[race]], or [[religion]].  

Equal opportunity practices that are [[race-blind]] or [[gender-blind]] may be distinguished from practices that involve or require [[affirmative action]] or [[reverse discrimination]]. The [[United States federal government]] and various state and [[local government]]s require affirmative action in terms of governmental hiring and contracting; many other countries make such action illegal.

The method of providing equal opportunity is often a subject of controversy, as is the means by which to measure the success or failure of equal opportunity policies. ''Opportunity'' itself is often difficult - if not impossible - to accurately measure. Thus, in practice, equal opportunity is said to exist when people with similar abilities reach similar results after doing a similar amount of work. In other words, equal opportunity is measured by the degree of [[equality of outcome]] that it generates. Indeed, equal opportunity and equality of outcome are often seen as complementary. For example, as long as inequalities can be passed form one [[generation]] to another through gifts and wealth [[inheritance]], it is unclear that equality of opportunity for children can be achieved without greater equality of outcome for parents.

==See also==
*[[Universal access]]
*[[Equal Employment Opportunity Commission|Equal Employment Opportunity Commission (US)]]
*[[Office of Fair Housing and Equal Opportunity|Office of Fair Housing and Equal Opportunity  (US)]]
*[[Equal Opportuinity (New Brunswick)]]

==External links==
*Australia
**[http://www.hreoc.gov.au/ Australian Human Rights and Equal Opportunity Commission]
*United Kingdom
**[http://www.eoc.org.uk/ The Equal Opportunities Commission (gender equality)]
**[http://www.womenandequalityunit.gov.uk/ UK Governmen Women &amp; Equality Unit]
**[http://www.cre.gov.uk/ The Commission for Racial Equality (racial equality)]
**[http://www.drc-gb.org/ Disability Rights Commission (disablement equality)]
*United States
**[http://www.nafeo.org/ NAFEO - National Association For Equal Opportunity In Higher Education (US)]
**[http://www.doi.gov/diversity/ Department of the Interior Office for Equal Opportunity (US)]
**[http://www.ceousa.org/ Center for Equal Opportunity (US)]
*[http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/equal-opportunity/ Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy entry on Equality of Opportunity]

[[de:Chancengleichheit]]
[[fi:Mahdollisuuksien tasa-arvo]]

[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Social justice]]
[[Category:Rights of the disabled]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>