<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20091020095909|320975506" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="355849" pageid="355849" ns="0" title="Equal opportunity"><revisions><rev timestamp="2009-10-20T16:06:00Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{redirect|Equal opportunities|the Yes Minister episode|Equal Opportunities (Yes Minister)}}

'''Equality of opportunity''', sometimes known as '''Equal Opportunity''', is a term which has differing definitions and there is no consensus as to the precise meaning.&lt;ref&gt;Rabe, Johan. 2001. Equality, Affirmative Action, and Justice. Books on Demand. p. 83&lt;/ref&gt; In the classical sense, ''equality of opportunity'' is closely aligned with the concept of [[equality before the law]], and ideas of [[meritocracy]].

Equality of opportunity is in philosophical contrast to the concept of [[equality of outcome|equality of ''outcome'']].

==Examples==
Some use it as a descriptive term for an approach intended to provide a certain [[social environment]] in which people are not excluded from the activities of society, such as [[education]], [[employment]], or [[health care]], on the basis of [[immutable]] traits. Equal opportunity practices include measures taken by organizations to ensure fairness in the employment process. A basic definition of equality is the idea of equal treatment and respect.

In job advertisements and descriptions, the fact that the employer is an equal opportunity employer is sometimes indicated by the abbreviations EOE or MFDV which stands for Minority, Female, Disabled, Veteran.

==See also==
'''Equality of opportunity:'''
* [[Universal access]]
* [[Meritocracy]]
* [[Egalitarianism]]

'''Equality of outcome:'''
* [[Asset-based egalitarianism]]
* [[Affirmative action]]
* [[Affirmative action in the United States]]
* [[Women and children first (saying)]]

==External links==
*United Kingdom
**[http://www.womenandequalityunit.gov.uk/ UK Government Women &amp; Equality Unit]

*United States
**[http://www.eeoc.gov/ U.S. Equal Employment Opportunity Commission (EEOC) (US)] - the branch of the U.S. government that enforces equal opportunity laws in workplaces.
**[http://www.doi.gov/diversity/ Department of the Interior Office for Equal Opportunity (US)]
*[http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/equal-opportunity/ Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy entry on Equality of Opportunity]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Disability rights]]
[[Category:Anti-racism]]
[[Category:Civil rights and liberties]]
[[Category:Egalitarianism]]

[[de:Chancengleichheit]]
[[es:Igualdad de oportunidades]]
[[fr:Égalité des chances]]
[[hi:समान अवसर]]
[[it:Pari opportunità]]
[[nl:Gelijkwaardige behandeling]]
[[ja:機会均等]]
[[fi:Mahdollisuuksien tasa-arvo]]
[[sv:Lika möjligheter]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>