<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20101103180406|394624822" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="23266996" pageid="23266996" ns="0" title="Patriarchy"><revisions><rev timestamp="2010-11-09T09:36:40Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Other uses|Patriarchy (disambiguation)}}
'''Patriarchy''' is an [[androcentrism|androcentric]] social system in which the role of the male as the primary authority figure is central to social organization, and where fathers hold authority over women, children, and property. Historically, the principle of patriarchy has been central to the social, legal, political, and economic organization of Hebrew, Greek, Roman, Indian, and Chinese cultures, and has had a deep influence on modern civilization.&lt;ref&gt;Mac Millan Encyclopedia of Sex and Gender p. 1104&lt;/ref&gt; 

Most forms of [[feminism]] characterize patriarchy as an unjust social system that is oppressive to women. In [[feminist theory]] the concept of patriarchy often includes all the social mechanisms that reproduce and exert male dominance over women.

==Definition and usage==
Patriarchy is a multidimensional condition of [[power]]/[[Social status|status]]. Whyte's 1978 comprehensive study examined 52 indicators of patriarchy, to which corresponded 10 relatively independent [[dimension]]s. The ten dimensions are:&lt;ref&gt;Wood and Eagly 2002, p.711-2&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Whyte (1978) ''The status of women in preindustrial societies''&lt;/ref&gt;
*lack of [[property]] control by women
*lack of power of women in [[kinship]] contexts
*low value placed on the lives of women
*low value placed on the labor of women
*lack of [[domestic authority]] of women
*absence of ritualized [[female solidarity]]
*absence of control over women's marital and [[human sexuality|sexual]] lives
*absence of ritualized [[fear of women]]
*lack of male-female joint participation in warfare, work, and [[Participation (decision making)|community decision making]]
*lack of women's indirect influence on decision making

Within feminist theory, patriarchy refers to the structure of modern cultural and political systems, which are ruled by men.  Such systems are said to be detrimental to the rights of women. However, it has been noted that patriarchal systems of government do not benefit all men of all classes.&lt;ref name="userpages.umbc.edu"&gt;http://userpages.umbc.edu/~korenman/wmst/patriarchy.html&lt;/ref&gt;

While the term patriarchy generally refers to institutions, the term is sometimes used less effectively in describing societal attitudes.  It has been argued, "institutions are very persistent and may last, with little change, into a period in which attitudes have altered considerably since the institutions were devised."  Gordon Rattray Taylor used the words "patrist" and "matrist" to describe attitudes (as opposed to institutions), and noted that the outlook of the dominant social group seems to swing between the two extremes.  However, the patrist assertion that the patriarchal system of authority was the original and universal system of social organization, invariably leads to the establishment of corresponding institutions.&lt;ref name="Sex in History"&gt;[http://www.ourcivilisation.com/smartboard/shop/taylorgr/sxnhst/chap18.htm], Theories of Matriarchy and Patriarchy&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
According to [[Robert M. Strozier]], historical research has not yet found an "initiating event" of the origin of patriarchy.&lt;ref name="Strozier"&gt;Strozier, Robert M. (2002) ''[http://books.google.com/books?id=fuDdNSLXPI8C Foucault, Subjectivity, and Identity: : Historical Constructions of Subject and Self]'' p.46&lt;/ref&gt; However many scholars point to about six thousand years ago (4000 [[BCE]]), as the point of the invention of [[fatherhood]] and the spread of patriarchy.&lt;ref&gt;SEBASTIAN KRAEMER B.A., M.R.C.P., F.R.C.Psych (1991) ''[http://www.blackwell-synergy.com/doi/abs/10.1111/j.1545-5300.1991.00377.x The Origins of Fatherhood: An Ancient Family Process]'' Family Process 30 (4), 377–392. doi:10.1111/j.1545-5300.1991.00377.x&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Wilhelm Reich]] [1936] ''The Sexual Revolution''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Eagly99"&gt;Alice H. Eagly and Wendy Wood (1999) [http://www.sscnet.ucla.edu/anthro/faculty/fiske/facets/eagly&amp;wood.htm The Origins of Sex Differences in Human Behavior: Evolved Dispositions Versus Social Roles] American Psychologist, v54 n6 p408-23 Jun 1999&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://cat.inist.fr/?aModele=afficheN&amp;cpsidt=11879852 Ehrenberg, 1989]; Harris, M. (1993) ''The Evolution of Human Gender Hierarchies''; Leibowitz, 1983; Lerner, 1986; Sanday, 1981&lt;/ref&gt;

Domination by men of women is found in the [[Ancient Near East]] as far back as 3100 BCE, as are restrictions on a woman's reproductive capacity and exclusion from "the process of representing or the construction of history".&lt;ref name="Strozier"/&gt; With the appearance of the [[Hebrew]] cult, there is also "the exclusion of woman from the God-humanity covenant".&lt;ref name="Strozier"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Lerner, Gerda (1986) ''[http://books.google.com/books?&amp;id=Zc318kI-TPMC The Creation of Patriarchy]'' 8-11&lt;/ref&gt; The hegemonic spread of patriarchy is linked with the [[Kurgan hypothesis]], by now widely accepted among scholars.

In the 3rd century BCE, [[Aristotle]] taught that the city-state developed out of the patriarchal family, although the two were different in many regards.&lt;ref name="Locke, John"&gt;Two Treatises of Government, with a supplement Patriarcha by Robert Filmer, edited with an introduction by Thomas I. Cook, New York: Hafner Press, 1947.&lt;/ref&gt;  He wrote that the highest form of human community is the political community.  In Aristotle's ''[[Politics (Aristotle)|Politics]]'', he attempts to illustrate the nature of the [[hierarchies]] that exist in the political community and its subordinate communities. He argues for an origin of male rule.  In Chapter Thirteen he states that men and women have different kinds of virtue, “just as those who are natural subjects differ (from those who rule by nature.)”  Other types of community, such as the household, are subordinate and inferior to the polis.  Aristotle proposed that the household is subordinate to the political community because the aim of life in the household is the mere preservation of life, or the satisfaction of life's daily needs, whereas the aim of membership in the political community is to live well.  He also proposed that the household is inferior to the political community in the character of its rule.  In the household, the man rules by virtue of his age and sex, monarchically at best and tyrannically at worst, while in the polis, citizens choose their rulers on the basis of merit.&lt;ref name="sitemason. vanderbilt.edu"&gt;http://sitemason.vanderbilt.edu/files/e5Vjfa/Aristotle_s%20Account%20STAUFFER.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

Other ancient societies contemporary with Aristotle, as well as many Athenians, did not share these views of women, family organization, or political and economic structure.&lt;ref name="del Giorgio, J.F."&gt;The Oldest Europeans, Gaudeamus, Caracas, Venezuela, 2003.&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Egypt]] left no philosophical record, but [[Herodotus]] left a record of his shock at the contrast between the roles of Egyptian women and the women of Athens.  He observed that Egyptian women attended market and were employed in [[trade]].  In ancient Egypt a middle-class woman might sit on a local [[tribunal]], engage in [[real estate]] transactions, and inherit or bequeath [[property]].  Women also secured loans, and witnessed legal documents.  Greek influence spread, however, with the conquests of [[Alexander the Great]], who was educated by Aristotle.&lt;ref&gt;Bristow, John Temple. ''What Paul Really Said About Women: an Apostle's liberating views on equality in marriage, leadership, and love'', HarperCollins, New York, 1991.&lt;/ref&gt;  Eventually, when Alexander wanted to unite his two empires in equality, Aristotle was adamant that all non-Greeks should be enslaved.&lt;ref name="Sparknotes.com"&gt;http://www.sparknotes.com/biography/aristotle/section3.rhtml&lt;/ref&gt;

From the time of [[Martin Luther]], [[Protestantism]] regularly used the commandment in Exodus 20:12 to justify the duties owed to all superiors.  ‘Honor thy father,’ became a euphemism for the duty to obey the king.  But it was primarily as a secular doctrine that Aristotle’s appeal took on political meaning.  Although many 16th and 17th Century theorists agreed with Aristotle’s views concerning the place of women in society, none of them tried to prove political obligation on the basis of the patriarchal family until sometime after 1680. The patriarchal political theory is associated primarily with Sir [[Robert Filmer]]. Sometime before 1653, Filmer completed a work entitled ''Patriarcha''.  However, it was not published until after his death.  In it, he defended the divine right of kings as having title inherited from [[Adam]], the first man of the human race, according to [[Judeo-Christian]] tradition.&lt;ref name="encyclopedia.com"&gt;http://www.encyclopedia.com/doc/1G2-3404900841.html&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 19th Century, [[Sarah Grimke]] dared to question the divine origin of the scriptures. Later, [[Elizabeth Cady Stanton]] used Grimke’s criticism of biblical sources to establish a basis for feminist thought.  She published [[The Woman's Bible]], which proposed a feminist reading of the Old and New Testament.  This tendency was enlarged by Feminist theory, which denounced the patriarchal Judeo-Christian tradition.&lt;ref&gt;Castro, Ginette. ''American Feminism: a contemporary history'', New York University Press, 1990.&lt;/ref&gt;

By 1673, [[François Poullain de la Barre]], "On the Equality of the Two Sexes", had turned feminism into a systematic Enlightenment philosophy (as opposed to the previous Renaissance feminism).&lt;ref name="answers.com"&gt;"[http://www.answers.com/topic/feminism Feminism]", French Literature Companion: Answers.com&lt;/ref&gt; However, in 1861, [[Johann Jakob Bachofen]], a German romantic and writer of the counter-Enlightenment said that matriarchy preceded patriarchy, and is superior to patriarchy on moral grounds.  Bachofen influenced [[Karl Marx]] and [[Frederick Engels]].  Marxist analysis has been a basis for subsequent feminist thought.&lt;ref&gt;Mestrovic, Stjepan Gabriel. ''Durkheim and postmodern culture'', A. de Gruyter, New York, 1992.&lt;/ref&gt;  From the beginning, socialist feminists in France, for example, were challenged by the republic, which "oppressed them as workers and women; by Marxism, which ignores gender; and by the misogyny of their socialist brothers.  This struggle continues within all parties of the left."&lt;ref name="answers.com" /&gt;

Some [[19th-century]] scholars formulated a unilinear theory of [[cultural evolution]].&lt;ref name="Encyclopedia Britanica"&gt;Encyclopedia Britanica&lt;/ref&gt; One [[hypothesis]]  suggested that human societies evolve through a series of stages: sexual promiscuity was followed by matriarchy, which was in turn followed by patriarchy. This description was later refuted by most experts studying the subject.&lt;ref name="Encyclopedia Britanica"/&gt;

==Sociobiology versus Sociology==
{{POV|May 2010|date=May 2010}}
Sociobiologist [[Steven Goldberg]] wrote in 1973, "The ethnographic studies of every society that has ever been observed explicitly state that these feelings (feelings of both men and women that the male’s will dominates the female’s) were present, there is literally no variation at all." &lt;ref name="Goldberg, Steven"&gt;The inevitability of Patriarchy, William Morrow, New York, 1973&lt;/ref&gt; Goldberg had critics among anthropologists.  Concerning Goldberg's claims about the "feelings of both men and women" Eleanor Leacock countered that the data on women’s attitudes are “sparse and contradictory,” and that the data on male attitudes about male-female relations are “ambiguous.”  Also the effects of colonialism on the cultures represented in the studies were not considered. &lt;ref name="Leacock, Eleanor"&gt;Review of The inevitability of patriarchy by Steven Goldberg, American Anthropologist, New Series, Vol. 76, No. 2 (Jun., 1974), pp. 363-365, Blackwell publishing&lt;/ref&gt;

Most sociologists reject predominantly biological explanations of patriarchy and contend that social and cultural conditioning is primarily responsible for establishing male and female gender roles.&lt;ref name="Sanderson"&gt;{{cite book|title=The Evolution of Human Sociality|first=Stephen K.|last=Sanderson|publisher=Rowman &amp; Littlefield|year=2001|page=198}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Henslin"&gt;{{cite book|title=Essentials of Sociology|first=James M.|last=Henslin|publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis|year=2001|pages=65–67, 240}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to standard sociological theory, patriarchy is the result of sociological constructions that are passed down from generation to generation.&lt;ref name="Sanderson"/&gt; These constructions are most pronounced in societies with traditional cultures and less economic development.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Sociology: A Global Introduction|first=John J.|last=Macionis|publisher=Prentice Hall|year=2000|page=347}}&lt;/ref&gt; Even in modern developed societies, however, gender messages conveyed by family, mass media, and other institutions largely favor males having a dominant status.&lt;ref name="Henslin"/&gt;

There is considerable variation in the role that gender plays in human societies. Although there are no known examples of strictly matriarchal cultures,&lt;ref name=Britannica&gt;{{cite encyclopedia|title=Matriarchy|encyclopedia=Encyclopædia Britannica|year=2007|quote=The view of matriarchy as constituting a stage of cultural development is now generally discredited. Furthermore, the consensus among modern anthropologists and sociologists is that a strictly matriarchal society never existed.}}&lt;/ref&gt; there are a number of societies that have been shown to be [[matrilinear]] or [[matrilocal]] and gynocentric, especially among indigenous tribal groups.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Male dominance and female autonomy: domestic authority in matrilineal societies|first=Alice|last=Schlegel|year=1972|publisher=HRAF Press}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some [[hunter-gatherer]] groups have been characterized as largely [[egalitarianism|egalitarian]].&lt;ref name="erdal"&gt;Erdal, D. &amp; Whiten, A. (1996) "Egalitarianism and Machiavellian Intelligence in Human Evolution" in Mellars, P. &amp; Gibson, K. (eds) Modelling the Early Human Mind. Cambridge Macdonald Monograph Series.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Patriarchy in anthropology, archaeology and mythology==
{{POV|May 2010|date=May 2010}}
In simple societies, which match evolutionary conditions, women are not occupied solely with caring for children and they contribute about 44% of the food.  In one study, one third of the societies studied were egalitarian.  The men were not warlike or controlling of women and many other adaptive behaviors evolutionary psychologists would expect were not present.&lt;ref&gt;” [http://web.nmsu.edu/~jshughes/SocialRole_Biosocial%20Theory.ppt]”, The University of New Mexico”, Biosocial/Social role theory&lt;/ref&gt;

In the case of mate selection, a core area of [[evolutionary psychology]], it has been shown that choices can be influenced by the observed choices of others.  In fact, it is thought that in some cases, cultural evolution may change “the extent to which biological evolutionary accounts work at all.” &lt;ref&gt;Introduction. Cultural transmission and the evolution of human behaviour, ‘’Philosophical transactions of the Royal Society’’, vol. 363 (Nov. 2008) 3469-3476&lt;/ref&gt;

A third study suggests that [[egalitarianism]] is a matter of degree. Susan Kent found that egalitarianism “is a continuum, not an absolute entity; societies are only more or less egalitarian.”  Recent studies show that divisions of work, wealth and political power produce “inegalitarian” social structures.&lt;ref&gt;”[http://foragers.wikidot.com/egalitarianism]”, egalitarianism&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 1970s, mythologist [[Joseph Campbell]] wrote in “[[The Power of Myth]]”, that the Hebrews were part of an invading force consisting of Indo-Europeans and Semites who drove out the goddess sacred to the Canaanite people. Campbell said these goddess-worshipping people were agricultural, whereas the Semites and [[Indo-European]]s were herding/hunting peoples and natural killers.  He lauded the Greeks for the fact that [[Zeus]] was married to a goddess, giving them credit for the tradition of the virgin birth. (see, [[virgin birth (mythology)]]) and condemning the Hebrews for having no comparable mythology.  He observed that the Hebrews referred to the Canaanite goddess as the abomination.&lt;ref&gt;The Power of Myth, Mystic Fire Video, New York, 2001.&lt;/ref&gt;

However, archaeological evidence has shown that when the Hebrews began to settle in Palestine, there was already extreme economic stratification under an Egyptian administration.  It is likely the Hebrews belonged to marginal units consisting of permanent peoples and [[nomad]]s with distinct values and principles.  “One of the cultural traits of the rulers of Palestine in the Middle Urban age is their custom of burying the dead with their horses and donkeys.  The best examples in Palestine of the custom were found by [[Sir Flinders Petrie]] at Tell el-Ajjul, “the tell of the chariots,” near [[Gaza]].”  This represents [[Hyksos]] and not Hebrew influence, as the Hebrews did not bury humans with animals.

When the Hyksos rule ended in [[Phoenicia]] about 1600 BC, it brought no changes to the social and political structure of Palestine. Canaanite divinities were “ruthless, atrocious and fearful”.  There was [[human sacrifice]], [[sacred prostitution]], and [[serpent worship]]. [[Totalitarianism]] virtually enslaved the majority of the population, and so the [[nobility]] lived in fortified cities.  Archaeologist Emmanuel Anati found a lack of creativity and individuality in the art and material culture in this period and attributed this to the hardships of the [[feudal]] system and the brutal religion.&lt;ref&gt;Palestine Before the Hebrews, Knopf, New York, 1963.&lt;/ref&gt;

Many of the Hebrew tribes were not able to continue their nomadic lifestyle in [[Canaan]] because there were too many other tribes already occupying the land, so they lived in close proximity to the Phoenician cities. Taking up [[agriculture]] was not always viewed as an advance for nomadic people.  [[Aryans]] value agriculture but the [[Semites]] do not.  Even after settling down, the Hebrews retained their nomadic sensibilities.  Evidence for this is the Hebrew belief that [[Cain]] sinned by forcing the ground.  Cain, a red and hairy man, was part of a solar myth.  City-building and agriculture are the domain of solar figures. Solar figures are typically male.

In the wake of [[Masters and Johnson]]'s pioneering research on [[female orgasm]], a new theory of patriarchy was proposed. [[Mary Jane Sherfey]], suggested that the "ungovernable cyclic sexual drive of women" had to be forcefully suppressed by social codes in order for settled [[agrarian]] societies, composed of stable biological families, to exist.&lt;ref&gt;Sherfey, M.J. (1966). A theory on female sexuality. In Escoffier, J. (Ed.), "Sexual revolution" (91-99). New York: Thunder's Mouth Press. ISBN 1560255250.&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==

{{Wiktionary|patriarchy}}

* [[Anti-feminism]]
* [[Chinese patriarchy]]
* [[Domitius]]
* [[Gender role]]
* [[Homemaker]]
* [[Masculinity]]
* [[Matriarchy]]
* [[Nature versus nurture]]
* [[Patriarch]]
* [[Patriarch magazines]]
* [[Patriarchs (Bible)]]
* [[Sociology of fatherhood]]
* [[Kyriarchy]]

==Notes and references==

{{Reflist|2}}

==Additional reading==

* Adeline, Helen B. ''Fascinating Womanhood''. New York: Random House, 2007.
* [[Simon Baron-Cohen|Baron-Cohen, Simon]]. ''The Essential Difference: The Truth about the Male and Female Brain''. New York: Perseus Books Group, 2003.
* [[Simone de Beauvoir|Beauvoir, Simone de]]. ''Le Deuxième Sexe''. Paris: [[Éditions Gallimard]], 1949. (original French edition)
* [[Simone de Beauvoir|Beauvoir, Simone de]]. ''The Second Sex''. London: [[Jonathan Cape]], 1953. (first UK edition, in translation)
* [[Simone de Beauvoir|Beauvoir, Simone de]]. ''The Second Sex''. New York: [[Alfred A. Knopf]], 1953. (first USA edition, in translation)
* [[Ernest Borneman|Bornemann, Ernest]]. ''Das Patriarchat - Ursprung und Zukunft unseres Gesellschaftssystems'', Fischer, Frankfurt am Main 1991 (Original German edition 1975), ISBN 3-596-23416-6
* [[Pierre Bourdieu|Bourdieu, Pierre]]. ''Masculine Domination''. Translated by Richard Nice. Stanford: [[Stanford University Press]], 2001.
* [[Louann Brizendine|Brizendine, Louann]]. ''The Female Brain''. New York: Morgan Road Books, 2006.
* [[Donald Brown (anthropologist)|Brown, Donald E]]. ''[[Human Universals]]''. New York: [[McGraw Hill]], 1991.
* [[Giorgio de Santillana|de Santillana, Giorgio]] &amp; Hertha von Dechend. ''Hamlet's Mill: an essay investigating the origins of human knowledge and its transmission through myth''. David R. Godine, publisher, Jaffrey, New Hampshire, 1977. The effects of evolutionary theory on the study of culture, pp.&amp;nbsp;68–72.
* Eisler, Riane. ' 'The Chalice and the Blade' '. Harper Collins, 1987. "The most important book since Darwin's ' 'Origin of Species' '--Ashley Montagu
* [[Marija Gimbutas|Gimbutas, Marija]]. ''The civilization of the goddess: the world of Old Europe''. Harper Collins, San Francisco, 1991.
* Jay, Jennifer W. [http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0003-0279%28199604%2F06%29116%3A2%3C220%3AIM%22OWI%3E2.0.CO%3B2-R&amp;size=LARGE&amp;origin=JSTOR-enlargePage 'Imagining Matriarchy:] "Kingdoms of Women" in Tang China'. ''[[Journal of the American Oriental Society]]'' '''116''' (1996): 220-229.
* [[Melvin Konner|Konner, Melvin]]. ''[http://www.henryholt.com/tangledwing/tangledwingnotes.pdf The Tangled Wing:] Biological Constraints on the Human Spirit''. 2nd edition, revised and updated. ([[Henry Holt|Owl Books]], 2003). 560p. ISBN 0805072799 [first published 1982, [http://www.anthropology.emory.edu/FACULTY/ANTMK/TangledWing.htm Endnotes]
* Lepowsky, Maria. ''[http://www.columbia.edu/cu/cup/catalog/data/023108/0231081200.HTM  Fruit of the Motherland:] Gender in an Egalitarian Society''.  New York: [[Columbia University Press]], 1993.
* [[Margaret Mead|Mead, Margaret]]. 'Do We Undervalue Full-Time Wives'. ''[[Redbook]]'' 122 (1963).
* Mies, Maria. ''Patriarchy and Accumulation on a World Scale: Women in the International Division of Labour''. [[Palgrave Macmillan|Palgrave MacMillan]], 1999.
* Moir, Anne and David Jessel. ''[[Brain Sex]]: The Real Difference Between Men and Women''.
* [[Sherry Ortner|Ortner, Sherry Beth]]. 'Is Female to Male as Nature is to Culture?'. In MZ Rosaldo and L Lamphere (eds). ''Woman, Culture and Society''. Stanford: Stanford University Press, 1974, pp.&amp;nbsp;67–87.
* [[Sherry Ortner|Ortner, Sherry Beth]]. 'So, Is Female to Male as Nature is to Culture?'. In S Ortner. ''Making Gender: The Politics and Erotics of Culture.'' Stanford: Stanford University Press, 1996, pp.&amp;nbsp;173–180.
* Pilcher, Jane and Imelda Wheelan. ''50 Key Concepts in Gender Studies''. London: Sage Publications, 2004.
* [[Steven Pinker|Pinker, Steven]]. ''The Blank Slate: A Modern Denial of Human Nature''. London: [[Penguin Books]], 2002.
* [[Wendy Wood|Wood, Wendy]] and Alice H. Eagly. ''A cross-cultural analysis of the behavior of women and men: Implications for the origins of sex differences''. Psychological Bulletin. 128(5) (Sep. 2002):699-727.
==External links==
* "[http://www.newscientist.com/article/dn4220-cattle-ownership-makes-it-a-mans-world.html Cattle ownership makes it a man's world]". ''[[New Scientist]]'' (2003).
* [http://www.scribd.com/doc/16671406/Womens-Status-and-War-in-CrossCultural-Perspective-A-Reconsideration-World-Cultures-152-2006-209247 Women’s Status and War in Cross-Cultural Perspective: A Reconsideration]
* [[Mary Wollstonecraft]]. ''[http://oregonstate.edu/instruct/phl302/texts/wollstonecraft/woman-a.html#CHAPTER%20II A Vindication of the Rights of Women]''. Boston: Peter Edes for Thomas and Andrews, 1792.
* Pannekoek, Anton. ''[http://www.marxists.org/archive/pannekoe/1912/marxism-darwinism.htm Arguments based on natural science, when applied to social questions, must almost always lead to wrong conclusions.].''Marxism and Darwinism'', 1912.
* [[Simone de Beauvoir]]. ''[http://www.marxists.org/reference/subject/philosophy/works/fr/2ndsex.htm The Second Sex]''. Translated by HM Parshley. London: Penguin, 1972.
* "[http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/equality Equality]". In ''[[Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy]]''. Stanford University, 2001.

[[Category:Biology of gender]]
[[Category:Cultural anthropology]]
[[Category:Family]]
[[Category:Fatherhood]]
[[Category:Forms of government]]
[[Category:Gender studies]]
[[Category:Men]]
[[Category:Sociology]]
[[Category:Sociobiology]]
[[Category:Feminism and society]]

[[ar:نظام أبوي]]
[[az:Patriarxat]]
[[bg:Патриархат]]
[[cs:Patriarchát]]
[[da:Patriarkat]]
[[de:Patriarchat (Soziologie)]]
[[et:Patriarhaalsus]]
[[el:Πατριαρχία]]
[[es:Patriarcado]]
[[eo:Patriarkeco]]
[[eu:Patriarkatu]]
[[fa:پدرسالاری]]
[[fr:Patriarcat (sociologie)]]
[[ko:가부장제]]
[[hr:Patrijarhat]]
[[he:משפחה פטריארכלית]]
[[lt:Patriarchatas]]
[[mk:Патријархат]]
[[nl:Patriarchaat (sociologie)]]
[[ja:家父長制]]
[[no:Patriarki]]
[[oc:Patriarcat]]
[[pl:Patriarchat (ustrój)]]
[[pt:Patriarcado]]
[[ru:Патриархат]]
[[sk:Patriarchát (muži)]]
[[sl:Patriarhat]]
[[sr:Патријархат]]
[[fi:Patriarkaatti (yhteiskuntatieteet)]]
[[sv:Patriarkat (sociologi)]]
[[tr:Ataerkillik]]
[[zh:父權]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>