<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20111117153511|461122073" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="15179951" pageid="15179951" ns="0" title="Human sexuality"><revisions><rev timestamp="2011-11-18T11:31:05Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{About|human sexual perceptions|information about sexual activities and practices|Human sexual activity}}
{{Close Relationships}}
'''Human sexuality''' is how people experience the erotic and express themselves as sexual beings; the awareness of themselves as males or females; the capacity they have for erotic experiences and responses.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.definition-of.com/human%20sexuality&lt;/ref&gt; Human sexuality can be described as the way someone is sexually attracted to another person of the opposite [[sex]] ([[heterosexuality]]), to the same sex ([[homosexuality]]), to both sexes ([[bisexuality]]), or attracted to no sexes in a sexual way ([[asexuality]]).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.soc.ucsb.edu/sexinfo/ University of California, Santa Barbara's SexInfo]&lt;/ref&gt;

It used to be believed that human sexual behavior was different from the sexual behavior of most other animals, in that it was practiced for reasons besides copulation. Current understanding is that many species that were formerly believed monogamous have now been proven to be promiscuous or opportunistic in nature; a wide range of species appear both to masturbate and to use objects as tools to help them do so, where procreation is not the aim. See [[animal sexual behaviour]].

The term ''human sexuality'' can also cover [[Culture|cultural]], [[Politics|political]], [[Law|legal]] and [[philosophy|philosophical]] aspects. It may also refer to issues of [[morality]], [[ethics]], [[theology]], [[spirituality]] or [[religion]] and how they relate to all things sexual.

==Nature versus nurture debate==
{{main|Nature versus nurture}}
Like all things in biology, there is no simple answer.

Sexual drives among heterosexuals, homosexuals, bisexuals, and others are all driven partially by their genetics and also by superior mental activity and by social, cultural, educational, and normative characteristics of those places where the subjects grow up and their personality develops.&lt;ref name="sexology.it"&gt;Boccadoro L., Carulli S., (2008) ''Il posto dell'amore negato. Sessualità e psicopatologie segrete'' ([http://www.sexology.it/abstract_english.html The place of the denied love. Sexuality and secret psychopathologies – ''Abstract'']). Tecnoprint Editrice, Ancona. ISBN 978-88-95554-03-7&lt;/ref&gt;

Each of these sexual lifestyles will then drive [[Identity (social science)|personal identity]] and in the [[social evolution]] of individuals.&lt;ref name="sexology.it"/&gt; And will be a powerful force that affects all social activities.&lt;ref&gt;Deleuze and Guattari (1972) ''[[Anti-Oedipus]]'' pp. 322, 114–5{{cquote|[[Familialism]] maintains that sexuality operates only in the family [...] the truth is that sexuality is everywhere: the way a bureaucrat fondles his records, a judge administers justice, a business causes money to circulate; the way the burgeoisie fucks the proletariat; and so on. And there is no need to resort to metaphors, any more than for the libido to go by way of metamorphoses. }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Evolutionary Aspects==
Sex in private distinguishes us from [[Bonobos]], [[Chimpanzees]] and [[Gorillas]]. Testis and [[Penis size]] are related to family structure: [[monogamy]] or [[promiscuity]], [[harem]], in [[human]], [[chimpanzee]] and [[gorilla]], respectively (see [[The Third Chimpanzee]] and “[[Why is Sex Fun?]]” by [[Jared  Diamond]]). Involvement of the father in education, [[concealed ovulation]] and [[menopause]] in women, are quite unique to our species, at least when compared to other [[Homininae]]. Concealed (or “hidden”) ovulation means that the phase of fertility is not detectable in woman, whereas  chimpanzee advertise ovulation by  an obvious swelling of the genitals. Women can be partly aware of their ovulation, along the menstrual phases, but men are essentially unable to detect ovulation in women. Most primates have semi-concealed ovulation, thus one can think that the common ancestor had semi-concealed ovulation, that he transmitted to gorillas, but that later evolved in [[concealed ovulation]] in humans and advertised ovulation in [[chimpanzee]] (see"[[Why is Sex Fun?]]").

==Biology and Physiology Aspects==

The biological aspects of humans' sexuality deal with [[human reproduction]] and the physical means with which to carry it out([[sexual intercourse]]). They also deal with the influence of biological factors on other aspects of sexuality, such as [[sexual arousal|organic and neurological responses]],&lt;ref name="Ross81"&gt;Ellen Ross, Rayna Rapp ''[http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0010-4175%28198101%2923%3A1%3C51%3ASASARN%3E2.0.CO%3B2-B Sex and Society: A Research Note from Social History and Anthropology]'' Comparative Studies in Society and History, Vol. 23, No. 1 (Jan., 1981), pp. 51–72&lt;/ref&gt; [[heredity]], [[hormones|hormonal issues]], [[gender]] issues and [[sexual dysfunction]].&lt;ref name="Rathus2007"&gt;Rathus, Spencer A., Jeffrey S. Nevid, and Lois Fichner-Rathus. 2007. Human Sexuality in a World of Diversity. Allyn &amp; Bacon.&lt;/ref&gt;

For the sake of reproduction, normally a man will stimulate a woman until she is ready to have sex. Then he will penetrate her vagina with his penis. After repeated thrusts of his midsection and buttocks—causing the penis to partially retract from, then reenter, the vagina—the man will ejaculate his [[semen]]. This may lead to [[insemination]], which may lead to pregnancy.

During this time there are many other biological changes which have little or nothing to do with reproduction and can be generalized to any sexual act, not just that between a man and a woman. These include, increase in body temperature, increase in levels of pleasurable [[hormones]].

==Psychological aspects==
[[File:Sigmund en Anna.jpg|thumb|right|120px|[[Sigmund Freud]] with daughter Anna]]
Sexuality in humans generates profound emotional and psychological responses. Some theorists identify sexuality as the central source of human personality.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=[[John Russon]] |title=Bearing Witness to Epiphany: Persons, Things, and the Nature of Erotic Life |publisher=State University of New York Press |location=Albany |year=2009 |pages= |isbn=978-1-4384-2504-7 |oclc= |doi=|url=http://www.amazon.com/Bearing-Witness-Epiphany-Contemporary-Continental/dp/143842504X}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Psychological studies of sexuality focus on psychological influences that affect sexual behavior and experiences.&lt;ref name="Rathus2007"/&gt; Early psychological analyses were carried out by [[Sigmund Freud]], who believed in a [[Psychoanalysis|psychoanalytic]] approach. He also conjectured the concepts of [[erogenous zone]]s, [[psychosexual development]], and the [[Oedipus complex]], among others.&lt;ref&gt;[http://psychology.about.com/od/theoriesofpersonality/ss/psychosexualdev.htm What is Psychosexual Development? Pschology from About.com.] Retrieved 12 October 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Behaviorism|Behavior theorists]] such as [[John B. Watson]] and [[B. F. Skinner]] examine the actions and consequences and their ramifications. These theorists would, for example, study a child who is punished for sexual exploration and see if they grow up to associate negative feelings with sex in general.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.essortment.com/all/bfskinner_rgjj.htm B. F. Skinner and behaviorism. From essortment.] Retrieved 12 October 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Social cognitive theory|Social-learning theorists]] use similar concepts, but focus on cognitive activity and [[Mental model|modeling]].

[[Gender identity]] is a person's own sense of identification as female, male, both, neither, or somewhere in between. The [[social construction]] of gender has been discussed by a wide variety of scholars, [[Judith Butler]] notable among them. Recent contributions consider the influence of [[feminist theory]] and courtship research.&lt;ref&gt;Buss, D.M. (2002) Human mating strategies. ''Samdunfsokonemen'', 4: 48–58.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Farrell, W. (1988) ''Why Men Are The Way They Are'', New York: Berkley Books&lt;/ref&gt;

==Sociocultural aspects==
[[File:Leffler - WomensLib1970 WashingtonDC.jpg|thumb|right|200px|[[Second-wave feminism|Women's liberation]] demonstration, 1970]]
Human sexuality can also be understood as part of the [[social relation|social life]] of humans, governed by implied rules of behavior and the [[status quo]]. This focus narrows the view to groups within a society.&lt;ref name="Rathus2007"/&gt; The sociocultural aspect examines influences on and from [[Norm (sociology)|social norms]], including the effects of [[politics]] and the [[mass media]]. Such movements can help to bring about massive changes in the social norm&amp;nbsp;— examples include the [[sexual revolution]] and the rise of [[feminism]].&lt;ref&gt;. [http://www.amazon.com/gp/reader/1560255250/ Escoffier, Jeffrey. (Editor): Sexual Revolution. Running Press, 2003. ISBN 1560255250]. Retrieved 12 October 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2006/02/05/national/05friedan.html?ex=1296795600&amp;en=30472e5004a66ea3&amp;ei=5090 Betty Friedan, Who Ignited Cause in 'Feminine Mystique,' Dies at 85] – ''The New York Times,'' February 5, 2006. Retrieved 12 October 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

The link between constructed [[sex meanings]] and racial ideologies has been studied. Sexual meanings are constructed to maintain racial-ethnic-national boundaries, by denigration of "others" and regulation of [[Human sexual activity|sexual behavior]] within the [[Group (sociology)|group]]. "Both adherence to and deviation from such approved behaviors, define and reinforce racial, ethnic, and [[nationalist]] regimes."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author=Joane Nagel | title=Ethnicity and Sexuality | journal=Annual Review of Sociology | volume=26 | pages=107–133 | date=August 2000 |doi=10.1146/annurev.soc.26.1.107}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author=Joane Nagel | title=Racial, Ethnic, and National Boundaries: Sexual Intersections and Symbolic Interactions | journal=Symbolic Interaction | doi=10.1525/si.2001.24.2.123 | year=2001 | volume=24 | issue=2 | pages=123–139}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The age and manner in which children are informed of issues of sexuality is a matter of [[sex education]]. The school systems in almost all developed countries have some form of sex education, but the nature of the issues covered varies widely. In some countries (such as Australia and much of Europe) "age-appropriate" sex education often begins in pre-school, whereas other countries leave sex education to the pre-teenage and teenage years.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.theage.com.au/news/education-news/think-sex/2006/05/28/1148754861223.html Think Sex from TheAge.com.au.] Retrieved 11 October 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; Sex education covers a range of topics, including the physical, mental, and social aspects of sexual behavior.

===Religious sexual morality===
{{Main|Religion and sexuality}}
Most world religions have sought to address the moral issues that arise from people's sexuality in society and in human interactions. Each major religion has developed [[moral code]]s covering issues of sexuality, morality, ethics etc., which have sought to guide people's sexual activities and practices.

==Sexual behavior==
{{Main|Human sexual activity}}
Human sexual behavior, driven by the desire for [[pleasure]], encompasses the [[flirting|search for a partner]] or partners, interactions between individuals, [[physical intimacy|physical]], [[emotional intimacy]], and sexual contact that may lead to [[foreplay]], [[masturbation]] and ultimately [[orgasm]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.likeitis.org/sex_print.html Sex. From Likeitis.org.] Retrieved 12 October 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

Human sexual activities or human sexual practices or human sexual behavior refers to the manner in which humans experience and express their sexuality. People engage in a variety of sexual acts from time to time, and for a wide variety of reasons. Sexual activity normally results in [[sexual arousal]] and physiological changes in the aroused person, some of which are pronounced while others are more subtle. Sexual activity also includes conduct and activities which are intended to arouse the sexual interest of another, such as strategies to find or attract partners ([[courtship|mating]] and [[Display (zoology)|display]] behavior), and personal interactions between individuals, such as [[flirting]] and [[foreplay]].

Human sexual activity has biological, [[physical intimacy|physical]] and [[emotional intimacy|emotional aspects]]. [[Biology|Biologically]], it refers to the reproductive mechanism as well as the basic biological drive that exists in all species and can encompass [[sexual intercourse]] and sexual contact in all its forms. Emotional aspects deal with the intense [[Human bonding|personal bonds]] and emotions generated between [[sexual partners]] by a sexual activity. Physical issues around sexuality range from purely [[medicine|medical]] considerations to concerns about the [[physiology|physiological]] or even [[psychology|psychological]] and [[Sociology|sociological]] aspects of sexual behaviour.

{{See also|Sexual intercourse#Benefits|Sexual intercourse#Risks}}

In humans, sex has been claimed to produce health benefits as varied as improved sense of smell,&lt;ref&gt;Wood, H. Sex Cells Nature Reviews Neuroscience 4, 88 (February 2003) | doi:10.1038/nrn1044&lt;/ref&gt; [[Stress (biology)|stress]] and blood pressure reduction,&lt;ref name="webmd.com"&gt;Doheny, K. (2008) [http://www.webmd.com/sex-relationships/features/10-surprising-health-benefits-of-sex "10 Surprising Health Benefits of Sex,"] [[WebMD]] (reviewed by Chang, L., M.D.)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Light, K.C. et al., "More frequent partner hugs and higher oxytocin levels are linked to lower blood pressure and heart rate in premenopausal women." ''Biological Psychology'', April 2005; vol 69: pp 5–21.&lt;/ref&gt;
increased [[immune system|immunity]],&lt;ref&gt;Charnetski CJ, Brennan FX. Sexual frequency and salivary immunoglobulin A (IgA). ''Psychological Reports'' 2004 Jun;94(3 Pt 1):839-44. Data on length of relationship and sexual satisfaction were not related to the group differences.&lt;/ref&gt; and decreased risk of [[prostate cancer]].&lt;ref&gt;Michael F. Leitzmann; Edward Giovannucci. Frequency of Ejaculation and Risk of Prostate Cancer—Reply. ''JAMA''. (2004);292:329.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Leitzmann MF, Platz EA, Stampfer MJ, Willett WC, Giovannucci E. Ejaculation Frequency and Subsequent Risk of Prostate Cancer. ''JAMA''. (2004);291(13):1578–1586.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Giles GG, Severi G, English DR, McCredie MR, Borland R, Boyle P, Hopper JL. Sexual factors and prostate cancer. ''BJU Int''. (2003);92(3):211-6.PMID: 12887469&lt;/ref&gt; Sexual intimacy, as well as orgasms, increases levels of the hormone [[oxytocin]], also known as "the love hormone", which helps people bond and build trust.&lt;ref&gt;Lee HJ, Macbeth AH, Pagani JH, Young WS 3rd. Oxytocin: the great facilitator of life. ''Prog Neurobiol''. (2009);88(2):127-51. PMID: 19482229&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Riley AJ. Oxytocin and coitus. ''Sexual and Relationship Therapy'' (1988);3:29–36&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Carter CS. Oxytocin and sexual behavior. ''Neuroscience &amp; Biobehavioral Reviews'' (1992);16(2):131–144&lt;/ref&gt; A long-term study of 3,500 people between 30 and 101 by clinical neuropsychologist David Weeks, MD, head of old age psychology at the Royal Edinburgh Hospital in Scotland, found that "sex helps you look between four and seven years younger", according to impartial ratings of the subjects' photos. Exclusive causation, however, is unclear, and the benefits may be indirectly related to sex and directly related to significant reductions in stress, greater contentment, and better sleep that sex promotes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Blum|first=Jeffrey |title=Can Good Sex Keep You Young?|url=http://www.medicinenet.com/script/main/art.asp?articlekey=51501|publisher=WebMD|accessdate=8 October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Weeks|first=David|title=Secrets of the Superyoung|year=1999|publisher=Berkley|isbn=978-0425172582|page=277|url=http://www.amazon.com/Secrets-Superyoung-David-Weeks/dp/0425172589/}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Northrup|first=Christiane|title=Women's Bodies, Women's Wisdom: Creating Physical and Emotional Health and Healing|year=2010|publisher=Bantam|isbn=978-0553807936|page=960|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=V9S3keMnie8C&amp;pg=PA232&amp;lpg=PA232&amp;dq=David+Weeks}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In contrast to its benefits, sexual intercourse can also be a [[vector (epidemiology)|disease vector]].&lt;ref&gt;"[http://www.4parents.gov/sexrisky/stds/common_std/common_std.html Common Sexually Transmitted Diseases (STDs)]". U.S. Department of Health &amp; Human Services.&lt;/ref&gt; There are 19 million new cases of sexually transmitted diseases (STD) every year in the U.S.,&lt;ref name="CDC"&gt;Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. [http://www.cdc.gov/std/stats08/surv2008-Complete.pdf Sexually Transmitted Disease Surveillance], 2008. Atlanta, GA: U.S. Department of Health and Human Services; November 2009.[http://www.cdc.gov/std/stats08/2008survFactSheet.PDF Fact Sheet]&lt;/ref&gt; and worldwide there are over 340 million STDs a year.&lt;ref name="who"&gt;World Health Organization Fact Sheet on Sexually Transmitted Diseases. [http://www.who.int/mediacentre/factsheets/fs110/en/print.html] Accessed May 27, 2010&lt;/ref&gt; More than half of all STDs occur in adolescents and young adults aged 15–24 years.&lt;ref&gt;Weinstock H, et al. Sexually transmitted diseases among American youth: incidence and prevalence estimates, 2000. ''Perspectives on Sexual and Reproductive Health'' (2004);36(1):6–10.&lt;/ref&gt; At least one in four U.S. teenage girls has a sexually transmitted disease.&lt;ref name="CDC"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2008/03/12/science/12std.html?_r=1 Sex Infections Found in Quarter of Teenage Girls]. [[The New York Times]]. March 12, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; In the US, about 30% of 15–17 year old adolescents have had sexual intercourse, but only about 80% of 15–19 year old adolescents report using condoms for their first sexual intercourse.&lt;ref&gt;CDC. Sexual and Reproductive Health
of Persons Aged 10–24 Years —United States, 2002–2007. MMWR 20009; 58 (No. SS-6):1–59 [http://www.cdc.gov/mmwr/pdf/ss/ss5806.pdf]&lt;/ref&gt; More than 75% of young women age 18–25 years felt they were at low risk of acquiring an STD in one study.&lt;ref&gt;Yarnall KS, McBride CM, Lyna P, Fish LJ, Civic D, Grothaus L, Scholes D. Factors associated with condom use among at-risk women students and nonstudents seen in managed care. ''Prev Med''. (2003);37(2):163-70.PMID: 12855216&lt;/ref&gt;

===Sexual attraction===
[[Sexual attraction]] is an important aspect of the sexuality of the person being observed, as well as of the person observing. Each person determines the qualities that they find attractive, which vary from person to person. A person's [[sexual orientation]] has a significant influence on which qualities they will find attractive. The qualities that people can find sexually attractive may depend on the [[physical attraction|physical quality]], including both looks and movements of a person but can also be influenced by voice or smell as well as by [[individual]] preferences resulting from a variety of [[Genetics|genetic]], [[psychological]], and cultural factors.

===Creating a relationship===
[[File:Eugen de Blaas The Flirtation.jpg|thumb|right|150px|''The Flirt'', by [[Eugene de Blaas]]]]

People both consciously and subconsciously seek to attract others with whom they can form deeper relationships. This may be for [[companionship]], for [[procreation]], for an [[intimate relationship]], besides other possible purposes. This involves interactive processes whereby people find and attract potential partners, and maintain a relationship. These processes, which involve attracting a partner and maintaining sexual interest, can include:

*[[Flirting]] can be used to attract the sexual attention of another in order to encourage romance or sexual relations, and can involve [[body language]], conversation, joking or brief physical contact.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sirc.org/publik/flirt.html SIRC Guide to Flirting. What Social Science can tell you about flirting and how to do it.] Retrieved 13 October 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Seduction]] is the process whereby one person deliberately entices another to engage in some sort of [[human sexual behavior]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author=Greene, Robert | authorlink=Robert Greene (author) | title=The Art of Seduction | publisher=[[Penguin Books]]| year=2003 | isbn=0-14-200119-8}}&lt;/ref&gt; The medium of communication of sexual interest can be verbal or visual.
*[[Dating (activity)|Dating]] is the process of arranging meetings or outings with a potential partner to investigate or enhance their suitability for an [[Intimate relationship|intimate partnership]].
*The prospect of [[physical intimacy]] is, at times, the most effective means of sexual attraction. This can be by way of an expression of [[feeling]]s such as close [[friendship]] or [[love]], including [[holding hands]], [[hug]]ging, [[kiss]]ing, or [[petting|caressing]].

===Legal issues===
{{Main|Human sexual behavior#Legal issues|Sex and the law}}
There are many laws and social customs which prohibit, or in some way have an impact on sexual activities. These laws and customs vary from country to country, and have varied over time. They cover, for example, a prohibition to non-consensual sex, to sex outside of marriage, to sexual activity in public, besides many others. Many of these restrictions are non-controversial, but some have been the subject of public debate.

Most societies consider it a serious crime to force someone to engage in sexual acts or to engage in sexual activity with someone who does not consent. This is called [[sexual assault]], and if sexual penetration occurs it is called [[rape]], the most serious kind of sexual assault. The details of this distinction may vary among different legal jurisdictions. Also, what constitutes effective consent in sexual matters varies from culture to culture and is frequently debated. Laws regulating the minimum age at which a person can consent to have sex ([[age of consent]]) are frequently the subject of debate, as is [[adolescent sexual behavior]] in general.

==Sexuality and age==
===Child sexuality===
{{Main|Child sexuality}}
Since the industrial revolution{{Fact|date=November 2011}}, children were often assumed not to have sexuality until later development. [[Sigmund Freud]] was one of the first researchers to take [[child sexuality]] seriously. While his ideas, such as [[psychosexual development]] and the [[Oedipus conflict]], have been rejected or labeled obsolete, acknowledging the existence of child sexuality was a milestone.&lt;ref name="Santrock"/&gt; [[Alfred Kinsey]] also examined child sexuality in his [[Kinsey Reports]]. Children are naturally curious about their bodies and sexual functions. For example, they wonder where babies come from, they notice anatomical differences between males and females, and many engage in [[genital play]] (often mistaken for masturbation). Child sex play includes exhibiting or inspecting the genitals. Many children take part in some sex play, typically with siblings or friends.&lt;ref name="Santrock"&gt;Santrock, J.W. (2008). ''A Topical Approach to Life-Span Development (4''th''ed.).'' New York: McGraw-Hill.&lt;/ref&gt; Sex play with others usually decreases as children go through their elementary school years, yet they still may possess romantic interest in their peers. Curiosity levels remain high during these years, but it is not until adolescence that the main surge in sexual interest occurs.&lt;ref name="Santrock"/&gt;

===Sexuality in late adulthood===
{{Main|Sexuality in older age}}
Changes in sexual behavior occur with age and while humans in late adulthood may be impaired by infirmity, relationship needs such as closeness and sensuality remain. Aging produces changes in sexual performance. Men are more likely to experience these changes than women. For men, orgasms become less frequent and usually need more direct stimulation to produce an erection. One out of four men, ages 65 to 80, had severe problems getting or keeping erections and this percentage increased with men over 80 years of age. Yet, the use of drugs to treat [[erectile dysfunction]] increases the expectations of older adults to have sex. Despite medical complications and opinions that people in late adulthood should be celibate, many older adults continue to engage in sexual intercourse. The results of a recent interview study involving 3,000 adults 57 to 85 years of age have shown that health plays a role in the level of older adults' sexual activity. The percentage of sexually active older adults is higher for those that are in good health than those in poor health. Older women may be less sexually active due to outliving their partners or men's tendency to marry younger women. While older adults engage in sexual activity, intimacy and companionship tend to be more important than sex.&lt;ref name="Santrock"/&gt;

==Sexuality in history==
{{Main|History of human sexuality}}
[[File:Wien NHM Venus von Willendorf.jpg|thumb|right|150px|The prehistoric [[Venus of Willendorf]]]]
[[File:Min.jpg|right|thumb|120px|[[Min (god)|Min]]: the ancient Egyptian god of fertility]]
Art and artifacts from past eras help to portray human perception of sexuality of the time.&lt;ref name="Rathus2007"/&gt;

===Ancient civilizations===
Many of the ancient civilisations provide evidence of developments in sexuality. In particular:
*[[Egypt]]: The couple [[Khnumhotep and Niankhkhnum]], now buried in a joint [[Fifth dynasty of Egypt|Fifth-dynasty]] (2498–2345 BC) era tomb in [[Saqqara]], [[Egypt]], are believed to be the oldest recorded same-sex couple in human history. The Ancient Egyptians related the cult of phallus with [[Osiris]]. When Osiris' body was cut in 13 pieces, Set scattered them all over Egypt and his wife [[Isis]] retrieved all of them except one, his penis, which was swallowed by a fish (see the [[Legend of Osiris and Isis]]). The phallus was a symbol of fertility, and the god [[Min (god)|Min]] was often depicted ''ithyphallic'' (with a penis).

*[[History of sex in India|India]]: Ancient texts from [[Hinduism]], [[Buddhism]] and [[Jainism]] such as the [[Rig Veda|Vedas]] reveal moral perspectives on sexuality, marriage and fertility prayers. The epics of ancient India, the [[Ramayana]] and [[Mahabharata]], possibly from as early as [[1400 BC]], later influenced [[China|Chinese]], [[Japan]]ese, [[Tibet]]an and [[South East Asia]]n culture. They indicate that sex was considered a mutual duty between a married couple, but where sex was considered a private affair. The most publicly known sexual literature of India are the texts of the [[Kama Sutra|sixty-four arts]].
*[[Mesopotamia]]: In ancient Mesopotamia, [[Ishtar]] was the primary Goddess of life, men and women, nature and fertility, sex, sexual power and birth. Ishtar was also the goddess of war and weapons and any victory was celebrated in her temples with offerings of produce and money as well as through a feast and orgy of sex and intercourse with holy [[temple prostitute]]s.
*[[China]]: In the ''[[I Ching]]'' (The ''Book of Changes'', a Chinese classic text dealing with what would be in the West termed metaphysics), sexual intercourse is one of two fundamental models used to explain the world. Heaven is described as having sexual intercourse with Earth. The male lovers of early Chinese men of great political power are mentioned in one of the earliest great works of philosophy and literature, the ''[[Zhuang Zi]]''.
*[[Japan]]: In perhaps the earliest novel in the world, the ''[[Genji Monogatari]]'' (''[[Tale of Genji]]''), dating back to around the 11th century AD, eroticism is treated as a central part of the aesthetic life of members of the nobility.
*[[Greece]]: In ancient [[Greece]], the [[phallus]], often in the form of a [[herma]], was an object of worship as a symbol of fertility. One ancient Greek male idea of female sexuality was that women envied [[penis]]es of males. Wives were considered as commodity and instruments for bearing legitimate children. They had to compete sexually with [[eromenoi]], [[hetaera]]s and slaves in their own homes.
*[[Rome]]: Ancient Roman civilization included celebrations associated with human reproductive organs. Over time there emerged institutionalization of voluntary sex as well as prostitution. This resulted in a virtual sexual caste system in Roman civilization – different grades and degrees of sexual relationships. Apart from the legally wedded spouses, a number of males used to have [[Delicatue]], mistresses of wealthy and prominent men. The next were the Famosae, mostly the daughters and even wives of the wealthy families who enjoyed sex for its own sake. There was another class known as [[Lupae]], willing to have sexual union with anyone for a price. Copae were the serving girls in the taverns and inns and who did not mind being hired as bedmates for the night by travelers.

===Modern developments===
{{Main|Sexology}}

In contemporary academia, sexuality is studied in the fields of [[sexology]] and [[gender and sexuality studies]], among many other fields.

Sexology, the study of sexual interests, behavior, and function, covers [[sexual development]] and [[sexual relationship]]s including [[sexual intercourse]]. It also documents the sexualities of groups such as the disabled, children, and the [[geriatric sexology|elderly]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www2.hu-berlin.de/sexology/GESUND/ARCHIV/HISTORY.HTM Erwin J. Haeberle: A Brief History of Sexology. Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin]. Retrieved 15 October 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Alfred Kinsey]] became interested in the different forms of sexual practices around 1933 when he developed the [[Kinsey Scale]], which ranges from 0 to 6, where 0 is exclusively heterosexual and 6 is exclusively homosexual. His [[Kinsey Reports]] starting with the publication of [[Sexual Behavior in the Human Male]] in 1948 and [[Sexual Behavior in the Human Female]] in 1953 contributed to the sexual revolution of the 1960s.

==See also==
{{Portal|Sexuality}}
&lt;!--If you want to add general topics, add them to the list below--&gt;
* [[Index of human sexuality articles]]
* [[Sex magic]]
* [[Sexologies: European Journal of Sexual Health (Revue Européenne de Santé Sexuelle)]]
* [[Sexology]]
* [[Sexualisation|Sexualization]]
* [[Mental roots of sexual orientation]]

==Footnotes==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==External links==
* [http://nsrc.sfsu.edu/MagWebpage.cfm?&amp;Page=175 American Sexuality Magazine]
* [http://www.sexology.it/glossario_sessuologia.html Glossario di sessuologia clinica – Glossary of clinical sexology]
* [http://www.uvm.edu/~dhowell/EBS/History_of_Surveys_of_Sexual_Behavior1.pdf History of Surveys of Sexual Behavior] from [http://www.uvm.edu/~dhowell/EBS/ Encyclopedia of Behavioral Statistics]
* [http://www2.hu-berlin.de/sexology/IES/index.html International Encyclopedia of Sexuality] [http://www2.rz.hu-berlin.de/sexology/GESUND/ARCHIV/IES/BEGIN.HTM full text]
* Janssen, D. F., [http://www2.hu-berlin.de/sexology/GESUND/ARCHIV/GUS/INDEXATLAS.HTM ''Growing Up Sexually. Volume I. World Reference Atlas''] [full text]
* [http://nsrc.sfsu.edu National Sexuality Resource Center]
* [http://data360.org/pdf/20070416064139.Global%20Sex%20Survey.pdf Durex Global Sex Survey 2005] at [http://data360.org/index.aspx data360.org]
* [http://db.jhuccp.org/popinform/basic.html POPLINE] is a searchable database of the world's [[reproductive health]] literature.
* [http://www.kinseyinstitute.org/ccies/ The Continuum Complete International Encyclopedia of Sexuality at the Kinsey Institute]
* [http://www.sexualityinstitute.org The Sexuality and Rights Institute]
* [http://www.asiasrc.org The South and Southeast Asia Resource Centre on Sexuality]
* [http://www.educatedearth.net/video.php?id=3940 MRI Video of Human Copulation]
* {{Cite episode|airdate=February 13, 2006 |title=Naked Science: What's Sexy? |url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NTfBQtVFhXo |seriesno=2 |number=1 |format= |series=Naked Science | serieslink=Naked Science |language= |network=National Geographic Channel |location= }}

{{Human sexuality}}
{{Sex}}
{{Sexual ethics}}
{{Sexual urban legends}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Human Sexuality}}
[[Category:Human sexuality| ]]
[[Category:Fertility]]

{{Link GA|ja}}
[[frp:Sèxualitât humèna]]
[[ca:Sexualitat]]
[[cy:Rhywioldeb dynol]]
[[de:Sexualität des Menschen]]
[[et:Seksuaalsuhe]]
[[es:Sexualidad humana]]
[[eu:Giza sexualitate]]
[[fr:Sexualité humaine]]
[[fur:Sessualitât umane]]
[[la:Sexualitas humana]]
[[li:Miensjelike seksualiteit]]
[[ja:人間の性]]
[[nrm:Sexualité]]
[[pt:Sexualidade humana]]
[[ru:Сексуальность человека]]
[[sc:Sessualidade de s'òmine]]
[[simple:Human sexuality]]
[[sk:Ľudská sexualita]]
[[sr:Људска сексуалност]]
[[th:เพศสภาพของมนุษย์]]
[[tr:İnsan cinselliği]]
[[uk:Сексуальність людини]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>