<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20091115030234|325910988" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="15179951" pageid="15179951" ns="0" title="Human sexuality"><revisions><rev timestamp="2009-11-15T12:04:08Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Otheruses4|human sexual perceptions|information about sexual activities and practices|Human sexual behavior}}
[[File:KamaSutra44.jpg|thumb|right|250px|Sexuality as illustrated in the [[Kama Sutra]]]]
{{Portalpar|Sexuality}}

'''Human sexuality''' is how people experience the erotic and express themselves as sexual beings.&lt;ref name="Rathus2007"&gt;Rathus, Spencer A., Jeffrey S. Nevid, and Lois Fichner-Rathus. 2007. Human Sexuality in a World of Diversity. Allyn &amp; Bacon.&lt;/ref&gt; Frequently driven by the desire for [[Human sexual behavior|sexual pleasure]], human sexuality has biological, physical and emotional aspects. [[Biology|Biologically]], it refers to the reproductive mechanism as well as the basic biological drive that exists in all species and can encompass [[sexual intercourse]] and [[Human sexual behavior|sexual contact]] in all its forms. Emotional aspects deal with the intense emotions relating to sexual acts and associated social bonds. Physical issues around sexuality range from purely [[medicine|medical]] considerations to concerns about the [[physiology|physiological]] or even [[psychology|psychological]] and [[Sociology|sociological]] aspects of sexual behaviour. 

The term can also cover [[Culture|cultural]], [[Politics|political]], [[Law|legal]] and [[philosophy|philosophical]]  aspects. It may also refer to issues of [[morality]], [[ethics]], [[theology]], [[spirituality]] or [[religion]] and how they relate to all things sexual.  Recent studies on human sexuality have highlighted that sexual aspects are of major importance in building up [[Identity (social science)|personal identity]] and in the [[social evolution]] of individuals:&lt;ref&gt;Boccadoro L., Carulli S., (2008) ''Il posto dell'amore negato. Sessualità e psicopatologie segrete'' ([http://www.sexology.it/abstract_english.html The place of the denied love. Sexuality and secret psychopathologies - ''Abstract'']). Tecnoprint Editrice, Ancona. &lt;small&gt;ISBN 978-88-95554-03-7&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;
{{cquote|Human sexuality is not simply imposed by instinct or stereotypical conducts, as it happens in animals, but it is influenced both by superior mental activity and by social, cultural, educational and normative characteristics of those places where the subjects grow up and their personality develops. Consequently, the analysis of sexual sphere must be based on the convergence of several lines of development such as affectivity, emotions and relations.}}

Deleuze and Guattari, in their 1972 classic ''[[Anti-Oedipus]]'', discussed how sexuality is a powerful force that invests all the social activities:&lt;ref&gt;Deleuze and Guattari (1972) ''[[Anti-Oedipus]]'' pp. 322, 114-5&lt;/ref&gt;
{{cquote|[[Familialism]] mantains that sexuality operates only in the family [...] the thruth is that sexuality is everywhere: the way a bureaucrat fondles his records, a judge administers justice, a business causes money to circulate; the way the burgeoise fucks the proletariat; and so on. And there is no need to resort to metaphors, any more than for the libido to go by way of metemorphoses. Hitler gave the fascists a hard-on. Flags, nations, armies, banks give a lot of people hard-ons.}}

[[File:Wien NHM Venus von Willendorf.jpg|thumb|right|150px|The prehistoric Willendorf Venus]]
Art and artifacts from past eras help to portray human sexuality of the time.&lt;ref name="Rathus2007"/&gt;

==Biology and physiology==
{{seealso|Sexual intercourse#Health benefits}}
[[File:Picture couple pregnant woman.jpg|thumb|right|100px|Successful pregnancy]]
The biological aspects of human sexuality deal with [[human reproduction]] and the physical means with which to carry it out. They also deal with the influence of biological factors on other aspects of sexuality, such as [[sexual arousal|organic and neurological responses]],&lt;ref name="Ross81"&gt;Ellen Ross, Rayna Rapp ''[http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0010-4175%28198101%2923%3A1%3C51%3ASASARN%3E2.0.CO%3B2-B Sex and Society: A Research Note from Social History and Anthropology]'' Comparative Studies in Society and History, Vol. 23, No. 1 (Jan., 1981), pp. 51-72&lt;/ref&gt; [[heredity]], [[hormones|hormonal issues]], [[gender]] issues and [[sexual dysfunction]].&lt;ref name="Rathus2007"/&gt;

===Benefits===

Apart from the possibility of its resulting in successful [[pregnancy]] and [[childbirth]], sex has a wide range of health benefits including relief from [[Stress (biology)|stress]], more immunity through increased [[antibody|immunoglobulin A]], reduced risk of [[Myocardial infarction|heart attack]] and of [[prostate cancer]], sounder [[sleep]] and [[Weight loss|loss in body weight]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.webmd.com/sex-relationships/features/10-surprising-health-benefits-of-sex Kathleen Doheny: 10 Surprising Health Benefits of Sex. From WebMD]. Retrieved 11 October 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Risks===
[[File:Préservatif enroulé.jpg|thumb|right|100px|A rolled up male condom]]
Human intercourse can however also result in [[sexually transmitted disease]]s such as those arising from [[HIV]]/[[AIDS]], [[chlamydia]], [[syphilis]], [[gonorrhea]], and [[Human papillomavirus|HPV]]. For this reason, some people require potential sex partners to be tested for sexually transmitted diseases before engaging in sex.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.soc.ucsb.edu/sexinfo/article/stis-overview Sexually Transmitted Infections Overview. From University of California Santa Barbara.] Retrieved 11 October 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

Intercourse can also lead to unwanted [[pregnancy]]. This can be avoided by the use of [[birth control]] measures such as [[condom]]s, [[spermicide]]s, [[hormonal contraception]], and sterilization.&lt;ref&gt;[http://contraception.about.com/od/contraceptionoverview/g/glossary.htm   Dawn Stacey: Contraception. About.com.] Retrieved 11 October 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Sociocultural aspects==
[[File:Leffler - WomensLib1970 WashingtonDC.jpg|thumb|right|200px|[[Second-wave feminism|Women's lib]] demonstration, 1970]]
Human sexuality can also be understood as part of the [[social relation|social life]] of humans, governed by implied rules of behavior and the [[status quo]]. This focus narrows the view to groups within a society.&lt;ref name="Rathus2007"/&gt; The sociocultural aspect examines influences on and from [[Norm (sociology)|social norms]], including the effects of [[politics]] and the [[mass media]]. Such movements can help to bring about massive changes in the social norm&amp;nbsp;— examples include the [[sexual revolution]] and the rise of [[feminism]].&lt;ref&gt;. [http://www.amazon.com/gp/reader/1560255250/ Escoffier, Jeffrey. (Editor): Sexual Revolution. Running Press, 2003. ISBN 1560255250]. Retrieved 12 October 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2006/02/05/national/05friedan.html?ex=1296795600&amp;en=30472e5004a66ea3&amp;ei=5090 Betty Friedan, Who Ignited Cause in 'Feminine Mystique,' Dies at 85] - ''The New York Times,'' February 5, 2006. Retrieved 12 October 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

The link between constructed [[sex meanings]] and racial ideologies has been studied. Sexual meanings are constructed to maintain racial-ethnic-national boundaries, by denigration of "others" and regulation of [[sexual behavior]] within the [[Group (sociology)|group]]. "Both adherence to and deviation from such approved behaviors, define and reinforce racial, ethnic, and [[nationalist]] regimes."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author=Joane Nagel | title=ETHNICITY AND SEXUALITY | journal=Annual Review of Sociology | volume=26 | pages=107–133 | date=August 2000 |doi=10.1146/annurev.soc.26.1.107}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author=Joane Nagel | title=Racial, Ethnic, and National Boundaries: Sexual Intersections and Symbolic Interactions | journal=Symbolic Interaction  | doi=10.1525/si.2001.24.2.123 | year=2001 | volume=24 | issue=2 | pages=123–139}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The age and manner in which children are informed of issues of sexuality is a matter of [[sex education]]. The school systems in almost all developed countries have some form of sex education but the nature of the issues covered varies widely. In some countries (such as Australia and much of Europe) "age-appropriate" sex education often begins in pre-school, whereas other countries leave sex education to the pre-teenage and teenage years.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.theage.com.au/news/education-news/think-sex/2006/05/28/1148754861223.html Think Sex from TheAge.com.au.] Retrieved 11 October 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; Sex education covers a range of topics, including the physical, mental, and social aspects of sexual behavior. In Europe, schools also  address children's [[insafe|safe use of the internet]].

==Psychological aspects==
[[File:Sigmund en Anna.jpg|thumb|right|120px|[[Sigmund Freud]] with daughter Anna]]
Sexuality in humans generates profound emotional and psychological responses.  Some theorists identify sexuality as the central source of human personality.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=[[John Russon]] |title=Bearing Witness to Epiphany: Persons, Things, and the Nature of Erotic Life |publisher=State University of New York Press |location=Albany |year=2009 |pages= |isbn=978-1-4384-2504-7 |oclc= |doi=|url=http://www.amazon.com/Bearing-Witness-Epiphany-Contemporary-Continental/dp/143842504X}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Psychological studies of sexuality focus on psychological influences that affect sexual behavior and experiences.&lt;ref name="Rathus2007"/&gt; Early psychological analyses were carried out by [[Sigmund Freud]], who believed in a [[Psychoanalysis|psychoanalytic]] approach. He also conjectured the concepts of [[erogenous zone]]s, [[psychosexual development]], and the [[Oedipus complex]], among others.&lt;ref&gt;[http://psychology.about.com/od/theoriesofpersonality/ss/psychosexualdev.htm What is Psychosexual Development? Pschology from About.com.] Retrieved 12 October 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Behaviorism|Behavior theorists]] such as [[John B. Watson]] and [[B. F. Skinner]] examine the actions and consequences and their ramifications. These theorists would, for example, study a child who is punished for sexual exploration and see if they grow up to associate negative feelings with sex in general.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.essortment.com/all/bfskinner_rgjj.htm B. F. Skinner and behaviorism. From essortment.] Retrieved 12 October 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Social cognitive theory|Social-learning theorists]] use similar concepts, but focus on cognitive activity and [[Mental model|modeling]].

[[Gender identity]] is a person's own sense of identification as female, male, both, neither, or somewhere in between. The [[social construction]] of gender has been discussed by a wide variety of scholars, [[Judith Butler]] notable among them.  Recent contributions consider the influence of [[feminist theory]] and courtship research.&lt;ref&gt;Buss, D.M. (2002) Human mating strategies. ''Samdunfsokonemen'', 4: 48-58.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Farrell, W. (1988) ''Why Men Are The Way They Are'', New York: Berkley Books&lt;/ref&gt;

==Fertility==
Both women and men have [[Hormones|hormonal]] cycles determining when a woman can achieve [[pregnancy]] and when a man is most virile. The female cycle is approximately 28 days long, but the male cycle is variable.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sexualhealthcentresaskatoon.ca/par/fertility.htm The Female Fertility Cycle. From SHCS.] Retrieved 14 October 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pamf.org/fertility/conception/male.html The Male Reproductive Cycle. From Palo Alto Medical Foundation.] Retrieved 14 October 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Menstrual cycle===
{{Main|Menstrual cycle}}
Although women can become pregnant at any time during their [[menstrual cycle]], peak fertility usually occurs two days before and two days after the ovulation date&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.duofertility.com/en/my-body/my-cycle/my-fertile-period.html My Fertile Days.] Retrieved 14 October 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;.

===Female fertility===
The average age of the first menstruation or [[menarche]] in the United States is about 12.5 years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Anderson SE, Dallal GE, Must A |title=Relative weight and race influence average age at menarche: results from two nationally representative surveys of US girls studied 25 years apart |journal=Pediatrics |volume=111 |issue=4 Pt 1 |pages=844–50 |year=2003 |month=April |pmid=12671122 |doi= 10.1542/peds.111.4.844|url=http://pediatrics.aappublications.org/cgi/content/full/111/4/844?maxtoshow=&amp;HITS=10&amp;hits=10&amp;RESULTFORMAT=&amp;searchid=1&amp;FIRSTINDEX=0&amp;minscore=5000&amp;resourcetype=HWCIT }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Women's fertility peaks around the age of 19-24, and can start to decline after 30. With a rise in women [[Advanced maternal age|postponing pregnancy]],&lt;ref&gt; [http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m1077/is_1_62/ai_n16807720 Late-in-life Pregnancy]. Retrieved 14 October 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; this can create an [[infertility]] problem. Of women trying to get pregnant, without using fertility drugs or [[in vitro fertilization]]:

*At age 30, 75% will get pregnant within one year, and 91% within four years.
*At age 35, 66% will get pregnant within one year, and 84% within four years.
*At age 40, 44% will get pregnant within one year, and 64% within four years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Fertility Treatment Less Successful After 35 | work=WebMD | url=http://www.webmd.com/content/article/89/100183.htm | dateformat=mdy | accessdate=July 4 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Male fertility and age===
[[Erectile dysfunction]] increases with age,&lt;ref name=semin&gt; [http://www.infertile.com/inthenew/sci/maleage.htm Effect of Age on Male Fertility] Seminars in Reproductive Endocrinology. Volume, Number 3, August 1991. Sherman J. Silber, M.D.&lt;/ref&gt; but fertility does not decline in men as sharply as it does in women.  There have been examples of males being fertile at 94 years old.&lt;ref name=semin/&gt; However, evidence suggests that increased male age is associated with a decline in semen volume, [[sperm motility]], and sperm morphology.&lt;ref name=Kidd&gt;{{cite journal |author=Kidd SA, Eskenazi B, Wyrobek AJ |title=Effects of male age on semen quality and fertility: a review of the literature |journal=Fertil. Steril. |volume=75 |issue=2 |pages=237–48 |year=2001 |month=February |pmid=11172821 |doi= 10.1016/S0015-0282(00)01679-4|url=http://linkinghub.elsevier.com/retrieve/pii/S0015-0282(00)01679-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
[[Sperm count]] declines with age, with men aged 50–80 years producing sperm at an average rate of 75% compared with men aged 20–50 years.

==Sexual behavior==
[[File:Brigitte Bardot.jpg|thumb|right|120px|[[Brigitte Bardot]]: Famous for [[sex appeal]]]]
Human sexual behavior, driven by the desire for [[pleasure]], encompasses the [[flirting|search for a partner]] or partners, interactions between individuals, [[physical intimacy|physical]], [[emotional intimacy]], and sexual contact which may lead to [[foreplay]], [[masturbation]] and ultimately [[orgasm]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.likeitis.org/sex_print.html Sex. From Likeitis.org.] Retrieved 12 October 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Attraction===
[[Sexual attraction]] is a person's ability to [[Attractiveness|attract]] the interest of another person. It may depend on the [[physical attraction|physical quality]], including both looks and movements, of a person but can also be influenced by voice or smell as well as by  [[individual]] preferences resulting from a variety of [[Genetics|genetic]], [[psychological]], and cultural factors.

Though attempts have been made to devise objective criteria, a person's sexual attractiveness is to a large extent a subjective measure dependent on another person's interest, perception and [[sexual orientation]] as well as on mutual attraction. [[Interpersonal attraction]] includes factors such as [[propinquity|physical or psychological similarity]], [[familiarity]], [[similarity (psychology)|similarity]], [[complementarity]], [[reciprocal liking]], and [[reinforcement]].&lt;ref&gt;Miller, R., Perlman, D., and Brehm, S.S. Intimate Relationships, 4th Edition, McGrawHill
Companies.&lt;/ref&gt;

Women are believed to be more generally attracted to men who are slightly taller and who have a relatively narrow waist and broad shoulders. Men may be attracted by women who are slightly shorter, have a youthful appearance and exhibit features such as a symmetrical face, full breasts, full lips, and a low waist-hip ratio.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/health/2190461.stm Tall men 'top husband stakes'. BBC News.] Retrieved 15 October 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.staff.ncl.ac.uk/daniel.nettle/procroysoc.pdf Daniel Nettle: Women’s height, reproductive success and the evolution of sexual dimorphism in modern humans. The Royal Society.] Retrieved 15 October 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Creating a partnership===
[[File:Eugen de Blaas The Flirtation.jpg|thumb|right|150px|[[Eugene de Blaas]]: Flirtation]]
{{Main|Human sexual behaviour}}

Several stages are involved here. Depending on the individuals concerned and the society in which they live, they may extend over a considerable period or may be completed quite quickly. They can consist of one or more of the following:
*[[Flirting]]: the manner in which an individual gains the attention of another in order to encourage romance or sexual relations by means of body language, conversation, joking or brief physical contact.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sirc.org/publik/flirt.html SIRC Guide to Flirting. What Social Science can tell you about flirting and how to do it.] Retrieved 13 October 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Seduction]]: the process of one person deliberately enticing another to engage in some sort of [[human sexual behavior]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author=Greene, Robert | authorlink=Robert Greene (author) | title=The Art of Seduction | publisher=[[Penguin Books]]| year=2003 | isbn=0-14-200119-8}}&lt;/ref&gt; It can have both positive and negative connotations.
*[[Dating (activity)|Dating]]: the process of arranging meetings or outings with a potential partner with a view to investigating or enhancing their suitability for an [[Intimate relationship|intimate partnership]].
[[File:The Gaze.jpg|thumb|right|150px|Creating a partnership]]
*[[Courtship]]: the traditional dating period before [[engagement]] and [[marriage]] when couples get to know each other better.
*[[Physical intimacy]]: usually an expression of [[feeling]]s such as close [[friendship]] or [[love]], including [[holding hands]], [[hug]]ging, [[kiss]]ing, [[petting|caressing]], often leading to [[Human sexual behavior|sexual activity]].
*[[Foreplay]]: leading on from the above, foreplay can include [[French kiss|deep tongue kissing]], touching and [[massaging]] [[erogenous zones]] over clothing or rubbing them together, and [[Striptease|undressing oneself or partner]].
*[[Non-penetrative sex|Mutual masturbation]]: stimulation of the genitals of one or both partners, usually using the hands, without penetration and sometimes resulting in orgasm.
*[[Sexual intercourse|Intercourse]]: the act, sometimes referred to as penetration, in which the [[Penis|male reproductive organ]] enters the [[Vagina|female reproductive tract]] with a view to achieving [[orgasm]].

===Unconventional practices===
[[File:Hogtie with handle.jpg|thumb|right|150px|Woman in bondage]]
Some people derive sexual pleasure from a variety of [[Kink (sexual)|unconventional practices]] ranging from [[fetishism]] to [[BDSM]].
*[[Sexual Fetishism|Fetishism]] can take many forms ranging from the desire for certain body parts, for example large breasts, rather than the actual partner. The object of desire is often clothing or rubber items. A fetish can however cause people significant psychosocial distress and can have detrimental effects on their lives, in which case treatment may be required.
*[[BDSM]]: a compound acronym covering [[Bondage (BDSM)|bondage]] and [[Discipline (BDSM)|discipline]], [[dominance and submission]], [[Sadomasochism|sadism and masochism]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aslavesheart.com/dictionary.html|title=BDSM Terms|publisher=A Slave's Heart|accessdate=2008-01-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; As a rule, one partner dominates the other during an agreed period of time The parties involved usually experience pleasure although many of the practices performed, such as inflicting pain, humiliation or being restrained would be considered unpleasant under normal circumstances. Oral, anal or vaginal intercourse may occur.

==Sex and religion==
{{main|Religion and sexuality}}
Most religions address the question of a "proper" role for sexuality in human interactions. Different religions have different codes of sexual morality, which regulate sexual activity or assign normative values to certain sexually charged actions or thoughts.

Some cultures discriminate against sexual contact outside of [[marriage]] although it is widely practiced. [[extramarital sex|Extramarital sexual activity]] is strictly forbidden by [[sex segregation and Islam|Islamic]] and [[Religion_and_sexuality#Judaism|Jewish]] law.

===Christianity===
In [[Christianity]], there are wide ranging views on what constitutes acceptable standards of sexual conduct from today's [[List of Christian denominations|Christian denominations]]. Virtually all modern Christians agree that [[Extramarital sex|extramarital affairs]] are clearly forbidden by the Bible. However, there are differing views on the interpretation of Bible passages dealing with the acceptability of [[homosexuality]], [[divorce]] and remarriage, and [[premarital sex]].
===Islam===
Most forms of sexual contact within a marriage are allowed. Sex is considered a pleasurable, even spiritual activity, and a duty. At least one [[hadith]] explicitly states that for a married couple to have sex is a good deed rewarded by God. Another hadith suggests that a man should not leave the proverbial bed until the woman is satisfied, a reference many say points to [[orgasm]].

[[Adultery]] warrants severe punishment. Pre-marital sex is also considered sinful, albeit less severe. All [[shari'a]] laws regulating sexual conduct apply to both men and women equally, apart from those concerning [[menstruation]].

===Judaism===
In traditional [[Judaism]], sex and reproduction are the holiest of acts, permitting one to imitate God, "The Creator". There are, however, many boundaries and guidelines. Within the boundaries, there are virtually no outright strictures. Judaism forbids sexual relations outside of heterosexual marriage, maintains biblical strictures on relations within marriage including observance of [[Niddah]], a prohibition on relations for a period including the menstrual period, and [[Tzniut]], requirements of modest dress and behavior. Traditional Judaism views adultery, incest, and male homosexuality as grave sins.

==Sexual activity and lifestyles==

===Sexual pleasure===
[[Sexual arousal|Sexual pleasure]] is [[pleasure]] derived from any kind of sexual activity. Though [[orgasm]] is generally known, sexual pleasure includes erotic pleasure during [[foreplay]], and pleasure due to [[Sexual fetishism|fetish]] or [[BDSM]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.channel4.com/health/microsites/0-9/4health/sex/sar_tips.html Sex and Relationships - Sex - 4Health from Channel 4&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m1608/is_1_18/ai_80957472 Improve your orgasm: you may have thought your sexual pleasure was the one thing that couldn't get any better. Think again - Sexual Fitness - physiology | Men's Fitness | Find Articles at BNET.com&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Heterosexuality===

{{main|Heterosexuality}}

Heterosexuality involves individuals of opposite [[sex]]es.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.worldsexexplorer.com/heterosexual-sex.html Heterosexual Sex. World Sex Explorer.] Retrieved 13 October 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

Different-sex sexual practices are limited by laws in many places. In some countries, mostly those where religion has a strong influence on [[social policy]], marriage laws serve the purpose of encouraging people to have sex only within marriage. [[Sodomy laws]] were seen as discouraging same-sex sexual practices, but may affect opposite-sex sexual practices. Laws also ban adults from committing [[sexual abuse]], committing sexual acts with anyone under an age of consent, performing sexual activities in public, and engaging in sexual activities for money ([[prostitution]]). Though these laws cover both same-sex and opposite-sex sexual activities, they may differ in regard to punishment, and may be more frequently (or exclusively) enforced on those who engage in same-sex sexual activities.&lt;ref&gt;[http://criminal.findlaw.com/crimes/more-criminal-topics/sex-offenders/sex-offenses-overview.html Sex Offenders and Sex Offenses: Overview. From FindLaw.] Retrieved 13 October 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

Different-sex sexual practices may be [[monogamy|monogamous]], serially monogamous, or [[Polyamory|polyamorous]], and, depending on the definition of sexual practice, [[abstinence|abstinent]] or [[Autosexuality|autoerotic]] (including [[masturbation]]).

Different religious and political movements have tried to influence or control changes in sexual practices including courting and marriage, though in most countries changes occur at a slow rate.&lt;ref&gt;[http://marriagepartner.com/forum/showthread.php?t=3840 Adultery extra marital sex. From MarriagePartner.com.] Retrieved 13 October 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Homosexuality===
{{main|Homosexuality}}
Homosexuality (from Greek homo = same) involves individuals of the same sex.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/homosexual Definition from the Merriam-Webster Online Dictionary.] Retrieved 13 October 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Gay couple.jpg|right|thumb|120px|Gay men]]
People with a homosexual orientation can express their sexuality in a variety of ways, and may or may not express it in their [[sexual behavior|behaviors]].&lt;ref name=APAHelp&gt;[http://www.apahelpcenter.org/articles/article.php?id=31 APA Help Center]&lt;/ref&gt; Some have sexual relationships predominately with people of their own [[gender identity]], another gender, [[bisexual]] relationships or they can be [[celibate]].&lt;ref name=APAHelp /&gt; Research indicates that many lesbians and gay men want, and succeed in having, committed and durable relationships. For example, survey data indicate that between 40% and 60% of gay men and between 45% and 80% of lesbians are currently involved in a romantic relationship.&lt;ref name=WhatIsNature&gt; [http://www.apa.org/topics/sorientation.html#whatisnature What is Nature]&lt;/ref&gt;

It is possible for a person whose sexual identity is mainly heterosexual to engage in sexual acts with people of the same sex. For example, [[mutual masturbation]] in the context of what may be considered normal heterosexual teen development. [[Gay]], [[lesbian]], and [[bisexual]] people who pretend to be heterosexual are often referred to as being [[closeted]], hiding their sexuality in "the closet". "Closet case" is a derogatory term used to refer to people who hide their sexuality. Making that orientation (semi-) public can be called "[[coming out]]" in the case of voluntary disclosure or "[[outing]]" in the case of disclosure by others against the subject's wishes. Among some communities (called "men on the DL" or "[[Down-low (sexual slang)|down-low]]"), same-sex sexual behavior is sometimes viewed as solely for physical pleasure. Men on the "down-low" may engage in sex acts with other men while continuing sexual and romantic relationships with women.

The definition of [[homosexuality]] is a preference to members of one's own sex, though people who engage exclusively in same-sex sexual practices may not identify themselves as [[bisexual]], [[gay]] or [[lesbian]].  In sex-segregated environments, individuals may seek relationships with others of their own gender (known as [[situational homosexuality]]).  In other cases, some people may experiment or explore their sexuality with same (and/or different) sex sexual activity before defining their [[sexual identity]]. Despite stereotypes and common misconceptions, there are no forms of sexual activity exclusive to same-sex sexual behavior that can not also be found in opposite-sex sexual behavior, save those involving contact of the same sex genitalia such as [[tribadism]] and [[frot]].

===Autoerotic sexuality===
[[File:Giorgione 054.jpg|thumb|right|150px|Giorgoni's [[Sleeping Venus (Giorgione)|Sleeping Venus]]]]
{{main|Autoeroticism}}
Autoeroticism, also know as autosexuality, is sexual activity that does not involve another person as a partner. It can involve [[masturbation]], though several [[paraphilia]]s require a partner. Many people use [[dildo]]s, [[Vibrator (sex toy)|vibrator]]s, [[anal beads]], [[sybian]] machines, and other [[sex toy]]s while alone.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.experiencefestival.com/a/Autosexuality/id/1923474 Autosexuality. From Global Oneness.] Retrieved 13 October 2009 &lt;/ref&gt; 

Though many autoerotic practices are relatively physically safe, some can be dangerous. These include [[erotic asphyxiation]] and [[self-bondage]]. The potential for injury or even death that exists while engaging in the partnered versions of these [[Fetishism|fetishes]] ([[Fainting game|choking]] and [[Bondage (sexual)|bondage]], respectively) becomes drastically increased due to the isolation and lack of assistance in the event of a problem.

===Coercive and abusive sexuality===
{{main|Sexual abuse}}

Sexual activity can also encompass sexual abuse&amp;nbsp;— that is, coercive or abusive use of sexuality. Examples include: [[rape]], [[lust murder]], [[child sexual abuse]], and [[zoosadism]] (animal abuse which may be sexual in nature), as well as (in many countries) certain non-consensual paraphilias such as [[frotteurism]], [[telephone scatophilia]] (indecent phonecalls), and non-consensual [[exhibitionism]] and [[voyeurism]] (known as "[[indecent exposure]]" and "[[peeping tom]]" respectively).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ojp.usdoj.gov/bjs/pub/pdf/soo.pdf Sex Offenses and Offenders. U.S. Department of Justice.] Retrieved 14 October 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[sexual abuse]] of individuals is widely prohibited by law and considered against the norms of society.


==History of sexuality==
{{Main|History of human sexuality}}
===Ancient civilizations===
[[File:Min.jpg|right|thumb|120px|[[Min (god)|Min]]: the ancient Egyptian god of fertility]]
Many of the ancient civilisations provide evidence of developments in sexuality. In particular:
*[[Egypt]]: The couple [[Khnumhotep and Niankhkhnum]], now buried in a joint [[Fifth dynasty of Egypt|Fifth-dynasty]] (2498-2345 BC) era tomb in [[Saqqara]], [[Egypt]], are the oldest recorded same-sex couple in human history. The Ancient Egyptians related the cult of phallus with [[Osiris]]. When Osiris' body was cut in 13 pieces, Seth scattered them all over Egypt and his wife [[Isis]] retrieved all of them except one, his penis, which was swallowed by a fish (see the [[Legend of Osiris and Isis]]). The phallus was a symbol of fertility, and the god [[Min (god)|Min]] was often depicted ''ithyphallic'' (with a penis).

*[[History of sex in India|India]]: Ancient texts from [[Hinduism]], [[Buddhism]] and [[Jainism]] such as the [[Rig Veda|Vedas]] reveal moral perspectives on sexuality, marriage and fertility prayers. The epics of ancient India, the [[Ramayana]] and [[Mahabharata]], possibly from as early as [[1400 BCE]], later influenced [[China|Chinese]], [[Japan]]ese, [[Tibet]]an and [[South East Asia]]n culture. They indicate that sex was considered a mutual duty between a married couple, but where sex was considered a private affair. The most publicly known sexual literature of India are the texts of the [[Kama Sutra|sixty-four arts]].
*[[Mesopotamia]]: In ancient Mesopotamia, [[Ishtar]] was the primary Goddess of life, men and women, nature and fertility, sex, sexual power and birth. Ishtar was also the goddess of war and weapons and any victory was celebrated in her temples with offerings of produce and money as well as through a feast and orgy of sex and fornication with holy [[temple prostitute]]s. 
*[[China]]: In the ''[[I Ching]]'' (The ''Book of Changes'', a Chinese classic text dealing with what would be in the West termed metaphysics), sexual intercourse is one of two fundamental models used to explain the world. Heaven is described as having sexual intercourse with Earth. The male lovers of early Chinese men of great political power are mentioned in one of the earliest great works of philosophy and literature, the ''[[Zhuang Zi]]''. China has had a long history of sexism, with even moral leaders such as [[Confucius]] giving extremely pejorative accounts of the innate characteristics of women. 
*[[Japan]]: In perhaps the earliest novel in the world, the ''[[Genji Monogatari]]'' (''[[Tale of Genji]]''), dating back to around the 8th century AD, eroticism is treated as a central part of the aesthetic life of members of the nobility.
*[[Greece]]: In ancient [[Greece]], the [[phallus]], often in the form of a [[herma]], was an object of worship as a symbol of fertility. One ancient Greek male idea of female sexuality was that women envied penises of males. Wives were considered as commodity and instruments for bearing legitimate children. They had to compete sexually with [[eromenoi]], [[hetaera]]s and slaves in their own homes.
*[[Rome]]: Ancient Roman civilization included celebrations associated with human reproductive organs. Over time there emerged institutionalization of voluntary sex as well as prostitution. This resulted in a virtual sexual caste system in Roman civilization – different grades and degrees of sexual relationships. Apart from the legally wedded spouses, a number of males used to have [[Delicatue]], mistresses of wealthy and prominent men. The next were the Famosae, mostly the daughters and even wives of the wealthy families who enjoyed sex for its own sake. There was another class known as [[Lupae]], willing to have sexual union with anyone for a price. Copae were the serving girls in the taverns and inns and who did not mind being hired as bedmates for the night by travelers.

===Modern developments===
{{Main|Sexology}}

In contemporary academia, sexuality is studied in the fields of [[sexology]] and [[gender and sexuality studies]], among many other fields.

Sexology, the study of sexual interests, behavior, and function, covers [[sexual development]] and [[sexual relationship]]s including [[sexual intercourse]].  It also documents the sexualities of groups such as the disabled, children, and the [[geriatric sexology|elderly]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www2.hu-berlin.de/sexology/GESUND/ARCHIV/HISTORY.HTM Erwin J. Haeberle: A Brief History of Sexology. Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin]. Retrieved 15 October 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Alfred Kinsey]] became interested in the different forms of sexual practices around 1933 when he developed the [[Kinsey Scale]] which ranges from 0 to 6, where 0 is exclusively heterosexual and 6 is exclusively homosexual. His [[Kinsey Reports]] starting with the publication of [[Sexual Behavior in the Human Male]] in 1948 and [[Sexual Behavior in the Human Female]] in 1953 contributed to the sexual revolution of the 1960s. 
 
===Foucault===
The French philosopher [[Michel Foucault]] wrote in ''[[The History of Sexuality]]'' (1976-1984) that the concept of "sexual" activities and sensations is historically (as well as regionally and culturally) determined. It is therefore part of a changing "discourse".&lt;ref name="Ross81"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Rathus2007"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Foucault76"&gt;[[Michel Foucault|Foucault, M.]] (1976) ''[[The History of Sexuality]]'', ''Vol I: [[The Will to Knowledge]]''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Weeks85"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;MARY WEISMANTEL ''[http://www.anthrosource.net/doi/abs/10.1525/aa.2004.106.3.495 Moche Sex Pots: Reproduction and Temporality in Ancient South America]'' [[American Anthropologist]] September 2004, Vol. 106, No. 3, pp. 495-505 &lt;/ref&gt; The [[sexual meanings]] (meanings of the erotic dimension of human sexual experience) are [[social and cultural constructs]]. They are made subjective only after cultural and social mediation.&lt;ref name="Parker89"&gt;Parker, Richard G. ''[Bodies and Pleasures: On the Construction of Erotic Meanings in Contemporary Brazil]'' Anthropology &amp; Humanism Quarterly. June 1989, Vol. 14, No. 2, pp. 58-64&lt;/ref&gt; As the main force conditioning human relationships, sex is essentially [[political]]. In any [[Social environment|social context]], the construction of a "sexual universe" is fundamentally linked to the structures of power.&lt;ref name="Ross81"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Parker89"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Gayle Rubin]] (1984) ''Thinking Sex: Notes for a Radical Theory of the Politics of  Sexuality''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Toward a Conversation about Sex in Feminism: A Modest Proposal
[http://www.sms.mailman.columbia.edu/faculty/vance.html Vance, Carole S.] ''[Pleasure and danger: Toward a politics of sexuality]''&lt;/ref&gt; The construction of sexual meanings is an instrument by which social institutions (religion, marketing, the educational system, psychiatry, etc.) control and shape [[Interpersonal relationship|human relationships]].&lt;ref name="Foucault76"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Weeks85"&gt;{{cite book |author=[[Jeffrey Weeks (sociologist)|Weeks, Jeffrey]] |title=Sexuality and its Discontents; Meanings, Myths, and Modern Sexualities |publisher=Routledge |location=New York |year= 1989|pages= |isbn=0-415-04503-7 |oclc= |doi=|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=QzkTiK9oQVIC}} pp.176-8&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Foucault, sexuality began to be regarded as a conceptual part of [[human nature]] in the 19th century. Sexuality began to be used as a means to define [[normality]] and its boundaries, and to conceive everything outside those boundaries in the realm of [[psychopathology]]. In the 20th century, with the theories of [[Sigmund Freud]] and of [[sexology]], the "not-normal" was seen more as a "discontent of civilization"&lt;ref name="Foucault76"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Cáceres2000"&gt;Cáceres ''The production of knowledge on sexuality in the AIDS era.''in {{cite book |author=Aggleton, Peter; Parker, Richard Bordeaux; Barbosa, Regina Maria |title=Framing the sexual subject: the politics of gender, sexuality, and power |publisher=University of California Press |location=Berkeley |year=2000 |pages= |isbn=0-520-21838-8 |oclc= |doi=}} pp.242-3&lt;/ref&gt; In a well known passage of his work, Foucault noted that the development of the notion of sexuality organized [[sex]] as a "[http://books.google.it/books?id=gyWuhD3Q3IcC&amp;pg=PA117&amp;lpg=PA117&amp;dq=%22fictitious+unity%22&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=guqQTNsvgf&amp;sig=qLCzv_FZSpELAE1mbYCkOBgvzBM&amp;hl=it&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;resnum=3&amp;ct=result#PPA117,M1 fictitious unity]" of "disparate parts, functions, behaviours, and feelings with no natural or necessary relation among them"; therefore the conception of what is "natural" is a [[social construct]].&lt;ref name="Strozier"&gt;Strozier, Robert M. (2002) ''[http://books.google.com/books?id=fuDdNSLXPI8C Foucault, Subjectivity, and Identity: : Historical Constructions of Subject and Self]'' pp.101-2, 108, 118-120&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Foucault 1976, p.154-5&lt;/ref&gt; To escape such cultural "sexuality", Foucault suggested focusing on "bodies and pleasures".&lt;ref name="Strozier"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Foucault 1976, p.157&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
&lt;!--If you want to add general topics, add them to the list below--&gt;
{{wikinews|Dr. Joseph Merlino on sexuality, insanity, Courtship, Freud, fetishes and apathy}}
* [[Index of human sexuality articles]]
* [[Sexology]]
* [[Sexualisation]]

==Footnotes==
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
* [http://nsrc.sfsu.edu/MagWebpage.cfm?&amp;Page=175 American Sexuality Magazine]
* [http://www.sexology.it/glossario_sessuologia.html Glossario di sessuologia clinica - Glossary of clinical sexology]
* [http://www.uvm.edu/~dhowell/EBS/History_of_Surveys_of_Sexual_Behavior1.pdf History of Surveys of Sexual Behavior] from [http://www.uvm.edu/~dhowell/EBS/ Encyclopedia of Behavioral Statistics]
* [http://www2.hu-berlin.de/sexology/IES/index.html International Encyclopedia of Sexuality] [http://www2.rz.hu-berlin.de/sexology/GESUND/ARCHIV/IES/BEGIN.HTM full text]
* Janssen, D. F., [http://www2.hu-berlin.de/sexology/GESUND/ARCHIV/GUS/INDEXATLAS.HTM ''Growing Up Sexually. Volume I.  World Reference Atlas''] [full text]
* [http://nsrc.sfsu.edu National Sexuality Resource Center]
* [http://data360.org/pdf/20070416064139.Global%20Sex%20Survey.pdf Durex Global Sex Survey 2005] at [http://data360.org/index.aspx data360.org]
* [http://db.jhuccp.org/popinform/basic.html POPLINE] is a searchable database of the world's [[reproductive health]] literature.
* [http://www.kinseyinstitute.org/ccies/ The Continuum Complete International Encyclopedia of Sexuality at the Kinsey Institute]
* [http://www.sexualityinstitute.org The Sexuality and Rights Institute]
* [http://www.asiasrc.org The South and Southeast Asia Resource Centre on Sexuality]

{{sex}}
{{Sexual ethics}}
{{Sexual urban legends}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Human Sexuality}}
[[Category:Human sexuality| ]]
[[Category:Fertility]]

[[bar:Sexualität]]
[[bs:Seksualnost]]
[[bg:Сексуалност]]
[[ca:Sexualitat]]
[[cs:Sexualita]]
[[cy:Rhywioldeb dynol]]
[[da:Seksualitet]]
[[de:Sexualität des Menschen]]
[[et:Seksuaalsus]]
[[es:Sexualidad]]
[[eo:Sekseco]]
[[fa:جنسیت]]
[[fr:Sexualité humaine]]
[[fur:Sessualitât umane]]
[[gl:Sexualidade]]
[[ko:인간의 성]]
[[hr:Seksualnost]]
[[is:Kynlíf]]
[[it:Sessualità]]
[[he:מיניות]]
[[ht:Seksyalite]]
[[la:Sexualitas humana]]
[[li:Miensjelike seksualiteit]]
[[hu:Szexualitás]]
[[mk:Сексуалност]]
[[nl:Seksualiteit]]
[[ja:人間の性]]
[[no:Seksualitet]]
[[nn:Seksualitet]]
[[pl:Seksualność]]
[[pt:Sexualidade]]
[[ksh:Sekksowallitäd]]
[[ro:Sexualitate]]
[[ru:Сексуальность человека]]
[[sc:Sessualidade de s'òmine]]
[[simple:Human sexuality]]
[[sk:Ľudská sexualita]]
[[sr:Људска сексуалност]]
[[fi:Seksuaalisuus]]
[[sv:Sexualitet]]
[[tr:İnsan cinselliği]]
[[vi:Tình dục]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>