<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20101020160732|391859433" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="280746" pageid="280746" ns="0" title="International Women&#039;s Day"><revisions><rev timestamp="2010-11-12T09:52:13Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Holiday |
|holiday_name=International Women's Day
|observedby=[[Albania]], [[Algeria]], [[Argentina]], [[Armenia]], [[Australia]], [[Azerbaijan]], [[Bangladesh]], [[Belarus]], [[Bhutan]], [[Bosnia and Herzegovina]], [[Brazil]], [[Bulgaria]], [[Burkina Faso]], [[Cambodia]], [[Cameroon]], [[Chile]], [[China]], [[Colombia]], [[Costa Rica]], [[Croatia]], [[Cuba]], [[Cyprus]], [[Ecuador]], [[Estonia]], [[Denmark]], [[Finland]], [[Georgia (country)|Georgia]], [[Greece]], [[Hungary]], [[Iceland]], [[India]], [[Italy]], [[Israel]], [[Laos]], [[Latvia]], [[Lithuania]], [[Kazakhstan]], [[Kosovo]], [[Kyrgyzstan]], [[Republic of Macedonia|Macedonia]], [[Malta]], [[Mexico]], [[Moldova]], [[Mongolia]], [[Montenegro]], [[Nepal]], [[Norway]], [[Poland]], [[Portugal]], [[Romania]], [[Russia]], [[Serbia]], [[Slovakia]], [[Slovenia]], [[South Africa]], [[Sweden]], [[Spain]], [[Syria]], [[Taiwan]], [[Tajikistan]], [[Thailand]], [[Turkey]], [[Turkmenistan]], [[Ukraine]], [[Uruguay]], [[Uzbekistan]], [[Vietnam]], [[Zambia]]
|date=March 8 (annually)
|type=
|relatedto=[[Mother's Day]], [[Universal Children's Day]], [[International Men's Day]]
}}
'''International Women's Day''' ('''IWD'''), originally called '''International Working Women’s Day''' is marked on the '''[[March 8|8th of March]]''' every year. It is a major day of global celebration of women. In different regions the focus of the celebrations ranges from general celebration of respect, appreciation and love towards women to a celebration for women's economic, political and social achievements. 

Started as a Socialist political event, the holiday blended in the culture of many countries, primarily [[Eastern Europe]], [[Russia]], and the former [[Soviet bloc]]. In many regions, the day lost its political flavour, and became simply an occasion for men to express their love for women in a way somewhat similar to a mixture of [[Mother's Day]] and [[St Valentine's Day]]. In other regions, however, the original political and human rights theme designated by the [[United Nations]] runs strong, and political and social awareness of the struggles of women worldwide are brought out and examined in a hopeful manner.

[[Image:NSW Builders Labourers march on IWD 1975.jpg|thumb|Female members of the Australian [[Builders Labourers Federation]] march on International Women's Day 1975 in Sydney]]
[[File:Acacia dealbata.jpg|thumb|The ''mimosa'' (technically, the [[Silver Wattle]]) is the symbol of the celebrations of Women's day in [[Italy]] and [[Russia]]]]
The first IWD was observed on 19 March 1911 in Germany following a declaration by the [[Socialist Party of America]]. The idea of having an international women's day was first put forward at the turn of the 20th century amid rapid world [[industrialization]] and economic expansion that led to protests over working conditions{{Citation needed|date=April 2010}}  

In 1910, [[Second International]] held the first international women's conference in [[Copenhagen]] (in the labour-movement building located at Jagtvej 69, which until recently housed [[Ungdomshuset]]).  An 'International Women's Day' was established. It was suggested by the important German Socialist [[Clara Zetkin]], although no date was specified.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.un.org/events/women/iwd/2008/history.shtml United Nations page on the background of the IWD]&lt;/ref&gt; The following year, 1911, IWD was marked by over a million people in [[Austria]], [[Denmark]], [[Germany]] and [[Switzerland]], on March 19.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.internationalwomensday.com/first.asp Internationalwomensday.com]&lt;/ref&gt; However, soon thereafter, on March 25, the Triangle Shirtwaist Factory fire in New York City killed over 140 garment workers. A lack of safety measures was blamed for the high death toll. Furthermore, on the eve of [[World War I]], women across [[Europe]] held peace rallies on 8 March 1913. In the West, International Women's Day was first observed in the 1970s.{{Citation needed|date=April 2010}}

Demonstrations marking International Women's Day in [[Russia]] proved to be the first stage of the [[Russian Revolution of 1917]].{{Citation needed|date=April 2010}}

Following the [[October Revolution]], the [[Bolshevik]] [[Alexandra Kollontai]] persuaded [[Lenin]] to make it an [[Public holiday|official holiday]] in the Soviet Union, and it was established, but was a working day until 1965. On May 8, 1965 by the decree of the [[USSR]] [[Presidium of the Supreme Soviet]] International Women's Day was declared a non working day in the USSR "in commemoration of the outstanding merits of Soviet women in communistic construction, in the defense of their Fatherland during the Great Patriotic War, in their heroism and selflessness at the front and in the rear, and also marking the great contribution of women to strengthening friendship between peoples, and the struggle for peace. But still, women's day must be celebrated as are other holidays."

== 2010 International Women's Day ==

On occasion of 2010 International Women's Day the [[International Committee of the Red Cross]] is drawing attention to the hardship displaced women endure. The displacement of populations is one of the gravest consequences of today's armed conflicts. It affects women in a host of ways.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.icrc.org/web/eng/siteeng0.nsf/htmlall/women-displacement-interview-020310 Women and displacement: strength in adversity] International Committee of the Red Cross.&lt;/ref&gt;

Women displaced by armed conflict – often living alone with their children – are frequently exposed to sexual violence, discrimination and intimidation. Many face poverty and social exclusion as well. International humanitarian law therefore includes specific provisions protecting women, for example when they are pregnant or as mothers of young children.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.icrc.org/Web/Eng/siteeng0.nsf/html/women-news-040310 International Women's Day: giving a say to displaced women] International Committee of the Red Cross.&lt;/ref&gt;

== In modern culture ==
[[Image:8marta.jpg|thumb|The 1932 Soviet poster dedicated to the 8th of March holiday. The text reads: "8th of March is the day of rebellion of the working women against kitchen slavery" and "Down with the oppression and narrow-mindedness of household work!". Originally in the USSR the holiday had a clear political character, emphasizing the role of the Soviet state in ''the liberation of women'' from their second-class-citizen status.]]
[[Image:8march landysh.jpg|thumb|However, with time the meaning of the holiday evolved to an apolitical celebration of women. Most late Soviet 8th of March postcards carried no political meaning.]]
The day is an official holiday in [[Afghanistan]],&lt;ref name="IWD"&gt;[http://www.irinnews.org/report.aspx?reportid=28296][[Angola]].&lt;/ref&gt; [[Armenia]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.armeniainfo.am/about/?section=holidays Armeniainfo.am].&lt;/ref&gt; [[Azerbaijan]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.azerbaijan.msntour.az/index.php?categoryID=7 MSNtour.az].&lt;/ref&gt; [[Belarus]],&lt;ref&gt;{{ru icon}} [http://www.pravo.by/webnpa/text_txt.asp?RN=P39800157 President's decree on public holidays in Belarus], 1998.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Burkina Faso]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.visarequest.co.za/visa/publicholidayssa.php?Embassy=Burkina%20Faso Visarequest.co.za].&lt;/ref&gt; [[Cambodia]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cambodiaevisa.com/2007/01/05/2007-cambodia-public-holiday/ Cambodiaevisa.com].&lt;/ref&gt; [[China]] (for women only),&lt;ref&gt;[http://sg2.mofcom.gov.cn/aarticle/aboutchina/publicholiday/200801/20080105327831.html Mofcom.gov.cn].&lt;/ref&gt; [[Cuba]],{{Citation needed|date=March 2009}} [[Georgia (country)|Georgia]], [[Guinea-Bissau]],&lt;ref name="IWD" /&gt; [[Eritrea]],&lt;ref name="IWD" /&gt; [[Kazakhstan]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://e.gov.kz/wps/portal/Content?contentPath=/library2/1_kazakhstan/kr/article/prazdniki&amp;lang=en E.gov.kz].&lt;/ref&gt; [[Kyrgyzstan]], [[Laos]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://laoyp.com/laopdr/events/ Laoyp.com].&lt;/ref&gt; [[Madagascar]] (for women only),&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.qppstudio.net/publicholidays2009/madagascar.htm QPPstudion.net].&lt;/ref&gt; [[Moldova]],&lt;ref&gt;{{ro icon}} [http://www.parlament.md/download/laws/ro/154-XV-28.03.2003.doc Article 111 (1c) of the work codex of Moldova] "Article 111. Non-working holidays. (1) in Moldova, non-working holidays, maintaining the average salary, are: (...) c) March 8 - International Women's Day; (...)".&lt;/ref&gt; [[Mongolia]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mongolia-web.com/content/view/33/39/ Mongolia-web.com].&lt;/ref&gt; [[Montenegro]],{{Citation needed|date=March 2009}}, [[Nepal]] (for women only),&lt;ref name="IWD" /&gt;, [[Russia]],&lt;ref name="IWD" /&gt; [[Tajikistan]],&lt;ref name="IWD" /&gt; [[Turkmenistan]],&lt;ref name="IWD" /&gt; [[Uganda]],&lt;ref name="IWD" /&gt; [[Ukraine]],&lt;ref name="IWD" /&gt; [[Uzbekistan]],&lt;ref name="IWD" /&gt; [[Vietnam]],{{Citation needed|date=March 2009}} and [[Zambia]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.qppstudio.net/publicholidays2009/zambia.htm QPPstudion.net].&lt;/ref&gt;

In some countries, such as [[Cameroon]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.qppstudio.net/publicholidays2009/cameroon.htm QPPstudio.net]&lt;/ref&gt;, [[Croatia]]{{Citation needed|date=March 2009}}, [[Romania]]{{Citation needed|date=March 2009}}, [[Serbia]]{{Citation needed|date=March 2009}} the day is not a public holiday, but is widely observed nonetheless.

On this day it is customary for men to give the women in their lives - mothers, wives, girlfriends, daughters, colleagues, etc. - flowers and small gifts. In some countries (such as Romania) it is also observed as an equivalent of Mother's Day, where children also give small presents to their mothers and grandmothers.

In Armenia, after the collapse of the Soviet Union celebrations of IWD were abandoned. Instead, April 7 was introduced as state holiday of ‘Beauty and Motherhood’. The new holiday immediately got popular among [[Armenians]], as it commemorates one of the main holidays of the [[Armenian Apostolic Church|Armenian Church]], the [[Annunciation]]. However, people still kept celebrating IWD on March 8 as well. Public discussion held on the topic of two ‘Women’s Days’ in Armenia resulted in the recognition of the so called ‘Women’s Month’ which is the period between March 8 and April 7.

In [[Italy]], to celebrate the day, men give [[Acacia dealbata|yellow mimosas]] to women.&lt;ref&gt;{{it icon}} [http://www.repubblica.it/online/societa/otto/otto/otto.html la Repubblica/societa: 8 marzo, niente manifestazione tante feste diverse per le donne].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.repubblica.it/2006/c/sezioni/politica/versoelezioni34/ciampidonne/ciampidonne.html Repubblica.it » politica » Festa della donna, parla Ciampi "La parità è ancora lontana"&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;].&lt;/ref&gt; Yellow mimosas and chocolate are also one of the most common March 8 presents in [[Russia]] and [[Albania]].

In many countries, such as In [[Bosnia and Herzegovina]], [[Brazil]], [[Bulgaria]], [[Croatia]], [[Estonia]], [[Hungary]], [[Lithuania]], [[Republic of Macedonia|Macedonia]], [[Moldova]], [[Montenegro]], [[Poland]], Romania, Russia, [[Serbia]], [[Slovakia]] and [[Slovenia]], the custom of giving women flowers still prevails. Women sometimes get gifts from their employers too. Schoolchildren often bring gifts for their teachers as well.

In countries like [[Portugal]] groups of women usually celebrate on the night of 8 March in "women-only" dinners and parties.{{Citation needed|date=March 2009}}

In [[India]], IWD holds a lot of significance. Many celebrations are held during the day.

In [[Pakistan]] working women in formal and informal sectors celebrate International Women's Day every year to commemorate their ongoing struggle for due rights, despite facing many cultural and religious restrictions. Some women working for change in society use IWM to help the movement for women's rights. In [[Poland]], for instance, every IWD includes large feminist demonstrations in major cities.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ippf.org/en/News/Intl+news/March+8+in+Poland+Still+Marching+Together+for+Freedom+and+Equality.htm IPPF.org].&lt;/ref&gt;
 
In 1975, which had been designated as International Women’s Year, the United Nations gave official sanction to and began sponsoring International Women's Day.
 
The 2005, Congress (conference) of the British [[Trades Union Congress]] overwhelmingly approved a resolution calling for IWD to be designated a public holiday in the [[United Kingdom]].

Since 2005, IWD has been celebrated in [[Montevideo]], either on the principal street, 18 de Julio, or alternatively through one of its neighbourhoods. The event has attracted much publicity due to a group of female drummers, [http://www.lamelaza.com/ La Melaza], who have performed each year.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.uruguaynow.com/la_melaza_candombe.php Uruguaynow.com].&lt;/ref&gt;

Today, many events are held by women's groups around the world. The UK-based marketing company [[Aurora (organization)|Aurora]] hosts a free worldwide register of IWD local events&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.internationalwomensday.com Internationalwomensday.com].&lt;/ref&gt; so that women and the media can learn about local activity. Many governments and organizations around the world support IWD.

There is a map of IWD events available at this location, for women's groups around the world.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sophiasirius.net].&lt;/ref&gt;

==Controversies==
In some cases International Women's Day has led to questionable practices that discriminated against men. For example [[Tower Hamlets Council]] closed off one of its libraries to all males to "celebrate" the occasion, forcing them to travel elsewhere, going as far as even banning male staff from the premises.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thelondonpaper.com/cs/Satellite/london/lcsearch/article/1157146635813?packedargs=suffix%3DArticleController Thelondonpaper.com].&lt;/ref&gt; Attacks have also been focused on religious institutions, such as when, on 8 March 2000, a group of militant [[Feminism|feminists]] in [[Montreal]], [[Quebec]], set [[Cross burning|burning crosses]] on the steps of a [[Catholic Church|Roman Catholic]] church as a part of a wider ransacking of the building following an International Women's Day march. The event garnered no response from the [[Cabinet of Canada|Cabinet]] at the time.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation |last=Gunter |first=Lorne |title=Real cross-burning ignored by Hedy Fry |newspaper=National Post |date=31 March 2001 |url=http://www.fact.on.ca/news/news0103/np010331.htm |accessdate=2009-10-02}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the Czech Republic (then part of Czechoslovak Socialist Republic), huge Soviet style celebrations were held annually. After the fall of Communism, the holiday, generally considered to be one of the major symbols of the old regime, fell into obscurity. International Women's Day was re-established as an official "important day" by the Parliament only recently, on the proposal of the Social-democrats and Communists. This has provoked some controversy as a large part of public as well as the political right see the holiday as a relic of the nation's Communist past. In 2008, the conservative Catholic People's party's deputies proposed abolishment of the holiday unsuccessfully. However, some non-government organizations consider International Women's Day's official recognition as an important reminder of the women's role in the society. Still, unlike in the past, the holiday is no longer observed by the general public in any significant way.{{Citation needed|date=May 2009}}

International Women's Day encountered violence in [[Tehran]], [[Iran]] on March 4, 2007, when police beat hundreds of men and women who were planning a rally. Police arrested dozens of women and some were released after several days of solitary confinement and interrogation.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/6426087.stm BBC.CO.UK].&lt;/ref&gt; [[Shadi Sadr]] and Mahbubeh Abbasgholizadeh, and several more community activists, were released on March 19, 2007, ending a fifteen day hunger strike.&lt;ref&gt;[http://hrw.org/english/docs/2007/03/07/iran15452.htm HRW.ORG].&lt;/ref&gt;

==Apocrypha==

A popular [[apocryphal]] story which surfaced in French Communist circles,&lt;ref name="emancipatie.nl"&gt;Temma Kaplan, On the Socialist Origins of International Women's Day, in: Feminist Studies, 11, 1985, S. 163-171. ([http://www.emancipatie.nl/_documenten/vvnl/doc/2006/KaplanSocialistOrigins.pdf PDF])&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Françoise Picq 1982"&gt;Liliane Kandel / Françoise Picq, Le Mythe des origines à propos de la journée internationale des femmes, in: La Revue d'en face, 12, 1982, S. 67-80.&lt;/ref&gt; claimed women from [[clothing]] and [[textile]] factories had staged a protest on 8 March 1857 in [[New York, New York|New York City]].&lt;ref&gt;Angela Howard Zophy, Handbook of American women's history, Garland, 1990, 187.&lt;/ref&gt; The story alleged that garment workers were protesting against very poor working conditions and low wages and were attacked and dispersed by [[police]]. It was claimed that this event led to a rally in commemoration of its 50th anniversary in 1907. Temma Kaplan&lt;ref name="emancipatie.nl"/&gt; explains that "neither event seems to have taken place, but many Europeans think March 8, 1907 inaugurated International Women's Day."&lt;ref name="emancipatie.nl"/&gt; Speculating about the origins of this 1857 legend, Liliane Kandel and Françoise Picq suggested it was likely that (in recent times) some felt it opportune to detach International Women's Day from its basis in Soviet history and ascribe to it a more 'international' origin which could be painted as more ancient than Bolshevism and more spontaneous than a decision of Congress or the initiative of those women affiliated to the Party.&lt;ref name="Françoise Picq 1982"/&gt;

==See also==
*[[International Men's Day]]
*[[Mother's Day]]
*[[Susan B. Anthony Day]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
{{wikisource|Supporting the Goals of International Women's Day}}
{{Commons category|International Women's Day}}
* [http://www.icrc.org/eng/women Women and war - International Committee of the Red Cross]
* [http://imaginingourselves.imow.org/ International Museum of Women]
* [http://www.freepeoplesmovement.org/fpm/page.php?277 Article from international communist organization on International Women's Day]
* [http://www.un.org/events/women/iwd/2007/ International Women's Day 2007 - United Nations web site]
* [http://www.internationalwomensday.com/ Internationalwomensday.com]
* [http://www.holidayyear.com/holidays/womens-day.html International Women's Day Celebration]
* [http://www0.un.org/cyberschoolbus/womensday/index.asp More detailed overview]
* [http://www.redcross.org.uk/news.asp?id=91320 Sewing a better future on International Women’s Day]
* [http://100yrswomensday.blogspot.com/ Towards International Women's Day 2011]
* [http://www.sophiasirius.net Wings &amp; Dreams: 4 Elements of a New Feminism]
* [http://www.democracynow.org/2010/3/8/international_womens_day_marked_around_the International Women’s Day Marked Around the World] - video by ''[[Democracy Now!]]''

{{Russia Holidays}}

[[Category:Civil awareness days]]
[[Category:Feminism]]
[[Category:Holidays in Russia]]
[[Category:Holidays in the Soviet Union]]
[[Category:International observances]]
[[Category:March observances]]
[[Category:United Nations days|Women's Day, International]]
[[Category:Women]]

{{Link GA|eo}}
{{Link FA|ka}}

[[ar:اليوم الدولي للمرأة]]
[[ast:Día Internacional de la Muyer]]
[[az:Beynəlxalq Qadınlar Günü]]
[[zh-min-nan:Kok-chè Hū-lú-cheh]]
[[bs:Međunarodni dan žena]]
[[bg:Международен ден на жената]]
[[ca:Dia de la Dona Treballadora]]
[[cv:Пĕтĕм тĕнчери хĕрарăмсен кунĕ]]
[[cs:Mezinárodní den žen]]
[[da:Kvindernes internationale kampdag]]
[[de:Internationaler Frauentag]]
[[et:Rahvusvaheline naistepäev]]
[[es:Día Internacional de la Mujer]]
[[eo:Internacia tago de virinoj]]
[[eu:Emakume Langilearen Nazioarteko Eguna]]
[[fa:روز جهانی زن]]
[[fr:Journée internationale des droits de la femme]]
[[gl:Día da Muller Traballadora]]
[[ko:세계 여성의 날]]
[[hr:Međunarodni dan žena]]
[[id:Hari Perempuan Internasional]]
[[is:Alþjóðlegur baráttudagur kvenna]]
[[it:Giornata Internazionale della Donna]]
[[he:יום האישה הבינלאומי]]
[[kn:ಅಂತರರಾಷ್ಟ್ರೀಯ ಮಹಿಳಾ ದಿನಾಚರಣೆ]]
[[ka:ქალთა საერთაშორისო დღე]]
[[kk:Халықаралық әйелдер күні]]
[[ku:Roja Jinên Cîhanê]]
[[lv:Starptautiskā sieviešu diena]]
[[lt:Tarptautinė moters diena]]
[[hu:Nemzetközi nőnap]]
[[mk:Меѓународен ден на жената]]
[[mr:जागतिक महिला दिन]]
[[arz:يوم الستات الدولى]]
[[ms:Hari Wanita Antarabangsa]]
[[mwl:Die anternacional de la mulhier]]
[[mn:Олон улсын эмэгтэйчүүдийн өдөр]]
[[nl:Internationale Vrouwendag]]
[[ja:国際女性デー]]
[[no:Den internasjonale kvinnedagen]]
[[nn:Den internasjonale kvinnedagen]]
[[uz:Xalqaro xotin-qizlar kuni]]
[[km:ទិវានារីអន្តរជាតិ]]
[[pl:Dzień Kobiet]]
[[pt:Dia Internacional da Mulher]]
[[ro:Ziua internațională a femeii]]
[[ru:Международный женский день]]
[[sq:Dita Ndërkombëtare e Gruas]]
[[scn:Jurnata Ntirnazziunali dâ Fìmmina]]
[[simple:International Women's Day]]
[[sk:Medzinárodný deň žien]]
[[sl:Dan žena]]
[[sr:Међународни дан жена]]
[[sh:Međunarodni dan žena]]
[[fi:Kansainvälinen naistenpäivä]]
[[sv:Internationella kvinnodagen]]
[[ta:அனைத்துலக பெண்கள் நாள்]]
[[te:అంతర్జాతీయ మహిళా దినోత్సవం]]
[[th:วันสตรีสากล]]
[[tg:Рӯзи байналхалқии занон]]
[[tr:8 Mart Dünya Kadınlar Günü]]
[[uk:Міжнародний жіночий день]]
[[vi:Ngày Quốc tế Phụ nữ]]
[[zh:国际妇女节]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>