<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20141119153312|634549649" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="280746" pageid="280746" ns="0" title="International Women&#039;s Day"><revisions><rev timestamp="2014-11-19T17:07:05Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Use mdy dates|date=May 2013}}
'''{{Infobox holiday|
|image=Frauentag 1914 Heraus mit dem Frauenwahlrecht.jpg
|caption=German poster for International Women's Day, March 8th, 1914; English translation: “Give Us Women’s Suffrage. Women’s Day, March 8, 1914. Until now, prejudice and reactionary attitudes have denied full civic rights to women, who as workers, mothers, and citizens wholly fulfill their duty, who must pay their taxes to the state as well as the municipality. Fighting for this natural human right must be the firm, unwavering intention of every woman, every female worker. In this, no pause for rest, no respite is allowed. Come all, you women and girls, to the 9th public women’s assembly on Sunday, March 8, 1914, at 3pm.” &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://germanhistorydocs.ghi-dc.org/sub_image.cfm?image_id=1651 |title=Give Us Women’s Suffrage (March 1914) |publisher=German History in Documents and Images |accessdate=2014-01-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|holiday_name=International women's day
|frequency = annual
|observedby = Worldwide
|scheduling=same day each year
|date=8 March 
|type = international
|significance  = Civil awareness day&lt;br /&gt;Women and girls day&lt;br /&gt;[[Sexism|Anti-sexism]] day &lt;br /&gt; Anti-Discrimination Day
|relatedto=[[Universal Children's Day]], [[International Men's Day]], [[International Workers' Day]]
}}
{{Feminism sidebar}}

'''International Women's Day''' ('''IWD'''), also called '''International Working Women's Day''', is celebrated on '''March 8''' every year.&lt;ref name = "UN"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.un.org/womenwatch/feature/iwd/history.html | title=UN WomenWatch: International Women's Day – History | publisher=UN.org | accessdate=2013-02-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; In different regions the focus of the celebrations ranges from general celebration of respect, appreciation and love towards women to a celebration for women's economic, political, and social achievements. Started as a Socialist political event, the holiday blended in the culture of many countries, primarily in Europe, including Russia. In some regions, the day lost its political flavor, and became simply an occasion for men to express their love for women in a way somewhat similar to a mixture of [[Mother's Day]] and [[Valentine's Day]]. In other regions, however, the political and human rights theme designated by the United Nations runs strong, and political and social awareness of the struggles of women worldwide are brought out and examined in a hopeful manner. This is a day which some people celebrate by wearing purple ribbons.

==History==
With February Revolution in Petrograd (a previous name for [[St. Petersburg]], [[Russia]]). In the winter of 1917, conditions in the capital, Petrograd, were grim. The layout of the city seemed to emphasise the divisions among its people. The workers' quarters and factories were located on the right bank of the River Neva. On the left bank were the fashionable areas,the Winter Palace, and official buildings, including the palace where the Duma met. In February 1917, food shortages were deeply felt in the worker's quarters. The winter was very cold ñ there had been exceptional frost and heavy snow. Parliamentarians wishing to preserve elected government, were opposed to the Tsarís desire to dissolve the Duma. On 22 February, a lockout took place at a factory on the right bank. The next day, workers in fifty factories called a strike in sympathy. In many factories, women led the way to strikes. This came to be called the International Women's Day.{{Copy edit-inline||date=November 2014}}{{citation needed|date=November 2014}}

The earliest Women’s Day observance was held on February 28, 1909, in New York; it was organized by the [[Socialist Party of America]] in remembrance of the 1908 strike of the [[International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union]].&lt;ref name="unevents"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.un.org/events/women/iwd/2008/history.shtml |title=United Nations page on the background of the IWD |publisher=Un.org |date= |accessdate=2012-03-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; There was no specific strike happening in March 8, despite later sources claiming so.&lt;ref name="mmf1"/&gt;

In August 1910, an International Women's Conference was organized to precede the general meeting of the Socialist [[Second International]] in [[Copenhagen]], [[Denmark]]. Inspired in part by the American socialists, German Socialist [[Luise Zietz]] proposed the establishment of an annual 'International Woman's Day' (singular) and was seconded by fellow socialist and later communist leader [[Clara Zetkin]], although no date was specified at that conference.&lt;ref name = "kaplan"&gt;Temma Kaplan, "On the Socialist Origins of International Women's Day", Feminist Studies, 11/1 (Spring, 1985)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title= History of International Women's Day |url= http://www.un.org/womenwatch/feature/iwd/history.html |publisher= United Nations |accessdate= May 26, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Delegates (100 women from 17 countries) agreed with the idea as a strategy to promote equal rights, including [[suffrage]], for women.&lt;ref name = "iwd"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.internationalwomensday.com/about.asp |title=About International Women's Day |publisher=Internationalwomensday.com |date=March 8, 1918 |accessdate=2013-03-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; The following year, on March 19, 1911, IWD was marked for the first time, by over a million people in Austria, Denmark, Germany and Switzerland.&lt;ref name="unevents"/&gt; In the Austro-Hungarian Empire alone, there were 300 demonstrations.&lt;ref name = "kaplan" /&gt; In Vienna, women paraded on the [[Ringstrasse]] and carried banners honouring the martyrs of the [[Paris Commune]].&lt;ref name = "kaplan" /&gt; Women demanded that women be given the right to vote and to hold public office. They also protested against employment sex discrimination.&lt;ref name = "UN" /&gt; Americans continued to celebrate National Women's Day on the last Sunday in February.&lt;ref name = "kaplan" /&gt;
[[Image:NSW Builders Labourers march on IWD 1975.jpg|thumb|Female members of the Australian [[Builders Labourers Federation]] march on International Women's Day 1975 in Sydney]]

In 1913 [[Russian Empire|Russian]] women observed their first International Women's Day on the last Sunday in February (by [[Julian calendar]] then used in Russia).&lt;ref name="mmf1"/&gt;

Although there were some women-led strikes, marches, and other protests in the years leading up to 1914, none of them happened on March 8.&lt;ref name="mmf1"/&gt; In 1914 International Women's Day was held on March 8, possibly because that day was a Sunday, and now it is always held on March 8 in all countries.&lt;ref name="mmf1"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.mmf2010.info/our-action/le-8-mars-2013-journee-internationale-des-femmes-a-la-recherche-de-la-memoire-perdue |title=8th of March - International woman’s day: in search of the lost memory |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110313064904/http://www.mmf2010.info/our-action/le-8-mars-2013-journee-internationale-des-femmes-a-la-recherche-de-la-memoire-perdue |archivedate=2011-03-13|deadurl=yes |accessdate=2014-03-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 1914 observance of the Day in Germany was dedicated to women's right to vote, which German women did not win until 1918.&lt;ref name="mmf1"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ipu.org/wmn-e/suffrage.htm |title=Women's Suffrage |publisher=Inter-Parliamentary Union |accessdate=2014-01-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In London there was a march from Bow to Trafalgar Square in support of women's suffrage on 8 March 1914.  Sylvia Pankhurst was arrested in front of Charing Cross station on her way to speak in Trafalgar Square.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Suffragist Disorders|url=http://www.thetimes.co.uk/tto/archive/article/1914-03-09/5/1.html#start%3D1785-01-01%26end%3D1985-12-31%26terms%3D%22Sylvia%20Pankhurst%22%20arrested%26back%3D/tto/archive/find/%252522Sylvia+Pankhurst%252522+arrested/w:1785-01-01%7E1985-12-31/o:date/4%26prev%3D/tto/archive/frame/goto/%252522Sylvia+Pankhurst%252522+arrested/w:1785-01-01%7E1985-12-31/o:date/32%26next%3D/tto/archive/frame/goto/%252522Sylvia+Pankhurst%252522+arrested/w:1785-01-01%7E1985-12-31/o:date/34|accessdate=9 May 2014|newspaper=The Times|date=9 March 1914}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1917 demonstrations marking International Women's Day in [[Saint Petersburg]] on the last Sunday in February (which fell on March 8 on the [[Gregorian calendar]]) initiated the [[February Revolution]].&lt;ref name = "UN" /&gt; Women in Saint Petersburg went on strike that day for “Bread and Peace" - demanding the end of World War I, an end to Russian food shortages, and the end of czarism.&lt;ref name="mmf1"/&gt; [[Leon Trotsky]] wrote, "23 February (8th March) was International Woman’s Day and meetings and actions were foreseen. But we did not imagine that this ‘Women’s Day’ would inaugurate the revolution. Revolutionary actions were foreseen but without date. But in morning, despite the orders to the contrary, textile workers left their work in several factories and sent delegates to ask for support of the strike… which led to mass strike... all went out into the streets." &lt;ref name="mmf1"/&gt;

Following the [[October Revolution]], the [[Bolshevik]] [[Alexandra Kollontai]] and [[Vladimir Lenin]] made it an [[Public holiday|official holiday]] in the Soviet Union, and it was established, but was a working day until 1965. On May 8th, 1965 by the decree of the [[USSR]] [[Presidium of the Supreme Soviet]] International Women's Day was declared a non-working day in the USSR "in commemoration of the outstanding merits of Soviet women in communistic construction, in the defense of their Fatherland during the Great Patriotic War, in their heroism and selflessness at the front and in the rear, and also marking the great contribution of women to strengthening friendship between peoples, and the struggle for peace. But still, women's day must be celebrated as are other holidays."

From its official adoption in Russia following the Soviet Revolution in 1917 the holiday was predominantly celebrated in communist and socialist countries. It was celebrated by the communists in China from 1922, and by Spanish communists from 1936.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Nelson|first=Jinty|title=International Women's Day: a centenary to celebrate|url=http://www.historyworkshop.org.uk/international-womens-day-a-centenary-to-celebrate/|publisher=History Workshop Online|accessdate=August 28, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; After the founding of the People's Republic of China on October 1, 1949 the state council proclaimed on December 23 that March 8 would be made an official holiday with women in China given a half-day off.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Anniversaries of important events|url=http://www.gov.cn/english/2005-08/10/content_28291.htm|work=China Factfile|publisher=Chinese Government|accessdate=August 28, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the West, International Women's Day was first observed as a popular event after 1977 when the [[United Nations General Assembly]] invited member states to proclaim March 8 as the [[UN Day]] for [[women's rights]] and [[world peace]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.un.org/womenwatch/feature/iwd/ |title=WomenWatch: International Women's Day |publisher=Un.org |date= |accessdate=2012-03-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 1980s historian [[Renée Coté]] uncovered the origins of the March 8th date for International Women's Day.&lt;ref name="mmf1"/&gt; Her research was published in 1984 in Canada, as, ''La Journée internationale des femmes ou les vrais dates des mystérieuses origines du 8 de mars jusqu'ici embrouillés, truquées, oubliées : la clef des énigmes.'' La vérité historique. Montreal: Les éditions du remue ménage.&lt;ref name="mmf1"/&gt;

==Official UN themes==
{|class="wikitable"
|-
!Year
!UN Theme&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.un.org/womenwatch/feature/iwd/index.html |title=WomenWatch: International Women's Day |publisher=Un.org |date= |accessdate=2013-02-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|1996
|Celebrating the Past, Planning for the Future
|-
|1997
|Women and the Peace Table
|-
|1998
|Women and Human Rights
|-
|1999
|World Free of Violence Against Women
|-
|2000
|Women Uniting for Peace
|-
|2001
|Women and Peace: Women Managing Conflicts
|-
|2002
|Afghan Women Today: Realities and Opportunities
|-
|2003
|Gender Equality and the Millennium Development Goals
|-
|2004
|Women and HIV/AIDS
|-
|2005
|Gender Equality Beyond 2005; Building a More Secure Future
|-
|2006
|Women in Decision-making
|-
|2007
|Ending Impunity for Violence Against Women and Girls
|-
|2008
|Investing in Women and Girls
|-
|2009
|Women and Men United to End Violence Against Women and Girls
|-
|2010
|Equal Rights, Equal Opportunities: Progress for All
|-
|2011
|Equal Access to Education, Training, and Science and Technology: Pathway to Decent Work for Women
|-
|2012
|Empower Rural Women, End Poverty and Hunger
|-
|2013
|A Promise is a Promise: Time for Action to End Violence Against Women
|-
|2014
|Equality for Women is Progress for All
|}

===2010 International Women's Day===
On the occasion of 2010 International Women's Day the [[International Committee of the Red Cross]] (ICRC) drew attention to the hardships displaced women endure. The displacement of populations is one of the gravest consequences of today's armed conflicts. It affects women in a host of ways.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.icrc.org/web/eng/siteeng0.nsf/htmlall/women-displacement-interview-020310 |title=Women and displacement: strength in adversity |publisher=International Committee of the Red Cross |date=March 2, 2010 |accessdate=2012-03-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===2011 International Women's Day===
[[File:Lt Col Pam Moody.jpg|thumb|upright|U.S. Army officer Lt Col Pam Moody with a group of Afghan women on International Women's Day 2011]]

Events took place in more than 100 countries&lt;ref name=RFE100&gt;{{cite web|last=Sindelar|first=Daisy|title=Women's Day Largely Forgotten in West, Where It Got Its Start|url=http://www.rferl.org/content/womens_day_feature_soviet_socialist_origins_100th_anniversary/2330712.html|work=Radio Free Europe|publisher=Radio Free Europe|accessdate=March 8, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; on March 8, 2011 to commemorate the 100th anniversary of International Women's Day.&lt;ref name=DT100&gt;{{cite web|last=Pasha|first=Masroor Afzal|title=To commemorate 100th International Women's Day|url=http://www.dailytimes.com.pk/default.asp?page=2011\03\08\story_8-3-2011_pg12_3|work=Daily Times|publisher=Daily Times|accessdate=March 8, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the United States, President [[Barack Obama]] proclaimed March 2011 to be "Women's History Month", calling Americans to mark IWD by reflecting on "the extraordinary accomplishments of women" in shaping the country's history.&lt;ref name=RFE100 /&gt; Secretary of State [[Hillary Clinton]] launched the "100 Women Initiative: Empowering Women and Girls through International Exchanges", on the eve of IWD.&lt;ref name=VOA100&gt;{{cite web|last=McKellogg|first=JulieAnn|title=Clinton Launches 100th Anniversary of International Women's Day|url=http://www.voanews.com/english/news/Clinton-Launches-100th-Anniversary-of-International-Womens-Day-117556638.html|work=VOA News|publisher=voanews.com|accessdate=March 8, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the run-up to 2011 International Women's Day, the ICRC called on States and other entities not to relent in their efforts to prevent rape and other forms of sexual violence that harm the lives and dignity of countless women in conflict zones around the world every year.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.icrc.org/eng/resources/documents/news-release/2011/women-news-2011-03-07.htm |title=International Women's Day: the fight against sexual violence must not falter |publisher=Icrc.org |date= |accessdate=2012-03-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;
In Pakistan, Punjab Govt. Project Gender Reform Action Plan, District Gujranwala celebrated this day in large scale in the Gift University Gujranwala. Mrs. Shazia Ashfaq Mattu, MPA and GRAP officer Mr. Dr. Yasir Nawaz Manj organized the events in very effective manners.{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}}

Australia issued a 100th anniversary [[Australian commemorative coins#20 cent coin|commemorative coin]].

In Egypt however, the day was a step back for women. In Egypt’s Tahrir Square, hundreds of men came out not in support for women but to harass the women who came out to stand up for their rights as the police and military stood by watching the events unfold in front of them. "The women - some in headscarves and flowing robes, others in jeans - had marched to Cairo's central Tahrir Square to celebrate International Women's Day. But crowds of men soon outnumbered them and chased them out," wrote Hadeel Al-Shalchi for AP.&lt;ref&gt;Hadeel Al-Shalchi, [http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2011/03/08/AR2011030803583.html "Egyptian women's rights protest marred by hecklers"], "The Washington Post", March 8, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

===2012 International Women's Day===
The UN theme for International Women's Day 2012 was Empower Rural Women – End Hunger and Poverty.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.un.org/womenwatch/feature/iwd/2012/ |title=UN WomenWatch: International Women's Day 2012 – UN Observances Worldwide |publisher=Un.org |date= |accessdate=2013-02-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; In that year, [[Oxfam]] America invited people to celebrate inspiring women in their lives by sending a free International Women's Day e-Card or honoring a woman whose efforts had made a difference in the fight against hunger and poverty with Oxfam's International Women's Day award.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://actfast.oxfamamerica.org/index.php/issues/women |title=International Women's Day Celebration |publisher=Actfast.oxfamamerica.org |date= |accessdate=2012-03-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On the occasion of International Women's Day 2012, the [[International Committee of the Red Cross|ICRC]] called for more action to help the mothers and wives of people who have gone missing during armed conflict. The vast majority of people who go missing in connection with conflict are men. As well as the anguish of not knowing what has happened to the missing husband or son, many of these women face economic and practical difficulties. The ICRC underlined the duty of parties to a conflict to search for the missing and provide information to the families.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.icrc.org/eng/resources/documents/news-release/2012/women-day-news-2012.htm Helping women take matters into their own hands] International Committee of the Red Cross&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Google Doodle]] for March 8, 2012 had an International Women's Day theme.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Peacock|first=Louisa|title=Women's Day 2014 celebrated with a Google Doodle|url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/technology/google/google-doodle/10682751/Womens-Day-2014-celebrated-with-a-Google-Doodle.html|accessdate=11 March 2014|newspaper=The Telegraph|date=7 March 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===2013 International Women's Day===
The UN theme for International Women's Day 2013 was "A promise is a promise: Time for action to end violence against women,"&lt;ref name=theme&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.internationalwomensday.com/theme.asp#.Uu5CY_l_uKY |title=UN WomenWatch: International Women's Day 2014 |publisher=Un.org |date= |accessdate=2014-02-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; while International Women's Day 2013 declared the year's theme as The Gender Agenda: Gaining Momentum.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.internationalwomensday.com/theme.asp#.USUK-YKJGE0 |title=INTERNATIONAL WOMEN'S DAY 2013 Theme: The Gender Agenda – Gaining Momentum |publisher=Aurora Ventures |date= |accessdate=2013-02-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The 2013 International Women's Day, the International Committee of the Red Cross (ICRC) draw attention to the plight of women in prison.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.icrc.org/eng/resources/documents/news-release/2013/03-07-women-day-2013.htm |title=The forgotten plight of women behind bars |publisher=ICRC |date= |accessdate=2013-03-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===2014 International Women's Day===
The UN theme for International Women's Day 2014 is "Equality for Women is Progress for All".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.unwomen.org/en/news/in-focus/international-womens-day |title=International Women's Day &amp;#124; UN Women - Headquarters |publisher=UN Women |date= |accessdate=2014-03-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=- 19:00 |url=http://www.unesco-ihe.org/international-womens-day-conference |title=International Women's Day conference |publisher=Unesco-Ihe |date= |accessdate=2014-03-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Google Doodle]] on the eve of IWD 2014 (7 March 2014) featured an {{YouTube|WbF6fHt_ZQE|International Women's day doodle video}}, showing images and videos of women around the world, with music by [[Zap Mama]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Women's Day 2014: Google doodles a music video featuring women from around the world|url=http://ibnlive.in.com/news/womens-day-2014-google-doodles-a-music-video-featuring-women-from-around-the-world/456414-11.html|accessdate=7 March 2014|newspaper=IBN Live|date=7 March 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Google Doodles for 2014|url=http://www.google.com/doodles/finder/2014/All%20doodles|publisher=Google|accessdate=7 March 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

American singer [[Beyoncé Knowles]] also posted an {{YouTube|c-s5Kszj1Wk|International Women's Day}} video to her YouTube account. Throughout the song, her song [[Flawless (Beyoncé song)|***Flawless]] plays, which includes a portion of the "we should all be feminists" speech given by author Chimamanda Ngozi Adichie. Knowles is a modern-day feminist.&lt;ref&gt;[http://time.com/1851/flawless-5-lessons-in-modern-feminism-from-beyonce/ Beyoncé: Lessons in Modern Feminism - TIME&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

===2017 International Women's Day===
[[File:FEMEN Calls for Sex-Boycott.jpg|thumb|Ukrainian group [[Femen]] calling for a [[sex strike]] to protest against sexual exploitation of women.]]

2017 will be the hundredth anniversary of the [[Russian Revolution]], which was sparked on March 8, 1917 by women protesting against bread shortages in St. Petersburg. These events culminated in the abdication of Tsar [[Nicholas II of Russia|Nicholas II]] on March 15. Worldwide celebrations and re-enactments are scheduled to begin on March 8, 2017. Among the organizers is the Ukrainian women's direct action group [[FEMEN]], which aims "to shake women in Ukraine, making them socially active; to organize in 2017 a women's revolution."&lt;ref name="ТаблоID"&gt;{{uk icon}} [http://tabloid.pravda.com.ua/photos/4c9787a7b35d4/ Femen: "Ми даємо чиновникам і політикам, проср...тися"], [[Табло ID]] (September 20, 2010)&lt;/ref&gt;
On this day a [[global women's strike]] including a [[sex strike]] is planned, called by, among others, the [http://www.iusw.org/ International Union of Sex Workers.]{{Citation needed|date=February 2013}}

==In modern culture==
[[File:International Women's Day celebration.png|thumb|left|
{{legend|red|official holiday}}
{{legend|orange|holiday for women}}
{{legend|yellow|non-official holiday}}]]
[[File:Acacia dealbata.jpg|thumb|right|The mimosa (technically, the [[Acacia dealbata|silver wattle]]) is the symbol of the celebrations of Women's day in Italy and Russia]]The day is an official holiday in Afghanistan,&lt;ref name="IWD"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.irinnews.org/report.aspx?reportid=28296 |title=IRIN Asia &amp;#124; AFGHANISTAN: Marking International Women's Day &amp;#124; Afghanistan &amp;#124; Gender Issues |publisher=Irinnews.org |date=March 8, 2005 |accessdate=2012-03-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; Angola, Armenia,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.armeniainfo.am/about/?section=holidays |title=Armenian Holidays – ARMENIA Information |publisher=Armeniainfo.am |date=July 5, 1995 |accessdate=2012-03-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; Azerbaijan,&lt;ref&gt;http://www.azerbaijan.msntour.az/index.php?categoryID=7&lt;/ref&gt; Belarus,&lt;ref&gt;{{ru icon}} [http://www.pravo.by/webnpa/text_txt.asp?RN=P39800157 President's decree on public holidays in Belarus – 1998]&lt;/ref&gt; Burkina Faso,&lt;ref name="capacity4dev"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://capacity4dev.ec.europa.eu/article/taking-international-womens-day-seriously-burkina-faso |title=Taking International Women's Day Seriously in Burkina Faso |author=Coordination Team |date=2011-05-22 |website=capacity4dev.ec.europa.eu |series= |publisher=[[EuropeAid Development and Cooperation|Development and Cooperation – EuropeAid]] |location= |accessdate=2014-03-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; Cambodia,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cambodiaevisa.com/2007/01/05/2007-cambodia-public-holiday/ |title=2007 Cambodia Public Holiday – Cambodia e-Visa Blog |publisher=Cambodiaevisa.com |date=August 4, 2007 |accessdate=2012-03-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; China (for women only),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=|url=http://sg2.mofcom.gov.cn/aarticle/aboutchina/publicholiday/200801/20080105327831.html |title=Public holidays in the People's Republic of China |publisher=Sg2.mofcom.gov.cn |date=January 9, 2008 |accessdate=2013-03-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; Cuba,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cubaminrex.cu/english/Multilaterales/Articulos/SocioHumanitarios/Others/2011/Press%20release.html |title=Ministerio de Relaciones Exteriores de Cuba |publisher=Cubaminrex.cu |date=March 8, 2011 |accessdate=2012-03-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; Georgia,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://embassy.mfa.gov.ge/index.php?lang_id=eng&amp;sec_id=11 |title=დღესასწაულები |publisher=Embassy.mfa.gov.ge |date= |accessdate=2012-03-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; Guinea-Bissau,&lt;ref name="IWD" /&gt; Eritrea,&lt;ref name="IWD" /&gt; Kazakhstan,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://egov.kz/wps/portal/Content?contentPath=%2Fegovcontent%2Femployment_relations%2Farticle%2Fholidays_calend&amp;lang=en|title=Holidays and weekends in the Republic of Kazakhstan in 2014 year|publisher=E.gov.kz |date= |accessdate=2014-03-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; Kyrgyzstan,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Kyrgyz and American Holidays (In Russian)|url=http://russian.bishkek.usembassy.gov/kyrgyz_american_holidays_ru.html|work=U.S. Embassy Bishkek|accessdate=March 7, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Laos,&lt;ref name="laoyp"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://laoyp.com/laopdr/events/ |title=Lao Cultural Events / Public Holidays |accessdate=2014-03-07 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080829170031/http://www.laoyp.com/laopdr/events/ |archivedate=2008-08-29 |deadurl=yes |work=laoyp.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; Macedonia (for women only), Madagascar (for women only),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.qppstudio.net/publicholidays2009/madagascar.htm |title=Madagascar 2009 Public Holidays |publisher=Qppstudio.net |date= |accessdate=2012-03-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; Moldova,&lt;ref&gt;{{ro icon}} [http://old.parlament.md/download/laws/ro/154-XV-28.03.2003.doc Article 111 (1c) of the work codex of Moldova], [http://myfiles.md/d/20495/aa/154-XV-28.03.2003.pdf PDF, page 53] "Article 111. Non-working holidays. (1) in Moldova, non-working holidays, maintaining the average salary, are: (...) c) March 8 – International Women's Day; (...)".&lt;/ref&gt; Mongolia,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mongolia-web.com/content/view/33/39/ |title=Mongolia Web News |publisher=Mongolia-web.com |date= |accessdate=2012-03-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nepal (for women only),&lt;ref name="IWD" /&gt; Russia,&lt;ref name="IWD" /&gt; Tajikistan,&lt;ref name="IWD" /&gt; Turkmenistan,&lt;ref name="IWD" /&gt; Uganda,&lt;ref name="IWD" /&gt; Ukraine,&lt;ref name="IWD" /&gt; Uzbekistan,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=National Holidays (In Russian)|url=http://mfa.uz/rus/ob_uzbekistane/naselenie_i_naionalnie_prazdniki/|work=Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Uzbekistan|accessdate=March 7, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Vietnam,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://en.www.info.vn/society/traffic/20965-hanoi-streets-jammed-on-intl-day-for-women-.html |title=Hanoi streets jammed on Int’l Day for Women &amp;#124; Vietnam News &amp; Information Portal |publisher=En.www.info.vn |date=March 9, 2011 |accessdate=2012-03-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Zambia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.qppstudio.net/publicholidays2009/zambia.htm |title=Zambia 2009 Public Holidays |publisher=Qppstudio.net |date= |accessdate=2012-03-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In some countries, such as Cameroon,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.qppstudio.net/publicholidays2009/cameroon.htm |title=QPPstudio.net |publisher=QPPstudio.net |date= |accessdate=2012-03-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; Croatia,&lt;ref&gt;{{hr icon}} [http://narodne-novine.nn.hr/clanci/sluzbeni/309949.html Zakon o blagdanima, spomendanima i neradnim danima u Republici Hrvatskoj]&lt;/ref&gt; Romania,&lt;ref name="agentia.org"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.agentia.org/monden/ziua-interna-ional-a-femeii-de-8-martie-google-posteaza-un-desen-pentru-acest-eveniment-8533.html |title=Ziua Internațională a Femeii. De 8 martie Google posteaza un desen pentru acest eveniment |publisher=Agentia.org |date=November 24, 2010 |accessdate=2012-03-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; Montenegro, {{Citation needed|date=March 2009}} Bosnia and Herzegovina,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.oslobodjenje.ba/vijesti/bih/zene-su-heroji-ovoga-drustva |title=Žene su heroji ovog društva (in Bosnian) |publisher=Oslobodjenje |date=March 8, 2012 |accessdate=March 8, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Serbia,{{Citation needed|date=March 2009}} Bulgaria{{Citation needed|date=February 2009}} and Chile,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.feriadoschilenos.cl/DiasNacionales.html#DiaNacionalDeLaMujer |title=Días Nacionales en Chile (in Spanish) |publisher=feriadoschilenos.cl |date= |accessdate=2012-03-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; the day is not a public holiday, but is widely observed nonetheless.
On this day it is customary for men to give the women in their lives – friends, mothers, wives, girlfriends, daughters, colleagues, etc. – flowers and small gifts. In some countries (such as Bulgaria and Romania) it is also observed as an equivalent of Mother's Day, where children also give small presents to their mothers and grandmothers.&lt;ref name="agentia.org"/&gt;

{{multiple image
   | direction = horizontal
   | width     = 180
   | footer    =
   | image1    = 8marta.jpg
   | alt1      = International Women's Day poster
   | caption1  = The 1932 Soviet poster dedicated to March 8 holiday. The text reads: "8th of March is the day of rebellion of the working women against kitchen slavery" and "Down with the oppression and narrow-mindedness of household work!". Originally in the USSR the holiday had a clear political character, emphasizing the role of the Soviet state in ''the liberation of women'' from their second-class-citizen status.
   | image2    = 8march landysh.jpg
   | alt2      = International Women's Day poster
   | caption2 = However, with time the meaning of the holiday evolved to an apolitical celebration of women. Most late Soviet March 8 postcards carried no political meaning.
  }}

In Armenia, after the collapse of the Soviet Union celebrations of IWD were abandoned. Instead, April 7 was introduced as state holiday of 'Beauty and Motherhood'. The new holiday immediately became popular among [[Armenians]], as it commemorates one of the main holidays of the [[Armenian Apostolic Church|Armenian Church]], the [[Annunciation]]. However, people still kept celebrating IWD on March 8 as well. Public discussion held on the topic of two ‘Women's Days’ in Armenia resulted in the recognition of the so-called ‘Women's Month’ which is the period between March 8 and April 7.

In Italy, to celebrate the day, men give [[Acacia dealbata|yellow mimosas]] to women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.repubblica.it/online/societa/otto/otto/otto.html |title=la Repubblica/societa: 8 marzo, niente manifestazione tante feste diverse per le donne |publisher=Repubblica.it |date= |accessdate=2012-03-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.repubblica.it/2006/c/sezioni/politica/versoelezioni34/ciampidonne/ciampidonne.html |title=politica » Festa della donna, parla Ciampi "La parità è ancora lontana" |publisher=Repubblica.it |date=March 8, 2006 |accessdate=2012-03-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Teresa Mattei]] chose the mimosa as the symbol of IWD in Italy because she felt that the French symbols of the day, [[Violet (plant)|violet]]s and [[lily-of-the-valley]], were too scarce and expensive to be used effectively in Italy.&lt;ref name=florentine&gt;{{cite news|first=Dierdre|last=Pirro|title=Teresa Mattei, Flower power |url=http://www.theflorentine.net/articles/article-view.asp?issuetocId=5425 |work=[[The Florentine]] |publisher= |date=March 25, 2013 |accessdate=2013-04-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; Yellow mimosas and chocolate are also one of the most common March 8 presents in Russia and Albania.

In many countries, such as in Armenia, Belarus, Bosnia and Herzegovina, Brazil, Bulgaria, Croatia, Colombia, Estonia, Hungary, Kazakhstan, Kyrgyzstan, Latvia, Lithuania, Poland, Macedonia, Moldova, Montenegro, Romania, Russia, Serbia, Slovakia, Slovenia and Ukraine the custom of giving women flowers still prevails [within these regions only]. Women also sometimes get gifts from their employers. Schoolchildren often bring gifts for their female teachers, too.

In countries like Portugal groups of women usually celebrate on the night of March 8 in "women-only" dinners and parties.{{Citation needed|date=March 2009}}

In Pakistan working women in formal and informal sectors celebrate International Women's Day every year to commemorate their ongoing struggle for due rights, despite facing many cultural and religious restrictions. Some women working for change in society use IWM to help the movement for women's rights. In Poland, for instance, every IWD includes large feminist demonstrations in major cities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ippf.org/en/News/Intl+news/March+8+in+Poland+Still+Marching+Together+for+Freedom+and+Equality.htm |title=March 8 in Poland: Still Marching Together for Freedom and Equality |publisher=Ippf.org |date= |accessdate=2012-03-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1975, which was designated as International Women's Year, the United Nations gave official sanction to, and began sponsoring, International Women's Day.

As for efforts to achieve official recognition in the [[United States of America]], actress and human rights activist [[Beata Pozniak]] worked with the Mayor of Los Angeles and the Governor of California to lobby members of the U.S. Congress to propose official recognition of the holiday. In February, 1994, H.J. Res. 316 was introduced by Rep. [[Maxine Waters]], along with 79 cosponsors, in an attempt to officially recognize March 8 of that year as International Women's Day. The bill was subsequently referred to, and remained in, the House Committee on Post Office and Civil Service. No vote of either house of Congress was achieved on this piece of legislation.&lt;ref name="billsummary"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://thomas.loc.gov/cgi-bin/bdquery/z?d103:h.j.res.00316: |title=Bill Summary &amp; Status 103rd Congress (1993 - 1994) H.J.RES.316 |publisher=Library of Congress |date= |accessdate=2012-03-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The 2005 Congress (conference) of the British [[Trades Union Congress]] overwhelmingly approved a resolution calling for IWD to be designated a public holiday in the United Kingdom.

Since 2005, IWD has been celebrated in [[Montevideo]], either on the principal street, 18 de Julio, or alternatively through one of its neighbourhoods. The event has attracted much publicity due to a group of female drummers, [http://www.lamelaza.com/ La Melaza], who have performed each year.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.uruguaynow.com/la_melaza_candombe.php |title=Travel Guide to Uruguay – Uruguay gets a female beat |publisher=UruguayNow |date= |accessdate=2012-03-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Today, many events are held by women's groups around the world. The UK-based marketing company [[Aurora (organization)|Aurora]] hosts a free worldwide register of IWD local events&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.internationalwomensday.com |title=International Women's Day 2013 |publisher=Internationalwomensday.com |date= |accessdate=2013-03-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; so that women and the media can learn about local activity. Many governments and organizations around the world support IWD.

70% of those living in poverty are women and Oxfam GB encourages women to Get Together&lt;ref name="oxfam1"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.oxfam.org.uk/womensday |title=www.oxfam.org.uk/womensday |publisher=Oxfam.org.uk |date= |accessdate=2012-03-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; on International Women's Day and fundraise to support Oxfam projects, which change the lives of women around the world. Thousands of people hold events for Oxfam on International Women's Day, join the celebration by visiting the website and registering their events.&lt;ref name="oxfam1"/&gt;

In Taiwan, International Women's Day is marked by the annual release of a government survey on women's waist sizes, accompanied by warnings that weight gain can pose a hazard to women's health.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.taipeitimes.com/News/taiwan/archives/2013/03/09/2003556662 |title=Women's waistlines increasing: bureau |publisher=Taipei Times |date=March 9, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Controversies==
In some cases International Women's Day has led to questionable practices that discriminated against men. For example [[Tower Hamlets Council]] closed off one of its libraries to all males to "celebrate" the occasion, forcing them to travel elsewhere, going as far as even banning male staff from the premises.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Phil Carradice |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/blogs/wales/posts/international_womens_day_global_centenary |title=International Women's Day, BBC blog |publisher=Bbc.co.uk |date=March 7, 2011 |accessdate=2013-03-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Communist regime in Czechoslovakia|Communist Czechoslovakia]], huge Soviet-style celebrations were held annually. After the fall of Communism, the holiday, generally considered to be one of the major symbols of the old regime, fell into obscurity. International Women's Day was re-established as an official "important day" by the [[Parliament of the Czech Republic]] only recently,{{When|date=January 2012}} on the proposal of the [[Czech Social Democratic Party|Social Democrats]] and [[Communist Party of Bohemia and Moravia|Communists]]. This has provoked some controversy as a large part of the public as well as the political right see the holiday as a relic of the nation's Communist past.{{citation needed|date=February 2014}} In 2008, the Christian conservative [[Christian and Democratic Union – Czechoslovak People's Party|Czechoslovak People's Party]]'s deputies unsuccessfully proposed the abolition of the holiday. However, some non-government organizations consider the official recognition of International Women's Day as an important reminder of women's role in the society.

International Women's Day sparked violence in [[Tehran]], Iran on March 4, 2007, when police beat hundreds of men and women who were planning a rally. Police arrested dozens of women and some were released after several days of solitary confinement and interrogation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Harrison |first=Frances |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/6426087.stm |title=Middle East &amp;#124; Iranian women struggle for equality |publisher=BBC News |date=March 8, 2007 |accessdate=2012-03-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Shadi Sadr]], [[Mahbubeh Abbasgholizadeh]] and several more community activists were released on March 19, 2007, ending a fifteen day hunger strike.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://hrw.org/english/docs/2007/03/07/iran15452.htm |title=Iran: Release Women's Rights Advocates &amp;#124; Human Rights Watch |publisher=Hrw.org |date=March 8, 2007 |accessdate=2012-03-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Apocrypha==
A popular [[apocrypha]]l story which surfaced in French Communist circles&lt;ref name="emancipatie.nl"&gt;Temma Kaplan, On the Socialist Origins of International Women's Day, in: Feminist Studies, 11, 1985, S. 163–171. ([http://www.emancipatie.nl/_documenten/vvnl/doc/2006/KaplanSocialistOrigins.pdf PDF])&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Françoise Picq 1982"&gt;Liliane Kandel / Françoise Picq, [http://www.archivesdufeminisme.fr/article.php3?id_article=80|"Le Mythe des origines à propos de la journée internationale des femmes"], in: La Revue d'en face, 12, 1982, S. 67–80.&lt;/ref&gt; claimed that women from clothing and textile factories had staged a protest on March 8, 1857 in New York City.&lt;ref&gt;Angela Howard Zophy, Handbook of American women's history, Garland, 1991, 187.&lt;/ref&gt; The story alleged that garment workers were protesting against very poor working conditions and low wages and were attacked and dispersed by police. It was claimed that this event led to a rally in commemoration of its 50th anniversary in 1907. Temma Kaplan&lt;ref name="emancipatie.nl"/&gt; explains that "neither event seems to have taken place, but many Europeans think March 8, 1907, inaugurated International Women's Day."&lt;ref name="emancipatie.nl"/&gt; Speculating about the origins of this 1857 legend, Liliane Kandel and Françoise Picq suggested it was likely that (in recent times) some felt it opportune to detach International Women's Day from its basis in Soviet history and ascribe to it a more "international" origin which could be painted as more ancient than Bolshevism and more spontaneous than a decision of Congress or the initiative of those women affiliated to the Party.&lt;ref name="Françoise Picq 1982"/&gt;

==Gallery==
&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Afghan girls in traditional clothes.jpg|Afghanistan, 2002 ceremony at the Ministry of Women's Affairs, which [[USAID]] helped rehabilitate.
File:Cameroon international womens day.jpg|Cloth commemorating International Women's Day, Cameroon, 2006.
File:Intl womens day colombia.jpg|Bogotà, Colombia, 2009.
File:Intl womens day warsaw march.jpg|Warsaw, Poland, 2010.
File:Flickr - NewsPhoto! - Demonstratie 100 jaar Internationale Vrouwendag.jpg|Amsterdam, Netherlands, 2010.
File:Intl womens day sydney.jpg|Sydney, Australia, 2011.
File:Intl womens day march maldives.jpg|Maldives, 2012.
File:Massai women rally.jpg|Arusha, Tanzania, 2012.
File:Drummers protest intl womens day brazil.jpg|Brazil, 2013.
&lt;!-- File:Intl womens day afghanistan.jpg|Dai Kundi Province, Afghanistan, 2010. --&gt;
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==See also==
{{portal|Feminism|Socialism|Soviet Union|Holidays}}
* [[Communist Women's International]]
* [[International Day for the Elimination of Violence against Women]]
* [[International Men's Day]]
* [[List of uprisings led by women]]
* [[Susan B. Anthony Day]]
* [[UN Women]]
{{-}}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==
{{Sister project links | wikt=no | commons= International Women's Day| b=Category:International Women's Day | n=Category:International Women's Day | q=International Women's Day | s= Portal:International Women's Day| v=International Women's Day | voy=no | species=no | d=Q38964| mw=no| display=International Women's Day}}
{{external links|date=May 2014}}
* [http://www.icrc.org/eng/women Women and war – International Committee of the Red Cross]
* [http://www.freepeoplesmovement.org/fpm/page.php?277 Article from international communist organization on International Women's Day]
* [http://www.internationalwomensday.com/ Internationalwomensday.com]
* [http://www.redcross.org.uk/news.asp?id=91320 Sewing a better future on International Women’s Day]
* [http://www.historyworkshop.org.uk/international-womens-day-a-centenary-to-celebrate/ On IWD's centenary, historian Jinty Nelson looks at its genesis and achievements – and the ground still to cover]


{{Russia Holidays}}
{{Ukraine Holidays}}

[[Category:Civil awareness days]]
[[Category:Feminism]]
[[Category:Public holidays in Russia]]
[[Category:Public holidays in the Soviet Union]]
[[Category:International observances]]
[[Category:March observances]]
[[Category:Recurring events established in 1909]]
[[Category:United Nations days|Women's Day, International]]
[[Category:Women]]
[[Category:United Nations observances]]
[[Category:Public holidays in Ukraine]]
[[Category:Women's events]]
[[Category:Women in history]]
[[Category:Fixed holidays]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>