<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20081014195445|245287358" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="280746" pageid="280746" ns="0" title="International Women&#039;s Day"><revisions><rev timestamp="2008-10-15T13:58:05Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''International Women's Day''' ('''IWD''') is marked on '''[[March 8]]''' every year. It is a major day of global celebration for the economic, political and social achievements of women. 

Started as a political event, the holiday blended in the culture of many countries (primarily [[Russia]] and the countries of former Soviet bloc). In some celebrations, the day lost its political flavour, and became simply an occasion for men to express their love to the women around them in a way somewhat similar to [[Mother's Day]] and [[St Valentine's Day]] mixed together. In others, however, the political and human rights theme as designated by the [[United Nations]] runs strong, and political and social awareness of the struggles of women worldwide are brought out and examined in a hopeful manner.

The IWD is also celebrated as the first spring holiday, as in the listed countries the first day of March is considered the first day of the spring season.

==History==
[[Image:8marchrallydhaka (55).JPG|thumb|March 8 rally in [[Dhaka]], [[Bangladesh]]]]
[[Image:NSW Builders Labourers march on IWD 1975.jpg|thumb|Female members of the Australian [[Builders Labourers Federation]] march on International Women's Day 1975 in Sydney]]
The first IWD was observed on [[28 February]] [[1909]] in the United States following a declaration by the [[Socialist Party of America]]. Among other relevant historic events, it came to commemorate the 1911 [[Triangle Shirtwaist Factory fire]]. The idea of having an international women's day was first put forward at the turn of the 20th century amid rapid world [[industrialization]] and economic expansion that led to protests over working conditions. By [[urban legend]],&lt;ref&gt;Temma Kaplan, On the Socialist Origins of International Women's Day, in: Feminist Studies, 11, 1985, S. 163-171. ([http://www.emancipatie.nl/_documenten/vvnl/doc/2006/KaplanSocialistOrigins.pdf PDF])&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Liliane Kandel / Françoise Picq, Le Mythe des origines à propos de la journée internationale des femmes, in: La Revue d'en face, 12, 1982, S. 67-80.&lt;/ref&gt; women from [[clothing]] and [[textile]] factories staged one such protest on [[8 March]] [[1857]] in [[New York, New York|New York City]].&lt;ref&gt;Angela Howard Zophy, Handbook of American women's history, Garland, 1990, 187.&lt;/ref&gt; The garment workers were protesting against very poor working conditions and low wages. The protesters were attacked and dispersed by [[police]]. These women established their first [[labor union]] in the same month two years later.

More protests followed on 8 March in subsequent years, most notably in 1908 when 15,000 women marched through New York City demanding shorter hours, better pay and voting rights{{Fact|date=March 2007}}. In 1910 the first international women's conference was held in [[Copenhagen]] (in the labour-movement building located at Jagtvej 69, which until recently housed [[Ungdomshuset]]) by the [[Second International]] and an 'International Women's Day' was established, which was submitted by the important German Socialist [[Clara Zetkin]], although no date was specified.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.un.org/events/women/iwd/2008/history.shtml Unites Nations page on the background of the IWD]&lt;/ref&gt; The following year, IWD was marked by over a million people in [[Austria]], [[Denmark]], [[Germany]] and [[Switzerland]]. However, soon thereafter, the Triangle Shirtwaist Factory fire in New York City killed over 140 garment workers. A lack of safety measures was blamed for the high death toll. Furthermore, on the eve of [[World War I]], women across [[Europe]] held peace rallies on [[8 March]] [[1913]]. In the West, International Women's Day was commemorated during the 1910s and 1920s, but dwindled. It was revived by the rise of [[feminism]] in the 1960s.

Demonstrations marking International Women's Day in [[Russia]] proved to be the first stage of the [[Russian Revolution of 1917]].

Following the [[October Revolution]], the [[Bolshevik]] feminist [[Alexandra Kollontai]] persuaded [[Lenin]] to make it an [[holiday|official holiday]] in Russia, and it was established, but was a working day until 1965. On [[May 8]], [[1965]] by the decree of the USSR [[Presidium of the Supreme Soviet]] International Women's Day was declared as a non working day in the [[USSR]] "in commemoration of outstanding merits of the Soviet women in communistic construction, in the defense of their Motherland during the [[Great Patriotic War]], their heroism and selflessness at the front and in rear, and also marking the big contribution of women to strengthening friendship between peoples and struggle for the peace."

== Women's Day in modern culture ==
[[Image:8marta.jpg|thumb|250px|The 1932 Soviet poster dedicated to the 8th of March holiday. The text reads: "8th of March is the day of the rebellion of the working women against the kitchen slavery" and "Down with the oppression and narrow-mindedness of the household work!". Originally in the USSR the holiday had a clear political character, emphasizing the role of the Soviet state in ''liberation of women'' from the second-class citizens' position...]]
[[Image:8march landysh.jpg|thumb|250px|However, with time the meaning of the Holiday evolved to an apolitical celebration of women with an emphasis on their beauty and motherhood. Most late Soviet 8th of March postcards carried no political meaning.]]
The day is an official holiday in [[Albania]], [[Algeria]], [[Armenia]], [[Azerbaijan]], [[Belarus]], [[Bosnia and Herzegovina]], [[Brazil]], [[Burkina Faso]], [[Cameroon]], [[China]], [[Cuba]], [[Italy]], [[Laos]], [[Kazakhstan]], [[Kyrgyzstan]], [[Republic of Macedonia|Macedonia]], [[Moldova]], [[Mongolia]], [[Montenegro]], [[Poland]], [[Romania]], Russia, [[Serbia]], [[Tajikistan]], [[Ukraine]], [[Uzbekistan]], [[Vietnam]], and [[Zambia]], and is observed by men giving the women in their lives - mothers, wives, girlfriends, colleagues, etc., flowers and small gifts. In some countries (such as Romania) it is also observed as an equivalent of Mother's Day, where children also give small presents to their mothers and grandmothers.  

After the collapse of the Soviet Union celebrations of IWD were abandoned in Armenia. Instead [[April 7]] was introduced as state holiday of ‘Beauty and Motherhood.’ The new holiday immediately got popular among [[Armenians]], as it commemorates one of the main holidays of [[Armenian Apostolic Church|Armenian Church]], [[Annunciation]]. However, people still kept celebrating IWD on March 8 as well. Public discussion held on the topic of two ‘Women’s Days’ in Armenia resulted in the recognition of the so called ‘Women’s Month’ which is the period between March 8 and April 7.       

In Italy, to celebrate the day, men give [[Acacia dealbata|yellow mimosas]] to women.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.repubblica.it/online/societa/otto/otto/otto.html la Repubblica/societa: 8 marzo, niente manifestazione tante feste diverse per le donne&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.repubblica.it/2006/c/sezioni/politica/versoelezioni34/ciampidonne/ciampidonne.html Repubblica.it » politica » Festa della donna, parla Ciampi "La parità è ancora lontana"&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Yellow mimosas and chocolate are also one of the most common March 8 presents in Russia.

In Bosnia and Herzegovina, Brazil, [[Croatia]], [[Hungary]], Romania, Moldova, Macedonia, Montenegro, Poland, [[Bulgaria]], [[Slovenia]] and Serbia the custom of giving women flowers still prevails. Women sometimes get gifts from their employers too.  School children often bring gifts for their teachers as well.

In countries like [[Portugal]] and Romania, it is usual, at the night of 8 March, groups of women celebrate in "women-only" dinners and parties.

In [[India]], IWD holds a lot of significance. Many celebrations are held during the day. This portrays the power of women in the modern era and how vital their role is in the society.{{Fact|date=March 2007}}
 
In 1975, which had been designated as [[International Women’s Year]], the United Nations gave official sanction to and began sponsoring International Women's Day.
 
The 2005 Congress (conference) of the British [[Trades Union Congress]] overwhelmingly approved a resolution calling for IWD to be designated a public holiday in the [[United Kingdom]].

International Women's Day encountered violence in [[Tehran]], [[Iran]] on March 4, 2007, when police beat hundreds of men and women who were planning a rally.  Police arrested dozens of women and some were released after several days of solitary confinement and interrogation.&lt;ref&gt;http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/6426087.stm&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Shadi Sadr]] and Mahbubeh Abbasgholizadeh, and several more community activists, were released on March 19th 2007, ending a fifteen day hunger strike.&lt;ref&gt;http://hrw.org/english/docs/2007/03/07/iran15452.htm&lt;/ref&gt; 
 
Today many events are held by women's groups around the world.(some that even close off libraries to men) The global women's organization [[Aurora (organization)|Aurora]] hosts a free worldwide register of IWD local events ([http://www.internationalwomensday.com www.internationalwomensday.com]) so that women and the media can locate local activity. Many governments and organisations around the world support IWD. For example, [[HSBC]] hosts a range of IWD activity including co-hosting of the United Kingdom's flagship IWD event with women's group Aurora. Global interest in IWD shows a steady increase.

==See also==
*[[International Men's Day]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://imaginingourselves.imow.org/ International Museum of Women]
* [http://www.freepeoplesmovement.org/fpm/page.php?277 Article from international communist organization on International Women's Day]
* [http://www.un.org/events/women/iwd/2007/ International Women's Day 2007 - United Nations web site]
* [http://www.internationalwomensday.com/ www.internationalwomensday.com]
* [http://www0.un.org/cyberschoolbus/womensday/index.asp More detailed overview]

[[Category:Civil awareness days]]
[[Category:Feminism]]
[[Category:History of socialism]]
[[Category:Holidays in Russia]]
[[Category:Holidays in the Soviet Union]]
[[Category:International observances]]
[[Category:March observances]]
[[Category:United Nations days|Women's Day, International]]
[[Category:Women]]

{{Link FA|ka}}
[[ar:اليوم العالمي للمرأة]]
[[bs:Međunarodni dan žena]]
[[bg:Международен ден на жената]]
[[ca:Dia de la Dona Treballadora]]
[[cv:Пĕтĕм тĕнчери хĕрарăмсен кунĕ]]
[[cs:Mezinárodní den žen]]
[[da:Kvindernes internationale kampdag]]
[[de:Internationaler Frauentag]]
[[et:Rahvusvaheline naistepäev]]
[[es:Día Internacional de la Mujer]]
[[eo:Internacia tago de virinoj]]
[[eu:Emakume Langilearen Nazioarteko Eguna]]
[[fa:روز جهانی زن]]
[[fr:Journée internationale de la femme]]
[[gl:Día da Muller Traballadora]]
[[ko:세계 여성의 날]]
[[hr:Međunarodni dan žena]]
[[id:Hari Perempuan Internasional]]
[[is:Alþjóðlegur baráttudagur kvenna]]
[[it:Giornata Internazionale della Donna]]
[[he:יום האישה הבינלאומי]]
[[ka:ქალთა საერთაშორისო დღე]]
[[kk:Халықаралық әйелдер күні]]
[[ku:Roja Jinên Cîhanê]]
[[lv:Starptautiskā sieviešu diena]]
[[lt:Tarptautinė moters diena]]
[[hu:Nemzetközi nőnap]]
[[mk:Меѓународен ден на жената]]
[[nl:Internationale Vrouwendag]]
[[ja:国際女性デー]]
[[no:Den internasjonale kvinnedagen]]
[[nn:Den internasjonale kvinnedagen]]
[[uz:Xalqaro xotin-qizlar kuni]]
[[pl:Dzień Kobiet]]
[[pt:Dia Internacional da Mulher]]
[[ro:Ziua internaţională a femeii]]
[[ru:Международный женский день]]
[[sq:Dita Ndërkombëtare e Gruas]]
[[scn:Jurnata Ntirnazziunali dâ Fìmmina]]
[[simple:International Women's Day]]
[[sk:Medzinárodný deň žien]]
[[sl:Dan žena]]
[[sr:Међународни дан жена]]
[[sh:Međunarodni dan žena]]
[[fi:Kansainvälinen naistenpäivä]]
[[sv:Internationella kvinnodagen]]
[[ta:அனைத்துலக பெண்கள் நாள்]]
[[te:అంతర్జాతీయ మహిళా దినోత్సవం]]
[[th:วันสตรีสากล]]
[[vi:Ngày Quốc tế Phụ nữ]]
[[tg:Рӯзи байналхалқии занон]]
[[tr:8 Mart Dünya Kadınlar Günü]]
[[uk:Міжнародний жіночий день]]
[[zh:国际妇女节]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>