<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061015194347|81648720" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="280746" pageid="280746" ns="0" title="International Women&#039;s Day"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-10-16T20:04:26Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[Image:iwd2006_global.gif|thumb|right|International Women's Day 2006 logo.]]

'''International Women's Day''' ('''IWD''') is marked on [[8 March]] every year. It is a major day of global celebration for the economic, political and social achievements of women. 

Started as a political event, the holiday blended in the culture of many countries (primarily [[Russia]] and the countries of former Soviet bloc).  In some celebrations, the day lost its political flavour, and became simply an occasion for men to express their sympathy and love to the women around them - somewhat similar to Western [[Mother's Day]] and [[St Valentine's Day]] mixed together. In others, however, the political and human rights theme as designated by the United Nations runs strong, and political and social awareness of the struggles of women worldwide are brought out and examined in a hopeful manner.

The IWD is also celebrated as the first spring holiday, as in the listed countries the first day of March is considered the first day of the spring season.

=== History ===

The first IWD was observed on [[28 February]] [[1909]] in the United States following a declaration by the [[Socialist Party of America]]. Among other relevant historic events, it commemorates the [[Triangle Shirtwaist Factory fire]] ([[New York]], [[1911]]), where over 140 women lost their lives. The idea of having an international women's day was first put forward at the turn of the [[20th century]] amid rapid world [[industrialization]] and economic expansion that led to protests over working conditions. Women from [[clothing]] and [[textile]] factories staged one such protest on [[8 March]] [[1857]] in [[New York, New York|New York City]]. The garment workers were protesting what they saw as very poor working conditions and low wages. The protesters were attacked and dispersed by [[police]]. These women established their first [[labor union]] in the same month two years later.
 
More protests followed on 8 March in subsequent years, most notably in [[1908]] when 15,000 women marched through New York City demanding shorter hours, better pay and voting rights. In [[1910]] the first international women's conference was held in [[Copenhagen]] by the [[Socialist International]] and an 'International Women's Day' was established, which was submitted by the important German Socialist [[Clara Zetkin]]. The following year, IWD was marked by over a million people in [[Austria]], [[Denmark]], [[Germany]] and [[Switzerland]]. However, soon thereafter, the [[Triangle Shirtwaist Factory fire]] in [[New York City]] killed over 140 garment workers. A lack of safety measures was blamed for the high death toll. Furthermore, on the eve of [[World War I]], women across [[Europe]] held peace rallies on [[8 March]] [[1913]]. In the West, International Women's Day was commemorated during the [[1910s]] and [[1920s]], but dwindled. It was revived by the rise of [[feminism]] in the [[1960s]]. 
 
Demonstrations marking International Women's Day in [[Russia]] proved to be the first stage of the [[Russian Revolution of 1917]]. Following the [[October Revolution]], the [[Bolshevik]] feminist [[Alexandra Kollontai]] persuaded [[Lenin]] to make it an [[holiday|official holiday]], and it was established, but was a working day until 1965. On [[May 8]] [[1965]] by the decree of the USSR [[Presidium of the Supreme Soviet]] International Women's Day was declared as a non working day in the [[USSR]] "in commemoration of outstanding merits of the Soviet women in communistic construction, in the defense of their Motherland during the [[Great Patriotic War]], their heroism and selflessness at the front and in rear, and also marking the big contribution of women to strengthening friendship between peoples and struggle for the peace".

When [[Czechoslovakia]] was part of the Soviet Block this celebration was supported officially and gradually turned into parody. During the rule of the [[Communist Party of Czechoslovakia]] in [[Czechoslovakia]] (1948–1989) the International Women's Day (in [[Czech language|Czech]]: ''Mezinárodní den žen'', in [[Slovak language|Slovak]]: ''Medzinárodný deň žien'', abbreviated as MDŽ) was used as a tool of the party [[propaganda]], which hoped to convince women that the party cared about them and considered their needs in formulating social policy. During the last decades of the regime, this event morphed into a parody of itself. On every March 8th almost every woman got a flower and a small gift (typically soap or a towel) from her employer. Many men took this day as a convenient opportunity to spend the day drinking in the local pub. As a result, the original aim of expressing respect and sympathy to women was completely lost. The party's ritualistic celebration of Women's Day became so stereotypical that it was even ridiculed in movies and on television in Czechoslovakia.

=== Women's Day in modern culture ===
[[Image:8marchrallydhaka (55).JPG|thumb|March 8 rally in [[Dhaka]], [[Bangladesh]]]]
The day remains an official holiday in [[Armenia]], [[Russia]], [[Azerbaijan]], [[Belarus]], [[Bulgaria]], [[Kazakhstan]], [[Kyrgyzstan]], [[Republic of Macedonia|Macedonia]], [[Moldova]], [[Mongolia]], [[Tajikistan]], [[Ukraine]], Uzbekistan and [[Vietnam]], and is observed by men giving the women in their lives - mothers, wives, girlfriends, colleagues, etc., flowers and small gifts. In some countries it is also observed as an equivalent of Mother's Day, where children also give small presents to their mothers and grandmothers.  

After the [[Velvet Revolution|fall of socialism]] in Czechoslovakia (1989) MDŽ was quickly abandoned as one of the most mocked symbols of the old regime. The few attempts to reestablish the celebration have been met with sarcasm. The slightly more popular attempt to establish [[Mother's Day]] as a replacement has largely failed as well.

In [[Hungary]], [[Poland]] and [[Romania]], Women's Day was used as a propaganda tool too, but nevertheless the custom of giving women flowers still prevails. Women usually get gifts from their employers too.

In [[India]], IWD holds a lot of significance. One can see a lot of celebrations going on on this day. This portrays the power of women in the modern era and how vital their role is in the society. 
 
In [[1975]], which had been designated as [[International Women’s Year]], the [[United Nations]] gave official sanction to and began sponsoring International Women's Day.
 
The 2005 Congress (conference) of the British [[Trades Union Congress]] overwhelmingly approved a resolution calling for IWD to be designated a public holiday in the United Kingdom.
 
Today many events are held by women's groups around the world. The global women's organization [[Aurora (organization)|Aurora]] hosts a free worldwide register of IWD local events ([http://www.internationalwomensday.com www.internationalwomensday.com]) so that women and the media can locate local activity. Many governments and organisatons around the world support IWD. For example, [[HSBC]] hosts a range of IWD activity including co-hosting of the [[United Kingdom|UK]]'s flagship IWD event with women's group Aurora. Global interest in IWD shows a steady increase.

==See also==
*[[Feminism]]
*[[Women's rights]]
*[[Marxist feminism]]
*[[Socialist feminism]]
*[[Marxism]]
* [[National Women's Day]] in [[South Africa]] on [[August 9]]

==External links==
* [http://www.un.org/events/women/iwd/2006/ International Women's Day 2006 - United Nations web site]
* [http://us.oneworld.net/section/us/perspectives/7/women OneWorld.net's Perspectives Magazine: Women in the Lead (February/March 2006)]
*[http://www.internationalwomensday.com www.internationalwomensday.com]
*[http://www.un.org/ecosocdev/geninfo/women/womday97.htm Early history of the day: short overview]
*[http://www0.un.org/cyberschoolbus/womensday/index.asp More detailed overview]
*[http://www.powa.co.za People Opposing Woman Abuse]

[[Category:holidays]]
[[Category:Holidays in Russia]]
[[Category:March observances]]
[[Category:United Nations observances|Women's Day, International]]
[[Category:Women]]

[[ar:اليوم العالمي للمرأة]]
[[bg:Международен ден на жената]]
[[ca:Dia de la Dona Treballadora]]
[[da:Kvindernes internationale kampdag]]
[[de:Internationaler Frauentag]]
[[et:Rahvusvaheline naistepäev]]
[[es:Día Internacional de la Mujer]]
[[eo:Internacia tago de virinoj]]
[[fr:Journée internationale des Femmes]]
[[gl:Día da Muller Traballadora]]
[[ko:세계 여성의 날]]
[[id:Hari Perempuan Internasional]]
[[it:Festa della donna]]
[[he:יום האישה הבינלאומי]]
[[ka:ქალთა საერთაშორისო დღე]]
[[lt:Tarptautinė moters diena]]
[[hu:Nemzetközi nőnap]]
[[mk:Меѓународен ден на жената]]
[[nl:Internationale Vrouwendag]]
[[ja:国際女性デー]]
[[no:Den internasjonale kvinnedagen]]
[[nn:Den internasjonale kvinnedagen]]
[[pl:Dzień Kobiet]]
[[pt:Dia Internacional da Mulher]]
[[ro:Ziua internaţională a femeii]]
[[ru:Международный женский день]]
[[simple:International Women's Day]]
[[sk:Medzinárodný deň žien]]
[[sl:Dan žena]]
[[sh:Međunarodni dan žena]]
[[fi:Kansainvälinen naistenpäivä]]
[[sv:Internationella kvinnodagen]]
[[vi:Ngày Quốc tế Phụ nữ]]
[[uk:Міжнародний жіночій день]]
[[zh:国际妇女节]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>