<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20220914234357|1110346989" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="18089868" pageid="18089868" ns="0" title="Linguistic discrimination"><revisions><rev timestamp="2022-11-19T15:25:36Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|Discrimination on the basis of language of an individual}}
{{redirect-distinguish|Linguicist|Linguistics}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=May 2018}}
{{Discrimination sidebar|expand-attributes=yes}}

'''Linguistic discrimination''' (also called '''glottophobia''', '''linguicism''' and '''languagism''') is unfair treatment of people which is based on [[usage (language)|their use of language]] and the characteristics of their speech, including their [[first language]], their [[accent (sociolinguistics)|accent]], the perceived size of their [[vocabulary]] (whether or not the speaker uses complex and varied words), their [[modality (semiotics)|modality]], and their [[syntax]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|publisher=Midwest New Media|title=Language Discrimination - Workplace Fairness|url=https://www.workplacefairness.org/language-discrimination|access-date=2021-08-13|website=www.workplacefairness.org|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; For example, an [[Occitan language|Occitan speaker]] in France will probably be treated differently from a [[French language|French speaker]].&lt;ref name="aclunc.org"&gt;The Legal Aid Society-Employment Law Center, &amp; the ACLU Foundation of North California (2002). Language Discrimination: Your Legal Rights. http://www.aclunc.org/library/publications/asset_upload_file489_3538.pdf {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120904172551/https://www.aclunc.org/library/publications/asset_upload_file489_3538.pdf |date=4 September 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Based on a difference in use of language, a person may automatically form judgments about another person's [[wealth]], [[education]], [[social status]], character or other traits, which may lead to discrimination.

In the mid-1980s, [[linguist]] [[Tove Skutnabb-Kangas]] captured the idea of language-based discrimination as linguicism, which was defined as "ideologies and structures which are used to legitimize, effectuate, and reproduce unequal divisions of power and resources (both material and non-material) between groups which are defined on the basis of language".&lt;ref&gt;Quoted in Skutnabb-Kangas, Tove, and Phillipson, Robert, "'Mother Tongue': The Theoretical and Sociopolitical Construction of a Concept." In Ammon, Ulrich (ed.) (1989). ''Status and Function of Languages and Language Varieties'', p. 455. Berlin, New York: Walter de Gruyter &amp; Co. {{ISBN|3-11-011299-X}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Although different names have been given to this form of discrimination, they all hold the same definition. It is also important to note that linguistic discrimination is culturally and socially determined due to preference for one use of language over others.

Scholars have analyzed the role of [[linguistic imperialism]] in linguicism, with some asserting that speakers of dominant languages gravitate towards discrimination against speakers of other, less dominant languages, while disadvantaging themselves linguistically by remaining monolingual.&lt;ref name="TBD1"&gt;{{cite news | first=Ebbe | last=Dommisse | url=https://www.businesslive.co.za/bd/life/books/2016-11-16-single-dominant-tongue-keeps-inequality-in-place/ | title=Single dominant tongue keeps inequality in place | date=16 November 2016 | newspaper=The Business Day | access-date=14 October 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to scholar Carolyn McKinley, this phenomenon is most present in [[Africa]], where the majority of the population speaks [[Languages of Europe|European languages]] introduced during the [[Colonisation of Africa|colonial era]]; African states are also noted as instituting European languages as the main medium of instruction, instead of [[indigenous language]]s.&lt;ref name="TBD1" /&gt; [[UNESCO]] reports have noted that this has historically benefitted only the African [[upper class]], conversely disadvantaging the majority of Africa's population who hold varying level of fluency in the European languages spoken across the continent.&lt;ref name="TBD1" /&gt; Scholars have also noted impact of the linguistic dominance of English on [[academic discipline]]; scholar Anna Wierzbicka has described disciplines such as [[social science]] and [[humanities]] being "locked in a conceptual framework grounded in English" which prevents academia as a whole from reaching a "more universal, culture-independent perspective".&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;Anna Wierzbicka, Professor of Linguistics, Australian National University and author of '[https://global.oup.com/academic/product/imprisoned-in-english-9780199321506?cc=be&amp;lang=en&amp; Imprisoned by English], The Hazards of English as a Default Language, written in [[Natural semantic metalanguage|Natural Semantic Metalanguage]] (NSM), the universally convertible currency of communication, which can serve as a common [[International auxiliary language|auxiliary]] [[Interlanguage|inter-language]] for speakers of different languages and a global means for clarifying, elucidating, storing, and comparing ideas" (194) ([http://journals.sagepub.com/doi/pdf/10.1177/0075424214558927 book review])&lt;/ref&gt;

==Linguistic prejudice==

It can be noted that speakers with certain accents may experience prejudice. For example, some accents hold more [[prestige (sociolinguistics)|prestige]] than others depending on the cultural context. However, with so many dialects, it can be difficult to determine which is the most preferable. The best answer linguists can give, such as the authors of ''Do You Speak American?'', is that it depends on the location and the speaker. Research has determined however that some sounds in languages may be determined to sound less pleasant naturally.&lt;ref&gt;Bresnahan, M. J., Ohashi, R., Nebashi, R., Liu, W. Y., &amp; Shearman, S. M. (2002). Attitudinal and effective response toward accented English. Language and Communication, 22, 171–185.&lt;/ref&gt; Also, certain accents tend to carry more prestige in some societies over other accents. For example, in the United States speaking [[General American]] (a variety associated with the privileged [[racism in the United States|white]] middle class) is widely preferred in many contexts such as television journalism. Also, in the United Kingdom, the [[Received Pronunciation]] is associated with being of higher class and thus more likable.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | url=http://www.indiana.edu/~hlw/PhonProcess/accents.html | title=HLW: Word Forms: Processes: English Accents}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition to prestige, research has shown that certain accents may also be associated with less intelligence, and having poorer social skills.&lt;ref&gt;Bradac, J. J. (1990). Language attitudes and impression formation. In H. Giles &amp; W. P. Robinson (Eds.), Handbook of language and social psychology (pp. 387–412). London: John Wiley.&lt;/ref&gt; An example can be seen in the difference between Southerners and Northerners in the United States, where people from the North are typically perceived as being less likable in character, and Southerners are perceived as being less intelligent. As sociolinguist, Lippi-Green, argues, "It has been widely observed that when histories are written, they focus on the dominant class... Generally studies of the development of language over time are very narrowly focused on the smallest portion of speakers: those with power and resources to control the distribution of information."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=English with an Accent: Language, ideology, and discrimination in the United States|last=Lippi-Green|first=Rosina|publisher=Routledge|year=2012|isbn=978-0-415-55911-9|location=Abingdon, Oxon|pages=40|edition=Second}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Language and social group saliency==

[[File:Patriotic_propaganda_(16627007085).jpg|thumb|150px|right|Linguistic discrimination is sometimes linked with belonging to a social group, as in [[patriotism]] and [[nationalism]]. This poster is propaganda from [[World War I]].]]

It is natural for human beings to want to identify with others. One way we do this is by categorizing individuals into specific [[Social identity theory|social groups]]. While some groups may be readily noticeable (such as those defined by ethnicity or gender), other groups are less [[Salience (language)|salient]]. Linguist Carmen Fought explains how an individual's use of language may allow another person to categorize them into a specific social group that may otherwise be less apparent.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url = https://www.pbs.org/speak/speech/| title = Do You Speak American . What Speech Do We Like Best? {{!}} PBS| website = [[PBS]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; For example, in the United States it is common to perceive Southerners as less intelligent. Belonging to a social group such as the South may be less salient than membership to other groups that are defined by ethnicity or gender. Language provides a bridge for prejudice to occur for these less salient social groups.&lt;ref&gt;Jaspal, R. (2009). Language and social identity: a psychosocial approach.  Psych-Talk, 64, 17-20.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Linguistic discrimination and colonization ==

=== History of linguistic imperialism ===

The impacts of colonization on linguistic traditions vary based on the form of colonization experienced: trader, settler or exploitation.&lt;ref name=":03"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Mufwene|first=Salikoko|date=2002|title=Colonisation, globalisation, and the future of languages in the twenty-first century|journal=International Journal on Multicultural Societies|volume=4|issue=2|pages=162–193|citeseerx=10.1.1.109.2253}}&lt;/ref&gt; Congolese-American linguist [[Salikoko Mufwene]] describes trader colonization as one of the earliest forms of European colonization. In regions such as the western coast of Africa as well as the Americas, trade relations between European colonizers and indigenous peoples led to the development of [[Pidgin|pidgin languages]].&lt;ref name=":03" /&gt; Some of these languages, such as Delaware Pidgin and [[Mobilian Jargon]], were based on Native American languages, while others, such as [[Nigerian Pidgin]] and [[Cameroonian Pidgin English|Cameroonian Pidgin]], were based on European ones.&lt;ref name=":7"&gt;{{Cite book|last1=Mufwene|first1=Salikoko|title=Globalization and language vitality: Perspectives from Africa|last2=Vigouroux|first2=Cécile B.|year=2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; As trader colonization proceeded mainly via these hybrid languages, rather than the languages of the colonizers, scholars like Mufwene contend that it posed little threat to indigenous languages.&lt;ref name=":7" /&gt;

[[File:Carlisle pupils.jpg|thumb|A photo of students at the Carlisle Indian Industrial School]]

Trader colonization was often followed by settler colonization, where European colonizers settled in these colonies to build new homes.&lt;ref name=":03" /&gt; Hamel, a Mexican linguist, argues that "segregation" and "integration" were two primary ways through which settler colonists engaged with aboriginal cultures.&lt;ref name=":6"&gt;{{Cite book|last=Hamel|first=Rainer Enrique|chapter=Indigenous education in Latin America: Policies and legal frameworks|title=Linguistic Human Rights|year=1995|publisher=DE GRUYTER MOUTON|doi=10.1515/9783110866391.271|isbn=978-3-11-086639-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; In countries such as Uruguay, Brazil, Argentina, and those in the [[Caribbean]], segregation and genocide decimated indigenous societies.&lt;ref name=":6" /&gt; Widespread death due to war and illness caused many indigenous populations to lose their [[indigenous language]]s.&lt;ref name=":03" /&gt; In contrast, in countries that pursued policies of "integration", such as Mexico, [[Guatemala]] and the [[Andean states]], indigenous cultures were lost as aboriginal tribes mixed with colonists.&lt;ref name=":6" /&gt; In these countries, the establishment of new European orders led to the adoption of colonial languages in governance and industry.&lt;ref name=":03" /&gt; In addition, European colonists also viewed the dissolution of indigenous societies and traditions as necessary for the development of a unified [[nation state]].&lt;ref name=":6" /&gt; This led to efforts to destroy tribal languages and cultures: in Canada and the United States, for example, Native children were sent to boarding schools such as Col. Richard Pratt's [[Carlisle Indian Industrial School]].&lt;ref name=":03" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Szasz|first=Margaret Connell|date=April 2009|title=Colin G. Calloway. White People, Indians, and Highlanders: Tribal People and Colonial Encounters in Scotland and America. Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2008. Pp. 368. $35.00 (cloth).|journal=Journal of British Studies|volume=48|issue=2|pages=522–524|doi=10.1086/598899|issn=0021-9371}}&lt;/ref&gt; Today, in countries such as the United States, Canada and Australia, which were once settler colonies, indigenous languages are spoken by only a small minority of the populace.

[[File:Thomas Babington Macaulay portret.jpg|thumb|Portrait of Lord Macaulay]]

Mufwene also draws a distinction between settler colonies and exploitation colonies. In the latter, the process of colonization was focused on the extraction of raw materials needed in Europe.&lt;ref name=":03" /&gt; As a result, Europeans were less invested in their exploitation colonies, and few colonists planned to build homes in these colonies. As a result, indigenous languages were able to survive to a greater extent in these colonies compared to settler colonies.&lt;ref name=":03" /&gt; In exploitation colonies, colonial languages were often only taught to a small local elite. During the period of [[British Raj|British rule in India]], for example, [[Thomas Babington Macaulay|Lord Macaulay]] highlighted the need for "...{{Nbsp}}a class who may be interpreters between us and the millions who govern... a class of persons, Indian in blood and color, but English in taste, in my opinion, in morals and in intellect" in his now-famous "Macaulay minutes", which were written in support of the [[English Education Act 1835|English Education Act of 1835]].&lt;ref name="Parameswaran 21–41"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Parameswaran|first=Radhika E.|s2cid=145358972|date=February 1997|title=Colonial Interventions and the Postcolonial Situation in India|journal=Gazette (Leiden, Netherlands)|volume=59|issue=1|pages=21–41|doi=10.1177/0016549297059001003|issn=0016-5492}}&lt;/ref&gt; The linguistic differences between the local elite and other locals exacerbated class stratification, and also increased inequality in access to education, industry and civic society in postcolonial states.&lt;ref name=":03" /&gt;

=== Linguistic discrimination and culture ===

Several postcolonial literary theorists have drawn a link between linguistic discrimination and the oppression of indigenous cultures. Prominent [[Kenya]]n author [[Ngũgĩ wa Thiong'o|Ngugi wa Thiong'o]], for example, argues in his book [[Decolonising the Mind|''Decolonizing the Mind'']] that language is both a medium of communication, as well as a carrier of culture.&lt;ref name=":32"&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Kamoche|first1=Jidlaph G.|last2=Thiong'o|first2=Ngũugĩ wa|date=1987|title=Decolonising the Mind: The Politics of Language in African Literature|journal=World Literature Today|volume=61|issue=2|pages=339|doi=10.2307/40143257|jstor=40143257|issn=0196-3570}}&lt;/ref&gt; As a result, linguistic discrimination resulting from colonization has facilitated the erasure of pre-colonial histories and identities.&lt;ref name=":32" /&gt; For example, [[Slavery in Africa|African slaves]] were taught English and forbidden to use their indigenous languages. This severed the slaves' linguistic and thus cultural connection to Africa.&lt;ref name=":32" /&gt;

=== Colonial languages and class ===

In contrast to settler colonies, in exploitation colonies, education in colonial tongues was only accessible to a small indigenous elite.&lt;ref name=":7" /&gt; Both the British Macaulay Doctrine, as well as French and Portuguese systems of [[Assimilation (French colonialism)|assimilation]], for example, sought to create an "elite class of colonial auxiliaries" who could serve as intermediaries between the colonial government and local populace.&lt;ref name=":7" /&gt; As a result, fluency in colonial languages became a signifier of class in colonized lands.

In postcolonial states, linguistic discrimination continues to reinforce notions of class. In Haiti, for example, working-class Haitians predominantly speak [[Haitian Creole]], while members of the local bourgeoise are able to speak both French and Creole.&lt;ref name=":13" /&gt; Members of this local elite frequently conduct business and politics in French, thereby excluding many of the working-class from such activities.&lt;ref name=":13" /&gt; In addition, D. L. Sheath, an advocate for the use of indigenous languages in India, also writes that the Indian elite associates nationalism with a unitary identity, and in this context, "uses English as a means of exclusion and an instrument of [[cultural hegemony]]”.&lt;ref name="Parameswaran 21–41" /&gt;

=== Linguistic discrimination in education ===

[[File:Haitian school children (8116999996).jpg|thumb|Photo of school children in Haiti]]

Class disparities in postcolonial nations are often reproduced through education. In countries such as [[Haiti]], schools attended by the bourgeoisie are usually of higher quality and use colonial languages as their means of instruction. On the other hand, schools attended by the rest of the population are often taught in [[Haitian Creole]].&lt;ref name=":13"&gt;{{Cite book|date=2019-01-08|editor-last=Chitpin|editor-first=Stephanie|editor2-last=Portelli|editor2-first=John P.|title=Confronting Educational Policy in Neoliberal Times|doi=10.4324/9781315149875|isbn=9781315149875|s2cid=213687921}}&lt;/ref&gt; Scholars such as Hebblethwaite argue that Creole-based education will improve learning, literacy and socioeconomic mobility in a country where 95% of the population are monolingual in Creole.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Hebblethwaite|first=Benjamin|date=2012|title=French and underdevelopment, Haitian Creole and development: Educational language policy problems and solutions in Haiti|journal=Journal of Pidgin and Creole Languages|volume=27|issue=2|pages=255–302|doi=10.1075/jpcl.27.2.03heb|issn=0920-9034}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, resultant disparities in colonial language fluency and educational quality can impede social mobility.&lt;ref name=":13" /&gt;

On the other hand, areas such as [[French Guiana]] have chosen to teach colonial languages in all schools, often to the exclusion of local indigenous languages.&lt;ref name=":22"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Bunyi|first=Grace|date=July 1999|title=Rethinking the place of African indigenous languages in African education|journal=International Journal of Educational Development|volume=19|issue=4–5|pages=337–350|doi=10.1016/s0738-0593(99)00034-6|issn=0738-0593|url=http://ir-library.ku.ac.ke/handle/123456789/10121 }}&lt;/ref&gt; As colonial languages were viewed by many as the "civilized" tongues, being "educated" often meant being able to speak and write in these colonial tongues.&lt;ref name=":22" /&gt; Indigenous language education was often seen as an impediment to achieving fluency in these colonial languages, and thus deliberately suppressed.&lt;ref name=":22" /&gt;

[[File:School in Uganda (5348565315).jpg|thumb|Photo of a school in Uganda]]

Certain [[Commonwealth of Nations|Commonwealth nations]] such as Uganda and Kenya have historically had a policy of teaching in indigenous languages and only introducing English in the upper grades.&lt;ref name=":4"&gt;{{Cite book|first1=Andrew W.|last1=Fishman|first2=Joshua A.|last2=Rubal-Lopez|first3=Alma|last3=Conrad|title=Post-Imperial English : Status Change in Former British and American Colonies, 1940-1990|date=13 October 2011|isbn=978-3-11-087218-7|oclc=979587836}}&lt;/ref&gt; This policy was a legacy of the "dual mandate" as conceived by [[Frederick Lugard, 1st Baron Lugard|Lord Lugard]], a British colonial administrator in [[Colonial Nigeria|Nigeria]].&lt;ref name=":4" /&gt; However, by the post-war period, English was increasingly viewed as necessary skill for accessing professional employment and better economic opportunities.&lt;ref name=":4" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|date=2005-12-31|editor-last=Lin|editor-first=Angel|editor2-last=Martin|editor2-first=Peter|title=Decolonisation, Globalisation|doi=10.21832/9781853598265|isbn=9781853598265}}&lt;/ref&gt; As a result, there was increasing support amongst the populace for English-based education, which Kenya's Ministry of Education adopted post-independence, and Uganda following their civil war. Later on, members of the Ominde Commission in Kenya expressed the need for [[Swahili language|Kiswahili]] in promoting a national and pan-African identity. Kenya therefore began to offer Kiswahili as a compulsory, non-examinable subject in primary school, but it remained secondary to English as a medium of instruction.&lt;ref name=":4" /&gt;

While the mastery of colonial languages may provide better economic opportunities, the [[Convention against Discrimination in Education]]&lt;ref&gt;Convention against Discrimination in Education, Article 5&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[Convention on the Rights of the Child|UN Convention on the Rights of the Child]] also states that minority children have the right to "use [their] own [languages]". The suppression of [[indigenous language]]s within the education system appears to contravene this treaty.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Rannut|first=Mart|title=Linguistic human rights: Overcoming linguistic discrimination (Vol. 67)|publisher=Walter de Gruyter|year=2010|isbn=978-3-11-086639-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title=UN: Convention on Rights of the Child, 1989|journal=International Documents on Corporate Responsibility|year=2005|doi=10.4337/9781845428297.00029|isbn=9781845428297|last1=Tully|first1=Stephen}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, children who speak indigenous languages can also be disadvantaged when educated in foreign languages, and often have high illiteracy rates. For example, when the French arrived to "civilize" Algeria, which included imposing French on local Algerians, the literacy rate in Algeria was over 40%, higher than that in France at the time. However, when the French left in 1962, the literacy rate in Algiers was at best 10-15%.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|last1=Canagarajah|first1=Suresh|chapter=Linguistic imperialism|publisher=Routledge|isbn=978-0-203-83565-4|last2=Said|first2=Selim Ben|title=The Routledge Handbook of Applied Linguistics|year=2010|doi=10.4324/9780203835654.ch27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Linguistic discrimination in governance ===

As colonial languages are used as the languages of governance and commerce in many colonial and postcolonial states,&lt;ref name=":03" /&gt; locals who only speak indigenous languages can be disenfranchised. For example, when representative institutions were introduced to the [[Algoma District|Algoma]] region in what is now modern-day Canada, the local returning officer only accepted the votes of individuals who were enfranchised, which required indigenous peoples to "read and write fluently... [their] own and another language, either English or French".&lt;ref name=":5"&gt;{{Cite book|last1=Evans|first1=Julie|title=Equal Subjects, Unequal Rights|last2=Grimshaw|first2=Patricia|last3=Phillips|first3=David|date=2003-08-21|publisher=Manchester University Press|doi=10.7228/manchester/9780719060038.001.0001|isbn=978-0-7190-6003-8}}&lt;/ref&gt; This caused political parties to increasingly identify with settler perspectives rather than indigenous ones.&lt;ref name=":5" /&gt;

Even today, many postcolonial states continue to use colonial languages in their public institutions, even though these languages are not spoken by the majority of their residents.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Brock-Utne|first=Birgit|date=2003|title=The language question in Africa in the light of globalisation, social justice and democracy.|journal=International Journal of Peace Studies|volume=8|issue=2|pages=67–87|jstor=41852902}}&lt;/ref&gt; For example, the [[South Africa]]n justice system still relies primarily on English and [[Afrikaans]] as its primary languages, even though most South Africans, particularly [[Bantu peoples of South Africa|Black South Africans]], speak indigenous languages.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Cote|first=David|date=2014|title=The right to language use in South African criminal courts|url=https://open.uct.ac.za/bitstream/handle/11427/4441/thesis_law_coted_2005.pdf?sequence=1|journal=Doctoral Dissertation, University of Cape Town}}&lt;/ref&gt; In these situations, the use of colonial languages can present barriers to participation in public institutions.

==Examples==

Linguistic discrimination is often defined in terms of prejudice of language. It is important to note that although there is a relationship between prejudice and discrimination, they are not always directly related.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Schütz | first1 = H. | last2 = Six | first2 = B. | year = 1996 | title = How strong is the relationship between prejudice and discrimination? A meta-analytic answer | journal = International Journal of Intercultural Relations | volume = 20 | issue = 3–4| pages = 441–462 | doi=10.1016/0147-1767(96)00028-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Prejudice]] can be defined as negative attitudes towards a person based on their membership of a social group, whereas [[discrimination]] can be seen as the acts towards them. The difference between the two should be recognized because prejudice may be held against someone, but it may not be acted on.&lt;ref&gt;Whitley, B.E., &amp; Kite, M.E. (2010) The Psychology of Prejudice and Discrimination. Ed 2. pp.379-383. Cencage Learning: Belmont.&lt;/ref&gt; The following are examples of linguistic prejudice which may result in discrimination.

===Linguistic prejudice and minority groups===

While, theoretically, any speaker may be the victim of linguicism regardless of social and ethnic status, oppressed and [[marginalized]] social minorities are often the most consistent targets, due to the fact that the speech varieties that come to be associated with such groups have a tendency to be [[social stigma|stigmatized]].

===In Canada===

====Francophones in Canada====

{{Expand section|1=explanations, examples and additional citations|section=1|date=February 2021|small=no}}
Historically, the Canadian federation and provinces have [[Anti-Quebec sentiment|discriminated against Canada's French-speaking population]], during some periods in the [[history of Canada]], they have treated its members as [[second-class citizen]]s, and they have favored the members of the more powerful English-speaking population. This form of discrimination has resulted in or contributed to many developments in Canadian history, including the rise of the [[Quebec sovereignty movement]], [[Quebecois nationalism]], the [[Lower Canada Rebellion]], the [[Red River Rebellion]], a proposed [[List of proposed provinces and territories of Canada|Acadia province]], extreme poverty and low [[socio-economic status]] of the [[French Canadian]] population, low francophone graduation rates as a result of the outlawing of francophone schools across Canada, differences in average earnings between francophones and anglophones in the same positions, fewer chances of being hired or promoted for francophones, and many other things.

====Anglophones in Quebec====

The [[Charter of the French Language]], first established in 1977 and amended several times since, has been accused of being discriminatory by English-speakers.{{Citation needed|date=July 2021}} The law makes French the official language of Quebec and mandates its use (with exceptions) in government offices and communiques, schools, and in commercial public relations. The law is a way of preventing linguistic discrimination against the majority francophone population of Quebec who were for a very long time controlled by the English minority of the province. The law also seeks to protect French against the growing social and economic dominance of English. Though the English-speaking population had been shrinking since the 1960s, it was hastened by the law, and the 2006 census showed a net loss of 180,000 native English-speakers.&lt;ref name="collectiverightsquebec"&gt;Richard Y. Bourhis &amp; Pierre Foucher, [http://qcgn.squarespace.com/storage/website-resources/library/documents/national-assembly/Bill%20103%20Impact%20Study%20Collective%20Rights%20and%20Vitality%202011.01.05.pdf "Bill 103: Collective Rights and the declining vitality of the English-speaking communities of Quebec "] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20131029195204/http://qcgn.squarespace.com/storage/website-resources/library/documents/national-assembly/Bill%20103%20Impact%20Study%20Collective%20Rights%20and%20Vitality%202011.01.05.pdf |date=29 October 2013 }}, ''Canadian Institute for Research on Linguistic Minorities'', Version 3, 25 November 2010&lt;/ref&gt; Despite this, speaking English at work continues to be strongly correlated with higher earnings, with French-only speakers earning significantly less.&lt;ref&gt;Louis N. Christofides &amp; Robert Swidinsky, [http://utpjournals.metapress.com/content/p0w06tr200310861/fulltext.pdf "The Economic Returns to the Knowledge and Use of a Second Official Language: English in Quebec and French in the Rest-of-Canada"] {{dead link|date=December 2017 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}, ''Canadian Public Policy – Analyse de Politiques Vol. XXXVI'', No. 2 2010 
&lt;/ref&gt; The law is credited with successfully raising the status of French in a predominantly English-speaking economy, and it has been influential in countries facing similar circumstances.&lt;ref name="collectiverightsquebec" /&gt; However, amendments have made it less powerful and thus less effective than it was in the past.{{Citation needed|date=July 2021}}

=== In Europe ===

==== Linguistic disenfranchisement rate ====

The linguistic disenfranchisement rate in the EU can significantly vary across countries. For residents in two EU-countries that are either native speakers of English or proficient in English as a foreign language the disenfranchisement rate is equal to zero. In his study "Multilingual communication for whom? Language policy and fairness in the European Union", [[Michele Gazzola]] comes to the conclusion that the current multilingual policy of the EU is not in the absolute the most effective way to inform Europeans about the EU; in certain countries, additional languages may be useful to minimize linguistic exclusion.&lt;ref name=":3"&gt;Michele Gazzola, [https://www.academia.edu/28511833/Multilingual_communication_for_whom_Language_policy_and_fairness_in_the_European_Union Multilingual communication for whom? Language policy and fairness in the European Union], European Union Politics, 2016, Vol. 17(4) 546–569&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 24 countries examined, an English-only language policy would exclude 51% to 90% of adult residents. A language regime based on English, French and German would disenfranchise 30% to 56% of residents, whereas a regime based on six languages would bring the shares of excluded population down to 9–22%.  After [[Brexit]], the rates of linguistic exclusion associated with a monolingual policy and with a trilingual and a hexalingual regime are likely to increase.&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt;

==== Linguistic discrimination towards languages in the Celtic nations ====

* During the period of [[British rule in Ireland]], the [[Irish language]] was not taught in schools and held no official status until the establishment of the [[Irish Free State]] in 1922.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=l37VBQAAQBAJ |title=An Irish-Speaking Island: State, Religion, Community, and the Linguistic Landscape in Ireland, 1770–1870 |last=Wolf |first=Nicholas M. |publisher=University of Wisconsin Press |year=2014 |isbn=978-0-299-30274-0 }}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Clarify|reason=The Republic of Ireland wasn't established until 1949 per [[Republic of Ireland Act 1948]]|date=September 2021}}

* In [[Wales]], English was seen as the language of progress and the speaking of [[Welsh language|Welsh]] was discouraged in schools, and the [[Welsh Not]] was used in some places to help with this during the 18th and 19th centuries.&lt;ref&gt;John Davies, ''A History of Wales'', Penguin, 1994, {{ISBN|0-14-014581-8}}, p 455&lt;/ref&gt;

* [[Scottish Gaelic]] had no official status until [[Languages in the United Kingdom#Status|2005]]; it was not taught in the educational system due to being "one of the chief, principal causes of barbarity and incivility" in the words of one statute.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Arnove|first1=R. F.|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=RkX2BwAAQBAJ&amp;q=scottish+gaelic+abolish+and+remove+education+history+barbarity&amp;pg=PA61|title=National Literacy Campaigns: Historical and Comparative Perspectives|last2=Graff|first2=H. J.|date=2013-11-11|publisher=Springer Science &amp; Business Media|isbn=9781489905055|language=en|access-date=19 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* [[Scots language|Scots]] was in 1946 not considered "a suitable medium of education or culture".&lt;ref&gt;Primary education: a report of the Advisory Council on Education in Scotland, Scottish Education Department 1946, p. 75&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Other examples ====

[[File:Euskarazko_hitz_egiteagatik_zigortutako_Bedaioko_ikasle_baten_koadernoa_2.jpg|thumb|"I will not speak Basque" punishment in the exercise book of a schoolchild during Franco's dictatorial regime]]

*[[Basque language|Basque]]: [[Language policies of Francoist Spain|public usage]] of Basque was persecuted and restricted during [[Francoist Spain]], 1936 to 1978. [[Galician language|Galician]] and [[Catalan language|Catalan]] have similar histories.

*[[Vergonha]] is the term used for the effect of various policies of the government of France on its citizens whose [[mother tongue]] was one of so-called patois. In 1539, with Article 111 of the [[Ordinance of Villers-Cotterêts]], French – the language of the [[Île-de-France]] – became the only official language in the country despite being spoken by only a minority of the population. In education and administration, it was forbidden to use regional languages, such as [[Occitan language|Occitan]], [[Catalan language|Catalan]], [[Basque language|Basque]] and [[Breton language|Breton]]. The French government still has not ratified the [[European Charter for Regional or Minority Languages]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url = https://www.thelocal.fr/20140123/in-france-there-is-only-one-language/| url-status = dead| archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20140128050816/http://www.thelocal.fr/20140123/in-france-there-is-only-one-language| archive-date = 2014-01-28| title = Hypocrisy? France and its regional languages - The Local}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 8 April 2021, the Breton MP [[Paul Molac]] tried to pass a law to protect minority languages, and this law was passed by the French Parliament in Paris.&lt;ref&gt;https://www.ouest-france.fr/education/enseignement/langues-regionales-la-proposition-de-loi-molac-definitivement-adoptee-9ae0f46c-9875-11eb-ba1d-f4b880206b36 {{Bare URL inline|date=August 2022}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the French Minister of Education, opposed to the teaching in minority languages, asked the [[Conseil Constitutionnel]] to declare it unconstitutional. This led to the law being constitutionally struck down on 21 May 2021.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url = https://www.lefigaro.fr/flash-actu/langues-regionales-le-conseil-constitutionnel-censure-partiellement-la-proposition-de-loi-20210521| title = Langues régionales : le Conseil constitutionnel censure partiellement la proposition de loi| date = 21 May 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt; This decision recognizes the right of central administration to oppose the spelling of Basque and Breton names when they contain an [[ñ]] letter and forbid such names.  

*[[Dutch in Belgium]] after its independence in 1830. French was for a long time the only official language and the only language of education, administration, law and justice despite Dutch being the most common language, due to reject in dirigencial classes because the identification with the [[Belgian Revolt#United Kingdom of the Netherlands|Netherlands rule between 1815 and 1830]]. This has led to widespread [[Francisation of Brussels|language shift in Brussels]]. Discrimination slowly faded over the decades and formally ended in the 1960s, when the Dutch version of the constitution became equal to the French version.

*[[Germanisation]]: [[Prussia]]n discrimination of [[West Slavs]] in the 19th century, such as the removal of [[Polish language|Polish]] from secondary (1874) and primary (1886) schools, the use of [[School corporal punishment|corporal punishment]] leading to such events as the [[Września children strike|Września school strike]].

*Low Saxon ([[Low German]]) in Germany: While [[Middle Saxon]] served as a lingua franca in the North and Baltic Sea areas from around the 12th/13th century until the early 16th century, nobility, institutions of authority and influential people in the 16th century started to force writers in Northern Germany to use [[Early New High German]] as their written language. This caused a change first in the written language and later on in the spoken language through a strong social stigmatization by what this process has been called an inner colonization by linguist [[:de:Peter von Polenz|Peter von Polenz]] that was similar to the Germanisation of Slavic peoples.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last1=Polenz|first1=Peter|pages=279–281|title=Deutsche Sprachgeschichte vom Spätmittelalter bis zur Gegenwart. Band 1, Einführung, Grundbegriffe, Deutsch in der frühbürgerlichen Zeit.|publisher=Walther de Gruyter|year=1991|isbn=3-11-012458-0}}&lt;/ref&gt; This was also the time when the name of the language changed from ''sassesch'' or ''sassesche sprâke'' (Saxon language) to ''Plattdütsch'' (lit. ''Flat German'').

*[[Magyarisation]]: For most of its existence, the Kingdom of Hungary had been a linguistically inclusionary state, but with the rise of ethnic nationalism in the early 19th century, this tradition was completely reversed due to a gradual adoption of nationalist and anti-minority policies by Hungary's ruling elites. The policy of Magyarisation (sometimes also "Hungarianisation") emerged in the 19th-century Kingdom of Hungary, and was practiced until the dissolution of Austria-Hungary in 1918. Magyarization saw efforts to marginalize and erase the use of minority languages in culture, education, politics, placenames and even everyday use. Targets included a number of Slavic languages (Slovak, Rusyn, Ukrainian, etc.), Romanian, and others. During the 1890s, hundreds of villages and towns throughout the Hungarian part of Austria-Hungary were forcibly renamed to more Hungarian forms. This included the renaming of already existing Hungarian placenames, previously in use for centuries, largelly to promote the exclusionary nationalist ideology of the era. The strictest pro-Magyarization policies were adopted as legislation in 1907, known as the Apponyi Laws (Lex Apponyi), spearheaded by [[Albert Apponyi]]. The laws, as adopted, intentionally discriminated all minority languages, in an effort to completely exclude them from use in public life. 

*[[Norwegianization]]: Former policy carried out by the Norwegian government directed at the [[Sámi people|Sámi]] and later the [[Kven people]] of the [[Sapmi|Sapmi region]] in [[Northern Norway]].

*[[Russification]]: [[Russification#Lithuania and Poland|19th century policies]] on the territories seized due to [[Partitions of Poland]], such as banning [[Polish language|Polish]], [[Lithuanian language|Lithuanian]] and [[Belarusian language|Belarusian]] in public places (1864), later (1880s), Polish was banned in schools and offices of [[Congress Poland]]. [[Chronology of Ukrainian language suppression|Ukrainian]] and [[Romanian language|Romanian]] were also discriminated against. Under the [[Russian Empire]], there were some attempts in 1899–1917 to [[Russification of Finland|make Russian the only official language of Finland]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = https://www.histdoc.net/history/keisarik.html | title = 1899. The Collection of Decrees of the Grand Duchy of Finland. No 3. | access-date = 2017-12-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{efn|The controversy concerning the reductions of Finnish autonomy is considered to already have begun in the early 1890s, see [[Woldemar von Daehn]].&lt;ref name=kansallisbiografia&gt;{{cite web |last1=Tyynilä |first1=Markku |title=Daehn, Woldemar von (1838 - 1900) |url=https://kansallisbiografia.fi/kansallisbiografia/henkilo/3266 |website=Kansallisbiografia |access-date=16 May 2020 |date=16 September 1997}}&lt;/ref&gt;}} 

In the [[Soviet Union]], following the phase of [[Korenizatsiya]] ("indigenization") and before [[Perestroika]] (late 1930s to late 1980s), Russian was called "the language of friendship of nations" to the disadvantage of other [[languages of the Soviet Union]].{{Citation needed|date=July 2012}}

*The russification and restraining of the linguistic rights of federal subjects in Russia, most notably in the [[federal subjects of Russia|federal subject]] of [[Tatarstan]].

*[[Language law of Slovakia|Controversy over 2009 amendment to Slovak language law]]: The 1995 Slovak language law defined [[Slovak language|Slovak]] as the official language of the [[Slovakia|Slovak Republic]], with other related laws guaranteeing rights to the country's minority languages (e.g. in bureaucracy, education, cultural venues, multilingual street and road signs). The law was subsequently amended in 1999, to guarantee further protection to minority language use and comply with EU standards. The law saw controversial amendments in 2009. Slovakia's 2006-2010 government passed a controversial amendment to aspects of the language law in 2009. [[Hungarians in Slovakia]] and politicians in Hungary accused the law of being discriminatory to their language group, claiming it endangers the rights to use [[Hungarian language|Hungarian]] in the country. The 2010-2012 Slovak government opened the law again in 2011, voting to remove the previous controversial amendments. 
 
* [[Serbs|Serb]] organisations in [[Montenegro]] have reported discrimination of Serbian.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://balkaninsight.com/2014/10/20/montenegrin-serbs-call-for-language-discrimination-to-stop/|title=Montenegrin Serbs Allege Language Discrimination|date=2014-10-20|website=Balkan Insight|language=en-US|access-date=2020-03-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Spain: [[Language policies of Francoist Spain]] refers to the attempted elevation of [[Spanish language|Castilian]] over the other [[languages of Spain]] during the dictatorship of [[Francisco Franco]] from 1936 to 1975.

* [[Ukraine]]: Since 1804, all Ukrainian-language schools [[Chronology of Ukrainian language suppression|were banned]] in Ukraine under the [[Russian Empire]]. Ukrainian language was denied its right of existence by the Russian rulers based on [[Valuev Circular]]. Since 1892 the books [[Chronology of Ukrainian language suppression|were not allowed to be translated]] from Russian into Ukrainian.

===In the United States===

====Perpetuation of discriminatory practices through terminology====

Here and elsewhere the terms 'standard' and 'non-standard' make analysis of linguicism difficult. These terms are used widely by linguists and non-linguists when discussing varieties of American English that engender strong opinions, a false dichotomy which is rarely challenged or questioned. This has been interpreted by linguists Nicolas Coupland, [[Rosina Lippi-Green]], and [[Robin Queen]] (among others) as a discipline-internal lack of consistency which undermines progress; if linguists themselves cannot move beyond the ideological underpinnings of 'right' and 'wrong' in language, there is little hope of advancing a more nuanced understanding in the general population.&lt;ref&gt;Coupland, N. (1999). "Sociolinguistic Prevarication About 'Standard English'" Review article appearing in Tony Bex and Richard J. Watts (eds) ''Standard English: the Widening Debate'' London:Routledge&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Lippi-Green, R. (2012) ''English with an Accent: Language, Ideology and Discrimination in the U.S..'' Second revised, expanded edition. New York: Routledge.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Black Americans====

Because some black Americans speak a particular non-standard variety of English which is often seen as substandard, they are often targets of linguicism. [[African American Vernacular English|AAVE]] is often perceived by members of mainstream American society as indicative of low intelligence or limited education, and as with many other non-standard dialects and especially creoles, it is usually called "lazy" or "bad" English.

The linguist [[John McWhorter]] has described this particular form of linguicism as particularly problematic in the United States, where non-standard linguistic structures are often deemed "incorrect" by teachers and potential employers in contrast to other countries such as Morocco, Finland and Italy where [[diglossia]] (the ability to switch between two or more dialects or languages) is an accepted norm, and non-standard usage in conversation is seen as a mark of regional origin, not of intellectual capacity or achievement.

In the [[African-American Vernacular English and education#Ann Arbor Decision|1977 Ann Arbor]] court case, AAVE was compared against standard English to determine how much of an education barrier existed for children that had been primarily raised with AAVE. The assigned linguists determined that the differences, stemming from a history of racial segregation, were significant enough for the children to receive supplementary teaching to better understand standard English.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Crystal|first=David|title=The Cambrdige Encyclopedia of Language|publisher=Cambridge University Press|year=2010|isbn=978-0-521-73650-3|location=United Kingdom at the University Press, Cambridge|pages=35}}&lt;/ref&gt;

For example, a black American who uses a typical AAVE sentence such as "He be comin' in every day and sayin' he ain't done nothing" may be judged as having a deficient command of grammar, whereas, in fact, such a sentence is constructed based on a complex grammar which is different from that of standard English, not a degenerate form of it.&lt;ref&gt;Dicker, Susan J. (2nd ed., 2003). ''Languages in America: A Pluralist View'', pp. 7-8. Multilingual Matters Ltd. {{ISBN|1-85359-651-5}}.&lt;/ref&gt; A listener may misjudge the user of such a sentence to be unintellectual or uneducated. The speaker may be intellectually capable, educated, and proficient in standard English, but chose to say the sentence in AAVE for social and sociolinguistic reasons such as the intended audience of the sentence, a phenomenon known as [[Code-switching|code switching]].

====Hispanic Americans and linguicism====

Another form of linguicism is evidenced by the following: in some parts of the United States, a person who has a strong Spanish accent and uses only simple English words may be thought of as poor, poorly educated, and possibly an [[undocumented immigrant]]. However, if the same person has a diluted accent or no noticeable accent at all and can use a myriad of words in complex sentences, they are likely to be perceived as more successful, better educated, and a "legitimate [[citizen]]".

====American Sign Language users====

Users of [[American Sign Language]] (ASL) have faced linguistic discrimination based on the perception of the legitimacy of signed languages compared to spoken languages. This attitude was explicitly expressed in the [[Second International Congress on Education of the Deaf|Milan Conference]] of 1880 which set precedence for public opinion of manual forms of communication, including ASL, creating lasting consequences for members of the Deaf community.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.verywell.com/deaf-history-milan-1880-1046547 |title=Deaf History - Milan 1880 |last=Berke |first=Jame |date=30 January 2017 |website=Very Well |archive-url=https://archive.today/OPQ9B?url=https://www.verywell.com/deaf-history-milan-1880-1046547 |archive-date= 1 January 1970 |url-status=live |access-date=12 May 2017 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  The conference almost unanimously (save a handful of allies such as [[Thomas Hopkins Gallaudet]]), reaffirmed the use of [[oralism]], instruction conducted exclusively in spoken language, as the preferred education method for Deaf individuals.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://hearinghealthmatters.org/hearinginternational/2016/the-international-deafness-controversy-of-1880/|title=The International Deafness Controversy of 1880|last=Traynor|first=Bob|date=1 June 2016|website=Hearing Health and Technology Matters}}&lt;/ref&gt;  These ideas were outlined in eight resolutions which ultimately resulted in the removal of Deaf individuals from their own educational institutions, leaving generations of Deaf persons to be educated single-handedly by hearing individuals.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://dvdean.weebly.com/milan-conference-of-1880.html|title=Milan Conference of 1880|website=Weebly }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Due to misconceptions about ASL, it was not recognized as its own, fully functioning language until recently. In the 1960s, linguist [[William Stokoe]] proved ASL to be its own language based on its unique structure and grammar, separate from that of English. Before this, ASL was thought to be merely a collection of gestures used to represent English. Because of its use of visual space, it was mistakenly believed that its users are of a lesser mental capacity. The misconception that ASL users are incapable of complex thought was prevalent, although this has decreased as further studies about its recognition of a language have taken place. For example, ASL users faced overwhelming discrimination for the supposedly "lesser" language that they use and were met with condescension especially when using their language in public.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Stewart|first1=David A.|last2=Akamatsu|first2=C. Tane|date=1988-01-01|title=The Coming of Age of American Sign Language|journal=Anthropology &amp; Education Quarterly|volume=19|issue=3|pages=235–252|doi=10.1525/aeq.1988.19.3.05x1559y|jstor=3195832}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another way discrimination against ASL is evident is how, despite research conducted by linguists like Stokoe or [[Clayton Valli]] and Cecil Lucas of [[Gallaudet University]], ASL is not always recognized as a language.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.unm.edu/~wilcox/UNM/facts.html|title=ASL as a Foreign Language Fact Sheet|website=www.unm.edu|language=en|access-date=2017-03-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; Its recognition is crucial both for those learning ASL as an additional language, and for prelingually-deaf children who learn ASL as their first language. Linguist Sherman Wilcox concludes that given that it has a body of literature and international scope, to single ASL out as unsuitable for a foreign language curriculum is inaccurate. Russel S. Rosen also writes about government and academic resistance to acknowledging ASL as a foreign language at the high school or college level, which Rosen believes often resulted from a lack of understanding about the language. Rosen and Wilcox's conclusions both point to discrimination ASL users face regarding its status as a language, that although decreasing over time is still present.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Rosen|first=Russell S.|date=2008-01-01|title=American Sign Language as a Foreign Language in U.S. High Schools: State of the Art|journal=The Modern Language Journal|volume=92|issue=1|pages=10–38|doi=10.1111/j.1540-4781.2008.00684.x|jstor=25172990}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the medical community, there is immense bias against deafness and ASL. This stems from the belief that spoken languages are superior to sign languages.&lt;ref name=":02"&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Hyde|first1=Merv|last2=Punch|first2=Renée|last3=Komesaroff|first3=Linda|date=2010-01-01|title=Coming to a Decision About Cochlear Implantation: Parents Making Choices for their Deaf Children|journal=Journal of Deaf Studies and Deaf Education|volume=15|issue=2|pages=162–178|doi=10.1093/deafed/enq004|pmid=20139157|jstor=42659026|doi-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt; Because 90% of deaf babies are born to hearing parents, who are usually unaware of the existence of the [[Deaf community]], they often turn to the medical community for guidance.&lt;ref name=":12"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Crouch|first=Robert A.|s2cid=2566163|date=1997-01-01|title=Letting the Deaf Be Deaf Reconsidering the Use of Cochlear Implants in Prelingually Deaf Children|journal=The Hastings Center Report|volume=27|issue=4|pages=14–21|doi=10.2307/3528774|pmid=9271717|jstor=3528774|url=https://semanticscholar.org/paper/9f0853cb5c046dcfb167aee35c6f2109e0fd216d}}&lt;/ref&gt; Medical and audiological professionals, who are typically biased against sign languages, encourage parents to get a [[cochlear implant]] for their deaf child in order for the child to use spoken language.&lt;ref name=":02" /&gt; Research shows, however, that deaf kids without cochlear implants acquire ASL with much greater ease than deaf kids with cochlear implants acquire spoken English. In addition, medical professionals discourage parents from teaching ASL to their deaf kid to avoid compromising their English&lt;ref name=":2"&gt;{{Cite book|jstor=10.5749/j.ctt9qh3m7.33|title=Deaf Gain|last1=Skutnabb-Kangas|first1=Tove|last2=Solomon|first2=Andrew|last3=Skuttnab-Kangas|first3=Tove|date=2014-01-01|publisher=University of Minnesota Press|isbn=9780816691227|series=Raising the Stakes for Human Diversity|pages=492–502}}&lt;/ref&gt; although research shows that learning ASL does not interfere with a child's ability to learn English. In fact, the early acquisition of ASL proves to be useful to the child in learning English later on. When making a decision about cochlear implantation, parents are not properly educated about the benefits of ASL or the Deaf Community.&lt;ref name=":12" /&gt; This is seen by many members of the Deaf Community as cultural and linguistic genocide.&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt;

=== In Africa ===

* [[Anglophone Cameroonian]]s: the central Cameroonian government has pushed ''francophonization'' in the English-speaking regions of the country despite constitutional stipulations on bilingualism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/global-opinions/wp/2017/03/21/cameroon-continues-its-oppression-of-english-speakers/|title=Cameroon continues its oppression of English speakers|last1=Foretia|first1=Denis|date=21 March 2017|newspaper=The Washington Post|access-date=15 May 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Measures include appointing French-speaking teachers and judges (in regions with [[Common Law]]) despite local opposition.

* [[South Africa]]: Carolyn McKinley&lt;ref&gt;Associate professor in the education department of the University of Cape Town and author of 'Language and Power in Post-Colonial Schooling: Ideologies in Practice'&lt;/ref&gt; is highly critical of the language policy in the South African educational system, which she describes as 'anglonormatif', because the increasing [[anglicisation]] becomes 'normative' in the education system. The [[University of Pretoria|universities of Pretoria]], [[University of the Free State|Free State]] and [[University of South Africa|Unisa]] want to anglicise completely.

=== In the Middle East ===

* At the turn of the eighth century, the [[Umayyad Caliphate|Umayyad caliph]] [[Abd al-Malik ibn Marwan]] decreed that [[Arabic]] would replace [[Medieval Greek]] and the [[Coptic language]] as the administrative language of the empire. Coptic gradually declined within a few hundred years and suffered violent persecutions, especially under the [[Mamluk Sultanate (Cairo)|Mamluke Sultanate of Cairo]], leading to its virtual extinction by the 17th century.

* The [[Kurdish languages]] are under pressure in many countries where they are spoken. Publishing materials in Kurdish in [[Syria]] is forbidden,&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.amnesty.org/wire/March2005/Syria Repression of Kurds in Syria is widespread] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20071015034722/http://web.amnesty.org/wire/March2005/Syria |date=15 October 2007 }}, [[Amnesty International]] Report, March 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; though this prohibition is not enforced any more due to the [[Syrian civil war]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.al-monitor.com/pulse/originals/2015/11/syria-kurdistan-self-governance-teach-kurdish-language.html|title=After 52-year ban, Syrian Kurds now taught Kurdish in schools|date=6 November 2015|url-status=live|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160510184634/http://www.al-monitor.com/pulse/originals/2015/11/syria-kurdistan-self-governance-teach-kurdish-language.html|archive-date=10 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Until 2002, Turkey placed severe restrictions on the use of Kurdish, including a ban on its use in education and broadcast media.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.amnestyusa.org/action/special/zana.html Special Focus Cases: Leyla Zana, Prisoner of Conscience] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20050510082350/http://www.amnestyusa.org/action/special/zana.html|date=2005-05-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.freemuse.org/sw6195.asp Kurdish performers banned, Appeal from International PEN] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120113034636/http://www.freemuse.org/sw6195.asp|date=2012-01-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many mayors were tried for issuing public documents in the Kurdish language.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=On trial for speaking Kurdish|url=http://en.firatnews.com/news/features/on-trial-for-speaking-kurdish.htm|access-date=12 June 2013|newspaper=ANF-Firatnews|date=11 May 2011|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://archive.today/20130615172358/http://en.firatnews.com/news/features/on-trial-for-speaking-kurdish.htm|archive-date=15 June 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Kurdish alphabet is not recognized in Turkey, and prior to 2013 the use of Kurdish names containing the letters ''Q'', ''W'', and ''X'', which do not exist in the [[Turkish alphabet]], was not allowed.&lt;ref name="cla3a"&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.unhchr.ch/minorities/statements10/CLA3a.doc | title = Submission to the Sub-Commission on Promotion and Protection of Human Rights: Working Group of Minorities; Tenth Session, Agenda Item 3 (a) | first = Saniye | last = Karakaş | publisher = [[United Nations Commission on Human Rights]] |date=March 2004 | access-date = 2006-11-07 | format = [[Microsoft Word|MS Word]]|quote = Kurds have been officially allowed since September 2003 to take Kurdish names, but cannot use the letters x, w, or q, which are common in Kurdish but do not exist in Turkey's version of the Latin alphabet. [...] Those letters, however, are used in Turkey in the names of companies, TV and radio channels, and trademarks. For example [[Turkish Army]] has company under the name of AXA [[OYAK]] and there is [[Show TV|SHOW TV]] television channel in Turkey. |archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20070628171743/http://www.unhchr.ch/minorities/statements10/CLA3a.doc &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archive-date = 2007-06-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.slate.com/blogs/lexicon_valley/2013/10/24/turkey_prime_minister_erdogan_s_democratizaton_package_legalizes_letters.html |title=Turkey legalizes the letters Q, W, and X. Yay Alphabet! |author=Mark Liberman |work=[[Slate (magazine)|Slate]] |date=2013-10-24 |access-date=2013-10-25 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Turkey began to allow private television channels to broadcast in Kurdish on a limited basis in 2006,&lt;ref&gt;[http://english.aljazeera.net/NR/exeres/D4687417-BAB7-426A-9F30-8D16A9DEE206.htm Turkey to get Kurdish television] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20060513082443/http://english.aljazeera.net/NR/exeres/D4687417-BAB7-426A-9F30-8D16A9DEE206.htm |date=13 May 2006 }}&lt;/ref&gt; with most restrictions lifted by 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.trt.net.tr/Haber/HaberDetay.aspx?HaberKodu=139bfcf2-18ef-46b2-937b-010ad9411f0f |title=TRT HABER - Özel Kürtçe Kanala Yeşil Işık |publisher=Trt.net.tr |date=28 November 2011 |access-date=2 December 2011 |url-status=live |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120118223608/http://www.trt.net.tr/Haber/HaberDetay.aspx?HaberKodu=139bfcf2-18ef-46b2-937b-010ad9411f0f |archive-date=18 January 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The state-run Turkish Radio and Television Corporation (TRT) started its [[TRT Kurdî|24-hour Kurdish television station]] in 2009, with full use of the letters ''Q'', ''W'', and ''X''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.kurdmedia.com/article.aspx?id=15316 |title=Kurdish TV starts broadcasting in Turkey |publisher=Kurdmedia.com |access-date=2 December 2011 |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120112035549/http://www.kurdmedia.com/article.aspx?id=15316 |archive-date=12 January 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2010, Kurdish municipalities in the southeast began printing [[marriage certificate]]s, water bills, construction and [[road sign]]s, as well as emergency, social and cultural notices in Kurdish alongside Turkish. Also, Imams began to deliver Friday [[Khutbah|sermons]] in Kurdish and [[Esnaf]] price tags in Kurdish.  In 2012, Kurdish-language lessons became an elective subject in public schools. Previously, Kurdish education had only been possible in private institutions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Turkey to allow Kurdish lessons in schools|url=http://www.aljazeera.com/news/europe/2012/06/2012612133656956705.html|access-date=12 June 2013|newspaper=Aljazeera|date=12 June 2012|url-status=live|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130313145427/http://www.aljazeera.com/news/europe/2012/06/2012612133656956705.html|archive-date=13 March 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== In Asia ===

* Suppression of [[Korean language|Korean]] during [[Korea under Japanese rule|Japanese rule in Korea]], 1910 to 1945.

*[[Anti-Chinese legislation in Indonesia]]

* The brutality and linguicism against Tamils in Sri Lanka which took thousands of Tamil lives because of their language. This was rooted from "[[Sinhala Only Act#cite note-Consolidated Acts-1|The Sinhala Only Act]]", formerly the Official Language Act No. 33 of 1956, that was passed in the Parliament of Ceylon in 1956. [[Black July]] was the peak of the violence against Tamils in 1983.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Haviland|first=Charles|url=https://www.bbc.com/news/world-asia-23402727|title=Remembering Sri Lanka's Black July|date=23 July 2013|access-date=7 May 2018|publisher=BBC}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*China: In the 2000s the Chinese government began promoting the use of [[Mandarin Chinese]] in areas where [[Cantonese]] is spoken. In 2010 this gave rise to the [[Guangzhou Television Cantonese controversy]]. This has also been a point of contention with [[Hong Kong]], which is located in the general area where Cantonese is spoken. Cantonese has become a means of asserting Hong Kong's political identity as separate from mainland China.

*After the [[Kuomintang]] retreated to [[Taiwan]] following the [[Chinese Civil War]], the Nationalist government promoted [[Mandarin Chinese|Mandarin]] and banned the public use of [[Taiwanese Hokkien|Taiwanese]] and other native languages as part of a deliberate political repression, especially in schools and broadcast media.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Sandel|first=Todd L.|year=2003|title=Linguistic capital in Taiwan: The KMT's Mandarin language policy and its perceived impact on language practices of bilingual Mandarin and Tai-gi speakers|journal=Language in Society|publisher=Cambridge University Press|volume=32|issue=4|pages=523–551|doi=10.1017/S0047404503324030|jstor=4169285|s2cid=145703339}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1964 use of Taiwanese in schools or official settings was forbidden,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Lin|first=Alvin|year=1999|title=Writing Taiwanese: The Development of Modern Written Taiwanese|url=http://www.sino-platonic.org/complete/spp089_taiwanese.pdf|journal=Sino-Platonic Papers|issue=89|oclc=41879041}}&lt;/ref&gt; and transgression in schools punished with beatings, fines and humiliation. This discrimination started to decrease and ended when [[Martial law in Taiwan|martial law]] ended in 1987.

*[[Bengali language movement]] occurred in a move to recognise [[Bengali language|Bengali]] as an [[official language]] in the then-[[Dominion of Pakistan]] of 1947.

*Kannada supremacism widely known as "activism" is common in [[Karnataka]] and enjoys political support. It forces all residents including those from outside Karnataka to speak [[Kannada]].

*Marathi superamacy in [[Maharashtra]] (mainly [[Mumbai]]) perpuated by [[Ultranationalism|ultranationalist]] regional [[Nativism (politics)|nativist]] parties like [[Shiv Sena]] and [[Maharashtra Navnirman Sena|MNS]] which labelled immigrants as 'job stealers' and 'outsiders', with South Indian [[Kannada people|Kannadigas]] and [[Tulu people|Tuluvas]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|first=Chander |last=Uday Singh|date=March 31, 1981|title=Maharashtra-Karnataka border morcha by Shiv Sena seen as an attempt to reaffirm its sagging image|url=https://www.indiatoday.in/magazine/indiascope/story/19810331-maharashtra-karnataka-border-morcha-by-shiv-sena-seen-as-an-attempt-to-reaffirm-its-sagging-image-772789-2013-11-25|access-date=2022-01-13|website=India Today|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; becoming the target of [[Bal Thackeray]]'s racist slurs and attack&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite magazine|author=Dipankar Gupta |date=November 30, 1999 |title=Why no one dared to mess with Shiv Sena?|url=https://www.indiatoday.in/magazine/special-report/story/20121203-bal-thackeray-death-shiv-sena-harvester-of-fear-760815-1999-11-30|access-date=2022-01-13|magazine=India Today|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; by Marathi goons who prided on their 'Marathi Manoos' &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Rampal|first=Nitish|date=2018-12-27|title=Thing Is, Thackeray Really Was As Hateful As the Trailer Suggests|url=https://www.thequint.com/news/india/bal-thackeray-biopic-marathi-pride|access-date=2022-01-13|website=TheQuint|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; status. Subsequently Bihari,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite magazine|date=September 4, 2012 |title=Uddhav takes Raj's hate campaign forward, wants permit system for Biharis in Mumbai|url=https://www.indiatoday.in/india/west/story/uddhav-thackeray-raj-thackeray-biharis-living-in-maharashtra-115148-2012-09-04|access-date=2022-01-13|magazine=India Today|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=Shiv Sena sharpens attack on North Indians, says they are uninvited|work=The Economic Times|url=https://economictimes.indiatimes.com/news/politics-and-nation/shiv-sena-sharpens-attack-on-north-indians-says-they-are-uninvited/articleshow/10593550.cms?from=mdr|access-date=2022-01-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; Gujarati  and other North Indian communities were targeted and attacked [[2008 attacks on Uttar Pradeshi and Bihari migrants in Maharashtra|resulting in an exodus in 2008]]. Till date, there have been sporadic attacks and discrimination towards non-Marathi communities in Mumbai.

*Imposition of [[Hindi]] by the Indian Government on non-Hindi speaking states, especially that of [[South India]] has led to anti Hindi agitations in states like [[Gokak agitation|Karnataka]] and [[Anti-Hindi agitations of Tamil Nadu|Tamil Nadu]]. The prioritization of Hindi in non-Hindi speaking states has led to discrimination towards people who do not know Hindi.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|date=2021-10-05|title=Hindi imposition in the banking sector has left Kannadigas disadvantaged|url=https://www.thenewsminute.com/article/hindi-imposition-banking-sector-has-left-kannadigas-disadvantaged-156101|access-date=2022-01-13|website=The News Minute|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Texts===

Linguicism applies to [[written language|written]], [[spoken language|spoken]], or [[Sign language|signed languages]].  The quality of a book or article may be judged by the language in which it is written.  In the scientific community, for example, those who evaluated a text in two language versions, English and the national [[Scandinavian language]], rated the English-language version as being of higher scientific content.&lt;ref&gt;Jenkins, Jennifer (2003). ''World Englishes: A Resource Book for Students'', p. 200. Routledge. {{ISBN|0-415-25805-7}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Internet]] operates a great deal using written language.  Readers of a [[web page]], [[Usenet]] group, [[internet forum|forum]] post, or chat session may be more inclined to take the author seriously if the language is written in accordance with the standard language.

===Prejudice===

In contrast to the previous examples of linguistic prejudice, linguistic discrimination involves the actual treatment of individuals based on use of language. Examples may be clearly seen in the workplace, in marketing, and in education systems. For example, some workplaces enforce an [[English-only movement|English-only]] policy, which is part of an American political movement that pushes for English to be accepted as the official language. In the United States, the federal law, Titles VI and VII of the [[Civil Rights Act of 1964]] protects non-native speakers from discrimination in the workplace based on their national origin or use of dialect. There are state laws which also address the protection of non-native speakers, such as the California Fair Employment and Housing Act. However, industries often argue in retrospect that clear, understandable English is often needed in specific work settings in the U.S.&lt;ref name="aclunc.org" /&gt;

==See also ==

{{div col|colwidth=22em}}
* [[Linguistic insecurity]]
* [[Schizoglossia]]
* [[Standard language ideology]]
* [[Cultural assimilation]]
* [[Cultural genocide]]
* [[Criticism of Esperanto]]
* [[Indigenous language]]
* [[Language death]]
* [[Language ideology]]
* [[Language policy]]
* [[Linguistic imperialism]]
* [[Linguistic profiling]]
* [[Linguistic racism]]
* [[Minoritized language]]
* [[Minority language]]
* [[Monolingualism]]
* [[Nonstandard dialect]]
* [[Official language]]
* [[Linguistic prescription|Linguistic prescriptivism]]
* [[Prestige (sociolinguistics)]]
* [[Economics of language]]
* [[Raciolinguistics]]
{{div col end}}

==Notes==
{{notelist}}

==References==

* {{citation|last=Skutnabb-Kangas|first=Tove|year=1988|title=Multilingualism and the education of minority children.}}
{{Reflist}}

==Literature==
*Skutnabb-Kangas et al. (eds.), ''Linguistic human rights: overcoming linguistic discrimination'', Walter de Gruyter (1995), {{ISBN|3-11-014878-1}}.
*R. Wodak and D. Corson (eds.), ''Language policy and political issues in education'', Springer, {{ISBN|0-7923-4713-7}}.

==External links==

*[http://www.linguistic-rights.org/en/Violations_of_Linguistic_Rights.html Action Linguistic Rights: Violations of Linguistic Rights]

{{Discrimination}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Linguistic Discrimination}}
[[Category:Linguistic discrimination| ]]
[[Category:Discrimination by type]]
[[Category:Sociolinguistics]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>