<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20131027021132|578901019" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="18089868" pageid="18089868" ns="0" title="Linguistic discrimination"><revisions><rev timestamp="2013-10-28T22:26:05Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{redirect-distinguish|Linguicist|Linguist}}
{{Discrimination sidebar}}

'''Linguistic discrimination''' (also called '''linguicism''' and '''languagism''') is the unfair treatment of an individual based solely on their use of language. This use of language may include the individual's native language or other characteristics of the person's speech, such as an [[Accent (dialect)|accent]], the size of [[vocabulary]] (whether the person uses complex and varied [[word]]s), and [[syntax]]. It may also involve a person's ability or inability to use one language instead of another; for example, one who speaks [[Japanese language|Japanese]] in [[France]] will probably be treated differently from one who speaks [[French language|French]].&lt;ref name="aclunc.org"&gt;The Legal Aid Society-Employment Law Center, &amp; the ACLU Foundation of North California (2002). Language Discrimination: Your Legal Rights. http://www.aclunc.org/library/publications/asset_upload_file489_3538.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; Based on a difference in use of language, a person may automatically form judgments about another person's [[wealth]], [[education]], [[social status]], character, and/or other traits. These perceived judgments may then lead to the unjustifiable treatment of the individual.

In the mid-1980s, [[linguistics|Linguist]] Tove Skutnabb-Kangas, captured this idea of discrimination based on language as the concept of linguicism. Kangas defined linguicism as the "ideologies and structures which are used to legitimate, effectuate, and reproduce unequal division of power and resources (both material and non-material) between groups which are defined on the basis of language."&lt;ref&gt;Quoted in Skutnabb-Kangas, Tove, and Phillipson, Robert, "'Mother Tongue': The Theoretical and Sociopolitical Construction of a Concept." In Ammon, Ulrich (ed.) (1989). ''Status and Function of Languages and Language Varieties'', p. 455. Berlin, New York: Walter de Gruyter &amp; Co. ISBN 3-11-011299-X.&lt;/ref&gt; Although different names have been given to this form of discrimination, they all hold the same definition. It is also important to note that linguistic discrimination is culturally and socially determined due to a preference for one use of language over another.

==Linguistic Prejudice==

It can be noted that use of language such as certain accents may result in an individual experiencing prejudice. For example, some accents hold more prestige than others depending on the cultural context. However, with so many dialects, it can be difficult to determine which is the most preferable. The best answer linguists can give, such as the authors of [http://www.randomhouse.com/doubleday/doyouspeak/ "Do You Speak American?"], is that it depends on the location and the individual. Research has determined however that some sounds in languages may be determined to sound less pleasant naturally.&lt;ref&gt;Bresnahan, M. J., Ohashi, R., Nebashi, R., Liu, W. Y., &amp; Shearman, S. M. (2002). Attitudinal and affective response toward accented English. Language and Communication, 22, 171–185.&lt;/ref&gt; Also, certain accents tend to carry more prestige in some societies over other accents. For example, in the United States, an absence of an accent or [http://www.pbs.org/speak/speech/ "speaking American"] is widely preferable. Also, in the United Kingdom, the [[Received Pronunciation]] is associated with being of higher class and thus more likeable.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.indiana.edu/~hlw/PhonProcess/accents.html&lt;/ref&gt; In addition to prestige, research has shown that certain accents may also be associated with less intelligence, and having poorer social skills.&lt;ref&gt;Bradac, J. J. (1990). Language attitudes and impression formation. In H. Giles &amp; W. P. Robinson (Eds.), Handbook of language and social psychology (pp. 387–412). London: John Wiley.&lt;/ref&gt; An example can be seen in the difference between Southerners and Northerners in the United States, where people from the North are typically perceived as being less likable in character, and Southerners are perceived as being less intelligent.

==Language and Social Group Saliency==

It is natural for human beings to want to identify with others. One way we do this is by categorizing individuals into specific [[Social identity theory|social groups]]. While some groups may be readily noticeable (such as those defined by race or gender), other groups are less [[Salience (language)|salient]]. Linguist [http://www.pbs.org/speak/speech/ Carmen Fought] explains how an individual's use of language may allow another person to categorize them into a specific social group that may otherwise be less apparent. For example, in the United States it is common to perceive Southerners as less intelligent. Belonging to a social group such as the South may be less salient than membership to other groups that are defined by race or gender. Language provides a bridge for prejudice to occur for these less salient social groups.&lt;ref&gt;Jaspal, R. (2009). Language and social identity: a psychosocial approach.  Psych-Talk, 64, 17-20.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Examples of Linguistic Discrimination==
Linguistic discrimination is often defined in terms of prejudice of language. It is important to note that although there is a relationship between prejudice and discrimination, they are not always directly related.&lt;ref&gt;Schütz, H., &amp; Six, B. (1996). How strong is the relationship between prejudice and discrimination? A meta-analytic answer. International Journal of Intercultural Relations, 20(3–4): pp. 441-462.&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Prejudice]] can be defined as negative attitudes towards an individual based solely on their membership of a social group, while [[discrimination]] can be seen as the acts towards the individual. The difference between the two should be recognized because an individual may hold a prejudice against someone due to their use of language, but they may not act out on that prejudice.&lt;ref&gt;Whitley, B.E., &amp; Kite, M.E. (2010)The Psychology of Prejudice and Discrimination. Ed 2. pp.379-383. Cencage Learning: Belmont.&lt;/ref&gt; The following are examples of linguistic prejudice that may result in discrimination.

===Linguistic Prejudice and Minority Groups===
While, theoretically, any individual may be the victim of linguicism regardless of social and ethnic status, oppressed and marginalized social minorities are often its most consistent targets, due to the fact that the speech varieties that come to be associated with such groups have a tendency to be stigmatized.

===In Canada===

====Quebec and Anglo Community====

The [[Charter of the French Language]], first established in 1977 and amended several times since, has been accused of being discriminatory by English speakers. The law makes French the official language of Quebec and mandates its use (with exceptions) in government offices and communiques, schools, and in commercial public relations. Though the proportion of English speakers had been in decline since the 1960s, the law accelerated this, and the 2006 census showed there had been a net drop of 180,000 native English speakers.&lt;ref name="collectiverightsquebec"&gt;Richard Y. Bourhis &amp; Pierre Foucher 
, [http://qcgn.squarespace.com/storage/website-resources/library/documents/national-assembly/Bill%20103%20Impact%20Study%20Collective%20Rights%20and%20Vitality%202011.01.05.pdf "Bill 103: Collective Rights and the declining vitality of the English-speaking communities of Quebec "], ''Canadian Institute for Research on Linguistic Minorities'', Version 3, November 25, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

Conversely, the law has been seen as a way of combating ''preventing'' linguistic discrimination against French speakers, as part of the law's wider objective of preserving the French language against the increasing social and economic dominance of English. Speaking English at work continues to be strongly correlated with higher earnings, with French-only speakers earning significantly less.&lt;ref&gt;Louis N. Christofides &amp; Robert Swidinsky, [http://utpjournals.metapress.com/content/p0w06tr200310861/fulltext.pdf "The Economic Returns to the Knowledge and Use of a Second Official Language: English in Quebec and French in the Rest-of-Canada"], ''Canadian Public Policy – Analyse de Politiques Vol. XXXVI'', No. 2 2010 
&lt;/ref&gt; Despite this, the law is widely credited with successfully raising the status of French in a predominantly English-speaking economy, and has been influential in other countries facing similar circumstances.&lt;ref name="collectiverightsquebec"/&gt;

===In the United States===

====African-Americans and linguicism====
Because some African-Americans speak a particular non-standard variety of English which is often seen as substandard, African-Americans are frequently the targets of linguicism. [[African American Vernacular English]] (AAVE) is often perceived by members of mainstream American society as indicative of low intelligence or limited education. Furthermore, as with many other non-standard dialects and especially creoles, AAVE sometimes has been called "lazy" or "bad" English.

The linguist [[John McWhorter]] has described this particular form of linguicism as particularly problematic in the United States, where non-standard linguistic structures are frequently judged by teachers and potential employers to be "incorrect," in contrast to a number of other countries such as Morocco, Finland and Italy where [[diglossia]] (a single person being able to switch between two or more dialects or languages) is an accepted norm, and use of non-standard grammar or vocabulary in conversation is seen as a mark of regional origin, not of intellectual capacity or achievement.

For example, an African-American who uses a typical AAVE sentence such as "He be comin' in every day and sayin' he ain't done nothing" may be judged as having a deficient command of grammar, whereas, in fact, such a sentence is constructed based on a complex grammar which is different from, and not a degenerate form of, standard English.&lt;ref&gt;Dicker, Susan J. (2nd ed., 2003). ''Languages in America: A Pluralist View'', pp. 7-8. Multilingual Matters Ltd. ISBN 1-85359-651-5.&lt;/ref&gt; A hearer may judge the user of such a sentence to be unintellectual or uneducated when none of these is necessarily the case. The user may be proficient in standard English, and may be intellectually capable, and educated but simply have chosen to say the sentence in AAVE for any one of a number of social and sociolinguistic reasons such as the intended audience of the sentence, a phenomenon known as [[Code-switching|code switching]].

====Hispanic Americans and linguicism====
Another form of linguicism is evidenced by the following: in some parts of the [[United States of America|United States]], a person who has a strong [[Mexico|Mexican]] accent and uses only simple [[English language|English]] words may be thought of as poor, poorly educated, and possibly an [[illegal immigrant]] by many of the people who meet them. However, if the same person has a diluted accent or no noticeable accent at all and can use a myriad of words in complex sentences, they are likely to be perceived as more successful, better educated, and a legitimate [[citizen]].

===Oralism===
In 1880, most [[deaf education|deaf schools]] (where [[sign languages]] are transmitted from children from deaf families to the children from non-signing hearing families) had adopted [[oralism]], an educational philosophy which prohibits the use of [[sign languages]] in favor of  [[oral language]]. Many sign languages had all but become extinct during this time sometimes called by Deaf people as the "Deaf Dark Ages." In 1960s, the United States became the first major country to switch back to [[manualism]]. Unfortunately, even today, many first-world nations retain [[oralist]] educational philosophies and attitudes.

===Linguicism and texts===

Linguicism, of course, applies to [[written language|written]] as well as [[spoken language]].  The quality of a book or article may be judged by the language in which it is written.  In the scientific community, for example, those who evaluated a text in two language versions, English and the national [[Scandinavian language]], rated the English-language version as being of higher scientific content.&lt;ref&gt;Jenkins, Jennifer (2003). ''World Englishes: A Resource Book for Students'', p. 200. Routledge. ISBN 0-415-25805-7.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Internet]] operates a great deal using written language.  Readers of a [[web page]], [[Usenet]] group, [[internet forum|forum]] post, or chat session may be more inclined to take the author seriously if the written language is spelled and constructed in accordance with the written norms of the standard language.

===Linguistic discrimination due to prejudice===
In contrast to the previous examples of linguistic prejudice, linguistic discrimination involves the actual treatment of individuals based on use of language. Examples may be clearly seen in the workplace, in the advertising industry, and in education systems. For example, some workplaces enforce an [[English-only movement|English-only policy]]. This policy is part of a larger political movement in the U.S. where English is being pushed towards being accepted as the official language of the U.S. In the United States, the federal law, Titles VI and VII of the Civil Rights Act of 1964 protects non-native speakers from being discriminated against in the workplace based on their national origin or use of dialect. There are state laws that also address the protection of non-native speaker, such as the California Fair Employment and Housing Act. However, industries often argue in retrospect that clear, understandable English is often needed in specific work settings in the U.S.&lt;ref name="aclunc.org"/&gt;

==Other Examples==
*The [[Coptic language]].  At the turn of the 8th century, [[Caliph]] [[Abd al-Malik ibn Marwan]] decreed that [[Arabic language|Arabic]] replace [[Koine Greek]] and Coptic as the sole administrative language. Literary Coptic gradually declined such that within a few hundred years, and suffered violent persecutions especially  under the [[Mamluk]]s, leading to its virtual extinction by the 17th century.
*Language policy of the British Empire in [[Ireland]], [[Wales]] and [[Scotland]]. [[Oliver Cromwell|Cromwell]]'s conquest, the long [[Plantations of Ireland|English colonisation]] and [[Great Irish Famine]] made [[Irish language|Irish]] a minority language by the end of 19th century. It had not official status until the establishment of [[Republic of Ireland]]. In Wales speaking of the [[Welsh language]] in schools was [[Welsh Not|prohibited]]. [[Scottish Gaelic]] also had not official status until [[Languages in the United Kingdom#Status|the end of 20th century]]. [[Scots language|Scots]] was not considered ''"a suitable medium of education or culture"''.&lt;ref&gt;Primary education: a report of the Advisory Council on Education in Scotland, Scottish Education Deptartment 1946, p. 75&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Basque language|Basque]]: [[Language policies of Francoist Spain|Public usage]] of Basque was prohibited in [[Spain under Franco]], 1939 to 1965. [[Galician language|Galician]] and [[Catalan language|Catalan]] have similar histories.
*[[Kurdish language|Kurdish]]: Kurdish remains banned in [[Syria]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.amnesty.org/wire/March2005/Syria Repression of Kurds in Syria is widespread], [[Amnesty International]] Report, March 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; Until August 2002, the [[Turkish government]] placed severe restrictions on the use of Kurdish, prohibiting the language in education and broadcast media&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.amnestyusa.org/action/special/zana.html Special Focus Cases: Leyla Zana, Prisoner of Conscience]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.freemuse.org/sw6195.asp Kurdish performers banned, Appeal from International PEN]&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Vergonha]] is the term used for the effect of various policies of the [[French government]] on its citizens whose mother tongue was one of so-called patois. In 1539 with Article 111 of the [[Ordinance of Villers-Cotterêts]], [[French language|French]] (the language of [[Ile-de-France]]) became the only official language in the country. Use of the languages of southern France ([[langues d'oc]]) as well as [[Breton language|Breton]] in education and administration was prohibited. The French government has not ratified the [[European Charter for Regional or Minority Languages]].
*[[Germanisation]]: [[Prussia]]n discrimination of [[Western Slavs]] in 19th century, such as the removal of the [[Polish language]] from secondary (1874) and primary (1886) schools, the use of [[School corporal punishment|corporal punishment]] leading to such events as [[Wrze%C5%9Bnia#Wrze.C5.9Bnia school strike of 1901|Września school strike of 1901]].
*[[Russification]]: [[Russification#Poland and Lithuania|19th century policies]] on the territories seized due to [[partitions of the Polish-Lithuanian Commonwealth]], such as banning the Polish, Lithuanian and [[Belarusian language]]s in public places (1864), later (1880s) Polish was banned in schools and offices of [[Congress Poland]]. Under the [[Russian Empire]] there were some [[Russification of Finland|attempts]] in 1899-1917 to make [[Russian language|Russian]]  the only official language of [[Finland]]{{Citation needed|date=July 2012}}. In the [[Soviet Union]], following the phase of [[Korenizatsiya]] ("indigenization") and before [[Perestroika]] (late 1930s to late 1980s), Russian was termed as "the language of friendship of nations", to the disadvantage of other [[languages of the Soviet Union]]{{Citation needed|date=July 2012}}
*Suppression of [[Korean language|Korean]] during [[Korea under Japanese rule|Japanese rule in Korea]], 1910 to 1945.
*[[Quebec]]'s [[Charter of the French Language|language policies]] have been frequently noted as linguistic discrimination against the province's Anglophone population (see [[Legal dispute over Quebec's language policy]]).
*[[Anti-Chinese legislation in Indonesia]]
*Anti-Hungarian Slovak language law
*Dutch in Belgium afters its independence in 1830. French was for a long time the only official language and the sole language of education, administration, law and justice despite Dutch being the language of the majority of the population. This led to a massive [[Francisation of Brussels|language shift in Brussels]], the capital. Discrimination slowly diminished over the decades and formally ended in the 1960s when the Dutch version of the constitution became equal to the French version.

==See also==
* [[Linguicide]]
* [[Linguistic imperialism]]
* [[Minority language]]
* [[Nonstandard dialect]]
* [[Prestige dialect]]
* [[Language ideology]]
* [[Language policy]]
* [[Prescriptivism]]

*[[Indigenous language]]
*[[Official language]]
*[[Cultural assimilation]]
*[[Cultural genocide]]

==References==
* {{citation|last=Skutnabb-Kangas|first=Tove|year=1988|title=Multilingualism and the education of minority children.}}
{{Reflist}}

==Literature==
*Skutnabb-Kangas et al. (eds.), ''Linguistic human rights: overcoming linguistic discrimination'', Walter de Gruyter (1995), ISBN 3-11-014878-1.
*R. Wodak and D. Corson (eds.), ''Language policy and political issues in education'', Springer, ISBN 0-7923-4713-7.

==External links==
*[http://www.linguistic-rights.org/en/Violations_of_Linguistic_Rights.html   Action Linguistic Rights: Violations of Linguistic Rights]

{{Discrimination}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Linguistic Discrimination}}
[[Category:Prejudices]]
[[Category:Sociolinguistics]]
[[Category:Dispositional beliefs]]
[[Category:Linguistic discrimination| ]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>