<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20161120165748|750578576" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="48497947" pageid="48497947" ns="0" title="Fourth-wave feminism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2016-11-20T16:58:13Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Feminism sidebar |history}}
The '''fourth wave of feminism''' might be a recent development within the feminist movement. The definition and boundaries of the term are currently much contested. In 2005, Pythia Peay first argued for the existence of a fourth wave of feminism, combining justice with [[thealogy|religious spirituality]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | last=Peay | first= Pythia | title =Feminism's fourth wave | work =[[Utne Reader]] | issue = 128 | date = March–April 2005 | pages =59–60 | url = http://www.utne.com/community/feminisms-fourth-wave.aspx}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, this spiritual component is not present in most other definitions for the term, which tend instead to focus on technological components. [[Jennifer Baumgardner]] identifies '''fourth-wave feminism''' as starting in 2008 and continuing into the present day.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.feminist.com/resources/artspeech/genwom/baumgardner2011.html|title=Is there a fourth wave? Does it matter?|last=Baumgardner|first=Jennifer|date=2011|website=Feminist.com|publisher=|access-date=21 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; In her view fourth-wave feminism was inspired partly by [[Take Our Daughters and Sons to Work Day|Take Our Daughters to Work Day]]s, incorporates online resources such as [[social media]], in turn inspired the Doula Project for children's services and inspired after-abortion talk lines, pursuit of [[reproductive justice]], [[plus-size clothing|plus-size]] fashion support, [[transgenderism (social movement)|transgenderism]] support, male feminism, and [[sex work]] acceptance; and led to developing media including [[Feministing]], Racialicious, [[blog]]s, and [[Twitter]] campaigns.&lt;ref&gt;Baumgardner, Jennifer, ''F'em!'', ''op. cit.'', pp.&amp;nbsp;250–251.&lt;/ref&gt; Researcher Diana Diamond defines fourth-wave feminism as a movement that "combines [[politics]], [[psychology]], and [[spirituality]] in an overarching vision of change." &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The fourth wave of feminism: psychoanalytic perspectives|last=Diamond|first=Diana|publisher=|year=2009|isbn=|location=|pages=213–223}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Kira Cochrane]], author of '' All the Rebel Women: The Rise of the Fourth Wave of Feminism'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Cochrane|first=Kira|author-link=Kira Cochrane | title = All the rebel women: the rise of the fourth wave of feminism | publisher = Guardian Books | location = London | url = https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/19387670-all-the-rebel-women | year = 2013 | oclc = 915373287 | isbn = 9781783560363 }}&lt;/ref&gt; defines fourth-wave feminism as a movement that is connected through technology.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=F 'em!: Goo Goo, Gaga, and Some Thoughts on Balls|last=Baumgardner|first=Jennifer|publisher=Seal Press|year=2011|isbn=|location=Berkeley CA|pages=250}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/dec/10/fourth-wave-feminism-rebel-women|title=The fourth wave of feminism: meet the rebel women|last=Cochrane|first=Kira|author-link=Kira Cochrane|date=10 December 2013|website=The Guardian|publisher=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt; In a 2009 interview with the [[The New York Times|New York Times]], feminist author and icon [[Jessica Valenti]] was asked whether or not she considered herself a [[Third-wave feminism|third wave feminist]]. Her response was as follows: "I don’t much like the terminology, because it never seems very accurate to me. I know people who are considered third-wave feminists who are 20 years older than me." After the interviewer's suggestion that perhaps we had moved forward into a fourth wave of feminism, Valenti stated that maybe the fourth wave was online.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2009/11/15/magazine/15fob-q4-t.html|title=The Blogger and Author on the Life of Women Online|last=Solomon|first=Deborah|date=13 November 2009|work=[[The New York Times]]|access-date=16 March 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Fourth-wave feminism is often associated with online feminism, especially using [[Facebook]], [[Twitter]], [[Instagram]], [[YouTube]], [[Tumblr]], and other forms of [[social media]] to discuss, uplift, and activate [[gender equality]] and [[social justice]].&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://bcrw.barnard.edu/wp-content/nfs/reports/NFS8-FemFuture-Online-Revolution-Report-April-15-2013.pdf|title=#FEMFUTURE: Online revolution|last=Martin, Valenti|first=Courtney E, Vanessa|date=|website=BRCW|publisher=Barnard Centre for Research on Women (BCRW)|access-date=21 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to [[National Organization for Women|NOW]] Toronto, the internet has created a "call-out" culture, in which [[sexism]] or [[misogyny]] can be called out and challenged immediately with relative ease.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://nowtoronto.com/news/feminisms-fourth-wave-is-the-shitlist/|title=FEMINISM’S FOURTH WAVE IS THE SHITLIST|last=Zerbisias|first=Antonia|date=16 September 2015|website=NOW Toronto|publisher=|access-date=21 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; This culture is indicative of the continuing influence of the third wave, with its focus on micro-politics and challenging sexism and misogyny insofar as they appear in everyday rhetoric, advertising, film, television and literature, the media, and so on.&lt;ref name="Munro"&gt;{{Cite journal | last = Munro | first = Ealasaid | title = Feminism: a fourth wave? | journal = Political Insight | volume = 4 | issue = 2 | pages = 22–25 | publisher = [[Political Studies Association]] via [[Sage Publications|Sage]] | doi = 10.1111/2041-9066.12021 | date = September 2013 | url = http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/2041-9066.12021 | ref = harv | postscript = .}} [http://www.readcube.com/articles/10.1111/2041-9066.12021 Pdf via ReadCube.] Also available [https://www.psa.ac.uk/insight-plus/feminism-fourth-wave online].&lt;/ref&gt; This online feminism aspect of the fourth wave has impacted how companies market to women so that they are not "called out" for sexism in their marketing strategies.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.packagingnews.co.uk/features/comment/soapbox/how-to-package-brands-for-the-fourth-wave-of-feminism-alex-hamilton-28-10-2015|title=How to package brands for the fourth wave of feminism|last=Hamilton|first=Alex|date=28 October 2015|website=Packaging News|publisher=|access-date=21 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Though the fourth wave of feminism often draws comparisons to the [[Third-wave feminism|third wave of feminism]], as with the past waves of feminism and their successors, fourth-wave feminism stands "on the shoulders" of the past wave. The addition of more advanced technology along with broader ideas of equal rights set the newest wave apart from the former.

Besides online feminism, the fourth wave has been associated with the increased focus on [[intersectionality]], including the repudiation of trans-exclusionary radical feminism and a focus on solidarity with other social justice movements.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;

Another aspect of fourth-wave feminism is the presence of individuals who are uncomfortable with the word ''feminism'', because of "assumptions of a [[gender binary]] and exclusionary subtext: 'For women only,'" according to Martha Rampton, director of the Centre for Gender Equality at [[Pacific University|Pacific University Oregon]]. "Yet the word is winning the day," she wrote in 2015 &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.pacificu.edu/about-us/news-events/four-waves-feminism|title=Four waves of feminism|last=Rampton|first=Martha|date=25 October 2015|website=Pacific University Oregon|publisher=|access-date=21 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Fourth-wave feminism and media ==
In 2014, Rhiannon Lucy Cosslett and Holly Baxter released their book ''The Vagenda.'' The authors consider themselves fourth-wave feminists. Like their website "The Vagenda", their book aims to flag and debunk the stereotypes of femininity promoted by the mainstream women's press.&lt;ref&gt;http://vagendamagazine.com/about/&lt;/ref&gt; One reviewer of the book has expressed disappointment with ''The Vagenda'', saying that instead of being the "call to arms for young women" that it purports to be, it reads like a joyless dissertation detailing "everything bad the media has ever done to women."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Sanghani|first=Radhika|title=My generation of feminists is depressing me|url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/women/womens-life/10773101/My-generation-of-feminists-is-depressing-me.html|accessdate=12 May 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In November 2015, a group of historians working with Clio Visualizing History  launched ''Click! The Ongoing Feminist Revolution.'' This digital history exhibit examines the history of American feminism from the era of World War Two to the present. The exhibit has three major sections: Politics and Social Movements; Body and Health; and Workplace and Family. There are also interactive timelines linking to a vast array of sources documenting the history of American feminism and providing information about current feminist activism.

== Fourth-wave feminism and technology ==
The fourth wave of feminism is often said to have started in 2008,&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; and many social networks were finding their footing not long beforehand. [[Twitter]], a social network that is most popular with the 18-29 age group,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Brodzky|first=Brandon|url=https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/20141118182103-28964915-social-media-user-statistics-age-demographics-for-2014|title=Social Media User Statistics &amp; Age Demographics for 2014|date=18 November 2014|website=LinkedIn Pulse|access-date=16 March 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; was created in 2006, and has made feminism more accessible to the general public. When [[Wendy Davis (politician)|Wendy Davis]] staged her 13-hour [[Filibuster in the United States Senate|filibuster]] to prevent an abortion bill from passing, many women showed their support by rallying around the [[Texas State Capitol]]. But for those who couldn't, they were still able to show their solidarity through using the [[hashtag]] #StandWithWendy. Similarly, girls of all ages protested the often sexist questions directed at female celebrities by tweeting the hashtag #askhermore.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Chittal|first=Nisha|url=http://www.msnbc.com/msnbc/how-social-media-changing-the-feminist-movement|title=How social media is changing the feminist movement|website=MSNBC|date=26 March 2015|access-date=16 March 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; While some may mock this relatively new concept of Twitter activism and call it a cop-out,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Guardado|first=Alex|url=http://www.newuniversity.org/2015/03/opinion/hashtag-activism-the-benefits-and-limitations-of-activism/|title=Hashtag Activism: The Benefits and Limitations of #Activism|website=New University|language=en-US|date=3 March 2015|access-date=16 March 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; it can also be seen as a way to get more young girls involved in issues, and a means to give women a voice when they would otherwise be silent. Social media like Twitter allows women to spread awareness of issues much farther than was ever possible in the past.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://time.com/3319081/whyistayed-hashtag-feminism-activism/|title=Behold the power of #hashtag feminism|last=Bennett|first=Jessica|date=10 September 2014|website=Time|publisher=|access-date=21 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although neither technology nor feminism are new to the world, the efficient and fervent use of them in unison is a defining factor of the fourth wave.

== Fourth-wave feminism and sexuality ==
In 2014, [[Betty Dodson]], who is also acknowledged as one of the leaders of the early 1980s [[Sex-positive feminism|pro-sex feminist]] movement, expressed that she considers herself a fourth wave feminist. Dodson expressed that the previous waves of feminist were banal and anti-sexual, which is why she has chosen to look at a new stance of feminism, fourth wave feminism. In 2014, Dodson worked with women to discover their sexual desires through masturbation. Dodson says her work has gained a fresh lease on life with a new audience of young, successful women who have never had an orgasm. This includes fourth-wave feminists - those rejecting the anti-pleasure stance they believe third-wave feminists stand for.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Smith|first=Lydia|title=Betty Dodson and Fourth-Wave Feminism: Masturbation is Key to Longer Life|url=http://www.ibtimes.co.uk/betty-dodson-fourth-wave-feminism-masturbation-key-longer-life-1447536|accessdate=12 May 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== The Fourth Wave Feminist Summit at Yale ==

[[File:WClogo5.png|thumb|Logo of the Fourth Wave Feminist Summit at Yale, 2015]]

The Fourth Wave Feminist Summit was a conference of feminist organizations from colleges across the Northeast United States including [[Middlebury College|Middlebury]], [[Barnard College|Barnard]], [[Quinnipiac University|Quinnipiac]], [[University of Pennsylvania|UPenn]], [[Bates College|Bates]], and [[Cornell University|Cornell]]. In this three day conference organized by [http://womenscenter.yale.edu/ The Women's Center] at [[Yale University]], college representatives shared their strategies on activism and discussed ways to improve solidarity across campus movements. As the keynote speaker, [[Reina Gossett|Reina Gosset]] spoke about activism for trans and gender non-conforming people, prison reform, overlapping systems of oppression and the relationship between personal and political.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.facebook.com/yalewomenscenter/photos/?tab=album&amp;album_id=719488071485454}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Fourth-wave feminism outside the United States==
In 2012–2013, in the U.K. and some other nations, according to [[Kira Cochrane]], a fourth wave was active. In an article she wrote, Kira describes that the fourth wave focuses on inequality manifesting in "street harassment, sexual harassment, workplace discrimination[,]&amp;nbsp;... body-shaming",&lt;ref name="4thWave-Guardian20131210"&gt;{{cite news|last=Cochrane|first=Kira|authorlink=Kira Cochrane|title=The fourth wave of feminism: meet the rebel women|url=http://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/dec/10/fourth-wave-feminism-rebel-women|accessdate=14 December 2013|newspaper=[[The Guardian]]|date=10 December 2013}} (Cochrane is also the author of ''All the Rebel Women: The Rise of the Fourth Wave of Feminism'' (Guardian Shorts Originals series ebook 2013).&lt;/ref&gt; media images, "online misogyny",&lt;ref name="4thWave-Guardian20131210" /&gt; "assault[s] on public transport",&lt;ref name="4thWave-Guardian20131210" /&gt; and [[intersectionality]], relying on [[social media]] technology for communication and online petitioning for organizing, and sharing with prior waves a perception that individual experiences are shared and thus can have political solutions.&lt;ref name="4thWave-Guardian20131210" /&gt; According to Cochrane, organizations and websites included the [[Everyday Sexism Project]] and [[Kat Banyard|UK Feminista]], events included [[Take Back the Night|Reclaim the Night]], [[One Billion Rising]], and "a Lose the Lads' mags protest",&lt;ref name="4thWave-Guardian20131210" /&gt; and "many of [the leaders]&amp;nbsp;... are in their teens and 20s".&lt;ref name="4thWave-Guardian20131210" /&gt;

The Everyday Sexism Project began as a social media campaign on 16 April 2012 by Laura Bates, a British feminist writer. The aim of the site was to document everyday examples of sexism as reported by contributors around the world.&lt;ref&gt;[[Everyday Sexism Project]]&lt;/ref&gt; Bates established the Everyday Sexism Project as an open forum where women could post their experiences of harassment.  Bates explains the Everyday Sexism Project's goal, "The project was never about solving sexism. It was about getting people to take the first step of just realising there is a problem that needs to be fixed."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Aitkenhead|first=Decca|title=Laura Bates interview: 'Two years ago, I didn't know what feminism meant'|url=http://www.theguardian.com/world/2014/jan/24/laura-bates-interview-everyday-sexism|accessdate=12 May 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The website was such a success that Bates decided to write and publish a book, ''Everyday Sexism'', which further emphasizes the importance of having this type of online forum for women. The book provides unique insight into the vibrant movement of the upcoming fourth wave and the untold stories that women shared through the Everyday Sexism Project.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Bates|first=Laura|title=Everyday Sexism|publisher=Simon and Schuster|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=lF6EAgAAQBAJ&amp;dq=the+everyday+sexism+project&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=IwVxU-2DHq-zsAT3woDoAg&amp;ved=0CDUQ6AEwAQ}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Criticism of fourth-wave feminism ==
One criticism of fourth-wave feminism is a perceived dependence on technology. As Ragna Rök Jóns argues in ''Bluestockings Magazine'', "The key problem that this '4th Wave' will face will be the disproportionate access to and ownership of digital media devices." The fourth wave is then left with the "inherent [[classism]] and [[ableism]]" created by giving the biggest voice to those who can afford and use technology.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://bluestockingsmag.com/2013/08/19/is-the-4th-wave-of-feminism-digital/|title=Is the "4th Wave" of Feminism Digital?|last=Jóns|first=Ragna Rök|website=bluestockings magazine|access-date=13 March 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

It is also argued that, that when people participate in Twitter activism, they don't feel the need to do anything else to help the effort. In an article for Newuniversity.org, the author argues that after contributing their say, people just "continue on with their day, liking other posts or retweeting." some may think of themselves as activists while never bothering to attend a single rally or extend their message beyond their Twitter fan base.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.newuniversity.org/2015/03/opinion/hashtag-activism-the-benefits-and-limitations-of-activism/|title=New University|last=Guardado|first=Alex|date=3 March 2015|website=NewUniversity.org|publisher=|access-date=21 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Fourth-wave feminism can therefore get a reputation as being lazy, be it true or not.

Jennifer Simpkins of [[The Huffington Post]] argues that fourth-wave feminism has created a hostile, ''[[Mean Girls]]''-like atmosphere where women are more likely to tear each other down. "I've actually never once been belittled and attacked by a man for believing in the cause of feminism" she states, "but women are just about lining up to take a whack at the shoddy piñata of my personal tastes and opinions." &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |last=Simpkins |first=Jennifer |url= http://www.huffingtonpost.co.uk/jennifer-simpkins/feminism-fourth-wave-became-mean-girls_b_4616597.html|title="You can't sit with us!" - how fourth-wave feminism became 'mean girls'|work=The Huffington Post |location= UK|language=en-GB|access-date=16 March 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After [[Suzanne Moore]] wrote an article which featured a "problematic" comment comparing the perfect female body by today's standards to a "Brazilian Transsexual", her friend [[Julie Burchill|Julie Birchill]] claimed Moore was forced off Twitter by a "gaggle of transsexuals".&lt;ref name="Munro" /&gt;

== References ==
{{Reflist|30em}}

{{Feminism}}

[[Category:Feminism]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>