<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20221109232337|1120994249" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="71996420" pageid="71996420" ns="0" title="Cisnormativity"><revisions><rev timestamp="2022-11-12T17:41:33Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|Assumption that everyone is, or ought to be, cisgender}}
{{Transgender sidebar}}

'''Cisnormativity''' or '''cissexual assumption''' is the assumption that everyone is, or ought to be, [[cisgender]]. The term can further refer to a wider range of presumptions about [[gender assignment]], such as the presumption of a [[gender binary]], or expectations of conformity to [[gender role]]s even when [[transgender]] identities are otherwise acknowledged. Cisnormativity is a form of '''cisgenderism''', an [[ideology]] which promotes various normative ideas about [[gender]], to the invalidation of individuals' own [[Gender identity|gender identities]], analogous to [[heterosexism]] or [[ableism|ablism]].

Cisnormativity is widespread in society. It manifests in speech as a separation of cisgender and transgender people where cisgender individuals are considered "normal" and transgender people, an exception. Cisnormative legislation may require [[mental health]] diagnoses or [[sterilization (medicine)|sterilization]] as a precondition for legal recognition of a transgender person's gender identity, and cisnormativity in health care results in transgender people having difficulties finding clinicians who are competent in [[transgender health care]], or being forced into [[sex]]-segregated spaces which they feel uncomfortable in. This further causes some transgender people to avoid medical care, or to avoid disclosing their transgender status to practitioners.

Cisnormativity is closely tied to [[heteronormativity]]. The combination of the two, termed ''hetero-cis-normativity'', represents the societally dominant view that sex, gender, and [[sexual orientation]] are all congruent.

==Definition==
According to [[Julia Serano]], writing in ''[[Whipping Girl]]'', "[cissexual assumption] occurs when a cissexual makes the common, albeit mistaken, assumption that the way they experience their physical and subconscious sexes […] applies to everyone else in the world". She argues that cisgender people "indiscriminately project" their experience of gender identity onto all others, "transforming cissexuality into a human attribute that is taken for granted".&lt;ref name="Serano, 2007"&gt;{{Vcite book |author=Serano, Julia |title=Whipping Girl: A Transsexual Woman on Sexism and the Scapegoating of Femininity |publisher=[[Seal Press]] |date=2007 |page=201}}&lt;/ref&gt; A 2009 article published in the ''Journal of the Association of Nurses in AIDS Care'' defines cisnormativity as "the expectation that all people are cissexual".&lt;ref name="Bauer et al., 2009" /&gt; ''The SAGE Encyclopedia of Trans Studies'' states that cisnormativity is "the presumption that most people do, or should, conform to the norms about gender assignment in their society". It elaborates: {{" '}}cisnormative' behavior varies depending on the gender norms in place within a given society. For example, in some societies, having only 'woman' and 'man' as gender categories would not be cisnormative".&lt;ref name="SAGE Cisnormativity"&gt;{{Vcite book |editor=Goldberg, Abbie; Beemyn, Genny |author=Berger, Israel; Ansara, Y. Gavriel |date=2021 |chapter=Cisnormativity |title=The SAGE Encyclopedia of Trans Studies |publisher=[[SAGE Publishing]] |pages=121–125}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A related concept is that of cisgenderism (also known as '''cissexism'''), defined by Erica Lennon and Brian J. Millster writing for ''[[Transgender Studies Quarterly]]'' as "the cultural and systemic ideology that denies, denigrates, or pathologizes self-identified gender identities that do not align with assigned gender at birth as well as resulting behavior, expression, and community".&lt;ref name="Lennon &amp; Millster, 2014"&gt;{{Vcite journal |author=Lennon, Erica; Millster, Brian J. |author.= |title=Cisgenderism |journal=[[Transgender Studies Quarterly]] |publisher=[[Duke University Press]] |date=2014 |volume=1 |issue=1–2 |pages=63–64}}&lt;/ref&gt; Cisgenderism was proposed as an alternative concept to [[transphobia]], focusing on a systemic ideology, rather than an individual "phobia". This draws from the earlier distinction between heterosexism and [[homophobia]]. According to the SAGE Encyclopedia, cisnormativity is one form of cisgenderism.&lt;ref name="SAGE Cisgenderism"&gt;{{Vcite book |editor=Goldberg, Abbie; Beemyn, Genny |author=Berger, Israel; Ansara, Y. Gavriel |date=2021 |chapter=Cisgenderism |title=The SAGE Encyclopedia of Trans Studies |publisher=[[SAGE Publishing]] |pages=118–121}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Pearce, 2018"&gt;{{Vcite book |author=Pearce, Ruth |chapter=Condition or movement? A genealogy of trans discourse |title=Understanding trans health |publisher=[[Policy Press]] |date=2018 |pages=43–44}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Ansara &amp; Hegarty, 2012"&gt;{{Vcite journal |author=Ansara, Y. Gavriel; Hegarty, Peter |title=Cisgenderism in psychology: pathologising and misgendering children from 1999 to 2008 |journal=Psychology &amp; Sexuality |publisher=[[Routledge]] |volume=3 |issue=2 |pages=137–160 |doi=10.1080/19419899.2011.576696}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Consequences==
According to the 2009 article, "Cisnormative assumptions are so prevalent that they are difficult at first to even recognize."&lt;ref name="Bauer et al., 2009"/&gt; Cisnormativity is present in the way cisgender people are addressed without qualification as "men" or "women", while trans individuals often are consistently referred to as ''trans'' men or women, regardless of context. That is, being cisgender is considered normal, while being trans requires clarification.&lt;ref name="SAGE Cisnormativity" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Bauer et al., 2009" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Frohart-Dourlent, 2016"&gt;{{Vcite book |author=Frohart-Dourlent, Hélène |title=Muddling Through Together: Educators Navigating Cisnormativity While Working with Trans and Gender-Nonconforming Students |publisher=[[University of British Columbia]] |date=2016 |pages=14–15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''The SAGE Encyclopedia of Trans Studies'' cites as examples of cisnormativity in legislation laws mandating mental health diagnoses to receive gender-affirming treatments or to have one's gender legally recognized, and laws requiring a trans person to be sterilized before they can change their [[legal gender]].&lt;ref name="SAGE Cisnormativity" /&gt;

===Health care===
[[Health care provider]]s often lack education and thus awareness about transgender topics, which causes them to be unprepared to treat transgender people. In 2015, 24% of transgender survey respondents in the United States reported having to educate health care providers about transgender health.&lt;ref&gt;{{Vcite book |author=James, S. E., Herman, J. L., Rankin, S., Keisling, M., Mottet, L., &amp; Anafi, M. |title=The Report of the 2015 U.S. Transgender Survey |publisher=[[National Center for Transgender Equality]] |date=2016 |url=https://transequality.org/sites/default/files/docs/usts/USTS-Full-Report-Dec17.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; Transgender people often feel unwelcome in sex-segregated wards or clinics, and some report being outright dismissed by doctors, or asked to seek help elsewhere, upon revealing that they are transgender. Past or anticipated experiences in cisnormative health care systems cause some transgender people to shy away from health care. According to the 2021 Trans Lives Survey report, 57% of respondents in the United Kingdom avoided seeing a doctor when ill. Some transgender people also avoid disclosing their transgender status to clinicians for fear of mistreatment; this may cause further problems due to inappropriate treatments, or from unintentional revelation of the patient's sex during examination.&lt;ref name="SAGE Cisnormativity" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Bauer et al., 2009"&gt;{{Vcite journal |author=Bauer, Greta R.; Hammond, Rebecca; Travers, Robb; Kaay, Matthias; Hohenadel, Karin M.; Boyce, Michelle |date=2009 |title='I Don’t Think This Is Theoretical; This Is Our Lives': How Erasure Impacts Health Care for Transgender People |journal=Journal of the Association of Nurses in AIDS Care |volume=20 |issue=5 |pages=384–361 |doi=10.1016/j.jana.2009.07.004}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Vinter, 2021"&gt;{{Vcite news |author=Vinter, Robin |title='GPs fob us off': most trans people avoid the doctor when they’re sick |work=[[The Observer]] |date=2021 Oct 10 |url=https://www.theguardian.com/society/2021/oct/10/gps-fob-us-off-most-trans-people-avoid-the-doctor-when-theyre-sick}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Relationship with heteronormativity==
Cisnormativity often appears together with heteronormativity.&lt;ref name="Worthen, 2016"&gt;{{Vcite journal |author=Worthen, Meredith G. F. |author.= |title=Hetero-cis-normativity and the gendering of transphobia |journal=International Journal of Transgenderism |volume=17 |issue=1 |pages=31–57 |doi=10.1080/15532739.2016.1149538}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Frohart-Dourlent, 2016" /&gt; According to [[Judith Butler]], the dominant view of gender assumes a "causal continuity among sex, gender, and desire".&lt;ref&gt;{{Vcite book |author=Butler, Judith |title=[[Gender Trouble|Gender Trouble: Feminism and the Subversion of Identity]] |publisher=[[Routledge]] |date=1990 |notes=Quoted in Frohard-Dourlent, 2016.}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2012, sociologist Meredith Worthen coined the term ''hetero-cis-normativity'' for this phenomenon:
{{blockquote|I identify hetero-cis-normativity as a system of norms, privilege, and oppression that organizes social power around sexual identity and gender identity whereby heterosexual cisgender people are situated above all others and thus, LGBTQ people are in a place of systemic disadvantage.&lt;ref name="Worthen, 2020"&gt;{{Vcite book |author=Worthen, Meredith G. F. |author.= |title=Queers, Bis, and Straight Lies: An Intersectional Examination of LGBTQ Stigma |publisher=[[Routledge]] |date=2020 |page=xv}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

According to Worthen, hetero-cis-normativity is a model to explain antipathy towards [[LGBT]] people,&lt;ref name="Worthen, 2020" /&gt; and transphobia may be a symptom thereof.&lt;ref name="Worthen, 2016"/&gt;

==See also==
*[[Gender essentialism]]
*[[Trans erasure]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

[[Category:Transgender studies]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>