<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20030801035212|1691785" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="162699" pageid="162699" ns="0" title="Heteronormativity"><revisions><rev timestamp="2003-11-08T06:49:00Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Heteronormativity''' describes a binary gender system, in which only two [[sex]]es are accepted, and sex is equated with [[gender identity]] and [[gender role]], and ([[heterosexual]]) [[sexual preference]]. 

* Woman: female [[genitalia]] = female identity = female behavior = desires male partners, but not female ones
* Man: male genitalia = male identity = male behavior = desires female partners, but not male ones

[[Behaviour]] or [[feeling]]s which could destabilize this basic assumption are strongly disapproved of or even forbidden. 

This scheme obviously has no room for: 
* [[Intersexual]]s
* [[Gay]]s, [[lesbian]]s, and [[Bisexual]]s
* [[Transgendered]] people
It strives to incorporate these people by:
;'''Intersexuals'''
: Are assigned a gender at birth, performing (often mutilative) medical procedures on them as soon as possible to make their body "fit" that gender and to encourage strong social pressure (by parents, doctors, teachers etc.) on the intersexual to behave according to the prescribed gender. Until today this is standard procedure in Europe and North America, although now more frequently challenged.
;'''Gays, lesbians, and Bisexuals'''
: Lesbian, gay, and bisexual behaviour is strongly disapproved of, always socially, almost always legally. If it cannot be suppressed so far as to at least disappear from the public view, the notion is strongly encouraged that gay men are not really "men", but have a strong female component (and vice versa) and/or that in a lesbian or gay partnership there is always a "male" (=active) and a "female" (=passive) partner. This has in some cases gone so far that homosexuals were encouraged (in Europe and North America in the 1960s and 1970s) or even forced to undergo [[sexual reassignment]] procedures (in [[South Africa]] in the 1980s and 1990s). As for bisexuals the stereotypes focus on the false notion that they are confused rather than on gender roles, but bisexuality is still considered outside heteronormativity.
;'''Transgender'''
: This behavior either has been pathologised so far that transgendered people routinely were locked away in psychiatric wards, or the plain right to live was taken away from them. This happens either by formally punishing transgender behavior by death (today, [[Saudi Arabia]]), or by refusing to track down and/or prosecute murderers of transgendered people (today, parts of North America and Europe). &lt;br&gt;
: A special case of incorporating transgendered people into a ''heteronormative'' system is [[transsexualism]]. If transgender behaviour in a person can not be suppressed, it is allowed on the condition that the person becomes entirely a member of ''the other'' sex, and thereby confirms the binary gender system. (Please note: This is a description of the heteronormative ''treatment of'' transsexual people, not a description of transsexual or transgendered people.)

The ''heteronormative'' system is usually justified with either religious or traditional arguments, or, especially in Western culture, with (pseudo-)scientific, (pseudo-)medical and (pseudo-)psychological arguments. 

''Heternormativity'' is often strongly associated with, and sometimes even confused with [[patriarchy]]. However, even a patriarchal system does not necessarily have a binary gender system; some patriarchal systems do have a [[third gender]].</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>