<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20141013031449|629388003" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="162699" pageid="162699" ns="0" title="Heteronormativity"><revisions><rev timestamp="2014-10-27T05:08:30Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{LGBT sidebar}}
'''Heteronormativity''' is the belief that people fall into distinct and complementary [[gender]]s ([[man]] and [[woman]]) with [[Essentialism#Essentialism and society and politics|natural roles in life]]. It asserts that [[heterosexuality]] is the only [[sexual orientation]] or only [[Norm (social)|norm]], and states that sexual and marital relations are most (or only) fitting between people of opposite sexes. Consequently, a "heteronormative" view is one that involves alignment of biological [[sex]], [[Human sexuality|sexuality]], [[gender identity]] and [[gender role]]s. Heteronormativity is often linked to [[heterosexism]] and [[homophobia]].&lt;ref name=lovaas&gt;Lovaas, Karen, and Mercilee M. Jenkins. [http://books.google.com/books?id=fTRcvkxWV-IC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=isbn:1412914434&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=tXQbU-fpDqyI2gWwpYD4DA&amp;ved=0CCsQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false "Charting a Path through the 'Desert of Nothing.'"] Sexualities and Communication in Everyday Life: A Reader. 8 July 2006. Sage Publications Inc. 5 May 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

==Origin of the term==
[[Michael Warner]] popularized the term in 1991,&lt;ref&gt;Warner, Michael (1991), "Introduction: Fear of a Queer Planet". ''Social Text''; 9 (4 [29]): 3–17&lt;/ref&gt; in one of the first major works of [[queer theory]].  The concept's roots are in [[Gayle Rubin]]'s notion of the "sex/gender system" and [[Adrienne Rich]]'s notion of [[Compulsory Heterosexuality and Lesbian Existence|compulsory heterosexuality]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Adrienne Rich]], 'Compulsory Heterosexuality and Lesbian Existence' ''Signs: Journal of Women in Culture and Society'', 5:631-60, 1980.&lt;/ref&gt;

In a series of articles, Samuel A. Chambers calls for an understanding of heteronormativity as a concept that reveals the expectations, demands, and constraints produced when heterosexuality is taken as normative within a society.&lt;ref&gt;Samuel A. Chambers, "Telepistemology of the Closet; Or, the Queer Politics of ''Six Feet Under''". ''Journal of American Culture'' 26.1: 24–41, 2003&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Samuel A. Chambers, "Revisiting the Closet: Reading Sexuality in ''Six Feet Under'', in ''Reading Six Feet Under''. McCabe and Akass, eds. IB Taurus, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!-- When and by who? What was the first usage? I've tried to edit to answer this question --&gt;  Originally conceived to describe the norms against which [[non-heterosexuals]] struggle, "heteronormativity" quickly became incorporated into both the [[gender]] and the [[transgender]] debate.&lt;ref name="Todd" /&gt;

==Discrimination==
Critics of heteronormative attitudes, such as [[Cathy J. Cohen]], [[Michael Warner]], and [[Lauren Berlant]], argue that they are oppressive, stigmatizing, marginalizing of perceived deviant forms of sexuality and gender, and make self-expression more difficult when that expression does not conform to the norm.&lt;ref name=lovaas /&gt;&lt;ref name="OutatWork"/&gt; This includes [[lesbian]], [[gay]], [[bisexual]], [[intersex]], [[transgender]] ([[LGBTQ]]) people, as well as others such as racial minorities.&lt;ref name="Todd" /&gt;&lt;ref name="OutatWork"/&gt; Heteronormative culture "privileges heterosexuality as normal and natural" and fosters a climate where LGBTQ are discriminated against in marriage, tax codes, and employment.&lt;ref name=OutatWork&gt;{{cite book|last=Krupat|first=Kitty|title=Out at Work: Building a Gay-Labor Alliance|year=2001|publisher=U of Minnesota Press|isbn=0-8166-3741-5|pages=268}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Against gay, lesbian, and bisexual individuals===
According to cultural anthropologist [[Gayle Rubin]], heteronormativity in mainstream society creates a "sex hierarchy" that gradates sexual practices from morally "good sex" to "bad sex." The hierarchy places reproductive, monogamous sex between committed heterosexuals as "good" and places any sexual acts and individuals who fall short of this standard lower until they fall into "bad sex." Specifically, this places long-term committed gay couples and promiscuous gays in between the two poles.&lt;ref name="thinkingsex"&gt;Rubin, Gayle. ''Thinking Sex: Notes for a Radical Theory of the Politics of Sexuality'', in Vance, Carole. ''Pleasure and Danger: Exploring Female Sexuality'' (1993)&lt;/ref&gt; Patrick McCreery, lecturer at [[New York University]], views this hierarchy as partially explanatory for the stigmatization of gay people for socially "deviant" sexual practices that are often practiced by straight people as well, such as consumption of pornography or sex in public places.&lt;ref name="OutatWork"/&gt;

McCreery states that this heteronormative hierarchy carries over to the workplace, where gay, lesbian and bisexual individuals face discrimination such as anti-homosexual hiring policies or workplace discrimination that often leaves "lowest hierarchy" individuals such as transsexuals vulnerable to the most overt discrimination and unable to find work.&lt;ref name="OutatWork"/&gt;

Applicants and current employees can be legally passed over or fired for being non-heterosexual or ''perceived'' as non-heterosexual in many countries, such as the case with chain restaurant [[Cracker Barrel]], which [[Cracker Barrel#Policy_toward_sexual_orientation|garnered national attention in 1991]] after they fired an employee for being openly lesbian, citing their policy that employees with "sexual preferences that fail to demonstrate normal heterosexual values were inconsistent with traditional American values." Workers such as the fired employee and others, such as effeminate male waiters (allegedly described as the true targets),&lt;ref name="OutatWork"/&gt; were legally fired by work policies "transgressing" against "normal" heteronormative culture.&lt;ref name="OutatWork"/&gt;

Analysing the interconnectivity of heteronormativity and sexual employment discrimination, Mustafa Bilgehan Ozturk traces the impact of patriarchal practices and institutions on the workplace experiences of lesbian, gay and bisexual employees in a variety of contexts in Turkey, demonstrating further the specific historicities and localised power/knowledge formations that give rise to physical, professional and psycho-emotive acts of prejudice against sexual minorities.&lt;ref name="SexualOrientationDiscrimination"&gt;Ozturk, Mustafa Bilgehan. "Sexual Orientation Discrimination: Exploring the Experiences of Lesbian, Gay and Bisexual Employees in Turkey, Human Relations, August 2011, 64(8), 1099-1118&lt;/ref&gt;

==Relation to marriage and the nuclear family==
Modern family structures in the past and present vary from what was typical of the 1950s [[nuclear family]].  The families of the second half of the 19th century and early 20th century in the United States were characterized by the death of one or both parents for many American children.&lt;ref name="Coontz"&gt;Coontz, S. (1992)&lt;/ref&gt; In 1985, the United States is estimated to have been home to approximately 2.5 million post-divorce, [[stepfamily]] households containing children.&lt;ref&gt;Coleman, M., Ganong, L. H., &amp; Goodwin, C.  (1994).  "The presentation of stepfamilies in marriage and family textbooks:  A reexamination".  ''[[Family Relations (journal)|Family Relations]]'' 45, 289–297.&lt;/ref&gt;  During the late 80s, almost 20% of families with children headed by a married couple were [[stepfamilies]].&lt;ref&gt;Coleman, Ganong, &amp; Goodwin, 1994.&lt;/ref&gt;

Over the past three decades rates of divorce, single parenting, and [[cohabitation]] have risen precipitously.&lt;ref name="Benfer"&gt;Benfer, Amy. [http://archive.salon.com/mwt/feature/2001/06/07/family_values/index.html The Nuclear Family Takes a Hit], Salon.com.  June 7, 2001&lt;/ref&gt; Nontraditional families (which diverge from "a middle-class family with a bread-winning father and a stay-at-home mother, married to each other and raising their biological children") constitute the majority of families in the [[United States]] today.&lt;ref name="Benfer"/&gt; [[Shared Earning/Shared Parenting Marriage]] (also known as Peer Marriage) where two heterosexual parents are both providers of resources and nurturers to children has become popular.  Modern families may also have single-parent headed families caused by divorce, separation or death, families who have two parents who are not married but have children, or families with same-sex parents. With [[artificial insemination]], [[surrogate mother]]s, and [[adoption]], families do not have to be formed by the heteronormative biological union of a male and a female.

The consequences of these changes for the adults and children involved are heavily debated. In a 2009 [[Massachusetts]] spousal benefits case, developmental psychologist [[Michael Lamb (psychologist)|Michael Lamb]] testified that parental sexual orientation does not negatively affect childhood development. "Since the end of the 1980s... it has been well established that children and adolescents can adjust just as well in nontraditional settings as in traditional settings," he argued.&lt;ref&gt;Michael Lamb, Ph.D.: [http://www.glad.org/uploads/docs/cases/2009-11-17-doma-aff-lamb.pdf Affidavit – United States District Court for the District of Massachusetts (2009)]&lt;/ref&gt;  However, columnist [[Maggie Gallagher]] argues that heteronormative social structures are beneficial to society because they are optimal for the raising of children.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.marriagedebate.com/pdf/SenateSept42003.pdf |title=Why Marriage Matters: The Case for Normal Marriage. Testimony before the U.S. Senate Subcommittee on the Constitution, Civil Rights, and Property Rights Hearing: "What is needed to defend the Bipartisan Defense of Marriage Act of 1996?" |author=Maggie Gallagher |publisher=Institute for Marriage and Public Policy |date=2003-09-04 |accessdate=2012-05-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Australian-Canadian ethicist [[Margaret Somerville]] argues that "giving same-sex couples the right to found a family unlinks parenthood from biology".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unisa.edu.au/hawkecentre/events/2007events/MSomerville_InConversation.asp Margaret Somerville – In Conversation]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Transgressions==
{{Wikinews|Dr. Joseph Merlino on sexuality, insanity, Freud, fetishes and apathy}}

===Intersex people===
[[intersexuality|Intersex]] people have biological characteristics that are ambiguously either male or female. If such a condition is detected, intersex people in most present-day societies are almost always assigned a normative sex shortly after birth.&lt;ref&gt;Fausto-Sterling, Anne. 2000. Sexing the Body: Gender Politics and the Construction of Sexuality. New York: Basic Books.&lt;/ref&gt; Surgery (usually involving modification to the genitalia) is often performed in an attempt to produce an unambiguously male or female body, with the parents'—rather than the individual's—consent.&lt;ref&gt;[[Judith Butler|Butler, Judith]]. 2004. ''[[Undoing Gender]]''. New York: Routledge.&lt;/ref&gt; The child is then usually raised and enculturated as a [[cisgender]] member of the assigned sex, which may or may not match their emergent [[gender identity]] throughout life or some remaining [[sex-determination system|sex characteristics]] (for example, chromosomes, genes or internal sex organs).&lt;ref&gt;Wilchins, Riki. 2002. 'A certain kind of freedom: power and the truth of bodies – four essays on gender.' In GenderQueer: Voices from beyond the sexual binary. Los Angeles: Alyson Books 23–66.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Transgender people===
The [[transgender]] people who seek [[sex reassignment therapy]] fall under the [[transsexual]] demographic underneath the '[[transgender]] umbrella'. They may not develop a [[gender identity]] that corresponds to their body or a gender identity that is plainly male or female. Transgender people may not behave according to the ''gender role'' imposed by society. Some societies consider transgender behavior a crime worthy of capital punishment, including [[Saudi Arabia]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ifge.org/news/1998/sept/nws9278.htm Saudis Arrest 5 Pakistani TGs]&lt;/ref&gt; and many other nations.

In some cases homosexuals were forced to undergo sex change treatments to "fix" their sex or gender: in some [[Europe|European countries]] during the 20th century,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.slate.com/id/2660/ The Unkindest Cut | The science and ethics of castration]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.glbtq.com/social-sciences/turing_a,2.html Turing, Alan (1912–1954)]&lt;/ref&gt; and in [[South Africa]] in the 1970s and 1980s.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2000/jul/29/chrismcgreal Gays tell of mutilation by apartheid army]&lt;/ref&gt;

In some countries, including North American&lt;ref name="cider"/&gt; and European countries, certain forms of violence against transgender people may be tacitly endorsed when prosecutors and juries refuse to investigate, prosecute, or convict those who perform the murders and beatings (currently, in some parts of North America and Europe).&lt;ref name="cider"&gt;{{cite journal |last=Frye|first=Phyllis|date=Fall 2000|title=The International Bill of Gender Rights vs. The Cide House Rules: Transgender people struggle with the courts over what clothing they are allowed to wear on the job, which restroom they are allowed to use on the job, their right to marry, and the very definition of their sex|journal=William and Mary Journal of Women and the Law|volume=7|pages=139–145}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="AmnestyUSA"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.amnestyusa.org/outfront/jamaica_report.html|title=OUTfront! Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual &amp; Transgendered Human Rights:"Battybwoys affi dead" Action against homophobia in Jamaica|date=May 7, 2004|publisher=AmnestyUSA.org|accessdate=4 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.splcenter.org/intel/intelreport/article.jsp?pid=276 SPLCenter.org: 'Disposable People'&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Other societies have considered transgender behavior as a [[psychiatric illness]] serious enough to justify [[institutionalization]].{{Citation needed|date=March 2011}}

In medical communities with these restrictions, patients have the option of either suppressing transsexual behavior and conforming to the norms of their birth sex (which may be necessary to avoid social stigma or even violence) or by adhering strictly to the norms of their "new" sex in order to qualify for sex reassignment surgery and hormonal treatments. Attempts to achieve an ambiguous or "alternative" gender identity would not be supported or allowed.&lt;ref name="Todd"&gt;{{cite journal |last=Weiss |first=Jillian Todd |title=The Gender Caste System: Identity, Privacy and Heteronormativity |publisher=Tulane Law School |year=2001 |url=http://phobos.ramapo.edu/~jweiss/tulane.pdf |format=PDF|accessdate=2007-02-25 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Sometimes sex reassignment surgery is a requirement for an official gender change, and often "male" and "female" are the only choices available, even for [[intersex]] and transgender people.&lt;ref&gt;Sydney Morning Herald, March 18, 2010, Chi Tranter, "Norrie's 'ungendered' status withdrawn", http://news.smh.com.au/breaking-news-national/norries-ungendered-status-withdrawn-20100318-qhw5.html&lt;/ref&gt; For governments which allow only heterosexual marriages, official gender changes can have implications for related rights and privileges, such as child custody, inheritance, and medical decision-making.&lt;ref name="Todd" /&gt;
&lt;!--
**Temporarily removed for uncited refs and weasel words**
Some governments and official agencies have also been criticized{{By whom|date=May 2010}} as having heteronormative systems that classify people into "male" and "female" genders in problematic ways.{{Citation needed|date=April 2010}} Different jurisdictions use different definitions of gender, including by genitalia, DNA, hormone levels (including some official sports bodies), or birth sex (which means one's gender cannot ever be officially changed).--&gt;

==Homonormativity==
Homonormativity is the assimilation of heteronormative ideals and constructs into [[LGBTQ]] culture and individual identity.  The term was used prominently by Lisa Duggan in 2003,&lt;ref name="Duggan, Lisa 2003"&gt;Duggan, Lisa. The Twilight of Equality?: Neoliberalism, Cultural Politics, and the Attack On Democracy. Beacon Press, 2003.&lt;/ref&gt; although transgender studies scholar [[Susan Stryker]] has noted that it was also used by transgender activists in the 1990s in reference to the imposition of gay/lesbian norms over the concerns of trans people.&lt;ref name="Stryker, Susan 2008"&gt;[[Susan Stryker|Stryker, Susan]].  2008. "Transgender History, Homonormativity, and Disciplinarity". Radical History Review. (100): 145-157.&lt;/ref&gt;   According to Penny Griffin, Politics and International Relations lecturer at the [[University of New South Wales]], homonormativity upholds [[neoliberalism]] rather than critiquing monogamy, procreation, and [[Gender binary|binary gender roles]] as [[heterosexist]] and [[racist]].&lt;ref&gt;Griffin, Penny. "Sexing the Economy in a Neo-liberal World Order: Neo-liberal Discourse and the (Re)Production of Heteronormative Heterosexuality." British Journal of Politics and International Relations 9.2 (2007): 220–238. Academic Search Premier. EBSCO. MCTC LIBRARY. 30 June 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;  Duggan asserts that homonormativity fragments LGBTQ communities into hierarchies of worthiness. LGBTQ people that come the closest to mimicking heteronormative standards of gender identity are deemed most worthy of receiving rights. LGBTQ individuals at the bottom of the hierarchy ([[transsexuals]], [[transvestites]], [[intersex]] people, [[bisexuals]], non-gender identified people) are seen as an impediment to this elite class of homonormative individuals receiving their rights.&lt;ref name="Duggan, Lisa 2003"/&gt;

==See also==
{{Col-begin}}
{{Col-2}}
* [[Bisexual erasure]]
* [[Complementarianism]]
* [[Egalitarianism]]
* [[Gender studies]]
* [[List of transgender-related topics]]
* [[Monique Wittig]]
{{Col-2}}
* [[Non-binary discrimination]]
* [[Normality (behavior)]]
* [[Sexual deviancy]]
* [[Structural functionalism]]
* [[Subject-SUBJECT consciousness]]
* [[Transphobia]]
{{Col-end}}

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Bibliography==
* Benfer, Amy. "The Nuclear Family Takes a Hit." Salon.com 7 June 2001. 5 May 2008 [http://archive.salon.com/mwt/feature/2001/06/07/family_values/index.html].
* Dreyer,Yolanda. "Hegemony and the Internalisation of Homophobia Caused by Heteronormativity." Department of Practical Theology. 2007. University of Pretoria.5 May 2008 [http://www.up.ac.za/dspace/bitstream/2263/2741/1/Dreyer_Hegemony(2007).pdf].
* Gray, Brandon."'Brokeback Mountain' most impressive of Tepid 2005."Box Office Mojo, LLC. 25 February 2006. 7 May 2008. [http://www.boxofficemojo.com/news/?id=2012&amp;p=.htm].
* Lovaas, Karen, and Mercilee M. Jenkins. "Charting a Path through the 'Desert of Nothing.'" Sexualities and Communication in Everyday Life: A Reader. 8 July 2006. Sage Publications Inc. 5 May 2008 [http://books.google.com/books?isbn=1412914434].
* Peele, Thomas. Composition Studies, Heteronormativity, and Popular Culture. 2001 Boise State University. 5 May 2008. [http://www.bgsu.edu/cconline/peele/CulturalStudies.html].
* The Pew Forum on Religion and Public Life. "U.S. Religious Landscape Survey." 7 May 2008. 7 May 2008. [http://religions.pewforum.org/reports].

==Further reading==
{{ISBNs}}
* [[Judith Butler]], ''Bodies That Matter''
* Judith Butler, ''[[Gender Trouble]]''
* [[Dag Øistein Endsjø]], [[Sex and Religion (book)|''Sex and Religion. Teachings and Taboos in the History of World Faiths'']]. Reaktion Books 2011.
* [[Michel Foucault]], ''[[History of Sexuality]]''
* [[Chrys Ingraham]]: ''The Heterosexual Imaginary: Feminist Sociology and Theories of Gender'': Sociological Theory: July 1994
* [[Michael Warner]], ed. ''Fear of a Queer Planet''. Minneapolis MN: University of Minnesota Press, 1993.
* [http://phobos.ramapo.edu/~jweiss/tulane.htm Jillian Todd Weiss: ''The Gender Caste System – Identity, Privacy, and Heteronormativity'']
* [http://sls.sagepub.com/content/20/3/349.abstract Recent academic article on legal challenges that have been made to the heteronormativity of marriage]
* [http://www.springerlink.com/content/75630n71288643t2/ "Heteronormativity and the European Court of Human Rights" examines heteronormativity in the context of human rights and judicial decision making]

&lt;!--{{LGBT|social=expanded}}--&gt;
{{Discrimination}}

[[Category:Discrimination against LGBT people]]
[[Category:Genderqueer]]
[[Category:Gender studies]]
[[Category:Heterosexuality]]
[[Category:Homophobia]]
[[Category:Neologisms]]
[[Category:Queer theory]]
[[Category:Sexism]]
[[Category:Sexual and gender prejudices]]
[[Category:Sexual orientation and society]]
[[Category:Transgender]]
[[Category:Transphobia]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>