<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20171103072657|808504845" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="162699" pageid="162699" ns="0" title="Heteronormativity"><revisions><rev timestamp="2017-11-03T14:45:44Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{LGBT sidebar}}
'''Heteronormativity''' is the belief that people fall into distinct and complementary [[gender]]s ([[male]] and [[female]]) with [[Essentialism#Essentialism and society and politics|natural roles in life]]. It assumes that [[heterosexuality]] is the only [[sexual orientation]] or only [[Norm (social)|norm]], and that sexual and marital relations are most (or only) fitting between people of opposite sexes. A "heteronormative" view therefore involves alignment of biological [[sex]], [[Human sexuality|sexuality]], [[gender identity]] and [[gender role]]s. Heteronormativity is often linked to [[heterosexism]] and [[homophobia]].&lt;ref name=lovaas&gt;Lovaas, Karen, and Mercilee M. Jenkins. [https://books.google.com/books?id=fTRcvkxWV-IC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=isbn:1412914434&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=tXQbU-fpDqyI2gWwpYD4DA&amp;ved=0CCsQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false "Charting a Path through the 'Desert of Nothing.'"] Sexualities and Communication in Everyday Life: A Reader. 8 July 2006. Sage Publications Inc. 5 May 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

==Origin of the term==
[[Michael Warner]] popularized the term in 1991,&lt;ref name="warner1991"&gt;Warner, Michael (1991), "Introduction: Fear of a Queer Planet". ''Social Text''; 9 (4 [29]): 3–17&lt;/ref&gt; in one of the first major works of [[queer theory]].  The concept's roots are in [[Gayle Rubin]]'s notion of the "sex/gender system" and [[Adrienne Rich]]'s notion of [[Compulsory Heterosexuality and Lesbian Existence|compulsory heterosexuality]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Adrienne Rich]], 'Compulsory Heterosexuality and Lesbian Existence' ''Signs: Journal of Women in Culture and Society'', 5:631-60, 1980.&lt;/ref&gt; From the outset, theories of heteronormativity included a critical look at [[gender]]; Warner wrote that "every person who comes to a queer self-understanding knows in one way or another that her stigmatization is intricated with gender. [...] Being queer[...] means being able, more or less articulately, to challenge the common understanding of what gender difference means."&lt;ref name="warner1991"/&gt;

In a series of articles, Samuel A. Chambers calls for an understanding of heteronormativity as a concept that reveals the expectations, demands, and constraints produced when heterosexuality is taken as normative within a society.&lt;ref&gt;Samuel A. Chambers, "Telepistemology of the Closet; Or, the Queer Politics of ''Six Feet Under''". ''Journal of American Culture'' 26.1: 24–41, 2003&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Samuel A. Chambers, "Revisiting the Closet: Reading Sexuality in ''Six Feet Under'', in ''Reading Six Feet Under''. McCabe and Akass, eds. IB Taurus, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Discrimination==
Critics of heteronormative attitudes, such as [[Cathy J. Cohen]], [[Michael Warner]], and [[Lauren Berlant]], argue that they are oppressive, stigmatizing, marginalizing of perceived deviant forms of sexuality and gender, and make self-expression more difficult when that expression does not conform to the norm.&lt;ref name=lovaas /&gt;&lt;ref name="OutatWork"/&gt; Heteronormativity describes how social institutions and policies reinforce the presumption that people are heterosexual and that gender and sex are natural binaries.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Gender in Communication|last = DeFrancisco|first = Victoria|publisher = SAGE Publication, Inc.|year = 2014|isbn = 978-1-4522-2009-3|location = U.S.A|pages = 16}}&lt;/ref&gt; Heteronormative culture "privileges heterosexuality as normal and natural" and fosters a climate where LGBT individuals are discriminated against in marriage, tax codes, and employment.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://www.rutgersuniversitypress.org/violence-against-queer-people/9780813573151|title=Violence against Queer People|last=Meyer|first=Doug|publisher=Rutgers University Press|year=2015|isbn=|location=|pages=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=OutatWork&gt;{{cite book|last=Krupat|first=Kitty|title=Out at Work: Building a Gay-Labor Alliance|year=2001|publisher=U of Minnesota Press|isbn=0-8166-3741-5|pages=268}}&lt;/ref&gt; Following Berlant and Warner, Laurie and Stark also argue that the domestic "intimate sphere" becomes "the unquestioned non-‐place that anchors heteronormative public discourses, especially those concerning marriage and adoption rights".&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | title= Reconsidering Kinship: Beyond the Nuclear Family With Deleuze and Guattari | first1= Timothy | last1= Laurie | first2= Hannah | last2= Stark | journal=Cultural Studies Review | volume= 18 | issue= 1 | pages= 19–39 | year= 2012 | url= https://www.academia.edu/2137674 | doi=10.5130/csr.v18i1.1612}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Against gay, lesbian, bisexual, and transgender individuals===
According to cultural anthropologist [[Gayle Rubin]], heteronormativity in mainstream society creates a "sex hierarchy" that graduates sexual practices from morally "good sex" to "bad sex." The hierarchy places reproductive, monogamous sex between committed heterosexuals as "good" and places any sexual acts and individuals who fall short of this standard lower until they fall into "bad sex." Specifically, this places long-term committed gay couples and promiscuous gays in between the two poles.&lt;ref name="thinkingsex"&gt;Rubin, Gayle. ''Thinking Sex: Notes for a Radical Theory of the Politics of Sexuality'', in Vance, Carole. ''Pleasure and Danger: Exploring Female Sexuality'' (1993)&lt;/ref&gt; Patrick McCreery, lecturer at [[New York University]], views this hierarchy as partially explanatory for the stigmatization of gay people for socially "deviant" sexual practices that are often practiced by straight people as well, such as consumption of pornography or sex in public places.&lt;ref name="OutatWork"/&gt;

McCreery states that this heteronormative hierarchy carries over to the workplace, where gay, lesbian and bisexual individuals face discrimination such as anti-homosexual hiring policies or workplace discrimination that often leaves "lowest hierarchy" individuals such as transsexual people vulnerable to the most overt discrimination and unable to find work.&lt;ref name="OutatWork"/&gt;

Applicants and current employees can be legally passed over or fired for being non-heterosexual or ''perceived'' as non-heterosexual in many countries, such as the case with chain restaurant [[Cracker Barrel]], which [[Cracker Barrel#Policy toward sexual orientation|garnered national attention in 1991]] after they fired an employee for being openly lesbian, citing their policy that employees with "sexual preferences that fail to demonstrate normal heterosexual values were inconsistent with traditional American values." Workers such as the fired employee and others, such as effeminate male waiters (allegedly described as the true targets),&lt;ref name="OutatWork"/&gt; were legally fired by work policies "transgressing" against "normal" heteronormative culture.&lt;ref name="OutatWork"/&gt;

Analysing the interconnectivity of heteronormativity and sexual employment discrimination, Mustafa Bilgehan Ozturk traces the impact of patriarchal practices and institutions on the workplace experiences of lesbian, gay and bisexual employees in a variety of contexts in Turkey, demonstrating further the specific historicities and localised power/knowledge formations that give rise to physical, professional and psycho-emotive acts of prejudice against sexual minorities.&lt;ref name="SexualOrientationDiscrimination"&gt;Ozturk, Mustafa Bilgehan. "Sexual Orientation Discrimination: Exploring the Experiences of Lesbian, Gay and Bisexual Employees in Turkey, Human Relations, August 2011, 64(8), 1099-1118&lt;/ref&gt;

==Relation to marriage and the nuclear family==
Modern family structures in the past and present vary from what was typical of the 1950s [[nuclear family]].  The families of the second half of the 19th century and early 20th century in the United States were characterized by the death of one or both parents for many American children.&lt;ref name="Coontz"&gt;Coontz, S. (1992)&lt;/ref&gt; In 1985, the United States is estimated to have been home to approximately 2.5 million post-divorce, [[stepfamily]] households containing children.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Coleman | first1 = M. | last2 = Ganong | first2 = L. H. | last3 = Goodwin | first3 = C. | year = 1994 | title = The presentation of stepfamilies in marriage and family textbooks:  A reexamination | url = | journal = [[Family Relations (journal)|Family Relations]] | volume = 45 | issue = | pages = 289–297 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  During the late 80s, almost 20% of families with children headed by a married couple were [[stepfamilies]].&lt;ref&gt;Coleman, Ganong, &amp; Goodwin, 1994.&lt;/ref&gt;

Over the past three decades rates of divorce, single parenting, and [[cohabitation]] have risen precipitously.&lt;ref name="Benfer"&gt;Benfer, Amy. [http://archive.salon.com/mwt/feature/2001/06/07/family_values/index.html The Nuclear Family Takes a Hit] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080522052539/http://archive.salon.com/mwt/feature/2001/06/07/family_values/index.html |date=2008-05-22 }}, Salon.com.  June 7, 2001&lt;/ref&gt; Nontraditional families (which diverge from "a middle-class family with a bread-winning father and a stay-at-home mother, married to each other and raising their biological children") constitute the majority of families in the [[United States]] today.&lt;ref name="Benfer"/&gt; [[Shared Earning/Shared Parenting Marriage]] (also known as Peer Marriage) where two heterosexual parents are both providers of resources and nurturers to children has become popular.  Modern families may also have single-parent headed families caused by divorce, separation or death, families who have two parents who are not married but have children, or families with same-sex parents. With [[artificial insemination]], [[surrogate mother]]s, and [[adoption]], families do not have to be formed by the heteronormative biological union of a male and a female.

The consequences of these changes for the adults and children involved are heavily debated. In a 2009 [[Massachusetts]] spousal benefits case, developmental psychologist [[Michael Lamb (psychologist)|Michael Lamb]] testified that parental sexual orientation does not negatively affect childhood development. "Since the end of the 1980s... it has been well established that children and adolescents can adjust just as well in nontraditional settings as in traditional settings," he argued.&lt;ref&gt;Michael Lamb, Ph.D.: [http://www.glad.org/uploads/docs/cases/2009-11-17-doma-aff-lamb.pdf Affidavit – United States District Court for the District of Massachusetts (2009)]{{dead link|date=April 2017 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;  However, columnist [[Maggie Gallagher]] argues that heteronormative social structures are beneficial to society because they are optimal for the raising of children.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.marriagedebate.com/pdf/SenateSept42003.pdf |title=Why Marriage Matters: The Case for Normal Marriage. Testimony before the U.S. Senate Subcommittee on the Constitution, Civil Rights, and Property Rights Hearing: "What is needed to defend the Bipartisan Defense of Marriage Act of 1996?" |author=Maggie Gallagher |publisher=Institute for Marriage and Public Policy |date=2003-09-04 |accessdate=2012-05-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Australian-Canadian ethicist [[Margaret Somerville]] argues that "giving same-sex couples the right to found a family unlinks parenthood from biology".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unisa.edu.au/hawkecentre/events/2007events/MSomerville_InConversation.asp Margaret Somerville – In Conversation] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20081205100541/http://www.unisa.edu.au/hawkecentre/events/2007events/MSomerville_InConversation.asp |date=2008-12-05 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Recent criticisms of this argument have been made by Timothy Laurie, who argues that both [[intersex]] conditions and [[infertility]] rates have always complicated links between biology, marriage and child-rearing.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news | title= Bigotry or Biology: The Hard Choice for an Opponent of Marriage Equality | first= Timothy | last= Laurie | newspaper= The Drum | year= 2015 | url= https://www.academia.edu/12765552}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A subset of heteronormativity is the concept of heteronormative temporality. This ideology states that the ultimate life goal for society is heterosexual marriage. Societal factors influence adults to search for a partner of the opposite sex to engage in heterosexual marriage with the goal of having children through the traditional nuclear family structure. Heteronormative temporality promotes [[abstinence]] only until marriage. Many American parents adhere to this heteronormative narrative, and teach their children accordingly. According to  Amy T. Schalet, it seems that the bulk of parent-child sex education revolves around [[Abstinence-only sex education|abstinence only]] practices in the United States, but this differs in other parts of the world.&lt;ref&gt;Schalet, Amy T. Not under My Roof: Parents, Teens, and the Culture of Sex. Chicago: U of Chicago, 2011. {{ISBN|9780226736181}}&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, George Washington University Professor Abby Wilkerson discusses the ways in which the healthcare and medicinal industries reinforce the views of heterosexual marriage in order to promote heteronormative temporality. The concept of heteronormative temporality extends beyond heterosexual marriage to include a pervasive system where heterosexuality is seen as a standard, and anything outside of that realm is not tolerated. Wilkerson explains that it dictates aspects of everyday life such as nutritional health, socio-economic status, personal beliefs, and traditional gender roles.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Wilkerson | first1 = Abby | year = 2013| title = I want to hold your hand: abstinence curricula, bioethics, and the silencing of desire | url = | journal = [[Journal of Medical Humanities]] | volume =  34| issue = | pages =  101–8| pmid = 23468394 | doi=10.1007/s10912-013-9213-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Transgressions==
{{Wikinews|Dr. Joseph Merlino on sexuality, insanity, Freud, fetishes and apathy}}

===Intersex people===
{{main|Intersex human rights|Intersex medical interventions}}
[[intersexuality|Intersex]] people have biological characteristics that are ambiguously either male or female. If such a condition is detected, intersex people in most present-day societies are almost always assigned a normative sex shortly after birth.&lt;ref&gt;Fausto-Sterling, Anne. 2000. Sexing the Body: Gender Politics and the Construction of Sexuality. New York: Basic Books.&lt;/ref&gt; Surgery (usually involving modification to the genitalia) is often performed in an attempt to produce an unambiguously male or female body, with the parents'—rather than the individual's—consent.&lt;ref&gt;[[Judith Butler|Butler, Judith]]. 2004. ''[[Undoing Gender]]''. New York: Routledge.&lt;/ref&gt; The child is then usually raised and enculturated as a [[cisgender]] [[heterosexual]] member of the [[sex assignment|assigned sex]], which may or may not match their emergent [[gender identity]] throughout life or some remaining [[sex characteristics]] (for example, chromosomes, genes or internal sex organs).&lt;ref&gt;Wilchins, Riki. 2002. 'A certain kind of freedom: power and the truth of bodies – four essays on gender.' In GenderQueer: Voices from beyond the sexual binary. Los Angeles: Alyson Books 23–66.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Transgender people===
Transgender people experience a mismatch between their [[gender identity]] or gender expression and their [[Sex assignment|assigned sex]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.stroud.gov.uk/info/gender_equality_scheme.pdf Stroud District Council "Gender Equality SCHEME AND ACTION PLAN 2007"] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080227114158/http://www.stroud.gov.uk/info/gender_equality_scheme.pdf |date=2008-02-27 }}, defines the state of being ''transgender'' as "Non-identification with, or non-presentation as, the sex (and assumed gender) one was assigned at birth."&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="glaad.org"&gt;Gay and Lesbian Alliance Against Defamation. [http://www.glaad.org/reference/transgender "GLAAD Media Reference Guide – Transgender glossary of terms"], "[[GLAAD]]", USA, May 2010. Retrieved on 2011-02-24. "An umbrella term for people whose gender identity and/or gender expression differs from what is typically associated with the sex they were assigned at birth."&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="usi"&gt;"[https://web.archive.org/web/20080608075230/http://www.usilgbt.org/index.php?categoryid=35 USI LGBT Campaign – Transgender Campaign]" (retrieved 11 January 2012) defines ''transgender people'' as "People who were assigned a sex, usually at birth and based on their genitals, but who feel that this is a false or incomplete description of themselves."&lt;/ref&gt; ''Transgender'' is also an [[umbrella term]] because, in addition to including [[trans men]] and [[trans women]] whose [[gender binary|binary gender]] identity is the opposite of their assigned sex (and who are sometimes specifically termed ''[[transsexual]]'' if they desire medical assistance to [[transitioning (transgender)|transition]]), it may include [[genderqueer]] people (whose identities are not exclusively masculine or feminine, but may, for example, be [[bigender]], [[pangender]], genderfluid, or agender).&lt;ref name="glaad.org" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Bilodeau"&gt;B Bilodeau, ''Beyond the gender binary: A case study of two transgender students at a Midwestern research university'', in the ''Journal of Gay &amp; Lesbian Issues in Education'' (2005): "Yet Jordan and Nick represent a segment of transgender communities that have largely been overlooked in transgender and student development research – individuals who express a non-binary construction of gender[.]"&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Layton"&gt;"[http://pep-web.org/document.php?id=paq.067.0341a Layton, Lynne. ''In Defense of Gender Ambiguity: Jessica Benjamin. Gender &amp; Psychoanalysis. I, 1996. Pp. 27–43'']". Retrieved 2007-03-06&lt;/ref&gt; Other definitions include [[third-gender]] people as transgender or conceptualize transgender people as a third gender,&lt;ref name="Stryker3G"&gt;Susan Stryker, Stephen Whittle, ''The Transgender Studies Reader'' ({{ISBN|1-135-39884-4}}), page 666: "The authors note that, increasingly, in social science literature, the term “third gender” is being replaced by or conflated with the newer term “transgender.”&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Chrisler"&gt;Joan C. Chrisler, Donald R. McCreary, ''Handbook of Gender Research in Psychology'', volume 1 (2010, {{ISBN|1-4419-1465-X}}), page 486: "Transgender is a broad term characterized by a challenge of traditional gender roles and gender identity[. …] For example, some cultures classify transgender individuals as a third gender, thereby treating this phenomenon as normative."&lt;/ref&gt; and infrequently the term is defined very broadly to include [[cross-dresser]]s.&lt;ref name="ReisnerEtAl"&gt;Sari L. Reisner, Kerith Conron, Matthew J. Mimiaga, Sebastien Haneuse, et al, ''Comparing in-person and online survey respondents in the US National Transgender Discrimination Survey: implications for transgender health research'', in ''LGBT Health'', June 2014, 1(2): 98-106. doi:10.1089/lgbt.2013.0018: "Transgender was defined broadly to cover those who transition from one gender to another as well as those who may not choose to socially, medically, or legally fully transition, including cross-dressers, people who consider themselves to be genderqueer, androgynous, and ..."&lt;/ref&gt;

Some transgender people seek [[sex reassignment therapy]], and may not behave according to the gender role imposed by society. Some societies consider transgender behavior a crime worthy of capital punishment, including [[Saudi Arabia]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ifge.org/news/1998/sept/nws9278.htm Saudis Arrest 5 Pakistani TGs]&lt;/ref&gt; and many other nations. In some cases, gay or lesbian people were forced to undergo sex change treatments to "fix" their sex or gender: in some [[Europe|European countries]] during the 20th century,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.slate.com/id/2660/ The Unkindest Cut | The science and ethics of castration]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.glbtq.com/social-sciences/turing_a,2.html Turing, Alan (1912–1954)] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090901020647/http://www.glbtq.com/social-sciences/turing_a%2C2.html |date=2009-09-01 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and in [[South Africa]] in the 1970s and 1980s.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.theguardian.com/world/2000/jul/29/chrismcgreal Gays tell of mutilation by apartheid army]&lt;/ref&gt;

In some countries, including North American&lt;ref name="cider"/&gt; and European countries, certain forms of violence against transgender people may be tacitly endorsed when prosecutors and juries refuse to investigate, prosecute, or convict those who perform the murders and beatings (currently, in some parts of North America and Europe).&lt;ref name="cider"&gt;{{cite journal |last=Frye|first=Phyllis|date=Fall 2000|title=The International Bill of Gender Rights vs. The Cide House Rules: Transgender people struggle with the courts over what clothing they are allowed to wear on the job, which restroom they are allowed to use on the job, their right to marry, and the very definition of their sex|journal=William and Mary Journal of Women and the Law|volume=7|pages=139–145}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="AmnestyUSA"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.amnestyusa.org/outfront/jamaica_report.html|title=OUTfront! Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual &amp; Transgendered Human Rights:"Battybwoys affi dead" Action against homophobia in Jamaica|date=May 7, 2004|publisher=AmnestyUSA.org|accessdate=4 June 2010|deadurl=yes|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100602192314/http://www.amnestyusa.org/outfront/jamaica_report.html|archivedate=2 June 2010|df=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.splcenter.org/intel/intelreport/article.jsp?pid=276 SPLCenter.org: 'Disposable People'&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Other societies have considered transgender behavior as a [[psychiatric illness]] serious enough to justify [[institutionalization]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.trans-health.com/2001/medicalization-of-transgenderism/|title=The Medicalization of Transgenderism - Trans Health|date=2001-07-18|newspaper=Trans Health|language=en-US|access-date=2017-02-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In medical communities with these restrictions, patients have the option of either suppressing transsexual behavior and conforming to the norms of their birth sex (which may be necessary to avoid social stigma or even violence) or by adhering strictly to the norms of their "new" sex in order to qualify for sex reassignment surgery and hormonal treatments. Attempts to achieve an ambiguous or "alternative" gender identity would not be supported or allowed.&lt;ref name="Todd"&gt;{{cite journal |last=Weiss |first=Jillian Todd |title=The Gender Caste System: Identity, Privacy and Heteronormativity |publisher=Tulane Law School |year=2001 |url=http://phobos.ramapo.edu/~jweiss/tulane.pdf |format=PDF|accessdate=2007-02-25 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Sometimes sex reassignment surgery is a requirement for an official gender change, and often "male" and "female" are the only choices available, even for intersex and transgender people.&lt;ref&gt;Sydney Morning Herald, March 18, 2010, Chi Tranter, "Norrie's 'ungendered' status withdrawn", http://news.smh.com.au/breaking-news-national/norries-ungendered-status-withdrawn-20100318-qhw5.html&lt;/ref&gt; For governments which allow only heterosexual marriages, official gender changes can have implications for related rights and privileges, such as child custody, inheritance, and medical decision-making.&lt;ref name="Todd" /&gt;
&lt;!--
**Temporarily removed for uncited refs and weasel words**
Some governments and official agencies have also been criticized{{By whom|date=May 2010}} as having heteronormative systems that classify people into "male" and "female" genders in problematic ways.{{Citation needed|date=April 2010}} Different jurisdictions use different definitions of gender, including by genitalia, DNA, hormone levels (including some official sports bodies), or birth sex (which means one's gender cannot ever be officially changed).--&gt;

==Homonormativity==
Homonormativity can refer to the perceived privileging of [[homosexuality]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | year = 2010  | chapter = Gender, Sexuality, Culture and the Closet in Theme Park Parades  | author = David Orzechowitz  | title = Gender and Sexuality in the Workplace  | editors = Christine L. Williams, Kirsten Dellinger  | publisher = Emerald Group  | isbn = 9781848553712  | page = 241  | chapter-url = https://books.google.com/books?id=JsXXD9n2zvAC&amp;pg=PA241&amp;dq=homonormative  |quote= The dominance of a '''homonormative''' culture in Parades subordinates male heterosexuality to male homosexuality.}}&lt;/ref&gt; or the perceived assimilation of heteronormative ideals and constructs into [[LGBTQ]] culture and individual identity.&lt;ref name=PSN&gt;{{cite web|title=Homonormativity |url=http://web.uvic.ca/psn/resources/terminology/homonormativity/ |website=web.uvic.ca |publisher=Positive Space Network |accessdate=3 January 2015 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150702182226/http://web.uvic.ca/psn/resources/terminology/homonormativity/ |archivedate=2 July 2015 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt; Specifically, Catherine Connell states that homonormativity "emphasizes commonality with the norms of heterosexual culture, including marriage, monogamy, procreation, and productivity".&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;Connell, Catherine. School's Out : Gay and Lesbian Teachers in the Classroom (1). Berkeley, US: University of California Press, 2014. ProQuest ebrary. Web. 15 March 2017.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Queer Twin Cities. Minneapolis, US: University of Minnesota Press, 2010. ProQuest ebrary. Web. 15 March 2017.&lt;/ref&gt; The term is almost always used in its latter sense, and was used prominently by Lisa Duggan in 2003,&lt;ref name="Duggan, Lisa 2003"&gt;Duggan, Lisa. The Twilight of Equality?: Neoliberalism, Cultural Politics, and the Attack On Democracy. Beacon Press, 2003.&lt;/ref&gt; although transgender studies scholar [[Susan Stryker]], in her article "Transgender History, Homonormativity, and Disciplinary",&lt;ref name="eds.a.ebscohost.com"&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://eds.a.ebscohost.com/eds/pdfviewer/pdfviewer?sid=0d090b57-5132-4ec4-b56b-a35ff1623e41@sessionmgr4010&amp;vid=3&amp;hid=4111|title=Transgender History, Homonormativity, and Disciplinarity.: Start Your Search!|website=eds.a.ebscohost.com|language=en|access-date=2017-02-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; noted that it was also used by transgender activists in the 1990s in reference to the imposition of gay/lesbian norms over the concerns of transgender people.&lt;ref name="Stryker, Susan 2008"&gt;[[Susan Stryker|Stryker, Susan]].  2008. "Transgender History, Homonormativity, and Disciplinarity". Radical History Review. (100): 145-157.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Cover, Rob. Queer Youth Suicide, Culture and Identity : Unliveable Lives?. Farnham, GB: Routledge, 2012. ProQuest ebrary. Web. 15 March 2017.&lt;/ref&gt; Transgender people were not included in healthcare programs combating the AIDS epidemic, and were often excluded from gay/ lesbian demonstrations in Washington.&lt;ref&gt;Stryker, Susan. ''Transgender History''. First Printing edition. Berkeley, CA: Seal Press, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; Homonormativity has also grown to include transnormativity, or "the pressure put on trans people to conform to traditional, oppositional sexist understandings of gender".&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Politics of Everybody|last=Lewis|first=Holly|publisher=Zed Books Ltd.|year=2016|isbn=978-1-78360-287-2|location=London|pages=222–230}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, homonormativity can be used today to cover or erase the radical politics of the queer community during the [[Gay liberation|Gay Liberation Movement]],&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Duggan, Lisa. "The New Homonormativity: The Sexual Politics of Neoliberalism." Materializing Democracy: Toward a Revitalized Cultural Politics. Ed. Dana D. Nelson and Russ Castronovo. N.p.: n.p., 2002. 175-94. Print. New Americanists.&lt;/ref&gt; by not only replacing these politics with more conservative goals like marriage equality and adoption rights, but also commercializing and mainstreaming queer subcultures.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Sex, Needs and Queer Culture|last=Alderson|first=David|publisher=Zed Books Ltd|year=2016|isbn=978-1-78360-512-5|location=London|pages=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Penny Griffin, Politics and International Relations lecturer at the [[University of New South Wales]], homonormativity upholds [[neoliberalism]] rather than critiquing [[monogamy]], procreation, and [[Gender binary|binary gender roles]] as inherently [[heterosexist]] and [[racist]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Griffin | first1 = Penny | year = 2007 | title = Sexing the Economy in a Neo-liberal World Order: Neo-liberal Discourse and the (Re)Production of Heteronormative Heterosexuality | url = | journal = British Journal of Politics and International Relations | volume = 9 | issue = 2| pages = 220–238 | doi=10.1111/j.1467-856x.2007.00280.x}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In this sense, homonormativity is deeply intertwined with the expansion and  maintenance of the internationally structured and structuring capitalistic worldwide system.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Stryker|first=Susan|year=2008|title=Transgender History, Homonormativity, and Disciplinarity|url=|journal=Radical Review History|volume=Issue 100|pages=145|via=Radical History Review}}&lt;/ref&gt; Duggan asserts that homonormativity fragments LGBT communities into hierarchies of worthiness, and that LGBT people that come the closest to mimicking heteronormative standards of gender identity are deemed most worthy of receiving rights. She also states that LGBT individuals at the bottom of this hierarchy (e.g. [[Bisexual community|bisexual people]], [[Transgender|trans people]], [[Genderqueer|non-binary people]], people of [[Gender systems#Non-European gender systems|non-Western genders]], [[intersex]] people, queers of color, queer sex workers) are seen as an impediment to this class of homonormative individuals receiving their rights.&lt;ref name="Duggan, Lisa 2003" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Ferguson, Roderick A. "Race-ing Homonormativity: Citizenship, Sociology, and Gay Identity." Black Queer Studies: A Critical Anthology. Ed. E. Patrick Johnson and Mae G. Henderson. N.p.: n.p., 2005. 52-67. Print. &lt;nowiki&gt;http://read.dukeupress.edu/content/black-queer-studies&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; For example, one empirical study found that in the Netherlands, transgender people and other gender non-conforming LGBT people are often looked down upon within their communities for not acting "normal." Those who do assimilate often become invisible in society and experience constant fear and shame about the non-conformers within their communities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Robinson | first1 = Brandon Andrew | year = 2012 | title = Is This What Equality Looks Like?: How Assimilation Marginalizes the Dutch LGBT Community | url = | journal = Sexuality Research &amp; Social Policy | volume = 9 | issue = 4| pages = 327–336 | doi = 10.1007/s13178-012-0084-3 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Stryker referenced theorist [[Jürgen Habermas]] and his view of the public sphere allowing for individuals to come together, as a group, to discuss diverse ideologies and by excluding the non-conforming LGBTQ community, society as a whole were undoubtedly excluding the gender-variant individuals from civic participation.&lt;ref name="eds.a.ebscohost.com"/&gt;

== Media representation ==
Five different studies have shown that gay characters appearing on TV decreases the prejudice among viewers.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2012/05/09/business/media/gay-on-tv-its-all-in-the-family.html|title=Gay on TV: It’s All in the Family|last=Stelter|first=Brian|date=2012-05-08|newspaper=The New York Times|issn=0362-4331|access-date=2016-12-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; Broadcasters are falling behind, with cable and streaming services being more inclusive and including characters who are lesbian, gay, bisexual and transgender.&lt;ref name="Egner"&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2015/10/28/arts/television/more-gay-and-transgender-characters-are-on-tv-report-shows.html|title=More Gay and Transgender Characters Are on TV, Report Shows|last=Egner|first=Jeremy|date=2015-10-27|newspaper=The New York Times|issn=0362-4331|access-date=2016-12-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; Cable and streaming services are lacking in diversity, according to a [[GLAAD]] report, with many of the LGBT characters being gay men (41% and 39% respectively).&lt;ref name="Egner"/&gt; The total number of LGBT characters counted on cable was reported to be 31% up from 2015, and bisexual representations saw an almost twofold increase.&lt;ref name="Egner" /&gt;

Intersex people are excluded almost completely. Intersex isn’t as rare as it seems; about 1% of the population is intersex in some way.&lt;ref name="Kerry, Stephen 2011"&gt;Kerry, Stephen (2011), ‘Representation of intersex in news media: the case of Kathleen Worrall’, ''Journal of Gender Studies,'' 20 (3), 263-77.&lt;/ref&gt; News medias outline what it means to be male or female, which causes a gap for anyone who doesn’t fall into those two categories.&lt;ref name="Kerry, Stephen 2011"/&gt; This has led newspapers to bring up issues like intersexuality in athletes due to sports being gendered, leaving the big question to everyone on what exactly is intersexuality. This was brought to worldwide attention with the case of Caster Semenya, where news spread on sporting officials having to determine whether she was to be considered female or male.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://edition.cnn.com/2009/HEALTH/08/20/gender.athlete.intersex/|title=Gender row athlete: What is intersexuality?  - CNN.com|last=CNN|first=By  Stephanie Busari|website=edition.cnn.com|access-date=2016-12-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Div col|colwidth=30em}}
* [[Bisexual erasure]]
* [[Complementarianism]]
* [[Discrimination against intersex people]]
* [[Egalitarianism]]
* [[Gender studies]]
* [[Intersex and LGBT]]
* [[List of transgender-related topics]]
* [[Monique Wittig]]
* [[Non-binary discrimination]]
* [[Normality (behavior)]]
* [[Paraphilia]]
* [[Structural functionalism]]
* [[Subject-SUBJECT consciousness]]
* [[The NeuroGenderings Network]]
* [[Transphobia]]
* [[Pink capitalism]]
{{div col end}}

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Bibliography==
* Dreyer, Yolanda. "Hegemony and the Internalisation of Homophobia Caused by Heteronormativity." Department of Practical Theology. 2007. University of Pretoria.5 May 2008 [http://www.hts.org.za/index.php/HTS/article/viewFile/197/130].
* Gray, Brandon."'Brokeback Mountain' most impressive of Tepid 2005."Box Office Mojo, LLC. 25 February 2006. 7 May 2008. [http://www.boxofficemojo.com/news/?id=2012&amp;p=.htm].
* Lovaas, Karen, and Mercilee M. Jenkins. "Charting a Path through the 'Desert of Nothing.'" Sexualities and Communication in Everyday Life: A Reader. 8 July 2006. Sage Publications Inc. 5 May 2008 [https://books.google.com/books?isbn=1412914434].
* Peele, Thomas. Composition Studies, Heteronormativity, and Popular Culture. 2001 Boise State University. 5 May 2008. [http://www.bgsu.edu/cconline/peele/CulturalStudies.html].
* The Pew Forum on Religion and Public Life. "U.S. Religious Landscape Survey." 7 May 2008. 7 May 2008. [http://religions.pewforum.org/reports].

==Further reading==
* [[Judith Butler]], ''Bodies That Matter''
* Judith Butler, ''[[Gender Trouble]]''
* [[Michel Foucault]], ''[[History of Sexuality]]''
* Chrys Ingraham, ''The Heterosexual Imaginary: Feminist Sociology and Theories of Gender'': Sociological Theory: July 1994
* [[Michael Warner]], ed. ''Fear of a Queer Planet''. Minneapolis MN: University of Minnesota Press, 1993.
* [http://phobos.ramapo.edu/~jweiss/tulane.pdf Jillian Todd Weiss: ''The Gender Caste System – Identity, Privacy, and Heteronormativity'']
* [http://sls.sagepub.com/content/20/3/349.abstract Recent academic article on legal challenges that have been made to the heteronormativity of marriage]
* [http://www.springerlink.com/content/75630n71288643t2/ "Heteronormativity and the European Court of Human Rights" examines heteronormativity in the context of human rights and judicial decision making]

&lt;!--{{LGBT|social=expanded}}--&gt;
{{LGBT}}
{{Discrimination}}

[[Category:Discrimination against LGBT people]]
[[Category:Feminism and sexuality]]
[[Category:Feminist terminology]]
[[Category:Genderqueer]]
[[Category:Gender studies]]
[[Category:Heterosexuality]]
[[Category:Homophobia]]
[[Category:Neologisms]]
[[Category:Postmodern theory]]
[[Category:Privilege (social inequality)]]
[[Category:Queer theory]]
[[Category:Sexism]]
[[Category:Sexuality and gender-related prejudices]]
[[Category:Sexual orientation and society]]
[[Category:Transgender]]
[[Category:Transphobia]]
[[Category:Words coined in the 1990s]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>