<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20211030175329|1052709487" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="162699" pageid="162699" ns="0" title="Heteronormativity"><revisions><rev timestamp="2021-11-18T02:44:12Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Ideology asserting heterosexuality as the only social norm}}
{{LGBT sidebar}}
{{Discrimination sidebar|state=collapsed}}
'''Heteronormativity''' is the concept that [[heterosexuality]] is the preferred or [[Norm (social)|normal]] mode of [[sexual orientation]].&lt;ref name="Harris"&gt;{{cite book|vauthors =Harris J, White V|title =A Dictionary of Social Work and Social Care|isbn = 978-0-19-251686-2 |publisher=[[Oxford University Press]] |year=2018|access-date=August 19, 2018|page=335|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=M3FGDwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT335}}&lt;/ref&gt; It assumes the [[gender binary]] (i.e., that there are only two distinct, opposite [[Gender|genders]]) and that sexual and marital relations are most fitting between people of opposite sex. A heteronormative view therefore involves alignment of biological [[sex]], [[Human sexuality|sexuality]], [[gender identity]] and [[gender role]]s. Heteronormativity is often linked to [[heterosexism]] and [[homophobia]].&lt;ref name="Harris"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Gorski"&gt;{{cite book|vauthors =Goodman RD, Gorski PC|title =Decolonizing "Multicultural" Counseling through Social Justice|isbn = 978-1-4939-1283-4 |publisher=[[Springer Publishing|Springer]]|year=2014|access-date=August 19, 2018|pages=28–30|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=MeYlBQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA28}}&lt;/ref&gt; The effects of societal heteronormativity on lesbian, gay and bisexual individuals can be examined as heterosexual or "straight" privilege.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Williford |first1=Beth |title=Heterosexual privilege |journal=Encyclopedia of Gender and Society |url=http://sk.sagepub.com/reference/gender/n208.xml}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Etymology==
[[Michael Warner]] popularized the term in 1991,&lt;ref name="warner1991"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Warner |first1=Michael |title=Introduction: Fear of a Queer Planet |journal=Social Text |date=1991 |issue=29 |pages=3–17 |jstor=466295 }}&lt;/ref&gt; in one of the first major works of [[queer theory]]. The concept's roots are in [[Gayle Rubin]]'s notion of the "sex/gender system" and [[Adrienne Rich]]'s notion of [[Compulsory Heterosexuality and Lesbian Existence|compulsory heterosexuality]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Rich |first1=Adrienne |title=Compulsory Heterosexuality and Lesbian Existence |journal=Signs |date=July 1980 |volume=5 |issue=4 |pages=631–660 |doi=10.1086/493756 |s2cid=143604951 }}&lt;/ref&gt; From the outset, theories of heteronormativity included a critical look at [[gender]]; Warner wrote that "every person who comes to a queer self-understanding knows in one way or another that her stigmatization is intricated with gender. ... Being queer ... means being able, more or less articulately, to challenge the common understanding of what gender difference means."&lt;ref name="warner1991"/&gt; [[Lauren Berlant]] and Warner further developed these ideas in their seminal essay, "Sex in Public."&lt;ref name="Berlant98"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Berlant |first1=Lauren |last2=Warner |first2=Michael |title=Sex in Public |journal=Critical Inquiry |date=1 January 1998 |volume=24 |issue=2 |pages=547–566 |doi=10.1086/448884 |url=https://www.journals.uchicago.edu/doi/10.1086/448884 |issn=0093-1896}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Discrimination==
Critics of heteronormative attitudes, such as [[Cathy J. Cohen]], [[Michael Warner]], and [[Lauren Berlant]],&lt;ref name="Berlant98" /&gt; argue that they are oppressive, stigmatizing, marginalizing of perceived deviant forms of sexuality and gender, and make self-expression more challenging when that expression does not conform to the norm.&lt;ref name=lovaas&gt;Lovaas, Karen, and Mercilee M. Jenkins. [https://books.google.com/books?id=fTRcvkxWV-IC&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage "Charting a Path through the 'Desert of Nothing.'"] Sexualities and Communication in Everyday Life: A Reader. 8 July 2006. Sage Publications Inc. 5 May 2008&lt;/ref&gt;{{page needed|date=August 2018}}&lt;ref name="OutatWork"/&gt; Heteronormativity describes how social institutions and policies reinforce the presumption that people are heterosexual and that gender and sex are natural binaries.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Gender in Communication|last = DeFrancisco|first = Victoria|publisher = SAGE Publication, Inc.|year = 2014|isbn = 978-1-4522-2009-3|location = U.S.A|pages = 16}}&lt;/ref&gt; Heteronormative culture privileges heterosexuality as normal and natural and fosters a climate where LGBT individuals are discriminated against in marriage, tax codes, and employment.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://www.rutgersuniversitypress.org/violence-against-queer-people/9780813573151|title=Violence against Queer People|last=Meyer|first=Doug|publisher=Rutgers University Press|year=2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=OutatWork&gt;{{cite book|last=Krupat|first=Kitty|title=Out at Work: Building a Gay-Labor Alliance|year=2001|publisher=U of Minnesota Press|isbn=978-0-8166-3741-6|pages=268}}&lt;/ref&gt; Following Berlant and Warner, Laurie and Stark also argue that the domestic "intimate sphere" becomes "the unquestioned non‐place that anchors heteronormative public discourses, especially those concerning marriage and adoption rights".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Laurie |first1=Timothy |last2=Stark |first2=Hannah |title=Reconsidering Kinship: Beyond the Nuclear Family with Deleuze and Guattari |journal=Cultural Studies Review |date=28 April 2011 |volume=18 |issue=1 |doi=10.5130/csr.v18i1.1612 |doi-access=free }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Against gay, lesbian, bisexual, and transgender individuals===
According to cultural anthropologist [[Gayle Rubin]], heteronormativity in mainstream society creates a "sex hierarchy" that graduates sexual practices from morally "good sex" to "bad sex". The hierarchy places reproductive, monogamous sex between committed heterosexuals as "good" and places any sexual acts and individuals who fall short of this standard lower until they fall into "bad sex". Specifically, this places long-term committed gay couples and promiscuous gays in between the two poles.&lt;ref name="thinkingsex"&gt;{{cite book|author=Rubin, Gayle|chapter=Thinking Sex: Notes for a Radical Theory of the Politics of Sexuality|editor=Vance, Carole|title=Pleasure and Danger: Exploring Female Sexuality|year=1993}}&lt;/ref&gt; Patrick McCreery, lecturer at [[New York University]], views this hierarchy as partially explanatory for the stigmatization of gay people for socially "deviant" sexual practices that are often practiced by straight people as well, such as consumption of pornography or sex in public places.&lt;ref name="OutatWork"/&gt; There are many studies of sexual orientation discrimination on college campuses.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Byron |first1=Reginald A. |last2=Lowe |first2=Maria R. |last3=Billingsley |first3=Brianna |last4=Tuttle |first4=Nathan |title=Performativity Double Standards and the Sexual Orientation Climate at a Southern Liberal Arts University |journal=Journal of Homosexuality |date=16 April 2017 |volume=64 |issue=5 |pages=671–696 |doi=10.1080/00918369.2016.1196994 |pmid=27267937 |s2cid=20963768 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

McCreery states that this heteronormative hierarchy carries over to the workplace, where gay, lesbian and bisexual individuals face discrimination such as anti-homosexual hiring policies or workplace discrimination that often leaves "lowest hierarchy" individuals such as transsexual people vulnerable to the most overt discrimination and unable to find work.&lt;ref name="OutatWork"/&gt;

Applicants and current employees can be legally passed over or fired for being non-heterosexual or ''perceived'' as non-heterosexual in many countries, such as the case with chain restaurant [[Cracker Barrel]], which [[Cracker Barrel#LGBT policies|garnered national attention in 1991]] after they fired an employee for being openly lesbian, citing their policy that employees with "sexual preferences that fail to demonstrate normal heterosexual values were inconsistent with traditional American values." Workers such as the fired employee and others, such as effeminate male waiters (allegedly described as the true targets),&lt;ref name="OutatWork"/&gt; were legally fired by work policies "transgressing" against "normal" heteronormative culture.&lt;ref name="OutatWork"/&gt;

Analysing the interconnectivity of heteronormativity and sexual employment discrimination, Mustafa Bilgehan Ozturk traces the impact of patriarchal practices and institutions on the workplace experiences of lesbian, gay and bisexual employees in a variety of contexts in Turkey, demonstrating further the specific historicities and localised power/knowledge formations that give rise to physical, professional and psycho-emotive acts of prejudice against sexual minorities.&lt;ref name="SexualOrientationDiscrimination"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Bilgehan Ozturk |first1=Mustafa |title=Sexual orientation discrimination: Exploring the experiences of lesbian, gay and bisexual employees in Turkey |journal=Human Relations |date=August 2011 |volume=64 |issue=8 |pages=1099–1118 |doi=10.1177/0018726710396249 |s2cid=59439253 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In some instances, different religions have been known to promote heteronormative beliefs through their teachings.&lt;ref name=":2"&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.soc.ucsb.edu/sexinfo/article/homosexuality-and-religion|title=Homosexuality and Religion {{!}} SexInfo Online|website=www.soc.ucsb.edu|access-date=2019-03-21|archive-date=2019-06-14|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190614100124/http://www.soc.ucsb.edu/sexinfo/article/homosexuality-and-religion|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to Sociology professors Samuel Perry and Kara Snawder from University of Oklahoma, multiple research studies in the past have shown that there can be and often is a link between the religious beliefs of Americans and homophobic behavior.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Perry |first1=Samuel L. |last2=Snawder |first2=Kara J. |title=Longitudinal Effects of Religious Media on Opposition to Same-Sex Marriage |journal=Sexuality &amp; Culture |date=December 2016 |volume=20 |issue=4 |pages=785–804 |doi=10.1007/s12119-016-9357-y |s2cid=148173061 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Out of the world's five major religions Christianity, Judaism, and Islam all uphold heteronormative views on marriage.&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt; Some examples of this playing out in recent years include the incident involving Kentucky clerk [[Kim Davis]], who refused to give marriage licenses to same-sex couples on the grounds that it violated her spiritual views,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last1=Blinder |first1=Alan |last2=Lewin |first2=Tamar |title=Clerk in Kentucky Chooses Jail Over Deal on Same-Sex Marriage |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2015/09/04/us/kim-davis-same-sex-marriage.html |work=The New York Times |date=3 September 2015 }}&lt;/ref&gt; as well as the Supreme Court case which ruled that a Colorado baker did not have to provide a wedding cake for a gay couple based on his religion.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.supremecourt.gov/opinions/17pdf/16-111_new2_22p3.pdf|title=Masterpiece Cake Shop, LTD v. Colorado Civil Rights Commission|date=March 21, 2019|website=supremecourt.gov|publisher=Supreme Court of the United States}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Relation to marriage and the nuclear family==
Modern family structures in the past and present vary from what was typical of the 1950s [[nuclear family]].  The families of the second half of the 19th century and early 20th century in the United States were characterized by the death of one or both parents for many American children.&lt;ref name="Coontz"&gt;Coontz, S. (1992){{fcn|date=April 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1985, the United States is estimated to have been home to approximately 2.5 million post-divorce, [[stepfamily]] households containing children.&lt;ref name=CGG&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Coleman |first1=Marilyn |last2=Ganong |first2=Lawrence H. |last3=Goodwin |first3=Chanel |title=The Presentation of Stepfamilies in Marriage and Family Textbooks: A Reexamination |journal=Family Relations |date=July 1994 |volume=43 |issue=3 |pages=289 |doi=10.2307/585420 |jstor=585420 }}&lt;/ref&gt; During the late 80s, almost 20% of families with children headed by a married couple were stepfamilies.&lt;ref name=CGG/&gt;

Over the past three decades rates of divorce, single parenting, and [[cohabitation]] have risen precipitously.&lt;ref name="Benfer"&gt;Benfer, Amy. [http://archive.salon.com/mwt/feature/2001/06/07/family_values/index.html The Nuclear Family Takes a Hit] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080522052539/http://archive.salon.com/mwt/feature/2001/06/07/family_values/index.html |date=2008-05-22 }}, Salon.com.  June 7, 2001&lt;/ref&gt; Nontraditional families (which diverge from "a middle-class family with a bread-winning father and a stay-at-home mother, married to each other and raising their biological children") constitute the majority of families in the [[United States]] and [[Canada]] today.&lt;ref name="Benfer"/&gt; [[Shared Earning/Shared Parenting Marriage]] (also known as Peer Marriage) where two heterosexual parents are both providers of resources and nurturers to children has become popular.  Modern families may also have single-parent headed families caused by divorce, separation or death, families who have two parents who are not married but have children, or families with same-sex parents. With [[artificial insemination]], [[surrogate mother]]s, and [[adoption]], families do not have to be formed by the heteronormative biological union of a male and a female. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title=The Widening Concept of Parent in Canada: Step- Parents, Same-Sex Partners, &amp; Parents by ART |journal=American University Journal of Gender, Social Policy &amp; the Law |year=2012 |last=Bala |first=Nicholas |last2=Ashbourne |first2=Christine |volume=30 |issue=3 |url=https://digitalcommons.wcl.american.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1577&amp;context=jgspl&amp;httpsredir=1&amp;referer= |accessdate=2021-07-04 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The consequences of these changes for the adults and children involved are heavily debated. In a 2009 [[Massachusetts]] spousal benefits case, developmental psychologist [[Michael Lamb (psychologist)|Michael Lamb]] testified that parental sexual orientation does not negatively affect childhood development. "Since the end of the 1980s... it has been well established that children and adolescents can adjust just as well in nontraditional settings as in traditional settings," he argued.&lt;ref&gt;Michael Lamb, Ph.D.: [https://www.webcitation.org/5n2qV1QIk?url=http://www.glad.org/uploads/docs/cases/2009-11-17-doma-aff-lamb.pdf Affidavit – United States District Court for the District of Massachusetts (2009)]&lt;/ref&gt;  However, columnist [[Maggie Gallagher]] argues that heteronormative social structures are beneficial to society because they are optimal for the raising of children.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.marriagedebate.com/pdf/SenateSept42003.pdf |title=Why Marriage Matters: The Case for Normal Marriage. Testimony before the U.S. Senate Subcommittee on the Constitution, Civil Rights, and Property Rights Hearing: "What is needed to defend the Bipartisan Defense of Marriage Act of 1996?" |author=Maggie Gallagher |publisher=Institute for Marriage and Public Policy |date=2003-09-04 |access-date=2012-05-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Australian-Canadian ethicist [[Margaret Somerville]] argues that "giving same-sex couples the right to found a family unlinks parenthood from biology".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unisa.edu.au/hawkecentre/events/2007events/MSomerville_InConversation.asp Margaret Somerville – In Conversation] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20081205100541/http://www.unisa.edu.au/hawkecentre/events/2007events/MSomerville_InConversation.asp |date=2008-12-05 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Recent criticisms of this argument have been made by Timothy Laurie, who argues that both [[intersex]] conditions and [[infertility]] rates have always complicated links between biology, marriage and child-rearing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last1=Laurie |first1=Timothy |title=Bigotry or biology: the hard choice for an opponent of marriage equality |url=https://www.abc.net.au/news/2015-06-03/laurie-bigotry-or-biology/6514156 |work=ABC News |date=3 June 2015 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

A subset of heteronormativity is the concept of heteronormative temporality. This ideology states that the ultimate life goal for society is heterosexual marriage. Societal factors influence adults to search for a partner of the opposite sex to engage in heterosexual marriage with the goal of having children through the traditional nuclear family structure. Heteronormative temporality promotes [[abstinence]] only until marriage. Many American parents adhere to this heteronormative narrative, and teach their children accordingly. According to Amy T. Schalet, it seems that the bulk of parent-child sex education revolves around [[Abstinence-only sex education|abstinence only]] practices in the United States, but this differs in other parts of the world.&lt;ref&gt;Schalet, Amy T. Not under My Roof: Parents, Teens, and the Culture of Sex. Chicago: U of Chicago, 2011. {{ISBN|978-0-226-73618-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, George Washington University Professor Abby Wilkerson discusses the ways in which the healthcare and medicinal industries reinforce the views of heterosexual marriage in order to promote heteronormative temporality. The concept of heteronormative temporality extends beyond heterosexual marriage to include a pervasive system where heterosexuality is seen as a standard, and anything outside of that realm is not tolerated. Wilkerson explains that it dictates aspects of everyday life such as nutritional health, socio-economic status, personal beliefs, and traditional gender roles.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Wilkerson |first1=Abby |title=I Want to Hold Your Hand: Abstinence Curricula, Bioethics, and the Silencing of Desire |journal=Journal of Medical Humanities |date=June 2013 |volume=34 |issue=2 |pages=101–108 |doi=10.1007/s10912-013-9213-0 |pmid=23468394 |s2cid=35152974 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Transgressions==
===Intersex people===
{{main|Intersex human rights|Intersex medical interventions}}
[[intersexuality|Intersex]] people have biological characteristics that are ambiguously either male or female. If such a condition is detected, intersex people in most present-day societies are almost always assigned a normative sex shortly after birth.&lt;ref&gt;Fausto-Sterling, Anne. 2000. Sexing the Body: Gender Politics and the Construction of Sexuality. New York: Basic Books.{{pn|date=February 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt; Surgery (usually involving modification to the genitalia) is often performed in an attempt to produce an unambiguously male or female body, with the parents'—rather than the individual's—consent.&lt;ref&gt;[[Judith Butler|Butler, Judith]]. 2004. ''[[Undoing Gender]]''. New York: Routledge.&lt;/ref&gt; The child is then usually raised and enculturated as a [[cisgender]] [[heterosexual]] member of the [[sex assignment|assigned sex]], which may or may not match their emergent [[gender identity]] throughout life or some remaining [[sex characteristics]] (for example, chromosomes, genes or internal sex organs).&lt;ref&gt;Wilchins, Riki. 2002. 'A certain kind of freedom: power and the truth of bodies – four essays on gender.' In GenderQueer: Voices from beyond the sexual binary. Los Angeles: Alyson Books 23–66.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Transgender people===
Transgender people experience a mismatch between their [[gender identity]] and their [[Sex assignment|assigned sex]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.stroud.gov.uk/info/gender_equality_scheme.pdf Stroud District Council "Gender Equality SCHEME AND ACTION PLAN 2007"] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080227114158/http://www.stroud.gov.uk/info/gender_equality_scheme.pdf |date=2008-02-27 }}, defines the state of being ''transgender'' as "Non-identification with, or non-presentation as, the sex (and assumed gender) one was assigned at birth."&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="glaad.org"&gt;Gay and Lesbian Alliance Against Defamation. [http://www.glaad.org/reference/transgender "GLAAD Media Reference Guide – Transgender glossary of terms"], "[[GLAAD]]", USA, May 2010. Retrieved on 2011-02-24. "An umbrella term for people whose gender identity and/or gender expression differs from what is typically associated with the sex they were assigned at birth."&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="usi"&gt;"[https://web.archive.org/web/20080608075230/http://www.usilgbt.org/index.php?categoryid=35 USI LGBT Campaign – Transgender Campaign]" (retrieved 11 January 2012) defines ''transgender people'' as "People who were assigned a sex, usually at birth and based on their genitals, but who feel that this is a false or incomplete description of themselves."&lt;/ref&gt; ''Transgender'' is also an [[umbrella term]] because, in addition to including [[trans men]] and [[trans women]] whose [[gender binary|binary gender]] identity is the opposite of their assigned sex (and who are sometimes specifically termed ''[[transsexual]]'' if they desire medical assistance to [[transitioning (transgender)|transition]]), it may include [[genderqueer]] people (whose identities are not exclusively masculine or feminine, but may, for example, be [[bigender]], [[pangender]], genderfluid, or agender).&lt;ref name="glaad.org" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Bilodeau"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Bilodeau |first1=Brent |title=Beyond the Gender Binary: A Case Study of Two Transgender Students at a Midwestern Research University |journal=Journal of Gay &amp; Lesbian Issues in Education |date=29 December 2005 |volume=3 |issue=1 |pages=29–44 |doi=10.1300/J367v03n01_05 |s2cid=144070536 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Layton"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Layton |first1=Lynne |title=In Defense of Gender Ambiguity: Jessica Benjamin. Gender &amp; Psychoanalysis. I, 1996. Pp. 27-43 |journal=Psychoanalytic Quarterly |volume=67 |issue=2 |year=1998 |pages=341 |url=https://www.pep-web.org/document.php?id=paq.067.0341a }}&lt;/ref&gt; Other definitions include [[third-gender]] people as transgender or conceptualize transgender people as a third gender,&lt;ref name="Stryker3G"&gt;Susan Stryker, Stephen Whittle, ''The Transgender Studies Reader'' ({{ISBN|1-135-39884-4}}), page 666: "The authors note that, increasingly, in social science literature, the term “third gender” is being replaced by or conflated with the newer term “transgender.”&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Chrisler"&gt;Joan C. Chrisler, Donald R. McCreary, ''Handbook of Gender Research in Psychology'', volume 1 (2010, {{ISBN|1-4419-1465-X}}), page 486: "Transgender is a broad term characterized by a challenge of traditional gender roles and gender identity[. …] For example, some cultures classify transgender individuals as a third gender, thereby treating this phenomenon as normative."&lt;/ref&gt; and infrequently the term is defined very broadly to include [[cross-dresser]]s.&lt;ref name="ReisnerEtAl"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Reisner |first1=Sari L. |last2=Conron |first2=Kerith |last3=Scout |first3=Nfn |last4=Mimiaga |first4=Matthew J. |last5=Haneuse |first5=Sebastien |last6=Austin |first6=S. Bryn |title=Comparing In-Person and Online Survey Respondents in the U.S. National Transgender Discrimination Survey: Implications for Transgender Health Research |journal=LGBT Health |date=June 2014 |volume=1 |issue=2 |pages=98–106 |doi=10.1089/lgbt.2013.0018 |pmid=26789619 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some transgender people seek [[sex reassignment therapy]], and may not behave according to the gender role imposed by society. Some societies consider transgender behavior a crime worthy of capital punishment, including [[Saudi Arabia]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ifge.org/news/1998/sept/nws9278.htm Saudis Arrest 5 Pakistani TGs]&lt;/ref&gt; and many other nations. In some cases, gay or lesbian people were forced to undergo sex change treatments to "fix" their [[sex or gender]]: in some [[Europe|European countries]] during the 20th century,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.slate.com/id/2660/ The Unkindest Cut | The science and ethics of castration]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.glbtq.com/social-sciences/turing_a,2.html Turing, Alan (1912–1954)] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090901020647/http://www.glbtq.com/social-sciences/turing_a%2C2.html |date=2009-09-01 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and in [[South Africa]] in the 1970s and 1980s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last1=McGreal |first1=Chris |title=Gays tell of mutilation by apartheid army |url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2000/jul/29/chrismcgreal |work=The Guardian |date=29 July 2000 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In some countries, including North American&lt;ref name="cider"/&gt; and European countries, certain forms of violence against transgender people may be tacitly endorsed when prosecutors and juries refuse to investigate, prosecute, or convict those who perform the murders and beatings.&lt;ref name="cider"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Frye |first1=Phyllis |title=The International Bill of Gender Rights vs. The Cider House Rules: Transgenders Struggle with the Courts Over What Clothing They Are Allowed to Wear on the Job, Which Restroom They are Allowed to Use on the Job, Their Right to Marry, and the Very Definition of Their Sex |journal=William &amp; Mary Journal of Race, Gender, and Social Justice |date=1 October 2000 |volume=7 |issue=1 |pages=133 |url=https://scholarship.law.wm.edu/wmjowl/vol7/iss1/6/ }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="AmnestyUSA"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.amnestyusa.org/outfront/jamaica_report.html|title=OUTfront! Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual &amp; Transgendered Human Rights:"Battybwoys affi dead" Action against homophobia in Jamaica|date=May 7, 2004|publisher=AmnestyUSA.org|access-date=4 June 2010|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100602192314/http://www.amnestyusa.org/outfront/jamaica_report.html|archive-date=2 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.splcenter.org/intel/intelreport/article.jsp?pid=276 |title=SPLCenter.org: 'Disposable People'&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt; |access-date=2004-06-10 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140711020836/http://www.splcenter.org/intel/intelreport/article.jsp?pid=276 |archive-date=2014-07-11 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; Other societies have considered transgender behavior as a [[psychiatric illness]] serious enough to justify [[institutionalization]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.trans-health.com/2001/medicalization-of-transgenderism/|title=The Medicalization of Transgenderism - Trans Health|date=2001-07-18|newspaper=Trans Health|language=en-US|access-date=2017-02-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In medical communities with these restrictions, patients have the option of either suppressing transsexual behavior and conforming to the norms of their birth sex (which may be necessary to avoid social stigma or even violence) or by adhering strictly to the norms of their "new" sex in order to qualify for sex reassignment surgery and hormonal treatments. Attempts to achieve an ambiguous or "alternative" gender identity would not be supported or allowed.&lt;ref name="Todd"&gt;{{cite journal |last=Weiss |first=Jillian Todd |title=The Gender Caste System: Identity, Privacy and Heteronormativity |journal=Law &amp; Sexuality|volume=10|pages=123–186|publisher=Tulane Law School |year=2001 |url=http://phobos.ramapo.edu/~jweiss/tulane.pdf |access-date=2007-02-25 |archive-url=https://wayback.archive-it.org/all/20070621130831/http://phobos.ramapo.edu/~jweiss/tulane.pdf |archive-date=2007-06-21 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; Sometimes sex reassignment surgery is a requirement for an official gender change, and often "male" and "female" are the only choices available, even for intersex and non-binary people.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last1=Tranter |first1=Chi |title=Norrie's 'ungendered' status withdrawn |url=https://www.smh.com.au/national/norries-ungendered-status-withdrawn-20100318-qhw5.html |work=The Sydney Morning Herald |date=18 March 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt; For governments which allow only heterosexual marriages, official gender changes can have implications for related rights and privileges, such as child custody, inheritance, and medical decision-making.&lt;ref name="Todd" /&gt;

==Homonormativity==
Homonormativity is a term which can refer to the privileging of [[homosexuality]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|year=2010|chapter=Gender, Sexuality, Culture and the Closet in Theme Park Parades|author=David Orzechowitz|title=Gender and Sexuality in the Workplace|editor=Christine L. Williams|editor2=Kirsten Dellinger|publisher=Emerald Group|isbn=978-1-8485-5371-2|page=241|chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=JsXXD9n2zvAC&amp;pg=PA241|quote=The dominance of a '''homonormative''' culture in Parades subordinates male heterosexuality to male homosexuality.}}&lt;/ref&gt; or the assimilation of heteronormative ideals and constructs into [[LGBTQ]] culture and individual identity.&lt;ref name=PSN&gt;{{cite web|title=Homonormativity |url=http://web.uvic.ca/psn/resources/terminology/homonormativity/ |website=web.uvic.ca |publisher=Positive Space Network |access-date=3 January 2015 |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150702182226/http://web.uvic.ca/psn/resources/terminology/homonormativity/ |archive-date=2 July 2015 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Specifically, Catherine Connell states that homonormativity "emphasizes commonality with the norms of heterosexual culture, including marriage, monogamy, procreation, and productivity".&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;Connell, Catherine. School's Out : Gay and Lesbian Teachers in the Classroom (1). Berkeley, US: University of California Press, 2014. ProQuest ebrary. Web. 15 March 2017.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Queer Twin Cities. Minneapolis, US: University of Minnesota Press, 2010. ProQuest ebrary. Web. 15 March 2017.&lt;/ref&gt; The term is almost always used in its latter sense, and was used prominently by Lisa Duggan in 2003,&lt;ref name="Duggan, Lisa 2003"&gt;Duggan, Lisa. The Twilight of Equality?: Neoliberalism, Cultural Politics, and the Attack On Democracy. Beacon Press, 2003.&lt;/ref&gt; although transgender studies scholar [[Susan Stryker]], in her article "Transgender History, Homonormativity, and Disciplinary",&lt;ref name="Stryker 2008"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Stryker |first1=Susan |title=Transgender History, Homonormativity, and Disciplinarity |journal=Radical History Review |date=1 January 2008 |volume=2008 |issue=100 |pages=145–157 |doi=10.1215/01636545-2007-026 }}&lt;/ref&gt; noted that it was also used by transgender activists in the 1990s in reference to the imposition of gay/lesbian norms over the concerns of transgender people.&lt;ref name="Stryker 2008"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Cover |first1=Rob |title=Queer Youth Suicide, Culture and Identity: Unliveable Lives? |date=2016 |publisher=Routledge |isbn=978-1-317-07255-3 }}{{pn|date=February 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt; Transgender people were not included in healthcare programs combating the AIDS epidemic, and were often excluded from gay/lesbian demonstrations in Washington, D.C.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Stryker |first1=Susan |title=Transgender History |date=2008 |publisher=Seal Press |isbn=978-1-58005-224-5 }}{{pn|date=February 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt; Homonormativity has also grown to include transnormativity, or "the pressure put on trans people to conform to traditional, oppositional sexist understandings of gender".&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Politics of Everybody|last=Lewis|first=Holly|publisher=Zed Books Ltd.|year=2016|isbn=978-1-78360-287-2|location=London|pages=222–230}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, homonormativity can be used today to cover or erase the radical politics of the queer community during the [[Gay liberation|Gay Liberation Movement]],&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Duggan |first1=Lisa |chapter=The New Homonormativity: The Sexual Politics of Neoliberalism |pages=175–194 |chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=O_7qRCNxzQcC&amp;pg=PA175 |editor1-last=Castronovo |editor1-first=Russ |editor2-last=Nelson |editor2-first=Dana D. |title=Materializing Democracy: Toward a Revitalized Cultural Politics |date=2002 |publisher=Duke University Press |isbn=978-0-8223-8390-1 }}&lt;/ref&gt; by not only replacing these politics with more conservative goals like marriage equality and adoption rights, but also commercializing and mainstreaming queer subcultures.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Sex, Needs and Queer Culture|last=Alderson|first=David|publisher=Zed Books Ltd|year=2016|isbn=978-1-78360-512-5|location=London}}{{pn|date=February 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Penny Griffin, Politics and International Relations lecturer at the [[University of New South Wales]], homonormativity upholds [[neoliberalism]] rather than critiquing the enforcement of [[monogamy]], procreation, and [[Gender binary|binary gender roles]] as inherently [[heterosexist]] and [[racist]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Griffin |first1=Penny |title=Sexing the Economy in a Neo-Liberal World Order: Neo-Liberal Discourse and the (Re)Production of Heteronormative Heterosexuality |journal=The British Journal of Politics and International Relations |date=May 2007 |volume=9 |issue=2 |pages=220–238 |doi=10.1111/j.1467-856x.2007.00280.x |s2cid=144295490 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In this sense, homonormativity is deeply intertwined with the expansion and  maintenance of the internationally structured and structuring capitalistic worldwide system.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Stryker |first1=S. |title=Transgender History, Homonormativity, and Disciplinarity |journal=Radical History Review |date=1 January 2008 |volume=2008 |issue=100 |pages=145–157 |doi=10.1215/01636545-2007-026 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Duggan asserts that homonormativity fragments LGBT communities into hierarchies of worthiness, and that LGBT people that come the closest to mimicking heteronormative standards of gender identity are deemed most worthy of receiving rights. She also states that LGBT individuals at the bottom of this hierarchy (e.g. [[Bisexual community|bisexual people]], [[Transgender|trans people]], [[Genderqueer|non-binary people]], people of [[Gender systems#Non-European gender systems|non-Western genders]], [[intersex]] people, queers of color, queer sex workers) are seen as an impediment to this class of homonormative individuals receiving their rights.&lt;ref name="Duggan, Lisa 2003" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Ferguson |first=Roderick A. |chapter=Race-ing Homonormativity: Citizenship, Sociology, and Gay Identity |title=Black Queer Studies: A Critical Anthology |editor=E. Patrick Johnson|editor2=Mae G. Henderson|publisher=Duke University Press|date=2005|pages=52–67|isbn=978-0-8223-8722-0|doi=10.1215/9780822387220}}&lt;/ref&gt; For example, one empirical study found that in the Netherlands, transgender people and other gender non-conforming LGBT people are often looked down upon within their communities for not acting "normal". Those who do assimilate often become invisible in society and experience constant fear and shame about the non-conformers within their communities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Robinson |first1=Brandon Andrew |title=Is This What Equality Looks Like?: How Assimilation Marginalizes the Dutch LGBT Community |journal=Sexuality Research and Social Policy |date=December 2012 |volume=9 |issue=4 |pages=327–336 |doi=10.1007/s13178-012-0084-3 |s2cid=146137993 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Stryker referenced theorist [[Jürgen Habermas]] and his view of the public sphere allowing for individuals to come together, as a group, to discuss diverse ideologies and by excluding the non-conforming LGBTQ community, society as a whole were undoubtedly excluding the gender-variant individuals from civic participation.&lt;ref name="Stryker 2008"/&gt;

== Media representation ==
Five different studies have shown that gay characters appearing on TV decreases the prejudice among viewers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last1=Stelter |first1=Brian |title=Gay on TV: It's All in the Family |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2012/05/09/business/media/gay-on-tv-its-all-in-the-family.html |work=The New York Times |date=9 May 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Cable and streaming services are beginning to include more characters who are lesbian, gay, bisexual and transgender than broadcast television.&lt;ref name="Egner"&gt;{{cite news |last1=Egner |first1=Jeremy |title=More Gay and Transgender Characters Are on TV, Report Shows |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2015/10/28/arts/television/more-gay-and-transgender-characters-are-on-tv-report-shows.html |work=The New York Times |date=27 October 2015 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Cable and streaming services are lacking in diversity, according to a [[GLAAD]] report, with many of the LGBT characters being gay men (41% and 39% respectively).&lt;ref name="Egner"/&gt; The total number of LGBT characters counted on cable was reported to be 31% up from 2015, and bisexual representations saw an almost twofold increase.&lt;ref name="Egner" /&gt;

Intersex people are excluded almost completely from television, though about 1% of the population is intersex.&lt;ref name="Kerry, Stephen 2011"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Kerry |first1=Stephen |title=Representation of intersex in news media: the case of Kathleen Worrall |journal=Journal of Gender Studies |date=September 2011 |volume=20 |issue=3 |pages=263–277 |doi=10.1080/09589236.2011.593325 |s2cid=144222294 }}&lt;/ref&gt; News medias outline what it means to be male or female, which causes a gap for anyone who doesn't fall into those two categories.&lt;ref name="Kerry, Stephen 2011"/&gt; Newspapers have covered the topic of intersex athletes with the case of [[Caster Semenya]], where news spread on sporting officials having to determine whether she was to be considered female or male.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://edition.cnn.com/2009/HEALTH/08/20/gender.athlete.intersex/|title=Gender row athlete: What is intersexuality? |first= Stephanie |last=Busari|website=edition.cnn.com|access-date=2016-12-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Those who do not identify as either woman or man are gender non-binary, or gender non-conforming.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Vijlbrief |first1=Afiah |last2=Saharso |first2=Sawitri |last3=Ghorashi |first3=Halleh |title=Transcending the gender binary: Gender non-binary young adults in Amsterdam |journal=Journal of LGBT Youth |date=2 January 2020 |volume=17 |issue=1 |pages=89–106 |doi=10.1080/19361653.2019.1660295 |doi-access=free }}&lt;/ref&gt; States in the United States are increasingly legalizing this "third" gender on official government documents as the existence of this identity is continuously debated among individuals.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last1=Harmon |first1=Amy |title=Which Box Do You Check? Some States Are Offering a Nonbinary Option |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2019/05/29/us/nonbinary-drivers-licenses.html |work=The New York Times |date=29 May 2019 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The controversy has resulted in minimal representation in the media, but recent television shows that have featured non-binary individuals include ''Ru Paul's Drag Race'' and ''The Fosters''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite thesis |last1=Higley |first1=Diana |title=Bending the Binary: Effects of Nonbinary Gender Media Representations on Disposition Formation and Media Enjoyment |date=1 May 2019 |url=https://stars.library.ucf.edu/etd/6290/ }}&lt;/ref&gt; Members of the LGBTQ community claim that representation in media of non-binary people has not expanded to the extent of gender-conforming trans people.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://efniks.com/the-deep-dive-pages/2018/10/17/gender-isnt-a-haircut-how-representation-of-nonbinary-people-of-color-requires-more-than-white-androgyny|title=Gender Isn't A Haircut: How Representation of Nonbinary People of Color Requires More Than White Androgyny|website=EFNIKS.com|language=en-US|access-date=2020-04-07}}{{Dead link|date=March 2021 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In today's media, specifically television, heterosexual character are used more often than homosexual characters. In 2018 only 8.8% of broadcast television has a LGBTQ person on the show.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |doi=10.4135/9781483371283.n173 |chapter=GLAAD |title=The SAGE Encyclopedia of LGBTQ Studies |year=2016 |isbn=978-1-4833-7130-6 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Media portrays heterosexuality as "normal" in today's society so we see less homosexuality on television because of this.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Critical Media Studies: An Introduction|last=Ott, Matt|first=Brian L., Robert L|publisher=Wiley Blackwell|year=2014|isbn=978-1-118-55397-8|location=Chichester|pages=216–222}}&lt;/ref&gt; There are many stereotypes that come with this, as it can be seen in advertising, newspapers, radio, and television.  For example, mainstream media promote the idea that gay men are more likely to be attracted to advertisements that sell expensive, flamboyant, and possibly feminine products because of their assumed attitudes and way of life.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Kates |first1=Steven M. |title=Making the Ad Perfectly Queer: Marketing 'Normality' to the Gay Men's Community? |journal=Journal of Advertising |date=March 1999 |volume=28 |issue=1 |pages=25–37 |doi=10.1080/00913367.1999.10673574 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Homosexuals and heterosexuals are also differentiated in the movies as well. Homosexual characters are predominantly seen in movies with issues regarding sexuality and the character is presented as homosexual.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title=America on film: representing race, class, gender, and sexuality at the movies |journal=Choice Reviews Online |date=1 August 2009 |volume=46 |issue=12 |pages=46–6690–46-6690 |doi=10.5860/choice.46-6690 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Television shows are also another aspect of media where there are stereotypes and negatively represented homosexuals. For example, the TV show ''Modern Family'' has two gay characters that are married and have a small adopted child together. Some may see this relationship as degrading and stereotypical of how the mainstream media views homosexuals. The show's sexual politics are considered fake {{by whom?|date=May 2021}} because of how their relationship is portrayed as overly colorful and excessively put together.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first1=Tison |last1=Pugh |chapter=Conservative Narratology, Queer Politics, and the Humor of Gay Stereotypes in Modern Family |title=The Queer Fantasies of the American Family Sitcom |year=2019 |pages=161–189 |publisher=Rutgers University Press |isbn=978-0-8135-9175-9 |doi=10.36019/9780813591759-007 |jstor=j.ctt1trkkgj.9 }}&lt;/ref&gt; 

More LGBT content was produced in the media in 2018.&lt;ref name=":3"&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.theverge.com/2018/10/26/18028908/glaad-report-television-tv-2018-lgbtq-diversity-gay-bisexual-trans-media-representation|title=2018 saw record growth in LGBTQ roles on television|last=Liao|first=Shannon|date=2018-10-26|website=The Verge|access-date=2019-03-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to GLAAD'S Annual Where We Are on TV Report, which records LGBTQ+ representation on television, the number of queer characters on TV shows rose 8.8%.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.glaad.org/whereweareontv18|title=Where We Are on TV Report - 2018|date=2018-10-23|website=GLAAD|language=en|access-date=2019-03-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; Queer people of color also saw an increase in screen time; they outnumbered white queer people on television for the first time in the reports history.&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt;

==See also==
{{Div col|colwidth=22em}}
* [[Amatonormativity]]
* [[Bisexual erasure]]
* [[Complementarianism]]
* [[Compulsory heterosexuality]]
* [[Discrimination against intersex people]]
* [[Egalitarianism]]
* [[Gender studies]]
* [[Intersex and LGBT]]
* [[List of transgender-related topics]]
* [[Monique Wittig]]
* [[Non-binary discrimination]]
* [[Normality (behavior)]]
* [[Pink capitalism]]
* [[Straightwashing]]
* [[Structural functionalism]]
* [[Subject-SUBJECT consciousness]]
* [[The NeuroGenderings Network]]
* [[Transphobia]]
{{div col end}}

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Bibliography==
* Berlant, Lauren, and Michael Warner. (1998) “Sex in Public.” Critical Inquiry, vol. 24, no. 2, pp. 547–566. JSTOR, www.jstor.org/stable/1344178.
* {{cite journal |last1=Dreyer |first1=Yolanda |title=Hegemony and the internalisation of homophobia caused by heteronormativity |journal=HTS Teologiese Studies |date=5 May 2007 |volume=63 |issue=1 |pages=1–18 |doi=10.4102/hts.v63i1.197 |doi-access=free }}
* Gray, Brandon."'Brokeback Mountain' most impressive of Tepid 2005."Box Office Mojo, LLC. 25 February 2006. 7 May 2008. [http://www.boxofficemojo.com/news/?id=2012&amp;p=.htm].
* {{cite book |last1=Lovaas |first1=Karen E. |last2=Jenkins |first2=Mercilee M. |title=Sexualities and Communication in Everyday Life: A Reader |date=2007 |publisher=SAGE |isbn=978-1-4129-1443-7 }}
* Peele, Thomas. Composition Studies, Heteronormativity, and Popular Culture. 2001 Boise State University. 5 May 2008. [http://www.bgsu.edu/cconline/peele/CulturalStudies.html].
* The Pew Forum on Religion and Public Life. "U.S. Religious Landscape Survey." 7 May 2008. 7 May 2008. [http://religions.pewforum.org/reports].

==Further reading==
* [[Judith Butler]], ''Bodies That Matter''
* Judith Butler, ''[[Gender Trouble]]''
* [[Michel Foucault]], ''[[History of Sexuality]]''
* {{cite journal |last1=Ingraham |first1=Chrys |title=The Heterosexual Imaginary: Feminist Sociology and Theories of Gender |journal=Sociological Theory |date=1994 |volume=12 |issue=2 |pages=203–219 |doi=10.2307/201865 |jstor=201865 |citeseerx=10.1.1.470.737 }}
* [[Michael Warner]], ed. ''Fear of a Queer Planet''. Minneapolis MN: University of Minnesota Press, 1993.
* {{cite journal |last1=Weiss |first1=Jillian Todd |title=The Gender Caste System: Identity, Privacy, and Heteronormativity |journal=Tulane Journal of Law and Sexuality |date=2001 |volume=10 |url=https://journals.tulane.edu/tjls/article/view/2751 }}
* {{cite journal |last1=Johnson |first1=Paul |title=Challenging the Heteronormativity of Marriage: The Role of Judicial Interpretation and Authority |journal=Social &amp; Legal Studies |date=September 2011 |volume=20 |issue=3 |pages=349–367 |doi=10.1177/0964663911406314 |s2cid=143823322 }}
* {{cite journal |last1=Johnson |first1=Paul |title=Heteronormativity and the European Court of Human Rights |journal=Law and Critique |date=February 2012 |volume=23 |issue=1 |pages=43–66 |doi=10.1007/s10978-011-9096-z |s2cid=145339435 }}

&lt;!--{{LGBT|social=expanded}}--&gt;
{{LGBT}}
{{Discrimination}}

[[Category:Feminist terminology]]
[[Category:Social justice terminology]]
[[Category:Neologisms]]
[[Category:1990s neologisms]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>