<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20191122202000|927488995" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="2162835" pageid="2162835" ns="0" title="Racism in the United States"><revisions><rev timestamp="2019-11-22T20:20:03Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{use American English|date=October 2018}}
{{use mdy dates|date=October 2017}}

{{Segregation}}

'''Racism in the United States''' has existed since the [[Colonial history of the United States|colonial era]], when [[white Americans]] were given legally or socially sanctioned privileges and rights while these same rights were denied to other [[Race and ethnicity in the United States|races and minorities]]. [[European Americans]]—particularly affluent [[white Anglo-Saxon Protestant]]s—enjoyed exclusive privileges in matters of education, [[immigration]], voting rights, citizenship, land acquisition, and criminal procedure throughout [[History of the United States|American history]]. Non-[[Protestantism|Protestant]] immigrants from Europe, particularly [[Irish people]], [[Poles]], and [[Italians]], often suffered xenophobic exclusion and other forms of ethnicity-based discrimination in American society until the late 19th century and early 20th century. In addition, groups like [[Jews]] and [[Arabs]] have faced continuous discrimination in the United States, and as a result, some people who belong to these groups do not identify as white. [[Asian Americans|East, South, and Southeast Asians]] have similarly faced racism in America.

Major racially and ethnically structured institutions include [[Slavery in the United States|slavery]], [[Racial segregation in the United States|segregation]], [[Native American reservations]], [[Native American boarding schools]], immigration and [[naturalization]] laws, and [[internment camps]].{{NoteTag|[[Internment camps]] are particularly associated with [[World War II]], but they also existed during [[World War I]]. Most significant was the [[Japanese American internment]] of 120,000 Japanese Americans during World War II. Additionally, almost 11,000 [[German Americans]] [[German American internment|were interned]] during World War II, and some [[Italian American internment|were also interned]].}} Formal racial discrimination was largely banned in the mid-20th century and it came to be perceived as being socially and morally unacceptable. Racial politics remains a major phenomenon, and racism continues to be [[Racial inequality in the United States|reflected in socioeconomic inequality]].{{NoteTag|In his 2009 visit to the US, the [UN] Special Rapporteur on Racism noted that "Socio-economic indicators show that poverty and race and ethnicity continue to overlap in the United States. This reality is a direct legacy of the past, in particular slavery, segregation, the forcible resettlement of Native Americans, which was confronted by the United States during the civil rights movement. However, whereas the country managed to establish equal treatment and non-discrimination in its laws, it has yet to redress the socioeconomic consequences of the historical legacy of racism."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author = CERD Task Force of the US Human Rights Network |title = Universal Periodic Review Joint Reports: United States of America |chapter = From Civil Rights to Human Rights: Implementing US Obligations Under the International Convention on the Elimination of All forms of Racial Discrimination (ICERD) |date = August 2010 |page = 44 }}&lt;/ref&gt;}}&lt;ref&gt;Henry, P. J., David O. Sears. Race and Politics: The Theory of Symbolic Racism. University of California, Los Angeles. 2002.&lt;/ref&gt; Racial stratification continues to occur in [[Racial wage gap in the United States|employment]], housing, education, lending, and government.

In the view of the [[United Nations]] and the [[U.S. Human Rights Network]], "discrimination in the United States permeates all aspects of life and extends to all [[people of color|communities of color]]."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title = Universal Periodic Review Joint Reports: United States of America |author = U.S. Human Rights Network |date = August 2010 |page = 8 |chapter = The United States of America: Summary Submission to the UN Universal Periodic Review }}&lt;/ref&gt; While the nature of the views held by average Americans has changed significantly over the past several decades, surveys by organizations such as ABC News have found that even in modern America, large sections of Americans admit to holding discriminatory viewpoints. For example, a 2007 article by ABC stated that about one in ten admitted to holding prejudices against Hispanic and Latino Americans and about one in four did so regarding Arab-Americans.&lt;ref name="abc" /&gt; A 2018 [[YouGov]]/[[The Economist|Economist]] poll found that 17% of Americans oppose [[interracial marriage]], with 19% of members of "other" ethnic groups, 18% of blacks, 17% of whites, and 15% of [[Hispanic and Latino Americans|Hispanics]] opposing it.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = https://d25d2506sfb94s.cloudfront.net/cumulus_uploads/document/y3tke5cxwy/econTabReport.pdf |title = The Economist/YouGov Poll |date=March 10–13, 2018 |website = [[YouGov]] |access-date=June 29, 2018 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some Americans saw the presidential candidacy of [[Barack Obama]], who served as [[president of the United States]] from 2009 to 2017 and was the nation's first [[Black people|black]] president, as a sign that the nation had entered a new, post-racial era.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = https://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=18489466 |title = A New, 'Post-Racial' Political Era in America |website=NPR.org |accessdate=2016-01-02 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":02"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Dawson |first1=Michael C. |last2=Bobo|first2=Lawrence D.|year=2009 |title=One Year Later and the Myth of a Post-Racial Society |url = https://dash.harvard.edu/handle/1/10347165 |journal=Du Bois Review |volume=6 |issue=2 |page = 247 |doi = 10.1017/S1742058X09990282 |access-date=2016-01-01 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Right-wing populism|right-wing populist]] radio and television host [[Lou Dobbs]] claimed in November 2009, "We are now in a 21st-century post-partisan, post-racial society."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = http://mediamatters.org/video/2009/11/12/dobbs-calls-on-listeners-to-rise-above-partisan/156917 |title = Dobbs calls on listeners to rise above "partisan and racial element that dominates politics" |website=Media Matters for America |accessdate=2016-01-02 |date=2009-11-12 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Two months later, [[Chris Matthews]], an [[MSNBC]] host, said that President Obama, "is post-racial by all appearances. You know, I forgot he was black tonight for an hour."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = http://www.realclearpolitics.com/video/2010/01/27/msnbcs_matthews_on_obama_i_forgot_he_was_black_tonight.html |title = MSNBC's Matthews On Obama: "I Forgot He Was Black Tonight" {{!}} RealClearPolitics |website=www.realclearpolitics.com |accessdate=2016-01-02 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The election of President [[Donald Trump]] in 2016 has been viewed by some commentators as a [[White backlash|racist backlash]] against the election of Barack Obama.&lt;ref name=":2"&gt;{{cite journal |url = https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2017/10/the-first-white-president-ta-nehisi-coates/537909/ |title = The First White President |last=Coates |first=Ta-Nehisi |author-link=Ta-Nehisi Coates |date=October 2017 |journal=The Atlantic |access-date=June 29, 2018 |quote=It is often said that Trump has no real ideology, which is not true—his ideology is white supremacy, in all its truculent and sanctimonious power.}}{{POV statement|date=February 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the 2010s, American society has continued to experience high levels of racism and discrimination. One new phenomenon has been the rise of the [[Alt-right|"alt-right" movement]]: a [[White nationalism|white nationalist]] coalition that seeks the expulsion of [[Sexual minority|sexual]] and [[Minority group|racial minorities]] from the United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = https://www.washingtonpost.com/amphtml/news/book-party/wp/2017/11/03/where-the-alt-right-wants-to-take-america-with-or-without-trump/ |title = Where the alt-right wants to take America — with or without Trump |last=Lozada|first=Carlos|date=November 3, 2017|website=[[Washington Post]]|access-date=April 3, 2018 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In August 2017, these groups attended a [[Unite the Right rally|rally]] in Charlottesville, Virginia, intended to unify various white nationalist factions. During the rally, a white supremacist demonstrator drove his car into a group of counter-protesters, killing one person and injuring 19.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/morning-mix/wp/2016/06/03/ugly-bloody-scenes-in-san-jose-as-protesters-attack-trump-supporters-outside-rally/ |title=Ugly, bloody scenes in San Jose as protesters attack Trump supporters outside rally |website=Washington Post }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite newspaper |url = https://www.nytimes.com/2017/12/14/us/charlottesville-fields-white-supremists.html/ |title=Murder Charge Increases in Charlottesville Protest Death |journal=The New York Times|date=2017-12-14|last1=Spencer|first1=Hawes|last2=Pérez-Peña|first2=Richard }}&lt;/ref&gt; Since the mid-2010s, the [[United States Department of Homeland Security|Department of Homeland Security]] and the [[Federal Bureau of Investigation]] have considered [[White supremacy|white supremacist]] violence to be the leading threat of domestic terrorism in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = https://foreignpolicy.com/2017/08/14/fbi-and-dhs-warned-of-growing-threat-from-white-supremacists-months-ago/ |title=FBI and DHS Warned of Growing Threat From White Supremacists Months Ago |last=Winter|first=Jana|date=August 14, 2017|website=Foreign Policy |access-date=April 19, 2018 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = https://www.documentcloud.org/documents/3924852-White-Supremacist-Extremism-JIB.html |title=White Supremacist Extremism Poses Persistent Threat of Lethal Violence|last=|first=|date=May 10, 2017|website=FBI Intelligence Bulletin|access-date=April 19, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Racism==
Racism is a systematized form of oppression by one race against another. Prejudicial attitudes existed between races for thousands of years, but systematized racial oppression first arose in the 1600s.  Before this, slaves in various cultures were taken without racism as the basis&amp;nbsp;– slaves were usually taken as a result of military conquest. But when European traders found that their superior technology in sailing ships and firearms gave them a tremendous advantage in Africa, they began plundering Africa's wealth and taking slaves. Slavers and slave owners tried to convince themselves that their African slaves had no previous culture, that they had been living as savages, which was false. White European Americans involved in the slave industry tried to justify their economic exploitation of black people by creating a [[Scientific racism|"scientific" theory of white superiority and black inferiority]]. One such slave owner was Thomas Jefferson, and it was his call for science to determine the obvious “inferiority” of blacks that is regarded as “an extremely important stage in the evolution of scientific racism."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Garrod |first1=Joel Z.|title=A Brave Old World: An Analysis of Scientific Racism and BiDil |journal=McGill Journal of Medicine |date= |url=https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2687899/}}&lt;/ref&gt; This was the start of systematized racism in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |jstor=41202851 |title=Uprooting Racism and Racists in the United States |last=Boggs |first=James |authorlink=James Boggs (activist) |journal=The Black Scholar |publisher=Paradigm Publishers |date=October 1970 |volume=2 |number=2 |pages=2–5|doi=10.1080/00064246.1970.11431000 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== African Americans{{anchor|African-Americans}} ==
{{See also|African-American history}}

=== Pre-Civil War ===
==== Atlantic slave trade ====

[[File:Slave Auction Ad.jpg|thumb|Right|Reproduction of a handbill advertising a slave auction in [[Charleston, South Carolina]], in 1769.]]
The [[Atlantic slave trade]] had an economic foundation. The dominant ideology among the European elite who structured national policy throughout the age of the Atlantic slave trade was [[mercantilism]], the belief that national policy should be centered around amassing military power and economic wealth. Colonies were sources of mineral wealth and crops, to be used to the colonizing country's advantage.&lt;ref name="Darity Jr."&gt;{{cite book|last=Darity Jr.|first=William|title=African Americans in the U.S. Economy (Africa, Europe, and the Origins of Uneven Development: The Role of Slavery)|year=2005|publisher=Rowman and Littlefield|location=Lanham, Md.|pages=15–16|url=http://cas.umkc.edu/econ/economics/faculty/Forstater/688/Reading/Black%20Political%20Economy/AfricaEuropeOriginsUnevenDevelopment.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; Using Europeans for labor in the colonies proved unsustainably expensive, as well as harmful to the domestic labor supply of the colonizing countries. Instead, the colonies imported African slaves, who were "available in large numbers at prices that made [[Plantation economy|plantation agriculture]] in the Americas profitable".&lt;ref&gt;"Darity Jr., 2005"&lt;/ref&gt;

It is also argued that along with the economic motives underlying slavery in the Americas, European world schemas played a large role in the enslavement of Africans. According to this view, the European in-group for humane behavior included the sub-continent, while African and American Indian cultures had a more localized definition of "an insider". While neither schema has inherent superiority, the technological advantage of Europeans became a resource to disseminate the conviction that underscored their schemas, that non-Europeans could be enslaved. With the capability to spread their schematic representation of the world, Europeans could impose a social contract, morally permitting three centuries of African slavery. While the disintegration of this social contract by the eighteenth century led to [[abolitionism]], it is argued that the removal of barriers to "insider status" is a very slow process, uncompleted even today (2017).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Eltis|first=David|title=Europeans and the Rise and Fall of African Slavery in the Americas: An Interpretation|journal=The American Historical Review|date=December 1993|volume=98|issue=5|pages=1402–1422|doi=10.2307/2167060|jstor=2167060}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As a result of the above, the [[Atlantic slave trade]] prospered. According to estimates in the Trans-Atlantic Slave Trade Database, between 1626 and 1860 more than 470,000 slaves were forcibly transported from Africa to what is now the United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Eltis|first=David|title=Extending the Frontiers: Essays on the New Transatlantic Slave Trade Database|year=2008|publisher=Yale University Press|location=United States of America|isbn=978-0-300-13436-0|page=31}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Eltis |first=David |title=Estimates |url=http://www.slavevoyages.org/tast/assessment/estimates.faces |accessdate=October 19, 2013 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131027021745/http://www.slavevoyages.org/tast/assessment/estimates.faces |archivedate=October 27, 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Prior to the [[American Civil War|Civil War]], eight serving presidents owned slaves, a practice protected by the U.S. Constitution.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Calore|first1=Paul|title=The Causes of the Civil War: The Political, Cultural, Economic and Territorial Disputes between North and South|date=2008|publisher=McFarland|page=10}}&lt;/ref&gt; Providing wealth for the white elite, approximately one in four [[Southern United States|Southern]] families held slaves prior to the Civil War. According to the 1860 U.S. census, there were about 385,000 slave owners out of a white population in the slave states of approximately 7 million.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fpri.org/articles/2008/08/teaching-about-slavery|title=Teaching about Slavery|work=Foreign Policy Research Institute}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Alonzo L. Hamby]], George Clack, and Mildred Sola Neely. [http://usinfo.state.gov/products/pubs/historybrf/index.htm "Outline of US History"] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080405170847/http://usinfo.state.gov/products/pubs/historybrf/index.htm |date=April 5, 2008 }}. US Department of State.&lt;/ref&gt;

Groups of armed white men, called [[slave patrol]]s, monitored enslaved African Americans. First established in South Carolina in 1704, the slave patrols' function was to police slaves, especially runaways. Slave owners feared slaves might organize a revolt or rebellion, so state militias were formed to provide a military command structure and discipline within the slave patrols to detect, encounter, and crush any organized slave meetings that might lead to revolt or rebellion.&lt;ref&gt;Loewen, James W. Lies Across America: What Our Historic Sites Get Wrong. The New Press, 2013. Print.&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Steps toward abolition of slavery ====
[[File:Whippedslaveedit.jpg|thumb|Scars of a whipped slave, April 2, 1863, [[Baton Rouge, Louisiana]] ]]
During the 1820s and 1830s, the [[American Colonization Society]] (A.C.S.) was had as its mission assisting free black Americans to where they could supposedly enjoy greater freedom in Africa,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fcnl.org/issues/item.php?item_id=731&amp;issue_id=75 |title=Background on conflict in Liberia |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110108042234/http://www.fcnl.org/issues/item.php?item_id=731&amp;issue_id=75 |archivedate=January 8, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1821 the A.C.S. established the colony of [[Liberia]], assisting thousands of former African-American slaves and free black people (with legislated limits) to move there from the United States. Some slaves were [[manumitted]] (set free) on condition that they emigrate. The slave states made no secret that they wanted to get rid of free blacks, whom they believe threatened their investment, the slaves, encouraging escapes and revolts. The support for the ACS was primarily Southern. The founder of the ACS, [[Henry Clay]] of Kentucky, stated that because of "unconquerable prejudice resulting from their color, they never could amalgamate with the free whites of this country. It was desirable, therefore, as it respected them, and the residue of the population of the country, to drain them off".&lt;ref name=ATH&gt;Maggie Montesinos Sale (1997). ''The slumbering volcano: American slave ship revolts and the production of rebellious masculinity''. p.264. Duke University Press, 1997. {{ISBN|0-8223-1992-6}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:1853 slave trader advertisement.jpg|thumb|left|Advertisement by a slave trader offering various amounts for slaves in [[Lexington, Kentucky]], 1853]]
Although in 1820 the [[Atlantic slave trade]] was equated with [[piracy]], punishable by death,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pdavis.nl/SlaverBackground.htm |title=The legal and diplomatic background to the seizure of foreign vessels |publisher=Pdavis.nl |accessdate=2013-02-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; the practice of chattel slavery continued to exist in the United States for another 35 years. The [[Slavery in the United States#Domestic slave trade and forced migration|domestic slave trade]] — "exporting" slaves south from Maryland and Virginia, which had surplusses; see [[Franklin and Armfield Office]] — was a major economic activity in the U.S. which lasted until the 1860s.&lt;ref name="CUP"&gt;{{Cite book |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=mhJcsiydNe8C&amp;pg=PA20 |page=20|title=Language, Discourse and Power in African American Culture|isbn=9780521001496|date=2002-07-04|last1=Morgan|first1=Marcyliena}}&lt;/ref&gt; Enslaved family members would be split up never to see or hear of each other again.&lt;ref name="CUP" /&gt; Between 1830 and 1840 nearly 250,000 slaves were taken across state lines.&lt;ref name="CUP" /&gt; In the 1850s more than 193,000 were transported, and historians estimate nearly one million in total were forced to migrate.&lt;ref name="CUP" /&gt;
[[File:Ashley's Sack (Slave Sack c. mid-19th century).jpg|thumb|right|[[Ashley's Sack]] is a cloth that recounts a slave sale separating a mother and her daughter. The sack belonged to a nine-year-old girl Ashley which was a parting gift from her mother, Rose, after Ashley had been sold. Rose filled the sack with a dress, braid of her hair, pecans, and "my love always"]]
The historian [[Ira Berlin]] called this forced migration of slaves the "Second Middle Passage", because it reproduced many of the same horrors as the [[Middle Passage]] (the name given to the transportation of slaves from Africa to North America). These sales of slaves broke up many families, with Berlin writing that whether slaves were directly uprooted or lived in fear that they or their families would be involuntarily moved, "the massive deportation traumatized black people".&lt;ref&gt;Berlin, ''Generations of Captivity'', pp. 161–62.&lt;/ref&gt; Individuals lost their connection to families and clans. Added to the earlier colonists combining slaves from different tribes, many ethnic Africans lost their knowledge of varying tribal origins in Africa. Most were descended from families who had been in the U.S. for many generations.&lt;ref name="CUP" /&gt;

==The emancipation==
[[File:Crowe-Slaves Waiting for Sale - Richmond, Virginia.jpg|thumb|left|''Slaves Waiting for Sale: Richmond, Virginia''. 1853]]
Effective January 1, 1863, [[Abraham Lincoln|President Lincoln]] stated in his [[Emancipation Proclamation]]: "That on the first day of January in the year of our Lord, one thousand eight hundred and sixty-three, all persons held as slaves within any State, or designated part of a State, the people whereof shall then be in rebellion against the United States shall be then, thenceforward, and forever free; and the executive government of the United States, including the military and naval authority thereof, will recognize and maintain the freedom of such persons, and will do no act or acts to repress such persons, or any of them, in any efforts they may make for their actual freedom."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ourdocuments.gov/doc.php?flash=true&amp;doc=34 |title=Emancipation Proclamation (1863) |publisher=Ourdocuments.gov |accessdate=2013-02-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Proclamation was momentous in its impact, yet of more limited application than at first appears. It exempted the border states of Delaware, Kentucky, Maryland, Missouri, and the new state of West Virginia. In those states slavery remained legal until ratification of the Thirteenth Amendment in 1865. Lincoln believed that the federal government did not have the authority to prohibit slavery; that would violate [[states' rights]]. (He did end slavery in the District of Columbia.) But he was also Commander of the Armed Forces. An action against states in rebellion, a step towards their defeat, was entirely appropriate. The South took it as a hostile act. This allowed Lincoln to prohibit slavery to a limited extent, without resistance from anti-abolitionist forces in the Union. No slaves outside of border areas were immediately affected, and it was the invading Northern armies who carried the enforcement of the prohibition with them.

While personally opposed to slavery (see [[Abraham Lincoln and slavery]]), Lincoln believed that the Constitution did not give Congress the power to end it, stating in his [[Abraham Lincoln's first inaugural address|first Inaugural Address]] that he "had no objection to [this] being made express and irrevocable" via the [[Corwin Amendment]].&lt;ref name="Walter"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ghostamendment.com/|title=Ghost Amendment: The Thirteenth Amendment That Never Was|last=Walter|first=Michael|year=2003|accessdate=December 15, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; On social and political rights for blacks, Lincoln stated, "I am not, nor ever have been in favor of making voters or jurors of negroes, nor of qualifying them to hold office, nor to intermarry with white people, I as much as any man am in favor of the superior position assigned to the white race."&lt;ref&gt;Abraham Lincoln, "Speeches and Writings 1832–1858: Speeches, Letters, and Miscellaneous Writings : the Lincoln-Douglas Debates, Volume 1". p. 638. Library of America, 1989&lt;/ref&gt; The Emancipation Proclamation did not apply to areas loyal to, or controlled by, the Union. Slavery was not actually abolished in the U.S. until the passage of the [[Thirteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|13th Amendment]] which was declared ratified on December 6, 1865.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.yale.edu/lawweb/avalon/amend1.htm#13 XIII – Slavery Abolished] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160819194412/http://www.yale.edu/lawweb/avalon/amend1.htm |date=August 19, 2016 }} The Avalon Project&lt;/ref&gt;

About four million [[African American|black]] [[slavery|slaves]] were freed in 1865. Ninety-five percent of blacks lived in the South, comprising one third of the population there as opposed to one percent of the population of the North. Consequently, fears of eventual emancipation were much greater in the South than in the North.&lt;ref&gt;James McPherson, Drawn with the Sword, page 15&lt;/ref&gt; Based on 1860 census figures, 8% of males aged 13 to 43 died in the civil war, including 6% in the North and 18% in the South.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.harvardmagazine.com/on-line/050155.html |title=The Deadliest War |publisher=Harvardmagazine.com |accessdate=2013-02-16 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070927225020/http://www.harvardmagazine.com/on-line/050155.html |archivedate=September 27, 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Reconstruction Era to World War II ===
{{Main|Nadir of American race relations |Mass racial violence in the United States}}

==== Reconstruction Era ====
[[File:Lynching-of-will-james.jpg|right|thumb|The mob-style [[lynching in the United States|lynching]] of Will James, Cairo, Illinois, 1909. A crowd of thousands watched the lynching.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Black Woman Reformer: Ida B. Wells, Lynching, &amp; Transatlantic Activism |date=2015 |publisher=University of Georgia Press |page=1}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
After the Civil War, the [[Thirteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|13th amendment]] in 1865, formally abolishing slavery, was ratified. Furthermore, Congress passed the [[Civil Rights Act of 1866]], which broadened a range of civil rights to all persons born in the United States. Despite this, the emergence of "[[Black Codes (United States)|Black Codes]]", sanctioned acts of subjugation against blacks, continued to bar African-Americans from due [[civil rights]]. The [[Naturalization Act of 1790]] limited U.S. citizenship to whites only, and in 1868 the effort toward civil rights was underscored with the [[Fourteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|14th amendment]] which granted citizenship to blacks.&lt;ref name="Schultz"&gt;{{cite book |last=Schultz|first=Jeffrey D.|title=Encyclopedia of Minorities in American Politics: African Americans and Asian Americans|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=WDV40aK1T-sC&amp;pg=PA284&amp;dq=African+Americans+discriminated+by+Naturalization+Act+of+1790&amp;cd=1#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false|page=284|year=2002|accessdate=2015-09-14|isbn=9781573561488}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Civil Rights Act of 1875]] followed, which was eliminated in a decision that undermined federal power to thwart private racial discrimination.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Estreicher|first=Samuel|title=Federal Power to Regulate Private Discrimination: The Revival of the Enforcement Clauses of the Reconstruction Era Amendments|journal=Columbia Law Review|year=1974|volume=74|issue=3|pages=452–454|jstor=112176|doi=10.2307/1121764}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nonetheless, the last of the [[Reconstruction Era]] amendments, the [[Fifteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|15th amendment]] promised [[voting rights]] to African-American men (previously only white men of property could vote), and these cumulative federal efforts, African-Americans began taking advantage of enfranchisement. African-Americans began voting, seeking office positions, utilizing [[public education]].

By the end of Reconstruction in the mid 1870s, violent [[white supremacist]]s came to power via [[paramilitary group]]s such as the [[Red Shirts (Southern United States)|Red Shirts]] and the [[White League]] and imposed [[Jim Crow]] laws that deprived African-Americans of voting rights and instituted systemic discriminatory policies through policies of unequal [[racial segregation]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Klarman|first=Michael|title=The Plessy Era|journal=The Supreme Court Review|volume=1998|year=1998|pages=307–308|jstor=3109701|doi=10.1086/scr.1998.3109701}}&lt;/ref&gt; Segregation, which began with slavery, continued with Jim Crow laws, with signs used to show blacks where they could legally walk, talk, drink, rest, or eat.&lt;ref name="Leon Litwack 2004"&gt;Leon Litwack, ''Jim Crow Blues'', Magazine of History (OAH Publications, 2004)&lt;/ref&gt; For those places that were racially mixed, non-whites had to wait until all white customers were dealt with.&lt;ref name="Leon Litwack 2004"/&gt; Segregated facilities extended from white only schools to white only graveyards.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-us-canada-38536668 "Barack Obama legacy: Did he improve US race relations?"]. BBC. Retrieved August 9, 2017&lt;/ref&gt;

== Native Americans ==
{{Main|Genocide of indigenous peoples|American Indian Wars|List of Indian massacres}}
{{See also|Indian Removal Act|California Genocide|Thomas Jefferson and Native Americans|Long Walk of the Navajo|Comanche campaign|Potawatomi Trail of Death|Sand Creek massacre|Yavapai Wars|Indian removals in Indiana|Indian removals in Ohio}}
[[File:Creeks in Oklahoma.png|thumb|left|Members of the [[Muscogee (Creek) Nation]] in Oklahoma around 1877. Notice the members with European and African ancestry. The Creek were originally from the Alabama region.]]
[[Indigenous peoples of the Americas|Native Americans]] have lived on the North American continent for at least 10,000 years and millions of Native Americans were living in what is today the United States at the time European settlers first arrived.&lt;ref&gt;Mann, Charles C., ''1491: New Revelations of the Americas Before Columbus'', Vintage Books, 2006, c.2005, p. 18&lt;/ref&gt; During the colonial and independent periods, European settlers waged a long series of conflicts, often with the objective of obtaining the resources of Native Americans. Through [[List of wars|wars]], [[population transfer|forced displacement]] (such as the [[Trail of Tears]]), and the imposition of treaties, land was taken. The loss of land often resulted in hardships for Native Americans. In the early 18th century, the English had enslaved nearly 800 Choctaws.&lt;ref name=brescia_era&gt;{{cite book| last = Brescia | first = William (Bill) | title = Tribal Government, A New Era | publisher = Choctaw Heritage Press | location = Philadelphia, Mississippi | chapter = Chapter 2, French-Choctaw Contact, 1680s–1763 | page = 8 | isbn = | year = 1982}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After the creation of the United States, the idea of [[Indian removal]] gained momentum. However, some Native Americans chose or were allowed to remain and avoided removal whereafter they were subjected to official racism. The Choctaws in [[Mississippi]] described their situation in 1849, "we have had our habitations torn down and burned, our fences destroyed, cattle turned into our fields and we ourselves have been scourged, manacled, fettered and otherwise personally abused, until by such treatment some of our best men have died."&lt;ref name=peterson&gt;{{cite book| last = Walter | first = Williams | title = Southeastern Indians: Since the Removal Era | publisher = University of Georgia Press | location = Athens, Georgia | chapter = Three Efforts at Development among the Choctaws of Mississippi | year = 1979}}&lt;/ref&gt; Joseph B. Cobb, who moved to Mississippi from Georgia, described the Choctaws as having "no nobility or virtue at all," and in some respect he found blacks, especially native Africans, to be more interesting and admirable, the red man's superior in every way. The Choctaw and Chickasaw, the tribes he knew best, were beneath contempt, that is, even worse than black slaves.&lt;ref name=charles_hudson&gt;{{cite book | last = Hudson | first = Charles | title = Red, White, and Black; Symposium on Indians in the Old South | publisher = University of Georgia Press | chapter = The Ante-Bellum Elite | page = 80 | id = SBN 820303089| year = 1971}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Ghost dance.jpg|thumb|right|The [[Ghost Dance]] ritual. The Natives believed the dance would reunite the living with the spirits of the dead, bring the spirits of the dead to fight on their behalf, make the white invaders vanish, and bring peace, prosperity, and unity to Indian peoples throughout the region]]
In the 1800s, ideologies such as [[Manifest destiny]], which held the view that the United States was destined to expand from coast to coast on the North American continent, fueled U.S. attacks against, and maltreatment of, Native Americans. In the years leading up to the [[Indian Removal Act |Indian Removal Act of 1830]] there were many armed conflicts between settlers and Native Americans.&lt;ref&gt;Worlds Together, Worlds Apart, Robert Tignor, Jeremy Adelman, Stephen Aron, Stephen Kotkin, Suzanne Marchand, Gyan Prakash, Michael Tsin, W.W. Norton &amp; Company, New York, 2000, p. 274.&lt;/ref&gt; A justification for the conquest and subjugation of indigenous people emanated from the stereotyped perception that Native Americans were "merciless Indian savages" (as described in the [[United States Declaration of Independence]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Out West|date=2000|publisher=University of Nebraska Press|page=96}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sam Wolfson in ''[[The Guardian]]'' writes, “The declaration’s passage has often been cited as an encapsulation of the dehumanizing attitude toward indigenous Americans that the US was founded on.”&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Facebook labels declaration of independence as 'hate speech' |url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2018/jul/05/facebook-declaration-of-independence-hate-speech |accessdate=August 7, 2019 |work=The Guardian}}&lt;/ref&gt; Simon Moya-Smith, culture editor at ''[[Indian Country Today]]'', states, "Any holiday that would refer to my people in such a repugnant, racist manner is certainly not worth celebrating. [July Fourth] is a day when we celebrate our resiliency, our culture, our languages, our children and we mourn the millions – literally millions – of indigenous people who have died as a consequence of American imperialism."&lt;ref&gt;[https://mic.com/articles/121671/native-americans-have-nothing-to-celebrate-on-july-4#.Qst75mbCL "Millions of Americans Have Nothing to Celebrate on the Fourth of July"]. Mic. Retrieved August 20, 2017&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1861, residents of [[Mankato, Minnesota]], formed the [[Knights of the Forest]], with the goal of 'eliminating all Indians from Minnesota.' An egregious attempt occurred with the [[California gold rush]], the first two years of which saw the death of thousands of Native Americans. Under [[Alta California|Mexican rule in California]], Indians were subjected to ''de facto'' enslavement under a system of [[peon]]age by the white elite. While in 1850, California formally entered the [[United States|Union]] as a [[Free state (United States)|free state]], with respect to the issue of [[Slavery in the United States|slavery]], the practice of Indian [[Indentured servant|indentured servitude]] was not outlawed by the [[California State Legislature|California Legislature]] until 1863.&lt;ref&gt;[[Edward D. Castillo|Castillo, Edward D.]] (1998). [http://www.ceres.ca.gov/nahc/califindian.html "Short Overview of California Indian History"] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20061214031402/http://www.ceres.ca.gov/nahc/califindian.html |date=December 14, 2006 }}, California Native American Heritage Commission.&lt;/ref&gt; The 1864 deportation of the [[Navajos]] by the U.S. government occurred when 8,000 Navajos were forcibly relocated to an [[internment camp]] in Bosque Redondo,&lt;ref name="Jaimes"/&gt; where, under armed guards, more than 3,500 Navajo and [[Mescalero Apache]] men, women, and children died from starvation and disease.&lt;ref name="Jaimes"&gt;M. Annette Jaimes (1992). ''The State of Native America: Genocide, Colonization, and Resistance''. p. 34. South End Press&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Woundedknee1891.jpg|thumb|left|Mass grave for the dead Lakota following the [[Wounded Knee massacre]]. Eyewitness [[American Horse]], chief of the Oglala Lakota, stated, “A people's dream died there. It was a beautiful dream&amp;nbsp;... the nation's hope is broken and scattered. There is no center any longer, and the sacred tree is dead."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | url=https://books.google.com/books?id=7p9VqRLiKqcC&amp;pg=PA218&amp;lpg=PA218| title =Black Elk Speaks: Being the Life Story of a Holy Man of the Oglala Sioux | author =Black Elk, John Gneisenau Neihardt | publisher = [[SUNY Press]] | page= 281 |date =2008|orig-year=1961| isbn =9781438425405 }}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
Native American nations on the plains in the west continued armed conflicts with the U.S. throughout the 19th century, through what were called generally [[American Indian Wars|Indian Wars]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |url=https://books.google.com/?id=9iQYSQ9y60MC&amp;pg=&amp;dq#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false |isbn=978-0-8061-2220-5 |page=48|title=American Indian Holocaust and Survival: A Population History Since 1492 |year=1990 |last1=Thornton |first1=Russell }}&lt;/ref&gt; Notable conflicts in this period include the [[Dakota War of 1862|Dakota War]], [[Great Sioux War of 1876|Great Sioux War]], [[Snake War]] and [[Colorado War]]. In the years leading up to the [[Wounded Knee massacre]] the U.S. government had continued to seize [[Lakota people|Lakota]] lands. A [[Ghost Dance]] ritual on the Northern Lakota reservation at Wounded Knee, [[South Dakota]], led to the U.S. Army's attempt to subdue the Lakota. The dance was part of a religion founded by [[Wovoka]] that told of the return of the Messiah to relieve the suffering of Native Americans and promised that if they would live righteous lives and perform the Ghost Dance properly, the European American invaders would vanish, the bison would return, and the living and the dead would be reunited in an Edenic world.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Plains Humanities: Wounded Knee Massacre|url=http://plainshumanities.unl.edu/encyclopedia/doc/egp.war.056|accessdate=August 4, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; On December 29, 1890, at Wounded Knee, gunfire erupted, and U.S. soldiers killed up to 300 Indians, mostly old men, women and children.&lt;ref name="Wounded Knee"&gt;{{cite web|title=Plains Humanities: Wounded Knee Massacre|url=http://plainshumanities.unl.edu/encyclopedia/doc/egp.war.056|accessdate=August 9, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the period surrounding the 1890 Wounded Knee Massacre, author [[L. Frank Baum]] wrote two editorials about Native Americans. Five days after the killing of the [[Lakota people|Lakota]] [[Sioux]] [[Medicine man|holy man]], [[Sitting Bull]], Baum wrote, "The proud spirit of the original owners of these vast prairies inherited through centuries of fierce and bloody wars for their possession, lingered last in the bosom of Sitting Bull. With his fall the nobility of the [[Redskin]] is extinguished, and what few are left are a pack of whining curs who lick the hand that smites them. The Whites, by the law of conquest, by a justice of civilization, are masters of the American continent, and the best safety of the frontier settlements will be secured by the total annihilation of the few remaining Indians. Why not annihilation? Their glory has fled, their spirit broken, their manhood effaced; better that they die than live the miserable wretches that they are."&lt;ref name="editorials"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.northern.edu/hastingw/baumedts.htm |title=L. Frank Baum's Editorials on the Sioux Nation |accessdate=2007-12-09 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20071209193251/http://www.northern.edu/hastingw/baumedts.htm |archivedate=December 9, 2007 }} Full text of both, with commentary by professor A. Waller Hastings&lt;/ref&gt; Following the December 29, 1890, massacre, Baum wrote, "The ''Pioneer'' has before declared that our only safety depends upon the total extermination [sic] of the Indians. Having wronged them for centuries we had better, in order to protect our civilization, follow it up by one more wrong and wipe these untamed and untamable creatures from the face of the earth. In this lies safety for our settlers and the soldiers who are under incompetent commands. Otherwise, we may expect future years to be as full of trouble with the redskins as those have been in the past."&lt;ref name="editorials" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Professor Robert Venables, Senior Lecturer Rural Sociology Department, Cornell University, "Looking Back at Wounded Knee 1890", ''Northeast Indian Quarterly'', Spring 1990&lt;/ref&gt;

Military and civil resistance by Native Americans has been a constant feature of American history. So too have a variety of debates around issues of sovereignty, the upholding of treaty provisions, and the civil rights of Native Americans under U.S. law.

=== Reservation marginalization ===
{{See also|Native American reservations}}
Once their territories were incorporated into the United States, surviving Native Americans were denied equality before the law and often treated as wards of the state.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.eskimo.com/~recall/bleed/0303.htm
|accessdate=2008-01-28
|title=Our Daily Bleed…
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Many Native Americans were moved to reservations—constituting 4% of U.S. territory. In a number of cases, treaties signed with Native Americans were violated. Tens of thousands of American Indians and Alaska Natives were forced to attend a [[Indian boarding school|residential school system]] which sought to reeducate them in white settler American values, culture and economy.&lt;ref&gt;Ward Churchill, ''Kill the Indian, Save the Man'', 2006. The basis for this theory was that inside every native person, there was a repressed white person screaming to come to the surface. Abuse both physical and psychological was common in these schools, and often their objective of 'compulsory whiteness' was not even ultimately achieved, with many of the Indians who later returned to the reservations afterwards not at all 'becoming white', but instead simply becoming heavy alcoholics and displaying signs of permanent psychological distress, and even [[mental illness]]. Further, these individuals were often either totally unemployable or only marginally employed, as it was sensed by those around them that on the one hand, they had not successfully assimilated into 'white society', nor were they any longer acceptable to the Indian societies from which they had originated.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/programmes/world_news_america/9097996.stm | work=BBC News | first1=Franz | last1=Strasser | first2=Sharon | last2=Carpenter | title=Native Americans battle teenage suicide | date=November 22, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The treatment of the Native Americans was admired by the Nazis.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.timesofisrael.com/american-laws-against-coloreds-influenced-nazi-racial-planners/ "American laws against ‘coloreds’ influenced Nazi racial planners"]. Times of Israel. Retrieved August 26, 2017&lt;/ref&gt; Nazi expansion eastward was accompanied with invocation of America's colonial expansion westward under the banner of Manifest Destiny, with the accompanying wars on the Native Americans.&lt;ref name="Westermann"/&gt; In 1928, Hitler praised Americans for having "gunned down the millions of Redskins to a few hundred thousand, and now kept the modest remnant under observation in a cage" in the course of founding their continental empire.&lt;ref&gt;Whitman, James Q. (2017). Hitler's American Model: The United States and the Making of Nazi Race Law. Princeton University Press. p. 47.&lt;/ref&gt; On Nazi Germany's expansion eastward, Hitler stated, "Our Mississippi [the line beyond which Thomas Jefferson wanted all Indians expelled] must be the Volga, and not the Niger."&lt;ref name="Westermann"&gt;{{cite book|last1=Westermann|first1=Edward. B.|title=Hitler's Ostkrieg and the Indian Wars: Comparing Genocide and Conquest|date=2016|publisher=University of Oklahoma Press|page=3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Further dispossession of various kinds continues into the present, although these current dispossessions, especially in terms of land, rarely make major news headlines in the country (e.g., the [[Lenape]] people's recent fiscal troubles and subsequent land grab by the [[State of New Jersey]]), and sometimes even fail to make it to headlines in the localities in which they occur. Through concessions for industries such as oil, mining and timber and through division of land from the [[Allotment Act]] forward, these concessions have raised problems of consent, exploitation of low royalty rates, environmental injustice, and gross mismanagement of funds held in trust, resulting in the loss of $10–40&amp;nbsp;billion.&lt;ref&gt;United States Senate, [http://www.indiantrust.com/index.cfm?FuseAction=OtherMedia.ViewDetail&amp;Other_id=12&amp;Month=3&amp;Year=2007 Oversight Hearing on Trust Fund Litigation, Cobell v. Kempthorne] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090112213806/http://www.indiantrust.com/index.cfm?FuseAction=OtherMedia.ViewDetail&amp;Other_id=12&amp;Month=3&amp;Year=2007 |date=January 12, 2009 }}. See also, [[Cobell v. Norton]].&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Worldwatch Institute]] notes that 317 reservations are threatened by environmental hazards, while [[Western Shoshone]] land has been subjected to more than 1,000 nuclear explosions.&lt;ref&gt;[[Winona LaDuke]], ''All Our Relations: Native Struggles for Land and Life'', 1999, p. 2-3.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Assimilation ===
{{further|Native American boarding schools}}
[[File:School Begins (Puck Magazine 1-25-1899).jpg|thumb|250px|Caricature showing Uncle Sam lecturing four children labeled Philippines, Hawaii, Puerto Rico and Cuba. A black boy is washing windows, a Native American sits separate from the class, and a Chinese boy is outside the door. The caption reads: School Begins. Uncle Sam (to his new class in Civilization)!]]

The government appointed agents, like [[Benjamin Hawkins]], to live among the Native Americans and to teach them, through example and instruction, how to live like whites.&lt;ref name=perdue&gt;{{cite book
 | last = Perdue
 | first = Theda
 | title = Mixed Blood Indians: Racial Construction in the Early South
 | publisher = The University of Georgia Press
 | chapter = Chapter 2 "Both White and Red"
 | page = 51
 | year = 2003
 | isbn = 978-0-8203-2731-0
}}&lt;/ref&gt; America's first president, [[George Washington]], formulated a policy to encourage the "civilizing" process.&lt;ref name=remini_reform_begins&gt;{{cite book
|last = Remini
|first = Robert
|title = Andrew Jackson
|publisher = History Book Club
|chapter="The Reform Begins"
|page = 201
|id = {{Listed Invalid ISBN|0-9650631-0-7}}
|year = 1977
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Naturalization Act of 1790 limited citizenship to whites only. The [[Indian Citizenship Act of 1924]] granted U.S. citizenship to all Native Americans. Prior to the passage of the act, nearly two-thirds of Native Americans were already U.S. citizens.&lt;ref name=2-3_us_citizenship&gt;{{cite web
 |url=http://digital.library.okstate.edu/kappler/vol4/html_files/v4p1165.html 
 |title=Indian affairs: laws and treaties Vol. IV, Treaties 
 |accessdate=2008-10-14 
 |last=Kappler 
 |first=Charles 
 |year=1904 
 |publisher=Government Printing Office 
 |url-status=dead 
 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20081011204536/http://digital.library.okstate.edu/kappler/vol4/html_files/v4p1165.html 
 |archivedate=October 11, 2008 
}}&lt;/ref&gt; The earliest recorded date of Native Americans becoming U.S. citizens was in 1831 when the Mississippi [[Choctaw]] became citizens after the United States Legislature ratified the [[Treaty of Dancing Rabbit Creek]]. Under article XIV of that treaty, any Choctaw who elected not to move to Native American Territory could become an American citizen when he registered and if he stayed on designated lands for five years after treaty ratification.

While formal equality has been legally recognized, [[Native Americans in the United States|American Indians]], [[Alaska Natives]], [[Native Hawaiians]], and [[Pacific Islanders]] remain among the most economically disadvantaged groups in the country, and according to National mental health studies, American Indians as a group tend to suffer from high levels of alcoholism, depression and suicide.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://mentalhealth.samhsa.gov/cre/fact4.asp |title=Substance Abuse and Mental Health Publications&amp;#124; SAMHSA Store |publisher=Mentalhealth.samhsa.gov |date=November 19, 2011 |accessdate=2013-02-16 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100527170646/http://mentalhealth.samhsa.gov/cre/fact4.asp |archivedate=May 27, 2010 |df=mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Anti-Chinese legislation==
{{main|Anti-Chinese sentiment in the United States|Anti-Chinese legislation in the United States}}
The 1879 Constitution of the [[State of California]] prohibited the employment of [[Chinese people]] by state and local governments, as well as by businesses that were incorporated in California. Also, the 1879 California constitution delegated power to local governments of California to remove Chinese people from within their borders.&lt;ref name="archives.cdn.sos.ca.gov"&gt;Article XIX of the [https://archives.cdn.sos.ca.gov/collections/1879/archive/1879-constitution.pdf Constitution of the State of California of 1879]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Hitler's American Model 2017 p. 35"&gt;[[James Whitman]], "Hitler's American Model: The United States and the Making of Nazi Race Law" (Princeton: [[Princeton University Press]], 2017), p. 35&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Chinese Exclusion Act]] banning immigration of Chinese laborers was enacted on the national level in 1882. Several massacres of Chinese people, including the [[Rock Springs massacre]] of 1885 and the [[Hells Canyon massacre]] of 1887 further exemplified deep American racist animus against Chinese people.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Chinese in America : a narrative history|last=Iris.|first=Chang|date=2004|origyear=2003|publisher=Penguin|isbn=0142004170|location=New York|oclc=55136302}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Post-Reconstruction Era ==
[[File:TulsaRaceRiot-1921.png|thumb|right|During the 1921 [[Tulsa race riot]] thousands of whites rampaged through the black community, killing men and women, burning and looting stores and homes. Up to 300 blacks were killed.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |author=Oklahoma Commission |contribution=Final Report |title=Oklahoma Commission to Study the Tulsa Race Riot of 1921 |place=Tulsa, Oklahoma |date=February 28, 2001 |contribution-url=http://www.okhistory.org/research/forms/freport.pdf |accessdate=April 10, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
The new century saw a hardening of [[institutionalized racism]] and legal discrimination against citizens of African descent in the United States. Throughout this post Civil War period, [[racial stratification]] was informally and systemically enforced, in order to solidify the pre-existing social order. Although technically able to vote, [[poll tax (United States)|poll taxes]], pervasive acts of terror such as [[lynching in the United States]] (often perpetrated by groups such as the reborn [[Ku Klux Klan]], founded in the Reconstruction South), and discriminatory laws such as [[grandfather clauses]] kept black Americans (and many [[Poor White]]s) disenfranchised particularly in the South. Furthermore, discrimination extended to state legislation that "allocated vastly unequal financial support" for black and white schools. In addition to this, county officials sometimes redistributed resources earmarked for blacks to white schools, further undermining educational opportunities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Beck|first=E.M.|author2=Tolnay, Stewart |title=Black Flight: Lethal Violence and the Great Migration, 1900–1930|journal=Social Science History|year=1990|volume=14|issue=3|pages=347–370|doi=10.2307/1171355|jstor=1171355}}&lt;/ref&gt; In response to de jure racism, protest and lobbyist groups emerged, most notably, the [[NAACP]] (National Association for the Advancement of Colored People) in 1909.&lt;ref&gt;Kwame Anthony Appiah, Henry Louis Gates, Jr., eds. ''Africana: The Encyclopedia of the African and African American Experience'', in articles "Civil Rights Movement" by Patricia Sullivan (pp 441–455) and "National Association for the Advancement of Colored People" by Kate Tuttle (pp 1,388–1,391). {{ISBN|0-465-00071-1}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

This time period is sometimes referred to as the [[nadir of American race relations]] because racism, [[Racial segregation in the United States|segregation]], [[racial discrimination]], and expressions of [[white supremacy]] all increased. So did anti-black violence, including [[Mass racial violence in the United States|race riots]] such as the [[Atlanta race riot|Atlanta Race riot]] of 1906 and the [[Tulsa race riot]] of 1921. The Atlanta riot was characterized by the French newspaper ''[[Le Petit Journal (newspaper)|Le Petit Journal]]'' as a "racial massacre of negroes".&lt;ref&gt;[http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/bpt6k6176609/f3.image "Un lynchage monstre"] (September 24, 1906) ''Le Petit Journal''&lt;/ref&gt; The Charleston ''[[The Post and Courier|News and Courier]]'' wrote in response to the Atlanta riots: "Separation of the races is the only radical solution of the negro problem in this country. There is nothing new about it. It was the Almighty who established the bounds of the habitation of the races. The negroes were brought here by compulsion; they should be induced to leave here by persuasion."&lt;ref&gt;[https://timesmachine.nytimes.com/timesmachine/1906/09/30/101799831.pdf "DEPORTING THE NEGROES"] (September 30, 1906) ''New York Times''&lt;/ref&gt;

== The Great Migration ==
[[Image:Omaha courthouse lynching.jpg|thumb|252px|A group of white men pose for a 1919 photograph as they stand over the black victim Will Brown who had been [[lynched]] and had his body mutilated and burned during the [[Omaha race riot of 1919]] in [[Omaha, Nebraska]]. Photographs and postcards of lynchings were popular souvenirs in the U.S.&lt;ref&gt;Moyers, Bill. [https://www.pbs.org/moyers/journal/11232007/profile2.html "Legacy of Lynching"]. PBS. Retrieved July 28, 2016&lt;/ref&gt;]]
In addition, racism, which had been viewed primarily as a problem in the Southern states, burst onto the national consciousness following the [[Great Migration (African American)|Great Migration]], the relocation of millions of African Americans from their roots in the rural Southern states to the industrial centers of the North and West between 1910 and 1970, particularly in cities such as [[Boston]], [[Chicago]], [[Detroit]], [[New York City]] ([[Harlem]]), [[Los Angeles]], [[Oakland, California|Oakland]], [[Seattle]], [[Portland, Oregon|Portland]], [[Phoenix, Arizona|Phoenix]], and [[Denver]]. Within Chicago, for example, between 1910 and 1970, the percentage of African-Americans leapt from 2.0 percent to 32.7 percent.&lt;ref name="Tolnay 2003 209–232"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Tolnay|first=Stewart|title=The African American 'Great Migration' and Beyond|journal=Annual Review of Sociology|year=2003|volume=29|pages=209–232|doi=10.1146/annurev.soc.29.010202.100009|jstor=30036966}}&lt;/ref&gt; The demographic patterns of black migrants and external economic conditions are largely studied stimulants regarding the Great Migration.&lt;ref name="Tolnay 2003 209–232"/&gt; For example, migrating blacks (between 1910 and 1920) were more likely to be literate than blacks that remained in the South. Known economic push factors played a role in migration, such as the emergence of a split labor market and agricultural distress from the [[boll weevil]] destruction of the cotton economy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Beck|first=E.M.|author2=Tolnay, Stewart |title=Black Flight: Lethal Violence and the Great Migration, 1900–1930|journal=Social Science History|year=1990|volume=14|issue=3|pages=351–352|doi=10.2307/1171355|jstor=1171355}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:We want white tenants.jpg|thumb|left|White tenants seeking to prevent blacks from moving into the [[Public housing in Detroit|housing project]] erected this sign. Detroit, 1942.]]
Southern migrants were often treated in accordance with pre-existing racial stratification. The rapid influx of blacks into the North and West disturbed the racial balance within cities, exacerbating hostility between both black and white residents in the two regions. Stereotypic schemas of Southern blacks were used to attribute issues in urban areas, such as crime and disease, to the presence of African-Americans. Overall, African-Americans in most Northern and Western cities experienced systemic discrimination in a plethora of aspects of life. Within employment, economic opportunities for blacks were routed to the lowest-status and restrictive in potential mobility. Within the housing market, stronger discriminatory measures were used in correlation to the influx, resulting in a mix of "targeted violence, [[restrictive covenants]], [[redlining]] and racial steering".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Tolnay|first=Stewart|title=The African American 'Great Migration' and Beyond|journal=Annual Review of Sociology|year=2003|volume=29|pages=218–221|doi=10.1146/annurev.soc.29.010202.100009|jstor=30036966}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Image:chicago-race-riot.jpg|thumb|right|A white gang looking for blacks during the [[Chicago race riot of 1919]]]]
Throughout this period, racial tensions exploded, most violently in Chicago, and [[lynching in the United States|lynchings]]—mob-directed hangings, usually racially motivated—increased dramatically in the 1920s. Urban riots—whites attacking blacks—became a northern and western problem.&lt;ref&gt;Michael O. Emerson, Christian Smith (2001). "Divided by Faith: Evangelical Religion and the Problem of Race in America". p. 42. Oxford University Press&lt;/ref&gt; Many whites defended their space with violence, intimidation, or legal tactics toward African Americans, while many other whites migrated to more racially homogeneous suburban or exurban regions, a process known as [[white flight]].&lt;ref name="Migration"&gt;{{cite book|last=Seligman|first=Amanda|title=Block by block : neighborhoods and public policy on Chicago's West Side|year=2005|publisher=University of Chicago Press|location=Chicago|isbn=978-0-226-74663-0|pages=213–14}}&lt;/ref&gt; Racially restrictive housing covenants were ruled unenforceable under the [[Fourteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Fourteenth Amendment]] in the 1948 landmark [[Supreme Court of the United States|Supreme Court]] case ''[[Shelley v. Kraemer]]''.&lt;ref&gt;''Shelley v. Kraemer'', 334 U.S. 1 (1948)&lt;/ref&gt;

Elected in 1912, President [[Woodrow Wilson]] ordered segregation throughout the federal government.&lt;ref&gt;Michael Kazin, Rebecca Edwards, Adam Rothman (2009). "The Princeton Encyclopedia of American Political History". p. 245. Princeton University Press&lt;/ref&gt; In World War I, blacks served in the [[United States Armed Forces]] in segregated units. Black soldiers were often poorly trained and equipped, and were often put on the frontlines in [[suicide mission]]s. The U.S. military was still heavily segregated in World War II. In addition, no African-American would receive the [[Medal of Honor]] during the war, and black soldiers had to sometimes give up their seats in trains to the Nazi prisoners of war.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nydailynews.com/news/national/forgotten-details-heroism-black-soldiers-wwii-article-1.2419211 "Forgotten' details heroism of black soldiers in WWII"]. New York Daily News. Retrieved August 5, 2017&lt;/ref&gt;

== World War II to Civil Rights Era ==
[[File:Segregation 1938b.jpg|thumb|left|A black youth at a [[Racial segregation|segregated]] drinking fountain in [[Halifax, North Carolina]], in 1938.]]
The [[Jim Crow Laws]] were state and local laws enacted in the [[Southern United States|Southern]] and [[Border states (Civil War)|border states]] of the United States and enforced between 1876 and 1965. They mandated "[[separate but equal]]" status for black Americans. In reality, this led to treatment and accommodations that were almost always inferior to those provided to [[white American]]s. The most important laws required that public schools, public places and public transportation, like trains and buses, have separate facilities for whites and blacks. State-sponsored school segregation was declared unconstitutional by the [[Supreme Court of the United States]] in 1954 in ''[[Brown v. Board of Education]]''. One of the first federal court cases to challenge segregation in schools was [[Mendez v. Westminster]] in 1946.

{{multiple image|align=right
 | footer    = [[Emmett Till]] was brutally murdered by white men for allegedly whistling at a white woman. The two defendents, Roy Bryant and J.W. Milam, were speedily acquitted by an all white jury.
 | image1    =
 | width1    = 185
 | image2    =
 | width2    = 230
}}

By the 1950s, the [[Civil Rights Movement]] was gaining momentum. Membership in the NAACP increased in states across the U.S. A 1955 lynching that sparked public outrage about injustice was that of [[Emmett Till]], a 14-year-old boy from Chicago. Spending the summer with relatives in [[Money, Mississippi]], Till was killed for allegedly having [[wolf-whistle]]d at a white woman. Till had been badly beaten, one of his eyes was gouged out, and he was shot in the head before being thrown into the [[Tallahatchie River]], his body weighed down with a {{convert|70|lbs|kg|adj=on}} [[cotton gin]] fan tied around his neck with barbed wire. David Jackson writes that [[Mamie Till]], Emmett's Mother, "brought him home to Chicago and insisted on an open casket. Tens of thousands filed past Till's remains, but it was the publication of the searing funeral image in ''Jet'', with a stoic Mamie gazing at her murdered child's ravaged body, that forced the world to reckon with the brutality of American racism."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://100photos.time.com/photos/emmett-till-david-jackson|title=How The Horrific Photograph of Emmett Till Helped Energize The Civil Rights Movement|website=100 Photographs {{!}} The Most Influential Images of All Time|access-date=2017-07-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; News photographs circulated around the country, and drew intense public reaction. The visceral response to his mother's decision to have an open-casket funeral mobilized the black community throughout the U.S.&lt;ref name="Atlantic"&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.theatlantic.com/entertainment/archive/2017/02/how-the-blood-of-emmett-till-still-stains-america-today/516891/|title=How 'The Blood of Emmett Till' Still Stains America Today|last=II|first=Vann R. Newkirk|work=The Atlantic|access-date=2017-07-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; Vann R. Newkirk wrote "the trial of his killers became a pageant illuminating the tyranny of [[white supremacy]]".&lt;ref name="Atlantic"/&gt; The state of Mississippi tried two defendants, Roy Bryant and J.W. Milam, but they were speedily acquitted by an [[all-white jury]].&lt;ref&gt;Whitfield, Stephen (1991). A Death in the Delta: The story of Emmett Till. pp 41–42. JHU Press.&lt;/ref&gt;

In response to heightening discrimination and violence, non-violent acts of protest began to occur. For example, in February 1960, in [[Greensboro, North Carolina]], four young African-American college students entered a Woolworth store and sat down at the counter but were refused service. The men had learned about non-violent protest in college, and continued to sit peacefully as whites tormented them at the counter, pouring ketchup on their heads and burning them with cigarettes. After this, many sit-ins took place in order to non-violently protest against racism and inequality. Sit-ins continued throughout the South and spread to other areas. Eventually, after many sit-ins and other non-violent protests, including marches and boycotts, places began to agree to desegregate.&lt;ref&gt;Carol Berkin, Christopher Miller, Robert Cherny, James Gormly (2011). "Making America: A History of the United States, Volume 2: From 1865". p. 749. Cengage Learning&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:US Marshals with Young Ruby Bridges on School Steps.jpg|thumb|Due to threats and violence against her U.S. Marshals escorted 6-year-old [[Ruby Bridges]] to and from the previously whites only [[William Frantz Elementary School]] in New Orleans, 1960. As soon as Bridges entered the school, white parents pulled their children out.]]
In June 1963, civil rights activist and [[NAACP]] member [[Medgar Evers]] was assassinated by [[Byron De La Beckwith]], a member of the [[White Citizens' Council]]. In his trials for murder De La Beckwith evaded conviction via all-white juries (both trials ended with hung juries).

The [[16th Street Baptist Church bombing]] marked a turning point during the Civil Rights Era. On Sunday, September 15, 1963 with a stack of dynamite hidden on an outside staircase, Ku Klux Klansmen destroyed one side of the Birmingham church. The bomb exploded in proximity to twenty-six children who were preparing for choir practice in the basement assembly room. The explosion killed four black girls, Carole Robertson (14), Cynthia Wesley (14), Denise McNair (11) and Addie Mae Collins (14).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Ravitz|first=Jessica|title=Siblings of the bombing: Remembering Birmingham church blast 50 years on|url=http://www.cnn.com/2013/09/14/us/birmingham-church-bombing-anniversary-victims-siblings/|accessdate=October 20, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Birmingham Church Bombed|url=http://www.cinema.ucla.edu/la-rebellion/timeline/birmingham-church-bombed-0|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20131015055957/http://www.cinema.ucla.edu/la-rebellion/timeline/birmingham-church-bombed-0|url-status=dead|archive-date=October 15, 2013|publisher=L.A. Rebellion: Film &amp; Television Archive|accessdate=October 20, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Rosa Parks being fingerprinted by Deputy Sheriff D.H. Lackey after being arrested for refusing to give up her seat for a white passenger on a segregated municipal bus in Montgomery, Alabama.jpg|thumb|left|[[Rosa Parks]] being fingerprinted by Deputy Sheriff D.H. Lackey after being arrested for not giving up her seat on the bus to a white person]]
With the bombing occurring only a couple of weeks after [[Martin Luther King Jr.]]'s [[March on Washington for Jobs and Freedom]], it became an integral aspect of transformed perceptions of conditions for blacks in America. It influenced the passage of the [[Civil Rights Act of 1964]] (that banned discrimination in public accommodations, employment, and labor unions) and [[Voting Rights Act of 1965]] which overruled remaining Jim Crow laws. Nonetheless, neither had been implemented by the end of the 1960s as civil rights leaders continued to strive for political and social freedom. 
[[File:Bayard Rustin NYWTS 3.jpg|thumb|[[Bayard Rustin]] (left) and [[Cleveland Robinson]] (right), organizers of the March, on August 7, 1963]]
Many U.S. states banned [[Interracial marriage in the United States|interracial marriage]]. In 1967, Mildred Loving, a black woman, and Richard Loving, a white man, were sentenced to a year in prison in [[Virginia]] for marrying each other.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Walker |first=Dionne |url=http://usatoday30.usatoday.com/news/nation/2007-06-10-loving_N.htm |date=June 10, 2007 |title=Pioneer of interracial marriage looks back |work=[[Associated Press]] | accessdate=2015-08-23 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Their marriage violated the state's [[Anti-miscegenation laws in the United States|anti-miscegenation]] statute, the [[Racial Integrity Act of 1924]], which prohibited marriage between people classified as white and people classified as "colored" (persons of non-white ancestry).&lt;ref&gt;Racial Integrity Act of 1924, [[s:Racial Integrity Act of 1924|Full Text]] at Wikisource.org&lt;/ref&gt; In the ''[[Loving v. Virginia]]'' case in 1967, the Supreme Court invalidated laws prohibiting interracial marriage in the U.S.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.charlielawing.com/modhist_lovingv.virginia.pdf | title=''Loving v. Virginia'' and the Hegemony of "Race" | last=Lawing | first=Charles B. | accessdate=2015-08-23 | url-status=dead | archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070704053526/http://www.charlielawing.com/modhist_lovingv.virginia.pdf | archivedate=July 4, 2007 | df=mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:WhiteTradeOnlyLancasterOhio.jpg|thumb|left|"We Cater to White Trade Only" sign on a restaurant window in [[Lancaster, Ohio]] in 1938. In 1964 [[Martin Luther King Jr.]] was arrested and spent a night in jail for attempting to eat at a white-only restaurant in [[St. Augustine, Florida]]]]
Segregation continued even after the demise of the Jim Crow laws. Data on house prices and attitudes toward integration suggest that in the mid-20th century, segregation was a product of collective actions taken by whites to exclude blacks from their neighborhoods.&lt;ref name="vigdor"&gt;''The Rise and Decline of the American Ghetto'' David M. Cutler, Edward L. Glaeser, Jacob L. Vigdor ''The Journal of Political Economy'', Vol. 107, No. 3 (Jun. 1999), pp. 455–506&lt;/ref&gt; Segregation also took the form of [[redlining]], the practice of denying or increasing the cost of services, such as banking, insurance, access to jobs,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.core.ucl.ac.be/services/psfiles/dp99/dp9913.pdf |title=Racial Discrimination and Redlining in Cities |accessdate=2013-02-16 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20071130210614/http://www.core.ucl.ac.be/services/psfiles/dp99/dp9913.pdf |archivedate=November 30, 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt; access to health care,&lt;ref&gt;See: [[Race and health]]&lt;/ref&gt; or even supermarkets&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |doi = 10.1023/A:1015772503007|year = 2001|last1 = Eisenhauer|first1 = Elizabeth|title = In poor health: Supermarket redlining and urban nutrition|journal = GeoJournal|volume = 53|issue = 2|pages = 125–133}}&lt;/ref&gt; to residents in certain, often racially determined,&lt;ref name="eastny"&gt;{{Cite book |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=TWo8OFJpFtAC |isbn=978-0-8147-8267-5 |page=42|title=How East New York Became a Ghetto |year=2003 |last1=Thabit |first1=Walter }}&lt;/ref&gt; areas. Although in the U.S. informal discrimination and segregation have always existed, redlining began with the [[National Housing Act of 1934]], which established the [[Federal Housing Administration]] (FHA). The practice was fought first through passage of the [[Fair Housing Act of 1968]] (which prevents redlining when the criteria for redlining are based on race, religion, gender, familial status, disability, or ethnic origin), and later through the [[Community Reinvestment Act]] of 1977, which requires banks to apply the same lending criteria in all communities.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |url=https://books.google.com/books?vid=ISBN0813339529 |isbn=978-0-8133-3952-8 |page=114 |quote=The goal was not to relax lending restrictions but rather to get banks to apply the same criteria in the inner-city as in the [[suburbs]].|title=Comeback Cities: A Blueprint for Urban Neighborhood Revival |date=2001-12-18 |last1=Grogan |first1=Paul |last2=Proscio |first2=Tony }}&lt;/ref&gt; Although redlining is illegal some argue that it continues to exist in other forms.

Up until the 1940s, the full revenue potential of what was called "the Negro market" was largely ignored by white-owned manufacturers in the U.S. with advertising focused on whites.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.wsj.com/articles/SB116831396726171042|title=How Pepsi Opened Door to Diversity|publisher=Wall Street Journal|date=January 9, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Blacks were also denied commercial deals. On his decision to take part in exhibition races against racehorses in order to earn money, Olympic champion [[Jesse Owens]] stated, "People say that it was degrading for an Olympic champion to run against a horse, but what was I supposed to do? I had four gold medals, but you can't eat four gold medals."&lt;ref name="espn1"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://espn.go.com/sportscentury/features/00016393.html| title=Owens Pierced a Myth|last=Schwartz|first=Larry| publisher=ESPN|accessdate=April 30, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; On the lack of opportunities, Owens added, "There was no television, no big advertising, no endorsements then. Not for a black man, anyway."&lt;ref&gt;Entine, Jon (2000). Taboo: Why Black Athletes Dominate Sports and why We are Afraid to Talk about it. PublicAffairs. p. 187.&lt;/ref&gt; In the reception to honor his Olympic success Owens was not permitted to enter through the main doors of the [[Waldorf Astoria New York]] and instead forced to travel up to the event in a freight elevator.&lt;ref name=schwartz&gt;{{cite web | last = Schwartz | first = Larry | title=Owens pierced a myth|url=http://espn.go.com/sportscentury/features/00016393.html| year=2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; The first black Academy Award recipient [[Hattie McDaniel]] was not permitted to attend the premiere of ''[[Gone with the Wind (film)|Gone with the Wind]]'' with Georgia being racially segregated, and at the Oscars ceremony in Los Angeles she was required to sit at a segregated table at the far wall of the room; the hotel had a strict no-blacks policy, but allowed McDaniel in as a favor.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/features/oscars-first-black-winner-accepted-774335|title=Oscar's First Black Winner Accepted Her Honor in a Segregated 'No Blacks' Hotel in L.A.|last=Abramovitch|first=Seth|date=February 19, 2015|work=[[The Hollywood Reporter]]|accessdate=August 10, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As the civil rights movement and dismantling of Jim Crow laws in the 1950s and 1960s deepened existing racial tensions in much of the Southern U.S, a Republican Party electoral strategy – the [[Southern strategy]] – was enacted to increase political support among white voters in the South by appealing to racism against African Americans.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Nixon's Southern strategy: 'It's All in the Charts'|last=Boyd|first=James|date=May 17, 1970|work=The New York Times|url=https://www.nytimes.com/packages/html/books/phillips-southern.pdf|accessdate=August 2, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Carter, Dan T. ''From George Wallace to Newt Gingrich: Race in the Conservative Counterrevolution, 1963–1994.'' p. 35.&lt;/ref&gt; Republican politicians such as presidential candidate [[Richard Nixon]] and Senator [[Barry Goldwater]] developed strategies that successfully contributed to the political realignment of many white, conservative voters in the South who had traditionally supported the Democratic Party rather than the Republican Party.&lt;ref name="Apple"&gt;{{cite news|title=G.O.P. Tries Hard to Win Black Votes, but Recent History Works Against It|last=Apple|first=R.W. Jr.|date=September 19, 1996|work=The New York Times|url=https://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E2DA1F3AF93AA2575AC0A960958260|archiveurl=https://www.webcitation.org/64t5A14Sz?url=http://www.nytimes.com/1996/09/19/us/gop-tries-hard-to-win-black-votes-but-recent-history-works-against-it.html?pagewanted=all&amp;src=pm|archivedate=January 22, 2012|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1971, angered by African delegates at the UN siding against the U.S. in a vote, then Governor of California [[Ronald Reagan]] stated in a phone call to president Nixon, “To see those... monkeys from those African countries - damn them, they're still uncomfortable wearing shoes!"&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-us-canada-49177034 “Ronald Reagan called Africans at UN 'monkeys', tapes reveal“]. BBC. Retrieved July 31, 2019&lt;/ref&gt; The perception that the Republican Party had served as the "vehicle of white supremacy in the South", particularly post 1964, made it difficult for the Party to win back the support of black voters in the South in later years.&lt;ref name="Apple"/&gt;

== 1980s to present ==
[[File:Emanuel African Methodist Episcopal (AME) Church Corrected.jpg|thumb|The [[Emanuel African Methodist Episcopal Church]] where nine blacks, including the pastor, were killed in the 2015 [[Charleston church shooting]]. The church had been rebuilt after one of the church's co-founders, [[Denmark Vesey]], was suspected of planning a slave rebellion in Charleston in 1822; 35 people, including Vesey, were hanged and the church was burned down.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |jstor = 2205070|title = The Vesey Plot: A Reconsideration|journal = The Journal of Southern History|volume = 30|issue = 2|pages = 143–161|last1 = Wade|first1 = Richard C.|year = 1964|doi = 10.2307/2205070}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
While substantial gains were made in the succeeding decades through middle class advancement and public employment, [[African-American poverty|black poverty]] and lack of education continued in the context of de-industrialization.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jbhe.com/latest/122905_statistical_shocker2005.html |title=JBHE Statistical Shocker of the Year |publisher=Jbhe.com |accessdate=2013-02-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Takaki-CivRights&gt;Ronald Takaki, ''A Different Mirror: A History of Multicultural America'' (New York: Little, Brown &amp; Co., 1993), 400–414.&lt;/ref&gt; Despite gains made after the [[16th Street Baptist Church bombing]], some violence against black churches has also continued – 145 fires were set to churches around the South in the 1990s,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Booth|first1=William|title=In Church Fires, a Pattern but No Conspiracy|url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-srv/national/longterm/churches/churches.htm|accessdate=2015-06-27|publisher=Washington Post|date=June 19, 1996}}&lt;/ref&gt; and a [[Charleston church shooting|mass shooting in Charleston]] was committed in 2015 at the historic [[Emanuel African Methodist Episcopal Church|Mother Emanuel Church]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ibtimes.com/charleston-church-shooting-south-carolina-racism-will-not-change-after-killings-black-1979391|title=Charleston Church Shooting: South Carolina Racism Will Not Change After Killings, Black Residents Say|author=Elizabeth Whitman|work=International Business Times|date=2015-06-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

From 1981 to 1997, the [[United States Department of Agriculture]] discriminated against tens of thousands of black American farmers, denying loans that were provided to white farmers in similar circumstances. The discrimination was the subject of the ''[[Pigford v. Glickman]]'' lawsuit brought by members of the [[National Black Farmers Association]], which resulted in two settlement agreements of $1.25&amp;nbsp;billion in 1999 and of $1.15&amp;nbsp;billion in 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news | issn = 0362-4331 | last = Southall | first = Ashley | title = Bias Payments Come Too Late for Some Farmers | work = The New York Times | accessdate = 2010-05-26 | date = May 25, 2010 | url = https://www.nytimes.com/2010/05/26/us/26farmers.html?scp=1&amp;sq=black%20farmers&amp;st=cse}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the 1980s and '90s a number of riots occurred that were related to longstanding racial tensions between police and minority communities. The [[1980 Miami riots]] were catalyzed by the killing of an African-American motorist by four white [[Miami-Dade Police]] officers. They were subsequently acquitted on charges of manslaughter and evidence tampering. Similarly, the six-day [[1992 Los Angeles riots]] erupted after the acquittal of four white [[Los Angeles Police Department|LAPD]] officers who had been filmed beating [[Rodney King]], an African-American motorist. [[Khalil Gibran Muhammad]], the Director of the Harlem-based [[Schomburg Center for Research in Black Culture]] has identified more than 100 instances of mass racial violence in the United States since 1935 and has noted that almost every instance was precipitated by a police incident.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.propublica.org/article/yes-black-america-fears-the-police-heres-why |title=Yes, Black America Fears the Police. Here's Why. |last1=Hannah-Jones |first1=Nikole |date=March 4, 2015 |website=[[ProPublica]] |access-date=2015-03-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Politically, the "[[Winner-Take-All Politics|winner-take-all]]" structure that applies to 48 out of 50 states&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.archives.gov/federal-register/electoral-college/faq.html#ecmystate|title=U. S. Electoral College: Frequently Asked Questions|website=www.archives.gov|access-date=2017-03-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; in the [[electoral college]] benefits white representation, as no state has voters of color as the majority of the electorate.&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{Cite book|title=Political sociology : oppression, resistance, and the state|last=Deric.|first=Shannon|date=January 1, 2011|publisher=Sage [u.a.]|isbn=9781412980401|oclc=815880812}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{dubious|date=January 2018}}&lt;!-- [[Majority minority]] says Hawaii, Mexico, California, Texas and Nevada have less than 50% non-Hispanic white populations, as does D.C. and all territories --&gt; This has been described as structural bias and often leads voters of color to feel [[Political alienation|politically alienated]], and therefore not to vote. The lack of representation in Congress has also led to lower voter turnout.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt; As of 2016, African Americans only made up 8.7% of Congress, and Latinos 7%.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Manning|first=Jennifer|year=2016|title=Membership of the 114th Congress: A Profile|url=https://www.senate.gov/CRSpubs/c527ba93-dd4a-4ad6-b79d-b1c9865ca076.pdf|journal=Congressional Research Service|volume=|pages=|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Many cite the [[2008 United States presidential election]] as a step forward in race relations: white Americans played a role in electing [[Barack Obama]], the country's first black president.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.latimes.com/news/printedition/asection/la-na-assess5-2008nov05,0,6354926.story White Americans play major role in electing the first black president], ''Los Angeles Times''&lt;/ref&gt; In fact, Obama received a greater percentage of the white vote (43%),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://pewresearch.org/pubs/1023/exit-poll-analysis-2008|title=Inside Obama's Sweeping Victory|date=November 5, 2008|publisher=Pew Research Center|access-date=April 21, 2011|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110509200438/http://pewresearch.org/pubs/1023/exit-poll-analysis-2008|archive-date=May 9, 2011|url-status=dead|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; than did the previous Democratic candidate, [[John Kerry]] (41%).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.cnn.com/ELECTION/2004/pages/results/states/US/P/00/epolls.0.html|title=U.S. President: National: Exit Poll|publisher=CNN}}&lt;/ref&gt; Racial divisions persisted throughout the election; wide margins of Black voters gave Obama an edge during the presidential primary, where 8 out of 10 African-Americans voted for him in the primaries, and an [[MSNBC]] poll found that race was a key factor in whether a candidate was perceived as being ready for office. In South Carolina, for instance,"Whites were far likelier to name [[Hillary Clinton|Clinton]] than Obama as being most qualified to be commander in chief, likeliest to unite the country and most apt to capture the White House in November. Blacks named Obama over Clinton by even stronger margins—two- and three-to one—in all three areas."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nbcnews.com/id/22859978 |title=Strong black vote gives Obama big boost|publisher=NBC News |date=January 26, 2008 |accessdate=2013-02-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Sociologist Russ Long stated in 2013 that there is now a more subtle racism that associates a specific race with a specific characteristic.&lt;ref&gt;Long, Russ. [http://dmc122011.delmar.edu/socsci/rlong/problems/chap-08.htm "How to Think about Racial and Ethnic Inequality"] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170826153922/http://dmc122011.delmar.edu/socsci/rlong/problems/chap-08.htm |date=August 26, 2017 }}.&lt;/ref&gt; In a 1993 study conducted by Katz and Braly, it was presented that "blacks and whites hold a variety of stereotypes towards each other, often negative".&lt;ref name="Leonard 1993"&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Leonard | first1 = Rebecca | last2 = Locke | first2 = Don C | year = 1993 | title = Communication Stereotypes: Is Interracial Communication Possible? | url = | journal = Journal of Black Studies | volume = 23 | issue = 3| pages = 332–343 | doi=10.1177/002193479302300303}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Katz and Braley study also found that African-Americans and whites view the traits that they identify each other with as threatening, interracial communication between the two is likely to be "hesitant, reserved, and concealing".&lt;ref name="Leonard 1993" /&gt; Interracial communication is guided by stereotypes; stereotypes are transferred into personality and character traits which then have an effect on communication. Multiple factors go into how stereotypes are established, such as age and the setting in which they are being applied.&lt;ref name="Leonard 1993" /&gt; For example, in a study done by the Entman-Rojecki Index of Race and Media in 2014, 89% of black women in movies are shown swearing and exhibiting offensive behavior while only 17% of white women are portrayed in this manner.&lt;ref&gt;Orbe, Mark P., and Tina M. Harris. "Interracial Communication: Theory Into Practice."Google Books. Sage Publications, n.d. Web. February 2, 2014&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2012, [[Trayvon Martin]], a seventeen-year-old teenager was fatally shot by [[George Zimmerman]] in Sanford, Florida. Zimmerman, a neighborhood-watch volunteer, claimed that Martin was being suspicious and called the Sanford police to report him.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://racialequity.org/docs/CIF5Timeline.pdf|title=Timeline of Race, Racism, Resistance and Philanthropy 1992-2014|last=Saloman|first=Larry|website=Racial Equity|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20181221144927/http://racialequity.org/docs/CIF5Timeline.pdf|archive-date=December 21, 2018|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; Between ending his call with police and their arrival, Zimmerman fatally shot Martin outside of the townhouse he was staying at following an altercation. Zimmerman was injured in the altercation and claimed self-defense. The incident caused national outrage after Zimmerman was not charged over the shooting. The national coverage of the incident lead Sandford police to arrest Zimmerman and charge him with second-degree murder, but he was found not guilty at trial. Public outcry followed the acquittal and created an abundance of mistrust between minorities and the [[Shooting of Trayvon Martin|Sanford police]]. 	

In 2014, the police [[shooting of Michael Brown]], an African American, in Ferguson, Missouri lead to widespread [[Ferguson unrest|unrest]] in the town. In the years following, mass media has followed other high profile police shootings of African-Americans, often with video evidence from police [[Body worn video (police equipment)|body-worn]] cameras. Amongst 15 high-profile police shooting deaths of African-Americans, only 1 officer faced prison time. High-profile shooting deaths of African-Americans lead to the creation of the Black Lives Matter movement.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2017/05/17/us/black-deaths-police.html|title=In 15 High-Profile Cases Involving Deaths of Blacks, One Officer Faces Prison Time|last=Lee|first=Jasmine|date=December 7, 2017|work=New York Times|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[U.S. Justice Department|U.S. Justice department]] launched the National Center for Building Community Trust and Justice in 2014.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://racialequity.org/docs/CIF5Timeline.pdf|title=Timeline of Race, Racism, Resistance and Philanthropy 1992-2014|last=Saloman|first=Larry|date=June 2014|website=Racial Equity|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20181221144927/http://racialequity.org/docs/CIF5Timeline.pdf|archive-date=December 21, 2018|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; This program collects data concerning racial profiling to create change in the criminal justice system concerning implicit and explicit racial bias towards African-Americans as well as other minorities.

In August 2017, the [[International Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Racial Discrimination#Committee on the Elimination of Racial Discrimination|UN Committee on the Elimination of Racial Discrimination]] issued a rare warning to the US and its leadership to "unequivocally and unconditionally" condemn racist speech and crime, following violence in Charlottesville during a rally organized by [[white nationalists]], [[white supremacists]], [[Klansmen]], [[neo-Nazis]] and various right-wing militias in July.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= https://www.aljazeera.com/news/2017/08/issues-rare-warning-alarming-racism-170823225952827.html|title=UN issues rare warning over 'alarming' racism in US|publisher=Al Jazeera|accessdate=24 August 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= https://www.thejournal.ie/un-racism-warning-to-us-3560646-Aug2017/|title=United Nations issues 'racism warning' over growing US tensions|accessdate=23 August 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Asian Americans ==
[[File:Alaska Death Trap.jpg|thumb|right|A [[World War II]] anti-Japanese propaganda poster utilizing the "Jap" slur and depicting the Japanese as rats, after they conquered parts of [[Alaska]].]]
[[Asian Americans]], including those of [[East Asia]]n, [[Southeast Asia]]n, and [[South Asia]]n descent, have experienced racism since the first major groups of Chinese immigrants arrived in America. The Naturalization Act of 1790 made Asians ineligible for citizenship.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=WDV40aK1T-sC&amp;pg=PA284&amp;dq=African+Americans+discriminated+by+Naturalization+Act+of+1790&amp;cd=1#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false|title=Encyclopedia of Minorities in American Politics: African Americans and Asian Americans|last=Schultz|first=Jeffrey D.|year=2002|isbn=9781573561488|page=284|accessdate=2015-09-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; First-generation immigrants, children of immigrants, and Asians adopted by non-Asian families are still impacted by discrimination.&lt;ref name="Eguchi, Shinsuke 2013" /&gt;

[[File:The only one barred out cph.3b48680.jpg|thumb|A political cartoon from 1882 ridiculing the [[Chinese Exclusion Act]], showing a Chinese man, surrounded by benefits of Chinese immigration, being barred entry to the "Golden Gate of Liberty", while other groups, including [[Communists]] and [[Crime|"hoodlums"]], are allowed to enter. The caption reads sarcastically, "We must draw the line ''somewhere'', you know."]]

During the [[Industrial Revolution in the United States]], labor shortages in the mining and rail industries were prevalent. Chinese immigrant labor was often used to fill this gap, most notably with the construction of the [[First Transcontinental Railroad]], leading to large-scale Chinese immigration.&lt;ref name="Eguchi, Shinsuke 2013"&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Eguchi | first1 = Shinsuke | year = 2013 | title = Revisiting Asiacentricity: Toward Thinking Dialectically about Asian American Identities and Negotiation | url = | journal = Howard Journal of Communications | volume = 24 | issue = 1| pages = 95–115 | doi=10.1080/10646175.2013.748556}}&lt;/ref&gt; These Chinese immigrants were seen as taking the jobs of whites for cheaper pay, and the phrase [[Yellow Peril]], which predicted the demise of Western Civilization as a result of Chinese immigrants, gained popularity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Chin | first1 = Philip | year = 2013 | title = The Chinese Exclusion Act: Ten Year Exclusion Act Debates and Passage – Part 3". | url = | journal = Chinese American Forum | volume = 29 | issue = 1| pages = 24–31 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Anti-Asian legislation in the late 1800s===
The 1879 Constitution of the [[State of California]] prohibited employment of Chinese people by state and local governments, and by businesses incorporated in California. Also, the 1879 California constitution delegated power to local governments of California to remove Chinese people from within their borders.&lt;ref name="archives.cdn.sos.ca.gov"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Hitler's American Model 2017 p. 35"/&gt; The [[Chinese Exclusion Act]] banning immigration of Chinese people was enacted on the national level in 1882, while the immigration of people from Asian countries in addition to China was banned by the sweeping [[Immigration Act of 1917]], also known as the Asiatic Barred Zone Act, which also banned [[homosexual]]s, people with [[intellectual disability]], and people with an [[anarchist]] worldview.&lt;ref name="Hitler's American Model 2017 p. 35"/&gt; The Chinese Exclusion Act was the first time that a law was passed to exclude a major ethnic group from the nation.&lt;ref name="Eguchi, Shinsuke 2013" /&gt;

Several massacres of Chinese people, including the [[Rock Springs massacre]] of 1885 and the [[Hells Canyon massacre]] of 1887 further exemplified deep American racist animus against Chinese people.&lt;ref name=":0"/&gt;

Local discriminatory laws were also enacted to stifle Chinese business and job opportunities; for example, in the 1886 [[Supreme Court of the United States|Supreme Court]] case of ''[[Yick Wo v. Hopkins]]'', a San Francisco city ordinance requiring permits for laundries (which were mostly Chinese-owned) was struck down, as it was evident the law solely targeted Chinese Americans. When the law was in effect, the city issued permits to virtually all non-Chinese permit applicants, while only granting one permit out of two hundred applications from Chinese laundry owners. When the Chinese laundries continued to operate, the city tried to fine the owners. In 1913, California, home to many Chinese immigrants, enacted an [[California Alien Land Law of 1913|Alien Land Law]], which significantly restricted land ownership by Asian immigrants, and [[California Alien Land Law of 1920|extended it]] in 1920, ultimately banning virtually all land ownership by Asians.&lt;ref name="ReferenceB"&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Sakamoto | first1 = Taylor | year = 2007 | title = The Triumph and Tragedies of Japanese Women in America: A View Across Four Generations | url = | journal = History Teacher | volume = 41 | issue = 1| pages = 97–122 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Japanese immigrants, who has been unaffected by the Chinese Exclusion Act, began in 1907 to enter the United States in large numbers, filling jobs that were once filled by Chinese workers. This influx also led to discrimination and [[Theodore Roosevelt|President Theodore Roosevelt]] restricted Japanese immigration. Later, Japanese immigration was closed when Japan entered into the [[Gentlemen's Agreement of 1907]] to stop issuing passports to Japanese workers intending to move to the U.S.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Eguchi | first1 = Shinsuke | year = 2013 | title = Revisiting Asia centricity: Toward Thinking Dialectically about Asian American Identities and Negotiation | url = | journal = Howard Journal of Communications | volume = 24 | issue = 1| pages = 95–115 | doi=10.1080/10646175.2013.748556}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During [[World War II]], the [[Taiwan|Republic of China]] was an ally of the United States, and the federal government praised the resistance of the Chinese against Japan in the [[Second Sino-Japanese War]], attempting to reduce anti-Chinese sentiment. In 1943, the [[Magnuson Act]] was passed by Congress, repealing the Chinese Exclusion Act and reopening Chinese immigration. However, at the time, the United States was actively fighting the [[Empire of Japan]], which was a member of the [[Axis powers]]. Anti-Japanese racism, which spiked after the [[attack on Pearl Harbor]], was tacitly encouraged by the government, which used slurs such as "[[Jap]]" in propaganda posters and even [[Internment of Japanese Americans|interned Japanese Americans]], citing possible security threats. Soldiers in the Pacific theater often dehumanized their enemy, leading to [[American mutilation of Japanese war dead]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://drive.google.com/file/d/0B-5-JeCa2Z7hN2ZkMWRiNmYtN2M4Ny00YjQ2LWJlMjYtZGY0NmMxMzM5NzQ2/view?ddrp=1&amp;hl=en&amp;pli=1&amp;usp=embed_facebook|title=Trophies of War, US Troops and the Mutilation of Japanese War Dead, 1941-1945 - James J Weingartner - PHR Vol 61 No 1 Feb 1992.pdf|website=Google Docs|access-date=2016-12-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; The racist nature of this dehumanization is apparent in the inconsistency of the treatment of corpses in the Pacific and the European theaters. Apparently some soldiers mailed home Japanese skulls as souvenirs, while none mailed home German or Italian skulls.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|url=http://uir.ulster.ac.uk/1559/|title=Skull trophies of the Pacific War: transgressive objects of remembrance|pages=817–836|last=Simon|first=Harrison|date=December 7, 2016|journal=Journal of the Royal Anthropological Institute|volume=12|issue=4|access-date=2016-12-07|doi=10.1111/j.1467-9655.2006.00365.x}}&lt;/ref&gt; This prejudice continued for some time after the war, and Asian racism affected U.S. policy in the Korean and Vietnam Wars, even though Asians were on both sides of those wars as well as World War II. Some historians have alleged that a climate of racism, with unofficial rules like the "mere gook rule",&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/?id=lWjLdLahLToC&amp;pg=PA31&amp;dq=mere+gook+rule#v=onepage&amp;q=mere%20gook%20rule&amp;f=false|title=The Washington Connection and Third World Fascism|last=Chomsky|first=Noam|last2=Herman|first2=Edward S.|date=January 1, 1979|publisher=South End Press|isbn=9780896080904|location=|pages=31|quote=|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.vice.com/read/vietnam-and-the-mere-gook-rule|title=The Secret History of the Vietnam War {{!}} VICE {{!}} United States|date=April 17, 2013|work=VICE|access-date=2016-12-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; allowed for a pattern in which South Vietnamese civilians were treated as less than human and war crimes became common.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/?id=6q3vpJ3ePH4C&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=kill+anything+that+moves#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|title=Kill Anything That Moves: The Real American War in Vietnam|last=Turse|first=Nick|date=January 15, 2013|publisher=Macmillan|isbn=9780805086911}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Prior to 1965, Indian immigration to the U.S. was small and isolated, with fewer than 50,000 Indian immigrants in the country. The [[Bellingham riots]] in [[Bellingham, Washington]], on September 5, 1907, epitomized the low tolerance in the U.S. for Indians and [[Hindu]]s. While anti-Asian racism was embedded in U.S. politics and culture in the early 20th century, Indians were also racialized, with U.S. officials casting them as "Hindu menaces" and pushing for Western imperial expansion abroad.&lt;ref name="Seema"&gt;{{cite book|author=Seema Sohi|title=Echoes of Mutiny: Race, Surveillance, and Indian Anticolonialism in North America|year=2014|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=978-0-19-937625-4|page=8 |quote=Indians in North America, nearly 90 percent of whom where Sikhs from the state of Punjab, were also racialized through colonial gendered discourses. During the early decades of the twentieth century, US Immigration, Justice, and State Department officials cast Indian anti-colonialists as a "Hindu" menace}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the 1923 case, ''[[United States v. Bhagat Singh Thind]]'', the Supreme Court ruled that high caste Hindus were not "white persons" and were therefore racially ineligible for naturalized citizenship.&lt;ref name="Thind" /&gt; The Court argued that the racial difference between Indians and whites was so great that the "great body of our people" would reject assimilation with Indians.&lt;ref name="Thind"&gt;Zhao, X. &amp; Park, E.J.W. (2013). Asian Americans: An Encyclopedia of Social, Cultural, Economic, and Political History&lt;/u&gt;. Greenwood. pp. 1142. {{ISBN|978-1-59884-239-5}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was after the [[Luce–Celler Act of 1946]] that a quota of 100 Indians per year could immigrate to the U.S. and become citizens.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.pbs.org/rootsinthesand/a_lucecellar.html |title=Roots in the Sand&amp;nbsp;– the Archives |publisher=PBS |date= |accessdate=2016-05-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Immigration and Nationality Act of 1965]] dramatically opened entry to the U.S. to immigrants other than traditional [[Northern European]] and [[Germanic peoples|Germanic groups]], and as a result would significantly, and unintentionally, alter the demographic mix in the U.S.&lt;ref name="Immigration law"&gt;{{cite web |title= 1965 immigration law changed face of America |author=Jennifer Ludden |url=https://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=5391395 |publisher=NPR |accessdate=2016-05-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; On the U.S. immigration laws prior to 1965, sociologist [[Stephen Klineberg]] stated the law "declared that Northern Europeans are a superior subspecies of the white race."&lt;ref name="Immigration law"/&gt; In 1990, Asian immigration was encouraged when nonimmigrant temporary working visas were given to help with the shortage of skilled labor within the United States.&lt;ref name="Eguchi, Shinsuke 2013" /&gt;

In modern times, Asians have been perceived as a "[[model minority]]". They are categorized as more educated and successful, and are stereotyped as intelligent and hard-working, but socially inept.&lt;ref name="Lai, Lei 2013"&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Lai | first1 = Lei | last2 = Babcock | first2 = Linda C. | year = 2013 | title = Asian Americans and Workplace Discrimination: The Interplay between Sex of Evaluators and the Perception of Social Skills | url = | journal = Journal of Organizational Behavior | volume = 34 | issue = 3| pages = 310–26 | doi=10.1002/job.1799}}&lt;/ref&gt; Asians may experience expectations of natural intelligence and excellence from whites as well as other minorities.&lt;ref name="ReferenceB" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Kim | first1 = Isok | year = 2014 | title = The Role of Critical Ethnic Awareness and Social Support in the discrimination–depression Relationship among Asian Americans: Path Analysis | url = | journal = Cultural Diversity and Ethnic Minority Psychology | volume = 20 | issue = 1| pages = 52–60 | doi=10.1037/a0034529| pmid = 24491128 }}&lt;/ref&gt; This has led to discrimination in the workplace, as Asian Americans may face unreasonable expectations because of this stereotype. According to the Journal of Organizational Behavior, in 2000, out of 1,218 adult Asian Americans, 92 percent of those who experienced personal discrimination believed that the unfair treatment was due to their ethnicity.&lt;ref name="Lai, Lei 2013" /&gt;

These stereotypes can also obstruct career paths; because Asians are seen as better skilled in engineering, computing, and mathematics, they are often encouraged to pursue technical careers. They are also discouraged from pursuing non-technical occupations or executive occupations requiring more social interaction, since Asians are perceived to have poor social skills. In the 2000 study, forty percent of those surveyed who experienced discrimination believed that they had lost hiring or promotion opportunities. In 2007, the [[Equal Employment Opportunity Commission]] reported that Asians make up 10 percent of professional jobs, while 3.7 percent of them held executive, senior level, or manager positions.&lt;ref name="Lai, Lei 2013" /&gt;

Other forms of discrimination against Asian Americans include racial profiling and hate crimes. The FBI noted that in 2015, 3.2 percent of all hate crimes involved anti-Asian bias.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://ucr.fbi.gov/hate-crime/2015/topic-pages/victims_final|title=Victims|website=FBI|access-date=2018-12-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2016, the [[Seattle]] Police Department reported that there was a 40 percent increase in race-based crimes against Asian-Americans, both criminal and non-criminal.&lt;ref&gt;Kebba, Michael T. Bias Crimes and Incidents Synopsis. Seattle: Seattle Police Department Memorandum, 2016. Print.&lt;/ref&gt;

Research shows that discrimination has led to more use of informal mental health services by Asian Americans. Asian Americans who feel discriminated against also tend to smoke more.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Chae | first1 = David H. | display-authors = etal | year = 2008 | title = Unfair Treatment, Racial/Ethnic Discrimination, Ethnic Identification, and Smoking among Asian Americans in the National Latino and Asian American Study | journal = American Journal of Public Health | volume = 98 | issue = 3| pages = 485–92 | doi=10.2105/ajph.2006.102012 | pmid=18235073 | pmc=2253562}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== European Americans{{anchor|European immigrants}} ==
{{See also|Anti-Catholicism|Anti-German sentiment|Anti-Irish sentiment|Anti-Italianism|Anti-Polish sentiment|Anti-Russian sentiment|Anti-Slavic sentiment}}
Various [[European Americans|European American]] immigrant groups have been subjected to discrimination either on the basis of their immigrant status (known as "[[Nativism (politics)|Nativism]]") or on the basis of their ethnicities (country of origin).
[[File:Philadelphia1844riot.jpg|thumb|[[Philadelphia nativist riots|Philadelphia Nativist riots]].]]
[[File:NINA-nyt.JPG|thumb|''[[New York Times]]'', 1854 ad, reading "No Irish need apply."]]
In the 19th century, this was particularly true because of [[Anti-Irish sentiment|anti-Irish prejudice]], which was based on [[Anti-Catholicism|anti-Catholic]] sentiment, and prejudice against the Irish as an ethnicity. This was especially true for Irish Catholics who immigrated to the U.S. in the mid-19th century; the large number of Irish (both Catholic and Protestant) who settled in America in the 18th century had largely (but not entirely) escaped such discrimination and eventually blended into the white American population. During the 1830s in the U.S., riots over control of job sites broke out in rural areas among rival labor teams from different parts of Ireland, and between Irish and local American work teams competing for construction jobs.&lt;ref&gt;Prince, Carl E. (1985) "The Great 'Riot Year': Jacksonian Democracy and Patterns of Violence in 1834." ''Journal of the Early Republic'' 5(1): 1–19. ISSN 0275-1275 examines 24 episodes including the January labor riot at the Chesapeake &amp; Ohio Canal, the New York City election riot in April, the Philadelphia race riot in August, and the Baltimore &amp; Washington Railroad riot in November.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Native American Party, commonly called the [[Know Nothing]] movement was a political party, whose membership was limited to Protestant men, that operated on a national basis during the mid-1850s and sought to limit the influence of Irish Catholics and other immigrants, thus reflecting nativism and anti-Catholic sentiment. There was widespread anti-Irish job discrimination in the United States and "No Irish need apply" signs were common.&lt;ref&gt;Fried, Rebecca A. (2015) "No Irish Need Deny: Evidence for the Historicity of NINA Restrictions in Advertisements and Signs" ''Journal of Social History'' 48. Accessed July 17, 2015. doi: 10.1093/jsh/shv066.
---- In addition to job postings, the article also surveys evidence relevant to several of Jensen's subsidiary arguments, including lawsuits involving NINA publications, NINA restrictions in housing solicitations, Irish-American responses to NINA advertisements, and the use of NINA advertisements in Confederate propaganda", and concludes (per the abstract) that "Jensen's thesis about the highly limited extent of NINA postings requires revision", and that "the earlier view of historians generally accepting the widespread reality of the NINA phenomenon is better supported by the currently available evidence."&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url = |title = The New York Herald|date = July 7, 1863|work = |access-date = |via = |volume = XXVIII|issue = 186|page = Page 11}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=LongIsland&gt;{{cite web |last = Young |first = Patrick |title = High School Student Proves Professor Wrong When He Denied "No Irish Need Apply" Signs Existed |url = http://www.longislandwins.com/columns/detail/high_school_student_proves_professor_wrong_when_he_denied_no_irish_need_app |date = July 19, 2015 |website = Long Island Wins |accessdate = August 16, 2015 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Kkk1928.jpg|thumb|left|[[Ku Klux Klan]] members march down Pennsylvania Avenue in Washington, D.C. in 1928. The second era Klan was a large nationwide movement with between four to six million members.]]
The second era [[Ku Klux Klan]] was a very large nationwide organization in the 1920s, consisting of between four to six million members (15% of the nation's eligible population) that especially opposed Catholics.&lt;ref&gt;Mattias Gardell (2003). "Gods of the Blood: The Pagan Revival and White Separatism". p. 80. Duke University Press&lt;/ref&gt; The revival of the Klan was spurred by the release of the 1915 film ''[[The Birth of a Nation]]''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hartford-hwp.com/archives/45a/316.html "A Painful Present as Historians Confront a Nation's Bloody Past"]. Los Angeles Times. Retrieved August 11, 2017&lt;/ref&gt; The second and third incarnations of the Ku Klux Klan made frequent references to America's "[[English Americans|Anglo-Saxon]]" blood.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|authorlink=Michael Newton (author)|author=Newton, Michael|title=The Invisible Empire: The Ku Klux Klan in Florida|date=2001|title-link=The Invisible Empire: The Ku Klux Klan in Florida}}&lt;/ref&gt; Anti-Catholic sentiment, which appeared in North America with the first Pilgrim and [[Puritan]] settlers in New England in the early 17th century, remained evident in the United States up to the presidential campaign of [[John F. Kennedy]], who went on to become the first Catholic U.S. president in 1961.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=America's dark and not-very-distant history of hating Catholics|url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2015/sep/12/america-history-of-hating-catholics|publisher=The Guardian|date=February 15, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{further|Nordic race#Nordicism in the United States}}
The 20th century saw discrimination against immigrants from southern and eastern Europe (notably Italian Americans and [[Polish Americans]]), partly from anti-Catholic sentiment (as well as discrimination against Irish Americans), and partly from [[Nordicism]]. The primary spokesman for Nordicism was the eugenicist [[Madison Grant]]. His 1916 book, ''[[The Passing of the Great Race|The Passing of the Great Race, or the Racial Basis of European History]]'' about Nordicism was highly influential among racial thinking and government policy making in the U.S.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Guterl|first=Matthew Pratt| authorlink=Matthew Pratt Guterl |title=''The Color of Race in America, 1900–1940|year=2004 |publisher=Harvard University Press|location=USA|isbn=978-0-674-01012-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|Biological laws tell us that certain divergent people will not mix or blend. The Nordics propagate themselves successfully. With other races, the outcome shows deterioration on both sides.|Future U.S. president [[Calvin Coolidge]], 1921.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal| last =Coolidge| first =Calvin | title = Whose Country is This?| journal = Good Housekeeping| volume =| page = 14| year = 1921}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

An advocate of the U.S. immigration laws that favored Northern Europeans, the Klansman [[Lothrop Stoddard]] wrote primarily on the alleged dangers posed by "[[colored]]" peoples to white civilization, with his most famous book ''[[The Rising Tide of Color Against White World-Supremacy]]'' in 1920. Nordicism led to the reduction in Southern European, along with [[Slavs|Slavic]] Eastern European and Russian immigrants in the [[National Origins Formula]] of the [[Emergency Quota Act]] of 1921 and the [[Immigration Act of 1924]], whose goal was to maintain the status quo distribution of ethnicity by limiting immigration of non-Northern Europeans. According to the U.S. Department of State the purpose of the act was "to preserve the ideal of American homogeneity".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=https://history.state.gov/milestones/1921-1936/immigration-act | work=U.S. Department of State Office of the Historian | title=The Immigration Act of 1924 (The Johnson-Reed Act) | accessdate=2012-02-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; The racial term ''[[Untermensch]]'' originates from the title of Stoddard's 1922 book ''The Revolt Against Civilization: The Menace of the Under-man''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| author = Stoddard, Lothrop| authorlink = Lothrop Stoddard| year = 1922| title = The Revolt Against Civilization: The Menace of the Under Man| publisher = [[Charles Scribner's Sons]]| location = New York| isbn =| url = https://archive.org/details/revoltagainstciv00stoduoft}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was later adopted by the Nazis (and its chief racial theorist [[Alfred Rosenberg]]) from that book's German version ''Der Kulturumsturz: Die Drohung des Untermenschen'' (1925).&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite journal| author = Losurdo, Domenico| authorlink = Domenico Losurdo| others = Translated by Marella &amp; Jon Morris| year = 2004| title = Toward a Critique of the Category of Totalitarianism| journal = [[Historical Materialism (journal)|Historical Materialism]]| volume = 12| issue = 2| pages = 25–55, here p. 50| issn = 1465-4466| doi = 10.1163/1569206041551663| url = http://www.pssp.org/bbs/data/document/1/Losurdo___Critique_of_Totalitarianism_%282004%29.pdf| format = PDF, 0.2 MB}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There was also discrimination against [[German Americans]] and Italian Americans due to Germany and Italy being enemy countries during [[World War I]] (Germany) and [[World War II]] (Germany and Italy). This resulted in a sharp decrease in German-American ethnic identity and a sharp decrease in the use of [[German in the United States]] following World War I, which had hitherto been significant, and to [[German American internment]] and [[Italian American internment]] during World War II; see also [[German American#World War I anti-German sentiment|World War I anti-German sentiment]].

Beginning in World War I, German Americans were sometimes accused of having political allegiances to Germany, and thus not to the United States.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.earlham.edu/%7Edominel/obituary.htm Hugo Münsterberg's obituary].&lt;/ref&gt; The Justice Department attempted to prepare a list of all German aliens, counting approximately 480,000 of them, more than 4,000 of whom were imprisoned in 1917–18. The allegations included spying for Germany, or endorsing the German war effort.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lib.byu.edu/~rdh/wwi/comment/yockel.htm The War Department: Keeper of Our Nation's Enemy Aliens During World War I] by [[Mitchell Yockelson]]. 1998.&lt;/ref&gt; Thousands were forced to buy war bonds to show their loyalty.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation |url=http://historymatters.gmu.edu/d/1/|title=Get the Rope! Anti-German Violence in World War I-era Wisconsin|accessdate=2008-08-01 |work=History Matters|publisher=George Mason University|date=}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[American Red Cross|Red Cross]] barred individuals with German last names from joining in fear of sabotage. One person was killed by a mob; in [[Collinsville, Illinois]], German-born [[Robert Prager]] was dragged from jail as a suspected spy and lynched.&lt;ref name=Hickey&gt;{{Citation |last=Hickey |first=Donald R. |title=The Prager Affair: A Study in Wartime Hysteria |journal=Journal of the Illinois State Historical Society |volume= |issue= |pages= 126–127 |date=Summer 1969 |url= |doi= |id= }}&lt;/ref&gt; Questions of German American loyalty increased due to events like the German [[Black Tom explosion|bombing of Black Tom island]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://timesmachine.nytimes.com/timesmachine/1916/07/31/104683616.pdf |title=How Eyewitnesses Survived Explosion: Police and Men on Craft Dodged Death on Land and Water to Save Themselves and Others |work=The New York Times |date= July 31, 1916 |accessdate=2010-07-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the U.S. entering World War I, many German Americans were arrested for refusing allegiance to the U.S.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Robbins |first=Jim |url=https://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F50C17FC355B0C708CDDAC0894DE404482 |title=Silence Broken, Pardons Granted 88 Years After Crimes of Sedition |work= The New York Times |date=May 3, 2006 |accessdate=2010-07-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; War hysteria led to the removal of German names in public, names of things such as streets,&lt;ref name="cincy"&gt;Kathleen Doane. [https://web.archive.org/web/20140120043547/http://cincinnati.com/blogs/ourhistory/2012/06/06/anti-german-hysteria-swept-cincinnati-in-1917/ "Anti-German hysteria swept Cincinnati in 1917"] . ''The Cincinnati Enquirer'', June 6, 2012. Accessed February 15, 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; and businesses.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardianlife.com/glife11pp/groups/camp_internet/@stellent_camp_website_glife_corpcomm_edits/documents/report/guardian2009annualreportfin.pdf Guardian 2009 Annual Report]{{dead link|date=November 2016 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}, p. 2; Anita Rapone, The Guardian Life Insurance Company, 1860–1920: A History of a German-American Enterprise (New York: New York University Press, 1987); Robert E. Wright and George David Smith, Mutually Beneficial: The Guardian and Life Insurance in America (New York: New York University Press, 2004).&lt;/ref&gt; Schools also began to eliminate or discourage the teaching of the German language.&lt;ref&gt;[http://digital-archives.ccny.cuny.edu/archival-collections/wp-content/uploads/2012/03/Archival-Finding-Aid.pdf CCNY Archival Finding Aid], p. 81.&lt;/ref&gt; Years later during the [[Second World War]], German Americans were once again the victims of war hysteria discrimination. Following its entry into the Second World War, the US Government [[German American internment|interned at least 11,000 American citizens]] of German ancestry. The last to be released, a German-American, remained imprisoned until 1948 at Ellis Island,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gaic.info/history.html |title=German American Internee Coalition |publisher=Gaic.info |accessdate=2010-07-30 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100301123425/http://www.gaic.info/history.html |archivedate=March 1, 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt; three and a half years after the cessation of hostilities against Germany.

Specific racism against other European-American ethnicities significantly diminished as a political issue in the 1930s, being replaced by a bi-racialism of black/white, as described and predicted by [[Lothrop Stoddard]], due to numerous causes. The National Origins Formula significantly reduced inflows of non-Nordic ethnicities; the [[Great Migration (African American)|Great Migration]] (of African-Americans out of the South) displaced anti-white immigrant racism with anti-black racism.&lt;ref name="Migration"/&gt;

=== Antiziganism ===
{{Main|Antiziganism}}

The [[Romani Americans|Roma population in America]] has blended more-or-less seamlessly into the rest of American society.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://feefhs.org/resource/romania-in-america|title=Romanians in America {{!}} FEEFHS|website=feefhs.org|access-date=2018-11-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the United States, the term "Gypsy" has come to be associated with a trade, a profession, or a lifestyle more than with the Romani ethnic/racial group.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.pri.org/stories/2014-07-03/what-does-it-mean-be-american-romani-or-gypsy|title=What does it mean to be American Romani or Gypsy?|work=Public Radio International|access-date=2018-11-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some Americans, especially those self-employed in the [[fortune-telling]] and psychic reading business, use the term "Gypsy" to describe themselves or their enterprise, despite having no ties to the Roma people. This can be chalked up to misperception and ignorance regarding the term rather than any bigotry or even anti-ziganism.&lt;ref&gt;Sutherland, Anne (1986). ''Gypsies: The Hidden Americans''. Waveland Press. p. 86. {{ISBN|0-88133-235-6}}&lt;br /&gt;{{ISBN|978-0-88133-235-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Latino Americans{{anchor|Hispanic_and_Latino_Americans}} ==
{{main|Hispanophobia|Anti-Mexican sentiment}}
Americans of [[Latin America]]n ancestry (often categorized as "[[Hispanic]]") come from a wide variety of racial and ethnic backgrounds. Latinos are not all distinguishable as a racial minority.

After the [[Mexican–American War]] (1846–1848), the United States annexed much of the current Southwestern region from Mexico. Mexicans residing in that territory found themselves subject to discrimination. It is estimated that at least 597 Mexicans were lynched between 1848 and 1928 (this is a conservative estimate due to lack of records in many reported lynchings). Mexicans were lynched at a rate of 27.4 per 100,000 of population between 1880 and 1930. This statistic is second only to that of the African American community during the same period, which suffered an average of 37.1 per 100,000 of population.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/?id=m_mXXvWYO-sC&amp;pg=PA135&amp;lpg=PA135&amp;dq=lynching+mexicans+in+the+us+in+1800s#v=onepage&amp;q=lynching%20mexicans%20in%20the%20us%20in%201800s&amp;f=false|title=Encyclopedia of the Mexican American Civil Rights Movement|publisher=Greenwood Publishing Group|date=2000|author1=Matt S. Meier |author2=Margo Gutierrez |isbn=9780313304255}}&lt;/ref&gt; Between 1848 and 1879, Mexicans were lynched at an unprecedented rate of 473 per 100,000 of population.&lt;ref name=autogenerated2&gt;{{cite web|url=http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m2005/is_2_37/ai_111897839/pg_9 |title=The lynching of persons of Mexican origin or descent in the United States, 1848 to 1928 &amp;#124; Journal of Social History &amp;#124; Find Articles at BNET.com |publisher=Findarticles.com |accessdate=2013-02-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:California_Santa_Cruz_illegales.jpg|thumb|right|Hispanic protest against California immigration policy. ''Todos somos ilegales – We are all Illegals''. Also, ''The land we stand on, every inch of it stolen''.]]
During the [[Great Depression]], the U.S. government sponsored a [[Mexican Repatriation]] program which was intended to encourage Mexican immigrants to voluntarily return to Mexico, however, many were forcibly removed against their will. In total, up to one million persons of Mexican ancestry were deported, approximately 60 percent of those individuals were actually U.S. citizens.

The [[Zoot Suit riots]] were vivid incidents of racial violence against Latinos (e.g., [[Mexican-Americans]]) in Los Angeles in 1943. Naval servicemen stationed in a Latino neighborhood conflicted with youth in the dense neighborhood. Frequent confrontations between small groups and individuals had intensified into several days of non-stop rioting. Large mobs of servicemen would enter civilian quarters looking to attack Mexican American youths, some of whom were wearing [[zoot suit]]s, a distinctive exaggerated fashion popular among that group.&lt;ref&gt;Richard Griswold del Castillo, "The Los Angeles "Zoot Suit Riots" Revisited: Mexican and Latin American Perspectives," ''Mexican Studies/Estudios Mexicanos'', Vol. 16, No. 2. (Summer, 2000), pp. 367–391.&lt;/ref&gt; The disturbances continued unchecked, and even assisted, by the local police for several days before base commanders declared downtown Los Angeles and Mexican American neighborhoods off-limits to servicemen.&lt;ref&gt;Arthur C. Verge, "The Impact of the Second World War on Los Angeles," ''The Pacific Historical Review'', Vol. 63, No. 3, Fortress California at War: San Francisco, Los Angeles, Oakland, and San Diego, 1941–1945. (Aug. 1994), pp. 306–07.&lt;/ref&gt;

Many public institutions, businesses, and homeowners associations had official policies to exclude Mexican Americans. School children of Mexican American descent were subject to racial segregation in the public school system. In many counties, Mexican Americans were excluded from serving as jurors in court cases, especially in those that involved a Mexican American defendant. In many areas across the Southwest, they lived in separate residential areas, due to laws and real estate company policies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.teachersdomain.org/resource/osi04.soc.ush.civil.mendez/ |title=Teachers' Domain: Mendez v. Westminster: Desegregating California's Schools |publisher=Teachersdomain.org |date=December 22, 2004 |accessdate=2013-02-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tshaonline.org/handbook/online/articles/jrh01 |title=Handbook of Texas Online – HERNANDEZ V. STATE OF TEXAS |publisher=Tshaonline.org |date=February 16, 1927 |accessdate=2013-02-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=autogenerated5&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.understandingrace.org/history/society/post_war_economic_boom.html |title=RACE – History – Post-War Economic Boom and Racial Discrimination |publisher=Understandingrace.org |date=December 21, 1956 |accessdate=2013-02-16 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130818185124/http://www.understandingrace.org/history/society/post_war_economic_boom.html |archive-date=August 18, 2013 |url-status=dead |df=mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/?id=CzarnBhJiZUC&amp;pg=PA53&amp;lpg=PA53&amp;dq=history+residential+discrimination+%22mexican+americans%22#PPA53,M1 |title=Black, Brown, Yellow, and Left: Radical Activism in Los Angeles – Laura Pulido – Google Boeken |date=December 17, 2005 |accessdate=2013-02-16|isbn=978-0-520-93889-2|last1=Pulido |first1=Laura }}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the 1960s, Mexican American youth formed the [[Chicano Movement|Chicano Civil Rights Movement]].

== Jewish Americans ==
{{main|Antisemitism in the United States|History of antisemitism in the United States}}
[[Antisemitism]] has also played a role in the United States. During the late 19th and early 20th centuries, hundreds of thousands of ethnic [[Jews]] escaped the [[pogrom]]s in Europe. They boarded boats which left ports that were located on the [[Baltic Sea]] as well as ports that were located in [[Northern Germany]], and they largely arrived at [[Ellis Island]], [[New York (state)|New York]].&lt;ref name="Takaki-JewishMigr"&gt;Ronald Takaki, ''A Different Mirror: A History of Multicultural America'' (New York: Little, Brown &amp; Co., 1993), 277–283.&lt;/ref&gt;

It is suggested by [[Leo Rosten]], in his book ''[[The Joys of Yiddish]]'', that as soon as they left their boats, they were subjected to racism by the port immigration authorities. The derogatory term ''[[kike]]'' was adopted in reference to Jews (because most of them could not write and as a result, they may have signed their immigration papers with circles – or kikels in [[Yiddish]]).&lt;ref&gt;Rosten, Leo (1968) ''The Joys of Yiddish''&lt;/ref&gt; Efforts were also made by the [[Asiatic Exclusion League]] to bar Jewish immigrants (along with other Middle Eastern ethnic groups, like [[Arabs]], [[Assyrian people|Assyrians]], and [[Armenians]]) from naturalization, but they (along with Assyrians and Armenians) were nevertheless granted US citizenship, despite being classified as Asians.&lt;ref&gt;[[iarchive:asiaticexclusion00asia|"Proceedings of the Asiatic Exclusion League"]] Asiatic Exclusion League. San Francisco: April 1910. Pg. 7. "To amend section twenty-one hundred and sixty-nine of the Revised Statutes of the United States. Be it enacted by the Senate and House of Representatives of the United States of America in Congress assembled, that section twenty-one hundred and sixty-nine of the Revised Statutes of the United States be, and the same is hereby, amended by adding thereto the following: And Mongolians, Malays, and other Asiatics, except Armenians, Assyrians, and Jews, shall not be naturalized in the United States."&lt;/ref&gt;

Beginning in the 1910s, Southern Jewish communities were attacked by the Ku Klux Klan, which objected to Jewish immigration, and often used "The Jewish Banker" caricature in its propaganda. In 1915, [[Leo Frank]] was lynched in Georgia after being convicted of [[rape]] and sentenced to death (his punishment was commuted to life imprisonment).&lt;ref name="lynching openly organized"&gt;Phagan, 1987, p. 27, states that "everyone knew the identity of the lynchers" (putting the words in her father's mouth). Oney, 2003, p. 526, quotes Carl Abernathy as saying, "They'd go to a man's office and talk to him or&amp;nbsp;... see a man on the job and talk to him," and an unidentified lyncher as saying "The organization of the body was more open than mysterious."&lt;/ref&gt; This event was a catalyst in the re-formation of the new Ku Klux Klan.&lt;ref name="time"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,898581,00.html|title=The Various Shady Lives of the Ku Klux Klan|date=April 9, 1965|work=[[Time magazine]]|publisher=|pages=|id=|quote=An itinerant Methodist preacher named William Joseph Simmons started up the Klan again in Atlanta. On Thanksgiving Eve 1915, Simmons took 15 friends to the top of Stone Mountain, near Atlanta, built an altar on which he placed an American flag, a Bible and an unsheathed sword, set fire to a crude wooden cross, muttered a few incantations about a "practical fraternity among men," and declared himself Imperial Wizard of the Invisible Empire of the Knights of the Ku Klux Klan.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Events in [[Nazi Germany]] also attracted attention in the United States. Jewish lobbying for intervention in Europe drew opposition from the [[isolationists]], amongst whom was Father [[Charles Coughlin]], a well known radio priest, who was known to be critical of Jews, believing that they were leading the United States into [[World War II|the war]].&lt;ref name="Coughlin"&gt;[http://coat.ncf.ca/our_magazine/links/53/coughlin.html Father Charles Edward Coughlin (1891–1971)] By Richard Sanders, editor, ''Press for Conversion!''&lt;/ref&gt; He preached in weekly, overtly anti-Semitic sermons and, from 1936, began publication of a newspaper, ''[[Social Justice (periodical)|Social Justice]]'', in which he printed anti-Semitic accusations such as ''[[The Protocols of the Elders of Zion]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Mary Christine Athans, "A New Perspective on Father Charles E. Coughlin," ''Church History'', Vol. 56, No. 2. (June 1987), pp. 224–235, [[American Society of Church History]]&lt;/ref&gt;

A number of Jewish organizations, Christian organizations, Muslim organizations, and academics consider the [[Nation of Islam]] [[Nation of Islam and antisemitism|anti-Semitic]]. Specifically, they claim that the Nation of Islam has engaged in revisionist and antisemitic interpretations of [[the Holocaust]] and exaggerates the [[Jewish views on slavery|role of Jews in the African slave trade]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.h-net.msu.edu/~antis/papers/occasional.papers.html|title=H-ANTISEMITISM OCCASIONAL PAPERS, NO. 1M|publisher=H-net.msu.edu|accessdate=2013-02-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Anti-Defamation League]] (ADL) alleged that the NOI's Health Minister, Dr. Abdul Alim Muhammad, accused Jewish doctors of injecting [[Black people|blacks]] with the [[HIV/AIDS|AIDS virus]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.adl.org/focus_sheets/focus_islam.asp|title=The Nation of Islam|publisher=Anti-Defamation League|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20060426194442/http://www.adl.org/focus_sheets/focus_islam.asp|archivedate=April 26, 2006|accessdate=July 17, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; an allegation that Muhammad and ''[[The Washington Post]]'' have refuted.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite newspaper|url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/archive/politics/1993/09/27/a-dc-clinics-controversial-rx-for-aids/19d2c4a8-5d3a-48a3-8df3-061eb6a99d26/|title=A D.C. Clinic's Controversial Rx for AIDS|last=Goldstein|first=Amy|date=September 27, 1993|work=The Washington Post|accessdate=July 17, 2016|quote=His critics, including the Anti-Defamation League, contend that Muhammad's speeches contain antisemitic slurs. The critics have provided evidence of such remarks made by [NOI leader Louis] Farrakhan but not by Muhammad. In his several taped speeches, Muhammad has named Israel among the countries in what he calls the genocidal AIDS conspiracy, but he does not single out Jews for criticism.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Although Jews are often considered white by mainstream American society, the relationship between Jews and the concept of whiteness remains complex, with some preferring not to identify as white.&lt;ref name="ReferenceA"&gt;Seth Korelitz, "The Menorah Idea: From Religion to Culture, From Race to Ethnicity," ''American Jewish History'' 1997 85(1): 75–100. 0164–0178&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Peter Novick, ''The Holocaust in American Life'' (1999); Hilene Flanzbaum, ed. ''The Americanization of the Holocaust'' (1999); Monty Noam Penkower, "Shaping Holocaust Memory," ''American Jewish History'' 2000 88(1): 127–132. 0164–0178&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Steve Siporin, "Immigrant and Ethnic Family Folklore," ''Western States Jewish History'' 1990 22(3): 230–242. 0749–5471&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Village Voice 1993"&gt;Lerner, Michael (May 18, 1993). "Jews Are Not White". ''[[The Village Voice]]''. XXXVIII (20). pp. 33–34.&lt;/ref&gt; Prominent activist and rabbi [[Michael Lerner (rabbi)|Michael Lerner]] argues, in a 1993 ''[[The Village Voice|Village Voice]]'' article, that "in America, to be 'white' means to be the beneficiary of the past 500 years of European exploration and exploitation of the rest of the world" and that "Jews can only be deemed white if there is massive amnesia on the part of non-Jews about the monumental history of anti-Semitism".&lt;ref name="Village Voice 1993" /&gt; African-American activist [[Cornel West]], in an interview with the [[United States Holocaust Memorial Museum]], has explained:

{{quote|Even if some Jews do believe that they're white, I think that they've been duped. I think that antisemitism has proven itself to be a powerful force in nearly every post of Western civilization where Christianity has a presence. And so even as a Christian, I say continually to my Jewish brothers and sisters: don't believe the hype about your full scale assimilation and integration into the mainstream. It only takes an event or two for a certain kind of anti-Jewish, antisemitic sensibility to surface in places that you would be surprised. But I'm just thoroughly convinced that America is not the promised land for Jewish brothers and sisters. A lot of Jewish brothers say, "No, that's not true. We finally&amp;nbsp;..." Yeah—they said that in [[History of the Jews in Egypt#Ptolemaic and Roman|Alexandria]]. You said that in [[Weimar Germany]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Voices on Antisemitism Podcast |url=http://www.ushmm.org/museum/exhibit/focus/antisemitism/voices/transcript/?content=20070719 |work=[[USHMM]] |accessdate=January 4, 2014 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070823095028/http://www.ushmm.org/museum/exhibit/focus/antisemitism/voices/transcript/?content=20070719 |archivedate=August 23, 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

=== New Antisemitism ===
{{Main|New antisemitism}}
In recent years, some scholars have advanced the concept of ''New antisemitism'', coming simultaneously from the [[Far-left politics|far left]], the [[Far-right politics|far right]], and [[Islamism|radical Islam]]. This tends to focus on opposition to the creation of a Jewish homeland in the [[State of Israel]], and it also argues that the language of [[Anti-Zionism]] and [[criticism of Israel]] are both used to attack Jews more broadly. According to this view, the proponents of the new concept believe that criticisms of Israel and [[Zionism]] are often disproportionate in degree and unique in kind, and they attribute this to antisemitism.&lt;ref&gt;Sources for the following are:
* [[Yehuda Bauer|Bauer, Yehuda]]. {{cite web|url=http://humanities.ucsc.edu/JewishStudies/docs/YBauerLecture.pdf|title=Problems of Contemporary Anti-Semitism|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20030705131522/http://humanities.ucsc.edu/JewishStudies/docs/YBauerLecture.pdf|archivedate=July 5, 2003|url-status=bot: unknown|accessdate=2003-07-05}}, 2003, retrieved April 22, 2006.
* [[Phyllis Chesler|Chesler, Phyllis]]. ''The New Anti-Semitism: The Current Crisis and What We Must Do About It'', Jossey-Bass, 2003, pp. 158–159, 181.
* Doward, Jamie. [http://observer.guardian.co.uk/uk_news/story/0,6903,1278580,00.html Jews predict record level of hate attacks: Militant Islamic media accused of stirring up new wave of anti-semitism], ''[[The Guardian]]'', August 8, 2004.
* [[Warren Kinsella|Kinsella, Warren]]. [http://www.warrenkinsella.com/words_extremism_nas.htm The New anti-Semitism] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20071014000502/http://www.warrenkinsella.com/words_extremism_nas.htm|date=October 14, 2007}}, accessed March 5, 2006.
* [[Jonathan Sacks|Sacks, Jonathan]]. [http://israel.jcca.org/articles.htm?y=620051118152416 "The New Antisemitism"] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080607061754/http://israel.jcca.org/articles.htm?y=620051118152416|date=June 7, 2008}}, Ha'aretz, September 6, 2002, retrieved on January 10, 2007.
* [[Mark Strauss (journalist)|Strauss, Mark]]. [https://web.archive.org/web/20031205153139/http://yaleglobal.yale.edu/display.article?id=2791 "Antiglobalism's Jewish Problem"] in Rosenbaum, Ron (ed). ''Those who forget the past: The Question of Anti-Semitism'', Random House 2004, p. 272.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Yehuda Bauer]], Professor of Holocaust Studies at the [[Hebrew University of Jerusalem]], has argued that the concept of a "new antisemitism" is essentially false since it is in fact an alternative form of the old antisemitism of previous decades, which he believes remains latent at times but recurs whenever it is triggered. In his view, the current trigger is the [[Israeli–Palestinian conflict|Israel-Palestine situation]]; if a compromise making ground in the [[Arab-Israeli peace process]] were achieved, he believes that antisemitism would once again decline but not disappear.

Noted critics of Israel, such as [[Noam Chomsky]] and [[Norman Finkelstein]], question the extent of new antisemitism in the United States. Chomsky has written in his work ''[[Necessary Illusions]]'' that the [[Anti-Defamation League]] casts any question of pro-Israeli policy as antisemitism, conflating and muddling issues as even Zionists receive the allegation.&lt;ref&gt;[http://home.nvg.org/~skars/ni/ni-c10-s20.html Noam Chomsky, ''Necessary Illusions'', Appendix V, Segment 20]&lt;/ref&gt; Finkelstein has stated that supposed "new antisemitism" is a preposterous concept advanced by the ADL to combat critics of Israeli policy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.democracynow.org/article.pl?sid=06/08/30/1418200|title=Congressmember Weiner Gets It Wrong on Palestinian Group He Tried To Bar From U.S.|date=August 30, 2006|publisher=[[Democracy Now!]]|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20071114051541/http://www.democracynow.org/article.pl?sid=06%2F08%2F30%2F1418200|archivedate=November 14, 2007|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On October 27, 2018, Robert D. Bowers opened fire in a [[synagogue]] in [[Pittsburgh]] with an [[AR-15 style rifle|AR-15-style assault rifle]] while shouting [[Antisemitism|anti-Semitic]] racial slurs. This attack resulted in 11 dead and 6 wounded, leaving the assailant charged with 29 criminal counts, one of which was the obstruction of free exercise of religious beliefs. Both President [[Donald Trump|Trump]] and Prime Minister [[Benjamin Netanyahu]] of Israel have commented on the event, condemning the attack.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2018/10/27/us/active-shooter-pittsburgh-synagogue-shooting.html|title=11 Killed in Synagogue Massacre; Suspect Charged With 29 Counts|access-date=2018-11-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Middle Eastern and South Asian Americans==
{{See also|Anti-Arabism|Islamophobia in the United States|Anti-Iranian sentiment|Anti-Indian sentiment}}
[[File:Assyrianchurchdetroit.jpg|thumb|An [[ACOE|Assyrian church]] vandalized in Detroit (2007). [[Assyrian people|Assyrians]], although not Arabs and mostly [[Syriac Christianity|Christians]], often face backlash in the US for their Middle Eastern background.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
|title = Arab American Institute Still Deliberately Claiming Assyrians Are Arabs
|url = http://www.aina.org/releases/20070416140021.htm
|work =
|publisher = [[Assyrian International News Agency]]
|location =
|id =
|pages =
|page =
|accessdate = 2008-02-09
|quote =
}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
People of Middle Eastern and South Asian descent historically occupied an ambiguous racial status in the United States. Middle Eastern and South Asian immigrants were among those who sued in the late 19th and early 20th century to determine whether they were "white" immigrants as required by naturalization law. By 1923, courts had vindicated a "common-knowledge" standard, concluding that "scientific evidence", including the notion of a "[[Caucasian race]]" including Middle Easterners and many South Asians, was incoherent. Legal scholar John Tehranian argues that in reality this was a "performance-based" standard, relating to religious practices, education, intermarriage and a community's role in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;John Tehranian, "Performing Whiteness: Naturalization Litigation and the Construction of Racial Identity in America," ''[[The Yale Law Journal]]'', Vol. 109, No. 4. (Jan. 2000), pp. 817–848.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Arab Americans ===
{{See also|Anti-Arabism in the United States}}
Racism against [[Arab Americans]]&lt;ref name=Leonard&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wkconline.org/resources/pdf/2005muslim_SAsian_Muslims.pdf|title=Leonard, Karen. University of California, Irvine. Western Knight Center. "American Muslims: South Asian Contributions to the Mix". 2005. July 28, 2007.}}&lt;/ref&gt; and racialized [[Islamophobia]] against Muslims have risen concomitantly with tensions between the American government and the Islamic world.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | publisher = Taylor &amp; Francis | isbn = 978-0-415-37542-9 | pages = 140–43 | editors = Zahia Smail Salhi (ed.) | last = Netton | first = Ian Richard |author2=Evelyn Alsultany | title = The Arab diaspora: Voices of an anguished scream | chapter = From ambiguity to abjection: Iraqi-Americans negotiating race in the United States | year = 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; Following the [[September 11, 2001 attacks]] in the United States, discrimination and [[racialized]] violence has markedly increased against Arab Americans and many other religious and cultural groups.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.hrw.org/reports/2002/usahate/usa1102.htm |title=United States |publisher=Hrw.org |date=September 11, 2001 |accessdate=2013-02-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; Scholars, including Sunaina Maira and Evelyn Alsultany, argue that in the post-September 11 climate, the markers of the [[racialization]] of Muslim Americans are cultural, political, and religious rather than [[Phenotype|phenotypic]].&lt;ref&gt;"While African-Americans, Asians, and Native Americans are racialized according to phenotype, Arab-Americans are often racialized according to religion and politics. Religious racialization conflates Arabs and Islam, and consequently positions all Arabs as Muslim; represents Islam as a monolithic religion erasing diversity among Arabs and Muslims; and marks Islam as a backwards, fanatical, uncivilized, and a terroristic belief system" (p. 127). "Whereas before September 11, Arab- and Muslim-Americans were not included in discourses on race and racism in the United States, a public discourse emerged after September 11 on whether Arabs and Muslims were being treated fairly or being subjected to racism with the rise in hate crimes and government measures targeting Arabs and Muslims" (p. 141). {{Cite book | publisher = [[Taylor &amp; Francis]] | isbn = 978-0-415-37542-9 | editors = Zahia Smail Salhi, Ian Richard Netton (eds.) | last = Alsultany | first = Evelyn | title = The Arab diaspora: Voices of an anguished scream | chapter = From ambiguity to abjection: Iraqi-Americans negotiating race in the United States | year = 2006 | page = 127}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;"'Muslim' identity has certainly congealed as a marker of exclusion and marginalization, in relation to white or mainstream America, which is subjected to similar processes of racialization, and racism, that operate for racial minority groups."{{Cite book | publisher = [[Duke University Press]] | isbn = 978-0-8223-4409-4 | last = Maira | first = Sunaina | title = Missing: youth, citizenship, and empire after 9/11 | date = January 2009 | page = 229}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Arab Americans in particular were most demonized after the September 11 attacks, which led to hatred towards Middle Easterners living in the United States and elsewhere in the Western world.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=Abdul Malik Mujahid |url=http://www.soundvision.com/info/peace/demonization.asp |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20040603093115/http://soundvision.com/info/peace/demonization.asp |url-status=dead |archive-date=2004-06-03 |title=Demonization of Muslims Caused the Iraq Abuse |publisher=Soundvision.com |accessdate=2013-02-16 }}&lt;/ref&gt; There have been attacks against Arabs not only on the basis of their religion ([[Islam]]), but also on the basis of their ethnicity; numerous [[Christian Arabs]] have been attacked based on their appearances.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.pbs.org/niot/citizens_respond/losaltos.html Attacks on Arab Americans] ([[PBS]])&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, other Middle Eastern peoples ([[Persian people|Persians]], [[Assyrian people|Assyrians]], [[Azerbaijanis]], [[Jews]], [[Turkish people|Turks]], [[Yazidis]], [[Kurds]], etc.) who are mistaken for Arabs because of perceived similarities in appearance have been collateral victims of anti-Arabism.

Non-Arab and non-Muslim Middle Eastern people, as well as [[South Asians]] of different ethnic/religious backgrounds ([[Hindu]]s, Muslims and [[Sikh]]s) have been stereotyped as "Arabs" and racialized in a similar manner. The case of [[Balbir Singh Sodhi]], a Sikh who was murdered at a Phoenix gas station by a [[white supremacist]] for "looking like an Arab terrorist" (because of the turban, a requirement of [[Sikhism]]), as well as that of Hindus being attacked for "being Muslims" have achieved prominence and criticism following the [[September 11 attacks]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Murphy, Jarrett |url=http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2002/11/25/national/main530749.shtml |title=Hindu Beaten Because He's Muslim, Mistaken Anti-Islam Thugs Pummel, Hogtie And Stab Deliveryman |publisher=[[CBS News]]|agency=Associated Press |date=February 11, 2009 |accessdate=2013-02-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://www.adl.org/presrele/hatcr_51/4277_51.asp|title = ADL Condemns Hate Crime Against Hindu|publisher = [[Anti-Defamation League]]|accessdate = 2008-07-18|url-status = dead|archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20080718203616/http://www.adl.org/presrele/hatcr_51/4277_51.asp|archivedate = July 18, 2008|df = mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Those of Middle Eastern descent who are in the [[United States military]] face racism from fellow soldiers. Army Spc Zachari Klawonn endured numerous instances of racism during his enlistment at [[Fort Hood, Texas]]. During his basic training, he was made to put cloth around his head and play the role of terrorist. His fellow soldiers had to take him down to the ground and draw guns on him. He was also called things such as "[[raghead]]", "sand monkey", and "Zachari bin Laden".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=http://abcnews.go.com/WN/army-discrimination-muslim-army-specialist-zachari-klawonn-shares/story?id=10372314 | title=Muslim-American Soldier Claims Harassment in the Army | publisher=[[American Broadcasting Company]] | work=[[ABC World News]] with [[Diane Sawyer]] | date=April 14, 2010 | accessdate=March 15, 2013 |author1=Bradley Blackburn |author2=Margaret Aro |lastauthoramp=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;
According to a 2004 study, although official parameters encompass Arabs as part of the "white American" racial category, some Arab American adolescents do not identify as white.&lt;ref name="caliber"&gt;{{cite journal |title=Gender, Race, and Symbolic Boundaries: Contested Spaces of Identity Among Arab American Adolescents|last=Ajrouch|first=Kristine J.|journal=Sociological Perspectives|volume=47|issue=4|pages=371–391|date=Winter 2004|jstor=10.1525/sop.2004.47.4.371|doi=10.1525/sop.2004.47.4.371}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Racial profiling]] is a growing problem for Arab Americans following the [[September 11 attacks]]. Particularly in airports, Arab Americans are often subject to heightened security screening, pre-boarding searches and interrogations, and are sometimes denied passage "based solely on the belief that ethnicity or national origin increases passengers' flight risk."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Chandrasekhar|first=Charu A.|date=|title=Flying while Brown: Federal Civil Rights Remedies to Post-9/11 Airline Racial Profiling of South Asians|url=https://heinonline.org/HOL/P?h=hein.journals/aslj10&amp;i=224|journal=Asian Law Journal|volume= 10| issue = 2|pages=215–252|via=HeinOnilne}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Originally, passenger profiling was introduced in the 1960s to identify potential hijackers that fit the "profile" of a person who is "likely to be a terrorist." However, this practice was discontinued in 1972 due to inefficiencies and was replaced by checkpoints and x-ray security. The Department Of Justice released a statement in 1997 claiming that automated passenger screenings would not have a "disparate impact on any group of passengers." The American-Arab Anti-Discrimination Committee (ADC) believes that "profiling, even under the best circumstances, provides an opportunity for the prejudices and stereotypes held by law enforcement and other officials to be expressed through discriminatory application of profiles. At worst, they are simply a recipe for bigoted behavior."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://heinonline.org/HOL/Page?collection=journals&amp;handle=hein.journals/jalc67&amp;id=1391&amp;men_tab=srchresults|title=Racial Profiling and Air Travel Security|last=|first=|date=|website=heinonline.org|access-date=2018-12-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Iranian Americans ===
{{See also|Anti-Iranian sentiment}}
[[File:Man holding sign during Iranian hostage crisis protest, 1979.jpg|thumb|A man holding a sign that reads "deport all Iranians" and "get the hell out of my country" during a protest of the [[Iran hostage crisis]] in Washington, D.C. in 1979.]]
The November 1979 [[Iranian hostage crisis]] of the U.S. embassy in [[Tehran]] precipitated a wave of anti-Iranian sentiment in the United States, directed both against the [[Iranian Revolution|new Islamic regime]] and Iranian nationals and immigrants. Even though such sentiments gradually declined after the release of the hostages at the start of 1981, they sometimes flare up. In response, some Iranian immigrants to the U.S. have distanced themselves from their nationality and instead identify primarily on the basis of their ethnic or religious affiliations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|first=Mehdi|last=Bozorgmehr|title=No solidarity: Iranians in the U.S|url=http://www.iranian.com/Opinion/2001/May/Iranians/index.html#3a|work=The Iranian|date=May 2, 2001|accessdate=2007-02-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Since the 1980s and especially since the 1990s, it has been argued, Hollywood's depiction of Iranians has gradually shown signs of vilifying Iranians.&lt;ref&gt;See detailed analysis in: ''The U.S. Media and the Middle East: Image and Perception''. Praeger, 1997; Greenwood, 1995.&lt;/ref&gt; Hollywood network productions such as ''[[24 (TV series)|24]]'',&lt;ref&gt;''[[Los Angeles Times]]'': [http://articles.latimes.com/2010/jun/27/entertainment/la-ca-iran-popculture-20100627 Essay: Iranians moving past negative depictions in pop culture]: "Iranians, left outside of the 9/11 conversation, began to leak fairly seamlessly into the best and worst of pop culture. In 2003, veteran Iranian actress Shohreh Aghadashloo starred in ''The House of Sand and Fog'', for which she became the first Iranian nominated for an Academy Award (although two years later the pendulum swung back when she played a member of a terrorist family on the hit TV show ''24'')." June 27, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[John Doe (TV series)|John Doe]]'', ''[[On Wings of Eagles]]'' (1986),&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite newspaper|last=O'Connor |first=John J. |authorlink=John J. O'Connor (journalist)|url=https://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE2DC163CF93BA25756C0A960948260 |title=Tv View; 'On Wings of Eagles' Plods To Superficial Heights |journal=The New York Times |date=May 18, 1986 |accessdate=2013-02-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Escape from Iran: The Canadian Caper]]'' (1981),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0082339/|title=Escape from Iran: The Canadian Caper (TV Movie 1981)|author=Richard Maurer (ram-30)|date=May 17, 1981|work=IMDb}}&lt;/ref&gt; and ''[[JAG (TV series)|JAG]]'' almost regularly host Persian speaking villains in their story line.

=== Indian Americans ===
{{Main|Indian Americans#Discrimination}}

[[Indian Americans]] have sometimes been mistaken in the United States for Arab or Muslim, and thus many of the same prejudices faced by Arab Americans have been experienced by Indian Americans also, regardless of actual religious or ethnic background.

In the 1980s, a gang known as the [[Dotbusters]] specifically targeted Indian Americans in [[Jersey City, New Jersey]] with violence and harassment.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Michel Marriott, Special to The New York Times |url=https://www.nytimes.com/1987/10/12/nyregion/in-jersey-city-indians-protest-violence.html?pagewanted=all |title=In Jersey City, Indians Protest Violence |location=Jersey City (Nj) |publisher=Nytimes.com |date=1987-10-12 |accessdate=2014-08-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; Studies of [[racial discrimination]], as well as [[stereotyping]] and [[scapegoating]] of Indian Americans have been conducted in recent years.&lt;ref name="Dhillon"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.kavitachhibber.com/main/main.jsp?id=legal-Jan2006|title=Kavita Chhibber|website=Kavitachhibber.com|accessdate=January 9, 2018|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180102072827/http://www.kavitachhibber.com/main/main.jsp?id=legal-Jan2006|archive-date=January 2, 2018|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; In particular, racial discrimination against Indian Americans in the workplace has been correlated with [[Indophobia]] due to the rise in [[outsourcing]]/[[offshoring]], whereby Indian Americans are blamed for US companies offshoring [[White-collar worker|white-collar]] labor to [[India]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.columbia.edu/~ap2231/ET/et80_July27-05.htm Indophobia: Facts versus Fiction], Arvind Panagariya, [[Columbia University]] archives of ''[[The Economic Times]]''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Yee"&gt;[http://modelminority.com/article705.html Worries about technical-job losses, discrimination] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080704175405/http://www.modelminority.com/article705.html |date=July 4, 2008 }}, by [[Amy Yee]], The Financial Times Ltd., 2004&lt;/ref&gt; According to the offices of the Congressional Caucus on India, many Indian Americans are severely concerned of a backlash, though nothing serious has taken place yet.&lt;ref name="Yee"/&gt; Due to various socio-cultural reasons, implicit racial discrimination against Indian Americans largely go unreported by the Indian American community.&lt;ref name="Dhillon"/&gt;

Numerous cases of religious stereotyping of [[Hinduism in the United States|American Hindus]] (mainly of Indian origin) have also been documented.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/reference/cshm/ohrc066.html |title=Center for the study of history and memory |publisher=Dlib.indiana.edu |date= |accessdate=2014-08-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Since the [[September 11, 2001 attacks]], there have been scattered incidents of Indian Americans becoming mistaken targets for [[hate crimes]]. In one example, a [[Sikh]], [[Balbir Singh Sodhi]], was murdered at a [[Phoenix, Arizona|Phoenix]] gas station in a [[hate crime]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Remembering Victims of Hate Crimes | publisher = Southern Poverty Law Center | accessdate = 2013-07-05 | url = http://www.splcenter.org/get-informed/intelligence-report/browse-all-issues/2002/spring/the-forgotten?page=0,6 }}&lt;/ref&gt; This happened after [[September 11 attacks|September 11]], and the murderer claimed that his [[turban]] made him think that the victim was a [[Middle-Eastern Americans|Middle Eastern American]]. In another example, a [[pizza]] deliverer was mugged and beaten in [[Massachusetts]] for "being [[Muslim]]" though the victim pleaded with the assailants that he was in fact a [[Hinduism|Hindu]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2002/11/25/national/main530749.shtml | work=CBS News | title=Hindu Beaten Because He's Muslim | date=2002-11-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; In December 2012, an Indian American in [[New York City]] was pushed from behind onto the tracks at the 40th Street-Lowery Street station in [[Sunnyside, Queens|Sunnyside]] and killed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url= https://www.nytimes.com/2012/12/29/nyregion/man-pushed-to-his-death-under-train-in-queens.html?_r=0|title= Woman Sought After 2nd Fatal Shove Onto Subway Tracks This Month|last1= Santora |first1=Marc|last2= Maslin Nir| first2=Sarah|date= December 28, 2012 |work=New York Times |accessdate=December 31, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The police arrested a woman, Erika Menendez, who admitted to the act and justified it, stating that she shoved him onto the tracks because she believed that he was "a Hindu or a Muslim" and she wanted to retaliate for the attacks on September 11, 2001.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url= https://www.nytimes.com/2013/01/01/nyregion/victim-of-fatal-subway-push-is-given-a-fond-farewell.html?_r=0|title= Subway Victim Recalled as Always Lending a Hand|last1= Lee|first1= Vivian|date= December 31, 2012 |work=New York Times|accessdate=December 31, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Consequences ==

=== Developmental ===
Using [[Psychometrics of racism|The Schedule of Racist Events]] (SRE), an 18-item self-report inventory that assesses the frequency of racist discrimination, Hope Landrine and Elizabeth A. Klonoff found that racist discrimination is rampant in the lives of African Americans and is strongly related to psychiatric symptoms.&lt;ref&gt;''The Schedule of Racist Events: A Measure of Racial Discrimination and a Study of Its Negative Physical and Mental Health Consequences'' Journal of Black Psychology, Vol. 22, No. 2, 144–168 (1996)&lt;/ref&gt; A study on racist events in the lives of African American women found that lifetime experiences of racism were positively related to lifetime history of both physical disease and frequency of recent common colds. These relationships were largely unaccounted for by other variables. Demographic variables such as income and education were not related to experiences of racism. The results suggest that racism can be detrimental to African American's well being.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Kwate NO, Valdimarsdottir HB, Guevarra JS, Bovbjerg DH |title=Experiences of racist events are associated with negative health consequences for African American women |journal=J Natl Med Assoc |volume=95 |issue=6 |pages=450–60 |date=June 2003 |pmid=12856911 |doi= |url= |pmc=2594553}}&lt;/ref&gt; The physiological stress caused by racism has been documented in studies by [[Claude Steele]], Joshua Aronson, and Steven Spencer on what they term "[[stereotype threat]]."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Blascovich J, Spencer SJ, Quinn D, Steele C |title=African Americans and high blood pressure: the role of stereotype threat |journal=Psychol Sci |volume=12 |issue=3 |pages=225–9 |date=May 2001 |pmid=11437305 |doi=10.1111/1467-9280.00340 |url=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Quite similarly, another example of the psychosocial consequences of discrimination have been observed in a study sampling Mexican-origin participants in Fresno, California. It was found that perceived discrimination is correlated with depressive symptoms, especially for those less acculturated in the United States, like Mexican immigrants and migrants.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Finch|first=Brian|title=Perceived Discrimination and Depression among Mexican-Origin Adults in California|journal=Journal of Health and Social Behavior|year=2000|volume=41|issue=3|pages=295–313|doi=10.2307/2676322|pmid=11011506|jstor=2676322}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Along the vein of somatic responses to discrimination, Kennedy et al. found that both measures of collective disrespect were strongly correlated with black mortality (r = 0.53 to 0.56), as well as with white mortality (r = 0.48 to 0.54). These data suggest that racism, measured as an ecologic characteristic, is associated with higher mortality in both blacks and whites.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Kennedy BP, Kawachi I, Lochner K, Jones C, Prothrow-Stith D |title=(Dis)respect and black mortality |journal=Ethn Dis |volume=7 |issue=3 |pages=207–14 |year=1997 |pmid=9467703 |doi= |url=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some researchers also suggest that racial segregation may lead to disparities in health and mortality. Thomas LaVeist (1989; 1993) tested the hypothesis that [[Racial segregation in the United States|segregation]] would aid in explaining race differences in infant mortality rates across cities. Analyzing 176 large and midsized cities, LaVeist found support for the hypothesis. Since LaVeist's studies, segregation has received increased attention as a determinant of racial disparities in mortality.{{citation needed|date=August 2017}} Studies have shown that mortality rates for male and female African Americans are lower in areas with lower levels of residential segregation. Mortality for male and female whites was not associated in either direction with residential segregation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Hart KD, Kunitz SJ, Sell RR, Mukamel DB |title=Metropolitan governance, residential segregation, and mortality among African Americans |journal=Am J Public Health |volume=88 |issue=3 |pages=434–8 |date=March 1998 |pmid=9518976 |pmc=1508338 |doi= 10.2105/AJPH.88.3.434}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Researchers Sharon A. Jackson, Roger T. Anderson, Norman J. Johnson and Paul D. Sorlie found that, after adjustment for family income, [[Mortality rate|mortality]] risk increased with increasing minority residential segregation among Blacks aged 25 to 44 years and non-Blacks aged 45 to 64 years. In most age/race/gender groups, the highest and lowest mortality risks occurred in the highest and lowest categories of residential segregation, respectively. These results suggest that minority residential segregation may influence mortality risk and underscore the traditional emphasis on the social underpinnings of disease and death.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Jackson SA, Anderson RT, Johnson NJ, Sorlie PD |title=The relation of residential segregation to all-cause mortality: a study in black and white |journal=Am J Public Health |volume=90 |issue=4 |pages=615–7 |date=April 2000 |pmid=10754978 |pmc=1446199 |doi= 10.2105/AJPH.90.4.615}}&lt;/ref&gt; Rates of heart disease among African Americans are associated with the segregation patterns in the neighborhoods where they live (Fang ''et al.'' 1998). Stephanie A. Bond Huie writes that neighborhoods affect health and mortality outcomes primarily in an indirect fashion through environmental factors such as smoking, diet, exercise, stress, and access to health insurance and medical providers.&lt;ref&gt;''[http://taylorandfrancis.metapress.com/(4mofmj45dowzx445b21cbw55)/app/home/contribution.asp?referrer=parent&amp;backto=issue,8,15;journal,30,40;linkingpublicationresults,1:102491,1 THE CONCEPT OF NEIGHBORHOOD IN HEALTH AND MORTALITY RESEARCH]{{dead link|date=January 2018 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}''&lt;/ref&gt; Moreover, segregation strongly influences premature mortality in the US.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Cooper RS, Kennelly JF, Durazo-Arvizu R, Oh HJ, Kaplan G, Lynch J |title=Relationship between premature mortality and socioeconomic factors in black and white populations of US metropolitan areas |journal=Public Health Rep |volume=116 |issue=5 |pages=464–73 |year=2001 |pmid=12042610 |pmc=1497360 |doi= 10.1016/S0033-3549(04)50074-2|url=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As early as 1866, the [[Civil Rights Act of 1866|Civil Rights Act]] provided a remedy for intentional race discrimination in employment by private employers and state and local public employers. The [[Civil Rights Act of 1871]] applies to public employment or employment involving state action prohibiting deprivation of rights secured by the federal constitution or federal laws through action under color of law. Title VII is the principal federal statute with regard to employment discrimination prohibiting unlawful employment discrimination by public and private employers, labor organizations, training programs and employment agencies based on race or color, religion, gender, and national origin. Title VII also prohibits retaliation against any person for opposing any practice forbidden by statute, or for making a charge, testifying, assisting, or participating in a proceeding under the statute. The [[Civil Rights Act of 1991]] expanded the damages available in Title VII cases and granted Title VII plaintiffs the right to a jury trial. Title VII also provides that race and color discrimination against every race and color is prohibited.

=== Societal ===

==== Schemas and stereotypes ====
[[File:1900sc Mammy Card Interracial.jpg|thumb|This racist [[postcard]] from the 1900s shows the casual denigration of black women. It states "I know you're not particular to a fault / Though I'm not sure you'll never be sued for assault / You're so fond of women that even a wench / Attracts your gross fancy despite her strong stench"]]

'''Media'''
{{See also|Stereotypes of African Americans|Stereotypes of East Asians in the Western world|Stereotypes of Native Americans}}
Popular culture (songs, theater) for European American audiences in the 19th century created and perpetuated negative stereotypes of African Americans. One key symbol of racism against African Americans was the use of [[blackface]]. Directly related to this was the institution of [[Blackface|minstrelsy]]. Other stereotypes of African Americans included the fat, dark-skinned "[[mammy archetype|mammy]]" and the irrational, hypersexual male "buck".

In recent years increasing numbers of African-American activists have asserted that [[rap music]] videos commonly utilize scantily clothed African-American performers posing as thugs or pimps. The [[NAACP]] and the [[National Congress of Black Women]] also have called for the reform of images on videos and on television. [[Julian Bond]] said that in a segregated society, people get their impressions of other groups from what they see in videos and what they hear in music.&lt;ref name="nytimes1"&gt;Felicia R. Lee, "[https://www.nytimes.com/2007/11/05/arts/05enou.html Protesting Demeaning Images in Media]" ''[[New York Times]]'' November 5, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Marissa Newhall, "[https://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2007/09/15/AR2007091501441.html Channeling Their Discontent, 500 Gather at Executive's D.C. Home to Protest Stereotypes]," ''[[Washington Post]]'', September 16, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.enoughisenoughcampaign.com/ |title=Enough is Enough! Campaign |publisher=Enough is Enough! Campaign |date=March 9, 2011 |accessdate=2013-02-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.whataboutourdaughters.com/ |title=What About Our Daughters? |publisher=Whataboutourdaughters.com |accessdate=2013-02-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:1899BalanceCartoon.jpg|thumb|left|In 1899 Uncle Sam balances his new possessions which are depicted as "savage" children. The figures are [[Puerto Rico]], Hawaii, [[Cuba]], [[Philippines]] and "Lad robes" (the [[Mariana Islands]]).]]
In a similar vein, activists protested against the BET show, ''Hot Ghetto Mess,'' which satirizes the culture of working-class African-Americans. The protests resulted in the change of the television show name to ''[[We Got to Do Better]].''&lt;ref name="nytimes1" /&gt;

It is understood that representations of minorities in the media have the ability to reinforce or change stereotypes. For example, in one study, a collection of white subjects were primed by a comedy skit either showing a stereotypical or neutral portrayal of African-American characters. Participants were then required to read a vignette describing an incident of sexual violence, with the alleged offender either white or black, and assign a rating for perceived guilt. For those shown the stereotypical African-American character, there was a significantly higher guilt rating for black alleged offender in the subsequent vignette, in comparison to the other conditions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Ford|first=Thomas|title=Effects of Stereotypical Television Portrayals of African-Americans on Person Perception|journal=Social Psychology Quarterly|year=1997|volume=60|issue=3|pages=266–275|doi=10.2307/2787086|jstor=2787086}}&lt;/ref&gt;

While schemas have an overt societal consequence, the strong development of them have lasting effect on recipients. Overall, it is found that strong in-group attitudes are correlated with academic and economic success. In a study analyzing the interaction of assimilation and racial-ethnic schemas for Hispanic youth found that strong schematic identities for Hispanic youth undermined academic achievement.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Altschul|first=Inna |author2=Daphna Oyserman |author3=Deborah Bybee|title=Racial-Ethnic Self-Schemas and Segmented Assimilation: Identity and the Academic Achievement of Hispanic Youth|journal=Social Psychology Quarterly|date=September 2008|volume=71|issue=3|pages=302–320 |doi=10.1177/019027250807100309|jstor=20141842}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Additional stereotypes attributed to minorities continue to influence societal interactions. For example, a 1993 Harvard Law Review article states that Asian-Americans are commonly viewed as submissive, as a combination of relative physical stature and Western comparisons of cultural attitudes. Furthermore, Asian-Americans are depicted as the model minority, unfair competitors, foreigners, and indistinguishable. These stereotypes can serve to dehumanize Asian-Americans and catalyze hostility and violence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Racial Violence against Asian Americans|journal=Harvard Law Review|year=1993|volume=106|issue=8|pages=1926–1943|jstor=1341790|doi=10.2307/1341790}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Formal discrimination ====
Formal discrimination against minorities has been present throughout American history. Leland T. Saito, Associate Professor of Sociology and American Studies &amp; Ethnicity at the [[University of Southern California]], writes, "Political rights have been circumscribed by race, class and gender since the founding of the United States, when the right to vote was restricted to white men of property. Throughout the history of the United States race has been used by whites – a category that has also shifted through time – for legitimizing and creating difference and social, economic and political exclusion."&lt;ref&gt;Leland T. Saito (1998). "Race and Politics: Asian Americans, Latinos, and Whites in a Los Angeles Suburb". p. 154. University of Illinois Press&lt;/ref&gt;

Within education, a survey of black students in sixteen majority white universities found that four of five African-Americans reported some form of racial discrimination. For example, in February 1988, the University of Michigan enforced a new anti discrimination code following the distribution of fliers saying blacks "don't belong in classrooms, they belong hanging from trees". Other forms of reported discrimination were refusal to sit next to black in lecture, ignored input in class settings, and informal segregation. While the penalties are imposed, the psychological consequences of formal discrimination can still manifest. Black students, for example, reported feelings of heightened isolation and suspicion. Furthermore, studies have shown that academic performance is stunted for black students with these feelings as a result of their campus race interactions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Wilkerson|first=Isabel|title=Campus Blacks Feel Racism's Nuances|url=https://www.nytimes.com/1988/04/17/us/campus-blacks-feel-racism-s-nuances.html?pagewanted=all&amp;src=pm|accessdate=November 5, 2013|work=The New York Times|date=April 17, 1988}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Minority-minority racism ====
{{Main|Interminority racism in the United States}}
Minority racism is sometimes considered controversial because of theories of [[power (sociology)|power]] in society. Some theories of racism insist that racism can only exist in the context of social power to impose it upon others.&lt;ref&gt;For example, Catherine A. Hansman, Leon Spencer, Dale Grant, Mary Jackson, "Beyond Diversity: Dismantling Barriers in Education," ''Journal of Instructional Psychology'', March 1999&lt;/ref&gt; Yet discrimination and racism between racially [[marginalized]] groups has been noted. For example, there has been ongoing violence between African American and [[Mexican American]] gangs, particularly in [[Southern California]].&lt;ref&gt;Andrew Blankstein And Joel Rubin. [http://articles.latimes.com/2008/jun/13/local/me-race13 L.A.'s top cops at odds: William Bratton, Lee Baca disagree on role of race in gang violence.] ''[[Los Angeles Times]]'', June 13, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.economist.com/world/na/displaystory.cfm?story_id=9587776 |title=Race relations &amp;#124; Where black and brown collide |publisher=Economist.com |date=August 2, 2007 |accessdate=2013-02-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2006/10/14/national/main2089618.shtml |title=Riot Breaks Out at Calif. High School, Melee Involving 500 People Erupts at Southern California School |publisher=Cbsnews.com |date=February 11, 2009 |accessdate=2013-02-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=5192595&amp;ft=1&amp;f=1001 |title=California Prisons on Alert After Weekend Violence |publisher=NPR |date=February 6, 2006 |accessdate=2013-02-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; There have been reports of racially motivated attacks against Mexican Americans who have moved into neighborhoods occupied mostly by African Americans, and vice versa.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite newspaper|author=Paul Harris |url=http://observer.guardian.co.uk/world/story/0,,2036580,00.html |title=A bloody conflict between Black and Hispanic gangs is spreading across Los Angeles |journal=The Guardian |date=March 18, 2007 |accessdate=2013-02-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.blackamericaweb.com/site.aspx/bawnews/stateof/hutchinson105 The Hutchinson Report: Thanks to Latino Gangs, There's a Zone in L.A. Where Blacks Risk Death if They Enter] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070513184220/http://www.blackamericaweb.com/site.aspx/bawnews/stateof/hutchinson105 |date=May 13, 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt; According to gang experts and law enforcement agents, a longstanding race war between the [[Mexican Mafia]] and the [[Black Guerilla Family]], a rival African American [[prison gang]], has generated such intense racial hatred among Mexican Mafia leaders, or shot callers, that they have issued a "green light" on all blacks. This amounts to a standing authorization for Latino gang members to prove their mettle by terrorizing or even murdering any blacks sighted in a neighborhood claimed by a gang loyal to the Mexican Mafia.{{dead link|date=November 2011}}&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.blackamericaweb.com/site.aspx/bawnews/stateof/hutchinson105] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20071011215616/http://www.blackamericaweb.com/site.aspx/bawnews/stateof/hutchinson105|date=October 11, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; There have been several significant riots in [[California prisons]] where Mexican American inmates and African Americans have targeted each other particularly, based on racial reasons.&lt;ref&gt;[http://jurist.law.pitt.edu/paperchase/2006/12/race-riot-put-down-at-california-state.php JURIST – Paper Chase: Race riot put down at California state prison] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100307234325/http://jurist.law.pitt.edu/paperchase/2006/12/race-riot-put-down-at-california-state.php |date=March 7, 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://newsmine.org/archive/security/incarceration/racial-segregation-continues-in-california-prisons.txt Racial segregation continues in California prisons] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110823060942/http://newsmine.org/archive/security/incarceration/racial-segregation-continues-in-california-prisons.txt |date=August 23, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

There has also been noted conflict between recent immigrant groups and their established ethnic counterparts within the United States. Rapid growth in [[Africans in the United States|African]] and [[Caribbean]] immigrants has come into conflict with American blacks. Interaction and cooperation between black immigrants and American blacks are, ironically, debatable. One can argue that racial discrimination and cooperation is not ordinarily based on color of skin but more on shared common, cultural experiences, and beliefs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.post-gazette.com/pg/06044/654613.stm |title=African immigrants face bias from blacks |publisher=Post-gazette.com |date=December 31, 1969 |accessdate=2013-02-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://abcnews.go.com/TheLaw/Story?id=5237459&amp;page=1 |title=Racism not always black and white |publisher=Abcnews.go.com |date=June 25, 2008 |accessdate=2013-02-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Interpersonal discrimination ====
In a manner that defines interpersonal discrimination in the United States, Darryl Brown of the Virginia Law Review states that while "our society has established a consensus against blatant, intentional racism and in decades since Brown v Board of Education has developed a sizeable set of legal remedies to address it", our legal system "ignores the possibility that 'race' is structural or interstitial, that it can be the root of injury even when not traceable to a specific intention or action"&lt;ref name=Brown&gt;{{cite journal|last=Brown|first=Darryl|title=Racism and Race Relations in the University|journal=Virginia Law Review|date=March 1990|volume=76|issue=2|pages=295–335|jstor=1073204|doi=10.2307/1073204|hdl=10288/8306|url=https://digitalarchive.wm.edu/xmlui/bitstream/10288/8306/1/BrownDarrylwm.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Interpersonal discrimination is defined by its subtlety. Unlike formal discrimination, interpersonal discrimination is often not an overt or deliberate act of racism. For example, in an incident regarding a racial remark from a professor at Virginia Law, a rift was created by conflicting definitions of racism. For the students that defended the professor's innocence, "racism was defined as an act of intentional maliciousness". Yet for African Americans, racism was broadened to a detrimental influence on "the substantive dynamics of the classroom". As an effect, it is argued that the "daily repetition of subtle racism and subordination in the classroom and on campus can ultimately be, for African Americans, more productive of stress, anxiety and alienation than even blatant racists acts". Moreover, the attention to these acts of discrimination diverts energy from academics, becoming a distraction that white students do not generally face.&lt;ref name=Brown /&gt;

=== Institutional racism===
[[Institutional racism]] is the theory that aspects of the structure, pervasive attitudes, and the established institutions in society disadvantage some racial groups, although not with an overtly discriminatory mechanism.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.eraseracismny.org/html/whatis/whatis.php What is Institutional and Structural Racism?] ERASE RACISM&lt;/ref&gt; There are several factors that play into institutional racism, including but not limited to: accumulated wealth/benefits from racial groups that have benefited from past discrimination, educational and occupational disadvantages faced by non-native English speakers in the United States, ingrained stereotypical images that still remain in the society (e.g. black men are likely to be criminals).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Bullock | first1 = III | last2 = Rodgers | first2 = Jr. | year = 1976 | title = Institutional Racism: Prerequisites, Freezing, and Mapping | url = | journal = Phylon | volume = 37 | issue = 3| pages = 212–223 | doi=10.2307/274450| jstor = 274450 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In his article, Peter Kaufman describes three instances in which institutional racism has contributed to current views of race.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title = Everyday Sociology Blog: Michael Brown, Ferguson, Missouri, and the Invisibility of Race|url = http://www.everydaysociologyblog.com/2014/08/michael-brown-ferguson-missouri-and-the-invisibility-of-race.html|website = www.everydaysociologyblog.com|accessdate = 2015-12-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; These are:
# The mis- and Missing Education of Race, in which he describes problems the educational system has in discussing "slavery, race, racism, and topics such as white privilege". He goes on to say that schools are still segregated based on class and race, which also contributes to race relations&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;
# Residential Racial Segregation. According to Kaufman, the reason that schools are still segregated is due to towns and cities being largely segregated still.
# Media Monsters. This describes the role in which the media has in the portrayal of race. Mass media tends to play on "depictions of racialized stereotypes in the mass media [which are] ubiquitous, and such caricaturized images shape our perceptions of various racial groups". An example of this is the stereotyping of Blacks as criminals.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;* {{cite book |first=Wilson |last=Head |title=A Life on the Edge: Experiences in Black and White in North America |publisher=University of Toronto Press |date=1995 |isbn=978-0-9680066-0-3 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Immigration ====
{{See also|Immigration to the United States}}

Access to United States [[citizenship]] was restricted by race, beginning with the [[Naturalization Act of 1790]] which excluded "non-whites" from citizenship.&lt;ref name="Schultz"/&gt;
Institutionalized prejudice existed against white followers of [[Roman Catholicism]] who immigrated from countries such as Ireland, Germany, Italy and France.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nhc.rtp.nc.us/tserve/nineteen/nkeyinfo/nromcath.htm Roman Catholics and Immigration in Nineteenth-Century America] by Julie Byrne, Dept. of Religion, Duke University, National Humanities Center&lt;/ref&gt; Other efforts include the 1882 [[Chinese Exclusion Act]] and the 1924 [[National Origins Act]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ourdocuments.gov/doc.php?flash=true&amp;doc=47 |title=Chinese Exclusion Act (1882) |publisher=Ourdocuments.gov |date=July 1, 1968 |accessdate=2013-02-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.historicaldocuments.com/ImmigrationActof1924.htm Immigration Act of 1924] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080210025205/http://www.historicaldocuments.com/ImmigrationActof1924.htm |date=February 10, 2008 }} HistoricalDocuments.com&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Immigration Act of 1924]] was aimed at further restricting the Southern and Eastern Europeans who had begun to enter the country in large numbers beginning in the 1890s. By limiting immigration of non-Northern Europeans, according to the U.S. Department of State Office of the Historian the purpose of the 1924 act was "to preserve the ideal of American homogeneity".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=https://history.state.gov/milestones/1921-1936/immigration-act | work=U.S. Department of State Office of the Historian | title=The Immigration Act of 1924 (The Johnson-Reed Act) | accessdate=2017-08-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Following the [[Immigration and Nationality Act of 1965]] that ended a racist preference for white immigrants dating to the 18th century,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=The Immigration Act of 1965 and the Creation of a Modern, Diverse America |url=https://www.huffpost.com/entry/the-immigration-act-of-19_b_8394570 |accessdate=August 4, 2019 |work=Huffington Post}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[white nationalism]] grew in the United States as the conservative movement developed in mainstream society.&lt;ref&gt;"Black Politics are in a Black Hole", ''Newsday'' (New York, January 14, 2005)&lt;/ref&gt; Political scientist [[Samuel P. Huntington]] argues that it developed as a reaction to a perceived decline in the essence of American identity as European, Anglo-Protestant and English-speaking.&lt;ref&gt;"Bush and Kerry Show Opposing Faces of Two Different Americas. ''Business Day'' (South Africa: October 21, 2004)&lt;/ref&gt;

In conjunction with immigration reform in the late 1980s (seen with the Immigration Reform and Control Act of 1986), there have been noted IRCA-related discriminatory behavior toward Hispanics within employment. As the measure made it unlawful to hire without authorization to work in the United States, avoidant treatment toward "foreign-appearing workers" increased to bypass the required record-keeping or risk of sanctions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Lowell|first=Lindsay|title=Unintended Consequences of Immigration Reform: Discrimination and HIspanic Employment|journal=Demography|date=November 1995|volume=32|issue=4|pages=617–628|doi=10.2307/2061678|jstor=2061678}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Use of the American racist model====
[[Adolf Hitler|Hitler]] and other [[Nazi Party|Nazis]] praised America's system of institutional racism and they also believed that it was the model which should be followed in their [[Reich]]. In particular, they believed that it was the model for the expansion of German territory into the territory of other nations and the elimination of their indigenous inhabitants, for the implementation of racist immigration laws which banned some races, and laws which denied full citizenship to blacks, which they also wanted to implement against Jews. Hitler's book ''[[Mein Kampf]]'' extolled America as the only contemporary example of a country with racist ("völkisch") citizenship statutes in the 1920s, and Nazi lawyers made use of the American models in crafting laws for [[Nazi Germany]].&lt;ref name="Whitman"/&gt; U.S. citizenship laws and [[Anti-miscegenation laws in the United States|anti-miscegenation laws]] directly inspired the two principal [[Nuremberg Laws]]—the Citizenship Law and the Blood Law.&lt;ref name="Whitman"&gt;{{cite book|last1=Whitman|first1=James Q.|title=Hitler's American Model: The United States and the Making of Nazi Race Law|date=2017|publisher=Princeton University Press|pages=37–47}}&lt;/ref&gt; Establishing a restrictive entry system for Germany, Hitler admiringly wrote: “The American Union categorically refuses the immigration of physically unhealthy elements, and simply excludes the immigration of certain races.”&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.timesofisrael.com/american-laws-against-coloreds-influenced-nazi-racial-planners/ "American laws against 'coloreds' influenced Nazi racial planners"]. ''Times of Israel''. Retrieved August 1, 2019&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Wealth ====
{{See also|Wealth inequality in the United States}}
Large racial differentials in wealth remain in the United States: between whites and African Americans, the gap is a factor of twenty.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|url=http://www.csmonitor.com/USA/2011/0726/Wealth-gap-widens-Whites-net-worth-is-20-times-that-of-blacks |title=Wealth gap widens: Whites' net worth is 20 times that of blacks |journal=Christian Science Monitor |date=July 26, 2011 |accessdate=2013-02-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; An analyst of the phenomenon, Thomas Shapiro, professor of law and social policy at Brandeis University argues, "The wealth gap is not just a story of merit and achievement, it's also a story of the historical legacy of race in the United States."&lt;ref&gt;"[http://www.nbcnews.com/id/15704759 Census report: Broad racial disparities persist]", November 14, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; Differentials applied to the [[Social Security (United States)|Social Security Act]] (which excluded agricultural workers, a sector that then included most black workers), rewards to military officers, and the educational benefits offered returning soldiers after [[World War II]]. Pre-existing disparities in wealth are exacerbated by tax policies that reward investment over waged income, subsidize mortgages, and subsidize private sector developers.&lt;ref&gt;George Lipsitz, "[https://www.jstor.org/stable/2713291 The Possessive Investment in Whiteness: Racialized Social Democracy and the "White" Problem in American Studies]," ''American Quarterly'', Vol. 47, No. 3. (September 1995), pp. 369–387.&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Health care ====
{{main|Race and health in the United States}}
There are major [[Race and health|racial differences in access to health care]] and in the quality of health care provided. A study published in the American Journal of Public Health estimated that: "over 886,000 deaths could have been prevented from 1991 to 2000 if African Americans had received the same care as whites". The key differences they cited were lack of insurance, inadequate [[health insurance|insurance]], poor service, and reluctance to seek care.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Woolf SH, Johnson RE, Fryer GE, Rust G, Satcher D |title=The health impact of resolving racial disparities: an analysis of US mortality data |journal=Am J Public Health |volume=94 |issue=12 |pages=2078–81 |date=December 2004 |pmid=15569956 |pmc=1448594 |doi= 10.2105/AJPH.94.12.2078}}&lt;/ref&gt; A history of government-sponsored experimentation, such as the notorious [[Tuskegee Syphilis Study]] has left a legacy of African American distrust of the medical system.&lt;ref&gt;"The History of Black 'Paranoia{{'"}}, ch. 3 of Alexander Cockburn and Jeffrey St. Clair, ''Whiteout: The CIA, Drugs, and the Press'', London: Verso, 1998.&lt;/ref&gt;

Inequalities in health care may also reflect a [[systemic bias]] in the way medical procedures and treatments are prescribed for different ethnic groups. A [[University of Edinburgh]] Professor of Public Health, Raj Bhopal, writes that the history of [[Scientific racism|racism in science]] and medicine shows that people and institutions behave according to the ethos of their times and warns of dangers to avoid in the future.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Bhopal R |title=Spectre of racism in health and health care: lessons from history and the United States |journal=BMJ |volume=316 |issue=7149 |pages=1970–3 |date=June 1998 |pmid=9641943 |pmc=1113412 |doi= 10.1136/bmj.316.7149.1970}}&lt;/ref&gt; A [[Harvard]] Professor of Social Epidemiology contended that much modern research supported the assumptions needed to justify racism. Racism she writes underlies unexplained inequities in health care, including treatment for heart disease,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Oberman A, Cutter G |title=Issues in the natural history and treatment of coronary heart disease in black populations: surgical treatment |journal=Am. Heart J. |volume=108 |issue=3 Pt 2 |pages=688–94 |date=September 1984 |pmid=6332513 |doi= 10.1016/0002-8703(84)90656-2|url=}}&lt;/ref&gt; renal failure,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Kjellstrand CM |title=Age, sex, and race inequality in renal transplantation |journal=Arch. Intern. Med. |volume=148 |issue=6 |pages=1305–9 |date=June 1988 |pmid=3288159 |doi= 10.1001/archinte.1988.00380060069016 }}&lt;/ref&gt; bladder cancer,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Mayer WJ, McWhorter WP |title=Black/white differences in non-treatment of bladder cancer patients and implications for survival |journal=Am J Public Health |volume=79 |issue=6 |pages=772–5 |date=June 1989 |pmid=2729474 |pmc=1349641 |doi= 10.2105/AJPH.79.6.772}}&lt;/ref&gt; and pneumonia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Yergan J, Flood AB, LoGerfo JP, Diehr P |title=Relationship between patient race and the intensity of hospital services |journal=Med Care |volume=25 |issue=7 |pages=592–603 |date=July 1987 |pmid=3695664 |doi= 10.1097/00005650-198707000-00003|url=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bhopal writes that these inequalities have been documented in various studies and that there are consistent findings that black Americans receive less health care than white Americans—particularly where this involves expensive new technology.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Black-white disparities in health care |journal=JAMA |volume=263 |issue=17 |pages=2344–6 |date=May 1990 |doi=10.1001/jama.263.17.2344 |pmid=2182918 |author1=Council on Ethical Judicial Affairs }}&lt;/ref&gt; The University of Michigan Health study found in 2010 that black patients in pain clinics received 50% of the amount of drugs that other patients who were white received.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.thoughtco.com/racism-in-health-care-still-a-problem-2834530|title=4 Ways Racism in Health Care Is Still a Problem Today|work=ThoughtCo|access-date=2018-05-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; Black pain in medicine links to the racial disparities between pain management and racial bias on behalf of the health professional. In 2011, Vermont organizers took a proactive stand against racism in their communities to defeat the biopolitical struggles faced on a daily basis. The first and only universal health care law was passed in the state.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://racialequity.org/docs/CIF5Timeline.pdf|title=Timeline of Race, Racism, Resistance and Philanthropy 1992-2014|last=Saloman|first=Larry|date=June 2014|website=Racial Equity|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Politics ====
It is argued that [[Dog-whistle politics|racial coding]] of concepts like crime and welfare has been used to strategically influence public political views. Racial coding is implicit; it incorporates racially primed language or imagery to allude to racial attitudes and thinking. For example, in the context of domestic policy, it is argued that Ronald Reagan implied linkages between concepts like "special interests" and "big government" with ill-perceived minority groups in the 1980s, using the conditioned negativity toward the minority groups to discredit certain policies and programs during campaigns. In a study analyzing how political ads prime attitudes, Valentino compares the voting responses of participants after being exposed to narration of a George W. Bush advertisement paired with three different types of visuals with different embedded racial cues to create three conditions: neutral, race comparison, and undeserving blacks. For example, as the narrator states "Democrats want to spend your tax dollars on wasteful government programs", the video shows an image of a black woman and child in an office setting. Valentino found that the undeserving blacks condition produced the largest primed effect in racialized policies, like opposition to affirmative action and welfare spending.&lt;ref name=Valentino&gt;{{cite journal|authorlink=Nicholas Valentino|last=Valentino|first=Nicholas|title=Cues that Matter: How Political Ads Prime Racial Attitudes during Campaigns|journal=The American Political Science Review|date=March 2002|volume=96|issue=1|pages=75–90|doi=10.1017/s0003055402004240|jstor=3117811}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Ian Haney López]], Professor of Law at the [[University of California, Berkeley]], refers to this phenomenon as [[dog-whistle politics]], which has pushed, he argues, middle class white Americans to vote against their economic self-interest in order to punish "undeserving minorities" who, they believe, are receiving too much public assistance at their expense. According to López, conservative middle-class whites, convinced that minorities are the enemy by powerful economic interests, supported politicians who promised to curb illegal immigration and crack down on crime, but inadvertently they also voted for policies that favor the extremely rich, such as slashing taxes for top income brackets, giving corporations more regulatory control over industry and financial markets, [[Union busting|busting unions]], cutting pensions for future public employees, reducing funding for public schools, and retrenching the social welfare state. He argues that these same voters cannot link rising inequality which has impacted their lives to the policy agendas they support, which resulted in a massive transfer of wealth to the top 1% of the population since the 1980s.&lt;ref&gt;[http://billmoyers.com/episode/ian-haney-lopez-on-the-dog-whistle-politics-of-race/ Full Show: Ian Haney López on the Dog Whistle Politics of Race, Part I]. ''[[Moyers &amp; Company]]'', February 28, 2014. See also: [[Ian Haney López]]. ''[https://global.oup.com/academic/product/dog-whistle-politics-9780199964277?cc=us&amp;lang=en&amp; Dog Whistle Politics: How Coded Racial Appeals Have Reinvented Racism and Wrecked the Middle Class] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20141218104049/https://global.oup.com/academic/product/dog-whistle-politics-9780199964277?cc=us&amp;lang=en&amp; |date=December 18, 2014 }}''. [[Oxford University Press]], 2014. {{ISBN|0-19-996427-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Justice system ====
{{Main|Race and crime in the United States}}
Racial disparities have been noted in all levels of the U.S. justice system. According to 2009 congressional testimony from Marc Mauer; while African Americans comprise 13% of the US population and 14% of monthly drug users they are 37% of the people arrested for drug offenses; as well as 56% of the people in state prisons for drug offenses. The U.S. Sentencing Commission reported in March 2010 that in the federal system black offenders receive sentences that are 10% longer than white offenders for the same crimes. A July 2009 report by the Sentencing Project found that two-thirds of the people in the U.S. with life sentences are non-white.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.huffpost.com/entry/fourteen-examples-of-raci_b_658947|title=Fourteen Examples of Racism in Criminal Justice System|author=Bill Quigley|date=July 26, 2010|website=Huffington Post}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to a new report, African-Americans are three times as likely to be killed by police as white Americans.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://policeviolencereport.org|title=2017 Police Violence Report|website=policeviolencereport.org|access-date=2018-05-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Contemporary issues ==

=== Hate crimes ===
{{Main|Hate crime}}
{{See also|Mass racial violence in the United States|Mass shootings in the United States#Contributing factors}}

In the United States, most crimes that target victims on the basis of their race or ethnicity are considered [[hate crimes]]. (For federal law purposes, crimes targeting Hispanics because of their identity are considered hate crimes based on ethnicity.) Leading forms of bias cited in the FBI's Uniform Crime Reporting (UCR) Program, based on law enforcement agency filings are: anti-black, anti-Jewish, anti-white, anti-homosexual, and anti-Hispanic bias in that order in both 2004 and 2005.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.fbi.gov/ucr/hc2004/openpage.htm Hate Crime Statistics, 2004]. [https://www.fbi.gov/ucr/hc2005/index.html Hate Crime Statistics, 2005].&lt;/ref&gt; According to the Bureau of Justice Statistics, whites, blacks, and Hispanics had similar rates of violent hate crime victimization between 2007 and 2011.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Hate Crime Victimization, 2003–2011 |url=http://www.bjs.gov/content/pub/pdf/hcv0311.pdf |publisher=Bureau of Justice Statistics |accessdate=August 30, 2014 |url-status=unfit |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150907020823/http://www.bjs.gov/content/pub/pdf/hcv0311.pdf |archivedate=September 7, 2015 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://bjs.ojp.usdoj.gov/content/pub/pdf/hcrvp.pdf Hate Crime Reported by Victims and Police] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130227040413/http://bjs.ojp.usdoj.gov/content/pub/pdf/hcrvp.pdf |date=February 27, 2013 }}, Bureau of Justice Statistics Special Report, November 2005, NCJ 209911.&lt;/ref&gt; However, from 2011 to 2012, violent hate crimes against Hispanic people increased by 300%.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=https://www.ncjrs.gov/spotlight/hate_crimes/facts.html | title=Highlights from Hate Crime Victimization, 2004–2012 – Statistical Tables | publisher=Bureau of Justice Statistics | accessdate=June 20, 2016 | archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20161216124400/https://www.ncjrs.gov/spotlight/Hate_Crimes/facts.html | archive-date=December 16, 2016 | url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; When considering all hate crimes, and not just violent ones, African Americans are far more likely to be victims than other racial groups.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=https://www.fbi.gov/about-us/cjis/ucr/hate-crime/2010/narratives/hate-crime-2010-incidents-and-offenses | title=FBI – Incidents and Offenses | publisher=Criminal Justice Information Services | accessdate=June 20, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=https://www.pbs.org/newshour/bb/fbi-blacks-often-targeted-hate-crimes/ | title=FBI: Blacks most often targeted in hate crimes | publisher=PBS | date=June 20, 2015 | accessdate=June 20, 2016 | author=Sreenivasan, Hari}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[New Century Foundation]], a [[White nationalism|white nationalist]] organization founded by [[Jared Taylor]], argues that blacks are more likely to commit hate crimes than whites, and it also argues that FBI figures inflate the number of hate crimes committed by whites by counting Hispanics as "white".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nc-f.org/colorcrime1999.htm The Color of Crime], 1999.&lt;/ref&gt; Other analysts are sharply critical of the NCF's findings, referring to the mainstream criminological view that "Racial and ethnic data must be treated with caution. Existing research on crime has generally shown that racial or ethnic identity is not predictive of criminal behavior with data which has been controlled for social and economic factors."&lt;ref&gt;Preface to Minnesota's official crime data reports, quoted in Southern Poverty Law Center, [http://www.splcenter.org/intel/intelreport/article.jsp?aid=255 Coloring Crime] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20141113123038/http://www.splcenter.org/intel/intelreport/article.jsp?aid=255 |date=November 13, 2014 }}.&lt;/ref&gt; NCF's methodology and statistics are further sharply criticized as flawed and deceptive by anti-racist activists Tim Wise and the Southern Poverty Law Center.&lt;ref&gt;Tim Wise, "[http://www.lipmagazine.org/~timwise/colorofdeception.html The Color of Deception: Race, Crime and Sloppy Social Science]," 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Southern Poverty Law Center, [http://www.splcenter.org/intel/intelreport/article.jsp?aid=255 Coloring Crime] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20141113123038/http://www.splcenter.org/intel/intelreport/article.jsp?aid=255 |date=November 13, 2014 }}.&lt;/ref&gt;

The first post-Jim Crow era hate crime to make sensational media attention was the [[murder of Vincent Chin]], an Asian American of Chinese descent in 1982. He was attacked by two white assailants who were recently laid off from a Detroit area auto factory job and blamed the Japanese for their individual unemployment. Chin was not of Japanese descent, but the assailants testified in the criminal court case that he "looked like a Jap", an ethnic slur that is used to describe Japanese and other Asians, and that they were angry enough to beat him to death.

=== Hateful views ===
Continuing [[antisemitism in the United States]] has remained an issue as the 2011 ''Survey of American Attitudes Toward Jews in America'', released by the [[Anti-Defamation League]] (ADL), has found that the recent [[Late-2000s recession|world economic recession]] increased some antisemitic viewpoints among Americans. Most people express [[Philo-Semitism|pro-Jewish sentiments]], with 64% of those surveyed agreeing that Jews have contributed much to U.S. social culture. Yet the polling found that 19% of Americans answered "probably true" to the [[antisemitic canard]] that "Jews have too much control/influence on Wall Street" while 15% concurred with the related statement that Jews seem "more willing to use shady practices" in business. Reflecting on the lingering antisemitism of about one in five Americans, [[Abraham H. Foxman]], ADL national director, has argued, "It is disturbing that with all of the strides we have made in becoming a more tolerant society, anti-Semitic beliefs continue to hold a vice-grip on a small but not insubstantial segment of the American public."&lt;ref name=adl-poll&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.jpost.com/Jewish-World/Jewish-News/ADL-poll-Anti-Semitic-attitudes-on-rise-in-USA|title=ADL poll: Anti-Semitic attitudes on rise in USA|publisher=[[The Jerusalem Post]]|date=November 3, 2011|accessdate=December 20, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

An [[ABC News]] report in 2007 recounted that past ABC polls across several years have tended to find that "six percent have self-reported prejudice against Jews, 27 percent against Muslims, 25 percent against Arabs," and "one in 10 concedes harboring at least some such feelings" against [[Hispanic and Latino Americans|Hispanic Americans]]. The report also remarked that a full 34% of Americans reported "some racist feelings" in general as a self-description.&lt;ref name=abc&gt;{{cite news|url=http://abcnews.go.com/images/US/1048a1Hispanics.pdf|title=Aquí Se Habla Español – and Two-Thirds Don't Mind|publisher=[[ABC News]]|date=October 8, 2007|accessdate=December 20, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; An [[Associated Press]] and [[Yahoo News]] survey of 2,227 adult Americans in 2008 found that 10% of white respondents stated that "a lot" of discrimination against African-Americans exists while 45% answered "some" compared to 57% of black respondents answering that "a lot" exists. In the same poll, more whites applied positive attributes to black Americans than negative ones, with blacks describing whites even more highly, but a significant minority of whites still called their fellow Americans "irresponsible", "lazy", or other such things.&lt;ref name=babington&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.foxnews.com/wires/2008Sep22/0,4670,APYahooPollRaceinAmerica,00.html |title=Poll: Views still differ sharply by race |first=Charles |last=Babington |publisher=[[Fox News Channel]] |date=September 22, 2008 |accessdate=January 16, 2010 |quote=[A] new Associated Press-Yahoo News poll, conducted with Stanford University, shows&amp;nbsp;... that a substantial portion of white Americans still harbor negative feelings toward blacks.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2008, Stanford University political scientist Paul Sniderman remarked that, in the modern U.S., racism and prejudices are "a deep challenge, and it's one that Americans in general, and for that matter, political scientists, just haven't been ready to acknowledge fully."&lt;ref name=babington /&gt;

In 2017, citizens gathered in the college community of [[Charlottesville]], Virginia to attend the [[Unite the Right rally]]. One woman was killed and dozens of other people were injured when a white supremacist drove his car into a group of counter-protesters.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.cnn.com/2017/08/12/us/charlottesville-car-crash-suspect-idd/index.html |title=Charlottesville car crash suspect ID'd as 20-year-old Ohio man|author=Chuck Johnston|publisher=CNN|url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20170813011757/http://www.cnn.com/2017/08/12/us/charlottesville-car-crash-suspect-idd/index.html|archivedate=August 13, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Vice President [[Mike Pence]] condemned the violence stating, "We have no tolerance for hate and violence from white supremacists, neo-Nazis or the KKK. These dangerous fringe groups have no place in American public life and in the American debate and we condemn them in the strongest possible terms."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.cnn.com/2017/08/13/us/charlottesville-white-nationalist-rally-car-crash/index.html|title=Charlottesville white nationalist rally: What we know|last=CNN|first=Holly Yan, Devon M. Sayers and Steve Almasy|work=CNN|access-date=2017-12-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Alleviation ==
There is a wide plethora of societal and political suggestions to alleviate the effects of continued discrimination in the United States. For example, within universities, it has been suggested that a type of committee could respond to non-sanctionable behavior.&lt;ref name=Brown /&gt;

It is also argued that there is a need for "white students and faculty to reformulate white-awareness toward a more secure identity that is not threatened by black cultural institutions and that can recognize the racial non-neutrality of the institutions whites dominate" (Brown, 334). Paired with this effort, Brown encourages the increase in minority faculty members, so the embedded white normative experience begins to fragment.&lt;ref name=Brown /&gt;

Within media, it is found that racial cues prime racial stereotypic thought. Thus, it is argued that "stereotype inconsistent cues might lead to more intentioned thought, thereby suppressing racial priming effects."&lt;ref name=Valentino /&gt; Social psychologists, such as [[Jennifer Eberhardt]], have done work that indicates such priming effects subconsciously help determine attitudes and behavior toward individuals regardless of intentions. These results have been incorporated into training, for example, in some police departments.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Scott |first1=Sam |title=A Hard Look at How We See Race |journal=[[Skeptical Inquirer]] |date=2018 |volume=42 |issue=1 |pages=37–41 |url=https://www.csicop.org/si/show/a_hard_look_at_how_we_see_race |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180623180420/https://www.csicop.org/si/show/a_hard_look_at_how_we_see_race |url-status=dead |archive-date=2018-06-23 |accessdate=23 June 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

It has been argued that more evidence-based guidance from psychologists and sociologists is needed to learn what is effective in alleviating racism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Radford |first1=Benjamin |authorlink=Benjamin Radford|title=Critical Thinking Approaches to Confronting Racism |journal=[[Skeptical Inquirer]] |date=2018 |volume=42 |issue=1 |page=31 |url=https://www.csicop.org/si/show/critical_thinking_approaches_to_confronting_racism |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180622191042/https://www.csicop.org/si/show/critical_thinking_approaches_to_confronting_racism |url-status=dead |archive-date=2018-06-22 |accessdate=23 June 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; Such evidence-based approaches can reveal, for example, the many psychological biases to which humans are subject, such as [[In-group favoritism|ingroup bias]] and the [[fundamental attribution error]], which can underlie racist attitudes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Foster |first1=Craig |last2=Samuels |first2=Steven|title=Psychology, Skepticism, and Confronting Racism |journal=[[Skeptical Inquirer]] |date=2018 |volume=42 |issue=1 |pages=32–33 |url=https://www.csicop.org/si/show/psychology_skepticism_and_confronting_racism |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180623185156/https://www.csicop.org/si/show/psychology_skepticism_and_confronting_racism |url-status=dead |archive-date=2018-06-23 |accessdate=23 June 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Psychologist [[Stuart Vyse]] has argued that argument, ideas, and facts will not mend divisions but that there is evidence, such as that provided by the [[Realistic conflict theory#Robbers cave study|Robbers Cave Experiment]], that seeking shared goals can help alleviate racism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Vyse |first1=Stuart|authorlink=Stuart Vyse |title=Combating Racism through Shared Goals |journal=[[Skeptical Inquirer]] |date=2018 |volume=42 |issue=1 |pages=34–35 |url=https://www.csicop.org/si/show/combating_racism_through_shared_goals |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180623182447/https://www.csicop.org/si/show/combating_racism_through_shared_goals |url-status=dead |archive-date=2018-06-23 |accessdate=23 June 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
{{Portal|United States}}
{{columns-list|colwidth=22em|
{{wikiquote}}
* [[Affirmative action in the United States]]
* [[Anti-Americanism]]
* [[:Category:Anti-black racism in the United States]]
* [[Anti-French sentiment in the United States]]
* [[Anti-Italianism in the United States]]
* [[Antisemitism in the United States]]
* [[Black Lives Matter]]
* [[Constitutional colorblindness]]
* [[Environmental racism#United States|Environmental racism in the United States]]
* [[Eugenics in the United States]]
* [[Illegal immigration to the United States]]
* [[List of race riots in the United States]]
* [[Native American mascot controversy]]
* [[Nativism in the United States]]
* [[Post-racial America]]
* [[Paris Peace Conference, 1919#Japanese approach|Racial equality proposal]]
* [[Racial profiling in the United States]]
* [[Racism by country]]
* [[Racism in early American film]]
** [[Racism in horror films]]
* [[Racism in United States politics]]
* [[Reverse discrimination]]
* [[Scientific racism in the United States]]
* [[U.S. Commission on Civil Rights]]
* [[White privilege in the United States]]
}}

== Notes ==
{{NoteFoot}}

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
* {{cite article
|title=The Color of Injustice
|first=Kelefa
|last=Sanneh
|author-link=Kelefa Sanneh
|magazine=[[The New Yorker]]
|date=August 19, 2019
|pages=18–22}}
* {{cite news
|work=[[The Guardian]]
|title='White supremacy' is really about white degeneracy
|first=Keith
|last=Kahn-Harris
|authorlink=Keith Kahn-Harris
|date=28 Nov 2018
|url = https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2018/nov/28/white-supremacy-degeneracy-far-right-populists
}}
* {{cite news
|authorlink=Alex Ross (music critic)
|first=Alex
|last=Ross
|url=https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2018/04/30/how-american-racism-influenced-hitler
|title=The Hitler Vortex: How American Racism Influenced Nazi Thought
|magazine=[[The New Yorker]]
|date=30 April 2018
|pages=66–73
}}

{{-}}
{{Americas topic|Racism in}}
{{Life in the United States}}
{{Demographics of the United States}}
{{United States topics}}
{{Racism topics|state=collapsed}}

[[Category:Racism in the United States| ]]
[[Category:Anti-black racism in the United States|*]]
[[Category:Anti-white racism in the United States|*]]
[[Category:Racism by country]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>