<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20121106012750|521601017" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="2235517" pageid="2235517" ns="0" title="Audism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2012-11-10T08:07:41Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Distinguish|Autism}}
{{POV|date=April 2009}}
{{Discrimination sidebar}}
'''Audism''' describes the mentality that to be able to hear and to speak is necessarily better and leads to a higher quality of life.  On this basis, different forms of discriminating behavior against [[deaf]] and [[hard of hearing]] people may arise {{Citation needed|date=February 2012}}. Audism can manifest in different areas of life, done mostly by hearing people. It can also occur within the [[Deaf Community]] as some deaf or hard of hearing person attempts to shares the attitude of being hearing is better. It is this mentality that led [[Tom L. Humphries]] to coin the term in his doctoral dissertation in 1975.&lt;ref&gt;Capital D Magazine, Vol. 1, Iss. 1&lt;/ref&gt; He defined it as the attitude that people who hear and speak (or hear and speak better) or have excellent English skills, are superior to others. The definition has since expanded to include discriminating behaviors{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}}. Examples of audism include; parents refusing to use sign language in the home and forcing their deaf or hard of hearing child to lipread and use speech, hearing people who know at least some sign language but refusing to use it and instead speaking loudly because the deaf person "can hear and speak to some degree," focusing on hearing aids and other methods to "fix" a deaf person and make them more hearing/oral, not using sign language in the presence of a deaf person, excluding a deaf person from an activity because they "can't hear." 

==Types of Audism==

===Physical Audism===
One common form of physical audism occurs when a given person with hearing loss is judged as incapable of a given behavior, occupation, skill, ability, or achievement due solely to that hearing loss, whether or not there is evidence of that incapability, and usually without the person who engages in such discrimination entertaining the possibility of change on the part of the victim{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}}. This form of audism is a reflection of a widely-held naturalistic belief by people who can hear in their own superiority{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}}.  Audism is partially responsible for the high unemployment rate of the deaf. &lt;ref&gt;http://www.netsignnews.com/Opinion_-_Discussion/Unemployment_Rates_In_The_Deaf_Community.php&lt;/ref&gt;  While it is technically correct to say that some forms of employment or activity utilize sound, alternatives can usually be found and are sometimes preferable to their auditory counterparts{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}}, as the prevalence of text messaging despite the existence of telephones would seem to demonstrate. While opponents of such discrimination argue that deaf people can do anything that hearing people can do except hear,{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}} they recognize that there are limitations for certain kinds of employment in which deafness could plausibly carry an increased safety risk{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}} such as service in the army or employment as a commercial pilot (although technology already exists and is used which depends on text for communication, and armies have used signs for communication and continue to do so to this day.) Aside from such examples, deaf people and their proponents are capable of excelling in a wide range of settings and deserve [[equal opportunity]]. This is true amongst political conservatives{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}} as well as progressives and liberals{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}}; noted conservative&lt;ref name="ea"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://198.181.165.52/article?assetid=0068080-00&amp;templatename=/article/article.html|title=Bush, George Herbert Walker|accessdate=March 29, 2008|publisher=Scholastic Library Publishing, Inc|archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080615195838/http://198.181.165.52/article?assetid=0068080-00&amp;templatename=/article/article.html |archivedate = June 15, 2008|deadurl=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[George Herbert Walker Bush]], for example, was instrumental in the development of the Americans with Disabilities Act, which attempts to provide for the alterations which makes such employment possible. This form of audism can also include exclusion of Deaf people or the disparagement of their ideas{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}}. A famous historical example is a criticism of the socialist ideals of [[Helen Keller]] by the Brooklyn Eagle, which implied that her ideas were of less value and should be taken less seriously than those of someone who could hear. (Note that Keller did not identify as culturally Deaf.){{Citation needed|date=February 2012}}

===Linguistic audism===

A less common form of audism, but one which is felt deeply by the American culturally Deaf community, is discrimination against those who use sign languages such as [[American Sign Language]] or [[British Sign Language]]{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}}. This can occur by banning use of these languages (several schools engaged in such prohibition in America in the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries, and some continue to do so.&lt;ref&gt;[http://abcnews.go.com/US/story?id=93532&amp;page=1#.T2JNh3nNnOM Bryan Robinson, Sign Language Ban Imposed on N.J. Girl] ''ABC News'' 18 April 2010 accessed 15 March 2012&lt;/ref&gt;) It can also occur by criticism and disparagement of the languages, or persistent denials that they are languages at all, despite ample scientific proof{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}}. From the eighteenth century, and some say before, great controversy has raged over the inclusion of such languages in education.{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}}

===Cultural audism===

A third form of audism is practiced against the Deaf person as a cultural entity{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}}. This can occur, for example, by criticism of aspects of Deaf peoples' cultures or by criticism against the right of Deaf people to have a culture as a whole. More subtle examples include the exclusion of Deaf people from representation in history{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}}, or their minimization and erasure as primal or secondary causes in history, movements, and other important aspects of national identity{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}}. Since being deaf is essentially to have an invisible difference, this is sometimes inadvertent rather than intentional. 

Yet another form of audism is scientific- or medically-based and propagates a set of stereotypes to an entire class of people{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}}. Similar forms of discrimination have been experienced by racial groups, for example, who often ascribe demeaning physical characteristics to each other, depending on who is in the majority. Popular examples include that of the forced sterilization of deaf and hard of hearing adults by the Nazi regime in Germany in the 1930s and 1940s; similar eugenics-driven movements have been seen in other countries around the world. 

===Internalized/dysconscious audism===

Additionally, Deaf people can practice forms of discrimination against members of their own community, based on what they believe is "right" behavior, use of language, or social association. Dr. Genie Gertz explored examples of such audism in American society in her published dissertation.&lt;ref&gt;Dysconscious Audism: A Theoretical Proposal in Open Your Eyes: Deaf Studies Talking&lt;/ref&gt; 

Audism can also occur between groups of deaf people, with some who choose not to use a sign language and not to identify with [[Deaf culture]] considering themselves to be 'better' than those who do, or vice versa. This is a type of dysconscious audism.

All these variations of audism, and many which have gone unmentioned, have their echoes in gender, racial, religious, cultural, social, and sexual discrimination.

==Surdophobia==
A term coined by Gardy van Gils, a Dutch social worker, now a Deaf Studies lecturer at [[Hogeschool Utrecht]]. It is used to describe a condition of fear towards deaf people and their culture. While Audism is more a specific condition, Surdophobia is a condition that will trigger the state of fear, known or unknown, in the person.{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}}

==Ideology==
As an ideology, audism has existed for many centuries no matter which definition is being used, although the more recent recognition of the Deaf community as a discrete language-using culture has afforded many more such examples. Audism is often seen either as a subset of racism or eugenics, and has been tied to [[cultural colonialism]] by Dr. [[Paddy Ladd]].
&lt;ref&gt;Understanding Deaf Culture: In Search of Deafhood 2008&lt;/ref&gt; Over time, however, audism has been seen as reflecting the attitudes cultures maintain about Deaf people, and examples are thus seen as existing primarily within a medical paradigm, cultural paradigm, and edu/linguistic paradigm, and much of the discourse about audism focuses on these three areas. In recent decades, with the proliferation of easily accessible communication technology, the discourse has expanded to focus on any area which involves deaf or Deaf people. Harlan Lane to some extent examines the development of Deaf-based educational principles in his history of Franco-American Deaf relations and educational philosophy.&lt;ref&gt;When The Mind Hears. Lane, 1980&lt;/ref&gt;

==Ethnic conflicts==

Much conflict exists around the concepts defined by the term audism,{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}} most often stemming from lack of clarity in use of the term - as in many other cultural or sociological debates. The term is sometimes used to describe typically xenophobic behaviors,{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}} for example. One of the earliest forms of audist ethnic conflict is found in the classics and in early Christian writings. Plato, for example, mentions users of a sign language, but he and Aristotle were in near-perfect agreement: without the ability to speak, Deaf people could be little more than barbarians {{Citation needed|date=January 2012}} . Similarly, writers such as St. Augustine propounded the notion that deafness, much as white supremacist conceptions of the nature of black skin, was a hereditary "curse" from God.{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}} Such thinking probably lay behind most early laws{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}} preventing Deaf people from owning property; Deaf people were considered either unintelligent or cursed, despite evidence to the contrary {{Citation needed|date=January 2012}} . It also contributed to conditions persisting until the early 15th century providing for the Church to prevent Deaf people joining, on the grounds that their inability to speak was both earned and a sign that they could not be saved {{Citation needed|date=January 2012}} . Such ideas additionally also provided for acceptable use of and mistreatment of Deaf peoples throughout the Middle Ages {{Citation needed|date=January 2012}} . Startling parallels exist in Church and state views of Black people and Native Americans at the time {{Citation needed|date=January 2012}}  (several prominent writers argued that such people had no souls. It is debatable whether the justification permits the treatment or whether the treatment required the justification.)

Such conceptions were not uniquely European. Many African cultures saw the deaf individual as cursed and were against the use of sign languages {{Citation needed|date=January 2012}} . Some insisted on the death of such individuals {{Citation needed|date=January 2012}} . (In contrast, many native American cultures integrated the use of sign languages with their societies, and others had specific roles for Deaf or disabled peoples within their society. {{Citation needed|date=January 2012}} )

Repeatedly, writers such as Ponce De Leon and Girolamo Cardano used personal experiences with Deaf individuals to demonstrate the injustice of such ideas.{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}} Throughout history those with personal experience with deaf individuals have fought against such systematic, ingrained misperceptions. It is to be noted, however, that industry exists which requires such misperceptions {{Citation needed|date=January 2012}} .

==See also==
*[[Deafhood]]
*[[Deaf culture]]
*[[Models of deafness]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.gallaudet.edu/library/research_help/research_help/frequently_asked_questions/cultural_social_medical/audism.html Audism FAQ ] by Gallaudet University
*[http://deafness.about.com/cs/deafculture/a/audism.htm deafness.about.com ] on audism
*[http://www.dawnsignpress.com/shopping/Detail.cfm?ProductID=213] Audism Unveiled, a film of interviews with Deaf people about how audism has impacted their lives

[[Category:Deafness]]
[[Category:Deaf culture]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]

[[de:Audismus]]
[[nl:Audisme]]
[[fi:Audismi]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>