<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20080726063135|227968062" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="2235517" pageid="2235517" ns="0" title="Audism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2008-11-08T17:34:13Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Discrimination sidebar}}
{{POV|date=December 2007}}

'''Audism''' is a term used to describe discrimination or stereotypes against [[deaf]] or [[hard of hearing]] people, for example by assuming that the cultural ways of hearing people are preferable or superior to those of [[Deaf culture|deaf]] or [[sign language|signing]] culture, or that deaf people are somehow less capable than hearing people.  It also can be used to describe the opposite, deaf people who scorn those with hearing.

Audists can either be hearing or deaf.  Audism occurs when a deaf person is judged as incapable of a given behavior, occupation, etc. simply because he or she cannot hear.  Audism is often coupled with a "hearing" superiority: an attitude of thinking one person is superior to another person because he or she can hear better than him or her.  Audism takes another form concerning interactions between the deaf: deaf people who will not use sign language and who will not identify with the Deaf community may consider themselves to be "better" than others who use sign language and are part of Deaf culture, or vice versa.

While opponents of audism seek to educate the public that Deaf people can do anything but hear, they recognize there are limitations in certain situations — service in the army, employment as a commercial pilot, or telemarketing, perhaps.  However, aside from a few, select examples, audism's opponents argue that the Deaf are capable of excelling in a myriad of settings and deserve [[equal opportunity]].

== Definitions ==
Audism (from Latin ''audire'', to hear, and ''-ism'', a system of practice, behavior, belief, or attitude) has been variously defined as:

*The belief that life without hearing is futile and miserable, that hearing loss is a tragedy and "the scourge of mankind," and that deaf people should struggle to be as much like hearing people as possible. Deaf activists Heidi Reed and Hartmut Teuber at D.E.A.F. Inc., a community service and advocacy organization in Boston, consider audism to be "a special case of [[ableism]]." Audists, hearing or deaf, shun [[Deaf culture]] and the use of [[American Sign Language|sign language]], and have what Reed and Teuber describe as "an obsession with the use of residual hearing, speech, and [[lip reading]] by deaf people." (Pelka 1997: 33)

*The notion that one is superior based on one's ability to hear or behave in the manner of one who hears. (Tom Humphries 1977, quoted in Zak 1996)

*An attitude based on pathological thinking which results in a negative stigma toward anyone who does not hear; like racism or sexism, audism judges, labels, and limits individuals on the basis of whether a person hears and speaks. (Humphrey and Alcorn 1995: 85)

*The corporate institution for dealing with deaf people--dealing with them by making statements about them, authorizing views of them, describing them, teaching about them, governing where they go to school and, in some cases, where they live; in short, audism is the hearing way of dominating, restructuring, and exercising authority over the deaf community. It includes such professional people as administrators of schools for deaf children and of training programs for deaf adults, interpreters, and some audiologists, speech therapists, otologists, psychologists, psychiatrists, librarians, researchers, social workers, and hearing aid specialists. (Lane 1992: 43)

== External links ==
*[http://library.gallaudet.edu/deaf-faq-audism.shtml Audism FAQ ]by Gallaudet University
*[http://deafness.about.com/cs/deafculture/a/audism.htm deafness.about.com ]on audism

[[Category:Deafness]]
[[Category:Deaf culture]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]

[[de:Audismus]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>