<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20141024082246|630905963" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="2235517" pageid="2235517" ns="0" title="Audism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2014-10-24T08:43:05Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Distinguish|Autism}}
{{Refimprove|date=April 2013}}

{{Discrimination sidebar}}
'''Audism''' is the notion that one is superior based on one's ability to hear or to behave in the manner of one who hears, or that life without hearing is futile and miserable, or an attitude based on pathological thinking which results in a negative stigma toward anyone who does not hear.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://libguides.gallaudet.edu/content.php?pid=114455&amp;sid=989379
|title=What Is Audism: Introduction
|first1=Tom|last1=Harrington
|first2=Laura|last2=Jacobi
|date=April 2009
|publisher=[[Gallaudet University]]
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Audism can manifest in many people, but it is most predominant in hearing people. It is this mentality that led [[Tom L. Humphries]] to coin the term in his doctoral dissertation in 1975.&lt;ref&gt;Capital D Magazine, Vol. 1, Iss. 1&lt;/ref&gt; People who practice audism are called audists. Audism is a form of [[ableism]], discrimination on the basis of (dis)ability.

==Types of audism==
Audism is partially responsible for the high unemployment rate of the deaf.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.netsignnews.com/Opinion_-_Discussion/Unemployment_Rates_In_The_Deaf_Community.php&lt;/ref&gt;

Linguistic audism can occur by banning use of commonly used sign languages such as [[American Sign Language]] and [[British Sign Language]]. Several schools have engaged in such prohibition in America in the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries, and some continue to do so.&lt;ref&gt;[http://abcnews.go.com/US/story?id=93532&amp;page=1#.T2JNh3nNnOM Bryan Robinson, Sign Language Ban Imposed on N.J. Girl] ''ABC News'' 18 April 2010 accessed 15 March 2012&lt;/ref&gt;

Additionally, Deaf people can practice forms of discrimination against members of their own community, based on what they believe is [[acceptable]] behavior, use of language, or social association. Dr. Genie Gertz explored examples of such audism in American society in her published dissertation.&lt;ref&gt;Dysconscious Audism: A Theoretical Proposal in Open Your Eyes: Deaf Studies Talking&lt;/ref&gt;

Audism can also occur between groups of deaf people, with some who choose not to use a sign language and not to identify with [[Deaf culture]] considering themselves to be superior to those who do, or vice versa. This is a type of 'dysconscious' audism, a phenomenon which is discussed in an essay by Genie Gertz in ''Open Your Eyes: Deaf Studies Talking''.

All these variations of audism, and many which have gone unmentioned, have their echoes in gender, racial, religious, cultural, social, and sexual discrimination, and, when found among the deaf community itself, bear resemblance to similar structures of self-loathing.

==Ideology==
According to [[Northeastern University (Boston, Massachusetts)|Northeastern University]] psychology professor [[Harlan Lane]], audism has existed for many centuries, although the recognition of the deaf community as a discrete language-using culture in the 20th century has afforded many more such examples. Audism has been seen as reflecting the attitudes cultures maintain about deaf people, and examples are seen as existing primarily within a medical paradigm, cultural paradigm, and education/linguistic paradigm. Lane has examined the development of deaf-based educational principles in his history of Franco-American deaf relations and educational philosophy.&lt;ref&gt;[[Lane, Harlan]] (1980). ''When the Mind Hears: A History of the Deaf'', [[Random House LLC]]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Phonocentrism]], the belief that speech and sounds are inherently superior to written language, has been described as being the root of audism.{{fact|date=October 2014}}

==See also==
* [[Deafhood]]
* [[Deaf culture]]
* [[Models of deafness]]
* [[Surdophobia]]

==References==
{{Cleanup-bare URLs|date=July 2013}}
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
*[http://www.gallaudet.edu/library/research_help/research_help/frequently_asked_questions/cultural_social_medical/audism.html Audism FAQ ] by Gallaudet University
*[http://deafness.about.com/cs/deafculture/a/audism.htm deafness.about.com ] on audism
*[http://www.dawnsignpress.com/shopping/Detail.cfm?ProductID=213] Audism Unveiled, a film of interviews with Deaf people about how audism has impacted their lives

[[Category:Deafness]]
[[Category:Deaf culture]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>