<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061103151505|85480550" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="252622" pageid="252622" ns="0" title="Heterosexism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-11-05T17:12:08Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Heterosexism''' is a predisposition towards [[heterosexuality|heterosexual]] people, which some see as biased against [[lesbian]], [[gay]], [[bisexuality|bisexual]], [[queer]], [[transgender]] or [[intersexed]], people among others. A related term is '''Sexual Prejudice''', a negative attitude toward someone because of her or his sexual orientation. &lt;ref&gt; Matlin, Margaret W.,Ph.D., "The Psychology of Women", (2004)&lt;/ref&gt; 
This bias is not the same as [[homophobia|Homophobia]], but rather is the discrimination towards or against non-heterosexuals due to cultural or sociobiological bias. Heterosexism suggests that the problem of bias is not an individual problem but rather a cultural failing or perhaps a fact of evolutionary psychology that results in biased attitudes towards sexual orientations other than heterosexuality.

An earlier definition of this term is:
Heterosexism is a belief or argument that [[heterosexuality|male-female sexuality]] is the only [[natural]], [[normal]], or [[moral]] mode of sexual behavior, and is also used to refer to the effects of that instinct. The word 'heterosexualism' has also been proposed to mean essentially the same thing. &lt;!--In The Dictionary of Psychology [1] &lt;b&gt;heterosexism&lt;/b&gt; is defined as 
"An argument that male-female sexuality is the only correct, natural, proper, or moral mode of sexual activity. [Also proposed as] 'heterosexualism'. --&gt; &lt;ref&gt;Corsini, Raymond J., ''The Dictionary of Psychology'' (2001), ISBN 1-58391-328-9&lt;br&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; This word has been suggested as an alternative to [[homophobia]] &lt;ref&gt;Herek, Gregory M., Ph.D., " Beyond 'Homophobia': Thinking About Sexual Prejudice and Stigma in the Twenty-First Century."   Sexuality Research &amp; Social Policy (April, 2004)&lt;/ref&gt;, in part because it uses a parallel structure to [[sexism]] or [[racism]]. The intent of heterosexism is the examination of the cultural bias towards non-heterosexuals rather than individual bias, which is the focus of homophobia.

Heterosexism should not be confused with '''heterocentrism''', which is an (often subconscious) assumption that everyone is heterosexual, and the attitudes associated with that assumption.  Heterocentrism often shows up in unintentional ways in every day life.  For instance, when a woman says she is going on a date, many people will ask, "What's his name?" or "Is he cute?" assuming it is a heterosexual date. Nevertheless, these people may not have anything against same-sex dating.  In [[queer theory]], the term heterocentrism is closely related to [[heteronormativity]].{{citeneeded}}

Since heterosexist pyschologies help reinforce heterosexual behavior, the prevalence of heterosexism can be explained in cultural and, perhaps, evolutionary terms as the idea that heterosexist individuals are more likely to engage in heterosexual behavior and produce offspring than homosexist individuals. As such heterosexism may be viewed as an evolutionarily advantageous trait which promotes behavior more likely to propagate and ensure the existence of the population in which it exists.

== Sources ==
&lt;references /&gt;

The term homophobia is widely used in academic writing and in everyday usage. It has come to describe the most visible forms of anti-gay prejudice.However, there are a number of limitations surrounding its use because it refers to individual psychologies. Although heterosexism is increasingly being used because of its potential to include political and social conditions, it is poorly understood. The following is proposed as a three-part definition to enable the development of a theory of heterosexism to conceptualise LGB oppression:
(i)Heterosexism is a belief system that values heterosexuality as inherently normal and superior to homosexuality.
(ii)Heterosexism is based on the assumption that everyone is, or should be, heterosexual. 
(iii)Heterosexism intersects with other forms of oppression such as sexism, racism and disabilism. 4 &lt;sup&gt;Superscript text&lt;/sup&gt; 

4. Fish, J. (Oct, 2006) Heterosexism in Health &amp; Social Care. Basingstoke: Palgrave.

http://www.palgrave.com/newsearch/Catalogue.aspx?is=1403941238

== See also ==

*[[Homophobia]]
*[[Heteronormativity]]

[[Category:Gender studies]]
[[Category:Queer theory]]
[[Category:Sexual orientation and society]]
[[Category:Prejudices]]
[[Category:Transgender]]

[[br:Arallrevouriezh]]
[[bg:Хетеросексизъм]]
[[da:Heterosexisme]]
[[de:Heterosexismus]]
[[el:Ετεροσεξισμός]]
[[es:Heterosexismo]]
[[fr:Hétérosexisme]]
[[mk:Хетеросексизам]]
[[pt:Heterossexismo]]
[[ru:Гетеросексизм]]
[[tr:Heteroseksizm]]
[[zh:异性恋主义]]


{{LGBT-stub}}</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>