<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20111025162436|457338650" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="252622" pageid="252622" ns="0" title="Heterosexism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2011-11-10T11:24:32Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{LGBT sidebar}}
'''Heterosexism''' is a system of [[Attitude (psychology)|attitudes]], [[bias]], and [[discrimination]] in favor of opposite-sex sexuality and relationships.&lt;ref name="JungSmith"&gt;{{cite book|last=Jung|first=Patricia Beattie|coauthors=Smith, Ralph F.|title=Heterosexism: An Ethical Challenge|publisher=State University of New York Press|year=1993|isbn=0791416968}}&lt;/ref&gt;  It can include the presumption that everyone is [[Heterosexuality|heterosexual]] or that opposite-sex attractions and relationships are the only [[norm (sociology)|norm]]&lt;ref name="granddictionnaire.com"&gt;http://www.granddictionnaire.com/btml/fra/r_motclef/index800_1.asp&lt;/ref&gt; and therefore superior. Although heterosexism is defined in the online editions of the ''[[American Heritage Dictionary of the English Language]]'' and the ''[[Webster's Dictionary|Merriam-Webster Collegiate Dictionary]]'' as anti-gay discrimination and/or prejudice "by heterosexual people"&lt;ref&gt;http://education.yahoo.com/reference/dictionary/entry/heterosexism accessed Oct 9, 2009&lt;/ref&gt; and "by heterosexuals",&lt;ref&gt;http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/heterosexism accessed on Oct 9, 2009&lt;/ref&gt; people of any [[sexual orientation]] can hold such attitudes and bias. Nonetheless, heterosexism as discrimination ranks [[gay]] men, [[lesbian]]s, and [[bisexual]]s as [[second-class citizen]]s with regard to various legal and [[civil rights]], economic opportunities, and [[social equality]] in the majority of the [[LGBT rights by country or territory|world’s jurisdictions]] and societies.

== Background ==
While the ''[[Webster's Dictionary|Merriam-Webster Collegiate Dictionary]]'' notes first use of the term heterosexism as having occurred some time in 1972, the first published use was in 1971 by [[gay rights activist]], [[Craig Rodwell]]. &lt;ref&gt;Rodwell, Craig. ' 'The Tarnished Golden Rule' ' pg. 5, QQ Magazine, Queen's Quarterly Publishing, New York. (January/February 1971 issue, Vol. 3, No. 1) Retrieved July 21, 2011. &lt;/ref&gt;

===Etymology and usage===
Similar terms include "heterocentrism" and "heterosexualism".&lt;ref&gt;Corsini, Raymond J. (1992). ''The Dictionary of Psychology''. ISBN 1583913289.&lt;/ref&gt; Although the well-established term ''heterosexism'' is often explained as a [[Neologism|coinage]] modeled on ''[[sexism]]'', the derivation of its meaning points more to (1.) ''heterosex(ual)'' + ''-ism'' than (2.) ''hetero-'' + ''sexism''. In fact, the [[portmanteau]] word ''heterosexualism'' has been used as an equivalent to sexism and racism.&lt;ref&gt;Gregory M. Herek. [http://psychology.ucdavis.edu/rainbow/html/prej_defn.html "Definitions: Homophobia, Heterosexism, and Sexual Prejudice"].&lt;/ref&gt;

Given this lack of [[Transparency (linguistic)#Descriptive|semantic transparency]], researchers, outreach workers, [[critical theorists]] and [[LGBT]] activists have proposed and use terms such as ''institutionalized homophobia'', ''state(-sponsored) homophobia'',&lt;ref&gt;International Lesbian and Gay Association. [http://www.ilga.org/news_results.asp?LanguageID=1&amp;FileID=1058&amp;FileCategory=10&amp;ZoneID=7 "State-sponsored Homophobia"]&lt;/ref&gt; ''sexual prejudice'', ''anti-gay [[bigotry]]'', ''[[straight privilege'', ''[[La pensée straight|The Straight Mind]]'' (a collection of essays by French writer [[Monique Wittig]]), ''heterosexual bias'', ''compulsory heterosexuality''&lt;ref&gt;LGBTQ on-line encyclopedia of gay, lesbian, bisexual, transgender, and queer culture&lt;/ref&gt; or the much lesser known terms ''heterocentrism'', ''[[homonegativity]]'', and from [[gender theory]] and [[queer theory]], ''[[heteronormativity]]''.

===Heterosexism vs. homophobia===

''[[Homophobia]]'' refers both to "unreasoning fear of or [[antipathy]] towards homosexuals and homosexuality"&lt;ref name=dictionary.com&gt;{{cite web|url=http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/homophobia homophobia|title=Dictonary.com|accessdate=2008-01-29|year=2008|publisher=Dictonary.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; and to "behavior based on such a feeling".&lt;ref&gt;http://education.yahoo.com/reference/dictionary/entry/homophobia&lt;/ref&gt; ''Heterosexism'', however, denotes the "system of ideological thought that makes heterosexuality the sole norm to follow for sexual practices".&lt;ref name="granddictionnaire.com"&gt;http://www.granddictionnaire.com/btml/fra/r_motclef/index800_1.asp&lt;/ref&gt; As a bias favoring heterosexuals and heterosexuality, heterosexism has been described as being "encoded into and characteristic of the major social, cultural, and economic institutions of our society"&lt;ref&gt;Dines, Gail (2002). ''Gender, Race, and Class in Media: A Text-Reader''. ISBN 076192261X.&lt;/ref&gt; and stems from the [[essentialist]] cultural notion that [[maleness]]-[[masculinity]] and femaleness-[[femininity]] are complementary.

Researcher, author, and psychology professor Gregory M. Herek states that "[Heterosexism] operates through a dual process of invisibility and attack. Homosexuality usually remains culturally invisible; when people who engage in homosexual behavior or who are identified as homosexual become visible, they are subject to attack by society."&lt;ref name="psychology.ucdavis.edu"&gt;http://psychology.ucdavis.edu/rainbow/HTML/prej_defn.html&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, in interviews with perpetrators of [[anti-gay violence]], [[forensic psychology|forensic psychologist]] Karen Franklin points out that “heterosexism is not just a personal [[value system]], [rather] it is a tool in the maintenance of [[gender]] dichotomy.”&lt;ref name="Franklin"&gt;Franklin, Karen (1998). "Inside the Minds of People Who Hate Gays" Retrieved May 29, 2008: http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/pages/frontline/shows/assault/roots/franklin.html&lt;/ref&gt; She continues by saying that “assaults on homosexuals and other individuals who deviate from [[Gender role|sex role]] norms are viewed as a learned form of [[social control]] of deviance rather than a defensive response to personal threat.”&lt;ref name="Franklin"/&gt;

===Parallels and intersections===
{{Rquote|right|Using the term heterosexism highlights the parallels between antigay sentiment and other forms of prejudice, such as racism, antisemitism, and sexism.  |[[Gregory M. Herek]], researcher, author, and professor of psychology at [[University of California at Davis|UC Davis]].|&lt;ref name="psychology.ucdavis.edu"/&gt;}}

It has been argued that the concept of heterosexism is similar to the concept of [[racism]] in that both ideas promote privilege for dominant groups within a given society. For example, borrowing from the racial concept of [[white privilege]], the concept of [[heterosexual privilege]]&lt;ref name="genderknot149"&gt;{{cite book|last=Johnson|first=Allan J.|title=The Gender Knot|publisher=Temple University Press|location=Philadelphia|year=1997|pages=149|isbn=1566395194}}&lt;/ref&gt; has been applied to benefits of (presumed) heterosexuality within society that heterosexuals take for granted. The analogy is that just as racism against non-white people places white people as superior to [[Person of color|non-white]]s, heterosexism places heterosexual people or relationships as superior to [[non-heterosexual]] ones.  In trying to rebut this premise, some commentators point to differences&lt;ref&gt;[http://blogs.bet.com/news/youthvote/4-reasons-why-gay-is-not-the-new-black/4 Reasons 'Why Gay is NOT the New Black', accessed Aug 30, 2009]&lt;/ref&gt; between the categories of race and sexual orientation, claiming they are too complex to support any generalizations.  For example, "[[Diversity training|trainer on diversity]]" and consultant Jamie Washington has commented, although heterosexism and racism are "woven from the same fabric" they are "not the same thing".&lt;ref&gt;[http://susquehanna.edu/crusader/article.cfm?IssueID=59&amp;SectionID=1&amp;ArticleID=2573 Issues of race and sexuality discussed, Susquehanna Crusader Online, accessed Aug 29, 2009 ]&lt;/ref&gt;  Conservative leaders such as [http://www.laprogressive.com/author/rev.-irene-monroe/ Rev. Irene Monroe] comment that those who suggest or state "gay is [[the new black]]", as in a cover story of [[The Advocate]] magazine,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.advocate.com/exclusive_detail_ektid65744.asp Gay is the New Black, accessed Aug 30, 2009]&lt;/ref&gt; exploit [[black people]]'s suffering and experiences to legitimate their own.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.irenemonroe.com/2008/12/16/gay-is-not-the-new-black/ Gay is NOT the new Black, accessed Aug 29, 2009]&lt;/ref&gt; Nonetheless, a study presented at the [[British Psychological Society]]’s Division of Occupational Psychology 2009 Conference shows that heterosexist prejudice is more pervasive than racism.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.bps.org.uk/media-centre/press-releases/releases$/division-of-occupational-psychology/prejudice-study-finds-gay-is-the-new-black.cfm Prejudice study finds gay is the new black, accessed Sept 3, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

Heterosexism can, also [[Intersectionality|intersect]] with racism by further emphasizing differences among arbitrary groups of people.&lt;ref name="tatum22"&gt;{{cite book|last=Tatum|first=Beverly|title=Why are all the Black kids sitting together in the cafeteria?|publisher=Basic Books|year=1997|pages=21–22}}&lt;/ref&gt; For example, heterosexism can compound the effects of racism by:
*promoting injustices towards a person already facing injustices because of their race
*establishing [[social hierarchies]] that allow one group more privilege than other groups.

Likewise, racism can allow LGBT people to be subjected to additional discrimination or violence if they belong to or are considered a part of a socially devalued racial category.&lt;ref&gt;(2008) Heterosexism and Homophobia. Encyclopedia of Race and Racism, 2, 1–4. Retrieved March 31, 2008 from Gale Virtual Reference Library: http://find.galegroup.com/ips/start.do?prodId=IPS.&lt;/ref&gt; Some of the privileges afforded to people falling into the categories of white people and (perceived) heterosexuals include, but are not limited to, social acceptance, prestige, freedom from negative [[stereotypes]], and the comfort of being within the [[Norm (sociology)|norm]] and thereby not being [[marginalized]] or viewed as different.&lt;ref&gt;Simoni, J. M. &amp; Walters, K. L. (2001). Heterosexual Identity and Heterosexism: Recognizing Privilege to Reduce Prejudice. Journal of Homosexuality, 1(1), 157–173. Retrieved March 30, 2008 from Google Scholar: http://www.haworthpress.com/store/E-Text/View_EText.asp?a=3&amp;fn=J082v41n01_06&amp;i=1&amp;s=J082&amp;v=41&lt;/ref&gt;

== As a set of beliefs and attitudes ==
{{See also|Religion and homosexuality|Homosexuality and psychology|Sexual orientation and medicine|Social attitudes toward homosexuality}}

=== Individual and group level ===
Heterosexism as a set of beliefs and attitudes relies on a core [[tenet]] according to which [[heteronormativity|homosexuality and bisexuality do not normally exist]] and, as such, constitute illnesses or [[deviant behavior]]s.&lt;ref name="genderknot17"&gt;{{cite book|last=Johnson|first=Allan J.|title=The Gender Knot|publisher=Temple University Press|location=Philadelphia|year=1997|pages=17|isbn=1566395194}}&lt;/ref&gt; Within a heterosexist ideology or [[mindset]], the concept of [[sexual orientation]] is rejected or deemed irrelevant. A set of more nuanced heterosexist views, which some may consider faith, [[dogma]], [[Moral absolutism|universal truth]]s, natural law, [[Appeal to authority|appeals to authority]], or popular beliefs, but others consider to be [[conventional wisdom]] or [[sociobiology|sociobiological]] knowledge can include, among others, the following:

[[Image:Save Our Children Brochure inside.jpg|thumb|250 px|Inside of Save Our Children's brochure, showing a collage of headlines connecting homosexuality to [[pedophilia]]; the flap opens to reveal 17 headlines and parts of newspaper stories.]]
*Non-heterosexual persons should keep their sexual orientations private (i.e., they should remain "[[closeted]]").&lt;ref name="JungSmith" /&gt;&lt;sup&gt; p.&amp;nbsp;15&lt;/sup&gt;
*The attitude that gay men aren't [[machismo|"real" men]] or lesbians aren't "real" women because of the socially pervasive view that heterosexual attractions or activities are the "norm" and therefore superior.&lt;ref name="genderknot149" /&gt;
*"God created [[Adam and Eve]], not [[Adam and Steve]] (or Madame and Eve)" and similar essentialist cultural notions that maleness-masculinity and femaleness-femininity are complementary;
*Homosexuality being wrong, ungodly, and against nature, it is therefore a [[sin]], [[evil]] or subhuman.&lt;ref name="JungSmith" /&gt;&lt;sup&gt; p.&amp;nbsp;18&lt;/sup&gt;
*Views identical or akin to [[Anita Bryant]]'s notorious statement during her [[Anita Bryant#Save Our Children|Save Our Children]] campaign in the U.S. (''See campaign brochure image at right''):
:"As a mother, I know that homosexuals cannot biologically reproduce children; therefore, they must [[Homosexual recruitment|recruit]] our children."
*Because of their lifestyle, homosexuals do not have families with children, so they undermine the survival of the human race. ([[natalism]])
*Homosexuality is an affectional or [[mental disorder]] or simply a social ill, therefore, it can be cured or stamped out. If it is not eradicated, it will lead to [[Social solidarity|social disintegration]] and [[societal collapse]].
*Homosexuals can be converted "back" to heterosexuality.&lt;ref name="JungSmith" /&gt;&lt;sup&gt; p.&amp;nbsp;109&lt;/sup&gt;

===Institutional level===
As well as comprising attitudes held by an individual or a social group, heterosexism can also exist as the expression of attitudes within an institution. As a result, schools, hospitals, and correctional facilities can act as a showcase for heterosexist attitudes in various ways. First, schools may implement these attitudes and ideas through unequal and inconsistent disciplinary actions. One such example is meting out harsher punishment to a same-sex couple violating the school ground rules while allowing a heterosexual couple to pass with an easier and more subtle disciplinary action for an equal or identical violation. Also, hospitals may limit patient visiting only to immediate family, i.e., relatives, and exclude same sex partners.&lt;ref&gt;Heterosexism and Homophobia. Encyclopedia of Race and Racism, 2, 1–4. Retrieved March 31, 2008 from Gale Virtual Reference Library: http://find.galegroup.com/ips/start.do?prodId=IPS.&lt;/ref&gt;

Heterosexism affects the family in several ways. For example, in most jurisdictions, same-sex marriage is not allowed, so non-heterosexual persons must remain unmarried or enter into heterosexual marriage.&lt;ref name="TFDASJ" /&gt; Many jurisdictions also deny rights and benefits to same-sex couples, including custodial and adoption rights for children, Social Security benefits, and automatic durable power of attorney and hospital spousal rights.&lt;ref name="TFDASJ"&gt;{{cite book|last=Adams|first=Maurianne|coauthors=Bell, Lee Anne and Griffin, Pat|title=Teaching for Diversity and Social Justice|publisher=Routledge|year=2007|edition=2|chapter=Appendix 9H|isbn=041595200X }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== As discrimination ==
===Explicit or open discrimination===

This type of heterosexism includes [[LGBT rights opposition|anti-gay]] laws, policies, and institutional practices, harassment based on sexual orientation or perceived sexual orientation; negative [[stereotyping]], discriminatory language and discourse, and other forms of discrimination against gay men, lesbians, bisexuals such as:

*[[Hate speech]], [[terms of disparagement]], [[hate mail]], [[death threats]], [[Stop Murder Music|murder music]]
*[[Scapegoating]], [[mobbing]], [[Witch-hunt#Political usage|witch-hunts]], [[moral panic]]; using gay men and homosexuality as a [[folk devil]] for the [[AIDS pandemic]].
*Negative portrayals or stereotypes of gay men, lesbians, and bisexuals solely as villains, suicide or murder victims,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title= Psychological perspectives on lesbian and gay male experiences|last= Garnets |first= Linda|coauthors= Kimmel, Douglas C. |year= 1993|publisher= [[Columbia University Press]]|isbn= 0231078846}}&lt;/ref&gt; the butt of jokes, objects of curiosity. This can occur on television and in movies as well as in jokes between friends or among co-workers.
*Using the [[gay panic defense]] in assault or murder cases.
*[[Sodomy law]]s when enforced almost exclusively against consenting, adult, same-sex partners. ''See also: [[Bowers v. Hardwick]] and [[Lawrence v. Texas]]''
*In some countries where [[Homosexuality laws of the world|homosexuality is criminalized]], such as Sudan, Mauritania, Saudi Arabia, and the Islamic Republic of Iran, offenders may receive the maximum sentence of [[capital punishment]]. ''See also: [[Paragraph 175]]''
*Discrepancies in [[Age of consent#Homosexual and heterosexual age discrepancies in law|age of consent]] laws in which legal sexual activity between members of the same sex is set at a higher age than that for opposite-sex partners. Most such laws apply explicitly (or have historically applied) only to male homosexual sexual activity. ''See also: [[Chris Morris (activist)|Morris v. The United Kingdom]]'', [[State v. Limon]]
*Prohibiting youth from bringing a same-sex date to [[Prom|high school prom]].&lt;ref&gt;[[American Civil Liberties Union]]: [http://gbge.aclu.org/schools/free-speech-free-expression-and-prom Free Speech, Free Expression and Prom]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=Aaron Fricke decided he wanted to go to his senior prom with Paul Guilbert. His principal wouldn't let him.|title=Who are you taking to the prom this year? |date=31 December 2000|publisher=[[American Civil Liberties Union]]|accessdate=21 December 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;''See also: [[Fricke v. Lynch]], [[Marc Hall v. Durham Catholic School Board]]''
*Adoption bans against either same-sex couples or gay, lesbian, or bisexual individuals. ''See also: [[LGBT adoption]], [[In re: Gill]]''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gordonmoyes.com/2009/02/26/parliamentary-inquiries-same-sex-adoption/  Gordon Moyes]&lt;/ref&gt;
*Legislation that prevents legal and [[social equality]], i.e., laws that prohibit protection against discrimination based on sexual orientation or perceived sexual orientation, particularly with regard to health care, housing, and employment.
*The institution of opposite-sex marriage and reserving the right to marry strictly for opposite-sex couples via explicit definitions or through bans on [[same-sex marriage]] such as “[[Marriage Protection Act|marriage protection act]]s” or “[[Defense of Marriage Act|defense of marriage act]]s”;&lt;ref name="JungSmith" /&gt;&lt;sup&gt; pp.&amp;nbsp;145–151&lt;/sup&gt; In order to obtain the legal protections of marriage, same-sex couples who cannot get married must pay thousands of (U.S.) dollars in attorney's fees.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.chicagotribune.com/news/chi-gays-pay-more-18-jan18,0,2205178.story|title='Marriage' benefits costly for gay couples|last=Huppke|first=Rex|date=18 January 2010|publisher=[[Chicago Tribune]]|accessdate=21 January 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Also, the above restriction even when same-sex couples have access to [[civil union]]s that are either analogous to or not on a par with marriage;
*Reserving civil unions strictly for opposite-sex couples;
*Barring gay men, lesbians, and bisexuals from serving in the armed forces or from working in the education field; this can include policies such as the [[Military of the United States|U.S. military]]’s “[[Don't ask, don't tell]]” policy or [[Lech Kaczyński]] and other conservative Polish politicians’ stance to exclude gay men and lesbians from entering the teaching profession. ''See also: [[LGBT rights in Poland]]''
*Organized opposition to [[gay rights]]; [[Labeling theory|labeling]] such rights and privileges as "[[special rights]]" or the "[[Homosexual agenda|Gay Agenda]]";
*Referring to a suspected criminal's homosexuality or bisexuality when in analogous situations there is no mention of a suspect's heterosexuality.

===Implicit or hidden discrimination===
This form of heterosexism operates through invisibility, under-representation, and [[wikt:erasure|erasure]]. It includes:

*Lack or under-representation of homosexual or bisexual people in advertising to the general public;
*Censorship of homosexual or bisexual characters, themes, and issues in works of art, literature, entertainment; ''see also [[Postcards from Buster#Controversial episodes|"Sugar Time" episode of Postcards from Buster]]''
*Exclusion of historical and political figures’ and celebrities’ homosexuality or bisexuality; their portrayal as heterosexuals;
*Complete avoidance of mentioning these people and their positive contributions particularly in news media;
*In the context of sex education or professional advice, referring only to opposite-sex partners when discussing female or male [[sexual attraction]] and activity;
*Silence on issues affecting homosexual and bisexual people at school or work or absence of their discussion in a positive light; *Implementation and use of [[content-control software]] (censorware) to filter out information and websites that focus on homosexuality or bisexuality;
*[[Postal censorship]] and border control or customs seizure of publications deemed obscene solely on the basis of them containing material related to homosexuality even when they contain no erotic or pornographic material; ''see also [[Little Sister's Book and Art Emporium]]''
*Work environments that tacitly require gay men, lesbians, and bisexuals not to reveal their sexual orientation via discussion of their relationship status while heterosexuals can discuss their relationships and [[marital status]] freely;
*At public libraries or bookstores: rejection, removal or destruction of [[Homosexuality in children's literature|books]] (e.g. ''[[Jenny lives with Eric and Martin]]''), films, and posters with homosexual themes;
*Refusal to include families headed by [[Same-sex parenting|same-sex parents]] at school events or to represent such family diversity in school curricula; ''see also [[anti-bias curriculum]]'';
*Coercive or forced [[sex reassignment surgery]] on gay men, lesbian women, and bisexuals – an issue addressed in [[Tanaz Eshaghian]]'s 2008 documentary, ''[[Be Like Others]]''. ''See also: [[LGBT rights in Iran]]''
*[[Forced disappearance]], ''[[damnatio memoriae]]'', [[ostracism]], [[shunning]], and other forms of [[social rejection]] geared towards making homosexual or bisexual people ''[[Persona non grata|personae non gratae]]''.

== Effects ==

Heterosexism causes a range of effects on people of any sexual orientation. However, the main effects of heterosexism are marginalization, and anti-LGBT violence and abuse.

=== Marginalization ===

The main effect of heterosexism is the [[marginalization]] of gay men, lesbians, and bisexuals within society. Heterosexism has led to [[Social stigma|stigmatization]] and persecution of not only these people but also those of other sexual diversity such as transgender, and transsexual people. Along with [[homophobia]], [[lesbophobia]], and [[Homophobia#Internalized homophobia|internalized homophobia]], heterosexism continues to be a significant social reality that compels people to conceal their homosexual or bisexual orientation, or metaphorically, to remain in [[Closeted|the closet]] in an effort to [[Passing (sexual orientation)|pass]] for heterosexual.

Marginalization also occurs when marriage rights are heterosexist. More specifically, when marriage rights are exclusive to opposite-sex couples, all same-sex couples, be they gay, lesbian, straight or mixed, are prevented from enjoying marriage’s corresponding legal privileges, especially those regarding property rights, health benefits, and child custody. Moreover, such limitation prevents same-sex couples from receiving the inherent social respect of marriage and its cultural symbolism.

=== Anti-LGBT violence and abuse ===

Yolanda Dreyer, professor of practical theology at [[University of Pretoria]], has claimed that “Heterosexism leads to prejudice, discrimination, harassment, and [[Violence against LGBT people|violence]].  It is driven by fear and hatred (Dreyer 5).”&lt;ref&gt;Dreyer,Yolanda. “Hegemony and the Internalisation of Homophobia Caused by Heteronormativity.” Department of Practical Theology. 2007. University of Pretoria.5 May 2008 [www.up.ac.za/dspace/bitstream/2263/2741/1/Dreyer_Hegemony(2007).pdf.]&lt;/ref&gt; Along the same lines, forensic psychologist Karen Franklin explains violence caused by heterosexism toward both men and women, regardless of their sexual orientations:

&lt;blockquote&gt;[T]hrough heterosexism, any male who refuses to accept the dominant culture's assignment of appropriate masculine behavior is labeled early on as a "[[Sissy#Pejorative|sissy]]" or "[[Fag (slang)|fag]]" and then subjected to [[bullying]]. Similarly, any woman who opposes male dominance and control can be labeled a lesbian and attacked. The potential of being [[Ostracism|ostracized]] as homosexual, regardless of actual sexual attractions and behaviors, puts pressure on all people to conform to a narrow standard of appropriate gender behavior, thereby maintaining and reinforcing our society's hierarchical gender structure.”&lt;ref name="Franklin"/&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Another form of heterosexist violence as [[social control]] that most often targets lesbian women is [[corrective rape]]: a [[gang rape]] of a lesbian to "cure" her of her same-sex attractions. A notorious example from South Africa is the corrective rape and murder of [[Eudy Simelane]], [[LGBT social movements|LGBT-rights]] activist and member of the [[South Africa women's national football team|women's national football team]].&lt;ref name="guardian120309"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2009/mar/12/eudy-simelane-corrective-rape-south-africa|title=Raped and killed for being a lesbian: South Africa ignores 'corrective' attacks|last=Kelly|first=Annie|date=12 March 2009|publisher=[[The Guardian]]|accessdate=2009-03-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Responses ==

On singing duo [[Romanovsky and Phillips]]' album ''Be Political, Not Polite'', the song "When Heterosexism Strikes" discusses possible actions in response to example cases of heterosexism. ([http://www.romanovskyandphillips.com/politicallyrics.htm#hetero lyrics])

== See also ==
{{multicol}}
* [[Culture war]]
* [[Identity politics]]
* [[Minority group]]
* [[Minority rights]]
* [[Norm (sociology)]]
* [[Second-class citizen]]
* [[Discrimination]]
* [[Persecution of homosexuals]]
* [[Discrimination against people with HIV/AIDS]]
{{multicol-break}}
{{Portal box|LGBT|Sociology}}
* [[Harassment#Categories|Harassment (categories and types)]]
* [[Heterophobia]]
* [[Transphobia|Cissexism]]
* [[Heteronormativity]]
* [[Toleration|Intolerance]]
* [[LGBT rights by country or territory]]
* [[LGBT rights opposition]]
* [[LGBT stereotypes]]
* [[Slogans of anti-gay ideology]]
{{multicol-end}}

==References==
{{Ibid|date=March 2010}}
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.mun.ca/the The Heterosexism Enquirer] – "an electronic magazine dedicated to challenging heterosexism in society's institutions, individuals, families and communities"
* [http://www.mun.ca/the/themain.html Is My Workplace Heterosexist? and Are My Attitudes Heterosexist? – Tests] Click ''Test Yourself'' from the menu on the left.
* [http://www.cs.earlham.edu/~hyrax/personal/files/student_res/straightprivilege.htm "Daily effects of straight privilege"] examples of benefits within society that heterosexuals take for granted

{{LGBT|social=expanded}}
{{Discrimination|state=uncollapsed}}

[[Category:Discrimination against homosexuals]]
[[Category:Sexual orientation and society]]
[[Category:LGBT rights]]
[[Category:Sexual and gender prejudices]]
[[Category:Homophobia]]
[[Category:Gender studies]]
[[Category:Queer theory]]
[[Category:Transgender]]

[[br:Arallrevouriezh]]
[[bg:Хетеросексизъм]]
[[ca:Heterosexisme]]
[[cy:Heterorywiaeth]]
[[da:Heterosexisme]]
[[de:Heterosexismus]]
[[el:Ετεροσεξισμός]]
[[es:Heterosexismo]]
[[fr:Hétérosexisme]]
[[gl:Heterosexismo]]
[[id:Heteroseksisme]]
[[he:הטרוסקסיזם]]
[[lt:Heteroseksizmas]]
[[mk:Хетеросексизам]]
[[no:Heterosexisme]]
[[pl:Heteroseksizm]]
[[pt:Heterossexismo]]
[[ro:Heterosexism]]
[[ru:Гетеросексизм]]
[[sr:Хетеросексизам]]
[[sh:Heteroseksizam]]
[[sv:Heterosexism]]
[[tr:Heteroseksizm]]
[[uk:Гетеросексизм]]
[[vi:Chủ nghĩa dị tính luyến ái]]
[[zh:异性恋主义]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>