<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20071111025736|170670396" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="252622" pageid="252622" ns="0" title="Heterosexism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-11-11T07:42:24Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Moresources|date=August 2007}}
{{LGBT}}

'''Heterosexism''' is a term denoting the presumption that everyone is [[Heterosexuality|heterosexual]] and/or the belief that heterosexual people are naturally superior to [[Homosexuality|homosexual]] and [[Bisexuality|bisexual]] people. Heterosexism may also specify [[discrimination]] and [[prejudice]] in favor of heterosexual people over [[gay]], [[lesbian]], and bisexual people. As a predisposition toward heterosexuals and heterosexuality, heterosexism has been described as being "encoded into and characteristic of the major social, cultural, and economic institutions of our society."&lt;ref&gt;Dines, Gail (2002). ''Gender, Race, and Class in Media: A Text-Reader''. ISBN 076192261X.&lt;/ref&gt;

Heterosexism thus includes the underlying [[belief]]s and [[Attitude (psychology)|attitude]]s of such preference. Stemming from the [[essentialist]] cultural notion that [[maleness]]-[[masculinity]] and [[femaleness]]-[[femininity]] are complementary, heterosexism is not limited to heterosexuals; people of any [[sexual orientation]], including gay men, lesbians or bisexuals, can hold '''heterosexist''' beliefs.{{Fact|date=August 2007}} 

== Etymology and usage==

The term '''''heterocentrism''''' or '''''[[heterosexualism]]''''' may be equivalent to ''heterosexism'' &lt;ref&gt;Corsini, Raymond J. (1992). ''The Dictionary of Psychology''. ISBN 1583913289.&lt;/ref&gt;. Although the well-established term ''heterosexism'' is often explained as a [[Neologism|coinage]] modeled on ''[[sexism]]'', the derivation of its meaning points more to (1.) ''heterosex&lt;s&gt;ual&lt;/s&gt;'' + ''-ism'' than (2.) ''hetero-'' + ''sexism''. In fact, the [[portmanteau]] word ''heterosexualism'' has been proposed as a near equivalent. &lt;ref&gt;Gregory M. Herek. [http://psychology.ucdavis.edu/rainbow/html/prej_defn.html "Definitions: Homophobia, Heterosexism, and Sexual Prejudice"].&lt;/ref&gt;

Given this lack of [[Transparency (linguistic)#Descriptive|semantic transparency]], researchers, outreach workers, [[critical theorists]] and [[LGBT]] activists have proposed and use terms such as ''institutionalized [[homophobia]]'', ''state(-sponsored) homophobia'',&lt;ref&gt;International Lesbian and Gay Association. [http://www.ilga.org/news_results.asp?LanguageID=1&amp;FileID=1058&amp;FileCategory=10&amp;ZoneID=7 "State-sponsored Homophobia"]&lt;/ref&gt; ''sexual prejudice'', ''anti-gay [[bigotry]]'', ''straight [[privilege]]'', ''heterosexual [[bias]]'' or the much lesser known terms ''[[heterocentrism]]'', ''[[homonegativity]]'', and from [[gender theory]] and [[queer theory]], ''[[heteronormativity]]''. In everyday speech and writing, however, ''heterosexism'' is commonly confused with or eclipsed by the word ''homophobia'', whose key meaning is [[antipathy]] towards gay men and lesbians.

== Heterosexism as a set of beliefs and attitudes ==

:''See also: [[Religion and homosexuality]], [[Homosexuality and psychology]], [[Sexual orientation and medicine]], and [[Social attitudes toward homosexuality]]''

Heterosexism as a set of beliefs and attitudes relies on a core [[tenet]] according to which homosexuality and bisexuality do not exist normally and, as such, constitute [[deviant behavior]]s. Within a heterosexist [[ideology]] or [[mindset]], the well-established concept of [[sexual orientation]] is rejected. A set of more nuanced heterosexist views, which some may consider [[faith]], [[dogma]], [[Moral absolutism|universal truth]]s, [[Appeal to authority|appeals to authority]], or popular beliefs, but others consider to be [[sociobiology|sociobiological]] knowledge can include, among others, the following:
*A person can choose his or her sexual “preference” and, as a result, homosexuality is a [[lifestyle]] choice or a current [[Fads and trends|fad]].
*Homosexuality being wrong, ungodly, and against nature, it is therefore a [[sin]], [[evil]] or subhuman.
*Since they cannot reproduce among themselves, homosexuals must [[Homosexual recruitment|recruit]] the young; conversely, they can be converted back to heterosexuality through [[reparative therapy]] or [[religious conversion]].
*Homosexuality is a [[mental disorder]] or social ill, therefore, it can be cured or stamped out. If it is not eradicated, it will lead to [[social disintegration]] and [[societal collapse]]. (Until fairly recently, many psychologists considered [[lesbianism]] and male homosexuality as being forms of [[sexual deviance]].)
*Because of their lifestyle, homosexuals do not have families with children, so they undermine the survival of the human race. ([[natalism]])

== Heterosexism as discrimination ==
{{Discrimination}}
=== Explicit or open discrimination ===

This type of heterosexism includes [[anti-gay]] laws, [[harassment]] based on sexual orientation or perceived sexual orientation; negative [[stereotyping]], discriminatory language and [[discourse]], and other forms of discrimination against gay men, lesbians, and bisexuals such as:

*[[Hate speech]], [[terms of disparagement]], [[hate mail]], [[death threats]], [[Murder Music]]
*Negative portrayals or stereotypes of gay men, lesbians, and bisexuals solely as villains, the butt of jokes, objects of curiosity. This can occur on television and in movies as well as in jokes between friends or among co-workers.
*Using the [[gay panic defense]] in [[assault]] or [[murder]] cases.
*[[Sodomy law]]s when enforced almost exclusively against consenting, adult, [[same-sex]] partners. ''See also: [[Bowers v. Hardwick]] and [[Lawrence v. Texas]]''
*In some countries where [[Homosexuality laws of the world|homosexuality is criminalized]], such as [[Sudan]], [[Mauritania]], [[Saudi Arabia]], and the [[Islamic Republic]] of [[Iran]], offenders may receive the maximum sentence of [[capital punishment]]. ''See also: [[Paragraph 175]]''
*Discrepancies in [[Age of consent#Homosexual and heterosexual age discrepancies in law|age of consent]] laws in which legal sexual activity between members of the same sex is set at a higher age than that for opposite-sex partners. ''See also: [[Chris Morris (activist)|Morris v. The United Kingdom]]''
*“[[Marriage Protection Act|marriage protection act]]s” or “[[Defense of Marriage Act|defense of marriage act]]s” that [[ban (law)|Ban]] [[same-sex marriage]];
*[[Adoption]] bans against either same-sex couples or gay, lesbian, or bisexual individuals. ''See also: [[LGBT adoption]]''
*Creating parallel institutions to marriage, such [[civil union]]s, or opening them to gay men, lesbians, and bisexuals only as stopgap measures to avoid granting same-sex couples the privileges, protection, respect, and [[symbolism]] that only a legally and socially accepted marriage can confer.
*Proposals or legislation to prohibit [[equal rights]] protection against discrimination based on sexual orientation or perceived sexual orientation, particularly with regard to [[health care]], [[housing]], and [[employment]].
*Banning gay men, lesbians, and bisexuals from serving in the [[armed force]]s or working in the [[education]] field; this can include policies such as the [[Military of the United States|U.S. military]]’s “[[Don't ask, don't tell]]” policy or [[Lech Kaczyński]] and the [[Polish government]]’s stance to exclude gay men and lesbians from entering the teaching profession. ''See also: [[LGBT rights in Poland]]''
*Organized opposition to equal rights for gay men, lesbians, bisexuals ([[Gay rights|LGBT rights]]) and same-sex couples
*Referring to a suspected criminal's homosexuality or bisexuality when in analogous situations there is no mention of a suspect's heterosexuality.

=== Implicit or hidden discrimination ===
This form of heterosexism operates through invisibility, underrepresentation, and [http://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/erasure erasure]. It includes:

*Lack of portraying LGBT people in advertising to the general public;
*[[Censorship]] of LGBT characters, themes, and issues in works of art, literature, entertainment;
*Exclusion of historical and political figures’ and celebrities’ homosexuality or bisexuality, on equal terms with homosexuality; their portrayal as heterosexuals;
*Complete avoidance of mentioning these people and their positive contributions particularly in [[news media]];
*In the context of sex education or professional advice, referring only to opposite-sex partners when discussing female or male [[sexual attraction]] and activity;
*Total silence on [[Portal:LGBT|LGBT issues]] at school or work or absence of their discussion in a positive light;
*Implementation and use of [[content-control software]] (censorware) to filter out information and websites that focus on LGBT topics and issues;
*[[Postal censorship]] and border control or customs seizure of publications deemed [[obscene]] solely on the basis of them containing LGBT-related material even when they contain no [[erotic]] or [[pornographic]] material; ''see also [[Little Sister's Book and Art Emporium]]''
*Work environments that tacitly require gay men, lesbians, and bisexuals not to reveal their sexual orientation via discussion of their relationship status while heterosexuals can discuss their relationships and [[marital status]] freely;
*At public libraries or bookstores: rejection, removal or destruction of LGBT-themed books, films, and posters;
*Refusal to include [[LGBT parenting|LGBT parented]] families at school events or to represent such family diversity in school curricula; ''see also [[anti-bias curriculum]]'';
*Coercive or forced [[sex reassignment surgery]] on gay men and lesbians. For example, many [[Iranian people|Iranian]] gay men and lesbians must turn to sex-reassignment surgery as a strategy to avoid [[persecution]] and a death sentence; [[transsexuality]] and being [[transgender]] are not outright forbidden in the [[Qu'ran]]. ''See also: [[LGBT rights in Iran]]''

== Effects of heterosexism ==

The main effect of heterosexism is the [[marginalization]] of gay men, lesbians, and bisexuals within society. Heterosexism has led to [[social stigma|stigmatization]] and [[persecution]] of not only these people but also those of other sexual diversity such as transgender, and transsexual people. Along with [[violence against LGBT people]], [[homophobia]], [[lesbophobia]], and [[Homophobia#Internalized homophobia|internalized homophobia]], heterosexism continues to be a significant social reality that compels people to conceal their homosexual or bisexual orientation, or metaphorically, to remain in [[the closet]] in an effort to [[Passing (sexual orientation)|pass]] for heterosexual.

== References ==
{{reflist}}

== See also ==

* [[Norm (sociology)]] | [[Heteronormativity]] | [[Compulsory Heterosexuality and Lesbian Existence|Compulsory heterosexuality]]
* [[Diversity training]]
* [[Harassment#Categories|Harassment (categories and types)]]
* [[Homophobia]]
* [[Lesbophobia]]
* [[Human sexuality]] | [[Sociobiology]]
* [[LGBT stereotypes]] | [[AIDS#Stigma|AIDS/HIV stigma (against homosexuals and bisexuals)]] | [[Tokenism]]
* [[Second-class citizen]] | [[Jim Crow laws]]
* [[Gay rights opposition]] | [[Slogans of anti-gay ideology]]
* [[Supremacism]]

[[Category:Sexual orientation and society]]
[[Category:LGBT civil rights]]
[[Category:Sexual and gender prejudices]]
[[Category:Homophobia]]
[[Category:Gender studies]]
[[Category:Queer theory]]
[[Category:Transgender]]

[[br:Arallrevouriezh]]
[[bg:Хетеросексизъм]]
[[da:Heterosexisme]]
[[de:Heterosexismus]]
[[el:Ετεροσεξισμός]]
[[es:Heterosexismo]]
[[fr:Hétérosexisme]]
[[mk:Хетеросексизам]]
[[no:Heterosexisme]]
[[pt:Heterossexismo]]
[[ro:Heterosexism]]
[[ru:Гетеросексизм]]
[[sr:Хетеросексизам]]
[[tr:Heteroseksizm]]
[[zh:异性恋主义]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>