<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20040606091602|7050660" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="113664" pageid="113664" ns="0" title="Class discrimination"><revisions><rev timestamp="2004-11-02T06:37:19Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[Classism]] can be a term formed by analogy with [[racism]] is any form of [[prejudice]] or [[oppression]] against people who are in, or who are perceived as being like those who are in, a lower [[social class]] (especially in the form of lower [[socioeconomic status]]) within a [[class society]]. Classism also refers to the ideology behind class conscious peoples. Often times [[anarchists]] and [[communists]] refer to themselves as classists.

The classism carried by the ruling class is that of prejudice, and is often seeded in [[capitalists]]. Capitalists regard members of the working class to be lower than those people who are members of the ruling class. Classism is also found consistently in most areas of bourgeois culture. 

Classism in it's revolutionary context is an open prejudice against members of the ruling class by members of the working class. Anarchist classism is rooted in the rejection of all forms of the ruling class, including communist parties. Communist classists on the other hand, refer to themselves as the means to abolish class, and exempt from classist analysis.</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>