<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20210929231740|1047267598" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="113664" pageid="113664" ns="0" title="Class discrimination"><revisions><rev timestamp="2021-10-04T20:51:13Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{redirect-distinguish|Classism|Classicism}}
{{short description|Discrimination on the basis of social class}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2020}}
{{Discrimination sidebar}}'''Class discrimination''', also known as '''classism''', is [[prejudice]] or [[discrimination]] on the basis of [[social class]]. It includes individual attitudes, behaviors, systems of policies and practices that are set up to benefit the [[upper class]] at the expense of the [[Under class|lower class]].&lt;ref name=Kadi&gt;{{cite book|last=Kadi|first=Joanna|title=Thinking Class|publisher=[[South End Press]]|year=1996|url=https://archive.org/details/thinkingclassske00kadi|url-access=registration|isbn=0-89608-548-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Social class refers to the grouping of individuals in a hierarchy based on wealth, income, education, occupation, and social network.

== History ==
Class structures existed in a somewhat simplified form in pre-agricultural societies, but it has evolved into a more complex and established structure following the establishment of permanent agriculture-based civilizations with a food surplus.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=A Brief History of the World Course No. 8080 [Audio CD]|author=Peter N. Stearns (Narrator)|publisher=The Teaching Company|asin=B000W595CC}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Classism started to be practiced around the 18th century.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Young|first1=Serinity|title=Encyclopedia of Women and World Religion|date=1999|publisher=Macmillan|isbn=0028648609|page=181|author2=Katie Cannon|editor=Serinity Young|format=Print|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=RYgYAAAAIAAJ}}&lt;/ref&gt; Segregation into classes was accomplished through observable traits (such as race or profession) that were accorded varying status and privileges. Feudal classification systems might include merchant, serf, peasant, warrior, priestly, and noble classes. Rankings were far from invariant with the merchant class in Europe outranking the peasantry while merchants were explicitly inferior to peasants during the Tokugawa Shogunate in Japan. Modern classism, with less rigid class structures, is harder to identify. In a professional association posting, psychologist Thomas Fuller-Rowell states, "Experiences of [class] discrimination are often subtle rather than blatant, and the exact reason for unfair treatment is often not clear to the victim."{{r|APS}}

==Intersections with other systems of oppression==
Socioeconomic, racial/ethnic and gender inequalities in academic achievement have been widely reported in the United States, but how these three axes of inequality intersect to determine academic and non-academic outcomes among school-aged children is not well understood.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Bécares|first1=Laia|last2=Priest|first2=Naomi|date=27 October 2015|title=Understanding the Influence of Race/Ethnicity, Gender, and Class on Inequalities in Academic and Non-Academic Outcomes among Eighth-Grade Students: Findings from an Intersectionality Approach|journal=PLOS ONE|volume=10|issue=10|pages=e0141363|doi=10.1371/journal.pone.0141363|issn=1932-6203|pmc=4624767|pmid=26505623|doi-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Institutional versus personal classism ==
The term classism can refer to personal prejudice against lower classes as well as to institutional classism, just as the term [[racism]] can refer either strictly to personal prejudice or to [[institutional racism]]. The latter has been defined as "the ways in which conscious or unconscious classism is manifest in the various institutions of our society".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://gustavus.edu/reslife/documents/Classism.doc|title=Classism Definitions|website=gustavus.edu|access-date=18 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As with social classes, the difference in social status between people determines how they behave toward each other and the prejudices they likely hold toward each other. People of higher status do not generally mix with lower-status people and often are able to control other people's activities by influencing laws and social standards.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.encyclopedia.com/social-sciences/news-wires-white-papers-and-books/social-class-prejudice|title=Social Class Prejudice|website=Encyclopedia.com|access-date=2019-01-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The term "interpersonal" is sometimes used in place of "personal" as in "institutional classism (versus) interpersonal classism"&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|last1=Langhout|first1=Regina Day|title=Assessing Classism in Academic Settings|date=Winter 2007|url=https://muse.jhu.edu/login?auth=0&amp;type=summary&amp;url=/journals/review_of_higher_education/v030/30.2langhout.html|last2=Rosselli|last3=Feinstein|first2=Francine|first3=Jonathan|journal=The Review of Higher Education|volume=30|issue=2|pages=145–184|doi=10.1353/rhe.2006.0073|s2cid=144691197}}&lt;/ref&gt; and terms such as "attitude" or "attitudinal" may replace "interpersonal" as contrasting with institutional classism as in the Association of Magazine Media's definition of classism as "any attitude or institutional practice which subordinates people due to income, occupation, education and/or their economic condition".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.magazine.org/diversity/managing/defining/8478.aspx "Glossary"].{{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120309015508/http://www.magazine.org/diversity/managing/defining/8478.aspx|date=9 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Classism is also sometimes broken down into more than two categories as in "personal, institutional and cultural" classism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|editor1-last=Adams|editor1-first=Maurianne|editor2-last=Bell|editor2-first=Lee Anne|editor3-last=Griffin|editor3-first=Pat|title=Teaching for Diversity and Social Justice|edition=2nd|publisher=Routledge|year=2007|page=317|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=OI-5SlHR9PMC|isbn=978-0-415-95199-9}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is common knowledge in sociolinguistics that metasocial language abounds in lower registers, thus the slang for various classes or racial castes.

In the [[United Arab Emirates|UAE]], [[Western world|Western]] workers and local nationals are given better treatment or are preferred.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.thenational.ae/uae/western-workers-favoured-in-uae-survey-respondents-say-1.21895|title='Western workers favoured in UAE', survey respondents say|website=The National|language=en|access-date=2019-11-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Media representation ==
Class discrimination can be seen in many different forms of media such as television shows, films and social media. Classism is also systemic,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Gamble |first1=Matt |title=Classism: America's Overlooked Problem |url=https://www.therutgersreview.com/2018/02/10/classism-americas-overlooked-problem/ |website=The Rutgers Review |date=10 February 2018 |access-date=21 March 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; and its implications can go unnoticed in the media that is consumed by society. Class discrimination in the media displays the knowledge of what people feel and think about classism. When seeing class discrimination in films and television shows, people are influenced and believe that is how things are in real life, for whatever class is being displayed. Children can be exposed to class discrimination through movies, with a large pool of high-grossing G-rated movies portraying classism in various contexts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Streib |first1=Jessi |title=Class Inequality in Children's Movies |url=https://classism.org/class-inequality-in-childrens-movies/ |website=Class Action |date=18 April 2016 |access-date=21 March 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; Children may develop biases at a young age that shape their beliefs throughout their lifetime, which would demonstrate the issues with class discrimination being prevalent in the media.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Suttie |first1=Jill |title=How Adults Communicate Bias to Children |url=https://greatergood.berkeley.edu/article/item/how_adults_communicate_bias_to_children |access-date=21 March 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; Media is a big influence on the world today, with that something such as classism is can be seen in many different lights. Media plays an important role in how certain groups of people are perceived, which can make certain biases stronger.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Burke |first1=Krista |title=Media Portrayal of Individuals in the Lower Class |url=https://digitalcommons.calpoly.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?referer=https://www.google.com/&amp;httpsredir=1&amp;article=1162&amp;context=comssp |website=Digital Commons |access-date=21 March 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; Usually, the lower income people are displayed in the media as dirty, lack of education and manners and homeless.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://web.stanford.edu/class/e297c/poverty_prejudice/mediarace/portrayal.htm|title=Portrayal of Minorities in the Film, Media and Entertainment Industries|website=web.stanford.edu|access-date=18 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; People can use the media to learn more about different social classes&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.criticalmediaproject.org/cml/topicbackground/race-ethnicity/|title=Race &amp; Ethnicity|website=criticalmediaproject.org|access-date=18 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; or use the media, such as social media to influence others on what they believe.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://blogs.harvard.edu/andresmh/2013/04/classism-accountability-and-social-media/|title=Classism, Accountability, and Social Media|website=blogs.harvard.edu|access-date=18 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; In some cases, people who are in a social class that is portrayed negatively by the media can be affected in school and social life as "[t]eenagers who grew up in poverty reported higher levels of discrimination, and the poorer the teens were, the more they experienced discrimination".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.med.wisc.edu/news-events/social-class-discrimination-contributes-to-poorer-health/38020|title=Social-class discrimination contributes to poorer health|website=wisc.edu|access-date=18 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Legislation ==
The [[European Convention on Human Rights]], in Article 14, contains protections against social class ("social origin") discrimination.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.echr.coe.int/documents/convention_eng.pdf European Convention on Human Rights as amended by Protocols Nos. 11, 14 and 15, supplemented by Protocols Nos. 1, 4, 6, 7, 12, 13 and 16]&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
{{columns-list|colwidth=22em|
* [[Apartheid]]
* [[Caste system]]
* [[Class conflict]]
* [[Class consciousness]]
* [[Debtors' prison]]
* [[Economic inequality]]
* [[Economic stratification]]
* [[Elitism]]
* [[Legacy preferences]]
* [[Marxism]]
* [[Populism]]
* [[Racial discrimination]]
* [[Rankism]]
* [[Social inequality]]
* [[Forced adoption]]
*[[Baby Scoop Era]]

}}

== References ==
{{reflist|refs=
&lt;ref name=APS&gt;
  {{cite news
  | title = Social-Class Discrimination Contributes to Poorer Health
  | newspaper = Association of Psychological Science
  | date = 18 June 2012
  | url = https://www.psychologicalscience.org/news/releases/social-class-discrimination-contributes-to-poorer-health.html
  | access-date = 10 December 2019
  }}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

== Further reading ==
* Bowker, Geoffrey C., and Susan Leigh Star. ''Sorting Things Out: Classification and Its Consequences''. MIT Press, 1999.
* {{cite web |last=Capuano |first=Angelo |url=http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/journals/UNSWLawJl/2016/3.pdf |title=Giving Meaning to 'Social Origin' in International Labour Organization ('ILO') Conventions, the Fair Work Act 2009 (Cth) and the Australian Human Rights Commission Act 1986 (Cth): 'Class' Discrimination and Its Relevance to the Australian Context}} (2016) 39(1) [[University of New South Wales Law Journal]] 84. {{SSRN|2771056}}
* ''A People's History of the United States'' by [[Howard Zinn]].
* Hill, Marcia, and Esther Rothblum. Classism and Feminist Therapy: Counting Costs. New York: Haworth Press, 1996.
* [[bell hooks|hooks, bell]]. Where we stand: class matters. New York &amp; London: Routledge, 2000.
* Gans, Herbert. The War Against the Poor, 1996.
* Homan, Jacqueline S. Classism For Dimwits. Pennsylvania: Elf Books, 2007/2009.
* Packard, Vance. Status Seekers, 1959.
* Beegle, Donna M. See Poverty - Be the Difference, 2009.
* [[Betsy Leondar-Wright|Leondar-Wright, Betsy]].  Class Matters: Cross-Class Alliance Building for Middle-Class Activists: New Society Publishers, 2005.

==External links==
{{Wiktionary|Class discrimination}}
{{wikiquote}}
{{Commons category}}
*[https://www.pbs.org/peoplelikeus/about/index.html "People Like Us"] at [[PBS]]
*[http://www.classism.org Class Action]

{{Discrimination}}
{{Social class}}

[[Category:Class discrimination| ]]
[[Category:Political terminology]]
[[Category:Social classes]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>