<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20121024222231|519651947" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="113664" pageid="113664" ns="0" title="Class discrimination"><revisions><rev timestamp="2012-10-24T22:22:36Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{distinguish|Classicism}}
{{Discrimination sidebar}}
'''Classism''' is [[prejudice]] or [[discrimination]] on the basis of [[social class]]. It includes individual attitudes and behaviors, systems of policies and practices that are set up to benefit the upper classes at the expense of the lower classes.&lt;ref name=Kadi&gt;{{cite book
  | last = Kadi
  | first = Joanna
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | title = Thinking Class
  | publisher = [[South End Press]]
  | year = 1996
  | location = U.S.
  | pages =
  | url =
  | doi =
  | id =
  | isbn = 0-89608-548-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; It can also include attitudes and behavior of prejudice and discrimination by members of the lower class to members of the higher class.

==Institutional versus personal classism==

The term classism can refer to personal prejudice against 'lower' classes as well as to institutional classism, just as the term [[racism]] can refer  either strictly to personal bigotry or to [[institutional racism]]. The former has been defined as "the ways in which conscious or unconscious classism is manifest in the various institutions of our society."&lt;ref&gt;[https://gustavus.edu/reslife/documents/Classism.doc Classism Definitions]&lt;/ref&gt;  Economics, education, health outcomes, fashion, capitalism and music are inherently designed to favor people who have more money/wealth over those who do not have money or wealth.

The term "interpersonal" is sometimes used in place of "personal" as in, "institutional classism (versus) interpersonal classism.",&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation
  | last=Langhout
  | first=Regina Day
  | last2=Rosselli
  | first2=Francine
  | last3=Feinstein
  | first3=Jonathan
  | author-link=Oliver Cowdery
  | title=Assessing Classism in Academic Settings
  | newspaper=The Review of Higher Education
  | volume=30
  | issue=2
  | pages=145–184  | year=2007 winter
  | date=October 1835
  | url=http://muse.jhu.edu/login?uri=/journals/review_of_higher_education/v030/30.2langhout.html  }}&lt;/ref&gt; and terms such as "attitude" or "attitudinal" may replaced "interpersonal" as contrasting with institutional classism, as in the Association of Magazine Media's definition of classism as "any ''attitude or institutional practice'' which subordinates people due to income, occupation, education and/or their economic condition."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.magazine.org/diversity/managing/defining/8478.aspx Glossary]&lt;/ref&gt;

Classism is also sometimes broken down into more than two categories, as in "personal, institutional and cultural" classism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
|editor1-last=  Adams
|editor1-first= Maurianne
|editor2-last= Bell
|editor2-first= Lee Anne
|editor3-last= Griffin
|editor3-first= Pat
|title= Teaching for Diversity and Social Justice
|edition=Second
|publisher= Routledge
|year= 2007
|page=317
|url= http://books.google.com/books?id=OI-5SlHR9PMC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;source=gbs_ge_summary_r&amp;cad=0#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false
|isbn= 978-0-415-95199-9}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Terms associated with personal or attitudinal classism include "[[white trash]]",  "[[William J. H. Boetcker|little men]]" or "little people," "trailer trash,", "the [[unwashed masses]]", "moochers," and "[[bludger]]s". In earlier historical periods, classist terms and phrases as [[Hoi_polloi#Appearances_in_the_nineteenth_century|''hoi polloi'' or plebs]], which are "derogatory of the lower classes," were  more commonly used than they are today.

==Accusations of classism==
There is disagreement{{By whom|date=June 2011}} over what degree modern industrialized societies are [[economic stratification|economically stratified]] into discernible classes.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}} There is also often disagreement over matters of understanding, such as whether negative treatment is due to prejudice against members of certain classes, or whether the behavior is a rational reaction to actions of the person being so treated, or due to racial, ethnic, sexual, or other identity.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

People who generally tend to find charges of classism against 'lower' classes to be unfounded or unreasonably harsh often characterize the perceived prejudice as expressive of classist [[class envy]]. Those who argue classism is especially pervasive or fundamental to the society that they live in often identify classism as the expression of systematic economic [[exploitation]] by the 'higher' classes, and may connect it with an explicit notion of [[class conflict|class warfare]].{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}} However, any particular accusation of classism does not, ''as such'', presuppose any such claim, just as people may agree on examples of overt [[racism]], while disagreeing intensely over how widespread or deep-seated [[racist]] attitudes are in their society.

==See also==
*[[Caste system]]
*[[Class conflict]]
*[[Elitism]]
*[[Social inequality]]
*[[Economic inequality]]
*[[Economic stratification]]
*[[Class Consciousness]]
*[[Rankism]]
*[[Marxism]]

==Further reading==
*''[[A People's History of the United States]]'' by [[Howard Zinn]]
*Hill, Marcia, and Esther Rothblum. Classism and Feminist Therapy : Counting Costs. New York: Haworth Press, 1996.
*[[Bell hooks|hooks, bell]]. where we stand : class matters. new york &amp; london: routledge, 2000.
*Gans, Herbert. The War Against the Poor, 1996
*Homan, Jacqueline S. Classism For Dimwits. Pennsylvania: Elf Books, 2007,2009
*Packard, Vance. Status Seekers. 1959
*Beegle, Donna M. See Poverty - Be the Difference. 2001
*Carrier, Jerry The Making of the Slave Class Algora Publishing 2010
*[[Betsy Leondar-Wright|Leondar-Wright, Betsy]].  Class Matters: Cross-Class Alliance Building for Middle-Class Activists: New Society Publishers, 2005

==External links==
* [http://www.pbs.org/peoplelikeus/about/index.html]"People Like Us" Web site at PBS
* [http://www.classism.org Class Action] - [[website]]
* [http://www.dickinson.edu/~barone/ExtendClassRGC.PDF „Extending Our Analysis of Class Oppression“] - [[PDF]] document
* [http://users.dickinson.edu/~barone/ClassFoundations.PDF "Foundations of Class and Classism. 2002"] - [[PDF]] by Chuck Barone
*[http://www.inequality.org Inequality.org] Compendium of statistics, news, and opinions on inequality in the U.S.
*[http://www.classmatters.org Class Matters]
*[http://www.classism.org/blog] "Classism Exposed"

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{Discrimination}}

[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Political terms]]
[[Category:Social classes]]

[[ca:Classisme]]
[[de:Klassismus]]
[[es:Clasismo]]
[[it:Classismo]]
[[fi:Luokkasyrjintä]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>