<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20071105161546|169397795" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="597792" pageid="597792" ns="0" title="Sex segregation"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-11-07T03:49:16Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Discrimination2}}
'''Sex segregation''' is the separation, or [[Ethnic segregation|segregation]], of people according to [[sex]] or [[gender]]. [[Toilet#Public toilets|Public bathroom]]s, public [[shower]]s, [[dorm]]itories, changing rooms, prisons and other areas are often sex segregated. Sometimes there are separate hours or separate facilities in public [[sauna]]s.  Some religious buildings have separate entrances and worship areas for men and women. Some trains have designated [[women-only passenger car]]s.

Men and women also tend to work in different occupations; for example, more than 90% of [[nurse]]s in the United States are women. This is referred to as occupational segregation.

In education, entire schools might consist of a student body of only one gender.  In co-ed schools sometimes certain classes, such as [[sex education]], are sex segregated.  

The term '''gender apartheid''' (or '''sexual apartheid''') is a derogatory term applied to segregation of people by gender, implying that it is [[sexual discrimination]].  Gender segregation is a controversial policy, with the strongest critics contending that in most or all circumstances it is a violation of human rights, and strong supporters holding that it is necessary to maintain decency, sacredness, modesty, or the family unit.

== In Judaism ==
In traditional [[Judaism|Jewish]] [[synagogue]]s, the females' section is separated from the males' section by a wall or curtain called a [[mechitza]].&lt;ref name="separation"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jewfaq.org/shul.htm|title=Synagogues, Shuls and Temples|work=jewfaq.org|accessdate=2007-02-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Israel there are a few "modesty buses", serving [[Haredi|ultra-orthodox]] Jewish neighbourhoods, which are segregated by sex, with men in front and women in the back of the bus.&lt;ref&gt;Katya Alder, [http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/6584661.stm "Israel's 'modesty buses' draw fire"], ''[[BBC News]]'', [[24 April]] [[2007]]&lt;/ref&gt;

== In Islam ==
{{main|Sex segregation in Islam}}

[[Islam]] discourages social interaction between men and women but not all interaction between men and women. This is shown in the example of [[Khadija]], who employed [[Muhammad]] and met with him to conduct trade before they were married, and in the example set by the other [[Muhammad's marriages|wives of Muhammad]], who taught and counselled the men and women of [[Medina]].  

The textual basis for insisting on total segregation of the sexes is the [[hadith]] on ''[[zina]]'' (fornication and [[adultery]]) of the limbs narrated from [[Ibn Mas`ud]] by [[Imam Ahmad]] in his Musnad with a strong chain: "The two eyes commit ''zina'', the two hands commit ''zina'', the two feet commit ''zina'', and the genitals commit ''zina''." Another wording with a passable chain in the Musnad includes the tongue and specifies in the end: "Then the genitals actualize it or belly it.". However, it does not necessarily follow that this hadith can be used as justification for saying "Therefore, according to [[Shari'ah]], to look, speak, listen, etc. to any [[Ghayr Mahram]] (women you are not related to or married to) except at the time of extreme necessity is Haraam and impermissible."

Sex segregation is strictly enforced in some Islamic countries.

==In Christianity==
The terms "gender apartheid" and "sexual apartheid" have also been used to describe differential treatment of women in institutions such as the [[Church of England]]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.guardian.co.uk/uk_news/story/0,3604,580180,00.html&lt;/ref&gt; or the [[Roman Catholic Church]]. See, for example, Patricia Budd Kepler in her 1978 ''Theology Today'' article "Women Clergy and the Cultural Order".&lt;ref&gt;http://theologytoday.ptsem.edu/jan1978/v34-4-article6.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

In churches, men and women sit together in most [[Western Catholic]] parishes, while in many [[Eastern Catholic]] and [[Eastern Orthodox]] parishes, there is a separation of genders. This is not as common in the New World as it is in the Old World, especially in more rural areas where men will sit on the right (near Christ's icon) and women will sit on the left (near Mary's icon).

==In Education==
In Louisiana following the forced race integration of public schools, the schools were segregated by sex. St. Bernard and Jefferson Parishes (surrounding New Orleans) instituted sex segregation to prevent black and white students from dating.  The last year of sex segregation in Jefferson Parish public schools was 1975.

== See also ==
* [[Sexism]]
* [[Criticism of Islam]]
*[[Golden Needle Sewing School]]

==References==
&lt;div class="references-small"&gt;
&lt;references /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

==External links==
*[http://www.rawa.org/index.php RAWA - Revolutionary Association of the Women of Afghanistan. Documenting Taliban atrocities against women]
*[http://www.arches.uga.edu/~haneydaw/twwh/apartheid.html Gender Apartheid]  an essay on the topic from Third World Women's Health
*[http://www.helpafghanwomen.com/Global_Petition_Flyer.pdf Stop Gender Apartheid in Afghanistan] an anti-Taliban pamphlet from the [[Feminist Majority Foundation]]
*[http://www.womensenews.org/article.cfm/dyn/aid/2212/context/ourdailylives Taking the Gender Apartheid Tour in Saudi Arabia]
*[http://www.petertatchell.net/direct%20action/sexual%20apartheid.htm Direct Action is Necessary Because Homophobia is Sexual Apartheid] by Peter Tatchell, [[October 7]] [[1994]]
*[http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn/A15193-2001Dec21?language=printer  Saudi Arabia's Apartheid] by Colbert King, ''[[Washington Post]]'' [[December 22]] [[2001]]
*[http://www.wpiran.org/Against%20Sexual%20Apartheid.htm Against Sexual Apartheid in Iran] Interview with [[Azar Majedi]]
*[http://www.findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_hb3327/is_199409/ai_n8033813 Sexual Apartheid in Iran] by Mahin Hassibi
*[http://www.guardian.co.uk/uk_news/story/0,3604,580180,00.html Church persists with sexual apartheid, say women priests] ''The Guardian'', [[October 25]] [[2001]]

{{Types of Segregation}}

[[Category:Sexism]]
[[Category:Islam-related controversies]]
[[Category:Women's rights in religious movements]]
[[Category:Gender]]
[[Category:Sexuality and society]]
[[Category:Apartheid]]

[[cs:Segregace]]
[[de:Segregation]]
[[es:Segregación]]
[[he:הפרדת עיסוקים מגדרית]]
[[ru:Сегрегация]]
[[sr:Сегрегација]]
[[sv:Segregation]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>