<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20111117034027|461057813" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="597792" pageid="597792" ns="0" title="Sex segregation"><revisions><rev timestamp="2011-11-17T04:13:27Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Discrimination sidebar}}
{{Refimprove|date=October 2008}}
{{Globalize|date=April 2010}}
'''Sex segregation''' is the separation of people according to their [[sex]].

The term '''[[gender apartheid]]''' (or '''sexual apartheid''') also has been applied to segregation of people by gender,&lt;ref name=clergy&gt;{{Cite news|title=Women clergy accuse Church of sexual apartheid|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/uk_news/story/0,3604,580180,00.html |newspaper=The Guardian |publisher=Guardian Unlimited | location=London | first=Stephen | last=Bates | date=2001-10-25 | accessdate=2010-05-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; implying that it is [[sexual discrimination]].&lt;ref name=Otto&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Otto D |title=Holding Up half the Sky, But For Whose Benefit: A Critical Analysis of the Fourth World Conference on Women |journal=Austl Feminist LJ. |month= |year=1996 |volume=7 |issue= |pages= |url=http://heinonlinebackup.com/hol-cgi-bin/get_pdf.cgi?handle=hein.journals/afemlj6&amp;section=6 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In some circumstances, gender segregation is a controversial policy, with critics contending that in most or all circumstances it is a violation of [[human rights]], and supporters arguing that it is necessary to maintain [[decency]], [[sacred]]ness, [[modesty]], female [[safety]],&lt;ref name="AI"&gt;[[Amnesty International]] includes segregated toilets among the measures to ensure the safety of girls/boys in schools. ''[http://www.amnestyusa.org/document.php?id=ENGACT770232007&amp;lang=e Six steps to stop violence against schoolgirls]'', Document ACT 77/008/2007, November 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; or the family unit.&lt;ref name=Claussen&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Claussen CL |title=Incorporating Women's Reality into Legal Neutrality in the European Community: The Sex Segregation of Labor and Work-Family Nexus |journal=Law Policy Intern'l Bus. |month= |year=1991 |volume=22 |issue= |pages= |url=http://www.questia.com/PM.qst?a=o&amp;se=gglsc&amp;d=5000143625 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Public facilities==
[[Image:Ladies Only Train.jpg|thumb|left|A sign on a station platform in Osaka, Japan, showing the boarding point for a ladies-only car.]]

In almost all parts of the world, places for activities which involve nudity – for example, showers, toilets, changing rooms – are usually segregated by sex.{{Citation needed|date=April 2010}} There are exceptions to this: [[Nude beach|clothing-optional beaches]] and [[Art school|art classrooms]] for [[figure drawing]] are generally not segregated. [[Sauna]]s and [[Bathing|bath]]s may or may not be, depending on the [[culture]].

The degree of segregation can vary. In some places, separate changing rooms for men and women are the norm, while elsewhere, a single change room with cubicles is normal. With the widespread practice of [[groping]] women in crowded public places (e.g. [[street harassment]] or [[eve teasing]]), some countries have designated [[women-only passenger car]]s or compartments on trains.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news| title =Belarus rail targets 'smelly men' | url =http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/4439735.stm | accessdate = 2008-06-11 | work=BBC News | date=2005-04-13 | first=Tatyana | last=Nechapayka}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="mainichi-disability"&gt;{{Cite news
|title=Visually-impaired want railways to clarify stance on riding in women-only carriages
|url=http://mdn.mainichi-msn.co.jp/national/news/20070405p2a00m0na017000c.html
|publisher=[[Mainichi Shimbun]] |date=2007-04-05 |deadurl=2008-05-26 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Metroreserves&gt;{{cite web|title=Metro reserves compartments for females |url=http://www.telegraphindia.com/1080907/jsp/calcutta/story_9796361.jsp }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In most countries of the world, [[prison]]s are segregated.
Often contact with prisoners of the opposite sex is forbidden or limited to specific moments.
Prison officers often are of the same sex as the inmates.

==Sports==
Organized competitive sports are frequently segregated by gender, especially at higher levels. Where performance is strength-related (such as upper-body weight-lifting), any alternative would see women excluded from the higher levels of competition. A few sports, such as [[equestrianism]] or [[paragliding]], are mixed-gender at all levels. A very few, such as [[Korfball]], specify mixed-gender participation in the rules.

Some sports that do not rely on physical contact, such as [[bowling]] or [[golf]], may have separate sporting events. In archery, though, it is normal for both sexes and all ages to shoot alongside each other: in a handicap tournament they will, in fact, be competing against each other.{{Citation needed|date=April 2010}}

To cater to the religious requirements of various [[faith]]s, and for other preference reasons, sometimes separation is achieved by allocating times or facilities for the exclusive use of one gender, usually of women. This is sometimes done with public [[sauna]]s, [[swimming pool]]s and [[gym]]nasiums{{Citation needed|date=April 2010}}.

Many countries now have laws outlawing discrimination on the basis of sex, and regard the refusal to provide facilities on an equal basis to both men and women as [[sexual discrimination]].

==Education==
{{multiple image
| footer = The decorative doors of PS116 in [[Murray Hill, Manhattan‎]] feature separate entrances for male and female students.
| width = 150
| align = left
| image1 = PS116 boys door.jpg
| alt1 = Boys door to PS116
| image2 = PS116 girls door.jpg
| alt2 = Girls door to PS116
}}
In much of the world education, especially institutional education, was available only to boys until the last few hundred years. In some parts of the world, especially in Europe, when education was made available to girls as well as boys, educational establishments were frequently single-gender, a situation which in some cases exists in the United Kingdom to this day{{Citation needed|date=April 2010}}. Sometimes a reason was historical – an all-male education institution refusing to change. Arguments were made that the presence of the opposite sex would distract students from their studies, as well as allowing for inappropriate conduct.

There have been studies conducted to analyze whether [[single-sex education|single-sex schools]] or [[Mixed-sex education|co-ed schools]] produce better educational outcomes, but each has its advocates and critics.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal| title=Effects of single-sex secondary schools on student achievement and attitudes.
|author=Lee, Valerie E.; Bryk, Anthony S.
|journal=Journal of Educational Psychology|publisher=American Psychological Association |volume= 78|issue=5 |date=October 1986|pages= 381–395}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aftau.org/site/News2?page=NewsArticle&amp;id=6859 "Keep Boys and Girls Together, New Research Suggests"]. Aftau.org (2008-04-11). Retrieved on 2011-06-13.&lt;/ref&gt; Even in co-ed schools, certain classes, such as [[sex education]], are sometimes segregated on the basis of gender{{Citation needed|date=April 2010}}. Some schools decide to segregate students only in core subjects; this is called [[parallel education]]{{Citation needed|date=April 2010}}.

In Louisiana following the forced race integration of public schools, the schools were segregated by sex. St. Bernard and Jefferson Parishes (surrounding New Orleans) instituted sex segregation to reduce the likelihood of black and white students dating.&lt;ref name=Mayeri&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Mayeri S |title= The Strange Career of Jane Crow: Sex Segregation and the Transformation of Anti-Discrimination Discourse |journal=Yale JL Human. |month=Summer |year=2006 |volume=18 |issue= |page=187 |url=https://litigation-essentials.lexisnexis.com/webcd/app?action=DocumentDisplay&amp;crawlid=1&amp;doctype=cite&amp;docid=18+Yale+J.L.+%26+Human.+187&amp;srctype=smi&amp;srcid=3B15&amp;key=7a1233c4c7c9232acd07363052a6b296 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The last year of sex segregation in Jefferson Parish public schools was 1975{{Citation needed|date=April 2010}}.

==Female safety, privacy and sensitivity==
Some sex segregation occurs for reasons of safety. For example a refuge for 'battered mothers or wives' may refuse to admit men, even those who are themselves the victims of domestic violence, both to prevent access by those who might commit or threaten violence to women or because women who have been subjected to abuse by a male might feel threatened by the presence of any man.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/society/2009/apr/05/domestic-violence-charity-funding |publisher=The Guardian|title=Women's refuges told they must admit men | location=London | first=Gaby | last=Hinsliff | date=2009-04-05 | accessdate=2010-05-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; Non-segregated toilets might also be a threat to safety&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.amnestyusa.org/document.php?id=ENGACT770232007&amp;lang=e |publisher=Amnesty International USA|title=Six Steps to Stop Violence Against Schoolgirls }}&lt;/ref&gt; and rights of privacy.  Until the mid-20th century (in the USA), bars, clubs and pubs formerly prohibited women customers from entering, bartenders refused to sell or allow female visitors buying drinks and sitting in their seats. Today that is considered [[sex discrimination]] and has became illegal in western countries. The same was true for public beaches in the [[Victorian Age]] for women to not be publicly seen by other men outside the family (see [[bathing machines]]).

==Religion==
{{Main|Sex segregation and religion}}

===Islam===
{{See|Sex segregation in Islam|Purdah|Awrah}}
[[Islam]] discourages social interaction between male non-relatives and women, and especially between unmarried strange men and women. Sex segregation is strictly enforced in some Islamic countries by [[religious police]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20090621174103/http://www.asianews.it/view.php?l=en&amp;art=5869 SAUDI ARABIA Catholic priest arrested and expelled from Riyadh – Asia News]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/2399885.stm Middle East | Saudi minister rebukes religious police]. Asia News (04/10/2006). Retrieved on 2011-06-13.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the Muslim world, [[Purdah|preventing women from being seen by men]] is closely linked to the concept of [[Namus]].&lt;ref name=book-sch&gt;Werner Schiffauer, "Die Gewalt der Ehre. Erklärungen zu einem deutsch-türkischen Sexualkonflikt." ("The Force of the Honour"), Suhrkamp: Frankfurt am Main, 1983. ISBN 3-518-37394-3.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Dilek Cindoglu pp. 215"&gt;Dilek Cindoglu, "[[Virginity test]]s and [[hymenorrhaphy|artificial virginity]] in modern Turkish medicine," pp. 215–228, in ''Women and sexuality in Muslim societies'', P. Ýlkkaracan (Ed.), Women for Women’s Human Rights, Istanbul, 2000.&lt;/ref&gt; Namus is an [[ethical]] category, a [[virtue]], in [[Middle East]]ern [[Muslim]] [[patriarchal]] character. It is a strongly [[gender]]-specific category of relations within a family described in terms of [[honor]], [[attention]], [[respect]]/respectability, and [[modesty]]. The term is often translated as "honor".&lt;ref name="book-sch"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Dilek Cindoglu pp. 215"/&gt;

Recently, some countries that previously advocated non-segregation developed initiatives favoring gender segregation. E.g. Turkey started, after the AKP came to power, sanctioning non-related men and women holding each others hands.{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}}

===Judaism===
{{See|Tzniut|Yichud|Gender separation in Judaism}}
It is common for [[Orthodox Judaism]], especially of the [[Hasidic]] sect, to maintain gender-specific events, where men and women sit or be present separately among members of the same sex. Orthodox [[Orthodox Judaism|Jewish]] [[synagogue]]s have separate men's and women's sections, typically separated by a wall or curtain called a [[mechitza]].&lt;ref name="separation"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jewfaq.org/shul.htm|title=Synagogues, Shuls and Temples|work=jewfaq.org|accessdate=2007-02-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Israel there are a dozens of buses, serving [[Haredi|ultra-orthodox]] Jewish neighbourhoods of [[Jerusalem]], which are segregated by sex, with males sitting in the front and females sitting in the back of the bus. There are segregated sidewalks in [[Mea Shearim]] and some sex segregated clinics and groceries in Israel.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Katya Alder|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/6584661.stm |title=Israel's 'modesty buses' draw fire|publisher=BBC News|date= 24 April 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.irac.org/userfiles/Excluded,%20For%20God%27s%20Sake%20-%20Report%20on%20Gender%20Segregation%20in%20the%20Public%20Sphere%20in%20Israel.pdf |title=Excluded, For God’s Sake: Gender Segregation in Public Space in Israel}}&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.haaretz.com/weekend/week-s-end/divide-and-rule-1.323075 |title=Divide and Rule|Haaretz|November 5, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ynetnews.com/articles/0,7340,L-4135718,00.html |title=Court: No sex segregation in Mea Shearim| Ynet| October 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Christianity===
In many [[Eastern Catholic]] and [[Eastern Orthodox]] parishes, there is sex segregation.&lt;ref name=Rhodes&gt;{{Cite book|author=Dickemann M |title=The Balkin Sworn Virgin: A Cross-Gendered Female Role In: ''Islamic homosexualities: culture, history, and literature'' |editor=Murray SO, Roscoe W |pages=197–203 |year=1997 |publisher=New York University Press |location=New York |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=hQuHFPKp8L0C&amp;pg=PA197&amp;dq=%22Eastern+Orthodox%22+%22sex+segregation%22 }}&lt;/ref&gt; This is not as common in the New World as it is in the Old World, especially in more rural areas where men will sit on the right (near Christ's icon) and women will sit on the left (near Mary's icon){{Citation needed|date=April 2010}}.

==Segregation by occupation==
{{Main|Occupational sex segregation}}
Some jobs and occupations have been reserved for one gender or the other. This is often considered a form of sex segregation, even though they may not be physically segregated from workers of different genders in other fields. Some jobs have also been predominantly carried out by one gender or the other, and this can be considered sex segregation, even though there are no rules excluding either gender.

===History===
{{See also|Occupational segregation}}
The roles of men and women have been different for most of human history since prehistoric times. In [[hunter-gatherer]] societies, both past and present, hunting has been largely a male preserve while gathering has been a female role. Other roles are often carried out by only one of the genders.&lt;ref name=Shostak&gt;{{Cite book|author=Marjorie Shostak |year=1983 |title=Nisa: The Life and Words of a ǃKung Woman |location=New York |publisher=Vintage Books |page=13 }}&lt;/ref&gt; However differences in roles did not imply disparity of status.&lt;ref name=Kiefer&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.suluarchipelago.com/E20Website2002/default.htm|title=Anthropology E-20|accessdate=2008-03-11 |author=Thomas M. Kiefer |date=Spring 2002 |work=Lecture 8 Subsistence, Ecology and Food production|publisher=Harvard University}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=gawdy&gt;{{Cite book|title=Limited Wants, Unlimited Means: A reader on Hunter-Gatherer Economics and the Environment |author=Johm Gowdy|year=1998 |publisher=Island Press |location=St Louis |isbn=155963555X |page=342 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Historically [[military]] occupations have been exclusively (with few exceptions) reserved to males. This has ceased only in the later twentieth century. Related occupations such as [[police]] have been exclusively male in some countries{{Citation needed|date=April 2010}}.

In occupations where physical strength is a necessity differences in strength between men and women can mean that more men than women are suitable.&lt;ref name=Greenhorn&gt;{{cite web|author=Greenhorn DR, Stevenson JM |title=Gender based biomechanical difference that impact on task performance |year=1995 |url=http://www.cfsanslimites.ca/en/psp/HumanPerformance/pdfs/TrainingPrograms/Chap1/GEN_0006.PDF }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Professional sports]] and [[major league]]s including in the USA remain virtually all-male and in some cases like the [[WNBA]] are absolutely gender-specific participation apart from the [[NBA]] in basketball. {{Citation needed|date=September 2010}}

==See also==
* [[Gender inequality]]
* [[Sexism]]
* [[Occupational sexism]]
* [[Occupational inequality]]
* [[Separatist feminism]]
* [[Women and children first (saying)]]
* [[Religion and sex segregation]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==
* [http://www.rawa.org/index.php RAWA – Revolutionary Association of the Women of Afghanistan. Documenting Taliban atrocities against women]
* [http://www.arches.uga.edu/~haneydaw/twwh/apartheid.html Gender Apartheid] an essay on the topic from Third World Women's Health
* [http://www.helpafghanwomen.com/Global_Petition_Flyer.pdf Stop Gender Apartheid in Afghanistan] an anti-Taliban pamphlet from the [[Feminist Majority Foundation]]
* [http://www.womensenews.org/article.cfm/dyn/aid/2212/context/ourdailylives Taking the Gender Apartheid Tour in Saudi Arabia]
* [http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn/A15193-2001Dec21?language=printer Saudi Arabia's Apartheid] by Colbert King, ''[[Washington Post]]'' December 22, 2001
* [http://www.wpiran.org/Against%20Sexual%20Apartheid.htm Against Sexual Apartheid in Iran] Interview with [[Azar Majedi]]
* [http://www.findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_hb3327/is_199409/ai_n8033813 Sexual Apartheid in Iran] by Mahin Hassibi

{{Islamism}}
{{Segregation by type}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Sex Segregation}}
[[Category:Sex segregation| ]]
[[Category:Sexism]]
[[Category:Islam-related controversies]]
[[Category:Women's rights in religious movements]]
[[Category:Gender]]
[[Category:Sexuality and society]]
[[Category:Purdah]]
[[Category:Single sex societies]]

[[ca:Segregació per sexes]]
[[de:Geschlechtertrennung]]
[[fa:جدایی جنسیتی]]
[[he:הפרדה מגדרית]]
[[sr:Сегрегација]]
[[sv:Segregation]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>