<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20050919133621|23524668" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="597792" pageid="597792" ns="0" title="Sex segregation"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-10-28T10:46:15Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{cleanup-date|August 2005}}
{{POV}}

[[Image:Pictograms.png|right|Pictogram for public toilets with segregated male and female figures]]

'''Sex segregation''' is the separation, or [[segregation]], of people according to [[sex]] or [[gender]]. [[Toilet#Public_toilets|Public bathroom]]s, public [[shower]]s, [[dorm]]itories, and other areas are often sex segregated. Sometimes there are separate hours or separate facilities in public [[sauna]]s. Entrances and worship areas of some [[Islam]]ic [[mosque]]s and some [[Judaism|Jewish]] [[Synagogue|synagogues]] are sex segregated. [[Sex education]] in [[public school]]s is often sex segregated. [[Private school]]s are sometimes entirely sex segregated or contain an entirely sex segregated student body. Some trains have, apart from mixed-sex cars, also cars for women only, see e.g. [[Josei Senyo Sharyo]].

== Segregation of the sexes in Islam ==

{{SectNPOV}}

[[Islam]] discourages social interaction between men and women but not all interaction between men and women. This is shown in the example of [[Khadija]], who employed [[Muhammad]] and met with him to conduct trade before they were married, and in the example set by the other [[Muhammad's marriages|wives of Muhammad]], who taught and counselled the men and women of [[Medina]].  

The textual basis for insisting on total segregation of the sexes is the [[hadith]] on ''[[zina]]'' (fornication and [[adultery]]) of the limbs narrated from [[Ibn Mas`ud]] by [[Imam Ahmad]] in his Musnad with a strong chain: "The two eyes commit ''zina'', the two hands commit ''zina'', the two feet commit ''zina'', and the genitals commit ''zina''." Another wording with a passable chain in the Musnad includes the tongue and specifies in the end: "Then the genitals actualize it or belly it.". However, it does not necessarily follow that this hadith can be used as justification for saying "Therefore, according to [[Shari'ah]], to look, speak, listen, etc. to any [[Ghayr Mahram]] (women you are not related to or married to) except at the time of extreme necessity is Haraam and impermissible." 

The Qur'anic verses which address the interaction of men and women in the social context include:

:"Tell the believing men to lower their gaze and to be mindful of their chastity: this will be most conducive to their purity - (and,) verily, God is aware of all that they do. And tell the believing women to lower their gaze and to be mindful of their chastity, and not to display their charms (in public) beyond what may (decently) be apparent thereof; hence let them draw their head-coverings over their bosoms.(24:30-31)"

and

:"O Prophet! Tell thy wives and thy daughters, as well as all (other) believing women, that they should draw over themselves some of their outer garments (when in public): this will be more conducive to their being recognized (as decent women) and not annoyed.(33:59)"

Implicit in these verses is the expectation that men and women will be interacting. Muslims are instructed to do so in such a way as to focus on attributes other than the physical, namely the spiritual and intellectual.

The following [[hadith]] indicate that the separation practiced in some Islamic societies today has little precedence in early Islamic practices:

Narrated [[Sahl]],

:When [[Abu Usaid As-Saidi]] got married, he invited the Prophet and his companions. None prepared the food for them and brought it to them but his wife. She soaked some dates in water in a stone pot overnight, and when the Prophet had finished his food, she provided him with the drink.([[Bukhari]], Vol. 7, No. 111)

Narrated [[Anas bin Malik]],

:Once an Ansari woman came to the Prophet and he took her aside and said (to her), "By God, you (Ansar) are the most beloved people to me."(Bukhari, Vol.7, No. 161)

Narrated Ar-Rabi' bint Mu'awidh,

:We used to take part in holy battles with the Prophet by providing the people with water and serving them and bringing the killed and the wounded back to Medina. (Bukhari, Vol.4, No.134) (See also Nos. 131-133 and Muslim, Nos. 4453-4460).

Other hadith also confirm that men and women eating at the same place, and even at the same table, is not ''[[Haraam|haram]]''. 

[[Abu Hurairah]] reported,

:A man came to the Prophet (peace and blessings be upon him) and said; "I am hard pressed by hunger.'' He (peace and blessings be upon him) sent a word to one of his wives who replied: "By Him Who has sent you with the Truth, I have nothing except water.'' Then he sent the same message to another (wife) and received the same reply. He sent this message to all of them (i.e., his wives) and received the same reply. Then he (peace and blessings be upon him) said, "Who will entertain this (man) as guest?'' One of the Ansar said: "O Messenger of Allah, I will.'' So he took him home and said to his wife: "Serve the guest of Messenger of Allah (peace and blessings be upon him).''  

Another narration is, 

:An Ansari man asked his wife: "Have you got anything?'' She answered: "Nothing, except a little food for the children.'' He said: "Keep them busy with something, and when they ask for food put them to sleep. When the guest enters, extinguish the light and give him the impression that we are also eating.'' So they sat down and the guest ate and they passed the night hungry. When he came to the Prophet (peace and blessings be upon him) in the morning, he said to him, "Allah admired what you did with your guest last night.'' (Reported by Al-Bukhari and Muslim). 

Based on this hadith, the scholars concluded that it is part of hospitality that the husband and wife eat with their guest.  

Also, [[Imam Malik]], as reported in Al-Muwatta', was asked about a woman eating with non-mahrem, and he said: "There is no harm in doing this."

Similarly in many Muslim communities today, women are discouraged or prohibited from going to the mosques. Yet, the Prophet specifically admonished the men not to keep their wives from going to the mosques:

[[Ibn Omar]] reported, 

:The Messenger of God said, "Do not prevent the maid-servants of God from going to the mosque."(Muslim, No.888) (See also Nos. 884-891 and Bukhari Vol.1, Nos. 824, 832)

Also, it is clear from the following hadith that the women simply prayed behind the men and were not separated in a separate room or even concealed by a curtain or partition as is practiced in so many mosques today:

Asma' daughter of [[Abu Bakr]] said, 

:I heard the Apostle of God say, "One of you who believes in God and in the Last Day should not raise her head until the men raise their heads (after prostration) lest she should see the private parts of men."(Sunan Abu Dawud, No. 850).

The emphasis in the [[Quran]] and the [[Sunnah]] is thus not on total segregation but on minimizing factors that promote physical attractiveness or may lead to the unlawful. Thus Islam requires believers to:

# Treat one another with respect at all times in all situations.
# Behave modestly.
# Avoid situations of seclusion (khalwa).
# Dress modestly (by covering ones body and (for females) hair).

== See also ==
* [http://www.alislam.org/library/women.html Islam and Women]
* [http://www.alislam.org/library/WOMANINISLAM.pdf Women in Islam (Speech)]
* [[Sexism]]

[[Category:Gender]]
[[Category:Human sexuality]]
[[Category:Sexism]]
[[he:הפרדת עיסוקים מגדרית]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>