<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20070619020702|139114128" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="9412713" pageid="9412713" ns="0" title="Patient dumping"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-09-16T18:28:05Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Homeless dumping''' is the practice of hospital employees or emergency workers releasing [[homeless]] patients on the streets instead of placing them into the custody of a relative or [[homeless shelter|shelter]] or retaining them in a hospital where they may require expensive medical care. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first= |last= |authorlink= |coauthors= |title=Dumped On Skid Row |url=http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2007/05/17/60minutes/main2823079.shtml |work= |publisher=[[60 Minutes]] |date= |accessdate=2007-05-21 }}&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first= |last= |authorlink= |coauthors= |title=L.A. charges hospital in dumping of homeless |url=http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/15752013 |work= |publisher=[[MSNBC]] |date=[[November 16]], [[2006]] |accessdate=2007-05-21 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Cleanup-remainder|date=June 2007}}

==Usage==
*[[Associated Press]]; [[February 9]], [[2007]]; [[Los Angeles]]. A hospital van dropped off a homeless paraplegic man on Skid Row and left him crawling in the street with nothing more than a soiled gown and a broken colostomy bag, police said.... Police said the incident was a case of ''"homeless dumping"'' and were questioning officials from the hospital.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/17062674/ Police probe alleged L.A. homeless dumping: Hospital van reportedly spotted dropping off paraplegic man on [[Skid Row]]], [[MSNBC]] via [[Associated Press]], [[February 9]], [[2007]]&lt;/ref&gt;

*[[Associated Press]], [[October 25]], [[2006]]; [[Los Angeles]]. "L.A. Police Allege ''Homeless Dumping''." Authorities have launched a criminal investigation into suspected dumping of homeless people on Skid Row after police witnessed ambulances leaving five people on a street there during the weekend.

==See also==
*[[Patient dumping]]
*[[Emergency Medical Treatment and Active Labor Act]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

[[Category:Homelessness|Dumping, homeless]]

{{poli-stub}}</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>