<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20241119172603|1258424663" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="637623" pageid="637623" ns="0" title="Glass ceiling"><revisions><rev timestamp="2024-11-19T17:26:58Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|Obstacles keeping a population from achievement}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=September 2023}}
{{about|a metaphor |more information about the barrier that prevents minorities from reaching the upper rungs of the corporate ladder|Gender pay gap}}
[[File:Average earnings of workers by education and sex - 2006.png|thumb|A chart illustrating the [[Gender pay gap|differences in earnings]] between men and women of the same educational level (USA 2006) {{update inline|date=May 2021}}]] {{Discrimination sidebar|state=collapsed}}

A '''glass ceiling''' is a [[metaphor]] usually applied to women, used to represent an [[Discrimination|invisible barrier]] that prevents a given [[demographic]] from rising beyond a certain level in a [[hierarchy]].&lt;ref name="DOL2"&gt;Federal Glass Ceiling Commission. [http://www.dol.gov/oasam/programs/history/reich/reports/ceiling2.pdf ''Solid Investments: Making Full Use of the Nation's Human Capital''.] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20141108194808/http://www.dol.gov/oasam/programs/history/reich/reports/ceiling2.pdf |date=2014-11-08 }} Washington, D.C.: U.S. Department of Labor, November 1995, p. 13-15.&lt;/ref&gt; The metaphor was first used by [[feminism|feminists]] in reference to [[Misogyny|barriers]] in the careers of high-achieving women.&lt;ref name="DOL1"&gt;Federal Glass Ceiling Commission. [http://www.dol.gov/oasam/programs/history/reich/reports/ceiling.pdf ''Good for Business: Making Full Use of the Nation's Human Capital.''] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140810033848/http://www.dol.gov/oasam/programs/history/reich/reports/ceiling.pdf |date=2014-08-10 }} Washington, D.C.: U.S. Department of Labor, March 1995.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Blackwell Encyclopedia of Gender and Sexuality Studies. Vol. 5.|last=Wiley|first=John|publisher=John Wiley and Sons|year=2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was coined by [[Marilyn Loden]] during a speech in 1978.&lt;ref name="auto2"&gt;{{cite book |author=Laermer |first1=Richard |title=Full frontal PR |last2=Prichinello |first2=Michael |publisher=Bloomberg Press |year=2003 |isbn=9781576600993}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="auto1"&gt;{{cite book |url=http://www.ecatalognow.com/article/Marilyn+Loden+On+Feminine+Leadership/766271/73810/article.html |publisher=Pelican Bay Post |title=Marilyn Loden On Feminine Leadership |date=May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Glass ceiling originator"&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www.bbc.com/news/world-42026266 |title=100 Women: 'Why I invented the glass ceiling phrase' |date=2017-12-12 |website=BBC News |access-date=2017-12-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the United States, the concept is sometimes extended to refer to [[racial inequality in the United States|racial inequality]].&lt;ref name="DOL1" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.washingtontimes.com/news/2016/apr/26/hillary-clinton-as-a-white-person-i-have-to-discus/|title=Hillary Clinton: 'As a white person,' I have to discuss racism 'every chance I get'|newspaper=[[The Washington Times]]|access-date=2016-05-02|archive-date=2016-04-27|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160427112228/http://www.washingtontimes.com/news/2016/apr/26/hillary-clinton-as-a-white-person-i-have-to-discus/|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; Minority women in white-majority countries often find the most difficulty in "breaking the glass ceiling" because they lie at the [[Intersectionality|intersection]] of two historically marginalized groups: women and [[people of color]].&lt;ref&gt;"Demarginalising the Intersection of Race and Sex: A Black Feminist Critique of Anti-discrimination Doctrine, Feminist Theory, and Anti-racist Politics" by Kimberlé Crenshaw in ''Framing Intersectionality'', edited by Helma Lutz et al. (Ashgate, 2011).&lt;/ref&gt; East Asian and [[East Asian American]] news outlets have coined the term "[[bamboo ceiling]]" to refer to the obstacles that all East Asian Americans face in advancing their careers.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Breaking the Bamboo Ceiling: Career Strategies for Asians|last=Hyun|first=Jane|publisher=New York: HarperBusiness|year=2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.americanprogress.org/issues/labor/news/2013/04/09/59720/top-10-numbers-that-show-why-pay-equity-matters-to-asian-american-women-and-their-families/|title=Top 10 Numbers that Show Why Pay Equity Matters to Asian American Women and Their Families|website=name|date=9 April 2013|access-date=2016-05-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, a multitude of barriers that [[refugee]]s and [[asylum seeker]]s face in their search for meaningful employment is referred to as the "canvas ceiling".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Lee|first1=Eun Su|last2=Szkudlarek|first2=Betina|last3=Nguyen|first3=Duc Cuong|last4=Nardon|first4=Luciara|date=April 2020|title=Unveiling the Canvas Ceiling : A Multidisciplinary Literature Review of Refugee Employment and Workforce Integration|url=https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/ijmr.12222|journal=International Journal of Management Reviews|language=en|volume=22|issue=2|pages=193–216|doi=10.1111/ijmr.12222|s2cid=216204168|issn=1460-8545}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Within the same concepts of the other terms surrounding the workplace, there are similar terms for restrictions and barriers concerning women and their roles within organizations and how they coincide with their maternal responsibilities. These "Invisible Barriers" function as metaphors to describe the extra circumstances that women go through, usually when they try to advance within areas of their careers and often while they try to advance within their lives outside their work spaces.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Smith|first1=Paul|last2=Caputi|first2=Peter|year=2012|title=A Maze of Metaphors|url=https://ro.uow.edu.au/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=4091&amp;context=hbspapers|journal=Faculty of Health and Behavioral Sciences|volume=27|issue=7 |pages=436–448|via=University of Wollongong Research Online|doi=10.1108/17542411211273432}}&lt;/ref&gt;

"A glass ceiling" represents a blockade that prohibits women from advancing toward the top of a hierarchical [[corporation]]. These women are prevented from getting promoted, especially to the executive rankings within their corporation. In the last twenty years, the women who have become more involved and pertinent in industries and organizations have rarely been in the executive ranks.

== Definition ==
The United States Federal Glass Ceiling Commission (1991–1996)&lt;ref name="20230819CUL"&gt;{{cite web |title=Glass Ceiling Commission (1991–1996) |url=https://ecommons.cornell.edu/handle/1813/72763 |website=[[Cornell University Library]] |access-date=19 August 2023}}&lt;/ref&gt; defined the glass ceiling as "the unseen, yet unbreachable barrier that keeps minorities and women from rising to the upper rungs of the corporate ladder, regardless of their qualifications or achievements."&lt;ref name="DOL2" /&gt;

David Cotter et al. (2001) defined four distinctive characteristics that must be met to conclude that a ''glass ceiling'' exists. A glass ceiling inequality represents:
# "A gender or racial difference that is not explained by other job-relevant characteristics of the employee."
# "A gender or racial difference that is greater at higher levels of an outcome than at lower levels of an outcome."
# "A gender or racial inequality in the chances of advancement into higher levels, not merely the proportions of each gender or race currently at those higher levels."
# "A gender or racial inequality that increases over the course of a career."
Cotter and colleagues found that glass ceilings are correlated strongly with gender, with both white and minority women facing a glass ceiling in the course of their careers. In contrast, the researchers did not find evidence of a glass ceiling for African-American men.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Cotter | first1 = David A. | last2 = Hermsen | first2 = Joan M. | last3 = Ovadia | first3 = Seth | last4 = Vanneman | first4 = Reece | year = 2001 | title = The glass ceiling effect | url = http://www.bsos.umd.edu/socy/vanneman/papers/CotterHOV01.pdf | journal = Social Forces | volume = 80 | issue = 2| pages = 655–81 | doi=10.1353/sof.2001.0091| s2cid = 145245044 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The glass ceiling metaphor has often been used to describe invisible barriers ("glass") through which women can see elite positions but cannot reach them ("ceiling").&lt;ref&gt;*{{cite journal | last1 = Davies-Netzley | first1 = Sally A | year = 1998 | title = Women above the Glass Ceiling: Perceptions on Corporate Mobility and Strategies for Success | jstor = 190289 | journal = Gender and Society | volume = 12 | issue = 3| page = 340 | doi = 10.1177/0891243298012003006 | s2cid = 146681214 }}&lt;/ref&gt; These barriers prevent large numbers of women and ethnic minorities from obtaining and securing the most powerful, prestigious and highest-grossing jobs in the workforce.&lt;ref&gt;Hesse-Biber and Carter 2005, p. 77.&lt;/ref&gt; Moreover, this effect prevents women from filling high-ranking positions and puts them at a disadvantage as potential candidates for advancement.&lt;ref&gt;Nevill, Ginny, Alice Pennicott, Joanna Williams, and Ann Worrall. ''Women in the Workforce: The Effect of Demographic Changes in the 1990s''. London: The Industrial Society, 1990, p. 39, {{ISBN|978-0-85290-655-2}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=US Department of Labor|title=Good for Business: Making Full Use of the Nation's Human Capital|url=http://www.dol.gov/oasam/programs/history/reich/reports/ceiling.htm|publisher=Office of the Secretary|access-date=9 April 2011|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20111028205421/http://www.dol.gov/oasam/programs/history/reich/reports/ceiling.htm|archive-date=28 October 2011|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==
In 1839, French feminist and author [[George Sand]] used a similar phrase, ''une voûte de cristal impénétrable'', in a passage of ''Gabriel'', a never-performed play: "I was a woman; for suddenly my wings collapsed, ether closed in around my head like ''an impenetrable crystal vault'', and I fell...." [emphasis added]. The statement, a description of the heroine's dream of soaring with wings, has been interpreted as a feminine [[Icarus]] tale of a woman who attempts to ascend above her accepted role.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Harlan|first=Elizabeth|title=George Sand|year=2008|publisher=Yale University Press|isbn=978-0-300-13056-0|page=256}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Marilyn Loden]] invented the phrase ''glass ceiling'' during a 1978 speech.&lt;ref name="auto2"/&gt;&lt;ref name="auto1"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Glass ceiling originator"/&gt;

According to the April 3, 2015, ''[[The Wall Street Journal]]'' the term glass ceiling was notably used in 1979 by Maryanne Schriber and Katherine Lawrence at [[Hewlett-Packard]]. Lawrence outlined the concept at the [[National Press Club (United States)|National Press Club]] at the national meeting of the Women's Institute for the Freedom of the Press in Washington DC.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.wsj.com/articles/the-phrase-glass-ceiling-stretches-back-decades-1428089010|title=The Phrase 'Glass Ceiling' Stretches Back Decades|last=Zimmer|first=Ben|newspaper=Wall Street Journal|date=3 April 2015|language=en-US|access-date=2020-01-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ceiling was defined as discriminatory promotion patterns where the written promotional policy is non-discriminatory, but in practice denies promotion to qualified females.

The term was later used in March 1984 by [[Gay Bryant]], who is credited with popularizing the glass ceiling concept.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Frenkiel|first1=Nora|title=The Up-and-Comers: Bryant Takes Aim At The Settlers-In|publisher=AdWeek|date=March 1984}}&lt;/ref&gt; She was the former editor of ''[[Working Woman (magazine)|Working Woman]]'' magazine and was changing jobs to be the editor of ''[[Family Circle]].'' In an ''[[Adweek]]'' article written by Nora Frenkel, Bryant was reported as saying, "Women have reached a certain point—I call it the glass ceiling. They're at the top of middle management and they're stopping and getting stuck. There isn't enough room for all those women at the top. Some are going into business for themselves. Others are going out and raising families."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title=The Up-and-Comers; Bryant Takes Aim At the Settlers-In |last=Frenkiel |first=Nora |journal=Adweek |volume=Special Report |date=March 1984 |publisher=Magazine World}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Cornell&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/research/questionofthemonth/jan05.html |title=Question of the Month: Where did the term 'glass ceiling' originate? |date=January 2005 |author=Catherwood Library reference librarians |publisher=Cornell University, ILR School |access-date=June 30, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Success&gt;{{cite book |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Y71-YCYv-48C&amp;pg=PA9 |pages=9–10 |title=Women in Media Careers: Success Despite the Odds |first1=Lee |last1=Bollinger |first2=Carole |last2=O'Neill |publisher=University Press of America |year=2008 |isbn=978-0-7618-4133-3}}&lt;/ref&gt; Also in 1984, Bryant used the term in a chapter of the book ''The Working Woman Report: Succeeding in Business in the 1980s.'' In the same book, Basia Hellwig used the term in another chapter.&lt;ref name=Cornell /&gt;

In a widely cited article in the ''[[Wall Street Journal]]'' in March 1986 the term was used in the article's title: "The Glass Ceiling: Why Women Can't Seem to Break The Invisible Barrier That Blocks Them From the Top Jobs". The article was written by Carol Hymowitz and Timothy D. Schellhardt. Hymowitz and Schellhardt introduced glass ceiling was "not something that could be found in any corporate manual or even discussed at a business meeting; it was originally introduced as an invisible, covert, and unspoken phenomenon that existed to keep executive level leadership positions in the hands of Caucasian males."&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt;

As the term "glass ceiling" became more common, the public responded with differing ideas and opinions. Some argued that the concept is a myth because women choose to stay home and showed less dedication to advance into executive positions.&lt;ref name=":3"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Wilson|first=Eleanor|date=September 4, 2014|title=Diversity, Culture and the Glass Ceiling|journal=Journal of Cultural Diversity|volume=21|issue=3|pages=83–9|pmid=25306838}}&lt;/ref&gt; As a result of continuing public debate, the [[United States Department of Labor|US Labor Department]]'s chief, [[Lynn Morley Martin]], reported the results of a research project called "The Glass Ceiling Initiative", formed to investigate the low numbers of women and minorities in executive positions. This report defined the new term as "those artificial barriers based on attitudinal or organizational bias that prevent qualified individuals from advancing upward in their organization into management-level positions."&lt;ref name="Cornell" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Success" /&gt;

In 1991, as a part of Title II of the [[Civil Right Act]] of 1991,&lt;ref name=":2"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Redwood|first=Rene A.|date=October 13, 1995|title=Breaking The Glass Ceiling: Good for Business, Good for America|url=https://www.proquest.com/openview/720eed4717a4012eb80aeb984880623c/1?pq-origsite=gscholar&amp;cbl=27059|journal=National Council of Jewish Women}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[The United States Congress]] created the Glass Ceiling Commission. This 21 member Presidential Commission was chaired by Secretary of Labor [[Robert Reich]],&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt; and was created to study the "barriers to the advancement of minorities and women within corporate hierarchies[,] to issue a report on its findings and conclusions, and to make recommendations on ways to dis- mantle the glass ceiling."&lt;ref name="DOL2" /&gt; The commission conducted extensive research including, surveys, public hearings and interviews, and released their findings in a report in 1995.&lt;ref name="DOL1" /&gt; The report, "Good for Business", offered "tangible guidelines and solutions on how these barriers can be overcome and eliminated".&lt;ref name="DOL2" /&gt; The goal of the commission was to provide recommendations on how to "shatter" the glass ceiling, specifically in the world of business. The report issued 12 recommendations on how to improve the workplace by increasing diversity in organizations and reducing discrimination through policy.&lt;ref name="DOL2" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Johns|first=Merida L.|date=January 1, 2013|title=Breaking the Glass Ceiling: Structural, Cultural, and Organizational Barriers Preventing Women from Achieving Senior and Executive Positions|journal=Perspectives in Health Information Management}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Breaking The Glass Ceiling: Can Women Reach The Top Of America's Largest Corporations? Updated Edition|last1=Morrison|first1=Ann|last2=White|first2=Randall P.|last3=Velsor|first3=Ellen Van|publisher=Personnel Decisions, Inc.|year=1982|location=Beverly, MA|pages=xii}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The number of women [[Chief executive officer|CEOs]] in the [[Fortune 500|Fortune Lists]] has increased between 1998 and 2020,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Hinchliffe |first1=Emma |title=The number of female CEOs in the Fortune 500 hits an all-time record |url=https://fortune.com/2020/05/18/women-ceos-fortune-500-2020/ |website=Fortune |publisher=Fortune Media IP Limited |access-date=11 October 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt; despite women's labor force participation rate decreasing globally from 52.4% to 49.6% between 1995 and 2015. Only 19.2% of [[S&amp;P 500 Index|S&amp;P 500 Board Seats]] were held by women in 2014, 80.2% of whom were considered white.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.catalyst.org/knowledge/statistical-overview-women-workforce|title=Statistical Overview of Women in the Workforce|last=acostigan|date=2012-10-17|website=Catalyst|access-date=2016-05-03|archive-date=2016-05-05|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160505164231/http://www.catalyst.org/knowledge/statistical-overview-women-workforce|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Glass Ceiling Index ==
{{main|Glass Ceiling Index}}
In 2017, ''[[The Economist]]'' updated their Glass Ceiling Index, combining data on higher education, labour-force participation, pay, child-care costs, maternity and paternity rights, business-school applications, and representation in senior jobs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine|url=https://www.economist.com/blogs/graphicdetail/2017/03/daily-chart-0|title=Daily chart: The best and worst places to be a working woman|newspaper=[[The Economist]]|date=8 March 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; The countries where inequality was the lowest were [[Iceland]], [[Sweden]], Norway, Finland, and Poland.

== Gender stereotypes ==
[[File:Gallup Poll Results.png|thumb|2001 Gallup Poll{{update inline|date=May 2021}}: Men are perceived as more aggressive, women are perceived as more emotional&lt;ref name=":4" /&gt;]]

In a 1993 report released through the U.S. Army Research Institute for the Behavioral and Social Sciences, researchers noted that although women have the same educational opportunities as their male counterparts, the Glass Ceiling persist due to systematic barriers, low representation, mobility, and [[stereotype]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Glass Ceiling: Potential Causes and Possible Solutions|s2cid=29423552|date=1993|publisher=U.S. Army Research Institute for the Behavioral and Social Sciences|doi=10.21236/ada278051|last1=Felber|first1=Helene R.|last2=Bayless|first2=J. A.|last3=Tagliarini|first3=Felicity A.|last4=Terner|first4=Jessica L.|last5=Dugan|first5=Beverly A.|hdl=2027/uva.x002608263 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The perpetuation of sexist stereotypes is one widely recognized reason as to why female employees are systematically inhibited from receiving advantageous opportunities in their chosen fields.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.aauw.org/research/barriers-and-bias/|title=Barriers and Bias: The Status of Women in Leadership|last=Hill|first=Catherine|website=AAUW}}&lt;/ref&gt; A majority of Americans perceive women to be more emotional and men to be more aggressive.&lt;ref name=":4"&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://news.gallup.com/poll/1978/americans-see-women-emotional-affectionate-men-more-aggressive.aspx|title=Americans See Women as Emotional and Affectionate, Men As More Aggressive|last=Newport|first=Frank|date=February 21, 2001|website=Gallup}}&lt;/ref&gt; Gender stereotypes influence how leaders are chosen by employers and how workers of different sex are treated. Another stereotype towards women in workplaces is known as the "gender status belief" which claims that men are more competent and intelligent than women, which would explain why they have higher positions in the career hierarchy. Ultimately, this factor leads to perception of gender-based jobs in the labor market, so men are expected to have more work-related qualifications and hired for top positions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.econstor.eu/bitstream/10419/29811/1/605208190.pdf|title=''Glass Ceiling Effect and Earnings – The Gender Pay Gap in Managerial Positions in Germany''|website=Econstor.eu}}&lt;/ref&gt; Perceived feminine stereotypes contribute to the glass ceiling faced by women in the workforce.

Gender stereotyping is thinking that men are better than women in management and leadership roles; it is the concept of alluding that women are inferior and better suited in their biological roles of mother and spouse.&lt;ref name="Great Expectations 2011"&gt;Glass Ceiling and Great Expectations: Gender stereotype Impact on Female Professionals, 2011, J. B. Johnson&lt;/ref&gt; The nature of this stereotype is toxic and hindering to women's success and their rights in every aspect but it is even more damaging in the workplace in a patriarchal society. It represents an invisible but strong barrier that stands in the way of women. Men are put at the utmost positions for they are primally viewed as better leaders whereas women are stuck in low or medium level positions.&lt;ref name="Century 2009"&gt;The Glass Ceiling in the 21st Century: Understanding Barriers to Gender Equality, 2009, by Manuela Barreto, PhD, Michelle K. Ryan, PhD, and Michael T. Schmitt, PhD. Chapter 1&lt;/ref&gt; These barriers to women's progression in management roles and a of significant issue. For example, the few women that have worked hard and relentlessly to break those barriers and have earned their deserving place in a leadership role are either viewed as "competent or warm" but never both.&lt;ref name="Great Expectations 2011"/&gt; This is because the idea of a successful woman is stereotyped within the idea that she must be a ruthless, competitive, cold person whereas a woman of a warm and caring nature will be perceived as not having the right skill set for leadership and progression because "she does not have what it takes".&lt;ref name="Century 2009"/&gt;

== Hiring practices ==
When women leave their current place of employment to start their own businesses, they tend to hire other women, and men to hire other men. These hiring practices (seemingly) diminish "the glass ceiling" effect because there is a perception of less competition of capabilities and sex discrimination. They appear to ally with the idea of "men's work" and "women's work".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title=Occupational gender segregation Trends and explanations|issue=5|pages=611–624|journal=The Quarterly Review of Economics and Finance|volume=39|doi=10.1016/S1062-9769(99)00029-0|date=January 1999|last1=Preston|first1=Jo Anne}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Cross-cultural context ==
Few women tend to reach positions in the upper echelon of society, and organizations are largely still almost exclusively led by men.{{Citation needed|date=October 2020}} Studies have shown that the glass ceiling still exists in varying levels in different nations and regions across the world.&lt;ref name=":6"&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Bullough|first1=A.|last2=Moore|first2=F.|last3=Kalafatoglu|first3=T.|date=2017|title=Research on women in international business and management: then, now, and next|journal=Cross Cultural &amp; Strategic Management|volume=24|issue=2|pages=211–230|doi=10.1108/CCSM-02-2017-0011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":7"&gt;{{Cite book|title=Women in Business and Management: Gaining momentum|last=ILO|publisher=International Labour Office|year=2015|location=Geneva}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Pursuit of Gender Equality: An Uphill Battle|last=OECD|publisher=OECD Publishing|year=2017|location=Paris}}&lt;/ref&gt; The stereotypes of women as emotional and sensitive could be seen as key characteristics as to why women struggle to break the glass ceiling. It is clear that even though societies differ from one another by culture, beliefs, and norms, they hold similar expectations of women and their role in society. These female stereotypes are often reinforced in societies that have traditional expectations of women.&lt;ref name=":6" /&gt; The stereotypes and perceptions of women are changing slowly across the world, which also reduces gender segregation in organizations.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Glass|first1=C.|last2=Cook|first2=A.|date=2016|title=Leading at the top: Understanding women's challenges above the glass ceiling|journal=The Leadership Quarterly|volume=27|issue=1|pages=51–63|doi=10.1016/j.leaqua.2015.09.003}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":7" /&gt;

== Overcoming glass ceiling ==
Despite significant improvement of women's participation in the labor force due to equity programs,&lt;ref&gt;Ainsworth, S., Knox, A. and O'Flynn, J. (2010). A blinding lack of progress: Management rhetoric and affirmative action. Gender, Work and Organization.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Jain, H., Lawler, J., Bai, B. and Lee, E. (2010). Effectiveness of Canada's employment equity legislation for women (1997–2004): Implications for policy makers.&lt;/ref&gt; advanced education levels,&lt;ref&gt;Turcotte, M. (2011). Women in Canada: A gender based statistical report.&lt;/ref&gt; and work-life balanced policies,&lt;ref&gt;Hakim, C. (2006). Women, careers, and work-life preferences. British Journal of Guidance and Counselling.&lt;/ref&gt; women are still underrepresented in upper-level positions in the workplace.&lt;ref&gt;Riccucci, N. 2009. The pursuit of social equity in the federal government: A Road Less Traveled? Public Administration Review.&lt;/ref&gt; There has been substantial invisible barriers for them to reach high-level management position such as lack of social capital,&lt;ref&gt;Hersby, M., Ryan, M. and Jetten, J. (2009). Getting together to get ahead: The impact of social structure on women's networking. British Journal of Management.&lt;/ref&gt; low level of self-efficacy and self-esteem,&lt;ref&gt;Matthews, C., Monk-Turner, E. and Sumter, M. (2010). Promotional opportunities: How women in corrections perceive their chances for advancement at work.&lt;/ref&gt; gender stereotypes,&lt;ref&gt;Lee, P.M. &amp; James, E.H. (2007). Gender effects and investor reactions to the announcements of top executive appointments. Strategic Management Journal.&lt;/ref&gt; and masculine organizational culture.&lt;ref&gt;Connell, R. (2006). Glass ceiling or gendered Institutions? Mapping the Gender Regimes of Public Sector Worksites. Public Administration Review.&lt;/ref&gt; In fact, individual, government and organization effort are needed to break double glass ceilings in which not only cultural and gender biases but also limitation of access to resources and opportunities have been rooted in the male-dominated workplace.

==="Individual effort"===
One of the effective strategies that women can use to overcome the glass ceiling effect on their own is networking. Social networks are critical for promoting one's career and receiving access to resources.&lt;ref&gt;Catalyst. (2004). The bottom line: Connecting corporate performance and gender diversity.&lt;/ref&gt; Establishing intensive connections within and outside an organization can contribute to better interpersonal understanding and reduction of negative stereotypical views of women and thus achieving career advancement in return.&lt;ref&gt;Deutsch, F. M. (2007). Undoing Gender. Gender and Society.&lt;/ref&gt; Social networks can be constructed through connections with individuals on various dimensions such as formal vs. informal, homogeneity vs. heterogeneity, instrumental vs. psychosocial and strong vs. weak ties.&lt;ref&gt;Ibarra, H., Kilduff, M., &amp;. Tsai, W. (2005). Zooming in and out: Connecting individuals and collectivities at the frontiers of organizational netwotk research. Organisational Science.&lt;/ref&gt; Women have strong capabilities of building and maintaining social relationship.&lt;ref&gt;Kite, M. (2001). Gender Stereotypes. Academic Press.&lt;/ref&gt; They can create internal network within their organizations that influence on deciding promotion and acceptance while an external network with outsiders contributes to psychosocial support.&lt;ref&gt;Burke, R. J., Rothstein, M. G, &amp; Bristor, J. M. (1995). Interpersonal networks of managerial and professional women. Women in Management Review.&lt;/ref&gt; They can build social networks in different ways depending on their social identity and cultural background.&lt;ref name="Hunt, L. 2009"&gt;Hunt, L., Laroche, G., [[Stacy Blake-Beard|Blake-Beard, S.]], Chin, E., Arroyave, M., &amp; Scully, M. (2009). The Glass Ceiling in the 21st Century: Understanding Barriers to Gender Equality. American Psychological Association.&lt;/ref&gt; However, building and maintaining networks can be time-consuming and not straightforward.&lt;ref name="Hunt, L. 2009"/&gt; Women can also face additional barriers to construct networks in an organization that have been dominated by powerful men.&lt;ref&gt;Catalyst. (2004). The bottom line: Connecting corporate performance and gender diversity&lt;/ref&gt;

The benefits accumulated from social networks become social capital for individuals.&lt;ref&gt;Murrell, A. J., &amp; Zagenczyk, T. J. (2006). Gender, race, and role model status: Exploring the impact of informal developmental relationships on management careers.&lt;/ref&gt; Thus, the quality of one's social network can determine the value of its social capital.&lt;ref&gt;Ibarra, H., Kilduff, M., &amp;. Tsai, W. (2005). Zooming in and out: Connecting individuals and collectivities at the frontiers of organizational network research. Organisational Science.&lt;/ref&gt; Social capital can contribute several positive career outcomes such as task accomplishment and social support for career advancement.&lt;ref&gt;Wang, J. (2009). Networking in the workplace: Implications for women's career development. New Directions for Adult and Continuing Education.&lt;/ref&gt; Women can enhance their social capital and promote their professional images through mentoring. Mentoring plays a critical role in supporting women to achieve executive-level positions in an organization.&lt;ref&gt;Yu, H., &amp; Lee, D. (2021). Women and public organization: An examination of mentorship and its effect on reporting workplace discrimination. Review of Public Personnel Administration.&lt;/ref&gt; Mentoring means a senior with advanced knowledge, skills and experience helps a junior through career and psychological support.&lt;ref&gt;Sosik, J. J., &amp; Lee, D. L. (2002). Mentoring in organizations: A social judgement perspective for developing tomorrow's leaders. Journal of Leadership and Organizational Studies.&lt;/ref&gt; Career support includes sponsorship, coaching and visibility&lt;ref&gt;Baugh, S. G., Lankau, M. J., &amp; Scandura, T. A. (1996). An investigation of the effects of protégé gender on responses to mentoring. Journal of Vocational Behavior.&lt;/ref&gt; while psychological support includes acceptance, emotional support and role modeling.&lt;ref&gt;Reid, M. F., Allen, M. W., Riemenschneider, C. K., &amp; Armstrong, D. J. (2008). The role of mentoring and supervisor support for state IT employees' affective organizational commitment. Review of Public Personnel Administration.&lt;/ref&gt; A supportive supervisor or mentor can enhance the opportunity of being appointed to the critical roles and increase the probability of actual promotions through temporary promotions.&lt;ref&gt;Choi, S. (2018). Breaking through the glass ceiling: Social capital matters for women's career success? International Public Management Journal.&lt;/ref&gt; To achieve this, women can intentionally forge relationships across race, gender, occupation level and organizational culture.&lt;ref&gt;Blake-Beard, S., Munell, A., &amp; Thomas, D. (2006). Unfinished business: The impact of race on understanding mentoring relationships. [Working paper].&lt;/ref&gt; Moreover, they can borrow this kind of social capital from strategic partners to get important contacts.&lt;ref&gt;Burt, R. S. (1998). The Gender of Social Capital. Rationality and Society.&lt;/ref&gt; But, such kind of connection is related with only temporary promotions. Mentors are more likely to support the same-gender mentee in an organization.&lt;ref&gt;Nicholson-Crotty, J. (2011). Bureaucratic representation, distributional equity, and democratic values in the administration of public programs. Journal of Politics.&lt;/ref&gt; Female mentors may be sympathetic and understand about women's challenges and emotions in the battle of promotions.&lt;ref&gt;Lockwood, P. (2006). Someone like me can be successful: Do college students need same-gender role models? Psychology of Women Quarterly.&lt;/ref&gt; However, this benefit could be realized only when female mentors reach relatively high-level positions.&lt;ref name="Wyche, K. R. 2008"&gt;Wyche, K. R. (2008). Good is not good enough and other unwritten rules for minority professionals.&lt;/ref&gt; In fact, it is difficult for women to receive mentoring from the same gender since there are fewer senior management positions occupied by women.&lt;ref name="Wyche, K. R. 2008"/&gt;

Positive attitude towards glass ceiling can also help women to break glass ceiling. Optimistic beliefs about chances of being promoted in an organization can cause positive actions towards pursuing promotions. Resilience and denial are optimistic glass ceiling beliefs for subjective career success.&lt;ref name="Smith, P. 2012"&gt;Smith, P., Caputi, P., &amp; Crittenden, N. (2012). How are women's glass ceiling beliefs related to career success? Career Development International.&lt;/ref&gt; Resilience means women believe that they are able to break glass ceiling: they can fight for their rights to promotion and career development. Denial means women think that men and women experience the same issues and barriers in pursuing executive positions. On the other hand, resignation and acceptance are pessimistic glass ceiling beliefs for subjective career advancement.&lt;ref name="Smith, P. 2012"/&gt; Resignation means women are unwilling to break glass ceiling due to the belief of experiencing more negative consequences than men. Acceptance deals with women's preference on other goals such as family involvement instead of career advancement. Women who want to reach higher levels of management in an organization can analyze their levels of resilience and denial. Then, they will be able to build resilience skill through attitude, behavior and social support in order to overcome glass ceiling in a highly competitive contemporary workplace.

==="Organization effort"===
Overcoming the glass ceiling is not only a moral imperative but also a strategic advantage for organizations aiming to thrive in an increasingly diverse in a complex world. To break through this barrier and promote diversity and inclusivity in leadership, organizations must adopt a multifaceted and sustained approaches including development of policies, programs, leadership commitment and evaluation.

'''1. Policies'''

Effective diversity and inclusion policies play a pivotal role in breaking through organizational glass ceilings. Firstly, organizations must develop robust recruitment&lt;ref name="marketing91.com"&gt;Bhasin, H. (2020, August 22). Marketing91. Retrieved from What is the Glass Ceiling and How to Break it?: https://www.marketing91.com/what-is-glass-ceiling/&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="uk.indeed.com"&gt;Indeed Editorial Team. (2022, October 1). Glass Ceiling Definition and How to Break it in the Workplace. Retrieved from indeed: https://uk.indeed.com/career-advice/career-development/glass-ceiling-definition&lt;/ref&gt; and retention strategies that not only attract diverse talent but also address attrition rates among underrepresented employees through targeted retention programs.&lt;ref name="Eddy S 2017"&gt;Eddy S. Ng, and Greg J. Sears. (2017). The glass ceiling in context: the influence of CEO gender, recruitment practices and firm internationalisation on the representation of women in management. Human Resource Management Journal, 133–151.&lt;/ref&gt; To foster diversity at all levels, from recruitment to promotions,&lt;ref name="uk.indeed.com"/&gt; organizations should establish clear and comprehensive diversity and inclusion policies.&lt;ref name="marketing91.com"/&gt; These policies should not only outline specific objectives but also incorporate metrics and strategies that serve as guiding principles. Furthermore, compliance with all relevant anti-discrimination and equal opportunity laws is fundamental in cultivating a fair and inclusive workplace.&lt;ref name="marketing91.com"/&gt; Moreover, transparency in promotion and succession processes is essential.&lt;ref name="Eddy S 2017"/&gt; Maintaining clear communication regarding the criteria for advancement empowers employees to understand and actively pursue leadership opportunities, thereby dismantling the glass ceiling and promoting a more inclusive and equitable workplace. In addition to focusing on policy, organizations should also prioritize their programs for breaking through the glass ceiling.

'''2. Program'''

Firstly, organizations should prioritize the creation of comprehensive diversity and inclusion programs that clearly show their dedication to fairness and equal opportunities to all employees in workplaces. In addition, ensuring fairness in promotions is vital. Transparent promotion criteria must be developed and consistently applied across the organization to maintain fairness and equal opportunities for all.&lt;ref name="Eddy S 2017"/&gt; Furthermore, the implementation of leadership development programs is essential to identify and nurture potential leaders from diverse backgrounds. These programs may include elements such as mentorship,&lt;ref name="Indeed. 2022"&gt;Indeed. (2022, October 01). Glass ceiling definition and how to break it in the workplace. Retrieved from Indeed: https://uk.indeed.com/career-advice/career-development/glass-ceiling-definition&lt;/ref&gt; training, and opportunities for high-potential employees to gain valuable leadership experience.

To increase awareness and mitigate unconscious bias,&lt;ref name="uk.indeed.com"/&gt; organizations should provide diversity and inclusion training for all employees, including management and executives. This training should equip individuals with strategies to minimize the impact of bias on decision-making and team dynamics. Lastly, organizations should create platforms and events that facilitate networking opportunities for employees from diverse backgrounds to interact with senior leadership.&lt;ref name="uk.indeed.com"/&gt; Enhanced visibility through these initiatives is paramount for career progression and reinforces an organization's commitment to breaking through the glass ceiling and promoting diversity and inclusion.

'''3. Leadership commitment'''

Firstly, leaders must exemplify unwavering commitment to diversity and inclusion, serving as champions of this vital initiative. This should be evident in the organization's values, policies, and in the actions of its leaders.&lt;ref name="Eddy S 2017"/&gt; Secondly, organizations should establish clear accountability mechanisms. Leadership should be held responsible for achieving diversity and inclusion goals, with performance metrics directly tied to these objectives.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author1=Bishu, S. G.|author2=Kennedy, A. R.|date=2019 |title=Trends and Gaps: A Meta-Review of Representative Bureaucracy. Review of Public Personnel Administration |journal=Review of Public Personnel Administration |volume=40 |issue=4 |pages=559–588 |doi=10.1177/0734371X19830154 |s2cid=159153947 |url=https://journals-sagepub-com.helicon.vuw.ac.nz/doi/10.1177/0734371X19830154}}&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, promoting inclusive leadership is crucial. Organizations should invest in training their leaders to make equitable and inclusive decisions, manage teams with fairness, and engage in inclusive interactions.&lt;ref name="marketing91.com"/&gt; Effective communication plays a pivotal role in this journey. Organizations should transparently communicate their commitment to diversity and inclusion, both internally and externally. Regularly publishing diversity and inclusion reports helps maintain transparency and keeps stakeholders informed about progress.&lt;ref&gt;Ashikali, T., Groeneveld, S., and Kuipers, B. (2021). The Role of Inclusive Leadership in Supporting an Inclusive Climate in Diverse Public Sector Teams. Review of Public Personnel Administration, 497–519.&lt;/ref&gt; Lastly, cultural transformation is essential. Cultivating a workplace culture rooted in respect and open communication is paramount (Bhasin, 2020). Encouraging employees to report&lt;ref name="Indeed. 2022"/&gt; any instances of discrimination or harassment and providing a safe and supportive space for such reports is vital to addressing issues promptly and effectively.

'''4. Performance evaluation'''

To successfully overcome the glass ceiling at the organizational level, a commitment to continuous improvement is paramount.&lt;ref&gt;EvalCommunity. (n.a, n.a n.a). Importance of Monitoring and Evaluation. Retrieved from EvalCommunity: https://www.evalcommunity.com/career-center/importance-of-monitoring-and-evaluation/#:~:text=It%20helps%20to%20identify%20any,meeting%20their%20goals%20and%20objectives.&lt;/ref&gt; This entails regularly evaluating the effectiveness of diversity and inclusion initiatives through methods such as surveys, feedback mechanisms,&lt;ref name="marketing91.com"/&gt; and data analysis. Organizations must remain adaptable, ready to adjust their strategies as necessary to tackle evolving challenges and capitalize on opportunities for enhancement.

==Related concepts==
==="Glass escalator"===
{{main|Glass escalator}}
A parallel phenomenon called the "[[The Glass Escalator|glass escalator]]" has also been recognized. As more men join fields that were previously dominated by women, such as nursing and teaching, the men are promoted and given more opportunities compared to the women, as if the men were taking escalators and the women were taking the stairs.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title = A New Obstacle For Professional Women: The Glass Escalator|url = https://www.forbes.com/sites/jennagoudreau/2012/05/21/a-new-obstacle-for-professional-women-the-glass-escalator/|website = Forbes|access-date = 2015-10-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; The chart from Carolyn K. Broner shows an example of the glass escalator in favor of men for female-dominant occupations in schools.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title = MEN, WOMEN, &amp; THE GLASS ESCALATOR|url = http://www.womenonbusiness.com/men-women-the-glass-escalator/|website = Women on Business|date = 28 February 2013|access-date = 2015-10-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; While women have historically dominated the teaching profession, men tend to take higher positions in school systems such as deans or principals.{{citation needed|date=October 2020}}

Men benefit financially from their gender status in historically female fields, often "reaping the benefits of their token status to reach higher levels in female-dominated work".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.ssc.wisc.edu/~wright/ContemporaryAmericanSociety/Chapter%2015%20--%20Gender%20inequality%20--%20Norton%20August.pdf|title=Gender Inequality|last=Arnesen|first=Eric|date=2009|website=University Of Wisconsin Madison}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{citation needed|date=November 2016}}

A 2008 study published in ''[[Social Problems]]'' found that sex segregation in nursing did not follow the "glass escalator" pattern of disproportional vertical distribution; rather, men and women gravitated towards different areas within the field, with male nurses tending to specialize in areas of work perceived as "masculine".&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{cite journal|title=Revisiting the Glass Escalator: The Case of Gender Segregation in a Female Dominated Occupation|first1=Karrie Ann|last1=Snyder|first2=Adam Isaiah|last2=Green|date=1 May 2008|volume=55|issue=2|pages=271–299|via=socpro.oxfordjournals.org|doi=10.1525/sp.2008.55.2.271|journal=Social Problems}}&lt;/ref&gt; The article noted that "men encounter powerful social pressures that direct them away from entering female-dominated occupations (Jacobs 1989, 1993)". Since female-dominated occupations are usually characterized by more feminine activities, men who enter these jobs can be perceived socially as "effeminate, homosexual, or sexual predators".&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

==="Sticky floors"===
In the literature on gender discrimination, the concept of "sticky floors" complements the concept of a glass ceiling. Sticky floors can be described as the pattern that women are, compared to men, less likely to start to climb the job ladder. This is often due to discriminatory employment pattern that keeps workers, mainly women, in the lower ranks of the job scale, with low mobility and invisible barriers to career advancement. Thereby, this phenomenon is related to gender differentials at the bottom of the wage distribution. Building on the seminal study by Booth and co-authors in European Economic Review,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Booth | first1 = A. L. | last2 = Francesconi | first2 = M. | last3 = Frank | first3 = J. | year = 2003 | title = A sticky floors model of promotion, pay, and gender | journal = European Economic Review | volume = 47 | issue = 2| pages = 295–322 | doi = 10.1016/S0014-2921(01)00197-0 }}&lt;/ref&gt; during the last decade economists have attempted to identify sticky floors in the labour market.  They found empirical evidence for the existence of sticky floors in countries such as Australia, Belgium, Italy, Thailand, and the United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Baert | first1 = S. | last2 = De Pauw | first2 = A.-S. | last3 = Deschacht | first3 = N. | year = 2016 | title = Do Employer Preferences Contribute to Sticky Floors? | url = https://biblio.ugent.be/publication/5960457| journal = ILR Review | volume =  69| issue = 3| pages = 714–736 | doi = 10.1177/0019793915625213 | hdl = 1854/LU-5960457 | s2cid = 53589814 | hdl-access = free }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==="The frozen middle"===
Similar to the sticky floor, the frozen middle describes the phenomenon of women's progress up the corporate ladder slowing, if not halting, in the ranks of middle management.&lt;ref&gt;Martell, Richard F., et al. "Sex Stereotyping In The Executive Suite: 'Much Ado About Something'." Journal of Social Behavior &amp; Personality (1998) 127–138. Web.&lt;/ref&gt; Originally the term referred to the resistance corporate upper management faced from middle management when issuing directives. Due to a lack of ability or lack of drive in the ranks of middle management, these directives do not come into fruition and as a result the company's bottom line suffers. The term was popularized by a ''Harvard Business Review'' article titled "Middle Management Excellence".&lt;ref&gt;Byrnes, Jonathan. "Middle Management Excellence." Harvard Business Review 5 Dec. 2005 pag. print&lt;/ref&gt; Due to the growing proportion of women to men in the workforce, however, the term "frozen middle" has become more commonly ascribed to the aforementioned slowing of the careers of women in middle management.&lt;ref&gt;Lyness, Karen S., and Donna E. Thompson. "Climbing The Corporate Ladder: Do Female And Male Executives Follow The Same Route?." Journal of Applied Psychology (2000) 86–101. Web.&lt;/ref&gt; The 1996 study "A Study of the Career Development and Aspirations of Women in Middle Management" posits that social structures and networks within businesses that favor "good old boys" and norms of masculinity exist based on the experiences of women surveyed.&lt;ref&gt;Wentling, Rose Mary. "Women In Middle Management: Their Career Development And Aspirations." Business Horizon (1992) 47. Web.&lt;/ref&gt; According to the study, women who did not exhibit stereotypical masculine traits, (e.g. aggressiveness, thick skin, lack of emotional expression) and interpersonal communication tendencies were disadvantaged compared to their male peers.&lt;ref&gt;Wentling, Rose Mary. "Women In Middle Management: Their Career Development And Aspirations." Business Horizon, p. 252 (1992) 47. Web.&lt;/ref&gt; As the ratio of men to women increases in the upper levels of management,&lt;ref&gt;Helfat, Constance E., Dawn Harris, and Paul J. Wolfson. "The Pipeline To The Top: Women And Men In The Top Executive Ranks Of U.S. Corporations." Academy Of Management Perspectives (2006) 42–64. Web.&lt;/ref&gt; women's access to female mentors who could advise them on ways to navigate office politics is limited, further inhibiting upward mobility within a corporation or firm.&lt;ref&gt;Dezso, Cristian L., David Gaddis Ross, and Jose Uribe. "Is There An Implicit Quota On Women In Top Management? A Large-Sample Statistical Analysis." Strategic Management Journal (2016) 98–115. Web.&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, the frozen middle affects female professionals in western and eastern countries such as the United States and Malaysia, respectively,&lt;ref&gt;Mandy Mok Kim, Man, Miha Skerlavaj, and Vlado Dimovski. "Is There A 'Glass Ceiling' For Mid-Level Female Managers?." International Journal of Management &amp; Innovation (2009) 1–13. Web.&lt;/ref&gt; as well as women in a variety of fields ranging from the aforementioned corporations to STEM fields.&lt;ref&gt;Cundiff, Jessica, and Theresa Vescio. "Gender Stereotypes Influence How People Explain Gender Disparities In The Workplace." Sex Roles (2016): 126–138. Web.&lt;/ref&gt;

==="Second shift"===
The second shift focuses on the idea that women theoretically work a second shift in the manner of having a greater workload, not just doing a greater share of domestic work. All of the tasks that are engaged in outside the workplace are mainly tied to motherhood.{{citation needed|date=October 2020}} Depending on location, household income, educational attainment, ethnicity and location, data shows that women do work a second shift in the sense of having a greater workload, not just doing a greater share of domestic work, but this is not apparent if simultaneous activity is overlooked.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Craig|first=Lyn|year=2007|title=is herre really a second shift, and if so, who does it? a time-diary investigation|journal=Feminist Review|volume=86|issue=1|pages=149–170|jstor=30140855|doi=10.1057/palgrave.fr.9400339|s2cid=145510373}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Alva Myrdal]] and [[Viola Klein]] as early as 1956 focused on the potential of both men and women working in settings that included paid and unpaid types of work environments. Research indicated that men and women could have equal time for activities outside the work environment for family and extra activities.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Myrdal|first1=Alva|last2=Klein|first2=Viola|year=1957|title=Women's Two Roles: Home and Work|journal=American Sociological Review|volume=20|issue=2|pages=250|doi=10.2307/2088886|jstor=2088886}}&lt;/ref&gt; This "second shift" has also been found to have physical effects as well. Women who engage in longer hours of work in pursuit of family balance often face increased mental health problems such as [[Major depressive disorder|depression]] and [[Anxiety disorder|anxiety]]. Increased irritability, lower motivation and energy, and other emotional issues were also found to occur as well. The overall happiness of women can be improved if a balance of career and home responsibilities is found.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Ahmad|first=Muhammad|year=2011|title=Working women work–life conflict|journal=Business Strategy Series|volume=12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==="Mommy track"===
"Mommy track" refers to women who disregard their careers and professional responsibilities in order to satisfy the needs of their families. Women are often subject to long work hours that create an imbalance within the work-family schedule.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Hill|first1=E. Jeffery|last2=Martinson|first2=Vjkollca K.|last3=Baker|first3=Robin Zenger|last4=Ferris|first4=Maria|year=2004|title=Beyond The Mommy Track: The Influence of New Concept Part-Time Work for Professional Women on Work and Family|journal=Journal of Family and Economic Issues|volume=25|issue=1 |pages=121–136|doi=10.1023/B:JEEI.0000016726.06264.91|s2cid=145066152}}&lt;/ref&gt; There is research suggesting that women are able to operate on a part-time professional schedule compared to others who worked full-time while still engaged in external family activities.{{Clarify|date=October 2020}} This research also suggests that flexible work arrangements allow the achievement of a healthy work and family balance. A difference has also been discovered in the cost and amount of effort in childbearing between women in higher skilled positions and roles, as opposed to women in lower-skilled jobs. This difference leads women to delay and postpone goals and career aspirations over many years.

==="Concrete floor"===
The term ''concrete floor'' has been used to refer to the minimum number or the proportion of women necessary for a cabinet or board of directors to be perceived as legitimate.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=There are three rules of Cabinet appointments |url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/monkey-cage/wp/2016/11/25/there-are-three-rules-of-cabinet-appointments-will-donald-trump-break-them/ |newspaper=[[Wall Street Journal]] |date=November 25, 2016 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Quota Doctors==
Government intervention in the admission and promotion process results in beneficiaries being tagged as {{Anchor|Quota doctor}}'''quota doctors'''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |newspaper=[[Daily Excelsior]]
|url=https://www.dailyexcelsior.com/every-fifth-doctor-from-management-quota
|title=Every fifth Doctor from 'management' quota
|date=August 11, 2013}}{&lt;/ref&gt; These quotas are floor quotas, having a required minimum; their contrast is for ceiling quotas, [[Numerus clausus]].

==See also==
{{div col|colwidth=22em}}
* [[Bamboo ceiling]]
* [[Celluloid ceiling]]
* [[Equal Pay Day]]
* [[Equal pay for women]]
* [[Female labor force in the Muslim world]]
* [[Feminization of poverty]]
* [[Gender equality]]
* [[Gender inequality]]
* [[Gender pay gap]]
* [[Gender role]]
* [[Glass cliff]]
* [[Glassdoor]]
* [[Material feminism]]
* [[Mommy track]]
* [[Sex differences in humans]]
* [[Sexism]]
* [[Stained-glass ceiling]]
* [[Superwoman (sociology)]]
* [[Time bind]]
{{div col end}}

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

== Bibliography ==
* {{cite journal | last1 = Cholensky | first1 = Stephanie | year = 2015 | title = The Gender Pay Gap: NO MORE EXCUSES!. | journal = Judgment &amp; Decision Making | volume = 10 | issue = 2| pages = 15–16 }}
* {{Cite report | last = Federal Glass Ceiling Commission | title = Good for business: Making full use of the nation's human capital | publisher = [[United States Department of Labor|U.S. Department of Labor]] | location = Washington DC | date = March 1995a | url = http://www.dol.gov/oasam/programs/history/reich/reports/ceiling.pdf | access-date = 2011-04-09 | archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20140810033848/http://www.dol.gov/oasam/programs/history/reich/reports/ceiling.pdf | archive-date = 2014-08-10 | url-status = dead }}
* {{cite book | last1 = Fox | first1 = Mary | last2 = Hesse-Biber | first2 = Sharlene N. | title = Women at work | publisher = Mayfield Publishing Company | location = Palo Alto, California | year = 1984 | isbn = 978-0-87484-525-9 | url-access = registration | url = https://archive.org/details/womenatwork00mary }}
* {{cite book | last1 = Giele | first1 = Janet Z. | last2 = Stebbins | first2 = Leslie F | author-link1 = Janet Zollinger Giele | title = Women and equality in the workplace a reference handbook | publisher = ABC-CLIO | location = Santa Barbara, California | year = 2003 | isbn = 978-1-57607-937-9 }}
* {{cite book | last1 = Hesse-Biber | first1 = Sharlene N. | last2 = Carter | first2 = Gregg L. | title = Working women in America : split dreams | publisher = Oxford University Press | location = New York, New York | year = 2005 | isbn = 978-0-19-515047-6 }}
* {{Cite journal | last1 = Lyness | first1 = Karen S. | last2 = Thompson | first2 = Donna E. | s2cid = 25113738 | title = Above the glass ceiling? A comparison of matched samples of female and male executives | journal = [[Journal of Applied Psychology]] | volume = 82 | issue = 3 | pages = 359–375 | publisher = [[American Psychological Association]] | doi = 10.1037/0021-9010.82.3.359 | pmid = 9190144 | date = June 1997  }}
* National Partnership for Women and Families, comp. (April 2016). "America's Women and The Wage Gap" (PDF). ''Trade, Jobs and Wages''. Retrieved 2 May 2016.
* {{Cite journal | last1 = Ponnuswamy | first1 = Indra | last2 = Manohar | first2 = Hansa Lysander | title = Breaking the glass ceiling – a mixed methods study using Watkins and Marsick's learning organisation culture model | journal = [[Asian Women (journal)|Asian Women]] | volume = 30 | issue = 3 | pages = 85–111 | publisher = Research Institute of Asian Women (RIAW) | doi = 10.14431/aw.2014.09.30.3.85 | date = September 2014  | doi-access = free }}
* Redwood, Rene A. (October 13, 1995). "Breaking The Glass Ceiling: Good for Business, Good for America". ''National Council of Jewish Women''.
* {{Citation | last1 = Schneps | first1 = Leila | last2 = Colmez | first2 = Coralie | author-link1 = Leila Schneps | author-link2 = Coralie Colmez | contribution = Math error number 6: Simpson's paradox. The Berkeley sex bias case: discrimination detection | editor-last1 = Schneps | editor-first1 = Leila | editor-last2 = Colmez | editor-first2 = Coralie | editor-link1 = Leila Schneps | editor-link2 = Coralie Colmez | title = Math on trial: how numbers get used and abused in the courtroom | pages = 107–120 | publisher = Basic Books | location = New York | year = 2013 | isbn = 978-0-465-03292-1 |title-link=Math on Trial}}
* {{cite journal | last1 = Snyder | first1 = Karrie Ann | last2 = Isaiah Green | first2 = Adam | year = 2008 | title = Revisiting The Glass Escalator: The Case Of Gender Segregation In A Female Dominated Occupation | journal = Social Problems | volume = 55 | issue = 2| pages = 271–299 | doi=10.1525/sp.2008.55.2.271}}
* {{cite journal | last1 = Woodhams | first1 = Carol | last2 = Lupton | first2 = Ben | last3 = Cowling | first3 = Marc | year = 2015 | title = The Presence Of Ethnic Minority And Disabled Men In Feminised Work: Intersectionality, Vertical Segregation And The Glass Escalator | url =https://ore.exeter.ac.uk/repository/bitstream/10871/16156/2/woodhams.pdf | journal = Sex Roles | volume = 72 | issue = 7–8| pages = 277–293 | doi=10.1007/s11199-014-0427-z| hdl = 10871/16156 | s2cid = 144278250 | hdl-access = free }}
* Malpas, J., "Donald Davidson", ''The Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy'' (Winter 2012 Edition), Edward N. Zalta (ed.), &lt;[http://plato.stanford.edu/archives/win2012/entries/davidson/ Donald Davidson]&gt;. Web May 2, 2016.
* [http://www.laborrights.org/issues/women's-rights International Labor Rights Forum. (n.d.). Retrieved May 2, 2016]{{Dead link|date=March 2024 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}
* Hyun, Jane. ''Breaking the Bamboo Ceiling: Career Strategies for Asians''. New York: HarperBusiness, 2005. Print.
* Wiley, John. ''The Blackwell Encyclopedia of Gender and Sexuality Studies''. Vol. 5. Chicester: John Wiley and Sons, 2012. Print.
* ''Top 10 Numbers that Show Why Pay Equity Matters to Asian American Women and Their Families''. Retrieved May 1, 2016.

== External links ==
{{wikiquote}}
* Catalyst research report (1996). [https://web.archive.org/web/20170929135644/http://www.catalyst.org/file/219/women%20in%20corporate%20leadership%20-%20progress%20and%20prospects%201996.pdf ''Women in Corporate Leadership'': Progr (2003).] [https://web.archive.org/web/20110929042400/http://www.catalyst.org/file/74/women%20and%20men%20in%20u.s.%20corporate%20leadership%20same%20workplace,%20different%20realities.pdf ''Women and Men in U.S. Corporate Leadership: Same Workplace, Different Realities?'']
* Catalyst. [https://web.archive.org/web/20121111051125/http://catalyst.org/publication/145/women-and-men-in-us-corporate-leadership-same-workplace-different-realities ''Women and Men in U.S. Corporate Leadership: Same Workplace, Different Realities?''] New York, N.Y.: Catalyst, 2004, {{ISBN|978-0-89584-247-3}}.
* Catalyst. [https://web.archive.org/web/20110929042217/http://www.catalyst.org/file/420/2010_financial_post_500_women_senior_officers_and_top_earners_final.pdf ''2010 Catalyst Census: Financial Post 500 Women Senior Officers and Top Earners''.]
* Federal Glass Ceiling Commission. [https://web.archive.org/web/20140810033848/http://www.dol.gov/oasam/programs/history/reich/reports/ceiling.pdf ''Good for Business: Making Full Use of the Nation's Human Capital.''] Washington, D.C.: U.S. Department of Labor, March 1995.
* Federal Glass Ceiling Commission. [https://web.archive.org/web/20141108194808/http://www.dol.gov/oasam/programs/history/reich/reports/ceiling2.pdf ''Solid Investments: Making Full Use of the Nation's Human Capital''.] Washington, D.C.: U.S. Department of Labor, November 1995.
* Carvajal, Doreen. [https://www.nytimes.com/2011/01/27/world/27iht-rules27.html ''The Codes That Need to Be Broken''.] ''The New York Times'', January 26, 2011.
* {{cite journal | last1 = Cotter | first1 = David A. | last2 = Hermsen | first2 = Joan M. | last3 = Ovadia | first3 = Seth | last4 = Vanneman | first4 = Reece | year = 2001 | title = The glass ceiling effect | url = http://www.bsos.umd.edu/socy/vanneman/papers/CotterHOV01.pdf | journal = Social Forces | volume = 80 | issue = 2| pages = 655–81 | doi=10.1353/sof.2001.0091| s2cid = 145245044 }}
* [http://cjournal.cz/files/130.pdf Effects of Glass Ceiling on Women Career Development in Private Sector Organizations – Case of Sri Lanka]

{{Discrimination}}
{{Employment}}
{{Portal bar|Society}}
{{authority control}}

[[Category:Racism]]
[[Category:Feminist economics]]
[[Category:Feminist terminology]]
[[Category:Sexism]]
[[Category:Employment discrimination]]
[[Category:1970s neologisms]]
[[Category:Women-related neologisms]]
[[Category:Industrial and organizational psychology]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>