<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20161120044629|750507044" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="637623" pageid="637623" ns="0" title="Glass ceiling"><revisions><rev timestamp="2016-11-20T05:07:21Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{about|a metaphor |more information about the barrier that prevents women from reaching the upper rungs of the corporate ladder|Gender pay gap}}
{{globalize|article|Europe and the Anglosphere|date=February 2015}}
[[File:Average earnings of workers by education and sex - 2006.png|thumb|A chart illustrating the differences in earnings between men and women of the same educational level (USA 2006)]]
A '''glass ceiling''' is a metaphor used to represent an invisible barrier that keeps a given demographic (typically applied to women) from rising beyond a certain level in a hierarchy.&lt;ref name="DOL2"&gt;Federal Glass Ceiling Commission. [http://www.dol.gov/oasam/programs/history/reich/reports/ceiling2.pdf ''Solid Investments: Making Full Use of the Nation's Human Capital''.] Washington, D.C.: U.S. Department of Labor, November 1995, p. 13-15.&lt;/ref&gt;

The metaphor was first coined by [[Feminism|feminists]] in reference to barriers in the careers of high-achieving women.&lt;ref name="DOL1"&gt;Federal Glass Ceiling Commission. [http://www.dol.gov/oasam/programs/history/reich/reports/ceiling.pdf ''Good for Business: Making Full Use of the Nation's Human Capital.''] Washington, D.C.: U.S. Department of Labor, March 1995.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Blackwell Encyclopedia of Gender and Sexuality Studies. Vol. 5.|last=Wiley|first=John|publisher=John Wiley and Sons|year=2012|isbn=|location=|pages=}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the [[United States|US]], the concept is sometimes extended to refer to [[Racial inequality in the United States|obstacles hindering the advancement of minority men, as well as women]].&lt;ref name="DOL1" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.washingtontimes.com/news/2016/apr/26/hillary-clinton-as-a-white-person-i-have-to-discus/|title=Hillary Clinton: ‘As a white person,’ I have to discuss racism ‘every chance I get’|first=The Washington Times|last=http://www.washingtontimes.com|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Asian and Asian-American news outlets have coined the term "[[bamboo ceiling]]".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Breaking the Bamboo Ceiling: Career Strategies for Asians|last=Hyun|first=Jane|publisher=New York: HarperBusiness|year=2005|isbn=|location=|pages=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.americanprogress.org/issues/labor/news/2013/04/09/59720/top-10-numbers-that-show-why-pay-equity-matters-to-asian-american-women-and-their-families/|title=Top 10 Numbers that Show Why Pay Equity Matters to Asian American Women and Their Families|website=name|access-date=2016-05-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Within the same concepts of the other terms surrounding the workplace, there are similar terms for restrictions and barriers concerning women and their roles within organizations and how they coincide with their maternal duties. These "Invisible Barriers" function as a metaphors to describe the extra circumstances that women undergo, usually when trying to advance within areas of their careers and at often times while trying to advance within their lives outside of their work spaces. Their are a few metaphors that signify these barriers as well.

== Definition ==
The United States Federal Glass Ceiling Commission&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.dol.gov/dol/aboutdol/history/reich/reports/ceiling.htm|title=The Environmental Scan: A Fact-Finding Report of the Federal Glass Ceiling Commission Washington, D.C.|website=name|access-date=2016-09-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; defines the glass ceiling as "the unseen, yet unbreachable barrier that keeps minorities and women from rising to the upper rungs of the corporate ladder, regardless of their qualifications or achievements."&lt;ref name="DOL2" /&gt;

David Cotter and colleagues defined four distinctive characteristics that must be met to conclude that a ''glass ceiling'' exists. A glass ceiling inequality represents:
#"A gender or racial difference that is not explained by other job-relevant characteristics of the employee."
#"A gender or racial difference that is greater at higher levels of an outcome than at lower levels of an outcome."
#"A gender or racial inequality in the chances of advancement into higher levels, not merely the proportions of each gender or race currently at those higher levels."
#"A gender or racial inequality that increases over the course of a career."
Cotter and his colleagues found that glass ceilings are correlated strongly with gender. Both white and minority women face a glass ceiling in the course of their careers. In contrast, the researchers did not find evidence of a glass ceiling for African-American men.&lt;ref&gt;Cotter, David A., Joan M. Hermsen, Seth Ovadia, and Reece Vanneman (2001). [http://www.bsos.umd.edu/socy/vanneman/papers/CotterHOV01.pdf ''The glass ceiling effect''.] '''Social Forces''', Vol. 80 No. 2, pp. 655–81.&lt;/ref&gt;

The glass ceiling metaphor has often been used to describe invisible barriers ("glass") through which women can see elite positions but cannot reach them ("ceiling").&lt;ref&gt;*Davies-Netzley, Sally A. (1998).  ''Women above the Glass Ceiling: Perceptions on Corporate Mobility and Strategies for Success'' '''Gender and Society''', Vol. 12, No. 3, p. 340, {{DOI|10.1177/0891243298012003006}}.  {{jstor|190289}}.&lt;/ref&gt; These barriers prevent large numbers of women and ethnic minorities from obtaining and securing the most powerful, prestigious, and highest-grossing jobs in the workforce.&lt;ref&gt;Hesse-Biber and Carter 2005, p. 77.&lt;/ref&gt; Moreover, this effect prevents women from filling high-ranking positions and puts them at a disadvantage as potential candidates for advancement.&lt;ref&gt;Nevill, Ginny, Alice Pennicott, Joanna Williams, and Ann Worrall. ''Women in the Workforce: The Effect of Demographic Changes in the 1990s''. London: The Industrial Society, 1990, p. 39, ISBN 978-0-85290-655-2.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=US Department of Labor|title=Good for Business: Making Full Use of the Nation's Human Capital|url=http://www.dol.gov/oasam/programs/history/reich/reports/ceiling.htm|publisher=Office of the Secretary|accessdate=9 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==
The concept of the glass ceiling was originally introduced outside of print media at the National Press Club in July 1979.{{Citation needed|date=June 2016}}  This was at a Conference of the Women's Institute for Freedom of the Press led by Katherine Lawrence of [[Hewlett-Packard]]. This was part of an ongoing discussion of a clash between written policy of promotion versus action opportunities for women at HP. The term was coined by Lawrence and HP manager Maryanne Schreiber.

The term was later used in March 1984 by Gay Bryant. She was the former editor of ''Working Woman'' magazine and was changing jobs to be the editor of ''[[Family Circle]].'' In an ''[[Adweek]]'' article written by Nora Frenkel, Bryant was reported as saying, "Women have reached a certain point—I call it the glass ceiling. They're in the top of middle management and they're stopping and getting stuck. There isn't enough room for all those women at the top. Some are going into business for themselves. Others are going out and raising families."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title=The Up-and-Comers; Bryant Takes Aim At the Settlers-In |last=Frenkiel |first=Nora |journal=Adweek |volume=Special Report |date=March 1984 |publisher=Magazine World}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Cornell&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/research/questionofthemonth/jan05.html |title=Question of the Month: Where did the term 'glass ceiling' originate? |date=January 2005 |author=Catherwood Library reference librarians |publisher=Cornell University, ILR School |accessdate=June 30, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Success&gt;{{cite book |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Y71-YCYv-48C&amp;pg=PA9&amp;lpg=PA9 |pages=9–10 |title=Women in Media Careers: Success Despite the Odds |first1=Lee |last1=Bollinger |first2=Carole |last2=O'Neill |publisher=University Press of America |year=2008 |isbn=978-0-7618-4133-3}}&lt;/ref&gt; Also in 1984, Bryant used the term in a chapter of the book ''The Working Woman Report: Succeeding in Business in the 1980s.'' In the same book, Basia Hellwig used the term in another chapter.&lt;ref name=Cornell /&gt;

In a widely cited article in the ''[[Wall Street Journal]]'' in March 1986 the term was used in the
article's title: "The Glass Ceiling: Why Women Can't Seem to Break The Invisible Barrier That Blocks Them From the Top Jobs". The article was written by Carol Hymowitz and Timothy D. Schellhardt. Hymowitz and Schellhardt introduced glass ceiling was "not something that could be found in any corporate manual or even discussed at a business meeting; it was originally introduced as an invisible, covert, and unspoken phenomenon that existed to keep executive level leadership positions in the hands of Caucasian males."&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt;

As the term "Glass Ceiling" got more issued within society, public responded with differing ideas and opinions. Some argued that glass ceiling is a myth rather than a reality because women chose to stay home and showed less dedication to advance into executive suite.&lt;ref name=":3"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Wilson|first=Eleanor|date=September 4, 2014|title=Diversity, Culture and the Glass Ceiling|url=|journal=Journal of Cultural Diversity|doi=|pmid=|access-date=May 3, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; As a result of continuing public debate, the [[United States Department of Labor|US Labor Department]]'s chief, [[Lynn Morley Martin]], reported the results of a research project called "The Glass Ceiling Initiative" formed to investigate the low numbers of women and minorities in executive positions. This report defined the new term as "those artificial barriers based on attitudinal or organizational bias that prevent qualified individuals from advancing upward in their organization into management-level positions."&lt;ref name="Cornell" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Success" /&gt;

In 1991, as a part of Title II of the Civil Right Act of 1991,&lt;ref name=":2"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Redwood|first=Rene A.|date=October 13, 1995|title=Breaking The Glass Ceiling: Good for Business, Good for America|url=http://search.proquest.com/openview/720eed4717a4012eb80aeb984880623c/1?pq-origsite=gscholar&amp;cbl=27059|journal=National Council of Jewish Women|doi=|pmid=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Congress created the Glass Ceiling Commission. This 21 member Presidential Commission was chaired by Secretary of Labor Robert Reich,&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt; and was created to study the "barriers to the advancement of minorities and women within corporate hierarchies (the problem known as the glass ceiling), to issue a report on its findings and conclusions, and to make recommendations on ways to dis- mantle the glass ceiling."&lt;ref name="DOL2" /&gt; The commission conducted extensive research including, surveys, public hearings and interviews, and released their findings in a report in 1995.&lt;ref name="DOL1" /&gt; The report, "Good for Business", offered "tangible guidelines and solutions on how these barriers can be overcome and eliminated".&lt;ref name="DOL2" /&gt; The goal of the commission was to provide recommendations on how to shatter the glass ceiling, specifically in the world of business. The report issued 12 recommendations on how to improve the workplace by increasing diversity in the organization and reducing discrimination through policy&lt;ref name="DOL2" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Johns|first=Merida L.|date=January 1, 2013|title=Breaking the Glass Ceiling: Structural, Cultural, and Organizational Barriers Preventing Women from Achieving Senior and Executive Positions|url=|journal=Perspectives in Health Information Management|doi=|pmid=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Breaking The Glass Ceiling: Can Women Reach The Top Of America's Largest Corporations? Updated Edition|last=Morrison|first=Ann|last2=White|first2=Randall P.|last3=Velsor|first3=Ellen Van|publisher=Personnel Decisions, Inc.|year=1982|isbn=|location=Beverly, MA|pages=xii}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Number of women CEOs from the [[Fortune 500|Fortune Lists]] has been increasing from 2012–2014,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.catalyst.org/knowledge/fortune-500-ceo-positions-held-women|title=Fortune 500 CEO Positions Held By Women|last=jcombopiano|date=2012-11-27|website=Catalyst|access-date=2016-05-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; but ironically women's labor force participation rate decreased from 52.4% to 49.6% between 1995 and 2015 globally. However, it is evident that some countries like Australia has increased the labor force participation of women over 27% since 1978.  Furthermore, only 19.2% of [[S&amp;P 500 Index|S&amp;P 500 Board Seats]] were held by women in 2014, of whom 80.2% were considered white.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.catalyst.org/knowledge/statistical-overview-women-workforce|title=Statistical Overview of Women in the Workforce|last=acostigan|date=2012-10-17|website=Catalyst|access-date=2016-05-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Gender pay gap ==
{{See also|Gender pay gap|Gender pay gap in the United States}}

The gender pay gap is the difference between male and female earnings. In 2008 the [[OECD]] found that the median earnings of female full-time workers were 17% lower than the earnings of their male counterparts and that "30% of the variation in gender wage gaps across OECD countries can be explained by discriminatory practices in the [[Labour economics|labour market]]."&lt;ref&gt;[[OECD]]. [http://www.oecd.org/dataoecd/8/19/40937574.pdf ''OECD Employment Outlook – 2008 Edition Summary in English''.] OECD, Paris, 2008, p. 3-4.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="oecd2"&gt;[[OECD]]. [http://www.oecd.org/dataoecd/36/17/43244511.pdf ''OECD Employment Outlook. Chapter 3: The Price of Prejudice: Labour Market Discrimination on the Grounds of Gender and Ethnicity''.] OECD, Paris, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[European Commission]] found that women's hourly earnings were 17.5% lower on average in the 27 [[Member state of the European Union|EU Member States]] in 2008.&lt;ref&gt;[[European Commission]]. [http://ec.europa.eu/social/main.jsp?catId=685&amp;langId=en ''The situation in the EU''.] Retrieved on July 12, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; As of April 2016 the wage gap in the United States was "79 cents for every dollar paid to men, amounting to an annual gender wage gap $10,762".&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=National Partnership for Women and Families, comp.|first=|date=April 2016|title=America's Women and The Wage Gap|url=http://www.nationalpartnership.org/research-library/workplace-fairness/fair-pay/americas-women-and-the-wage-gap.pdf|journal=Trade, Jobs and Wages|doi=|pmid=|access-date=2 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; The wage gap is an even bigger problem for women of color. African American women are paid 60 cents to every dollar a white man makes while Latina women are paid only 55 cents. "Two Asian women are paid 84 cents for every dollar paid to white" men.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;

Although people argue that the gender pay gap is not relevant anymore, statistics show that it will take at least 70 years from now for the gap to close. According to the United States International Labor Rights Forum, every single country in the world suffers from gender pay gaps by margins of up to 40 percent.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|publisher=International Labor Rights Forum.|url= http://www.laborrights.org/issues/women’s-rights|title=Womens Rights|last=|first=|date=|website=|access-date=May 2, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; The United States ranks 65th in pay equality, and women are in the majority of most poverty stricken in America.{{citationneeded|date=November 2016}}

In her article "Women and Politics", Irina Zamfirache claims that the glass ceiling can be explained by woman's place in society. Statistically the gender pay gap is decreasing over time, which seems appropriate seeing as women are no longer portrayed as housewives.  However, according to Zamfirache despite the media still projecting a disadvantageous image of women, the change of stereotypes and perceptions of not only women but also minorities suggests that the glass ceiling can eventually be dissolved.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|url = |title = Women and politics – the glass ceiling|last = Zamfirache|first = Irina|date = 2010|journal = Journal of Comparative Research in Anthropology and Sociology|doi = |pmid = |access-date = }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== {{visible anchor|Glass escalator|Glass Escalator}} ==
In addition to the glass ceiling, which already is stopping women from climbing higher in success in the workplace, a parallel phenomenon called the "glass escalator" is occurring. This can be defined as how more men are joining fields that were previously occupied mainly by women, such as nursing and teaching, and within these job fields, the men are riding right past women and going straight to the top, similarly to if they were on an escalator and a woman was taking stairs. Men are being offered more promotions than women and even though women have worked just as hard, they are still not being offered the same chances as men are in some circumstances.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title = A New Obstacle For Professional Women: The Glass Escalator|url = http://www.forbes.com/sites/jennagoudreau/2012/05/21/a-new-obstacle-for-professional-women-the-glass-escalator/|website = Forbes|accessdate = 2015-10-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; The chart from Carolyn K. Broner, Ph.D. shows an example of the glass escalator in favor of men for female-dominant occupations in schools.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title = MEN, WOMEN, &amp; THE GLASS ESCALATOR|url = http://www.womenonbusiness.com/men-women-the-glass-escalator/|website = Women on Business|accessdate = 2015-10-23|language = en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt; While women have mostly occupied the position of teachers, men are taking the higher positions in school systems as deans or principals.

According to this scholarly article,&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://socpro.oxfordjournals.org/content/55/2/271|title=Revisiting the Glass Escalator: The Case of Gender Segregation in a Female Dominated Occupation|first1=Karrie Ann|last1=Snyder|first2=Adam Isaiah|last2=Green|date=1 May 2008|publisher=|volume=55|issue=2|pages=271–299|via=socpro.oxfordjournals.org|doi=10.1525/sp.2008.55.2.271}}&lt;/ref&gt; "men encounter powerful social pressures that direct them away from entering female-dominated occupations (Jacobs 1989, 1993)." Since female-dominated occupations are usually characterized with more feminine activities, men who enter these jobs can be perceived socially as "effeminate, homosexual, or sexual predators".&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; Research on the career paths of men who have occupations in female-dominated fields, such as nursing or teaching, come to a conclusion that men benefit financially from their gender status. This can be extended to say that men are able to abuse their gender advantages in such contexts, often "reaping the benefits of their token status to reach higher levels in female-dominated work."{{citationneeded|date=November 2016}}  Not only are males taking power from women in more female oriented jobs, but they are rising to the top more steadily than females.

== Sticky floor ==
In the literature on gender discrimination, the concept of "sticky floors" complements the concept of a glass ceiling. Sticky floors can be described as the pattern that women are, compared to men, less likely to start to climb the job ladder. Thereby, this phenomenon is related to gender differentials at the bottom of the wage distribution. Building on the seminal study by Booth and co-authors in European Economic Review,&lt;ref&gt;Booth, A. L., Francesconi, M., Frank, J. (2003)   A sticky floors model of promotion, pay, and gender, European Economic Review, 47, 295-322 {{DOI|10.1016/S0014-2921(01)00197-0}}.&lt;/ref&gt; during the last decade economists have attempted to identify sticky floors in the labour market.  They found empirical evidence for the existence of sticky floors in countries such as Australia, Belgium, Italy, Thailand and the United States.&lt;ref&gt;Baert, S., De Pauw, A.-S., Deschacht, N. (2016)  Do Employer Preferences Contribute to Sticky Floors? ILR Review, {{DOI|10.1177/0019793915625213}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== The frozen middle ==
Similar to the sticky floor, the frozen middle describes the phenomenon of women's progress up the corporate ladder slowing, if not halting, in the ranks of middle management.&lt;ref&gt;Martell, Richard F., et al. "Sex Stereotyping In The Executive Suite: `Much Ado About Something'." Journal Of Social Behavior &amp; Personality (1998) 127-138. Web.&lt;/ref&gt; Originally the term referred to the resistance corporate upper management faced from middle management when issuing directives. Due to a lack of ability or lack of drive in the ranks of middle management these directives do not come into fruition and as a result the company's bottom line suffers.The term was popularized by a Harvard Business Review article titled Middle Management Excellence.&lt;ref&gt;Byrnes, Jonathan. "Middle Management Excellence." Harvard Business Review 5 Dec. 2005 pag. print&lt;/ref&gt; Due to the growing proportion of women to men in the workforce, however, the term "frozen middle" has become more commonly ascribed to the aforementioned slowing of the careers of women in middle management.&lt;ref&gt;Lyness, Karen S., and Donna E. Thompson. "Climbing The Corporate Ladder: Do Female And Male Executives Follow The Same Route?." Journal Of Applied Psychology (2000) 86-101. Web.&lt;/ref&gt; The 1996 study "A Study of the Career Development and Aspirations of Women in Middle Management" posits that social structures and networks within businesses that favor "good old boys" and norms of masculinity exist based on the experiences of women surveyed.&lt;ref&gt;Wentling, Rose Mary. "Women In Middle Management: Their Career Development And Aspirations." Business Horizon (1992) 47. Web.&lt;/ref&gt; According to the study, women who did not exhibit stereotypical masculine traits, (e.g. aggressiveness, thick skin, lack of emotional expression) and interpersonal communication tendencies are at an inherent disadvantage compared to their male peers.&lt;ref&gt;Wentling, Rose Mary. "Women In Middle Management: Their Career Development And Aspirations." Business Horizon, p. 252 (1992) 47. Web.&lt;/ref&gt; As the ratio of men to women increases in the upper levels of management,&lt;ref&gt;Helfat, Constance E., Dawn Harris, and Paul J. Wolfson. "The Pipeline To The Top: Women And Men In The Top Executive Ranks Of U.S. Corporations." Academy Of Management Perspectives (2006) 42-64. Web.&lt;/ref&gt; women's access to female mentors who could advise them on ways to navigate office politics is limited, further inhibiting upward mobility within a corporation or firm.&lt;ref&gt;Dezso, Cristian L., David Gaddis Ross, and Jose Uribe. "Is There An Implicit Quota On Women In Top Management? A Large-Sample Statistical Analysis." Strategic Management Journal (2016) 98-115. Web.&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, the frozen middle affects female professionals in western and eastern countries such as the United States and Malaysia, respectively,&lt;ref&gt;Mandy Mok Kim, Man, Miha Skerlavaj, and Vlado Dimovski. "Is There A 'Glass Ceiling' For Mid-Level Female Managers?." International Journal Of Management &amp; Innovation (2009) 1-13. Web.&lt;/ref&gt; as well as women in a variety of fields ranging from the aforementioned corporations to STEM fields.&lt;ref&gt;Cundiff, Jessica, and Theresa Vescio. "Gender Stereotypes Influence How People Explain Gender Disparities In The Workplace." Sex Roles (2016): 126-138. Web.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Glass Ceiling Index ==
In 2016, the ''Economist'' updated their glass-ceiling index. It combines data on higher education, labour-force participation, pay, child-care costs, maternity rights, business-school applications and representation in senior jobs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.economist.com/blogs/graphicdetail/2015/03/daily-chart-1|title=Daily chart: The glass-ceiling index|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; The countries where inequality was lowest were, in order of most equality, Iceland, Norway, Sweden, Finland, and Hungary, which three of the five are the same as 2015 however Iceland and Hungary were not on the top 5 list before. Iceland had the lowest difference with women earning a score of 82.6 out of 100 as to what men make.

== Second shift ==
The second shift focuses on the idea that women ultimately work a second shift in the sense of having a greater workload, not just doing a greater share of domestic work, but it is obscure because it largely. All of the task that are engaged in outside of the workplace are mainly tied to motherhood. Depending on location, household income, educational attainment, ethnicity and location. Data shows that women do work a second shift in the sense of having a greater workload, not just doing a greater share of domestic work, but this is not apparent if simultaneous activity is overlooked.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Craig|first=Lyn|year=2007|title=is herre really a second shift, and if so, who does it? a time-diary investigation|url=|journal=Feminist Review|volume=86|pages=149-170|jstor=30140855}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Mommy Track ==
"Mommy Track" is a term describing women who simply disregard their career and professional duties in order to satisfy the needs of their families. Women are often subject to long work hours which places an imbalance within the work-family schedule.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Hill|first=E. Jeffery|last2=Martinson|first2=Vjkollca K.|last3=Baker|first3=Robin Zenger|last4=Ferris|first5=Maria|year=2004|title=Beyond The Mommy Track: The Influence of New Concept Part-Time Work for Professional Women on Work and Family|url=|journal=Journal of Family and economic Issues|volume=25|pages=|via=Google Scholar}}&lt;/ref&gt; There is research suggesting that women were able to function on a part-time professional schedule compared to others working full time while still engaging in external family activities and that a flexible work arrangement allows for the achievement of a healthy work and family balance.

== See also ==
{{div col|3}}

* [[Celluloid ceiling]]
* [[Equal Pay Day]]
* [[Equal pay for women]]
* [[Female labor force in the Muslim world]]
* [[Feminization of poverty]]
* [[Gender equality]]
* [[Gender inequality]]
* [[Gender pay gap]]
* [[Gender role]]
* [[Glass cliff]]
* [[Material feminism]]
* [[Mommy track]]
* [[Sex differences in humans]]
* [[Sexism]]
* [[Stained-glass ceiling]]
* [[Superwoman (sociology)]]
* [[Time bind]]
* [[Work–life balance]]
{{div col end}}

== References ==
{{Reflist|2|refs=Wiley, John. The Blackwell Encyclopedia of Gender and Sexuality Studies. Vol. 5. Chicester: John Wiley and Sons, 2012. Print}}

== Bibliography ==
* Cholensky, Stephanie. "The Gender Pay Gap: NO MORE EXCUSES!." ''Judgment &amp; Decision Making'' 10.2 (2015): 15-16. ''Academic Search Complete''. Web. 22 Oct. 2015.
* {{Cite report | last = Federal Glass Ceiling Commission | title = Good for business: Making full use of the nation's human capital  | publisher = [[United States Department of Labor|U.S. Department of Labor]] | location = Washington DC  | date = March 1995a | url = http://www.dol.gov/oasam/programs/history/reich/reports/ceiling.pdf | format = pdf | ref = harv }}
* {{cite book | last1 = Fox | first1 = Mary | last2 = Hesse-Biber | first2 = Sharlene N. | title = Women at work | publisher = Mayfield Publishing Company | location = Palo Alto, California | year = 1984 | isbn = 978-0-87484-525-9 }}
* {{cite book | last1 = Giele | first1 = Janet Z. | last2 = Stebbins | first2 = Leslie F | author-link1 = Janet Zollinger Giele | title = Women and equality in the workplace a reference handbook | publisher = ABC-CLIO | location = Santa Barbara, California | year = 2003 | isbn = 978-1-57607-937-9 }}
* {{cite book | last1 = Hesse-Biber | first1 = Sharlene N. | last2 = Carter | first2 = Gregg L. | title = Working women in America : split dreams | publisher = Oxford University Press | location = New York, New York | year = 2005 | isbn = 978-0-19-515047-6 }}
* {{Cite journal | last1 = Lyness | first1 = Karen S. | last2 = Thompson | first2 = Donna E. | title = Above the glass ceiling? A comparison of matched samples of female and male executives | journal = [[Journal of Applied Psychology]] | volume = 82 | issue = 3 | pages = 359–375 | publisher = [[American Psychological Association]] | doi = 10.1037/0021-9010.82.3.359 | date = June 1997  | ref = harv }}
* National Partnership for Women and Families, comp. (April 2016). "America's Women and The Wage Gap" (PDF). ''Trade, Jobs and Wages''. Retrieved 2 May 2016.
* {{Cite journal | last1 = Ponnuswamy | first1 = Indra | last2 = Manohar | first2 = Hansa Lysander | title = Breaking the glass ceiling – a mixed methods study using Watkins and Marsick's learning organisation culture model | journal = [[Asian Women (journal)|Asian Women]] | volume = 30 | issue = 3 | pages = 85–111 | publisher = Research Institute of Asian Women (RIAW) | doi = 10.14431/aw.2014.09.30.3.85 | date = September 2014  | ref = harv }}
* Redwood, Rene A. (October 13, 1995). "Breaking The Glass Ceiling: Good for Business, Good for America". ''National Council of Jewish Women''.
* {{Citation | last1 = Schneps | first1 = Leila | last2 = Colmez | first2 = Coralie | author-link1 = Leila Schneps | author-link2 = Coralie Colmez | contribution = Math error number 6: Simpson's paradox. The Berkeley sex bias case: discrimination detection | editor-last1 = Schneps | editor-first1 = Leila | editor-last2 = Colmez | editor-first2 = Coralie | editor-link1 = Leila Schneps | editor-link2 = Coralie Colmez | title = Math on trial: how numbers get used and abused in the courtroom | pages = 107–120 | publisher = Basic Books | location = New York | year = 2013 | isbn = 978-0-465-03292-1 | ref = harv }}
* Snyder, Karrie Ann, and Adam Isaiah Green. "Revisiting The Glass Escalator: The Case Of Gender Segregation In A Female Dominated Occupation." ''Social Problems'' 55.2 (2008): 271-299. ''Academic Search Complete''. Web. 22 Oct. 2015.
* Snyder, Karrie Ann, and Adam Isaiah Green. "Revisiting The Glass Escalator: The Case Of Gender Segregation In A Female Dominated Occupation." ''Social Problems'' 55.2 (2008): 271-299. ''Academic Search Complete''. Web. 22 Oct. 2015.
* Woodhams, Carol, Ben Lupton, and Marc Cowling. "The Presence Of Ethnic Minority And Disabled Men In Feminised Work: Intersectionality, Vertical Segregation And The Glass Escalator." ''Sex Roles'' 72.7/8 (2015): 277-293. ''Academic Search Complete''. Web. 22 Oct. 2015.
* Malpas, J., "Donald Davidson", ''The Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy'' (Winter 2012 Edition), Edward N. Zalta (ed.), &lt;http://plato.stanford.edu/archives/win2012/entries/davidson/&gt;. Web 2 May 2016.
* International Labor Rights Forum. (n.d.). Retrieved May 2, 2016, from http://www.laborrights.org/issues/women’s-rights
* Hyun, Jane. Breaking the Bamboo Ceiling: Career Strategies for Asians. New York: HarperBusiness, 2005. Print.
* Wiley, John. ''The Blackwell Encyclopedia of Gender and Sexuality Studies''. Vol. 5. Chicester: John Wiley and Sons, 2012. Print.
* "Top 10 Numbers that Show Why Pay Equity Matters to Asian American Women and Their Families". Retrieved 2016-05-01

== External links ==
*Catalyst research report (1996). [http://www.catalyst.org/file/219/women%20in%20corporate%20leadership%20-%20progress%20and%20prospects%201996.pdf ''Women in Corporate Leadership'': Progr (2003).] [http://www.catalyst.org/file/74/women%20and%20men%20in%20u.s.%20corporate%20leadership%20same%20workplace,%20different%20realities.pdf ''Women and Men in U.S. Corporate Leadership: Same Workplace, Different Realities?'']
*Catalyst. [http://www.catalyst.org/publication/145/women-and-men-in-us-corporate-leadership-same-workplace-different-realities ''Women and Men in U.S. Corporate Leadership: Same Workplace, Different Realities?''] New York, N.Y.: Catalyst, 2004, ISBN 978-0-89584-247-3.
*Catalyst. [http://www.catalyst.org/file/420/2010_financial_post_500_women_senior_officers_and_top_earners_final.pdf ''2010 Catalyst Census: Financial Post 500 Women Senior Officers and Top Earners''.]
*Federal Glass Ceiling Commission. [http://www.dol.gov/oasam/programs/history/reich/reports/ceiling.pdf ''Good for Business: Making Full Use of the Nation's Human Capital.''] Washington, D.C.: U.S. Department of Labor, March 1995.
*Federal Glass Ceiling Commission. [http://www.dol.gov/oasam/programs/history/reich/reports/ceiling2.pdf ''Solid Investments: Making Full Use of the Nation's Human Capital''.] Washington, D.C.: U.S. Department of Labor, November 1995.
*Carvajal, Doreen. [http://www.nytimes.com/2011/01/27/world/27iht-rules27.html ''The Codes That Need to Be Broken''.] ''The New York Times'', January 26, 2011.
*Cotter, David A., Joan M. Hermsen, Seth Ovadia, and Reece Vanneman (2001). [http://www.bsos.umd.edu/socy/vanneman/papers/CotterHOV01.pdf ''The glass ceiling effect''.] '''Social Forces''', Vol. 80 No. 2, pp.&amp;nbsp;655–81.
*[http://cjournal.cz/files/130.pdf Effects of Glass Ceiling on Women Career Development in Private Sector Organizations – Case of Sri Lanka]

{{Discrimination}}
{{Portal bar|Anthropology|Sociology}}

[[Category:Racism]]
[[Category:Feminist economics]]
[[Category:Sexism]]
[[Category:Employment discrimination]]
[[Category:Words coined in the 1970s]]
[[Category:Women-related neologisms]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>