<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20071108011857|170004215" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="637623" pageid="637623" ns="0" title="Glass ceiling"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-11-08T17:24:26Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">The term '''glass ceiling''' refers to situations where the advancement of a qualified person within the hierarchy of an organization is halted at a particular level because of some form of discrimination, most commonly [[sexism]] or [[racism]].

This situation is referred to as a "ceiling" as there is a limitation blocking upward advancement, and  "glass" (transparent) because the limitation is not immediately apparent and is normally an unwritten and unofficial policy.  The "glass ceiling" is distinguished from formal barriers to advancement, such as education or experience requirements.

==History==
Sex discrimination was outlawed in 1964 through the &lt;cite&gt;[[Civil Rights Act]]&lt;/cite&gt; in the hopes of allowing women to rise in the working world once proper experience has been achieved. 
 
The term "glass ceiling" has been thought to have first been used to refer to invisible barriers that impede the career advancement of women in the American workforce in an article by Carol Hymowitz and Timothy Schellhardt in the [[March 24]]th edition of the &lt;cite&gt;[[Wall Street Journal]]&lt;/cite&gt; in 1986.&lt;ref&gt; Baker &amp; Lightle, Cracks in the glass ceiling: An analysis of gender equity in the federal government auditing career field (2001), 18-26 [1] &lt;/ref&gt; However, the term was used prior to that; for instance, it was utilized in a March 1984 ''Adweek'' article by Gay Bryant.

== Breaking through ‘The Glass Ceiling’ ==
 
A senior V.P. at Patterson-- Smith Associates explains that women have succeeded in becoming prosperous agents, due to the fact that “they're more detail-oriented, more relationship-oriented and they relate well to clients.” &lt;ref&gt; C. McDonald, Women agents say they are breaking the glass ceiling(2001), 45 [2] &lt;/ref&gt;. 

&lt;!-- Image with unknown copyright status removed: [[Image:glassceiling.jpg]] --&gt;

== Variations and related terms ==
* '''Bamboo Ceiling''' - The exclusion of Asian-Americans from executive and managerial roles on the basis of subjective factors such as "lack of leadership potential" or "inferior communication ability" where the Asian-American candidate has superior objective credentials.
* '''Glass elevator''' (or '''glass escalator''') - The rapid promotion of men over women, especially into management, in female-dominated fields such as [[nursing]].
* [[Glass cliff]] - A situation wherein someone has been promoted into a risky, difficult job where the chances of failure are higher.
* [[Celluloid ceiling]], referring  to the small number of women in top positions in Hollywood, as documented by Lauzen (2002) and others.

=="Glass Ceiling" in popular culture==
Canadian indie rock band [[Metric (band)|Metric]] wrote a song called "Glass Ceiling" on their [[2005]] album &lt;i&gt;[[Live It Out]]&lt;/i&gt;, which is a reference to this type of situation.

The effect has also inspired a musical, bearing the same name. "Glass Ceiling" ([[2006]]), written by Bret VandenBos and Alex Krall, examined and parodied the idiosyncrasies of both males and females in the corporate workplace.&lt;ref&gt;
  {{cite web
  | last = Mays
  | first = Andy
  | title = NCA Cappies Album for "Glass Ceiling"
  | publisher = [[Cappies]]
  | date = July 2006
  | url = http://gallery.cappies.com/v/NationalCapitalAreaCappies/showcase06/performance/?g2_page=8
  | accessdate = 2007-04-19 }} &lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Stained-glass ceiling]]
* [[Equal pay for women]]
* [[Sexism]]
* [[Feminism]]
* [[Feminization of poverty]]
* [[Social equality|Equality]]
* [[Gender role]]
* [[Employment]]
* [[Glass cliff]]
* [[Masculism]]
* [[Racism]]

== Footnotes ==

&lt;!--See http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Footnotes for an explanation of how to generate footnotes using the &lt;ref(erences/)&gt; tags--&gt;
&lt;references/&gt;

== External links ==

*[http://www.apesma.asn.au/newsviews/professional_update/2000/may/glass_ceiling.htm Dealing with the Glass Ceiling] 

* [http://moviesbywomen.com/stats_celluloid_ceiling_2006.php Celluloid Ceiling: Behind-the-Scenes Employment of Women on the Top 250 Films of 2006] at [http://moviesbywomen.com Movies by Women]
* [http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/catherwood/Collections/CollectionGuides/glassceiling.html Report of the Glass Ceiling Commission] ([[Portable Document Format|PDF]] format)
*[http://digital.library.unt.edu/govdocs/crs/search.tkl?q=pay+equity&amp;search_crit=title&amp;search=Search&amp;date1=Anytime&amp;date2=Anytime&amp;type=form Read Congressional Research Service (CRS) Reports regarding Pay Equity]
*

{{fem-stub}}

[[Category:Feminism]]
[[Category:Racism]]
[[Category:Socioeconomics]]
[[Category:Economic problems]]

[[de:Gläserne Decke]]
[[fr:Plafond de verre]]
[[he:תקרת הזכוכית]]
[[ja:ガラスの天井]]
[[nl:Glazen plafond]]
[[pl:Szklany sufit]]
[[zh:玻璃天花板]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>