<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20051101194653|27095895" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="637623" pageid="637623" ns="0" title="Glass ceiling"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-11-09T01:54:31Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">A '''glass ceiling''' is an unofficial barrier to an upper [[management]] or other prominent position within a [[company]] or other organization which certain groups, particularly [[women]], are perceived to be unable to cross, due to discrimination. The term refers to the inconspicuous nature of such barriers, compared to formal barriers to career advancement. It is often credited as having been originally coined by Carol Hymowitz and Timothy Schellhardt in the [[March 24]] [[1986]] edition of the &lt;cite&gt;[[Wall Street Journal]]&lt;/cite&gt;. However, the term was used prior to that e.g. in a March 1984 Adweek article by Gay Bryant.

The term '''glass elevator''' is sometimes used to describe the rapid promotion of men over women, especially into management, in female-dominated fields like [[nursing]].

The term '''glass cliff''' describes a situation wherein someone, particularly a [[woman]], has been promoted into a risky, difficult job where the chances of failure are higher.

There is also a sometimes-used term '''glass floor''' which describes the theory that some factor both limits a group's (often women's) progress but also limits their numbers in situations like, say, imprisonment and the disproportionate numbers of male inmates. Biological factors are often quoted for these, although contentious.

The phrase '''glass floor''' is also sometimes used to describe the fact that men almost always occupy the least pleasant jobs in a society - [[sewage]] workers, [[mine]]rs, street cleaners, [[refuse]] workers etc.

The political aspects of these concepts limit the ability of research to clarify the issue.

==Worldwide statistics==

{| cellpadding="4" cellspacing="0"  border="1" valign="top" align=right
|+ '''Female share of seats in elected national chambers in November 2004 (percent)'''
|[[Sweden]]||45.3
|-
|[[Denmark]]||38.0
|-
|[[Finland]]||37.5
|-
|[[Norway]]||36.4
|-
|[[Netherlands]]||35.0
|-
|[[Germany]]||32.8
|-
|[[Iceland]]||30.2
|-
|[[New Zealand]]||28.3
|-
|[[Austria]]||27.5
|-
|[[Canada]]||21.1
|-
|[[China]]||20.2
|-
|[[United Kingdom|UK]](Commons)||17.8
|-
|[[United States]]||15.0
|-
|[[Japan]]||7.1
|}
The following is a sampling of statistics related to the relative status of women worldwide.

* Worldwide, women work more than men, when both paid employment and unpaid household tasks are accounted for, according to the [http://hdr.undp.org/reports/global/2004/pdf/hdr04_HDI.pdf United Nations Human Development Report 2004:  Section 28, Gender, Work Burden, and Time Allocation].  In rural areas of the developing countries surveyed, women perform an average of 20% more work than men, or an additional 98 minutes per day.  In the OECD countries surveyed, on average women performed 5% more work than men, or 18 minutes per day.
*Women own only 1 percent of the world's wealth, and earn 10 percent of the world's income, despite making up 49.5 percent of the population.  
*Women are underrepresented in all of the world's major legislative bodies (see [http://www.ipu.org/wmn-e/world.htm Women in National Parliaments, November 2004]). In [[1985]], [[Finland]] had the largest percentage of women in national legislature at approximately 32 percent (P. Norris, Women&lt;nowiki&gt;'s&lt;/nowiki&gt; Legislative Participation in Western Europe, ''West European Politics''). Currently, [[Sweden]] has the highest number of women at 45 percent. The [[United States]] has just 14 percent. The world average is just 9 percent. ([[Wales]], while not an independent country has 50% of its members being women.)

== See also ==

* [[Stained-glass Ceiling]]
* [[Rubber ceiling]]
* [[Equal pay for women]]
* [[Sexism]]
* [[Feminism]]
* [[Social equality|Equality]]
* [[Gender role]]
* [[Employment]]

== External links ==

* [http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/keyWorkplaceDocuments/government/federal/Glassceilingreport.html Report of the Glass Ceiling Commission] ([[Portable Document Format|PDF]] format)

{{fem-stub}}

[[Category:Feminism]]
[[Category:Socioeconomics]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>