<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20040926080400|6911088" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="637623" pageid="637623" ns="0" title="Glass ceiling"><revisions><rev timestamp="2004-10-27T21:19:07Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">A '''glass ceiling''' is an unofficial barrier to an upper [[management]] or such prominent position within a [[company]] or other organization which certain groups, particularly [[women]], are perceived to be unable to cross.  The term refers to the removal of formal barriers to career advancement when it is nevertheless believed that these groups are still kept out via [[discrimination]].  It was originally coined by Carol Hymowitz and Timothy Schellhardt in the March 24, 1986 edition of the Wall Street Journal.

The term '''glass elevator''' is sometimes used to describe the rapid promotion of men over women, especially into management, in female-dominated fields like [[nursing]].

The term '''glass cliff''' describes a situation wherein someone, particularly a [[woman]], has been promoted into a risky, difficult job where the chances of failure are higher.

== See also ==

* [[Equal pay for women]]
* [[Sexism]]
* [[Feminism]]
* [[Social equality|Equality]]
* [[Gender role]]
* [[Employment]]

== External links ==

* [http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/keyWorkplaceDocuments/government/federal/Glassceilingreport.html Report of the Glass Ceiling Commission] ([[Portable Document Format|PDF]] format)

{{stub}}

[[Category:Feminism]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>