<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20111118195245|461322582" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="20491560" pageid="20491560" ns="0" title="Ugly law"><revisions><rev timestamp="2011-11-18T22:52:43Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">From the late 1860s until the 1970s, several American cities had '''ugly laws''' making it illegal for persons with "unsightly or disgusting" disabilities to appear in public. Some of these laws were called '''Unsightly Beggar Ordinances'''. The goal of these laws was seemingly to preserve the quality of life for the community, similar in spirit to current [[homeowners association]] regulations and by-laws. 

==Examples==
The first appearance of the ordinance seems to date to 1867 in San Francisco, California.&lt;ref&gt;Schweik, Susan. The Ugly Laws (NYU Press 2009)&lt;/ref&gt; The ordinance seems to have been welcomed particularly from the 1880s on in Western and particularly Midwestern cities with strong, networked cultures of reform, towns bound to each other and the rest of the nation by railroad ties. Its zone extended eastward, too. The state of Pennsylvania passed a state version of the law in the early 1890s. Some New Yorkers, inspired by Pennsylvania, made an unsuccessful attempt to get a city ordinance passed in 1895.&lt;ref&gt;Brown, Patricia Leigh. "Viewing Ahab and Barbie Through the Lens of Disability." New York Times (August 20, 2000) as quoted by http://www.accessmylibrary.com/coms2/summary_0286-29736932_ITM&lt;/ref&gt;
* Chicago, Illinois. The most commonly cited Ugly Law is that of the "City of Chicago Ordinance, 1911" which is often unsourced.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.accessmylibrary.com/coms2/summary_0286-29736932_ITM Begging the question: disability, mendicancy, speech and the law.(Viewpoint essay), 01-JAN-07, Schweik, Susan, Ohio State University Press]&lt;/ref&gt; However, the Chicago Municipal Code, sec. 36034 did include an ordinance that provided:
:&lt;blockquote&gt;No person who is diseased, maimed, mutilated or in any way deformed so as to be an unsightly or disgusting object or improper person to be allowed in or on the public ways or other public places in this city, or shall therein or thereon expose himself to public view, under a penalty of not less than one dollar nor more than fifty dollars for each offense.&lt;ref name="chicago"&gt;Chicago Municipal Code, sec. 36034 (repealed 1974).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
* Columbus, Ohio. General Offense Code, sec. 2387.04.&lt;ref name="ohio"&gt;Columbus, Ohio General Offense Code, sec. 2387.04 (1972).&lt;/ref&gt;
* Omaha, Nebraska. Unsightly Beggar Ordinance Nebraska Municipal Code of 1941, sec. 25.&lt;ref name="nebraska"&gt;Unsightly Beggar Ordinance, Omaha, Nebraska Municipal Code of 1941, sec. 25 (1967).&lt;/ref&gt; 

Punishments for being caught in public ranged from incarceration to fines of up to $50.00 USD for each offense.

==Ugly Laws Repealed==
Many states' ugly laws were not repealed until the mid 1970s.&lt;ref name="burgdorf"&gt;Marcia Pearce Burgdorf and Robert Burgdorf, Jr., “A History of Unequal Treatment: The Qualifications of Handicapped Persons as a Suspect Class Under the Equal Protection Clause,” Santa Clara Lawyer 15:4 (1975) 855-910.&lt;/ref&gt; Omaha repealed its Ugly Law in 1967. Columbus withdrew its in 1972. Chicago was the last to repeal its Ugly Law as late as 1974.

==Ugly Laws and the Americans with Disabilities Act==
The recantation of Ugly Laws were tied to the passing of the [[Americans with Disabilities Act]] of 1990 where certain rights were granted to [[people with disabilities]]:

&lt;blockquote&gt;Individuals with disabilities are a [[United States v. Carolene Products Co.#Footnote Four|discrete and insular minority]] who have been faced with restrictions and limitations, subjected to a history of purposeful unequal treatment, and relegated to a position of political powerlessness in our society, based on characteristics that are beyond the control of such individuals and resulting from stereotypic assumptions not truly indicative of the individual ability of such individuals to participate in, and contribute to, society.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==See also==
* [[Lookism]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Ugly Law}}
[[Category:Disability]]
[[Category:Disability rights]]

[[sv:Ugly law]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>