<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20201115214443|988892451" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1297768" pageid="1297768" ns="0" title="Political repression"><revisions><rev timestamp="2020-11-18T13:20:26Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Political repression''' is the act of a state entity controlling a citizenry by force for political reasons, particularly for the purpose of restricting or preventing the citizenry's ability to take part in the [[politics|political life]] of a [[society]], thereby reducing their standing among their fellow citizens.&lt;ref&gt;[[Christian Davenport|Davenport, Christian]] (2007). [http://www.cambridge.org/catalogue/catalogue.asp?isbn=0521864909 ''State Repression and the Domestic Democratic Peace''] New York: Cambridge University Press.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Davenport, Christian, Johnston, Hank and Mueller, Carol (2004). [http://www.upress.umn.edu/Books/D/davenport_repression.html ''Repression and Mobilization''] Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press.&lt;/ref&gt; It is often manifested through policies such as [[human rights]] violations, [[surveillance abuse]], [[police brutality]], [[imprisonment]], [[Involuntary settlements in the Soviet Union|involuntary settlement]], [[Lishenets|stripping of citizen's rights]], [[lustration]] and violent action or [[Terror (politics)|terror]] such as the murder, [[summary execution]]s, [[torture]], [[forced disappearance]] and other [[extrajudicial punishment]] of [[political activist]]s, [[dissident]]s, or general population.&lt;ref&gt;Kittrie, Nicholas N. 1995. ''The War Against Authority: From the Crisis of Legitimacy to a New Social Contract. Baltimore, MD: Johns Hopkins University Press.''&lt;/ref&gt; Political repression can also be reinforced by means outside of written policy, such as by public and private media ownership and by [[self-censorship]] within the public.

Where political repression is sanctioned and organised by the state, it may constitute [[state terrorism]], [[genocide]], politicide or [[crimes against humanity]]. Systemic and violent political repression is a typical feature of [[dictatorship]]s, [[totalitarianism|totalitarian]] states and similar regimes.&lt;ref&gt;Serge, Victor, 1979, ''What Everyone Should Know About State Repression, London: New Park Publications.''&lt;/ref&gt; Acts of political repression may be carried out by [[secret police]] forces, army, [[paramilitary]] groups or [[death squad]]s.  Repressive activities have also been found within democratic contexts as well.&lt;ref&gt;Donner, Frank J. (1980). ''The Age of Surveillance: The Aims and Methods of America’s Political Intelligence System''. New York: Alfred A. Knopf. {{ISBN|0-394-40298-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Donner, Frank J. (1990). ''Protectors of Privilege: Red Squads and Police Repression in Urban America.'' Berkeley: University of California Press. {{ISBN|0-520-05951-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; This can even include setting up situations where the death of the target of repression is the end result.&lt;ref&gt;Haas, Jeffrey. ''The Assassination of Fred Hampton: How the FBI and the Chicago Police Murdered a Black Panther.'' Chicago, Ill.: Lawrence Hill /Chicago Review, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; If political repression is not carried out with the approval of the state, a section of government may still be responsible. An example are the [[Federal Bureau of Investigation|FBI]] [[COINTELPRO]] operations in the United States between 1956 and 1971.&lt;ref&gt;''COINTELPRO: The FBI's Covert Action Programs Against American Citizens, Final Report of the Senate Committee to Study Governmental Operations with respect to Intelligence Activities.''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Cunningham, D. 2004. ''There’s something happening here: The New Left, the Klan, and FBI counterintelligence.'' Berkeley: Univ. of California.&lt;/ref&gt;

In some states, "repression" can be an official term used in legislation or the names of government institutions. The [[Soviet Union]] had a legal policy of repression of political opposition defined in [[Article 58 (RSFSR Penal Code)|its penal code]] and [[Cuba]] under [[Fulgencio Batista]] had a secret police agency officially named the [[Bureau for the Repression of Communist Activities]]. According to [[Soviet and Communist studies]] scholar [[Stephen Wheatcroft]], in the case of the Soviet Union terms such as "[[Terror (politics)|the terror]]", "[[Great Purge|the purges]]" and "repression" are used to refer to the same events. He believes the most neutral terms are ''repression'' and ''[[mass killing]]s'', although in Russian the broad concept of repression is commonly held to include mass killings and is sometimes assumed to be synonymous with it, which is not the case in other languages.&lt;ref&gt;Wheatcroft, Stephen (1996). [http://sovietinfo.tripod.com/WCR-German_Soviet.pdf "The Scale and Nature of German and Soviet Repression and Mass Killings, 1930–45"]. ''Europe-Asia Studies''. '''48''' (8): 1319–1353. {{doi|10.1080/09668139608412415}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

== In political conflict ==
Political conflict strongly increases the likelihood of state repression. This is arguably the most robust finding in social science research on political repression. [[Civil war]]s are a strong predictor of repressive activity, as are other forms of challenges from non-government actors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Hill|first1=Daniel W.|last2=Jones|first2=Zachary M.|title=An Empirical Evaluation of Explanations for State Repression|journal=American Political Science Review|date=2014|volume=108|issue=3|pages=661–687|doi=10.1017/s0003055414000306}}&lt;/ref&gt; States so often engage in repressive behaviors in times of civil conflict that the relationship between these two phenomena has been termed the "Law of Coercive Responsiveness".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Davenport|first1=Christian|title=State Repression and Political Order|journal=Annual Review of Political Science|date=2007|volume=10|pages=1–23|doi=10.1146/annurev.polisci.10.101405.143216|doi-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt; When their authority or legitimacy is threatened, regimes respond by overtly or covertly suppressing dissidents to eliminate the behavioral threat. State repression subsequently affects dissident mobilization, though the direction of this effect is still an open question. Some strong evidence suggests that repression suppresses dissident mobilization by reducing the capacity of challengers to organize, yet it is also feasible that challengers can leverage state repressive behavior to spur mobilization among sympathizers by framing repression as a new grievance against the state.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Ritter|first1=Emily Hencken|title=Policy Disputes, Political Survival, and the Onset and Severity of State Repression|journal=Journal of Conflict Resolution|date=2014|volume=58|issue=1|pages=143–168|doi=10.1177/0022002712468724|s2cid=145054180}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Violence ==
Political repression is often accompanied by violence, which might be legal or illegal according to domestic law.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.ohchr.org/Documents/Publications/FS36_sp.pdf|title=Los Derechos Humanos y la trata de personas.|last=|first=|date=|website=www.ohchr.org|language=en-us|access-date=2017-05-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Violence can both eliminate political opposition directly by killing opposition members, or indirectly by instilling fear.

== Intolerance ==
Political repression is sometimes accompanied with [[Social tolerance|intolerance]]. This intolerance is manifested through discriminatory policies, [[human rights violations]], [[police brutality]], [[imprisonment]], [[Genocide|extermination]], [[exile]], [[extortion]], [[terrorism]], [[extrajudicial killing]], [[summary execution]], [[torture]], [[forced disappearance]] and other punishments against political activists, dissidents, and population in general.

== State terrorism ==
When political repression is sanctioned and organized by the state, situations of [[state terrorism]], [[genocide]] and [[crimes against humanity]] can be reached. Systematic and violent political repression is a typical feature of [[dictatorship]]s, [[totalitarianism]]s and similar regimes. In these regimes, acts of political repression can be carried out by the police and [[secret police]], the army, paramilitary groups and death squads. Sometimes regimes considered democratic exercise political repression and state terrorism to other states as part of their security policy.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Torturadores, apropiadores y asesinos : el terrorismo de estado en la obra dramática de Eduardo Pavlovsky.|last=Patricia.|first=Scipioni, Estela|date=2000-01-01|publisher=Edition Reichenberger|isbn=9783931887919|oclc=477299442}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Autocracy]]
* [[Police state]]
* [[Politicide]]
* [[Political prisoner]]
* [[Political violence]]
* [[Preventive repression]]
* [[Religious persecution]]
* [[Restrictions on political parties]]

== References ==
{{reflist}}

== Further reading ==
; Articles
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20081005014352/http://www.bsos.umd.edu/gvpt/davenport/jcr2005.pdf Understanding Covert Repressive Action: The Case of the U.S. Government against the Republic of New Africa ('''186kb PDF file''')] by Christian Davenport, Professor, University of Maryland.
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20070614024800/http://www.bsos.umd.edu/gvpt/davenport/STATER%7e2.PDF ''State Repression and Political Order''] by Christian Davenport, Professor, University of Maryland.
; Journals
* [http://www.interfacejournal.net/2011/05/interface-volume-3-issue-1-repression-and-social-movements/ Special issue of ''Interface: a journal for and about social movements'' on repression and social movements].
; Books
* Goldstein, Robert Justin, ''[[Political Repression in Modern America]]'' ([[University of Illinois Press]], 1978, 2001) {{ISBN|0-8467-0301-7}}.
* Jensen, Joan M. ''Army Surveillance in America, 1775 - 1980.'' New Haven. Yale University Press. 1991. {{ISBN|0-300-04668-5}}.
* Talbert, Jr. Roy. ''Negative Intelligence: The Army and the American Left, 1917 - 1941.'' Jackson. University Press of Mississippi, 1991. {{ISBN|0-87805-495-2}}.
* Irvin, Cynthia L. ''Militant Nationalism between movement and party in Ireland and the Basque Country.'' University of Minnesota Press, 1999.
*Seigel, Micol. 2018. ''Violence Work: State Power and the Limits of Police''. Duke University Press. 

[[Category:Political repression| ]]
[[Category:Human rights abuses]]
[[Category:Persecution]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>