<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20241123000742|1259028454" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1297768" pageid="1297768" ns="0" title="Political repression"><revisions><rev timestamp="2024-11-23T00:07:54Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Act of state entity involving restrictive political freedom of citizens}}
{{Discrimination sidebar}}
'''Political repression''' is the act of a state entity controlling a citizenry by force for political reasons, particularly for the purpose of restricting or preventing the citizenry's ability to take part in the [[politics|political life]] of a [[society]], thereby reducing their standing among their fellow citizens.&lt;ref&gt;[[Christian Davenport|Davenport, Christian]] (2007). [http://www.cambridge.org/catalogue/catalogue.asp?isbn=0521864909 ''State Repression and the Domestic Democratic Peace''] New York: Cambridge University Press.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Davenport, Christian, Johnston, Hank and Mueller, Carol (2004). [http://www.upress.umn.edu/Books/D/davenport_repression.html ''Repression and Mobilization''] Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press.&lt;/ref&gt; Repression tactics target the citizenry who are most likely to challenge the political ideology of the state in order for the government to remain in control.&lt;ref&gt;Hassan, Mai; Mattingly, Daniel; Nugent, Elizabeth R (November 30, 2021). "Political Control". Annual Review of Political Science.&lt;/ref&gt; In [[autocracies]], the use of political repression is to prevent anti-regime support and mobilization.&lt;ref&gt;Wang, Y. (2021). The Political Legacy of Violence During China's Cultural Revolution. British Journal of Political Science, 51(2), 463-487. doi:10.1017/S0007123419000255&lt;/ref&gt; It is often manifested through policies such as [[human rights]] violations, [[surveillance abuse]], [[police brutality]], [[imprisonment]], [[Involuntary settlements in the Soviet Union|involuntary settlement]], [[Lishenets|stripping of citizen's rights]], [[lustration]], and violent action or [[Terror (politics)|terror]] such as the murder, [[summary execution]]s, [[torture]], [[forced disappearance]], and other [[extrajudicial punishment]] of [[political activist]]s, [[dissident]]s, or general population.&lt;ref&gt;Kittrie, Nicholas N. 1995. ''The War Against Authority: From the Crisis of Legitimacy to a New Social Contract. Baltimore, MD: Johns Hopkins University Press.''&lt;/ref&gt; Direct repression tactics are those targeting specific actors who become aware of the harm done to them while covert tactics rely on the threat of citizenry being caught (wiretapping and monitoring).&lt;ref&gt;Sullivan, Christopher M. ''Resistance is Mobile: Dynamics of Repression, Challenger Adaptationm and Surveillance in US 'Red Squad' and Black Nationalist Archives''. Volume 55, Issue 2.&lt;/ref&gt; The effectiveness of the tactics differ: covert repression tactics cause dissidents to use less detectable opposition tactics&lt;ref&gt;Sullivan, Christopher M. ''Resistance is Mobile: Dynamics of Repression, Challenger Adaptationm and Surveillance in US 'Red Squad' and Black Nationalist Archives''. Volume 55, Issue 2.&lt;/ref&gt; while direct repression allows citizenry to witness and react to the repression.&lt;ref&gt;Hassan, Mai; Mattingly, Daniel; Nugent, Elizabeth R (November 30, 2021). "Political Control". Annual Review of Political Science.&lt;/ref&gt; Political repression can also be reinforced by means outside of written policy, such as by public and private media ownership and by [[self-censorship]] within the public.

Where political repression is sanctioned and organised by the state, it may constitute [[state terrorism]], [[genocide]], politicide or [[crimes against humanity]]. Systemic and violent political repression is a typical feature of [[dictatorship]]s, [[totalitarianism|totalitarian]] states and similar regimes.&lt;ref&gt;Serge, Victor, 1979, ''What Everyone Should Know About State Repression, London: New Park Publications.''&lt;/ref&gt; While the use of political repression varies depending on the authoritarian regime, it is argued that repression is a defining feature and the foundation of autocracies by creating a power hierarchy between the leader and citizenry, contributing to the longevity of the regime.&lt;ref&gt;Johannes Gerschewski (2013) The three pillars of stability: legitimation, repression, and co-optation in autocratic regimes, Democratization, 20:1, 13-38, DOI: 10.1080/13510347.2013.738860&lt;/ref&gt;  Repressive activities have also been found within democratic contexts as well.&lt;ref&gt;Donner, Frank J. (1980). ''The Age of Surveillance: The Aims and Methods of America’s Political Intelligence System''. New York: Alfred A. Knopf. {{ISBN|0-394-40298-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Donner, Frank J. (1990). ''Protectors of Privilege: Red Squads and Police Repression in Urban America.'' Berkeley: University of California Press. {{ISBN|0-520-05951-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; This can even include setting up situations where the death of the target of repression is the end result.&lt;ref&gt;Haas, Jeffrey. ''The Assassination of Fred Hampton: How the FBI and the Chicago Police Murdered a Black Panther.'' Chicago, Ill.: Lawrence Hill /Chicago Review, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; If political repression is not carried out with the approval of the state, a section of government may still be responsible. Some examples are the [[Federal Bureau of Investigation|FBI]] [[COINTELPRO]] operations from 1956 to 1971 and the [[Palmer Raids]] from 1919–1920.&lt;ref&gt;''COINTELPRO: The FBI's Covert Action Programs Against American Citizens, Final Report of the Senate Committee to Study Governmental Operations with respect to Intelligence Activities.''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Cunningham, D. 2004. ''There’s something happening here: The New Left, the Klan, and FBI counterintelligence.'' Berkeley: Univ. of California.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Justice Department Campaign Against the IWW, 1917-1920 |url=https://depts.washington.edu/iww/justice_dept.shtml |access-date=2023-04-13 |website=depts.washington.edu}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In some states, "repression" can be an official term used in legislation or the names of government institutions. The [[Soviet Union]] had a legal policy of repression of political opposition defined in [[Article 58 (RSFSR Penal Code)|its penal code]] and [[Republic of Cuba (1902-1959)|Cuba]] under [[Fulgencio Batista]] had a secret police agency officially named the [[Bureau for the Repression of Communist Activities]]. According to [[Soviet and communist studies]] scholar [[Stephen Wheatcroft]], in the case of the Soviet Union terms such as "[[Terror (politics)|the terror]]", "[[Great Purge|the purges]]" and "repression" are used to refer to the same events. He believes the most neutral terms are ''repression'' and ''[[mass killing]]s'', although in Russian the broad concept of repression is commonly held to include mass killings and is sometimes assumed to be synonymous with it, which is not the case in other languages.&lt;ref&gt;Wheatcroft, Stephen (1996). [http://sovietinfo.tripod.com/WCR-German_Soviet.pdf "The Scale and Nature of German and Soviet Repression and Mass Killings, 1930–45"]. ''Europe-Asia Studies''. '''48''' (8): 1319–1353. {{doi|10.1080/09668139608412415}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

== In political conflict ==
Political conflict strongly increases the likelihood of state repression. This is arguably the most robust finding in social science research on political repression. [[Civil war]]s are a strong predictor of repressive activity, as are other forms of challenges from non-government actors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Hill|first1=Daniel W.|last2=Jones|first2=Zachary M.|title=An Empirical Evaluation of Explanations for State Repression|journal=American Political Science Review|date=2014|volume=108|issue=3|pages=661–687|doi=10.1017/s0003055414000306|s2cid=54908565}}&lt;/ref&gt; States so often engage in repressive behaviors in times of civil conflict that the relationship between these two phenomena has been termed the "Law of Coercive Responsiveness".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Davenport|first1=Christian|title=State Repression and Political Order|journal=Annual Review of Political Science|date=2007|volume=10|pages=1–23|doi=10.1146/annurev.polisci.10.101405.143216|doi-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt; When their authority or legitimacy is threatened, regimes respond by overtly or covertly suppressing dissidents to eliminate the behavioral threat. State repression subsequently affects dissident mobilization, though the direction of this effect is still an open question. Some strong evidence suggests that repression suppresses dissident mobilization by reducing the capacity of challengers to organize, yet it is also feasible that challengers can leverage state repressive behavior to spur mobilization among sympathizers by framing repression as a new grievance against the state.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Ritter|first1=Emily Hencken|title=Policy Disputes, Political Survival, and the Onset and Severity of State Repression|journal=Journal of Conflict Resolution|date=2014|volume=58|issue=1|pages=143–168|doi=10.1177/0022002712468724|s2cid=145054180}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Violence ==
{{Main article|Political violence}}
[[File:Eino Niemisen pahoinpitely.jpg|thumb|Members of the right-wing [[Lapua Movement]] assault a former [[Red Guards (Finland)|Red Guard officer]] and the publisher of the [[Communism|communist]] newspaper at the [[Vaasa riot]] on June 4, 1930, in [[Vaasa]], [[Finland]].]]
Political repression is often accompanied by violence, which might be legal or illegal according to domestic law.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.ohchr.org/Documents/Publications/FS36_sp.pdf|title=Los Derechos Humanos y la trata de personas.|website=www.ohchr.org|language=en-us|access-date=2017-05-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Violence can both eliminate political opposition directly by killing opposition members, or indirectly by instilling fear.

== Intolerance ==
{{See also|Infrahumanisation}}
Political repression is sometimes accompanied with [[Social tolerance|intolerance]]. This intolerance is manifested through discriminatory policies, [[human rights violations]], [[police brutality]], [[imprisonment]], [[Genocide|extermination]], [[exile]], [[extortion]], [[terrorism]], [[extrajudicial killing]], [[summary execution]], [[torture]], [[forced disappearance]] and other punishments against political activists, dissidents, and populations in general.

Some regimes that govern societies experiencing sustained ethno-religious conflict may be consolidated on the basis of exclusionary notions of nationhood. In such discriminatory states, political right is generated through a distinction between citizens, who are afforded the rights and moral standing of "full persons," and outsiders, or the "subpersons" of society.&lt;ref&gt;Mills, Charles. “The Racial Contract.” Arguing About Political Philosophy, edited by Matt Zwolinski, Routledge, 2014, pp. 86-108.&lt;/ref&gt; The privileges enjoyed by citizens are given meaning because they are denied to subpersons, on account of their perceived inferiority.&lt;ref&gt;Pateman, Carole. The Sexual Contract, Polity Press, 1991.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Mohanty, Chandra Talpade. “Under Western Eyes: Feminist Scholarship and Colonial Discourses.” Feminist Review, no. 30, 1988, pp. 61–88.&lt;/ref&gt; The government thereby creates a political order that justifies and enables the dominance of citizens through the systemic "exploitation of [the] bodies, land, [and] resources [of noncitizens], and the denial of equal socioeconomic opportunities to them."&lt;ref&gt;Mills, Charles. “The Racial Contract.” Arguing About Political Philosophy, edited by Matt Zwolinski, Routledge, 2014, pp. 86-108.&lt;/ref&gt; In this way, the regime operationalizes the domination and subordination of certain groups to establish its political authority. These repressive states distinguish between citizens and subpersons on the basis of socially agreed-upon conceptions of identity. Governments acquire legitimacy by expounding exclusionary notions of national identity, which sanctify the division between the citizenry and outsiders.&lt;ref&gt;Pervez, Muhammad Shoaib. “India-Pakistan nuclear rivalry: the influence of ideology upon elites’ social practices.” Security Community in South Asia: India-Pakistan, Taylor and Francis, 2013, pp. 103-126.&lt;/ref&gt; 

Because the fabrication of nationhood often requires a reorientation of existing group identities, regimes will construe their national identity by taking advantage of soft power variables.&lt;ref&gt;Rafiq, Samah. “Linear Borders, Partition, and Identity in Postcolonial South Asia.” Geopolitics, vol. 27, no. 2, 2022, pp. 478-500.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Pervez, Muhammad Shoaib. “India-Pakistan nuclear rivalry: the influence of ideology upon elites’ social practices.” Security Community in South Asia: India-Pakistan, Taylor and Francis, 2013, pp. 103-126.&lt;/ref&gt; Muhammad Pervez defines soft power variables as attractive and intangible power resources like religion, cultural norms, and institutions, that appeal to people and encourage their compliance.&lt;ref&gt;Pervez, Muhammad Shoaib. “India-Pakistan nuclear rivalry: the influence of ideology upon 
elites’ social practices.” Security Community in South Asia: India-Pakistan, Taylor and Francis, 2013, pp. 103-126.&lt;/ref&gt; Soft power variables are constructed through the social imagination, meaning they are arbitrary and malleable. For this reason, when the citizenry utilizes soft power variables to contrive its national identity, it induces "securitized subjectivity," whereby "subjects in a state desire securitization when they are afraid or feel a threat to the existence of their identity. In this situation, every self-identity requires a threat from others."&lt;ref&gt;Pervez, Muhammad Shoaib. “India-Pakistan nuclear rivalry: the influence of ideology upon elites’ social practices.” Security Community in South Asia: India-Pakistan, Taylor and Francis, 2013, pp. 103-126.&lt;/ref&gt; State leaders, to further consolidate their political power and solidify the domination of the citizenry, deliberately vilify the subpersons of the political order and ensure a continued environment of securitized subjectivity.&lt;ref&gt;Pervez, Muhammad Shoaib. “India-Pakistan nuclear rivalry: the influence of ideology upon elites’ social practices.” Security Community in South Asia: India-Pakistan, Taylor and Francis, 2013, pp. 103-126.&lt;/ref&gt; By manufacturing an enduring security dilemma between dominant and subordinated groups, oppressive regimes convey to dominant groups that the protection provided by the state is necessary for the dominant identity group’s/nation state’s survival,&lt;ref&gt;Rafiq, Samah. “Linear Borders, Partition, and Identity in Postcolonial South Asia.” Geopolitics, vol. 27, no. 2, 2022, pp. 478-500.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Pervez, Muhammad Shoaib. “India-Pakistan nuclear rivalry: the influence of ideology upon elites’ social practices.” Security Community in South Asia: India-Pakistan, Taylor and Francis, 2013, pp. 103-126.&lt;/ref&gt; which legitimizes the state. In this way, through the manipulation of soft power variables, oppressive regimes manufacture a nationalism that is dependent on the demarcation between dominant and subordinate identity groups.

== State terrorism ==
When political repression is sanctioned and organized by the state, situations of [[state terrorism]], [[genocide]] and [[crimes against humanity]] can be reached. Systematic and violent political repression is a typical feature of [[dictatorship]]s, [[totalitarianism|totalitarian states]] and similar regimes. In these regimes, acts of political repression can be carried out by the police and [[secret police]], the army, paramilitary groups and death squads. Sometimes regimes considered democratic exercise political repression and state terrorism to other states as part of their security policy.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Torturadores, apropiadores y asesinos : el terrorismo de estado en la obra dramática de Eduardo Pavlovsky.|last=Patricia.|first=Scipioni, Estela|date=2000-01-01|publisher=Edition Reichenberger|isbn=9783931887919|oclc=477299442}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Direct vs. indirect repression ==
Direct repression is a form of repression where the state targets an opposing political actor by obvious violent action. The target is clearly aware of the harm that is caused to their life and livelihood. Direct repression does not exclusively occur within the boundaries of a state, but also across borders.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Hassan |first1=Mai |last2=Mattingly |first2=Daniel |last3=Nugent |first3=Elizabeth R |title=Political Control |journal=Annual Review of Political Science |date=November 30, 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt; In personalist dictatorships, initiating conflicts with other states and people outside their own borders is more common because of lack of accountability via extremely limited or no competitive elections.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Frantz |first1=Erica |title=Authoritarianism: What Everyone Needs to Know |date=November 15, 2018 |publisher=Oxford University Press |isbn=9780190880194 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Indirect repression relies on the threat of violence which constitutes harassment, intimidation, and administrative blockages. These tactics tend to be non-violent, yet still are built to control citizenry.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Hassan |first1=Mai |last2=Mattingly |first2=Daniel |last3=Nugent |first3=Elizabeth R |title=Political Control |journal=Annual Review of Political Science |date=November 30, 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Repressive success and monitoring ==
Individuals indirectly exposed to repression self-report higher trust in the leader and ruling party. This phenomenon was observed in [[Zimbabwe]] under [[Robert Mugabe]], where the effects of repression increased approaching elections, even with deteriorating social and economic conditions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last1=Garcîa-Ponce |first1=Omar |last2=Pasquale |first2=Benjamin |title=How Political Repression Shapes Attitudes Toward the State |date=2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; A large signifier of whether or not repression is successful in a state is evidence of [[preference falsification]]– where the preference expressed by an individual in public diverges from their private preference.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Kuran |first1=Timur |title=Now Out of Never: The Element of Surprise in the East European Revolution of 1989 |journal=World Politics |date=October 1991 |volume=44 |issue=1 |pages=7–48 |doi=10.2307/2010422 |jstor=2010422 |s2cid=154090678 |url=https://ir.lib.uwo.ca/economicsperg_ppe/19 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In [[North Korea]], accused of [[Political repression in North Korea|highly repressive activity]] in media and public culture, 100% of citizens vote in ‘no choice’ parliamentary elections so the state can identify defectors. Citizens are required to show complete devotion to North Korea's current leader and sacrifice their safety if they choose to speak out.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=North Koreans vote in 'no-choice' parliamentary elections |url=https://www.bbc.com/news/world-asia-47492747 |agency=BBC News |date=March 10, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; Repressive measures including prison camps, torture, forced labor, and threats of execution are just some of the costs of defection.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=North Korea: Systematic Repression |url=https://www.hrw.org/news/2020/01/14/north-korea-systematic-repression |website=Human Rights Watch |date=14 January 2020 |access-date=2 March 2023}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Chinese Communist Party]] implements extensive surveillance measures in the [[People's Republic of China]], including [[Internet censorship in China|Internet censorship]], [[Closed-circuit television|camera monitoring]], and other forms of [[Mass surveillance in China|mass surveillance]]. These practices involve the use of technologies such as [[Artificial Intelligence|AI]], [[Facial recognition technology|facial recognition]], [[Fingerprint recognition|fingerprint identification]], [[Biometrics|voice and iris recognition]], [[big data]] analysis, [[Genetic testing|DNA testing]], and are closely linked to the [[Social Credit System]] in mainland China.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=中国的威权主义未来：人工智能与无孔不入的监控|url=https://cn.nytimes.com/china/20180710/china-surveillance-technology/|accessdate=2019-11-14|author=孟宝勒|date=2018-07-17|format=|publisher=纽约时报中文网|language=zh|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20191016000049/https://cn.nytimes.com/china/20180710/china-surveillance-technology/|archive-date=2019-10-16|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=【聚焦】中国社会信用系统致力于为公民打分并改造社会行为|url=https://www.abc.net.au/chinese/2018-03-31/china-social-credit-system/9600054|accessdate=2019-11-14|author=Vicky Xiuzhong Xu|date=2018-03-31|format=|publisher=ABC中文|language=zh|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180929152024/http://www.abc.net.au/chinese/2018-03-31/china-social-credit-system/9600054|archive-date=2018-09-29|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the same time, many domestic Chinese technology companies are also involved in the country's large-scale surveillance programs. These primarily include companies such as [[Hikvision]], [[Sensetime]], [[Huawei]], [[ZTE]], and others.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=人臉識別 + 社會信用系統，一場重塑人類行為的社會實驗？|url=https://theinitium.com/article/20180525-wsj-introduction/|language=zh-Hant|website=theinitium.com|date=25 May 2018 |access-date=2019-11-14|archive-date=2021-08-04|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20210804235102/https://theinitium.com/article/20180525-wsj-introduction/}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=打造平安城市精品视频监控网络|url=https://www.huawei.com/mediafiles/CORPORATE/PDF/Magazine/communicate/69/HW_412473.pdf|accessdate=|author=|date=|format=|publisher=华为|language=|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190217064814/https://www.huawei.com/mediafiles/CORPORATE/PDF/Magazine/communicate/69/HW_412473.pdf|archive-date=2019-02-17|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":2"&gt;{{Cite web|title=单月50万次人脸识别：中国如何用AI监控维族人|url=https://cn.nytimes.com/technology/20190415/china-surveillance-artificial-intelligence-racial-profiling/|accessdate=2019-11-14|author=孟宝勒|date=2019-04-15|format=|publisher=纽约时报中文网|language=zh-hans|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20191016000001/https://cn.nytimes.com/technology/20190415/china-surveillance-artificial-intelligence-racial-profiling/|archive-date=2019-10-16|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=中国天网工程背后有三大功臣：包括中兴与华为|url=http://news.dwnews.com/china/news/2018-08-28/60080872.html|accessdate=2019-11-14|author=|date=|publisher=多维新闻|language=|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190410211135/http://news.dwnews.com/china/news/2018-08-28/60080872.html|archive-date=2019-04-10|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==

===Killings===

 {{div col}}
*[[1989 Tiananmen Square protests and massacre]] 
*[[Anti-communist mass killings]]
* [[Mass killings under communist regimes]]
{{div col end}}

===National institutions===
{{div col}}

*[[Secret Police]]
*[[Committee of Public Safety]]
*[[KGB]]
*[[Gestapo]]
*[[FBI]] (primarily during the [[Cold War]])
*[[Kangaroo court]] 
{{div col end}}

===Related systems===
{{div col}}
*[[Censorship]]
*[[Restrictions on political parties]]
*[[Press censorship]] 
{{div col end}}

===Types of persecution===
{{div col}}
*[[Lawfare|Judicial persecution]]
*[[Persecution]]
*[[Religious Persecution]] 
{{div col end}}

===Restrictions and actions===
{{div col}}
*[[Abuse of process]]
*[[Arbitrary arrest and detention]]
*[[Black Propaganda]]
*[[Censorship]]
*[[Forced disappearance]]
*[[Martial Law]]
*[[Mass Surveillance]]
*[[Massacre]]
*[[Agent provocateur|Provocateurs]]
*[[Red Terror]]
*[[Stalking]] or [[Harassment]]
*[[White Terror (disambiguation)|White Terror]]{{div col end}}

===Types of states and regimes===
{{div col}}
*[[Police state]]
*[[State Terrorism]]
*[[Dictatorship]]
*[[État légal]]
*[[Nanny State]]
*[[Military Dictatorship]]
*[[Police State]] 
{{div col end}}

===Institutions and groups===

{{div col}}
*[[Dissidents]]
*[[Government]] 
{{div col end}}

===Related concepts===

{{div col}}
*[[An unjust law is no law at all]]
*[[Human Rights]]
*[[National Security]] 
*[[Racism]]
*[[Totalitarianism]]
{{div col end}}

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

== Further reading ==
; Articles
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20081005014352/http://www.bsos.umd.edu/gvpt/davenport/jcr2005.pdf Understanding Covert Repressive Action: The Case of the U.S. Government against the Republic of New Africa ('''186kb PDF file''')] by Christian Davenport, Professor, University of Maryland.
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20070614024800/http://www.bsos.umd.edu/gvpt/davenport/STATER%7e2.PDF ''State Repression and Political Order''] by Christian Davenport, Professor, University of Maryland.
; Journals
* [http://www.interfacejournal.net/2011/05/interface-volume-3-issue-1-repression-and-social-movements/ Special issue of ''Interface: a journal for and about social movements'' on repression and social movements].
*{{cite journal |last1=Bartusevičius |first1=Henrikas |last2=van Leeuwen |first2=Florian |last3=Petersen |first3=Michael Bang |title=Political repression motivates anti-government violence |journal=Royal Society Open Science |date=June 2023 |volume=10 |issue=6 |doi=10.1098/rsos.221227}}
; Books
* Davenport, Christian; Appel, Benjamin (2022). ''The Death and Life of State Repression: Understanding Onset, Escalation, Termination, and Recurrence''. Oxford University Press.
* Goldstein, Robert Justin, ''[[Political Repression in Modern America]]'' ([[University of Illinois Press]], 1978, 2001) {{ISBN|0-8467-0301-7}}.
* Jensen, Joan M. ''Army Surveillance in America, 1775 - 1980.'' New Haven. Yale University Press. 1991. {{ISBN|0-300-04668-5}}.
* Talbert Jr. Roy. ''Negative Intelligence: The Army and the American Left, 1917 - 1941.'' Jackson. University Press of Mississippi, 1991. {{ISBN|0-87805-495-2}}.
* Irvin, Cynthia L. ''Militant Nationalism between movement and party in Ireland and the Basque Country.'' University of Minnesota Press, 1999.
*Seigel, Micol. 2018. ''Violence Work: State Power and the Limits of Police''. Duke University Press.
{{Discrimination}}{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Comparative politics]]
[[Category:Political repression| ]]
[[Category:Human rights abuses]]
[[Category:Persecution]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>