<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20111113170311|460462806" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="13200141" pageid="13200141" ns="0" title="Women in government"><revisions><rev timestamp="2011-11-14T06:42:36Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Women in society sidebar}}
[[File:Map3.8Government Participation by Women compressed.jpg|right|thumb| 350px| A world map showing countries governmental participation by women, 2010.]]

'''Women in government''' in the modern era are under-represented in most countries worldwide, in contrast to men. However, women are increasingly being politically elected to be heads of state and government. More than 20 countries currently have a woman holding office as the head of a national government, and the global participation rate of women in national-level parliaments is nearly 20%. A number of countries are exploring measures that may increase women's participation in government at all levels, from the local to the national.

==Importance==
{{Feminism sidebar}}
Increasing women’s representation in the government can empower women.&lt;ref name="unicef.org"&gt;UNICEF. 2006. “Equality in Politics and Government” and “Reaping the Double Dividend of Gender Equality,” in The State of the World Children 2007, pp. 51–87. New York: The United Nations Children’s Fund. http://www.unicef.org/sowc07/report/report.php&lt;/ref&gt; Increasing women’s representation in government is necessary to achieve gender parity.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.un.org/millenniumgoals/gender.shtml&lt;/ref&gt; This notion of women’s empowerment is rooted in the human [[capabilities approach]], in which individuals are empowered to choose the functioning that they deem valuable.&lt;ref name="Basu, Amriyta 2003"&gt;Basu, Amriyta; Jayal, Naraja Gopal; Nussbaum, Martha; Tambiah, Yasmin. 2003. Essays on Gender and Governance. India: Human Development Resource Center, United Nations Development Programme.&lt;/ref&gt;

Women, as the conventional primary caretakers of children, often have a more prominent role than men in advocating for children, resulting in a “double dividend” in terms of the benefits of women’s representation.&lt;ref name="unicef.org"/&gt; Female representatives not only advance women’s rights, but also advance the rights of children. In national legislatures, there is a notable trend of women advancing gender and family-friendly legislation. This advocacy has been seen in countries ranging from France, Sweden and the Netherlands, to South Africa, Rwanda, and Egypt.  Furthermore, a number of studies from both industrialized and developed countries indicate that women in local government tend to advance social issues.{{fact|date=October 2011}} In India, for instance, greater women’s representation has corresponded with a more equitable distribution of community resources, including more gender-sensitive spending on programs related to health, nutrition, and education.{{fact|date=October 2011}}

==Challenges faced by women==
Women face numerous obstacles in achieving representation in governance.&lt;ref name="unicef.org"/&gt;  Their participation has been limited by the assumption that women’s proper sphere is the “private” sphere.  Whereas the “public” domain is one of political authority and contestation, the “private” realm is associated with the family and the home.&lt;ref name="Basu, Amriyta 2003"/&gt;  By relegating women to the private sphere, their ability to enter the political arena is curtailed.

Gender inequality within families, inequitable [[division of labor]] within households, and cultural attitudes about [[gender roles]] further subjugate women and serve to limit their representation in public life.&lt;ref name="unicef.org"/&gt;  Societies that are highly [[patriarchal]] often have local power structures that make it difficult for women to combat.&lt;ref name="Social Development 2005"&gt;United Nations Research Institute for Social Development (UNRISD). 2005. Gender Equality: Striving for Justice in an Unequal World. France: UNRISD.&lt;/ref&gt;  Thus, their interests are often not represented.

Even once elected, women tend to hold lesser valued cabinet ministries or similar positions.&lt;ref name="Basu, Amriyta 2003"/&gt;  These are described as “soft industries” and include health, education, and welfare.  Rarely do women hold executive decision-making authority in more powerful domains or those that are associated with traditional notions of masculinity (such as finance and the military).  Typically, the more powerful the institution, the less likely it is that women’s interests will be represented.  Additionally, in more autocratic nations, women are less likely to have their interests represented.&lt;ref name="Social Development 2005"/&gt; Many women attain political standing due to kinship ties, as they have male family members who are involved in politics.&lt;ref name="Basu, Amriyta 2003"/&gt; These women tend to be from higher income, higher status families and thus may not be as focused on the issues faced by lower income families.

===Challenges within political parties===
In Canada, there is evidence that female politicians face gender stigma from male members of the political parties to which they belong, which can undermine the ability of women to reach or maintain leadership roles. [[Pauline Marois]], leader of the [[Parti Quebecois]] (PQ) and the official opposition of the [[National Assembly of Quebec]], was the subject of a claim by Claude Pinard, a PQ "[[backbencher]]", that many Quebecers do not support a female politician: "I believe that one of her serious handicaps is the fact she's a woman [...] I sincerely believe that a good segment of the population won't support her because she's a woman".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Banerjee|first=Sidhartha|title=PQ woes prompt debate in Quebec about whether women get a fair deal in politics|url=http://ca.news.yahoo.com/pq-leader-marois-dismisses-notion-being-female-hurting-180424871.html|accessdate=November 2, 2011|newspaper=The Canadian Press|date=November 2, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; A 2000 study that analyzed 1993 election results in Canada found that among "similarly situated women and men candidates", women actually had a small vote advantage. The study showed that neither voter turnout nor urban/rural constituencies were factors that help or hurt a female candidate, but "office-holding experience in non-political organizations made a modest contribution to women's electoral advantage".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Black, J.H. and Erickson, L.|title=Women candidates and voter bias: do women politicians need to be better?|journal=Electoral Studies|year=2003|month=March|volume=Volume 22|issue=Issue 1|pages=81-100|doi=http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0261-3794(01)00028-2|url=http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0261379401000282|accessdate=November 2, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Bruce M. Hicks, an electoral studies researcher at Université de Montréal, states that evidence shows that female candidates begin with a head start in voters' eyes of as much as 10 per cent, and that female candidates are often more favourably associated by voters with issues like health care and education.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Banerjee|first=Sidhartha|title=PQ woes prompt debate in Quebec about whether women get a fair deal in politics|url=http://ca.news.yahoo.com/pq-leader-marois-dismisses-notion-being-female-hurting-180424871.html|accessdate=November 2, 2011|newspaper=The Canadian Press|date=November 2, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;The electorate's perception that female candidates have more proficiency with traditional women's spheres such as education and health care presents a possibility that gender stereotypes can work in a female candidate's favour, at least among the electorate. In politics, however, Hicks points out that sexism is nothing new:
{{blockquote|(Marois' issue) does reflect what has been going on for some time now: women in positions of authority have problems in terms of the way they manage authority [...] The problem isn't them, it's the men under them who resent taking direction from strong women. And the backroom dirty dialogue can come into the public eye.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Banerjee|first=Sidhartha|title=PQ woes prompt debate in Quebec about whether women get a fair deal in politics|url=http://ca.news.yahoo.com/pq-leader-marois-dismisses-notion-being-female-hurting-180424871.html|accessdate=November 2, 2011|newspaper=The Canadian Press|date=November 2, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Within Quebec itself, Don McPherson pointed out that Pinard himself has enjoyed greater electoral success with Pauline Marois as party leader than under a previous male party leader, when Pinard failed to be elected in his riding. Demographically, Pinard's electoral riding is rural, with "relatively older, less-well educated voters".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=McPherson|first=Don|title=Pauline Marois's troubles aren't because of sexism|url=http://www.montrealgazette.com/news/Pauline+Marois+troubles+aren+because+sexism/5648719/story.html|accessdate=November 13, 2011|newspaper=Montreal Gazette|date=November 3, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Women's suffrage==
{{Main|Women's suffrage}}

==National representation==
As of 2011, the global average of women in national assemblies is 19.3%.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Women in Parliaments: World and Regional Averages|url=http://www.ipu.org/wmn-e/world.htm|publisher=Inter-Parliamentary Union|accessdate=October 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Women in national parliaments===
Out of 188 countries, listed in descending order by the percentage of women in the lower or single house, the top 10 countries with the greatest representation of women in national parliaments are (figures reflect information as of August 31, 2011):&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Women in Parliaments: World Classification|url=http://www.ipu.org/wmn-e/classif.htm|publisher=Inter-Parliamentary Union|accessdate=October 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class="wikitable"
|-
! Rank !! Country !! Lower or Single House !! Upper House or Senate 
|-
| 1 || Rwanda || 56.3% || 34.6% 
|-
| 2 || Andorra  || 53.6% || -
|-
| 3 || Sweden  || 45% || - 
|-
| 4 || South Africa ||  44.5% || 29.6% 
|-
| 5 || Cuba || 43.2% || - 
|-
| 6 || Iceland || 42.9% || - 
|-
|7 || Finland ||  42.5% || - 
|-
|8 || Norway||39.6%||-
|-
|9||Belgium||39.3%	||36.6%
|-
|"||Netherlands||39.3%||36.0%
|-
|10||	Mozambique||39.2%	||-
|-
|}

The major English-speaking democracies are placed in the top 40% of the ranked countries. New Zealand ranks at position 17 with women comprising 33.6% of its lower house in parliament. Australia (24.7% in the lower house, 35.5% in the upper house) and Canada (24.7% lower house, 35.9% upper house) rank at position 38 out of 188 countries. The United Kingdom is ranked at 48 (22.0% lower house, 20.1% upper house), while the United States ranks 69 (16.9% in the lower house, 17.0% in the upper house).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Women in Parliaments: World Classification|url=http://www.ipu.org/wmn-e/classif.htm|publisher=Inter-Parliamentary Union|accessdate=October 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; It should be noted that not all of these lower and/or upper houses in national parliaments are democratically elected; for example, in Canada members of the upper house (the Senate) are appointed. In a small number of countries, for example Saudi Arabia, women's suffrage does not exist, and therefore there is a 0% representation of women in the national government.

==Policies to increase women’s participation==
The United Nations has identified six avenues by which female participation in politics and government may be strengthened. These avenues are: equalization of educational opportunities, quotas for female participation in governing bodies, legislative reform to increase focus on issues concerning women and children, financing gender-responsive budgets to equally take into account the needs of men and women, increasing the presence of sex-disaggregated statistics in national research/data, and furthering the presence and agency of grassroots women’s [[empowerment]] movements &lt;ref name="unicef.org"/&gt;

===Education===
Women with formal education (at any level) are likelier to delay marriage and subsequent childbirth, be better informed about infant and child nutrition, and ensure childhood immunization. Children of mothers with formal education are better nourished and have higher survival rates.&lt;ref name="unicef.org"/&gt; Equalization of educational opportunities for boys and girls may take the form of several initiatives:

* abolishment of educational fees which would require parents to consider financial issues when deciding which of their children to educate. Poor children in rural areas are particularly affected by inequality resulting from educational fees.&lt;ref&gt;United Nations Children’s Fund and World Bank, ‘Building on what we know and defining sustained support’, School Fee Abolition Initiative Workshop, organized by UNICEF and the World Bank, Nairobi, 5–7 April 2006, p. 3&lt;/ref&gt;
* encouragement of parents and communities to institute gender-equal educational agendas. Perceived [[opportunity cost]] of educating girls may be addressed through a [[conditional cash transfer]] program which financially reward families who educate their daughters (thus removing the financial barrier that results from girls substituting school attendance for work in the family labor force).&lt;ref&gt;United Nations Children’s Fund, The State of the World’s Children 2004: Girls’ education and development, UNICEF, New York, 2003.&lt;/ref&gt;
*creation of “girl-friendly” schools to minimize bias and create a safe school environment for girls and young women. Currently, a barrier to female school attendance is the risk of [[sexual violence]] en route to school.&lt;ref name="Fund 2004"&gt;United Nations Children’s Fund, The State of the World’s Children 2004.&lt;/ref&gt; A “safe school environment” is one in which the school is located to minimize such violence, in addition to providing girls with educational opportunities (as opposed to using female students to perform janitorial work or other menial labor).&lt;ref name="Fund 2004"/&gt;

===Quotas===
Quotas are mechanisms by which governments seek to numerically increase the numbers of female represented in the governing body.&lt;ref name="Fund 2004"/&gt; Types of quotas include:&lt;ref name="Fund 2004"/&gt;
* Gender quota systems: institute a “critical value” below which is deemed an imbalanced government. Examples of such critical values include 20% of legislators, 50% of politicians, etc.
* Legal quota systems regulate the governance of political parties and bodies. Such quotas may be mandated by electoral law (as in Ecuador, for example) or may be constitutionally required (as in Nepal).
* Voluntary party quota systems may be used by [[political parties]] at will, yet are not mandated by electoral law or by a country’s constitution. If a country’s leading or majority political party engages in a voluntary party quota system, the effect may “trickle down” to minority political parties in the country (as in the case of the African National Congress in South Africa).
Quotas may be utilized during different stages of the political nomination/selection process to address different junctures at which women may be inherently disadvantaged:&lt;ref name="Fund 2004"/&gt;
* Potential candidacy: gender quota systems can mandate that from the pool of aspirants, a certain percentage of them must be female.
* Nomination: legal or voluntary quotas are enforced upon this stage, during which a certain portion of nominated candidates on the party’s ballot must be female.
* Election: “reserved seats” may be filled only by women.
Quota usage can have marked effects on female representation in governance. In 1995, Rwanda ranked 24th in terms of female representation, and jumped to 1st in 2003 after quotas were introduced. Similar effects can be seen in Argentina, Iraq, Burundi, Mozambique, and South Africa, for example.&lt;ref name="Fund 2004"/&gt; Of the top-ranked 20 countries in terms of female representation in government, 17 of these countries utilize some sort of quota system to ensure female inclusion. Though such inclusion is mainly instituted at the national level, there have been efforts in India to addresses female inclusion at the subnational level, through quotas for parliamentary positions.&lt;ref&gt;Inter-Parliamentary Union, ‘Women in Parliaments: World classification’, &lt;www.ipu.org/wmn-e/classsif.htm&gt;; and International Institute for Democracy and Electoral Assistance and Stockholm University, ‘Global Database of
Quotas for Women’, www.quotaproject.org/country.cfm?SortOrder=LastLowerPercenta&lt;/ref&gt;

===Legislation===
Legislative agendas, some pushed by female political figures, may focus on several key issues to address ongoing gender disparities:
* Reducing domestic and gender-based violence. The Convention on the Rights of the Child, in 1989, addressed home violence and its effects on children. The Convention stipulates that children are holders of human rights, and authorizes the State to 1) prevent all forms of violence, and 2) respond to past violence effectively.&lt;ref&gt;United Nations, Report of the independent expert for the United Nations study on violence against children, Provisional version, UN A/61/150 and Corr. 1, United Nations, New York, 23 August 2005&lt;/ref&gt; Gender-based violence, such as the use of rape as a tool of warfare, was addressed in Resolution 1325 of the UN Security Council in 2000. It calls for “all parties of armed conflict to take special measures to protect women and girls from gender-based violence.” &lt;ref&gt;United Nations, Security Council Resolution 1325, para. 10, adopted by the Security Council at its 4213th Meeting, United Nations, New York, 31 October 2000&lt;/ref&gt;  Currently, 64 countries have either drafted or are in the process of drafting laws to criminalize gender violence.&lt;ref name="unicef.org"/&gt;
* Reducing in-home discrimination through equalizing [[property]] and [[inheritance]]  rights. National legislation can supersede traditionally male-dominated inheritance models. Such legislation has been proven effective in countries like Colombia, where 60% of land is held in joint titles between men and women (compared to 18% before the passage of joint titling legislation in 1996).&lt;ref&gt;King, Elizabeth M., and Andrew D. Mason, ‘Engendering Development Through Gender Equality in Rights, Resources, and Voice’, World Bank and Oxford University Press, Washington, D.C., January 2001, p. 120&lt;/ref&gt;

===Financing===
Gender-responsive budgets address the needs and interests of different individuals and social groups, maintaining awareness of gender issues within the formation of policies and budgets. Such budgets are not necessarily a 50-50 male-female split, but accurately reflect the needs of each gender (such as increased allocation for women’s reproductive health.&lt;ref name="United Nations Development Programme 2005"&gt;United Nations Development Programme, Gender-Based Budgeting: Manual for Trainers. 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; Benefits of gender-responsive budgets include:
* Improved budget efficiency by ensuring that funds are allocated where they are needed most
* Strengthened government position by advocating for needs of all, including the poor and the underrepresented
* Increased information flow surrounding needs of those who are usually discriminated against
A gender-responsive budget may also work to address issues of unpaid care work and caring labor gaps.&lt;ref name="United Nations Development Programme 2005"/&gt;

===Research/data improvements===
Current research which uses sex-aggregated statistics may underplay or minimize the quantitative presentation of issues such as maternal mortality, violence against women, and girls’ school attendance.&lt;ref&gt;UNICEF. 2006. “Equality in Politics and Government” and “Reaping the Double Dividend of Gender Equality,” in The State of the World's Children 2007, pp. 51–87. New York: The United Nations Children’s Fund. ttp://www.unicef.org/sowc07/report/report.php&lt;/ref&gt; Sex-disaggregated statistics are lacking in the assessment of maternal mortality rates, for example. Prior to [[UNICEF]] and [[UNIFEM]] efforts to gather more accurate and comprehensive data, 62 countries had no recent national data available regarding maternal mortality rates.&lt;ref&gt;United Nations, The World’s Women 2005: Progress in statistics, United Nations Division of Economic and Social Affairs, New York, 2006, p. 26&lt;/ref&gt; Only 38 countries have sex-disaggregated statistics available to report frequency of violence against women.&lt;ref name="United Nations 2006"&gt;United Nations, Department of Social and Economic Affairs, The World’s Women 2005: Progress in Statistics, United Nations, New York, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; 41 countries collect sex-disaggregated data on school attendance, while 52 countries assess sex-disaggregated wage statistics.&lt;ref name="United Nations 2006"/&gt;

===Grassroots women’s empowerment movements===
Women’s informal collectives are crucial to improving the standard of living for women worldwide. Collectives can address such issues as nutrition, education, shelter, food distribution, and generally improved standard of living.&lt;ref&gt;McNulty, Stephanie, ‘Women’s Organizations During and After War: From service delivery to policy advocacy’, Research and Reference Services Project, United States Agency for International Development Center for
Development Information and Evaluation, Washington, D.C., 2 October 1998, p. 3.&lt;/ref&gt; Empowering such collectives can increase their reach to the women most in need of support and empowerment.

==Case studies==
===Brazil===
A 1995 Brazilian gender quota was extended first to city councilor positions in 1996, then extended to candidates of all political legislative positions by 1998.&lt;ref&gt;Sacchet, Teresa. "Beyond Numbers -- The Impact of Gender Quotas in Latin America" International Feminist Journal of Politics 10.3 (2008)&lt;/ref&gt; By 1998, 30% of political candidates had to be women, with varied results in terms of the gender balance of the officials ultimately elected. Though the percentage of national legislature seats occupied by women dropped in the initial years following the passage of the quota law, the percentage has since risen (from 6.2% pre-quota, to 5.7% in 1998, to 8.9% in 2006). However, Brazil has struggled with the quota law in several respects:
* Though the quota law mandates a certain percentage of candidate spots be reserved for women, it is not compulsory that those spots be filled by women.
* The quota law also allowed political parties to increase the number of candidates, further increasing electoral competition and having a negligible impact on the actual number of women elected.
* Brazil is the fifth-largest country in the world (in terms of both population size and also land area), making it difficult for women to accept the distance from home which would accompany traveling to seek a spot in the national legislative body.

===Finland===
The Finnish national quota law, introduced in 1995, mandates that among all indirectly elected public bodies (at both a national and a local level), at least 40% of the governing body must be female.&lt;ref&gt;Holli, Anne Maria; Luhtakallio, Eeva; Raevaara, Eeva. "Quota trouble: Talking about gender quotas in finnish local politics" International Feminist Journal of Politics 8.2 (2006).&lt;/ref&gt; The 1995 laws was a reformed version of a similar 1986 law. Unlike other countries’ quota laws, which affect party structure or electoral candidate lists, the Finnish law addresses indirectly elected bodies (nominated by official authorities)—the law does not address popularly elected bodies. The Finnish law heavily emphasizes local municipal boards and other subnational institutions. From 1993 (pre-quota law) to 1997 (post-quota law), the proportion of women on municipal executive boards increased from 25% to 45%. The quota law also affected gender segregation in local governance: before the passage of the law, there had been a gender imbalance in terms of female overrepresentation in “soft-sector” boards (those concerned with health, education, etc.) and female underrepresentation in “hard-sector” boards (those concerned with economics and technology). In 1997, the boards were balanced horizontally. However, areas not subject to quota laws continue to be imbalanced. In 2003, it was determined that only 16% of the chairs of municipal executive boards are female—chair positions in this area are not quota-regulated.&lt;ref&gt;Pikkala, S. 2000. ‘Representations of Women in Finnish Local Government: Effects of the 1995 Gender Quota Legislation’, paper presented at the European Consortium on Political Research Joint Sessions of Workshops, Copenhagen, 14– 19 April.
&lt;/ref&gt;

===Spain===
In 2007, Spain passed the Equality Law, requiring a “principle of balanced presence” by mandating political parties to include 40-60% of each sex among electoral candidates.&lt;ref&gt;Verge, Tània. "Gendering Representation in Spain: Opportunities and Limits of Gender Quotas" Journal of Women, Politics &amp; Policy 31.2 (2010). 23 Mar. 2011&lt;/ref&gt; This law is unique in that surpasses the 40% parity figure established by the European Commission in 1998; a figure which (according to the EC) indicates “parity democracy.” Though there is anecdotal of increasing female representation on a local and national level, there has not yet been national-level data to quantitatively bolster this assertion.

==Women in government office==
Women in politics have historically been under-represented in [[Western world|Western societies]] compared to men.  Some women, however, have been politically elected to be heads of state and government.

===Historic firsts for women in government===
*[[Sukhbaataryn Yanjmaa]], Mongolia (1953-1954): World's first female (acting) president
* [[Isabel Peron]], Argentina (1974-1976): World's first female (non-acting) president
* [[Vigdis Finnbogadottir]], Iceland (1980-1996): World's first female elected president, and first female world leader who did not have a father or husband who was also leader at one time
* [[Mary McAleese]], Ireland (1997-2011):First time that a female president directly succeeded another female president
* [[Sri Lanka]] (1994-2000): First time that a nation possessed a female prime minister and a female president simultaneously. Sri Lanka in 1994 also marked the first time that a female prime minister directly succeeded another female prime minister.
* [[Jóhanna Sigurðardóttir]], Iceland (2009-  ): World's first openly lesbian world leader, first female world leader to wed a same-sex partner while in office

Some of the most prominent female leaders of [[world power]]s in recent decades were (listed by name then position):
{{div col |2}}
*[[Corazon Aquino]], 11th President of The Philippines
*[[Gloria Macapagal-Arroyo]], 14th President of The Philippines
*[[Indira Gandhi]], Prime Minister of India
*[[Margaret Thatcher]], Prime Minister of the United Kingdom
*[[Tansu Çiller]], Prime Minister of Turkey
*[[Benazir Bhutto]]. Prime Minister of Pakistan
*[[Golda Meir]], Prime Minister of Israel
*[[Angela Merkel]], Chancellor of Germany
*[[Kim Campbell]], Prime Minister of Canada
*[[Edith Cresson]], Prime Minister of France
*[[Pratibha Patil]], President of India
*[[Soong Ching-ling|Soong Ching-ling (AKA Rosamond Soong)]] , President of the People's Republic of China
*[[Cultural Revolution|Director of the Cultural Revolution]], dictator [[Jiang Qing]]
{{div col end}}

===Current women leaders of national governments===
The following women leaders are currently in office as the either the head of their nation's government or the head of state (as of November 2011):

{| class="wikitable"
|-
! Date term began !! Title of office !! Name !! Country
|-
|01.03.2000||President||[[Tarja Halonen]]||Finland
|-
|22.11.2005||Chancellor||[[Angela Merkel]]||Germany
|-
|16.01.2006||President||[[Ellen Johnson-Sirleaf]]||Liberia
|-
|25.07.2007||President||[[Pratibha Patil]]||India
|-
|10.12.2007||President||[[Cristina Fernández de Kirchner]]||Argentina
|-
| 03.12.2008||Leader of the Government ||[[Antonella Mularoni]]||San Marino
|-
|06.01.2009||Prime Minister||[[Sheikh Hasina Wajed]]||Bangladesh
|-
|01.02.2009||Prime Minister|| [[Jóhanna Sigurðardóttir]]|| Iceland
|-
|10.06.2009||Interim President|| [[Rose Francine Rogombé]]|| Gabon
|-
|06.07.2009|| Prime Minister|| [[Jadranka Kosor]]|| Croatia
|-
| 12.07.2009|| President|| [[Dalia Grybauskaitė]]|| Lithuania
|-
| 19.05.2010|| President|| [[Roza Otunbayeva]]|| Kyrgyzstan
|-
| 08.05.2010|| President|| [[Laura Chinchilla Miranda]]|| Costa Rica
|-
|26.05.2010|| Prime Minister|| [[Kamla Persad-Bissessar]]||Trinidad and Tobago
|-
|24.06.2010||  Prime Minister|| [[Julia Gillard]]|| Australia
|-
| 08.07.2010|| Prime Minister|| [[Iveta Radičová]]|| Slovakia
|-
|10.10.2010|| Prime Minister|| [[Sarah Wescott-Williams]]|| Sint Maarten (Self-governing Part of the Kingdom of the Netherlands)
|-
|29.10.2010||Premier|| [[Paula A. Cox]]|| Bermuda (British Dependent Territory)
|-
|01.01.2011||Executive President|| [[Dilma Rousseff]]|| Brazil
|-
|01.01.2011||President||[[Micheline Calmy-Rey]]||Switzerland
|-
|19.03.2011||Prime Minister||[[Rosario Fernandez]]||Peru
|-
| 01.04.2011|| Capitano Reggente ||[[Maria Luisa Berti]]|| San Marino
|-
| 04.04.2011||-|| [[Cissé Mariam Kaïdama Sidibé]]||Mali
|-
|07.04.2011||President|| [[Atifete Jahjaga]]|| Kosovo
|-
|08.08.2011||Prime Minister|| [[Yingluck Shinawatra]]||Thailand
|-
|03.10.2011||Prime Minister|| [[Helle Thorning-Schmidt]]|| Denmark
|-
|}

===Women as cabinet ministers===
Women holding prominent cabinet posts have grown in numbers worldwide during the 20th and 21st centuries, and in recent years have increasingly held the top profile portfolios for their governments in non-traditional areas for women in government, such as national security and defense, finance, revenue and foreign relations.

====Ministers of foreign affairs====
The following women have held posts in recent years as ministers of foreign relations or the equivalent for their respective national governments:
{| class="wikitable"
|-
! Date term began !! Title of office !! Name !! Country
|-
|2007-08 and 2011-||-|| [[Erato Kozakou-Marcoullis]]|| Cyprus
|-
|2008- ||-||[[Rosemary Kobusingye Museminari]]||Rwanda
|-
|2008- ||-||[[Carolyn Rodrigues]]||Guyana
|-
|2008 ||-||[[Eka Tkeshelashvili]]|| Georgia
|-
|2008||-|| (Acting) [[Helen Clark]]||New Zealand
|-
|2008-||-|| [[Maxine McClean]]||Barbados
|-
|2008-||-|| [[Antonella Mularoni]]|| San Marino
|-
|2009- ||-||[[Dipu Moni]]||Bangladesh
|-
|2009 ||-||[[Maria Adiato Diallo Nandigna]]|| Guinea-Bissau
|-
|2009- ||-||[[Hilary Rodham Clinton]]||United States of America
|-
|2009 ||-||[[Patricia Isabel Rodas Baca]]|| Honduras
|-
|2009- ||-||[[Aurelia Frick]]|| Liechtenstein
|-
|2009-||-|| [[Maite Nkoana-Mashabane]]|| South Africa
|-
|2009-11||-|| [[Sujata Koirala]]|| Nepal
|-
|2009-11 ||-||[[Etta Banda]]|| Malawi
|-
|2009- ||-||[[Naha Mint Mouknass]]|| Mauritania
|-
|2009- ||-||[[Marie-Michele Rey]]|| Haiti
|-
|2009-||-|| [[Louise Mushikiwabo]]|| Rwanda
|-
|2010-||-|| [[Baroness Ashton of Upholland]]|| the European Union
|-
|2010 ||-||(Acting) [[Rasa Juknevičienė]]|| Lithuania
|-
|2010- ||-||[[Lene Espersen]]|| Denmark
|-
|2010-11||-|| [[Aminatou Djibrilla Maiga Touré]]|| Niger
|-
|2010-||-|| [[María Ángela Holguín-Cuéllar]]|| Colombia
|-
|2010-11 ||-||(Acting) [[Vlora Çitaku]]|| Kosovo
|-
|2010-||-|| [[Trinidad Jiménez García-Herrera]]|| Spain
|-
|2010-11 ||-||[[Michèle Alliot-Marie]]|| France
|-
|2011-||-|| [[Hina Rabbani Khar]]|| Pakistan
|-
|2011 ||-||(Acting) [[Erlinda F. Basilio]]|| Philippines
|-
|2011- ||-||[[Yvette Sylla]]|| Madagascar
|-
|}

====Ministers of defense and national security====
The following women have held posts in recent years as ministers of defense, national security or an equivalent for their respective national governments:
{| class="wikitable"
|-
! Date term began !! Title of office !! Name !! Country
|-
|2006-07 ||Minister of Defence ||[[Viviane Blanlot Soza]]||Chile
|-
|2006-11||Minister of Defense|| [[Cristina Fontes Lima]]|| Cape Verde
|-
|2007-09 ||Minister of Defence||[[Vlasta Parkanová]]||Czech Republic
|-
|2007 ||Minister of Defence||[[Guadalupe Larriva González]]|| Ecuador
|-
|2007 ||Minister of Defence ||[[Lorena Escudero Durán]]||Ecuador
|-
| 2007 ||(Acting) Minister of Defence||[[Marina Pendeš]]|| Bosnia and Herzegovina
|-
|2007-|| Secretary General of Defence with Rank of Minister || [[Ruth Tapia Roa]]|| Nicaragua
|-
|2007 ||Minister of Defence||[[Yuriko Koike]]|| Japan
|-
|2007-09||Minister of Defence||[[Cécile Manorohanta]]|| Madagascar
|-
|2008- ||Minister of Defence||[[Carme Chacón i Piqueras]]|| Spain
|-
|2008-10||Minister of Defence||[[Elsa Maria Neto D’Alva Texeira de Barros Pinto]]|| São Tomé e Príncipe
|-
|2008- ||Minister of Veterans' Affairs||[[ Judith Collins]]||New Zealand
|-
|2008- ||Associate Minister of Defence ||[[Heather Roy]]||New Zealand
|-
|2008- ||Minister of Disarmament and Arms Control||[[Georgina te Heuheu]]||New Zealand
|-
|2008-  ||Minister of Defence||[[Ljubica Jelušič]]|| Slovenia
|-
|2008- ||Minister of Defence||[[Rasa Juknevičienė]]|| Lithuania
|-
|2009- ||Minister of Defence and Veterans' Affairs||[[Lindiwe Nonceba Sisulu]]|| South Africa
|-
|2009-11 ||Minister of Defence||[[Bidhya Devi Bhandari]]|| Nepal
|-
|2009-11 ||Minister of Defence||[[Angélique Ngoma]]||Gabon
|-
|2009- ||Minister of Defence||[[Grete Faremo]]|| Norway
|-
|2010- ||Minister of Defence||[[Gitte Lillelund Bech]]|| Denmark
|-
|2010||(Acting) Minister of Defence and Security|| [[Lesego Motsumi]]|| Botswana
|-
|2011 ||Minister of Defence||[[María Cecilia Chacón Chacón]]|| Bolivia
|-
|}

====Ministers of finance or revenue====
The following women have held posts in recent years as ministers of finance, revenue, or an equivalent for their respective national governments:
{| class="wikitable"
|-
! Date term began !! Title of office !! Name !! Country
|-
|2008-11 ||Minister of Economy and Competitiveness|| [[Fátima Maria Carvalho Fialho]]||Capo Verde
|-
|2008-11 ||Minister of Finance|| [[Diana Dragutinović]]||Serbia
|-
|2008- ||Minister for the National Investment Plan|| [[Verica Kalanović]]||Serbia
|-
|2008 ||Minister of Finance|| [[Wilma Josefina Salgado Tamayo]]|| Ecuador
|-
|2008- ||Minister of Finance|| [[María Elsa Viteri Acaiturri]]|| Ecuador
|-
|2009- ||Minister of Economy|| [[Helena Nosolini Embalo]]|| Guinea-Bissau
|-
|2009- ||Chairperson of the Council of Economic Advisors|| [[Christina Romer]]|| United States
|-
|2009- ||Minister of Finance|| [[Clotilde Niragira]]|| Burundi
|-
|2009-11 ||Minister of Finance|| [[Syda Namirembe Bumba]]||Uganda
|-
|2009-11 ||Government Councillor of Finance and Economy|| [[Sophie Thevenoux]]|| Monaco
|-
|2009- ||Minister of Finance and Economy|| [[Elena Salgado Méndez]]|| Spain
|-
|2009- ||Minister of Finance|| [[Ingrida Simonytė]]|| Lithuania
|-
|2009-|| Minister of Economic Affairs|| [[Michelle Winklaar]]|| Aruba (Dutch External Territory)
|-
|2009-11 ||Minister of Finance ||[[Raya Haffar al-Hassan]]|| Lebanon
|-
|2010-11|| Minister of Economy|| [[Lamia Assi]]||Syria
|-
|2010- ||Minister of Economic Policy|| [[Katiuska Kruskaya King Mantilla]]|| Ecuador
|-
|2010- ||Chairperson of Economic Planning Council|| [[Christina Y. Liu]]||Taiwan
|-
|2010- ||Economic Secretary to the Treasury|| [[Justine Greening]]|| United Kingdom
|-
|2010- ||Minister of Economic and Stability Development ||[[Vera Kobalia]]|| Georgia
|-
|2010- ||Minister of Economy|| [[Darja Radić]]|| Slovenia
|-
|2010-11|| Minister of Finance|| [[Wonnie Boedhoe]]|| Suriname
|-
|2010- ||Minister of Finance|| [[Penny Wong]]|| Australia
|-
|2010- ||Federal Councillor of Finance|| [[Eveline Widmer-Sclumpf]]|| Switzerland
|-
|2010- ||Minister for Economy|| [[Kim Wilson]]|| Bermuda (British Dependent Territory)
|-
|2010 ||(Acting) Minister of Finance|| [[Elfreda Tamba]]|| Liberia
|-
|2010- ||Finance Minister|| [[Martina Dalić]]|| Croatia
|-
|2011 ||(Acting) Minister of Finance|| [[Dinara Shaydieva]]|| Kyrgyzstan
|-
|2011- ||Federal Minister of Finance|| [[Maria Fekter]]|| Austria
|-
|2011- ||Minister of National Revenue|| [[Gail Shea]]|| Canada
|-
|2011- ||Minister of Finance|| [[Jutta Urpilainen]]|| Finland
|-
|2011- ||Minister of Budget|| [[Valérie Pécresse]]||France
|-
|2011- ||Minister of Economy and Finances|| [[Adidjatou Mathys]]|| Benin
|-
|2011- ||Minister of Budget, Finances, Taxes, Numeric Economy|| [[Sonia Backès]]|| Nouvelles Caledonie (French External Territory)
|-
|2011- ||Minister of Finance and Economic Planning|| [[Maria Kiwanuka]]|| Uganda
|-
|2011- ||Minister of the Treasury|| [[Anne Craine]]|| Isle of Man
|-
|2011- ||Minister of Economy|| [[Margrethe Vestager]]|| Denmark
|-
|}

==Comparing women's integration into branches of government==
===Executive branch===
Women have been notably underrepresented in the executive branch of government.  The gender gap has been closing, however, albeit slowly &lt;ref name="Social Development 2005"/&gt; The first women other than monarchs to hold head of state positions were in socialist countries. The first was [[Khertek Anchimaa-Toka]] of the [[Tuvan People's Republic]] from 1940–1944, followed by [[Sükhbaataryn Yanjmaa]] of the [[Mongolian People's Republic]] 1953-1954 and [[Soong Ching-ling]] of the [[People's Republic of China]] from 1968–1972 and 1981.

Following the socialist countries, the Nordic countries have been forerunners in including women in the executive branch. The [[second cabinet Brundtland]] (1986–1989) was historical in that 8 out of 18 cabinet members were women, and in 2007 the [[second cabinet Stoltenberg]] (2005–present) was more than 50% women. Some current female politicians that have reached top positions in the Nordic countries are the President of [[Finland]], [[Tarja Halonen]] and [[Deputy Prime Minister of Sweden]], [[Maud Olofsson]].

In 2003, Finland had a historical moment when all top leaders of the country were women and also represented different political parties: [[Social Democratic Party of Finland|Social democrat]] [[Tarja Halonen]] was President, [[Riitta Uosukainen]] from [[National Coalition Party]] was [[Speaker of the Parliament of Finland|Speaker of the Parliament]] and after the [[Finnish parliamentary election, 2003|parliamentary elections of 2003]] [[Anneli Jäätteenmäki]] from [[Centre Party (Finland)|Center party]] was on her way to become the first female [[Prime Minister of Finland]]. By June 22, 2010 [[Mari Kiviniemi]] of the Centre Party was appointed the second female [[Prime Minister of Finland]].

The world's first elected [[List of elected or appointed female heads of state|female president]] was [[Vigdís Finnbogadóttir]] of [[Iceland]], whose term lasted from 1980 to 1996.

In 2005, [[Ellen Johnson Sirleaf]] of [[Liberia]] became Africa's first elected female head of state.

===Legislative branch===
It was not until World War I and the first socialist revolutions that the first few women became members of governments. [[Alexandra Kollontai]] became the first female to hold a minister position, as the People's Commissar for Social Welfare in [[Russian Soviet Federative Socialist Republic|Soviet Russia]] in 1917.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.guide2womenleaders.com/First-female-ministers.htm&lt;/ref&gt; [[Nina Bang]], Danish Minister of Education from 1924–26, was the world's second full female cabinet minister.

The first female head of government was [[Evgenia Bosh]], the [[Bolshevik]] military leader who held the People's Secretary of Internal Affairs position in the Ukraine People's Republic of the Soviets of Workers and Peasants from 1917–1918, which was responsible for executive functions.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.guide2womenleaders.com/Premier_Ministers.htm&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.worldstatesmen.org/Ukraine.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.kmu.gov.ua/control/uk/publish/article?art_id=1261011&amp;cat_id=661258&lt;/ref&gt; Nevertheless, development was slow and it was not until the end of the 20th century that female ministers stopped being unusual.

The first government organization formed with the goal of women's equality was the [[Zhenotdel]], in Soviet Russia.

According to a 2006 report by the [[Inter-Parliamentary Union]], 16% of all parliament members in the world are female. In 1995, the [[United Nations]] set a goal of 30% female representation.&lt;ref name="2006report"&gt;{{Cite news|author= |title=Women politicians 'making gains' |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/4758036.stm |work=BBC News |date=28 February 2006 |accessdate=2007-11-18 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The current annual growth rate of women in national parliaments is about 0.5% worldwide. At this rate, gender parity in national legislatures will not be achieved until 2068.&lt;ref name="unicef.org"/&gt;

The top ten countries in terms of number of female parliamentary members are [[Rwanda]] with 56.3%, [[Sweden]] (47.0%), [[Cuba]] (43.2%), [[Finland]] (41.5%), [[the Netherlands]] (41.3%), [[Argentina]] (40.0%), [[Denmark]] (38.0%), [[Angola]] (37.3%), [[Costa Rica]] (36.8%), [[Spain]] (36.3%)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ipu.org/wmn-e/arc/classif301108.htm]&lt;/ref&gt;. Cuba has the highest percentage for countries without a quota. In South Asia, Nepal is highest in the rank of women participation in politics with (33%)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sapint.org/]&lt;/ref&gt;. In the United States in 2008, the [[New Hampshire State Senate]] became the first state legislature upper house to possess an elected female majority.

The United Kingdom and United States are roughly in line with the world average. The [[House of Lords]] has 139 women (19.7%), while there are [[Women in the British House of Commons|125 women]] (19.4%) in the [[British House of Commons]].

===Local representation===
There has been an increasing focus on women’s representation at a local level.&lt;ref name="Basu, Amriyta 2003"/&gt;  Most of this research is focused on developing countries.  Governmental decentralization often results in local government structures that are more open to the participation of women, both as elected local councilors and as the clients of local government services.&lt;ref name="Social Development 2005"/&gt;
A 2003 survey conducted by United Cities and Local Governments (UCLG), a global network supporting inclusive local governments, found that the average proportion of women in local council was 15%.  In leadership positions, the proportion of women was lower: for instance, 5% of mayors of Latin American municipalities are women.

According to a comparative study of women in local governments in East Asia and the Pacific, women have been more successful in reaching decision-making position in local governments than at the national level.&lt;ref name="unicef.org"/&gt;  Local governments tend to be more accessible and have more available positions.  Also, women’s role in local governments may be more accepted because they are seen as an extension of their involvement in the community.

====Indian panchayats====
The local panchayat system in India provides an example of women’s representation at the local governmental level.&lt;ref name="Basu, Amriyta 2003"/&gt; The 73rd and 74th Constitutional Amendments in 1992 mandated panchayat elections throughout the country.  The reforms reserved 33% of the seats for women and for castes and tribes proportional to their population.  Over 700,000 women were elected after the reforms were implemented in April 1993.

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
*Eileen McDonagh (2009),  ''The Motherless State: Women's Political Leadership and American Democracy'', University of Chicago Press ISBN 9780226514550
*Helene Silverberg (1998),  "A Government of Men:  Gender, the City, and the New Science of Politics," in Silverberg (ed.), ''Gender and American Social Science:  the formative years'' (Princeton, NJ:  Princeton University Press).

==See also==
*[[List of the first female holders of political offices]]
*[[List of elected or appointed female heads of state]]
*[[List of elected or appointed female deputy heads of government]]
*[[Council of Women World Leaders]]

==External links==
*[http://www.qub.ac.uk/cawp/ Centre for Advancement of Women in politics] ([[Queens University, Belfast]])
* [http://www.planetrulers.com/female-leaders/ Current female leaders]
*[http://www.gutenberg.org/etext/27192 ''Political Women'' (Vol. 1 of 2)] by Sutherland Menzies ([[floruit|fl.]] 1840-1883)

{{DEFAULTSORT:Women In Politics}}
[[Category:Women in politics]]
[[Category:Gender studies]]
[[Category:Women's rights]]
[[de:Frauen in der Politik]]
[[pt:Mulheres na política]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>