<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20100918023157|385466445" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="13200141" pageid="13200141" ns="0" title="Women in government"><revisions><rev timestamp="2010-09-25T10:33:29Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Women in society}}
{{Refimprove|date=February 2009}}
'''Women in politics''' have historically been under-represented in [[Western world|Western societies]] compared to men.  Many women, however, have been politically elected to be heads of state and government.  Most prominent may be the female leaders of [[world power]]s such as  [[Prime Minister of India]] [[Indira Gandhi]], [[Prime Minister of the United Kingdom]] [[Margaret Thatcher]], [[Prime Minister of Israel]] [[Golda Meir]], [[Chancellor of Germany (Federal Republic)|Chancellor of Germany]] [[Angela Merkel]], [[Prime Minister of Canada]] [[Kim Campbell]], [[Prime Minister of France]] [[Edith Cresson]], [[President of India]] [[Pratibha Patil]], [[President of the People's Republic of China]] [[Soong Ching-ling|Soong Ching-ling (AKA Rosamond Soong)]], and [[Cultural Revolution|Director of the Cultural Revolution]], dictator [[Jiang Qing]].

==Women's suffrage==
{{Main|Women's suffrage}}
{{Expand section|date=July 2008}}

==Executive branch of government==
The first women other than monarchs to hold head of state positions were in socialist countries. The first was [[Khertek Anchimaa-Toka]] of the [[Tuvan People's Republic]] from 1940–1944, followed by [[Sükhbaataryn Yanjmaa]] of the [[Mongolian People's Republic]] 1953-1954 and [[Soong Ching-ling]] of the [[People's Republic of China]] from 1968–1972 and 1981.

Following the socialist countries, the Nordic countries have been forerunners in including women in the executive branch. The [[second cabinet Brundtland]] (1986–1989) were historical in that 8 out of 18 cabinet members were women, and in 2007 the [[second cabinet Stoltenberg]] (2005–present) was more than 50% women. Some current female politicians that have reached top positions in the Nordic countries are the President of [[Finland]], [[Tarja Halonen]] and [[Deputy Prime Minister of Sweden]], [[Maud Olofsson]].

In 2003 Finland had a historical moment when all top leaders of the country were women and also represented different political parties: [[Social Democratic Party of Finland|Social democrat]] [[Tarja Halonen]] was President, [[Riitta Uosukainen]] from [[National Coalition Party]] was [[Speaker of the Parliament of Finland|Speaker of the Parliament]] and after the [[Finnish parliamentary election, 2003|parliamentary elections of 2003]] [[Anneli Jäätteenmäki]] from [[Centre Party (Finland)|Center party]] was on her way to become the first female [[Prime Minister of Finland]]. By June 22, 2010 [[Mari Kiviniemi]] of the Centre Party was appointed the second female [[Prime Minister of Finland]].

The world's first elected [[List of elected or appointed female heads of state|female president]] was [[Vigdís Finnbogadóttir]] of [[Iceland]], whose term lasted from 1980 to 1996.

In 2005, [[Ellen Johnson Sirleaf]] of [[Liberia]] became Africa's first elected female head of state.

Eight [[U.S. state]]s have [[List of female state governors in the United States|woman as governors]], and twenty-three states have had a total of thirty-two. [[Governor of Wyoming|Wyoming Governor]] [[Nellie Tayloe Ross]] was the first woman to serve as a state governor, and [[Ella T. Grasso]], [[Governor of Connecticut]], was the first not to have been the wife or widow of a former governor.

==Legislative branch of government==
It was not until World War I and the first socialist revolutions that the first few women became members of governments. [[Alexandra Kollontai]] became the first female to hold a minister position, as the People's Commissar for Social Welfare in [[Soviet Russia]] in 1917 &lt;ref&gt;http://www.guide2womenleaders.com/First-female-ministers.htm&lt;/ref&gt;. [[Nina Bang]], Danish Minister of Education from 1924–26, was the world's second full female cabinet minister.

The first female head of government was [[Evgeniia Bosh]], the Bolshevik military leader who held the People's Secretary of Internal Affairs position in the Ukraine People's Republic of the Soviets of Workers and Peasants from 1917–1918, which was responsible for executive functions &lt;ref&gt;http://www.guide2womenleaders.com/Premier_Ministers.htm&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.worldstatesmen.org/Ukraine.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.kmu.gov.ua/control/uk/publish/article?art_id=1261011&amp;cat_id=661258&lt;/ref&gt;. Nevertheless, development was slow and it was not until the end of the 20th century that female ministers stopped being unusual.

The first government organization formed with the goal of women's equality was the [[Zhenotdel]], started by the government of Soviet Russia.

According to a 2006 report by the [[Inter-Parliamentary Union]], 16% of all parliament members in the world are female. In 1995, the [[United Nations]] set a goal of 30%.&lt;ref name="2006report"&gt;{{Cite news|author= |title=Women politicians 'making gains' |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/4758036.stm |work=BBC News |date=28 February 2006 |accessdate=2007-11-18 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The top ten countries are [[Rwanda]] with 56.3%, [[Sweden]] (47.0%), [[Cuba]] (43.2%), [[Finland]] (41.5%), [[the Netherlands]] (41.3%), [[Argentina]] (40.0%), [[Denmark]] (38.0%), [[Angola]] (37.3%), [[Costa Rica]] (36.8%), [[Spain]] (36.3%).[http://www.ipu.org/wmn-e/arc/classif301108.htm] Cuba has the highest percentage for countries without a quota. In South Asia, Nepal is highest in the rank of women participation in politics with (33%) [http://www.sapint.org/]

According to the same report, nine countries have no women parliament members.

The United Kingdom and United States are roughly in line with the world average. The [[House of Lords]] has 139 women (19.7%), while there are [[Women in the British House of Commons|125 women]] (19.4%) in the [[British House of Commons]]. In the U.S., 17 of the 100 [[United States Senators]] are [[Women in the United States Senate|women]], while 77 [[United States House of Representatives|Representatives]] are [[Women in the United States House of Representatives|women]] (17.9%).

==International organizations==
There has not yet been a female [[United Nations Secretary-General]].

==See also==
* [[List of the first female holders of political offices]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
*Eileen McDonagh (2009),  ''The Motherless State: Women's Political Leadership and American Democracy'', University of Chicago Press ISBN 9780226514550
*Helene Silverberg (1998),  "A Government of Men:  Gender, the City, and the New Science of Politics," in Silverberg (ed.), ''Gender and American Social Science:  the formative years'' (Princeton, NJ:  Princeton University Press).

==External links==
*[http://www.qub.ac.uk/cawp/ Centre for Advancement of Women in politics] ([[Queens University, Belfast]]
* [http://www.planetrulers.com/female-leaders/ Current female leaders]
*[http://www.gutenberg.org/etext/27192 ''Political Women'' (Vol. 1 of 2)] by Sutherland Menzies ([[floruit|fl.]] 1840-1883)

{{DEFAULTSORT:Women In Politics}}
[[Category:Women in politics| ]]

[[de:Frauen in der Politik]]
[[pt:Mulheres na política]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>