<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20240602005453|1226818075" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="33383624" pageid="33383624" ns="0" title="Gender in advertising"><revisions><rev timestamp="2024-07-25T20:33:33Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{About-distinguish|use of gender roles in advertising|Gender Advertisements}}
{{multiple issues|
{{essay-like|date=May 2015}}
{{disputed|date=December 2014}}
{{too few opinions|date=December 2014}}
{{more citations needed|date=January 2016}}
}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=March 2024}}
'''Gender in advertising''' refers to the images and concepts in [[advertising]] that depict and reinforce [[stereotypical]] [[gender roles]]. Advertisements containing subliminal or direct messages about physical attractiveness and beauty have been of particular interest regarding their impact on men, women, and youth. Gendered advertisements have and continue to shape what is expected of a distinct gender, regarding physique and attitude.

== Creation and maintenance of gender normality ==
Advertising is a significant agent of socialization in modern industrialized societies, and is used as a tool to maintain certain social constructions, such as gender. Men and women are depicted as differing in attitudes, behavior, and social statuses.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Belknap |first1=Penny |last2=Leonard |first2=Wilbert M. |date=1991-08-01 |title=A conceptual replication and extension of erving goffman's study of gender advertisements |url=https://doi.org/10.1007/BF00289848 |journal=Sex Roles |language=en |volume=25 |issue=3 |pages=103–118 |doi=10.1007/BF00289848 |issn=1573-2762}}&lt;/ref&gt; These images are crafted to mimic real life, leading to confusion when separating the concepts of fantasy and reality in regards to advertising. In his book Gender Advertising,&lt;ref name=":13"&gt;{{Cite book |last=Goffman |first=Erving |title=Gender advertisements |date=1979 |publisher=Harper &amp; Row |isbn=0060906332 |edition=1st Harper colophon |series=Harper colophon books |location=New York}}&lt;/ref&gt; author Erving Goffman uses the term "commercial realism" for advertisers' attempts to present the advertising world in ways which it could be real. While often exaggerated, the gender stereotypes presented in the media are very much real. This is at least in some part due to the fact that when biases are present in an advertisement, they are more easily integrated into the viewer's beliefs, or if the beliefs are already present, then they are strengthened.&lt;ref name=":06"&gt;{{Citation |last=Grau |first=Stacy Landreth |title=Gender stereotypes in advertising: a review of current research |date=2018-12-14 |work=Current Research on Gender Issues in Advertising |pages=3–12 |url=http://dx.doi.org/10.4324/9781351213745-1 |access-date=2024-04-01 |publisher=Routledge |isbn=978-1-351-21374-5 |last2=Zotos |first2=Yorgos C.}}&lt;/ref&gt; When viewers saw an advertisement in which men were behaving non-stereotypically, the viewer was less likely to stereotype others on the basis of their gender.&lt;ref name=":06"/&gt; Men have historically been portrayed as dominant, financial providers, career-focused, assertive and independent, whereas women have been shown as subordinate, low-position workers, or loving wives and mothers whose responsibilities focus on raising children and doing housework. Those who do not mimic the stereotypical gender portrayals seen in advertisements and other forms of media may feel that they are inferior because of their differences, which can deter a person from choosing to pursue the life they desire, posing a threat to their mental health.&lt;ref name=":03"&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Antoniou |first=Alexandros |last2=Akrivos |first2=Dimitris |date=2020-01-02 |title=Gender portrayals in advertising: stereotypes, inclusive marketing and regulation |url=https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/17577632.2020.1783125 |journal=Journal of Media Law |language=en |volume=12 |issue=1 |pages=78–115 |doi=10.1080/17577632.2020.1783125 |issn=1757-7632}}&lt;/ref&gt; Goffman compares the dominant and subordinate positions of men and women as similar to that of a parent and child.

There are three prominent ideologies regarding the relationship between advertisements and societal beliefs. The mirror ideology looks at advertisements as a reflection of the culture from which the advertisements are produced, whereas the mold ideology thinks of advertising as the cast that molds the culture.&lt;ref name=":06"/&gt; The last suggested relationship between advertisements and societal beliefs is a mixture of the first two and takes from both sides. Advertising professionals tend to follow the mirror ideology, and while many of them are just as capable as the consumer of identifying sexism in advertisements, these professionals tend to have a higher tolerance for sexist themes.&lt;ref name=":06" /&gt; Chinese advertising professionals, when asked in a study, view their adverts as a replication of reality rather than as a pseudo-reality that is replicated by the real world.&lt;ref name=":06" /&gt; There is much debate in the advertising world as to whether or not self-regulation is all that is needed to make discriminatory themes less common, with those in favor of this way forward advocating for awards and positive reinforcement to encourage changes while those in opposition argue that this has failed to bring about the necessary changes so far.&lt;ref name=":06" /&gt;

== Presentation of gender roles ==
=== Displays in youth advertising ===
Advertisements can be found in wide range aspects of life, such as on TV, billboards, and on social media. Children are now viewing this material at a younger age, in turn creating these perceptions whilst they are still very impressionable. Young children learn by observing and imitating what is presented to them.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Bakir |first1=Aysen |last2=Palan |first2=Kay M. |date=April 2010 |title=How are Children's Attitudes Toward Ads and Brands Affected by Gender-Related Content in Advertising? |url=http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.2753/JOA0091-3367390103 |journal=Journal of Advertising |language=en |volume=39 |issue=1 |pages=35–48 |doi=10.2753/JOA0091-3367390103 |issn=0091-3367}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Advertisements that market to young girls include a variety of stimuli that inform and shape children's inner constructs of gender. In advertisements marketed towards young girls, the color pink is frequently used, and the subjects are typically shown in clean and calm environments playing with toys that mimic real life expectations of women, such as toys that mimic household actions such as cooking and cleaning,&lt;ref name=":22"&gt;{{Cite book |last1=Frith |first1=Katherine Toland |url=https://www.worldcat.org/title/435967591 |title=Advertising and societies: global issues |last2=Mueller |first2=Barbara |date=2010 |publisher=Peter Lang |isbn=978-1-4331-0385-8 |edition=2nd |location=New York |oclc=435967591}}&lt;/ref&gt; as well as dress-up dolls. The most famous example of the dress-up doll is Barbie, which has played a role in the internalized body ideals of women across generations, resulting in a high level of body dissatisfaction.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Nesbitt |first1=Amy |last2=Sabiston |first2=Catherine M. |last3=deJonge |first3=Melissa |last4=Solomon-Krakus |first4=Shauna |last5=Welsh |first5=Timothy N. |date=2019-06-25 |editor-last=Urgesi |editor-first=Cosimo |title=Barbie's new look: Exploring cognitive body representation among female children and adolescents |journal=PLOS ONE |language=en |volume=14 |issue=6 |pages=e0218315 |doi=10.1371/journal.pone.0218315 |doi-access=free |issn=1932-6203 |pmc=6592527 |pmid=31237885|bibcode=2019PLoSO..1418315N }}&lt;/ref&gt;

High beauty standards are also placed on young girls through means such as teen magazines and social media, resulting in an increasing pressure on young girls to appear sexualized and conventionally attractive.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Papageorgiou |first1=Alana |last2=Fisher |first2=Colleen |last3=Cross |first3=Donna |author-link3=Donna Cross |date=2022-06-27 |title="Why don't I look like her?" How adolescent girls view social media and its connection to body image |journal=BMC Women's Health |volume=22 |issue=1 |pages=261 |doi=10.1186/s12905-022-01845-4 |issn=1472-6874 |pmc=9238066 |pmid=35761231 |doi-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt; Recent studies have shown that young girls that spend more time on social media show increased pressure and efforts in emulating the images that they see.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Papageorgiou |first1=Alana |last2=Fisher |first2=Colleen |last3=Cross |first3=Donna |date=December 2022 |title="Why don't I look like her?" How adolescent girls view social media and its connection to body image |journal=BMC Women's Health |language=en |volume=22 |issue=1 |doi=10.1186/s12905-022-01845-4 |doi-access=free |issn=1472-6874 |pmc=9238066 |pmid=35761231}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Young boys are commonly seen in advertisements displaying aggressive, and occasionally violent behavior when playing with their toys.&lt;ref name=":22" /&gt; Boys can be seen playing with a variety of toys with themes of violence, such as action figures wielding weapons, or toy weapons, with research suggesting that this type of play can desensitize young boys to violence.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Basch |first1=Corey |last2=Guerra |first2=Laura |last3=Reeves |first3=Rachel |last4=Basch |first4=Charles |date=2015-10-25 |title=Advertising Violent Toys in Weekly Circulars of Popular Retailers in the United States |url=http://journals.tbzmed.ac.ir/HPP/Abstract/HPP_3153_20150601010123 |journal=Health Promotion Perspectives |language=en |volume=5 |issue=3 |pages=191–197 |doi=10.15171/hpp.2015.023 |pmid=26634197 |issn=2228-6497}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Boys have historically been subject to a wider variety of toys or games to play with. Some examples of these traditionally include hardware tools, cars, and action figures. Boys are also shown playing with toys that mimic a wider variety of skills and abilities that could be used in workplaces, influencing them to desire a wider variety of jobs from a young age.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Endendijk |first1=Joyce J. |last2=Portengen |first2=Christel M. |date=2022-01-19 |title=Children's Views About Their Future Career and Family Involvement: Associations With Children's Gender Schemas and Parents' Involvement in Work and Family Roles |journal=Frontiers in Psychology |volume=12 |doi=10.3389/fpsyg.2021.789764 |doi-access=free |pmid=35126242 |pmc=8809201 |issn=1664-1078}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Displays of feminine gender roles ===
Goffman states that women are weakened by advertising portrayals in five categories: relative size, feminine touch, function ranking ritualization of subordination, and licensed withdrawal. Advertisements that are targeted at women, or that use female actors, often draw from themes of family-life, the natural environment, and fashion.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Törrönen |first1=Jukka |last2=Rolando |first2=Sara |date=November 2017 |title=Women's changing responsibilities and pleasures as consumers: An analysis of alcohol-related advertisements in Finnish, Italian, and Swedish women's magazines from the 1960s to the 2000s |url=http://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.1177/1469540516631151 |journal=Journal of Consumer Culture |language=en |volume=17 |issue=3 |pages=794–822 |doi=10.1177/1469540516631151 |issn=1469-5405}}&lt;/ref&gt; Women are also less often in humorous advertisements, and when advertisements are less comical, the stereotypes they portray tend to be taken more seriously.&lt;ref name=":06"/&gt;

In the late 19th and early 20th centuries, products, such as; moisturizers, soaps, deodorants, and shampoos were marketed to women through newly developed tactics of fear, sex, and emulation,&lt;ref name=":32"&gt;{{Cite book |last=Sivulka |first=Juliann |title=Soap, sex, and cigarettes: a cultural history of american advertising |date=2012 |publisher=Wadsworth |isbn=978-1-133-31113-3 |edition=2 |location=Boston}}&lt;/ref&gt; three key strategies that continues to influence advertising into the modern era. Fear tactics in advertisements from this time period often depict women that fail to meet the social expectation that they always appear presentable facing social rejection, painting them as outcasts and undesirable to men, with many examples from advertisements of this period shaming women that fail to maintain an assumed level of personal hygiene. Advertisements held the promise that through buying their product, women would become more desirable.&lt;ref name=":32" /&gt;

Expectations that women were to maintain clean environments, care for their children, and serve their husbands were enforced through advertisements of this period as well. Many advertisers held the promise that a potential buyer will be able to perform these tasks more simply and more efficiently.&lt;ref name=":32" /&gt; Female subjects are commonly portrayed as helpless in any areas besides what is expected of them, relying on men to perform more mentally or physically laborious tasks for them.&lt;ref name=":13"/&gt;

=== Displays of masculine gender roles ===
Men have historically been portrayed in advertisements as independent, breadwinners, tough, invulnerable, athletic, and generally more capable than their female counterparts. Men in advertisements are usually pictured as leaders in and out of the household, being able to accomplish extreme tasks with little effort or assistance. When shown in advertisements with women, men are typically seen in a dominant position both socially and physically.&lt;ref name=":13"/&gt; This can be seen in advertisements that show a man finding entertainment in watching a woman perform daily tasks, or critiquing a woman's lack of ability to perform these tasks to his standard.&lt;ref name=":32" /&gt;

Research found more than 100 advertisements during sports coverage targeted towards men portrayed men as a part of a family, but only 7 of those portrayed said men with emotional aspects and connections with the children in their family.&lt;ref name=":42"/&gt; In 225 advertisements directed towards children, 7 of them portrayed the role of a father, with 20 of them portraying the role of a mother.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Gentry |first1=James |last2=Harrison |first2=Robert |date=March 2010 |title=Is advertising a barrier to male movement toward gender change? |url=http://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.1177/1470593109355246 |journal=Marketing Theory |language=en |volume=10 |issue=1 |pages=74–96 |doi=10.1177/1470593109355246 |issn=1470-5931}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 200 commercials during programming directed towards women, only 2 of the advertisements depicted fathers in a supportive role with children. Men that fail to meet these standards, or that show feminine traits such as compassion, emotionality can be seen in advertisements as weak, and often as a source of comedy. According to the concept of hegemonic masculinity, that suggests a social value is placed on the masculine performance of gender roles, displaying feminine traits such as these results in less favorable treatment than those who display traditional characteristics of masculinity.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Messerschmidt |first=James W. |title=Masculinities in the making: from the local to the global |date=2016 |publisher=Rowman &amp; Littlefield |isbn=978-1-4422-3292-1 |location=Lanham Boulder New York London}}&lt;/ref&gt; Advertisements that defy male stereotypes were also found to be mainly targeted towards women.&lt;ref name=":06"/&gt;

== Presentation of bodies ==
Many advertisements depict people with idealized bodies, many of which are photo-shopped or edited in some way.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Taylor |first1=Charles R. |last2=Cho |first2=Yoon-Na |last3=Anthony |first3=Carissa M. |last4=Smith |first4=Danielle B. |date=2018-10-02 |title=Photoshopping of models in advertising: A review of the literature and future research agenda |url=https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/20932685.2018.1511380 |journal=Journal of Global Fashion Marketing |language=en |volume=9 |issue=4 |pages=379–398 |doi=10.1080/20932685.2018.1511380 |issn=2093-2685}}&lt;/ref&gt; Studies have shown that consuming advertisements that contain ideal body image leads to an increase in body dissatisfaction, especially in young girls.&lt;ref name=":72"&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Pelletier |first1=Luc G. |last2=Dion |first2=Stéphanie C. |date=March 2007 |title=An Examination of General and Specific Motivational Mechanisms for the Relations Between Body Dissatisfaction and Eating Behaviors |url=http://guilfordjournals.com/doi/10.1521/jscp.2007.26.3.303 |journal=Journal of Social and Clinical Psychology |language=en |volume=26 |issue=3 |pages=303–333 |doi=10.1521/jscp.2007.26.3.303 |issn=0736-7236}}&lt;/ref&gt; Regardless of gender, self-objectification when viewing ideal body images in media may lead to negative feelings towards one's body. Thinking of one's body from an outside viewer's perspective may also lead to body shame, appearance anxiety, and may contribute to certain eating disorders or disordered eating.&lt;ref name=":72" /&gt;

=== Displays of female bodies ===
[[File:Gladys_Arista_in_Inca_Kola_photography,_1970s.jpg|thumb|Gladys Arista, a former model, posing in a swimsuit for an Inca Kola advertisement in 1972.]]
Advertisements use female bodies as a key form of marketing to consumers, with women often appearing as an object of desire, something to be controlled, something to be won by men, as well as delicate and fragile in nature. Many aspects of how female bodies are portrayed in advertising stem from the male gaze.

Female bodies in advertisements can be portrayed in a hyper-feminine, pornographic way in order to market to a heterosexual male audience.&lt;ref name=":02"&gt;{{Cite book |last=Cortese |first=Anthony J. |title=Provocateur: Images of Women &amp; Minorities in Advertising |publisher=Rowman &amp; Littlefield |year=2015 |isbn=9781442217225 |edition=4th |location=4501 Forbes Boulevard, Suite 200, Lanham, Maryland 20706 |pages=15–16, 26–34}}&lt;/ref&gt; Women are usually placed in positions of submission, and are urged to pursue beauty and sex appeal through acts and behaviors of submission.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=How do Media Images of Men Affect Our Lives? |url=https://www.medialit.org/reading-room/how-do-media-images-men-affect-our-lives |access-date=2024-04-09 |website=www.medialit.org}}&lt;/ref&gt; In many advertisements, phallic objects are shown aiming at the female subjects face, breasts genitalia, or anal region in order to induce images of sexual intercourse. Sexual objectification of women may lead to anxiety, depression, and eating disorders.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Ward |first1=L. Monique |last2=Daniels |first2=Elizabeth A. |last3=Zurbriggen |first3=Eileen L. |last4=Rosenscruggs |first4=Danielle |date=August 2023 |title=The sources and consequences of sexual objectification |url=https://www.nature.com/articles/s44159-023-00192-x |journal=Nature Reviews Psychology |language=en |volume=2 |issue=8 |pages=496–513 |doi=10.1038/s44159-023-00192-x |issn=2731-0574}}&lt;/ref&gt; Women often compare their bodies to idols like models and celebrities, which lead to dissatisfaction with their body.&lt;ref name=":42"&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Prieler |first=Michael |date=2016-05-03 |title=Gender Stereotypes in Spanish- and English-Language Television Advertisements in the United States |url=http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/15205436.2015.1111386 |journal=Mass Communication and Society |language=en |volume=19 |issue=3 |pages=275–300 |doi=10.1080/15205436.2015.1111386 |issn=1520-5436}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Women are displayed as fragile, with this being commonly pictured through the feminine touch. The feminine touch&lt;ref name=":13"/&gt; refers to the idea that women are gentle by nature, and often use the image of women's hands to frame the focus of the ad in a delicate way. The feminine touch can also refer to a woman lightly grazing her own body with her hands in a similarly delicate manner.  and often seen with vacant expressions, and in dynamic poses that convey them as something to be beheld.&lt;ref name=":02" /&gt;

Magazine advertisements highlighting a thin, attractive female model yield greater self-objectification and the process of inspecting this type of advertisement can encourage women to think about their physical appearance as if looking on as a critical observer.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Harper |first1=Brit |last2=Tiggemann |first2=Marika |date=2008-05-01 |title=The Effect of Thin Ideal Media Images on Women's Self-Objectification, Mood, and Body Image |url=https://doi.org/10.1007/s11199-007-9379-x |journal=Sex Roles |language=en |volume=58 |issue=9 |pages=649–657 |doi=10.1007/s11199-007-9379-x |issn=1573-2762}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Aging women are told through media that the way in which to maintain their femininity is to preserve their bodies. Advertisements profit off of sexually exploiting young women, but steer away from acknowledging the sexuality of aging women.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |first=Toni |last=Calasanti |title=Bodacious Berry, Potency Wood and the Aging Monster: Gender and Age Relations in Anti-Aging Ads |url=https://academic.oup.com/sf/article-abstract/86/1/335/2235010?redirectedFrom=fulltext&amp;login=false |journal=Social Forces |volume=86 |issue=1 |date= September 2007 |pages=335–355 |doi=10.1353/sof.2007.0091 |access-date=2024-04-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Displays of male bodies ===
Male bodies are displayed in advertising with dominance, aligning with the belief that men are physically stronger and overall more dominant than women. When pictured with women, this is often illustrated through a man holding physical control over a woman, with images of a man's hands with a firm hold on a part of a woman's body, or through men gazing at the female subject of the photo while her expression is placed elsewhere.&lt;ref name=":02" /&gt;

Men in advertisements are depicted with an ideal body type, resulting in them usually being objectified and depersonalized.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Kolbe |first1=Richard H. |last2=Albanese |first2=Paul J. |date=December 1996 |title=Man to Man: A Content Analysis of Sole-Male Images in Male-Audience Magazines |url=http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/00913367.1996.10673509 |journal=Journal of Advertising |language=en |volume=25 |issue=4 |pages=1–20 |doi=10.1080/00913367.1996.10673509 |issn=0091-3367}}&lt;/ref&gt; Muscular body types have become the desired norm for men, regardless of their sexuality.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Connell |first=Raewyn |title=Masculinities |date=2021 |publisher=Polity Press |isbn=978-0-7456-3427-2 |edition=Second, reprinted |location=Cambridge}}&lt;/ref&gt; Aging men also face the social pressure to defy aging in an attempt to maintain their masculinity, and thus, their power.

The representation of ectomorphs (thin and lightly muscled) in advertising is limited predominantly to the advertisement of clothing that may look more appealing on slimmer, taller men. Endomorphs (soft and round) are depicted less frequently, occasionally appearing as a target of ridicule when portrayed. Representations of male bodies are often used irrespective of their relevance to the product being promoted.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite thesis |title=The cultural evolution of masculine body image: An interdisciplinary analysis of male body image regulation within men's lifestyle magazines. |url=http://dx.doi.org/10.24124/2013/bpgub964 |publisher=University of Northern British Columbia |first=Benjamin |last=Taylor|date=2013 |doi=10.24124/2013/bpgub964 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Gender in advocacy advertising  ==
&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite book |last=Cortese |first=Anthony J. |title=Provocateur: Images of Women &amp; Minorities in Advertising |publisher=Rowman &amp; Littlefield |year=2015 |isbn=9781442217225 |edition=4th |location=Lanham, Maryland |pages=15–16, 26–34}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Purity ===
Throughout the 1990s and 2000s, many activist groups campaigned in advocacy of purity. Young people of the time, particularly young girls and women, were asked to pledge to not have sex until marriage, often pledging their virginity to their fathers. In her book, ''The Purity Myth: How America's Obsession with Virginity is Hurting Young Women'',&lt;ref name=":6"&gt;{{Cite book |last=Valenti |first=Jessica |title=The purity myth: how America's obsession with virginity is hurting young women |date=2010 |publisher=Seal Press |isbn=978-1-58005-314-3 |location=Berkeley, Calif}}&lt;/ref&gt; author Jessica Valenti documents the cultural impact of this campaign. Purity was promoted in advertisements through print and television, as well as sermons, conferences, magazines, and political campaigns to promote abstinence in young people.&lt;ref name=":6" /&gt;

Images of purity in advertising were often portrayed through young, thin white women wearing pure white dresses in order to conform to a traditional, evangelical Christian form of purity.&lt;ref name=":8"&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Natarajan |first1=Madison |last2=Wilkins-Yel |first2=Kerrie G. |last3=Sista |first3=Anushka |last4=Anantharaman |first4=Aashika |last5=Seils |first5=Natalie |date=September 2022 |title=Decolonizing Purity Culture: Gendered Racism and White Idealization in Evangelical Christianity |url=http://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.1177/03616843221091116 |journal=Psychology of Women Quarterly |language=en |volume=46 |issue=3 |pages=316–336 |doi=10.1177/03616843221091116 |issn=0361-6843}}&lt;/ref&gt; The evangelical origins of this campaign imply that there is an inherit complementary function to the bodies and traditional roles of men and women that is to be upheld.&lt;ref name=":8" /&gt;

People who pledged to save their virginity often wore forms of clothing, such as graphic t-shirts containing imagery of cherries, a traditional symbol of purity, and phrases often including the word ‘chaste’ to inform viewers of their sexual status as well as purity rings.&lt;ref name=":6" /&gt;

Fear tactics were used to promote these ideals. These fear tactics included telling young people that they are far more likely to receive sexually transmitted infections, with an emphasis on the fear of HIV/AIDS, if they had sex before marriage. American school systems taught students that abstinence was a morally correct option without teaching proper sex education. Additionally, young women were warned that if they were to take birth control, they were increasing their chances of contracting STIs, and that the performance of abortions may kill them. Additionally, pressure was put on young female celebrities to maintain a pure image, with a failure to do so resulting in public ridicule and shunning.&lt;ref name=":6" /&gt;

== Depictions across cultures ==

=== United States ===
A study analyzed the gender representation differences of 394 Spanish and English TV advertisements in the United States in 2013. The results show that gender stereotypes are common in both samples. For example, more women are depicted as young people, usually at home. Males usually dress formally, while females often wear suggestive clothes. Men obviously dominate the narrator role, and product category is closely related to gender. From the perspective of social cognitive theory, advertisements rarely depict women in the workplace, which may decrease interest in jobs traditionally related to the opposite sex.&lt;ref name=":42"/&gt;

In Spanish and English advertising samples, women wear more suggestive and sexy clothing than men, and men are more fully dressed. In addition, narrators were more often male in English (male: 65.1%; female: 34.9%) and Spanish TV advertisements (male: 73.7%; female: 26.3%). The age of the protagonist has obvious gender division. More women are younger than men. Society is more tolerant of men's aging.

=== Britain ===
Among British advertisements, there were no significant differences in the roles occupied by male and female lead characters. Females appear in business or professional settings and men take on family responsibilities. In British advertisements from 2000 to 2001, the distribution of advertising clues of men (52%) and women (48%) was similar. There were 61% of male leads playing professional roles, compared to 39% of women.&lt;ref name=":5"&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Nassif |first1=Atif |last2=Gunter |first2=Barrie |date=2008-06-01 |title=Gender Representation in Television Advertisements in Britain and Saudi Arabia |url=https://doi.org/10.1007/s11199-008-9394-6 |journal=Sex Roles |language=en |volume=58 |issue=11 |pages=752–760 |doi=10.1007/s11199-008-9394-6 |issn=1573-2762}}&lt;/ref&gt;

It is now illegal to use gender stereotypes to sell goods in Britain. Britain's [[Advertising Standards Authority (United Kingdom)|Advertising Standards Authority]] announced the ban in December 2019. The new regulation stipulates that "advertisements must not include gender stereotypes that are likely to cause harm, or serious or widespread offence", and cannot show people "failing to achieve a task specifically because of their gender". For example, the advertisers cannot show women having poor driving skills or men struggling with housework in advertisements. Still, there are those who have a deep understanding of the changes made to the ASA, such as Dr. Alexandros Antoniou and Dr. Dimitris Akrivos, who see them as more of a step in the right direction rather than the solution that is truly needed. The line between what is deemed acceptable or harmful was left unclear when advertisements focus on a person’s physical appearance.&lt;ref name=":03"/&gt; The guidelines showed a disregard for limiting nudity and sexualization of people in advertisements that are potentially demeaning.&lt;ref name=":03" /&gt; The complex interactions between gender and other aspects of a person’s identity were not mentioned at all, and no push was made to make advertisements more inclusionary of people who do not conform to the gender binary.&lt;ref name=":03" /&gt; Advertisements viewed as humorous are, at times, allowed by the ASA, even if the advertisements are potentially harmful, so whether or not humor makes an advertisement less harmful may need to be addressed by future ASA guideline changes.&lt;ref name=":03" /&gt;

=== Saudi Arabia ===
Saudi Arabia, which has one of the fastest growing markets for advertising, operates strictly according to Islamic law. Men and women enjoy different rights; women may appear on TV only in limited roles. Women are emphasized in decorative features in traditional family roles. Most narrators tend to be male, and women are less likely to appear in professional situations or the workplace than men.&lt;ref name=":5" /&gt;

The environments and occasions in which men and women appear differ as well. Women are more often shown around their families and indoors, whereas men are depicted outdoors, in the workplace or as leaders. The age range is very important in Saudi Arabia's advertisements because [[Islam]]ic dress codes for women are more strict from adolescence. Of advertisements containing professional roles, 78% were filled by males, compared to 22% by females.&lt;ref name=":5" /&gt;

=== YouTube Advertisements in Israel and Germany ===
In 2022, there were two billion people who used YouTube once a month, and a majority of users were men, although this majority has been diminishing over time.&lt;ref name=":04"&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Roth-Cohen |first=Osnat |last2=Kanevska |first2=Halyna Sofiia |last3=Eisend |first3=Martin |date=2023-02-17 |title=Gender roles in online advertising |url=https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/09589236.2022.2102970 |journal=Journal of Gender Studies |language=en |volume=32 |issue=2 |pages=186–200 |doi=10.1080/09589236.2022.2102970 |issn=0958-9236}}&lt;/ref&gt; An analysis of online advertisements is becoming increasingly important as YouTube’s users are predominantly young people who are actively forming their beliefs. Many differences were found between YouTube advertisements and advertisements from traditional media forms, as well as the types of gender stereotypes displayed in its advertisements. What kinds of differences those entail depends on where the viewer lives as well as the user viewing history on the site, which was accounted for in any statistics mentioned in this section.&lt;ref name=":04" /&gt;

While it is more common for media adverts to focus on stereotypes regarding employment, most gender stereotypes depicted in YouTube adverts are based on physical appearance.&lt;ref name=":04" /&gt; Women in adverts in Germany were twice as likely to have a body shape preferred by society, while in Israel, they were five times as likely.&lt;ref name=":04" /&gt; Women in Israeli advertising were overwhelmingly the consumers of a product and were rarely if ever, depicted as authority figures.&lt;ref name=":04" /&gt; In German advertisements, women were seven times more likely to be young, and in Israel, it was not much better as women were five times as likely to be young.&lt;ref name=":04" /&gt; So much of the time, women in these advertisements were young consumers who had appearances viewed as the ideal in society, which alienates the majority of women who do not fall into this demographic and can set sexist and unrealistic expectations. Women were half as likely to be in comedic advertisements.&lt;ref name=":04" /&gt; Like in many other cultures, the narration was dominated by male voices in both Israel and Germany.&lt;ref name=":04" /&gt; Men in both cultures were three times more likely than women to make fact-based arguments for a product; this rate was twice as high as that observed in traditional advertisements.&lt;ref name=":04" /&gt; To sum up, men are more often made to be funny and intellectual, while women tend to be objectified often without having a voice in the same way men do.

=== Television advertisements in Hong Kong, Japan, and South Korea ===
Often, countries and territories in general regions tend to be grouped together, but gender advertisements in any media form will always vary to some degree depending on the culture that produces the media. Still, general trends in advertising tend to be relatively consistent across cultures, as sexist media depictions exist just about everywhere media exists.&lt;ref name=":05"&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Prieler |first=Michael |last2=Ivanov |first2=Alex |last3=Hagiwara |first3=Shigeru |date=1970-01-01 |title=Gender representations in East Asian advertising: Hong Kong, Japan, and Shouth Korea |url=https://revistas.unav.edu/index.php/communication-and-society/article/view/35966 |journal=Communication &amp; Society |volume=28 |issue=1 |pages=27–42 |doi=10.15581/003.28.35966 |issn=2386-7876|hdl=10171/37952 |hdl-access=free }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In South Korea, men were over 56 times more likely to be fully clothed than women.&lt;ref name=":05" /&gt; Women were also four times as likely to be seen in a home setting, and less than .05% of the time, women were seen in the workplace.&lt;ref name=":05" /&gt; Of all three places studied, only South Korea had more female advertisers than males.&lt;ref name=":05" /&gt; Narration in South Korean advertisements was roughly evenly distributed between men and women, but when beauty and hygiene advertisements were ignored, men were more likely to be narrators.&lt;ref name=":05" /&gt;

In Japan, more than 45% of women in advertisements were dressed in a suggestive manner.&lt;ref name=":05" /&gt; Japan had arguably the most even overall representation of people in the workplace and people at home, albeit it was still very uneven. Men were 1.7 times as likely to be in a work environment, and women were 1.82 more likely to be in a domestic environment.&lt;ref name=":05" /&gt; In both Japan and South Korea, men tended to be more middle-aged.&lt;ref name=":05" /&gt;

Of the three countries and territories, Hong Kong was the most egalitarian in regard to gender. Women were only very slightly more likely than men to appear in advertisements in a home setting, but they were nearly seven times less likely to be in advertisements in a work setting.&lt;ref name=":05" /&gt; This was the only place out of the three where men in advertisements were also predominately young.&lt;ref name=":05" /&gt; Still, women in the advertisements were often young and suggestively dressed nearly 33% of the time.&lt;ref name=":05" /&gt;

In all countries and territories, women depicted in advertisements were young at least 70% of the time.&lt;ref name=":05" /&gt; Men were also across all three cultures never suggestively dressed more than 4% of the time.&lt;ref name=":05" /&gt; Women were always more likely to be provocatively dressed and were always less likely to be in a work environment.&lt;ref name=":05" /&gt; Aside from hygiene and beauty products, which women appeared in at twice the rate of men, women were less often the narrator.&lt;ref name=":05" /&gt;

== Viewers' perception of traditionally gendered advertisements ==
There exists a common misconception that gender stereotypes in advertising help boost sales, but this is largely the opposite of the truth. When advertisements’ depictions of gender were non-stereotypical, people generally viewed the brand and product in a more positive light while experiencing a feeling of social connectedness.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Liljedal |first=Karina T. |last2=Berg |first2=Hanna |last3=Dahlen |first3=Micael |date=2020-04-24 |title=Effects of Nonstereotyped Occupational Gender Role Portrayal in Advertising |url=http://dx.doi.org/10.2501/jar-2020-008 |journal=Journal of Advertising Research |volume=60 |issue=2 |pages=179–196 |doi=10.2501/jar-2020-008 |issn=0021-8499}}&lt;/ref&gt; Reactions are dependent on how one views gender, but generally, when men were the focus of these non-stereotypical advertisements, it resulted in more interest in the product, increased sales, and more attentive viewing of the advertisement.&lt;ref name=":06"/&gt; A study conducted in South Africa, the UK, and Poland found that regardless of political affiliation when men played roles where they displayed more warmth at the expense of competence, the advertisements were viewed more positively.&lt;ref name=":08"&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Zawisza |first=Magdalena |last2=Luyt |first2=Russell |last3=Zawadzka |first3=Anna Maria |last4=Buczny |first4=Jacek |date=2018-05-19 |title=Does it pay to break male gender stereotypes in advertising? A comparison of advertisement effectiveness between the United Kingdom, Poland and South Africa |url=https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/09589236.2016.1234369 |journal=Journal of Gender Studies |language=en |volume=27 |issue=4 |pages=464–480 |doi=10.1080/09589236.2016.1234369 |issn=0958-9236}}&lt;/ref&gt; The study found that the contents of the stereotype were more important than the fact that there simply existed a stereotype in the advertisement, and this could be an explanation for why studies looking at the effects of female stereotypes on consumer opinion often yielded conflicting results.&lt;ref name=":08" /&gt; Often, it seems that positive evaluations lie in likability and warmth rather than gender stereotypes.&lt;ref name=":08" /&gt;

Gender stereotypes in advertisements generally have a negative impact on the product and company, but the evaluation of these stereotypes and advertisements by an individual is much more nuanced than any generalization can be. In a South Korean study, it was found that a person’s desire to be unique and whether they tend to be independent or interdependent affected their perceptions of an advertisement that contained gender stereotypes. Those who felt a greater need for uniqueness and viewed themselves as relatively independent had a lower tolerance for gender stereotypes, whereas the opposite was true for those who think of themselves as generally interdependent and do not desire high levels of uniqueness.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Chu |first=Kyounghee |last2=Lee |first2=Doo-Hee |last3=Kim |first3=Ji Yoon |date=2015-11-27 |title=The effect of non-stereotypical gender role advertising on consumer evaluation |url=http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/02650487.2015.1110942 |journal=International Journal of Advertising |volume=35 |issue=1 |pages=106–134 |doi=10.1080/02650487.2015.1110942 |issn=0265-0487}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A large factor in the evaluation of advertisements depicting gender stereotypes or non-cis gendered people was political ideology. Conservatives in the aforementioned multinational study were found to view advertisements containing traditional gender roles slightly more positively than liberals.&lt;ref name=":08" /&gt; Despite conservatives in all countries liking the non-stereotypical advertisement more, in South Africa, conservatives were still more likely to purchase a product with advertising that showed traditional gender norms.&lt;ref name=":08" /&gt; The opposite was seen in Poland, but this may have been the result of Polish conservatives fearing being viewed as sexist.&lt;ref name=":08" /&gt; Tolerance for LGBTQ imagery depends to some degree on political affiliation.&lt;ref name=":12"&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Northey |first=Gavin |last2=Dolan |first2=Rebecca |last3=Etheridge |first3=Jane |last4=Septianto |first4=Felix |last5=van Esch |first5=Patrick |date=2020-04-24 |title=LGBTQ Imagery in Advertising |url=http://dx.doi.org/10.2501/jar-2020-009 |journal=Journal of Advertising Research |volume=60 |issue=2 |pages=222–236 |doi=10.2501/jar-2020-009 |issn=0021-8499}}&lt;/ref&gt; Conservatives often felt a greater level of disgust and did so more frequently than liberals when viewing LGBTQ imagery, aside from lesbian imagery, which was rated similarly to heterosexual imagery.&lt;ref name=":12" /&gt; Male homosexuality can be viewed as an affront to masculinity, which might explain why female homosexuality was rated as more favorable. The portrayal of gender in advertisements can elicit emotional responses from people, and generally, heterosexual individuals prefer less overt LGBTQ imagery.&lt;ref name=":12" /&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Criticism of advertising]]
* [[Effects of advertising on teen body image]]
* [[Exploitation of women in mass media]]
* ''[[Gender Advertisements]]''
* ''[[Killing Us Softly]]''
* [[Media and gender]]
* [[Sex in advertising]]

== References ==
{{Reflist|30em}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Advertising]]
[[Category:Gender roles]]
[[Category:Communication]]
[[Category:Sexual attraction]]
[[Category:Stereotypes]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>