<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20151121020713|691621624" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="33383624" pageid="33383624" ns="0" title="Gender in advertising"><revisions><rev timestamp="2015-11-21T02:08:12Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{multiple issues|
{{editorial|date=May 2015}}
{{disputed|date=December 2014}}
{{too few opinions|date=December 2014}}
}}
'''Gender advertisement''' refers to the images in [[advertising]] that depict [[stereotypical]] [[gender roles]] and displays. Gender displays are used heavily in advertising in order to establish the role of one gender in relation with the other, and some scholars argue that advertisers are obsessed with gender.&lt;ref name="sut objectification"&gt;{{cite web|last=Jhally|first=Sut|title=What's Wrong With a Little Objectification?|url=http://www.sutjhally.com/articles/whatswrongwithalit/|accessdate=14 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Advertisers focus on gender relationships, because people define themselves by gender, and gender can be “communicated at a glance,” making it easy for advertisers to use this theme in their work.&lt;ref name="sut objectification"/&gt;
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:Mencontrol7.jpg|thumb|Gender display: masculinity and femininity juxtaposition]] --&gt;

==Creation and maintenance of gender normality==

Advertising is a significant agent of socialization in modern industrialized societies, and is used as a tool to maintain certain social constructions, such as gender. Men and women are depicted as differing in attitudes, behavior, and social statuses.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | last1 = Belknap | first1 = Penny | last2 = Leonard II | first2 = Wilbert M. | title = A conceptual replication and extension of erving goffman's study of gender advertisements | journal = [[Sex Roles (journal)|Sex Roles]] | volume = 25 | issue = 3-4 | pages = 103–118 | publisher = [[Elsevier]] | doi = 10.1007/BF00289848 | date =August 1991 | url = http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/BF00289848 | accessdate = 4 December 2011 | ref = harv | postscript = .}}&lt;/ref&gt; These differences are what separate the sexes into different genders. Gender advertisements give the viewers a glimpse into a world laden with socially defined and constructed gender relations, displays, and roles.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | last = Attenborough | first = Frederick | author-link = Frederick T. Attenborough | title = Categorial feminism: New media and the rhetorical work of assessing a sexist, humorous, misogynistic, realistic advertisement | journal = [[Gender and Language]] | volume = 8 | issue = 2 | pages = 147-168 | publisher = [[Equinox Publishing (London)|Equinox]] | doi = 10.1558/genl.v8i2.147 | year = 2014 | url = https://dx.doi.org/10.1558%2Fgenl.v8i2.147 | ref = harv | postscript = .}} [http://www.academia.edu/7595138/Categorial_feminism_New_media_and_the_rhetorical_work_of_assessing_a_sexist_humorous_misogynistic_realistic_advertisement Pdf.]&lt;/ref&gt; These images are crafted to mimic real life and many mistake the concepts of fantasy and reality in regards to advertising.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | last1 = Hancock | first1 = Black Hawk | last2 = Garner | first2 = Roberta | title = Erving Goffman: Theorizing the self in the age of advanced consumer capitalism | journal = Journal for the Theory of Social Behaviour | publisher = [[John Wiley &amp; Sons|John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd.]] | doi = 10.1111/jtsb.12062 | date = March 2014 | url = http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/jtsb.12062 | ref = harv | postscript = .}} Early view (online version published before inclusion in an issue).&lt;/ref&gt; [[Erving Goffman]] would call it "Commercial Realism", when advertisers try to present the advertising world in ways which it could be real.&lt;ref name="Erving Gender"&gt;{{cite book | last = Goffman | first = Erving | title = Gender advertisements | publisher = [[Harvard University Press]] | location = Cambridge, Massachusetts | year = 1979 | isbn = 9780674341913 }}&lt;/ref&gt;   Goffman argues that advertisements do not look strange to us, when they should. Advertisements take something that exists already in the world and they change it, forming a distorted reflection. "They emphasize some things and de-emphasize others," it is a hyper ritualization of the world, and we recognize, and even relate with some of the images.&lt;ref name="sut objectification"/&gt;

==Role of gender in advertising==
It is argued that these images could be teaching the viewers a vast array of social [[Sensory cue|cues]], and even the most subtle ones make an impact on the viewers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Baran|first=Stanley J.|title=Mass communication theory: foundations, ferment, and future|year=2008|publisher=Cengage Learning|isbn=0-495-50363-0|pages=318|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=5TAebeoDnJ4C&amp;pg=PA318&amp;lpg=PA318&amp;dq=vulnerable+women+and+dominant+men+in+advertising&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=qNq6hI_8bb&amp;sig=zFlAIN7ldgTcmRmVOBFghNCU0gg&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=05OITszHI7ODsAK2u_m5Dw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=3&amp;sqi=2&amp;ved=0CEAQ6AEwAg#v=onepage&amp;q=vulnerable%20women%20and%20dominant%20men%20in%20advertising&amp;f=false|author2=Dennis K. Davis}}&lt;/ref&gt; Further it is said that gender relations are learned through advertisements.&lt;ref name="sut objectification"/&gt; Among these learned gender roles are those of [[femininity]] and [[masculinity]]. Men and women are portrayed in advertisements according to the constructed definition of femininity and masculinity. To be a woman is to be feminine and to be a man is to be masculine. There is little room for variation or a reversal of roles, except within the smaller frame of [[niche marketing]].&lt;ref name="MediaEd"/&gt;
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:Jonathan-rhys-meyers-energie.jpg|thumb|Man as alert, hand in pocket, standing upright, eyes open: Masculine]] --&gt;
===Masculinity in advertising===
In advertising, men are often portrayed in the following ways:&lt;ref name="MediaEd"/&gt;
* Alert and conscious of surroundings
* Standing upright
* Eyes open and looking around
* Bodies are controlled
* Mean expression on face
* Gripping things tightly with hands
* Hands in pockets
* Serious
* Physically active

"Bravery, adventurousness, being able to think rationally, being strong and effective, for example, are all "manly" traits that are usually encouraged. So also are the ability to think independently and take the initiative. [[Mass media|Media]] images supporting these behaviors include the strong, silent Marlboro man and military ads telling young men to be 'all you can be'."&lt;ref name="CML"&gt;{{cite web|last=Femiano|first=Sam|title=How do Media Images of Men Affect Our Lives?|url=http://www.medialit.org/reading-room/how-do-media-images-men-affect-our-lives|author2=Mark Nickerson}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Social pressure on men to endorse traditional masculinity and sexuality in advertising===
Since the 1980s, men’s bodies have been used more for advertising, depicting a similarly idealized body image to that portrayed of women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Elliott, R. and C. Elliott (2005)|title=Idealized images of the male body in advertising: a reader‐response exploration.|url=http://www.bath.ac.uk/criac/publications/pdf/15_Elliott.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; Research suggests that men feel social pressure to endorse traditional masculine male models in advertising. Research by Martin and Gnoth  (2009) found that feminine men preferred feminine models in private, but stated a preference for the traditional masculine models when their collective self was salient. In other words, when concerned about being classified by other men as feminine, feminine men endorsed traditional masculine models. The authors suggested this result reflected the social pressure on men to endorse traditional masculine norms.&lt;ref&gt;Martin, Brett A. S. and Juergen Gnoth (2009), [http://www.basmartin.com/wp-content/uploads/2010/08/Martin-Gnoth-2009.pdf "Is the Marlboro Man the Only Alternative? The Role of Gender Identity and Self-Construal Salience in Evaluations of Male Models"], ''Marketing Letters'', 20, 353–367.&lt;/ref&gt;

Further, a growing number of advertisements are showing men as [[sex object]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Kimmel, Allan J. and Elisabeth Tissier-Desbordes (1999)|title=Males, Masculinity, and Consumption: an Exploratory Investigation|url=http://www.acrwebsite.org/search/view-conference-proceedings.aspx?Id=11390}}&lt;/ref&gt; A study on male body obsession found that advertisements for everything from cars to underwear depicted body-builder images with “washboard abdominal muscles, massive chests, and inflated shoulders, a mixture of muscularity and leanness probably attainable only by drugs.”&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Pope Jr, H. G., K. A. Phillips, and R. Olivardia (2000)|title=The Adonis Complex: The Secret Crisis of Male Body Obsession.|url=http://ajp.psychiatryonline.org/article.aspx?articleid=175191}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Though women's equality is advancing in society, men have become more fixated with muscularity because it is still seen as a cultural symbol of masculinity. In addition, it has been suggested that a muscular body has become an aesthetic norm for [[Heterosexuality|heterosexuals]] as well as [[homosexual]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Connel|first=R.W (1995)|title=Masculinities.|url=http://books.google.ca/books/about/Masculinities.html?id=YuR2uFxxvPoC}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In a [[content analysis]] study of exclusively male images in men’s magazines, it was found that most of the bodies in advertising were not ‘ordinary’, but those of strong and hard ‘male figures’. The study showed that males in the advertisements were usually [[Objectification|objectified]] and [[Depersonalization|depersonalized]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Kolbe, R.H. and P.J. Albanese (1996)|title=Man to man: a content analysis of sole-male images in male audience magazines.|url=http://www.jstor.org/discover/10.2307/4189016?uid=3739400&amp;uid=2129&amp;uid=2&amp;uid=70&amp;uid=3737720&amp;uid=4&amp;sid=21101246160203}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The representation of [[Ectomorphic|ectomorphs]] (thin and lightly muscled) was limited predominantly to the advertising of clothing that may look more appealing on slimmer, taller men. [[Endomorphic|Endomorphs]] (soft and round) were rarely depicted and if they were, tended to be the object of humour. It is important to note that representations of male bodies are often used irrespective of their relevance to the product being promoted.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Patterson, M. and G. England (2000)|title=Body work: depicting the male body in men’s lifestyle
magazines, in: Proceedings of the Academy of Marketing Annual Conference, University of Derby,
CD ROM}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Femininity in advertising===
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:Guesswomandelicate.jpg|thumb|right|upright|Woman as delicate, not alert, and self-touching: Feminine]] --&gt;
[[File:Ad for a Cosmetic (059A) (7545162826).jpg|thumb|right|this ad suggests that women who do not use youth hormones will be sad because men will not love them{{cn|date=July 2015}}]]
Portrayals of women in advertising:&lt;ref name="MediaEd"/&gt;
* Touching self
* Caressing an object
* Lying on the floor
* Sitting on a bed or chair
* Eyes closed
* Not alert
* Confused
* Vulnerable
* Body contorted
* Dressed like a child
* Holding an object or a man for support
* Sexy and sexually available
* Seductive
* Playful
* Careless

These are positions of [[submissiveness]] and powerlessness. This can be clearly seen when women are shown lying on the floor as men are standing over them, literally depicting women as being beneath men.  Women are urged to pursue beauty and sex appeal, and part of the sex appeal is [[submission]].&lt;ref name="CML"/&gt;

The body – and particularly here the female body – is always inevitably controlled by [[social norm]]s&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Negrin|first=Llewellyn (1999)|title=The self as image: A critical appraisal of postmodern theories of fashion.|url=http://tcs.sagepub.com/content/16/3/99.short |accessdate=8 November 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[commodification]] of the body through industries such as fashion and beauty that exhibit femininity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Doane|first=Mary Ann (1987)|title=The Desire to Desire: The Woman's Film of The 1940s.|url=http://books.google.ca/books/about/The_Desire_to_Desire.html?id=FLWP6SPGQuYC&amp;redir_esc=y}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The discursive [[Social construction|constructions]] of these female bodies are quite plainly ‘prepared for [[Consumerism|consumption]]’ by men. These constructions not only reveal the inevitable gender-power relations about the body but also suggest the cultural ambivalence about sexualized bodily display and image management. This sort of ambivalence both idealizes and denigrates individuals' explicitly performed efforts to produce and portray bodies that conform to societal ‘ideals'.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Malson, H. and C. Swann (1987)|title=Prepared for Consumption: (Dis)orders of Eating and Embodiment.|url=http://books.google.ca/books?id=GvNCGwAACAAJ&amp;dq=Prepared+for+Consumption+%E2%80%93+dis(orders)+of+eating&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=BOiWUNDuGIfOigLwu4CgAw&amp;ved=0CDcQ6AEwAQ}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In advertising, women are made to appear a certain way to men, but women as well. Models and certain advertising strategies are used to draw in the consumer in order to purchase the product or shop at the specific store, but there are also many other outcomes. Women of all ages may look at an ad campaign, try on the clothing and automatically put one's self down for not appearing the same way the model does in the exact same piece of clothing. Femininity in advertising is not only used as a ploy of sexual appeal, as well as societal norms of how women are "supposed to look." A lot of major companies have started changing the way they advertise their company in order to be more accepting of the different types of consumers that may purchase their product. For example, American Eagle Outfitters has stopped using photoshop and other editing devices on their campaigns. Tattoos, cellulite, beauty marks, stretch marks and other things that used to be viewed as "imperfections" are now being left alone in their pictures to imply acceptance of all people. Companies like American Eagle are attempting to restore body image confidence in women and are starting to do so with their advertising. By using models that are more obtainable and realistic, consumers, especially women, will hopefully begin to feel better about the way they look and the way that they view their selves and others.

==Gender displays in advertising==
"If gender is defined as the [[culturally]] established correlates of sex (whether in consequence of biology or learning) then gender display refers to [[Convention (norm)|conventionalized]] portrayals of those correlates."&lt;ref name="Erving Gender"/&gt; Gender displays can otherwise be defined as [[rituals]] of gender behavior, and they are used to help interpret social reality.&lt;ref name="sut objectification"/&gt; This is what advertising mainly borrows from, and for Goffman this is the reason as to why ads do not look strange to the public.&lt;ref name="sut objectification"/&gt; Further, Goffman argues that there are codes which can be used to identify gender. These codes of gender can be seen in the portrayals of men and women in advertising. There are four categories under which we can see these codes of gender: the family, the feminine touch, the ritualization of [[Hierarchy|subordination]], and licensed withdrawal.&lt;ref name="Erving Gender"/&gt;

===Family===
It is said{{by whom|date=December 2014}} that grown women are depicted as young children, or [[wikt:infantilization|infantilized]] in advertising. They are shown with fingers in their mouths and dressed like children or dolls. When a family is shown in advertising, often the mother resembles the daughter, whereas that is not the case for boys and their fathers.&lt;ref name="MediaEd"&gt;{{cite web|last=Jhally|first=Sut|title=The Codes of Gender|url=http://www.mediaed.org/cgi-bin/commerce.cgi?preadd=action&amp;key=238&amp;template=PDGCommTemplates/HTN/Item_Preview.html|publisher=Media Education Foundation|accessdate=14 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  “Boys have to push their way into manhood…girls merely have to unfold.”&lt;ref name="Erving Gender"/&gt;

===Feminine touch===
It is argued{{by whom|date=December 2014}} that in ads women are often seen touching themselves, which is a sign that their body is delicate.&lt;ref name="Erving Gender"/&gt; Women are also depicted as barely touching an object or caressing it, whereas men firmly grasp an object, as if to say that they control over their life, while women are merely there.&lt;ref name="MediaEd"/&gt;

===Licensed withdrawal===
The idea that women in ads are often depicted as confused, un-alert, and mentally drifting for the scene unaware of her surroundings, while men are shown as alert, and prepared to fend off any potential threats.&lt;ref name="Erving Gender"/&gt;

===Ritualization of subordination===
Women are presented as submissive or subordinate to men. This submission can clearly be seen as the women are literally placed below men, and can often be found lying on the floor or on a bed, while men are standing upright, or sitting in a chair.&lt;ref name="Erving Gender"/&gt; Other subordinate gender displays include, head tilt, body tilt, “bashful knee bend,” other canting positions,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=White|first=Barbie|title=Sexist Advertisements: How to see through the soft sell|url=http://www.medialit.org/reading-room/sexist-advertisements-how-see-through-soft-sell|accessdate=14 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; lip biting, holding self, etc. All of these keep a person off-balance and at the mercy of their surroundings, all of these body postures signify submission.

==Role reversal==
Sometimes the traditional gender roles are reversed. When this happens, one can see men behaving in ways that are generally associated with femininity, and women behaving in typically masculine ways. This is often the case in [http://www.genderads.com/page7/gays/gays.html gay] and [http://www.genderads.com/page7/lesbians/lesbians.html lesbian] advertising. Witnessing these ads can be a shock to most, as they are not accustomed to this reversal of roles. This is an indicator that there is in fact a distinction between the genders in advertising.&lt;ref name="MediaEd"/&gt;

==Human body in consumer culture==
Within [[Consumerism|consumer culture]], the human body is celebrated as a site of pleasure. It is desirable and desiring and the closer the body is to the idealized images of youth, health, fitness, and beauty, the higher its [[exchange value]]. Consumer culture allows for the unabashed display of the human body.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Featherstone|first=Mike (1982)|title=The Body in Consumer Culture.|url=http://tcs.sagepub.com/content/1/2/18|pages=21–22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In modern times, clothing is designed to glorify the ’natural’ human physique, a stark contrast to the 19th century in which clothes were created to conceal the body. Victorian male garments (see [[Victorian fashion]]), loose fitting and conservative in subdued colours, reflected the emphasis for respectability of the male body. Victorian women had to be squeezed into corsets to accentuate the hourglass figure despite the vigorous propaganda against tight-lacing. In the bedroom, the naked body was not considered a source of beauty and joy—sex should take place in the dark.&lt;ref name="Featherstone"&gt;{{cite web|last=Featherstone|first=Mike (1982)|title=The Body in Consumer Culture.|url=http://tcs.sagepub.com/content/1/2/18|page=22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Conversely, with the rise of consumer culture in [[United States of America|America]] after [[World War II]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The American Consumer - The Rise Of The Consumer Culture, Contemporary Consumer Spending, Rising Debt, Decreasing Savings, And Stagnating Incomes.|url=http://www.libraryindex.com/pages/126/American-Consumer.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; the body was no longer an embodiment of sin but [[secularized]] and found increasingly in contexts for display both inside and outside the bedroom. Furthermore, the cultural popularity of the outdoor [[California]]n lifestyle and warm climate destinations has made leisure clothing and thus, the exposure of the human body, more acceptable.&lt;ref name="Featherstone"/&gt;

==Effects of advertisements==

Beauty can be defined largely as a perception. It is a group of social norms that interpret a particular form of appearance that is valued. Both men and women strive to achieve this beauty which influences them to shape themselves and alter their appearance in order to conform to those norms.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Cregan|first=Kate|title=Key Concepts in Body and Society|date=2012|publisher=SAGE|pages=16}}&lt;/ref&gt; These norms are largely derived from the medias presentation of models and well known stars through advertisements for products and magazine covers. As our society is now filled with these advertisements in all aspects of life, such as on TV, billboards, in supermarkets displayed with the products (particularly beauty products) and on social media, children are now viewing this material at a younger age and in turn creating the perception that this is the ideal appearance whilst they are still very impressionable.

In the early twentieth century, society began to pursue material goods with the goal of fulfilling a general desire to own the item rather than for later use.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Howson|first=Alexandra|title=The body in consumer culture|date=2004|pages=94–95}}&lt;/ref&gt; This is largely due to the use of advertising media and the perception, particularly with beauty products, that the models pictured obtain their looks buy using these products.

It is very common for young men and women to compare themselves to models in ads, in terms of their physical attractiveness.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Martin|first=Mary|author2=James Gentry|title=Stuck in the Model Trap: The Effects of Beautiful Models in Ads on Female Pre-Adolescents and Adolescents|journal=Journal of advertising|date=1997|pages=19}}&lt;/ref&gt; The appearance and body size of the models within the advertisements in the final image seen buy consumers are more often than not altered through editing programs such as Photoshop, in order to achieve the perfect (or impossible) desired look.  The use of these images creates a false beauty ideal for both men and women to aspire to, as well as creating the use of extreme dieting and surgical procedures in order to resemble a similar image that is displayed in advertising. This emphasis on an ideal body appearance has been regarded as being psychologically detrimental to the well-being of many young men and women, and on their self-image.

Magazine advertisements highlighting a thin, attractive female model yield greater self-objectification and the process of inspecting this type of advertisement can encourage women to think about their physical appearance as if looking on as a critical observer.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Harper |last2= Tiggemann|first1=Brit |first2= Marika|title=The Effect of Thin Ideal Media Images on Women's Self-Objectification, Mood, and Body Image|journal=Sex Roles|date=2008|pages=649|doi=10.1007/s11199-007-9379-x }}&lt;/ref&gt; Images from the media are frequently exposed to Western women, and the usage of skinny idealized women in advertising is prevalent. 

When sexuality is used in advertising, certain values and attitudes towards sex are 'sold' along with a product. The message may be that "innocence is sexy", that women enjoy being dominated, that the use of a certain product is naughty but legal, or that use of a certain product will make the user more attractive to the opposite sex, and many other messages.

==See also==
* [[Criticism of advertising]]
* [[Exploitation of women in mass media]]
* ''[[Killing Us Softly]]''
* [[Sex in advertising]]

== External links to YouTube ==

'''Classic advertisements'''
* [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=aBCyPdEIdOA&amp;feature=related%20 Lee Marvin - Pall Mall commercial]
* [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Spb0bo3IT0I&amp;feature=related 1960s Xerox commercial]
* [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vRYfouuHPvs&amp;feature=related 1960s Folgers coffee commercial]

'''Modern advertisements'''
* [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=I9tWZB7OUSU AXE body-spray commercial]
* [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=KGDVY_jyfDM Aqua di Gioia commercial]
* [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uLTIowBF0kE Old Spice commercial]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

[[Category:Advertising]]
[[Category:Gender]]
[[Category:Communication]]
[[Category:Sexual attraction]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>