<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20181123040141|870199033" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="6250226" pageid="6250226" ns="0" title="Reverse racism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2018-11-23T05:12:03Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{pp-vandalism|expiry=11:31, January 20, 2019|small=yes}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=October 2018}}
{{Discrimination sidebar}}

'''Reverse racism''' or '''reverse discrimination''' is a concept that portrays [[affirmative action]] in the United States and similar [[color-conscious]] programs as a form of anti-white [[racism]] on the part of [[black people]] and government agencies; it is commonly associated with [[Conservatism in the United States|conservative]] opposition to such programs.{{refn|name=Ansell|p=[https://books.google.com/books?id=8_y3Q6fzgQAC&amp;pg=PA17&amp;dq="conservative" 17]}} The concept has also been used to characterize various expressions of hostility or indifference toward [[white people]] by members of minority groups.{{refn|name=Cashmore}}

There is little to no empirical evidence to support the idea of reverse racism.{{sfnp|Ansell|2013|p=137}}{{refn|name=Garner}}{{refn|name=Spanierman &amp; Cabrera}} [[Ethnic minority|Racial and ethnic minorities]]  in the United States generally lack the power to damage the interests of white people, who remain the dominant group.{{refn|name=Dennis}} Claims of reverse racism tend to ignore such disparities in the exercise of power and authority, which scholars argue constitute an essential component of racism.{{refn|name=Cashmore}}{{refn|name=Yee}}

Despite a lack of evidence, belief in reverse racism is widespread in the United States.{{refn|name=Spanierman &amp; Cabrera}}{{refn|name=Dennis}} While the U.S. dominates the debate over the issue, the concept of reverse racism has been used internationally to some extent wherever [[white supremacy]] has diminished, such as in post-[[apartheid]] South Africa. Allegations of reverse racism therefore form part of a racial [[Backlash (sociology)|backlash]] against gains by people of colour.{{sfnp|Ansell|2013|pp=[https://books.google.com/books?id=8_y3Q6fzgQAC&amp;pg=PA17 17], 137}}

==In the United States==
{{anchor|United States}}

===Civil rights===
The concept of ''reverse racism'' in the United States is commonly associated with [[Conservatism in the United States|conservative]] opposition to color-conscious policies aimed at addressing racial inequality, such as [[affirmative action]]. Concerns that the advancement of [[African Americans]] might cause harm to [[White Americans]] date back as far as the [[Reconstruction Era]] in the context of debates over providing [[reparations for slavery]].{{refn|name=Ansell}}

Disparities in the exercise of power and authority are seen by scholars as an essential component of [[racism]]. In this view, isolated examples of favoring disadvantaged people over more privileged ones cannot constitute actual racism.{{refn|name=Yee}} Where past race-conscious policies such as [[Jim Crow]] have been used to maintain [[white supremacy]], modern programs such as affirmative action aim to reduce racial inequality.{{sfnp|Ansell|2013|pp=4, 46}}

The term "reverse racism" came into use as the struggle for African-American rights divided the white community. In 1966, [[Hosea Williams]] of the [[Southern Christian Leadership Conference]] (SCLC), publicly accused members of the [[Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee]] (SNCC) of reverse racism in their efforts to exclude or expel white people from local government in Alabama to make room for black people. Williams argued the SNCC's intended "all-black" campaign in Alabama would drive white moderates out of the [[civil rights movement]].{{refn|name="Strife"}} "Black racism" was a more common term in this era, used to describe SNCC and groups like the Black Panthers.{{refn|name="Sustar"}}{{Better source|date=December 2017}}

Allegations of reverse racism emerged prominently in the 1970s, building on the [[Racial color blindness|racially color-blind]] view that any preferential treatment linked to membership in a racial group was morally wrong.{{sfnp|Ansell|2013|p=136}} Despite affirmative-action programs' successes in reducing racial inequality, conservative opponents claim that such programs constituted a form of anti-white racism. This view was boosted by the Supreme Court's decision in ''[[Regents of the University of California v. Bakke]]'' (1978), which said that [[racial quota]]s for minority students were discriminatory toward white people.{{refn|name=McBride}}

While there has been little empirical study on the subject of reverse racism, the few existing studies have found little evidence that white males, in particular, are victimized by affirmative-action programs.{{sfnp|Ansell|2013|p=137}} Claims of reverse racism in the early 21st century tend to rely on [[anecdote]]s of isolated instances, often based on third- or fourth-hand reports, of a white person losing a job to a black person, for example; however, racial minorities in the United States generally lack the power to deny opportunities to white people as a group.{{refn|name=Dennis}} In a widely reprinted article, legal scholar [[Stanley Fish]] wrote that "'Reverse racism' is a cogent description of affirmative action only if one considers the cancer of racism to be morally and medically indistinguishable from the therapy we apply to it".&lt;ref&gt;Quoted in {{cite book |last1=Pincus |first1=Fred L. |title=Reverse Discrimination: Dismantling the Myth |date=2003 |publisher=Lynne Rienner Publishers |isbn=978-1-58-826203-5 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=JN3N3EmaIuIC&amp;q=%22reverse+racism%22 |pages=68–69}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Public attitudes===

While not empirically supported, the belief in reverse racism is widespread in the United States.{{refn|name=Spanierman &amp; Cabrera}} Whites' belief in reverse racism has steadily increased since the [[civil rights movement]] of the 1960s. The terms ''reverse racism'' and ''reverse discrimination'' initially arose in the 1970s in opposition to affirmative action and race-based policies that benefited minorities at the expense of whites. Despite data to the contrary, many whites in the early 21st century believe that anti-white racism is more prevalent than anti-black racism.{{refn|name=Newkirk}}

The critical race theorist [[David Theo Goldberg]] argues that the notion of reverse racism represents a denial of the historical and contemporary reality of racial discrimination.{{refn|name=Pinder}} In ''[[Racism without Racists]]'', the sociologist Eduardo Bonilla-Silva argues that such "color-blind racism" leads whites to dismiss efforts to redress inequality as being racist "in reverse".{{refn|name=Garner}}{{refn|name=Bonilla-Silva}} According to [[University of Kent]] sociologist Miri Song, "assertions of reverse racism often fail to consider the historically specific ways in which racial hierarchies and inequalities were institutionalized."{{refn|name=Song}}

[[Paul Kivel]] writes in ''Uprooting Racism: How White People Can Work for Racial Justice'' that instances of reverse racism are generally rare, and that many claims of reverse discrimination lack merit. According to Kivel, charges of reverse racism are "usually a white strategy to deny white racism and to counterattack attempts to promote racial justice".{{refn|name=Kivel}} Reverse racism is also said{{By whom|date=December 2017}} to deny the existence of [[white privilege]] and power in society.{{refn|name=Hill}}

====Research====
{{Refimprove science|section|date=August 2017}}
Researchers at [[Tufts University]] and [[Harvard]] reported in 2011 that many white Americans felt as though they then suffered the greatest discrimination among racial groups, despite data to the contrary.{{refn|name=Spanierman &amp; Cabrera}}{{refn|name=Fletcher}}{{refn|name=Ingraham}}

Whereas black respondents saw anti-black racism as a continuing problem, white ones tended to see such racism as a thing of the past, to the point that they saw prejudice against white people as being more prevalent.{{refn|name=Norton &amp; Sommers 2011}}{{refn|name=Norton &amp; Sommers May 2011 Jockeying}}

A 2013 study found that priming white people with status-legitimizing beliefs—which include the belief that anyone can become successful if they work hard enough—led white people to be more supportive of others who claimed they were victims of anti-white racism.{{refn|name=Wilkins et al.}}

A 2014 study by the same research team showed that white Americans who think the U.S. status hierarchy is legitimate (i.e. that those who are successful have earned their success) are more likely to think that anti-white racism exists.{{refn|name=Wilkins &amp; Kaiser}}

===Admissions===
The Supreme Court held in 2003 that racial preferences in university admissions for minority students do not necessarily violate [[Equal Protection]] in cases such as ''[[Grutter v. Bollinger]]''. The term gained widespread use in debates and legal actions concerning [[affirmative action in the United States]].{{refn|name=Sanneh}}

In 2016, the Supreme Court held in ''[[Fisher v. University of Texas (2016)|Fisher v. University of Texas]]'' that affirmative action as practiced by the [[University of Texas at Austin]] was lawful.{{refn|name=Massie}}

=== Affirmative action in the courts ===
Legal challenges concerning so-called "reverse racism" date back as far as the 1970s as asserted in such cases as ''Regents of the University of California v. Bakke''; ''Gratz v. Bollinger''; and ''Grutter v. Bollinger'' (regarding discrimination in higher education admissions) and ''Ricci v. DeStefano'' (regarding employment discrimination).{{refn|name=Norton &amp; Sommers 2011}}

==In South Africa==
The term has been used actively by both black and white South Africans after the end of [[apartheid]]. Accusations of reverse racism have been leveled particularly at government efforts to transform the demographics of South Africa's white-dominated civil service.&lt;ref&gt;Susan de Villiers and Stefan Simanowitz, [https://www.questia.com/library/1G1-288429746/south-africa-the-anc-at-100 "South Africa: The ANC at 100"], ''Contemporary Review'' 294, March 2012; accessed [http://search.proquest.com/docview/1013463231 via ProQuest], November 6, 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Nelson Mandela]] in 1995 described "racism in reverse" when Black students demonstrated in favor of changing the racial makeup of staff at South African universities.&lt;ref&gt;Karen MacGregor, [http://www.timeshighereducation.co.uk/story.asp?storyCode=97135&amp;sectioncode=26 "Mandela slams 'reverse racism'"], ''Times Higher Education", March 24, 1995.&lt;/ref&gt; Students denied Mandela's claim and argued that a great deal of ongoing actual racism persisted from apartheid.&lt;ref&gt;Abiola Sinclair, "MEDIA WATCH: All is not well, disappointments, racial clashes", ''New York Amsterdam News'', September 16, 1995; accessed [http://search.proquest.com/docview/390340787 via ProQuest]. "The students maintained that the university was living in the apartheid past with the upper echelons reserved for whites. The students are demanding that some jobs be reserved for Blacks. AZASM had denied the charge of reverse racism. They maintain it is unfair for thousands of Black teachers to be out of work while white teachers sit up in good jobs in Black schools."&lt;/ref&gt;

Mandela was later himself charged with reverse racism, during 1997 proceedings of the national [[Truth and Reconciliation Commission (South Africa)|Truth and Reconciliation Commission]]&lt;ref&gt;Dean Murphy, "Apartheid-Era Leader Defies Subpoena; S. Africa: Truth commission urges contempt charges against former President Pieter W. Botha", ''The Washington Post'', December 20, 1997; accessed [http://search.proquest.com/docview/421209639 via ProQuest]. "The move to charge Botha is particularly sensitive because it comes just days after President Nelson Mandela, in a racially charged address to the ruling African National Congress, harshly criticized white South Africans for protecting their positions of privilege and doing little to reconcile with the black majority. The speech, hailed as accurate by blacks, brought calls of reverse racism from many whites."&lt;/ref&gt; and for supporting the 1998 [[Employment Equity Bill]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|first=Gumisai|last=Mutume|url=http://www.ipsnews.net/1998/04/politics-south-africa-racism-spoils-it-for-new-democracy|title=Racism Spoils It for New Democracy|publisher=Inter-Press Service|date=April 3, 1993}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Kate Dunn, [http://www.csmonitor.com/1998/0226/022698.intl.intl.6.html "Mandela Hits White Wealth]", ''The Christian Science Monitor'', February 26, 1998.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Coloured|Mixed-race]] South Africans have also sometimes claimed to be victimized by reverse racism of the new government.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|first=Lydia|last=Polgreen|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2003/07/27/world/for-mixed-race-south-africans-equity-is-elusive.html|title=For Mixed-Race South Africans, Equity Is Elusive|work=The New York Times|date=July 27, 2003|archiveurl=https://www.webcitation.org/6C9BBHNcM|archivedate=November 13, 2012|deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt; Similar accusations have been leveled by [[Coloureds#Post-apartheid era|Indian]] and [[Afrikaner]] groups, who feel that they have not been dominant historically but now suffer from discrimination by the government.&lt;ref&gt;Danna Harman, "[http://www.csmonitor.com/2002/0926/p01s03-woaf.html South Africans try to 'beat' a segregated past]", ''The Christian Science Monitor'', September 26, 2002.&lt;/ref&gt; 

Claims of reverse racism continued into the 21st century. [[Helen Suzman]], a prominent white anti-apartheid politician, charged the [[African National Congress]] and the Mbeki administration with reverse racism since Mandela's departure in 1999.&lt;ref&gt;Scott Calvert, [http://articles.baltimoresun.com/2005-05-14/news/0505140451_1_helen-suzman-apartheid-white-liberals "Against apartheid, at odds with blacks"], ''The Baltimore Sun'', May 14, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;

South African critics of the "reverse racism" concept use similar arguments as those employed by Americans.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|accessdate=November 6, 2015|first1=Yolisa|last1=Dalamba|title=Towards An African Renaissance: Identity, Race And Representation In Post-Apartheid South Africa|journal=Journal of Cultural Studies|volume=2|issue=1|pages=40–61|year=2000|url=http://www.ajol.info/index.php/jcs/article/view/6231|doi=10.4314/jcs.v2i1.6231}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist|30em|refs=

&lt;ref name="Ansell"&gt;{{cite book |ref=harv |last=Ansell |first=Amy Elizabeth |title=Race and Ethnicity: The Key Concepts |date=2013 |publisher=Routledge |isbn=978-0-415-33794-6 |pages=[https://books.google.com/books?id=8_y3Q6fzgQAC&amp;dq=%22reverse+racism%22+%22color-concious%22 46], 135–6 |url= https://books.google.com/books?id=8_y3Q6fzgQAC}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Bonilla-Silva"&gt;{{cite book |last=Bonilla-Silva |first=Eduardo |title=Racism without Racists: Color-blind Racism and the Persistence of Racial Inequality in the United States |date=2010 |publisher=Rowman &amp; Littlefield |isbn=978-1-44-220217-7 |page=263 |edition=3rd |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=gV-NL8EJI7UC&amp;pg=PA263&amp;dq=%22racist+in+reverse%22 |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Cashmore"&gt;{{cite book |editor-last=Cashmore |editor-first=Ellis |title=Encyclopedia of Race and Ethnic Studies |date=2004 |publisher=Routledge |isbn=978-1-13-444706-0 |page=373 |chapterurl=https://books.google.com/books?id=2L-5lBDPJJMC&amp;pg=PA373&amp;dq=%22reverse+racism%22 |chapter=Reverse Racism/Discrimination}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Dennis"&gt;{{cite book |last=Dennis |first=R.M. |editor1-last=Kuper |editor1-first=A. |editor2-last=Kuper |editor2-first=J. |title= The Social Science Encyclopedia, Volume 2 |date=2004 |publisher= Routledge |location= London; New York |isbn=1-13-435969-1 |edition=3rd |chapterurl=https://books.google.com/books?id=EiNiAgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT2122&amp;dq=%22reverse+racism%22 |chapter=Racism }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Fletcher"&gt;{{cite news |last=Fletcher |first=Michael A. |title=Whites think discrimination against whites is a bigger problem than bias against blacks |url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/wonk/wp/2014/10/08/white-people-think-racial-discrimination-in-america-is-basically-over |work=The Washington Post |date=October 8, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Garner"&gt;{{cite book |last=Garner |first=Steve |title=Racisms: An Introduction |date=2017 |publisher=SAGE Publications |location=Los Angeles, Calif. |isbn=978-1-41-296176-9 |edition=2nd |url=https://books.google.com/books/about/Racisms.html?id=FGACDgAAQBAJ&amp;q=%22reverse+racism%22 |quote=Scholars should reflect on the objectives of using such a concept [as reverse racism] as a political strategy, but should not discount it from analysis just because it is not borne out as an empirical phenomenon.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Hill"&gt;{{cite book |last=Hill |first=Jane H. |title=The Everyday Language of White Racism |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Krq4fG08_38C&amp;pg=PT15 |date=2011 |publisher=John Wiley &amp; Sons |isbn=978-1-4443-5669-4 |page=15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Ingraham"&gt;{{cite news |last=Ingraham |first=Christopher |title=White Trump voters think they face more discrimination than blacks. The Trump administration is listening |url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/wonk/wp/2017/08/02/white-trump-voters-think-they-face-more-discrimination-than-blacks-the-trump-administration-is-listening |work=The Washington Post |date=August 2, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Kivel"&gt;{{cite book |author=Kivel, Paul |title=Uprooting Racism: How White People Can Work for Racial Justice |edition=3rd |date=2011 |publisher=New Society Publishers |isbn=978-0-86571-688-9 |pages=74–75 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=MayCo-8M5vgC&amp;q=%22reverse+racism%22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Massie"&gt;{{cite news |author=Massie, Victoria M. |title=Americans are split on "reverse racism". That still doesn't mean it exists. |work=Vox |date=June 29, 2016 |url=https://www.vox.com/2016/6/29/12045772/reverse-racism-affirmative-action |accessdate=September 18, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="McBride"&gt;{{cite book |last=McBride |first=David |editor1-last=Carlisle |editor1-first= Rodney P. |title= Encyclopedia of Politics: The Left and The Right, Volume 1: The Left |date=2005 |publisher=SAGE Publications |location=Thousand Oaks, Calif. |isbn=978-1-41-290409-4 |page=8 |chapterurl=https://books.google.com/books?id=Z6I5DQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA8&amp;dq=%22reverse+racism%22 |chapter=Affirmative Action}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Newkirk"&gt;{{cite magazine |first=Vann R. II |last=Newkirk |date=August 5, 2017 |title=How The Myth of Reverse Racism Drives the Affirmative Action Debate |work=The Atlantic |url=https://www.theatlantic.com/education/archive/2017/08/myth-of-reverse-racism/535689/ |access-date=March 18, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Norton &amp; Sommers 2011"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Norton |first1=Michael I. |last2=Sommers |first2=Samuel R. |title=Whites See Racism as a Zero-Sum Game That They Are Now Losing |date=2011 |journal=Perspectives on Psychological Science |volume=6 |issue=3 |pages=215–18 |pmid=26168512 |doi=10.1177/1745691611406922 |laysummary=http://now.tufts.edu/news-releases/whites-believe-they-are-victims-racism-more-o |laysource=TuftsNow |laydate=May 23, 2011 |url=http://www.people.hbs.edu/mnorton/norton%20sommers.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Norton &amp; Sommers May 2011 Jockeying"&gt;{{cite news |last1=Norton |first1=Michael I. |last2=Sommers |first2=Samuel R. |url=https://www.nytimes.com/roomfordebate/2011/05/22/is-anti-white-bias-a-problem/jockeying-for-stigma |title=Jockeying for Stigma |work=The New York Times |date=May 23, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Pinder"&gt;{{cite book |last=Pinder |first=Sherrow O. |title=Colorblindness, Post-raciality, and Whiteness in the United States |date=2015 |publisher=Palgrave Macmillan |location=New York |isbn=978-1-13-743488-3 |url=https://books.google.com/books/about/Colorblindness_Post_raciality_and_Whiten.html?id=HaihCgAAQBAJ&amp;q=%22reverse+racism%22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Sanneh"&gt;{{cite magazine |first=Kelefah |last=Sanneh |url=http://www.newyorker.com/talk/comment/2009/08/10/090810taco_talk_sanneh |title=Discriminating Tastes |work=The New Yorker |date=August 10, 2009 |archiveurl=https://www.webcitation.org/6C9DcUQni |archivedate=November 13, 2012 |deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Song"&gt;{{cite journal |last=Song |first=Miri |title=Challenging a culture of racial equivalence |journal=The British Journal of Sociology |date=March 2014 |volume=65 |issue=1 |pages=107–29|doi=10.1111/1468-4446.12054}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Spanierman &amp; Cabrera"&gt;{{cite book |ref=harv |last1=Spanierman |first1=Lisa |last2=Cabrera |first2=Nolan |editor1=Watson, V. |editor2=Howard-Wagner, D. |editor3=Spanierman, L. |title=Unveiling Whiteness in the Twenty-First Century: Global Manifestations, Transdisciplinary Interventions |date=2014 |publisher=Lexington Books |isbn=978-0-73-919297-9 |page=16 |chapterurl=https://books.google.com/books/about/Unveiling_Whiteness_in_the_Twenty_First.html?id=vt0eDQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA16&amp;dq=%22reverse+racism%22 |chapter=The Emotions of White Racism and Antiracism}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Strife"&gt;{{cite news |title=Strife on Two Civil Rights Fronts in Alabama: SNCC is Scored by King Group |work=Chicago Daily Defender |date=April 25, 1966 |page=1 |quote=The move was called 'reverse racism' by [[Hosea Williams]], Southern program director for King's Southern Christian Leadership conference. He described the effort to exclude all whites from public office as being as racist as excluding all blacks. It isn't integration, he indicated, and it isn't likely — in the long run — to help cure the nation's number one headache.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Sustar"&gt;{{cite news |last=Sustar |first=Lee |title=The fallacy of 'reverse racism' |newspaper= Socialist Worker |date= October 12, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Wilkins et al."&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Wilkins |first1=Clara L. |last2=Wellman |first2=Joseph D. |last3=Kaiser |first3=Cheryl R. |title=Status legitimizing beliefs predict positivity toward Whites who claim anti-White bias |journal=Journal of Experimental Social Psychology |date=November 2013 |volume=49 |issue=6 |pages=1114–19 |doi=10.1016/j.jesp.2013.05.017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Wilkins &amp; Kaiser"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Wilkins |first1=C. L. |last2=Kaiser |first2=C. R. |title=Racial Progress as Threat to the Status Hierarchy: Implications for Perceptions of Anti-White Bias|journal=Psychological Science |date=2013 |volume=25 |issue=2 |pages=439–46 |doi=10.1177/0956797613508412 |pmid=24343099}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Yee"&gt;{{cite book |last=Yee |first=June Ying |editor-last=Shaefer |editor-first=Richard T. |title=Encyclopedia of Race, Ethnicity, and Society |date=2008 |publisher=SAGE |isbn=978-1-41-292694-2 |pages=1118–19 |chapterurl=https://books.google.com/books?id=YMUola6pDnkC&amp;pg=PT1244&amp;dq=%22reverse+racism%22 |chapter=Racism, Types of}}&lt;/ref&gt;

}}

==Further reading==
{{wikimedia|collapsible=true}}

* {{cite journal |last=Aberger |first=Peter |year=1980 |title=Leopold Senghor and the Issue of Reverse Racism |journal=Phylon |volume=41 |issue=3 |pages=276–83 |jstor=274791 |doi=10.2307/274791}}
* {{cite journal |last=Cabrera |first=Nolan León |title=Exposing whiteness in higher education: white male college students minimizing racism, claiming victimization, and recreating white supremacy|journal=Race Ethnicity and Education |date=September 28, 2012 |volume=17 |issue=1 |pages=30–55 |doi=10.1080/13613324.2012.725040}}
* {{cite journal |last=Chang |first=Robert S. |year=1995 |title=Reverse Racism!: Affirmative Action, the Family, and the Dream That Is America |journal=Hastings Constitutional Law Quarterly |volume=23 |pages=1115–34 |url=http://www.hastingsconlawquarterly.org/archives/V23/I4/chang.pdf |accessdate=November 22, 2014}}
* {{cite magazine |url=https://www.theatlantic.com/past/docs/politics/race/fish.htm |title=Reverse Racism, or How the Pot Got to Call the Kettle Black |work=The Atlantic |date=November 1993 |author=Fish, Stanley}}
* {{cite book |last=Suiter |first=Tad |editor-last=Kiuchi |editor-first=Yuya |title=Race Still Matters: The Reality of African American Lives and the Myth of Postracial Society |date=2016 |publisher=SUNY Press |location=Albany, N.Y. |isbn=978-1-43-846273-8 |chapterurl=https://books.google.com/books?id=EC9_DQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA3 |chapter=Reverse Racism: A Discursive History}}
* {{cite book |editor1-last=Valelly |editor1-first=Richard M. |title=Encyclopedia of U.S. political history. Vol. 7 : The clash of conservatism and liberalism, 1976 to present |date=2010 |publisher=CQ Press |location=Washington, D.C. |isbn=978-0-87-289318-4 |pages=318–}}

{{Portal bar|Criminal justice|Discrimination|United States}}

[[Category:Definition of racism controversy]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Racism]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>