<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20221112001047|1121378666" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="6250226" pageid="6250226" ns="0" title="Reverse racism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2022-11-24T03:20:36Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{pp-vandalism|small=yes}}
{{short description|Concept that affirmative action and similar programs constitute anti-white discrimination}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=November 2022}}
{{Discrimination sidebar|expanded=Related}}

'''Reverse racism''', sometimes referred to as [[reverse discrimination]],{{r|Ansell}} is the concept that [[affirmative action]] and similar [[color-conscious]] programs for redressing [[racial inequality]] are a form of anti-white [[racism]].{{r|Ansell}} The concept is often associated with [[conservative]] social movements{{r|Ansell|Garner}} and the belief that social and economic gains by [[black people]] in the United States and elsewhere cause disadvantages for [[white people]].{{r|Ansell|Mazzocco}}

Belief in reverse racism is widespread in the United States; however, there is little to no empirical evidence that [[white Americans]] suffer [[systemic discrimination]].{{refn|group=Note |{{bulleted list |"Not much sober empirical study has been applied to the subject, but the studies that do exist find little evidence that reverse racism in fact exists." {{harv|Ansell|2013|p=137}} |"[T]here is no evidence that [reverse racism] is a social fact, or that a pattern of disadvantageous outcomes for white people {{lang|la|qua}} white people exists." {{harv|Garner|2017|p=185}} |"While there is no empirical basis for white people experiencing 'reverse racism', this view is held by a large number of Americans." {{harv|Spanierman|Cabrera|2014|p=16}} }} }} Racial and ethnic minorities generally lack the power to damage the interests of whites, who remain the dominant group in the U.S.{{r|Dennis}} Claims of reverse racism tend to ignore such disparities in the exercise of power and authority, which most scholars argue constitute an essential component of racism.{{r|Yee|Cashmore|Garner}}

Allegations of reverse racism by opponents of affirmative action began to emerge in the 1970s{{r|Ansell|Bonilla-Silva p211}} and have formed part of a [[White backlash|racial backlash]] against social gains by people of color.{{sfnp|Ansell|2013|pp=17, 137}} While the U.S. dominates the debate over the issue, the concept of reverse racism has been used internationally to some extent wherever [[white supremacy]] has diminished, such as in post-[[apartheid]] South Africa.{{sfnp|Ansell|2013|p=137}}

==United States==
{{See also|Race and ethnicity in the United States}}

===Overview===
The concept of ''reverse racism'' in the United States is commonly associated with [[Conservatism in the United States|conservative]] opposition to color-conscious policies aimed at addressing racial inequality, such as [[Affirmative action in the United States|affirmative action]]. Amy E. Ansell of [[Emerson College]] identifies three main claims about reverse racism: (1) that government programs to redress racial inequality create "invisible victims" in [[White Americans|white]] men; (2) that racial preferences violate the individual right of [[Equal protection clause|equal protection]] before the law; and (3) that [[color consciousness]] itself prevents moving beyond the legacy of racism.{{r|Ansell}} The concept of reverse racism has also been used in relation to various expressions of hostility, prejudice or discrimination toward white people by members of minority groups.{{r|Cashmore}}

While there has been little empirical study on the subject of reverse racism, the few existing studies have found little evidence that white males, in particular, are victimized by affirmative-action programs.{{sfnp|Ansell|2013|p=137}} [[Ethnic minority|Racial and ethnic minorities]] in the United States generally lack the power to damage the interests of white people, who remain the dominant group.{{r|Dennis}} Relations between the groups have been historically shaped by [[European imperialism]] and long-standing oppression of blacks by whites.{{r|Cashmore}} Such disparities in the exercise of power and authority are seen by scholars as an essential component of [[racism]]; in this view, individual beliefs and examples of favoring disadvantaged people do not constitute racism.{{r|Yee|Garner}} Sociologist [[Ellis Cashmore]] writes that the terms ''reverse racism'' and ''reverse discrimination'' misleadingly imply that racism is only a question of beliefs and prejudices, ignoring the material relations between different groups.{{r|Cashmore}} According to sociologist [[Rutledge Dennis]], individual members of minority groups in the United States "may be racists" toward white people, but cannot wield institutional power or shape the opportunities available to the majority as the majority does in relation to minorities.{{r|Dennis}}

===History===
Concerns that the advancement of [[African Americans]] might cause harm to [[White Americans]] date back as far as the [[Reconstruction Era]] in the context of debates over providing [[reparations for slavery]].{{r|Ansell}} Claims of reverse racism in the early 21st century tend to rely on individual [[anecdote]]s, often based on third- or fourth-hand reports, such as of a white person losing a job to a black person.{{r|Dennis}}

Allegations of reverse racism emerged prominently in the 1970s, building on the [[Racial color blindness|racially color-blind]] view that any preferential treatment linked to membership in a racial group was morally wrong.{{r|Ansell}} In his 1975 book ''Affirmative Discrimination'', sociologist [[Nathan Glazer]] described affirmative action as a kind of reverse racism.{{sfnp|Mazzocco|2017|p=23}}&lt;ref name="Blauner p377"&gt;{{cite book |last1=Blauner |first1=Bob |title=Black Lives, White Lives Three Decades of Race Relations in America. |date=2022 |publisher=University of California Press |isbn=978-0-5203-8602-0 |pages=377–378}}&lt;/ref&gt; Where past race-conscious policies such as [[Jim Crow]] have been used to maintain [[white supremacy]], modern programs such as affirmative action aim to reduce racial inequality.{{sfnp|Ansell|2013|pp=4, 46}} Despite affirmative-action programs' successes in doing so, conservative opponents claimed that such programs constituted a form of anti-white racism. This view was boosted by the Supreme Court's decision in ''[[Regents of the University of California v. Bakke]]'' (1978), which said that [[racial quota]]s for minority students were discriminatory toward [[white people]].{{r|McBride}}

===Public attitudes===

While not empirically supported, belief in reverse racism is widespread in the United States,{{r|Spanierman &amp; Cabrera}} where it has contributed to the rise of conservative social movements such as the [[Tea Party movement|Tea Party]].{{r|Garner}} White people's belief in reverse racism has steadily increased since the [[civil rights movement]] of the 1960s{{r|Newkirk}} as part of a [[White backlash|backlash]] against government actions meant to remedy racial discrimination.{{sfnp|Ansell|2013|pp=17, 137}} Ansell associates the idea of reverse racism with that of the "[[angry white male]]" in American politics.{{r|Ansell}} 

The perception of decreasing anti-black discrimination has been correlated with white people's belief in rising anti-white discrimination.{{r|Mazzocco}} A majority (57%) of white respondents to a 2016 survey by the [[Public Religion Research Institute]] said they believed discrimination against white people was as significant a problem as discrimination against black people, while only a minority of African Americans (29%) and Hispanics (38%) agreed.{{r|Massie|Jones et al.}} Researchers at [[Tufts University]] and [[Harvard]] report that as of the early 2010s many white Americans feel as though they suffer the greatest discrimination among racial groups, despite data to the contrary.{{r|Spanierman &amp; Cabrera|Fletcher|Ingraham}} Whereas black respondents see anti-black racism as a continuing problem, white ones tend to think it has largely disappeared, to the point that they see prejudice against white people as being more prevalent.{{r|Norton &amp; Sommers 2011 Losing|Norton &amp; Sommers 2011 Jockeying}} Among white respondents since the 1990s:

{{quote|Whites have replaced Blacks as the primary victims of discrimination. This emerging perspective is particularly notable because by nearly any metric [...] statistics continue to indicate drastically poorer outcomes for Black than White Americans.&lt;ref&gt;Norton &amp; Sommers, quoted in {{harvtxt|Garner|2017|p=185}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

According to Ansell, conservatives in the U.S. believe affirmative action based on membership in a designated racial group threatens the American system of individualism and [[meritocracy]].{{sfnp|Ansell|2013|p=17}} Psychological studies with white Americans have shown belief in anti-white racism to be linked with support for the existing racial hierarchy in the U.S.{{sfnp|Mazzocco|2017|p=85}}{{r|Wilkins &amp; Kaiser}} as well as the meritocratic belief that success comes from "hard work".{{r|Cyr|Wilkins et al.}}

The critical race theorist [[David Theo Goldberg]] argues that the notion of reverse racism represents a denial of the historical and contemporary reality of racial discrimination,{{r|Pinder}} while the anthropologist [[Jane H. Hill]] writes that charges of reverse racism tend to deny the existence of [[white privilege]] and power in society.{{r|Hill}} In a widely reprinted article, legal scholar [[Stanley Fish]] wrote that {{" '}}Reverse racism' is a cogent description of affirmative action only if one considers the cancer of racism to be morally and medically indistinguishable from the therapy we apply to it".{{r|Fish}} Sociologist [[Eduardo Bonilla-Silva]] calls the "anti–affirmative action and 'reverse racism' mentality" that has become dominant since the 1980s part of a "mean-spirited white racial animus".&lt;ref name="Bonilla-Silva p211"&gt;{{cite book |last1=Bonilla-Silva |first1=Eduardo |title=Racism Without Racists: Color-blind Racism and the Persistence of Racial Inequality in the United States |date=2010 |publisher=Rowman &amp; Littlefield |location=Lanham, Md. |isbn=978-1-4422-0218-4 |page=211 |edition=3rd}}&lt;/ref&gt; He argues that this results from a new dominant ideology of "[[color-blind racism]]", which treats racial inequality as a thing of the past, thereby allowing it to continue by opposing concrete efforts at reform.{{sfnp|Garner|2017|p=186}}

===Legal challenges===

Legal challenges concerning so-called "reverse racism" date back as far as the 1970s as asserted in such cases as ''Regents of the University of California v. Bakke''; ''[[Gratz v. Bollinger]]''; and ''[[Grutter v. Bollinger]]'' (regarding discrimination in higher education admissions) and ''[[Ricci v. DeStefano]]'' (regarding employment discrimination).{{r|Norton &amp; Sommers 2011 Losing}} The idea of reverse racism later gained widespread use in debates and legal actions concerning [[affirmative action in the United States]].{{r|Sanneh}}

==South Africa==
{{Undue weight|section|date=March 2019|to=individual allegations of reverse racism rather than the broader social impact of the term/concept}}
{{See also| Racism in South Africa}}
The concept of ''reverse racism'' has been used by some white South Africans concerned about "reverse apartheid" following the end of [[Apartheid|white-supremacist rule]].{{sfnp|Ansell|2013|p=137}} Affirmative action in South Africa's white-dominated civil service was also met with charges of "reverse racism".&lt;ref name="de Villiers 2012"&gt;{{cite magazine |first1=Susan |last1=de Villiers |first2=Stefan |last2=Simanowitz |date=March 2012 |title=South Africa: The ANC at 100 |magazine=The Contemporary Review |volume=294 |issue=1704 |pages=39–45 |issn=0010-7565 |url=http://search.proquest.com/docview/1013463231 |via=ProQuest |quote=[A]ffirmative action and black economic empowerment were controversial and often misrepresented. In a society in which the greater majority of desk and management jobs were held by whites, there was a clear need for action to move towards a more level job market. Yet many whites have persisted in claiming 'reverse racism'.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Nelson Mandela]] in 1995 described "racism in reverse" when black students demonstrated in favor of changing the racial makeup of staff at [[List of universities in South Africa|South African universities]].&lt;ref name="MacGregor 1995"&gt;{{cite news |last1=MacGregor |first1=Karen |title=Mandela slams 'reverse racism' |url=https://www.timeshighereducation.com/news/mandela-slams-reverse-racism/97135.article?storyCode=97135&amp;sectioncode=26 |work=Times Higher Education |publication-place=London |date=March 24, 1995 |issn=0049-3929 |url-access=registration}}&lt;/ref&gt; Students denied Mandela's claim and argued that a great deal of ongoing actual racism persisted from apartheid.&lt;ref name="Sinclair 1995"&gt;{{cite news |first=Abiola |last=Sinclair |title=Media Watch: All is not well, disappointments, racial clashes |newspaper=New York Amsterdam News |date=September 16, 1995 |page=26 |issn=1059-1818 |quote=The students maintained that the university was living in the apartheid past with the upper echelons reserved for whites. The students are demanding that some jobs be reserved for Blacks. AZASM had denied the charge of reverse racism. They maintain it is unfair for thousands of Black teachers to be out of work while white teachers sit up in good jobs in Black schools.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Mixed-race South Africans]] have also sometimes claimed to be victimized by reverse racism of the new government.&lt;ref name="Polgreen 2003"&gt;{{cite news |first=Lydia |last=Polgreen |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2003/07/27/world/for-mixed-race-south-africans-equity-is-elusive.html |title=For Mixed-Race South Africans, Equity Is Elusive |work=The New York Times |date=July 27, 2003 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130331044842/http://www.nytimes.com/2003/07/27/world/for-mixed-race-south-africans-equity-is-elusive.html |archive-date=March 31, 2013 |url-status=live |url-access=limited}}&lt;/ref&gt; Similar accusations have been leveled by [[Coloureds#Post-apartheid era|Indian]] and [[Afrikaner]] groups, who feel that they have not been dominant historically but now suffer from discrimination by the government.&lt;ref name="Harman 2002"&gt;{{cite news |last1=Harman |first1=Dana |title=South Africans try to 'beat' a segregated past |url=https://www.csmonitor.com/2002/0926/p01s03-woaf.html |work=Christian Science Monitor |date=September 26, 2002 |page=1 |issn=2166-3262 |url-access=limited |quote=But old feelings die hard, and some groups{{dash}}in particular the Afrikaner and Indian minorities{{dash}}even complain that they are now being targeted by a reverse racism.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Helen Suzman]], a prominent white anti-apartheid politician, charged the [[African National Congress]] and the Mbeki administration with reverse racism since Mandela's departure in 1999.&lt;ref name="Calvert 2005"&gt;{{cite news |last1=Calvert |first1=Scott |title=Against apartheid, at odds with blacks |url=https://www.baltimoresun.com/news/bs-xpm-2005-05-14-0505140451-story.html |work=The Baltimore Sun |date=May 13, 2005 |issn=1930-8965}}&lt;/ref&gt;

South African critics of the "reverse racism" concept use similar arguments as those employed by Americans.&lt;ref name="Dalamba 2000"&gt;{{cite journal |first=Yolisa |last=Dalamba |title=Towards An African Renaissance: Identity, Race And Representation In Post-Apartheid South Africa |journal=Journal of Cultural Studies |volume=2 |issue=1 |pages=40–61 |year=2000 |doi=10.4314/jcs.v2i1.6231}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Verify source|date=March 2019}}

==See also==
* [[Racism in South Africa]]
* [[Racism in the United States]]
* {{Anl|Xenoracism}}

==Notes==
{{reflist|group=Note}}

==References==
{{Reflist|refs=

&lt;ref name="Ansell"&gt;{{cite book |last=Ansell |first=Amy Elizabeth |title=Race and Ethnicity: The Key Concepts |date=2013 |publisher=Routledge |isbn=978-0-415-33794-6 |pages=135–136}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Cashmore"&gt;{{cite book |editor-last=Cashmore |editor-first=Ellis |title=Encyclopedia of Race and Ethnic Studies |date=2004 |publisher=Routledge |isbn=978-1-13-444706-0 |page=373 |chapter=Reverse Racism/Discrimination |chapter-url=https://archive.org/details/encyclopediaofra0000cash/page/373/mode/1up?view=theater |chapter-url-access=registration}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Cyr"&gt;{{cite book |last=Cyr |first=Lauren |editor1-last=Kim Gertz |editor1-first=S. |editor2-last=Huang |editor2-first=B. |editor3-last=Cyr |editor3-first=L. |title=Diversity and Inclusion in Higher Education and Societal Contexts: International and Interdisciplinary Approaches |date=2018 |publisher=Palgrave Macmillan |location=Cham, Switzerland |isbn=978-3-31-970174-5 |page=24 |chapter=Literature Review: Interdisciplinary Findings on Diversity and Inclusion}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Dennis"&gt;{{cite book |last=Dennis |first=Rutledge M. |editor1-last=Kuper |editor1-first=A. |editor2-last=Kuper |editor2-first=J. |title=The Social Science Encyclopedia, Volume 2 |date=2004 |publisher=Routledge |location= |pages=843–845 |isbn=978-1-13-435970-7 |edition=3rd |chapter=Racism}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Fish"&gt;Fish, quoted in {{cite book |last1=Pincus |first1=Fred L. |title=Reverse Discrimination: Dismantling the Myth |date=2003 |publisher=Lynne Rienner Publishers |isbn=978-1-58-826203-5 |url=https://archive.org/details/reversediscrimin0000pinc/page/68/mode/1up?view=theater |url-access=registration |pages=68–69}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Fletcher"&gt;{{cite news |last=Fletcher |first=Michael A. |title=Whites think discrimination against whites is a bigger problem than bias against blacks |url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/wonk/wp/2014/10/08/white-people-think-racial-discrimination-in-america-is-basically-over |work=The Washington Post |date=October 8, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Garner"&gt;{{cite book |last=Garner |first=Steve |title=Racisms: An Introduction |date=2017 |publisher=SAGE Publications |location=London |isbn=978-1-5264-1285-0 |edition=2nd |page=185}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Hill"&gt;{{cite book |last=Hill |first=Jane H. |title=The Everyday Language of White Racism |date=2011 |publisher=John Wiley &amp; Sons |isbn=978-1-4443-5669-4 |page=15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Ingraham"&gt;{{cite news |last=Ingraham |first=Christopher |title=White Trump voters think they face more discrimination than blacks. The Trump administration is listening |url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/wonk/wp/2017/08/02/white-trump-voters-think-they-face-more-discrimination-than-blacks-the-trump-administration-is-listening |work=The Washington Post |date=August 2, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Jones et al."&gt;{{cite report |last1=Jones |first1=Robert P. |display-authors=etal |title=How Immigration and Concerns About Cultural Changes Are Shaping the 2016 Election: Findings from the 2016 PRRI/Brookings Immigration Survey |date=June 23, 2016 |publisher=Public Religion Research Institute |location=Washington, D.C. |page=2 |url=http://www.prri.org/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/PRRI-Brookings-2016-Immigration-survey-report.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Massie"&gt;{{cite news |author=Massie, Victoria M. |title=Americans are split on "reverse racism". That still doesn't mean it exists. |work=Vox |date=June 29, 2016 |url=https://www.vox.com/2016/6/29/12045772/reverse-racism-affirmative-action |access-date=September 18, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Mazzocco"&gt;{{cite book |last=Mazzocco |first=Philip J. |title=The Psychology of Racial Colorblindness: A Critical Review |date=2017 |publisher=Palgrave Macmillan |location=New York |isbn=978-1-13-759967-4 |page=91}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="McBride"&gt;{{cite book |last=McBride |first=David |editor1-last=Carlisle |editor1-first=Rodney P. |title=Encyclopedia of Politics: The Left and The Right, Volume 1: The Left |date=2005 |publisher=SAGE Publications |location=Thousand Oaks, Calif. |isbn=978-1-41-290409-4 |page=8 |chapter=Affirmative Action}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Newkirk"&gt;{{cite magazine |first=Vann R. II |last=Newkirk |date=August 5, 2017 |title=How The Myth of Reverse Racism Drives the Affirmative Action Debate |magazine=The Atlantic |url=https://www.theatlantic.com/education/archive/2017/08/myth-of-reverse-racism/535689/ |access-date=March 18, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Norton &amp; Sommers 2011 Losing"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Norton |first1=Michael I. |last2=Sommers |first2=Samuel R. |title=Whites See Racism as a Zero-Sum Game That They Are Now Losing |date=2011 |journal=Perspectives on Psychological Science |volume=6 |issue=3 |pages=215–18 |pmid=26168512 |doi=10.1177/1745691611406922 |s2cid=10616480 |url=http://www.people.hbs.edu/mnorton/norton%20sommers.pdf}}
*{{cite press release |date=May 23, 2011 |title=Whites Believe They Are Victims of Racism More Often Than Blacks |website=TuftsNow |url=http://now.tufts.edu/news-releases/whites-believe-they-are-victims-racism-more-o}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Norton &amp; Sommers 2011 Jockeying"&gt;{{cite news |last1=Norton |first1=Michael I. |last2=Sommers |first2=Samuel R. |url=https://www.nytimes.com/roomfordebate/2011/05/22/is-anti-white-bias-a-problem/jockeying-for-stigma |title=Jockeying for Stigma |work=The New York Times |date=May 23, 2011 |url-access=limited}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Pinder"&gt;{{cite book |last=Pinder |first=Sherrow O. |title=Colorblindness, Post-raciality, and Whiteness in the United States |date=2015 |publisher=Palgrave Macmillan |location=New York |isbn=978-1-13-743488-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Sanneh"&gt;{{cite magazine |first=Kelefah |last=Sanneh |url=http://www.newyorker.com/talk/comment/2009/08/10/090810taco_talk_sanneh |title=Discriminating Tastes |magazine=The New Yorker |date=August 10, 2009 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20121114014324/http://www.newyorker.com/talk/comment/2009/08/10/090810taco_talk_sanneh |archive-date=November 14, 2012 |url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Spanierman &amp; Cabrera"&gt;{{cite book |last1=Spanierman |first1=Lisa |last2=Cabrera |first2=Nolan |editor1=Watson, V. |editor2=Howard-Wagner, D. |editor3=Spanierman, L. |title=Unveiling Whiteness in the Twenty-First Century: Global Manifestations, Transdisciplinary Interventions |date=2014 |publisher=Lexington Books |isbn=978-0-73-919297-9 |page=16 |chapter=The Emotions of White Racism and Antiracism}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Wilkins et al."&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Wilkins |first1=Clara L. |last2=Wellman |first2=Joseph D. |last3=Kaiser |first3=Cheryl R. |title=Status legitimizing beliefs predict positivity toward Whites who claim anti-White bias |journal=Journal of Experimental Social Psychology |date=November 2013 |volume=49 |issue=6 |pages=1114–19 |doi=10.1016/j.jesp.2013.05.017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Wilkins &amp; Kaiser"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Wilkins |first1=C. L. |last2=Kaiser |first2=C. R. |title=Racial Progress as Threat to the Status Hierarchy: Implications for Perceptions of Anti-White Bias |journal=Psychological Science |date=2013 |volume=25 |issue=2 |pages=439–46 |doi=10.1177/0956797613508412 |pmid=24343099 |s2cid=6934961}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Yee"&gt;{{cite book |last=Yee |first=June Ying |editor-last=Shaefer |editor-first=Richard T. |title=Encyclopedia of Race, Ethnicity, and Society |date=2008 |publisher=SAGE |isbn=978-1-41-292694-2 |pages=1118–19 |chapter=Racism, Types of}}&lt;/ref&gt;

}}

==Further reading==
* {{cite book |last=Anderson |first=Kristin J. |title=Benign Bigotry: The Psychology of Subtle Prejudice |date=2010 |publisher=Cambridge University Press |isbn=978-0-52-187835-7 |pages=278–334 |chapter='Affirmative Action is reverse racism': The myth of merit}} 
* {{cite book |last=Ansell |first=Amy Elizabeth |title=New Right, New Racism: Race and Reaction in the United States and Britain |date=1997 |publisher=Macmillan |location=London |isbn=0-33-364945-1 |pages=132–138}}
* {{cite journal |last=Chang |first=Robert S. |year=1996 |title=Reverse Racism!: Affirmative Action, the Family, and the Dream That Is America |journal=Hastings Constitutional Law Quarterly |volume=23 |issue=4 |issn=0094-5617 |pages=1115–34 |url=https://www.hastingsconstitutionallawquarterly.org/s/chang-9bh5.pdf}}
* {{cite book |last1=Dennis |first1=Rutledge M. |editor1-last=Kuper |editor1-first=Adam |editor2-last=Kuper |editor2-first=Jessica |title=The social science encyclopedia |date=1996 |publisher=Routledge |location=London |isbn=0-415-10829-2 |pages=715–717 |edition=2nd |chapter-url=https://archive.org/details/socialscienceenc0002unse/page/715/mode/1up?view=theater |chapter-url-access=registration |chapter=Racism}}
* {{cite magazine |url=https://www.theatlantic.com/past/docs/politics/race/fish.htm |title=Reverse Racism, or How the Pot Got to Call the Kettle Black |magazine=The Atlantic |date=November 1993 |author=Fish, Stanley}}
* {{cite journal |last=Song |first=Miri |title=Challenging a culture of racial equivalence |journal=The British Journal of Sociology |date=March 2014 |volume=65 |issue=1 |pages=107–29 |doi=10.1111/1468-4446.12054 |pmid=24697716 |url=https://kar.kent.ac.uk/49226/1/Song%20racism%20BJS.2014.docx}}
* {{cite book |last=Suiter |first=Tad |editor-last=Kiuchi |editor-first=Yuya |title=Race Still Matters: The Reality of African American Lives and the Myth of Postracial Society |date=2016 |publisher=SUNY Press |location=Albany, N.Y. |isbn=978-1-43-846273-8 |chapter=Reverse Racism: A Discursive History}}
* {{cite web |title=What Does Reverse Racism Mean? |url=https://www.dictionary.com/e/politics/reverse-racism/ |website=Politics Dictionary |publisher=Dictionary.com}}
* {{cite book |last=Brown |first=Michael K. |editor1-last=Valelly |editor1-first=Richard M. |title=Encyclopedia of U.S. Political History, Volume 7: The Clash of Conservatism and Liberalism, 1976 to Present |date=2010 |publisher=CQ Press |location=Washington, D.C. |isbn=978-1-60-426647-4 |page=318 |chapter=Race}}

==External links==
{{wikimedia|collapsible=true}}
* [http://www.eeoc.gov/significant-eeoc-racecolor-casescovering-private-and-federal-sectors#reverse List of cases involving allegations of reverse discrimination], U.S. Equal Employment Opportunity Commission

{{Racism topics}}

{{Portal bar|Law|United States}}

[[Category:Conservatism]]
[[Category:Majority–minority relations]]
[[Category:Opposition to affirmative action]]
[[Category:Political terminology in South Africa]]
[[Category:Political terminology of the United States]]
[[Category:Race in the United States]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>