<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20151122161419|691848228" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="6250226" pageid="6250226" ns="0" title="Reverse racism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2015-11-22T16:15:49Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{pp-pc1|expiry=29 February 2016|small=yes}}
{{See also|Reverse discrimination}}
{{Discrimination sidebar}}

'''Reverse racism''' is a [[phenomenon]] in which discrimination, sometimes officially sanctioned, against a dominant or formerly dominant racial or other group representative of the majority in a particular society takes place, for a variety of reasons, often initially as an attempt at redressing past wrongs. It has been described as "preferential treatment, discriminating in favor of members of under-represented groups, which have been treated unjustly in the past, against innocent people".&lt;ref&gt;Louis P. Pojman,[http://www.csus.edu/indiv/g/gaskilld/business_computer_ethics/the%20case%20against%20affirmative%20action.htm/The-Case-Against-Affirmative-Action-Sacramento-State "The Case Against Affirmative Action"], csus.edu; accessed November 25, 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="about1"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://racerelations.about.com/od/understandingrac1/a/DoesReverseRacismExist.htm|title=Define Reverse Racism - Reverse Discrimination - Reverse Racism Examples|publisher=Racerelations.about.com|accessdate=2013-05-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Norton Sommers 2011"&gt;{{cite journal|doi=10.1177/1745691611406922|laysummary=http://now.tufts.edu/news-releases/whites-believe-they-are-victims-racism-more-o|laysource=TuftsNow|laydate=May 23, 2011|title=Whites See Racism as a Zero-Sum Game That They Are Now Losing|year=2011|last1=Norton|first1=Michael I.|last2=Sommers|first2=Samuel R.|journal=Perspectives on Psychological Science|volume=6|issue=3|pages=215–18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The usage of the term is controversial, with many groups (especially those concerning the interests of [[ethnic minorities]]) denying its existence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author1=Emma Compeau|title=UTMSU 'reverse racism' post faces criticism|url=http://thevarsity.ca/2015/08/26/utmsu-reverse-racism-post-faces-criticism|website=The Varsity|accessdate=August 29, 2015|date=August 26, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author1=Emily Torbett|title=Reverse racism: Can't exist by definition, insulting to minority groups|url=http://www.thedaonline.com/opinion/article_25e8b7cc-47bc-11e5-bb94-7f79b1590106.html|website=The Daily Athenaeum|accessdate=August 29, 2015|date=August 21, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==In the United States==
===Civil rights===
The term "reverse racism" came into use as the struggle for African-American rights divided the white community. In 1966, [[Hosea Williams]] of the [[Southern Christian Leadership Conference]] (SCLC), publicly accused members of the [[Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee]] (SNCC) of reverse racism in their efforts to exclude or expel whites from local government in Alabama to make room for blacks. Williams argued that the SNCC's intended "all-black" campaign in Alabama would drive white moderates out of the [[African-American Civil Rights Movement (1955–1968)|civil rights movement]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Strife on Two Civil Rights Fronts in Alabama: SNCC is Scored by King Group|work=Chicago Daily Defender|date=April 25, 1966|page=1|quote=The move was called 'reverse racism' by [[Hosea Williams]], Southern program director for King's Southern Christian Leadership conference. He described the effort to exclude all whites from public office as being as racist as excluding all blacks. It isn't integration, he indicated, and it isn't likely — in the long run — to help cure the nation's number one headache.}}&lt;/ref&gt; "Black racism" was a more common term in this era, used to describe SNCC and groups like the Black Panthers.&lt;ref name=SW&gt;{{cite journal|first=Lee|last=Sustar|title=The fallacy of 'reverse racism'|journal=Socialist Worker|date=October 12, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

It was not until the 1970s that discourse surrounding reverse racism emerged most forcefully, especially in reaction to [[affirmative action]], as an outgrowth against [[Color blindness (race) in the United States|colorblind]] hegemonic approaches in the post-civil rights era.&lt;ref name="Ansell2013"&gt;{{cite book|author=Amy Elizabeth Ansell|title=Race and Ethnicity: The Key Concepts|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=8_y3Q6fzgQAC&amp;pg=PA136|year=2013|publisher=Routledge|isbn=978-0-415-33794-6|page=136|accessdate=November 6, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Instances in which white minorities' right of franchise were threatened or denied include:
* The [[New Black Panther Party voter intimidation case]] in 2008 in [[Philadelphia, Pennsylvania]], which [[Attorney General]] [[Eric Holder]] refused to prosecute despite a default judgment.{{refn|The government had obtained a default judgement in a civil action against defendant Minister King Samir Shabazz and dismissed charges against all other defendants.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.slideshare.net/LegalDocs/findlaw-voting-rights-new-black-panther-party-figure-shabazzs-weapons-order|title=Order|work=Civil Action No. 09-65 in United States Civil Court for the Eastern District of Pennsylvania|date=18 May 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
* The case of the [[Noxubee County Democratic Executive Committee]], in [[Macon, Mississippi]], investigation and prosecution of which began in 2005 during [[George W. Bush]]'s administration over allegations of violations of the [[Voting Rights Act]] in regard to the county's white minority.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2006/10/11/us/politics/11voting.html?_r=0 ''"The Justice Department has chosen this no-stoplight, courthouse town buried in the eastern Mississippi prairie for an unusual civil rights test: the first federal lawsuit under the Voting Rights Act accusing blacks of suppressing the rights of whites. To do that, the department says, he and his allies devised a watertight system for controlling the all-determining Democratic primary, much as segregationists did decades ago. Mr. Brown is accused in the lawsuit and in supporting documents of paying and organizing notaries, some of whom illegally marked absentee ballots or influenced how the ballots were voted; of publishing a list of voters, all white, accompanied by a warning that they would be challenged at the polls; of importing black voters into the county; and of altering racial percentages in districts by manipulating the registration rolls."''], nytimes.com, October 11, 2006; accessed November 23, 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Criticism===
Many advocates for [[racial justice]] argue that reverse racism is just misinterpreted racial prejudice. According to Calgary Anti Racism Education (CARED), "Racial Prejudice can be directed at white people (i.e. white people can't dance) but is not considered racism because of the systemic relationship of power."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Reverse Racism-Myth or Reality?|url=http://www.ucalgary.ca/cared/mythofreverseracism|website=CARED Calgary Anti Racism Education|accessdate=26 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some sociologists do not believe in the existence of reverse racism because of the hierarchy in which those who are in the subordinated position do not have the power to commit reverse racism without larger, institutional support. Based on David Wellman's definition of [[racism]] in Portraits of White Racism as "culturally sanctioned beliefs, which, regardless of intentions involved, defend the advantages whites have because of the subordinated position of racial minorities," reverse racism could not exist because it cannot defend advantages of racial groups who are disadvantaged in society.&lt;ref&gt;Wellman, David T. Portraits of White Racism. (1993). New York, NY: Cambridge University Press. pg. x.; accessed November 6, 2015.&lt;!--ISSN/ISBN needed--&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; 

[[Paul Kivel]] writes in ''Uprooting Racism: How White People Can Work for Racial Justice'' that instances of reverse racism are generally rare, and that many claims of reverse discrimination lack merit. According to Kivel, charges of reverse racism are "usually a white strategy to deny white racism and to counterattack attempts to promote racial justice".&lt;ref name="Kivel2013"&gt;{{cite book|author=Paul Kivel|title=Uprooting Racism: How White People Can Work for Racial Justice Ð 3rd Edition|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=MayCo-8M5vgC&amp;pg=PA75|date=October 18, 2013|publisher=New Society Publishers|isbn=978-1-55092-495-4|pages=74–75}}&lt;/ref&gt; Reverse racism is also said to deny the existence of [[white privilege]] and power in society.&lt;ref name="Hill2011"&gt;{{cite book|author=Jane H. Hill|title=The Everyday Language of White Racism|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=Krq4fG08_38C&amp;pg=PT15|date=September 15, 2011|publisher=John Wiley &amp; Sons|isbn=978-1-4443-5669-4|page=15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Admissions===
The Supreme Court held in 2009 that racial preferences in university admissions for minority students do not necessarily violate [[Equal Protection]] in cases such as ''[[Grutter v. Bollinger]]''. The term gained widespread use in debates and legal actions concerning [[Affirmative action in the United States|affirmative action]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|first1=Kelefah|last1=Sanneh|url=http://www.newyorker.com/talk/comment/2009/08/10/090810taco_talk_sanneh|title=Discriminating Tastes|work=The New Yorker|date=August 10, 2009|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/6C9DcUQni|archivedate=November 13, 2012|deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A 2011 study conducted at Tufts and Harvard sought to quantify perceptions of reverse racism by surveying Americans who identified as "White" or "Black". The study was titled ''White People See Racism as a Zero-Sum Game That They Are Now Losing''. The study found that Whites feel as though they now suffer disproportionately from racism. (Blacks claimed that anti-black racism had decreased over time, but did not perceive or acknowledge increases in anti-white bias.) These results were constant for people of different ages and levels of education.&lt;ref name="Norton Sommers 2011"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.people.hbs.edu/mnorton/norton%20sommers.pdf|doi=10.1177/1745691611406922|journal=Perspectives on Psychological Science|date=June 2011|pages=215–18|author1=Michael I. Norton|author2=Samuel R. Sommers|title=Whites See Racism as a Zero-Sum Game That They Are Now Losing|accessdate=November 23, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|first1=Michael I.|last1=Norton|first2=Samuel R.|last2=Sommers|url=http://www.nytimes.com/roomfordebate/2011/05/22/is-anti-white-bias-a-problem/jockeying-for-stigma|title=Jockeying for Stigma|work=New York Times|date=May 23, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==In South Africa==
The term has been used actively by both black and white South Africans after the end of [[apartheid]]. Accusations of reverse racism have been leveled particularly at government efforts to transform the demographics of South Africa's white-dominated civil service.&lt;ref&gt;Susan de Villiers and Stefan Simanowitz, "[http://www.questia.com/library/1G1-288429746/south-africa-the-anc-at-100 South Africa: The ANC at 100]", ''Contemporary Review'' 294, March 2012; accessed [http://search.proquest.com/docview/1013463231 via ProQuest], November 6, 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Nelson Mandela]] in 1995 described "racism in reverse" when Black students demonstrated in favor of changing the racial makeup of staff at South African universities.&lt;ref&gt;Karen MacGregor, [http://www.timeshighereducation.co.uk/story.asp?storyCode=97135&amp;sectioncode=26 "Mandela slams `reverse racism'"], ''Times Higher Education", March 24, 1995.&lt;/ref&gt; Students denied Mandela's claim and argued that a great deal of ongoing actual racism persisted from apartheid.&lt;ref&gt;Abiola Sinclair, "MEDIA WATCH: All is not well, disappointments, racial clashes", ''New York Amsterdam News'', September 16, 1995; accessed [http://search.proquest.com/docview/390340787 via ProQuest]. "The students maintained that the university was living in the apartheid past with the upper echelons reserved for whites. The students are demanding that some jobs be reserved for Blacks. AZASM had denied the charge of reverse racism. They maintain it is unfair for thousands of Black teachers to be out of work while white teachers sit up in good jobs in Black schools."&lt;/ref&gt;

Some charged that Mandela's government moved slowly in other areas of social change, due to fears of being perceived as "reverse racist".&lt;ref&gt;Paul Taylor, "Black Capitalists Rare In New South Africa; Apartheid's Legacy, Cultural Ethos Cited", ''Washington Post'', March 19, 1995; accessed [http://search.proquest.com/docview/307803664 via ProQuest]. "So far Mandela's government has moved slowly on that front. 'I think the government is still looking over its shoulder, afraid of the tag of reverse racism', said Thami Mazwai, editor of ''Enterprise'', a glossy monthly magazine devoted to black businesses. He noted that [earlier that year] a white ad agency and the nation's only black ad agency competed for a major government contract to publicize the public hearing process for the writing of a new constitution. Although the black agency has won several industry awards, the white agency got the contract."&lt;/ref&gt; 

Mandela was later himself charged with reverse racism, during 1997 proceedings of the national [[Truth and Reconciliation Commission (South Africa)|Truth and Reconciliation Commission]]&lt;ref&gt;Dean Murphy, "Apartheid-Era Leader Defies Subpoena; S. Africa: Truth commission urges contempt charges against former President Pieter W. Botha", ''Washington Post'', December 20, 1997; accessed [http://search.proquest.com/docview/421209639 via ProQuest]. "The move to charge Botha is particularly sensitive because it comes just days after President Nelson Mandela, in a racially charged address to the ruling African National Congress, harshly criticized white South Africans for protecting their positions of privilege and doing little to reconcile with the black majority. The speech, hailed as accurate by blacks, brought calls of reverse racism from many whites."&lt;/ref&gt; and for supporting the 1998 [[Employment Equity Bill]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|first=Gumisai|last=Mutume|url=http://www.ipsnews.net/1998/04/politics-south-africa-racism-spoils-it-for-new-democracy|title=Racism Spoils It for New Democracy|agency=Inter-Press Service|date=April 3, 1993}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Kate Dunn, [http://www.csmonitor.com/1998/0226/022698.intl.intl.6.html "Mandela Hits White Wealth]", ''Christian Science Monitor'', February 26, 1998.&lt;/ref&gt;

Claims of reverse racism continued into the 21st century. [[Helen Suzman]], a prominent white anti-apartheid politician, charged the [[African National Congress]] and the Mbeki administration with reverse racism since Mandela's departure in 1999.&lt;ref&gt;Scott Calvert, [http://articles.baltimoresun.com/2005-05-14/news/0505140451_1_helen-suzman-apartheid-white-liberals "Against apartheid, at odds with blacks"], ''Baltimore Sun'', May 14, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt; In 2004, a group of young white members of the trade union [[Solidarity (South African trade union)|Solidarity]] locked themselves into a zoo to protest discrimination against whites.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.amren.com/news/2004/12/youth_cage_them "Youth Cage Themselves in Zoo to Protest Against Discrimination]", ''The Statesman'' (Press Trust of India), December 27, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;

South African critics of the "reverse racism" concept use similar arguments as those employed by Americans.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|accessdate=November 6, 2015|first1=Yolisa|last1=Dalamba|title=Towards An African Renaissance: Identity, Race And Representation In Post-Apartheid South Africa|journal=Journal of Cultural Studies|volume=2|issue=1|pages=40–61|year=2000|url=http://www.ajol.info/index.php/jcs/article/view/6231|doi=10.4314/jcs.v2i1.6231}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Coloured|Mixed-race]] South Africans have also sometimes claimed to be victimized by reverse racism of the new Black government.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|first=Lydia|last=Polgreen|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2003/07/27/world/for-mixed-race-south-africans-equity-is-elusive.html|title=For Mixed-Race South Africans, Equity Is Elusive|work=New York Times|date=July 27, 2003|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/6C9BBHNcM|archivedate=November 13, 2012|deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt; Similar accusations have been leveled by Indian and Afrikaner groups, who feel that they have not been dominant historically but now suffer from discrimination by the Black government.&lt;ref&gt;Danna Harman, "[http://www.csmonitor.com/2002/0926/p01s03-woaf.html South Africans try to 'beat' a segregated past]", ''Christian Science Monitor'', September 26, 2002.&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Black power]]
* [[Black supremacy]]
* [[Double standard]]
* [[Racial formation theory]]
* [[Racism]]
* [[White guilt]]

{{Portal bar|Criminal justice|Discrimination|United States}}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
* {{cite journal|first1=Peter|last1=Aberger|year=1980|title=Leopold Senghor and the Issue of Reverse Racism|journal=Phylon|volume=41|issue=3|pages=276–83|jstor=274791}}
* {{cite journal|first1=Robert S.|last1=Chang|year=1995|title=Reverse Racism!: Affirmative Action, the Family, and the Dream That Is America|journal=Hastings Constitutional Law Quarterly|volume=23|pages=1115–34|url=http://www.hastingsconlawquarterly.org/archives/V23/I4/chang.pdf|accessdate=November 22, 2014}}
* {{cite book|author=Fred L. Pincus|title=Reverse Discrimination: Dismantling the Myth|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=JN3N3EmaIuIC|year=2003|publisher=Lynne Rienner Publishers|isbn=978-1-58826-203-5|accessdate=November 6, 2015}}

==External link==
{{wikimedia|collapsible=true}}

[[Category:Definition of racism controversy]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Racism]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>