<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20041111224858|7360984" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="6675" pageid="6675" ns="0" title="Conservatism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2004-11-11T23:33:07Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Conservatism''' or '''political conservatism''' is any of several historically related [[political philosophy|political philosophies]] or political ideologies. There are also a number of [[Conservative Party|Conservative political parties]] in various countries. All of these are primarily (though not necessarily exclusively) identified with the [[right-wing politics|political right]].

Among the significant usages of the term "conservatism" are:

1. '''Classical conservatism''' or ''institutional conservatism'' - Opposition to rapid change in governmental and societal institutions. This kind of conservatism is anti-[[ideology|ideological]] insofar as it emphasizes means (slow change) over ends (any particular form of government). To the classical conservative, whether one arrives at a right- or left-leaning government is less important than whether change is effected through rule of law rather than through revolution and sudden innovation. 

2. '''Ideological conservatism''' or ''right conservatism'' - In contrast to the anti-ideological ''classical conservatism'', ''right conservatism'' is, as its name implies, ''ideological.'' It is typified by three distinct subideologies: ''social conservatism'', ''fiscal conservatism'', and ''economic conservatism''. Together, these subideologies comprise the conservative ideology in most English-speaking countries: separately, these subideologies are incorporated into other political positions.

* ''Social conservatism'' is generally dominated by defense of existing social norms and values, of local customs and of societal evolution, rather than social upheaval, though the distinction is not absolute. Applied to foreign policy, a mild ''social conservatism'' manifests itself in [[Rudyard Kipling]]'s defense of the Indian natives against British imperialism and in American opposition to the "forced democratization" of post-war Iraq, but conversely, betraying the complexity of ideology, the vast majority of American conservatives in keeping with their accepted values fully support the current effort at democratization or, rather, liberation (in the sense that liberty increases dramatically). In its more extreme foreign-policy manifestations, ''social conservatism'' breeds [[nationalism]], tending towards [[isolationism]], on the order of [[Pat Buchanan]]'s [[anti-immigrant|anti-immigration]], anti-[[internationalism|internationalist]] stance.

* ''Fiscal conservatism'' is the stance that the government must "live within its means". Above all, fiscal conservatives oppose excessive government [[debt]]; this belief in [[balanced budgets]] tends to be coupled with a belief that government [[welfare]] programs should be narrowly tailored and that [[taxation|tax rates]] should be low, which implies relatively small government institutions.

* This belief in small government combines with fiscal conservatism to produce a broader ''economic conservatism'', which wishes to minimize government intervention in the economy. This amounts to support for ''[[laissez faire]]'' economics. This ''economic conservatism'' comes from two schools of thought: the classical conservative's pragmatism and the libertarian's notion of "rights." The classical conservative maintains that free markets work best, while the libertarian contends that free markets are the only ethical markets.

''Economic'' and ''fiscal'' conservatism coupled with social [[liberalism]] is called (at least in the U.S.) ''[[libertarianism]]'', or (in its more extreme form) [[anarchism]]. Economic liberalism coupled with social conservatism is typically referred to as [[populism]] or  [[fascism]].

3. '''Neoconservatism''' -- strictly a U.S. term -- refers to the views of a subclass of conservatives who support a more assertive foreign policy coupled with one or more other facets of ''ideological conservatism.'' Historically, conservatives tend to be mildly [[isolationist]], but with the rising [[internationalism]] represented by such groups as [[NATO]] or the [[UN]], ''[[neoconservatism (United States)|neoconservatism]]'' is on the rise. The "unipolar" assertions of columnist [[Charles Krauthammer]] are an example of neoconservatism. Neoconservatism underlies the policy of the [[George W. Bush]] administration in the [[Middle East]], including (but not limited to) the [[2003 Iraq War]] and [[U.S.-led occupation of Iraq|its aftermath]].

4. "[[Compassionate conservatism]]" a term popularized by George W. Bush, is held by many conservatives to be redundant, and a public-relations buzzword. Insofar as the presidency of George W. Bush has increased [[welfare]] substantially in the form of what is historically the greatest expansion of [[Medicare (United States)|Medicare]] ever and in the form of the [[No Child Left Behind]] act, it may be that ''compassionate conservativism'' is simply the synthesis of ''social conservatism'' and ''fiscal liberalism''.


= An Introduction to Conservatism =

Conservatism can be contrasted on the one hand to radical [[libertarianism]] or [[anarchism]], and on the other to such [[statist]] movements as [[fascism]], [[communism]], and [[socialism]]. In terms of the relation of the individual and the state, conservatism falls in the middle. While one end of the spectrum sees no need for the state to exist, the other sees the state as more important than the individual. 

There is an ambiguity inherent in the term "conservative" as used today. Classical Conservatism emphasizes the importance of tradition and continuity. An individual may fall anywhere from the right to the center-left on the traditional [[Left-Right politics|left-right political spectrum]] and be a ''classical conservative''. On the other hand, ''ideological conservatism'' is specifically on the [[right]] side of the spectrum. Thus, to talk meaningfully about ''conservativism'', one must consider both ''classical conservatism'' and ''ideological conservatism''.

The ideals of classical conservatism and [[Liberalism#Classical_liberalism|classical liberalism]] can and often do coexist within a party, a regime, or even an individual. They are not always in conflict, but they are inevitably in tension. Classical conservatism emphasizes tradition and continuity; classical liberalism emphasizes individual liberty. Sometimes these two ideals are mutually supportive (as in support for [[freedom of speech|freedom of political speech]]); sometimes they are in conflict (as in matters relating to [[gender role]]s); sometimes they are in complicated and dynamic relation to one another (as in matters relating to [[welfare]]).

In the popular imagination, "liberal" and "conservative" have always been at odds, irrespective of whether "conservative" meant old Whig, Dixiecrat, or neoconservative or whether "liberal" meant old Tory, Jeffersonian, or Communist. In the context of contemporary Anglo-American politics, nearly all conservatism incorporates many aspects of classical liberalism, but it remains in contrast to and in conflict with modern liberalism and democratic socialism. 

== Classical conservatism as non-ideological ==

Conservatism as an identifiably distinct political philosophy began with ''classical conservatism''. Classical conservatism is "non-ideological" in that classical conservativism is defined more by its choice of means than of ends. Professional philosophers refer to this as a ''[[deontology|deontological]]'' (as against a ''[[consequentialism|consequentialist]]'') position. Classical conservatism, by definition, is skeptical of plans to re-model human society after an ideological model. While an individual classical conservative may favor left- or right-leaning government, the ''defining'' aspect of classical conservatism is a belief in the importance of continuity with tradition, and that political change should come about through legitimate governmental channels. Classical conservatives generally oppose disenfranchisement, gerrymandering, or other political chicanery; above all, they oppose [[revolution]]. So long as rule of law is upheld, and so long as change is effected gradually and constitutionally rather than revolution, the classical conservative is content.

''Classical conservatism'' is, by definition, not [[revolutionary]]; it is also not counter-revolutionary. When the term "conservative" is applied to the entire political [[Right-wing politics|right]], it is extended to embrace some people who are not classical conservatives, in that they advocate extra-constitutional [[reactionary]] changes to the [[status quo]]. Right-wing politics is not inherently conservative, and the classical conservative opposes rapid change right ''or'' left.

A classical conservative does not necessarily simply support keeping things exactly as they currently are. Even "anti-ideological" classical conservatives have political preferences. In this vein, the intellectual source of conservatism as a "modern" philosophy can be traced to [[Edmund Burke]]. Burke developed his ideas in reaction to the so-called [[Enlightenment]], when European thinkers were beginning to develop the ideology of [[modernism]], which emphasizes social construction guided by abstract "Reason." Burke was troubled by the Enlightenment and the by belief that "Reason" is a sufficient base for justice: he argued, instead, for the value of tradition.

Some men, argued Burke, have more reason than others, and thus some men will make worse governments if they rely upon reason than others. To Burke, the proper formulation of government came not from abstractions such as "Reason," but from time-honored development of the state and of other important societal institutions such as the family and the Church. "''We are afraid to put men to live and trade each on his own private stock of reason;''" Burke wrote, "''because we suspect that this stock in each man is small, and that the individuals would do better to avail themselves of the general bank and capital of nations and ages. Many of our men of speculation, instead of exploding general prejudices, employ their sagacity to discover the latent wisdom which prevails in them. If they find what they seek, and they seldom fail, they think it more wise to continue the prejudice, with the reason involved, than to cast away the coat of prejudice, and to leave nothing but naked reason; because prejudice, with its reason, has a motive to give action to that reason, and an affection which will give it permanence.''"

Burke argued that tradition is a much sounder foundation than "reason". The conservative paradigm he established emphasizes the futility of attempting to ground human society based solely in pure abstractions (such as "reason," "equality," or, more recently, "diversity"), and the necessity of humility in the face of the unknowable. Existing institutions have virtues that cannot be fully grasped by any single person or interest group or, in Burke's view, even any single generation: in his ''[[Reflections on the Revolution in France]]'', Burke referred to ''"the living"'' as ''"the temporary possessors and life-renters"'' of ''"the commonwealth and laws... that they should not think it among their rights to cut off the entail, or commit waste on the inheritance, by destroying at their pleasure the whole original fabric of their society."'' [http://www.users.bigpond.com/smartboard/burke/church.htm] Tradition draws on the wisdom of many generations and the tests of time, while "reason" may be a mask for the preferences of one man, and at best represents only the untested wisdom of one generation. In the conservative view, an attempt to modify the complex web of human interactions that form human society for the sake of some doctrine or theory runs the risk of running afoul of the iron law of [[unintended consequence]]s. Burke advocates vigilance against the possibility of [[moral hazard]]s. 

The classical conservative embraces an attitude that is deeply suspicious of any attempt to remake society in the service of any ideology or doctrine, whether that doctrine is radical [[libertarianism]], [[socialism]], [[Nazism]], or anything else.  Classical conservatives see history as being full of disastrous schemes that seemed like good ideas at the time. Human society, in their view, is something rooted and organic; to try to prune and shape it according to the plans of an ideologue is to invite unforeseen disaster.

== Conservatism as "Ideology," or political philosophy ==

In contrast to classical conservatism, ''social conservatism'' and ''economic conservatism'' are inherently concerned with consequences as well as means (with the modest programme of fiscal conservatism lying somewhere between classical conservatism and these more consequentialist political philosophies). Classical conservatives are inherently anti-ideological (some would even say anti-philosophical [http://www.nhinet.org/burke.htm]), promoting rather, as [[Russell Kirk]] explains, a steady flow of "prescription and prejudice". Kirk's use of the word "prejudice" here is not intended to carry its contemporary pejorative connotation: a conservative himself, he believes that the inherited wisdom of the ages may be a better guide than apparently rational individual judgment.

Social conservatives, like classical conservatives, are generally skeptical of rapid social change. Moreso than classical conservatives, they are liable to seek rather strong government intervention to prevent social change. A good example from ([[as of 2004]]) contemporary U.S. politics is the issue of [[same-sex marriage]]: many social conservatives have supported the proposed [[Federal Marriage Amendment]], a [[United States Constitution|constitutional]] amendment defining [[marriage]] as between a man and a woman. Many people who are more inclined to classical conservatism than social conservatism oppose such an amendment on the grounds that the [[United States Constitution|Constitution]] ought not be tampered with unnecessarily. The tension in policy is the choice between social goal (defining marriage) and the political means (amending the Constitution). While the goal is arguably conservative, amending the constitution on a whim is arguably not conservative. Thus, one will find conservatives on both sides of the issue.

Generally, economic conservatism opposes [[graduated tax]]es as counterproductive and inequitable, and instead proposes [[flat tax]]es (or, in the case of radical [[libertarian]]s, proposes to abolish taxes in favor of "user fees"). Further, economic conservatism opposes rampant [[welfare]] as unnecessary and even (in the view of [[Ayn Rand]]) counterproductive, opposes what it calls "double-taxation" (taxing both companies and individuals along the path of a transaction), and calls for broad [[deregulation]] of industry and a substantially decreased government [[bureaucracy]]. For some this is a matter of principle, as it is for the libertarians and others influenced by thinkers such as Ayn Rand and [[Ludwig von Mises]], who believe that government intervention in the economy is inevitably wasteful and inherently immoral. For classical conservatives, "free market economics" simply represents the most efficient way to promote economic growth: they support it not based on some moral principle, but because, pragmatically, it simply "works."

Throughout much of the 20th century, one of the primary forces uniting the occasionally disparit strands of conservative thought was an opposition to [[communism]], which was seen not only as an enemy of the traditional order, but also of western freedom and democracy in general. 

=== Social conservatism and tradition ===
Social conservatives emphasize traditional views of social units such as the [[family]], [[church]], or locale. Social conservatives are a product of their environment, and would typically define family in terms of local histories and tastes. To the Muslim or [[Fundamentalist Church of Jesus Christ of Latter Day Saints|fundamentalist Mormon]], social conservatism may entail support for polygamy. To the Protestant or Catholic, social conservatism may entail support for "traditional" marriage. 

From this same respect for local traditions comes the correlation between conservatism and [[patriotism]]. Conservatives, out of their respect for traditional, established institutions, tend to strongly identify with [[nationalism|nationalist]] movements, existing governments, and its defenders: police, the military, and national poets, authors, and artists.  Conservatives hold that military institutions embody admirable values like [[honor|honour]], [[duty]], [[courage]], and [[loyalty]]. Military institutions are independent sources of tradition and ritual pageantry that conservatives tend to admire. In its degenerative form, such respect may become typefied by [[jingoism]], [[populism]], and perhaps even bigotry or [[isolationism]]. 

Support for socially conservative policies may not indicate political conservatism. For example, many [[Communism|Communist]] parties and most [[Communist state|Communist regimes]] have been very [[puritanism|puritanical]] with respect to [[sexuality]], arguing, for instance, that [[homosexuality]] was a [[bourgeois]] [[vice]]. 

Conversely, while classical conservatives may embrace traditional values in their personal lives, they are generally wary of government intervention into the private lives of citizens, even when that intervention is in support of traditional values.

=== Fiscal conservatism ===

Although often conjoined to social or classical conservatism, ''fiscal conservatism'' is less of a broad political philosophy and is simply the principle that it is not prudent for governments to take on debts they cannot easily pay back or that will cause an undue burden of taxation. 

Burke, in his ''Reflections on the Revolution in France'', articulated the principles of fiscal conservatism: 

&lt;blockquote&gt;...[I]t is to the property of the citizen, and not to the demands of the creditor of the state, that the first and original faith of civil society is pledged. The claim of the citizen is prior in time, paramount in title, superior in equity. The fortunes of individuals, whether possessed by acquisition or by descent or in virtue of a participation in the goods of some community, were no part of the creditor's security, expressed or implied...[T]he public, whether represented by a monarch or by a senate, can pledge nothing but the public estate; and it can have no public estate except in what it derives from a just and proportioned imposition upon the citizens at large.&lt;/blockquote&gt; 

In other words, a government doesn't have the right to run up large debts and then throw the burden on the taxpayer; the taxpayers' right not to be taxed oppressively takes precedence even over paying back debts a government may have imprudently undertaken.

Fiscal conservatives tend to be conservative in their entire outlook as are most otherwise defined conservatives, but necessarily, conservative goals at times prohibit certain fiscal conservative goals, vide the Reagan Administration due to Cold War expenses. Correspondingly, a nonconservative entity, which holds the notion of fiscal conservatism in low, or, rather, in lower regard than most other considerations may achieve said goals, vide the Clinton Administration, though arguably and most probably due to the fiscally conservative Republican majority in the Congress. Regardless, having a balanced budget or, more generally, reducing nondefense discretionary spending is a "conservative" principle, but, as discussed below, there is much more to a broader economic conservatism.

=== Economic conservatism ===
''Economic conservatism'' can go well beyond ''fiscal conservatism's'' concern for fiscal prudence, to a belief or principle that it is not prudent for governments to intervene in markets. It is also, sometimes, extended to a broader "[[minarchism|small government]]" philosophy. Economic conservatism is associated with [[free-market]], or [[laissez-faire]] economics.

Economic conservatism, insofar as it is ''ideological'', owes its creation to the "[[Liberalism#Classical_liberalism|classical liberal]]" tradition, in the vein of [[Adam Smith]], [[Friedrich A. Hayek]], [[Milton Friedman]], and [[Ludwig von Mises]].

Yet ''classical conservatism'' supports free market policies as well, which raises the question: why the agreement between the classical liberals and conservatives? Part of the confusion is semantic, while "liberal" and "conservative" are regarded in some contexts as antagonistic many "liberal" and "conservative" principles are drawn from the same body of thought, and based on a fundamental agreement about the importance of such concepts as "the rule of law" and the importance of individual liberties. 

Simply, while the results are the same, the arguments are different. ''Classical liberals'' and ''libertarians'' support free markets on moral, ideological grounds: principles of individual liberty morally dictate support for free markets. Supporters of the moral grounds for free markets include [[Ayn Rand]] and [[Ludwig von Mises]]. The liberal tradition is suspicious of government authority, and prefers individual choice, and hence tends to see capitalist economics as the preferable means of achieving economic ends.

Classical conservatives, on the other hand, derive support for free markets from practical grounds. Free markets, they argue, are the most productive markets. Thus the classical conservative supports free markets not out of necessity, but out of expedience. The support is not moral or ideological, but driven on the Burkean notion of prescription: what works best is what is right.

It must be noted that while classical liberals and classical conservatives reached free markets through different means historically, to-date the lines have blurred. Rarely will a politician claim that free markets are "simply more productive" or "simply the right thing to do" but a combination of both. This blurring is very much a product of the merging of the classical liberal and conservative positions under the "umbrella" of the conservative movement. 

The archetypal free-market conservative administrations of the late 20th century -- the [[Margaret Thatcher]] government in the UK and the [[Ronald Reagan]] government in the U.S. -- both held the unfettered operation of the market to be the cornerstone of contemporary economic conservatism. To that end, Thatcher privatized [[British Airways]], with remarkable success, and [[British Rail]], with rather more mixed results; both Reagan and Thatcher cut taxes (especially on the upper income brackets) and slowed governmental growth. Proponents of economic conservatism attribute the unparalleled economic boom of the early 1980s to the late 1990s to these policies. 

Yet economic conservatism is not simply [[capitalism]]. The [[free-market]], to the conservative, begs for regulation, but only insofar as accountability must be maintained. [[Antitrust]] laws were championed in the early 1900s by noted conservative [[William Howard Taft]], who also championed his political mentor (and, later, rival) [[Theodore Roosevelt]]'s policy of creating [[National Parks]].

The interests of [[capitalism]], fiscal and economic conservatism, and [[free market|free-market economy]] do not necessarily coincide with those of social conservatism. At times, aspects of capitalism and free markets have been profoundly subversive of the existing social order, as in the [[enclosure]] movement and other changes that have replaced a traditional [[agrarianism|agrarian]] society with [[agribusiness]], or of traditional attitudes toward the proper position of sex in society, as in the now near-universal availability of [[pornography]]. To that end, on issues at the intersection of economic and social policy, conservatives of one school or another are often at odds.

== "Right-wing" is not necessarily "conservative"  ==

Although some people (mainly on the [[political left]]) use the terms "Conservatism" and "[[right-wing]]" interchangeably, many on the [[political right]] have little in common with most conservatives. 

Classical conservatives' opposition to sudden and radical change is almost as strong when that change comes from the right as from the left. For example, conservatives generally keep quite distant from right-wing groups in some European republics that wish to restore a monarchy, or with those in America who wish to formally establish Christianity as a state religion, and would generally characterize these people as something other than simply conservative. [[Edmund Burke]], considered the founder of classical conservatism, was the leader of the anti-monarchical [[Whigs (UK)|Whig]] party, hardly a right-wing position. 

That is not to say that there would never be coalitions of interest with such groups, just that both sides in such a coalition would recognize that they were dealing with a partner with a different politics. In practice, in European parliamentary systems, conservatives are at least as likely to ally with centrist groups or even some on the left rather than with certain portions of the right. A good contemporary ([[as of 2004]]) example of this is the [[French presidential election, 2002|2002 French]] presidential election, where centrist conservative [[Jacques Chirac]] was quite comfortable accepting the support of even Socialists against radical rightist [[Jean-Marie Le Pen]] of the [[Front National]].

== Conservative political movements ==
Contemporary political conservatism -- the actual politics of people and parties professing to be conservative -- in most [[Western world|western]] [[democratic]] countries is an amalgam of social and institutional conservatism, generally combined with fiscal conservatism, and usually containing elements of broader economic conservatism as well. As with liberalism, it is a pragmatic and protean politics, opportunistic at times, rooted more in a tradition than in any formal set of principles. 

It is certainly possible for one to be a fiscal and economic conservative but not a social conservative; in the United States at present, this is the stance of libertarianism. It is also possible to be a social conservative but not an economic conservative -- at present, this is a common political stance in, for example, [[Ireland]] -- or to be a fiscal conservative without being either a social conservative or a broader economic conservative, such as the "deficit hawks" of the [[United States Democratic Party]]. In general use, the unqualified term "conservative" is often applied to social conservatives who are not fiscal or ecomomic conservatives. It is rarely applied in the opposite case, except in specific contrast to those who are neither.

It can be argued that classical conservatism tends to represent the establishment. Yet, this is not always the case. Considering the conservative's opposition to political abstractions, the true conservative will never support a contrived social state, be that on the left ([[Communism]]) or on the right ([[Nazism]]). There is an independent justification of the attitude of conservatism, which tends to favour what is organic and has been shaped by history, against the planned and artificial.

==Conservatism and Change==

"Conservatism" is not opposed to change. For example, the Reagan administration in the US and that of [[Margaret Thatcher]] in the UK both professed conservatism, but during Reagan's term of office, the United States radically revised its tax code, while Thatcher dismantled several previously nationalized industries and made major reforms in taxation and housing; furthermore, both took, or attempted, significant measures to reduce the power of [[labor union]]s. However some opponents, and also some of the members of these governments themselves, characterised those changes as regressive, as "changing back" to a defunct status quo.

In less recent history, the [[Reform Act of 1867]], supported by Conservative UK Prime Minister [[Benjamin Disraeli, 1st Earl of Beaconsfield|Benjamin Disraeli]] was the single greatest expansion of the [[suffrage|franchise]] in the UK prior to [[women's suffrage]]. Various "Conservative" parties have presided over periods of economic expansion which have been disruptive of previous social and political arrangements, for example the Republican Party in 1920s America, and the BJP in late 1990s India.

Political memory can be of various durations, and the traditions conservatives embrace can be of relatively recent invention. The prevalence of the [[nuclear family]] is, at most, a few centuries old. Western democracy itself is a late 18th century invention. Corporate capitalism is even newer. The race-blind [[meritocracy]] now embraced by many U.S. conservatives as an alternative to [[affirmative action]] would have seemed quite radical to most U.S. conservatives in the 1950s.

==Other Topics==

=== Conservatism vs. Fascism ===
While conservatives often identify with nationalist movements, there is a clear distinction between conservative nationalism and the ultra-nationalism of [[fascism]]. Conservatism, at its root, is an attitude of political and social [[quietism]].  The big plans of the Big Man, the noisy and levelling mass movements, the ''[[Führer]]prinzip'', the [[personality cult]]s, and the strong propensity toward [[totalitarianism]] that are central to fascism, are antithetical to the positions of classical conservatism. Conservatism stands for learning from the mistakes of the past, and ''[[primum non nocere]]'' is an essential conservative principle. 

Nonetheless, historically, some conservative traditionalists have been drawn to Fascist movements. Some may have admired the moral and military renewal that Fascist leaders promised. Others may have merely thought fascism a more palatable alternative to socialism or communism. For example, in mid-1930s Britain, conservative media baron [[Lord Rothermere's]] ''[[Daily Mail]]'' enthusiastically backed Sir [[Oswald Mosley]]'s [[British Union of Fascists]], whilst a number of Tory peers and MPs supported closer ties with Nazi Germany. For a more contemporary example, in a 2003 article in ''[[National Review]]'', [[John Laughland]] accuses contemporary neoconservative [[Michael Ledeen]] of "flirting with fascism", citing examples of the latter's praise for Italian fascist [[Gabriele D'Annunzio]]. [http://www.amconmag.com/06_30_03/feature.html]

=== Conservatism and conservation ===

The [[North America]]n [[conservation movement]] has its roots in the conservative movement of the late eighteen hundreds. These "first wave" environmentalists were generally well-to-do and advocated protection of natural areas due to the fact that these untouched areas were choice spots for vacations away from the dirty cities. In modern times, the "third wave" environmental movement, popularized by [[Ronald Reagan]] harkens back to the classical conservative's justification for free markets: simply, free markets are viewed as the best instrument for protecting the environment. Given that pollution is an inefficiency, and given that consumers like "eco-friendly" or "organic" products, it makes sense to the third-wave environmentalist that being environmentally friendly is a boost to sales. "Second-wave" environmentalists, represented by "command-and-control" techniques and the radical social change of the 60s, were generally not conservative in any sense of the word. Yet the nationalist overtones of the second-wave environmental movement did appeal to many [[populists]] and social conservatives, who were not averse to anti-commercial values. Many of these viewed ecological conservation as necessary to preserve traditional values and viewed conservation of resources -- especially public resources -- as part of long-term fiscal conservativism.  Mistakenly, many note the generally [[social democrat]]ic and sometimes radical economic goals of [[Greens]] and conclude that they have nothing in common with conservatives.  In the UK, a [[Blue-Green Alliance]] is an alignment of these "green" and "right" forces, although in the U.S. the terms [[Green Republican]] or [[Green Libertarian]] have come into use to imply the same.  [[Dan Sullivan]] has written on the convergence of Libertarian and Green views in the U.S. [http://geolib.pair.com/essays/sullivan.dan/greenlibertarians.html "Greens and Libertarians"]

=== Conservatives in different countries ===

What constitutes conservative politics and policies, obviously, will depend on the traditions and customs of a given country.  

In the [[United States]], most persons who call themselves conservatives believe strongly in the [[Judeo-Christian tradition|Judeo-Christian social tradition]] and [[Strict constructionism|strict construction]] of the [[U.S. Constitution]]. The origins of conservatism in the U.S. can be traced from the [[Whigs]] of [[George Washington]] through the [[Federalists]] of [[John Adams]], and the [[United States Republican Party|Republicans]] of [[Abraham Lincoln]] (the ideological heirs to the [[Federalist]] legacy). In the [[U.S. Civil War|Civil War]] era, other issues dominated, and for the next century conservatives were roughly equally divided among the two major parties. One particularly notable element were the southern [[U.S. Democratic Party|Democrats]], some of whom bolted the party as the third-party [[Dixiecrat]]s, backing [[Strom Thurmond]]'s [[1948]] presidential candidacy. 

Ironically, as the Democratic Party became identified with the [[Civil Rights Movement]] of the 1950s through 1970s, many former southern Democrats joined the [[U.S. Republican Party|Republican Party]], even in the face of greater proportional support for [[civil rights]] legislation among Republicans, thereby increasingly cementing the Republicans' alignment as a conservative party. 

Conservatism is a large political philosophy, and its central tenets may be used as justification for or opposition to civil rights legislation. "Mr. Conservative," U.S. Senator [[Barry Goldwater]], in his 1960 ''[[Conscience of a Conservative]]'', argues that the reason conservatives split on the issue of civil rights was due to some conservatives advocating ends (integration, even in the face of what they saw as unconstitutional Federal involvement) and some advocating means (constitutionality above all else, even in the face of [[Racial segregation|segregation]]). 

Today in the U.S., geographically the [[U.S. Southern states|South]], the less industrial parts of the [[U.S. Midwest|Midwest]], and the non-coastal [[U.S. West|West]] are conservative strongholds.

In the UK, contemporary conservatives may trace their roots to both the [[Tories]] of Canning and the early [[Whigs]] (who opposed the monarchy). The Tories, who continued to represent the interests of the aristocracy, in contrast to the Whiggish mercantile class, dominated British politics from the [[1770s]] and the [[1830s]]. It is during this period that [[Edmund Burke]], the so-called "Father of Modern Conservatism," articulated the anti-monarchial conservative position through the [[Whig]] party.

Nominally, the modern Conservative party was founded out of the Tory party by Sir [[Robert Peel]] in the [[1840s]], splitting almost immediately, over the issue of [[protectionism]]. The anti-protectionist faction joined with some Whigs and radicals to form the [[Liberal]] coalition, which was to dominate for much of the rest of the [[nineteenth century]]. In the twenty-two years between [[1852]] and [[1874]], the Conservative Party, which continued to be known colloquially as the Tory party, enjoyed less than four years of power. However, after the Liberals split over Home Rule in [[Ireland]], the Conservatives returned to prominence under [[Benjamin Disraeli]], and were in power for twelve of the next twenty years. Power alternated between the Conservatives and the Liberals for the next two decades, until a coalition between the two parties was formed during the [[first World War]]. This, along with the rise of the [[Labour Party (UK)|Labour Party]], led to the collapse of the Liberals in the 1920s. A number of former Liberals, including [[Winston Churchill]], chose to join the Tory Party, under [[Stanley Baldwin]], instead of Labour. During the [[1930s]], the Conservatives dominated [[Ramsay Macdonald]]'s "National" government and instituted the protectionist policies they had attempted to introduce in the [[1920s]]. After Macdonald resigned the Conservatives were openly in government, but many of the traditional Conservative policies of economic intervention in the interests of business leaders and land-owners were dropped from the party's platform, in favour of more ameliorative welfare policies. After the [[second World War]], under a movement that would come to be known as "[[One Nation Conservatism]]", the Conservative party made a number of concessions to the socialist policies of the left. This was partly in order to regain power, but also the result of the early successes of [[central planning]] and state-ownership forming a cross-party consensus. In the early [[1970s]], [[Edward Heath]] attempted to restore traditional Conservative economic policies by under-pining them with a socially responsible outlook, but found little support in the private sector and soon retreated to the post-war consensus. With the advent of [[Margaret Thatcher]], the Tories were seen as having returned to their traditional policies. However, some Conservatives saw the Thatcher administration as lacking the traditional Conservative policies of charity and responsibility, while others, outside of the traditional ranks of the Conservative Party, saw Thatcherism as the intellectual successor to [[classical liberalism]], particularly with regard to its belief in free trade and laissez-faire economics. Thatcher's core economic policies have since formed a broad, Conservative consensus in British politics, similar to the Labour consensus that dominated from the [[1940s]] until the [[1970s]], and the Liberal consensus of the [[1860s]] to the [[1910s]].
 
Conservatism in the UK and US should not be confused with conservatism abroad. Conservatism is not necessarily democratic: in fact, insofar as democracy is absolutism and "tyranny of the majority," conservatism is inherently ''undemocratic.''  A case in point is the radical "democracy" of [[Marxism]] (of the USSR, Communist China, Cuba, etc.), opposed by the conservative. However, the conservative would not find the government of [[Iran]] or, more appropriately, of [[Pakistan]] to be inherently objectionable. Neither [[Islam]] nor [[theocracy]] are incompatible with conservatism, provided rule of law still exists. Yet where Iran or Pakistan trample the rule of law &amp;ndash; there the conservative would object. 

Conservative goals can vary not only between countries, but in the same country over time.  Many U.S. conservatives (especially the onetime Southern Democrats: ''see [[Dixiecrat]]'') once supported enforced racial [[segregation]], but no conservative today can realistically enter office holding this position and few true conservatives still hold it, seeing it as something which prevents free people from fully participating in the benefits of a capitalist economy, among other problems. 

Although most conservatives today agree on the value of [[free market]]s and reducing regulation (although to a much lesser extent than favored by [[libertarian]]s), there is great disagreement on support for traditional morality vs. opposition to government intervention in the private realm.  Many conservatives feel it is proper for government to take strong actions against [[homosexuality]], [[abortion]], and [[drug abuse]].  Other conservatives are concerned that such actions constitute unwarranted intrusion on personal [[freedom]].

=== Intellectual conservatism in the United States ===

In United States intellectual circles, there are several distinct types of conservatism. Among these are:

* [[Neoconservatism (United States)|Neoconservatism]], many of whose most prominent figures are of Jewish background and are former liberals or even former socialists, primarily from the Northeast or the West Coast, whose politics turned sharply to the right from the 1960s onwards. They are almost uniformly free-traders and strong supporters of [[Israel]].
**Neoconservative publications: ''[[Commentary]]'', ''The Public Interest'', ''First Things'' (although this last has expressed controversial attitudes towards religion and against separation of church and state that many other neoconservatives reject).

* The [[Paleoconservative]]s, by contrast, originated away from the coasts. Choosing their self-designation deliberately to contrast to "Neoconservative", the "Paleos", they are almost uniformly from Christian backgrounds. They are far more socially and culturally conservative than the "Neos", more inclined toward issues like states' rights, often opposed to free trade, and overtly suspicious of the "Neos'" often liberal or socialist backgrounds.
**Paleoconservative publications: ''[[The American Conservative]]'', ''[[Modern Age]]'', ''[[The University Bookman]]'', [[Chronicles (paleoconservative)|Chronicles]]'', ''[[The Chesterton Review]]'', ''[[The Salisbury Review]]''.

Other strands of conservatism have been influenced by the counterrevolutionary [[Catholic]] thought of figures like [[Joseph de Maistre]], and the [[distributism]] of [[G. K. Chesterton]] and the French traditionalists (e.g. [[Henri Corbin]]). Some conservatives positions originated from the [[Frankfurt School]], after taking (like the neoconservatives) a turn to the right &amp;mdash; such as the editors of ''Telos''.

As has already been remarked, libertarians generally agree with conservative views on the economy, but they disagree on social issues. However, there are some libertarians, such as [[Lew Rockwell]] or [[Murray Rothbard]], whose views on social or cultural issues are closer to conservatism; these are sometimes called "paleolibertarians."

=== Conservatism in the United States electoral politics ===

In the United States, the [[United States Republican Party|Republican Party]] is generally considered to be the party of conservatism.  This has been the case since the [[1960s]], when the conservative wing of that party consolidated its hold, causing it to shift permanently to the right of the [[United States Democratic Party|Democratic Party]]; also, in varying degrees at various times over the second half of the twentieth century, numerous conservative white southerners left the Democratic Party and (in most cases) became Republicans. One of the most prominent examples would be [[Strom Thurmond]].

In addition, many United States libertarians, in the [[United States Libertarian Party|Libertarian Party]] and even some in the Republican Party, see themselves as conservative, even though they advocate significant economic and social changes - for instance, further dismantling the welfare system or liberalising drug policy.  They see these as conservative policies because they conform to the spirit of individual liberty that they consider to be a traditional [[American value]]. 

On the other end of the scale, some Americans see themselves as conservative while not being supporters of free market policies.  These people generally favour [[protectionist]] trade policies and government intervention in the market to preserve American jobs.  Many of these conservatives were originally supporters of [[neoliberalism]] who changed their stance after perceiving that countries such as [[China]] were benefitting from that system at the expense of American production.

Finally, many people see the entire American political mainstream as having reached a conservative consensus, with the federal government being run by successive "[[Republicrat]]" and right-wing Republican administrations.  In support of this theory, they point out that the only recent Democratic President ([[Bill Clinton]]) was from the moderate, conservative wing of the Democratic Party.  They also suggest that many progressives are switching to the [[United States Green Party|Green Party]] and thus leaving the [[first past the post electoral system|electable mainstream]].

Americans are often stereotyped by western Europeans as conservative due to their religious and right-wing tendencies as well as what the Europeans consider to be puritan attitudes towards sex and drugs (particularly [[alcoholic beverages|alcohol]]).

== History of conservatism ==

The modern split between conservative and liberal can be traced back to the [[English Civil War]] and the [[French Revolution]]. In England, specifically, the predecessors of the conservatives tended to be supporters of the [[monarchy]], and conversely for the predecessors to the liberals. To note the tenuous position of the conservatives: early conservative thinkers included [[Edmund Burke]] who argued forcefully against the French Revolution, but in favor of the American Revolution. Conservatism was not institutionally adopted until the [[Congress of Vienna]] where the ideology of conservatism reached the forefront of [[Europe]]an society.

The Congress of Vienna was only the beginning of a conservative reaction which was bent on containing the liberal and nationalist forces unleashed by the French revolution. Prince [[Metternich]] and most of the other participants at the Congress of Vienna were representatives of the ideology known as conservatism. Conservatism generally dates back to [[1790]] when the most well known figure of conservatism Edmund Burke wrote ''Reflections on the Revolution in France ''. Burke, however, was not the only kind of conservative. [[Joseph de Maistre]], a Frenchman, was the most influential spokesperson for a counterrevolutionary and authoritarian conservatism. De Maistre believed in hereditary monarchies because they would bring "order to society" which was in short supply in his eyes after the chaos of the French Revolution. Despite any differences most conservatives held to some general principles and beliefs.

===Contemporary conservative platform===
In the [[United States]] and western [[Europe]], conservatism is generally associated with the following views, as noted by [[Russell Kirk]] in his [[The Conservative Mind]]:

*1.	"Belief in a transcendent order, or body of natural law, which rules society as well as conscience."
 
*2.	"Affection for the proliferating variety and mystery of human existence, as opposed to the narrowing uniformity, egalitarianism, and utilitarian aims of most radical systems;" 

*3.	"Conviction that civilized society requires orders and classes, as against the notion of a 'classless society'." 

*4.	"Persuasion that freedom and property are closely linked: separate property from private possession, and the Leviathan becomes master of all." 

*5.	"Faith in prescription and distrust of 'sophisters, calculators, and economists' who would reconstruct society upon abstract designs." 

*6.	"Recognition that change may not be salutary reform: hasty innovation may be a devouring conflagration, rather than a torch of progress."

== Famous conservatives ==

===Leaders and Commentators===
*[[Glenn Beck]]
*[[Neal Boortz]]
*[[Pat Buchanan]]
*[[William F. Buckley]]
*[[Tucker Carlson]]
*[[Chuck Colson]]
*[[Ann Coulter]]
*[[James Dobson]]
*[[Dinesh D'Souza]]
*[[Jerry Falwell]]
*[[Steve Forbes]]
*[[Sean Hannity]]
*[[Herbert Hoover]]
*[[David Horowitz]]
*[[Brit Hume]]
*[[Michael Johns]]
*[[Charles Krauthammer]]
*[[Erik Ritter von Kuehnelt-Leddihn]] 
*[[G. Gordon Liddy]]
*[[Rush Limbaugh]]
*[[Michelle Malkin]]
*[[Michael Medved]]
*[[Edwin Meese]]
*[[Peggy Noonan]]
*[[Grover Norquist]]
*[[Oliver North]]
*[[Robert Novak]]
*[[Barbara Olson]]
*[[Diane Ravitch]]
*[[Pat Robertson]]
*[[William Safire]]
*[[Michael Savage (commentator)|Michael Savage]]
*[[Phyllis Schlafly]]
*[[Laura Schlessinger]]
*[[Ben Stein]]
*[[Donald Trump]]

===Entertainers===
*[[Sonny Bono]]
*[[Lara Flynn Boyle]]
*[[Drew Carey]]
*[[Emma Caulfield]]
*[[Lou Costello]]
*[[Bo Derek]]
*[[Shannon Doherty]]
*[[Robert Duvall]]
*[[Clint Eastwood]]
*[[Mel Gibson]]
*[[Patricia Heaton]]
*[[Charlton Heston]]
*[[Bob Hope]]
*[[Heather Locklear]]
*[[David Lynch]]
*[[Victor Mature]]
*[[Dennis Miller]]
*[[George Murphy]]
*[[Wayne Newton]]
*[[Ronald Reagan]]
*[[Arnold Schwarzenegger]]
*[[Tom Selleck]]
*[[Jessica Simpson]]
*[[Ben Stein]]
*[[John Wayne]]
*[[Bruce Willis]]
*[[James Woods]]

===Novelists===
*[[William F. Buckley]]
*[[Tom Clancy]]
*[[George Gissing]]
*[[Nathaniel Hawthorne]]
*[[Russell Kirk]]
*[[Rudyard Kipling]]
*[[W.H. Mallock]]

===Philosophers===
*[[Aristotle]]
*[[Edmund Burke]]
*[[Alexis de Tocqueville]]
*[[Milton Friedman]]
*[[Friedrich Hayek]]
*[[Alexander Hamilton]]
*[[James Madison]]
*[[Ludwig von Mises]]
*[[Ayn Rand]]
*[[George Santayana]]
*[[Adam Smith]]
*[[Leo Strauss]]

===Politicians===
*; [[John Adams]] : [[Federalism|Federalist]] First [[Vice President]] of the [[United States]] ([[1789]]-[[1797]]) and second [[President of the United States]] ([[1797]]-[[1801]]).

*; [[John C. Calhoun]] : [[United States]] [[Senator]] for [[South Carolina]], [[Secretary of State]], [[Secretary of War]], seventh [[United States]] [[Vice President]] ([[1824]]-[[1828]]).

*; [[Winston Churchill]] : [[Conservative Party (UK)|Conservative]] and [[Liberal Party (UK)|Liberal]] politician, UK [[Prime Minister]] in [[WWII]] ([[1940]]-[[1945|45]], [[1951]]-[[1955|55]]).

*; [[Benjamin Disraeli]] : [[Conservative Party (UK)|Conservative]] politician, 1st and only Jewish UK [[Prime Minister]] ([[1868]], [[1874]]-[[1880]]), 1st [[Earl of Beaconsfield]]. 

*; [[Barry Goldwater]] : [[United_States_Republican_Party|Republican]] candidate for US Presidency, [[1964]], [[United States]] [[Senator]] from [[Arizona]].

*; [[Alexander Hamilton]] : Principal author of the [[Federalist Papers]], 1st [[United States]] [[Secretary of the Treasury]] ([[1789]]-[[1795]]). 

*; [[Ito Hirobumi]] : Famous Japanese conservative politician and one of the architects of modern [[Japan]].

*; [[John Jay]] : Coauthor of the [[Federalist Papers]], 1st [[Chief Justice of the United States]] ([[1789]]-[[1794]]).

*; [[Ruud Lubbers]] : [[Prime Minister of the Netherlands]] (1982-1994)

*; [[John Randolph of Roanoke]] : [[Representative]] and [[Senator]] ([[1825]]-[[1827]]) from [[Virginia]], [[United States]] Minister to [[Russia]]

*; [[Ronald Reagan]] : Republican [[President of the United States]] ([[1981]]-[[1989|89]]).

*; [[Margaret Thatcher]] : [[Conservative Party (UK)|Conservative]] UK Prime Minister ([[1979]]-[[1990]])

*; [[George W. Bush]] : [[United States Republican Party|Republican]] [[President of the United States]]  ([[2000]]-)

==See also==

*[[American Enterprise Institute]]
*[[Bioconservatism]]
*[[Common sense conservative]]
*[[Conservative Party (UK)]]
*[[Conservative Party of Canada]]
*[[Christian Democratic Union of Germany]]
*[[Heritage Foundation]]
*[[John Birch Society]]
*[[Libertarianism]]
*[[Neoconservatism (China)]]
*[[Neoconservatism (United States)]]
*[[New Right]]
*[[Old Right]]
*[[Paleoconservative]]
*''[[Policy Review]]''
*[[Reactionary]]
*[[Reagan Doctrine]]
*[[Religious right]]
*[[United States Republican Party]]

== Further reading ==
* [[Albert O. Hirschman]]. 1991. ''The Rhetoric of Reaction: Perversity, Futility, Jeopardy''. Cambridge, MA: The belknap Press of Harvard University Press.  ISBN 0674768671 (cloth) and ISBN 067476868X (paper). ([[As of 2004]], this book is out of print.) 
* [[Russell Kirk]]. ''The Conservative Mind''.  [[Regnery Publishing]]; 7th edition (October 1, 2001): ISBN 0895261715 (hardcover).

== External links and references ==
*[http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/cgi-local/DHI/dhi.cgi?id=dv1-60 ''Dictionary of the History of Ideas'':] Conservatism
*[http://www.libertyforums.com/ LibertyForums] - Classical Liberal, Libertarian &amp; Objectivist Discussion Board
*[http://www.chroniclesmagazine.org Chronicles Magazine]
*[http://www.nationalreview.com National Review]
*[http://www.firstthings.com First Things]
*[http://polaris.gseis.ucla.edu/pagre/conservatism.html Phil Agre] What is Conservatism and what is wrong with it?

[[Category:Conservatism]]
[[Category:Social philosophy]]

[[de:Konservatismus]]
[[es:Conservador]]
[[lt:Konservatizmas]]
[[nl:Conservatisme]]
[[ja:&amp;#20445;&amp;#23432;]]
[[pl:Konserwatyzm]]
[[zh:&amp;#20445;&amp;#23432;&amp;#20027;&amp;#20041;]]
[[he:%D7%A9%D7%9E%D7%A8%D7%A0%D7%95%D7%AA]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>