<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20020618001726|159005" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="6675" pageid="6675" ns="0" title="Conservatism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2002-08-16T15:25:33Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">=== Conservatism as a political doctrine ===

While the word &lt;b&gt;Conservatism&lt;/b&gt; is often used to describe merely an attitude of supporting how things currently are, it can also refer to a political doctrine that originates in [[Edmund Burke]]. Conservatives are not opposed to progress per se, although they are often more doubtful about it than followers of many other ideologies. Conservatives do not reject reason completely, but they place much more emphasis tradition or faith than is common in politics today. According to the author of the [http://counterrevolution.net/consfaq.html Conservatism FAQ], the essence of conservatism is "its emphasis on tradition as a source of wisdom that goes beyond what can be demonstrated or even explicitly stated."

Conservatives emphasize traditional views of institutions such as the family and the church. Generally speaking, they are less likely to consider unmarried couples, even those with children, as families. They are quite unlikely to consider gay couples as families, also even when they have children. They usually oppose the adoption of children by gay couples, and they are extremely unlikely to countenance legal recognition of gay or other unorthodox family structures. In religious life, they are likely to reject any reinterpretation or modification of traditional beliefs, such as in areas of morality and biblical scholarship.

Within the United States, there are several distinct elements in the conservative movement. [[Neoconservative]]s originate in American [[liberalism|liberals]], primarily from the Northeast or the West Coast, who during the 1960s began to move starkly to the [[right-wing politics|right]]. Palaeoconseratives, by contrast, originated in other parts of the United States; they lack the background of having formerly been proponents of liberalism.

Conservative views on the economy often overlap with those of [[libertarians]], but they disagree with the libertarian position on social issues. However, there are some libertarians whose views on social or cultural issues are closer to conservatism than most libertarians are, such as [[Llewellyn Rockwell]] or [[Murray Rothbard]]; these are sometimes called palaeolibertarians.

Other sources of the thought of some conservatives include the [[distributism]] of [[G. K. Chesterton]] and the French traditionalists (e.g. [[Henri Corbin]]). Some conservatives have also originated from the Frankfurt School, after taking (like the neoconservatives) a turn to the right; such are the editors of Telos.

Palaeoconservative publications: Modern Age, Chronicles &lt;br&gt;
Neoconservative publications: Commentary, The Public Interest, First Things (has expressed controversial attitudes towards religion and against separation of church and state that many other neoconservatives reject).

=== Conservatism as an attitude ===

Conservatism is the attitude or lack thereof that justifies whatever state of things currently are.

In a [[communism|communist]] country, conservatives are communists.
In a [[mercantilism|mercantilist]] country, conservatives are mercantilists.
In a [[social-democracy|social-democrat]] country, conservatives are social-democrats.
In a [[feudalism|feudal]] country, conservatives are for feudality.
In a [[libertarianism|libertarian]] country, conservatives are libertarians.
etc.

In this sense conservatism is not a consistent ideology per se, and does not refer to any particular idea, unless a reference is given as to the country and times considered.</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>