<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20081114203027|251833734" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="6675" pageid="6675" ns="0" title="Conservatism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2008-11-15T17:56:21Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{this|conservatism as a political philosophy|Conservatism (disambiguation)}}
{{Conservatism}}
'''Conservatism''' is a term with different meaning in accounting, culture, environment, mathematics, and Western politics.

In Western politics, conservatism refers to the thought started by thinkers such as Edmund Burke. [[Edmund Burke]] was among the first to support [[American Revolution]], while opposing the [[French Revolution]] he saw as violent and chaotic. He pressed for parliamentary control of royal patronage and expenditure.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/historic_figures/burke_edmund.shtml BBC: Edmund Burke (1729 - 1797)]&lt;/ref&gt; Scholar [[R.J. White]] once put it this way: "To put conservatism in a bottle with a label is like trying to liquify the atmosphere … The difficulty arises from the nature of the thing. For conservatism is less a political doctrine than a habit of mind, a mode of feeling, a way of living."&lt;ref&gt;As part of introduction to ''The Conservative Tradition'', ed. R.J. White (London: Nicholas Kaye, 1950)&lt;/ref&gt; [[Ronald Reagan]] often is quoted as saying: "I believe the very heart and soul of conservatism is [[libertarianism]]."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.reason.com/news/show/29318.html Inside Ronald Reagan], a [[Reason (magazine)| Reason magazine]] Interview with Ronald Reagan, July 1975.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Russell Kirk]] considered conservatism "the negation of ideology".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.kirkcenter.org/kirk/ten-principles.html "10 Conservative Principles"]&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Conservative political parties]] have diverse views. For instance, the [[Liberal Democratic Party (Japan)|Liberal Democratic Party]] in Japan, the [[Conservative Party (UK)|Conservative Party]] in Britain, and the [[Liberal Party of Australia]] are all major conservative parties with varying positions.

In [[accounting]], conservatism is a guideline that understates assets and revenues and overstates liabilities and expenses.&lt;ref name="accounting"/&gt; Cultural conservatism is a philosophy that supports preservation of the heritage of a nation or culture. In environment, it refers to the [[conservation ethic]], which is an [[ethic]] of resource use, allocation, and protection. Its primary focus is upon maintaining the health of the [[Natural environment|natural world]]: its [[forest]]s, [[fishery|fisheries]], [[habitat (ecology)|habitats]], and [[biological diversity]].

==Development of Western conservatism==
[[Image:Edmund Burke2.jpg|thumb|160px|Edmund Burke (1729–1797)]] 
{{Refimprove|section|date=November 2008}}
Although political thought from its beginnings contains many strains that can be retrospectively labeled conservative, it was not until the [[Age of Enlightenment]], and in particular the reaction to events surrounding the [[French Revolution]] of 1789, that conservatism began to rise as a distinct political attitude or train of thought. Many point to the rise of a conservative disposition in the wake of the [[Protestant Reformation]], specifically to the works of influential [[Anglican]] theologian, [[Richard Hooker (theologian)|Richard Hooker]], emphasizing moderation in the political balancing of interests towards the goals of social harmony and common good. [[Edmund Burke]]’s polemic ''[[Reflections on the Revolution in France]]'' helped conservatism gain prominence.

[[Edmund Burke]] was among the first to support [[American Revolution]], while opposing the [[French Revolution]] he saw as violent and chaotic. He pressed for parliamentary control of royal patronage and expenditure.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/historic_figures/burke_edmund.shtml BBC: Edmund Burke (1729 - 1797)]&lt;/ref&gt;

His classical conservative position often insisted that conservatism has no ideology, in the sense of a [[utopia]]n program, with some form of master plan. Burke developed his ideas in response to the ''enlightened'' idea of a society guided by abstract reason. Although he did not use the term, he anticipated the critique of [[modernism]], a term first used at the end of the 19th century by the Dutch religious conservative [[Abraham Kuyper]]. Burke was disinclined "to give praise or blame to any thing which relates to human actions, and human concerns, on a simple view of the object in all the nakedness and solitude of metaphysical abstraction".&lt;ref&gt;RRF, Langford 1981-, Volume VIII, 58&lt;/ref&gt;

Burke argued that some people had less reason than others, and thus some people will make better governments than others if they rely upon reason. To Burke, the proper formulation of government came not from abstractions such as reason, but from time-honoured development of the state, piecemeal progress through experience and the continuation of other important societal institutions such as the family and the Church. He argued that tradition draws on the wisdom of many generations and the tests of time, while reason may be a mask for the preferences of one man, and at best represents only the untested wisdom of one generation. However, Burke wrote, "A state without the means of change is without the means of its conservation." Burke insisted further change be organic rather than revolutionary. An attempt to modify the complex web of human interactions that form human society, for the sake of some doctrine or theory, runs the risk of running afoul of the iron law of [[unintended consequence]]s. 

Conservatives strongly support the right of property, and Carl B. Cone, in ''Burke and the Nature of Politics'', pointed out that this view, expressed as philosophy, also served the interests of the people involved.&lt;ref&gt; Carl B. Cone, ''Burke and the Nature of Politics'', University of Kentucky Press, 1957 {{OCLC|399586}} &lt;/ref&gt;

===Liberal conservatism===
[[Liberal conservatism]] is a variant of conservatism that combines conservative values and policies with [[Liberalism|liberal]] stances. As these latter two terms have had different meanings over time and across countries, liberal conservatism also has a wide variety of meanings. Historically, the term often referred to the combination of [[Liberal theory of economics|economic liberalism]], which champions [[laissez-faire]] markets, with the classical conservatism concern for established [[tradition]], respect for authority and religious values. It contrasted itself with [[classical liberalism]], which supported [[Individual freedom|freedom for the individual]] in both the economic and social spheres.

Over time, the general conservative ideology in many countries adopted economic liberal arguments, and the term ''liberal conservatism'' was replaced with ''conservatism''. This is also the case in countries where liberal economic ideas have been the tradition, such as the United States, and are thus considered conservative. In other countries where liberal conservative movements have entered the political mainstream, such as [[Italy]] and  [[Spain]], the terms ''liberal'' and ''conservative'' may be synonymous. The liberal conservative tradition in the United States combines the economic [[individualism]] of the classical liberals with a [[Edmund Burke|Burkean]] form of conservatism (which has also become part of the [[American conservatism|American conservative]] tradition, such as in the writings of [[Russell Kirk]]).

A secondary meaning for the term '' liberal conservativism'' that has developed in [[Europe]] is a combination of more modern conservative (less [[Traditionalism|traditionalist]]) views with those of [[social liberalism]]. This has developed as an opposition to the more [[collectivist]] views of [[socialism]]. Often this involves stressing what are now conservative views of free-market economics and belief in [[individual]] [[responsibility]], with social liberal views on defence of [[civil rights]], [[environmentalism]] and support for a limited [[welfare state]]. This philosophy is that of [[Sweden|Swedish]] Prime Minister [[Fredrik Reinfeldt]]. In continental Europe, this is sometimes also translated into [[English language|English]] as [[social conservatism]].

===Conservative liberalism===
[[Conservative liberalism]] is a variant of [[liberalism]] that combines liberal values and policies with [[Conservatism|conservative]] stances, or, more simply, the right wing of the liberal movement.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ipolitique.fr/liberalisme-conservateur.htm&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.parties-and-elections.de/contents.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Mair"&gt;[[Michael Gallagher (academic)|M. Gallagher]], M. Laver and [[Peter Mair|P. Mair]], ''Representative Government in Europe'', p. 221.&lt;/ref&gt; The roots of conservative liberalism are found at the beginning of the [[History of liberal thought|history of liberalism]]. Until the two [[World Wars]], in most European countries the political class was formed by conservative liberals, from [[Germany]] to [[Italy]]. Conservative liberalism is a more [[Positive liberty|positive]] and less [[radical]] version of [[classical liberalism]].&lt;ref&gt;Allen R.T., ''Beyond Liberalism'', p. 2.&lt;/ref&gt; The events such as [[World War I]] occurring after 1917 brought the more radical version of classical liberalism to a more conservative (i.e. more moderate) type of liberalism.&lt;ref&gt;Allen R.T., ''Beyond Liberalism'', p. 13.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Libertarian conservatism===
{{main|Libertarian conservatism}}
[[Libertarian conservatism]] describes certain political ideologies within the [[United States]] and [[Canada]] which combines [[libertarian]] economic issues with aspects of conservatism. Its four main branches are [[Constitutionalism]], [[paleolibertarianism]], [[American conservatism|small government conservatism]] and [[Christian libertarianism]]. They generally differ from [[paleoconservatives]], in that they are in favor of more [[freedom|personal]] and [[economic freedom]].{{Fact|date=August 2008}} [[Agorist]]s such as [[Samuel Edward Konkin III]] labeled libertarian conservatism [[right-libertarianism]].&lt;ref name="nlm"&gt;{{cite web|title=New Libertarian Manifesto|url=http://agorism.info/NewLibertarianManifesto.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="int"&gt;{{cite web|title=Interview With Samuel Edward Konkin III|url=http://www.spaz.org/~dan/individualist-anarchist/software/konkin-interview.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In contrast to [[paleoconservative]]s, libertarian conservatives support strict [[laissez-faire]] policies such as [[free trade]], opposition to the [[Federal Reserve]] and opposition to all [[regulations|business regulations]]. They are vehemently opposed to [[environmental regulation]]s, [[corporate welfare]], [[subsidies]], and other areas of economic intervention. Many of them have views in accord to [[Ludwig von Mises]].{{Fact|date=August 2008}} However, many of them oppose [[abortion]], as they see it as a [[positive liberty]] and violates the [[non-aggression principle]] because abortion is aggression towards the fetus.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lewrockwell.com/vance/vance133.html|title=Is Ron Paul Wrong on Abortion?|last=Vance|first=Laurence |date=January 29, 2008|publisher=LewRockwell.com|language=English|accessdate=2008-07-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Fiscal conservatism===
[[Fiscal conservatism]] is the economic philosophy of prudence in government spending and debt. Edmund Burke, in his '[[Reflections on the Revolution in France]]', articulated its principles:

&lt;blockquote&gt;''...[I]t is to the property of the citizen, and not to the demands of the creditor of the state, that the first and original faith of civil society is pledged. The claim of the citizen is prior in time, paramount in title, superior in equity. The fortunes of individuals, whether possessed by acquisition or by descent or in virtue of a participation in the goods of some community, were no part of the creditor's security, expressed or implied...[T]he public, whether represented by a monarch or by a senate, can pledge nothing but the public estate; and it can have no public estate except in what it derives from a just and proportioned imposition upon the citizens at large.''&lt;/blockquote&gt;

In other words, a government does not have the right to run up large debts and then throw the burden on the taxpayer; the taxpayers' right not to be taxed oppressively takes precedence even over paying back debts a government may have imprudently undertaken.

===Green conservatism===
[[Green conservatism]] is a term used to refer to conservatives who have incorporated [[Green politics|green]] concerns into their [[ideology]]. The [[Conservative Party (United Kingdom)|Conservative Party]] in the United Kingdom under [[David Cameron]] has embraced a green agenda that includes proposals designed to impose a tax on workplace car parking spaces, a halt to airport growth, a tax on gas-guzzling 4x4 vehicles and restrictions on car advertising.

===Ideological interaction and influence===
Many forms of conservatism incorporate elements of other [[ideology|ideologies]] and philosophies. In turn, conservatism has influence upon them. Most conservatives strongly support the [[sovereign nation]] (although that was not so in the 19th century), and [[patriotism|patriotically]] identify with their own nation. Nationalist [[separatist]] movements may be both radical and conservative.

State question divides conservatives. Some conservatives are friendly toward the idea of nation, for instance, the [[liberal conservative]] [[New-Flemish Alliance]] has sought peaceful secession of [[Flanders]] from [[Belgium]]. Other conservatives oppose the state. For example, [[G. K. Chesterton]] wrote, "'My country, right or wrong,' is a thing that no patriot would think of saying except in a desperate case. It is like saying, 'My mother, drunk or sober.'" Further, [[paleoconservatives]] and others say that in this era of the [[managerial state]], there is no clear consensus on what institutions should be conserved; therefore, the term ''conservative'' can only mean that any idea or ideology or institution that preserves human rights, and the rights of other sentient beings to exist in peace, is what should be preserved.

Conservatives are usually [[economic liberal]]s, diverging from [[classical liberalism]] in the tradition of [[Adam Smith]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.americanchronicle.com/articles/viewArticle.asp?articleID=1689 American Chronicle | Liberal / Conservative (Part 1) Economics&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;   Some conservatives  look to a modified free market order, such as the [[American System (economic plan)|American System]], [[ordoliberalism]], or [[Friedrich List|Friedrich List's]] [[National System]].  The latter view differs from strict [[laissez-faire]] in that the state's role is to promote competition while maintaining the national interest, community and identity.
 
"Liberal" tends to refer to [[classical liberal]] policies outside the [[Anglosphere]]. For example, "[[liberal conservative]]" is a common term in Europe and Asia.

==Western conservatism in different countries==
{{further|[[right-wing]] and [[political spectrum]]}}
===Australia===
[[Image:Turnbull.JPG|thumb|110px|[[Malcolm Turnbull]], the leader of [[Liberal Party of Australia]].]] 
Conservatism in [[Australia]] is related to British and American conservatism in many respects, but has a distinct political tradition. One scholar argues that Australian conservatism is traditionally composed of diverse groups and interests that are united more by opposition to certain political developments than by a distinct shared ideology.&lt;ref name="gw"/&gt; In terms of partisan politics, conservatism has often been defined as opposition to the [[Australian Labor Party]]. Australian groups that have historically been grouped on the conservative side include social conservatives, [[British Empire]] nationalists, organizations supporting rural interests, anti-socialist [[Catholics]], fundamentalist Christians and [[free-market]] [[Liberalism|liberals]]."&lt;ref name="gw"/&gt; 

Historically, for the first 70 years after the [[Federation of Australia]], the non-Labor (and hence implicitly conservative) side of Australian politics was associated with policies of moderate [[protectionism]] in trade, and of support for the [[welfare state]], coupled with maintenance of Australia's ties to the British Empire. Many scholars have seen the government of [[Robert Menzies]] as exemplifying this trend.&lt;ref name="gw"/&gt; However, from the 1980s, [[free-market]] economic policies were increasingly associated with conservatism in Australian politics, following the same trend as the United States under [[Ronald Reagan]] and the United Kingdom  under [[Margaret Thatcher]].&lt;ref name="gw"/&gt; In contemporary Australian politics, the [[Liberal Party of Australia]] is often seen as the  main conservative party.

===Botswana===
[[Image:SeretseKhama.jpg|thumb|100px|left|[[Seretse Khama]], a conservative pioneer in Africa.]]
[[Seretse Khama]] founded the conservative [[Botswana Democratic Party]] and it has been the most popular party in Botswana. According to the [[Economic Freedom of the World]] survey, Botswana is Africa's second most capitalist country.

===Canada===
{{main|Canadian conservatism}}
Canadian conservatism has always been rooted in a preference for the traditional and established ways of doing things, even as it has shifted in economic, foreign and social policy. Like Burke, they rejected the sense of both [[ideology]] and [[revolution]], preferring [[pragmatism]] and [[evolution]]. It is for that reason that unlike in the [[Conservatism in the United States|conservatives in the United States]], Canadian conservatives are generally not [[Republicanism in Canada|republicans]], preferring the [[Monarchism in Canada|monarchy]] and [[Westminster system]] of government. (The United States is a federal [[republic]], while Canada is a [[constitutional monarchy]], a distinction resulting from the [[American Revolution]] and its aftermath.)

===Germany===
[[Image:Angela Merkel (2008).jpg|thumb|130px|[[Angela Merkel]], the first female chancellor of Germany.]]
In Germany, conservatism has often been represented by [[Christian Democracy|Christian Democratic]] parties. They form the bulk of the [[European Peoples Party]] faction in the [[European Parliament]]. The origin of these parties is usually in Catholic parties of the late 19th and early 20th centuries, and [[Catholic social teaching]] was their original inspiration. Over the years, conservatism gradually became their main ideological inspiration, and they generally became less Catholic. The German [[Christian Democratic Union of Germany|Christian Democratic Union]] (CDU), its Bavarian sister party [[Christian Social Union of Bavaria|Christian Social Union]] (CSU), and the Dutch [[Christian Democratic Appeal]] (CDA) are Protestant-Catholic parties.

===Israel===
In [[Israel]], [[Likud]] is the major [[Centre-right|centre-right]] political party. Founded in 1973 as an alliance of several right-wing and liberal parties, Likud's victory in the [[Israeli legislative election, 1977|1977 elections]] was a major turning point in the country's political history.&lt;ref&gt;Israel at the Polls, 1992 By Daniel Judah Elazar, Shmuel Sandler&lt;/ref&gt; Likud supports [[free market]] [[capitalism]] and [[liberalism]]. Likud, under the guidance of [[Finance minister]] [[Binyamin Netanyahu]], pushed through legislation to reduce [[value added tax]] (VAT), income and corporate taxes, as well as [[customs duty]]. The party has instituted free trade (especially with the [[European Union]] and the [[United States]]) and has dismantled certain monopolies (e.g. [[Bezeq]] and the sea ports). It has privatized numerous government-owned companies (e.g. [[El Al]] and [[Bank Leumi]]).

===Japan===
[[Image:Koizumi in Graceland 2006.jpg|thumb|right|[[Junichiro Koizumi]], a leader of the right-wing [[Liberal Democratic Party (Japan)|Liberal Democratic Party (LDP)]] who won the largest party majority ever in modern Japanese history.]]
Japan's conservative [[Liberal Democratic Party (Japan)|Liberal Democratic Party]]  - which has dominated elections for half a century - traditionally identified itself with a number of general goals: rapid, export-based economic growth; close cooperation with the [[United States]] in foreign and defense policies; and several newer issues, such as administrative reform. Administrative reform encompassed several themes: simplification and streamlining of government bureaucracy; privatization of [[Japanese public corporations|stateowned enterprises]]; and adoption of measures, including tax reform, needed to prepare for the strain on the economy posed by an [[Aging of Japan|aging society]].

Other priorities in the early 1990s included promoting a more active and positive role for Japan in the rapidly developing Asia-Pacific region, internationalizing Japan's economy by liberalizing and promoting domestic demand, creating a hightechnology information society, and promoting scientific research.

===Netherlands===
[[Image:Ayaan-Hirsi-Ali-VVD.NL-1200x1600.JPG|left|90px|thumb|[[Ayaan Hirsi Ali]], a writer and a former MEP from the [[People's Party for Freedom and Democracy]].]]
The Dutch conservative-liberal [[People's Party for Freedom and Democracy]] advocates lower taxes, legal cannabis and legal euthanasia.

===New Zealand===
[[Image:John Key National Party2.jpg|thumb|100px|[[John Key]], New Zealand's Prime Minister designate.]]

The [[New Zealand National Party]] ("National" or "the Nats") [[as of 2008|currently]] is expected to form the largest (in terms of parliamentary seats) [[political party]] in the next [[New Zealand Parliament]], and thus function as the core of a governing coalition. For many decades "National" has been the largest liberal-conservative political party in New Zealand. 

The National Party [[as of 2007|currently]] advocates policies of reducing [[tax]]es, reducing [[social welfare]] payments, promoting [[free trade]], restoring or maintaining New Zealand's defence alliances, and promoting one standard of citizenship for all New Zealanders ("One law for all").

===Republic of China===
[[Image:2006INGTaipeiMarathon-077.jpg|thumb|140px|[[Taiwan]]'s current President [[Ma Ying-jeou]], who pledged to expand [[free trade]].]]
In the [[Republic of China]], the conservative [[Kuomintang]] (the most popular party) generally seeks warmer relations with the [[People's Republic of China]] in terms of [[free trade]].

===Scandinavian countries===
In [[Scandanavia]]n countries, conservatism has been represented in [[Liberal conservatism|liberal conservative]] parties such as the [[Kokoomus|National Coalition party]] in [[Finland]], the [[Moderate Party]] in Sweden, [[Høyre (party)|Høyre]] in Norway and the [[Conservative People's Party (Denmark)|Conservative People's Party]] in Denmark.  Domestically, these parties generally support market-oriented policies. Denmark's conservative-liberal [[Venstre (Denmark)|Venstre]] has been characterized as a classical liberal party. Their current leader ([[Anders Fogh Rasmussen]]) wrote the book ''Fra Socialstat til Minimalstat'' ({{lang-en|From Social State to Minimal State}}), which advocated an extensive reform along classical liberal lines.

===South Korea===
The liberal conservative [[Grand National Party]] is the most popular party in South Korea. Left-wing parties are unpopular among South Koreans, the largest left-wing party receiving only some 3% of votes. After decades of free market policies, free trade, and low taxation, South Korea is a major [[G20 industrial nations|economic power]] and one of the wealthiest countries in Asia. It had one of the world's fastest growing economies since the 1960s, now highly [[developed country|developed]]&lt;ref name="autogenerated1"&gt;[http://travel.state.gov/travel/cis_pa_tw/cis/cis_1018.html Korea, Republic of&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[List of Asian countries by GDP|fourth largest]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite paper
 |author=IMF
 |title=World Economic Outlook Database, October 2007
|version = 2007
 |publisher=IMF
 |date=2007
 |url=http://www.imf.org/external/pubs/ft/weo/2007/02/weodata/weorept.aspx?sy=2006&amp;ey=2008&amp;scsm=1&amp;ssd=1&amp;sort=country&amp;ds=.&amp;br=1&amp;pr1.x=56&amp;pr1.y=12&amp;c=512%2C941%2C914%2C446%2C612%2C666%2C614%2C668%2C311%2C672%2C213%2C946%2C911%2C137%2C193%2C962%2C122%2C674%2C912%2C676%2C313%2C548%2C419%2C556%2C513%2C678%2C316%2C181%2C913%2C682%2C124%2C684%2C339%2C273%2C638%2C921%2C514%2C948%2C218%2C686%2C963%2C688%2C616%2C518%2C223%2C728%2C516%2C558%2C918%2C138%2C748%2C196%2C618%2C278%2C522%2C692%2C622%2C694%2C156%2C142%2C624%2C449%2C626%2C564%2C628%2C283%2C228%2C853%2C924%2C288%2C233%2C293%2C632%2C566%2C636%2C964%2C634%2C182%2C238%2C453%2C662%2C968%2C960%2C922%2C423%2C714%2C935%2C862%2C128%2C716%2C611%2C456%2C321%2C722%2C243%2C942%2C248%2C718%2C469%2C724%2C253%2C576%2C642%2C936%2C643%2C961%2C939%2C813%2C644%2C199%2C819%2C184%2C172%2C524%2C132%2C361%2C646%2C362%2C648%2C364%2C915%2C732%2C134%2C366%2C652%2C734%2C174%2C144%2C328%2C146%2C258%2C463%2C656%2C528%2C654%2C923%2C336%2C738%2C263%2C578%2C268%2C537%2C532%2C742%2C944%2C866%2C176%2C369%2C534%2C744%2C536%2C186%2C429%2C925%2C178%2C746%2C436%2C926%2C136%2C466%2C343%2C112%2C158%2C111%2C439%2C298%2C916%2C927%2C664%2C846%2C826%2C299%2C542%2C582%2C443%2C474%2C917%2C754%2C544%2C698&amp;s=PPPGDP&amp;grp=0&amp;a=
 |accessdate=2008-02-12}}
&lt;/ref&gt; in Asia and [[List of countries by GDP (nominal)|13th largest]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite paper
 |author=IMF
 |title=World Economic Outlook Database, October 2007
|version = 2007
 |publisher=IMF
 |url=http://www.imf.org/external/pubs/ft/weo/2007/02/weodata/weorept.aspx?pr.x=56&amp;pr.y=6&amp;sy=2007&amp;ey=2007&amp;scsm=1&amp;ssd=1&amp;sort=country&amp;ds=.&amp;br=1&amp;c=512%2C941%2C914%2C446%2C612%2C666%2C614%2C668%2C311%2C672%2C213%2C946%2C911%2C137%2C193%2C962%2C122%2C674%2C912%2C676%2C313%2C548%2C419%2C556%2C513%2C678%2C316%2C181%2C913%2C682%2C124%2C684%2C339%2C273%2C638%2C921%2C514%2C948%2C218%2C686%2C963%2C688%2C616%2C518%2C223%2C728%2C516%2C558%2C918%2C138%2C748%2C196%2C618%2C278%2C522%2C692%2C622%2C694%2C156%2C142%2C624%2C449%2C626%2C564%2C628%2C283%2C228%2C853%2C924%2C288%2C233%2C293%2C632%2C566%2C636%2C964%2C634%2C182%2C238%2C453%2C662%2C968%2C960%2C922%2C423%2C714%2C935%2C862%2C128%2C716%2C611%2C456%2C321%2C722%2C243%2C942%2C248%2C718%2C469%2C724%2C253%2C576%2C642%2C936%2C643%2C961%2C939%2C813%2C644%2C199%2C819%2C184%2C172%2C524%2C132%2C361%2C646%2C362%2C648%2C364%2C915%2C732%2C134%2C366%2C652%2C734%2C174%2C144%2C328%2C146%2C258%2C463%2C656%2C528%2C654%2C923%2C336%2C738%2C263%2C578%2C268%2C537%2C532%2C742%2C944%2C866%2C176%2C369%2C534%2C744%2C536%2C186%2C429%2C925%2C178%2C746%2C436%2C926%2C136%2C466%2C343%2C112%2C158%2C111%2C439%2C298%2C916%2C927%2C664%2C846%2C826%2C299%2C542%2C582%2C443%2C474%2C917%2C754%2C544%2C698&amp;s=PPPGDP&amp;grp=0&amp;a= October 2007
 |accessdate=2008-02-12}}
&lt;/ref&gt; in the world. Forming the [[G20 industrial nations]] and the world's top ten [[List of countries by exports|exporters]], it is an [[APEC]] and [[OECD]] member, defined as a High Income Nation by the [[World Bank Group|World Bank]] and an Advanced Economy by the [[IMF]] and [[CIA]]. The [[Four Asian Tigers|Asian Tiger]] is leading the [[Next Eleven]] nations and is still among the world's fastest growing [[developed country|developed countries]].&lt;ref name="autogenerated1" /&gt; Today, its success story is known as the "[[Miracle on the Han River]]", a role model for many [[developing country|developing countries]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,361781,00.html Seoul's Green Revolution - TIME&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

===United Kingdom===
Conservatism in the [[United Kingdom]] is related to its counterparts in other Western nations, but has a distinct tradition. [[Edmund Burke]] is often considered the ''father of conservatism'' in the English-speaking world.. Burke was a [[British Whig Party|Whig]], while the term ''[[Tory]]'' is given to the later Conservative Party. One [[Australia]]n scholar argues, "For Edmund Burke and Australians of a like mind, the essence of conservatism lies not in a body of theory, but in the disposition to maintain those institutions seen as central to the beliefs and practices of society."&lt;ref name="gw"&gt;Worthington, Glen, [http://web.archive.org/web/20060913184447/http://www.aph.gov.au/library/pubs/rn/2001-02/02RN29.htm Conservatism in Australian National Politics], Parliament of Australia Parliamentary Library, 19 February 2002&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:Thatcher - Reagan c872-9.jpg|thumb|left|100px|[[Margaret Thatcher]], a radical reformer of Britain.]]
The old established form of English, and after the [[Acts of Union 1707|Act of Union]], British conservatism, was the Tory Party. It reflected the attitudes of a rural land owning class, and championed the institutions of the monarchy, the [[Anglican Communion|Anglican Church]], the family, and property as the best defence of the social order. In the early stages of the [[industrial revolution]], it seemed to be totally opposed to a process that seemed to undermine some of these bulwarks. The new industrial elite were seen by many as enemies to the social order. Sir [[Robert Peel]] was able to reconcile the new industrial class to the Tory landed class by persuading the latter to accept the repeal of the [[Corn Laws]] in 1846. He created a new political group that sought to preserve the old status quo while accepting the basics of [[laissez-faire]] and [[free trade]]. The new coalition of traditional landowners and sympathetic industrialists constituted the new [[Conservative Party (UK)|Conservative Party]].

[[Benjamin Disraeli, 1st Earl of Beaconsfield|Benjamin Disraeli]] gave the new party a political ideology. As a young man, he was influenced by the [[romantic movement]] and [[medievalism]], and developed a devastating critique of industrialism. In his novels, he outlined an England divided into two nations, each living in perfect ignorance of each other. He foresaw, like [[Karl Marx]], the phenomenon of an alienated industrial proletariat. His solution involved a return to an idealised view of a corporate or organic society, in which everyone had duties and responsibilities towards other people or groups. This "one nation" conservatism is still a significant tradition in British politics. It has animated a great deal of social reform undertaken by successive Conservative governments.

Although nominally a Conservative, Disraeli was sympathetic to some of the demands of the [[Chartists]] and argued for an alliance between the landed aristocracy and the working class against the increasing power of the middle class, helping to found the [[Young England]] group in 1842 to promote the view that the rich should use their power to protect the poor from exploitation by the middle class. The conversion of the Conservative Party into a modern mass organisation was accelerated by the concept of [[Tory Democracy]] attributed to Lord [[Randolph Churchill]].

[[Image:CMEC 1 009.jpg|thumb|[[David Cameron]], the leader of [[Conservative Party (UK)|Conservative Party]].]]
A Liberal-Conservative coalition during [[World War I]], coupled with the ascent of the [[Labour Party (UK)|Labour Party]], hastened the collapse of the Liberals in the 1920s. After [[World War II]], the Conservative Party made concessions to the socialist policies of the Left. This compromise was a pragmatic measure to regain power, but also the result of the early successes of [[central planning]] and state ownership forming a cross-party consensus. This was known as [[Butskellism]], after the almost identical [[Keynesian]] policies of [[Rab Butler]] on behalf of the Conservatives, and [[Hugh Gaitskell]] for Labour.

However, in the 1980s, under the leadership of [[Margaret Thatcher]], and the influence of Sir [[Keith Joseph]], there was a dramatic shift in the ideological direction of British conservatism, with a movement towards [[free-market]] economic policies. As one commentator explains, "The [[privatization]] of state owned industries, unthinkable before, became commonplace [during Thatcher's government] and has now been imitated all over the world."&lt;ref name="mt"&gt;Davies, Stephen, [http://www.ashbrook.org/publicat/onprin/v1n2/davies.html Margaret Thatcher and the Rebirth of Conservatism], Ashbrook Center for Public Affairs, July 1993&lt;/ref&gt; Some commentators have questioned whether [[Thatcherism]] was consistent with the traditional concept of conservatism in the [[United Kingdom]], and saw her views as more consistent with radical [[classical liberalism]]. Thatcher was described as "a radical in a conservative party"&lt;ref name="mt"/&gt;, and her ideology has been seen as confronting "established institutions" and the "accepted beliefs of the elite"&lt;ref name="mt"/&gt;, both concepts incompatible with the traditional conception of conservatism as signifying support for the established order and existing social convention.

===United States===
''[[Conservatism in the United States]]''
Conservatism in the [[United States]] includes a variety of political ideologies including [[fiscal conservatism]], [[supply-side economics]], [[social conservatism]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://usconservatives.about.com/od/theconservativephilosophy/p/social.htm The Conservative Philosophy]&lt;/ref&gt; [[libertarian conservatism]], [[bioconservative|bioconservatism]] and religious conservatism,&lt;ref&gt;[http://atheism.about.com/library/weekly/aa070898.htm About atheism]&lt;/ref&gt; as well as support for a strong [[military]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.conservative.org/columnists/divine/001226dd.asp The American Conservative Union]&lt;/ref&gt; and [[federalism]]. Modern American conservatism was largely born out of alliance between [[Classical liberalism|classical liberals]] and social conservatives in the late 19th and early 20th centuries.&lt;ref name="Clark"&gt;Clark, B. (1998). ''Political economy: A comparative approach''. Westport, CT: Praeger.&lt;/ref&gt;

American conservatism in general traces its heritage back to Irish political philosopher [[Edmund Burke]], who developed his views in response to the [[French Revolution]].&lt;ref&gt;Kirk, Russell, ''The Conservative Mind,'' p. 6.&lt;/ref&gt; US President [[Abraham Lincoln]] wrote, that conservativism is "adherence to the old and tried, against the new and untried."&lt;ref&gt;Kirk, Russell, ''The Conservative Mind,'' p. 8.&lt;/ref&gt; US president [[Ronald Reagan]] is widely seen as a symbol of American conservatism.&lt;ref name="Columbia"&gt;{{cite encyclopedia|title=conservatism|url=http://www.bartleby.com/65/co/conservatsm.html|encyclopedia=The Columbia Encyclopedia|year=2008|edition=6th}}&lt;/ref&gt; Organizations in the US committed to promoting conservative ideology include the [[John Birch Society]], [[Hoover Institution]], [[Heritage Foundation]], [[Eagle Forum]], [[Goldwater Institute]] and [[American Conservative Union]].

In the US, social conservatives emphasize traditional views of social units such as the [[family]], [[Church body|church]], or locale. Social conservatives would typically define family in terms of local histories and tastes. Social conservatism may entail restricting [[marriage]] to relationships between a man and a woman (thereby banning [[same-sex marriage]]) and laws placing restrictions on [[abortion]]. While many religious conservatives (like in the [[Christian Right]]) believe that government should have a role in promoting their values, libertarian conservatives like [[Barry Goldwater]] believe a hands-off government should apply to social values as well.

==Other use of the term==
===Accounting===

Conservatism is an accounting guideline that understates assets and revenues and overstates liabilities and expenses. Net income should thus result in a lower number than the actual number.

Conservatism believes that less financial readers are hurt by being pessimist than being optimist.&lt;ref name="accounting"&gt;Dictionary of Accounting Terms, 4th edition, by Joel G. Siegel and Jae K. Shim&lt;/ref&gt;

===Culture===
{{main|Cultural conservatism}}
Cultural conservatism is a philosophy that supports preservation of the heritage of a nation or culture. The culture in question may be as large as [[Western culture]] or [[China|Chinese]] [[civilization]] or as small as that of [[Tibet]]. Cultural conservatives try to adapt norms handed down from the past. The norms may be romantic, like the [[anti-metric movement]] that demands the retention of [[avoirdupois]] weights and measures in Britain and opposes their replacement with the [[Metrication#United Kingdom|metric system]]. They may be institutional: in the West this has included [[chivalry]] and [[feudalism]], as well as [[capitalism]], [[laicité]] and the [[rule of law]].

In the subset [[social conservatism]], the norms may also be what is viewed as a question of morality. In some cultures,  practices such as [[homosexuality]] are seen as immoral. In others, it is considered immoral for a woman to reveal too much of her body. 

Cultural conservatives often argue that old institutions have adapted to a particular place or culture and therefore ought to be preserved. Others argue that a people have a right to their cultural norms, their own language and traditions. 

===Environment===
The [[conservation ethic]] is an [[ethic]] of resource use, allocation, and protection. Its primary focus is upon maintaining the health of the [[Natural environment|natural world]]: its [[forest]]s, [[fishery|fisheries]], [[habitat (ecology)|habitats]], and [[biological diversity]]. Secondary focus is on [[materials]] conservation and [[energy conservation]], which are seen as important to protect the natural world.
[[Image:Bolivia-Deforestation-EO.JPG|thumb|right|200px|Satellite photograph of deforestation in progress in the Tierras Bajas project in eastern Bolivia. Photograph courtesy NASA.]]

To [[habitat conservation|conserve habitat]] in [[terrestrial ecoregion]]s and stop [[deforestation]] is a goal widely shared by many groups with a wide variety of motivations. ''These issues and groups are covered in their own articles.''

To protect sea life from [[extinction]] due to [[overfishing]] is another commonly stated goal of conservation &amp;mdash; ensuring that "some will be available for our children" to continue a way of life.

The consumer conservation ethic is sometimes expressed by the ''four R's'': " Rethink, Reduce, Reuse, Recycle,"
This social ethic primarily relates to [[local purchasing]], [[moral purchasing]], the [[sustainability|sustained]], and efficient use of [[renewable resource]]s, the moderation of destructive use of finite resources, and the prevention of harm to common resources such as [[air pollution|air]] and [[water pollution|water]] quality, the natural functions of a living earth, and cultural values in a [[built environment]].

The principal value underlying most expressions of the conservation ethic is that the natural world has intrinsic and intangible worth along with utilitarian value &amp;mdash; a view carried forward by the scientific [[conservation movement]] and some of the older [[Romanticism|Romantic]] schools of [[ecology movement]].

More [[utilitarian ethics|Utilitarian]] schools of conservation seek a proper valuation of local and global impacts of human activity upon nature in their effect upon human [[measuring well-being|well being]], now and to our posterity. How such values are assessed and exchanged among people determines the social, political, and personal restraints and imperatives by which conservation is practiced. This is a view common in the modern [[environmental movement]].

These movements have diverged but they have deep and common roots in the [[conservation movement]].

===Epistemology===
[[Epistemic conservatism]] is a view in [[epistemology]] about the structure of reasons or [[justification (epistemology)|justification]] for [[belief]]. While there are various forms, epistemic conservatism is generally the view that a person's believing some claim is a reason in support of the claim, at least on the face of it.&lt;ref&gt;Fumerton (2007), p. 63.&lt;/ref&gt; Others formulate epistemic conservatism as the view that one is, to some degree, justified in believing something simply because one believes it.&lt;ref&gt;Christensen (1994), p. 69.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Religion===
Religious conservatives seek to apply the teachings of particular ideologies to politics, sometimes by proclaiming the value of those teachings, at other times seeking to have those teachings influence laws. Religious conservatism may support, or be supported by, secular customs. In other places or at other times, religious conservatism may find itself at odds with the culture in which the believers reside. In some cultures, there is conflict between two or more different groups of religious conservatives, each claiming both that their view is correct, and that opposing views are wrong.

Because many religions preserve a founding text, or at least a set of well-established traditions, the possibility of radical religious conservatism arises. These are radical both in the sense of abolishing the status quo and of a perceived return to the radix or root of a belief. They are ante conservative in their claim to be preserving the belief in its original or pristine form. Radical religious conservatism generally sees the status quo as corrupted by abuses, corruption, or heresy. One example of such a movement was the [[Radical Reformation]] within the [[Protestant Reformation]] and the later [[Restorationists]] of the 1800s.

Similar phenomena have arisen in practically all the world's religions, in many cases triggered by the violent cultural collision between the traditional society in question and the modern Western society that has developed throughout the world over the past 500 years. Much of what is labeled as radical religious conservatism in the modern world is in fact an indigenous fusion of traditional religious ideals with modern, European revolutionary philosophy, sometimes Marxist in nature.{{Fact|date=February 2008}}

In [[Iran]], conservatism is represented by parties such as the [[Combatant Clergy Association]] (CCA), which includes the nation’s foremost politicized clerics (including the current [[Ayatollah]]) &lt;ref&gt;http://www.s2online.org/news/country/Iraq/IRANpol.htm&lt;/ref&gt; and is considered to be part of the "Islamic right".&lt;ref&gt;http://www.uvm.edu/~fgause/168read.htm Elections Summaries for POLS 168 -- Middle East Politics (Fall 2007)]&lt;/ref&gt; The CCA was the majority party in the fourth and fifth parliaments after the [[Islamic revolution]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.akhbar-rooz.com/article.jsp?essayId=4844 akhbare-rooz (iranian political Bulletin)&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; It was founded in 1977 by a group of clerics with intentions to use cultural approachs to overthrow [[the Shah]]. Nevertheless, they allied with a number of diverse groups, including Marxists.&lt;ref&gt;[http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0304-2421(199606)25%3A3%3C349%3AICAATR%3E2.0.CO%3B2-9]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Saudi Arabia]] has been under the influence of conservative clerics who uphold a strict interpretation of [[Islamic law]], and the monarchy supports conservative social polices.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oxfordislamicstudies.com/article/opr/t236/e0709 Oxford Islamic Studies Online Saudi Arabia]&lt;/ref&gt;  Women are required to dress modestly, and all sexual activity outside of a traditional heterosexual marriage is illegal. Dancing, playing music or showing movies in public are forbidden.&lt;ref&gt;[http://travel.state.gov/travel/cis_pa_tw/cis/cis_1012.html Saudi Arabia Country Specific Information]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Mathematics===
In [[mathematical logic]], a [[logical theory]] &lt;math&gt;T_2&lt;/math&gt; is a ([[Proof theory|proof theoretic]]) [[conservative extension]] of a theory &lt;math&gt;T_1&lt;/math&gt; if the language of &lt;math&gt;T_2&lt;/math&gt; extends the language of &lt;math&gt;T_1&lt;/math&gt;  and every theorem of &lt;math&gt;T_1&lt;/math&gt;is a theorem of &lt;math&gt;T_2&lt;/math&gt; and any theorem of &lt;math&gt;T_2&lt;/math&gt; which is in the language of &lt;math&gt;T_1&lt;/math&gt; is already a theorem of &lt;math&gt;T_1&lt;/math&gt;.

To put it informally, the new theory may possibly be more convenient for proving [[theorem]]s, but it proves no new theorems about the old theory.

==Psychological research==
A North American left-wing author [[Robert Altemeyer]] has developed his theories of "conservatism" (to which he gives his own definition not related to any political movement) with some following. A meta-analysis by Jost, Glaser, Kruglanski, and Sulloway in 2003 analyzed 88 studies from 12 countries, with total around 22,000 responses to paper or Internet surveys typically given to American college students, and found that [[terror management theory| death anxiety]], [[Ambiguity tolerance| intolerance of ambiguity]], lack of openness to experience, uncertainty avoidance, need for [[Cognitive closure (psychology)| cognitive closure]], need for personal structure, and threat of loss of position or [[self-esteem]] all contribute to the degree of one's overall Altemeyer-defined conservatism.&lt;ref&gt;Jost, J.J, Glaser, J., Kruglanski, A.A., &amp; Sulloway, F.J. (2003). Political conservatism as motivated social cognition. ''Psychological Bulletin, 129''(3), 339-375.&lt;/ref&gt; The researchers suggest that these results show that conservatives stress resistance to change and are motivated by needs that are aimed at reducing threat and uncertainty. According to Robert Altemeyer, individuals that are Altemeyer-conservative tend to rank high on [[right-wing authoritarianism]], as measured by Altemeyer's RWA scale.&lt;ref&gt;Altemeyer, B. (1981). Right-wing authoritarianism. Winnipeg, Canada: University of Manitoba Press.&lt;/ref&gt; Psychologist Felicia Pratto and her colleagues have found evidence to support the idea that a high [[social dominance orientation]] (SDO) is strongly correlated with conservative views. Altemeyer admits he can't find a correlation with voting right-wing or left-wing parties.&lt;ref&gt;Enemies of Freedom. By Robert Altemeyer. p. 239&lt;/ref&gt; Studies have shown that outside North America authoritarianism correlates with support for the socialist left.&lt;ref&gt;Altemeyer &amp; Kamenshikov (1991)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;McFarland, Ageyev and Abalakina-Paap (1992)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hamilton, Sanders &amp; McKearney (1995)&lt;/ref&gt;

Research by [[Jonathan Haidt]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://warner.blogs.nytimes.com/2008/09/11/no-laughing-matter/ New York Times, September 11, 2008]&lt;/ref&gt; suggests that American conservatives are much better at projecting themselves into the minds of American liberals than American liberals are at projecting themselves into the minds of American conservatives:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Haidt has conducted research in which liberals and conservatives were asked to project themselves into the minds of their opponents and answer questions about their moral reasoning. Conservatives, he said, prove quite adept at thinking like liberals, but liberals are consistently incapable of understanding the conservative point of view. “Liberals feel contempt for the conservative moral view, and that is very, very angering. Republicans are good at exploiting that anger,” he told me in a phone interview.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

There is also evidence that American conservatives are, on average, happier than American liberals.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newsmax.com/kessler/conservatives_liberals/2008/05/13/95708.html Wasington Insider with Ronald Kessler, 13 May 2008]&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
&lt;table border="0"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td valign="top" width="400"&gt;
*[[Free market]]
*[[Free trade]]
*[[Globalization]]
*[[Liberalism]]
*[[Classical liberalism]]
*[[Liberal conservatism]]
*[[Conservative liberalism]]
*[['And' theory of conservatism]]
*[[Black conservatism]]
*[[Conservative Political Parties]]
*[[Conservative Revolutionary movement]]
*[[Libertarianism]]
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td valign="top"&gt;
*[[Paleoconservatism]]
*[[Paleoconservative worldview]]
*[[Political spectrum]]
*[[Republitarianism]]
*[[Right-wing politics]]
*[[Reactionary]]
*[[Roman Catholic conservatism]]
*[[Liberal Democratic Party (Japan)]]
*[[Conservative Party (UK)]]
*[[Liberal Party of Australia]]
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

===Further reading===
*[http://www.rightwingersguide.com / Conservative political humor book]
*''Our Culture, What's Left of It: The Mandarins and the Masses'' / [[Anthony Daniels (psychiatrist)|Theodore Dalrymple]] (2005) ISBN 1566636434
*Fascists and conservatives : the radical right and the establishment in twentieth-century Europe / Martin Blinkhorn., 1990
*[[Edmund Burke]]. ''Reflections on the Revolution in France'', Hackett Publishing Company, Inc. October 1997: ISBN 0-87220-020-5 (paper).
*Crunden, Robert, ''The Superfluous Men: Critics of American Culture, 1900–1945'', 1999. ISBN 1-882926-30-7
*Recent conservative political thought : American perspectives / Russell G Fryer., 1979
*Paul E. Gottfried, ''The Conservative Movement'', 1993. ISBN 0-8057-9749-1
*The British Right : Conservative and right wing politics in Britain / Neill Nugent., 1977
*America alone : the neo-conservatives and the global order / Stefan A Halper., 2004
*Ted Honderich ''Conservatism''
*[[Russell Kirk]], ''The Conservative Mind'', 7th Ed., 2001. ISBN 0-89526-171-5
*[[Russell Kirk]], ''The Politics of Prudence'', 1993. ISBN 1-882926-01-3
*The conservative press in twentieth-century America / Ronald Lora., 1999
*From the New Deal to the New Right: race and the southern origins of modern conservatism / Joseph E Lowndes., 2008
*Jerry Z. Muller ''Conservatism''
*Right-wing women : from conservatives to extremists around the world / P Bacchetta., 2002
*Unmaking law : the Conservative campaign to roll back the common law / Jay M Feinman., 2004
*Radicals or conservatives? The contemporary American right / James McEvoy., 1971
*[[Robert Nisbet]] ''Conservatism: Dream and Reality'', 2001. ISBN 0-7658-0862-5
*James Page, 'Ought the Neo-Cons Be Considered Conservatives? A Philosophical Response'.AQ: Journal of Contemporary Analysis. 75(6):32-33/40. 2003; available on-line at http://eprints.qut.edu.au/archive/00003599/
*Conservatism in America since 1930 : a reader / Gregory L Schneider., 2003
*Noel O'Sullivan ''Conservatism''
*The new racism : conservatives and the ideology of the tribe / Martin Barker., 1982
*A time for choosing : the rise of modern American conservatism / Jonathan M Schoenwald., 2001
*[[Roger Scruton]] ''The Meaning of Conservatism''
*Facing fascism : the Conservative party and the European dictators, 1935–1940 / N J Crowson., 1997
*[[Alexander Lee]] and [[Timothy Stanley]] ''[[The End of Politics]]: Triangulation, Realignment and the Battle for the Centre Ground'' (Politico's Publishing, 17 July 2006): ISBN 1-84275-174-3 (hardcover)
*[[James Fitzjames Stephen]], ''Liberty, Equality, Fraternity''.

==External links==
{{wikiquote}}
{{Wiktionary}}
*[http://www.urbanconservative.com/2007/02/13/best-conservative-blogs-on-the-internet/ "Best Conservative Blogs on the Internet,"] UrbanConservative.
*[http://www.reaganconservatives.us ReaganConservatives.us]
*[http://chronicleofbias.com "Chronicle of Bias,"] a site that seeks to advance the conservative viewpoint in the media and argue against liberal bias.
*[http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/cgi-local/DHI/dhi.cgi?id=dv1-60 ''Dictionary of the History of Ideas'', Conservatism].
*[http://thedailyconservative.net ''The Daily Conservative''].
*[http://www.fundacionfaes.es "Fundación Faes"] Fundación Faes

*[http://conservativeoasis.com "Conservative Oasis,"] analysis, opinion, and political humor, reflecting on current Conservative events and news.
*[http://www.conservativehawk.com ''The Conservative Hawk'']
*[http://www.realclearpolitics.com ''Real Clear Politics'']
*[http://christsassembly.com A Conservative, Independent, and Unitarian Communion of Saints.]
*[http://www.rightwingsquadron.com Right Wing Squadron], Conservative politics, views and opinions

{{Political ideologies}}

[[Category:Conservatism| ]]
[[Category:Political ideologies]]

[[ar:سياسة محافظة]]
[[br:Mirouriezh]]
[[bg:Консерватизъм]]
[[ca:Conservadorisme]]
[[cs:Konzervatismus]]
[[cy:Ceidwadaeth]]
[[da:Konservatisme]]
[[de:Konservatismus]]
[[et:Konservatism]]
[[el:Συντηρητισμός]]
[[es:Conservadurismo]]
[[eo:Konservativismo]]
[[fa:محافظه‌کاری]]
[[fr:Conservatisme]]
[[ga:Coimeádachas]]
[[gl:Conservadorismo]]
[[ko:보수주의]]
[[hr:Konzervativizam]]
[[ig:Conservatism]]
[[id:Konservatisme]]
[[is:Íhaldsstefna]]
[[it:Conservatorismo]]
[[he:שמרנות]]
[[ku:Şopparêzî]]
[[la:Conservatismus]]
[[lv:Konservatīvisms]]
[[lt:Konservatizmas]]
[[hu:Konzervativizmus]]
[[mk:Конзерватизам]]
[[nl:Conservatisme]]
[[ja:保守]]
[[no:Konservatisme]]
[[nn:Konservatisme]]
[[pl:Konserwatyzm]]
[[pt:Conservadorismo]]
[[ro:Conservatorism]]
[[ru:Консерватизм]]
[[simple:Conservatism]]
[[sk:Konzervativizmus]]
[[sr:Конзервативизам]]
[[sh:Konzervativizam]]
[[fi:Konservatismi]]
[[sv:Konservatism]]
[[ta:பழமைவாதம்]]
[[th:อนุรักษนิยม]]
[[tr:Muhafazakârlık]]
[[uk:Консерватизм]]
[[yi:קאנסערוואטיזם]]
[[bat-smg:Kuonservatėzmos]]
[[zh:保守主义]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>