<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20031107084427|1688835" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="6675" pageid="6675" ns="0" title="Conservatism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2003-11-07T17:33:00Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[de:Konservatismus]]

'''Convervatism''' is a [[political philosophy]] whose chief characteristic is an avowed tendency to resist rapid change and to support traditional norms. 
The term is much used in the context of politics &amp;ndash; either to describe movements which attempt to preserve aspects of the ''[[status quo]]'', or, more specifically, to describe a particular ideology of this sort in the [[Western countries]].  
''Conservatives'' are the counterpart to ''radicals'' and ''revolutionaries.''

'''Conservative''', as a descriptive word, is generally opposed to progressive, or more specifically to [[Political liberalism|liberal]],  [[Socialism|socialist]] or [[revolutionary]] [[ideology|ideologies]]. It is often used as a synonym for [[right-wing]], though there are significant right-wing movements that are far too [[radical]] or [[reactionary]] to be properly considered Conservative.

'''Political conservatism''' is, broadly speaking, support of traditional political views and values.  
Consequently, what might be conservative in one society might be quite radical in a different society.
In addition, in some cases people who regard themselves as ''conservatives'' may advocate quite radical [[reactionary]] changes to the [[status quo]].

=== Conservatism as an anti-ideology ===
Attempts at defining "conservatism" run into an immediate problem.  Conservatism, by definition, is [[scepticism|sceptical]] of plans to new-model human society after an [[ideology|ideological]] model.  It is more a habit of mind than a doctrine.  As such, it is easier to define conservatives in reference to what they oppose than what they support.

While the word '''Conservatism''' is often used to simply describe the attitude of supporting how things as they currently are, it can also refer to a social doctrine originated by [[Edmund Burke]]. Burke wrote at a time when European thinkers were beginning to develop the ideology of [[modernism]], which emphasizes progress guided by reason.  Conservatives are not opposed to progress ''per se'', although they are often more doubtful about it than followers of many other ideologies. Conservatives do not reject reason completely, but they place much more emphasis on tradition or faith than is common in other schools of political thought. According to the author of the [http://counterrevolution.net/consfaq.html Conservatism FAQ], the essence of conservatism is "its emphasis on tradition as a source of wisdom that goes beyond what can be demonstrated or even explicitly stated."  

The conservative world view emphasises the unknowable.  Existing institutions have virtues that cannot be fully grasped by any single person or interest group.  An attempt to modify the complex web of human interactions that form human society for the sake of some doctrine or theory runs the risk of running afoul of the iron law of [[unintended consequence]]s.  Conservatives attempt to remain vigilant against the possibility of [[moral hazard]]s.  

Rather, the conservative embraces an attitude that is deeply suspicious of any attempt to remake society in the service of any [[ideology]] or [[doctrine]], whether that doctrine is [[libertarian]], [[socialist]], or developed from some other source.  They see history as being full of disastrous schemes that seemed like good ideas at the time.  Human society is something rooted and organic; to try to prune and shape it according to the plans of an ideologue is to invite unforeseen disaster.  Conservatism is more of a mindset than a doctrine.  It is  &lt;i&gt;[[List of Latin phrases|ad hoc]]&lt;/i&gt; by necessity.  It is easier to say what it is not, than to define it.  [[Russell Kirk]]'s ''[[The Conservative Mind]]'' envisions a conservatism that is as hostile to the levelling wrought by the market economy as it is to the plans of socialists and social reformers.

=== Conservatism and tradition ===
Conservatives emphasize traditional views of institutions such as the family and the church. Generally speaking, they are less likely to consider unmarried couples, even those with children, as families.  On the issue of [[homosexuality]], they are quite unlikely to consider gay couples as families, also even when they have children. They usually oppose the adoption of children by gay couples, and they are extremely unlikely to countenance legal recognition of gay or other unorthodox family structures. In religious life, they are likely to reject any reinterpretation or modification of traditional beliefs, such as in areas of morality and biblical scholarship.

The relationship of political conservatism to the [[religious right]] is a perennial source for commentary.  It could be argued that the religious right is scarcely conservative: it is instead a movement for social reform with a strong ideological basis, wishing to remake society through forced obedience to its version of Christian values.  The religious right is called conservative primarily because there is a strong element of [[nostalgia]] in its plan for social reform; it sees [[liberalism|liberal]], [[secularism|secular]] society as deviating from a better world that it believes used to exist.  Its plan to remake the world involves reviving an older vision.  Were [[reactionary]] a neutral term, it would apply here.

A similar tension might be said to exist between conservatism and [[patriotism]].  Conservatives, out of their respect for traditional, established institutions, tend to strongly identify with [[nationalism|nationalist]] movements, existing governments, and the [[military]].  Conservatives often believe that these institutions embody admirable values like [[honor|honour]], [[duty]], [[courage]], and [[loyalty]].  They are independent sources of tradition and ritual pageantry that conservatives tend to admire.  They suspect their political opponents of being too open to foreign influences, and too [[intellectual]]ly remote and [[elitism|elitist]] to feel nationalistic pride.  In admiring these institutions, conservatives may be less attentive to the fact that these institutions are often the causes for major social change; and that they tend to break down regional differences and local customs, and mix together people from widely differing regions and backgrounds.

=== Conservatism and Fascism ===
To speak of nationalism, of course, is to call to mind the ugly history of [[Fascism]].  Is there a difference between conservatism and Fascism?  Some liberals will be tempted to say no.  

But conservatism, at its root, is an attitude of political and social [[quietism]].  The big plans of the Big Man, the noisy and levelling mass movements, the ''[[Führer]]prinzip'', and the [[personality cult]]s that are central to most systems that are called Fascist [[totalitarianism]] ought to be  deeply unsettling to the conservative mindset.  In [[history]], it is a regrettable truth that some conservative traditionalists have been drawn to Fascist movements.  Some may have admired the moral and military renewal that Fascist leaders promised.  Others may have only thought Fascism a more palatable alternative to [[socialism]].  Conservatism stands for learning from the mistakes of the past, and ''[[List of Latin phrases|primum non nocere]]'' is an essential conservative principle.  Almost all contemporary conservatives vow that they "won't be fooled again."

=== Conservatism and conservation ===
Although the [[conservation movement]] has roots in social conservative anti-commercial values, the relationship between political conservatives and [[green politics]] is uneven.  Some on both sides, with very solid anthropological and other scientific backing, view ecological conservation and respect for traditional lifeways as a part of fiscal conservativism and necessary to preserve traditional values.  Others note the generally socially liberal and sometimes radical [[accounting reform]], [[monetary reform]] and [[education reform]] goals of [[Greens]] and conclude that they have nothing in common with conservatives.  In the UK, a [[Blue-Green Alliance]] is an alignment of these "green" and "right" forces, although in the US the terms [[Green Republican]] or [[Green Libertarian]] have come into use to imply the same.  [[Dan Sullivan]] has written on the convergence of Libertarian and Green views in the USA.

=== Conservatism and critical theory ===
A large body of writing has been produced by the [[critical theory|critical theorists]] associated with the [[Frankfurt School]], vaguely critical of the "[[hegemony]]" of "[[late capitalism|late capitalist]]" "discourse."  At least a part of the agenda of this body of doctrine, especially as it relates to [[multiculturalism]], and objects to the steamrollering of local [[folkways]] by the commercial media originating in affluent urban societies, seems to be fundamentally aligned with cultural conservatism.  This, too, is a world-view that is sceptical of the claims of [[modernism]] to represent unalloyed [[progress]], and is sceptical of the claims of any ideology to represent anything but the selfish will of the ideologue.   

But although the literary critical theorists seem to have abandoned [[Marxism|Marxist]] [[dialectical materialism]] in exchange for a [[Neoplatonism|neo-Platonic]] [[idealism]] based on a postulate of universal [[social construction]], conservatives are understandably leery of its Marxist origins, its pervasive [[moral relativism]], the [[egalitarianism]] that seems to be its only moral absolute, its harping on [[race]] and [[gender role]]s, and its fascination with the "transgressive".  Still, it may be that the chief dividing line between these two critics of modernism is the lack of a shared [[jargon]].

=== Conservative political movements ===
Contemporary political conservatism, in most [[western]] [[democratic]] countries has two important aspects:
* [[Fiscal conservatism]]: the support of a traditional economic system of a place (or of an idealized version of such a system, perhaps never fully realized).
* [[Social conservatism]]: the support of traditional values, i.e., morality, and particularly of religious morality; also, support of governmental restrictions on personal behavior with an aim of upholding traditional values.

It is possible for one to be a fiscal conservative but not a social conservative; in the United States at present, this is the stance of [[libertarianism]].  It is also possible to be a social conservative but not a fiscal conservative.  At present, this is a common political stance in, for example, [[Ireland]] and among some American [[leftist]]s.

Some have claimed that conservatism is the attitude or lack thereof that justifies whatever state of things currently are.  In a [[communism|communist]] country, conservatives are communists; in a [[mercantilism|mercantilist]] country, conservatives are mercantilists; in a [[social-democracy|social-democrat]] country, conservatives are social-democrats; in a [[feudalism|feudal]] country, conservatives are for feudality;  in a [[libertarianism|libertarian]] country, conservatives are libertarians.  Yet this cannot be the whole story; there is an independent justification of the attitude of conservatism, which tends to favour what is organic and has been shaped by history, against the planned and artificial.  Some commentators have argued that despite the movement's rhetoric, it has been an agent for change, and the traditions which it supports are in fact of relatively recent invention. [links/references?]

Within the United States, there are several distinct elements to conservatism. The [[Neoconservatism (United States)|Neoconservative]] movement originates in American [[liberalism]], primarily from the Northeast or the West Coast, but is marked by a significant move to the [[right-wing politics|right]] from the 1960s onwards. Palaeoconserativism, by contrast, originated in other parts of the United States; its proponents are unlikely to have once been liberals.

Conservative views on the economy often overlap with those of [[libertarians]], but they disagree with the libertarian position on social issues. However, there are some libertarians whose views on social or cultural issues are closer to conservatism than most libertarians are, such as [[Llewellyn Rockwell]] or [[Murray Rothbard]]; these are sometimes called paleolibertarians.

Other strands of conservatism have been influenced by the counterrevolutionary [[Catholic]] thought of figures like [[Joseph de Maistre]], and the [[distributism]] of [[G. K. Chesterton]] and the French traditionalists (e.g. [[Henri Corbin]]). Some conservatives positions originated from the [[Frankfurt School]], after taking (like the neoconservatives) a turn to the right &amp;mdash; such as the editors of Telos.

[[Paleoconservative]] publications: Modern Age, Chronicles &lt;br&gt;
Neoconservative publications: Commentary, The Public Interest, First Things (has expressed controversial attitudes towards religion and against separation of church and state that many other neoconservatives reject).

In the [[United States]] and western [[Europe]], conservatism is generally associated with the following views:
* Personal responsibility
* General opposition to "[[big government]]" policies or [[state inverventionism]]
* Support for [[Judeo-Christian_tradition|Judeo-Christian religious and moral values]].
* Support for strong law enforcement and strong penalties for crimes.
* Restraint in taxation and regulation of businesses.
* Support for a strong military, and well-defended protected borders with regulated immigration
* Support for [[drug prohibition]].
* Opposition to (or support for lessening) many state-run social programs such as welfare and medical care
* Opposition to policies such as [[affirmative action]] and [[multi-lingual education]] which can be perceived as un-[[patriotism|patriotic]] or government favoritism of minority groups.

Conservatives differ widely on some issues as well.  For example, many support open international trade, while some support some form of protection for domestic business such as import tariffs.

=== Conservatives in different countries ===
What constitutes conservative politics and policies, obviously, will depend on the traditions and customs of a given country.  

In the [[United States]], most persons who call themselves conservatives believe strongly in the [[Second Amendment]] and are deeply opposed to [[gun control]]. In many other industrialized democracies, guns are strictly regulated - in [[Japan]] and the [[United Kingdom]] it is extremely difficult for a private citizen to own [[firearm]]s, and the conservative movements of those countries do not generally favor changing these laws. It is likely that most conservatives in those countries would actively oppose a movement to make gun ownership as unregulated as it is in the USA. 

The concept of [[social conservatism]] may in some countries, for instance in [[Continental Europe]], represent a [[paternalism|paternalist]] interest for the social conditions of the people, exemplified by [[Otto von Bismarck|Brismarck]]'s reforms on old-age pensions and health insurance, and in other countries represent the promotion of traditional values and religious morality.

In non-democratic countries, conservatives may be the advocates of the existing non-democratic government. For example, in [[China]] the conservatives are the leading [[Communist party]] officials, while in [[Iran]] the conservatives are the hardline [[Islamic]] fudamentalists.  In these nations, the "conservative" label characterizes people who are against sudden and radical changes in the form of government and believe that the nation is best served with a focus on stability rather than on political or economic revolution.

In [[Latin America]], conservatives traditionally aligned with the [[Roman Catholic Church]], against separation of church and state, against extending voting rights to decendants of [[Native American]]s, and against public education. As in the USA and many other parts of the world, during the [[20th century]] mainstream conservatives gradually moved their positions to closer to that of the traditional liberals. In Latin America, with the more liberal clergy of the post [[Vatican II]] era, conservatives are less strictly aligned with the Church, but continue to afirm what they consider traditional Catholic values.

Conservative goals can vary not only between countries, but in the same country over time.  Many conservatives (see [[Dixiecrat]]) in the USA once supported enforced racial [[segregation]], but no mainstream conservative today (see [[United States Republican Party]]) would advocate this position.

Although some conservatives generally today agree on the value of [[free market]]s and reducing regulation (although to a much lesser extent than favored by [[libertarian]]s), there is great disagreement on moral questions.  Many conservatives feel it is proper for government to take strong actions against [[homosexuality]], [[abortion]], and [[drug abuse]].  Other conservatives are concerned that such actions constitute unwarranted intrusion on personal [[freedom]].

=== History of conservatism ===
The modern split between conservative and liberal can be traced back to the [[English Civil War]] and the [[French Revolution]]. Broadly speaking, the predecessors of the conservatives tended to be opposed to the [[revolution]] and changes in the [[monarchy]], and conversely for the predecessors to the liberals. Early conservative thinkers included [[Edmund Burke]] who argued forcefully against the French Revolution.

Although conservativism shares a common historical root, the beliefs of different conservatives have diverged so that it is difficult to state what constitutes conservative doctrine except in the very broadest terms, and different conservatives will often strongly disagree among themselves.

In this sense conservatism is not a consistent ideology per se, and does not refer to any particular idea, unless a reference is given as to the country and times considered.

''add more''

=== Conservatism in the United States ===

In the United States, the [[United States Republican Party|Republican Party]] is generally considered to be the party of conservatism.  This has been the case since the 1960s, when the conservative wing of that party consolidated its hold, causing it to shift permanently to the right of the [[United States Democratic Party|Democratic Party]].

''add more''

In addition, many United States [[libertarian|libertarians]], in the [[United States Libertarian Party|Libertarian Party]] and even some in the [[Republican Party]], see themselves as conservative, even though they advocate significant economic and social changes - for instance, further dismantling the welfare settlement or liberalising drug policy.  They see these as conservative policies because they conform to the the spirit of individual liberty that they consider to be a traditional American value. 

On the other end of the scale, some Americans see themselves as conservative while not being supporters of free market policies.  These people generally favour [[protectionist]] trade policies and government intervention in the market to preserve American jobs.  Many of these conservatives were originally supporters of [[neoliberalism]] who changed their stance after perceiving that countries such as [[China]] were benefitting from that system at the expense of American production.

Finally, many people see the entire American political mainstream as having reached a conservative consensus, with the federal government being run by successive "Republicrat" and right-wing Republican administrations.  In support of this theory, they point out that the only recent Democratic President ([[Bill Clinton]]) was from the moderate, conservative wing of the Democratic Party.  They also suggest that many progressives are switching to the [[United States Green Party|Green Party]] and thus leaving the [[first past the post electoral system|electable mainstream]].

Americans are often stereotyped by western Europeans as conservative due to their religious and right-wing tendencies as well as what they consider to be puritan attitudes towards sex and drugs (particularly [[ethanol|alcohol]]).

=== Famous conservatives ===

Political leaders:
*[[Winston Churchill]]
** (UK) [[The Conservative Party (UK)|Conservative]] and [[Liberal Party (UK)|Liberal]] politician, [[World War II|wartime]] [[Prime Minister]]
*[[Margaret Thatcher]]
** (UK) [[The Conservative Party (UK)|Conservative]] Prime Minister
*[[Ronald Reagan]]
*[[Henry Kissinger]]

Print and media:
*[[Rush Limbaugh]]
*[[Robert Novak]]
*[[William F. Buckley]]
*[[David Horowitz]]
*[[Matt Drudge]]

Philosphers:
*[[Edmund Burke]]
*[[Ayn Rand]]
*[[Leo Strauss]]
*[[Milton Friedman]]

===See also===

*[[Paleoconservative]]
*[[Reactionary]]
*[[The Conservative Party (UK)]]
*[[Progressive Conservative Party of Canada]]
*[[Neoconservatism (United States)]]
*[[New Right]]
*[[Old Right]]
*[[Religious right]]
*[[Neoconservatism (China)]]
*[[Common sense conservative]]

=== External links and references ===
* [http://www.libertyforums.com/ LibertyForums] - Classical Liberal, Libertarian &amp; Objectivist Discussion Board
*[http://www.chroniclesmagazine.org Chronicles Magazine]
*[http://www.nationalreview.com National Review]
*[http://www.firstthings.com First Things]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>