<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20091024134039|321754498" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="4912935" pageid="4912935" ns="0" title="Stop Murder Music"><revisions><rev timestamp="2009-11-03T03:53:55Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Stop Murder Music''' is jointly run by [[OutRage!]], the [[Black Gay Men's Advisory Group]], and Jamaican gay rights organization Jamaica Forum of Lesbians, All-Sexuals and Gays ([[J-Flag]]).&lt;ref&gt;Burrell, Ian (2005).[http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qn4158/is_20050307/ai_n11857274 "'Murder music' silenced by a tough operator"], ''Independent, The'' (London),  Mar 7, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;

The term 'Murder Music' was coined by British [[LGBT rights in the United Kingdom|gay rights]] activist [[Peter Tatchell]] in the mid-1990s to describe the [[homophobic]] work of certain [[Jamaica|Jamaican]] musicians, primarily [[dancehall]] and [[ragga]] artists who called for and encouraged physical violence and murder of [[Homosexuality|homosexuals]]{{fact|date=June 2008}}.

The Stop Murder Music Campaign have accused [[Beenie Man]], [[Elephant Man (musician)|Elephant Man]], [[Sizzla]], [[Bounty Killer]], [[Vybz Kartel]], [[Capleton]], [[T.O.K.]], [[Buju Banton]] and other artists of promoting anti-gay violence, harassment, and bigotry through their music.

Tatchell has called for laws against homophobic music and the Campaign participated in protests outside concerts. The Campaign has especially objected to lyrics which seem to support violence, including murder, towards gay men. Tatchell's campaign began in the early 1990s when [[Buju Banton]]'s song "Boom Bye-Bye" was released and has continued to date. Dennis Carney, chair of the Black Gay Men's Advisory Group, argued that the [[MOBO Awards]] had a responsibility to exclude anti-gay artists because, "homophobic lyrics in music normalise hatred towards black gay men."&lt;ref&gt;Graver, Mark (2004). [http://www.medicalnewstoday.com/articles/13190.php "Why homophobic lyrics in reggae music are a health issue for black gay men"], ''MedicalNewsToday.com''. Article Date: 10 Sep 2004 - 9:00 PDT.&lt;/ref&gt; Tatchell picketed the [[MOBO Awards]] ceremony to protest at their inviting performers of murder music.&lt;ref name="Reggae singers"&gt;[http://www.outrage.org.uk/Tatchell-reggaesingers.asp outrage.org.uk]&lt;/ref&gt; Tatchell received [[death threat]]s and was labelled a [[racism|racist]]. Tatchell defended himself by pointing to a life's work campaigning against racism, and stated that his statements on Jamaica were in support of terrorised black groups within Jamaica.

Tatchell has also criticised other musicians, including [[Eminem]].&lt;ref name="Eminem"&gt;Tatchell, Peter. [http://www.petertatchell.net/popmusic/iseminemqueer.htm  "Is Eminem Queer?"], ''PeterTatchell.net''.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Canada==
Stop Murder Music (Canada) is an independent branch of the organization in [[Canada]].  It was founded by Akim Ade Larcher, after learning at a local [[West Indian]] store about a Canadian Tour by [[Elephant_Man_(musician)|Elephant Man]].  Larcher, a lawyer, brought together 20 organizations who service the African and Caribbean communities in Canada to form the group.  Murder Music is criminal in Canada because, as it advocates hatred against an identifiable group, it is an indictable offence under the [[Hate_speech_laws_in_Canada#Canada|Criminal Code of Canada]] .  The group has been successful in getting murder music removed from many retailers such as [[Apple_Inc.|Apple]]'s [[ITunes_Store|iTunes Store Canada]]. 

==Reggae Compassionate Act==
The '''Reggae Compassionate Act''' was an agreement allegedly signed in 2007 by artists including Beenie Man, Capleton, and Sizzla, supporting the Stop Murder Music campaign&lt;ref&gt;Colin (2007). [http://www.newnownext.com/2007/06/reggae_stars_si.html "Reggae Stars Sign On To Cut Out Homophobic Lyrics"], ''NewNowNext'', LOGOonline.com. June 13, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Andy (2007). [http://www.towleroad.com/2007/06/reggae_stars_re.html "Reggae Stars Renounce Homophobia, Condemn Anti-gay Violence"], ''Towelroad.com''. 06/13/2007.&lt;/ref&gt;.

The Reggae Compassionate Act has now been somewhat discredited as some artists have felt it was badly worded,&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ttgapers.com/Article1777.html&lt;/ref&gt; whilst others (such as Beenie Man) have denied signing it.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.jamaicaobserver.com/lifestyle/html/20070721T200000-0500_125498_OBS_BEENIE_MAN_DENIES_SIGNING_DEAL_WITH_GAY_GROUP_.asp&lt;/ref&gt; Others (including Elephant Man, TOK, Bounty Killa, and Vybz Kartel) have point blank refused to sign it.&lt;ref&gt; http://www.petertatchell.net/popmusic/reggaestarsditchantigaylyrics.htm&lt;/ref&gt;  

==Criticism==
Tatchell and the Stop Murder Music campaign have been criticized by [[The Black Music Council]], formed in response to the campaign by the president of [[Blacker Dread Records]], Blacker Dread, in order, "to protect the rights of the eight artistes placed on the OutRage! hit list"&lt;ref name="BMC"&gt;Alicia Roache, Staff Reporter. [http://www.sosjamaica.org/test/new.asp?ID=1468 "Black Music Council Defends DJ’s"], ''The Sunday Gleaner'' (sosjamaica.org). 13/12/2004.&lt;/ref&gt;.

Vice-chairman of the BMC, [[Doctah X]]&lt;ref name="archive"&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20050419120025/www.blackmusiccouncil.com/index.php?subaction=showfull&amp;id=1103143546&amp;archive=&amp;start_from=&amp;ucat=1&amp; Archive copy of "Can music incite murder?"], ''The Black Music Council Site'' at the [[Internet Archive]]. Report Date:15 Dec 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;, points out that Jamaica does not have strict anti-gay laws such as [[Saudi Arabia]], which punishes homosexuality with beheading, and said that Jamaica is an easier target for British activists. Dread accuses Tatchell of racism and extremism, saying, “He’ has gone over way over the top. It’s simply racist to put Hitler and Sizzla in the same bracket and just shows how far he is prepared to go.”&lt;ref name="BMC"/&gt;

Doctah X says that "Tatchell is like a new [[Tipper Gore]]," arguing that, "They both pick on black music. They both believe in [[censorship]]."&lt;ref name="archive"/&gt;.

==References==
{{reflist}}
==See also==
* [[Brian Williamson]]
* [[LGBT rights in Jamaica]]

==External links==
*[http://arts.guardian.co.uk/fridayreview/story/0,,1369875,00.html Article in Guardian Unlimited, UK]
*http://partyxtraz.blogspot.com/2007/10/stop-murder-music-blocks-sizzla-and.html
*[http://www.xtra.ca/public/viewstory.aspx?STORY_ID=4593&amp;PUB_TEMPLATE_ID=2 iTunes Canada article at Xtra.ca]
*http://www.freemuse.org/sw28060.asp
*[http://www.stopmurdermusic.ch Stop Murder Music Bern]
*[http://www.egale.ca/index.asp?lang=E&amp;item=1374 Stop Murder Music (Canada) at Egale.ca]
*[http://www.soulrebels.org/dancehall.htm Murder Inna Dancehall]

[[Category:Homophobic violence]]
[[Category:Dancehall]]
[[Category:LGBT terms]]

[[de:Murder music]]
[[fr:Murder music]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>