<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20151116012057|690844553" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="924166" pageid="924166" ns="0" title="LGBTQ rights by country or territory"><revisions><rev timestamp="2015-11-16T01:25:31Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{about|current LGBT rights around the world|historical and current movements to further LGBT rights|LGBT social movements}}
{{pp-semi-indef}}
{{pp-move-indef}}
{{World homosexuality laws map}}{{LGBT rights at the UN}}
'''Laws''' affecting '''lesbian, gay, bisexual, and transgender''' ('''[[LGBT]]''') people vary greatly by country or territory&amp;mdash;everything from legal recognition of [[same-sex marriage]] or [[Civil union|other types of partnerships]], to the [[death penalty]] as punishment for same-sex romantic/sexual activity or identity.

LGBT rights are considered [[human rights]] by the [[Amnesty International]]&lt;ref name=AI&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.amnestyusa.org/our-work/issues/lgbt-rights/about-lgbt-human-rights | title=About LGBT Human Rights | publisher=Amnesty International | accessdate=29 March 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[civil rights]] by some.&lt;ref name=Becker&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/john-becker/lgbt-rights-are-civil-rights_b_1368381.html | title=LGBT Rights Are Civil Rights | publisher=Huffington Post | date=23 March 2012 | accessdate=29 March 2013 | author=Becker, John}}&lt;/ref&gt; LGBT rights laws include, but are not limited to, the following: 
* allowing of [[MSM blood donor controversy|men who have sex with men to donate blood]]
* government recognition of same-sex relationships (such as via same-sex marriage or similar unions)
* allowing of [[LGBT adoption]]
* recognition of [[LGBT parenting]]
* [[anti-bullying legislation]] and student non-discrimination laws to protect LGBT children and/or students
* [[immigration equality]] laws
* anti-discrimination laws for employment and housing
* hate crime laws providing enhanced criminal penalties for prejudice-motivated [[violence against LGBT people]]
* equal [[age of consent]] laws
* equal access to [[assisted reproductive technology]]
* access to [[sex reassignment surgery]] and [[hormone replacement therapy (transgender)|hormone replacement therapy]]
* [[Legal aspects of transsexualism|legal recognition and accommodation of reassigned gender]]
* laws related to [[sexual orientation and military service]]

As of July 2015, eighteen countries, most of them located in the [[Americas]] and [[Western Europe]],{{efn|Countries with same-sex marriage recognized nationwide are: Argentina, Belgium, Brazil, Canada, Denmark,{{efn|Excluding the Faroe Islands}} France, Iceland, Luxembourg, the Netherlands,{{efn|Excluding Aruba, Curaçao and Sint Maarten}} New Zealand,{{efn|Excluding Niue, Tokelau and the Cook Islands}} Norway, Portugal, South Africa, Spain, Sweden, the United Kingdom,{{efn|Exlcuding Northern Ireland, the Crown dependencies and most British Overseas Territories. (Same-sex marriage is legal in the Pitcairn Islands).}} the United States {{efn|Excluding most [[Same-sex marriage under United States tribal jurisdictions|Native American tribes]]. (Same-sex marriage is legal in at least 24 of them). Application to American Samoa unclear.}} and Uruguay.}} recognize same-sex marriage and grant most of (if not all) the other rights listed above to its LGBT citizens.

Anti-LGBT laws include, but are not limited to, the following: [[sodomy law]]s penalizing consensual same-sex sexual activity with fines, jail terms, or the death penalty; anti-"[[lesbian]]ism" laws; and higher ages of consent for same-sex activity.

In 2011, the [[United Nations Human Rights Council]] passed its first resolution recognizing LGBT rights, which was followed up with a report from the UN Human Rights Commission documenting violations of the rights of LGBT people, including [[hate crime]], criminalization of [[homosexuality]], and [[discrimination]]. Following up on the report, the UN Human Rights Commission urged all countries which had not yet done so to enact laws protecting basic LGBT rights.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2011/06/17/un-gay-rights-protection-resolution-passes-_n_879032.html |date=17 June 2011 |agency=Associated Press |first=Frank |last=Jordans |title=U.N. Gay Rights Protection Resolution Passes, Hailed As 'Historic Moment' }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |publisher=United Nations |title=UN issues first report on human rights of gay and lesbian people |url=http://www.un.org/apps/news/story.asp?NewsID=40743 |date=15 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As of July 2015, seventy two countries{{efn|Countries with laws criminalizing homosexuality are: Afghanistan, Algeria, Angola, Antigua and Barbuada, Bangladesh, Barbados, Belize, Bhutan, Botswana, Brunei, Burundi, Cameroon, Comoros, Dominica, Egypt, Eritrea, Ethiopia, Gambia, Ghana, Grenada, Guinea, Guyana, India, Iran, Jamaica, Kenya, Kiribati, Kuwait, Liberia, Libya, Malawi, Malaysia, Maldives, Mauritania, Morocco, Myanmar, Namibia, Nauru, Nigeria, Oman, Pakistan,  Papua New Guinea, Qatar, Saint Kitts and Nevis, Saint Lucia, Saint Vincent and the Grenadines, Samoa, Saudi Arabia, Senegal, Seychelles, Sierra Leone, Singapore, Solomon Islands, Somalia, South Sudan, Sri Lanka, Sudan, Swaziland, Syria, Tanzania, Togo, Tonga, Trinidad and Tobago, Tunisia, Turkmenistan, Tuvalu, Uganda, United Arab Emirates, Uzbekistan, Yemen, Zambia and Zimbabwe.}} as well as five sub-national jurisdictions{{efn| These five sub-national jurisdictions are: the provinces of Aceh and South Sumatra (Indonesia), the Cook Islands (New Zealand), Gaza (Palestine) and Marawi City (the Philippines).}} have laws criminalizing homosexuality, most of them are located in [[Asia]] and [[Africa]]

==History of LGBT-related laws==
{{See also|LGBT history|Timeline of LGBT history|LGBT social movements|History of homosexuality|Sodomy law#History}}
{{LGBT rights}}

===Ancient Celts===
According to [[Aristotle]], although most "belligerent nations" were strongly influenced by their women, the Celts were unusual because their men openly preferred male lovers (''[[Politics (Aristotle)|Politics]]'' II 1269b).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Percy, William A.|title= Pederasty and Pedagogy in Archaic Greece|publisher= University of Illinois Press|year= 1996|url=http://www.google.com/books?id=TCvoj1efp8UC&amp;pg=PA18&amp;dq=celts%2BAthenaeus%2Bboy%2Blover&amp;sig=6jEo_4NaMuXlkX5Z-kpMCM6gOgo|page= 18|isbn= 0-252-06740-1|accessdate= 2009-09-18}}; Rankin, H.D. ''Celts and the Classical World'', p.55&lt;/ref&gt; H. D. Rankin in ''Celts and the Classical World'' notes that "Athenaeus echoes this comment (603a) and so does [[Ammianus Marcellinus|Ammianus]] (30.9). It seems to be the general opinion of antiquity."&lt;ref&gt;Rankin, p. 55&lt;/ref&gt; In book XIII of his ''[[Deipnosophistae|Deipnosophists]]'', the Roman Greek rhetorician and grammarian [[Athenaeus]], repeating assertions made by [[Diodorus Siculus]] in the 1st century BC ([[Bibliotheca historica]] 5:32), wrote that Celtic women were beautiful but that the men preferred to sleep together. Diodorus went further, stating that "the young men will offer themselves to strangers and are insulted if the offer is refused". Rankin argues that the ultimate source of these assertions is likely to be [[Poseidonius]] and speculates that these authors may be recording male "bonding rituals".&lt;ref&gt;Rankin, p.78&lt;/ref&gt;

===Ancient India===
Throughout [[Hindu]] and [[Vedic]] texts there are many descriptions of saints, demigods, and even the Supreme Lord transcending gender norms and manifesting multiple combinations of sex and gender.&lt;ref&gt;ritiya-Prakriti: People of the Third Sex, p. 40&lt;/ref&gt; There are several instances in ancient   [[Indian epic poetry]] of same sex depictions and unions by gods and goddesses. There are several stories of depicting love between same sexes especially among kings and queens. [[Kamasutra]], the ancient [[Ancient India|Indian]] treatise on love talks about feelings for same sexes. [[Transsexuals]] are also venerated e.g. [[Lord Vishnu]] as [[Mohini]] and [[Lord Shiva]] as [[Ardhanarishwara]] (which means half woman).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://galva108.org/deities.html |title=Gay and Lesbian Vaishnava Association, Inc |publisher=Galva108.org |accessdate=2013-11-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Ancient West Asia===

====Ancient Israel====
The ancient [[Law of Moses]] (the [[Torah]]) forbids men lying with men (intercourse) in Leviticus 18 and gives a story of attempted homosexual rape in [[Book of Genesis|Genesis]] in the story of [[Sodom and Gomorrah]], the cities being soon destroyed after that. The death penalty was prescribed. In Deuteronomy 22:5, cross-dressing is condemned as being "abominable".

====Ancient Persia====
In Persia homosexuality and homoerotic expressions were tolerated in numerous public places, from monasteries and seminaries to taverns, military camps, bathhouses, and coffee houses. In the early [[Safavids|Safavid]] era (1501–1723), male houses of [[prostitution]] (''amrad khane'') were legally recognized and paid taxes. Persian poets, such as [[Saadi (poet)|Sa’di]] (d. 1291), [[Hafiz Shirazi|Hafiz]] (d. 1389), and [[Jami]] (d. 1492), wrote poems replete with homoerotic allusions. The two most commonly documented forms were commercial sex with transgender young males or males enacting transgender roles exemplified by the [[köçek]]s and [[Sufi]] spiritual practices in which the practitioner admired the form of a beautiful boy in order to enter ecstatic states and glimpse the beauty of God.

====Ancient Mesopotamia====
[[Assyrian Empire#Middle Assyrian period|Middle Assyrian]] [[Assyrian law|Law Codes]] dating 1075 BC states: "If a man have(sic) intercourse with his brother-in-arms, they shall turn him into a eunuch."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Halsall|first1=Paul|title=The Code of the Assura|url=https://legacy.fordham.edu/halsall/ancient/1075assyriancode.asp|website=[[Internet History Sourcebooks Project]]|accessdate=16 November 2015|publisher=[[Fordham University]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Ancient Rome===
The "conquest mentality" of the [[ancient Romans]] shaped [[Homosexuality in ancient Rome|Roman homosexual practices]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Eva Cantarella]], ''Bisexuality in the Ancient World'' (Yale University Press, 1992, 2002, originally published 1988 in Italian), p. xi; Marilyn B. Skinner, introduction to ''Roman Sexualities'' (Princeton University Press, 1997), p. 11.&lt;/ref&gt; In the [[Roman Republic]], a [[Roman citizenship|citizen]]'s political liberty was defined in part by the right to preserve his body from physical compulsion or use by others;&lt;ref&gt;Thomas A.J. McGinn, ''Prostitution, Sexuality and the Law in Ancient Rome'' (Oxford University Press, 1998), p. 326.&lt;/ref&gt; for the male citizen to submit his body to the giving of pleasure was considered servile.&lt;ref&gt;Catharine Edwards, "Unspeakable Professions: Public Performance and Prostitution in Ancient Rome," in ''Roman Sexualities'', pp. 67–68.&lt;/ref&gt; As long as a man played the penetrative role, it was socially acceptable and considered natural for him to have [[Pathicus|same-sex relations]], without a perceived loss of his [[Sexuality in ancient Rome#Male sexuality|masculinity or social standing]].&lt;ref&gt;Amy Richlin, ''The Garden of Priapus: Sexuality and Aggression in Roman Humor'' (Oxford University Press, 1983, 1992), p. 225, and "Not before Homosexuality: The Materiality of the ''cinaedus'' and the Roman Law against Love between Men," ''Journal of the History of Sexuality'' 3.4 (1993), p. 525.&lt;/ref&gt; The bodies of citizen youths were strictly off-limits, and the ''[[Lex Scantinia]]'' imposed penalites on those who committed a sex crime ''([[stuprum]])'' against a [[Sexuality in ancient Rome#Sexuality and children|freeborn male minor]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Plutarch]], ''Moralia'' 288a; Thomas Habinek, "The Invention of Sexuality in the World-City of Rome," in ''The Roman Cultural Revolution'' (Cambridge University Press, 1997), p. 39; Richlin, "Not before Homosexuality," pp. 545–546. Scholars disagree as to whether the ''Lex Scantinia'' imposed the death penalty or a hefty fine.&lt;/ref&gt; Acceptable same-sex partners were males excluded from legal protections as citizens: [[Slavery in ancient Rome|slaves]], male [[Prostitution in ancient Rome|prostitutes]], and the ''[[Sexuality in ancient Rome#Pleasure and infamy|infames]]'', entertainers or others who might be technically free but whose lifestyles set them outside the law.

"Homosexual" and "heterosexual" were thus not categories of [[Sexuality in ancient Rome|Roman sexuality]], and no words exist in [[Latin]] that would precisely translate these concepts.&lt;ref&gt;Craig Williams, ''Roman Homosexuality'' (Oxford University Press, 1999, 2010), p. 304, citing Saara Lilja, ''Homosexuality in Republican and Augustan Rome'' (Societas Scientiarum Fennica, 1983), p. 122.&lt;/ref&gt; A male citizen who willingly performed [[Sexuality in ancient Rome#Os impurum|oral sex]] or received [[Sexuality in ancient Rome#Anal sex|anal sex]] was disparaged, but there is only limited evidence of legal penalties against these men, who were presumably "homosexual" in the modern sense.&lt;ref&gt;Williams, ''Roman Homosexuality'', pp. 214–215; Richlin, "Not before Homosexuality," ''passim''.&lt;/ref&gt; In courtroom and political rhetoric, charges of [[Sexuality in ancient Rome#Effeminacy and transvestism|effeminacy]] and passive sexual behaviors were directed particularly at "democratic" politicians ''([[populares]])'' such as [[Julius Caesar]] and [[Mark Antony]].&lt;ref&gt;Catharine Edwards, ''The Politics of Immorality in Ancient Rome'' (Cambridge University Press, 1993), pp. 63–64.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Roman law]] addressed the [[Sexuality in ancient Rome#The rape of men|rape of a male citizen]] as early as the 2nd century BC, when a ruling was issued in a case that may have involved a man of same-sex orientation. It was ruled that even a man who was "disreputable and questionable" had the same right as other citizens not to have his body subjected to forced sex.&lt;ref&gt;As recorded in a fragment of the speech ''De Re Floria'' by [[Cato the Elder]] (frg. 57 Jordan = [[Aulus Gellius]] 9.12.7), noted and discussed by Richlin, "Not before Homosexuality," p. 561.&lt;/ref&gt; A law probably dating to the [[Roman dictator|dictatorship]] of Julius Caesar defined rape as forced sex against "boy, woman, or anyone"; the rapist was subject to execution, a rare penalty in Roman law.&lt;ref&gt;Richlin, "Not before Homosexuality," pp. 562–563. See also ''Digest'' 48.5.35 [34] on legal definitions of rape that included boys.&lt;/ref&gt; A male classified as ''infamis'', such as a prostitute or actor, could not as a matter of law be raped, nor could a slave, who was legally classified as property; the slave's owner, however, could prosecute the rapist for property damage.&lt;ref&gt;Under the ''[[Lex Aquilia]]''. See McGinn, ''Prostitution, Sexuality, and the Law in Ancient Rome'', p. 314.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the [[Roman army]] of the Republic, [[Sexuality in ancient Rome#Sex in the military|sex among fellow soldiers]] violated the decorum against intercourse with citizens and was subject to harsh penalties, including death,&lt;ref&gt;McGinn, ''Prostitution, Sexuality and the Law in Ancient Rome'', p. 40.&lt;/ref&gt; as a violation of [[military discipline]].&lt;ref&gt;Sara Elise Phang, ''Roman Military Service: Ideologies of Discipline in the Late Republic and Early Principate'' (Cambridge University Press, 2008), p. 93.&lt;/ref&gt; The Greek historian [[Polybius]] (2nd century BC) lists [[desertion|deserters]], thieves, [[perjury|perjurers]], and "those who in youth have abused their persons" as subject to the ''[[fustuarium]]'', clubbing to death.&lt;ref&gt;[[Polybius]], ''[[The Histories (Polybius)|Histories]]'' [http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Polybius/6*.html#37 6.37.9] (translated as [[bastinado]]).&lt;/ref&gt; Ancient sources are most concerned with the effects of [[sexual harassment]] by officers, but the young soldier who brought an accusation against his superior needed to show that he had not willingly taken the passive role or prostituted himself.&lt;ref&gt;Phang, ''The Marriage of Roman Soldiers'', pp. 280–285.&lt;/ref&gt; Soldiers were free to have [[Sexuality in ancient Rome#Master-slave relations|relations with their male slaves]];&lt;ref&gt;Phang, ''The Marriage of Roman Soldiers'', p. 3.&lt;/ref&gt; the use of a fellow citizen-soldier's body was prohibited, not homosexual behaviors per se.&lt;ref&gt;Williams, ''Roman Homosexuality'', p. 112 ''et passim''.&lt;/ref&gt; By the late Republic and throughout the [[Roman Empire|Imperial period]], there is increasing evidence that men whose lifestyle marked them as "homosexual" in the modern sense served openly.&lt;ref&gt;Phang, ''The Marriage of Roman Soldiers'', [https://books.google.com/books?id=jyFdUxqYZ48C&amp;pg=PA285&amp;dq=%22more+tolerant+of+homosexual+relations+between+soldiers%22&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=xiu5TpHrGoSCtgfHkfGZBw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CC4Q6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=%22more%20tolerant%20of%20homosexual%20relations%20between%20soldiers%22&amp;f=false pp. 285–292.]&lt;/ref&gt;

Although Roman law did not recognize marriage between men, and in general Romans regarded marriage as a heterosexual union with the primary purpose of producing children, in the early Imperial period some male couples were celebrating [[Marriage in ancient Rome|traditional marriage rites]]. [[Juvenal]] remarks with disapproval that his friends often attended such ceremonies.&lt;ref&gt;Juvenal, ''Satire'' 2; Williams, ''Roman Homosexuality'', p. 28.&lt;/ref&gt; The emperor [[Nero]] had two marriages to men, once as the bride (with a [[freedman]] [[Pythagoras (freedman)|Pythagoras]]) and once as the groom. His consort [[Sporus]] appeared in public as Nero's wife wearing the regalia that was customary for the Roman empress.&lt;ref&gt;[[Suetonius]] ''Life of Nero'' 28–29; Williams, ''Roman Homosexuality'', p. 279ff.&lt;/ref&gt;

Apart from measures to protect the prerogatives of citizens, the prosecution of homosexuality as a general crime began in the 3rd century of the Christian era when male prostitution was banned by [[Philip the Arab]]. By the end of the 4th century, after the [[Roman Empire]] had come under [[Constantine the Great and Christianity|Christian rule]], passive homosexuality was [[Death by burning|punishable by burning]].&lt;ref&gt;Michael Groneberg, "Reasons for Homophobia: Three Types of Explanation," in ''Combatting Homophobia: Experiences and Analyses Pertinent to Education'' (LIT Verlag, 2011), p. 193.&lt;/ref&gt; "Death by sword" was the punishment for a "man coupling like a woman" under the [[Theodosian Code]].&lt;ref&gt;''Codex Theodosianus'' 9.7.3 (4 December 342), introduced by the sons of Constantine in 342.&lt;/ref&gt; Under [[Justinian]], all same-sex acts, passive or active, no matter who the partners, were declared contrary to nature and punishable by death.&lt;ref&gt;Groneberg, "Reasons for Homophobia," p. 193.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Congo ===
[[E. E. Evans-Pritchard]] recorded that in the past male [[Azande]] warriors in the northern [[Democratic Republic of the Congo|Congo]] routinely took on young male lovers between the ages of twelve and twenty, who helped with household tasks and participated in [[intercrural sex]] with their older husbands. The practice had died out by the early 20th century, after Europeans had gained control of African countries, but was recounted to Evans-Pritchard by the elders to whom he spoke.&lt;ref name=evanspritchard&gt;[[E. E. Evans-Pritchard|Evans-Pritchard, E. E.]] (December, 1970). Sexual Inversion among the Azande. American Anthropologist, New Series, 72(6), 1428–1434.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Feudal Japan ===
In feudal [[Japan]], homosexuality was recognized, between equals (bi-do), in terms of [[pederasty]] (wakashudo), and in terms of prostitution. The younger partner in a pederastic relationship often was expected to make the first move; the opposite was true in ancient Greece. In religious circles, same-sex love spread to the warrior ([[samurai]]) class, where it was customary for a boy in the ''[[wakashū]]'' age category to undergo training in the martial arts by apprenticing to a more experienced adult man. The man was permitted, if the boy agreed, to take the boy as his lover until he came of age; this relationship, often formalized in a "brotherhood contract",&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Leupp |first=Gary P. |title=Male Colors: The Construction of Homosexuality in Tokugawa Japan |publisher=University of California Press |year=1999 |pages=53–54 |isbn=0-520-20909-5 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=a6q-PqPDAmIC&amp;pg=PA53 }}&lt;/ref&gt; was expected to be exclusive, with both partners swearing to take no other (male) lovers. The [[Samurai]] period was one in which homosexuality was seen as particularly positive. Later when Japanese society became pacified, the middle classes adopted many of the practices of the warrior class.

=== Lesotho ===
Anthropologists [[Stephen O. Murray|Stephen Murray]] and [[Will Roscoe]] reported that women in [[Lesotho]] engaged in socially sanctioned "long term, erotic relationships" called ''motsoalle.''&lt;ref name=murrayroscoe&gt;{{Cite book|title=Boy Wives and Female Husbands: Studies of African Homosexualities |last=Murray |first=Stephen (ed.) |authorlink=Stephen O. Murray |coauthors=[[Will Roscoe|Roscoe, Will]] (ed.) |year=1998 |publisher=[[St. Martin's Press]] |location=New York |isbn=0-312-23829-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Papua New Guinea ===
In [[Papua New Guinea]], same-sex relationships were an integral part of the culture until the middle of the last century. The [[Etoro tribe|Etoro]] and [[Marind-anim]] for example, even viewed heterosexuality as wasteful and celebrated homosexuality instead. They believed that in sharing semen, they are sharing their life force, yet women simply wasted this force any time they didn't get pregnant after sex. In many traditional Melanesian cultures a prepubertal boy would be paired with an older adolescent who would become his mentor and who would "inseminate" him (orally, anally, or topically, depending on the tribe) over a number of years in order for the younger to also reach puberty.&lt;ref name=melanesia&gt;{{citation |title=Ritualized Homosexuality in Melanesia |first=Gilbert H. |last=Herdt |year=1984 |publisher=University of California Press |isbn=0-520-08096-3 |pages=128–136}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==LGBT-related laws by country or territory==

===Maps===
{|
|[[File:World laws pertaining to homosexual relationships and expression.svg|thumb|Right|800px|'''Laws regarding same-sex sexuality by country or territory'''
{{legend|#002255|Same-sex marriage}}
{{legend|#0066FF|Other type of partnership (or unregistered cohabitation)}}
{{legend|#00FFDE|Foreign same-sex marriages recognized}}
{{legend|#CCCCCC|No recognition of same-sex couples}}
{{legend|#decd87|Laws restricting freedom of expression and association}}
{{legend|#f9dc36|[[De jure]] penalty that is [[de facto]] not enforced}}
{{legend|#ec8028|Imprisonment}}
{{legend|#e73e21|Imprisonment (up to life sentence)}}
{{legend|#800000|Up to death}}
]]

[[File:LGBT rights at the UN.svg|thumb|Right|800px|'''[[LGBT rights at the United Nations]]'''
{{legend|#00FF00|'''Support'''&lt;br&gt;Countries which have signed a [[United Nations General Assembly|General Assembly]] declaration of LGBT rights and/or sponsored the [[United Nations Human Rights Council|Human Rights Council]]'s [http://www.pinknews.co.uk/2011/06/17/un-passes-gay-rights-resolution/ 2011 resolution on LGBT rights] ({{nowrap|'''96 members'''}})}}
{{legend|#FF0000|Oppose&lt;br&gt;Countries which signed [http://www.reuters.com/article/2008/12/18/us-un-homosexuality-idUSTRE4BH7EW20081218 a 2008 statement opposing LGBT rights] (initially 57 members, {{nowrap|now '''54 members'''}})}}
{{legend|#e0e0e0|Neither&lt;br&gt;Countries which, as regards the UN, have expressed neither official support nor opposition to LGBT rights ({{nowrap|'''44 members'''}}}}
{{legend|#000000|Non-UN member&lt;br&gt;Countries that are non-UN members ({{nowrap|'''14 non-UN members'''}})}}
]]

[[File:Homosexual "propaganda" laws by country or territory.svg|thumb|Right|800px|'''Homosexual "propaganda" laws by country or territory'''{{legend|#decd87|Homosexual "propaganda" laws by country or territory}}{{legend|#cccccc|Countries or territories that don't have homosexual "propaganda" laws}}]]

[[File:Decriminalization of Homosexuality by country or territory.svg|thumb|Right|800px|'''Decriminalization of same-sex sexual intercourse by country or territory'''
{{legend|#FFB380|1790–1799}}
{{legend|#C87137|1800–1819}}
{{legend|SaddleBrown|1820–1829}}
{{legend|Maroon|1830–1839}}
{{legend|#FF0000|1840–1859}}
{{legend|Tomato|1860–1869}}
{{legend|#FF6600|1870–1879}}
{{legend|Orange|1880–1889}}
{{legend|#FFFF00|1890–1909}}
{{legend|Khaki|1910–1919}}
{{legend|DarkKhaki|1920–1929}}
{{legend|Goldenrod|1930–1939}}
{{legend|GreenYellow|1940–1949&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;}}
{{legend|#00FF00|1950–1959}}
{{legend|#008800|1960–1969}}
{{legend|#00FFFF|1970–1979}}
{{legend|#0000FF|1980–1989}}
{{legend|#000080|1990–1999&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;}}
{{legend|#800080|2000–2009}}
{{legend|#FF00FF|2010-present&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;}}
{{legend|#cccccc|Same-sex sexual activity legal&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;}}
{{legend|#6C5353|Male same-sex sexual intercourse illegal}}
{{legend|#2B0000|Same-sex sexual intercourse illegal}}
&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;During [[World War II]], [[Nazi Germany]] annexed territory or established [[reichskommissariat]]s which extended [[Paragraph 175|Germany's laws against same-sex sexual intercourse]] to those territories and reichskommissariats. Same-sex sexual intercourse was previously legalized in the following countries or territories before German annexation or establishment of reichskommissariats: [[Bas-Rhin]] ([[LGBT rights in France|legal in 1791]]), [[Belgium]] ([[LGBT rights in Belgium|legal in 1795]]), [[Province of Belluno|Belluno]] ([[LGBT rights in Italy|legal in 1890]]), [[Friuli-Venezia Giulia]] ([[LGBT rights in Italy|legal in 1890]]), [[Haut-Rhin]] ([[LGBT rights in France|legal in 1791]]), [[Luxembourg]] ([[LGBT rights in Luxembourg|legal in 1795]]), [[Moselle]] ([[LGBT rights in France|legal in 1791]]), [[Kingdom of the Netherlands|Netherlands]] ([[LGBT rights in the Netherlands|legal in 1811]]), [[Nord (French department)|Nord]] ([[LGBT rights in France|legal in 1791]]), [[Pas-de-Calais]] ([[LGBT rights in France|legal in 1791]]), [[Second Polish Republic|Poland]] ([[LGBT rights in Poland|legal in 1932]]), and [[Trentino-Alto Adige/Südtirol]] ([[LGBT rights in Italy|legal in 1890]]). All countries and territories listed that where annexed or established into reichskommissariats by Nazi Germany during World War II where restored as independent countries or reincorporated into their previous countries during or after the war and thus re-legalized same-sex sexual intercourse in those areas.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;In May 1973, the [[Libyan Arab Republic]] annexed the [[Aouzou Strip]] from [[Chad]]. Libya's laws against same-sex sexual intercourse where thus extended to the annexed Aouzou Strip. In August 1987, during the [[Toyota War]] between the [[Great Socialist People's Libyan Arab Jamahiriya]] and Chad, Aouzou fell to the Chadian forces, only to be repelled by an overwhelming Libyan counter-offensive. The Aouzou dispute was concluded on February 3, 1994, when the judges of the [[International Court of Justice]] by a majority of 16 to 1 decided that the Aouzou Strip belonged to Chad. Monitored by international observers, the withdrawal of Libyan troops from the Strip began on April 15, 1994, and was completed by May 10, 1994. The formal and final transfer of the Aouzou Strip from Libya to Chad took place on May 30, 1994, when the sides signed a joint declaration stating that the Libyan withdrawal had been effected.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;During the [[Iraqi insurgency (2011–14)|Iraq Crisis]] / [[Iraqi Civil War (2014–present)|Iraqi Civil War]], from 2013 to present, parts of [[Iraq]] were taken over by the [[Islamic State of Iraq and the Levant|Islamic State]], enacting [[sharia]] and executing [[LGBT]] people. Territories, from 2014 to present, retaken by Iraqi government and [[LGBT rights in Iraq|thus re-legalized same-sex sexual intercourse in those areas]].&lt;br /&gt;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;Same-sex sexual intercourse was never criminalized in the following countries and territories: [[LGBT rights in Benin|Benin]], [[LGBT rights in Burkina Faso|Burkina Faso]], [[LGBT rights in Cambodia|Cambodia]], [[LGBT rights in the Central African Republic|Central African Republic]], [[LGBT rights in Chad|Chad]] (excluding [[Aouzou Strip]]), [[LGBT rights in France|Clipperton Island]], [[LGBT rights in the Republic of the Congo|Republic of the Congo]], [[LGBT rights in Côte d'Ivoire|Côte d'Ivoire]], [[LGBT rights in the Democratic Republic of the Congo|Democratic Republic of Congo]], [[LGBT rights in Djibouti|Djibouti]], [[LGBT rights in France|French Polynesia]], [[LGBT rights in France|French Southern and Antarctic Lands]], [[LGBT rights in Gabon|Gabon]], [[LGBT rights in Indonesia|Indonesia]], (excluding [[Aceh]], [[British Bencoolen]], [[Dutch East Indies|Netherlands East-Indies]] (prior to 1811), and [[South Sumatra]]) [[LGBT rights in Laos|Laos]], [[LGBT rights in Madagascar|Madagascar]], [[LGBT rights in Mali|Mali]], [[LGBT rights in France|Mayotte]], [[LGBT rights in France|New Caledonia]], [[LGBT rights in Niger|Niger]], [[LGBT rights in North Korea|North Korea]], [[LGBT rights in South Korea|South Korea]], [[LGBT rights in Vietnam|Vietnam]], and [[LGBT rights in France|Wallis and Futuna]].]]

[[File:Equalization of age of consent laws for same-sex couples by country or territory'.svg|thumb|Right|800px|'''[[Age of consent#By country or region|Equalization of age of consent laws for same-sex couples by country or territory]]'''
{{legend|#FFB380|1790–1829}}
{{legend|Maroon|1830–1839}}
{{legend|#FF0000|1840–1859}}
{{legend|Tomato|1860–1869}}
{{legend|#FF6600|1870–1879}}
{{legend|Orange|1880–1889}}
{{legend|#FFFF00|1890–1929}}
{{legend|Goldenrod|1930–1939}}
{{legend|GreenYellow|1940–1949&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;}}
{{legend|#00FF00|1950–1959}}
{{legend|#008800|1960–1969}}
{{legend|#00FFFF|1970–1979}}
{{legend|#0000FF|1980–1989}}
{{legend|#000080|1990–1999}}
{{legend|#800080|2000–2009}}
{{legend|#FF00FF|2010-present}}
{{legend|#cccccc|Equal age of consent laws for opposite and same-sex couples}}
{{legend|#2B0000|Unequal age of consent laws for same-sex couples}}
&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;During [[World War II]], [[Nazi Germany]] annexed territory or established [[reichskommissariat]]s which extended [[Paragraph 175|Germany's laws against same-sex sexual intercourse]] to those territories and reichskommissariats. Age of consent was previously equalized for same-sex couples in the following countries or territories before German annexation or establishment of reichskommissariats: [[Province of Belluno|Belluno]] ([[LGBT rights in Italy|legal in 1890]]), [[Friuli-Venezia Giulia]] ([[LGBT rights in Italy|legal in 1890]]), [[Second Polish Republic|Poland]] ([[LGBT rights in Poland|legal in 1932]]), and [[Trentino-Alto Adige/Südtirol]] ([[LGBT rights in Italy|legal in 1890]]). All countries and territories listed that where annexed or established into reichskommissariats by Nazi Germany during World War II where restored as independent countries or reincorporated into their previous countries during or after the war and thus re-legalized equal age of consent laws for same-sex couples in those areas.]]

[[File:World same-sex adoption laws.svg|right|thumb|800px|'''[[LGBT adoption#Legal status|Legal status of adoption by same-sex couples by country or territory]]'''
{{legend|#800080|Joint adoption allowed&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;}}
{{legend|#ba75ff|Second-parent adoption allowed&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;}}
{{legend|#e0e0e0|No laws allowing adoption by same-sex couples}}
&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;In Finland a law will come into force in 2017&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;In Estonia a law will come into force in 2016]]

[[File:Military service - sexual orientation.svg|thumb|Right|800px|'''[[Sexual orientation and military service|LGBT service in national militarizes by country or territory]]'''
{{legend|#408|All LGBT people can serve}}
{{legend|#03F|GBT men can serve}}
{{legend|#08F|LGB people can serve}}
{{legend|#0CF|GB men can serve}}
{{legend|#ff6600|Ambiguous or conditional policy}}
{{legend|#800|LGBT people are banned from serving}}
{{legend|#808080|No military}}
{{legend|#EEE|No data on LGBT service}}
]]

[[File:LGBT employment discrimination laws by country or territory.svg|thumb|Right|800px|'''[[List of anti-discrimination acts|Employment discrimination laws by sexual orientation and/or gender identity by country or territory]]'''
{{legend|#800080|Sexual orientation and gender identity: all employment}}
{{legend|#BA75FF|Sexual orientation with anti–employment discrimination ordinance and gender identity solely in public employment}}
{{legend|#0000ff|Sexual orientation: all employment}}
{{legend|Pink|Gender identity: all employment}}
{{legend|Thistle|Sexual orientation and gender identity: federal public employment and federal contractors}}
{{legend|#ff00ff|Sexual orientation and gender identity: public employment}}
{{legend|#00ffff|Sexual orientation: public employment}}
{{legend|#cccccc|No national-level employment laws covering sexual orientation and/or gender identity}}]]

[[File:LGBT constitutional discrimination laws by country or territory.svg|thumb|Right|800px|'''[[List of anti-discrimination acts|Constitutional discrimination laws by sexual orientation and/or gender identity by country or territory]]'''
{{legend|#0000ff|Sexual orientation covered}}
{{legend|Pink|Gender identity covered}}
{{legend|#cccccc|No national or local level constitutional discrimination laws covering sexual orientation and/or gender identity}}]]

[[File:LGBT hate crime laws by country or territory.svg|thumb|Right|800px|'''[[Hate crime#Hate crime laws|LGBT hate crime laws by country or territory]]'''
{{legend|#800080|Sexual orientation and gender identity hate crime laws}}{{legend|#0000ff|Sexual orientation hate crime laws}}{{legend|#cccccc|No LGBT hate crime laws}}]]

[[File:Incitement to hatred based on sexual orientation and gender identity prohibited by country or territory.svg|thumb|Right|800px|'''[[Hate speech#By country|Incitement to hatred based on sexual orientation and gender identity prohibited by country or territory]]'''
{{legend|#800080|Incitement to hatred based on sexual orientation and gender identity}}
{{legend|#0000ff|Incitement to hatred based on sexual orientation prohibited}}
{{legend|#cccccc|No prohibition on incitement to hatred based on sexual orientation and gender identity}}]]

[[File:Bans on LGBT conversion therapy for minors by country or territory.svg|thumb|Right|800px|'''Bans on LGBT conversion therapy for minors by country or territory'''
{{legend|#0000ff|Ban on LGBT conversion therapy for minors}}
{{legend|#cccccc|No prohibition LGBT conversion therapy for minors}}]]

[[File:LGBT immigration equality by country or territory.svg|thumb|Right|800px|'''[[Immigration equality#LGBT immigration issues|LGBT immigration equality by country or territory]]'''
{{legend|#0000ff|Recognition of same-sex couples in national immigration laws}}
{{legend|#cccccc|Unknown/ambiguous}}]]

[[File:Bans on same-sex unions by country.svg|thumb|Right|800px|'''[[Same-sex union legislation#Constitutional efforts to prohibit same-sex unions|Bans on same-sex unions by country or territory]]'''
{{legend|#cccccc|No specific prohibition of same-sex marriages or unions}}
{{legend|#ff9999|Statute bans same-sex marriage}}
{{legend|#ff0000|Constitution bans same-sex marriage}}
{{legend|#990000|Constitution bans same-sex marriage and equivalent/similar union}}]]

[[File:MSM Blood Donation Map.svg|thumb|Right|800px|'''[[Men who have sex with men blood donor controversy#Current situation|Blood donation policies for men who have sex with men by country or territory]]'''
{{legend|#ff9999|Men who have sex with men may donate blood; No deferral}}
{{legend|#ff0000|Men who have sex with men may donate blood; Temporary deferral}}
{{legend|#990000|Men who have sex with men may not donate blood; Permanent deferral&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;}}
{{legend|#DCDCDC|No Data}}
&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;No restriction in Israel and the United States of America if last MSM activity was before 1977.]]

[[File:Female partners of men who have sex with men blood ban by country.svg|thumb||thumb|Right|800px|'''[[Men who have sex with men blood donor controversy#Current situation|Blood donation policies for female sex partners of men who have sex with men by country or territory]]'''
{{legend|#000080|Female sex partners of men who have sex with men may donate blood; No deferral}}{{legend|#0000FF|Female sex partners of men who have sex with men may donate blood; Temporary deferral}}{{legend|#FF0000|Female sex partners of men who have sex with men may not donate blood; Permanent deferral}}{{legend|#DCDCDC|No Data}}]]

[[File:Laws concerning gender identity-expression by country or territory.svg|thumb||thumb|Right|800px|'''[[Legal aspects of transgenderism|Laws concerning gender identity-expression by country or territory]]'''
{{legend|#800080|Legal identity change}}
{{legend|#FF0000|No legal identity change}}
{{legend|#CCCCCC|Unknown/Ambiguous}}]]
|}

{{LGBT rights table Africa |world=yes}}
{{LGBT rights table Americas |world=yes}}
{{LGBT rights table Asia |world=yes}}
{{LGBT rights table Europe |world=yes}}
{{LGBT rights table Oceania |world=yes}}

==See also==
{{portal|LGBT|Human rights|Geography}}
{{div col||20em}}
* [[Buggery]]
* [[Civil union]]
* [[Heterosexism]]
* [[Homophobia]]
* [[Intersex human rights]]
* [[Movements for civil rights]]
* [[Transphobia]]
* [[List of human rights articles by country]]
* [[List of LGBT rights articles by region]]
* [[List of transgender-rights organizations]]
* [[LGBT people in prison]]
* [[Religion and homosexuality]]
* [[Same-sex marriage]]
* [[Sexual revolution]]
* [[Socialism and LGBT rights]]
* [[Societal attitudes toward homosexuality]]
* [[Status of same-sex marriage]]
* [[Yogyakarta Principles]]
{{div col end}}

==Notes==
{{Notelist}}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==
&lt;!--======================== {{No more links}} ============================
    | PLEASE BE CAUTIOUS IN ADDING MORE LINKS TO THIS ARTICLE. Wikipedia  |
    | is not a collection of links nor should it be used for advertising. |
    |                                                                     |
    |           Excessive or inappropriate links WILL BE DELETED.         |
    | See [[Wikipedia:External links]] &amp; [[Wikipedia:Spam]] for details.  |
    |                                                                     |
    | If there are already plentiful links, please propose additions or   |
    | replacements on this article's discussion page, or submit your link |
    | to the relevant category at the Open Directory Project (dmoz.org)   |
    | and link back to that category using the {{dmoz}} template.         |
    ======================= {{No more links}} =============================--&gt;
&lt;!--NOTE: Sodomylaws.org is not listed here as it is out-of-date for some regions. Do not use it as your only source for a country's legal status--&gt;
* [http://www.ilga.org/ International Lesbian and Gay Association]
** [http://old.ilga.org/Statehomophobia/ILGA_State_Sponsored_Homophobia_2012.pdf State-sponsored Homophobia report (2012 edition)]
** [http://old.ilga.org/Statehomophobia/ILGA_map_2012_A4.pdf Lesbian and Gay Rights in the World map (2012 edition)]
* {{DMOZ|/Society/Gay,_Lesbian,_and_Bisexual/Law|Gay, Lesbian, and Bisexual: Law}}
* [http://www.amnestyusa.org/lgbt-human-rights/country-information/page.do?id=1106576 Amnesty International USA: LGBT legal status around the world] — interactive map
* [http://www.gaylawnet.com/laws/laws.htm GayLawNet: Laws] — information by country
* [http://www.iglhrc.org/cgi-bin/iowa/home/index.html International Gay and Lesbian Human Rights Commission]
** [http://www.iglhrc.org/cgi-bin/iowa/content/takeaction/resourcecenter/index.html Resource links] — for researching legal information
*[[International Commission of Jurists]], [http://www.icj.org/dwn/database/Sexual%20Orientation,%20Gender%20Identity%20and%20Justice-%20A%20Comparative%20Law%20Casebook%5B1%5D.pdf Sexual Orientation, Gender Identity and Justice - A Comparative Law Casebook]
*[[United Nations]] [[Human Rights Council]], [http://www2.ohchr.org/english/bodies/hrcouncil/docs/19session/A.HRC.19.41_English.pdf Discriminatory laws and practices and acts of violence against individuals based on their sexual orientation and gender identity], an annual report
{{LGBT|rights=expanded}}
{{Law country lists}}
{{Particular human rights}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=November 2010}}

&lt;!--this is the correct interwiki --&gt;

{{commons category|LGBT rights by country or territory}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Lgbt Rights By Country Or Territory}}
[[Category:LGBT-related legislation| ]]
[[Category:Ageism]]
[[Category:Minimum ages]]
[[Category:Sex laws]]
[[Category:Sexuality and age]]
[[Category:Youth rights]]
[[Category:LGBT rights by region| ]]
[[Category:Law lists]]
[[Category:Human rights-related lists]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>