<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20121031131259|520742084" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="924166" pageid="924166" ns="0" title="LGBTQ rights by country or territory"><revisions><rev timestamp="2012-11-01T13:25:31Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{pp-semi-indef}}{{pp-move-indef}}
{{about|current LGBT rights around the world|historical and current movements to further LGBT rights|LGBT social movements}}
{{World homosexuality laws map|align=right|size=350px}}[[File:UN-SOGI-Updated.png|thumb|right|400px|Signatories to the [[Sexual orientation and gender identity at the United Nations|UN declaration on sexual orientation and gender identity]] are colored in blue and signatories to the opposing statement in green. Data are current as of June 2012.]]
Laws affecting '''lesbian, gay, bisexual, and transgender''' ([[LGBT]]) people vary greatly by country or territory&amp;mdash;everything from legal recognition of [[same-sex marriage]] or [[Same-sex union|other types of partnerships]], to the [[death penalty]] as punishment for same-sex romantic/sexual activity or identity. 

LGBT rights are [[human rights]] and [[civil rights]]. LGBT rights laws include, but are not limited to, the following: government recognition of same-sex relationships (such as via same-sex marriage or civil unions), [[LGBT adoption]], recognition of [[LGBT parenting]], [[anti-bullying legislation]] and student non-discrimination laws to protect LGBT children and/or students, [[immigration equality]] laws, anti-discrimination laws for employment and housing, hate crime laws providing enhanced criminal penalties for prejudice-motivated [[violence against LGBT people]], equal [[age of consent]] laws, and laws related to [[sexual orientation and military service]].

Anti-LGBT laws include, but are not limited to, the following: [[sodomy law]]s penalizing consensual same-sex sexual activity with fines, jail terms, or the death penalty, anti-'[[lesbian]]ism' laws, and higher ages of consent for same-sex activity.

In 2011, the [[United Nations Human Rights Council]] passed its first resolution recognizing LGBT rights, which was followed up with a report from the UN Human Rights Commission documenting violations of the rights of LGBT people, including [[hate crime]], criminalization of [[homosexuality]], and [[discrimination]]. Following up on the report, the UN Human Rights Commission urged all countries, which had not yet done so, to enact laws protecting basic LGBT rights.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2011/06/17/un-gay-rights-protection-resolution-passes-_n_879032.html |date=June 17, 2011 |agency=Associated Press |first=Frank |last=Jordans |title=U.N. Gay Rights Protection Resolution Passes, Hailed As 'Historic Moment' }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |publisher=United Nations |title=UN issues first report on human rights of gay and lesbian people |url=http://www.un.org/apps/news/story.asp?NewsID=40743 |date=15 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History of LGBT-related laws==
{{See also|Timeline of LGBT history|LGBT social movements|Sodomy law#History}}
{{LGBT rights}}
===Ancient India===
Throughout [[Hindu]] and [[Vedic]] texts there are many descriptions of saints, demigods, and even the Supreme Lord transcending gender norms and manifesting multiple combinations of sex and gender.&lt;ref&gt;ritiya-Prakriti: People of the Third Sex, p. 40&lt;/ref&gt; There are several instances in ancient   [[Indian epic poetry]] of same sex depictions and unions by gods and goddesses. There are several stories of depicting love between same sexes especially among kings and queens. [[Kamasutra]], the ancient [[Ancient India|Indian]] treatise on love talks about feelings for same sexes. [[Transsexuals]] are also venerated e.g. [[Lord Vishnu]] as [[Mohini]] and [[Lord Shiva]] as [[Ardhanarishwara]] (which means half woman).&lt;ref&gt;http://galva108.org/deities.html&lt;/ref&gt;

===Ancient Israel and the Near East===
The ancient [[Law of Moses]] (the [[Torah]]) forbids men lying with men (intercourse) in Leviticus 18 and gives a story of attempted homosexual rape in [[Book of Genesis|Genesis]] in the story of [[Sodom and Gomorrah]], the cities being soon destroyed after that. The death penalty was prescribed.

[[Assyrian Empire#Middle Assyrian period|Middle Assyrian]] [[Assyrian law|Law Codes]] dating 1075 BC states: "If a man have intercourse with his brother-in-arms, they shall turn him into a eunuch.{{citation needed|date=September 2011}}

===Ancient Rome===
The "conquest mentality" of the [[ancient Romans]] shaped [[Homosexuality in ancient Rome|Roman homosexual practices]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Eva Cantarella]], ''Bisexuality in the Ancient World'' (Yale University Press, 1992, 2002, originally published 1988 in Italian), p. xi; Marilyn B. Skinner, introduction to ''Roman Sexualities'' (Princeton University Press, 1997), p. 11.&lt;/ref&gt; In the [[Roman Republic]], a [[Roman citizenship|citizen]]'s political liberty was defined in part by the right to preserve his body from physical compulsion or use by others;&lt;ref&gt;Thomas A.J. McGinn, ''Prostitution, Sexuality and the Law in Ancient Rome'' (Oxford University Press, 1998), p. 326.&lt;/ref&gt; for the male citizen to submit his body to the giving of pleasure was considered servile.&lt;ref&gt;Catharine Edwards, "Unspeakable Professions: Public Performance and Prostitution in Ancient Rome," in ''Roman Sexualities'', pp. 67–68.&lt;/ref&gt; As long as a man played the penetrative role, it was socially acceptable and considered natural for him to have [[Sexuality in ancient Rome#Male-male sex|same-sex relations]], without a perceived loss of his [[Sexuality in ancient Rome#Male sexuality|masculinity or social standing]].&lt;ref&gt;Amy Richlin, ''The Garden of Priapus: Sexuality and Aggression in Roman Humor'' (Oxford University Press, 1983, 1992), p. 225, and "Not before Homosexuality: The Materiality of the ''cinaedus'' and the Roman Law against Love between Men," ''Journal of the History of Sexuality'' 3.4 (1993), p. 525.&lt;/ref&gt; The bodies of citizen youths were strictly off-limits, and the ''[[Lex Scantinia]]'' imposed penalites on those who committed a sex crime ''([[stuprum]])'' against a [[Sexuality in ancient Rome#Sexuality and children|freeborn male minor]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Plutarch]], ''Moralia'' 288a; Thomas Habinek, "The Invention of Sexuality in the World-City of Rome," in ''The Roman Cultural Revolution'' (Cambridge University Press, 1997), p. 39; Richlin, "Not before Homosexuality," pp. 545–546. Scholars disagree as to whether the ''Lex Scantinia'' imposed the death penalty or a hefty fine.&lt;/ref&gt; Acceptable same-sex partners were males excluded from legal protections as citizens: [[Slavery in ancient Rome|slaves]], male [[Prostitution in ancient Rome|prostitutes]], and the ''[[Sexuality in ancient Rome#Pleasure and infamy|infames]]'', entertainers or others who might be technically free but whose lifestyles set them outside the law.

"Homosexual" and "heterosexual" were thus not categories of [[Sexuality in ancient Rome|Roman sexuality]], and no words exist in [[Latin]] that would precisely translate these concepts.&lt;ref&gt;Craig Williams, ''Roman Homosexuality'' (Oxford University Press, 1999, 2010), p. 304, citing Saara Lilja, ''Homosexuality in Republican and Augustan Rome'' (Societas Scientiarum Fennica, 1983), p. 122.&lt;/ref&gt; A male citizen who willingly performed [[Sexuality in ancient Rome#Os impurum|oral sex]] or received [[Sexuality in ancient Rome#Anal sex|anal sex]] was disparaged, but there is only limited evidence of legal penalties against these men, who were presumably "homosexual" in the modern sense.&lt;ref&gt;Williams, ''Roman Homosexuality'', pp. 214–215; Richlin, "Not before Homosexuality," ''passim''.&lt;/ref&gt; In courtroom and political rhetoric, charges of [[Sexuality in ancient Rome#Effeminacy and transvestism|effeminacy]] and passive sexual behaviors were directed particularly at "democratic" politicians ''([[populares]])'' such as [[Julius Caesar]] and [[Mark Antony]].&lt;ref&gt;Catharine Edwards, ''The Politics of Immorality in Ancient Rome'' (Cambridge University Press, 1993), pp. 63–64.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Roman law]] addressed the [[Sexuality in ancient Rome#The rape of men|rape of a male citizen]] as early as the 2nd century BC, when a ruling was issued in a case that may have involved a man of same-sex orientation. It was ruled that even a man who was "disreputable and questionable" had the same right as other citizens not to have his body subjected to forced sex.&lt;ref&gt;As recorded in a fragment of the speech ''De Re Floria'' by [[Cato the Elder]] (frg. 57 Jordan = [[Aulus Gellius]] 9.12.7), noted and discussed by Richlin, "Not before Homosexuality," p. 561.&lt;/ref&gt; A law probably dating to the [[Roman dictator|dictatorship]] of Julius Caesar defined rape as forced sex against "boy, woman, or anyone"; the rapist was subject to execution, a rare penalty in Roman law.&lt;ref&gt;Richlin, "Not before Homosexuality," pp. 562–563. See also ''Digest'' 48.5.35 [34] on legal definitions of rape that included boys.&lt;/ref&gt; A male classified as ''infamis'', such as a prostitute or actor, could not as a matter of law be raped, nor could a slave, who was legally classified as property; the slave's owner, however, could prosecute the rapist for property damage.&lt;ref&gt;Under the ''[[Lex Aquilia]]''. See McGinn, ''Prostitution, Sexuality, and the Law in Ancient Rome'', p. 314.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the [[Roman army]] of the Republic, [[Sexuality in ancient Rome#Sex in the military|sex among fellow soldiers]] violated the decorum against intercourse with citizens and was subject to harsh penalties, including death,&lt;ref&gt;McGinn, ''Prostitution, Sexuality and the Law in Ancient Rome'', p. 40.&lt;/ref&gt; as a violation of [[military discipline]].&lt;ref&gt;Sara Elise Phang, ''Roman Military Service: Ideologies of Discipline in the Late Republic and Early Principate'' (Cambridge University Press, 2008), p. 93.&lt;/ref&gt; The Greek historian [[Polybius]] (2nd century BC) lists [[desertion|deserters]], thieves, [[perjury|perjurers]], and "those who in youth have abused their persons" as subject to the ''[[fustuarium]]'', clubbing to death.&lt;ref&gt;[[Polybius]], ''[[The Histories (Polybius)|Histories]]'' [http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Polybius/6*.html#37 6.37.9] (translated as [[bastinado]]).&lt;/ref&gt; Ancient sources are most concerned with the effects of [[sexual harassment]] by officers, but the young soldier who brought an accusation against his superior needed to show that he had not willingly taken the passive role or prostituted himself.&lt;ref&gt;Phang, ''The Marriage of Roman Soldiers'', pp. 280–285.&lt;/ref&gt; Soldiers were free to have [[Sexuality in ancient Rome#Master-slave relations|relations with their male slaves]];&lt;ref&gt;Phang, ''The Marriage of Roman Soldiers'', p. 3.&lt;/ref&gt; the use of a fellow citizen-soldier's body was prohibited, not homosexual behaviors per se.&lt;ref&gt;Williams, ''Roman Homosexuality'', p. 112 ''et passim''.&lt;/ref&gt; By the late Republic and throughout the [[Roman Empire|Imperial period]], there is increasing evidence that men whose lifestyle marked them as "homosexual" in the modern sense served openly.&lt;ref&gt;Phang, ''The Marriage of Roman Soldiers'', [http://books.google.com/books?id=jyFdUxqYZ48C&amp;pg=PA285&amp;dq=%22more+tolerant+of+homosexual+relations+between+soldiers%22&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=xiu5TpHrGoSCtgfHkfGZBw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CC4Q6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=%22more%20tolerant%20of%20homosexual%20relations%20between%20soldiers%22&amp;f=false pp. 285–292.]&lt;/ref&gt;

Although Roman law did not recognize marriage between men, and in general Romans regarded marriage as a heterosexual union with the primary purpose of producing children, in the early Imperial period some male couples were celebrating [[Marriage in ancient Rome|traditional marriage rites]]. [[Juvenal]] remarks with disapproval that his friends often attended such ceremonies.&lt;ref&gt;Juvenal, ''Satire'' 2; Williams, ''Roman Homosexuality'', p. 28.&lt;/ref&gt; The emperor [[Nero]] had two marriages to men, once as the bride (with a [[freedman]] [[Pythagoras (freedman)|Pythagoras]]) and once as the groom. His consort [[Sporus]] appeared in public as Nero's wife wearing the regalia that was customary for the Roman empress.&lt;ref&gt;[[Suetonius]] ''Life of Nero'' 28–29; Williams, ''Roman Homosexuality'', p. 279ff.&lt;/ref&gt;

Apart from measures to protect the prerogatives of citizens, the prosecution of homosexuality as a general crime began in the 3rd century of the Christian era when male prostitution was banned by [[Philip the Arab]]. By the end of the 4th century, after the [[Roman Empire]] had come under [[Constantine the Great and Christianity|Christian rule]], passive homosexuality was [[Death by burning|punishable by burning]].&lt;ref&gt;Michael Groneberg, "Reasons for Homophobia: Three Types of Explanation," in ''Combatting Homophobia: Experiences and Analyses Pertinent to Education'' (LIT Verlag, 2011), p. 193.&lt;/ref&gt; "Death by sword" was the punishment for a "man coupling like a woman" under the [[Theodosian Code]].&lt;ref&gt;''Codex Theodosianus'' 9.7.3 (4 December 342), introduced by the sons of Constantine in 342.&lt;/ref&gt; Under [[Justinian]], all same-sex acts, passive or active, no matter who the partners, were declared contrary to nature and punishable by death.&lt;ref&gt;Groneberg, "Reasons for Homophobia," p. 193.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Feudal Japan===
In feudal [[Japan]], homosexuality was recognized, between equals (bi-do), in terms of [[pederasty]] (wakashudo), and in terms of prostitution. The [[Samurai]] period was one in which homosexuality was seen as particularly positive. In Japan, the younger partner in a pederastic relationship was expected to make the first move; the opposite was true in ancient Greece. Homosexuality was later briefly criminalized due to Westernization.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gay-art-history.org/gay-history/gay-customs/japan-samurai-male-love/japan-samurai-homosexual-shudo.html The Beautiful Way of the Samurai] Native Tradition and Hellenic Echo&lt;/ref&gt;

===China===
Laws prohibiting homosexuality were also passed in [[China]]. ([[China]] neither adopted an Abrahamic religion nor was colonized, except for [[Hong Kong]] and [[Macau]] which were colonized with Victorian era social mores and maintain separate legal system from the rest of China.) Homosexuality was not decriminalized there until 1997.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://web.archive.org/web/19960101-re_/http://news.xinhuanet.com/english/2005-12/26/content_3970520.htm |title=Xinhua - English |publisher=Web.archive.org |accessdate=2010-01-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; Prior to 1997, homosexual in mainland China was found guilty included in a general definition under the vague vocabulary of hooliganism,  there are no specifically anti-homosexual laws.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = 晓飞 | first = 郭 | authorlink = | coauthors = | title = 中国法视野下的同性恋 | publisher = 知识产权出版社 | date = 2007-05-01 | location = | pages = | url = | doi = | id = | isbn = 978-7-80198-697-9 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==LGBT-related laws by country or territory==
[[File:Decriminalization of homosexuality by country.png|thumb|right|400px|Decriminalization of homosexuality by country]]
In modern times nine countries have no official heterosexist discrimination. They are Argentina, Belgium, Canada,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Adoptive parents.ca - Adoption in Nunavut |url=http://www.adoptiveparents.ca/nun_issues.shtml| title=Adoption in Nunavut}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Adoptive Parents.ca - Adoption in Yukon| url=http://www.adoptiveparents.ca/yk_issues.shtml| title=Adoption in Yukon}}&lt;/ref&gt; Iceland, Netherlands, Norway, Sweden, South Africa, and Spain. This full non-discrimination includes the rights of marriage and adoption. Portugal has also marriage rights for same-sex couples but this right does not include same-sex adoption. The Canadian Blood Services’ policy indefinitely defers any man who has sex with another man, even once, since 1977.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Canadian Blood Services - Société canadienne du sang |url=http://www.blood.ca/centreapps/internet/uw_v502_mainengine.nsf/page/Questions%20and%20Answers?OpenDocument#HT3 |title=Canadian Blood Services - Société canadienne du sang - Questions and Answers |publisher=Blood.ca |date= |accessdate=2010-06-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the U.S., mandated by federal law {{USPL|103|160}} ({{usc|10|654}}), the [[Military of the United States|U.S. armed forces]]’ policy on homosexuality in the military, commonly known as [[Don’t ask, don’t tell]], prohibited [[coming out]] ("a statement that a member is homosexual or bisexual" or anything that would reveal sexual orientation, i.e. talking about a boyfriend, girlfriend, or attractions) because it was considered tantamount to "a propensity or intent to engage in homosexual acts". More than 13,500 service members were discharged from the military under the 1993 law. However, the policy was repealed by Congress in December 2010. In the Senate, repeal passed by a majority of 63–33, including six Republicans voting in favour of gays serving openly in the military.  The repeal was effective September 20th, 2011. Also in the U.S., LGBT people face different laws for certain medical procedures than other groups. For example, gay men have been prohibited from [[giving blood]] since 1983,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/18827137/ |title=FDA says gay men still can’t donate blood - AIDS |publisher=MSNBC |date=23 May 2007 |accessdate=2010-01-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Resnick |first=Eric |url=http://www.gaypeopleschronicle.com/stories06/march/0317062.htm |title=Red Cross now seeks to allow gay blood donation |publisher=Gaypeopleschronicle.com |date=17 March 2006 |accessdate=2010-01-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[George W. Bush]]'s FDA guidelines barred them from being [[sperm donor]]s as of 2005, even though all donated sperm is screened for sexually-transmitted diseases.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.buzzle.com/editorials/6-7-2005-71220.asp FDA Recommends Barring Gay Men From Being Sperm Donors] By Linda Orlando&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.reproductivehealthctr.com/treatments_for_men_tdonor.htm American Society for Reproductive Medicine (ASRM) requires sperm donors be screened for all infections]&lt;/ref&gt;

{{LGBT rights table Africa |world=yes}}
{{LGBT rights table Americas |world=yes}}
{{LGBT rights table Asia |world=yes}}
{{LGBT rights table Europe |world=yes}}
{{LGBT rights table Oceania |world=yes}}

==See also==
{{Multicol}}
* [[Buggery]]
* [[Civil rights movement]]
* [[Civil union]]
* [[Heterosexism]]
* [[Homophobia]]
* [[Transphobia]]
{{Multicol-break}}
{{Portal box|LGBT|Human rights}}
* [[List of LGBT rights articles by region]]
* [[List of transgender-rights organizations]]
* [[LGBT people in prison]]
* [[Religion and homosexuality]]
* [[Same-sex marriage]]
* [[Sexual Revolution]]
* [[Socialism and LGBT rights]]
* [[Status of same-sex marriage]]
* [[The Yogyakarta Principles]]
{{Multicol-break}}
{{Multicol-end}}

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
&lt;!--======================== {{No more links}} ============================
    | PLEASE BE CAUTIOUS IN ADDING MORE LINKS TO THIS ARTICLE. Wikipedia  |
    | is not a collection of links nor should it be used for advertising. |
    |                                                                     |
    |           Excessive or inappropriate links WILL BE DELETED.         |
    | See [[Wikipedia:External links]] &amp; [[Wikipedia:Spam]] for details.  |
    |                                                                     |
    | If there are already plentiful links, please propose additions or   |
    | replacements on this article's discussion page, or submit your link |
    | to the relevant category at the Open Directory Project (dmoz.org)   |
    | and link back to that category using the {{dmoz}} template.         |
    ======================= {{No more links}} =============================--&gt;
&lt;!--NOTE: Sodomylaws.org is not listed here as it is out-of-date for some regions. Do not use it as your only source for a country's legal status--&gt;
* [http://www.ilga.org/ International Lesbian and Gay Association]
** [http://www.ilga.org/map/LGBTI_rights.jpg Map on LGBTI rights around the world] — 2008 version
** [http://www.ilga.org/statehomophobia/ILGA_State_Sponsored_Homophobia_2008.pdf State-sponsored Homophobia] — 2008 edition of worldwide survey of homosexuality laws
** [http://www.ilga.org/statehomophobia/ILGA_State_Sponsored_Homophobia_2009.pdf State-sponsored Homophobia] — 2009 edition of worldwide survey of homosexuality laws
* {{DMOZ|/Society/Gay,_Lesbian,_and_Bisexual/Law|Gay, Lesbian, and Bisexual: Law}}
* [http://www.amnestyusa.org/lgbt-human-rights/country-information/page.do?id=1106576 Amnesty International USA: LGBT legal status around the world] — interactive map
* [http://www.gaylawnet.com/laws/laws.htm GayLawNet: Laws] — information by country
* [http://www.iglhrc.org/cgi-bin/iowa/home/index.html International Gay and Lesbian Human Rights Commission]
** [http://www.iglhrc.org/cgi-bin/iowa/content/takeaction/resourcecenter/index.html Resource links] — for researching legal information
*[[International Commission of Jurists]], [http://www.icj.org/dwn/database/Sexual%20Orientation,%20Gender%20Identity%20and%20Justice-%20A%20Comparative%20Law%20Casebook%5B1%5D.pdf Sexual Orientation, Gender Identity and Justice - A Comparative Law Casebook]
*[[United Nations]] [[Human Rights Council]], [http://www2.ohchr.org/english/bodies/hrcouncil/docs/19session/A.HRC.19.41_English.pdf Discriminatory laws and practices and acts of violence against individuals based on their sexual orientation and gender identity], an annual report
{{LGBT|rights=expanded}}
{{Lists by country}}
{{Particular human rights}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=November 2010}}

&lt;!--this is the correct interwiki --&gt;

{{commons category|LGBT rights by country or territory}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Lgbt Rights By Country Or Territory}}
[[Category:LGBT-related legislation| ]]
[[Category:Sex laws]]
[[Category:LGBT rights by region| ]]
[[Category:Law lists]]
[[Category:Human rights-related lists]]

[[ca:Legislació sobre l'homosexualitat en el món]]
[[cs:Zákony týkající se homosexuality]]
[[cy:Deddfwriaeth ar gyfunrywioldeb yn ôl gwlad]]
[[de:Gesetze zur Homosexualität]]
[[el:Δικαιώματα ΛΟΑΤ ανά χώρα]]
[[es:Legislación sobre la homosexualidad en el mundo]]
[[eo:Samseksemo en la mondo]]
[[fa:وضعیت قانونی و حقوقی همجنس‌گرایی در کشورهای گوناگون]]
[[fr:Droits des personnes LGBT dans le monde]]
[[id:Hak LGBT menurut negara]]
[[it:Diritti LGBT nel mondo]]
[[he:זכויות להט"ב]]
[[hu:LMBT-törvények listája]]
[[ms:Hak LGBT mengikut negara]]
[[ja:国・地域別のLGBTの権利]]
[[pl:Sytuacja prawna i społeczna osób LGBT na świecie]]
[[pt:Legislação sobre a homossexualidade no mundo]]
[[ru:Права ЛГБТ в государствах и территориальных областях]]
[[sh:Prava LGBT osoba]]
[[fi:Homoseksuaalisuus ja laki]]
[[tr:Ülkelerine göre LGBT hakları]]
[[zh:LGBT法律]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>