<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20121031152620|520758103" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="18055330" pageid="18055330" ns="0" title="Victimisation"><revisions><rev timestamp="2012-10-31T15:28:19Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Victimisation''' ([[American and British English spelling differences#-ise.2C_-ize_.28-isation.2C_-ization.29|or]] '''victimization''') is the process of being victimised or becoming a [[wikt:victim|victim]]. Research that studies the process, rates, incidence, and prevalence of victimisation falls under the body of [[victimology]].

==Peer victimisation==
{{Main|Peer victimisation}}
Peer victimisation is the experience among children of being a target of the aggressive behaviour of other children, who are not siblings and not necessarily age-mates.&lt;ref name=twenty&gt;{{cite journal | author = Hawker D.S.J., Boulton M.J. | year = 2000 | title = Twenty years' research on peer victimisation and psychosocial maladjustment: a meta-analytic review of cross-sectional studies | url = | journal = Journal of Child Psychology and Psychiatry | volume = 41 | issue = 4| pages = 441–455 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Secondary victimisation==
'''Secondary victimisation''' (also known as '''post crime victimisation'''&lt;ref name=criminologytoday&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.prenhall.com/cjcentral/crimtoday4e/glossary/p.html |title=post-crime victimization or secondary victimization|work=Comprehensive Criminal Justice Terminology| publisher=Prentice Hall}}&lt;/ref&gt; or '''double victimisation'''&lt;ref name=Doerner&gt;{{cite book|last=Doerner|first=William|title=Victimology|year=2012|publisher=Elseiver, Inc.|location=Burlington, MA|isbn=978-1-4377-3486-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;) relates to further victimisation following on from the original victimisation.&lt;ref name=criminologytoday/&gt; For example, victim blaming, inappropriate post-assault behaviour or language by medical personnel or other organisations with which the victim has contact may further add to the victim's suffering.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Campbell R, Raja S |title=Secondary victimization of rape victims: insights from mental health professionals who treat survivors of violence |journal=Violence Vict |volume=14 |issue=3 |pages=261–75 |year=1999 |pmid=10606433 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Victims may also experience secondary victimisation by justice system personnel upon entering the criminal justice system. Victims will lose time, suffer reductions in income, often be ignored by bailiffs and other courthouse staff and will remain uninformed about updates in the case such as hearing postponements, to the extent that their frustration and confusion will turn to apathy and a declining willingness to further participate in system proceedings.&lt;ref name="Doerner"/&gt;

For example, rape is especially [[Social stigma|stigmatising]] in cultures with strong customs and [[taboos]] regarding sex and sexuality. For example, a rape victim (especially one who was previously a [[virgin]]) may be viewed by society as being "damaged." Victims in these cultures may suffer [[solitude|isolation]], be disowned by friends and family, be prohibited from marrying, or be divorced if already married.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nycagainstrape.org/survivors_factsheet_49.html#6 NYCagainstrape.org]&lt;/ref&gt;

The re-traumatisation of the [[sexual assault]], [[abuse]], or [[rape]] victim through the responses of individuals and institutions is an example of secondary victimisation. Secondary victimisation is especially common in cases of [[date rape drug|drug-facilitated]], [[date rape|acquaintance]], and [[statutory rape]].

==Revictimisation==
The term '''revictimisation''' refers to a pattern wherein the victim of abuse and/or crime has a statistically higher tendency to be victimised again, either shortly thereafter&lt;ref name="Finkelhor-2007"&gt;{{Cite journal  | last1 = Finkelhor | first1 = D. | last2 = Ormrod | first2 = RK. | last3 = Turner | first3 = HA. | title = Re-victimization patterns in a national longitudinal sample of children and youth | journal = Child Abuse Negl | volume = 31 | issue = 5 | pages = 479–502 | month = May | year = 2007 | doi = 10.1016/j.chiabu.2006.03.012 | pmid = 17537508 }}&lt;/ref&gt; or much later in adulthood in the case of abuse as a child.  This latter pattern is particularly notable in cases of sexual abuse.&lt;ref name=rad&gt;{{cite journal|title=Sexual Assault Revictimization |journal=Research &amp; Advocacy Digest |volume=6 |issue=2 |date=May 2004 |pages=1 |author=Janet Anderson|publisher=The Washington Coalition of Sexual Assault Programs}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=messman&gt;{{cite journal|doi=10.1016/0272-7358(96)00019-0|title=Child Sexual Abuse and its Relationship to Revictimization in Adult Women|author=Messman Terri L., Long Patricia J.|journal=Clinical Psychology Review |volume=16 |issue=5 |pages=397–420|year=1996}}&lt;/ref&gt;  While an exact percentage is almost impossible to obtain, samples from many studies suggest the rate of revictimisation for people with histories of sexual abuse is very high.  The vulnerability to victimisation experienced as an adult is also not limited to sexual assault, and may include [[Domestic violence|physical abuse]] as well.&lt;ref name=rad/&gt;

Reasons as to why revictimisation occurs vary by event type, and some mechanisms are unknown.  Revictimisation in the short term is often the result of risk factors that were already present, which were not changed or mitigated after the first victimisation; sometimes the victim cannot control these factors.  Examples of these risk factors include living or working in dangerous areas, chaotic familial relations, having an aggressive temperament, drug or alcohol usage and unemployment.&lt;ref name=rad/&gt;

Revictimisation of adults who were previously sexually abused as children is more complex.  Multiple theories exist as to how this functions.  Some scientists propose a maladaptive form of [[Learning theory (education)|learning]]; the initial abuse teaches inappropriate beliefs and behaviours that persist into adulthood.  The victim believes that abusive behaviour is "normal" and comes to expect it from others in the context of relationships, and thus may unconsciously seek out abusive partners or cling to abusive relationships.  Another theory draws on the principle of [[learned helplessness]].  As children, they are put in situations that they have little to no hope of escaping, especially when the abuse comes from a caregiver.&lt;ref name=messman/&gt;  One theory goes that this state of being unable to [[Fight-or-flight response|fight back or flee]] the danger leaves the last primitive option:  freeze, an off-shoot of [[Apparent death|death-feigning]].  In adulthood, this response remains, and some professionals have noted that victimisers sometimes seem to pick up subtle cues of this when choosing a victim.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author = Wheeler S., Book A.S., Costello K. | year = 2009 | title = Psychopathic traits and perceptions of victim vulnerability | url = | journal = Criminal Justice and Behavior | volume = 36 | issue = 6| pages = 635–648 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  This behaviour makes the victim an easy target, as they sometimes make little effort to fight back or even vocalise.  And after the fact, they often [[make excuses]] and [[Minimisation (psychology)|minimise]] what happened to them, sometimes never even reporting the assault to the authorities.

==Self-victimisation==
{{Main|Victim playing}}
Self-victimisation (or victim playing) is the fabrication of victimhood for a variety of reasons such to justify abuse of others, to manipulate others, a [[coping strategy]] or [[attention seeking]].

==Self-image of victimisation (victim mentality)==
{{Main|Victim mentality}}
Victims of [[abuse]] and [[Psychological manipulation|manipulation]] often get trapped into a [[self-image]] of victimisation. The psychological profile of victimisation includes a pervasive sense of helplessness, passivity, loss of control, [[pessimism]], negative thinking, strong feelings of [[guilt (emotion)|guilt]], [[shame]], [[Blame#Self-blame|self-blame]] and [[Depression (mood)|depression]]. This way of thinking can lead to hopelessness and despair.&lt;ref name=braiker&gt;Braiker, Harriet B., Who's Pulling Your Strings ? How to Break The Cycle of Manipulation (2006)&lt;/ref&gt;

==Rates of victimisation in United States==
Levels of criminal activity are measured through three major data sources: the [[Uniform Crime Reports]] (UCR), self-report surveys of criminal offenders, and the [[National Crime Victimization Survey]] (NCVS). However, the UCR and self-report surveys generally report details regarding the offender and the criminal offense; information on the victim is only included so far as his/her relationship to the offender, and perhaps a superficial overview of his/her injuries. The NCVS is a tool used to measure the existence of actual, rather than only those reported, crimes — the victimisation rate —&lt;ref name="NCVS"&gt;[http://wwww.ojp.usdoj.gov/bjs/cvict.htm National Crime Victimization Survey Official web site]&lt;/ref&gt; by asking individuals about incidents in which they may have been victimised. The National Crime Victimization Survey is the [[United States]]' primary source of information on crime victimisation.  Each year, data is obtained from a nationally represented sample of 77,200 households comprising nearly 134,000 persons on the frequency, characteristics and consequences of criminal victimisation in the United States.  This survey enables the (government) to estimate the likelihood of victimisation by [[Rape]] (more valid estimates were calculated after the surveys redesign in 1992 that better tapped instances of sexual assault, particularly of [[Date rape]]),&lt;ref name="Doerner"/&gt; [[robbery]], [[assault]], [[theft]], household burglary, and motor vehicle theft for the population as a whole as well as for segments of the population such as women, the elderly, members of various racial groups, city dwellers, or other groups."&lt;ref name="NCVS" /&gt; According to the [[Bureau of Justice Statistics]] (BJS), the NCVS reveals that, from 1994 to 2005, violent crime rates have declined, reaching the lowest levels ever recorded.&lt;ref name="NCVS" /&gt; Property crimes continue to decline.&lt;ref name="NCVS" /&gt;

==Victimisation in employment law==
Victimisation is a concept in [[employment law]]. It refers to situations where people are targeted with abuse, suffer detriment to their employment conditions or are dismissed as a result of bringing a claim for another form of discrimination. If an employee is "victimised" for complaining about another part of work, then a separate and independent claim for such treatment would arise.
If an employee has brought a discrimination claim, acted as a witness in someone else's claim or raised issues relating to potential discrimination, any action taken against them because of this will be unlawful.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title= This section provides general information on employment law in the UK|publisher=UK Film Council|year=2009|url= http://www.diversitytoolkit.org.uk/workinginfilm/employmentlaw/discriminationlaw/harassment/|accessdate=2009-10-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{columns-list|2|
*[[Blame]]
*[[Bullying]]
*[[Dehumanisation]]
*[[Destabilisation]]
*[[Just-world hypothesis]]
*[[Mobbing]]
*[[Race card]]
*[[Scapegoating]]
*[[United Kingdom employment discrimination law]] {{nb10}}
*[[Victim blaming]]
*[[Victim playing]]
*[[Victimisation Symptoms]]
}}

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
'''General'''
* Elias, Robert The Politics of Victimization: Victims, Victimology, and Human Rights (1986)
* Finkelhor, David Childhood Victimization: Violence, Crime, and Abuse in the Lives of Young People (Interpersonal Violence) (2008)
* Harris, Monica J. Bullying, Rejection, &amp; Peer Victimization: A Social Cognitive Neuroscience Perspective (2009)
* Hazler, Richard J. Breaking The Cycle Of Violence: Interventions For Bullying And Victimization (1996)
* Maher, Charles A &amp; Zins, Joseph &amp; Elias, Maurice Bullying, Victimization, And Peer Harassment: A Handbook of Prevention And Intervention (2006)
* Meadows, Robert J. Understanding Violence and Victimization (5th Edition) (2009)
*{{cite book |author=Lerner, Melvin J.; Montada, Leo |title=Responses to victimizations and belief in a just world |publisher=Plenum Press |location=New York |year=1998 |isbn=0-306-46030-0 |series=Critical issues in social justice }}
* Mullings, Janet &amp; Marquart, James &amp; Hartley, Deborah The Victimization of Children: Emerging Issues (2004)
* Westervelt, Saundra Davis Shifting The Blame: How Victimization Became a Criminal Defense (1998)
*{{cite journal |doi=10.1207/s15374424jccp3401_2 |author=Prinstein, Mitchell J., Cheah, Charissa S.L., Guyer, Amanda E. |title=Peer Victimization, Cue Interpretation, and Internalizing Symptoms: Preliminary Concurrent and Longitudinal Findings for Children and Adolescents |journal=Journal of Clinical Child and Adolescent Psychology |volume=34 |issue=1 |pages=11–24 |year=2005 |url=http://www.unc.edu/~mjp1970/Publications/Prinstein,%20Cheah,%20and%20Guyer%202005.pdf |format=PDF |pmid=15677277}}

'''Revictimisation'''
* Carlton, Jean Victim No More: Your Guide to Overcome Revictimization  (1995)
*{{cite book |author=Cho, Hyunkag |title=Effects of Arrest on Domestic Violence Incidence and Revictimization: Logistic Regression and Regression Time Series Analysis of the National Crime Victimization Survey from 1987 to 2003 |publisher=VDM Verlag Dr. Müller |year=2009 |isbn=3-639-12183-X }}
*{{cite journal |author=Cohen, Ruth |title=Sex Abuse: Revictimization Must Stop |journal=Clinical Psychiatry News |volume=37 |issue=3 |pages=18 |year=2009 |month=March |doi=10.1016/S0270-6644(09)70080-3 |url=http://www.clinicalpsychiatrynews.com/article/S0270-6644%2809%2970080-3/ |format=Editorial}}
*{{cite book |author=Dietrich, Anne Marie |title=When the Hurting Continues: Revictimization and Perpetration in the Lives of Childhood Maltreatment Survivors |publisher=VDM Verlag |year=2008 |isbn=3-639-02345-5 }}
*{{cite journal |doi=10.1300/J070v14n02_02 |author=Kogan SM |title=The role of disclosing child sexual abuse on adolescent adjustment and revictimization |journal=J Child Sex Abus |volume=14 |issue=2 |pages=25–47 |year=2005 |pmid=15914409 }}
*{{cite book |author=Pequegnat, Willo; Koenig, Linda Lee; Lynda Doll; O'Leary, Ann |title=From Child Sexual Abuse to Adult Sexual Risk: Trauma, Revictimization, and Intervention |publisher=American Psychological Association (APA) |year=2003 |isbn=1-59147-030-7 }}
*{{cite journal |author=Macy, R.J. |title=A coping theory framework toward preventing sexual revictimization  |journal=Aggression and Violent Behavior |volume=12 |issue=2 |pages=177–192 |year=2007 |month=March–April  |doi=10.1016/j.avb.2006.09.002 |url=http://www.sciencedirect.com/science?_ob=ArticleURL&amp;_udi=B6VH7-4MC0TPV-1&amp;_user=10&amp;_coverDate=04%2F30%2F2007&amp;_alid=1517834580&amp;_rdoc=1&amp;_fmt=high&amp;_orig=search&amp;_origin=search&amp;_zone=rslt_list_item&amp;_cdi=6059&amp;_sort=r&amp;_st=13&amp;_docanchor=&amp;view=c&amp;_ct=1&amp;_acct=C000050221&amp;_version=1&amp;_urlVersion=0&amp;_userid=10&amp;md5=80d7a499dae2f5bbc310ec4b8589d286&amp;searchtype=a}}
*{{cite journal |author=Messman-Moore, Terri L., Long, Patricia J. |year=2000 |month=May |title=Child Sexual Abuse and Revictimization in the Form of Adult Sexual Abuse, Adult Physical Abuse, and Adult Psychological Maltreatment |journal=Journal of Interpersonal Violence |volume=15 |issue=5 |pages=489 |doi=10.1177/088626000015005003 |url=http://jiv.sagepub.com/cgi/content/abstract/15/5/489}}
* Schiller, Ulene Addressing re-victimization of the sexually abused child: Training programme for state prosecutors working with sexually abused children during forensic procedures (2009)
*{{cite journal |doi=10.1016/S0270-6644(09)70146-8 |author=Wendling, Patrice |title=Revictimization far more likely for women |journal=Clinical Psychiatry News |volume=37 |issue=5 |pages=18 |year=2009 |month=May |url=http://www.clinicalpsychiatrynews.com/article/S0270-6644%2809%2970146-8/preview}}

==External links==
*[http://oxfordbibliographiesonline.com/display/id/obo-9780195396607-0051 "Fear of Crime and Perceived Risk." Oxford Bibliographies Online: Criminology.]

{{abuse}}
{{Bullying}}
{{Psychological manipulation}}

[[Category:Social psychology]]
[[Category:Abuse]]
[[Category:Bullying]]
[[Category:Victimology]]
[[Category:Labour law]]

[[ar:تضحية]]
[[de:Viktimisierung]]
[[fr:Victimisation]]
[[ru:Виктимизация]]
[[sr:Виктимизација]]
[[sv:Viktimisering]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>