<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20071002211756|161876647" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="584318" pageid="584318" ns="0" title="Political polarization"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-10-02T21:19:05Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Unreferenced|date=September 2006}}

In [[politics]], '''polarization''' is the process by which the public opinion divides and goes to the extremes.  It can also refer to when the extreme factions of a political party gain dominance in a party.  In either case [[moderate]] voices often find that they have lost power.  

In recent times, some Americans, such as ''[[American Demographics]]'' magazine editor [[John McManus]], have seen increasing polarization in the [[Politics of the United States|U.S. political system]].  Some point to [[Jim Jeffords]]' resignation from the [[United States Republican Party|Republican Party]] in 2001 because of his feelings that the party was becoming increasingly polarized and that moderate voices were getting shut out. President [[Bill Clinton]] said on the 9/18/06 ''[[The Daily Show|Daily Show]]'' that he thinks the current republican party believes in polarization.

Others, such as [[Constitution Party (United States)|Constitution Party]] analyst [[Michael Peroutka]], take the view that the U.S. political parties themselves are actually quite close in terms of actual policy and party leadership.  They say that political rhetoric is polarized in order to create some illusion of policy difference; however, in practice and action, both parties take a similar approach to government.  Examples include vast bipartisan and popular support for one side of various supposedly controversial issues; a majority of both major parties in Congress voted to cut taxes in [[2001]], to authorize use of force in [[Iraq]] in 2002, and to ban [[partial-birth abortion]] in [[2003]].  Additionally, since [[1948]], the Congress and the President--whether Democratic or Republican--have shown the same willingness to grow the size of the Federal Government.  Supporters of this theory also say that public opinion has not gone to the extreme; rather, both parties have come closer to the center.  Thus, for the average "[[centrist]]" voter, it is easier to decide which party/candidate is closest to them.

Mr. Peroutka's is a minority opinion{{Fact|date=February 2007}}; most Americans and most in the news media see a very real rift growing within the fabric of U.S. society, as was shown most dramatically through the [[United States presidential election, 2000|2000]] and [[United States presidential election, 2004|2004]] [[President of the United States|Presidential]] elections, when the vote was virtually half and half between the two sides. However, it may be argued that those election results merely confirm that both major parties are essentially equivalent and as such attract a nearly equal number of votes.

Perhaps the most disturbing sign of the schism has been the ominous division of the country into rigid geographic blocs, a phenomenon that has not been seen in America since the days leading up to the [[American Civil War|Civil War]] in the [[United States presidential election, 1852|1852]], [[United States presidential election, 1856|1856]], and [[United States presidential election, 1860|1860]] Presidential elections. 

An example of polarization was in [[Germany]] in the early years after the [[World War I|First World War]], when there was support for political parties on the [[extreme left]] such as the [[Spartacist League|Spartacists]], and also the [[extreme right]], such as the [[Nazi Party]].

[[Category:Political terms]]


{{poli-stub}}

[[nl:Polarisatie (conflict)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>