<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20050613092842|16415841" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="584318" pageid="584318" ns="0" title="Political polarization"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-07-13T18:42:48Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">In [[politics]], '''polarization''' is the process by which the public opinion divides and goes to the extremes.  It can also refer to when the extreme factions of a political party gain dominance in a party.  In either case [[moderate]] voices often find that they have lost power.  It may be one of the first steps to a [[civil war]].

In recent times, some Americans, such as [[American Demographics]] magazine editor [[John McManus]], have seen increasing polarization in the U.S. political system.  Some point to [[Jim Jeffords]]' resignation from the [[United States Republican Party|Republican Party]] in 2001 because of his feelings that the party was becoming increasingly polarized and that moderate voices were getting shut out.  Republicans point to the campaign of [[John Kerry]] in 2004 as evidence that the [[United States Democratic Party|Democratic Party]] is also becoming increasingly polarized.

Others, such as [[Constitution Party]] analyst [[Michael Peroutka]], take the view that the U.S. political parties themselves are actually quite close in terms of actual policy and party leadership.  They say that political rhetoric is polarized in order to create some illusion of policy difference; however, in practice and action, both parties take a similar approach to government.  Examples include vast bipartisan and popular support for one side of various supposedly controversial issues; a majority of both major parties in Congress voted to cut taxes in [[2001]], to authorize use of force in [[Iraq]] in 2002, and to ban [[partial-birth abortion]] in [[2003]].  Additionally, since [[1948]], the Congress and the President--whether Democratic or Republican--have shown the same willingness to grow the size of the Federal Government.  Supporters of this theory also say that public opinion has not gone to the extreme; rather, both parties have come closer to the center.  Thus, for the average "[[centrist]]" voter, it is easier to decide which party/candidate is closest to them.

{{poli-stub}} 
[[Category:Political terms]]

[[nl:Polarisatie (conflict)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>