<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20080910212715|237579372" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="584318" pageid="584318" ns="0" title="Political polarization"><revisions><rev timestamp="2008-11-11T13:27:16Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">In [[politics]], '''polarization''' is the process by which the public opinion divides and goes to the extremes.  It can also refer to when the extreme factions of a political party gain dominance in a party.  In either case [[moderate]] voices often find that they have lost power.  

==Definitions of polarization==
The term "polarization" comes from [[political science]].  There, it is a measure of the electorate's ''response'' to a political figure or position;&lt;ref name="heth-paper"&gt;{{cite paper |last=Hetherington |first=Marc J. |coauthors=Bruce I. Oppenheimer |url=http://www.polisci.wisc.edu/epsteinconference/Hetherington.pdf |title=The Discounted Voter: Polarization at the Congressional District Level |publisher=[[University of Wisconsin]] Epstein Conference |date=April 2007|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt; it is not an assessment of, or a value judgment upon, a political figure.  It does not mean that a political figure is necessarily unelectable.&lt;ref name="jacob-book-7"&gt;Jacobson, ''A Divider, Not a Uniter'', pp. 7, 9.&lt;/ref&gt;  Political figures can receive a polarized response from the public through actions of their own,&lt;ref name="jacob-book"&gt;{{cite book | last=Jacobson | first=Gary C. | authorlink=Gary Jacobson | title=A Divider, Not a Uniter: George W. Bush and the American People — The 2006 Election and Beyond | publisher=[[Pearson Longman]] | year=2008 | isbn=978-0-205-52974-2}} pp. 14–15.&lt;/ref&gt; through historical trends or accidents,&lt;ref name="jacob-book"/&gt; or due to external forces such as [[media bias]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite paper | last=Bernhardt | first=Dan | coauthors=Stefan Krasa, Mattias Polborn | url=http://works.bepress.com/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1012&amp;context=polborn | title=Political Polarization and the Electoral Effects of Media Bias | work=CESifo Working Paper Series No. 1798 | publisher=[[Ludwig Maximilian University of Munich]]/[[Ifo Institut für Wirtschaftsforschung]] | date=January 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;  

Political scientists principally measure polarization in two ways.&lt;ref&gt;Jacobson, ''A Divider, Not a Uniter'', pp. 35–36.&lt;/ref&gt;  One is "plain" or generic polarization, often referred to as '''popular polarization''',&lt;ref name="heth-paper"/&gt; which happens when opinions diverge towards poles of distribution or intensity.&lt;ref name="heth-paper"/&gt;  Political scientists several kinds of metrics to measure popular polarization, such as the [[American National Election Studies]]' "feeling thermometer" polls, which measure the degree of opinion about a political figure.&lt;ref name="sulfaro-paper"&gt;{{cite journal |last=Sulfaro |first=Valerie A. |year=2007 |month=September |title=Affective evaluations of first ladies: a comparison of Hillary Clinton and Laura Bush | url=http://www.accessmylibrary.com/coms2/summary_0286-33219066_ITM | format=Fee or registration required | journal=[[Presidential Studies Quarterly]] |volume=37 |issue=3 |pages=486–514 |doi=10.1111/j.1741-5705.2007.02608.x}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="burrell-paper"&gt;{{cite journal |last=Burrell |first=Barbara |year=2000 |month=October |title=Hillary Rodham Clinton as first lady: the people’s perspective |journal=[[The Social Science Journal]] |volume=37 |issue=4 |pages=529–546 |doi=10.1016/S0362-3319(00)00094-X}}&lt;/ref&gt;  

The other form that political scientists examine is '''partisan polarization''', which happens when support for a political figure or position differentiates itself along [[political party]] lines.&lt;ref name="jacob-book"/&gt;  

Popular media definitions and uses of "polarization" tend to be looser.  

==Polarization in United States politics==
In recent times, some Americans, such as ''[[American Demographics]]'' magazine editor [[John McManus]], have seen increasing polarization in the [[Politics of the United States|U.S. political system]].  Some point to [[Jim Jeffords]]' resignation from the [[United States Republican Party|Republican Party]] in 2001 because of his feelings that the party was becoming increasingly polarized and that moderate voices were getting shut out. Former President [[Bill Clinton]] said on the 9/18/06 ''[[The Daily Show|Daily Show]]'' that he thinks the Republican Party believes in polarization. 

Others, such as [[Constitution Party (United States)|Constitution Party]] analyst [[Michael Peroutka]], take the view that the U.S. political parties themselves are actually quite close in terms of actual policy and party leadership.  They say that political rhetoric is polarized in order to create some illusion of policy difference; however, in practice and action, both parties take a similar approach to government.  Examples include vast bipartisan and popular support for one side of various supposedly controversial issues; a majority of both major parties in Congress voted to cut taxes in 2001, to authorize use of force in [[Iraq]] in 2002, and to ban [[partial-birth abortion]] in 2003.  Additionally, since 1948, the Congress and the President--whether Democratic or Republican--have shown the same willingness to grow the size of the Federal Government.  Supporters of this theory also say that public opinion has not gone to the extreme; rather, both parties have come closer to the center.  Thus, for the average "[[centrist]]" voter, it is easier to decide which party/candidate is closest to them.  This can be demonstrated in both the [[United States presidential election, 2000|2000]] and [[United States presidential election, 2004|2004]] [[President of the United States|Presidential]] elections, when the vote was virtually half and half between the two sides. Essentially, both parties are equally desirable to average Americans.

==Polarization in other national politics==
An example of polarization was in [[Germany]] in the early years after the [[World War I|First World War]], when there was support for political parties on the [[extreme left]] such as the [[Spartacist League|Spartacists]], and also the [[extreme right]], such as the [[Nazi Party]].

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

[[Category:Political terms]]

[[nl:Polarisatie (conflict)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>