<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20220427160112|1084961459" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="70215221" pageid="70215221" ns="0" title="Dialect discrimination"><revisions><rev timestamp="2022-04-27T17:10:56Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:Cartoon Dialect Discrimnation.jpeg|thumb|&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |date=2021-02-22 |title=Accents, Dialects, and Discrimination {{!}} The Walrus |url=https://thewalrus.ca/accents-dialects-and-discrimination/ |access-date=2022-04-07 |language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;]] --&gt;{{Discrimination sidebar}}

'''Dialect discrimination''' refers to the unequal treatment of those whose [[dialect]] contains linguistic features identifying them with a certain geographical or [[social group]]. One may experience dialect discrimination in a number of settings, but this type of discrimination may be most prominent in the [[workplace]]. While there is not enough data to know how often it occurs, it is possible that a number of people may experience dialect discrimination during the [[Job application|job application process]], as employers strive for their staff to utilize a more “[[standardized]]” or “neutral” form of speaking. Dialect discrimination may also be present in [[education]] and [[politics]]. Children in school whose dialect does not closely resemble the standard form of speaking may not receive the same [[education]]. Likewise, those who speak in a manner that is not associated with the common dialect of an area or country may be [[slandered]] or even unable to vote in politics. It is disputed whether or not this form of [[discrimination]] is prohibited by the [[Equal Employment Opportunity Commission|EEOC]].

== Discrimination ==
Discrimination can be defined as the unfair treatment of a person or a group based on something for which they identify.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Discrimination: What it is, and how to cope |url=https://www.apa.org/topics/racism-bias-discrimination/types-stress |access-date=2022-04-07 |website=www.apa.org}}&lt;/ref&gt; Discrimination is often seen as categorical. Some categorical examples of this include, but are not limited to; [[Race (human categorization)|race]], [[gender]], age or [[sexual orientation]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Discrimination: What it is, and how to cope |url=https://www.apa.org/topics/racism-bias-discrimination/types-stress |access-date=2022-04-07 |website=www.apa.org}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although it is not clear why humans practice discrimination, many researchers believe that it may stem from fear and misunderstanding of something, like a dialect, that others may not resonate with. This article will mainly focus on the discrimination that is dialect and language-based.

== How specific language discrimination is linked ==
[[Language]] discrimination is when someone is treated/looked at differently than others because of their native language. This kind of discrimination is viewed on a national level and is illegal.“Title VII of the [[Civil Rights Act of 1964]] prohibits an employer from discriminating against any individual with respect to his or her compensation, terms, condition, or privileges of employment because of that individual’s national origin…” (Marina 347). Other types of discrimination like dialect or accent discrimination are considered to be on a more federal level and not considered national.

Language discrimination is not technically seen as part of the EEOC, other than the category of national origin. Considering this, punishment for discrimination that is seen within the category that would be considered “Language” can be minimal but could stretch as large as jail time.

=== Examples ===
Workplace: A really good example of dialect discrimination would be workplace dialect discrimination. A lot of times individuals will not be hired for a job because of the way he or she speaks or sounds. And another thing that is difficult and at the Forefront of media, today is the fact that if your primary language is not [[English language|English]] and you are trying to get hired by an English-speaking company many companies will not hire you because of this. Although this is seen as illegal in many states it is still a very wide reason why some people do not get jobs. The employer may not tell the employee that that is the reason he or she is not being hired but usually, it is the underlying cause.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |first=Midwest New Media, LLC- |title=Language Discrimination - Workplace Fairness |url=https://www.workplacefairness.org/language-discrimination |access-date=2022-04-07 |website=workplacefairness |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Language Discrimination |url=https://legalaidatwork.org/factsheet/language-discrimination/ |access-date=2022-04-07 |website=Legal Aid at Work |language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Schools: Dialect Discrimination can be found is in schools. Something that a lot of families struggle with is they will put their child in a school that is primarily English-speaking and the child will get discriminated against and not get the same tools that other students are getting as far as learning goes because of the way they speak or sound. A lot of times [[Hispanic]] languages get looked down on in primary education schools. Because of this a lot of Hispanic immersion schools have been created however language and dialect discrimination is the root cause.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=Álvarez |first=Brenda |title=Linguistic Discrimination Still Lingers in Many Classrooms {{!}} NEA |url=https://www.nea.org/advocating-for-change/new-from-nea/linguistic-discrimination-still-lingers-many-classrooms |access-date=2022-04-07 |website=www.nea.org |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Political: There is dialect discrimination in politics. A lot of times candidates running for a government position are discriminated against because of the way they sound. A lot of time [[Society]] will label a political figure as undereducated based on the way that they sound. Obviously, this is a problem and is categorized as discrimination ended up itself. Also, citizens have been banned and can be denied the right to vote based on whether or not they passed a [[literacy test]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Language discrimination in politics |url=http://encyclopedia.uia.org/en/problem/145782}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== References ==
{{reflist}}

{{Discrimination}}

[[Category:Prejudice and discrimination by type]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>