<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20031031144336|1653121" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="162173" pageid="162173" ns="0" title="Islamophobia"><revisions><rev timestamp="2003-10-31T15:28:12Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Islamophobia''' is the fear and hatred of [[Muslim]]s or [[Islamic culture]] in general.  Given the strong association between [[Arab]]s and the religion of [[Islam]], Islamophobia often expresses itself as a form of [[anti-Arab]] racism, though not all Arabs are Muslim and the majority of Muslims are not in fact Arab.

The term itself is of [[neologism|recent coinage]], and reflects the influence of such [[1990s]] movements as [[multi-culturalism]] and [[identity politics]].  It most often appears in discourse on the condition of [[immigrant]] Muslims living as [[minority|minorities]] in [[Western countries|the West]].

However, its origin dates back to the [[Crusades]]. It has remained present in [[Europe]] for many centuries.

In [[France]], a more recent factor contributing to Islamophobia was the occupation of [[Algeria]] and systematic [[human rights violation]]s such as [[torture]] carried out by the occupiers, since fear and hatred of victims is a natural part of any colonization process.

Another factor driving Islamophobia is the rise of [[anti-Western]] [[Islamism|Islamist]] movements, which have either come to power outright in some countries ([[Iran]], [[Sudan]], post-Soviet-era [[Afghanistan]]), or else exerted a strong influence on government policy in others ([[Saudi Arabia]], [[Pakistan]]).

It is sometimes claimed that the increasing fraction of [[North American]]s and [[European]]s who identify themselves as Muslims is a factor driving Islamophobia. However, Islamophobia (or any other racist fear) is often present among populations with extremely few Muslims (or other perceived minority).

Perhaps the most important factor shaping the present wave of Islamophobia ([[as of 2003]]), though, is the extremely large and disproportionate [[media]] coverage given to Islamist-inspired [[terrorism]], for example, to the [[September 11 Terrorist Attack]]s, while relatively little [[media]] coverage is given to equivalent acts of [[terrorism]] by other groups or [[nation-state]]s.  As a result, Islamophobia is characterized by the belief that Muslims are religious fanatics, have violent tendencies towards non-Muslims, and reject as directly opposed to Islam such concepts as [[equality]], [[tolerance]], and [[democracy]].

Though such characteristics do in fact apply to most Islamist movements, many people mistakenly believe that most Muslims are Islamist, when in fact the Islamist movement is only a minority position.  How big of a minority, though, is a matter of intense controversy.  The American scholar [[Daniel Pipes]], for example, has been branded an Islamophobe and bigot by the [[Council on American-Islamic Relations]] for suggesting that as many as 10% of Muslims have Islamist sympathies[http://www.danielpipes.org/article/954].

Recently there have been several efforts by non-Muslims to combat Islamophobia.  In the wake of September 11, for example, a few non-Muslim women practiced [[hijab]] in a show of solidarity with their Muslim counterparts, who it was feared would be particularly vulnerable for reprisal given their distinctive dress.  Non-Muslims also helped form community watches to protect [[mosque]]s from attack.

In [[Israel]], there are many organizations working to end anti-Muslim bias among Jews, as well as to end [[anti-Semitism|hatred of Jews]] among Arabs. See the entry on [[projects working for peace among Israelis and Arabs]].

==Examples of Islamophobia==

* [[Ann Coulter]]: "We should invade their countries, kill their leaders and convert them to Christianity."[http://www.nationalreview.com/coulter/coulter091301.shtml]
* a [[news wire]] photo from the time of the September 11 attacks showed the words "kill arabs" written in the dust of one of the collapsed [[World Trade Center]] towers

See also: [[anti-Islamism]], [[dhimmi]], [[persecution of Muslims]], [[persecution of Christians]], [[Islam and anti-Semitism]]

==External Links==
* example uses of the term by Muslim writer Faisal Bodi:
** [[The Guardian]]: [http://www.guardian.co.uk/comment/story/0,3604,715150,00.html ''Call this monster by its name'']
** [[The Guardian]]: [http://www.guardian.co.uk/comment/story/0,3604,528063,00.html ''Old hatred, new style'']
* [[The Guardian]]: [http://www.guardian.co.uk/g2/story/0,3604,719159,00.html ''To say that jihadis are a threat is not Islamophobic'']</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>