<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20101116133057|397098778" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="162173" pageid="162173" ns="0" title="Islamophobia"><revisions><rev timestamp="2010-11-17T17:16:21Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{sprotect|small=yes}}
:''This article is about discrimination. For neutral criticism, see [[Criticism of Islam]]. For criticism of political Islam, see [[Criticism of Islamism]]''
{{Discrimination sidebar}}
{{Criticism of Islam sidebar}}
'''Islamophobia''' is [[prejudice]] against, or hatred or fear of [[Islam]] or [[Muslim]]s.&lt;ref&gt;"''[http://books.google.com/books?id=c8Xf5N8ExXIC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=teaching+the+global+dimensions&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=w5TgTLnRHIuChQeepNSJDQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CC0Q6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=teaching%20the%20global%20dimensions&amp;f=false Teaching the Global Dimension]"'' David Hick, Cathie Holden (2007). P.140. &lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
* Sandra Fredman, ''Discrimination and Human Rights'', Oxford University Press, ISBN 0-19-924603-3, p.121.
* Yvonne Yazbeck Haddad, ''Muslims in the West: From Sojourners to Citizens'', Oxford University Press, ISBN 0-19-514806-1, p.19
* ''Islamophobia: A Challenge for Us All'', [[Runnymede Trust]], 1997, p. 1, cited in Quraishi, Muzammil. ''Muslims and Crime: A Comparative Study'', Ashgate Publishing Ltd., 2005, p. 60. ISBN 0-7546-4233-X. Early in 1997, the Commission on [[British Muslims]] and Islamophobia, at that time part of the Runnymede Trust, issued a consultative document on Islamophobia under the chairmanship of Professor Gordon Conway, [[Vice-Chancellor]] of the [[University of Sussex]]. The final report, ''Islamophobia: A Challenge for Us All'', was launched in November 1997 by [[Home Secretary]] [[Jack Straw]]&lt;/ref&gt;
The term seems to date back to the late 1980s,&lt;ref&gt;''Islamophobia: A Challenge for Us All'', [[Runnymede Trust]], 1997, p. 1, cited in Quraishi, Muzammil. ''Muslims and Crime: A Comparative Study'', Ashgate Publishing Ltd., 2005, p. 60; [[Kofi Annan|Annan, Kofi]]. [http://www.un.org/News/Press/docs/2004/sgsm9637.doc.htm "Secretary-General, addressing headquarters seminar on confronting Islamophobia"], [[United Nations]] press release, December 7, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;
but came into common usage after the [[September 11, 2001 attacks]] in the United States to refer to types of political dialogue that appeared prejudicially resistant to [[pro-Islamic]] argument.&lt;ref&gt;
* Casciani, Dominic. [http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/3768327.stm "Islamophobia pervades UK - report"], BBC News, June 2, 2004.
* Rima Berns McGowan writes in ''Muslims in the Diaspora'' (University of Toronto Press, 1991, p. 268) that the term "Islamophobia" was first used in an unnamed American periodical in 1991.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1997, the British [[Runnymede Trust]] defined Islamophobia as the "dread or hatred of Islam and therefore, to the fear and dislike of all Muslims," stating that it also refers to the practice of [[Discrimination|discriminating]] against Muslims by excluding them from the economic, social, and public life of the nation. It includes the perception that Islam has no values in common with other cultures, is inferior to the West and is a violent [[political ideology]] rather than a [[religion]].&lt;ref name=Runnymede5&gt;Runnymede 1997, p. 5, cited in Quraishi 2005, p. 60.&lt;/ref&gt; Professor Anne Sophie Roald writes that steps were taken toward official acceptance of the term in January 2001 at the "Stockholm International Forum on Combating Intolerance", where Islamophobia was recognized as a form of intolerance alongside [[Xenophobia]] and [[Antisemitism]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|first=Anne Sophie |last=Roald |title=New Muslims in the European Context: The Experience of Scandinavian Converts |page=53 |publisher=Brill |year=2004}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A perceived trend of increasing  "Islamophobia" during the 2000s has been attributed by some commentators to the September 11 attacks,&lt;ref&gt;Benn, Jawad (2004) p. 111&lt;/ref&gt; while others associate it with the rapidly growing
Muslims populations in the Western world, especially in [[Islam in Western Europe|Western Europe]], due to both [[immigration to Europe|immigration]] and high [[fertility rate]].&lt;ref name="Vertovec"&gt;Steven Vertovec, "Islamophobia and Muslim Recognition in Britain"; in Haddad (2002) pp. 32-33&lt;/ref&gt;
In May 2002, the [[European Monitoring Centre on Racism and Xenophobia]] (EUMC), a [[European Union]] watchdog, released a report entitled "Summary report on Islamophobia in the EU after 11 September 2001", which described an increase in Islamophobia-related incidents in European member states post-9/11.&lt;ref&gt;See:
*Greaves (2004) p. 133
*Allen, Chris; Nielsen, Jorgen S.; Summary report on Islamophobia in the EU after 11 September 2001 (May 2002), EUMC.&lt;/ref&gt;
Although the term is widely recognized and used, it has not been without controversy.&lt;ref name = Routledge&gt;{{Cite book
 |title=Encyclopedia of Race and Ethnic studies p. 218, Routledge 2003
 |year=2003
 |publisher=Routledge
 |page=218
|quote=The Runnymede Trust has been successful in that the term Islamophobia is now widely recognized and used, though many right-wing commentators either reject its existence or argue that it is justified.
 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Definitions==
The word ''Islamophobia'' is a  [[neologism]] formed from ''Islam'' and ''-[[phobia]]''. The compound form ''Islamo-'' contains the [[thematic stem|thematic vowel]] ''[[:wikt:-o-|-o-]]'', and is found in earlier coinages such as ''Islamo-Christian'' from the 19th century.
As opposed to being a [[psychological]] or individualistic phobia, according to associate professor of religion Peter Gottschalk, "Islamophobia" connotes a [[social anxiety]] about Islam and Muslims.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wesleyan.edu/newsletter/campus/2007/1107islambook.html |title=Faculty, Alumnus Discuss Concept of "Islamophobia" in Co-Authored Book |accessdate=2007-12-29 |date=2007-11-20 |author=Corrina Balash Kerr |work=[[Wesleyan University]] Newsletter}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.politicalaffairs.net/article/articleview/6181/1/296/ |title=Images of Muslims: Discussing Islamophobia with Peter Gottschalk |accessdate=2007-12-29 |date=2007-11-19 |work=Political Affairs. |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20071206034654/http://www.politicalaffairs.net/article/articleview/6181/1/296/ &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-12-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A number of individuals and organizations have made attempts to define the concept. [[Kofi Annan]] told a UN conference on Islamophobia in 2004: "[W]hen the world is compelled to coin a new term to take account of increasingly widespread [[bigotry]], that is a sad and troubling development. Such is the case with Islamophobia."&lt;ref name=Annan&gt;[[Kofi Annan|Annan, Kofi]]. [http://www.un.org/News/Press/docs/2004/sgsm9637.doc.htm "Secretary-General, addressing headquarters seminar on confronting Islamophobia"], [[United Nations]] press release, December 7, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1996, the [[Runnymede Trust]] established the Commission on British Muslims and Islamophobia, chaired by Professor Gordon Conway, the vice-chancellor of the [[University of Sussex]]. Their report, Islamophobia: A Challenge for Us All, was launched in November 1997 by the Home Secretary, [[Jack Straw]]. In this report, Islamophobia was defined by the Trust as "an outlook or world-view involving an unfounded dread and dislike of Muslims, which results in practices of exclusion and discrimination."&lt;ref name="EoRE215"&gt;Encyclopedia of Race and Ethics, p. 215&lt;/ref&gt; An early documented use of the word in the [[United States]] was by the conservative American [[Insight (magazine)|''Insight'' magazine]] in 1991, used to describe [[Russia]]n activities in [[Afghanistan]].&lt;ref name="EoRE215"/&gt; Other claims of early use include usage by Iranian clerics in 1979,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.prochoix.org/frameset/26/islamophobie26.html ''Islamophobie?''], [[Caroline Fourest]] &amp; Fiammetta Venner; in prochoix, no.26/27, 2003.&lt;/ref&gt; or its use in 1921 by the painter [[Étienne Dinet]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.minorites.org/article.php?IDA=1319 :: Minorités ::&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]{{dead link|date=October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The American Muslim writer [[Stephen Schwartz (journalist)|Stephen Schwartz]] has defined Islamophobia as the condemnation of the entirety of [[Islam]] and its history as [[Extremism|extremist]]; denying the existence of a moderate Muslim majority; regarding Islam as a problem for the world; treating conflicts involving Muslims as necessarily their own fault; insisting that Muslims make changes to their religion; and inciting war against Islam as a whole.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.frontpagemag.com/Articles/ReadArticle.asp?ID=17874 "The 'Islamophobes' That Aren't"], ''FrontPage Magazine'', April 28, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;

In a 2007 article in ''Journal of Sociology'' defines Islamophobia as anti-Muslim racism and a continuation of anti-[[Asian people|Asian]] and [[Anti-Arabism|anti-Arab]] racism.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Scott Poynting, Victoria Mason |title=The resistible rise of Islamophobia |journal=Journal of Sociology |volume=43 |issue=1 |pages=61–86 |year=2007 |doi=10.1177/1440783307073935}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Similarly, [[John Denham (politician)|John Denham]] has drawn parallels between modern Islamophobia and the [[antisemitism]] of the 1930s.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/uk/article6832035.ece The Times: Fascism fears: John Denham speaks out over clashes]&lt;/ref&gt; So has [[Maud Olofsson]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.svd.se/nyheter/inrikes/artikel_3674445.svd SvD: Reinfeldt: Kärnan i partiets idé]&lt;/ref&gt; Professor [[Jan Hjärpe]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.svd.se/nyheter/inrikes/artikel_3674029.svd SvD: Sverigedemokrat till hårt angrepp mot muslimsk ideologi i tal]&lt;/ref&gt; and [[George Galloway]].&lt;ref name=Galloway/&gt;

In a 2008 article in the "Journal of Political Ideologies" Jose P. Zuquete argues that Islamophobia is a catch-all term that should be avoided. Islamophobia places under the broad umbrella of 'fear or hatred of Islam' discourses and criticisms that may have distinct sources, motivations and goals. He argues instead for the use of "anti-Islamic" (because it distinguishes between different discourses about Islam).

==Perceptions==
The Runnymede report identified eight perceptions related to Islamophobia:

:#Islam is seen as a [[monolith]]ic bloc, static and unresponsive to change.
:#It is seen as separate and "other." It does not have values in common with other cultures, is not affected by them and does not influence them.
:#It is seen as inferior to the West. It is seen as barbaric, irrational, primitive, and [[sexist]].
:#It is seen as violent, aggressive, threatening, supportive of [[terrorism]], and engaged in a [[clash of civilizations]].
:#It is seen as a political [[ideology]], used for political or military advantage.
:#Criticisms made of "the West" by Muslims are rejected out of hand.
:#Hostility towards Islam is used to justify discriminatory practices towards Muslims and exclusion of Muslims from mainstream society.
:#Anti-Muslim hostility is seen as natural and normal.&lt;ref name=Runnymede1997&gt;{{PDFlink|[http://www.runnymedetrust.org/uploads/publications/pdfs/islamophobia.pdf "Islamophobia: A Challenge for Us All"]|69.7&amp;nbsp;KB}}, ''Runnymede Trust'', 1997.&lt;/ref&gt;

The above perceptions are seen as closed views on Islam. These are contrasted, in the report, with open views on Islam which, while founded on respect for Islam, permit legitimate disagreement, dialogue and critique.&lt;ref&gt;Benn; Jawad (2004) p. 162&lt;/ref&gt; According to Benn and Jawad, The Runnymede Trust notes that anti-Muslim discourse is increasingly seen as respectable, providing examples on how hostility towards Islam and Muslims is accepted as normal, even among those who may actively challenge other prevalent forms of discrimination.&lt;ref name="Brill165"&gt;Benn; Jawad (2004) p. 165&lt;/ref&gt;

In some societies, Islamophobia has materialized due to the portrayal of Islam and Muslims as the national "[[Other]]", where exclusion and discrimination occurs on the basis of their religion and civilization which differs with national tradition and identity. Examples include Pakistani and Algerian migrants in Britain and France respectively.&lt;ref&gt;See:
*Encyclopedia of Race and Ethnic studies, p. 216
*Miles; Brown (2003) p. 163&lt;/ref&gt; This sentiment, according to Malcolm Brown and  Robert Miles, significantly interacts with [[racism]], although Islamophobia itself is not racism.&lt;ref&gt;Miles; Brown (2003) p. 163, 164&lt;/ref&gt; The publication "''Social Work and Minorities: European Perspectives''" describes Islamophobia as the new form of racism in Europe,&lt;ref&gt;Johnson; Soydan; Williams (1998) p. 182&lt;/ref&gt; arguing that "Islamophobia is as much a form of racism as [[Anti-Semitism]], a term more commonly encountered in Europe as a sibling of Racism, Xenophobia and Intolerance."&lt;ref&gt;Johnson; Soydan; Williams (1998) p. xxii&lt;/ref&gt;

Brown and Miles write that another feature of Islamophobic discourse is to amalgamate nationality (i.e. Arab), religion (Islam), and politics (terrorism, fundamentalism) — while most other religions are not associated with terrorism, or even "ethnic or national distinctiveness."&lt;ref name = "Brown-p163"&gt;Miles; Brown (2003) p. 163&lt;/ref&gt; They feel that "many of the stereotypes and misinformation that contribute to the articulation of Islamophobia are rooted in a particular perception of Islam", such as the notion that Islam promotes terrorism; especially prevalent after the [[September 11, 2001 attacks]].&lt;ref&gt;Miles; Brown (2003) p. 166&lt;/ref&gt;

===Media===
According to Elizabeth Poole in the  ''Encyclopedia of Race and Ethnic studies'', the media has been criticized for perpetrating Islamophobia. She cites a case study examining a sample of articles in the British press from between 1994 and 2004, which concluded that Muslim viewpoints were underrepresented and that issues involving Muslims usually depicted them in a negative light. Such portrayals, according to Poole, include the depiction of Islam and Muslims as a threat to Western security and values.&lt;ref&gt;Encyclopedia of Race and Ethnic studies, p. 217&lt;/ref&gt; Benn and Jawad write that hostility towards Islam and Muslims are "closely linked to media portrayals of Islam as barbaric, irrational, primitive and sexist."&lt;ref name="Brill165"/&gt; Egorova and Tudor cite European researchers in suggesting that expressions used in the media such as "Islamic terrorism", "Islamic bombs" and "violent Islam" have resulted in a negative perception of Islam.&lt;ref&gt;See Egorova; Tudor (2003) pp. 2-3, which cites the conclusions of Marquina and Rebolledo in: "A. Marquina, V. G. Rebolledo, ‘The Dialogue between the European Union and the Islamic World’ in Interreligious Dialogues: Christians, Jews, Muslims, Annals of the European Academy of Sciences and Arts, v. 24, no. 10, Austria, 2000, pp. 166-8. "&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2008 [[Fairness and Accuracy in Reporting]] published a study "Smearcasting, How Islamophobes Spread Bigotry, Fear and Misinformation." It described as bigoted against Islam authors [[Bruce Bawer]] and [[Robert Spencer (author)|Robert Spencer]], television and radio talk show hosts [[Sean Hannity]], [[Glenn Beck]] and [[Michael Savage (commentator)|Michael Savage]], political commentators [[David Horowitz]], [[Alan Dershowitz]] and [[Daniel Pipes]] and televangelist [[Pat Robertson]], among others.&lt;ref&gt;Steve Rendall and Isabel Macdonald, [http://www.fair.org/index.php?page=3648 Making Islamophobia Mainstream; How Muslim-bashers broadcast their bigotry], summary of [[Fairness and Accuracy in Reporting]] report, at its website, November/December 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

There have been several initiatives, based upon the sixty recommendations listed in the Runnymede Trust's report, aimed at increase Muslim participation in media and politics. Soon after the release of the Runnymede report, the [[Muslim Council of Britain]] was formed to serve as an umbrella body aiming to "represent Muslims in the public sphere, to lobby government and other institutions." The "[[Forum Against Islamophobia and Racism]]" (FAIR) was also established, designed to monitor coverage in the media and establish dialogue with media organizations. Following the attacks of September 11, the [[Islam Awareness Week]] and the "''Best of British Islam Festival''" were introduced to improve community relations and raise awareness about Islam.&lt;ref&gt;Encyclopedia of Race and Ethnic studies, p. 218&lt;/ref&gt;

==Trends==
Islamophobia has become a topic of increasing sociological and political importance.&lt;ref name = "Brown-p163"/&gt; According to Benn and Jawad, Islamophobia has increased since [[Ayatollah Khomeini]]'s denouncement of [[Salman Rushdie]]'s "''[[The Satanic Verses]]''" and the September 11 attacks.&lt;ref&gt;Benn; Jawad (2004) p. 111&lt;/ref&gt; [[Anthropologist]] Steven Vertovec writes that the purported growth in Islamophobia may be associated with increased Muslim presence in society and successes.&lt;ref name="Vertovec" /&gt; He suggests a [[Vicious circle|circular model]], where increased hostility towards Islam and Muslims results in governmental countermeasures such as institutional guidelines and changes to legislation, which itself may fuel further Islamophobia due to increased accommodation for Muslims in public life. Vertovec concludes: "As the public sphere shifts to provide a more prominent place for Muslims, Islamophobic tendencies may amplify."&lt;ref name="Vertovec" /&gt;
[[File:Ground Zero Marine Protest Muslim Bomb.jpg|thumb|left|A mannequin symbolizing a Muslim in a [[keffiyeh]], strapped to a "Made in the USA" bomb display at a protest of [[Park51]] in [[New York City]].]]
Patel, Humphries, and Naik claim that "Islamophobia has always been present in Western countries and cultures. In the last two decades, it has become accentuated, explicit and extreme."&lt;ref&gt;Naina Patel, Beth Humphries and Don Naik, "The 3 Rs in social work; Religion,‘race’ and racism in Europe", in Johnson; Soydan; Williams (1998) pp. 197-198&lt;/ref&gt; However, Vertovec states that some have observed that Islamophobia has not necessarily escalated in the past decades, but that there has been increased public scrutiny of it.&lt;ref name="Vertovec" /&gt; According to Abduljalil Sajid, one of the members of the Runnymede Trust's Commission on British Muslims and Islamophobia, "Islamophobias" have existed in varying strains throughout history, with each version possessing its own distinct features as well as similarities or adaptations from others.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Islamophobia: A new word for an old fear |url=http://www.wcrp.be/articles/Sajid9-11-04.htm |author=Imam Dr Abduljalil Sajid |accessdate=2007-08-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; An observatory report  on Islamophobia by the [[Organisation of the Islamic Conference]] similarly states that Islamophobia has existed for as long as Islam itself.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oic-oci.org/oicnew/is11/english/Islamophobia-rep-en.pdf 1st OIC Observatory Report on Islamophobia]{{dead link|date=October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some [[Muslims in India]] have complained about substantial discrimination. According the controversial [[Sachar Committee]] report, Muslims are heavily under-represented in different government and social areas.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.indianexpress.com/story/19623.html Sachar report to be implemented in full]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.indianexpress.com/sunday/fullcoverage/53.html The Missing Muslim], ''the Sunday Express. Full coverage on Sachar Report''&lt;/ref&gt; Among other claims, it declared that in the province of [[West Bengal]], where Muslims make up 27% of the population, their employment in the government sector was below 3%.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thestar.com/News/World/article/246411 Fearful Muslims adopt Hindu IDs], ''The Toronto Star, August 15, 2007''&lt;/ref&gt; These findings have been disputed, in particular, by Indian [[Muslim]] politician [[Mukhtar Abbas Naqvi]] (who is generally very critical of Islamophobic hatred&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.indianexpress.com/news/varuns-hatemuslim-speech-makes-bjp-squirm/435472/ Varun’s hate-Muslim speech makes BJP squirm&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;) as politically motivated [[propaganda]] designed to secure votes from the substantially sized Muslim electorate in India by cultivating division in Indian society.&lt;ref&gt;[http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/NEWS/India/Report_shows_Sachar_findings_manipulated_BJP/articleshow/1837930.cms Report shows Sachar findings manipulated]&lt;/ref&gt; Numerous prominent Indian Muslims have declared that Muslims in India are treated exceedingly well compared to other countries.&lt;ref&gt;
*[[Azim Premji]] - "'ll tell a Muslim, if you want to be Premji, you’ve every chance to do that in India"[http://www.expressindia.com/news/fullstory.php?newsid=34868]
*[[Feroz Khan]] - "I am a proud Indian. India is a secular country. The Muslims there are making lot of progress unlike in Pakistan. Our [[President]] is a Muslim and our Prime Minister a [[Sikh]]. Pakistan was made in the name of Islam, but look how the Muslims are killing Muslims here." [http://www.dnaindia.com/world/report_musharraf-says-no-entry-to-feroz_1030084]
&lt;/ref&gt;

Some Muslims of the [[Xinjiang]] region in the [[People's Republic of China]] bordering [[Afghanistan]] and [[Pakistan]] have complained of discrimination from [[Han Chinese]].&lt;ref name="uyghur-nyt"&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2008/10/19/world/asia/19xinjiang.html?_r=2&amp;pagewanted=1 Wary of Islam, China Tightens a Vise of Rules], [[New York Times]]&lt;/ref&gt; Adherents of the [[East Turkestan Islamic Movement]] (ETIM), a secessionist movement among [[Uyghur people|Uyghur]] [[Sunni]] Muslims in the region have also complained about government policies that affect Muslims. For example, the government monitors [[Hajj]] tours, mindful of events like an ETIM bomb plot that involved recruiting hajji Uyghurs,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jamestown.org/uploads/media/TM_008_68.pdf|title=Uyghurs Convicted in East Turkestan Islamic Movement Plot in Dubai|work=Terrorism Monitor|date=2010-06-22|accessdate=2010-07-31|publisher=[[Jamestown Foundation]]|first=Raffaello Pantucci}}&lt;/ref&gt; requires that restaurants stay open at [[Ramadan]], and disallows [[heterodox]] [[Koranic]] teachings.&lt;ref name="uyghur-nyt"/&gt; [[Human Rights Watch]] has criticised state control over religion in China, including the vetting of [[imam]]s, that China says is necessary to combat [[religious extremism]] and [[Islamic terrorism|terrorism]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/asia-pacific/4435135.stm | work=BBC News | title=China 'crushing Muslim Uighurs' | date=2005-04-12 | accessdate=2010-05-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A [[Pew Research Center|Pew report]] released in 2009 noted that nearly six-in-ten American adults see Muslims as being subject to a lot of discrimination, far more than [[Mormons]], [[Atheists]], or [[Jews]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.reuters.com/article/pressRelease/idUS198159+09-Sep-2009+PRN20090909 Among U.S. Religious Groups, Muslims Seen as Facing More Discrimination]&lt;/ref&gt;

===EUMC reports===
The largest project monitoring Islamophobia was undertaken following 9/11 by the EU watchdog, [[European Monitoring Centre on Racism and Xenophobia]] (EUMC). Their May 2002 report "Summary report on Islamophobia in the EU after 11 September 2001", written by [[Chris Allen (UK)|Chris Allen]] and Jorgen S. Nielsen of the [[University of Birmingham]], was based on 75 reports &amp;mdash; 15 from each EU member nation.&lt;ref name="EUMCNews"&gt;{{Cite news|title=EUMC presents reports on Discrimination and Islamophobia in the EU |publisher="European Monitoring Centre on Racism and Xenophobia media release" |url=http://www.eumc.europa.eu/eumc/index.php?fuseaction=content.dsp_cat_content&amp;catid=43d8bc25bc89d&amp;contentid=4582ddc822d41 |date=2006-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=EUMC&gt;Allen, Chris and Nielsen, Jorgen S. [http://www.raxen.eumc.eu.int/1/webmill.php?id=32813&amp;ditem=3101&amp;lin=detail "Summary report on Islamophobia in the EU after 11 September 2001"], EUMC, May, 2002.&lt;/ref&gt; The report highlighted the regularity with which ordinary Muslims became targets for abusive and sometimes violent retaliatory attacks after 9/11. Despite localized differences within each member nation, the recurrence of attacks on recognizable and visible traits of Islam and Muslims was the report's most significant finding. Incidents consisted of verbal abuse, blaming all Muslims for [[List of terrorist incidents|terrorism]], forcibly removing women's [[hijab]]s, spitting on Muslims, calling children "[[Osama bin Laden|Usama]]", and random assaults. Muslims have been hospitalized and on one occasion paralyzed.&lt;ref name=EUMC/&gt; The report also discussed the portrayal of Muslims in the media. Inherent negativity, stereotypical images, fantastical representations, and exaggerated caricatures were all identified. The report concluded that "a greater receptivity towards anti-Muslim and other xenophobic ideas and sentiments has, and may well continue, to become more tolerated."&lt;ref name=EUMC/&gt;

The EUMC has since released a number of publications related to Islamophobia, including "''The Fight against Antisemitism and Islamophobia: Bringing Communities together (European Round Tables Meetings)''" (2003) and "''Muslims in the European Union: Discrimination and Islamophobia''" (2006).&lt;ref&gt;[http://fra.europa.eu/fra/index.php?fuseaction=content.dsp_cat_content&amp;catid=1 EUMC website - Publications] {{accessdate|2007-11-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Criticism of concept==
[[Image:Salman Rushdie by Kubik 01.JPG|left|thumb|170px|[[Salman Rushdie]] was one of 12 writers who signed a statement regarding Islamophobia; "We refuse to renounce our critical spirit out of fear of being accused of "Islamophobia", a wretched concept that confuses criticism of Islam as a religion and stigmatisation of those who believe in it."&lt;ref name=Rushdie/&gt;]]

The concept of Islamophobia has been criticized on several grounds.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.brusselsjournal.com/node/816 Muslims Create Islamophobes, Then Want Islamophobes Punished | The Brussels Journal&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="autogenerated1"&gt;[http://atheism.about.com/b/2005/01/10/islamophobia-as-an-excuse-to-silence-critics-of-islam.htm Islamophobia as an Excuse to Silence Critics of Islam?&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://michellemalkin.com/2006/09/28/critics-of-islam-under-fireagain/ Michelle Malkin » Critics of Islam under fire…again&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Some critics argue that it is real, but is just another form of racism and does not require its own category,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news| url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/politics/2004/jan/12/race.religion | work=The Guardian | location=London | title=Islamophobia should be as unacceptable as racism | date=2004-01-12 | accessdate=2010-05-05 | first=Faisal | last=Bodi}}&lt;/ref&gt; while others argue that it is used to censor criticism, that its use threatens [[free speech]],&lt;ref name="autogenerated1" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news| url=http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qn4158/is_20060819/ai_n16669355 | title=Tyranny begins with self-censorship | Independent, The (London) | Find Articles at BNET}} {{Dead link|date=August 2010|bot=RjwilmsiBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; or is used to silence issues relating to Muslim populations in Western countries.&lt;ref name="Burleigh, M 2009 P440"&gt;Burleigh, M (2009) Blood and Rage, A Cultural History of Terrorism, Harper Perennial, P440&lt;/ref&gt;

Novelist [[Salman Rushdie]] and others signed a manifesto entitled [[MANIFESTO: Together facing the new totalitarianism|''Together facing the new totalitarianism'']] in March 2006 which denounced Islamophobia as "a wretched concept."&lt;ref name=Rushdie&gt;"We refuse to renounce our critical spirit out of fear of being accused of "Islamophobia", a wretched concept that confuses criticism of Islam as a religion and stigmatisation of those who believe in it." [[Salman Rushdie|Rushdie, Salman]] ''et al.'' [http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/4764730.stm "Writers' statement on cartoons"], BBC News, March 1, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; British academic [[Michael Burleigh]] argues that the term 'spares anyone the need to examine what has gone wrong within [Europe's Muslim] communities'.&lt;ref name="Burleigh, M 2009 P440"/&gt; Some opponents argue that Islamophobia is justified.&lt;ref name = Routledge/&gt; Others, such as [[Edward Said]], consider Islamophobia as it is evinced in [[Orientalism]] to be a 'secret sharer' in a more general antisemitic Western tradition.&lt;ref&gt;Edward W.Said, ''Orientalism'', Pantheon Books, New York 1978 pp.27-28&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Edward W. Said, ‘Orientalism Reconsidered’ in Francis Barker, Peter Hulme, Margaret Iversen, Diana Loxley (eds),'' Literature, Politics, and Theory,'' Methuen &amp; Co, London 1986 pp.210-229, pp.220f.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bryan Stanley Turner, introd. to Bryan S. Turner (ed.) ''Orientalism: Early Sources'', (Vol 1, Readings in Orientalism), Routledge, London (2000) reprint 2002 p.12&lt;/ref&gt; However, [[Daniel Pipes]] says that "'Islamophobia' deceptively conflates two distinct phenomena: fear of Islam and fear of radical Islam."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|last=Pipes |first=Daniel |url=http://www.danielpipes.org/article/3075 |date=2005-10-25 |title=Islamophobia? |work=[[New York Sun]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The concept of Islamophobia as formulated by Runnymede is criticized by professor [[Fred Halliday]] on several levels. He writes that the target of hostility in the modern era is not Islam and its tenets as much as it is Muslims and their actions, suggesting that a more accurate term would be "Anti-Muslimism."&lt;ref name="Aldridge1"&gt;{{Cite book
 |last=Aldridge
 |first=Alan
 |title=Religion in the Contemporary World: A Sociological Introduction
 |date=February 1, 2000
 |publisher=Polity Press
 |isbn=978-0745620831
 |page=138
 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Poole responds by noting that many Islamophobic discourses attack what they perceive to be Islam's tenets, while Miles and Brown write that Islamophobia is usually based upon negative stereotypes about Islam which are then translated into attacks on Muslims.&lt;ref name="MB165"&gt;Miles; Brown (2003) pp. 165-166&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Encyclopedia of Race and Ethnic Studies (2003)p. 219&lt;/ref&gt; Halliday also states that strains and types of prejudice against Islam and Muslims vary across different nations and cultures, which is not recognized in the Runnymede analysis. Miles and Brown respond by arguing that "the existence of different ‘Islamophobias’ does not invalidate the concept of Islamophobia any more than the existence of different racisms invalidates the concept of racism."&lt;ref name="MB165"/&gt; Halliday argues that the concept of Islamophobia unwittingly plays into the hands of extremists.&lt;ref name="Aldridge1"/&gt;

British writer and academic [[Kenan Malik]] believes that the charge of Islamophobia confuses discrimination against Muslims with criticism of Islam, and that it is used to silence critics and Muslim reformers. He writes that the extent to which Muslims are more vulnerable to [[social exclusion]] and attacks than other groups is frequently and allows for a culture of victimhood, where all failings are attributed to Islamophobia. Islamophobia is not a form of racism, in his view, because Islam is a belief system.&lt;ref name=Malik&gt;Malik, Kenan.[http://www.prospect-magazine.co.uk/article_details.php?id=6679 "Islamophobia Myth"]{{dead link|date=October 2010}}, Prospect, February 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; This analysis is criticized by [[Inayat Bunglawala]] from the [[Muslim Council of Britain]] and Abdul Wahid from the [[Islamism|Islamist]] group [[Hizb ut-Tahrir]].&lt;ref name=Bunglawala&gt;Bunglawala, Inayat &amp; Wahid, Abdul. [http://www.prospect-magazine.co.uk/pdfarticle.php?id=6764 "Is Islamophobia a Myth?"]{{dead link|date=October 2010}}, ''Prospect Magazine'', March 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; Bunglawala writes that Malik's argument is limited to overt acts of violence against Muslims, without recognizing less overt forms of prejudice or discrimination. By ignoring non-violent examples of Islamophobia, Malik's commentary "makes a mockery of victims of prejudice by pretending they have not been discriminated against," according to Bunglawala.&lt;ref name=Bunglawala/&gt;

In the wake of the [[Jyllands-Posten Muhammad cartoons controversy]], a group of 12 writers signed a statement in the French weekly satirical newspaper ''[[Charlie Hebdo]]'' in March 2006, warning against the use of the term Islamophobia to prevent criticism of "[[Islamic totalitarianism]]". The novelist [[Salman Rushdie]] was among these signatories.&lt;ref name=autogenerated2&gt;[[Salman Rushdie|Rushdie, Salman]] ''et al.'' [http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/4764730.stm "Writers' statement on cartoons"], BBC News, March 1, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; These views are shared by Dutch law professor [[Afshin Ellian]].&lt;ref name="Ellian"&gt;[[Afshin Ellian|Ellian, Afshin]]. [http://kvc.minbuza.nl/uk/current/2006/february/ellian.html "Stop Capitulating to Threats"]{{dead link|date=October 2010}}, February 2006&lt;/ref&gt; Critics cite the case of British journalist [[Polly Toynbee]], who was nominated in May 2003 for the title of "Most Islamophobic Media Personality of the Year" at the 'Annual Islamophobia Awards' overseen by the [[Islamic Human Rights Commission]], for claiming that Islam "... imposes harsh regimes that deny the most [[Human rights|basic human rights]]."&lt;ref name=Toynbee&gt;Toynbee, Polly. [http://www.guardian.co.uk/Columnists/Column/0,,563618,00.html "Last chance to speak out"]{{dead link|date=October 2010}}, ''The Guardian'', October 5, 2001.&lt;/ref&gt;

In an article called "Fighting Islamophobia: A Response to Critics", Assistant Professor [[Deepa Kumar]] writes that the modern-day demonization of Arabs and Muslims by US politicians and others is racist and Islamophobic, and employed in support of an unjust war. About the public impact of this rhetoric, she says that "One of the consequences of the relentless attacks on Islam and Muslims by politicians and the media is that Islamophobic sentiment is on the rise." She also chides some "people on the left" for using the same "Islamophobic logic as the Bush regime". She concludes with the statement "At times like this, people of conscience need to organize and speak out against Islamophobia."&lt;ref name="Fighting Islamophobia"&gt;[http://mrzine.monthlyreview.org/kumar030406.html Fighting Islamophobia: A Response to Critics] - Deepa Kumar, MRZine, February 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Johann Hari]] of ''[[The Independent]]'' has criticized the use of the term by organizations like [[Islamophobia Watch]], arguing that [[Liberal movements within Islam|liberal Muslims]] interested in reform are left unsupported because people fear being accused of Islamophobia.&lt;ref name=Hari&gt;He writes: "If Muslim women and Muslim gays are going to have any kind of decent life, the [Muslim] liberals need to receive solidarity and support – but slap-dash charges of Islamophobia intimidate people who could offer it ... While Islamophobia Watch talk about defending Muslims, they end up defending the nastiest and most right-wing part of the [[Ummah|Muslim community]] – the ones who are oppressing and killing the rest."- Hari, Johann. [http://www.johannhari.com/archive/article.php?id=897 "Don't call me an Islamophobe"], June 6, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; Writing in the [[New Humanist]], philosopher [[Piers Benn]] suggests that people who fear the rise of Islamophobia foster an environment "not intellectually or morally healthy", to the point that what he calls "Islamophobia-phobia" can undermine "critical scrutiny of Islam as somehow impolite, or ignorant of the religion's true nature."&lt;ref name=Benn&gt;[http://newhumanist.org.uk/524 "On Islamophobia-phobia"].&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[The New Criterion]]'' editor [[Roger Kimball]] argues that the word "Islamophobia" is a misnomer. "A phobia describes an [[Phobia|irrational fear]], and it is axiomatic that fearing the effects of radical Islam is not irrational, but on the contrary very well-founded indeed, so that if you want to speak of a legitimate phobia... ...we should speak instead of Islamophobia-phobia, the fear of and revulsion towards Islamophobia."&lt;ref name=Kimball&gt;Kimball, Roger. [http://web.archive.org/web/20060103053941/http://www.newcriterion.com/archives/24/01/after-the-suicide/ "After the suicide of the West"], January 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Neuroscientist]] and [[best selling]] [[author]] [[Sam Harris]] has openly criticized the term Islamophobia in an article stating:&lt;ref&gt;http://www.thedailybeast.com/blogs-and-stories/2010-08-13/ground-zero-mosque/3/&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;''There is no such thing as Islamophobia. Bigotry and racism exist, of course—and they are evils that all well-intentioned people must oppose. And prejudice against Muslims or Arabs, purely because of the accident of their birth, is despicable. But like all religions, Islam is a system of ideas and practices. And it is not a form of bigotry or racism to observe that the specific tenets of the faith pose a special threat to civil society. Nor is it a sign of intolerance to notice when people are simply not being honest about what they and their co-religionists believe.''&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==Public discourse==
===Efforts against Islamophobia===
There have been efforts against Islamophobia by many organizations in many countries; some of these are detailed below.
* In 2006 the [[Organisation of the Islamic Conference]] (OIC) set up an observatory on Islamophobia which will monitor and document activities perceived as Islamophobic around the world.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.islamonline.com/cgi-bin/news_service/world_full_story.asp?service_id=2398 "OIC set up observatory on Islamophobia"]{{dead link|date=October 2010}} ''IslamOnline'', May 9, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;
* A [[Talk radio|radio talk show]] host from 630 [[WMAL]] on November 26, 2006 exposed the prevalence of Islamophobia by seeming to advocate a government program to force all Muslims to wear "identifying markers."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=In U.S., fear and distrust of Muslims runs deep |author=Bernd Debusmann |publisher=Reuters|date=December 1, 9:05|url=http://www.asiamedia.ucla.edu/article.asp?parentid=58909 |accessdate=December 16, 2006 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The hoax was revealed at the end of the program. See [[Jerry Klein’s 2006 Islamophobia Radio Experiment]] for more details.
* During the accession talks regarding Turkey's possible entry to the EU, then [[Prime Minister of the Netherlands|Prime Minister of Holland]], [[Jan Peter Balkenende]], said Islamophobia must not affect the possibility of Turkey's entry to the [[European Union]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/3913335.stm Islam 'must not cloud Turkey bid'] BBC -Wednesday, 21 July 2004&lt;/ref&gt;
* 50,000 people signed a petition urging [[French President]] [[Jacques Chirac]] to "consider Islamophobia as a new form of racism, punishable by law. The statement reads that the publishing of insulting cartoons of [[Muhammad]] by the French press hurt and offended the feelings of [[French Muslim]]s."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.adnki.com/index_2Level_English.php?cat=Religion&amp;loid=8.0.306056413&amp;par= FRANCE: 50,000 SIGN UP AGAINST ISLAMOPHOBIA]{{dead link|date=October 2010}} - ADN Kronos - June 2, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;
* In [[London Borough of Tower Hamlets|Tower Hamlets]], a densely populated area in [[London]] with a large Muslim community, a crime reporting scheme called "Islamophobia - Don't Suffer in Silence" has been set up which police hope will raise awareness of Islamophobia and help them to understand the extent of the problem.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/england/london/4017617.stm Scheme to fight faith hate crimes] BBC - Wednesday, 17 November 2004&lt;/ref&gt;
* The British [[National Union of Teachers]] (NUT) has issued guidance to teachers in the union advising that teachers have to "Challenge Islamophobia", and that they have a "crucial role" to play in helping to "dispel myths about Muslim communities."&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/education/4687417.stm Teaching tolerance amid tension] BBC - Friday, 15 July 2005&lt;/ref&gt;
* Following an Islamist demonstration outside the Danish Embassy in London organized by the [[Al Ghurabaa]] organization in response to the [[Jyllands-Posten Muhammad cartoons controversy]], the [[Muslim Association of Britain]] organized a peaceful rally in [[Trafalgar Square]]. Organizers made available placards and [[T-shirt]]s bearing the rally's official slogan, the phrase, "United against Islamophobia, united against incitement."&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/help/3681938.stm Prayer mats lined the pavements] BBC - Saturday, 11 February 2006&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/cartoonprotests/story/0,,1708080,00.html Muslims fly flag for peaceful protest against cartoons] The Guardian - Sunday February 12, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;
* Following the [[July 7 bombings]], the British government set up a number of initiatives aimed at combating Islamophobia, including the "National Forum against extremism and Islamophobia".&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/4423668.stm Call for Muslim scholars to tour] BBC - Thursday, 10 November 2005&lt;/ref&gt; There was also plans by the British government to ban incitement to "religious hatred", however, this failed to get through the [[British House of Commons|House of Commons]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/programmes/bbc_parliament/4652669.stm Racial and Religious Hatred Bill] BBC - Friday, 27 January 2006&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/politics/4668266.stm Religious hatred: How MPs voted] BBC - Wednesday, 1 February 2006&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[The Hashemite Kingdom of Jordan]] issued a call in 1999 to world leaders to combat Islamophobia.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/453060.stm Jordan: Stop attacking Islam] BBC - Tuesday, September 21, 1999&lt;/ref&gt; Abdel-Elah Khatib, the Jordanian [[foreign minister]] said "The [[international community]] must consider how to confront this phenomenon of Islamophobia in order to prevent its proliferation".
* The [[Muslim Council of Britain]] ([[MCB]]) and the [[Trades Union Congress]] ([[TUC]]) held a seminar on how to combat Islamophobia.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.kuna.net.kw/Home/Story.aspx?Language=en&amp;DSNO=970534 Kuwait News Agency: Drive to combat Islamophobia]{{dead link|date=October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===List of incidents described as "Islamophobic"===
{{summarize section}}
{{Synthesis|date=September 2010}}
{{See also|Persecution of Muslims}}

====Balkans====
In the 1990s, the [[Bosnian Genocide]] and [[Kosovo War]], both of which involved the "mass murder of innocent Muslims," have been linked to Islamophobia.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|author=Z. Husain &amp; D. M. Rosenbaum|contribution=Perceiving Islam: The Causes and Consequences of Islamophobia in the Western Media|title=Religious fundamentalism in the contemporary world: critical social and political issues|editor=Santosh C. Saha|publisher=[[Lexington Books]]|year=2004|isbn=0739107607|pages=177–8|postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to the [[International Committee of the Red Cross|ICRC]] data on the Bosnian Genocide, "200,000 people were killed, 12,000 of them children, up to 50,000 women were raped, and 2.2 million were forced to flee their homes."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.un.org/ga/63/generaldebate/pdf/bosniaherzegovina_en.pdf Statement by Dr. Haris Silajdžić Chairman of the Presidency Bosnia and Herzegovina, Head of the Delegation of Bosnia and Herzegovina. at the 63rd Session of the General Assembly on the occasion of the General Debate], [http://www.un.org/ga/63/generaldebate/bosniaandherzegovina.shtml Summary], 23 September 2008, pp. 2.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Canada====
Halima Mautbur, from the [[Canadian Council on American-Islamic Relations]] called an attack on a [[hijab]]i Muslim woman "an Islamophobic incident".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.news.utoronto.ca/inthenews/archive/2006_03_16.html Muslim groups want action from U of T]{{dead link|date=October 2010}}, ''University of Toronto News'', March 16, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; On January 4, 2010, in [[Hamilton, Ontario|Hamilton]] city of [[Ontario]], [[Canada]] the largest mosque of the city on [[Stone Church Road (Hamilton, Ontario)|Stone Church Road]] was firebombed.&lt;ref&gt;
{{Cite news
  | title = Hamilton mosque firebombed
  | newspaper = CBC News
  | location = Toronto
  | publisher = Canadian Broadcasting Corporation
  | date = 04 Jenuary 2010
  | url = http://www.cbc.ca/canada/toronto/story/2010/01/04/hamilton-mosque-firebomb.html
  | accessdate = 2010-01-06&lt;!-- 15:08:17--&gt;}}
&lt;/ref&gt; Hamilton police’s [[hate crime]] unit and chief [[arson]] investigator discovered "evidence of [[vandalism]] at the property as well as an incendiary device".&lt;ref&gt;
{{Cite news
  | last = Morse
  | first = Paul
  | title = Shock, outrage over attack on city mosque
  | newspaper = The Hamilton Spectator
  | location = Hamilton - Ontario - Canada
  | publisher = Torstar Corporation
  | date = 04 Jenuary 2010
  | url = http://www.thespec.com/article/697777
  | accessdate = 2010-01-06&lt;!-- 15:02:56--&gt;}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}
&lt;/ref&gt; Attackers had used a large rock, lighter and [[Molotov cocktail]].&lt;ref&gt;
{{Cite news
  | last = Morse
  | first = Paul
  | title = Mosque firebombing sparks outrage
  | newspaper = The Hamilton Spectator
  | location = Hamilton - Ontario - Canada
  | publisher = Torstar Corporation
  | date = 05 Jenuary 2010
  | url = http://www.thespec.com/article/697876
  | accessdate = 2010-01-06&lt;!-- 15:41:50--&gt;}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

====Denmark====
[[Doudou Diène]] in a report prepared by the [[UN Commission on Human Rights]] released on March 7, 2006 mentioned the publishing of the cartoons at the heart of the [[Jyllands-Posten Muhammad cartoons controversy]] regarding, "The development of Islamophobia or any racism and racial discrimination ..."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.un.org/apps/news/story.asp?NewsID=17718&amp;Cr=racis&amp;Cr1 Racism and racial discrimination on rise around the world, UN expert warns], ''UN NEWS CENTRE'', March 7, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

====France====
[[Image:Castres3.jpg|right|thumb|The Mosque of [[Castres]] after vandal attack.]]

148 French Muslim graves were desecrated near Arras. A pig's head was hung from a headstone and profanities insulting Islam and Muslims were daubed on some graves.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/7333344.stm  French Muslim war graves defaced], ''BBC'', April 6, 2008&lt;/ref&gt; Dalil Boubakeur, a director of a Paris mosque described the [[vandalism]] on a Mosque in [[Paris]], [[France]] as Islamophobic.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/france/story/0,,1419719,00.html Vandals target Paris mosque] The Guardian - Tuesday February 22, 2005&lt;/ref&gt; On December 13, 2009, The Mosque of [[Castres]] in southern [[France]], was [[Vandalism|vandalized]] in the night.&lt;ref&gt;
{{Cite news
  | last = O.
  | first = M.
  | coauthors = Ennaharonline
  | title = Desecration of a mosque in France
  | newspaper = Ennahar Online English
  | location = Hydra - Alger
  | publisher = El Athir For the Press
  | date = 13 December 2009
  | url = http://www.ennaharonline.com/en/international/2612.html
  | accessdate = 16 December 2009}}
&lt;/ref&gt; [[Swastika]] in black paint, "[[Sieg Heil]]" in German, "[[Mitterrand and the far right|France to the French]]" in French, and "[[White Power]]" in English were scrawled on the [[mosque]].&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite news
  | title = Anti-Muslim graffiti found on French mosque
  | agency = Associated Press
  | date = 13 December 2009
  | url = http://www.google.com/hostednews/ap/article/ALeqM5jpsrZrKYldfsDqg5mNG2btrR3QVwD9CIJJTG0
  | accessdate = 16 December 2009}}{{dead link|date=October 2010}}
&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, a [[pig]] feet was hung on the mosque.&lt;ref&gt;
{{Cite news
  | title = Anti-Muslim Graffiti Found on French Mosque
  | newspaper = The New York Times
  | publisher = The New York Times Company
  | date = 13 December 2009
  | url = http://www.nytimes.com/aponline/2009/12/13/world/AP-EU-France-Anti-Muslim-Graffiti.html
  | accessdate = 16 December 2009}} {{Dead link|date=August 2010|bot=RjwilmsiBot}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Islamic scarf controversy in France|Islamic headscarf ban]] at schools in 2004 has been accused of being Islamophobic. As a consequence, the years following the ban has seen an increasing number of [[Madrasah|Islamic secondary schools]] being established, [[Islam in France|French Muslim]] female students increasingly choosing to study at home, some shaving their hair, and others migrating away from France with their families.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Amara Bamba|title=French Anti-Hijab Law: Four Years On|publisher=[[IslamOnline]]|date=April 12, 2008|url=http://www.islamonline.net/servlet/Satellite?c=Article_C&amp;cid=1203758927834&amp;pagename=Zone-English-Euro_Muslims%2FEMELayout|accessdate=2010-04-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; Muslim students have also increasingly enrolled at Catholic schools, which are usually more tolerant towards Islam than the secular public schools.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=French Muslims Find Haven in Catholic Schools|work=[[New York Times]]|author=KATRIN BENNHOLD|date=September 29, 2008|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2008/09/30/world/europe/30schools.html?_r=1|accessdate=2010-04-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2010, a study entitled, ''Are French Muslims Discriminated Against in Their Own Country?'', has shown that "Muslims sending out resumes in hopes of a job interview had 2.5 times less chance than Christians" with similar credentials "of a positive response to their applications."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Study shows French Muslims hit by religious bias|date=26 Mar 2010|work=[[Otago Daily Times]]|url=http://www.odt.co.nz/news/world/99211/study-shows-french-muslims-hit-religious-bias|accessdate=2020-04-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Germany====
On July 1, 2009, [[Marwa El-Sherbini]] was stabbed to death in a courtroom in [[Dresden]], [[Germany]]. She had just given evidence against her attacker who had used racist insults against her because she wore an [[Islamic headscarf]].

====Nigeria====
During the [[Yelwa massacre]] on May 2, 2004, a Christian militia killed hundreds of Muslims in [[Yelwa]], [[Nigeria]], and thousands of Muslims were forced to flee the area.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=Nigerian Muslims struggle to cope after village massacre|author=Tume Ahemba|work=[[The Guardian]]|date=8 May 2004|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2004/may/08/2|accessdate=2010-04-12 | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====United Kingdom====
In March 2006, Jamia Masjid mosque in Preston was attacked by gangs of white youths using brick and concrete block. The white youths damaged a number of cars outside the mosque and stabbed a 16 year-old Muslim teenager. In the same town, a 20 year-old Muslim, Shezsan Umarji, was killed by three youths in July 2005.&lt;ref name=arabicnews&gt;{{cite web|title=Muslim teenager stabbed during attack on UK mosque|publisher=Arabic News|date=10/3/2006|url=http://www.arabicnews.com/ansub/Daily/Day/061003/2006100304.html|accessdate=2010-04-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; On July 6, 2009, the [[Glasgow]] branch of [[Islamic Relief]] was badly damaged by a fire which police said was started deliberately, and which members of the Muslim community of [[Scotland]] allege were Islamophobic.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/scotland/glasgow_and_west/8137021.stm Islamic charity fire 'deliberate'] BBC News, 6 July 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2005, ''The Guardian'' commissioned an [[ICM (polling)|ICM]] poll which indicated an increase in Islamophobic incidents, particularly after the [[7/7|London bombings]] in July 2005.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/attackonlondon/story/0,,1536222,00.html Two-thirds of Muslims consider leaving UK] The Guardian - Tuesday July 26, 2005&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://image.guardian.co.uk/sys-files/Politics/documents/2005/07/26/Muslim-Poll.pdf ICM-Guardian poll] Poll of Muslims in the UK. The Guardian - Tuesday July 26, 2005&lt;/ref&gt; Another survey of Muslims, this by the [[Open Society Institute]], found that of those polled 32% believed they had suffered religious discrimination at airports, and 80% said they had experienced Islamophobia.&lt;ref&gt;[http://islamonline.net/English/News/2004-11/22/article06.shtml Spiraling Islamophobia Alienating British Muslims: Report] [[Islamonline.net|Islam Online]] - Nov 22 2004&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/islam/story/0,,1362423,00.html ... And why we urgently need new answers] Sarfraz Manzoor - The Guardian - November 30, 2004&lt;/ref&gt; In July 2005, a Muslim man, Kamal Raza Butt, was beaten to death outside a corner shop in [[Nottingham]] by a gang of youths who shouted anti-Islamic abuse at him.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=Islamophobia blamed for attack|author=Vikram Dood|work=[[The Guardian]]|date=13 July 2005|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/uk/2005/jul/13/race.july7|accessdate=2010-04-04 | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On the 26 August 2007 fans of the English football club [[Newcastle United]] directed Islamophobic chants at Egyptian [[Middlesbrough F.C.]] striker [[Mido (footballer)|Mido]]. An [[The Football Association|FA]] investigation was launched&lt;ref name="Briefs3-FA investigating claims of racist chanting against Mido"&gt;{{Cite news
| title = Briefs3-FA investigating claims of racist chanting against Mido
| url = http://uk.reuters.com/article/footballNews/idUKL137257820081201
| publisher = Reuters
| date = 2008-12-01
| accessdate = 2008-12-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; He revealed his anger at The FA's investigation, believing that they would make no difference to any future abuse.&lt;ref name="Mido fury at FA over repeat of racist taunts at Tyne-Tees clash"&gt;{{Cite news
| first = Simon
| last = Williams
| title = Mido fury at FA over repeat of racist taunts at Tyne-Tees clash
| url = http://www.guardian.co.uk/football/2008/dec/04/middlesbrough-premierleague
| publisher = The Guardian
| date = 2008-12-04
| accessdate = 2008-12-05
| location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; Two men were eventually arrested over the chanting and were due to appear at Teesside Magistrates Court.&lt;ref name="Two arrested over Mido chanting"&gt;{{Cite news
| title = Two arrested over Mido chanting
| url = http://news.bbc.co.uk/sport1/hi/football/teams/m/middlesbrough/7758089.stm
| publisher = BBC Sport
| date = 2008-12-05
| accessdate = 2008-12-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:EDL4.jpg|left|thumb|200px|[[English Defence League]] is a far right group that attracts far-right activists to take part in demonstrations across the [[United Kingdom]].]]

In January 2010, a report from the [[University of Exeter]]'s European Muslim research centre noted that the number of anti-Muslim [[hate crime]]s has increased, ranging from "death threats and murder to persistent low-level assaults, such as spitting and name-calling," for which the media and politicians have been blamed with fueling anti-Muslim hatred. The Islamophobic incidents it described include: "Neil Lewington, a violent extremist nationalist convicted in July 2009 of a bomb plot; Terence Gavan, a violent extremist nationalist convicted in January 2010 of manufacturing nail bombs and other explosives, firearms and weapons; a gang attack in November 2009 on Muslim students at [[City University London|City University]]; the murder in September 2009 of Muslim pensioner, Ikram Syed ul-Haq; a serious assault in August 2007 on the [[Imam]] at [[London Central Mosque]]; and an arson attack in June 2009 on Greenwich Islamic Centre."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=Media and politicians 'fuel rise in hate crimes against Muslims'|author=Vikram Dood|work=[[The Guardian]]|date=28 January 2010|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/uk/2010/jan/28/hate-crimes-muslims-media-politicians|accessdate=2010-04-04 | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Dr. Jonathan Githens-Mazer &amp; Dr. Robert Lambert|title=Islamophobia and Anti-Muslim Hate Crime: a London Case Study|publisher=[[University of Exeter]]|url=http://centres.exeter.ac.uk/emrc/publications/Islamophobia_and_Anti-Muslim_Hate_Crime.pdf|accessdate=2010-04-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other Islamophobic incidents mentioned in the report include "Yasir, a young Moroccan," being "nearly killed while waiting to take a bus from [[Willesden]] to [[Regent's Park]] in London" and "left in a coma for three months"; "Mohammed Kohelee," a "caretaker who suffered burns to his body while trying to prevent an arson attack against Greenwich Mosque"; "the murder" of "[[Tooting]] pensioner Ekram Haque" who "was brutally beaten to death in front of his three year old granddaughter" by a "race-hate" gang; and "police officers" being injured "during an [[English Defence League]] (EDL) march in [[Stoke-on-Trent|Stoke]]."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=Muslims in the UK: beyond the hype|author=Jonathan Githens-Mazer &amp; Robert Lambert|work=[[The Guardian]]|date=28 January 2010|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/belief/2010/jan/28/muslims-media-hate-crimes|accessdate=2010-04-04 | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====United States of America====
[[Image:Gathering of eagles.jpg|right|thumb|A protester at a counter-demonstration against the [[September 15, 2007 anti-war protest]] in Washington, D.C.]]

In the [[aftermath of 9/11]], [[hate crime]]s against people of Middle-Eastern descent increased from 354 attacks in 2000 to 1,501 attacks in 2001.&lt;ref name="Oswald"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Oswald |first=Debra L. |date=September 2005|title=Understanding Anti-Arab Reactions Post-9/11: The Role of Threats, Social Categories, and Personal Ideologies |journal=Journal of Applied Social Psychology |volume=35 |issue=9 |pages=1775–1799 |doi=10.1111/j.1559-1816.2005.tb02195.x}}&lt;/ref&gt; Among the victims of the backlash was a Middle-Eastern man in [[Houston]], [[Texas]] who was shot and wounded after an assailant accused him of "blowing up the country"&lt;ref name="aaiusa"/&gt; and four immigrants shot and killed by a man named Larme Price who confessed to killing them as "revenge" for the [[September 11 attacks]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2003/04/01/nyregion/vibes-made-man-kill-and-confess-police-say.html 'Vibes Made Man Kill... and Confess, Police Say]&lt;/ref&gt; Although Price described his victims as Arabs, only one was from an Arab country. This appears to be a trend; on account of [[Stereotypes of Arabs and Muslims|stereotypes of Arabs]], several non-Arab, non-Muslim groups were subjected to attacks in the wake of 9/11, including several [[Sikh]] men attacked for wearing their religiously mandated [[turban]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news| title =Hate crime reports up in wake of terrorist attacks  | work =US News  | publisher =CNN  | date =September 17, 2001  | url =http://archives.cnn.com/2001/US/09/16/gen.hate.crimes/  | accessdate =2008-04-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to a report prepared by the [[Arab American Institute]], three days after the [[Oklahoma City bombing]], "more than 200 serious hate crimes were committed against [[Arab American]]s and [[American Muslim]]s. The same was true in the days following September 11."&lt;ref name="aaiusa"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.humanitykingdom.com/library/general/arab-american.pdf |title=Arab American Institute 2001 report submitted to the United States Commission on Civil Rights |format=PDF |publisher=[[Arab American Institute]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Zohreh Assemi, an [[Iranian American]] [[Muslim]] owner of a nail salon in [[Locust Valley]], [[New York]], was robbed, beaten, and called a "terrorist" in September 2007 in what authorities call a bias crime.&lt;ref name=nypost&gt;[http://www.nypost.com/seven/09162007/news/regionalnews/muslim_biz_gal_beaten.htm Muslim Biz Gal Beaten&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Assemi was kicked, sliced with a boxcutter, and had her hand smashed with a hammer. The perpatrators, who forcibly removed $2,000 from the salon and scrawled anti-Muslim slurs on the mirrors, also told Assemi to "get out of town" and that her kind were not "welcomed" in the area. The attack followed two weeks of phone calls in which Iranian-American Zohreh Assemi was called a "terrorist" and told to "get out of town," friends and family said.&lt;ref name=nypost /&gt;

While en route to Chicago, [[Shahrukh Khan]], a well-known [[Bollywood]] actor, was held for what he described as "humiliating" questioning for several hours in [[Newark Airport]], [[New Jersey]] because of his common Muslim surname [[Khan (name)|Khan]]. He was released only following the intervention of the Indian embassy.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thaindian.com/newsportal/entertainment/srk-detained-at-newark-airport-over-khan-name-second-lead_100232947.html SRK detained at Newark airport over ‘Khan’ name (Second Lead)&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/entertainment/bollywood/news-interviews/The-world-sees-Muslims-differently-Mahesh-Bhatt/articleshow/4896370.cms&lt;/ref&gt;

On August 25, 2010, a New York taxi driver was stabbed after a passenger asked if he was Muslim.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news| url=http://www.cnn.com/2010/CRIME/08/25/new.york.muslim.stabbed/index.html?hpt=T2 | work=CNN | title=Taxi driver stabbed after passenger asks if he's Muslim | date=August 26, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Dove World Outreach Center]] church in Gainesville, Florida planned to burn [[Quran]]s on the ninth anniversary of the [[9/11]] attacks. Despite warning from the military leadership in the [[Afghan War]], Terry Jones, the pastor of the centre, said it would be "tragic" if anybody's life was lost as a result of the planned Quran burning. While he added "Still, I must say that we feel that we must sooner or later stand up to Islam, and if we don't, it's not going to go away." His church's website claims to "expose Islam" as a "violent and oppressive religion;" it also displays a sign reading "Islam is of the Devil."&lt;ref&gt;[http://english.aljazeera.net/news/asia/2010/09/2010973657442887.html Warnings against Quran burning plan - Central &amp; South Asia - Al Jazeera English&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Allegations of Islamophobic views===
* [[Carl Ernst]], a scholar of [[Islamic studies]], and the [[Council on American-Islamic Relations]] has alleged that [[Robert Spencer (writer)|Robert Spencer]] is "Islamophobic".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cair-net.org/default.asp?Page=articleView&amp;id=1853&amp;theType=NR CA Synagogue That Hosted Islamophobe Urged to Invite Muslim Speaker], CAIR News Releases, [[November 8|November 08]], 2005&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Ernst"&gt;[http://www.unc.edu/~cernst/courses/2004/026/001/spencer.htm Notes on the Ideological Patrons of an Islamophobe, Robert Spencer by Carl W. Ernst] - [[University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill]], 2004&lt;/ref&gt; Spencer responded to this labeling, and invited Ernst to debate.&lt;ref&gt;[http://jihadwatch.org/archives/012899.php An open letter to Carl Ernst], August 27, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;
* The Council on American-Islamic Relations has stated that the views of [[Ann Coulter]] are Islamophobic.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cair-net.org/default.asp?Page=articleView&amp;id=1048&amp;theType=NR Ann Coulter says Muslims 'Smell Bad'], ''Council on American-Islamic Relations'', March 10, 2004&lt;/ref&gt;
* Oliver Duff of ''[[The Independent]]'' said in 2006 that the [[British National Party]] attempted to use increasing Islamophobia to make gains in local elections.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.independent.co.uk/uk/politics/article356477.ece Rising Islamophobia makes Birmingham fertile ground for BNP], ''The Independent'', April 8, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;
* Liz McGregor and John Hooper of [[The Guardian]], has alleged that the views and writings of [[Oriana Fallaci]], an Italian journalist and author of "[[The Force of Reason]]", was "Islamaphobic" [sic].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/italy/story/0,,1873911,00.html Obituary of Oriana Fallaci] - [[The Guardian]], 16 September 2006. "''Controversial Italian journalist famed for her interviews and war reports but notorious for her Islamaphobia''"&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[Islamic Human Rights Commission]] gave U.S [[Attorney General]] [[John Ashcroft]] a nomination for their 2003 "Islamophobe of the year" award for publicly saying, "Islam is a religion in which God requires you to send your son to die for him. Christianity is a faith in which God sends his son to die for you"&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.inminds.co.uk/islamophobia-awards-2003.html Annual Islamophobia Awards, 2003]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?file=/c/a/2002/02/22/MN146728.DTL "The gospel according to John (Ashcroft)"] San Francisco Chronicle&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[Islamic Human Rights Commission]] made [[Daniel Pipes]] a nominee for their 2004 and 2005 "Islamophobe of the year" awards.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ihrc.org.uk/show.php?id=1124 Winners of Islamophobia Awards 2004], ''Islamic Human Rights Commission'', June 26, 2004. *[http://www.ihrc.org.uk/show.php?id=1657 Winners of the Islamophobia Awards 2005], ''Islamic Human Rights Commission'', December 17, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;
* A December 2005 interview by [[Vlaams Belang]] frontman [[Filip Dewinter]] with the American-Jewish newsweekly [[The Jewish Week]] included a question if "Jews should vote for a party that espouses xenophobia". Dewinter responded by saying: "Xenophobia is not the word I would use. If it absolutely must be a ‘phobia,’ let it be ‘Islamophobia.’"&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20060208183342/http://www.thejewishweek.com/news/newscontent.php3?artid=11767 Filip Dewinter interview], ''Jewish Week'', December 9, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[United Kingdom|UK]] Minister Peter Hain's statement that Britain's Muslim community is "isolationist" was met with accusations of Islamophobia, as well as [[Italy|Italian]] prime minister [[Silvio Berlusconi]]'s public claim that Western civilization is superior to Islam.&lt;ref name="spiked"&gt;[http://www.spiked-online.co.uk/Articles/00000006D95B.htm Who's afraid of Islamophobia?], ''Spiked'', July 2, 2002&lt;/ref&gt;
* Some suggestions in the [[United Kingdom debate over veils]] (which concerned the circumstances in which Muslim women should be required to remove the [[Niqab]]) were considered Islamophobic by MP [[John McDonnell (politician)|John McDonnell]].&lt;ref name="McDonnell"&gt;See, e.g., "[http://www.john4leader.org.uk/2006/10/wave-of-islamophobia.html Wave of Islamophobia]", a [[Blog|blog post]] by [[John McDonnell (politician)|John McDonnell]] MP from October 6, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;
* CAIR and [[Associated Press|the Associated Press]] called United States Rep. [[Virgil Goode|Virgil H. Goode, Jr.]] (R-VA) islamophobic for his Dec. 2006 letter stating that Rep-elect [[Keith Ellison (politician)|Keith Ellison]]'s desire to use the Qur'an during the swearing in ceremonies was a threat to "the values and beliefs traditional to the United States of America" and for saying "I fear that in the next century we will have many more Muslims in the United States if we do not adopt the strict immigration policies."&lt;ref name="Howsare"&gt;{{Cite news|title=Anti-Muslim letter goes out to hundreds - not all are amused|author=Erika Howsare|date=2006-12-19|url=http://www.c-ville.com/index.php?cat=141404064431134&amp;ShowArticle_ID=11041812060944420 |accessdate=December 20, 2006 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Congressman Will Not Apologize for IslamophobiaBy The Associated Press|agency=Associated Press|date=2006-12-21|url=http://www.diversityinc.com/public/1064.cfm |accessdate=December 21, 2006 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Concerning the US state of [[North Carolina]]’s position (as expressed by their attorney general’s office) in the ongoing case of [[ACLU of N.C. &amp; Syidah Matteen v. State of North Carolina]] that the only swearing-in for testimony in court that was valid had to be on a [[Bible|Christian Bible]] (and that all others must choose to affirm), CAIR's Legal Director in Washington D.C, Arsalan Iftikhar, said “This shows there's a lot of anti-Muslim sentiment, especially here in the United States.”&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.csmonitor.com/2005/0720/p02s02-usju.html|title=Raise your right hand and swear to tell the truth... on the Koran?|date=2005-07-20|author=Patrik Jonsson|publisher=The Christian Science Monitor |accessdate=January 22, 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Statements that incite Islamophobia from [[Franklin Graham]], [[Pat Robertson]] and [[Benny Hinn]], according to [[John Esposito]]. [[q:John Esposito|read relevant quotes]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.un.org/Pubs/chronicle/2004/webArticles/112204_Conference.asp|title=Unlearning Intolerance|publisher=UN Chronicle Online Edition|date=2004-07-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*In 2004, Professor Richard E. Johnson wrote a book entitled ''(Mis)representing Islam: the racism and rhetoric of British broadsheet newspapers'', criticizing the [[Media of the United Kingdom|British media]] for propogating negative [[Stereotypes of Arabs and Muslims|stereotypes of Muslims]] and fueling anti-Muslim prejudice.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Richardson|first=John E.|title=(Mis)representing Islam: the racism and rhetoric of British broadsheet newspapers|publisher=[[John Benjamins Publishing Company]]|year=2004|isbn=9027226997|url=http://books.google.com/?id=WanqiF2XULsC&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q=|postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; The media has also been criticized for under-reporting [[hate crime]]s against Muslims.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Islamophobia and anti-Muslim hate crime in London|author=Jenny Bourne|publisher=[[Institute of Race Relations]]|date=4 February 2010|url=http://www.irr.org.uk/2010/february/ha000015.html|accessdate=2010-04-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Western media has also been criticized for over-reporting a few [[Islamist terrorist]] incidents but under-reporting the much larger number of non-Islamist terrorist attacks carried out by non-Muslim [[White people|white]] extremists.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Know your enemy|author=Mehdi Hasan|work=[[New Statesman]]|date=9 July 2009|url=http://www.newstatesman.com/2009/07/mehdi-hasan-muslim-terrorism-white-british|accessdate=2010-04-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; A [[Europol]] report showed that, contrary to media representation, more than 99% of terrorist attacks in Europe from 2006 to 2009 were, in fact, carried out by non-Muslims.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=
This tide of anti-Muslim hatred is a threat to us all|author=Seumas Milne|work=[[The Guardian]]|date=25 February 2010|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/belief/2010/feb/25/anti-muslim-hatred-threat-to-all|accessdate=2010-04-08 | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=EU TERRORISM SITUATION AND TREND REPORT|publisher=[[Europol]]|year=2007-2009|url=http://www.europol.europa.eu/index.asp?page=publications&amp;language=|accessdate=2010-04-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; An [[FBI]] report has shown that, contrary to popular opinion, only a small minority of terrorist attacks in the United States from 1980 to 2005 were carried out by Islamist extremists, while the same report concludes that "whereas the violent, global jihadist movement manifested itself primarily in terrorist preventions in the United States from 2002 through 2005, internationally the movement claimed major attacks against U.S. and Western targets that resulted in American casualties".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Terrorism 2002–2005|publisher=[[FBI]]|year=2005|url=http://www.fbi.gov/publications/terror/terrorism2002_2005.htm|accessdate=2010-04-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Cabinet of the United Kingdom|British cabinet]] ministers had been criticized in October 2006 for helping to "unleash a public anti-Muslim backlash" in the United Kingdom by blaming the [[Islam in the United Kingdom|Muslim community]] over issues of integration despite a study commisioned by the [[Home Office]] on white and [[British Asian|Asian]]-Muslim youths demonstrating otherwise: that Asian-Muslim youths "are in fact the most tolerant of all" and that [[white British]] youths "have far more intolerant attitudes," concluding that intolerance from the white British community was a greater "barrier to integration" in the United Kingdom.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=White pupils less tolerant, survey shows|author=Vikram Dood|work=[[The Guardian]]|date=21 October 2006|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/uk/2006/oct/21/schools.religion|accessdate=2010-04-04 | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=Muslim students 'more tolerant'|publisher=BBC News|date=11 October 2006|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/lancashire/6033155.stm|accessdate=2010-04-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; A Europe-wide survey by [[Gallup]] in May 2009 also found that the [[Islam in Europe|Muslim communities]] in Britain, Germany and France felt more patriotic towards those countries than the general populations in those countries,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Poll: European Muslims more patriotic than average populace|publisher=[[Deutsche Presse-Agentur]]|date=7 May 2009|url=http://www.haaretz.com/hasen/spages/1083892.html|accessdate=2010-04-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Muslims more patriotic than Brits|publisher=Politics|date=7 May 2009|author=Ian Dunt|url=http://www.politics.co.uk/news/equality/muslims-more-patriotic-than-brits-$1293822.htm|accessdate=2010-04-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; while another survey found that Muslims supported the role of Christianity in British life more so than Christians themselves.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=79 per cent of Muslims say Christianity should have strong role in Britain|author=Nick Allen|date=24 February 2009|work=[[The Daily Telegraph]]|url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/newstopics/religion/4799345/79-per-cent-of-Muslims-say-Christianity-should-have-strong-role-in-Britain.html|accessdate=2010-04-05 | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*The [[British Social Attitudes Survey]] in January 2010 found that the British public "is far more likely to hold negative views of Muslims than of any other religious group,"&lt;ref name=Galloway&gt;{{cite web|title=Sinister parallels of hatred|date=14 March 2010|author=[[George Galloway]]|work=[[Morning Star (UK newspaper)|Morning Star]]|url=http://www.morningstaronline.co.uk/index.php/news/content/view/full/87933|accessdate=2010-04-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; with "just one in four" feeling "positively about Islam," and a "majority of the country would be concerned if a mosque was built in their area, while only 15 per cent expressed similar qualms about the opening of a church."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=Britain divided by Islam, survey finds|work=[[The Daily Telegraph]]|date=11 Jan 2010|url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/newstopics/religion/6965276/Britain-divided-by-Islam-survey-finds.html|accessdate=2010-04-04 | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;

ABC News has reported that "[p]ublic views of Islam are one casualty of the post-Sept. 11, 2001 conflict: Nearly six in 10 Americans think the religion is prone to violent extremism, nearly half regard it unfavorably, and a remarkable one in four admits to prejudicial feelings against Muslims and Arabs alike."&lt;ref name=ABCMarch8&gt;[http://abcnews.go.com/US/story?id=1700599 "Poll: Americans Skeptical of Islam and Arabs"], ”ABC News”, March 8, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; They also report that 27 percent of Americans admit feelings of prejudice against Muslims.&lt;ref name=ABCMarch8/&gt; According to Gallup polls, 40 percent of Americans admit to prejudice against Muslims, and 39 percent believe Muslims should carry special identification.&lt;ref&gt;[http://abcnews.go.com/GMA/Story?id=2413473&amp;page=2 "Islamophobia Felt 5 Years after 9/11"], ''Good Morning America'', September 9, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Incidents on aircraft===
Some incidents with Muslim passengers on aircraft have given rise to the expression "[[Flying while Muslim]]".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cnn.com/2006/US/11/21/passengers.removed/index.html Airline checks claim of 'Muslim while flying' discrimination] [[CNN]] November 21, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;
* On 16 August 2006 British passengers on-board a flight from Malaga to Manchester requested the removal of two men of Asian descent from a plane. According to a spokesman for the [[Civil Guard]] in Malaga, "These men had aroused suspicion because of their appearance and the fact that they were speaking in a [[foreign language]] thought to be an [[Arabic language]], and the pilot was refusing to take off until they were escorted off the plane." A security sweep of the plane found no explosives or any item of a terrorist nature. [[Monarch Airlines]] booked the men, who were Urdu speakers, into a hotel room, gave them a free meal and sent them home on a later plane. The men later responded, "Just because we're Muslim, does not mean we are suicide bombers." The Islamic Human Rights Commission blamed "ever-increasing Islamophobia" related to the "war on terror" for the incident.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dailymail.co.uk/pages/live/articles/news/news.html?in_article_id=401419&amp;in_page_id=1770&amp;in_page_id=1770&amp;ct=5&amp;expand=true#StartComments Mutiny as passengers refuse to fly until Asians are removed] - [[Daily Mail|Mail on Sunday]]. 20 August 2006&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mirror.co.uk/news/tm_objectid=17607948&amp;method=full&amp;siteid=94762&amp;headline=exclusive--malaga-jet-mutiny-pair-s-shock-at-plane-ejection-name_page.html Exclusive: Malaga Jet mutiny pair's shock at plane ejection] - [[The Daily Mirror]]. 23 August 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/airlines/story/0,,1854722,00.html Removal of men from holiday flight condemned]{{dead link|date=October 2010}}[[The Guardian]]. 21 August 2006&lt;/ref&gt;
* A passenger traveling to the [[British Virgin Islands]] on a plane bound for the United States from Manchester in the UK was forced off the plane prior to [[takeoff]]. The man, a British-born Muslim residing in the United States, said he was singled out because he was a Muslim pilot and was left feeling "demoralized and humiliated. I must have met the profile on the day. I have an Arabic name, I am a Muslim, I'm from Britain and I know how to fly."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.manchestereveningnews.co.uk/news/s/220/220381_muslim_pilot_kicked_off_jet_in_terror_alert.html Muslim pilot kicked off jet in terror alert] - [[Manchester Evening News]]. 11 August 2006&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.independent.co.uk/uk/this_britain/article1220859.ece Muslim pilot reveals shock at being ordered off flight] - [[The Independent]]. 22 August 2006&lt;/ref&gt;
* On 21 November 2006, six [[imams]] were forcefully removed from a [[US Airways]] flight at [[Minneapolis St. Paul International Airport]] for security reasons. The event led to an outcry from Muslim organizations in America saying that what happened showed the growing prejudice against Muslims in America.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2006/11/21/AR2006112100687.html "U.S. Muslims outraged after imams kicked off plane"]{{dead link|date=October 2010}}, ''[[The Washington Post]]'', 22 November 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; Investigations by the airline and police so far have reported that the airline and ground crews responded to security concerns properly in removing the men from the plane.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.washingtontimes.com/national/20061205-112831-5995r.htm Probes dismiss imams' racism claim]&lt;/ref&gt; See [[Flying Imams controversy]] for more details regarding this incident.
* In 2009 [[AirTran Airways]] removed nine [[Muslim]] passengers, including three children, from a flight and turned them over to the [[FBI]] after one of the men commented to another that they were sitting right next to the engines and wondered aloud where the safest place to sit on the plane was. Although the FBI subsequently cleared the passengers and called the incident a "misunderstanding," AirTran refused to seat the passengers on another flight, forcing them to purchase last minute tickets on another airline that had been secured with the FBI's assistance. A spokesman for AirTran initially defended the airline's actions and said they would not reimburse the passengers for the cost of the new tickets. Although the men had traditional [[beards]] and the women [[headscarves]], AirTran denied that their actions were based on the passengers' appearance.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2009/01/01/AR2009010101932.html?hpid=topnews 9 Muslim Passengers Removed From Jet]&lt;/ref&gt; The following day, after the incident received widespread media coverage, AirTran reversed its position and issued a public apology, adding that it would in fact reimburse the passengers for the cost of their rebooked tickets.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2009/01/02/AR2009010201695.html Airline Offers Apology Over Detained Muslim Passengers]&lt;/ref&gt;

===In video games===
* ''[[Muslim Massacre: The Game of Modern Religious Genocide]]'' is a controversial 2008 amateur [[shoot 'em up]] [[computer game]], as the aim of the game is to kill all Muslims that appear on the screen.  The game's creator took down the game's download site with a statement of apology on his personal website, claiming his original intention in releasing the game, to "mock the foreign policy of the United States and the commonly held belief in the United States that Muslims are a hostile people to be held with suspicion", had backfired and not been understood by the wider public, and that its release "did not achieve its intended effect and instead only caused hurt to hospitable, innocent people.".&lt;ref&gt;[http://kotaku.com/5049613/muslim-massacre-creator-tucks-tail-apologizes 'Muslim Massacre' Creator Tucks Tail, Apologizes] Kotaku.com, 14 September 2008. Retrieved 29 September 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; However it later emerged that the apology was indeed fake.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gamepolitics.com/2008/09/17/muslim-massacre-creator-my-apology-was-fake Muslim Massacre Creator: My Apology Was Fake | GamePolitics&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Thereafter, the ''[[LA Times]]'' Middle East blog ''Babylon &amp; Beyond'' printed a comment from an anonymous contributor to an article on the website of the Arab TV channel [[Al Arabiya]] about the game, which stated, "if it were a game showing Muslims [[Under Siege (2005 video game)|killing Israelis]], the whole world would have sought revenge."&lt;ref&gt;[http://latimesblogs.latimes.com/babylonbeyond/2008/09/middle-east-mus.html MIDDLE EAST: "Muslim massacre" game stirs debate]&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{col-begin}}
{{col-break}}
* [[Alliance of Civilizations]]
* [[Anti-Arabism]]
* [[Anti-Iranian sentiment]]
* [[Anti-Turkism]]
* [[Antireligion]]
* [[Antitheism]]
* [[The Clash of Civilizations]]
* [[Criticism of Islam]]
{{col-break}}
* [[Christian debate on persecution and toleration]]
* [[Islamophobia Watch]]
* [[Islamofascism]]
* [[Persecution of Muslims]]
* [[War against Islam]]
* [[Religious intolerance]]
* [[Religious persecution]]
* [[Religious segregation]]
* [[International Freedom Alliance]]
{{col-end}}

==Notes==
{{Reflist|2}}

==References==
* {{Cite encyclopedia |editor=Cashmore, E | encyclopedia=Encyclopedia of Race and Ethnic Studies |year=2003 |publisher=Routledge}}
* {{Cite book|last=Benn |first=T. |  coauthors=Jawad, H. |title=Muslim Women in the United Kingdom and Beyond: Experiences and Images |year=2004 |publisher=[[Brill]] |isbn=9004125817}}
*{{Cite book|last=Egorova |first=Y. |  coauthors=Parfitt, T. |title=Jews, Muslims, and Mass Media: Mediating the 'Other' |year=2003 |publisher=Routledge Curzon |location=London |isbn=0415318394}}
*{{Cite book|last=Haddad |first=Y. |  title=Muslims in the West: From Sojourners to Citizens |year=2002 |publisher=Oxford University Press |location=Oxford |isbn=0195148053}}
* {{Cite book|last=Johnson |first=M. R. D. |  coauthors=Soydan, H; Williams, C. |title=Social Work and Minorities: European Perspectives |location=London; New York |year=1998 |publisher=Routledge |isbn=0415169623}}
* {{Cite book|last=Miles |first=R. |  coauthors=Brown, M. |title=Racism |year=2003 |location=London; New York |publisher=Routledge |isbn=0415296765}}

===Further reading===
*{{Cite book|last=Abbas |first= Tahir |title=Muslim Britain: Communities Under Pressure |year=2005 |publisher=Zed |isbn=978-1842774496}}
*{{Cite book|last=van Driel |first=B. |title=Confronting Islamophobia In Educational Practice |year=2004 |publisher=Trentham Books |isbn=1858563402}}
*{{Cite book|last=Gottschalk |first=P. |coauthors=Greenberg, G. |title=Islamophobia: Making Muslims the Enemy |year=2007 |publisher=Rowman &amp; Littlefield publishers |location=Lanham |isbn=978-0742552869}}
*{{Cite book|last=Greaves |first=R. |title=Islam and the West Post 9/11 |year=2004 |publisher=Ashgate publishing Ltd|isbn=0754650057}}
*Kaplan, Jeffrey (2006). ''Islamophobia in America?: September 11 and Islamophobic Hate Crime'', Terrorism and Political Violence (Routledge), 18:1, 1 - 33.
* Kincheloe, Joe L. and Shirley R. Steinberg (2004).The Miseducation of the West: How the Schools and Media Distort Our Understanding of Islam. Westport, Connecticut: Praeger Press. (Arabic Edition, 2005).
*Pynting, Scott; Mason, Victoria (2007). ''The resistible rise of Islamophobia: Anti-Muslim racism in the UK and Australia before 11 September 2001''. Journal of Sociology, The Australian Sociological Association. 43(1): 61–86.
*{{Cite book|last=Richardson|first=John E.|title=(Mis)representing Islam: the racism and rhetoric of British broadsheet newspapers|publisher=[[John Benjamins Publishing Company]]|year=2004|isbn=9027226997|url=http://books.google.com/?id=WanqiF2XULsC&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q=|postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}}
* Shryock, Andrew, ed. ''Islamophobia/Islamophilia: Beyond the Politics of Enemy and Friend'' (Indiana University Press; 2010) 250 pages; essays on Islamophobia past and present; topics include the "neo-Orientalism" of three Muslim commentators today: Ayaan Hirsi Ali, Reza Aslan, and Irshad Manji.
*Tausch, Arno with Christian Bischof, Tomaz Kastrun and Karl Mueller (2007), ‘'Against Islamophobia: Muslim Communities, Social Exclusion and the Lisbon Process in Europe'’ Hauppauge, N.Y.: Nova Science Publishers
*Tausch, Arno with Christian Bischof, and Karl Mueller (2007), "Muslim Calvinism”, internal security and the Lisbon process in Europe Amsterdam: Rozenberg Publishers
* Tausch, Arno (2007), Against Islamophobia. Quantitative analyses of global terrorism, world political cycles and center periphery structures Hauppauge, N.Y.: Nova Science Publishers
*{{Cite book|last=Quraishi |first=M. |title=Muslims and Crime: A Comparative Study |year=2005 |publisher=Ashgate publishing Ltd|isbn=0-7546-4233-X}}
*{{Cite book|last=Ramadan |first=T. |title=Western Muslims and the Future of Islam |year=2004 |publisher=Oxford University Press |location=Oxford |isbn=0-19-517111-X}}
* Zuquete, Jose Pedro (2008), The European extreme-right and Islam: New directions, [http://www.citeulike.org/journal/routledg-cjpi['''Journal of Political Ideologies'''&amp;#93;]

==External links==
{{Sister project links}}
{{External links|date=August 2010}}
* [http://www.islamophobia.org/ Islamophobia.org]
* [http://www.reuters.com/article/pressRelease/idUS198159+09-Sep-2009+PRN20090909 Among U.S. Religious Groups, Muslims Seen as Facing More Discrimination]
* [http://www.islamawareness.net/Islamophobia/ "Islamophobia"], ''Islamicawareness.net''
* [http://www.islamophobia-watch.com/ Islamophobia Watch]
* [http://www.smearcasting.com/ Smearcasters]
* [http://www.guardian.co.uk/uk_news/story/0,,1997888,00.html "From Aladdin to Lost Ark, Muslims get angry at 'bad guy' film images"] -[[The Guardian]], 25 January 2007
* [http://www.sevenoaksmag.com/features/cupehumanrights.html Speech against Islamophobia and racism at CUPE National Conference in Vancouver, Canada]
* [http://islamonline.net/English/artculture/2005/01/article08.shtml Muslims and Islam in European History Textbooks]
* [http://www.keralanext.com/news/?id=1078945 Grant Bangladeshi Hindu migrants refugee status, but deport Bangladeshi Muslims: Rajnath Singh]{{dead link|date=October 2010}}
* [http://www.eyetopic.co.uk/Against_Islamophobia/index.htm "Rally against incitement and Islamophobia in London"], ''[[eyetopic.co.uk]]'', February 11, 2006.
* [[Chris Allen (UK)]] [http://www.chris-allen.co.uk/ Islamophobia resources: writing, articles &amp; publications]
* Dr. Louay Safi's [http://aninsight.org/labels/Islamophobia.html Articles on Islamophobia]
* Brooks, James. [http://www.islamonline.net/English/Views/2003/05/article11.shtml "Deep roots of Islamophobia]{{dead link|date=October 2010}} Islamonline.net.
* Deane, Claudia and Fears, Darryl. [http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2006/03/08/AR2006030802221.html Negative Perception Of Islam Increasing], ''The Washington Post'', March 9, 2006.
* [[Khaled Abou Al-Fadl|El Fadl, Khaled Abou]]. [http://www.scholarofthehouse.org/onrebi.html "On revising bigotry"], chapter from '' The Conference on the Books: The Search for Beauty in Islam'', ''Scholars of the House''.
* [[Muriel Gray|Gray, Muriel]]. [http://www.sundayherald.com/53959 "How can we have respect for Islam when we are too fearful to criticise it?"]{{dead link|date=October 2010}}, ''The Glasgow Herald'', February 5, 2006.
* Hassan, Fardusa. [http://www.guardian.co.uk/race/story/0,,1862329,00.html "Beauty queen enters Islamophobia debate"], ''The Guardian'', August 31, 2006.
* Hassan, Ghali. [http://www.uruknet.info/?p=m20398&amp;l=i&amp;size=1&amp;hd=0 The Road to the Muslim Holocaust], ''Globalresearch.ca'', February 7, 2006.
* Khan, Ali. [http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=935319 The Essentialist Terrorist] (how puritanical Islam is portrayed as essentially violent).
* [[Norman Lamont (1942)|Lamont, Norman]]. [http://www.telegraph.co.uk/opinion/main.jhtml?xml=/opinion/2002/05/08/do0801.xml "Down with multiculturalism, book-burning and fatwas"], ''The Daily Telegraph'', May 8, 2002.
* Marud, Abdal-Hakim. [http://www.masud.co.uk/ISLAM/ahm/right.htm "Muslims and the European Right"], ''Masud.co.uk'', first delivered as a lecture on April 30, 2000.
* [[Brigitte L. Nacos|Nacos, Brigitte L.]], ''Fueling Our Fears: Stereotyping, Media Coverage, and Public Opinion of Muslim Americans''. 2006
* O'Keefe, Derrick. [http://www.sevenoaksmag.com/commentary/macleans.html Maclean's magazine goes over-the-top with racist cover story], ''Seven Oaks Magazine'', October 27, 2006.
* [[Daniel Pipes|Pipes, Daniel]]. [http://www.danielpipes.org/article/3075 "Islamophobia?"], ''New York Sun'', October 25, 2005.
* Ramji, Rubina. [http://www.unomaha.edu/jrf/Vol9No2/RamjiIslam.htm "From ''Navy Seals'' to ''The Siege'': Getting to Know the Muslim Terrorist, Hollywood Style"] ''The Journal of Religion and Film'', Vol. 9, No.2, October 2005
* Riyanto, Geger. [http://www.thejakartapost.com/yesterdaydetail.asp?fileid=20061027.F04 "The Genealogy of today's Islamophobia"]{{dead link|date=October 2010}}, ''The Jakarta Post'', October 27, 2006.
* [[Walter Laqueur]]. [http://blog.oup.com/2006/10/the_origins_of_2/ The Origins of Fascism: Islamic Fascism, Islamophobia, Antisemitism], [[Oxford University Press]] blog.
* Barry Van, ''Confronting Islamophobia in Educational Practice'' ISBN 1-85856-340-2
* [[Stephen Castle|Castle, Stephen]]. [http://news.independent.co.uk/europe/article2084525.ece "Islamophobia takes a grip across Europe"], ''[[The Independent]]'', December 18, 2006.

{{Islam topics|state=collapsed}}
{{Discrimination}}
{{Theology}}

[[Category:Islam-related controversies]]
[[Category:Anti-Islam sentiment| ]]
[[Category:Political neologisms]]

[[ar:إسلاموفوبيا]]
[[be-x-old:Антыісламізм]]
[[bg:Ислямофобия]]
[[ca:Islamofòbia]]
[[cs:Islamofobie]]
[[cy:Islamophobia]]
[[da:Islamofobi]]
[[de:Islamophobie]]
[[el:Ισλαμοφοβία]]
[[es:Islamofobia]]
[[eo:Islamofobio]]
[[fa:اسلام‌هراسی]]
[[fr:Islamophobie]]
[[id:Islamofobia]]
[[it:Islamofobia]]
[[he:אסלאמופוביה]]
[[lv:Islāmfobija]]
[[ml:ഇസ്ലാമോഫോബിയ]]
[[arz:إسلاموفوبيا]]
[[ms:Islamofobia]]
[[nl:Islamofobie]]
[[ja:イスラム恐怖症]]
[[no:Islamofobi]]
[[uz:Islomofobiya]]
[[pl:Islamofobia]]
[[pt:Islamofobia]]
[[ro:Islamofobie]]
[[ru:Исламофобия]]
[[simple:Islamophobia]]
[[fi:Islamofobia]]
[[sv:Islamofobi]]
[[te:ఇస్లామోఫోబియా]]
[[tr:İslamofobi]]
[[zh:伊斯兰恐惧症]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>