<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20171122211312|811626126" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="162173" pageid="162173" ns="0" title="Islamophobia"><revisions><rev timestamp="2017-11-23T11:29:06Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{about|negative attitudes towards Muslims|religious persecution of Muslims|Persecution of Muslims|the scholarly criticism of Islam|Criticism of Islam}}
{{Islamophobia|expanded=all}}
{{Islam |related |width=22.0em}}
{{Discrimination sidebar}}
'''Islamophobia''' is defined as "Intense dislike or fear of Islam, esp. as a political force; hostility or prejudice towards Muslims".&lt;ref name=OED&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.oed.com/view/Entry/248449?|publisher=Oxford University Press|title=Oxford English Dictionary: Islamophobia}}{{paywall}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;See also:
* {{cite web|title=Islamophobia|url=https://en.oxforddictionaries.com/definition/islamophobia|website=en.oxforddictionaries.com|accessdate=10 November 2016}}
* {{cite web|title=Islamophobia|url=http://www.dictionary.com/browse/islamophobia|website=dictionary.com|accessdate=10 November 2016}}
* {{cite web|title=Islamophobia|url=http://www.collinsdictionary.com/dictionary/english/islamophobia|website=collinsdictionary.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The term Islamophobia was first used in the early 20th century and it emerged as a [[neologism]] in the 1970s, then it became increasingly salient during the 1980s and 1990s, and it reached public policy prominence with the report by the [[Runnymede Trust]]'s Commission on British Muslims and Islamophobia (CBMI) entitled ''Islamophobia: A Challenge for Us All'' (1997). The introduction of the term was justified by the report's assessment that "anti-Muslim prejudice has grown so considerably and so rapidly in recent years that a new item in the vocabulary is needed".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Meer|first1=Nasar|last2=Modood|first2=Tariq|title=Refutations of racism in the 'Muslim question'|journal=Patterns of Prejudice|date=July 2009|volume=43|issue=3-4|pages=335–54|doi=10.1080/00313220903109250}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The causes and characteristics of Islamophobia are still debated. Some commentators have posited an increase in Islamophobia resulting from the [[September 11 attacks]], while others have associated it with the increased presence of [[Muslims in the United States]] and [[Muslims in the European Union|in the European Union]]. Some people also question the validity of the term.  The academics S. Sayyid and Abdoolkarim Vakil maintain that Islamophobia is a response to the emergence of a distinct Muslim public identity globally, the presence of Muslims is in itself not an indicator of the degree of Islamophobia in a society. Sayyid and Vakil maintain that there are societies where virtually no Muslims live but many institutionalized forms of Islamophobia still exist in them.&lt;ref&gt;(Sayyid and Vakil, 2010)&lt;/ref&gt;

==Terms==
There are a number of other possible terms which are also used in order to refer to negative feelings and attitudes towards Islam and Muslims, such as '''anti-Muslimism''', '''intolerance against Muslims''', '''anti-Muslim prejudice''', '''anti-Muslim bigotry''', '''hatred of Muslims''', '''anti-Islamism''', '''Muslimophobia''', '''demonisation of Islam''', or '''demonisation of Muslims'''. In German, ''Islamophobie'' (fear) and ''Islamfeindlichkeit'' (hostility) are used. The Scandinavian term ''Muslimhat'' literally means "hatred of Muslims".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Kaya|first1=Ayhan|editor1-last=Cesari|editor1-first=Jocelyne|title=The Oxford Handbook of European Islam|date=2014|publisher=[[Oxford University Press]]|isbn=978-0-19-960797-6|chapter=Islamophobia}}&lt;/ref&gt;

When discrimination towards Muslims has placed an emphasis on their religious affiliation and adherence, it has been termed Muslimphobia, the alternative form of Muslimophobia,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Carpente|first1=Markus|title=Diversity, Intercultural Encounters, and Education|date=2013|page=65}}&lt;/ref&gt; Islamophobism,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Pande|first1=Rekha|title=Globalization, Technology Diffusion and Gender Disparity|date=2012|page=99}}&lt;/ref&gt; antimuslimness and antimuslimism.&lt;ref&gt;Racism and Human Rights. p. 8, Raphael Walden – 2004&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Muslims in Western Europe. p. 169, Jørgen S. Nielsen – 2004&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Children's Voices: Studies of Interethnic Conflict and Violence in European schools, Mateja Sedmak, p124&lt;/ref&gt; Individuals who discriminate against Muslims in general have been termed ''Islamophobes'', ''Islamophobists'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Kuwara|first1=Ibrahim|title=Islam Nigeria-UK Road Tour|date=2004|page=6}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''anti-Muslimists'',&lt;ref&gt;2002, Fred halliday, Two hours that shook the world, p. 97&lt;/ref&gt; ''antimuslimists'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Kollontai|first1=Pauline|title=Community Identity: Dynamics of Religion in Context|date=2007|page=254}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''islamophobiacs'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Seid|first1=Amine|title=Islamic Terrorism and the Tangential Response of the West|date=2011|page=39}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''anti-Muhammadan'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Goknar|first1=Erdag|title=Orhan Pamuk, Secularism and Blasphemy|date=2013|page=219}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Muslimphobes'' or its alternative spelling of ''Muslimophobes'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Arasteh|first1=Kamyar|title=The American Reichstag|date=2004|page=94}}&lt;/ref&gt; while individuals motivated by a specific anti-Muslim agenda or bigotry have been described as being ''anti-mosque'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Dressler|first1=Markus|title=Secularism and Religion-Making|date=2011|page=250}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''anti-Shiites''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Kaim|first1=Markus|title=Great Powers and Regional Orders|date=2013|page=157}}&lt;/ref&gt; (or ''Shiaphobes''&lt;ref&gt;2013, Glen Perry, The International Relations of the Contemporary Middle East, p. 161&lt;/ref&gt;), ''anti-Sufism''&lt;ref&gt;Toyin Falola – 2001, Violence in Nigeria: The Crisis of Religious Politics and Secular Ideologies, p. 240, ''"'''Anti-Sufism''' itself is therefore a marker of identity, and the formation of the Izala proves this beyond any reasonable doubt''".&lt;/ref&gt; (or ''Sufi-phobia'')&lt;ref&gt;Colonialism and Revolution in the Middle East, p. 197, Juan Ricardo Cole – 1999, ''"Ironically, the '''Sufi-phobia''' of the British consuls in the aftermath of 1857 led them to look in the wrong places for urban disturbances in the 1860s.''"&lt;/ref&gt; and ''anti-Sunni'' (or ''Sunniphobes'').&lt;ref&gt;'''2005''', Ahmed Hashim, ''Insurgency and Counter-insurgency in Iraq'', Cornell University Press (2006), {{ISBN|9780801444524}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Etymology and definitions ==
The word ''Islamophobia'' is a [[neologism]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |accessdate=2013-09-19 |url=http://uni-bonn.academia.edu/RolandImhoff/Papers/544018/Differentiating_Islamophobia_Introducing_a_new_scale_to_measure_Islamoprejudice_and_Secular_Islam_Critique |title=Differentiating Islamophobia: Introducing a new scale to measure Islamoprejudice and Secular Islam Critique |author=Roland Imhoff &amp; Julia Recker (University of Bonn) |publisher= |year=}}&lt;/ref&gt; formed from ''Islam'' and ''-phobia'', a [[suffix]] used in English to form "nouns with the sense 'fear of – – ', 'aversion to – – '."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.oed.com/view/Entry/142572?rskey=Glm8gY&amp;result=2#eid|publisher=Oxford University Press|title=Oxford English Dictionary: -phobia, ''comb. form''}}{{paywall}}&lt;/ref&gt; The compound form ''Islamo-'' contains the [[thematic stem|thematic vowel]] ''[[:wikt:-o-|-o-]]'', and is found in earlier coinages such as ''Islamo-Christian'' from the 19th century.

According to the ''[[Oxford English Dictionary]]'', the word means "Intense dislike or fear of Islam, esp. as a political force; hostility or prejudice towards Muslims" and is [[Attested language|attested]] in English as early as 1923.&lt;ref name="OED"/&gt;  The Berkeley University ''Islamophobia Research &amp; Documentation Project'' suggested the working definition: "Islamophobia is a contrived fear or prejudice fomented by the existing Eurocentric and Orientalist global power structure.  It is directed at a perceived or real Muslim threat through the maintenance and extension of existing disparities in economic, political, social and cultural relations, while rationalizing the necessity to deploy violence as a tool to achieve 'civilizational rehab' of the target communities (Muslim or otherwise).  Islamophobia reintroduces and reaffirms a global racial structure through which resource distribution disparities are maintained and extended."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://crg.berkeley.edu/content/islamophobia/defining-islamophobia|title=Defining "Islamophobia"  |publisher=Center for Race &amp; Gender}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Debate on the term and its limitations===
In 1996, the [[Runnymede Trust]] established the Commission on British Muslims and Islamophobia, chaired by [[Gordon Conway]], the [[vice-chancellor (education)|vice-chancellor]] of the [[University of Sussex]]. The Commission's report, ''Islamophobia: A Challenge for Us All'', was published in November 1997 by the Home Secretary, [[Jack Straw]]. In the Runnymede report, Islamophobia was defined as "an outlook or world-view involving an unfounded dread and dislike of Muslims, which results in practices of exclusion and discrimination."&lt;ref name="EoRE215"&gt;Encyclopedia of Race and Ethics, p. 215&lt;/ref&gt; [[Johannes Kandel]],{{who|date=May 2017}} in a 2006 comment wrote that Islamophobia "is a vague term which encompasses every conceivable actual and imagined act of hostility against Muslims", and proceeds to argue that five{{which|date=May 2017}} of the criteria put forward by the Runnymede Trust are invalid.&lt;ref&gt;Kandel, Johannes (August 2006). {{cite web|url= http://www.fes.de/BerlinerAkademiegespraeche/publikationen/islamundpolitik/documents/Islamophobia.pdf |title=Islamophobia&amp;nbsp;– On the Career of a Controversial Term }}&amp;nbsp;{{small|(118&amp;nbsp;KB)}}, [[Friedrich Ebert Foundation|Friedrich-Ebert-Stiftung]]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2008 a workshop on 'Thinking Thru Islamophobia' was held at the University of Leeds, organized by the Centre for Ethnicity and Racism Studies, the participants included S.Sayyid, Abdoolkarim Vakil, Liz Fekete, and Gabrielle Maranci among others.  The symposium proposed a definition of Islamophobia which rejected the idea of Islamophobia as being the product of closed and open views of Islam, and focused on Islamophobia as performative which problematized Muslim agency and identity. The symposium was an early attempt to bring insights from critical race theory, postcolonial and decolonial thought to bear on the question of Islamophobia. The presentations from the symposium were turned into an edited volume: Sayyid and Vakil eds. (2010) ''Thinking Through Islamophobia: Global Perspectives'' New York, Columbia University Press.

At a 2009 symposium on "Islamophobia and Religious Discrimination", Robin Richardson, a former director of the Runnymede Trust&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.runnymedetrust.org/bgRanimed.html|title=Runnymede Trust – Ranimed, Runnymede and a Long Report|publisher=|accessdate=18 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the editor of ''Islamophobia: a challenge for us all'',&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mcb.org.uk/article_detail.php?article=announcement-862 Mcb.org.uk] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120306001003/http://www.mcb.org.uk/article_detail.php?article=announcement-862 |date=2012-03-06 }}&lt;/ref&gt; said that "the disadvantages of the term Islamophobia are significant" on seven different grounds, including that it implies it is merely a "severe mental illness" affecting "only a tiny minority of people"; that use of the term makes those to whom it is applied "defensive and defiant" and absolves the user of "the responsibility of trying to understand them" or trying to change their views; that it implies that hostility to Muslims is divorced from factors such as skin color, immigrant status, fear of fundamentalism, or political or economic conflicts; that it conflates prejudice against Muslims in one's own country with dislike of Muslims in countries with which the West is in conflict; that it fails to distinguish between people who are against all religion from people who dislike Islam specifically; and that the actual issue being described is hostility to Muslims, "an ethno-religious identity within European countries", rather than hostility to Islam. Nonetheless, he argued that the term is here to stay, and that it is important to define it precisely.&lt;ref name=Richardson2009&gt;Richardson, Robin (December 2009). {{cite web|url= http://www.insted.co.uk/anti-muslim-racism.pdf |title="Islamophobia or anti-muslim racism&amp;nbsp;– or what?" }}&amp;nbsp;{{small|(119&amp;nbsp;KB)}}, Insted website. Accessed December 30, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

The exact definition of Islamophobia continues to be discussed with academics such as [[Chris Allen (academic)|Chris Allen]] saying that it lacks a clear definition.&lt;ref name=termlimits&gt;* {{cite book|author=[[Chris Allen (academic)|Allen, Chris]]|title=Islamophobia|publisher=Ashgate|year=2010|isbn=978-0754651390|page=21}}
{{cite journal|author=Bleich, Erik|date=December 2011|url=http://abs.sagepub.com/content/55/12/1581.abstract |title=What Is Islamophobia and How Much Is There? Theorizing and Measuring an Emerging Comparative Concept|journal=[[American Behavioral Scientist]]|volume=55|issue=12|pages=1581–1600|doi=10.1177/0002764211409387}}
* Cesari, Jocelyne (1 June 2006). {{cite web|url= http://www.euro-islam.info/wp-content/uploads/pdfs/securitization_and_religious_divides_in_europe.pdf |title=Muslims In Western Europe After 9/11: Why the term Islamophobia is more a predicament than an explanation }}&amp;nbsp;{{small|(118&amp;nbsp;KB)}}, [[Euro-Islam.Info]]: p. 5
{{cite journal|author=Imhoff, Roland &amp; Recker, Julia|title=Differentiating Islamophobia:Introducing a new scale to measure Islamoprejudice and Secular Islam Critique|journal=Political Psychology|volume=33|issue=6|pages=811–24|date=December 2012|doi=10.1111/j.1467-9221.2012.00911.x|last2=Recker}}{{cite book|editor=Andrew Shryock|title=[[Islamophobia/Islamophilia: Beyond the Politics of Enemy and Friend]]|year=2010|isbn=978-0-253-22199-5|publisher=[[Indiana University Press]]|page=6}}
{{cite book|title=Muslims in 21st Century Europe: Structural and Cultural Perspectives|editor=Anna Triandafyllidou|year=2010|publisher=Routledge|isbn=978-0415497091|page=28|author=Burak Erdenir}}&lt;/ref&gt;
According to Erik Bleich, in his article "Defining and Researching Islamophobia", even when definitions are more specific, there is still significant variation in the precise formulations of Islamophobia. As with parallel concepts like homophobia or xenophobia, Islamophobia connotes a broader set of negative attitudes or emotions directed at individuals of groups because of perceived membership in a defined category.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Bleich|first1=Erik|title=Defining and Researching Islamophobia|journal=Review Of Middle East Studies|volume=46|issue=2|page=181|accessdate=2015-11-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Mattias Gardell]] defines Islamophobia as "socially reproduced prejudices and aversion to Islam and Muslims, as well as actions and practices that attack, exclude or discriminate against persons on the basis that they are or perceived to be Muslim and be associated with Islam".&lt;ref name=levandedefinitioner/&gt;

===Fear===
[[File:IVČRN 14-03-2015 2.JPG|thumb|Speaker at demonstration of initiative ''We don't want Islam in the Czech Republic'' on March 14, 2015 in [[České Budějovice]], Czech Republic]]
As opposed to being a psychological or individualistic phobia, according to professors of religion Peter Gottschalk and Gabriel Greenberg, "Islamophobia" connotes a [[social anxiety]] about Islam and Muslims.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.wesleyan.edu/newsletter/campus/2007/1107islambook.html |title=Faculty, Alumnus Discuss Concept of "Islamophobia" in Co-Authored Book |accessdate=2007-12-29 |date=2007-11-20 |author=Corrina Balash Kerr |work=[[Wesleyan University]] Newsletter |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080820031422/http://www.wesleyan.edu/newsletter/campus/2007/1107islambook.html |archivedate=2008-08-20 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.politicalaffairs.net/article/articleview/6181/1/296/ |title=Images of Muslims: Discussing Islamophobia with Peter Gottschalk |accessdate=2007-12-29 |date=2007-11-19 |work=Political Affairs. |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20071206034654/http://www.politicalaffairs.net/article/articleview/6181/1/296/ &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-12-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some social scientists have adopted this definition and developed instruments to measure Islamophobia in form of fearful attitudes towards, and avoidance of, Muslims and Islam,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Lee | first1 = S. A. | last2 = Gibbons | first2 = J. A. | last3 = Thompson | first3 = J. M. | last4 = Timani | first4 = H. S. | year = 2009 | title = The islamophobia scale: Instrument development and initial validation | url = | journal = International Journal for the Psychology of Religion | volume = 19 | issue = 2| pages = 92–105 | doi = 10.1080/10508610802711137}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=kunst2012b&gt;{{cite journal |last1 = Kunst |first1 = J. R. |last2 = Sam |first2 = D. L. |last3 = Ulleberg |first3 = P. |year = 2012 |title = Perceived islamophobia: Scale development and validation |journal = International Journal of Intercultural Relations |volume = 37 |pages = 225–37|doi = 10.1016/j.ijintrel.2012.11.001}}&lt;/ref&gt; arguing that Islamophobia should "essentially be understood as an affective part of social stigma towards Islam and Muslims, namely fear".&lt;ref name=kunst2012b/&gt;{{rp|page=2}}

===Racism===
{{see also|New racism}}
Several scholars consider Islamophobia to be a form of [[xenophobia]] or [[racism]]. A 2007 article in ''Journal of Sociology'' defines Islamophobia as anti-Muslim racism and a continuation of anti-[[Asian people|Asian]], [[Anti-Turkism|anti-Turkic]] and [[Anti-Arabism|anti-Arab]] racism.&lt;ref name=racismquotes&gt;[http://www.tariqmodood.com/uploads/1/2/3/9/12392325/multicultural_state_we_are_in.pdf "The Multicultural State We're In: Muslims,'Multiculture' and the 'Civic Re‐balancing' of British Multiculturalism"], ''Political Studies'': 2009 Vol 57, 473–97
* [https://www.surrey.ac.uk/cronem/files/Tariq-Modood-article.pdf ''Remaking multiculturalism after 7/7'', Tariq Modood], 29 September 2005 {{quote|The most important such form of cultural racism today is anti-Muslim racism, sometimes called Islamophobia.}}
* {{cite book|title=The Islamophobia Industry: How the Right Manufactures Fear of Muslims|author=Nathan Lean|isbn=978-0745332543|year=2012|publisher=Pluto Press}}{{quote| "Biological racist discourses have now been replaced by what is called the 'new racism' or 'cultural racist' discourses." }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | last1 = Poynting | first1 = S. | last2 = Mason | first2 = V. | doi = 10.1177/1440783307073935 | title = The resistible rise of Islamophobia: Anti-Muslim racism in the UK and Australia before 11 September 2001 | journal = Journal of Sociology | volume = 43 | pages = 61–86 | year = 2007 | pmid =  | pmc = }}&lt;/ref&gt; In their books [[Deepa Kumar]] and Junaid Rana have argued that formation of Islamophobic discourses has paralleled the development of other forms of racial bigotry.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Review: beyond "post 9/11" (''Islamophobia and the Politics of Empire'' by Deepa Kumar; ''Terrifying Muslims: Race and Labor in the South Asian Diaspora'' by Junaid Rana)|author=Erik Love|journal=Contexts| volume=12|number=1|year=2013|pages=70–72|url=https://www.jstor.org/stable/41960426|via=[[JSTOR]]|subscription=yes|quote=Taking these two works together, Kumar and Rana put forth a strong argument that while Islam is certainly a religion, and not a race, and Muslims (like all religious communities) are a highly diverse group in terms of ethnicity, nationality, and even racial backgrounds, Islamophobia is in fact a form of racism. Both books effectively provide historical accounts showing the parallel development of Islamophobic discourses alongside other forms of racial bigotry and discrimination.}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Similarly, [[John Denham (politician)|John Denham]] has drawn parallels between modern Islamophobia and the [[antisemitism]] of the 1930s,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/uk/article6832035.ece|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110510093750/http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/uk/article6832035.ece|archive-date=May 10, 2011|title=Fascism fears: John Denham speaks out over clashes|publisher=|date=September 12, 2009|accessdate=18 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; so have [[Maud Olofsson]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.svd.se/nyheter/inrikes/artikel_3674445.svd|title=Reinfeldt: Kärnan i partiets idé|author=Dan Nilsson-dan.nilsson@svd.se|work=SvD.se|accessdate=18 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Jan Hjärpe]], among others.&lt;ref&gt;
* [http://www.nasarmeer.com/uploads/7/7/4/6/7746984/meer_and_noorani_-_the_sociological_review.pdf "A sociological comparison of anti-Semitism and anti-Muslim sentiment in Britain", Nasar Meer, Tehseen Noorani ''[[The Sociological Review]]'', Volume 56, Issue 2, pp. 195–219, May 2008] {{quote|Across Europe activists and certain academics are struggling to get across an understanding in their governments and their countries at large that anti-Muslim racism/Islamophobia is now one of the most pernicious forms of contemporary racism and that steps should be taken to combat it.}}
* [http://rac.sagepub.com/content/52/3/77.short Anti-Semitism and Islamophobia – new enemies, old patterns]&lt;/ref&gt;

Others have questioned the supposed relationship between Islamophobia and racism. Jocelyne Cesari writes that "academics are still debating the legitimacy of the term and questioning how it differs from other terms such as racism, anti-Islamism, anti-Muslimness, and anti-Semitism."&lt;ref&gt;Jocelyne Cesari [http://www.euro-islam.info/wp-content/uploads/pdfs/securitization_and_religious_divides_in_europe.pdf "Muslims In Western Europe After 9/11: Why the term Islamophobia is more a predicament than an explanation"] Submission to the Changing Landscape of Citizenship and Security: 6th PCRD of European Commission. 1 June 2006: p. 6&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=cesariA&gt;{{cite book|title=Islamophobia: The Challenge of Pluralism in the 21st Century|editor=[[John L. Esposito]]|year=2011|publisher=[[Oxford University Press]]|isbn=978-0199753642|page=21}}&lt;/ref&gt; Erdenir finds that "there is no consensus on the scope and content of the term and its relationship with concepts such as racism ..."&lt;ref name=Triandafyllidou&gt;{{cite book|title=Muslims in 21st Century Europe: Structural and Cultural Perspectives|editor=Anna Triandafyllidou|year=2010|publisher=Routledge|isbn=978-0415497091|page=28}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Shryock, reviewing the use of the term across national boundaries, comes to the same conclusion.&lt;ref name=ShryockA&gt;{{cite book|title=Islamophobia/Islamophilia: Beyond the Politics of Enemy and Friend|editor=Andrew Shryock|year=2010|pages=6–25|publisher=Indiana University Press|isbn=978-0253221995}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some scholars view Islamophobia and racism as partially overlapping phenomena. Diane Frost defines Islamophobia as anti-Muslim feeling and violence based on "race" or religion.&lt;ref name=DianeFrost&gt;{{Cite journal | last1 = Frost | first1 = D. | title = Islamophobia: Examining causal links between the media and "race hate" from "below" | doi = 10.1108/01443330810915251 | journal = International Journal of Sociology and Social Policy | volume = 28 | issue = 11/12 | pages = 564–78 | year = 2008 | pmid =  | pmc = }}&lt;/ref&gt; Islamophobia may also target people who have Muslim names, or have a look that is associated with Muslims.&lt;ref name="levandehistoria"/&gt; According to [[Alan Johnson]], Islamophobia sometimes can be nothing more than xenophobia or racism "wrapped in religious terms."&lt;ref name=Johnson20110306&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.worldaffairsjournal.org/blog/alan-johnson/idea-'islamophobia'|title=The Idea of 'Islamophobia'|author=Alan Johnson|date=6 Mar 2011|publisher=World Affairs}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[European Commission against Racism and Intolerance]] (ECRI) defines Islamophobia as "the fear of or prejudiced viewpoint towards Islam, Muslims and matters pertaining to them", adding that whether "it takes the shape of daily forms of racism and discrimination or more violent forms, Islamophobia is a violation of human rights and a threat to social cohesion".&lt;ref name=levandedefinitioner&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.levandehistoria.se/fakta-fordjupning/islamofobi/definitioner-och-uttryck|title=Islamofobi – definitioner och uttryck|work=Forum för levande historia|accessdate=18 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Proposed alternatives===
The concept of Islamophobia as formulated by Runnymede was also criticized by professor [[Fred Halliday]] on several levels. He writes that the target of hostility in the modern era is not Islam and its tenets as much as it is Muslims, suggesting that a more accurate term would be "Anti-Muslimism". He also states that strains and types of prejudice against Islam and Muslims vary across different nations and cultures, which is not recognized in the Runnymede analysis, which was specifically about Muslims in Britain.&lt;ref name="Aldridge1"&gt;{{Cite book| last=Aldridge |first=Alan |title=Religion in the Contemporary World: A Sociological Introduction |date=February 1, 2000 |publisher=Polity Press |isbn=978-0-7456-2083-1 |page=138 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Poole responds that many Islamophobic discourses attack what they perceive to be Islam's tenets, while Miles and Brown write that Islamophobia is usually based upon negative stereotypes about Islam which are then translated into attacks on Muslims. They also argue that "the existence of different 'Islamophobias' does not invalidate the concept of Islamophobia any more than the existence of different racisms invalidates the concept of racism."&lt;ref name="MB165"&gt;Miles; Brown (2003) pp. 165–66&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Poole, E. (2003) p. 219&lt;/ref&gt;

In a 2011 paper in ''American Behavioral Scientist'', Erik Bleich stated "there is no widely accepted definition of Islamophobia that permits systematic comparative and causal analysis", and advances "indiscriminate negative attitudes or emotions directed at Islam or Muslims" as a possible solution to this issue.&lt;ref name="Bleich"&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Bleich | first1 = Erik | year = 2011 | title = What Is Islamophobia and How Much Is There? Theorizing and Measuring an Emerging Comparative Concept | url = http://abs.sagepub.com/content/55/12/1581.abstract | journal = [[American Behavioral Scientist]] | volume = 55 | issue = 12| pages = 1581–1600 | doi=10.1177/0002764211409387}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In order to differentiate between prejudiced views of Islam and secularly motivated criticism of Islam, Roland Imhoff and Julia Recker formulated the concept "Islamoprejudice", which they subsequently operationalised in an experiment. The experiment showed that their definition provided a tool for accurate differentiation.&lt;ref name=Imhoff&gt;Imhoff, Roland &amp; Recker, Julia [http://uni-bonn.academia.edu/RolandImhoff/Papers/544018/Differentiating_Islamophobia_Introducing_a_new_scale_to_measure_Islamoprejudice_and_Secular_Islam_Critique "Differentiating Islamophobia: Introducing a new scale to measure Islamoprejudice and Secular Islam Critique"] Journal of Political Psychology&lt;/ref&gt; Nevertheless, other researchers' experimental work indicates that, even when Westerners seem to make an effort to distinguish between criticizing (Muslim) ideas and values and respecting Muslims as persons, they still show prejudice and discrimination of Muslims—compared to non-Muslims—when these targets defend supposedly antiliberal causes.&lt;ref&gt;Van der Noll, J., Saroglou, V., Latour, D., &amp; Dolezal, N. (2017). Western anti-Muslim prejudice: Value conflict or discrimination of persons too? ''Political Psychology''.https://dx.doi.org/10.1111/pops.12416&lt;/ref&gt;

==Origins and causes==

===History of the term===

One early use cited as the term's first use is by the painter [[Étienne Dinet|Alphonse Étienne Dinet]] and [[Algeria]]n intellectual Sliman ben Ibrahim in their 1918 biography of Islam's prophet [[Muhammad]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=La Vie de Mohammed, Prophète d’Allah |last1=Dinet |first1=Alphonse Étienne |last2=ben Ibrahim |first2=Sliman |year=1918 |publisher= |location=Paris}} cited from {{Cite book|last1=Otterbeck |first1=Jonas |last2=Bevelander |first2=Pieter |year=2006 |title=Islamofobi&amp;nbsp; – en studie av begreppet, ungdomars attityder och unga muslimars utsatthet |publisher=Forum för levande historia |publication-place=Stockholm |language=Swedish |isbn=91-976073-6-3 |url=http://www.levandehistoria.se/files/islamofobi.pdf |format=PDF |accessdate=23 November 2011 |quote="modern orientalists [are partially] influenced by an islamofobia, which is poorly reconciled with science and hardly worthy of our time" |others=Anders Lange |postscript={{inconsistent citations}} |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120119025153/http://www.levandehistoria.se/files/islamofobi.pdf |archivedate=19 January 2012 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Allen2010pp5-6&gt;Allen, Christopher (2010). ''Islamophobia''. [[Ashgate Publishing]]. pp.&amp;nbsp;5–6.&lt;/ref&gt; Writing in French, they used the term ''{{wiktfr|islamophobie}}''. Robin Richardson writes that in the English version of the book the word was not translated as "Islamophobia" but rather as "feelings inimical to Islam". Dahou Ezzerhouni has cited several other uses in French as early as 1910, and from 1912 to 1918.&lt;ref&gt;Ezzerhouni, Dahou. [http://www.algerie-focus.com/2010/02/03/lislamophobie-un-racisme-apparu-avec-les-colonisations/ "L'islamophobie, un racisme apparu avec les colonisations"], ''Algerie-Focus'', February 3, 2010. "Le mot serai ainsi apparu pour la première fois dans quelques ouvrages du début du XXème siècle. On peut citer entre autre « La politique musulmane dans l’Afrique Occidentale Française » d’Alain Quellien publié en 1910, suivi de quelques citations dans la Revue du Monde Musulman en 1912 et 1918, la Revue du Mercure de France en 1912, « Haut-Sénégal-Niger » de Maurice Delafosse en 1912 et dans le Journal of Theological Studies en 1924. L’année suivante, Etienne Dinet et Slimane Ben Brahim, employaient ce terme qui «conduit à l’aberration » dans leur ouvrage « L’Orient vu par l’Occident »."&lt;/ref&gt; These early uses of the term did not, according to [[Chris Allen (academic)|Christopher Allen]], have the same meaning as in contemporary usage, as they described a fear of Islam by liberal Muslims and Muslim feminists, rather than a fear or dislike/hatred of Muslims by non-Muslims.&lt;ref name=Allen2010pp5-6/&gt;&lt;ref name=Allen2007&gt;{{Cite journal|url=http://www.isn.ethz.ch/isn/Digital-Library/Publications/Detail/?ots591=0c54e3b3-1e9c-be1e-2c24-a6a8c7060233&amp;lng=en&amp;id=45668|title=Islamophobia and its Consequences|author=[[Chris Allen (academic)|Chris Allen]]|journal=European Islam|publisher=Centre for European Policy Studies|year=2007|pages=144–67}}&lt;/ref&gt; On the other hand, Fernando Bravo López argues that Dinet and ibn Sliman's use of the term was as a criticism of overly hostile attitudes to Islam by a Belgian orientalist, Henri Lammens, whose project they saw as a "'pseudo-scientific crusade in the hope of bringing Islam down once and for all.'" He also notes that an early definition of Islamophobia appears in the Ph.D. thesis of Alain Quellien, a French colonial bureaucrat:
&lt;blockquote&gt;For some, the Muslim is the natural and irreconcilable enemy of the Christian and the European; Islam is the negation of civilization, and barbarism, bad faith and cruelty are the best one can expect from the Mohammedans.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
Furthermore, he notes that Quellien's work draws heavily on the work of the French colonial department's 1902–06 administrator, who published a work in 1906, which to a great extent mirrors [[John Esposito]]'s ''The Islamic Threat: Myth or Reality?''.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | last1 = Bravo López | first1 = F. | title = Towards a definition of Islamophobia: Approximations of the early twentieth century | doi = 10.1080/01419870.2010.528440 | journal = Ethnic and Racial Studies | volume = 34 | issue = 4 | pages = 556–73 | year = 2011 | pmid =  | pmc = }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The first recorded use of the term in English, according to the [[Oxford English Dictionary]], was in 1923 in an article in ''[[The Journal of Theological Studies]]''.&lt;ref name=OED/&gt; The term entered into common usage with the publication of the Runnymede Trust's report in 1997.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last1=Otterbeck |first1=Jonas |last2=Bevelander |first2=Pieter |year=2006 |title=Islamofobi&amp;nbsp; – en studie av begreppet, ungdomars attityder och unga muslimars utsatthet |publisher=Forum för levande historia |publication-place=Stockholm |language=Swedish |isbn=91-976073-6-3 |url=http://www.levandehistoria.se/files/islamofobi.pdf |accessdate=23 November 2011 |others=Anders Lange |postscript={{inconsistent citations}} |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120119025153/http://www.levandehistoria.se/files/islamofobi.pdf |archivedate=19 January 2012 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt; Kofi Annan asserted at a 2004 conference entitled "Confronting Islamophobia" that the word Islamophobia had to be coined in order to "take account of increasingly widespread bigotry".&lt;ref Name=Annan&gt;[[Kofi Annan|Annan, Kofi]]. [https://www.un.org/News/Press/docs/2004/sgsm9637.doc.htm "Secretary-General, addressing headquarters seminar Wed Confronting Islamophobia"], [[United Nations]], press release, December 7, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Contrasting views on Islam===
The Runnymede report contrasted "open" and "closed" views of Islam, and stated that the following eight "closed" views are equated with Islamophobia:

:#Islam is seen as a monolithic bloc, static and unresponsive to change.
:#It is seen as separate and "other". It does not have values in common with other cultures, is not affected by them and does not influence them.
:#It is seen as inferior to the West. It is seen as barbaric, irrational, primitive, and [[sexist]].
:#It is seen as violent, aggressive, threatening, supportive of [[terrorism]], and engaged in a [[clash of civilizations]].
:#It is seen as a political [[ideology]], used for political or military advantage.
:#Criticisms made of "the West" by Muslims are rejected out of hand.
:#Hostility towards Islam is used to justify discriminatory practices towards Muslims and exclusion of Muslims from mainstream society.
:#Anti-Muslim hostility is seen as natural and normal.&lt;ref name=Runnymede1997&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.runnymedetrust.org/uploads/publications/pdfs/islamophobia.pdf |title="Islamophobia: A Challenge for Us All" }}&amp;nbsp;{{small|(69.7&amp;nbsp;KB)}}, ''Runnymede Trust'', 1997.&lt;/ref&gt;

These "closed" views are contrasted, in the report, with "open" views on Islam which, while founded on respect for Islam, permit legitimate disagreement, dialogue and critique.&lt;ref&gt;Benn; Jawad (2004) p. 162&lt;/ref&gt; According to Benn and Jawad, The Runnymede Trust notes that anti-Muslim discourse is increasingly seen as respectable, providing examples on how hostility towards Islam and Muslims is accepted as normal, even among those who may actively challenge other prevalent forms of discrimination.&lt;ref name="Brill165"&gt;Benn; Jawad (2004) p. 165&lt;/ref&gt;

===Identity politics===
[[File:ARUNPATHAK5.JPG|thumb|[[Hindutva|Hindu nationalist]] politician [[Arun Pathak]] organised a celebration in Varanasi to commemorate the [[Demolition of Babri Masjid|1992 demolition of the Babri Masjid mosque]].]]
It has been suggested that Islamophobia is closely related to [[identity politics]], and gives its adherents the perceived benefit of constructing their identity in opposition to a negative, essentialized image of Muslims. This occurs in the form of self-righteousness, assignment of blame and key identity markers.&lt;ref name="doving1"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Døving |first1=Cora Alexa |year=2010 |title=Anti-Semitism and Islamophobia: A Comparison of Imposed Group Identities |journal=Tidsskrift for Islamforskning |issue=2 |pages=52–76 |publisher=Forum for Islamforskning |url=http://islamforskning.dk/files/journal/2010/FIFO-2010-2-del4.pdf |format=PDF |accessdate=23 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Davina Bhandar writes that:&lt;ref name="Bhandar"&gt;{{Cite journal | last1 = Bhandar | first1 = D. | title = Cultural politics: Disciplining citizenship | doi = 10.1080/13621021003731963 | journal = Citizenship Studies | volume = 14 | issue = 3 | pages = 331–43 | year = 2010 | pmid =  | pmc = }}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|text=[...] the term 'cultural' has become synonymous with the category of the ethnic or minority (...). It views culture as an entity that is highly abstracted from the practices of daily life and therefore represents the illusion that there exists a spirit of the people. This formulation leads to the homogenisation of cultural identity and the ascription of particular values and proclivities onto minority cultural groups.}}

She views this as an [[ontology|ontological]] trap that hinders the perception of culture as something "materially situated in the living practices of the everyday, situated in time-space and not based in abstract projections of what constitutes either a particular tradition or culture."

In some societies, Islamophobia has materialized due to the portrayal of Islam and Muslims as the national "[[Other (philosophy)|Other]]", where exclusion and discrimination occurs on the basis of their religion and civilization which differs with national tradition and identity. Examples include Pakistani and Algerian migrants in Britain and France respectively.&lt;ref&gt;Poole, E. (2003) p. 216&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = "Brown-p163"/&gt; This sentiment, according to Malcolm Brown and Robert Miles, significantly interacts with [[racism]], although Islamophobia itself is not racism.&lt;ref name="Miles; Brown 2003 pp. 163, 164"&gt;Miles; Brown (2003) pp. 163–64&lt;/ref&gt; Author [[Doug Saunders]] has drawn parallels between [[Islamophobia in the United States]] and its older [[Anti-Catholicism in the United States|discrimination and hate against Roman Catholics]], saying that Catholicism was seen as backwards and imperial, while Catholic immigrants had poorer education and some were responsible for crime and terrorism.&lt;ref&gt;Saunders, Doug (18 September 2012). [https://www.nytimes.com/2012/09/18/opinion/catholics-then-muslims-now.html "Catholics Then, Muslims Now"]. ''The New York Times''. Retrieved 18 February 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="racismlist"&gt;
{{cite book
|author=Fredman, Sandra
|title=Discrimination and human rights: the case of racism
|publisher=Oxford University Press
|location=Oxford [Oxfordshire]
|year=2001
|isbn=0-19-924603-3
|page=121}}
* {{cite book
|author=[[Yvonne Haddad|Haddad, Yvonne Yazbeck]]
|title=Muslims in the West: from sojourners to citizens
|publisher=Oxford University Press
|location=Oxford [Oxfordshire]
|year=2002
|isbn=0-19-514806-1
|page=19}}
* ''Islamophobia: A Challenge for Us All'', Runnymede Trust, 1997, p. 1, cited in {{cite book
|author=Quraishi, Muzammil
|title=Muslims and crime: a comparative study
|publisher=Ashgate
|location=Aldershot, Hants, England
|year=2005
|isbn=0-7546-4233-X|page=60}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=HoldenHicks&gt;{{cite book
|author1=Holden, Cathie |author2=Hicks, David V. |title=Teaching the global dimension: key principles and effective practice
|publisher=Routledge
|location=New York
|year=2007
|isbn=0-415-40448-7|page=140}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="HoldenHicks"/&gt;&lt;ref name=levandehistoria&gt;[http://www.levandehistoria.se/files/islamofobi.pdf Islamofobi – en studie av begreppet, ungdomars attityder och unga muslimers utsatthet] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120119025153/http://www.levandehistoria.se/files/islamofobi.pdf |date=2012-01-19 }}, published by [[Forum för levande historia]]
&lt;br /&gt;[http://hdl.handle.net/1885/45034 The rise of anti-Muslim racism in Australia: who benefits?]
&lt;br /&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Poynting | first1 =  | last2 = Mason | first2 =  | year = 2006 | title = Tolerance, Freedom, Justice and Peace?: Britain, Australia and Anti-Muslim Racism since 11 September 2001 | url = | journal = Journal of Intercultural Studies | volume = 27 | issue = 4| pages = 365–91 | doi = 10.1080/07256860600934973 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Brown and Miles write that another feature of Islamophobic discourse is to amalgamate nationality (e.g. Saudi), religion (Islam), and politics (terrorism, fundamentalism)&amp;nbsp; – while most other religions are not associated with terrorism, or even "ethnic or national distinctiveness."&lt;ref name = "Brown-p163"&gt;Miles; Brown (2003) p. 163&lt;/ref&gt; They feel that "many of the stereotypes and misinformation that contribute to the articulation of Islamophobia are rooted in a particular perception of Islam", such as the notion that Islam promotes terrorism&amp;nbsp; – especially prevalent after the [[September 11, 2001 attacks]].&lt;ref&gt;Miles; Brown (2003) p. 166&lt;/ref&gt;

The two-way stereotyping resulting from Islamophobia has in some instances resulted in mainstreaming of earlier controversial discourses, such as liberal attitudes towards gender equality&lt;ref name="doving1"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Bhandar"/&gt; and homosexuals.&lt;ref name=Mepschen2010&gt;{{Cite journal | last1 = Mepschen | first1 = P. | last2 = Duyvendak | first2 = J. W. | last3 = Tonkens | first3 = E. H. | doi = 10.1177/0038038510375740 | title = Sexual Politics, Orientalism and Multicultural Citizenship in the Netherlands | journal = Sociology | volume = 44 | issue = 5 | pages = 962–79 | year = 2010 | pmid =  | pmc = }}&lt;/ref&gt; Christina Ho has warned against framing of such mainstreaming of gender equality in a [[colonialism|colonial]], [[paternalism|paternal]] discourse, arguing that this may undermine minority women's ability to speak out about their concerns.&lt;ref name=Ho2007&gt;{{Cite journal | last = Ho | first = Christina | title = Muslim women's new defenders: Women's rights, nationalism and Islamophobia in contemporary Australia | journal = [[Women's Studies International Forum]] | volume = 30 | issue = 4 | pages = 290–98 | doi = 10.1016/j.wsif.2007.05.002 | date = July–August 2007 | ref = harv | postscript = .}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Steven Salaita]] contends that, since 9/11, [[Arab Americans]] have evolved from what Nadine Naber described as an invisible group in the United States into a highly visible community that directly or indirectly has an effect on the United States' culture wars, foreign policy, presidential elections and legislative tradition.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|url = |title = Beyond Orientalism and Islamophobia: 9/11, Anti-Arab Racism, and the Mythos of National Pride|last = Salaita|first = Steven|date = Fall 2006|journal = CR: The New Centennial Review|doi = |pmid = |access-date = November 20, 2015|issue = 2|volume = 6}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Links to ideologies===
Cora Alexa Døving, a senior scientist at the Norwegian [[Center for Studies of the Holocaust and Religious Minorities (Norway)|Center for Studies of the Holocaust and Religious Minorities]], argues that there are significant similarities between Islamophobic discourse and European pre-Nazi antisemitism.&lt;ref name="doving1"/&gt; Among the concerns are imagined threats of minority growth and domination, threats to traditional institutions and customs, skepticism of integration, threats to [[secularism]], fears of sexual crimes, fears of [[misogyny]], fears based on historical cultural inferiority, hostility to modern Western [[Age of Enlightenment|Enlightenment]] values, etc.

[[Matti Bunzl]] has argued that there are important differences between Islamophobia and antisemitism. While antisemitism was a phenomenon closely connected to European [[nation-building]] processes, he sees Islamophobia as having the concern of European civilization as its focal point.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Anti-semitism and Islamophobia: hatreds old and new in Europe |last=Bunzl |first=Matti |year=2007 |publisher=Prickly Paradigm Press |location=Chicago |isbn=978-0-9761475-8-9 |page=13 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=37UsAQAAIAAJ&amp;q=%22Islamophobic+claims%22#search_anchor |accessdate=23 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Døving, on the other hand, maintains that, at least in Norway, the Islamophobic discourse has a clear national element.&lt;ref name="doving1"/&gt; In a reply to Bunzl, French scholar of Jewish history, [[Esther Benbassa]], agrees with him in that he draws a clear connection between modern hostile and essentializing sentiments towards Muslims and historical antisemitism. However, she argues against the use of the term ''Islamophobia'', since, in her opinion, it attracts unwarranted attention to an underlying racist current.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Anti-Semitism and Islamophobia: Hatred Old and New in Europe |chapter=Xenophobia, Anti-Semitism, and Racism |last=Benbassa |first=Esther |year=2007 |publisher=Prickly Paradigm Press |location=Chicago |isbn=978-0-9761475-8-9 |pages=86ff |url=http://www.estherbenbassa.net/SCANS/XENOPHOBIA.PDF |format=PDF |accessdate=23 November 2011 |editor-last=Bunzl |editor-first=Matti}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The head of the Media Responsibility Institute in [[Erlangen]], Sabine Schiffer, and researcher Constantin Wagner, who also define Islamophobia as anti-Muslim racism, outline additional similarities and differences between Islamophobia and antisemitism.&lt;ref name =schiffer&gt;{{Cite journal | last1 = Schiffer | first1 = S. | last2 = Wagner | first2 = C. | doi = 10.1177/0306396810389927 | title = Anti-Semitism and Islamophobia – new enemies, old patterns | journal = Race &amp; Class | volume = 52 | issue = 3 | pages = 77–84 | year = 2011 | pmid =  | pmc = }}&lt;/ref&gt; They point out the existence of equivalent notions such as "Judaisation/Islamisation", and metaphors such as "a state within a state" are used in relation to both Jews and Muslims. In addition, both discourses make use of, among other rhetorical instruments, "religious imperatives" supposedly "proven" by religious sources, and conspiracy theories.

The differences between Islamophobia and antisemitism consist of the nature of the perceived threats to the "Christian West". Muslims are perceived as "inferior" and as a visible "external threat", while on the other hand, Jews are perceived as "omnipotent" and as an invisible "internal threat". However, Schiffer and Wagner also note that there is a growing tendency to view Muslims as a privileged group that constitute an "internal threat" and that this convergence between the two discources makes "it more and more necessary to use findings from the study of anti-Semitism to analyse Islamophobia". Schiffer and Wagner conclude,

{{quote|The achievement in the study of anti-Semitism of examining Jewry and anti-Semitism separately must also be transferred to other racisms, such as Islamophobia. We do not need more information about Islam, but more information about the making of racist stereotypes in general.}}

The publication ''Social Work and Minorities: European Perspectives'' describes Islamophobia as the new form of racism in Europe,&lt;ref&gt;Johnson; Soydan; Williams (1998) p. 182&lt;/ref&gt; arguing that "Islamophobia is as much a form of racism as [[anti-semitism]], a term more commonly encountered in Europe as a sibling of racism, xenophobia and Intolerance."&lt;ref&gt;Johnson; Soydan; Williams (1998) p. xxii&lt;/ref&gt; [[Edward Said]] considers Islamophobia as it is evinced in [[Orientalism]] to be a trend in a more general antisemitic Western tradition.&lt;ref&gt;Edward W. Said, 'Orientalism Reconsidered' in Francis Barker, Peter Hulme, Margaret Iversen, Diana Loxley (eds),'' Literature, Politics, and Theory,'' Methuen &amp; Co, London 1986 pp. 210229, pp. 220ff.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Bryan S. Turner (sociologist)|Bryan Stanley Turner]], introd. to Bryan S. Turner (ed.) ''Orientalism: Early Sources'', (Vol 1, Readings in Orientalism), Routledge, London (2000) reprint 2002 p. 12&lt;/ref&gt; Others note that there has been a transition from anti-Asian and anti-Arab racism to anti-Muslim racism,&lt;ref&gt;[http://jos.sagepub.com/content/43/1/61.abstract The resistible rise of Islamophobia – Anti-Muslim racism in the UK and Australia before 11 September 2001], [[Journal of Sociology]] March 2007 vol. 43 no. 1 61–86&lt;/ref&gt; while some note a racialization of religion.&lt;ref&gt;Contemporary racism and Islamaphobia in Australia – Racializing religion, Ethnicities December 2007 vol. 7 no. 4 564–589&lt;/ref&gt;

According to a 2012 report by a UK anti-racism group, [[counterjihad|counter-jihadist]] outfits in Europe and North America are becoming more cohesive by forging alliances, with 190 groups now identified as promoting an Islamophobic agenda.&lt;ref name = "MaTo 14Apr2012"&gt;{{cite news |url= https://www.theguardian.com/world/2012/apr/14/breivik-trial-norway-mass-murderer |title= Far-right anti-Muslim network on rise globally as Breivik trial opens |author= Mark Townsend |date= 14 April 2012 |publisher= guardian.co.uk |accessdate= 15 April 2012 |location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; In ''Islamophobia and its consequences on young people'' (p.&amp;nbsp;6) Ingrid Ramberg writes "Whether it takes the shape of daily forms of racism and discrimination or more violent forms, Islamophobia is a violation of human rights and a threat to social cohesion.". Professor [[John Esposito]] of [[Georgetown University]] calls Islamophobia "the new anti-Semitism".&lt;ref name="thestar.com"&gt;{{cite news| url=https://www.thestar.com/news/insight/article/1055298--islamophobia-the-new-anti-semitism |title=Islamophobia: The new anti-Semitism| location=Toronto | work=The Star}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Mohamed Nimer]] compares Islamophobia with anti-Americanism. He argues that while both Islam and America can be subject to legitimate criticisms without detesting a people as a whole, bigotry against both are on the rise.&lt;ref name=NimerA&gt;{{cite book|title=Islamophobia: The Challenge of Pluralism in the 21st Century|editor=[[John L. Esposito]]|author=Mohamed Nimer|year=2011|publisher=[[Oxford University Press]]|isbn=978-0199753642|page=76}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Opposition to multiculturalism===
According to Gabrielle Maranci, the increasing Islamophobia in the West is related to a rising [[Criticism of multiculturalism|repudiation of multiculturalism]]. Maranci concludes that "Islamophobia is a 'phobia' of multiculturalism and the transruptive effect that Islam can have in Europe and the West through transcultural processes."&lt;ref&gt;Gabriele Marranci: "Multiculturalism, Islam and the clash of civilisations theory: rethinking Islamophobia", ''Culture and Religion: An Interdisciplinary Journal'', Vol. 5, No. 1 (2004), pp. 105–17 (116f.)&lt;/ref&gt;

==Manifestations==
{{main article|Islamophobic incidents}}

===Media===
{{main article|Islamophobia in the media}}
[[File:Gathering of eagles.jpg|thumb|An American protester holding a sign saying that he is Islamophobic]]
According to Elizabeth Poole in the ''Encyclopedia of Race and Ethnic Studies'', the media have been criticized for perpetrating Islamophobia. She cites a case study examining a sample of articles in the British press from between 1994 and 2004, which concluded that Muslim viewpoints were underrepresented and that issues involving Muslims usually depicted them in a negative light. Such portrayals, according to Poole, include the depiction of Islam and Muslims as a threat to Western security and values.&lt;ref&gt;Poole, E. (2003) p. 217&lt;/ref&gt; Benn and Jawad write that hostility towards Islam and Muslims are "closely linked to media portrayals of Islam as barbaric, irrational, primitive and sexist."&lt;ref name="Brill165"/&gt; Egorova and Tudor cite European researchers in suggesting that expressions used in the media such as "Islamic terrorism", "Islamic bombs" and "violent Islam" have resulted in a negative perception of Islam.&lt;ref&gt;See Egorova; Tudor (2003) pp. 2–3, which cites the conclusions of Marquina and Rebolledo in: "A. Marquina, V. G. Rebolledo, 'The Dialogue between the European Union and the Islamic World' in Interreligious Dialogues: Christians, Jews, Muslims, Annals of the European Academy of Sciences and Arts, v. 24, no. 10, Austria, 2000, pp. 166–68. "&lt;/ref&gt; John E. Richardson's 2004 book ''(Mis)representing Islam: the racism and rhetoric of British broadsheet newspapers'', criticized the [[Media of the United Kingdom|British media]] for propagating negative [[Stereotypes of Arabs and Muslims|stereotypes of Muslims]] and fueling anti-Muslim prejudice.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Richardson|first=John E.|title=(Mis)representing Islam: the racism and rhetoric of British broadsheet newspapers|publisher=[[John Benjamins Publishing Company]]|year=2004|isbn=90-272-2699-7|url=https://books.google.com/?id=WanqiF2XULsC&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q=|postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; In another study conducted by John E. Richardson, he found that 85% of mainstream newspaper articles treated Muslims as a homogeneous mass who were imagined as a threat to British society.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Richardson | first1 = J. E. | year = 2009 | title = 'Get Shot of the Lot of Them': Election Reporting of Muslims in British Newspapers | url = | journal = Patterns of Prejudice | volume = 43 | issue = 3–4| pages = 355–77 | doi=10.1080/00313220903109276}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2009 [[Mehdi Hasan]] in the ''[[New Statesman]]'' criticized Western media for over-reporting a few [[Islamist terrorist]] incidents but under-reporting the much larger number of planned non-Islamist terrorist attacks carried out by "non-Irish [[White people|white]] folks".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Know your enemy|author=Mehdi Hasan|work=[[New Statesman]]|date=9 July 2009|url=http://www.newstatesman.com/2009/07/mehdi-hasan-muslim-terrorism-white-british|accessdate=2010-04-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;  A 2012 study indicates that Muslims across different European countries, such as France, Germany and the United Kingdom, experience the highest degree of Islamophobia in the media.&lt;ref name=kunst2012b/&gt;

Media personalities have been accused of Islamophobia. The obituary in ''[[The Guardian]]'' for the Italian journalist [[Oriana Fallaci]] described her as "notorious for her Islamaphobia" [sic].&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.theguardian.com/italy/story/0,1873911,00.html Obituary of Oriana Fallaci] – [[The Guardian]], 16 September 2006. "''Controversial Italian journalist famed for her interviews and war reports but notorious for her Islamaphobia''"&lt;/ref&gt;

Some media outlets are working explicitly against Islamophobia. In 2008 [[Fairness and Accuracy in Reporting]] ("FAIR") published a study "Smearcasting, How Islamophobes Spread Bigotry, Fear and Misinformation." The report cites several instances where mainstream or close to mainstream journalists, authors and academics have made analyses that essentialize negative traits as an inherent part of Muslims' moral makeup.&lt;ref&gt;Steve Rendall and Isabel Macdonald, [http://www.fair.org/index.php?page=3648 Making Islamophobia Mainstream; How Muslim-bashers broadcast their bigotry], summary of [[Fairness and Accuracy in Reporting]] report, at its website, November/December 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; FAIR also established the "[[Forum Against Islamophobia and Racism]]", designed to monitor coverage in the media and establish dialogue with media organizations. Following the [[September 11 attacks|attacks of September 11, 2001]], the [[Islamic Society of Britain]]'s "Islam Awareness Week" and the "Best of British Islam Festival" were introduced to improve community relations and raise awareness about Islam.&lt;ref&gt;Encyclopedia of Race and Ethnic studies, p. 218&lt;/ref&gt; In 2012 the [[Organisation of Islamic Cooperation]] stated that they will launch a TV channel to counter  Islamophobia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.arabnews.com/node/411340 | title=OIC will launch channel to counter Islamophobia | date=April 19, 2012 | agency=Arab News | accessdate=January 9, 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, Nathan Lean believes that there is an actual "Islamophobia Industry." However, unlike the relationship of a buyer and a seller, it is a relationship of mutual benefit, where ideologies and political proclivities converge to advance the same agenda.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = The Islamophobia Industry: How the Right Manufactures Fear of Muslims|last = Lean|first = Nathan|publisher = Pluto Press|year = 2012|isbn = |location = |page = 66}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There are growing instances of Islamophobia in Hindi cinema, or Bollywood, in films such as Aamir (2008), ''New York'' (2009) and ''My Name is Khan'' (2010), which corresponds to a growing anti-minorities sentiment that followed the resurgence of the Hindu right.&lt;ref&gt;Gabriel, Karen, "The Country in the City: The Bye-lanes of Identity", ''South Asian Journal Special Issue Cinema in South Asia'', July – September 2010 pp. 53–64.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Gabriel, Karen and P. K. Vijayan, "Orientalism, Terrorism and Bombay Cinema", (2012) ''Journal of Postcolonial Writing Special Issue on Orientalism and Terrorism'', Pavan Kumar Malreddy &amp; Birte Heidemann (eds.) July 2012 volume 48, number 3, pp. 299–310.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Organizations===
{{see also|List of organizations designated by the Southern Poverty Law Center as hate groups#Anti-Muslim}}
[[File:English Defence League protest in Newcastle.jpg|thumb|An English Defence League demonstration. The placard reads ''Shut down the mosque command and control centre''.]]
[[Stop Islamization of America]] (SIOA) and the ''Freedom Defense Initiative'' are designated as [[hate groups]] by the [[Anti-Defamation League]]&lt;ref&gt;[[Anti-Defamation League]], [http://www.adl.org/main_Extremism/sioa.htm "Backgrounder: Stop Islamization of America (SIOA)"] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120502054200/http://www.adl.org/main_Extremism/sioa.htm |date=2012-05-02 }}, ''Extremism'', March 25, 2011 [August 26, 2010]. Retrieved February 16, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[Southern Poverty Law Center]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |work=The Intelligence Report |publisher=Southern Poverty Law Center |url=http://www.splcenter.org/get-informed/intelligence-report/browse-all-issues/2011/summer/jihad-against-islam |date=Summer 2011 |issue=142 |first=Robert |last=Steinback |title=Jihad Against Islam}}
* {{cite web|title=Pamela Geller &amp; Stop Islamization of America|url=http://www.splcenter.org/get-informed/intelligence-files/profiles/pamela-geller|publisher=Southern Poverty Law Center|accessdate=27 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=nydaily&gt;{{Cite news |url=http://articles.nydailynews.com/2011-02-25/local/28647400_1_islamic-center-anti-islamic-pamela-geller |work=New York Daily News |date=February 25, 2011 |first=Corky |title=Southern Poverty Law Center lists anti-Islamic NYC blogger Pamela Geller, followers a hate group |last=Siemaszko}}&lt;/ref&gt; In August 2012 SIOA generated media publicity by sponsoring billboards in New York subway stations claiming there had been 19,250 terrorist attacks by Muslims since 9/11 and stating "it's not Islamophobia, it's Islamorealism."&lt;ref&gt;*[http://www.cbsnews.com/8301-201_162-57495509/anti-islamic-ad-claiming-its-not-islamophobia-its-islamorealism-goes-up-in-ny-train-stations/ Anti-Islamic ad claiming "it's not Islamophobia, it's Islamorealism" goes up in NY train stations], [[Associated Press]], August 17, 2012. Note that [[Bryan Fischer]], Director of Issues Analysis for the [[American Family Association]] also used the phrase "Islamo-realism" in the column [http://www.renewamerica.com/columns/fischer/100504 Times Square another argument for restricting Muslim immigration], May 4, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; It later ran advertisements reading "In any war between the civilized man and the savage, support the civilized man. Support Israel. Defeat Jihad." Several groups condemned the advertisements as "hate speech" about all Muslims&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nypost.com/p/news/opinion/editorials/free_speech_free_for_all_SJ7F1HEiw0fquIdzjaHkPO|title=Free-speech free-for-all|date=Oct 6, 2012|newspaper=New York Post}}
* {{cite news|url=http://cityroom.blogs.nytimes.com/2012/10/04/pro-muslim-subway-ads-to-hang-near-anti-jihad-ads/|newspaper=The New York Times|title=Pro-Muslim Subway Ads to Hang Near Anti-Jihad Ads|date=Oct 4, 2012|author=Ashwaq Masood}}
* {{cite web|last=Jewish Council for Public Affairs|title=JCPA Condemns Bigoted, Divisive, and Unhelpful Anti-Muslim Ads|url=http://engage.jewishpublicaffairs.org/blog/comments.jsp?key=477&amp;blog_entry_KEY=6561&amp;t=|publisher=JCPA|accessdate=September 21, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; while others defended the ad as a narrow criticism of violent [[Jihadism]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nypost.com/p/news/opinion/editorials/shocking_assumption_gwMiupSSPR0d6waO4lVt6J|title=A shocking assumption|newspaper=The New York Post|date=September 29, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; In early January 2013 the Freedom Defense Initiative put up advertisements next to 228 clocks in 39 New York subway stations showing the 2001 [[September 11 attacks|attacks on the World Trade Center]] with a quote attributed to the 151st verse of chapter 3 of the Quran: "Soon shall we cast terror into the hearts of the unbelievers."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://corpus.quran.com/translation.jsp?chapter=3&amp;verse=151|title=The Quranic Arabic Corpus – Translation|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cbsnews.com/8301-201_162-57562947/new-anti-muslim-ads-up-in-nyc-subway-stations/ New anti-Muslim ads up in NYC subway stations], [[CBS News]], January 9, 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[New York City Transit Authority]], which said it would have to carry the advertisements on [[First Amendment to the United States Constitution|First Amendment]] grounds, insisted that 25% of the ad contain a Transit Authority disclaimer.&lt;ref&gt;Emily Anne Epstein, [http://observer.com/2012/12/pamela-geller-mta-new-anti-islam-ads-to-debut-this-month-now-with-25-more-mta-disclaimer/ New Anti-Islam Ads to Debut This Month, Now With 25% More MTA Disclaimer], [[The New York Observer]], December 7, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2012/12/14/nyregion/controversial-group-has-new-anti-jihad-subway-ads.html?ref=nyregion&amp;_r=1&amp;|title=Controversial Group Plans More Ads in Subway Stations|date=Dec 13, 2012|newspaper=New York Times|author=Matt Flegenheimer}}&lt;/ref&gt; These advertisements also were criticized.&lt;ref&gt;Murtaza Hussain, [http://www.aljazeera.com/indepth/opinion/2012/12/20121230135815198642.html Anti-Muslim violence spiraling out of control in America], [[Al-Jazeera]], December 31, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Wajahat Ali, [http://www.salon.com/2012/12/31/death_by_brown_skin/ Death by brown skin], [[Salon (website)|Salon]], December 31, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[English Defence League]] (EDL), an organization in the United Kingdom, has been described as anti-Muslim. It was formed in 2009 to oppose what it considers to be a spread of Islamism, Sharia law and [[Islamic extremism]] in the UK.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.academia.edu/545302/Differentiating_Islamophobia_Introducing_a_new_scale_to_measure_Islamoprejudice_and_Secular_Islam_Critique|title=Differentiating Islamophobia: Introducing a new scale to measure Islamoprejudice and Secular Islam Critique|author=Roland Imhoff|publisher=|accessdate=18 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; The EDL's former leader, [[Tommy Robinson (activist)|Tommy Robinson]], left the group in 2013 saying it had become too extreme and that street protests were ineffective.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.theguardian.com/uk-news/2013/oct/08/tommy-robinson-english-defence-league|title=Tommy Robinson quits EDL saying it has become 'too extreme'|author=Haroon Siddique|date=8 Oct 2013|newspaper=The Guardian}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Furthermore, the [[7 July 2005 London bombings]] and the resulting efforts of the British civil and law enforcement authorities to help seek British Muslims'  help in identifying potential threats to create prevention is observed by Michael Lavalette as institutionalized Islamophobia. Lavalette alleges that there is a continuity between the former two British governments over prevention that aims to stop young Muslim people from being misled, misdirected and recruited by extremists who exploit grievances for their own "jihadist" endeavors. Asking and concentrating on Muslim communities and young muslims to prevent future instances, by the authorities, is in itself Islamophobia as such since involvement of Muslim communities will highlight and endorse their compassion for Britain and negate the perceived threats from within their communities.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Race, Racism and Social Work: Contemporary issues and debates|last = Lavalette|first = Michael|publisher = Policy Press at the University of Bristol|year = 2014|isbn = |location = England|pages = 167–90|chapter = Institutionalised Islamophobia and the 'Prevent' agenda: 'winning hearts and minds' or welfare as surveillance and control?}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Public opinion===
[[File:02015-10-02 Der anti-islamische Protest in Polen.JPG|thumb|Anti-Islam rally in [[Poland]] in 2015]]
The extent of negative attitudes towards Muslims vary across different parts of the world.
{{bar box
|title=Unfavorable views of Muslims, 2016
|titlebar=#ddd
|left1='''Country'''
|right1='''Percent'''
|width=400px
|bars=
{{bar percent|[[Hungary]]&lt;ref name="Pew3"&gt;{{cite report |url=http://assets.pewresearch.org/wp-content/uploads/sites/2/2016/07/Pew-Research-Center-EU-Refugees-and-National-Identity-Report-FINAL-July-11-2016.pdf |title=Europeans Fear Wave of Refugees Will Mean More Terrorism, Fewer Jobs |last1=Wike |first1=Richard |last2=Stokes |first2=Bruce |last3=Simmons |first3=Katie |date=July 2016 |website= |publisher=Pew Research Center |page=4 |access-date=27 November 2016 |quote=}}&lt;/ref&gt;|peru|72}}
{{bar percent|[[Italy]]&lt;ref name="Pew3" /&gt;|peru|69}}
{{bar percent|[[Poland]]&lt;ref name="Pew3" /&gt;|peru|66}}
{{bar percent|[[Greece]]&lt;ref name="Pew3" /&gt;|peru|65}}
{{bar percent|[[Spain]]&lt;ref name="Pew3" /&gt;|darkorange|50}}
{{bar percent|[[United States|United States of America]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.brookings.edu/blog/markaz/2015/12/09/what-americans-really-think-about-muslims-and-islam/ |title=What Americans really think about Muslims and Islam |last= |first= |date=9 December 2015 |website= |publisher=Brookings Institution |access-date=27 November 2016 |quote=}}&lt;/ref&gt;|darkorange|46}}
{{bar percent|[[Canada]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.crrf-fcrr.ca/en/programs-3/capturing-the-pulse-of-the-nation-2/item/26625-state-of-relations-2016 |title=State of Relations 2016 |last= |first= |date=4 March 2016 |website=Canadian Race Relations Foundation |publisher=Leger Marketing |page=4 |access-date=27 November 2016 |quote=}}&lt;/ref&gt;|darkorange|43}}
{{bar percent|[[Netherlands]]&lt;ref name="Pew3" /&gt;|orange|35}}
{{bar percent|[[Sweden]]&lt;ref name="Pew3" /&gt;|orange|35}}
{{bar percent|[[France]]&lt;ref name="Pew3" /&gt;|gold|29}}
{{bar percent|[[Germany]]&lt;ref name="Pew3" /&gt;|gold|29}}
{{bar percent|[[United Kingdom]]&lt;ref name="Pew3" /&gt;|gold|28}}

}}

==Trends==
Islamophobia has become a topic of increasing sociological and political importance.&lt;ref name = "Brown-p163"/&gt; According to Benn and Jawad, Islamophobia has increased since [[Ayatollah Khomeini]]'s 1989 fatwa inciting Muslims to attempt to murder [[Salman Rushdie]], the author of ''[[The Satanic Verses]]'', and since the September 11 attacks (in 2001).&lt;ref&gt;Benn; Jawad (2004) p. 111&lt;/ref&gt; [[Anthropologist]] Steven Vertovec writes that the purported growth in Islamophobia may be associated with increased Muslim presence in society and successes.&lt;ref name="Vertovec"&gt;Steven Vertovec, "Islamophobia and Muslim Recognition in Britain"; in Haddad (2002) pp. 32–33&lt;/ref&gt; He suggests a [[Vicious circle|circular model]], where increased hostility towards Islam and Muslims results in governmental countermeasures such as institutional guidelines and changes to legislation, which itself may fuel further Islamophobia due to increased accommodation for Muslims in public life. Vertovec concludes: "As the public sphere shifts to provide a more prominent place for Muslims, Islamophobic tendencies may amplify."&lt;ref name="Vertovec" /&gt;
[[File:Ground Zero Marine Protest Muslim Bomb.jpg|thumb|left|A mannequin symbolizing a Muslim in a [[keffiyeh]], strapped to a "Made in the USA" bomb display at a protest of [[Park51]] in [[New York City]].]]
Patel, Humphries, and Naik (1998) claim that "Islamophobia has always been present in Western countries and cultures. In the last two decades, it has become accentuated, explicit and extreme."&lt;ref&gt;Naina Patel, Beth Humphries and Don Naik, "The 3 Rs in social work; Religion,'race' and racism in Europe", in Johnson; Soydan; Williams (1998) pp. 197–98&lt;/ref&gt; However, Vertovec (2002) states that some have observed that Islamophobia has not necessarily escalated in the past decades, but that there has been increased public scrutiny of it.&lt;ref name="Vertovec" /&gt; According to Abduljalil Sajid, one of the members of the Runnymede Trust's Commission on British Muslims and Islamophobia, "Islamophobias" have existed in varying strains throughout history, with each version possessing its own distinct features as well as similarities or adaptations from others.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Islamophobia: A new word for an old fear |url=http://www.wcrp.be/articles/Sajid9-11-04.htm |author=Imam Abduljalil Sajid |accessdate=2007-08-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2005 [[Ziauddin Sardar]], an [[Islamic scholar]], wrote in the  ''New Statesman'' that Islamophobia is a widespread European phenomenon.&lt;ref name=Sardar&gt;[http://www.newstatesman.com/node/152128 "The next holocaust"], ''New Statesman'', 5 December 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; He noted that each country has anti-Muslim political figures, citing [[Jean-Marie Le Pen]] in France; [[Pim Fortuyn]] in the Netherlands; and Philippe van der Sande of [[Vlaams Blok]], a [[Flemish people|Flemish]] nationalist party in Belgium. Sardar argued that Europe is "post-colonial, but ambivalent." Minorities are regarded as acceptable as an underclass of menial workers, but if they want to be upwardly mobile anti-Muslim prejudice rises to the surface. Wolfram Richter, professor of economics at [[Dortmund University of Technology]], told Sardar: "I am afraid we have not learned from our history. My main fear is that [[Holocaust|what we did to Jews]] we may now do to Muslims. The next holocaust would be against Muslims."&lt;ref name=Sardar/&gt; Similar fears, as noted by [[Kenan Malik]] in his book ''From Fatwa to Jihad'', had been previously expressed in the UK by Muslim philosopher [[Shabbir Akhtar]] in 1989, and Massoud Shadjareh, chair of the [[Islamic Human Rights Commission]] in 2000. In 2006 [[Salma Yaqoob]], a [[Respect Party]] Councillor, claimed that Muslims in Britain were "subject to attacks reminiscent of the gathering storm of anti-Semitism in the first decades of the last century.".&lt;ref name=malik131-2&gt;Malik, Kenan. ''From Fatwa to Jihad''. Atlantic Books, London (2009): pp. 131–32.&lt;/ref&gt; Malik, a senior visiting fellow in the Department of Political, International and Policy Studies at the [[University of Surrey]], has described these claims of a brewing holocaust as "hysterical to the point of delusion"; whereas Jews in Hitler's Germany were given the official designation of ''[[Untermenschen]]'', and were subject to escalating legislation which diminished and ultimately removed their rights as citizens, Malik noted that in cases where "Muslims are singled out in Britain, it is often for privileged treatment"  such as the 2005 legislation banning "incitement to religious hatred", the special funding Muslim organizations and bodies receive from local and national government, the special provisions made by workplaces, school and leisure centres for Muslims, and even suggestions by the Archbishop of Canterbury [[Rowan Williams]] and the former Lord Chief Justice, [[Nicholas Phillips, Baron Phillips of Worth Matravers|Lord Phillips]], that [[sharia]] law should be introduced into Britain.&lt;ref name=malik132&gt;Malik (2009): p. 132&lt;/ref&gt; The fact is, wrote Malik, that such well-respected public figures as Akhtar, Shadjareh and Yaqoob need "a history lesson about the real Holocaust reveals how warped the Muslim grievance culture has become."&lt;ref name=malik132/&gt;

In 2006 [[ABC News]] reported that "public views of Islam are one casualty of the post-Sept. 11, 2001 conflict: Nearly six in 10 Americans think the religion is prone to [[violent extremism]], nearly half regard it unfavorably, and a remarkable one in four admits to prejudicial feelings against Muslims and Arabs alike." They also report that 27 percent of Americans admit feelings of prejudice against Muslims.&lt;ref name=ABCMarch8&gt;[http://abcnews.go.com/US/story?id=1700599 "Poll: Americans Skeptical of Islam and Arabs"], "ABC News", March 8, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; Gallup polls in 2006 found that 40 percent of Americans admit to prejudice against Muslims, and 39 percent believe Muslims should carry special identification.&lt;ref&gt;[http://abcnews.go.com/GMA/Story?id=2413473&amp;page=2 "Islamophobia Felt 5 Years after 9/11"], ''Good Morning America'', September 9, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; These trends have only worsened with the use of Islamophobia as a campaign tactic during the 2008 American presidential election (with several Republican politicians and pundits, including Donald Trump, asserting that Democratic candidate Barack Obama is secretly a Muslim), during the 2010 mid-term elections (during which a proposed Islamic community center was dubbed the "Ground Zero Mosque"&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Corbett|first=Rosemary R.|title=Making Moderate Islam: Sufism, Service, and the Ground Zero Mosque Controversy|year=2016|publisher=Stanford University Press |isbn=9781503600812}}&lt;/ref&gt;), and the 2016 presidential election, during which Republican nominee Donald Trump proposed banning the entrance into the country of all Muslims. Associate Professor [[Deepa Kumar]] writes that "Islamophobia is about politics rather than religion per se"&lt;ref name=Kumarbook&gt;{{cite book|last=Kumar|first=Kumar|title=Islamophobia and the Politics of Empire|year=2012|publisher=Haymarket Books|isbn=978-1608462117|page=6}}&lt;/ref&gt;  and that modern-day demonization of Arabs and Muslims by US politicians and others is racist and Islamophobic, and employed in support of what she describes as an unjust war. About the public impact of this rhetoric, she says that "One of the consequences of the relentless attacks on Islam and Muslims by politicians and the media is that Islamophobic sentiment is on the rise." She also chides some "people on the left" for using the same "Islamophobic logic as the Bush regime".&lt;ref name="Fighting Islamophobia"&gt;[http://mrzine.monthlyreview.org/kumar030406.html Fighting Islamophobia: A Response to Critics]&amp;nbsp;– Deepa Kumar, MRZine, February 2006&lt;/ref&gt; In this regards, Kumar confirms the assertions of [[Stephen Sheehi]], who "conceptualises Islamophobia as an ideological formation within the context of the American empire. Doing so "allows us to remove it from the hands of 'culture' or from the myth of a single creator or progenitor, whether it be a person, organisation or community." An ideological formation, in this telling, is a constellation of networks that produce, proliferate, benefit from, and traffic in Islamophobic discourses."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dawn.com/news/732513/cover-story-islamophobia-an-ideological-formation Dawn.com] "Cover Story: Islamophobia as an Ideological Formation." August 7, 2012&lt;/ref&gt;

The writer and scholar on religion [[Reza Aslan]] has said that "Islamophobia has become so mainstream in this country that Americans have been trained to expect violence against Muslims&amp;nbsp; – not excuse it, but expect it"&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.nytimes.com/2012/08/11/us/if-the-sikh-temple-had-been-a-muslim-mosque-on-religion.html "If the Sikh Temple Had Been a Mosque" Samuel G Freedman] ''New York Times'', August 10, 2012&lt;/ref&gt;

A January 2010 [[British Social Attitudes Survey]] found that the British public "is far more likely to hold negative views of Muslims than of any other religious group,"&lt;ref name=Galloway&gt;{{cite web|title=Sinister parallels of hatred|date=14 March 2010|author=[[George Galloway]]|work=[[Morning Star (UK newspaper)|Morning Star]]|url=http://www.morningstaronline.co.uk/index.php/news/content/view/full/87933|accessdate=2010-04-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; with "just one in four" feeling "positively about Islam," and a "majority of the country would be concerned if a mosque was built in their area, while only 15 per cent expressed similar qualms about the opening of a church."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=Britain divided by Islam, survey finds|work=[[The Daily Telegraph]]|date=11 Jan 2010|url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/newstopics/religion/6965276/Britain-divided-by-Islam-survey-finds.html|accessdate=2010-04-04 | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A 2016 report by [[Council on American–Islamic Relations|CAIR]] and [[University of California, Berkeley]]'s Center for Race and Gender said that groups promoting islamophobia in the US had access to 206 million USD between 2008 and 2013. The author of the report said that "The hate that these groups are funding and inciting is having real consequences like attacks on mosques all over the country and new laws discriminating against Muslims in America."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2016/jun/20/islamophobia-funding-cair-berkeley-report |title=The Guardian: Funding Islamophobia: $206m went to promoting 'hatred' of American Muslims |last1=Kazem |first1=Halima|date=20 June 2016 |website=The Guardian |publisher= |access-date=24 June 2016 |quote=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Anti-Islamic hate crimes data in the United States===
Data on types of hate crimes have been collected by the U.S. [[Federal Bureau of Investigation|FBI]] since 1992, to carry out the dictates of the 1990 [[Hate Crime Statistics Act]].  Hate crime offenses include crimes against persons (such as assaults) and against property (such as [[arson]]), and are classified by various race-based, religion-based, and other motivations.

The data show that recorded anti-Islamic hate crimes in the United States jumped dramatically in 2001.  Anti-Islamic hate crimes then subsided, but continued at a significantly higher pace than in pre-2001 years.  The step up is in contrast to decreases in total hate crimes and to the [[Crime in the United States#Crime over time|decline in overall crime in the U.S.]] since the 1990s.

Specifically, the FBI's annual hate crimes statistics reports from 1996 to 2013 document average numbers of anti-Islamic offenses at 31 per year before 2001, then a leap to 546 in 2001 (the year of [[9-11]] attacks), and averaging 159 per since.  Among those offenses are anti-Islamic arson incidents which have a similar pattern:  arson incidents averaged .4 per year pre-2001, jumped to 18 in 2001, and averaged 1.5 annually since.&lt;ref name=fbiData&gt;The FBI reports anti-Islamic [[hate crimes]] directed against persons or property its annual reports indexed [https://www.fbi.gov/about-us/cjis/ucr/ucr-publications#Hate here].  Data reported here are from the FBI Hate Crime reports of [https://www.fbi.gov/about-us/cjis/ucr/hate-crime/2013/tables/4tabledatadecpdf/table_4_offenses_offense_type_by_bias_motivation_2013.xls 2013], [https://www.fbi.gov/about-us/cjis/ucr/hate-crime/2012/tables-and-data-declarations/4tabledatadecpdf/table_4_offenses_offense_type_by_bias_motivation_2012.xls 2012], [https://www.fbi.gov/about-us/cjis/ucr/hate-crime/2011/tables/table-4 2011], [https://www.fbi.gov/about-us/cjis/ucr/hate-crime/2010/tables/table-4-offenses-offense-type-by-bias-motivation-2010.xls 2010], [https://www2.fbi.gov/ucr/hc2009/data/table_04.html 2009], [https://www2.fbi.gov/ucr/hc2008/data/table_04.html 2008], [https://www2.fbi.gov/ucr/hc2007/table_04.htm 2007], [https://www2.fbi.gov/ucr/hc2006/table4.html 2006], [https://www2.fbi.gov/ucr/hc2005/table4.htm 2005], [https://www2.fbi.gov/ucr/hc2004/hctable4.htm 2004], [https://www.fbi.gov/about-us/cjis/ucr/hate-crime/2003/hatecrime03.pdf 2003], [https://www.fbi.gov/about-us/cjis/ucr/hate-crime/2002/hatecrime02.pdf 2002], [https://www.fbi.gov/about-us/cjis/ucr/hate-crime/2001/hatecrime01.pdf 2001], [https://www.fbi.gov/about-us/cjis/ucr/hate-crime/2000/hatecrime00.pdf 2000], [https://www.fbi.gov/about-us/cjis/ucr/hate-crime/1999/hatecrime99.pdf 1999], [https://www.fbi.gov/about-us/cjis/ucr/hate-crime/1998/hatecrime98.pdf 1998], [https://www.fbi.gov/about-us/cjis/ucr/hate-crime/1997/hatecrime97.pdf 1997], and [https://www.fbi.gov/about-us/cjis/ucr/hate-crime/1996/hatecrime96.pdf 1996].  Totals and averages reported here are derived as calculations from the FBI data.&lt;/ref&gt;

Year-by-year anti-Islamic hate crimes, all hate crimes, and arson subtotals are as follows:
{|
| align="center" style="background:#f0f0f0;"|
| align="center" style="background:#f0f0f0;" colspan="2"|'''Anti-Islamic hate crimes'''
| align="center" style="background:#f0f0f0;" colspan="2"|'''All hate crimes'''
|- style="background:#f0f0f0;"
| Year||Arson offenses||Total offenses||Arson offenses||Total offenses
|-
| 1996||0||33||75||10,706
|-
| 1997||1||31||60||9,861
|-
| 1998||0||22||50||9,235
|-
| 1999||1||34||48||9,301
|-
| 2000||0||33||52||9,430
|- style="background:Gainsboro;"
| 2001||18||546||90||11,451
|-
| 2002||0||170||38||8,832
|-
| 2003||2||155||34||8,715
|-
| 2004||2||193||44||9,035
|-
| 2005||0||146||39||8,380
|-
| 2006||0||191||41||9,080
|-
| 2007||0||133||40||9,006
|-
| 2008||5||123||53||9,168
|-
| 2009||1||128||41||7,789
|-
| 2010||1||186||42||7,699
|-
| 2011||2||175||42||7,254
|-
| 2012||4||149||38||6,718
|-
| 2013||1||165||36||6,933
|-
| ||||||||
|- style="background:#f0f0f0;"
| Total||38||2,613||863||158,593
|- style="background:#f0f0f0;"
|- style="background:Gainsboro;"
| Average||2.1||145.2||47.9||8810.7
|- style="background:#f0f0f0;"
| ||||||||
|- style="background:#f0f0f0;"
| 1996–2000 avg||.40||30.6||57.0||9,707
|- style="background:#f0f0f0;"
| 2001||18||546||90||11,451
|- style="background:#f0f0f0;"
| 2002–2013 avg||1.50||159.5||40.7||8,217
|-
|}
In contrast, the overall numbers of arson and total offenses declined from pre-2001 to post-2001.

===Anti-Islamic hate crimes in the European countries===
There have also been reports of hate crimes targeting Muslims across Europe. These incidents have increased after terrorist attacks by extremist groups such as ISIL.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.com/news/uk-england-london-34995431|title=Anti-Islam hate crimes triple in London after Paris attacks|date=4 December 2015|publisher=|via=www.bbc.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Far-right politics|Far-right]] and [[Right-wing populism|right-wing populist]] political parties and organizations have also been accused of fueling fear and hatred towards Muslims.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.reuters.com/article/us-europe-migrants-protests-germany-idUSKCN0VF0P4|title=Anti-Islam movement PEGIDA stages protests across Europe|date=6 February 2017|publisher=|via=Reuters}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2015/11/18/world/europe/marine-le-pens-anti-islam-message-gains-influence-in-france.html|title=Marine Le Pen's Anti-Islam Message Gains Influence in France|first=Adam|last=Nossiter|date=17 November 2015|publisher=|via=NYTimes.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.wsj.com/articles/germanys-afd-adopts-anti-islam-stance-at-party-conference-1462120609|title=Germany's AfD Adopts Anti-Islam Stance at Party Conference|first=Ruth|last=Bender|date=1 May 2016|publisher=|via=www.wsj.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://news.vice.com/story/poland-populist-government-far-right-extremism|title=Poland's populist government let far-right extremism explode into mainstream|first=Tim|last=Hume|date=9 May 2017|publisher=|via=news.vice.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hate crimes such as arson and physical violence have been attempted or have occurred in Norway,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thelocal.no/20160520/woman-attempted-to-set-fire-to-oslo-mosque|title=Woman attempted to set fire to Oslo mosque|date=20 May 2016|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Poland,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.opendemocracy.net/can-europe-make-it/kasia-narkowicz-konrad-pedziwiatr/why-are-polish-people-so-wrong-about-muslims-in|title=Why are Polish people so wrong about Muslims in their country?|date=13 January 2017|publisher=openDemocracy}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.islamophobiaeurope.com/reports/2015/en/EIR_2015_POLAND.pdf|title=European Islamophobia Report|date=2015|publisher=SETA}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sweden,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.com/news/world-europe-30658482|title=Sweden protest after three mosque fires in one week|date=2 January 2015|publisher=|via=www.bbc.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; France,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/2016/07/27/fears-of-anti-muslim-backlash-as-police-investigate-possible-ars/|title=Fears of anti-Muslim backlash as police investigate possible arson attack on French mosque|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Spain,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dawn.com/news/1282879|title=Spanish hooligans held for assault on hijab-wearing pregnant Muslim woman|date=8 September 2016|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Denmark.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://cphpost.dk/news/muslim-school-in-denmark-vandalised-with-anti-islam-graffiti.html|title=Muslin School in Denmark Vandalised with Anti-Islam Graffiti|publisher=The Copenhagen Post }}&lt;/ref&gt; Politicians have also made anti-Muslim comments when discussing [[European migrant crisis]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aljazeera.com/news/2015/09/refugees-hungary-train-station-150903064140564.html|title=Hungarian PM: We don't want more Muslims|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/worldviews/wp/2016/06/21/the-next-e-u-president-says-islam-has-no-place-in-his-country/|title=Slovakia's leader said Islam has 'no place' in his country. Now he's taking a leadership role in the E.U.|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.theguardian.com/world/2015/jul/02/poles-dont-want-immigrants-they-dont-understand-them-dont-like-them 'Poles don't want immigrants. They don't understand them, don't like them']&lt;/ref&gt;

===Reports by governmental organizations===
The largest project monitoring Islamophobia was undertaken following 9/11 by the EU watchdog, [[European Monitoring Centre on Racism and Xenophobia]] (EUMC). Their May 2002 report "Summary report on Islamophobia in the EU after 11 September 2001", written by [[Chris Allen (academic)|Chris Allen]] and Jorgen S. Nielsen of the [[University of Birmingham]], was based on 75 reports&amp;nbsp; – 15 from each EU member nation.&lt;ref name="EUMCNews"&gt;{{Cite news|title=EUMC presents reports on Discrimination and Islamophobia in the EU |publisher="European Monitoring Centre on Racism and Xenophobia media release" |url=http://www.eumc.europa.eu/eumc/index.php?fuseaction=content.dsp_cat_content&amp;catid=43d8bc25bc89d&amp;contentid=4582ddc822d41 |date=2006-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=EUMC&gt;Allen, Chris and Nielsen, Jorgen S. [http://www.raxen.eumc.eu.int/1/webmill.php?id=32813&amp;ditem=3101&amp;lin=detail "Summary report on Islamophobia in the EU after 11 September 2001"] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20071112213546/http://www.raxen.eumc.eu.int/1/webmill.php?id=32813&amp;ditem=3101&amp;lin=detail |date=12 November 2007 }}, EUMC, May, 2002.&lt;/ref&gt; The report highlighted the regularity with which ordinary Muslims became targets for abusive and sometimes violent retaliatory attacks after 9/11. Despite localized differences within each member nation, the recurrence of attacks on recognizable and visible traits of Islam and Muslims was the report's most significant finding. Incidents consisted of verbal abuse, blaming all Muslims for [[List of terrorist incidents|terrorism]], forcibly removing women's [[hijab]]s, spitting on Muslims, calling children "[[Osama bin Laden|Osama]]", and random assaults. A number of Muslims were hospitalized and in one instance paralyzed.&lt;ref name=EUMC/&gt; The report also discussed the portrayal of Muslims in the media. Inherent negativity, stereotypical images, fantastical representations, and exaggerated caricatures were all identified. The report concluded that "a greater receptivity towards anti-Muslim and other xenophobic ideas and sentiments has, and may well continue, to become more tolerated."&lt;ref name=EUMC/&gt;

The EUMC has since released a number of publications related to Islamophobia, including ''The Fight against Antisemitism and Islamophobia: Bringing Communities together (European Round Tables Meetings)'' (2003) and ''Muslims in the European Union: Discrimination and Islamophobia'' (2006).&lt;ref&gt;[http://fra.europa.eu/fra/index.php?fuseaction=content.dsp_cat_content&amp;catid=1 EUMC website&amp;nbsp;– Publications] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20071223010504/http://fra.europa.eu/fra/index.php?fuseaction=content.dsp_cat_content&amp;catid=1 |date=2007-12-23 }}. Retrieved 2007-11-17.&lt;/ref&gt;

Professor in History of Religion, Anne Sophie Roald, states that Islamophobia was recognized as a form of intolerance alongside [[xenophobia]] and [[antisemitism]] at the "Stockholm International Forum on Combating Intolerance",&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|first=Anne Sophie |last=Roald|title=New Muslims in the European Context: The Experience of Scandinavian Converts |page=53 |publisher=Brill|year=2004|isbn=90-04-13679-7}}&lt;/ref&gt; held in January 2001.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fasena.de/download/rechts/SIFCI.pdf Fasena.de]&lt;/ref&gt; The conference, attended by UN Secretary General [[Kofi Annan]], High Commissioner for Human Rights [[Mary Robinson]], the [[Organization for Security and Co-operation in Europe]] Secretary General [[Ján Kubis]] and representatives of the [[European Union]] and [[Council of Europe]], adopted a declaration to combat "genocide, ethnic cleansing, racism, antisemitism, Islamophobia and xenophobia, and to combat all forms of racial discrimination and intolerance related to it."&lt;ref name="humanrights.gov.se"&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.humanrights.gov.se/stockholmforum/2001/conference_2001.html |publisher=Chancellery of the Government of Sweden |title=Conference Two: Combating Intolerance |accessdate=19 November 2011 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100923211418/http://www.humanrights.gov.se/stockholmforum/2001/conference_2001.html |archivedate=September 23, 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Organisation of Islamic Cooperation]], in its 5th report to Islamophobia Observatory of 2012, found an "institutionalization and legitimization of the phenomenon of Islamophobia" in the West over the previous five years.&lt;ref name=Arabnews121113&gt;{{cite news|title=OIC warns of exploiting Islamophobia phenomenon|url=http://www.arabnews.com/oic-warns-exploiting-islamophobia-phenomenon|accessdate=18 October 2013|newspaper=Arab News|date=13 November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2014 Integrationsverket (the Swedish National Integration Board) defined Islamophobia as "racism and discrimination expressed towards Muslims."&lt;ref&gt;[http://motargument.se/2014/02/23/terminologi-islamofobi/ Terminologi – islamofobi] ''"rasistiska och diskriminerande uttryck gentemot muslimer."''&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2016, the European Islamophobia Report (EIR) presented the "European Islamophobia Report 2015"&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Reports – European Islamophobia|journal=European Islamophobia Reports EIR|date=May 3, 2016|issue=2015|url=http://www.islamophobiaeurope.com/reports/2015-reports/|accessdate=18 May 2016|publisher=European Parliament|language=English|format=.html/.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=EIR_2015.pdf|journal=European Islamophobia Reports EIR|date=May 3, 2016|issue=2015|url=http://www.islamophobiaeurope.com/reports/2015/en/EIR_2015.pdf|accessdate=18 May 2016|publisher=European Parliament|language=English|format=.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; at [[European Parliament]] which analyzes the "trends in the spread of Islamophobia" in 25 European states in 2015.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Feroz|first1=Emran|title=Europe's First Report on Islamophobia Shows the Dangerous Climate Muslims Live In|url=http://www.alternet.org/grayzone-project/europes-first-report-islamophobia-shows-dangerous-climate-muslims-live|accessdate=13 May 2016|work=AlterNet|date=4 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; The EIR defines Islamophobia as anti-Muslim racism. While not every criticism of Muslims or Islam is necessarily Islamophobic, anti-Muslim sentiments expressed through the dominant group scapegoating and excluding Muslims for the sake of power is.&lt;ref name=eirquote&gt;{{cite web|title=Definition – About European Islamophobia Report (EIR)|url=http://www.islamophobiaeurope.com/about-us/|website=©2016 European Islamophobia|publisher=European Parliament|accessdate=12 May 2016|language=English|format=.html|date=May 3, 2016|quote=When talking about Islamophobia, we mean anti-Muslim racism. As Anti-Semitism Studies has shown, the etymological components of a word do not necessarily point to its complete meaning, nor how it is used. Such is also the case with Islamophobia Studies. Islamophobia has become a well known term used in academia as much as in the public sphere. Criticism of Muslims or of the Islamic religion is not necessarily Islamophobic. Islamophobia is about a dominant group of people aiming at seizing, stabilizing and widening their power by means of defining a scapegoat – real or invented – and excluding this scapegoat from the resources/rights/definition of a constructed 'we'. Islamophobia operates by constructing a static 'Muslim' identity, which is attributed in negative terms and generalized for all Muslims. At the same time, Islamophobic images are fluid and vary in different contexts, because Islamophobia tells us more about the Islamophobe than it tells us about the Muslims/Islam.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Research on Islamophobia and its correlates===
Various studies have been conducted to investigate Islamophobia and its correlates among majority populations and among [[Muslim]] minorities themselves. To start with, an experimental study showed that anti-Muslim attitudes may be stronger than more general [[xenophobic]] attitudes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Spruyt | first1 = B. | last2 = Elchardus | first2 = M. | year = 2012 | title = Are anti-Muslim feelings more widespread than anti-foreigner feelings? Evidence from two split-sample experiments | doi = 10.1177/1468796812449707 | journal = Ethnicities | volume =  12| issue = | pages =  800–20}}&lt;/ref&gt; Moreover, studies indicate that anti-Muslim prejudice among majority populations is primarily explained by the perception of Muslims as a cultural threat, rather than as a threat towards the respective nation's economy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = González | first1 = K. V. | last2 = Verkuyten | first2 = M. | last3 = Weesie | first3 = J. | last4 = Poppe | first4 = E. | year = 2008 | title = Prejudice Towards Muslims in The Netherlands: Testing Integrated Threat Theory | doi = 10.1348/014466608X28444 | journal = The British journal of social psychology | volume = 47 | issue = 4| pages = 667–85 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Savelkoul | first1 = M. | last2 = Scheepers | first2 = P. | last3 = Tolsma | first3 = J. | last4 = Hagendoorn | first4 = L. | year = 2010 | title = Anti-Muslim attitudes in the Netherlands: Tests of contradictory hypotheses derived from ethnic competition theory and intergroup contact theory | doi = 10.1093/esr/jcq035 | journal = European Sociological Review | volume = 27 | issue = 6| pages = 741–58 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Schlueter | first1 = E. | last2 = Scheepers | first2 = P. | year = 2010 | title = The relationship between outgroup size and anti-outgroup attitudes: A theoretical synthesis and empirical test of group threat- and intergroup contact theory | doi = 10.1016/j.ssresearch.2009.07.006 | journal = Social Science Research | volume = 39 | issue = 2| pages = 285–95 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Studies focusing on the experience of Islamophobia among Muslims have shown that the experience of [[religious discrimination]] is associated with lower national identification and higher religious identification.&lt;ref name=kunst2012a&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Kunst | first1 = J. R. | last2 = Tajamal | first2 = H. | last3 = Sam | first3 = D. L. | last4 = Ulleberg | first4 = P. | year = 2012 | title = Coping with Islamophobia: The effects of religious stigma on Muslim minorities' identity formation | doi = 10.1016/j.ijintrel.2011.12.014 | journal = International Journal of Intercultural Relations | volume = 36 | issue = 4| pages = 518–32 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Verkuyten | first1 = M. | last2 = Yildiz | first2 = A. A. | year = 2007 | title = National (dis)identiﬁcation and ethnic and religious identity: A study among Turkish-Dutch Muslims | doi = 10.1177/0146167207304276 | journal = Personality and Social Psychology Bulletin | volume = 33 | issue = 10| pages = 1448–62 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In other words, religious discrimination seems to lead Muslims to increase their identification with their religion and to decrease their identification with their nation of residence. Some studies further indicate that societal Islamophobia negatively influences Muslim minorities' health.&lt;ref name=kunst2012b/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Johnston | first1 = D. | last2 = Lordan | first2 = G. | year = 2011 | title = Discrimination makes me sick! An examination of the discrimination–health relationship | doi = 10.1016/j.jhealeco.2011.12.002 | journal = Journal of Health Economics | volume = 31 | issue = 1| pages = 99–111 }}&lt;/ref&gt; One of the studies showed that the perception of an Islamophobic society is associated with more [[psychological problem]]s, such as [[Depression (mood)|depression]] and [[Neuroticism|nervousness]], regardless whether the respective individual had personally experienced religious [[discrimination]].&lt;ref name=kunst2012b/&gt; As the authors of the study suggest, [[anti-discrimination law]]s may therefore be insufficient to fully protect Muslim minorities from an environment which is hostile towards their religious group.

[[Farid Hafez]] and Enes Bayrakli publish an annual [[European Islamophobia Report]] since 2015.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.islamophobiaeurope.com|title=European Islamophobia|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; The European Islamophobie Report aims to enable policymakers as well as the public to discuss the issue of Islamophobia with the help of qualitative data. It is the first report to cover a wide range of Eastern European countries like Serbia, Croatia, Hungary, Lithuania, and Latvia. Farid Hafez is also editor of the German-English [[Islamophobia Studies Yearbook]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jahrbuch-islamophobie.de|title=Jahrbuch für Islamophobieforschung |first=Farid|last=Hafez|publisher=Islamophobieforschung}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Geographic trends===
An increase of Islamophobia in Russia follows the growing influence of the strongly conservative sect of [[Wahhabism]], according to Nikolai Sintsov of the National Anti-Terrorist Committee.&lt;ref name=rbth130625&gt;{{cite news|url=
http://rbth.ru/news/2013/06/25/wahhabism_expansion_in_russia_leads_to_growth_of_islamophobia_-_national_27468.html|title=Wahhabism expansion in Russia leads to growth of Islamophobia – National Anti-Terrorist Committee|date=June 25, 2013|newspaper=Rossiyskaya Gazeta}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Various translations of the Qur'an have been banned by the Russian government for promoting extremism and Muslim supremacy.&lt;ref name=guardian131008&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.theguardian.com/books/booksblog/2013/oct/08/russian-court-bans-quran-translation|title=Russian court bans Qur'an translation|author=Daniel Kalder|date=8 Oct 2013|newspaper=Guardian}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.csmonitor.com/Books/chapter-and-verse/2013/1009/Russia-blacklists-translation-of-the-Quran|title=Russia blacklists translation of the Quran|date=Oct 9, 2013|newspaper=Christian Science Monitor|author=Husna Haq}}&lt;/ref&gt; Anti-Muslim rhetoric is on the rise in Georgia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.economist.com/news/europe/21587829-georgia-appears-have-moved-backwards-under-bidzina-ivanishvili-no-change-better|title=No change for the better: Georgia appears to have moved backwards under Bidzina Ivanishvili|date=Oct 12, 2013|newspaper=The Economist}}&lt;/ref&gt; In Greece, Islamophobia accompanies anti-immigrant sentiment, as immigrants are now 15% of the country's population and 90% of the EU's illegal entries are through Greece.&lt;ref name=gm110103&gt;{{cite news|title=Rising tide of Islamophobia engulfs Athens|url=
https://www.theglobeandmail.com/news/world/rising-tide-of-islamophobia-engulfs-athens/article560119/|date=Jan 3, 2011|newspaper=Globe and Mail|location=Toronto}}&lt;/ref&gt; In France Islamophobia is tied, in part, to the nation's long-standing tradition of secularism.&lt;ref name=local130215&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.thelocal.fr/20130215/islamophobia-has-become-trivialised-in-france|title=Islamophobia has been trivialized in France|date=15 Feb 2013|newspaper=The Local|author=Ben McPartland}}&lt;/ref&gt; In Burma the [[969 Movement]] has been accused of events such as the [[2012 Rakhine State riots]].

Jocelyne Cesari, in her study of discrimination against Muslims in Europe,&lt;ref name=CesariStudy&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.euro-islam.info/wp-content/uploads/pdfs/securitization_and_religious_divides_in_europe.pdf |title=Muslims In Western Europe After 9/11: Why the term Islamophobia is more a predicament than an explanation }}&lt;/ref&gt; finds that anti-Islamic sentiment may be difficult to separate from other drivers of discrimination. Because Muslims are mainly from immigrant backgrounds and the largest group of immigrants in many Western European countries, [[xenophobia]] overlaps with Islamophobia, and a person may have one, the other, or both. So, for example, some people who have a negative perception of and attitude toward Muslims may also show this toward non-Muslim immigrants, either as a whole or certain groups (such as, for example, Eastern Europeans, sub-Saharan Africans, or Roma), whereas others would not. [[Nigel Farage]], for example, is anti-EU and in favor of crackdowns on immigration from Eastern Europe, but is favourable to immigration from Islamic Commonwealth countries such as Nigeria and Pakistan.&lt;ref&gt;https://www.theguardian.com/politics/2015/apr/22/nigel-farage-immigrants-india-australia-better-than-eastern-Europeans&lt;/ref&gt; In the United States, where immigrants from Latin America and Asia dominate and Muslims are a comparatively small fraction, xenophobia and Islamophobia may be more easily separable. [[Classism]] is another overlapping factor in some nations. Muslims have lower income and poorer education in France, Spain, Germany, and the Netherlands while Muslims in the US have higher income and education than the general population. In the UK, Islam is seen as a threat to [[secularism]] in response to the calls by some Muslims for [[blasphemy laws]]. In the Netherlands, Islam is seen as a socially conservative force that threatens [[gender equality]] and the acceptance of homosexuality.

The [[European Network Against Racism]] (ENAR) reports that Islamophobic crimes are on the increase in France, England and Wales. In Sweden crimes with an Islamophobic motive increased by 69% from 2009 to 2013.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://europe.newsweek.com/new-report-exposes-huge-rise-racist-crime-europe-326929|title=New report exposes huge rise in racist crime in Europe|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A report from Australia has found that the levels of Islamophobia among Buddhists and Hindus are significantly higher than among followers of other religions.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unisa.edu.au/Global/EASS/MnM/Publications/Islamophobia_report.pdf Islamophobia, social distance and fear of terrorism in Australia: a preliminary report]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Criticism of term and use==
{{expand section|date=September 2016}}
Although by the first decade of the 21st century the term "Islamophobia" had become widely recognized and used,&lt;ref&gt;Poole, E. (2003) p. 218.  "The Runnymede Trust has been successful in that the term Islamophobia is now widely recognized and used, though many right-wing commentators reject its existence or argue that it is justified. However, now becoming a catch-all label for any harassment involving Muslims, it should not be considered unproblematic."&lt;/ref&gt; its use, its construction and the concept itself have been criticized. Roland Imhoff and Julia Recker, in an article that puts forward the term "Islamoprejudice" as a better alternative, write that "... few concepts have been debated as heatedly over the last ten years as the term Islamophobia."&lt;ref name=Imhoff /&gt;

===Academic debate===
Jocelyne Cesari reported widespread challenges in the use and meaning of the term in 2006.&lt;ref name=Allen2007/&gt;&lt;ref name=Cesari2006&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.euro-islam.info/wp-content/uploads/pdfs/securitization_and_religious_divides_in_europe.pdf|title=Muslims in Western Europe After 9/11:Why the term Islamophobia is more a predicament than an explanation|author=Jocelyne Cesari|date=December 15–16, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to ''The Oxford Encyclopedia of Islam and Politics'', "Much debate has surrounded the use of the term, questioning its adequacy as an appropriate and meaningful descriptor. However, since Islamophobia has broadly entered the social and political lexicon, arguments about the appropriateness of the term now seem outdated."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last1=Allen | first1=Chris | last2=Moten | first2=Abdul Rashid | title=
The Oxford Encyclopedia of Islam and Politics | publisher=Oxford University Press | location=Oxford New York | year=2014 | isbn=978-0-19-973935-6}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Paul Jackson, in a critical study of the anti-Islamic [[English Defence League]], argues that the criteria put forward by the Runnymede report for Islamophobia "can allow for any criticism of Muslim societies to be dismissed...". He argues that both jihadi Islamists and far right activists use the term "to deflect attention away from more nuanced discussions on the make-up of Muslim communities", feeding "a language of polarised polemics". On one hand, it can be used "to close down discussion on genuine areas of criticism" regarding jihadi ideologies, which in turn has resulted in all accusations of Islamophobia to be dismissed as "spurious" by far right activists. Consequently, the term is "losing much [of its] analytical value".&lt;ref name=JacksonStudy&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://nectar.northampton.ac.uk/6015/7/Jackson20116015.pdf|title=The EDL: Britain's 'New Far Right' Social Movement|last=Jackson|first=Paul|publisher=RMN Publications, University of Northampton|pages=10–11|year=2001|accessdate=28 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Professor Eli Göndör wrote that the term Islamophobia should be replaced with "Muslimophobia".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.corren.se/asikter/kolumner/eli-gondor-begreppet-islamofobi-bor-bytas-ut-6394258-artikel.aspx|title=Eli Göndör: Begreppet islamofobi bör bytas ut|publisher=|accessdate=18 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; As Islamophobia is "a rejection of a population on the grounds of Muslimness", other researches suggest "Muslimism".&lt;ref&gt;Bunzl 2007, Bravo Lopéz 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

Professor Mohammad H. Tamdgidi of the University of Massachusetts, Boston, has generally endorsed the definition of Islamophobia as defined by the Runnymede Trust's ''Islamophobia: A Challenge for Us All''. However, he notes that the report's list of "open" views of Islam itself presents "an inadvertent definitional framework for Islamophilia": that is, it "falls in the trap of regarding Islam monolithically, in turn as being characterized by one or another trait, and does not adequately express the complex heterogeneity of a historical phenomenon whose contradictory interpretations, traditions, and sociopolitical trends have been shaped and has in turn been shaped, as in the case of any world tradition, by other world-historical forces."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Tamdgidi | first1 = Mohammad H. | year = 2012 | title = Beyond Islamophobia and Islamophilia as Western Epistemic Racisms: Revisiting Runnymede Trust's Definition in a World-History Context | url = http://crg.berkeley.edu/sites/default/files/Tamdgidi.pdf | format = PDF | journal = Islamophobia Studies Journal | volume = 1 | issue = 1| page = 76 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Philosopher [[Michael Walzer]] says that fear of religious militancy is not phobia, and compares fear of radical Islam with the fear Muslims and Jews could feel towards Christians during the [[crusades]].&lt;ref&gt;Michael Walzer: [http://www.dissentmagazine.org/article/islamism-and-the-left Islamism and the Left] ''Dissent'', Winter 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Commentary===
In the wake of the [[Jyllands-Posten Muhammad cartoons controversy|''Jyllands-Posten'' Muhammad cartoons controversy]], a group of 12 writers, including novelist [[Salman Rushdie]], signed a manifesto entitled ''Together facing the new totalitarianism'' in the French weekly satirical newspaper ''[[Charlie Hebdo]]'', warning against the use of the term Islamophobia to prevent criticism of "Islamic totalitarianism".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Writers issue cartoon row warning|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/4763520.stm|accessdate=19 February 2014|work=BBC News|date=1 March 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Rushdie"&gt;[[Salman Rushdie|Rushdie, Salman]] ''et al.'' (March 1, 2006). [http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/4764730.stm "Writers' statement on cartoons"], ''BBC News''. Retrieved 18 February 2014.  "We refuse to renounce our critical spirit out of fear of being accused of "Islamophobia", a wretched concept that confuses criticism of Islam as a religion and stigmatisation of those who believe in it."&lt;/ref&gt; Writing in the ''[[New Humanist]]'', philosopher [[Piers Benn]] suggests that people who fear the rise of Islamophobia foster an environment "not intellectually or morally healthy", to the point that what he calls "Islamophobia-phobia" can undermine "critical scrutiny of Islam as somehow impolite, or ignorant of the religion's true nature."&lt;ref name="Benn"&gt;Benn, Piers (31 May 2007). [http://rationalist.org.uk/524 "On Islamophobia-phobia"]. ''rationalist''.org.uk. (originally published in ''New Humanist'' in 2002). Retrieved 18 February 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;

Alan Posener and Alan Johnson have written that, while the idea of Islamophobia is sometimes misused, those who claim that hatred of Muslims is justified as opposition to Islamism actually undermine the struggle against Islamism.&lt;ref name=Johnson20110306 /&gt; [[Roger Kimball]] argues that the word "Islamophobia" is inherently a prohibition or fear of criticizing of [[radical Islam]].&lt;ref name=Kimball&gt;Kimball, Roger. {{cite web|url=http://www.newcriterion.com/archives/24/01/after-the-suicide/ |title="After the suicide of the West" |accessdate=2007-06-02 |deadurl=bot: unknown |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20060103053941/http://www.newcriterion.com/archives/24/01/after-the-suicide/ |archivedate=January 3, 2006 |df= }}, January 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; According to [[Pascal Bruckner]], the term was invented by [[Islamic fundamentalism in Iran|Iranian fundamentalists]] in the late 1970s analogous to "[[xenophobia]]" in order to denounce as racism what he feels is legitimate criticism of Islam.&lt;ref name="The invention of Islamophobia"&gt;[[Pascal Bruckner]]: [http://www.signandsight.com/features/2123.html ''The invention of Islamophobia''], [[signandsight.com]], 3 January 2011, retrieved 29 September 2012; originally published in French in [[Libération]]: [http://www.liberation.fr/societe/01012303767-l-invention-de-l-islamophobie ''L’invention de l’«islamophobie»''], 23 November 2010&lt;/ref&gt; The author [[Sam Harris (author)#Islam and Muslims|Sam Harris]], while denouncing bigotry, racism, and prejudice against Muslims or Arabs, rejects the term, Islamophobia,&lt;ref&gt;Sam Harris, "[http://www.samharris.org/blog/item/lifting-the-veil-of-islamophobia#sthash.bM4Un8kE.H21DmKxR.dpuf Lifting the Veil of 'Islamophobia'] A Conversation with [[Ayaan Hirsi Ali]]", May 8, 2014.&lt;/ref&gt; as an invented psychological disorder, and states criticizing those Islamic beliefs and practices he believes pose a threat to civil society is not a form of bigotry or racism.&lt;ref&gt;[[Sam Harris (author)|Harris, Sam]] (August 13, 2010). [http://www.thedailybeast.com/blogs-and-stories/2010-08-13/ground-zero-mosque/3/ "What Obama Got Wrong About the Mosque"]. ''[[The Daily Beast]]''.&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, [[Pascal Bruckner]] calls the term, "a clever invention because it amounts to making Islam a subject that one cannot touch without being accused of racism."&lt;ref name=Bruckner&gt;{{cite news|last1=[[Michael Walzer]]|title=Islamism and the Left|url=https://www.dissentmagazine.org/article/islamism-and-the-left|accessdate=2 November 2015|publisher=[[Dissent (American magazine)]]|date=Winter 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

French Prime Minister [[Manuel Valls]] said in January 2015 following the [[Charlie Hebdo shooting|''Charlie Hebdo'' shooting]] "It is very important to make clear to people that Islam has nothing to do with [[Islamic State of Iraq and the Levant|ISIS]]. There is a prejudice in society about this, but on the other hand, I refuse to use this term 'Islamophobia,' because those who use this word are trying to invalidate any criticism at all of Islamist ideology. The charge of 'Islamophobia' is used to silence people".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Goldberg|first1=Jeffrey|title=French Prime Minister: I Refuse to Use This Term Islamophobia|url=https://www.theatlantic.com/international/archive/2015/01/french-prime-minister-manuel-valls-on-islamophobia/384592/|accessdate=17 February 2015|work=[[The Atlantic]]|date=16 January 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Writing in 2008 [[Ed Husain]], a former member of [[Hizb ut-Tahrir]] and co-founder of [[Quilliam (think tank)|Quilliam]],&lt;ref&gt;Nawaz, Maajid. ''Radical''. W.H. Allen, London: 2012: p. 109&lt;/ref&gt; said that under pressure from Islamist extremists, "'Islamophobia' has become accepted as a phenomenon on a par with racism", claiming that "Outside a few flashpoints where the [[British National Party|BNP]] is at work, most Muslims would be hard-pressed to identify Islamophobia in their lives".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url= http://www.standard.co.uk/news/stop-pandering-to-the-islamist-extremists-6912982.html| title= Stop pandering to the Islamist extremists | work=London Evening Standard| date=7 July 2008| accessdate=24 October 2013 | author=Ed Husain| location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Salman Rushdie]] criticized the coinage of the word 'Islamophobia' saying that it "was an addition to the vocabulary of Humpty Dumpty Newspeak. It took the language of analysis, reason and dispute, and stood it on its head".&lt;ref&gt;Rushdie, Salman (2012). [http://www.carvaka4india.com/2012/10/joseph-anton-salman-rushdie-and.html ''Joseph Anton: A Memoir''], pp. 344–46, Jonathan Cape. Quoted at ''cārvāka4india.com''. Retrieved 18 February 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Christopher Hitchens]] stated that the "stupid term – Islamophobia – has been put into circulation to try and suggest that a foul prejudice lurks behind any misgivings about Islam's infallible 'message.'"&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.salon.com/2015/12/27/we_need_a_progressive_debate_on_islam_this_is_the_right_way_to_counter_donald_trump_and_be_honest_about_extremism/ Salon: "We need a progressive debate on Islam: This is the right way to counter Donald Trump, and be honest about extremism Freedom of speech, secularism and equal rights must guide the way we discuss all religions – and take on bigots" by Jeffrey Tayler] December 27, 2015&lt;/ref&gt;

In his paper 'A Measure of Islamophobia' Salman Sayyid (2014) argues that these criticisms are a form of etymological fundamentalism and echo earlier comments on racism and anti-Semitism. Racism and anti-Semitism were also accused of blocking free speech, of being conceptually weak and too nebulous for practical purposes.&lt;ref&gt;Sayyid (2014) 'A measure of Islamophobia' Islamophobia Studies Journal, Vol 2. No. 1, pp. 10-25.&lt;/ref&gt;

===''The Associated Press Stylebook''===
In December 2012, media sources reported that the terms "homophobia" and "Islamophobia" would no longer be included in the ''[[AP Stylebook]]'', and Deputy Standards Editor Dave Minthorn expressed concern about the usage of the terms, describing them as "just off the mark" and saying that they seem "inaccurate". Minthorn stated that AP decided that the terms should not be used in articles with political or social contexts because they imply an understanding of the mental state of another individual. The terms no longer appears on the online stylebook, and Minthorn believes journalists should employ more precise phrases to avoid "ascribing a mental disability to someone".&lt;ref name=huffpogay&gt;{{cite news|title= The Associated Press and Terms Like'Homophobia'|author=Warren J. Blumenfeld|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/warren-j-blumenfeld/the-associated-press-and-terms-like-homophobia_b_2235169.html|newspaper= Huffington Post|date= 5 December 2012|accessdate=6 June 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=APNixes&gt;{{cite news|title= AP Nixes 'homophobia', 'ethnic cleansing' |author=Dylan Byers|url=http://www.politico.com/blogs/media/2012/11/ap-nixes-homophobia-ethnic-cleansing-150315.html|newspaper=Politico|date=26 December 2012|accessdate=5 June 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Discrimination|Islam}}
* [[Anti-Christian sentiment]]
** [[Anti-Catholicism]]
** [[Anti-Protestantism]]
** [[Anti-Mormonism]]
* [[Anti-Judaism]]
* [[Discrimination against atheists]]
* [[Islamophobia in the media]]
* [[Muslims Condemn]]
* [[Persecution of Bahá'ís]]
* [[Persecution of Muslims]]
* [[Religious antisemitism]]
* [[Religious intolerance]]
* [[Religious persecution]]

==References==

===Footnotes===
{{Reflist|30em}}

===Sources===
* {{Cite encyclopedia |editor-last=Cashmore|editor-first=Ellis|author-last=Poole|author-first=E.| encyclopedia=Encyclopedia of Race and Ethnic Studies |article=Islamophobia |year=2003 | isbn=978-0-415-44714-0 |pages=215–19|publisher=Routledge}}
* {{Cite book|last=Benn |first=T. |author2=Jawad, H. |title=Muslim Women in the United Kingdom and Beyond: Experiences and Images |year=2004 |publisher=[[Brill Publishers]] |isbn=90-04-12581-7}}
* {{Cite book|last=Egorova |first=Y. |author2=Parfitt, T. |title=Jews, Muslims, and Mass Media: Mediating the 'Other' |year=2003 |publisher=Routledge Curzon |location=London |isbn=0-415-31839-4}}
* {{Cite book|last=Haddad |first=Y. | title=Muslims in the West: From Sojourners to Citizens |year=2002 |publisher=Oxford University Press |location=Oxford |isbn=0-19-514805-3}}
* {{Cite book|last=Johnson |first=M. R. D. |author2=Soydan, H |author3=Williams, C.  |title=Social Work and Minorities: European Perspectives |location=London; New York |year=1998 |publisher=Routledge |isbn=0-415-16962-3}}
* {{Cite book|author1=R Miles |author2=M Brown |title=Racism |year=2003 |location=London; New York |publisher=Routledge |isbn=0-415-29676-5}}
* Sayyid and Vakil eds. (2010) ''Thinking Through Islamophobia: Global Perspectives'' New York, Columbia University Press.

==Further reading==
* [[Chris Allen (academic)|Allen, Chris]] (2011). ''Islamophobia''. Ashgate Publishing Company.
* {{Cite book|last=Abbas|first= Tahir|title=Muslim Britain: Communities Under Pressure|year=2005|publisher=Zed|isbn=978-1-84277-449-6}}
* {{Cite book|last=van Driel|first=B.|title=Confronting Islamophobia In Educational Practice|year=2004|publisher=Trentham Books|isbn=1-85856-340-2}}
* "[https://www.americanprogress.org/issues/religion/report/2011/08/26/10165/fear-inc/ Fear, Inc.: The Roots of the Islamophobia Network in America]," Wajahat Ali, Eli Clifton, Matthew Duss, Lee Fang, Scott Keyes, and Faiz Shakir, accessed February 24, 2015.
* "[https://www.americanprogress.org/issues/religion/report/2015/02/11/106394/fear-inc-2-0/ Fear, Inc. 2.0: The Islamophobia Network's Efforts to Manufacture Hate in America]," Matthew Duss, Yasmine Taeb, Ken Gude, and Ken Sofer, accessed February 24, 2015.
* {{Cite book|last=Gottschalk|first=P.|author2=Greenberg, G. |title=Islamophobia: Making Muslims the Enemy|year=2007|publisher=Rowman &amp; Littlefield publishers |location=Lanham |isbn=978-0-7425-5286-9}}
* {{Cite book|last=Greaves|first=R.|title=Islam and the West Post 9/11|year=2004|publisher=Ashgate publishing Ltd|isbn=0-7546-5005-7}}
* Kaplan, Jeffrey (2006). "Islamophobia in America?: September 11 and Islamophobic Hate Crime", ''Terrorism and Political Violence'' (Routledge), '''18''':1, 1–33.
* Kincheloe, Joe L. and Shirley R. Steinberg (2004). ''The Miseducation of the West: How the Schools and Media Distort Our Understanding of Islam''. Westport, Connecticut: Praeger Press. (Arabic Edition, 2005).
* Kincheloe, Joe L. and Shirley R. Steinberg (2010). ''Teaching Against Islamophobia''. New York: Peter Lang.
* Konrad, Felix (2011). [http://nbn-resolving.de/urn:nbn:de:0159-2011020147 ''From the "Turkish Menace" to Exoticism and Orientalism: Islam as Antithesis of Europe (1453–1914)?''], [[European History Online]], Mainz: [[Institute of European History]]. Retrieved: June 22, 2011.
* Kundnani, Arun. (2014) ''The Muslims Are Coming! Islamaphobia, Extremism, and the Domestic War on Terror'' (Verso; 2014) 327 pages
* {{cite journal |last1=Pynting |first1=Scott|last2=Mason|first2=Victoria|year=2007|title=''The Resistible Rise of Islamophobia: Anti-Muslim Racism in the UK and Australia before 11 September 2001". ''Journal of Sociology |url= |journal=The Australian Sociological Association |volume=43 |issue=1|pages=61–86}}
* {{Cite book|last=Quraishi|first=M.|title=Muslims and Crime: A Comparative Study |year=2005 |publisher=Ashgate Publishing|isbn=0-7546-4233-X}}
* {{Cite book|last=Ramadan |first=T.|title=Western Muslims and the Future of Islam |year=2004 |publisher=Oxford University Press |location=Oxford |isbn=0-19-517111-X}}
* {{Cite book|last=Richardson|first=John E.|title=(Mis)representing Islam: the racism and rhetoric of British broadsheet newspapers|publisher=[[John Benjamins Publishing Company]]|year=2004|isbn=90-272-2699-7|url=https://books.google.com/?id=WanqiF2XULsC&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q=|postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}}
* [[Stephen Sheehi|Sheehi, Stephen]] (2011). ''Islamophobia: The Ideological Campaign Against Muslims''. Clarity Press.
* Shryock, Andrew, ed. (2010). ''[[Islamophobia/Islamophilia: Beyond the Politics of Enemy and Friend]]''. [[Indiana University Press]]. p.&amp;nbsp;250. Essays on Islamophobia past and present; topics include the "neo-Orientalism" of three Muslim commentators today: Ayaan Hirsi Ali, Reza Aslan, and Irshad Manji.
* Tausch, Arno with Christian Bischof, Tomaz Kastrun and Karl Mueller (2007). ''Against Islamophobia: Muslim Communities, Social-Exclusion and the Lisbon Process in Europe''. Hauppauge, N.Y.: Nova Science Publishers. {{ISBN|978-1-60021-535-3}}.
* Tausch, Arno with Christian Bischof, and Karl Mueller (2008). ''Muslim Calvinism: Internal Security and the Lisbon Process in Europe.'' Purdue University Press. {{ISBN|978-905170995-7}}.
* Tausch, Arno (2007). ''Against Islamophobia: Quantitative Analyses of Global Terrorism, World Political Cycles and Center Periphery Structures''. Hauppauge, N.Y.: Nova Science Publishers. {{ISBN|978-1-60021-536-0}}.
* Itaoui, Rhonda (2016). "The Geography of Islamophobia in Sydney: mapping the spatial imaginaries of young Muslims", in Australian Geographer. Vol 47:3, 261–79.

==External links==
{{Sister project links}}
* [http://crg.berkeley.edu/content/islamophobia/islamophobia-studies-journal ''Islamophobia Studies Journal''] – Islamophobia Research &amp; Documentation Project, UC Berkeley
* [http://www.islamophobiaeurope.com/reports/2015-reports/ ''Reports – European Islamophobia''] – European Islamophobia Reports EIR
* [http://www.islamophobiatoday.com/ ''Islamophobia Today'' newspaper] – an Islamophobia news clearing house
* [http://www.academia.edu/24419416/UNDERSTANDING_and_COUNTERING_ISLAMOPHOBIA Sammy Aziz Rahmatti, ''Understanding and Countering Islamophobia'']

{{Islam topics |collapsed}}
{{Discrimination}}

[[Category:Islamophobia| ]]
[[Category:Political neologisms]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>