<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061112133619|87331989" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="162173" pageid="162173" ns="0" title="Islamophobia"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-11-12T18:04:53Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{totallydisputed}}
[[Image:AgainstIslamophobiaRally.jpg|right|thumb|350px|Photograph of a rally against Islamophobia in London's [[Trafalgar Square]] on [[February 11]], [[2006]], in the wake of the [[Jyllands-Posten Muhammad cartoons controversy|Muhammad cartoons controversy]]. Image by [http://www.eyetopic.co.uk/ eyetopic.co.uk].]]
'''Islamophobia''' is a [[neologism]] defined as the phenomenon&lt;ref&gt;Edward Kessler, Neil Wenborn, ''A Dictionary of Jewish-Christian Relations'', Cambridge University Press,  ISBN 0521826926  p.429 &lt;/ref&gt;  of a [[prejudice]] against or demonization of [[Muslim]]s which manifests itself in general negative attitudes, violence, harassment, discrimination, and stereotyping (and particularly being vilified in the media).&lt;ref&gt; Sandra Fredman , ''Discrimination and Human Rights'', Oxford University Press, ISBN 0199246033, p.121. &lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt; Yvonne Yazbeck Haddad, ''Muslims in the West: From Sojourners to Citizens'', Oxford University Press, ISBN 0195148061, p.19 &lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Islamophobia: A Challenge for Us All'', [[Runnymede Trust]], 1997, p. 1, cited in Quraishi, Muzammil. ''Muslims and Crime: A Comparative Study'', Ashgate Publishing Ltd., 2005, p. 60. ISBN 075464233X. Early in 1997, the Commission on British Muslims and Islamophobia, at that time part of the Runnymede Trust, issued a consultative document on Islamophobia under the chairmanship of Professor Gordon Conway, Vice-Chancellor of the [[University of Sussex]]. The final report, ''Islamophobia: A Challenge for Us All'', was launched in November 1997 by the Home Secretary, [[Jack Straw]]. The word "Islamophobia" is formed with the Greek suffix [[-phob-|-phobia]] 'fear of -' in a similar way to [[xenophobia]] or [[homophobia]].&lt;/ref&gt; The term dates back to the late 1980s&lt;ref name=Runnymede1&gt;Runnymede 1997, p. 1, cited in Quraishi 2005, p. 60.&lt;/ref&gt; or early 90s,&lt;ref name=Annan&gt;[[Kofi Annan|Annan, Kofi]]. [http://www.un.org/News/Press/docs/2004/sgsm9637.doc.htm "Secretary-General, addressing headquarters seminar on confronting Islamophobia"], United Nations press release, December 7, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt; although its use has increased since the [[September 11, 2001]] attacks.&lt;ref name=Casciani&gt;Casciani, Dominic. [http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/3768327.stm "Islamophobia pervades UK - report"], BBC News, June 2, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Rima Berns McGowan writes in ''Muslims in the Diaspora'' (University of Toronto Press, 1991, p. 268) that the term "Islamophobia" was first used in an unnamed American periodical in 1991.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Kofi Annan]], Secretary-General of the [[United Nations]], told a UN conference in 2004: "[W]hen the world is compelled to coin a new term to take account of increasingly widespread [[bigotry]], that is a sad and troubling development. Such is the case with Islamophobia."&lt;ref name=Annan/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Muzammil Quraishi, senior lecturer in Criminology at the [[University of Salford]], writes that "whether we refer to behaviour as 'anti-Muslimism' or 'Islamophobia' seems a moot point. If we are agreed that either term refers to behaviour encapsulating hatred, and/or dislike to the extent of social and economic exclusion of Muslims, we must move to discover the extent of such behaviour and to evaluate how this influences crime and victimization ..." (Quraishi, Muzammil. ''Muslims and Crime: A Comparative Study'', Ashgate Publishing Ltd., 2005, p. 60).&lt;/ref&gt;

Anja Rudiger, Executive Coordinator of the [[European Monitoring Centre on Racism and Xenophobia]], argues that it is no longer acceptable to use [[skin color]] as an attribute to distinguish people, and that [[religion]] and [[culture]] have become the "markers of seemingly 'natural' kinds of differences." She writes that Islam has become "the new 'other' ..."&lt;ref name=Rudiger&gt;Rudiger, Anja. "Discrimination and Legislation," session 5, Conference on "Muslims in Europe post 9/11," St. Antony's-Princeton Conference, [[St Antony's College, Oxford]], April 26, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Also see the [[European Monitoring Centre on Racism and Xenophobia]] report, "Summary report on Islamophobia in the EU after 11 September 2001" by Chris Allen and Jorgen S. Nielsen of the [[University of Birmingham]], May 2002, the largest monitoring project on Islamophobia to have been commissioned to date.&lt;/ref&gt;

The British [[Runnymede Trust]] described Islamophobia in 1997 as the view that Islam has no values in common with other cultures; is inferior to the West; is a violent political ideology rather than a religion; that its criticisms of the West have no substance; and that discriminatory practices against Muslims are justified.&lt;ref name=Runnymede5&gt;Runnymede 1997, p. 5, cited in Quraishi 2005, p. 60.&lt;/ref&gt; American writer [[Stephen Schwartz (journalist)|Stephen Schwartz]], director of the Center for Islamic Pluralism, has cautioned against what he sees as a tendency to accuse all opponents of [[Islamism|Islamic radicalism]] of Islamophobia, but writes that it is nevertheless a real phenomenon. He defines it as the condemnation of the entirety of Islam and its history as [[Extremism|extremist]]; 'denying' the existence of a moderate Muslim majority; regarding Islam as a problem for the world; treating conflicts involving Muslims as necessarily their own fault; insisting that Muslims make changes to their religion; and inciting war against Islam as a whole.&lt;ref name=Schwartz&gt;[[Stephen Schwartz (journalist)|Schwartz, Stephen]]. [http://www.frontpagemag.com/Articles/ReadArticle.asp?ID=17874 "The 'Islamophobes' That Aren't"], ''FrontPage Magazine'', April 28, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;

British writer and academic [[Kenan Malik]] has criticized the concept, calling it a "myth." Malik argues that it confuses discrimination against Muslims with criticism of Islam, and is used to silence critics of the religion, including Muslims who want to reform it.&lt;ref name=Malik&gt;[[Kenan Malik|Malik, Kenan]]. [http://www.prospect-magazine.co.uk/article_details.php?id=6679 "Islamophobia Myth"], Prospect, February 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;
The novelist [[Salman Rushdie]] was among the signatories to a statement in March 2006 calling Islamophobia a "wretched concept that confuses criticism of Islam as a religion and stigmatisation of those who believe in it."&lt;ref name=Rushdie&gt;[[Salman Rushdie|Rushdie, Salman]] ''et al''. [http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/4764730.stm "Writers' statement on cartoons"], BBC News, March 1, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;
French writer [[Robert Redeker]] argues that the history of the term demonstrates that the term Islamophobia was created by "radical islamists" to "tackle feminists".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.robertredeker.net/mondecontemporain_lalaicite,l_islamophobie.htm]"  L'islamophobie, l'arme des islamistes contre la laïcité."&lt;/ref&gt;

== Nature of the concept ==
[[Image:AnyaRudiger.jpg|right|frame|Dr. Anya Rudiger of the [[European Monitoring Centre on Racism and Xenophobia|EUMC]] argues that Islam is "the new 'other'".&lt;ref name=Rudiger/&gt;]]
Sociologist and cultural analysts argue that, during the 1990s, there was a shift in forms of prejudice from race-based prejudice to discrimination based on culture and religion.&lt;ref name=Seabrook&gt;Seabrook, Jeremy. [http://www.guardian.co.uk/race/story/0,11374,1267567,00.html "Religion as a fig leaf for racism"], ''The Guardian'', July 23, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Rudiger/&gt;

Jeremy Seabrook writes in ''[[The Guardian]]'' that Islamophobia became the only form of prejudice to which the middle class will admit. "Officially, all right-thinking people have forsworn racism ... Islamophobia is the half-open door through which it makes its triumphal re-entry into respectable society." Seabrook argues that the perception of Islam as advocating the [[Sexism|repression of women]] and [[Homophobia|gays]] makes Islamophobia an acceptable form of prejudice.&lt;ref name=Seabrook/&gt;

Speaking to the [[United Nations commission on human rights|UNCHR]], [[Ekmeleddin İhsanoğlu]], secretary general of the [[Organization of the Islamic Conference]], said that Islamophobia was "a new name to an old phenomenon", and that "stereotypes and disrespectful comments about Islam were allowed to circulate and be published with the outcome that hatred and prejudice against Islam gained credibility, and the stereotyping in media coverage became a global sport."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oic-oci.org/press/english/2005/March%202005/SG-Geneva.htm Speech of H.E. Prof. Ekmeleddin Ihsanoglu, Secretary-General of the Organization of the Islamic conference], before the sixty-first session of the United Nations commission on human rights - [[15 March]], [[2005]]&lt;/ref&gt;

Anya Rudiger of the [[European Monitoring Centre on Racism and Xenophobia]] told an Oxford conference on Muslims in Europe that, since 9/11, religion has surpassed race as the primary focus of conflict, and that a person's religion is regarded as synonymous with their culture. In the case of Muslims, this opens up another dimension of prejudice, argues Rudiger, in that European Muslims are regarded as representing a unified culture quite different from European culture, one that is strongly linked to certain non-European countries. These perceptions are part of the process of labeling Islam as Europe's "other."&lt;ref name=Rudiger/&gt;

In 1996, the [[Runnymede Trust]], an independent anti-racist think tank in the UK, established the Commission on British Muslims and Islamophobia, chaired by Professor Gordon Conway, the vice-chancellor of the [[University of Sussex]]. The commission's 1997 report, ''Islamophobia: A Challenge For Us All'', lists eight distinctive features of Islamophobia:

:# Islam is seen as a [[monolith]]ic bloc, static and unresponsive to change.    
:# It is seen as separate and “other”. It does not have values in common with other cultures, is not affected by them and does not influence them.        
:# It is seen as inferior to the West. It is seen as barbaric, irrational, primitive, and [[sexism|sexist]].    
:# It is seen as violent, aggressive, threatening, supportive of terrorism, and engaged in a [[Clash of Civilizations]].
:# It is seen as a political [[ideology]], used for political or military advantage.     
:# Criticisms made of 'the West' by Islam are rejected out of hand.     
:# Hostility towards Islam is used to justify discriminatory practices towards Muslims and exclusion of Muslims from mainstream society.     
:# Anti-Muslim hostility is seen as natural and normal.&lt;ref name=Runnymede1997&gt;{{PDFlink|[http://www.runnymedetrust.org/publications/pdfs/islamophobia.pdf "Islamophobia: A Challenge for Us All"]}}, ''Runnymede Trust'', 1997.&lt;/ref&gt; 
&lt;br&gt;
The commission published a follow-up report in 2004 suggesting that young British Muslims felt they did not belong in Britain, and that they were vulnerable to social exclusion and violence. Dr Abduljalil Sajid, an [[imam]] and adviser to the commission, said he believed that Islamophobia had become institutionalized, citing what he regarded as police harassment of Muslims since 9/11. "Even one of the country's Muslim [[Peerage|peers]], [[Nazir Ahmed, Baron Ahmed|Lord Ahmed]], has been stopped twice by police," Sajid told the BBC.&lt;ref name=Casciani/&gt;

===Criticism of the concept===
The concept has been criticized on a number of grounds. Some critics argue that Islamophobia is real but is just another form of racism and doesn't deserve its own category, while others argue that, unlike racism, Islam is a religion that people can choose to adopt or not, retain or [[apostacy|apostatize]] from. Many argue that the term Islamophobia is often used to censor criticism and therefore its use threatens [[free speech]]. 
[[Image:Salman-Rushdie-2.jpg|right|thumb|200px|[[Salman Rushdie]] was one of 12 prominent writers who signed a statement condemning Islamophobia as a "wretched concept."&lt;ref name=Rushdie/&gt;]]

In March 2006, in the wake of the [[Jyllands-Posten Muhammad cartoons controversy]], a group of 12 prominent writers put their names to a statement in the French weekly satirical newspaper ''[[Charlie Hebdo]]'', in which they warned against the use of the term Islamophobia to prevent criticism of what they called Islamic totalitarianism. The statement alleged that "Islamism is a reactionary ideology that kills equality, freedom and secularism wherever it is present." It continued: "We refuse to renounce our critical spirit out of fear of being accused of "Islamophobia", a wretched concept that confuses criticism of Islam as a religion and stigmatisation of those who believe in it."&lt;ref name=Rushdie/&gt; The signatories included British novelist [[Salman Rushdie]], French philosopher [[Bernard-Henri Lévy]], American writer [[Ibn Warraq]], French journalist and ''Charlie Hebdo'' editor [[Philippe Val]], Bengali physician and writer [[Taslima Nasrin]], Canadian journalist [[Irshad Manji]], and Dutch writer and politician [[Ayaan Hirsi Ali]].&lt;ref name=Rushdie/&gt;

British columnist Josie Appleton argues that the Runnymede Trust's use of Islamophobia is an attempt to discourage [[criticism of Islam]]. "Rather than engage Muslims in debate, non-Muslims are supposed to tiptoe around them, for fear of causing offence."&lt;ref name=Appleton&gt;Appleton, Josie. '[http://www.spiked-online.co.uk/Articles/00000006D95B.htm "Who's afraid of Islamophobia"], 'Spiked Online'', July 2, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Afshin Ellian]], a Dutch law professor, writes that the concept is used to delegitimize criticism by characterizing it as [[Psychopathology|pathological]],&lt;ref name="Ellian"&gt;[[Afshin Ellian|Ellian, Afshin]]. [http://kvc.minbuza.nl/uk/current/2006/february/ellian.html "Stop Capitulating to Threats"], February 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; while civil-rights activist Bahram Soroush has called it "[i]ntellectual blackmail".&lt;ref&gt;[http://bussorah.tripod.com/soroush.html TV International Interview with Bahram Soroush], June 7, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt; 

Critics have cited the case of British journalist [[Polly Toynbee]], who was nominated in May 2003 for the title of "Most Islamophobic Media Personality of the Year" at the [[Annual Islamophobia Awards]] overseen by the [[Islamic Human Rights Commission]]. The nomination was based on her comments in ''The Guardian'' that "[w]herever Islam either is the government or bears down upon the government, it imposes harsh regimes that deny the most basic human rights."&lt;ref name=Toynbee&gt;Toynbee, Polly. [http://www.guardian.co.uk/Columnists/Column/0,,563618,00.html "Last chance to speak out"], ''The Guardian'', October 5, 2001.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Kenan Malik]] argues that Islamophobia is an irrational concept, confusing criticism of Muslims with criticism of their religion, and that the extent to which Muslims are more vulnerable to social exclusion and attacks than other groups is exaggerated. He writes that the concept allows politicians who may have supported the [[Iraq War|war in Iraq]] or the [[War against Terror]] to "reclaim the moral high ground" and "pitch for the Muslim vote."&lt;ref name=Malik/&gt; The result, he argues, is the creation of a culture of victimhood, allowing individual Muslims to attribute low achievement to Islamophobia, and not to themselves. Malik cites [[Yasmin Alibhai Brown]], who writes: "It is not Islamophobia that makes parents take 14 year old bright girls out of school to marry illiterate men ..."&lt;ref name=Malik/&gt; Malik argues that Islamophobia is not a form of racism because it's a belief system. "I can be hateful about other beliefs, such as conservatism or communism. So why can't I be hateful about religion too?&lt;ref name=Malik/&gt;

[[Johann Hari]] of ''[[The Independent]]'' has criticized the use of the term by organizations like [[Islamophobia Watch]], arguing that liberal Muslims interested in reform are left unsupported because people fear being accused of Islamophobia. He writes: "If Muslim women and Muslim [[gay]]s are going to have any kind of decent life, the [Muslim] liberals need to receive solidarity and support – but slap-dash charges of Islamophobia intimidate people who could offer it ... While Islamophobia Watch talk about defending Muslims, they end up defending the nastiest and most right-wing part of the Muslim community – the ones who are oppressing and killing the rest."&lt;ref name=Hari&gt;Hari, Johann. [http://www.johannhari.com/archive/article.php?id=897 "Don't call me an Islamophobe"], June 6, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Islamophobia-phobia====
Writing in the [[New Humanist]], philosopher Piers Benn suggests that people who fear the rise of Islamophobia foster an environment "not intellectually or morally healthy", to the point that what he calls "Islamophobia-phobia" can undermine "critical scrutiny of Islam as somehow impolite, or ignorant of the religion's true nature", encouraging "sentimental pretence that all claims to religious truth are somehow 'equal', or that critical scrutiny of Islam (or any belief system) is ignorant, prejudiced, or ‘phobic’".&lt;ref name=Benn&gt;[http://www.rationalist.org.uk/newhumanist/issue02summer/benn.shtml "On Islamophobia-phobia"].&lt;/ref&gt;

''[[The New Criterion]]'' editor [[Roger Kimball]] argues that the word "Islamophobia" is a misnomer. "A phobia describes an irrational fear, and it is axiomatic that fearing the effects of radical Islam is not irrational, but on the contrary very well-founded indeed, so that if you want to speak of a legitimate phobia — it’s a phobia I experience frequently — we should speak instead of Islamophobia-phobia, the fear of and revulsion towards Islamophobia."&lt;ref name=Kimball&gt;Kimball, Roger. [http://64.233.161.104/search?q=cache:lwExDa3Rx_8J:www.dsf.unica.it/~fiore/AftertheSuicideoftheWest.html+ "After the suicide of the West"], January 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Response to criticism===
[[Image:JehanzebHasan.jpg|left|frame|Jehanzeb Hasan argues that the conflation of  "[[Osama bin Laden|Osamaism]]" with [[Islam]] has given rise to Islamophobia.]]
Jehanzeb Hasan, a research assistant at [[California State University]], argues that those he calls Islamophobes are actually reacting to "[[Osama bin Laden|Osamaism]]," not Islam. Hasan argues that Islam is a religion of peace, not violence, and is misrepresented by its most vocal proponents and critics. "Osamaists and Islamophobes ignore the dynamic nature of the religion and deny the diversity of belief within Islam. Instead of constantly being pondered and contemplated for meanings, Islam is [[Lowest common denominator|dumbed down]] by those who seek to essentialize it for the purpose of augmenting their own sociopolitical agendas."&lt;ref name=Hasan&gt;Hasan, Jehanzeb. [http://world.mediamonitors.net/content/view/full/33816 "Confronting the Monolith: The Struggle against Islamophobia and Osamaism"], ''Media Monitors Network'', August 7, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; The aggressive behavior and beliefs of what he calls a "group of far-right individuals" claiming to follow a particular religion should not be [[Conflation|conflated]] with the behavior and beliefs of every single other individual who practises that religion. Those he calls "mired in the conflation-prone school of thought" are unable or unwilling to differentiate Osamism from Islam, and with the deliberate or inadvertent erection of the "[[monolith]]" comes Islamophobia.

Hasan is equally critical of attempts to dismiss Islamophobia as a [[myth]]. He asks: "[W]ho could seriously argue that fear, hatred, or prejudice towards Muslims doesn't exist?" But while accusations of racism can indeed be misused, that does not mean they are ''always'' misused, Hasan argues. Dismissal of the concept because of its misuse is simply a "convenient justification to pooh-pooh the problem away."&lt;ref name=Hasan/&gt;

Hasan also attacks the argument that Islamophobia is not racism, given that Islam is a religion and adherence to it a matter of choice. That Islam is not a race is a "tired catchphrase," he argues. "Both forms of prejudice are founded upon a monolithic and [[Stereotype|stereotypical]] presupposition. For example, while a racist would assume all or most African-Americans think or behave a certain way, an Islamophobe, too, would believe that all or most Muslims think or behave a certain way." Islamophobia and racism are, he writes, conceptually very much the same thing.&lt;ref name=Hasan/&gt;

==Islamophobia in Europe==
Ziauddin Sardar writes in ''The New Statesman'' that Islamophobia is a widespread European phenomenon, so widespread that he asks whether Muslims will be the victims of the next [[pogroms]].&lt;ref name=Sardar&gt;[http://www.newstatesman.com/200512050006 "The next holocaust"], ''New Statesman'', December 5, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; He writes that each country has its extremes, citing [[Jean-Marie Le Pen]] in France; [[Pim Fortuyn]], who was assassinated in Holland; and Philippe Van der Sande of [[Vlaams Blok]], a [[Flemish]] nationalist party founded in Belgium. [[Filip Dewinter]], the leader of the nationalist Flemish "[[Vlaams Belang]]" has said his party is "Islamophobic." He said: "Yes, we are afraid of Islam. The Islamisation of Europe is a frightening thing."&lt;ref&gt;[http://flemishrepublic.org/current_issue.php?id=50 "Belgian Establishment Fears Crack-Up"], The Flemish Republic.org newsletter, April-June 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

The clash between [[Culture of Europe|European liberal culture]] and that culture's perception of Islam gives rise to allegations of Islamophobia in a number of areas. Italian prime minister [[Silvio Berlusconi]]'s statement that Western civilization is "superior" to Islam was regarded as an example of Islamophobic.&lt;ref name=Appleton/&gt; In Germany, the state of [[Baden-Württemberg]] requires citizenship applicants from the member states of the [[Organization of the Islamic Conference]] to answer questions about their attitudes on [[homosexuality]] and [[domestic violence]]. [http://www.expatica.com/source/site_article.asp?subchannel_id=52&amp;story_id=26707&amp;name=Failing+the+tolerance+test] [http://www.militantislammonitor.org/article/id/1524]. Clothing has become a flashpoint. France, which has a strong secular tradition separating church and state, [http://yaleglobal.yale.edu/display.article?id=3013] was accused of Islamophobia when girls who wear muslim headscarfs were expelled from school under a new law. [http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/4616664.stm]&lt;ref&gt; The French policy extends to all visible religious paraphernalia, including large Christian crosses and Jewish [[kippah|scullcaps]], although small [[crucifix]]es and [[Star of David|stars of David]] are still allowed.&lt;/ref&gt; In January 2006, the Dutch parliament voted in favour of a proposal to ban the [[burqa]] in public, which led to similar accusations.&lt;ref name=Mardell&gt;Madell, Mark. [http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/4616664.stm "Dutch MPs to decide on burqa ban"], BBC News, January 16, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

Sardar argues that Europe is "post-colonial, but ambivalent." Minorities are regarded as acceptable as an underclass of menial workers, but if they want to be upwardly mobile, as Sardar says young Muslims do, the prejudice rises to the surface. Wolfram Richter, professor of economics at [[Dortmund University]], told Sardar: "I am afraid we have not learned from our history. My main fear is that what we did to Jews we may now do to Muslims. The next holocaust would be against Muslims."&lt;ref name=Sardar/&gt;

===EUMC report===
The largest monitoring project to be commissioned into Islamophobia was undertaken following 9/11 by the [[European Monitoring Centre on Racism and Xenophobia]] (EUMC). Their May 2002 report "Summary report on Islamophobia in the EU after 11 September 2001," written [[Dr. Chris Allen]] and Jorgen S. Nielsen of the [[University of Birmingham]], was based on 75 reports – 15 from each EU member nation.&lt;ref name=EUMC&gt;Allen, Chris and Nielsen, Jorgen S. [http://www.raxen.eumc.eu.int/1/webmill.php?id=32813&amp;ditem=3101&amp;lin=detail "Summary report on Islamophobia in the EU after 11 September 2001"], EUMC, May, 2002.&lt;/ref&gt;
 
The report highlighted the regularity with which ordinary Muslims became targets for abusive and sometimes violent retaliatory attacks after 9/11. Despite localized differences within each member nation, the recurrence of attacks on recognizable and visible traits of Islam and Muslims was the report's most significant finding. The attacks took the form of verbal abuse; blaming all Muslims for terrorist attacks; women having their [[hijab]] torn from their heads; male and female Muslims being spat at; children being called "Usama"; and random assaults, which left victims hospitalized, and on one occasion, left a victim paralysed.&lt;ref name=EUMC/&gt;

The report also discussed the representation of Muslims in the media. Inherent negativity, stereotypical images, fantastical representations, and exaggerated caricatures were all identified. The report concluded that "a greater receptivity towards anti-Muslim and other xenophobic ideas and sentiments has, and may well continue, to become more tolerated."&lt;ref name=EUMC/&gt;

==Effect on Arabs==
{{main|Anti-Arabism}}
Since [[9/11]], given the strong association between [[Arab]]s and the religion of [[Islam]], Islamophobia is sometimes expressed as a form of [[anti-Arab]] racism, though the majority of Muslims are not Arabs. In the UK, anti-Arab sentiment is quite rare and so Islamophobia has been seen, to some degree at least, as being transitory: a cultural racism that has shifted from markers of race to markers of religion. In Germany, the majority of victims have not been Arabs, but rather are from [[Turkey]], perhaps the most secular Islamic country. Anti-Muslim bias has also occasionally been expressed in violent attacks on [[Sikh]]s who were mistaken for Muslims on account of their distinctive turbans.

==Country-specific polls and surveys== 
===Australia===
In 2006, the ''[[Sunday Herald Sun]]'' commissioned a [[Gallup Poll]], published on July 30, which reported that four in ten of those [[Australia]]ns surveyed "believe Islam is a threat to our way of life" and one in three people are more fearful of Muslims since the [[September 11, 2001 attacks]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.greenleft.org.au/back/2006/678/678p3b.htm Islamophobia and imperialist wars] - Green left Weekly. [[August 9]], [[2006]]&lt;/ref&gt; A similar poll from Australia in March of that year saw that one quarter of those surveyed say Islam as "either a fundamentalist or intolerant faith". However, one of the researchers behind the study, New South Wales University's Kevin Dunn said people tended to feel less threatened by Islam when they had direct contact with its followers. "That varies according to the extent of knowledge someone has and also, fundamentally, the extent of daily contact someone has with Muslims. If you know a few Muslims, you're much less likely to perceive a threat from them."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.abc.net.au/news/newsitems/200603/s1595826.htm Poll shows ignorance of Islam] - [[Australian Broadcasting Corporation]], [[March 20]], [[2006]].&lt;/ref&gt;

===Germany===
In 2006 a survey of [[Germany|Germans]] by the Allensbach Institute commissioned by the [[Frankfurter Allgemeine Zeitung]] revealed that 56% of those surveyed wanted the government to ban the building of [[mosque]]s, 62% believed that there would always be ‘[[Clash of Civilizations|major conflicts]]’ between Islam and Christianity. 91% linked Islam to the "oppression of women" while 71% believed Islam was "intolerant". 40% of the participants believed that "tough limits should be imposed on the practice of Islam in Germany". The Allensbach Institute concluded that "The clash of civilizations has already begun in the minds of (German) citizens".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.islamonline.com/cgi-bin/news_service/world_full_story.asp?service_id=2425 Islamophobia on the rise in Germany – Poll] - [[Islam Online]], [[May 22]], [[2006]]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Spain===
A 2006 [[Instituto Elcano]] poll in Spain indicated that 68% of Spanish, consider Muslim societies as "violent", and 79% as "non-tolerant". Also 74% think that there is already a [[clash of civilizations]] between western countries and [[Muslim World]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.20minutos.es/noticia/110187/0/opinion/espanoles/iran/ El 79% de los españoles cree que los musulmanes son intolerantes y el 68 % dice que son violentos] - 20 Minutos.es&lt;/ref&gt;

===Sweden===
In 2006, a survey of Swedes by Demoskop, reported in ''[[Dagens Nyheter]]'', shows that 33% of over-65s think that [[Islam in Sweden|Muslims]] threaten Swedish culture; 15% of those between 15 and 27 answered yes to the same question.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dn.se/DNet/jsp/polopoly.jsp?d=572&amp;a=551542&amp;previousRenderType=2 DN: "Var tredje pensionär kritisk till invandringen"]&lt;/ref&gt;

===United Kingdom===
A BBC survey taken in the summer of 2004 found that employment applicants with Muslim names were far less likely to be called for an interview than applicants whose names did not appear to be Muslim. This study was taken by using fictitious applications to jobs using candidate descriptions that were similar in qualification and education, but under different names. The survey found that while a quarter of 'nonmuslim applicants' were invited to an interview, only 9% of the applications with Muslim names were responded to with invitations.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/pressoffice/pressreleases/stories/2004/07_july/12/minorities_survey.shtml Five Live survey suggests ethnic minority applicants still discriminated against in UK job market] - [[BBC News]] [[Press Office]]. [[July 12]], [[2004]].&lt;/ref&gt; Groups, such as the [[Muslim Council of Britain]] have cited this as further evidence for the widespread existence of Islamophobia.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.prospect-magazine.co.uk/article_details.php?id=6764 Is Islamophobia a myth?] - [[Prospect (magazine)]]. [[January]], [[2005]].&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2005, ''The Guardian'' commissioned an [[ICM (polling)|ICM]] poll which indicated an increase in Islamophobic incidents, particularly after the [[7/7|London bombings]] in July 2005.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/attackonlondon/story/0,,1536222,00.html Two-thirds of Muslims consider leaving UK] The Guardian - Tuesday July 26, 2005&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://image.guardian.co.uk/sys-files/Politics/documents/2005/07/26/Muslim-Poll.pdf ICM-Guardian poll] Poll of Muslims in the UK. The Guardian - Tuesday July 26, 2005&lt;/ref&gt; Another survey of Muslims, this by the Open Society Institute, found that of those polled 32% believed they had suffered religious descrimination at airports, and 80% said they had experienced Islamophobia.&lt;ref&gt;[http://islamonline.net/English/News/2004-11/22/article06.shtml Spiraling Islamophobia Alienating British Muslims: Report] Islam Online - Nov 22 2004&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/islam/story/0,,1362423,00.html ... And why we urgently need new answers] Sarfraz Manzoor - The Guardian - November 30, 2004&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2006, a [[YouGov]] poll indicated that 53% of those people polled felt threatened by Islam, as distinct from fundamentalist Islamists; 18% believed that "a large proportion of British Muslims feel no sense of loyalty to this country and are prepared to condone or even carry out acts of terrorism," while 16% believe "practically all British Muslims are peaceful, law-abiding citizens who deplore terrorist acts as much as anyone else."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/main.jhtml?xml=/news/2006/08/25/nislam25.xml Islam poses a threat to the West, say 53pc in poll] - [[Daily Telegraph]]. [[25 August]], [[2006]]&lt;/ref&gt;

===United States===
[[Image:StoptheHateBanner2.jpg|right|300px|thumb|The Islamic Political Party of America launched its "Stop the Hate" campaign against Islamophobia to cooincide with the [[United Nations]] conference on the subject, "Unlearning Intolerance," on [[December 7]], [[2004]].]]

Arabs and Muslims immigrated and assimilated in American society without great difficulty until the 1970s when stereotypes of Arabs and Muslims became more negative.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ameu.org/page.asp?iid=117&amp;aid=159&amp;pg=1 The Muslim Experience in the United States] by: Yvonne Y. Haddad. - The Link, via Americans for Middle East Understanding. [[September]] - [[October]], [[1979]].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.everyculture.com/multi/Le-Pa/Lebanese-Americans.html Lebanese Americans] - by Paula Hajar and J. Sydney Jones. Via Every Culture.com.&lt;/ref&gt; 
Immediately after [[September 11, 2001 Attacks|9/11]], American attitudes toward Islam were generally positive, with 47% favorable and 39% unfavorable,&lt;ref name="Pewpoll"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://pewforum.org/publications/surveys/Inter-Religious-Understanding.pdf | title=Prospects for Inter-Religious Understanding: Will Views Toward Muslims and Islam Follow Historical Trends?| accessdate=2006-08-19| month=March 22| =2006|  work=Pew FOrum on Religion and Public Life}}&lt;/ref&gt; (whereas Catholism polled at 48% favorable, 37% unfavorable [http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2006/04/12/national/main1494697.shtml]).

Since then, public opinion in the U.S. has moved from neutrality towards apparent fear of Arabs and Muslims, with Islam polling between 19-41% favorable&lt;ref name="Gallupinter"&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.usatoday.com/news/sept11/2002/02/27/usat-poll.htm| title=Many in Islamic world doubt Arabs behind 9/11| first=Andrea| last=Stone| month=February 27| year=2002|  publisher=USA TOday}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Pewpoll"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2006/04/12/national/main1494697.shtml CBS News] [[4 April]], [[2006]]&lt;/ref&gt; despite the fact that most Arab Americans have [[Christian]] related backgrounds.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.aaiusa.org/arab-americans/22/demographics|publisher=[[Editor and Publisher]] |date=[[2005-07-11]]|title = Arab Americans}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A 2006 [[Gallup]] survey of American public opinion found that "many Americans harbor strong bias against U.S. Muslims".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.editorandpublisher.com/eandp/news/article_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1002984956 |publisher=[[Editor and Publisher]] |date=[[2006-08-10]]|title= Gallup: Many Americans Harbor Strong Bias Against U.S. Muslims}}&lt;/ref&gt; 	 
* 22% say they would not like to have a Muslim as a neighbor. 	 
* 34% believe U.S. Muslims support al-Qaeda. 	 
* 49% believe U.S. Muslims are loyal to the United States. 	 
* 39% advocate that U.S. Muslims should carry special ID

A poll of Americans, commissioned by [[CAIR]], suggested that one in four Americans believe Muslims value human life less than others and teach their children to hate.&lt;ref&gt;[http://english.aljazeera.net/NR/exeres/F8CE9C6E-86E4-4ED1-82E3-ADE787D3AF48.htm Poll reveals US Islamophobia] - October 05, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Use in public discourse and examples==
{{Islam}}

===Efforts against Islamophobia===
There have been a series of efforts against islamophobia by many organizations in many countries, some of these efforts are detailed below.

*[[Council on American-Islamic Relations]] (CAIR) states that throughout the 2000s, it has been active in defending [[Islam in the United States|American Muslims]] against Islamophobia.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cair-net.org/default.asp?Page=corePrinciples The Council on American-Islamic Relations - CAIR: Core Principles] ''CAIR''&lt;/ref&gt;
*In 2006, the [[Organization of the Islamic Conference]] (OIC) set up an observatory on Islamophobia which will monitor and document all anti-Islamic activities around the world.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.islamonline.com/cgi-bin/news_service/world_full_story.asp?service_id=2398 "OIC set up observatory on Islamophobia"] ''IslamOnline'', May 9, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; 
* During the ascession talks regarding Turkeys possible entry to the EU, then [[Prime Minister of Holland]], [[Jan Peter Balkenende]], said Islamophobia must not affect the possibility of Turkey's entry to the [[European Union]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/3913335.stm Islam 'must not cloud Turkey bid'] BBC -Wednesday, 21 July, 2004&lt;/ref&gt;
*50,000 people signed a petition urging the [[President of France]], [[Jacques Chirac]] to curb the growing hatred and discrimination towards Muslims in France.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.adnki.com/index_2Level_English.php?cat=Religion&amp;loid=8.0.306056413&amp;par= FRANCE: 50,000 SIGN UP AGAINST ISLAMOPHOBIA] - ADN Kronos - June 2, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;
*In the UK, a number of methods aimed at curbing Islamophobia have been set up. In [[Tower Hamlets]], a densely populated area with a large Muslim community, a crime reporting scheme called "Islamophobia - Don't Suffer in Silence" has been set up which police hope will raise awareness of Islamophobia and help them to understand the extent of the problem.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/england/london/4017617.stm Scheme to fight faith hate crimes] BBC - Wednesday, 17 November, 2004&lt;/ref&gt; The British [[National Union of Teachers]] (NUT) has issued guidance to teachers in the union advising that teachers have to "Challenge Islamophobia", and that they have a "crucial role" to play in helping to "dispel myths about Muslim communities".&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/education/4687417.stm Teaching tolerance amid tension] BBC - Friday, 15 July, 2005&lt;/ref&gt; 
* Following an Islamist demonstration outside the Danish Embassy in London organized by the [[Al Ghurabaa]] organization in response to the [[Jyllands-Posten Muhammad cartoons controversy]], the [[Muslim Association of Britain]] organized a peaceful rally in [[Trafalgar Square]] attended by over three thousand people, many came by bus from towns and citys throughout the UK. Organizers made available placards and T-shirts bearing the rally's official slogan, the phrase, "United against Islamophobia, united against incitement."&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/help/3681938.stm Prayer mats lined the pavements] BBC - Saturday, 11 February 2006&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/cartoonprotests/story/0,,1708080,00.html Muslims fly flag for peaceful protest against cartoons] The Guardian - Sunday February 12, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; 
*Following the [[July 7 bombings]], the British government set up a number of initiatives aimed at combatting Islamophobia, including the "National Forum against extremism and Islamophobia".&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/4423668.stm Call for Muslim scholars to tour] BBC - Thursday, 10 November 2005&lt;/ref&gt; There was also plans by the British government to ban incitement to "religious hatred", however, this failed to get through the [[British House of Commons|House of Commons]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/programmes/bbc_parliament/4652669.stm Racial and Religious Hatred Bill] BBC - Friday, 27 January 2006&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/politics/4668266.stm Religious hatred: How MPs voted] BBC - Wednesday, 1 February 2006&lt;/ref&gt;
*The [[Mayor of London]], [[Ken Livingstone]], said that the Media bore some responsibility for the apparent rise in Islamophobia, and said that a "rising tide of Islamophobia" in the media must be challenged. He compared the reporting of Muslims in contemporary Britain to the way the flight of Jews from Russia had been covered 100 years ago.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/4197218.stm Muslim media image 'must change'] BBC - Wednesday, 31 August 2005&lt;/ref&gt;
*In 2006 the ''Catholic Mission Austria'' and the ''Islamic Demonination Austria'' created a platform called [http://www.christenundmuslime.at Christians and Muslims], which works against stereotypes and hostility and aims to increase tolerance and respect. As of July 25, 2006 the platform has 1452 supporters.
*In 1991 the [http://www.funci.org/ Islamic Culture Foundation (FUNCI)] organised, in collaboration with UNESCO and the Institut du Monde Arabe of Paris, an International Conference about the Contribution of Islamic Civilization in European Culture. In [[March 13]] [[2003]] they created a [http://www.funci.org/en/2003/manifesto-against-islamophobia/ Manifesto against Islamophobia].
*[[The Hashemite Kingdom of Jordan]] issued a call in 1999 to world leaders to combat Islamophobia.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/453060.stm Jordan: Stop attacking Islam] BBC - Tuesday, September 21, 1999&lt;/ref&gt; Abdel-Elah Khatib, the Jordanian foreign minister said "The international community must consider how to confront this phenomenon of Islamophobia in order to prevent its proliferation".

===Acts attributed to Islamophobia===
* Dr Amanda Wise and Ghali Hassan from GlobalResearch.ca have alleged that the [[2005 Cronulla riots]] were the result of a climate of "Islamophobia" in Australia.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.abc.net.au/ra/news/viewpoints/s1535149_to.htm Racial unrest offers opportunity for discussion], ''Australian Broadcasting Corporation'', December 20, 2005&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.globalresearch.ca/index.php?context=viewArticle&amp;code=HAS20051214&amp;articleId=1485 The Rise of Islamophobia in ‘White Australia’], ''Global Research'', December 14, 2005&lt;/ref&gt; 
* Dalil Boubakeur, a director of a Paris mosque described the vandalism on a Mosque in [[Paris]], [[France]] as Islamophobic.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/france/story/0,,1419719,00.html Vandals target Paris mosque] The Guardian - Tuesday February 22, 2005&lt;/ref&gt;
* Attack on a Mosque in [[Brisbane]], [[Australia]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/asia-pacific/1544481.stm Mosque attacked in Australia], ''BBC News'', September 14, 2001&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.adcq.qld.gov.au/pubs/annualrep2002/page05.html Annual Report 2001-02 for the Anti-Discrimination Commission Queensland], ''Anti-Discrimination Commission Queensland'', October 30, 2002&lt;/ref&gt;
* Giles Tremlett of ''[[The Guardian]]'' referred to the burning of a Muslim Sanctuary in the Spanish city of [[Ceuta]], as an instance of Islamophobia.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/international/story/0,,1755600,00.html Burning of sanctuary stokes fears of Islamophobia in Spain], ''The Guardian'', April 18, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;
* Smearing of a [[Qur'an]] with what appeared to be [[feces]] and dumping it in [[Nashville, Tennessee]], [[United States]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tennessean.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20050802/NEWS0202/508020337/1009/NEWS Purcell, city leaders reach out to Muslims], ''The Tennessean'', August 2, 2005&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newschannel5.com/content/news/12326.asp Burning Of Koran Investigated As Hate Crime], ''NewsChannel 5 Network'', [[June 23]], [[2005]]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Halima Mautbur, from the [[Canadian Council on American-Islamic Relations]] called an attack on a [[hijab]]i Muslim woman "an Islamophobic incident".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.news.utoronto.ca/inthenews/archive/2006_03_16.html Muslim groups want action from U of T], ''University of Toronto News'', March 16, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Doudou Diène]] in a report prepared by the [[UN Commission on Human Rights]] released on March 7, 2006 mentioned the publishing of the cartoons at the heart of the [[Jyllands-Posten Muhammad cartoons controversy]] regarding, "The development of Islamophobia or any racism and racial discrimination ..."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.un.org/apps/news/story.asp?NewsID=17718&amp;Cr=racis&amp;Cr1 Racism and racial discrimination on rise around the world, UN expert warns], ''UN NEWS CENTRE'', March 7, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; 
* In a February 10, 2004 report by [[Al Jazeera]] the head of the Party of France's Muslims, [[Muhammad Latreche]] in discussing the [[French law on secularity and conspicuous religious symbols in schools]] was quoted as saying that the legislation would, "institutionalise Islamophobia".&lt;ref&gt;[http://english.aljazeera.net/NR/exeres/6C6049B0-28A1-4093-9FDA-83DEF32D9793.htm French parliament approves hijab ban], ''Al Jazeera'', February 10, 2004&lt;/ref&gt;
* On March 8, 2006 the [[Islamic Human Rights Commission]] made a press release entitled, "Islamophobia in Prisons stretches far beyond Belmarsh" concerning prisons in Britain.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ihrc.org.uk/show.php?id=1746 Islamophobia in Prisons stretches far beyond Belmarsh], ''Islamic Human Rights Commission'', March 8, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; 
* Destruction and vandalism of Muslim graves in France.&lt;ref&gt;[http://archives.cnn.com/2002/WORLD/europe/05/24/eu.violence/index.html EU reports post-Sept. 11 racism] CNN - May 24, 2002&lt;/ref&gt;
* Vandalism of Muslim Graves in Charlton cemetery in Plumstead, London.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mcb.org.uk/media/presstext.php?ann_id=76 Appalling Desecration of Muslim Graves in Plumstead] Mulsim Council of Britan - 19 Mar 2004 &lt;/ref&gt;
* Muslim protesters alleged that the [[2 June 2006 London terror raid|Forest Gate anti terror raid]] in London was Islamophobic.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mabonline.info/english/modules.php?name=News&amp;file=article&amp;sid=706 MAB Horrified at Forest Gate Security Blunder], ''The Muslim Association of Britain'', June 7, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rinf.com/columnists/news/muslims-call-on-police-chief-to-resign-over-forest-gate-terror-raid Muslims call on Police chief to resign over Forest Gate terror raid], ''RINF'', June 11, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;
*France, which has a strong secular tradition [[Separation of church and state|separating church from State]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://yaleglobal.yale.edu/display.article?id=3013 France to Ban Pupils' Religious Dress], ''YaleGlobal'', December 12, 2003&lt;/ref&gt; was accused of Islamophobia when the [[French law on secularity and conspicuous religious symbols in schools|law on secularity and conspicuous religious symbols in schools]] was passed, which bans the wearing of conspicuous religious symbols in public schools. The policy extends to Muslim headscarves, large Christian crosses, Jewish skullcaps, and other visible signs of religion, although the display of small[http://www.assemblee-nationale.fr/12/rapports/r1381.asp][http://www.bbc.co.uk/religion/news/indepth/france/] religious symbols (such as the [[Star of David]], [[cross]]es, and [[Hand of Fatima]]s) is permitted. 
*In Germany, the state of [[Baden-Württemberg]] has proposed regulations that require citizenship applicants from the member states of the [[Organization of the Islamic Conference]] to answer questions about their attitudes on [[homosexuality]], [[domestic violence]] and other religious issues.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.muslimnews.co.uk/paper/index.php?article=2296 ‘German loyalty tests are Islamophobic’] - The Muslim News - Friday 27 January 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

===Views labeled as Islamophobic===
* The [[United American Committee]] has often been charged with being an Islamophobic organization.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.islamophobia-watch.com/islamophobia-watch/2006/9/12/protestors-hang-bin-laden-effigy-outside-us-mosque.html  Islamophobia Watch], September 11, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.socialistworker.org/2006-1/579/579_12_Racism.shtml  Socialist Worker Online: UAC Displays Prophet Muhammad Cartoons], March 10, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Carl Ernst]], an academic scholar of Islamic studies, and the [[Council on American-Islamic Relations]] include those who asserts that [[Robert Spencer]] is an Islamophobe.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.cair-net.org/default.asp?Page=articleView&amp;id=1853&amp;theType=NR CA Synagogue That Hosted Islamophobe Urged to Invite Muslim Speaker], CAIR News Releases, November 08, 2005 &lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Ernst"&gt; [http://www.unc.edu/courses/2004spring/reli/026/001/spencer.htm Notes on the Ideological Patrons of an Islamophobe, Robert Spencer by Carl W. Ernst] - [[University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill]], [[2004]]&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[Council on American-Islamic Relations]] has stated that the views of [[Ann Coulter]] are Islamophobic&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cair-net.org/default.asp?Page=articleView&amp;id=1048&amp;theType=NR Ann Coulter says Muslims 'Smell Bad'], ''Council on American-Islamic Relations'', March 10, 2004&lt;/ref&gt;
* Oliver Duff of ''[[The Independent]]'' has claimed that the [[British National Party]] has attempted to use increasing Islamophobia to make gains in local elections.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.independent.co.uk/uk/politics/article356477.ece  Rising Islamophobia makes Birmingham fertile ground for BNP], ''The Independent'', April 8, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; In previous decades, the BNP was also deemed [[anti-semitic]] by Jewish groups.
* [[Oriana Fallaci]], who was an Italian journalist and authored "[[The Force of Reason]]",&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/italy/story/0,,1873911,00.html Obituary of Oriana Fallaci] - [[The Guardian]], [[16 September]], [[2006]]. "''Controversial Italian journalist famed for her interviews and war reports but notorious for her Islamaphobia''"&lt;/ref&gt; she was also accused of outright [[racism]] towards Mexicans and Arabs&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/farright/story/0,11981,731126,00.html Bible of the Muslim haters], ''The Guardian'', June 11, 2002&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.zmag.org/content/showarticle.cfm?ItemID=9365 Institutionalised Hatred and Instigating Murder], ''Z Magazine'', December 20, 2005&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[Islamic Human Rights Commission]] gave U.S Attorney General [[John Ashcroft]] a nomination for their 2003 "Islamophobe of the year" award for publicly saying: "Islam is a religion in which God requires you to send your son to die for him. Christianity is a faith in which God sends his son to die for you"&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.inminds.co.uk/islamophobia-awards-2003.html Annual Islamophobia Awards, 2003]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?file=/c/a/2002/02/22/MN146728.DTL "The gospel according to John (Ashcroft)"] San Francisco Chronicle&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[Islamic Human Rights Commission]] made [[Daniel Pipes]] a nominee for their 2004 and 2005 "Islamophobe of the year" awards.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ihrc.org.uk/show.php?id=1124 Winners of Islamophobia Awards 2004], ''Islamic Human Rights Commission'', June 26, 2004. *[http://www.ihrc.org.uk/show.php?id=1657 Winners of the Islamophobia Awards 2005], ''Islamic Human Rights Commission'', December 17, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;
* The political views of [[ultranationalist]] Flemish politician [[Filip Dewinter]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.filipdewinter.org/page.php?linkID=238 Filip Dewinter interview], ''Jewish Week'', December 9, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[United Kingdom|UK]] Minister Peter Hain's statement that Britain's Muslim community is "isolationist" was met with accusations of Islamophobia, as well as [[Italy|Italian]] prime minister [[Silvio Berlusconi]]'s public claim that Western civilization is superior to Islam.&lt;ref name="spiked"&gt;[http://www.spiked-online.co.uk/Articles/00000006D95B.htm Who's afraid of Islamophobia?], ''Spiked'', July 2, 2002&lt;/ref&gt;
* Some suggestions in the [[United Kingdom debate over veils]] (which concerned the circumstances in which Muslim women should be required to remove the [[Niqab]]) were considered Islamophobic &lt;ref name="McDonnell"&gt;See, e.g., "[http://www.john4leader.org.uk/2006/10/wave-of-islamophobia.html Wave of Islamophobia]", a blog post by [[John McDonnell]] MP from [[October 6]], [[2006]].&lt;/ref&gt;

===General references to Islamophobia===
*While in [[Kazakhstan]], the former [[Pontiff]], [[Pope John Paul II]], prayed for "both Christian and Muslims to raise an intense prayer to the one almighty God", and begged "God to keep the world in peace".  He won praise from the [[President of Kazakhstan]], [[Nursultan Nazarbayev]], for "protecting the world from Islamophobia".&lt;ref&gt;[http://archives.cnn.com/2001/WORLD/asiapcf/central/09/23/gen.kazak.pope.peace/index.html Pope prays for peace] CNN - September 23, 2001&lt;/ref&gt;
*In March 2005, [[Queen Noor of Jordan]], while on the BBC television programme "[[Breakfast with Frost]]", said, "What grieves me today, truly, is the fact that not only in the United States but also in Europe we've seen the rise, over the last few years, of Islamophobia" adding, "Muslim populations and the Muslim world has been increasingly, not decreasingly, viewed as a menace, as alien, as, perhaps, incompatible with Western societies and values. And I passionately believe that that is not true and that we have a great deal of work to do there.".&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/programmes/breakfast_with_frost/4365853.stm Jordan's Queen] BBC Transcript of Breakfast with Frost. Sunday, 20 March. &lt;/ref&gt;

=== Publications and publishers labeled as Islamophic ===
[[Carl Ernst]], an academic scholar of Islamic studies, states that particular publications are promoted and supported by right-wing organizations, who are perpetuating Islamophobia. These presses publish books written by Islamophobics. Ernst lists '[[Regnery Publishing|Regnery Publishing Inc]]', '[[Encounter Books]]' and '[[Free Congress Foundation|The Free Congress Foundation]]' and makes some remarks on their funding sources.&lt;ref name="Ernst"&gt; [http://www.unc.edu/courses/2004spring/reli/026/001/spencer.htm Notes on the Ideological Patrons of an Islamophobe, Robert Spencer by Carl W. Ernst] - [[University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill]], [[2004]]&lt;/ref&gt; For example Ernst writes that '[[Encounter Books]]' has been funded with $4,635,000 for its publications over the past ten years all from the Lynde and Harry Bradley Foundation. The free Congress Foundation has received almost $24 million in funding from the Lynde and Harry Bradley Foundation and other conservative sources in the past twenty years.&lt;ref name="Ernst"&gt; [http://www.unc.edu/courses/2004spring/reli/026/001/spencer.htm Notes on the Ideological Patrons of an Islamophobe, Robert Spencer by Carl W. Ernst] - [[University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill]], [[2004]]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Incidents on aircraft===
*On [[23 August]] [[2006]], [[Netherlands|Dutch]] aviation authorities returned a plane to [[Amsterdam Schiphol Airport]] where they detained 12 Indian nationals from the flight, which was bound for [[Mumbai]]. India lodged a strong protest with the Netherlands and relatives of the Indian passengers claimed that their detention was motivated by racial and religious prejudice while the men were released the following day without charge. The sister-in-law of one of the detained men said "He flies frequently for trade fairs and business. But he is Muslim, so he was arrested."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.forbes.com/home/feeds/ap/2006/08/25/ap2973295.html India Protests Dutch Handling of Flight] - [[Forbes]]. [[25 August]], [[2006]]&lt;/ref&gt;

*On [[16 August]] [[2006]], British passengers onboard a flight from Malaga to Manchester requested the removal of two men of Asian descent from a plane. According to a spokesman for the Civil Guard in Malaga, "These men had aroused suspicion because of their appearance and the fact that they were speaking in a foreign language thought to be an Arabic language, and the pilot was refusing to take off until they were escorted off the plane." A security sweep of the plane found no explosives or any item of a terrorist nature. [[Monarch Airlines]] booked the men, who were Urdu speakers, into a hotel room, gave them a free meal and sent them home on a later plane. The men later responded: "Just because we're Muslim, does not mean we are suicide bombers". The Islamic Human Rights Commission blamed "ever-increasing Islamophobia" related to the "war on terror" for the incident.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dailymail.co.uk/pages/live/articles/news/news.html?in_article_id=401419&amp;in_page_id=1770&amp;in_page_id=1770&amp;ct=5&amp;expand=true#StartComments Mutiny as passengers refuse to fly until Asians are removed] - [[Daily Mail|Mail on Sunday]]. [[20 August]], [[2006]]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mirror.co.uk/news/tm_objectid=17607948&amp;method=full&amp;siteid=94762&amp;headline=exclusive--malaga-jet-mutiny-pair-s-shock-at-plane-ejection-name_page.html Exclusive: Malaga Jet mutiny pair's shock at plane ejection] - [[The Daily Mirror]]. [[23 August]],[[2006]].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/airlines/story/0,,1854722,00.html Removal of men from holiday flight condemned][[The Guardian]]. [[21 August]][[2006]]&lt;/ref&gt;

*A passenger travelling to the [[British Virgin Islands]] on a plane bound for the United States from Manchester in the UK was forced off the plane prior to [[takeoff]]. The man, a British-born Muslim residing in the U.S., said he was singled out because he was a Muslim pilot and was left feeling "demoralised and humiliated". "I must have met the profile on the day. I have an Arabic name, I am a Muslim, I'm from Britain and I know how to fly."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.manchestereveningnews.co.uk/news/s/220/220381_muslim_pilot_kicked_off_jet_in_terror_alert.html Muslim pilot kicked off jet in terror alert] - [[Manchester Evening News]]. [[11 August]], [[2006]]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.independent.co.uk/uk/this_britain/article1220859.ece Muslim pilot reveals shock at being ordered off flight] - [[The Independent]]. [[22 August]], [[2006]]&lt;/ref&gt;

*A passenger on a [[United Airlines]] flight was removed by staff after another passenger complained that his recitation of the Muslim evening prayer, ''[[Maghrib]]'', was suspicious. United Airlines ejected the passenger, a Muslim doctor from [[Winnipeg, Manitoba|Winnipeg]], and two of his colleagues  at [[Denver International Airport]] following the report by the concerned passenger, who it is claimed had previously threatened the Muslim doctor. The ejected trio were forced to pay for accommodation and another flight back home. The passenger has demanded an official apology and compensation from United Airlines.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cbc.ca/story/canada/national/2006/08/18/doctor-winnipeg.html Muslim doctor wants apology from U.S. airline] - [[Canadian Broadcasting Corporation]], [[19 August]], [[2006]].&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also== 

* [[Anti-Arabism]]
* [[Persecution of Muslims]]
* [[Islam]]
* [[Criticism of Islam]]
* [[Alliance of Civilizations]]
* [[Clash of Civilizations]]
* [[Islamophobia Watch]]
* [[Religious intolerance]]
* [[Islamofascism]]

==Notes==
&lt;div class="references-small" style="-moz-column-count:2; column-count:2;"&gt;
&lt;references /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

==Further reading==
* [http://www.fairuk.org Forum against Islamophobia and Racism]
* [http://www.backtoislam.com/?cat=50 Misconceptions about Islam]
* [http://www.islamophobia.org Islamophobia.org]
* [http://www.islamawareness.net/Islamophobia/ "Islamophobia"], ''Islamicawareness.net''
* [http://www.islamophobia-watch.com/ Islamophobia Watch]
*[http://islamonline.net/English/artculture/2005/01/article08.shtml Muslims and Islam in European History Textbooks][http://islamonline.net/English/artculture/2005/01/article08-1.shtml Britain] [http://islamonline.net/English/artculture/2005/01/article08-2.shtml Hungary] [http://islamonline.net/English/artculture/2005/01/article08-3.shtml Italy] [http://islamonline.net/English/artculture/2005/01/article08-4.shtml Austria] [http://islamonline.net/English/artculture/2005/01/article08-5.shtml Europe] [http://islamonline.net/English/artculture/2005/01/article08-6.shtml France,Poland] [http://islamonline.net/English/artculture/2005/01/article08-8.shtml Israel] [http://islamonline.net/English/artculture/2005/01/article08-9.shtml USA] [http://islamonline.net/English/artculture/2005/01/article08-7.shtml Greece]Islamonline.net
* [http://www.eyetopic.co.uk/Against_Islamophobia/index.htm "Rally against incitement and Islamophobia in London"], ''[[eyetopic.co.uk]]'', February 11, 2006.
*[[Dr. Chris Allen]] [http://www.chris-allen.co.uk Islamophobia resources: writing, articles &amp; publications]
*Brooks, James. [http://www.islamonline.net/English/Views/2003/05/article11.shtml "Deep roots of Islamophobia] Islamonline.net.

*Deane, Claudia and Fears, Darryl. [http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2006/03/08/AR2006030802221.html Negative Perception Of Islam Increasing], ''The Washington Post'', March 9, 2006.
*[[Khaled Abou Al-Fadl|El Fadl, Khaled Abou]]. [http://www.scholarofthehouse.org/onrebi.html "On revising bigotry"], chapter from '' The Conference on the Books: The Search for Beauty in Islam'', ''Scholars of the House''.
*[[Muriel Gray|Gray, Muriel]]. [http://www.sundayherald.com/53959 "How can we have respect for Islam when we are too fearful to criticise it?"], ''The Glasgow Herald, February 5, 2006.
*Hasan, Jehanzeb. [http://usa.mediamonitors.net/content/view/full/33820 "Confronting the Monolith: The Struggle Against Islamophobia and Osamaism"], Media Monitors Network, August 7, 2006.
*Hassan, Fardusa.  [http://www.guardian.co.uk/race/story/0,,1862329,00.html "Beauty queen enters Islamophobia debate"], ''The Guardian'', August 31, 2006.
*Hassan, Ghali. [http://www.uruknet.info/?p=m20398&amp;l=i&amp;size=1&amp;hd=0 The Road to the Muslim Holocaust], ''Globalresearch.ca'', February 7, 2006.
*[[Norman Lamont|Lamont, Norman]]. [http://www.telegraph.co.uk/opinion/main.jhtml?xml=/opinion/2002/05/08/do0801.xml "Down with multiculturalism, book-burning and fatwas"], ''The Daily Telegraph'', May 8, 2002.
*Marud, Abdal-Hakim. [http://www.masud.co.uk/ISLAM/ahm/right.htm "Muslims and the European Right"], ''Masud.co.uk'', first delivered as a lecture on April 30, 2000.
*[[Brigitte L. Nacos|Nacos, Brigitte L.]], ''Fueling Our Fears: Stereotyping, Media Coverage, and Public Opinion of Muslim Americans''. 2006
*O'Keefe, Derrick. [http://www.sevenoaksmag.com/commentary/macleans.html Maclean's magazine goes over-the-top with racist cover story], Seven Oaks Magazine, October 27, 2006. 
[[Daniel Pipes|Pipes, Daniel]]. [http://www.danielpipes.org/article/3075 "Islamophobia?"], ''New York Sun'', October 25, 2005.
*Ramji, Rubina. [http://www.unomaha.edu/jrf/Vol9No2/RamjiIslam.htm "From ''Navy Seals'' to ''The Siege'': Getting to Know the Muslim Terrorist, Hollywood Style"] ''The Journal of Religion and Film'', Vol. 9, No.2, October 2005 
*[[Ali Sina|Sina, Ali]]. [http://www.faithfreedom.org/oped/sina60526.htm "Islamophobia is ad hominem], www.faithfreedom.org, May 26, 2006.
*[[Walter Laqueur]]. [http://blog.oup.com/oupblog/2006/10/the_use_of_the_.html The Origins of Fascism: Islamic Fascism, Islamophobia, Antisemitism], [[Oxford University Press]] blog.

[[Category:Anti-Islam sentiment]]
[[Category:Islam]]
[[Category:Islamic politics and Islamic world studies]]
[[Category:Phobias]]
[[Category:Political neologisms]]
[[Category:Pejorative political terms]]

[[bg:Ислямофобия]]
[[ca:Islamofòbia]]
[[cs:Islamophobie]]
[[da:Islamofobi]]
[[de:Islamophobie]]
[[fa:اسلام‌ستیزی]]
[[fr:Islamophobie]]
[[he:איסלאמופוביה]]
[[nl:Islamofobie]]
[[no:Islamofobi]]
[[pt:Islamofobia]]
[[ro:Islamofobie]]
[[fi:Islamofobia]]
[[sv:Islamofobi]]
[[tr:İslamofobi]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>