<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20051105001013|27401082" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="162173" pageid="162173" ns="0" title="Islamophobia"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-11-07T23:16:15Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Islamophobia''' is a [[neologism]] used to refer to an irrational fear or [[prejudice]] towards [[Muslims]] and the religion of [[Islam]].

Some believe that prejudice against Muslims has increased since the [[September 11, 2001]] attacks. Dr Abduljalil Sajid, an adviser to the Commission on British Muslims, an anti-racism group, has said he believes many organizations are "institutionally Islamophobic". He has said that "since the 11 September attacks the single most important concern has been [[police]] harassment of Muslims. Even one of [Britain's] Muslim [[Peerage|peers]] ... has been stopped twice by police." [http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/3768327.stm] [[United Nations]]

Many human rights organizations have documented this recent increase in Islamophobic events and [[hate crimes]] against Muslims [http://www.hrw.org/reports/2002/usahate/] and Islamic organizations have done the same [http://www.cair.com/asp/execsum2005.asp]. Secretary-General [[Kofi Annan]] told a [[December 7]], [[2004]] UN conference on the emergence of Islamophobia that "[w]hen the world is compelled to coin a new term to take account of increasingly widespread [[bigotry]] &amp;mdash; that is a sad and troubling development. Such is the case with 'Islamophobia'." [http://www.rferl.org/featuresarticle/2004/12/7e9a94b2-7e8d-4811-a017-1500bde65e62.html] 

[[United States|American]] journalist Stephen Schwartz has defined Islamophobia as the condemnation of the entirety of Islam and its history as [[Extremism|extremist]], denying the existence of a moderate Muslim majority, regarding Islam as a problem for the world, treating conflicts involving Muslims as necessarily their own fault, insisting that Muslims make changes to their religion, and inciting war against Islam as a whole. [http://www.frontpagemag.com/Articles/ReadArticle.asp?ID=17874]

The concept of Islamophobia has been questioned, with some commentators arguing that the term can also be used to censor legitimate criticism of Islam and of individuals. [http://bussorah.tripod.com/soroush.html]

== History and use of the term ==

Islamophobia, as a phenomenon, is believed to date back to the initial [[History of Islam#The spread of Islam|expansion of Islam]] and grew as a result of the [[crusades]]. It has been argued that Islamophobia exists outside the West, for example in India. This is more closely related to communal politics in India, although Islamophobia in India does share, with western Islamophobia, the denigration of Islamic culture and history. {{ref|Dalrymple}}

The term 'Islamophobia' is a [[neologism]] dating from the early 1990s and is formed with the suffix [[-phobia]] in a similar way to [[Xenophobia]] or [[Homophobia]]. As such, it reflects the influence of such [[1990s]] movements as [[multi-culturalism]] and [[identity politics]]. During this period, some [[Sociology|sociologists]] and cultural analysts argued that there was a shift in forms of prejudice from ones based on race to ones based on notions of cultural superiority and otherness. {{ref|Seabrook}} {{ref|Rudiger}} 

Actions and beliefs typically described as Islamophobic range from systematic discrimination to physical assault. Hate crimes against Muslims are commonly categorized as Islamophobic, as is inflammatory hate speech, and criticism. The [[United Kingdom|UK]] Minister Peter Hain's statement that [[Britain]]'s Muslim community is "isolationist" was met with accusations of Islamophobia, and [[Italy|Italian]] prime minister [[Silvio Berlusconi]]'s statement that Western civilization is "superior" to Islam was similarly deemed Islamophobic. [http://www.spiked-online.co.uk/Articles/00000006D95B.htm]

The term most often appears in discourse on the condition of [[immigrant]] Muslims living as [[minority|minorities]] in the [[United States]], [[Europe]], and [[Australia]], although it has also been used in recent years in countries such as [[India]], and occasionally in connection with non-immigrant Muslim communities or individuals. In the most prominent cases, however, experiences of immigrant communities of unemployment, rejection, alienation, and violence have allegedly combined with Islamophobia to make integration difficult. {{ref|Radman}} It has been argued that this has led, in the [[United Kingdom]] for example, to Muslim communities suffering higher levels of unemployment, poor housing, poor health, and levels of racially motivated violence than other communities. {{ref|Malik}} 

After September 11, Given the strong association between [[Arab]]s and the religion of [[Islam]], Islamophobia is often expressed as a form of [[anti-Arab]] racism, though not all Arabs are Muslim and the majority of Muslims are not Arab. Anti-Muslim bias has occasionally been expressed in violent attacks on [[Sikh]]s who were mistaken for Muslims on account of their distinctive turbans. Many human rights organizations have documented this recent trend of Islamophobic events and hate crimes against Muslims. [http://www.hrw.org/reports/2002/usahate/]

==Runnymede Trust usage==
In the [[United Kingdom]], the term "Islamophobia" was not used in government policy until 1997, when the UK race-relations think-tank [[Runnymede Trust]] published the report "Islamophobia: A Challenge For Us All". [http://www.runnymedetrust.org/publications/pdfs/islamophobia.pdf] (pdf) [http://www.spiked-online.co.uk/Articles/00000006D95B.htm] In a section entitled "The Nature of Islamophobia," the report itemizes eight features that Runnymede attributed to Islamophobia:

#Islam is seen as a monolithic bloc, static and unresponsive to change.    
#Islam is seen as separate and "other". It does not have values in common with other cultures, is not affected by them and does not influence them.        
#Islam is seen as inferior to the West. It is seen as barbaric, irrational, primitive, and [[Sexism|sexist]].    
#Islam is seen as violent, aggressive, threatening, supportive of terrorism, and engaged in a 'clash of civilizations'.    
#Islam is seen as a political [[ideology]] and is used for political or military advantage.     
#Criticisms made of the West by Islam are rejected out of hand.     
#Hostility towards Islam is used to justify discriminatory practices towards Muslims and exclusion of Muslims from mainstream society.     
#Anti-Muslim hostility is seen as natural or normal.
#Students in many Western schools report insults against Muslims. 

The Runnymede description of Islamophobia was accepted by the [[European Monitoring Centre on Racism and Xenophobia]] {{fact}} and by numerous Muslim organizations such as FAIR UK, the forum against Islamophobia and racism. British columnist Josie Appleton criticized the definition and wrote:

&lt;blockquote&gt;This [Runnymede] report talked about a rising 'anti-Muslim prejudice' that needed addressing in policy. But the section titled 'The nature of Islamophobia' suggests a very broad notion of prejudice &amp;mdash; examples of Islamophobia included people seeing Islam as inferior to the West, rather than just distinctively different; seeing Islam as monolithic and static, rather than diverse and progressive; seeing Islam as an enemy, rather than a partner to cooperate with (7). This also seemed to be founded on an over-sensitivity, an attempt to stem any kind of criticism of Islam. Rather than engage Muslims in debate, non-Muslims are supposed to tiptoe around them, for fear of causing offence. Since 11 September we have seen how this attitude can stifle discussion. [http://www.spiked-online.co.uk/Articles/00000006D95B.htm]&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==Criticism of the concept==
Some commentators have questioned the concept of Islamophobia, arguing that use of the term is often an attempt to police or [[censorship|censor]] opinion by characterizing any criticism of Islam or Muslims as pathological and irrational, just as use of the term [[anti-Semitism]], many people would argue, may be an attempt to censor criticism of [[Israel]]. Some of these critics cite the case of the [[liberalism|liberal]] [[feminism|feminist]] British journalist [[Polly Toynbee]], who was nominated for the title of "Most Islamophobic Media Personality of the Year" at the [[Annual Islamophobia Awards]], because of her constant insults on Islam without any concrete proof, overseen by the [[Islamic Human Rights Commission]] in May 2003. The nomination was based on her comments in an article she had written for the London-based liberal newspaper ''[[The Guardian]]'': 

&lt;blockquote&gt;Religious politics scar India, Kashmir, Northern Ireland, Sri Lanka, Sudan ... the list of countries wrecked by religion is long. But the present danger is caused by Islamist theocracy &amp;#8230; There is no point in pretending it is not so. Wherever Islam either is the government or bears down upon the government, it imposes harsh regimes that deny the most basic human rights. {{ref|Toynbee}} {{ref|IHRC}}&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;!--The corresponding notes are missing--&gt;

Toynbee has rejected the label of "Islamophobe" and argued that her comments must be judged on their truth or falsity, not on the offence they might give to most members of the Muslim community.

Civil-rights activist Bahram Soroush views the term Islamophobia as a meaningless deflection. He claims the term is a means of avoiding legitimate criticism of Islam and Islamic history by means of name-calling, or is used to create the appearence of widespread hatred against Muslims. [http://bussorah.tripod.com/soroush.html]

== Anti-Islamophobia efforts ==
* The Forum on Islamophobia and Racism (FAIR) dedicates itself to fighting Islamophobia in the United Kingdom. [http://www.fairuk.org/]

* The [[Council on American-Islamic Relations]] (CAIR) recently organized a conference [http://www.cair-net.org/2005conference/program.asp] with the topic of "Islamophobia and Anti-Americanism: Causes and Remedies," which touched on the issue of Islamophobia. Guest speakers included those from several American universities, Amnesty International, and former Deputy Premier of Malaysia [[Anwar Ibrahim]].

Aside from this many Islamic organizations in the west have taken step forwards to correct certain misconceptions about Islam that have become more prevalent in the post-9/11 world.

== Hate crimes against Muslims ==
* Attack on a Mosque in [[Brisbane]], [[Australia]].  [http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/asia-pacific/1544481.stm] &lt;small&gt;(*)&lt;/small&gt;
* Attack on a Mosque in [[Chicago, Illinois]], [[USA]]. [http://www.cair-net.org/default.asp?Page=articleView&amp;id=137&amp;theType=AA]
* Attack on a Mosque in [[Reading, Berkshire|Reading]], [[England]]. [http://www.muslimnews.co.uk/index/press.php?pr=165]
* The attack on a [[Quincy Mosque|Mosque]] in [[Quincy]], [[Massachusetts]]. [http://www.indianewengland.com/media/paper549/news/2003/08/15/Community/Mosque.Hopes.To.Improve.Security.In.Wake.Of.Arson-449819.shtml] &lt;small&gt;(*)&lt;/small&gt;
* Smearing a [[Qur'an]] with [[feces]] and dumping it in [[Nashville, Tennessee]], [[USA]]. [http://www.tennessean.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20050802/NEWS0202/508020337/1009/NEWS] &lt;small&gt;(*)&lt;/small&gt;
* Attack on a pregnant woman in [[Islam and clothing|Islamic dress]] in [[Arlington County, Virginia]], [[USA]] [http://www.nbc4.com/news/4830091/detail.html] &lt;small&gt;(*)&lt;/small&gt;

&lt;small&gt;(*) These articles do not specifically use the term 'Islamophobia'&lt;/small&gt;

==See also== 

* [[Persecution of Muslims]]
* [[Religious intolerance]]
* [[Islamism]]
* [[Islamist terrorism]]

==References==

# {{note|Seabrook}} [http://www.guardian.co.uk/race/story/0,11374,1267567,00.html Religion as a fig leaf for racism], Jeremy Seabrook, [[The Guardian]], [[23 July]] [[2004]], retrieved [[29 January]] [[2005]] from http://www.guardian.co.uk/race/story/0,11374,1267567,00.html 
# {{note|Rudiger}} [http://www.sant.ox.ac.uk/princeton/pap_rudiger.shtml Discrimination and Legislation - Response of Dr. Anya Rudiger] from Discrimination and Legislation session of Muslims in Europe post 9/11 conference, 2003-04-26, [[St Antony's College, Oxford|St Antony's College]], [[University of Oxford|Oxford]] retrieved 2005-01-29 from http://www.sant.ox.ac.uk/princeton/pap_rudiger.shtml
# {{note|Radman}} [http://eumc.eu.int/eumc/index.php?fuseaction=content.dsp_cat_content&amp;contentid=3e3e8c602f879&amp;catid=3e3e6e32a2316&amp;search=1&amp;frmsearch=Islamophobia&amp;lang=EN Islam and Muslims in Europe], [[Tariq Ramadan]], [http://eumc.eu.int/eumc/index.php?fuseaction=content.dsp_cat_content&amp;catid=3d938674101aa Equal Voices] issue 10, published by [[European Monitoring Centre on Racism and Xenophobia]] (EUMC) verified 2005-01-29 from http://eumc.eu.int/eumc/index.php?fuseaction=content.dsp_cat_content&amp;catid=3e3e6e32a2316&amp;contentid=3e3e8c602f879
# {{note|Malik}} [http://www.sant.ox.ac.uk/princeton/pap_malik.shtml Discrimination and Legislation] from Muslims in Europe post 9/11 conference, 2003-04-26, [[St Antony's College, Oxford|St Antony's College]], [[University of Oxford|Oxford]] retrieved 2005-01-29 from http://www.sant.ox.ac.uk/princeton/pap_malik.shtml
# {{note|Dalrymple}} [http://books.guardian.co.uk/review/story/0,,1172782,00.html Trapped in the ruins], William Dalrymple, [[The Guardian]], 2004-03-20, verified 2005-01-29 from http://books.guardian.co.uk/review/story/0,,1172782,00.html
# {{note|DePaul}} [http://www.thedepaulia.com/story.asp?artid=77&amp;sectid=1 Loop professor takes heat for conduct], The DePaulia, verified [[17 May]] [[2005]] from http://www.thedepaulia.com/story.asp?artid=77&amp;sectid=1
# {{note|Said}} Orientalism, [[Edward Said|Edward W. Said ]], ISBN 0614216303 (1996 edition, Kazi Pubns Inc), quote given is taken from Page 74 of the "2003 Edition", publisher unknown.

==External links==
* [http://www.islamophobia-watch.com/ Islamophobia Watch]
* [http://www.religioustolerance.org/isl_hate.htm Large list of hate-crimes against Muslims]
* [http://www.hrw.org/reports/2002/usahate/ A hate crime report/publication by Human Rights Watch (HRW) in the USA]
* [http://www.cair.com/asp/execsum2005.asp A summary of Islamophobic-related statistics by the Council on American Islamic Relations] 
* [http://www.spiked-online.co.uk/Articles/00000006D95B.htm "Who's afraid of Islamophobia?"] by Josie Appleton, ''Spiked'', July 2, 2002
* [http://www.fairuk.org Forum against Islamophobia and Racism]
* [http://www.trueislaam.free-online.co.uk/ trueislam.com]
* [http://www.mwlusa.org Muslim Women's League]
* [http://www.islamawareness.net/Islamophobia/ "Islamophobia"], ''Islamicawareness.net''
* [http://www.masud.co.uk Masud.co.uk]
* [http://www.masud.co.uk/ISLAM/ahm/right.htm "Muslims and the European Right"] by Abdal-Hakim Murad, ''Masud.co.uk'', first delivered as a lecture on April 30, 2000
* [http://www.islamonline.net/ Islamonline.net]
* [http://www.islamonline.net/English/Views/2003/05/article11.shtml "Deep roots of Islamophobia] by James Brooks, Islamonline.net
* [http://members.tripod.com/~Bregava/phobia/ tripod.com "Eurocentrism and Islamophobia"] by Saeid Reza Ameli, Islamic Centre of England, October 1997
* [http://members.tripod.com/~Bregava/islamophobia-index/ tripod.com Links about Islamophobia], Islamic Human Rights Commission
* [http://www.musalman.com/muslimphobia/ "Muslimphobia Alerts"], Muslaman.com
* [http://www.cair-net.org/ Council on American Islamic Relations]
* [http://www.canadianislamiccongress.com/mc/media_communique.php?mcdate=2003-02-13/ "Canadian Media Are Fuelling Hatred of Islam, Says Cic], Canadian Muslim Congress, February 13, 2003
* [http://www.scholarofthehouse.org/onrebi.html  Scholars of the house-on revising bigotry]
*[http://www.danielpipes.org/article/3075 Islamophobia?] by [[Daniel Pipes]], published in the [[New York Sun]], October 25 2005


[[Category:Moral panics]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Prejudices]]
[[Category:Religious persecution]]
[[Category:Racism]]
[[Category:Phobias]]

[[de:Islamophobie]]
[[fr:Islamophobie]]
[[he:איסלאמופוביה]]
[[sv:Islamofobi]]
[[Category:Moral panics]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Prejudices]]
[[Category:Religious persecution]]
[[Category:Racism]]
[[Category:Phobias]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>