<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20071114081936|171392376" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="162173" pageid="162173" ns="0" title="Islamophobia"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-11-14T13:09:49Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{pov}}

'''Islamophobia''' is a term that refers to [[prejudice]] or [[discrimination]] against [[Islam]] or [[Muslim]]s.&lt;ref&gt;
* Sandra Fredman, ''Discrimination and Human Rights'', Oxford University Press, ISBN 0199246033, p.121.
* Yvonne Yazbeck Haddad, ''Muslims in the West: From Sojourners to Citizens'', Oxford University Press, ISBN 0195148061, p.19
* ''Islamophobia: A Challenge for Us All'', [[Runnymede Trust]], 1997, p. 1, cited in Quraishi, Muzammil. ''Muslims and Crime: A Comparative Study'', Ashgate Publishing Ltd., 2005, p. 60. ISBN 075464233X. Early in 1997, the Commission on [[British Muslims]] and Islamophobia, at that time part of the Runnymede Trust, issued a consultative document on Islamophobia under the chairmanship of Professor Gordon Conway, [[Vice-Chancellor]] of the [[University of Sussex]]. The final report, ''Islamophobia: A Challenge for Us All'', was launched in November 1997 by [[Home Secretary]] [[Jack Straw (politician)|Jack Straw]].
* Edward Kessler, Neil Wenborn, ''A Dictionary of Jewish-Christian Relations'', [[Cambridge University Press]], ISBN 0521826926 p.429.
* Abduljalil Sajid. "Islamophobia: A New Word for an Old Fear" in ''Islamophobia and Antisemitism'', Markus Wiener Publishers, 2006, p. 1: defines the term as "anti-Muslim prejudice."
*Social Inequalities in Comparative Perspective By Mary C. Waters, Fiona Devine, pg. 106
*Muslims in Western Europe By Jørgen S. Nielsen, pg. 169&lt;/ref&gt; The term dates back to the late 1980s,&lt;ref&gt;''Islamophobia: A Challenge for Us All'', [[Runnymede Trust]], 1997, p. 1, cited in Quraishi, Muzammil. ''Muslims and Crime: A Comparative Study'', Ashgate Publishing Ltd., 2005, p. 60; [[Kofi Annan|Annan, Kofi]]. [http://www.un.org/News/Press/docs/2004/sgsm9637.doc.htm "Secretary-General, addressing headquarters seminar on confronting Islamophobia"], [[United Nations]] press release, [[December 7]] [[2004]].&lt;/ref&gt; but came into common usage after the [[September 11, 2001 attacks]].&lt;ref&gt;
* Casciani, Dominic. [http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/3768327.stm "Islamophobia pervades UK - report"], BBC News, [[June 2]] [[2004]].
* Rima Berns McGowan writes in ''Muslims in the Diaspora'' (University of Toronto Press, 1991, p. 268) that the term "Islamophobia" was first used in an unnamed American periodical in 1991.&lt;/ref&gt; 

In 1997, the British [[Runnymede Trust]] defined Islamophobia as the "dread or hatred of Islam and therefore, to the fear and dislike of all Muslims," stating that it also refers to the behavior of excluding Muslims from the "economic, social, and public life of the nation." It includes the perception that Islam has no values in common with other cultures, is inferior to the West, is a violent [[political ideology]] rather than a religion, and that discriminatory practices against Muslims are justified.&lt;ref name=Runnymede5&gt;Runnymede 1997, p. 5, cited in Quraishi 2005, p. 60.&lt;/ref&gt;

Opponents of the concept criticize the concept, allege that it is often misused to undermine legitimate [[criticism of Islam]],&lt;ref name=Malik&gt;Malik, Kenan. [http://www.prospect-magazine.co.uk/article_details.php?id=6679 "Islamophobia Myth"], Prospect, [[February 2005]],&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
* "There really isn't a phenomena like "Islamophobia" - at least no more than there was a "Germanophobia" in hating Hitler or "Russiaphobia" in detesting Stalin." - Historian Victor Davis Hanson, in the ''The Politically Incorrect Guide to Islam (and the Crusades)'' By Robert Spencer, ISBN 0895260131, Regnery Publishing, Pg. 200
* "All this indicates that "Islamophobia" is virtually useless as an analytical tool. To adopt it is to accept the most virulent form of theological equivalence, and to affirm, against all the evidence, that every religious tradition is equally capable of inspiring violence." - The Politically Incorrect Guide to Islam (and the Crusades) By Robert Spencer, ISBN 0895260131, Regnery Publishing, Pg. 199
* "This term is a fabricated and question-begging linguistic manoeuvre designed to present the protection of religious sensibilities as a civil liberty issue." - [http://oliverkamm.typepad.com/blog/2006/10/the_islamophobi.html The "Islamophobia" scam], [[Oliver Kamm]]
* "The pseudo-psychiatric term Islamophobia is a statement that any criticism of Muslims is evidence of clinical pathology. Yet the label is often attached to valid criticisms of particular Muslims whose behaviour has laid them open to legitimate censure." - [[Dave Green (journalist)|David Green]], [http://www.3ammagazine.com/3am/bad-faith-2/ Bad Faith VI]
* "The trouble with the idea is that it confuses hatred of, and discrimination against, Muslims on the one hand with criticism of Islam on the other." [[Kenan Malik|Malik, Kenan.]] [http://www.prospect-magazine.co.uk/article_details.php?id=6679 "Islamophobia Myth"], Prospect, [[February 2005]].
* "... Islamophobia", a wretched concept that confuses criticism of Islam as a religion and stigmatisation of those who believe in it." [[Salman Rushdie|Rushdie, Salman]] ''et al''. [http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/4764730.stm "Writers' statement on cartoons"], BBC News, March 1, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; and call it a "myth".&lt;ref name=Malik/&gt; Novelist [[Salman Rushdie]] and others signed a manifesto entitled [[MANIFESTO: Together facing the new totalitarianism|''Together facing the new totalitarianism'']] in [[March 2006]] calling Islamophobia a "wretched concept that confuses criticism of Islam as a religion and stigmatization of those who believe in it."&lt;ref name=Rushdie&gt;[[Salman Rushdie|Rushdie, Salman]] ''et al''. [http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/4764730.stm "Writers' statement on cartoons"], BBC News, March 1, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;
{{discrimination2|right}}
==Etymology==
The term is formed of ''Islam'', the post-classical Latin ''-o-'' connecting vowel, and the post-classical Latin combining form ''-phobia'' which is used to form nouns with the sense 'irrational fear of' or 'aversion to.' &lt;ref&gt;"Islamophobia". ''Oxford English Dictionary''. Oxford University Press. Draft Entry Sept. 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; See [[List of anti-ethnic and anti-national terms]] for other "-phobia" coinages.

==Definitions==
A number of individuals and organizations have made attempts to define the concept. [[Kofi Annan]] told a UN conference on Islamophobia in 2004: "[W]hen the world is compelled to coin a new term to take account of increasingly widespread [[bigotry]], that is a sad and troubling development. Such is the case with Islamophobia."&lt;ref name=Annan&gt;[[Kofi Annan|Annan, Kofi]]. [http://www.un.org/News/Press/docs/2004/sgsm9637.doc.htm "Secretary-General, addressing headquarters seminar on confronting Islamophobia"], [[United Nations]] press release, December 7, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1996, the [[Runnymede Trust]] established the Commission on British Muslims and Islamophobia, chaired by Professor Gordon Conway, the vice-chancellor of the [[University of Sussex]]. Their report, Islamophobia: A Challenge for Us All, was launched in November 1997 by the Home Secretary, [[Jack Straw]]. In this report, Islamophobia was defined by the Trust as "an outlook or world-view involving an unfounded dread and dislike of Muslims, which results in practices of exclusion and discrimination."&lt;ref name="EoRE215"&gt;Encyclopedia of Race and Ethics, p. 215&lt;/ref&gt; An early documented use of the word in the [[United States]]  was by [[Insight (magazine)|Insight magazine]] in 1991, used to describe [[Russia]]n activities in [[Afghanistan]].&lt;ref name="EoRE215"/&gt;

The American writer [[Stephen Schwartz (journalist)|Stephen Schwartz]] has defined Islamophobia as the condemnation of the entirety of [[Islam]] and its history as [[Extremism|extremist]]; "denying" the existence of a moderate Muslim majority; regarding Islam as a problem for the world; treating conflicts involving Muslims as necessarily their own fault; insisting that Muslims make changes to their religion; and inciting war against Islam as a whole.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.frontpagemag.com/Articles/ReadArticle.asp?ID=17874 "The 'Islamophobes' That Aren't"], ''FrontPage Magazine'', [[April 28]] [[2005]].&lt;/ref&gt;

In ''Journal of Sociology'', Vol. 43, No. 1, 61-86 (2007) islamophobia is defined as anti-Muslim racism and a continuation of anti-Asian and anti-Arab racism.&lt;ref&gt;''Journal of Sociology'', Vol. 43, No. 1, 61-86 (2007)[http://jos.sagepub.com/cgi/content/abstract/43/1/61]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Perceptions==

The Runnymede report identified eight perceptions related to Islamophobia:

:#Islam is seen as a [[monolith]]ic bloc, static and unresponsive to change.
:#It is seen as separate and "other." It does not have values in common with other cultures, is not affected by them and does not influence them.
:#It is seen as inferior to the West. It is seen as barbaric, irrational, primitive, and [[sexist]].
:#It is seen as violent, aggressive, threatening, supportive of [[terrorism]], and engaged in a [[clash of civilizations]].
:#It is seen as a political [[ideology]], used for political or military advantage.
:#Criticisms made of "the West" by Muslims are rejected out of hand.
:#Hostility towards Islam is used to justify discriminatory practices towards Muslims and exclusion of Muslims from mainstream society.
:#Anti-Muslim hostility is seen as natural and normal.&lt;ref name=Runnymede1997&gt;{{PDFlink|[http://www.runnymedetrust.org/uploads/publications/pdfs/islamophobia.pdf "Islamophobia: A Challenge for Us All"]|69.7&amp;nbsp;[[Kibibyte|KiB]]&lt;!-- application/pdf, 71377 bytes --&gt;}}, ''Runnymede Trust'', 1997.&lt;/ref&gt;

The above perceptions are seen as closed views on Islam. These are contrasted, in the report, with open views on Islam which, while founded on respect for Islam, permits legitimate disagreement, dialogue and critique.&lt;ref&gt;Benn; Jawad (2004) p. 162&lt;/ref&gt; According to Benn and Jawad, The Runnymede Trust notes that anti-Muslim discourse is increasingly seen as respectable, providing examples on how hostility towards Islam and Muslims is accepted as normal, even among those who may actively challenge other prevelant forms of discrimination.&lt;ref name="Brill165"&gt;Benn; Jawad (2004) p. 165&lt;/ref&gt;

In some societies, Islamophobia has materialized due to the portrayal of Islam and Muslims as the national "[[Other]]", where exclusion and discrimination occurs on the basis of their religion and civilization which differs with national tradition and identity. Examples include Pakistani and Algerian migrants in Britain and France respectively.&lt;ref&gt;See:
*Encyclopedia of Race and Ethnic studies, p. 216
*Miles; Brown (2003) p. 163&lt;/ref&gt; This sentiment, according to Malcolm Brown and  Robert Miles, significantly interacts with [[racism]], although Islamophobia itself is not racism.&lt;ref&gt;Miles; Brown (2003) p. 163, 164&lt;/ref&gt; The publication "''Social Work and Minorities: European Perspectives''" describes Islamophobia as the new form of racism in Europe,&lt;ref&gt;Johnson; Soydan; Williams (1998) p. 182&lt;/ref&gt; arguing that "Islamophobia is as much a form of racism as [[Anti-Semitism]], a term more commonly encountered in Europe as a sibling of Racism, Xenophobia and Intolerance."&lt;ref&gt;Johnson; Soydan; Williams (1998) p. xxii&lt;/ref&gt;

Another feature of Islamophobic discourse is to amalgamate nationality (i.e. Arab), religion (Islam), and politics (terrorism, fundamentalism) — while most other religions are not associated with terrorism, or even "ethnic or national distinctiveness."&lt;ref&gt;Miles; Brown (2003) p. 163&lt;/ref&gt; Brown and Miles write that "many of the stereotypes and misinformation that contribute to the articulation of Islamophobia are rooted in a particular perception of Islam", such as the notion that Islam promotes terrorism; especially prevalent after the [[September 11, 2001 attacks]].&lt;ref&gt;Miles; Brown (2003) p. 166&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Media ===
According to Elizabeth Poole in the  ''Encyclopedia of Race and Ethnic studies'', the media has been criticized for perpetrating Islamophobia. She cites a case study examining a sample of articles in the British press from between 1994 and 2004, which concluded that Muslim viewpoints were underrepresented and that issues involving Muslims usually depicted them in a negative light. Such portrayals, according to Poole, include the depiction of Islam and Muslims as a threat to Western security and values.&lt;ref&gt;Encyclopedia of Race and Ethnic studies, p. 217&lt;/ref&gt; Benn and Jawad write that hostility towards Islam and Muslims are "closely linked to media portrayals of Islam as barbaric, irrational, primitive and sexist."&lt;ref name="Brill165"/&gt; Egorova and Tudor cite European researchers in suggesting that expressions used in the media such as "Islamic terrorism", "Islamic bombs" and "violent Islam" have resulted in a negative perception of Islam.&lt;ref&gt;See Egorova; Tudor (2003) pp. 2-3, which cites the conclusions of Marquina and Rebolledo in: "A. Marquina, V. G. Rebolledo, ‘The Dialogue between the European Union and the Islamic World’ in Interreligious Dialogues: Christians, Jews, Muslims, Annals of the European Academy of Sciences and Arts, v. 24, no. 10, Austria, 2000, pp. 166-8. "&lt;/ref&gt;

There have been several initiatives, based upon the sixty recommendations listed in the Runnymede Trust's report, aimed at increase Muslim participation in media and politics. Soon after the release of the Runnymede report, the [[Muslim Council of Britain]] was formed to serve as an umbrella body aiming to "represent Muslims in the public sphere, to lobby government and other institutions." The "Forum against Islamophobia and Racism" (FAIR ) was also established, designed to monitor coverage in the media and establish dialogue with media organizations. Following the attacks of September 11, the [[Islam Awareness Week]] and the "''Best of British Islam Festival''" were introduced to improve community relations and raise awareness about Islam.&lt;ref&gt;Encyclopedia of Race and Ethnic studies, p. 218&lt;/ref&gt;

==Trends==
Islamophobia has become a topic of increasing sociological and political importance.&lt;ref&gt;Miles; Brown (2003) p. 163&lt;/ref&gt; According to Benn and Jawad, Islamophobia has increased since British Muslims' denouncement of [[Salman Rushdie]]'s "''[[The Satanic Verses]]''" and the September 11 attacks.&lt;ref&gt;Benn; Jawad (2004) p. 111&lt;/ref&gt; [[Anthropologist]] Steven Vertovec writes that the purported growth in Islamophobia may be associated with increased Muslim presence in society and successes.&lt;ref name="Vertovec"&gt;Steven Vertovec, "Islamophobia and Muslim Recognition in Britain"; in Haddad (2002) pp. 32-33&lt;/ref&gt; He suggests a [[Vicious circle|circular model]], where increased hostility towards Islam and Muslims results in governmental countermeasures such as institutional guidelines and changes to legislation, which itself may fuel further Islamophobia due to increased accommodation for Muslims in public life. Vertovec concludes: "As the public sphere shifts to provide a more prominent place for Muslims, Islamophobic tendencies may amplify."&lt;ref name="Vertovec" /&gt;

Patel, Humphries, and Naik claim that "Islamophobia has always been present in Western countries and cultures. In the last two decades, it has become accentuated, explicit and extreme."&lt;ref&gt; Naina Patel, Beth Humphries and Don Naik, "The 3 Rs in social work; Religion,‘race’ and racism in Europe", in Johnson; Soydan; Williams (1998) pp. 197-198&lt;/ref&gt; However, Vertovec states that some have observed that Islamophobia has not necessarily escalated in the past decades, but that there has been increased public scrutiny of it.&lt;ref name="Vertovec" /&gt; According to Abduljalil Sajid, one of the members of the Runnymede Trust's Commission on British Muslims and Islamophobia, "Islamophobias" have existed in varying strains throughout history, with each version possessing its own distinct features as well as similarities or adaptations from others.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Islamophobia: A new word for an old fear | url =http://www.wcrp.be/articles/Sajid9-11-04.htm | author=Imam Dr Abduljalil Sajid | accessdate=2007-08-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite being a sizeable minority, many [[Muslims in India]] tend to complain about substantial discrimination by [[Hindus]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.keralanext.com/news/?id=1078945 Grant Bangladeshi Hindu migrants refugee status, but deport Bangladeshi Muslims: Rajnath Singh]&lt;/ref&gt; According to a recently published report to government, called the Sachar Report, Muslims are heavily under-represented in different government and social areas.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.milligazette.com/dailyupdate/2006/200612141_Sachar_Report_Status_Indian_Muslims.htm Summarised Sachar Report on Status of Indian Muslims]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.indianexpress.com/story/19623.html Sachar report to be implemented in full]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.indianexpress.com/sunday/fullcoverage/53.html The Missing Muslim], ''the Sunday Express. Full coverage on Sachar Report''&lt;/ref&gt; Among other facts, it found that in the province of [[West Bengal]], where Muslims make up 27% of the population, their employment in the government sector was below 3%.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thestar.com/News/World/article/246411 Fearful Muslims adopt Hindu IDs], ''The Toronto Star, August 15, 2007''&lt;/ref&gt; 

===EUMC report===
The largest project monitoring Islamophobia was undertaken following 9/11 by the EU watchdog, [[European Monitoring Centre on Racism and Xenophobia]] (EUMC). Their May 2002 report "Summary report on Islamophobia in the EU after 11 September 2001", written [[Chris Allen (UK)]] and Jorgen S. Nielsen of the [[University of Birmingham]], was based on 75 reports &amp;mdash; 15 from each EU member nation.&lt;ref name="EUMCNews"&gt;{{cite news| title ="EUMC presents reports on Discrimination and Islamophobia in the EU" | publisher="European Monitoring Centre on Racism and Xenophobia media release" | url=http://www.eumc.europa.eu/eumc/index.php?fuseaction=content.dsp_cat_content&amp;catid=43d8bc25bc89d&amp;contentid=4582ddc822d41 | date=2006-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=EUMC&gt;Allen, Chris and Nielsen, Jorgen S. [http://www.raxen.eumc.eu.int/1/webmill.php?id=32813&amp;ditem=3101&amp;lin=detail "Summary report on Islamophobia in the EU after 11 September 2001"], EUMC, May, 2002.&lt;/ref&gt; The report highlighted the regularity with which ordinary Muslims became targets for abusive and sometimes violent retaliatory attacks after 9/11. Despite localized differences within each member nation, the recurrence of attacks on recognizable and visible traits of Islam and Muslims was the report's most significant finding. Incidents consisted of verbal abuse, blaming all Muslims for [[List of terrorist incidents|terrorism]], forcibly removing women's [[hijab]]s, spitting on Muslims, calling children "[[Osama bin Laden|Usama]]," and random assaults. Muslims have been hospitalized and on one occasion paralyzed.&lt;ref name=EUMC/&gt;

The report also discussed the portrayal of Muslims in the media. Inherent negativity, stereotypical images, fantastical representations, and exaggerated caricatures were all identified. The report concluded that "a greater receptivity towards anti-Muslim and other xenophobic ideas and sentiments has, and may well continue, to become more tolerated."&lt;ref name=EUMC/&gt;

==Views==
[[Image:Salman Rushdie by Kubik 01.JPG|left|thumb|170px|[[Salman Rushdie]] was one of 12 prominent writers who signed a statement condemning Islamophobia as a "wretched concept."&lt;ref name=Rushdie/&gt;]]
The concept of Islamophobia has been criticized on several grounds. Some critics argue that it is real, but is just another form of racism and does not require its own category, while others argue that, unlike racism, Islam is a religion that people can choose to adopt, to retain or to leave or [[apostatize]]. Others argue that it is used to censor criticism and that its use threatens [[free speech]].

British writer and academic [[Kenan Malik]] has called the concept a "myth," arguing that it confuses discrimination against Muslims with criticism of Islam, and that it is used to silence critics and Muslim reformers. He writes that the extent to which Muslims are more vulnerable to social exclusion and attacks than other groups is exaggerated, and that the concept allows politicians who may have supported the [[2003 invasion of Iraq]] or the [[War on Terror]] to "reclaim the moral high ground" and "pitch for the Muslim vote." He argues that the result is the creation of a culture of victimhood, allowing individual Muslims to attribute low achievement to Islamophobia, and not to themselves. Islamophobia is not a form of racism, in his view, because Islam is a belief system. "I can be hateful about other beliefs, such as [[conservatism]] or [[communism]]. So why can't I be hateful about religion too?"&lt;ref name=Malik&gt;Malik, Kenan.[http://www.prospect-magazine.co.uk/article_details.php?id=6679 "Islamophobia Myth"], Prospect, February 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;

Malik's analysis of Islamophobia was criticized by [[Inayat Bunglawala]] from the [[Muslim Council of Britain]] and Abdul Wahid from the [[Islamism|Islamist]] group [[Hizb ut-Tahrir]].&lt;ref name=Bunglawala&gt;Bunglawala, Inayat &amp; Wahid, Abdul. [http://www.prospect-magazine.co.uk/pdfarticle.php?id=6764 "Is Islamophobia a Myth?"], ''Prospect Magazine'', March 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; Bunglawala writes that Malik's argument is limited to overt acts of violence against Muslims. As an example of less overt prejudice, Bunglawala cites a BBC study that found applicants for jobs who had English-sounding names were more likely to secure an interview than those with Muslim names. By ignoring non-violent examples of alleged Islamophobia, Malik's commentary "makes a mockery of victims of prejudice by pretending they have not been discriminated against," according to Bunglawala. In addition, he argues that Malik did not adequately study the proposed law against the incitement of religious hatred, and that he failed to appreciate the definitions of the term "Islamophobia" according to the very sources he uses in his article.&lt;ref name=Bunglawala/&gt;

In the wake of the [[Jyllands-Posten Muhammad cartoons controversy]], a group of 12 prominent writers signed a statement in the French weekly satirical newspaper ''[[Charlie Hebdo]]'' in March 2006, warning against the use of the term Islamophobia to prevent criticism of "[[Islamic totalitarianism]]." The novelist [[Salman Rushdie]] was among these signatories. The statement alleged that "Islamism is a reactionary ideology that kills equality, freedom and [[secularism]] wherever it is present. We refuse to renounce our critical spirit out of fear of being accused of "Islamophobia", a wretched concept that confuses criticism of Islam as a religion and stigmatization of those who believe in it."&lt;ref name=Rushdie&gt;[[Salman Rushdie|Rushdie, Salman]] ''et al''. [http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/4764730.stm "Writers' statement on cartoons"], BBC News, March 1, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

British columnist Josie Appleton argues Runnymede Trust uses the term Islamophobia to prevent [[criticism of Islam]]. "Rather than engage Muslims in debate, non-Muslims are supposed to tiptoe around them, for fear of causing offense."&lt;ref name=Appleton&gt;Appleton, Josie. [http://www.spiked-online.co.uk/Articles/00000006D95B.htm "Who's afraid of Islamophobia"], ''Spiked Online'', [[July 2]] [[2004]].&lt;/ref&gt; [[Afshin Ellian]], a Dutch [[law professor]], writes that the concept is used to delegitimize criticism by characterizing it as [[Psychopathology|pathological]]&lt;ref name="Ellian"&gt;[[Afshin Ellian|Ellian, Afshin]]. [http://kvc.minbuza.nl/uk/current/2006/february/ellian.html "Stop Capitulating to Threats"], [[February 2006]]&lt;/ref&gt; while [[Civil rights|civil-rights]] activist [[Bahram Soroush]] has called it "intellectual blackmail".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.maryamnamazie.com/tv/islamophobia_term_scaremongering.html "The term Islamophobia is being used for scaremongering"] - International TV interview with Bahram Soroush, [[June 7]] [[2004]].&lt;/ref&gt; French writer [[Robert Redeker]] argues that the history of the term demonstrates that the term Islamophobia was created by "radical islamists" to "tackle feminists".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.robertredeker.net/mondecontemporain_lalaicite,l_islamophobie.htm]" L'islamophobie, l'arme des islamistes contre la laïcité."&lt;/ref&gt;

"Whoever coined the term 'Islamophobia' was quite shrewd," chimes in [[Dennis Prager]]. "Notice the intellectual sleight of hand here. … One can rightly or wrongly fear Islam, or more usually, aspects of Islam, and have absolutely no bias against all Muslims, let alone be a racist. The equation of Islamophobia with racism is particularly dishonest. Muslims come in every racial group, and Islam has nothing to do with race. … Even granting that there are people who fear Islam, how does that in any way correlate with racism? If fear of an ideology rendered one racist, all those who fear [[conservatism]] or [[liberalism]] should be considered racist. … However, the only religion the West permits criticism of is [[Christianity]]. People write books, give lectures and conduct seminars on the falsity of Christian claims, or on the immoral record of Christianity, and no one attacks them for racism or bigotry, let alone attacks them physically. … The fact remains that the term 'Islamophobia' has one purpose — to suppress any criticism, legitimate or not, of Islam."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.townhall.com/columnists/DennisPrager/2007/07/31/why_islamophobia_is_a_brilliant_term Why "Islamophobia" Is a Brilliant Term] by [[Dennis Prager]], [[July 31]], [[2007]]&lt;/ref&gt; Prager had himself been accused of Islamophobia after he compared the Muslim sacred text, the [[Qur'an]], with Adolf [[Hitler]]s [[Mein Kampf]] and when he suggested that [[US Congress]]man [[Keith Ellison (politician)|Keith Ellison]]'s decision to take his oath of office on [[Thomas Jefferson]]'s Qur'an "undermines American civilization".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.worldnetdaily.com/news/article.asp?ARTICLE_ID=53235 A response to my critics – and a solution] - Dennis Prager - [[December 5]], [[2006]]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://blogs.usatoday.com/ondeadline/2006/12/quran_controver_1.html Quran controversy continues: Prager catching flak] - [[USA Today]] Blog - [[December 04]], [[2006]]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Johann Hari]] of ''[[The Independent]]'' has criticized the use of the term by organizations like [[Islamophobia Watch]], arguing that [[Liberal movements within Islam|liberal Muslims]] interested in reform are left unsupported because people fear being accused of Islamophobia. He writes: "If Muslim women and Muslim [[gay]]s are going to have any kind of decent life, the [Muslim] liberals need to receive solidarity and support – but slap-dash charges of Islamophobia intimidate people who could offer it ... While Islamophobia Watch talk about defending Muslims, they end up defending the nastiest and most right-wing part of the [[Ummah|Muslim community]] – the ones who are oppressing and killing the rest."&lt;ref name=Hari&gt;Hari, Johann. [http://www.johannhari.com/archive/article.php?id=897 "Don't call me an Islamophobe"], June 6, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

Critics have cited the case of British journalist [[Polly Toynbee]], who was nominated in May 2003 for the title of "Most Islamophobic Media Personality of the Year" at the [[Annual Islamophobia Awards]] overseen by the [[Islamic Human Rights Commission]], who has argued that there is no such thing as Islamophobia.&lt;ref name=Toynbee&gt;[[Polly Toynbee|Toynbee, Polly]]. [http://www.guardian.co.uk/Archive/Article/0,4273,4266035,00.html "Behind the burka"], ''The Guardian'', September 28, 2001.&lt;/ref&gt; The nomination was based on her comments in ''The Guardian'' that "[w]herever Islam either is the government or bears down upon the government, it imposes harsh regimes that deny the most [[Human rights|basic human rights]]."&lt;ref name=Toynbee&gt;Toynbee, Polly. [http://www.guardian.co.uk/Columnists/Column/0,,563618,00.html "Last chance to speak out"], ''The Guardian'', October 5, 2001.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Islamophobia-phobia====
Writing in the [[New Humanist]], philosopher [[Piers Benn]] suggests that people who fear the rise of Islamophobia foster an environment "not intellectually or morally healthy", to the point that what he calls "Islamophobia-phobia" can undermine "critical scrutiny of Islam as somehow impolite, or ignorant of the religion's true nature", encouraging "sentimental pretence that all claims to religious truth are somehow 'equal', or that critical scrutiny of Islam (or any belief system) is ignorant, prejudiced, or 'phobic'".&lt;ref name=Benn&gt;[http://newhumanist.org.uk/524 "On Islamophobia-phobia"].&lt;/ref&gt;

''[[The New Criterion]]'' editor [[Roger Kimball]] argues that the word "Islamophobia" is a misnomer. "A phobia describes an [[Phobia|irrational fear]], and it is axiomatic that fearing the effects of radical Islam is not irrational, but on the contrary very well-founded indeed, so that if you want to speak of a legitimate phobia — it’s a phobia I experience frequently — we should speak instead of Islamophobia-phobia, the fear of and revulsion towards Islamophobia."&lt;ref name=Kimball&gt;Kimball, Roger. [http://web.archive.org/web/20060103053941/http://www.newcriterion.com/archives/24/01/after-the-suicide/ "After the suicide of the West"], January 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

American writer [[Stephen Schwartz (journalist)|Stephen Schwartz]], director of the Center for Islamic Pluralism, has cautioned against what he sees as a tendency to accuse all opponents of Islamic radicalism of Islamophobia, but writes that it is nevertheless a real phenomenon. He defines it as the condemnation of the entirety of [[Islam]] and its history as [[Extremism|extremist]]; denying the existence of a moderate Muslim majority; regarding Islam as a problem for the world; treating conflicts involving Muslims as necessarily their own fault; insisting that Muslims make changes to their religion; and inciting war against Islam as a whole.&lt;ref name=Schwartz&gt;[[Stephen Schwartz (journalist)|Schwartz, Stephen]]. [http://www.frontpagemag.com/Articles/ReadArticle.asp?ID=17874 "The 'Islamophobes' That Aren't"], ''FrontPage Magazine'', April 28, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;

Turkish writer Ali Bulaç says, We should draw a line between the concept of “Islamophobia” as reflected in Europe and in the United States. (...) The difference of views and perceptions between Europe and the United States regarding the Muslim world and the Islamophobia that breaks out in Western countries is an issue for which Muslims and their opinions should be taken into consideration.&lt;ref name=Bulac&gt;Bulac, Ali [http://www.maviye.com/comments.asp?id=94 Two versions of phobia], ''Zaman (newspaper)'', September 27, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Public discourse==
===Efforts against perceived Islamophobia===
There have been efforts against alleged Islamophobia by many organizations in many countries; some of these are detailed below.
* In 2006 the [[Organization of the Islamic Conference]] (OIC) set up an observatory on Islamophobia which will monitor and document activities perceived as Islamophobic around the world.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.islamonline.com/cgi-bin/news_service/world_full_story.asp?service_id=2398 "OIC set up observatory on Islamophobia"] ''IslamOnline'', May 9, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;
* A [[Talk radio|radio talk show]] host from 630 [[WMAL]] on November 26, 2006 allegedly exposed the prevalence of Islamophobia by seeming to advocate a government program to force all Muslims to wear "identifying markers."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=In U.S., fear and distrust of Muslims runs deep | author=Bernd Debusmann | publisher=Reuters|date=Dec 1, 9:05|url=http://www.asiamedia.ucla.edu/article.asp?parentid=58909}} Retrieved on Dec. 16, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; The hoax was revealed at the end of the program. See [[Jerry Klein’s 2006 Islamophobia Radio Experiment]] for more details.
* During the accession talks regarding Turkeys possible entry to the EU, then [[Prime Minister of Holland]], [[Jan Peter Balkenende]], said Islamophobia must not affect the possibility of Turkey's entry to the [[European Union]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/3913335.stm Islam 'must not cloud Turkey bid'] BBC -Wednesday, 21 July, 2004&lt;/ref&gt;
* 50,000 people signed a petition urging [[French President]] [[Jacques Chirac]] to "consider Islamophobia as a new form of racism, punishable by law. The statement reads that the publishing of insulting cartoons of [[Muhammad]] by the French press hurt and offended the feelings of French- Muslims."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.adnki.com/index_2Level_English.php?cat=Religion&amp;loid=8.0.306056413&amp;par= FRANCE: 50,000 SIGN UP AGAINST ISLAMOPHOBIA] - ADN Kronos - June 2, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;
* In [[London Borough of Tower Hamlets|Tower Hamlets]], a densely populated area in [[London]] with a large Muslim community, a crime reporting scheme called "Islamophobia - Don't Suffer in Silence" has been set up which police hope will raise awareness of Islamophobia and help them to understand the extent of the alleged problem.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/england/london/4017617.stm Scheme to fight faith hate crimes] BBC - Wednesday, 17 November, 2004&lt;/ref&gt;
* The British [[National Union of Teachers]] (NUT) has issued guidance to teachers in the union advising that teachers have to "Challenge Islamophobia", and that they have a "crucial role" to play in helping to "dispel myths about Muslim communities."&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/education/4687417.stm Teaching tolerance amid tension] BBC - Friday, 15 July, 2005&lt;/ref&gt;
* Following an Islamist demonstration outside the Danish Embassy in London organized by the [[Al Ghurabaa]] organization in response to the [[Jyllands-Posten Muhammad cartoons controversy]], the [[Muslim Association of Britain]] organized a peaceful rally in [[Trafalgar Square]]. Organizers made available placards and [[T-shirt]]s bearing the rally's official slogan, the phrase, "United against Islamophobia, united against incitement."&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/help/3681938.stm Prayer mats lined the pavements] BBC - Saturday, 11 February 2006&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/cartoonprotests/story/0,,1708080,00.html Muslims fly flag for peaceful protest against cartoons] The Guardian - Sunday February 12, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;
* Following the [[July 7 bombings]], the British government set up a number of initiatives aimed at combating alleged Islamophobia, including the "National Forum against extremism and Islamophobia".&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/4423668.stm Call for Muslim scholars to tour] BBC - Thursday, 10 November 2005&lt;/ref&gt; There was also plans by the British government to ban incitement to "religious hatred", however, this failed to get through the [[British House of Commons|House of Commons]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/programmes/bbc_parliament/4652669.stm Racial and Religious Hatred Bill] BBC - Friday, 27 January 2006&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/politics/4668266.stm Religious hatred: How MPs voted] BBC - Wednesday, 1 February 2006&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[The Hashemite Kingdom of Jordan]] issued a call in 1999 to world leaders to combat Islamophobia.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/453060.stm Jordan: Stop attacking Islam] BBC - Tuesday, September 21, 1999&lt;/ref&gt; Abdel-Elah Khatib, the Jordanian [[foreign minister]] said "The [[international community]] must consider how to confront this phenomenon of Islamophobia in order to prevent its proliferation".
* The [[Muslim Council of Britain]] ([[MCB]]) and the [[Trades Union Congress]] ([[TUC]]) held a seminar on how to combat Islamophobia.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.kuna.net.kw/Home/Story.aspx?Language=en&amp;DSNO=970534 Kuwait News Agency: Drive to combat Islamophobia]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Acts considered Islamophobia===
[[Image:Gathering of eagles.jpg|right|thumb|A protester at a counter-demonstration against the [[September 15, 2007 anti-war protest]] in Washington, D.C.]]
* Dr Amanda Wise and Ghali Hassan from GlobalResearch.ca have alleged that the [[2005 Cronulla riots]] were the result of a climate of "Islamophobia" in Australia.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.abc.net.au/ra/news/viewpoints/s1535149_to.htm Racial unrest offers opportunity for discussion], ''Australian Broadcasting Corporation'', December 20, 2005&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.globalresearch.ca/index.php?context=viewArticle&amp;code=HAS20051214&amp;articleId=1485 The Rise of Islamophobia in ‘White Australia’], ''Global Research'', December 14, 2005&lt;/ref&gt;
* Dalil Boubakeur, a director of a Paris mosque described the [[vandalism]] on a Mosque in [[Paris]], [[France]] as Islamophobic.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/france/story/0,,1419719,00.html Vandals target Paris mosque] The Guardian - Tuesday February 22, 2005&lt;/ref&gt;
* Giles Tremlett of ''[[The Guardian]]'' referred to the burning of a Muslim Sanctuary in the Spanish city of [[Ceuta]], as an instance of Islamophobia.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/international/story/0,,1755600,00.html Burning of sanctuary stokes fears of Islamophobia in Spain], ''The Guardian'', April 18, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;
* Halima Mautbur, from the [[Canadian Council on American-Islamic Relations]] called an attack on a [[hijab]]i Muslim woman "an Islamophobic incident".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.news.utoronto.ca/inthenews/archive/2006_03_16.html Muslim groups want action from U of T], ''University of Toronto News'', March 16, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Doudou Diène]] in a report prepared by the [[UN Commission on Human Rights]] released on March 7, 2006 mentioned the publishing of the cartoons at the heart of the [[Jyllands-Posten Muhammad cartoons controversy]] regarding, "The development of Islamophobia or any racism and racial discrimination ..."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.un.org/apps/news/story.asp?NewsID=17718&amp;Cr=racis&amp;Cr1 Racism and racial discrimination on rise around the world, UN expert warns], ''UN NEWS CENTRE'', March 7, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;
* On March 8, 2006 the [[Islamic Human Rights Commission]] made a press release entitled, "Islamophobia in Prisons stretches far beyond Belmarsh" concerning prisons in Britain.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ihrc.org.uk/show.php?id=1746 Islamophobia in Prisons stretches far beyond Belmarsh], ''Islamic Human Rights Commission'', March 8, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;
* Destruction and vandalism of Muslim graves in France were seen as Islamophobic by a report of the European Monitoring Centre on Racism and Xenophobia.&lt;ref&gt;[http://archives.cnn.com/2002/WORLD/europe/05/24/eu.violence/index.html EU reports post-Sept. 11 racism] CNN - May 24, 2002&lt;/ref&gt;
* Vandalism of Muslim Graves in Charlton cemetery in Plumstead, London.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mcb.org.uk/media/presstext.php?ann_id=76 Appalling Desecration of Muslim Graves in Plumstead] Mulsim Council of Britain - 19 Mar 2004 &lt;/ref&gt;
* Muslim protesters alleged that the [[2 June 2006 London terror raid|Forest Gate anti terror raid]] in London was Islamophobic.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mabonline.info/english/modules.php?name=News&amp;file=article&amp;sid=706 MAB Horrified at Forest Gate Security Blunder], ''The Muslim Association of Britain'', June 7, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;
* In Germany, the state of [[Baden-Württemberg]] has proposed regulations that require citizenship applicants from the member states of the [[Organization of the Islamic Conference]] to answer questions about their attitudes on [[homosexuality]], [[domestic violence]] and other religious issues.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.muslimnews.co.uk/paper/index.php?article=2296 ‘German loyalty tests are Islamophobic’] - The Muslim News - Friday 27 January 2006&lt;/ref&gt;
* A BBC survey taken in the summer of 2004 found that employment applicants with [[Arabic name|Muslim names]] were far less likely to be called for an interview than applicants whose names did not appear to be Muslim. This study was taken by using fictitious applications to jobs using candidate descriptions that were similar in qualification and education, but under different names. The survey found that while a quarter of 'nonmuslim applicants' were invited to an interview, only 9% of the applications with Muslim names were responded to with invitations.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/pressoffice/pressreleases/stories/2004/07_july/12/minorities_survey.shtml Five Live survey suggests ethnic minority applicants still discriminated against in UK job market] - [[BBC News]] [[Press Office]]. [[July 12]], [[2004]].&lt;/ref&gt; Groups, such as the [[Muslim Council of Britain]] have cited this as further evidence for the widespread existence of Islamophobia.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.prospect-magazine.co.uk/article_details.php?id=6764 Is Islamophobia a myth?] - [[Prospect (magazine)]]. [[January 2005]].&lt;/ref&gt;
* In 2005, ''The Guardian'' commissioned an [[ICM (polling)|ICM]] poll which indicated an increase in Islamophobic incidents, particularly after the [[7/7|London bombings]] in July 2005.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/attackonlondon/story/0,,1536222,00.html Two-thirds of Muslims consider leaving UK] The Guardian - Tuesday July 26, 2005&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://image.guardian.co.uk/sys-files/Politics/documents/2005/07/26/Muslim-Poll.pdf ICM-Guardian poll] Poll of Muslims in the UK. The Guardian - Tuesday July 26, 2005&lt;/ref&gt; Another survey of Muslims, this by the [[Open Society Institute]], found that of those polled 32% believed they had suffered religious discrimination at airports, and 80% said they had experienced Islamophobia.&lt;ref&gt;[http://islamonline.net/English/News/2004-11/22/article06.shtml Spiraling Islamophobia Alienating British Muslims: Report] [[Islamonline.net|Islam Online]] - Nov 22 2004&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/islam/story/0,,1362423,00.html ... And why we urgently need new answers] Sarfraz Manzoor - The Guardian - November 30, 2004&lt;/ref&gt;
* France, which has a strong secular tradition [[Separation of church and state|separating church from State]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://yaleglobal.yale.edu/display.article?id=3013 France to Ban Pupils' Religious Dress], ''YaleGlobal'', December 12, 2003&lt;/ref&gt; was accused of Islamophobia when the [[French law on secularity and conspicuous religious symbols in schools|law on secularity and conspicuous religious symbols in schools]] was passed, which bans the wearing of conspicuous [[Religious symbolism|religious symbols]] in public schools. The policy extends to Muslim headscarves, large Christian crosses, Jewish skullcaps, and other visible signs of religion, although the display of small&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.assemblee-nationale.fr/12/rapports/r1381.asp http://www.assemblee-nationale.fr/12/rapports/r1381.asp] ''Assemblee.nationale.fr'' Retrieved on 05-24-07 &lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/religion/news/indepth/france/ http://www.bbc.co.uk/religion/news/indepth/france/] ''BBC.co.uk'' Retrieved on 05-24-07 &lt;/ref&gt; religious symbols (such as the [[Star of David]], [[cross]]es, and [[Hand of Fatima]]s) is permitted.
* In a [[February 10, 2004]] report by [[Al Jazeera]] the head of the Party of France's Muslims, [[Muhammad Latreche]] in discussing the [[French law on secularity and conspicuous religious symbols in schools]] was quoted as saying that the legislation would, "institutionalise Islamophobia".&lt;ref&gt;[http://english.aljazeera.net/NR/exeres/6C6049B0-28A1-4093-9FDA-83DEF32D9793.htm French parliament approves hijab ban], ''Al Jazeera'', February 10, 2004&lt;/ref&gt;
* In January 2006 the Dutch parliament voted in favor of a proposal to ban the [[burqa]] in public, leading to accusations of Islamophobia.&lt;ref name="Mardell"&gt;Madell, Mark. [http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/4616664.stm "Dutch MPs to decide on burqa ban"], BBC News, January 16, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Filip Dewinter]], the leader of [[Vlaams Belang]] bloc has said his party is "Islamophobic." He said: "Yes, we are afraid of Islam. The Islamisation of Europe is a frightening thing."&lt;ref&gt;[http://flemishrepublic.org/current_issue.php?id=50 "Belgian Establishment Fears Crack-Up"], The Flemish Republic.org newsletter, April-June 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;
* An [[Arab]] teenage is driven to suicide because of bullying. He failed at the sucide attempt. He plans on living a better life.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.reuters.com/article/domesticNews/idUSN0639402720070608?src=060807_1744_ARTICLE_PROMO_also_on_reuters "New York is hell for young Osama"], Reuters, June 8 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;
* After [[Salman Rushdie]] was awarded a [[Knighthood of Salman Rushdie|knighthood]] in the [[Queen's Birthday Honours]] in June 2007, the [[Iran]]ian [[Foreign Ministry]] qualified the honoring of "a hated [[apostate]]" as Islamophobic.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www2.irna.com/en/news/view/line-203/0706177335144730.htm | title = British knighthood for Rushdie, clear sign of Islamophobia | accessdate = 2007-06-17 | publisher = Iranian Foreign Ministry / [[IRNA]] }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*On the [[26 August]] [[2007]] fans of the English football club [[Newcastle United]] alledgedly directed Islamophobic chants at Egyptian [[Middlesbrough F.C.]] striker [[Mido]]. An [[The Football Association|FA]] investigation was launched but was soon dropped after it was later revealed that chants directed at him were because of his similarity to the shoe bomber [[Richard Reid]].

===Views considered Islamophobic===
* [[Carl Ernst]], a scholar of [[Islamic studies]], and the [[Council on American-Islamic Relations]] has alleged that [[Robert Spencer]] is "Islamophobic".&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.cair-net.org/default.asp?Page=articleView&amp;id=1853&amp;theType=NR CA Synagogue That Hosted Islamophobe Urged to Invite Muslim Speaker], CAIR News Releases, [[November 8|November 08]], 2005 &lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Ernst"&gt; [http://www.unc.edu/~cernst/courses/2004/026/001/spencer.htm Notes on the Ideological Patrons of an Islamophobe, Robert Spencer by Carl W. Ernst] - [[University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill]], [[2004]]&lt;/ref&gt; Spencer responded to this labeling, and invited Ernst to debate.&lt;ref&gt; [http://jihadwatch.org/archives/012899.php], An open letter to Carl Ernst, [[August 27]], 2006 &lt;/ref&gt;
* The Council on American-Islamic Relations has stated that the views of [[Ann Coulter]] are Islamophobic.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cair-net.org/default.asp?Page=articleView&amp;id=1048&amp;theType=NR Ann Coulter says Muslims 'Smell Bad'], ''Council on American-Islamic Relations'', March 10, 2004&lt;/ref&gt;
* Oliver Duff of ''[[The Independent]]'' said in 2006 that the [[British National Party]] attempted to use increasing Islamophobia to make gains in local elections.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.independent.co.uk/uk/politics/article356477.ece Rising Islamophobia makes Birmingham fertile ground for BNP], ''The Independent'', April 8, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;
* Liz McGregor and John Hooper of [[The Guardian]], has alleged that the views and writings of [[Oriana Fallaci]], an Italian journalist and author of "[[The Force of Reason]]", was "Islamaphobic" [sic]. &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/italy/story/0,,1873911,00.html Obituary of Oriana Fallaci] - [[The Guardian]], [[16 September]], [[2006]]. "''Controversial Italian journalist famed for her interviews and war reports but notorious for her Islamaphobia''"&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[Islamic Human Rights Commission]] gave U.S [[Attorney General]] [[John Ashcroft]] a nomination for their 2003 "Islamophobe of the year" award for publicly saying, "Islam is a religion in which God requires you to send your son to die for him. Christianity is a faith in which God sends his son to die for you"&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.inminds.co.uk/islamophobia-awards-2003.html Annual Islamophobia Awards, 2003]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?file=/c/a/2002/02/22/MN146728.DTL "The gospel according to John (Ashcroft)"] San Francisco Chronicle&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[Islamic Human Rights Commission]] made [[Daniel Pipes]] a nominee for their 2004 and 2005 "Islamophobe of the year" awards.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ihrc.org.uk/show.php?id=1124 Winners of Islamophobia Awards 2004], ''Islamic Human Rights Commission'', [[June 26]] [[2004]]. *[http://www.ihrc.org.uk/show.php?id=1657 Winners of the Islamophobia Awards 2005], ''Islamic Human Rights Commission'', [[December 17]] [[2005]].&lt;/ref&gt;
* A December 2005 interview by [[Vlaams Belang]] frontman [[Filip Dewinter]] with the American-Jewish newsweekly [[The Jewish Week]] included a question if "Jews should vote for a party that espouses xenophobia". Dewinter responded by saying: "Xenophobia is not the word I would use. If it absolutely must be a ‘phobia,’ let it be ‘Islamophobia.’"&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20060208183342/http://www.thejewishweek.com/news/newscontent.php3?artid=11767 Filip Dewinter interview], ''Jewish Week'', December 9, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[United Kingdom|UK]] Minister Peter Hain's statement that Britain's Muslim community is "isolationist" was met with accusations of Islamophobia, as well as [[Italy|Italian]] prime minister [[Silvio Berlusconi]]'s public claim that Western civilization is superior to Islam.&lt;ref name="spiked"&gt;[http://www.spiked-online.co.uk/Articles/00000006D95B.htm Who's afraid of Islamophobia?], ''Spiked'', July 2, 2002&lt;/ref&gt;
* Some suggestions in the [[United Kingdom debate over veils]] (which concerned the circumstances in which Muslim women should be required to remove the [[Niqab]]) were considered Islamophobic by MP [[John McDonnell (politician)|John McDonnell]].&lt;ref name="McDonnell"&gt;See, e.g., "[http://www.john4leader.org.uk/2006/10/wave-of-islamophobia.html Wave of Islamophobia]", a [[Blog|blog post]] by [[John McDonnell]] MP from [[October 6]], [[2006]].&lt;/ref&gt;
* CAIR and [[Associated Press|the Associated Press]] called United States Rep. [[Virgil Goode|Virgil H. Goode, Jr.]] (R-VA) islamophobic for his Dec. 2006 letter stating that Rep-elect [[Keith Ellison (politician)|Keith Ellison]]'s desire to use the Qur'an during the swearing in ceremonies was a threat to "the values and beliefs traditional to the United States of America" and for saying "I fear that in the next century we will have many more Muslims in the United States if we do not adopt the strict immigration policies."&lt;ref name="Howsare"&gt;{{cite news|title=Anti-Muslim letter goes out to hundreds - not all are amused|author=Erika Howsare|date=12/19/2006|url=http://www.c-ville.com/index.php?cat=141404064431134&amp;ShowArticle_ID=11041812060944420}} Retrieved Dec. 20, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title= Congressman Will Not Apologize for IslamophobiaBy The Associated Press| publisher=Associated Press| date=2006-12-21|url=http://www.diversityinc.com/public/1064.cfm}} Retrieved on Dec. 21, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;
* Concerning the US state of [[North Carolina]]’s position (as expressed by their attorney general’s office) in the ongoing case of [[ACLU of N.C. &amp; Syidah Matteen v. State of North Carolina]] that the only swearing-in for testimony in court that was valid had to be on a [[Bible|Christian Bible]] (and that all others must choose to affirm), CAIR's Legal Director in Washington D.C, Arsalan Iftikhar, said “This shows there's a lot of anti-Muslim sentiment, especially here in the United States.”&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.csmonitor.com/2005/0720/p02s02-usju.html|title=Raise your right hand and swear to tell the truth... on the Koran?|date=2005-07-20|author=Patrik Jonsson|publisher=The Christian Science Monitor}} Retrieved on Jan. 22, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;
*Statements that incite Islamophobia from [[Franklin Graham]], [[Pat Robertson]] and [[Benny Hinn]], according to [[John Esposito]]. [[q:John Esposito|read relative quotes]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.un.org/Pubs/chronicle/2004/webArticles/112204_Conference.asp|title=Unlearning Intolerance| publisher=UN Chronicle Online Edition|date=2004-7-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;
ABC News has reported that "[p]ublic views of Islam are one casualty of the post-Sept. 11, 2001 conflict: Nearly six in 10 Americans think the religion is prone to violent extremism, nearly half regard it unfavorably, and a remarkable one in four admits to prejudicial feelings against Muslims and Arabs alike."&lt;ref name=ABCMarch8&gt;[http://abcnews.go.com/US/story?id=1700599 "Poll: Americans Skeptical of Islam and Arabs"], ”ABC News”, March 8, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; They also report that 27 percent of Americans admit feelings of prejudice against Muslims.&lt;ref name=ABCMarch8/&gt; According to Gallup polls, 40 percent of Americans admit to prejudice against Muslims, and 39 percent believe Muslims should carry special identification. &lt;ref&gt;[http://abcnews.go.com/GMA/Story?id=2413473&amp;page=2 "Islamophobia Felt 5 Years after 9/11"], ''Good Morning America'', September 9, 2006. &lt;/ref&gt;

===Incidents on aircraft===
Some incidents with Muslim passengers on aircraft have given rise to the expression "[[Flying while Muslim]]".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cnn.com/2006/US/11/21/passengers.removed/index.html Airline checks claim of 'Muslim while flying' discrimination] [[CNN]] November 21, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;
* On [[16 August]] [[2006]] British passengers on-board a flight from Malaga to Manchester requested the removal of two men of Asian descent from a plane. According to a spokesman for the [[Civil Guard]] in Malaga, "These men had aroused suspicion because of their appearance and the fact that they were speaking in a [[foreign language]] thought to be an [[Arabic language]], and the pilot was refusing to take off until they were escorted off the plane." A security sweep of the plane found no explosives or any item of a terrorist nature. [[Monarch Airlines]] booked the men, who were Urdu speakers, into a hotel room, gave them a free meal and sent them home on a later plane. The men later responded, "Just because we're Muslim, does not mean we are suicide bombers." The Islamic Human Rights Commission blamed "ever-increasing Islamophobia" related to the "war on terror" for the incident.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dailymail.co.uk/pages/live/articles/news/news.html?in_article_id=401419&amp;in_page_id=1770&amp;in_page_id=1770&amp;ct=5&amp;expand=true#StartComments Mutiny as passengers refuse to fly until Asians are removed] - [[Daily Mail|Mail on Sunday]]. [[20 August]], [[2006]]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mirror.co.uk/news/tm_objectid=17607948&amp;method=full&amp;siteid=94762&amp;headline=exclusive--malaga-jet-mutiny-pair-s-shock-at-plane-ejection-name_page.html Exclusive: Malaga Jet mutiny pair's shock at plane ejection] - [[The Daily Mirror]]. [[23 August]],[[2006]].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/airlines/story/0,,1854722,00.html Removal of men from holiday flight condemned][[The Guardian]]. [[21 August]][[2006]]&lt;/ref&gt;
* A passenger traveling to the [[British Virgin Islands]] on a plane bound for the United States from Manchester in the UK was forced off the plane prior to [[takeoff]]. The man, a British-born Muslim residing in the United States, said he was singled out because he was a Muslim pilot and was left feeling "demoralized and humiliated. I must have met the profile on the day. I have an Arabic name, I am a Muslim, I'm from Britain and I know how to fly."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.manchestereveningnews.co.uk/news/s/220/220381_muslim_pilot_kicked_off_jet_in_terror_alert.html Muslim pilot kicked off jet in terror alert] - [[Manchester Evening News]]. [[11 August]], [[2006]]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.independent.co.uk/uk/this_britain/article1220859.ece Muslim pilot reveals shock at being ordered off flight] - [[The Independent]]. [[22 August]], [[2006]]&lt;/ref&gt;
* On [[21 November]] [[2006]], six [[imams]] were forcefully removed from a [[US Airways]] flight at [[Minneapolis St. Paul International Airport]] on suspicions of terrorism. The event led to an outcry from Muslim organizations in America saying that what happened showed the growing prejudice against Muslims in America.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2006/11/21/AR2006112100687.html "U.S. Muslims outraged after imams kicked off plane"], ''[[The Washington Post]]'', [[22 November]], [[2006]].&lt;/ref&gt; Details of the accusations made against the imams can be found in the official police report on the incident (currently exclusively hosted [http://pajamasmedia.com/2006/12/the_faking_imams_pajamas_media.php here]), which includes written witness testimony of the imams' extremely suspicious activity, such as praising terrorism, praying unnecessarily loudly, asking for [[Seat belt|seat-belt]] extensions that were obviously not needed (then putting said extensions under their seats), not sitting in their assigned seats (having someone near each exit in a pattern shared by hijackers of the past), and getting up to move around and confer with each other repeatedly. See [[Flying Imams controversy]] for more details regarding this incident.

==See also==
* [[Anti-Arabism]]
* [[Persecution of Muslims]]
* [[Islamist terrorism]]
* [[Islam]]
* [[Criticism of Islam]]
* [[Alliance of Civilizations]]
* [[Clash of Civilizations]]
* [[Islamophobia Watch]]
* [[Religious intolerance]]
* [[Islamofascism]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist|2}}

==References==
* {{cite encyclopedia | editor=Cashmore, E | encyclopedia=Encyclopedia of Race and Ethnic Studies | year=2003 | publisher=Routledge}}
* {{cite book | last=Benn | first=T. |  coauthors=Jawad, H. | title=Muslim Women in the United Kingdom and Beyond: Experiences and Images | year=2004 | publisher=[[Brill]] | id=ISBN 9004125817}}
*{{cite book | last=Egorova | first=Y. |  coauthors=Parfitt, T. | title=Jews, Muslims, and Mass Media: Mediating the 'Other' | year=2003 | publisher=Routledge Curzon | location = London | id=ISBN 0415318394}}
*{{cite book | last=Haddad | first=Y. |  title=Muslims in the West: From Sojourners to Citizens | year=2002 | publisher=Oxford University Press | location = Oxford | id=ISBN 0195148053}}
* {{cite book | last=Johnson | first=M. R. D. |  coauthors=Soydan, H; Williams, C. | title=Social Work and Minorities: European Perspectives | location = London; New York | year=1998 | publisher=Routledge | id=ISBN 0415169623}}
* {{cite book | last=Miles | first=R. |  coauthors=Brown, M. | title=Racism | year=2003 | location = London; New York | publisher=Routledge | id=ISBN 0415296765}}

===Further reading===
*{{cite book | last=van Driel | first=B. | title=Confronting Islamophobia In Educational Practice | year=2004 | publisher=Trentham Books | id=ISBN 1858563402}}
*{{cite book | last=Greaves | first=R. | title=Islam and the West Post 9/11 | year=2004 | publisher=Ashgate publishing Ltd| id=ISBN 0754650057}}
*{{cite book | last=Ramadan | first=T. | title=Western Muslims and the Future of Islam | year=2004 | publisher=Oxford University Press | location = Oxford | id=ISBN 019517111X}}
*{{cite book | last=Quraishi | first=M. | title=Muslims and Crime: A Comparative Study | year=2005 | publisher=Ashgate publishing Ltd| id=ISBN 075464233X}}

==External links==
{{sisterlinks}}
* [http://www.fairuk.org Forum against Islamophobia and Racism]
* [http://www.islamophobia.org Islamophobia.org]
* [http://www.islamawareness.net/Islamophobia/ "Islamophobia"], ''Islamicawareness.net''
* [http://www.islamophobia-watch.com/ Islamophobia Watch]
* [http://www.guardian.co.uk/uk_news/story/0,,1997888,00.html "From Aladdin to Lost Ark, Muslims get angry at 'bad guy' film images"] -[[The Guardian]], 25 January 2007
* [http://www.sevenoaksmag.com/features/cupehumanrights.html Speech against Islamophobia and racism at CUPE National Conference in Vancouver, Canada]
* [http://islamonline.net/English/artculture/2005/01/article08.shtml Muslims and Islam in European History Textbooks]
* [http://www.keralanext.com/news/?id=1078945 Grant Bangladeshi Hindu migrants refugee status, but deport Bangladeshi Muslims: Rajnath Singh]
* [http://www.eyetopic.co.uk/Against_Islamophobia/index.htm "Rally against incitement and Islamophobia in London"], ''[[eyetopic.co.uk]]'', February 11, 2006.
* [[Chris Allen (UK)]] [http://www.chris-allen.co.uk Islamophobia resources: writing, articles &amp; publications]
* Dr. Louay Safi's [http://aninsight.org/labels/Islamophobia.html Articles on Islamophobia]
* Brooks, James. [http://www.islamonline.net/English/Views/2003/05/article11.shtml "Deep roots of Islamophobia] Islamonline.net.
* Deane, Claudia and Fears, Darryl. [http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2006/03/08/AR2006030802221.html Negative Perception Of Islam Increasing], ''The Washington Post'', March 9, 2006.
* [[Khaled Abou Al-Fadl|El Fadl, Khaled Abou]]. [http://www.scholarofthehouse.org/onrebi.html "On revising bigotry"], chapter from '' The Conference on the Books: The Search for Beauty in Islam'', ''Scholars of the House''.
* [[Muriel Gray|Gray, Muriel]]. [http://www.sundayherald.com/53959 "How can we have respect for Islam when we are too fearful to criticise it?"], ''The Glasgow Herald'', February 5, 2006.
* Hassan, Fardusa. [http://www.guardian.co.uk/race/story/0,,1862329,00.html "Beauty queen enters Islamophobia debate"], ''The Guardian'', August 31, 2006.
* Hassan, Ghali. [http://www.uruknet.info/?p=m20398&amp;l=i&amp;size=1&amp;hd=0 The Road to the Muslim Holocaust], ''Globalresearch.ca'', February 7, 2006.
* Khan, Ali. [http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=935319 The Essentialist Terrorist] (how puritanical Islam is protrayed as essentially violent).
* [[Norman Lamont|Lamont, Norman]]. [http://www.telegraph.co.uk/opinion/main.jhtml?xml=/opinion/2002/05/08/do0801.xml "Down with multiculturalism, book-burning and fatwas"], ''The Daily Telegraph'', May 8, 2002.
* Marud, Abdal-Hakim. [http://www.masud.co.uk/ISLAM/ahm/right.htm "Muslims and the European Right"], ''Masud.co.uk'', first delivered as a lecture on April 30, 2000.
* [[Brigitte L. Nacos|Nacos, Brigitte L.]], ''Fueling Our Fears: Stereotyping, Media Coverage, and Public Opinion of Muslim Americans''. 2006
* O'Keefe, Derrick. [http://www.sevenoaksmag.com/commentary/macleans.html Maclean's magazine goes over-the-top with racist cover story], ''Seven Oaks Magazine'', October 27, 2006.
* [[Daniel Pipes|Pipes, Daniel]]. [http://www.danielpipes.org/article/3075 "Islamophobia?"], ''New York Sun'', [[October 25]] [[2005]].
* Ramji, Rubina. [http://www.unomaha.edu/jrf/Vol9No2/RamjiIslam.htm "From ''Navy Seals'' to ''The Siege'': Getting to Know the Muslim Terrorist, Hollywood Style"] ''The Journal of Religion and Film'', Vol. 9, No.2, October 2005
* Riyanto, Geger. [http://www.thejakartapost.com/yesterdaydetail.asp?fileid=20061027.F04 "The Genealogy of today's Islamophobia"], ''The Jakarta Post'', October 27, 2006.
* [[Walter Laqueur]]. [http://blog.oup.com/oupblog/2006/10/the_use_of_the_.html The Origins of Fascism: Islamic Fascism, Islamophobia, Antisemitism], [[Oxford University Press]] blog.
* Barry Van, ''Confronting Islamophobia in Educational Practice'' ISBN 1-85856-340-2
* [[Stephen Castle|Castle, Stephen]]. [http://news.independent.co.uk/europe/article2084525.ece "Islamophobia takes a grip across Europe"], ''[[The Independent]]'', December 18, 2006.

{{Muslims and controversies footer}}
{{Islam topics|state=collapsed}}

[[Category:Islamic politics and Islamic world studies]]
[[Category:Islam-related controversies]]
[[Category:Islamophobia| ]]
[[Category:Political neologisms]]

[[ar:معاداة الإسلام]]
[[bg:Ислямофобия]]
[[ca:Islamofòbia]]
[[cs:Islamofobie]]
[[da:Islamofobi]]
[[de:Islamfeindlichkeit]]
[[es:Islamofobia]]
[[fa:اسلام‌ستیزی]]
[[fr:Islamophobie]]
[[it:Islamofobia]]
[[he:אסלאמופוביה]]
[[nl:Islamofobie]]
[[ja:イスラム恐怖症]]
[[no:Islamofobi]]
[[pl:Islamofobia]]
[[pt:Islamofobia]]
[[ro:Islamofobie]]
[[ru:Исламофобия]]
[[simple:Islamophobia]]
[[fi:Islamofobia]]
[[sv:Islamofobi]]
[[tr:İslamofobi]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>