<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20041110001628|7355024" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="162173" pageid="162173" ns="0" title="Islamophobia"><revisions><rev timestamp="2004-11-11T20:45:08Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Islamophobia''' is the fear and/ or hatred of [[Islam]],  [[Muslim]]s or [[Islamic culture]]. Islamophobia can be characterized by the belief that all or most Muslims are religious fanatics, have violent tendencies towards non-Muslims, and reject as directly opposed to Islam such concepts as [[social equality|equality]], [[tolerance]], and [[democracy]]. 

Some argue that Islamophobia is a new form of [[racism]] whereby Muslims, an ethno-religious group, not a race, are nevertheless constructed as a race. A set of negative assumptions are made of the entire group to the detriment of members of that group. During the [[1990]]&amp;#8217;s many sociologists and cultural analysts observed a shift in racist ideas from ones based on skin colour to ones based on notions of cultural superiority and [[otherness]] (see paper by Dr Anya Rudiger and article by Jeremy Seabrook in [[#External Links|links]]). 

The term is a [[neologism]] dating from the early 1990&amp;#8217;s and derives from [[Xenophobia]]. As such, it reflects the influence of such 1990s movements as [[multi-culturalism]] and [[identity politics]]. 

The term most often appears in discourse on the condition of [[immigrant]] Muslims living as [[minority|minorities]] in [[Western countries |the West]]. In this case, the common experiences of immigrant communities of unemployment, rejection, alienation and violence has combined with Islamophobia to make integration particularly difficult. (See article by Tariq Ramadan in links.) This has led, in the [[United Kingdom]], for example, to Muslim communities suffering higher levels of unemployment, poor housing, poor health and levels of racially motivated violence than other communities. (See paper by Maleiha Malik in links). 

Islamophobia, as a phenomenon, dates back at least as far as the [[Crusades]]. It has been present in [[Europe]] and the West for many centuries. It has been argued that Islamophobia exists outside the West, for example in India. This is more closely related to [[Communal Politics in India]], although Islamophobia in India does share, with western Islamophobia, the denigration of Islamic culture and history (see linked article by [[William Dalrymple]]). 

It has been argued by some, most notably [[Edward Said]], that the denigration of Islamic civilisation associated with Islamophobia is central to the concept of [[Western Civilisation]]. The ousting and marginalising of Islam marks the debut of &amp;#8216;Western&amp;#8217; Civilisation and, thus, explains the depth and longevity of western Islamophobia:
:: '' &amp;#8220;Islam was a provocation in many ways. It lay uneasily close to Christianity, geographically and culturally. It drew on the Judeo-Hellenic traditions. It borrowed creatively from Christianity - it could boast unrivalled military and political successes. Nor was this all. The Islamic lands sit adjacent to and even on top of the biblical lands. Moreover, the heart of the Islamic domain has always been the region closest to Europe... Arabic and Hebrew are Semitic languages, and together they dispose and re-dispose of material that is urgently important to Christianity. From the end of the 7th century to the 16th century, Islam in either its Arab, Ottoman, North African or Spanish form dominated or effectively threatened European Christianity. That Islam outstripped and outshone Rome cannot have been absent from the mind of any European." '' 
Edward Said: Orientalism. 2003 Edition. Page 74.

The [[Runnymede Trust]] has identified eight components that they say define Islamophobia. This definition, from the [[1997]] document &amp;#8216; Islamophobia: A Challenge For Us All&amp;#8217; is widely accepted, including by the [[European Monitoring Centre on Racism and Xenophobia]]. The eight components are:

#Islam is seen as a monolithic bloc, static and unresponsive to change.
#Islam is seen as separate and 'other'. It does not have values in common with other cultures, is not affected by them and does not influence them.
#Islam is seen as inferior to the West. It is seen as barbaric, irrational, primitive and sexist.
#Islam is seen as violent, aggressive, threatening, supportive of terrorism and engaged in a 'clash of civilisations'.
#Islam is seen as a political ideology and is used for political or military advantage. 
#Criticisms made of the West by Islam are rejected out of hand. 
#Hostility towards Islam is used to justify discriminatory practices towards Muslims and exclusion of Muslims from mainstream society. 
#Anti-Muslim hostility is seen as natural or normal.

Given the strong association between [[Arab]]s and the religion of [[Islam]], Islamophobia is often expressed as a form of [[anti-Arab]] racism, though not all Arabs are Muslim and the majority of Muslims are not in fact Arab. Ironically, anti-Muslim bias has occasionally been expressed in violent attacks on [[Sikh]]s. In these cases, Sikhs were mistaken for Muslims on account of their distinctive turbans.

An alleged factor, that some argue provokes Islamophobia, is the rise of [[anti-Western]] [[Islamism|Islamist]] movements, which have either come to power outright in some countries ([[Iran]], [[Sudan]], post-Soviet-era [[Afghanistan]]), or else exerted a strong influence on government policy in others ([[Saudi Arabia]], [[Pakistan]]). Many people mistakenly believe that most Muslims are Islamist, when in fact the Islamist movement is only a minority position.

Recently there have been several efforts by non-Muslims to combat Islamophobia. In the wake of September 11, for example, a few non-Muslim women practiced [[hijab]] in a show of solidarity with their Muslim counterparts, who it was feared would be particularly vulnerable for reprisal given their distinctive dress. Non-Muslims also helped form community watches to protect [[mosque]]s from attack.


==Examples of Islamophobia==

* Rep. C. [[Saxby Chambliss]] (R-GA): "Just turn (the sheriff) loose and have him arrest every Muslim that crosses the state line" (to Georgia law officers, November 2001) [http://www.visalaw.com/03feb1/17feb103.html]
* [[Ann Coulter]]: "We should invade their countries, kill their leaders and convert them to Christianity."[http://www.nationalreview.com/coulter/coulter091301.shtml]
*  Will Cummins: "It is the black heart of Islam, not the black face, to which millions object." [http://www.sport.telegraph.co.uk/opinion/main.jhtml?xml=/opinion/2004/07/18/do1802.xml&amp;sSheet=/opinion/2004/07/18/ixopinion.html]
*[[Robert Kilroy-Silk]]: "Muslims everywhere behave with equal savagery. They behead criminals, stone to death female - only female - adulteresses, throw acid in the faces of women who refuse to wear the chador, mutilate the genitals of young girls and ritually abuse animals"  [http://www.fact-index.com/r/ro/robert_kilroy_silk.html] 
* [[Jean-Marie Le Pen]]: "These elements have a negative effect on all of public security. They are strengthened demographically both by natural reproduction and by immigration, which reinforces their stubborn ethnic segregation, their domineering nature. This is the world of Islam in all its aberrations."[http://www.fpp.co.uk/online/02/04/Haaretz_LePen.html]
* [[Jerry Vines]]: "Christianity was founded by the virgin-born Jesus Christ. Islam was founded by Mohammed, a demon-possessed paedophile who had 12 wives, and his last one was a 9-year-old girl."[http://www.biblicalrecorder.org/content/news/2002/6_14_2002/ne140602vines.shtml]
*[[Michael Savage (commentator)|Michael Savage]]: "I think these people [Arabs and Muslims] need to be forcibly converted to Christianity ... It's the only thing that can probably turn them into human beings." [05/12/03] (on his radio show [[The Savage Nation]])
*Rabbi [[Meir Kahane]] (1974): "There are no 'moderate' Arabs. There are only clever and less clever, patient and impatient. The final solution for all is the same - the elimination of any Jewish State. And so we repeat: There is no 'Palestine people' and there is no 'Palestine.'"[http://kahanetzadak.com/palestine.html]
See also: [[anti-Islamism]], [[persecution of Muslims]], [[Religious intolerance]]

==External Links==

*[http://www.guardian.co.uk/race/story/0,11374,1267567,00.html  Jeremy Seabrook: Religion as a Fig Leaf for Racism]
*[http://www.aicongress.org/hate.html The American Islamic Congress offers its own guide on recognizing hatespeech towards adherents of Islam. Responding to Hate Speech: A Citizen's Guide]
*[http://www.sant.ox.ac.uk/princeton/pap_rudiger.shtml  Dr Anya Rudiger of The European Monitoring Centre on Racism and Xenophobia discusses Islamophobia as a form of racism.]
*[http://eumc.eu.int/eumc/index.php?fuseaction=content.dsp_cat_content&amp;contentid=3e3e8c602f879&amp;catid=3e3e6e32a2316&amp;search=1&amp;frmsearch=Islamophobia&amp;lang=EN Tariq Ramadan: Islam and Muslims in Europe]
*[http://www.sant.ox.ac.uk/princeton/pap_malik.shtml   Maleiha Malik discusses the social exclusion of Muslims in UK due to Islamophobia.]
*[http://www.runnymedetrust.org/publications/pdfs/islamophobia.pdf  Runnymede Trust. Islamophobia: A Challenge for Us All]
*[http://www.fairuk.org/  Forum Against Islamophobia and Racism,  a charity that promotes inter faith understanding and defines Islamophobia as a form of racism.]
*[http://www.sant.ox.ac.uk/princeton/index.shtml Oxford &amp; Princeton Universities: Muslims in Europe Post 9/11.]
*[http://books.guardian.co.uk/review/story/0,,1172782,00.html Trapped in the Ruins. William Dalrymple examines attempts to re-write the history of Islam in India.]
*[http://eumc.eu.int/eumc/index.php European Monitoring Centre on Racism and Xenophobia]
*[http://www.adl.org/terrorism_america/adl_responds.asp ADL Responds to Violence and Harassment against Arab Americans and Muslim Americans]

==Examples of Use==

Examples of use by the writer Faisal Bodi:
*[[The Guardian]]: [http://www.guardian.co.uk/comment/story/0,3604,715150,00.html ''Call this monster by its name'']
*[[The Guardian]]: [http://www.guardian.co.uk/comment/story/0,3604,528063,00.html ''Old hatred, new style'']
*[[The Guardian]]: [http://www.guardian.co.uk/g2/story/0,3604,719159,00.html ''To say that jihadis are a threat is not Islamophobic'']


[[Category:Phobias]]
[[Category:Prejudices]]

[[de:Islamophobie]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>