<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20111115015938|460710097" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="162173" pageid="162173" ns="0" title="Islamophobia"><revisions><rev timestamp="2011-11-15T02:01:45Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{sprotect|small=yes}}
:''This article is about discrimination. For criticism of Islam, see [[Criticism of Islam]]. For criticism of political Islam, see [[Criticism of Islamism]]''
{{Status of religious freedom}}
'''Islamophobia''' describes [[prejudice]] against, hatred or irrational fear of [[Islam]] or [[Muslim]]s&lt;ref&gt;"''[http://books.google.com/books?id=c8Xf5N8ExXIC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=teaching+the+global+dimensions&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=w5TgTLnRHIuChQeepNSJDQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CC0Q6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=teaching%20the%20global%20dimensions&amp;f=false Teaching the Global Dimension]"'' David Hick, Cathie Holden (2007). P.140. &lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
* Sandra Fredman, ''Discrimination and Human Rights'', Oxford University Press, ISBN 0-19-924603-3, p.121.
* Yvonne Yazbeck Haddad, ''Muslims in the West: From Sojourners to Citizens'', Oxford University Press, ISBN 0-19-514806-1, p.19
* ''Islamophobia: A Challenge for Us All'', [[Runnymede Trust]], 1997, p. 1, cited in Quraishi, Muzammil. ''Muslims and Crime: A Comparative Study'', Ashgate Publishing Ltd., 2005, p. 60. ISBN 0-7546-4233-X. Early in 1997, the Commission on [[British Muslims]] and Islamophobia, at that time part of the Runnymede Trust, issued a consultative document on Islamophobia under the chairmanship of Professor Gordon Conway, [[Vice-Chancellor]] of the [[University of Sussex]]. The final report, ''Islamophobia: A Challenge for Us All'', was launched in November 1997 by [[Home Secretary]] [[Jack Straw]]&lt;/ref&gt;
The term dates back to the late 1980s or early 1990s,&lt;ref&gt;''Islamophobia: A Challenge for Us All'', [[Runnymede Trust]], 1997, p. 1, cited in Quraishi, Muzammil. ''Muslims and Crime: A Comparative Study'', Ashgate Publishing Ltd., 2005, p. 60; [[Kofi Annan|Annan, Kofi]]. [http://www.un.org/News/Press/docs/2004/sgsm9637.doc.htm "Secretary-General, addressing headquarters seminar on confronting Islamophobia"], [[United Nations]] press release, December 7, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt; but came into common usage after the [[September 11, 2001 attacks]] in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;
* Casciani, Dominic. [http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/3768327.stm "Islamophobia pervades UK – report"], BBC News, June 2, 2004.
* Rima Berns McGowan writes in ''Muslims in the Diaspora'' (University of Toronto Press, 1991, p. 268) that the term "Islamophobia" was first used in an unnamed American periodical in 1991.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1997, the British [[Runnymede Trust]] defined Islamophobia as the "dread or hatred of Islam and therefore, to the fear and dislike of all Muslims," stating that it also refers to the practice of [[Discrimination|discriminating]] against Muslims by excluding them from the economic, social, and public life of the nation. It includes the perception that Islam has no values in common with other cultures, is inferior to the West and is a violent [[political ideology]] rather than a [[religion]].&lt;ref name=Runnymede5&gt;Runnymede 1997, p. 5, cited in Quraishi 2005, p. 60.&lt;/ref&gt; Professor Anne Sophie Roald writes that steps were taken toward official acceptance of the term in January 2001 at the "Stockholm International Forum on Combating Intolerance", where Islamophobia was recognized as a form of intolerance alongside [[Xenophobia]] and [[Antisemitism]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|first=Anne Sophie |last=Roald |title=New Muslims in the European Context: The Experience of Scandinavian Converts |page=53 |publisher=Brill |year=2004|isbn=9004136797}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A perceived trend of increasing Islamophobia during the 2000s has been attributed by some commentators to the September 11 attacks,&lt;ref&gt;Benn, Jawad (2004) p. 111&lt;/ref&gt; while others associate it with the rapidly growing Muslim populations in the Western world, especially in [[Islam in Western Europe|Western Europe]], due to both [[immigration to Europe|immigration]] and high [[fertility rate]].&lt;ref name="Vertovec"&gt;Steven Vertovec, "Islamophobia and Muslim Recognition in Britain"; in Haddad (2002) pp. 32–33&lt;/ref&gt;
In May 2002, the [[European Monitoring Centre on Racism and Xenophobia]] (EUMC), a [[European Union]] watchdog, released a report entitled "Summary report on Islamophobia in the EU after 11 September 2001", which described an increase in Islamophobia-related incidents in European member states post-9/11.&lt;ref&gt;See:
*Greaves (2004) p. 133
*Allen, Chris; Nielsen, Jorgen S.; Summary report on Islamophobia in the EU after 11 September 2001 (May 2002), EUMC.&lt;/ref&gt;
Although the term is widely recognized and used, both the term and the concept have been criticized.

==Definitions==
The word ''Islamophobia'' is a  [[neologism]] formed from ''Islam'' and ''-[[phobia]]''. The compound form ''Islamo-'' contains the [[thematic stem|thematic vowel]] ''[[:wikt:-o-|-o-]]'', and is found in earlier coinages such as ''Islamo-Christian'' from the 19th century.
As opposed to being a psychological or individualistic phobia, according to professor of religion Peter Gottschalk and Gabriel Greenberg, "Islamophobia" connotes a [[social anxiety]] about Islam and Muslims.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wesleyan.edu/newsletter/campus/2007/1107islambook.html |title=Faculty, Alumnus Discuss Concept of "Islamophobia" in Co-Authored Book |accessdate=2007-12-29 |date=2007-11-20 |author=Corrina Balash Kerr |work=[[Wesleyan University]] Newsletter}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.politicalaffairs.net/article/articleview/6181/1/296/ |title=Images of Muslims: Discussing Islamophobia with Peter Gottschalk |accessdate=2007-12-29 |date=2007-11-19 |work=Political Affairs. |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20071206034654/http://www.politicalaffairs.net/article/articleview/6181/1/296/ &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-12-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A number of individuals and organizations have made attempts to define the concept. [[Kofi Annan]] told a UN conference on Islamophobia in 2004: "[W]hen the world is compelled to coin a new term to take account of increasingly widespread [[bigotry]], that is a sad and troubling development. Such is the case with Islamophobia."&lt;ref name=Annan&gt;[[Kofi Annan|Annan, Kofi]]. [http://www.un.org/News/Press/docs/2004/sgsm9637.doc.htm "Secretary-General, addressing headquarters seminar on confronting Islamophobia"], [[United Nations]] press release, December 7, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1996, the [[Runnymede Trust]] established the Commission on British Muslims and Islamophobia, chaired by Professor Gordon Conway, the vice-chancellor of the [[University of Sussex]]. Their report, Islamophobia: A Challenge for Us All, was launched in November 1997 by the Home Secretary, [[Jack Straw]]. In this report, Islamophobia was defined by the Trust as "an outlook or world-view involving an unfounded dread and dislike of Muslims, which results in practices of exclusion and discrimination."&lt;ref name="EoRE215"&gt;Encyclopedia of Race and Ethics, p. 215&lt;/ref&gt; An early documented use of the word in the United States was by the conservative American news magazine ''[[Insight on the News]]'' in 1991, used to describe Russian activities in [[Afghanistan]].&lt;ref name="EoRE215"/&gt; Other claims of early use include usage by Iranian clerics in 1979,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.prochoix.org/frameset/26/islamophobie26.html ''Islamophobie?''], [[Caroline Fourest]] &amp; Fiammetta Venner; in prochoix, no.26/27, 2003.&lt;/ref&gt; or its use in 1921 by the painter [[Étienne Dinet]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.minorites.org/article.php?IDA=1319 :: Minorités ::&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]{{dead link|date=October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The American Muslim writer [[Stephen Schwartz (journalist)|Stephen Schwartz]] has defined Islamophobia as the condemnation of the entirety of [[Islam]] and its history as [[Extremism|extremist]]; denying the existence of a moderate Muslim majority; regarding Islam as a problem for the world; treating conflicts involving Muslims as necessarily their own fault; insisting that Muslims make changes to their religion; and inciting war against Islam as a whole.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.frontpagemag.com/Articles/ReadArticle.asp?ID=17874 "The 'Islamophobes' That Aren't"], ''FrontPage Magazine'', April 28, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;

In a 2007 article in ''Journal of Sociology'' defines Islamophobia as anti-Muslim racism and a continuation of anti-[[Asian people|Asian]] and [[Anti-Arabism|anti-Arab]] racism.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Scott Poynting, Victoria Mason |title=The resistible rise of Islamophobia |journal=Journal of Sociology |volume=43 |issue=1 |pages=61–86 |year=2007 |doi=10.1177/1440783307073935}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Similarly, [[John Denham (politician)|John Denham]] has drawn parallels between modern Islamophobia and the [[antisemitism]] of the 1930s,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/uk/article6832035.ece The Times: Fascism fears: John Denham speaks out over clashes]&lt;/ref&gt; so have [[Maud Olofsson]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.svd.se/nyheter/inrikes/artikel_3674445.svd SvD: Reinfeldt: Kärnan i partiets idé]&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Jan Hjärpe]], among others.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.svd.se/nyheter/inrikes/artikel_3674029.svd SvD: Sverigedemokrat till hårt angrepp mot muslimsk ideologi i tal]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vg.no/nyheter/innenriks/artikkel.php?artid=10089287 VG: Erna Solberg mener muslimer hetses som jødene på 30-tallet]&lt;/ref&gt;

In a 2008 article in the "Journal of Political Ideologies" Jose P. Zuquete argues that Islamophobia is a catch-all term that should be avoided. Islamophobia places under the broad umbrella of 'fear or hatred of Islam' discourses and criticisms that may have distinct sources, motivations and goals. He argues instead for the use of "anti-Islamic" (because it distinguishes between different discourses about Islam).

==Criticism of concept==
[[Image:Salman Rushdie by Kubik 01.JPG|left|thumb|170px|[[Salman Rushdie]] was one of 12 writers who signed a statement regarding Islamophobia; "We refuse to renounce our critical spirit out of fear of being accused of "Islamophobia", a wretched concept that confuses criticism of Islam as a religion and stigmatisation of those who believe in it."&lt;ref name=Rushdie/&gt;]]

The concept of Islamophobia has been criticized on several grounds.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.brusselsjournal.com/node/816 Muslims Create Islamophobes, Then Want Islamophobes Punished | The Brussels Journal&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="autogenerated1"&gt;[http://atheism.about.com/b/2005/01/10/islamophobia-as-an-excuse-to-silence-critics-of-islam.htm Islamophobia as an Excuse to Silence Critics of Islam?&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://michellemalkin.com/2006/09/28/critics-of-islam-under-fireagain/ Michelle Malkin » Critics of Islam under fire…again&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Some critics argue that it is real, but is just another form of racism and does not require its own category,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news| url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/politics/2004/jan/12/race.religion | work=The Guardian | location=London | title=Islamophobia should be as unacceptable as racism | date=2004-01-12 | accessdate=2010-05-05 | first=Faisal | last=Bodi}}&lt;/ref&gt; while others argue that it is used to censor criticism, that its use threatens [[free speech]],&lt;ref name="autogenerated1" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news| url=http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qn4158/is_20060819/ai_n16669355 | title=Tyranny begins with self-censorship | Independent, The (London) | Find Articles at BNET}} {{Dead link|date=August 2010|bot=RjwilmsiBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; or is used to silence issues relating to Muslim populations in Western countries.&lt;ref name="Burleigh, M 2009 P440"&gt;Burleigh, M (2009) Blood and Rage, A Cultural History of Terrorism, Harper Perennial, P440&lt;/ref&gt;

Novelist [[Salman Rushdie]] and others signed a manifesto entitled [[MANIFESTO: Together facing the new totalitarianism|''Together facing the new totalitarianism'']] in March 2006 which denounced Islamophobia as "a wretched concept."&lt;ref name=Rushdie&gt;"We refuse to renounce our critical spirit out of fear of being accused of "Islamophobia", a wretched concept that confuses criticism of Islam as a religion and stigmatisation of those who believe in it." [[Salman Rushdie|Rushdie, Salman]] ''et al.'' [http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/4764730.stm "Writers' statement on cartoons"], BBC News, March 1, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; British academic [[Michael Burleigh]] argues that the term 'spares anyone the need to examine what has gone wrong within [Europe's Muslim] communities'.&lt;ref name="Burleigh, M 2009 P440"/&gt;  Others, such as [[Edward Said]], consider Islamophobia as it is evinced in [[Orientalism]] to be a 'secret sharer' in a more general antisemitic Western tradition.&lt;ref&gt;Edward W.Said, ''Orientalism'', Pantheon Books, New York 1978 pp.27–28&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Edward W. Said, ‘Orientalism Reconsidered’ in Francis Barker, Peter Hulme, Margaret Iversen, Diana Loxley (eds),'' Literature, Politics, and Theory,'' Methuen &amp; Co, London 1986 pp.210–229, pp.220f.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Bryan S. Turner (sociologist)|Bryan Stanley Turner]], introd. to Bryan S. Turner (ed.) ''Orientalism: Early Sources'', (Vol 1, Readings in Orientalism), Routledge, London (2000) reprint 2002 p.12&lt;/ref&gt; However, [[Daniel Pipes]] says that "'Islamophobia' deceptively conflates two distinct phenomena: fear of Islam and fear of radical Islam."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|last=Pipes |first=Daniel |url=http://www.danielpipes.org/article/3075 |date=2005-10-25 |title=Islamophobia? |work=[[New York Sun]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The concept of Islamophobia as formulated by Runnymede is criticized by professor [[Fred Halliday]] on several levels. He writes that the target of hostility in the modern era is not Islam and its tenets as much as it is Muslims and their actions, suggesting that a more accurate term would be "Anti-Muslimism."&lt;ref name="Aldridge1"&gt;{{Cite book
 |last=Aldridge
 |first=Alan
 |title=Religion in the Contemporary World: A Sociological Introduction
 |date=February 1, 2000
 |publisher=Polity Press
 |isbn=978-0745620831
 |page=138
 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Poole responds by noting that many Islamophobic discourses attack what they perceive to be Islam's tenets, while Miles and Brown write that Islamophobia is usually based upon negative stereotypes about Islam which are then translated into attacks on Muslims.&lt;ref name="MB165"&gt;Miles; Brown (2003) pp. 165–166&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Encyclopedia of Race and Ethnic Studies (2003)p. 219&lt;/ref&gt; Halliday also states that strains and types of prejudice against Islam and Muslims vary across different nations and cultures, which is not recognized in the Runnymede analysis. Miles and Brown respond by arguing that "the existence of different ‘Islamophobias’ does not invalidate the concept of Islamophobia any more than the existence of different racisms invalidates the concept of racism."&lt;ref name="MB165"/&gt; Halliday argues that the concept of Islamophobia unwittingly plays into the hands of extremists.&lt;ref name="Aldridge1"/&gt;

British writer and academic [[Kenan Malik]] believes that the charge of Islamophobia confuses discrimination against Muslims with criticism of Islam, and that it is used to silence critics and Muslim reformers. He writes that the extent to which Muslims are more vulnerable to [[social exclusion]] and attacks than other groups is frequently and allows for a culture of victimhood, where all failings are attributed to Islamophobia. Islamophobia is not a form of racism, in his view, because Islam is a belief system.&lt;ref name=Malik&gt;Malik, Kenan.[http://www.prospect-magazine.co.uk/article_details.php?id=6679 "Islamophobia Myth"]{{dead link|date=October 2010}}, Prospect, February 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; This analysis is criticized by [[Inayat Bunglawala]] from the [[Muslim Council of Britain]] and Abdul Wahid from the [[Islamism|Islamist]] group [[Hizb ut-Tahrir]].&lt;ref name=Bunglawala&gt;Bunglawala, Inayat &amp; Wahid, Abdul. [http://www.prospect-magazine.co.uk/pdfarticle.php?id=6764 "Is Islamophobia a Myth?"]{{dead link|date=October 2010}}, ''Prospect Magazine'', March 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; Bunglawala writes that Malik's argument is limited to overt acts of violence against Muslims, without recognizing less overt forms of prejudice or discrimination. By ignoring non-violent examples of Islamophobia, Malik's commentary "makes a mockery of victims of prejudice by pretending they have not been discriminated against," according to Bunglawala.&lt;ref name=Bunglawala/&gt;

In the wake of the [[Jyllands-Posten Muhammad cartoons controversy]], a group of 12 writers signed a statement in the French weekly satirical newspaper ''[[Charlie Hebdo]]'' in March 2006, warning against the use of the term Islamophobia to prevent criticism of "[[Islamic totalitarianism]]". The novelist [[Salman Rushdie]] was among these signatories.&lt;ref name=autogenerated2&gt;[[Salman Rushdie|Rushdie, Salman]] ''et al.'' [http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/4764730.stm "Writers' statement on cartoons"], BBC News, March 1, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; These views are shared by Dutch law professor [[Afshin Ellian]].&lt;ref name="Ellian"&gt;[[Afshin Ellian|Ellian, Afshin]]. [http://kvc.minbuza.nl/uk/current/2006/february/ellian.html "Stop Capitulating to Threats"]{{dead link|date=October 2010}}, February 2006&lt;/ref&gt; Critics cite the case of British journalist [[Polly Toynbee]], who was nominated in May 2003 for the title of "Most Islamophobic Media Personality of the Year" at the 'Annual Islamophobia Awards' overseen by the [[Islamic Human Rights Commission]], for claiming that Islam "... imposes harsh regimes that deny the most [[Human rights|basic human rights]]."&lt;ref name=Toynbee&gt;Toynbee, Polly. [http://www.guardian.co.uk/Columnists/Column/0,,563618,00.html "Last chance to speak out"]{{dead link|date=October 2010}}, ''The Guardian'', October 5, 2001.&lt;/ref&gt;

In an article called "Fighting Islamophobia: A Response to Critics", Assistant Professor [[Deepa Kumar]] writes that the modern-day demonization of Arabs and Muslims by US politicians and others is racist and Islamophobic, and employed in support of an unjust war. About the public impact of this rhetoric, she says that "One of the consequences of the relentless attacks on Islam and Muslims by politicians and the media is that Islamophobic sentiment is on the rise." She also chides some "people on the left" for using the same "Islamophobic logic as the Bush regime". She concludes with the statement "At times like this, people of conscience need to organize and speak out against Islamophobia."&lt;ref name="Fighting Islamophobia"&gt;[http://mrzine.monthlyreview.org/kumar030406.html Fighting Islamophobia: A Response to Critics] – Deepa Kumar, MRZine, February 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Johann Hari]] of ''[[The Independent]]'' has criticized the use of the term by organizations like [[Islamophobia Watch]], arguing that [[Liberal movements within Islam|liberal Muslims]] interested in reform are left unsupported because people fear being accused of Islamophobia.&lt;ref name=Hari&gt;He writes: "If Muslim women and Muslim gays are going to have any kind of decent life, the [Muslim] liberals need to receive solidarity and support – but slap-dash charges of Islamophobia intimidate people who could offer it ... While Islamophobia Watch talk about defending Muslims, they end up defending the nastiest and most right-wing part of the [[Ummah|Muslim community]] – the ones who are oppressing and killing the rest."- Hari, Johann. [http://www.johannhari.com/archive/article.php?id=897 "Don't call me an Islamophobe"], June 6, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; Writing in the [[New Humanist]], philosopher [[Piers Benn]] suggests that people who fear the rise of Islamophobia foster an environment "not intellectually or morally healthy", to the point that what he calls "Islamophobia-phobia" can undermine "critical scrutiny of Islam as somehow impolite, or ignorant of the religion's true nature."&lt;ref name=Benn&gt;[http://newhumanist.org.uk/524 "On Islamophobia-phobia"].&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[The New Criterion]]'' editor [[Roger Kimball]] argues that the word "Islamophobia" is a misnomer. "A phobia describes an [[Phobia|irrational fear]], and it is axiomatic that fearing the effects of radical Islam is not irrational, but on the contrary very well-founded indeed, so that if you want to speak of a legitimate phobia... ...we should speak instead of Islamophobia-phobia, the fear of and revulsion towards Islamophobia."&lt;ref name=Kimball&gt;Kimball, Roger. [http://web.archive.org/web/20060103053941/http://www.newcriterion.com/archives/24/01/after-the-suicide/ "After the suicide of the West"], January 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Neuroscientist]] and author [[Sam Harris (author)|Sam Harris]] has openly criticized the term Islamophobia in an article stating:&lt;ref&gt;http://www.thedailybeast.com/blogs-and-stories/2010-08-13/ground-zero-mosque/3/&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;''There is no such thing as Islamophobia. Bigotry and racism exist, of course—and they are evils that all well-intentioned people must oppose. And prejudice against Muslims or Arabs, purely because of the accident of their birth, is despicable. But like all religions, Islam is a system of ideas and practices. And it is not a form of bigotry or racism to observe that the specific tenets of the faith pose a special threat to civil society. Nor is it a sign of intolerance to notice when people are simply not being honest about what they and their co-religionists believe.''&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==Contrasting views of Islam==
The Runnymede report contrasted "open" and "closed" views of Islam, and stated that the following eight "closed" views are equated with Islamophobia:

:#Islam is seen as a monolithic bloc, static and unresponsive to change.
:#It is seen as separate and "other." It does not have values in common with other cultures, is not affected by them and does not influence them.
:#It is seen as inferior to the West. It is seen as barbaric, irrational, primitive, and [[sexist]].
:#It is seen as violent, aggressive, threatening, supportive of [[terrorism]], and engaged in a [[clash of civilizations]].
:#It is seen as a political [[ideology]], used for political or military advantage.
:#Criticisms made of "the West" by Muslims are rejected out of hand.
:#Hostility towards Islam is used to justify discriminatory practices towards Muslims and exclusion of Muslims from mainstream society.
:#Anti-Muslim hostility is seen as natural and normal.&lt;ref name=Runnymede1997&gt;{{PDFlink|[http://www.runnymedetrust.org/uploads/publications/pdfs/islamophobia.pdf "Islamophobia: A Challenge for Us All"]|69.7&amp;nbsp;KB}}, ''Runnymede Trust'', 1997.&lt;/ref&gt;

These "closed" views are contrasted, in the report, with "open" views on Islam which, while founded on respect for Islam, permit legitimate disagreement, dialogue and critique.&lt;ref&gt;Benn; Jawad (2004) p. 162&lt;/ref&gt; According to Benn and Jawad, The Runnymede Trust notes that anti-Muslim discourse is increasingly seen as respectable, providing examples on how hostility towards Islam and Muslims is accepted as normal, even among those who may actively challenge other prevalent forms of discrimination.&lt;ref name="Brill165"&gt;Benn; Jawad (2004) p. 165&lt;/ref&gt;

In some societies, Islamophobia has materialized due to the portrayal of Islam and Muslims as the national "[[Other]]", where exclusion and discrimination occurs on the basis of their religion and civilization which differs with national tradition and identity. Examples include Pakistani and Algerian migrants in Britain and France respectively.&lt;ref&gt;See:
*Encyclopedia of Race and Ethnic studies, p. 216
*Miles; Brown (2003) p. 163&lt;/ref&gt; This sentiment, according to Malcolm Brown and  Robert Miles, significantly interacts with [[racism]], although Islamophobia itself is not racism.&lt;ref&gt;Miles; Brown (2003) p. 163, 164&lt;/ref&gt; The publication "''Social Work and Minorities: European Perspectives''" describes Islamophobia as the new form of racism in Europe,&lt;ref&gt;Johnson; Soydan; Williams (1998) p. 182&lt;/ref&gt; arguing that "Islamophobia is as much a form of racism as [[anti-semitism]], a term more commonly encountered in Europe as a sibling of racism, xenophobia and Intolerance."&lt;ref&gt;Johnson; Soydan; Williams (1998) p. xxii&lt;/ref&gt;

Brown and Miles write that another feature of Islamophobic discourse is to amalgamate nationality (i.e. Arab), religion (Islam), and politics (terrorism, fundamentalism) — while most other religions are not associated with terrorism, or even "ethnic or national distinctiveness."&lt;ref name = "Brown-p163"&gt;Miles; Brown (2003) p. 163&lt;/ref&gt; They feel that "many of the stereotypes and misinformation that contribute to the articulation of Islamophobia are rooted in a particular perception of Islam", such as the notion that Islam promotes terrorism; especially prevalent after the [[September 11, 2001 attacks]].&lt;ref&gt;Miles; Brown (2003) p. 166&lt;/ref&gt;

===Media===
According to Elizabeth Poole in the  ''Encyclopedia of Race and Ethnic studies'', the media has been criticized for perpetrating Islamophobia. She cites a case study examining a sample of articles in the British press from between 1994 and 2004, which concluded that Muslim viewpoints were underrepresented and that issues involving Muslims usually depicted them in a negative light. Such portrayals, according to Poole, include the depiction of Islam and Muslims as a threat to Western security and values.&lt;ref&gt;Encyclopedia of Race and Ethnic studies, p. 217&lt;/ref&gt; Benn and Jawad write that hostility towards Islam and Muslims are "closely linked to media portrayals of Islam as barbaric, irrational, primitive and sexist."&lt;ref name="Brill165"/&gt; Egorova and Tudor cite European researchers in suggesting that expressions used in the media such as "Islamic terrorism", "Islamic bombs" and "violent Islam" have resulted in a negative perception of Islam.&lt;ref&gt;See Egorova; Tudor (2003) pp. 2–3, which cites the conclusions of Marquina and Rebolledo in: "A. Marquina, V. G. Rebolledo, ‘The Dialogue between the European Union and the Islamic World’ in Interreligious Dialogues: Christians, Jews, Muslims, Annals of the European Academy of Sciences and Arts, v. 24, no. 10, Austria, 2000, pp. 166–8. "&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2008 [[Fairness and Accuracy in Reporting]] published a study "Smearcasting, How Islamophobes Spread Bigotry, Fear and Misinformation." It described as bigoted against Islam authors [[Bruce Bawer]] and [[Robert Spencer (author)|Robert Spencer]], television and radio talk show hosts [[Sean Hannity]], [[Glenn Beck]] and [[Michael Savage (commentator)|Michael Savage]], political commentators [[David Horowitz]], [[Alan Dershowitz]] and [[Daniel Pipes]] and televangelist [[Pat Robertson]], among others.&lt;ref&gt;Steve Rendall and Isabel Macdonald, [http://www.fair.org/index.php?page=3648 Making Islamophobia Mainstream; How Muslim-bashers broadcast their bigotry], summary of [[Fairness and Accuracy in Reporting]] report, at its website, November/December 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

There have been several initiatives, based upon the sixty recommendations listed in the Runnymede Trust's report, aimed at increasing Muslim participation in media and politics. Soon after the release of the Runnymede report, the [[Muslim Council of Britain]] was formed to serve as an umbrella body aiming to "represent Muslims in the public sphere, to lobby government and other institutions." The "[[Forum Against Islamophobia and Racism]]" (FAIR) was also established, designed to monitor coverage in the media and establish dialogue with media organizations. Following the attacks of September 11, the [[Islam Awareness Week]] and the "''Best of British Islam Festival''" were introduced to improve community relations and raise awareness about Islam.&lt;ref&gt;Encyclopedia of Race and Ethnic studies, p. 218&lt;/ref&gt;

==Trends==
Islamophobia has become a topic of increasing sociological and political importance.&lt;ref name = "Brown-p163"/&gt; According to Benn and Jawad, Islamophobia has increased since [[Ayatollah Khomeini]]'s denouncement of [[Salman Rushdie]]'s "''[[The Satanic Verses]]''" and the September 11 attacks.&lt;ref&gt;Benn; Jawad (2004) p. 111&lt;/ref&gt; [[Anthropologist]] Steven Vertovec writes that the purported growth in Islamophobia may be associated with increased Muslim presence in society and successes.&lt;ref name="Vertovec" /&gt; He suggests a [[Vicious circle|circular model]], where increased hostility towards Islam and Muslims results in governmental countermeasures such as institutional guidelines and changes to legislation, which itself may fuel further Islamophobia due to increased accommodation for Muslims in public life. Vertovec concludes: "As the public sphere shifts to provide a more prominent place for Muslims, Islamophobic tendencies may amplify."&lt;ref name="Vertovec" /&gt;
[[File:Ground Zero Marine Protest Muslim Bomb.jpg|thumb|left|A mannequin symbolizing a Muslim in a [[keffiyeh]], strapped to a "Made in the USA" bomb display at a protest of [[Park51]] in [[New York City]].]]
Patel, Humphries, and Naik claim that "Islamophobia has always been present in Western countries and cultures. In the last two decades, it has become accentuated, explicit and extreme."&lt;ref&gt;Naina Patel, Beth Humphries and Don Naik, "The 3 Rs in social work; Religion,‘race’ and racism in Europe", in Johnson; Soydan; Williams (1998) pp. 197–198&lt;/ref&gt; However, Vertovec states that some have observed that Islamophobia has not necessarily escalated in the past decades, but that there has been increased public scrutiny of it.&lt;ref name="Vertovec" /&gt; According to Abduljalil Sajid, one of the members of the Runnymede Trust's Commission on British Muslims and Islamophobia, "Islamophobias" have existed in varying strains throughout history, with each version possessing its own distinct features as well as similarities or adaptations from others.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Islamophobia: A new word for an old fear |url=http://www.wcrp.be/articles/Sajid9-11-04.htm |author=Imam Dr Abduljalil Sajid |accessdate=2007-08-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; An observatory report on Islamophobia by the [[Organisation of Islamic Cooperation|Organisation of the Islamic Conference]] similarly states that Islamophobia has existed for as long as Islam itself.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oic-oci.org/oicnew/is11/english/Islamophobia-rep-en.pdf 1st OIC Observatory Report on Islamophobia]{{dead link|date=October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===EUMC reports===
The largest project monitoring Islamophobia was undertaken following 9/11 by the EU watchdog, [[European Monitoring Centre on Racism and Xenophobia]] (EUMC). Their May 2002 report "Summary report on Islamophobia in the EU after 11 September 2001", written by [[Chris Allen (UK)|Chris Allen]] and Jorgen S. Nielsen of the [[University of Birmingham]], was based on 75 reports — 15 from each EU member nation.&lt;ref name="EUMCNews"&gt;{{Cite news|title=EUMC presents reports on Discrimination and Islamophobia in the EU |publisher="European Monitoring Centre on Racism and Xenophobia media release" |url=http://www.eumc.europa.eu/eumc/index.php?fuseaction=content.dsp_cat_content&amp;catid=43d8bc25bc89d&amp;contentid=4582ddc822d41 |date=2006-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=EUMC&gt;Allen, Chris and Nielsen, Jorgen S. [http://www.raxen.eumc.eu.int/1/webmill.php?id=32813&amp;ditem=3101&amp;lin=detail "Summary report on Islamophobia in the EU after 11 September 2001"], EUMC, May, 2002.&lt;/ref&gt; The report highlighted the regularity with which ordinary Muslims became targets for abusive and sometimes violent retaliatory attacks after 9/11. Despite localized differences within each member nation, the recurrence of attacks on recognizable and visible traits of Islam and Muslims was the report's most significant finding. Incidents consisted of verbal abuse, blaming all Muslims for [[List of terrorist incidents|terrorism]], forcibly removing women's [[hijab]]s, spitting on Muslims, calling children "[[Osama bin Laden|Usama]]", and random assaults. Muslims have been hospitalized and on one occasion paralyzed.&lt;ref name=EUMC/&gt; The report also discussed the portrayal of Muslims in the media. Inherent negativity, stereotypical images, fantastical representations, and exaggerated caricatures were all identified. The report concluded that "a greater receptivity towards anti-Muslim and other xenophobic ideas and sentiments has, and may well continue, to become more tolerated."&lt;ref name=EUMC/&gt;

The EUMC has since released a number of publications related to Islamophobia, including "''The Fight against Antisemitism and Islamophobia: Bringing Communities together (European Round Tables Meetings)''" (2003) and "''Muslims in the European Union: Discrimination and Islamophobia''" (2006).&lt;ref&gt;[http://fra.europa.eu/fra/index.php?fuseaction=content.dsp_cat_content&amp;catid=1 EUMC website – Publications] {{accessdate|2007-11-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Islamophobic incidents==
{{main|List of Islamophobic incidents}}
{{See also|Persecution of Muslims}}

==Efforts against Islamophobia==
There have been efforts against Islamophobia by many organizations in many countries; some of these are detailed below.
* In 2006 the [[Organisation of Islamic Cooperation|Organisation of the Islamic Conference]] (OIC) set up an observatory on Islamophobia which will monitor and document activities perceived as Islamophobic around the world.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.islamonline.com/cgi-bin/news_service/world_full_story.asp?service_id=2398 "OIC set up observatory on Islamophobia"]{{dead link|date=October 2010}} ''IslamOnline'', May 9, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;
* A [[Talk radio|radio talk show]] host from 630 [[WMAL (AM)|WMAL]] on November 26, 2006 exposed the prevalence of Islamophobia by seeming to advocate a government program to force all Muslims to wear "identifying markers."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=In U.S., fear and distrust of Muslims runs deep |author=Bernd Debusmann |publisher=Reuters|date=December 1, 9:05|url=http://www.asiamedia.ucla.edu/article.asp?parentid=58909 |accessdate=December 16, 2006 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The hoax was revealed at the end of the program. See [[Jerry Klein’s 2006 Islamophobia Radio Experiment]] for more details.
* During the accession talks regarding Turkey's possible entry to the EU, then [[Prime Minister of the Netherlands|Prime Minister of Holland]], [[Jan Peter Balkenende]], said Islamophobia must not affect the possibility of Turkey's entry to the [[European Union]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/3913335.stm Islam 'must not cloud Turkey bid'] BBC -Wednesday, 21 July 2004&lt;/ref&gt;
* 50,000 people signed a petition urging [[French President]] [[Jacques Chirac]] to "consider Islamophobia as a new form of racism, punishable by law. The statement reads that the publishing of insulting cartoons of [[Muhammad]] by the French press hurt and offended the feelings of [[French Muslim]]s."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.adnki.com/index_2Level_English.php?cat=Religion&amp;loid=8.0.306056413&amp;par= FRANCE: 50,000 SIGN UP AGAINST ISLAMOPHOBIA]{{dead link|date=October 2010}} – ADN Kronos – June 2, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;
* In [[London Borough of Tower Hamlets|Tower Hamlets]], a densely populated area in [[London]] with a large Muslim community, a crime reporting scheme called "Islamophobia – Don't Suffer in Silence" has been set up which police hope will raise awareness of Islamophobia and help them to understand the extent of the problem.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/england/london/4017617.stm Scheme to fight faith hate crimes] BBC – Wednesday, 17 November 2004&lt;/ref&gt;
* The British [[National Union of Teachers]] (NUT) has issued guidance to teachers in the union advising that teachers have to "Challenge Islamophobia", and that they have a "crucial role" to play in helping to "dispel myths about Muslim communities."&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/education/4687417.stm Teaching tolerance amid tension] BBC – Friday, 15 July 2005&lt;/ref&gt;
* Following an Islamist demonstration outside the Danish Embassy in London organized by the [[Al Ghurabaa]] organization in response to the [[Jyllands-Posten Muhammad cartoons controversy]], the [[Muslim Association of Britain]] organized a peaceful rally in [[Trafalgar Square]]. Organizers made available placards and [[T-shirt]]s bearing the rally's official slogan, the phrase, "United against Islamophobia, united against incitement."&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/help/3681938.stm Prayer mats lined the pavements] BBC – Saturday, 11 February 2006&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/cartoonprotests/story/0,,1708080,00.html Muslims fly flag for peaceful protest against cartoons] The Guardian – Sunday February 12, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;
* Following the [[July 7 bombings]], the British government set up a number of initiatives aimed at combating Islamophobia, including the "National Forum against extremism and Islamophobia".&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/4423668.stm Call for Muslim scholars to tour] BBC – Thursday, 10 November 2005&lt;/ref&gt; There was also plans by the British government to ban incitement to "religious hatred", however, this failed to get through the [[British House of Commons|House of Commons]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/programmes/bbc_parliament/4652669.stm Racial and Religious Hatred Bill] BBC – Friday, 27 January 2006&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/politics/4668266.stm Religious hatred: How MPs voted] BBC – Wednesday, 1 February 2006&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[The Hashemite Kingdom of Jordan]] issued a call in 1999 to world leaders to combat Islamophobia.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/453060.stm Jordan: Stop attacking Islam] BBC – Tuesday, September 21, 1999&lt;/ref&gt; Abdel-Elah Khatib, the Jordanian [[foreign minister]] said "The [[international community]] must consider how to confront this phenomenon of Islamophobia in order to prevent its proliferation".
* The [[Muslim Council of Britain]] ([[MCB]]) and the [[Trades Union Congress]] ([[TUC]]) held a seminar on how to combat Islamophobia.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.kuna.net.kw/Home/Story.aspx?Language=en&amp;DSNO=970534 Kuwait News Agency: Drive to combat Islamophobia]{{dead link|date=October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;


==See also==

* [[Religious intolerance]]
* [[Religious persecution]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist|2}}

==References==
* {{Cite encyclopedia |editor=Cashmore, E | encyclopedia=Encyclopedia of Race and Ethnic Studies |year=2003 |publisher=Routledge}}
* {{Cite book|last=Benn |first=T. |  coauthors=Jawad, H. |title=Muslim Women in the United Kingdom and Beyond: Experiences and Images |year=2004 |publisher=[[Brill Publishers]] |isbn=9004125817}}
*{{Cite book|last=Egorova |first=Y. |  coauthors=Parfitt, T. |title=Jews, Muslims, and Mass Media: Mediating the 'Other' |year=2003 |publisher=Routledge Curzon |location=London |isbn=0415318394}}
*{{Cite book|last=Haddad |first=Y. |  title=Muslims in the West: From Sojourners to Citizens |year=2002 |publisher=Oxford University Press |location=Oxford |isbn=0195148053}}
* {{Cite book|last=Johnson |first=M. R. D. |  coauthors=Soydan, H; Williams, C. |title=Social Work and Minorities: European Perspectives |location=London; New York |year=1998 |publisher=Routledge |isbn=0415169623}}
* {{Cite book|last=Miles |first=R. |  coauthors=Brown, M. |title=Racism |year=2003 |location=London; New York |publisher=Routledge |isbn=0415296765}}

===Further reading===
* Allen, Chris. ''Islamophobia'' (Ashgate Publishing Company; 2011)
*{{Cite book|last=Abbas |first= Tahir |title=Muslim Britain: Communities Under Pressure |year=2005 |publisher=Zed |isbn=978-1842774496}}
*{{Cite book|last=van Driel |first=B. |title=Confronting Islamophobia In Educational Practice |year=2004 |publisher=Trentham Books |isbn=1858563402}}
*{{Cite book|last=Gottschalk |first=P. |coauthors=Greenberg, G. |title=Islamophobia: Making Muslims the Enemy |year=2007 |publisher=Rowman &amp; Littlefield publishers |location=Lanham |isbn=978-0742552869}}
*{{Cite book|last=Greaves |first=R. |title=Islam and the West Post 9/11 |year=2004 |publisher=Ashgate publishing Ltd|isbn=0754650057}}
*Kaplan, Jeffrey (2006). ''Islamophobia in America?: September 11 and Islamophobic Hate Crime'', Terrorism and Political Violence (Routledge), 18:1, 1–33.
* Kincheloe, Joe L. and Shirley R. Steinberg (2004).The Miseducation of the West: How the Schools and Media Distort Our Understanding of Islam. Westport, Connecticut: Praeger Press. (Arabic Edition, 2005).
* Konrad, Felix: [http://nbn-resolving.de/urn:nbn:de:0159-2011020147 ''From the "Turkish Menace" to Exoticism and Orientalism: Islam as Antithesis of Europe (1453–1914)?''], [[European History Online]], Mainz: [[Institute of European History]], 2011, retrieved: June 22, 2011.
*Pynting, Scott; Mason, Victoria (2007). ''The resistible rise of Islamophobia: Anti-Muslim racism in the UK and Australia before 11 September 2001''. Journal of Sociology, The Australian Sociological Association. 43(1): 61–86.
*{{Cite book|last=Richardson|first=John E.|title=(Mis)representing Islam: the racism and rhetoric of British broadsheet newspapers|publisher=[[John Benjamins Publishing Company]]|year=2004|isbn=9027226997|url=http://books.google.com/?id=WanqiF2XULsC&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q=|postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}}
* Shryock, Andrew, ed. ''Islamophobia/Islamophilia: Beyond the Politics of Enemy and Friend'' (Indiana University Press; 2010) 250 pages; essays on Islamophobia past and present; topics include the "neo-Orientalism" of three Muslim commentators today: Ayaan Hirsi Ali, Reza Aslan, and Irshad Manji.
*Tausch, Arno with Christian Bischof, Tomaz Kastrun and Karl Mueller (2007), ‘'Against Islamophobia: Muslim Communities, Social Exclusion and the Lisbon Process in Europe'’ Hauppauge, N.Y.: Nova Science Publishers
*Tausch, Arno with Christian Bischof, and Karl Mueller (2007), "Muslim Calvinism”, internal security and the Lisbon process in Europe Amsterdam: Rozenberg Publishers
* Tausch, Arno (2007), Against Islamophobia. Quantitative analyses of global terrorism, world political cycles and center periphery structures Hauppauge, N.Y.: Nova Science Publishers
*{{Cite book|last=Quraishi |first=M. |title=Muslims and Crime: A Comparative Study |year=2005 |publisher=Ashgate publishing Ltd|isbn=0-7546-4233-X}}
*{{Cite book|last=Ramadan |first=T. |title=Western Muslims and the Future of Islam |year=2004 |publisher=Oxford University Press |location=Oxford |isbn=0-19-517111-X}}
* Zuquete, Jose Pedro (2008), The European extreme-right and Islam: New directions, [http://www.citeulike.org/journal/routledg-cjpi['''Journal of Political Ideologies'''&amp;#93;]

==External links==
{{Sister project links}}
{{External links|date=August 2010}}
* [http://www.islamophobia.org/ Islamophobia.org]
* [http://www.reuters.com/article/pressRelease/idUS198159+09-Sep-2009+PRN20090909 Among U.S. Religious Groups, Muslims Seen as Facing More Discrimination]
* [http://www.islamawareness.net/Islamophobia/ "Islamophobia"], ''Islamicawareness.net''
* [http://www.islamophobia-watch.com/ Islamophobia Watch]
* [http://www.smearcasting.com/ Smearcasters]
* [http://www.guardian.co.uk/uk_news/story/0,,1997888,00.html "From Aladdin to Lost Ark, Muslims get angry at 'bad guy' film images"] -[[The Guardian]], 25 January 2007
* [http://www.sevenoaksmag.com/features/cupehumanrights.html Speech against Islamophobia and racism at CUPE National Conference in Vancouver, Canada]
* [http://islamonline.net/English/artculture/2005/01/article08.shtml Muslims and Islam in European History Textbooks]
* [http://www.keralanext.com/news/?id=1078945 Grant Bangladeshi Hindu migrants refugee status, but deport Bangladeshi Muslims: Rajnath Singh]{{dead link|date=October 2010}}
* [http://www.eyetopic.co.uk/Against_Islamophobia/index.htm "Rally against incitement and Islamophobia in London"], ''[[eyetopic.co.uk]]'', February 11, 2006.
* [[Chris Allen (UK)]] [http://www.chris-allen.co.uk/ Islamophobia resources: writing, articles &amp; publications]
* Dr. Louay Safi's [http://aninsight.org/labels/Islamophobia.html Articles on Islamophobia]
* Brooks, James. [http://www.islamonline.net/English/Views/2003/05/article11.shtml "Deep roots of Islamophobia]{{dead link|date=October 2010}} Islamonline.net.
* Deane, Claudia and Fears, Darryl. [http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2006/03/08/AR2006030802221.html Negative Perception Of Islam Increasing], ''The Washington Post'', March 9, 2006.
* [[Khaled Abou Al-Fadl|El Fadl, Khaled Abou]]. [http://www.scholarofthehouse.org/onrebi.html "On revising bigotry"], chapter from '' The Conference on the Books: The Search for Beauty in Islam'', ''Scholars of the House''.
* [[Muriel Gray|Gray, Muriel]]. [http://www.sundayherald.com/53959 "How can we have respect for Islam when we are too fearful to criticise it?"]{{dead link|date=October 2010}}, ''The Glasgow Herald'', February 5, 2006.
* Hassan, Fardusa. [http://www.guardian.co.uk/race/story/0,,1862329,00.html "Beauty queen enters Islamophobia debate"], ''The Guardian'', August 31, 2006.
* Hassan, Ghali. [http://www.uruknet.info/?p=m20398&amp;l=i&amp;size=1&amp;hd=0 The Road to the Muslim Holocaust], ''Globalresearch.ca'', February 7, 2006.
* Khan, Ali. [http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=935319 The Essentialist Terrorist] (how puritanical Islam is portrayed as essentially violent).
* [[Norman Lamont (1942)|Lamont, Norman]]. [http://www.telegraph.co.uk/opinion/main.jhtml?xml=/opinion/2002/05/08/do0801.xml "Down with multiculturalism, book-burning and fatwas"], ''The Daily Telegraph'', May 8, 2002.
* Marud, Abdal-Hakim. [http://www.masud.co.uk/ISLAM/ahm/right.htm "Muslims and the European Right"], ''Masud.co.uk'', first delivered as a lecture on April 30, 2000.
* [[Brigitte L. Nacos|Nacos, Brigitte L.]], ''Fueling Our Fears: Stereotyping, Media Coverage, and Public Opinion of Muslim Americans''. 2006
* O'Keefe, Derrick. [http://www.sevenoaksmag.com/commentary/macleans.html Maclean's magazine goes over-the-top with racist cover story], ''Seven Oaks Magazine'', October 27, 2006.
* [[Daniel Pipes|Pipes, Daniel]]. [http://www.danielpipes.org/article/3075 "Islamophobia?"], ''New York Sun'', October 25, 2005.
* Ramji, Rubina. [http://www.unomaha.edu/jrf/Vol9No2/RamjiIslam.htm "From ''Navy Seals'' to ''The Siege'': Getting to Know the Muslim Terrorist, Hollywood Style"] ''The Journal of Religion and Film'', Vol. 9, No.2, October 2005
* Riyanto, Geger. [http://www.thejakartapost.com/yesterdaydetail.asp?fileid=20061027.F04 "The Genealogy of today's Islamophobia"]{{dead link|date=October 2010}}, ''The Jakarta Post'', October 27, 2006.
* [[Walter Laqueur]]. [http://blog.oup.com/2006/10/the_origins_of_2/ The Origins of Fascism: Islamic Fascism, Islamophobia, Antisemitism], [[Oxford University Press]] blog.
* Barry Van, ''Confronting Islamophobia in Educational Practice'' ISBN 1-85856-340-2
* [[Stephen Castle|Castle, Stephen]]. [http://news.independent.co.uk/europe/article2084525.ece "Islamophobia takes a grip across Europe"], ''[[The Independent]]'', December 18, 2006.
* Responses to Islamophobia: [http://www.rissc.jo/index.php/responses-to-islamophobia.html www.rissc.jo]
{{Islam topics|state=collapsed}}
{{Discrimination}}
{{Theology}}

[[Category:Islam-related controversies]]
[[Category:Anti-Islam]]
[[Category:Political neologisms]]

[[ar:إسلاموفوبيا]]
[[be-x-old:Антыісламізм]]
[[bg:Ислямофобия]]
[[ca:Islamofòbia]]
[[cs:Islamofobie]]
[[cy:Islamoffobia]]
[[da:Islamofobi]]
[[de:Islamfeindlichkeit]]
[[el:Ισλαμοφοβία]]
[[es:Islamofobia]]
[[eo:Islamofobio]]
[[fa:اسلام‌هراسی]]
[[fr:Islamophobie]]
[[id:Islamofobia]]
[[it:Islamofobia]]
[[he:אסלאמופוביה]]
[[lv:Islāmfobija]]
[[ml:ഇസ്ലാമോഫോബിയ]]
[[arz:إسلاموفوبيا]]
[[ms:Islamofobia]]
[[nl:Islamofobie]]
[[ja:イスラム恐怖症]]
[[no:Islamofobi]]
[[uz:Islomofobiya]]
[[pl:Islamofobia]]
[[pt:Islamofobia]]
[[ro:Islamofobie]]
[[ru:Исламофобия]]
[[simple:Islamophobia]]
[[fi:Islamofobia]]
[[sv:Islamofobi]]
[[te:ఇస్లామోఫోబియా]]
[[tr:İslamofobi]]
[[zh:伊斯兰恐惧症]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>