<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20190818104344|911353096" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="38824009" pageid="38824009" ns="0" title="Feminist digital humanities"><revisions><rev timestamp="2019-10-01T17:04:20Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Feminist Digital Humanities''' is a more recent development in the field of [[Digital Humanities]] as a whole. Feminist Digital Humanities has risen partly due to recent criticism of the propensity of Digital Humanities to&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1pPscJX7I7Vvuc4YIBbd38nbWgIjp-0FiI5yZ1sxG6Vk/edit#gid=0|title=Women in DH|work=Google Docs|access-date=2018-11-08|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt; further patriarchal or hegemonic discourses in the Academy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| publisher= U of Minnesota P| editor= Matthew K. Gold |last=Liu|first=Alan|chapter=Where is Cultural Criticism in the Digital Humanities?|title= Debates in the Digital Humanities|location= Minneapolis | year= 2012|url=http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/30}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some of the research in feminist digital humanities centres on the exclusion of women from histories of technology&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| last=Chun|first=Wendy|title=On Software, or the Persistence of Visible Knowledge| journal= Grey Room| year= 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the use of technology to promote feminist scholarship. Feminist Digital Humanities emphasizes the role of women, feminists, and cyberfeminists in technology, overturning ideas such as “Men invented the Internet”, as written in a June 2012 New York Times article.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2012/06/03/technology/lawsuit-against-kleiner-perkins-is-shaking-silicon-valley.html|title=Lawsuit Shakes Foundation of a Man's World of Tech|date=3 June 2012|website=The New York Times}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A list&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1pPscJX7I7Vvuc4YIBbd38nbWgIjp-0FiI5yZ1sxG6Vk/edit#gid=0|title=Women in DH|work=Google Docs|access-date=2018-11-08|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt; of women in the digital humanities begun by [[Jacqueline Wernimont]] makes available a compendium of women working in the field.

==Objectives==
Media Theorist [[Lisa Nakamura]] notes that "[as] women of color acquire an increasing presence online, their particular interests which spring directly from gender and racial identifications, that is to say, those identities associated with a physical body off-line, are being addressed."&lt;ref&gt;Nakamura, Lisa. “Cybertyping and the Work of Race in the Age of Digital Reproduction.” New Media, Old Media. Eds. Wendy Hui Kyong Chun and Thomas Keenan. Routledge: New York, 2006.p321&lt;/ref&gt;  Likewise, [[Science, technology and society|Science and Technology Studies]] professor [[Donna Haraway]] has also pioneered specifically feminist approaches to the study of digital humanities.&lt;ref&gt;Wajcman, Judy. “Addressing Technological Change: The Challenge to Social Theory.” Society, Ethics and Technology. Eds. Morton E. Winston and Ralph D. Edelbach. Cengage Learning: 2011. Page 112.&lt;/ref&gt;

This intervention is notably crystallized in the work of [[FemTechNet]], "an activated network of scholars, artists, and students who work on, with, and at the borders of technology, science and feminism in a variety of fields including STS, Media and Visual Studies, Art, Women’s, Queer, and Ethnic Studies".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://femtechnet.newschool.edu/directories/ |title=Archived copy |access-date=2014-10-07 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20141026065848/http://femtechnet.newschool.edu/directories/ |archive-date=2014-10-26 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; FemTechNet has collaborated on a number of projects that reflect the aims of Feminist Digital Humanities, including Wikistorming, DOCC: Distributed Open Collaborative Course, and video dialogues. Their methods emphasize distribution through networks to connect diverse institutions, nations, and fields.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://femtechnet.newschool.edu/docc2013/ |title=Archived copy |access-date=2014-10-07 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20141003094412/http://femtechnet.newschool.edu/docc2013/ |archive-date=2014-10-03 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Professors of Digital Humanities, Bethany Nowviskie and Miriam Posner have blogged about the structures in place that have kept women from engaging in digital humanities. There have been efforts to increase the racial representations within the field as well. These feminist digital humanities projects include #transformDH, That Camp Theory, [[Critical code studies|Critical Code Studies]], and [[Crunk Feminist Collective]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.crunkfeministcollective.com/&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite article|last=Bailey| first= Moya Z.|title=All the Digital Humanists Are White, All the Nerds Are Men, but Some of Us Are Brave| journal=Journal of Digital Humanities| year=2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Black Girls Code]] is a project that has recently garnered attention, with founder [[Kimberly Bryant (technologist)|Kimberly Bryant]] receiving a Standing O-vation presented by Toyota and [[Oprah Winfrey]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| last=Shumaker | first=Laura|title= "Oprah gives San Francisco’s Kimberly Bryant a Standing O-vation"| journal=SFGate| year=2014|url=http://blog.sfgate.com/lshumaker/2014/11/17/oprah-gives-san-franciscos-kimberly-bryant-a-standing-o-vation/}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Archiving==
One goal of feminist literary scholars has been to increase the scope of women's literary works in visible archives. [http://orlando.cambridge.org/ The Orlando Project] and [[Women Writers Project|The Women Writers Project]] are two early projects that undertook the task of filling in the gaps that existed in literary history in the 1980s.&lt;ref name="Dig. Humanities"&gt;{{cite article|last=Wernimont | first=Jacqueline |title=Whence Feminism? Assessing Feminist Interventions in Digital Literary Archives | journal=Digital Humanities Quarterly | publisher=The Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations |year=2013 |url=http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/7/1/000156/000156.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; Both efforts sought to use the electronic format "to overcome the problems of inaccessibility and scarcity which had rendered women’s writing invisible for so long."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wwp.brown.edu/about/history/|title=WWP has moved|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Dig. Humanities" /&gt;
One critique of a content-oriented approach to combating the marginalization of women's literary works is that it's simply not enough to add content to a system that is built upon a patriarchal methodology. "Literary scholars who depend on archival or rare book materials still confront, whether they acknowledge it or not, the legacy of an institutional form through which patriarchal power exercised the authority to determine value, classification, and access."&lt;ref name="Dig. Humanities" /&gt;

==See also==
*[[Cyberfeminism]]
*[[Feminist technoscience|Feminist Technoscience]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{Feminist theory}}

[[Category:Digital humanities]]
[[Category:Feminism]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>