<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20071106234410|169720033" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="37476" pageid="37476" ns="0" title="Civil liberties"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-11-12T13:45:27Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[Image:Li-ber-ty.jpg|thumb|&amp;nbsp;|Broken Liberty: Istanbul Archaeology Museum.]]
'''Civil liberties''' is the name given to [[Freedom (political)|freedoms]] that completely protect the individual from government. Civil liberties set limits for government so that it can not abuse its power and interfere with the lives of its citizens. 

Common civil liberties include [[freedom of association]], [[freedom of assembly]], [[freedom of religion]], and [[freedom of speech]], and additionally, the right to [[due process]], to [[Right to a fair trial|fair trial]], to [[Right to bear arms|bear arms]] (as in the USA), and to [[privacy]]. 

The formal concept of civil liberties dates back to the [[Magna Carta]] of 1215 which in turn was based on pre-existing documents.

Republics or democracies such as the United States have a [[Constitution]], a [[bill of rights]] and similar constitutional documents that enumerate and seek to guarantee civil liberties.  Other states have enacted similar laws through a variety of legal means, including signing and ratifying or otherwise giving effect to key conventions such as the [[European Convention on Human Rights]] and the [[International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights]].  

It might be said that the protection of civil liberties is a key responsibility of all [[citizens]] of [[List of types of democracy|democratic states]], as distinct from [[Authoritarianism|authoritarian states]]. 

The existence of some claimed civil liberties is a matter of dispute, as are the extent of most civil liberties.  Controversial examples include [[reproductive rights]], [[same-sex marriage]], [[Gun politics|possession of guns/arms]], and the use of certain drugs. Another matter of debate is the suspension or alteration of certain civil liberties in times of [[war]] or [[state of emergency]], including whether and to what extent this should occur.

==Civil liberties by country==
The [[European Convention on Human Rights]], to which most European countries, including all of the [[European Union]], belong, enumerates a number of civil liberties and is of varying constitutional force in different European states. [[France]]'s [[1789]] [[Declaration of the Rights of Man and of the Citizen]] listed many civil liberties and is of constitutional force.

The [[Constitution of Canada]] includes the [[Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms]] which guarantees many of the same rights as the U.S. constitution, with the notable exceptions of protection against [[establishment of religion]]. However, the Charter does protect [[freedom of religion]].  The Charter also omits any mention of, or protection for, property.

The [[Constitution of Russian Federation| Constitution of Russian Federation]]  guarantees many of the same rights and civil liberties as U.S. except to bear arms, i.e.: freedom of speech, freedom of religion, freedom of association and assembly, freedom to choose language, to due process, to a fair trial, privacy, freedom to vote, right for education, etc.

The [[Constitution of the People's Republic of China| Constitution of People's Republic of China]] (apply to [[mainland China]] only, not to [[Hong Kong]], [[Macau]] and [[Taiwan]]) , especially its Fundamental Rights and Duties of Citizens, claims to protect  many civil liberties. See [[Civil liberties in the People's Republic of China]]

While the [[United Kingdom]] has no codified constitution, relying on a number of legal conventions and pieces of legislation, it is a signatory to the [[European Convention on Human Rights]] which covers both [[human rights]] and civil liberties.  The [[Human Rights Act 1998]] incorporates the great majority of Convention rights directly into UK law.

The [[United States Constitution]], especially its [[United States Bill of Rights|Bill of Rights]], protects many civil liberties. See [[Civil liberties in the United States]]

==See also==
*[[American Civil Liberties Union]]
*[[Bill of Rights Defense Committee]]
*[[Rutherford Institute]]
*[[Civil]]
*[[Privacy]]
*[[Teaching for social justice]]

==References==
*[[Alan Dershowitz|Dershowitz, Alan]].  [http://chronicle.com/free/v48/i05/05b00901.htm "Preserving Civil Liberties."]  ''Reflections on the Fractured Landscape,'' spec. sec. of ''[[Chronicle of Higher Education]]'', ''Chronicle Review'', [[September 28]], [[2001]].  Accessed [[August 11]], [[2006]].
*[[Jean Edward Smith|Smith, Jean Edward]], and Herbert M. Levine.  ''Civil Liberties and Civil Rights Debated''.  Englewood Cliffs, NJ: Prentice Hall, 1988.

==External links==
&lt;!--This list is sorted alphabetically by the title of the site. If you are adding a link, please put it in the correct place in the list--&gt;
{{wikiquote|Civil Liberties}}
*[http://civilliberty.about.com/ About.com: Civil Liberties]
*[http://www.aclu.org/ American Civil Liberties Union]
*[http://www.bordc.org/ Bill of Rights Defense Committee]
*[http://www.cato.org/current/civil-liberties/index.html The Cato Institute: Civil Liberties]
*[http://www.usdoj.gov/pclo/ USDOJ: Privacy and Civil Liberties Office]
*[http://www.cmcla.org Canadian Muslim Civil Liberties Association]
*[http://www.bccla.org British Columbia Civil Liberties Association]
*[http://www.constitution.ru/en/10003000-03.htm Rights, Civil Liberties and Freedoms in Russia]
*[http://www.liberty-human-rights.org.uk/ Liberty: a UK based Civil Rights organisation]
*[http://www.equalityhumanrights.com Equality and Human Rights Commission: A UK Quango promoting Human and Civil Rights] 
*[http://www.statewatch.org/ Statewatch watches the European Union on Civil Liberties]

{{enlightenment}}

[[Category:Civil liberties| ]]
[[Category:Social philosophy]]
[[Category:Political philosophy]]

[[bg:Граждански свободи]]
[[fr:Libertés publiques]]
[[no:Borgerfriheter]]
[[sr:Грађанске слободе]]
[[zh:公民自由]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>