<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20221121091202|1123024521" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="72159018" pageid="72159018" ns="0" title="Social determinants of mental health"><revisions><rev timestamp="2022-11-26T12:43:18Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[File:SDOH model.gif|thumb|Social determinants of mental health include social, economic, and environmental factors]]The '''social determinants of mental health''' (SDOMH) are societal problems that disrupt mental health, increase risk of mental illness among certain groups, and worsen outcomes for individuals with mental illnesses.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Shim |first1=Ruth S. |last2=Compton |first2=Michael T. |date=January 2020 |title=The Social Determinants of Mental Health: Psychiatrists' Roles in Addressing Discrimination and Food Insecurity |journal=FOCUS |language=en |volume=18 |issue=1 |pages=25–30 |doi=10.1176/appi.focus.20190035 |pmid=32047394 |pmc=7011221 |issn=1541-4094}}&lt;/ref&gt; Much like the [[social determinants of health]] (SDOH), SDOMH include the non-medical factors that play a role in the likelihood and severity of health outcomes, such as income levels, education attainment, access to housing, and social inclusion.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Social determinants of health |url=https://www.who.int/health-topics/social-determinants-of-health |access-date=2022-11-01 |website=www.who.int |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; Disparities in mental health outcomes are a result of a multitude of factors and social determinants, including fixed characteristics on an individual level – such as age, gender, race/ethnicity, and sexual orientation – and environmental factors that stem from social and economic inequalities – such as inadequate access to proper food, housing, and transportation, and exposure to pollution.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=General |first=Office of the Surgeon |date=2021-12-07 |title=U.S. Surgeon General Issues Advisory on Youth Mental Health Crisis Further Exposed by COVID-19 Pandemic |url=https://www.hhs.gov/about/news/2021/12/07/us-surgeon-general-issues-advisory-on-youth-mental-health-crisis-further-exposed-by-covid-19-pandemic.html |access-date=2022-11-01 |website=HHS.gov |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;
== Definitions ==
[[File:Mental Health Word Cloud.svg|thumb|Mental health describes emotional, psychological, and social well-being ]]
[[Mental health]], as defined by the CDC, encompasses individuals' emotional, psychological, and social well-being, while the most common mental disorders include [[Anxiety disorder|anxiety-disorders]] such as generalized anxiety disorder, social anxiety, and panic disorder; [[Depression (mood)|depression]]; and [[Post-traumatic stress disorder|post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD)]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |date=2021-11-23 |title=About Mental Health |url=https://www.cdc.gov/mentalhealth/learn/index.htm |access-date=2022-11-10 |website=www.cdc.gov |language=en-us}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=A Look at The Three Most Common Mental Illnesses |url=https://www.inspirahealthnetwork.org/news/look-three-most-common-mental-illnesses |access-date=2022-11-10 |website=https://www.inspirahealthnetwork.org/ |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The concept of social determinants stems from the life course approach. It draws from theories that explain the social, economic, environmental, and physical patterns that result in health disparities and vary across different stages of life (e.g. prenatal, early years, working age, and older ages).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Jones |first1=Nancy L. |last2=Gilman |first2=Stephen E. |last3=Cheng |first3=Tina L. |last4=Drury |first4=Stacy S. |last5=Hill |first5=Carl V. |last6=Geronimus |first6=Arline T. |date=January 2019 |title=Life Course Approaches to the Causes of Health Disparities |journal=American Journal of Public Health |language=en |volume=109 |issue=S1 |pages=S48–S55 |doi=10.2105/AJPH.2018.304738 |pmid=30699022 |pmc=6356123 |issn=0090-0036}}&lt;/ref&gt; Identifying the social and structural determinants of mental health, in addition to individual determinants, enables policy makers to promote mental health and reduce risk of illness by designing appropriate interventions and taking action beyond the health sector.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=World Health Organization |url=https://apps.who.int/iris/handle/10665/356119 |title=World mental health report: transforming mental health for all |date=2022 |publisher=World Health Organization |isbn=978-92-4-004933-8 |pages=xviii |hdl=10665/356119 |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Inequities in mental health ==
Globally, in 2019, 1 in every 8 individuals (12.5% of the population) lived with a mental disorder; however, in 2020, due to the [[Mental health during the COVID-19 pandemic|COVID-19 pandemic]], that number grew dramatically by around 27%.{{Citation needed|date=November 2022}} While mental illnesses and disorders have become more prevalent, studies have shown that mental health outcomes are worse for some populations and communities than others. One such inequity is that of gender: females are twice as likely to have a mental illness than males.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Weissman |first1=Myrna M. |last2=Olfson |first2=Mark |date=1995-08-11 |title=Depression in Women: Implications for Health Care Research |url=https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.7638596 |journal=Science |language=en |volume=269 |issue=5225 |pages=799–801 |doi=10.1126/science.7638596 |pmid=7638596 |bibcode=1995Sci...269..799W |s2cid=21510901 |issn=0036-8075}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Desai |first1=Hirai D. |last2=Jann |first2=Michael W. |date=July 2000 |title=Women's Health Series Major Depression in Women: A Review of the Literature |url=http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/s1086-5802(15)30400-9 |journal=Journal of the American Pharmaceutical Association (1996) |volume=40 |issue=4 |pages=525–537 |doi=10.1016/s1086-5802(15)30400-9 |issn=1086-5802}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=World Health Organization |url=https://apps.who.int/iris/handle/10665/112828 |title=Social determinants of mental health |date=2014 |publisher=World Health Organization |hdl=10665/112828 |isbn=978-92-4-150680-9 |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Fixed characteristics ==
Fixed characteristics refers to those that are genetic and biological and/or are not subjected to be influenced by the environment or social living conditions of an individual.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Alegría |first1=Margarita |last2=NeMoyer |first2=Amanda |last3=Falgàs Bagué |first3=Irene |last4=Wang |first4=Ye |last5=Alvarez |first5=Kiara |date=November 2018 |title=Social Determinants of Mental Health: Where We Are and Where We Need to Go |journal=Current Psychiatry Reports |language=en |volume=20 |issue=11 |pages=95 |doi=10.1007/s11920-018-0969-9 |pmid=30221308 |pmc=6181118 |issn=1523-3812}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Gender ===
The second leading cause of global disability burden in 2020 was unipolar depression, and research showed that depression was twice as likely to be prevalent in women than in men.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Weissman |first1=Myrna M. |last2=Olfson |first2=Mark |date=1995-08-11 |title=Depression in Women: Implications for Health Care Research |url=https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.7638596 |journal=Science |language=en |volume=269 |issue=5225 |pages=799–801 |doi=10.1126/science.7638596 |pmid=7638596 |bibcode=1995Sci...269..799W |s2cid=21510901 |issn=0036-8075}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Desai |first1=Hirai D. |last2=Jann |first2=Michael W. |date=July 2000 |title=Women's Health Series Major Depression in Women: A Review of the Literature |url=http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/s1086-5802(15)30400-9 |journal=Journal of the American Pharmaceutical Association (1996) |volume=40 |issue=4 |pages=525–537 |doi=10.1016/s1086-5802(15)30400-9 |issn=1086-5802}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=World Health Organization |url=https://apps.who.int/iris/handle/10665/356119 |title=World mental health report: transforming mental health for all |date=2022 |publisher=World Health Organization |hdl=10665/356119 |isbn=978-92-4-004933-8 |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; Gender-based mental health disparities suggest that gender is a factor that could be leading to unequal health outcomes.

Research studies included in ''[[The Lancet Psychiatry|Lancet Psychiatry]]'' Women's Mental Health Series focuses on understanding why some of these gendered disparities might exist.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Riecher-Rössler |first=Anita |date=January 2017 |title=Sex and gender differences in mental disorders |url=https://linkinghub.elsevier.com/retrieve/pii/S2215036616303480 |journal=The Lancet Psychiatry |language=en |volume=4 |issue=1 |pages=8–9 |doi=10.1016/S2215-0366(16)30348-0|pmid=27856397 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Kuehner in her article ''Why is depression more common among women than among men?'' mentions several risk factors that contributes to these inequities, including the role of a women's sex hormones and "blunted hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal axis response to stress".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Kuehner |first=Christine |date=February 2017 |title=Why is depression more common among women than among men? |url=https://linkinghub.elsevier.com/retrieve/pii/S2215036616302632 |journal=The Lancet Psychiatry |language=en |volume=4 |issue=2 |pages=146–158 |doi=10.1016/S2215-0366(16)30263-2|pmid=27856392 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Other factors include a woman's increased likelihood to body shaming and rumination and stressors on an interpersonal level, as well as sexual abuse during childhood. Further, the prevalence of gender inequality and discrimination in society against women may also be a contributing factor. Li et al. finds that the monthly and lifespan fluctuations of sex hormones oestradiol and progesterone in women may also influence the gender gap, especially in the context of trauma-related, stress-related, and anxiety disorders, such as through increasing vulnerability to development of these disorders and permitting the continued persistence of symptoms for these disorders.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Li |first1=Sophie H |last2=Graham |first2=Bronwyn M |date=January 2017 |title=Why are women so vulnerable to anxiety, trauma-related and stress-related disorders? The potential role of sex hormones |url=https://linkinghub.elsevier.com/retrieve/pii/S2215036616303583 |journal=The Lancet Psychiatry |language=en |volume=4 |issue=1 |pages=73–82 |doi=10.1016/S2215-0366(16)30358-3|pmid=27856395 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Increased likelihood of gender-based violence for women compared to men is also another risk factor that was studied by Oram et al. Researchers found that women have a higher risk of being subjected to domestic and sexual violence, thereby increasing their prevalence to post-traumatic stress, anxiety, and depression. Also notable to consider in the context of gender-based trauma are female genital mutilation, forced and early marriage, human trafficking, and honor crimes.  

While women are reported to experience higher rates of depressive and anxiety related disorders, men are more likely to commit suicide than women: in the UK, suicide is the biggest cause of death for men 45 and younger, and in the likelihood of committing suicide, men are four times more likely in Russia and Argentina, three and a half times more likely in the United States, and three times more likely in Australia, than women, to name a few countries.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=Schumacher |first=Helene |title=Why more men than women die by suicide |url=https://www.bbc.com/future/article/20190313-why-more-men-kill-themselves-than-women |access-date=2022-11-01 |website=www.bbc.com |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Gender differences in suicide]] are commonly explained by pressure for gender roles and higher risk-taking behavior among men.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Murphy |first=George E |date=July 1998 |title=Why women are less likely than men to commit suicide |url=https://linkinghub.elsevier.com/retrieve/pii/S0010440X98900578 |journal=Comprehensive Psychiatry |language=en |volume=39 |issue=4 |pages=165–175 |doi=10.1016/S0010-440X(98)90057-8|pmid=9675500 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Sexual orientation ===
In studies comparing mental health outcomes between members of the lesbian, gay, bisexual, transgender, queer (questioning), intersex, asexual and agender ([[LGBT|LGBTQIA+]]) community with heterosexuals, the former showed increased risks of poor mental health.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Bränström |first=Richard |date=May 2017 |title=Minority stress factors as mediators of sexual orientation disparities in mental health treatment: a longitudinal population-based study |journal=Journal of Epidemiology and Community Health |language=en |volume=71 |issue=5 |pages=446–452 |doi=10.1136/jech-2016-207943 |pmid=28043996 |pmc=5484026 |issn=0143-005X}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Robertson |first1=Lee |last2=Akré |first2=Ellesse-Roselee |last3=Gonzales |first3=Gilbert |date=2021-11-01 |title=Mental Health Disparities at the Intersections of Gender Identity, Race, and Ethnicity |url=https://www.liebertpub.com/doi/10.1089/lgbt.2020.0429 |journal=LGBT Health |language=en |volume=8 |issue=8 |pages=526–535 |doi=10.1089/lgbt.2020.0429 |pmid=34591707 |s2cid=238239420 |issn=2325-8292}}&lt;/ref&gt; In fact, LGBTQIA+ individuals are twice as likely to have a mental disorder compared to their heterosexual counterparts, and two and a half times more likely to experience anxiety, depression, and substance misuse.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Semlyen |first1=Joanna |last2=King |first2=Michael |last3=Varney |first3=Justin |last4=Hagger-Johnson |first4=Gareth |date=December 2016 |title=Sexual orientation and symptoms of common mental disorder or low wellbeing: combined meta-analysis of 12 UK population health surveys |journal=BMC Psychiatry |language=en |volume=16 |issue=1 |pages=67 |doi=10.1186/s12888-016-0767-z |pmid=27009565 |pmc=4806482 |issn=1471-244X}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation |title=Current Issues in Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, and Transgender (LGBT) Health: Introduction |date=2013-04-11 |url=http://dx.doi.org/10.4324/9780203057582-5 |work=Current Issues in Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, and Transgender Health |pages=17–28 |publisher=Routledge |doi=10.4324/9780203057582-5 |isbn=978-0-203-05758-2 |access-date=2022-11-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Based on the [[minority stress]] model, these mental health disparities among LGBTQIA+ people are due to discrimination and stigma. In fact, LGBTQIA+ individuals have expressed difficulty in accessing healthcare due to experienced discrimination and stigma, which as a result, causes them to not seek healthcare at all or rather delay it.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Safer |first1=Joshua D. |last2=Coleman |first2=Eli |last3=Feldman |first3=Jamie |last4=Garofalo |first4=Robert |last5=Hembree |first5=Wylie |last6=Radix |first6=Asa |last7=Sevelius |first7=Jae |date=April 2016 |title=Barriers to healthcare for transgender individuals |url=https://journals.lww.com/01266029-201604000-00014 |journal=Current Opinion in Endocrinology, Diabetes &amp; Obesity |language=en |volume=23 |issue=2 |pages=168–171 |doi=10.1097/MED.0000000000000227 |pmid=26910276 |pmc=4802845 |issn=1752-296X}}&lt;/ref&gt; Further societal isolation and feelings of rejection may also contribute to the prevalence of mental disorders among this community.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Hsieh |first=Ning |date=July 2014 |title=Explaining the Mental Health Disparity by Sexual Orientation: The Importance of Social Resources |url=http://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.1177/2156869314524959 |journal=Society and Mental Health |language=en |volume=4 |issue=2 |pages=129–146 |doi=10.1177/2156869314524959 |s2cid=146921163 |issn=2156-8693}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition to the perceived and experienced stigma, LGBTQIA+ have an increased likelihood of being victims of violence.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |title=hate-crimes-and-violence-against-lesbian-gay-bisexual-and-transgender-people-may-2009-19pp |url=http://dx.doi.org/10.1163/2210-7975_hrd-9800-0005 |access-date=2022-11-01 |website=Human Rights Documents online|doi=10.1163/2210-7975_hrd-9800-0005 }}&lt;/ref&gt; These factors, alongside others, contribute significantly to differences in mental health experiences for members of the LGBTQIA+ community in comparison to their heterosexual counterparts, thereby result in mental health inequities by sexual orientation.

=== Race/ethnicity ===
Studies in the conducted in the United States have indicated that minorities have similar or smaller rates of prevalence for mental health disorders as their majority counterparts.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Williams |first=David R. |date=2005-10-01 |title=The Health of U.S. Racial and Ethnic Populations |url=https://academic.oup.com/psychsocgerontology/psychsocgerontology/article/2965174/The |journal=The Journals of Gerontology: Series B |language=en |volume=60 |issue=Special_Issue_2 |pages=S53–S62 |doi=10.1093/geronb/60.Special_Issue_2.S53 |pmid=16251591 |issn=1079-5014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Blacks (24.6%) and Hispanics (19.6%) have lower depression rates than their White counterparts (34.7%) in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Budhwani |first1=Henna |last2=Hearld |first2=Kristine Ria |last3=Chavez-Yenter |first3=Daniel |date=2014-09-11 |title=Depression in Racial and Ethnic Minorities: the Impact of Nativity and Discrimination |url=http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s40615-014-0045-z |journal=Journal of Racial and Ethnic Health Disparities |volume=2 |issue=1 |pages=34–42 |doi=10.1007/s40615-014-0045-z |s2cid=207501450 |issn=2197-3792}}&lt;/ref&gt; While racial/ethnic minority groups may have similar prevalence rates, the consequences because of mental illness are more prolonged – which may be partly explained due to the smaller access rates for mental health treatments.  In 2018, while 56.7% of the general US population who had a mental illness didn't seek treatment, 69.4% and 67.1% Black and Hispanics didn't access care.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Rubin |first=Rita |date=2020-06-23 |title=Pandemic Highlights Behavioral Health Disparities |url=https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jama/fullarticle/2767308 |journal=JAMA |language=en |volume=323 |issue=24 |pages=2452 |doi=10.1001/jama.2020.10318 |pmid=32573656 |s2cid=219990834 |issn=0098-7484}}&lt;/ref&gt; Further, in the instances of some mental illnesses, such as [[schizophrenia]], Blacks in the United States have been reported to have higher rates compared to their White counterparts, however, research suggests that this could be due to an [[overdiagnosis]] among clinicians and underdiagnosis for other illnesses, such as mood disorders, for which Blacks had lower reported prevalence rates for major depression.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Neighbors |first1=Harold W. |last2=Trierweiler |first2=Steven J. |last3=Ford |first3=Briggett C. |last4=Muroff |first4=Jordana R. |date=September 2003 |title=Racial Differences in DSM Diagnosis Using a Semi-Structured Instrument: The Importance of Clinical Judgment in the Diagnosis of African Americans |url=http://dx.doi.org/10.2307/1519777 |journal=Journal of Health and Social Behavior |volume=44 |issue=3 |pages=237–256 |doi=10.2307/1519777 |jstor=1519777 |pmid=14582306 |issn=0022-1465}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Strakowski |first=S |date=1996-07-08 |title=Racial influence on diagnosis in psychotic mania |url=https://linkinghub.elsevier.com/retrieve/pii/0165032796000286 |journal=Journal of Affective Disorders |language=en |volume=39 |issue=2 |pages=157–162 |doi=10.1016/0165-0327(96)00028-6|pmid=8827426 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=McGuire |first1=Thomas G. |last2=Miranda |first2=Jeanne |date=March 2008 |title=New Evidence Regarding Racial And Ethnic Disparities In Mental Health: Policy Implications |journal=Health Affairs |language=en |volume=27 |issue=2 |pages=393–403 |doi=10.1377/hlthaff.27.2.393 |pmid=18332495 |pmc=3928067 |issn=0278-2715}}&lt;/ref&gt; These instances of misdiagnosis may be due to "lack of cultural understanding by health care providers,…language differences between patient and provider, [[stigma of mental illness]] among minority groups, and cultural presentation of symptoms.

== Environmental factors ==

{{Empty section|date=November 2022}}

=== Inadequate access to proper food ===

=== Housing ===

=== Transportation ===

=== Pollution ===

=== Lack of health insurance ===

== Social factors ==

{{Empty section|date=November 2022}}

=== Discrimination ===

=== Stigma ===

== Other factors ==

{{Empty section|date=November 2022}}

=== Biological factors ===

== Interventions ==

{{Empty section|date=November 2022}}

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

[[Category:Public health]]
[[Category:Determinants of health]]
[[Category:Social problems in medicine]]
[[Category:Mental health]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>