<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20241017145101|1251691950" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1809033" pageid="1809033" ns="0" title="Stereotype threat"><revisions><rev timestamp="2024-11-17T12:18:55Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|Situational predicament}}
{{good article}}
{{Discrimination sidebar|Related}}

'''Stereotype threat''' is a situational predicament in which people are or feel themselves to be at risk of conforming to [[stereotype]]s about their social group.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.apa.org/research/action/stereotype|title=Stereotype threat widens achievement gap|date=July 15, 2006|work=American Psychological Association|access-date=2019-10-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="SteeleAronson"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Steele CM, Aronson J | title = Stereotype threat and the intellectual test performance of African Americans | journal = Journal of Personality and Social Psychology | volume = 69 | issue = 5 | pages = 797–811 | date = November 1995 | pmid = 7473032 | doi = 10.1037/0022-3514.69.5.797 | s2cid = 4665022 | author-link1 = Claude Steele | url=http://users.nber.org/~sewp/events/2005.01.14/Bios+Links/Good-rec2-Steele_&amp;_Aronson_95.pdf }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Steele CM | title = A threat in the air. How stereotypes shape intellectual identity and performance | journal = The American Psychologist | volume = 52 | issue = 6 | pages = 613–629 | date = June 1997 | pmid = 9174398 | doi = 10.1037/0003-066x.52.6.613 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Stereotype Threat |website=Chief Officer for Scientific Workforce Diversity at NIH |url=https://diversity.nih.gov/sociocultural-factors/stereotype-threat|access-date=2020-09-02 |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is theorized to be a contributing factor to long-standing [[Achievement gaps in the United States|racial and gender gaps]] in academic performance.&lt;ref name=":8"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Osborne JW | title = Testing Stereotype Threat: Does Anxiety Explain Race and Sex Differences in Achievement? | journal = Contemporary Educational Psychology | volume = 26 | issue = 3 | pages = 291–310 | date = July 2001 | pmid = 11414722 | doi = 10.1006/ceps.2000.1052 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":9"&gt;{{Cite journal| vauthors = Goldsmith PA |date=April 2004|title=Schools' Racial Mix, Students' Optimism, and the Black-White and Latino-White Achievement Gaps|journal=Sociology of Education|language=en-US|volume=77|issue=2|pages=121–147|doi=10.1177/003804070407700202|s2cid=145433651|issn=0038-0407}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":10"&gt;{{Cite journal| vauthors = Ellison G, Swanson A |date=June 2010|title=The Gender Gap in Secondary School Mathematics at High Achievement Levels: Evidence from the American Mathematics Competitions|journal=Journal of Economic Perspectives|language=en|volume=24|issue=2|pages=109–128|doi=10.1257/jep.24.2.109|s2cid=51730381|issn=0895-3309|url=http://www.nber.org/papers/w15238.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="GilovichKeltner2006" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":13"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = VanLandingham H, Ellison RL, Laique A, Cladek A, Khan H, Gonzalez C, Dunn MR | title = A scoping review of stereotype threat for BIPOC: Cognitive effects and intervention strategies for the field of neuropsychology | journal = The Clinical Neuropsychologist | volume = 36 | issue = 2 | pages = 503–522 | date = February 2022 | pmid = 34233577 | doi = 10.1080/13854046.2021.1947388 | s2cid = 235769090 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Since its introduction into the academic literature, stereotype threat has become one of the most widely studied topics in the field of [[social psychology]].&lt;ref name="Schmader2008"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Schmader T, Johns M, Forbes C | title = An integrated process model of stereotype threat effects on performance | journal = Psychological Review | volume = 115 | issue = 2 | pages = 336–356 | date = April 2008 | pmid = 18426293 | pmc = 2570773 | doi = 10.1037/0033-295X.115.2.336 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Situational factors that increase stereotype threat can include the difficulty of the task, the belief that the task measures their abilities, and the relevance of the stereotype to the task. Individuals show higher degrees of stereotype threat on tasks they wish to perform well on and when they identify strongly with the stereotyped group. These effects are also increased when they expect [[discrimination]] due to their identification with a negatively stereotyped group.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | vauthors = Steele CM, Spencer SJ, Aronson J | title = Advances in Experimental Social Psychology Volume 34 | doi = 10.1016/S0065-2601(02)80009-0 | chapter = Contending with group image: the psychology of stereotype and social identity threat | volume = 34 | pages = 379–440 | date = 2002 | isbn = 9780120152346 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Repeated experiences of stereotype threat can lead to a [[Virtuous circle and vicious circle|vicious circle]] of diminished confidence, poor performance, and loss of interest in the relevant area of achievement.&lt;ref name="GilovichKeltner2006"&gt;{{cite book| vauthors = Gilovich T, Keltner D, Nisbett RE | chapter = Being a member of a stigmatized group: stereotype threat |title=Social psychology|pages=[https://archive.org/details/socialpsychology0000gilo/page/467 467–468]|publisher=W.W. Norton|location=New York|year=2006|isbn=978-0-393-97875-9| chapter-url=https://archive.org/details/socialpsychology0000gilo/page/467}}&lt;/ref&gt; Stereotype threat has been argued to show a reduction in the performance of individuals who belong to negatively stereotyped groups.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | vauthors = Steele CM, Spencer SJ, Aronson J |author-link1=Claude Steele | title = Advances in experimental social psychology | volume = 34 |pages=379–440 | veditors = Zanna MP | chapter = Contending with group image: the psychology of stereotype and social identity threat|location=Amsterdam|publisher=Academic Press|isbn=9780120152346|year=1964}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Steele CM | title = A threat in the air. How stereotypes shape intellectual identity and performance | journal = The American Psychologist | volume = 52 | issue = 6 | pages = 613–629 | date = June 1997 | pmid = 9174398 | doi = 10.1037/0003-066X.52.6.613 | citeseerx = 10.1.1.318.9608 | author-link = Claude Steele }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Its role in affecting public [[health disparities]] has also been suggested.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Aronson J, Burgess D, Phelan SM, Juarez L | title = Unhealthy interactions: the role of stereotype threat in health disparities | journal = American Journal of Public Health | volume = 103 | issue = 1 | pages = 50–56 | date = January 2013 | pmid = 23153125 | pmc = 3518353 | doi = 10.2105/AJPH.2012.300828 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the theory, if negative stereotypes are present regarding a specific group, group members are likely to become [[Anxiety|anxious]] about their performance, which may hinder their ability to perform to their full potential.&lt;ref name="scholarship.law.bu.edu"&gt;{{cite journal| vauthors = Feingold J |date=2011|title=Racing Towards Colorblindness: Stereotype Threat and the Myth of Meritocracy|url=https://scholarship.law.bu.edu/faculty_scholarship/826|journal=Georgetown Journal of Law and Modern Critical Race Perspectives |volume=3}}&lt;/ref&gt; Importantly, the individual does not need to subscribe to the stereotype for it to be activated. It is hypothesized that the mechanism through which anxiety (induced by the activation of the stereotype) decreases performance is by depleting [[working memory]] (especially the phonological aspects of the working memory system).&lt;ref name="BeilockEtAl2007"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Beilock SL, Rydell RJ, McConnell AR | title = Stereotype threat and working memory: mechanisms, alleviation, and spillover | journal = Journal of Experimental Psychology. General | volume = 136 | issue = 2 | pages = 256–76 | date = May 2007 | pmid = 17500650 | doi = 10.1037/0096-3445.136.2.256 | citeseerx = 10.1.1.669.9881 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The opposite of stereotype threat is '''stereotype boost''', which is when people perform better than they otherwise would have, because of exposure to [[positive stereotype]]s about their social group.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{cite book | vauthors = Shih MJ, Pittinsky TL, Ho GC |title=Stereotype threat: theory, process, and application |pages=[https://books.google.com/books?id=G_EIrkhfQLsC&amp;pg=5 5–6], [https://books.google.com/books?id=G_EIrkhfQLsC&amp;pg=141 141–143]|year=2011| veditors = Inzlicht M, Schmader T | chapter = Stereotype boost: positive outcomes from the activation of positive stereotypes |location=New York, New York|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=978-0-19-973244-9}}&lt;/ref&gt; A variant of stereotype boost is '''stereotype lift''', which is people achieving better performance because of exposure to negative stereotypes about other social groups.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

Some researchers have suggested that stereotype threat should not be interpreted as a factor in real-life performance gaps, and have raised the possibility of [[publication bias]].&lt;ref name="Ganley2013"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Ganley CM, Mingle LA, Ryan AM, Ryan K, Vasilyeva M, Perry M | title = An examination of stereotype threat effects on girls' mathematics performance | journal = Developmental Psychology | volume = 49 | issue = 10 | pages = 1886–1897 | date = October 2013 | pmid = 23356523 | doi = 10.1037/a0031412 | url = https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/85192141/2013-ganley.pdf | url-status = dead | citeseerx = 10.1.1.353.4436 | archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20140719005546/https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/85192141/2013-ganley.pdf | archive-date = 19 July 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Stoet2012" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Flore2014" /&gt; Other critics have focused on correcting what they claim are misconceptions of early studies showing a large effect.&lt;ref name="Sackett2004a" /&gt; [[Meta-analysis|Meta-analyses]] and systematic reviews have shown significant evidence for the effects of stereotype threat, though the phenomenon defies over-simplistic characterization.&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":4"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Nguyen HH, Ryan AM | title = Does stereotype threat affect test performance of minorities and women? A meta-analysis of experimental evidence | journal = The Journal of Applied Psychology | volume = 93 | issue = 6 | pages = 1314–1334 | date = November 2008 | pmid = 19025250 | doi = 10.1037/a0012702 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":5"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Walton GM, Spencer SJ | title = Latent ability: grades and test scores systematically underestimate the intellectual ability of negatively stereotyped students | journal = Psychological Science | volume = 20 | issue = 9 | pages = 1132–1139 | date = September 2009 | pmid = 19656335 | doi = 10.1111/j.1467-9280.2009.02417.x | s2cid = 25810191 | doi-access = free }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":6"&gt;{{Cite journal| vauthors = Gentile A, Boca S, Giammusso I |date=2018-11-01|title='You play like a Woman!' Effects of gender stereotype threat on Women's performance in physical and sport activities: A meta-analysis|journal=Psychology of Sport and Exercise|volume=39|pages=95–103|doi=10.1016/j.psychsport.2018.07.013|s2cid=149490634|issn=1469-0292}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":7"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Lamont RA, Swift HJ, Abrams D | title = A review and meta-analysis of age-based stereotype threat: negative stereotypes, not facts, do the damage | journal = Psychology and Aging | volume = 30 | issue = 1 | pages = 180–193 | date = March 2015 | pmid = 25621742 | pmc = 4360754 | doi = 10.1037/a0038586 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":2"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Picho K, Rodriguez A, Finnie L | title = Exploring the moderating role of context on the mathematics performance of females under stereotype threat: a meta-analysis | journal = The Journal of Social Psychology | volume = 153 | issue = 3 | pages = 299–333 | date = May 2013 | pmid = 23724702 | doi = 10.1080/00224545.2012.737380 | s2cid = 45950675 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":14"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Liu S, Liu P, Wang M, Zhang B | title = Effectiveness of stereotype threat interventions: A meta-analytic review | journal = The Journal of Applied Psychology | volume = 106 | issue = 6 | pages = 921–949 | date = June 2021 | pmid = 32772526 | doi = 10.1037/apl0000770 | s2cid = 221098319 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":13" /&gt;

==Empirical studies==
As of 2015, more than 300 studies have been published showing the effects of stereotype threat on performance in a variety of domains.&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":5" /&gt; Stereotype threat is considered by some researchers to be a contributing factor to long-standing [[Achievement gaps in the United States|racial and gender achievement gaps]], such as under-performance of black students relative to white ones in various academic subjects, and under-representation of women at higher echelons in the field of mathematics.&lt;ref name=":8" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":9" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":10" /&gt;&lt;ref name="GilovichKeltner2006" /&gt;

The strength of the stereotype threat that occurs depends on how the task is framed. If a task is framed to be neutral, stereotype threat is not likely to occur; however, if tasks are framed in terms of active stereotypes, participants are likely to perform worse on the task.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|date=15 July 2006|title=Stereotype Threat Widens Achievement Gap|url=https://www.apa.org/research/action/stereotype|website=American Psychological Association}}&lt;/ref&gt; For example, a study on chess players revealed that female players performed more poorly than expected when they were told they would be playing against a male opponent. In contrast, women who were told that their opponent was female performed as would be predicted by past ratings of performance.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal| vauthors = Maass A, D'Ettole C, Cadinu M |year=2008|title=Checkmate? The role of gender stereotypes in the ultimate intellectual sport|journal=European Journal of Social Psychology|volume=38|issue=2|pages=231–245|doi=10.1002/ejsp.440|s2cid=144308852 |issn=0046-2772|doi-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt; Female participants who were made aware of the stereotype of females performing worse at chess than males performed worse in their chess games.

A 2007 study extended stereotype threat research to [[entrepreneurship]], a traditionally male-stereotyped profession. The study revealed that stereotype threat can depress women's entrepreneurial intentions while boosting men's intentions. However, when entrepreneurship is presented as a gender-neutral profession, men and women express a similar level of interest in becoming entrepreneurs.&lt;ref name="Stereotype Threat and Entrepreneurial Intentions"&gt;{{cite journal| vauthors = Gupta VK, Bhawe NM |year=2007|title=The Influence of Proactive Personality and Stereotype Threat on Women's Entrepreneurial Intentions|journal=[[Journal of Leadership &amp; Organizational Studies]]|volume=13|issue=4|pages=73–85|doi=10.1177/10717919070130040901|s2cid=145318243|issn=1071-7919}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another experiment involved a golf game which was described as a test of "natural athletic ability" or of "sports intelligence". When it was described as a test of athletic ability, European-American students performed worse, but when the description mentioned intelligence, African-American students performed worse.&lt;ref name="StoneLynch1999"&gt;{{cite journal| vauthors = Stone J, Lynch CI, Sjomeling M, Darley JM |year=1999|title=Stereotype threat effects on Black and White athletic performance|journal=[[Journal of Personality and Social Psychology]]|volume=77|issue=6|pages=1213–1227|citeseerx=10.1.1.687.5039|doi=10.1037/0022-3514.77.6.1213|issn=0022-3514}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Other studies have demonstrated how stereotype threat can negatively affect the performance of European Americans in athletic situations&lt;ref name="White Men Can't Jump"&gt;{{cite journal| vauthors = Stone J, Perry W, Darley JM |year=1997|title="White Men Can't Jump": Evidence for the Perceptual Confirmation of Racial Stereotypes Following a Basketball Game|journal=Basic and Applied Social Psychology|volume=19|issue=3|pages=291–306|doi=10.1207/s15324834basp1903_2|issn=0197-3533}}&lt;/ref&gt; as well as the performance of men who are being tested on their social sensitivity.&lt;ref name="Stereotype Threat in Men"&gt;{{cite journal| vauthors = Koenig AM, Eagly AH |year=2005|title=Stereotype Threat in Men on a Test of Social Sensitivity|journal=Sex Roles|volume=52|issue=7–8|pages=489–496|doi=10.1007/s11199-005-3714-x|s2cid=7884932|issn=0360-0025}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although the framing of a task can produce stereotype threat in most individuals, certain individuals appear to be more likely to experience stereotype threat than others. Individuals who highly identify with a particular group appear to be more vulnerable to experiencing stereotype threat than individuals who do not identify strongly with the stereotyped group.

The mere presence of other people can evoke stereotype threat. In one experiment, women who took a mathematics exam along with two other women got 70% of the answers right, whereas women who took the same exam in the presence of two men got an average score of 55%.&lt;ref name="InzlichtBen-Zeev2000"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Inzlicht M, Ben-Zeev T | title = A threatening intellectual environment: why females are susceptible to experiencing problem-solving deficits in the presence of males | journal = Psychological Science | volume = 11 | issue = 5 | pages = 365–71 | date = September 2000 | pmid = 11228906 | doi = 10.1111/1467-9280.00272 | citeseerx = 10.1.1.24.1847 | s2cid = 2887128 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The goal of a study conducted by Desert, Preaux, and Jund in 2009 was to see if children from lower [[Socioeconomic status|socioeconomic groups]] are affected by stereotype threat. The study compared children that were 6–7 years old with children that were 8–9 years old from multiple elementary schools. These children were presented with the [[Raven's Progressive Matrices|Raven's Matrices]] test, which is an intellectual ability test. Separate groups of children were given directions in an evaluative way and other groups were given directions in a non-evaluative way. The "evaluative" group received instructions that are usually given with the Raven Matrices test, while the "non-evaluative" group was given directions which made it seem as if the children were simply playing a game. The results showed that third graders performed better on the test than the first graders did, which was expected. However, the lower socioeconomic status children did worse on the test when they received directions in an evaluative way than the higher socioeconomic status children did when they received directions in an evaluative way. These results suggested that the framing of the directions given to the children may have a greater effect on performance than socioeconomic status. This was shown by the differences in performance based on which type of instructions they received. This information can be useful in classroom settings to help improve the performance of students of lower socioeconomic status.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal| vauthors = Desert M, Marie P, Jund R |year=2009|title=So young and already victims of stereotype threat: Socio-economic status and performance of 6 to 9 years old children on Raven's progressive matrices|journal=European Journal of Psychology of Education|volume=24|issue=2|pages=207–218|doi=10.1007/BF03173012|s2cid=144090741}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There have been studies on the effects of stereotype threat based on age. A study was done on 99 senior citizens ranging in age from 60–75 years. These seniors were given multiple tests on certain factors and categories such as memory and physical abilities, and were also asked to evaluate how physically fit they believe themselves to be. Additionally, they were asked to read articles that contained both positive and negative outlooks about seniors, and they watched someone reading the same articles. The goal of this study was to see if priming the participants before the tests would affect performance. The results showed that the control group performed better than those that were [[Priming (psychology)|primed]] with either negative or positive words prior to the tests. The control group seemed to feel more confident in their abilities than the other two groups.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|  vauthors = Horton S, Baker J, Pearce W, Deakin J |year=2010|title=Immunity to Popular Stereotypes of Aging? Seniors and Stereotype Threat|journal=Educational Gerontology|volume=36|issue=5|pages=353–371|doi=10.1080/03601270903323976| s2cid = 145113151 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Other studies have found that stereotype activation in older adults can improve memory performance,&lt;ref&gt;Barber, S. J., &amp; Mather, M. (2013). Stereotype threat can both enhance and impair older adults’ memory. Psychological science, 24(12), 2522-2529.&lt;/ref&gt; resulting in a distinction between stereotype threat mechanisms in aging compared with other groups.&lt;ref&gt;Barber, S. J. (2017). An examination of age-based stereotype threat about cognitive decline: Implications for stereotype-threat research and theory development. Perspectives on Psychological Science, 12(1), 62-90.&lt;/ref&gt;

Many psychological experiments carried out on Stereotype Threat focus on the physiological effects of negative stereotype threat on performance, looking at both high and low status groups. Scheepers and Ellemers tested the following hypothesis: when assessing a performance situation on the basis of current beliefs the low status group members would show a physiological threat response, and high-status members would also show a physiological threat response when examining a possible alteration of the status quo (Scheepers &amp; Ellemers, 2005).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal| vauthors = Scheepers D, Ellemers N | date=March 2005|title=When the pressure is up: The assessment of social identity threat in low and high status groups|journal=Journal of Experimental Social Psychology|volume=41|issue=2|pages=192–200|doi=10.1016/j.jesp.2004.06.002}}&lt;/ref&gt; The results of this experiment were in line with expectations. As predicted, participants in the low status condition showed higher blood pressure immediately after the status feedback, while participants in the high-status condition showed a spike in blood pressure while anticipating the second round of the task.

In 2012, Scheepers et al. hypothesized that when high social power is stimulated 'an efficient cardiovascular pattern (challenge)' is produced, whereas, 'an inefficient cardiovascular pattern' or threat is caused by the activation of low social power (Scheepers, de Wit, Ellemers &amp; Sassenberg, 2012). Two experiments were carried out in order to test this hypothesis. The first experiment looked at power priming and the second experiment related to role play. Both results from these two experiments provided evidence in support for the hypothesis.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal| vauthors = Scheepers D, de Wit F, Ellemers N, Sassenberg K |date=January 2012|title=Social power makes the heart work more efficiently: Evidence from cardiovascular markers of challenge and threat|journal=Journal of Experimental Social Psychology|volume=48|issue=1|pages=371–374|doi=10.1016/j.jesp.2011.06.014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Cleopatra Abdou and Adam Fingerhut were the first to develop experimental methods to study stereotype threat in a health care context,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Abdou CM, Fingerhut AW | title = Stereotype threat among black and white women in health care settings | journal = Cultural Diversity &amp; Ethnic Minority Psychology | volume = 20 | issue = 3 | pages = 316–23 | date = July 2014 | pmid = 25045944 | pmc = 5449200 | doi = 10.1037/a0036946 }}&lt;/ref&gt; including the first study indicating that health care stereotype threat is linked with adverse health outcomes and disparities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Abdou CM, Fingerhut AW, Jackson JS, Wheaton F | title = Healthcare Stereotype Threat in Older Adults in the Health and Retirement Study | journal = American Journal of Preventive Medicine | volume = 50 | issue = 2 | pages = 191–8 | date = February 2016 | pmid = 26497263 | pmc = 4755717 | doi = 10.1016/j.amepre.2015.07.034 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://health.usnews.com/health-news/articles/2015/10/20/stereotypes-can-hurt-a-patients-care|title=Stereotypes Can Hurt a Patient's Care| vauthors = Preidt R |work=U.S. News &amp; World Report|access-date=September 29, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some studies have found null results. The single largest experimental test of stereotype threat (N = 2064), conducted on Dutch high school students, found no effect.&lt;ref name=":12"&gt;{{cite journal| vauthors = Flore P, Mulder J, Wicherts J |date=2018|title=The influence of gender stereotype threat on mathematics test scores of Dutch high school students: a registered report|url=https://pure.uvt.nl/ws/files/29125573/MTO_Flore_influence_of_gender_stereotype_CRiSP_2019.pdf|journal=Comprehensive Results in Social Psychology|volume=3|issue=2|pages=140–174|doi=10.1080/23743603.2018.1559647|name-list-style=vanc|doi-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt; The authors state, however, that these results are limited to a narrow age-range, experimental procedure and cultural context, and call for further registered reports and replication studies on the topic.&lt;ref name=":12" /&gt; Despite these limitations, they state in conclusion that their study shows "that the effects of stereotype threat on math test performance should not be overgeneralized."&lt;ref name=":12" /&gt;

Numerous meta-analyses and systematic reviews have shown significant evidence for the effects of stereotype threat.&lt;ref name=":3"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Pennington CR, Heim D, Levy AR, Larkin DT | title = Twenty Years of Stereotype Threat Research: A Review of Psychological Mediators | journal = PLOS ONE | volume = 11 | issue = 1 | pages = e0146487 | date = 2016-01-11 | pmid = 26752551 | pmc = 4713435 | doi = 10.1371/journal.pone.0146487 | bibcode = 2016PLoSO..1146487P | doi-access = free }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":4" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":5" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":6" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":7" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":14" /&gt; However they also point to ways in which the phenomenon defies over-simplistic characterization.&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":4" /&gt; For instance, one meta-analysis found that with female subjects "subtle threat-activating cues produced the largest effect, followed by blatant and moderately explicit cues" while with minorities "moderately explicit stereotype threat-activating cues produced the largest effect, followed by blatant and subtle cues".&lt;ref name=":4" /&gt;

==Mechanisms==
Although numerous studies demonstrate the effects of stereotype threat on performance, questions remain as to the specific cognitive factors that underlie these effects. Steele and Aronson originally speculated that attempts to suppress stereotype-related thoughts lead to anxiety and the narrowing of [[attention]]. This could contribute to the observed deficits in performance. In 2008, [[Toni Schmader]], Michael Johns, and Chad Forbes published an integrated model of stereotype threat that focused on three interrelated factors:

#[[Stress (psychological)|stress]] arousal;
# performance monitoring, which narrows attention; and,
# efforts to suppress negative thoughts and emotions.&lt;ref name="Schmader2008" /&gt;

Schmader et al. suggest that these three factors summarize the pattern of evidence that has been accumulated by past experiments on stereotype threat. For example, stereotype threat has been shown to disrupt working memory and [[executive function]],&lt;ref name="Working Memory"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Schmader T, Johns M | title = Converging evidence that stereotype threat reduces working memory capacity | journal = Journal of Personality and Social Psychology | volume = 85 | issue = 3 | pages = 440–52 | date = September 2003 | pmid = 14498781 | doi = 10.1037/0022-3514.85.3.440 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="ego depletion" /&gt; increase arousal,&lt;ref name="arousal"&gt;{{cite journal| vauthors = Ben-Zeev T, Fein S, Inzlicht M |year=2005|title=Stereotype Threat and Arousal|url=http://michaelinzlicht.com/research/research_articles/Ben-Zeev,%20Fein,%20Inzlicht.pdf|url-status=dead|journal=Journal of Experimental Social Psychology|volume=41|issue=2|pages=174–181|doi=10.1016/j.jesp.2003.11.007|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120306003643/http://www.michaelinzlicht.com/research/research_articles/Ben-Zeev,%20Fein,%20Inzlicht.pdf|archive-date=2012-03-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; increase [[self-consciousness]] about one's performance,&lt;ref name="Causal Mechanisms of Stereotype Threat"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Beilock SL, Jellison WA, Rydell RJ, McConnell AR, Carr TH | title = On the causal mechanisms of stereotype threat: can skills that don't rely heavily on working memory still be threatened? | journal = Personality &amp; Social Psychology Bulletin | volume = 32 | issue = 8 | pages = 1059–71 | date = August 2006 | pmid = 16861310 | doi = 10.1177/0146167206288489 | citeseerx = 10.1.1.472.7033 | s2cid = 14741767 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and cause individuals to try to suppress negative thoughts as well as negative emotions such as anxiety.&lt;ref name="emotion regulation"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Johns M, Inzlicht M, Schmader T | title = Stereotype threat and executive resource depletion: examining the influence of emotion regulation | journal = Journal of Experimental Psychology. General | volume = 137 | issue = 4 | pages = 691–705 | date = November 2008 | pmid = 18999361 | pmc = 2976617 | doi = 10.1037/a0013834 | url = http://michaelinzlicht.com/research/research_articles/Johns,%20Inzlicht,%20&amp;%20Schmader,%202008.pdf | archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20120306003358/http://www.michaelinzlicht.com/research/research_articles/Johns%2C%20Inzlicht%2C%20%26%20Schmader%2C%202008.pdf | url-status = dead | archive-date = 2012-03-06 }}&lt;/ref&gt; People have a limited amount of cognitive resources available. When a large portion of these resources are spent focusing on anxiety and performance pressure, the individual is likely to perform worse on the task at hand.

A number of studies looking at physiological and neurological responses support Schmader and colleagues' integrated model of the processes that produce stereotype threat. Supporting an explanation in terms of stress arousal, one study found that African Americans under stereotype threat exhibit larger increases in arterial [[blood pressure]].&lt;ref name="blood pressure"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Blascovich J, Spencer SJ, Quinn D, Steele C | title = African Americans and high blood pressure: the role of stereotype threat | journal = Psychological Science | volume = 12 | issue = 3 | pages = 225–9 | date = May 2001 | pmid = 11437305 | doi = 10.1111/1467-9280.00340 | s2cid = 2590855 }}&lt;/ref&gt; One study found increased cardiovascular activation amongst women who watched a video in which men outnumbered women at a math and science conference.&lt;ref name="Mary Murphy study"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Murphy MC, Steele CM, Gross JJ | title = Signaling threat: how situational cues affect women in math, science, and engineering settings | journal = Psychological Science | volume = 18 | issue = 10 | pages = 879–85 | date = October 2007 | pmid = 17894605 | doi = 10.1111/j.1467-9280.2007.01995.x | s2cid = 21648665 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Other studies have similarly found that individuals under stereotype threat display increased heart rates.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Croizet JC, Després G, Gauzins ME, Huguet P, Leyens JP, Méot A | title = Stereotype threat undermines intellectual performance by triggering a disruptive mental load | journal = Personality &amp; Social Psychology Bulletin | volume = 30 | issue = 6 | pages = 721–31 | date = June 2004 | pmid = 15155036 | doi = 10.1177/0146167204263961 | s2cid = 34488431 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Stereotype threat may also activate a [[Neuroendocrine system|neuroendocrine stress response]], as measured by increased levels of [[cortisol]] while under threat.&lt;ref name="Cortisol"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Townsend SS, Major B, Gangi CE, Mendes WB | title = From "in the air" to "under the skin": cortisol responses to social identity threat | journal = Personality &amp; Social Psychology Bulletin | volume = 37 | issue = 2 | pages = 151–64 | date = February 2011 | pmid = 21239591 | pmc = 3538844 | doi = 10.1177/0146167210392384 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The physiological reactions that are induced by stereotype threat can often be subconscious, and can distract and interrupt cognitive focus from the task.

With regard to performance monitoring and vigilance, studies of brain activity have supported the idea that stereotype threat increases both of these processes. Forbes and colleagues recorded [[electroencephalogram]] (EEG) signals that measure electrical activity along the scalp, and found that individuals experiencing stereotype threat were more vigilant for performance-related stimuli.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Forbes CE, Schmader T, Allen JJ | title = The role of devaluing and discounting in performance monitoring: a neurophysiological study of minorities under threat | journal = Social Cognitive and Affective Neuroscience | volume = 3 | issue = 3 | pages = 253–61 | date = September 2008 | pmid = 19015117 | pmc = 2566773 | doi = 10.1093/scan/nsn012 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Gray727 anterior cingulate cortex.png|thumb|right|300px|Researchers found that women experiencing stereotype threat while taking a math test showed heightened activation in the ventral stream of the [[anterior cingulate cortex]] (ACC).]]

Another study used [[functional magnetic resonance imaging]] (fMRI) to investigate brain activity associated with stereotype threat. The researchers found that women experiencing stereotype threat while taking a math test showed heightened activation in the ventral stream of the [[anterior cingulate cortex]] (ACC), a neural region thought to be associated with social and emotional processing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Krendl AC, Richeson JA, Kelley WM, Heatherton TF | title = The negative consequences of threat: a functional magnetic resonance imaging investigation of the neural mechanisms underlying women's underperformance in math | journal = Psychological Science | volume = 19 | issue = 2 | pages = 168–75 | date = February 2008 | pmid = 18271865 | doi = 10.1111/j.1467-9280.2008.02063.x | s2cid = 2692771 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Wraga and colleagues found that women under stereotype threat showed increased activation in the ventral ACC and that the amount of this activation predicted performance decrements on the task.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Wraga M, Helt M, Jacobs E, Sullivan K | title = Neural basis of stereotype-induced shifts in women's mental rotation performance | journal = Social Cognitive and Affective Neuroscience | volume = 2 | issue = 1 | pages = 12–9 | date = March 2007 | pmid = 18985116 | pmc = 2555429 | doi = 10.1093/scan/nsl041 }}&lt;/ref&gt; When individuals were made aware of performance-related stimuli, they were more likely to experience stereotype threat. However, a study using fMRI to investigate stereotype threat in older adults showed heightened activation in parietal midline regions including the [[posterior cingulate cortex]] (PCC) and [[precuneus]] during both working memory and episodic memory tasks.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Chen YT, McDonough IM, Faig KE, Norman GJ, Gallo DA | title = Impact of stereotype threat on brain activity during memory tasks in older adults | journal = NeuroImage | volume = 260 | pages = 119413 | date = October 2022 | pmid = 35853542 | pmc = 9436003 | doi = 10.1016/j.neuroimage.2022.119413 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The heightened activation in these brain areas also was associated with better memory accuracy, inconsistent with the notion that stereotype threat always leads to impaired performance. 

A study conducted by Boucher, Rydell, Loo, and Rydell has shown that stereotype threat not only affects performance, but can also affect the ability to learn new information. In the study, undergraduate men and women had a session of learning followed by an assessment of what they learned. Some participants were given information intended to induce stereotype threat, and some of these participants were later given "gender fair" information, which it was predicted would reduce or remove stereotype threat. As a result, participants were split into four separate conditions: control group, stereotype threat only, stereotype threat removed before learning, and stereotype threat removed after learning. The results of the study showed that the women who were presented with the "gender fair" information performed better on the math related test than the women who were not presented with this information. This study also showed that it was more beneficial to women for the "gender fair" information to be presented prior to learning rather than after learning. These results suggest that eliminating stereotype threat prior to taking mathematical tests can help women perform better, and that eliminating stereotype threat prior to mathematical learning can help women learn better.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Boucher KL, Rydell RJ, Van Loo KJ, Rydell MT |year=2012|title=Reducing Stereotype threat in order to facilitate learning|journal=European Journal of Social Psychology|volume=42|issue=2|pages=174–179|doi=10.1002/ejsp.871}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Original study==
[[File:Stereotype threat bw.jpg|thumb|right|300px|"The Effects of Stereotype Threat on the Standardized Test Performance of College Students (adjusted for group differences on SAT)". From J. Aronson, C.M. Steele, M.F. Salinas, M.J. Lustina, ''Readings About the Social Animal'', 8th edition, ed. E. Aronson]]
In 1995, [[Claude Steele]] and [[Joshua Aronson]] performed the first experiments demonstrating that stereotype threat can undermine intellectual performance.&lt;ref name=SteeleAronson /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2012/10/07/opinion/sunday/intelligence-and-the-stereotype-threat.html|title=Intelligence and the Stereotype Threat| vauthors = Paul AM |date=2012-10-06|work=The New York Times|access-date=2019-10-13|issn=0362-4331}}&lt;/ref&gt; Steele and Aronson measured this through a word completion task.&lt;ref name="SteeleAronson" /&gt;

They had African-American and [[European American|European-American]] college students take a difficult verbal portion of the [[Graduate Record Examination]] test. As would be expected based on national averages, the African-American students did not perform as well on the test. Steele and Aronson split students into three groups: stereotype-threat (in which the test was described as being "diagnostic of intellectual ability"), non-stereotype threat (in which the test was described as "a laboratory problem-solving task that was nondiagnostic of ability"), and a third condition (in which the test was again described as nondiagnostic of ability, but participants were asked to view the difficult test as a challenge). All three groups received the same test.

Steele and Aronson concluded that changing the instructions on the test could reduce African-American students' concern about confirming a negative stereotype about their group. Supporting this conclusion, they found that African-American students who regarded the test as a measure of intelligence had more thoughts related to negative stereotypes of their group. Additionally, they found that African Americans who thought the test measured intelligence were more likely to complete word fragments using words associated with relevant negative stereotypes (e.g., completing "__mb" as "dumb" rather than as "numb").

Adjusted for previous SAT scores, subjects in the non-diagnostic-challenge condition performed significantly better than those in the non-diagnostic-only condition and those in the diagnostic condition. In the first experiment, the race-by-condition interaction was marginally significant. However, the second study reported in the same paper found a significant interaction effect of race and condition. This suggested that placement in the diagnostic condition significantly impacted African Americans compared with European Americans.&lt;ref name="SteeleAronson" /&gt;

==Stereotype lift and stereotype boost==
Stereotype threat concerns how stereotype cues can harm performance. However, in certain situations, stereotype activation can also lead to performance enhancement through stereotype lift or stereotype boost. Stereotype lift increases performance when people are exposed to negative stereotypes about another group.&lt;ref name="Walton 2003 456–467"&gt;{{cite journal| vauthors = Walton GM, Cohen GL |title=Stereotype lift|journal=Journal of Experimental Social Psychology|year=2003|volume=39|issue=5|pages=456–467|doi=10.1016/S0022-1031(03)00019-2}}&lt;/ref&gt; This enhanced performance has been attributed to increases in [[self-efficacy]] and decreases in self-doubt as a result of negative [[Ingroups and outgroups|outgroup]] stereotypes.&lt;ref name="Walton 2003 456–467"/&gt; Stereotype boost suggests that positive stereotypes may enhance performance.&lt;ref name="Shih, M. J. 2012 141–156"&gt;{{cite book|title=Stereotype Threat: Theory, Process, and Application|year=2012|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=978-0199732449 |pages=[https://books.google.com/books?id=G_EIrkhfQLsC&amp;pg=141 141–156]| vauthors = Shih MJ, Pittinsky TL, Ho GC | veditors = Inzlicht M, Schmader T |chapter=Stereotype boost: Positive outcomes from the activation of positive stereotypes}}&lt;/ref&gt; Stereotype boost occurs when a positive aspect of an individual's social identity is made salient in an identity-relevant domain. Although stereotype boost is similar to stereotype lift in enhancing performance, stereotype lift is the result of a negative outgroup stereotype, whereas stereotype boost occurs due to activation of a positive [[Ingroups and outgroups|ingroup]] stereotype.&lt;ref name="Shih, M. J. 2012 141–156"/&gt;

Consistent with the positive racial stereotype concerning their superior quantitative skills, [[Asian American]] women performed better on a math test when their Asian identity was [[Priming (psychology)|primed]] compared to a [[Treatment and control groups|control condition]] where no social identity was primed. Conversely, these participants did worse on the math test when instead their gender identity—which is associated with stereotypes of inferior quantitative skills—was made salient, which is consistent with stereotype threat.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal| vauthors = Shih M, Pittinsky TL, Trahan A |title=Domain-specific effects of stereotypes on performance|journal=Self and Identity|year=2006|volume=5|issue=1|pages=1–14|doi=10.1080/15298860500338534|s2cid=145488980|url=https://research.hks.harvard.edu/publications/getFile.aspx?Id=171}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Steen LA | title = Mathematics education: a predictor of scientific competitiveness | journal = Science | volume = 237 | issue = 4812 | pages = 251–302 | date = July 1987 | pmid = 17772052 | doi = 10.1126/science.237.4812.251 | url = http://www.stolaf.edu/people/steen/Papers/87predict.pdf | citeseerx = 10.1.1.367.4122 | url-status = dead | archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20131203040055/http://www.stolaf.edu/people/steen/Papers/87predict.pdf | archive-date = 3 December 2013 | bibcode = 1987Sci...237..251S }}&lt;/ref&gt; Two [[Reproducibility|replications]] of this result have been attempted. In one case, the effect was only reproduced after excluding participants who were unaware of stereotypes about the mathematical abilities of Asians or women,&lt;ref name = "Gibson_2014"&gt;{{cite journal | title=A Replication Attempt of Stereotype Susceptibility (Shih, Pittinsky, &amp; Ambady, 1999) | vauthors = Gibson CE, Losee J, Vitiello C | journal=Social Psychology | year=2014 | volume=45 | issue=3 | pages=194–198 | doi=10.1027/1864-9335/a000184| doi-access=free }}&lt;/ref&gt; while the other replication failed to reproduce the original results even considering several moderating variables.&lt;ref name = "Gibson_2014" /&gt;

==Long-term and other consequences==
{{further|Minority stress#Health outcomes}}
Decreased performance is the most recognized consequence of stereotype threat. However, research has also shown that stereotype threat can cause individuals to blame themselves for perceived failures,&lt;ref name="Women and computers"&gt;{{cite journal| vauthors = Koch S, Muller S, Sieverding M |title=Women and computers. Effects of stereotype threat on attribution of failure|journal=Computers &amp; Education|volume=51|issue=4|year=2008|pages=1795–1803|issn=0360-1315|doi=10.1016/j.compedu.2008.05.007|url=http://archiv.ub.uni-heidelberg.de/volltextserver/19328/1/Koch-M%C3%BCller-Sieverding_women_computers_2008.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[self-handicapping|self-handicap]],&lt;ref name="SteeleAronson" /&gt; discount the value and validity of performance tasks,&lt;ref name="Discounting the Difficult"&gt;{{cite journal| vauthors = Lesko AC, Corpus JH |title=Discounting the Difficult: How High Math-Identified Women Respond to Stereotype Threat|journal=Sex Roles|volume=54|issue=1–2|year=2006|pages=113–125|issn=0360-0025|doi=10.1007/s11199-005-8873-2|s2cid=144649525}}&lt;/ref&gt; distance themselves from negatively stereotyped groups,&lt;ref name="Identity and Achievement"&gt;{{cite journal| vauthors = Cohen GL, Garcia J |title=Identity, Belonging, and Achievement: A Model, Interventions, Implications|journal=Current Directions in Psychological Science|volume=17|issue=6|year=2008|pages=365–369|issn=0963-7214|doi=10.1111/j.1467-8721.2008.00607.x|s2cid=141427088}}&lt;/ref&gt; and disengage from situations that are perceived as threatening.&lt;ref name="Coping with Negative Stereotypes"&gt;{{cite journal| vauthors = Major B, Spencer S, Schmader T, Wolfe C, Crocker J |title=Coping with Negative Stereotypes about Intellectual Performance: The Role of Psychological Disengagement|journal=Personality and Social Psychology Bulletin|volume=24|issue=1|year=1998|pages=34–50|issn=0146-1672|doi=10.1177/0146167298241003|hdl=2027.42/68558|s2cid=145328690|url=https://deepblue.lib.umich.edu/bitstream/2027.42/68558/2/10.1177_0146167298241003.pdf|hdl-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Studies examining stereotype threat in Black Americans have found that when subjects are aware of the stereotype of [[Criminal stereotype of African Americans|Black criminality]], anxiety about encountering police increases. This, in turn, can lead to self-regulatory efforts, more anxiety, and other behaviors that are commonly perceived as suspicious to police officers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Najdowski CJ, Bottoms BL, Goff PA | title = Stereotype threat and racial differences in citizens' experiences of police encounters | journal = Law and Human Behavior | volume = 39 | issue = 5 | pages = 463–77 | date = October 2015 | pmid = 26030449 | doi = 10.1037/lhb0000140 | url = https://www.apa.org/pubs/journals/features/lhb-lhb0000140.pdf }}&lt;/ref&gt; Because police officers tend to perceive Black people as threatening, their reactions to these anxiety-induced behaviors are commonly more harsh than reactions to White people with the same behavior, and influences whether or not they decide to [[Police brutality in the United States|shoot the person]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Eberhardt JL, Goff PA, Purdie VJ, Davies PG | title = Seeing black: race, crime, and visual processing | journal = Journal of Personality and Social Psychology | volume = 87 | issue = 6 | pages = 876–93 | date = December 2004 | pmid = 15598112 | doi = 10.1037/0022-3514.87.6.876 | citeseerx = 10.1.1.486.8434 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Graham S, Lowery BS | title = Priming unconscious racial stereotypes about adolescent offenders | journal = Law and Human Behavior | volume = 28 | issue = 5 | pages = 483–504 | date = October 2004 | pmid = 15638206 | doi = 10.1023/B:LAHU.0000046430.65485.1f | url = https://www.gsb.stanford.edu/faculty-research/working-papers/priming-unconscious-racial-stereotypes-about-adolescent-offenders | citeseerx = 10.1.1.595.3436 | s2cid = 15006874 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Correll J, Park B, Judd CM, Wittenbrink B | title = The police officer's dilemma: using ethnicity to disambiguate potentially threatening individuals | journal = Journal of Personality and Social Psychology | volume = 83 | issue = 6 | pages = 1314–29 | date = December 2002 | pmid = 12500813 | doi = 10.1037/0022-3514.83.6.1314 | s2cid = 7473245 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|vauthors=Correll J, Park B, Judd CM, Wittenbrink B|date=3 July 2007|title=The influence of stereotypes on decisions to shoot|url=https://faculty.chicagobooth.edu/bernd.wittenbrink/research/pdf/cpjw07.pdf|journal=European Journal of Social Psychology|volume=37|issue=6|pages=1102–1117|doi=10.1002/ejsp.450|access-date=19 November 2021|archive-date=21 February 2020|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20200221125318/https://faculty.chicagobooth.edu/bernd.wittenbrink/research/pdf/cpjw07.pdf|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Correll J, Park B, Judd CM, Wittenbrink B, Sadler MS, Keesee T | title = Across the thin blue line: police officers and racial bias in the decision to shoot | journal = Journal of Personality and Social Psychology | volume = 92 | issue = 6 | pages = 1006–23 | date = June 2007 | pmid = 17547485 | doi = 10.1037/0022-3514.92.6.1006 | url = http://faculty.chicagobooth.edu/bernd.wittenbrink/research/pdf/cpjwsk07.pdf | access-date = 2021-11-19 | archive-date = 2020-06-05 | archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20200605173215/https://faculty.chicagobooth.edu/bernd.wittenbrink/research/pdf/cpjwsk07.pdf | url-status = dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the long run, the chronic experience of stereotype threat may lead individuals to disidentify with the stereotyped group. For example, a woman may stop seeing herself as "a math person" after experiencing a series of situations in which she experienced stereotype threat. This disidentification is thought to be a psychological coping strategy to maintain [[self-esteem]] in the face of failure.&lt;ref name="Learning in a Man's World"&gt;{{cite journal| vauthors = Steele J, James JB, Barnett RC |title=Learning in a Man's World: Examining the Perceptions of Undergraduate Women in Male-Dominated Academic Areas|journal=Psychology of Women Quarterly|volume=26|issue=1|year=2002|pages=46–50|issn=0361-6843|doi=10.1111/1471-6402.00042|s2cid=55384021}}&lt;/ref&gt; Repeated exposure to anxiety and nervousness can lead individuals to choose to distance themselves from the stereotyped group.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.thehindu.com/thread/arts-culture-society/article9022211.ece|title=Math is awesome, math culture is terrible| vauthors = Desikan S |date=2016-08-23|work=The Hindu|access-date=2019-10-13|issn=0971-751X}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Although much of the research on stereotype threat has examined the effects of coping with negative stereotype on academic performance, recently there has been an emphasis on how coping with stereotype threat could "spillover" to dampen self-control and thereby affect a much broader category of behaviors, even in non-stereotyped domains.&lt;ref name="stereotype threat spillover"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Inzlicht M, Kang SK | title = Stereotype threat spillover: how coping with threats to social identity affects aggression, eating, decision making, and attention | journal = Journal of Personality and Social Psychology | volume = 99 | issue = 3 | pages = 467–81 | date = September 2010 | pmid = 20649368 | doi = 10.1037/a0018951 | url = http://michaelinzlicht.com/research/publications/Inzlicht%20&amp;%20Kang,%202010.pdf | citeseerx = 10.1.1.600.1063 | archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20120306003450/http://www.michaelinzlicht.com/research/publications/Inzlicht%20%26%20Kang%2C%202010.pdf | url-status = dead | archive-date = 2012-03-06 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Research by [[Michael Inzlicht]] and colleagues suggest that, when women cope with negative stereotypes about their math ability, they perform worse on math tests, and that, well after completing the math test, women may continue to show deficits even in unrelated domains. For example, women might overeat, be more aggressive, make more risky decisions,&lt;ref name="stereotype threat spillover" /&gt; and show less endurance during physical exercise.&lt;ref name="ego depletion"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Inzlicht M, McKay L, Aronson J | title = Stigma as ego depletion: how being the target of prejudice affects self-control | journal = Psychological Science | volume = 17 | issue = 3 | pages = 262–9 | date = March 2006 | pmid = 16507068 | doi = 10.1111/j.1467-9280.2006.01695.x | s2cid = 1930863 | url = http://michaelinzlicht.com/research/research_articles/Inzlicht,%20McKay,%20&amp;%20Aronson.pdf | archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20120306003531/http://www.michaelinzlicht.com/research/research_articles/Inzlicht%2C%20McKay%2C%20%26%20Aronson.pdf | url-status = dead | archive-date = 2012-03-06 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The perceived discrimination associated with stereotype threat can also have negative long-term consequences on individuals' [[mental health]]. Perceived discrimination has been extensively investigated in terms of its effects on mental health, with a particular emphasis on [[Depression (mood)|depression]].&lt;ref name="Inzlicht, M. 2012 107–123"&gt;{{cite book | vauthors = Inzlicht M, Tullett AM, Gutsell JN | veditors = Inzlicht M, Schmader T | chapter = Stereotype threat spillover: The short- and long-term effects of coping with threats to social identity | chapter-url = https://books.google.com/books?id=G_EIrkhfQLsC&amp;pg=PT107 | title = Stereotype threat: theory, process, and application |pages=[https://books.google.com/books?id=G_EIrkhfQLsC&amp;pg=107 107–123] | publisher = Oxford University Press | location = New York, New York | year = 2012 | isbn = 9780199732449}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Cross-sectional study|Cross-sectional studies]] involving diverse [[minority group]]s, including those relating to [[internalized racism]], have found that individuals who experience more perceived discrimination are more likely to exhibit depressive symptoms.&lt;ref name="Inzlicht, M. 2012 107–123"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Williams DR, Mohammed SA | title = Discrimination and racial disparities in health: evidence and needed research | journal = Journal of Behavioral Medicine | volume = 32 | issue = 1 | pages = 20–47 | date = February 2009 | pmid = 19030981 | pmc = 2821669 | doi = 10.1007/s10865-008-9185-0 | url = http://scholar.harvard.edu/files/davidrwilliams/files/2009-discrimination_and_racial-williams.pdf/ }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Mouzon DM, McLean JS | title = Internalized racism and mental health among African-Americans, US-born Caribbean Blacks, and foreign-born Caribbean Blacks | journal = Ethnicity &amp; Health | volume = 22 | issue = 1 | pages = 36–48 | date = February 2017 | pmid = 27354264 | doi = 10.1080/13557858.2016.1196652 | s2cid = 4628237 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, perceived discrimination has also been found to predict depressive symptoms in children and adolescents.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Brody GH, Chen YF, Murry VM, Ge X, Simons RL, Gibbons FX, Gerrard M, Cutrona CE | display-authors = 6 | title = Perceived discrimination and the adjustment of African American youths: a five-year longitudinal analysis with contextual moderation effects | journal = Child Development | volume = 77 | issue = 5 | pages = 1170–89 | year = 2006 | pmid = 16999791 | doi = 10.1111/j.1467-8624.2006.00927.x }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Greene ML, Way N, Pahl K | title = Trajectories of perceived adult and peer discrimination among Black, Latino, and Asian American adolescents: patterns and psychological correlates | journal = Developmental Psychology | volume = 42 | issue = 2 | pages = 218–36 | date = March 2006 | pmid = 16569162 | doi = 10.1037/0012-1649.42.2.218 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Other negative mental health outcomes associated with perceived discrimination include a reduced general well-being, [[Posttraumatic stress disorder|post-traumatic stress disorder]], anxiety, and rebellious behavior.&lt;ref name="Inzlicht, M. 2012 107–123"/&gt; A [[meta-analysis]] conducted by Pascoe and Smart Richman has shown that the strong link between perceived discrimination and negative mental health persists even after controlling for factors such as education, [[socioeconomic status]], and employment.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Pascoe EA, Smart Richman L | title = Perceived discrimination and health: a meta-analytic review | journal = Psychological Bulletin | volume = 135 | issue = 4 | pages = 531–54 | date = July 2009 | pmid = 19586161 | pmc = 2747726 | doi = 10.1037/a0016059 | hdl = 10161/11809 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Mitigation==
Additional research seeks ways to boost the test scores and academic achievement of students in negatively stereotyped groups. Such studies suggest various ways in which the effects of stereotype threat may be mitigated.  For example, there have been increasing concerns about the negative effects of stereotype threats on MCAT, SAT, LSAT scores, etc.&lt;ref name="scholarship.law.bu.edu"/&gt;  One effort at mitigation of the negative consequences of stereotype threat involves rescaling standardized test scores to adjust for the adverse effects of stereotypes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal| vauthors = Feingold J, Souza D |date=2013|title=Measuring the Racial Unevenness of Law School|url=https://scholarship.law.bu.edu/faculty_scholarship/831|journal=Berkeley Journal of African-American Law &amp; Policy|volume=15|page=96}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Perhaps most prominently, well replicated findings suggest that teaching students to re-evaluate stress and adopt an incremental theory of intelligence can be an effective way to mitigate the effects of stereotype threat. Two studies sought to measure the effects of persuading participants that intelligence is malleable and can be increased through effort. Both suggested that if people believe that they can improve their performance based on effort, they are more likely to believe that they can overcome negative stereotypes, and thus perform well.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|vauthors=Aronson J, Fried CB, Good C|year=2002|title=Reducing the Effects of Stereotype Threat on African American College Students by Shaping Theories of Intelligence|journal=Journal of Experimental Social Psychology|volume=38|issue=2|pages=113–125|citeseerx=10.1.1.411.6221|doi=10.1006/jesp.2001.1491|issn=0022-1031}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="malleable intelligence"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Good C, Aronson J, Inzlicht M |year=2003|title=Improving Adolescents' Standardized Test Performance: An Intervention to Reduce the Effects of Stereotype Threat|url=http://michaelinzlicht.com/research/research_articles/Good,%20Aronson,%20Inzlicht,%202003.pdf|url-status=dead|journal=Journal of Applied Developmental Psychology|volume=24|issue=6|pages=645–662|doi=10.1016/j.appdev.2003.09.002|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120426082553/http://michaelinzlicht.com/research/research_articles/Good,%20Aronson,%20Inzlicht,%202003.pdf|archive-date=2012-04-26|name-list-style=vanc}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another study found that having students reexamine their situation or anxiety can help their executive resources (attentional control, working memory, etc.), rather than allowing stress to deplete them, and thus improve test performance.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Johns M, Inzlicht M, Schmader T | title = Stereotype threat and executive resource depletion: examining the influence of emotion regulation | journal = Journal of Experimental Psychology. General | volume = 137 | issue = 4 | pages = 691–705 | date = November 2008 | pmid = 18999361 | pmc = 2976617 | doi = 10.1037/a0013834 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Subsequent research has found that students who are taught an incremental view of intelligence do not attribute academic setbacks to their innate ability, but rather to a situational attribute such as a poor study strategy. As a result, students are more likely to implement alternative study strategies and seek help from others.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal| vauthors = Yeager D |date=2011|title=Social-Psychological interventions in education: They're not magic|journal=Review of Educational Research|volume=81|issue=2|pages=267–301|doi=10.3102/0034654311405999|s2cid=14405719|name-list-style=vanc}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Research on the power of [[self-affirmation]] exercises has shown promising results as well. One such study found that a self-affirmation exercise (in the form of a brief in-class writing assignment about a value that is important to them) significantly improved the grades of African-American middle-school students, and reduced the racial achievement gap by 40%.&lt;ref name=":11" /&gt; The authors of this study suggest that the racial achievement gap could be at least partially ameliorated by brief and targeted social-psychological interventions.&lt;ref name=":11"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Cohen GL, Garcia J, Apfel N, Master A | title = Reducing the racial achievement gap: a social-psychological intervention | journal = Science | volume = 313 | issue = 5791 | pages = 1307–10 | date = September 2006 | pmid = 16946074 | doi = 10.1126/science.1128317 | bibcode = 2006Sci...313.1307C | s2cid = 34989510 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Another such intervention was attempted with UK medical students, who were given a written assignment and a clinical assessment. For the written assignment group, white students performed worse than minority students. For the clinical assessment, both groups improved their performance, though the gap between racial groups was maintained.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Woolf K, McManus IC, Gill D, Dacre J | title = The effect of a brief social intervention on the examination results of UK medical students: a cluster randomised controlled trial | journal = BMC Medical Education | volume = 9 | pages = 35 | date = June 2009 | pmid = 19552810 | pmc = 2717066 | doi = 10.1186/1472-6920-9-35 | doi-access = free }}&lt;/ref&gt; Allowing participants to think about a positive value or attribute about themselves prior to completing the task seemed to make them less susceptible to stereotype threat. Self-affirmation has also been shown to mitigate the performance gap between female and male participants on mathematical and geometrical reasoning tests.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal| vauthors = Martens A, Johns M, Greenberg J, Schimel J |date=2006|title=Combating stereotype threat: The effect of self-affirmation on women's intellectual performance |journal=Journal of Experimental Social Psychology|volume=42 | issue = 2 |pages=236–243|doi=10.1016/j.jesp.2005.04.010|hdl=10092/507|hdl-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, it has been shown that encouraging women to think about their multiple roles and identities by creating self-concept map can eliminate the gender gap on a relatively difficult standardized test. Women given such an opportunity for reflection did equally well as men on the math portion of the [[Graduate Record Examinations|GRE]], while women who did not create a self-concept map did significantly worse on the math section than men did.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal| vauthors = Gresky D |date=2005|title=Effects of Salient Multiple Identities on women's performance under mathematics stereotype threat|journal=Sex Roles|volume=53|issue=9–10|pages=703–716|doi=10.1007/s11199-005-7735-2|s2cid=73702463|name-list-style=vanc}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Increasing the representation of minority groups in a field has also been shown to mitigate stereotype threat. In one study, women in [[Science, technology, engineering, and mathematics|STEM]] fields were shown a video of a conference with either a balanced or unbalanced ratio of men to women. The women viewing an unbalanced ratio reported a lower sense of belonging and less desire to participate. Decreasing cues that reflect only a majority group and increasing cues of minority groups can create environments that mitigate against stereotype threat.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Murphy MC, Steele CM, Gross JJ | title = Signaling threat: how situational cues affect women in math, science, and engineering settings | journal = Psychological Science | volume = 18 | issue = 10 | pages = 879–885 | date = October 2007 | pmid = 17894605 | doi = 10.1111/j.1467-9280.2007.01995.x | name-list-style = vanc | s2cid = 21648665 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Further research has focused on constructing environments such that the physical objects in the environment do not reflect one majority group. For instance, in one study, researchers argued that individuals make decisions about group membership based on the group's environment and showed that altering the physical objects in a room boosted minority participation. In this study, removing stereotypical computer science objects and replacing them with non-stereotypical objects increased female participation in computer science to an equal level as male peers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Cheryan S, Plaut VC, Davies PG, Steele CM | title = Ambient belonging: how stereotypical cues impact gender participation in computer science | journal = Journal of Personality and Social Psychology | volume = 97 | issue = 6 | pages = 1045–1060 | date = December 2009 | pmid = 19968418 | doi = 10.1037/a0016239 | author-link1 = Sapna Cheryan }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Directly communicating that diversity is valued may also be effective. One study revealed that a company's pamphlet stating a direct value of diversity, compared to a color blind approach, caused African Americans to report an increase in trust and comfort towards the company.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Purdie-Vaughns V, Steele CM, Davies PG, Ditlmann R, Crosby JR | title = Social identity contingencies: how diversity cues signal threat or safety for African Americans in mainstream institutions | journal = Journal of Personality and Social Psychology | volume = 94 | issue = 4 | pages = 615–630 | date = April 2008 | pmid = 18361675 | doi = 10.1037/0022-3514.94.4.615 | citeseerx = 10.1.1.468.8070 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Promoting cross-group relations between people of varying backgrounds has also been shown to be effective at promoting a sense of belonging among minority group members. For instance, a 2008 study indicates that students have a lower sense of belonging at institutions where they are the minority, but developing friendships with members of other racial groups increased their sense of belonging.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Mendoza-Denton R, Page-Gould E | title = Can cross-group friendships influence minority students' well-being at historically white universities? | journal = Psychological Science | volume = 19 | issue = 9 | pages = 933–939 | date = September 2008 | pmid = 18947360 | doi = 10.1111/j.1467-9280.2008.02179.x | s2cid = 10524027 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2007, a study by Greg Walton and Geoffrey Cohen showed results in boosting the grades of African-American college students, and eliminating the racial achievement gap between them and their white peers over the first year of college, by emphasizing to participants that concerns about social belonging tend to lessen over time.&lt;ref name="Social belonging"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Walton GM, Cohen GL | title = A question of belonging: race, social fit, and achievement | journal = Journal of Personality and Social Psychology | volume = 92 | issue = 1 | pages = 82–96 | date = January 2007 | pmid = 17201544 | doi = 10.1037/0022-3514.92.1.82 | citeseerx = 10.1.1.320.7960 }}&lt;/ref&gt; These findings suggest that allowing individuals to feel as though they are welcomed into a desirable group makes them more likely to ignore stereotypes. The upshot is that if minority college students are welcomed into the world of academia, they are less likely to be influenced by the negative stereotypes of poor minority performance on academic tasks.&lt;ref name="Social belonging" /&gt;

One early study suggested that simply informing college women about stereotype threat and its effects on performance was sufficient to eliminate the predicted gender gap on a difficult math test.&lt;ref name="pmid15733195"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Johns M, Schmader T, Martens A | title = Knowing is half the battle: teaching stereotype threat as a means of improving women's math performance | journal = Psychological Science | volume = 16 | issue = 3 | pages = 175–179 | date = March 2005 | pmid = 15733195 | doi = 10.1111/j.0956-7976.2005.00799.x | s2cid = 10010358 | url = https://halshs.archives-ouvertes.fr/halshs-01584247/file/geriatrics-01-00020%20%281%29.pdf }}&lt;/ref&gt; The authors of this study argued that making people aware of the fact that they will not necessarily perform worse despite the existence of a stereotype can boost their performance.&lt;ref name="pmid15733195" /&gt; However, other research has found that merely providing information is not enough, and can even have the opposite effect. In one study, women were given a text "summarizing an experiment in which stereotypes, and not biological differences, were shown to be the cause of women's underperformance in math", and then they performed a math exercise. It was found that "women who properly understood the meaning of the information provided, and thus became knowledgeable about stereotype threat, performed significantly worse at a calculus task".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|vauthors=Tomasetto C, Appoloni A|date=June 2013|title=A lesson not to be learned? Understanding stereotype threat does not protect women from stereotype threat|journal=Social Psychology of Education|volume=16|issue=2|pages=199–213|doi=10.1007/s11218-012-9210-6|s2cid=144471307}}&lt;/ref&gt; In such cases, further research suggests that the manner in which the information is presented –– that is, whether subjects are made to perceive themselves as targets of negative stereotyping –– may be decisive.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Wout DA, Shih MJ, Jackson JS, Sellers RM | title = Targets as perceivers: how people determine when they will be negatively stereotyped | journal = Journal of Personality and Social Psychology | volume = 96 | issue = 2 | pages = 349–362 | date = February 2009 | pmid = 19159136 | pmc = 2791406 | doi = 10.1037/a0012880 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Criticism==
Some researchers have argued that stereotype threat should not be interpreted as a factor in real-world [[Achievement gaps in the United States|achievement gaps]].&lt;ref name="Sackett2004a" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Stoet2012" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Ganley2013" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal| vauthors = Whaley AL |year=2017|title=Advances in stereotype threat research on African Americans: continuing challenges to the validity of its role in the achievement gap|journal=Social Psychology of Education|volume=21|issue=1|pages=111–137|doi=10.1007/s11218-017-9415-9|s2cid=148588128}}&lt;/ref&gt; Reviews have raised concerns that the effect might have been over-estimated in the performance of schoolgirls and argued that the field likely suffers from [[publication bias]].&lt;ref name="Flore2014" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Ganley2013" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Stoet2012" /&gt;

According to Paul R. Sackett, Chaitra M. Hardison, and Michael J. Cullen, both the media and scholarly literature have wrongly concluded that eliminating stereotype threat could completely eliminate differences in test performance between European Americans and African Americans.&lt;ref name="Sackett2004a"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Sackett PR, Hardison CM, Cullen MJ | title = On interpreting stereotype threat as accounting for African American-White differences on cognitive tests | journal = The American Psychologist | volume = 59 | issue = 1 | pages = 7–13 | date = January 2004 | pmid = 14736315 | doi = 10.1037/0003-066X.59.1.7 | url = http://www2.uni-jena.de/svw/igc/studies/ss03/sackitt_hardison_cullen_2004.pdf | url-status = dead | archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20130404150510/http://www2.uni-jena.de/svw/igc/studies/ss03/sackitt_hardison_cullen_2004.pdf | archive-date = 2013-04-04 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Sackett et al. argued that, in Steele and Aronson's (1995) experiments where stereotype threat was mitigated, an achievement gap of approximately one [[standard deviation]] remained between the groups, which is very close in size to that routinely reported between African American and European Americans' average scores on large-scale standardized tests such as the SAT. In subsequent correspondence between Sackett et al. and Steele and Aronson, Sackett et al. wrote that "They [Steele and Aronson] agree that it is a misinterpretation of the Steele and Aronson (1995) results to conclude that eliminating stereotype threat eliminates the African American-White test-score gap."&lt;ref name="Sackett2004b"&gt;{{cite journal| vauthors = Sackett PR, Hardison CM, Cullen MJ |title=On the Value of Correcting Mischaracterizations of Stereotype Threat Research|journal=American Psychologist|volume=59|issue=1|year=2004|pages=48–49|issn=1935-990X|doi=10.1037/0003-066X.59.1.48|url=https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/85192141/2004-sackett.pdf|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160304050208/https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/85192141/2004-sackett.pdf|archive-date=2016-03-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, in that same correspondence, Steele and Aronson point out that "it is the stereotype threat conditions, and not the no-threat conditions, that produce group differences most like those of real-life testing."&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Steele CM, Aronson JA | title = Stereotype threat does not live by Steele and Aronson (1995) alone | journal = The American Psychologist | volume = 59 | issue = 1 | pages = 47–48; discussion 48–49 | date = January 2004 | pmid = 14736323 | doi = 10.1037/0003-066X.59.1.47 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In a 2009 meta-analysis, Gregory M. Walton and Steven J. Spencer argued that studies of stereotype threat may in fact systematically under-represent its effects, since such studies measure "only that portion of psychological threat that research has identified and remedied. To the extent that unidentified or unremedied psychological threats further undermine performance, the results underestimate the bias."&lt;ref name=":5" /&gt; Despite these limitations, they found that efforts to mitigate stereotype threat significantly reduced group differences on high-stakes tests.&lt;ref name=":5" /&gt;

In 1998, [[Arthur R. Jensen]] criticized stereotype threat theory on the basis that it invokes an additional mechanism to explain effects which could be, according to him, explained by other, at the time better known and more established theories, such as [[test anxiety]] and especially the [[Yerkes–Dodson law]]. In Jensen's view, the effects which are attributed to stereotype threat may simply reflect "the interaction of ability level with test anxiety as a function of test complexity".&lt;ref name=jensen&gt;{{citation | vauthors = Jensen AR | author-link = Arthur Robert Jensen | contribution = Population differences in ''g'': causal hypotheses | veditors = Jensen AR | editor-link = Arthur Robert Jensen | title = The g factor: the science of mental ability | pages = [https://archive.org/details/gfactorscienc00jens/page/513 513–515] | publisher = Praeger | location = Westport, Connecticut | year = 1998 | isbn = 9780275961039 | quote = the phenomenon of stereotype threat can be explained in terms of a more general construct, test anxiety, which has been studied since the early days of psychometrics. Test anxiety tends to lower performance levels on tests in proportion to the degree of complexity and the amount of mental effort they require of the subject. The relatively greater effect of test anxiety in the black samples, who had somewhat lower SAT scores, than the white subjects in the Stanford experiments constitutes an example of the Yerkes-Dodson law ... by conducting the same type of experiment using exclusively white (or black) subjects, divided into lower- and higher-ability groups, it might be shown that the phenomenon attributed to stereotype threat has nothing to do with race as such, but results from the interaction of ability level with test anxiety as a function of test complexity. | postscript = . | url = https://archive.org/details/gfactorscienc00jens/page/513 }}&lt;/ref&gt; However, a subsequent study by Johannes Keller specifically controlled for Jensen's hypothesis and still found significant stereotype threat effects.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Keller J | title = Stereotype threat in classroom settings: the interactive effect of domain identification, task difficulty and stereotype threat on female students' maths performance | journal = The British Journal of Educational Psychology | volume = 77 | issue = Pt 2 | pages = 323–338 | date = June 2007 | pmid = 17504550 | doi = 10.1348/000709906X113662 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Gijsbert Stoet and [[David C. Geary]] reviewed the evidence for the stereotype threat explanation of the achievement gap in mathematics between men and women. They concluded that the relevant stereotype threat research has many methodological problems, such as failing to adjust for pre-existing mathematics scores and not having a control group, and that some literature on this topic misrepresents stereotype threat as being more well-established than it is. It was only when using the studies that used adjusted mathematics scores, and not when including the studies that did not make such adjustments, that they found evidence for an effect of stereotype threat.&lt;ref name="Stoet2012"&gt;{{Cite journal | vauthors = Stoet G, Geary DC | doi = 10.1037/a0026617 | title = Can stereotype threat explain the gender gap in mathematics performance and achievement? | journal = Review of General Psychology | volume = 16 | pages = 93–102 | year = 2012 | s2cid = 145724069 |url=http://volition.gla.ac.uk/~stoet/pdf/Stoet-Geary-RGP2012.pdf |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160112130459/http://volition.gla.ac.uk/~stoet/pdf/Stoet-Geary-RGP2012.pdf |archive-date=2016-01-12 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Spencer SJ, Logel C, Davies PG | title = Stereotype Threat | journal = Annual Review of Psychology | volume = 67 | pages = 415–437 | date = 2016 | pmid = 26361054 | doi = 10.1146/annurev-psych-073115-103235 |doi-access=free | s2cid = 6588396 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

A 2019 meta-analysis of 212 studies combining to a total of 10,000 participants found that by limiting the studies examined to those studies that used subtle and less blatant stereotype manipulations, which are more likely to occur in actual high-stakes test scenarios, the actual stereotype threat effect size observed was small to negligible. They also observed a large amount of publication bias, as have other studies on the subject.&lt;ref name="h673"&gt;{{cite journal | last=Shewach | first=Oren R. | last2=Sackett | first2=Paul R. | last3=Quint | first3=Sander | title=Stereotype threat effects in settings with features likely versus unlikely in operational test settings: A meta-analysis. | journal=Journal of Applied Psychology | volume=104 | issue=12 | date=2019 | issn=1939-1854 | doi=10.1037/apl0000420 | pages=1514–1534}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="q999"&gt;{{cite web | last=Dolan | first=Eric W. | title=Largest meta-analysis to date suggests the effects of stereotype threat 'range from negligible to small' | website=PsyPost - Psychology News | date=2019-11-07 | url=https://www.psypost.org/largest-meta-analysis-to-date-suggests-the-effects-of-stereotype-threat-range-from-negligible-to-small/ | access-date=2024-11-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Publication bias ===

A meta-analysis by Flore and Wicherts (2015) concluded that the average reported effect of stereotype threat is small, and that those reports may be inflated by [[publication bias]]. They argued that, correcting for this, the most likely effect size may be near zero.&lt;ref name="Flore2014"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Flore PC, Wicherts JM | title = Does stereotype threat influence performance of girls in stereotyped domains? A meta-analysis | journal = Journal of School Psychology | volume = 53 | issue = 1 | pages = 25–44 | date = February 2015 | pmid = 25636259 | doi = 10.1016/j.jsp.2014.10.002 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Ganley et al. (2013) examined stereotype threat in a well-powered (total number approximately 1000) multi-experiment study and concluded that "no evidence that the mathematics performance of school-age girls was impacted by stereotype threat" was found.&lt;ref name="Ganley2013" /&gt; Positing that large, well-controlled studies have tended to find smaller or non-significant effects, the authors argued that evidence for stereotype threat in children may reflect publication bias. They also suggested that, among the many underpowered studies run, researchers may have selectively published those in which [[false-positive]] effects reached significance.&lt;ref name=Ganley2013/&gt;

A 2020 meta-analysis by Liu et al. found that, while publication bias may inflate the effectiveness of interventions to mitigate stereotype threat, the level of bias is insufficient to overturn the consensus that such interventions are associated with performance benefits.&lt;ref name=":14" /&gt; The authors broke down the studies they analyzed into three types – belief-based, identity-based, and resilience-based – finding greater evidence for publication bias in the last of these and more robust evidence for the effectiveness of intervention in the first two types.&lt;ref name=":14" /&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Golem effect]]
* [[Intergroup anxiety]]
* [[John Henryism]]
* [[Metascience]]
* [[Minority stress]]
* [[Model minority]]
* [[Pygmalion effect]]
* [[Self-fulfilling prophecy]]
* [[Social identity threat]]
* [[Thin-slicing]]
* [[Weathering hypothesis]]

== References ==
{{reflist|30em}}

== Further reading ==
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite news | vauthors = Gladwell M |title=The Art of Failure: Why some people choke and others panic|url=http://www.gladwell.com/2000/2000_08_21_a_choking.html|access-date=29 May 2011|newspaper=The New Yorker|date=21 August 2000|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110514032153/http://www.gladwell.com/2000/2000_08_21_a_choking.html|archive-date=14 May 2011}}
* {{Cite journal | vauthors = Walton GM, Murphy MC, Ryan AM | title = Stereotype threat in organizations: implications for equity and performance | journal = [[Annual Review of Organizational Psychology and Organizational Behavior]] | volume = 2 | pages = 523–550 | doi = 10.1146/annurev-orgpsych-032414-111322 |doi-access=free | date = April 2015 }}
* {{Cite journal | vauthors = Pruysers S, Blais J | title = Why won't Lola run? An experiment examining stereotype threat and political ambition | journal = [[Politics &amp; Gender]] | volume = 13 | issue = 2 | pages = 232–252 | doi = 10.1017/S1743923X16000544 | date = June 2017 | s2cid = 151679445 }}
{{refend}}

== External links ==
* {{cite web |author=American Psychological |year=2006 |url=https://www.apa.org/topics/racism-bias-discrimination/stereotypes |title=Stereotype Threat Widens Achievement Gap}}
* {{cite web |url=https://advisingmatters.berkeley.edu/grow/advancing-practice-libraryarchive/conceptual/understanding-stereotype-threat |title=Understanding Stereotype Threat |publisher=University of California, Berkeley}}
* {{cite web |url=https://teachingcenter.wustl.edu/resources/inclusive-teaching-learning/reducing-stereotype-threat/ |title=Reducing Stereotype Threat |date=18 March 2024 |publisher=Washington University in St. Louis}}

{{Biases}}
{{SocialPsychology}}
{{Discrimination}}

[[Category:Psychological theories]]
[[Category:Stereotypes]]
[[Category:Social inequality]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>