<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20120825193128|509130403" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1809033" pageid="1809033" ns="0" title="Stereotype threat"><revisions><rev timestamp="2012-09-30T23:02:29Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{good article}}
'''Stereotype threat''' is the experience of [[anxiety]] or concern in a situation where a person has the potential to confirm a negative [[stereotype]] about their social group.&lt;ref name="GilovichKeltner2006" /&gt; Since its introduction into the academic literature in 1995, stereotype threat has become one of the most widely studied topics in the field of [[social psychology]].&lt;ref name="An Integrated Process Model of Stereotype Threat Effects on Performance"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Schmader|first1=Toni|last2=Johns|first2=Michael|last3=Forbes|first3=Chad|title=An integrated process model of stereotype threat effects on performance|journal=Psychological Review|volume=115|issue=2|year=2008|pages=336–356|issn=1939-1471|doi=10.1037/0033-295X.115.2.336|pmid=18426293|pmc=2570773}}&lt;/ref&gt;
First described by social psychologist [[Claude Steele]] and his colleagues, stereotype threat has been shown to reduce the performance of individuals who belong to negatively stereotyped groups. If negative stereotypes are present regarding a specific group, they are likely to become anxious about their performance which may hinder their ability to perform at their maximum level. For example, stereotype threat can lower the intellectual performance of African-Americans taking the [[SAT|SAT reasoning test]] used for college entrance in the United States, due to the stereotype that African-Americans are less intelligent than other groups.&lt;ref name="SteeleAronson" /&gt; 

Stereotype threat is a potential contributing factor to long-standing racial and gender gaps in academic performance. However, it may occur whenever an individual's performance might confirm a negative stereotype. This is because stereotype threat is thought to arise from the particular situation rather than from an individual's personality traits or characteristics. Since most people have at least one [[social identity]] which is negatively stereotyped, most people are vulnerable to stereotype threat if they encounter a situation in which the stereotype is relevant. Situational factors that increase stereotype threat can include the difficulty of the task, the belief that the task measures their abilities, and the relevance of the negative stereotype to the task. Individuals show higher degrees of stereotype threat on tasks they wish to perform well on and when they identify strongly with the stereotyped group. These effects are also increased when they expect discrimination due to their identification with negatively stereotyped group.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | title = Contending with Group Image: The Psychology of Stereotype and Social Identity Threat | year = 2002 | journal = Advances in Experimental Social Psychology | pages = 439 | volume = 34 | issue = 379 | last1 = Steele| first1 = Claude M. | last2 = Spencer | first2 = Steven J. | last3 = Aronson| first3 = Joshua}}&lt;/ref&gt; Repeated experiences of stereotype threat can lead to  a [[Virtuous circle and vicious circle|vicious circle]] of diminished confidence, poor performance and loss of interest in the relevant area of achievement.&lt;ref name="GilovichKeltner2006"&gt;{{cite book|last1=Gilovich|first1=Thomas|last2=Keltner|first2=Dacher|last3=Nisbett|first3=Richard E.|title=Social psychology|year=2006|publisher=W.W. Norton|isbn=978-0-393-97875-9|pages=467–468}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

The adverse effect in comparison to stereotype threat is known as stereotype enhancement, which entails an individual's potential to confirm a positive stereotype about their social group, and a subsequent increase in performance ability in the related task as compared to their ability prior to their exposure to the stereotype.{{fact|date=July 2012}}

Advocates of stereotype threat explanation have been criticized for exaggerating the importance of stereotype threat and for misrepresenting evidence as more conclusive than it is.&lt;!-- refs in Criticism section below --&gt;

==Effects on performance==
[[File:Stereotype threat bw.jpg|thumb|right|300px|''The Effects of Stereotype Threat on the Standardized Test Performance of College Students'', J. Aronson, C.M. Steele, M.F. Salinas, M.J. Lustina - Readings About the Social Animal, 8th edition, E. Aronson ]]
In the early 1990s, Claude Steele, in collaboration with Joshua Aronson, performed the first experiments demonstrating that stereotype threat can undermine intellectual performance. They had African-American and European-American college students take a difficult verbal portion of the [[Graduate Record Examination]] test. As would be expected based on national averages, the African-American students performed less well on the test. In a subsequent experiment, Steele and Aronson changed the instructions of the test so that participants no longer believed that the test accurately measured intellectual performance. This change reduced the performance gap between the two groups.&lt;ref name="SteeleAronson"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Steele|first1=Claude M.|last2=Aronson|first2=Joshua|title=Stereotype threat and the intellectual test performance of African Americans|journal=Journal of Personality and Social Psychology|volume=69|issue=5|year=1995|pages=797–811|issn=0022-3514|doi=10.1037/0022-3514.69.5.797|pmid=7473032}}&lt;/ref&gt; Steele and Aronson concluded that changing the instructions on the test can reduce African-American students' concern about confirming a negative stereotype about their group. Supporting this conclusion, they found that African-American students who regarded the test as a measure of intelligence had more thoughts related to negative stereotypes of their group. Steele and Aronson measured this through a word completion task. They found that African-Americans who thought the test measured intelligence were more likely to complete word fragments using words that are associated with relevant negative stereotypes (e.g., completing __mb as "[[wikt:dumb|dumb]]" rather than "[[wikt:numb|numb]]").&lt;ref name="SteeleAronson" /&gt;

More than 300 published papers document the effects of stereotype threat on performance in a variety of domains.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.arizona.edu/sites/arizona.edu/files/users/user14/Stereotype%20Threat%20Overview.pdf |title=Stereotype Threat: An Overview |last1=Stroessner |first1=Steve |last2=Good |first2=Catherine |date= |work=www.dingo.sbs.arizona.edu |publisher=Reducing Stereotype Threat.org |accessdate=6 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Inducing stereotype threat is dependent on the framing of a task. If a task is framed to be neutral, stereotype threat is not likely to occur; however if tasks are framed in terms of active stereotypes, participants are likely to perform worse on the task. 
For example, a [[Chess strategy|study on chess players]] revealed that women players performed more poorly than expected when they were told they would be playing against a male opponent. In contrast, women who were told that their opponent was female performed as would be predicted by past ratings of performance.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Maass|first1=Anne|last2=D'Ettole|first2=Claudio|last3=Cadinu|first3=Mara|title=Checkmate? The role of gender stereotypes in the ultimate intellectual sport|journal=European Journal of Social Psychology|volume=38|issue=2|year=2008|pages=231–245|issn=00462772|doi=10.1002/ejsp.440}}&lt;/ref&gt; Female participants who were made aware of the stereotype of females performing worse at chess than male participants, performed worse in their chess games. The mere presence of other people can evoke stereotype threat. In one experiment, women who took a mathematics exam along with two other women got 70% of the answers right; while those doing the same exam in the presence of two men got an average score of 55%.&lt;ref name="InzlichtBen-Zeev2000"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Inzlicht|first1=M.|last2=Ben-Zeev|first2=T.|title=A Threatening Intellectual Environment: Why Females Are Susceptible to Experiencing Problem-Solving Deficits in the Presence of Males|journal=Psychological Science|volume=11|issue=5|year=2000|pages=365–371|issn=0956-7976|doi=10.1111/1467-9280.00272}}&lt;/ref&gt; Researchers [http://www2.binghamton.edu/som/faculty/gupta.html Vishal Gupta], [http://business.missouri.edu/28/243.aspx Daniel Turban], and [http://www.nachiketbhawe.com/ Nachiket Bhawe] extended stereotype threat research to [[entrepreneurship]], a traditionally male-stereotyped profession. Their study revealed that stereotype threat can depress women's entrepreneurial intentions while boosting men's intentions. However, when entrepreneurship is presented as a gender-neutral profession, men and women express a similar level of interest in becoming entrepreneurs.&lt;ref name = "Stereotype Threat and Entrepreneurial Intentions"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Gupta|first1=V. K.|last2=Bhawe|first2=N. M.|title=The Influence of Proactive Personality and Stereotype Threat on Women's Entrepreneurial Intentions|journal=Journal of Leadership &amp; Organizational Studies|volume=13|issue=4|year=2007|pages=73–85|issn=1071-7919|doi=10.1177/10717919070130040901}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another experiment involved a golf game which was described as a test of "natural athletic ability" or of "sports intelligence". When it was described as a test of athletic ability, European-American students performed worse, but when the description mentioned intelligence, African-American students performed worse.&lt;ref name="StoneLynch1999"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Stone|first1=Jeff|last2=Lynch|first2=Christian I.|last3=Sjomeling|first3=Mike|last4=Darley|first4=John M.|title=Stereotype threat effects on Black and White athletic performance.|journal=Journal of Personality and Social Psychology|volume=77|issue=6|year=1999|pages=1213–1227|issn=0022-3514|doi=10.1037/0022-3514.77.6.1213}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Overall, findings suggest that stereotype threat is likely to occur in any situation where an individual faces the potential of confirming a negative stereotype. For example, stereotype threat can negatively affect the performance of [[European Americans]] in athletic situations&lt;ref name="White Men Can't Jump"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Stone|first1=Jeff|last2=Perry|first2=W.|last3=Darley|first3=John|title="White Men Can't Jump": Evidence for the Perceptual Confirmation of Racial Stereotypes Following a Basketball Game|journal=Basic and Applied Social Psychology|volume=19|issue=3|year=1997|pages=291–306|issn=0197-3533|doi=10.1207/s15324834basp1903_2}}&lt;/ref&gt; as well as men who are being tested on their social sensitivity.&lt;ref name="Stereotype Threat in Men"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Koenig|first1=Anne M.|last2=Eagly|first2=Alice H.|title=Stereotype Threat in Men on a Test of Social Sensitivity|journal=Sex Roles|volume=52|issue=7–8|year=2005|pages=489–496|issn=0360-0025|doi=10.1007/s11199-005-3714-x}}&lt;/ref&gt; The experience of stereotype threat again depends on the framing of a task. An example of framing effects would be a study in which Asian-American women were subjected to a gender stereotype that expected them to be poorer at mathematics than males, and a racial stereotype that expects them to do particularly well. Subjects from this group performed better on a math test when their racial identity was made salient; and worse when their gender identity was made salient.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation| title = Stereotype Susceptibility: Identity Salience and Shifts in Quantitative Performance| year = 1999| journal = Psychological Science| pages = 80–83| volume = 10| issue = 1| last1 = Shih | first1 = Margaret| last2 = Pittinsky | first2 = Todd L.| last3 = Ambady | first3 = Nalini |doi=10.1111/1467-9280.00111}}&lt;/ref&gt; This study illustrates how stereotypes can either positively or negatively influence participants performance, depending on the direction of the stereotype.  

[[File:Stereotype threat - osborne 2007.png|thumb|right|350px|The effect of Stereotype Threat (ST) on math test scores for girls and boys. Data from Osborne (2007).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Osborne|first1=Jason W.|title=Linking Stereotype Threat and Anxiety|journal=Educational Psychology|volume=27|issue=1|year=2007|pages=135–154|issn=0144-3410|doi=10.1080/01443410601069929}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
Although the framing of a task can produce stereotype threat in most individuals, certain individuals appear to be more likely to experience stereotype threat than others. Individuals who are highly identified with a particular group appear to be more vulnerable to experiencing stereotype threat than individuals who do not identify strongly with the stereotyped group. 

The goal of the study Desert, Preaux, and Jund was to see if children from lower socioeconomic groups are affected by stereotype threat. The study that was conducted took children that were 6-7 years old and children that were 8-9 years old from multiple elementary schools, and presented them with Raven’s matrix test (which is an intellectual ability test and then answering a short questionnaire). Separate groups of children were given directions in an evaluative way and other groups were given directions in a non-evaluative way. The "evaluative" group received instructions that are usually given with the Raven matrices test and the "non-evaluative" group was given directions which made it seem as if the children were simply playing a game. The results showed that third graders performed better on the test than the first graders did, which was expected. However, the lower socioeconomic status children did worse on the test when they received directions in an evaluative way than the higher socioeconomic status children did when they received directions in an evaluative way. These results also reflected the hypothesis of the study, which suggested that the framing of the directions given to the children may have a greater effect on their performance than their socioeconomic status does. This was shown by the differences in performance based on which type of instructions they received. This information can be useful in classroom settings to help improve the performance of students of lower socioeconomic status.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Desert|first=Michael|coauthors=Marie Preaux, Robin Jund|title=So young and already victims of stereotype threat: Socio-economic status and performance of 6 to 9 years old children on Raven's progressive matrices.|journal=European Journal of Psychology of Education|year=2009|volume=24|issue=2|pages=207–218|doi=10.1007/BF03173012}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

There have been studies on senior citizens and the effects of stereotype threat based on aging. A study was done on 99 senior citizens ranging in age from 60-75 years. These seniors were given multiple tests on certain factors and categories that they find important such as memory and physical abilities. They were also asked to evaluate how physically fit they believe themselves to be. They were also asked to read articles which contained both positive and negative outlooks about seniors. In addition they watched someone reading the same articles. The goal of this study was to see if priming the participants before the tests would affect performance. The results showed that the control group performed better than those that were primed with either negative or positive words prior to the tests. The control group seemed to feel more confident in their abilities than the other two groups. However, these results could have been affected by the sample of seniors that were used. The participants were all well educated, healthy, and living at a place which was welcoming to seniors. This particular group of seniors may be the ones that could remain resistant to negative stereotype threats towards those who are aging.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Horton|first=Sean|coauthors=Joseph Baker, William Pearce, Janice Deakin|title=Immunity to Popular Stereotypes of Aging? Seniors and Stereotype Threat|journal=Educational Gerontology|year=2010|volume=36|issue=5|pages=353–371|doi=10.1080/03601270903323976}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Mechanisms==
Although numerous studies demonstrate the effects of stereotype threat on performance, questions remain as to the specific cognitive factors which underlie these effects. Steele and Aronson originally speculated that anxiety and narrowed attention, resulting from attempts to suppress stereotype-related thoughts could contribute to the observed deficits in performance. In 2008, Toni Schmader, Michael Johns, and Chad Forbes published an integrated model of stereotype threat that focused on three interrelated factors:&lt;br&gt;
# stress arousal; 
# performance monitoring, which narrows attention; and, 
# efforts to suppress negative thoughts and emotions.&lt;ref name="An Integrated Process Model of Stereotype Threat Effects on Performance"/&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Schmader et al. suggest that these three factors summarize the pattern of evidence that has been accumulated by past experiments on stereotype threat. For example, stereotype threat has been shown to disrupt working memory and executive function,&lt;ref name="Working Memory"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Schmader|first1=Toni|last2=Johns|first2=Michael|title=Converging Evidence That Stereotype Threat Reduces Working Memory Capacity|journal=Journal of Personality and Social Psychology|volume=85|issue=3|year=2003|pages=440–452|issn=0022-3514|doi=10.1037/0022-3514.85.3.440|pmid=14498781}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="ego depletion" /&gt;, increase arousal,&lt;ref name=arousal&gt;{{cite journal|last=Ben-Zeev|first=Talia|coauthors=Fein, Steven; Inzlicht, Michael|title=Stereotype Threat and Arousal|journal=Journal of Experimental Social Psychology|volume=41|pages=174–181|url=http://michaelinzlicht.com/research/research_articles/Ben-Zeev,%20Fein,%20Inzlicht.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; increase self-consciousness about one's performance,&lt;ref name="Causal Mechanisms of Stereotype Threat"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Beilock|first1=S. L.|title=On the Causal Mechanisms of Stereotype Threat: Can Skills That Don't Rely Heavily on Working Memory Still Be Threatened?|journal=Personality and Social Psychology Bulletin|volume=32|issue=8|year=2006|pages=1059–1071|issn=0146-1672|doi=10.1177/0146167206288489|pmid=16861310|last2=Jellison|first2=WA|last3=Rydell|first3=RJ|last4=McConnell|first4=AR|last5=Carr|first5=TH}}&lt;/ref&gt; and cause individuals to try and suppress negative thoughts as well as negative emotions such as anxiety.&lt;ref name="emotion regulation"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Johns|first=Mike|coauthors=Inzlicht, Michael; Schmader, Toni|title=Stereotype Threat and Executive Resource Depletion: The Influence of Emotion Regulation|journal=Journal of Experimental Psychology: General|year=2008|volume=137|pages=691–705|url=http://michaelinzlicht.com/research/research_articles/Johns,%20Inzlicht,%20&amp;%20Schmader,%202008.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; People have a limited amount of cognitive resources available. When a large portion of these resources are spent focusing on anxiety and nervousness, the individual is likely to perform worse on the task at hand. 

A number of studies looking at physiological and neurological responses support Schmader, Johns, and Forbes' integrated model of the processes that produce stereotype threat. Supporting an explanation in terms of stress arousal, one study found that African-Americans under stereotype threat exhibit larger increases in arterial [[blood pressure]].&lt;ref name = "blood pressure"&gt;{{cite journal |author=Blascovich J, Spencer SJ, Quinn D, Steele C |title=African Americans and high blood pressure: the role of stereotype threat |journal=Psychologial Science |volume=12 |issue=3 |pages=225–9 |year=2001 |month=May |pmid=11437305 |doi=10.1111/1467-9280.00340 }}&lt;/ref&gt; One study found increased cardiovascular activation amongst women who watched a video in which men outnumbered women at a math and science conference.&lt;ref name="Mary Murphy study"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Murphy|first1=M. C.|last2=Steele|first2=C. M.|last3=Gross|first3=J. J.|title=Signaling Threat: How Situational Cues Affect Women in Math, Science, and Engineering Settings|journal=Psychological Science|volume=18|issue=10|year=2007|pages=879–885|issn=0956-7976|doi=10.1111/j.1467-9280.2007.01995.x|pmid=17894605}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other studies have similarly found that individuals under stereotype threat display increased heart rates.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Croizet JC, Després G, Gauzins ME, Huguet P, Leyens JP, Méot A |title=Stereotype threat undermines intellectual performance by triggering a disruptive mental load |journal=Personality and Social Psychology Bulletin |volume=30 |issue=6 |pages=721–31 |year=2004 |month=June |pmid=15155036 |doi=10.1177/0146167204263961 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Stereotype threat may also activate a [[Neuroendocrine system|neuroendocrine stress response]], as measured by increased levels of [[cortisol]] while under threat.&lt;ref name="Cortisol"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Townsend|first1=S. S. M.|last2=Major|first2=B.|last3=Gangi|first3=C. E.|last4=Mendes|first4=W. B.|title=From "In the Air" to "Under the Skin": Cortisol Responses to Social Identity Threat|journal=Personality and Social Psychology Bulletin|volume=37|issue=2|year=2011|pages=151–164|issn=0146-1672|doi=10.1177/0146167210392384|pmid=21239591}}&lt;/ref&gt; The physiological reactions which are induced by stereotype threat can often be subconscious, and can distract and interrupt cognitive focus from the task. 

In regards to performance monitoring and vigilance, studies of brain activity have supported the idea that stereotype threat increases both of these processes. Forbes and colleagues evoked electroencephalogram ([[EEG]]) signals which measure electrical activity along the scalp. This allowed the researchers ascertain that individuals experiencing stereotype threat were more vigilant for performance related stimuli.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | title = The role of devaluing and discounting in performance monitoring: a neurophysiological study of minorities under threat | year = 2008 | journal = Social Cognitive Affective Neuroscience | pages = 253–261 | volume = 3 | last1 = Forbes | first1 = C. | last2 = Schmader | first2 = T.| last3 = Allen | first3 = J.J.B.|doi=10.1093/scan/nsn012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another used functional magnetic resonance ([[fMRI]]) to investigate brain activity associated with stereotype threat.[[File:Gray727 anterior cingulate cortex.png|thumb|right|300px|Researchers found that women experiencing stereotype threat while taking a math test showed heightened activation in the ventral stream of the [[anterior cingulate cortex]] (ACC).]] The researchers found that women experiencing stereotype threat while taking a math test showed heightened activation in the ventral stream of the [[anterior cingulate cortex]] (ACC), a neural region thought to be associated with social and emotional processing.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | title = The negative consequences of threat: A functional magnetic resonance imaging investigation of the neural mechanisms underlying women's underperformance in math | year = 1995 | journal = Psychological Science | pages = 168–175 | volume = 19 | issue = 2 | last1 = Krendle | first1 = Anne C. | last2 = Richeson | first2 = Jennifer A. | last3 = Kelley | first3 = William M. | last4 = Heatherton | first4 = Todd F. |doi=10.1111/j.1467-9280.2008.02063.x}}&lt;/ref&gt; Wraga and colleagues found that women under stereotype threat showed increased activation in the ventral ACC and the amount of this activation predicted performance decrements on the task.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Wraga|first1=M.|last2=Helt|first2=M.|last3=Jacobs|first3=E.|last4=Sullivan|first4=K.|title=Neural basis of stereotype-induced shifts in women's mental rotation performance|journal=Social Cognitive and Affective Neuroscience|volume=2|issue=1|year=2006|pages=12–19|issn=1749-5016|doi=10.1093/scan/nsl041}}&lt;/ref&gt; When individuals were made aware of a performance related stimuli, they were more likely to experience stereotype threat. 

A study done by Rydell, Rydell, and Boucher has shown that not only can stereotype threat effect performance but it can also affect the ability to learn new information. A study was done on undergraduate women in which half of them were presented with “gender fair” information and the other half was not. In addition, the study also investigated the benefit of the “gender fair” information on women taking a mathematical test. The women were split into four separate condition groups: control group, stereotype threat only, stereotype threat removed before learning, and stereotype threat removed after learning. The results of the study showed that the women who were presented with the “gender fair” information performed better on the math related test than the women who were not presented with this information. This study also showed that it is more beneficial for the “gender fair” information to be presented prior to learning rather than after learning. This topic does need further study but these results do show that eliminating threat prior to women taking mathematical tests can help them to perform better. It seems that if stereotype is recognized prior to the test, performance will decrease.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Boucher|first=Kathryn L.|coauthors=Robert Rydell, Katie Van Loo, Michael Rydell|title=Reducing Stereotype threat in order to facilitate learning.|journal=European Journal of Social Psychology|year=2012|volume=42|issue=2|pages=174–179|doi=10.1002/ejsp.871}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 
A similar study showed that the number of math problems that women chose to attempt was reduced due to the activation of stereotype threat. This study was done on men and women at a private university who had taken calculus I and higher level math courses. Saliva samples were collected from the participants to obtain cortisol levels. They also had to use a likert scale to rate perceived level of math ability of the male examiner. The results could have been affected by the fact that participants were being evaluated on the number of problems attempted, rather than the number of problems answered correctly which is not typical in normal classroom settings. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Rivardo|first=Mark G.|coauthors=Rhodes, Michael E., Camaione, Tyler C., Legg, Jessica M.|title=Stereotype Threat Leads to Reduction in Number of Math Problems Women Attempt|journal=North American Journal of Psychology|year=2001|volume=13|issue=1|pages=5–16|url=http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_6894/is_1_13/ai_n56920321/|accessdate=12 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

==Long-term and other consequences==
Decreased performance is the most recognized consequence of stereotype threat, however studies have also shown that stereotype threat can also lead individuals blaming themselves for perceived failures,&lt;ref name="Women and computers"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Koch|first1=S|last2=Muller|first2=S|last3=Sieverding|first3=M|title=Women and computers. Effects of stereotype threat on attribution of failure|journal=Computers &amp; Education|volume=51|issue=4|year=2008|pages=1795–1803|issn=03601315|doi=10.1016/j.compedu.2008.05.007}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[self-handicapping|self-handicap]],&lt;ref name="SteeleAronson" /&gt; discount the value and validity of tests and other performance tasks,&lt;ref name="Discounting the Difficult"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Lesko|first1=Alexandra C.|last2=Corpus|first2=Jennifer Henderlong|title=Discounting the Difficult: How High Math-Identified Women Respond to Stereotype Threat|journal=Sex Roles|volume=54|issue=1–2|year=2006|pages=113–125|issn=0360-0025|doi=10.1007/s11199-005-8873-2}}&lt;/ref&gt; distance themselves from negatively stereotyped groups,&lt;ref name="Identity and Achievement"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Cohen|first1=Geoffrey L.|last2=Garcia|first2=Julio|title=Identity, Belonging, and Achievement: A Model, Interventions, Implications|journal=Current Directions in Psychological Science|volume=17|issue=6|year=2008|pages=365–369|issn=09637214|doi=10.1111/j.1467-8721.2008.00607.x}}&lt;/ref&gt; and disengage from situations and environments that are perceived as threatening.&lt;ref name="Coping with Negative Stereotypes"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Major|first1=B.|last2=Spencer|first2=S.|last3=Schmader|first3=T.|last4=Wolfe|first4=C.|last5=Crocker|first5=J. |title=Coping with Negative Stereotypes about Intellectual Performance: The Role of Psychological Disengagement|journal=Personality and Social Psychology Bulletin|volume=24|issue=1|year=1998|pages=34–50|issn=0146-1672|doi=10.1177/0146167298241003}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Over the long-term, the chronic experience of stereotype threat may lead individuals to dis-identify with the group which received the stereotype. For example, a woman may stop seeing herself as "a math person" after experiencing a series of situations in which she experienced stereotype threat. This ''dis-identification'' is thought to be a psychological coping strategy to maintain self-esteem in the face of failure.&lt;ref name="Learning in a Man's World"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Steele|first1=Jennifer|last2=James|first2=Jacquelyn B.|last3=Barnett|first3=Rosalind Chait|title=Learning in a Man's World: Examining the Perceptions of Undergraduate Women in Male-Dominated Academic Areas|journal=Psychology of Women Quarterly|volume=26|issue=1|year=2002|pages=46–50|issn=0361-6843|doi=10.1111/1471-6402.00042}}&lt;/ref&gt; Repeated exposure to anxiety and nervousness can lead individuals to choose to distance themselves from the stereotyped group. 

Although much of the research on stereotype threat has examined the effects of coping with negative stereotype on academic performance, recently there has been an emphasis on how coping with stereotype threat could "spillover" to dampen self-control and thereby affect a much broader category of behaviors, even in non-stereotyped domains.&lt;ref name="stereotype threat spillover"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Inzlicht|first=Michael|coauthors=Kang, Sonia|title=Stereotype threat spillover: How coping with threats to social identity affects, aggression, eating, decision-making, and attention|journal=Journal of Personality and Social Psychology|year=2010|volume=99|pages=467–481|url=http://michaelinzlicht.com/research/publications/Inzlicht%20&amp;%20Kang,%202010.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; Research by Michael Inzlicht suggests that when women cope with negative stereotype about their math ability, they perform worse on math tests. However, even after they have completed the math test, they may continue to show deficits even in unrelated domains; for example, they might be more aggressive, they might overeat, they may make risky decisions&lt;ref name="stereotype threat spillover" /&gt;; they might even show less endurance during physical exercise.&lt;ref name="ego depletion"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Inzlicht|first=Michael|coauthors=McKay, Linda; Aronson, Joshua|title=Stigma as ego-depletion: How being the target of prejudice affects self-control|journal=Psychological Science|year=2006|volume=17|pages=262–269|url=http://michaelinzlicht.com/research/research_articles/Inzlicht,%20McKay,%20&amp;%20Aronson.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Interventions==
Additional research seeks ways to boost the test scores and academic achievement of students in negatively-stereotyped groups. In one study, teaching college women about stereotype threat and its effects on performance was sufficient to eliminate the predicted gender gap on a difficult math test.&lt;ref name="pmid15733195"&gt;{{cite journal |author=Johns M, Schmader T, Martens A |title=Knowing is half the battle: teaching stereotype threat as a means of improving women's math performance |journal=Psychological Science |volume=16 |issue=3 |pages=175–9 |year=2005 |month=March |pmid=15733195 |doi=10.1111/j.0956-7976.2005.00799.x}}&lt;/ref&gt; Making people aware of the fact that they will not necessarily perform worse simply due to the existence of a stereotype, can boost their performance. Another approach involves persuading participants that intelligence is malleable and can be increased through effort. If people believe that they can improve their performance based on effort, they are more likely to believe that they can overcome negative stereotypes and perform well.  &lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Aronson J, Fried CB, Good C|title=Reducing the Effects of Stereotype Threat on African American College Students by Shaping Theories of Intelligence|journal=Journal of Experimental Social Psychology|volume=38|issue=2|year=2002|pages=113–125|issn=00221031|doi=10.1006/jesp.2001.1491}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="malleable intelligence"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Good|first=Catherine|coauthors=Aronson, Joshua; Inzlicht, Michael|title=Improving Adolescents’ Standardized Test Performance: An Intervention to Reduce the Effects of Stereotype Threat|journal=Journal of Applied Developmental Psycholoogy|year=2003|volume=24|pages=645–662|url=http://michaelinzlicht.com/research/research_articles/Good,%20Aronson,%20Inzlicht,%202003.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A third type of intervention involves having participants engage in [[self-affirmation]], which is a process in which participants write about a value that is important to them. In 2006, researchers Geoffrey L. Cohen, Julio Garcia, Nancy Apfel, and Allison Master found that a self-affirmation exercise (in the form of a brief in-class writing assignment) significantly improved the grades of [[African-American]] middle-school students, and reduced the racial achievement gap by 40%. Cohen et al. have suggested that the racial achievement gap could be at least partially ameliorated by brief and targeted social-psychological interventions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Cohen GL, Garcia J, Apfel N, Master A |title=Reducing the racial achievement gap: a social-psychological intervention |journal=Science |volume=313 |issue=5791 |pages=1307–10 |year=2006 |month=September |pmid=16946074 |doi=10.1126/science.1128317}}&lt;/ref&gt; One such intervention was attempted with UK medical students, who were given a written assignment and a clinical assessment. For the written assignment group, white students performed worse than minority students. For the clinical assessment, both groups improved their performance maintaining the racial difference.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Woolf K, McManus IC, Gill D, Dace J |title=The effect of a brief social intervention on the examination results of UK medical students: a cluster randomised controlled trial |journal=BMC Medical Education |volume=9|pages=35 |year=2009 |month=June |pmid= 19552810|doi=10.1186/1472-6920-9-35 |url=http://www.biomedcentral.com/1472-6920/9/35/ |pmc=2717066 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Allowing participants to think about a positive value or attribute about themselves prior to completing the task, seemed to make them less susceptible to stereotype threat. 

A fourth intervention for stereotype threat involves increasing participants' feelings of social belonging within the academic world. Greg Walton and Geoffrey Cohen were able to boost the grades of African-American college students, as well as eliminate the racial achievement gap over the first year of college, by telling participants that concerns about social belonging tend to lessen over time.&lt;ref name="Social belonging"&gt;{{cite journal |author=Walton, G. M.; Cohen, G. L. |title=A question of belonging: race, social fit, and achievement |journal=Journal of Personality and Social Psychology |volume=92 |issue=1 |pages=82–96 |year=2007 |month=January |pmid=17201544 |doi=10.1037/0022-3514.92.1.82 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Allowing individuals to feel as though they are welcomed into a desirable group, they are more likely to ignore stereotypes. If minority college students are welcomed into the world of academia, they are less likely to be influenced by the negative stereotypes of poor minority performance on academic tasks. 

==Criticism==
The stereotype threat explanation of [[achievement gap]]s has attracted criticism. According to Paul R. Sackett, Chaitra M. Hardison, and Michael J. Cullen, both the media and scholarly literature have wrongly concluded that eliminating stereotype threat can completely eliminate differences in test performance between [[European-American]] and [[African-American]] individuals.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal ||last1=Sackett|first1=Paul R.|last2=Hardison|first2=Chaitra M.|last3=Cullen|first3=Michael J.|title=On interpreting stereotype threat as accounting for African American-White differences on cognitive tests |journal=American Psychologist |volume=59 |issue=1 |pages=7–13 |year=2004 |month=January |pmid=14736315 |doi=10.1037/0003-066X.59.1.7 |url=http://www2.uni-jena.de/svw/igc/studies/ss03/sackitt_hardison_cullen_2004.pdf|format=PDF|issn=1935-990X}}&lt;/ref&gt; For example, Sackett et al. have pointed out that in Steele and Aronson's (1995) experiments where stereotype threat was removed, there was still a remaining achievement gap that closely correlates with the gap between African-American and European-Americans' average scores on large-scale standardized tests such as the SAT. In subsequent correspondence between Sackett et al. and Steele and Aronson, Sackett et al. wrote that "They [Steele and Aronson] agree that it is a misinterpretation of the Steele and Aronson (1995) results to conclude that eliminating stereotype threat eliminates the African American-White test-score gap."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Sackett|first1=Paul R.|last2=Hardison|first2=Chaitra M.|last3=Cullen|first3=Michael J.|title=On the Value of Correcting Mischaracterizations of Stereotype Threat Research|journal=American Psychologist|volume=59|issue=1|year=2004|pages=48–49|issn=1935-990X|doi=10.1037/0003-066X.59.1.48}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Gijsbert Stoet and [[David C. Geary]] reviewed the evidence for the stereotype threat explanation of the achievement gap in mathematics between men and women. They concluded that the relevant stereotype threat research has many methodological problems, such as not having a control group, and that the stereotype threat literature on this topic misrepresents itself as "well established". They concluded that the evidence is in fact very weak.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Stoet|first1=Gijsbert|last2=Geary|first2=David C.|title=Can stereotype threat explain the gender gap in mathematics achievement and performance?|journal=Review of General Psychology|volume=16|year=2012|pages=93–102}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Intergroup anxiety]]
* [[Pygmalion effect]]
* [[Self-fulfilling prophecy]]

==References==
{{reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
* {{cite journal|last1=Steele|first1=Claude M.|title=A threat in the air: How stereotypes shape intellectual identity and performance|journal=American Psychologist|volume=52|issue=6|year=1997|pages=613–629|issn=0003-066X|doi=10.1037/0003-066X.52.6.613|pmid=9174398}}
* {{cite book|last1=Inzlicht|first1=Michael|last2=Schmader|first2=Toni|title=Stereotype Threat: Theory, Process, and Application |year=2011|publisher=Oxford University Press|url=http://www.us.oup.com/us/catalog/general/subject/Psychology/Social/?view=usa&amp;view=usa&amp;ci=9780199732449}}
* {{cite news|last=Gladwell|first=Malcolm|title=The Art of Failure: Why some people choke and others panic| url=http://www.gladwell.com/2000/2000_08_21_a_choking.html|accessdate=29 May 2011|newspaper=The New Yorker|date=21 August 2000}}

==External links==
* [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iJAOltce6jI Can stereotype threat explain the sex gap in mathematics achievement and performance?] Video by Gijsbert Stoet, University of Leeds, hosted by Youtube.com

{{biases}}

[[Category:Psychological theories]]
[[Category:Psychology terms]]
[[Category:Social inequality]]

[[ar:خطر الصورة النمطية]]
[[de:Bedrohung durch Stereotype]]
[[fr:Menace du stéréotype]]
[[pl:Zagrożenie stereotypem]]
[[sv:Stereotyphot]]
[[zh:成见威胁]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>