<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20101117202609|397368450" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1809033" pageid="1809033" ns="0" title="Stereotype threat"><revisions><rev timestamp="2010-11-17T20:28:55Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{cleanup|date=November 2009}}

Stereotype threat is when a person who belongs to a group that has a negative stereotype attached to it subconsciously conforms to the negative stereotype by performing a task to a lesser degree than they would otherwise.
For example: black people have the "less intelligent" stereotype attached to them, so a black person might perform poorly on an IQ test. If said person was either unaware of the stereotype or knew the stereotype to be wrong (stereotype threat is not present) then they would perform better. 

'''Stereotype threat''' "is a disruptive concern, when facing a negative stereotype, that one will be evaluated based on this stereotype." &lt;ref&gt;Myers, D. G., &amp; Spencer, S. J. (2006). Social Psychology. p. 443. Toronto: McGraw Hill Ryerson.&lt;/ref&gt; One published meta-analysis conducted by Walton &amp; Spencer (2009) found significant evidence that stereotype threat impairs the standardized test performances of African Americans and women on the SAT.&lt;ref&gt; Latent ability: Grades and test scores systematically
underestimate the intellectual ability of negatively stereotyped students. Psychological
Science, 20, 1132–1139.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Definition ==
Stereotype threat is "a disruptive concern, when facing a negative stereotype, that one will be evaluated based on such a stereotype." &lt;ref&gt;Myers, D. G., &amp; Spencer, S. J. (2006). Social Psychology. p. 443. Toronto: McGraw Hill Ryerson.&lt;/ref&gt; Stereotype threat has been shown to undermine the performance of members of a number of groups in a number of domains.
“[C]ulturally-shared stereotypes suggesting poor performance of certain groups can, when made salient in a context involving the stereotype, disrupt performance of an individual who identifies with that group” &lt;ref name="ReducingStereotypeThreat.org"&gt;[http://www.reducingstereotypethreat.org/definition.html ReducingStereotypeThreat.org&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;(Steele, Aronson 1995).

Although Steele and  Aronson focused on the emphasis on race affecting test performance, similar studies have demonstrated the same results for emphasis on gender. In other studies, researchers found that “consistent exposure to stereotype threat (e.g., faced by some ethnic minorities in academic environments and women in math) can reduce the degree to which individuals value the domain in question” &lt;ref name="ReducingStereotypeThreat.org"/&gt;(Aronson, et al. 2002; Osborne, 1995; Steele, 1997). Also, research has found that there are varying degrees of an individual on a certain group to be affected by stereotype threat:

"…some members may be more vulnerable to its negative consequences than others; factors such as the strength of one’s group identification or domain identification have been shown to be related to one's subsequent vulnerability to stereotype threat" (http://www.reducingstereotypethreat.org/definition.html) 

Further research has also found that when an individual identifies with a specific group, performance can be negatively affected, because of concerns that they will, in fact, confirm the negative stereotypes of that group.

==Evidence==
===Race===

During the 1960’s, psychologist Irwin Katz suggested that titles could influence performance on IQ tests.  Katz found that blacks were able to score better on an IQ subtest if the test was presented as a test of [[hand-eye coordination]]. Blacks also scored higher on an IQ test when they believed the test would be compared to that of other blacks.&lt;ref&gt;''Review of Evidence Relating to Effects of Desegregation on the Intellectual Performance of Negroes'' I Katz – American Psychologist, 1964&lt;/ref&gt; Katz concluded that his subjects were thoroughly aware of the judgment of intellectual inferiority held by many white Americans. With little expectation of overruling this judgment, their motivation was low, and so were their scores.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,902708,00.html Race and IQ] TIME. Monday, Sep. 07, 1970&lt;/ref&gt;

The phenomenon was later examined by the social psychologists [[Claude Steele]] and Joshua Aronson, who articulated the mechanism of "stereotype threat" that contributes to test performance of minority groups.  In one such study, Steele and Aronson (1995) administered the [[Graduate Record Examination]] to [[European American]] and [[African American]] students.  Half of each group was told that their intelligence was being measured, while the other half didn't know what the test was measuring. The European American students performed almost equally in the two conditions of the experiment. African Americans, in contrast, performed far worse than they otherwise would have when they were told their intelligence was being measured. The researchers concluded this was because stereotype threat made the students anxious about confirming the stereotype regarding African American [[Intelligence quotient|IQ]]. The researchers found that the difference was even more noticeable when race was emphasized.

&lt;blockquote&gt;"When capable black college students fail to perform as well as their white counterparts, the explanation often has less to do with preparation or ability than with the threat of stereotypes about their capacity to succeed."&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;- [[Claude M. Steele]], [[The Atlantic Monthly]], August 1999 ''[http://www.theatlantic.com/doc/prem/199908/student-stereotype Thin Ice: Stereotype Threat and Black College Students]''&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Steele and Aronson write that making race salient when taking a test of cognitive ability negatively affected high-ability African American students.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Steele CM, Aronson J |title=Stereotype threat and the intellectual test performance of African Americans |journal=J Pers Soc Psychol |volume=69 |issue=5 |pages=797–811 |year=1995 |month=November |pmid=7473032 |doi=10.1037/0022-3514.69.5.797 |url=http://content.apa.org/journals/psp/69/5/797}}&lt;/ref&gt; Steele writes that the stigma of being African American is still relevant, as it has  an effect on the educational outcomes of African Americans. Stereotypes such as Asian Americans usually excelling in mathematics, or African Americans usually testing poorly, can be extremely harmful. Stereotype threats can seriously alter academic achievement and motivation.&lt;ref&gt;[http://sitemaker.umich.edu/356.pitts/stereotype_threat_ Racial Identity and Academic Achievement]&lt;/ref&gt;

In a paper prepared for APA convention, Steele writes: "''Thus the predicament of 'stereotype vulnerability': The group members then know that anything about them or anything they do that fits the stereotype can be taken as confirming it as self-characteristic, in the eyes of others, and perhaps even in their own eyes. This vulnerability amounts to a jeopardy of double devaluation: once for whatever bad thing the stereotype-fitting behavior or feature would say about anyone, and again for its confirmation of the bad things alleged in the stereotype.''"

===Gender===
[[Image:Stereotype threat gender.jpg|thumb|left|300px|The effect of Stereotype Threat (ST) on math test scores for girls and boys. Data from ''Linking Stereotype Threat and Anxiety''&lt;ref&gt;''[http://www.eric.ed.gov/ERICWebPortal/custom/portlets/recordDetails/detailmini.jsp?_nfpb=true&amp;_&amp;ERICExtSearch_SearchValue_0=EJ763423&amp;ERICExtSearch_SearchType_0=no&amp;accno=EJ763423 Linking Stereotype Threat and Anxiety]''  Jason W. Osborne. North Carolina State University, ''Educational Psychology'' Vol. 27. Page. 135-154. Feb 2007&lt;/ref&gt;]]

A recent study, involving male and female chess players in an anonymous tournament, revealed that women played more poorly than their rated strength, when told that they would be playing men, and that "recent studies had shown that men earn clearly superior scores than women in chess games". Women who were told (either truthfully or falsely), that they were playing against other women, performed as their ratings would predict.&lt;ref&gt;[Maass, A. et al., "Checkmate? The Role of Gender Stereotypes in the Ultimate Intellectual Sport," European Journal of Social Psychology (March/April 2008).]&lt;/ref&gt;

In recent study, Vishal Gupta, Daniel Turban, and Nachiket Bhawe extended stereotype threat research to entrepreneurship, a traditionally male-stereotyped profession. Their study revealed that stereotype threat can depress women's entrepreneurial intentions, and boost men's intentions. However, when entrepreneurship is presented as a gender-neutral profession, they found that men and women had similar entrepreneurial intentions. This study is important partly because it extends stereotype threat research beyond academic performance to career intentions. [Gupta, V. K., Turban, D. B., &amp; Bhawe, N. M., "The effect of gender stereotype activation on entrepreneurial intentions," Journal of Applied Psychology (Vol. 93, iss 5, 2008).]

==Physiological responses==
Stereotype threat can result in physiological responses, since the pressure and fear caused by negative stereotypes is so great. For example, a study by Blascovich J, Spencer SJ, Quinn D and Steele C. found that African Americans under stereotype threat exhibited larger increases in arterial blood pressure during an academic test, and performed more poorly on difficult test items. Some researchers feel this may explain the higher death rates from hypertension-related disorders among African Americans.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Blascovich J, Spencer SJ, Quinn D, Steele C |title=African Americans and high blood pressure: the role of stereotype threat |journal=Psychol Sci |volume=12 |issue=3 |pages=225–9 |year=2001 |month=May |pmid=11437305 |doi=10.1111/1467-9280.00340 |url=}}&lt;/ref&gt; A study by Toni Schmader and Michael Johns found that stereotype threat can effectively reduce working memory capacity, another factor in poor test performance.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Schmader T, Johns M |title=Converging evidence that stereotype threat reduces working memory capacity |journal=J Pers Soc Psychol |volume=85 |issue=3 |pages=440–52 |year=2003 |month=September |pmid=14498781 |doi=10.1037/0022-3514.85.3.440 |url=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Stereotype threat may undermine intellectual performance by triggering a disruptive mental load. Studies have found increased heart rates for test subject operating under stereotype threat.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Croizet JC, Després G, Gauzins ME, Huguet P, Leyens JP, Méot A |title=Stereotype threat undermines intellectual performance by triggering a disruptive mental load |journal=Pers Soc Psychol Bull |volume=30 |issue=6 |pages=721–31 |year=2004 |month=June |pmid=15155036 |doi=10.1177/0146167204263961 |url=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Interpreting stereotype threat ==
The stereotype threat phenomenon has been confirmed in over three hundred scientific journal articles (Steele, Spencer, &amp; Aronson, 2002; see http://www.reducingstereotypethreat.org).  While the findings show that stereotypes may play a role in test score [[achievement gap]]s, they do not necessarily show that stereotypes are the entire source of the gaps. Paul R. Sackett, Chaitra M. Hardison, and Michael J. Cullen write that stereotype threat research has often been misinterpreted in the media, psychology textbooks, and the scholarly literature as showing that eliminating stereotype threat completely eliminates the difference in test performance between [[European American]] and [[African American]] individuals.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Sackett PR, Hardison CM, Cullen MJ |title=On interpreting stereotype threat as accounting for African American-White differences on cognitive tests |journal=Am Psychol |volume=59 |issue=1 |pages=7–13 |year=2004 |month=January |pmid=14736315 |doi=10.1037/0003-066X.59.1.7 |url=http://www2.uni-jena.de/svw/igc/studies/ss03/sackitt_hardison_cullen_2004.pdf|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt; They worry that this misinterpretation will shift the focus in public policy on closing the gap away from deeper systemic issues of [[racism]], [[sexism]] and inequality. In their own words:

&lt;blockquote&gt;Our concern about the misinterpretation that removing threat from a testing setting eliminates Black – White differences is that such misinterpretation has the potential to wrongly lead to the belief that there is less need for research and intervention aimed at a broad range of potential contributing factors, such as differences in educational and economic opportunities of African American and White youth. If group differences in scores on the SAT and other tests were largely explainable by the mind-set with which examinees approach the testing situation, it would then follow that differences in factors such as quality of instruction or per-pupil educational expenditure do not matter much in terms of achievement in the domains measured by high-stakes tests. Hence, caution in interpretation of threat research is warranted.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Furthermore, while Sackett et al. do not dispute the fact that stereotype threat has a real, measurable effect on test scores, they posit that in the part of the experiment where Steele and Aronson removed the stereotype threat, the ''achievement gap which did remain'' correlated closely with the existing African American – White achievement gap on large-scale standardized testing such as the SAT. In their own words:

&lt;blockquote&gt;Thus, rather than showing that eliminating threat eliminates the large score gap on standardized tests, the research actually shows something very different. Specifically, absent stereotype threat, the African American-White difference is just what one would expect based on the African American-White difference in SAT scores, whereas in the presence of stereotype threat, the difference is ''larger'' than would be expected based on the difference in SAT scores.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

In subsequent correspondence between Sackett et al. and Steele and Aronson, Sackett et al. wrote that "They [Steele and Aronson] agree that it is a misinterpretation of the Steele and Aronson (1995) results to conclude that eliminating stereotype threat eliminates the African American-White test-score gap."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www2.uni-jena.de/svw/igc/studies/ss03/sackitt_hardison_cullen_2004_reply.pdf On the Value of Correcting Mischaracterizations of Stereotype Threat Research]&lt;/ref&gt;

In an editorial article entitled [http://www.opinionjournal.com/extra/?id=110004973 "The Threat in the Air"], which was published on April 18, 2004 in the [[Wall Street Journal]], professor Amy Wax of the [[University of Pennsylvania Law School]] was highly critical of what she sees as Steele and Aronson's presentation of their research.  She was also skeptical of what she sees as claims about the real-world effect of stereotype threat on the black-white achievement gap.
 
===Practical applications===
The theory has generated a good deal of intervention work, some of which has boosted the achievement and test scores of low performing minority students.&lt;ref name="pmid15733195"&gt;{{cite journal |author=Johns M, Schmader T, Martens A |title=Knowing is half the battle: teaching stereotype threat as a means of improving women's math performance |journal=Psychol Sci |volume=16 |issue=3 |pages=175–9 |year=2005 |month=March |pmid=15733195 |doi=10.1111/j.0956-7976.2005.00799.x |url=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Reducing the effects of stereotype threat on African American college students by shaping theories of intelligence.'' Aronson, J, Fried, C and Good, C. Journal of Experimental Social Psychology 38.2 (March 2002): p113(13).&lt;/ref&gt; Since stereotype threat appears to be one of the key contributing factors to the gaps in test scores, researchers Geoffrey L. Cohen, Julio Garcia, Nancy Apfel, and Allison Master proposed intervention methods to address the problem in 2006. The intervention, a brief in-class writing assignment, significantly improved the grades of African American students and reduced the racial achievement gap by 40%. These results suggest that the racial achievement gap, a major social concern in the United States, could be ameliorated by the use of timely and targeted social-psychological interventions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Cohen GL, Garcia J, Apfel N, Master A |title=Reducing the racial achievement gap: a social-psychological intervention |journal=Science (journal) |volume=313 |issue=5791 |pages=1307–10 |year=2006 |month=September |pmid=16946074 |doi=10.1126/science.1128317 |url=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Psychometrics of racism]]
*[[Stereotype]]
*[[Self-fulfilling prophecy]]
*[[Acting white]]
*[[Race and intelligence]]
*[[Sex and intelligence]]
*[[Confounds and Artifacts]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}
*Aronson, E., Wilson, T.D., &amp; Akert, A.M. (2005). ''Social Psychology (5th ed.).'' Upper Saddle River, NJ: Prentice Hall.

*Aronson, J., Lustina, M. J., Good, C., Keough, K., Steele, C. M., &amp; Brown, J. (1999).  When white men can’t do math: Necessary and sufficient factors in stereotype threat. '' Journal of Experimental Social Psychology, 35,'' 29–46.

*{{cite journal |author=Sackett PR, Hardison CM, Cullen MJ |title=On interpreting stereotype threat as accounting for African American-White differences on cognitive tests |journal=Am Psychol |volume=59 |issue=1 |pages=7–13 |year=2004 |month=January |pmid=14736315 |doi=10.1037/0003-066X.59.1.7 |url=http://www2.uni-jena.de/svw/igc/studies/ss03/sackitt_hardison_cullen_2004.pdf|format=PDF}}

*{{cite journal |author=Steele CM, Aronson J |title=Stereotype threat and the intellectual test performance of African Americans |journal=J Pers Soc Psychol |volume=69 |issue=5 |pages=797–811 |year=1995 |month=November |pmid=7473032 |doi=10.1037/0022-3514.69.5.797 |url=http://content.apa.org/journals/psp/69/5/797}}

*Steele, C. M., Spencer, S., &amp; Aronson, J.  (2002). Contending with group image: The psychology of stereotype and social identity threat. In M. Zanna (Ed.),'' Advances in Experimental Social Psychology Vol. 37.''  Academic Press.

[[Category:Stereotypes]]

[[de:Bedrohung durch Stereotype]]
[[fr:Menace du stéréotype]]
[[pl:Zagrożenie stereotypem]]
[[sv:Stereotyphot]]
[[zh:成见威胁]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>