<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20101112000155|396222387" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="2107559" pageid="2107559" ns="0" title="Islamic feminism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2010-11-12T00:02:31Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[Image:Islamic Feminism Symbol.svg|thumb|A symbol for Islamic Feminism]]
{{Feminism sidebar |expanded=Subtypes}}
'''Islamic feminism''' is a form of [[feminism]] concerned with the role of [[Women and Islam|women in Islam]]. It aims for the full equality of all [[Muslims]], regardless of gender, in public and private life. Islamic feminists advocate [[women's rights]], [[gender equality]], and [[social justice]] grounded in an Islamic framework. Although rooted in [[Islam]], the movement's pioneers have also utilised [[Secularity|secular]] and European or non-Muslim feminist discourses and recognize the role of Islamic feminism as part of an integrated global feminist movement.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.feminismeislamic.org/eng/index.htm International Congress on Islamic Feminism]&lt;/ref&gt;

Advocates of the movement seek to highlight the deeply rooted teachings of equality in the religion, and encourage a questioning of the [[patriarchal]] interpretation of Islamic teaching through the Quran (holy book), ''[[hadith]]'' (sayings of [[Muhammad]]) and ''[[sharia]]'' (law) towards the creation of a more equal and just society.&lt;ref&gt;[http://weekly.ahram.org.eg/2002/569/cu1.htm Al-Ahram Weekly | Culture | Islamic feminism: what's in a name?&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Muslim majority countries]] have produced several female head of states and prime ministers: [[Benazir Bhutto]] of [[Pakistan]], [[Mame Madior Boye]] of [[Senegal]], [[Tansu Çiller]] of [[Turkey]], [[Kaqusha Jashari]] of [[Kosovo]], and [[Megawati Sukarnoputri]] of [[Indonesia]]. [[Bangladesh]] was the first country in the world to have one female head of state follow another, those two being [[Khaleda Zia]] and [[Sheikh Hasina]].{{Citation needed|date=August 2010}}

==History==
===Early reforms under Islam===
{{Main|Early social changes under Islam}}

During the [[Muslim history|early days of Islam]] in the 7th century [[Common Era|CE]], reforms in [[women's rights]] affected marriage, divorce and inheritance.&lt;ref name="oxfordislamicstudies.com"&gt;[http://www.oxfordislamicstudies.com/article/opr/t125/e2510?_hi=6&amp;_pos=2 "Women and Islam" in ''Oxford Islamic Studies Online'']&lt;/ref&gt; Women were not accorded such legal status in other cultures, including the West, until centuries later.&lt;ref&gt;Jones, Lindsay. p.6224&lt;/ref&gt; ''The Oxford Dictionary of Islam'' states that the general improvement of the status of [[women in Arab societies]] included prohibition of [[female infanticide]] and recognizing women's full personhood&lt;ref name="oxfordislamicstudies.com"/&gt; (see [[Islamic ethics]]). Under Islamic law, marriage was no longer viewed as a status but rather as a contract, in which the woman's consent was imperative.&lt;ref name="majid"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Espos"/&gt;&lt;ref name="OxfordDicT"&gt;Esposito (2004), p. 339&lt;/ref&gt; "The [[dowry]], previously regarded as a [[bride price|bride-price]] paid to the father, became a nuptial gift retained by the wife as part of her personal property"&lt;ref name="majid"&gt;Khadduri (1978)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Espos"&gt;Esposito (2005) p. 79&lt;/ref&gt; (see also [[Dower]]). "Women were given inheritance rights in a [[patriarchal society]] that had previously restricted inheritance to male relatives."&lt;ref name="Espos"/&gt;

[[Annemarie Schimmel]] states that "compared to the pre-Islamic position of women, [[sharia|Islamic legislation]] meant an enormous progress; the woman has the right, at least according to the letter of the law, to administer the wealth she has brought into the family or has earned by her own work."&lt;ref name = "Schimmel"&gt;Schimmel (1992) p.65&lt;/ref&gt; [[William Montgomery Watt]] states that [[Muhammad]], in the historical context of his time, can be seen as a figure who testified on behalf of women's rights and improved things considerably. Watt explains: "At the time Islam began, the conditions of women were terrible - they had no right to own [[property]], were supposed to be [[chattel|the property of the man]], and if the man died everything went to his sons." Muhammad, however, by "instituting rights of property ownership, inheritance, education and divorce, gave women certain basic safeguards."&lt;ref&gt;Maan, McIntosh (1999)&lt;/ref&gt; Haddad and [[John Esposito|Esposito]] state that "Muhammad granted women rights and privileges in the sphere of family life, marriage, education, and economic endeavors, rights that help improve women's status in society."&lt;ref&gt;Haddad, Esposito (1998) p.163&lt;/ref&gt;

===Islamic Golden Age===
{{See also|Women in Islam|Islamic Golden Age}}

Whilst in the pre-modern period there was not a formal feminist movement, nevertheless there were a number of important figures who argued for improving women's rights and autonomy. These range from the medieval mystic and philosopher [[Ibn Arabi]], who argued that women could achieve spiritual stations as equally high as men&lt;ref name=Hakim-2002&gt;{{citation|title=Ibn 'Arabî's Twofold Perception of Woman: Woman as Human Being and Cosmic Principle|first=Souad|last=Hakim|journal=Journal of the Muhyiddin Ibn 'Arabi Society|volume=31|year=2002|pages=1–29}}&lt;/ref&gt; to [[Nana Asma’u]], daughter of eighteenth-century reformer [[Usman Dan Fodio]], who pushed for literacy and education of Muslim women.&lt;ref name=Mack-2000&gt;{{citation|title=One Woman's Jihad: Nana Asma’u, Scholar and Scribe|first=Beverly B.|last=Mack|coauthors=Jean Boyd|location=USA|publisher=Indiana University Press|year=2000}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Education====
{{See also|Madrasah}}

Women played an important role in the foundations of many Islamic educational institutions, such as [[Fatima al-Fihri]]'s founding of the [[University of Al Karaouine]] in 859 CE. This continued through to the [[Ayyubid dynasty]] in the 12th and 13th centuries, when 160 [[mosque]]s and [[madrasah]]s were established in [[Damascus]], 26 of which were funded by women through the [[Waqf]] ([[charitable trust]] or [[trust law]]) system. Half of all the royal [[Patronage|patrons]] for these institutions were also women.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|title=Daily Life in the Medieval Islamic World|first=James E.|last=Lindsay|publisher=[[Greenwood Publishing Group]]|year=2005|isbn=0313322708|page=197}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the [[Sunni]] scholar [[Ibn Asakir]] in the 12th century, there were opportunities for [[female education]]. He wrote that girls and women could study, earn ''[[ijazah]]s'' ([[academic degree]]s), and qualify as scholars (''[[ulema]]'') and teachers. This was especially the case for learned and scholarly families, who wanted to ensure the highest possible education for both their sons and daughters.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|title=Daily Life in the Medieval Islamic World|first=James E.|last=Lindsay|publisher=[[Greenwood Publishing Group]]|year=2005|isbn=0313322708|pages=196 &amp; 198}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ibn Asakir had himself studied under 80 different female teachers. Female education in the Islamic world was inspired by [[Muhammad's wives]]: [[Khadijah]], a successful businesswoman, and [[Aisha]], a renowned [[Muhaddith|scholar of the ''hadith'']] and [[Battle of Bassorah|military leader]]. [[hadith|Muhammad is said]] to have praised the women of [[Medina]] for their desire for religious knowledge:&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|title=Daily Life in the Medieval Islamic World|first=James E.|last=Lindsay|publisher=[[Greenwood Publishing Group]]|year=2005|isbn=0313322708|pages=196}}&lt;/ref&gt; "How splendid were the women of the ''[[Ansar (Islam)|ansar]]''; shame did not prevent them from becoming learned in the faith."

While it was not common for women to enroll as students in formal classes, they did attend informal lectures and study sessions at mosques, madrasahs and other public places. Although there were no legal restrictions on female education, some men did not approve of this practice. For example, Muhammad ibn al-Hajj (d. 1336) was appalled at the behaviour of some women who informally [[audit]]ed lectures in his time:&lt;ref name=Lindsay&gt;{{citation|title=Daily Life in the Medieval Islamic World|first=James E.|last=Lindsay|publisher=[[Greenwood Publishing Group]]|year=2005|isbn=0313322708|page=198}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|"[Consider] what some women do when people gather with a [[Sheikh|shaykh]] to hear [the recitation of] books. At that point women come, too, to hear the readings; the men sit in one place, the women facing them. It even happens at such times that some of the women are carried away by the situation; one will stand up, and sit down, and shout in a loud voice. [Moreover,] her ''awra'' will appear; in her house, their exposure would be forbidden — how can it be allowed in a mosque, in the presence of men?"}}

(''[[Awrah|'awra]]'' refers to the parts of the body that should remain covered; see also ''[[hijab]]'' for the rules of modesty governing both men and women.)

On the question of women in medieval Islam, Abdul Hakim Murad writes
&lt;blockquote&gt;
the orientalist Ignaz Goldziher showed that perhaps fifteen percent of medieval hadith scholars were women, teaching in the mosques and universally admired for their integrity. Colleges such as the Saqlatuniya Madrasa in Cairo were funded and staffed entirely by women. The most recent study of Muslim female academicians, by Ruth Roded, charts an extraordinary dilemma for the researcher:

'If U.S. and European historians feel a need to reconstruct women's history because women are invisible in the traditional sources, Islamic scholars are faced with a plethora of source material that has only begun to be studied. [ . . . ] In reading the biographies of thousands of Muslim women scholars, one is amazed at the evidence that contradicts the view of Muslim women as marginal, secluded, and restricted.'

Stereotypes come under almost intolerable strain when Roded documents the fact that the proportion of female lecturers in many classical Islamic colleges was higher than in modern Western universities.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.masud.co.uk/ISLAM/ahm/gender.htm&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

In the 15th century, [[Al-Sakhawi]] devotes an entire volume of his 12-volume [[biographical dictionary]] ''Daw al-lami'' to female scholars, giving information on 1,075 of them.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|title=Women in Iran from the Rise of Islam to 1800|last=Guity Nashat|first=Lois Beck|publisher=[[University of Illinois Press]]|year=2003|isbn=0252071212|page=69}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Civil and military work====
The [[labor force]] in the [[Caliphate]] came from diverse ethnic and religious backgrounds, while both men and women were involved in diverse occupations and [[Islamic economics in the world|economic activities]].&lt;ref&gt;Maya Shatzmiller, pp. 6–7.&lt;/ref&gt; Women were employed in a wide range of commercial activities and diverse occupations&lt;ref name=Maya-400-1&gt;Maya Shatzmiller (1994), ''Labour in the Medieval Islamic World'', [[Brill Publishers]], ISBN 90-04-09896-8, pp. 400–1&lt;/ref&gt; in the primary sector (as farmers for example), secondary sector (as construction workers, dyers, spinners, etc.) and tertiary sector (as investors, doctors, nurses, presidents of [[guild]]s, brokers, peddlers, lenders, scholars, etc.).&lt;ref&gt;Maya Shatzmiller, pp. 350–62.&lt;/ref&gt; Muslim women also held a monopoly over certain branches of the [[textile industry]],&lt;ref name=Maya-400-1/&gt; the largest and most specialized and market-oriented industry at the time, in occupations such as [[Spinning (textiles)|spinning]], [[dying]], and [[embroidery]]. In comparison, female [[property rights]] and [[wage labour]] were relatively uncommon in Europe until the [[Industrial Revolution]] in the 18th and 19th centuries.&lt;ref&gt;Maya Shatzmiller (1997), "Women and Wage Labour in the Medieval Islamic West: Legal Issues in an Economic Context", ''Journal of the Economic and Social History of the Orient'' '''40''' (2), pp. 174–206 [175–7].&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 12th century, the famous [[Islamic philosophy|Islamic philosopher]] and ''[[qadi]]'' (judge) [[Averroes|Ibn Rushd]], known to the West as ''Averroes'', claimed that women were equal to men in all respects and possessed equal capacities to shine [[Peace In Islamic Thought|in peace]] and [[Islamic military jurisprudence|in war]], citing examples of female warriors among the Arabs, Greeks and Africans to support his case.&lt;ref name=Ahmad&gt;{{citation|last=Ahmad|first=Jamil|date=September 1994|title=Ibn Rushd|journal=[[Al-Mawrid|Monthly Renaissance]]|volume=4|issue=9|url=http://www.monthly-renaissance.com/issue/content.aspx?id=744|accessdate=2008-10-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; In early [[Muslim history]], examples of notable women who fought during the [[Muslim conquests]] and [[Fitna (word)|Fitna]] (civil wars) as soldiers or generals included [[Nusaybah Bint k'ab Al Maziniyyah]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.realnews247.com/girl_power.htm Girl Power], ''[[ABC News]]''&lt;/ref&gt; [[Aisha]],&lt;ref name="Baghdad"&gt;{{Citation|last=Black|first=Edwin|title=Banking on Baghdad: Inside Iraq's 7,000 Year History of War, Profit, and Conflict|publisher=John Wiley and Sons|year= 2004|isbn=047170895X|page=34}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Kahula]] and Wafeira.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | title=Woman's Record: Or, Sketches of All Distinguished Women, from "The Beginning Till A.D. 1850, Arranged in Four Eras, with Selections from Female Writers of Every Age| author=Hale, Sarah Josepha Buell |publisher=Harper Brothers|year=1853|page=120}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Property, marriage, and other rights====
In terms of women's rights, women generally had fewer legal restrictions under Islamic law (''[[sharia]]'') than they did under certain Western legal systems until the 20th century. For example, under traditional interpretations of ''sharia'', women had the right to keep their surnames upon marriage; inherit and bestow inheritance; independently manage their financial affairs; and contract marriages and divorce. In contrast, restrictions on the legal capacity of married women under [[French law]] were not removed until 1965.&lt;ref name=Badr-1984&gt;{{citation|title=Islamic Criminal Justice|first=Gamal M.|last=Badr|journal=The American Journal of Comparative Law|volume=32|issue=1|date=Winter 1984|pages=167–169 [167–8]|doi=10.2307/840274|url=http://jstor.org/stable/840274|author2=Mayer, Ann Elizabeth|publisher=The American Journal of Comparative Law, Vol. 32, No. 1}}&lt;/ref&gt; Noah Feldman, a law professor at [[Harvard University]], notes:

{{quote|As for [[sexism]], the [[common law]] long denied married women any property rights or indeed legal personality apart from their husbands. When the British applied their law to Muslims in place of Shariah, as they did in some colonies, the result was to strip married women of the property that Islamic law had always granted them — hardly progress toward equality of the sexes.&lt;ref name=Feldman&gt;{{cite news|author=Noah Feldman|title=Why Shariah?|publisher=[[New York Times]]|date=March 16, 2008|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2008/03/16/magazine/16Shariah-t.html?ei=5070&amp;em=&amp;en=5c1b8de536ce606f&amp;ex=1205812800&amp;pagewanted=all|accessdate=2008-10-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

In contrast to the [[Western world]] where divorce was relatively uncommon until modern times, divorce was a common occurrence at certain points in the pre-modern [[Muslim world]], where it was known as ''[[Talaq (Nikah)|talaq]]''. In the [[Mamluk Sultanate (Cairo)|Mamluk Sultanate]] and early [[Ottoman Empire]], the rate of divorce was higher than it is today in the modern Middle East.&lt;ref name=Rapoport&gt;{{citation|title=Marriage, Money and Divorce in Medieval Islamic Society|first=Yossef|last=Rapoport|publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]]|year=2005|isbn=052184715X|page=2}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 15th century [[Egypt]], [[Al-Sakhawi]] recorded the marital history of 500 women, the largest [[Sampling (statistics)|sample]] on marriage in the [[Middle Ages]], and found that at least a third of all women in the [[Mamluk Sultanate]] of [[Egypt]] and [[Syria]] married more than once, with many marrying three or more times.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|title=Marriage, Money and Divorce in Medieval Islamic Society|first=Yossef|last=Rapoport|publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]]|year=2005|isbn=052184715X|pages=5–6}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Nineteenth century===
{{Ref improve section|date=October 2009}}
The modern movement of Islamic feminism began in the late nineteenth century. Egyptian jurist [[Qasim Amin]], the author of the 1899 pioneering book ''Women's Liberation'' (''Tahrir al-Mar'a''), is often described as the father of the [[Feminism in Egypt|Egyptian feminist movement]]. In his work, Amin criticized some of the practices prevalent in his society at the time, such as [[Polygyny in Islam|polygyny]], [[Islam and clothing|the veil]], and ''[[purdah]]'', i.e. [[sex segregation in Islam]]. He condemned them as un-Islamic and contradictory to the true spirit of Islam. His work had an enormous influence on women's political movements throughout the Islamic and [[Arab world]], and is read and cited today.

Despite Qasim Amin's effects on modern-day Islamic feminist movements, present-day scholar Leila Ahmed considers his works both [[androcentric]] and [[colonialist]].&lt;ref&gt;Leila Ahmed. Women and Gender in Islam. New Haven and London: Yale University Press, 1992. pp.155-163, 171, 179.&lt;/ref&gt; Muhammad 'Abdu, an Egyptian nationalist,&lt;ref&gt;Leila Ahmed. Women and Gender in Islam. New Haven and London: Yale University Press, 1992. pp.136-137.&lt;/ref&gt; could easily have written the chapters of his work that show honest considerations of the negative effects of the veil on women.&lt;ref&gt;Leila Ahmed. Women and Gender in Islam. New Haven and London: Yale University Press, 1992. pp.159,161.&lt;/ref&gt; Amin even posed many male-centered misconceptions about women, such as their inability to experience love, that women needlessly (when they had very good reason to) talk about their husbands outside their presence, and that Muslim marriage is based on ignorance and sensuality, of which women were the chief source.&lt;ref&gt;Leila Ahmed. Women and Gender in Islam. New Haven and London: Yale University Press, 1992. pp.157-159.&lt;/ref&gt;

Less known, however, are the women who preceded Amin in their feminist critique of their societies. The women's press in Egypt started voicing such concerns since its very first issues in 1892. Egyptian, Turkish, Iranian, Syrian and Lebanese women and men had been reading European feminist magazines even a decade earlier, and discussed their relevance to the Middle East in the general press.&lt;ref&gt;see "Great Ancestors: Women Asserting Rights in Muslim Contexts," by Farida Shaheed with Aisha L.F. Shaheed (London/Lahore: WLUML/Shirkat Gah, 2005) [http://www.wluml.org/english/pubsfulltxt.shtml?%5B87%5D=i-87-186208]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Twentieth century===
[[Aisha Abd al-Rahman]], writing under her pen name ''Bint al-Shati'' ("Daughter of the Riverbank"), was the first modern woman to undertake [[Quran]]ic [[exegesis]], and though she did not considered herself to be a feminist, her works reflect feminist themes. She began producing her popular books in 1959, the same year that [[Naguib Mahfouz]] published his allegorical and feminist version of the life of Muhammad.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|first=Ruth|last=Roded|title=Bint al-Shati's Wives of the Prophet: Feminist or Feminine?|journal=British Journal of Middle Eastern Studies|date=May 2006|volume=33|issue=1|pages=51–66|doi=10.1080/13530190600603915}}&lt;/ref&gt; She wrote biographies of early [[women in Islam]], including the [[Aminah bint Wahb|mother]], [[Muhammad's wives|wives]] and [[Family tree of Muhammad|daughters]] of the [[Prophets of Islam|Prophet]] Muhammad, as well as [[literary criticism]].&lt;ref name="zeidan"&gt;Arab Women Novelists: The Formative Years and Beyond by Joseph T. Zeidan, State University of New York Press, 1995&lt;/ref&gt;

Recently Islamic feminists have begun advocating for equality in the mosque and equality in prayer, as you can see in the "Equality in the Mosque" and "Equality in Prayer" sections further down in this article.

==Areas of campaign==
===Personal law===
{{Ref improve section|date=May 2010}}
{{See also|Islamic marital jurisprudence}}

One of the major areas of scholarship and campaigning for Islamic feminists are aspects of ''[[sharia]]'' (Islamic law) known as Muslim personal law (MPL) or Muslim family law. Some of the thorny issues regarding the way in which MPL has thus far been formulated include [[Polygamy in Islam|polygyny]], [[Divorce in Islam|divorce]], custody of children, maintenance and marital property. In addition, there are also more macro issues regarding the underlying assumptions of such legislation, for example, the assumption of the man as [[head of the household]].

[[Muslim majority countries]] that have promulgated some form of MPL include [[Saudi Arabia]], [[Afghanistan]], [[Pakistan]], [[Libya]], [[Sudan]], [[Senegal]], [[Tunisia]], [[Egypt]], [[Indonesia]], and [[Bangladesh]]. Muslim minority countries that already have incorporated MPL into their own law or are considering passing legislation on aspects of MPL include [[India]], [[Israel]], and [[South Africa]].

Islamic feminists have objected to the MPL legislation in many of these countries, arguing that these pieces of legislation discriminate against women. Some Islamic feminists have taken the attitude that a reformed MPL which is based on the [[Quran]] and [[sunnah]], which includes substantial input from Muslim women, and which does not discriminate against women is possible. Such Islamic feminists have been working on developing women-friendly forms of MPL. (See, for example, [http://www.ccmw.com/GTAForum/index.htm the Canadian Council of Muslim Women] for argument based on the Quran and not on what they call medieval male consensus.) Other Islamic feminists, particularly some in Muslim minority contexts which are democratic states, argue that MPL should not be reformed but should be rejected and that Muslim women should seek redress, instead, from the [[civil law]]s of those states. &lt;!--this paragraph needs to cite sources and name the women or groups, instead of "some Islamic feminists."--&gt;

===Sexuality and marriage===
{{See also|Islamic sexual jurisprudence|Homosexuality and Islam}}

Despite the taboo status of sex and [[human sexuality|sexuality]] in many Muslim societies, some [[ulema|Quranic scholars]] have argued that the Quran itself discusses these subjects openly and positively, and that Islam is one of the most sexually accepting of the major world religions.&lt;ref name="safra"&gt;[http://www.safraproject.org/sgi-womenssexualtiyinislam.htm SAFRA Project Essay on Islam and Sexuality]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;See the works of Asra Nomani for more details&lt;/ref&gt;

As for Surah 4:34 of the Quran, which has been used to justify wife-beating, many Islamic feminists claim it was never meant to do so. In 2007 [[Laleh Bakhtiar]] published a translation of the Quran, with her translation of Surah 4:34 substituting "go away" for "beat" (they are the same word in Classical Arabic). Her translation of Surah 4:34 reads: "Men are supporters of wives because God has given some of them an advantage over others and because they spend of their wealth. So the ones who are in accord with morality are the ones who are morally obligated, the ones who guard the unseen of what God has kept safe. But those whose resistance you fear, then admonish them and abandon them in their sleeping place, then go away from them; and if they obey you, surely look not for any way against them ; truly God is Lofty, Great” &lt;ref&gt;http://www.sublimequran.org/&lt;/ref&gt;."

There is debate over the interpretations of the Quranic verses that have been cited to outlaw [[homosexuality]], principally the verse relating to the story of [[Islamic view of Lot|Lot]] (see Quran verses: 11:69-83, 29:28-35). Quranic verses appear to relate specifically to male homosexuality. Contemporary interpreters and campaigning organisations are working to reinterpret texts to allow for a wider spectrum of sexual relationships, including homosexual and [[bisexual]], but there is much resistance from the mainstream Muslim community.&lt;ref name="safra" /&gt;

===Dress codes===
{{See also|Sartorial hijab|Islam and clothing|Awrah|Purdah}}
Another issue that concerns Muslim women is the [[dress code]] expected of them. Islam requires both men and women to dress modestly; this concept is known as ''[[hijab]]'' and covers a wide interpretation of behavior and garments. In some countries such as [[Afghanistan]] and [[Saudi Arabia]] women are expected to wear the all-covering ''[[burqa]]'' or ''[[abaya]]''; in others such as [[Tunisia]] and [[Turkey]] they are forbidden to wear even the [[headscarf]] (often known as the veil) in public buildings. There is mixed opinion among Muslim feminists over extremes of externally imposed control.

A number of Islamic feminists, including [[Fadela Amara]] and [[:fr:Hédi M'henni|Hedi Mhenni]] support bans on the ''hijab'', for various reasons. Amara explained her support for France's ban of the garment in public buildings: "The veil is the visible symbol of the subjugation of women, and therefore has no place in the mixed, [[Laïcité|secular spaces]] of [[education in France|France's public school system]]."&lt;ref name="guardian.co.uk"&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2006/jul/17/france.politicsphilosophyandsociety | work=The Guardian | location=London | title=Ghetto warrior | date=July 17, 2006 | accessdate=May 5, 2010 | first=Rose | last=George}}&lt;/ref&gt; When some feminists began defending the headscarf on the grounds of "tradition", Amara saw red. "It's not tradition, it's archaic! French feminists are totally contradictory. When [[women in Algeria|Algerian women]] fought against wearing the headscarf in [[Algeria]], [[feminism in France|French feminists]] supported them. But when it's some young girl in a [[Banlieue|French suburb]] school, they don't. They define [[Liberté, égalité, fraternité|liberty and equality]] according to what colour your skin is. It's nothing more than [[neocolonialism]]."&lt;ref name="guardian.co.uk"/&gt; Mhenni also expressed support for [[Tunisia]]'s ban on the veil: "If today we accept the headscarf, tomorrow we'll accept that women's rights to work and vote and receive an education be banned and they'll be seen as just a tool for reproduction and housework."&lt;ref&gt;http://www.islamonline.net/English/News/2006-10/06/06.shtml&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Sihem Habchi]], Muslim feminist and director of [[Ni Putes Ni Soumises]], expressed support for France's ban on the burqa in public places, stating that the ban was a matter of 'democratic principle' and protecting French women from the 'obscurantist, fascist, right-wing movement' that she claims the burqa represents.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/today/hi/today/newsid_8568000/8568024.stm | work=BBC News | title=France's burka dilemma | date=March 15, 2010 | first=Zubeida | last=Malik}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.vingtparismagazine.com/2010/01/ni-putes-ni-soumises-organizes-a-protest-against-the-burqa.html&lt;/ref&gt;

The Quran does state that both men and women should be dressed modestly (33:59-60, 24:30-31; in translation by Ali, 1988, 1126–27). It however does not use the words veil, hijab, burka, chador, or abaya. It uses the words ''jilbab'' meaning cloak and ''khumur'' meaning shawl. These do not cover the face, hands or feet. Furthermore until the third through the ninth century women prayed in the mosques unveiled. The whole body covering with the burka, chador, and other items of clothing is a tradition and cultural manifest from a conservative reading of the Quran by Mullahs; men. It is not what the Quran itself states. The Quran, 2:256, states "Let there be no compulsion in religion".&lt;ref&gt;"Believing Women inIslam" by Asma Barlos, University of Texas Press, Austin. 2002, 53-55.&lt;/ref&gt; However, body covering with clothing are historically based in the teachings and the customs of the Prophet Muhammad and his companions.{{Citation needed|date=June 2010}}

===Equality in the Mosque===

A survey by the Council on American Islamic Relations showed that two of three mosques in 2000 required women to pray in a separate area, up from one of two in 1994 [http://www.thedailybeast.com/blogs-and-stories/2010-02-27/let-these-women-pray/]. Islamic feminists have begun to protest this, advocating for women to be allowed to pray beside men without a partition as they do in Mecca [http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2010/05/21/AR2010052104253.html] [http://www.womensenews.org/story/religion/100222/protesters-break-prayer-rules-at-leading-mosque]. In 2003, [[Asra Nomani]] challenged rules at her mosque in Morgantown, West Virginia, requiring that women enter through a back door and pray in a secluded balcony [http://www.thedailybeast.com/blogs-and-stories/2010-02-27/let-these-women-pray/]. She argued that since in the 7th century the Islamic prophet Muhammad didn't put women behind partitions, that the barriers were just sexist man-made rules [http://www.thedailybeast.com/blogs-and-stories/2010-02-27/let-these-women-pray/]. The men at her mosque put her on trial to be banished [http://www.thedailybeast.com/blogs-and-stories/2010-02-27/let-these-women-pray/].

In 2005, following public agitation on the issue, Muslim organizations, including CAIR and the Islamic Society of North America, issued a report on making mosques "women-friendly," asserting women's rights in mosques, including the right to pray in the main hall without a partition [http://www.thedailybeast.com/blogs-and-stories/2010-02-27/let-these-women-pray/].

American Muslim Fatima Thompson and a few others organized and participated in a "pray-in" in 2010 at the Islamic Center of Washington in D.C. [http://www.thedailybeast.com/blogs-and-stories/2010-02-27/let-these-women-pray/]. Police were summoned and threatened to arrest the women when they refused to leave the main prayer hall and continued their protest against being corralled in what they referred to as the "penalty box" of a prayer space reserved for women [http://www.thedailybeast.com/blogs-and-stories/2010-02-27/let-these-women-pray/]. A second protest staged by the same women on the eve of International Women's Day in 2010 resulted in calls to the police and threats of arrest again [http://www.thedailybeast.com/blogs-and-stories/2010-02-27/let-these-women-pray/]. However, the women were not arrested on either occasion [http://www.thedailybeast.com/blogs-and-stories/2010-02-27/let-these-women-pray/].

Furthermore, in May 2010 five women prayed with the men at the Dar al-Hijrah mosque, one of the Washington region's largest Islamic centers [http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2010/05/21/AR2010052104253.html]. After the prayers, a member of the mosque called Fairfax police, who asked the women to leave [http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2010/05/21/AR2010052104253.html]. However, later in 2010 it was decided that D.C. police would no longer intervene in such protests [http://www.washingtonexaminer.com/local/D_C_-police-won_t-intervene-to-remove-women-from-mosques-96758814.html].

===Equality in Prayer===

According to currently existing traditional schools of [[Islam]], a woman cannot lead a mixed gender congregation in salat (prayer). Some schools make exceptions for [[Tarawih]] (optional [[Ramadan]] prayers) or for a congregation consisting only of close relatives. Certain medieval scholars—including [[Muhammad ibn Jarir al-Tabari]] (838–923), [[Abu Thawr]] (764–854), [[Isma'il Ibn Yahya al-Muzani]] (791–878), and [[Ibn Arabi]] (1165–1240) considered the practice permissible at least for optional ([[nafl]]) prayers; however, their views are not accepted by any major surviving group. Islamic feminists have begun to protest this.

In 1994, Muslim scholar and Islamic studies professor at Virginia Commonwealth University, [[Amina Wadud]], was invited to deliver the sermon before the congregational prayer, the khutbah at the Claremont Road Mosque in [[Capetown]], [[South Africa]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.upenn.edu/gazette/0306/voices.html One Faith, Many Fragments] By Amina Wadud for the University of Pennsylvania (2006)&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2004, then 20-year-old Maryam Mirza delivered the second half of the ''[[Eid al-Fitr]]'' khutbah at the Etobicoke mosque in [[Toronto]], [[Canada]], run by the [[United Muslim Association]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tribuneindia.com/2004/20041116/world.htm First Muslim woman delivers sermon]&lt;/ref&gt;

In the same year also in Canada Yasmin Shadeer led the night [[Isha]] prayer for a mixed-gender (men as well as women praying and hearing the sermon) congregation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.cbc.ca/thesundayedition/media/sisterhood_se050227.ram|title=One for the Sisterhood: A documentary by Karin Wells|publisher=[[CBC.ca|CBC]]|year=2005|accessdate=2008-03-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On March 18, 2005, Wadud gave a sermon and led the Friday prayers for a Muslim congregation consisting of men as well as women, with no curtain dividing the men and women.&lt;ref name="nytimes.com"&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.nytimes.com/2005/03/19/nyregion/19muslim.html | work=The New York Times | title=Woman Leads Muslim Prayer Service in New York | first=Andrea | last=Elliott | date=March 19, 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another woman sounded the call to prayer, while not wearing a headscarf at that same event.&lt;ref name="nytimes.com"/&gt; The prayer took place in the Synod House of the Cathedral of St. John the Divine in New York, after mosques refused to host the prayer.&lt;ref name="nytimes.com"/&gt; This was the first time a woman led a mixed-gender Muslim congregation in prayer in American history.&lt;ref name="nytimes.com"/&gt;

Furthermore, in April 2005, [[Raheel Raza]] led Toronto's first woman-led mixed-gender Friday prayer service, delivering the khutbah and leading the prayers of the mixed-gender congregation organized by the [[Muslim Canadian Congress]] to celebrate [[Earth Day]] in the backyard of the downtown Toronto home of activist Tarek Fatah.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.muslimcanadiancongress.org/20050423.pdf Woman leads mixed-gender prayers for city Muslims] Toronto Star&lt;/ref&gt;

On July 1, 2005, Pamela Taylor, a Muslim convert since 1986 and co-chair of the [[New York]]-based [[Progressive Muslim Union]], became the first woman to lead the Friday ''[[khutbah]]'' and led the mixed-gender prayers in Toronto at the UMA mosque at the invitation of the Muslim Canadian Congress on [[Canada Day]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.awid.org/eng/Issues-and-Analysis/Library/Woman-led-prayer-honours-IWD Woman-led prayer honours IWD]&lt;/ref&gt; In addition to leading the prayers, Taylor also gave a sermon on the importance of equality among people regardless of gender, race, sexual orientation, and/or disability.&lt;ref&gt;[http://pluralism.org/reports/view/111 The Pluralism Project - Research Report]&lt;/ref&gt;

In late October 2005 Wadud also led a mixed gender congregational prayer in Barcelona at during the first Islamic Feminist conference attended by Muslim feminists, men and women, around the world and partly organized by the Spanish imam, Abdennur Prado.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.muslimwakeup.com/main/archives/2005/10/amina-wadud-lea.php Amina Wadud Leads Mixed Gender Friday Prayer in Barcelona]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2005/oct/31/gender.religion Muslim women launch international 'gender jihad']&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nodo50.org/csca/agenda08/palestina/arti338.html ¿Qué es el feminismo musulmán? Por la promoción de un cambio cultural en favor de la igualdad de géneros] (Spanish)&lt;/ref&gt;

The former Mufti of [[Marseille]], France, [[Soheib Bencheikh]], requested that either Raheel Raza&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.raheelraza.com|title=Raheel Raza - Profile|accessdate=2008-03-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; or Pamela Taylor lead him in prayer during a visit to Canada in February 2006. The prayers were held in a private venue with a mixed gender congregation.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wluml.org/zh-hans/node/2747 Canada: French Islamic Scholar to join woman-led prayer in Toronto]&lt;/ref&gt;

Women have continued to lead mixed gender prayers in the United States; for example, Nakia Jackson led Eid prayers in 2006 and 2007 with academic Laury Silvers giving the [[khutbah]]. In May 2007, as a guest of the Muslim Youth Movement, Silvers gave the Friday sermon at the Claremont Road Mosque in Cape Town, South Africa and an associated mosque in Johannesburg, South Africa.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.raheelraza.com/med.htm Pray Hear: Muslim Women want Larger Roles] By Karla Bruning for Columbia News Service&lt;/ref&gt;

On October 17, 2008, Wadud became the first woman to lead a mixed-gender congregation in prayer in the [[United Kingdom]], when she performed the Friday prayers at Oxford's Wolfson College.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/2008/oct/17/religion-islam-women-prayers It's Muslim men we must modernise]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.naplesnews.com/news/2006/dec/02/islams_gender_boundaries_being_pushed/ Islam's gender boundaries being pushed]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2010 [[Raheel Raza]] became the first Muslim-born woman to lead a mixed-gender British congregation through Friday prayers.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.independent.co.uk/news/uk/home-news/first-woman-to-lead-friday-prayers-in-uk-1996228.html First woman to lead Friday prayers in UK]&lt;/ref&gt;

Laury Silvers with lawyer and activist [[El-Farouk Khaki]] founded the El-Tawhid Juma Circle in downtown Toronto. The circle is gender-equal, homosexual-friendly, and religiously non-discriminatory, where all Muslims are welcome to lead the prayer and give the sermon.&lt;ref name=PostJul2&gt;Rachel Sa, "Making history first mosque prayers led by a woman: Mixed-gender service", ''National Post'', July 2, 2005&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=GlobeJul2&gt;Jen Gerson, "Woman leads Islamic prayers in mosque, a first for Canada -- Country could become the conscience of the religion, she says in Friday sermon", ''Globe &amp; Mail'', July 2, 2005&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=NewsweekWPprofile&gt;[http://newsweek.washingtonpost.com/onfaith/pamela_k_taylor/], ''Washington Post/Newsweek&lt;/ref&gt;

==Definitions==
There are subtle yet substantial differences to be noted between the terms 'Islamic feminist', 'Muslim feminist' and 'Islamist'. Any of these terms can be used of men or women.

===Islamic feminists===
Islamic feminists ground their arguments in Islam and its teachings,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.milligazette.com/Archives/2004/16-31Jan04-Print-Edition/1631200425.htm 'Islamic feminism means justice to women', The Milli Gazette, Vol.5 No.02, MG96 (16-31 Jan 04)&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; seek the full equality of women and men in the personal and public sphere, and can include non-Muslims in the discourse and debate.

Islamic feminism is defined by [[Islamic scholars]] as being more radical than secular [[feminism]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://weekly.ahram.org.eg/2002/569/cu1.htm "Islamic feminism: what's in a name?"] by Margot Badran, ''Al-Ahram'', January 17–23, 2002&lt;/ref&gt; and as being anchored within the [[discourse]] of Islam with the [[Quran]] as its central text.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wilsoncenter.org/index.cfm?topic_id=1426&amp;fuseaction=topics.event_summary&amp;event_id=42775 "Exploring Islamic Feminism"] by Margot Badran, Center for Muslim-Christian Understanding, Georgetown University, November 30, 2000&lt;/ref&gt;

In recent times the concept of Islamic feminism has grown further, with Islamic groups looking to garner support from as many aspects of society as possible, and educated Muslim women striving to articulate their role in society.&lt;ref&gt;Humphreys, R. Stephen: "Between Memory and Desire - The Middle East in a Troubled Age", ''University of California Press'', 2005&lt;/ref&gt;

===Islamists===
[[Islamists]] are advocates of [[Political aspects of Islam|political Islam]], the notion that the [[Quran]] and ''[[hadith]]'' mandate a [[caliphate]], i.e. an Islamic government. Some Islamists advocate women's rights in the [[public sphere]] but do not challenge [[Gender equality|gender inequality]] in the personal, [[private sphere]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.iran-bulletin.org/women/Islamic_feminism_IB.html Islamic Feminism And The Politics Of Naming]&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Women in Islam]] and [[Sex segregation and Islam]]
*[[Rights and obligations of spouses in Islam]]
*[[Female figures in the Qur'an]]
*[[Sisters in Islam]]
*[[Role of women in religion]]
*[[Asra Nomani]]
*[[Islamic Bill of Rights for Women in the Mosque]]
*[[History of feminism]]
*[[Rada (fiqh)]]
*[[Tynetta Muhammad]]

'''Other countries:'''
*[[Sex segregation in Iran]]
*[[Women's rights in Iran]]
*[[Women's rights in Saudi Arabia]]
*[[Women's rights in Kuwait]]
*[[Feminism in Egypt]]
*[[Women in Lebanon]]

'''Afghanistan:'''
*[[Taliban treatment of women]]
*[[Golden Needle Sewing School]]
*[[Gender roles in Afghanistan]]
*[[Revolutionary Association of the Women of Afghanistan]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

Alya Baffoun "Women and Social Change in the Muslim World" (Women's Studies International Forum, V, 1982, 227-242).

Baffoun, Alya (1994) "Feminism and Muslim fundamentalism: the Tunisian and Algerian cases" in Valentine M. Moghadam (ed.)
ISBN 0 8133 8692 6.

Baffoun, Alya. 1989 African women participation for research and development : roles and functions of AAWORD. Tunis University publication n:7.

Baffoun, Alya (1980) "Some remarks on Women and Development in the Maghreb" in The Changing Middle Eastern City. State University of New-York.

Baffoun, Alya (1984) "Critical Methodological Approach to the problem of Sexual Asymmetry" in Social Science Research on Women in the Arab World. UNESCO.

==Further reading==
{{External links|date=November 2010}}
*[http://www.islamonline.net/servlet/Satellite?c=Article_C&amp;pagename=Zone-English-Family%2FFYELayout&amp;cid=1157279526015 The Genderless God] By Sheikh Abdal Hakim Murad
*[http://www.islamonline.net/English/family/2005/03/article04c.shtml The Maternal God] By Sheikh Abdal Hakim Murad
*[http://www.oxfordislamicstudies.com/article/opr/t125/e2510?_hi=6&amp;_pos=2 Women and Islam in Oxford Islamic Studies Online]
*[http://www.asmasociety.org/wise/ Women's Islamic Initiative in Spirituality and Equity]
* [http://www.ccmw.com/GTAForum/index.htm Canadian Council of Muslim Women] Several examples of closely argued essays for female equality, based on the Quran.
*[http://www.salafimanhaj.com/pdf/SalafiManhaj_Noble.pdf The Noble Women Scholars of Hadeeth]
*[http://modernmuslimwoman.com The Modern Muslimah Forum]
*[http://globalwebpost.com/farooqm/writings/islamic/bloom.html Women Scholars of Islam: They Must Bloom Again] by Dr. Mohammad Omar Farooq
*[http://www.islamonline.net/English/family/2005/03/article04e.shtml The Feminine Abode] By Sheikh Abdal Hakim Murad
*[http://www.islamicfeminism.org/ IslamicFeminism.org]
*[http://www.maryams.net/dervish/index.php/2003/08/31/feminist_movements_in_islam What is Muslim feminism?] Introduction to the history and concept of Muslim feminism.
*[http://www.jannah.org/sisters/feminism.html "Islamic Traditions and the Feminist Movement: Confrontation or Cooperation?"] by Dr. Lois Lamya' al Faruqi.
*[http://shams.za.org/articles.htm Articles by a South African Islamic feminist] by Shamima Shaikh
*[http://naeemjeenah.shams.za.org/IslamicFeministhHerm.pdf "Towards an Islamic Feminist Hermeneutic"] by Na'eem Jeenah, ''Journal for Islamic Studies'', Vol. 21, 2001, 36-70.
*[http://naeemjeenah.shams.za.org/IslcFemsinSA.pdf "The National Liberation Struggle and Islamic Feminisms in South Africa"] by Na'eem Jeenah, ''Women's Studies International Forum 29'', January 2006, 27-41.
*[http://www.milligazette.com/Archives/2004/16-31Jan04-Print-Edition/1631200425.htm "Islamic feminism means justice to women"] interview with Prof Margot Badran, ''The Milli Gazette'', January 16–31, 2004
*[http://www.islam101.com/women/jameelah.htm "Feminism and Islam"] analysis of Feminism from a traditional Islamic perspective, ''Maryam Jameelah'', July 13, 2005
*[http://www.islam-democracy.org/4th_Annual_Conference-Anwar_address.asp "Islamisation and its Impact on Democractic Governance and Women's Rights in Islam: A Feminist Perspective"] by Zainah Anwar, Center for the Study of Islam and Democracy, May 17, 2003
*[http://www.secularislam.org/rights/declaration.htm "A Declaration of the Rights of Women in Islamic Societies"], ''SecularIslam.com'', undated
*[http://www.ntpi.org/html/liberationofwomen.html "The Liberation of Women in the Middle East"] by Azam Kamguian, undated
*Foreign Affairs Committee of the National Council of Resistance of Iran. [http://www.iran-e-azad.org/english/book_on_women.html ''Women, Islam, and Equality''], an ebook
*Badran, Margot. ''"Feminists, Islam, and Nation: Gender and the Making of Modern Egypt''.
*Eleanor H. Perry ''Opening the Gates: A Century of Arab Feminist Writing'' (June 1, 1993) Article for Domes
* "[http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2005/11/04/AR2005110402306.html A Gender Jihad For Islam's Future]" by [[Asra Nomani]], in the ''[[Washington Post]]'', November 6, 2005
* [http://www.penkatali.org/ Divine Feminine] A feminist Sufi's perspective
*Sutherland, Joan. [http://www.guardian.co.uk/women/story/0,,1746156,00.html "The ideas interview: Phyllis Chesler"], ''The Guardian'', April 4, 2006
*[http://www.diabolicdigest.net/Guest%20pens/Badra_en.htm More to life than window dressing] In this special feature, a successful Belgian-Algerian Muslim woman recounts what it was like growing up immersed in two cultures with divergent views of women. August 2006
*Ahmed, Leila. ''Women and Gender in Islam: Historical Roots of a modern Debate'', 1992, Yale University Press, ISBN 0-300-04942-0
*[http://www.iht.com/articles/2005/12/01/news/islam6.php Muslim women take charge of their faith]'', International Herald Tribune, December 4, 2005
*"Islamic feminism: what's in a name? Islamic feminism is on the whole more radical than Muslims' secular feminisms" by Margot Badran. ''Al-Ahram Weekly Online'', 17–23 January 2002, Issue No.569.

{{Spoken Wikipedia|Wikipedia_-_Islamic_feminism.ogg|2008-03-31}}

{{islam topics}}
{{feminism}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Islamic Feminism}}
[[Category:Women's rights in religious movements]]
[[Category:Feminist theology]]
[[Category:Feminist theory]]
[[Category:Islam and women]]
[[Category:Islam-related controversies]]
[[Category:Islamic feminists| ]]
[[Category:Feminism and spirituality]]
[[Category:Multicultural feminism]]

[[de:Islamischer Feminismus]]
[[es:Feminismo islámico]]
[[fa:فمینیسم اسلامی]]
[[fr:Féminisme musulman]]
[[nl:Moslimfeminisme]]
[[sh:Islamski feminizam]]
[[sv:Islamisk feminism]]
[[tr:İslamcı feminizm]]
[[zh:伊斯蘭女性主義]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>