<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20151116223703|690981047" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="2107559" pageid="2107559" ns="0" title="Islamic feminism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2015-11-16T22:41:21Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[File:Islamic Feminism Symbol.svg|thumb|A symbol for Islamic feminism]]
{{Islam}}
{{Feminism sidebar |variants}}

'''Islamic feminism''' is a form of [[feminism]] concerned with the role of [[women in Islam]]. It aims for the full equality of all [[Muslims]], regardless of gender, in public and private life. Islamic feminists advocate [[women's rights]], [[gender equality]], and [[social justice]] grounded in an Islamic framework. Although rooted in [[Islam]], the movement's pioneers have also utilised [[Secularity|secular]], Western, or otherwise non-Muslim feminist discourses, and have recognized the role of Islamic feminism as part of an integrated global feminist movement.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.feminismeislamic.org/eng/index.htm International Congress on Islamic Feminism]&lt;/ref&gt;

Advocates of the movement seek to highlight the deeply rooted teachings of equality in the religion and to encourage a questioning of the [[patriarchal]] interpretation of Islamic teaching through the Qur'an (holy book), ''[[hadith]]'' (sayings of [[Muhammad]]) and ''[[sharia]]'' (law) towards the creation of a more equal and just society.&lt;ref&gt;[http://weekly.ahram.org.eg/2002/569/cu1.htm Al-Ahram Weekly | Culture | Islamic feminism: what's in a name?&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Muslim majority countries]] have produced several female heads of state, prime ministers, and state secretaries such as [[Lala Shovkat]] of [[Azerbaijan]], [[Benazir Bhutto]] of [[Pakistan]], [[Mame Madior Boye]] of [[Senegal]], [[Tansu Çiller]] of [[Turkey]], [[Kaqusha Jashari]] of [[Kosovo]], and [[Megawati Sukarnoputri]] of [[Indonesia]]. [[Bangladesh]] was the second country in the world (after Mary and [[Elizabeth I]] in 16th century [[England]]) to be ruled by one female followed by another, those two being [[Khaleda Zia]] and [[Sheikh Hasina]]. They have ruled the country as prime ministers since 1991---longer than men have managed, which might make Bangladesh unique in the history of the world’s republics.&lt;ref name="The Economist"&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.economist.com/blogs/banyan/2013/08/women-and-property-rights |title=Who owns Bangladesh? |agency=The Economist |accessdate=December 2, 2013 |date=August 21, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Definitions==
There are substantial differences to be noted between the terms 'Islamic feminist' and 'Islamist'. Any of these terms can be used by men or women.

===Islamic feminists===
Islamic feminists ground their arguments in Islam and its teachings,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.milligazette.com/Archives/2004/16-31Jan04-Print-Edition/1631200425.htm 'Islamic feminism means justice to women', The Milli Gazette, Vol.5 No.02, MG96 (16-31 Jan 04)]&lt;/ref&gt; seek the full equality of women and men in the personal and public sphere, and can include non-Muslims in the discourse and debate.

Islamic feminism is defined by [[Islamic scholars]] as being more radical than secular [[feminism]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://weekly.ahram.org.eg/2002/569/cu1.htm "Islamic feminism: what's in a name?"] by Margot Badran, ''Al-Ahram'', January 17–23, 2002&lt;/ref&gt; and as being anchored within the [[discourse]] of Islam with the [[Qur'an]] as its central text.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wilsoncenter.org/index.cfm?topic_id=1426&amp;fuseaction=topics.event_summary&amp;event_id=42775 "Exploring Islamic Feminism"] by Margot Badran, Center for Muslim-Christian Understanding, Georgetown University, November 30, 2000&lt;/ref&gt;

During recent times, the concept of Islamic feminism has grown further with Islamic groups looking to garner support from many aspects of society. In addition, educated Muslim women are striving to articulate their role in society.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.monitor.upeace.org/innerpg.cfm?id_article=789] Rob L. Wagner: "Saudi-Islamic Feminist Movement: A Struggle for Male Allies and the Right Female Voice", University for Peace (Peace and Conflict Monitor), March 29, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

===Islamists===
[[Islamists]] are advocates of [[Political aspects of Islam|political Islam]], the notion that the [[Qur'an]] and ''[[hadith]]'' mandate a [[caliphate]], i.e. an Islamic government. Some Islamists advocate women's rights in the [[public sphere]] but do not challenge [[Gender equality|gender inequality]] in the personal, [[private sphere]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.iran-bulletin.org/women/Islamic_feminism_IB.html Islamic Feminism And The Politics Of Naming]&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==

===Early reforms under Islam===
{{main|Early social changes under Islam}}
During the [[Muslim history|early days of Islam]] in the 7th century [[Common Era|CE]], reforms in [[women's rights]] affected marriage, divorce and inheritance.&lt;ref name="oxfordislamicstudies.com"&gt;[http://www.oxfordislamicstudies.com/article/opr/t125/e2510?_hi=6&amp;_pos=2 "Women and Islam" in ''Oxford Islamic Studies Online'']&lt;/ref&gt; Women were not accorded such legal status in other cultures, including the West, until centuries later.&lt;ref&gt;Jones, Lindsay. p.6224&lt;/ref&gt; ''The Oxford Dictionary of Islam'' states that the general improvement of the status of [[women in Arab societies]] included prohibition of [[female infanticide]] and recognizing women's full personhood&lt;ref name="oxfordislamicstudies.com"/&gt; (see [[Islamic ethics]]). Under Islamic law, marriage was no longer viewed as a status but rather as a contract, in which the woman's consent was imperative.&lt;ref name="majid"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Espos"/&gt;&lt;ref name="OxfordDicT"&gt;Esposito (2004), p. 339&lt;/ref&gt; "The [[dowry]], previously regarded as a [[bride price|bride-price]] paid to the father, became a nuptial gift retained by the wife as part of her personal property"&lt;ref name="majid"&gt;Khadduri (1978)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Espos"&gt;Esposito (2005) p. 79&lt;/ref&gt; (see also [[Dower]]). "Women were given inheritance rights in a [[patriarchal society]] that had previously restricted inheritance to male relatives."&lt;ref name="Espos"/&gt;

[[Annemarie Schimmel]] states that "compared to the pre-Islamic position of women, [[sharia|Islamic legislation]] meant an enormous progress; the woman has the right, at least according to the letter of the law, to administer the wealth she has brought into the family or has earned by her own work."&lt;ref name = "Schimmel"&gt;Schimmel (1992) p.65&lt;/ref&gt; [[William Montgomery Watt]] states that [[Muhammad]], in the historical context of his time, can be seen as a figure who testified on behalf of women's rights and improved things considerably. Watt explains: "At the time Islam began, the conditions of women were terrible&amp;nbsp;– they had no right to own [[property]], were supposed to be [[chattel|the property of the man]], and if the man died everything went to his sons." Muhammad, however, by "instituting rights of property ownership, inheritance, education and divorce, gave women certain basic safeguards."&lt;ref&gt;Maan, McIntosh (1999)&lt;/ref&gt; Haddad and [[John Esposito|Esposito]] state that "Muhammad granted women rights and privileges in the sphere of family life, marriage, education, and economic endeavors, rights that help improve women's status in society."&lt;ref&gt;Haddad, Esposito (1998) p.163&lt;/ref&gt;

===Islamic Golden Age===
{{See also|Women in Islam|Islamic Golden Age}}

Whilst the pre-modern period lacked a formal feminist movement, nevertheless a number of important figures argued for improving women's rights and autonomy. These range from the medieval mystic and philosopher [[Ibn Arabi]], who argued that women could achieve spiritual stations as equally high as men&lt;ref name=Hakim-2002&gt;{{citation|title=Ibn 'Arabî's Twofold Perception of Woman: Woman as Human Being and Cosmic Principle | first = Souad | last = Hakim | journal =Journal of the Muhyiddin Ibn 'Arabi Society|volume=31|year=2002|pages=1–29}}&lt;/ref&gt; to [[Nana Asma’u]], daughter of eighteenth-century reformer [[Usman Dan Fodio]], who pushed for literacy and the education of Muslim women.&lt;ref name=Mack-2000&gt;{{citation|title=One Woman's Jihad: Nana Asma’u, Scholar and Scribe|first=Beverly B.|last=Mack|coauthors=Jean Boyd | location = USA | publisher=Indiana University Press|year=2000}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Education====
{{See also|Madrasah}}

Women played an important role in the foundations of many Islamic educational institutions: note for example [[Fatima al-Fihri]]'s founding of the [[University of Al Karaouine]] in 859 CE. This continued through to the [[Ayyubid dynasty]] in the 12th and 13th centuries: of 160 [[mosque]]s and [[madrasah]]s established in [[Damascus]], women funded 26 through the [[Waqf]] ([[charitable trust]] or [[trust law]]) system. Half of all the royal [[Patronage|patrons]] for these institutions were also women.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |title=Daily Life in the Medieval Islamic World|first=James E.|last=Lindsay|publisher=[[Greenwood Publishing Group]]|year=2005|isbn=0-313-32270-8|page=197}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the [[Sunni]] scholar [[Ibn Asakir]] in the 12th century, there were opportunities for [[female education]]. He wrote that girls and women could study, earn ''[[ijazah]]s'' ([[academic degree]]s), and qualify as scholars (''[[ulema]]'') and teachers. This was especially the case for learned and scholarly families, who wanted to ensure the highest possible education for both their sons and daughters.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|title=Daily Life in the Medieval Islamic World|first=James E.|last=Lindsay|publisher=[[Greenwood Publishing Group]]|year=2005|isbn=0-313-32270-8|pages=196 &amp; 198}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ibn Asakir had himself studied under 80 different female teachers. Female education in the Islamic world was inspired by [[Muhammad's wives]]: [[Khadijah]], a successful businesswoman, and [[Aisha]], a renowned [[Muhaddith|scholar of the ''hadith'']] and [[Battle of Bassorah|military leader]]. [[hadith|Muhammad is said]] to have praised the women of [[Medina]] for their desire for religious knowledge:&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|title=Daily Life in the Medieval Islamic World|first=James E.|last=Lindsay|publisher=[[Greenwood Publishing Group]]|year=2005|isbn=0-313-32270-8|page=196}}&lt;/ref&gt; "How splendid were the women of the ''[[Ansar (Islam)|ansar]]''; shame did not prevent them from becoming learned in the faith."

While it was not common for women to enroll as students in formal classes, they did attend informal lectures and study sessions at mosques, madrasahs and other public places. Although there were no legal restrictions on female education, some men did not approve of this practice. For example, Muhammad ibn al-Hajj (d. 1336) was appalled at the behaviour of some women who informally [[audit]]ed lectures in his time:&lt;ref name=Lindsay&gt;{{citation|title=Daily Life in the Medieval Islamic World|first=James E.|last=Lindsay|publisher=[[Greenwood Publishing Group]]|year=2005|isbn=0-313-32270-8|page=198}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|[Consider] what some women do when people gather with a [[Sheikh|shaykh]] to hear [the recitation of] books. At that point women come, too, to hear the readings; the men sit in one place, the women facing them. It even happens at such times that some of the women are carried away by the situation; one will stand up, and sit down, and shout in a loud voice. [Moreover,] her ''awra'' will appear; in her house, their exposure would be forbidden&amp;nbsp;— how can it be allowed in a mosque, in the presence of men?}}

(''[[Awrah|'awra]]'' refers to the parts of the body that should remain covered; see also ''[[hijab]]'' for the rules of modesty governing both men and women.)

On the question of women in medieval Islam, Abdul Hakim Murad writes
&lt;blockquote&gt;
the orientalist Ignaz Goldziher showed that perhaps fifteen percent of medieval hadith scholars were women, teaching in the mosques and universally admired for their integrity. Colleges such as the Saqlatuniya Madrasa in Cairo were funded and staffed entirely by women. The most recent study of Muslim female academicians, by Ruth Roded, charts an extraordinary dilemma for the researcher:

'If U.S. and European historians feel a need to reconstruct women's history because women are invisible in the traditional sources, Islamic scholars are faced with a plethora of source material that has only begun to be studied. [. . .] In reading the biographies of thousands of Muslim women scholars, one is amazed at the evidence that contradicts the view of Muslim women as marginal, secluded, and restricted.'

Stereotypes come under almost intolerable strain when Roded documents the fact that the proportion of female lecturers in many classical Islamic colleges was higher than in modern Western universities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Abdal Hakim Murad |url=http://www.masud.co.uk/ISLAM/ahm/gender.htm |title=Islam, Irigaray, and the retrieval of Gender |publisher=Masud.co.uk |accessdate=2012-08-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

In the 15th century, [[Al-Sakhawi]] devotes an entire volume of his 12-volume [[biographical dictionary]] ''Daw al-lami'' to female scholars, giving information on 1,075 of them.&lt;ref&gt;
{{citation | title = Women in Iran from the Rise of Islam to 1800 | last = Guity Nashat | first = Lois Beck | publisher = [[University of Illinois Press]] | year = 2003 | isbn = 0-252-07121-2 | page=69
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

====Civil and military work====
The [[labor force]] in the [[Caliphate]] came from diverse ethnic and religious backgrounds, while both men and women were involved in diverse occupations and [[Islamic economics in the world|economic activities]].&lt;ref&gt;Maya Shatzmiller, pp. 6–7.&lt;/ref&gt; Women were employed in a wide range of commercial activities and diverse occupations&lt;ref name=Maya-400-1&gt;Maya Shatzmiller (1994), ''Labour in the Medieval Islamic World'', [[Brill Publishers]], ISBN 90-04-09896-8, pp. 400–1&lt;/ref&gt; in the primary sector (as farmers for example), secondary sector (as construction workers, dyers, spinners, etc.) and tertiary sector (as investors, doctors, nurses, presidents of [[guild]]s, brokers, peddlers, lenders, scholars, etc.).&lt;ref&gt;Maya Shatzmiller, pp. 350–62.&lt;/ref&gt; Muslim women also held a monopoly over certain branches of the [[textile industry]],&lt;ref name=Maya-400-1/&gt; the largest and most specialized and market-oriented industry at the time, in occupations such as [[Spinning (textiles)|spinning]], [[dyeing]], and [[embroidery]]. In comparison, female [[property rights]] and [[wage labour]] were relatively uncommon in Europe until the [[Industrial Revolution]] in the 18th and 19th centuries.&lt;ref&gt;Maya Shatzmiller (1997), "Women and Wage Labour in the Medieval Islamic West: Legal Issues in an Economic Context", ''Journal of the Economic and Social History of the Orient'' '''40''' (2), pp. 174–206 [175–7].&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 12th century, the famous [[Islamic philosophy|Islamic philosopher]] and ''[[qadi]]'' (judge) [[Averroes|Ibn Rushd]], known to the West as ''Averroes'', claimed that women were equal to men in all respects and possessed equal capacities to shine [[Peace In Islamic Thought|in peace]] and [[Islamic military jurisprudence|in war]], citing examples of female warriors among the Arabs, Greeks and Africans to support his case.&lt;ref name=Ahmad&gt;{{citation|last=Ahmad|first=Jamil|date=September 1994|title=Ibn Rushd|journal=[[Al-Mawrid|Monthly Renaissance]]|volume=4|issue=9|url=http://www.monthly-renaissance.com/issue/content.aspx?id=744|accessdate=2008-10-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; In early [[Muslim history]], examples of notable women who fought during the [[Muslim conquests]] and [[Fitna (word)|Fitna]] (civil wars) as soldiers or generals included [[Nusaybah Bint k'ab Al Maziniyyah]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.realnews247.com/girl_power.htm Girl Power], [[ABC News]]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Aisha]],&lt;ref name="Baghdad"&gt;{{Citation|last=Black|first=Edwin|title=Banking on Baghdad: Inside Iraq's 7,000 Year History of War, Profit, and Conflict|publisher=John Wiley and Sons|year= 2004|isbn=0-471-70895-X|page=34}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Kahula]] and Wafeira.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | title=Woman's Record: Or, Sketches of All Distinguished Women, from "The Beginning Till A.D. 1850, Arranged in Four Eras, with Selections from Female Writers of Every Age| author=Hale, Sarah Josepha Buell |publisher=Harper Brothers|year=1853|page=120}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Property, marriage, and other rights====
In terms of women's rights, women generally had fewer legal restrictions under Islamic law (''[[sharia]]'') than they did under certain Western legal systems until the 20th century. For example, under traditional interpretations of ''sharia'', women had the right to keep their surnames upon marriage; inherit and bestow inheritance; independently manage their financial affairs; and contract marriages and divorce. In contrast, restrictions on the legal capacity of married women under [[French law]] were not removed until 1965.&lt;ref name=Badr-1984&gt;{{citation|title=Islamic Criminal Justice|first=Gamal M.|last=Badr|journal=The American Journal of Comparative Law|volume=32|issue=1|date=Winter 1984|pages=167–169 [167–8]|doi=10.2307/840274|author2=Mayer, Ann Elizabeth|publisher=The American Journal of Comparative Law, Vol. 32, No. 1|jstor=840274}}&lt;/ref&gt; Noah Feldman, a law professor at [[Harvard University]], notes:

{{quote|As for [[sexism]], the [[common law]] long denied married women any property rights or indeed legal personality apart from their husbands. When the British applied their law to Muslims in place of Shariah, as they did in some colonies, the result was to strip married women of the property that Islamic law had always granted them&amp;nbsp;— hardly progress toward equality of the sexes.&lt;ref name=Feldman&gt;{{cite news|author=Noah Feldman|title=Why Shariah?|publisher=New York Times|date=March 16, 2008|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2008/03/16/magazine/16Shariah-t.html?ei=5070&amp;em=&amp;en=5c1b8de536ce606f&amp;ex=1205812800&amp;pagewanted=all|accessdate=2008-10-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

In contrast to the [[Western world]], during the 15th century and afterward, where divorce was relatively uncommon until modern times, divorce (''[[Talaq (Nikah)|talaq]]'') was a more common occurrence at certain points during that era in the [[Muslim world]]. In the [[Mamluk Sultanate (Cairo)|Mamluk Sultanate]] and early [[Ottoman Empire]], the rate of divorce was higher than it is today in the modern Middle East, at least according to one study.&lt;ref name=Rapoport&gt;{{citation|title=Marriage, Money and Divorce in Medieval Islamic Society |first=Yossef|last=Rapoport|publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]]|year=2005|isbn=0-521-84715-X|page=2}}
&lt;/ref&gt; In 15th-century [[Egypt]], [[Al-Sakhawi]] recorded the marital history of 500 women, the largest [[Sampling (statistics)|sample]] on marriage in the [[Middle Ages]], and found that at least a third of all women in the [[Mamluk Sultanate (Cairo)|Mamluk Sultanate]] of [[Egypt]] and [[Syria]] married more than once, with many marrying three or more times.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|title=Marriage, Money and Divorce in Medieval Islamic Society |first= Yossef|last=Rapoport|publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]]|year=2005|isbn=0-521-84715-X|pages=5–6}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

===Nineteenth century===
The modern movement of Islamic feminism began in the nineteenth century. The [[Iran]]ian poetess [[Táhirih]] was the first [[Modern history|modern]] woman to undertake Qur'anic [[exegesis]]. Born and raised in a traditional Muslim family, she would later become a prominent member of the Bábí Faith, during which time she openly denounced [[polygyny]], the wearing of the veil and other restraints put upon women. One of her most notable quotes is her final utterance prior to her execution, "You can kill me as soon as you like, but you cannot stop the emancipation of women."&lt;ref&gt;Shoghi Effendi, God Passes By, (Bahá'í Publishing Trust, Wilmette, rev. ed. 1953), p. 75]&lt;/ref&gt;

Egyptian jurist [[Qasim Amin]], the author of the 1899 pioneering book ''Women's Liberation'' (''Tahrir al-Mar'a''), is often described as the father of the [[Feminism in Egypt|Egyptian feminist movement]]. In his work, Amin criticized some of the practices prevalent in his society at the time, such as [[Polygyny in Islam|polygyny]], [[Islam and clothing|the veil]], and ''[[purdah]]'', i.e. [[sex segregation in Islam]]. He condemned them as un-Islamic and contradictory to the true spirit of Islam. His work had an enormous influence on women's political movements throughout the Islamic and [[Arab world]], and is read and cited today.

Despite Qasim Amin's effects on modern-day Islamic feminist movements, present-day scholar Leila Ahmed considers his works both [[androcentric]] and [[colonialist]].&lt;ref&gt;Leila Ahmed. Women and Gender in Islam. New Haven and London: Yale University Press, 1992. pp.155-163, 171, 179.&lt;/ref&gt; Muhammad 'Abdu, an Egyptian nationalist,&lt;ref&gt;Leila Ahmed. Women and Gender in Islam. New Haven and London: Yale University Press, 1992. pp.136-137.&lt;/ref&gt; could easily have written the chapters of his work that show honest considerations of the negative effects of the veil on women.&lt;ref&gt;Leila Ahmed. Women and Gender in Islam. New Haven and London: Yale University Press, 1992. pp.159,161.&lt;/ref&gt; Amin even posed many male-centered misconceptions about women, such as their inability to experience love, that women needlessly (when they had very good reason to) talk about their husbands outside their presence, and that Muslim marriage is based on ignorance and sensuality, of which women were the chief source.&lt;ref&gt;Leila Ahmed. Women and Gender in Islam. New Haven and London: Yale University Press, 1992. pp.157-159.&lt;/ref&gt;

Less known, however, are the women who preceded Amin in their feminist critique of their societies. The women's press in Egypt started voicing such concerns since its very first issues in 1892. Egyptian, Turkish, Iranian, Syrian and Lebanese women and men had been reading European feminist magazines even a decade earlier, and discussed their relevance to the Middle East in the general press.&lt;ref&gt;see "Great Ancestors: Women Asserting Rights in Muslim Contexts", by Farida Shaheed with Aisha L.F. Shaheed (London/Lahore: WLUML/Shirkat Gah, 2005) [http://www.wluml.org/english/pubsfulltxt.shtml?%5B87%5D=i-87-186208]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Twentieth century===
[[Aisha Abd al-Rahman]], writing under her pen name ''Bint al-Shati'' ("Daughter of the Riverbank"), was the second modern woman to undertake [[Qur'an]]ic [[exegesis]], and though she did not consider herself to be a feminist, her works reflect feminist themes. She began producing her popular books in 1959, the same year that [[Naguib Mahfouz]] published his allegorical and feminist version of the life of Muhammad.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|first=Ruth|last=Roded|title=Bint al-Shati's Wives of the Prophet: Feminist or Feminine?|journal=British Journal of Middle Eastern Studies|date=May 2006|volume=33|issue=1|pages=51–66|doi=10.1080/13530190600603915}}&lt;/ref&gt; She wrote biographies of early [[women in Islam]], including the [[Aminah bint Wahb|mother]], [[Muhammad's wives|wives]] and [[Family tree of Muhammad|daughters]] of the [[Prophets of Islam|Prophet]] Muhammad, as well as [[literary criticism]].&lt;ref name="zeidan"&gt;Arab Women Novelists: The Formative Years and Beyond by Joseph T. Zeidan, State University of New York Press, 1995&lt;/ref&gt; [[Fatema Mernissi]] has argued that much of the suppression of women's rights in Islamic societies is the result of political motivation and its consequent manipulative interpretation of [[hadith]], which runs counter to the egalitarian Islamic community of men and women envisioned by [[Muhammed]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Mernissi |first=Fatima |authorlink=Fatima Mernissi |year=1992 |title=The Veil and the Male Elite: A Feminist Interpretation of Islam |publisher=New York: Basic Books |isbn=978-0201-63221-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some strains of modern Islamic feminism have opted to expunge hadith from their ideology altogether in favor of a movement focusing only on Qur'anic principles. [[Riffat Hassan]] has advocated one such movement, articulating a theology wherein what are deemed to be universal rights for humanity outlined in the Qur'an are prioritized over contextual laws and regulations.&lt;ref&gt;Hassan, Riffat. "Women's Rights inIslam: Normative Teaching versus Practice," in ''Islam and Human Rights: Advancing a U.S.- Muslim Dialogue'', edited by Shireen T. Hunter with Huma Malik, The CSIS Press, Washington D.C., 2005, pp. 43-66.&lt;/ref&gt; She has additionally claimed that the Qur'an, taken alone as scripture, does not present females either as a creation preceded by the male or as the instigator of the "[[Original sin|Fall of Man]]".&lt;ref&gt;Hassan, Riffat. "Woman and Man's "fall": A Qur'anic Theological Perspective," in ''Muslima Theology: The Voices of Muslim Women Theologians'', edited by Ednan Aslan, Marcia Hermansen, and Elif Medini, Peter Lang, Frankfurt, 2013, pp. 101-113.&lt;/ref&gt; This theological movement has been met with criticism from other Muslim feminists such as Kecia Ali, who has criticized its selective nature for ignoring elements within the Muslim tradition that could prove helpful in establishing more egalitarian norms in Islamic society.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Sexual Ethics &amp; Islam|last = Ali|first = Kecia|publisher = Oneworld|year = 2006|isbn = 978-1-85168-456-4|location = London|pages = 154-155}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Recently Islamic feminists have begun advocating for equality in the mosque and equality in prayer, as you can see in the "Equality in the Mosque" and "Equality in Prayer" sections further down in this article.

==Areas of campaign==

===Personal law===
{{Refimprove section|date=May 2010}}
{{See also|Islamic marital jurisprudence}}

One of the major areas of scholarship and campaigning for Islamic feminists are aspects of ''[[sharia]]'' (Islamic law) known as Muslim personal law (MPL) or Muslim family law. There is dispute that the use of ''sharia'' law is oppressive because they are based mainly on "man-made misinterpretations of the sacred texts" and are not based in Islam.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.clarionproject.org/understanding-islamism/womens-rights-under-sharia&lt;/ref&gt; Some of the thorny issues regarding the way in which MPL has thus far been formulated include [[Polygamy in Islam|polygyny]], [[Divorce in Islam|divorce]], custody of children, maintenance and marital property. In addition, there are also more macro issues regarding the underlying assumptions of such legislation, for example, the assumption of the man as [[head of the household]].

[[Muslim majority countries]] that have promulgated some form of MPL include [[Saudi Arabia]], [[Afghanistan]], [[Pakistan]], [[Libya]], [[Sudan]], [[Senegal]], [[Tunisia]], [[Egypt]], [[Indonesia]], and [[Bangladesh]]. Muslim minority countries that already have incorporated MPL into their own law or are considering passing legislation on aspects of MPL include [[India]], [[Israel]], and [[South Africa]].

Islamic feminists have objected to the MPL legislation in many of these countries, arguing that these pieces of legislation discriminate against women. Some Islamic feminists have taken the attitude that a reformed MPL which is based on the [[Qur'an]] and [[sunnah]], which includes substantial input from Muslim women, and which does not discriminate against women is possible. Such Islamic feminists have been working on developing women-friendly forms of MPL. (See, for example, [http://www.ccmw.com/GTAForum/index.htm the Canadian Council of Muslim Women] for argument based on the Qur'an and not on what they call medieval male consensus.) Other Islamic feminists, particularly some in Muslim minority contexts which are democratic states, argue that MPL should not be reformed but should be rejected and that Muslim women should seek redress, instead, from the [[Civil law (legal system)|civil law]]s of those states. &lt;!--this paragraph needs to cite sources and name the women or groups, instead of "some Islamic feminists."--&gt;

===Dress codes===
{{See also|Sartorial hijab|Islam and clothing|Awrah|Purdah}}
Another issue that concerns Muslim women is the [[dress code]] expected of them. Islam requires both men and women to dress modestly; this concept is known as ''[[hijab]]'' and covers a wide interpretation of behavior and garments.  There is mixed opinion among Muslim feminists over extremes of externally imposed control.

A number of Islamic feminists, including [[Fadela Amara]] and [[:fr:Hédi M'henni|Hedi Mhenni]] support bans on the ''hijab'' for various reasons. Amara explained her support for France's ban of the garment in public buildings: "The veil is the visible symbol of the subjugation of women, and therefore has no place in the mixed, [[Laïcité|secular spaces]] of [[education in France|France's public school system]]."&lt;ref name="guardian.co.uk"&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2006/jul/17/france.politicsphilosophyandsociety | work=The Guardian | location=London | title=Ghetto warrior | date=July 17, 2006 | accessdate=May 5, 2010 | first=Rose | last=George}}&lt;/ref&gt; When some feminists began defending the headscarf on the grounds of "tradition", Amara was quoted as saying: "It's not tradition, it's archaic! French feminists are totally contradictory. When [[women in Algeria|Algerian women]] fought against wearing the headscarf in [[Algeria]], [[feminism in France|French feminists]] supported them. But when it's some young girl in a [[Banlieue|French suburb]] school, they don't. They define [[Liberté, égalité, fraternité|liberty and equality]] according to what colour your skin is. It's nothing more than [[neocolonialism]]."&lt;ref name="guardian.co.uk"/&gt; Mhenni also expressed support for [[Tunisia]]'s ban on the veil: "If today we accept the headscarf, tomorrow we'll accept that women's rights to work and vote and receive an education be banned and they'll be seen as just a tool for reproduction and housework."&lt;ref&gt;http://www.islamonline.net/English/News/2006-10/06/06.shtml&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Sihem Habchi]], Muslim feminist and director of [[Ni Putes Ni Soumises]], expressed support for France's ban on the burqa in public places, stating that the ban was a matter of 'democratic principle' and protecting French women from the 'obscurantist, fascist, right-wing movement' that she claims the burqa represents.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/today/hi/today/newsid_8568000/8568024.stm | work=BBC News | title=France's burka dilemma | date=March 15, 2010 | first=Zubeida | last=Malik}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vingtparismagazine.com/2010/01/ni-putes-ni-soumises-organizes-a-protest-against-the-burqa.html]{{dead link|date=August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Alternatively, there is also strong support in favor of the veil. Both men and women now view the veil as a symbol of Islamic freedom.  “It is no longer a bandanna version of the all-encompassing Afghan burqa, signaling a woman's brainwashed submissiveness or at the very least her lack of choice”.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://content.time.com/time/world/article/0,8599,2076653,00.html | work=Time | title=Is the Veil Now a Symbol of Islamic Freedom? | date=June 13, 2011 | first=Azadeh | last=Moeveni}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Many scholars agree that there is no scripture that requires women to wear the hijab but many still do as an act of religious piety.

The Qur'an does state that both men and women should be dressed modestly (33:59-60, 24:30-31; in translation by Ali, 1988, 1126–27). However it does not use the words veil, hijab, burka, chador, or abaya. It uses the words ''jilbab'' meaning cloak and ''khumur'' meaning shawl. These do not cover the face, hands, or feet. Furthermore, until the third through the ninth century women prayed in the mosques unveiled. The whole body covering with the burka, chador, and other items of clothing is a tradition and cultural manifest from a conservative reading of the Qur'an by Mullahs; men. It is not what the Qur'an itself states. The Qur'an, 2:256, states "Let there be no compulsion in religion".&lt;ref&gt;"Believing Women in Islam" by Asma Barlos, University of Texas Press, Austin. 2002, 53-55.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Rachel Woodlock]], an academic and writer specializing in Islam, has detailed in an article that the issue of wearing the veil depends on specific cultures along with cultural context. In addition, modern Muslim feminists believe that ultimately the importance lies in a woman's freedom of choice---her choice to wear the veil or not to, and not have her right to do so threatened. Muslim women should be able to define dress codes for themselves and what they deem to be morally right.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.irfi.org/articles/articles_301_350/veiling_and_hijab_as_understood.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

===Equality in the Mosque===

A survey by the Council on American Islamic Relations showed that two of three mosques in 2000 required women to pray in a separate area, up from one of two in 1994.&lt;ref name="thedailybeast1"&gt;{{cite web|author=Asra Q. Nomani |url=http://www.thedailybeast.com/blogs-and-stories/2010-02-27/let-these-women-pray/ |title=Let These Women Pray! |publisher=The Daily Beast |date=2010-02-27 |accessdate=2012-08-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Islamic feminists have begun to protest this, advocating for women to be allowed to pray beside men without a partition as they do in Mecca.&lt;ref name="washingtonpost1"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2010/05/21/AR2010052104253.html |title=Mosque pray-ins against segregation of sexes are springing up |publisher=Washingtonpost.com |accessdate=2012-08-13 |first1=William |last1=Wan |first2=Michael |last2=Laris |date=May 22, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Marsh |first=Julia |url=http://www.womensenews.org/story/religion/100222/protesters-break-prayer-rules-at-leading-mosque |title=Protesters Break Prayer Rules at Leading Mosque |publisher=Women's eNews |date=2010-02-22 |accessdate=2012-08-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In 2003, [[Asra Nomani]] challenged the rules at her mosque in Morgantown, West Virginia, that required women to enter through a back door and pray in a secluded balcony.&lt;ref name="thedailybeast1"/&gt;  She argued that in the 7th century the Islamic prophet Muhammad didn't put women behind partitions. Barriers preventing women from praying equally with men are just sexist man-made rules.&lt;ref name="thedailybeast1"/&gt;  The men at her mosque put her on trial to be banished.&lt;ref name="thedailybeast1"/&gt;

In 2005, following public agitation on the issue, Muslim organizations that included the CAIR and the Islamic Society of North America issued a report on making mosques "women-friendly", to assert women's rights in mosques, and to include women's right to pray in the main hall without a partition.&lt;ref name="thedailybeast1"/&gt;

In 2010, American Muslim Fatima Thompson and a few others organized and participated in a "pray-in" at the Islamic Center of Washington in D.C.&lt;ref name="thedailybeast1"/&gt; Police were summoned and threatened to arrest the women when they refused to leave the main prayer hall. The women continued their protest against being corralled in what they referred to as the "penalty box" (a prayer space reserved for only women). Fatima Thompson called the penalty box "an overheated, dark back room." &lt;ref name="thedailybeast1"/&gt;  A second protest also staged by the same group on the eve of International Women's Day in 2010 resulted in calls to the police and threats of arrest again.&lt;ref name="thedailybeast1"/&gt;  However, the women were not arrested on either occasion.&lt;ref name="thedailybeast1"/&gt; 

Furthermore, in May 2010, five women prayed with men at the Dar al-Hijrah mosque, one of the Washington region's largest Islamic centers.&lt;ref name="washingtonpost1"/&gt;  After the prayers, a member of the mosque called Fairfax police who asked the women to leave.&lt;ref name="washingtonpost1"/&gt;  However, later in 2010, it was decided that D.C. police would no longer intervene in such protests.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.washingtonexaminer.com/local/D_C_-police-won_t-intervene-to-remove-women-from-mosques-96758814.html]{{dead link|date=August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Equality in leading prayer===
{{Main|Women as imams}}

According to currently existing traditional schools of [[Islam]], a woman cannot lead a mixed gender congregation in salat (prayer). Some schools make exceptions for [[Tarawih]] (optional [[Ramadan]] prayers) or for a congregation consisting only of close relatives. Certain medieval scholars—including [[Muhammad ibn Jarir al-Tabari]] (838–923), [[Abu Thawr]] (764–854), [[Isma'il Ibn Yahya al-Muzani]] (791–878), and [[Ibn Arabi]] (1165–1240) considered the practice permissible at least for optional ([[nafl]]) prayers; however, their views are not accepted by any major surviving group. Islamic feminists have begun to protest this.

On March 18, 2005, Amina Wadud led a mixed-gender congregational Friday prayer in New York City. It sparked a controversy within the Muslim community because the imam was a woman, Wadud, who also delivered the khutbah.&lt;ref name=Hammer&gt;{{cite book|last=Hammer|first=Juliane|title=American Muslim Women, Religious Authority, and Activism|year=2012|publisher=University of Texas Press|location=Austin}}&lt;/ref&gt; Moreover, the congregation she addressed was not separated by gender. This event that departed from the established ritual practice became an embodied performance of gender justice in the eyes of its organizers and participants. The event was widely publicized in the global media and caused in equally global debate among Muslims.&lt;ref name=Hammer /&gt; However, many Muslims, including women, remain in disagreement with the idea of a women as imam. Muzammil Siddiqi, chairman of the Fiqh Council of North America, argued that prayer leadership should remain restricted to men &lt;ref name=Hammer /&gt;  He based his argument on the longstanding practice and thus community consensus and emphasized the danger of women distracting men during prayers.

The events that occurred in regards to equality in the Mosque and women leading prayers, show the enmity Muslim feminists may receive when voicing opposition toward sexism and establishing efforts to combat it. Those who criticize Muslim feminists state that those who question the faith's views on gender segregation, or who attempt to make changes, are overstepping their boundaries and are acting offensively. On the other hand, people have stated that Islam does not advocate gender segregation. Britain's influential Sunni imam, [[Ahtsham Ali]], has stated, "gender segregation has no basis in Islamic law" nor is it justified in the Quran. &lt;ref&gt;http://english.alarabiya.net/en/News/middle-east/2014/08/02/UK-imam-Quran-does-not-justify-gender-segregation-.html&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notable people==
*[[Leila Ahmed]] - Egyptian-American professor of women's studies
*[[Qasim Amin]] - an early advocate of women's rights in Islamic society
*[[Elvia Ardalani]] - a Mexican writer and author of ''De cruz y media luna/ From Cross and Crescent Moon''
*[[Begum Rokeya|Begum Rokeya Sakhawat Hussain]] - A [[Bangladeshi]] gender equality activist, founder of the first Muslim girls' school in [[Bengal]], authored ''[[Sultana's Dream]]'' (an early work of [[feminist science fiction]]), ''[[Begum Rokeya#Works|The Woman in Captivity]]'' (Bengali: অবরোধবাসিনী), ''[[Begum Rokeya#Works|Essence of the lotus]]'' (Bengali: পদ্মরাগ) and several other feminism based publications.
*[[Asma Barlas]] - Pakistani-American professor at [[Ithaca College]], and author of ''"Believing Women" in Islam: Unreading Patriarchal Interpretations of the Qur'an''
*[[Mukhtaran Bibi]] - Pakistani advocate for rape prevention and women's rights
*[[Shirin Ebadi]] - Iranian lawyer and human rights activist who founded the Association for Support of Children's Rights.  Also, a [[Nobel Peace Prize]] winner in 2003 for her efforts in promoting democracy and human rights especially for women and children.
*[[Farid Esack]] - male supporter and scholar
*[[Soumya Naâmane Guessous]] - Moroccan sociologist and campaigner on inheriting citizenship
*[[Zaib-un-Nissa Hamidullah]] - Pakistan's first woman columnist and editor, first woman to speak at [[Al-Azhar University]], and author of ''The Bull and the She Devil''
*[[Riffat Hassan]] - Pakistani-American theologian and scholar of the Qur'an
*[[Hamida Javanshir]] - Azerbaijani philanthropist, co-founder in 1910 of the Muslim Women's Caucasian Benevolent Society
*[[Na'eem Jeenah]] - South African scholar and activist
*[[Shamsunnahar Mahmud]] - Bengali writer, educationalist, politician and activist.
*[[Irshad Manji]] - Canadian journalist, author of ''[[The Trouble with Islam Today]]''
*[[Fatema Mernissi]] - Moroccan writer
*[[Ebrahim Moosa]] - South African scholar on Islamic law, based at [[Duke University]]
*[[Shirin Neshat]] - Iranian-born American artist
*[[Asra Nomani]] - Indian-American journalist, author of ''[[Standing Alone in Mecca|Standing Alone in Mecca: An American Woman's Struggle for the Soul of Islam]]'' 
*[[Nawal El Saadawi]] - Egyptian author
*[[Hoda Shaarawi]] - early advocate of Egyptian women's rights
*[[Shamima Shaikh]] - South African women's rights activist and journalist
*[[Zilla Huma Usman]] - Pakistani politician and activist, assassinated Feb 2007
*[[Amina Wadud]] - African American professor and author
*[[Benazir Bhutto]]- Prime Minister of Pakistan, assassinated December 27, 2007
*[[Raheel Raza]] - Canadian writer, speaker, human rights advocate to lead 1st woman-led prayer
*[[Shahla Sherkat]] - Award-winning Iranian journalist, prominent feminist author, a pioneer of the [[Women's rights movement in Iran]]
*Ziba Mir Hosseynni 
*Asma Lamrabet 
*Oumayma Abu Bakr
*Zainah Anwar

==See also==
{{div col|cols=2}}
*[[Female figures in the Qur'an]]
*[[Feminism in Egypt]]
*[[Feminism in India]]
*[[Gender roles in Afghanistan]]
*[[Gender segregation and Islam]]
*[[Golden Needle Sewing School]]
*[[History of feminism]]
*[[Islamic Bill of Rights for Women in the Mosque]]
*[[Rada (fiqh)]]
*[[Revolutionary Association of the Women of Afghanistan]]
*[[Rights and obligations of spouses in Islam]]
*[[Role of women in religion (disambiguation)|Role of women in religion]]
*[[Sex segregation in Iran]]
*[[Sisters in Islam]]
*[[Taliban treatment of women]]
*[[Women in Islam]]
*[[Women in Lebanon]]
*[[Women's rights in Iran]]
*[[Women's rights in Saudi Arabia]]
*[[Women's rights in Kuwait]]
*[[Women's rights movement in Iran]]
{{div col end}}

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
* Ali, Kecia, "Feminist Thought in Islam", in Muhammad in History, Thought, and Culture: An Encyclopedia of the Prophet of God (2 vols.), Edited by C. Fitzpatrick and A. Walker, Santa Barbara, ABC-CLIO, 2014, Vol I, pp.&amp;nbsp;195–197.
* {{Cite journal | last = Baffoun | first = Alya | title = Women and social change in the Muslim Arab world | journal = [[Women's Studies International Forum]], special issue: Women and Islam | volume = 5 | issue = 2 | pages = 227–242 | publisher = [[ScienceDirect]] | doi = 10.1016/0277-5395(82)90030-9 | date = 1982 | url = http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0277-5395(82)90030-9 | ref = harv | postscript = .}}
* Baffoun, Alya (1994) "Feminism and Muslim fundamentalism: the Tunisian and Algerian cases" in Valentine M. Moghadam (ed.) ISBN 0-8133-8692-6.
* Baffoun, Alya. 1989 African women participation for research and development : roles and functions of AAWORD. Tunis University publication n:7.
* Baffoun, Alya (1980) "Some remarks on Women and Development in the Maghreb" in The Changing Middle Eastern City. State University of New-York.
* Baffoun, Alya (1984) "Critical Methodological Approach to the problem of Sexual Asymmetry" in Social Science Research on Women in the Arab World. UNESCO.
* Fernea, Elizabeth Warnock (1998). In Search of Islamic Feminism: One Woman's Global Journey, New York: Doubleday. 
*[http://www.oxfordislamicstudies.com/article/opr/t125/e2510?_hi=6&amp;_pos=2 Women and Islam in Oxford Islamic Studies Online]
*[http://www.asmasociety.org/wise/ Women's Islamic Initiative in Spirituality and Equity]
*[http://www.ccmw.com Canadian Council of Muslim Women] Several examples of closely argued essays for female equality, based on the Qur'an.
*[http://modernmuslimwoman.com The Modern Muslimah Forum] å
*[http://globalwebpost.com/farooqm/writings/islamic/bloom.html Women Scholars of Islam: They Must Bloom Again] by Dr. Mohammad Omar Farooq
*[http://www.jannah.org/sisters/feminism.html "Islamic Traditions and the Feminist Movement: Confrontation or Cooperation?"] by Dr. Lois Lamya' al Faruqi.
*[http://shams.za.org/articles.htm Articles by a South African Islamic feminist] by Shamima Shaikh
* {{Cite journal | last = Jeenah | first = Na'eem | author-link = Na'eem Jeenah | title = Towards an Islamic feminist hermeneutic | journal = Journal for Islamic Studies | volume = 21 | issue = | pages = 36–70 | publisher = Centre for Contemporary Islam | location = Cape Town | doi = 10.4314/jis.v21i1.39954 | date = 2001 | url = http://dx.doi.org/10.4314/jis.v21i1.39954 | ref = harv | postscript = .}}
* {{Cite journal | last = Jeenah | first = Na'eem | author-link = Na'eem Jeenah | title = The national liberation struggle and Islamic feminisms in South Africa | journal = [[Women's Studies International Forum]] | volume = 29 | issue = 1 | pages = 27–41 | publisher = [[Elsevier]] | doi = 10.1016/j.wsif.2005.10.004 | date = January–February 2006 | url = http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.wsif.2005.10.004 | ref = harv | postscript = .}}
*[http://www.milligazette.com/Archives/2004/16-31Jan04-Print-Edition/1631200425.htm "Islamic feminism means justice to women"] interview with Prof Margot Badran, ''The Milli Gazette'', January 16–31, 2004
*[http://www.islam101.com/women/jameelah.htm "Feminism and Islam"] analysis of Feminism from a traditional Islamic perspective, ''Maryam Jameelah'', July 13, 2005
*[http://www.islam-democracy.org/4th_Annual_Conference-Anwar_address.asp "Islamisation and its Impact on Democratic Governance and Women's Rights in Islam: A Feminist Perspective"] by Zainah Anwar, Center for the Study of Islam and Democracy, May 17, 2003
*[http://www.secularislam.org/rights/declaration.htm "A Declaration of the Rights of Women in Islamic Societies"], ''SecularIslam.com'', undated
*Foreign Affairs Committee of the National Council of Resistance of Iran. [http://www.iran-e-azad.org/english/book_on_women.html ''Women, Islam, and Equality''], an ebook
*Badran, Margot. ''"Feminists, Islam, and Nation: Gender and the Making of Modern Egypt''.
*Eleanor H. Perry ''Opening the Gates: A Century of Arab Feminist Writing'' (June 1, 1993) Article for Domes
* "[http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2005/11/04/AR2005110402306.html A Gender Jihad For Islam's Future]" by [[Asra Nomani]], in the ''[[Washington Post]]'', November 6, 2005
*Sutherland, Joan. [http://www.guardian.co.uk/women/story/0,,1746156,00.html "The ideas interview: Phyllis Chesler"], ''The Guardian'', April 4, 2006
*[http://www.diabolicdigest.net/Guest%20pens/Badra_en.htm More to life than window dressing] In this special feature, a successful Belgian-Algerian Muslim woman recounts what it was like growing up immersed in two cultures with divergent views of women. August 2006
*Ahmed, Leila. ''Women and Gender in Islam: Historical Roots of a modern Debate'', 1992, Yale University Press, ISBN 0-300-04942-0
*[http://www.iht.com/articles/2005/12/01/news/islam6.php Muslim women take charge of their faith]'', International Herald Tribune, December 4, 2005
*"Islamic feminism: what's in a name? Islamic feminism is on the whole more radical than Muslims' secular feminisms" by Margot Badran. ''Al-Ahram Weekly Online'', 17–23 January 2002, Issue No.569.
*''Windows of Faith: Muslim Women Scholar-Activists in North America,'' edited by Gisela Webb, 2000, Syracuse University Press, ISBN 0-8156-2852-8
*[http://en.qantara.de/The-Silent-Revolution/18942c19849i1p500/index.html Feminism in the Arab World: The Silent Revolution] ''Qantara.de''
*[http://en.qantara.de/Against-the-Politicisation-of-the-Koran/18950c19857i1p500/index.html Islamic Feminism and Reformist Islam: Against the Politicisation of the Koran] by Nimet Seker, ''Qantara.de''
* [http://www.jstor.org/discover/10.2307/25597322?uid=2&amp;uid=4&amp;sid=21104205002061 Alexander Safarian, On the History of Turkish Feminism, "Iran and the Caucasus", vol.11.1, Brill, Leiden - Boston, 2007, pp. 141-152.]
{{Spoken Wikipedia|Wikipedia_-_Islamic_feminism.ogg|2008-03-31}}

{{islam topics}}
{{feminism}}
{{Theology}}
{{Relpolnav}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Islamic Feminism}}
[[Category:Women's rights in religious movements]]
[[Category:Feminist theology]]
[[Category:Feminist theory]]
[[Category:Islam and women]]
[[Category:Islam-related controversies]]
[[Category:Islamic feminism| ]]
[[Category:Feminism and spirituality]]
[[Category:Multicultural feminism]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>