<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20221107045038|1120467803" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="2107559" pageid="2107559" ns="0" title="Islamic feminism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2022-11-10T13:45:54Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Feminist discourse and practice articulated within an Islamic paradigm}}
{{Feminism sidebar |Variants (religious)}}
{{Islam}}
'''Islamic feminism''' is a form of [[feminism]] concerned with the role of [[women in Islam]]. It aims for the full equality of all [[Muslims]], regardless of gender, in public and private life. Islamic feminists advocate [[women's rights]], [[gender equality]], and [[social justice]] grounded in an Islamic framework. Although rooted in [[Islam]], the movement's pioneers have also utilized [[Secularity|secular]], Western, or otherwise non-Muslim feminist discourses, and have recognized the role of Islamic feminism as part of an integrated global feminist movement.

Advocates of the movement seek to highlight the teachings of equality in the religion, and encourage a questioning of [[patriarchal]] interpretations of Islam by reinterpreting the [[Quran]] and [[hadith]].  

Prominent thinkers include [[Amina Wadud]], [[Leila Ahmed]], [[Fatema Mernissi]], [[Azizah Y. al-Hibri|Azizah al-Hibri]], [[Riffat Hassan]], [[Asma Lamrabet]], and [[Asma Barlas]].

==Definition and background==
===Islamic feminists===
{{Main|Hermeneutics of feminism in Islam}}
Since the mid-nineteenth century, Muslim women and men have been critical of restrictions placed on women regarding [[Female education|education]], [[Islam and gender segregation|seclusion]], [[Hijab|veiling]], [[polygyny]], [[Islamic views on slavery|slavery]], and [[Islamic views on concubinage|concubinage]]. Modern Muslims have questioned these practices and advocated for reform.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Women and Islam - Oxford Islamic Studies Online |url=http://www.oxfordislamicstudies.com/article/opr/t125/e2510 |access-date=2022-06-03 |website=www.oxfordislamicstudies.com |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; There is an ongoing debate about the status of women in Islam, with both conservatives and Islamic feminists using the Quran, the hadith, and prominent women in Muslim history as evidence for the discussion on women's rights, with feminists arguing that early Islam represented more egalitarian ideals, while conservatives argue that gender asymmetries are "divinely ordained".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Mojab |first=Shahrzad |date=2001-11-01 |title=Theorizing the Politics of 'Islamic Feminism' |journal=Feminist Review |language=en |volume=69 |issue=1 |pages=124–146 |doi=10.1080/01417780110070157 |issn=0141-7789 |s2cid=143067473}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Islamic feminists are Muslims who interpret the Quran and hadith in an egalitarian manner and advocate for women's rights and equality in the public and personal sphere. Islamic feminists critique patriarchal, sexist and misogynistic understandings of Islam.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |date=2017-12-01 |title=Margot Badran: What does Islamic feminism have to offer? Where does it come from? Where is it going? {{!}} Opinion {{!}} The Guardian |website=[[TheGuardian.com]] |url=https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/belief/2008/nov/09/islam-women |access-date=2022-06-03 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171201232847/https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/belief/2008/nov/09/islam-women |archive-date=2017-12-01 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Islamic feminists understand the Qur'an as advocating gender equality.&lt;ref name=":6"&gt;{{Cite web |last=Fawcett |first=Rachelle |title=The reality and future of Islamic feminism |url=https://www.aljazeera.com/opinions/2013/3/28/the-reality-and-future-of-islamic-feminism |access-date=2022-06-03 |website=www.aljazeera.com |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Islamic feminism is anchored within the [[discourse]] of Islam with the Quran as its central text.&lt;ref name="Exploring Islamic Feminism"&gt;
[http://www.wilsoncenter.org/index.cfm?topic_id=1426&amp;fuseaction=topics.event_summary&amp;event_id=42775 "Exploring Islamic Feminism"] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20050416072620/http://www.wilsoncenter.org/index.cfm?topic_id=1426&amp;fuseaction=topics.event_summary&amp;event_id=42775|date=2005-04-16}} by Margot Badran, Center for Muslim-Christian Understanding, Georgetown University, November 30, 2000
&lt;/ref&gt; The historian [[Margot Badran]] states that Islamic feminism "derives its understanding and mandate from the Qur’an, seeks rights and justice for women, and for men, in the totality of their existence."&lt;ref&gt;Badran, Margot. Feminism in Islam : Secular and Religious Convergences. Oxford : Oneworld, 2009., 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":6" /&gt; 

Islamic feminists differ from Islamists. [[Islamists]] are advocates of [[Political aspects of Islam|political Islam]], the notion that the Quran and [[hadith]] mandate an Islamic government. Some Islamists advocate women's rights in the [[public sphere]] but do not challenge [[gender inequality]] in the personal, [[private sphere]].&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web |title=ISLAMIC FEMINISM AND THE POLITICS OF NAMING |url=http://www.iran-bulletin.org/women/Islamic_feminism_IB.html |url-status=live |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150924040110/http://www.iran-bulletin.org/women/Islamic_feminism_IB.html |archive-date=2015-09-24 |access-date=9 December 2015 |work=iran-bulletin.org}}
&lt;/ref&gt; [[Su'ad al-Fatih al-Badawi]], a Sudanese academic and Islamist politician, has argued that feminism is incompatible with ''[[taqwa]]'' (the Islamic conception of piety), and thus Islam and feminism are mutually exclusive.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Hale |first=Sondra |title=Women and Globalization in the Arab Middle East: Gender, Economy, and Society |date=2013 |publisher=Lynne Rienner |isbn=978-1588261342 |editor1-last=Doumato |editor1-first=Eleanor |pages=208 |chapter=Sudanese Women in National Service, Militias &amp; the Home |editor2-last=Posusney |editor2-first=Marsha |chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=xq0WKr_yFCYC}}&lt;/ref&gt; Badran argues that Islam and feminism are not mutually exclusive.&lt;ref name=":5"&gt;
{{Cite web |title=Independent Lens . SHADYA . Muslim Feminism {{!}} PBS |url=http://www.pbs.org/independentlens/shadya/muslimfeminism.html |url-status=live |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180622133343/http://www.pbs.org/independentlens/shadya/muslimfeminism.html |archive-date=2018-06-22 |access-date=2018-10-27 |website=www.pbs.org}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

Islamic feminists have differed in their understandings and definitions of Islamic feminism. Islamic scholar [[Asma Barlas]] shares Badran's views, discussing the difference between secular feminists and Islamic feminism and in countries where Muslims make up 98% of the population, it is not possible to avoid engaging “its basic beliefs.”&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/belief/2008/nov/09/islam-women|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20171201232847/https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/belief/2008/nov/09/islam-women|url-status=dead|title=Margot Badran: What does Islamic feminism have to offer? Where does it come from? Where is it going?|date=November 9, 2008|archivedate=December 1, 2017|website=the Guardian}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Elizabeth Segran]] states that just talking about human rights mentioned in the [[Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination Against Women]] (CEDAW) does not create immediate resonance with ordinary Muslim women; since Islam is the source of their values, integrating human rights frameworks with Islam makes sense.&lt;ref name=":4"&gt;
{{cite journal |last=Segran |first=Elizabeth |date=2013-12-04 |title=The Rise of the Islamic Feminists |url=https://www.thenation.com/article/rise-islamic-feminists/ |url-status=live |journal=The Nation |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170520091837/https://www.thenation.com/article/rise-islamic-feminists/ |archive-date=2017-05-20 |access-date=2017-05-20 |via=www.thenation.com}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

South African Muslim scholar [[Fatima Seedat]] agrees with both Barlas and Badran about the importance of feminism in the Islamic world. However, she debates the term “Islamic Feminism” is unnecessary since feminism is a “social practice, not merely of personal identity.”&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Seedat | first1 = Fatima | year = 2016 | title = Beyond the Text: Between Islam and Feminism | journal = Journal of Feminist Studies in Religion | volume = 32 | issue = 2| page = 138 | doi = 10.2979/jfemistudreli.32.2.23 | s2cid = 151549625 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Seedat believes the convergence of both Islamic and feminism creates more conflict and opens more doors for “Islamists” to interpret or misinterpret the Qur'an to suit their political needs. She believes it is important to speak about and illustrate how feminism has existed in the lines of the Qur'an. By separating the two and giving their own space, it will be more inclusive to everyone (men, women, Muslims and non-Muslims). In the same article, “Feminism, and Islamic Feminism: Between Inadequacy and Inevitability,” Seedat explains that the existence of such a term separates Muslims and isolates them from the rest of the world and the universal feminist movement. She states in her essay the importance of sharing with the rest of the world what Islam has to offer feminism, and to show the true image of Islam by not referring to themselves as Islamic feminists.

Some Muslim women writers and activists have eschewed identifying themselves as Islamic feminists out of a belief Western feminism is exclusionary to Muslim women and women of color more generally.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Hidayatollah |first=Aysha |title=Feminist Edges of the Qur'an |publisher=Oxford University Press |year=2014 |pages=12 |language=English}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Azizah Y. al-Hibri|Azizah al-Hibri]], a Lebanese-American Muslim scholar, has identified herself as a "womanist".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Floyd-Thomas |first=Stacey M. |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=0_k98AmJWAQC&amp;dq=azizah+al+hibri+womanism&amp;pg=PA47 |title=Deeper Shades of Purple: Womanism in Religion and Society |date= August 2006|publisher=NYU Press |isbn=978-0-8147-2753-9 |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Context in the Quran ===
Islamic feminists understand the Quran as advocating gender equality.&lt;ref name=":6" /&gt; In the view of feminist legal scholar Azizah al-Hibri, the Quran teaches all human beings are creations of God from one soul, who were divided into nations and tribes to know each other, and the most honored individuals are those who are the most pious. Therefore, al-Hibri writes that the Quran recognizes differences between human beings while asserting their natural equality and no man is recognized as superior by his gender alone.&lt;ref&gt;Al-Hibri, Azizah. "An Introduction to Muslim Women's Rights" in ''Windows of Faith: Muslim Women Scholar-Activists in North America,'' edited by Gisela Webb. Syracuse University Press. pp.&amp;nbsp;52–53. [[ISBN (identifier)|ISBN]]&amp;nbsp;[[Special:BookSources/0815628528|&lt;bdi&gt;0815628528&lt;/bdi&gt;]].&lt;/ref&gt;

===Early Muslims and modern Islamic Feminists===
Modern Muslim feminists and progressive Muslims have taken early figures in Islamic history as role models including [[Khadija bint Khuwaylid|Khadijah]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=The Original Feminist Jihadist - Ms. Magazine |url=https://msmagazine.com/2010/03/16/islams-first-feminist/ |access-date=2022-06-03 |website=msmagazine.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Aisha]], [[Hafsa bint Umar|Hafsa]], [[Umm Salama]], [[Fatimah|Fatima]], and [[Zaynab bint Ali]]. [[Zainab Alwani]] cites Aisha as an empowered and intelligent woman who repeatedly confronted the misogyny of other [[Companions of the Prophet|sahaba]].&lt;ref&gt;Alwani, Zainab. "Muslim Women as Religious Scholars: A Historical Survey," in ''Muslima Theology: The Voices of Muslim Women Theologians'', edited by Ednan Aslan, Marcia Hermansen, and Elif Medini, Peter Lang, Frankfurt, 2013, pp. 45-58.&lt;/ref&gt; Moroccan feminist Asma Lamrabet has also argued Aisha was an empowered female intellectual against what Lamrabet sees as a misogynistic intellectual history.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Aisha, épouse du prophète où l'islam au féminin |url=http://www.asma-lamrabet.com/articles/aisha-epouse-du-prophete-ou-l-islam-au-feminin/ |access-date=2022-06-11 |website=www.asma-lamrabet.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; Lamrabet has also praised Umm Salama as a feminist figure.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=When the Qur'an responds to women claims… |url=http://www.asma-lamrabet.com/articles/when-the-qur-an-responds-to-women-claims/ |access-date=2022-06-11 |website=www.asma-lamrabet.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Iranian revolutionary thinker [[Ali Shariati]] wrote [[Fatemeh Is Fatemeh|Fatemeh is Fatemeh]], a biography of Muhammad's daughter Fatima, that holds her as a role model for women.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Dr. Ali Shariati: Fatima is Fatima |url=https://www.iranchamber.com/personalities/ashariati/works/fatima_is_fatima1.php |access-date=2022-06-10 |website=www.iranchamber.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Ednan Aslan]] suggests Fatima is an example of female empowerment in early Islam, as she was not afraid to oppose [[Abu Bakr]] and demand her inheritance.&lt;ref&gt;Aslan, Ednan. "Early Community Politics and the Marginalization of Women in Islamic Intellectual History ," in ''Muslima Theology: The Voices of Muslim Women Theologians'', edited by Ednan Aslan, Marcia Hermansen, and Elif Medini, Peter Lang, Frankfurt, 2013, pp. 36-37.&lt;/ref&gt;

Some Muslim feminists have asserted [[Muhammad]] himself was a feminist.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |date=2016-10-28 |title=Muhammad Was A Feminist |url=https://www.huffpost.com/entry/muhammad-was-a-feminist_b_12638112 |access-date=2022-06-03 |website=HuffPost |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
In the past 150 years or so, many scholarly interpretations have developed from within the Islamic tradition itself that seek to redress social wrongs perpetrated against [[Women in Islam|Muslim women]].&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt; For example, new Islamic jurisprudence is emerging that seeks to forbid practices like [[female genital mutilation]], equalize family law, support women as clergy and in administrative positions in mosques, and supports equal opportunities for Muslim women to become judges in civil as well as religious institutions.&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt; Modern feminist Islamic scholars perceive their work as restoration of rights provided by God and the Prophet but denied by society.&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt; 

===Nineteenth century===
The modern movement of Islamic feminism began in the nineteenth century.

[[Aisha Taymur#:~:text%3DAisha%20Taymur%2C-From%20Wikipedia%2C%20the|Aisha Taymur]] (1840 - 1902) was a prominent writer and early activist for women's rights in Egypt. Taymur's writings criticized male domination over women and celebrated women's intellect and courage.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title='A'isha Taymur – Accessing Muslim Lives |url=https://accessingmuslimlives.org/profile/aisha-taymur/ |access-date=2022-06-02 |language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Another early Muslim feminist activist and writer was [[Zaynab Fawwaz]] (1860 - 1914). Fawwaz argued for women's social and intellectual quality with men and wrote a book of biographies of famous women.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Booth |first=Marilyn |date=1995 |title=Exemplary Lives, Feminist Aspirations: Zaynab Fawwāz and the Arabic Biographical Tradition |url=https://www.jstor.org/stable/4183369 |journal=Journal of Arabic Literature |volume=26 |issue=1/2 |pages=120–146 |doi=10.1163/157006495X00120 |jstor=4183369 |issn=0085-2376}}&lt;/ref&gt;

An early feminist activist in the [[Bengal|Bengal region]] was Rokeya Sakhawat Hossain, known as [[Begum Rokeya]] (1880 - 1932). Hossain was an activist for women's education and writer. She criticized patriarchy in South Asian societies and the practice of [[purdah]], the veiling and segregation of women.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=Nasir |first=Amna |date= |title=Begum Rokeya: The Writer Who Introduced Us To Feminist Sci-Fi {{!}} #IndianWomenInHistory |url=https://feminisminindia.com/2017/07/06/begum-rokeya-essay/ |url-status=live |website=Feminism in India}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Egyptian jurist [[Qasim Amin]], the author of the 1899 pioneering book ''Women's Liberation'' (''Tahrir al-Mar'a''), is often described as the father of the [[Feminism in Egypt|Egyptian feminist movement]]. In his work, Amin criticized some of the practices prevalent in his society at the time, such as [[Polygyny in Islam|polygyny]], [[Islam and clothing|the veil]], and ''[[purdah]]'', i.e. [[sex segregation in Islam]]. He condemned them as un-Islamic and contradictory to the true spirit of Islam. His work had an enormous influence on women's political movements throughout the Islamic and [[Arab world]], and is read and cited today.{{Citation needed|date=June 2022}}

Despite Qasim Amin's effects on modern-day Islamic feminist movements, present-day scholar [[Leila Ahmed]] considers his works both [[androcentric]] and [[colonialist]].&lt;ref&gt;Leila Ahmed. Women and Gender in Islam. New Haven and London: Yale University Press, 1992. pp.155-163, 171, 179.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Muhammad Abduh|Muhammad 'Abdu]], an Egyptian nationalist&lt;ref&gt;Leila Ahmed. Women and Gender in Islam. New Haven and London: Yale University Press, 1992. pp.136-137.&lt;/ref&gt; and proponent of [[Islamic modernism]], could easily have written the chapters of his work that show honest considerations of the negative effects of the veil on women.&lt;ref&gt;Leila Ahmed. Women and Gender in Islam. New Haven and London: Yale University Press, 1992. pp.159,161.&lt;/ref&gt; Amin even posed many male-centered misconceptions about women, such as their inability to experience love, that women needlessly talk about their husbands outside their presence, and that Muslim marriage is based on ignorance and sensuality, of which women were the chief source.&lt;ref&gt;Leila Ahmed. Women and Gender in Islam. New Haven and London: Yale University Press, 1992. pp.157-159.&lt;/ref&gt;

Lesser known, however, are the women who preceded Amin in their feminist critique of their societies. The women's press in Egypt started voicing such concerns since its very first issues in 1892. Egyptian, Turkish, Iranian, Syrian and Lebanese women and men had been reading European feminist magazines even a decade earlier, and discussed their relevance to the Middle East in the general press.&lt;ref&gt;
see "Great Ancestors: Women Asserting Rights in Muslim Contexts", by Farida Shaheed with Aisha L.F. Shaheed (London/Lahore: WLUML/Shirkat Gah, 2005) [http://www.wluml.org/english/pubsfulltxt.shtml?%5B87%5D=i-87-186208]{{Dead link|date=February 2019|bot=InternetArchiveBot|fix-attempted=yes}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

===Twentieth century===
[[Aisha Abd al-Rahman]], writing under her pen name ''Bint al-Shati'' ("Daughter of the Riverbank"), was one of the first to undertake Quranic [[exegesis]], and though she did not consider herself to be a feminist, her works reflect feminist themes. She began producing her popular books in 1959, the same year that [[Naguib Mahfouz]] published his allegorical and feminist version of the life of Muhammad.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|first=Ruth|last=Roded|title=Bint al-Shati's Wives of the Prophet: Feminist or Feminine?|journal=British Journal of Middle Eastern Studies|date=May 2006|volume=33|issue=1|pages=51–66|doi=10.1080/13530190600603915|s2cid=159905564}}&lt;/ref&gt; She wrote biographies of early [[women in Islam]], including the [[Aminah bint Wahb|mother]], wives and [[Family tree of Muhammad|daughters]] of the [[Prophets of Islam|Prophet]] Muhammad, as well as [[literary criticism]].&lt;ref name="zeidan"&gt;Arab Women Novelists: The Formative Years and Beyond by Joseph T. Zeidan, State University of New York Press, 1995&lt;/ref&gt; 

Moroccan writer and sociologist, [[Fatema Mernissi]] was a prominent Muslim feminist thinker. Her book ''Beyond the Veil'' explores the oppression of women in Islamic societies and sexual ideology and gender identity through the perspective of Moroccan society and culture.&lt;ref name="autogenerated1"&gt;{{Cite web |last=Rassam |first=Amal |title=Mernissi, Fatima |url=http://www.oxfordislamicstudies.com/article/opr/t236/e0527 |url-status=live |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190108020056/http://www.oxfordislamicstudies.com/article/opr/t236/e0527 |archive-date=January 8, 2019 |access-date=October 24, 2019 |website=Oxford Islamic Studies}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Fatema Mernissi|Mernissi]] argued in her book ''The Veil and the Male Elite'' that the suppression of women's rights in Islamic societies is the result of political motivation and its consequent manipulative interpretation of hadith, which runs counter to the egalitarian Islamic community of men and women envisioned by Muhammad.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Mernissi |first=Fatima |url=https://archive.org/details/veilmaleelite00mern |title=The Veil and the Male Elite: A Feminist Interpretation of Islam |publisher=New York: Basic Books |year=1992 |isbn=978-0201-63221-7 |author-link=Fatima Mernissi}}&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Fatema Mernissi|Mernissi]] argued that the ideal Muslim woman being "silent and obedient" has nothing to do with the message of Islam. In her view, conservative Muslim men manipulated the Quran to preserve their patriarchal system in order to prevent women from sexual liberation; thus enforcing justification of strict veiling and limiting their rights.&lt;ref name="autogenerated1" /&gt;

A later 20th-century Islamic feminist is [[amina wadud]]. Wadud was born into an African-American family and converted to Islam. In 1992, wadud published ''Quran and Woman'', a work that critiqued patriarchal interpretations of the Quran.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Without Women, You Cannot Understand the Qur'an |url=http://www.oasiscenter.eu/en/without-women-you-cannot-understand-the-quran |access-date=2022-06-03 |website=Fondazione Internazionale Oasis}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Some strains of modern Islamic feminism have opted to expunge hadith from their ideology altogether in favor of a movement focusing only on Qur'anic principles. [[Riffat Hassan]] has advocated one such movement, articulating a theology wherein what are deemed to be universal rights for humanity outlined in the Qur'an are prioritized over contextual laws and regulations.&lt;ref&gt;Hassan, Riffat. "Women's Rights inIslam: Normative Teaching versus Practice," in ''Islam and Human Rights: Advancing a U.S.- Muslim Dialogue'', edited by Shireen T. Hunter with Huma Malik, The CSIS Press, Washington D.C., 2005, pp. 43-66.&lt;/ref&gt; She has additionally claimed that the Qur'an, taken alone as scripture, does not present females either as a creation preceded by the male or as the instigator of the "[[Original sin|Fall of Man]]".&lt;ref&gt;Hassan, Riffat. "Woman and Man's "fall": A Qur'anic Theological Perspective," in ''Muslima Theology: The Voices of Muslim Women Theologians'', edited by Ednan Aslan, Marcia Hermansen, and Elif Medini, Peter Lang, Frankfurt, 2013, pp. 101-113.&lt;/ref&gt; This theological movement has been met with criticism from other Muslim feminists such as Kecia Ali, who has criticized its selective nature for ignoring elements within the Muslim tradition that could prove helpful in establishing more egalitarian norms in Islamic society.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Sexual Ethics &amp; Islam|last = Ali|first = Kecia|publisher = Oneworld|year = 2006|isbn = 978-1-85168-456-4|location = London|pages = 154–155}}&lt;/ref&gt;
===Twenty-first century===
Islamic feminist scholarship and activism has continued into the 21st century.

In 2015, a group of Muslim activists, politicians, and writers issued a Declaration of Reform which, among other things, supports women's rights and states in part, "We support equal rights for women, including equal rights to inheritance, witness, work, mobility, personal law, education, and employment. Men and women have equal rights in mosques, boards, leadership and all spheres of society. We reject [[sexism]] and [[misogyny]]."&lt;ref name="secularism1"&gt;
{{cite web|url=http://www.secularism.org.uk/news/2015/12/muslim-reform-movement-embraces-secularism-and-universal-human-rights|title=National Secular Society|access-date=9 December 2015|date=2015-12-08|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20151212175308/http://www.secularism.org.uk/news/2015/12/muslim-reform-movement-embraces-secularism-and-universal-human-rights|archive-date=2015-12-12|url-status=live}}
&lt;/ref&gt; The Declaration also announced the founding of the [[Muslim Reform Movement]] organization to work against the beliefs of Middle Eastern terror groups.&lt;ref name="washingtontimes.com"&gt;
{{cite web|url=http://www.washingtontimes.com/news/2015/dec/6/muslim-reform-movement-decries-radical-islam-calls/?page=all|title=Muslim Reform Movement decries radical Islam, calls for equality|work=The Washington Times|access-date=9 December 2015|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20151209080633/http://www.washingtontimes.com/news/2015/dec/6/muslim-reform-movement-decries-radical-islam-calls/?page=all|archive-date=2015-12-09|url-status=live}}
&lt;/ref&gt; [[Asra Nomani]] and others placed the Declaration on the door of the [[Islamic Center of Washington]].&lt;ref name="washingtontimes.com" /&gt;

Feminism in the Middle East is over a century old, and having been impacted directly by the war on terror in Afghanistan, continues to grow and fight for women's rights and equality in all conversations of power and everyday life.&lt;ref&gt;
{{Cite journal|last=Badran|first=Margot|date=2011-01-26|title=Between Secular and Islamic Feminism/s: Reflections on the Middle East and Beyond|url=https://muse.jhu.edu/article/408727/summary|journal=Journal of Middle East Women's Studies|volume=1|issue=1|pages=6–28|issn=1558-9579|access-date=2016-10-10|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20161011060321/https://muse.jhu.edu/article/408727/summary|archive-date=2016-10-11|url-status=live}}
&lt;/ref&gt; 

Muslim feminist writers today include [[Aysha Hidayatullah|Aysha Hidayatollah]], [[Kecia Ali]], [[Asma Lamrabet]], [[Olfa Youssef|Olfa Yousef]], and [[Mohja Kahf]]. 

== Muslim feminist groups and initiatives ==

=== Revolutionary Association of the Women of Afghanistan ===
{{Main|Revolutionary Association of the Women of Afghanistan|Meena Keshwar Kamal}}
[[File:Meena founder of RAWA speaking in 1982.jpg|thumb|[[Meena Keshwar Kamal]] (1956 - 1987), founder of RAWA]]
The [[Revolutionary Association of the Women of Afghanistan]] (RAWA) is a women's organization based in [[Quetta]], Pakistan, that promotes women's rights and [[secular democracy]]. The organization aims to involve [[women in Afghanistan|women of Afghanistan]] in both political and social activities aimed at acquiring their [[human rights]] and continuing the struggle against the [[government of Afghanistan]] based on democratic and secular - not fundamentalist - principles, in which women can participate fully.&lt;ref name="Lantos"&gt;{{cite web |date=December 18, 2001 |title=RAWA testimony to the Congressional Human Rights Caucus Briefing |url=http://lantos.house.gov/HoR/CA12/Human+Rights+Caucus/Briefing+Testimonies/Fahima+Vorgetts.htm |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070628022728/http://lantos.house.gov/HoR/CA12/Human+Rights+Caucus/Briefing+Testimonies/Fahima+Vorgetts.htm |archive-date=June 28, 2007 |publisher=U.S. Congressional Human Rights Caucus}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The organization was founded in 1977 by a group of intellectuals led by [[Meena Keshwar Kamal|Meena]] (she did not use a last name). They founded the organization to promote equality and education for women; it continues to "give voice to the deprived and silenced women of Afghanistan". Before 1978, RAWA focused mainly on women's rights and democracy, but after the coup of 1978, directed by Moscow, and the 1979 Soviet Occupation of Afghanistan, "Rawa became directly involved in the war of resistance, advocating democracy and secularism from the outset".&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;Mehta, Sunita. ''Women for Afghan Women: Shattering Myths and Claiming the Future''. New York: Palgrave Macmillan, 2002. Print.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1979 RAWA campaigned against the [[Democratic Republic of Afghanistan]], and organized meetings in schools to mobilize support against it, and in 1981, launched a bilingual [[List of feminist art magazines|feminist magazine]], ''[[Payam-e-Zan]]'' (Women's Message).&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Chavis2011"&gt;{{cite book |author=Melody Ermachild Chavis |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=RyJEynFyznkC&amp;pg=PT1 |title=Meena: Heroine Of Afghanistan |date=30 September 2011 |publisher=Transworld |isbn=978-1-4464-8846-1 |pages=1– |access-date=30 March 2016 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160429164329/https://books.google.com/books?id=RyJEynFyznkC&amp;pg=PT1 |archive-date=29 April 2016 |url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Gioseffi2003"&gt;{{cite book |last=Gioseffi |first=Daniela |url=https://archive.org/details/womenonwarintern00gios |title=Women on War: An International Anthology of Women's Writings from Antiquity to the Present |publisher=Feminist Press at CUNY |year=2003 |isbn=978-1-55861-409-3 |page=[https://archive.org/details/womenonwarintern00gios/page/283 283] |author-link=Daniela Gioseffi |access-date=2016-03-30 |url-access=registration}}&lt;/ref&gt; RAWA also founded Watan Schools to aid [[Afghan refugees|refugee children and their mothers]], offering both hospitalization and the teaching of practical skills.&lt;ref name="Gioseffi2003" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://laconneau.com/NewsletterNovember2009.html|title=Brave Women in a War-Torn World: RAWA and Afghanistan}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Sisters in Islam ===
[[File:Zainah Anwar 7 September 2016.jpg|thumb|right|[[Zainah Anwar]]]]
[[Sisters in Islam]] (SIS) is a Malaysian civil society organization committed to promoting the rights of women within the frameworks of Islam and universal human rights. SIS work focuses on challenging laws and policies made in the name of Islam that discriminate against women. As such it tackles issues covered under Malaysia's Islamic family and [[Syariah Court|syariah]] laws, such as polygamy,&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web |date=21 May 2010 |title=Polygamy not a God-given right to Muslims |url=http://www.malaysiakini.com/news/132369 |url-status=live |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170413195426/http://www.malaysiakini.com/news/132369 |archive-date=2017-04-13 |access-date=2017-04-22}}
&lt;/ref&gt; child marriage,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Syariah court fails to protect and safeguard Muslim girls — Sisters in Islam |url=http://www.themalaysianinsider.com/sideviews/article/syariah-court-fails-to-protect-and-safeguard-muslim-girls-sisters-in-islam |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140714201933/http://www.themalaysianinsider.com/sideviews/article/syariah-court-fails-to-protect-and-safeguard-muslim-girls-sisters-in-islam |archive-date=2014-07-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; moral policing,&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web |title=Archives |url=http://www.thestar.com.my/story.aspx/?file=%2f2006%2f12%2f17%2fnation%2f16348692&amp;sec=nation |url-status=live |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140714180102/http://www.thestar.com.my/story.aspx/?file=%2f2006%2f12%2f17%2fnation%2f16348692&amp;sec=nation |archive-date=2014-07-14 |access-date=2017-04-22}}
&lt;/ref&gt; Islamic legal theory and jurisprudence, the hijab and modesty,&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web |title=Sisters In Islam: News / Comments / Dress and Modesty in Islam |url=http://www.sistersinislam.org.my/comment.php?comment.news.309 |url-status=live |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130823113231/http://www.sistersinislam.org.my/comment.php?comment.news.309 |archive-date=2013-08-23 |access-date=2017-04-22}}
&lt;/ref&gt; violence against women and [[hudud]].&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web |title=Sisters In Islam: Sisters in Islam remains firmly opposed to the implementation of Hudud law for Malaysia |url=http://www.sistersinislam.org.my/news.php?item.903.121 |url-status=live |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170920045148/http://www.sistersinislam.org.my/news.php?item.903.121 |archive-date=2017-09-20 |access-date=2017-04-22}}
&lt;/ref&gt; Their mission is to promote the principles of gender equality, justice, freedom, and dignity of Islam and empower women to be advocates for change.&lt;ref name="ReferenceA"&gt;
{{Cite web |title=Sisters In Islam: Mission Statement and Objectives |url=http://www.sistersinislam.org.my/page.php?36 |url-status=live |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20151117025724/http://www.sistersinislam.org.my/page.php?36 |archive-date=2015-11-17 |access-date=2015-11-16 |website=www.sistersinislam.org.my}}
&lt;/ref&gt; They seek to promote a framework of women's rights in Islam which take into consideration women's experiences and realities; they want to eliminate the injustice and discrimination that women may face by changing mindsets that may hold women to be inferior to men; and they want to increase the public knowledge and reform laws and policies within the framework of justice and equality in Islam.&lt;ref name="ReferenceA" /&gt; Prominent members are [[Zainah Anwar]]&lt;ref name="SIS"&gt;
{{cite magazine |last=Power |first=Carla |author-link=Carla Power |date=17 February 2009 |title=Muslim Women Demand End to Oppressive Laws |url=http://www.time.com/time/world/article/0,8599,1879864,00.html |url-status=dead |magazine=Time |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130826152136/http://www.time.com/time/world/article/0,8599,1879864,00.html |archive-date=2013-08-26 |access-date=2017-04-22 |via=www.time.com}}
&lt;/ref&gt; and co-founder [[Amina Wadud|amina wadud]].&lt;ref name="sistersinislam.org.my"&gt;
[http://www.sistersinislam.org.my/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=916&amp;Itemid=312 New Straits Times - The day I met Amina Wadud] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170911162138/http://www.sistersinislam.org.my/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=916&amp;Itemid=312|date=2017-09-11}} By Siti Nurbaiyah Nadzmi
&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Musawah ===
In 2009, twelve women from the Arab world formed the global movement [[Musawah]], whose name means "equality" in Arabic. Musawah advocates for feminist interpretations of Islamic texts and calls on nations to abide by international human rights standards such as those promulgated in the [[Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination Against Women]]. Musawah's approach is modeled after that of Sisters in Islam. Secular feminists have criticized Musawah, arguing that Islam is shaky ground on which to build a feminist movement, given that interpretation of Islamic sources is subjective.&lt;ref name=":4" /&gt;

=== Sister-hood ===
[[Sister-hood]] is an international platform for the voices of women of Muslim heritage founded in 2007 by Norwegian film-maker and human rights activist [[Deeyah Khan]] through her media and arts production company [[Fuuse]].&lt;ref&gt;
{{Cite web |author=Victoria Craw |date=6 June 2016 |title=Emmy-award winning filmmaker Deeyah Khan launches online magazine Sister-hood aimed at giving Muslim women a voice |url=http://www.news.com.au/lifestyle/real-life/news-life/emmyaward-winning-filmmaker-deeyah-khan-launches-online-magazine-sisterhood-aimed-at-giving-muslim-women-a-voice/news-story/f61efcf5b0650060e3f54cc17f5c291b |url-status=live |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160606123922/http://www.news.com.au/lifestyle/real-life/news-life/emmyaward-winning-filmmaker-deeyah-khan-launches-online-magazine-sisterhood-aimed-at-giving-muslim-women-a-voice/news-story/f61efcf5b0650060e3f54cc17f5c291b |archive-date=2016-06-06 |access-date=6 June 2016 |publisher=www.news.com.au}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

Sister-hood was relaunched in 2016 as a global online magazine and live events platform promoting the voices of women of Muslim heritage.
Sister-hood magazine ambassadors include [[Farida Shaheed]] from Pakistan, Egyptian [[Mona Eltahawy]], Palestinian [[Rula Jebreal]], [[Leyla Hussein]] of Somali heritage and Algerian [[Marieme Helie Lucas]].

=== Women Living Under Muslim Laws (WLUML) ===

[[Women Living Under Muslim Laws]] is an international solidarity network established in 1984 that advocates for both Muslim and non-Muslim women who live in states governed by Islamic law. The group does research on Islamic law and women and advocacy work.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Shaheed |first=Farida |date=1994 |title=Controlled or Autonomous: Identity and the Experience of the Network, Women Living under Muslim Laws |url=https://www.jstor.org/stable/3175010 |journal=Signs |volume=19 |issue=4 |pages=997–1019 |doi=10.1086/494948 |jstor=3175010 |s2cid=144483762 |issn=0097-9740}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Muslim Women's Quest for Equality ===
Muslim Women's Quest for Equality is an Indian activist group that petitioned the [[Supreme Court of India]] against the practices of ''[[w:Divorce in Islam|talaq-e-bidat]]'' (triple talaq), ''[[nikah halala]]'' and [[Polygyny in Islam|polygyny]] under the Muslim personal laws as being illegal and [[Constitution of India|unconstitutional]]&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web |date=2016-09-06 |title=Muslim women's group demands complete ban on Shariah courts &amp;#124; india-news |url=http://www.hindustantimes.com/india-news/muslim-women-s-group-demands-complete-ban-on-shariah-courts/story-kgNMV7LwDSgEaMRAOIecfI.html |url-status=live |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160906210001/http://www.hindustantimes.com/india-news/muslim-women-s-group-demands-complete-ban-on-shariah-courts/story-kgNMV7LwDSgEaMRAOIecfI.html |archive-date=2016-09-06 |access-date=2016-09-07 |publisher=Hindustan Times}}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite news |last1=Rajagopal |first1=Krishnadas |date=2016-08-26 |title=SC admits Muslim woman's plea to declare triple talaq illegal |newspaper=The Hindu |url=http://www.thehindu.com/news/sc-admits-muslim-womans-plea-to-declare-triple-talaq-illegal/article9036511.ece |url-status=live |access-date=2016-09-07 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160826123403/http://www.thehindu.com/news/sc-admits-muslim-womans-plea-to-declare-triple-talaq-illegal/article9036511.ece |archive-date=2016-08-26}}
&lt;/ref&gt; in September 2016.

=== Ni Putes Ni Soumises ===

[[Ni Putes Ni Soumises]], whose name translates to Neither Whores nor Submissives, is a French feminist organization founded by [[Samira Bellil]] and other young women of African backgrounds, to address the sexual and physical violence that women in Muslim majority neighborhoods in France faced.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=George |first=Rose |date=2004-09-13 |title=Obituary: Samira Bellil |url=http://www.theguardian.com/news/2004/sep/13/guardianobituaries.france |access-date=2022-06-06 |website=the Guardian |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
== International conferences on Islamic feminism ==
Few international conferences on Islamic feminism have taken place. One international congress on Islamic feminism was held in Barcelona, Spain in 2008.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|date=2008-10-27|title=Fighting for Muslim women's rights|language=en-GB|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/in_depth/7689897.stm|access-date=2020-05-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Musawah]] ('equality'; in [[Arabic]]: {{lang|ar|مساواة}}) is a global [[Social movement|movement]] for equality and justice in the Muslim family, led by [[feminists]] since 2009, "seeking to reclaim [[Islam]] and the [[Koran]] for themselves".&lt;ref name="Nation"&gt;{{cite news|author=Segran, Elizabeth|date=4 December 2013|title=The Rise of the Islamic Feminists|agency=The Nation thenation.com|url=http://www.thenation.com/article/rise-islamic-feminists/|access-date=7 June 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Musawah movement operates on the principle that patriarchy within Muslim countries is a result of the way male interpreters have read Islamic texts,&lt;ref name="Nation" /&gt; and that feminists can progressively interpret the [[Quran]] to achieve the goal of [[Universal Declaration of Human Rights|international human rights standards]].&lt;ref name="Nation" /&gt; The first female Muslim [[Ulama|'ulema]] congress was held in Indonesia in 2017.&lt;ref name=":2"&gt;{{Cite web|title=EDITORIAL: Women ulema for the world|url=https://www.thejakartapost.com/academia/2017/04/28/editorial-women-ulema-for-the-world.html|access-date=2020-05-31|website=The Jakarta Post|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; The women ulema congress issued a [[fatwa]] to lift the minimum age for girls to marry to 18.&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt; Malaysian feminist [[Zainah Anwar]] informed the congress that women have an equal right to define Islam and that women need to fight against male domination in Quranic interpretations.&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt; During the congress, [[Nur Rofiah]], a professor in Quranic studies, stated that, Islam asks every human being to elevate the status of humankind, and polygamy does not, and that polygamy is not the teaching of Islam&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt;

==Areas of campaign==

===Women in politics ===

[[Muslim majority countries]] have produced several female heads of state, prime ministers, and state secretaries such as [[Lala Shovkat]] of [[Islam in Azerbaijan|Azerbaijan]], [[Benazir Bhutto]] of [[Islam in Pakistan|Pakistan]], [[Mame Madior Boye]] of [[Islam in Senegal|Senegal]], [[Tansu Çiller]] of [[Islam in Turkey|Turkey]], [[Kaqusha Jashari]] of [[Kosovo]], and [[Megawati Sukarnoputri]] of [[Islam in Indonesia|Indonesia]]. In [[Bangladesh]], [[Khaleda Zia]] was elected the country's first female prime minister in 1991, and served as prime minister until 2009, when she was replaced by [[Sheikh Hasina]], who maintains the prime minister's office at present making [[Bangladesh]] the country with the longest continuous female premiership.&lt;ref name="The Economist"&gt;"Prime Minister of Bangladesh - PM Office Email Address." ''MediaBangladeshnet about Bangladesh Print Electronic Internet More''. N.p., 15 Nov. 2015. Web. 1 Oct. 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Personal law===
{{See also|Islamic marital jurisprudence}}

[[File:Manal al-Sharif (منال الشريف) - Oslo Freedom Forum 2012 (1).jpg|thumb|Manal al-Sharif speaking at the Oslo Freedom Forum in 2012 about the #Women2Drive campaign she co-founded.]]
One of such controversial interpretations involve passages in the Quran that discuss the idea of a man's religious obligation to support women.&lt;ref name=":02"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Fluehr-Lobban |first1=Carolyn |title=Toward a Theory of Arab-Muslim Women as Activists in Secular and Religious Movements |journal=Arab Studies Quarterly |date=1993 |volume=15 |issue=2 |pages=87–106 |jstor=41858975}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some scholars, such as anthropologist [[Carolyn Fluehr-Lobban]] in her work on Arab-Muslim women activists' engagement in secular religious movements, argue that this assertion of a religious obligation "has traditionally been used as a rationale for the social practice of male authority."&lt;ref name=":02" /&gt; In some countries the legislative and administrative application of male authority is used to justify denying women access to the public sphere through the "denial of permission to travel or work outside the home, or even drive a car."&lt;ref name=":02" /&gt; On Sept. 26, 2017 [[Saudi Arabia]] announced it would end its longstanding policy banning women from driving in June 2018.&lt;ref&gt;
{{Cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2017/09/26/world/middleeast/saudi-arabia-women-drive.html|title=Saudi Arabia Agrees to Let Women Drive|last=Hubbard|first=Ben|date=2017-09-26|work=The New York Times|access-date=2018-03-01|language=en-US|issn=0362-4331|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180228041921/https://www.nytimes.com/2017/09/26/world/middleeast/saudi-arabia-women-drive.html|archive-date=2018-02-28|url-status=live}}
&lt;/ref&gt; Various female activists had protested the ban, among them Saudi women's rights activists [[Manal al-Sharif]],&lt;ref&gt;
{{Citation|last=al-Sharif|first=Manal|title=A Saudi woman who dared to drive|date=14 June 2013 |url=https://www.ted.com/talks/manal_al_sharif_a_saudi_woman_who_dared_to_drive/transcript#t-21085|language=en|access-date=2018-03-01|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160520144308/http://www.ted.com/talks/manal_al_sharif_a_saudi_woman_who_dared_to_drive/transcript#t-21085|archive-date=2016-05-20|url-status=live}}
&lt;/ref&gt; by posting videos of them driving on social media platforms. One of the women's rights activists from Saudi Arabia, [[Loujain al-Hathloul]] had been imprisoned for more than 3 years and was sentenced on 28 December 2020 to a total of 5 years and 8 months in prison for allegedly conspiring against the kingdom in alignment with foreign nations following her protest against the ban on driving for women in Saudi. Two years and ten months of her prison sentence was reduced leaving only 3 months of time left to serve. However, the charges against her were false and the authorities denied arresting her for protesting against driving ban on women in Saudi Arabia. The prosecutors who were charged with torturing her during detention; sexually and otherwise, were cleared of charges by the government stating lack of evidence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2020/dec/28/saudi-rights-activist-loujain-al-hathloul-sentenced-to-almost-six-years-in-jail|title=Saudi rights activist Loujain al-Hathloul sentenced to almost six years in jail|access-date=28 December 2020|website=The Guardian|date=28 December 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Islamic feminists have objected to the MPL legislation in many of these countries, arguing that these pieces of legislation discriminate against women. Some Islamic feminists have taken the attitude that a reformed MPL which is based on the Quran and [[sunnah]], which includes substantial input from Muslim women, and which does not discriminate against women is possible.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Women's Rights In Islam|last=Chaudry|first=Muhammad Sharif|publisher=Adam &amp; Distributors|year=1991|location=Delhi}}&lt;/ref&gt; Such Islamic feminists have been working on developing women-friendly forms of MPL. (See, for example, [https://web.archive.org/web/20070626213151/http://www.ccmw.com/GTAForum/index.htm the Canadian Council of Muslim Women] for argument based on the Qur'an and not on what they call medieval male consensus.) Other Islamic feminists, particularly some in Muslim minority contexts which are democratic states, argue that MPL should not be reformed but should be rejected and that Muslim women should seek redress, instead, from the [[Civil law (legal system)|civil law]]s of those states. &lt;!--this paragraph needs to cite sources and name the women or groups, instead of "some Islamic feminists."--&gt;

Islamic feminists have been active in advocating for women's rights in the Islamic world. In 2012, Jordanian women protested against laws that allowed the dropping of charges if a rapist marries his victim, Tunisian women marched for equality for women in a new constitution, Saudi women protested against the ban against car driving, and Sudanese women created a silent wall of protest demanding freedom for arrested women.&lt;ref name=":4" /&gt;

===Dress code===
{{Main|Islamic feminist views on dress codes}}
{{See also|Haya (Islam)|Islam and clothing|Awrah|Purdah|Hijab by country}}Another issue that concerns Muslim women is [[dress code]]. Islam requires both men and women to dress modestly; this concept is known as ''[[hijab]]'' and covers a wide interpretation of behavior and garments.

Despite the controversy over hijab in sections of Western society, the veil is not controversial in mainstream Islamic feminist discourse, except in those situations where it is the result of social pressure or coercion. There is in fact strong support from most Muslim feminists in favor of the veil. Many Muslim men and women now view the veil as a symbol of Islamic freedom.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite magazine | url=http://content.time.com/time/world/article/0,8599,2076653,00.html | magazine=Time | title=Is the Veil Now a Symbol of Islamic Freedom? | date=June 13, 2011 | first=Azadeh | last=Moeveni | access-date=2014-05-02 | archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140503061813/http://content.time.com/time/world/article/0,8599,2076653,00.html | archive-date=2014-05-03 | url-status=live }}
&lt;/ref&gt; While there are some Islamic scholars who interpret Islamic scripture as not mandating hijab, many Islamic feminists still observe hijab as an act of religious piety or sometimes as a way of symbolically rejecting Western culture by making a display of their Muslim identity.

A small fringe of Islamic feminists, including [[Fadela Amara]] and [[:fr:Hédi M'henni|Hedi Mhenni]], oppose hijab and even support legal bans on the garment for various reasons. Amara explained her support for [[Islamic scarf controversy in France|France's ban of the garment in public buildings]]: "The veil is the visible symbol of the subjugation of women, and therefore has no place in the mixed, [[Laïcité|secular spaces]] of [[education in France|France's public school system]]."&lt;ref name="guardian17Jul2006"&gt;
{{cite news | url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2006/jul/17/france.politicsphilosophyandsociety | work=The Guardian | location=London | title=Ghetto warrior | date=July 17, 2006 | access-date=May 5, 2010 | first=Rose | last=George | archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130830072547/http://www.theguardian.com/world/2006/jul/17/france.politicsphilosophyandsociety | archive-date=2013-08-30 | url-status=live }}
&lt;/ref&gt; When some feminists began defending the headscarf on the grounds of "tradition", Amara said: "It's not tradition, it's archaic! French feminists are totally contradictory. When [[women in Algeria|Algerian women]] fought [[Hijab by country#Algeria|against wearing the headscarf in Algeria]], [[feminism in France|French feminists]] supported them. But when it's some young girl in a [[Banlieue|French suburb]] school, they don't. They define [[Liberté, égalité, fraternité|liberty and equality]] according to what colour your skin is. It's nothing more than [[neocolonialism]]."&lt;ref name="guardian17Jul2006"/&gt; Mhenni also expressed support for [[Hijab by country#Tunisia|Tunisia's ban on the veil]]: "If today we accept the headscarf, tomorrow we'll accept that women's rights to work and vote and receive an education be banned and they'll be seen as just a tool for reproduction and housework."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.islamonline.net/English/News/2006-10/06/06.shtml |title=IslamOnline.net- News |access-date=August 31, 2009 |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100601165818/http://www.islamonline.net/English/News/2006-10/06/06.shtml |archive-date=June 1, 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Masih Alinejad]] began the movement [[My Stealthy Freedom]] in protest of forced hijab policies in Iran. The movement began as a Facebook page where women uploaded pictures of themselves defying Iran's mandatory hijab laws.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |date=2015-11-17 |title=In Iran, Exposing Hair In Public Is A 'Stealthy Freedom' |url=https://www.nhpr.org/2015-11-17/in-iran-exposing-hair-in-public-is-a-stealthy-freedom |access-date=2022-06-02 |website=New Hampshire Public Radio |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Sihem Habchi]], director of [[Ni Putes Ni Soumises]], expressed support for [[Hijab by country#France|France's ban on the burqa in public places]], stating that the ban was a matter of 'democratic principle' and protecting French women from the 'obscurantist, fascist, right-wing movement' that she claims the burqa represents.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite news | url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/today/hi/today/newsid_8568000/8568024.stm | work=BBC News | title=France's burka dilemma | date=March 15, 2010 | first=Zubeida | last=Malik | access-date=2010-07-15 | archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100809035550/http://news.bbc.co.uk/today/hi/today/newsid_8568000/8568024.stm | archive-date=2010-08-09 | url-status=live }}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
{{Cite web |url=http://www.vingtparismagazine.com/2010/01/ni-putes-ni-soumises-organizes-a-protest-against-the-burqa.html |title=Ni Putes Ni Soumises Organizes a Protest Against the Burqa - VINGT Paris News |access-date=2010-07-15 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100522080511/http://www.vingtparismagazine.com/2010/01/ni-putes-ni-soumises-organizes-a-protest-against-the-burqa.html |archive-date=2010-05-22 |url-status=dead }} 
&lt;/ref&gt;

===Equality in the mosque===
{{See also|Islamic Bill of Rights for Women in the Mosque}}
[[File:Woman at Gate of Mosque (No Ladies Allowed) - Hazratbal Shrine - Srinagar - Jammu &amp; Kashmir - India (26770523561).jpg|thumb|upright|Woman sitting at the threshold of the main building of [[Hazratbal shrine]] in [[Srinagar]] as the sign on the gate reads "''Ladies Are Not Allowed''"]]
A survey by the [[Council on American Islamic Relations]] showed that two out of three mosques in 2000 required women to pray in a separate area, up from one out of two in 1994.&lt;ref name="thedailybeast1"&gt;{{cite web |author=Asra Q. Nomani |url=http://www.thedailybeast.com/blogs-and-stories/2010-02-27/let-these-women-pray/ |title=Let These Women Pray! |publisher=The Daily Beast |date=2010-02-27 |access-date=2012-08-13 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110518000448/http://www.thedailybeast.com/blogs-and-stories/2010-02-27/let-these-women-pray/ |archive-date=2011-05-18 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; Islamic feminists have begun to protest this, advocating for women to be allowed to pray beside men without a partition, as they do in Mecca.&lt;ref name="washingtonpost1"&gt;
{{cite news |url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2010/05/21/AR2010052104253.html |title=Mosque pray-ins against segregation of sexes are springing up |work=Washingtonpost.com |access-date=2012-08-13 |first1=William |last1=Wan |first2=Michael |last2=Laris |date=May 22, 2010 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20121111035356/http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2010/05/21/AR2010052104253.html |archive-date=2012-11-11 |url-status=live }}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web |last=Marsh |first=Julia |url=http://www.womensenews.org/story/religion/100222/protesters-break-prayer-rules-at-leading-mosque |title=Protesters Break Prayer Rules at Leading Mosque |publisher=Women's eNews |date=2010-02-22 |access-date=2012-08-13 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120817034253/http://womensenews.org/story/religion/100222/protesters-break-prayer-rules-at-leading-mosque |archive-date=2012-08-17 |url-status=live }}
&lt;/ref&gt; In 2003, [[Asra Nomani]] challenged the rules at her mosque in Morgantown, West Virginia, that required women to enter through a back door and pray in a secluded balcony.&lt;ref name="thedailybeast1"/&gt; She argued that Muhammad didn't put women behind partitions, and that barriers preventing women from praying equally with men are just sexist man-made rules.&lt;ref name="thedailybeast1"/&gt; The men at her mosque put her on trial to be banished.&lt;ref name="thedailybeast1"/&gt;

In 2004, some American mosques had constitutions prohibiting women from voting in board elections.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2004/07/22/us/muslim-women-seeking-a-place-in-the-mosque.html|title=Muslim Women Seeking a Place in the Mosque|date=22 July 2004|work=The New York Times|access-date=2017-02-19|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170701103425/http://www.nytimes.com/2004/07/22/us/muslim-women-seeking-a-place-in-the-mosque.html|archive-date=2017-07-01|url-status=live}}
&lt;/ref&gt; In 2005, following public agitation on the issue, Muslim organizations that included the CAIR and the [[Islamic Society of North America]] issued a report on making mosques "women-friendly", to assert women's rights in mosques, and to include women's right to pray in the main hall without a partition.&lt;ref name="thedailybeast1"/&gt;

In 2010, American Muslim Fatima Thompson and a few others organized and participated in a "pray-in" at the Islamic Center of Washington in D.C.&lt;ref name="thedailybeast1"/&gt; Police were summoned and threatened to arrest the women when they refused to leave the main prayer hall. The women continued their protest against being corralled in what they referred to as the "[[penalty box]]" (a prayer space reserved for only women). Thompson called the penalty box "an overheated, dark back room."&lt;ref name="thedailybeast1"/&gt; A second protest also staged by the same group on the eve of [[International Women's Day]] in 2010 resulted in calls to the police and threats of arrest again.&lt;ref name="thedailybeast1"/&gt; However, the women were not arrested on either occasion.&lt;ref name="thedailybeast1"/&gt; In May 2010, five women prayed with men at the [[Dar al-Hijrah]] mosque, one of the Washington region's largest Islamic centers.&lt;ref name="washingtonpost1"/&gt; After the prayers, a member of the mosque called Fairfax police who asked the women to leave.&lt;ref name="washingtonpost1"/&gt; However, later in 2010, it was decided that D.C. police would no longer intervene in such protests.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite news |last=Myers |first=Bill |date=21 June 2010 |title=Police won't intervene to remove women from mosques |url=http://www.washingtonexaminer.com/d.c.-police-wont-intervene-to-remove-women-from-mosques/article/12885 |work=Washington Examiner |access-date=August 1, 2010 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160827094134/http://www.washingtonexaminer.com/d.c.-police-wont-intervene-to-remove-women-from-mosques/article/12885 |archive-date=2016-08-27 |url-status=live }}
&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2015 a group of Muslim activists, politicians, and writers issued a Declaration of Reform which states in part, "Men and women have equal rights in mosques, boards, leadership and all spheres of society. We reject sexism and misogyny."&lt;ref name="secularism1"/&gt; That same year Asra Nomani and others placed the Declaration on the door of the Islamic Center of Washington.&lt;ref name="washingtontimes.com"/&gt;

===Equality in leading prayer===
{{Main|Women as imams}}

In 'A Survey and Analysis of Legal Arguments on Woman-Led Prayer in Islam named "I am one of the People"' Ahmed Elewa states that not because of external expectation but in due course with enlightened awareness Muslim communities should adopt women lead mixed gender prayers. In the same research paper Silvers emphasizes on example of Umm Salama who insisted that women are 'one of the people' and suggests women to assert their inclusion with equal rights. Elewa and Silvers research calls contemporary prohibitions of women lead prayer frustrating.&lt;ref name=":3"&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Elewa|first1=Ahmed|last2=Silvers|first2=Laury|year=2010|title=I am one of the People: A Survey and Analysis of Legal Arguments on Woman-Led Prayer in Islam|url=https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/journal-of-law-and-religion/article/i-am-one-of-the-people-a-survey-and-analysis-of-legal-arguments-on-womanled-prayer-in-islam1/269FE071D66D033CB92D0F11A283159F|journal=Journal of Law and Religion|language=en|volume=26|issue=1|pages=141–171|doi=10.1017/S074808140000093X|s2cid=232349598|issn=0748-0814}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to currently existing traditional schools of Islam, a woman cannot lead a mixed gender congregation in salat (prayer). Traditionalists like [[Muzammil H. Siddiqi|Muzammil Siddiqi]] states that women are not supposed to lead prayer because "It is not permissible to introduce any new style or liturgy in Salat." In other words, there must be no deviation from the tradition of men teaching.&lt;ref&gt;
{{Cite web|title=Woman Imam Leading Men and Women in Salat - IslamiCity|url=http://www.islamicity.org/2576/woman-imam-leading-men-and-women-in-salat/.|url-status=live|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20181027151744/https://www.islamicity.org/2576/woman-imam-leading-men-and-women-in-salat/|archive-date=2018-10-27|access-date=2018-10-27|website=www.islamicity.org|language=en-US}}
&lt;/ref&gt; Some schools make exceptions for [[Tarawih]] (optional [[Ramadan]] prayers) or for a congregation consisting only of close relatives. Certain medieval scholars—including [[Muhammad ibn Jarir al-Tabari]] (838–923), [[Abu Thawr]] (764–854), Isma'il Ibn Yahya al-Muzani (791–878), and [[Ibn Arabi]] (1165–1240) considered the practice permissible at least for optional (''[[Nafl prayer|nafl]]'') prayers; however, their views are not accepted by any major surviving group. Islamic feminists have begun to protest this.

On March 18, 2005, [[Amina Wadud]] led a mixed-gender congregational Friday prayer in New York City. It sparked a controversy within the Muslim community because the imam was a woman, Wadud, who also delivered the khutbah.&lt;ref name=Hammer&gt;{{cite book|last=Hammer|first=Juliane|title=American Muslim Women, Religious Authority, and Activism|year=2012|publisher=University of Texas Press|location=Austin}}&lt;/ref&gt; Moreover, the congregation she addressed was not separated by gender. This event that departed from the established ritual practice became an embodied performance of gender justice in the eyes of its organizers and participants. The event was widely publicized in the global media and caused an equally global debate among Muslims.&lt;ref name=Hammer /&gt; However, many Muslims, including women, remain in disagreement with the idea of a woman as imam. Muzammil Siddiqi, chairman of the Fiqh Council of North America, argued that prayer leadership should remain restricted to men.&lt;ref name=Hammer /&gt; He based his argument on the longstanding practice and thus community consensus and emphasized the danger of women distracting men during prayers.

The events that occurred in regards to equality in the mosque and women leading prayers, show the enmity Muslim feminists may receive when voicing opposition toward sexism and establishing efforts to combat it. Those who criticize Muslim feminists state that those who question the faith's views on gender segregation, or who attempt to make changes, are overstepping their boundaries and are acting offensively. On the other hand, people have stated that Islam does not advocate gender segregation. Britain's influential Sunni imam, Ahtsham Ali, has stated, "gender segregation has no basis in Islamic law" nor is it justified in the Quran.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web|url=http://english.alarabiya.net/en/News/middle-east/2014/08/02/UK-imam-Quran-does-not-justify-gender-segregation-.html|title=British imam: Quran does not rule on segregation|website=english.alarabiya.net|date=2 August 2014|access-date=2015-05-03|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140808110851/http://english.alarabiya.net/en/News/middle-east/2014/08/02/UK-imam-Quran-does-not-justify-gender-segregation-.html|archive-date=2014-08-08|url-status=live}}
&lt;/ref&gt; Elewa and Silvers deduce that with lack of any explicit evidence to contrary one ought to assume, women lead prayer adds nothing new to God established worship but just a default state of command expects men and women both to lead the prayer.&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt;

=== Internet &amp; social media impact ===
Internet &amp; social media debates opened up easy access to religious texts for Muslim women which helps them understand scriptural backing for the gender equality rights they which they fight for.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Clubhouse redefines debates on Islam in Kerala|url=https://www.newindianexpress.com/states/kerala/2021/jul/03/clubhouse-redefines-debates-on-islam-in-kerala-2325125.html|access-date=2021-07-04|website=The New Indian Express}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Criticism ==
Hakimeh Entesari, an Iranian academic said, "The thoughts and writings of these people [Islamic feminists] suffer from a fundamental problem, and that is the absolute detachment of this movement from the cultural and indigenous realities of Islamic societies and countries..." She also believes that the use of the term "Islamic feminism" is wrong and it should be "Muslim feminists".&lt;ref&gt;[https://hawzah.net/fa/Magazine/View/3992/8151/107366 How and why (about) Islamic feminism] Retrieved 26 April 2022&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Maria Massi Dakake]], an American Muslim academic, criticized [[Asma Barlas]]' assertion the Quran is inherently anti-patriarchal and sought to undo patriarchal social structures. Dakake writes, "She [Asma Barlas] makes a number of important and substantial points about the limitations to traditional "patriarchal" rights of fathers and husbands in the Quran. However, the conclusion that the Qur'an is "anti-patriarchal" as such is hard to reconcile with the Quran's fairly explicit endorsement of male leadership - even if not absolute authority - over the marital unit in 4:34."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last= |first= |title=The Study Quran |publisher=HarperCollins |year=2015 |editor-last=Nasr |editor-first=Seyyed Hossein |pages=1794 |language=English |editor-last2=Dagli |editor-first2=Caner |editor-last3=Massi Dakake |editor-first3=Maria |editor-last4=Rustom |editor-first4=Muhammad |editor-last5=Lumbard |editor-first5=Joseph}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Ibtissam Bouachrine]], a professor at [[Smith College]], has critiqued the writings of [[Fatema Mernissi]]. According to Bouachrine, Mernissi, in her book, ''The Veil and the Male Elite'', critiques male interpretations of [[Zaynab bint Jahsh|Quran 33:53]], but not of Quran 24:31, "which evokes the veil in the context of the feminine body in public space." She also criticizes how Mernissi focuses on the [[hadith]] over the Quran because it is easier to criticize the hadith than the Quran which is seen as the word of God, but the hadith are the words of human beings. Bouachrine also critiques how Mernissi presents Muhammad as a "revolutionary heretic who sides with women against the Arabian male elite and their patriarchal values" but does not critique Muhammad's marriage to nine-year-old [[Aisha]]. Bouachrine also states that Mernissi does not mention that Zaynab was the former wife of [[Zayd ibn Haritha al-Kalbi|Muhammad's adopted son]].&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;

Bouachrine also critiques [[Amina Wadud]]’s interpretation of [[An-Nisa, 34|4:34]] in ''Quran and Woman''. According to Bouachrine, although 4:34 seems to call for men to physically discipline their wives, "Wadud argues that the Qur’an would not encourage violence against women and therefore the obedience required of women is to God not to the husband." Wadud also proposes that ''daraba'' means to set an example instead of to use physical force. According to Bouachrine, these reinterpretations do not help women in the Muslim world suffering from domestic violence.&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{Cite book |last=Bouachrine |first=Ibtissam |title=Women and Islam: Myths, Apologies, and the Limits of feminist Critique |publisher=Lexington Books |year=2014 |language=English}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Ahmadian, head of Isfahan Institute of Theology: "Some have created a fake title which is called "Islamic Feminism" in order to solve the conflict between Islam and feminism, that is considered to be a paradoxical combination and its principles are not consistent with the principles of Islam religion. Based on Islamic teachings, there are differences between the roles and positions of men/women, and this distinction doesn't lower the dignity of women in any way.&lt;ref&gt;[https://isfahan.iqna.ir/fa/news/3980444/%D9%86%D9%82%D8%AF-%D8%B9%D9%86%D9%88%D8%A7%D9%86-%D8%AC%D8%B9%D9%84%DB%8C-%D9%81%D9%85%DB%8C%D9%86%DB%8C%D8%B3%D9%85-%D8%A7%D8%B3%D9%84%D8%A7%D9%85%DB%8C-%D8%AF%D8%B1-%DA%A9%D8%AA%D8%A7%D8%A8-%D9%81%D9%85%DB%8C%D9%86%DB%8C%D8%B3%D9%85-%D9%88-%D8%AE%D8%A7%D9%86%D9%88%D8%A7%D8%AF%D9%87 Criticism of the fake title "Islamic Feminism" in the book "Feminism and Family"] Retrieved 16 August 2022&lt;/ref&gt;

Seyed Hussein Ishaghi, Ph.D. in Islamic Theology: "It is more appropriate to call Islamic feminism a woman-oriented interpretation of Islam religion... A group in the interaction of Islamic and Western culture faced an identity crisis; and on the other hand, in this confrontation, a group with its heart attached to Western culture denied religious teachings. That group promoted materialistic viewpoints by considering the mentioned beliefs as class or superstitious."&lt;ref&gt;[https://hawzah.net/fa/Magazine/View/3992/7678/96652/%D9%85%D8%A7%D9%87%DB%8C%D8%AA-%D9%88-%D8%A7%D9%87%D8%AF%D8%A7%D9%81-%D9%81%D9%85%DB%8C%D9%86%DB%8C%D8%B3%D9%85-%D8%A7%D8%B3%D9%84%D8%A7%D9%85%DB%8C The nature and goals of Islamic feminism] Retrieved 17 August 2022&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notable people==
{{Main|List of Muslim feminists}}

==See also==
{{Portal|Islam|Feminism}}

===In particular countries===
{{div col|colwidth=20em|small=yes}}
*[[Feminism in Egypt]]
*[[Feminism in India]]
*[[Gender roles in Afghanistan]]
*[[Golden Needle Sewing School]]
*[[International Conference on Population and Development]]
*[[Revolutionary Association of the Women of Afghanistan]]
*[[Women in Lebanon]]
*[[Women's rights in Iran]]
*[[Women's rights in Saudi Arabia]]
*[[Women's rights in Kuwait]]
*[[Women's rights movement in Iran]]
{{div col end}}

===General===
{{div col|colwidth=20em|small=yes}}
*[[Hermeneutics of feminism in Islam]]
*[[List of Muslim feminists]]
*[[Islam and abortion|Abortion and Islam]]
*[[LGBT in Islam]]
*[[Female figures in the Qur'an]]
*[[Feminationalism]]
*[[Gender segregation and Islam]]
*[[History of feminism]]
*[[Postcolonial feminism]]
*[[Purplewashing]]
*[[Rada (fiqh)]]
*[[Rights and obligations of spouses in Islam]]
*[[Role of women in religion]]
*[[Sex segregation in Iran]]
*[[Taliban treatment of women]]
*[[Women in Islam]]
* [[World Hijab Day]]
* [[Glossary of Islam]]
* [[Gender roles in Islam]]
* [[Islamic clothing]]
{{div col end}}

==Further reading==
{{Spoken Wikipedia|Wikipedia_-_Islamic_feminism.ogg|date=2008-03-31}}
* {{cite book | last = Ahmed | first = Leila | title = Women and gender in Islam: historical roots of a modern debate | publisher = Yale University Press | location = New Haven, Connecticut | year = 1992 | isbn = 9780300049428 }}
* {{citation | last = Ali | first = Kecia | contribution = Feminist thought in Islam | editor-last1 = Fitzpatrick | editor-first1 = Coeli | editor-last2 = Hani Walker | editor-first2 = Adam | title = Muhammad in history, thought, and culture: an encyclopedia of the Prophet of God | pages = 195&amp;ndash;197 | publisher = ABC-CLIO, LLC | location = Santa Barbara, California | year = 2014 | isbn = 9781610691789 | postscript = .}}
* {{cite web | last = Anwar | first = Zainah | title = Islamisation and its Impact on Democratic Governance and Women's Rights in Islam: A Feminist Perspective | url = http://www.islam-democracy.org/4th_Annual_Conference-Anwar_address.asp | website = islam-democracy.org | publisher = Center for the Study of Islam and Democracy | date = May 17, 2003 | url-status = dead | archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20050308115532/http://www.islam-democracy.org/4th_Annual_Conference-Anwar_address.asp | archive-date = March 8, 2005 }}
* {{cite book | last = Badran | first = Margot | title = Feminists, Islam, and Nation: Gender and the Making of Modern Egypt | publisher = Princeton University Press | location = Princeton | year = 2001 | isbn = 9781400821433 }}
* {{cite news | last = Badran | first = Margot | title = Islamic feminism: what's in a name? Islamic feminism is on the whole more radical than Muslims' secular feminisms | work = Al-Ahram Weekly Online }} 17–23 January 2002, Issue No.569.
* {{cite news | last = Noushad | first = Mohammed | title = Islamic feminism means justice to women | url = http://www.milligazette.com/Archives/2004/16-31Jan04-Print-Edition/1631200425.htm | work = [[The Milli Gazette]] | date = January 16, 2004 }} Interview with Prof Margot Badran.
* {{Cite journal | last = Baffoun | first = Alya | author-link = Alya Baffoun | title = Women and social change in the Muslim Arab world | journal = Women's Studies International Forum | volume = 5 | issue = 2 | pages = 227–242 | date = 1982 | doi = 10.1016/0277-5395(82)90030-9 }}
* {{citation | last = Baffoun | first = Alya | contribution = Feminism and Muslim fundamentalism: the Tunisian and Algerian cases | editor-last = Moghadam | editor-first = Valentine M. | title = Identity politics and women: cultural reassertions and feminisms in international perspective | publisher = Westview Press | location = Boulder | year = 1994 | isbn = 9780813386928 }}
* {{cite news | last = Djait | first = Badra | title = More to life than window dressing | archive-url = https://archive.today/20130111220243/http://www.diabolicdigest.net/Guest%20pens/Badra_en.htm | archive-date = January 11, 2013 | url = http://www.diabolicdigest.net/Guest%20pens/Badra_en.htm | date = August 2006 | url-status = dead }} In this special feature, a successful Belgian-Algerian Muslim woman recounts what it was like growing up immersed in two cultures with divergent views of women.
* {{cite book | last = Fernea | first = Elizabeth Warnock | title = In search of Islamic feminism: one woman's global journey | url = https://archive.org/details/insearchofislami00fern | url-access = registration | publisher = Doubleday | location = New York | year = 1998 | isbn = 9780385488587 }}
*[http://www.oxfordislamicstudies.com/article/opr/t125/e2510?_hi=6&amp;_pos=2 Women and Islam in Oxford Islamic Studies Online]
*{{Cite web |url=http://www.asmasociety.org/wise/ |title=Women's Islamic Initiative in Spirituality and Equity |access-date=2009-02-12 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090121205928/http://www.asmasociety.org/wise/ |archive-date=2009-01-21 |url-status=dead }}
*[http://www.ccmw.com Canadian Council of Muslim Women] Several examples of closely argued essays for female equality, based on the Qur'an.
* {{cite web | last = Farooq | first = Mohammad Omar | title = Women Scholars of Islam: They Must Bloom Again | url = http://globalwebpost.com/farooqm/writings/islamic/bloom.html | url-status = dead | archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20060615015430/http://globalwebpost.com/farooqm/writings/islamic/bloom.html | archive-date = 2006-06-15 }}
*Foreign Affairs Committee of the National Council of Resistance of Iran. [http://www.iran-e-azad.org/english/book_on_women.html ''Women, Islam, and Equality''], an ebook
* {{cite web | last = Jameelah | first = Maryam | title = The feminist movement and the Muslim woman | url = http://www.islam101.com/women/jameelah.htm | website = islam101.com | publisher = Islam 101 | date = July 13, 2005 }}
* {{Cite journal | last = Jeenah | first = Na'eem | author-link = Na'eem Jeenah | title = Towards an Islamic feminist hermeneutic | journal = Journal for Islamic Studies | volume = 21 | pages = 36–70 | date = 2001 | doi = 10.4314/jis.v21i1.39954 }}
* {{Cite journal | last = Jeenah | first = Na'eem | author-link = Na'eem Jeenah | title = The national liberation struggle and Islamic feminisms in South Africa | journal = [[Women's Studies International Forum]] | volume = 29 | issue = 1 | pages = 27–41 | date = January–February 2006 | doi = 10.1016/j.wsif.2005.10.004 | s2cid = 143801194 }}
* {{cite journal | last = Khader | first = Serene J. | title = Do Muslim women need freedom? Traditionalist feminisms and transnational politics | journal = [[Politics &amp; Gender]] | volume = 12 | issue = 4 | pages = 727&amp;ndash;753 | date = December 2016 | doi = 10.1017/S1743923X16000441 | s2cid = 148442266 }}
* {{cite web | last = Lamya' al Faruqi | first = Lois | title = Islamic Traditions and the Feminist Movement: Confrontation or Cooperation? | url = http://www.jannah.org/sisters/feminism.html }}
* {{cite news | last = Muñoz | first = Gema Martín | title = Feminism in the Arab World: The Silent Revolution | url = http://en.qantara.de/content/feminism-in-the-arab-world-the-silent-revolution | work = Qantara.de | date = 2012 }}
* {{cite news | last = Nomani | first = Asra | author-link = Asra Nomani | title = A Gender Jihad For Islam's Future | url = https://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2005/11/04/AR2005110402306.html | newspaper =[[Washington Post]] | date = November 6, 2005 }}
* {{cite book | last = Perry | first = Eleanor H. | title =Opening the Gates: A Century of Arab Feminist Writing | date = June 1, 1993 }} Article for Domes
* {{Cite journal | last = Safarian | first = Alexander | title = On the history of Turkish feminism | journal = [[Iran and the Caucasus|Iran &amp; the Caucasus]] | volume = 11 | issue = 1 | pages = 141–152 | jstor = 25597322 | date = 2007 | doi = 10.1163/157338407X224978 }}
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20060901003434/http://www.secularislam.org/rights/declaration.htm "A Declaration of the Rights of Women in Islamic Societies"], ''SecularIslam.com'', undated
* {{cite news | last = Seker | first = Nimet | title = Islamic Feminism and Reformist Islam: Against the Politicisation of the Koran | url = http://en.qantara.de/content/islamic-feminism-and-reformist-islam-against-the-politicisation-of-the-koran | work = Qantara.de | date = 2012 }}
* {{cite web | last = Shaikh | first = Shamima | title = Articles by the South African Islamic feminist | url = http://shams.za.org/articles.htm | url-status = dead | archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20060207000440/http://shams.za.org/articles.htm | archive-date = 2006-02-07 }} Articles by a South African Islamic feminist 
* {{cite news | last = Simons | first = Marlise | title = Muslim women take charge of their faith | archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20110805045648/http://www.nytimes.com/2005/12/01/world/europe/01iht-islam6.html | archive-date = August 5, 2011 | url = https://www.nytimes.com/2005/12/01/world/europe/01iht-islam6.html | work = The New York Times | date = December 4, 2005 }}
* {{cite book | last = Svensson | first = Jonas | title = Women's Human Rights and Islam. A Study of Three Attempts at Accommodation | publisher = Almquist &amp; Wiksell | location = Stockholm | year = 2001 }}[https://www.researchgate.net/publication/303727470_Women%27s_human_rights_and_Islam_A_study_of_three_attempts_at_accommodation]
* {{cite book | last = Webb | first = Gisela | title = Windows of faith: Muslim women scholar-activists in North America | publisher = Syracuse University Press | location = Syracuse, New York | year = 2000 | isbn = 9780815628521 }}
* Mir-Hosseini, Ziba. ''Journeys Toward Gender Equality in Islam''. United Kingdom, Oneworld Publications, 2022. {{ISBN|9780861543281}}
* Shamim, Amna. Ed. ''Towards Islamic Feminism''. Jaipur, Aadi Publications, 2016. {{ISBN|9789382630807}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{Islam topics}}
{{Feminism}}
{{Theology}}
{{Relpolnav}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Islamic Feminism}}
[[Category:Islamic feminism| ]]
[[Category:Feminist theory]]
[[Category:Women's rights in Islam]]
[[Category:Islam-related controversies]]
[[Category:Multicultural feminism]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>