<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20101007164853|389348655" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1185505" pageid="1185505" ns="0" title="Violence against transgender people"><revisions><rev timestamp="2010-10-07T16:53:27Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">__NOTOC__
{{Transgender sidebar}}
'''Trans-bashing''' is the act of victimizing a person physically, sexually, or verbally because they are [[transgender]] or [[transsexual]].&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.news.com.au/heraldsun/story/0,21985,20774504-5005961,00.html Guilty plea over transsexual bashing] By Mariza O'Keefe in ''Herlad Sun''&lt;/ref&gt; Unlike [[gay bashing]], it is committed because of the target's actual or perceived [[gender identity]], not [[sexual orientation]].  The term has also been applied to [[hate speech]] directed at transgender people&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.washingtonblade.com/2007/4-27/view/columns/10484.cfm Demagogues of defamation     Gay: Where is the outrage when cable TV’s talking heads trash trans people?]&lt;/ref&gt; and at depictions of transgender people in the media that reinforce negative stereotypes about them.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=Mary|last=McNamara|title=Transgender Artists, Work Gaining Acceptance|publisher=[[Los Angeles Times]]|date=2001-02-08|accessdate=2007-12-01 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Discrimination, including physical or sexual violence against trans people due to [[transphobia]] or [[homophobia]], is a common occurrence for trans people.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;ct=res&amp;cd=40&amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.opha.on.ca%2Fppres%2F2003-06_pp.pdf&amp;ei=H7tNR_yFJp3m0ASBwKHiDQ&amp;usg=AFQjCNHJKzms3yGsHHYiITIVTShWePUv7Q&amp;sig2=26GpID7ftyT6IfHUszh3Sw Trans Health Project: A position paper and resolution adopted by the Ontario Public Health Association]&lt;/ref&gt;{{Dead link|date=October 2009}}&lt;ref&gt;Hill, D.B. (2001). Genderism, transphobia, and gender bashing: A framework for
interpreting anti-transgender violence. In B. Wallace, &amp; R. Carter (Eds.). A multicultural
approach for understanding and dealing with violence: A handbook for psychologists and
educators. Thousand Oaks, CA: Sage Publishing.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Namaste, V.K. (2000a). Invisible lives: The erasure of transsexual and transgendered people. Chicago: University of Chicago Press.&lt;/ref&gt;  Hate crimes against trans people are common even recently, and "in some instances, inaction by police or other government officials leads to the untimely deaths of transgender victims."&lt;ref name="cider"&gt;{{cite journal |last=Frye|first=Phyllis|year=2000|month=Fall|title=The International Bill of Gender Rights vs. The Cide House Rules: Transgenders struggle with the courts over what clothing they are allowed to wear on the job, which restroom they are allowed to use on the job, their right to marry, and the very definition of their sex|journal=William and Mary Journal of Women and the Law|volume=7|pages=139–145}}&lt;/ref&gt;

One of the most famous incidents was the December 1993 rape and murder of [[Brandon Teena]], a young [[transman]] who was raped and murdered by two male friends after they found out that he had been born female.&lt;ref name="trutv5"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.trutv.com/library/crime/notorious_murders/not_guilty/brandon/5.html|title=Teena Brandon|last=Ramsland|first=Katherine|publisher=[[TruTV]]|pages=pg 5|accessdate=2009-02-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; The events became internationally known when told in the feature film ''[[Boys Don't Cry (film)|Boys Don't Cry]]'', which earned [[Hilary Swank]] an [[Academy Award]] for best actress. 

In [[Seattle]]'s [[gay village]] of [[Capitol Hill, Seattle, Washington|Capitol Hill]], there is some evidence of an increase in incidents of trans-bashing over the past two years.&lt;ref&gt; [http://spectator.seattleu.edu/news/story.aspx?ID=14050 Gentrification ousting local gay community]&lt;/ref&gt;{{Dead link|date=July 2009}}

== Differentiating trans-bashing from gay-bashing ==

At least since the [[Stonewall riots]] in 1969, transgender people have often been politically aligned with the lesbian, gay, and bisexual communities.&lt;ref&gt;Kay Dayus, Transgenders Protest HRC Exec's Visit to Houston, Hous. Voice, Sept. 29, 2000&lt;/ref&gt;  However, some transgender activists argue trans-bashing should be categorized separately from violence committed on the basis of sexual orientation ("gay-bashing").&lt;ref name="cider"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Discrimination and Hate Crimes Against Gender Variant People, It's Time Illinois . . . Political Action for the Gender Variant Community (May 2000)&lt;/ref&gt; One argument is that conflating violence against trans people with violence against gay people erases the identities of trans people and the truth of what happens to them.  However, campaigns against gay-bashing and trans-bashing are often seen as a common cause.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.workers.org/ww/1998/bashing1008.php 'Zero tolerance for gay-trans bashing': Protests mount]&lt;/ref&gt;

In one case, perpetrators accused of hate crimes against trans people have tried to use a [[trans panic]] defense, an extension of [[gay panic defense]].&lt;ref name="TRTH"&gt; [http://books.google.com/books?id=SiaNoJ3puyQC&amp;pg=PA47&amp;dq=%22gwen+araujo%22&amp;lr=&amp;as_brr=3#PPA47,M1 ''Transpeople: Repudiation, Trauma, Healing''] by Christopher A. Shelley.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="TMCIAC"&gt; [http://www.ebar.com/news/article.php?sec=news&amp;article=153 "Two murder convictions in Araujo case"], Zak Szymanski; ''[[Bay Area Reporter]]'' 15 September 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;  The jury deadlocked, but there is evidence they rejected the trans-panic defense.  One law journal provided an analysis of the trans-panic defense, arguing in part that the emotional premise of a trans panic defense (shock at discovering unexpected genitals) is different from the emotional premise of a gay panic defense (shock at being propositioned by a member of the same sex, perhaps because of one's repressed homosexuality).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Steinberg|first=Victoria L.|year=2005|month=Spring|title=A Heat of Passion Offense: Emotions and Bias in "Trans Panic" Mitigation Claims: Hiding From Humanity|journal=Boston College Third World Law Journal|volume=25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== U.S. hate crime laws covering gender identity ==

In the United States, currently ten states plus the District of Columbia have hate crime laws protecting people victimized on the basis of their gender identity (they are [[Hawaii]], [[California]], [[Connecticut]], [[New Mexico]], [[Mississippi]], [[Missouri]], [[Minnesota]], [[Pennsylvania]], [[Vermont]], [[Washington (U.S. state)|Washington]] state&lt;ref&gt; [http://apps.leg.wa.gov/billinfo/summary.aspx?year=2006&amp;bill=2661 HB 2661 - 2005-06: Expanding the jurisdiction of the human rights commission]&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Washington, D.C.]]).&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.nctequality.org/Hate_Crimes.asp National Center for Transgender Equality: Hate crimes]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hrc.org/issues/hate_crimes/1083.htm Human Rights Campaign: Mississippi Hate Crimes Law]&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Matthew Shepard Act]] expanded the federal hate crime laws to include gender, gender identity, and sexual orientation.

== See also ==
* [[Gay bashing]]
* [[Hate crime]]
* [[Transphobia]]
* [[Violence against LGBT people]]
* [[List of unlawfully killed transgender people]]

== References ==
{{reflist|2}}

== External links ==
* [http://www.nctequality.org/Hate_Crimes.asp National Center for Transgender Equality], including information on hate crime laws in the United States
* [http://www.masstpc.org/projects/dor-malist.shtml Transgender victims in Massachusetts]

{{abuse}}
{{transgender footer}}

[[Category:Sexual orientation and society]]
[[Category:Pejoratives]]
[[Category:Abuse]]
[[Category:LGBT terms]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>