<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20230917223521|1175860336" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="4765088" pageid="4765088" ns="0" title="Reappropriation"><revisions><rev timestamp="2023-10-04T19:18:09Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|Valuing a formerly pejorative term in esteem}}
{{Redirect|Reclaiming|the neopagan organization of this name|Reclaiming (neopaganism)|other uses|Reclaim (disambiguation){{!}}Reclaim}}
[[File:Monet - Impression, Sunrise.jpg|thumb|300px|Monet's ''[[Impression, soleil levant]]'' was ridiculed as "Impression-ist" in 1872, but the term then became the name of the art movement, "[[impressionism]]", and painters began to self-identify as "impressionist"]]

In [[linguistics]], '''reappropriation''', '''reclamation''', or '''resignification'''&lt;ref name=":02" /&gt; is the [[cultural]] process by which a group reclaims words or artifacts that were previously used in a way disparaging of that group. It is a specific form of a [[semantic change]] (i.e. change in a word's meaning). Linguistic reclamation can have wider implications in the fields of [[discourse]] and has been described in terms of personal or sociopolitical [[empowerment]].

== Characteristics ==
{{Anchor|Linguistic reappropriation or reclaimation}} &lt;!-- old name; please keep to avoid breaking old in-links --&gt;

A ''reclaimed'' or ''reappropriated'' word is a word that was at one time [[pejorative]] but has been brought back into acceptable usage, usually starting within its original target, i.e. the communities that were pejoratively described by that word, and later spreading to the general populace as well.&lt;ref name="Slurs2"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Croom|first1=A.M.|year=2011|title=Slurs|journal=Language Sciences|volume=33|issue=3|pages=343–358|doi=10.1016/j.langsci.2010.11.005|quote=...that slurs are in certain cases felicitously used to mean something non-derogatory (e.g. in an appropriative manner) is now a well documented linguistic phenomenon.. For instance Russell Simmons, founder of Def Jam Records, reports from the perspective of hip-hop culture that "When we say ‘nigger’ now, it’s very positive. Now all white kids who buy into hip-hop culture call each other ‘nigger’ because they have no history with the word other than something positive..."}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":02"&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Brontsema |first=Robin |date=2004-06-01 |title=A Queer Revolution: Reconceptualizing the Debate Over Linguistic Reclamation |journal=Colorado Research in Linguistics |volume=17 |issue=1 |doi=10.25810/dky3-zq57 |issn=1937-7029 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20210718185817/https://journals.colorado.edu/index.php/cril/article/download/255/235/ |archive-date=2021-07-18 |url=https://journals.colorado.edu/index.php/cril/article/download/255/235/ |quote=Linguistic reclamation, also known as linguistic resignification or reappropriation, refers to the appropriation of a pejorative epithet by its target(s).}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt; Some of the terms being reclaimed have originated as non-pejorative terms that over time became pejorative. Reclaiming them can be seen as restoring their original intent. This, however, does not apply to all such words as some were used in a derogatory fashion from the very beginning.&lt;ref name=":02" /&gt;

In terms of [[Theoretical linguistics|linguistic theory]], reappropriation can be seen as a specific case of a type of a [[semantic change]], namely, of ''amelioration'' - a process through which a word's meaning becomes more positive over time.&lt;ref name="Curzan2014"&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=YKlkAwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA146|title=Fixing English: Prescriptivism and Language History|first=Anne|last=Curzan|date=8 May 2014|publisher=Cambridge University Press|isbn=978-1-107-02075-7|pages=146–148}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Robin Brontsema suggested that there are at least three identifiable goals of reclamation:

# Value reversal
# Neutralization
# Stigma exploitation

Value reversal refers to changing the meaning from pejorative to positive, while neutralization refers to changing the meaning from pejorative to neutral. Stigma exploitation, finally, refers to retaining the derogatory nature of such terms as a reminder that a given group has been subject to unfair treatment. Those goals are mutually exclusive.&lt;ref name=":02" /&gt;

Reclamation can be seen as both a psychological, individual process and as a sociological, society-wide process.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Godrej|first=Farah|date=2011|title=Spaces for Counter-Narratives: The Phenomenology of Reclamation|journal=Frontiers: A Journal of Women Studies|volume=32|issue=3|pages=111–133|doi=10.5250/fronjwomestud.32.3.0111|issn=0160-9009|jstor=10.5250/fronjwomestud.32.3.0111|pmid=22299194|s2cid=28011738}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Godrej2"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://mpsa.indiana.edu/conf2003papers/1032831537.pdf|title=Spaces for Counter-Narratives: The Phenomenology of Reclamation|last=Godrej|first=Farah|date=April 3, 2003|work=Paper prepared for the Midwest Political Science Association Meeting|publisher=University of Indiana|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20051025220344/http://mpsa.indiana.edu/conf2003papers/1032831537.pdf|archive-date=2005-10-25|access-date=July 25, 2011}} Citing Patricia Hill Collins, ''Black Feminist Thought: Knowledge, Consciousness and the Politics of Empowerment''  (New York: Routledge, 1991)&lt;/ref&gt; In terms of a personal process, it has been discussed in the context of empowerment that comes from "disarming the power of a dominant group to control one’s own and others’ views of oneself", and gaining control over the way one is described, and hence, one's [[self-image]], [[self-control]] and [[self-understanding]].&lt;ref name="Godrej2" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt; Brontsema wrote that "At the heart of linguistic reclamation is the right of [[self-definition]], of forging and naming one’s own existence."&lt;ref name=":02" /&gt; Other scholars have connected this concept to that of [[self-labelling]].&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt; The empowerment process, and the denial of language as a tool of oppression as abuse of power, has also been stressed by scholars such as [[Judith Butler]] and [[Michel Foucault]], the latter who also referred to it as a "[[reverse discourse]]".&lt;ref name="CG" /&gt;

In terms of the wider sociopolitical empowerment process, reclamation process has also been credited with promoting [[social justice]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Herbert|first=Cassie|date=2015-11-01|title=Precarious projects: the performative structure of reclamation|journal=Language Sciences|series=Slurs|volume=52|pages=131–138|doi=10.1016/j.langsci.2015.05.002|issn=0388-0001}}&lt;/ref&gt; and building  [[group solidarity]];&lt;ref name="CG" /&gt; activists groups that engage in this process have been argued to be more likely to be seen as representative of their groups and see those groups as raising in power and status in their society.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt; Scholars have argued that those who use such terms to describe themselves in the act of reappropriation "will feel powerful and therefore see his or her group label as less stigmatizing. Observers will infer that the group has power and will therefore see the label as less saturated in negativity".&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;

Although those terms are most often used in the context of language, this concept has also been used in relation to other cultural concepts, for example in the discussion of reappropriation of [[stereotype]]s,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Reyes|first=Angela Rosario|date=2003-01-01|title="The other Asian": Linguistic, ethnic and cultural stereotypes at an after -school Asian American teen videomaking project|url=https://repository.upenn.edu/dissertations/AAI3087455|journal=Dissertations Available from ProQuest|pages=1–347}}&lt;/ref&gt; reappropriation of popular culture (e.g., the reappropriation of [[science fiction literature]] into elite, [[High culture|high literature]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Tamás|first=Bényei|date=2001|title=Leakings: Reappropriating Science Fiction--The Case of Kurt Vonnegut|journal=Journal of the Fantastic in the Arts|volume=11|issue=4 (44)|pages=432–453|issn=0897-0521|jstor=43308479}}&lt;/ref&gt;), or reappropriation of traditions.&lt;ref name="Meilicke2005"&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=mPEZjhVYCCsC&amp;pg=PA23|title=Jerome Rothenberg's Experimental Poetry and Jewish Tradition|first=Christine A.|last=Meilicke|publisher=Lehigh University Press|year=2005|isbn=978-0-934223-76-8|pages=23–}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Controversy and objections ==
Reclaimed words often remain controversial for a time, due to their original pejorative nature. For some terms, even "reclaimed" usage by members of the community concerned is a subject of controversy.&lt;ref name=":02" /&gt; Often, not all members of a given community support the idea that a particular slur should be reclaimed at all.&lt;ref name=":02" /&gt; In other cases, a word can be seen as acceptable when used by the members of the community that has reclaimed it (in-group usage), but its use by outside parties (out-group usage) can still be seen as derogatory and thus controversial.&lt;ref name="CG" /&gt; For example, Brontsema noted in 2003 in his discussion of the reclaimed terms that while "[the term [[nigger]]] may be acceptable for [[African Americans]] to use it freely, it is off-limits to whites, whose usage of nigger cannot be the same, given its history and the general history of racial oppression and racial relations in the United States."&lt;ref name=":02" /&gt; A similar argument has been made in 2009 for words associated with the [[LGBT social movements|LGBT movement]] like [[queer]] or [[dyke (slang)|dyke]].&lt;ref name="Mallon2009"&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=EdWNAgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA388|title=Social Work Practice with Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, and Transgender People|first=Gerald P.|last=Mallon|date=2 June 2009|publisher=Routledge|isbn=978-1-135-26686-8|page=388}}&lt;/ref&gt; A related discourse occurred with regards to the [[Washington Redskins name controversy]], with the [[Native Americans in the United States|American Indians]] community was divided on whether the term has been reclaimed or not.&lt;ref name="CG" /&gt;

Those opposed to the reclamation of terms have argued that such terms are irredeemable and are forever connected to their derogatory meaning, and their usage will continue to hurt those who remember its original intent&lt;ref name=":02" /&gt; and even reinforce the existing stigma.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt; The supporters of reclamation argue, in turn, that many such words had non-derogatory meanings that are simply being restored and that in either case, reclaiming such a word denies it to those who would want to use it to oppress others and represents a form of moral victory for the group that reclaimed it.&lt;ref name=":02" /&gt;

In 2017, the [[US Supreme Court]], heard arguments for ''[[Matal v. Tam]]''. In that case, the [[US Patent and Trademark Office]] refused a trademark registration for an [[Asian American]] band, [[The Slants]], because it deemed the term disparaging. However, the court ruled unanimously in its favor. [[Washington University in St. Louis]] conducted an extensive study on reappropriation based on the band name and found that reclaimed words could be an effective tool for neutralizing disparaging words: "Reappropriation does seem to work in the sense of defusing insults, rendering them less disparaging and harmful."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://source.wustl.edu/2019/11/toward-a-more-civil-discourse/|title=Toward a more civil discourse {{!}} The Source {{!}} Washington University in St. Louis|date=2019-11-14|website=The Source|language=en-US|access-date=2019-12-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Examples==
{{Anchor|Words that could be considered reclaimed}} &lt;!-- old name, please keep to avoid breaking in-links --&gt;

===Sex and sexuality===
There are many recent examples of linguistic reappropriation in the areas of [[human sexuality]], [[gender role]]s, [[sexual orientation]], etc. Among these are:

* [[Dyke (slang)|dyke]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nclrights.org/site/PageServer?pagename=press_pr_dykesonbikes_071405|title=Trademark Office says no to Dykes on Bikes|publisher=National Center for Lesbian Rights|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110718090612/http://www.nclrights.org/site/PageServer?pagename=press_pr_dykesonbikes_071405|archive-date=2011-07-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":02" /&gt;&lt;ref name="CG" /&gt;
* [[Faggot (slang)|faggot]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Cheves |first1=Alexander |title=21 Words the Queer Community Has Reclaimed (and Some We Haven't) |url=https://www.advocate.com/arts-entertainment/2017/8/02/21-words-queer-community-has-reclaimed-and-some-we-havent |website=The Advocate |access-date=22 June 2021 |language=en |date=2017-08-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Ellis |first1=Philip |title=Reclaiming the word 'faggot' is a tricky business |url=https://www.gq-magazine.co.uk/lifestyle/article/faggot-meaning |website=GQ |date=6 July 2019 |publisher=Condé Nast |access-date=22 June 2021 |archive-date=16 October 2022 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20221016102718/https://www.gq-magazine.co.uk/lifestyle/article/faggot-meaning |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[hermaphrodite]]&lt;ref name="TransStudies"&gt;{{cite book |author1 = Abbie E. Goldberg |author2 = Genny Beemyn |year= 2021 |title = The SAGE Encyclopedia of Trans Studies |publisher = SAGE Publications |page = 953 |isbn = 978-1-5443-9384-1 |url = https://books.google.com/books?id=Fb4IEAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT953}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[queer]]&lt;ref name=":02" /&gt;&lt;ref name="CG" /&gt;
* [[Tongzhi (term)|tongzhi]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Wong|first=Andrew D.|date=November 2005|title=The reappropriation of tongzhi|journal=Language in Society|volume=34|issue=5|pages=763–793|doi=10.1017/S0047404505050281|s2cid=145325619|issn=1469-8013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Politics===
In England, [[Cavalier]] was a derogatory nickname reappropriated as self-identification,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite EB1911|short=1 |author=Anonymous |wstitle=Cavalier |volume=5}}&lt;/ref&gt; in contrast to the term [[Roundhead]] which, despite being used by the Royalists for the supporters of the Parliamentary cause, remained a derisory word up to the point of it being a punishable offense if used to refer to a soldier of the [[New Model Army]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Worden |first=Blair |year=2009 |title=The English Civil Wars 1640–1660|location=London |publisher=Penguin Books |page=2 |isbn=978-0-14-100694-9}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Tory]]'' (originally from the [[Middle Irish]] word for 'pursuer' {{lang|mga|[[tóraidhe]]}}), ''[[Whig (British political party)|Whig]]'' (from ''whiggamore''; see the [[Whiggamore Raid]]) and ''[[Suffragette]]'' are other British examples.

In the American colonies, British officers used [[Yankee]], a term originated in reference to Dutch settlers, as a derogatory term against the colonists. British officers created the early versions of the song ''[[Yankee Doodle]]'', as a criticism of the uncultured colonists, but during the Revolution, as the colonists began to reappropriate the label ''yankee'' as a point of pride, they likewise reappropriated the song, altering verses, and turning it into a patriotic anthem. The term is now widely used as an affectionate nickname for Americans in general.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://www.slate.com/blogs/lexicon_valley/2013/11/05/dude_etymology_of_the_word_is_traced_to_doodle_as_in_yankee_doodle_dandy.html|title = Mystery Solved: The Etymology of Dude|date = 5 Nov 2013|access-date = 10 Aug 2015|website = Slate|publisher = The Slate Group|last = Okrent|first = Arika}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 1850s in the United States, a secretive political party was derisively dubbed the [[Know Nothing]] party, based on their penchant for saying "I know nothing" when asked for details by outsiders; this became the common name for the party. It eventually became a popular name, sufficiently so that consumer products like tea, candy, and even a freighter were branded with the name.&lt;ref&gt;William E. Gienapp. "Salmon P. Chase, Nativism, and the Formation of the Republican Party in Ohio", pp. 22, 24. ''Ohio History'', p. 93.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Anarchism]] was mostly a derogatory term used by opponents of collectivist forms of socialism, until it was adopted by the anarchist movement in the late 1800s.&lt;ref&gt;Baker, Zoe (2023). "Means And Ends: The Revolutionary Practice of Anarchism In Europe And The United States". AK Press. p. 30&lt;/ref&gt;

During the [[2016 United States presidential election]], [[Hillary Clinton]] referred to some Trump supporters as a "[[Basket of deplorables]]". Many Trump supporters endorsed the phrase.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.usatoday.com/story/news/politics/onpolitics/2016/09/12/deplorable-and-proud-some-trump-supporters-embrace-label/90290760/|title = 'Deplorable' and proud: Some Trump supporters embrace the label| website=[[USA Today]] }}&lt;/ref&gt; Donald Trump also played the song "[[Do You Hear the People Sing?]]" from the musical ''[[Les Misérables (musical)|Les Misérables]]'' as an introduction to one of his rallies, using a graphic captioned "Les Deplorables".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.businessinsider.com/trump-les-miserables-deplorables-miami-2016-9|title = Trump walks onstage to theme of 'Les Miserables,' greets 'deplorables' at his Miami rally| website=[[Business Insider]] }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite magazine|url=https://ew.com/article/2016/09/16/donald-trump-les-mis-deplorables/|title = Donald Trump Enters Stage to 'Les Mis' Theme, Welcomes 'Deplorables'| magazine=[[Entertainment Weekly]] }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Subsequently, Trump called Clinton a "[[nasty woman]]" during the final presidential debate, resulting in that expression being described as a "rallying cry" for women.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Women Reclaim 'Nasty Woman' as Their Own Rallying Cry |url=https://www.globalcitizen.org/en/content/aghast-at-trump-women-reclaim-nasty-women-as-their/ |access-date=2020-12-15 |website=Global Citizen |date=21 October 2016 |language=en }}&lt;/ref&gt;  It was soon featured on merchandise and used by Clinton's campaign surrogates.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Hatch|first=Jenavieve|date=2016-10-20|title=18 Perfect Pieces Of Merch For The Nasty Woman In All Of Us|url=https://www.huffpost.com/entry/18-perfect-pieces-of-merch-for-the-nasty-woman-in-all-of-us_n_5807c5c4e4b0b994d4c3705c|access-date=2020-12-15|website=HuffPost|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Clinton seizes upon 'nasty woman' as Trump takes verbal self-destruction to new heights |url=https://www.washingtontimes.com/news/2016/oct/26/hillary-clinton-seizes-upon-nasty-woman-as-trump-t/ |access-date=2020-12-15 |website=The Washington Times| language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;
===Religion===
One of the older examples of successful reclaiming is the term ''[[Jesuit]]'' to refer to members of the [[Society of Jesus]]. This was originally a derogatory term referring to people who too readily invoked the name of [[Jesus]] in their politics, but which members of the Society adopted over time for themselves, so that the word came to refer exclusively to them, and generally in a positive or neutral sense,&lt;ref&gt;{{CathEncy|wstitle= Society of Jesus |volume= 14 |last= Pollen |first= John Hungerford |author-link= John Hungerford Pollen (Jesuit) |short=1 }}&lt;/ref&gt; even though the term "Jesuitical" is derived from the Society of Jesus and is used to mean things like: manipulative, conspiring, treacherous, capable of intellectually justifying anything by convoluted reasoning.&lt;ref name="Peschier2005"&gt;{{cite book|last=Peschier|first=D.|title=Nineteenth-Century Anti-Catholic Discourses: The Case of Charlotte Brontë|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=iV2CDAAAQBAJ&amp;q=Jesuitical&amp;pg=PA49|date=21 June 2005|publisher=Palgrave Macmillan|location=New York, NY|isbn=978-0-230-50502-5|page=49}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Stevenson2010"&gt;{{cite book|last=Stevenson|first=Angus|title=Oxford Dictionary of English|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=anecAQAAQBAJ&amp;q=Jesuitical&amp;pg=PA940|date=19 August 2010|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=Oxford, UK|isbn=978-0-19-957112-3|page=940}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Aikio"&gt;{{cite book|last1=Aikio|first1=Annukka|last2=Vornanen|first2=Rauni|title=Uusi sivistyssanakirja|date=1982|publisher=Otava|ref=Aikio|language=fi}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="March1906"&gt;{{cite book|last=March|first=Francis Andrew|title=A Thesaurus Dictionary of the English Language Designed to Suggest Immediately Any Desired Word Needed to Express Exactly a Given Idea|url=https://archive.org/details/thesaurusdiction00marcrich|quote=Jesuitical.|year=1906|publisher=Historical Publishing Company|location=Philadelphia, PA|page=[https://archive.org/details/thesaurusdiction00marcrich/page/1089 1089]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Other examples can be found in the origins of [[Methodism]]; early members were originally mocked for their "methodical" and rule-driven religious devotion, founder [[John Wesley]] embraced the term for his movement.&lt;ref name="Atkins-2010"&gt;{{cite book |last=Atkins |first=Martyn |url=http://www.methodist.org.uk/static/deepeningdiscipleship/discipleshipandmethodistsmatkins.pdf |title=Discipleship... and the people called Methodists |publisher=The Methodist Church in Britain |date=2010 |page=9 |asin=B006OA0XRU |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150315234625/http://methodist.org.uk/static/deepeningdiscipleship/discipleshipandmethodistsmatkins.pdf |archive-date=2015-03-15 |quote=...to be a ‘Methodist’ was originally a term of ridicule because of the zeal and rigour with which they pursued a life of holiness and sought to be the best disciples of Christ they could.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Members of the [[Religious Society of Friends]] were termed ''Quakers'' as an epithet, but took up the term themselves. Similarly, the term [[Protestant]] was originally a derogatory term, and more recently the term [[pagan]] has been subject to a similar change in meaning.&lt;ref name=CG&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Coles|first=Gregory|date=2016|title=EMERGING VOICES: The exorcism of language: Reclaimed derogatory terms and their limits|journal=College English|volume=78|issue=5|pages=424–446|id={{ProQuest|1787109531}}}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Race, ethnicity, and nationality===
To a lesser extent, and more controversially among the groups referred to, many racial, ethnic, and class terms have been reappropriated:

*[[Baster]], the name is derived from bastaard, the Dutch word for "bastard". They are a Southern African ethnic group descended from White European men and Black African women. The Basters reappropriated it as a "proud name", claiming their ancestry and history.&lt;ref name="lang"&gt;{{cite journal|title=The Population Development of the Rehoboth Basters |first=Hartmut|last=Lang|journal=Anthropos|volume= 93 |issue= 4./6 |date=1998 |pages=381–391|jstor=40464838}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Black people|Black]], ''[[negro]]'', ''[[nigga]]'', or ''[[nigger]]'' by [[African Americans]]&lt;ref name="Slurs2"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Kennedy-2008"&gt;{{cite book |last=Kennedy |first=Randall  |title=Nigger: The Strange Career of a Troublesome Word |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=VgVzXgUxFB4C&amp;pg=PR17 |access-date=16 January 2018 |date=18 December 2008 |publisher=Knopf Doubleday Publishing Group |isbn=978-0-307-53891-8 |page=xvii |oclc=838223786}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Curry, used a derogatory term for [[South Asian ethnic groups|South Asians]] (often in conjunction with [[List of ethnic slurs|muncher]] or slurper), reappropriated by some members of the South Asian expatriate or [[American-Born Confused Desi]] community.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2018/12/11/world/australia/subtle-asian-traits-facebook-group.html|title=How 'Subtle Asian Traits' Became a Global Hit|last=Kwai|first=Isabella|date=2018-12-11|work=The New York Times|access-date=2019-10-23|language=en-US|issn=0362-4331}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Jew (word)|Jew]] by the [[Jewish people]] (the word used to be seen as pejorative in English).&lt;ref name="MillerMorris2010"&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=elfiE2XUUXgC&amp;pg=PA153|title=Radical Poetics and Secular Jewish Culture|author1=Stephen Paul Miller|first2=Daniel|last2=Morris|publisher=University of Alabama Press|year=2010|isbn=978-0-8173-5563-0|page=153}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Weiss1998"&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=kRO6VMDXQloC&amp;pg=PA66|title=Gertrude Stein and Richard Wright: The Poetics and Politics of Modernism|author=M. Lynn Weiss|publisher=Univ. Press of Mississippi|year=1998|isbn=978-1-60473-188-0|page=66}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=akwmAQAAIAAJ|title=Jewish Language Review|publisher=Association for the Study of Jewish Languages|year=1988|page=416}}&lt;/ref&gt; That process is still not complete in some Slavic languages, where the word [[Zhyd]] can still be seen as pejorative.&lt;ref name="timesofisrael"&gt;Winer, Stuart. 19 December 2012. "[http://www.timesofisrael.com/ukraine-okays-slur-zhyd-for-jews/ Ukraine okays 'zhyd' slur for Jews]." ''The Times of Israel''.&lt;/ref&gt;
* ''[[Kugel (slang)|Kugel]]'', playful [[South African English]] slang for a materialistic young woman, originally was a derogatory term used by the elder generation of [[South African Jews]] for a young Jewish woman who forsook traditional Jewish dress values for those of the ostentatiously wealthy and became overly materialistic and overgroomed. The term was then reclaimed by those women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Sarah Britten |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=sZTLigR2t5UC&amp;pg=PT132 |title=The Art of the South African Insult |year=2006 |publisher=30 degrees South Publishers |pages=198–199 |isbn=978-1920143053 |access-date=July 2, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* ''[[Peckerwood]]'', originally black slang in the Southern United States for poor whites, reclaimed by white prison gangs&lt;ref name="Allen-1983"&gt;{{cite book |last=Allen |first=Irving L.  |title=The Language of Ethnic Conflict: Social Organization and Lexical Culture |url=https://archive.org/details/languageofethnic0000alle |url-access=registration |access-date=16 January 2018 |year=1983 |publisher=Columbia University Press |isbn=978-0-231-05557-4 |page=[https://archive.org/details/languageofethnic0000alle/page/127 127] |oclc=469875261}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Carceral-2006"&gt;{{cite book |last1=Carceral |first1=K.C.  |last2=Bernard |first2=Thomas J |title=Prison, Inc: A Convict Exposes Life Inside a Private Prison |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=UbcglPvW_5oC&amp;pg=PA118 |access-date=16 January 2018 |series=Alternative criminology series |year=2006 |publisher=NYU Press |location=New York |isbn=978-0-8147-9954-3 |page=118 |oclc=748855316}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web  |title=Peckerwood {{!}} Hate Symbols Database {{!}} ADL  |author=&lt;!--staff writers, no byline--&gt;  |url=https://www.adl.org/education/references/hate-symbols/peckerwood  |website=ADL  |publisher=Anti-Defamation League  |access-date=16 January 2018  }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*''[[Smoggie]]'', originally a derogatory term for people from the [[North East England]] town of [[Middlesbrough]], in reference to the town's notorious [[industrial pollution]], now commonly used in self-identification.&lt;ref name="Sarah McKeown"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.macmillandictionaryblog.com/smoggy|title=Ich bin ein Smoggy: reclaiming regional pride|last=McKeown|first=Sarah|date=22 June 2009|publisher=Macmillan Dictionary Blog|access-date=30 September 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* ''[[White trash]]'', a classist slur referring to [[poor white]] people, reappropriated by some in the [[Southern United States|Southern states]] of the United States of America as a cultural symbol and badge of pride&lt;ref name="Griffin-2012"&gt;{{cite book |last1=Griffin |first1=Larry J.  |last2=Hargis |first2=Peggy G.  |last3=Wilson |first3=Charles Reagan  |title=The New Encyclopedia of Southern Culture  |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=GKNULfdTxXkC&amp;pg=PA370 |access-date=16 January 2018 |volume=20: Social Class |date=1 July 2012 |publisher=Univ of North Carolina Press |isbn=978-0-8078-8254-2 |page=370 |oclc=852835385}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Galinsky-2015"&gt;{{cite book |last1=Galinsky |first1=Adam |last2=Schweitzer |first2=Maurice  |title=Friend &amp; Foe: When to Cooperate, When to Compete, and How to Succeed at Both |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=gd4MBgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA129 |access-date=16 January 2018 |date=29 September 2015 |publisher=Crown Publishing Group |location=New York |isbn=978-0-307-72025-2 |page=129 |oclc=919338995 |quote=In a movie (''8 Mile''), Eminem declares, 'I'm a piece of white trash; I say it proudly.'}}&lt;/ref&gt; - however this reappropriation has not been as evident in mainstream [[British English]] syntax where it is used in a more condescending or [[Sarcasm|sarcastic]] manner.
* ''[[Wog]]'' by Australians of [[Greek Australians|Greek]], [[Italian Australians|Italian]], [[Arab Australians|Arab]] or [[Turkish Australians|Turkish]] descent.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2005/oct/13/australia.andrewclark|title=A bad word made good|first=Andrew|last=Clark|date=12 October 2005|website=The Guardian}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Disability===

* ''cripple'', ''crip'', ''gimp'' by people with disabilities.&lt;ref name="Baglieri-2012"&gt;{{cite book |last1=Baglieri |first1=Susan  |last2=Shapiro |first2=Arthur  |title=Disability Studies and the Inclusive Classroom: Critical Practices for Creating Least Restrictive Attitudes |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=tkaC2eYg-eUC&amp;pg=PA49 |access-date=16 January 2018 |volume=New York |year=2012 |publisher=[[Routledge]] |isbn=978-0-415-99372-2 |page=49 |oclc=768335668}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Mad Pride|''mad'' by people with mental disorders]]

===Art movements===
* ''[[Impressionists]]'' In 1874 during their first independent art show, critic [[Louis Leroy]] penned a hostile review of the show in ''[[Le Charivari]]'' newspaper under the title "The Exhibition of the Impression-ists". In particular he used the painting ''[[Impression, Sunrise|Impression, soleil levant]]'' by [[Claude Monet]] to ridicule the painters for their lack of seriousness preferring to paint "fleeting impressions of the moment" rather than allegorical or ultra-realist themes.&lt;ref name="Ciganiero-2014"&gt;{{cite web |last=Cigainero |first=Jake |date=October 29, 2014 |title=Dating a Seminal Painting Paris Exhibition Traces Origins of Monet's 'Impression, Sunrise' |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2014/10/23/arts/international/paris-exhibition-traces-origins-of-monets-impression-sunrise.html |work=The New York Times |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20141115085344/http://www.nytimes.com/2014/10/23/arts/international/paris-exhibition-traces-origins-of-monets-impression-sunrise.html |archive-date=2014-11-15 |access-date=2015-12-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="AsselinLamoureux2008"&gt;{{cite book|first1=Olivier|last1=Asselin|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=hXw1kI1yt7wC&amp;pg=PA356|title=Precarious Visualities: New Perspectives on Identification in Contemporary Art and Visual Culture|first2=Johanne|last2=Lamoureux|first3=Christine|last3=Ross|date=21 July 2008|publisher=McGill-Queen's Press - MQUP|isbn=978-0-7735-7439-7|pages=356–}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* ''[[Stuckism]]'' is an international [[art movement]] founded in 1999; its members produce [[figurative art]]. [[Tracey Emin]], one of the [[Young British Artists]] known for their [[conceptual art]], accused her then-boyfriend of lack of imagination or reach, of being "stuck". He took on the term.&lt;ref name="milner7"&gt;[[Charles Thomson (artist)|Thomson, Charles]] (August 2004), "A Stuckist on Stuckism: Stella Vine", from: Ed. Frank Milner (2004), ''The Stuckists Punk Victorian'', pp. 7–9, [[National Museums Liverpool]], {{ISBN|1-902700-27-9}}. Available online at [http://www.stuckism.com/Walker/AStuckistOnStuckism.html#TwoStarts "The Two Starts of Stuckism"] and [http://www.stuckism.com/Walker/AStuckistOnStuckism.html#Virtual "The Virtual Stuckists"] on stuckism.com.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Feminism ===
Words some feminist activists have argued should be reclaimed include:

*[[Bitch (slang)|bitch]]&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{Citation|last1=Groom|first1=Carla|chapter=The reappropriation of stigmatizing labels: implications for social identity|date=2003-01-01|volume=5|pages=221–256|series=Research on Managing Groups and Teams|publisher=Emerald Group Publishing Limited|doi=10.1016/s1534-0856(02)05009-0|quote=reappropriation, the process of taking possession of a slur previously used exclusively by dominant groups to reinforce a stigmatized group’s lesser status|last2=Bodenhausen|first2=Galen V|last3=Galinsky|first3=Adam D|last4=Hugenberg|first4=Kurt|title=Identity Issues in Groups|isbn=0-7623-0951-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[cunt]]&lt;ref name=":02" /&gt;
*[[slut]]&lt;ref&gt;[[Brooke Candy|Candy, Brooke]] (2013). "Das Me". "You say that I'm a slut, It ain't your business who I'm fucking with, A dude could fuck 3 bitches and they'd say that he's the man, But I get it in with twins, she's a whore, That's what they saying, It's time to take the word back 'Slut' is now a compliment, A sexy-ass female who running shit and confident, Lady who on top of it, a female with a sex drive."&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[lady]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Reid Boyd|first1=Elizabeth|title=Lady: A Feminist Four Letter Word? |journal=Women and Language|date=2012|volume=35|issue=2|pages=35–52|url=https://www.academia.edu/9400071}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Détournement]], a similar strategy used for images
* [[Dysphemism|Dysphemism treadmill]], the process by which offensive terms can become acceptable without deliberate intervention
* [[Gaysper]], reappropriated LGBT symbol

* [[Geographical renaming]], which can include reclaiming an earlier pre-colonial name

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

[[Category:Sociolinguistics]]
[[Category:Historical linguistics]]
[[Category:Stereotypes]]
[[Category:Semantics]]
[[Category:Political terminology]]
[[Category:Linguistic controversies]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>