<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20131118130412|582200051" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="277978" pageid="277978" ns="0" title="Ethnic joke"><revisions><rev timestamp="2013-11-18T13:19:16Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Multiple issues|
{{expert-subject|date=November 2008}}
{{refimprove|date=November 2008}}
}}

An '''ethnic joke''' is a remark attempting humour relating to an ethnic, racial or cultural group, often referring to a [[ethnic stereotype|stereotype]] of the group in question for its punchline.

==History==

Ethnic jokes have been around since people first noticed they were different from one another, and ethnocentrism and a sense of ethnic identity appeared. Jokes feed upon difference and distinctions (not only ethnic, of course) and if one of the functions of ethnic jokes is to ridicule and depreciate these in-out groups, another function is to maintain and strengthen a sense of one’s identity in some in-group. It may be that ethnic humour helps us deal with hostility verbally instead of physically, but these slurs also reinforce our stereotypes and sometimes lead to calls for violence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| url=http://books.google.co.in/books?id=aZkRJJnc6BUC&amp;pg=PA57&amp;dq=Davies,+Christie.+Ethnic+Humor&amp;source=gbs_toc_r&amp;cad=0_0#PPA67,M1 |title=An Anatomy of Humor}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ethnic jokes are often considered to be offensive and as a form of [[hate speech]].{{Citation needed|date=February 2009}} Perceived as such, they may sometimes be referred to as '''race jokes''', or '''racist jokes'''.{{Citation needed|date=May 2010}}

But in other cases the ethnic jokes are addressed against those who are historically seen as the aggressors, like the multiple jokes published in Mexico about the Americans (also called [[Gringo#Meanings|gringos]] there).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |url=http://books.google.com.mx/books?id=i8f5jo8gIDgC&amp;q=americanos+sana#v=snippet&amp;q=americanos%20sana&amp;f=false |title=Americans, healthy people. |publisher=Selector, Mexico}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |url=http://books.google.com.mx/books?id=7ecupfC7XwIC&amp;q=guerra+mueran+gringos#v=snippet&amp;q=guerra%20mueran%20gringos&amp;f=false |title=The most popular Mexican slogan in WWII. |publisher=Selector, Mexico}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |url=http://books.google.com.mx/books?id=s8tvM701ZbQC&amp;q=gringo+patada+#v=snippet&amp;q=gringo%20patada&amp;f=false |title=Mexican kicking American testicles |publisher=Selector, Mexico}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |url=http://books.google.com.mx/books?id=i5jICGTri-AC&amp;q=paisa+gringo+gargajo+cara#v=snippet&amp;q=paisa%20gringo%20gargajo%20cara&amp;f=false |title=Mexican spitting in American face |publisher=Selector, Mexico}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |url=http://books.google.com.mx/books?id=YAwk0VJ1GfcC&amp;q=gringo+lechita+dormir#v=snippet&amp;q=gringo%20lechita%20dormir&amp;f=false |title=You drink your milk and go to sleep |publisher=Selector, Mexico}}&lt;/ref&gt; Similar jokes have also been published in [[Barcelona]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |url=http://books.google.com.mx/books?id=tOpawFXETKgC&amp;q=gringos+estados+unidos#v=onepage&amp;q=gringos%20estados%20unidos&amp;f=false |title=The best politically incorrect jokes |publisher=Grasindo, Barcelona}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, [[Jewish people|Jew]] jokes and [[Italian American]] jokes in the USA have generated controversy on the level of how offensive they can be, though not as politically charged than, say, [[African American]] or black jokes told by non-blacks in the USA are viewed as rude, immoral and socially unacceptable. {{Citation needed|date=May 2010}}

As public awareness of racism has increased, racial and ethnic jokes have become increasingly socially unacceptable in recent years, and have become socially [[taboo]] to tell in public in many regions. This can however, depend on who is telling the joke. For example, it may be deemed offensive for a white person to make a joke about Asians, whereas it would be more acceptable for an Asian to make a similar joke about their own culture, or an Asian make a joke about white people can be variously funny or offending to some extent. Many [[comedians]] from diverse ethnic backgrounds do this on a regular basis, about whites, other groups and themselves. 

It is sometimes held that such [[stereotypes]] must contain a grain of truth; research suggests that this is most often not the case.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/9598717/|title=Science gets the last laugh on ethnic jokes|publisher=MSNBC}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, it is claimed by some that ethnic jokes have a basis in fact,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/1972565.stm|title=Why do people find racist jokes funny?|publisher=[[BBC News]]|date=2002-05-07|accessdate=2009-01-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; and some ethnic jokes deliberately try to prove their point, for instance:

{{cquote2|Q : How does every ethnic joke start?&lt;br&gt;A : With a look over your shoulder.}}

When talking about ethnic humour, distinctions are sometimes made as to whether the humour comes from the inside or the outside, the idea being that when self-mocking humour comes from the inside, it pushes out the boundaries of acceptable or expected behaviours by making fun of one or more of the group characteristics known to the insider. Complimentary humour coming from the inside works to increase group pride and satisfaction. In contrast, jokes coming from the outside are more likely to be critical or insulting. And even if they are no more critical than insider jokes, they are viewed more negatively, as their effect is to tighten the boundaries or freeze the stereotypes because the outsider is not in a position to bring about group change. What these distinctions ignore is that insult humour is only one kind of joking.

Most of the researchers like Davies and Leon Rappoport have argued that ethnic jokes do not propagate ethnic stereotypes, but are often a way of positive interaction between communities.{{citation needed|date=September 2012}}

Other examples : In [[Costa Rica]], there are [[Nicaragua]]n jokes, due to the influx of Nicaraguan immigrants (often illegal) looking for jobs. And  [[Mexican people|Mexican]] jokes in the USA remain popular, despite social protest by [[Mexican American]]s and immigrant rights groups. In France, jokes about Belgian people,{{citation needed|date=September 2012}} in Quebec, about inhabitants of [[Drummondville]],{{citation needed|date=September 2012}} in Germany, about people of [[East Frisia]]{{citation needed|date=September 2012}}, in Austria, about people of the [[Burgenland]] state,{{citation needed|date=September 2012}} in Syria, about inhabitants of [[Homs]].{{citation needed|date=September 2012}}

==Theory of ethnic humor==

The predominant and most widely known theory of ethnic humor attempts to discover social regularities in the anecdote traditions of different countries by contextually describing jokes. Professor [[Christie Davies]], author of this theory, has posed the main arguments in his article ''Ethnic Jokes, Moral Values and Social Boundaries'', published in 1982. His approach is based on [[Victor Raskin]]'s (1985) [[Semantic Script Theory of Humor]] (SSTH), or to be more precise, on the arguments connected with ethnic humor on binary oppositions. While Raskin merely describes the main binary oppositions providing examples mostly from the [[Jewish humor]]), Davies explores the situations where the scripts apply; for example, he has discovered that the most common opposition, stupid/clever, is applied under particular circumstances in the social reality of two ethnic groups concerned.

Davies in his monograph published in 1990 has surmised that "Jokes in every country (or reasonably homogeneous cultural and linguistic domain) have certain targets for stupidity jokes - people who dwell on the edge of that nation or domain and who are perceived as culturally ambiguous by the dominant people of the center. In addition, they will likely be rustic people or immigrants in search of unskilled and low-prestige manual work. They are to a great extent similar to the joke-tellers themselves, share the same cultural background or even speak a similar or identical language." According to Davies, ethnic jokes are centered around the three main themes of stupidity, canniness and sexual behavior.

Davies is featured in the 2010 documentary film, ''Polack'', exploring the source of the [[Polish joke]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.polackthefilm.com/ website for ''Polack'', 2010 documentary]&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Allport's Scale]]
* [[An Englishman, an Irishman and a Scotsman]]
* [[Jewish humour]]
* [[Black stereotypes]]
* [[Russell Peters]], Indo-Canadian comedian for his off-color routines on various ethnicities.
* [[Margaret Cho]], American comedian of Korean descent known for self-humor of [[Koreans]] and [[Asian Americans]]
* [[Sardarji joke]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}
*Davies, Christie. ''Ethnic Humor Around the World''. Bloomington: Indiana University Press, 1990, ISBN 0-253-31655-3
*Draitser, Emil. ''Taking Penguins to the Movies:: Ethnic Humor in Russia''. Detroit: Wayne State University Press, 1998. ISBN 0-8143-2327-8.
*{{cite web|url=http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/AJS/journal/issues/v108n6/108627/108627.html | publisher=American Journal of Sociology | title = Book review: ''The Mirth of Nations'' | author=Charles Jaret}}
* Leon Rappoport. ''Punchlines: The Case for Racial, Ethnic, and Gender Humor'', Greenwood Publishing Group, 2005 [http://books.google.co.in/books?id=P3HkmPhf2mYC&amp;dq=Davies,+Christie.+Ethnic+Humor&amp;source=gbs_summary_s&amp;cad=0].
* Henry Mitchell, "Ethnic Humor Around the World", National Review, June 24, 1991 [http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m1282/is_n11_v43/ai_10874371?tag=content;col1]
* Arthur Asa Burger, ''An anatomy of humor'' [http://books.google.co.in/books?id=aZkRJJnc6BUC&amp;pg=PA57&amp;dq=Davies,+Christie.+Ethnic+Humor&amp;source=gbs_toc_r&amp;cad=0_0#PPA67,M1].

==External links==
*[https://pi.library.yorku.ca/ojs/index.php/soi/article/view/8011/7167 Identity is a Joking Matter: Intergroup Humor in Bosnia]
*[http://goliath.ecnext.com/coms2/gi_0199-5991337/Just-how-ethnic-is-ethnic.html Just how ethnic is ethnic humour?]
* [http://www.socresonline.org.uk/17/3/reviews/1.html Book review of  Simon Weaver's doctoral thesis: ''The Rhetoric of Racist Humour'' (Reviewed  by N Nikoghosyan)]
* [http://www2.le.ac.uk/offices/press/press-releases/2012/february/when-racist-jokes-aren2019t-a-laughing-matter-2013-new-study ''When racist jokes aren’t a laughing matter – new study'' University of Leicester's summary of Dr Weaver's theories in his dissertation ''The Rhetoric of Racist Humour'']

[[Category:Jokes based on national and racial stereotypes]]
[[Category:Ethnic humor| ]]

[[sv:Etniska skämt]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>