<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20071107141535|169868084" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="277978" pageid="277978" ns="0" title="Ethnic joke"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-11-09T19:48:23Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{expert-subject|Sociology}}
{{expert-subject|Comedy}}

'''Ethnic jokes''' are [[joke]]s that exploit [[ethnic stereotypes]].  They are often [[racist]] and frequently considered offensive.  

For example, the [[Briton|British]] tell jokes starting "[[An Englishman, an Irishman and a Scotsman]]..." which exploit the supposed [[parsimony]] of the [[Scottish people|Scot]], stupidity of the [[Irish people|Irish]], or some combination. It is sometimes held that such [[stereotypes]] must contain a grain of truth; research suggests that this is not the case.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/9598717/|title=Science gets the last laugh on ethnic jokes|publisher=MSNBC}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Ethnicity|Ethnic]] jokes are often aimed at [[minorities]] within countries, or peoples from neighboring countries. A common ethnic joke format is the "stupid person" joke, where the [[stock character]] who is the butt of the joke belongs to an ethnic group singled out for abuse. Such jokes are often interchangeable, with the [[stigma|stigmatized]] "stupid" group varying from country to country, and region to region. For example, the English tell such jokes about the Irish, [[Brazil|Brazilians]] tell them about the [[Portuguese]], and so on. In other ethnic jokes, the targeted ethnic group is one that has historically been associated with the privileged ruling class, as in the "van der Merwe" jokes of [[South Africa]], which make fun of [[Afrikaner]]s (van der Merwe being a stereotypical Dutch name).

Ethnic jokes come and go with [[social change]], particularly with waves of [[immigration]] from one country to another; for example, [[Poland|Polish]] jokes, once common in the [[United States]] during widespread Polish immigration, are now little used{{Fact|date=June 2007}}, as Polish and other [[Eastern Europe|Eastern European]] immigrants have long since been absorbed into the large community. Similarly, Irish jokes have become far less common in the [[United Kingdom]] as the [[social status]] of Irish people has risen with increased [[wealth]] in Ireland, the consequent reduction in Irish [[itinerant labor]], and the absorption of Irish people into the community; Irish people in England are now as likely to be accountants or lawyers as building laborers.

Members of particular ethnic groups may often tell [[self-deprecating]] jokes about their own group; for example, [[Jewish jokes]] are popular among Jews{{Fact|date=June 2007}}, and [[British humor]] is often self-deprecating{{Fact|date=June 2007}}. In general, members of groups telling jokes "against" their own group is regarded as more socially acceptable than members of other groups telling the same jokes.{{Fact|date=June 2007}} For example, the acts of many Black American [[comedian|comedians]] feature jokes that would be regarded as unforgivably [[racism|racist]] if told by a non-Black comedian.

At their most offensive, ethnic jokes depict their targets as being inherently subhuman, criminal or depraved{{Fact|date=June 2007}}. Such jokes are usually explicitly, rather than implicitly, racist, often describing their subjects using [[ethnic slur]]s, and are generally regarded as [[hate speech]].{{Fact|date=June 2007}} 

People with different [[skin color]] are particularly singled out for offensive jokes, [[Black people]] being a particularly common target in many countries. In England, people of [[India]]n, [[Pakistan|Pakistani]] and [[Bangladesh|Bangladeshi]] descent, who are a substantial [[minority group]] in that country, are the target of similar jokes. [[Jews]] are also a common target of ethnic jokes. 

As public awareness of racism has increased, racial and ethnic jokes have become increasingly socially unacceptable in recent years, and have become socially [[taboo]] to tell in public in many countries. 

A closely related topic is the telling of jokes about people with [[disability|disabilities]], such as jokes making fun of the [[mentally ill]], which often mirrors that of racist jokes.  The same can be said for jokes about [[gays|gays]].

In an effort to presereve ethnic humor while not targeting real ethnic groups, some people coined the term "[[Yougarian]]," from [[Yugoslavia]]n and [[Hungarian]]. One such writer was [[Al Boliska]], author of the joke book ''Wipeouts!'' Others, such as Isaac Asimov, would use [[Ruritania]] as the butt of ethnic jokes based on outright slurs.

== See also ==
* [[Allport's Scale]]
* [[Sardarji jokes]]

== References ==
&lt;references/&gt;

== External links ==
* {{cite web|url=http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/AJS/journal/issues/v108n6/108627/108627.html | publisher=American Journal of Sociology | title = Book review: The Mirth of Nations | author=Charles Jaret}}

[[ja:エスニックジョーク]]

[[Category:Ethnic comedy|*]]
[[Category:Racism]]
[[Category:Stereotypes|*]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>