<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20081110151359|250880288" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="277978" pageid="277978" ns="0" title="Ethnic joke"><revisions><rev timestamp="2008-11-10T15:26:15Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Expert-subject|Sociology|date=November 2008}}
{{Expert-subject|Comedy|date=November 2008}}

'''Ethnic jokes''', sometimes referred to as '''race jokes''', or '''racist jokes''' are [[joke]]s that exploit [[ethnic stereotypes]]. They are often considered to be offensive and as a form of [[hate speech]], though they still remain popular. 

Ethnic jokes come and go with [[social change]], particularly with waves of [[immigration]] from one country to another; for example, [[Poland|Polish]] jokes, once common in the [[United States]] during widespread Polish immigration, are now little used{{Fact|date=June 2007}}, as Polish and other [[Eastern Europe]]an immigrants have long since been absorbed into the large community. Similarly, Irish jokes have become far less common in the [[United Kingdom]] as the [[social status]] of Irish people has risen with increased [[wealth]] in Ireland, the consequent reduction in Irish itinerant labor, and the absorption of Irish people into the community. As public awareness of racism has increased, racial and ethnic jokes have become increasingly socially unacceptable in recent years, and have become socially [[taboo]] to tell in public in many regions.

It is sometimes held that such [[stereotypes]] must contain a grain of truth; research suggests that this is most often not the case.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/9598717/|title=Science gets the last laugh on ethnic jokes|publisher=MSNBC}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, it is claimed by some that ethnic jokes have a basis in fact&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/1972565.stm&lt;/ref&gt;, and some ethnic jokes deliberately try to prove their point, for instance: 

{{cquote2|Q : How does every ethnic joke start ? &lt;br/&gt; A : With a look over your shoulder }}

==Racial targets==
[[Ethnicity|Ethnic]] jokes are often aimed at [[minorities]] within certain regions, or peoples from neighboring areas. A common ethnic joke format is the "stupid person" joke, where the [[stock character]], who is the butt of the joke, belongs to an ethnic group singled out for abuse. Such jokes are often interchangeable, with the [[stigma]]tized group varying from region to region (e.g. the English tell such jokes about the Irish, [[Canada|Canadians]] about the [[Newfie]]s). In other ethnic jokes, the targeted ethnic group is one that has historically been associated with the privileged ruling class, as in the "Jan van der Merwe" jokes of [[South Africa]], which make fun of [[Afrikaner]]s (Jan van der Merwe being a stereotypical Dutch name).

People with different [[skin color]] may be singled out for offensive jokes, with [[Black people]] being an example of a common target in certain countries.{{Fact|date=April 2008}} People of [[India]]n, [[Pakistan]]i and [[Bangladesh]]i descent, who are a substantial [[minority group]] in England, are the target of similar jokes. [[Jews]] (and sometimes [[Poles]] as well) are also a common target of ethnic jokes within Europe and North America.{{Fact|date=April 2008}}

===Black Race===
Black people are often portrayed stereotypically as being very good at basketball, as well as athletically fit, though at the same time being portrayed negatively as criminals and as being lazy. 

{{cquote2|Q : Why are black people so good at basketball?&lt;br/&gt;A : They are good at running, stealing, and shooting}}

===Asian Race===
Asian people are often portrayed stereotypically as athletically inferior, [[nerd]]ish, and for males having small penises'&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.kaitaia.com/jokes/White%20Jokes/White_Jokes6.htm]&lt;/ref&gt;. One particular joke that is made to highlight the Asian races alleged nerdish behaviour is :

{{cquote2|Q : What did the Asian guy do before his blood test?  &lt;br/&gt; A : He studied}}

====Irish Nationality====
The Irish were common subjects of stereotypical ethnic jokes from the [[English people|English]] during the early and mid 20th century, when many Irish immigrants had emigrated to England. Jokes typically portrayed the Irish as being incredibly stupid and having a culture entirely revolving around [[potatoes]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.kaitaia.com/jokes/Irish%20Jokes.htm]&lt;/ref&gt;. One example which portrays both of these qualities goes thus:

{{cquote2|An Englishman, a Welshman and an Irishman crashed in Germany during the [[second world war]]. A German troop entered the house where the group was, and they hid in sacks to escape capture. The German officer, suspecting that enemies were in the house, kicked the first sack, and the Englishman shouted "woof". The German kicked the second sack, and the Welshman shouted "meow". The German kicked the third sack, and the Irishman shouted "potato"!}}

====Jews====
The Jews were stereotypically presented as being only interested in money. An example of a joke highlighting this is :

{{cquote2|Q : How do you kill two Jews? &lt;br/&gt; A : Throw some money in front of them and watch them fight to death over it.}}

===Arabs===
Arabs are often depicted in ethnic jokes as being stupid, unclean or as Islamic extremists.

==Other targets==
A closely related topic is the telling of jokes about people with [[disability|disabilities]], such as jokes making fun of the [[mentally ill]], which often mirrors that of racist jokes. The same can be said for jokes about [[homosexuals]], the [[obese]], and people of a certain [[gender]].

===Roman Catholics===
In stereotypical jokes, Roman Catholic priests are often depicted as [[paedophiles]]. For instance;

{{cquote2|Q : How do you kill two Catholic priests ? &lt;br/&gt; A : Throw a baby in the middle of them and watch them fight to death over it }}

===Muslims===
In jokes, Muslims are often depicted as being terrorists and wife-beaters. 

===Homosexuals===
Homosexuals are often portrayed in jokes about them as being sexually promiscuous and having the [[AIDS]] virus.

==See also==
* [[Allport's Scale]]
* [[Sardarji jokes]]
* [[Jewish humour]]

==References==
{{reflist}}
*Davies, Christie. Ethnic Humor Around the World. Bloomington: Indiana University Press, 1990. 
*Draitser, Emil. Taking Penguins to the Movies:: Ethnic Humor in Russia. Detroit: Wayne State University Press, 1998. ISBN 0814323278.
*{{cite web|url=http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/AJS/journal/issues/v108n6/108627/108627.html | publisher=American Journal of Sociology | title = Book review: The Mirth of Nations | author=Charles Jaret}}

==External links==
*[http://www.joke-master.com/ethnic-jokes.php Ethnic Jokes]
*[http://www.newfiejokes.net/ Newfie Jokes]
*[http://www.gr8jokes.com/list_jokes.php?cat=110 Examples of ethnic jokes]

[[Category:Ethnic comedy|*]]
[[Category:Racism]]
[[Category:Stereotypes|*]]

[[ja:エスニックジョーク]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>