<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20081115201621|252014603" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="29045" pageid="29045" ns="0" title="Speciesism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2008-11-15T20:25:59Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{alib}}
'''Speciesism''' involves assigning different values or rights to beings on the basis of their [[species]] membership.  The term was coined by British psychologist [[Richard D. Ryder]] in 1973 to denote a prejudice based on physical differences.&lt;ref name=Ryder2005&gt;Ryder, Richard. [http://www.guardian.co.uk/animalrights/story/0,11917,1543799,00.html "All beings that feel pain deserve human rights"], ''The Guardian'', August 6, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;  "I use the word 'speciesism'," he explained two years later, "to describe the widespread discrimination that is practised by man against other species [...].  Speciesism and [[racism]] both overlook or underestimate the similarities between the discriminator and those discriminated against."&lt;ref&gt;Ryder 1975, p. 16.&lt;/ref&gt;

The term is used mostly by advocates of [[animal rights]], who believe that it is [[rationality|irrational]] or morally incorrect to regard animals (some of which many people believe to be sentient&lt;ref&gt;Ryder, significantly, prefers the word "painient".  In a piece for ''[[The Guardian]]'' in 2005, entitled "All beings that feel pain deserve human rights", he wrote, "Our concern for the pain and distress of others should be extended to any 'painient' — pain-feeling — being regardless of his or her sex, class, race, religion, nationality or species.  Indeed, if [[extraterrestrial life|alien]]s from [[outer space]] turn out to be painient, or if we ever manufacture machines who are painient, then we must widen the moral circle to include them.  Painience is the only convincing basis for attributing rights or, indeed, interests to others."  (Ryder 2005)&lt;/ref&gt; beings) as mere objects or property.  The view is motivated by an acceptance of [[Darwinism]] and the logical upshot which suggests that humans as they are today would be just as speciesist towards their lesser evolved forms.&lt;ref&gt;Ryder 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;  Some [[philosophy|philosopher]]s and [[scientist]]s, however, disagree with the condemnation of speciesism, arguing that it is an acceptable position and behaviour.

Philosophers [[Tom Regan]] and [[Peter Singer]] have both argued against the human tendency to exhibit speciesism.  Regan believes that all animals have inherent rights and that we cannot assign them a lesser value because of a perceived lack of rationality, while assigning a higher value to infants and the mentally impaired solely on the grounds of their being members of the supposedly superior human species.&lt;ref&gt;Ryder has argued along similar lines: "We treat the other animals not as relatives but as unfeeling things.  We would not dream of treating our [[infant|babies]], or [[mental retardation|mentally handicapped]] adults, in these ways - yet these humans are sometimes less intelligent and less able to communicate with us than are some exploited nonhumans."&lt;/ref&gt;  Singer's philosophical arguments against speciesism are based on the principle of [[equal consideration of interests]].

== Opponents ==
[[Gary Francione]]'s position differs significantly from that of Singer, author of ''[[Animal Liberation (book)|Animal Liberation]]'' (1975).  Singer, a [[utilitarianism|utilitarian]], rejects [[moral rights]] as a general matter and, like Ryder, regards [[sentience]] as sufficient for moral status.  Singer maintains that most animals do not care about ''whether'' we kill and use them for our own purposes; they care only about ''how'' we treat them when we do use and kill them.  As a result, and despite our having laws that supposedly protect animals, Francione contends that we treat animals in ways that would be regarded as [[torture]] if only humans were involved.

[[Richard Dawkins]] touches briefly on the subject in ''[[The Blind Watchmaker]]'' and ''[[The God Delusion]]'', elucidating the Darwinian connection.  He compares former [[racism|racist]] attitudes and assumptions to their present-day speciesist counterparts.  In a chapter of former book entitled "The one true tree of life", he argues that it is not just [[zoology|zoological]] [[taxonomy]] that is saved from awkward ambiguity by the [[extinction]] of intermediate forms, but also human [[ethics]] and [[law]].  He describes discrimination against [[chimpanzee]]s thus:

{{cquote|Such is the breathtaking speciesism of our [[Christianity|Christian]]-inspired attitudes, the [[abortion]] of a single human [[zygote]] (most of them are destined to be spontaneously aborted anyway) can arouse more moral solicitude and righteous indignation than the [[vivisection]] of any number of intelligent adult chimpanzees! [...]  The only reason we can be comfortable with such a double standard is that the [[human evolution|intermediates between humans and chimps]] are all dead.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | first = Richard | last = Dawkins | authorlink = Richard Dawkins | title = The Blind Watchmaker | publisher = W. W. Norton &amp; Company, Inc. | location = New York | origyear = 1986 | year = 1996 | id = ISBN 0-393-31570-3 }}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Dawkins more recently elaborated on his personal position towards speciesism in a live discussion with Singer at The Center for Enquiry on [[December 7]], [[2007]]. &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pointofinquiry.org/richard_dawkins_science_and_the_new_atheism Richard Dawkins - Science and the New Atheism, December 7, 2007.]&lt;/ref&gt;

{{cquote|What I am doing is going along with the fact that I live in a society where meat eating is accepted as the norm, and it requires a level of social courage which I haven't yet produced to break out of that.  It's a little bit like the position which many people would have held a couple of hundred years ago over [[slavery]].  Where lots of people felt morally uneasy about slavery but went along with it because the whole economy of the [[Southern Colonies|South]] depended upon slavery.}}

David Nibert seeks to expand the field of [[sociology]] "in order to understand how social arrangements create oppressive conditions for both humans and other animals".  He compares speciesism  to racism and [[sexism]].&lt;ref&gt;''Humans and other animals: sociology's moral and intellectual challenge'' David Nibert. ''International Journal of Sociology and Social Policy''. Year:  2003  Volume:  23  Issue:  3  Page:  4 - 25.&lt;/ref&gt;

Some have suggested that simply to fight speciesism is not enough because intrinsic value of nature can be extended beyond sentient beings, termed the ethic of "libertarian extension".&lt;ref&gt;1999 The Puzzle of Ethics. London: Harper Collins. Vardy, P., and P. Grosch&lt;/ref&gt;  This belief system seeks to apply the principle of individual rights not only to all animals but also objects without a nervous system such as trees, plants and rocks.&lt;ref&gt;''IN NEED OF NEW ENVIRONMENTAL ETHICS FOR TOURISM?'' Andrew Holden. Annals of Tourism Research, Vol. 30, No. 1, pp. 94–108, 2003.

Ryder rejects this in writing that "value cannot exist in the absence of consciousness or potential consciousness.  Thus, rocks and rivers and houses have no interests and no rights of their own.  This does not mean, of course, that they are not of value to us, and to many other painients, including those who need them as habitats and who would suffer without them."  (Ryder 2005)&lt;/ref&gt;

== Proponents ==
Some philosophers and scientists defend Speciesism as an acceptable if not good behavior for humans.  [[Carl Cohen]], a Professor of Philosophy at the Residential College of the University of Michigan, writes: {{cquote|I am a speciesist. Speciesism is not merely plausible; it is essential for right conduct, because those who will not make the morally relevant distinctions among species are almost certain, in consequence, to misapprehend their true obligations. &lt;ref&gt;C. Cohen (1986) The case for the use of animals in biomedical research, The New England Journal of Medicine, Vol. 315, No. 14.&lt;/ref&gt;}} 

[[Jeffrey Alan Gray]], British psychologist and a lecturer in experimental psychology at Oxford, similarly wrote that: {{cquote|I would guess that the view that human beings matter to other human beings more than animals do is, to say the least, widespread. At any rate, I wish to defend speciesism... &lt;ref&gt;J. A. Gray (1980) In defense of speciesism, Behavioral and Brain Sciences, Vol. 13 No. 1.&lt;/ref&gt;}} 

A common theme in defending speciesism tend to be the argument that humans "have the right to compete with and exploit other species to preserve and protect the human species." &lt;ref&gt;D. Graft (1997) Against strong speciesism, Journal of Applied Philosophy, Vol.14, No. 2, &lt;/ref&gt;

== Great ape personhood ==
{{Discrimination sidebar}}
{{Main|Great Ape personhood}}
Great Ape personhood is a concept in which the attributes of the [[Great Ape]]s are deemed to merit recognition of their sentience and personhood within the law, as opposed to mere protection under [[animal cruelty]] legislation. This would cover matters such as their own best interest being taken into account in their treatment by people.&lt;ref name="rights"&gt; [http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/magazine/6505691.stm Should apes have human rights?] &lt;/ref&gt;

== Animal holocaust ==
{{main|Animal rights and the Holocaust}}
David Sztybel holds that the treatment of animals can be compared to the [[Holocaust]] in a valid and meaningful way. In his paper ''Can the Treatment of Animals Be Compared to the Holocaust?'' using a thirty-nine-point comparison Sztybel asserts that the comparison is not offensive and that it does not overlook important differences, or ignore supposed affinities between the human abuse of fellow animals, and the Nazi abuse of fellow humans. The comparison of animal treatment and the Holocaust came into the public eye with [[People for the Ethical Treatment of Animals]]' "Holocaust on your Plate" exhibit. Sztybel equates the racism of the Nazis with the speciesism inherent in eating meat, or using animal by products particularly those produced on factory farms.&lt;ref&gt;Sztybel, David ''Can the Treatment of Animals Be Compared to the Holocaust?'' Ethics &amp; the Environment - Volume 11, Number 1, Spring 2006, pp. 97-132&lt;/ref&gt; However, even among the supports of the concept of speciesism as a critical tool, such comparisons are not always supported.  Y. Michael Barilan writes that speciesism is not the same thing as "Nazi racism" because Nazi racism extolled the abuser and condemned the weaker and the abused. He describes speciesism as the recognition of rights on the basis of group membership rather than solely on the basis of moral considerations.&lt;ref&gt;''Speciesism as a precondition to justice'' Y. Michael Barilan, MD, MA. Politics and the Life Sciences Article: pp. 22–33&lt;/ref&gt;

== In fiction ==
In science fiction, speciesism takes on the idea of superiority via sentience. In such it is a galactic form of [[racism]], saying that one species is superior to another for certain reasons. In [[Star Wars]], such is a common problem that is forbidden by law, except during the "dark times". The most common variation is [[Anthropocentrism|humanocentrism]], which is basically Human Supremacy (itself similar to real life [[white supremacy]]), where supremacy is declared by being the majority. Such is challenged by another form called [[Misanthropy#Science fiction|Anti-Humanism]].

== Criticism ==
=== Philosophical ===
[[Image:Trial of Bill Burns.jpg|left|thumb|270px|A painting of the Trial of Bill Burns, showing [[Richard Martin (politician)|Richard Martin]] with the donkey in an astonished courtroom, leading to the world's first known conviction for animal cruelty, a story that delighted London's newspapers and [[music hall]]s.]]
([[Priesthood (Catholic Church)|Rev.]]) [[John Tuohey]] writes that the logic behind charges of speciesism fails to hold up, and that, although it has been popularly appealing, it is philosophically flawed. Even though the animal rights movement in the United States has been influential in slowing and in some cases stopping biomedical research involving animals, no one has offered a clear and compelling argument for the equality of species&lt;ref&gt;''Fifteen years after “Animal Liberation”: Has the animal rights movement achieved philosophical legitimacy?'' Journal of Medical Humanities. Volume 13, Number 2 / June, 1992. John Tuohey&lt;/ref&gt;. Nel Noddings has criticized Peter Singer's concept of speciesism for being too simplistic, and failing to take into account the context of species preference as concepts of racism and sexism have taken in to account the context of discrimination against humans.&lt;ref&gt;''Comment on Donovan's "Animal Rights and Feminist Theory"'' Nel Noddings Signs, Vol. 16, No. 2 (Winter, 1991), pp. 418-422&lt;/ref&gt; Some people who work for racial or sexual equality have said that comparisons between speciesism and racism or sexism are insulting,&lt;ref&gt;''[http://www.bbc.co.uk/religion/ethics/animals/rights/speciesism.shtml The ethics of speciesism]''&lt;/ref&gt; for example [[Peter Staudenmaier]] writes:
&lt;blockquote&gt;The central analogy to the civil rights movement and the women’s movement is trivializing and ahistorical. Both of those social movements were initiated and driven by members of the dispossessed and excluded groups themselves, not by benevolent men or white people acting on their behalf. Both movements were built precisely around the idea of reclaiming and reasserting a shared humanity in the face of a society that had deprived it and denied it. No civil rights activist or feminist ever argued, “We’re sentient beings too!” They argued, “We’re fully human too!” Animal liberation doctrine, far from extending this humanist impulse, directly undermines it. -Peter Staudenmaier&lt;ref&gt;''[http://www.communalism.org/Archive/5/aar.print.html Ambiguities of Animal Rights]'' Peter Staudenmaier COMMUNALISM: International Journal for a Rational Society ISSUE 5 | MARCH 2003&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Although [[Camilla Kronqvis]] sympathizes with Singer’s aims, she does not accept his arguments. She writes "To say that our morality rests on attending to somebody’s pleasure and pain, also seems to be a pretty crude description of what it is to be a moral being." And concludes "I also find it highly unlikely that a polar bear would care for my interests of leading a long, healthy life if it decided to have me for lunch, and I wonder if I would have time to present it with Singer’s arguments when it started to carry out this intention."&lt;ref&gt;''Speciesism - Arguments for Whom? '' Camilla Kronqvis. Ethics, Agency &amp; Love.&lt;/ref&gt;  Singer responds that that fact that animals are not moral agents does not prevent them from being moral patients, just as humans who are not moral agents remain moral patients, so that their ability to be harmed remains the characteristic taken into consideration.

Some more radical opponents of the idea of speciesism believe that animals exist so that humans may make use of them, be it for food, entertainment or other uses. This special status conveys [[special rights]], such as the [[right to life]], and also unique responsibilities, such as [[Stewardship (theology)|stewardship]] of the [[environment (biophysical)|environment]].

Carl Cohen argued that racism and sexism are wrong because there are no relevant differences between the sexes or races. Between people and animals however, there are significant differences, and they do not qualify for [[Kant]]ian personhood, and as such have no rights.&lt;ref&gt;The case against animal rights, Carl Cohen&lt;/ref&gt;  Animal rights advocates point out that because many humans do not qualify for Kantian personhood, and yet have rights, this cannot be a morally relevant difference.

[[Objectivism (Ayn Rand)|Objectivists]] argue that giving more rights to animals means taking rights away from thinking beings who are, unlike animals, capable of creating [[Objectivist theory of value|value]].  Animal rights advocates respond by pointing out that not all humans are capable of "creating value" by this definition of value, so if "creating value" were the morally relevant characteristic, it would still not track along the lines of species alone.  Conversely, any definition of "creating value" that included all humans would include many animals as well.

=== Religious ===
Some believers in [[human exceptionalism]] base the concept in the [[Abrahamic religion]]s, such as the verse in [[Genesis]] 1:26 "And God said, Let us make man in our image, after our likeness: and let them have dominion over the fish of the sea, and over the fowl of the air, and over the cattle, and over all the earth, and over every creeping thing that creepeth upon the earth." Animal rights advocates however argue that dominion refers to stewardship and does not demote any right to mistreat other animals. And, still others often point out the overlooking of verses 3:19-21 from Ecclesiastes, which confronts this matter directly. Some say Jonah 4:11 also re-enforces the worth of animals whilst not placing them before humans: "And should I not pity Nineveh, that great city, in which are more than one hundred and twenty thousand persons who cannot discern between their right hand and their left—and much livestock?" [[Buddhism]], despite its reputation for respect for animals, explicitly accords humans a higher status&lt;ref name = "tsos"/&gt; in the progression of [[reincarnation]]. Animals may be reincarnated as humans, but only humans can reach enlightenment.&lt;ref name="tsos"&gt;The Specter of Speciesism: Buddhist and Christian Views of Animals. By PAUL WALDAU. American Academy of Religion, Academy Series. Oxford: OXFORD UNIVERSITY PRESS, 2002.&lt;/ref&gt; However, [[Felipe Fernández-Armesto]] writes that early hunter-gatherer societies such as the [[Innu]] &lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=5eEASHGLg3MC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=hunter-gatherers,&amp;sig=L62XtDi4-08Bg3vfTek2UojmaLA#PPA53,M1 The Cambridge Encyclopedia of Hunters and Gatherers By Richard B. Lee, Richard Heywood Daly]&lt;/ref&gt; and many [[animist]] religions  have lacked a concept of humanity and have placed non human animals and plants on an equal footing with humans. &lt;ref&gt; [http://books.google.com/books?id=tFIAAAAACAAJ&amp;dq=Ideas+that+changed+the+world+by+Felipe+Fernandez+Armesto ''Ideas that changed the world'' Felipe Fernández-Armesto. human exceptionalism . Page:  138] &lt;/ref&gt;

=== Scientific ===
Others take a [[secular]] approach, such as pointing to evidence of unusual rapid evolution of the [[human brain]] and the emergence of "exceptional" [[aptitude]]s.  As one commentator put it, "Over the course of [[human history]], we have been successful in cultivating our faculties, shaping our development, and impacting upon the wider world in a deliberate fashion, quite distinct from [[evolution|evolutionary processes]].&lt;ref&gt;Starr, Sandy. ''[http://www.spiked-online.com/Articles/0000000CA855.htm What Makes Us Exceptional?]''. Spiked Science&lt;/ref&gt; Constance K. Perry asserts that the use of 'non-autonomous' animals instead of humans in risky research can be based on solid moral ground and is not necessarily speciesism.&lt;ref&gt;''A Compassionate Autonomy Alternative to Speciesism'' Constance K. Perry Volume 22, Number 3 / June, 2001 Theoretical Medicine and Bioethics&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
&lt;!-- Please avoid repeating links --&gt;
*[[Anthropocentrism]]
*[[Biocentrism]]
*[[Deep ecology]]
*[[Humanism]]
*[[Misanthropy]]

== References ==
*[[Richard D. Ryder|Ryder, Richard D.]] ''Victims of Science: The Use of [[Animal testing|Animals in Research]]''. Davis-Poynter, [[1975 in literature|1975]].
*—. "All beings that feel [[pain]] deserve [[human rights]]: [[Egalitarianism|Equality]] of the [[species]] is the logical conclusion of post-[[Charles Darwin|Darwin]] [[ethics|morality]]." ''[[The Guardian]], 6 August [[2005 in literature|2005]].

== Notes ==
{{Reflist}}

== Further reading ==
*Dunayer, Joan. 2004. ''Speciesism''. Ryce Publishing: Illinois. ISBN 0-9706475-6-5
*[http://www.rightsforanimals.org Why should anti-speciesism concern me?"], ''Rights for Animals''.
*[http://www.antispe.de/english.html Anti-speciesism ]
*''[http://www.cahiers-antispecistes.org/ Les Cahiers Antispécistes]'' (in [[French language|French]])
*''[http://www.eco.utexas.edu/Homepages/Faculty/Cleaver/wk6animals.html The Struggle for Animal Equality]''

[[Category:Animal rights]]
[[Category:Prejudices]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]

[[cs:Speciesismus]]
[[da:Speciesisme]]
[[de:Speziesismus]]
[[el:Σπισισμός]]
[[es:Especismo]]
[[fr:Antispécisme]]
[[it:Specismo]]
[[he:סוגנות]]
[[lt:Rūšizmas]]
[[nl:Speciesisme]]
[[ja:種差別]]
[[no:Spesiesisme]]
[[pl:Szowinizm gatunkowy]]
[[pt:Especismo]]
[[ru:Спесиецизм]]
[[fi:Spesismi]]
[[sv:Speciesism]]
[[tr:Türcülük]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>