<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20071112201216|171027785" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="29045" pageid="29045" ns="0" title="Speciesism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-11-14T18:59:27Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Animal liberation movement}}
'''Speciesism''' involves assigning different values or rights to beings on the basis of their [[species]] membership. The term was coined by British psychologist [[Richard D. Ryder]] in 1973 to denote a prejudice based on morally irrelevant physical differences.&lt;ref name=Ryder2005&gt;Ryder, Richard. [http://www.guardian.co.uk/animalrights/story/0,11917,1543799,00.html "All beings that feel pain deserve human rights"], ''The Guardian'', August 6, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;

The concept of speciesism is used mostly by advocates of [[animal rights]], who believe that it is [[Rationality|irrational]] or morally wrong to regard sentient beings as objects or property. Philosophers [[Tom Regan]] and [[Peter Singer]] have both argued against the human tendency to exhibit speciesism. Regan argues that all animals have inherent rights and that we cannot assign them a lesser value because of a perceived lack of rationality, while assigning a higher value to infants and the mentally impaired solely on the grounds of being members of a certain species. Singer's philosophical arguments against speciesism are based on the principle of [[equal consideration of interests]].  

==Proponents==
[[Gary L. Francione]]’s position differs significantly from that of [[Peter Singer]], author of ''[[Animal Liberation]]'' (1975).  Singer, who is a [[utilitarian]], rejects [[moral rights]] as a general matter and regards [[sentience]] as sufficient for moral status. Singer maintains that most animals do not care about ''whether'' we kill them and use them for our purposes but care only about ''how'' we treat them when we do use and kill them. As a result, despite having laws that supposedly protect animals, Francione contends that we treat animals in ways that would be regarded as [[torture]] if humans were involved.

[[Richard Dawkins]] briefly touches on the subject in ''[[The Blind Watchmaker]]'' and ''[[The God Delusion]]''. He compares former [[racist]] attitudes and assumptions to their present day speciesist counterparts. In the chapter "The one true tree of life" he argues that it is not just zoological [[classification]] that is saved from awkward ambiguity by the [[extinction]] of intermediate forms, but also human [[ethics]] and [[law]]. He describes discrimination against [[chimpanzee]]s thus:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | first = Richard | last = Dawkins | authorlink = Richard Dawkins | title = The Blind Watchmaker | publisher = W. W. Norton &amp; Company, Inc. | location = New York | origyear = 1986 | year = 1996 | id = ISBN 0-393-31570-3 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Quotation|Such is the breathtaking speciesism of our [[Christianity|Christian]]-inspired attitudes, the [[abortion]] of a single human [[zygote]] (most of them are destined to be spontaneously aborted anyway) can arouse more moral solicitude and righteous indignation than the [[vivisection]] of any number of intelligent adult chimpanzees! [...] The only reason we can be comfortable with such a double standard is that the [[human evolution|intermediates between humans and chimps]] are all dead.}}

David Nibert seeks to expand the field of sociology "...in order to understand how social arrangements create oppressive conditions for both humans and other animals..."  He compares speciesism  to [[racism]] and [[sexism]]. &lt;ref&gt;''Humans and other animals: sociology’s moral and intellectual challenge'' David Nibert. International Journal of Sociology and Social Policy. Year:  2003  Volume:  23  Issue:  3  Page:  4 - 25&lt;/ref&gt; Some have suggested that simply fighting speciesism is not enough because intrinsic value of nature can be extended beyond sentient beings, termed the ethic of "libertarian extension."&lt;ref&gt;1999 The Puzzle of Ethics. London: Harper Collins. Vardy, P., and P. Grosch&lt;/ref&gt; This belief system seeks to apply the principle of individual rights to not only all non-human animals but also all objects such as trees, plants, and rocks.&lt;ref&gt;''IN NEED OF NEW ENVIRONMENTAL ETHICS FOR TOURISM?'' Andrew Holden. Annals of Tourism Research, Vol. 30, No. 1, pp. 94–108, 2003&lt;/ref&gt;

==Great ape personhood==
{{Main|Great Ape personhood}}
Great Ape personhood is a concept in which the attributes of the [[Great Ape]]s are deemed to merit recognition of their [[sentience]] and personhood within the law, as opposed to mere protection under [[animal cruelty]] legislation. This would cover matters such as their own best interest being taken into account in their treatment by people.&lt;ref name="rights"&gt; [http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/magazine/6505691.stm Should apes have human rights?] &lt;/ref&gt;

==Science fiction==
Speciesism is a popular theme in [[science fiction]], referring to a prejudice against other intelligent species, equivalent to racism. For example, during the reign of the [[Galactic Empire (Star Wars)|Galactic Empire]] in ''[[Star Wars]]'', many [[extraterrestrial life|alien]] species were oppressed by the ruling government, which consisted mainly of humans. In this context, it is sometimes referred to as [[xenophobia]].{{Fact|date=November 2007}}

==Animal holocaust==
{{main|Animal rights and the Holocaust}}
David Sztybel holds that the treatment of animals can be compared to the [[Holocaust]] in a valid and meaningful way. In his paper ''Can the Treatment of Animals Be Compared to the Holocaust?''using a thirty-nine-point comparison Sztybel asserts that the comparison is not offensive and that it does not overlook important differences, or ignore supposed affinities between animal liberationists and Nazis. The comparison of animal treatment and the Holocaust came into the public eye with [[People for the Ethical Treatment of Animals]]' "Holocaust on your Plate" exhibit. Sztybel equates the racism of the Nazis with the speciesism inherent in eating meat, or using animal by products particularly those produced on factory farms.&lt;ref&gt;Sztybel, David ''Can the Treatment of Animals Be Compared to the Holocaust?'' Ethics &amp; the Environment - Volume 11, Number 1, Spring 2006, pp. 97-132&lt;/ref&gt; However, even among the supports of the concept of speciesism as a critical tool, such comparisons are not always supported.  Y. Michael Barilan writes that speciesism is not the same thing as "Nazi racism" because Nazi racism extolled the abuser and condemned the weaker and the abused. He describes speciesism as the recognition of rights on the basis of group membership rather than solely on the basis of moral considerations.&lt;ref&gt;''Speciesism as a precondition to justice'' Y. Michael Barilan, MD, MA. Politics and the Life Sciences Article: pp. 22–33&lt;/ref&gt;

== Criticism ==
John Tuohey writes that the logic behind charges of speciesism fails to hold up, and that, although it has been popularly appealing, it is philosophically flawed. Even though the animal rights movement in the United States has been influential in slowing and in some cases stopping biomedical research involving animals, no one has offered a clear and compelling argument for the equlity of species.&lt;ref&gt;''Fifteen years after “Animal Liberation”: Has the animal rights movement achieved philosophical legitimacy?'' Journal of Medical Humanities. Volume 13, Number 2 / June, 1992. John Tuohey&lt;/ref&gt; Nel Noddings has criticized Peter Singer's concept of speciesism for being too simplistic, and failing to take into account the context of species preference as concepts of racism and sexism have taken in to account the context of discrimination against humans.&lt;ref&gt;''Comment on Donovan's "Animal Rights and Feminist Theory"'' Nel Noddings Signs, Vol. 16, No. 2 (Winter, 1991), pp. 418-422&lt;/ref&gt; Some people who work for racial or sexual equality have said that comparisons between speciesism and racism or sexism are insulting,&lt;ref&gt;''[http://www.bbc.co.uk/religion/ethics/animals/rights/speciesism.shtml The ethics of speciesism]''&lt;/ref&gt; for example Peter Staudenmaier writes:
&lt;blockquote&gt;The central analogy to the civil rights movement and the women’s movement is trivializing and ahistorical. Both of those social movements were initiated and driven by members of the dispossessed and excluded groups themselves, not by benevolent men or white people acting on their behalf. Both movements were built precisely around the idea of reclaiming and reasserting a shared humanity in the face of a society that had deprived it and denied it. No civil rights activist or feminist ever argued, “We’re sentient beings too!” They argued, “We’re fully human too!” Animal liberation doctrine, far from extending this humanist impulse, directly undermines it. -Peter Staudenmaier&lt;ref&gt;''[http://www.communalism.org/Archive/5/aar.print.html Ambiguities of Animal Rights]'' Peter Staudenmaier COMMUNALISM: International Journal for a Rational Society ISSUE 5 | MARCH 2003&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Although Camilla Kronqvis sympathizes with Singer’s aims, she does not accept his arguments. She writes "To say that our morality rests on attending to somebody’s pleasure and pain, also seems to be a pretty crude description of what it is to be a moral being." And concludes "I also find it highly unlikely that a polar bear would care for my interests of leading a long, healthy life if it decided to have me for lunch, and I wonder if I would have time to present it with Singer’s arguments when it started to carry out this intention."&lt;ref&gt;''Speciesism - Arguments for Whom? '' Camilla Kronqvis. Ethics, Agency &amp; Love.&lt;/ref&gt;

Some more radical opponents of the idea of speciesism believe that non-human animals exist so that humans may make use of them, be it for food, entertainment or other uses. This special status conveys [[special rights]], such as the [[right to life]], and also unique responsibilities, such as [[Stewardship (theology)|stewardship]] of the [[Natural environment|environment]]. 

Some believers in [[human exceptionalism]] base the concept in the [[Abrahamic religion]]s, such as the verse in [[Genesis]] 1:26 "And God said, Let us make man in our image, after our likeness: and let them have dominion over the fish of the sea, and over the fowl of the air, and over the cattle, and over all the earth, and over every creeping thing that creepeth upon the earth." Likewise, the [[Buddhism]], despite its reputation for respect for animals, explicitly accords humans a higher status in the progression of [[reincarnation]]. Animals may be reincarnated as humans, but only humans can reach enlightenment.&lt;ref&gt;The Specter of Speciesism: Buddhist and Christian Views of Animals. By PAUL WALDAU. American Academy of Religion, Academy Series. Oxford: OXFORD UNIVERSITY PRESS, 2002.&lt;/ref&gt;  Nearly every human culture has made a distinction between human and non-human life that is in some way speciesist.

Others take a [[secular]] approach, such as pointing to evidence of unusual rapid evolution of the [[human brain]] and the emergence of "exceptional" [[aptitude]]s.  As one commentator put it, "Over the course of [[human history]], we have been successful in cultivating our faculties, shaping our development, and impacting upon the wider world in a deliberate fashion, quite distinct from [[evolution|evolutionary processes]].&lt;ref&gt;Starr, Sandy. ''[http://www.spiked-online.com/Articles/0000000CA855.htm What Makes Us Exceptional?]''. Spiked Science&lt;/ref&gt; Constance K. Perry asserts that the use of 'non-autonomous' animals instead of humans in risky research can be based on solid moral ground and is not necessarily speciesism.&lt;ref&gt;''A Compassionate Autonomy Alternative to Speciesism'' Constance K. Perry Volume 22, Number 3 / June, 2001 Theoretical Medicine and Bioethics&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
&lt;!-- Please avoid repeating links --&gt;
*[[Anthropocentrism]]
*[[Deep ecology]]
*[[Humanism]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
*Dunayer, Joan. 2004. ''Speciesism''. Ryce Publishing: Illinois. ISBN 0-9706475-6-5
*[http://www.rightsforanimals.org Rights for animals]
*[http://www.antispe.de/english.html Anti-speciesism ]
* ''[http://www.cahiers-antispecistes.org/ Les Cahiers Antispécistes]'' (in [[French language|French]])   
* ''[http://www.eco.utexas.edu/Homepages/Faculty/Cleaver/wk6animals.html The Struggle for Animal Equality]''

[[Category:Animal rights]]
[[Category:Prejudices]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]

[[cs:Speciesismus]]
[[da:Speciesisme]]
[[de:Speziesismus]]
[[el:Σπησισισμός]]
[[es:Especismo]]
[[fr:Antispécisme]]
[[it:Specismo]]
[[he:סוגנות]]
[[lt:Rūšizmas]]
[[nl:Speciesisme]]
[[ja:種差別]]
[[pl:Gatunkizm]]
[[pt:Especismo]]
[[sv:Speciesism]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>