<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20051018141436|25828949" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="29045" pageid="29045" ns="0" title="Speciesism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-10-20T02:18:19Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Template:Animal liberation movement}}

'''Speciesism''' is the concept that different species should have different rights. As such it is seen as discriminatory in the same way as [[sexism]] or other [[discrimination|discriminatory practices]] by some people, who argue that animals should be recognized as having broad inalienable rights and respect as sentient feeling living beings, regardless of historical notions that draw a line between humans (a divine or higher species who are entitled to these) and "mere animals" (who are lower and are therefore not). 

This view is strongly contested by others, who feel that it is naive or anthropomorphic, and romanticizes animals beyond what is known about them, to credit them with an inner world that merits such treatment. Such people tend to see animals as being more appropriately protected by strong and broad animal cruelty and similar laws.

At the heart of this debate lie complex issues and questions that are still being explored by [[ethology|ethologists]], [[philosophy|philosophers]], [[lawyer]]s and specialists in many related fields: What does it mean to be a human or animal? Are we different or better than them? What rights do we have to use what we find on earth? What degree of animal pain is justified to attain a measure of potential human benefit? How do we balance custodianship and utility? And, do animals feel or think in a way that makes giving them rights meaningful, or are they simply instinctive beings with minimal self-awareness beyond the "now", which are useful and benefit human beings? 

Although not usually discussed under the name "speciesism", a term which can sound [[extremism|extremist]] or fringe, the underlying issues are mainstream ones and actively debated in many ways at present.

==Terminology==
The term, a contraction of "species-ism", was coined by [[Richard D. Ryder]] in 1970 and is used to denote [[prejudice]] similar in kind to [[sexism]] and [[racism]]. The term has not yet entered everyday language.

Some people who use the term feel that all animals should have the same rights, or, that all animals and people should have the same rights (similar to [[human rights]] legislation). Others feel that rights might vary according to species none the less, thus a chimpanzee might be given a higher level of rights, than (for example) a rat or an ant. Others see some core rights due to all animals, with additional rights for those species to which they might apply. The commonality between all these views is they all reject the "human v. other" dichotomy which is embedded in current law, as inappropriate and disrespectful of animals' status as living sentient beings.

==Reasons why animals and people have different status at present==

It is hypothesized that the majority of people and human culture in general have a great difficulty in accepting animals as equals. 

As well, humans gain great advantage from animals and from their ability to use them in a utilitarian manner, and they lack an ability to communicate in spoken words or process conceptual thought to the extent people can, leading people to see them as lower. 

Historically, most religions define animals as lower forms of life, on earth merely to serve and be used for humans' benefit, by divine law.

==Supporters and critics==
The idea of speciesism is used mostly by advocates of [[animal rights]], who believe that it is [[Rationality|irrational]] or [[moral]]ly wrong, and who disapprove of [[anthropocentrism|anthropocentric]] ethics or discrimination against non-human animals by [[Human|human beings]]. [[Ingrid Newkirk]], the founder of [[PETA]], writes:
:''""How dare you compare my ancestors' subjugation to the subjugation of cows prodded down the slaughter line to their deaths?!" I can, because it is right to do so and wrong to reject the concept ... Generally speaking, mustn't rhinos think that rhino suffering is more important than vervet monkey suffering and vervet monkeys think that their suffering is more important than songbird suffering? I'd imagine so, for a monkey mother who must choose between rescuing her own baby or a squirrel baby from drowning would surely pluck the monkey baby from the water? Just so, humans who define themselves by religion or culture or nationality or skin color think that their suffering can never be compared, no matter how factually, with any other human or animal's suffering. To do so makes them feel belittled, reduced. But perhaps that's just our primitive biology crying out to protect and save our own kind, the more narrowly defined the better, and the rest be damned. I reject that. Or I try to. Only supremacism makes us think that "our kind," our narrow view of ourselves as Protestants, Muslims, white, black, a woman, a man, a human being, is more important than the rest. But a broader definition of ourselves is simply that we are all animals. Our indignation at injustice to fellow whatever-we-are should go further - to indignation at injustice to anyone. Otherwise, what are we, but selfish little supremacists."'' [http://www.ingridnewkirk.com/archives/2005/08/we_are_all_anim.html] (Other critics of speciesism feel that this quote is unduly emotive and that as president of PETA, a much stronger and well thought out case could and should have been made)

Philosophers [[Tom Regan]] and [[Peter Singer]] have both criticized speciesism. Regan rejects it because it permits unjustified violations of animals' inherent [[rights]]; Singer, because it violates the principle of [[equal consideration of interests]].

On the other hand, whilst many feel animals should have some rights - perhaps if only the rights they are given now - the idea of giving them fundamentally new sets of rights is controversial. Behind this objection lies a sense in the minds of most people, that animals are not people, and that they should not and cannot be treated as equals in this way - precisely the heart of arguments put forward by proponents. It is also seen by some as a grey area and one which owould be hard to know how to enforce. There is no research suggesting that those who fight against discrimination in other ways - sexism or racism for example - are any different in this area to others in society when it comes to animals and their place in society. In this sense, [[parochial]]ism is probably grounded in human beings no less than in any other species, and the instinct amongst people is to protect what is closest first. Comparison between that, and sexism and racism, for example, is often viewed as insulting, and critics observe that virtually all non-human animals treat members of their own species better than those of other species and that such behaviour shoudl therefore be no less acceptable in human beings. [http://www.bbc.co.uk/religion/ethics/animals/speciesism1.shtml] 

A counter point to this, is that most sets of rights have evolved gradually and society adapted over time. Things are unacceptable now that would have been accepted a century ago. So our view as humans and society towards other animals and their rights can change too.

==Cultural views==
Some religions and cultures are less speciesist than others. While [[animism|animists]] may believe in the equality of all [[Sentience|sentient]] beings, [[monotheism|monotheists]] tend to believe that human beings are superior to other lifeforms by [[God|divine]] intention. Generally speaking, the teachings of [[Jainism]], [[Hinduism]], and [[Buddhism]] are examples of religions that tilt towards being less speciesist, though the extent to which this is reflected in daily life in countries where those religions are influential is mixed.

==Animal status around the world==
In most countries, animals are [[chattel]] - property. They have no rights, including a right to life or bodily integrity, save that it is a crime to be "cruel" to them in many jurisdictions.

One notable exception is [[Rhode Island]], which in [[2001]] became the first state to pass a law recasting "animal owners" as "animal guardians" in animal legislation. Although described by some as a mere "feel good" exercise, others believe that viewing animals legally as living, feeling beings instead of property has been a "huge step in promoting human compassion" with "potentially enormous legal implications". A similar move has been undertaken in many other towns and states.

:''[http://www.nabr.org/AnimalLaw/Guardianship National Association for Biomedical Research web page on this movement]''

==Animal legal rights proposals==

{{mergeto|Animal_rights}}

A step further, David Favre, a law professor at [[Michigan State University]], has proposed establishing a new legal tort, which he calls intentional interference with the primary interests of an individual chimpanzee. It is likely that chimpanzees in particular were chosen for several reasons: they are the species closest to humans biologically, able to communicate significantly in [[American Sign Language]], highly studied and hence with the highest likelihood of recognition of selfhood and legal rights. 

This new tort would require the interests of a chimpanzee to be balanced with the specific interests that a university, researcher, zoo, etc. has in that particular animal, and was presented at a talk at [[Harvard]] sponsored by the [[Chimpanzee Collaboratory’s Legal Committee]] in 2002.

"Personhood" for certain animals is a more nebulous concept, but has also had its legal discussion, [http://www.nabr.org/AnimalLaw/Personhood/index.htm here]. Again for the same reasons, the primary species considered are Great Apes.

==In science fiction==

Speciesism is a popular theme in [[science fiction]], referring to a prejudice against other intelligent species. For example, during the reign of the [[Galactic Empire]] in ''[[Star Wars]]'', many [[extraterrestrial|alien]] species were oppressed by the ruling government, which consisted mainly of humans. In this context, it is sometimes referred to as [[xenophobia]].

==See also==
*[[Animal rights]]
*[[Humanism]]
*[[Painism]]
*[[Peter Singer]], [[Tom Regan]], [[Steven Best]], [[Richard D. Ryder]]

==External links==
*[http://www.rightsforanimals.org Rights for animals]
*[http://www.antispe.de/english.html Anti-speciesism ]
*[http://www.guardian.co.uk/animalrights/story/0,11917,1543799,00.html "All beings that feel pain deserve human rights"] by Richard Ryder, ''The Guardian'', August 6, 2005

[[Category:Animal liberation movement]]

[[de:Speziesismus]]
[[fr:Antispécisme]]
[[ja:&amp;#31278;&amp;#24046;&amp;#21029;]]
[[sv:Speciesism]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>