<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20040909181020|6873138" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="29045" pageid="29045" ns="0" title="Speciesism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2004-10-26T11:32:37Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[de:Speziesismus]] [[fr:spécisme]][[sv:speciesism]]

'''Speciesism''' is the notional act of assigning different [[value]]s or [[right]]s to [[being]]s on the basis of their biological [[species]], by analogy with such terms as [[sexism]] and [[racism]]. The term is used and considered meaningful chiefly by advocates of extensive [[animal rights]] -- that is, those who believe that speciesism, so defined, is ethically incorrect and its consequences morally wrong.

Like other words of political and moral disputation (such as the Marxist use of "[[exploitation]]", or the various meanings of "[[sexual liberation]]"), use of the term implies a certain position on the subject it discusses. To refer to ''speciesism'' implies that it is possible and desirable to treat members of various species -- specifically, nonhuman animals traditionally considered "lower" animals -- with moral value equal to that which society bestows upon humans.

In practice the term is used to refer to discrimination against non-human animals by [[Homo sapiens|human beings]] -- that is, to [[anthropomorphism|anthropomorphic]] speciesism. Speciesism is condemned by proponents of what is generally known as [[animal rights]] including philosophers such as [[Tom Regan]] and [[Peter Singer]]. The former rejects it as allowing for unjustified violations of animals' inherent rights; the latter, as being against the principle of [[equal consideration of interests]].

The teachings of some religions can be considered less speciesist than others. For example, while some [[animism|animists]] may believe in the equality of [[sentience]] of all things, some [[monotheism|monotheists]] may believe that humans are superior by divine intention and inherently a class apart from other lifeforms. 

Generally speaking, the teachings of [[Jainism]], [[Hinduism]], and [[Buddhism]] are examples of religions which tilt towards being less specieist on a spectrum of various religious beliefs, though the extent to which this is reflected in daily life in countries where those religions are influential is mixed. 

The term 'speciesism' was coined by [[Richard D. Ryder]] in 1970.

See also discussion under [[physicalism]]

==External links==

*[http://www.rightsforanimals.org/ Rights for Animals]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>