<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20121118002023|523583920" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="29045" pageid="29045" ns="0" title="Speciesism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2012-11-18T00:36:44Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Discrimination sidebar}}

'''Speciesism''' involves the assignment of different values, rights, or special consideration to individuals solely on the basis of their [[species]] membership. The term is mostly used by [[animal rights]] advocates, who argue that speciesism is a prejudice similar to [[racism]] or [[sexism]], in that the treatment of individuals is predicated on group membership and morally irrelevant physical differences. The argument is that species membership has no moral significance.&lt;ref&gt;Ryder (2009), p. 320&lt;/ref&gt; Therefore, speciesism refers to discrimination against individuals of sentient species ([[sentiocentrism]]), not discrimination of living species ([[Biocentrism (ethics)|biocentrism]]).

The term is used to embrace two ideas: "human speciesism," which is the exclusion of all nonhuman [[animals]] from the protections afforded to humans, and the more general idea of assigning value to a being on the basis of their species, so that human beings favouring rights for [[chimpanzees]] over rights for [[dogs]] because of human-chimpanzee similarities, would be an example of "human-chimpanzee speciesism."&lt;ref name=Waldau2001p5&gt;Waldau (2001), pp. 5, 23–29&lt;/ref&gt;

The arguments are contested on various grounds, including the position of some religions that human beings were created as superior in status to other animals, and were awarded "dominion" over them, whether as owners or stewards. It is also argued that the physical differences between humans and other species are indeed morally relevant, and that to deny this is to engage in [[anthropomorphism]]. Such proponents may explicitly embrace and accept the charge of speciesism, arguing that it recognizes the importance of all human beings, and that species loyalty is justified.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jstor.org/stable/3751526 Lafollette and Shanks (1996)]; [http://www.hughlafollette.com/papers/origin.of.speciesism.pdf courtesy link]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Origins==
===Origin of the term===
{{see|Animals, Men and Morals|Oxford Group (animal rights)}}
The general concept of speciesism is an old one. [[Paul Waldau]] writes that the overriding of animals' interests was traditionally justified by arguing that they existed for human use; [[Aristotle]] made this claim in the 4th century BCE, as did [[Cicero]] in the 1st century CE.&lt;ref&gt;Waldau (2009), p. 321&lt;/ref&gt;

The term "speciesism," and the argument that it was simply a prejudice, first appeared in 1970 in a privately printed pamphlet, titled "Speciesism," written by British psychologist [[Richard D. Ryder]]. Ryder had written three letters to ''The Daily Telegraph'' in April and May 1969 with criticisms of animal experiments, based on incidents he had witnessed in laboratories, and thereafter joined a group of intellectuals and writers in Oxford – the nascent animal rights community, now known as the Oxford Group. One of the group's activities was writing and distributing pamphlets about areas of concern; the pamphlet about speciesism, written to protest against [[Animal testing|animal experimentation]], was one of them.&lt;ref&gt;Ryder (2000), p. 6&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:Richard D Ryder in 2012 film The Superior Human?.png|thumb|220px|right|[[Richard D. Ryder]] coined the term "speciesism" in 1970.]] --&gt;
Ryder argued in the pamphlet that "Since Darwin, scientists have agreed that there is no 'magical' essential difference between humans and other animals, biologically-speaking. Why then do we make an almost total distinction morally? If all organisms are on one physical continuum, then we should also be on the same moral continuum." He wrote that, at that time in the UK, 5,000,000 animals were being used each year in experiments, and that attempting to gain benefits for our own species through the mistreatment of others is "just 'speciesism' and as such it is a selfish emotional argument rather than a reasoned one."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.criticalsocietyjournal.org.uk/Archives_files/1.%20Speciesism%20Again.pdf Ryder (2010)]&lt;/ref&gt;

Ryder used the term again in an essay, "Experiments on Animals," in ''[[Animals, Men and Morals]]'' (1971), a collection of essays on animal rights edited by three other members of the Oxford Group, philosophy graduate students Stanley and Roslind Godlovitch, and John Harris. He wrote:

&lt;blockquote&gt;In as much as both "race" and "species" are vague terms used in the classification of living creatures according, largely, to physical appearance, an analogy can be made between them. Discrimination on grounds of race, although most universally condoned two centuries ago, is now widely condemned. Similarly, it may come to pass that enlightened minds may one day abhor "speciesism" as much as they now detest "racism". The illogicality in both forms of prejudice is of an identical sort. If it is accepted as morally wrong to deliberately inflict suffering upon innocent human creatures, then it is only logical to also regard it as wrong to inflict suffering on innocent individuals of other species. ... The time has come to act upon this logic.&lt;ref&gt;Ryder (1971), p. 81&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

===Spread of the idea===
{{see|Animal Liberation (book)}}
The idea was popularized by the Australian philosopher [[Peter Singer]] – who had known Ryder from his own time as a postgraduate philosophy student at Oxford – in his ''Animal Liberation'' (1975).&lt;ref&gt;Diamond (2004), p. 93&lt;/ref&gt; Singer argued from a [[Preference utilitarianism|preference-utilitarian]] perspective, writing that speciesism violates the principle of [[equal consideration of interests]], the idea based on [[Jeremy Bentham]]'s principle: "each to count for one, and none for more than one." Singer argued that, although there may be differences between animals and humans, they share the capacity to suffer, and we must give equal consideration to that suffering; any position that allows similar cases to be treated in a dissimilar fashion fails to qualify as an acceptable moral theory.&lt;ref&gt;Singer (1990), pp. 120–121&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Peter Singer MIT Veritas.jpg|thumb|160px|[[Peter Singer]] popularized the idea in ''Animal Liberation'' (1975).]]
Singer credited Ryder for having coined the term, and used it in the title of his book's fifth chapter: "Man's Dominion ... ''a short history of speciesism''," defining it as "a prejudice or attitude of bias in favour of the interests of members of one's own species and against those of members of other species":

&lt;blockquote&gt;Racists violate the principle of equality by giving greater weight to the interests of members of their own race when there is a clash between their interests and the interests of those of another race. Sexists violate the principle of equality by favouring the interests of their own sex. Similarly, speciesists allows the interests of their own species to override the greater interests of members of other species. The pattern is identical in each case.&lt;ref&gt;Singer (1990), pp. 6, 9&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The term caught on; Singer wrote that it was an awkward word but that he could not think of a  better one. It became an entry in the ''Oxford English Dictionary'' in 1985, defined as "discrimination against or exploitation of animal species by human beings, based on an assumption of mankind's superiority."&lt;ref name=Wise2004p26&gt;Wise (2004), p. 26&lt;/ref&gt; In 1994, the ''Oxford Dictionary of Philosophy'' offered a wider definition: "By analogy with racism and sexism, the improper stance of refusing respect to the lives, dignity, or needs of animals of other than the human species."&lt;ref&gt;Blackburn (1994), p. 358&lt;/ref&gt;

==Arguments==
===The anti-speciesism critique===
The arguments against speciesism – known as the anti-speciesism critique – are based on the view that species membership has no moral significance. The American legal scholar [[Steven M. Wise]] argues that speciesism is a bias as arbitrary as any other, a point conceded even by some critics of animal rights. He cites the philosopher [[R.G. Frey]], a leading animal rights critic, who wrote in 1983 that, if forced to choose between abandoning experiments on animals and allowing experiments on "marginal-case" humans, he would choose the latter, "not because I begin a monster and end up choosing the monstrous, but because I cannot think of anything at all compelling that cedes all human life of any quality greater value than animal life of any quality."&lt;ref&gt;Wise (2004), p. 26, citing Frey (1983), pp. 115–116&lt;/ref&gt;

Philosopher [[Tom Regan]] argues that animals have inherent value and moral rights as "subjects-of-a-life." His position is that logically we cannot assign animals a lesser value because of a perceived lack of rationality, while at the same time assigning a higher value to human beings who lack rationality, such as infants and the mentally impaired, solely on the grounds of their species membership. Law professor [[Gary Francione]] contends that we treat animals in ways that would be regarded as torture if humans were involved.&lt;!--needs source and fleshing out--&gt;

===Argument from marginal cases===
{{see|Argument from marginal cases}}
One argument used to show that speciesism is an arbitrary discrimination is the argument from marginal cases. This says that if marginal-case human beings – such as infants, the senile, the comatose, and the cognitively disabled – have a certain moral status, then non-human animals must have it too, since there is no morally relevant ability that the marginal-case humans have that non-human animals lack. "Moral status" may include a right not to be killed or made to suffer, or a general moral requirement to be treated in a certain way.&lt;!--source--&gt;

===The "discontinuous mind"===
[[File:Richard dawkins lecture.jpg|thumb|140px|[[Richard Dawkins]] argues against speciesism as an example of the "discontinuous mind."]]
[[Richard Dawkins]], the evolutionary biologist, argued against speciesism in ''[[The Blind Watchmaker]]'' (1986), ''The Great Ape Project'' (1993), and ''[[The God Delusion]]'' (2006), elucidating the connection with [[modern evolutionary synthesis|evolutionary theory]]. He compares former racist attitudes and assumptions to their present-day speciesist counterparts. In a chapter of ''The Blind Watchmaker'' entitled "The one true tree of life," he argues that it is not just zoological [[taxonomy]] that is saved from awkward ambiguity by the extinction of intermediate forms, but also human ethics and law. Dawkins argues that what he calls the "discontinuous mind" is ubiquitous, dividing the world into units that reflect nothing but our use of language, and animals into discontinuous species:&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.animal-rights-library.com/texts-m/dawkins01.htm Dawkins (1993)]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Such is the breathtaking speciesism of our Christian-inspired attitudes, the abortion of a single human [[zygote]] (most of them are destined to be spontaneously aborted anyway) can arouse more moral solicitude and righteous indignation than the [[vivisection]] of any number of intelligent adult chimpanzees! [...]  The only reason we can be comfortable with such a double standard is that the [[human evolution|intermediates between humans and chimps]] are all dead.&lt;ref&gt;Dawkins (1996)&lt;!--needs a page number--&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Dawkins elaborated on his position towards speciesism and vegetarianism in a live discussion with Singer at The Center for Inquiry in 2007:

&lt;blockquote&gt;What I am doing is going along with the fact that I live in a society where meat eating is accepted as the norm, and it requires a level of social courage which I haven't yet produced to break out of that. It's a little bit like the position which many people would have held a couple of hundred years ago over slavery. Where lots of people felt morally uneasy about slavery but went along with it because the whole economy of the [[Southern United States|South]] depended upon slavery.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pointofinquiry.org/richard_dawkins_science_and_the_new_atheism Dawkins (7 December 2007)]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

===Great ape personhood===
{{see|Great Ape personhood|Great Ape Project}}
Great Ape personhood is a concept in which the attributes of the [[Great Ape]]s are deemed to merit recognition of their sentience and personhood within the law, as opposed to mere protection under [[animal cruelty]] legislation. Awarding personhood to nonhuman primates would require that their individual interests be respected or taken into account, rather than regarding them merely as members of a group.&lt;ref&gt;Karcher (2009)&lt;/ref&gt;

===Animal holocaust===
{{see|Animal rights and the Holocaust}}
[[David Sztybel]] argues in his paper, "Can the Treatment of Animals Be Compared to the Holocaust?" (2006), that the racism of the Nazis is comparable to the speciesism inherent in eating meat or using animal by-products, particularly those produced on factory farms.&lt;ref&gt;[http://muse.jhu.edu/login?auth=0&amp;type=summary&amp;url=/journals/ethics_and_the_environment/v011/11.1sztybel.html Sztybel (2006)]&lt;/ref&gt; Y. Michael Barilan, an Israeli physician, argues that speciesism is not the same thing as Nazi racism, because the latter extolled the abuser and condemned the weaker and the abused. He describes speciesism as the recognition of rights on the basis of group membership, rather than solely on the basis of moral considerations.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/16859377 Barlian (2004)]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Centrality of consciousness===
Some have suggested that simply to fight speciesism is not enough because the intrinsic value of nature can be extended beyond sentient beings, termed the ethic of "libertarian extension".&lt;ref&gt;Vardy and Grosch (1999)&lt;!--page number?--&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;  This belief system seeks to apply the principle of individual rights not only to all animals but also to objects without a nervous system such as trees, plants and rocks.&lt;ref&gt;Holden (2003)&lt;/ref&gt; Ryder rejects this argument, writing that "value cannot exist in the absence of consciousness or potential consciousness. Thus, rocks and rivers and houses have no interests and no rights of their own. This does not mean, of course, that they are not of value to us, and to many other painients, including those who need them as habitats and who would suffer without them."&lt;ref&gt;(Ryder 2005)&lt;/ref&gt;
===In Pop Culture===

[[Alec Baldwin]] and [[Pamela Anderson]] are two notables out of a long list of [[List of vegans|vegan celebrities]] who remain passionate and out-spoken about animal rights and speciesism. Both Baldwin and Anderson are spokespersons for [[PETA]], with Baldwin narrating the documentary [[Meet Your Meat]] which exposes the truth about the treatment of animals in factory farming. Anderson has been in several ads and campaigns for PETA, stating she has been involved in animal rights since starring in the television show [[Baywatch]]&lt;ref name="Pamela Anderson"&gt;{{cite web|last=DeSpain Freeman|first=China|title=Pamela Anderson’s Passions: Motherhood and Animal Rights|url=http://www.ecorazzi.com/2012/08/06/pamela-anderson-my-kids-know-i-save-animals/|publisher=Ecorazzi|accessdate=15 November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;. 
Other public figures&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Osborne|first=Graham|title=Vegans are glam!|url=www.smh.com.au/lifestyle/diet-and-fitness/vegans-are-glam-20120903-259tq.html|publisher=The Sydney Morning Herald|accessdate=7 November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; who are maintaining or have switched to a vegan lifestyle for reasons of compassion and/or health include [[Ellen DeGeneres]], [[Ozzy Osbourne]], [[Woody Harrelson]] and [[Bill Clinton]].

===Expert Opinions===

Having travelled extensively throughout the United States and Isreal&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Yourofsky|first=Gary|title=The Best Speech You Will Ever Hear &gt;&gt; How Israel was taken by storm|url=http://www.gary-tv.com/garymain/?page_id=2587|publisher=garytv.com|accessdate=7 November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; to over 60,000 people&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Yourofsky|first=Gary|title=About the ADAPTT Lecture|url=www.adaptt.org/tour.html|publisher=ADAPTT.org|accessdate=7 November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;, '''[[Gary Yourofsky]]''' is an animal rights activist and the founder of the ethical vegan organization ADAPTT&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Yourofsky|first=Gary|title=ADAPTT animals deserve absolute protection today and tomorrow|url=www.adaptt.org/index.html|publisher=ADAPTT.org|accessdate=7 November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;. Founded in 1996, "Animals Deserve Absolute Protection Today and Tomorrow (ADAPTT) believes that all animals have an inherent right to be free and live completely unfettered by human dominance. Sadly, most humans continue to embrace animal slavery, animal torture, and animal murder. Billions of animals are killed every year in a premeditated, systematic massacre. Remember, without universal equality, one type of equality will always create another type of inequality."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Yourofksky|first=Gary|title=ADAPTT animals deserve absolute protection today and tomorrow|url=www.adaptt.org/about.html|publisher=ADAPTT.org|accessdate=7 November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;  

Aside from being a John Howard Harris Professor of Philosophy at [[Bucknell University]], '''Dr.''' '''[[Gary Steiner]]'''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Steiner|first=Gary|title=Animals merit moral status comparable|url=http://www.facstaff.bucknell.edu/gsteiner/|publisher=Gary Steiner|accessdate=7 November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;   is also the author of several books and an animal rights activist who is a strong believer in that animals have the same rights to life and freedom as we, as humans, do. In his 2012 interview with Kathryn Kopchik he states, "I don't see any morally relevant distinctions between different types of sentient beings, beings that can experience pleasure and pain, can have conscious awareness, beings for whom life matters. It's only on the basis of what some people call speciesism or anthropocentrism that we make such distinctions and privilege human beings. These speciesistic prejudices are comparable to the sorts of arbitrary hierarchies proclaimed by racists and sexists."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Steiner|first=Gary|title=Ask the Experts: Gary Steiner on animal rights and the vegan imperative|url=www.bucknell.edu/x77439.xml|publisher=Bucknell University|accessdate=7 November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Counter-arguments==
===Philosophical===
A common theme in defending speciesism is the argument that humans "have the right to compete with and exploit other species to preserve and protect the human species".&lt;ref&gt;Graft (1997)&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Carl Cohen]], a professor of philosophy at the Residential College of the University of Michigan, writes: "Speciesism is not merely plausible; it is essential for right conduct, because those who will not make the morally relevant distinctions among species are almost certain, in consequence, to misapprehend their true obligations.&lt;ref&gt;Cohen (1986)&lt;/ref&gt; Cohen argues that racism and sexism are wrong because there are no relevant differences between the sexes or races. Between people and animals, he argues, there are significant differences; his view is that animals do not qualify for [[Kant]]ian personhood, and as such have no rights.&lt;ref&gt;Cohen (2001)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!--needs source and to be written differently: Animal rights advocates respond that many humans might also fail to qualify for Kantian personhood, yet do have rights.--&gt;

[[Maurice Merleau-Ponty]], similarly to Buddhism and Indigenous thought uses the term "embodied perceptual awareness" and the ability to feel, as being the common denominator of all life, not intelligence or emotion.

[[File:Trial of Bill Burns.jpg|thumb|200px|The Trial of Bill Burns (1838) in London, showing [[Richard Martin (politician)|Richard Martin]], MP for Galway, in court with a donkey Burns had beaten, leading to the world's first known conviction for animal cruelty.]]

[[Nel Noddings]], the American feminist, has criticized Singer's concept of speciesism for being simplistic, and for failing to take into account the context of species preference, as concepts of racism and sexism have taken into account the context of discrimination against humans.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jstor.org/discover/10.2307/3174525 Noddings (Winter 1991)]&lt;/ref&gt; Some people who work for racial or sexual equality have said that comparisons between speciesism and racism or sexism are trivializing; for example, [[Peter Staudenmaier]] writes:

&lt;blockquote&gt;The central analogy to the civil rights movement and the women’s movement is trivializing and ahistorical. Both of those social movements were initiated and driven by members of the dispossessed and excluded groups themselves, not by benevolent men or white people acting on their behalf. Both movements were built precisely around the idea of reclaiming and reasserting a shared humanity in the face of a society that had deprived it and denied it. No civil rights activist or feminist ever argued, “We’re sentient beings too!” They argued, “We’re fully human too!” Animal liberation doctrine, far from extending this humanist impulse, directly undermines it.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.communalism.org/Archive/5/aar.print.html Staudenmaier (March 2003)]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

[[Objectivism (Ayn Rand)|Objectivism]] holds that humans, as the only beings with a conceptual consciousness, as the animals possessing a reasoning faculty and the ability to think, which is the key characteristic setting them apart from other animals, and with their life as the standard of moral value, is the ''only'' species entitled to rights. "To demand that man [humans] defer to the "rights" of other species", it is argued, "is to deprive man himself of the [[right to life]]".&lt;ref&gt;Peikoff (1991), p. 358&lt;/ref&gt;

===Scientific===
Others take a [[secular]] approach, such as pointing to evidence of unusual rapid evolution of the [[human brain]] and the emergence of "exceptional" [[aptitude]]s.  As one commentator put it, "Over the course of [[human history]], we have been successful in cultivating our faculties, shaping our development, and impacting upon the wider world in a deliberate fashion, quite distinct from [[evolution|evolutionary processes]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.spiked-online.com/Articles/0000000CA855.htm Starr]&lt;/ref&gt; Constance K. Perry asserts that the use of 'non-autonomous' animals instead of humans in risky research can be based on solid moral grounds and is not necessarily speciesism.&lt;ref&gt;Perry (June 2001)&lt;/ref&gt; [[Jeffrey Alan Gray]], lecturer in experimental psychology at Oxford, wrote that: "I would guess that the view that human beings matter to other human beings more than animals do is, to say the least, widespread. At any rate, I wish to defend speciesism..."&lt;ref&gt;Gray (1990)&lt;/ref&gt; 

===Religious===
The Rev. John Tuohey, founder of the Providence Center for Health Care Ethics, writes that the logic behind the anti-speciesism critique is flawed, and that, although the animal rights movement in the United States has been influential in slowing animal experimentation, and in some cases halting particular studies, no one has offered a compelling argument for species equality.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/11652083 Tuohey (June 1992)]&lt;/ref&gt; 

Some opponents of the idea of speciesism believe that animals exist so that humans may make use of them. They argue that this special status conveys [[special rights]], such as the [[right to life]], and also unique responsibilities, such as [[Stewardship (theology)|stewardship]] of the [[environment (biophysical)|environment]]. This belief in [[human exceptionalism]] is often rooted in the [[Abrahamic religion]]s, such as the [[Book of Genesis]] 1:26: "Then God said, "Let Us make man in Our image, according to Our likeness; and let them rule over the fish of the sea and over the birds of the sky and over the cattle and over all the earth, and over every creeping thing that creeps on the earth." Animal rights advocates argue that dominion refers to stewardship, not ownership.&lt;ref&gt;Scully (2003)&lt;!--needs page number--&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; 

[[Buddhism]], despite its reputation for respect for animals, accords humans a somewhat higher status in the progression of [[reincarnation]].&lt;ref name = "tsos"/&gt; Animals may be reincarnated as humans, and humans can be demoted in the next life as non-humans, depending on their behaviour; only humans can immediately reach enlightenment. In a very similar way in [[Hinduism]], animals are respected, as it is believed that each animal has a role to play. Some Hindus are vegetarians, with a deep respect for cows especially (representing the earth/mother, the central figure).&lt;ref name="tsos"&gt;Waldau (2001)&lt;!--needs page number--&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; [[Felipe Fernández-Armesto]] writes that early hunter-gatherer societies, such as the [[Innu]], and many [[animist]] religions, such as Native American religions, traditionally lacked a concept of humanity and placed non-human animals and plants on an equal footing with humans, even though they are used for food; but equally they are part of all life, according to this view.&lt;ref&gt;Felipe, p. 138&lt;!--needs year--&gt;; also see Lee and Daly&lt;!--needs year and page number--&gt;.&lt;/ref&gt;

==In the media==
In [[science fiction]] and works of fantasy, speciesism takes on a role similar to [[racism]], discriminating against other [[Sentience#Science fiction|sentients]] based on a sense of superiority. It varies from human beings regarding themselves as [[Anthropocentrism#In fiction|superior to nonhumans]], nonhumans being [[Antihumanism#In fiction|superior to humans]], or certain nonhumans being superior to other nonhumans. This can take place on a [[Earth|terrestrial]], [[Extraterrestrial life|extraterrestrial]], [[wikt:extragalactic|extragalactic]], or [[Extra dimensions|extradimensional]] plane.

===Films about speciesism===
*[[The Animals Film]] (1981)
*[[A Cow at My Table]] (1998)
*[[Meet Your Meat]] (2002)
*[[Earthlings (film)|Earthlings]] (2005)
*[[Behind the Mask (2006 documentary film)|Behind the Mask]] (2006)
*[[District 9]] (2009)
*[[Peaceable Kingdom: The Journey Home (film)|Peaceable Kingdom: The Journey Home]] (2009)
*[[The Cove (film)|The Cove]] (2009)
*The Superior Human? (2012)&lt;ref&gt;[http://thesuperiorhuman.ultraventus.info/ "The Superior Human?"], official website; [http://drstevebest.wordpress.com/2012/04/02/now-online-debut-of-new-anti-speciesist-film-the-superior-animal Best (2 April 2012)]; [http://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/animal-emotions/201204/the-superior-human-who-do-we-think-we-are Bekoff (2 April 2012)].&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Speciesism: The Movie]] (2012)

==See also==
&lt;!-- Please avoid repeating links --&gt;
*[[Anthropocentrism]]
*[[Antinaturalism (politics)]]
*[[biocentrism (ethics)|Biocentrism]]
*[[Deep ecology]]
*[[Great ape personhood]]
*[[Sentiocentrism]]
*[[Veganism]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist|2}}

==References==
*Barlian, Y. Michael (2004). [http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/16859377 "Speciesism as a precondition to justice"], ''Politics and the Life Sciences''. Mar;23(1):22-33.&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Marc Bekoff|Bekoff, Marc]] (2 April 2012). [http://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/animal-emotions/201204/the-superior-human-who-do-we-think-we-are "The Superior Human? Who Do We Think We Are?"], ''Psychology Today''.
*[[Steven Best|Best, Steven]] (2 April 2012). [http://drstevebest.wordpress.com/2012/04/02/now-online-debut-of-new-anti-speciesist-film-the-superior-animal "Now Online! Debut of New Anti-Speciesist Film, ''The Superior Human?''"], drstevebest.wordpress.com.
*[[Simon Blackburn|Blackburn, Simon]] (1994). "Speciesism," ''Oxford Dictionary of Philosophy''. Oxford University Press.
*[[Carl Cohen|Cohen, Carl]]. (1986). "The case for the use of animals in biomedical research," ''The New England Journal of Medicine'', Vol. 315, No. 14.
*Cohen, Carl and [[Tom Regan|Regan, Tom]] (2001). ''The Animal Rights Debate''. Rowman &amp; Littlefield Publishers.
*[[Cora Diamond|Diamond, Cora]] (2004). "Eating Meat and Eating People," in [[Cass Sunstein]] and [[Martha Nussbaum]]. ''Animal Rights: Current Debates and New Directions''. Oxford University Press.
*[[Richard Dawkins|Dawkins, Richard]] (1993). [http://www.animal-rights-library.com/texts-m/dawkins01.htm "Gaps in the mind"], in [[Paola Cavalieri]] and [[Peter Singer]] (eds.). ''The Great Ape Project''. St. Martin's Griffin, 1993, pp. 81-87.
*Dawkins, Richard (1996) [1986]. ''The Blind Watchmaker''. W. W. Norton &amp; Company, Inc.
*Dawkins, Richard (7 December 2007). [http://www.pointofinquiry.org/richard_dawkins_science_and_the_new_atheism "Richard Dawkins - Science and the New Atheism"], interview.
*Fernández-Armesto, Felipe. ''Ideas that changed the world''.
*[[Raymond Frey|Frey, R. G.]] (1983). ''Rights, Killing and Suffering''. Blackwell.
*Graft, D. (1997). "Against strong speciesism," ''Journal of Applied Philosophy'', Vol.14, No. 2.
*Gray, J. A. (1990). "In defense of speciesism," ''Behavioral and Brain Sciences'', Vol. 13 No. 1.
*Holden, Andrew (2003). "In Need of New Environmental Ethics for Tourism?" ''Annals of Tourism Research'', Vol. 30, No. 1, pp. 94–108.
*Karcher, Karin (2009) [1998]. "Great Ape Project," in [[Marc Bekoff]]. ''Encyclopedia of Animal Rights and Animal Welfare''. Greenwood.
*Lafollette, Hugh and [[Niall Shanks|Shanks, Niall]]. [http://www.jstor.org/stable/3751526 "The Origin of Speciesism"], ''Philosophy'', Vol. 71, No. 275 (Jan., 1996), pp. 41-61; [http://www.hughlafollette.com/papers/origin.of.speciesism.pdf courtesy link].
*Lee, Richard B. and Daly, Richard Heywood. ''The Cambridge Encyclopedia of Hunters and Gatherers''.
*Noddings, Nel (Winter 1991). [http://www.jstor.org/discover/10.2307/3174525 "Comment on Donovan's 'Animal Rights and Feminist Theory'"], ''Signs'', Vol. 16, No. 2, pp. 418-422.
*[[Leonard Peikoff|Peikoff, Leonard]] (1991). ''[[Objectivism: The Philosophy of Ayn Rand]]''.&lt;!--publisher--&gt;
*Perry, Constance K. (June 2001). "A Compassionate Autonomy Alternative to Speciesism," ''Theoretical Medicine and Bioethics'', Volume 22, Number 3.
*[[Richard D. Ryder|Ryder, Richard D.]] (1971). "Experiments on Animals," in Stanley and Roslind Godlovitch and John Harris. ''Animals, Men and Morals''. Victor Gollanz, pp. 41–82.
*Ryder, Richard D. (2000) [1989]. ''Animal Revolution''. Berg.
*Ryder, Richard D. (2009) [1998]. "Speciesism," in [[Marc Bekoff]]. ''Encyclopedia of Animal Rights and Animal Welfare''. Greenwood.
*Ryder, Richard D. (2010). [http://www.criticalsocietyjournal.org.uk/Archives_files/1.%20Speciesism%20Again.pdf "Speciesism Again: The Original Leaflet"], ''Critical Society'', Spring, Issue 2.
*[[Matthew Scully|Scully, Matthew]] (2003). ''Dominion: The Power of Man, the Suffering of Animals, and the Call to Mercy''. St. Martin's Griffin.
*[[Peter Singer|Singer, Peter]] (1990) [1975]. ''Animal Liberation''. New York Review/Random House.
*Starr, Sandy. [http://www.spiked-online.com/Articles/0000000CA855.htm "What Makes Us Exceptional?]", ''Spiked Science''.
*Staudenmaier, Peter (March 2003). [http://www.communalism.org/Archive/5/aar.print.html "Ambiguities of Animal Rights"], ''Communalism: International Journal for a Rational Society', Issue 5.
*[[David Sztybel|Sztybel, David]] (2006). ''Can the Treatment of Animals Be Compared to the Holocaust?'' Ethics &amp; the Environment - Volume 11, Number 1, Spring, pp. 97-132.
*Tuohey, John (1992). [http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/11652083 "Fifteen years after ''Animal Liberation'': Has the animal rights movement achieved philosophical legitimacy?"], ''Journal of Medical Humanities'', Volume 13, Number 2, June.
*Vardy, P. and Grosch, P. (1999). ''The Puzzle of Ethics''. Harper Collins.
*[[Paul Waldau|Waldau, Paul]] (2001). ''The Specter of Speciesism: Buddhist and Christian Views of Animals''. Oxford University Press, pp. 5, 23–29.
*Waldau, Paul (2009) [1998]. "Speciesism: Historical Views," in [[Marc Bekoff]]. ''Encyclopedia of Animal Rights and Animal Welfare''. Greenwood.
*[[Steven M. Wise|Wise, Steven M.]] (2004). "Animal Rights, One Step at a Time," in [[Cass Sunstein]] and [[Martha Nussbaum]]. ''Animal Rights: Current Debates and New Directions''. Oxford University Press.

==Further reading==
*BBC (2012). [http://www.bbc.co.uk/religion/ethics/animals/rights/speciesism.shtml "The ethics of speciesism"].
*[[Joan Dunayer|Dunayer, Joan]]. 2004. ''Speciesism''. Ryce Publishing: Illinois. ISBN 0-9706475-6-5
*Geoghegan, Tom (29 March 207). [http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/magazine/6505691.stm "Should apes have human rights?"], BBC News Magazine.
*[[David Nibert|Nibert, David]] (2003). [http://www.emeraldinsight.com/journals.htm?articleid=850441 "Humans and other animals: sociology's moral and intellectual challenge"], ''International Journal of Sociology and Social Policy'', Volume 23, Issue 3, pp. 4–25.
*[[Richard D. Ryder|Ryder, Richard D.]] ''Victims of Science: The Use of Animals in Research''. Davis-Poynter, 1975.
*[http://www.antispe.de/english.html Anti-speciesism ]
*''[http://www.cahiers-antispecistes.org/ Les Cahiers Antispécistes]'' (in [[French language|French]])
*''[http://www.liberazioni.org/archivio-numeri.html Liberazioni]'' (in [[Italian language|Italian]])
*[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GYYNY2oKVWU&amp;feature=player_embedded Discussion between Peter Singer and Richard Dawkins]

{{Animal rights|state=collapsed}}

[[Category:Animal rights]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Ethical theories]]
[[Category:Prejudices]]

[[ast:Especismu]]
[[ca:Especisme]]
[[cs:Speciesismus]]
[[da:Speciesisme]]
[[de:Speziesismus]]
[[et:Spetsiesism]]
[[el:Σπισισμός]]
[[es:Especismo]]
[[fa:گونه‌پرستی]]
[[fr:Antispécisme]]
[[hr:Specizam]]
[[it:Specismo]]
[[he:סוגנות]]
[[la:Specismus]]
[[lv:Sudzisms]]
[[lt:Rūšizmas]]
[[nl:Speciesisme]]
[[nds-nl:Speciesisme]]
[[ja:種差別]]
[[no:Artssjåvinisme]]
[[pl:Szowinizm gatunkowy]]
[[pt:Especismo]]
[[ru:Видовая дискриминация]]
[[sl:Specizem]]
[[fi:Spesismi]]
[[sv:Speciesism]]
[[tr:Türcülük]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>