<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20211017165645|1050409623" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="48661985" pageid="48661985" ns="0" title="Anti-African sentiment"><revisions><rev timestamp="2021-11-28T14:59:56Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Fear or hatred of African people}}
{{Discrimination sidebar|expanded=Ethnic/national}}
'''Afrophobia, Afroscepticism''', or '''Anti-African sentiment''' is a perceived fear and hatred of the cultures of [[ethnic groups of Africa|peoples of Africa]] and the [[African diaspora]].&lt;ref name="Pwpa"&gt;{{cite book|author1=Kivuto Ndeti |author2=Kenneth R. Gray |author3=Gerard Bennaars |title=The second scramble for Africa: a response &amp; a critical analysis of the challenges facing contempory &amp;#91;sic&amp;#93; sub-Saharan Africa|date=1992|publisher=Professors World Peace Academy|isbn=9966835733|page=127|url=https://www.google.com/books?id=ScsDAQAAIAAJ|access-date=10 December 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Lexicology==
Primarily a cultural phenomenon, Afrophobia pertains to the various traditions and peoples of [[Africa]], irrespective of racial origin.&lt;ref name="Pwpa"/&gt; As such, Afrophobia is distinct from the historical racial phenomenon of ''[[negrophobia]]'', which is specifically based on contempt for ''[[Negroid|negro]]'' peoples.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The Congregational Review, Volume 2|year=1862|publisher=J.M. Whittemore|page=629|url=https://www.google.com/books?id=LkZKAAAAMAAJ|access-date=10 December 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; The opposite of Afrophobia is [[Afrophilia]], which is a love for all things pertaining to Africa.&lt;ref name="Pwpa"/&gt;

== By location ==
It has been observed that writing and terminology about racism, including about Afrophobia, has been somewhat centered on the US. In 2016, "Afrophobia" has been used as a term for racism against darker-skinned persons in China. In such usage, that is an inexact term because the racism is directed against darker-skinned persons from anywhere, without regard to any connection to Africa. Conversely, Chinese views for lighter-than-average skin are more positive, as is reflected in advertising.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://africanarguments.org/2016/08/12/claims-of-chinas-afrophobia-show-we-need-new-ways-to-think-about-race-and-racism/ |title=Claims of "China's Afrophobia" show we need new ways to think about race and racism |date=August 12, 2016 |author=Roberto Castillo}} (posted originally at The Conversation, with the title [https://theconversation.com/of-washing-powder-afrophobia-and-racism-in-china-60274 Of washing powder, Afrophobia and racism in China], August 11, 2016)&lt;/ref&gt;

== Terminology ==
The terms "Afrophobia" and "Afroscepticism" are similar to [[Anti-Europeanism|Europhobia]] and [[Euroscepticism]] and can refer to three different ideas:

# Afrophobia, or Anti-African sentiment, is a perceived fear and hatred of the cultures and peoples of Africa, as well as the African diaspora, which is also a social struggle about who has the right to be cared for by the state and society and a fight for the collective balance of rights and economic resource allocation by the modern state. 
# Hard Afroscepticism is a principled opposition to [[African integration]] and therefore can be seen in groups that think that their countries should not be part of it or whose policies towards the integration are tantamount to being opposed to the whole project of African integration, as it is currently conceived and/or projected to be.
# Soft Afroscepticism does not have a principled objection to African integration but has concerns on one or a number of policy areas, which lead to the expression of qualified and justified opposition to the integration, or there is a sense that national rights and interests are currently at odds with the integration's trajectory.

==Activism==
To overcome any perceived "Afrophobia", writer [[Langston Hughes]] suggested that [[European Americans]] must achieve peace of mind and accommodate the uninhibited emotionality of [[African Americans]]. Author [[James Baldwin]] similarly recommended that White Americans could quash any "Afrophobia" on their part by getting in touch with their repressed feelings, empathizing to overcome their "emotionally stunted" lives, and thereby overcome any dislike or fear of African Americans.&lt;ref name="Washington"&gt;{{cite book|date=2001|title=The Ideologies of African American Literature|author =Washington, Robert E.|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=PP6DSxXSFhsC|page=272|publisher=[[Rowman &amp; Littlefield]]|isbn=9780742509504}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2016, [[Tess Asplund]] made a viral protest against [[Neo-Nazism]] as part of her activism against Afrophobia.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2016/may/04/woman-defied-neo-nazis-sweden-tess-asplund-viral-photograph|title=Woman who defied 300 neo-Nazis at Swedish rally speaks of anger|last=Crouch|first=David|date=2016-05-04|newspaper=The Guardian|language=en-GB|issn=0261-3077|access-date=2016-12-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==In academia==
Some Afrophobic sentiments are based on the belief that Africans are unsophisticated. Such perceptions include the belief that Africans lack a history of [[civilization]], and visual imagery of such [[stereotypes of Africans|stereotypes perpetuate the notion that Africans]] still live in mud huts and carry spears, along with other notions that indicate their primitiveness.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Mays |first1=Vickie M. |title=The Black American and psychotherapy: The dilemma. |journal=Psychotherapy: Theory, Research, Practice, Training |date=1985 |volume=22 |issue=2S |pages=379–388 |doi=10.1037/h0085518}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first1=Ngonidzashe |last1=Marongwe |first2=Munyaradzi |last2=Mawere |chapter=Violence, Identity and Politics of Belonging: The April 2015 Afrophobic Attacks in South Africa and the Emergence of Some Discourses |pages=89–116 |chapter-url=https://muse.jhu.edu/chapter/1878812 |editor1-last=Munyaradzi |editor1-first=Mawere |editor2-last=Ngonidzashe |editor2-first=Marongwe |title=Violence, Politics and Conflict Management in Africa: Envisioning Transformation, Peace and Unity in the Twenty-First Century |date=2016 |publisher=Langaa RPCIG |isbn=978-9956-763-54-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Afrophobia in academia may also occur through by oversight with regards to lacking deconstruction in mediums such as African art forms, omitting historical African polities in world cartography, or promoting a eurocentric viewpoint by ignoring historic African contributions to world civilization.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Skinner |first1=Ryan Thomas |title=Walking, talking, remembering: an Afro-Swedish critique of being-in-the-world |journal=African and Black Diaspora |date=24 April 2018 |volume=12 |issue=1 |pages=1–19 |doi=10.1080/17528631.2018.1467747 |s2cid=149746823 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Afrophilia]]
*[[Aporophobia]]
*[[Xenophobia]]
*[[Ethnocentrism]]
*[[Discrimination based on skin color]]
*[[White nationalism]]
*[[White supremacy]]
*[[Negro]]
*[[Nigger]]
*[[Antiziganism]]
*[[Anti-Mexican sentiment]]
*[[Hispanophobia]]
*[[Racial antisemitism]]
*[[Anti-Europeanism]]
*[[Antisemitism]]
*[[Racism against Black Americans]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{Anti-cultural sentiment}}
{{White nationalism}}

[[Category:Xenophobia]]
[[Category:African society]]

{{socio-stub}}
{{africa-stub}}</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>