<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20201116211951|989065114" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="33813650" pageid="33813650" ns="0" title="Persecution of minority Muslim groups"><revisions><rev timestamp="2020-11-16T21:59:04Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{See also|Persecution of Muslims}}

A number of Sub-groups within the [[Islam|Muslim faith]] have been persecuted for different reasons by different Muslim-majority sects during various periods in the [[history of Islam]] and the reasons for their persecution include but are not limited to theological disagreements.

==Ahmadis==

{{Main|Persecution of Ahmadiyya}}
The [[Ahmadiyya]] regard themselves as Muslims, but that is disputed by many Muslim groups for a disagreement over the belief in the finality of [[Prophets in Islam|prophethood]] since the death of [[Muhammad]].

In Bangladesh, armed groups including the group[[Khatme Nabuwwat]] ("Finality of Prophethood"), have launched violent attacks that targeted their mosques.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Bangladesh: Breach of Faith|url=http://hrw.org/reports/2005/bangladesh0605/|publisher=Hrw.org|accessdate=20 August 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Pakistan, the anti-Ahmadiyya movement led Pakistani prime minister Zulfiqar Ali Bhutto to declare that the Ahmadiyyas were "non-Muslims".&lt;ref name="loc"&gt;[http://lcweb2.loc.gov/cgi-bin/query/r?frd/cstdy:@field(DOCID+pk0121) Jamaat-i-Islami] Federal Research Division US Library of Congress&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.law.harvard.edu/students/orgs/hrj/iss16/khan.shtml Persecution of the Ahmadiyya Community in Pakistan: An Analysis Under International Law and International Relations]&lt;/ref&gt; In 1984, the Government of [[Pakistan]], under General [[Muhammad Zia-ul-Haq|Zia-ul-Haq]], passed [[Ordinance XX]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thepersecution.org/50years/paklaw.html Ordinance XX]&lt;/ref&gt; which banned proselytizing by Ahmadis and also banned Ahmadis from referring to themselves as [[Muslim]]s. According to this ordinance, any Ahmadi who refers to oneself as a Muslim by words, either spoken or written, or by visible representation, directly or indirectly, or makes the call for prayer as other Muslims do, is punishable by imprisonment of up to 3 years. Because of these difficulties, [[Mirza Tahir Ahmad]] migrated to London, UK.

==Alawites==

The [[Alawites]] are a sub group of the muslim faith that believe in the divine nature of [[Ali]], the cousin of [[Muhammad]].

[[Ibn Taymiyyah]] pointed out that [[Alawites]] were not Shi'ites and a heretics outside Islam, arguably being the most virulent anti-Alawite in his fatwas&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Daniel Pipes|title=Greater Syria|date=1992|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=978-0-19-536304-3|page=163|quote=|ref={{harvid|Pipes|1992}}}}&lt;/ref&gt; where he cited that [[Alawites]] "are more infidel than Jews or Christians, even more infidel than many polytheists. They have done greater harm to the community of Muhammad than have the warring infidels such as the Franks, the Turks, and others. To ignorant Muslims they pretend to be Shi’is, though in reality they do not believe in God or His prophet or His book…Whenever possible, they spill the blood of Muslims…They are always the worst enemies of the Muslims…war and punishment in accordance with Islamic law against them are among the greatest of pious deeds and the most important obligations".&lt;ref&gt;The Nusayris are more infidel than Jews or Christians, even more infidel than many polytheists. They have done greater harm to the community of Muhammad than have the warring infidels such as the Franks, the Turks, and others. To ignorant Muslims they pretend to be Shi’is, though in reality they do not believe in God or His prophet or His book…Whenever possible, they spill the blood of Muslims…They are always the worst enemies of the Muslims…war and punishment in accordance with Islamic law against them are among the greatest of pious deeds and the most important obligations". – Ibn Taymiyyah, as quoted by Daniel Pipes (1992). Greater Syria. Oxford University Press. p. 163. {{ISBN|9780195363043}}.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Ottomans]] have often relied on Ibn Taymiyya religious ruling to justify their persecution of [[Alawites]] .&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title= The Druzes: An Annotated Bibliography|first=Samy|last= S. Swayd|year= 2009| isbn= 9780966293203| page =25 |publisher=University of Michigan Press|quote= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Mutazilites==

In medieval Iraq, the [[Mu'tazili]] theological movement was made a state doctrine in 832, igniting the [[Mihna]] (ordeal) a struggle over the application of Greek logical proof of the Qu'ran; people who would not accept Mu'tazili claims that the Qur'an was created rather than eternal were sometimes persecuted. The most famous victims of the Mihna were [[Ahmad Ibn Hanbal]] who was imprisoned and tortured, and the judge Ahmad Ibn Nasr al-Khuza'i who was crucified.&lt;ref&gt;[http://iskandrani.wordpress.com/2008/02/09/do-not-envy-anyone-who-has-not-been-harmed-for-the-sake-of-this-affair/ “Do not envy anyone who has not been harmed for the sake of this affair.” « A Resource of Translated Islamic Texts]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Ahmad Ibn Hanbal]] was dragged before the inquisition, known as the [[Mihna]], ordered by the caliph [[al-Maʾmūn]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/10121/Ahmad-ibn-Hanbal Ahmad ibn Hanbal -- Britannica Online Encyclopedia]&lt;/ref&gt;

However, it lost official support soon afterwards. This coincided with the rise to prominence of the [[Ash'ari]] approach to Islam, of which [[Al-Ghazali]] was a staunch defender. [[Sunni]] and [[Shi'a]] Islam became the mainstream schools of Islam.
in the centuries to follow, some Mutazili scholars were victims of persecution themselves.[https://web.archive.org/web/20110927172216/http://www.cmima.csic.es/mirror/mattom/science+society/lectures/illustrations/lecture16/ibnsina.html Science, civilization and society]&lt;/ref&gt; Mu'tazilite doctrine - by now regarded as heretical by Sunnis - continued to be influential amongst some Shia in Persia and Zaydis in Yemen.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.muslimphilosophy.com/ip/rep/H052 Ash'ariyya and Mu'tazila]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Shi'a==

{{Main|Persecution of Shia Muslims|Shi'a–Sunni relations}}

Through different parts of history, Shi'a Muslims have faced persecution. All of the [[Twelve Imams]] of [[Shia Islam]] have been martyred and their followers persecuted by either [[Kharijites]], the [[Umayyads]], or [[Abassids]]. In 1513, [[Ottoman Empire|Ottoman]] Sultan [[Selim I]] ("The Grim") ordered the massacre of 40,000 [[Shia]] Muslim "heretics" in Anatolia during the Safavid-Ottoman struggles.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thomasmorestudies.org/segn/control/context?docId=65&amp;searchDocId=65&amp;selectedDoc=65&amp;offset=0&amp;version=modern&amp;xpath=/wp:Document/wp:Content/page%5B1%5D&amp;allDoc=true St Thomas More Studies] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20111002035109/http://www.thomasmorestudies.org/segn/control/context?docId=65&amp;searchDocId=65&amp;selectedDoc=65&amp;offset=0&amp;version=modern&amp;xpath=%2Fwp%3ADocument%2Fwp%3AContent%2Fpage%5B1%5D&amp;allDoc=true |date=2011-10-02 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.uni-mannheim.de/mateo/camenaref/cmh/cmh103.html The Ottoman Conquest]&lt;/ref&gt;

While the dominant strand in modern Sunni dogma regards Shiism as a valid ''madhhab'', following [[Al Azhar]], some Sunnis both now and in the past have regarded it as beyond the pale, and have attacked its adherents.  In modern times, notable examples include the bombing campaigns by the Sunni [[Sipah-e-Sahaba]] against Shia mosques in [[Pakistan]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://ipsnews.net/news.asp?idnews=39432 RELIGION-PAKISTAN: Shia-Sunni Tensions Surface on Campus] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120115013021/http://ipsnews.net/news.asp?idnews=39432 |date=2012-01-15 }}&lt;/ref&gt; the genocide of [[Hazara people|Hazara]] under the [[Taliban]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/south_asia/1608289.stm BBC News | SOUTH ASIA | Hazara people's long suffering]&lt;/ref&gt; and the bloody attacks linked with [[Zarqawi]] and his Sunni followers against Shia in Iraq.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/6293230.stm BBC NEWS | Middle East | Crushing Iraq's human mosaic]&lt;/ref&gt;

Some of the worst Shia-Sunni sectarian strife has occurred before (under Saddam regime responsible for at least 400,000 Shia deaths) after the [[Iraq War|American invasion of Iraq]], steadily building up to present.{{when|date=July 2012}}&lt;ref name="Civil War"&gt;[https://www.motherjones.com/news/featurex/2007/03/civil_war.html Civil War]&lt;/ref&gt; According to one estimate, as of early 2008, 1,121 Sunni suicide bombers have blown themselves up in Shia-majority Iraq.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.commondreams.org/archive/2008/03/14/7682/ March 14, 2008 The Independent/UK "The Cult of the Suicide Bomber" by Robert Fisk ] "month-long investigation by The Independent, culling four Arabic-language newspapers, official Iraqi statistics, two Beirut news agencies and Western reports"&lt;/ref&gt; Sunni [[suicide attack|suicide bombers]] have targeted not only thousands of civilians,&lt;ref&gt;over half of the 20,000 fatalities worldwide from terrorism in 2006 occurred in Iraq according to the American National Counterterrorism Center [http://wits.nctc.gov/reports/crot2006nctcannexfinal.pdf Report on Terrorist Incidents 2006] p.3 {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090326171214/http://wits.nctc.gov/reports/crot2006nctcannexfinal.pdf |date=March 26, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; but [[2006 al-Askari Mosque bombing|mosques]], shrines,&lt;ref&gt;[http://english.aljazeera.net/NR/exeres/BA05CFF2-8D0A-4B2D-BBD0-B92EB85E1267.htm Al Jazeera English - News - Car Bomb Blast Near Iraq Shrine]&lt;/ref&gt; wedding and funeral processions,&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.cbc.ca/news/world/iraqi-funeral-procession-bombed-at-least-26-killed-1.679220 Iraqi funeral procession bombed; at least 26 killed]&lt;/ref&gt; markets, hospitals, offices, and streets.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvp|Nasr|2007|p=203}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Saudi Arabian government has been viewed as repressive against Shias living in Saudi Arabia, mainly because it encourages the [[Salafi]] faith, which denounces Shia Islam as heretical. Shias are mainly persecuted due to the belief that they are Iranian "puppets" and traitors. In several Saudi Arabian cities, Shia [[azans]] and [[Day of Ashura|Ashura]] demonstrations are banned.{{citation needed|date=August 2016}}

==Sunni Madhabs==

Yaqub Beg's Uyghur forces declared a Jihad against [[Hui people|Chinese Muslims]] under T'o Ming during the [[Dungan revolt (1862–1877)|Dungan revolt]]. The Uyghurs thought that the Chinese Muslims were [[Shafi`i]], and since the Uyghurs were [[Hanafi]] that they should wage war against them. Yaqub Beg enlisted non Muslim Han Chinese militia under Hsu Hsuehkung in order to fight against the Chinese Muslims. T'o Ming's forces were defeated by Yaqub, who planned to conquer Dzungharia. Yaqub intended to seize all Dungan territory.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvp|Fairbank|Liu|Twitchett|1980|p=223}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvp|Fairbank|Liu|Twitchett|1980|p=224}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Takfiris==

Certain small groups - the [[Kharijite]]s of early medieval times, and [[Takfir wal Hijra]]- follow ''[[takfir]]ist'' doctrines, regarding almost all other Muslims as infidels whose blood may legitimately be shed.&lt;ref&gt;[http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qa5400/is_200112/ai_n21482222/pg_9 new global threat: Transnational Salafis and Jihad], The Middle East Policy&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200405/cmselect/cmfaff/36/5020105.htm House of Commons - Foreign Affairs - Minutes of Evidence]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Wahhabis==

The [[Kuomintang]] [[Sufi]] [[Hui people|Chinese Muslim]] General [[Ma Bufang]], who backed the [[Yihewani]] (Ikhwan) Muslims, persecuted the Salafi/[[Wahhabi]]s. The Yihewani forced the Salafis into hiding. They were not allowed to move or worship openly. The Yihewani had become secular and Chinese nationalist, and they considered the Salafiyya to be "Heterodox" (xie jiao), and people who followed foreigner's teachings (waidao). Only after the Communists took over were the Salafis allowed to come out and worship openly.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=wEih57-GWQQC&amp;pg=PA79&amp;dq=ma+bufang+secret+war&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=Lh6YTKKkLYT68AbGy7iKAQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CCgQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=ma%20bufang%20secret%20war&amp;f=false|title=Guide to Islamist Movements|author=BARRY RUBIN|year=2000|publisher=M.E. Sharpe|location=|page=79|isbn=0-7656-1747-1|accessdate=2010-06-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Sectarian violence among Muslims]]
* [[Persecution of Sufis]]

==References==
{{Reflist|32em}}

===Bibliography===
{{refbegin}}
*{{cite book |last=Das |first=Arbind |year=1996 |title=Arthashastra of Kautilya and Fatwa-i-Jahandari of Ziauddin Barrani: an analysis |publisher=Pratibha Publications |location=Delhi |isbn=81-85268-45-2 |ref=harv}}
*{{cite book |last1=Fairbank |first1=John King |first2=Kwang-ching |last2=Liu |first3=Denis Crispin |last3=Twitchett |year=1980 |title=Late Ch'ing, 1800–1911 |publisher=Cambridge University Press|location=|isbn=0-521-22029-7 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=pEfWaxPhdnIC&amp;dq=t%27o+ming+yakub&amp;q=jihad#v=onepage&amp;q=religious%20war%20against%20the%20tungans%20also%20sunnis&amp;f=false |ref=harv}}
*{{cite book |last=Nasr |first=Vali |year=2007 |title=The Shia Revival: How Conflicts within Islam Will Shape the Future |publisher=W.&amp;nbsp;W. Norton &amp; Co. |isbn=9780393066401 |ref=harv}}
{{refend}}

[[Category:History of Islam]]
[[Category:Persecution of Muslims]]
[[Category:Persecution by Muslims]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>