<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20240930080526|1248572092" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="33813650" pageid="33813650" ns="0" title="Persecution of minority Muslim groups"><revisions><rev timestamp="2024-09-30T08:06:51Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|History of religious oppression}}
{{distinguish|Persecution of Muslims}}
{{Discrimination sidebar|expand-religious=yes}}
A number of minority groups within Islam have faced persecution by other Muslims for allegedly being incompatible with the regional majority of [[Islam]]. Accusation of [[heresy]] or [[Apostasy in Islam|apostasy]] can result in [[takfir]] ([[excommunication]]).&lt;ref name="EncyclopediaofIslam"&gt;{{cite encyclopedia |author1-last=Hunwick |author1-first=Ed |author2-last=Hunwick |author2-first=J. O. |year=2000 |title=Takfīr |editor1-last=Bosworth |editor1-first=C. E. |editor1-link=Clifford Edmund Bosworth |editor2-last=van Donzel |editor2-first=E. J. |editor2-link=Emeri Johannes van Donzel |editor3-last=Heinrichs |editor3-first=W. P. |editor3-link=Wolfhart Heinrichs |editor4-last=Lewis |editor4-first=B. |editor5-last=Pellat |editor5-first=Ch. |editor5-link=Charles Pellat |editor6-last=Bearman |editor6-first=P. J. |editor6-link=Peri Bearman |encyclopedia=[[Encyclopaedia of Islam#2nd edition, EI2|Encyclopaedia of Islam]] |edition=2nd |location=[[Leiden]] |publisher=[[Brill Publishers]] |volume=10 |doi=10.1163/1573-3912_islam_COM_1154 |isbn=978-90-04-16121-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Ahmadis==

{{Main|Persecution of Ahmadiyya}}
The [[Ahmadiyya]] regard themselves as Muslims, but are seen by many other Muslims as non-Muslims and "heretics" since they are accused of not believing in the finality of [[Prophets in Islam|prophethood]] since the death of [[Muhammad]]. Armed groups, led by the umbrella organization [[Khatme Nabuwat Andolon Bangladesh|Khatme Nabuwwat]] ("Finality of Prophethood"), have launched violent attacks against their mosques in Bangladesh.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Bangladesh: Breach of Faith|url=http://hrw.org/reports/2005/bangladesh0605/|publisher=Hrw.org|access-date=20 August 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

They committed massacres against them which resulted in 2,000 Ahmadiyya deaths in Pakistani Punjab. Eventually, martial law had to be established and Governor general Ghulam Mohamed dismissed the federal cabinet. This anti-Ahmadiyya movement led Pakistani prime minister Zulfiqar Ali Bhutto to declare that the Ahmadiyyas were "non-Muslims".&lt;ref name="loc"&gt;[http://lcweb2.loc.gov/cgi-bin/query/r?frd/cstdy:@field(DOCID+pk0121) Jamaat-i-Islami] Federal Research Division US Library of Congress&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.law.harvard.edu/students/orgs/hrj/iss16/khan.shtml Persecution of the Ahmadiyya Community in Pakistan: An Analysis Under International Law and International Relations]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1984, the Government of [[Pakistan]], under General [[Muhammad Zia-ul-Haq|Zia-ul-Haq]], passed [[Ordinance XX]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thepersecution.org/50years/paklaw.html Ordinance XX]&lt;/ref&gt; which banned proselytizing by Ahmadis and also banned Ahmadis from referring to themselves as [[Muslim]]s. According to this ordinance, any Ahmadi who refers to oneself as a Muslim by words, either spoken or written, or by visible representation, directly or indirectly, or makes the call for prayer as other Muslims do, is punishable by imprisonment of up to 3 years. Because of these difficulties, [[Mirza Tahir Ahmad]] migrated to London, UK.

==Ajlafs and Arzals==

{{Main|Caste system among South Asian Muslims}}
Despite the claims of [[Islam]]'s egalitarian tenets,{{additional citation|date=June 2017}} units of social stratification, termed as "castes" by many, have developed among Muslims in some parts of South Asia.&lt;ref name="Britannica"&gt;[http://www.britannica.com/eb/article-9042918 "Islamic caste."] Encyclopædia Britannica. 2006. Encyclopædia Britannica Online. 18 Oct. 2006&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="EoI"&gt;[[John Burton-Page|Burton-Page, J.]], [http://www.brillonline.nl/subscriber/entry?entry=islam_SIM-2884 Hindū], ''[[Encyclopaedia of Islam]]''. Edited by: [[Peri Bearman|P. Bearman]], Th. Bianquis, [[C. E. Bosworth]], E. van Donzel and [[W. P. Heinrichs]]. Brill, 2006. Brill Online.&lt;/ref&gt; Various theories have been put forward regarding the development of castes among Indian Muslims. Majority of  sources state that the castes among Muslims developed as the result of close contact with Hindu culture and Hindu converts to Islam,&lt;ref name="Britannica"/&gt;&lt;ref name="EoI"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Muslim Caste in Uttar Pradesh (A Study of Culture Contact), Ghaus Ansari, Lucknow, 1960, Page 66&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Sikand"&gt;{{cite web|last = Singh Sikand|first = Yoginder|title = Caste in Indian Muslim Society|publisher = Hamdard University|url = http://stateless.freehosting.net/Caste%20in%20Indian%20Muslim%20Society.htm|access-date = 18 October 2006 }}&lt;/ref&gt; while few others feel that these developed based on claims of descent from Muhammad.&lt;ref name="Alvi"&gt;Sajida Sultana Alvi, Advice on the art of governance, an Indo-Islamic Mirror for Princes P122, State University of New York Press, {{ISBN|0-88706-918-5}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Imtiaz"&gt;Ahmad, Imtiaz, "The Ashraf-Ajlaf dichotomy in Muslim social structure in India", Indian economic and social history review 33 (1966) pgs 268-78&lt;/ref&gt;

Sections of the ulema (scholars of Islamic jurisprudence) have declared the religious legitimacy of the caste system with the help of the concept of kafa'a.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Sinnett, William M.|url=http://worldcat.org/oclc/437925442|title=Audit fee survey : May 2009|date=2009|publisher=FERF|isbn=978-1-4416-2268-6|oclc=437925442}}&lt;/ref&gt; A classic example of scholarly literature supporting the Muslim caste system is the ''Fatawa-i Jahandari'', written by the 14th century Turkish scholar, Ziauddin Barani, a member of the court of  [[Muhammad bin Tughlaq]], of the Tughlaq dynasty of the Delhi Sultanate. Barani was known for his intensely casteist views, and he regarded the Ashraf Muslims as racially superior to the Ajlaf Muslims{{Citation needed|date=May 2009}}.

He divided the Muslims into grades and sub-grades. In his scheme, all high positions and privileges were to be a monopoly of the high born Turks, not the Indian Muslims{{Citation needed|date=May 2009}}. Even in his interpretation of the Koranic verse "Indeed, the pious amongst you are most honored by Allah", he considered piety to be associated with noble birth.&lt;ref name="Alvi"/&gt; Barrani was specific in his recommendation that the "sons of Mohamed" [i.e. Ashrafs] "be given a higher social status than the low-born [i.e. Ajlaf].&lt;ref name="Das_138_139"&gt;{{harvp|Das|1996|pp=138–139}}&lt;/ref&gt; His most significant contribution in the fatwa was his analysis of the castes with respect to Islam.&lt;ref name="Das2"&gt;{{harvp|Das|1996|p=124}}&lt;/ref&gt; His assertion was that castes would be mandated through state laws or "Zawabi" which would carry precedence over [[Sharia]] law whenever they were in conflict.&lt;ref name="Das2"/&gt;

In the Fatwa-i-Jahandari (advice XXI), he wrote about the "qualities of the high-born" as being "virtuous" and the "low-born" as being the "custodians of vices". Every act which is "contaminated with meanness and based on ignominy, comes elegantly [from the Ajlaf]".&lt;ref&gt;{{harvp|Das|1996|p=143}}&lt;/ref&gt; Barani had a clear disdain for the Ajlaf and strongly recommended that they be denied education, lest they usurp the Ashraf masters{{Citation needed|date=May 2009}}. He sought appropriate religious sanction to that effect.&lt;ref name="Sikand"/&gt; Barrani also developed an elaborate system of promotion and demotion of Imperial officers ("Wazirs") that was conducted primarily on the basis of caste.&lt;ref name="Das_138_139"/&gt;

In addition to the Ashraf/Ajlaf divide, there is also the ''Arzal'' caste among Muslims,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.bbc.com/news/world-asia-india-36220329|title=Why are many Indian Muslims seen as untouchable?}}&lt;/ref&gt; whose members were regarded by anti-Caste activists like Babasaheb [[B. R. Ambedkar|Ambedkar]] as the equivalent of untouchables.&lt;ref name="Ambedkar"&gt;{{cite book |last = Ambedkar |first = Bhimrao |author-link = B.R. Ambedkar |title = Pakistan or the Partition of India |publisher =  Thackers Publishers  }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Ambedkaronline"&gt;[http://www.columbia.edu/itc/mealac/pritchett/00ambedkar/ambedkar_partition/410.html Web resource for ''Pakistan or the Partition of India'']&lt;/ref&gt; The term "Arzal" stands for "degraded" and the Arzal castes are further subdivided into Bhanar, Halalkhor, Hijra, Kasbi, Lalbegi, Maugta, Mehtar etc.&lt;ref name="Ambedkar"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Ambedkaronline"/&gt; The Arzal group was recorded in the 1901 census in India and its members are also called [[Dalit]] Muslims "with whom no other Muhammadan would associate, and who are forbidden to enter the mosque or to use the public burial ground"{{Citation needed|date=May 2009}}.They are relegated to "menial" professions such as scavenging and carrying [[night soil]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.indianexpress.com/story/12109.html Dereserve these myths] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080516075059/http://www.indianexpress.com/story/12109.html |date=2008-05-16 }} by Tanweer Fazal,''Indian express''&lt;/ref&gt;

==Alawites==

The [[Alawites]] are a sub group of the Muslim faith that believes in the divine nature of [[Ali]], the cousin of [[Muhammad]].

[[Ibn Taymiyyah]] asserted that Alawites were not Shi'ites and were heretics outside Islam, arguably being the most virulent anti-Alawite in his fatwas&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Daniel Pipes|title=Greater Syria|date=1992|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=978-0-19-536304-3|page=163|ref={{harvid|Pipes|1992}}}}&lt;/ref&gt; where he stated that Alawites "are more infidel than Jews or Christians, even more infidel than many polytheists. They have done greater harm to the community of Muhammad than have the warring infidels such as the Franks, the Turks, and others. To ignorant Muslims they pretend to be Shi’is, though in reality they do not believe in God or His prophet or His book&lt;nowiki&gt;[...]&lt;/nowiki&gt; Whenever possible, they spill the blood of Muslims&lt;nowiki&gt;[...]&lt;/nowiki&gt; They are always the worst enemies of the Muslims&lt;nowiki&gt;[...]&lt;/nowiki&gt; war and punishment in accordance with Islamic law against them are among the greatest of pious deeds and the most important obligations".&lt;ref&gt;The Nusayris are more infidel than Jews or Christians, even more infidel than many polytheists. They have done greater harm to the community of Muhammad than have the warring infidels such as the Franks, the Turks, and others. To ignorant Muslims they pretend to be Shi’is, though in reality they do not believe in God or His prophet or His book…Whenever possible, they spill the blood of Muslims…They are always the worst enemies of the Muslims…war and punishment in accordance with Islamic law against them are among the greatest of pious deeds and the most important obligations". – Ibn Taymiyyah, as quoted by Daniel Pipes (1992). Greater Syria. Oxford University Press. p. 163. {{ISBN|9780195363043}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Ottoman Empire|Ottomans]] often relied on Ibn Taymiyya's religious rulings to justify their persecution of Alawites.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title= The Druzes: An Annotated Bibliography|first=Samy|last= S. Swayd|year= 2009| isbn= 9780966293203| page =25 |publisher=University of Michigan Press}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Mutazilites==

In medieval Iraq, the [[Mu'tazili]] theological movement was made a state doctrine in 832, igniting the [[Mihna]] (ordeal) a struggle over the application of Greek logical proof of the Qu'ran; people who would not accept Mu'tazili claims that the Qur'an was created rather than eternal were sometimes persecuted.  The most famous victims of the Mihna were [[Ahmad Ibn Hanbal]] who was imprisoned and tortured, and the judge Ahmad Ibn Nasr al-Khuza'i who was crucified.&lt;ref&gt;[http://iskandrani.wordpress.com/2008/02/09/do-not-envy-anyone-who-has-not-been-harmed-for-the-sake-of-this-affair/ “Do not envy anyone who has not been harmed for the sake of this affair.” « A Resource of Translated Islamic Texts]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Ahmad Ibn Hanbal]] was dragged before the inquisition, known as the [[Mihna]], ordered by the caliph [[al-Maʾmūn]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/10121/Ahmad-ibn-Hanbal Ahmad ibn Hanbal – Britannica Online Encyclopedia]&lt;/ref&gt;

However, it lost official support soon afterwards. This coincided with the rise to prominence of the [[Ash'ari]] approach to Islam, of which [[Al-Ghazali]] was a staunch defender. [[Sunni]] and [[Shi'a]] Islam became the mainstream schools of Islam.
As a consequence, the tables turned and some Mutazili scholars were victims of persecution themselves in the centuries to follow. Some [[Islamic philosophy|Islamic philosophers]] like [[Averroes]] and [[Avicenna]] also faced persecution from fellow Muslims in their time.&lt;ref&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20110927172216/http://www.cmima.csic.es/mirror/mattom/science+society/lectures/illustrations/lecture16/ibnsina.html Science, civilization and society]&lt;/ref&gt; Mu'tazilite doctrine – by now regarded as heretical by Sunnis – continued to be influential amongst some Shia in Persia and Zaydis in Yemen.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.muslimphilosophy.com/ip/rep/H052 Ash'ariyya and Mu'tazila]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Shi'a==

{{Main|Persecution of Shia Muslims|Shi'a–Sunni relations}}

Throughout history, Shi'as have faced genocide in Sunni majority locations. In 1513, [[Ottoman Empire|Ottoman]] Sultan [[Selim I]] ("The Grim") ordered the massacre of 40,000 [[Shia]] "heretics" in Anatolia during the Safavid-Ottoman struggles.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thomasmorestudies.org/segn/control/context?docId=65&amp;searchDocId=65&amp;selectedDoc=65&amp;offset=0&amp;version=modern&amp;xpath=/wp:Document/wp:Content/page%5B1%5D&amp;allDoc=true St Thomas More Studies] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20111002035109/http://www.thomasmorestudies.org/segn/control/context?docId=65&amp;searchDocId=65&amp;selectedDoc=65&amp;offset=0&amp;version=modern&amp;xpath=%2Fwp%3ADocument%2Fwp%3AContent%2Fpage%5B1%5D&amp;allDoc=true |date=2011-10-02 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.uni-mannheim.de/mateo/camenaref/cmh/cmh103.html The Ottoman Conquest]&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Mughal Empire|Mughal]] emperor [[Aurangzeb|Aurengzeb]] is also recorded to have persecuted Shi‘a communities. His persecution of the [[Isma'ilism|Ismaili]] successor to Imam al-Din, or Imamshah, changed the course of the history of his community of followers. Common folk took up arms against the military and captured the fortress of Broach. However, their initial success did not last and, along with other sister communities, they were put down.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Virani|first=Shafique N.|title=Taqiyya and Identity in a South Asian Community|url=https://www.academia.edu/36996009|journal=The Journal of Asian Studies|year=2011|volume=70|issue=1|pages=99–139|doi=10.1017/S0021911810002974|s2cid=143431047|issn=0021-9118}}&lt;/ref&gt;

While some strand in Sunni regards Shiism as a valid ''madhhab'', following [[Al Azhar]], some Sunnis both now and in the past have regarded it as beyond the pale, and have attacked its adherents.  In modern times, notable examples include the bombing campaigns by the Sunni [[Sipah-e-Sahaba]] against Shia mosques in [[Pakistan]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://ipsnews.net/news.asp?idnews=39432 RELIGION-PAKISTAN: Shia-Sunni Tensions Surface on Campus] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120115013021/http://ipsnews.net/news.asp?idnews=39432 |date=2012-01-15 }}&lt;/ref&gt; the genocide of [[Hazara people|Hazara]] under the [[Taliban]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/south_asia/1608289.stm BBC News | SOUTH ASIA | Hazara people's long suffering]&lt;/ref&gt; and the bloody attacks linked with [[Zarqawi]] and his Sunni followers against Shia in Iraq.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/6293230.stm BBC NEWS | Middle East | Crushing Iraq's human mosaic]&lt;/ref&gt;

Some of the worst Shia-Sunni sectarian strife has occurred before (under Saddam regime responsible for at least 400,000 Shia deaths) and after the [[Iraq War|American invasion of Iraq]].&lt;ref name="Civil War"&gt;[https://www.motherjones.com/news/featurex/2007/03/civil_war.html Civil War]&lt;/ref&gt; According to one estimate, as of early 2008, 1,121 Sunni suicide bombers have blown themselves up in Shia-majority Iraq.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.commondreams.org/archive/2008/03/14/7682/ March 14, 2008 The Independent/UK "The Cult of the Suicide Bomber" by Robert Fisk ] "month-long investigation by The Independent, culling four Arabic-language newspapers, official Iraqi statistics, two Beirut news agencies and Western reports"&lt;/ref&gt; Sunni [[suicide attack|suicide bombers]] have targeted not only thousands of civilians,&lt;ref&gt;over half of the 20,000 fatalities worldwide from terrorism in 2006 occurred in Iraq according to the American National Counterterrorism Center [http://wits.nctc.gov/reports/crot2006nctcannexfinal.pdf Report on Terrorist Incidents 2006] p.3 {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090326171214/http://wits.nctc.gov/reports/crot2006nctcannexfinal.pdf |date=March 26, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; but [[2006 al-Askari Mosque bombing|mosques]], shrines,&lt;ref&gt;[http://english.aljazeera.net/NR/exeres/BA05CFF2-8D0A-4B2D-BBD0-B92EB85E1267.htm Al Jazeera English – News – Car Bomb Blast Near Iraq Shrine]&lt;/ref&gt; wedding and funeral processions,&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.cbc.ca/news/world/iraqi-funeral-procession-bombed-at-least-26-killed-1.679220 Iraqi funeral procession bombed; at least 26 killed]&lt;/ref&gt; markets, hospitals, offices, and streets.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvp|Nasr|2007|p=203}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Saudi Arabian government has been viewed as repressive against Shias living in Saudi Arabia, mainly because it encourages the [[Salafi]] faith, which denounces Shia Islam as heretical. Shias are mainly persecuted due to the belief that they are Iranian "puppets" and traitors. In several Saudi Arabian cities, Shia [[azans]] and [[Day of Ashura|Ashura]] demonstrations are banned.{{citation needed|date=August 2016}}

==Sunni==
{{Main|Anti-Sunnism}}
The [[Safavid conversion of Iran to Shia Islam]] was a process that took place roughly over the 16th through 18th centuries and turned [[Iran]] (Persia), which previously had a [[Sunni]] majority, into the spiritual bastion of [[Twelver|Twelver Shi'ism]]. It was a process that involved [[forced conversion]]&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=UOk7DwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA40|title=Psycho-nationalism|publisher=Cambridge University Press|year=2017|page=40|author=Arshin Adib-Moghaddam|isbn=9781108423076|quote=Shah Ismail pursued a relentless campaign of forced conversion of the majority Sunni population in Iran to (Twelver) Shia Islam...}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=-84NDgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT92|title=Conversion and Islam in the Early Modern Mediterranean: The Lure of the Other|page=92|publisher=Routledge|year=2017|isbn=9781317159780}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=huOBwihhwyQC|title=Islam: Art and Architecture|publisher=Könemann|year=2004|page=501|isbn=9783833111785|quote=Shah persecuted the philosophers, mystics, and Sufis who had been promoted by his grandfather, and unleashed fanatical campaigns of forcible conversion on Sunnis, Jews, Christians and other religious minorities}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=1CLD3-paPYQC&amp;pg=PA61|title=What Every American Should Know about the Middle East|publisher=Penguin|author=Melissa L. Rossi|year=2008|isbn=9780452289598|quote=Forced conversion in the Safavid Empire made Persia for the first time dominantly Shia and left a lasting mark: Persia, now Iran, has been dominantly Shia ever since, and for centuries the only country to have a ruling Shia majority.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Ismail I]] consolidated his rule over the country and launched a thorough and, at times, brutal campaign to convert the majority Sunni population to [[Twelver Shiism]] and thus transform the religious landscape of Iran.&lt;ref&gt;[https://archive.org/details/modernmiddleeast0000kamr/page/29 &lt;!-- quote=safavid persia conversion. --&gt; The modern Middle East: a political history since the First World War].  Mehran Kamrava, p. 29.&lt;/ref&gt; His methods of converting Iran included:
*Imposing Shiism as the state and mandatory religion for the whole nation and much forcible conversion of Iranian Sufi Sunnis to Shiism.&lt;ref&gt;Modern Iran: roots and results of revolution].  Nikki R Keddie, Yann Richard, pp. 13, 20&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=MziRd4ddZz4C&amp;dq=safavid+persia+conversion&amp;pg=PA360 The Encyclopedia of world history: ancient, medieval, and modern].  Peter N. Stearns, William Leonard Langer, p. 360.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Immortal: A Military History of Iran and Its Armed Forces.  Steven R Ward, pg.43&lt;/ref&gt;
*He reintroduced the Sadr (Arabic, leader) – an office that was responsible for supervising religious institutions and endowments. With a view to transforming Iran into a [[Shiite]] state, the Sadr was also assigned the task of disseminating Twelver doctrine.&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=J7YJoty2kuIC&amp;dq=safavid+persia+conversion&amp;pg=PA77 Iran: a short history: from Islamization to the present].  Monika Gronke, p. 91.&lt;/ref&gt;
*He destroyed Sunni mosques. This was even noted by [[Tomé Pires]], the Portuguese ambassador to China who visited Iran in 1511–12, who when referring to Ismail noted: "He (i.e. Ismail) reforms our churches, destroys the houses of all [[Moors]] who follow (the [[Sunnah]] of) Muhammad…"&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=Yjf0bM5sFaEC&amp;dq=safavid+persia+conversion&amp;pg=PA20 The Judeo-Persian poet ‘Emrānī and his "Book of treasure": ‘Emrānī's Ganǰ…]  'Emrānī, David Yeroushalmi, p. 20.&lt;/ref&gt;
*He enforced the ritual and compulsory cursing of the first three Muslim Caliphs ([[Abu Bakr]], [[Umar]], and [[Uthman]]) as usurpers, from all mosques, disbanded Sunni [[Tariqah]]s and seized their assets, used state patronage to develop Shia shrines, institutions and religious art and imported Shia scholars to replace Sunni scholars.&lt;ref&gt;A new introduction to Islam.  Daniel W Brown, p. 191.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=EDdGPxC1stIC&amp;dq=safavid+persia+conversion&amp;pg=RA1-PA459  Encyclopaedic Historiography of the Muslim World].  NK Singh, A Samiuddin, p. 90.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=Fz5kgjMDnOIC&amp;dq=sunni+iran&amp;pg=PA72 The Cambridge illustrated history of the Islamic world].  Francis Robinson, p. 72.&lt;/ref&gt;
*He killed Sunnis and destroyed and desecrated their graves and mosques. This caused the Ottoman Sultan [[Bayezid II]] (who initially congratulated Ismail on his victories) to advise and ask the young monarch (in a "fatherly" manner) to stop the anti-Sunni actions. However, Ismail was strongly anti-Sunni, ignored the Sultan's warning, and continued to spread the Shia faith by the sword.&lt;ref&gt;Immortal: A Military History of Iran and Its Armed Forces.  Steven R. Ward, p. 44.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Iran and America: re-kindling a love lost].  Badi Badiozamani, pp. 174–5.&lt;/ref&gt;
*He persecuted, imprisoned, exiled, and executed stubbornly resistant Sunnis.&lt;ref&gt;The Cambridge illustrated history of the Islamic world.  Francis Robinson, p. 72.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=pfrUjjLbv3wC&amp;dq=sunni+iran&amp;pg=RA1-PA51  Iraq: Old Land, New Nation in Conflict].  William Spencer, p. 51.&lt;/ref&gt;
*With the establishment of Safavid rule, there was a very raucous and colourful, almost carnival-like holiday on 26 [[Dhu al-Hijjah]] (or alternatively, 9 [[Rabi' al-awwal]]) celebrating the [[Eid-e-Shuja'|Eid-e-Shuja' or Celebration of assassination of Caliph Umar]]. The highlight of the day was making an effigy of Umar to be cursed, insulted, and finally burned. However, as relations between Iran and Sunni countries improved, the holiday was no longer observed (at least officially).&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=8ZIjyEi1pd8C&amp;pg=PA185 Culture and customs of Iran].  Elton L Daniel, 'Alī Akbar Mahdī, p. 185.&lt;/ref&gt;
*In 1501, Ismail invited all the [[Twelver|Shia]] living outside Iran to come to Iran and be assured of protection from the Sunni majority.&lt;ref&gt;Iraq: Old Land, New Nation in Conflict.  William Spencer, p. 51.&lt;/ref&gt;
*Safavid rulers vandalized and desecrated the grave of famous Early Muslim theologian [[Abu Hanifa]].
*Safavids expelled large number of Iranian Sunni Muslims from [[Iran]] who refused to convert [[Twelver]] shi'ism. Most of these Sunnis settled in the neighbouring Empires; [[Mughal Empire]], [[Ottoman Empire]] and Gulf Arab states.

Yaqub Beg's Uyghur forces declared a Jihad against [[Hui people|Chinese Muslims]] under T'o Ming during the [[Dungan revolt (1862–1877)|Dungan revolt]]. The Uyghurs thought that the Chinese Muslims were [[Shafi`i]], and since the Uyghurs were [[Hanafi]] that they should wage war against them. Yaqub Beg enlisted non Muslim Han Chinese militia under Hsu Hsuehkung in order to fight against the Chinese Muslims. T'o Ming's forces were defeated by Yaqub, who planned to conquer Dzungharia. Yaqub intended to seize all Dungan territory.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvp|Fairbank|Liu|Twitchett|1980|p=223}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvp|Fairbank|Liu|Twitchett|1980|p=224}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Takfiris==

Certain small groups – the [[Kharijite]]s of early medieval times, and [[Takfir wal Hijra]]- follow ''[[takfir]]ist'' doctrines, regarding almost all other Muslims as infidels whose blood may legitimately be shed.&lt;ref&gt;[http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qa5400/is_200112/ai_n21482222/pg_9 new global threat: Transnational Salafis and Jihad], The Middle East Policy&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm200405/cmselect/cmfaff/36/5020105.htm House of Commons – Foreign Affairs – Minutes of Evidence]&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Sectarian violence among Muslims]]
* [[Persecution of Sufis]]
* [[Zandaqa]]
* [[Al-Baqara 256]] – Verse of the Quran saying "there is no compulsion in religion"

==References==
{{Reflist}}

===Bibliography===
{{refbegin}}
*{{cite book |last=Das |first=Arbind |year=1996 |title=Arthashastra of Kautilya and Fatwa-i-Jahandari of Ziauddin Barrani: an analysis |publisher=Pratibha Publications |location=Delhi |isbn=81-85268-45-2 }}
*{{cite book |last1=Fairbank |first1=John King |first2=Kwang-ching |last2=Liu |first3=Denis Crispin |last3=Twitchett |year=1980 |title=Late Ch'ing, 1800–1911 |publisher=Cambridge University Press|isbn=0-521-22029-7 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=pEfWaxPhdnIC&amp;q=religious+war+against+the+tungans+also+sunnis }}
*{{cite book |last=Nasr |first=Vali |year=2007 |title=The Shia Revival: How Conflicts within Islam Will Shape the Future |publisher=W.&amp;nbsp;W. Norton &amp; Co. |isbn=9780393066401 }}
{{refend}}
{{Islam topics|state=collapsed}}
{{Religious persecution}}

[[Category:History of Islam]]
[[Category:Persecution by Muslims]]
[[Category:Persecution of Muslims| ]]
[[Category:Islam-related controversies]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>