<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20231127225115|1187175670" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="40494939" pageid="40494939" ns="0" title="Ecofeminism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2023-11-28T00:53:00Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|Approach to feminism influenced by ecologist movement}}
[[File:Françoise d'Eaubonne wikipédia.jpg|thumb|French writer [[Françoise d'Eaubonne]] coined the term in a 1974 book]]
{{Green politics sidebar|Perspectives}}
{{Feminism sidebar|Variants (general)}}

'''Ecofeminism''' is a branch of [[feminism]] and [[political ecology]]. Ecofeminist thinkers draw on the concept of [[gender]] to analyse the relationships between humans and the natural world.&lt;ref name="MacGregor"&gt;{{cite book |last=MacGregor |first=Sherilyn |title=Beyond mothering earth: ecological citizenship and the politics of care |year=2006 |publisher=[[University of British Columbia Press]] |location=Vancouver |isbn=978-0-7748-1201-6 |page=286}}&lt;/ref&gt; The term was coined by the French writer [[Françoise d'Eaubonne]] in her book {{lang|fr|[[Feminism or death|Le Féminisme ou la Mort]]}} (1974).&lt;ref name="Merchant"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Warren"&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Glazebrook |first=Trish |date=September 2002|title=Karen Warren's Ecofeminism |journal=Ethics &amp; the Environment |volume=7 |issue=2 |pages=12–26 |doi=10.2979/ETE.2002.7.2.12|s2cid=144641656 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Ecofeminist theory asserts a feminist perspective of [[Green politics]] that calls for an egalitarian, collaborative society in which there is no one dominant group.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite book |title=Radical Ecology |last=Merchant |first=Carolyn |publisher=[[Routledge]] |year=2005 |pages=193–221 |chapter=Ecofeminism}}&lt;/ref&gt; Today, there are several branches of ecofeminism, with varying approaches and analyses, including liberal ecofeminism, spiritual/cultural ecofeminism, and social/socialist ecofeminism (or materialist ecofeminism).&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; Interpretations of ecofeminism and how it might be applied to social thought include [[ecofeminist art]], [[social justice]] and [[political philosophy]], religion, contemporary feminism, and poetry.

Ecofeminist analysis explores the connections between women and nature in culture, economy, religion, politics, literature and iconography, and addresses the parallels between the oppression of nature and the oppression of women. These parallels include but are not limited to seeing women and nature as property, seeing men as the curators of culture and women as the curators of nature, and how men dominate women and humans dominate nature. Ecofeminism emphasizes that both women and nature must be respected.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |title=Ecofeminism and the Sacred |last=Adams |first=Carol |publisher=Continuum |year=2007 |pages=1–8}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Though the scope of ecofeminist analysis is dynamic,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://social-ecology.org/wp/wp-content/uploads/2011/12/Sturgeon-Ecofeminist-Movements.pdf |title=Ecofeminist Movements}}&lt;/ref&gt; American author and ecofeminist [[Charlene Spretnak]] has offered one way of categorizing ecofeminist work: 1) through the study of political theory as well as history; 2) through the belief and study of [[Earth religion|nature-based religions]]; 3) through [[environmentalism]].&lt;ref name=":2"&gt;{{cite book |last=Spretnak |first=Charlene |chapter=Ecofeminism: Our Roots and Flowering |title=Reweaving the World: The Emergence of Feminism |editor1-first=Irene |editor1-last=Diamond |editor2-first=Gloria |editor2-last=Ornstein |publisher=Sierra Club Books |date=1990 |pages=3–14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Overview ==
While diverse ecofeminist perspectives have emerged from female activists and thinkers all over the world, academic studies of ecofeminism have been dominated by North American universities. Thus, in the 1993 essay entitled "Ecofeminism: Toward Global Justice and Planetary Health" authors [[Greta Gaard]] and [[Lori Gruen]] outline what they call the "ecofeminist framework". The essay provides a wealth of data and statistics in addition to outlining the theoretical aspects of the ecofeminist critique. The framework described is intended to establish ways of viewing and understanding our current global situations so that we can better understand how we arrived at this point and what may be done to ameliorate the ills.

Building on the work of North American scholars Rosemary Ruether and [[Carolyn Merchant]], Gaard and Gruen argue that there are four sides to this framework:

# The [[Mechanistic Materialism|mechanistic materialist]] model of the universe that resulted from the [[Scientific Revolution|scientific revolution]] and the subsequent reduction of all things into mere resources to be optimized, dead inert matter to be used.
# The rise of [[patriarchal religion]]s and their establishment of gender hierarchies along with their denial of [[Immanence|immanent]] divinity.
# The self and other dualisms and the inherent power and domination ethic it entails.
# Capitalism and its claimed intrinsic need for the exploitation, destruction and instrumentalization of animals, earth and people for the sole purpose of creating [[wealth]].

They hold that these four factors have brought us to what ecofeminists see as a "separation between nature and culture" that is for them the root source of our planetary ills.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Gaard, Greta and|first=Gruen, Lori|date=1993|title=Ecofeminism: Toward Global Justice and Planetary Health|journal=Society and Nature|volume=2|pages=1–35}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Ecofeminism developed out of [[anarcha-feminist]] concerns with abolishing all forms of domination, while focusing on the oppressive nature of humanity's relationship to the natural world.&lt;ref name="Tuana"&gt;{{cite book |editor1-last=Tuana |editor1-first=Nancy |editor2-last=Tong |editor2-first=Rosemarie |title=Feminism And Philosophy: Essential Readings In Theory, Reinterpretation, And Application |date=2018 |publisher=[[Routledge]] |isbn=978-0-8133-2212-4 |pages=327–9 |chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=6wDFDwAAQBAJ&amp;q=ecofeminist+ecofeminism |chapter=Anarcha Feminist and Ecological Feminist Perspectives |via=[[Google Books]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to [[Françoise d'Eaubonne]] in her book ''[[Feminism or death|Le Féminisme ou la Mort]]'' (1974), ecofeminism relates the [[oppression]] and [[Dominance hierarchy|domination]] of all marginalized groups (women, people of color, children, the poor) to the oppression and domination of nature (animals, land, water, air, etc.). In the book, the author argues that oppression, domination, exploitation, and [[colonization]] from the Western [[Patriarchy|patriarchal]] society has directly caused irreversible environmental damage.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt; [[Françoise d'Eaubonne]] was an activist and organizer, and her writing encouraged the eradication of all social injustice, not just injustice against [[women and the environment]].&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{Cite book |title=Ecofeminist Philosophy: A Western Perspective on What It Is and Why It Matters |last=Warren |first=Karen J. |publisher=[[Rowman &amp; Littlefield]] Publishers, Inc |year=2000 |isbn=9780847692996 |location=Lanham, Maryland}}&lt;/ref&gt;

This tradition includes a number of influential texts including: ''Women and Nature'' ([[Susan Griffin]] 1978), ''The Death of Nature'' ([[Carolyn Merchant]] 1980) and ''Gyn/Ecology'' ([[Mary Daly]] 1978). These texts helped to propel the association between domination by men of women and the domination of culture over nature. From these texts feminist activism of the 1980s linked ideas of ecology and the environment. Movements such as the National Toxics Campaign, [[Mothers of East Los Angeles]] (MELA), and Native Americans for a Clean Environment (NACE) were led by women devoted to issues of human health and environmental justice.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |title=Radical Ecology |last=Merchant |first=Carolyn |publisher=[[Routledge]] |year=2005 |pages=169–173}}&lt;/ref&gt; Writings in this circle discussed ecofeminism drawing from Green Party politics, [[peace movement]]s, and [[direct action]] movements.&lt;ref name=":3"&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Lamar |first=Stephanie |year=1991 |title=Ecofeminist Theory and Grassroots Politics |journal=[[Hypatia (journal)|Hypatia]] |volume=6 |issue=1 |pages=28–45 |doi=10.1111/j.1527-2001.1991.tb00207.x |s2cid=145518119}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Gendering nature ==
[[File:Petra Kelly.jpg|thumb|[[Petra Kelly]]]]
Ecofeminist theory asserts that [[capitalist|capitalism]] reflects only [[paternalistic]] and patriarchal values. This notion implies that the effects of capitalism have not benefited women and has led to a harmful split between [[nature]] and [[culture]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Oksala |first=Johanna |date=Spring 2018 |title=Feminism, Capitalism, and Ecology |journal=[[Hypatia (journal)|Hypatia]] |volume=33 |issue=2 |pages=216–234 |doi=10.1111/hypa.12395 |s2cid=149338235}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the 1970s, early ecofeminists discussed that the split can only be healed by the feminine instinct for nurture and [[holistic]] knowledge of nature's processes.

Since then, several ecofeminist scholars have made the distinction that it is not ''because'' women are female or "feminine" that they relate to nature, but because of their similar states of oppression by the same male-dominant forces. The [[marginalization]] is evident in the [[Language and gender|gendered language]] used to describe nature, such as "Mother Earth" or "Mother Nature", and the animalized language used to describe women in derogatory terms.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Warren |first1=Karen J. |title=Feminist Environmental Philosophy |url=https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/feminism-environmental/#LinPer |website=The Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy |publisher=Metaphysics Research Lab, Stanford University |date=2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some discourses link women specifically to the environment because of their traditional social role as a nurturer and [[caregiver]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Stoddart |first1=Mark |last2=Tindall |first2=D. B. |year=2011 |title=Ecofeminism, Hegemonic Masculinity, And Environmental Movement Participation In British Columbia, Canada, 1998-2007: "Women Always Clean Up The Mess" |journal=Sociological Spectrum |volume=31 |issue=3 |pages=342–368 |doi=10.1080/02732173.2011.557065 |s2cid=146343509}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ecofeminists following in this line of thought believe that these connections are illustrated through the coherence of socially-labeled values associated with 'femininity' such as nurturing, which are present both among women and in nature.

Alternatively, ecofeminist and activist [[Vandana Shiva]] wrote that women have a special connection to the environment through their daily interactions and that this connection has been underestimated. According to Shiva, women in subsistence [[Economy|economies]] who produce "wealth in partnership with nature, have been experts in their own right of holistic and ecological knowledge of nature's processes". She makes the point that "these alternative modes of knowing, which are oriented to the social benefits and sustenance needs are not recognized by the [[capitalism|capitalist]] [[Reductionism|reductionist]] paradigm, because it fails to perceive the interconnectedness of nature, or the connection of women's lives, work and knowledge with the creation of wealth (23)".&lt;ref name="Shiva"&gt;{{cite book |last=Shiva |first=Vandana |author-link=Vandana Shiva |title=Staying alive: women, ecology and development |year=1988 |publisher=[[Zed Books]] |location=London |isbn=978-0-86232-823-8}}&lt;/ref&gt; &amp;nbsp;Shiva blames this failure on the Western patriarchal perceptions of development and progress. According to Shiva, patriarchy has labeled women, nature, and other groups not growing the economy as "unproductive".&lt;ref&gt;Shiva, Vandana. "Development as a New Project of Western Patriarchy." ''Reweaving the World: The Emergence of Feminism,'' edited by Irene Diamond and Gloria Ornstein, Sierra Club Books, 1990, pp. 189-200.&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, Australian ecofeminist [[Ariel Salleh]] deepens this materialist ecofeminist approach in dialogue with green politics, [[ecosocialism]], [[genetic engineering]] and climate policy.

== Concepts ==

=== Modern science and ecofeminism ===
In ''Ecofeminism'' (1993) authors [[Vandana Shiva]] and [[Maria Mies]] ponder [[modern science]] and its acceptance as a universal and value-free system. They view the dominant stream of modern science not as objective science but as a projection of Western men's values.&lt;ref name="Mies"&gt;(Mies, Maria, and Vandana Shiva. ''Ecofeminism''. Halifax, N.S. : Fernwood Publications; 1993. 24.)&lt;/ref&gt; The privilege of determining what is considered scientific knowledge and its usage has been controlled by men, and for the most part of history restricted to men. Many examples exist, including the medicalization of [[childbirth]] and the industrialization of [[plant reproduction]].

A common claim within ecofeminist literature is that patriarchal structures justify their dominance through binary opposition, these include but are not limited to: [[heaven]]/earth, mind/body, [[male]]/[[female]], human/animal, spirit/matter, culture/nature and [[White people|white]][[Non-white|/non-white]]. Oppression, according to them, is reinforced by assuming truth in these binaries, which factuality they challenge, and instilling them as 'marvelous to behold' through what they consider to be religious and scientific constructs.&lt;ref name="Hobgood-Oster"&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.clas.ufl.edu/users/bron/PDF--Christianity/Hobgood-Oster--Ecofeminism-International%20Evolution.pdf |title=Ecofeminism: Historic and International Evolution |first=Laura |last=Hobgood-Oster |access-date=March 17, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Vegetarian ecofeminism ===
{{Main|Vegetarian ecofeminism}}
The application of ecofeminism to animal rights has established [[vegetarian ecofeminism]], which asserts that "omitting the oppression of animals from feminist and ecofeminist analyses … is inconsistent with the activist and philosophical foundations of both feminism (as a "movement to end all forms of oppression") and ecofeminism."&lt;ref name="gaard"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Gaard |first1=Greta Claire |year=2002 |title=Vegetarian ecofeminism: A review essay |journal=Frontiers: A Journal of Women Studies |volume=23 |issue=2 |pages=117–146 |doi=10.1353/fro.2003.0006 |s2cid=143879458}}&lt;/ref&gt; It puts into practice "[[the personal is political]]", as many ecofeminists believe that "meat-eating is a form of patriarchal domination…that suggests a link between male violence and a meat-based diet."&lt;ref name="gaard" /&gt; During a 1995 interview with ''On the Issues,'' Carol J. Adams stated, "Manhood is constructed in our culture in part by access to meat-eating and control of other bodies, whether it's women or animals".&lt;ref name=":5"&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://caroljadams.com/new-page-2 |title=Do Feminists Need to Liberate Animals, Too? |website=Carol J. Adams |language=en-US |access-date=2019-04-30 |date=1995}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to Adams, "We cannot work for justice and challenge the oppression of nature without understanding that the most frequent way we interact with nature is by eating animals".&lt;ref name=":5" /&gt; Vegetarian ecofeminism combines sympathy with the analysis of culture and politics to refine a system of ethics and action.&lt;ref name="gaard" /&gt;

=== Materialist ecofeminism ===
The key activist-scholars in materialist ecofeminism are [[Maria Mies]] and Veronika Bennholdt-Thomsen in Germany; Vandana Shiva in India; Ariel Salleh in Australia; Mary Mellor in the UK; and Ana Isla in Peru. Materialist ecofeminism is not widely known in North America aside from the journal collective at ''Capitalism Nature Socialism''. A materialist view connects institutions such as labor, power, and property as the source of domination over women and nature. There are connections made between these subjects because of the values of production and reproduction.&lt;ref name="Borders" /&gt; This dimension of ecofeminism may also be referred to as "social feminism", "socialist ecofeminism", or "Marxist ecofeminism". According to Carolyn Merchant, "Social ecofeminism advocates the liberation of women through overturning economic and social hierarchies that turn all aspects of life into a market society that today even invades the womb".&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; Ecofeminism in this sense seeks to eliminate social hierarchies which favor the production of commodities (dominated by men) over biological and social reproduction.

=== Spiritual and cultural ecofeminism ===
Spiritual ecofeminism is another branch of ecofeminism, and it is popular among ecofeminist authors such as [[Starhawk]], [[Riane Eisler]], and Carol J. Adams. Starhawk calls this an earth-based spirituality, which recognizes that the Earth is alive, and that we are an interconnected community.&lt;ref&gt;Starhawk. "Power, Authority, and Mystery: Ecofeminism and Earth-based Spirituality." ''Reweaving the World: The Emergence of Ecofeminism,'' edited by Irene Diamond and Gloria Orenstein, Sierra Club Books, 1990, pp. 73-86.&lt;/ref&gt; Spiritual ecofeminism is not linked to one specific religion, but is centered around values of caring, [[compassion]], and non-violence.&lt;ref name=":4"&gt;Eisler, Riane. "The Gaia Tradition &amp; The Partnership Future: An Ecofeminist Manifesto." ''Reweaving the World: The Emergence of Ecofeminism,'' edited by Irene Diamond and Gloria Orenstein, Sierra Club Books, 1990, pp. 23-34.&lt;/ref&gt; Often, ecofeminists refer to more ancient traditions, such as the worship of [[Gaia]], the Goddess of nature and spirituality (also known as Mother Earth).&lt;ref name=":4" /&gt; Wicca and Paganism are particularly influential to spiritual ecofeminism. Most Wicca covens demonstrate a deep respect for nature, a feminine outlook, and an aim to establish strong community values.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |title=Radical Ecology |last=Merchant |first=Carolyn |publisher=[[Routledge]] |year=2005 |pages=124–125 |chapter=Spiritual Ecology}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In her book ''Radical Ecology,'' Carolyn Merchant refers to spiritual ecofeminism as "cultural ecofeminism". According to Merchant, cultural ecofeminism, "celebrates the relationship between women and nature through the revival of ancient rituals centered on goddess worship, the moon, animals, and the female reproductive system."&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; In this sense, cultural ecofeminists tend to value intuition, an ethic of caring, and human-nature interrelationships.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

== Environmental movements ==
Susan A. Mann, an eco-feminist and professor of [[Sociological theory|sociological]] and feminist theory, considers the roles women played in these activisms to be the starter for ecofeminism in later centuries. Mann associates the beginning of ecofeminism not with feminists but with women of different races and class backgrounds who made connections among gender, race, class, and environmental issues. This ideal is upheld through the notion that in activist and theory circles marginalized groups must be included in the discussion. In early environmental and women's movements, issues of varying races and classes were often separated.&lt;ref name="Mann" /&gt;

Beginning in the late 20th century, women worked in efforts to protect [[wildlife]], food, air and water.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Glazebrook|first=Trish|date=Autumn 2002|title=Karen Warren's Ecofeminism|journal=Ethics &amp; the Environment|volume=7|issue=2|pages=12–27|doi=10.2979/ete.2002.7.2.12|s2cid=144641656 }}&lt;/ref&gt; These efforts depended largely on new developments in the environmental movement from influential writers, such as [[Henry David Thoreau]], [[Aldo Leopold]], [[John Muir]], and [[Rachel Carson]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Norlock |first=Kathryn J. |date=December 2011 |title=Building Receptivity: Leopold's Land Ethic and Critical Feminist Interpretation |url=https://philpapers.org/rec/NORBRL |journal=[[Journal for the Study of Religion, Nature and Culture]] |volume=5 |issue=4 |pages=491–509 |doi=10.1558/jsrnc.v5i4.491|type=Submitted manuscript}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Seager|first=Joni|date=Spring 2003|title=Rachel Carson Died of Breast Cancer: The Coming of Age of Feminist Environmentalism|journal=Signs: Journal of Women in Culture and Society|volume=28|issue=3|pages=945–973|doi=10.1086/345456|s2cid=146687251}}&lt;/ref&gt; Fundamental examples of women's efforts in the 20th century are the books ''[[Silent Spring]]'' by Rachel Carson and ''Refuge'' by [[Terry Tempest Williams]].

Ecofeminist author [[Karen J. Warren|Karen Warren]] lists Aldo Leopold's essay "[[Land ethic|Land Ethic]]" (1949) as a fundamental work to the ecofeminist conception, as Leopold was the first to pen an ethic for the land which understands all non-human parts of that community (animals, plants, land, air, water) as equal to and in a relationship with humans. This inclusive understanding of the environment launched the modern [[Conservation movement|preservation movement]] and illustrated how issues can be viewed through a framework of caring.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;

Women have participated in [[environmental movement]]s, specifically preservation and conservation beginning in the late nineteenth century and continuing into the early twentieth century.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Mann|first=Susan A.|date=2011|title=Pioneers of U.S. Ecofeminism and Environmental Justice|journal=Feminist Formations|volume=23|issue=2|pages=1–25|doi=10.1353/ff.2011.0028|jstor=41301654|s2cid=146349456}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Movements of the 1970s and 80s ===

In [[India]], in the state of [[Uttarakhand]] in 1973, women took part in the [[Chipko movement]] to protect forests from [[deforestation]]. Many men during this time were moving to cities in search of work, and women that stayed in the rural parts of India were reliant on the forests for subsistence.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.nhpr.org/environment/2021-06-26/sunderlal-bahuguna-chipko-movement-in-india|title=The Life and Legacy of Sunderlal Bahuguna and the Chipko Movement in India |last1=Poon |first1=Felix |website=New Hampshire Public Radio|date=10 January 2022 |access-date= April 9, 2023}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Non violent protest|Non-violent protest]] tactics were used to occupy trees so that [[loggers]] could not cut them down.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;
[[File:Wangari Maathai no Brasil.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Wangari Maathai]]]]
In [[Kenya]] in 1977, the [[Green Belt Movement]] was initiated by environmental and political activist Professor [[Wangari Maathai]]. It is a rural [[tree planting]] program led by women, which Maathai designed to help prevent [[desertification]] in the area. The program created a '[[green belt]]' of at least 1,000 trees around villages, and gave participants the ability to take charge in their communities. In later years, the Green Belt Movement was an advocate for informing and empowering citizens through seminars for civic and environmental education, as well as holding national leaders accountable for their actions and instilling agency in citizens.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.greenbeltmovement.org/who-we-are/our-history|title=Our History|website=The Green Belt Movement|access-date=October 8, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; The work of the Green Belt Movement continues today.

In 1978 in [[New York (state)|New York]], mother and environmentalist [[Lois Gibbs]] led her community in protest after discovering that their entire neighborhood, [[Love Canal]], was built on top of a toxic [[dump site]]. The toxins in the ground were causing illness among children and reproductive issues among women, as well as [[birth defect]]s in babies born to pregnant women exposed to the toxins. The Love Canal movement eventually led to the evacuation and relocation of nearly 800 families by the [[Federal government of the United States|federal government]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://chej.org/about-us/story/love-canal/|title=Love Canal|website=Center for Health, Environment, &amp; Justice|access-date=October 8, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1980 and 1981, women like ecofeminist Ynestra King organized a peaceful protest at the [[Pentagon building|Pentagon]]. Women stood, hand in hand, demanding equal rights (including social, economic, and [[reproductive rights]]) as well as an end to militaristic actions taken by the government and exploitation of the community (people and the environment). This movement is known as the Women's Pentagon Actions.&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt;

In 1985, the [[Akwesasne]] Mother's Milk Project was launched by [[Katsi Cook]]. This study was funded by the government, and investigated how the higher level of contaminants in water near the Mohawk [[Indian reservation|reservation]] impacted babies. It revealed that through [[breast milk]], Mohawk children were being exposed to 200% more toxins than children not on the reservation. Toxins contaminate water all over the world, but due to [[environmental racism]], certain marginalized groups are exposed to a much higher amount.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.personal.psu.edu/cjm5/blogs/english/2012/04/mothers-milk-project.html|title=Mother's Milk Project|last=Doverspike|first=Nicole|year=2012|website=English 487W Blog: West of Everything|access-date=October 9, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Greening of Harlem Coalition is another example of an ecofeminist movement. In 1989, [[Bernadette Cozart]] founded the coalition, which is responsible for many urban gardens around [[Harlem]]. Cozart's goal is to turn vacant lots into [[community gardens]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/1993/12/26/nyregion/neighborhood-report-harlem-sowing-a-future-with-green-in-it.html?scp=1&amp;sq=Bernadette%20Cozart&amp;st=cse|title=Neighborhood Report: Harlem; Sowing a Future With Green in It|last=Bernstein|first=Emily|date=1993|newspaper=The New York Times|access-date=October 9, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; This is economically beneficial, and also provides a way for very urban communities to be in touch with nature and each other. The majority of people interested in this project (as noted in 1990) were women. Through these gardens, they were able to participate in and become leaders of their communities. [[Green urbanism|Urban greening]] exists in other places as well. Beginning in 1994, a group of [[African Americans|African-American]] women in [[Detroit]] have developed city gardens, and call themselves the Gardening Angels. Similar garden movements have occurred globally.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Wild Politics: Feminism, Globalisation, Bio/diversity|last=Hawthorne|first=Susan|publisher=Spinifex Press|year=2002|location=Melbourne, Australia}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The development of [[vegetarian ecofeminism]] can be traced to the mid-80s and 90s, where it first appeared in writing. However, the roots of a [[Vegetarianism|vegetarian]] ecofeminist view can be traced back further by looking at sympathy for non-humans and [[Counterculture of the 1960s|counterculture movements]] of the 1960s and 1970s.&lt;ref name="gaard" /&gt; At the culmination of the decade ecofeminism had spread to both coasts and articulated an [[Intersectionality|intersectional analysis]] of women and the environment. Eventually, challenging ideas of environmental [[classism]] and racism, resisting toxic dumping and other threats to the impoverished.&lt;ref name="Gaard" /&gt;

[[File:Video Vandana Shiva 2014.webm|thumb|[[Vandana Shiva]]]]

== Major critiques ==

=== {{anchor|Essentialism}} Accused essentialism ===
In the 1980s and 1990s ecofeminism began to be heavily critiqued as '[[essentialism]]'. The critics believed ecofeminism to be reinforcing patriarchal dominance and norms.&lt;ref name="Borders" /&gt; Post structural and third wave feminists argued that ecofeminism equated women with nature and that this [[dichotomy]] grouped all women into one category enforcing the very societal norms that feminism is trying to break. However the criticism was based on a category mistake made by those who missed the emerging political critique of patriarchal ideology.{{Citation needed|date=January 2022}}

The ascribed essentialism appears in two main areas:

* Ecofeminism demonstrates an adherence to the strict dichotomy, among others, between men and women. Some critiques of ecofeminism note that the dichotomy between women and men and nature and culture creates a [[dualistic cosmology|dualism]] that is too stringent and focused on the differences of women and men. In this sense, ecofeminism too strongly correlates the [[social status]] of women with the social status of nature, rather than the non-[[Essentialism|essentialist]] view that women along with nature have both feminine and masculine qualities, and that just as feminine qualities have often been seen as less worthy, nature is also seen as having lesser value than culture.&lt;ref name="greenfuse" /&gt;
* Ecofeminism asserts a divergent view regarding participation in existing social structures. As opposed to [[Radical feminism|radical]] and [[Women's liberation movement|liberation-based]] feminist movements, mainstream feminism is tightly bound with [[hegemonic]] social status and strives to promote equality within the existing social and political structure,&lt;ref&gt;hooks, bell. "Feminist Theory: From Margin to Center" Cambridge, MA: South End Press 1984&lt;/ref&gt; such as making it possible for women to occupy positions of power in business, industry and politics, using direct involvement as the main tactic for achieving pay equity and influence. In contrast, many ecofeminists oppose active engagement in these areas, as these are the very structures that the movement intends to dismantle.&lt;ref name="greenfuse" /&gt;

Ecofeminist and author Noel Sturgeon says in an interview that what anti-essentialists are critiquing is a strategy used to mobilize large and diverse groups of both theorists and activists.&lt;ref&gt;Michiels, Nete. "Social Movements And Feminism." Women &amp; Environments International Magazine, no. 92/93, 2013, pp. 15-17.&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, according to ecofeminist and author Charlene Spretnak, modern ecofeminism is concerned about a variety of issues, including reproductive technology, equal pay and equal rights, toxic pollution, Third World development, and more.&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt;

As it propelled into the 21st century, ecofeminists became aware of the criticisms, and in response they began doing research and renaming the topic, i.e. queer ecologies, global feminist [[environmental justice]], and [[gender]] and the environment.&lt;ref name="Gaard" /&gt; The essentialism concern was mostly found among North American academics. In Europe and the global South, class, race, gender and species dominations were framed by more grounded materialist understandings.{{Citation needed|date=February 2021}}

=== Socialist feminist critiques ===
[[Social ecology (Bookchin)|Social ecologist]] and feminist [[Janet Biehl]] has criticized ecofeminism for focusing too much on a [[mystical]] connection between women and nature and not enough on the actual conditions of women.&lt;ref name="Biehl"&gt;{{cite book |last=Biehl |first=Janet |author-link=Janet Biel |title=Rethinking eco-feminist politics |year=1991 |publisher=[[South End Press]] |location=Boston, Massachusetts |isbn=978-0-89608-392-9}}&lt;/ref&gt; She has also stated that rather than being a forward-moving theory, ecofeminism is an anti-progressive movement for women.&lt;ref name="Biehl" /&gt; The ecofeminist believes that women and nature have a strong bond because of their shared history of patriarchal oppression; whereas, the [[Socialist feminism|socialist feminist]] focuses on gender roles in the political economy. The socialist feminist may oppose the ecofeminist by arguing that women do not have an intrinsic connection with nature; rather, that is a socially constructed narrative.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Rocheleau |first=Dianne |display-authors=etal |title=Feminist Political Ecology: Global Issues &amp; Local Experiences |location=New York |publisher=[[Routledge]] |year=1996}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Rosemary Radford Ruether]] also critiqued this focus on mysticism over work that focuses on helping women, but argues that spirituality and activism can be combined effectively in ecofeminism.&lt;ref name="Ecofeminism&amp;Globalization"&gt;{{cite book |last=Ruether |first=Rosemary Radford |author-link=Rosemary Radford Ruether |title=Ecofeminism and Globalization |year=2003 |editor1-first=Heather |editor1-last=Eaton |editor2-first=Lois Ann |editor2-last=Lorentzen |publisher=[[Rowman &amp; Littlefield]] |location=Lanham, Boulder, New York, Toronto, Oxford |isbn=978-0-7425-2697-6 |pages=vii–xi}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== (Anti-essentialist) Intersectional ecofeminisms ===
A. E. Kings as well as Norie Ross Singer theorize that ecofeminism must be approached from an intersectionality perspective, and advance an anti-essentialist critical ecofeminism of difference accounting for how multiple axes of identity such as gender, race, and class variously intermesh in human-nonhuman relationships.&lt;ref&gt;Norie Ross Singer, "Toward Ecofeminist Communication Studies," ''Communication Theory'', 2020, vol. 30, no. 3, pp. 268-89. https://doi.org/10.1093/ct/qtz023&lt;/ref&gt; Kings argues&lt;ref&gt;A. E. Kings, "Intersectionality and the Changing Face of Ecofeminism," Ethics and the Environment, 2017, vol. 22, no. 1, pp. 63-87. https://doi.org/10.2979/ethicsenviro.22.1.04&lt;/ref&gt; that the discipline is fundamentally intersectional given that it is built upon the idea that patriarchal violence against women is connected to domination of nature. Simultaneously, Kings warns against the presumption of intersectional thought as a natural component of ecofeminism, so as not to disregard the distinctive academic contributions of intersectional feminists.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Kings |first=A. E. |date=Spring 2017 |title=Intersectionality and the Changing Face of Ecofeminism |journal=Ethics and the Environment |volume=22 |pages=63–87 |doi=10.2979/ethicsenviro.22.1.04 |s2cid=148809508}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Feminist thought surrounding ecofeminism grew in some areas as it was criticized; vegetarian ecofeminism contributed intersectional analysis; and ecofeminisms that analyzed [[animal rights]], [[labor rights]] and activisms as they could draw lines among oppressed groups. To some, the inclusion of non-human animals also came to be viewed as essentialist.{{Citation needed|date=February 2021}}

=== Ableism and white saviorism ===
Environmental movements have often been criticized for their lack of consideration for the participation of people with disabilities.&lt;ref name=":6"&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Charles |first=Andrew |last2=Thomas |first2=Huw |date=June 2007 |title=Deafness and Disability—Forgotten Components of Environmental Justice: Illustrated by the Case of Local Agenda 21 in South Wales |url=http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/13549830601183677 |journal=Local Environment |language=en |volume=12 |issue=3 |pages=209–221 |doi=10.1080/13549830601183677 |issn=1354-9839}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although environmental justice and feminist care ethics have made political pushes for participation of marginalized groups, people with disabilities face issues of access and representation in policy making. In a paper by author Andrew Charles, Deaf people in Wales show concern about their quality of life when unable to safely access outdoor spaces and engage in political movements.&lt;ref name=":6" /&gt; There is also an overt nurturing aspect of essentialist ecofeminism that is potentially both oppressive and patronizing to marginalized groups. Through a [[Bioessentialism|bioessentialist]] and [[Matriarchy|matriarchal]] lens, ecofeminism can create environments where activists may speak for underrepresented groups they aren't a part of or participate in [[volunteer tourism]]. This form of radical [[white savior complex]] is not unique to ecofeminism, but in any intersectional space it has potential to disrupt self advocacy of marginalized groups.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Bandyopadhyay |first=Ranjan |last2=Patil |first2=Vrushali |date=2017-08-08 |title=‘The white woman's burden’ – the racialized, gendered politics of volunteer tourism |url=https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/14616688.2017.1298150 |journal=Tourism Geographies |language=en |volume=19 |issue=4 |pages=644–657 |doi=10.1080/14616688.2017.1298150 |issn=1461-6688}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Wild animal suffering ===
[[Catia Faria]] argues that the view held by ecofeminists that the largest source of harm to non-human animals in the wild is patriarchal culture and that the conservation of nature and natural processes is the best way to help these individuals is mistaken. She instead contends that natural processes are a source of immense [[Wild animal suffering|suffering for these animals]] and that we should work towards alleviating the harms they experience, as well as eliminating patriarchal sources of harm, such as hunting.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |last=Ruiz Carreras |first=María |date=2016-11-04 |title="La lucha por la igualdad y la justicia es necesariamente feminista y antiespecista" |language=es |trans-title=The fight for equality and justice is necessarily feminist and antispeciesist |work=Diagonal |url=https://www.diagonalperiodico.net/global/29972-lo-personal-es-politico-feminismo-y-antiespecismo.html |access-date=2021-02-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Theorists ==
*[[Judi Bari]] – Bari was a principal organizer of the [[Earth First!]] movement and experienced sexist hostility.
*[[Françoise d'Eaubonne]] – Called upon women to lead an ecological revolution in order to save the planet. This entailed revolutionizing gender relations and human relations with the natural world.&lt;ref name=Merchant&gt;{{cite book |last=Merchant |first=Carolyn |chapter=Chapter 8 |title=Radical ecology: the search for a livable world |location=New York |publisher=[[Routledge]] |date=1992 |page=184}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Greta Gaard]] – Greta Gaard is an American ecofeminist scholar and activist. Her major contributions to the field connect ideas of queer theory, vegetarianism, and animal liberation. Her major theories include ecocriticism which works to include literary criticism and composition to inform ecofeminism and other feminist theories to address a wider range of social issues within ecofeminism. She is an ecological activist and leader in the U.S. Green Party, and the Green Movement.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www.uwrf.edu/FacultyStaff/5617517.cfm |title=Greta Gaard |website=www.uwrf.edu |language=en |access-date=2019-10-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Susan Griffin]] - A radical feminist philosopher, essayist and playwright particularly known for her innovative, hybrid-form ecofeminist works. A Californian, she taught as an adjunct professor at UC Berkeley as well as at Stanford University and California Institute of Integral Studies.
*[[Sallie McFague]] – A prominent ecofeminist [[theologian]], McFague uses the metaphor of God's body to represent the universe at large. This metaphor values inclusive, mutualistic and interdependent relations amongst all things.&lt;ref&gt;Ralte, Lalrinawmi. [http://www.rethinkingmission.org.uk/articles/The%20World%20as%20the%20body%20of%20God%20article.pdf The World as the Body of God Ecofeminist Theological Discourse with Special Reference to Tribal Women in India.] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160522063507/http://rethinkingmission.org.uk/articles/The%20World%20as%20the%20body%20of%20God%20article.pdf |date=2016-05-22 }}, rethinkingmission.org, accessed March 24, 2012&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Carolyn Merchant]] – Historian of science who taught at [[University of California, Berkeley]] for many years. Her book ''The Death of Nature: Women, Ecology and the Scientific Revolution'' is a classic ecofeminist text.
*Mary Mellor – UK sociologist who moved to ecofeminist ideas from an interest in cooperatives. Her books ''Breaking the Boundaries'' and ''Feminism and Ecology'' are grounded in a materialist analysis.{{citation needed|date=January 2023}}
*[[Maria Mies]] – Mies is a German [[Social criticism|social critic]] who has been involved in feminist work throughout [[Europe]] and [[India]]. She works particularly on the intersections of patriarchy, [[poverty]], and the environment on a local and global scale.&lt;ref name="Ecofeminism&amp;Globalization" /&gt;
*[[Adrian Parr]] – A cultural and environmental theorist. She has published eight books and numerous articles on environmental activism, feminist new materialism, and imagination. Most notable is her trilogy – ''Hijacking Sustainability'', ''The Wrath of Capital'', and ''Birth of a New Earth''.
*[[Val Plumwood]] – Val Plumwood, formerly Val Routley, was an Australian ecofeminist intellectual and activist, who was prominent in the development of radical [[ecosophy]] from the early 1970s through the remainder of the 20th century. In her work ''Feminism and the Mastery of Nature'' she describes the relationship of mankind and the environment relating to an eco-feminist ideology.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |title=Feminism and the Mastery of Nature |last=Plumwood |first=Val |publisher=[[Routledge]] |year=2003 |location=New Fetter Lane, London}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Alicia Puleo]] – The author of several books and articles on ecofeminism and gender inequality, Alicia Puleo has been characterized as "arguably Spain's most prominent explicator-philosopher of the worldwide movement or theoretical orientation known as ecofeminism."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=I1RWyk2PwEgC&amp;pg=PA107 |title=Global Issues in Contemporary Hispanic Women's Writing |chapter=For a Better World: Alicia Puleo's Critical Ecofeminism |first=Roberta |last=Johnson |editor1-first=Estrella |editor1-last=Cibreiro |editor2-first=Francisca |editor2-last=López |isbn=9780415626941 |page=107 |year=2013 |publisher=Routledge |access-date=20 February 2019 |via=[[Google Books]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Rosemary Radford Ruether]] – Has written 36 books and over 600 articles exploring the intersections of feminism, theology, and [[Creation Care|creation care]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=LaRosa |first=Patricia |title=Finding Aid for Rosemary Radford Ruether Papers, 1954-2002 |url=http://library.columbia.edu/content/dam/libraryweb/libraries/burke/fa/awts/ldpd_5632346.pdf |access-date=15 March 2013 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20121221205023/http://library.columbia.edu/content/dam/libraryweb/libraries/burke/fa/awts/ldpd_5632346.pdf |archive-date=21 December 2012 |url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ruether was the first person to connect the domination of the earth with the oppression of women.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Bouma-Prediger |first=Steven |url=https://www.worldcat.org/oclc/33105042 |title=The greening of theology: the ecological models of Rosemary Radford Ruether, Joseph Sittler, and Juergen Moltmann |date=1995 |publisher=Scholars Press |isbn=0-7885-0163-1 |location=Atlanta, Ga. |oclc=33105042}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{page needed|date=January 2023}}
*[[Ariel Salleh]] – Australian ecofeminist with a global perspective; a founding editor of the journal ''Capitalism Nature Socialism''; author of three books and some 200 articles examining links with [[Deep ecology|deep]] and [[Social ecology (Bookchin)|social ecology]], green politics and [[eco-socialism]].
*[[Vandana Shiva]] – Shiva is a scientist by training, prolific author and Indian ecofeminist activist.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Who's Who of Women and the Environment |url=http://www.unep.org/women_env/w_details.asp?w_id=107 |access-date=15 March 2013 |archive-date=28 October 2012 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20121028084032/http://www.unep.org/women_env/w_details.asp?w_id=107 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; She was a participant in the [[Chipko movement]] of the 1970s, which used non-violent activism to protest and prevent deforestation in the [[Garhwal Himalaya|Garhwal]] [[Himalayas]] of [[Uttarakhand]], India, then in [[Uttar Pradesh]]. Her fight against genetically modified organisms (GMOs) (together with the fights led by Rachel Carson against DDT and Erin Brockovich against hexavalent chromium) has been described as an example of ecofeminist position.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Barthold |first1=Charles |last2=Bevan |first2=David |last3=Corvellec |first3=Hervé |title=An ecofeminist position in critical practice: Challenging corporate truth in the Anthropocene |journal=Gender, Work &amp; Organization |year=2022 |volume=29 |orig-year=11 July 2022 |issue=6 |pages=1796–1814 |doi=10.1111/gwao.12878 |s2cid=250467484|doi-access=free }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Charlene Spretnak]] – Spretnak is an American writer largely known for her writing on ecology, politics and spirituality. Through these writings Spretnak has become a prominent ecofeminist. She has written many books which discuss ecological issues in terms of effects with social criticisms, including feminism. Spretnak's works had a major influence in the development of the [[Green Party of the United States|Green Party]]. She has also won awards based on her visions on ecology and social issues as well as feminist thinking.&lt;ref name="Spretnak"&gt;Charlene Spretnak, "The Early Years of the Green Movement in the United States", in Zelko and Brinkmann, eds., ''Green Parties'', p.&amp;nbsp;48.&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Starhawk]] – An American writer and activist, Starhawk is known for her work in spiritualism and ecofeminism. She advocates for social justice in issues surrounding nature and spirit. These social justice issues fall under the scope of feminism and ecofeminism. She believes in fighting oppression through intersectionality and the importance of spirituality, eco consciousness and [[Sexual liberation|sexual]] and gender liberation.&lt;ref name=Starhawk&gt;see [[Starhawk]]&lt;/ref&gt;{{circular reference|date=January 2023}}
*[[Vanessa Lemgruber]] – Lemgruber is a Brazilian lawyer, writer,&lt;ref name="amazon.com.br"&gt;{{Cite book |url=https://www.amazon.com.br/Guia-ecofeminista-mulheres-direito-ecologia-ebook/dp/B08C1FNZ55/ref=sr_1_1?__mk_pt_BR=%C3%85M%C3%85%C5%BD%C3%95%C3%91&amp;dchild=1&amp;keywords=guia+ecofeminista&amp;qid=1593658492&amp;sr=8-1 |title=Guia ecofeminista: Mulheres, direito, ecologia |language=es |trans-title=}}&lt;/ref&gt; activist, and ecofeminist.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://medium.com/ecofeminist-talks |title=Ecofeminist Talks – Medium}}{{self-published source|date=January 2023}}&lt;/ref&gt; She defends&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://sites.google.com/d/1xtLXhg1fJPFNUeszu6svDNtubQl3lcwM/p/1BtP5jbRogM3ZHVKVwT0-2M3bpQprHhqU/edit |title=Meet Google Drive – One place for all your files}}{{dead link|date=January 2023|fix-attempted=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[the Doce river]] in Brazil and advocates for [[water quality]] and [[zero waste]] movements.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=https://www.instagram.com/ecofeminist.lab/ | title=Instagram }}{{self-published source|date=January 2023}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Douglas Vakoch]] – An American ecocritic whose edited volumes include ''Ecofeminism and Rhetoric: Critical Perspectives on Sex, Technology, and Discourse'' (2011),&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Ecofeminism and rhetoric: critical perspectives on sex, technology, and discourse |last=Vakoch |first=Douglas A. |date=2011-01-01 |publisher=[[Berghahn Books]] |isbn=9780857451873 |location=New York |language=en |oclc=714734848}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Feminist Ecocriticism: Environment, Women, and Literature'' (2012),&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |title=Feminist ecocriticism: environment, women, and literature |last=Vakoch |first=Douglas A. |date=2012-01-01 |publisher=[[Lexington Books]] |isbn=9780739176825 |location=Lanham, Md. |language=en |oclc=815941726}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Dystopias and Utopias on Earth and Beyond: Feminist Ecocriticism of Science Fiction'' (2021),&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |url=https://www.routledge.com/Dystopias-and-Utopias-on-Earth-and-Beyond-Feminist-Ecocriticism-of-Science/Vakoch/p/book/9780367716233 |title=Dystopias and Utopias on Earth and Beyond: Feminist Ecocriticism of Science Fiction |publisher=[[Routledge]] |year=2021 |isbn=9780367716233 |editor-last=Vakoch |editor-first=Douglas A. |location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Ecofeminist Science Fiction: International Perspectives on Gender, Ecology, and Literature'' (2021),&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |url=https://www.routledge.com/Ecofeminist-Science-Fiction-International-Perspectives-on-Gender-Ecology/Vakoch/p/book/9780367716417 |title=Ecofeminist Science Fiction: International Perspectives on Gender, Ecology, and Literature |publisher=[[Routledge]] |year=2021 |isbn=9780367716417 |editor-last=Vakoch |editor-first=Douglas A. |location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''The Routledge Handbook of Ecofeminism and Literature'' (2023),&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |url=https://www.routledge.com/The-Routledge-Handbook-of-Ecofeminism-and-Literature/Vakoch/p/book/9781032050119 |title=The Routledge Handbook of Ecofeminism and Literature |publisher=[[Routledge]] |year=2023 |isbn=9781032050119 |editor-last=Vakoch |editor-first=Douglas A. |editor-link=Douglas Vakoch}}&lt;/ref&gt; (with Nicole Anae) ''Indian Feminist Ecocriticism'' (2022),&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |url=https://rowman.com/ISBN/9781666908718/Indian-Feminist-Ecocriticism |title=Indian Feminist Ecocriticism |publisher=[[Lexington Books]] |year=2022 |isbn=978-1-66690-871-8 |editor1-last=Vakoch |editor1-first=Douglas A. |editor1-link=Douglas Vakoch |editor2-last=Anae |editor2-first=Nicole}}&lt;/ref&gt; and (with Sam Mickey) ''Ecofeminism in Dialogue'' (2018),&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |title=Ecofeminism in Dialogue |last1=Vakoch |first1=Douglas A. |last2=Mickey |first2=Sam |publisher=[[Lexington Books]] |year=2018 |isbn=9781498569279 |location=Lanham, MD |oclc=1005695115}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Literature and Ecofeminism: Intersectional and International Voices'' (2018),&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |title=Literature and Ecofeminism: Intersectional and International Voices |last1=Vakoch |first1=Douglas A. |last2=Mickey |first2=Sam |publisher=[[Routledge]] |year=2018 |isbn=978-0815381723 |location=London |oclc=1020319048}}&lt;/ref&gt; and ''Women and Nature?: Beyond Dualism in Gender, Body, and Environment'' (2018).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |title=Women and Nature?: Beyond Dualism in Gender, Body, and Environment |last1=Vakoch |first1=Douglas |last2=Mickey |first2=Sam|publisher=[[Routledge]] |year=2018 |isbn=9781138053427 |location=London |language=en |oclc=975383028}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Karen J. Warren]] – Warren received her B.A. in philosophy from the [[University of Minnesota]] (1970) and her Ph.D. from the [[University of Massachusetts Amherst|University of Massachusetts-Amherst]] in 1978. Before her long tenure at [[Macalester College]], which began in 1985, Warren was Professor of Philosophy at [[St. Olaf College]] in the early 1980s. Warren was the Ecofeminist-Scholar-in-Residence at [[Murdoch University]] in Australia.&lt;ref name="MacGregor" /&gt; In 2003, she served as an [[University of Oxford|Oxford University]] Round Table Scholar and as Women's Chair in Humanistic Studies at [[Marquette University]] in 2004. She has spoken widely on environmental issues, feminism, critical thinking skills and peace studies in many international locations including [[Buenos Aires]], [[Gothenburg]], [[Helsinki]], [[Oslo]], [[Manitoba]], [[Melbourne]], [[Moscow]], [[Perth]], the [[Earth Summit|U.N. Earth Summit]] in [[Rio de Janeiro]] (1992), and San Jose.
*[[Laura Wright (academic)|Laura Wright]] — Wright proposed [[Vegan studies]] as an academic discipline.{{citation needed|date=January 2023}}

== See also ==
{{div col|colwidth=25em}}
* [[Chipko movement]]
* [[Climate change and gender]]
* [[Cottagecore]]
* [[Critical Animal Studies]]
* [[Deep ecology]]
* [[Deep Green Resistance]]
* [[Ecofeminist art]]
* [[Green syndicalism]]
* [[Intersectionality]]
* [[List of ecofeminist authors]]
* [[Queer ecology]]
* [[Romanticism]]
* [[Sexecology]]
* [[Social ecology (Bookchin)|Social ecology]]
* [[Vegan studies]]
* [[Vegetarian Ecofeminism|Vegetarian ecofeminism]]
* [[Women and the environment through history]]
{{div col end}}

== References ==
{{reflist|refs=
&lt;ref name=Gaard&gt;{{cite journal|last=Gaard|first=Greta|title=Ecofeminism Revisited: Rejecting Essentialism and Re-Placing Species in a Material Feminist Environmentalism|journal=Feminist Formations|date=2011|volume=23|issue=2|pages=26–53|doi=10.1353/ff.2011.0017|s2cid=145195744}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Mann&gt;{{cite journal|last=Mann|first=Susan A|title=Pioneers of U.S. Ecofeminism and Environmental Justice|journal=Feminist Formations|date=2011|volume=23|issue=2|pages=1–25|doi=10.1353/ff.2011.0028|s2cid=146349456}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
&lt;ref name=Borders&gt;{{cite web|title=Ecofeminism: Is the Movement Still Relevant? |url=http://www.genderacrossborders.com/2012/03/22/ecofeminism-is-the-movement-still-relevant/|publisher=Gender Across Borders}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="greenfuse"&gt;{{cite web|title=Ecofeminism Critique|url=http://www.thegreenfuse.org/ecofemcrit.htm#root|publisher=The Green Fuse}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
}}

== Further reading ==

=== Key works ===
* ''Ancient Futures: Learning from Ladakh'', by [[Helena Norberg-Hodge]]
* ''The Body of God'' by [[Sallie McFague]]
* ''The Chalice &amp; The Blade: Our History, Our Future'', by [[Riane Eisler]]
* ''The Death of Nature: Women, Ecology, and the Scientific Revolution'' by [[Carolyn Merchant]]
* ''Ecofeminism'' by [[Maria Mies]] and [[Vandana Shiva]]
* ''Ecofeminism in Latin America'' by Mary Judith Ross
* ''Ecofeminist Philosophy'' by [[Karen J. Warren]]
* ''Environmental Culture'' by [[Val Plumwood]]
* ''Feminism and the Mastery of Nature'' by Val Plumwood
* ''Gaia &amp; God: An Ecofeminist Theology of Earth Healing'' by [[Rosemary Radford Ruether]]
* ''Integrating Ecofeminism, Globalization, and World Religions'' by Rosemary Radford Ruether
* ''Neither Man Nor Beast'' by [[Carol J. Adams]]
* ''Refuge: An Unnatural History of Family and Place'' by [[Terry Tempest Williams]]
* ''The Resurgence of the Real: Body, Nature, and Place in a Hypermodern World'' by [[Charlene Spretnak]]
* ''Sacred Longings: Ecofeminist theology and Globalization'' by [[Mary Grey (theologian)|Mary Grey]]
* ''The Sexual Politics of Meat'' by [[Carol J. Adams]]
* ''[[Silent Spring]]'' by [[Rachel Carson]]
* ''[[The Spiral Dance]]'' by [[Starhawk]]
* ''Staying Alive: Women, Ecology and Development'' by [[Vandana Shiva]]
* ''Thinking Green! Essays on Environmentalism, Feminism, and Nonviolence'' by [[Petra Kelly]]
* ''Tomorrow's Biodiversity'' by [[Vandana Shiva]]
* ''Woman and Nature: The Roaring Inside Her'' by [[Susan Griffin]]
* ''Breaking the Boundaries'' by Mary Mellor
* ''Feminism and Ecology'' by Mary Mellor
* ''Ecofeminism as Politics: nature, Marx, and the postmodern'' by [[Ariel Salleh]]
* ''The Greening of Costa Rica'' by Ana Isla

===Anthologies===
* ''Animals and Women: Feminist Theoretical Explorations'', edited by [[Carol J. Adams]] and Josephine Donovan
* ''Dystopias and Utopias on Earth and Beyond: Feminist Ecocriticism of Science Fiction'', edited by [[Douglas Vakoch|Douglas A. Vakoch]]
*''Ecofeminism: Women, Animals, Nature'', edited by [[Greta Gaard]]
* ''Ecofeminism: Women, Culture, Nature'', edited by Karen J. Warren with editorial assistance from [[Nisvan Erkal]]
* ''EcoFeminism &amp; Globalization: exploring culture, context and religion'', edited by Heather Eaton &amp; Lois Ann Lorentzen
* ''Ecofeminism and Rhetoric: Critical Perspectives on Sex, Technology, and Discourse'', edited by Douglas A. Vakoch
* ''Ecofeminism and the Sacred'', edited by Carol J. Adams
* ''Ecofeminism in Dialogue'', edited by Douglas A. Vakoch and Sam Mickey
* ''Ecofeminist Science Fiction: International Perspectives on Gender, Ecology, and Literature'', edited by Douglas A. Vakoch
* ''Eco-Sufficiency &amp; Global Justice: Women write Political Ecology'', edited by [[Ariel Salleh]]
*''Feminist Ecocriticism: Environment, Women, and Literature'', edited by Douglas A. Vakoch
*''Indian Feminist Ecocriticism'', edited by Douglas A. Vakoch and Nicole Anae
* ''Literature and Ecofeminism: Intersectional and International Voices'', edited by Douglas A. Vakoch and Sam Mickey
* ''The Politics of Women's Spirituality: Essays on the Rise of Spiritual Power within the Feminist Movement'', edited by [[Charlene Spretnak]]
* ''Readings in Ecology and Feminist Theology'', edited by Mary Heather MacKinnon and Moni McIntyre
* ''Reclaim the Earth'', edited by Leonie Caldecott &amp; Stephanie Leland
* ''Reweaving the World: The Emergence of Ecofeminism'', edited by Irene Diamond and Gloria Feman Orenstein
* ''The Routledge Handbook of Ecofeminism and Literature'', edited by Douglas A. Vakoch
* ''Women and Nature?: Beyond Dualism in Gender, Body, and Environment'', edited by Douglas A. Vakoch and Sam Mickey
* ''Women Healing Earth: Third World Women on Ecology, Feminism, and Religion'', edited by Rosemary Radford Ruether
* '' GUIA ECOFEMINISTA - mulheres, direito, ecologia, written by Vanessa Lemgruber edited by Ape'Ku''

===Journal articles===
*{{cite journal | last1 = Gaard | first1 = Greta Claire | year = 2011 | title = Ecofeminism Revisited: Rejecting Essentialism and Re-Placing Species in a Material Feminist Environmentalism | journal = Feminist Formations | volume = 23 | issue = 2| pages = 26–53 | doi=10.1353/ff.2011.0017| s2cid = 145195744 }}
* {{cite journal | last1 = Huggan | first1 = Graham | year = 2004 | title = "Greening" Postcolonialism: Ecocritical Perspectives | journal = MFS Modern Fiction Studies | volume = 50 | issue = 3| pages = 701–733 | doi=10.1353/mfs.2004.0067| s2cid = 143900488 }}
* {{cite journal | last1 = Mack-Canty | first1 = Colleen | year = 2004 | title = Third-Wave Feminism and the Need to Reweave the Nature/ Culture Duality | journal = NWSA Journal | volume = 16 | issue = 3| pages = 154–179 | doi=10.1353/nwsa.2004.0077}}
* {{cite journal | last1 = MacGregor | first1 = Sherilyn | year = 2004 | title = From care to citizenship: Calling ecofeminism back to politics | journal = Ethics &amp; the Environment | volume = 9 | issue = 1| pages = 56–84 | doi=10.1353/een.2004.0007| s2cid = 144880391 }}
* {{cite journal | last1 = Mallory | first1 = Chaone | year = 2013 | title = Locating Ecofeminism in Encounters with Food and Place | journal = Journal of Agricultural and Environmental Ethics | volume = 26 | issue = 1| pages = 171–189 | doi=10.1007/s10806-011-9373-8| s2cid = 144880945 }}
*Mann, Susan A. 2011. Pioneers of U.S. Ecofeminism and Environmental Justice, "Feminist Formations" 23(2): 1-25.
*{{cite journal | last1 = Wildy | first1 = Jade | year = 2012 | title = The Artistic Progressions of Ecofeminism: The Changing Focus of Women in Environmental Art | journal = International Journal of the Arts in Society | volume = 6 | issue = 1| pages = 53–65 | doi=10.18848/1833-1866/cgp/v06i01/35978}}
* Salleh, Ariel (1984) 'From Feminism to Ecology', ''[http://www.socialalternatives.com Social Alternatives]'', Vol. 4, No. 3, 8–12.
* Salleh, Ariel (2019) '[https://globaldialogue.isa-sociology.org/ecofeminist-sociology-as-a-new-class-analysis/ Ecofeminist Sociology as a New Class Analysis]' in Klaus Dorre and Brigitte Aulenbacher (eds.), ''Global Dialogue'', International Sociological Association Newsletter: Vol. 9, No. 1.

===Fiction===
{{see also|Feminist science fiction}}
* ''A Door Into Ocean'' by [[Joan Slonczewski]]
* ''[[Always Coming Home]]'' by [[Ursula K. Le Guin]]
* ''[[Buffalo Gals, Won't You Come Out Tonight]]'' by Ursula K. Le Guin
* ''[[The Fifth Sacred Thing]]'' by [[Starhawk]]
* ''[[The Gate to Women's Country]]'' by [[Sheri S. Tepper]]
* ''The Holdfast Chronicles'' by [[Suzy McKee Charnas]]
* ''The Madonna Secret'' by Sophie Strand
* ''Native Tongue'' by [[Suzette Haden Elgin]]
* ''The Parable of the Sower'' by [[Octavia Butler]]
* '' Prodigal Summer'' by [[Barbara Kingsolver]]
* ''[[Surfacing (novel)|Surfacing]]'' by [[Margaret Atwood]]
* ''The Wanderground'' by [[Sally Miller Gearhart]]
* ''[[Woman on the Edge of Time]]'' by [[Marge Piercy]]
* ''[[The Kin of Ata are Waiting for You]]'' by [[Dorothy Bryant]]
* ''Bear'' by [[Marian Engel]]
* ''[[The Temple of My Familiar]]'' by [[Alice Walker]]
* ''[[Sultana's Dream]]'' by [[Begum Rokeya|Begum Rokeya Sakhawat Hossain]]

=== Poetry ===
*''The Sea of Affliction'' (1987, reprinted 2010) by [[Rosemarie Rowley]]

== External links ==
{{Wikiversity|Women's Studies}}
{{commons category|Ecofeminism}}
* [http://lgruen.faculty.wesleyan.edu/files/2011/05/Gaard.pdf Ecofeminism: Toward global justice and planetary health] Feminist Greta Gaard and Lori Gruen's ecofeminist framework
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20061001140008/http://www.metanexus.net/metanexus_online/show_article2.asp?id=2669 "An Ecology of Knowledge: Feminism, Ecology and the Science and Religion Discourse"] [[Metanexus Institute]] by Lisa Stenmark
* [http://www.users.drew.edu/ckeller/Dark-Vibe.pdf "Ecofeminism and the Democracy of Creation"] by Catherine Keller (2005) ; cf. [[Carol P. Christ]], "Ecofeminism", in [[Michel Weber]] and Will Desmond (eds.), ''[https://www.academia.edu/279955/Handbook_of_Whiteheadian_Process_Thought Handbook of Whiteheadian Process Thought]'', Frankfurt / Lancaster, ontos verlag, 2008, pp.&amp;nbsp;87–98.
* [http://www.lespantheresroses.org/textes/ecology_toward_a_queer_ecofeminism.pdf "Toward a Queer Ecofeminism"] by Greta Gaard
* [https://www.cadtm.org/Feminism-and-ecology-the-same-struggle-The-shaping-of-ecofeminism Feminism and ecology: the same struggle? – The shaping of ecofeminism] by Marijke Colle
* [https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/feminism-environmental/ Feminist Environmental Philosophy] by Karen Warren
* [https://www.perlego.com/knowledge/study-guides/what-is-ecofeminism/ What is Ecofeminism?] Perlego Books

{{Feminist theory}}
{{Feminism}}
{{Green politics}}
{{Environmental humanities}}
{{Environmental social science}}
{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Ecofeminism| ]]
[[Category:1974 neologisms]]
[[Category:Articles containing video clips]]
[[Category:Environmental humanities]]
[[Category:Environmental movements]]
[[Category:Environmental social science concepts]]
[[Category:Environmentalism]]
[[Category:Feminism and health]]
[[Category:Feminism and history]]
[[Category:Feminist movements and ideologies]]
[[Category:Feminist theory]]
[[Category:Green politics]]
[[Category:Left-wing politics]]
[[Category:Liberalism]]
[[Category:Political ecology]]
[[Category:Progressivism]]
[[Category:Relational ethics]]
[[Category:Social justice]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>