<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20181111003107|868249763" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="40494939" pageid="40494939" ns="0" title="Ecofeminism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2018-11-24T17:59:30Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Green politics sidebar |Schools}}
{{Feminism sidebar |Variants (general)}}

The term '''Ecofeminism''' is used to describe a [[feminism|feminist]] approach to understanding [[ecology]]. Ecofeminist thinkers draw on the concept of [[gender]] to theorize on the relationship between humans and the natural world.&lt;ref name="MacGregor"&gt;{{cite book |author=MacGregor, Sherilyn |title=Beyond mothering earth: ecological citizenship and the politics of care |year=2006 |publisher=UBC Press |location=Vancouver |isbn=978-0-7748-1201-6 |page=286}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The term was coined by the French writer [[Françoise d'Eaubonne]] in her book ''Le Féminisme ou la Mort'' (1974).&lt;ref name="Merchant"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Warren"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Warren|first=Karen|date=September 2002|title=Karen Warren's Ecofeminism|url=|journal=Ethics &amp; the Environment|volume=7|pages=12|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Today, there are many interpretations of ecofeminism and how it might be applied to social thought, including: [[ecofeminist art]], ecofeminist theory, [[social justice]] and [[political philosophy]], religion, contemporary feminism and poetry. As there are several different types of feminism and different beliefs held by feminists, there are different versions of ecofeminism.

Ecofeminism is widely referred to as the third wave of feminism, it adds to the former feminist theory that an environmental perspective is a necessary part of feminism. Ecofeminism uses the parallels between the oppression of nature and the oppression of women as a way to highlight the idea that both must be understood in order to properly recognize how they are connected. These parallels include but are not limited to seeing women and nature as property, seeing men as the curators of culture and women as the curators of nature, and how men dominate women and humans dominate nature.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Ecofeminism and the Sacred|last=Adams|first=Carol|publisher=Continuum|year=2007|isbn=|location=|pages=1–8}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Charlene Spretnak]] has offered one way of categorizing ecofeminist work: 1) through the study of political theory as well as history; 2) through the belief and study of [[Earth religion|nature-based religions]]; 3) through [[environmentalism]].&lt;ref name=":2"&gt;Spretnak, Charlene. "Ecofeminism: Our Roots and Flowering." ''Reweaving the World: The Emergence of Feminism'', edited by Irene Diamond and Gloria Ornstein, Sierra Club Books, 1990, pp. 3-14.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Anti-Oppression==

According to [[Françoise d'Eaubonne]] in her book ''Le Féminisme ou la Mort'' (1974, Ecofeminism relates the [[oppression]] and [[Dominance hierarchy|domination]] of all subordinate groups (women, people of color, children, the poor) to the oppression and domination of nature (animals, land, water, air, etc.). In the book, the author argues that oppression, domination, exploitation, and [[colonization]] from the Western [[Patriarchy|patriarchal]] society has directly caused irreversible environmental damage.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt; [[Françoise d'Eaubonne]] was an activist and organizer, and her writing encouraged the eradication of all social injustice, not just injustice against women and the environment.&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{Cite book|title=Ecofeminist Philosophy: A Western Perspective on What It Is and Why It Matters|last=Warren|first=Karen J.|publisher=Roman &amp; Littlefield Publishers, Inc|year=2000|isbn=9780847692996|location=Lanham, Maryland|pages=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

This tradition includes a number of influential texts including: ''Women and Nature'' ([[Susan Griffin]] 1978), ''The Death of Nature'' ([[Carolyn Merchant]] 1980) and ''Gyn/Ecology'' ([[Mary Daly]] 1978). These texts helped to propel the association between domination by man on women and the domination of culture on nature. From these texts feminist activism of the 1980s linked ideas of ecology and the environment. For example, conferences for women devoted to living on the earth and protests against [[nuclear testing]] and other [[militarism]] that oppresses [[femininity]]. Writing in this circle discussed ecofeminism drawing from Green Party politics, [[peace movement]]s, and [[direct action]] movements.&lt;ref name=":3"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Lamar|first=Stephanie|year=1991|title=Ecofeminist Theory and Grassroots Politics|journal=Hypatia|volume=6|issue=1|pages=28–45|doi=10.1111/j.1527-2001.1991.tb00207.x}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Modern ecofeminism, or feminist eco-criticism, eschews such [[essentialism]] and instead focuses more on [[intersectional]] questions, such as how the nature-culture split enables the oppression of female and nonhuman bodies. It is also an activist and academic movement that sees critical connections between the exploitation of nature and the domination over women both caused by men.

==Gendering Nature==
[[File:Petra Kelly.jpg|thumb|[[Petra Kelly]].]]
One ecofeminist theory is that [[capitalist]] values reflect [[paternalistic]] and gendered values. In this interpretation effects of capitalism has led to a harmful split between [[nature]] and [[culture]]. In the 1970s, early ecofeminists discussed that the split can only be healed by the feminine instinct for nurture and [[holistic]] knowledge of nature's processes.

Several feminists make the distinction that it is not ''because'' women are female or "feminine" that they relate to nature, but because of their similar states of oppression by the same male-dominant forces. The [[marginalization]] is evident in the [[Language and gender|gendered language]] used to describe nature and the animalized language used to describe women. Some discourses link women specifically to the environment because of their traditional social role as a nurturer and [[caregiver]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Stoddart|first=Mark|last2=Tindall|first2=D. B.|year=2011|title=Ecofeminism, Hegemonic Masculinity, And Environmental Movement Participation In British Columbia, Canada, 1998-2007: "Women Always Clean Up The Mess"|journal=Sociological Spectrum|volume=31|issue=3|pages=342–368|doi=10.1080/02732173.2011.557065}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ecofeminists following in this line of thought believe that these connections are illustrated through the coherence of socially-labeled values associated with 'femininity' such as nurturing, which are present both among women and in nature.

[[Vandana Shiva]] says that women have a special connection to the environment through their daily interactions and this connection has been ignored. She says that women in subsistence [[Economy|economies]] who produce "wealth in partnership with nature, have been experts in their own right of holistic and ecological knowledge of nature's processes". She makes the point that "these alternative modes of knowing, which are oriented to the social benefits and sustenance needs are not recognized by the [[capitalism|capitalist]] [[Reductionism|reductionist]] paradigm, because it fails to perceive the interconnectedness of nature, or the connection of women's lives, work and knowledge with the creation of wealth (23)".&lt;ref name="Shiva"&gt;{{cite book |author=Shiva, Vandana |title=Staying alive: women, ecology and development |year=1988 |publisher=Zed Books |location=London |isbn=978-0-86232-823-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;  &amp;nbsp;Shiva blames this failure on the West's [[patriarchy]], and the patriarchal idea of what development is. According to Shiva, patriarchy has labeled women, nature, and other groups not growing the economy as "unproductive".&lt;ref&gt;Shiva, Vandana. "Development as a New Project of Western Patriarchy." ''Reweaving the World: The Emergence of Feminism,'' edited by Irene Diamond and Gloria Ornstein, Sierra Club Books, 1990, pp. 189-200.&lt;/ref&gt;

==An "Ecofeminist Framework"==

In the 1993 essay entitled "Ecofeminism: Toward Global Justice and Planetary Health" authors [[Greta Gaard]] and [[Lori Gruen]] outline what they call the "ecofeminist framework". The essay provides a wealth of data and statistics in addition to laying out the theoretical aspects of the ecofeminist critique. The framework described is intended to establish ways of viewing and understanding our current global situations so that we are better able to understand how we arrived at this point and what may be done to ameliorate the ills.

Gaard and Gruen argue that there are four sides to this framework:

# The [[Mechanistic Materialism|mechanistic materialist]] model of the universe that resulted from the [[Scientific Revolution|scientific revolution]] and the subsequent reduction of all things into mere resources to be optimized, dead inert matter to be used
# The rise of [[patriarchal religion]]s and their establishment of gender hierarchies along with their denial of [[Immanence|immanent]] divinity
# Self and other dualisms and the inherent power and domination ethic it entails
# Capitalism and its intrinsic need for the exploitation, destruction and instrumentalization of animals, earth and people for the sole purpose of creating [[wealth]].

They hold that these four factors have brought us to what ecofeminists see as a "separation between nature and culture" that is the root source of our planetary ills.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Gaard, Greta and|first=Gruen, Lori|date=1993|title=Ecofeminism: Toward Global Justice and Planetary Health|url=|journal=Society and Nature|volume=2|pages=1–35|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Concepts ==

=== Modern science and ecofeminism ===
In ''Ecofeminism'' (1993) authors [[Vandana Shiva]], [[Maria Mies]] and [[Evan Bondi]] ponder [[modern science]] and its acceptance as a universal and value-free system. Instead, they view the dominant stream of modern science as a projection of Western men's values.&lt;ref name="Mies"&gt;(Mies, Maria, and Vandana Shiva.  ''Ecofeminism''. Halifax, N.S. : Fernwood Publications; 1993. 24.)&lt;/ref&gt; The privilege of determining what is considered scientific knowledge has been controlled by men, and for the most part of history restricted to men. Bondi and Miles list examples including the medicalization of [[childbirth]] and the industrialization of [[plant reproduction]].&lt;ref name="Mies" /&gt;

Bondi argues that the [[medicalization]] of childbirth has marginalized [[midwife]] knowledge and changed the natural process of childbirth into a procedure dependent on specialized technologies and appropriated expertise.
A common claim within ecofeminist literature is that patriarchal structures justify their dominance through binary opposition, these include but are not limited to: [[heaven]]/earth, mind/body, [[male]]/[[female]], human/animal, spirit/matter, culture/nature and [[White people|white]][[Non-white|/non-white]].&lt;ref name="Hobgood-Oster"&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.clas.ufl.edu/users/bron/PDF--Christianity/Hobgood-Oster--Ecofeminism-International%20Evolution.pdf|title=Ecofeminism: Historic and International Evolution|author=Laura Hobgood-Oster|accessdate=March 17, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Oppression is reinforced by assuming truth in these binaries and instilling them as 'marvelous to behold' through religious and scientific constructs.&lt;ref name="Hobgood-Oster" /&gt;

=== Vegetarian ecofeminism ===
The application of ecofeminism to animal rights has established [[vegetarian ecofeminism]], which asserts that "omitting the oppression of animals from feminist and ecofeminist analyses […] is inconsistent with the activist and philosophical foundations of both feminism (as a "movement to end all forms of oppression") and ecofeminism."&lt;ref name="gaard"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Gaard|first1=Greta Claire|year=2002|title=Vegetarian ecofeminism: A review essay|url=http://muse.jhu.edu/journals/frontiers/v023/23.3gaard.html|journal=Frontiers: A Journal of Women Studies|volume=23|issue=2|page=}}&lt;/ref&gt; It puts into practice "[[the personal is political]]" for it believes that "meat-eating is a form of patriarchal domination…that suggests a link between male violence and a meat-based diet."&lt;ref name="gaard" /&gt; Vegetarian ecofeminism combines sympathy with the analysis of culture and politics to refine a system of ethics and action.&lt;ref name="gaard" /&gt;

=== Materialist ecofeminism ===
Ecofeminism as materialist is another common theme in ecofeminism. A materialist view connects some institutions such as labor, power and property as the source of domination over women and nature. There are connections made between these subjects because similarly there are varying values in production and reproduction.&lt;ref name="Borders" /&gt;

=== Spiritual ecofeminism ===
[[Spiritual ecofeminism]] is another branch of ecofeminism, and is popular among ecofeminist authors such as [[Starhawk]], [[Riane Eisler]], Carol J. Adams, and more. Starhawk calls this an earth-based spirituality, which recognizes that the Earth is alive, that we are interconnected, as well as a community.&lt;ref&gt;Starhawk. "Power, Authority, and Mystery: Ecofeminism and Earth-based Spirituality." ''Reweaving the World: The Emergence of Ecofeminism,'' edited by Irene Diamond and Gloria Orenstein, Sierra Club Books, 1990, pp. 73-86.&lt;/ref&gt; Spiritual ecofeminism is not linked to one specific religion, but is centered around values of caring, [[compassion]], and non-violence.&lt;ref name=":4"&gt;Eisler, Riane. "The Gaia Tradition &amp; The Partnership Future: An Ecofeminist Manifesto." ''Reweaving the World: The Emergence of Ecofeminism,'' edited by Irene Diamond and Gloria Orenstein, Sierra Club Books, 1990, pp. 23-34.&lt;/ref&gt; Often, ecofeminists refer to more ancient traditions, such as the worship of [[Gaia]], the Goddess of nature and spirituality (also known as Mother Earth).&lt;ref name=":4" /&gt;

'''Buddhism'''

Buddhism and feminism simultaneously gained momentum in America during the 1960s. Some of the parallels between these movements include their experiential epistemology, the intersection of the constrained mind, intersectionality and connection, using emotional energy as a coping mechanism, relational ethics, and a communal mindset and lifestyle.&lt;ref&gt;Kaza, Stephanie. “Acting with Compassion: Buddhism, Feminism, and the Environmental Crisis” ''Ecofeminism and the Sacred,'' edited by Carol Adams, Continuum, 1993, Pg 50-69.&lt;/ref&gt;  Both Buddhist and ecofeminist practitioners viewed nature as a pathway to enlightenment and as a source of many jumping off points for introspection and deeper thought about the relationship of nature and humans.&lt;ref&gt;Bloom, Alfred. “Buddhism, Nature and the Environment.” ''The Eastern Buddhist'', vol. 5, no. 1, 1972, pp. 115–129. ''JSTOR'', JSTOR, www.jstor.org/stable/44361321.&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Judaism'''

Jewish ideology emphasizes leaving the earth as it was found (or in better condition than it was found in). This concept is also promoted through ecofeminist theories and movements. Both Judaism and ecofeminism do not always present as social justice movements, but they often contribute ideals and motivations for social change.&lt;ref&gt;Plaskow, Judith. “Feminist Judaism and Repair of the World” ''Ecofeminism and the Sacred,'' edited by Carol Adams, Continuum, 1993, Pg 70-83.&lt;/ref&gt; Social justice is an important part of Judaism, and many practitioners see social justice as a form of spirituality, and some feel this form of spirituality through environmental and feminist movements.&lt;ref&gt;Schwartz, Eilon. “Judaism and Nature: Theological and Moral Issues to Consider While Renegotiating a Jewish..” ''Judaism'', vol. 44, no. 4, Fall 1995, p. 437. ''EBSCOhost'', echo.louisville.edu/login?url=&lt;nowiki&gt;https://search.ebscohost.com/login.aspx?direct=true&amp;db=a9h&amp;AN=9601090437&amp;site=ehost-live&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Hinduism'''

In Hinduism, the Ganges River is personified by the Goddess Ganga. She is a paradoxical deity, as she is supposed to be independent yet guarded, pure yet polluted. Ganga is referred to as a deity to be both subjugated and protected. The underlying tone of the passages is patriarchal despite being reverent. The pollution or purity of the Ganges river is a reflection on Ganga, which represents the relationship between spirituality and nature.&lt;ref&gt;Gupta, Lina. “Ganga: Purity, Pollution, and Hinduism” ''Ecofeminism and the Sacred,'' edited by Carol Adams, Continuum, 1993, Pg 99-116.&lt;/ref&gt; Hinduism emphasizes that all lives are connected and indistinguishable. In this context, every life, be it human or animal, is important.&lt;ref&gt;Singh, Rana PB. "Ecospirituality in Indian Tradition: Messages for Global Order."&lt;/ref&gt;

==Environmental Movements==
Women participated in the [[environmental movement]]s, specifically preservation and conservation beginning in the late nineteenth century and continuing into the early twentieth century.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Mann|first=Susan A.|date=2011|title=Pioneers of U.S. Ecofeminism and Environmental Justice|journal=Feminist Formations|volume=23|issue=2|pages=1–25|doi=10.1353/ff.2011.0028|jstor=41301654}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Movements of the 1970s ===

In [[northern India]] in 1973, women took part in the [[Chipko movement]] to protect forests from [[deforestation]]. [[Non violent protest|Non-violent protest]] tactics were used to occupy trees so that [[loggers]] could not cut them down.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;
[[File:Wangari Maathai no Brasil.jpg|thumb|120px|[[Wangari Maathai]].]]
In [[Kenya]] in 1977, the [[Green Belt Movement]] was initiated by Professor [[Wangari Maathai]], environmental and political activist, and is ongoing today. It is rural [[tree planting]] program led by women, which Maathai designed to help prevent [[desertification]] in the area. The program created a '[[green belt]]' of at least 1,000 trees around villages, and gives participants the ability to take charge in their communities. In later years, the Green Belt Movement was an advocate for informing and empowering citizens through seminars for civic and environmental education, as well as holding national leaders accountable for their actions and instilling agency in citizens.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.greenbeltmovement.org/who-we-are/our-history|title=Our History|last=|first=|date=|website=The Green Belt Movement|publisher=|access-date=October 8, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1978 in [[New York (state)|New York]], mother and environmentalist [[Lois Gibbs]] led her community in protest after discovering that their entire neighborhood, [[Love Canal]], was built on top of a toxic [[dump site]]. The toxins in the ground were causing illness among children and reproductive issues among women, as well as [[birth defect]]s in babies born to pregnant women exposed to the toxins. The Love Canal movement eventually led to the evacuation and relocation of nearly 800 families by the [[Federal government of the United States|federal government]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://chej.org/about-us/story/love-canal/|title=Love Canal|last=|first=|date=|website=Center for Health, Environment, &amp; Justice|publisher=|access-date=October 8, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1980 and 1981, members of such a conference organized a peaceful protest at the [[Pentagon building|Pentagon]]. Women stood, hand in hand, demanding equal rights (including social, economic, and [[reproductive rights]]) as well as an end to militaristic actions taken by the government and exploitation of the community (people and the environment). This movement is known as the [[Women's Pentagon Actions]].&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt;

In 1985, the [[Akwesasne]] Mother's Milk Project was launched by [[Katsi Cook]]. This study was funded by the government, and investigated how the higher level of contaminants in water near the Mohawk [[Indian reservation|reservation]] impacted babies. It revealed that through [[breast milk]], Mohawk children were being exposed to 200% more toxins than children not on the reservation. Toxins contaminate water all over the world, but to due [[environmental racism]], certain subversive groups are exposed to a much higher amount.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.personal.psu.edu/cjm5/blogs/english/2012/04/mothers-milk-project.html|title=Mother's Milk Project|last=Doverspike|first=Nicole|year=2012|website=English 487W Blog: West of Everything|publisher=|access-date=October 9, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Greening of Harlem Coalition]] is another example of an ecofeminist movement. In 1989, [[Bernadette Cozart]] founded the coalition, which is responsible for many urban gardens around [[Harlem]]. Cozart's goal is to turn vacant lots into [[community gardens]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/1993/12/26/nyregion/neighborhood-report-harlem-sowing-a-future-with-green-in-it.html?scp=1&amp;sq=Bernadette%20Cozart&amp;st=cse|title=Neighborhood Report: Harlem; Sowing a Future With Green in It|last=Bernstein|first=Emily|date=1993|newspaper=The New York Times|access-date=October 9, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; This is economically beneficial, and also provides a way for very urban communities to be in touch with nature and each other. The majority of people interested in this project (as noted in 1990) were women. Through these gardens, they were able to participate in and become leaders of their communities. [[Green urbanism|Urban greening]] exists in other places as well. Beginning in 1994, a group of [[African Americans|African-American]] women in [[Detroit]] have developed city gardens, and call themselves the Gardening Angels. Similar garden movements have been occurring globally.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Wild Politics: Feminism, Globalisation, Bio/diversity|last=Hawthorne|first=Susan|publisher=Spinifex Press|year=2002|isbn=|location=Melbourne, Australia|pages=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The development of [[vegetarian ecofeminism]] can be traced to the mid-80s and 90s, where it first appeared in writing. However, the roots of a [[Vegetarianism|vegetarian]] ecofeminist view can be traced back further by looking at sympathy for non-humans and [[Counterculture of the 1960s|counterculture movements]] of the 1960s and 1970s.&lt;ref name="gaard" /&gt; At the culmination of the decade ecofeminism had spread to both coasts and articulated an [[Intersectionality|intersectional analysis]] of women and the environment. Eventually, challenging ideas of environmental [[classism]] and racism, resisting toxic dumping and other threats to the impoverished.&lt;ref name="Gaard" /&gt;

In the 1980s and 1990s some began to see the advancing theories in ecofeminism as essentialist. Through analysis done by post structural and third wave feminists it was argued that ecofeminism equated women with nature. This [[dichotomy]] is dangerous because it groups all women into one category and enforces the very societal norms that feminism is trying to break. Out of this critique rose the [[Gender essentialism|anti-essentialist]] argument. Ecofeminist and author [[Noel Sturgeon]] says in an interview that what anti-essentialists are critiquing is a strategy used to mobilize large and diverse groups of both theorists and activists.&lt;ref&gt;Michiels, Nete. "Social Movements And Feminism." Women &amp; Environments International Magazine, no. 92/93, 2013, pp. 15-17.&lt;/ref&gt;

===1990s–present===
[[File:Video Vandana Shiva 2014.webm|thumb|[[Vandana Shiva]].]]
Coming out of the 90s, ecofeminism met a lot of criticism from anti-essentialist feminism, which heavily critiqued what they viewed as [[essentialism]]. The essentialist view saw ecofeminism as reinforcing and growing patriarchal dominance and norms.&lt;ref name="Borders" /&gt; Feminist thoughts surrounding ecofeminism grew in some areas as it was criticized; vegetarian ecofeminism contributed intersectional analysis; and ecofeminisms that analyzed [[animal rights]], [[labor rights]] and activisms as they could draw lines among oppressed groups. To some, the inclusion of non-human animals also became to be viewed as essentialist. According to ecofeminist and author [[Charlene Spretnak]], modern ecofeminism is concerned about a variety of issues, including reproductive technology, [[Equal pay for equal work|equal pay]] and equal rights, toxic poisoning, [[Third World]] development, and more.&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt;

Ecofeminism as it propelled into the 21st century became aware of the criticisms, and in response ecofeminists with a materialist lens began doing research and renaming the topic, i.e. queer ecologies, global feminist [[environmental justice]], and [[gender]] and the environment.&lt;ref name="Gaard" /&gt;

=== Movements based on literature ===
Beginning in the late 20th century, women worked in efforts to protect [[wildlife]], food, air and water.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Glazebrook|first=Trish|date=Autumn 2002|title=Karen Warren's Ecofeminism|url=|journal=Ethics &amp; the Environment|volume=7|issue=2|pages=12–27|doi=10.2979/ete.2002.7.2.12|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt; These efforts depended largely on new developments in the environmental movement from influential writers, such as [[Henry David Thoreau]], [[Aldo Leopold]], [[John Muir]], and [[Rachel Carson]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Norlock|first=Kathryn J.|date=December 2011|title=Building Receptivity: Leopold's Land Ethic and Critical Feminist Interpretation|url=https://philpapers.org/rec/NORBRL|journal=Journal for the Study of Religion, Nature &amp; Culture|volume=5|issue=4|pages=491–509|doi=10.1558/jsrnc.v5i4.491|via=|type=Submitted manuscript}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Seager|first=Joni|date=Spring 2003|title=Rachel Carson Died of Breast Cancer: The Coming of Age of Feminist Environmentalism|url=|journal=Signs: Journal of Women in Culture and Society|volume=28|issue=3|pages=945–973|doi=10.1086/345456|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Fundamental examples of women's efforts in the 20th century are the books ''[[Silent Spring]]'' by Rachel Carson and ''Refuge'' by [[Terry Tempest Williams]]. These works truly opened American's eyes to the environmental harm they were perpetuating, and created a platform for change.

Ecofeminist author [[Karen J. Warren|Karren Warren]] lists [[Aldo Leopold|Aldo Leopold's]] essay "[[Land ethic|Land Ethic]]" (1949) as a fundamental work to the ecofeminist conception, as Leopold was the first to pen an ethic for the land which understands all non-human parts of that community (animals, plants, land, air, water) as equal to and in a relationship with humans. This inclusive understanding of the environment launched the modern [[Conservation movement|preservation movement]] and illustrated how issues can be viewed through a framework of caring.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;

[[Susan A. Mann]] an eco-feminist and professor of [[Sociological theory|sociological]] and feminist theory considers the roles women played in these activisms to be the starter for ecofeminism in later centuries. Mann associates the beginning of ecofeminism not with feminists but with women of different race and class backgrounds who made connections among gender, race, class and environmental issues. This ideal is upheld through the notion that in activist and theory circles marginalized groups must be included in the discussion. In early environmental and women's movements, issues of varying races and classes were often separated.&lt;ref name="Mann" /&gt;

==Major critiques==
The major criticism of ecofeminism is that it is essentialist.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Gaard|first=Greta|date=Summer 2011|title=Ecofeminism Revisited: Rejecting Essentialism and Re-Placing Species in a Material Feminist Environmentalism|url=|journal=Feminist Formations|volume=23|issue=2|pages=26–53|via=|doi=10.1353/ff.2011.0017}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ascribed essentialism appears in two main areas:

* '''Adherence to strict dichotomy between men and women:''' Some eco-feminist critiques are that the [[dichotomy]] between women and men and nature and culture creates a [[dualistic cosmology|dualism]] that is too stringent and focused in the difference of women and men. That eco-feminism too strongly correlates the [[social status]] of women with the social status of nature, rather than the non-[[Essentialism|essentialist]] view that women along with nature both have masculine and feminine qualities, and that just like feminine qualities have often been seen as less worthy, nature is also seen as having lesser value than culture, or the qualities involved in these concepts.&lt;ref name="greenfuse" /&gt;
* '''Divergent view regarding participation in oppressive structures:''' As opposed to [[Radical feminism|radical]] and [[Liberal feminism|liberation-based]] feminist movements, mainstream feminism which is most tightly bound with [[hegemonic]] social status strives to promote equality within the existing social and political structure,&lt;ref&gt;hooks, bell. "Feminist Theory: From Margin to Center" Cambridge, MA: South End Press 1984&lt;/ref&gt; such as making it possible for women to occupy positions of power in business, industry and politics, using direct involvement as the main tactic for achieving pay equity and influence. In contrast, many ecofeminists oppose active engagement in these areas, as these are the very structures that the movement intends to dismantle.&lt;ref name="greenfuse" /&gt;

[[Social ecology (Bookchin)|Social ecologist]] and feminist [[Janet Biehl]] has criticized ecofeminism for focusing too much on a [[mystical]] connection between women and nature and not enough on the actual conditions of women.&lt;ref name="Biehl"&gt;{{cite book |author=Biehl, Janet |title=Rethinking eco-feminist politics |year=1991 |publisher=[[South End Press]] |location=Boston, Massachusetts |isbn=978-0-89608-392-9}}&lt;/ref&gt; She has also stated that rather than being a forward-moving theory, ecofeminism is an anti-progressive movement for women.&lt;ref name="Biehl" /&gt;

[[Rosemary Radford Ruether]] also critiques this focus on [[mysticism]] over work that focuses on helping women, but argues that spirituality and activism can be combined effectively in ecofeminism.&lt;ref name="Ecofeminism&amp;Globalization"&gt;{{cite book|last=Ruether|first=Rosemary Radford|title=Ecofeminism and Globalization|year=2003|editor=Heather Eaton &amp; Lois Ann Lorentzen|publisher=Rowman and Littlefield|location=Lanham, Boulder, New York, Toronto, Oxford|isbn=978-0-7425-2697-6|pages=vii – xi}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[A.E. Kings]] has criticized ecofeminism for limiting itself to focusing only on gender and the environment, and neglecting to take an intersectional approach. Kings says that ecofeminists claim to be intersectional, however have fallen short on their commitment until recently.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Kings|first=A.E.|date=Spring 2017|title=Intersectionality and the Changing Face of Ecofeminism|url=|journal=Ethics and the Environment|volume=22|pages=63–87|via=|doi=10.2979/ethicsenviro.22.1.04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Theorists==

*'''[[Judi Bari]]''' – Bari was a member of the [[Earth First!]] movement and says she was targeted due to her womanhood.
*'''[[Françoise d'Eaubonne]]''' – Called upon women to lead an ecological revolution in order to save the planet. This entailed revolutionizing gender relations and human relations with the natural world.&lt;ref name=Merchant&gt;(Merchant, Carolyn. "Chapter 8." In Radical ecology: the search for a livable world. New York: Routledge, 1992. 184)&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''[[Greta Gaard]]''' – Greta Gaard is an American ecofeminist scholar and activist. Her major contributions to the field connect ideas of queer theory, vegetarianism, and animal liberation. Her major theories include ecocriticism which works to include literary criticism and composition to inform ecofeminism and other feminist theories to address wider range of social issues within ecofeminism. She is an ecological activist and leader in the U.S. Green Party, and the Green Movement.
*'''[[Sallie McFague]]''' – A prominent ecofeminist [[theologian]], McFague uses the metaphor of God's body to represent the universe at large. This metaphor values inclusive, mutualistic and interdependent relations amongst all things.&lt;ref&gt;Ralte, Lalrinawmi. [http://www.rethinkingmission.org.uk/articles/The%20World%20as%20the%20body%20of%20God%20article.pdf The World as the Body of God Ecofeminist Theological Discourse with Special Reference to Tribal Women in India.], rethinkingmission.org, accessed March 24, 2012&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''[[Carolyn Merchant]]''' – Historian of science who taught at [[University of California, Berkeley|Berkeley]] for many years. Her book ''The Death of Nature: Women, Ecology and the Scientific Revolution'' is a classic ecofeminist text.
*'''[[Mary Mellor]]''' – UK sociologist who moved to ecofeminist ideas from an interest in cooperatives. Her books - ''Breaking the Boundaries'' and ''Feminism and Ecology'' are grounded in a materialist analysis.
*'''[[Maria Mies]]''' – Mies is a [[Germany|German]] [[Social criticism|social critic]] who has been involved in feminist work throughout [[Europe]] and [[India]]. She works particularly on the intersections of patriarchy, [[poverty]], and the environment on a local and global scale.&lt;ref name="Ecofeminism&amp;Globalization" /&gt;
*'''[[Val Plumwood]]''' – Val Plumwood, formerly Val Routley, was an Australian ecofeminist intellectual and activist, who was prominent in the development of radical [[ecosophy]] from the early 1970s through the remainder of the 20th century. In her works "Feminism and the Mastery of Nature" she describes the relationship of mankind and the environment relating to an eco-feminist ideology.
*'''[[Rosemary Radford Ruether]]''' – Has written 36 books and over 600 articles exploring the intersections of feminism, theology, and [[Creation Care|creation care]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=LaRosa|first=Patricia|title=Finding Aid for Rosemary Radford Ruether Papers, 1954-2002|url=http://library.columbia.edu/content/dam/libraryweb/libraries/burke/fa/awts/ldpd_5632346.pdf|accessdate=15 March 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''[[Ariel Salleh]]''' – Australian ecofeminist with a global perspective; a founding editor of the journal ''Capitalism Nature Socialism''; author of two books and some 200 articles examining links with [[Deep ecology|deep]] and [[Social ecology (Bookchin)|social ecology]], green politics and [[eco-socialism]].
*'''[[Vandana Shiva]]''' – Shiva is a [[physicist]], author, activist, feminist and philosopher from India.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Who's Who of Women and the Environment|url=http://www.unep.org/women_env/w_details.asp?w_id=107|accessdate=15 March 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;  She was a participant in the [[Chipko movement]] of the 1970s, which used non-violent activism to protest and prevent deforestation in the [[Garhwal Himalaya|Garhwal]] [[Himalayas]] of [[Uttarakhand]], India then in [[Uttar Pradesh]].
*'''[[Charlene Spretnak]]''' – Spretnak is an American writer largely known for her writing on ecology, politics and spirituality. Through these writings Spretnak has become a prominent ecofeminist. She has written many books which discuss ecological issues in terms of effects with social criticisms, including feminism. Spretnak works had a major influence in the development of the [[Green Party of the United States|Green Party]]. She has also won awards based on her visions on ecology and social issues as well as feminist thinking.&lt;ref name="Spretnak"&gt;Charlene Spretnak, "The Early Years of the Green Movement in the United States", in Zelko and Brinkmann, eds., ''Green Parties'', p.&amp;nbsp;48.&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''[[Starhawk]]''' – An American writer and activist Starhawk is known for her work in spiritualism and ecofeminism. She advocates for social justice in issues surrounding nature and spirit. These social justice issues fall under the scope of feminism and ecofeminism. She believes in fighting oppression through intersectionality and the importance of spirituality, eco consciousness and [[Sexual liberation|sexual]] and gender liberation.&lt;ref name=Starhawk&gt;see [[Starhawk]]&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''[[Douglas Vakoch]]'''  – An American ecocritic whose edited volumes include ''Ecofeminism and Rhetoric: Critical Perspectives on Sex, Technology, and Discourse'' (2011),&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://www.worldcat.org/title/ecofeminism-and-rhetoric-critical-perspectives-on-sex-technology-and-discourse/oclc/714734848|title=Ecofeminism and rhetoric: critical perspectives on sex, technology, and discourse|last=Vakoch|first=Douglas A|date=2011-01-01|publisher=Berghahn Books|isbn=9780857451873|location=New York|language=English}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Feminist Ecocriticism: Environment, Women, and Literature'' (2012),&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://www.worldcat.org/title/feminist-ecocriticism-environment-women-and-literature/oclc/815941726|title=Feminist ecocriticism: environment, women, and literature|last=Vakoch|first=Douglas A|date=2012-01-01|publisher=Lexington Books|isbn=9780739176825|location=Lanham, Md.|language=English}}&lt;/ref&gt; and (with Sam Mickey) ''Ecofeminism in Dialogue'' (2018),&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://www.worldcat.org/title/ecofeminism-in-dialogue/oclc/1005695115|title=Ecofeminism in Dialogue|last=Vakoch|first=Douglas A.|last2=Mickey|first2=Sam|publisher=Lexington Books|year=2018|isbn=9781498569279|location=Lanham, MD|pages=}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Literature and Ecofeminism: Intersectional and International Voices'' (2018),&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://www.worldcat.org/title/literature-and-ecofeminism-intersectional-and-international-voices/oclc/1020319048|title=Literature and Ecofeminism: Intersectional and International Voices|last=Vakoch|first=Douglas A.|last2=Mickey|first2=Sam|publisher=Routledge|year=2018|isbn=978-0815381723|location=London|pages=}}&lt;/ref&gt; and ''Women and Nature?: Beyond Dualism in Gender, Body, and Environment'' (2018).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://www.worldcat.org/title/women-and-nature-beyond-dualism-in-gender-body-and-environment/oclc/975383028|title=Women and Nature?: Beyond Dualism in Gender, Body, and Environment|last=Vakoch|first=Douglas|last2=Mickey|first2=Sam|publisher=Routledge|year=2018|isbn=9781138053427|location=London|pages=|language=English}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
*'''[[Karen J. Warren|Karen Warren]]''' – received her B.A. in philosophy from the [[University of Minnesota]] (1970) and her Ph.D. from the [[University of Massachusetts Amherst|University of Massachusetts-Amherst]] in 1978. Before her long tenure at [[Macalester College]], which began in 1985, Warren was Professor of Philosophy at [[St. Olaf College]] in the early 1980s. Warren was the Ecofeminist-Scholar-in-Residence at [[Murdoch University]] in Australia.&lt;ref name="MacGregor" /&gt; In 2003, she served as an [[University of Oxford|Oxford University]] Round Table Scholar and as Women's Chair in Humanistic Studies at [[Marquette University]] in 2004. She has spoken widely on environmental issues, feminism, critical thinking skills and peace studies in many international locations including [[Buenos Aires]], [[Gothenburg]], [[Helsinki]], [[Oslo]], [[Manitoba]], [[Melbourne]], [[Moscow]], [[Perth]], the [[Earth Summit|U.N. Earth Summit]] in [[Rio de Janeiro]] (1992), and San Jose.

== See also ==
{{div col|colwidth=18em}}
* [[Anarcha-feminism]]
* [[Chipko movement]]
* [[Deep ecology]]
* [[Deep Green Resistance]]
* [[Ecofeminist art]]
* [[Green syndicalism]]
* [[Intersectionality]]
* [[List of ecofeminist authors]]
* [[Social ecology (Bookchin)|Social ecology]]
* [[Queer ecology]]
* [[Vegetarian Ecofeminism|Vegetarian ecofeminism]]
* [[Women and the environment through history]]
{{div col end}}

== References ==
{{Reflist|refs=
&lt;ref name=Gaard&gt;{{cite journal|last=Gaard|first=Greta|title=Ecofeminism Revisited: Rejecting Essentialism and Re-Placing Species in a Material Feminist Environmentalism|journal=Feminist Formations|date=2011|volume=23|issue=2|pages=26–53|doi=10.1353/ff.2011.0017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Mann&gt;{{cite journal|last=Mann|first=Susan A|title=Pioneers of U.S. Ecofeminism and Environmental Justice|journal=Feminist Formations|date=2011|volume=23|issue=2|pages=1–25|doi=10.1353/ff.2011.0028}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
&lt;ref name=Borders&gt;{{cite web|title=Ecofeminism: Is the Movement Still Relevant? |url=http://www.genderacrossborders.com/2012/03/22/ecofeminism-is-the-movement-still-relevant/|publisher=Gender Across Borders}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="greenfuse"&gt;{{cite web|title=Ecofeminism Critique|url=http://www.thegreenfuse.org/ecofemcrit.htm#root|publisher=The Green Fuse}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
}}

==Further reading==

===Key works===
* ''Ancient Futures: Learning from Ladakh'', by [[Helena Norberg-Hodge]]
* ''The Body of God'' by [[Sallie McFague]]
* ''The Chalice &amp; The Blade: Our History, Our Future'', by [[Riane Eisler]]
* ''The Death of Nature: Women, Ecology, and the Scientific Revolution'' by [[Carolyn Merchant]]
* ''Ecofeminism'' by [[Maria Mies]] and [[Vandana Shiva]]
* ''Ecofeminism in Latin America'' by Mary Judith Ross
* ''Ecofeminist Philosophy'' by [[Karen J. Warren]]
* ''Environmental Culture'' by [[Val Plumwood]]
* ''Feminism and the Mastery of Nature'', by [[Val Plumwood]]
* ''Gaia &amp; God: An Ecofeminist Theology of Earth Healing'', by [[Rosemary Radford Ruether]]
* ''Integrating Ecofeminism, Globalization, and World Religions'', by [[Rosemary Radford Ruether]]
* ''Neither Man Nor Beast'' by [[Carol J. Adams]]
* ''Refuge: An Unnatural History of Family and Place'' by [[Terry Tempest Williams]]
* ''The Resurgence of the Real: Body, Nature, and Place in a Hypermodern World'' by [[Charlene Spretnak]]
* ''Sacred Longings: Ecofeminist theology and Globalization'' by [[Mary Grey (theologian)|Mary Grey]]
* ''The Sexual Politics of Meat'' by [[Carol J. Adams]]
* ''[[Silent Spring]]'' by [[Rachel Carson]]
* ''[[The Spiral Dance]]'' by [[Starhawk]]
* ''Staying Alive: Women, Ecology and Development'' by [[Vandana Shiva]]
* ''Thinking Green! Essays on Environmentalism, Feminism, and Nonviolence,'' by [[Petra Kelly]]
* ''Tomorrow's Biodiversity'' by [[Vandana Shiva]]
* ''Woman and Nature: The Roaring Inside Her'', by [[Susan Griffin]]
* ''Breaking the Boundaries'', by [[Mary Mellor]]
* ''Ecofeminism as Politics: nature, Marx, and the postmodern'', by [[Ariel Salleh]]

===Anthologies===
* ''Animals and Women: Feminist Theoretical Explorations'', edited by [[Carol J. Adams]] and Josephine Donovan
* ''Ecofeminism: Women, Animals, Nature'', edited by [[Greta Gaard]]
* ''Ecofeminism: Women, Culture, Nature'', edited by Karen J. Warren with editorial assistance from Nisvan Erkal
* ''EcoFeminism &amp; Globalization: exploring culture, context and religion'', edited by Heather Eaton &amp; Lois Ann Lorentzen
* ''Ecofeminism and Rhetoric: Critical Perspectives on Sex, Technology, and Discourse'', edited by [[Douglas Vakoch|Douglas A. Vakoch]]
* ''Ecofeminism and the Sacred'', edited by Carol J. Adams
* ''Ecofeminism in Dialogue'', edited by [[Douglas Vakoch|Douglas A. Vakoch]] and Sam Mickey
* ''Feminist Ecocriticism: Environment, Women, and Literature'', edited by [[Douglas Vakoch|Douglas A. Vakoch]]
* ''Literature and Ecofeminism: Intersectional and International Voices'', edited by [[Douglas Vakoch|Douglas A. Vakoch]] and Sam Mickey
* ''The Politics of Women's Spirituality: Essays on the Rise of Spiritual Power within the Feminist Movement'', edited by [[Charlene Spretnak]]
* ''Readings in Ecology and Feminist Theology'', edited by Mary Heather MacKinnon and Moni McIntyre
* ''Reclaim the Earth'', edited by Leonie Caldecott &amp; Stephanie Leland
* ''Reweaving the World: The Emergence of Ecofeminism'', edited by Irene Diamond and Gloria Feman Orenstein
* ''Women and Nature?: Beyond Dualism in Gender, Body, and Environment'', edited by [[Douglas Vakoch|Douglas A. Vakoch]] and Sam Mickey
* ''Women Healing Earth: Third World Women on Ecology, Feminism, and Religion'', edited by Rosemary Radford Ruether

===Journal articles===
*{{cite journal | last1 = Gaard | first1 = Greta Claire | year = 2011 | title = Ecofeminism Revisited: Rejecting Essentialism and Re-Placing Species in a Material Feminist Environmentalism | url = | journal = Feminist Formations | volume = 23 | issue = 2| pages = 26–53 | doi=10.1353/ff.2011.0017}}
* {{cite journal | last1 = Huggan | first1 = Graham | year = 2004 | title = "Greening" Postcolonialism: Ecocritical Perspectives | url = | journal = MFS Modern Fiction Studies | volume = 50 | issue = 3| pages = 701–733 | doi=10.1353/mfs.2004.0067}}
* {{cite journal | last1 = Mack-Canty | first1 = Colleen | year = 2004 | title = Third-Wave Feminism and the Need to Reweave the Nature/ Culture Duality | url = | journal = NWSA Journal | volume = 16 | issue = 3| pages = 154–179 | doi=10.1353/nwsa.2004.0077}}
* {{cite journal | last1 = MacGregor | first1 = Sherilyn | year = 2004 | title = From care to citizenship: Calling ecofeminism back to politics | url = | journal = Ethics &amp; the Environment | volume = 9 | issue = 1| pages = 56–84 | doi=10.1353/een.2004.0007}}
* {{cite journal | last1 = Mallory | first1 = Chaone | year = 2013 | title = Locating Ecofeminism in Encounters with Food and Place | url = | journal = Journal of Agricultural &amp; Environmental Ethics | volume = 26 | issue = 1| pages = 171–189 | doi=10.1007/s10806-011-9373-8}}
*Mann, Susan A. 2011. Pioneers of U.S. Ecofeminism and Environmental Justice, "Feminist Formations" 23(2): 1-25.
*{{cite journal | last1 = Wildy | first1 = Jade | year = 2012 | title = The Artistic Progressions of Ecofeminism: The Changing Focus of Women in Environmental Art | url = | journal = International Journal of the Arts in Society | volume = 6 | issue = 1| pages = 53–65 | doi=10.18848/1833-1866/cgp/v06i01/35978}}

===Fiction===
{{see also|Feminist science fiction}}
* "Clementa" by Jim Martin
* ''A Door Into Ocean'' by [[Joan Slonczewski]]
* ''[[Always Coming Home]]'' by [[Ursula K. Le Guin]]
* ''[[Buffalo Gals, Won't You Come Out Tonight]]'' by [[Ursula K. Le Guin]]
* ''[[The Fifth Sacred Thing]]'' by [[Starhawk]]
* ''[[The Gate to Women's Country]]'' by [[Sheri S. Tepper]]
* ''The Holdfast Chronicles'' by [[Suzy McKee Charnas]]
* ''Native Tongue'' by [[Suzette Haden Elgin]]
* ''The Parable of the Sower'' by [[Octavia Butler]]
* '' Prodigal Summer'' by [[Barbara Kingsolver]]
* ''[[Surfacing (novel)|Surfacing]]'' by [[Margaret Atwood]]
* ''The Wanderground'' by [[Sally Miller Gearhart]]
* ''[[Woman on the Edge of Time]]'' by [[Marge Piercy]]
* ''[[The Kin of Ata are Waiting for You]]'' by [[Dorothy Bryant]]
* ''Bear'' by [[Marian Engel]]
* ''[[The Temple of My Familiar]]'' by [[Alice Walker]]
* ''A Bengali play, "NEELKANTHA DESH" (2010), by Supratim Roy
* ''Sultana's Dream (1905), by Begum Rokeya Sakhawat Hossain

==Poetry==
*''The Sea of Affliction'' (1987, reprinted 2010) by [[Rosemarie Rowley]]

== External links ==
{{wikiversity|Women's Studies}}
*[http://lgruen.faculty.wesleyan.edu/files/2011/05/Gaard.pdf Ecofeminism: Toward global justice and planetary health] Feminist Greta Gaard and Lori Gruen's ecofeminist framework
*[http://www.ecofem.org ecofem.org] Includes the regularly updated "Ecofeminism Bibliography"
*[http://www.ecofeminism.net ecofeminism.net]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20061001140008/http://www.metanexus.net/metanexus_online/show_article2.asp?id=2669 "An Ecology of Knowledge: Feminism, Ecology and the Science and Religion Discourse" [[Metanexus Institute]]] by Lisa Stenmark
*[http://www.users.drew.edu/ckeller/Dark-Vibe.pdf "Ecofeminism and the Democracy of Creation"] by Catherine Keller (2005) ; cf. [[Carol P. Christ]], "Ecofeminism," in [[Michel Weber]] and Will Desmond (eds.), ''[https://www.academia.edu/279955/Handbook_of_Whiteheadian_Process_Thought Handbook of Whiteheadian Process Thought]'', Frankfurt / Lancaster, ontos verlag, 2008, pp.&amp;nbsp;87–98.
*[http://www.lespantheresroses.org/textes/ecology_toward_a_queer_ecofeminism.pdf "Toward a Queer Ecofeminism"] by Greta Gaard

{{Feminist theory}}
{{Environmental humanities}}
{{Environmental social science}}
{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Ecofeminism| ]]
[[Category:Environmentalism]]
[[Category:Feminist theory]]
[[Category:Relational ethics]]
[[Category:Environmental movements]]
[[Category:Feminist movements and ideologies]]
[[Category:Feminism and health]]
[[Category:Feminism and history]]
[[Category:Environmental social science concepts]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>