<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061020172215|82656688" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="40494939" pageid="40494939" ns="0" title="Ecofeminism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-10-21T07:29:34Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Feminism}}
'''Ecofeminism''' is a social and political movement which unites [[environmentalism]] and [[feminism]], with some currents linking [[deep ecology]] and [[feminism]].&lt;ref name="ruether"&gt;{{cite book | first=Rosemary Radford | last=Ruether | title=Ecofeminism and the Sacred | publisher=The Continuum Publishing Company | location=New York, New York | pages=13 | year=1993 | editor=[[Carol Adams]] | chapter=Ecofeminism: Symbolic and Social Connections of the Oppression of Women and the Domination of Nature | chapterurl=http://www.class.uidaho.edu/envphilsummer/readings/Wk%2010%20Ecofeminism/ruether.pdf | id=ISBN 0-8264-0586-X}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Ecofeminists argue that a relationship exists between the [[oppression]] of [[Woman|women]] and the degradation of [[Natural environment|nature]], and explore the [[intersectionality]] between [[sexism]], the [[domination of nature]], [[racism]], [[speciesism]], and other characteristics of [[social inequality]]. Some current work emphasizes that the capitalist and patriarchal system is based on triple domination of the "Southern people" (those people who live in Third World countries, the majority of which are south of the equator), women, and nature. &lt;ref&gt;introduction of ''Ecofeminism'' by [[Maria Mies]] and [[Vandana Shiva]]&lt;/ref&gt;    

== Ecofeminist analysis == 

Ecofeminism, or ecological feminism is a term coined in 1974 by [[Françoise d'Eaubonne]]. It is a [[philosophy]] and movement born from the union of feminist and ecological thinking, and the belief that the social mentality that leads to the domination and oppression of women is directly connected to the social mentality that leads to the abuse of the environment. It combines [[eco-anarchism]] or [[bioregional democracy]] with a strong ideal of feminism. Its advocates often emphasize the importance of interrelationships between humans, non-human others (e.g., animals and insects), and the earth.  

A central tenet in ecofeminism states that male ownership of land has led to a dominator culture (patriarchy), manifesting itself in food export, over-grazing, the [[tragedy of the commons]], exploitation of people, and an abusive land ethic, in which animals and land are valued only as economic resources. Other ecofeminists explain how the degradation of nature contributes to the degradation of women.  For example, Thomas-Slayter, and Rocheleau detail how in Kenya, the capitalist driven export economy caused most of the land to be used for monoculture cash crops.  This lead to intensification of pesticide use, resource depletion and marginalization of the subsistence farmers, especially women, to the hillsides and less productive land, where their deforestation and cultivation led to soil erosion furthering the environmental degradation that hurts their own productivity (Thoma-Slayter, B. and D. Rocheleau.  (1995)  Gender, Environment and Development in Kenya: A Grassroots Perspective).

Vandana Shiva makes it clear that one of the missions of ecofeminism is to redefine how societies look at productivity and activity of both women and nature who have mistakenly been deemed passive, allowing for them both to be ill-used. For example, she draws a picture of a stream in a forest.  According to her, in our society it is seen to be unproductive if it is simply there fulfilling the water needs of women’s families and communities until engineers come along and tinker with it, perhaps damming it and using it for hydropower.  The same is true of a forest unless it is planted with a monoculture plantation of commercial species.   A forest may very well be being productive, protecting groundwater, creating oxygen, allowing villagers to harvest fruit, fuel and craft materials and creating a habitat for animals that are also a valuable resource.  However, for many, if it isn't for export or contribute to GDP, without a dollar value attached it cannot seen as a productive resource (4 Staying Alive: Women, Ecology and Development 1988). 

Some ecofeminists point to the linguistic links between oppression of women and land, such as the terms, "rape the land", "tame nature," and "reap nature's bounty." Terms also express nature as feminine (using the pronoun "she" and the term "mother nature") and women as "wild" and "untamed" (like nature). Ecofeminists also criticize Western lifestyle choices, such as consuming food that has travelled thousands of miles and playing sports (like [[golf]] and [[bobsledding]]), which inherently require ecological destruction. 

Feminist and [[social ecology|social ecologist]] [[Janet Biehl]] has criticized ecofeminism as [[idealism|idealist]], focusing too much on the idea of a mystical connection with nature and not enough on the actual conditions of women. However, this line of criticism may not apply to many ecofeminists who reject both [[mysticism]] and [[essentialism|essentialist]] ideas about the connection between women and nature.  This antiessentialist ecofeminism has become more prominent since the early 1990s. [http://www.lancs.ac.uk/staff/twine/ecofem/bookreview.html]

And some "spiritual" ecofeminists can't be accused of inconsistency: they have an epistemological analysis of the Enlightenment&lt;ref&gt; see chapter 1 of "ecofeminism" Mies and Shiva, which applies to materialist and spiritualist ecofeminism&lt;/ref&gt;, want to place the spirituality in immanent world and then practice modern activism&lt;ref name=Starhawk&gt; see [[Starhawk]]&lt;/ref&gt;, discuss economical and political issues while working with the power of Great mother earth (metaphorically or magically according to their tendencies).

===Views on technology ===
Françoise d'eaubonne proned a cooperative system, in small unities (villages) with autonomization, without alienating technology.  With ecofeminist ideals and [[pagan]] practices&lt;ref name=Starhawk/&gt;, sometimes these projects are seen as a form of [[primitivism]]. However, while some see technology as almost inherently alienating, many ecofeminists see a substantial role for modern technologies in the creation and operation of such villages. For instance, a number of ecofeminists advocate the use of technologies such as [[solar power]]&lt;ref&gt; Vandana Shiva, for example http://www.solarconference.net/news.htm &lt;/ref&gt; as a way to stay off 'the grid', which they regard as more important than not relying on poisonous industrial processes or materials. The ecology movement is itself split on issues like this.  However, it is likely that intermediate technology, [[appropriate technology]] would be preferred in general, if an ecofeminist movement sought to spread into [[developing nations]] quickly.


===Feminist Political Ecology ===
The study of the relationship between environment, gender and development has grown recently because of the restructuring of economies, environment and culture at a global and local level. Men and women have been affected as actors who determine environmental management, resource use, and the creation of environmental policies of health and well-being. Although some scholars do not see any differences between gender and their relation to the environment, other scholars see a major difference in the impact of environment between men and women.  This impact is not caused by biological differences between genders, but by the social constructs of gender, which vary depending on culture, class, race, and geographical location, and they change over time with individuals and societies.

There are different relevant schools of feminist thought and activism that relate to the analysis of the environment. Ecofeminism argues that there is a connection between women and nature that comes from their shared history of oppression by a patriarchal western society; this connection also comes from the positive identification of women with nature. This relationship can be argued from an essentialist position, attributing it to biological factors, or from a position that explains it as a social construct. Vandana Shiva explains how women's special connection to the environment through her daily interactions with it has been ignored.  "Women in subsistence economies, producing and reproducing wealth in partnership with nature, have been experts in their own right of holistic and ecological knowledge of nature’s processes.  But these alternative modes of knowing, which are oriented to the social benefits and sustenance needs are not recognised by the [capitalist] reductionist paradigm, because it fails to perceive the interconnectedness of nature, or the connection of women’s lives, work and knowledge with the creation of wealth.”  (Staying Alive: Women Ecology and Development, 1988:24). 

Feminist environmentalists study gender interests in natural resources and processes based on their different roles in daily work and responsibilities. Social feminists focus on the role of gender in political economy by analyzing the impact of production and reproduction of men and women’s relation to economic systems. Feminist poststructuralists explain gender’s relation to the environment as a reflection of beliefs of identity and difference such as race, class, gender, age, and ethnicity. In this way it tries to explain the relation of gender and development. Liberal feminist environmentalists treat women as having an active role in environmental protection and conservation programs. This role can become problematic.  There is a common symbolism in the idea of ‘man’ pitted against nature while nature is feminized and “woman” is assumed to have profound connections with her environment.  (Varadarajan, "Women and Environment  Eco-feminists’ perspectives". In Empowerment of Women and Ecological Development 2002:445).  This becomes problematic because it places all the responsibility for conserving on her rather than him and doesn’t allow her to be seen as profiting from using the environment as well.
	
These views of gender and environment constitute feminist political ecology, which links feminist cultural ecology, political ecology, geographical ecology and feminist political ecology into one concept. It argues that gender is a relevant factor in determining access and control of natural resources as it relates to class, race, culture and ethnicity to transform the environment and to achieve the community’s opportunities of sustainable development (Rochelau, Thomas-Slayter and Wangari, 1996).

==Notable ecofeminist anthologies==
* ''Animals and Women: Feminist Theoretical Explorations'', edited by [[Carol J. Adams]] and [[Josephine Donovan]]
* ''Ecofeminism: Animals, Women, Nature'', edited by [[Greta Gaard]]
* ''EcoFeminism &amp; Globalization: exploring culture, context and religion'', edited by Heather Eaton &amp; Lois Ann Lorentzen
* ''Ecofeminism and the Sacred'', edited by Carol J. Adams
* ''[[Reclaim the Earth]]'', edited by [[Leonie Caldecott]] &amp; [[Stephanie Leland]]
* ''Reweaving the World: The Emergence of Ecofeminism'', edited by Irene Diamond and Gloria Feman Orenstein
* ''Women Healing Earth: Third World Women on Ecology, Feminism, and Religion'', edited by Rosemary Radford Ruether

==Notable ecofeminist books==
===Nonfiction===

* ''Ancient Futures: Learning from Ladakh'', by [[Helena Norberg-Hodge]]
* ''The Chalice &amp; The Blade: Our History, Our Future'', by [[Riane Eisler]]
* ''Ecofeminism'' by [[Maria Mies]] and [[Vandana Shiva]]
* ''Feminism and the Mastery of Nature'', by [[Val Plumwood]]
* ''Gaia &amp; God: An Ecofeminist Theology of Earth Healing'', by [[Rosemary Radford Ruether]]
* ''Integrating Ecofeminism, Globalization, and World Religions'', by [[Rosemary Radford Ruether]]
* ''[[Neither Man Nor Beast]]'' by [[Carol J. Adams]]
* ''Sacred Longings: Ecofeminist theology and Globalization'' by [[Mary Grey]]
* ''[[The Sexual Politics of Meat]]'' by [[Carol J. Adams]]
* ''[[The Spiral Dance]]'' by [[Starhawk]]
* ''[[Tomorrow's Biodiversity]]'' by [[Vandana Shiva]]
* ''Woman and Nature: The Roaring Inside Her'', by [[Susan Griffin]]
* ''Ecofeminist Philosophy'' by [[Karen Warren]]
* ''Environmental Culture'' by [[Val Plumwood]]
* ''The Body of God'' by [[Sallie McFague]]
* ''Staying Alive: Women, Ecology and Development'' by [[Vandana Shiva]]

=== Fiction ===
* ''[[A Door Into Ocean]]'' by [[Joan Slonczewski]]
* ''[[Always Coming Home]]'' by [[Ursula K. Le Guin]]
* "[[Buffalo Gals Won't You Come Out Tonight?]]" by [[Ursula K. Le Guin]]
* ''[[The Fifth Sacred Thing]]'' by [[Starhawk]]
* ''[[The Gate to Women's Country]]'' by [[Sheri S. Tepper]]
* ''[[The Holdfast Chronicles]]'' by [[Suzy McKee Charnas]]
* ''[[Native Tongue]]'' by [[Suzette Haden Elgin]]
* ''[[The Parable of the Sower]]'' by [[Octavia Butler]]
* ''[[Surfacing (novel)|Surfacing]]'' by [[Margaret Atwood]]
* ''[[The Wanderground]]'' by [[Sally Miller Gearhart]]
* ''[[Woman on the Edge of Time]]'' by [[Marge Piercy]]
* "[[The Kin of Ata Are Waiting for You]]" by [[Dorothy Bryant]]

{{listdev}}

==  Notes ==
&lt;div class="references-small"&gt;&lt;references /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

==See also==
* [[List of ecofeminist authors]]
* [[Deep ecology]]
* [[Anarcha-feminism]]
* [[Anarcho-primitivism]]
* [[Social ecology]]
* [[Green syndicalism]]
* [[Ubuntu (ideology)|Ubuntu]]
* [[Feminism]]
* [[Animal rights]]
* [[Animal liberation]]
* [[Gaia theory (science)|Gaia theory]]
* [[Gaia philosophy]]

== External links ==
*[http://www.dancingrabbit.org/ Dancing Rabbit Ecovillage]
*[http://www.aquapulse.net/knowledge/nature De/colonizing Nature, by Stephen Hui]  ''link ?''
*[http://www.ecofem.org www.ecofem.org]
*[http://marc.smartelectronix.com/rtso/ An Ecofeminist Look at the Patriarchal Social Order]
*[http://x.webring.com/hub?ring=ecofem Ecofeminism Web Ring]
*[http://www.ecofeminism.net Ecofeminism.net]
*[http://eve.enviroweb.org/index.html Eve Online]
*[http://www.triroc.com/caroladams/ Carol Adams' Website]
*[http://www.starhawk.org/ Starhawk's Website]
*[http://www.vshiva.net/ Vandana Shiva's Website]
*[http://www.ic.org/eco/  Feminist Ecovillage Project]
*[http://www.users.drew.edu/ckeller/Dark-Vibe.pdf Catherine Keller's 2005 pdf article: Ecofeminism and the Democracy of Creation]
*[http://www.metanexus.net/metanexus_online/show_article2.asp?ID=2669 An Ecology of Knowledge: Feminism, Ecology and the Science and Religion Discourse]" by Lisa Stenmark

[[Category:Anarchism]]
[[Category:Anti-globalization]]
[[Category:Currents within green politics]]
[[Category:Feminism]]
[[Category:Social movements]]

[[br:Ekobenelouriezh]]
[[de:Ökofeminismus]]
[[et:Ökofeminism]]
[[el:Οικοφεμινισμός]]
[[es:Ecofeminismo]]
[[fr:Écoféminisme]]
[[gl:Ecofeminismo]]
[[pl:Ekofeminizm]]
[[pt:Ecofeminismo]]
[[tr:Ekofeminizm]]
[[zh:生態女性主義]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>