<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20121022160150|519222204" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="40494939" pageid="40494939" ns="0" title="Ecofeminism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2012-10-24T06:49:11Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Green politics sidebar |expanded=all}}
{{Feminism sidebar |expanded=Waves}}

'''Ecofeminism''' describes movements and philosophies that link [[feminism]] with [[ecology]].&lt;ref name=MacGregor&gt;{{Cite book |author=MacGregor, Sherilyn |title=Beyond mothering earth: ecological citizenship and the politics of care |year=2006 |publisher=UBC Press |location=Vancouver |isbn=0-7748-1201-X |page=286}}&lt;/ref&gt; The term is believed to have been coined by the French writer, [[Françoise d'Eaubonne]] in her book, ''Le Féminisme ou la Mort''.&lt;ref name=Merchant/&gt; Ecofeminism connects the exploitation and domination of women with that of the environment, and argues that there is a connection between women and nature that comes from their shared history of oppression by a patriarchal Western society. 

[[Vandana Shiva]] claims that women have a special connection to the environment through their daily interactions with it that has been ignored. She says that women in subsistence economies who produce "wealth in partnership with nature, have been experts in their own right of holistic and ecological knowledge of nature's processes." However she makes the point that "these alternative modes of knowing, which are oriented to the social benefits and sustenance needs are not recognized by the [[capitalism|capitalist]] [[Reductionism|reductionist]] paradigm, because it fails to perceive the interconnectedness of nature, or the connection of women's lives, work and knowledge with the creation of wealth."&lt;ref name=Shiva&gt;{{Cite book |author=Shiva, Vandana |title=Staying alive: women, ecology and development |year=1988 |publisher=Zed Books |location=London |isbn=978-0-86232-823-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;

However, feminist and [[social ecology|social ecologist]] [[Janet Biehl]] has criticized ecofeminism for focusing too much on a mystical connection between women and nature and not enough on the actual conditions of women.&lt;ref name= Biehl&gt;{{Cite book |author=Biehl, Janet |title=Rethinking eco-feminist politics |year=1991 |publisher=[[South End Press]] |location=Boston, Massachusetts |isbn=978-0-89608-392-9}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Concepts ==
In ''Ecofeminism'' (1993) authors Vandana Shiva and Maria Mies critique modern science and its acceptance as a universal and value free system. Instead, they view the dominant stream of modern science as a projection of Western men's values.&lt;ref name=Miles&gt;(Mies, Maria, and Vandana Shiva.  ''Ecofeminism''. Halifax, N.S. : Fernwood Publications; 1993. 24.)&lt;/ref&gt; The privilege of determining what is considered scientific knowledge has been controlled by men, and for the most part of history restricted to men. Shiva and Miles list examples including the medicalization of childbirth and the industrialization of plant reproduction.&lt;ref name=Miles/&gt; 

These authors argue that the medicalization of childbirth has marginalized [[midwife]] knowledge and changed the natural process of childbirth into a procedure dependent on specialized technologies and appropriated expertise. Similarly, the dependence of agriculture on industrially produced seed and fertilizer makes a natural, regenerative process dependent on technological input.&lt;ref name=Miles/&gt;

A common claim within ecofeminist literature is that patriarchal structures justify their dominance through binary opposition, these include but are not limited to: heaven/earth, mind/body, male/female, human/animal, spirit/matter, culture/nature and white/non-white.&lt;ref name=Hobgood-Oster/&gt;  Oppression is reinforced by assuming truth in these binaries and instilling them as 'sacred' through religious and scientific constructs.&lt;ref name=Hobgood-Oster&gt;(Hobgood-Oster, Laura. "Ecofeminism: Historic and International Evolution." www.clas.ufl.edu/users/bron/PDF--Christianity/Hobgood-Oster--Ecofeminism-International%20Evolution.pdf (accessed March 17, 2012) )&lt;/ref&gt;

== Theorists ==

[[Françoise d'Eaubonne]] called upon women to lead an ecological revolution in order to save the planet. This entailed revolutionizing gender relations and human relations with the natural world.&lt;ref name=Merchant&gt;(Merchant, Carolyn. "Chapter 8." In Radical ecology: the search for a livable world. New York: Routledge, 1992. 184)&lt;/ref&gt;

Sallie McFague, a prominent ecofeminist theologian, uses the metaphor of God's body to represent the universe at large. This metaphor values inclusive, mutualistic and interdependent relations amongst all things.&lt;ref&gt;(Ralte, Lalrinawmi . "The World as the Body of God Ecofeminist Theological Discourse with Special Reference to Tribal Women in India. Www. rethinkingmission.org.uk/articles/The%20World%20as%20the%20body%20of%20God%20article.pdf (accessed March 24, 2012))&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Anarcha-feminism]]
* [[Deep ecology]]
* [[Deep Green Resistance]]
* [[Intersectionality]]
* [[Green syndicalism]]
* [[List of ecofeminist authors]]
* [[Social ecology]]
* [[Women and the environment through history]]

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
;Anthologies
* ''Animals and Women: Feminist Theoretical Explorations'', edited by [[Carol J. Adams]] and Josephine Donovan
* ''Ecofeminism: Women, Animals, Nature'', edited by [[Greta Gaard]]
* ''EcoFeminism &amp; Globalization: exploring culture, context and religion'', edited by Heather Eaton &amp; Lois Ann Lorentzen
* ''Ecofeminism and the Sacred'', edited by Carol J. Adams
* ''The Politics of Women's Spirituality: Essays on the Rise of Spiritual Power within the Feminist Movement'', edited by [[Charlene Spretnak]]
* ''Readings in Ecology and Feminist Theology'', edited by Mary Heather MacKinnon and Moni McIntyre
* ''Reclaim the Earth'', edited by Leonie Caldecott &amp; Stephanie Leland
* ''Reweaving the World: The Emergence of Ecofeminism'', edited by Irene Diamond and Gloria Feman Orenstein
* ''Women Healing Earth: Third World Women on Ecology, Feminism, and Religion'', edited by Rosemary Radford Ruether

;Journal articles
* Mack-Canty, Colleen. 2004. Third-Wave Feminism and the Need to Reweave the Nature/ Culture Duality, ''NWSA Journal'' 16(3):154-179.
* MacGregor, Sherilyn. 2004. From care to citizenship: Calling ecofeminism back to politics, ''Ethics &amp; the Environment'' 9(1):56-84.
* Huggan, Graham. 2004. "Greening" Postcolonialism: Ecocritical Perspectives, ''MFS Modern Fiction Studies'' 50(3):701-733.

;Non-fiction
* ''Ancient Futures: Learning from Ladakh'', by [[Helena Norberg-Hodge]]
* ''The Body of God'' by [[Sallie McFague]]
* ''The Chalice &amp; The Blade: Our History, Our Future'', by [[Riane Eisler]]
* ''The Death of Nature: Women, Ecology, and the Scientific Revolution'' by [[Carolyn Merchant]]
* ''Ecofeminism'' by [[Maria Mies]] and [[Vandana Shiva]]
* ''Ecofeminist Philosophy'' by [[Karen J. Warren]]
* ''Environmental Culture'' by [[Val Plumwood]]
* ''Feminism and the Mastery of Nature'', by [[Val Plumwood]]
* ''Gaia &amp; God: An Ecofeminist Theology of Earth Healing'', by [[Rosemary Radford Ruether]]
* ''Integrating Ecofeminism, Globalization, and World Religions'', by [[Rosemary Radford Ruether]]
* ''Neither Man Nor Beast'' by [[Carol J. Adams]]
* ''Refuge: A Unnatural History of Family and Place'' by [[Terry Tempest Williams]]
* ''The Resurgence of the Real: Body, Nature, and Place in a Hypermodern World'' by [[Charlene Spretnak]]
* ''Sacred Longings: Ecofeminist theology and Globalization'' by [[Mary Grey (theologian)|Mary Grey]]
* ''The Sexual Politics of Meat'' by [[Carol J. Adams]]
* ''[[Silent Spring]]'' by [[Rachel Carson]]
* ''[[The Spiral Dance]]'' by [[Starhawk]]
* ''Staying Alive: Women, Ecology and Development'' by [[Vandana Shiva]]
* ''Thinking Green! Essays on Environmentalism, Feminism, and Nonviolence,'' by [[Petra Kelly]]
* ''Tomorrow's Biodiversity'' by [[Vandana Shiva]]
* ''Woman and Nature: The Roaring Inside Her'', by [[Susan Griffin]]

;Fiction
''Also see [[ecotopian literature]] and [[feminist science fiction]]''
* "Clementa" by Jim Martin
* ''A Door Into Ocean'' by [[Joan Slonczewski]]
* ''[[Always Coming Home]]'' by [[Ursula K. Le Guin]]
* ''[[Buffalo Gals, Won't You Come Out Tonight]]'' by [[Ursula K. Le Guin]]
* ''[[The Fifth Sacred Thing]]'' by [[Starhawk]]
* ''[[The Gate to Women's Country]]'' by [[Sheri S. Tepper]]
* ''The Holdfast Chronicles'' by [[Suzy McKee Charnas]]
* ''Native Tongue'' by [[Suzette Haden Elgin]]
* ''The Parable of the Sower'' by [[Octavia Butler]]
* '' Prodigal Summer'' by [[Barbara Kingsolver]]
* ''[[Surfacing (novel)|Surfacing]]'' by [[Margaret Atwood]]
* ''The Wanderground'' by [[Sally Miller Gearhart]]
* ''[[Woman on the Edge of Time]]'' by [[Marge Piercy]]
* ''[[The Kin of Ata are Waiting for You]]'' by [[Dorothy Bryant]]
* ''Bear'' by [[Marian Engel]]
* ''[[The Temple of My Familiar]]'' by [[Alice Walker]]
* ''A Bengali play "NEELKANTHA DESH" (2010) by Supratim Roy

== External links ==
{{wikiversity|Women's Studies}}
*[http://www.ecofem.org ecofem.org] Includes the regularly updated "Ecofeminism Bibliography"
*[http://www.ecofeminism.net ecofeminism.net]
*[http://www.metanexus.net/metanexus_online/show_article2.asp?ID=2669 "An Ecology of Knowledge: Feminism, Ecology and the Science and Religion Discourse" [[Metanexus Institute]]] by Lisa Stenmark
*[http://www.users.drew.edu/ckeller/Dark-Vibe.pdf "Ecofeminism and the Democracy of Creation"] by Catherine Keller (2005)
*[http://www.lespantheresroses.org/textes/ecology_toward_a_queer_ecofeminism.pdf "Toward a Queer Ecofeminism"] by Greta Gaard

{{Feminist theory}}

[[Category:Ecofeminism| ]]
[[Category:Environmentalism]]
[[Category:Feminist theory]]
[[Category:Relational ethics]]
[[Category:Environmental movements]]
[[Category:Feminist movement]]
[[Category:Feminism and health]]
[[Category:Feminism and history]]

[[bg:Екофеминизъм]]
[[br:Ekobenelouriezh]]
[[de:Ökofeminismus]]
[[et:Ökofeminism]]
[[el:Οικοφεμινισμός]]
[[es:Ecofeminismo]]
[[eu:Ekofeminismo]]
[[fr:Écoféminisme]]
[[gl:Ecofeminismo]]
[[ko:생태여성주의]]
[[hr:Ekofeminizam]]
[[it:Ecofemminismo]]
[[he:אקופמיניזם]]
[[nl:Ecofeminisme]]
[[ja:エコフェミニズム]]
[[no:Økofeminisme]]
[[pl:Ekofeminizm]]
[[pt:Ecofeminismo]]
[[ru:Экофеминизм]]
[[sh:Ekofeminizam]]
[[fi:Ekofeminismi]]
[[sv:Ekofeminism]]
[[tr:Ekofeminizm]]
[[zh:生態女性主義]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>