<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20241125135525|1259493229" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="732260" pageid="732260" ns="0" title="Religious segregation"><revisions><rev timestamp="2024-11-25T13:57:16Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Separation of people according to their religion}}
[[File:Endingen Doppeltuer.jpg|thumb|right|Two separate doors (one for Jews, and one for Christians) on a house in the town of [[Endingen, Switzerland]]]]{{Discrimination sidebar|state=collapsed}}'''Religious segregation''' is the separation of people according to their [[religion]]. The term has been applied to cases of religious-based segregation which occurs as a social phenomenon, as well as segregation which arises from laws, whether they are explicit or implicit.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Religious Segregation in the Schools of Northern Ireland|last=Knox|first=H. M.|journal=British Journal of Educational Studies|volume=21|issue = 3|pages=307–312|date=October 1973|jstor = 3120328|doi=10.1080/00071005.1973.9973387}} "...[S]egregated schooling, although in theory open to all, is in practice availed of by virtually only one denomination...." Also refers to pre-[[Partition of Ireland|Partition]] religious schools which retained their exclusively Catholic demographics after Partition.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=American Cultural Pluralism and Law|last1=Norgren|first1=Jill|last2=Nanda|first2= Serena|author2-link=Serena Nanda |isbn=978-0-275-98692-6|publisher=Greenwood Publishing Group|year=2006|pages=132}}, quoting U.S. Supreme Court Justice [[Anthony Kennedy]] in ''[[Board of Education of Kiryas Joel Village School District v. Grumet]]'': "...[D]rawing school district lines along the religious lines of the village impermissibly involved the state in accomplishing the religious segregation."&lt;/ref&gt;

The similar term '''religious apartheid''' has also been used for situations where people are separated based on their religion, including sociological phenomena.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.christianitytoday.com/ct/2000/septemberweb-only/26.0b.html|title=Pakistan's Christians Demand End to 'Religious Apartheid' at Polls|work=Christianity Today|last=Akkaro|first=Anta|access-date=2008-08-18|date=2000-09-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite episode|title=Religion In Schools|url=http://www.teachers.tv/video/24057|series=The Big Debate|airdate=2008-01-29|minutes=0:09:29 and 0:11:52|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080921052334/http://www.teachers.tv/video/24057|archive-date=2008-09-21}}, in which Rabbi Dr Jonathan Romain says (at 0:09:29): "If you have separate Jewish, Catholic, Muslim, Sikh, Hindu schools, essentially you're segregating children, you're separating children" and (at 0:11:52): "It's a religious apartheid society we're creating."&lt;/ref&gt;

==Bahrain==
{{Main|Human rights in Bahrain|Freedom of religion in Bahrain}}

==Bosnia and Herzegovina==
Religious segregation has been practiced in Bosnia and Herzegovina since the 12th century.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Alibašić |first=Ahmet |url=https://academic.oup.com/edited-volume/34375/chapter-abstract/291538221?redirectedFrom=fulltext# |title=The Oxford Handbook of European Islam |date=2015-01-06 |publisher=Oxford Academic |pages=429-474 |chapter=10 Bosnia and Herzegovina |doi=10.1093/oxfordhb/9780199607976.013.17}}&lt;/ref&gt; Being historically a multi-ethnic and multi-religious nation, ethnicity and religion are interchangeable within the nation: [[Croats of Bosnia and Herzegovina|Croatians]] are largely [[Catholic Church|Catholic]], [[Bosniaks]] are largely [[Muslims|Muslim]], and [[Serbs]] are largely [[Serbian Orthodox Church|Orthodox]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Begicevic |first=Alma |last2=Balint |first2=Jennifer |date=2023-12-30 |title=Constricted rights and imagined identities: Peace and accountability processes and constitution-making in Bosnia and Herzegovina |url=https://academic.oup.com/icon/article/21/4/1069/7559249 |journal=International Journal of Constitutional Law |language=en |volume=21 |issue=4 |pages=1069–1098 |doi=10.1093/icon/moad097 |issn=1474-2640}}&lt;/ref&gt; These [[Ethnoreligious group|ethnoreligious]] linkages have influenced political and cultural dynamics, especially during periods of political dominance under foreign dominance where in one group would hold power over the others. Bosniak Muslims held more political influence and power under the [[Ottoman Empire]] than any other group, the Catholic Croats held power under the [[Austria-Hungary|Austro-Hungarian Empire]], and the Serbs held major political influence during the [[Kingdom of Yugoslavia]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Alibašić |first=Ahmet |date=2020-12-11 |title=History of Inter-Religious Dialogue in Bosnia and Herzegovina: From Force-Feeding to Sustainability? |url=https://brill.com/view/journals/jrat/6/2/article-p343_6.xml |journal=Interdisciplinary Journal for Religion and Transformation in Contemporary Society |volume=6 |issue=2 |pages=343–364 |doi=10.30965/23642807-00602006 |issn=2365-3140}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Schooling in Bosnia and Herzegovina has been segregated by religion with educational services being provided by religious groups and organizations, this practice finds its roots as far back as the [[Vidovdan Constitution]] of 1921.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Religious education for a plural society in Bosnia and Herzegovina. Intersections between separate school systems, religious actors and public institutions {{!}} PAPERS |url=https://papers.aarweb.org/paper/religious-education-plural-society-bosnia-and-herzegovina-intersections-between-separate |access-date=2024-07-29 |website=papers.aarweb.org}}&lt;/ref&gt; Religious segregation in schooling continued during [[Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia|Communist Yugoslavia]] with government intervention proving ineffective. Since 1995 with the implementation of the [[Dayton Agreement]], the Bosnian government has agreed and maintained upon a “two schools under one roof policy”, allowing religious schooling to continue as a form of cultural protection.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=Soetermeer |first=M. |date=2023-12-07 |title=The “Two Schools under One Roof” System: Bosnia’s Challenges to Reconciliation |url=https://www.fomoso.org/en/mosopedia/essays/the-two-schools-under-one-roof-system-bosnias-challenges-to-reconciliation/ |access-date=2024-07-29 |website=FOMOSO |language=en-GB}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2014, [[Herzegovina-Neretva Canton|Herzegovina-Neretva]] became the first canton to ban religious schooling.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=TransConflict |date=2017-03-14 |title=Two Schools Under One Roof: Lesson In Ethnic Unmixing From Bosnia’s Segregated School System – Analysis |url=https://www.eurasiareview.com/14032017-two-schools-under-one-roof-lesson-in-ethnic-unmixing-from-bosnias-segregated-school-system-analysis/ |access-date=2024-07-29 |website=Eurasia Review |language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==India==
{{main|Religious violence in India|Violence against Muslims in independent India|Violence against Christians in India}} 
{{See also|Freedom of religion in India|Caste-related violence in India}}

The debate over the ban on non-Hindus entering Hindu temples began around 30 years ago when singer [[Yesudas]], who planned to take part in a music program, was stopped at the [[Guruvayur Temple]] gate. He finally had to sing ''[[bhajan]]s'' outside the temple wall. Though several temples in [[Kerala]] have signs saying non-Hindus are barred entry, few of them enforce it as strictly as Guruvayur Temple, which insists on following its distinct traditions. 'Only Orthodox Hindus are allowed’, reads a signboard hanging from the Lion's Gate of the Sri Jagannath Temple in [[Puri]]. The issue has triggered many a controversy in the past and continues to arouse strong feelings even today.&lt;ref name="OutlookInd"&gt;{{cite web |last1=Sahu |first1=Sandeep |title=SC For Entry Of Non-Hindus Into Puri Jagannath Temple, Will Servitors Allow? |url=https://www.outlookindia.com/website/story/sc-for-entry-of-non-hindus-into-puri-jagannath-temple-will-servitors-allow/313183 |website=Outlookindia.com |publisher=Outlook |access-date=25 July 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{citation needed|date=January 2019}}

In the past a number of dignitaries, including former [[Prime Minister of India|prime minister]] [[Indira Gandhi]], had not been allowed to enter the 12th century shrine; she was married to a [[Parsi]], [[Feroze Gandhi]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |date=2018-06-27 |title=Not Just President Kovind, Even Mahatma Gandhi and Indira Were Stopped at Jagannath Temple |url=https://www.news18.com/news/india/not-just-president-kovind-even-mahatma-gandhi-and-indira-were-stopped-at-jagannath-temple-1792257.html |access-date=2024-07-29 |website=News18 |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2005, Princess [[Sirindhorn|Mahachakri Sirindhorn]] of [[Thailand]] was not allowed inside the temple as she is a [[Buddhism in Thailand|Buddhist]].&lt;ref name="OutlookInd"/&gt;{{citation needed|date=January 2019}}

In 2006, the shrine did not allow a citizen of [[Switzerland]] named Elizabeth Jigler, who had donated 17.8 million Indian rupees to the temple, because she is a Christian. Kashi Vishvanath Varanasi in [[Varanasi]], the temple stands on the western bank of the [[holy river]] [[Ganges|Ganga]], and is one of the [[12 Jyotirlingas]], the holiest of Shiva temples. The most famous of the many temples in Varanasi is the one dedicated to ''Vishveswara''—[[Shiva]] as Lord of the Universe. Non-Hindus are not allowed inside the temple, although this is not always enforced. On the northern side of [[Kashi Vishwanath Temple|Vishwanath Temple]] is the Gyan Kupor Well. Non-Hindus are also strictly forbidden entry here.{{citation needed|date=January 2019}}

==Partition of British India==
{{POV section|note=This should also include the violence against Muslims inside India during partition|date=November 2023}}
[[File:Population density map of British India according to 1911 Census.jpg|thumb|300px|Map of [[colonial India]], which was [[partition of India|partitioned]] to create Pakistan as a homeland for [[Islam in India|Indian Muslims]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Haqqani |first1=Hussain |title=Pakistan: Between Mosque and Military |date=2010 |publisher=Brookings Institution Press |page=4 |language=en |quote=Coalescing in the All-India Muslim League and led by Muhammad Ali Jinnah, these Muslim nationalists asserted that India's Muslims constituted a nation separate from non-Muslim Indians and subsequently demanded a separate homeland in areas with a Muslim majority.}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
The [[partition of India]] entailed creating two countries - India and Pakistan - on the basis of religion,&lt;ref name="Sinha2014"&gt;{{cite book |last1=Sinha |first1=Jai B. P. |title=Psycho-Social Analysis of the Indian Mindset |date=2014 |publisher=Springer |isbn=978-81-322-1804-3 |page=190 |language=en |quote=The partition of the Indian subcontinent was based on the formula of religious segregation. Many Muslims migrated to Pakistan, but many more also decided to stay back. The country had an obligation to protect Islamic interests as Muslims in India tied their destiny with the rest. There were also Christians, Jews, Sikhs, Buddhists, Jains and other communities which were living mostly in peace for centuries.}}&lt;/ref&gt; as demanded by [[Muhammad Ali Jinnah]] and the [[All India Muslim League]], though not without [[opposition to the partition of India|significant opposition]].&lt;ref name="Ashraf2017"&gt;{{cite web |last1=Ashraf |first1=Ajaz |title=India's Muslims and the Price of Partition |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2017/08/17/opinion/india-muslims-hindus-partition.html |work=[[The New York Times]] |date=17 August 2017|quote= Many Indian Muslims, including religious scholars, ferociously opposed the Muslim League's demand for Pakistan.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Ahmed2016"&gt;{{cite web |last1=Ahmed |first1=Ishtiaq |title=The dissenters |url=https://www.thefridaytimes.com/tft/the-dissenters/ |publisher=[[The Friday Times]] |language=en |date=27 May 2016|quote=However, the book is a tribute to the role of one Muslim leader who steadfastly opposed the Partition of India: the Sindhi leader Allah Bakhsh Soomro. Allah Bakhsh belonged to a landed family. He founded the Sindh People's Party in 1934, which later came to be known as ‘Ittehad’ or ‘Unity Party’. ... Allah Bakhsh was totally opposed to the Muslim League's demand for the creation of Pakistan through a division of India on a religious basis. Consequently, he established the Azad Muslim Conference. In its Delhi session held during April 27–30, 1940 some 1400 delegates took part. They belonged mainly to the lower castes and working class. The famous scholar of Indian Islam, Wilfred Cantwell Smith, feels that the delegates represented a ‘majority of India's Muslims’. Among those who attended the conference were representatives of many Islamic theologians and women also took part in the deliberations.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title=Asia and the Americas |journal=Asia and the Americas |date=1946 |volume=46 |page=212 |publisher=Asia Press |language=en |quote=Many Muslim organizations are opposed to it. Every non-Muslim, whether he is a Hindu or Sikh or Christian or Parsi, is opposed to it. Essentially the sentiment in favor of partition has grown in the areas where Muslims are in a small minority, areas which, in any event, would remain undetached from the rest of India. Muslims in provinces where they are in a majority have been less influenced by it; naturally, for they can stand on their own feet and have no reason to fear other groups. It is least evident in the Northwest Frontier Province (95 per cent Muslim) where the Pathans are brave and self-reliant and have no fear complex. Thus, oddly enough, the Muslim League's proposal to partition India finds far less response in the Muslim areas sought to be partitioned than in the Muslim minority areas which are unaffected by it.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the colonial Indian province of [[Sind Province (1936–55)|Sind]], the historian [[Ayesha Jalal]] describes the actions that the All India Muslim League used in order to undermine the government of [[Allah Bakhsh Soomro]], which [[opposition to the partition of India|stood for a united India]]:&lt;ref name="Jalal2002"&gt;{{cite book |last1=Jalal |first1=Ayesha |title=Self and Sovereignty: Individual and Community in South Asian Islam Since 1850 |date=2002 |publisher=Routledge |isbn=9781134599370 |page=415 |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{blockquote|Even before the 'Pakistan' demand was articulated, the dispute over the Sukkur Manzilgah had been fabricated by provincial Leaguers to unsettle Allah Bakhsh Soomro's ministry which was dependent on support from the Congress and Independent Party. Intended as a way station for Mughal troops on the move, the Manzilgah included a small mosque which had been subsequently abandoned. On a small island in the near distance was the temple of Saad Bela, sacred space for the large number of Hindus settled on the banks of the Indus at Sukkur. The symbolic convergence of the identity and sovereignty over a forgotten mosque provided ammunition for those seeking office at the provincial level. Making an issue out of a non-issue, the Sind Muslim League in early June 1939 formally reclaimed the mosque. Once its deadline of 1 October 1939 for the restoration of the mosque to Muslims had passed, the League started an agitation.&lt;ref name="Jalal2002"/&gt;}}

In the few years before the partition, the Muslim League "monetarily subsidized" mobs that engaged in communal violence against Hindus and Sikhs in the areas of Multan, Rawalpindi, Campbellpur, Jhelum and Sargodha, as well as in the [[Hazara District]].&lt;ref name="Abid2014"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Chitkara1996"&gt;{{cite book |last1=Chitkara |first1=M. G. |title=Mohajir's Pakistan |date=1996 |publisher=APH Publishing |isbn=9788170247463 |language=en |quote=When the idea of Pakistan was not accepted in the Northern States of India, the Muslim League sent out its goons to drive the Hindus out of Lahore, Multan and Rawalpindi and appropriate their property.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Bali1949"&gt;{{cite book |last1=Bali |first1=Amar Nath |title=Now it can be told |date=1949 |publisher=Akashvani Prakashan Publishers |page=19 |language=en |quote=The pamphlet 'Rape of Rawalpindi' gives gruesome details of what was done to the minorities in the Rawalpindi Division. No such details have been published for other towns but the pattern of barbarities committed by the Muslim League goondas was the same everywhere.}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Muslim League paid assassins money for every Hindu and Sikh they murdered.&lt;ref name="Abid2014"&gt;{{cite web |last1=Abid |first1=Abdul Majeed |title=The forgotten massacre |url=https://nation.com.pk/29-Dec-2014/the-forgotten-massacre |website=The Nation |date=29 December 2014 |quote=On the same dates, Muslim League-led mobs fell with determination and full preparations on the helpless Hindus and Sikhs scattered in the villages of Multan, Rawalpindi, Campbellpur, Jhelum and Sargodha. The murderous mobs were well supplied with arms, such as daggers, swords, spears and fire-arms. (A former civil servant mentioned in his autobiography that weapon supplies had been sent from NWFP and money was supplied by Delhi-based politicians.) They had bands of stabbers and their auxiliaries, who covered the assailant, ambushed the victim and if necessary disposed of his body. These bands were subsidized monetarily by the Muslim League, and cash payments were made to individual assassins based on the numbers of Hindus and Sikhs killed. There were also regular patrolling parties in jeeps which went about sniping and picking off any stray Hindu or Sikh. ... Thousands of non-combatants including women and children were killed or injured by mobs, supported by the All India Muslim League.}}&lt;/ref&gt; As such, leaders of the pro-separatist Muslim League, including Muhammad Ali Jinnah, issued no condemnation of the violence against Hindus and Sikhs in the Punjab.&lt;ref name="Ranjan2018"&gt;{{cite book |last1=Ranjan |first1=Amit |title=Partition of India: Postcolonial Legacies |date=2018 |publisher=[[Taylor &amp; Francis]] |isbn=9780429750526 |language=en |quote=In the evening of 6 March Muslim mobs numbering in the thousands headed towards Sikh villages in Rawalpindi, Attock and Jhelum districts. ... According to British sources, some two thousand people were killed in the carnage in three rural district: almost all non-Muslims. The Sikhs claimed seven thousand dead. Government reports showed that Muslim ex-service persons had taken part in the planned attacks. The Muslim League leaders, Jinnah and others did not issue any condemenation of these atrocities.}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{blockquote|Amid a terrible slaughter in which all main communities were both aggressors and victims, somewhere between half a million and a million people were killed. Tens of thousands of women were abducted, usually by men of a different religion. In Punjab in particular, where Hindus, Muslims and Sikhs had lived together for generations and spoke the same language, a stark segregation was brought about as Muslims headed west to Pakistan and Hindus and Sikhs fled east to India. —[[British Broadcasting Corporation]]&lt;ref name="BBC2017"&gt;{{cite web |title=Partition 70 years on: The turmoil, trauma - and legacy |url=https://www.bbc.com/news/world-asia-40643413 |publisher=[[BBC]] |access-date=11 June 2020 |language=en |date=27 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

== Iran ==
[[Shi'a Islam]] has been the [[state religion]] of [[Iran]] since the [[Iranian Revolution]] in 1979. While [[Judaism]], [[Christianity]], and [[Zoroastrianism]] are officially recognized and legally protected religious minorities, they are not allowed to evangelize or allow Muslim Iranians to convert to other faiths.

Other religious minorities, such as those of the [[Baháʼí Faith]], are not recognized by the government and thus do not have any legal protections nor the [[Constitution of the Islamic Republic of Iran|constitutional]] right to practice their religion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fidh.org/IMG/pdf/ir0108a.pdf|title=Discrimination against religious minorities in IRAN|page=6|publisher=FIDH|access-date=2008-08-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Muslim Network for Baháʼí Rights has reported cases of Baháʼí students being expelled from [[university]] due to their religion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bahairights.org/2007/07/18/bahais-in-iran-deprived-of-their-education/|title=Baha'i children in Egypt not being admitted to schools because of their faith|work=Muslim Network for Bahá'í Rights|access-date=2008-08-03|archive-date=2019-03-01|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190301013418/http://www.bahairights.org/2007/07/18/bahais-in-iran-deprived-of-their-education/|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mideastyouth.com/2008/07/06/schools-out-for-the-bahais/|title=School's Out for the Bahá'ís|access-date=2008-08-03|work=Mideast Youth|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://archive.today/20120525144733/http://www.mideastyouth.com/2008/07/06/schools-out-for-the-bahais/|archive-date=2012-05-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.bahai.org/story/575|title=Confidential Iran memo exposes policy to deny Bahá'í students university education|work=Bahá'í World News Service|access-date=2008-08-03|date=2007-08-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;
According to the Times Higher Education, Baháʼí educators are required to renounce their faith in order to teach in Iranian universities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.timeshighereducation.co.uk/story.asp?storyCode=203640&amp;sectioncode=26|title=Segregation in Iran|work=Times Higher Education|access-date=2008-08-03|publisher=TSL Education Ltd.|date=2006-06-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; Due to its [[Heterodoxy|heterodox]] beliefs, the Baháʼí faith is officially considered a [[heresy|heretical]] movement because of the Baháʼí belief that [[Bahá'u'lláh]] is a divinely ordained prophet in contradiction of the [[Qur'an]], which asserts that Muhammad is the [[Seal of the prophets|last and final messenger]] sent to mankind.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.iranian.ws/iran_news/publish/article_26173.shtml |access-date=2008-08-03 |title=Iran: Religious minority reports arson attacks |work=Persian Journal |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130610153003/http://www.iranian.ws/iran_news/publish/article_26173.shtml |archive-date=June 10, 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.abc.net.au/rn/talks/8.30/relrpt/stories/s892997.htm|title=Islam and apostasy|work=The Religion Report|publisher=ABC Radio National (Australia)|access-date=2008-08-05|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20111012073200/http://www.abc.net.au/rn/talks/8.30/relrpt/stories/s892997.htm|archive-date=2011-10-12|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.clarionledger.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20080719/FEAT04/807190313/1022|title=Bahá'í believers know freedom and oppression|work=Clarion Ledger|access-date=2008-08-03}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Malaysia==
In 2015, Malaysian human rights activist Shafiqah Othman Hamzah noted that the practice of apartheid policies against different religions in [[Malaysia]] is institutionalised and widespread, adding that "What we are living in Malaysia is almost no different from apartheid."&lt;ref name="HSO"&gt;{{Cite web|last=Hamzah|first=Shafiqah Othman|title=Are we headed for a Malaysian apartheid? {{!}} Malay Mail|url=https://www.malaymail.com/news/opinion/2015/12/04/are-we-headed-for-a-malaysian-apartheid/1016713|access-date=17 November 2021|website=www.malaymail.com|date=4 December 2015 |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Myanmar==
{{main|2012 Rakhine State riots}}

The 2012 Rakhine State riots are a series of ongoing conflicts between Rohingya Muslims and ethnic Rakhine in northern [[Rakhine State]], [[Myanmar]]. The riots broke out after weeks of sectarian disputes and they have been condemned by most people on both sides of the conflict.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=https://www.reuters.com/article/us-myanmar-violence-idUSBRE85714E20120608 | title=Four killed as Rohingya Muslims riot in Myanmar: government | work=Reuters | date=8 June 2012 | access-date=9 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
The immediate cause of the riots is unclear, with many commentators citing the killing of ten Burmese Muslims by ethnic Rakhine after the gang rape and murder of a Rakhine woman as the main cause.&lt;ref name=PhilInquirer&gt;{{cite news|last=Lauras|first=Didier|title=Myanmar stung by global censure over unrest|url=http://newsinfo.inquirer.net/271174/myanmar-stung-by-global-censure-over-unrest|access-date=15 September 2012|newspaper=Agence France-Presse in the Philippine Daily Inquirer|date=15 September 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Whole villages have been "decimated".&lt;ref name=PhilInquirer /&gt;  Over three hundred houses and a number of public buildings have been razed. According to Tun Khin, the President of the Burmese Rohingya Organisation UK (BROUK), as of 28 June 650 Rohingyas have been killed, 1,200 are missing, and more than 80,000 have been displaced.&lt;ref name="dvb_hindstorm"/&gt; According to the Myanmar authorities, the violence, between ethnic Rakhine Buddhists and Rohingya Muslims, left 78 people dead, 87 injured, and thousands of homes destroyed. It also displaced more than 52,000 people.&lt;ref name="UN News"&gt;{{cite news|title=UN refugee agency redeploys staff to address humanitarian needs in Myanmar|work=UN News|date=29 June 2012|url=https://www.un.org/apps/news/story.asp?NewsID=42356|access-date=29 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The government has responded by imposing curfews and by deploying troops in the region. On 10 June 2012, a [[state of emergency]] was declared in Rakhine, allowing the military to participate in the administration of the region.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://burma.irrawaddy.org/archives/11901 | title=အေရးေပၚအေျခအေန ေၾကညာခ်က္ ႏုိင္ငံေရးသမားမ်ား ေထာက္ခံ | publisher=The Irrawaddy | date=11 June 2012 | access-date=11 June 2012 | author=Linn Htet}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news | first = Fergal | last = Keane | author-link = Fergal Keane | title = Old tensions bubble in Burma | url = https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-18402678 | publisher = BBC News | date = 11 June 2012 | access-date = 2012-06-11 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The Burmese army and police have been accused of targeting Rohingya Muslims through mass arrests and arbitrary violence.&lt;ref name="dvb_hindstorm"&gt;{{cite news|last=Hindstorm|first=Hanna|title=Burmese authorities targeting Rohingyas, UK parliament told|url=http://www.dvb.no/news/burmese-authorities-targeting-rohingyas-uk-parliament-told/22676|access-date=9 July 2012|date=28 June 2012|agency=[[Democratic Voice of Burma]]|archive-date=25 September 2018|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180925033559/http://www.dvb.no/news/burmese-authorities-targeting-rohingyas-uk-parliament-told/22676|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; A number of monks' organisations that played a vital role in Burma's struggle for democracy have taken measures to block any humanitarian assistance to the Rohingya community.&lt;ref name="ti_hindstorm"&gt;{{cite news|last=Hindstorm|first=Hanna|title=Burma's monks call for Muslim community to be shunned|url=https://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/asia/burmas-monks-call-for-muslim-community-to-be-shunned-7973317.html|access-date=25 July 2012|date=25 July 2012|work=[[The Independent]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;
In July 2012, the Myanmar Government did not include the Rohingya minority group–-classified as [[Statelessness|stateless]] Bengali Muslims from Bangladesh. Myanmar immigration law was amended in 1982 declared 135 indigenous ethnic races of Myanmar without the Rohingya and therefore they are not granted the indigenous rights and only small part of the people can claim Myanmar citizenship per the law.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url= http://www.thehindu.com/news/international/article3703383.ece|title= Rohingyas are not citizens: Myanmar minister| date= 1 August 2012 |website=The Hindu |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160107231250/http://www.thehindu.com/news/international/article3703383.ece |archive-date= Jan 7, 2016 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to [[Amnesty International]], the Muslim [[Rohingya people]] have continued to suffer from [[human rights]] violations under the Burmese [[Military dictatorship|junta]] since 1978, and many have fled to neighbouring [[Bangladesh]] as a result.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-18921960 |title=Muslims in Burma's Rakhine state 'abused' - Amnesty |date=20 July 2012 |website=BBC News |url-status=live |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20231107182338/https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-18921960 |archive-date= Nov 7, 2023 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.amnesty.org/en/news/myanmar-rohingya-abuses-show-human-rights-progress-backtracking-2012-07-19 |date=19 July 2012 |title=Myanmar: Abuses against Rohingya erode human rights progress |website=Amnesty International |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150221095159/http://www.amnesty.org/en/news/myanmar-rohingya-abuses-show-human-rights-progress-backtracking-2012-07-19 |archive-date=2015-02-21 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Desperate plight of Burma's Rohingya people |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/south_asia/8605669.stm |date=4 June 2010 |website=BBC News |url-status=live |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20231031124434/http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/south_asia/8605669.stm |archive-date= Oct 31, 2023 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

As of 2005, the UNHCR ([[United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees]]) had been assisting with the repatriation of Rohingya from Bangladesh, but allegations of human rights abuses in the refugee camps have threatened this effort.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 |url         = http://www.newagebd.com/2005/may/21/front.html#9
 |title       = UNHCR threatens to wind up Bangladesh operations
 |publisher   = New Age BDNEWS, Dhaka
 |date        = 2005-05-21
 |access-date  = 2007-04-25
 |url-status     = dead
 |archive-url  = https://web.archive.org/web/20090425140346/http://www.newagebd.com/2005/may/21/front.html#9
 |archive-date = 2009-04-25
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite earlier efforts by the UN, the vast majority of Rohingya refugees have remained in Bangladesh, unable to return because of the regime in Myanmar. Now they face problems in Bangladesh where they do not receive support from the government.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/asia-pacific/7019882.stm |title=Burmese exiles in desperate conditions |author=Mark Dummett |date=29 September 2007 |website=BBC News |access-date=29 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; In February 2009, many Rohingya refugees were helped by [[Acehnese people|Acehnese]] [[sailor]]s in the [[Strait of Malacca]], after 21 days at sea.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://epaper.kompas.id/|title=ePaper Kompas|first=PT Kompas Media Nusantara|last=kompas@kompas.com|website=ePaper kompas.id}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{failed verification|date=February 2019}}

Over the years thousands of Rohingya also have fled to Thailand. There are roughly 111,000 refugees housed in nine camps along the Thai-Myanmar border. There have been charges that groups of them have been shipped and towed out to open sea from Thailand, and left there. In February 2009, there was evidence of the Thai army towing a boatload of 190 Rohingya refugees out to sea. A group of refugees rescued by Indonesian authorities also in February 2009 told harrowing stories of being captured and beaten by the Thai military, and then abandoned at open sea. By the end of February, there were reports that of a group of five boats were towed out to open sea, of which four boats sank in a storm, and one washed up on the shore. On 12 February 2009, Thailand's prime minister [[Abhisit Vejjajiva]] said there were "some instances" in which Rohingya people were pushed out to sea.
&lt;blockquote&gt;"There are attempts, I think, to let these people drift to other shores. [...] when these practices do occur, it is done on the understanding that there is enough food and water supplied. [...] It's not clear whose work it is [...] but if I have the evidence who exactly did this I will bring them to account."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://edition.cnn.com/2009/WORLD/asiapcf/02/12/thailand.refugees.admission/index.html |title = Thai PM admits boat people pushed out to sea - CNN.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==Nepal==
On the banks of the [[Bagmati River]] in [[Kathmandu]], Nepal is a [[Pashupatinath Temple]] dedicated to [[Pashupati]]nath. This temple complex which is on the [[UNESCO World Heritage Sites]]'s list since 1979 was erected anew in the 15th century by King kirat Yalamber.

Entry into the inner courtyard is strictly monitored by the temple security, which is selective of who is allowed inside. Only practicing Hindus and Buddhists of Indian and Tibetan descendant are allowed into temple courtyard. Practicing [[Hindus]] and [[Buddhists]] of other than Nepali, Indian, Tibetan descent are not allowed into the temple complex along with other non Hindu visitors. Others can look at the main temple from adjacent side of the river.

== Northern Ireland ==
{{See also|Segregation in Northern Ireland}}
[[File:Belfast peace line Cupar Way.jpg|thumb|A "[[peace lines|peace line]]" in [[Belfast]], Northern Ireland, 2010]]
In [[Northern Ireland]] religious segregation has been a phenomenon which increased in many areas, particularly in the capital city of [[Belfast]] and [[Derry]]. This trend increased since the [[Troubles]], a protracted series of conflicts and tensions between [[Roman Catholics]] and [[Protestants]] from the late 1960s to the late 2000s. Segregation does not occur everywhere. State schools are non-denominational, but many Roman Catholics send their children to Roman Catholic Maintained Schools.

In government housing, most people will choose to be housed within their own communities. This form of segregation is most common among lower income people who live in larger towns and cities, and areas where there have been heightened levels of violence.

In 2012 ''[[Foreign Policy (magazine)|Foreign Policy]]'' reported: {{blockquote|The number of "[[peace wall|peacewall]]s{{sic|,"|hide=yes}} physical barriers separating Catholic and Protestant communities, has increased sharply since the first ceasefires in 1994. Most people in the region cannot envisage the barriers being removed, according to a recent survey conducted by the University of Ulster. In housing and education, Northern Ireland remains one of the most segregated tracts of land anywhere on the planet—less than one in 10 children attends a school that is integrated between Catholics and Protestant. This figure has remained stubbornly low despite the cessation of violence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://foreignpolicy.com/articles/2012/12/20/return_of_the_troubles|title=Return of the Troubles|access-date=29 November 2016|via=Foreign Policy}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

==Pakistan==
Today, Pakistan is officially an Islamic country and defines who is and who is not a Muslim. Under these conditions, [[Ahmadi Muslims]] are declared non-Muslim by law of the land and cannot claim to be Muslim. They are not permitted to call their mosques as mosques, or meet with people with the Islamic [[As-salamu alaykum|greeting of Peace]]. Ahmadi Muslims are excluded from government and any other high-profile positions within Pakistan unless they sign a covenant stating themselves to be non-Muslim. There have been cases when the Ahmadi Muslims have been expelled from schools, colleges and universities, for being Ahmadi Muslim.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://tribune.com.pk/story/269390/ahmadis-expelled-from-school | title=Ahmadis expelled from school | publisher=Express Tribune | access-date=April 6, 2014 | date=October 8, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.humanrights.asia/news/forwarded-news/AHRC-FPR-047-2013 | title=Persecution of Ahmadis in September 2013
 | publisher=Human Rights Asia | access-date= April 6, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Once the entire population of [[Rabwah]], the Pakistani headquarters of Ahmadi Muslims was charged under Anti-Ahmadiyya laws.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.thepersecution.org/press/08/rbw080719.html | title=ENTIRE POPULATION OF RABWAH CHARGED UNDER ANTI-AHMADIYYA LAWS IN PAKISTAN | publisher=thepersecution.org | access-date=April 6, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Pakistan also houses some holy sites for Sikhism. Due to security concerns, Muslims are not allowed in the Samadhi of Ranjit Singh at Lahore fort.

==Saudi Arabia==
[[Image:Christian Bypass.jpg|thumb|right|upright=1.25|Road sign on a highway into Mecca, stating that one direction is "Muslims only" while another direction is "obligatory for non-Muslims". [[Committee for the Promotion of Virtue and the Prevention of Vice (Saudi Arabia)|Religious police]] are stationed beyond the turnoff on the main road to prevent non-Muslims from entering Mecca. Non-Muslims may enter Medina, but  must keep distance from the Al-Masjid al-Nabawi.&lt;ref name=mackeymecca /&gt;]]
{{main|Freedom of religion in Saudi Arabia}}

Prior to 1 March 2004, the official Saudi government website stated that [[Jews]] were forbidden from entering the country; however, this practice was not enforced.&lt;ref&gt;"The official tourism website stated that Jews were banned from entering the country; however, it was not enforced in practice." [[United States Department of State]]. [https://2001-2009.state.gov/g/drl/rls/hrrpt/2004/41731.htm Saudi Arabia] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20211107004858/https://2001-2009.state.gov/g/drl/rls/hrrpt/2004/41731.htm |date=2021-11-07 }}, Country Reports on Human Rights Practices - 2004, February 28, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=cnn2004-02-28&gt;{{cite news
|url=http://www.cnn.com/2004/WORLD/meast/02/28/visa.flap/index.html
|title=Jews barred, said Saudi Web site
|date=February 28, 2004
|publisher=CNN
|access-date=2008-06-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 |url=http://www.sauditourism.gov.sa/sct/indexlist.php?catid=39&amp;maincat=Travel_Tips 
 |title=www.sauditourism.gov.sa 
 |access-date=2008-07-21 
 |url-status=dead 
 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20040206173019/http://www.sauditourism.gov.sa/sct/indexlist.php?catid=39&amp;maincat=Travel_Tips 
 |archive-date=2004-02-06 
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Mecca]], only Muslims are allowed, while non-Muslims may not enter or pass through. Attempting to enter Mecca as a non-Muslim can result in penalties such as a fine;&lt;ref name=mackeymecca&gt;[[Sandra Mackey]]'s account of her attempt to enter Mecca in {{cite book|last=Mackey|first=Sandra|title=The Saudis: Inside the Desert Kingdom|year=1987|pages=63–64|publisher=W. W. Norton &amp; Company|isbn=978-0-393-32417-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; being in Mecca as a non-Muslim can result in deportation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=An A To Z Of Places And Things Saudi|last=Cuddihy|first=Kathy|pages=148|year=2001|publisher=Stacey International|isbn=978-1-900988-40-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Medina]], non-Muslims are not allowed to enter Nabawi Square, where the [[Nabawi Mosque|Al-Masjid Al-Nabawi]] is located.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sikhanswers.com/gurmat-islam/why-guru-nanak-visit-mecca-if-not-muslim/|title=How could Guru Nanak visit Mecca if he wasn't a Muslim? - Sikh Answers|access-date=29 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{unreliable source?|date=December 2017}}&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://2009-2017.state.gov/documents/organization/171744.pdf|title=United States Department of State}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Religion}}

{{div col|colwidth=20em}}
*[[Apartheid]]
*[[Badge of shame]]
*[[Caste]]
*[[Devshirme]]
*[[Dhimmi]] laws
*[[Ghetto]]
*[[Jim Crow laws]]
*[[Jewish hat]]
*[[Mellah]]
*[[Millet (Ottoman Empire)|Millet]]
*[[Minority religion]]
*[[Nuremberg laws]]
*[[Pillarization]]
*[[Racial segregation]]
*[[Racial segregation of churches in the United States|Racial segregation in U.S. churches]]
*[[Religious stratification]]
*[[Second-class citizen]]
*[[Yellow badge]]
{{div col end}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{Segregation by type}}
{{Religious persecution|right}}
{{Discrimination}}
{{Relpolnav}}
{{Religion topics}}



[[Category:Religion and politics]]
[[Category:Religious discrimination]]
[[Category:Segregation]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>