<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061026135652|83842286" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="732260" pageid="732260" ns="0" title="Religious segregation"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-11-05T17:51:25Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Religious segregation''' involves the separation of people on the basis of [[religion]].  

==Muslim world==
Religious segregation occurs in  the Muslim world, where some nations deny non-[[Islam|Muslims]], including [[Jew]]s and [[Christian]]s along with Roman Catholics, some of the civil rights and voting privileges they grant to Muslims. Many Muslim countries consign non-Muslim [[monotheism|monotheists]] to the status of [[dhimmi]]s, both officially and by custom. Saudi Arabia in particular is notorious for very stringent religious laws banning the practice of non-Muslim religions, even prescribing imprisonment and the [[death penalty]] for attempting to convert Muslims to other religions. 

The following links are to articles about discrimination against non-Muslims in 
*[[Status of religious freedom in Afghanistan|Afghanistan]], 
*[[Status of religious freedom in Iran|Iran]], 
*[[Status of religious freedom in Malaysia|Malaysia]], 
*[[Status of religious freedom in Mauritania|Mauritania]], 
*[[Status of religious freedom in Pakistan|Pakistan]], 
*[[Status of religious freedom in Saudi Arabia|Saudi Arabia]],
*[[Status of religious freedom in Sudan|Sudan]].

==[[Northern Ireland]]==

Many [[Ireland|Irish]] [[nationalist]]s and [[Republicanism|republicans]] have described Northern Ireland as being a [[gerrymander]]ed or even [[apartheid]] state, on the grounds that it was created to ensure a built-in [[Protestant]] majority, resulting in discrimination against [[Catholic]]s in government, [[education]], housing and employment. One legacy of this has been that most state schools in Northern Ireland are either Protestant or Catholic, although there now also a number of integrated schools. This has often exacerbated religious, political and cultural differences between the two communities. 

Between [[1922]] and [[1972]], Northern Ireland was governed by the [[Parliament of Northern Ireland]], which was Protestant-dominated, while at local government level, electoral boundaries were devised to create Protestant majorities. The outbreak of the [[The Troubles|Troubles]] led to the imposition of direct rule by the [[United Kingdom|British government]], which has since sought to introduce power sharing between [[Unionism (Ireland)|unionists]] and nationalists.


==See also==
*[[Blood money (term)|Blood money]] laws
*[[Devshirme|Devşirme system]]
*[[Dhimmi]] laws
*[[Ghetto]]
*[[Jim Crow laws]]
*[[Jizyah]] tax
*[[Judenhut]]
*[[Mellah]]
*[[Millet (Ottoman Empire)|Ottoman Millet system]]
*[[Minority religion]]
*[[Nuremberg laws]]
*[[Racial segregation]]
*[[Second-class citizen]]
*[[Yellow badge]]

==External links to articles about discrimination in the Muslim world==
* [http://www.google.com/search?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;oe=UTF-8&amp;q=%2B%22Islamic+apartheid%22+OR+%22arab+apartheid%22+OR+%22Muslim+apartheid%22 Links to articles on apartheid in the Arab Muslim world]
* [http://www.dhimmi.com Dhimmi.Com: Victims of Muslim Religious Apartheid]
* [http://www.saudiinstitute.org/najran.htm religious apartheid in the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia]
* [http://www.shianews.com/hi/americas/news_id/0000232.php Allegations of apartheid]
* [http://www.house.gov/lantos/caucus/TestimonyAhmed060402.htm Directory of the Saudi Institute gives testimony to US House of Representatives on religious apartheid in Saudi Arabia]

[[Category:Religion and politics]]
[[Category:Religion and society]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>