<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20031103133051|1671851" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="232627" pageid="232627" ns="0" title="Gender-blind"><revisions><rev timestamp="2003-11-04T12:53:04Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Gender-blind''' or '''unisex''' is the option of either a third choice or no use of [[sex]] or [[gender_role|gender]] data in typically binary gender-based services or facilities.  

An example of this would be a college offering a gender-blind dormitory in addition to their pre-existing all-male and all-female dorms.  In the gender-blind dorm, roommates could be assigned without regard to any person’s gender.  This allows [[transgender]] persons and persons who do not accept gender labels to live in more comfortable settings than may otherwise be impossible in single-sex housing. It is also good for heterosexuals who otherwise couldn't live with their partners while at the university. 

The first gender-blind dorm in the [[United States]] opened in the fall of [[2003]] on the campus of [[Wesleyan University]] in [[Middletown, Connecticut]]. 

== Choice of words ==

''Unisex'' is an older term and some feel it carries the connotation of actually being ''duo''-sex, whereas ''genderblind'' goes against most tenets of [[heteronormativity]], by not looking at gender at all. 

==See also== 
*[[Race-blind]]
*[[Non-sexist language]]
*[[Equal opportunity]]
*[[Third gender]]
*[[Genderqueer]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>