<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20101031085509|393943097" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="232627" pageid="232627" ns="0" title="Gender-blind"><revisions><rev timestamp="2010-11-12T20:45:28Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{refimprove|date=March 2010}}

'''Gender-blind''' (or '''unisex''') is a term describing activities undertaken and services provided without regard to the [[gender]] of those who participate.

== Choice of words ==
''Unisex'' is an older term, and a [[misnomer]] meaning "one sex".
A more appropriate term would be bisex (which would mean two sexes). It should not be confused with [[bisexuality]].
''Gender-blind'' however goes against most tenets of [[heteronormativity]] by not looking at gender at all.{{Citation needed|date=October 2010}}

== The National Student Genderblind Campaign ==

In 2006 the [http://www.genderblind.org National Student Genderblind Campaign] was created as a collaborative grass-roots organization intended to educate [[college]] students, administrators, and others throughout the [[United States]]. The NSGC advocates for the implementation of gender-inclusive [[dormitory|dorm]] room and [[washroom|bathroom]] options.

==Mixed-gender hospital rooms==

The use of mixed-gender hospital rooms has proved controversial in both [[Great Britain]] and [[Canada]].&lt;ref&gt;John Miner, Shared room sparks rage,London Free Press, June 17, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;  Manitoba's Health Minister, [[Theresa Oswald]], has campaigned actively against such rooms after receiving complaints from a Winnipeg patient, Ollie Ingram.&lt;ref&gt;Bruce Owen, Oswald vows action to stop coed rooms in hospitals, Winnipeg Free Press, May 14, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;  Oswald said if humanity can "put somebody on the moon," it can find a way to honor gender requests without leading to delays for patients.&lt;ref&gt;Bruce Owen, Oswald vows action to stop coed rooms in hospitals, Winnipeg Free Press, May 14, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;  At the same time, some medical ethicists have been critical of efforts to return to single-sex rooms.&lt;ref&gt;Bruce Owen, Oswald vows action to stop coed rooms in hospitals, Winnipeg Free Press, May 14, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;   [[Jacob Appel]], an advocate for mixed rooms in the [[United States]], has written that opposition to gender-mixed rooms stems from "old-fashioned prejudice" and argues that: "Because some people have been brought up to fear or dislike sharing a room with a person of the opposite sex, or blush at the prospect of catching a glimpse of an unwelcome body part when a robe slips open, we enshrine and perpetuate this prejudice in social policy.&lt;ref&gt;Jacob Appel, Are We Ready for Coed Hospital Rooms? ''Huffington Post'', June 18, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;  Great Britain has agreed to phase out such rooms by 2010.&lt;ref&gt;John Miner, Shared room sparks rage,London Free Press, June 17, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Color blindness (race)]]
*[[Non-sexist language]]
*[[Equal opportunity]]
*[[Third gender]]
*[[Genderqueer]]
*[[Unisex]]
*[[All-women shortlists]]

==References==
&lt;references /&gt;

{{DEFAULTSORT:Gender-Blind}}
[[Category:Gender]]
[[Category:Gender studies]]
[[Category:Political correctness]]

[[ko:젠더 블라인드]]
[[ja:ジェンダーフリー]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>