<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20080118035214|185137541" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="232627" pageid="232627" ns="0" title="Gender-blind"><revisions><rev timestamp="2008-09-20T19:19:31Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Gender-blind''' (or '''unisex''') is a term describing activities undertaken and services provided without regard to the [[gender]] of those who participate.

== Choice of words ==
{{weasel}}
''Unisex'' is an older term, and a [[misnomer]] meaning "one sex". Some feel it carries the connotation of being ''duo''-sex, (which would mean ''two at the same time'') and many being afraid to use the more appropriate term, ''bisex'', because of the sexual connotations. Whereas, ''gender-blind'' goes against most tenets of [[heteronormativity]], by not looking at gender at all.

== The National Student Genderblind Campaign ==

In 2006 the [http://www.genderblind.org National Student Genderblind Campaign] was created as a collaborative grass-roots organization intended to educate [[college]] students, administrators, and others throughout the country. The NSGC advocates for the implementation of gender-inclusive [[dormitory|dorm]] room and [[washroom|bathroom]] options.

The goal of the gender-blind dorm policy campaign is to allow roommates to be assigned without regard to any person’s sex. The backers of the proposal claim it would allow [[transgender]] people and people who do not accept gender labels to live in more comfortable settings than may otherwise be possible in single-sex housing.{{Fact|date=September 2007}} They also claim it is a good policy for [[heterosexual]]s who otherwise couldn't live with their partners while at the university.{{Fact|date=September 2007}}

In December 2006, the National Student Genderblind Campaign found itself in national controversy after receiving what it claimed to be biased and negligent coverage by Boston's Fox 25 News.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.onlinegreensboro.com/~matthillnc/archives/1683 " National ‘gender-blind’ college housing student advocacy organization concerned with biased coverage," MattHillNC.com | The Q-triad Blog, December 13, 2006]&lt;/ref&gt; The controversy triggered a formal press statement released nationally&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.genderblind.org/press121506slander.pdf NSGC Statement (PDF), December 15, 2006]&lt;/ref&gt; and an appearance on Fox News Channel's "Heartland" show with John Kasich on December 16, 2006.

==See also==
*[[Color blindness (race)]]
*[[Non-sexist language]]
*[[Equal opportunity]]
*[[Third gender]]
*[[Genderqueer]]
*[[Unisex]]

==References==
&lt;references /&gt;

[[Category:Gender]]
[[Category:Gender_studies]]

[[ko:젠더 블라인드]]
[[ja:ジェンダーフリー]]
[[fi:Unisex]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>