<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20121116154702|523339864" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="2298034" pageid="2298034" ns="0" title="Rape culture"><revisions><rev timestamp="2012-11-16T16:07:30Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2012}}
{{about|the concept of rape culture|the similarly named 1975 film|Rape Culture (film)}}

{{Feminism sidebar |expanded=Waves}}

'''Rape culture''' is a concept used to describe a [[culture]] in which [[rape]] and [[sexual violence]] are common and in which prevalent [[attitude (psychology)|attitudes]], [[norm (sociology)|norms]], practices, and [[mass media|media]] [[normalization (sociology)|normalize]], excuse, tolerate, or even condone rape. 

Examples of behaviors commonly associated with rape culture include [[victim blaming]], [[sexual objectification]], and trivializing rape.  Rape culture has been used to model behaviour within social groups, including prison systems where [[prison rape]] is common and conflict areas where [[war rape]] is used as psychological warfare. Entire countries have also been alleged to be rape cultures.&lt;ref name=leaderu /&gt;&lt;ref name=rozee&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.raperesistance.org/research/rape_culture.html |title=Resisting a Rape Culture |author=Rozee, Patricia |publisher=Rape Resistance |accessdate=11 January 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Steffes&gt;{{cite web |url=http://hpr1.com/feature/article/the_rape_culture/ |title=The American Rape Culture |author=Steffes, Micah |date=January 2008 |publisher=High Plains Reader |accessdate=11 January 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Maitse1998"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Maitse|first1=Teboho|title=Political change, rape, and pornography in postapartheid South Africa|journal=Gender &amp; Development|volume=6|issue=3|year=1998|pages=55–59|issn=1355-2074|doi=10.1080/741922834}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Prof Upendra Baxi India = Rape Culture"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Baxi|first=Upendra|title=THE SECOND GUJARAT CATASTROPHE|journal=Economic and Political Weekly|year=2002|month=August|volume=37|issue=34|pages=3519–3531|url=http://www.jstor.org/stable/4412519|accessdate=22 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Although the concept of rape culture is a generally accepted theory in feminist academia, there is disagreement over what defines a rape culture and to what degree a given society meets the criteria to be considered a rape culture.

Rape culture has been observed to correlate with other social factors and behaviours. Research identifies correlation between rape myths, victim blaming and trivialisation of rape with increased incidence of racism, homophobia, ageism, classism, religious intolerance and other forms of discrimination.&lt;ref name=AOSVOD001&gt;{{cite journal|last=Aosved|first=Allison C.|coauthors=Long, Patricia J.|title=Co-occurrence of Rape Myth Acceptance, Sexism, Racism, Homophobia, Ageism, Classism, and Religious Intolerance|journal=Sex Roles|date=28 November 2006|volume=55|issue=7-8|pages=481–492|doi=10.1007/s11199-006-9101-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Suarez|first=E.|coauthors=Gadalla, T. M.|title=Stop Blaming the Victim: A Meta-Analysis on Rape Myths|journal=Journal of Interpersonal Violence|date=11 January 2010|volume=25|issue=11|pages=2010–2035|doi=10.1177/0886260509354503}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Origins and usage==
During the early 1970s, feminists began to engage in [[consciousness-raising]] efforts to educate the public about the reality of rape. Until then, rape was rarely discussed or acknowledged: "Until the 1970s, most Americans assumed that rape, incest, and wife-beating rarely happened."&lt;ref&gt;Review of ''Against Our Will: Men, Women, and Rape'' quoted in {{cite journal |title=Sexual Violence Against Women: Putting Rape Research in Context |author=Rutherford, Alexandra |journal=Psychology of Women Quarterly |doi=10.1177/0361684311404307 |date=June 2011 |volume=35 |issue=2 |pages=342-347 |accessdate=15 June 2012 |url=http://pwq.sagepub.com/content/35/2/342.extract}}&lt;/ref&gt; The idea of rape culture was one result of these efforts. According to the 2004 ''Encyclopedia of Rape'', "The term 'rape culture' originated in the 1970s during the 2nd wave feminist movement and is often used by feminists to describe contemporary American culture as a whole."&lt;ref name=Smith2004&gt;{{cite book|last=Smith|first=Merril D.|title=Encyclopedia of Rape|year=2004|publisher=Greenwood Press|location=Westport, Conn.|isbn=0-313-32687-8|edition=1st|page=174}}&lt;/ref&gt; The concept appeared in multiple forms of media during the mid 1970s:

The term was used 1974 in ''Rape: The First Sourcebook for Women'', edited by [[Noreen Connell]] and Cassandra Wilson&lt;!-- careful before wikilinking - currently leads to a singer --&gt; for the [[New York Radical Feminists]].&lt;ref name="FeministsConnell1974"&gt;{{cite book|author1=New York Radical Feminists|author2=Noreen Connell|author3=Cassandra Wilson|title=Rape: the first sourcebook for women|url=http://books.google.co.uk/books?ei=04yuT9qECsfB0QWW_ZikCQ&amp;id=ej1BAAAAIAAJ&amp;q=%22Rape+Culture%22|accessdate=14 May 2012|date=31 October 1974|publisher=New American Library|isbn=9780452250864|page=105|chapter=3}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was one of the first books to include first-person accounts of rape, which were one reason for rape entering the public view.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.nytimes.com/books/98/10/11/letters/letters.html |title=Letters to the Editor: Speaking Out |newspaper=New York Times |date=11 October 1998 |author=[[Helen Benedict]] |accessdate=15 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the book, the group stated that "our ultimate goal is to eliminate rape and that goal cannot be achieved without a revolutionary transformation of our society."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.faar-aegis.org/NovDec_74/review_NovDec74.html |title=Book Review: Rape: The First Sourcebook for Women (New York Radical Feminists) |author=Freada Klein |work=Feminist Alliance Against Rape Newsletter |date=November/December 1974 |publisher=Feminist Alliance Against Rape Newsletter |accessdate=15 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The 1975 documentary film ''[[Rape Culture (film)|Rape Culture]]'', produced and directed by [[Margaret Lazarus]] and [[Renner Wunderlich]] for [[Cambridge Documentary Films]], discussed prison rape in the context of a larger cultural normalization of rape.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.cambridgedocumentaryfilms.org/rapeculture.html |title=Rape Culture |publisher=Cambridge Documentary Films  |accessdate=8 January 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Norsigian 29–30"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Norsigian|first=Judy|title=Women, Health, and Films|journal=Women &amp; Health|date=20 January 1975|volume=1|issue=1|pages=29–30|doi=10.1300/J013v01n01_07|url=http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1300/J013v01n01_08#preview|accessdate=11 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2000, Lazarus stated that she believed the movie was the first use of the term.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Rape Culture |url=http://userpages.umbc.edu/~korenman/wmst/rapeculture2.html |date=15 March 2000&lt;!-- 10:15:39 --&gt;|accessdate=8 January 2012 |author=Lazarus, Margaret}}&lt;/ref&gt; The film featured the work of the DC Rape Crisis Centre in co-operation with Prisoners Against Rape Inc.&lt;ref name="smith"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Follet|first=Joyce|title=LORETTA ROSS|journal=Voices of Feminism Oral History Project, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College, Northampton, MA 01063|year=2004–2005|pages=122–124|url=http://www.smith.edu/libraries/libs/ssc/vof/vof-intro.html|accessdate=7 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; It included interviews with rapists and victims as well prominent anti-rape activists like feminist philosopher and theologian [[Mary Daly]] and author and artist Emily Culpepper. The film also explored the mass media, how film-makers, song writers, writers and magazines perpetuated attitudes towards rape.&lt;ref name="Norsigian 29–30"/&gt;

In a 1992 paper in the ''Journal of Social Issues'' entitled "A Feminist Redefinition of Rape and Sexual Assault: Historical Foundations and Change," Patricia Donat and John D'Emilio suggested that the term originated as "rape-supportive culture"&lt;ref&gt;Patricia Donat and John D'Emilio, "A Feminist Redefinition of Rape and Sexual Assault: Historical Foundations and Change", ''Journal of Social Issues'', vol. 48, n. 1, 1992; published in Di Karen J. Maschke, "The legal response to violence against women",  Routledge 1997, ISBN 978-0-8153-2519-2.&lt;/ref&gt; in [[Susan Brownmiller]]'s 1975 book ''[[Against Our Will: Men, Women, and Rape]]''. Brownmiller, a member of the New York Radical Feminists, showed how both academia and the general public ignored the existence of rape.&lt;ref name=rutherford&gt;{{cite journal |title=Sexual Violence Against Women: Putting Rape Research in Context |author=Rutherford, Alexandra |journal=Psychology of Women Quarterly |doi=10.1177/0361684311404307 |date=June 2011 |volume=35 |issue=2 |pages=342-347 |accessdate=15 June 2012 |url=http://pwq.sagepub.com/content/35/2/342.extract}}&lt;/ref&gt; The book is considered a "landmark" work on feminism and sexual violence and one of the pillars of modern rape studies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Transforming a Rape Culture | editor1-last  =Buchwald | editor1-first =Emilie | editor2-last  =Fletcher | editor2-first =Pamela | editor3-last  =Roth | editor3-first =Martha |publisher=Milkweed Editions |year=1993 |chapter=Editor's Preface |last1=Buchwald |first1=Emilie |last2=Fletcher |first2=Pamela |last3=Roth |first3=Martha |isbn=0915943069 |page=1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Slutwalk===
Although it had been in academic usage since its inception, the term "rape culture" was scarcely used in popular culture and the media until 2011.{{fact|date=November 2012}} The [[Slutwalk]] and [[Besharmi Morcha]] movements are credited with popularizing the term via certain mass media reports about the protesters in the English speaking, Western media.&lt;ref name=time1&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.time.com/time/nation/article/0,8599,2088234-1,00.html |title=Will SlutWalks Change the Meaning of the Word Slut? |author=Gibson, Megan |publisher=TIME Magazine |date=12 August 2011 |accessdate=18 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{not in source|date=November 2012}} The rallies aim to raise awareness of rape culture - which they define as a culture where "sexual violence is both made to be invisible and inevitable"—and to end [[slut-shaming]] and victim blaming.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://slutwalknyc.com/FAQ |title=FAQ |publisher=Slutwalk NYC |accessdate=18 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=TL&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.timeslive.co.za/local/2011/09/23/slutwalk-joburg-takes-to-the-streets |title=Slutwalk Joburg takes to the streets |newspaper=Times LIVE |date=23 September 2011 |accessdate=18 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Feminist theory==
According to the rape culture theory, acts of [[sexism]] are commonly employed to validate and [[Rationalization (psychology)|rationalize]] normative [[misogyny|misogynistic]] practices. For instance, sexist jokes may be told to foster disrespect for women and an accompanying disregard for their well-being. An example would be a female rape victim being blamed for her being raped because of how she dressed or acted.  In rape culture, sexualized violence towards women is regarded as a continuum in a society that regards women's bodies as sexually available by default.&lt;ref&gt;Chris O'Sullivan, "Fraternities and the Rape Culture", in ''Transforming a Rape Culture'', edited by Emilie Buchwald, Pamela R. Fletcher &amp; Martha Roth, ISBN 0-915943-06-9&lt;/ref&gt; 

The root cause of rape culture is generally agreed to be the "domination and objectification of women".&lt;ref name=SA &gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.ncjrs.gov/App/Publications/abstract.aspx?ID=127046 |title=Sexual Face of Violence: Rapists on Rape (abstract) |author=Vogelman, L. |publisher=Raven Press Ltd (book); National Criminal Justice Reference Service (abstract) |accessdate=18 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, academic theory holds that rape culture does not necessarily have a single cause, and causes may be localized based on other social aspects of culture.&lt;ref name=herman &gt;Herman, Dianne F. "[http://homepage.smc.edu/delpiccolo_guido/Soc1/soc1readings/rape%20culture_final.pdf The Rape Culture]." Printed in ''Women: A Feminist Perspective'' (ed. Jo Freeman). Mcgraw Hill, 1994. Retrieved 18 October 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; For example, in South Africa the overriding "war culture" which emphasized masculinity and violence led to a culture in which [[war rape|rape was normalized]].&lt;ref name=TL /&gt;&lt;ref name=SA /&gt; A University of California Davis public document alleged that the enforcement of the following of social rules by women and the conditioning of gender roles were major causes.&lt;ref name=UCDavis&gt;{{cite web |url=http://students.haverford.edu/masar/documents/RapeCulture.pdf |title=Defining a Rape Culture |publisher=University of California Davis |accessdate=18 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In a study of [[date rape]], gender-based miscommunications were held to be a major factor supporting a [[campus rape]] culture.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |url=http://psycnet.apa.org/psycinfo/1993-21940-001 |title=Date and acquaintance rape among a sample of college students (abstract) |author=Mills, Crystal S. and Granoff, Barbara J. |journal=Social Work |volume=37 |issue=6 |date=November 1992 |pages=504–509 |accessdate=18 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The general unwillingness of police and district attorneys to prosecute rapes where force was not involved or where the victim had some sort of relationship with the aggressor is also cited as a motivation for date rape and campus rape.&lt;ref name=herman /&gt; Rape culture is also closely related to slut-shaming and [[victim blaming]], where rape victims are considered at fault for being raped, and it is argued that this connection is due to the presence of a culture that shames all female sexuality.&lt;ref name=herman /&gt; That some rapes are not reported to the police due to fear that they would not be believed is often cited as a symptom of a rape culture,&lt;ref name=herman /&gt;&lt;ref name=real&gt;{{cite news |title=Rape culture is real |url=http://cupwire.ca/articles/47672 |author=Ketterling, Jean |newspaper=The Xaverian Weekly |publisher=Canadian University Press |date=23 September 2011 |accessdate=18 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; that they thought the police would not believe them is cited as a reason by 6% of women who did not report rape.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Backman |first1=Ronet  |last2= |first2= |year=1988 |title=The factors related to rape reporting behavior and arrest: new evidence from the National Crime Victimization Survey |journal=Criminal Justice and Behavior |volume=25 |issue=1 |pages=8 |publisher= |doi= |url= |accessdate= }}&lt;/ref&gt; Pornography has also been commonly targeted as a contributor to rape culture because it is said to contribute to larger patterns of oppression. One of the ways that it is said to do this is by reducing the female body to a commodity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Willis|first=Ellen|title=Feminism, Moralism, and Pornography|url=http://heinonline.org/HOL/LandingPage?collection=journals&amp;handle=hein.journals/nyls38&amp;div=26&amp;id=&amp;page=|publisher=Wesleyan University Press|accessdate=8 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Although much of its early use as a theory to explain the occurrence of rape and [[domestic violence]] was focused on the rape of women, rape culture has been described as detrimental to men as well as women. Some writers and speakers, such as [[Jackson Katz]], [[Michael Kimmel]], and [[Don McPherson]], have said that it is intrinsically linked to [[gender role]]s that limit male self-expression and cause psychological harm to men.&lt;ref&gt;Jackson Katz, "Tough Guise" videorecording, Media Education Foundation, 2002&lt;/ref&gt;

==Rape culture and incidents by nation==
===South Africa===
As far back as the 1970s, activist [[Steve Biko]] wrote about the issues of rape, politics, and [[apartheid]] in South Africa. Rape was common in the black townships.&lt;ref name="Biko1987"&gt;{{cite book|author=Steve Biko|title=I Write What I Like|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=Aq5PJWaSTzUC|accessdate=25 May 2012|year=1987|publisher=Heinemann|isbn=978-0-435-90598-9}}&lt;/ref&gt; Biko also highlighted how the issues of powerlessness and impotence and an induced inferiority complex were known issues or "Black Consciousness".&lt;ref name="JacobsJacobson2000"&gt;{{cite book|author1=Susie M. Jacobs|author2=Ruth Jacobson|author3=Jen Marchbank|title=States of Conflict: Gender, Violence, and Resistance|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=tzLKEX3WlhwC&amp;pg=PA198|accessdate=25 May 2012|date=8 April 2000|publisher=Palgrave Macmillan|isbn=978-1-85649-656-8|pages=198–}}&lt;/ref&gt;  

In 1982, [[Stellenbosch University]] [[sociologist]] [[Cherryl Walker]] highlighted how black women's issues were made invisible by the larger issue of apartheid. Even the management of known rape issues through rape crisis centres were still for the future due to lack of funding and government support.&lt;ref name="Walker1982"&gt;{{cite book | last = Walker | first = Cherryl | title = Women and resistance in South Africa | publisher = Onyx Press | location = London | year = 1982 | isbn = 9780906383148 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Under apartheid, there were multiple levels of oppression against both men and women. Some were legally based, while others were caused by the suppression of cultural values and practices. There were concerns as to how these would manifest with the end of Apartheid and the arrival of the new South Africa constitution as of 1993.&lt;ref name=Campbell1992&gt;{{Cite journal |title = Learning to kill? Masculinity, the family and violence in Natal|year = 1992|author = Campbell, Catherine|journal = Journal of Southern African Studies|volume = 18|issue = 3|doi = 10.1080/03057079208708328 |pages = 614}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1996, Taboho Maitse (Presently a commissioner of the South African Commission for gender Equality [http://www.cge.org.za/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=65&amp;Itemid=76] appointed 30 November 2011 [http://www.info.gov.za/speech/DynamicAction?pageid=461&amp;sid=23697&amp;tid=50768]) researched the post-Apartheid cultural change.&lt;ref name="JacobsJacobson2000" /&gt; Women identified how under Apartheid they had no protection from male violence, white or coloured. Apartheid suppressed the non-white majority, and oppressed women the most. Maitse concluded that there was a confusion of how the roles of women had changed under the new constitution. Meiste observed the ongoing clashes of traditional culture with the new constitutional order. Both men and women wished to preserve traditional cultural and tribal identity but this also promoted gender conflict. The new South African Constitution fundamentally changed the rights of women, but they lacked knowledge and support in exercising those rights. [[Lobolo]] - a traditional dowry system both emphasised women as possessions and also made them unable to speak out about treatment. Maitse found that Apartheid, nationalism and the liberation struggle had played a clear part in how women were perceived and also perceived themselves. In 1998&lt;ref name="Maitse1998" /&gt; Maitse concluded:

&lt;blockquote&gt;In answer to the question why men are violent toward women in South Africa, two primary inter-connected theories emerge. The first is that of sexist ideology and the male preoccupation with all the qualities assigned to the male sex role. The second draws a shocking picture of South African society as a “rape culture”, in which violence against women is tacitly accepted.&lt;ref name="Sweetman1999"&gt;{{cite book|author=Caroline Sweetman|title=Violence Against Women|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=8jMKZ41ZquMC&amp;pg=PA56|accessdate=25 May 2012|date=1 January 1999|publisher=Oxfam|isbn=978-0-85598-401-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="RichterDawes2004"&gt;{{cite book|author1=Linda M. Richter|author2=Andrew Dawes|author3=Craig Higson-Smith|title=Sexual Abuse Of Young Children In Southern Africa|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=rhznn_8QJY4C&amp;pg=PA102|accessdate=25 May 2012|year=2004|publisher=HSRC Press|isbn=978-0-7969-2053-9}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Maitse has further linked the use of pornography and the emergence of Information and Communication Technologies to the issues. Under the Apartheid regime pornography was illegal, even if available. Under the new constitution pornography is legal and has been embraced as sign of post Apartheid liberation. This mixed with the free market economy and consumerism where mobile phones and other ITC products have also been adopted as signs of wealth, freedom and nationalism, the dissemination of pornography ion all forms has exploded since 1992/4. Ongoing concerns as to the role of ITC in South Africa were expressed by Shereen Essof in 2009.&lt;ref name=Essof1&gt;{{cite web|last=Essof|first=Shereen|title=South Africa: Violence against Women and ICT|url=http://www.genderit.org/content/south-africa-violence-against-women-and-information-communication-technologies|publisher=genderit.org|accessdate=25 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

In 1997 Interpol reported that South Africa had, on a Global analysis the highest per capita rates of murder and rape, the second highest rate of robbery and violent theft and the fourth highest rates of serious assault and sexual offences of the 110 counties reported on.&lt;ref name="Schönteich2000"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Schönteich|first1=Martin|title=South Africa's position in Africa's crime rankings|journal=African Security Review|volume=9|issue=4|year=2000|pages=51–65|issn=1024-6029|doi=10.1080/10246029.2000.9628065}}&lt;/ref&gt;  

Interpol reported in 2001 that South Africa had the highest reported statistics of rape from any member country.&lt;ref name="Graham2012"&gt;{{cite book|author=Lucy Valerie Graham|title=State of Peril: Race and Rape in South African Literature|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=ckasEYxoDn4C&amp;pg=PA4|accessdate=25 May 2012|date=June 2012|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=978-0-19-979637-3}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was recognised even then that the statistical findings were believed to be low due to lack of infrastructure, and the complexities of how sexual coercion were perceived.&lt;ref name="JewkesAbrahams2002"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Jewkes|first1=Rachel|last2=Abrahams|first2=Naeema|title=The epidemiology of rape and sexual coercion in South Africa: an overview|journal=Social Science &amp; Medicine|volume=55|issue=7|year=2002|pages=1231–1244|issn=02779536|doi=10.1016/S0277-9536(01)00242-8}}&lt;/ref&gt; The South African government concluded in 2001 that multiple statistical research efforts dealing with rape all correlated with a high incidence.&lt;ref name=statssa.gov.za1&gt;{{cite web|last=Government Of South Africa|title=Quantitative research findings on rape in South Africa,|url=http://www.statssa.gov.za/publications/statsdownload.asp?PPN=Rape&amp;SCH=2350|publisher=Statistics South Africa - statssa.gov.za|accessdate=25 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

The subject started to gain Global attention and was covered by the international media. The incidence of child rape had increased and was linked to beliefs that sex with a virgin could cure HIV/Aids - the [[Virgin cleansing myth]]. Some reports indicated that up to 50% of rape victims acquired Aids due to the rape.

FEW: The Forum for the Empowerment of Women was founded in 2001/2.&lt;ref name="(JWG)001"&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.webcitation.org/686CrgXxG | title=Forum for the Empowerment of Women (FEW) | publisher=The Joint Working Group (JWG) | author=Forum for the Empowerment of Women (FEW)}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Her Story001"&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.webcitation.org/686DPOQKL | title=Her Story | publisher=few.org.za | author=Forum for the Empowerment of Women (FEW)}}&lt;/ref&gt; Their research through the project "This Rose Has Thorns" helped to quantify the extent and nature of corrective rape came from the work of [[Zanele Muholi]], who worked with women who had been raped and also interviewed rapist who targeted lesbians.&lt;ref name="Zanele Muholi002"&gt;{{cite book | title=Mapping Our Histories: A Visual History of Black Lesbians in Post-Apartheid. South Africa | publisher=Zanele Muholi | author=Zanele Muholi | year=2006 | pages=45 | url=http://www.webcitation.org/686GIqQhh}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Sister Namibia"&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.thefreelibrary.com/Campaign+to+stop+violence+against+lesbian+women+in+South+Africa.-a0128170742 | title=Campaign to stop violence against lesbian women in South Africa. | work=Sister Namibia | date=1 November 2003 | agency=THEFREELIBRARY.COM, Farlex, Inc.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Yolanda Mufweba, writing in The Star Newspaper pointed to how lesbianism by white women was seen as a none African issue. The rape of black South African lesbians was to "turn you into a real African woman", and indicating how the subject was racially linked and polarised.&lt;ref name="JbergstarYolandaMufwebaNov2003"&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.webcitation.org/6862uwX79 | title=Corrective rape makes you an African woman | work=The Star | date=7 November 2003 | agency=Independent Newspapers (Pty) Limited | author=Yolanda Mufweba | location=Johannesburg}}&lt;/ref&gt; Whilst the subject did receive some international attention afterwards,&lt;ref name="CleoOzMay2005"&gt;{{cite news | title=Men who rape gay women to turn them straight | work=Cleo Magazine | date=May 2005 | agency=ninemsn Pty Ltd | author=Annmarie Conte | pages=93–96}}&lt;/ref&gt; it was not until the 2006 corrective rape and murder of Zoliswa Nkonyana&lt;ref name="ZoliswaNkonyanaJan2006"&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.webcitation.org/6867pONm1 | title=Not just another murder | work=Mail &amp; Guardian | date=26 February 2006 | agency=M&amp;G Media | accessdate=1 June 2012 | author=Marianne Thamm | location=Johannesburg}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the 2008 murder of [[Eudy Simelane]], national women's team soccer player and gay rights activist, that international media interest and attention on the issue developed. Further international attention resulted from the Action Aid 2009 report "Hate crimes: The rise of  ‘corrective’ rape in South Africa".&lt;ref name="ActionAidMar2009"&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.webcitation.org/686HH0fGz | title=Hate crimes: The rise of ‘corrective’ rape in South Africa | publisher=ActionAid | date=12 March 2009 | author=Andrew Martin, Annie Kelly, Laura Turquet,Stephanie Ross. | pages=11}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="reutersmar2009"&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.webcitation.org/686GIqQhh | title=South African gangs use rape to "cure" lesbians | date=13. März 2009 | agency=Reuters Deutschland | author=Rebecca Harrison}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="telegraphMar2009"&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.webcitation.org/686IWMmGr | title=Lesbians subjected to "corrective rape" in South Africa | date=13 March 2009 | agency=The Telegraph}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Research carried out by [[The Gallup Organization]] in March–April 2009 showed that 97% of South Africans believed  rape to be "a major problem".&lt;ref name=Gallup1&gt;{{cite web|last=Gallup, Inc|title=Rape Troubles Nearly All in South Africa|url=http://www.webcitation.org/67vqUyVZJ|publisher=The Gallup Organization|accessdate=25 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="C4news12mar2009"&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.webcitation.org/686IlLLvU | title='Corrective rape' in South Africa | date=12 March 2009 | agency=Channel 4 News | author=Samira Ahmed}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In April 2012, there was debate in the South African parliament converging the issues of rape. Further evidence from Interpol listed South Africa as having the highest rape statistics globally. The findings indicated that a South African woman was more likely to be raped than learn to read, and that a rape took place every 17 seconds. Members of the legislature were concerned that when visiting centres that dealt with rape victims they found services overwhelmed. Annelize van Wyk was concerned to find forensic samples from child rape cases left and unprocessed months after the samples were taken. A recent police study estimated that only one in 36 rape cases are reported. Approximately 33% of reported rape cases were prosecuted. In child rape cases only 22% reached court. The South African government appointed a further 800 forensic experts to deal with the levels of crime has been put on hold.&lt;ref name=SABC001&gt;{{cite news|title=South Africa, world's rape capital: Interpol|url=http://www.webcitation.org/67vrhWz4y|accessdate=25 May 2012|newspaper=SABC|date=19 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===United States===
As the United States is a major purveyor of entertainment and culture, as well as the primary site of many feminism and anti-rape movements, many prominent examples of alleged rape culture have occurred there. Various commentators have also labeled the United States itself as a rape culture.&lt;ref name=leaderu /&gt;&lt;ref name="rozee"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Steffes"/&gt;

In February 2011, seventeen United States veterans filed suit against the Pentagon and defense secretary [[Robert Gates]] and former secretary [[Donald Rumsfield]], alleging that they allowed a culture in the military where rape was unevenly reported and punished. In several of the plaintiffs' cases, the victim was forced to work with the accused rapist after reporting them for sexual assault. Unit commanders often have heavy influence over military rape cases, and less than one in five cases are prosecuted.&lt;ref&gt;Parker, Ashley (15 February 2011). [http://www.nytimes.com/2011/02/16/us/16military.html Lawsuit Says Military Is Rife With Sexual Abuse]. [[New York Times]]. Retrieved 16 March 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hefling, Kimberly (16 February 2011). ''U.S. Veterans Say Military is Mishandling Rape Case''. [[The Day (New London)|The Day]].&lt;/ref&gt; According to a 2011 [[Newsweek]] report, 1 in 5 females and 1 in 15 males in the United States military reported having been sexually assaulted by servicemembers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=The Military's Secret Shame |author=Ellison, Jesse |url=http://www.newsweek.com/2011/04/03/the-military-s-secret-shame.html |newspaper=Newsweek |date=3 April 2011 |accessdate=11 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; (See also: [[Sexual assault in the United States military]])

In March 2011, a group of 16 current and former [[Yale University]] students filed a [[Title IX]] complaint against the school with the US Department of Education's Office for Civil Rights, alleging that the administration did not respond decisively to misogyny on campus, such as [[Delta Kappa Epsilon]] fraternity members chanting sexist slogans.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Yale is Subject of Title IX Inquiry |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/04/01/us/01yale.html |newspaper=New York Times |date=31 March 2011 |accessdate=10 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The fraternity was subsequently suspended for five years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Foderaro|first=Lisa|title=Yale Restricts a Fraternity for Five Years|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/05/18/education/18yale.html?_r=1|work=New York Times|date=17 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Academic studies have examined fraternity cultures at other universities and discussed their roles in the creation of rape culture.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title=Fraternities and Collegiate Rape Culture: Why Are Some Fraternities More Dangerous Places for Women? |author=Boswell, A. Ayres and Spade, Joan Z. |journal=Gender and Society |pages=133–147 |volume=10 |issue=2 |date=April 1996 |accessdate=18 October 2011 |jstor=189830}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In March 2011, editorials on [[Salon.com]] and [[The Huffington Post]] criticised a ''New York Times'' article, saying that the article focused on victim-blaming on an eleven-year-old girl rather than the fact that she was raped. The article in question dealt with the November 2010 [[gang rape]] of the child in [[Cleveland, Texas]].&lt;ref&gt;Williams, Mary Elizabeth (9 March 2011). [http://www.salon.com/life/feature/2011/03/09/new_york_times_blames_11_year_old_rape_victim/index.html The New York Times' sloppy, slanted child rape story]. [[Salon.com]]. Retrieved on 16 March 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/marina-delvecchio/post_1849_b_838788.html |title=Rape Culture and How it Betrays Women |author=DelVecchio, Marina |newspaper=The Huffington Post |date=21 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Other incidents===
In 2010, the webcomic [[Penny Arcade (webcomic)|Penny Arcade]] published a strip which featured a male rape victim in the setting of a video game. After complaints about the content of the strip, a follow-up apology strip was published which many bloggers alleged was offensive to and made light of rape victims.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|first=Milli A|title=Shaker|url=http://shakespearessister.blogspot.com/2010/08/rape-is-hilarious-part-53-in-ongoing.html|work="Rape Is Hilarious, Part 53 in an Ongoing Series"|accessdate=9 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; This "dickwolves" controversy generated reactions even in mainstream media, particularly after [[Wil Wheaton]] made a statement opposing the actions of Penny Arcade's creators.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://twitter.com/#!/wilw/statuses/22921833346 |title=Don't be a dickwolf! http://twitpic.com/2kxpej |first1=Wil (@wilw)|last1=Wheaton |authorlink=Wil Wheaton |date=3 September 2010 |publisher=Twitter |accessdate=15 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Myers, Maddy (16 August 2010). [http://thephoenix.com/BLOGS/laserorgy/archive/2010/08/16/penny-arcade-s-dubious-apology-for-dark-humor.aspx Penny Arcade surprised to find that rape jokes offend people]. [[The Boston Phoenix]]. Retrieved 5 March 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Myers, Maddy (2 March 2011). [http://thephoenix.com/Boston/life/116456-gaming-rape-culture-and-how-i-stopped-reading-pe/ Gaming, rape culture, and how I stopped reading Penny Arcade]. [[The Boston Phoenix]]. Retrieved 5 March 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

In August and September 2011, [[Facebook]] faced criticism for refusing to remove pages that allegedly supported rape culture. Those criticizing the site claimed the pages violated Facebook's own content policies, which prohibit hate speech.&lt;ref name=guardianfacebook&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/technology/2011/sep/30/facebook-refuses-pull-rape-jokepages?newsfeed=true |title=Facebook refuses to take down rape joke pages |newspaper=The Guardian |author=Davies, Lizzy |date=30 September 2011 |accessdate=18 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.facebook.com/communitystandards |title=Facebook community standards |publisher=Facebook Inc. |accessdate=23 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; A prominent petition to Facebook stated "Allowing such groups to congregate serves only to further normalise rape culture and the high instance of sexual violence that exists in society."&lt;ref name=guardianfacebook /&gt;&lt;!--Petition cannot be linked due to spam blacklist; it is linked from the article.--&gt;

== Criticisms ==
[[Christina Hoff Sommers]] has disputed the existence of rape culture, arguing that the common "one in four women will be raped in her lifetime" is based on a flawed study, but frequently cited because it leads to campus anti-rape groups receiving public funding. Sommers has also examined and criticized many other rape studies for their flawed methodology, and states "There are many researchers who study rape victimization, but their relatively low figures generate no headlines."&lt;ref name="leaderu"&gt;Sommers, Dr. Christina Hoff. [http://www.leaderu.com/real/ri9502/sommers.html Researching the "Rape Culture" of America]. Retrieved 4 March 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; 

Joyce E. Williams has criticised the monolithic nature of the concept of rape culture, due to the implication that ultimately all women are victimised by all men.&lt;ref name=ConSociEncycJEWilliams&gt;{{cite book|last=Edited by George Ritzer|title=The concise encyclopedia of sociology|publisher=Wiley-Blackwell|location=Oxford|isbn=978-1-4051-8352-9|pages=493|author=Joyce E Williams}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Other writers, such as [[bell hooks]], have criticized the rape culture paradigm on the grounds that it ignores rape's place in an overarching "culture of violence."&lt;ref&gt;[[bell hooks]], ''Feminist Theory: From Margin to Center'', quoted in ''Feminism is for Everybody'' by bell hooks, ISBN 0-89608-628-3&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
*{{cite book |title=Transforming a Rape Culture |editor=Emilie Buchwald, Pamela R. Fletcher and Martha Roth |year=1993 |ISBN=1-57131-204-8}}
*{{cite journal |pmid=7373511 |author=M. R. Burt |title=Cultural myths and supports for rape |year=1980 |journal=Journal of Personality and Social Psychology |volume=38 |pages=217–230}}
*{{cite journal |url=http://www3.interscience.wiley.com/journal/119570811/abstract?CRETRY=1&amp;SRETRY=0 |title=Rape myths, rape definitions, and probability of conviction |author=M. R. Burt and R. S. Albin |year=1981 |journal=Journal of Applied Social Psychology |volume=11 |pages=212–230}}

{{Sexual abuse}}

[[Category:Feminism and sexuality]]
[[Category:Feminist theory]]
[[Category:Cultural studies]]
[[Category:Misogyny]]
[[Category:Rape]]

[[it:Cultura dello stupro]]
[[he:תרבות אונס]]
[[ru:Культура изнасилования]]
[[tr:Tecavüz kültürü]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>