<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20081104214614|249731202" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="2298034" pageid="2298034" ns="0" title="Rape culture"><revisions><rev timestamp="2008-11-15T11:08:21Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Rape}}
'''Rape culture''' is a widely used term within [[women's studies]] and [[feminism]] describing a [[culture]] in which [[rape]] and other [[sexual violence]] (usually against women) are common and in which prevalent [[attitude (psychology)|attitudes]], [[norm (sociology)|norms]], practices, and [[mass media|media]] condone, [[normalization (sociology)|normalize]], excuse, or encourage [[violence against women|sexualized violence]]. Within the [[paradigm]], acts of "harmless" [[sexism]] are commonly employed to validate and rationalize normative [[misogyny|misogynistic]] practices; for instance, sexist jokes may be told to foster disrespect for women and an accompanying disregard for their well-being, which ultimately make their rape and abuse seem acceptable.  Examples of behaviors said to typify rape culture include [[victim blaming]], trivializing [[prison rape]], and [[sexual objectification]].

In a 1992 paper in the ''Journal of Social Issues'' entitled "A Feminist Redefinition of Rape and Sexual Assault: Historical Foundations and Change," Patricia Donat and John D'Emilio suggested that the term originated as "rape-supportive culture" in [[Susan Brownmiller]]'s 1975 book ''Against Our Will: Men, Women, and Rape''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.spssi.org/jsi.html Journal of Social Issues]&lt;/ref&gt;

In addition to its use as a theory to explain the occurrence of rape and [[domestic violence]], rape culture has been described as detrimental to men as well as women. Some writers and speakers, such as [[Jackson Katz]], [[Michael Kimmel]], and [[Don McPherson]], have said that it is intrinsically linked to [[gender role]]s that limit male self-expression and cause psychological harm to men. &lt;ref&gt;Jackson Katz, "Tough Guise" videorecording, Media Education Foundation, 2002&lt;/ref&gt; It has also been linked to [[homophobia]]. For instance, in her 1983 "Twenty-Four Hour Truce" speech, [[Andrea Dworkin]] said that "if you want to do something about homophobia, you are going to have to do something about the fact that men rape, and that forced sex is not incidental to male sexuality but is in practice paradigmatic."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nostatusquo.com/ACLU/dworkin/WarZoneChaptIIIE.html Letters from a Warzone: I Want a Twenty-Four-Hour Truce During Which There Is No Rape] - [[Andrea Dworkin]]&lt;/ref&gt; Also, researchers such as Philip Rumney and Martin Morgan-Taylor have used the rape culture paradigm to explain differences in how people perceive and treat male versus female victims of sexual assault.&lt;ref&gt;Phillip N.S. Rumney &amp; Martin Morgan-Taylor, "The Construction of Sexual Consent in Male Rape and Sexual Assault", in ''Making Sense of Sexual Consent'', edited by Mark Cowling and Paul Reynolds, ISBN 0-7546-3687-9&lt;/ref&gt;

==Criticisms of the paradigm==
The conceptualization of rape culture has been criticized by various writers for various reasons. Some, such as [[Christina Hoff Sommers]], have disputed the existence of rape culture, arguing that [http://www.leaderu.com/real/ri9502/sommers.html rape is overreported and overemphasized].  However, this is completely untrue as statistics and studies show that every 2 minutes someone in America is sexually assaulted.  Furthermore, 60% of sexual assaults go unreported to the police. (http://www.rainn.org/statistics?gclid=CLCxo-Oy2pYCFRIfDQodT1jP3A )  Others, such as [[bell hooks]], have criticized the rape culture paradigm on the grounds that it ignores rape's place in an overarching "culture of violence". &lt;ref&gt;bell hooks, ''Feminist Theory:From Margin to Center'', quoted in ''Feminism is for Everybody'' by bell hooks, ISBN 0-89608-628-3&lt;/ref&gt; These critics say that singling out rape and its sexual underpinnings from other forms of violence makes efforts to combat rape less effective and neglects or trivializes other forms of violence.

== See also ==
*[[War rape]]

==Resources and references==
{{Reflist}}
{{sourcesstart}}
*''Transforming a Rape Culture'', ISBN 1-57131-204-8, edited by Emilie Buchwald, Pamela R. Fletcher, and [http://www.martharoth.com/transformingarapeculture.htm Martha Roth]
{{sourcesend}}

[[Category:Feminist theory]]
[[Category:Sociology]]
[[Category:Cultural studies]]
[[Category:Rape]]
[[Category:Violence against women]]

[[it:Cultura dello stupro]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>