<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20111112183006|460320530" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="2298034" pageid="2298034" ns="0" title="Rape culture"><revisions><rev timestamp="2011-11-18T11:11:27Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Rape culture''' is a term which originated in [[women's studies]] and [[feminist theory]], describing a [[culture]] in which [[rape]] and [[sexual violence]] against women are common and in which prevalent [[attitude (psychology)|attitudes]], [[norm (sociology)|norms]], practices, and [[mass media|media]] condone, [[normalization (sociology)|normalize]], excuse, or tolerate sexual [[violence against women]]. Examples of behaviors commonly associated with rape culture include [[victim blaming]], [[sexual objectification]] and [[rape apologism]]. Use of the term has recently become more common.

==Origins and usage==
According to the ''Encyclopedia of Rape'', "The term rape culture originated in the 1970s during the 2nd wave feminist movement and is often used by feminists to describe contemporary American culture as a whole."&lt;ref name=Smith2004&gt;{{cite book|last=Smith|first=Merril D.|title=Encyclopedia of Rape|year=2004|publisher=Greenwood Press|location=Westport, Conn.|isbn=0313326878|edition=1st|page=174}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The term was used as a title of a 1975 documentary film, ''Rape Culture'', produced and directed by [[Margaret Lazarus]] and [[Renner Wunderlich]] for Cambridge Documentary Films, which depicted mass media normalization of violence against women. In a 1992 paper in the ''Journal of Social Issues'' entitled "A Feminist Redefinition of Rape and Sexual Assault: Historical Foundations and Change," Patricia Donat and John D'Emilio suggested that the term originated as "rape-supportive culture"&lt;ref&gt;Patricia Donat and John D'Emilio, "A Feminist Redefinition of Rape and Sexual Assault: Historical Foundations and Change", ''Journal of Social Issues'', vol. 48, n. 1, 1992; published in Di Karen J. Maschke, "The legal response to violence against women",  Routledge 1997, ISBN 978-0-8153-2519-2. &lt;/ref&gt; in [[Susan Brownmiller]]'s 1975 book ''Against Our Will: Men, Women, and Rape''.

===Slutwalk===
Although it had been in academic usage since its inception, the term 'rape culture' was scarcely used in popular culture and the media until 2011. The [[Slutwalk]] movement is credited with popularizing the term via mass media reports about the protesters.&lt;ref name=time1&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.time.com/time/nation/article/0,8599,2088234-1,00.html |title=Will SlutWalks Change the Meaning of the Word Slut? |author=Gibson, Megan |publisher=TIME Magazine |date=12 August 2011 |accessdate=18 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The rallies aim to raise awareness of rape culture - which they define as a culture where "sexual violence is both made to be invisible and inevitable" - and to end slut-shaming and victim blaming.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://slutwalknyc.com/FAQ |title=FAQ |publisher=Slutwalk NYC |accessdate=18 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=TL&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.timeslive.co.za/local/2011/09/23/slutwalk-joburg-takes-to-the-streets |title=Slutwalk Joburg takes to the streets |newspaper=Times LIVE |date=23 September 2011 |accessdate=18 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Feminist theory==
According to the rape culture theory, acts of [[sexism]] are commonly employed to validate and [[Rationalization (psychology)|rationalize]] normative [[misogyny|misogynistic]] practices. For instance, sexist jokes may be told to foster disrespect for women and an accompanying disregard for their well-being. An example would be a female rape victim being blamed for her being raped because of how she dressed or acted.  In rape culture, sexualized violence towards women is regarded as a continuum in a society that regards women's bodies as sexually available by default.&lt;ref&gt;Chris O'Sullivan, "Fraternities and the Rape Culture", in ''Transforming a Rape Culture'', edited by Emilie Buchwald, Pamela R. Fletcher &amp; Martha Roth, ISBN 0-915943-06-9&lt;/ref&gt; 

The root cause of rape culture is generally agreed to be the "domination and objectification of women".&lt;ref name=SA &gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.ncjrs.gov/App/Publications/abstract.aspx?ID=127046 |title=Sexual Face of Violence: Rapists on Rape (abstract) |author=Vogelman, L. |publisher=Raven Press Ltd (book); National Criminal Justice Reference Service (abstract) |accessdate=18 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, academic theory holds that rape culture does not necessarily have a single cause, and causes may be localized based on other social aspects of culture.&lt;ref name=herman &gt;Herman, Dianne F. "[http://homepage.smc.edu/delpiccolo_guido/Soc1/soc1readings/rape%20culture_final.pdf The Rape Culture]." Printed in ''Women: A Feminist Perspective'' (ed. Jo Freeman). Mcgraw Hill, 1994. Retrieved 18 October 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; For example, in South Africa the overriding "war culture" which emphasized masculinity and violence led to a culture in which [[war rape|rape was normalized]].&lt;ref name=SA /&gt;&lt;ref name=TL /&gt; A University of California Davis public document alleged that the enforcement of the following of social rules by women and the conditioning of gender roles were major causes.&lt;ref name=UCDavis&gt;{{cite web |url=http://students.haverford.edu/masar/documents/RapeCulture.pdf |title=Defining a Rape Culture |publisher=University of California Davis |accessdate=18 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In a study of [[date rape]], gender-based miscommunications were held to be a major factor supporting a [[campus rape]] culture.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |url=http://psycnet.apa.org/psycinfo/1993-21940-001 |title=Date and acquaintance rape among a sample of college students (abstract) |author=Mills, Crystal S. and Granoff, Barbara J. |journal=Social Work |volume=37 |issue=6 |date=November 1992 |pages=504-509 |accessdate=18 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The general unwillingness of police and district attorneys to prosecute rapes where force was not involved or where the victim had some sort of relationship with the aggressor is also cited as a motivation for date rape and campus rape.&lt;ref name=herman /&gt; Rape culture is also closely related to slut-shaming and [[victim blaming]], where rape victims are considered at fault for being raped, and it is argued that this connection is due to the presence of a culture that shames all female sexuality.&lt;ref name=herman /&gt; That some rapes are not reported to the police due to fear that they would not be believed is often cited as a symptom of a rape culture,&lt;ref name=real&gt;{{cite news |title=Rape culture is real |url=http://cupwire.ca/articles/47672 |author=Ketterling, Jean |newspaper=The Xaverian Weekly |publisher=Canadian University Press |date=23 September 2011 |accessdate=18 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=herman /&gt; that they thought the police would not believe them is cited as a reason by 6% of women who did not report rape.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Backman |first1=Ronet  |last2= |first2= |year=1988 |title=The factors related to rape reporting behavior and arrest: new evidence from the National Crime Victimization Survey |journal=Criminal Justice and Behavior |volume=25 |issue=1 |pages=8 |publisher= |doi= |url= |accessdate= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Although its use as a theory to explain the occurrence of rape and [[domestic violence]] was focused on the rape of women, rape culture has been described as detrimental to men as well as women. Some writers and speakers, such as [[Jackson Katz]], [[Michael Kimmel]], and [[Don McPherson]], have said that it is intrinsically linked to [[gender role]]s that limit male self-expression and cause psychological harm to men.&lt;ref&gt;Jackson Katz, "Tough Guise" videorecording, Media Education Foundation, 2002&lt;/ref&gt;

==Prominent incidents and allegations of rape culture==

In 2010, the webcomic [[Penny Arcade]] published a strip which featured a male rape victim in the setting of a video game. After complaints about the content of the strip, a follow-up apology strip was published which many bloggers alleged was offensive to and made light of rape victims.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|first=Milli A|title=Shaker|url=http://shakespearessister.blogspot.com/2010/08/rape-is-hilarious-part-53-in-ongoing.html|work="Rape Is Hilarious, Part 53 in an Ongoing Series"|accessdate=9 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; This "dickwolves" controversy generated reactions even in mainstream media, particularly after [[Wil Wheaton]] made a statement opposing the actions of Penny Arcade's creators.&lt;ref&gt;Myers, Maddy (16 Aug 2010). [http://thephoenix.com/BLOGS/laserorgy/archive/2010/08/16/penny-arcade-s-dubious-apology-for-dark-humor.aspx Penny Arcade surprised to find that rape jokes offend people]. [[The Boston Phoenix]]. Retrieved 5 March 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Myers, Maddy (2 March 2011). [http://thephoenix.com/Boston/life/116456-gaming-rape-culture-and-how-i-stopped-reading-pe/ Gaming, rape culture, and how I stopped reading Penny Arcade]. [[The Boston Phoenix]]. Retrieved 5 March 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

In February 2011, seventeen United States veterans filed suit against the Pentagon and defense secretary [[Robert Gates]] and former secretary [[Donald Rumsfield]], alleging that they allowed a culture in the military where rape was unevenly reported and punished. In several of the plaintiff's cases, the victim was forced to work with the accused rapist after reporting them for sexual assault. Unit commanders often have heavy influence over military rape cases, and less than one in five cases are prosecuted. &lt;ref&gt;Parker, Ashley (15 Feb. 2011). [http://www.nytimes.com/2011/02/16/us/16military.html Lawsuit Says Military Is Rife With Sexual Abuse]. [[New York Times]]. Retrieved 16 March 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hefling, Kimberly (16 Feb. 2011). ''U.S. Veterans Say Military is Mishandling Rape Case''. [[The Day]].&lt;/ref&gt; According to a 2011 [[Newsweek]] report, 1 in 5 females and 1 in 15 males in the United States military reported having been sexually assaulted by servicemembers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=The Military's Secret Shame |author=Ellison, Jesse |url=http://www.newsweek.com/2011/04/03/the-military-s-secret-shame.html |newspaper=Newsweek |date=3 April 2011 |accessdate=11 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; (See also: [[Sexual assault in the United States military]])

In March 2011, a group of 16 current and former [[Yale University]] students filed a [[Title IX]] complaint against the school with the US Department of Education's Office for Civil Rights, alleging that the administration did not respond decisively to misogyny on campus, such as [[Delta Kappa Epsilon]] fraternity members chanting sexist slogans.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Yale is Subject of Title IX Inquiry |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/04/01/us/01yale.html |newspaper=New York Times |date=31 March 2011 |accessdate=10 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The fraternity was subsequently suspended for five years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Foderaro|first=Lisa|title=Yale Restricts a Fraternity for Five Years|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/05/18/education/18yale.html?_r=1|work=New York Times|date=17 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Academic studies have examined fraternity cultures at other universities and discussed their roles in the creation of rape culture.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title=Fraternities and Collegiate Rape Culture: Why Are Some Fraternities More Dangerous Places for Women? |author=Boswell, A. Ayres and Spade, Joan Z. |journal=Gender and Society |pages=133-147 |volume=10 |issue=2 |date=April 1996 |accessdate=18 October 2011 |jstor=189830}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In March 2011, editorials on [[Salon.com]] and [[The Huffington Post]] criticised a ''New York Times'' article, saying that the article focused on victim-blaming on an eleven-year-old girl rather than the fact that she was raped. The article in question dealt with the November 2010 gang rape of the girl in [[Cleveland, Texas]].&lt;ref&gt;Williams, Mary Elizabeth (9 March 2011). [http://www.salon.com/life/feature/2011/03/09/new_york_times_blames_11_year_old_rape_victim/index.html The New York Times' sloppy, slanted child rape story]. [[Salon.com]]. Retrieved on 16 March 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/marina-delvecchio/post_1849_b_838788.html |title=Rape Culture and How it Betrays Women |author=DelVecchio, Marina |newspaper=The Huffington Post |date=21 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

When [[Roman Polanski]] was arrested in Zurich in 2009 on [[Roman Polanski sexual abuse case|sexual abuse charges]], more than 100 Hollywood figures signed a petition of support,&lt;ref&gt;[http://bighollywood.breitbart.com/bighollywood/2009/09/29/naming-names-the-free-roman-polanski-petition/ Naming Names: The ‘Free Roman Polanski’ Petition]. Big Hollywood.&lt;/ref&gt; which resulted in a public and media backlash against those who supported him and believed his accomplishments should mitigate his action.&lt;ref&gt;Weinberger, Jillian (18 May 2010). [http://msmagazine.com/blog/blog/2010/05/18/roman-polanski-the-undetected-rapist/ Roman Polanski, the Undetected Rapist?] [[Ms. Magazine]]. Accessed 4 March 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hess, Amanda (28 Sept 2009). [http://www.washingtoncitypaper.com/blogs/sexist/2009/09/28/common-roman-polanski-defenses-refuted/ Common Roman Polanski Defenses Refuted]. [[Washington City Paper]]. Accessed 4 March 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

In August and September 2011, [[Facebook]] faced criticism in the United States and the UK for refusing to remove pages that allegedly supported rape culture. Although the pages were legal per free speech laws in both area, those criticizing the site claimed the pages violated Facebook's own content policies, which prohibit hate speech.&lt;ref name=guardianfacebook&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/technology/2011/sep/30/facebook-refuses-pull-rape-jokepages?newsfeed=true |title=Facebook refuses to take down rape joke pages |newspaper=The Guardian |author=Davies, Lizzy |date=30 September 2011 |accessdate=18 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; A prominent petition to Facebook stated "Allowing such groups to congregate serves only to further normalise rape culture and the high instance of sexual violence that exists in society."&lt;ref name=guardianfacebook /&gt;&lt;!--Petition cannot be linked due to spam blacklist; it is linked from the article.--&gt;

==Criticisms==
Some writers, such as [[Christina Hoff Sommers]], have disputed the existence of rape culture, arguing that the common "one in four women will be raped in her lifetime" is based on a flawed study, but frequently cited because it leads to campus anti-rape groups receiving public funding. Sommers has also examined and criticized many other rape studies for their flawed methodology, and also states "There are many researchers who study rape victimization, but their relatively low figures generate no headlines."&lt;ref name="leaderu"&gt;Sommers, Dr. Christina Hoff. [http://www.leaderu.com/real/ri9502/sommers.html Researching the "Rape Culture" of America]. Accessed 4 March 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; Other writers, such as [[bell hooks]], have criticized the rape culture paradigm on the grounds that it ignores rape's place in an overarching "culture of violence".&lt;ref&gt;bell hooks, ''Feminist Theory: From Margin to Center'', quoted in ''Feminism is for Everybody'' by bell hooks, ISBN 0-89608-628-3&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
*{{cite book |title=Transforming a Rape Culture |editor=Emilie Buchwald, Pamela R. Fletcher and Martha Roth |year=1993 |ISBN=1-57131-204-8}}
*{{cite journal |pmid=7373511 |author=M. R. Burt |title=Cultural myths and supports for rape |date=1980 |journal=Journal of Personality and Social Psychology |volume=38 |pages=217-230}}
*{{cite journal |url=http://www3.interscience.wiley.com/journal/119570811/abstract?CRETRY=1&amp;SRETRY=0 |title=Rape myths, rape definitions, and probability of conviction |author=M. R. Burt and R. S. Albin |date=1981 |journal=Journal of Applied Social Psychology |volume=11 |pages=212-230}}

{{Sexual abuse}}
[[Category:Feminist theory]]
[[Category:Cultural studies]]
[[Category:Misogyny]]
[[Category:Rape]]

[[it:Cultura dello stupro]]
[[ru:Культура изнасилования]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>