<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20051104054757|27324247" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="2298034" pageid="2298034" ns="0" title="Rape culture"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-11-04T18:56:30Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Rape culture''' is a term used to denote a [[culture]] in which [[rape]] and other sexual violence is common and in which prevalent [[attitude (psychology)|attitudes]], [[norm (sociology)|norms]], practices, and [[mass media|media]] condone, [[normalization|normalize]], excuse, or encourage rape or other violence against women.  In this [[paradigm]], such a thing as "trivial" or "harmless" [[sexism]] does not exist; for instance, telling a sexist joke is seen as fostering a [[misogyny|misogynistic]] disrespect for women and an accompanying disregard for their well-being that can ultimately make rape seem acceptable.  

The term is widely used within [[women's studies]] and [[feminism]] (particularly [[radical feminism]]).  In a 1992 paper in the ''Journal of Social Issues'' entitled "A Feminist Redefinition of Rape and Sexual Assault: Historical Foundations and Change," Patricia Donat and John D'Emilio suggested that the term originated as "rape-supportive culture" in [[Susan Brownmiller]]'s 1975 book ''Against Our Will: Men, Women, and Rape.''  

Rape culture has been described as detrimental to men in addition to women.  Some writers and speakers, such as Jackson Katz and Don Mcpherson, have said that it is intrinsically linked to [[gender role]]s that limit male self-expression and cause psychological harm to men.  It has also been linked to [[homophobia]].  For instance, [[Andrea Dworkin]], in her 1983 "Twenty-Four Hour Truce" speech, said, "If you want to do something about homophobia, you are going to have to do something about the fact that men rape, and that forced sex is not incidental to male sexuality but is in practice paradigmatic."

==Criticisms of the Paradigm==
The conceptualization of rape culture has been criticized by various writers for various reasons.  Some, such as [[Christina Hoff Sommers]], have attempted to disprove the existence of rape culture, arguing that rape is overreported and overemphasized.  Others, such as [[bell hooks]], have criticized the rape culture paradigm on the grounds that it ignores rape's place in an overarching "culture of violence".  These critics say that singling out rape and its social underpinnings from other forms of violence makes efforts to combat rape less effective and neglects or trivializes other forms of violence.

==Resources and References==
*[http://orgs.sa.ucsb.edu/ssr/rapeculture.html Rape Culture] - an overview by Students Stopping Rape at [[University of California, Santa Barbara|UCSB]]
*''Transforming a Rape Culture'', ISBN 1561312692 by Emilie Buchwald, Pamela R. Fletcher, and Martha Roth


[[Category:Sociology]]
[[Category:Feminist theory]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>