<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20101116061715|397056188" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="2298034" pageid="2298034" ns="0" title="Rape culture"><revisions><rev timestamp="2010-11-16T06:18:34Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Rape culture''' is a term used within [[women's studies]] and [[feminism]], describing a [[culture]] in which [[rape]] and other [[sexual violence]] (usually against women) are common and in which prevalent [[attitude (psychology)|attitudes]], [[norm (sociology)|norms]], practices, and [[mass media|media]] condone, [[normalization (sociology)|normalize]], excuse, or encourage [[violence against women|sexualized violence]]. 

Within the [[paradigm]], acts of [[sexism]] are commonly employed to validate and [[Rationalization (psychology)|rationalize]] normative [[misogyny|misogynistic]] practices; for instance, sexist jokes may be told to foster disrespect for women and an accompanying disregard for their well-being, which ultimately make their rape and abuse seem "acceptable". Examples of behaviors said{{by whom|date=May 2010}} to typify rape culture include [[victim blaming]] and [[sexual objectification]].

In a 1992 paper in the ''Journal of Social Issues'' entitled "A Feminist Redefinition of Rape and Sexual Assault: Historical Foundations and Change," Patricia Donat and John D'Emilio suggested that the term originated as "rape-supportive culture"&lt;ref&gt;Patricia Donat and John D'Emilio, "A Feminist Redefinition of Rape and Sexual Assault: Historical Foundations and Change", ''Journal of Social Issues'', vol. 48, n. 1, 1992; published in Di Karen J. Maschke, "The legal response to violence against women",  Routledge 1997, ISBN 978-0-8153-2519-2. &lt;/ref&gt; in [[Susan Brownmiller]]'s 1975 book ''Against Our Will: Men, Women, and Rape''.

In addition to its use as a theory to explain the occurrence of rape and [[domestic violence]], rape culture has been described as detrimental to men as well as women. Some writers and speakers, such as [[Jackson Katz]], [[Michael Kimmel]], and [[Don McPherson]], have said that it is intrinsically linked to [[gender role]]s that limit male self-expression and cause psychological harm to men.&lt;ref&gt;Jackson Katz, "Tough Guise" videorecording, Media Education Foundation, 2002&lt;/ref&gt; 

Researchers such as Philip Rumney and Martin Morgan-Taylor have used the rape culture paradigm to explain differences in how people perceive and treat male versus female victims of [[sexual assault]].&lt;ref&gt;Phillip N.S. Rumney &amp; Martin Morgan-Taylor, "The Construction of Sexual Consent in Male Rape and Sexual Assault", in ''Making Sense of Sexual Consent'', edited by Mark Cowling and Paul Reynolds, ISBN 0-7546-3687-9&lt;/ref&gt;

==Criticisms of the paradigm==
Some writers, such as [[Christina Hoff Sommers]], have disputed the existence of rape culture, arguing that the common "one in four women will be raped in her lifetime" is based on a flawed study, but frequently cited because it leads to campus anti-rape groups receiving public funding.&lt;ref name="leaderu"&gt;http://www.leaderu.com/real/ri9502/sommers.html&lt;/ref&gt; Others, such as [[bell hooks]] and Sommers have criticized the rape culture paradigm on the grounds that it ignores rape's place in an overarching "culture of violence".&lt;ref&gt;bell hooks, ''Feminist Theory:From Margin to Center'', quoted in ''Feminism is for Everybody'' by bell hooks, ISBN 0-89608-628-3&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
*''Transforming a Rape Culture'', ISBN 1-57131-204-8, edited by Emilie Buchwald, Pamela R. Fletcher, and [http://www.martharoth.com/transformingarapeculture.htm Martha Roth]
*M.R. Burt, [http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/7373511 "Cultural myths and supports for rape"], in ''Journal of personality and social psychology'', n.38, 1980, at pages 217-230.
*M.R. Burt and R.S. Albin,[http://www3.interscience.wiley.com/journal/119570811/abstract?CRETRY=1&amp;SRETRY=0 "Rape myths, rape definitions, and probability of conviction."] in ''Journal of applied social psychology'', n.11, 1981, at pages 212-230.
*Thornhill, R. and Palmer, C. (2000), A Natural History of Rape: Biological Bases of Sexual Coercion. Cambridge: MIT Press. ISBN 0-262-20125-9 
{{Sexual abuse}}

[[Category:Feminist theory]]
[[Category:Cultural studies]]
[[Category:Rape]]

[[it:Cultura dello stupro]]
[[ru:Культура изнасилования]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>