<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20170714044916|790505276" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="8687670" pageid="8687670" ns="0" title="Fear of children"><revisions><rev timestamp="2017-07-27T04:42:23Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Discrimination sidebar}}
'''Fear of children''', '''fear of [[infant]]s''' or '''fear of [[childhood]]''' is alternatively called '''pedophobia''' (American English), '''paedophobia'''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 |last=Lewis |first=Paul
 |title=Fear of teenagers is growing in Britain, study warns
 |url=https://www.theguardian.com/society/2006/oct/23/youthjustice.familyandrelationships
 |location=London |publisher=Guardian |date=23 October 2006 |accessdate=2 January 2011
 |quote=But it appears that an aversion to young people, or "paedophobia", is becoming a national phenomenon.
}}&lt;/ref&gt; or '''pediaphobia'''.&lt;ref&gt;Kring, A., Davison, G., et al. (2006) ''Abnormal Psychology'' Wiley.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Djordjevic, S. (2004) ''Dictionary of Medicine: French-English with English-French Glossary.'' Schreiber Publishing, Inc.&lt;/ref&gt; Other age-focused fears are [[ephebiphobia]] and [[gerontophobia]]. Recognised outcomes of pedophobia include [[paternalism]], [[adultism]], and by extension, [[ageism]].

==Etymology==

The word ''pedophobia'' comes from the Greek roots παιδ- ''paid-'' "child" and φόβος ''-phóbos'' "fear".

==Scientific analysis==
The fear of children has been diagnosed and treated by psychiatrists, with studies examining the effects of multiple forms of treatment.&lt;ref&gt;Schwartz, C., Houlihan, D., Krueger, K. F., Simon, D. A. (1997) "The Behavioral Treatment of a Young Adult with Post Traumatic Stress Disorder and a Fear of Children," ''Child &amp; Family Behavior Therapy, 19''1, p37-49.&lt;/ref&gt; Sociologists have situated "contemporary fears about children and childhood", e.g. paedophobia, as "contributing to the ongoing social construction of childhood", suggesting that "generational power relations, in which children's lives are bounded by adult surveillance" affect many aspects of society.&lt;ref&gt;Scott, S., Jackson, S., &amp; Backett-milburnswings, K. (1998) "Swings and roundabouts: Risk anxiety and the everyday worlds of children," ''Sociology, 32'' p. 689-705. [[Cambridge University Press]].&lt;/ref&gt; More than one study has identified the fear of children as a factor affecting biological conception in humans.&lt;ref&gt;Kemeter, P. &amp; Fiegl, J. (1998) "Adjusting to life when assisted conception fails," ''Human Reproduction. 13''4 p. 1099–1105.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;McDonald, R. (1968) "The Role of Emotional Factors in Obstetric Complications: A Review," ''Psychosomatic Medicine 30'' p. 222-237. American Psychosomatic Society.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Popular perception==
Paedophobia is the ''raison d'etre'' for several international [[social justice]] movements addressing young people, including [[children's rights]] and [[youth participation]]. Major international organisations addressing paedophobia, either outright or by implication, include [[Save the Children]] and [[Children's Defense Fund]]. However, some organisations, particularly those associated with the [[youth rights]] movement, claim that these movements perpetuate paedophobia.&lt;ref&gt;Axon, K. (n.d.) [http://www.asfar.org/zine/1st/Paedophobia.html ''The Anti-Child Bias of Children's Advocacy Groups''] Chicago, IL: Americans for a Society Free of Age Restrictions.&lt;/ref&gt;

The complicity of this notion is exacerbated by observations by experts such as [[Letty Cottin Pogrebin]], a founding editor of ''[[Ms. magazine]]'', who is said to have diagnosed America as having an "epidemic of paedophobia", saying that, "[t]hough most of us make exceptions for our own offspring, we do not seem particularly warm-hearted towards other peoples' children".&lt;ref&gt;L. Pogrebin, as cited in Zelizer, V. (1994) ''Pricing the Priceless Child: The Changing Social Value of Children'' [[Princeton University Press]].&lt;/ref&gt;

==Causes==
One author suggests that the cause of the fear of children in [[academia]] specifically extends from [[adult|adults']] distinct awareness of the capacity of children as she wrote, "Children embarrass us because they point ever too cleverly and clearly to our denial of personal, material, and maternal history."&lt;ref&gt;Coiner, C. &amp; George, D.H. (1998) ''The Family Track: Keeping Your Faculties while You Mentor, Nurture, Teach, and Serve'' [[University of Illinois Press]].&lt;/ref&gt; A separate report suggests that the source of current trends in the fear of children have a specific source, namely,

:[[James Q. Wilson]], a professor at [[UCLA]]'s School of Management... back in 1975... helped inaugurate the current climate of paedophobia [when he said] 'a [[Critical mass (sociodynamics)|critical mass]] of younger persons... creates an explosive increase in the amount of crime.'&lt;ref&gt;Murashige, M. (2001). ''The Future of Change: Youth Perspectives on Social Justice and Cross-Cultural Collaborative Action in Los Angeles.'' Los Angeles: [http://mcc-la.org MultiCultural Collaborative].&lt;/ref&gt;

==Addressing the issue==
As mentioned above, [[social service]], [[human rights]], and [[social justice]] organisations have been tackling the fear of children for dozens of years. The United Nations has created the [[Convention on the Rights of the Child]], which is implicitly designed to address paedophobia by fostering [[intergenerational equity]] between children and adults.&lt;ref&gt;Penn, J. (1999) &lt;!-- [http://www.childcarecanada.org/pubs/fs/fs5.pdf ''The Rights Of Young Children.''] ???--&gt; London University Institute of Education.&lt;/ref&gt;

As evidenced above, paedophobia is distinctly addressed by academic, especially evidenced since the creation of the field of [[Youth studies]]. The influence of the fear of children in [[American popular culture]] is examined by critical media analysts who have identified the effects of paedophobia in both [[List of notable Disney feature films|Disney]]&lt;ref&gt;Giroux, H. (1999) ''The Mouse that Roared: Disney and the End of Innocence.'' [[Rowman &amp; Littlefield Publishers]]&lt;/ref&gt; and [[horror movies|horror]] films.&lt;ref&gt;Phillips, K. (2005) ''Projected Fears: Horror Films and American Culture.'' [[Praeger Publishers]]&lt;/ref&gt;

A wide range of other authors and scholars, including [[Henry Giroux]],&lt;ref&gt;(n.d.) [http://www.freechild.org/ReadingList/henry_giroux.htm Reading List on Henry Giroux]. [[The Freechild Project]].&lt;/ref&gt; [[Mike Males]] and [[Barbara Kingsolver]],&lt;ref&gt;Dudley-Marling, C., Jackson, J., &amp; Patel, L. (2006) "Disrespecting Childhood, ''[[Phi Delta Kappan]] 87''10 (June 2006).&lt;/ref&gt; have suggested that the popular modern fear of children stems from [[corporatisation]] of [[mass media]] and its complicity with a range of [[political]] and [[economic]] interests. Males perhaps goes the furthest, and wrote an entire book exploring the subject.&lt;ref&gt;Males, M. (2001) ''Kids and Guns: How Politicians, Experts, and the Media Fabricate Fear of Youth.'' Common Courage Press.&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Fear of childbirth]]
* [[Gerontophobia|Fear of seniors]]
* [[Ephebiphobia|Fear of youth]]
* [[List of phobias]]

==References==
{{reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
{{wiktionary|pedophobia}}
{{wiktionary|hebephobia}}
*''Raising Cain: Protecting the Emotional Life of Boys'' by Daniel J. Kindlon, Michael Thompson, et al.
*Prout, R. (2001) ''Fear and Gendering: Pedophobia, Effeminophobia, and Hyermasculine Desire in the Work of Juan Goytisolo,'' '''Worlds of Change, 42''.
*Scharf, R. (2001) "Pedophobia, the [[gynarchy]], and the [[androcracy]]," ''Journal of Psychohistory 28''(3) (Winter 2001) p.&amp;nbsp;281-302.

{{Youth empowerment}}
{{Mental and behavioral disorders|selected = neurotic}}
{{Discrimination}}

[[Category:Anxiety disorders]]
[[Category:Phobias]]
[[Category:Prejudice and discrimination]]
[[Category:Youth]]
[[Category:Ageing]]
[[Category:Ageism]]
[[Category:Childhood]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>