<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20081107220348|250321157" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="3191713" pageid="3191713" ns="0" title="Nuremberg Laws"><revisions><rev timestamp="2008-11-12T19:28:02Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{The Holocaust}}
The '''[[Nuremberg]] Laws''' ([[German language|German]]: ''Nürnberger Gesetze'') of [[1935]] were [[laws]] passed in [[Nazi Germany]]. They used a [[pseudoscience|pseudoscientific]] basis for [[Racial policy of Nazi Germany|racial discrimination against Jewish people]]. The laws classified people as German if all four of their grandparents were of "German blood" (white circles on the chart), while people were classified as Jews if they descended from three or four Jewish grandparents (black circles in top row right). A person with one or two Jewish grandparents was a [[Mischling]], a crossbreed, of "mixed blood".

==Introduction and History ==
[[Image:Nurembergracechart.jpg|left|thumb|250px|1935 chart from [[Nazi Germany]] used to explain the Nuremberg Laws]]

During the spring and summer of 1933, disenchantment with how the Third Reich had developed in practice as opposed to what had been promised had led to many in the Nazi Party, especially the ''Alte Kämpfer'' (Old Fighters; i.e those who joined the Party before 1930, and who tended to be the most ardent anti-Semitics in the Party), and the [[Sturmabteilung|SA]] into lashing out against Germany's Jewish minority as a way of expressing their frustrations against a group that the authorities would not generally protect.&lt;ref&gt;Kershaw, Ian Hitler 1889-1936: Hubris, New York: W.W Norton &amp; Company, 1998, 1999 pages 560-561.&lt;/ref&gt; A [[Gestapo]] report from the spring of 1935 stated that the rank and file of the Nazi Party would "set in motion by us from below" a solution to the "Jewish problem", "that the government would then have to follow".&lt;ref&gt;Kershaw, Ian ''Hitler 1889-1936: Hubris'', New York: W.W Norton &amp; Company, 1998, 1999 page 561.&lt;/ref&gt; As a result, Nazi Party activists and SA members started a major wave of assaults, vandalism and boycotts against German Jews.&lt;ref&gt;Kershaw, Ian ''Hitler 1889-1936: Hubris'', New York: W.W Norton &amp; Company, 1998, 1999 pages 561-562.&lt;/ref&gt; A conference of ministers was held on [[August 20]] [[1935]] to discuss the negative economic effects of Party actions against Jews. [[Adolf Wagner]], the Party representative at the conference, argued that such effects would cease, once the [[government]] decided on a firm policy against the Jews. 

Dr. [[Hjalmar Schacht]], the Economics Minister, criticized arbitrary behavior by Party members as this inhibited his policy of rebuilding Germany's [[economy]].&lt;ref&gt;Kershaw, Ian ''Hitler 1889-1936: Hubris'', New York: W.W Norton &amp; Company, 1998, 1999 page 563&lt;/ref&gt; It made no economic sense since Jews were believed to have certain entrepreneurial skills that could be usefully employed to further his policies. Schacht made no moral condemnation of Jewish policy and advocated the passing of legislation to clarify the situation. Following complaints from Dr. Schacht plus reports that the German public did not approve of the wave of anti-Semitic violence, and that continuing police toleration of the violence was hurting the regime's popularity with the wider public, Hitler ordered a stop to "individual actions" against German Jews on [[August 8]] [[1935]].&lt;ref&gt;Kershaw, Ian Hitler 1889-1936: Hubris, New York: W.W Norton &amp; Company, 1998, 1999 page 563&lt;/ref&gt; On [[August 20]] [[1935]], the Interior Minister Dr. [[Wilhelm Frick]] threatened to impose harsh penalties on those Party members who ignored the order of [[August 8]] and continued to assault Jews.&lt;ref&gt;Kershaw, Ian ''Hitler 1889-1936: Hubris'', New York: W.W Norton &amp; Company, 1998, 1999 page 563&lt;/ref&gt; From Hitler's perspective, it was imperative to bring in harsh new anti-Semitic laws as a consolation prize for those Party members who were disappointed with Hitler's halt order of [[August 8]], especially because Hitler had only reluctantly given the halt order for pragmatic reasons, and his symapthies were with the Party radicals.&lt;ref&gt;Kershaw, Ian ''Hitler 1889-1936: Hubris'', New York: W.W Norton &amp; Company, 1998, 1999 page 563&lt;/ref&gt;

The Nazi Party Rally held at Nuremberg in September 1935 had featured the first session of the ''Reichstag'' held at that city since [[1543]]. Hitler had planned to have the ''Reichstag'' pass a law making the Nazi Swastika flag the flag of the German ''Reich'', and a major speech in support of the impending Italian aggression against Ethiopia.&lt;ref&gt;Kershaw, Ian ''Hitler 1889-1936: Hubris'', New York: W.W Norton &amp; Company, 1998, 1999 page 567&lt;/ref&gt; However, at the last minute, the German Foreign Minister Baron [[Konstantin von Neurath]] persuaded Hitler to cancel his speech as being too provocative to public opinion abroad, thus leaving Hitler with the sudden need to have something else to address the historic first meeting of the ''Reichstag'' in Nuremberg since 1543, other than the ''Reich'' Flag Law.&lt;ref&gt;Kershaw, Ian ''Hitler 1889-1936: Hubris'', New York: W.W Norton &amp; Company, 1998, 1999 pages 567-568&lt;/ref&gt; On [[September 13]] [[1935]], Dr. Bernhard Lösener, the Interior Ministry official in charge of drafting anti-Semitic laws was hastily summoned to the Nuremberg Party Rally by plane together with another Interior Ministry official, ''Ministeralrat'' (Ministerial Counsellor) Franz Albrecht Medicus, to start drafting at once a law for Hitler to present to the ''Reichstag'' for [[September 15]].&lt;ref&gt;Kershaw, Ian Hitler 1889-1936: Hubris, New York: W.W Norton &amp; Company, 1998, 1999 pages 567&lt;/ref&gt; Lösener and Medicus arrived in Nuremberg on the morning of [[September 14]] and because of the short time available for the drafting  of the laws, both measures were hastily improvised (there was even a shortage of drafting paper so that menu cards had to be used).&lt;ref&gt;Kershaw, Ian ''Hitler 1889-1936: Hubris'', New York: W.W Norton &amp; Company, 1998, 1999 pages 568-570 &amp; 759-760.&lt;/ref&gt; On the evening of [[September 15]], two measures were announced at the annual [[Nuremberg Rally|Party Rally]] in Nuremberg, becoming known as the Nuremberg Laws.&lt;ref&gt;Kershaw, Ian ''Hitler 1889-1936: Hubris'', New York: W.W Norton &amp; Company, 1998, 1999 pages 568&lt;/ref&gt;

The first law, '''The Law for the Protection of German Blood and German Honour,'''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ess.uwe.ac.uk/documents/gerblood.htm Nuremberg Law for the Protection of German Blood and German Honor], English translation at the University of the West of England&lt;/ref&gt; prohibited marriages and extramarital intercourse between "Jews" (the name was now officially used in place of "non-Aryans") and "Germans" and also the employment of "German" females under forty-five in Jewish [[household]]s. The second law, '''The Reich Citizenship Law''' &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ess.uwe.ac.uk/documents/citizen.htm Reich Citizenship Law], English translation at the University of the West of England&lt;/ref&gt;, stripped persons not considered of German blood of their German [[citizenship]] and introduced a new distinction between "Reich [[citizen]]s" and "nationals".

The Nuremberg Laws by their general nature formalized the unofficial and particular measures taken against Jews up to 1935. The Nazi leaders made a point of stressing the consistency of this legislation with the Party programme which demanded that Jews should be deprived of their rights as citizens. The laws were passed unanimously by the [[Reichstag (institution)|Reichstag]], or German Parliament, in a special session held during a [[Nuremberg Rally]]. 
After the example of the Nuremberg Laws, [[Law for protection of the nation|The Law for Protection of the Nation]] was passed in [[Bulgaria]] during [[World War II]], which also had a strong [[Antisemitism|antisemitic character]].

Several authors have argued that the Nuremberg Laws were inspired partly by the [[anti-miscegenation laws]] of the United States of America.&lt;ref&gt; [http://history.berkeley.edu/faculty/Hollinger/articles/amalgamation_and_hypodescent] David Hollinger (2003) Amalgamation and Hypodescent: The Question of Ethnoracial Mixture in the History of the United States, American Historical Review, Vol. 108, Iss. 5]&lt;/ref&gt;

== The Laws for the Protection of German Blood and German Honour ==
{{Discrimination sidebar}}

{{quotation|([[September 15]] [[1935]])&lt;br/&gt;
Entirely convinced that the purity of German blood is essential to the further existence of the German people, and inspired by the uncompromising determination to safeguard the future of the German nation, the Reichstag has unanimously resolved upon the following law, which is promulgated herewith:
&lt;p&gt;
; Section 1
#[[Marriage]]s between Jews and citizens of German or kindred blood are forbidden. Marriages concluded in defiance of this law are void, even if, for the purpose of evading this law, they were concluded abroad.
#Proceedings for annulment may be initiated only by the [[Public Prosecutor]]. 
&lt;p&gt;

; Section 2
#Extramarital sexual intercourse between Jews and subjects of the state of Germany or related blood is forbidden.
&lt;p&gt;
''(Supplementary decrees set Nazi definitions of racial Germans, Jews, and half-breeds or [[Mischling]]e --- see the latter entry for details and citations. Jews could not vote or hold public office.)'' 
&lt;p&gt;
; Section 3
: Jews will not be permitted to employ female citizens of German or kindred blood as [[domestic worker]]s under the age of 45.
&lt;p&gt;
; Section 4
#Jews are forbidden to display the Reich and [[national flag]] or the [[national colours]]. 
#On the other hand they are permitted to display the Jewish colours. The exercise of this right is protected by the State.
&lt;p&gt;
; Section 5
#A person who acts contrary to the prohibition of Section 1 will be punished with [[hard labour]]. 
#A person who acts contrary to the prohibition of Section 2 will be punished with [[imprisonment]] or with hard labour. 
#A person who acts contrary to the provisions of Sections 3 or 4 will be punished with imprisonment up to a year and with a [[fine (penalty)|fine]], or with one of these penalties.
&lt;p&gt;
; Section 6
: The Reich Minister of the Interior in agreement with the Deputy Führer and the Reich [[Minister of Justice]] will issue the legal and administrative regulations required for the enforcement and supplementing of this law.
&lt;p&gt;
; Section 7
: The law will become effective on the day after its promulgation; Section 3, however, not until [[January 1]] [[1936]].
}}

==German Discrimination Against Jews== 
[[Image:German Jewish Passport.jpg|left|thumb|200px|German Jewish passports could be used to leave but not to return.]]
{{See also|Anti-Jewish legislation in prewar Nazi Germany}}
While the Nuremberg Laws established for the first time very clearly who was defined as a Jew, legal discrimination against Jews had come into being earlier and steadily grew as time went on. Among other things, Jews were banned from working for the state or being employed as lawyers, doctors or journalists. Jews were prohibited from using hospitals and could not be educated past the age of 14. Public parks, libraries, beaches were closed to Jews. War memorials were to have Jewish names expunged. Even the lottery could not award winnings to Jews.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
|title=Examples of Antisemitic Legislation, 1933-1939
|publisher=United States Holocaust Memorial Museum
|url=http://www.ushmm.org/wlc/article.php?lang=en&amp;ModuleId=10007459
|accessdate=2008-07-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Jews were required to adopt a middle name: "Sara" for women and "Israel" for men. Their identification cards were required to have a large "J" stamped on them.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
|title=The Nuremberg Race Laws
|publisher=United States Holocaust Memorial Museum
|url=http://www.ushmm.org/outreach/nlaw.htm
|accessdate=2008-07-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;   

Some Nazi allies in Europe also emulated the Nuremberg laws, passing similar legislation.

==Existing Copies==
An original typescript of the laws signed by Hitler himself was found by the 203rd Detachment of the US Army's Counter-Intelligence Corps (CIC), commanded by Martin Dannenberg, in [[Eichstätt]], [[Bavaria]], [[Germany]], on [[April 27]] [[1945]]. It was appropriated by General [[George S. Patton]], in violation of [[JCS 1067]]. During a visit to [[Los Angeles, California]], he secretly handed it over to the [[The Huntington Library|Huntington Library]]. The document was stored until [[June 26]] [[1999]] when its existence was revealed. Although legal ownership of the document has not been established, it is on permanent loan to the [[Skirball Cultural Center]], which placed it on public display three days later.

==See also==
* [[Nazism and race]]
* [[Aryan paragraph]]

==Endnotes==
{{reflist}}

==References==
*[[Ian Kershaw|Kershaw, Ian]] ''Hitler 1889-1936: Hubris'', New York: W.W Norton &amp; Company, 1998, 1999, ISBN 0-393-04671-0.

==External links==
* [http://www.mtsu.edu/~baustin/nurmlaw2.html The Nuremberg Laws on Citizenship and Race text], translated into English
* [http://www.shoaheducation.com/pNEW.html#race Race Laws]

{{Segregation by type|state=collapsed}}
[[Category:Antisemitism]]
[[Category:Nazi Germany]]
[[Category:German law]]
[[Category:Jewish German history]]
[[Category:Race-related legal issues]]
[[Category:Nazi eugenics]]
[[Category:Religion and race]]
[[Category:1935 in law]]
[[Category:1935 in Germany]]

[[cs:Norimberské zákony]]
[[de:Nürnberger Gesetze]]
[[el:Νόμοι της Νυρεμβέργης]]
[[es:Leyes de Núremberg]]
[[fa:سیاست نژادی آلمان نازی]]
[[fr:Lois de Nuremberg]]
[[he:חוקי נירנברג]]
[[nl:Rassenwetten van Neurenberg]]
[[ja:ニュルンベルク法]]
[[no:Nürnberglovene]]
[[pl:Ustawy norymberskie]]
[[pt:Leis de Nuremberg]]
[[ro:Legile de la Nürnberg]]
[[ru:Нюрнбергские расовые законы]]
[[simple:Nuremberg Laws]]
[[sk:Norimberské zákony]]
[[fi:Nürnbergin lait]]
[[sv:Nürnberglagarna]]
[[yi:נירנבערג געזעצן]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>