<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20121109025123|522110632" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="3191713" pageid="3191713" ns="0" title="Nuremberg Laws"><revisions><rev timestamp="2012-11-12T04:23:59Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{about||the set of guidelines for determining what constitutes a war crime|Nuremberg principles|the set of research ethics principles for human experimentation|Nuremberg Code}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2011}}

[[File:RGBL I 1935 S 1145.jpg|right|thumb|250px|Title page of RGB I No. 100 proclaiming the laws. Issued 16.09.1935.]]
{{wikisourcelang|de|Nürnberger Gesetze|Nuremberg Laws}}

The '''Nuremberg Laws''' ({{lang-de|link=no|Nürnberger Gesetze}}) of 1935 were [[antisemitism|antisemitic]] laws in [[Nazi Germany]] introduced at the annual [[Nuremberg Rally]] of the [[Nazi Party]]. After the [[Machtergreifung|takeover of power in 1933]] by [[Hitler]], [[Nazism]] became an official ideology incorporating [[antisemitism]] as a form of [[scientific racism]]. There was a rapid growth in German legislation directed at Jews and other groups, such as the [[Law for the Restoration of the Professional Civil Service]] which banned "non-Aryans" and political opponents of the Nazis, from the civil-service.

The lack of a clear legal method of [[Who is a Jew?|defining who was Jewish]] had, however, allowed some Jews to escape some forms of discrimination aimed at them. The enactment of laws identifying who was Jewish made it easier for the Nazis to enforce legislation restricting the basic rights of German Jews.

The Nuremberg Laws classified people with four German grandparents as "German or kindred blood", while people were classified as Jews if they descended from three or four Jewish grandparents. A person with one or two Jewish grandparents was a ''[[Mischling]]'', a crossbreed, of "mixed blood".&lt;ref&gt;In many cases a person with exactly two Jewish grandparents was deemed a "Jew". There were a number of [[legal test]]s used, to determine if such a person—with precisely two Jewish grandparents—was to be classified as a "Jew" or a "Mischling". ''See'' [[Mischling Test]].&lt;/ref&gt; These laws deprived Jews of [[German citizenship]] and prohibited marriage between Jews and other Germans.&lt;ref&gt;Hunt, L. (2009). The Making of the West: Peoples and Cultures, Vol. C: Since 1740. Bedford/St. Martin's.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Nuremberg Laws also included a ban on sexual intercourse between people defined as "Jews" and non-Jewish Germans and prevented "Jews" from participating in German civic life. These laws were both an attempt to return the Jews of 20th-century Germany to the position that Jews had held before their emancipation in the 19th century; although in the 19th century Jews could have evaded restrictions by converting, this was no longer possible.

The laws were a legal embodiment of an already existing [[Nazi boycott of Jewish businesses]].

==Background history==
[[File:Nuremberg laws.jpg|left|thumb|250px|1935 chart from [[Nazi Germany]] used to explain the Nuremberg Laws]]

Before 1806, when general citizenship was largely non-existent in the [[Holy Roman Empire]], its inhabitants were subject to different [[Estates of the realm|estate]] regulations. Varying from one territory of the Empire to another, these regulations classified inhabitants into different groups, such as dynasts, members of the court entourage, other aristocrats, city dwellers ([[bourgeoisie|burgher]]s), Jews, [[Huguenot]]s (in Prussia a special estate until 1810), free [[peasant]]s, [[serf]]s, peddlers and [[Romani people|Gypsies]], with different privileges and burdens attached to each classification. Legal inequality was the principle.

The concept of citizenship was mostly restricted to cities, especially [[Free imperial city|free imperial cities]]. There was no general franchise, which remained a privilege for the few, who inherited the status or acquired it when they reached a certain level of taxed income or could afford the expensive citizen's fee (Bürgergeld). Citizenship was often further restricted to city dwellers affiliated with the locally dominant Christian denomination (Calvinist, Catholic or Lutheran). City dwellers of other denominations or religions and those who lacked the necessary wealth to qualify as citizens were considered as mere inhabitants who lacked political rights and were sometimes subject to revocable staying permits.

Most Jews then living in German locales that allowed their settlement were automatically defined as mere indigenous inhabitants, depending on permits that were typically less generous than those granted to Gentile indigenous inhabitants. In the 18th c. some Jews and their families (such as [[Daniel Itzig]] in Berlin) gained equal status with their fellow Christian city dwellers, but had a different status than noblemen, Huguenots, or serfs. They often did not enjoy the freedom of movement across territorial or even municipal boundaries, let alone enjoy the same status in the new place as in the old.

With the abolition of legal status differences in the Napoleonic era and its aftermath citizenship was established as a new franchise generally applying to all former subjects of the monarchs. While [[Jewish emancipation#Dates of emancipation|Jewish emancipation]] did not eliminate all forms of discrimination against Jews, who often remained barred from holding official positions with the State, such forms of discrimination were no longer the guiding principle for ordering society, but a violation of it. These restrictions were mostly abolished in the 1840s, in few smaller states as late as 1869.

In the mid-19th century, the fiercely anti-Semitic [[Völkisch movement|''völkisch'']] movement appeared in Germany. One of the major demands of the various ''völkisch'' groups had been the disemancipation of German Jews and banning sexual relations between those considered to be of the “Semitic race” and those considered to be of the “Aryan race”. In 1881, a petition presented to the German government by the ''völkisch'' groups demanding Jewish disemancipation and the banning of marriage and sexual intercourse between “Aryans” and “Jews” had collected over a million signatures. Reflecting the strength of the ''völkisch'' movement, from 1892 when the so-called Tivoli Program was adopted, the [[German Conservative Party|Conservative Party]] formally advocated disemancipation of German Jews.&lt;ref&gt;[[George Mosse|Mosse, George]]| "Racism" pages 1217 pages 1206–1213 from ''The Encyclopedia of the Holocaust'' Volume 3 edited by Israel Gutman, New York: Macmillan, 1990.&lt;/ref&gt; In his best-selling 1912 book ''Wenn ich der Kaiser wär'' (''If I were the Kaiser''), [[Heinrich Class]], the leader of one of the more powerful ''völkisch'' groups, the ''[[Alldeutscher Verband]],'' urged that all German Jews be stripped of their German citizenship and be reduced to ''Fremdenrecht'' (alien status).&lt;ref name="Friedländer, Saul page 76"&gt;Friedländer, Saul ''Nazi Germany and the Jews: The Years of Persecution, 1933–1939'', New York: HarperCollins, 1997 page 76&lt;/ref&gt; Class went on to urge in ''Wenn ich der Kaiser wär'' that Jews be totally excluded from all aspects of German life with Class recommending that Jews be forbidden to own land, hold public office, and to participate in journalism, banking, and the liberal professions.&lt;ref name="Friedländer, Saul page 76"/&gt;

Within Germany, persecution of the Sinti and Roma (Gypsies) long preceded the Nazi regime. In 1899, Alfred Dillmann established the Central Office for Fighting the Gypsy Nuisance in Munich. This office collected information and the fingerprints of Gypsies. In 1926 in Bavaria, the ‘Law for the Combating the Gypsies, Travellers, and Work-Shy’ required the systematic registration of all Sinti and Roma, and sent Gypsies over 16 to workhouses for two years if they could not prove regular employment.   The law prohibited Gypsies from "roam[ing] about or camp[ing] in bands," and this law became the national norm in 1929.&lt;ref name="Holocaust Teacher Resource Centre"&gt;{{cite web| title =Holocaust Teacher Resource Centre| publisher= United States Holocaust Memorial Museum |url=http://www.holocaust-trc.org/sinti.htm  | accessdate= 3 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title =Timeline of Gypsies and the Holocaust A Chronology of Persecution and Mass Murder Under the Third Reich | publisher= about.com |url= http://history1900s.about.com/od/holocaust/a/Gypsies-Timeline.htm | accessdate= 3 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Toward the Nuremberg Laws==
After the First World War, the Jews of Germany were among the most assimilated in Western Europe, speaking German, as opposed to Yiddish, as their first language. Many were secular or atheistic{{Citation needed|date=May 2012}} and many had fought for Germany in the First World War.

The [[National Socialist German Workers’ Party]] (NSDAP), which had been founded in 1919 as an offshoot of the ''völkisch'' movement, adopted the movement's demands to disemancipate the Jews as its own.&lt;ref&gt;[[Martin Broszat|Broszat, Martin]] "National Socialism" pages 1033–1037 from ''The Encyclopedia of the Holocaust'' edited by [[Israel Gutman]], Volume 3, Macmilllan: New York, 1990 page 1033&lt;/ref&gt; Attacks on Jews started shortly after the Nazi [[Machtergreifung|assumption of power]] on 30 January 1933, when [[Adolf Hitler]] assumed the Chancellorship. The [[Nazi boycott of Jewish businesses]], the first nationwide stage of the anti-Semitic campaign, began on 1 April 1933.

However, the ''völkisch'' demand for laws disemancipating Jews and banning sex or marriage between "non-Aryans" and "Aryans" were not immediately met. A dispute between the Interior Ministry and the NSDAP over the precise "racial" definition of a Jew, namely how many Jewish grandparents did one have to have to be considered Jewish, led to the entire process being hopelessly bogged down by 1935.&lt;ref&gt;Mommsen, Hans "The Realization of the Unthinkable: The "Final Solution of the Jewish Question" in the Third Reich" pages 217–264 from ''The Nazi Holocaust Part 3 The "Final Solution": The Implementation of Mass Murder'' Volume 1 edited by Michael Marrus, Westpoint: Meckler, 1989 pages 222–223.&lt;/ref&gt;

The lack of a clear definition of who was a Jew confused efforts to enforce anti-Semitic laws and measures. The first Nuremberg law, nominally designed for the "prevention of the propagation of hereditary illness", did not attack Jews explicitly. Other laws claimed to preserve German blood and honour, but again were not specifically anti-Semitic.&lt;ref&gt;Sereny, Gitta. Albert Speer: His Battle with Truth. New York: Vintage, 1996. Print.&lt;/ref&gt;

The original German Gypsy policy, as it was laid during the 19th century and the beginning of the 20th century, focused on integrating Gypsies into the “ordinary” German society. However, during the Nazi regime, the same theories that were behind the Nazi idea of the Jews as an anti-race, were used to deem Gypsies as an inferior race that was a danger to the survival of the German people and the purity of the German ‘blood’.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title = The Gypsies during the Holocaust | publisher=Peter Vogelsang &amp; Brian B. M. Larsen |url=http://www.holocaust-education.dk/holocaust/sigojnerne.asp | accessdate= 3 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In July 1933, under the "Law for the Prevention of Hereditarily Diseased Offspring" physicians sterilized an unknown number of Gypsies, part-Gypsies, and Gypsies in [[Anti-miscegenation laws#Nazi Germany|mixed marriages]]. Under the "Law against Dangerous Habitual Criminals" of November 1933, the police arrested many Gypsies along with others the Nazis viewed as "asocials", and "work shy", including prostitutes, beggars, chronic alcoholics, and homeless vagrants, and imprisoned them in concentration camps.&lt;ref name="Holocaust Teacher Resource Centre"/&gt; 

During the spring and summer of 1935, many ''[[Alte Kämpfer]]'' (Old Fighters; i.e. those who joined the [[Nazi Party]] before 1930, and who tended to be the most ardent anti-Semites in the Party) and [[Sturmabteilung|SA]] members, disenchanted with unfulfilled promises by the Nazi party, were eager to lash out against Germany's Jewish minority as a way of expressing their frustrations against a group that the authorities would not generally protect.&lt;ref name="K1"&gt;''Kershaw'' pp. 560–61.&lt;/ref&gt; The German historian [[Hans Mommsen]] wrote about the ''Alte Kämpfer'' that:&lt;blockquote&gt;"After the Nazi seizure of power, those groups in the NSDAP that originated in the extreme ''völkisch'' movement—including the vast majority of the ''Alte Kämpfer''—did not become socially integrated. Many of them remained unemployed, while others failed to obtain posts commensurate with the services they believed they had rendered the movement. The social advancement that they had hoped for usually failed to materialize. This potential for protest was increasingly diverted into the sphere of Jewish policy. Many extremists in the NSDAP, influenced by envy and greed as well as by a feeling that they had been excluded from attractive positions within the higher civil service, grew even more determined to act decisively and independently in the "Jewish Question". The pressures exerted by the militant wing of the party on the state apparatus were most effective when they were in harmony with the official ideology".&lt;ref name="Mommsen pages 217-264"&gt;Mommsen, Hans "The Realization of the Unthinkable: The "Final Solution of the Jewish Question" in the Third Reich" pages 217–264 from ''The Nazi Holocaust Part 3 The "Final Solution": The Implementation of Mass Murder'' Volume 1 edited by Michael Marrus, Westpoint: Meckler, 1989 page 222&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; A ''[[Gestapo]]'' report from the spring of 1935 stated that the rank and file of the Nazi Party would set in motion a solution to the "[[Jewish problem]]" "by us from below that the government would then have to follow".&lt;ref name="K1"/&gt; The ensuing wave of assaults, vandalism and [[boycotts]] by the ''Alte Kämpfer'' and SA members against German Jews in the spring and summer of 1935 was far more violent than the anti-Semitic campaigns in the two previous years.&lt;ref name="K2"&gt;''Kershaw'' pp. 561–62.&lt;/ref&gt; As a result of this anti-Semitic agitation, these matters were raised to the forefront of the state agenda.&lt;ref&gt;Bankier, David "Nuremberg Laws" pages 1076–1077 from ''The Encyclopedia of the Holocaust'' Volume 3 edited by Israel Gutman, New York: Macmillan, 1990 page 1077.&lt;/ref&gt; The Israeli historian Otto Dov Kulka, a leading expert on public opinion in Nazi Germany argued that there was a vast disparity of views between those of the ''Alte Kämpfer'' and the general German public, but that even those Germans who were not politically active favored bringing in tougher new anti-Semitic laws in 1935.&lt;ref&gt;Marrus, Michael The Holocaust In History, Toronto: Key Porter, 2000 pages 92–93&lt;/ref&gt;

Dr. [[Hjalmar Schacht]], the Economics Minister and ''Reichsbank'' president, criticized arbitrary behavior by Party members as this inhibited his policy of developing the [[Economy of Nazi Germany|German economy]].&lt;ref name="K3"&gt;''Kershaw'' p. 563.&lt;/ref&gt; From Dr. Schacht's viewpoint, the violent anti-Semitic campaign waged by the ''Alte Kämpfer'' and SA made no economic sense, since Jews were believed to have certain entrepreneurial skills that could be usefully employed to further his policies. Schacht made no moral condemnation of anti-Jewish policy and advocated the passing of legislation to clarify the situation. Following complaints from Dr. Schacht plus reports on the public disagreement with the wave of anti-Semitic violence, Hitler ordered a stop to "individual actions" against German Jews on 8 August 1935.&lt;ref name="K3"/&gt; A conference of ministers was held on 20 August 1935 to discuss the negative economic effects of Party actions against Jews. Hitler argued that such effects would cease once the [[Nazi government|government]] decided on a firm policy against the Jews. At the same time, the Interior Minister Dr. [[Wilhelm Frick]] threatened to impose harsh penalties on those Party members who ignored the order of 8 August and continued to assault Jews.&lt;ref name="K3"/&gt; From Hitler's perspective, it was imperative to bring in harsh new anti-Semitic laws as a consolation for those Party members who were disappointed with Hitler's order of 8 August, especially because Hitler had only reluctantly given the order for pragmatic reasons, and his sympathies were with the Party radicals.&lt;ref name="K3"/&gt;

The seventh [[Nuremberg Rally|Nazi Party Rally]] was held in Nuremberg from 10–16 September 1935. It was meant to celebrate the Nazi regime's renunciation of Part V of the [[Treaty of Versailles]] in March 1935, which had disarmed Germany, hence its motto ''Party Rally of Freedom''. The rally saw the ''Reichstag'' pass the ''Reich'' Flag Law, which was Hitler’s response to the "[[SS Bremen (1929)|''Bremen'']] incident" of 26 July 1935 in New York, in which a group of anti-Nazi demonstrators boarded the ''Bremen'', tore the Nazi party flag which the ''Bremen'' had been provocatively flying from its jackstaff and tossed it into the Hudson River. When the German Consul protested, U.S. officials responded that the German national flag had not been harmed, only a political party symbol.&lt;ref&gt;Brian Leigh Davis: Flags &amp; standards of the Third Reich, Macdonald &amp; Jane's, London 1975, ISBN 0-356-04879-9&lt;/ref&gt; On 15 September 1935 Hitler declared the Nazi Swastika flag the national flag of Germany.&lt;ref name="SV"&gt;{{cite book | last = Huchthausen | first = Peter A. | authorlink = Peter Huchthausen | title = Shadow Voyage: The Extraordinary Wartime Escape of the Legendary SS Bremen | publisher=John Wiley &amp; Sons | year = 2005 | location = Hoboken, New Jersey | isbn = 0-471-45758-2 | oclc = 55764562 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | url = http://www.larkspring.com/Kid/Book2.html | first = Bill | last = Bailey | title = The kid from Hoboken: an autobiography | year = 1993 | chapterurl = http://www.larkspring.com/Kid/Book2/2-14.html | chapter = Chapter XIV: Ripping the Swastika off the Bremen | location = San Francisco | publisher=Circus Lithographic Prepress | oclc = 27835027 | accessdate =2 November 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.fotw.net/flags/de_his.html | title = Historical flags (Germany) | date = 27 December 2003 | accessdate =2 November 2007 | work=Flags of the World }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Party Rally of September 1935 had featured the first session of the ''Reichstag'' held at that city since 1543.&lt;ref name="K4"&gt;''Kershaw'' pp. 567–68.&lt;/ref&gt; Hitler had planned to have the ''Reichstag'' pass a law making the Nazi Swastika flag the flag of the German ''Reich'', and a major speech in support of the impending Italian aggression against Ethiopia.&lt;ref name="K4" /&gt; However, at the last minute, the German Foreign Minister Baron [[Konstantin von Neurath]] persuaded Hitler to cancel his speech as being too provocative to public opinion abroad as it blatantly contradicted the message of Hitler's "peace speeches", thus leaving Hitler with the sudden need to have something else to address the historic first meeting of the ''Reichstag'' in Nuremberg since 1543, other than the ''Reich'' Flag Law.&lt;ref name="K4"/&gt; Hitler's need for something to present to the ''Reichstag'' was especially acute as he had invited all of the senior foreign diplomats in Berlin to the Party Rally of 1935 to hear what was billed as an especially important speech on foreign policy.&lt;ref name="Mommsen pages 217-264"&gt;Mommsen, Hans "The Realization of the Unthinkable: The "Final Solution of the Jewish Question" in the Third Reich" pages 217–264 from ''The Nazi Holocaust Part 3 The "Final Solution": The Implementation of Mass Murder'' Volume 1 edited by Michael Marrus, Westpoint: Meckler, 1989 page 223&lt;/ref&gt;

On 12 September 1935, two days after the beginning of the party rally, leading Nazi physician [[Gerhard Wagner (Nazi physician)|Gerhard Wagner]] surprisingly announced in a speech that the Nazi government would soon introduce a "law for the protection of German blood" to prevent mixed marriages between Jews and "Aryans" in the future. Hitler immediately decided to extend the legal scope. On 13 September, Dr. Bernhard Lösener, the Interior Ministry official in charge of drafting anti-Semitic laws together with another Interior Ministry official, ''Ministerialrat'' (Ministerial Counsellor) Franz Albrecht Medicus, was hastily summoned to the Nuremberg Party Rally by plane by Dr. [[Wilhelm Stuckart]], the State Secretary of the Interior Ministry, and directed to start drafting at once a law for Hitler to present to the ''Reichstag'' for 15 September.&lt;ref name="K5"&gt;''Kershaw'' p. 567.&lt;/ref&gt; Lösener and Medicus arrived in Nuremberg on the morning of 14 September.

Because of the short time available for the drafting of the laws, both measures were hastily improvised—there was even a shortage of drafting paper so that menu cards had to be used instead.&lt;ref name="K6"&gt;''Kershaw'' pp. 568–70 &amp; 759–60.&lt;/ref&gt; Such was the degree of improvisation that [[Franz Gürtner]], the Justice Minister, first learned of the adoption of the laws from listening to the radio.&lt;ref name="Mommsen pages 217-264"/&gt; Most of the debates about the drafting of the laws concerned a precise definition of what constituted a Jew in Nazi "racial" terms, i.e. how many Jewish grandparents one had to have in order to qualify as Jewish under Nazi racial theories.&lt;ref name="K6"&gt;''Kershaw'' pp. 568–70&lt;/ref&gt;

Hitler himself spent the night of 14–15 September hesitant and indecisive over just which of the various definitions of a Jew to adopt, and finally excused himself from the debate.&lt;ref name= "Mommsen pages 217-264"/&gt; On 15 September, Hitler presented the laws drafted by Stuckart, Lösener and Medicus to the ''Reichstag''.

==Introduction==
On the evening of 15 September 1935, two measures were announced to the ''Reichstag'' at the annual [[Nuremberg Rally|Party Rally]] in Nuremberg, becoming known as the Nuremberg Laws.&lt;ref name="K4"/&gt;

The first law, '''The Law for the Protection of German Blood and German Honour''',&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ess.uwe.ac.uk/documents/gerblood.htm Nuremberg Law for the Protection of German Blood and German Honor], English translation at the University of the West of England&lt;/ref&gt; prohibited [[Rassenschande|marriages and extramarital intercourse]] between "Jews" (the name was now officially used in place of "non-Aryans") and "Germans" and also the employment of "German" females under forty-five in Jewish households. The second law, '''The Reich Citizenship Law''',&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ess.uwe.ac.uk/documents/citizen.htm Reich Citizenship Law], English translation at the University of the West of England&lt;/ref&gt; declared those not of German blood to be ''Staatsangehörige'' (state subjects) while those classified as "Aryans" were ''Reichsbürger'' (citizens of the ''Reich'').&lt;ref name="ReferenceA"&gt;Bankier, David "Nuremberg Laws" pages 1076–1077 from ''The Encyclopedia of the Holocaust'' Volume 3 edited by Israel Gutman, New York: Macmillan, 1990 page 1076&lt;/ref&gt; Between November 1935 to July 1943, 13 implementation ordinances were issued dealing with the enforcement of ''Reich'' Citizenship Law that progressively marginalized the Jewish community in Germany.&lt;ref name="ReferenceA"/&gt;

Hitler appeared before the ''Reichstag'' in Nuremberg, introducing the laws and their alleged motivation, before the laws were formally read and proposed for adoption by [[Hermann Göring]], the President of the Reichstag. In his speech he laid out his case for the new laws:

{{bquote|...Bitter complaints have come in from countless places citing the provocative behavior of Jews....a certain amount of [conspiratorial] planning was involved....[To prevent] vigorous defensive action by the [Aryan] people,&lt;ref&gt;It was a standard tactic of Hitler's to transfer the blame for his aggressive actions onto his adversary so that his action was simply a "defensive" one.&lt;/ref&gt; we have no choice but to contain the problem through legislative measures....it may be possible, through a definitive secular solution, to create a basis on which the German people can have a tolerable relationship with the Jews.&lt;ref&gt;Even a cursory review of ''[[Mein Kampf]]'' and Hitler's speeches before 1935 would make it clear to anyone that this prospect of "hope of toleration" extended by Hitler is a blatant lie. ''See also'' ''Kershaw'' p. 565.&lt;/ref&gt; ... This law is an attempt to find a legislative solution....if this attempts fails, it will be necessary to transfer [the Jewish problem] ... to the National Socialist Party for a final solution by law ({{lang-de|link=no|endgültige Lösung}}).&lt;ref&gt;The ominous term "[[final solution]]" did not yet, in ordinary discourse in 1935, necessarily entail the complete eradication of European or World Jewry. Neither did it exclude that possibility.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

The measures were unanimously adopted by the ''Reichstag''. In 12 years of Nazi rule, the ''Reichstag'' only passed four laws: the Nuremberg laws were two of them.&lt;ref&gt;''Shirer'' p. 234n. Most laws in the Nazi state were simply decreed by Hitler under powers vested in him by the [[Enabling Act of 1933]]; there was no legal need for the "legislature" here, and having the ''Reichstag'' adopt these laws at the party rally was done for propaganda purposes. ''Kershaw'' p. 268-75.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Nuremberg Laws formalized the unofficial and particular measures taken against Jews up to 1935. The Nazi leaders made a point of stressing the consistency of this legislation with the [[National Socialist Program|Party programme]], which demanded that Jews should be deprived of their [[citizenship]] rights.

==Laws==
;The Laws for the Protection of German Blood and German Honour

{{Quote|
(5 September 1935)
Moved by the understanding that the purity of German blood is essential to the further existence of the German people, and inspired by the uncompromising determination to safeguard the future of the German nation, the Reichstag has unanimously resolved upon the following law, which is promulgated herewith:

; Section 1
:#Marriages between Jews and citizens ({{lang-de|link=no|Staatsangehörige}}) of German or kindred blood are forbidden. Marriages concluded in defiance of this law are void, even if, for the purpose of evading this law, they were concluded abroad.
:#Proceedings for annulment may be initiated only by the [[Public Prosecutor]].
; Section 2
:[[Rassenschande|Extramarital sexual intercourse between Jews and subjects of the state of Germany or related blood is forbidden]].
:::*''(This concept was unofficially termed [[Rassenschande]] - 'defilement of blood'. Supplementary decrees set Nazi definitions of racial Germans, Jews, and half-breeds or [[Mischling]]e --- see the latter entry for details and citations and [[Mischling Test]] for how such decrees were applied. Jews could not vote or hold public office under the parallel "citizenship" law.)''
; Section 3
: Jews will not be permitted to employ female citizens under the age of 45, of German or kindred blood, as [[domestic worker]]s.
; Section 4
:#Jews are forbidden to display the [[Reich]] and [[national flag]] or the [[national colours]].
:#On the other hand they are permitted to display the Jewish colours. The exercise of this right is protected by the State.
; Section 5
:#A person who acts contrary to the prohibition of Section 1 will be punished with [[hard labour]].
:#A person who acts contrary to the prohibition of Section 2 will be punished with [[imprisonment]] or with hard labour.
:#A person who acts contrary to the provisions of Sections 3 or 4 will be punished with imprisonment up to a year and with a [[fine (penalty)|fine]], or with one of these penalties.
; Section 6
: The Reich Minister of the Interior in agreement with the Deputy Führer and the Reich [[Minister of Justice]] will issue the legal and administrative regulations required for the enforcement and supplementing of this law.
; Section 7
: The law will become effective on the day after its promulgation; Section 3, however, not until 1 January 1936.
}}

==Effect==
[[File:German Jewish Passport.jpg|left|thumb|201px|German Jewish passports could be used to leave, but not to return.]]
{{See also|Anti-Jewish legislation in prewar Nazi Germany}}

Legal discrimination against Jews had come into being before the Nuremberg Laws and steadily grew as time went on; however, for discrimination to be effective, it was essential to have a clear definition of who was or was not a Jew. This was one important function of the Nuremberg laws and the numerous supplementary decrees that were proclaimed to further them.

The ''Reich'' Citizenship Law had little practical effect as it deprived German Jews only of the right to vote and hold office.&lt;ref name="ReferenceB"&gt;Mommsen, Hans "The Realization of the Unthinkable: The "Final Solution of the Jewish Question" in the Third Reich" pages 217–264 from ''The Nazi Holocaust Part 3 The "Final Solution": The Implementation of Mass Murder'' Volume 1 edited by Michael Marrus, Westpoint: Meckler, 1989 page 224&lt;/ref&gt; Much to the fury of the ''Alte Kämpfer'' and the other radicals in the NSDAP, the recommendation from the Interior Ministry that the ''Reich'' Citizenship Law applied only to those classified as "full Jews" and those "half-Jews" who practiced Judaism or were not in a mixed marriage was taken up; those ''Mischling'' who were Christians or were in a mixed marriage retained their German citizenship.&lt;ref name="ReferenceB"/&gt; The NSDAP had wanted the ''Reich'' Citizenship Law to apply to "Grade 1 and Grade 2 persons of mixed descent".&lt;ref name="ReferenceB"/&gt; The suggestion of Dr. Frick for creation of a tribunal before which every German would have to prove that they were Aryans in order to keep their German citizenship was not followed.&lt;ref name="ReferenceB"/&gt; Because of this, the Nuremberg Laws were highly unpopular with the Party radicals.&lt;ref name="ReferenceB"/&gt; [[Joseph Goebbels]] had the radio broadcast recording the passing of the laws by the ''Reichstag'' cut short, and ordered the German media not to mention the laws until a way of implementing them had been found.&lt;ref name="ReferenceC"&gt;Mommsen, Hans "The Realization of the Unthinkable: The "Final Solution of the Jewish Question" in the Third Reich" pages 217–264 from ''The Nazi Holocaust Part 3 The "Final Solution": The Implementation of Mass Murder'' Volume 1 edited by Michael Marrus, Westpoint: Meckler, 1989 page 225&lt;/ref&gt; At a secret conference held in Munich on 24 September to finally resolve the dispute over who was a "racial" Jew or who was a "half-Jew", Hitler accepted Lösener's less sweeping definitions of three or four Jewish grandparents, and ruled that the laws were not to apply to those ''Mischling'' who were Christians and to "Grade 2 persons of mixed descent".&lt;ref name ="ReferenceC"/&gt; However immediately afterwards in a meeting with [[Martin Bormann]], Hitler declared that paragraph six of the First Ordinance of the Reich Citizenship Law was not to be applied in practice, and instead accepted Bormann's suggestion of excluding ''Mischling'' from a whole host of German institutions such as the [[German Labour Front|DAF]].&lt;ref name="ReferenceC"/&gt;

People defined as Jews could then be barred from employment as lawyers, doctors or journalists. Jews were prohibited from using state hospitals and could not be educated by the state past the age of 14. Public parks, libraries and beaches were closed to Jews. War memorials were to have Jewish names expunged. Even the lottery could not award winnings to Jews.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Examples of Antisemitic Legislation, 1933–1939|publisher=United States Holocaust Memorial Museum no|url= http://www.ushmm.org/wlc/article.php?lang=en&amp;ModuleId=10007459|accessdate=12 July 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;
With the so-called ''Namensänderungsverordnung'' ("Regulation of Name Changes") of 17 August 1938, Jews with first names of non-Jewish origin were required to adopt a middle name: "Sara" for women and "Israel" for men. At the instigation of Swiss immigration official Heinrich Rothmund, passports of German Jews were required to have a large "J" stamped on them and could be used to leave Germany—but not to return.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The Nuremberg Race Laws|publisher=United States Holocaust Memorial Museum|url=http://www.ushmm.org/outreach/nlaw.htm|accessdate=12 July 2008 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080424000601/http://www.ushmm.org/outreach/nlaw.htm |archivedate = 24 April 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The obligation to wear the [[yellow badge]], introduced in [[German occupation of Poland|German-occupied Poland]] in September 1939, was extended to all Jewish people living within the Nazi empire in September 1941.

Later the death penalty was applied under the ''Law for the Protection of German Blood and Honour''. For example, in a Nuremberg a Jewish businessman named Leo Kazenberger was accused of having a sexual relationship with a younger German woman. He was denounced and arrested but he and his alleged girlfriend denied the charges. The case was heard by [[Oswald Rothaug]] who, according to many observers, used the case as an opportunity for getting noticed by Hitler. Under wartime law when a crime had been committed during [[Blackout (wartime)|blackout]] hours death penalty could be applied. Kazenberger was sentenced to death and [[guillotine]]d on 2 June 1942.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.duhaime.org/LawMuseum/LawArticle-1180/oswald-rothaug.aspx Oswald Rothaug]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Application of the Laws to other non Jewish groups==
A supplemental decree issued in November 1935 expanded the Blood Protection Law to include additional groups, specifically Romani and Negroes, that were considered to be a threat to German blood. The interpretation of "racially alien blood" was further expanded in subsequent decrees, which included special categories for Germans with mental and genetic deformities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Nuremberg Laws|publisher=enotes.com| url=http://www.enotes.com/nuremberg-laws-reference/nuremberg-laws|accessdate=30 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;     

The legal and administrative machinery necessary to enforce the Reich Citizenship Law fell under the jurisdiction of Reich Minister of the Interior William Frick, who expanded the law's reach to "members of other races whose blood is not related to German blood, as, for example, Gypsies and Negroes."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Nuremberg Laws|publisher=enotes.com| url=http://www.enotes.com/nuremberg-laws-reference/nuremberg-laws| accessdate=30 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Criteria defining who was a Gypsy were exactly twice as strict as those defining any other group.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=A Brief Romani Holocaust Chronology|publisher=Roma ParticipationProgramme| url=http://www.osi.hu/rpp/holocaust.html| accessdate=30 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Nazi Eugenics and Racial belief==

{{Main|Nazi eugenics|Nazism and race}}
The Nuremberg laws were based on a belief in [[Scientific racism]] and derived from a primitive understanding of [[genetics]]. Although the Nazis took these ideas to violent extremes, they were based on thinking that already existed across Europe and America. Nazi laws banning "inter-marriage" assumed that nations were "races" and that [[Aryan race|Aryans]] were a [[Master race]] and in accordance with ideas expressed in [[Eugenics]] and [[Social Darwinism]];&lt;ref&gt;Science in the early twentieth century: an encyclopaedia by Jacob Darwin Hamblin 2005, page 104&lt;/ref&gt; they therefore sought to preserve their supposed racial superiority by banning inter-marriage with people they regarded as inferior or as a threat, in particular Jews and Gypsies.&lt;ref&gt;See the Nazi post at http://www2.facinghistory.org/Campus/rm.nsf/61A7F88FF16FBD9585256E8E001178AC/F71118D32CED30AB8525718000570CB1?OpenDocument, See also http://www.thebreman.org/exhibitions/online/1000kids/racialtheory.html,
The Nuremberg Laws by Amy Newman page 43&lt;/ref&gt;

==Impact outside Germany==

Allies of the Nazis passed their own versions of the Nuremberg laws including [[Law for protection of the nation|The Law for Protection of the Nation]] in Bulgaria, in 1940 the ruling [[Iron Guard]] in Romania passed the Law defining the Legal Status of Romanian Jews,&lt;ref&gt;The Routledge History of the Holocaust page 279&lt;/ref&gt; in 1941 the Codex Judaicus was enacted in Slovakia&lt;ref&gt;A history of Slovakia: the struggle for survival by Stanislav J. Kirschbaum page 197&lt;/ref&gt; and in 1941 the [[Ustasha]] in Croatia also passed legislation defining who was a Jew and restricting contact with them.&lt;ref&gt;Serbia's Secret War: Propaganda and the Deceit of History by Philip J. Cohen,David Riesman&lt;/ref&gt; Hungary passed its first "Jewish Law" in May 1938 banning Jews from various professions; further laws emulating the Nuremberg regulations were added in 1941.&lt;ref&gt;The Routledge History of the Holocaust page 250&lt;/ref&gt;

==Existing copies==
An original typescript of the laws signed by Hitler was found by the 203rd Detachment of the [[Counterintelligence Corps (United States Army)|U.S. Army's Counter-Intelligence Corps]] (CIC), commanded by [[Martin Dannenberg]], in [[Eichstätt]], Bavaria, on 27 April 1945. It was appropriated by General [[George S. Patton]], in violation of [[Morgenthau Plan#JCS 1067|JCS 1067]]. During a visit to Los Angeles, he secretly handed it over to the [[The Huntington Library|Huntington Library]]. The document was stored until 26 June 1999, when its existence was revealed. Although legal ownership of the document has not been established, it was given on permanent loan to the [[Skirball Cultural Center]], which placed it on public display three days later, until the document's transfer to the [[National Archives and Records Administration|National Archives]] in Washington D.C. on 25 August 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/newstopics/world-war-2/7964839/Nuremberg-Laws-handed-over-to-US-National-Archives.html| title =Nuremberg Laws handed over to US National Archives|publisher=Daily Telegraph, UK|date=26 August 2010|accessdate=26 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Hans Globke]]
*[[Nazism and race]]
*[[Aryan paragraph]]
*[[Manifesto of Race]] in Italy
*[[Jim Crow Laws]]
*[[Apartheid]]
*[[Reichstag Fire Decree]]
*[[Visigothic Code]]

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==Further reading==
{{Refbegin}}
*Banker, David "The 'Jewish Question' as a Focus of Conflict Between Trends of Institutionalization and Radicalization in the Third Reich, 1934–1935" pages 357–371 from ''In Nation and History: Studies in the History of the Jewish People; Based on the Papers Delivered at the Eight World Congress of Jewish Studies'', Volume 2 edited by Samuel Ettinger, Jerusalem, 1984.
*Bankier, David "Nuremberg Laws" pages 1076–1077 from the ''[[Encyclopedia of the Holocaust]]'' Volume 3 edited by [[Israel Gutman]], New York: Macmillan, 1990, ISBN 0-02-864527-8.
*Ehrenreich, Eric. ''The Nazi Ancestral Proof: Genealogy, Racial Science, and the Final Solution''. Bloomington, IN: Indiana University Press, 2007. ISBN 978-0-253-34945-3
*{{cite book | last = Fest| first = Joachim C. | title = Hitler | author-link=Joachim C. Fest| publisher=Houghton Mifflin Harcourt | year = 2002 | isbn = 0-15-602754-2}}
*{{cite book | last = Fischer | first = Conan | title = The Rise of the Nazis| publisher=Manchester University Press | year = 2002 |author-link=| isbn = 0-7190-6067-2}}
*Gruchmann, L. "'Blutschutzgestz' und Justiz: Zur Entstehung und Auswirkung des Nürnberger Gesetzes von 15 September 1935" pages 418–442 from ''Vierteljahrshefte für Zeitgeschichte'', Volume 31, 1983.
*{{cite book |last=Kershaw|first=Ian|isbn = 0-393-04671-0 |author-link=Ian Kershaw|title= Hitler 1889–1936: Hubris|location=New York|publisher=W. W. Norton &amp; Company|year=1999 }}
*Kulka, Otto Dov "Die Nürnberger Rassengesetze und die deutsche Bevölkerugn um Lichte geheimer NS-Lage und Stimmungsberichte" pages 582–624 from ''Vierteljahrshefte für Zeitgeschichte'', Volume 32, 1984.
*Margaliot, A. "The Reaction of the Jewish Public in Germany to the Nuremberg Laws" pages 193–229 from ''Vad Yashem Studies'', Volume 12, 1977.
*Mommsen, Hans "The Realization of the Unthinkable: The "Final Solution of the Jewish Question" in the Third Reich" pages 217–264 from ''The Nazi Holocaust Part 3 The "Final Solution": The Implementation of Mass Murder'' Volume 1 edited by [[Michael Marrus]], Westpoint: Meckler, 1989, ISBN 0-88736-266-4.
*Schleunes, Karl ''The Twisted Road to Auschwitz: Nazi Policy towards German Jews, 1933–1939'', Urbana, Ill, 1970.
*{{cite book | last = Shirer | first = William L. | title = The Rise and Fall of the Third Reich| author-link = William L. Shirer | publisher=Simon &amp; Schuster| location = New York | year = 1960 }}
*{{cite book | last = Toland | first = John | title = Adolf Hitler | author-link=John Toland (author)| publisher=Doubleday &amp; Company | year = 1976 | location = Garden City, New York | isbn = 0-385-03724-4 }}
{{Refend}}

==External links==
*[http://www1.yadvashem.org/yv/en/holocaust/about/01/persecution.asp?WT.mc_id=wiki Rise of the Nazis and Beginning of Persecution] on the [[Yad Vashem]] website
*[http://www.mtsu.edu/~baustin/nurmlaw2.html The Citizenship Law, together with Supplementary Decree of 14 November 1935]
*[http://www.ess.uwe.ac.uk/documents/citizen.htm The Citizenship Law], English translation at the University of the West of England
*[http://www.ess.uwe.ac.uk/documents/gerblood.htm The Blood Law], English translation at the University of the West of England
*[http://www.shoaheducation.com/pNEW.html#race Race Laws] (Nazi and other)
*[http://www.ushmm.org/wlc/article.php?lang=en&amp;ModuleId=10007459 Info from Holocaust Museum]
*[http://www.ushmm.org/wlc/article.php?lang=en&amp;ModuleId=10007459 Nazi Race Laws to 1939]
*[http://www.passportland.com/images/lewin-simon/lewin-simon.html Images of a 1938 German "J" Jewish passport] from www.passportland.com

{{The Holocaust (end)}}
{{Segregation by type|state=collapsed}}
{{Nationality laws}}

[[Category:1935 in Germany]]
[[Category:1935 in law]]
[[Category:Antisemitism]]
[[Category:History of nationality]]
[[Category:Holocaust racial laws]]
[[Category:Jewish German history]]
[[Category:Nazi eugenics]]
[[Category:Law in Nazi Germany]]
[[Category:Race-related legal issues]]
[[Category:Religion and race]]
[[Category:Repealed German legislation]]

[[bg:Нюрнбергски закони]]
[[ca:Lleis de Nuremberg]]
[[cs:Norimberské zákony]]
[[cy:Deddfau Nuremberg]]
[[da:Nürnberglovene]]
[[de:Nürnberger Gesetze]]
[[el:Νόμοι της Νυρεμβέργης]]
[[es:Leyes de Núremberg]]
[[eo:Nurenbergaj leĝoj]]
[[fa:قوانین نورنبرگ]]
[[fr:Lois de Nuremberg]]
[[ga:Dlíthe Nürnberg]]
[[ko:뉘른베르크 법]]
[[hi:नुरेम्बर्ग कानून]]
[[hr:Nürnberški zakoni]]
[[id:Undang-Undang Nuremberg]]
[[he:חוקי נירנברג]]
[[hu:Nürnbergi törvények]]
[[mr:न्युर्नबर्ग कायदे]]
[[nl:Rassenwetten van Neurenberg]]
[[ja:ニュルンベルク法]]
[[no:Nürnberglovene]]
[[pl:Ustawy norymberskie]]
[[pt:Leis de Nuremberg]]
[[ro:Legile de la Nürnberg]]
[[ru:Нюрнбергские расовые законы]]
[[simple:Nuremberg Laws]]
[[sk:Norimberské zákony]]
[[sr:Нирнбершки закони]]
[[fi:Nürnbergin lait]]
[[sv:Nürnberglagarna]]
[[tr:Nürnberg Yasaları]]
[[yi:נירנבערג געזעצן]]
[[zh:纽伦堡法案]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>