<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061031091042|84803514" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="3191713" pageid="3191713" ns="0" title="Nuremberg Laws"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-10-31T18:11:05Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Mergefrom|Reich Citizenship Law|date=September 2006}}
[[Image:Nurembergracechart.jpg|thumb|250px|1935 chart from [[Nazi Germany]] used to explain the Nuremberg Laws]]

The Nazi '''[[Nuremberg]] Laws''' of [[1935]] were [[Denaturalization|denaturalization laws]] passed by the government of [[Nazi Germany]]. They used a [[pseudoscience|pseudoscientific]] basis for [[Racial policy of Nazi Germany|racial discrimination against Jews]]. People with four German grandparents (white circles on the chart) were of "German blood", while people were classified as Jews if they descended from three or more Jewish grandparents (black circles in top row right). One or two Jewish grandparents made someone "mixed blood."   The Nazis used the religious observance of a person's grandparents to determine their race.


== History ==

A conference of ministers was held on [[August 20]], [[1935]], to discuss the economic effects of Party actions against Jews. [[Adolf Wagner]], the Party representative at the conference, argued that such actions would cease, once the [[government]] decided on a firm policy against the Jews. 

[[Hjalmar Schacht|Dr. Schacht]], the [[Economics Minister]], criticized arbitrary behavior by Party members as this inhibited his policy of rebuilding Germany's [[economy]]. It made no economic sense since Jews were believed to have certain entrepreneurial skills that could be usefully employed to further his policies. Schacht made no moral condemnation of Jewish policy and advocated the passing of legislation to clarify the situation. The following month two measures were announced at the annual [[Party Rally]] in Nuremberg, becoming known as the Nuremberg Laws. Both measures were hastily improvised (there was even a shortage of drafting paper so that menu cards had to be used) and Jewish experts from the [[Ministry of the Interior]] were ordered to Nuremberg by plane. 

The first law, '''The Law for the Protection of German Blood and German Honor,'''  prohibited marriages and extra-marital intercourse between “Jews” (the name was now officially used in place of “non-Aryans”) and “Germans” and also the employment of “German” females under forty-five in Jewish [[household]]s. The second law, '''The Reich Citizenship Law''', stripped Jews of their German [[citizenship]] and introduced a new distinction between “Reich [[citizen]]s” and “nationals.” 

The Nuremberg Laws by their general nature formalized the unofficial and particular measures taken against Jews up to [[1935]]. The Nazi leaders made a point of stressing the consistency of this legislation with the Party program which demanded that Jews should be deprived of their rights as citizens.

== Law for the Protection of German Blood and German Honour ==

([[September 15]], [[1935]])

Entirely convinced that the purity of German blood is essential to the further existence of the German people, and inspired by the uncompromising determination to safeguard the future of the German nation, the Reichstag has unanimously resolved upon the following law, which is promulgated herewith:

===Section 1===

#[[Marriage]]s between Jews and citizens of German or kindred blood are forbidden. Marriages concluded in defiance of this law are void, even if, for the purpose of evading this law, they were concluded abroad.
#Proceedings for annulment may be initiated only by the [[Public Prosecutor]].

===Section 2===

The laws deprived Jews of German citizenship and forbade marriage or sexual relations between Jews and “citizens of German or cognate blood.” Supplementary decrees defined a Jew as a person with at least one Jewish grandparent and declared that Jews could not vote or hold public office

===Section 3===
Jews will not be permitted to employ female citizens of German or kindred blood as [[domestic worker]]s under the age of 45.

===Section 4===

#Jews are forbidden to display the Reich and [[national flag]] or the [[national colors]]. 
#On the other hand they are permitted to display the [[Jewish colors]]. The exercise of this right is protected by the State.

As J. Boas notes in "German-Jewish Internal Politics under Hitler" (see [http://history-of-the-holocaust.org/LIBARC/LIBRARY/Themes/Jews/Boas.html]), the "Jewish colors" referred to in this article were actually the Blue-and-White [[Zionist]] banner which is presently the national flag of [[Israel]].

===Section 5===

#A person who acts contrary to the prohibition of Section 1 will be punished with [[hard labour]]. 
#A person who acts contrary to the prohibition of Section 2 will be punished with [[imprisonment]] or with hard labour. 
#A person who acts contrary to the provisions of Sections 3 or 4 will be punished with imprisonment up to a year and with a [[fine]], or with one of these penalties .

===Section 6===

The Reich Minister of the Interior in agreement with the Deputy Fuhrer and the Reich [[Minister of Justice]] will issue the legal and administrative regulations required for the enforcement and supplementing of this law.

===Section 7===

The law will become effective on the day after its promulgation; Section 3, however, not until [[January 1]], [[1936]].

== The Reich Citizenship Law ==
([[September 15]], [[1935]])

The Reich Citizenship Law stripped Jews of their German citizenship and introduced a new distinction between “Reich citizens ” and “nationals.” Certificates of Reich citizenship were in fact never introduced, and all Germans other than Jews were provisionally classed as Reich citizens until [[1945]].

===Article 1===

#A subject of the State is a person who belongs to the protective union of the German Reich, and who therefore has particular obligations towards the Reich. 
#The status of subject is acquired in accordance with the provisions of the Reich and State Law of Citizenship. 

===Article 2===

#A citizen of the Reich is that subject only who is of German or kindred blood and who, through his conduct, shows that he is both desirous and fit to serve the German people and Reich faithfully. 
#The right to citizenship is acquired by the granting of Reich citizenship papers. 
#Only the citizen of the Reich enjoys full political rights in accordance with the provision of the laws. 

===Article 3===

The Reich Minister of the Interior in conjunction with the Deputy of the Führer will issue the necessary legal and administrative decrees for carrying out and supplementing this law.

==See also==
*[[Mischling]]
*[[Rhineland Bastards]]
*[[German Blood Certificate]]
*[[The Reich Citizenship Law]]
*[[Racial policy of Nazi Germany]]
*[[Useful Jew]]
*[[Limpieza de sangre]]
*[[Second-class citizen]]
*[[T-4 Euthanasia Program]]
*[[Nazi eugenics]]

==External links==
*[http://www.shoaheducation.com/pNEW.html#race Race Laws]

[[cs:Norimberské zákony]]
[[de:Nürnberger Rassegesetze]]
[[es:Leyes de Núremberg]]
[[fr:Lois de Nuremberg]]
[[he:חוקי נירנברג]]
[[pl:Ustawy norymberskie]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>