<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20051112162313|28123104" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="25613" pageid="25613" ns="0" title="Racism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-11-12T16:23:53Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[Image:ColoredDrinking.jpg|thumb|250px|A black man drinks out of a water fountain designated for black people in 1939 at a streetcar terminal.]]

'''Racism''' refers to the beliefs and practices that assume inherent and significant differences exist between the genetics of various groups of human beings; that assume these differences can be measured on a scale of "superior" to "inferior"; and that result in the social, political and economic advantage of one group in relation to others. 

In general, a racist practices the separation of groups according to race, and considers one's own race the most valuable and others less valuable. The belief that the character and abilities of individuals are correlated with their [[race]] is not necessarily racism, since this can be asserted without implying an inequality in value. The application of this belief in dealing with members of that race, especially with little regard for variations within "races", is known as '''racial [[prejudice]]'''. Granting or withholding [[right]]s or [[privilege]]s based on race or refusing to associate with persons based on race is racial [[discrimination]].

Racism has historically been defined as the belief that race is the primary determinant of human capacities, that a certain race is inherently superior or inferior to others, and/or that individuals should be treated differently according to their racial designation. Sometimes ''racism'' means beliefs, practices, and institutions that discriminate against people based on their perceived or ascribed race. There is a growing, but somewhat controversial, opinion that racism is a ''system'' of oppression -- a nexus of racist beliefs, whether explicit, tacit or unconscious; practices; organizations and institutions that combine to discriminate against and societally marginalize a class of people who share a common racial designation, based on that designation.

Some believe that the term also is often used incorrectly by supporters of [[cultural relativism]] and [[political correctness]] to stigmatise their adversaries due to the association between racism and extreme violence in parts of the twentieth century.

Since the last quarter of the [[20th century]], there have been few in [[developed nation]]s who describe themselves as ''racist'', so that identification of a group or person as ''racist'' is nearly always controversial. Racism is regarded by many as an affront to basic human dignity and a violation of [[human rights]]. A number of international treaties have sought to end racism. The [[United Nations]] uses a definition of '''racist discrimination''' laid out in the ''International Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Racial Discrimination'' and adopted in [[1966]]:

&lt;blockquote&gt;...any distinction, exclusion, restriction or preference based on race, colour, descent, or national or ethnic origin which has the purpose or effect of nullifying or impairing the recognition, enjoyment or exercise, on an equal footing, of human rights and fundamental freedoms in the political, economic, social, cultural or any other field of public life. [http://www.unhchr.ch/html/menu3/b/d_icerd.htm]&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==From "racial theory" to "racism"==

Before considering ''racism'', it is an important methodological point to distinguish historically when the concept of "racism" became known as such. Historians disagree largely when "race" emerged as a concept, ranging from those who believe aspects of it have always existed among humans, to those who place it as a concept separate from general distrust of "difference" (in which case it emerged either in the [[Age of Exploration]] or even as late as the [[19th century]]). In any event, the division of people into discrete groups, usually based on external anatomical features or assumed geographic origin, and theories about how many "races" there were, and theories of how to "rank" these races against each other, existed long before they acquired any sort of distinct stigma against them.  Fear of sexual relations between Colored men and White women was central to the tenets of racism. During the late-19th century, a number of thinkers emphasized that these views were morally and ethically unjust, but this was a significantly minority opinion. Even those who opposed institutions such as [[slavery]] often did so not on the basis of equality of races, but on overall equality ''in treatment'' of "mankind".  

In the [[20th century]], however, there began a growth of thought that theories of racial "superiority" and "inferiority" were inherently problematic and wrong. Much of the discourse relating to racial theory of this sort came out of the [[United States]] in the years after the [[American Civil War]], while European thinkers began to think of people in terms of linguistic "nations" more than they did "races." The term "racism", according to the [[Oxford English Dictionary]], emerged in the early [[1930s]] as distinct from the "theories of race" which had existed for at least a hundred years before that. 

A turning point in racial thinking came with the rise of [[Adolf Hitler]]'s [[Nazism]], which built much of its political agenda upon the rhetoric of [[anti-Semitism]] and overt statements of racial superiority and inferiority. Full opposition to these ideas did not begin until the outbreak of [[World War II]], and a large part of [[Allied]] [[propaganda]] efforts were in labeling Nazi Germany as a "racist" state, and distinguishing their own states from them. By the end of the war, the association of racism with the Nazis, and the [[genocide|genocidal]] policies they undertook, thoroughly established the [[meme]] that "racism" was something to be opposed. In the United States, the experience of the [[Civil Rights Movement]] further emphasized this point. Now, "racism" is seen as something entirely to be opposed by almost all mainstream voices, though there is little agreement over what is "racism". It is worth remembering this, when looking at current concepts of "racism". In hindsight, many eminent scientists, philosophers, and statesmen appear "racist" by late-20th century standards, though the recognition of the historical nature of these judgements is deemed by many to ''exonerate'' these figures or governments for their ideas or actions.

== Origins of racism ==

One view of the origins of racism emphasizes [[stereotype]]s, which [[psychologist]]s generally believe are influenced by cultural factors. People generally respond to others differently based on what they know, which may include superficial characteristics often associated with [[race]].  A "[[Caucasian race|white]]" person walking after dark in a primarily "[[African-American|black]]" neighborhood in an American city might be anxious for a combination of reasons.  The same may be said for an [[African-American]] walking in a white neighborhood. A police officer who spends most of his day in that same city encountering criminality or hostility among people of a certain [[ethnic]] background might be expected to react negatively to a member of that same ethnic group whom he meets off-duty. A law-abiding [[African-American]] man is less likely than a law-abiding white man to view that same police officer as an ally and protector, and more as a threat to his or her personal safety and well-being.  In both sets of cases, theories of [[conditioning]] may apply.

Debates over the origins of racism often suffer from a lack of clarity over the term.  Many use the term "racism" to refer to more general phenomena, such as [[xenophobia]] and [[ethnocentrism]].  Others conflate recent forms of racism with earlier forms of ethnic and national conflict.  In most cases, ethno-national conflict seems to owe to conflict over land and strategic resources.  In some cases [[ethnicity]] and [[nationalism]] were harnessed to rally [[combatant]]s in wars between great religious empires (for example, the Muslim Turks and the Catholic Austro-Hungarians).  As [[Benedict Anderson]] has suggested in ''Imagined Communities'', ethnic identity and ethno-nationalism became a source of conflict within such empires with the rise of [[print-capitalism]].

Notions of race and racism, however, often have played central roles in such conflicts.  Historically, when an adversary is identified as "other" based on notions of race or ethnicity (particularly when "other" is construed to mean "inferior"), the means employed by the self-presumed "superior" party to appropriate territory, human chattel, or material wealth often have been more ruthless, more brutal, and less constrained by [[morality|moral]] or [[ethics|ethical]] considerations.  Indeed, based on such racist presumptions, the political or moral decision to enter into armed conflict can be made less weighty when one's potential adversaries are "other than," because their lives are perceived as having lesser importance, lesser value.  In history, some examples of the brutalizing and dehumanizing effects of racism, are:  the trading of [[Population_history_of_American_indigenous_peoples#Note_re_disease:_smallpox_blanket_incident|smallpox-infested blankets]] among Native Americans as a biological weapon in order to reduce their population.

In the western world, racism evolved, twinned with the doctrine of [[white supremacy]], and helped fuel the [[Europe|European]] exploration, conquest, and colonization of much of the rest of the world -- especially after [[Christopher Columbus]] reached the Americas.  [[Basil Davidson]] insists in his documentary, ''[[Africa: Different but Equal]]'', that racism, in fact, only just recently surfaced—as late as the 1800’s, due to the need for a justification of slavery in the Americas. The idea of slavery as an "equal-opportunity employer" was denounced with the introduction of Christian theory in the West.  Maintaining that Africans were "subhuman" was the only loophole in the then accepted law that "men are created equal" that would allow for the sustenance of the [[Triangular Trade]].  New peoples in the Americas, possible slaves, were encountered, fought, and ultimately subdued, but then due to western diseases, their population decreased innumerably.  Through both influences, theories about "race" developed, and these helped many to justify the differences in position and treatment of people whom they categorized as belonging to different races (see Eric Wolf's ''Europe and the People Without History'').  Some people like [[Juan Ginés de Sepúlveda]] even argued that the [[Indigenous peoples of the Americas|Native Americans]] were natural slaves. In Asia, the Chinese and Japanese Empires were both strong colonial powers, with the Chinese making colonies and vassal states of much of mainland Asia, and the Japanese doing the same in the west Pacific. In both cases, the Asian imperial powers believed they were ethnically and racially superior to their vassals, and entitled to be their masters.

== Expressions ==

Racism may be expressed individually and consciously, through explicit thoughts, feelings, or acts, or socially and unconsciously, through institutions that promote inequalities among "races".  Although some speakers attempt to express a semantic distinction by using the word ''racism'' rather than ''racialism'' (or vice versa), many treat the terms as synonymous (see below).

Racism may be divided in three major subcategories: individual racism, structural racism, and ideological racism. 

Examples of individual racism include an employer not hiring a person, failing to promote or giving harsher duties or imposing harsher working conditions, or firing, someone, in whole or in part due to his race.

Researchers at the [[University of Chicago]] (Marianne Bertrand) and [[Harvard University]] ([[Sendhil Mullainathan]]) found in a [[2003]] study that there was widespread discrimination in the workplace against job applicants whose names were merely perceived as "sounding black." These applicants were 50% less likely than candidates perceived as having "white-sounding names" to receive callbacks for interviews, no matter their level of previous experience. Results were stronger for higher quality resumes. The researchers view these results as strong evidence of unconscious biases rooted in the country's long history of discrimination.  This is an example of structural racism, because it shows a widespread established belief system.  Another example is apartheid in [[South Africa]], and the system of [[Jim Crow]] laws in the [[United States of America]].  Another source is lending inequities of banks, and so-called [[redlining]].

Racism is usually directed against a minority population, but may also be directed against a majority population.  Examples include racial [[History of South Africa in the Apartheid Era|apartheid]] in [[South Africa]], wherein whites (a minority) discriminated against blacks (a majority) or contemporary United States of America wherein federal legislation has been interpreted as mandating preferential treatment for non whites; this form of racism also occurred during the former colonial rule of such countries as [[Vietnam]] (by [[France]]) and [[India]] (by the [[United Kingdom]]). This is known in United States politics as "[[reverse racism]]".

"Reverse racism" is a controversial concept; it is usually applied to instances of perceived discrimination against members of a dominant (rather than minority) group, usually as a reaction to previous policies racism by said group. In the United States, many people, mostly conservatives, criticize policies such as [[affirmative action]] as an example of reverse racism. They point out that insofar as these policies provide preference to certain racial groups and not others, they are race-based discrimination, even if their goal is to correct a previous act of discrimination. Supporters of affirmative action argue that those policies counteract a systemic and cultural racism by providing a balancing force, and that it does not qualify as racist because they are enacted by politicians (mostly part of the majority) and directed towards their own race.  

Increasingly significant numbers of white people (i.e. people of European ethnicity) believe that [[political correctness]] has led to a denigration of the white race, through "special attention" paid to minority races.  For example, they consider the existence of Black History Month (February) but not a White History Month, Amerindian History Month, or Asian History Month to be &lt;i&gt;de facto&lt;/i&gt; racism directed at the majority and non-black minorities. Yet again, others argue that the lack of a White History Month is due to the fact that much of the school year is devoted to teaching history from a Eurocentric perspective.

[[Racial discrimination]] is and has been official government policy in many countries.  In the [[1970s]], [[Uganda]] expelled tens of thousands of ethnic [[India|Indians]].  Until 2003, [[Malaysia]] enforced discriminatory policies limiting access to university education for ethnic [[China|Chinese]] and [[India|Indian]] students who are citizens by birth of Malaysia, and many other policies explicitly favoring [[bumiputra]]s (Malays) remain in force. Russia launched anti-Semitic [[pogroms]] against Jews in [[1905]] and after. During the [[1930s]] and [[1940s]], attempts were made to prevent Jews from immigrating to the Middle East. Following the creation of [[Israel]], land-ownership in many Israeli towns was limited to [[Jew]]s, and many [[Muslim]] countries expelled Jewish Arabs and continue to refuse entry to Jews.

In the United States, [[Racial profiling|racial profiling]] of minorities by law enforcement officials is a controversial subject. Some people consider this to be a form of racism.  Some claim that profiling young Arab male fliers at airports will only lead to increased recruitment of older, non-Arab, and female terrorists, as well as Arab males who might be mistaken for white males. Many critics of racial profiling claim that it is an unconstitutional practice because it amounts to questioning individuals on the basis of what crimes they might commit or could possibly commit, instead of what crimes they have actually committed. See the article on [[racial profiling]] for more information on this dispute.

==Racism by country==

In [[19th century]] Europe and America, some scientists developed various theories about biological differences among [[race]]s, and these theories were in turn used to legitimize racist beliefs and practices. Much of this work has since been rejected by the scientific community as flawed and even as [[pseudoscience]].

Today there are some scientists who claim that "race", in the general sense in which the term is used, is a [[social construct]]: the way in which individuals are classified into racial groups varies from person to person, and from place to place, and from time to time. These scientists say that superficial characteristics which are associated with racial groupings are poor predictors of genetic variability. There can be more genetic variation within a racial grouping than between two racial groupings. They also point to the lack of well-defined boundaries to racial classifications; for example characteristics such as skin colour and facial appearance can be shown to vary as a continuum from place to place. Other scientists counter that "sex" and "species" are likewise seen by some as socially constructed. After all, humans and chimpanzees (or males and females) are far more genetically alike than different. According to this view, categories need not be absolute in order to have scientific utility. 

===Australia===

See [[White Australia Policy]] and [[Terra nullius]].

=== Austria ===	 	

Austria has sometimes been criticised of trying to sweep its Nazi past under the carpet, typifed by the widely pronounced myth that Austria was a victim of Nazi aggression rather than a willing participant. This has its origins as an Allied propaganda tactic. This complacency was severly tested in the [[1986]] presidential race when it emerged that [[Kurt Waldheim]] (a former [[UN secretary general]]) had concealed (or forgotten) certain facts about his war-time military service with the [[Wehrmacht]]. The revelations caused much controversy in Austria as well as in the outide world. Nevertheless Waldheim was elected President. Controversy again erupted in [[2000]] when [[Jörg Haider]]'s conservative [[Freedom Party]] entered into coalition with the centre-right [[People's Party]] having gained 27% of the vote. 

However much progress has been made with settling the disputes and compensation for Jews and others whose property and assets were seized during the Nazi era, with a deal completed in [[2001]]. Elections in [[2002]] saw a significant drop in support for the Freedom Party, with the party subsequently splitting into opposing factions. Herr Haider now leads the Bündnis Zukunft Österreich.

===Canada===
While [[Canada]] often depicts its society as being a very progressive, tolerant, diverse, and [[multicultural]] nation, Canada also has its own history of racism.  Although the historical records are not very clear at the very beginnings of the country's history, one can argue that the first event of racism in Canada occurred during the first trip of [[Jacques Cartier]] in [[1534]], when he brought back two [[Iroquois]] more or less against their will to [[France]], which greatly amused the [[List of French monarchs|French royal court]].  Later, although still not very clearly recognised in the mainstream culture (where it is more seen as territorial wars), much racism occurred between the French and the [[First Nations]] people, between First Nations tribes themselves (fuelled by alliances of certain tribes with the French, and others with the English), between the English and the First Nations, and between the English and the French. Although the country's history was influenced greatly by these wars, the relationships between all those ethnicities has changed a lot since the beginning of European settlement in Canada.

Moreover, there are notable records of [[Slavery in Canada|slavery in Canada]] in the [[1700s]].  More than half of all Canadian slaves were [[First Nations|aboriginal]]. In [[1793]], [[Upper Canada]] governor [[John Graves Simcoe]] passed a bill making it illegal to bring a person into the colony for the purposes of enslavement, and slavery was fully outlawed in [[1834]]. 

Starting in [[1858]], [[China|Chinese]] "[[coolies]]" were brought to Canada to work in the mines and on the [[Canadian Pacific Railway]]. However, they were denied by law the rights of citizenship, including the right to vote, and in the [[1880s]], "[[Head Tax|head taxes]]" were implemented to curtail immigration from China. In [[1907]], a riot in [[Vancouver, British Columbia|Vancouver]] targeted Chinese and Japanese-owned businesses. In [[1923]], the federal government passed the ''[[Chinese Immigration Act of 1923|Chinese Immigration Act]]'', commonly known as the ''Exclusion Act'', prohibiting further Chinese immigration except under "special circumstances". The Exclusion Act was repealed in [[1947]], the same year in which [[Chinese Canadian]]s were finally given the right to vote. 

Restrictions still existed on immigration from Asia. In [[1967]], these restrictions were repealed and Asian immigrants were given the same rights as any other group. In [[1999]], [[Adrienne Clarkson]], the child of Chinese immigrants who moved to Canada in [[1942]] under the "special circumstances" clause, became [[Governor General of Canada]].  [[Japanese Canadian]]s were also subject to anti-Asian racism, particularly during [[World War II]] when many Canadians of Japanese heritage -- even those who were born in Canada -- were forcibly moved to internment camps. The government of Canada officially made restitution for the treatment of Japanese Canadians in [[1988]].

More recently, Canada has been perceived as practicing systemic, [[Institutionalized Racism|institutionalized racism]] by allowing employers to require Canadian-based job experience in a potential employee. This puts landed immigrants at a clear disadvantage, and can often result in highly educated people working for much lower pay than their Canadian educated counterparts, or even struggling with a minimum wage job. This unequal footing has left many new immigrants feeling disillusioned with the entire immigration process, and segregated from [[Canadian culture]] as a whole. Both as an expression of protest, and as a means of warning potential immigrants still overseas, online groups have formed to share information and stories of victimization. [http://www.canadaimmigrants.com], [http://www.notcanada.com]

However, racism in Canada has not only been connected to immigration. French Canadians, including [[Acadian]]s, [[Québécois]] and [[Franco-ontarian]]s, and [[First Nations|aboriginals]] have purportedly also been subject to discriminatory treatment in Canada.  However, having French recognised as an official language was seen as a step towards today's "multiculturalism".

Notable organizations in Canadian history have included the ''[[Parti national social chrétien]]'', and the ''[[Heritage Front]]''. Other notable individuals in this context include [[Adrien Arcand]], [[Ernst Zündel]], [[Doug Christie (lawyer)|Doug Christie]], [[Wolfgang Droege]] and [[Don Andrews]].

=== Finland ===
[[Sami people]] were traditionally feared for being wizards and Russians for being criminals, but the fear was more cultural. In 19th century, the ruling Swedish-speaking minority considered Finnish-speaking people to be a separate race and inferior to Germanic race. The discrimination since transformed into mainly linguistic, but there is still inferiority complex within the Finnish-speaking majority.

Finns have generally been curious about different-looking people. Immigrants of Chinese, Vietnamese, Thai and Japanese origin have been welcomed since cultures of these immigrant groups have been sound with the mainstream culture.

In the beginning of 1990s, a large [[Somali]] immigrant population came to the country. Somali immigrants had problems with high criminality and unemployment rates, notably street violence and rapes raising attention. This created racist views and discrimination towards Somalis, extending to all Somali-looking Afro-Finnish immigrants. The discrimination has since occured, especially outside [[Helsinki]]. Problems are currently under hot debate.

=== France ===
The French have a long history of ethnic and racial conflicts. Anti-Semitism, a common trend in European history is also highlighted in French history by events such as the Dreyfus affaire, and France's irresponsible treatment of its Jewish population during Nazi occupation. Likewise, the treatment of North Africans and other former colonials during the colonial era, the atrocities committed by France during the Algerian War of independence (1954-1962) are also signs of intolerance.   The fact that Algerians formed the bulk of late-twentieth century immigration has raised delicate issues, which are exacerbated by the degradation of the general social situation. In the 1970s [[Jean Raspail]] wrote [[The Camp of the Saints]] which some felt implied African immigrants should be drowned or shot to prevent them from entering France.

In [[1998]] the Council of Europe's European Commission Against Racism and Intolerance (ECRI) made a report stating concern about racist activities in France and accused the French authorities of not doing enough to combat this. The report and other groups have expressed concern about organizations like [[Front National (France)]]. In a recent [[Pew Research Center|Pew Survey]], 47% of the French deem immigration from Eastern Europe to be a bad thing. A small minority shows signs of Anti-Semitism. Roughly 11% had an unfavorable view of Jews [http://pewglobal.org/reports/display.php?PageID=795] and 8% felt that US policy was most influenced by the Jews [http://pewglobal.org/reports/display.php?PageID=803]. In the colonial age some French also displayed negative sentiments toward black Africans.

Nevertheless these judgments should be balanced by the following: Canadians had roughly the same percentage linking US policy to Jews as France did. Furthermore, France had been ruled by Jewish leaders during the twentieth century (most notably [[Leon Blum]] and [[Pierre Mendes-France]], who were both highly popular...) Indeed, France has a long history of support for universalism dating back to the [[Age of Enlightenment|Enlightenment]] : the unenforced constitution of 1794 gave the right to vote to all "foreigners" (independently of any racial consideration) living in France for more than one year. The French also generally have a greater interest in African culture and aid to the region.

In late October of 2005, [[2005 Paris riots|violent riots]] erupted in north-east Paris, and later other cities around France, after two youths of North African origin were accidentally electrocuted after supposedly fleeing police.

=== Germany=== 

==== Nazi Germany ====
[[Image:Nurembergracechart.jpg|thumb|250px|1935 chart from [[Nazi Germany]] used to explain the Nuremberg Laws]]

The [[Nuremberg Laws]] of 1935 used a [[pseudoscientific]] basis for racial discrimination against Jews. People with four German grandparents (white circles on the chart illustration) were of "German blood", while people were classified as Jews if they descended from three or more Jewish grandparents (black circles in top row right). One or more Jewish grandparents made someone "mixed blood."   The Nazis used the religious observance of a person's grandparents to determine their race.

See also:
*[[Nazism]]
*[[General Government]] an attempt to introduce racial segregation in Poland, which was occupied by Nazi Germany. There were several separated races (in order of privileges):
** [[Reichdeutsche]]
** [[Volksdeutsche]]
** [[Ukrainians]]
** [[Goralenvolk]]
** [[Poles]]
** [[Russia]]n
** [[Jew]]s

===India===
Elements of [[Sangh Parivar]] and [[Vishva Hindu Parishad]] have been accused of inciting ethnic tension.  In general tensions in India are more religious than racial in nature, but there have been some reports of ethnic tension between [[Tamil people]] and the [[Hindi]] majority. Others state some in India accepted [[Aryan_Invasion_Theory#Racial_interpretations_of_the_Vedic_Aryans Racial interpretations of Vedic writing]].

Of some relevance is [[Asit Krishna Mukherji]] who was a [[Bengali]] [[Brahmin]] who openly supported Hitler and married an [[Esoteric Hitlerist]].

See also [[Ethnic conflict in India]].

=== Indonesia ===
See [[Jakarta Riots of May 1998]].

===Ireland===

Traditionally there has been very little immigration by non-whites to the Republic of Ireland due to historic poverty, though in recent times growing prosperity in the country (see: [[Celtic Tiger]]) has attracted increasing numbers of immigrants, mainly from Africa, China, and Eastern Europe. Also the absence of any colonisation of other country has meant that foreign people are not drawn to Ireland by "[[mother country]]" factors that have effected other European countries. Descendants of Irish people who emigrated in the past have also started moving to the country. Most immigrants have settled in [[Dublin]] and the other cities. Though these developments have been accepted or tolerated by most, there has been a rise in so-called racist attitudes among some sections of society. Although most racism takes the form of verbal and other petty abuses.

Several issues relating to immigration have gained widespread publicity in recent years. After [[1997]] and prior to [[2005]] any baby born in the Republic was entitled to Irish citizenship due to stipulations in the Good Friday agreement. This led to many pregnant women (overwhelmingly from Nigeria) from Africa, having discarded their identification documentation to travel directly to Ireland expressly to give birth and thus allow their child to gain Irish citizenship. This became known as [[citizenship tourism]]. Following the noted abuses of the loophole in the Irish Constitution a referendum on the issue was held. The referendum was duly carried and the loophole was closed.

In [[2005]] Nigerian student Olukunle Elukanlo was deported after his asylum application failed, despite the fact that he had not yet completed his exams. Following an outcry by various activist groups at the descision he was allowed to return to complete his exams. The issue highlighted the growing numbers of failed asylum seekers been deported, and issue which is often controversial to some (despite that fact that very few failed applicants are actually deported). This has been highlighted in recent television and radio programmes focused on exposing the extreme high cost to the Irish taxpayer of processing false asylum claims in addition to the cost of returning bogus asylum-seekers to their country of origin.

Many Irish people are very proud of being in the European Union, but increasingly large numbers resent migrants from outside the Union coming to Ireland expressly for the purpose of claiming asylum, without having applied for asylum in other countries along their route as is required by international law. There are several "anti-racism" groups active in the Republic, as well as those seeking tighter immigration laws such as the [[Immigration Control Platform]].

===Japan===

''See [[Ethnic issues in Japan]]''

=== New Zealand ===

The 2005 general election has been criticized in some quarters as playing on [[Maori]] issues in a racial way.[http://www.abc.net.au/worldtoday/content/2005/s1449282.htm] A 2003 study by the Human Rights Commission showed 70% of New Zealanders think that Asians face significant discrimination. 

Although New Zealand did not have an official policy along the lines of the [[White Australia Policy]], it did engage in the land wars with the aboriginal Maori during the mid-19th Century, and imposed a poll tax on Chinese immigrants during the [[19th Century|19th]] and early [[20th Century| 20th centuries]]. In one high profile incident in 1905, an elderly Chinese man was shot dead in Wellington by Lionel Terry, a recently arrived Englishman who was later committed to a mental asylum. The poll tax was effectively lifted in the [[1930s]] following the invasion of China by Japan, and was finally repealed in [[1944]].

After World War II, immigration policy remained largely Anglocentric until the mid-[[1980s]], although war refugees and non-Anglo-Celtic migrants were allowed in the country in limited numbers. In the [[1975]] election campaign, opposition leader [[Robert Muldoon]] ran a scare campaign directed against [[Pacific Islands]] migrant workers, which was followed by a series of dawn raids on suspected overstayers. Land issues came to a head in the late [[1970s]] with Maori protesters occupying the Raglan Golf Course and Bastion Point, with land claims on both being settled by the following decade. 

In [[1986]], country-of-origin rules were abolished, leading to major inflows of immigration for the first time in years. However, anti-immigration rhetoric from populist politician [[Winston Peters]] has since forced immigration rules to be tightened.

===United Kingdom===
[[Image:AS 1900s postcard 01.jpg|thumb|300px|This [[postcard]] from the [[1900s]] depicts an Englishman calling "BOY!" to a Chinaman to bring him a drink. The caption reads "The Call of the East".]]
There were [[race riot]]s across the [[United Kingdom]] in [[1919]]: [[South Shields]], [[Glasgow]], London's [[East End; London|East End]], [[Liverpool]], [[Cardiff]], [[Barry]], and [[Newport]]. There were further riots by immigrant and minority populations in East London during the [[1930s]], [[Notting Hill]] in the [[1950s]], and [[Brixton]], [[Toxteth]] and [[Blackbird Leys]], [[Oxford]] in the [[1980s]]. More recently in [[2001]], there have been riots in [[Bradford]] and [[Oldham]]. These riots have followed cases of perceived racism - either the public displays of racist sentiment (including crimes against members of ethnic minorities which were subsequently ignored by the authorities), or, as in the [[Brixton Riots|Brixton]] and [[Toxteth]] riots, [[racial profiling]] and alleged harassment by the [[police]] force.

Racism in one form or another was widespread in Britain before the [[twentieth century]], and during the [[1900s]] particularly towards Jewish groups and immigrants from Eastern Europe. The English establishment even considered the [[Irish people|Irish]] a separate and degenerate race until well into the [[19th Century]].  Since [[World War I]], public expressions of white supremacism have been limited to far-right political parties such as the [[British Union of Fascists]] in the [[1930s]] and the [[British National Front]] in the [[1970s]], whilst most mainstream politicians have publicly condemned all forms of racism. However, anecdotal evidence suggests that racism remains widespread, and some politicians and public figures have been accused of excusing or pandering to racist attitudes in the media, particularly with regard to [[immigration]]. There have been growing concerns in recent years about [[institutional racism]] in public and private bodies, and the tacit support this gives to crimes resulting from racism, such as the murder of [[Stephen Lawrence]], Gavin Hopely and Ross Parker. 

The [[Race Relations Act 1965]] outlawed public discrimination, and established the [[Race Relations Board]]. Further Acts in [[1968]] and [[1976]] outlawed discrimination in employment, housing and social services, and replaced the Race Relations Board with [[Commission for Racial Equality]]. The [[Human Rights Act 1999]] made organizations in Britain, including public authorities, subject to the [[European Convention on Human Rights]]. The [[Race Relations Act 2000]] extends existing legislation for the public sector to the police force, and requires public authorities to promote equality.

There have been tensions over [[immigration]] since at least the early [[1900s]]. These were originally engendered by hostility towards Jews and immigrants from [[Russia]] and [[Eastern Europe]]. Britain first began restricting immigration in [[1905]] and has also had very strong limits on immigration since the early [[1960s]]. Legislation was particularly targeted at members of the [[British Commonwealth]], who had previously been able to migrate to the UK under the [[British Nationality Act 1948]]. Virtually all legal immigration, except for those claiming refugee status, ended with the [[Immigration Act 1971]]; however, free movement for citizens of the [[European Union]] was later established by the [[Immigration Act 1988]]. Legislation in [[1993]], [[1996]] and [[1999]] gradually decreased the rights and benefits given to those claiming refugee statues ("asylum seekers"). A further government Act in [[2002]] gave Britain the most restrictive immigration laws of any country in the [[European Union]].

Some commentators believe that a huge amount of racism has been undocumented within the UK, adducing the many British cities whose populations have a clear racial divide. While these commentators believe that race relations have improved immensely over the last thirty years, they still believe that [[racial segregation]] remains an important but largely unaddressed problem.

==== Scotland ====
It has been reported that racial minorities are underrepresented in the police force[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/scotland/4684429.stm]. Philomena de Lima noted that Scots sometimes feel there is "no problem here" because ethnic minorities are regarded as small in number, "invisible", and "silent."  However, she found that in most schools, least 4% of students were minorities. In the urban areas tensions between Whites and Pakistanis occasionally flare up. In the past football(soccer in US English) has at times divided on racial lines with "Asian teams" versus "Scottish teams" causing conflict. Among the Scottish under 15 years old there is the positive sign that, "younger white pupils rarely drew on racist discourses."[http://www.scotland.gov.uk/library5/education/mepess-05.asp]

==== Northern Ireland ====

Racism in the United Kingdom is particularly acute in [[Northern Ireland]]. Despite having the smallest numbers of non-whites in the UK it has the highest levels of racist violence in the country (racially motivated attacks are at 16.4% per 1000 of the minority population, whilst in [[England]] and [[Wales]] the figure is 12.6%). 

Traditionally there has been segregration, hatred and violence between Northern Ireland's two main communities: the Unionists/Loyalists, mostly Protestant, who want to remain within the UK and Nationalists/Republicans, mostly Catholic, who want a united Ireland. Following the partition of Ireland and the creation of Northern Ireland the government of the province was controlled by and for Protestants, with a policy of systematic discrimination against Catholics, who formed roughly 1/3 of the population. Tensions eventually erupted in 'the Troubles' in [[1968]], which saw a renewed campaign of [[IRA]] activity and corresponding Loyalist paramilitary violence, the presence of British soldiers and extreme sectarianism fostered by frequent riots and violence.

More recently non-white people, especially Chinese, have started to live in Northern Ireland, primarily in the captial [[Belfast]]. Northern Ireland is 99% white, and racism against non-white communities is endemic, earning it the nickname 'the race hate capital of Europe.' Discrimination takes many forms such as the spraying of racist graffiti, intimidation, systematic intimidation with the aim or forcing out non-whites, assaults, general harrassment, protection racketing, vandalism and house burning. Attempts to build a mosque in Belfast was met by much opposition - the plan was eventually dropped.

===Soviet Union, U.S.S.R., Russia etc=== 
See [[Racism in Russia]], [[Liberal Democratic Party of Russia]] and [[History of the Jews in Russia and the Soviet Union]]. 

The subject of racism in Russia is at present controversial and heated. However a Pew Survey showed that of those who believed some religions are more violent than others 10% of Russians named Judaism[http://pewglobal.org/reports/display.php?PageID=811] as the most violent. This was the highest percentage outside the Muslim world. Further a previous poll showed that 25% of Russians had an unfavorable view of Jews.[http://pewglobal.org/reports/display.php?PageID=795] Racism towards Central Asians is said to be even more widespread.

===United States of America===
{{main|Racism in the United States}}
[[Image:1900sc Mammy Card Interracial.jpg|thumb|right|250px|This racist item from the [[1900s]] shows a casual denigration of black women.]]

Apologists mistakenly claim the United States is free of racism. They point to the comparatively positive view Americans have of immigrants,[http://pewglobal.org/reports/display.php?PageID=805] or the lack of racial genocide in US history when compared to the levels seen in Germany or by European imperialists. [[Jim Crow]] laws, [[Japanese internment]] camps, and the fate of [[Cheyenne]] in the [[Sand Creek massacre]] may not have been taken into account are but a few examples of the strong racism that has existed in the US.
  
In colonial America, before colonial slavery became completely based on racial lines, thousands of African slaves served whites, alongside other whites serving a term of indentured servitude. In some cases for African slaves, a term of service meant freedom and a land grant afterward, but these were rarely awarded, and few black Africans became landowners this way. In [[1676]], [[Nathaniel Bacon]] led a [[Bacon's Rebellion|revolt]] against the Governor of [[Virginia]] and the system of exploitation he represented: exploitation of poorer colonists by the increasingly wealthy landowners. However, Bacon died, probably of [[dysentery]], and the revolt lost steam.

The central cause of concern to landowners was the unity of Bacon's populist movement. It raised the question to the landowners of how to divide the population politically in ways that would keep the poorer colonists divided enough to rule.  To the Governor, the most threatening, and unexpected, aspect of Bacon's rebellion was its multi-racial aspect.  So from that time on, the wealthy landowners determined that only Africans would be used as slaves - and white colonists were promised whatever benefits would have gone to Africans had they continued to be indentured servants.  The fuel of the racism was due to the fear of sex among whites and blacks.  This relationship was specifically afraid of black, Native American, Asian, and Hispanic men with White women.  The thousands of lynchings were testimony to this.  This legacy is still seen in the antimiscegenation laws which were repealed only within the past few years.  This change began the infamously long period of the American slave society, in which slaves were primarily used for [[agriculture|agricultural]] labor, notably in the production of [[cotton]] and [[tobacco]].  Black slavery in the Northeast was less common, usually confined to involuntary domestic servitude.  The social rift along color lines soon became engrained in every aspect of colonial American culture.

Slavery in the [[Confederate States of America]] was unaffected by the [[Emancipation Proclamation]], which was issued on [[January 1]], [[1863]] by President [[Abraham Lincoln]], a whole two years after the beginning of the civil war. The United States Federal Government no longer had any legal power in the Confederate States, and as such, made no great sacrifice in outlawing slavery in territories which they no longer controlled. Slavery ended in the whole country with the [[Thirteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|13th Amendment]] which was declared ratified on [[December 18]], [[1865]].  Despite this, remnants of racism continued in the United States with the existence of [[Jim Crow]] laws, educational disparities, widespread criminal acts perpetrated by local and vigilante groups, and vigorous action by trade unions and their allies to enact [[Minimum wages]], which had the effect of pricing the typically unskilled and untrained black and immigrant laborers out of the labor market.

In the 1950's and 1960's a mass based movement of predominately African Americans capitalizing on the gains made by the New Deal engaged in a series of local movements, national lobbying and legal attacks on segregation and discrimination. These groups included the [[Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee]], The [[Congress of Racial Equality]], the [[NAACP Legal Defense Fund]], and a variety of local groups and labor unions. This movement culminated in the passage of the [[Civil Rights Act of 1964]] and the [[Voting Rights Act]].

:"I have a dream that my four little children will one day live in a nation where they will not be judged by the color of their skin but by the content of their character" - [[Martin Luther King, Jr.|Martin Luther King]], ''[[I Have a Dream|"I Have a Dream"]]'' speech at the Lincoln Memorial, Washington D.C. ([[28 August]], [[1963]]).

While the relationship between races in the United States has largely been limited to that between whites and blacks, the changing racial makeup of the American population at the beginning of the 21st century has caused many voices to call for the inclusion of other races in the equation. It is estimated that by 2050, whites in America will comprise less than 50% of the total population (Hispanics, for example will acount for 25 % of the US population). The relationship between races in the US is therefore being redefined to include Hispanics and Asian Americans, the fastest growing ethnic groups. At this writing, at least 4 states, California, Texas, Hawaii, and New Mexico (and the District of Columbia) are deemed "majority minority" states, where whites are not the majority of the population.

===South Africa===

See [[History of South Africa in the Apartheid Era]].

===Sri Lanka===
There has been a good deal of tension over the decades between the [[Sinhala]] and [[Tamil]]. For more in depth information see [[Ethnic conflict in Sri Lanka]].

=== Switzerland ===

[[Switzerland|The Swiss Confederation]] or ''Confederatio Helvetica'' is a nation composed of four subcultural groups: German-speaking (63.7%), French-speaking (12.9%), Italian-speaking (7.6%) and [[Romansch]]-speaking (0.6%). With this diversity and its history of [[neutrality]], Switzerland has been seen as a safe refuge for those genuinely fleeing from persecution. Switzerland has seen an increase in refugees in recent years, (particularly from Africa), who have claimed asylum directly in Switzerland. In 1992, the federal refugee office registered some 7,000 black Africans requesting asylum. In the first nine months of 2002 the number was 17,000.

However, there is evidence of increased intolerance of immigrants in recent years. There have been  attacks against African immigrants popularly believed to be economic immigrants rather than genuine asylum seekers. As a result of these reports, Switzerland has come in for harsh crticism in recent years from bodies such as the UN. Furthermore, the SVP or [[Swiss People's Party]] has significantly increased its share of the vote in recent years on a percieved "anti-immigrant" platform. It is best known for opposing Swiss membership in international organisations such as the EU and [[United Nations]] and for its campaigning against perceived flaws in the immigration, asylum and penal laws. 

An official research report released in [[2004]] by the [http://www.edi.admin.ch/ekr/index.html Federal Commission against Racism] in [[Bern]], Switzerland revealed both public and officials in Switzerland to exhibit a high degree of widespread racism[http://www.edi.admin.ch/ekr/dokumentation/shop/00019/00142/index.html?lang=fr]. According to this report, discrimination based on skin colour in is not exceptional, and affects immigrants decades after their immigration. Immigrants have also labelled the Swiss way of integrating dark skinned foreigners as 'silent apartheid'. They are targeted by police and intimidated by authorities, experience frequent public humiliation and hate stares, and seats in public transport are typically left empty next to a Black person. The report concludes that it would be good to alert Black people to this issue about Switzerland, as up to the release of this report, many people assumed Switzerland to be free of racism.

===Rhodesia===
Until majority rule in [[1980]], the minority white government of [[Rhodesia]] (as [[Zimbabwe]] was then called) practised institutionalised racism similar in a few respects to the [[apartheid]] system in [[South Africa]]. White Rhodesians "''lived in the best houses, owned most of the best land, enjoyed a high standard of living and controlled the executive, the legislature, the judiciary and the means of coercion."'' (Godwin, P. &amp; Hancock, I., 1993. ''Rhodesians never Die'', Baobab Books, Harare, Zimbabwe.)

The laws enforcing [[racial segregation]], however, were not always welcomed by the local white community. They were viewed as not only being racist, but expensive and unnecessary. This was highlighted in an incident, called "[[Reps Theatre#"The Battle of the Toilets"|The Battle of the Toilets]]" in [[1960]], involving a new [[Reps Theatre|theatre]] that would be open to all races.

Twenty years after [[Zimbabwe#Independance|Independance]], whites in Zimbabwe remained a [[Market dominant minorities|market dominant minority]] through their continued ownership of the vast majority of [[arable]] land, the most valuable resource in a country like Zimbabwe where agriculture is the leading industry. In [[2000]] the government, arguing that the country's landownership patters were the result of longtime failure to address the legacies of colonialism and racism in Zimbabwean society, began a controversial [[Land reform in Zimbabwe|land reform]] process directed at redistributing land to the poor black majority.

== Some examples of specific types of alleged racism ==

''see [[Categories of Racism]]''

==Related concepts==

*''[[Affirmative action]]'' is the practice of favoring or benefiting members of a particular race in areas such as [[college]] admissions and workplace advancement, in an attempt to create atmospheres of racial [[diversity]] and racial [[social equality|equality]]. Though lauded by many as a boon to society, giving the less privileged a chance at success, the practice is condemned as racially discriminatory by others.
*''Historical economic or social disparity'' is alleged to be a form of discrimination which is caused by past racism, affecting the present generation through deficits in the formal education and other kinds of preparation in the parents' generation, and, through primarily unconscious racist attitudes and actions on members of the general population.  (E.g. A member of Race Y, Mary, has her opportunities adversely affected (directly and/or indirectly) by the mistreatment of her ancestors of race Y.) 
*''[[Institutional racism]]'' or ''structural racial discrimination'' -- racial discrimination by governments, corporations, or other large organizations with the power to influence the lives of many individuals. See [[Affirmative Action]].
*''Cultural'' racial discrimination occurs when the assumption of inferiority of one or more races is built into the culturally maintained image of itself held by members of one culture. (e.g. Members of group X are taught to believe that they are members of a superior race, and, consequently, members of other races are inferior.)
*''Racial discrimination'' is differences in treatment of people on the basis of characteristics which may be classified as racial, including skin color, cultural heritage, and religion.  (e.g. Mary refuses to hire John because he is of race Y.) This is a concept not unanimously agreed upon. While this usually refers to discrimination against minority racial groups in Western societies, it can also (arguably) refer to the opposite situation, and in that case is often called [[reverse discrimination]] when it is due to [[affirmative action]] or other attempts to remedy past or current discrimination against minority racial groups. (e.g. Mary cannot get a job, despite her qualifications, because she is of the dominant race Y.) Many do not consider this racism, but simply a form of discrimination.
*''[[Racialism]]'' is a term often found within [[white separatist]] [[literature]], inferring an emphasis in [[Race|racial origin]] in [[social]] matters. Racism infers an assumption of [[racial superiority]] and a harmful intent, whereas separatists sometimes prefer the term racialism, indicating a strong interest in matters of race without a necessary inference of superiority or a desire to be harmful to others. Rather their focus is on [[Racial segregation|racial segregation]] and [[white pride]].
*''Racial prejudice'' is pre-formed personal opinions about individuals on the basis of their race.  (E.g. John thinks that Mary will have bad attribute X solely because Mary is a member of race Y.)

== Some examples of organizations often accused of racism==

Note: The use of the word "often" means that one or more valid sources is required. Being self-described as racist counts as a source.

*[[Aryan Nations]] - a group of militant [[white supremacist]]s[http://bethuneinstitute.org/documents/cift.html] 
*[[Black Hebrew Israelites]] - A group of Black Israelites that deems Jews to be evil.[http://www.splcenter.org/intel/intelreport/article.jsp?aid=172 SPLC]
*[[Mansions of Rastafari|Bobo Ashanti]]-An offshoot of [[Rastafarianism]] that considers whites to be inherently evil. [http://www.guardian.co.uk/arts/fridayreview/story/0,12102,1369875,00.html Guardian]
*[[British National Party]] - a [[far-right]] political party in the UK.[http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/main.jhtml?xml=/news/2005/07/20/nbnp20.xml Britain's "The Telegraph"]
*[[Christian Identity]] - A radical offshoot of [[British Israelism]] that deems "Aryans" to be the chosen people and that the Jewish community is "false Jews" born of "barbarians" or Satan.[http://www.cesnur.org/testi/FBI_006.htm#Anchor-III-43266 Cesnur],[http://www.tolerance.org/maps/hate/ SPLC], etc.
*[[Creativity Movement|The Creativity Movement]] - formerly known as "The World Church of the Creator", a religion founded by [[Ben Klassen]] which bills itself as "A White Racial Religion" and advocates "[[Racial Holy War]]" [http://www.cnn.com/2003/US/Midwest/01/08/white.supremacist/index.html CNN] and self-described.
*[[National Front (France)|Front National]] - a political party in [[France]] whose leader proposed deporting 3 million non-Europeans from [[France]] in his [[1995]] presidential election bid. [http://www.economist.com/research/articlesBySubject/displayStory.cfm?story_ID=1109867&amp;subject=Netherlands&amp;tranMode=none The Economist]
*[[Imperium europa]] - A [[far-right]] party in the small nation of [[Malta]] that gained some attention for its leader being sued for inciting racial hatred. [http://www.timesofmalta.com/core/article.php?id=200050&amp;hilite=imperium Times of Malta] See [[Norman Lowell]]
*[[Jewish Defense League]] &amp; [[Kahane Chai]]- [[Meir Kahane|Kahanist]] fringe organizations accused of violence against Arabs and others. Kahanism is the ideology named after [[Meir Kahane]].(Israeli Supreme Court, see their article)
*[[Ku Klux Klan]] - a group of American white supremacists, founded after the [[American Civil War]]. [http://www.spartacus.schoolnet.co.uk/USAkkk.htm Spartacus], [http://www.adl.org/learn/ext_us/KKK.asp?xpicked=4&amp;item=18 ADL], etc.
*[[National Alliance]] - [[White separatist]] group founded by [[William Luther Pierce|William Pierce]], a former member of [[George Lincoln Rockwell]]'s [[American Nazi Party]].([http://www.adl.org/learn/ext_us/N_Alliance.asp ADL] and self-described) 
*[[National Socialist Japanese Workers and Welfare Party]] - Japanese variant of [[Nazism]].(self described)
*[[Neo-Nazism]](self described)
*[[New Black Panther Party]] - an anti-white, [[anti-Catholic]], anti-semitic organization not sanctioned by the living members of the original [[Black Panther Party]]([http://www.splcenter.org/intel/map/hate.jsp?T=17&amp;m=3 SPLC])
*[[New Zealand National Front]] - a group in [[New Zealand]] which describes itself as "[[nationalist]]" but which has been called "[[neo-nazi]]".[http://www.stuff.co.nz/stuff/0,2106,3258406a10,00.html Stuff.co.nz]
*[[Patriotic Youth League]] - Australian group linked to [[Neo-Nazi]]sm, [http://www.smh.com.au/news/National/Race-hate-group-unstuck/2004/12/18/1103312781334.html/ Sydney Morning Herald]
*[[Posse Comitatus (U.S. movement)]] - Many adhere to Anti-Semitic and related ideals.[http://www.splcenter.org/intel/intelreport/article.jsp?aid=73 SPLC]
*[[Nazi-Skinheads|Racist Skinheads]] - self described 
*[[White Australia Movement]] - a whites-only immigration movement in Australia. Now largely extinct.

== Related terminology ==

The terms ''[[racialism]]'' and ''racialist'' is sometimes used by those who think it is a different concept in which negativity or hatred is not prescribed. People who call themselves "racialists" tend to be [[separatists]] ([[white nationalists]] or sometimes [[black nationalists]]) and sometimes see a difference between themselves and racial supremacists.

Many people who study racism, such as [[Betty A. Dobratz]] and [[Stephanie Shanks-Meile]], contend that terms such as ''white separatism'' and ''white nationalism'' are [[euphemism]]s that have been adopted by [[neo-Nazi]] and racist groups in order to make their views seem less extreme. What relationship, if any, black nationalism has to [[black supremacism]] is less understood. Why?

==See also==
[[Affirmative action]], [[Afrophobia]], [[Afrocentrism]], [[anti-racism]], [[anti-Polonism]], [[anti-Semitism]], [[Apartheid]], [[Ascribed characteristics]], [[Asian fetish]], [[The Bell Curve]], [[Black power]], [[Black supremacy]], [[Blackface]], [[Chauvinism]], [[Civil rights movement]], [[Collectivism]], [[Criminal Blackman Myth]], [[Discrimination]], [[Dominant minority]], [[Environmental racism]], [[Essentialism]], [[Ethnic stereotype]], [[Ethnic cleansing]], [[Ethnocentrism]], [[Eugenics]], [[Eurocentrism]], 
[[Genocide]], [[Golliwogg]], [[Hate crime]], [[Health disparities]], [[Homophobia]], [[Institutional racism]], [[Islamophobia]], [[Jim Crow laws]], [[Ku Klux Klan]], [[Isaac La Peyrère]], [[Lynching]], [[Master race]], [[Miscegenation]], [[Nazism]], [[Neo-Nazism]], [[nigger (word)|Nigger]], [[Pigmentocracy]], [[Pre-Adamite]], [[Race]], [[Race riot]], [[Racialism]], [[Racial profiling]], [[Racial realism]], [[Racial segregation]], [[Task Force to Overcome Racism in Topeka]],  [[Rankism]], [[Sexism]], [[Skinhead]], [[Social Darwinism]], [[Social stereotype]], [[Tulsa Race Riot]], [[White Australia policy]], [[White nationalism]], [[White power]], [[White pride]], [[White separatism]], [[White supremacy]], [[White trash]], [[Wog]], [[Xenophobia]], [[Media_and_ethnicity]], [[Cultural_Imperialism]]

[[List of ethnic slurs]]

==References==
* Elazar Barkan, ''The retreat of scientific racism: changing concepts of race in Britain and the United States between the world wars'' (New York: Cambridge University Press, 1992).
* Bruce Dain, ''A hideous monster of the mind: American race theory in the early republic'' (Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard University Press, 2002). (18th century US racial theory)
*Vincent F. Rocchio, ''Reel Racism. Confronting Hollywood's Construction of Afro-American Culture'', Westview Press 2000
* Ann Laura Stoler, "Racial histories and their regimes of truth," ''Political Power and Social Theory'', 11 (1997): 183-206. ([[historiography]] of race and racism)

== External links ==
{{Commonscat|Racism}}
* From ''Nova Online'': George W. Gill [http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/nova/first/gill.html argues here for the biological concept of "race"] and, in a matching article, C. Loring Brace [http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/nova/first/brace.html argues against the existence of "race" as a biological entity].

* From ''California Newsreel'': [http://www.pbs.org/race Race: The Power of an Illusion], an in-depth website (companion to a [http://www.newsreel.org/nav/title.asp?tc=CN0149 California Newsreel film]), presenting the argument that while race is a biological fiction, racism permeates the structure of society.

[[Category:Racism|*]]
[[Category:Sociology]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Politics and race]]
[[Category:Core issues in ethics]]

[[ar:عنصرية]]
[[ca:Racisme]]
[[cs:Rasismus]]
[[da:Racisme]]
[[de:Rassismus]]
[[et:Rassism]]
[[es:Racismo]]
[[eo:Rasismo]]
[[fr:Racisme]]
[[gl:Racismo]]
[[he:גזענות]]
[[sw:Ubaguzi wa rangi]]
[[lt:Rasizmas]]
[[hu:Rasszizmus]]
[[my:Rasism]]
[[nl:Racisme]]
[[ja:人種差別]]
[[no:Rasisme]]
[[nn:Rasisme]]
[[pl:Rasizm]]
[[pt:Racismo]]
[[ru:Расизм]]
[[simple:Racism]]
[[fi:Rasismi]]
[[sv:Rasism]]
[[zh:种族主义]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>