<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20031106095717|1691196" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="25613" pageid="25613" ns="0" title="Racism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2003-11-08T03:50:43Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[de:Rassismus]] [[eo:Rasismo]][[nl:Racisme]] [[fr:Racisme]][[simple:Racism]] [[sv:Rasism]]

'''Racism''', also called '''racialism''', is a form of [[discrimination]] based on the belief that humans can be divided into distinct and unequal races.

== Beliefs behind racism ==

Racists (also: racialists) believe that certain inherited [[trait]]s, such as [[skin color]], are highly correlated to other characteristics of the individuals bearing those traits. By grouping humans sharing one trait, such as skin color, one automatically includes in that group those humans who have other salient characteristics. The supposed economy of action lies in the idea that by selecting for something that is easy to determine, e.g., skin color, one automatically picks out the individuals bearing some other characteristic that is intrinsically difficult to determine, such as intelligence. The consensus of modern day scientists and anthropologists is that such beliefs have no basis in fact. One cannot reliably predict the intelligence or moral qualities of a person based upon their race, especially so since race itself is difficult to define.  Thus, such ideas are generally viewed as pseudoscience. These ideas by themselves are not necessarilly considered racism; rather, they are considered by scientists to be unjustifiable and incorrect.

The decisive factor in racism (or racialism) is when people hold that most (or all) members of a given race share undesirable mental or moral qualities.  Thus, a racist would see an entire ethnic or racial group, such as blacks, European caucasians, Hispanics, Asians, etc, as being significantly inferior to members of their own group.

== Expressions ==

Racism may be expressed individually and consciously, through explicit thoughts, feelings, or acts, or socially and unconsciously, through institutions that promote inequalities among "races".  Although some speakers attempt to express a semantic distinction by using the word ''racism'' rather than ''racialism'' (or vice versa), many treat the terms as synonymous (see below). 

Racism could be divided in three major subcategories: individual racism, structural racism, and ideological racism.  Some categories of racism are:

*''[[Racial prejudice]]'' is pre-formed personal opinions about individuals on the basis of their race.  (E.g. John thinks that Mary will have bad attribute X solely because Mary is a member of race Y.)
*''[[Racial discrimination]]'' is differences in treatment of people on the basis of characteristics which may be classified as racial, including skin color, cultural heritage, and religion.  (e.g. Mary refuses to hire John because he is of race Y.)
*''[[Institutional racism]]'' or ''structural racial discrimination'' -- racial discrimination by governments, corporations, or other large organizations.  (e.g. Mary cannot get a job, despite her qualifications, because she is of race Y.)
*''Cultural'' racial discrimination occurs when the assumption of inferiority of one or more races is built into the culturally maintained image of itself held by members of one culture. (e.g. Members of group X are taught to believe that they are members of a superior race, and, consequently, members of other races are inferior.
*''Historical economic or social disparity'' is alleged to be a form of discrimination which is caused by past racism, affecting the present generation through deficits in the formal education and other kinds of preparation in the parents' generation, and, through primarily unconscious racist attitudes and actions on members of the general population.  (E.g. A member of Race Y, Mary, has her opportunities adversely affected (directly and/or indirectly) by the mistreatment of her ancestors of race Y.) However, many people dispute the idea that this can be called racism; many hold that this view infantilizes members of a given ethnic group (e.g. blacks or Hispanics) and treats an entire race as victims unable to improve themselves through their own efforts. In this opposing view, it is racist to believe that a group is being held back by such concerns.

Racism is usually directed against a minority population, but may also be directed against a majority population.  Examples of the former include the enslavement of black [[Africa]]ns and repression of their descendants in the [[United States]].  The existence of the latter is often controversial, but agreed upon examples include racial [[apartheid]] in [[South Africa]], wherein whites (a minority) discriminated against blacks (a majority); this form of racism also occurred during the former colonial rule of such countries as [[Vietnam]] (by [[France]]) and [[India]]  ( by the [[United Kingdom]]).

'''Reverse racism''' is a controversial concept; it refers to a form of racism against a dominant group. In the United States, many people, mostly conservatives, criticize policies such as [[affirmative action]] as an example of reverse racism. They say that these policies are race-based discrimination. Supporters of affirmative action argue that affirmative action policies counteract a systemic and cultural racism by providing a balancing force, and that affirmative action does not qualify as racist because the policies are enacted by politicians (who are mostly part of the white majority in the United States) and directed towards their own race.

Some Americans believe that reverse racism exists in the United States, but that it is cultural racism, and not primarily systemic.  For example, some African-Americans discriminate against white people -- this too can be called reverse racism. 

In addition, some white people believe that [[political correctness]] has led to a denigration of the white race, through perceived special attention paid to minority races.  For example, they consider the existence of Black History Month (February) but not a White History Month, Hispanic History Month or Asian History Month to be &lt;i&gt;de facto&lt;/i&gt; racism directed at the majority and non-black minorities.

Racism is and has been official policy in many countries.  In the [[1970s]], [[Uganda]] expelled tens of thousands of ethnic [[India|Indians]].  [[Malaysia]] currently enforces discriminatory laws limiting access to university education for [[China|Chinese]] students who are citizens by birth of Malaysia. Russia launched anti-Semitic [[pogroms]] against Jews in [[1905]] and after. In some towns [[Israel]] has limited land ownership to Jews. Many Arab nations forbid Jews from emigration or becoming citizens; in these nations it is often forbidden to sell land to a Jewish person.

In the United States, [[Racial profiling|racial profiling]] of minorities by law enforcement officials is a controversial subject. Some people consider this to be a form of racism.  

Supporters of racial profiling believe it to be a necessary tool for law enforcement because members of certain minority groups are statistically much more likely to commit certain types of crimes.  For example, most terrorists have been young Arab males, while female Christian Europeans have only participated in terrorist actions on extremely rare occasions. Thus it is both logical and useful to have security officers at airports take special note of young Arab male fliers, and not to examine all fliers equally. Critics of this policy hold that any form of special treatment is racist by definition, and thus immoral and illegal.  Some claim that profiling young Arab male fliers at airports will only lead to increased recruitment of older, non-Arab, and female terrorists. (Terrorism experts generally disagree with claim.) Many critics of racial profiling claim that it is an unconstitutional practice because it amounts to questioning individuals on the basis of what crimes they might commit or could possibly commit, instead of what crimes they have actually committed. See the article on [[racial profiling]] for more information on this dispute.

==History of racism in the modern world==

In [[19th century]] Europe and American, many people legitimized racist beliefs and practices through psuedo-scientific theories about biological differences among races. Today, all scientists have rejected pseudo-scientific theories of race that existed then. The ideas, claims and positions have been shown to be based on biased research, gross generalizations, and poorly controlled or totally uncontrolled studies.

Today scientists who study the concept of [[race]] have a very different understanding of what a "race" is; all human races are held to have vastly more in common, and very little that is different between them. The differences between races do exist on many levels (skin color, facial cartilage distribution, genetic diseases, predisposition to certain traits) but the difference between races is now understood to be vastly smaller than was imagined in the 19th century. Compared to 19th century definitions of the term, one might even say that different human races (as then defined) do not exist.

===United States of America===

In colonial America, what few African slaves there were served alongside poor whites in indentured servitude; a term of service meant freedom and a land grant afterward. A number of black Africans became landowners this way, before colonial slavery became based on racial lines. In [[1676]], [[Nathaniel Bacon]] led a revolt against the Governor and the system of exploitation he represented: exploitation of poorer colonists by the increasingly wealthy landowners. However, Bacon died, probably of [[dysentery]], and the revolt lost steam.

The central cause of concern to landowners was the unity of Bacon's populist movement. It raised the question to the landownders of how to divide the population politically in ways that would keep the poorer colonists divided enough to rule.  To the Governor, the most threatening, and unexpected, aspect of Bacon's rebellion was its multi-racial aspect.  So from that time on, the wealthy landowners determined that only Africans would be used as slaves - and white colonists were promised whatever benefits would have gone to Africans had they continued to be indentured servants.  This change began the infamously long period of the American slave society, in which slaves were primarily used for [[agriculture|agricultural]] labor, notably in the production of [[cotton]] and [[tobacco]].  The social rift along color lines soon became engrained in every aspect of colonial American culture.

===Germany, Austria and Poland===

In the 19th and 20th century many Germans, Austrians and Poles came to accept a form of racism towards Jewish people, racial [[anti-Semitism]]. Many people in these countries believe erroneously that the Jewish people were a distinct race, and further, that this race was inherently morally inferior to the putative "Aryan races". (Scientists today reject the existence of any Aryan race as fictitious, and as a recent ideological construct.) Jews were commonly referred to as inherently greedly, selfish, and "parasitical". They were often referred to as viruses or parasites.  Over time these ideas lead many people in these nations to accept the Nazi teachings that the Jewish "parasites" must be exterminated in a literal sense; this led to the [[Holocaust]].

===South Africa===

[[Apartheid]]

===United Kingdom===

There were [[race riot]]s across the [[United Kingdom]] in [[1919]]: [[South Shields]], [[Glasgow]], London's [[East End; London|East End]], [[Liverpool]], [[Cardiff]], [[Barry]], and [[Newport]].

===Israel===

Many Arabs accuse Israelis of harboring racist beliefs towards them. One fringe Jewish extremist group, [[Kach]], does preach racism towards Arabs. Many Jews accuse Palestinian Arabs of harboring anti-Semitic beliefs towards them. Many schools and mosques run by the [[Palestinian Authority]] quote from anti-Semitic sources such as the [[Protocols of the Elders of Zion]] and Adolph Hitler's [[Mein Kampf]]; in many madrassas and Palestinian mosques Jews are dscribed as descedants of monkeys and pigs.

[[Anti-Semitism]], [[Islamophobia]].

== Some examples of specific types of alleged racism ==

*[[Afrocentrism]] - (not always considered racist); the belief that black African cultures were historically more powerful and influential than is widely believed
*[[Anti-Semitism]] - usually, racism directed towards Jews, though Arabs are sometimes included as well.
*[[Apartheid]] - a system of racism, now abolished, that once existed in [[South Africa]]; some refer to current Israeli policies towards Palestinians as apartheid as well.
*[[Black supremacy]] - the belief that those of African descent are the superior race.
*[[Colorism]] - racism among blacks, based on skin-tone, exemplified in terms such as "high yellow" (sometimes written and/or pronounced as "high yaller") as well as the [[brown paper bag test]]. There seems to be an implicit calculus behind this belief that makes the goodness of the individual inversely related to the darkness of his/her skin.
*[[Eurocentrism]] - the sometimes unconscious practice of historically and culturally focusing on white Europeans, to the exclusion of study, or even mention of, significant achievements of other groups of people.
*[[Islamophobia]] - the manifestations of hatred and hostility towards [[Muslim]]s and [[Arab]] people in general.
*[[Manifest Destiny]] - a historical form of the racist belief that asserted that white Americans had the right and duty to colonize the west and "[[civilize]]" the [[Native American]] inhabitants.
*[[Nazism]] - a historical form of political organization (called national socialism) coupled with extreme racism, that directed its energies against the Roma (the so-called [[Gypsy|Gypsies]]), [[Jew]]s, [[Poland|Poles]], [[Russia]]ns and [[Slav]]s, among other groups. Some adherents of Nazi ideology continue to exist today.
*[[Racial segregation]] - (not always considered necessarily racist) the belief that the so-called races should be kept separate, either geographically or culturally.
*[[Racial purity]] - the belief that the various so-called races should be kept "pure" by not permitting interbreeding 
*[[White supremacy]] - the belief that those whose skin color is what is commonly described as being "white" (but strangely not the similarly colored [[Ainu]] people of Japan or [[albino]] members of non-European stock) are the superior race, or [[master race| 'master race']]. 
*Attitudes of [[suburb]] and [[gated community]] developers, who are often accused of pandering to racist views by emphasizing "crime risk" in more racially diverse downtowns, especially in [[North America]]. 
*[[Zionism is racism|Zionism]] in its modern political form, including "settlement" of areas established by UN resolutions to belong to Arabs.

=== Some examples of allegedly racist organisations ===
*[[Aryan Nation]] - a group of militant white supremacists
*[[Front National]] - a political party in [[France]] whose leader proposed deporting ''3 million non-Europeans'' from [[France]] in his [[1995]] presidential election bid
*[[Kahane Chai]] - an [[Israel]]i organization that preaches Jewish supremacy, named after [[Meir Kahane]]
*[[Ku Klux Klan]] - a group of American white supremacists, founded after the [[Civil War]]
*[[Nation of Islam]] - a group of African-Americans sometimes considered currently or historically racist
*[[White Australia Movement]] - a white supremacist organization in Australia

See also: [[affirmative action]], [[Afrocentrism]], [[anti-Semitism]], [[apartheid]], [[ascribed characteristics]], ''[[The Bell Curve]]'', [[black supremacy]], [[chauvinism]], [[Civil rights movement]], [[collectivism]], [[Criminal Blackman Myth]], [[discrimination]], [[essentialism]], [[ethnic stereotype]], [[ethnocentrism]], [[Eurocentrism]], [[genocide]], [[hate crime]], [[homophobia]], [[Islamophobia]], [[Jim Crow laws]], [[Ku Klux Klan]], [[master race]], [[Miscegenation]], [[Naziism]], [[nigger (word)|nigger]], [[race]], [[race riot]], [[racial segregation]], [[racialism]], [[Racism/racial and ethnic slurs]], [[sexism]], [[skinhead]], [[social stereotype]], [[White Australia policy]], [[white supremacy]], [[white trash]], [[wog]]

[[List of ethnic slurs]]

== External link ==

* [http://academic.udayton.edu/race/01race/race.htm What is Race?]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>