<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20021103173316|403968" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="25613" pageid="25613" ns="0" title="Racism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2002-11-04T15:28:49Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[nl:Racisme]]'''Racism''' refers to pejorative beliefs and/or harmful actions that are directed towards a person on the basis of that person’s race because of the belief that racial characteristics have some sort of effect on the individual's character or abilities.  Often, racism takes the form of racial supremacy.  For example, Race X supremacists believe in the inherent superiority of Race X, usually coupled with extreme hatred towards other races.

Types of discrimination
*''[[Racial prejudice]]'' is pre-formed personal opinions about individuals on the basis of their race.  (e.g. John thinks that Mary will have bad attribute X solely because Mary is a member of race Y)
*''[[Racial discrimination]]'' is differences in treatment of people on the basis of n characteristics which may be classified as racial, including skin color, cultural heritage, and religion.  (e.g. John refuses to hire Mary because she is of race Y)
*''Institutional'' or ''structural'' racial discrimination -- racial discrimination by governments, corporations, or other large organizations.  (e.g. Mary cannot get a job, despite her qualifications, because she is of race Y.)
*''Cultural'' racial prejudices or discrimination refers to a state of affairs when the de facto inferiority of a race is considered normal by another race.  (e.g. People &lt;I&gt;expect&lt;/I&gt; Mary to work a poorly paying job because she is of race Y, or accept this state of affairs without objection)
*''Historical economic disparity'' is a form of discrimination which is caused by past racism, affecting the present through primarily unconscious racist attitudes and actions.  (e.g. A member of Race Y, Mary, has her opportunities adversely affected (directly and/or indirectly) by the mistreatment of her ancestors of race Y)
*''[[Racialism]]'' is [[science|scientific]] or [[pseudoscience|pseudo-scientific]] claims about differences in ability among races.  (e.g. Dr. Smith writes a book claiming that members of race Y are, on average, less intelligent than members of race Z)

In addition to the basic types of discrimination above, racism can also be divided into two broader categories: racism against a minority (of a certain population) versus racism against a majority (of a certain population).  Examples of the former include the enslavement of [[Africa]]ns and continued repression of their descendants in the [[United States]].  The existence of the latter is often controversial, but agreed upon examples include racial [[apartheid]] in [[South Africa]], wherein whites (a minority) discriminated against blacks (a majority); this form of racism also occurred during the former colonial rule of such countries as [[Vietnam]] and [[India]] by [[France]] and the [[United Kingdom]].

‘’’Reverse racism’’’ is a highly controversial form of racism against a majority that refers to several ideas.  The current occurrence of reverse racism in the United States (where the term originated and is primarily used) is highly disputed.

In the United States, many people, largely conservative, criticize policies such as [[affirmative action]] as an example of reverse racism, and claim that it is systemic racially-based discrimination.  Supporters argue that affirmative action policies counteract the systemic and cultural racism against minorities by providing a balancing force, and that affirmative action does not qualify as racist because the policies are enacted by politicians (who are mostly part of the white majority in the United States) and directed towards their own race.

Some Americans believe that reverse racism exists in the United States, but that it is cultural racism, and not primarily systemic.  For example, some African-Americans discriminate against white people--this can be called reverse racism.

In addition, some white people believe that [[political correctness]] has led to a denigration of the white race, through percieved special attention paid towards minority races.  For example, they consider the existence of Black History Month (February) but not a White History Month, Hispanic History Month or Asian History Month to be de facto racism directed at the majority and non-black minorities.

Racism is and has been official policy in many countries.  In the [[1970s]], [[Uganda]] expelled tens of thousands of ethnic [[India|Indians]].  [[Malaysia]] currently enforces discriminatory laws limiting access to university education for [[China|Chinese]] students. Russia launched anti-Semitic [[pogroms]] against Jews in 1905 and after.

[[Racial profiling]], or prejudicial treatment of minorities by law enforcement officials, in the United States is another highly controversial example of racism.  Arguments on the subject tend to focus on whether it is cultural discrimination on the part of law enforcement officers, or an official policy of discrimination among law enforcement agencies.  Supporters of racial profiling also believe it is a necessary tool for law enforcement, because, they claim, members of certain minorities are more likely to commit crimes.  For example, most terrorists have been young Arab males, they claim, and so it is both logical and useful to have security officers at airports take special note of young Arab male fliers.  Critics dispute the numbers of criminals of various races (such as the existence of Christian, Hindi, Israeli and Latino terrorists; see [[racial profiling]] for more information on this aspect of the dispute) as well as the usefulness of racial profiling.  They claim, for example, that racially profiling young Arab male fliers at airports will only lead to increased recruitment of older, non-Arab and female terrorists.  In addition, many critics of racial profiling claim that it is an unconstitutional practice because it amounts to detaining individuals on the basis of what crimes they might commit or could possibly commit, instead of what crimes they have actually committed.

Some specific types of alleged racism:
*[[Afrocentrism]] - (not always considered racist); the belief that black African cultures were historically more powerful and influential than is widely believed
*[[Anti-Semitism]] - usually, racism directed towards Jews, though Arabs are sometimes included as well
*[[Apartheid]] - a system of racism, now abolished, that once existed in [[South Africa]]; some refer to current Israeli policies towards Palestinians as apartheid as well
*[[Aryan Nation]] - a group of militant white supremacists
*[[Black Panthers]] - a group of African-Americans sometimes considered currently or historically racist
*[[Black supremacy]] - the belief that those of African descent are the superior race
*[[Eurocentrism]] - the sometimes unconscious practice of historically and culturally focusing on white Europeans, to the exclusion of significant achievements of other races
*[[Kahane Chai]] - an [[Israel]]i organization that preaches Jewish supremacy, named after [[Meir Kahane]]
*[[Klu Klux Klan]] - a group of American white supremacists, founded after the [[Civil War]]
*[[Manifest Destiny]] - a historical form of racist belief, that white Americans have the right and duty to colonize the west and "civilize" the [[Native American]] inhabitants
*[[Nation of Islam]] - a group of African-Americans sometimes considered currently or historically racist
*[[Naziism]] - a historical form of national socialism, coupled with extreme racism, directed towards [[Gypsy|Gypsies]], [[Jew]]s, [[Poland|Poles]], [[Russia]]ns and [[Slav]]s, among other groups; some adherents continue to exist
*[[Racial segregation]] - (not always considered necessarily racist) the belief that the races should be kept separate, either geographically or culturally
*[[White Australia Movement]] - a white supremacist organization in Australia
*[[White supremacy]] - the belief that those of European (or only northern/western European, and sometimes excluding Ireland) descent are the superior race

See also: [[affirmative action]], [[Afrocentrism]], [[anti-Semitism]], [[apartheid]], [[ascribed characteristics]], [[Bell Curve]], [[Black Panthers]], [[black supremacy]], [[chauvinism]], [[Civil Rights Movement]], [[collectivism]], [[discrimination]], [[essentialism]], [[ethnic stereotype]], [[ethnocentrism]], [[Eurocentrism]], [[genocide]], [[hate crime]], [[homophobia]], [[Jim Crow laws]], [[Klu Klux Klan]], [[Naziism]], [[nigger]], [[race]], [[race riot]], [[racial segregation]], [[Racism/racial and ethnic slurs]], [[sexism]], [[skinhead]], [[social stereotype]], [[White Australia policy]], [[white supremacy]], [[white trash]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>