<?xml version="1.0"?><api batchcomplete=""><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="25613" pageid="25613" ns="0" title="Racism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2001-10-28T16:48:11Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[Racism]] is the political or ideological application of the concept of [[race]], especially in terms of racial superiority. 

A vernacular use of ''racism'' extends to any form of discrimination based on characteristics which may be classified as racial, including skin color, cultural heritage, and religion. This is also known as "racial discrimination".

Racism is and has been official policy in many countries.  In the [[1970s]] [[Uganda]] expelled tens of thousands of ethnic [[India|Indians]].  [[Malaysia]] has discriminatory laws limiting access to university education for the ethnic [[China|Chinese]].  Some forms of government sponsored racism are less overt.  For example, many police jurisdictions of the [[United States]] practice [[racial profiling]], where members of certain racial minorities are the targets of closer police scrutiny.

One specific kind of racism is [[anti-semitism]], racism against [[Jews]], which has been common in many countries in [[Europe]], [[North America]], and the [[Middle East]].  In the [[United States]] and elsewhere (notably [[Germany]]), white racists are behind a closely-watched [[white supremacy]] movement.

In [[1994]], a book called ''The Bell Curve: Intelligence and Class Structure in American Life,'' by [[Richard J. Herrnstein]] and [[Charles Murray]] (New York: Free Press), created a huge controversy in the United States.  ''(We're going to want to represent this controversy as fairly as possible...)''

Also see [[collectivism]], [[hate crime]], [[civil rights movement]], [[race]], [[white supremacy]], [[apartheid]],
[[race riot]], [[white trash]]

[[/racial and ethnic slurs]]--a discussion moved from "[[white trash]]"

[[/Talk]]
----
Here is the old version of this article:

'''Racism''' is the belief, or more often the attitude, that one race is superior to another race or races--that is, that persons of a particular race are inherently superior to people of another race, or of all other races--because race determines important moral and personal character traits and capacities.  [[Racist|Racists]] often believe that members of their own race are in need of protection from the allegedly inferior or superior race or races.  Racism is sometimes seen as a type of [[xenophobia]].

Closely related to racism is [[racial discrimination]], which is discrimination based on racial grounds.

Racism is and has been official policy in many countries.  In the [[1970s]] [[Uganda]] expelled tens of thousands of [[Indian]]s, merely because of their race.  [[Malaysia]] has discriminatory laws limiting university access to the ethnic [[China|Chinese]].

One specific kind of racism is [[anti-semitism]], racism against [[Jews]], which has been common in many countries in [[Europe]], [[North America]], and the [[Middle East]].  In the [[United States]] and elsewhere (notably [[Germany]]), white racists are behind a closely-watched [[white supremacy]] movement.

In [[1994]], a book called ''The Bell Curve: Intelligence and Class Structure in American Life,'' by [[Richard J. Herrnstein]] and [[Charles Murray]] (New York: Free Press), created a huge controversy in the United States.  ''(We're going to want to represent this controversy as fairly as possible...)''

Also see [[collectivism]], [[hate crime]], [[civil rights movement]], [[race]], [[white supremacy]], [[apartheid]], [[race riot]]

[[/Talk]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>