<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061113220923|87623829" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="25613" pageid="25613" ns="0" title="Racism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-11-13T22:16:07Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{cleanup|October 2006}} 
[[Image:ColoredDrinking.jpg|thumb|250px|An [[African-American]] man drinks out of the "colored only" water cooler at a [[racial segregation|racially segregated]] [[streetcar]] terminal in the [[United States]] in 1939.]]
'''Racism''' is commonly defined as a [[belief]] or [[doctrine]] where inherent biological differences among the various [[human]] races determine cultural or individual achievement, with a [[corollary]] that one's own [[race]] is superior and has the right to rule others.  &lt;ref name="freedict"&gt; {{cite web |http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/racism}}&lt;/ref &gt;  

The term racism is sometimes used to refer to preference for one's own ethnic group ([[ethnocentrism]]),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.hawaii.edu/cpis/psi/gender/gender_colonialism.html | title = Document equating ethnocentrism with racism&lt;/ref&gt; fear of difference ([[xenophobia]]), views or preferences against interbreeding of the races ([[miscegenation]]),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.oah.org/pubs/magazine/family/cruz-berson.html |title = Document equating views against miscegenation with racism}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[nationalism]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url = http://www.experiencefestival.com/nationalism_-_racism| title = Document equating nationalism with racism&lt;/ref&gt; regardless of any explicit belief in superiority or inferiority imbedded within such views or preferences. Racism has been used to justify social discrimination, [[racial segregation]] and violence, including [[genocide]].

The term racist, when used to describe someone who supports racism, has been a [[pejorative]] term since at least the 1940s, and the identification of a group or person as racist is nearly always controversial.

Racism is also used commonly in [[comedy]]. 

==Definitions of racism==
{{Unreferencedsect}}
{{Further|[[Race (historical definitions)]]}}
When racism, a belief, is applied in practice, it takes forms such as prejudice, [[Discrimination#Racial discrimination|discrimination]], segregation or [[subordination]]. Racism can more narrowly refer to a ''system'' of oppression, such as [[institutional racism]].

Historian Barbara Field argued in "Slavery, Race and Ideology in the United States of America" that racism is a "historical phenomenon" which does not explain racial ideology.{{fact}} She suggests that investigators should consider the term to be an [[United States|American]] [[rhetorical device]], with a historical explanation. She suggests that using race as a word with real meaning is a common error akin to [[superstition]]. Other scholars, however, say that races do exist, and the concept has significant meaning.

Organizations and institutions that put racism into action discriminate against, and marginalize, a class of people who share a common racial designation. The term racism is usually applied to the [[dominant]] group in a society, because it is that group that has the means to oppress others. The term can also apply to any individual or group, regardless of social status or dominance. 

Racism can be both overt and covert. Individual racism sometimes consists of overt acts by individuals, which can result in violence or the destruction of property.  Institutional racism is often more covert and subtle. It often appears within the operation of established and respected forces in the society, and frequently receives less public condemnation than the overt type.

[[W.E.B. DuBois]] argued that [[racialism]] is the belief that differences between the races exist, be they [[Biological process|biological]], [[social]], [[psychological]], or in the realm of the [[soul]]. He argued that racism is using this belief to promote the belief that one's particular race is superior to the others.

According to Jared Diamond in his work ''[[Guns, Germs and Steel]]'', race is essentially a social and historical construction. It has no real basis in science, nor can it be used to explain why Europe gained the upper hand in world conquests.

==Academic racism==
Refers to the tradition of prejudicial study of people's societies and cultures, languages and peoples in circles of academia. With regards to African people its basis was formed during slavery and colonialism to remove any form of noble claim from the victims of these systems, thus reducing them and justifying their position as “natural” and a continuation of their historical “worthlessness.” Legendary quotes come from some of Europe's most respected scholars such as, Darwin, David Hume, and Immanuel Kant. David Hume, also said, ‘I am apt to suspect the Negroes to be naturally inferior to the Whites. There scarcely ever was a civilised nation of that complexion, nor even any individual, eminent either in action or in speculation. No ingenious manufacture among them, no arts, no sciences”. In the nineteenth century the German philosopher Hegel simply declared ‘ Africa is no historical part of the world.’ This openly racist view, that Africa had no history, was repeated by Hugh Trevor-Roper, Regius Professor of History at Oxford University, as late as 1963.

===Scientific racism===
[[Image:Races and skulls.png|200px|right|thumb|Nott and Gliddon's ''Indigenous races of the earth'' (1857) used misleading imagery to suggest that "Negroes" ranked between whites and [[chimpanzee]]s. Note the different angles at which the "white" and "negro" skulls are positioned. Nott and Gliddon's work is considered one of the classics of [[scientific racism]].]]

[[Image:Kniga donski.jpg|200px|right|thumb|[[Alexander Donski]]'s ''Ethnological differences between Macedonians and Bulgarians'' (2000). Pictured on the left column are: [[Alexander the Great]], [[Gotse Delchev]] and [[Metodija Andonov Cento]]. On the right column: two alleged pictures of Middle Age Bulgars, and the late [[Todor Zhivkov]]. Note how misleading imagery is used to emphasize what the author perceives to be an "ethnological difference" - A statue of a person of great prominence ([[Alexander the Great]]) on the left is compared with a alleged facial reconstruction of a [[Bulgars|Bulgar]]. On the second row a photo of a person lived in the late 19th century is compared to a drawing. On the third row, a picture of a middle aged person is compared to that of a bald person in his eighties, wearing glasses]]

{{main|Scientific racism}}
[[Scientific racism]] refers to the use of science (or the veneer of science) to justify and support racist beliefs. The use of science to justify racist beliefs goes back at least to the early 18th century, though it gained most of its influence in the mid-19th century. Works like [[Arthur Gobineau]]'s ''[[An Essay on the Inequality of the Human Races]]'' (1853-1855) attempted to frame racism within the terms of biological difference among human beings, and with the rise of theories of [[evolution]] after the work of [[Charles Darwin]] became well-known, it became common to consider some races more evolved than others. These points of view were very common within the scientific community at the time—even Darwin, who was an active [[abolitionist]] and considered all humans to be of the same species (against a trend of [[polygenism]] popular in anthropology at the time) believed that there were inherent biological differences in the mental capacities of different races. Ideologies such as [[social Darwinism]] and [[eugenics]] used and reinforced many of these views.

There were also scientists who argued against biological reenforcement of racism, even if they believed that biological races did exist (though some did not). In the sciences of anthropology and biology, though, these were minority positions until the mid-20th century. During the rise of [[Nazism]] in Germany, many scientists in Western nations worked to de-bunk the racial theory on which the regime rested its claims of superiority. This, combined with repulsion to [[Nazi eugenics]] and the racial motivations behind [[the Holocaust]], lead to a re-orientation of opinion around scientific research into race in the years following [[World War II]]. Changes within scientific disciplines—such as the rise of [[Franz Boas|Boasian]] school of anthropology in the United States—also contributed to this shift. Since then, many of the scientific studies which some claim support racist claims have since been methodologically debunked by scientists with specifically anti-racist agendas, such as [[Stephen J. Gould]].  However, Gould himself has been accused by a number of scientists of misrepresenting the positions of those he engages, being politically motivated in his attacks, and being selective in his use of material to those ends.

The status of the concept of biological race remains very controversial within science, though practically no mainstream scientists admit to using scientific data to justify racist beliefs. Some scientists, such as [[Arthur Jensen]] and [[Richard Lynn]], have argued that the threat of being labeled as a "scientific racist" has made the scientific study of race and racial differences politically [[taboo]] and has stifled true scientific discourse. These charges have surfaced most often during the study of [[intelligence]], [[IQ]], and the concept in [[psychometrics]] termed [[general intelligence factor]].  Many scientists, though, believe that there is no evidence for typological notions of biological race, nor scientific justifications for racist beliefs.

==Individual racism==
===Racial [[prejudice]]===
This refers to pre-formed personal opinions about individuals on the basis of their race.

===Crypto-racism and aversive racism===
Elmar Holenstein uses the term ''crypto-racism'' as a synonym what he calls "hidden racism".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://them.polylog.org/4/ahe-en.htm | title = Document describing crypto-racism as hidden racism|work=A Dozen Rules of Thumb for Avoiding Intercultural Misunderstandings |publisher=Forum For Intercultural Philosophy}}&lt;/ref&gt; while blogger Josh Marshall uses it in contrast to "closet racism" (usage example [http://www.talkingpointsmemo.com/archives/009423.php]).

Some scholars use the term "aversive racism" to refer to the “subtle, unintentional form of bias that is presumed to characterize a substantial proportion of White liberals” (Son Hing et al, 275).&lt;ref&gt;Leanne S. Son Hing, Greg A. Chung-Yan, Robert Grunfeld, Lori K. Robichaud, and Mark P. Zanna.“Exploring the Discrepancy Between Implicit and Explicit Prejudice: A Test of Aversive Racism Theory” in &lt;em&gt;Social Motivation: Conscious and Unconscious Processes&lt;/em&gt;.  Joseph P. Forgas, Kipling D. Williams, Simon M. Laham,eds. Cambridge University Press. 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;  

Because they have internalized liberal egalitarian values, aversive racists are motivated to experience themselves as being nonprejudiced, but at the same time have unconscious, unavoidable racist feelings or judgements of which they’re typically unaware (ibid).  Aversive racists will express these racist feelings or judgements in situations where a non-racialized justification to do so exists.  "Thus, aversive racists are able to discriminate without acknowledging their prejudice because they excuse or justify their behaviour on‘reasonable’ grounds” (ibid, 290). It's likely that most people living in a liberal democratic, racially-structured society are aversive racists.

===Same-race racism===
This can occur where members of one race associate behaviors or appearances of other members of their race as being in relation to another race which is regarded negatively. For example, there have been issues with darker-skinned [[African-American]]s disliking lighter-skinned African-Americans because of their lighter shade of skin, which may be associated with White parentage at some point in their genealogy (but may also not). A form of cultural racism (see above) can also be related to this, where members of a racial group are chastized by members of their own group for co-opting a culture which is perceived to be associated with another race (for example, there exists a stigma in many African-American communities against "acting White").

==Institutional racism==
{{main|Institutional racism}}
===Racism as official government policy===
{{See|Institutional racism|State racism|Racial profiling}}
[[Institutional racism]] or structural racial discrimination is racial discrimination by governments, corporations, or other large organizations with the power to influence the lives of many individuals. See [[Affirmative Action]]. [[Nazi Germany]]'s [[state racism]] is the most famous example, along with [[History of South Africa in the apartheid era|South Africa during the apartheid era]].  Examples of racism in [[United States]] [[domestic policy]] include [[slavery]] and discrimination against [[Native Americans in the United States|Native Americans]].  

The practice of racist [[Jim Crow laws]] by [[Southern states]] was common until the [[1964 Civil Rights Act]] gave the Federal government more enforcement power.  During World War II, people of [[Japanese people|Japanese]] ancestry who were living on the [[West Coast of the United States|west coast]] of the U.S. were imprisoned in [[Japanese American internment|internment camps]]. Other examples of racism in U.S. domestic policy included human experimentation without consent, the most famous case being the [[Tuskegee Syphilis Study]] in which Black males infected with syphilis were purposefully not treated in order to study the long-term effects of the disease. 

In the 1970s, [[Uganda|Ugandan]] President [[Idi Amin]] expelled tens of thousands of ethnic [[India|Indians]]. [http://www.bbc.co.uk/insideout/west/series2/ugandan_asians.shtml].  Until 2003, [[Malaysia]] enforced discriminatory policies limiting access to university education for ethnic [[China|Chinese]] and Indian students who were citizens of Malaysia by birth, and many other policies explicitly favoring [[bumiputra]]s (Malays) remain in force{{citation needed}}. 

Some critics, including [[Gore Vidal#Views on 2001-09-11 terrorist attacks against the United States|Gore Vidal]], British MP [[George Galloway#Political views and characteristics|George Galloway]] and [[Ward Churchill]], have suggested that [[United Kingdom|British]] and United States foreign policy in the [[Middle East]] is racist.  George Galloway has also claimed that Arabs in the [[Guantanamo Bay detainment camp]], Iraqis in the [[Abu Ghraib prison]] and other jails, and civilians in [[Iraq]], are not being treated as human beings by the United States{{fact}}.

[[Racial profiling]] of minorities by [[law enforcement]] officials is considered by some people to be a form of racism. Some claim that profiling young Arab males at airports will only lead to increased recruitment by terrorists of old non-Arab females, as well as Arab males who can "pass" as a non-Arab{{fact}}. Some state that this profiling is unnecessary, as it brings about the mistrust of many people{{fact}}.  Some critics claim that racial profiling of citizens in the United States is an [[Constitutionality|unconstitutional]] practice because the government is infringing upon an individual's freedom just on the basis of what a racial group is believed to be more likely to do (in this case, commit [[terrorism]]).{{fact}}  French philosopher [[Michel Foucault]] argued in ''[[Discipline and Punish]]'' (1975) that such profiling shifts the emphasis from the act itself (the crime) to the person (the "criminal"), and that a general tendency of "disciplinary societies" is to create the psychological category of "[[delinquent]]".

Based on the [[Mandal commission]] report submitted during 1980, the [[Indian Government]] decided to reserve 27% more seats to students from [[Other BackwardCastes|Backwards classes]] in all educational institutions(Government &amp; Private) and bring the total reservation percentage up to 50%.  Subsequent surveys conducted by the [[Indian Government]] indicated that Population figures given by Mandal commission is exaggerated.[http://www.southasianmedia.net/cnn.cfm?id=292238&amp;category=Social%20Sectors&amp;Country=INDIA] [http://www.thehindubusinessline.com/2006/05/18/stories/2006051800251000.htm] Certain [[India]]n [[states and territories of India|states]], such as [[Tamil Nadu]], reserve around 69% of the total seats in educational institutions and Government jobs to students belonging to certain castes.[http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/articleshow/msid-39296115,prtpage-1.cms.].Many analysts and Government surveys[http://mospi.nic.in/rept%20_%20pubn/ftest.asp?rept_id=469&amp;type=NSSO surveys] have indicated Other Backward Classes or comparable to Upper Castes in many spheres of life.[http://www.business-standard.com/common/storypage.php?autono=264481&amp;leftnm=4&amp;subLeft=0&amp;chkFlg=]

In recent years, so called upper castes are able to secure only 2.3 percentage of total seats in professional education as against their population of 13% in states like [[Tamilnadu]][http://www.thehindubusinessline.com/2006/05/18/stories/2006051800251000.htm][http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reservation_in_India#Caste_Based_Reservations_in_Tamil_Nadu].A person born in a backward caste is eligible for reservation irrespective of their economical or social status. Many politicians, film stars, and rich industrialists also reap reservation benefits.[http://www.expressindia.com/fullstory.php?newsid=72900].  Accusations have been made that the [[Indian parliament]], has amended [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reservation_in_India#Reservations_and_Judiciary] the constitution whenever a court judgement was not in favour of reservation decisions

===Economics and racism===
Historical economic or social disparity is alleged to be a form of [[discrimination]] which is caused by past racism, affecting the present generation through deficits in the formal education and other kinds of preparation in the parents' generation, and, through primarily unconscious racist attitudes and actions on members of the general population. (E.g. A member of Race Y, Mary, has her opportunities adversely affected (directly and/or indirectly) by the mistreatment of her ancestors of race Y.)

Some scholars have suggested that capitalism has played a large role in promoting racism especially socioeconomic racism. The Western hemisphere slave trade and colonialist activities were mostly conducted by the earliest capitalist economies ie; Spain, Great Britain, the United States and the Netherlands. [http://.www.zmag.org/CrisesCurEvts/bohmerrace.htm][http://.race.eserver.org/toward-a-theory-of-racism.html ].Critics have pointed out that a slave labor economy was the sometimes considered ultimate form of capitalism because the capitalists made pure profits because they used free labor.[http://.flag.blackened.net/revolt/talks/racism.html].

[[Global apartheid]] is a phrase used by those who argue that the international economic and political system is racist and is designed so that a white minority internationally accrue more wealth and power and enjoy more human and legal rights than the non-white world majority.

===Racial discrimination===
This is differences in treatment of people on the basis of characteristics which may be classified as racial, including skin color and place of birth. (e.g. Mary refuses to hire John because he is of race Y.) This is a concept not unanimously agreed upon. While this usually refers to discrimination against minority racial groups in Western societies, it can also (arguably) refer to the opposite situation, and in that case is often called [[reverse discrimination]] when it is due to [[affirmative action]] or other attempts to remedy past or current discrimination against minority racial groups. Many do not consider this racism, but simply a form of discrimination.

Researchers at the [[University of Chicago]] (Marianne Bertrand) and [[Harvard University]] ([[Sendhil Mullainathan]]) found in a 2003 study that there was widespread discrimination in the workplace against job applicants whose names were merely perceived as "sounding black." These applicants were 50% less likely than candidates perceived as having "white-sounding names" to receive callbacks for interviews, no matter their level of previous experience. Results were stronger for higher quality résumés. The researchers view these results as strong evidence of unconscious biases rooted in the [[United States]]' long history of discrimination. This is an example of structural racism, because it shows a widespread established belief system. Another example is apartheid in [[South Africa]], and the system of [[Jim Crow laws|Jim Crow]] laws in the [[United States of America]]. Another source is lending inequities of banks, and so-called [[redlining]].

A number of international treaties have sought to end racial discrimination. The [[United Nations]] uses the definition of racial discrimination laid out in the ''International Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Racial Discrimination'' and adopted in 1966:

:''...any distinction, exclusion, restriction or preference based on race, color, descent, or national or ethnic origin which has the purpose or effect of nullifying or impairing the recognition, enjoyment or exercise, on an equal footing, of human rights and fundamental freedoms in the political, economic, social, cultural or any other field of public life.''.

In 2000, the European Union banned racism along with many other forms of social discrimination: "Article 21 of the charter prohibits discrimination on any ground such as sex, race, color, ethnic or social origin, genetic features, language, religion or belief, political or any other opinion, membership of a national minority, property, disability, age or sexual orientation and also discrimination on the grounds of nationality."[http://europa.eu.int/comm/justice_home/fsj/rights/discrimination/printer/fsj_rights_discrim_en.htm]

===Reverse racism===
{{See|Reverse discrimination}}
Reverse racism is a controversial term used to describe attitudes, behaviors, and policies which are racially discriminatory in a manner which is contrary (reverse) to a historical pattern of racial discrimination.  Usually a historically sociopolitically non-dominant race is perceived to benefit at the expense of a historically sociopolitically dominant race.

[[Affirmative action]] (sometimes called [[positive discrimination]] outside the U.S.) is a government policy or a program of giving preferences to members of particular social groups, including races. Opponents contend that such preferential treatment by the government is a form of institutionalized reverse racism which unfairly discriminates against individuals by racial category.  Proponents contend that such preferential treatment promotes [[racial integration]] and economic equality of groups which have been affected by racism.

Many opponents of the term reverse racism claim that use of the term itself is [[pejorative]], racist and no more legitimate than any other form of racism. Some believe the term to be used almost exclusively against their racial group, implying that only members of their race are capable of being racists.  Many opponents of the concept say that racism is by definition exclusively of the race in power.{{fact}}

A more literal and modern interpretation of the term "reverse racism" refers to the idea of projecting racial bias onto another person's behavior that does not pertain to their own race. For example, saying that a Caucasian who dresses and talks like a rapper is "acting black", is an example of reverse racism; it does not show racial bias against the person in question, but perpetuates racial roles with the sentiment that races are expected to act or dress a specific way. Another example is to automatically assume that one or both members of an interracial couple have a "race fetish" for their significant other's race, rather than assuming the relationship is based on other factors. This is reverse racism due to the projection of a possibly false racial bias onto another person.

==Ideological racism==
===Racialism===
{{Main|Racialism}}
This is a term often found within [[white separatist]] [[literature]], inferring an emphasis in [[Race|racial origin]] in [[social]] matters. Racism infers an assumption of [[racial superiority]] and a harmful intent, whereas separatists sometimes prefer the term racialism, indicating a strong interest in matters of race without a necessary inference of superiority or a desire to be harmful to others. Rather their focus is on [[racial segregation]] and [[white pride]]. In most English dictionaries currently there is no sharp distinction between "racism" and "racialism".

===Antisemitism===
{{Antisemitism}}
{{Main|Antisemitism|History of antisemitism}}

Antisemitism is a specific case of racism targeting the [[Jew]]s, although scholars argue whether it should be considered a ''[[sui generis]]'' specie or not. 
[[Image:Nurembergracechart.jpg|thumb|left|250px|The [[Nuremberg Laws]] of 1935 used a [[pseudo-science|pseudo-scientific]] theory for racial discrimination against Jews. People with four German grandparents (white circles) were of "German blood," while people were classified as Jews if they descended from three or more Jewish grandparents (black circles in top row right). One or two Jewish grandparents made someone "[[Mischling|mixed blood]]." (1935 chart from [[Nazi Germany]])]]

Scholars distinguish traditional, ''religious antisemitism'', which derives from [[Christianity|Christian]] accusation of the [[deicide]] (cleared at the [[Second Vatican Council]] in 1965), with 19th-20th centuries ''[[racial antisemitism]]'', which ultimately led to [[the Holocaust]] in which about 6 million European Jews, 1.5 million of them children, were systematically murdered. ''See also [[Holocaust denial]].''

In Medieval Europe, massive violent attacks against Jews have been recorded since at least the [[12th century]]. In the [[Middle Ages]] [[Iberian peninsula]], the system of [[limpieza de sangre]] (cleanliness of blood) ostracized [[New Christians]] (offspring of [[Sephardi]]c Jews who were forced to convert to [[Catholicism]]) from the rest of society. In [[Portugal]], the legal distinction between New and Old Christians was ended in 1772.

Expelled en masse from [[History of the Jews in England|England]], [[History of the Jews in France|France]], [[History of the Jews in Spain|Spain]] and most other [[Western Europe]]an countries at various times, and persecuted in [[History of the Jews in Germany|Germany]] in the [[14th century]], many Jews accepted [[Casimir III of Poland|Casimir III]]'s invitation to settle in [[History of the Jews in Poland|Polish]]-controlled areas of [[Eastern Europe]]. 

The traditional measures of keeping the [[Russian Empire]] free of Jews failed when the main territory of [[Polish-Lithuanian Commonwealth]] was annexed during the [[Partitions of Poland]]. As large Jewish populations were taken over by Russia, [[Catherine II of Russia|Catherine II]] established the [[Pale of Settlement]] in 1791. The official [[segregation]] of the [[History of the Jews in Russia and the Soviet Union|Russian Jews]] was compounded by waves of [[pogroms]] and oppressive legislation such as the 1882 [[May Laws]] and led to mass [[emigration]] and political activism. 

Modern European antisemitism has its origin in 19th century [[pseudo-science|pseudo-scientific]] theories that viewed the Jewish people as entirely different from the [[Aryan]], or [[Proto-Indo-Europeans|Indo-European]], populations. In this view, Jews are not opposed on account of their [[religion]], but on account of their supposed hereditary or genetic [[racial characteristics]]. The growth of [[nationalism]] in many countries viewed Jews as a separate and often "alien" nation within the countries in which Jews resided. Such sentiments were exposed in the [[Dreyfus affair]] in 1890s France. ''See also [[Rootless cosmopolitan]]ism.''

The rise of views of the Jews as a malevolent "race" generated antisemitic [[conspiracy theories]] that the Jews, as a group, were plotting to control or otherwise influence the world. From the early infamous Russian literary [[hoax]], ''[[The Protocols of the Elders of Zion]]'', published by the Tsar's [[okhranka|secret police]], a key element of antisemitic thought has been that Jews influence or control the world. 

In a recent incarnation, extremist groups, such as [[Neo-Nazi]] parties and [[Islamist]] groups, claim that the aim of [[Zionism]] is global domination; they call this the Zionist conspiracy and use it to support antisemitism. This position is associated with [[fascism]] and [[Nazism]], though it is becoming a tendency within parts of the [[Left wing politics|Left]] as well, and termed [[New antisemitism]].

==History of racism==
:''Related article: [[Racism by country]].''
===The medieval discourse of ''race struggle''===
Although anti-Semitism has a long European history, racism itself is frequently described as a ''modern'' phenomenon. In the view of the French intellectual [[Michel Foucault]], the first formulation of racism emerged in the [[Middle Ages]] as the "[[discourse]] of race struggle", a historical and political discourse which Foucault opposed to the philosophical and juridical discourse of [[sovereignty]].&lt;ref&gt;Michel Foucault, ''Society Must Be Defended'' (1976-77)&lt;/ref&gt; According to Foucault, this first appearance of racism as a theoretical discourse (as opposed to simple [[xenophobia]], which some might argue has existed in all places and times) may be found during the 1688 [[Glorious Revolution]] in [[Great Britain]], in [[Edward Coke]] or [[John Lilburne]]'s work. 

However, this "discourse of race struggle", as interpreted by Foucault, must be distinguished from 19th century biological racism, also known as [[race science]] or [[scientific racism]]. Indeed, this medieval discourse has many points of difference with modern racism. First of all, in this "discourse of race struggle", "race" is not considered a biological notion &amp;mdash; which would divide [[humanity]] into biological groups &amp;mdash; but as a ''historical notion''. Moreover, this discourse is opposed to the sovereign's discourse: it is used by the [[bourgeoisie]], the people and the aristocracy as a mean of struggle against the monarchy. 

This discourse, which first appeared in Great Britain, was then carried on in France by people such as [[Boulainvilliers]], [[Nicolas Fréret]], and then, during the [[French Revolution]], [[Sieyès]], and afterward [[Augustin Thierry]] and [[Cournot]]. Boulainvilliers, which created the matrix of such racist discourse in medieval France, conceived the "race" as something closer to the sense of "nation", that is, in his times, "[[people]]". Hence, he conceived France as divided between various nations &amp;mdash; the unified [[nation-state]] is, of course, here an [[anachronism]] &amp;mdash; which themselves formed different "races". Boulainvilliers opposed the [[absolute monarchy]], who tried to bypass the [[aristocracy]] by establishing a direct relationship to the [[Third Estate]]. Thus, he created this theory of the French aristocrats as being the descendants of foreign invaders, whom he called the "[[Franks]]", while the Third Estate constituted according to him the autochthonous, vanquished [[Gallo-Romans]], who were dominated by the Frankish aristocracy as a consequence of the [[right of conquest]]. 

Henceforth, medieval racism was opposed to [[nationalism]] and the nation-state: the [[comte de Montlosier]], in exile during the French Revolution, who borrowed Boulainvilliers' discourse on the "Nordic race" as being the French aristocracy that invaded the plebeian "Gauls", thus showed his despise for the Third Estate calling it "this new people born of slaves... [[miscegenation|mixture of all races and of all times]]". While 19th century racism is related to nationalism (some authors have opposed a "close nationalism", based on racism, etc., towards an "open nationalism", based on the [[universalism|universalist]] conception of the nation, etc.), medieval racism precisely divides the nation into various non-biological "races", which are the consequences of historical conquests and [[social conflict]]s.

===19th century transformation of medieval discourse===
{{See|Scientific racism}}
Michel Foucault thus traces the genealogy of modern racism to this medieval "historical and political discourse of race struggle". According to him, it divided itself in the 19th century according to two rival lines: on one hand, it was incorporated by racists, biologists and [[eugenicists]], who gave it the modern sense of "race" and, even more, transformed this popular discourse into a "[[state racism]]" (Nazism); on the other hand, [[Marxism|Marxists]] also seized this discourse, transforming the [[essentialist]] notion of "race" into the historical notion of "[[class struggle]]", defined by socially structured position: capitalist or proletarian.

Thus, biological racism was invented in the 19th century. [[Arthur de Gobineau]]'s ''[[An Essay on the Inequality of the Human Races]]'' (1853-55) may be considered as one of the first theorizations of this new racism, founded on an essentialist notion of race, and which would progressively tie itself to nationalism and to the state, creating this new form of nationalism which appeared in the [[New Imperialism]] period and, in France, in the midst of the [[Dreyfus Affair]]. [[Hannah Arendt]] has shown in ''[[The Origins of Totalitarianism]]'' (1951) the emergence of "continental [[imperialism]]s", i.e. [[pan-Germanism]] and [[pan-Slavism]], both racist [[ideology|ideologies]] which would play a decisive role after the 1919 [[Treaty of Versailles]]. 

Other famous authors include [[Edouard Drumont]], an anti-Semitic French author; [[Vacher de Lapouge]]'s "anthroposociology"; [[Herder]], who applied race to nationalist theory to develop militant ethnic nationalism; [[Houston Stewart Chamberlain|H.S. Chamberlain]] at the end of the 19th century (a British citizen who [[naturalization|naturalized]] himself as German because of his admiration for the "[[Aryan]] race"); [[Madison Grant]], a renowned [[eugenicist]], author of ''[[The Passing of the Great Race]]'' (1916)... Such authors posited the historical existence of national races such as German and French, branching from basal races supposed to have existed for millennia, such as the [[Aryan race]], and believed political boundaries should mirror these supposed racial ones.

===Ethnic conflicts===
{{See|Ethnicity}}
Debates over the origins of racism often suffer from a lack of clarity over the term. Many use the term "racism" to refer to more general phenomena, such as [[xenophobia]] and [[ethnocentrism]], although scholars attempt to clearly distinguish those phenomena from racism as an [[ideology]] or from [[scientific racism]], which has little to do with ordinary xenophobia.

Others conflate recent forms of racism with earlier forms of ethnic and national conflict. In most cases, ethno-national conflict seems to owe to conflict over land and strategic resources. In some cases [[ethnicity]] and [[nationalism]] were harnessed to rally [[combatant]]s in wars between great religious empires (for example, the Muslim Turks and the Catholic Austro-Hungarians).

Notions of race and racism often have played central roles in such ethnic conflicts. Historically, when an adversary is identified as "other" based on notions of race or ethnicity (particularly when "other" is construed to mean "inferior"), the means employed by the self-presumed "superior" party to appropriate territory, human chattel, or material wealth often have been more ruthless, more brutal, and less constrained by [[morality|moral]] or [[ethics|ethical]] considerations.

One example of the brutalizing and dehumanizing effects of racism was the attempt to [[Population history of American indigenous peoples#Deliberate infection.3F|deliberately infect]] [[Native Americans in the United States|Native Americans]] with smallpox during [[Pontiac's Rebellion]] in 1763, itself a war intended to [[ethnic cleansing|ethnically cleanse]] the "other" (Anglo-Americans) from Native American land.

According to historian Daniel Richter, Pontiac's Rebellion saw the emergence on both sides of the conflict of "the novel idea that all Native people were 'Indians,' that all Euro-Americans were 'Whites,' and that all on one side must unite to destroy the other." (Richter, ''Facing East from Indian Country'', p. 208)

In the Western world, racism evolved, twinned with the doctrine of [[white supremacy]], and helped fuel the [[Europe|European]] exploration, conquest, and colonization of much of the rest of the world -- especially after [[Christopher Columbus]] reached the Americas. [[Basil Davidson]] insists in his documentary, ''[[Africa: Different but Equal]]'', that racism, in fact, only just recently surfaced—as late as the 1800s, due to the need for a justification of slavery in the Americas. The idea of slavery as an "equal-opportunity employer" was denounced with the introduction of Christian theory in the West.

Maintaining that Africans were "subhuman" was the only loophole in the then accepted law that "men are created equal" that would allow for the sustenance of the [[Triangular Trade]]. New peoples in the Americas, possible slaves, were encountered, fought, and ultimately subdued, but then due to western diseases, their population decreased innumerably. Through both influences, theories about "race" developed, and these helped many to justify the differences in position and treatment of people whom they categorized as belonging to different races (see Eric Wolf's ''Europe and the People without History'').

Some people like [[Juan Ginés de Sepúlveda]] have argued during the [[Valladolid controversy]] in the middle of the 16th century, that the [[Indigenous peoples of the Americas|Native Americans]] were natural slaves because they had no "souls". In Asia, the Chinese and Japanese Empires were both strong colonial powers, with the Chinese making colonies and vassal states of much of East Asia throughout history, and the Japanese doing the same in the 19th-20th centuries. In both cases, the Asian imperial powers believed they were ethnically and raciacial prefrences too.  

===European colonialism===
[[Image:Völkerschau (Human Zoo) Stuttgart1928.jpg|right|thumb|300px|[[Human Zoo]] (''Völkerschau'') in [[Stuttgart]] (Germany) in 1928.]]
{{Main|Colonialism}}
Authors such as [[Hannah Arendt]], in her 1951 book ''[[The Origins of Totalitarianism]]'', have pointed out how the racist [[ideology]] ("popular racism") developed at the end of the 19th century helped legitimize the [[New Imperialism|imperialist conquests]] of foreign territories, and the crimes that accompanied it (such as the [[Herero and Namaqua Genocide]], 1904-1907). [[Auguste Comte]]'s [[positivism|positivist]] ideology of necessary [[social progress]] as a consequence of [[scientific progress]] lead many Europeans to believe in the inherent superiority of the "White Race" over non-whites.  

[[Rudyard Kipling]]'s poem on ''[[The White Man's Burden]]'' (1899) is one of the most famous illustrations of such belief, though also thought to be a satirical vantage of such imperialism. Racist ideology thus helped legitimize subjugation, slavery and the dismantling of the traditional societies of indigenous peoples, which were thus conceived as humanitarian obligations as a result of these racist rationalizations. Other colonialists recognized the depravity of their actions but persisted for personal gain and there are some Europeans during the time period who objected to the injustices caused by colonialism and lobbied on behalf of aboriginal peoples. Thus, when the so-called "[[Hottentot Venus]]" was displayed in England in the beginning of the 19th century, the African Association publicly opposed itself to this shameful exhibition. The same year that Kipling published his poem, [[Joseph Conrad]] published ''[[Heart of Darkness]]'' (1899), a clear criticism of the [[Congo Free State]] owned by [[Leopold II of Belgium]].

[[Human zoo]]s were an important means of bolstering ''popular racism'' by connecting it to [[scientific racism]]: they were both objects of public curiosity and of [[anthropology]] and [[anthropometry]].&lt;ref&gt; [http://migs.concordia.ca/occpapers/zoo.htm On A Neglected Aspect Of Western Racism], Kurt Jonassohn, December 2000 &lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt; {{cite news | authors=Pascal Blanchard, Sandrine Lemaire and Nicolas Bancel | title=Human zoos - Racist theme parks for Europe's colonialists | publisher=[[Le Monde Diplomatique]] | date=August 2000 | url=http://mondediplo.com/2000/08/07humanzoo}} {{en icon}}; {{cite news | title= Ces zoos humains de la République coloniale | publisher=[[Le Monde diplomatique]]  | date=August 2000|url=http://www.monde-diplomatique.fr/2000/08/BANCEL/14145.html}} {{fr icon}} (available to everyone) &lt;/ref&gt; [[Joice Heth]], an African-American slave, was displayed by [[Phineas Taylor Barnum|P.T. Barnum]] in 1836, a few years after the exhibition of [[Saartjie Baartman]], the "Hottentot Venus", in England. Such exhibitions became common in the New Imperialism period, and remained so until [[World War II]]. 

Congolese pygmy [[Ota Benga]] was displayed in 1906 by [[eugenicist]] [[Madison Grant]], head of the [[Bronx Zoo]], as an attempt to illustrate the "missing link" between humans and orangutans: thus, racism was tied to [[Darwinism]], creating a [[social Darwinism]] ideology which tried to ground itself in [[Charles Darwin|Darwin]]'s scientific discoveries. The 1931 Paris [[Colonial Exhibition]] displayed [[Kanaks]] from [[New Caledonia]].&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.port.ac.uk/special/france1815to2003/chapter6/interviews/filetodownload,18533,en.pdf The Colonial Exhibition of May 1931] (PDF) by Michael G. Vann, History Dept., [[Santa Clara University]], USA &lt;/ref&gt;  A "Congolese village" was on display as late as 1958 at the [[Expo '58|Brussels' World Fair]].

===Racism in the United States===
{{Main|Racism in the United States}}
====Racism against Native Americans====
The [[Native Americans]] have faced racism in the United States since the days of [[Colonial America]]. Indeed, in 1606, Marc Lescarbot's "The Theatre of Neptune in New France" cast First nations as "Savages" who offer their complete subordination to the colonial masters. While the "Savages" were played by Frenchmen, the audience was composed of people from the Mi'kmaq Nation, setting a disturbing precedent.

The Native Americans were massacred by US forces in the 19th century, which some claim was genocide  [http://www.iearn.org/hgp/aeti/aeti-1997/native-americans.html ] [http://www.wicocomico-indian-nation.com/pages/genocide.html ].  US President Andrew Jackson was quoted as saying that" the only good Indian is a dead Indian" [http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/aia/part4/4p2959.html]. Native Americans continue to face struggles. The Shoshone nation has accused the US government of racism for testing nuclear weapons close to their tribal lands.[http://nuclearfiles.org/.../subcritical_article-shoshone-against-testinghtm ] [http://www.indiancountry.com/content.cfm?id=1096410030&amp;CFID=541633&amp;].
[http://www.wsdp.org/un_cerd_wsdp.htm].

====Slavery in the United States====
{{Main|Slavery in the United States}}
Contention over the morality and legality of the institution of slavery was one of the cardinal issues which led to the [[American Civil War]].  The failed attempt at secession by the Southern United States led to the [[Thirteenth_Amendment_to_the_United_States_Constitution|Thirteenth Amendment]] to the Constitution, which was the official end of legal slavery in the United States.

Emancipated blacks in the United States still had to struggle against institutional racism, forced segregation, violation of voting rights, and even terrorism.  The [[Ku Klux Klan]] is perhaps the most notorious of these organizations espousing racist ideologies and enforcing discriminatory cultural norms with murderous violence and the threat of murderous violence.

====Religion and Racism====
In the [[19th century]], many U.S. Christians were taught that Africans, as the descendents of [[Ham%2C_son_of_Noah|Ham]], deserved to be slaves. On the other hand, [[abolitionism|abolition]] movements were also justified using Christian teaching.

====Discrimination against Japanese-Americans and Italian-Americans during World War II====
During the second world war, over 100,000 Japanese-Americans and Japanese-Canadians were forcibly placed in concentration camps where they remained until the end of hostilities with Japan [http://www.lm.liverpool.k12.ny.us/Whacked/Manzanar1/Manzanar.html ][http://mason.gmu.edu/~jboggs/openseason/resources.html ].
The incident that triggered the surge of anti-Japanese racism was  the Japanese Imperial Navy's attack on Pearl Harbor similar to how the events of 9/11 triggered a backlash against Arabs, Iranians and Muslims. Racism differs from country to country.{{fact}} 

Tens of thousands of Italian-Americans were put in internment camps during World War II as well. Thousands more were placed under surveillence or had their property repossessed by the government. [[Joe DiMaggio]]'s father, who lived in San Francisco, had his boat and house confiscated. One official stated that if it had not been for Joe DiMaggio's status as a baseball player, his father would most likely had been sent to an internment camp.

====Racism against Arabs, Iranians, and Middle Easterners====
{{Main|Anti-Arabism|Anti-Iranianism}}
There are reports of a large increase in anti-Arab/anti-Iranian racism in the [[United States]] since the [[September 11 2001 attacks]].[http://www.religionlink.org/tip_030407b.php] [[Racial profiling]] of people with a [[Middle Eastern]] ethnic background was  proposed by a [[New York]] [[Congressman]] on [[2006-08-15]].[http://www.adc.org/index.php?id=2930] In movies and jokes, Arabs and Iranians have been shown as being terrorists and barbarians or as inferior people.[http://www.adc.org/index.php?id=2357] . Iraq and Iran were demonized by the US government and this led to hatred towards Arabs and Iranians living in the United States [http://www.freepress.org/departments/display/13/2004/814]
[http://www.soundvision.com/info/peace/demonization.asp]  There have been attacks against Arabs and Iranians not only on the basis of their religion (Islam), but on the basis of their ethnicity because numerous Christian Arabs and Iranians have also been racially attacked.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pbs.org/niot/citizens_respond/losaltos.html Attacks on Arab Americans] (PBS)&lt;/ref&gt;

===Racism in Mexico, Central America, and South America===
Though not widely known throughout the world, Latin America has a history of racism highly influenced by the colonial attitudes and devastation created by the Spanish conquest in the 16th and 17th centuries. During the conquest, the offspring of Spaniards and Native Americans became distinct and low caste in colonial society. The offspring are now the majority thougout Latin America and in Spanish-speaking countries they are called  ''indios'', ''nacos'' or ''[[mestizos]]'' by racists. 
 
Europeans in Latin America during the colonial period intended ''[[mestizo]]s'' to be a serf race to "pure" European colonial overlords in designated fiefdoms (haciendas). A practical example of this practice can be found in the colonial government structure that required the top levels of government to be in the hands of European born individuals, called ''peninsulares''. Middle management fell upon Europeans born in America without American blood, called ''[[Creole peoples|criollos]]''. Those of ''mestizo'' blood were cast in the lowest echelon of society as miners and agricultural workers. However, ''mestizos'' with lighter complexion sometimes rose to higher positions. Latin America’s history of exploitation and feudal economic practices contributed to the popularity of Socialist and Communist movements in Latin America throughout the 20th century. The legacy of the fiefdoms is the reason why Latin America is constituted by so many small nations.

See the writings of [[Alvaro Vargas Llosa]] for discussion on relationships between development and culture in Latin America. Free trade agreements (like [[Mercosur]]) are challenging the need for borders among the nearly identical national cultures. Further, information technology and media consolidation is serving to further unify the Latin America's vast ''mestizo'' majority.

===Nazism and Japanese imperialism===
{{Main|Nazism|Japanese Nationalism}}
The Nazi, and Nazi-resembling regimes which rose to power in Europe and Japan before [[World War II]] advocated and implemented policies and attitudes which were racist, xenophobic, and often genocidal. While racism, xenophobia, and genocide were not new, the scope of the acts committed by the German Nazis and the Japanese governments was larger than other examples.

==Allegedly racist groups==
&lt;!-- Note: The use of the word "often" means that one or more valid sources is required. Being self-described as racist counts as a source. --&gt;

*[[Aryan Nations]][http://bethuneinstitute.org/documents/cift.html]
*[[Black Hebrew Israelites]][http://www.splcenter.org/intel/intelreport/article.jsp?aid=172]
*[[British National Party]][http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/main.jhtml?xml=/news/2005/07/20/nbnp20.xml]
*[[Christian Identity]][http://www.cesnur.org/testi/FBI_006.htm#Anchor-III-43266] [http://www.tolerance.org/maps/hate]
*[[Creativity Movement|The Creativity Movement]] (formerly The World Church of the Creator)[http://www.cnn.com/2003/US/Midwest/01/08/white.supremacist/index.html] 
*[[National Front (France)|Front National]][http://www.economist.com/research/articlesBySubject/displayStory.cfm?story_ID=1109867&amp;subject=Netherlands&amp;tranMode=none]
*[[Grey Wolves]][http://www.etext.org/Politics/MIM/countries/turkey/turanian.html ][http://www.xs4all.nl/~afa/alert/engels/greyw.html][http://www.etext.org/Politics/Autonome.Forum/Kurdistan/Articles/grey-wolves-terrorists.txt]
*[[Gray Wolves]]
*[[Imperium Europa]][http://www.timesofmalta.com/core/article.php?id=225455]
*[[Jewish Defense League]]
*[[Kahane Chai]]
*[[Ku Klux Klan]][http://www.spartacus.schoolnet.co.uk/USAkkk.htm] [http://www.adl.org/learn/ext_us/KKK.asp?xpicked=4&amp;item=18]
*[[Nation of Aztlán]][http://www.splcenter.org/intel/intelreport/article.jsp?aid=186][http://www.adl.org/Learn/Aztlan/default.asp][http://www.adl.org/learn/Aztlan/atzlan_printable.html][http://www.prisonplanet.com/articles/march2006/290306ethniccleansing.htm]
*[[The Nation of Gods and Earths]]
*[[Nation of Islam]]
*[[National Alliance]][http://www.adl.org/learn/ext_us/N_Alliance.asp]
*[[National Socialist Japanese Workers and Welfare Party]]
*[[New Zealand National Front]][http://www.stuff.co.nz/stuff/0,2106,3258406a10,00.html]
*[[Patriotic Youth League]][http://www.smh.com.au/news/National/Race-hate-group-unstuck/2004/12/18/1103312781334.html]
*[[Posse Comitatus (U.S. movement)|Posse Comitatus]][http://www.splcenter.org/intel/intelreport/article.jsp?aid=73]
*[[Stormfront.org]]
*[[White Aryan Resistance]][http://www.resist.com]
*[[New Black Panthers]]

== References ==
&lt;!--&lt;nowiki&gt;
See http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Footnotes for an explanation of how to generate footnotes using the&lt;ref&gt; and &lt;/ref&gt; tags, and the template below. 
&lt;/nowiki&gt;--&gt;
{{FootnotesSmall|resize=100%}}

==Bibliography==

* Barkan, Elazar (1992), ''The Retreat of Scientific Racism : Changing Concepts of Race in Britain and the United States between the World Wars'', Cambridge University Press, New York, NY.

* Dain, Bruce (2002), ''A Hideous Monster of the Mind : American Race Theory in the Early Republic'', Harvard University Press, Cambridge, MA. (18th century US racial theory)

* Diamond, Jared (1999), "Guns, Germs, and Steel", W.W. Norton, New York, NY.

* [[Claude Lévi-Strauss|Lévi-Strauss, Claude]] (1952), ''Race and History'', ([[UNESCO]]).

* Rocchio, Vincent F. (2000), ''Reel Racism : Confronting Hollywood's Construction of Afro-American Culture'', Westview Press.

* Stokes, DaShanne (forthcoming), ''Legalized Segregation and the Denial of Religious Freedom'', [http://www.geocities.com/eaglefeatherlaw/stokes.article.html URL].

* Stoler, Ann Laura (1997), "Racial Histories and Their Regimes of Truth", ''Political Power and Social Theory'' 11 (1997), 183–206. ([[historiography]] of race and racism)

* [[Pierre-André Taguieff|Taguieff, Pierre-André]] (1987), ''La Force du préjugé : Essai sur le racisme et ses doubles'', Tel Gallimard, La Découverte.

==See also==
{| style="background-color: transparent; width: {{{width|100%}}}"
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
| width="50%" align="{{{align|left}}}" valign="{{{valign|top}}}" |
*[[Affirmative action]]
*[[Afrophobia]]
*[[Afrocentrism]]
*[[anti-Arabism]]
*[[anti-Italianism]]
*[[anti-racism]]
*[[anti-Semitism]]
*[[Apartheid]]
*[[Asian pride]]
*[[The Bell Curve]]
*[[Black Panthers]]
*[[Black power]]
*[[Black supremacy]]
*[[Blackface]]
*[[Bumiputra]]
*[[Chauvinism]]
*[[Civil rights movement]]
*[[Criminal Blackman Myth]]
*[[Dominant minority]]
*[[Environmental racism]]
*[[Ethnic cleansing]]
*[[Ethnic issues in Japan]]
*[[Ethnic nepotism]]
*[[Ethnic stereotype]]
*[[Ethnocentrism]]
*[[Eugenics]]
*[[Eurocentrism]]
*[[Genocide]]
*[[Hate crimes]]
*[[Health disparities]]
*[[Houston Stewart Chamberlain]]
*[[Human Zoo]]
*[[Intercultural competence]]
*[[Institutional racism]]
*[[List of ethnic slurs]]
*[[Anti-Japanese sentiment]]

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
| width="50%" align="{{{align|left}}}" valign="{{{valign|top}}}" |

*[[Jim Crow laws]]
*[[Ku Klux Klan]]
*[[List of songs about racism]]
*[[Martial race]]
*[[Master race]]
*[[Media and ethnicity]]
*[[Miscegenation]]
*[[Nazi punk]]
*[[Nazi-Skinheads]]
*[[Nazism]]
*[[Neo-Nazism]]
*[[Nigger]]
*[[Prejudice]]
*[[Race]]
*[[Race riot]]
*[[Race and crime]]
*[[Genetics and violence]]
*[[Race and intelligence]]
*[[Racialism]]
*[[Racial profiling]]
*[[Racial realism]]
*[[Racial segregation]]
*[[Racism in Mass Media]]
*[[Sinophobia]]
*[[Social Darwinism]]
*[[Social stereotype]]
*[[Tulsa Race Riot]]
*[[White Australia policy]]
*[[White nationalism]]
*[[White power]]
*[[White pride]]
*[[White separatism]]
*[[White supremacy]]
*[[White trash]]
*[[Wog]]
*[[Yellow Peril]]
*[[Xenophobia]]
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
|}

==External links==
{{Commonscat|Racism}}
*[http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/nova/first/gill.html Does race exist?] argument for the biological concept of ''race'' 
*[http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/nova/first/brace.html Does race exist?] argument against the existence of race as a biological entity
*[http://www.pbs.org/race Race] in-depth website about race
*[http://www.newsreel.org/nav/title.asp?tc=CN0149 Race - the power of illusion] argument that while race is a biological fiction, racism permeates the structure of society
*[http://www.amren.com/0306issue/0306issue.html#article1 Race Denial: The Power of a Delusion] detailed critique seeking to refute the film
* [http://www.globalissues.org/HumanRights/Racism.asp Racism and human rights] Racism from Global Issues
* [http://www.irr.org.uk/ Institute for Race Relations]
* [http://www.geocities.com/eaglefeatherlaw Eagle feather law] details racism in religion law regarding eagle feathers for Native and non-Native Americans
*[http://www.rationalrevolution.net/articles/darwin_nazism.htm The Mis-portrayal of Darwin as a Racist] Refutes claims that Darwin was a racist
*[http://kitoba.com/pedia/Racism.html Racism] brief summary of the root causes of racism

[[Category:Core issues in ethics]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Politics and race]]
[[Category:Racism|*]]
[[Category:Sociology]]
[[Category:Pejorative terms for people]]

[[ar:عنصرية]]
[[bs:Rasizam]]
[[bg:Расизъм]]
[[ca:Racisme]]
[[cs:Rasismus]]
[[da:Racisme]]
[[de:Rassismus]]
[[et:Rassism]]
[[el:Ρατσισμός]]
[[es:Racismo]]
[[eo:Rasismo]]
[[eu:Arrazismo]]
[[fr:Racisme]]
[[gl:Racismo]]
[[ko:인종 차별]]
[[it:Razzismo]]
[[he:גזענות]]
[[sw:Ubaguzi wa rangi]]
[[lb:Rassismus]]
[[lt:Rasizmas]]
[[hu:Rasszizmus]]
[[mk:Расизам]]
[[nl:Racisme]]
[[ja:人種差別]]
[[no:Rasisme]]
[[nn:Rasisme]]
[[pl:Rasizm]]
[[pt:Racismo]]
[[ro:Rasism]]
[[ru:Расизм]]
[[scn:Razzismu]]
[[simple:Racism]]
[[sk:Rasizmus]]
[[sr:Расизам]]
[[sh:Rasizam]]
[[fi:Rasismi]]
[[sv:Rasism]]
[[vi:Phân biệt chủng tộc]]
[[zh:种族主义]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>