<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061112020314|87254061" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="46530" pageid="46530" ns="0" title="Human Rights Watch"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-11-13T22:39:02Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[Image:Human_Rights_Watch_banner.gif|right|frame|Human Rights Watch Banner|200px]]
'''Human Rights Watch''' is a [[United States]]-based international [[non-government organization]] that conducts research and advocacy on [[human rights]]. Its headquarters is in [[New York City]].

==Profile==

Human Rights Watch produces research reports on violations of international human rights norms as set out by the [[Universal Declaration of Human Rights]] and other internationally-accepted human rights norms. This is intended to draw international attention to abuses and to put pressure on governments and international organizations to reform. Researchers conduct fact-finding missions to investigate suspect situations and generate coverage in local and international [[News media|media]]. Issues raised by Human Rights Watch in its reports include social and [[discrimination|gender discrimination]], [[torture]], [[military use of children]], [[political corruption]], and abuses in [[criminal justice]] systems. Human Rights Watch documents and reports violations of the laws of [[war]] and international humanitarian law.

Human Rights Watch was founded under the name [[Helsinki Watch]] in [[1978]] to monitor the former [[Soviet Union]]'s compliance with the [[Helsinki Accords]]. As the organization grew, it formed other "watch committees" to cover other regions of the world. In [[1988]], all of the committees were united under one umbrella to form Human Rights Watch. One of the original founders and a president of the organization was [[Robert L. Bernstein]].

Human Rights Watch was one of six international NGOs that founded the [[Coalition to Stop the Use of Child Soldiers]] in [[1998]]. It is also the co-chair of the [[International Campaign to Ban Landmines]], a global coalition of civil society groups that successfully lobbied to introduce the [[Ottawa Convention]], a treaty that prohibits the use of anti-personnel landmines.

Each year, Human Rights Watch gives grants to writers worldwide who are in financial need and who they consider to have been victims of persecution. The Hellman/Hammett grants are financed by the estate of the playwright [[Lillian Hellman]] in funds set up in her name and that of her long-time companion, the novelist [[Dashiell Hammett]]. In addition to providing financial assistance, the Hellman/Hammett grants attempt to raise awareness of censorship &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hrw.org/about/info/helham.html Hellman-Hammett Grants],''Human Rights Watch''&lt;/ref&gt;.

Pursuant to the [[Universal Declaration of Human Rights]], Human Rights Watch opposes violations of basic human rights, including the [[death penalty]] and discrimination on the basis of [[gay rights|sexual orientation]].  Human Rights Watch advocates freedoms in connection with fundamental human rights, such as [[freedom of religion]] and [[freedom of the press|the press]].

Human Rights Watch is a founding member of the [[International Freedom of Expression Exchange]], a global network of [[non-governmental organizations]] that monitor [[censorship]] worldwide.

Human Rights Watch has 233 paid staff, and a budget of US$26 million a year.  &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hrw.org/donations/finance.htm Financial statement],''Human Rights Watch''&lt;/ref&gt;

The current executive director of is Kenneth Roth. He has held this position since 1993. Roth is a graduate of Yale Law School and Brown University. His father fled Nazi Germany in 1938. Roth started working on human rights after the declaration of martial law in Poland in 1981, and later became engaged in Haiti issues. &lt;ref&gt;[http://hrw.org/about/bios/kroth.htm Kenneth Roth Bio],''Human Rights Watch''&lt;/ref&gt;

==Issues and campaigns==
* Traffic in [[small arms]]
* [[Land mines]]
* [[Abortion rights]]
* [[Gay rights]]
* Rights of [[AIDS]] victims
* Safety of civilians in war; opposes use of [[cluster bombs]]
* [[Child labor]]
* [[Child soldiers]]
* [[Street children]]
* [[Genocide]], [[war crimes]] and [[crimes against humanity]]
* [[Torture]]
* [[Extrajudicial killing]]s and [[abduction]]s
* [[Legal proceedings]] against human rights abusers
* [[Trafficking in women]] and girls
*

==Recent==

Human Rights Watch made recent headlines by criticizing the [[Jordan|Jordanian government]] for arresting elected officials who praised [[Abu Musab al-Zarqawi]], the head of [[Al Qaeda in Iraq]], at ceremonies held in response to his death.  Human Rights Watch also spoke out against the [[Mass murder#Mass murder by a state|mass killings]] and government-imposed [[famine]]s during the last decade of former [[Iraq|Iraqi]] leader [[Saddam Hussein|Saddam Hussein's]] [[History of Iraq#Under Saddam|rule]] &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hrw.org/doc?t=mideast&amp;c=iraq&amp;document_limit=260,20 Middle east and North Africa],''Human Rights Watch''&lt;/ref&gt;.

==Publications==

Human Rights Watch publishes reports on several topics &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hrw.org/doc/?t=pubs Publications],''Human Rights Watch''&lt;/ref&gt; and compiles annual reports ("World Report") presenting an overview of the worldwide state of human rights.

Human Rights Watch has published extensively on the [[Rwandan Genocide]] of 1994 &lt;ref&gt;[http://hrw.org/doc?t=africa&amp;c=rwanda Rwandan genocide report],''Human Rights Watch''&lt;/ref&gt; and the conflicts in the [[Democratic Republic of the Congo]] &lt;ref&gt;[http://hrw.org/doc?t=africa&amp;c=congo Congo report],''Human Rights Watch''&lt;/ref&gt;.

==Comparison with Amnesty International==

Human Rights Watch is much smaller than Amnesty International.  It is US-based, whereas Amnesty is UK-based.  Human Rights Watch's main products are its crisis-directed research and lengthy reports, whereas Amnesty focuses on mass letter-writing campaigns, adopting individuals as "prisoners of conscience" and lobbying for their release.  Human Rights Watch will openly lobby for specific actions for other governments to take against human rights offenders, including naming specific individuals for arrest, or for sanctions to be levied against certain countries, recently calling for punitive sanctions against the top leaders in Sudan who have overseen a killing campaign in Darfur.

Its documentations of human rights abuses often include extensive analyses of the political and historical backgrounds of the conflicts concerned, some of which have been published in academic journals.  AI's reports, on the other hand, tend to contain less analysis, and instead focus on specific abuses of rights.

==Criticisms==
{{POV-section}}

===Allegations of anti-Semitism===

Human Rights Watch has been criticized as having an [[anti-Semitism|anti-Semitic]] and [[anti-Zionism|anti-Israel]] bias by the [[Committee for Accuracy in Middle East Reporting in America]] ([[Committee for Accuracy in Middle East Reporting in America|CAMERA]]), the [[Anti-Defamation League]], [[Honest Reporting]], the [[Jerusalem Center for Public Affairs]]' [[NGO Monitor]] and Gerald Steinberg, the Australia/Israel &amp; Jewish Affairs Council (AIJAC), Abraham Cooper, [[Anne Bayefsky]],  Isi Leibler, [[Shimon Peres]], and [[Ana Palacio]].  

In 2002 the [[Anti-Defamation League]], in response to coverage of the [[Battle of Jenin]], stated that Human Rights Watch “pre-judged Israel's behavior.” The [[Anti-Defamation League]] also wrote, “Human Rights Watch charged Israel with violations of international law and war crimes. Neither discussed the international law violations involved in arming a refugee camp, or demanded the United Nations be held in any way accountable for its lack of oversight in the camp. While Human Rights Watch acknowledged in a May 3 report that there was no evidence of a massacre and that Palestinian gunmen had contributed to endangering Palestinian civilians, they continued to emphasize that there was prima facie evidence Israel committed war crimes.”&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.adl.org/Israel/jenin/ Anatomy of Anti-Israel Incitement: Jenin],''Anti-Defamation League''&lt;/ref&gt;

In a [[2006]] [[communiqué]] [[Honest Reporting]], a media watchdog group that monitors and reports on what it perceives as [[anti-Israel]] bias, wrote, “Human Rights Watch, along with many other organizations which claim to focus solely on human rights without a political agenda, have hardly proven themselves to be an "unbiased" source.” Furthermore, the [[communiqué]] asserted, “Human Rights Watch is not held accountable to anybody but its own staff” and, “The organization's bias against Israel is hardly new.”&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.honestreporting.com/articles/45884734/critiques/-Unbiased-_Advice.asp Human Rights Watch and Saeb Erekat lack objectivity],''honestreporting.com&lt;/ref&gt;

[[NGO Monitor]], a program of the [[Jerusalem Center for Public Affairs]], released a summary in [[2006]] which commented, “While NGO Monitor's analysis shows a significant reduction in Human Rights Watch's disproportionate focus on Israel in 2005, compared with 2004, clear evidence of systematic political bias remains...Many Humans Right Watch publications continue to reflect what can be described as gratuitous political attacks against Israel, often based on unverified media reports, and reflecting a hostile political agenda. ...Human Rights Watch's use of language to condemn Israel is highly politicized, especially when compared to reports on other countries in the Middle East...and continues to deny Israel the right to self-defense under international law.”&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.stoptheism.com/Default.asp?M=21&amp;T=214 The Bias in Human Rights Watch],''Stop The ISM''&lt;/ref&gt; NGO Monitor also carried out a [[quantitative]] study which asserted an [[anti-Zionism|anti-Israel]] bias.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ngo-monitor.org/archives/news/ComparativeAnalysisOfHRWMEActivities.pdf Comparative analysis of HRW Activities],''NGO-monitor.org''&lt;/ref&gt; 

[[NGO Monitor]]'s director, Gerard Steinberg, had earlier written “During the height of the terror attacks against Israel, Human Rights Watch focused one-third of its entire Middle East effort on condemnations directed at Israel.” Steinberg asserted further, “The most infuriating instance of Human Rights Watch’s bias came in 2004, when Roth went to...Jerusalem to promote 'Razing Rafah', a one sided denunciation of Israeli policy. Its contents were based primarily on unsubstantiated reports of Palestinians, selected journalists, and so-called experts on tunneling.” &lt;ref&gt;[http://article.nationalreview.com/?q=YzdkNDA3NTY4ZmMwMzFmNWYwYTBkMWU4MzFiMTMxNGM= Human-Rights Schizophrenia],''National Review''&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Anne Bayefsky]], a [[Professor]] at [[York University]] and editor of [http://www.eyeontheun.org/ Eye on the UN], argued that Human Rights Watch allowed [[anti-Zionism|anti-Israel]] and [[anti-Semitism|anti-Semitic]] to occur, based on her participation in the 2001 [[World Conference against Racism]]. Bayefsky also wrote, “When it comes to anti-Semitism and anti-Israel bias, Human Rights Watch still has a lot of explaining to do, notwithstanding Executive Director Ken Roth's umbrage at criticism.” Bayefsky commented, “As we arrived at our meeting the chief Durban representative of Human Rights Watch, advocacy director Reed Brody, publicly announced that as a representative of a Jewish group I was unwelcome and could not attend.”&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ngo-monitor.org/archives/op-eds/041304-1.htm Human Rights Watch Coverup] by Anne Bayefsky&lt;/ref&gt;  Abraham Cooper, Associate Dean of the [[Simon Wiesenthal Center]] and another participant at the conference, wrote “Contrary to the May 27 letter by the executive directors of Human Rights Watch and Amnesty International U.S.A., Anne Bayefsky...was correct to criticize those two groups for their roles at the [Durban] conference”.  Cooper added regarding the [[forum]] [[document]], “The concerns of one group of victims -- the Jewish people -- were left off that document, with the silent acquiescence of Amnesty International and Human Rights Watch.” He also recounted, “Like many other Jewish delegates at the conference, I was subjected to physical intimidation and threats.”&lt;ref&gt;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E7DE143AF930A35755C0A9649C8B63&amp;n=Top%2fReference%2fTimes%20Topics%2fOrganizations%2fH%2fHuman%20Rights%20Watch  Human Rights and Jews],''New York Times''&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Committee for Accuracy in Middle East Reporting in America]] ([[Committee for Accuracy in Middle East Reporting in America|CAMERA]]), a member of the [[Israel Campus Roundtable]], ran an article on their [[website]] in [[2005]] titled “What is Human Rights Watch's Agenda?” In this article [[Committee for Accuracy in Middle East Reporting in America|CAMERA]] stated that Human Rights Watch is “A self-appointed arbiter of human rights abuses around the world” and that, “This would be a noble and worthy mission if it were carried out objectively, without regard to political or ideological agenda. Regrettably, this is not the case.”&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.camera.org/index.asp?x_context=7&amp;x_issue=39&amp;x_article=914 What is Human Rights Watch's Agenda?],''camera.org''&lt;/ref&gt; CAMERA has also stated, in a blog entry, “AI and another "voice of international appeasement" — Human Rights Watch — have consistently directed their righteous ire at Israel, sparing the real human rights abusers”, but doesn't identify the latter. &lt;ref&gt;[http://blog.camera.org/archives/2005/05/voices_of_inter.html Voices of International Appeasement],''Camera.org blog''&lt;/ref&gt;

The Australia/Israel &amp; Jewish Affairs Council, a public affairs organization for the Australian Jewish community, concluded an [[anti-Zionism|anti-Israel]] [[bias]] in the [[2002]] article titled, “Israel’s critics and their war with the truth.” Regarding an apparent [[double standard]], this article questioned, “It is hard to explain why victims of slavery and slaughter are virtually ignored by American progressives. How can it be that there is no storm of indignation at Amnesty International or Human Rights Watch, which, though they rushed to Jenin to investigate false reports of Jews massacring Arabs, care so much less about Arab-occupied Juba, South Sudan's black capital? How can it be that they have not raised the roof about Khartoum's black slaves?”&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aijac.org.au/updates/Oct-02/111002.html Israel's critics and their war with the truth], ''Australia/Israel and Jewish Affairs Council''&lt;/ref&gt; Human Rights Watch published a backgrounder in March 2002 on slavery in Sudan. "Human Rights Watch has long denounced slavery in Sudan in the context of the nineteen-year civil war."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hrw.org/backgrounder/africa/sudanupdate.htm Sudan Update],''Human Rights Watch''&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2005 Isi Leibler, a columnist for [[The Jerusalem Post]], stated that Human Rights Watch is among the groups that “Have long track records of bias and employing double standards in relation to Israel.”&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.campus-watch.org/article/id/2257 Middle East studies in the News],''Campuswatch.org archive of the Jerusalem Post''&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2001, regarding the [[World Conference against Racism]], which Human Rights Watch moved to distance itself from, [[CNN]] cited [[Shimon Peres]], an [[Israeli]] [[politician]], as saying, “It is an outburst of hate, of anti-Semitism, anti-Zionism without any consideration.”&lt;ref&gt;[http://archives.cnn.com/2001/WORLD/africa/09/02/durban.racism/index.html Israel branded 'racist' by rights forum],''CNN''&lt;/ref&gt;

In a 2005 address to the [[Anti-Defamation League]], a former [[Foreign Minister]] of [[Spain]], [[Ana Palacio]], asserted that Human Rights Watch ignored [[anti-Semitism]] as an issue of importance over other [[human rights]] issues, such as [[gay]] or [[refugee]] rights. In this address she stated, “Disinterested NGOs like Human Rights Watch or Amnesty International pay little attention to anti-Semitism.”&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.adl.org/Anti_semitism/speech_palacio.asp Anti-Semitism in Europe: Fighting Back],''Anti-Defamation League''&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Response ====

Kenneth Roth, the executive director of Human Rights Watch, published a response to criticism from Israel's supporters on  April 1, 2004 in the ''Jerusalem Post'', titled "The Truth Hurts" &lt;ref&gt;[http://hrw.org/english/docs/2004/04/12/isrlpa8422.htm The Truth Hurts],''Human rights Watch''&lt;/ref&gt;. Roth defends Human Rights Watch's allegations that Israel breaks humanitarian law, referring to "assassinating suspects when they could be arrested, punishing families for the acts of one of their members, employing abusive interrogation techniques, imposing punitive restrictions on the Palestinian population that go well beyond security requirements, building a security barrier not on the Green Line but with deep incursions into the West Bank to protect settlements that themselves violate the Geneva Conventions".

Roth responds to Gerald Steinberg's accusation that Human Rights Watch "was present in Durban when the NGO community hijacked a UN conference on racism to promote its own racist anti-Zionist agenda", pointing out that "Human Rights Watch publicly disassociated itself from the NGO's manifesto because of its unfounded attacks on Israel". Roth denies Steinberg's allegations of only one exception to '"consistent silence" in the face of Palestinian suicide bombing', pointing to 11 condemnations available to see on Human Rights Watch's website, and similarly denies his charge of "protecting Middle Eastern tyrants".

Aryeh Neier, a founder of Human Rights Watch and former Adjunct Professor of Law at New York University, writing in the [[New York Review of Books]], defends Roth and Human Rights Watch from charges of  anti-Semitic and anti-Israel bias. "Unfortunately, the criticisms are based on misunderstandings and distortions of international humanitarian law. They contribute to an atmosphere that makes rational discussion in the United States of Israel's policies and practices increasingly difficult." &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nybooks.com/articles/19500 The Attack on Human Rights Watch by Aryeh Neier],''nybooks.com''&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Philip Weiss]], an investigative journalist writing in ''[[The Nation]]'', quotes a number of Human Rights Watch officials and board members responding to attacks on it by the ''[[New York Sun]]'' and others &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thenation.com/doc/20060918/weiss Israel Lobby Watch by Phulip Weiss],''Thenation.com''&lt;/ref&gt;.

Weiss quotes Human Rights Watch emergency director [[Peter Bouckaert]]: "We always get attacked for our findings by the government involved. What makes this case different is, it's not the government, it's the external lobby. We have a difficult but positive dialogue with the Israeli government and the IDF. They don't dismiss us as morally repugnant or irrelevant. They take our findings seriously. The attacks are not about the facts, they're about insulating Israel from any type of criticism."

Weiss also quotes [[Sarah Leah Whitson]], executive director of Human Rights Watch's Middle East and North Africa division. "There's a deep schizophrenia in some of the Jewish community, and people who are at the forefront of every single rights issue, from racial justice in the United States to the ethnic cleansing in Darfur--on Israel, it crumbles, and there is all this hand-wringing. And everyone [who is critical] is successfully marginalized."

Weiss also points to criticism of Human Rights Watch for being too soft on Israel.



==See also==
*[[Amnesty International]]
*[[Democracy Watch (International)]]
*[[Helsinki Committee for Human Rights]]
*[[Human rights abuse]]
*[[International Freedom of Expression Exchange]]
*[[Freedom House]]

==References==  	 
&lt;div class="references-small" style="-moz-column-count:2; column-count:2;"&gt; 	 
&lt;references /&gt;
*Neier, Aryeh (2006)  [http://www.nybooks.com/articles/19500 "The Attack on Human Rights Watch"], ''New York Review of Books'', 53(17) November 2, 2006, accessed 20 October 2006. 
&lt;/div&gt;

==External links==
===Human Rights Watch website===
* [http://www.hrw.org Human Rights Watch] (official website)
* [http://www.hrw.org/wr2k6/ Human Rights Watch World Report 2006]
* [http://www.hrw.org/english/docs/2006/01/13/global12428.htm Press info on Human Rights Watch World Report 2006]
===Critical viewpoints===
* [http://www.zmag.org/content/showarticle.cfm?SectionID=55&amp;ItemID=10011 Haiti and Human Rights Watch] (Joe Emersberger, ZNet)
* [http://www.ngo-monitor.org/archives/infofile/hrw_criticised_for_israel_attacks_280806.html Human Rights Watch receives unprecedented public criticism for its attacks on Israeli actions in Lebanon] NGO Monitor
* [[Jonathan Cook]]: [http://electronicintifada.net/v2/article5698.shtml How Human Rights Watch lost its way in Lebanon]; [http://www.counterpunch.org/whitson09222006.html response] from the Executive Director of the Middle East &amp; North Africa Division of Human Rights Watch; Cook's [http://www.zmag.org/content/showarticle.cfm?ItemID=11048 response]

[[Category:Non-governmental organizations]]
[[Category:Civil rights]]
[[Category:Human rights bodies]]
[[Category:Social justice]]
[[Category:Terrorism]]

[[da:Human Rights Watch]]
[[de:Human Rights Watch]]
[[es:Human Rights Watch]]
[[fi:Human Rights Watch]]
[[fr:Human Rights Watch]]
[[id:Human Rights Watch]]
[[is:Mannréttindavaktin]]
[[ja:ヒューマン・ライツ・ウォッチ]]
[[nl:Human Rights Watch]]
[[no:Human Rights Watch]]
[[pl:Human Rights Watch]]
[[sv:Human Rights Watch]]
[[ta:மனித உரிமைகள் கண்காணிப்பு]]
[[zh:人权观察]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>