<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20051014213110|25535374" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="46530" pageid="46530" ns="0" title="Human Rights Watch"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-10-31T18:23:00Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Human Rights Watch''' is an international [[non-governmental organization]] based in [[New York City]], [[United States|USA]], that conducts advocacy and research on [[human rights]] issues.

The organization was founded under the name [[Helsinki Watch]] in [[1978]] to monitor the former [[Soviet Union]]'s compliance with the [[Helsinki Accords]]. As the organization grew, it formed other "watch committees" to cover other regions of the world. In [[1988]], all of the committees were united under one umbrella to form Human Rights Watch.

Human Rights Watch's specialty is the production of authoritative research reports on human rights violations, usually intended to draw international attention to abuses, and to put pressure on governments and international organizations to prevent further violations of human rights. Researchers conduct fact-finding missions to countries to investigate violations and generate extensive coverage in local and international media. Major issues raised by the organization in its reports include social and [[gender discrimination]], [[torture]], [[military use of children]], government [[corruption]], and abuses in [[criminal justice]] systems in many nations. It also specializes in documenting and reporting violations of the laws of armed conflict and international humanitarian law.

Human Rights Watch was one of six international NGOs that founded the [[Coalition to Stop the Use of Child Soldiers]] in [[1998]]. It is also the co-chair of the [[International Campaign to Ban Landmines]], a global coalition of civil society groups that successfully lobbied to introduce the [[Ottawa Convention]], a treaty that prohibits the use of anti-personnel landmines.

Each year, Human Rights Watch gives grants to writers all over the world who have been victims of political persecution and are in financial need. The Hellman/Hammett grants are financed by the estate of the playwright [[Lillian Hellman]] in funds set up in her name and that of her long-time companion, the novelist [[Dashiell Hammett]]. The two American writers were interrogated in the 1950s about their political beliefs and affiliations. In addition to providing much needed financial assistance, the Hellman/Hammett grants raise awareness of censorship around the world [http://www.hrw.org/about/info/helham.html].

Human Rights Watch is also a member of the [[International Freedom of Expression Exchange]], a global network of [[non-governmental organisations]] that monitors [[censorship]] worldwide and campaigns to defend journalists, writers, Internet users and others who are persecuted for exercising their right to freedom of expression.

Like many human rights groups, Human Rights Watch opposes the [[death penalty]], opposes restrictions to [[abortion]], and proposes that marriage be re-defined to include same-sex couples [http://www.hrw.org/press/2003/09/us090403.htm].  It has also called for condom distribution in prisons [http://hrw.org/english/docs/2005/04/27/usdom10551.htm].

==See also==

*[[Amnesty International]]
*[[Democracy Watch (International)]]
*[[Helsinki Committee for Human Rights]]
*[[Human rights abuse]]
*[[International Freedom of Expression Exchange]]

==External link==

* [http://www.hrw.org Human Rights Watch]

[[Category:Social justice]]
[[Category:Human rights bodies]]  
[[Category:Civil rights]]

[[de:Human Rights Watch]]
[[es:Human Rights Watch]]
[[fi:Human Rights Watch]]
[[fr:Human Rights Watch]]
[[nb:Human Rights Watch]]
[[nl:Human Rights Watch]]
[[pl:Human Rights Watch]]
[[sv:Human Rights Watch]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>