<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20101101164219|394197077" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="46530" pageid="46530" ns="0" title="Human Rights Watch"><revisions><rev timestamp="2010-11-07T13:00:09Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{distinguish|Bahrain Human Rights Watch Society}}
{{Infobox NPO
|organization_name  = Human Rights Watch
|organization_logo  = [[File:Hrw logo.svg|200px]]
|organization_motto = 
|organization_type  = [[Non-profit organization|Non-profit]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Non-governmental organisation|NGO]] 
|founded            = 1978 under the name [[Helsinki Watch]]&lt;br /&gt;Adopted current name in 1988.&lt;ref name="OH"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hrw.org/en/node/75134|title=Our History |publisher=Human Rights Watch|accessdate=2009-07-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|location           = [[New York City]]
|key_people         = [[Kenneth Roth]], ''Executive Director''
|fields             = [[Human rights]], [[Activism]]
|services           = 
|num_members        = 
|homepage           = http://www.hrw.org
}}

'''Human Rights Watch''' (formerly '''Helsinki Watch''') is an international [[non-governmental organization]] that conducts research and advocacy on [[human rights]]. Its headquarters are in [[New York City]] and it has offices in Berlin, Brussels, Chicago, Geneva, Johannesburg, London, Los Angeles, Moscow, Paris, San Francisco, Tokyo, Toronto, and Washington D.C.&lt;ref name="FAQ"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hrw.org/en/node/75138|title=Frequently Asked Questions|publisher=Human Rights Watch|accessdate=2009-07-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==
{{Main|Helsinki Watch}}
[[File:Msc 2008-Saturday, 14.00 - 16.00 Uhr-Moerk026 Roth.jpg|thumb|Current executive Director [[Kenneth Roth]] speaking at the 44th [[Munich Security Conference]] 2008.]]
Human Rights Watch was founded under the name [[Helsinki Watch]] in 1978 to monitor the former [[Soviet Union]]'s compliance with the [[Helsinki Accords]]. Helsinki Watch adopted a methodology of publicly "naming and shaming" abusive governments through media coverage and through direct exchanges with policymakers. By shining the international spotlight on human rights violations in the Soviet Union and its [[vassal state]]s in [[Eastern Europe]], Helsinki Watch contributed to the democratic transformations of the region in the late 1980s.{{Citation needed|date=October 2009}} Americas Watch was founded in 1981 while bloody civil wars engulfed [[Central America]]. Relying on extensive on-the-ground fact-finding, Americas Watch not only addressed perceived abuses by government forces but also applied international humanitarian law to investigate and expose [[war crime]]s by rebel groups. In addition to raising its concerns in the affected countries, Americas Watch also examined the role played by foreign governments, particularly the [[United States government]], in providing military and political support to abusive regimes. Asia Watch (1985), Africa Watch (1988), and Middle East Watch (1989) were added to what was then known as "The Watch Committees." In 1988, all of the committees were united under one umbrella to form Human Rights Watch.

== Profile ==
Pursuant to the [[Universal Declaration of Human Rights]], Human Rights Watch opposes violations of what it considers basic human rights, which include [[capital punishment]] and discrimination on the basis of [[LGBT social movements|sexual orientation]]. Human Rights Watch advocates freedoms in connection with fundamental human rights, such as [[freedom of religion]] and [[freedom of the press|the press]].

Human Rights Watch produces research reports on violations of international human rights norms as set out by the Universal Declaration of Human Rights and what it perceives to be other internationally accepted human rights norms. These reports are used as the basis for drawing international attention to abuses and pressuring governments and international organizations to reform. Researchers conduct fact-finding missions to investigate suspect situations and generate coverage in local and international [[News media|media]]. Issues raised by Human Rights Watch in its reports include social and [[discrimination|gender discrimination]], [[torture]], [[military use of children]], [[political corruption]], abuses in [[criminal justice]] systems, and the legalization of [[abortion]].&lt;ref name="hrw-qa-abortion"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hrw.org/en/news/2005/06/15/qa-human-rights-law-and-access-abortion|title=Q&amp;A: Human Rights Law and Access to Abortion|date=2005-06-15|publisher=Human Rights Watch|accessdate=1 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Human Rights Watch documents and reports violations of the laws of [[war]] and international humanitarian law.

Human Rights Watch also supports writers worldwide who are being persecuted for their work and are in need of financial assistance. The Hellman/Hammett grants are financed by the estate of the playwright [[Lillian Hellman]] in funds set up in her name and that of her long-time companion, the novelist [[Dashiell Hammett]]. In addition to providing financial assistance, the Hellman/Hammett grants help raise international awareness of activists who are being silenced for speaking out in defence of human rights.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hrw.org/about/info/helham.html Hellman-Hammett Grants],''Human Rights Watch''&lt;/ref&gt;

Each year, Human Rights Watch presents the Human Rights Defenders Award to activists around the world who demonstrate leadership and courage in defending human rights. The award winners work closely with Human Rights Watch in investigating and exposing human rights abuses.{{Citation needed|date=August 2009}}

Human Rights Watch was one of six international NGOs that founded the [[Coalition to Stop the Use of Child Soldiers]] in 1998. It is also the co-chair of the [[International Campaign to Ban Landmines]], a global coalition of civil society groups that successfully lobbied to introduce the [[Ottawa Treaty]], a treaty that prohibits the use of anti-personnel landmines.

Human Rights Watch is a founding member of the [[International Freedom of Expression Exchange]], a global network of [[non-governmental organizations]] that monitor [[censorship]] worldwide. It also co-founded the [[Cluster Munition Coalition]], which brought about an international convention banning the weapons. Human Rights Watch employs more than 275 staff -- country experts, lawyers, journalists, and academics – and operates in more than 90 countries around the world. &lt;ref name="WWA"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hrw.org/en/node/75136|title=Who We Are |publisher=Human Rights Watch|accessdate=2009-07-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The current executive director of Human Rights Watch is [[Kenneth Roth]], who has held the position since 1993. Roth conducted investigations on abuses in [[Poland]] after martial law was declared 1981. He later focused on [[Haiti]], which had just emerged from the Duvalier dictatorship but continued to be plagued with problems. Roth’s awareness of human rights began with stories that his father told about escaping [[Nazi Germany]] in 1938. He graduated from [[Yale Law School]] and [[Brown University]].

== Financing and services ==
For the financial year ending June 2008, HRW reported receiving approximately US$44 million in public donations.&lt;ref name="FS-2008"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hrw.org/sites/default/files/related_material/FinancialStatements2008.pdf|title=Financial Statements. Year Ended June 30, 2008|publisher=Human Rights Watch|accessdate=2009-07-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2009, Human Rights Watch stated that they receive almost 75% of their financial support from North America, 25% from Western Europe and less than 1% from the rest of the world.&lt;ref name="SA-2009-07"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hrw.org/en/node/84512|title=Human Rights Watch Visit to Saudi Arabia |date=2009-07-17|publisher=Human Rights Watch|accessdate=2009-07-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;
According to a 2008 financial assessment, HRW reports that it does not accept any direct or indirect funding from governments and is financed through contributions from private individuals and foundations.&lt;ref name="Financials"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hrw.org/en/news/2008/09/22/financials|title=Financials |date=2008-09-22|publisher=Human Rights Watch|accessdate=2009-07-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Notably, [[billionaire]] financier and philanthropist [[George Soros]] announced in 2010 his intention to donate US$100 million to HRW over a period of ten years. He said, "Human Rights Watch is one of the most effective organizations I support. Human rights underpin our greatest aspirations: they're at the heart of open societies."&lt;ref&gt;http://www.jpost.com/International/Article.aspx?id=187450 Soros to give Human Rights Watch $100m. over 10 years&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=WashingtonPost2010-09&gt;
{{cite news
| url= http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2010/09/11/AR2010091105057.html
| title= With $100 million Soros gift, Human Rights Watch looks to expand global reach
| publisher=[[Washington Post]]
| date=2010-09-12
| author=Colum Lynch
| quote= The donation, the largest single gift ever from the Hungarian-born investor and philanthropist, is premised on the belief that U.S. leadership on human rights has been diminished by a decade of harsh policies in the war on terrorism.
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The donation will increase Human Rights Watch's operating budget from $48 million to $80 million. The donation was the largest in the organization's history. &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2010/sep/07/george-soros-100-million-human-rights-watch George Soros gives $100 million to Human Rights Watch (The Guardian, Sept. 7, 2010)]&lt;/ref&gt;

[http://www.charitynavigator.org/index.cfm?bay=search.summary&amp;orgid=3845 Charity Navigator] gave Human Rights Watch a four-star rating, the highest number of stars possible. [http://charityreports.bbb.org/public/seal.aspx?ID=34521032010 The Better Business Bureau] said Human Rights Watch meets its standards for charity accountability. 

Human Rights Watch published the following program and support services spending details for the financial year ending June 2008.
{| 
| align="center" style="background:#f0f0f0;"|'''Program services'''
| align="center" style="background:#f0f0f0;"|'''2008 Expenses (USD)'''&lt;ref name="FS-2008"/&gt;
|-
| Africa||$5,532,631
|-
| Americas||$1,479,265
|-
| Asia||$3,212,850
|-
| Europe and Central Asia||$4,001,853
|-
| Middle East and North Africa||$2,258,459
|-
| United States||$1,195,673
|-
| Children's Rights||$1,642,064
|-
| International Justice||$1,385,121
|-
| Woman's Rights||$1,854,228
|-
| Other Programs||$9,252,974
|-
| align="center" style="background:#f0f0f0;"|'''Supporting services'''
|-
| Management and general||$1,984,626
|-
| Fundraising||$8,641,358
|-
| 
|}

==Notable staff==
Some notable current and former staff members of Human Rights Watch have included:&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hrw.org/en/node/75139 Human Rights Watch: Our People]&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!---note that subsection reword means former notables can be listed---&gt;
*[[Robert L. Bernstein]], Founding Chair Emeritus 
*[[Kenneth Roth]], Executive Director
*[[Minky Worden]], Media Director
*[[Jamie Fellner]], Senior Counsel for the United States Program of Human Rights Watch
*[[Scott Long]], Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, and Transgender Rights Director
*[[Sarah Leah Whitson]], Middle East and North Africa Director
*[[Joe Stork]]
*[[Marc Garlasco]], former staff member
*[[Sharon Hom]]

== Issues and campaigns ==
* Traffic in [[small arms]]
* [[Land mine]]s
* [[Pro-choice|Legalisation of abortion on demand]]
* [[Matriarchy|Pro-Matriarchy]]/[[Feminism]]
* [[LGBT social movements|Gay rights]]
* Rights of [[AIDS]] patients
* Safety of civilians in war; opposes use of [[cluster bomb]]s
* [[Child labor]]
* [[Military use of children|Child soldiers]]
* [[Street children]]
* [[Genocide]], [[war crime]]s and [[crime against humanity|crimes against humanity]]
* [[Torture]]
* [[Extrajudicial punishment|Extrajudicial killings]] and abductions
* [[Extraordinary rendition by the United States]]
* [[Legal proceedings]] against human rights abusers
* [[Human trafficking|Trafficking in women]] and girls
* Abolition of [[capital punishment]] worldwide

===Recent===
{{Recentism|section|date=February 2010}}
Human Rights Watch criticized the [[Jordan|Jordanian government]] for arresting elected officials who praised [[Abu Musab al-Zarqawi]], the former head of [[Al-Qaeda in Iraq]], at ceremonies held in response to his death. Human Rights Watch also spoke out against the [[Mass murder#Mass murder by a state|mass killings]] and government-imposed [[famine]]s during the last decade of former [[Iraq]]i leader [[Saddam Hussein|Saddam Hussein's]] [[History of Iraq#Under Saddam|rule]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hrw.org/doc?t=mideast&amp;c=iraq&amp;document_limit=260,20 Middle east and North Africa],''Human Rights Watch''&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2007 HRW denounced [[Spain]] for holding hundreds of migrant children in emergency centers in the [[Canary Islands]]. They were living in  squalid, overcrowded conditions&lt;ref&gt;[http://hrw.org/english/docs/2007/07/26/spain16449.htm HRW.org]&lt;/ref&gt; and faced the risk of abuse from their custodians and other children. The Canary Islands government, which runs the facilities, replied in a statement that the report lacked "rigor" and that "an internal investigation had failed to corroborate" Human Rights Watch's findings.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.iht.com/articles/2007/07/26/asia/abuse.php Human Rights Watch says migrant children are at risk in Canary Islands],''International Herald Tribune''&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Robert L. Bernstein]], a founder and former chairman of HRW, argued in October 2009 that "Human Rights Watch has lost critical perspective" on events in the Middle East.&lt;ref name="Bernstein_19102009"&gt;{{cite news 
|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2009/10/20/opinion/20bernstein.html?_r=1&amp;em
|title=Rights Watchdog, Lost in the Mideast
|last=Bernstein
|first=Robert L.
|date=2009-10-19
|publisher=The NY Times
|accessdate=2009-10-20}}
&lt;/ref&gt;  Bernstein argued that "[t]he region is populated by authoritarian regimes with appalling human rights records. Yet in recent years Human Rights Watch has written far more condemnations of Israel for violations of international law than of any other country in the region."&lt;ref name="Bernstein_19102009"/&gt; He urged the organization to recognize "a difference between wrongs committed in self-defense and those perpetrated intentionally."&lt;ref name="Bernstein_19102009"/&gt;

Tom Porteus, director of the London branch of Human Rights Watch, replied that the organization rejected Bernstein's "obvious double standard. Any credible human rights organisation must apply the same human rights standards to all countries."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2009/oct/30/human-rights-watch-ngo-monitor ''The Guardian'': Credible approach on human rights]&lt;/ref&gt; Jane Olson and Jonathan Fanton wrote "we were saddened to see [[Robert L. Bernstein]] argue that Israel should be judged by a different human rights standard than the rest of the world" and "as long as open societies commit human rights abuses, Human Rights Watch has a vital role to play in documenting those violations and advocating to bring them to an end."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2009/10/21/opinion/l21israel.html ''New York Times'': Crossfire: A Rights Group and Israel]&lt;/ref&gt; Human Rights Watch noted that Bernstein brought his concerns to the Human Rights Watch Board of Directors in April 2009 and also noted that the board unanimously rejected his proposed reconsideration of reporting policies in the Middle East.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hrw.org/en/news/2009/10/20/why-we-report-open-societies Human Rights Watch: Why We Report on 'Open' Societies]&lt;/ref&gt; 

Human Rights Watch made headlines in September 2009 when its Middle East military analyst, [[Marc Garlasco]] who led investigations into Israeli wars in Lebanon and Gaza, was suspended with pay pending an investigation after several media reports highlighted his interest in Second World War artifacts.&lt;ref name="Huff-2009-09-11"&gt;{{cite news
|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/marc-garlasco/human-rights-watch-invest_b_284075.html
|title=Responding to Accusations
|last=Garlasco
|first=Marc
|date=2009-09-11
|publisher=The Huffington Post
|accessdate=2009-09-13}}
&lt;/ref&gt; and accused him of collecting [[Nazi]] memorabilia.&lt;ref name="israelis_see_NYT"&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2009/09/15/world/middleeast/15nazi.html?hp Israelis See Clear Bias in Activist], New York Times, John Schwartz, September 14, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="The Guardian"&gt;{{cite news 
|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2009/sep/15/human-rights-watch-nazi-israel
|title=Human Rights Watch investigator suspended over Nazi memorabilia
|last=Pilkington
|first=Ed
|date=2009-09-15
|publisher=The Guardian
|accessdate=2010-02-15}}
&lt;/ref&gt; Garlasco has said that the allegations of Nazi sympathies were "defamatory nonsense, spread maliciously by people with an interest in trying to undermine Human Rights Watch's reporting."&lt;ref name="Huff-2009-09-11"/&gt; HRW has said the charges leveled against Garlasco are "demonstrably false" and fit "into a campaign to deflect attention from Human Rights Watch's rigorous and detailed reporting on violations of international human rights and humanitarian law by the Israeli government".&lt;ref name="HRW-2009-09-10"&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.hrw.org/en/node/85545
|title=Protecting Civilians: Military Expert Marc Garlasco
|date=2009-09-10
|publisher=Human Rights Watch
|accessdate=2009-09-11}}
&lt;/ref&gt; [[Corey Flintoff]] wrote that "critics of Human Rights Watch have suggested that Garlasco's enthusiasm for Nazi-era badges and uniforms goes beyond historical interest and makes him a Nazi sympathizer or anti-Semite."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wbur.org/news/npr/112900014 WBUR]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Publications ==
Human Rights Watch publishes reports on several topics
&lt;ref name="HRW-pub"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hrw.org/en/publications|title=Publications|publisher=Human Rights Watch|accessdate=2009-07-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; and compiles annual reports ("World Report") presenting an overview of the worldwide state of human rights.&lt;ref name="HRW-WR"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hrw.org/en/node/79288|title=Previous World Reports|publisher=Human Rights Watch|accessdate=2009-07-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; Human Rights Watch has published extensively on the [[Rwandan Genocide]] of 1994&lt;ref&gt;[http://hrw.org/doc?t=africa&amp;c=rwanda Rwandan genocide report],''Human Rights Watch''&lt;/ref&gt; and the conflicts in the [[Democratic Republic of the Congo]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://hrw.org/doc?t=africa&amp;c=congo Congo report],''Human Rights Watch''&lt;/ref&gt;

== Comparison with Amnesty International ==
Human Rights Watch and [[Amnesty International]] are the only two western-oriented international human rights organizations operating worldwide in most situations of severe oppression or abuse. Though close allies, the two groups play complementary roles, reflecting a division of labor{{Citation needed|date=March 2009}}. The major differences lie in the groups’ structure and methods for promoting change.

Amnesty International is a mass-membership organization. Mobilization of those members is the organization's central advocacy tool. Human Rights Watch's main products are its crisis-directed research and lengthy reports, whereas Amnesty lobbies and writes detailed reports, but also focuses on mass letter-writing campaigns, adopting individuals as "[[prisoners of conscience]]" and lobbying for their release. Human Rights Watch will openly lobby for specific actions for other governments to take against human rights offenders, including naming specific individuals for arrest, or for [[International sanctions|sanctions]] to be levied against certain countries, recently calling for punitive sanctions against the top leaders in [[Sudan]] who have overseen a killing campaign in [[Darfur]]. The group has also called for human rights activists who have been detained in Sudan to be released.&lt;ref&gt;[http://africa.reuters.com/top/news/usnJOE4AQ00Q.html Human rights group says activists detained in Sudan]&lt;/ref&gt;

Its documentations of human rights abuses often include extensive analysis of the political and historical backgrounds of the conflicts concerned, some of which have been published in academic journals. AI's reports, on the other hand, tend to contain less analysis, and instead focus on specific abuses of rights.

In 2010 [[The Times]] of London wrote that HRW has "all but eclipsed" Amnesty International.  According to The Times, instead of being supporting by a mass membership, as AI is, HRW depends on wealthy donors who like to see the organization's reports make headlines.  For this reason, according to the Times, HRW tends to "concentrate too much on places that the media already cares about," especially in disproportionate coverage of Israel.&lt;ref name=Scandal engulfs Human Rights Watch &gt;[http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/world/us_and_americas/article7076462.ece?token=null&amp;offset=0&amp;page=1/Nazi scandal engulfs Human Rights Watch] The Sunday Times, March 28, 2010 &lt;/ref&gt;

There are some small differences in policy: for example, Human Rights Watch believes that women have the right to wear a veil&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hrw.org/en/reports/2009/02/25/discrimination-name-neutrality-0 Discrimination in the Name of Neutrality]&lt;/ref&gt; whereas Amnesty has no policy on this issue.

== Criticisms ==

&lt;!-- PLEASE NOTE BEFORE EDITING: This section is for a summary of criticisms of HRW, and therefore must represent each criticism with equal weight. Including the newest news item about HRW does not meet this requirement. That type of material should be placed on the main criticisms article. --&gt;

{{Main|Criticism of Human Rights Watch}}

Criticism of Human Rights Watch may be classified into four major categories: accusations of poor research methods producing inaccurate reports, accusations of [[selection bias]], accusations of [[ideology|ideological]] bias, and questions regarding their funding practices.&lt;ref name=Scandal engulfs Human Rights Watch &gt;[http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/world/us_and_americas/article7076462.ece?token=null&amp;offset=0&amp;page=1/Nazi scandal engulfs Human Rights Watch] The Sunday Times, March 28, 2010 &lt;/ref&gt;   In the second category, Human Rights Watch has been criticized for perceived biases that are anti-China, [[Serbophobia|anti-Serb]],{{Citation needed|date=December 2008}} anti-Sri Lanka,&lt;ref&gt;[http://defence.lk/new.asp?fname=20090221_03 Human Rights Watch hell-bent on attacking Sri Lankan government]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.defence.lk/new.asp?fname=20090324_07 Human Right Watch is now trying to block the IMF loan]&lt;/ref&gt; anti-Israel,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.adl.org/Anti_semitism/speech_palacio.asp Anti-Semitism in Europe: Fighting Back],''Anti-Defamation League''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ngo-monitor.org/article/human_rights_watch_hrw_ NGO Monitor summary of Human Rights Watch ]&lt;/ref&gt;, pro-Israel &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.counterpunch.org/finkelstein11292006.html [[Norman Finkelstein]]'s pros and cons of HRW and Israel]&lt;/ref&gt; anti-Ethiopian government,&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation |title=The government says Human Rights Watch got it Wrong. Really? |journal=[[The Economist]] |date=February 7, 2009 |page=41 |url=http://www.economist.com/world/middle-east/displaystory.cfm?story_id=E1_TPDGTGRN }}.&lt;/ref&gt; and pro-USA.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.zmag.org/content/showarticle.cfm?ItemID=10011 ZNet |Haiti | Haiti and Human Rights Watch&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; In 2008, Venezuela expelled the organization for its criticism.&lt;ref&gt;[http://uk.reuters.com/article/idUKN1940239020080919 Reuters News] retrieved September 22, 2009&lt;/ref&gt; In the third category, Human Rights Watch was accused of using anti-Israeli sentiment to elicit support while fund-raising in [[Saudi Arabia]].&lt;ref&gt;Keinon, Herb.  [http://www.jpost.com/servlet/Satellite?pagename=JPost/JPArticle/ShowFull&amp;cid=1246443832672 "Diplomacy: Israel vs. Human Rights Watch."] ''[[Jerusalem Post]]''.  18 July 2009.  18 July 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Bernstein"&gt;Bernstein, David.  [http://online.wsj.com/article/SB124528343805525561.html "Human Rights Watch Goes to Saudi Arabia."] ''[[The Wall Street Journal]]''.  15 July 2009.  15 July 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, [[The New Republic]] has published in April 2010 a very critical piece of HRW's stance towards Israel"&lt;ref&gt;Minority Report: Human Rights Watch fights a civil war over Israel, Benjamin Birnbaum, [[The New Republic]], April 27, 2010 [http://www.tnr.com/article/minority-report-2?page=0,0]&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
{{Portal|Human rights}}
*[[American Freedom Campaign]]
*[[Avocats Sans Frontières]]
*[[Democracy Watch (International)]]
*[[Freedom House]]
*[[Helsinki Committee for Human Rights]]
*[[Human Rights First]]
*[[International Freedom of Expression Exchange]]
*[[US Human Rights Network]]

== References ==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

== External links ==
{{Commons category|Human Rights Watch}}
* [http://www.hrw.org Human Rights Watch] (official website)
* [http://www.hrw.org/world-report-2009 World Report 2009]
* [http://venezuelanalysis.com/analysis/3841 Human Rights Watch in Venezuela: Lies, Crimes and Cover-ups] James Petras, 29 September 2008

{{International human rights organizations}}

[[Category:Human Rights Watch| ]]
[[Category:Non-governmental organizations]]
[[Category:Civil rights organizations]]
[[Category:International human rights organizations]]

[[ar:مراقبة حقوق الإنسان]]
[[bs:Human Rights Watch]]
[[bg:Хюман Райтс Уоч]]
[[ca:Human Rights Watch]]
[[cs:Human Rights Watch]]
[[cy:Human Rights Watch]]
[[da:Human Rights Watch]]
[[de:Human Rights Watch]]
[[es:Human Rights Watch]]
[[eo:Human Rights Watch]]
[[fa:دیدبان حقوق بشر]]
[[fr:Human Rights Watch]]
[[hr:Human Rights Watch]]
[[id:Human Rights Watch]]
[[is:Mannréttindavaktin]]
[[it:Human Rights Watch]]
[[he:משמר זכויות האדם]]
[[ka:ჰუმან რაითს ვოჩი]]
[[lt:Human Rights Watch]]
[[nl:Human Rights Watch]]
[[ja:ヒューマン・ライツ・ウォッチ]]
[[no:Human Rights Watch]]
[[nn:Human Rights Watch]]
[[pl:Human Rights Watch]]
[[pt:Human Rights Watch]]
[[ro:Human Rights Watch]]
[[ru:Хьюман Райтс Вотч]]
[[simple:Human Rights Watch]]
[[sr:Hjuman rajts voč]]
[[sh:Human Rights Watch]]
[[fi:Human Rights Watch]]
[[sv:Human Rights Watch]]
[[ta:மனித உரிமைகள் கண்காணிப்பகம்]]
[[tr:İnsan Hakları İzleme Örgütü]]
[[uk:Г'юман Райтс Вотч]]
[[vi:Tổ chức Theo dõi Nhân quyền]]
[[yo:Human Rights Watch]]
[[zh:人权观察]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>