<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20081113114530|251539861" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="46530" pageid="46530" ns="0" title="Human Rights Watch"><revisions><rev timestamp="2008-11-14T22:08:56Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{distinguish|Bahrain Human Rights Watch Society}}
[[Image:Hrw logo.gif|thumb|right|200px|Human Rights Watch Logo]]
'''Human Rights Watch''' is a [[United States]] based, international [[non-governmental organization]] that conducts research and advocacy on [[human rights]]. Its headquarters are in [[New York City]]. 

==History==
Human Rights Watch was founded under the name [[Helsinki Watch]] in 1978 to monitor the former [[Soviet Union]]'s compliance with the [[Helsinki Accords]]. As the organization grew, it formed other "watch committees" to cover other regions of the world. In 1988, all of the committees were united under one umbrella to form Human Rights Watch. [[Robert L. Bernstein]] was a president of the organization and is one of the original founders.

==Profile==
Pursuant to the [[Universal Declaration of Human Rights]], Human Rights Watch opposes violations of basic human rights, which include [[capital punishment]] and discrimination on the basis of [[LGBT social movements|sexual orientation]]. Human Rights Watch advocates freedoms in connection with fundamental human rights, such as [[freedom of religion]] and [[freedom of the press|the press]].

Human Rights Watch produces research reports on violations of international human rights norms as set out by the Universal Declaration of Human Rights and what it perceives to be other internationally-accepted human rights norms. These reports are used as the basis for drawing international attention to abuses and pressuring governments and international organizations to reform. Researchers conduct fact-finding missions to investigate suspect situations and generate coverage in local and international [[News media|media]]. Issues raised by Human Rights Watch in its reports include social and [[discrimination|gender discrimination]], [[torture]], [[military use of children]], [[political corruption]], abuses in [[criminal justice]] systems, and the legalization of [[abortion]]. Human Rights Watch documents and reports violations of the laws of [[war]] and international humanitarian law.

Human Rights Watch also supports writers worldwide who are being persecuted for their work and are in need of financial assistance. The Hellman/Hammett grants are financed by the estate of the playwright [[Lillian Hellman]] in funds set up in her name and that of her long-time companion, the novelist [[Dashiell Hammett]]. In addition to providing financial assistance, the Hellman/Hammett grants help raise international awareness of activists who are being silenced for speaking out in defence of human rights.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hrw.org/about/info/helham.html Hellman-Hammett Grants],''Human Rights Watch''&lt;/ref&gt;

Each year, Human Rights Watch presents the Human Rights Defenders Award to activists around the world who demonstrate leadership and courage in defending human rights. The award winners work closely with Human Rights Watch in investigating and exposing human rights abuses.&lt;ref&gt;[http://hrw.org/events/2007/dinner/index.htm],''Human Rights Watch''&lt;/ref&gt;

Human Rights Watch was one of six international NGOs that founded the [[Coalition to Stop the Use of Child Soldiers]] in 1998. It is also the co-chair of the [[International Campaign to Ban Landmines]], a global coalition of civil society groups that successfully lobbied to introduce the [[Ottawa Treaty]], a treaty that prohibits the use of anti-personnel landmines.

Human Rights Watch is a founding member of the [[International Freedom of Expression Exchange]], a global network of [[non-governmental organization]]s that monitor [[censorship]] worldwide.

Human Rights Watch has more than 230 paid staff, and a budget of over US$30 million a year.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hrw.org/annual-report/finStmt2006.pdf Financial statement],''Human Rights Watch''&lt;/ref&gt;

The current executive director of Human Rights Watch is [[Kenneth Roth]]. He has held this position since 1993. Roth is a graduate of [[Yale Law School]] and [[Brown University]]. His father fled Nazi [[Germany]] in 1938. Roth started working on human rights after the declaration of martial law in [[Poland]] in 1981, and later became engaged in [[Haiti]] issues.&lt;ref&gt;[http://hrw.org/about/bios/kroth.htm Kenneth Roth Bio],''Human Rights Watch''&lt;/ref&gt;

==Issues and campaigns==
* Traffic in [[small arms]]
* [[Land mine]]s
* [[Pro-choice|Legalisation of abortion]]
* [[LGBT social movements|Gay rights]]
* Rights of [[AIDS]] patients
* Safety of civilians in war; opposes use of [[cluster bomb]]s
* [[Child labor]]
* [[Military use of children|Child soldiers]]
* [[Street children]]
* [[Genocide]], [[war crime]]s and [[crime against humanity|crimes against humanity]]
* [[Torture]]
* [[Extrajudicial punishment|Extrajudicial killings]] and abductions
* [[Legal proceedings]] against human rights abusers
* [[Human trafficking|Trafficking in women]] and girls
* Abolition of [[capital punishment]] worldwide

==Recent==
Human Rights Watch made recent headlines by criticizing the [[Jordan|Jordanian government]] for arresting elected officials who praised [[Abu Musab al-Zarqawi]], the head of [[Al-Qaeda in Iraq]], at ceremonies held in response to his death. Human Rights Watch also spoke out against the [[Mass murder#Mass murder by a state|mass killings]] and government-imposed [[famine]]s during the last decade of former [[Iraq]]i leader [[Saddam Hussein|Saddam Hussein's]] [[History of Iraq#Under Saddam|rule]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hrw.org/doc?t=mideast&amp;c=iraq&amp;document_limit=260,20 Middle east and North Africa],''Human Rights Watch''&lt;/ref&gt;

On July 26, 2007 HRW denounced that hundreds of migrant children held in emergency centers in the Spanish [[Canary Islands]] are living in [http://hrw.org/english/docs/2007/07/26/spain16449.htm squalid, overcrowded conditions] and face the risk of abuse from their custodians and other children. The Canary Islands government, which runs the facilities, replied in a statement&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.iht.com/articles/2007/07/26/asia/abuse.php Human Rights Watch says migrant children are at risk in Canary Islands],''International Herald Tribune''&lt;/ref&gt; that the report lacked "rigor" and that "an internal investigation had failed to corroborate" Human Rights Watch's findings.

==Publications==
[[Image:HRW-WR 2007 Cover.jpg|thumb|250px|Human Rights Watch World Report 2007]]

Human Rights Watch publishes reports on several topics&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hrw.org/doc/?t=pubs Publications],''Human Rights Watch''&lt;/ref&gt; and compiles annual reports ("World Report") presenting an overview of the worldwide state of human rights.

Human Rights Watch has published extensively on the [[Rwandan Genocide]] of 1994&lt;ref&gt;[http://hrw.org/doc?t=africa&amp;c=rwanda Rwandan genocide report],''Human Rights Watch''&lt;/ref&gt; and the conflicts in the [[Democratic Republic of the Congo]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://hrw.org/doc?t=africa&amp;c=congo Congo report],''Human Rights Watch''&lt;/ref&gt;

==Comparison with Amnesty International==
Human Rights Watch and [[Amnesty International]] are the only two western orientated international human rights organizations operating worldwide in most situations of severe oppression or abuse. Though close allies, the two groups play complementary roles, reflecting a division of labour. The major differences lie in the groups’ structure and methods for promoting change.

Amnesty International is a mass-membership organization. Mobilization of those members is the organization's central advocacy tool. Human Rights Watch's main products are its crisis-directed research and lengthy reports, whereas Amnesty lobbies and writes detailed reports, but also focuses on mass letter-writing campaigns, adopting individuals as "prisoners of conscience" and lobbying for their release. Human Rights Watch will openly lobby for specific actions for other governments to take against human rights offenders, including naming specific individuals for arrest, or for [[International sanctions|sanctions]] to be levied against certain countries, recently calling for punitive sanctions against the top leaders in [[Sudan]] who have overseen a killing campaign in [[Darfur]].

Its documentations of human rights abuses often include extensive analyses of the political and historical backgrounds of the conflicts concerned, some of which have been published in academic journals. AI's reports, on the other hand, tend to contain less analysis, and instead focus on specific abuses of rights.

==Criticisms==
{{main|Criticism of Human Rights Watch}}

Human Rights Watch has been criticized for perceived anti-Western, anti-China, anti-Serb and anti-Israel bias while others have criticized it for having a pro-Western and pro-Israel bias. According to a report in the Egyptian press, "the government often accuses human rights groups [including Human Rights Watch] of importing a Western agenda that offends local religious and cultural values."&lt;ref&gt;[http://weekly.ahram.org.eg/2004/680/eg9.htm Not just the Queen Boat: HRW is asking the Egyptian government to stop persecuting homosexuals and commit to reform]&lt;/ref&gt;.
Given the referenced roots of the organisation; to be orientated towards monitoring Soviet activities on the West's behalf, it is always open to criticism of continuation of this agenda with a pro-western bias. This is further compounded by its US location and dominant US managerial base.


==See also==
*[[Amnesty International]]
*[[Democracy Watch (International)]]
*[[Freedom House]]
*[[Helsinki Committee for Human Rights]]
*[[Human rights]]
*[[International Freedom of Expression Exchange]]
*[[US Human Rights Network]]
*[[American Freedom Campaign]]

==References==
&lt;div class="references-small" style="-moz-column-count:2; column-count:2;"&gt; 	 
&lt;references /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

==External links==
* [http://www.hrw.org Human Rights Watch] (official website)
* [http://www.hrw.org/wr2k7/ Human Rights Watch World Report 2007]
* [http://www.hrw.org/wr2k6/ Human Rights Watch World Report 2006]
* [http://www.hrw.org/english/docs/2006/01/13/global12428.htm Press info on Human Rights Watch World Report 2006]
* [http://hrw.org/englishwr2k8/docs/2008/01/31/usint17940.htm 2008 Report: Democracy Charade Undermines Rights]
* Edward S. Herman, David Peterson, and George Szamuely, [http://www.zmag.org/content/showarticle.cfm?ItemID=12200 Human Rights Watch in Service to the War Party: Including A Review of “Weighing the Evidence: Lessons from the Slobodan Milosevic Trial” (Human Rights Watch, December, 2006)], ZNet, February 25, 2007  
*Michael Barker, "[http://www.zmag.org/content/showarticle.cfm?ItemID=13436 Hijacking Human Rights: A Critical Examination of Human Rights Watch’s Americas Branch and their Links to the ‘Democracy’ Establishment]", ''Znet'', August 3, 2007
*Neier, Aryeh (2006)  [http://www.nybooks.com/articles/19500 "The Attack on Human Rights Watch"], ''New York Review of Books'', 53(17) November 2, 2006, accessed 20 October 2006. 
* [http://www.breakinglegalnews.com/entry/HRW-claims-US-involved-in-secret-detention-of-Somalis Human Rights Watch claims US involved in secret detention of Somalis]

{{Human rights}}

[[Category:Human Rights Watch| ]]
[[Category:Non-governmental organizations]]
[[Category:Civil rights organizations]]
[[Category:International human rights organizations]]

[[ar:هيومان رايتس واتش]]
[[bs:Human Rights Watch]]
[[bg:Хюман Райтс Уоч]]
[[cs:Human Rights Watch]]
[[da:Human Rights Watch]]
[[de:Human Rights Watch]]
[[es:Human Rights Watch]]
[[fa:دیدبان حقوق بشر]]
[[fr:Human Rights Watch]]
[[id:Human Rights Watch]]
[[is:Mannréttindavaktin]]
[[it:Human Rights Watch]]
[[he:Human Rights Watch]]
[[ka:ჰუმან რაითს ვოჩი]]
[[lt:Human Rights Watch]]
[[nl:Human Rights Watch]]
[[ja:ヒューマン・ライツ・ウォッチ]]
[[no:Human Rights Watch]]
[[nn:Human Rights Watch]]
[[pl:Human Rights Watch]]
[[pt:Human Rights Watch]]
[[ru:Хьюман Райтс Вотч]]
[[simple:Human Rights Watch]]
[[fi:Human Rights Watch]]
[[sv:Human Rights Watch]]
[[ta:மனித உரிமைகள் கண்காணிப்பகம்]]
[[vi:Tổ chức Theo dõi nhân quyền]]
[[zh:人权观察]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>