<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20121028125305|520257981" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="46530" pageid="46530" ns="0" title="Human Rights Watch"><revisions><rev timestamp="2012-11-14T12:08:39Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Redirect|HRW|other meanings of HRW|HRW (disambiguation)}}
{{Distinguish|Bahrain Human Rights Watch Society}}

{{Infobox non-profit
| name              = Human Rights Watch
| image             = [[File:Hrw logo.svg|200px]]
| type              = [[Non-profit organization|Non-profit]] [[Non-governmental organisation|NGO]]
| founded_date      = 1978
| tax_id            = 
| registration_id   =
| founder           = 
| location          = [[Empire State Building]]&lt;br&gt;[[New York City]], [[United States of America|United States]]
| origins           = 
| key_people        = {{Unbulleted list|[[Kenneth Roth]] &lt;small&gt;(Executive Director)&lt;/small&gt;|[[James F. Hoge, Jr.]] &lt;small&gt;(Chairman)&lt;/small&gt;}}
| area_served       = Worldwide
| product           = 
| mission           = 
| focus             = [[Human rights]] [[activism]]
| method            = 
| revenue           = 
| endowment         = 
| num_volunteers    = 
| num_employees     = 
| num_members       = 
| subsid            = 
| owner             = 
| non-profit_slogan = 
| former name       = Helsinki Watch
| homepage          = [http://www.hrw.org hrw.org]
| dissolved         = 
| footnotes         = 
}}
[[File:Msc 2008-Saturday, 14.00 - 16.00 Uhr-Moerk026 Roth.jpg|thumb|Current executive Director [[Kenneth Roth]] speaking at the 44th [[Munich Security Conference]] 2008]]

'''Human Rights Watch''' is an international [[non-governmental organization]] that conducts research and [[advocacy]] on [[human rights]]. Its headquarters are in [[New York City]] and it has offices in [[Berlin]], [[Beirut]], [[Brussels]], [[Chicago]], [[Geneva]], [[Johannesburg]], [[London]], [[Los Angeles]], [[Moscow]], [[Paris]], [[San Francisco]], [[Tokyo]], [[Toronto]], and [[Washington D.C.|Washington]].&lt;ref name="FAQ"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hrw.org/en/node/75138|title=Frequently Asked Questions|publisher=Human Rights Watch|accessdate=2009-07-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As of June 2011, the organization’s annual expenses totaled $50.6 million.&lt;ref name="Financial Statements, Year Ended June 30, 2011"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hrw.org/sites/default/files/related_material/financial-statements-2011.pdf|title=Financial Statements, Year Ended June 30, 2011|publisher=Human Rights Watch|accessdate=2012-06-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[George Soros]] [[Open Society Institute|Open Society Foundation]] is the primary donor of the Human Rights Watch, contributing $100 million of $128 million of contributions and grants received by the HRW in the 2011 financial year.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hrw.org/sites/default/files/related_material/financial-statements-2011.pdf See page 16 for the Open Society Foundation's contribution]&lt;/ref&gt; The $100 million contribution from the Open Society Foundation will be paid out over ten years in $10 million annual installments.&lt;ref name="George Soros to Give $100 Million to Human Rights Watch"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hrw.org/news/2010/09/07/global-challenge|title=George Soros to Give $100 Million to Human Rights Watch|publisher=Human Rights Watch}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==
{{Main|Helsinki Watch}}
Human Rights Watch was founded as a private American [[NGO]] in 1978, under the name of [[Helsinki Watch]], to monitor the former [[Soviet Union]]'s compliance with the [[Helsinki Accords]].&lt;ref name="OH"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hrw.org/en/node/75134|title=Our History |publisher=Human Rights Watch|accessdate=2009-07-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; Helsinki Watch adopted a methodology of publicly "[[name and shame|naming and shaming]]" abusive governments through media coverage and through direct exchanges with policymakers. By shining the international spotlight on human rights violations in the Soviet Union and its [[Europe]]an partners, Helsinki Watch contributed to the democratic transformations of the region in the late 1980s.&lt;ref name="OH" /&gt;

'''Americas Watch''' was founded in 1981 while bloody civil wars engulfed [[Central America]]. Relying on extensive on-the-ground fact-finding, Americas Watch not only addressed perceived abuses by government forces but also applied [[international humanitarian law]] to investigate and expose [[war crime]]s by rebel groups. In addition to raising its concerns in the affected countries, Americas Watch also examined the role played by foreign governments, particularly the [[United States government]], in providing military and political support to abusive regimes.

'''Asia Watch''' (1985), '''Africa Watch''' (1988), and '''Middle East Watch''' (1989) were added to what was then known as "'''The Watch Committees'''." In 1988, all of the committees were united under one umbrella to form Human Rights Watch.

== Profile ==
Pursuant to the [[Universal Declaration of Human Rights]], Human Rights Watch opposes violations of what it considers basic human rights, which include [[capital punishment]] and discrimination on the basis of [[LGBT social movements|sexual orientation]]. Human Rights Watch advocates freedoms in connection with fundamental human rights, such as [[freedom of religion]] and [[freedom of the press|the press]].

Human Rights Watch produces research reports on violations of [[international human rights law|international human rights norms]] as set out by the Universal Declaration of Human Rights and what it perceives to be other internationally accepted human rights norms. These reports are used as the basis for drawing international attention to abuses and pressuring governments and international organizations to reform. Researchers conduct fact-finding missions to investigate suspect situations also using diplomacy, staying in touch with victims, making files about public and also individuals and providing required security for them in critical situations and in a proper time generate coverage in local and international [[News media|media]]. Issues raised by Human Rights Watch in its reports include social and [[discrimination|gender discrimination]], [[torture]], [[military use of children]], [[political corruption]], abuses in [[criminal justice]] systems, and the legalization of [[abortion]].&lt;ref name="OH" /&gt; Human Rights Watch documents and reports violations of the laws of [[war]] and international humanitarian law.

Human Rights Watch also supports writers worldwide who are being persecuted for their work and are in need of [[financial assistance]]. The Hellman/Hammett grants are financed by the estate of the playwright [[Lillian Hellman]] in funds set up in her name and that of her long-time companion, the novelist [[Dashiell Hammett]]. In addition to providing financial assistance, the Hellman/Hammett grants help raise international awareness of activists who are being silenced for speaking out in defence of human rights.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hrw.org/about/info/helham.html Hellman-Hammett Grants],''Human Rights Watch''&lt;/ref&gt;

Each year, Human Rights Watch presents the Human Rights Defenders Award to activists around the world who demonstrate leadership and courage in defending human rights. The award winners work closely with Human Rights Watch in investigating and exposing human rights abuses.{{Citation needed|date=August 2009}}

Human Rights Watch was one of six international NGOs that founded the [[Coalition to Stop the Use of Child Soldiers]] in 1998. It is also the co-chair of the [[International Campaign to Ban Landmines]], a global coalition of civil society groups that successfully lobbied to introduce the [[Ottawa Treaty]], a treaty that prohibits the use of anti-personnel landmines.

Human Rights Watch is a founding member of the [[International Freedom of Expression Exchange]], a global network of [[non-governmental organizations]] that monitor [[censorship]] worldwide. It also co-founded the [[Cluster Munition Coalition]], which brought about an international convention banning the weapons. Human Rights Watch employs more than 275 staff—country experts, lawyers, journalists, and academics – and operates in more than 90 countries around the world.&lt;ref name="WWA"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hrw.org/en/node/75136|title=Who We Are |publisher=Human Rights Watch|accessdate=2009-07-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The current executive director of Human Rights Watch is [[Kenneth Roth]], who has held the position since 1993. Roth conducted investigations on abuses in [[Poland]] after martial law was declared 1981. He later focused on [[Haiti]], which had just emerged from the Duvalier dictatorship but continued to be plagued with problems. Roth’s awareness of human rights began with stories that his father told about escaping [[Nazi Germany]] in 1938. He graduated from [[Yale Law School]] and [[Brown University]].

== Financing and services ==
For the financial year ending June 2008, HRW reported receiving approximately US$44 million in public donations.&lt;ref name="FS-2008"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hrw.org/sites/default/files/related_material/FinancialStatements2008.pdf|title=Financial Statements. Year Ended June 30, 2008|publisher=Human Rights Watch|accessdate=2009-07-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2009, Human Rights Watch stated that they receive almost 75% of their financial support from North America, 25% from Western Europe and less than 1% from the rest of the world.&lt;ref name="SA-2009-07"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hrw.org/en/node/84512|title=Human Rights Watch Visit to Saudi Arabia |date=2009-07-17|publisher=Human Rights Watch|accessdate=2009-07-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to a 2008 financial assessment, HRW reports that it does not accept any direct or indirect funding from governments and is financed through contributions from private individuals and foundations.&lt;ref name="Financials"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hrw.org/en/news/2008/09/22/financials|title=Financials |date=2008-09-22|publisher=Human Rights Watch|accessdate=2009-07-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to [[NGO Monitor]] this policy is violated by support from the [[Dutch government]] and a May 2009 fund raising trip to [[Saudi Arabia]].&lt;ref name="Sponsors"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ngo-monitor.org/article/human_rights_watch_hrw_|title=Sponsors |date=2010-11-30|publisher=NGO Monitor|accessdate=2010-11-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Notably, [[billionaire]] financier and philanthropist [[George Soros]] announced in 2010 his intention to donate US$100 million to HRW over a period of ten years. He said, "Human Rights Watch is one of the most effective organizations I support. Human rights underpin our greatest aspirations: they're at the heart of open societies."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jpost.com/International/Article.aspx?id=187450 Soros to give Human Rights Watch $100m. over 10 years]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=WashingtonPost2010-09&gt;{{cite news| url= http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2010/09/11/AR2010091105057.html
| title= With $100 million Soros gift, Human Rights Watch looks to expand global reach
| publisher=Washington Post| date=2010-09-12| author=Colum Lynch| quote= The donation, the largest single gift ever from the Hungarian-born investor and philanthropist, is premised on the belief that U.S. leadership on human rights has been diminished by a decade of harsh policies in the war on terrorism.}}&lt;/ref&gt; The donation increases Human Rights Watch's operating budget from $48 million to $80 million. The donation was the largest in the organization's history.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2010/sep/07/george-soros-100-million-human-rights-watch George Soros gives $100 million to Human Rights Watch (The Guardian, Sept. 7, 2010)]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Charity Navigator]] gave Human Rights Watch a four-star rating overall, but only a three-star rating in their financial rating.&lt;ref&gt;"Charity Rating - Human Rights Watch." ''Charity Navigator - America's Largest Charity Evaluator | Human Rights Watch.'' [http://www.charitynavigator.org/index.cfm?bay=search.summary&amp;orgid=3845]&lt;/ref&gt; [http://charityreports.bbb.org/public/seal.aspx?ID=34521032010 The Better Business Bureau] said Human Rights Watch meets its standards for charity accountability.

Human Rights Watch published the following program and support services spending details for the financial year ending June 2011.
{|
|-  style="text-align:center; background:#f0f0f0;"
||'''Program services'''
||'''2011 Expenses (USD)'''&lt;ref name="Financial Statements, Year Ended June 30, 2011"/&gt;
|-
| [[Africa]]||$5,859,910 
|-
| [[Americas]]||$1,331,448 
|-
| [[Asia]]||$4,629,535 
|-
| [[Europe]] and [[Central Asia]]||$4,123,959 
|-
| [[Middle East]] and [[North Africa]]||$3,104,643 
|-
| [[United States]]||$1,105,571 
|-
| [[Children's Rights]]||$1,551,463 
|-
| Health &amp; Human Rights||$1,962,015   
|-
| [[International Justice]]||$1,325,749  
|-
| [[Woman's Rights]]||$2,083,890  
|-
| Other programs||$11,384,854
|-
|  style="text-align:center; background:#f0f0f0;"|'''Supporting services'''
|-
| Management and general||$3,130,051 
|-
| Fundraising||$9,045,910 
|-
|
|}

Human Rights Watch published the following program and support services spending details for the financial year ending June 2008.
{|
|-  style="text-align:center; background:#f0f0f0;"
||'''Program services'''
||'''2008 Expenses (USD)'''&lt;ref name="FS-2008"/&gt;
|-
| [[Africa]]||$5,532,631
|-
| [[Americas]]||$1,479,265
|-
| [[Asia]]||$3,212,850
|-
| [[Europe]] and [[Central Asia]]||$4,001,853
|-
| [[Middle East]] and [[North Africa]]||$2,258,459
|-
| [[United States]]||$1,195,673
|-
| [[Children's Rights]]||$1,642,064
|-
| [[International Justice]]||$1,385,121
|-
| [[Woman's Rights]]||$1,854,228
|-
| Other programs||$9,252,974
|-
|  style="text-align:center; background:#f0f0f0;"|'''Supporting services'''
|-
| Management and general||$1,984,626
|-
| Fundraising||$8,641,358
|-
|
|}

==Notable staff==
Some notable current and former staff members of Human Rights Watch have included:&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hrw.org/en/node/75139 Human Rights Watch: Our People]&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!---note that subsection reword means former notables can be listed---&gt;
*[[Robert L. Bernstein]], Founding Chair Emeritus
*[[James F. Hoge, Jr.]], Chairman of the Board
*[[Kenneth Roth]], Executive Director
*[[Jan Egeland]], Deputy Director and the Director of Human Rights Watch Europe
*[[Minky Worden]], Media Director
*[[Jamie Fellner]], Senior Counsel for the United States Program of Human Rights Watch
*[[Scott Long]], Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, and Transgender Rights Director
*[[Sarah Leah Whitson]], Middle East and North Africa Director
*[[Joe Stork]]
*[[Marc Garlasco]], former staff member
*[[Sharon Hom]]
* [[Baik Tae-Ung|Tae-Ung Baik]], former research consultant
*[[Nabeel Rajab]], member of the Advisory Committee of Human Rights Watch's Middle East Division

== Issues and campaigns ==
{{div col|2}}
* Abolition of [[capital punishment]] worldwide
* [[Arms trafficking]]
* [[Child labor]]
* [[Military use of children|Child soldiers]]
* [[Extrajudicial punishment|Extrajudicial killings]] and abductions
* [[Extraordinary rendition by the United States]]
* [[LGBT social movements|Gay rights]]
* [[Genocide]], [[war crime]]s and [[crime against humanity|crimes against humanity]]
* [[Land mine]]s
* Legal proceedings against human rights abusers
* [[Pro-choice|Legalisation of abortion on demand]]
* Rights of people with [[AIDS]]
* Safety of [[civilian]]s in war; opposes use of [[cluster bomb]]s
* [[Street children]]
* [[Torture]]
* [[Human trafficking|Trafficking in women]] and girls
* [[Women's rights]]
{{div col end}}
*[[Police brutality]]

== Publications ==
Human Rights Watch publishes reports on several topics&lt;ref name="HRW-pub"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hrw.org/en/publications|title=Publications|publisher=Human Rights Watch|accessdate=2009-07-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; and compiles annual reports, ''World Report,'' presenting an overview of the worldwide state of human rights.&lt;ref name="HRW-WR"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hrw.org/en/node/79288|title=Previous World Reports|publisher=Human Rights Watch|accessdate=2009-07-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; The next publication, ''World Report 2012,'' is being released in February 2012 by [[Seven Stories Press]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sevenstories.com/book/?GCOI=58322100060670 World Report 2012], ''Seven Stories Press''&lt;/ref&gt; Human Rights Watch has published extensively on the subjects such as [[Rwandan Genocide]] of 1994&lt;ref&gt;[http://hrw.org/doc?t=africa&amp;c=rwanda Rwandan genocide report],''Human Rights Watch''&lt;/ref&gt; and the conflicts in the [[Democratic Republic of the Congo]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://hrw.org/doc?t=africa&amp;c=congo Congo report],''Human Rights Watch''&lt;/ref&gt;

== Comparison with Amnesty International ==
Human Rights Watch and [[Amnesty International]] are the only two Western-oriented international human rights organizations operating worldwide in most situations of severe oppression or abuse.{{Citation needed|date=February 2011}} The major differences lie in the groups' structure and methods for promoting change.

Amnesty International is a mass-membership organization. Mobilization of those members is the organization's central advocacy tool. Human Rights Watch's main products are its crisis-directed research and lengthy reports, whereas Amnesty lobbies and writes detailed reports, but also focuses on mass letter-writing campaigns, adopting individuals as "[[prisoners of conscience]]" and lobbying for their release. Human Rights Watch will openly lobby for specific actions for other governments to take against human rights offenders, including naming specific individuals for arrest, or for [[International sanctions|sanctions]] to be levied against certain countries, recently calling for punitive sanctions against the top leaders in [[Sudan]] who have overseen a killing campaign in [[Darfur]]. The group has also called for human rights activists who have been detained in Sudan to be released.&lt;ref&gt;[http://africa.reuters.com/top/news/usnJOE4AQ00Q.html Human rights group says activists detained in Sudan]&lt;/ref&gt;

Its documentations of human rights abuses often include extensive analysis of the political and historical backgrounds of the conflicts concerned, some of which have been published in academic journals. AI's reports, on the other hand, tend to contain less analysis, and instead focus on specific abuses of rights.

In 2010 ''[[The Times]]'' of London wrote that HRW has "all but eclipsed" Amnesty International.  According to ''The Times'', instead of being supported by a mass membership, as AI is, HRW depends on wealthy donors who like to see the organization's reports make headlines. For this reason, according, HRW tends to "concentrate too much on places that the media already cares about", especially in disproportionate coverage of Israel.&lt;ref name="Nazi scandal engulfs Human Rights Watch" &gt;[http://www.ngo-monitor.org/article/ngo_monitor_research_featured_in_sunday_times_nazi_scandal_engulfs_human_rights_watch_ NGO Monitor research featured in Sunday Times: "Nazi scandal engulfs Human Rights Watch"], March 28, 2010. Retrieved 2012-07-19.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Criticism ==
&lt;!-- PLEASE NOTE BEFORE EDITING: This section is for a summary of criticisms of HRW, and therefore must represent each criticism with equal weight. Including the newest news item about HRW does not meet this requirement. That type of material should be placed on the main criticisms article. --&gt;
{{Main|Criticism of Human Rights Watch}}
HRW has been criticized by national governments, other NGOs, its founder and former Chairman [[Robert L. Bernstein]], and the media. It has been accused by critics&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2000/feb/25/chechnya.marktran Russia investigates alleged Chechnya atrocities (The Guardian, Feb. 25, 2000)]&lt;BR&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/1965471.stm 'No Jenin massacre' says rights group (BBC, May 3, 2002)]&lt;BR&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/2677661.stm Libyan human rights in the spotlight (BBC, January 20, 2003)]&lt;/ref&gt; of being influenced by [[United States]] government policy,&lt;ref name="naiman_hrw_washington"&gt;{{Cite web| last =Naiman| first =Robert| authorlink =| coauthors =| title =Latin America Scholars Urge Human Rights Watch to Speak Up on Honduras Coup| work =| publisher =[[Huffington Post]]| date =2009-08-21| url =http://www.huffingtonpost.com/robert-naiman/latin-america-scholars-ur_b_265282.html | doi =| accessdate =2009-08-22 |archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5jELkhpuR |archivedate=2009-08-22 |deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt; in particular in relation to reporting on [[Latin America]];&lt;ref name="washtimesaircraft"&gt;{{Cite web| author=Steve Miller and Joseph Curl | year=2004 | url=http://newsmine.org/archive/war-on-terror/haiti/march-04-coup/aristide-removal/aristide-accuses-us-of-forcing-his-ouster.txt | title= Aristide accuses U.S. of forcing his ouster | publisher=Washington Times | accessdate=2005-12-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="demnow"&gt;{{Cite web| title = Aristide related articles| publisher = [[Democracy Now]]| url = http://www.democracynow.org/index.pl?issue=20040301 | accessdate=2006-07-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="ZNet_Haiti2004"&gt;{{Cite web| last =Emersberger| first =Joe| authorlink =| coauthors =| title=Haiti and Human Rights Watch| work =| publisher =[[Z Communications]]| date =2006-03-29| url =http://www.zmag.org/znet/viewArticle/4131 |format =| doi =| accessdate =2009-08-11 |archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5ixS2Xhem |archivedate=2009-08-11 |deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="coha"&gt;[[Council on Hemispheric Affairs]], 12 January 2009, [http://www.coha.org/2009/01/scholars-respond-to-hrw-directors-riposte-on-venezuelan-human-rights/ Scholars Respond to HRW’s Kenneth Roth’s Riposte on Venezuelan Human Rights]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="commond_90experts_HRW_hn"&gt;{{Cite web| last =Grandin| first =Greg| authorlink =Greg Grandin| coauthors =Adrienne Pine| title =Over 90 Experts Call on Human Rights Watch to Speak Out on Honduras Abuses| work =| publisher =[[Common Dreams]]| date =2009-08-22| url =http://www.commondreams.org/newswire/2009/08/21 |format =| doi =| accessdate =2009-08-22 |archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5jE3pnzk8 |archivedate=2009-08-22 |deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt; ignoring [[anti-Semitism]] in Europe or being anti-Semitic;&lt;ref name="adl_hrwantisemit"&gt;[http://www.adl.org/Anti_semitism/speech_palacio.asp Anti-Semitism in Europe: Fighting Back],''Anti-Defamation League''&lt;/ref&gt; biases in relation to the [[Arab–Israeli conflict]]; and unfair and biased reporting of [[Human rights in Eritrea|human rights issues]] in [[Eritrea]] and [[Ethiopia]].&lt;ref name="HRW-Service-for-Life"&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.hrw.org/en/news/2009/04/16/eritrea-repression-creating-human-rights-crisis
|title=Eritrea: Repression Creating Human Rights Crisis|date=2009-04-16|publisher=Human Rights Watch|accessdate=2009-08-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="AC-Tesfamariam"&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.americanchronicle.com/articles/view/100657|title=Human Rights Watch at Chatham House-A Peddlers Event|last=Tesfamariam|first=Sophia|date=2009-04-29|publisher=American Chronicle|accessdate=2009-08-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="economist_hrw_ethiopia"&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.economist.com/research/articlesBySubject/displaystory.cfm?subjectid=1521509&amp;story_id=13061682 | work=The Economist | title=A row over human rights | date=2009-02-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; Accusations in relation to the Arab–Israeli conflict include claims that HRW is biased against [[Israel]]&lt;ref name="Huff-Swiftboating"&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/daniel-levy/the-swiftboating-of-human_b_241634.html|title=The "Swiftboating" of Human Rights Watch|last=Levy|first=Daniel|date=2009-07-20|publisher=The Huffington Post|accessdate=2009-08-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="JP-Israel-vs-HRW"&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://fr.jpost.com/servlet/Satellite?cid=1246443832672&amp;pagename=JPost/JPArticle/ShowFull|title=Diplomacy: Israel vs. Human Rights Watch|last=Keinon|first=Herb|date=2009-07-16|publisher=The Jerusalem Post|accessdate=2009-08-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="HRW-false-allegations"&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.hrw.org/en/news/2009/08/14/false-allegations-about-human-rights-watch-s-latest-gaza-report|title=False Allegations about Human Rights Watch’s Latest Gaza Report|date=2009-08-14|publisher=Human Rights Watch|accessdate=2009-08-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; and that requesting or accepting donations from [[Saudi Arabia]]n citizens causes it to be biased;&lt;ref name="Bernstein"&gt;Bernstein, David.  [http://online.wsj.com/article/SB124528343805525561.html "Human Rights Watch Goes to Saudi Arabia."] ''[[The Wall Street Journal]]''.  15 July 2009.  15 July 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; it has also been accused of unbalanced reporting against [[Palestinian militant]] groups by [[Jonathan Cook]].&lt;ref name="finkelstein_humanshields"&gt;http://www.counterpunch.org/cook11302006.html&lt;/ref&gt;

HRW has publicly responded to criticisms relating to its reporting on Latin America&lt;ref name="nacla_roth_on_ve"&gt;https://nacla.org/node/5369&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="newstates_porteoushas"&gt;Tom Porteus, 30 September 2008, ''[[New Statesman]]'', [http://www.newstatesman.com/human-rights/2008/09/hrw-chavez-shaughnessy HRW v Chavez II]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="hrw_indirectly_responds_to_93academics"&gt;{{Cite web| author=Human Rights Watch| title=Honduras: Rights Report Shows Need for Increased International Pressure| publisher =Human Rights Watch| date =2009-08-25| accessdate =2009-08-28 |archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5jNGgJhhK |archivedate=2009-08-28 |url=http://www.hrw.org/en/news/2009/08/25/honduras-rights-report-shows-need-increased-international-pressure}}&lt;/ref&gt; and in the context of the Arab–Israeli conflict.&lt;ref name="HRW-false-allegations" /&gt;&lt;ref name="JP-Derfner-2009-07-22"&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://fr.jpost.com/servlet/Satellite?cid=1248277865531&amp;pagename=JPost/JPArticle/ShowFull|title=Rattling the Cage: The smearing of human rights organizations|last=Derfner|first=Larry|date=2009-07-22|publisher=The Jerusalem Post|accessdate=2009-08-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="hrw_saudi_response_1"&gt;Visit to Saudi Arabia and False Allegations of Human Rights Watch 'Bias' [http://www.hrw.org/en/node/84956]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="HRW_response"&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.hrw.org/en/node/84512 |title=Human Rights Watch Visit to Saudi Arabia |publisher=Human Rights Watch}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="cookcounterpunch"&gt;{{Cite web| last = Whitson | first = Sarah Leah | authorlink = | coauthors = | title = Hezbollah's Rockets and Civilian Casualties: A Response to Jonathan Cook | work = | publisher = Counterpunch | date = September 22, 2006 | url = http://www.counterpunch.org/whitson09222006.html | doi = | accessdate = 2006-10-14 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===World report 2012===
''[[The Washington Post]]'' reports that [[Iraq]] Prime Minister [[Nouri al-Maliki]] said the report was "one-sided and deeply flawed." Iraqi government spokesman, Ali Hadi al-Moussawi said that it "relied on sources that are inaccurate, biased and not factual."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.washingtonpost.com/world/middle_east/human-rights-watch-details-iraq-crackdowns-warns-of-budding-police-state/2012/01/22/gIQAlSFkIQ_story.html Human Rights Watch details Iraq crackdowns, warns of ‘budding police state']&lt;/ref&gt; Writing in [[China Daily]], Shen Hui says that "the report seriously lacks in objectivity and impartiality."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.chinadaily.com.cn/sunday/2012-01/29/content_14498392.htm Human rights report flawed by omissions and bias]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Robin Sheppard]], writing in ''[[The Jewish Chronicle]]'', says that western governments should not believe report's message that "much like the revolutions that upended [[Revolutions of 1989|Eastern Europe in 1989]], the Arab upheavals were inspired by a vision of freedom, a desire for a voice in one's destiny, and a quest for governments that are accountable to the public rather than captured by a ruling elite." Sheppard continues and says that it is not a 'vision of freedom' and that referring to 1989 is "dangerously misleading."&lt;ref name="thejc.com"&gt;[http://www.thejc.com/comment-and-debate/analysis/62617/human-rights-watch-gets-egypt-all-wrong Human Rights Watch gets Egypt all wrong]&lt;/ref&gt; Sheppard, however, is offering his own commentary when he says that "hostility to Israel is deeply intertwined with the kind of vitriolic mass antisemitism".&lt;ref name="thejc.com"/&gt;

==Recent controversies==
{{merge|Criticism of Human Rights Watch|date=February 2011}}

[[Robert L. Bernstein]], a founder and former chairman of HRW, argued in October 2009 that "Human Rights Watch has lost critical perspective" on events in the [[Middle East]].&lt;ref name="Bernstein_19102009"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2009/10/20/opinion/20bernstein.html?_r=1&amp;em|title=Rights Watchdog, Lost in the Mideast|last=Bernstein|first=Robert L.|date=2009-10-19|publisher=The NY Times|accessdate=2009-10-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bernstein argued that "[t]he region is populated by authoritarian regimes with appalling human rights records. Yet in recent years Human Rights Watch has written far more condemnations of Israel for violations of international law than of any other country in the region."&lt;ref name="Bernstein_19102009"/&gt; Tom Porteus, director of the London branch of Human Rights Watch, replied that the organization rejected Bernstein's "obvious double standard. Any credible human rights organisation must apply the same human rights standards to all countries."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2009/oct/30/human-rights-watch-ngo-monitor ''The Guardian'': Credible approach on human rights]&lt;/ref&gt; 

Strong criticism against Human Rights Watch was caused by the Organization's declarations in favour of [[CIA]] illegal actions of [[Extraordinary rendition by the United States|Extraordinary rendition]] towards suspected terrorists.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.huffingtonpost.com/tom-hayden/cia-secret-rendition-poli_b_162916.html CIA Secret Rendition Policy Backed by Human Rights Groups?], ''The Huffington Post''&lt;/ref&gt;

Human Rights Watch made headlines in September 2009 when its Middle East military analyst, [[Marc Garlasco]] who led investigations into Israeli wars in [[Lebanon]] and [[Gaza]], was found posing on the internet dressed in a sweat shirt with a German [[Iron Cross]]. After pressure from the media HRW suspended Marc with pay pending an investigation. Several media reports highlighted his interest in [[World War II]] artifacts&lt;ref name="Huff-2009-09-11"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/marc-garlasco/human-rights-watch-invest_b_284075.html|title=Responding to Accusations|last=Garlasco
|first=Marc|date=2009-09-11|publisher=The Huffington Post|accessdate=2009-09-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; and accused him of collecting [[Nazi]] memorabilia.&lt;ref name="israelis_see_NYT"&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2009/09/15/world/middleeast/15nazi.html?hp Israelis See Clear Bias in Activist], New York Times, John Schwartz, September 14, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="The Guardian"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2009/sep/15/human-rights-watch-nazi-israel|title=Human Rights Watch investigator suspended over Nazi memorabilia|last=Pilkington|first=Ed|date=2009-09-15|publisher=The Guardian|accessdate=2010-02-15}}
&lt;/ref&gt; Garlasco has said that the allegations of Nazi sympathies were "defamatory nonsense, spread maliciously by people with an interest in trying to undermine Human Rights Watch's reporting."&lt;ref name="Huff-2009-09-11"/&gt; HRW has said the charges leveled against Garlasco are "demonstrably false" and fit "into a campaign to deflect attention from Human Rights Watch's rigorous and detailed reporting on violations of international human rights and humanitarian law by the Israeli government".&lt;ref name="HRW-2009-09-10"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hrw.org/en/node/85545|title=Protecting Civilians: Military Expert Marc Garlasco
|date=2009-09-10|publisher=Human Rights Watch|accessdate=2009-09-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

In February 2011, HRW appointed Shawan Jabarin to their Mideast Advisory Board. Jabarin is a very controversial figure, labeled "[[Dr. Jekyll and Mr. Hyde]]" by the Israeli [[Supreme Court]], for his dual roles in both the terrorist organization [[PFLP]], and the human rights organization, [[Al Haq]]. HRW’s decision to include Jabarin on its Mideast Board sparked criticism from [[Robert L. Bernstein]], a founder of HRW, Stuart Robinowitz, a prominent New York attorney who has undertaken human-rights missions for the [[American Bar Association]] and [[Helsinki Watch]] (the predecessor to HRW) in Yugoslavia, Bulgaria and El Salvador, and Prof. [[Gerald Steinberg]], the president of the Jerusalem-based [[NGO Monitor]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jpost.com/International/Article.aspx?id=208768 HRW appoints alleged terrorist to Mideast Board]&lt;/ref&gt;

In a Los Angeles Times op-ed, February 24, 2011, after the [[2011 Libyan civil war]] intensified, [[Sarah Leah Whitson]], head of the Middle East and North Africa division of HRW, acknowledged the absence of human rights reforms in Libya and said “With no progress on any institutional or legal reforms. For sure, most Libyans we spoke with never had much faith that [Muammar Gaddafi] would learn new tricks, or that the announced reforms were anything more than an endless loop of promises made and broken.”&lt;ref&gt;[http://articles.latimes.com/2011/feb/24/opinion/la-oe-whitson-libya-20110224 Libya: To oust a tyrant]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Jeffrey Goldberg]], writing in the [[Atlantic Monthly]], took Whitson to task for her having had "something of a soft spot" for Gaddafi and his son.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.theatlantic.com/international/archive/2011/02/giving-qaddafi-the-benefit-of-the-doubt/71782/ Giving Qaddafi the Benefit of the Doubt]&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
{{Portal|Human rights}}
*[[American Freedom Campaign]]
*[[Avocats Sans Frontières]]

*[[Freedom House]]
*[[Helsinki Committee for Human Rights]]
*[[Human Rights First]]
*[[International Freedom of Expression Exchange]]
*[[US Human Rights Network]]

== References ==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}
{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
{{Commons category|Human Rights Watch}}
* [http://www.hrw.org Human Rights Watch] (official website)

{{International human rights organizations}}

[[Category:Civil rights organizations]]
[[Category:Human Rights Watch| ]]
[[Category:International human rights organizations]]
[[Category:Non-governmental organizations]]
[[Category:Organizations established in 1978]]

[[ar:هيومن رايتس ووتش]]
[[bn:হিউম্যান রাইটস্‌ ওয়াচ]]
[[bg:Хюман Райтс Уоч]]
[[bs:Human Rights Watch]]
[[ca:Human Rights Watch]]
[[cs:Human Rights Watch]]
[[cy:Human Rights Watch]]
[[da:Human Rights Watch]]
[[de:Human Rights Watch]]
[[es:Human Rights Watch]]
[[eo:Human Rights Watch]]
[[fa:دیدبان حقوق بشر]]
[[fr:Human Rights Watch]]
[[hr:Human Rights Watch]]
[[id:Human Rights Watch]]
[[is:Mannréttindavaktin]]
[[it:Human Rights Watch]]
[[he:משמר זכויות האדם]]
[[ka:ჰუმან რაითს ვოჩი]]
[[la:Human Rights Watch]]
[[lt:Human Rights Watch]]
[[nl:Human Rights Watch]]
[[ja:ヒューマン・ライツ・ウォッチ]]
[[no:Human Rights Watch]]
[[nn:Human Rights Watch]]
[[pl:Human Rights Watch]]
[[pt:Human Rights Watch]]
[[ro:Human Rights Watch]]
[[ru:Хьюман Райтс Вотч]]
[[simple:Human Rights Watch]]
[[sr:Hjuman rajts voč]]
[[sh:Human Rights Watch]]
[[fi:Human Rights Watch]]
[[sv:Human Rights Watch]]
[[ta:மனித உரிமைகள் கண்காணிப்பகம்]]
[[tr:İnsan Hakları İzleme Örgütü]]
[[uk:Г'юман Райтс Вотч]]
[[vi:Tổ chức Theo dõi Nhân quyền]]
[[yo:Human Rights Watch]]
[[zh:人权观察]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>