<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20161114234543|749561532" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="46530" pageid="46530" ns="0" title="Human Rights Watch"><revisions><rev timestamp="2016-11-17T03:23:35Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{redirect|HRW}}
{{Distinguish|Bahrain Human Rights Watch Society|Human Rights Campaign}}
{{Infobox non-profit
| name              = Human Rights Watch
| image             = Hrw logo.svg
| image_size        = 200px
| type              = [[Non-profit organization|Non-profit]] [[Non-governmental organization|NGO]]
| founded_date      = {{start date and age|1978}}
| tax_id            =
| registration_id   =
| founder           =
| headquarters      = [[Empire State Building]]&lt;br&gt;[[New York City]], [[New York (state)|New York]], [[United States|U.S.]]
| origins           =
| key_people        = [[Kenneth Roth]]&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;(Executive Director)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br /&gt;[[James F. Hoge, Jr.]]&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;(Chairman)&lt;/small&gt;
| area_served       = Worldwide
| product           = non profit human rights advocacy
| mission           = To become a voice of Justice
| focus             = [[Human rights]] [[activism]]
| method            =
| revenue           =
| endowment         =
| num_volunteers    =
| num_employees     =
| num_members       =
| subsid            =
| owner             =
| non-profit_slogan =
| former name       = Helsinki Watch
| homepage          = [https://www.hrw.org/ hrw.org]
| dissolved         =
| footnotes         =
}}
[[File:Msc 2008-Saturday, 14.00 - 16.00 Uhr-Moerk026 Roth.jpg|thumb|Current executive Director [[Kenneth Roth]] speaking at the 44th [[Munich Security Conference]] 2008]]

'''Human Rights Watch''' ('''HRW''') is an American-founded international [[non-governmental organization]] that conducts research and [[advocacy]] on [[human rights]]. HRW headquarters are in [[New York City]] with offices in [[Amsterdam]], [[Beirut]], [[Berlin]], [[Brussels]], [[Chicago]], [[Geneva]], [[Johannesburg]], [[London]], [[Los Angeles]], [[Moscow]], [[Nairobi]], [[Paris]], [[San Francisco]], [[Sydney]], [[Tokyo]], [[Toronto]], [[Washington, D.C.]], and [[Zurich]].&lt;ref name="FAQ"&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.hrw.org/node/75138|title=Frequently Asked Questions|publisher=Human Rights Watch|accessdate=2015-01-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The organization's annual expenses totaled $50.6 million in 2011&lt;ref name="Financial Statements, Year Ended June 30, 2011"&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.hrw.org/sites/default/files/related_material/financial-statements-2011.pdf|title=Financial Statements, Year Ended June 30, 2011|publisher=Human Rights Watch|accessdate=2012-06-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; and $69.2 million in 2014.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.hrw.org/sites/default/files/related_material/financial-statements-2014.pdf|title=Financial Statements, Year Ended June 30, 2014|publisher=Human Rights Watch|accessdate=2016-08-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==
{{Main|Helsinki Watch}}
Human Rights Watch was founded as a private American [[NGO]] in 1978, under the name [[Helsinki Watch]], to monitor the former [[Soviet Union]]'s compliance with the [[Helsinki Accords]].&lt;ref name="OH"&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.hrw.org/en/node/75134|title=Our History |publisher=Human Rights Watch|accessdate=2009-07-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; Helsinki Watch adopted a practice of publicly "[[name and shame|naming and shaming]]" abusive governments through media coverage and through direct exchanges with policymakers. By shining the international spotlight on human rights violations in the Soviet Union and its [[Europe]]an partners, Helsinki Watch contributed to the democratic transformations of the region in the late 1980s.&lt;ref name="OH" /&gt;

'''Americas Watch''' was founded in 1981 while bloody civil wars engulfed [[Central America]]. Relying on extensive on-the-ground fact-finding, Americas Watch not only addressed perceived abuses by government forces but also applied [[international humanitarian law]] to investigate and expose [[war crime]]s by rebel groups. In addition to raising its concerns in the affected countries, Americas Watch also examined the role played by foreign governments, particularly the [[United States government]], in providing military and political support to abusive regimes.

'''Asia Watch''' (1985), '''Africa Watch''' (1988), and '''Middle East Watch''' (1989) were added to what was known as "'''The Watch Committees'''". In 1988, all of these committees were united under one umbrella to form Human Rights Watch.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Our History|url=https://www.hrw.org/node/75134|agency=Human Rights Watch (HRW.org) |accessdate=28 February 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Chauhan|first=Yamini|title=Human Rights Watch|url=http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/1459072/Human-Rights-Watch|work=Encyclopedia Britannica}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Profile ==

Pursuant to the [[Universal Declaration of Human Rights]], Human Rights Watch (HRW) opposes violations of what it considers basic human rights. This includes [[capital punishment]] and discrimination on the basis of [[LGBT social movements|sexual orientation]]. HRW advocates freedoms in connection with fundamental human rights, such as [[freedom of religion]] and [[freedom of the press]].

Human Rights Watch publishes research reports on violations of [[international human rights law|international human rights norms]] as set out by the Universal Declaration of Human Rights and what it perceives to be other internationally accepted, human-rights norms. These reports are used as the basis for drawing international attention to abuses and pressuring governments and international organizations to reform. Researchers conduct fact-finding missions to investigate suspect situations also using diplomacy, staying in touch with victims, making files about public and individuals, and providing required security for them in critical situations and in a proper time generate coverage in local and international [[News media|media]]. Issues raised by Human Rights Watch in its reports include social and [[discrimination|gender discrimination]], [[torture]], [[military use of children]], [[political corruption]], abuses in [[criminal justice]] systems, and the legalization of [[abortion]].&lt;ref name="OH" /&gt; HRW has documented and reported various violations of the laws of [[war]] and international humanitarian law.

Human Rights Watch also supports writers worldwide, who are being persecuted for their work and are in need of [[Welfare (financial aid)|financial assistance]]. The Hellman/Hammett grants are financed by the estate of the playwright [[Lillian Hellman]] in funds set up in her name and that of her long-time companion, the novelist [[Dashiell Hammett]]. In addition to providing financial assistance, the Hellman/Hammett grants help raise international awareness of activists who are being silenced for speaking out in defense of human rights.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.hrw.org/about/info/helham.html Hellman-Hammett Grants],''Human Rights Watch''&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Nabeel Rajab and Abdulhadi Alkhawaja helping an old woman after police attacked a peaceful protest in August 2010.jpg|thumb|[[Nabeel Rajab]] helping an old woman after [[Bahrain]]i police attacked a peaceful protest on 14 August 2010]]

Each year, Human Rights Watch presents the Human Rights Defenders Award to activists around the world who demonstrate leadership and courage in defending human rights. The award winners work closely with HRW in investigating and exposing human rights abuses.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Human Rights Watch|title=Five Activists Win Human Rights Watch Awards|url=https://www.hrw.org/news/2008/09/14/five-activists-win-human-rights-watch-awards|publisher=Human Rights Watch|accessdate=23 February 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="SocialSciences.in"&gt;{{cite web|last=SocialSciences.in|title=Human Rights Watch|url=http://socialsciences.in/article/human-rights-watch|accessdate=23 February 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Human Rights Watch was one of six international NGOs that founded the [[Coalition to Stop the Use of Child Soldiers]] in 1998. It is also the co-chair of the [[International Campaign to Ban Landmines]], a global coalition of civil society groups that successfully lobbied to introduce the [[Ottawa Treaty]], a treaty that prohibits the use of anti-personnel landmines.

Human Rights Watch is a founding member of the [[International Freedom of Expression Exchange]], a global network of [[non-governmental organizations]] that monitor [[censorship]] worldwide. It also co-founded the [[Cluster Munition Coalition]], which brought about an international convention banning the weapons. HRW employs more than 275 staff—country experts, lawyers, journalists, and academics – and operates in more than 90 countries around the world.&lt;ref name="WWA"&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.hrw.org/en/node/75136|title=Who We Are |publisher=Human Rights Watch|accessdate=2009-07-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The current executive director of HRW is [[Kenneth Roth]], who has held the position since 1993. Roth conducted investigations on abuses in [[Poland]] after martial law was declared 1981. He later focused on [[Haiti]], which had just emerged from the Duvalier dictatorship but continued to be plagued with problems. Roth’s awareness of the importance of human rights began with stories his father had told about escaping [[Nazi Germany]] in 1938. Roth graduated from [[Yale Law School]] and [[Brown University]].

=== Allegations of bias ===
{{Main|Criticism of Human Rights Watch}}
HRW has been criticized for perceived bias by the national governments it has investigated for human rights abuses,&lt;ref&gt;"[http://www.nytimes.com/2014/08/13/world/middleeast/egypt-human-rights-watch-muslim-brotherhood.html After Human Rights Watch Report, Egypt Says Group Broke Law]". ''The New York Times.'' 12 August 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;"[http://yalibnan.com/2016/07/01/saudi-arabia-outraged-by-amnesty-international-and-human-rights-watchs-criticism/ Saudi Arabia outraged by Amnesty International and Human Rights Watch’s criticism]". [[Ya Libnan]]. 1 July 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="economist_hrw_ethiopia"&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.economist.com/research/articlesBySubject/displaystory.cfm?subjectid=1521509&amp;story_id=13061682 | work=The Economist | title=A row over human rights | date=2009-02-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; and by [[NGO Monitor]],&lt;ref name="HRW profile from NGO-Monitor"&gt;{{cite web|title=HUMAN RIGHTS WATCH (HRW)|url=http://www.ngo-monitor.org/article/human_rights_watch_hrw_|website=http://www.ngo-monitor.org/|accessdate=2014-08-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; and HRW's founder, and former Chairman, [[Robert L. Bernstein]].&lt;ref name="Bernstein_19102009"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2009/10/20/opinion/20bernstein.html?_r=1&amp;em|title=Rights Watchdog, Lost in the Mideast|last=Bernstein|first=Robert L.|date=2009-10-19|publisher=The NY Times|accessdate=2009-10-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bias allegations include undue influence by United States government policy, and claims that HRW is biased both for Israel and against Israel.  HRW has routinely publicly responded to, and often rejected, criticism of its reporting and findings.&lt;ref name="Knuckey"&gt;''The Transformation of Human Rights Fact-Finding''; Sarah Knuckey; [[Oxford University Press]], 2015; Pgs. 355-376&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="cookonhrwone"&gt;{{cite web| last = Cook | first = Jonathan | authorlink = Jonathan Cook | title = The Israel Lobby Works Its Magic, Again | work = | publisher = [[CounterPunch]] | date = 7 September 2006 | url = http://www.counterpunch.org/2006/09/07/the-israel-lobby-works-its-magic-again/ }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="cookcounterpunch"&gt;{{cite web| last = Whitson | first = Sarah Leah | authorlink = | title = Hezbollah's Rockets and Civilian Casualties: A Response to Jonathan Cook | work = | publisher = Counterpunch | date = September 22, 2006 | url = http://web.archive.org/web/20080223090033/http://www.counterpunch.org/whitson0922 | doi = | accessdate = 2006-10-14 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| last = Cook | first = Jonathan | authorlink = Jonathan Cook | title = Human Rights Watch still denying Lebanon the right to defend itself | work = | publisher = [[Z Communications]] | date = September 26, 2006 | url = http://www.zmag.org/content/showarticle.cfm?ItemID=11048 | doi = | accessdate = 2006-10-14 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.counterpunch.org/cook11302006.html |title=Palestinians Are Being Denied the Right of Non-Violent Resistance? » CounterPunch: Tells the Facts, Names the Names |publisher=CounterPunch |date=2006-11-30 |accessdate=2013-08-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.counterpunch.org/2006/11/29/human-rights-watch-must-retract-its-shameful-press-release/ Human Rights Watch Must Retract Its Shameful Press Release]; ''[[CounterPunch]]''; November 29, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.globalresearch.ca/human-rights-watch-hrw-whitewashes-israel-the-law-supports-hamas-reflections-on-israels-latest-massacre/5393036 Human Rights Watch (HRW) Whitewashes Israel, The Law Supports Hamas: Reflections on Israel’s Latest Massacre]; ''[[Centre for Research on Globalization]]''; [[Norman Finkelstein]]; July 20, 2014&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Comparison with Amnesty International ===
Human Rights Watch and [[Amnesty International]] are the only two Western-oriented international human rights organizations operating in most situations of severe oppression or abuse worldwide.&lt;ref name="SocialSciences.in"/&gt; The major differences lie in the group's structure and methods for promoting change.

Amnesty International is a mass-membership organization. Mobilization of those members is the organization's central advocacy tool. Human Rights Watch's main products are its crisis-directed research and lengthy reports, whereas Amnesty International lobbies and writes detailed reports, but also focuses on mass letter-writing campaigns, adopting individuals as "[[prisoners of conscience]]" and lobbying for their release. Human Rights Watch will openly lobby for specific actions for other governments to take against human rights offenders, including naming specific individuals for arrest, or for [[International sanctions|sanctions]] to be levied against certain countries, recently calling for punitive sanctions against the top leaders in [[Sudan]] who have overseen a killing campaign in [[Darfur]]. The group has also called for human rights activists who have been detained in Sudan to be released.&lt;ref&gt;[http://africa.reuters.com/top/news/usnJOE4AQ00Q.html Human rights group says activists detained in Sudan]&lt;/ref&gt;

Its documentations of human rights abuses often include extensive analysis of the political and historical backgrounds of the conflicts concerned, some of which have been published in academic journals. AI's reports, on the other hand, tend to contain less analysis, and instead focus on specific abuses of rights.{{citation needed|date=September 2013}}

In 2010, ''[[The Times]]'' of London wrote that HRW has "all but eclipsed" Amnesty International. According to ''The Times'', instead of being supported by a mass membership, as AI is, HRW depends on wealthy donors who like to see the organization's reports make headlines. For this reason, according to ''The Times'', HRW tends to "concentrate too much on places that the media already cares about", especially in disproportionate coverage of Israel.&lt;ref name="Nazi scandal engulfs Human Rights Watch" &gt;[http://www.ngo-monitor.org/article/ngo_monitor_research_featured_in_sunday_times_nazi_scandal_engulfs_human_rights_watch_ NGO Monitor research featured in Sunday Times: "Nazi scandal engulfs Human Rights Watch"], March 28, 2010. Retrieved 2012-07-19.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Financing and services ==
For the financial year ending June 2008, HRW reported receiving approximately US$44 million in public donations.&lt;ref name="FS-2008"&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.hrw.org/sites/default/files/related_material/FinancialStatements2008.pdf|title=Financial Statements. Year Ended June 30, 2008|publisher=Human Rights Watch|accessdate=2009-07-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2009, Human Rights Watch stated that they receive almost 75% of their financial support from North America, 25% from Western Europe and less than 1% from the rest of the world.&lt;ref name="SA-2009-07"&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.hrw.org/en/node/84512|title=Human Rights Watch Visit to Saudi Arabia |date=2009-07-17|publisher=Human Rights Watch|accessdate=2009-07-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to a 2008 financial assessment, HRW reports that it does not accept any direct or indirect funding from governments and is financed through contributions from private individuals and foundations.&lt;ref name="Financials"&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.hrw.org/en/news/2008/09/22/financials|title=Financials |date=2008-09-22|publisher=Human Rights Watch|accessdate=2009-07-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Financier and philanthropist [[George Soros]] of the [[Open Society Institute|Open Society Foundation]] announced in 2010 his intention to grant US $100 million to HRW over a period of ten years to help it expand its efforts internationally. He said, "Human Rights Watch is one of the most effective organizations I support. Human rights underpin our greatest aspirations: they're at the heart of open societies."&lt;ref name="George Soros to Give $100 Million to Human Rights Watch"&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.hrw.org/news/2010/09/07/global-challenge|title=George Soros to Give $100 Million to Human Rights Watch|publisher=Human Rights Watch}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=WashingtonPost2010-09&gt;{{cite news| url= http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2010/09/11/AR2010091105057.html
| title= With $100 million Soros gift, Human Rights Watch looks to expand global reach
| publisher=Washington Post| date=2010-09-12| author=Colum Lynch| quote= The donation, the largest single gift ever from the Hungarian-born investor and philanthropist, is premised on the belief that U.S. leadership on human rights has been diminished by a decade of harsh policies in the war on terrorism.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.hrw.org/sites/default/files/related_material/financial-statements-2011.pdf See page 16 for the Open Society Foundation's contribution]&lt;/ref&gt; The donation increases Human Rights Watch's operating staff of 300 by 120 people. The donation was the largest in the organization's history.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2010/sep/07/george-soros-100-million-human-rights-watch George Soros gives $100 million to Human Rights Watch (The Guardian, Sept. 7, 2010)]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Charity Navigator]] gave Human Rights Watch a four-star rating overall, and its financial rating increased from three stars in 2015 to the maximum four as of June 2016.&lt;ref&gt;"Charity Rating - Human Rights Watch." ''Charity Navigator - America's Largest Charity Evaluator | Human Rights Watch.'' [https://www.charitynavigator.org/index.cfm?bay=search.summary&amp;orgid=3845]&lt;/ref&gt; [http://charityreports.bbb.org/public/seal.aspx?ID=34521032010 The Better Business Bureau] said Human Rights Watch meets its standards for charity accountability.

Human Rights Watch published the following program and support services spending details for the financial year ending June 2011.
{|
|-  style="text-align:center; background:#f0f0f0;"
||'''Program services'''
||'''2011 expenses (USD)'''&lt;ref name="Financial Statements, Year Ended June 30, 2011"/&gt;
|-
| [[Africa]]||$5,859,910
|-
| [[Americas]]||$1,331,448
|-
| [[Asia]]||$4,629,535
|-
| [[Europe]] and [[Central Asia]]||$4,123,959
|-
| [[Middle East]] and [[North Africa]]||$3,104,643
|-
| [[United States]]||$1,105,571
|-
| [[Children's Rights]]||$1,551,463
|-
| Health &amp; Human Rights||$1,962,015
|-
| [[International Justice]]||$1,325,749
|-
| [[Woman's Rights]]||$2,083,890
|-
| Other programs||$11,384,854
|-
|  style="text-align:center; background:#f0f0f0;"|'''Supporting services'''
|-
| Management and general||$3,130,051
|-
| Fundraising||$9,045,910
|-
|
|}

Human Rights Watch published the following program and support services spending details for the financial year ending June 2008.
{|
|-  style="text-align:center; background:#f0f0f0;"
||'''Program services'''
||'''2008 expenses (USD)'''&lt;ref name="FS-2008"/&gt;
|-
| [[Africa]]||$5,532,631
|-
| [[Americas]]||$1,479,265
|-
| [[Asia]]||$3,212,850
|-
| [[Europe]] and [[Central Asia]]||$4,001,853
|-
| [[Middle East]] and [[North Africa]]||$2,258,459
|-
| [[United States]]||$1,195,673
|-
| [[Children's Rights]]||$1,642,064
|-
| [[International Justice]]||$1,385,121
|-
| [[Woman's Rights]]||$1,854,228
|-
| Other programs||$9,252,974
|-
|  style="text-align:center; background:#f0f0f0;"|'''Supporting services'''
|-
| Management and general||$1,984,626
|-
| Fundraising||$8,641,358
|-
|
|}

==Notable staff==
[[File:Kenneth Roth (Human Rights Watch) (6806930135).jpg|thumb|210px|[[Kenneth Roth]] and the Prime Minister of the Netherlands, [[Mark Rutte]], 2 February 2012]]
Some notable current and former staff members of Human Rights Watch have included:&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.hrw.org/en/node/75139 Human Rights Watch: Our People] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090917042132/https://www.hrw.org/en/node/75139 |date=September 17, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!---note that subsection reword means former notables can be listed---&gt;
*[[Robert L. Bernstein]], Founding Chair Emeritus
*[[Kenneth Roth]], Executive Director
*[[Jan Egeland]], Deputy Director and the Director of Human Rights Watch Europe
*[[John Studzinski]], Vice Chair;&lt;ref name=hrw&gt;[https://www.hrw.org/bios/john-j-studzinski John J. Studzinski]. Human Rights Watch.&lt;/ref&gt; developed European arm;&lt;ref&gt;Wachman, Richard. [http://www.theguardian.com/business/2006/oct/08/theobserver.observerbusiness11 "Cracking the Studzinski code"]. ''[[The Observer]]''. October 7, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=influential&gt;[http://www.telegraph.co.uk/finance/2954886/Most-influential-Americans-in-the-UK-20-to-11.html "Most influential Americans in the UK: 20 to 11"]. ''[[Daily Telegraph|The Telegraph]]''. November 22, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; former Director; member of Executive Committee; Chairman of Investment Committee&lt;ref name=tate2007&gt;[http://www.tate.org.uk/about/press-office/press-releases/donation-provides-cornerstone-new-transforming-tate-modern "Donation provides cornerstone for new Transforming Tate Modern development"]. [[Tate Modern]]. May 22, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=debretts&gt;[http://www.debretts.com/people-of-today/profile/26188/John-STUDZINSKI John Studzinski]. ''[[Debrett's]]''.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=ippr&gt;[http://www.ippr.org/people/policy-advisory-council/john-studzinski John Studzinski]. [[Institute for Public Policy Research]].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bowdoin.edu/news/archives/1bowdoincampus/004862.shtml "Royal Honor for John Studzinski '78, Architectural Accolades for Namesake"]. [[Bowdoin College]] Campus News. ''Bowdoin.edu''. February 26, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Human Rights Watch. [https://books.google.com/books?id=oFmIOWMjYhsC&amp;pg=PA558 ''Human Rights Watch World Report, 2003'']. Human Rights Watch, 2003. p. 558.&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Minky Worden]], Media Director
*[[Jamie Fellner]], Senior Counsel for the United States Program of Human Rights Watch
*[[Brad Adams]], Asia Director
*[[Scott Long]], Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, and Transgender Rights Director
*[[Sarah Leah Whitson]], Middle East and North Africa Director
*[[Joe Stork]]
*[[Marc Garlasco]], former staff member, resigned due to a scandal involving his Nazi memorabilia collection&lt;ref name="The Guardian"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2009/sep/15/human-rights-watch-nazi-israel|title=Human Rights Watch investigator suspended over Nazi memorabilia|last=Pilkington|first=Ed|date=2009-09-15|publisher=The Guardian|accessdate=2010-02-15}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Sharon Hom]]
* [[Baik Tae-Ung|Tae-Ung Baik]], former research consultant
*[[Nabeel Rajab]], member of the Advisory Committee of Human Rights Watch's Middle East Division

== Publications ==
Human Rights Watch publishes reports on many different topics&lt;ref name="HRW-pub"&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.hrw.org/en/publications|title=Publications|publisher=Human Rights Watch|accessdate=2009-07-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; and compiles an annual ''World Report'' presenting an overview of the worldwide state of human rights.&lt;ref name="HRW-WR"&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.hrw.org/en/node/79288|title=Previous World Reports|publisher=Human Rights Watch|accessdate=2009-07-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; It has been published by [[Seven Stories Press]] since 2006; the current edition, ''World Report 2015,'' was released in February 2015, and covers events of 2014.&lt;ref&gt;[http://catalog.sevenstories.com/products/world-report-2013-events-of-2012 World Report 2013], Seven Stories Press.&lt;/ref&gt; Human Rights Watch has reported extensively on subjects such as the [[Rwandan Genocide]] of 1994,&lt;ref&gt;[https://hrw.org/doc?t=africa&amp;c=rwanda Rwandan genocide report],''Human Rights Watch''&lt;/ref&gt; [[Democratic Republic of the Congo]]&lt;ref&gt;[https://hrw.org/doc?t=africa&amp;c=congo Congo report],''Human Rights Watch''&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Sex offender registries in the United States|US sex offender registries]] due to their over-breadth and application to juveniles.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=No Easy Answers: Sex Offender Laws in the US|url=https://www.hrw.org/reports/2007/09/11/no-easy-answers-0|publisher=Human Rights Watch|date=12 September 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Raised on the Registry: The Irreparable Harm of Placing Children on Sex Offender Registries in the US|url=https://www.hrw.org/reports/2013/05/01/raised-registry|publisher=Human Rights Watch|date=1 May 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the summer of 2004, the Rare Book and Manuscript Library at Columbia University in New York became the depository institution for the Human Rights Watch Archive, an active collection that documents decades of human rights investigations around the world. The archive was transferred from its previous location at the Norlin Library at the University of Colorado, Boulder. The archive includes administrative files, public relations documents, as well as case and country files. With some exceptions for security considerations, the Columbia University community and the public have access to field notes, taped and transcribed interviews with alleged victims of human rights violations, video and audio tapes, and other materials documenting the organization’s activities since its founding in 1978 as Helsinki Watch.&lt;ref&gt;[http://lj.libraryjournal.com/2004/03/ljarchives/human-rights-watch-archive-moves-to-columbia-university/ ''Library Journal'', March 11, 2004]&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
{{Portal|Human rights}}
*[[American Freedom Campaign]]
*[[Avocats Sans Frontières]]
*[[Freedom House]]
*[[Helsinki Committee for Human Rights]]
*[[Human Rights First]]
*[[International Freedom of Expression Exchange]]
*[[Shia Rights Watch]]
*[[US Human Rights Network]]

== References ==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

== External links ==
{{Commons category|Human Rights Watch}}
* [https://www.hrw.org/ Human Rights Watch] (official website)

{{International human rights organizations}}
{{Authority control}}
[[Category:Civil rights organizations]]
[[Category:Human Rights Watch| ]]
[[Category:Non-governmental organizations]]
[[Category:Organizations established in 1978]]
[[Category:Human rights organizations]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>