<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20131120173558|582550807" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="3634424" pageid="3634424" ns="0" title="Violence against women"><revisions><rev timestamp="2013-11-20T17:47:31Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2012}}
{{pp-semi-sock|small=yes}}
{{Violence against women}}
The phrase '''violence against women''' is a [[Technical terminology|technical term]] used to collectively refer to violent acts that are primarily or exclusively committed against [[woman|women]].  Similar to a [[hate crime]], which it is sometimes considered,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=2YdCbgXjr-EC&amp;pg=PA405 |chapter=Hate Crime Statutes: A Promising Tool for Fighting Violence Against Women |first=Marguerite |last=Angelari |title=Pornography, sex work, and hate speech |editor=Karen J. Maschke |publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis |year=1997}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=DiBIZcx1nPcC&amp;pg=PA58 |title=Hate Crimes: Causes, Controls, and Controversies |first=Phyllis B. |last=Gerstenfeld |year=2013 |publisher=Sage}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=2ZNnXj_SbOsC&amp;pg=PA271 |title=Hate and bias crime: a reader |editor=Barbara Perry |year=2003 |publisher=Psychology Press |first=Beverly |last=McPhail |chapter=Gender-Bias Hate Crimes: A Review}}&lt;/ref&gt; this type of violence targets a specific group with the victim's [[gender]] as a primary motive.

The [[United Nations General Assembly]] defines "violence against women" as ''"any act of gender-based violence that results in, or is likely to result in, [[physical abuse|physical]], [[sexual abuse|sexual]] or [[emotional abuse|mental]] harm or suffering to women, including threats of such acts, coercion or arbitrary deprivation of [[liberty]], whether occurring in public or in private life."'' The 1993 [[Declaration on the Elimination of Violence Against Women]] noted that this violence could be perpetrated by assailants of either gender, family members and even the "State" itself.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unhchr.ch/huridocda/huridoca.nsf/(Symbol)/A.RES.48.104.En?Opendocument United Nations General Assembly ''Declaration on the Elimination of Violence against Women'' (1993)]&lt;/ref&gt;

Worldwide governments and organizations actively work to combat violence against women through a variety of programs. A [[UN resolution]] designated 25 November as ''[[International Day for the Elimination of Violence against Women]]''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.un.org/womenwatch/daw/news/vawd.html UN Resolution 54/134-'&amp;#39;International Day for the Elimination of Violence against Women'&amp;#39;]. Un.org.&lt;/ref&gt;

==History of violence against women==
[[File:Map3.1NEW Womens Physical Security 2011 compressed.jpg|right|thumb| 400px| A world map showing countries by women's physical security, 2011.]]
Some historians believe that the history of violence against women is tied to the history of women being viewed as property and a gender role assigned to be subservient to men and also other women.&lt;ref&gt;Penelope Harvey &amp; Peter Gow ''Sex and violence : issues in representation and experience'' (1994)  pg 36 Routledge ISBN 0-415-05734-5&lt;/ref&gt;

The UN Declaration on the Elimination of Violence against Women (1993) states that "violence against women is a manifestation of historically unequal power relations between men and women, which have led to domination over and discrimination against women by men and to the prevention of the full advancement of women, and that violence against women is one of the crucial social mechanisms by which women are forced into a subordinate position compared with men.”&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.un.org/documents/ga/res/48/a48r104.htm A/RES/48/104. Declaration on the Elimination of Violence against Women]. United Nations.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unfpa.org/rights/violence.htm Addressing Gender-Based Violence: Advancing Human Rights]. UNFPA.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 1870s courts in the United States stopped recognizing the common-law principle that a husband had the right to "physically chastise an errant wife".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Calvert R |year=1974 |chapter=Criminal and civil liability in husband-wife assaults |title=Violence in the family |pages=88–91 |editor=Steinmetz S, Straus M |publisher=Harper &amp; Row |location=New York}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the UK the traditional right of a husband to inflict moderate [[corporal punishment]] on his wife in order to keep her "within the bounds of duty" was removed in 1891.&lt;ref&gt;R. v. Jackson [1891]. 1 Q.B. 671&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Encyclopædia Britannica Eleventh Edition]], 1911. Article ''Corporal punishment''&lt;/ref&gt;

==Impact on society==
The [[World Health Organization]] reports that violence against women puts an undue burden on health care services with women who have suffered violence being more likely to need health services and at higher cost, compared to women who have not suffered violence.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.who.int/mediacentre/factsheets/fs239/en/index.html WHO Factsheet '&amp;#39;Violence against women'&amp;#39;]. World Health Organization (1 September 2011).&lt;/ref&gt;
Several studies have shown a link between poor treatment of women and international violence.  These studies show that one of the best predictors of inter- and intranational violence is the maltreatment of women in the society.&lt;ref&gt;Maffly, Brian (21 March 2009). [http://www.sltrib.com/ci_11967564 "BYU study links women's safety, nation's peace"]. ''The Salt Lake Tribune''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.womanstats.org/images/StearmerEmmettAPSA07.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

==Types of violence==

===Rape===
{{main|Rape}}
Rape is a type of [[sexual assault]] usually involving [[sexual intercourse]], which is initiated by one or more persons against another person without that person's [[consent]]. The act may be carried out by physical force, [[coercion]], abuse of authority or with a person who is incapable of valid consent, such as one who is unconscious, incapacitated, or below the legal [[age of consent]].&lt;ref name="merriam-webster.com"&gt;{{cite web|title=Rape|publisher=''[[Merriam-Webster]]''|date=April 15, 2011|url=http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/rape%5B3%5D}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="who.int"&gt;{{cite web|title=Sexual violence chapter 6|publisher=''[[World Health Organization]]''|date=April 15, 2011|url=http://whqlibdoc.who.int/publications/2002/9241545615_chap6_eng.pdf
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="dictionary.reference.com"&gt;{{cite web|title=Rape|publisher=dictionary.reference.com|date=April 15, 2011|url=http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/rape}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="thefreedictionary.com"&gt;{{cite web|title=Rape|publisher=legal-dictionary.thefreedictionary.com|date=April 15, 2011|url=http://legal-dictionary.thefreedictionary.com/rape}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Internationally, the incidence of rapes recorded by the police during 2008 varied between 0.1 in [[Egypt]] per 100,000 people and 91.6 per 100,000 people in [[Lesotho]] with 4.9 per 100,000 people in [[Lithuania]] as the [[median]].&lt;ref name="unodc1"&gt;[http://www.unodc.org/documents/data-and-analysis/Crime-statistics/Sexual_violence_sv_against_children_and_rape.xls "Rape at the National Level, number of police recorded offenses".] [[United Nations]].&lt;/ref&gt; According to the [[American Medical Association]] (1995), sexual violence, and rape in particular, is considered the most underreported violent crime.&lt;ref&gt;American Medical Association (1995) Sexual Assault in America. AMA.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="rds.homeoffice.gov.uk"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://rds.homeoffice.gov.uk/rds/pdfs05/hors293.pdf |title=A gap or a chasm? Attrition in reported rape cases|format=PDF |accessdate=2010-12-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; The rate of reporting, prosecution and convictions for rape varies considerably in different jurisdictions. Rape by strangers is usually less common than rape by persons the victim knows.&lt;ref name="Abbey"&gt;Abbey, A., BeShears, R., Clinton-Sherrod, A. M., &amp; McAuslan, P. (2004). Psychology of Women Quarterly, 28, 323–332.[http://www.hawaii.edu/hivandaids/Similarities_And_Differences_In_Women_s_Sexual_Assault_Experiences_Based_On_Tactics.pdf "Similarities and differences in women's sexual assault experiences based on tactics used by the perpetrator"]. Retrieved 10 December 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=rainn&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rainn.org/statistics/|title=Statistics &amp;#124; Rape, Abuse &amp; Incest National Network|publisher=www.rainn.org|accessdate=2008-01-01}}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="ncjrs.gov"&gt;Alberto R. Gonzales et al. [http://www.ncjrs.gov/pdffiles1/nij/210346.pdf Extent, Nature, and Consequences of Rape Victimization: Findings From the National Violence Against Women Survey]. U.S. Department of Justice Office of Justice Programs. January 2006&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Australia"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.abs.gov.au/ausstats/abs@.nsf/mf/4523.0 |title=Sexual Assault in Australia: A Statistical Overview, 2004|publisher=Abs.gov.au |date=2006-12-08 |accessdate=2010-12-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="UK"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://rds.homeoffice.gov.uk/rds/pdfs2/r159.pdf |title=Rape and sexual assault of women: findings from the British Crime Survey |format=PDF |accessdate=2010-12-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Victims of rape can be severely [[Psychological trauma|traumatized]] and may suffer from [[posttraumatic stress disorder]];&lt;ref name="aaets"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aaets.org/article178.htm |title=Post Traumatic Stress Disorder in Rape Survivors |publisher=The American Academy of Experts in Traumatic Stress |year=1995 |accessdate=2013-04-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; in addition to psychological harm resulting from the act, rape may cause physical injury, or have additional effects on the victim, such as acquiring of a [[sexually transmitted infection]] or becoming [[pregnant]]. 

====Violence against victims of rape====
Following a rape, a victim may face violence or threats of thereof from the rapist, and, in some cultures, from the victim's own family and relatives. Violence or intimidation of the victim may be perpetrated by the rapist or by friends and relatives of the rapist, as a way of preventing the victims from reporting the rape, of punishing them for reporting it, or of forcing them to withdraw the complaint; or it may be perpetrated by the relatives of the victim as a punishment for "bringing shame" to the family. This is especially the case in cultures where female [[virginity]] is highly valued and considered mandatory before marriage; in extreme cases, rape victims are killed in [[honor killings]]. Victims may also be forced by their families to marry the rapist in order to restore the family's "honor". &lt;ref name="zeenews.india"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://zeenews.india.com/news/uttar-pradesh/rape-victim-threatened-to-withdraw-case-in-up_694364.html |title=Rape victim threatened to withdraw case in UP |publisher=Zeenews.india.com |date=2011-03-19 |accessdate=2013-02-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="wisemuslimwomen"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wisemuslimwomen.org/currentissues/stigmitizationofrape/ |title=Stigmatization of Rape &amp; Honor Killings |publisher=WISE Muslim Women |date=2002-01-31 |accessdate=2013-02-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="bbc"&gt;{{cite web|last=Harter |first=Pascale |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-africa-13760895 |title=BBC News - Libya rape victims 'face honour killings' |publisher=BBC News |date=2011-06-14 |accessdate=2013-02-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-africa-17379721&lt;/ref&gt;

===Domestic violence===
{{main|Domestic violence}}
[[File:Girl in Ethiopia (5762561619).jpg|thumb|Girl in [[Ethiopia]]. An analysis by the UN of several international studies found domestic violence against women to be most prevalent in Ethiopia&lt;ref&gt;http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/6040180.stm&lt;/ref&gt;]]
Women are more likely to be [[victimized]] by someone that they are intimate with, commonly called "Intimate Partner Violence" or (IPV). Instances of IPV tend not to be reported to police and thus many experts believe that the true magnitude of the problem is hard to estimate.&lt;ref name="CDC"&gt;{{cite web
| year = 2006
| title = Intimate Partner Violence: Overview
| publisher = Centers for Disease Control and Prevention
| accessdate = 2007-09-04
| url = http://www.cdc.gov/ncipc/factsheets/ipvfacts.htm
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Women are much more likely than men to be [[murdered]] by an intimate partner. In the United States, in 2005, 1181 women, in comparison with 329 men, were killed by their intimate partners.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cdc.gov/violencePrevention/intimatepartnerviolence/consequences.html CDC – Consequences – Intimate Partner Violence – Violence Prevention – Injury]. Cdc.gov.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.theduluthmodel.org/wheelgallery.php&lt;/ref&gt;  In [[England and Wales]] about 100 women are killed by partners or former partners each year while 21 men were killed in 2010.&lt;ref name=BBC&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-13058300 |title=All domestic abuse deaths to have multi-agency review |date=13 April 2011 |publisher=BBC |accessdate=14 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2008, in [[France]], 156 women in comparison with 27 men were killed by their intimate partner.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.interieur.gouv.fr/sections/a_votre_service/aide_aux_victimes/violence-couple/downloadFile/attachedFile/morts_violentes_au_sein_couples.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

According to WHO, globally, as many as 38% of murders of women are committed by an intimate partner.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.who.int/mediacentre/factsheets/fs239/en/&lt;/ref&gt; A UN report compiled from a number of different studies conducted in at least 71 countries found domestic violence against women to be most prevalent in [[Ethiopia]].&lt;ref&gt;http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/6040180.stm&lt;/ref&gt;

In Western Europe, a country which has received major international criticism for the way it has dealt legally with the issue of violence against women is [[Finland]]; with authors pointing that a high level of equality for women in the public sphere (as in Finland) should never be equated with equality in all other aspects of women's lives.&lt;ref name="academia.edu"&gt;http://www.academia.edu/992154/The_Paradoxical_Approach_to_Intimate_Partner_Violence_in_Finland&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="scottishaffairs.org"&gt;http://www.scottishaffairs.org/backiss/pdfs/sa48/sa48_McKie_and_Hearn.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt;According to a report by Amnesty International: "Finland is repeatedly reminded of its widespread problem of violence against women and recommended to take more efficient measures to deal with the situation. International criticism concentrates on the lack of measures to combat violence against women in general and
in particular on the lack of a national action plan to combat such violence and on the lack of legislation on domestic violence. (...) Compared to Sweden, Finland has been slower to reform legislation on violence against
women. In Sweden, domestic violence was already illegal in 1864, while in Finland such
violence was not outlawed until 1970, over a hundred years later. In Sweden the punishment of victims of incest was abolished in 1937, but not until 1971 in Finland. Rape within marriage was criminalised in Sweden in 1962, but the equivalent Finnish legislation only came into force in 1994 – making Finland one of the last European countries to criminalise marital rape. In addition, assaults taking place on private property did not become impeachable offences in Finland until 1995. Only in 1997 did victims of sexual offences and domestic violence in Finland become entitled to government-funded counselling and support services for the duration of their court cases." (pg 89 - 91)-  ''Case Closed - Rape and human rights in the Nordic countries'' [http://www.amnesty.dk/sites/default/files/mediafiles/44/case-closed.pdf]&lt;/ref&gt;

A study by [[Pan American Health Organization]] conducted in 12 [[Latin American]] countries found the highest prevalence of domestic violence against women to be in [[Bolivia]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www2.paho.org/hq/dmdocuments/violence-against-women-lac.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

Though this form of violence is often portrayed as an issue within the context of heterosexual relationships, it also occurs in lesbian relationships,&lt;ref name="Girshick"&gt;Girshick, Lori B., "No Sugar, No Spice: Reflections on Research on Woman-to-Woman Sexual Violence." ''Violence Against Women'' Vol. 8 No. 12, December 2002, pgs. 1500–1520.&lt;/ref&gt; daughter-mother relationships, [[roommate]] relationships and other domestic relationships involving two women. Violence against women in lesbian relationships is about as common as violence against women in heterosexual relationships.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.musc.edu/vawprevention/lesbianrx/factsheet.shtml Fact Sheet: Lesbian Partner Violence]. Musc.edu.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Diagnosis planning====
The [[American Psychiatric Association]] planning and research committees for the forthcoming [[DSM-5]] (2013) have canvassed a series of new [[Relational disorder]]s which include ''Marital Conflict Disorder Without Violence'' or ''Marital Abuse Disorder (Marital Conflict Disorder With Violence)''.&lt;ref&gt;First, M.B., Bell, C.C., Cuthbert, B., Krystal, J.H., Malison, R., Offord, D.R., Riess, D., Shea, T., Widiger, T., Wisner, K.L., Personality Disorders and Relational Disorders, pp.164,166 Chapter 4 of Kupfer, D.J., First, M.B., &amp; Regier, D.A. [http://appi.org/book.cfm?id=2292 A Research Agenda For DSM-V]. Published by American Psychiatric Association (2002)&lt;/ref&gt; Couples with marital disorders sometimes come to clinical attention because the couple recognize long-standing dissatisfaction with their marriage and come to the [[clinician]] on their own initiative or are referred by an astute health care professional. Secondly, there is serious violence in the marriage which is -"usually the husband battering the wife".&lt;ref&gt;First, M.B., Bell, C.C., Cuthbert, B., Krystal, J.H., Malison, R., Offord, D.R., Riess, D., Shea, T., Widiger, T., Wisner, K.L., Personality Disorders and Relational Disorders, p.163, Chapter 4 of Kupfer, D.J., First, M.B., &amp; Regier, D.A.  [http://appi.org/book.cfm?id=2292 A Research Agenda For DSM-V]. Published by American Psychiatric Association (2002)&lt;/ref&gt; In these cases the emergency room or a legal authority often is the first to notify the [[clinician]]. Most importantly, marital violence "is a major risk factor for serious injury and even death and women in violent marriages are at much greater risk of being seriously injured or killed ([[National Advisory Council on Violence Against Women]] 2000)."&lt;ref name=autogenerated2&gt;First, M.B., Bell, C.C., Cuthbert, B., Krystal, J.H., Malison, R., Offord, D.R., Riess, D., Shea, T., Widiger, T., Wisner, K.L., Personality Disorders and Relational Disorders, p.166, Chapter 4 of Kupfer, D.J., First, M.B., &amp; Regier, D.A. [http://appi.org/book.cfm?id=2292 A Research Agenda For DSM-V]. Published by American Psychiatric Association (2002)&lt;/ref&gt; The authors of this study add that "There is current considerable controversy over whether male-to-female marital violence is best regarded as a reflection of male [[psychopathology]] and control or whether there is an empirical base and clinical utility for conceptualizing these patterns as relational."&lt;ref name=autogenerated2 /&gt;

Recommendations for clinicians making a diagnosis of ''Marital Relational Disorder'' should include the assessment of actual or "potential" male violence as regularly as they assess the potential for suicide in depressed patients. Further, "clinicians should not relax their vigilance after a battered wife leaves her husband, because some data suggest that the period immediately following a marital separation is the period of greatest risk for the women. Many men will [[stalking|stalk]] and [[battery (crime)|batter]] their wives in an effort to get them to return or punish them for leaving. Initial assessments of the potential for violence in a marriage can be supplemented by standardized interviews and questionnaires, which have been reliable and valid aids in exploring marital violence more systematically."&lt;ref name=autogenerated2 /&gt;
 
The authors conclude with what they call "very recent information"&lt;ref name=autogenerated1&gt;First, M.B., Bell, C.C., Cuthbert, B., Krystal, J.H., Malison, R., Offord, D.R., Riess, D., Shea, T., Widiger, T., Wisner, K.L., Personality Disorders and Relational Disorders, p.167,168 Chapter 4 of Kupfer, D.J., First, M.B., &amp; Regier, D.A. [http://appi.org/book.cfm?id=2292 A Research Agenda For DSM-V]. Published by American Psychiatric Association (2002)&lt;/ref&gt; on the course of violent marriages which suggests that "over time a husband's battering may abate somewhat, but perhaps because he has successfully [[intimidate]]d his wife. The risk of violence remains strong in a marriage in which it has been a feature in the past. Thus, treatment is essential here; the clinician cannot just wait and watch."&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt; The most urgent clinical priority is the protection of the wife because she is the one most frequently at risk, and clinicians must be aware that supporting assertiveness by a battered wife may lead to more beatings or even death.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt;

====Honor killings====
[[Honor killings]] are a common form of violence against women in certain parts of the world. In honor killings, women and girls are killed by family members (usually husbands, fathers, uncles or brothers) because the women are believed to have brought shame or dishonor upon the family. These killings are a traditional practice, believed to have originated from tribal customs where an allegation against a woman can be enough to defile a family's reputation.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.bbc.co.uk/ethics/honourcrimes/crimesofhonour_1.shtml&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/honor%20killing&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/honor+killing?s=t&lt;/ref&gt; Women are killed for reasons such as refusing to enter an [[arranged marriage]], being in a relationship that is disapproved by their relatives, attempting to leave a marriage, having sex outside marriage, becoming the victim of rape, dressing in ways which are deemed inappropriate.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.bbc.co.uk/ethics/honourcrimes/crimesofhonour_1.shtml#h1&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-africa-13760895&lt;/ref&gt;

Honor killings are common in countries such as Afghanistan, Egypt, Iraq, Jordan, Lebanon,  Libya, Morocco, Pakistan, Saudi Arabia, Syria, Turkey, Yemen.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.unhchr.ch/huridocda/huridoca.nsf/AllSymbols/985168F508EE799FC1256C52002AE5A9/$File/N0246790.pdf &lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.khaama.com/240-cases-of-honor-killing-recorded-in-afghanistan-aihrc-2177&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://latinbusinesstoday.com/2013/06/aihrc-400-rape-honor-killings-registered-in-afghanistan-in-2-years/&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-africa-13760895&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.reuters.com/article/2012/03/06/us-iraq-women-idUSTRE82510920120306&lt;/ref&gt; Honor killings also occur in immigrant communities in Europe, the United States and Canada. Although honor killings are most often associated with the Middle East and South Asia, they occur in other parts of the world too.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.bbc.co.uk/ethics/honourcrimes/crimesofhonour_1.shtml#h3&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.sanctuaryforfamilies.org/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=252&amp;Itemid=259&lt;/ref&gt; In India, honor killings occur in the northern regions of the country, especially in the states of Punjab, Haryana, Bihar, Uttar Pradesh, Rajasthan, Jharkhand, Himachal Pradesh and Madhya Pradesh.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.bbc.co.uk/worldservice/specials/1817_wawryw/page4.shtml&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/10364986&lt;/ref&gt; In Turkey, honor killings are a serious problem in Southeastern Anatolia.&lt;ref&gt;http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/4357158.stm&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.unfpa.org/upload/lib_pub_file/676_filename_honourkillings.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

====Dowry violence====
[[Image:Say no to dowry.jpg|thumb|Anti-dowry poster in [[Bangalore, India]]]]

The custom of [[dowry]], which is common in South Asia, especially in India, is the trigger of many forms of violence against women. [[Bride burning]] is a form of violence against women in which a bride is killed at home by her husband or husband's family due to his dissatisfaction over the dowry provided by her family. [[Dowry death]] refers to the phenomenon of women and girls being killed or committing [[suicide]] due to disputes regarding dowry. Dowry violence is common in India, Pakistan, Bangladesh and Nepal. In India, in 2011 alone, the National Crime Records Bureau reported 8,618 dowry deaths, while unofficial figures suggest the numbers to be at least three times higher.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.unwomen.org/en/news/stories/2012/12/confronting-dowry-related-violence-in-india-women-at-the-center-of-justice/&lt;/ref&gt;

====Female genital mutilation====
[[Female genital mutilation]] (FGM) is defined by the [[World Health Organization]] (WHO) as "all procedures that involve partial or total removal of the external female genitalia, or other injury to the female genital organs for non-medical reasons."&lt;ref&gt;http://www.who.int/mediacentre/factsheets/fs241/en/&lt;/ref&gt; According to a 2013 UNICEF report, 125 million women and girls in Africa and the Middle East have experienced FGM.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.unicef.org/media/files/FGCM_Lo_res.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; The WHO states that: "''The procedure has no health benefits for girls and women''" and "''Procedures can cause severe bleeding and problems urinating, and later cysts, infections, infertility as well as complications in childbirth increased risk of newborn deaths''" and "''FGM is recognized internationally as a violation of the human rights of girls and women. It reflects deep-rooted inequality between the sexes, and constitutes an extreme form of discrimination against women''".&lt;ref&gt;http://www.who.int/mediacentre/factsheets/fs241/en/&lt;/ref&gt; According to a UNICEF report, the top rates for FGM are in Somalia (with 98 percent of women affected), Guinea (96 percent), Djibouti (93 percent), Egypt (91 percent), Eritrea (89 percent), Mali (89 percent), Sierra Leone (88 percent), Sudan (88 percent), Gambia (76 percent), Burkina Faso (76 percent), Ethiopia (74 percent), Mauritania (69 percent), Liberia (66 percent), and Guinea-Bissau (50 percent).&lt;ref&gt;http://www.unicef.org/media/files/FGCM_Lo_res.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

====Acid throwing====
[[File:Acid attack victim.jpg|Acid attack victim in [[Cambodia]]|thumb|250px]]
[[Acid throwing]], also called acid attack, or vitriolage, is defined as the act of throwing acid onto the body of a person "with the intention of injuring or disfiguring [them] out of jealousy or revenge".&lt;ref name=Vij&gt;{{Cite book | author=Vij, Krishan | title=''Textbook of Forensic Medicine and Toxicology : Principles and Practice'', 5th Edition | year=2003 | page=462 |publisher=Elsevier India | isbn=978-81-312-2684-1 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The most common types of acid used in these attacks are sulfuric, nitric, or hydrochloric acid.&lt;ref&gt;http://cgi.unc.edu/uploads/media_items/it-was-like-burning-in-hell-a-comparative-exploration-of-acid-attack-violence.original.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; Perpetrators of these attacks throw [[acid]] at their victims, usually at their faces, burning them, and damaging [[skin]] tissue, often exposing and sometimes dissolving the bones.&lt;ref name=Swanson&gt;{{Cite news
 | last = Swanson
 | first = Jordan
 | date = Spring 2002
 | title = Acid attacks: Bangladesh’s efforts to stop the violence.
 | periodical = Harvard Health Policy Review
 | page = 3
 | number = 1
 | volume = 3
 | url = http://www.hcs.harvard.edu/~epihc/currentissue/spring2002/swanson.php
 | accessdate =2008-06-18
 | postscript = &lt;!--None--&gt;
}}&lt;/ref&gt; The long term consequences of these attacks include [[blindness]] and permanent [[scarring]] of the face and body.&lt;ref&gt;http://web.archive.org/web/20070922210725/http://archives.cnn.com/2000/ASIANOW/south/11/11/bangladesh.acid.ap/index.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Bahl_Syed&gt;{{Cite book | author=Bahl, Taru &amp; M.H. Syed | title=Encyclopaedia of the Muslim World | year=2004 | publisher=Anmol Publications PVT. LTD | isbn=978-81-261-1419-1 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Women and girls are the victims in 75-80% of cases.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/magazine-23631395&lt;/ref&gt; Acid attacks are often connected to domestic disputes, including dowry disputes, and refusal of a proposition for marriage, or of sexual advances. Such attacks are common in South Asia, in countries such as Bangladesh, Pakistan, India; and in Southeast Asia, especially in Cambodia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.newstatesman.com/world-affairs/2012/11/acid-attacks-pakistan-sorry-litany-male-egotism |title=Acid attacks in Pakistan: A sorry litany of male egotism |publisher=Newstatesman.com |date= |accessdate=2013-09-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author= |url=http://www.huffingtonpost.ca/2012/08/28/nikolas-stefanatos-quebec-acid-attack_n_1838232.html |title=Longueuil Woman Burned And In Coma After Acid Attack |publisher=Huffingtonpost.ca |date= |accessdate=2013-09-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2012/11/28/nurbanu-acid-attack_n_2206621.html |title=Nurbanu, Bangladeshi Woman, Forced To Return To Husband After Acid Attack (WARNING: DISTURBING IMAGES) |publisher=Huffingtonpost.com |date= |accessdate=2013-09-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Scholte&gt;{{cite news | last =Scholte| first =Marianne| title =Acid Attacks in Bangladesh: A Voice for the Victims| publisher = [[Spiegel Online]]| date = 2006-03-17| url =http://www.spiegel.de/international/0,1518,406485,00.html| accessdate =2008-03-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www2.ohchr.org/english/bodies/cedaw/docs/cedaw_crc_contributions/AvonGlobalCenterforWomenandJustice.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.cambodianacidsurvivorscharity.org/docs/breaking_the_silence.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

====Forced marriage====
A [[forced marriage]] is a marriage in which one or both of the parties is married against their will. Forced marriages are common in South Asia, the Middle East and Africa. The customs of [[bride price]] and [[dowry]], that exist in many parts of the world, contribute to this practice. A forced marriage is also often the result of a dispute between families, where the dispute is 'resolved' by giving a female from one family to the ofter. &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/ethics/slavery/modern/modern_1.shtml#section_2 Ethics – Slavery: Modern slavery]. BBC. Retrieved on 5 September 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ohchr.org/Documents/HRBodies/HRCouncil/RegularSession/Session21/A-HRC-21-41_en.pdf Report of the Special Rapporteur on contemporary forms of slavery, including its causes and consequences, Gulnara Shahinian]. United Nations. Human Rights Council Twenty-first session. 10 July 2012&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt;http://www.undp.org.fj/pdf/unp/evaw.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

The custom of [[bride kidnapping]] continues to exist in some societies, such as Central Asia and the Caucasus, or parts of Africa, especially Ethiopia. A girl or a woman is abducted by the would be groom, who is often helped by his friends. The victim is often raped by the would be groom, after which he may try to negotiate a bride price with the village elders to legitimize the marriage.&lt;ref&gt;http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/371944.stm&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.irinnews.org/report/69993/ethiopia-surviving-forced-marriage&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.pathfinder.org/publications-tools/pdfs/Causes-and-Consequesnces-of-Early-Marriage-in-the-Amhara-Region-of-Ethiopia.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

===Mob violence===
In 2010 [[Amnesty International]] reported that [[Hassi Messaoud mob attacks against women|mob attacks]] against single women were taking place in [[Hassi Messaoud]], Algeria.&lt;ref name=Amnesty&gt;{{cite web|title=Algerian authorities must investigate and stop attacks against women|url=http://www.amnesty.org.au/news/comments/22931/|publisher=Amnesty International|accessdate=13 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to Amnesty International,  "some women have been sexually abused" and were targeted "not just because they are women, but because they are living alone and are economically independent."&lt;ref name=Amnesty/&gt;

===State violence===

====War rape and sexual slavery during military conflict====
[[File:Paul Jamin - Le Brenn et sa part de butin 1893.jpg|thumb|200 px|''"[[Brennus (4th century BC)|Brennus]] and His Share of the Spoils"'', by [[Paul Jamin]], 1893.]]
[[File:Chinese girl from one of the Japanese Army's 'comfort battalions'.jpg|thumb|200 px|[[Rangoon]], [[Myanmar|Burma]]. August 8, 1945. A young [[Chinese diaspora|ethnic Chinese]] woman who was in one of the [[Imperial Japanese Army]]'s "comfort battalions"  is interviewed by an [[Allies of World War II|Allied]] officer.]]

Militarism produces special environments that allow for increased violence against women. [[War rapes]] have accompanied warfare in virtually every known historical era.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last= Levinson |first=Bernard M |title= Gender and Law in the Hebrew Bible and the Ancient Near East |url=http://books.google.com/?id=2rZnXQwPX8gC&amp;dq=rape+in+warfare+ancient |page= 203 |year=2004 |isbn= 978-0-567-08098-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Rape in the course of war is mentioned multiple times in the Bible: "For I will gather all the nations against Jerusalem to battle, and the city shall be taken and the houses plundered and the women raped..." {{bibleref|Zechariah|14:2|ESV}} "Their little children will be dashed to death before their eyes. Their homes will be sacked, and their wives will be raped."{{bibleref|Isaiah|13:16|NLT}}

War rapes are rapes committed by soldiers, other combatants or civilians during armed conflict or war, or during military occupation, distinguished from sexual assaults and rape committed amongst troops in military service. It also covers the situation where women are forced into prostitution or [[sexual slavery]] by an occupying power. During World War II the Japanese military established brothels filled with "[[comfort women]]", girls and women who were forced into sexual slavery for soldiers, exploiting women for the purpose of creating access and entitlement for men.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.inthesetimes.com/article/3848/ "Why Soldiers Rape – Culture of misogyny, illegal occupation, fuel sexual violence in military"]&lt;/ref&gt; 
&lt;ref name="bare_url"&gt;{{Citation
|url=http://www.japanfocus.org/-Tessa-Morris_Suzuki/2373
|title=Japan's 'Comfort Women': It's time for the truth (in the ordinary, everyday sense of the word)
|author=Tessa Morris-Suzuki
|date=March 8, 2007
|accessdate=2011-08-04
|publisher=[[The Asia-Pacific Journal: Japan Focus]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="definition"&gt;{{Harvnb|WCCW|2004}}.&lt;/ref&gt;
 
Another example of violence against women incited by militarism during war took place in the [[Kaunas Ghetto|Kovno Ghetto]]. Jewish male prisoners had access to (and used) Jewish women forced into camp brothels by the Nazis, who also used them.&lt;ref&gt;Dworkin, Andrea: ''Scapegoat: The Jews, Israel and Women's Liberation.'' pg. 316. Free Press, 2000. ISBN 0-684-83612-2&lt;/ref&gt;

Rape was committed during the [[Bangladesh Liberation War]] by members of the [[Pakistan Armed Forces|Pakistani military]] and the [[militia]]s that supported them. Over a period of nine months, hundreds of thousands of women were raped. [[Susan Brownmiller]], in her report on the [[1971 Bangladesh atrocities|atrocities]], said that girls from the age of eight to grandmothers of seventy-five suffered attacks.  (See also: [[Rape during the Bangladesh Liberation War]])

Rape used as a weapon of war was practiced during the [[Bosnian War]] where rape was used as a highly systematized instrument of war by Serb armed forces predominantly targeting women and girls of the Bosniak ethnic group for physical and moral destruction.  Estimates of the number of women raped during the war range from 50,000 to 60,000;  as of 2010 only 12 cases have been prosecuted.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.icty.org/x/file/About/Reports%20and%20Publications/AnnualReports/annual_report_1997_en.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;  (See also [[Rape during the Bosnian War]]).

The 1998 [[International Criminal Tribunal for Rwanda]] recognized rape as a war crime.  Presiding judge [[Navanethem Pillay]] said in a statement after the verdict: "From time immemorial, rape has been regarded as spoils of war. Now it will be considered a war crime. We want to send out a strong message that rape is no longer a trophy of war."&lt;ref&gt;Quoted in citation for honorary doctorate, Rhodes University, April 2005 accessed at [http://www.ru.ac.za/academic/graduation/addresses_and_citations/2005/Judge_Pillay_citation.doc] March 23, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;  (See also: [[Rwandan Genocide]])

In 2006, five [[United States Army|U.S. troops]] from a six-man unit [[gang rape]]d and killed a 14-year-old girl in a village near the town of [[Mahmoudiyah, Iraq|Al-Mahmudiyah]], Iraq. After the rape the girl was shot in her head and the lower part of her body, from her stomach down to her feet, was set on fire.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cnn.com/2006/WORLD/meast/08/08/iraq.mahmoudiya/index.html |title=Soldier: 'Death walk' drives troops 'nuts' - Aug 8, 2006 |publisher=CNN.com |date= |accessdate=2012-11-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="greenNews"&gt;{{cite news|publisher=BBC News|date=2009-05-07|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/americas/8039257.stm|title=US ex-soldier guilty of Iraq rape}}&lt;/ref&gt; (See also: [[Mahmudiyah killings]])

A 1995 study of female war veterans found that 90 percent had been sexually harassed.   A 2003 survey found that 30 percent of female vets said they were raped in the military and a 2004 study of veterans who were seeking help for post-traumatic stress disorder found that 71 percent of the women said they were sexually assaulted or raped while serving.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=103844570 "The Nation: The Plight of Women Soldiers"]&lt;/ref&gt;

====Forced sterilization and forced abortion====
[[Forced sterilization]] and [[forced abortion]] are forms of gender-based violence.&lt;ref&gt;http://eige.europa.eu/content/what-is-gender-based-violence&lt;/ref&gt; These procedures are reported to be practiced in countries such as Uzbekistan and China.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/magazine-17612550&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b01fjx63&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.globalpost.com/dispatch/news/regions/asia-pacific/china/130409/china-mother-dies-after-forced-sterilization-one-child-policy&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.amnesty.org/en/news-and-updates/thousands-risk-forced-sterilization-china-2010-04-22&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-china-18435126&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.hrnk.org/uploads/pdfs/HRNK_HiddenGulag2_Web_5-18.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

====Violence by the police and other authority figures====
When police officers misuse their power as agents of the state to physically and [[sexual harassment|sexually harass]] and assault victims, the survivors, including women, feel much less able to report the violence.&lt;ref name=FreshAir&gt;{{Cite episode
| title        = Covering 'Tainted Justice' And Winning A Pulitzer
| episodelink  = 
| url          = http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=126386819
| series       = Fresh Air
| serieslink   = Fresh Air
| credits      = Barbara Laker and Wendy Ruderman, hosted by [[Terry Gross]]
| network      = NPR
| station      = [[WHYY-FM|WHYY]]
| city         = Philadelphia
| airdate      = 3 May 2010
| began        = 
| ended        = 
| season       = 
| seriesno     =
| number       = 
| minutes      = 
| transcript   =  
| transcripturl= }}&lt;/ref&gt;  It is standard procedure for police to force entry into the victim's home even after the victim's numerous requests for them to go away.&lt;ref&gt;[[Jeannie Suk|Professor Jeannie Suk]], ''At Home in the Law: How the Domestic Violence Revolution Is Transforming Privacy,'' [[Yale University Press]], 27 October 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; Government agencies often disregard the victim's right to [[Freedom of association#Intimate association|freedom of association]] with their perpetrator.&lt;ref&gt;Cheryl Hanna, "No Right to Choose: Mandated Victim Participation in Domestic Violence Prosecutions," ''[[Harvard Law Review]]'', 1996, Vol. 109, pp.1850–1910.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Women's shelter|Shelter]] workers are often reduced themselves to contributing to violence against women by exploiting their [[vulnerability]] in exchange for a paying job.&lt;ref&gt;Koyama, Emi "Disloyal to feminism: Abuse of survivors within the domestic violence shelter system." in Smith A, Richie BE, Sudbury J, eds. ''The Color of Violence: INCITE! Anthology.'' Cambridge, Mass.: South End Press, 2006. ISBN 0-89608-762-X&lt;/ref&gt;

Human rights violations perpetrated by police and military personnel in many countries are correlated with decreased access to public health services and increased practices of risky behavior among members of vulnerable groups, such as women and female sex workers.&lt;ref name="Beletsky L, Martinex G, Gaines T, et al. 2012 403–410"&gt;{{cite journal|author=Beletsky L, Martinex G, Gaines T, et al.|title=Mexico’s northern border conflict: collateral damage to health and human rights of vulnerable groups|journal=Rev Panam Salud Publica|year=2012|pmid=22767041|volume=31|issue=5|pmc=PMC3660986|pages=403–410}}&lt;/ref&gt; These practices are especially widespread in settings with a weak rule of law and low levels of police and military management and professionalism. Police abuse in this context has been linked to a wide range of risky behaviors and health outcomes, including post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD), and substance abuse.&lt;ref name="Beletsky L, Martinex G, Gaines T, et al. 2012 403–410"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Strathdee S, Lozada R, Martinez G, et al.|title=Social and structural factors associated with HIV infection among female sex workers who inject drugs in the Mexico-US border region|journal=PLoS ONE|year=2011|pmid=21541349|doi=10.1371/journal.pone.0019048|volume=6|issue=4|pmc=PMC3081836|page=e19048}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Ramos R, Ferreira-Pinto J, Brouwer K, et al.|title=A tale of two cities: social and environmental influences shaping risk factors and protective behaviors in two Mexico-US border cities|journal=Health Place|year=2009|pmid=19464228|doi=10.1016/j.healthplace.2009.04.004|volume=15|issue=4|pmc=PMC2735581|pages=999–1005}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Pollini R, Brouwer K, Lozada R, et al.|title=Syringe possession arrests are associated with receptive syringe sharing in two Mexico-US border cities|journal=Addiction|year=2008|pmid=18028520|volume=103|issue=1|pmc=PMC2214830|pages=101–108}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Pollini R, Gallardo M, Hassan S, et al.|title=High prevalence of abscesses and self-treatment among injection drug users in Tijuana, Mexico|journal=Int J Infect Dis|year=2010|pmid=20381396|doi=10.1016/j.ijid.2010.02.2238|volume=14|supplement=3|pmc=PMC2917477|pages=117–122}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Strathdee S, Lozada R, Pollini R, et al.|title=Individual, social, and environmental influences associated with HIV infection among injection drug users in Tijuana, Mexico|journal=JAIDS|year=2008|pmid=18176320|doi= 10.1097/QAI.0b013e318160d5ae|volume=47|issue=3|pmc=PMC2752692|pages=369–376}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Raj A, Gupta J.|title=Women, migration, conflict and risk for HIV|editors= Martin S, Tirman J|title=Women, Migration, and Conflict: Breaking a Deadly Cycle|publisher=Springer|year=2009|page=107}}&lt;/ref&gt; Extortion of sexual services and police sexual abuse have been linked to a decrease in condom use and an elevated risk of STI and HIV infections among vulnerable groups.&lt;ref name="Beletsky L, Martinex G, Gaines T, et al. 2012 403–410"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Blankenship K, Koester S.|title=Criminal law, policing policy, and HIV risk in female street sex workers and injection drug users|journal=J Law Med Ethics|year=2002|pmid=12561263|volume=30|issue=4|pages=548–559}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Stoning and flogging====
[[Stoning]], or lapidation, refers to a form of [[capital punishment]] whereby an organized group throws stones at an individual until the person dies. Stoning is a punishment that is included in the laws of several countries, including Iran, Saudi Arabia, Sudan, Pakistan, Yemen, the United Arab Emirates, and some states in Nigeria, as punishment for [[adultery]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.google.com/hostednews/afp/article/ALeqM5ixvYN7oeF8ehN9beAHZ4G_YlfKeA?hl=en&lt;/ref&gt; [[Flogging]] or flagellation is the act of methodically beating or whipping the human body. It is a judicial punishment in various countries for specific crimes, including [[sex outside marriage]]. These punishments employed for sexual relations outside marriage, apart from constituting a form of violence in themselves, can also deter victims of [[sexual violence]] from reporting the crime, because the victims may themselves be punished (if they cannot prove their case, if they are deemed to have been in the company of an unrelated male, or if they were unmarried and not virgins at the time of the rape).&lt;ref&gt;http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-21595814&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.today.com/id/15836746/ns/today-today_news/t/rape-case-calls-saudi-legal-system-question/#.UolafidedO6&lt;/ref&gt;

===Gender-based violence by male college athletes===

Violence against women is a topic of concern in the United States' collegiate athletic community. From the 2010 UVA lacrosse murder, in which a male athlete was charged guilty with second degree murder of his girlfriend, to the 2004 University of Colorado Football Scandal when players were charged with nine alleged sexual assaults,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Vaughan|first=Kevin|title=Colorado woman seeks justice in alleged sexual assault  Read more: Colorado woman seeks justice in alleged sexual assault|url=http://www.denverpost.com/firstinthepost/ci_12557039|work=denver Post|accessdate=17 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; studies suggest that athletes are at higher risk for committing sexual assault against women than the average student.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Brady|first=Jeff|title=Scandal Returns to University of Colorado Football|url=http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=105381707|work=NPR weekend edition|publisher=NPR|accessdate=12 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="chandler1999"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Chandler|first=Steve B|coauthors=JOHNSON, DEWAYNE J. CARROLL, PAMELA S.|title=Abusive Behaviors of College Athletes|journal=College Student Journal|date=12/01/1999|year=1999|month=December|volume=33|issue=4|accessdate=12 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is reported that one in three college assaults are committed by athletes.&lt;ref name="johnshopkins1"&gt;{{cite web|last=Mak|first=Stephanie|title=Are Athletes More Abusive Than the Rest of the Student Population?|url=http://web1.johnshopkins.edu/hurj/issue3/spotlight-mak.html|publisher=Hopkins Undergraduate Research Journal Online|accessdate=12 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Surveys suggest that male student athletes who represent 3.3% of the college population, commit 19% of reported sexual assaults and 35% of domestic violence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Statistics|url=http://www.ncava.org/Statistics.html|publisher=The National Coalition Against Violent Athletes|accessdate=12 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The theories that surround these statistics range from misrepresentation of the student-athlete to an unhealthy mentality towards women within the team itself.&lt;ref name="johnshopkins1"/&gt;

====Controversy over contributing factors====

Sociologist Timothy Curry, after conducting an observational analysis of two big time sports’ locker room conversations, deduced that the high risk of male student athletes for gender abuse is a result of the team’s subculture.&lt;ref name=Curry1991&gt;{{cite journal|last=Curry|first=Timothy Jon|title=Fraternal Bonding in the Locker Room: A Profeminist Analysis Of Talk About Competition And Women|journal=Sociology of Sport Journal|year=1991|volume=8|issue=2|pages=119–135|accessdate=12 March 2012|url=http://www.umt.edu/sociology/faculty_staff/ellestad/documents/275_Curry1991fraternalbondinginthelockerroom_s10.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; He states, "Their locker room talk generally treated women as objects, encouraged sexist attitudes toward women and, in its extreme, promoted rape culture."&lt;ref name=Curry1991/&gt; He proposes that this objectification is a way for the male to reaffirm his heterosexual status and hyper-masculinity. Claims have been made that the atmosphere changes when an outsider (especially women) intrude in the locker room. In the wake of the reporter [[Lisa Olson]] being harassed by a Patriots player in the locker room in 1990, she reflected, "We are taught to think we must have done something wrong and it took me a while to realize I hadn't done anything wrong."&lt;ref name=lisa&gt;{{cite journal|last=Disch|first=Lisa|coauthors=Kane, Mary Jo|title=When a Looker is Really a Bitch: Lisa Olson, Sport, and the Heterosexual Matrix|journal=Signs|year=1996|month=Winter|volume=21|issue=2|pages=278–308|url=http://www.jstor.org/stable/3175065|accessdate=17 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other female sports reporters (college and professional) have claimed that they often brush off the players' comments which leads to further objectification.&lt;ref name=lisa /&gt;  Other sociologists challenge this claim. Steve Chandler notes that because of their celebrity status on campus, “athletes are more likely to be scrutinized or falsely accused than non-athletes.”&lt;ref name="chandler1999"/&gt;  Another contender, Stephanie Mak, notes that, “if one considers the 1998 estimates that about three million women were battered and almost one million raped, the proportion of incidences that involve athletes in comparison to the regular population is relatively small."&lt;ref name="johnshopkins1"/&gt;

====Response to violence by male college athletes====

In response to the proposed link between college athletes and gender-based violence, and media coverage holding Universities as responsible for these scandals more universities are requiring athletes to attend workshops that promote awareness. For example, St. John's University holds sexual assault awareness classes in the fall for its incoming student athletes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Newsom|first=John|title=Share on emailShare on redditMore Sharing Services  Few Colleges Tackle Issue of Athlete Sex Assaults|url=http://articles.latimes.com/1992-03-22/news/mn-7249_1_sexual-assault|publisher=Los Angeles Times Online|accessdate=12 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Other groups, such as the National Coalition Against Violent Athletes, have formed to provide support for the victims as their mission statement reads, "The NCAVA works to eliminate off the field violence by athletes through the implementation of prevention methods that recognize and promote the positive leadership potential of athletes within their communities.  In order to eliminate violence, the NCAVA is dedicated to empowering individuals affected by athlete violence through comprehensive services including advocacy, education and counseling."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Mission|url=http://www.ncava.org/Mission.html|publisher=National Coalition Against Violent Athletes|accessdate=12 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Activism==
Many activists believe that working towards the elimination of domestic violence means working to eliminate a societal hierarchy enforced through sexism. [[INCITE! Women of Color Against Violence]] cited racism within the anti-violence movement and suggest that violence against women will not end until the anti-violence movement re-directs its goal from "ending violence against women" to "ending violence against women of color."&lt;ref&gt;[[INCITE! Women of Color Against Violence]]: ''Color of Violence: The INCITE! Anthology.'' pg 4. South End Press, 2006. ISBN 0-89608-762-X&lt;/ref&gt; The same conclusion can be drawn for other systems of oppression.  [[Shows red card to abuser]] ({{lang-es|Saca tarjeta roja al maltratador}}) is a campaign against domestic violence launched by the [[Spanish Ministry of Equality]] that has the support of many famous artists, journalists and athletes.&lt;ref&gt;[http://thebridgeoflostdesires.tumblr.com/post/2403755354/a-public-advertisement-in-madrid-against-domestic  Advertisement against domestic violence in Spain]&lt;/ref&gt;  It is considered very effective in helping "to abandon complicity  and take a step in favour of [[justice]]."&lt;ref name="elpais1"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.elpais.com/articulo/sociedad/Tarjeta/roja/maltratador/elpepusoc/20100318elpepusoc_8/Tes |title=Tarjeta roja al maltratador · ELPAÍS.com |publisher= journal [[Elpais.com]] |date=18-03-2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==

*[[Acid attack]]
*[[Bride burning]]
*[[Domestic violence]]
*[[Eve teasing]]
*[[Female genital mutilation]]
*[[Human trafficking]]
*[[Infibulation]]
*[[Military sexual trauma]]
*[[Murder of pregnant women]]
*[[Convention on preventing and combating violence against women and domestic violence]]
*[[Sexual assault in the U.S. military]]
*[[Sexual slavery]]
*[[Violence Against Women Act]]
*[[Violence against men]]

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
* {{Cite journal | last1 = Durham | first1 = Meenakshi G. | authorlink1 = Meenakshi Gigi Durham | title = ''"Vicious assault shakes Texas town"'': the politics of gender violence in The New York Times' coverage of a schoolgirl's gang rape | journal = Journalism Studies | volume = 14 | issue = 1 | pages = 1–12 | publisher = Taylor &amp; Francis Online | doi = 10.1080/1461670X.2012.657907 | date = February 2013 | url = http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/1461670X.2012.657907 | ref = harv | postscript = .}}

==External links==
*{{dmoz|Society/People/Women/Issues/Violence_and_Abuse}}
* [http://www.echr.coe.int/NR/rdonlyres/39C38938-2E29-4151-9280-D5AC063DD02E/0/FICHES_Violence_femmes_EN.pdf Violence against women], a factsheet on [[ECtHR]] case law
* [http://www.endvawnow.org/ Virtual Knowledge Centre to End Violence against Women and Girls] (in English, French, and Spanish)
* [http://www.ohchr.org/EN/Issues/Women/SRWomen/Pages/SRWomenIndex.aspx UN Special Rapporteur on violence against women, its causes and consequences]

{{abuse}}
{{Domestic violence}}

&lt;references /&gt;

{{DEFAULTSORT:Violence Against Women}}
[[Category:Violence against women| ]]
[[Category:Sex industry]]
[[Category:Feminism and health]]
[[Category:Gender-based violence]]
[[Category:Misogyny]]
[[Category:Crimes against women]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>