<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20171118001105|810871603" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="3634424" pageid="3634424" ns="0" title="Violence against women"><revisions><rev timestamp="2017-11-21T03:05:27Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{For|the journal|Violence Against Women (journal)}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2012}}
{{pp-semi-sock|small=yes}}
{{Violence against women}}

'''Violence against women''' ('''VAW'''), also known as '''gender-based violence''',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | title=Gender-Based Violence: Concepts, Methods, and Findings | journal=Annals of the New York Academy of Sciences | year=2006 | volume=1087 | pages=178–205 | doi=10.1196/annals.1385.024 |author=Russo, Nancy Felipe |author2=Angela Pirlott}}&lt;/ref&gt; is, collectively, violent acts that are primarily or exclusively committed against [[woman|women]]. Sometimes considered a [[hate crime]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=2YdCbgXjr-EC&amp;pg=PA405 |chapter=Hate Crime Statutes: A Promising Tool for Fighting Violence Against Women |first=Marguerite |last=Angelari |title=Pornography, sex work, and hate speech |editor=Karen J. Maschke |publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis |year=1997}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=DiBIZcx1nPcC&amp;pg=PA58 |title=Hate Crimes: Causes, Controls, and Controversies |first=Phyllis B. |last=Gerstenfeld |year=2013 |publisher=Sage}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=2ZNnXj_SbOsC&amp;pg=PA271 |title=Hate and bias crime: a reader |editor=Barbara Perry |year=2003 |publisher=[[Psychology Press]]|first=Beverly |last=McPhail |chapter=Gender-Bias Hate Crimes: A Review}}&lt;/ref&gt; this type of violence targets a specific group with the victim's [[gender]] as a primary motive. This type of violence is gender-based, meaning that the acts of violence are committed against women expressly because they are women. The UN [[Declaration on the Elimination of Violence Against Women]] states, "violence against women is a manifestation of historically unequal power relations between men and women" and "violence against women is one of the crucial social mechanisms by which women are forced into a subordinate position compared with men."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.un-documents.net/a48r104.htm |title=A/RES/48/104 - Declaration on the Elimination of Violence against Women |publisher=United Nations General Assembly |accessdate=2014-08-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Kofi Annan]], [[Secretary-General of the United Nations]], declared in a 2006 report posted on the [[United Nations Development Fund for Women]] (UNIFEM) website:&lt;blockquote&gt;Violence against women and girls is a problem of [[pandemic]] proportions. At least one out of every three women around the world has been beaten, coerced into sex, or otherwise abused in her lifetime with the abuser usually someone known to her.&lt;ref name="Moradian"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://en.tolerancy.org/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=176:2009-09-15-08-37-55&amp;catid=43:events-a-reports&amp;Itemid=90 |title=Domestic Violence against Single and Married Women in Iranian Society |last=Moradian |first=Azad |work=Tolerancy.org |publisher=[[The Chicago School of Professional Psychology]] |date=2010-09-10 |deadurl=no |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120425230632/http://en.tolerancy.org/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=176%3A2009-09-15-08-37-55&amp;catid=43%3Aevents-a-reports&amp;Itemid=90 |archivedate=25 April 2012 |accessdate=2015-03-01 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Violence against women can fit into several broad categories. These include violence carried out by "individuals" as well as "states". Some of the forms of violence perpetrated by individuals are: [[rape]], [[domestic violence]], [[sexual harassment]], [[reproductive coercion]], [[female infanticide]], [[sex selective abortion|prenatal sex selection]], obstetric violence, and [[mob violence]]; as well as harmful customary or traditional practices such as [[honor killings]], [[dowry death|dowry violence]], [[female genital mutilation]], [[marriage by abduction]] and [[forced marriage]]. Some forms of violence are perpetrated or condoned by the state such as [[war rape]]; [[sexual violence]] and [[sexual slavery]] during conflict; [[forced sterilization]]; [[forced abortion]]; violence by the police and authoritative personnel; [[stoning]] and [[flogging]]. Many forms of VAW, such as [[trafficking in women]] and [[forced prostitution]] are often perpetrated by organized criminal networks.&lt;ref name="Prügl, E. 2013"&gt;Prügl, E. (Director) (25 November 2013). Violence Against Women. Gender and International Affairs Class 2013. Lecture conducted from [[The Graduate Institute of International and Development Studies]] (IHEID), Geneva, Switzerland.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[World Health Organization]] (WHO), in its research on VAW, has analyzed and categorized the different forms of VAW occurring through all stages of life from before birth to old age.&lt;ref&gt;(1997). [http://www.who.int/gender/violence/v4.pdf Violence against women: Definition and scope of the problem.] World Health Organization, 1, 1-3. Retrieved 30 November 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;

In recent years, there has been a trend of approaching VAW at an international level, through instruments such as conventions; or, in the [[European Union]], through [[Directive (European Union)|directive]]s, such as the directive against [[sexual harassment]],&lt;ref&gt;Directive 2002/73/EC - equal treatment of 23 September 2002 amending Council Directive 76/207/EEC on the implementation of the principle of equal treatment for men and women as regards access to employment, vocational training and promotion, and working conditions [http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=CONSLEG:1976L0207:20021005:EN:PDF]&lt;/ref&gt; and the directive against [[human trafficking]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2011:101:0001:0011:EN:PDF |format=PDF |title= "Directive 2011/36/EU of the European Parliament and of the Council of 5 April 2011 on preventing and combating trafficking in human beings and protecting its victims, and replacing Council Framework Decision 2002/629/JH" |work=Official Journal of the European Union |accessdate=2016-04-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Definition==
The [[Council of Europe Convention on preventing and combating violence against women and domestic violence]], also known as the Istanbul Convention, provides the following definition of violence against women:&lt;ref name="COE 210"&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.coe.int/en/web/conventions/full-list/-/conventions/treaty/210 |title=Details of Treaty No.210: Council of Europe Convention on preventing and combating violence against women and domestic violence |publisher=Council of Europe |date= |accessdate=2016-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Quotation|"violence against women" is understood as a violation of human rights and a form of discrimination against women and shall mean all acts of gender-based violence that result in, or are likely to result in, physical, sexual, psychological or economic harm or suffering to women, including threats of such acts, coercion or arbitrary deprivation of liberty, whether occurring in public or in private life}}

Although the 1979 [[Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination Against Women]] (CEDAW) includes VAW in its General Recommendations 12 and 19,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.un.org/womenwatch/daw/cedaw/recommendations/ |title=General recommendations adopted by the Committee on the Elimination of Discrimination against Women |publisher=United Nations |date=2003-12-31 |accessdate=2016-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[Vienna Declaration and Programme of Action]] mentions VAW at paragraph 18,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |date=12 July 1993 |url=http://www.refworld.org/cgi-bin/texis/vtx/rwmain?page=topic&amp;tocid=459d17822&amp;toid=459b17a82&amp;docid=3ae6b39ec&amp;skip=O |title=Vienna Declaration and Programme of Action |publisher=refworld |accessdate=2016-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; it was the 1993 [[United Nations General Assembly]] resolution on the [[Declaration on the Elimination of Violence Against Women]], which became the first international instrument to explicitly define VAW and elaborate on the subject.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.unwomen.org/en/what-we-do/ending-violence-against-women/global-norms-and-standards |title=What We Do: Ending Violence against Women: Global Norms and Standards |publisher=UN Women |accessdate=2016-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other definitions of VAW are provided by the 1994 ''Inter-American Convention on the Prevention, Punishment, and Eradication of Violence against Women''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.oas.org/juridico/english/treaties/a-61.html |title=Inter-American Convention On The Prevention, Punishment And Eradication Of Violence Against Women "Convention Of Belem Do Para" |publisher=Organization of American States |accessdate=2016-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; and by the 2003 [[Maputo Protocol]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.achpr.org/files/instruments/women-protocol/achpr_instr_proto_women_eng.pdf |format=PDF |title=Protocol to the African Charter on Human and Peoples' Rights on the Rights of Women in Africa |publisher=African Commission on Human and Peoples' Rights |accessdate=2016-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In addition, the term ''gender-based violence'' refers to "any acts or threats of acts intended to hurt or make women suffer physically, sexually or psychologically, and which affect women because they are women or affect women disproportionately".&lt;ref&gt;Richters, J. M. (1994). Women, Culture and Violence; a Development, Health and Human Rights Issue.Women Autonomy Centre (VENA), 1, 1-205.&lt;/ref&gt; The definition of gender-based violence is most often "used interchangeably with violence against women",&lt;ref name="Krantz"&gt;{{cite journal|author1=Krantz, G.|author2=Garcia-Moreno, C.|date=2005|title=Violence against Women|journal=[[Journal of Epidemiology and Community Health]]|volume=59 | issue = 10 |pages=818–821|jstor=25570854 |doi=10.1136/jech.2004.022756 |pmid=16166351 |pmc=1732916}}&lt;/ref&gt; and some articles on VAW reiterate these conceptions by suggesting that men are the main perpetrators of this violence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Sen, P.|date=1998|title=Development Practice and Violence against Women|journal=Gender and Development|volume=6 | issue = 3 |pages=7–16|jstor=4030497|doi=10.1080/741922827}}&lt;/ref&gt; Moreover, the definition stated by the 1993 Declaration on the Elimination of Violence Against Women also supported the notion that violence is rooted in the inequality between men and women when the term violence is used together with the term 'gender-based.'&lt;ref name="Krantz"/&gt;

In ''Recommendation Rec(2002)5 of the Committee of Ministers to member states on the protection of women against violence'', the Council of Europe stipulated that VAW "includes, but is not limited to, the following":&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |date=30 April 2002 |url=https://wcd.coe.int/ViewDoc.jsp?id=280915&amp;Site=CM&amp;BackColorInternet=C3C3C3&amp;BackColorIntranet=EDB021&amp;BackColorLogged=F5D383 |format=PDF |title=Recommendations of the Committee of Ministers to member states on the protection of women against violence |publisher=Council of Europe Committee of Ministers |accessdate=2016-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

a. violence occurring in the family or domestic unit, including, ''inter alia'', physical and mental aggression, emotional and psychological abuse, rape and sexual abuse, incest, rape between spouses, regular or occasional partners and cohabitants, crimes committed in the name of honour, female genital and sexual mutilation and other traditional practices harmful to women, such as forced marriages;

b. violence occurring within the general community, including, ''inter alia'', rape, sexual abuse, sexual harassment and intimidation at work, in institutions or elsewhere trafficking in women for the purposes of sexual exploitation and economic exploitation and sex tourism;

c. violence perpetrated or condoned by the state or its officials;

d. violation of the human rights of women in situations of armed conflict, in particular the taking of hostages, forced displacement, systematic rape, sexual slavery, forced pregnancy, and trafficking for the purposes of sexual exploitation and economic exploitation.

These definitions of VAW as being gender-based are seen by some to be unsatisfactory and problematic. These definitions are conceptualized in an understanding of society as patriarchal, signifying unequal relations between men and women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Ertürk, Y.|date=2009|title=Towards a Post-Patriarchal Gender Order: Confronting the universality and the particularity of violence against women|journal=Sociologisk Forskning|volume=46 | issue = 4 |pages=61–70|jstor=20853687}}&lt;/ref&gt; Opponents of such definitions argue that the definitions disregard violence against men and that the term ''[[gender]]'', as used in ''gender based violence'', only refers to women. Other critics argue that employing the term ''gender'' in this particular way may introduce notions of inferiority and subordination for femininity and superiority for masculinity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Visaria, L.|date=2000|title=Violence against Women: A Field Study|journal=[[Economic and Political Weekly]]|volume=35 | issue = 20 |pages=1742–1751|jstor=4409296}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Michau, L. 2007 pp.96"&gt;{{cite journal|author=Michau, L. |date=2007|title=Approaching Old Problems in New Ways: Community Mobilisation as a Primary Prevention Strategy to Combat Violence against Women|journal=[[Gender and Development]]|volume=15 | issue = 1 |pages=95–109|jstor=20461184 |doi=10.1080/13552070601179144}}&lt;/ref&gt; There is no widely accepted current definition that covers all the dimensions of gender based violence rather than the one for women that tends to reproduce the concept of binary oppositions: masculinity versus femininity.&lt;ref name="Prügl, E. 2013"/&gt;

==History==

===Overview===
[[File:Grandville Cent Proverbes page69.png|thumb|right|An illustration from [[Jean Ignace Isidore Gérard|JJ Grandville]]'s ''Cent Proverbes'' (1845) captioned "Qui aime bien châtie bien" (''Who loves well, punishes well''). A man beating a woman is shown in the back.]]
[[File:Torturing and execution of witches in medieval miniature.jpg|thumb|Burning witches, with others held in Stocks]]
[[File:Sati ceremony.jpg|thumb|[[Sati (practice)|Sati]] (a Hindu practice whereby a [[widow]] immolates herself on the funeral pyre of her husband) ceremony.]]
[[File:Bound feet (X-ray).jpg|thumb|X-ray of [[bound feet]], China]]
The history of violence against women remains vague in scientific literature. This is in part because many kinds of violence against women (specifically rape, sexual assault, and domestic violence) are under-reported, often due to societal norms, taboos, stigma, and the sensitive nature of the subject.&lt;ref name="WHO World Report on violence and health" /&gt;&lt;ref name="VAM: Global scope &amp; magnitude" /&gt; It is widely recognized that even today, a lack of reliable and continuous data is an obstacle to forming a clear picture of violence against women.&lt;ref name="UN In-depth Study on all Forms of Violence Against Women" /&gt;

Although the history of violence against women is difficult to track, it is clear that much of the violence was accepted, condoned and even legally sanctioned.&lt;ref name="Film script"&gt;{{cite web|last=Ireland|first=Patricia|title=Script|url=https://www.pbs.org/kued/nosafeplace/script/script.html|work=No Safe Place: Violence Against Women|publisher=PBS|accessdate=2 December 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Examples include that Roman law gave men the right to chastise their wives, even to the point of death,&lt;ref name="Roman Law"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Stedman|first=Berne|title=Right of Husband to Chastise Wife|journal=Virginia Law Register|date=August 1917|volume=3|issue=4|page=241|url=http://heinonline.org/HOL/LandingPage?handle=hein.journals/valrgn3&amp;div=35&amp;id=&amp;page=|accessdate=2 December 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; the burning of witches, which was condoned by both the church and the state.&lt;ref name="Film script" /&gt;

The history of violence against women is closely related to the historical view of women as property and a gender role of subservience.&lt;ref&gt;Penelope Harvey &amp; Peter Gow ''Sex and violence : issues in representation and experience'' (1994) p. 36 Routledge {{ISBN|0-415-05734-5}}&lt;/ref&gt; Explanations of [[patriarchy]] and an overall world system or status quo in which gender inequalities exist and are perpetuated are cited to explain the scope and history of violence against women.&lt;ref name="VAM: Global scope &amp; magnitude"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Watts|first=Charlotte|author2=Zimmerman, Cathy |title=Violence against women: global scope and magnitude|journal=The Lancet|date=April 2002|volume=359|issue=9313|pages=1232–1237|doi=10.1016/S0140-6736(02)08221-1|pmid=11955557}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="UN In-depth Study on all Forms of Violence Against Women" /&gt; The UN Declaration on the Elimination of Violence against Women (1993) states, "violence against women is a manifestation of historically unequal power relations between men and women, which have led to domination over and discrimination against women by men and to the prevention of the full advancement of women, and that violence against women is one of the crucial social mechanisms by which women are forced into a subordinate position compared with men."&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.un.org/documents/ga/res/48/a48r104.htm A/RES/48/104. Declaration on the Elimination of Violence against Women]. United Nations.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unfpa.org/rights/violence.htm Addressing Gender-Based Violence: Advancing Human Rights]. UNFPA.&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the UN, "there is no region of the world, no country and no culture in which women's freedom from violence has been secured."&lt;ref name="UN In-depth Study on all Forms of Violence Against Women" /&gt; Several forms of violence are more prevalent in certain parts of the world, often in developing countries. For example, [[dowry death|dowry violence]] and [[bride burning]] is associated with [[India]], [[Bangladesh]], [[Sri Lanka]], and [[Nepal]]. [[Acid throwing]] is also associated with these countries, as well as in [[Southeast Asia]], including [[Cambodia]]. [[Honor killing]] is associated with the [[Middle East]] and [[South Asia]]. [[Female genital mutilation]] is found mostly in [[Africa]], and to a lesser extent in the Middle East and some other parts of Asia. [[Marriage by abduction]] is found in [[Ethiopia]], [[Central Asia]] and the [[Caucasus]]. Abuse related to payment of [[bride price]] (such as violence, trafficking and forced marriage) is linked to parts of Sub-Saharan Africa and Oceania. (Also see [[lobolo]].)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.violenceisnotourculture.org/News-and-Views/papua-new-guinea-police-cite-bride-price-major-factor-marital-violence |title=Papua New Guinea: Police Cite Bride Price Major Factor in Marital Violence |publisher=Violence is not our Culture |date=2011-11-21 |accessdate=2014-08-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mrc.ac.za/gender/Bridepricedomesticviolence.pdf |title=An Exploratory Study of Bride Price and Domestic Violence in Bundibugyo District, Uganda |publisher=Centre for Human Rights Advancement (Cehura) |date=April 2012 |accessdate=2014-08-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Certain regions are no longer associated with a specific form of violence, but such violence was common until quite recently in those places; this is true of honor-based crimes in Southern/Mediterranean Europe.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.sascv.org/ijcjs/pdfs/kirtietalicjs2011i&amp;iind.pdf |title=The Face of Honour Based Crimes: Global Concerns and Solutions |journal=International Journal of Criminal Justice Sciences |volume=6 |number=1 &amp; 2 |date=2011 |accessdate=2014-08-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; For instance, in [[Italy]], before 1981, the Criminal Code provided for mitigating circumstances in case of a killing of a woman or her sexual partner for reasons related to honor, providing for a reduced sentence.&lt;ref&gt;Before 1981, Art. 587 read: He who causes the death of a spouse, daughter, or sister upon discovering her in illegitimate carnal relations and in the heat of passion caused by the offence to his honour or that of his family will be sentenced to three to seven years. The same sentence shall apply to whom, in the above circumstances, causes the death of the person involved in illegitimate carnal relations with his spouse, daughter, or sister. [http://www.surt.org/gvei/docs/national_report_italy.pdf]&lt;/ref&gt;

Invoking culture to explain particular forms of violence against women risks appearing to legitimize them. There is also debate and controversy about the ways in which cultural traditions, local customs and social expectations, as well as various interpretations of religion, interact with abusive practices.&lt;ref name="UN In-depth Study on all Forms of Violence Against Women" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Uma Narayan, Cross‐Cultural Connections, Border‐Crossings, and "Death by Culture": Thinking about Dowry-Murders in India and Domestic‐Violence Murders in the United States. In Dislocating Cultures: Identities, Traditions and Third World Feminism (New York: Routledge, 1997): 83–117.&lt;/ref&gt; Specifically, cultural justifications for certain violent acts against women are asserted by some states and social groups within many countries claiming to defend their traditions. These justifications are questionable precisely because the defenses are generally voiced by political leaders or traditional authorities, not by those actually affected.&lt;ref name="UN In-depth Study on all Forms of Violence Against Women" /&gt; The need for sensitivity and respect of culture is an element that cannot be ignored either; thus a sensitive debate has ensued and is ongoing.

There has also been a history of recognizing the harmful effects of this violence. In the 1870s, courts in the United States stopped recognizing the common-law principle that a husband had the right to "physically chastise an errant wife".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Calvert R |year=1974 |chapter=Criminal and civil liability in husband-wife assaults |title=Violence in the family |pages=88–91 |veditors=Steinmetz S, Straus M |publisher=Harper &amp; Row |location=New York}}&lt;/ref&gt; The first state to rescind this right was Alabama in 1871.&lt;ref name="USDOJ-History of VAWA" /&gt; In the UK the right of a husband to inflict moderate [[corporal punishment]] on his wife to keep her "within the bounds of duty" was removed in 1891.&lt;ref&gt;R. v. Jackson [1891]. 1 Q.B. 671&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Encyclopædia Britannica Eleventh Edition]], 1911. Article ''Corporal punishment''&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 20th and 21st centuries, and in particular since the 1990s, there has been increased activity on both the national and international levels to research, raise awareness and advocate for the prevention of all kinds of violence against women.&lt;ref name="UN In-depth Study on all Forms of Violence Against Women" /&gt; Most often, violence against women has been framed as a health issue, and also as a violation of human rights. A study in 2002 estimated that at least one in five women in the world had been physically or sexually abused by a man sometime in their lives, and "gender-based violence accounts for as much death and ill-health in women aged 15–44 years as cancer, and is a greater cause of ill-health than malaria and traffic accidents combined."&lt;ref name="VAW: A Global Burden" /&gt;

Certain characteristics of violence against women have emerged from the research. For example, acts of violence against women are often not unique episodes, but are ongoing over time. More often than not, the violence is perpetrated by someone the woman knows, not by a stranger.&lt;ref name="VAM: Global scope &amp; magnitude" /&gt; The research seems to provide convincing evidence that violence against women is a severe and pervasive problem the world over, with devastating effects on the health and well-being of women and children.&lt;ref name="UN In-depth Study on all Forms of Violence Against Women" /&gt;

===Milestones===
Some of the most important milestones on the international level for the prevention of violence against women include:

*The 1979 [[Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination against Women]] (CEDAW), which recognizes violence as a part of discrimination against women in recommendations 12 and 19.&lt;ref name="UN Women: Global Norms &amp; Standards"&gt;{{cite web|title=Global Norms and Standards: Ending Violence against Women|url=http://www.unwomen.org/en/what-we-do/ending-violence-against-women/global-norms-and-standards|publisher=UN Women|accessdate=2 December 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*The 1993 [[World Conference on Human Rights]], which recognized violence against women as a human rights violation, and which contributed to the following UN declaration.&lt;ref name="UN Women: Global Norms &amp; Standards" /&gt;
*The 1993 UN [[Declaration on the Elimination of Violence against Women]] was the first international instrument explicitly defining and addressing violence against women. This document specifically refers to the historically forever-present nature of gender inequalities in understanding violence against women.&lt;ref name="UN Women: Global Norms &amp; Standards"/&gt; (Include current 2nd paragraph here). This Declaration, as well as the World Conference of the same year, is often viewed as a "turning point" at which the consideration of violence against women by the international community began to be taken much more seriously, and after which more countries mobilized around this problem.&lt;ref name="VAW: A Global Burden" /&gt;&lt;ref name="WHO Multicountry Study"&gt;{{cite book|last=Garcia-Moreno|first=Claudia|title=WHO Multi-country Study on Women's Health and Domestic Violence against Women|year=2005|publisher=WHO|location=Switzerland|isbn=924159358X|url=http://cdrwww.who.int/gender/violence/who_multicountry_study/Introduction-Chapter1-Chapter2.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*The 1994 [[International Conference on Population and Development]], linking violence against women to reproductive health and rights, and also providing recommendations to governments on how to prevent and respond to violence against women and girls.&lt;ref name="UN Women: Global Norms &amp; Standards"/&gt;
*In 1996, the [[World Health Assembly]] (WHA) declared violence a major public health issue, and included in the subtypes recognized were intimate partner violence and sexual violence, two kinds of violence often perpetrated as violence against women. This was followed by a WHO report in 2002 (see below).&lt;ref name="WHO World Report on violence and health"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Krug|first=Etienne G|author2=Mercy, James A |author3=Dahlberg, Linda L |author4= Zwi, Anthony B |title=The world report on violence and health|journal=The Lancet|date=October 2002|volume=360|issue=9339|pages=1083–1088|doi=10.1016/S0140-6736(02)11133-0}}&lt;/ref&gt; The UN also created the Trust Fund to Support Actions to Eliminate Violence Against Women.&lt;ref name="Fried"&gt;Fried, Susana T. "Violence against Women". ''Health and Human Rights'' 6.2 (2003): 88.&lt;/ref&gt; 
*In 1999, the UN adopted the [[Optional Protocol to the Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination against Women]] and designated [[November 25]] as the [[International Day for the Elimination of Violence against Women]].&lt;ref name="VAW: A Global Burden"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Venis|first=Sarah|author2=Horton, Richard |title=Violence against women: a global burden|journal=The Lancet|date=April 2002|volume=359|issue=9313|page=1172|doi=10.1016/S0140-6736(02)08251-X}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
*In 2002, as a follow-up of the WHA declaration in 1996 of violence as a major public health issue, the [[World Health Organization]] published the first World Report on Violence and Health, which addressed many types of violence and their effect on public health, including forms of violence affecting women particularly strongly. The report specifically noted the sharp rise in civil society organizations and activities directed at responding to gender-based violence against women from the 1970s to the 1990s.&lt;ref name="WHO World Report on violence and health" /&gt; 
*In 2004, the [[World Health Organization]] published its "Multi-country study on Women's Health and Domestic Violence against Women", a study of women's health and [[domestic violence]] by surveying over 24,000 women in 10 countries from all regions of the world, which assessed the prevalence and extent of violence against women, particularly violence by intimate partners, and linked this with health outcomes to women as well as documenting strategies and services that women use to cope with intimate-partner violence.&lt;ref name="WHO Multicountry Study" /&gt;
*The 2006 UN Secretary General's "In-depth study on all forms of violence against women", the first comprehensive international document on the issue.&lt;ref name="UN In-depth Study on all Forms of Violence Against Women"&gt;{{cite web |title=In-depth study on all forms of violence against women. Report of the Secretary-General.|url=https://www.un.org/ga/search/view_doc.asp?symbol=A/61/122/Add.1|publisher=United Nations General Assembly|accessdate=2 December 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
*The 2011 Council of Europe [[Convention on preventing and combating violence against women and domestic violence]], which is the second regional legally-binding instrument on violence against women and girls.&lt;ref name="UN Women: Global Norms &amp; Standards"/&gt; 
*In 2013, the [[United Nations Commission on the Status of Women]] (CSW) adopted, by consensus, Agreed Conclusions on the elimination and prevention of all forms of violence against women and girls (formerly, there were no agreed-upon conclusions).&lt;ref name="UN Women: Global Norms &amp; Standards"/&gt;
*Also in 2013, the [[UN General Assembly]] passed its first resolution calling for the protection of [[human rights defender|defenders]] of women's human rights.&lt;ref name="Norway Post"&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.norwaypost.no/index.php/news/latest-news/29260-protection-of-women-human-rights-defenders |title=Protection of Women Human Rights Defenders |publisher=The Norway Post |date=2013-11-30 |accessdate=2014-08-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; The resolution urges states to put in place gender-specific laws and policies for the protection of women's [[human rights defender]]s and to ensure that defenders themselves are involved in the design and implementation of these measures, and calls on states to protect women's human rights defenders from reprisals for cooperating with the UN and to ensure their unhindered access to and communication with international human rights bodies and mechanisms.&lt;ref name="awid.org"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.awid.org/Library/UN-adopts-landmark-resolution-on-Protecting-Women-Human-Rights-Defenders |title=UN adopts landmark resolution on Protecting Women Human Rights Defenders |publisher=AWID |date=2013-11-28 |accessdate=2014-08-06 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140819203819/http://www.awid.org/Library/UN-adopts-landmark-resolution-on-Protecting-Women-Human-Rights-Defenders |archivedate=19 August 2014 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Additionally, on the national level, individual countries have also organized efforts (legally, politically, socially) to prevent, reduce and punish violence against women. As a particular case study, here are some developments since the 1960s in the United States to oppose and treat violence against women:&lt;ref name="USDOJ-History of VAWA"&gt;{{cite web|last=U.S. Department of Justice, Office of Violence Against Women (OVM)|title=The History of the Violence Against Women Act|url=http://www.ovw.usdoj.gov/docs/history-vawa.pdf|publisher=U.S. Department of Justice|accessdate=2 December 2013|deadurl=yes|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20111017204719/http://www.ovw.usdoj.gov/docs/history-vawa.pdf|archivedate=17 October 2011|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
*1967: One of the country's first domestic violence shelters opened in Maine.
*1972: The country's first rape help hotline opened in Washington, D.C.
*1978: Two national coalitions, the National Coalition Against Sexual Assault and the [[National Coalition Against Domestic Violence]], were formed, to raise awareness of these two forms of violence against women.
*1984: The U.S. Attorney General created the Department of Justice Task Force on Family Violence, to address ways in which the criminal justice system and community response to domestic violence should be improved.
*1994: Passage of the [[Violence Against Women Act]] or VAWA, legislation included in the [[Violent Crime Control and Law Enforcement Act]] of 1994, sponsored by then-Senator Joseph Biden, which required a strengthened community response to crimes of domestic violence and sexual assault, strengthened federal penalties for repeat sex offenders and strengthened legislative protection of victims, among many other provisions.
*2000: President Clinton signed into law the VAWA of 2000, further strengthening federal laws, and emphasizing assistance of immigrant victims, elderly victims, victims with disabilities, and victims of dating violence.
*2006: President Bush signed into law the VAWA of 2006, with an emphasis on programs to address violence against youth victims, and establishing programs for Engaging Men and Youth, and Culturally and Linguistically Specific Services.
*2007: The National Teen Dating Abuse Hotline opened.
*2009: President Obama declared April as Sexual Assault Awareness Month.
*2013: President Obama signed into law the VAWA of 2015, which granted Native American tribes the ability to prosecute non-Native offenders, and regulated reports of sexual assault on college campuses.&lt;ref&gt;Kohlman, Cindy. "Inceptia Institute Violence Against Women Act (VAWA) New Reporting Requirements Effective July 1, 2015 – Are You Ready? Inceptia Institute, 9 June 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;"Tribal Justice: Prosecuting Non-Natives for Sexual Assault on Reservations". PBS. 5 September 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;

Other countries have also enacted comparable legislative, political and social instruments to address violence against women. Experts in the international community generally believe, however, that solely enacting punitive legislation for prevention and punishment of violence against women is not sufficient to address the problem. For example, although much stricter laws on violence against women have been passed in Bangladesh, violence against women is still rising.&lt;ref name="VAW: A Global Burden" /&gt; Instead, it is thought that wide societal changes to address gender inequalities and women's empowerment will be the way to reduce violence against women.&lt;ref name="UN In-depth Study on all Forms of Violence Against Women" /&gt;&lt;ref name="VAW: A Global Burden" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Nigeria-Female Hawkers-Interventions"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Fawole|title=Interventions for Violence Prevention among Young Female Hawkers in Motor Parks in South-Western Nigeria: A Review of Effectiveness|journal=African Journal of Reproductive Health|year=2003|pages=71–82|jstor=3583347|volume=7|doi=10.2307/3583347}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="WHO VAM Factsheet"&gt;{{cite web |title=Violence against women|url=http://www.who.int/mediacentre/factsheets/fs239/en/|publisher=WHO|accessdate=2 December 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Effect on society==
[[File:Map3.1NEW Womens Physical Security 2011 compressed.jpg|thumb|A map of the world showing countries by level of women's physical security, 2011]]
According to an article in the [[Health and Human Rights (journal)|Health and Human Rights Journal]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Fried, S. T.|date=2003|title=Violence against Women|journal=[[Health and Human Rights]]|volume=6 | issue = 2 |pages=88–111|jstor=4065431 |doi=10.2307/4065431}}&lt;/ref&gt; regardless of many years of advocacy and involvement of many feminist activist organizations, the issue of violence against women still "remains one of the most pervasive forms of human rights violations worldwide".&lt;ref name="Fried, S. T. 2003 pp.91"&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Fried | first1 = S. T. | year = 2003 | title = Violence against Women | journal = Health and Human Rights | volume = 6 | issue = 2| pages = 88–111 [91] | jstor=4065431 | doi=10.2307/4065431}}&lt;/ref&gt; The violence against women can occur in both public and private spheres of life and at any time of their life span. Violence against women often keeps women from wholly contributing to social, economic, and political development of their communities.&lt;ref name="Fried"/&gt; Many women are terrified by these threats of violence and this essentially influences their lives so that they are impeded to exercise their human rights; for instance, they fear contributing to the development of their communities socially, economically and politically. Apart from that, the causes that trigger VAW or gender-based violence can go beyond just the issue of gender and into the issues of age, class, culture, ethnicity, religion, sexual orientation and specific geographical area of their origins.

Importantly, other than the issue of social divisions, violence can also extend into the realm of health issues and become a direct concern of the public health sector.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Colarossi, L.|date=2005|title=A Response to Danis &amp; Lockhart: What Guides Social Work Knowledge about Violence Against Women? |journal=Journal of Social Work Education|volume=41 | issue = 1 |pages=147–159|jstor=23044038|doi=10.5175/jswe.2005.200400418}}&lt;/ref&gt; A health issue such as [[HIV/AIDS]] is another cause that also leads to violence. Women who have HIV/AIDS infection are also among the targets of the violence.&lt;ref name="Fried, S. T. 2003 pp.91"/&gt; The [[World Health Organization]] reports that violence against women puts an undue burden on health care services, as women who have suffered violence are more likely to need health services and at higher cost, compared to women who have not suffered violence.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.who.int/mediacentre/factsheets/fs239/en/index.html "Violence against women"]. World Health Organization (1 September 2011).&lt;/ref&gt; Another statement that confirms an understanding of VAW as being a significant health issue is apparent in the recommendation adopted by the Council of Europe, violence against women in private sphere, at home or [[domestic violence]], is the main reason of "death and disability" among the women who encountered violence.&lt;ref name="Fried, S. T. 2003 pp.91" /&gt;

In addition, several studies have shown a link between poor treatment of women and international violence. These studies show that one of the best predictors of inter- and intranational violence is the maltreatment of women in the society.&lt;ref&gt;Maffly, Brian (21 March 2009). [http://www.sltrib.com/ci_11967564 "BYU study links women's safety, nation's peace"] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100202080318/http://www.sltrib.com/ci_11967564 |date=2 February 2010 }}. ''The Salt Lake Tribune''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.womanstats.org/images/StearmerEmmettAPSA07.pdf |title=The Great Divide: Revealing Differences in the Islamic World Regarding the Status of Women and its Impact on International Peace |publisher= |date=2007 |accessdate=2014-08-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==WHO's typology table==

{|
|-
!
|}

=== Throughout the life cycle ===
{| class="wikitable"
|-
| '''Phase''' || '''Type of violence'''
|-
|- style="vertical-align: top;"
| Pre-birth || Sex-selective abortion; effects of battering during pregnancy on birth
outcomes
|-
|- style="vertical-align: top;"
| Infancy || Female infanticide; physical, sexual and psychological abuse
|-
|- style="vertical-align: top;"
| Girlhood || Child marriage; female genital mutilation; physical, sexual and
psychological abuse; incest; child prostitution and pornography
|-
|- style="vertical-align: top;"
| Adolescence and adulthood || Dating and courtship violence (e.g. acid throwing and date rape); economically coerced sex (e.g. school girls having sex with "sugar daddies" in return for school fees); incest; sexual abuse in the workplace; rape; sexual harassment; forced prostitution and pornography; trafficking in women; partner violence; marital rape; dowry abuse and murders; partner homicide; psychological abuse; abuse of women with disabilities; forced pregnancy
|-
|- style="vertical-align: top;"
| Elderly || Forced "suicide" or homicide of widows for economic reasons; sexual, 
physical and psychological abuse&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.who.int/gender/violence/v4.pdf |title=Violence against women: Definition and scope of the problem |publisher=World Health Organization |date=June 1997 |accessdate=30 November 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|}

Significant progress towards the protection of women from violence has been made on international level as a product of collective effort of lobbying by many women's rights movements; international organizations to civil society groups. As a result, worldwide governments and international as well as civil society organizations actively work to combat violence against women through a variety of programs. Among the major achievements of the women's rights movements against violence on girls and women, the landmark accomplishments are the "[[Declaration on the Elimination of Violence Against Women]]" that implies "political will towards addressing VAW " and the legal binding agreement, "the Convention on Elimination of all forms of Discrimination Against Women ([[CEDAW]])".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.oxfam.org/sites/www.oxfam.org/files/bn-ending-violence-against-women-action-plan-220213-en.pdf|title=Rosche, D., &amp; Dawe, A. (2013). Ending Violence Against Women: the Case for a Comprehensive International Action Plan. Oxfam Briefing Note, 1, 1-10. |page=2 |publisher=Oxfam |accessdate=29 November 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, the UN General Assembly resolution also designated 25 November as [[International Day for the Elimination of Violence against Women]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.un.org/womenwatch/daw/news/vawd.html |title=International Day for the Elimination of Violence against Women |publisher=United Nations |date= |accessdate=2016-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Another typology: over time ===
[[File:Typology of Violence Against Women over Time.png|thumbnail|300 px|A diagram of typology of violence against women over time, as conceived by authors Charlotte Watts &amp; Cathy Zimmerman.]]

This similar typology from an academic journal article on violence against women shows similarly the different types of violence perpetrated against women according to what time period in a women's life the violence takes place.&lt;ref name="VAM: Global scope &amp; magnitude" /&gt; However, it also classifies the types of violence according to the perpetrator. One important point to note is that more of the types of violence inflicted on women are perpetrated by someone the woman knows, either a family member or intimate partner, rather than a stranger.

==Types==
Violence against women can take a number of forms:

===Rape===
{{main article|Rape}}
Rape is a type of [[sexual assault]], usually involving [[sexual intercourse]]. Rape is usually perpetrated by men against boys, women, and girls; women are usually assaulted more often than boys and girls and usually all by someone they know.

Internationally, the incidence of rapes recorded by the police during 2008 varied between 0.1 in [[Egypt]] per 100,000 people and 91.6 per 100,000 people in [[Lesotho]] with 4.9 per 100,000 people in [[Lithuania]] as the [[median]].&lt;ref name="unodc1"&gt;[http://www.unodc.org/documents/data-and-analysis/Crime-statistics/Sexual_violence_sv_against_children_and_rape.xls "Rape at the National Level, number of police recorded offenses".] [[United Nations Office on Drugs and Crime]].&lt;/ref&gt; According to the [[American Medical Association]] (1995), sexual violence, and rape in particular, is considered the most underreported violent crime.&lt;ref&gt;American Medical Association (1995) Sexual Assault in America. AMA.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="rds.homeoffice.gov.uk"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://rds.homeoffice.gov.uk/rds/pdfs05/hors293.pdf |title=A gap or a chasm? Attrition in reported rape cases |format=PDF |accessdate=2010-12-31 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20110314171826/http://rds.homeoffice.gov.uk/rds/pdfs05/hors293.pdf |archivedate=14 March 2011 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; The rate of reporting, prosecution and convictions for rape varies considerably in different jurisdictions. Rape by strangers is usually less common than rape by persons the victim knows.&lt;ref name="Abbey"&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Abbey | first1 = A. | last2 = BeShears | first2 = R. | last3 = Clinton-Sherrod | first3 = A. M. | last4 = McAuslan | first4 = P. | year = 2004 | title = Similarities and differences in women's sexual assault experiences based on tactics used by the perpetrator | url = http://www.hawaii.edu/hivandaids/Similarities_And_Differences_In_Women_s_Sexual_Assault_Experiences_Based_On_Tactics.pdf | format = PDF | journal = Psychology of Women Quarterly | volume = 28 | issue = | pages = 323–332 | doi = 10.1111/j.1471-6402.2004.00149.x | deadurl = yes | archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20130108020408/http://www.hawaii.edu/hivandaids/Similarities_And_Differences_In_Women_s_Sexual_Assault_Experiences_Based_On_Tactics.pdf | archivedate = 8 January 2013 | df = dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=rainn&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rainn.org/statistics/|title=Statistics |publisher=Rape, Abuse &amp; Incest National Network |accessdate=2008-01-01}}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="ncjrs.gov"&gt;Alberto R. Gonzales et al. [http://www.ncjrs.gov/pdffiles1/nij/210346.pdf Extent, Nature, and Consequences of Rape Victimization: Findings From the National Violence Against Women Survey]. U.S. Department of Justice Office of Justice Programs. January 2006&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Australia"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.abs.gov.au/ausstats/abs@.nsf/mf/4523.0 |title=Sexual Assault in Australia: A Statistical Overview, 2004|publisher=Abs.gov.au |date=2006-12-08 |accessdate=2010-12-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="UK"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://rds.homeoffice.gov.uk/rds/pdfs2/r159.pdf |title=Rape and sexual assault of women: findings from the British Crime Survey |format=PDF |accessdate=2010-12-31 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20110218135832/http://rds.homeoffice.gov.uk/rds/pdfs2/r159.pdf |archivedate=18 February 2011 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Victims of rape can be severely [[Psychological trauma|traumatized]] and may suffer from [[posttraumatic stress disorder]];&lt;ref name="aaets"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aaets.org/article178.htm |title=Post Traumatic Stress Disorder in Rape Survivors |publisher=The American Academy of Experts in Traumatic Stress |year=1995 |accessdate=2013-04-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; in addition to psychological harm resulting from the act, rape may cause physical injury, or have additional effects on the victim, such as acquiring of a [[sexually transmitted infection]] or becoming [[pregnant]].

====Violence against victims====
Following a rape, a victim may face violence or threats of violence from the rapist, and, in many cultures, from the victim's own family and relatives. Violence or intimidation of the victim may be perpetrated by the rapist or by friends and relatives of the rapist, as a way of preventing the victims from reporting the rape, of punishing them for reporting it, or of forcing them to withdraw the complaint; or it may be perpetrated by the relatives of the victim as a punishment for "bringing shame" to the family. This is especially the case in cultures where female [[virginity]] is highly valued and considered mandatory before marriage; in extreme cases, rape victims are killed in [[honor killings]]. Victims may also be forced by their families to marry the rapist in order to restore the family's "honor".&lt;ref name="zeenews.india"&gt;{{cite news | agency=[[Press Trust of India]] | title = Rape victim threatened to withdraw case in UP | url = http://zeenews.india.com/news/uttar-pradesh/rape-victim-threatened-to-withdraw-case-in-up_694364.html | publisher = zeenews.india.com | date = 19 March 2011 | accessdate = 3 February 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="wisemuslimwomen"&gt;{{cite news | title = Stigmatization of rape &amp; honor killings | url = http://www.wisemuslimwomen.org/currentissues/stigmitizationofrape/ | publisher = [[Women's Islamic Initiative in Spirituality and Equality|WISE Muslim Women]] | date = 31 January 2002 | accessdate = 3 February 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="bbc2011"&gt;{{cite news | last = Harter | first = Pascale | title = Libya rape victims 'face honour killings' | url = http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-africa-13760895 | publisher = [[BBC News]] | date=14 June 2011 |accessdate= 3 February 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | title = Morocco protest after raped Amina Filali kills herself | url = http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-africa-17379721 | publisher = [[BBC News]] | date = 15 March 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In Lebanon, the [[Campaign Against Lebanese Rape Law - Article 522]] was launched in December 2016 to abolish the article that permitted a rapist to escape prison by marrying his victim.

===Marital rape===
{{Main article|Marital rape}}
Marital rape, also known as spousal rape, is non-consensual sex perpetrated by the victim's spouse. Once widely condoned or ignored by law, spousal rape is now repudiated by international conventions and increasingly criminalized. Still, in many countries, spousal rape either remains legal, or is illegal but widely tolerated and accepted as a husband's prerogative. The criminalization of marital rape is recent, having occurred during the past few decades. Traditional understanding and views of [[marriage]], [[rape]], [[sexuality]], [[gender roles]] and [[self determination]] have started to be challenged in most Western countries during the 1960s and 1970s, which has led to the subsequent criminalization of marital rape during the following decades. With a few notable exceptions, it was during the past 30 years when most laws against marital rape have been enacted. Some countries in Scandinavia and in the former Communist Bloc of Europe made spousal rape illegal before 1970, but most Western countries criminalized it only in the 1980s and 1990s. In many parts of the world the laws against marital rape are very new, having been enacted in the 2000s.

In [[Canada]], marital rape was made illegal in 1983, when several legal changes were made, including changing the rape statute to ''sexual assault'', and making the laws gender neutral.&lt;ref name=grady&gt;O'Grady William (2011). Crime in Canadian Context: debates and controversies. Oxford University Press {{ISBN|0195433785}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.statcan.gc.ca/pub/85f0033m/85f0033m2008019-eng.pdf |title=Canadian Centre for Justice Statistics Profile Series |format=PDF |publisher=Statistics Canada |date=2010-05-17 |accessdate=2014-08-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sexualityandu.ca/uploads/files/SexualAssault-OCT2011-ENG.pdf |title=Sexual Assault in Canada: What Do We Know? |publisher=The Sex Information and Education Council of Canada |accessdate=2014-08-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Republic of Ireland|Ireland]] spousal rape was outlawed in 1990.&lt;ref name="Temkin86"&gt;Jennifer Temkin, ''Rape and the legal process'', Oxford University Press, 2002 {{ISBN|0198763549}}, p. 86.&lt;/ref&gt;
In the US, the criminalization of marital rape started in the mid-1970s and in 1993 North Carolina became the last state to make marital rape illegal.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://news.google.com/newspapers?nid=1957&amp;dat=19930702&amp;id=_xYxAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=UOEFAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=6288,228462 |title=N.C. the last state to outlaw marital rape |newspaper=The Daily Gazette |date=2 July 1993 |accessdate=2014-08-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;
In [[England and Wales]], marital rape was made illegal in 1991. The views of Sir Matthew Hale, a 17th-century jurist, published in ''The History of the Pleas of the Crown'' (1736), stated that a husband cannot be guilty of the rape of his wife because the wife "hath given up herself in this kind to her husband, which she cannot retract"; in England and Wales this would remain law for more than 250 years, until it was abolished by the [[Appellate Committee of the House of Lords]], in the case of ''R v R'' in 1991.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bailii.org/uk/cases/UKHL/1991/12.html |title=R v R [1991&amp;#93; UKHL 12 (23 October 1991) |publisher=British and Irish Legal Information Institute |accessdate=2014-08-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the [[Netherlands]] marital rape was also made illegal in 1991.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Zeegers |first=Nicolle |url=http://www.bjutijdschriften.nl/tijdschrift/rem/2012/1/ReM_2212-2508_2012_002_001_005.pdf |title=What Epistemology Would Serve Criminal Law Best in Finding the Truth about Rape? |publisher= |accessdate=2014-08-06 }}{{dead link|date=September 2017 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt; One of the last Western countries to criminalize marital rape was [[Germany]], in 1997.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Kieler |first=Marita |url=http://www.jurawelt.com/sunrise/media/mediafiles/13792/tenea_juraweltbd52_kieler.pdf |title=Tatbestandsprobleme der sexuellen Nötigung, Vergewaltigung sowie des sexuellen Mißbrauchs widerstandsunfähiger Personen |publisher=Tenea |accessdate=2014-08-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The relation between some religions ([[Christianity]] and [[Islam]]) and marital rape is controversial. The [[Bible]] at 1 Corinthians 7:3-5 explains that one has a "conjugal duty" to have sexual relations with one's spouse (in sharp opposition to [[sex outside marriage]], which is considered a [[sin]]) and states, "The wife does not have authority over her own body, but the husband does. And likewise the husband does not have authority over his own body, but the wife does. Do not deprive one another..."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=1+corinthians%207:3-7:5&amp;version=NKJV |title=1 corinthians 7:3-7:5 NKJV |publisher=Bible Gateway |accessdate=2014-08-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some conservative religious figures interpret this as rejecting to possibility of marital rape.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.adn.com/2011/07/22/1980301/readers-blast-valley-paper-over.html |title=Valley paper criticized over pastor's column on spousal rape |publisher=Alaska Dispatch |date=2011-07-22 |accessdate=2014-08-06 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131029203959/http://www.adn.com/2011/07/22/1980301/readers-blast-valley-paper-over.html |archivedate=29 October 2013 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; Islam makes reference to sexual relations in marriage too, notably: "Allah's Apostle said, 'If a husband calls his wife to his bed (i.e. to have sexual relation) and she refuses and causes him to sleep in anger, the angels will curse her till morning';"&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sacred-texts.com/isl/bukhari/bh4/bh4_464.htm |title=Hadith 4:460 |publisher=Sacred-texts.com |accessdate=2014-08-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; and several comments on the issue of marital rape made by Muslim religious leaders have been criticized.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Josh Halliday |url=https://www.theguardian.com/media/2010/nov/08/islam-channel-ofcom |title=Islam Channel censured by Ofcom |publisher=The Guardian |date=8 November 2010 |accessdate=2014-08-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/asia-pacific/7843909.stm | publisher=BBC News | title=Cleric 'must deny' views on rape | date=22 January 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Domestic violence===
[[File:Anti-domestic violence sign in Liberia panoramio (193).jpg|thumb|Anti-domestic violence sign in [[Liberia]]]]
{{main article|Domestic violence}}
Women are more likely to be [[victimized]] by someone that they are intimate with, commonly called "[[intimate partner violence]]" or (IPV). Instances of IPV tend not to be reported to police and thus many experts believe that the true magnitude of the problem is hard to estimate.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Intimate partner violence: overview | url = https://www.cdc.gov/ncipc/factsheets/ipvfacts.htm | archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20070211183916/http://www.cdc.gov/ncipc/factsheets/ipvfacts.htm | archive-date = 11 February 2007 | publisher = [[Centers for Disease Control and Prevention]] | date = 2006 | accessdate = 4 September 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; Women are much more likely than men to be [[murdered]] by an intimate partner. In the United States, in 2005, 1181 women, in comparison with 329 men, were killed by their intimate partners.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Injury prevention &amp; control: division of violence prevention: Intimate partner violence: consequences | url = https://www.cdc.gov/violencePrevention/intimatepartnerviolence/consequences.html | publisher = [[Centers for Disease Control and Prevention]] }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Wheel gallery | url = http://www.theduluthmodel.org/wheelgallery.php | archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20110728093413/http://www.theduluthmodel.org/wheelgallery.php | archive-date = 28 July 2011 | publisher=The Duluth Model}}&lt;/ref&gt; In [[England and Wales]] about 100 women are killed by partners or former partners each year while 21 men were killed in 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-13058300 |title=All domestic abuse deaths to have multi-agency review |date=13 April 2011 | publisher = [[BBC news]] |accessdate=14 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2008, in [[France]], 156 women in comparison with 27 men were killed by their intimate partner.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | title = L'action du ministère dans le cadre des violences au sein du couple / Aide aux victimes: présentation des différents dispositifs | url = http://www.interieur.gouv.fr/sections/a_votre_service/aide_aux_victimes/violence-couple/downloadFile/attachedFile/morts_violentes_au_sein_couples.pdf | format = PDF | language = French | publisher = [[Minister of the Interior (France)|Ministère de l'Intérieur]] | accessdate = 6 August 2014 | deadurl = yes | archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20120320014223/http://www.interieur.gouv.fr/sections/a_votre_service/aide_aux_victimes/violence-couple/downloadFile/attachedFile/morts_violentes_au_sein_couples.pdf | archivedate = 20 March 2012 | df = dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to WHO, globally, as many as 38% of murders of women are committed by an intimate partner.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author-link = World Health Organization |url=http://www.who.int/mediacentre/factsheets/fs239/en/ |title=Violence against women | publisher= [[World Health Organization]] | accessdate = 6 August 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt; A UN report compiled from a number of different studies conducted in at least 71 countries found domestic violence against women to be most prevalent in [[Ethiopia]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | title = Ethiopian women are most abused | url = http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/6040180.stm | publisher = [[BBC News]] | date = 11 October 2006 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Western Europe, a country that has received major international criticism for the way it has dealt legally with the issue of violence against women is [[Finland]]; with authors pointing that a high level of equality for women in the public sphere (as in Finland) should never be equated with equality in all other aspects of women's lives.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | last = Clarke | first = Kris | title = The paradoxical approach to intimate partner violence in Finland | journal = [[Tokiwa University#Publications|International Perspectives in Victimology]] | volume = 6 | issue = 1 | pages = 9–19 | publisher = [[Tokiwa University]] via [[California State University|The Press at California State University]] | doi = 10.5364/ipiv.6.1.19 | date = August 2011 | ref = harv }} [https://www.academia.edu/992154/The_Paradoxical_Approach_to_Intimate_Partner_Violence_in_Finland Available through academia.edu.]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=McKie |first1=Linda |last2=Hearn |first2=Jeff |title=Gender-neutrality and gender equality: comparing and contrasting policy responses to 'domestic violence' in Finland and Scotland |journal=[[Scottish Affairs]] |volume=48 |issue=1 |pages=85–107 |publisher=[[Edinburgh University Press]] |doi=10.3366/scot.2004.0043 |date=August 2004 |ref=harv }} [https://web.archive.org/web/20131021023708/http://www.scottishaffairs.org/backiss/pdfs/sa48/sa48_McKie_and_Hearn.pdf Pdf.]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite report |date=September 2008 |title=Case Closed: Rape and Human Rights in the Nordic Countries |publisher=Amnesty International |url=https://amnesty.dk/media/1557/case-closed.pdf | pages = 89–91 | quote = Finland is repeatedly reminded of its widespread problem of violence against women and recommended to take more efficient measures to deal with the situation. International criticism concentrates on the lack of measures to combat violence against women in general and in particular on the lack of a national action plan to combat such violence and on the lack of legislation on domestic violence. (...) Compared to Sweden, Finland has been slower to reform legislation on violence against women. In Sweden, domestic violence was already illegal in 1864, while in Finland such violence was not outlawed until 1970, over a hundred years later. In Sweden the punishment of victims of incest was abolished in 1937, but not until 1971 in Finland. Rape within marriage was criminalised in Sweden in 1962, but the equivalent Finnish legislation only came into force in 1994 – making Finland one of the last European countries to criminalise marital rape. In addition, assaults taking place on private property did not become impeachable offences in Finland until 1995. Only in 1997 did victims of sexual offences and domestic violence in Finland become entitled to government-funded counselling and support services for the duration of their court cases. | ref = harv | postscript = .}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A study by [[Pan American Health Organization]] conducted in 12 [[Latin American]] countries found the highest prevalence of domestic violence against women to be in [[Bolivia]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last1 = Bott | first1 = Sarah | last2 = Guedes | first2 = Alessandra | last3 = Goodwin | first3 = Mary | last4 = Mendoza | first4 = Jennifer Adams | title = Violence against women in Latin America and the Caribbean: a comparative analysis of population-based data from 12 countries | url = http://www.paho.org/Hq/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=8175%3A2013-violence-against-women-latin-america-caribbean-comparative-analysis&amp;catid=1505%3Aabout-us&amp;lang=en | publisher = [[Centers for Disease Control and Prevention]] and the [[Pan American Health Organization]] | date = 2012 }} [http://www1.paho.org/hq/dmdocuments/violence-against-women-lac.pdf English pdf.] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160204013306/http://www1.paho.org/hq/dmdocuments/violence-against-women-lac.pdf |date=4 February 2016 }} [http://www.paho.org/Hq/index.php?option=com_docman&amp;task=doc_download&amp;gid=24353&amp;Itemid=270&amp;lang=en Spanish pdf.] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150408155433/http://www.paho.org/Hq/index.php?option=com_docman&amp;task=doc_download&amp;gid=24353&amp;Itemid=270&amp;lang=en |date=8 April 2015 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Though this form of violence is often portrayed as an issue within the context of heterosexual relationships, it also occurs in lesbian relationships,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | last = Girshick | first = Lori B. | title = No sugar, no spice: reflections on research on woman-to-woman sexual violence | journal = [[Violence Against Women (journal)|Violence Against Women]] | volume = 8 | issue = 12 | pages = 1500–1520 | publisher = [[Sage Publications|Sage]] | doi = 10.1177/107780102237967 | date = December 2002 | ref = harv }}&lt;/ref&gt; daughter-mother relationships, [[roommate]] relationships and other domestic relationships involving two women. Violence against women in lesbian relationships is about as common as violence against women in heterosexual relationships.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last = Rose | first = Suzana | title = Lesbian partner violence fact sheet | url = http://www.musc.edu/vawprevention/lesbianrx/factsheet.shtml | publisher = [[Medical University of South Carolina]] }}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Diagnosis planning====
The [[American Psychiatric Association]] planning and research committees for the forthcoming [[DSM-5]] (2013) have canvassed a series of new [[Relational disorder]]s, which include ''Marital Conflict Disorder Without Violence'' or ''Marital Abuse Disorder (Marital Conflict Disorder With Violence)''.&lt;ref name="Personality"&gt;{{cite book| last1 = First | first1 = Michael B. | last2 = Bell | first2 = Carl C. | last3 = Cuthbert | first3 = Bruce | last4 = Krystal | first4 = John H. | last5 = Malison | first5 = Robert | last6 = Offord | first6 = David R. | last7 = Reiss | first7 = David | last8 = Shea | first8 = M. Tracie | last9 = Widger | first9 = Tom | last10 = Wisner | first10 = Katherine L. | chapter = Personality disorders and relational disorders: a research agenda for addressing crucial gaps in DSM | editor-last1 = Kupfer | editor-first1 = David J. | editor-last2 = First | editor-first2 = Michael B. | editor-last3 = Regier | editor-first3 = Darrel A. | title = A research agenda for DSM-V | publisher = [[American Psychiatric Association]] | location = Washington, D.C. | year = 2002 | isbn = 9780890422922 | ref = harv | postscript = .}} [https://contextualscience.org/system/files/Kupfer,2002.pdf Pdf.]&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|164, 166}} Couples with marital disorders sometimes come to clinical attention because the couple recognize long-standing dissatisfaction with their marriage and come to the [[clinician]] on their own initiative or are referred by an astute health care professional. Secondly, there is serious violence in the marriage that is -"usually the husband battering the wife".&lt;ref name="Personality" /&gt;{{rp|163}} In these cases the emergency room or a legal authority often is the first to notify the [[clinician]]. Most importantly, marital violence "is a major risk factor for serious injury and even death and women in violent marriages are at much greater risk of being seriously injured or killed ([[National Advisory Council on Violence Against Women]] 2000)".&lt;ref name="Personality" /&gt;{{rp|166}} The authors of this study add, "There is current considerable controversy over whether male-to-female marital violence is best regarded as a reflection of male [[psychopathology]] and control or whether there is an empirical base and clinical utility for conceptualizing these patterns as relational."&lt;ref name="Personality" /&gt;{{rp|166}}

Recommendations for clinicians making a diagnosis of ''Marital Relational Disorder'' should include the assessment of actual or "potential" male violence as regularly as they assess the potential for suicide in depressed patients. Further, "clinicians should not relax their vigilance after a battered wife leaves her husband, because some data suggest that the period immediately following a marital separation is the period of greatest risk for the women. Many men will [[stalking|stalk]] and [[battery (crime)|batter]] their wives in an effort to get them to return or punish them for leaving. Initial assessments of the potential for violence in a marriage can be supplemented by standardized interviews and questionnaires, which have been reliable and valid aids in exploring marital violence more systematically."&lt;ref name="Personality" /&gt;{{rp|166}}
 
The authors conclude with what they call "very recent information"&lt;ref name="Personality" /&gt;{{rp|167, 168}} on the course of violent marriages, which suggests that "over time a husband's battering may abate somewhat, but perhaps because he has successfully [[intimidate]]d his wife. The risk of violence remains strong in a marriage in which it has been a feature in the past. Thus, treatment is essential here; the clinician cannot just wait and watch."&lt;ref name="Personality" /&gt;{{rp|167, 168}} The most urgent clinical priority is the protection of the wife because she is the one most frequently at risk, and clinicians must be aware that supporting assertiveness by a battered wife may lead to more beatings or even death.&lt;ref name="Personality" /&gt;{{rp|167, 168}}

====Honor killings====
[[Honor killings]] are a common form of violence against women in certain parts of the world. In honor killings, women and girls are killed by family members (usually husbands, fathers, uncles or brothers) because the women are believed to have brought shame or dishonor upon the family. These killings are a traditional practice, believed to have originated from tribal customs where an allegation against a woman can be enough to defile a family's reputation.&lt;ref name="BBC_ethics"&gt;{{cite news | title = Ethics guide: honour crimes |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/ethics/honourcrimes/crimesofhonour_1.shtml | publisher = BBC }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = honor killing (definition) | url = http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/honor%20killing | publisher = [[Merriam-Webster]] }}&lt;/ref&gt; Women are killed for reasons such as refusing to enter an [[arranged marriage]], being in a relationship that is disapproved by their relatives, attempting to leave a marriage, having sex outside marriage, becoming the victim of rape, dressing in ways that are deemed inappropriate.&lt;ref name="BBC_ethics" /&gt;&lt;ref name="bbc.co.uk"&gt;{{cite news | last = Harter | first = Pascale | url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-africa-13760895 | publisher= [[BBC News]] | title=Libya rape victims 'face honour killings' | date=14 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Honor killings are common in countries such as Afghanistan, Egypt, Iraq, Jordan, Lebanon, Libya, Morocco, Pakistan, Saudi Arabia, Syria, Turkey, Yemen.&lt;ref name="bbc.co.uk"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | title = Working towards the elimination of crimes against women committed in the name of honour | url = https://www.un.org/womenwatch/daw/vaw/v-work-ga.htm | id = A/57/169 | publisher = [[United Nations General Assembly]] | date = July 2002 }} [http://daccess-ods.un.org/access.nsf/Get?Open&amp;DS=A/57/169&amp;Lang=A Arabic pdf.] [http://daccess-ods.un.org/access.nsf/Get?Open&amp;DS=A/57/169&amp;Lang=C Chinese pdf.] [http://daccess-ods.un.org/access.nsf/Get?Open&amp;DS=A/57/169&amp;Lang=E English pdf.] [http://daccess-ods.un.org/access.nsf/Get?Open&amp;DS=A/57/169&amp;Lang=F French pdf.] [http://daccess-ods.un.org/access.nsf/Get?Open&amp;DS=A/57/169&amp;Lang=R Russian pdf.] [http://daccess-ods.un.org/access.nsf/Get?Open&amp;DS=A/57/169&amp;Lang=S Spanish pdf.]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | last = Ghanizada | title = 240 cases of honor killing recorded in Afghanistan, AIHRC | url = http://www.khaama.com/240-cases-of-honor-killing-recorded-in-afghanistan-aihrc-2177 | publisher = [[Khaama Press]] | location = Afghanistan | date = 9 June 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |agency=[[United Press International]] | title = AIHRC: 400 rape, honor killings registered in Afghanistan in 2 years | url = http://latinbusinesstoday.com/2013/06/aihrc-400-rape-honor-killings-registered-in-afghanistan-in-2-years/ | archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20150214224858/http://latinbusinesstoday.com/2013/06/aihrc-400-rape-honor-killings-registered-in-afghanistan-in-2-years/ | archive-date = 14 February 2015 | publisher = Latin Business Today | location = Kabul, Afghanistan | date = 10 June 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | last1 = Bayoumy | first1 = Yara | last2 = Kami | first2 = Aseel | title="Honor killings" require tougher laws, say Iraqi women | url=https://www.reuters.com/article/2012/03/06/us-iraq-women-idUSTRE82510920120306 | publisher = [[Reuters]] | date=6 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Honor killings also occur in immigrant communities in Europe, the United States and Canada. Although honor killings are most often associated with the Middle East and South Asia, they occur in other parts of the world too.&lt;ref name="BBC_ethics" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = International Domestic Violence Issues | url = http://www.sanctuaryforfamilies.org/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=252&amp;Itemid=259 | archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20141016194204/http://www.sanctuaryforfamilies.org/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=252&amp;Itemid=259 | archive-date = 16 October 2014 | publisher = Sanctuary for Families }}&lt;/ref&gt; In India, honor killings occur in the northern regions of the country, especially in the states of Punjab, Haryana, Bihar, Uttar Pradesh, Rajasthan, Jharkhand, Himachal Pradesh and Madhya Pradesh.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | last1 = Donald | first1 = Alice | last2 = Bishop | first2 = Hilary | title = World agenda: what justice? | url = http://www.bbc.co.uk/worldservice/specials/1817_wawryw/page4.shtml | publisher = [[BBC World Service]] }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | title = India court seeks 'honour killing' response | url = http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/10364986 | publisher = [[BBC News]] |date = 21 June 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In Turkey, honor killings are a serious problem in Southeastern Anatolia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | last = Rainsford | first = Sarah | title = 'Honour' crime defiance in Turkey | url = http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/4357158.stm | publisher = [[BBC News]] | date = 19 October 2005 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Kardam | first = Filiz | editor-last = Murray | editor-first = Genevra | title = The dynamics of honor killings in Turkey: prospects for action | url = http://www.unfpa.org/publications/dynamics-honour-killings-turkey | publisher = [[United Nations Development Programme]], Population Association (Turkey) and [[United Nations Population Fund]] | date = 2005 }} [http://www.unfpa.org/upload/lib_pub_file/676_filename_honourkillings.pdf Pdf.]&lt;/ref&gt;

====Dowry violence====
[[Image:Say no to dowry.jpg|thumb|upright|Anti-dowry poster in [[Bangalore, India]]]]

The custom of [[dowry]], which is common in South Asia, especially in India, is the trigger of many forms of violence against women. [[Bride burning]] is a form of violence against women in which a bride is killed at home by her husband or husband's family due to his dissatisfaction over the dowry provided by her family. [[Dowry death]] refers to the phenomenon of women and girls being killed or committing [[suicide]] due to disputes regarding dowry. Dowry violence is common in India, Pakistan, Bangladesh and Nepal. In India, in 2011 alone, the National Crime Records Bureau reported 8,618 dowry deaths, while unofficial figures suggest the numbers to be at least three times higher.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Confronting dowry-related violence in India: women at the center of justice | url = http://www.unwomen.org/en/news/stories/2012/12/confronting-dowry-related-violence-in-india-women-at-the-center-of-justice | publisher = [[UN Women]] | date = 24 December 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Forced marriage====
[[File:Oskar Shmerling. Free love (Forced marriage). Molla Nasreddin.jpg|thumb|220px|left|Criticism of the [[Azerbaijani people|Azeri]] custom of [[forced marriage]], as depicted in the early 20th-century satirical periodical [[Molla Nasraddin (magazine)|Molla Nasraddin]]]]
A [[forced marriage]] is a marriage in which one or both of the parties is married against their will. Forced marriages are common in South Asia, the Middle East and Africa. The customs of [[bride price]] and [[dowry]], that exist in many parts of the world, contribute to this practice. A forced marriage is also often the result of a dispute between families, where the dispute is 'resolved' by giving a female from one family to the other.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/ethics/slavery/modern/modern_1.shtml#section_2 Ethics – Slavery: Modern slavery]. BBC. Retrieved on 5 September 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ohchr.org/Documents/HRBodies/HRCouncil/RegularSession/Session21/A-HRC-21-41_en.pdf Report of the Special Rapporteur on contemporary forms of slavery, including its causes and consequences, Gulnara Shahinian]. United Nations. Human Rights Council Twenty-first session. 10 July 2012&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.undp.org.fj/pdf/unp/evaw.pdf |title=Archived copy |accessdate=8 July 2011 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110708174234/http://www.undp.org.fj/pdf/unp/evaw.pdf |archivedate=8 July 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The custom of [[bride kidnapping]] continues to exist in some Central Asian countries such as Kyrgyzstan, Kazakhstan, Uzbekistan, and the Caucasus, or parts of Africa, especially Ethiopia. A girl or a woman is abducted by the would be groom, who is often helped by his friends. The victim is often raped by the would be groom, after which he may try to negotiate a bride price with the village elders to legitimize the marriage.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/371944.stm | publisher=BBC News | title=Ethiopia: Revenge of the abducted bride | date=18 June 1999}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.irinnews.org/report/69993/ethiopia-surviving-forced-marriage |title=Ethiopia: Surviving forced marriage |publisher=[[IRIN]] |date=2007-02-23 |accessdate=2016-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.pathfinder.org/publications-tools/pdfs/Causes-and-Consequesnces-of-Early-Marriage-in-the-Amhara-Region-of-Ethiopia.pdf |format=PDF |title=Report on Causes and Consequences of Early Marriage in Amhara Region |publisher=Pathfinder.org |accessdate=2016-04-03 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130323124732/http://www.pathfinder.org/publications-tools/pdfs/Causes-and-Consequesnces-of-Early-Marriage-in-the-Amhara-Region-of-Ethiopia.pdf |archivedate=23 March 2013 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Force-feeding====
In some countries, notably Mauritania, young girls are forcibly fattened to prepare them for marriage, because obesity is seen as desirable. This practice of [[force-feeding]] is known as ''[[leblouh]]'' or ''gavage''.&lt;ref&gt;Popenoe, Rebecca. 2004. Feeding Desire: Fatness, Beauty, and Sexuality among a Saharan People. New York: Routledge. {{ISBN|978-0415280969}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.savagemind.org/tag/body/ |title=body |publisher=Savage Mind body &amp;#124; An outsider's ethnographic blog on Toronto and beyond |date=2012-08-03 |accessdate=2016-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;LaFraniere, Sharon. [https://www.nytimes.com/2007/07/04/world/africa/04mauritania.html "In Mauritania, Seeking to End an Overfed Ideal"], ''[[The New York Times]]'', 4 July 2007. retrieved 30 June 2011.
*"Girls as young as 5 and as old as 19 had to drink up to five gallons of fat-rich camel's or cow's milk daily, aiming for silvery stretch marks on their upper arms. If a girl refused or vomited, the village weight-gain specialist might squeeze her foot between sticks, pull her ear, pinch her inner thigh, bend her finger backward or force her to drink her own vomit. In extreme cases, girls die, due to a burst stomach. The practice was known as gavage, a French term for force-feeding geese to obtain foie gras."&lt;/ref&gt;

The practice goes back to the 11th century, and has been reported to have made a significant comeback after a [[2008 Mauritanian coup d'état|military junta took over the country in 2008]].&lt;ref&gt;Smith, Alex Duval. [https://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/mar/01/mauritania-force-feeding-marriage "Girls being force-fed for marriage as junta revives fattening farms"], ''The Observer'', 1 March 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Abuse related to son-preference====
[[File:2011 Census sex ratio map for the states and Union Territories of India Boys to Girls 0 to 1 age group.svg|thumb|250px|left|A map of [[India]]'s child sex ratio, 2011.]]
[[File:2012 Birth Sex Ratio World Map.jpg|thumb|250px|World map of birth sex ratios, 2012]]
[[File:Chinese anti infanticide tract from 1800.jpg|thumb|right|250px|Chinese anti-infanticide tract circa 1800. China has a long history of son preference, which was aggravated after the enforcement of the [[one child policy]].]]
''Son preference'' is a custom rooted in gender inequality that is prevalent in many countries and found across religions and classes.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.stopvaw.org/harmful_practices_son_preference&lt;/ref&gt; Although preference for a specific sex of the child may be common in an abstract way in many cultures, when such preference is so strong as to lead to the rejection of the child or to violence against the mother, this crosses the line into [[domestic violence]], [[child abuse]] and violence against women. Such forms of son preference are common especially in parts of [[South Asia]], [[East Asia]] and the [[Caucasus]]. Manifestations of such practices include [[sex selective abortion]], [[female infanticide]], [[child abandonment|female child abandonment]], as well as favoring sons with regard to allocating of family resources.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.stopvaw.org/harmful_practices_son_preference&lt;/ref&gt;

[[China]] and [[India]] have a very strong son preference. In China, the [[one child policy]] was largely responsible for an unbalanced sex ratio. Sex-selective abortion, as well as rejection of girl children is common. [[The Dying Rooms]] is a 1995 [[television]] [[documentary film]] about Chinese state orphanages, which documented how parents abandoned their newborn girls into [[orphanages]], where the staff would leave the children in rooms to die of thirst, or starvation.
Another manifestation of son preference is the violence inflicted against mothers who give birth to girls.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.bbc.com/news/world-asia-16787534&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt;http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/city/bareilly/23-year-old-woman-killed-for-giving-birth-to-twin-daughters/articleshow/57785767.cms&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.deccanchronicle.com/131127/news-world/article/56-killed-giving-birth-girl-child-pakistan&lt;/ref&gt;

===Acid throwing===
[[File:Acid attack victim.jpg|left|Acid attack victim in [[Cambodia]]|thumb|250px]]
[[Acid throwing]], also called acid attack, or vitriolage, is defined as the act of throwing acid onto the body of a person "with the intention of injuring or disfiguring [them] out of jealousy or revenge".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | author=Vij, Krishan | title=Textbook of Forensic Medicine and Toxicology : Principles and Practice | year=2003 | page=462 |publisher=Elsevier India |edition=5th | isbn=978-81-312-2684-1 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The most common types of acid used in these attacks are sulfuric, nitric, or hydrochloric acid.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://cgi.unc.edu/uploads/media_items/it-was-like-burning-in-hell-a-comparative-exploration-of-acid-attack-violence.original.pdf |format=PDF |title=Center for Global Initiatives : Carolina Papers on International Health |publisher=University of North Carolina |accessdate=2016-04-03 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130123191359/http://cgi.unc.edu/uploads/media_items/it-was-like-burning-in-hell-a-comparative-exploration-of-acid-attack-violence.original.pdf |archivedate=23 January 2013 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; Perpetrators of these attacks throw [[acid]] at their victims, usually at their faces, burning them, and damaging [[skin]] tissue, often exposing and sometimes dissolving the bones.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news
 | last = Swanson
 | first = Jordan
 | date = Spring 2002
 | title = Acid attacks: Bangladesh's efforts to stop the violence.
 | periodical = Harvard Health Policy Review
 | page = 3
 | number = 1
 | volume = 3
 | url = http://www.hcs.harvard.edu/~epihc/currentissue/spring2002/swanson.php
 | accessdate =2008-06-18
 | postscript = &lt;!--None--&gt;
}}&lt;/ref&gt; The long term consequences of these attacks include [[blindness]] and permanent [[scarring]] of the face and body.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://archives.cnn.com/2000/ASIANOW/south/11/11/bangladesh.acid.ap/index.html |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070922210725/http://archives.cnn.com/2000/ASIANOW/south/11/11/bangladesh.acid.ap/index.html |archivedate=2007-09-22 |title= Bangladesh combats an acid onslaught against women |publisher=CNN|date=2000-11-12 |accessdate=2016-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |author1=Bahl, Taru |author2=M. H. Syed |lastauthoramp=yes | title=Encyclopaedia of the Muslim World | year=2004 | publisher=Anmol Publications PVT. LTD | isbn=978-81-261-1419-1 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Women and girls are the victims in 75-80% of cases.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/magazine-23631395 | publisher=BBC News | title=How many acid attacks are there? | date=9 August 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Acid attacks are often connected to domestic disputes, including dowry disputes, and refusal of a proposition for marriage, or of sexual advances. Such attacks are common in South Asia, in countries such as Bangladesh, Pakistan, India; and in Southeast Asia, especially in Cambodia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.newstatesman.com/world-affairs/2012/11/acid-attacks-pakistan-sorry-litany-male-egotism |title=Acid attacks in Pakistan: A sorry litany of male egotism |publisher=Newstatesman.com |accessdate=2013-09-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.ca/2012/08/28/nikolas-stefanatos-quebec-acid-attack_n_1838232.html |title=Longueuil Woman Burned And In Coma After Acid Attack |publisher=Huffingtonpost.ca |accessdate=2013-09-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2012/11/28/nurbanu-acid-attack_n_2206621.html |title=Nurbanu, Bangladeshi Woman, Forced To Return To Husband After Acid Attack |publisher=The Huffington Post |accessdate=2013-09-08 |first=Cosima |last=Ungaro |date=28 November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | last =Scholte| first =Marianne| title =Acid Attacks in Bangladesh: A Voice for the Victims| publisher = [[Spiegel Online]]| date = 2006-03-17| url =http://www.spiegel.de/international/0,1518,406485,00.html| accessdate =2008-03-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www2.ohchr.org/english/bodies/cedaw/docs/cedaw_crc_contributions/AvonGlobalCenterforWomenandJustice.pdf |format=PDF |title=Combating Acid Violence in Bangladesh, India, and Cambodia |publisher=[[Office of the United Nations High Commissioner for Human Rights]] |accessdate=2016-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.cambodianacidsurvivorscharity.org/docs/breaking_the_silence.pdf |format=PDF |title=Breaking the Silence : Addressing Acid Attacks in Cambodia |publisher=Cambodian Acid Survivors Charity |accessdate=2016-04-03 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131219010314/http://www.cambodianacidsurvivorscharity.org/docs/breaking_the_silence.pdf |archivedate=19 December 2013 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Reproductive coercion===
[[File:Mauricio rugendas - el malon.jpg|thumb|The painting depicts a Chilean woman being kidnapped during a [[malón]]. [[Bride kidnapping]] for the purpose of [[forced marriage]] and [[forced pregnancy]] was common through the history in many countries.]]
{{Main|Reproductive coercion|Forced pregnancy|Bride kidnapping}}
Reproductive coercion is violent, manipulative or deceptive behavior against [[reproductive health]] or [[reproductive rights]] within an intimate relation and includes a collection of behaviors intended to lead to [[forced pregnancy]].&lt;ref name="ACOG"&gt;{{cite journal |author=Committee on Health Care for Underserved Women | date = February 2013 | title = Committee Opinion No. 554: Reproductive and Sexual Coercion | url = https://www.acog.org/Resources-And-Publications/Committee-Opinions/Committee-on-Health-Care-for-Underserved-Women/Reproductive-and-Sexual-Coercion | journal = Obstetrics and Gynecology | volume = 121 | issue = 2 Pt 1| pages = 411–5 | pmid = 23344307 | doi=10.1097/01.AOG.0000426427.79586.3b}}&lt;/ref&gt; Reproductive coercion is a form of [[domestic violence]], also known as [[intimate partner violence]], where behavior concerning reproductive health is used to maintain power, control, and domination within a relationship and over a partner through an unwanted pregnancy. It is considered a serious public health issue.&lt;ref name="ACOG"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Chamberlain, Linda, and Rebecca Levenson. ''[http://www.futureswithoutviolence.org/userfiles/file/HealthCare/Repro_Guide.pdf Reproductive Health and Partner Violence Guidelines: An Integrated Response to Intimate Partner Violence and Reproductive Coercion].'' San Francisco: Family Violence Prevention Fund, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; This reproductive control is highly correlated to [[unintended pregnancy]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Coker | first1 = AL | date = April 2007 | title = Does physical intimate partner violence affect sexual health? A systematic review | url = | journal = Trauma Violence Abuse | volume = 8 | issue = 2| pages = 149–77 | doi = 10.1177/1524838007301162 | pmid = 17545572 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Forced pregnancy is the practice of forcing a woman or girl to become [[pregnant]], often as part of a [[forced marriage]], including by means of [[bride kidnapping]], through rape (including [[marital rape]], [[war rape]] and [[genocidal rape]]) or as part of a program of breeding [[slave]]s (see [[Slave breeding in the United States]]). In the 20th century, state mandated forced marriage with the aim of increasing the population was practiced by some authoritarian governments, notably during the [[Khmer Rouge]] regime in [[Cambodia]], which systematically forced people into marriages ordering them to have children, in order to increase the population and continue the revolution.&lt;ref&gt;Natalae Anderson, [http://www.d.dccam.org/Abouts/Intern/Natalae_Forced_marriage.pdf "Memorandum: Charging Forced Marriage as a Crime Against Humanity"], Documentation Center of Cambodia, 22 September 2010.]&lt;/ref&gt; Forced pregnancy is strongly connected to the custom of [[bride price]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.popcouncil.org/uploads/pdfs/councilarticles/sfp/SFP301Bawah.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

Within the discourse on reproductive rights, the issue of [[abortion]] is often debated. [[Abortion law]] falls within the jurisdiction of each country, although [[forced abortion]] is prohibited by international law. The [[Convention on preventing and combating violence against women and domestic violence|Istanbul Convention]] prohibits forced abortion and [[forced sterilization]] (Article 39).&lt;ref&gt;https://rm.coe.int/168046031c&lt;/ref&gt; The issue of ''forced continuation of pregnancy'' (ie. denying a woman safe and legal abortion) is also seen by some organizations as a violation of women's rights, although there are no binding international obligations on this issue. However, the [[Committee on the Elimination of Discrimination against Women]] considers the criminalization of abortion a "violations of women's sexual and reproductive health and rights" and a form of "gender based violence"; paragraph 18 of its ''General recommendation No. 35 on gender based violence against women, updating general recommendation No. 19'' states, "Violations of women’s sexual and reproductive health and rights, such as forced sterilizations, forced abortion, forced pregnancy, ''criminalisation of abortion'', ''denial or delay of safe abortion and post abortion care'', ''forced continuation of pregnancy'', abuse and mistreatment of women and girls seeking sexual and reproductive health information, goods and services, are forms of gender based violence that, depending on the circumstances, may amount to torture or cruel, inhuman or degrading treatment."&lt;ref&gt;http://tbinternet.ohchr.org/Treaties/CEDAW/Shared%20Documents/1_Global/CEDAW_C_GC_35_8267_E.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

===Mob violence===
In 2010 [[Amnesty International]] reported that [[Hassi Messaoud mob attacks against women|mob attacks]] against single women were taking place in [[Hassi Messaoud]], Algeria.&lt;ref name="Amnesty"&gt;{{cite web|title=Algerian authorities must investigate and stop attacks against women|url=https://www.amnesty.org.au/news/comments/22931/|publisher=Amnesty International|accessdate=13 August 2011|deadurl=yes|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110903140432/http://www.amnesty.org.au/news/comments/22931/|archivedate=3 September 2011|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to Amnesty International, "some women have been sexually abused" and were targeted "not just because they are women, but because they are living alone and are economically independent".&lt;ref name="Amnesty" /&gt;

===Dating abuse===
{{See|Dating abuse|Teen dating violence}}
Dating abuse or dating violence is the perpetration of coercion, intimidation or assault in the context of [[dating]] or [[courtship]]. It is also when one partner tries to maintain [[abusive power and control]]. Dating violence is defined by the CDC as "the physical, sexual, psychological, or emotional violence within a dating relationship, including stalking".&lt;ref&gt;https://www.cdc.gov/violenceprevention/intimatepartnerviolence/teen_dating_violence.html&lt;/ref&gt; In some countries it is common for older men to engage in "compensated dating" with underage girls. Such relationships are called [[enjo kōsai]] in Japan, and are also common in Asian countries such as Taiwan, South Korea, Hong Kong. The WHO condemned "economically coerced sex (e.g. school girls having sex with “sugar daddies” in return for school fees)" as a form of violence against women.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.who.int/gender/violence/v4.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

===Sexual violence on college campuses===
{{See|Campus sexual assault}}
Sexual violence on college campuses is considered a major problem in the United States. According to the conclusion of a major Campus Sexual Assault (CSA) Study: "The CSA Study data suggest women at universities are at considerable risk for experiencing sexual assault."&lt;ref&gt;https://www.ncjrs.gov/pdffiles1/nij/grants/221153.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; Sexual violence on campus has been researched in other countries too, such as Canada,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=DeKeseredy|first1=Walter|last2=Kelly|first2=Katharine|title=The Incidence and Prevalence of Woman Abuse in Canadian University and College dating relationships|journal=Canadian Journal of Sociology|date=1993|volume=18|issue=2|pages=137–159|jstor=3341255|doi=10.2307/3341255}}&lt;/ref&gt; the UK,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Hidden Marks: A study of women student's experiences of harassment, stalking, violence, and sexual assault|url=http://www.nus.org.uk/Global/NUS_hidden_marks_report_2nd_edition_web.pdf |publisher=National Union of Students|accessdate=10 January 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; New Zealand.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Gavey|first1=Nicola|title=Sexual victimization prevalence among New Zealand university students.|journal=Journal of Consulting and Clinical Psychology|date=1991|volume=59|issue=3|pages=464–466|url=http://psycnet.apa.org/journals/ccp/59/3/464/|doi=10.1037/0022-006x.59.3.464}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Restrictions on freedom of movement===
Women are, in many parts of the world, severely restricted in their [[freedom of movement]].
Freedom of movement is an essential right, recognized by international instruments, including Article 15 (4) of [[CEDAW]].&lt;ref&gt;https://www.webcitation.org/5xc2eRFDv?url=http://www.un.org/womenwatch/daw/cedaw/text/econvention.htm&lt;/ref&gt; Nevertheless, in some countries, women are not legally allowed to leave home without a [[Wali (Islamic legal guardian)|male guardian]] (male relative or husband).&lt;ref&gt;http://www.bbc.com/news/world-middle-east-13932287&lt;/ref&gt; Even in countries where there are no laws against women traveling alone, there are strong social norms, such as [[purdah]] - a religious and social practice of female [[seclusion]] prevalent especially among some [[Muslim]] and [[Hindu]] communities in [[South Asia]]. Many countries have laws on what type of clothing women may or may not wear in public (see [[Hijab by country]]). Women in some cultures are forced into [[social isolation]] during their [[menstruation|menstrual period]]s. In parts of Nepal for instance, they are forced to live in sheds, are forbidden to touch men or even to enter the courtyard of their own homes, and are barred from consuming milk, yogurt, butter, meat, and various other foods, for fear they will contaminate those goods. (see [[Chhaupadi]]). Women have died during this period because of starvation, bad weather, or bites by snakes.&lt;ref&gt;http://kathmandupost.ekantipur.com/news/2016-11-19/pm-concerned-over-death-of-woman-in-chaupadi.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://edition.cnn.com/2017/07/10/asia/nepal-menstruation-hut-deaths-outrage/index.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.bbc.com/news/world-asia-40885748&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.aljazeera.com/news/2016/12/nepali-girl-dies-menstruation-chhaupadi-161219090727200.html&lt;/ref&gt; In cultures where women are restricted from being in public places, by law or custom, women who break such restrictions often face violence.&lt;ref&gt;https://www.empowerwomen.org/en/who-we-are/news/2016/2/freedom-of-movement-and-womens-economic-empowerment &lt;/ref&gt;

===Stalking===
{{Main article|Stalking}}
Stalking is unwanted or obsessive attention by an individual or group toward another person, often manifested through persistent [[harassment]], [[intimidation]], or following/monitoring of the victim. Stalking is often understood as "course of conduct directed at a specific person that would cause a reasonable person to feel fear".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.victimsofcrime.org/our-programs/stalking-resource-center/stalking-information |title=Stalking Information |publisher=Victimsofcrime.org |date= |accessdate=2016-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although stalkers are frequently portrayed as being strangers, they are most often known people, such as former or current partners, friends, colleagues or acquaintances. In the U.S., a survey by NVAW found that only 23% of female victims were stalked by strangers.&lt;ref name="victimsofcrime.org"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.victimsofcrime.org/docs/src/mcfarlane-j-m-campbell-j-c-wilt-s-sachs-c-j-ulrich-y-xu-x-1999.pdf?sfvrsn=0 |format=PDF |title=Stalking and Intimate Partner Femicide |publisher=Victimsofcrime.org |accessdate=2016-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; Stalking by partners can be very dangerous, as sometimes it can escalate into severe violence, including murder.&lt;ref name="victimsofcrime.org"/&gt; Police statistics from the 1990s in Australia indicated that 87.7% of stalking offenders were male and 82.4% of stalking victims were female.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aic.gov.au/media_library/conferences/stalking/dussuyer.pdf |format=PDF |title=Is Stalking Legislation Effective in Protecting Victims? |publisher=Australian Institute of Criminology |accessdate=2016-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Sexual harassment===
{{Main article|Sexual harassment}}
Sexual harassment is abusive, uninvited and unwelcome behavior of a sexual nature, typically in the work/studying place, which may include [[intimidation]], [[bullying]] or [[coercion]] of a sexual nature, or the inappropriate promise of rewards in exchange for sexual favors. It can be verbal or physical, and it is often perpetrated by a person in a position of authority against a subordinate.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.un.org/womenwatch/osagi/pdf/whatissh.pdf |format=PDF |title=What is Sexual Harassment |publisher=United Nations |accessdate=2016-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the United States, sexual harassment is a form of discrimination that violates Title VII of the Civil Rights Act of 1964. The [[Council of Europe Convention on preventing and combating violence against women and domestic violence]] defines sexual harassment as: "any form of unwanted verbal, non-verbal or physical conduct of a sexual nature with the purpose or effect of violating the dignity of a person, in particular when creating an intimidating, hostile, degrading, humiliating or offensive environment".&lt;ref name="COE 210" /&gt;

===Human trafficking and forced prostitution===
[[File:Map3.3Trafficking compressed.jpg|thumb|230px|right|A world map showing countries by prevalence of female trafficking]]
{{Main article|Human trafficking|Forced prostitution}}
Human trafficking refers to the acquisition of persons by improper means such as force, fraud or deception, with the aim of [[Exploitation of labour|exploiting]] them.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.unodc.org/unodc/human-trafficking/index.html?ref=menuside |title=Human Trafficking |publisher=[[United Nations Office on Drugs and Crime]] |date= |accessdate=2016-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Protocol to Prevent, Suppress and Punish Trafficking in Persons, especially Women and Children]] states,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.osce.org/odihr/19223 |title=U.N. Protocol to Prevent, Suppress and Punish Trafficking in Persons, Especially Women and Children, Supplementing the United Nations Convention Against Transnational Organized Crime |publisher=OSCE |date=2000-11-15 |accessdate=2016-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

: "Trafficking in persons" shall mean the recruitment, transportation, transfer, harbouring or receipt of persons, by means of the threat or use of force or other forms of coercion, of abduction, of fraud, of deception, of the abuse of power or of a position of vulnerability or of the giving or receiving of payments or benefits to achieve the consent of a person having control over another person, for the purpose of exploitation. Exploitation shall include, at a minimum, the exploitation of the prostitution of others or other forms of sexual exploitation, forced labour or services, slavery or practices similar to slavery, servitude or the removal of organs.

Because of the illegal nature of trafficking, reliable data on its extent is very limited.&lt;ref name="apps.who.int"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://apps.who.int/iris/bitstream/10665/77394/1/WHO_RHR_12.42_eng.pdf?ua=1 |format=PDF |title=Understanding and addressing violence against women |publisher=WHO |accessdate=2016-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[World health organization|WHO]] states "Current evidence strongly suggests that those who are trafficked into the [[sex industry]] and as domestic servants are more likely to be women and children."&lt;ref name="apps.who.int"/&gt;
A 2006 study in Europe on trafficked women found that the women were subjected to serious forms of abuse, such as physical or sexual violence, that affected their physical and mental health.&lt;ref name="apps.who.int"/&gt;

[[Forced prostitution]] is [[prostitution]] that takes place as a result of [[coercion]] by a third party. In forced prostitution, the party/parties who force the victim to be subjected to unwanted sexual acts exercise control over the victim.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.unhchr.ch/huridocda/huridoca.nsf/0/3d25270b5fa3ea998025665f0032f220?OpenDocument#Bsl |title=Archived copy |accessdate=25 January 2014 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130112211407/http://www.unhchr.ch/huridocda/huridoca.nsf/0/3d25270b5fa3ea998025665f0032f220?OpenDocument |archivedate=12 January 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Mistreatment of widows===
[[File:Balinese rite of Suttee in Houtman 1597 Verhael vande Reyse ... Naer Oost Indien.jpg|thumb|200px|Description of the [[Bali]]nese rite of ''Suttee'', in Houtman's 1597 ''Verhael vande Reyse ... Naer Oost Indien'']]
{{Main article|Widow}}
A widow is a woman whose spouse has died. In some parts of the world, widows are subjected to serious forms of abuse, often fueled by traditional practices such as [[widow inheritance]].&lt;ref&gt;Owen, Margaret. ''A World of Widows''. Illustrated. Atlantic Highlands, NJ: Zed Books, 1996. 181-183. eBook.&lt;/ref&gt; The sacrifice of widows (such as [[Sati (practice)|sati]]) has been prevalent historically in various cultures (especially in [[India]]). Although sati in India is today an almost defunct practice, isolated incidents have occurred in recent years, such as the 1987 sati of [[Roop Kanwar]], as well as several incidents in rural areas in 2002,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/south_asia/2178102.stm | publisher=BBC News | title=Arrests in Indian ritual burning | date=7 August 2002}}&lt;/ref&gt; and 2006.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/south_asia/5366506.stm | publisher=BBC News | title=Sons arrested in sati death probe | date=21 September 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Accusations of witchcraft===
[[File:Schiltach Flugblatt.JPG|thumb|left|upright|A 1533 account of the execution of a witch charged with burning the [[Germany|German]] town of [[Schiltach]] in 1531]]
[[Witch trials in the early modern period]] (between the 15th and 18th centuries) were common in Europe and in the European colonies in North America. Today, there remain regions of the world (such as parts of [[Sub-Saharan Africa]], rural [[North India]], and [[Papua New Guinea]]) where belief in [[witchcraft]] is held by many people, and women accused of being witches are subjected to serious violence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://scholarship.law.duke.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1129&amp;context=djcil#H2N1 |format=PDF |title=Conflict Between State Legal Norms and Norms Underlying Popular Beliefs: Witchcraft in Africa as a Case Study* |publisher=Duke University |accessdate=2016-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mrc.ac.za/crime/witchhunts.pdf |format=PDF |title=Witch Hunts in Modern South Africa: an Under-represented Facet of Gender-based Violence |publisher=[[South African Medical Research Council]] |accessdate=2016-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-21363894 | publisher=BBC News | title=Woman burned alive for 'sorcery' in Papua New Guinea | date=7 February 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, there are also countries that have criminal legislation against the practice of witchcraft. In [[Saudi Arabia]], witchcraft remains a crime [[punishable by death]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.amnesty.org/en/news/saudi-arabia-beheading-sorcery-shocking-2011-12-12 |title=Saudi Arabia: Beheading for 'sorcery' shocking |publisher=Amnesty International |date=2011-12-12 |accessdate=2016-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===State violence===

====War rape and sexual slavery during military conflict====
[[File:Paul Jamin - Le Brenn et sa part de butin 1893.jpg|thumb|200 px|''[[Brennus (4th century BC)|Brennus]] and His Share of the Spoils'', by [[Paul Jamin]], 1893.]]
[[File:Chinese girl from one of the Japanese Army's 'comfort battalions'.jpg|thumb|200 px|[[Rangoon]], [[Myanmar|Burma]]. 8 August 1945. A young [[Chinese diaspora|ethnic Chinese]] woman from one of the [[Imperial Japanese Army]]'s "comfort battalions" is interviewed by an [[Allies of World War II|Allied]] officer.]]

Militarism produces special environments that allow for increased violence against women. [[War rapes]] have accompanied warfare in virtually every known historical era.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last= Levinson |first=Bernard M |title= Gender and Law in the Hebrew Bible and the Ancient Near East |url=https://books.google.com/?id=2rZnXQwPX8gC&amp;dq=rape+in+warfare+ancient |page= 203 |year=2004 |isbn= 978-0-567-08098-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; Rape in the course of war is mentioned multiple times in the Bible: "For I will gather all the nations against Jerusalem to battle, and the city shall be taken and the houses plundered and the women raped..." {{bibleref|Zechariah|14:2|ESV}} "Their little children will be dashed to death before their eyes. Their homes will be sacked, and their wives will be raped."{{bibleref|Isaiah|13:16|NLT}}

War rapes are rapes committed by soldiers, other combatants or civilians during armed conflict or war, or during military occupation, distinguished from sexual assaults and rape committed amongst troops in military service. It also covers the situation where women are forced into prostitution or [[sexual slavery]] by an occupying power. During World War II the Japanese military established brothels filled with "[[comfort women]]", girls and women who were forced into sexual slavery for soldiers, exploiting women for the purpose of creating access and entitlement for men.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Benedict |first=Helen |url=http://www.inthesetimes.com/article/3848/ |title=Why Soldiers Rape |work=In These Times |date=2008-08-13 |accessdate=2016-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web
|url=http://www.japanfocus.org/-Tessa-Morris_Suzuki/2373
|title=Japan's 'Comfort Women': It's time for the truth (in the ordinary, everyday sense of the word)
|author=Tessa Morris-Suzuki
|date=8 March 2007
|accessdate=2011-08-04
|publisher=japanfocus.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|WCCW|2004}}.&lt;/ref&gt;
 
Another example of violence against women incited by militarism during war took place in the [[Kaunas Ghetto|Kovno Ghetto]]. Jewish male prisoners had access to (and used) Jewish women forced into camp brothels by the Nazis, who also used them.&lt;ref&gt;Dworkin, Andrea: ''Scapegoat: The Jews, Israel and Women's Liberation''. pg. 316. Free Press, 2000. {{ISBN|0-684-83612-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Rape was committed during the [[Bangladesh Liberation War]] by members of the [[Pakistan Armed Forces|Pakistani military]] and the [[militia]]s that supported them. Over a period of nine months, hundreds of thousands of women were raped. [[Susan Brownmiller]], in her report on the [[1971 Bangladesh atrocities|atrocities]], said that girls from the age of eight to grandmothers of seventy-five suffered attacks. (See also: [[Rape during the Bangladesh Liberation War]])

Rape used as a weapon of war was practiced during the [[Bosnian War]] where rape was used as a highly systematized instrument of war by Serb armed forces predominantly targeting women and girls of the Bosniak ethnic group for physical and moral destruction. Estimates of the number of women raped during the war range from 50,000 to 60,000; as of 2010 only 12 cases have been prosecuted.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.icty.org/x/file/About/Reports%20and%20Publications/AnnualReports/annual_report_1997_en.pdf |title=Archived copy |accessdate=26 December 2012 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120804004034/http://www.icty.org/x/file/About/Reports%20and%20Publications/AnnualReports/annual_report_1997_en.pdf |archivedate=4 August 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt; (See also [[Rape during the Bosnian War]]).

The 1998 [[International Criminal Tribunal for Rwanda]] recognized rape as a war crime. Presiding judge [[Navanethem Pillay]] said in a statement after the verdict: "From time immemorial, rape has been regarded as spoils of war. Now it will be considered a war crime. We want to send out a strong message that rape is no longer a trophy of war."&lt;ref&gt;Quoted in citation for honorary doctorate, Rhodes University, April 2005 accessed at {{cite web|url=http://www.ru.ac.za/academic/graduation/addresses_and_citations/2005/Judge_Pillay_citation.doc |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2008-02-27 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20060926231120/http://www.ru.ac.za/academic/graduation/addresses_and_citations/2005/Judge_Pillay_citation.doc |archivedate=26 September 2006 |df=dmy }} 23 March 2007&lt;/ref&gt; (See also: [[Rwandan Genocide]])

In 2006, five [[United States Army|U.S. troops]] from a six-man unit [[gang rape]]d and killed a 14-year-old girl in a village near the town of [[Mahmoudiyah, Iraq|Al-Mahmudiyah]], Iraq. After the rape the girl was shot in her head and the lower part of her body, from her stomach down to her feet, was set on fire.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.cnn.com/2006/WORLD/meast/08/08/iraq.mahmoudiya/index.html |title=Soldier: 'Death walk' drives troops 'nuts' - 8 August 2006 |publisher=CNN.com |accessdate=2012-11-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|publisher=BBC News|date=2009-05-07|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/americas/8039257.stm|title=US ex-soldier guilty of Iraq rape}}&lt;/ref&gt; (See also: [[Mahmudiyah killings]])

A 1995 study of female war veterans found that 90 percent had been sexually harassed. A 2003 survey found that 30 percent of female vets said they were raped in the military and a 2004 study of veterans who were seeking help for post-traumatic stress disorder found that 71 percent of the women said they were sexually assaulted or raped while serving.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Helen Benedict |url=http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=103844570 |title=The Nation: The Plight of Women Soldiers |publisher=NPR |date=2009-05-06 |accessdate=2016-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to one report, the [[Islamic State of Iraq and the Levant]]'s capture of Iraqi cities in June 2014 was accompanied by an upsurge in crimes against women, including kidnap and rape.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Surging Violence Against Women in Iraq|url=http://www.ipsnews.net/2014/06/op-ed-surging-violence-against-women-in-iraq/|publisher=[[Inter Press Service]]|date=27 June 2014|accessdate=5 July 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Winterton|first1=Clare|title=Why We Must Act When Women in Iraq Document Rape|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/clare-winterton/why-we-must-act_b_5528162.html|date=25 June 2014|publisher=The Huffington Post|accessdate=10 July 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=إسراء محمد علي|title=إعلامي كويتي: "داعش" يطالب أهالي الموصل بتقديم غير المتزوجات لـ"جهاد النكاح|url=http://www.almasryalyoum.com/news/details/466402|website=المصری الیوم|accessdate=10 July 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[The Guardian]]'' reported that ISIL's extremist agenda extended to women's bodies and that women living under their control were being captured and raped.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Susskind|first=Yifat|title=Under Isis, Iraqi women again face an old nightmare: violence and repression|url=https://www.theguardian.com/global-development/poverty-matters/2014/jul/03/isis-iraqi-women-rape-violence-repression|date=3 July 2014|newspaper=The Guardian|accessdate=17 July 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Fighters are told that they are free to have sex and rape non-Muslim captive women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|language=sv|title=Det jag har bevittnat i al-Raqqa kommer alltid förfölja mig|url=http://www.dn.se/nyheter/varlden/det-jag-har-bevittnat-i-al-raqqa-kommer-alltid-forfolja-mig/|accessdate=25 September 2014|work=[[Dagens Nyheter]]|date=23 September 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Yazidi girls in Iraq allegedly [[War rape|raped]] by ISIL fighters committed [[suicide]] by jumping to their death from [[Mount Sinjar]], as described in a witness statement.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Ahmed|first=Havidar|title=The Yezidi Exodus, Girls Raped by ISIS Jump to their Death on Mount Shingal|date=14 August 2014|url=http://rudaw.net/english/kurdistan/140820142|publisher=[[Rudaw Media Network]]|accessdate=26 August 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Haleh Esfandiari from the [[Woodrow Wilson International Center for Scholars]] has highlighted the abuse of local women by ISIL militants after they have captured an area. "They usually take the older women to a makeshift slave market and try to sell them. The younger girls ... are raped or married off to fighters", she said, adding, "It's based on temporary marriages, and once these fighters have had sex with these young girls, they just pass them on to other fighters."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Brekke|first1=Kira|title=ISIS Is Attacking Women, And Nobody Is Talking About It|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2014/09/08/isis-attacks-on-women_n_5775106.html?cps=gravity |publisher=The Huffington Post |date=8 September 2014 |accessdate=11 September 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Speaking of [[Yazidi]] women captured by ISIS, [[Nazand Begikhani]] said "[t]hese women have been treated like cattle... They have been subjected to physical and sexual violence, including systematic rape and sex slavery. They've been exposed in markets in Mosul and in Raqqa, Syria, carrying price tags."&lt;ref&gt;Ivan Watson, [http://www.cnn.com/2014/10/30/world/meast/isis-female-slaves/ "'Treated like cattle': Yazidi women sold, raped, enslaved by ISIS"], [[CNN]], 30 October 2014&lt;/ref&gt; In December 2014 the [[Ministry of Human Rights (Iraq)|Iraqi Ministry of Human Rights]] announced that the [[Islamic State of Iraq and the Levant]] had killed over 150 women and girls in [[Fallujah]] who refused to participate in [[sexual jihad]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=ISIS Just Executed More Than 150 Women In Fallujah|url=http://www.businessinsider.com/isis-just-executed-more-than-150-women-in-fallujah-2014-12|agency=[[NOW News]]|publisher=[[Business Insider]]|date=Dec 17, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Forced sterilization and forced abortion====
{{See|Eugenics in the United States}}
[[File:SOU 1929 14 Betänkande med förslag till steriliseringslag s 57 Laughlin.jpg|200px|thumb|right|A map from a 1929 Swedish royal commission report displays the U.S. states that had implemented sterilization legislation by then]]
[[Forced sterilization]] and [[forced abortion]] are forms of gender-based violence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://eige.europa.eu/content/what-is-gender-based-violence |title=What is gender-based violence? |publisher=European Institute for Gender Equality |date=2015-08-24 |accessdate=2016-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; Forced sterilization has occurred throughout much of the world, both at the hands of the state and from intimate partners. Studies show forced sterilizations often target socially and politically disadvantaged groups such as racial and ethnic minorities, the poor, and indigenous populations.&lt;ref name="Volscho, Thomas W 2010"&gt;Volscho, Thomas W. "Sterilization Racism and Pan-Ethnic Disparities of the Past Decade: The Continued Encroachment on Reproductive Rights". ''Wicazo Sa Review'' 2010; 25(1): 17-31.&lt;/ref&gt; According to the Convention on the Elimination of all forms of Discrimination Against Women, all "women are guaranteed the right to decide freely and responsibly on the number of and spacing of their children, and to have access to information, education, and means to enable them to exercise these rights."&lt;ref&gt;"Text of the Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination against Women". UN News Center. n.d. 9 May 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;

In China, the [[one child policy]] included forced abortions and forced sterilization.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Post |url=http://www.globalpost.com/dispatch/news/regions/asia-pacific/china/130409/china-mother-dies-after-forced-sterilization-one-child-policy |title=China: Mother of 2 dies after forced sterilization |publisher=GlobalPost |date=2013-04-09 |accessdate=2016-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.amnesty.org/en/news-and-updates/thousands-risk-forced-sterilization-china-2010-04-22 |title=Everything you need to know about human rights |publisher=Amnesty International |date= |accessdate=2016-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-china-18435126 | publisher=BBC News | title=China forced abortion photo sparks outrage | date=14 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hrnk.org/uploads/pdfs/HRNK_HiddenGulag2_Web_5-18.pdf |format=PDF |title=The Hidden Gulag |publisher=The Committee for Human Rights in North Korea |accessdate=2016-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the United States, much of the history of forced sterilization is connected to the legacy of eugenics. Many doctors thought that they were doing the country a service by sterilizing poor, disabled, and/or minority women, whom they considered a drain on the system.&lt;ref name="Volscho, Thomas W 2010"/&gt;&lt;ref name="North Carolina Sterilization Program 2011"&gt;"Victims Speak out about North Carolina Sterilization Program, Which Targeted Women, Young Girls and Blacks". NBC News. N.p., 7 November 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

In Europe, there have been a number of lawsuits and accusations towards the [[Czech Republic]] and [[Slovakia]] of sterilizing Roma women without adequate information and waiting period.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=|first=|year=2016|title=Coercive and Cruel a Report by the European Roma Rights Centre |url=http://www.errc.org/cms/upload/file/coercive-and-cruel-28-november-2016.pdf|journal=European Roma Right Centre|volume=|pages=|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt; In response, both nations have instituted a mandatory seven-day waiting period and written consent. Slovakia has been condemned on the issue of forced sterilization of Roma women several times by the [[European Court for Human Rights]] (see [[V. C. vs. Slovakia]], [[N. B. vs. Slovakia]] and [[I.G. and Others vs. Slovakia]]).

In [[Peru]], in 1995, [[Alberto Fujimori]] launched a family planning initiative that especially targeted poor and indigenous women. In total, over 215,000 women were sterilized, with over 200,000 believed to have been coerced.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Boesten | first1 = Jelke | year = 2007 | title = Free Choice or Poverty Alleviation? Population Politics in Peru under Alberto Fujimori | url = | journal = ERLACS European Review of Latin American and Caribbean Studies | volume = 82 | issue = | page = 3 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2002, Health Minister [[Fernando carbone|Fernando Carbone]] admitted that the government gave misleading information, offered food incentives, and threatened to fine parents if they had additional children. The procedures have also been found to have been negligent, with less than half using proper anesthetic.&lt;ref&gt;"Mass Sterilisation Scandal Shocks Peru". BBC News. 24 July 2002.&lt;/ref&gt;

Forced sterilization is also practiced in Uzbekistan.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/magazine-17612550 | publisher=BBC News | title=Uzbekistan's policy of secretly sterilising women | date=12 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=20:30 |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b01fjx63 |title=BBC Radio 4 - Crossing Continents, Forced Sterilisation in Uzbekistan |publisher=BBC |date=2012-04-16 |accessdate=2016-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Violence by the police and other authority figures====
[[File:Taliban beating woman in public RAWA.jpg|right|thumb|250px|A member of the Taliban's [[Mutaween#Other groups|religious police]] beating an Afghan woman in [[Kabul]] on 26 August 2001.]]
When police officers misuse their power as agents of the state to physically and [[sexual harassment|sexually harass]] and assault victims, the survivors, including women, feel much less able to report the violence.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite episode
| title        = Covering 'Tainted Justice' And Winning A Pulitzer
| episodelink  = 
| url          = http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=126386819
| series       = Fresh Air
| serieslink   = Fresh Air
| credits      = Barbara Laker and Wendy Ruderman, hosted by [[Terry Gross]]
| network      = NPR
| station      = [[WHYY-FM|WHYY]]
| location         = Philadelphia
| airdate      = 3 May 2010
| began        = 
| ended        = 
| season       = 
| seriesno     =
| number       = 
| minutes      = 
| transcript   =  
| transcripturl= }}&lt;/ref&gt;  It is standard procedure for police to force entry into the victim's home even after the victim's numerous requests for them to go away.&lt;ref&gt;[[Jeannie Suk|Professor Jeannie Suk]], ''At Home in the Law: How the Domestic Violence Revolution Is Transforming Privacy,'' [[Yale University Press]], 27 October 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; Government agencies often disregard the victim's right to [[Freedom of association#Intimate association|freedom of association]] with their perpetrator.&lt;ref&gt;Cheryl Hanna, "No Right to Choose: Mandated Victim Participation in Domestic Violence Prosecutions", ''[[Harvard Law Review]]'', 1996, Vol. 109, pp.1850–1910.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Women's shelter|Shelter]] workers are often reduced themselves to contributing to violence against women by exploiting their [[vulnerability]] in exchange for a paying job.&lt;ref&gt;Koyama, Emi "Disloyal to feminism: Abuse of survivors within the domestic violence shelter system", in Smith A, Richie BE, Sudbury J, eds. ''The Color of Violence: INCITE! Anthology''. Cambridge, Mass.: South End Press, 2006. {{ISBN|0-89608-762-X}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Human rights violations perpetrated by police and military personnel in many countries are correlated with decreased access to public health services and increased practices of risky behavior among members of vulnerable groups, such as women and female sex workers.&lt;ref name="Beletsky L, Martinex G, Gaines T, et al. 2012 403–410"&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Beletsky L, Martinex G, Gaines T, etal |title=Mexico's northern border conflict: collateral damage to health and human rights of vulnerable groups|journal=[[Pan American Journal of Public Health]] |year=2012|pmid=22767041|volume=31|issue=5|pmc=3660986|pages=403–410|doi=10.1590/s1020-49892012000500008}}&lt;/ref&gt; These practices are especially widespread in settings with a weak rule of law and low levels of police and military management and professionalism. Police abuse in this context has been linked to a wide range of risky behaviors and health outcomes, including post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD), and substance abuse.&lt;ref name="Beletsky L, Martinex G, Gaines T, et al. 2012 403–410"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Strathdee S, Lozada R, Martinez G, etal |title=Social and structural factors associated with HIV infection among female sex workers who inject drugs in the Mexico-US border region|journal=PLoS ONE|year=2011|pmid=21541349|doi=10.1371/journal.pone.0019048|volume=6|issue=4|pmc=3081836|page=e19048}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Ramos R, Ferreira-Pinto J, Brouwer K, etal |title=A tale of two cities: social and environmental influences shaping risk factors and protective behaviors in two Mexico-US border cities|journal=Health Place|year=2009|pmid=19464228|doi=10.1016/j.healthplace.2009.04.004|volume=15|issue=4|pmc=2735581|pages=999–1005}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Pollini R, Brouwer K, Lozada R, etal |title=Syringe possession arrests are associated with receptive syringe sharing in two Mexico-US border cities|journal=Addiction|year=2008|pmid=18028520|volume=103|issue=1|pmc=2214830|pages=101–108|doi=10.1111/j.1360-0443.2007.02051.x}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Pollini R, Gallardo M, Hassan S, etal |title=High prevalence of abscesses and self-treatment among injection drug users in Tijuana, Mexico|journal=International Journal of Infectious Diseases |year=2010|pmid=20381396|doi=10.1016/j.ijid.2010.02.2238|volume=14|issue=supplement 3|pmc=2917477|pages=117–122}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |vauthors=Strathdee S, Lozada R, Pollini R, etal |title=Individual, social, and environmental influences associated with HIV infection among injection drug users in Tijuana, Mexico|journal=JAIDS Journal of Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndromes |year=2008|pmid=18176320|doi= 10.1097/QAI.0b013e318160d5ae|volume=47|issue=3|pmc=2752692|pages=369–376}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|vauthors=Raj A, Gupta J |veditors=Martin S, Tirman J|title=Women, Migration, and Conflict: Breaking a Deadly Cycle|publisher=Springer|year=2009|page=107}}&lt;/ref&gt; Extortion of sexual services and police sexual abuse have been linked to a decrease in condom use and an elevated risk of STI and HIV infections among vulnerable groups.&lt;ref name="Beletsky L, Martinex G, Gaines T, et al. 2012 403–410"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|vauthors=Blankenship K, Koester S |title=Criminal law, policing policy, and HIV risk in female street sex workers and injection drug users|journal=The Journal of Law, Medicine &amp; Ethics |year=2002|pmid=12561263|volume=30|issue=4|pages=548–559|doi=10.1111/j.1748-720x.2002.tb00425.x}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Stoning and flogging====
[[Stoning]], or lapidation, refers to a form of [[capital punishment]] whereby an organized group throws stones at an individual until the person dies. Stoning is a punishment that is included in the laws of several countries, including Iran, Saudi Arabia, Sudan, Pakistan, Yemen, the United Arab Emirates, and some states in Nigeria, as punishment for [[adultery]].&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.google.com/hostednews/afp/article/ALeqM5ixvYN7oeF8ehN9beAHZ4G_YlfKeA?hl=en ]{{dead link|date=April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Flogging]] or flagellation is the act of methodically beating or whipping the human body. It is a judicial punishment in various countries for specific crimes, including [[sex outside marriage]]. These punishments employed for sexual relations outside marriage, apart from constituting a form of violence in themselves, can also deter victims of [[sexual violence]] from reporting the crime, because the victims may themselves be punished (if they cannot prove their case, if they are deemed to have been in the company of an unrelated male, or if they were unmarried and not virgins at the time of the rape).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-21595814 | publisher=BBC News | title=Maldives girl to get 100 lashes for pre-marital sex | date=26 February 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.today.com/id/15836746/ns/today-today_news/t/rape-case-calls-saudi-legal-system-question/#.UolafidedO6 |title=Rape case brings Saudi laws into focus |work=Today |date= |accessdate=2016-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Female genital mutilation===
{{Main article|Female genital mutilation}}
[[File:Fgm map.gif|thumb|250px|Map showing the prevalence of FGM in Africa]]
[[File:FGM road sign, Bakau, Gambia, 2005.jpg|thumb|250 px|Anti-[[FGM]] road sign, Bakau, Gambia, 2005]]
Female genital mutilation (FGM) is defined by the [[World Health Organization]] (WHO) as "all procedures that involve partial or total removal of the external female genitalia, or other injury to the female genital organs for non-medical reasons".&lt;ref name="WHO FGM"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.who.int/mediacentre/factsheets/fs241/en/ |title=Female genital mutilation |publisher=WHO |date= |accessdate=2016-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to a 2013 UNICEF report, 125 million women and girls in Africa and the Middle East have experienced FGM.&lt;ref name="unicef.org"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.unicef.org/media/files/FGCM_Lo_res.pdf |format=PDF |title=Female Genital Mutilation/Cutting |publisher=UNICEF |accessdate=2016-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; The WHO states: "The procedure has no health benefits for girls and women" and "Procedures can cause severe bleeding and problems urinating, and later cysts, infections, infertility as well as complications in childbirth increased risk of newborn deaths" and "FGM is recognized internationally as a violation of the human rights of girls and women. It reflects deep-rooted inequality between the sexes, and constitutes an extreme form of discrimination against women."&lt;ref name="WHO FGM"/&gt; According to a UNICEF report, the top rates for FGM are in Somalia (with 98 percent of women affected), Guinea (96 percent), Djibouti (93 percent), Egypt (91 percent), Eritrea (89 percent), Mali (89 percent), Sierra Leone (88 percent), Sudan (88 percent), Gambia (76 percent), Burkina Faso (76 percent), Ethiopia (74 percent), Mauritania (69 percent), Liberia (66 percent), and Guinea-Bissau (50 percent).&lt;ref name="unicef.org"/&gt;

According to some local practitioners, it is believed that FGM is linked to cultural rites and customs. It is considered to be a traditional practice that continues to take place in different communities/countries of Africa and Middle East, including in places where it is banned by national legislation. FGM is defined as a "harmful traditional practice"&lt;ref name="Shell-Duncan"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Shell-Duncan|first=Bettina|title=From Health to Human Rights: Female Genital Cutting and the Politics of Intervention|journal=American Anthropologist|date=10 July 2008|volume= 110|issue=2|pages=225–236|doi=10.1111/j.1548-1433.2008.00028.x }}&lt;/ref&gt; in accordance to the Inter-African Committee. 
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:UNFPA-UNICEF Joint Programme On FGM 2012.png|thumbnail|alt=map|300 px|right|Prevalence of FGM among African women aged 15-49. For more detailed maps, see [http://www.unfpa.org/webdav/site/global/shared/documents/publications/2013/UNICEF-UNFPA%20Joint%20Programme%20AR_final_v14.pdf] UNFPA-UNICEF Joint Programme on FGM, 2012]] --&gt;
Due to globalization and immigration, FGM is spreading beyond the borders of Africa and Middle East, to countries such as Australia, Belgium, Canada, France, New Zealand, the U.S., and UK.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Nussbaum|first=Martha|title=Sex and Social Justice|year=2000|publisher=Oxford University Press, USA|location=USA|isbn=0195112105|pages=120–121|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=hHY_kjkAYKQC&amp;pg=PT11&amp;lpg=PT11&amp;dq=martha+nussbaum+judging+other+cultures+the+case+of+genital+mutilation&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=Dct3fEjZzl&amp;sig=yS0Qk9qP6ALyhrf0FHiXkGbv8HA&amp;hl=ru&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=d_WZUo2jKceGywO-kYLIAw&amp;redir_esc=y#v=onepage&amp;q=martha%20nussbaum%20judging%20other%20cultures%20the%20case%20of%20genital%20mutilation&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Convention on preventing and combating violence against women and domestic violence|Istanbul Convention]] prohibits female genital mutilation (Article 38).&lt;ref&gt;https://rm.coe.int/168046031c&lt;/ref&gt;

As of 2016, in [[Africa]], FGM has been legally banned in Benin, Burkina Faso, Central African Republic, Chad, Côte d'Ivoire, Djibouti, Egypt, Eritrea, Ethiopia, Gambia, Ghana, Guinea, Guinea Bissau, Kenya, Mauritania, Niger, Nigeria, Senegal, South Africa, Tanzania, Togo, Uganda, and Zambia.&lt;ref&gt;Lyons, Kate. "The Gambia Bans Female Genital Mutilation". ''The Guardian''. 24 November 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Richards, Kimberly. "History Has Been Made. Female Genital Mutilation Banned In Nigeria." ''A Plus''. Aljazeera, 3 June 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;"Female Genital Mutilation (FGM) Frequently Asked Questions". UNFPA. United Nationals Population Fund, December 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;

There exist several approaches that were set up by international health organizations and civil societies (for example, [[Tostan]]) aimed at eliminating the practice of FGM in implemented countries: 
# FGM as a Health issue (also known as health risks approach)
# FGM as a Human Rights issue (also known as Human Rights-based approach)

Some scholars suggests that, when dealing with FGM, it is necessary to take lessons from history, particularly 19th-century campaign against [[foot-binding]] in China,&lt;ref name="Kwame Appiah"&gt;{{cite news|last=Kwame Appiah|first=Anthony|title=The art of social change|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2010/10/24/magazine/24FOB-Footbinding-t.html?pagewanted=all |newspaper=The New York Times |date=22 October 2010 |accessdate=2 December 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; which was successful.

===Breast ironing===
{{Main article|Breast ironing}}
Breast ironing (also known as "breast flattening") is the practice of pounding and massaging the [[breasts]] of a [[puberty|pubescent girl]], using hard or heated objects, in an attempt to try to make them stop developing or disappear.&lt;ref name="west-info.eu"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.west-info.eu/files/Feinstein-International-Center-Understanding-breast-ironing-a-study-of-the-methods-motivations-and-outcomes-of-breast-flattening-practices-in-Cameroon-20121.pdf |format=PDF |title=Understanding Breast "Ironing": a Study of the Methods, Motivations, and Outcomes of Breast Flattening Practices in Cameroon |publisher=WEST / Welfare Society Territory |accessdate=2016-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="BBC Cameroon Breast Ironing"&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/5107360.stm | publisher=BBC News | title=Cameroon girls battle 'breast ironing' | date=23 June 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.cbsnews.com/pictures/surviving-breast-ironing-in-cameroon/ | publisher=CBS News |title= Surviving "breast ironing" in Cameroon |accessdate = 8 December 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is typically carried out by the girl's mother, with the aim of making the girl less sexually attractive to men and boys, so that her virginity is preserved and she can continue her education.&lt;ref name="BBC Cameroon Breast Ironing"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Ngunshi, Rosaline. "Breast Ironing: A Harmful Practice That Has Been Silenced for Too Long". ''Gender Empowerment and Development'' (n.d.): n. pag. ''National Criminal Justice Reference Service''. 24 August 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; It is practiced primarily in [[Cameroon]], but has also been reported across other areas in [[West Africa|West]] and [[Central Africa]].&lt;ref name="west-info.eu"/&gt;&lt;ref name="BBC Cameroon Breast Ironing"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://edition.cnn.com/2011/WORLD/africa/07/27/cameroon.breast.ironing/ | publisher=CNN | title=Breast ironing tradition targeted in Cameroon | date=28 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Breast ironing is very painful and can have negative emotional and physical consequences.&lt;ref name="west-info.eu"/&gt;&lt;ref name="BBC Cameroon Breast Ironing"/&gt;

===Obstetric violence===
{{See|Abuse during childbirth}}
"Obstetric violence" refers to acts categorized as physically or psychologically violent in the context of labor and birth. In most developed and many developing countries, birth takes place in an increasingly medicalized environment; with numerous surgical interventions that the pregant woman can sometimes be coerced into accepting, or which are done without her consent, or which are unnecessary.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title=Possible feto-maternal clinical risk of the Kristeller's expression |author=Habek, D.|journal=Central European Journal of Medicine |year=2008|display-authors=etal |doi=10.2478/s11536-008-0008-z |volume=3}}&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://whqlibdoc.who.int/hq/1996/WHO_FRH_MSM_96.24.pdf |title=Care in Normal Birth: A Practical Guide |author=World Health Organization |year=1996}}&lt;/ref&gt; On the other hand, pregnant women can also be pushed against their will into [[natural childbirth]], which can also be harmful.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.channelnewsasia.com/news/asiapacific/china-hospital-deemed-negligent-after-pregnant-woman-denied-c-9200496&lt;/ref&gt;

Many such practices originate in patriarchal ideologies. Some sources refer to North American obstetricians and gynecologists, especially between the 1950s and 1980s, practicing what was called ''the husband's stitch'': placing extra stitches in the woman's vagina after the episiotomy or natural tearing, supposedly to increase the husband's future sexual pleasure and often causing long-term pain and discomfort to the woman. However, there is no proof that such a practice was widespread in North America,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Aesthetic Surgery of the Female Genitalia |author=Julie M.L.C.L. Dobbeleir |author2=Koenraad Van Landuyt |author3=Stan J. Monstrey |publisher=Seminars in Plastic Surgery, 25(2): 130-141 |date=May 2011 |pmc=3312147 |pmid=22547970 |doi=10.1055/s-0031-1281482 |volume=25 |journal=Seminars in Plastic Surgery |pages=130–41}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=0HeP-60VkIgC&amp;pg=PA14&amp;lpg=PA14&amp;dq=%22husband's+stitch%22&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=5nXjC_YytA&amp;sig=e3CzXUAa3hqz_jMX3cuwy_hGfcQ&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=yWKcUoG7CJH8yAO1pYGQBA&amp;ved=0CDEQ6AEwAzgK#v=onepage&amp;q=%22husband's%20stitch%22&amp;f=false |title=Women's Bodies, Women's Wisdom: Creating Physical and Emotional Health and Healing |author=Northrup, Christiane |publisher=Bantam |year=2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; but mentions of it frequently appear in studies about episiotomy, also in other American countries such as Brazil.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.rhm-elsevier.com/article/S0968-8080(04)23112-3/fulltext |title=&amp;thinsp;'The Cut Above' and 'the Cut Below': The Abuse of Caesareans and Episiotomy in São Paulo, Brazil |author1=Simone G Diniz|author2= Alessandra S Chacham |journal=Reproductive Health Matters|volume =12|issue =23|pages= 100–110 |date=May 2004 |doi=10.1016/s0968-8080(04)23112-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;
The WHO recently stated, "in normal birth, there should be a valid reason to interfere with the natural process. The aim of care is to achieve a healthy mother and child with the least possible level of intervention compatible with safety."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.who.int/chd/publications/newslet/dialog/8/keeping_birth_normal.htm |title=Keeping Birth Normal |author=Rosser, Jilly |website=World Health Organization |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131203063430/http://www.who.int/chd/publications/newslet/dialog/8/keeping_birth_normal.htm |archivedate=3 December 2013 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; 

The term "obstetric violence" is particularly used in Latin American countries, where the law prohibits such behavior. Such laws exist in several countries, including Argentina, Puerto Rico and Venezuela.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.who.int/reproductivehealth/topics/maternal_perinatal/statement-childbirth-govnts-support/en/&lt;/ref&gt;
 
In recent years, however, it has been argued that the push towards 'natural childbirth' in Western countries is exaggerated, and can harm women.&lt;ref&gt;https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2015/mar/05/natural-childbirth-report-midwife-musketeers-morcambe-bay&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2015/may/29/obsession-natural-birth-judge-women-pregnant-medical&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.bbc.com/news/health-27239241&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Violence against indigenous women ===
Indigenous women around the world are often targets of sexual assault or physical violence. Many indigenous communities are rural, with few resources and little help from the government or non-state actors. These groups also often have strained relationships with law enforcement, making prosecution difficult. Many indigenous societies also find themselves at the center of land disputes between nations and ethnic groups, often resulting in these communities bearing the brunt of national and ethnic conflicts.&lt;ref&gt;United Nations Children Fund, United Nations Entity for Gender Equality and the Empowerment of Women, United Nations Population Fund, International Labor Organization, and Office of the Special Representative of the Secretary-General on Violence against Children. "Breaking the Silence on Violence against Indigenous Girls, Adolescents and Young Women". (n.d.): n. pag. May 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;

Violence against indigenous women is often perpetrated by the state, such as in [[Peru]], in the 1990s. President [[Alberto Fujimori]] (in office from 1990 to 2000) has been accused of [[genocide]] and [[crimes against humanity]] as a result of a [[forced sterilization]] program put in place by his administration.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news | title=Mass sterilization scandal shocks Peru | date=July 24, 2002 | publisher=[[BBC News]] | url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/americas/2148793.stm | accessdate=April 30, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; During his presidency, Fujimori put in place a program of forced sterilizations against indigenous people (mainly the [[Quechua people|Quechuas]] and the [[Aymara people|Aymaras]]), in the name of a "[[public health]] plan", presented 28 July 1995. 

[[Domestic violence in Bolivia|Bolivia has the highest rate of domestic violence]] in Latin America.&lt;ref&gt;Dhillon, Jaskiran, and Siku Allooloo. "Violence against Indigenous Women Is Woven into Canada's History". ''The Guardian''. 14 December 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Shiriari, Sara. "Bolivia Struggles with Gender-based Violence". Aljazeera, 30 April 2015.&lt;/ref&gt; Indigenous women self-report physical or sexual violence from a current or former partner at rates of twenty-nine percent, in comparison to the national average of twenty four percent.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite report |title=Thematic Paper on the Elimination and Responses to Violence, Exploitation and Abuse of Indigenous Girls, Adolescents and Young Women |date=June 2014 |publisher=Inter-agency Support Group on Indigenous Peoples' Issues |url=https://www.un.org/en/ga/president/68/pdf/wcip/IASG%20Thematic%20Paper_%20Violence%20against%20Girls%20and%20Women%20-%20rev1.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bolivia is largely indigenous in its ethnic demographics, and Quechua, Aymara, and Guarani women have been monumental in the nation's fight against violence against women.&lt;ref&gt;"Bolivian Women Battle against Culture of Harassment". BBC News. 12 March 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Shahriari, Sara. "Combating Violence Against Women in Bolivia". Pulitzer Center. N.p., 6 March 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Guatemala]]n indigenous women have also faced extensive violence. Throughout over three decades of conflict, [[Maya civilization|Maya]] women and girls have continued to be targeted. The Commission for Historical Clarification found that 88% of women affected by state-sponsored rape and sexual violence against women were indigenous.

The concept of White dominion over indigenous women's bodies has been rooted in American history since the beginning of colonization. The theory of manifest destiny went beyond simple land extension and into the belief that European settlers had the right to exploit Native women's bodies as a method of taming and "humanizing" them.&lt;ref name="Bubar, Roe 2004"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Ramirez, Renya. "Healing, Violence, and Native American Women". ''Social Justice'' 31.4 (98), Native Women and State Violence (2004): 103-16. 10 May 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Canada]] has an extensive problem with violence against indigenous women, by both indigenous men and non-aboriginals. Native Canadian women are 3.5 times more likely to experience violence than non-indigenous women.&lt;ref&gt;Statistics Canada. (2006). Measuring violence against women: Statistical trends 2006. Catalogue no. 85-570-XIE. Ottawa: Minister of Industry.&lt;/ref&gt; While Canadian national averages of violence against women are falling, they have remained the same for aboriginal communities throughout the years. The history of [[Canadian Indian residential school system|residential schools]] and economic inequality of indigenous Canadians has resulted in communities facing violence, unemployment, drug use, alcoholism, political corruption, and high rates of suicide.&lt;ref name="Bubar, Roe 2004"&gt;Bubar, Roe, and Pamela Jumper Thurman. "Violence Against Native Women". ''Social Justice'' 98th ser. 31.4 (2004): 70-86. Print.&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, there has been clear and admitted racism towards indigenous people by the [[Royal Canadian Mounted Police]], making victims less likely to report cases of domestic violence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Jackson |first=Kenneth |title=Top Mountie Admits Racism in Ranks towards Indigenous People |publisher=Aboriginal People's Television Network |date=9 December 2015 |url=http://aptn.ca/news/2015/12/09/top-mountie-admits-racism-in-ranks-towards-indigenous-people/}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Many of the issues facing indigenous women in Canada have been addressed via the Murdered and Missing Indigenous Women (MMIW) initiatives. Thousands of Native Canadian women have gone missing or been killed in the past 30 years, with little representation or attention from the government. Efforts to make the Canadian public aware of these women's disappearances have mostly been led by Aboriginal communities, who often reached across provinces to support one another. In 2015, prime minister [[Stephen Harper]] commented that the issue of murdered and missing indigenous women was "not high on our radar",&lt;ref&gt;News, CBC. "Full Text of Peter Mansbridge's Interview with Stephen Harper". CBC News. 4 February 2015.&lt;/ref&gt; prompting outrage in already frustrated indigenous communities. A few months later, Prime Minister [[Justin Trudeau]] launched an official inquiry into the Murdered and Missing Indigenous Women.

In the United States, Native American women are more than twice as likely to experience violence than any other demographic.&lt;ref name="Bubar, Roe 2004"/&gt; One in three Native women is sexually assaulted during her life, and over 85% of these assaults are perpetrated by non-Natives.&lt;ref name="Bubar, Roe 2004"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Chekuru, Kavitha. "Sexual Violence Scars Native American Women". Al Jazeera English. N.p., 6 March 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; The disproportionate rate of assault to indigenous women is due to a variety of causes, included but limited to the legal inability of tribes to prosecute perpetrators who are not tribal members. Tribes currently cannot exercise criminal jurisdiction over non-Natives. In theory, tribes can send cases to the federal level in order to prosecute non-Natives, but the majority of these cases are thrown out.&lt;ref&gt;Bachman, Ronet. ''Violence against American Indian and Alaska Native Women and the Criminal Justice Response: What Is Known''. Rockville, MD: United States Department of Justice, National Institute of Justice, National Criminal Justice Reference Service, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; As a result of this, many reservations have become popular destinations for rapists and serial killers.&lt;ref&gt;Gettys, Travis. "Outsiders Have Been Raping Native American Women with 'impunity' — but Legal Loophole May Finally Close". Raw Story. 6 April 2015.&lt;/ref&gt; Multiple versions of the Violence Against Women Act have attempted to address this issue, but these sections have often been removed from official versions of the act. Although the 2013 version of the act does allow tribes to prosecute non-Natives for domestic violence and violating restraining orders, it does not allow prosecution of perpetrators of incidents not included in a bought of domestic violence.&lt;ref&gt;"Introduction to the Violence Against Women Act", ''The Violence Against Women Act – Title IX: Safety for Indian Women''. N.p., n.d.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Violence against immigrant and refugee women===
Immigrant and refugee women often face violence, both in the private sphere (by partners and other family members) and in the public sphere (by the police and other authorities). These women are often in a vulnerable position: they do not speak the language of the country they are in, they do not know its laws, and sometimes they are in a legal position where they may be deported if they make contact with the authorities. Women who seek protection from armed conflict in their countries of origin often face more violence while travelling to the destination country or when they arrive there.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1016/j.rhm.2016.05.003 |pmid=27578335 |title=Sexual and gender-based violence against refugee women: A hidden aspect of the refugee 'crisis' |journal=Reproductive Health Matters |volume=24 |issue=47 |pages=18–26 |year=2017 |last1=Freedman |first1=Jane }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.euro.who.int/__data/assets/pdf_file/0018/319311/9-Sexual-violence-refugee-women.pdf?ua=1{{full citation needed|date=April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Sport-related===

Sport-related violence against women refers to any physical, sexual, mental acts that are "perpetrated by both male athletes and by male fans or consumers of sport and sporting events, as well as by coaches of female athletes".&lt;ref name="Catherine Palmer"&gt;{{cite book|last=Palmer|first=Catherine|title=Violence against women and sport: Literature review|year=2011|publisher=Durham University|location=London|pages=2–5|url=http://www.endviolenceagainstwomen.org.uk/resources/22/violence-against-women-and-sport-a-literature-review-by-dr-catherine-palmer}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The documenting reports and literature suggest that there are obvious connections between contemporary sport and violence against women. Such events as the [[2010 World Cup]], the [[Olympic Games|Olympic]] and [[Commonwealth Games]] "have highlighted the connections between sports spectatorship and intimate partner violence, and the need for police, authorities and services to be aware of this when planning sporting events".&lt;ref name="Catherine Palmer" /&gt;

Sport-related violence can occur in various contexts and places, including homes, pubs, clubs, hotel rooms, the streets.&lt;ref name="Catherine Palmer" /&gt;

====Sport-related violence by male college athletes====

Violence against women is a topic of concern in the United States' collegiate athletic community. From the 2010 UVA lacrosse murder, in which a male athlete was charged guilty with second degree murder of his girlfriend, to the 2004 University of Colorado Football Scandal when players were charged with nine alleged sexual assaults,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Vaughan|first=Kevin|title=Colorado woman seeks justice in alleged sexual assault Read more: Colorado woman seeks justice in alleged sexual assault|url=http://www.denverpost.com/firstinthepost/ci_12557039|work=Denver Post|accessdate=17 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; studies suggest that athletes are at higher risk for committing sexual assault against women than the average student.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Brady|first=Jeff|title=Scandal Returns to University of Colorado Football|url=http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=105381707|work=Weekend Edition|publisher=NPR|accessdate=12 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="chandler1999"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Chandler|first=Steve B|author2=Johnson, Dewayne J.|author3=Carroll, Pamela S.|title=Abusive Behaviors of College Athletes|journal=College Student Journal|date=1 December 1999|volume=33|issue=4}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is reported that one in three college assaults are committed by athletes.&lt;ref name="johnshopkins1"&gt;{{cite web|last=Mak|first=Stephanie|title=Are Athletes More Abusive Than the Rest of the Student Population?|url=http://web1.johnshopkins.edu/hurj/issue3/spotlight-mak.html|publisher=Hopkins Undergraduate Research Journal Online|accessdate=12 March 2012|deadurl=yes|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120229044851/http://web1.johnshopkins.edu/hurj/issue3/spotlight-mak.html|archivedate=29 February 2012|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; Surveys suggest that male student athletes who represent 3.3% of the college population, commit 19% of reported sexual assaults and 35% of domestic violence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Statistics|url=http://www.ncava.org/Statistics.html|publisher=The National Coalition Against Violent Athletes|accessdate=12 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The theories that surround these statistics range from misrepresentation of the student-athlete to an unhealthy mentality towards women within the team itself.&lt;ref name="johnshopkins1"/&gt;

====Controversy over contributing factors====

Sociologist Timothy Curry, after conducting an observational analysis of two big time sports' locker room conversations, deduced that the high risk of male student athletes for gender abuse is a result of the team's subculture.&lt;ref name=Curry1991&gt;{{cite journal|last=Curry|first=Timothy Jon|title=Fraternal Bonding in the Locker Room: A Profeminist Analysis Of Talk About Competition And Women|journal=Sociology of Sport Journal|year=1991|volume=8|issue=2|pages=119–135 |url=http://www.umt.edu/sociology/faculty_staff/ellestad/documents/275_Curry1991fraternalbondinginthelockerroom_s10.pdf |accessdate=12 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; He states, "Their locker room talk generally treated women as objects, encouraged sexist attitudes toward women and, in its extreme, promoted rape culture."&lt;ref name=Curry1991/&gt; He proposes that this objectification is a way for the male to reaffirm his heterosexual status and hyper-masculinity. Claims have been made that the atmosphere changes when an outsider (especially women) intrude in the locker room. In the wake of the reporter [[Lisa Olson]] being harassed by a Patriots player in the locker room in 1990, she reflected, "We are taught to think we must have done something wrong and it took me a while to realize I hadn't done anything wrong."&lt;ref name="Disch"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Disch|first=Lisa|author2=Kane, Mary Jo |title=When a Looker is Really a Bitch: Lisa Olson, Sport, and the Heterosexual Matrix|journal=Signs|date=Winter 1996|volume=21|issue=2|pages=278–308|jstor=3175065|doi=10.1086/495067}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other female sports reporters (college and professional) have claimed that they often brush off the players' comments, which leads to further objectification.&lt;ref name="Disch" /&gt; Other sociologists challenge this claim. Steve Chandler notes that because of their celebrity status on campus, "athletes are more likely to be scrutinized or falsely accused than non-athletes."&lt;ref name="chandler1999"/&gt; Another contender, Stephanie Mak, notes that, "if one considers the 1998 estimates that about three million women were battered and almost one million raped, the proportion of incidences that involve athletes in comparison to the regular population is relatively small."&lt;ref name="johnshopkins1"/&gt;

====Response to violence by male college athletes====

In response to the proposed link between college athletes and gender-based violence, and media coverage holding Universities as responsible for these scandals more universities are requiring athletes to attend workshops that promote awareness. For example, St. John's University holds sexual assault awareness classes in the fall for its incoming student athletes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Newsom|first=John|title=Share on emailShare on redditMore Sharing Services Few Colleges Tackle Issue of Athlete Sex Assaults|url=http://articles.latimes.com/1992-03-22/news/mn-7249_1_sexual-assault|publisher=Los Angeles Times Online |date=22 March 1992 |accessdate=12 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other groups, such as the National Coalition Against Violent Athletes, have formed to provide support for the victims as their mission statement reads, "The NCAVA works to eliminate off the field violence by athletes through the implementation of prevention methods that recognize and promote the positive leadership potential of athletes within their communities. In order to eliminate violence, the NCAVA is dedicated to empowering individuals affected by athlete violence through comprehensive services including advocacy, education and counseling."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Mission|url=http://www.ncava.org/Mission.html|publisher=National Coalition Against Violent Athletes|accessdate=12 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Cyberbullying===
[[Cyberbullying]] is a form of intimidation using electronic forms of contact. In the 21st century, cyberbullying has become increasingly common, especially among teenagers in Western countries.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Cyberbullying: its nature and impact in secondary school pupils|journal=The Journal of Child Psychology and Psychiatry | doi=10.1111/j.1469-7610.2007.01846.x|volume=49|issue=4|pages=376–385|year=2008|last1=Smith|first1=Peter K.|last2=Mahdavi|first2=Jess|last3=Carvalho|first3=Manuel|last4=Fisher|first4=Sonja|last5=Russell|first5=Shanette|last6=Tippett|first6=Neil}}&lt;/ref&gt;
On 24 September 2015, the [[United Nations Broadband Commission]] released a report that claimed that almost 75% percent of women [[online]] have encountered harassment and threats of violence, otherwise known as [[cyber violence]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.unwomen.org/en/news/stories/2015/9/cyber-violence-report-press-release |title=cyber violence report press release |publisher=UN Women |date= |accessdate=2016-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; Misogynistic rhetoric is prevalent online, and the public debate over gender-based attacks has increased significantly, leading to calls for policy interventions and better responses by social networks like [[Facebook]] and [[Twitter]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last= Jane |first= Emma Alice |title= 'Back to the kitchen, cunt': speaking the unspeakable about online misogyny |journal= [[Continuum: Journal of Media &amp; Cultural Studies]] |volume= 28 |issue= 4 |year= 2014 |pages= 558–570 |doi= 10.1080/10304312.2014.924479}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last= Philipovic |first= Jill |title= Blogging While Female: How Internet Misogyny Parallels Real-World Harassment| journal = Yale Journal of Law and Feminism |volume= 19 |issue= 2|pages= 295–303 |year= 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Activism==
[[File:A Russian poster urging open your eyes - against women being abused.jpg|thumb|250px|A Russian poster urging people to open their eyes about domestic violence against women]]
[[File:MintoParkMemorial.JPG|thumb|left|Memorial in [[Minto Park]], [[Ottawa]], of the victims of the [[École Polytechnique massacre]]]]
===Background and history===
Activism refers to "a doctrine or practice that emphasizes direct vigorous action especially in support of or opposition to one side of a controversial issue".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/activism |title=Activism |publisher=Merriam-Webster |date= |accessdate=2016-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the activism for violence against women, the objectives are to address and draw public attention on the issues of VAW as well as seek and recommend measures to prevent and eliminate this violence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Youngs, G.|date=2003|title= Private Pain/Public Peace: Women's Rights as Human Rights and Amnesty International's Report on Violence against Women|journal=Signs|volume=28 | issue = 4 |pages=1209–1229|jstor=10.1086/368325|doi=10.1086/368325}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many scholarly articles suggest that the VAW is considered as a violation of human rights&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author1=Htun, M.|author2= Weldon, S.|date=2012|title= The Civic Origins of Progressive Policy Change: Combating Violence against Women in Global Perspective, 1975–2005|journal=[[American Political Science Review]]|volume=1|pages=1–22 |url=http://polisci.unm.edu/common/documents/htun_apsa-article.pdf |accessdate= 2 December 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Carraway, G. C.|date=1991|title= Violence against Women of Color|journal=[[Stanford Law Review]]|volume=43 | issue = 6 |pages=1301–1309|jstor=1229040 |doi=10.2307/1229040}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Robinson, N. P.|date=2006|title= Origins of the International Day for the Elimination of Violence against Women: The Caribbean Contribution|journal=[[Caribbean Studies]]|volume=34 | issue = 2 |pages=141–161|jstor=25613539}}&lt;/ref&gt; as well as "public health issue".&lt;ref name="Michau, L. 2007 95–109"&gt;{{cite journal|author=Michau, L.|date=2007|title=Approaching Old Problems in New Ways: Community Mobilisation as a Primary Prevention Strategy to Combat Violence against Women|journal=Gender and Development|volume=15 | issue = 1 |pages=95–109|jstor=20461184|doi=10.1080/13552070601179144}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In order to better comprehend the anti-violence movements against VAW, there is a need to also understand the generic historical background of [[feminist movements]] in a holistic manner. Talking about the international women's movement, many feminist scholars have categorized these movements into three waves&lt;ref&gt;Kroløkke, C., &amp; Sørensen, A. S. (2006). Chapter 1: Three Waves of Feminism: From Suffragettes to Grrls. Gender communication theories &amp; analyses: from silence to performance (pp. 1-23). Thousand Oaks, Calif.: Sage Publications.&lt;/ref&gt; according to their different beliefs, strategies and goals.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author1=Rupp, L. J.|author2= Taylor, V.|date=1999|title= Forging Feminist Identity in an International Movement: A Collective Identity Approach to Twentieth-Century Feminism|journal=Signs|volume=24 | issue = 2 |pages=363–386|jstor=3175646|doi=10.1086/495344}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The emergence of the first women's movements, or so called the first wave of feminism, dated back in the years the late 19th Century and early 20th Century in the United States and Europe. During this period, the first series of feminist movements developed from the context of "industrial society and liberal politics" that trigger the 'feminist groups' with the concern of equal access and opportunity for women.&lt;ref&gt;Kroløkke, C., &amp; Sørensen, A. S. (2006). Chapter 1: Three Waves of Feminism: From Suffragettes to Grrls. Gender communication theories &amp; analyses: from silence to performance (pp. 1-23). Thousand Oaks, Calif.: Sage Publications, pp. 1&lt;/ref&gt; This wave marks a period of "suffrage, independence, rights to nationality, work and equal pay" for women.&lt;ref name="Prügl, E. Dec. 2013"&gt;Prügl, E. (Lecturer) (2 December 2013, ). Gender and International Affairs 2013. International Feminist Movements. Lecture conducted from The Graduate Institute of International and Development Studies (IHEID), Geneva, Switzerland.&lt;/ref&gt;

The second wave of feminist movements was the series of movements from the period of the "late 1960s to early 1970s". It was noted by feminist scholars that this wave could be characterized as a period of women's liberation and the rise of a branch of feminism known as 'radical feminism'.&lt;ref&gt;Kroløkke, C., &amp; Sørensen, A. S. (2006). Chapter 1: Three Waves of Feminism: From Suffragettes to Grrls. Gender communication theories &amp; analyses: from silence to performance (pp. 1-23). Thousand Oaks, Calif.: Sage Publications, pp. 7-8&lt;/ref&gt; This wave of feminism emerged in the context of postwar period&lt;ref&gt;Kroløkke, C., &amp; Sørensen, A. S. (2006). Chapter 1: Three Waves of Feminism: From Suffragettes to Grrls. Gender communication theories &amp; analyses: from silence to performance (pp. 1-23). Thousand Oaks, Calif.: Sage Publications, pp. 8&lt;/ref&gt; and society where other mainstream movements also played a large role; for instance, the civil rights movements,&lt;ref name="Prügl, E. Dec. 2013" /&gt; which meant to condemn 'capitalism', 'imperialism' and 'oppression' of people based on the notion of race, ethnicity, gender identity and sexual orientation.&lt;ref&gt;Kroløkke, C., &amp; Sørensen, A. S. (2006). Chapter 1: Three Waves of Feminism: From Suffragettes to Grrls. Gender communication theories &amp; analyses: from silence to performance (pp. 1–23). Thousand Oaks, Calif.: Sage Publications, pp. 9&lt;/ref&gt; This wave marks a period of equal rights at home and workplace as well as rights to development&lt;ref name="Prügl, E. Dec. 2013" /&gt; for the purposes of people of different races, ethnicities, economic statuses and gender identities.

The third wave of feminism is the newest wave of feminism led by young feminists whose understanding and context are of the globalized world order with an invention of many new technologies Also, this wave is a transition of the fall communism&lt;ref&gt;Kroløkke, C., &amp; Sørensen, A. S. (2006). Chapter 1: Three Waves of Feminism: From Suffragettes to Grrls. Gender communication theories &amp; analyses: from silence to performance (pp. 1-23). Thousand Oaks, Calif.: Sage Publications, pp. 17&lt;/ref&gt; to more complex issues of new kinds of 'warfare', threats and violence. This new wave also "embraces ambiguity"&lt;ref&gt;Kroløkke, C., &amp; Sørensen, A. S. (2006), pp. 16&lt;/ref&gt; and introduced a feminist approach of 'intersectionality' that includes the issues of "gender, race, class and age-related".&lt;ref&gt;Kroløkke, C., &amp; Sørensen, A. S. (2006): pp. 17&lt;/ref&gt; Other than that, the third wave marks a period of feminism dealing with identity politics, body politics as well as the issues of violence.&lt;ref&gt;Lind, A. (Lecturer) (2 December 2013). Gender and International Affairs 2013. International Feminist Movements. Lecture conducted from The Graduate Institute of International and Development Studies (IHEID), Geneva, Switzerland.&lt;/ref&gt;

Nonetheless, the VAW movement was initiated in the 1970s where some feminist movements started to bring the discussion on the issue of violence into the feminist discourse&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ncdsv.org/images/Ms_StoppingVAWTheMovementFromInterventionToPrevention_Aug2005.pdf |format=PDF |title=Stopping the Violence Against Women: The Movement From Intervention to Prevention |publisher=National Center on Domestic and Sexual Violence |accessdate=2016-04-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; and that many other groups, on the national as well as international levels, had attempted to push for the betterment of women through lobbying of the state officials and delegates, demanding the conferences on 'gender issues'&lt;ref name="Prügl, E. Dec. 2013" /&gt; and thus made the VAW known to a wider range of population. Therefore, to put this into the theoretical context, VAW can be categorized along with the third wave of feminism whose one of its focuses is on 'violence.'

VAW activist movements come in many forms and operate through different levels at "local, national and international levels"&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Youngs, G.|date=2003|title=Private Pain/Public Peace: Women's Rights as Human Rights and Amnesty International's Report on Violence against Women|journal=Signs|volume=28 | issue = 4 |pages=1209–1229|jstor= 10.1086/368325|doi=10.1086/368325}}&lt;/ref&gt; and different approaches: health and human rights frameworks.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Miller, A. M.|date=2004|title=Sexuality, Violence against Women, and Human Rights: Women Make Demands and Ladies Get Protection|journal=[[Health and Human Rights]]|volume=7 | issue = 2 |pages=16–47|jstor=4065347 |doi=10.2307/4065347}}&lt;/ref&gt; The movements stemmed mostly from social movements and groups of women who see the need to create organizations to 'lobby' their governments to establish "sanctuaries, shelters" and provision of services that help protecting these victims or so-called ''battered women'' from acts of violence. The term ''battered women'' was used in a number of VAW movements and had its root in the early stage of organizing efforts to tackle the problem of violence against women in many regions of the world such as Africa, Asia Pacific, Latin American and the Caribbean.&lt;ref&gt;Fried, Susana T. "Violence Against Women". ''Health and Human Rights'' 6, no. 2 (2003): 88-111, pp. 94&lt;/ref&gt; The activist organizations against VAW, some with and the others without the support of their governments, attempted to develop "innovative efforts" to assist the ''battered women'' by providing services such as shelters and centers for these women; drafting and lobbying the governments to include the recognition and language of VAW into national legislations and [[international human rights instruments]]; advocating to raise the awareness of people via education and training sessions; forming national, regional as well as international networks to empower the movements; organizing demonstration and gathering more efforts to end violence acts against women.&lt;ref&gt;Fried, pp. 88-89&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, many women's rights activist groups see the issue of violence against women as a central focus of their movements. Many of these groups take 'human rights' approach as the integral framework of their activism. These VAW movements also employ the idea of 'women's rights are human rights', transform the concepts and ideas of 'human rights', which are mostly reckoned to be 'Western concepts' and '[[Vernacularization|vernacularize]] them into the concepts that can be understood in their local institutions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Merry | first1 = S. E. | year = 2006 | title = Transnational Human Rights and Local Activism: Mapping the Middle | url = | journal = American Anthropologist | volume = 108 | issue = 1| pages = 38–51 [39] | doi=10.1525/aa.2006.108.1.38}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Levels of activist movements ===
[[File:Girl_Summit_-_22nd_July_in_London_(14498368279).jpg|thumb|250px|Poster against child and forced marriage]]
[[File:Marcha_Ni_una_menos_1.JPG|thumb|250px|right|Mass protest against violence against women in [[Buenos Aires]] in 2015]]
On the local or national level, the VAW movements are diverse and differ in their strategic program of intervention. The strategies used in a number of the movements focus on the individual level with the emphases on individuals, relationships and family. Also, many of them take the 'preventive' as an approach to tackle the issues on the ground by encouraging people to "reexamine their attitudes and beliefs" in order to trigger and create fundamental changes in these "deep-rooted beliefs and behaviors".&lt;ref name="Michau, L. 2007 95–109"/&gt; Despite the fact that these strategies can be life changing, helpful to those who participate and feasible over a long time frame, the effects on societal level seem to be restricted and of minimal effects. In order to achieve the objectives of the movement, ending the violence against women, many activists and scholar seem to argue that they have to initiate the changes on the communal level in the norms and cultural attitudes, which were the sources that permit the abusive behavior of men toward women.&lt;ref&gt;Heise, L., M. Ellsberg and M. Gottemoeller (1999). Ending Violence Against Women, ''Population Reports'', Series L, No. 11, Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University School of Public Health, Population and Information Program, p. 38&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/ref&gt; An example of activism on the local level can be seen in South Africa. The movements of VAW in this context employ a strategy that is based on the 'prevention' approach, which is applicable on individual and societal levels: in families and communities. This movement encourages the individuals and small populations to rethink about their attitudes and beliefs in order to create a possibility to alter these deep-rooted beliefs and behaviors, which lead to the act of violence against women.&lt;ref name="Michau, L. 2007 pp.96"/&gt; Another example is the local level movement in East Africa that employs the prevention approach, which is applicable on the communal level. They call this approach a 'raising voices' approach. This approach employs an 'ad hoc' framework that can be used complementarily with the individual approach where the strategy is to aggravate the status quo issues onto the individuals' and communities' perception and establish a common ground of interests for them to push for the movement, but in a short time of period.&lt;ref name="Michau, L. 2007 pp.96"/&gt; In addition, on the domestic level, there seems to be many 'autonomous movements.'&lt;ref name="cambridge1"&gt;{{cite journal|author1=Htun, M.|author2=Weldon, S. L.|date=2012|title=The Civic Origins of Progressive Policy Change: Combating Violence against Women in Global Perspective, 1975–2005|journal=[[American Political Science Review]]|volume=1|pages= 1–22 |url=http://journals.cambridge.org/abstract_S0003055412000226 |accessdate=15 December 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; feminist movements (for VAW) can be understood as "a form of women's mobilization that is devoted to promoting women's status and well-being independently of political parties and other associations that do not have the status of women as their main concern".&lt;ref name="cambridge1"/&gt;

A number of regions of the world have come together to address violence against women. In South America, the Southern Cone Network Against Domestic Violence has worked extensively to address sexual and domestic violence since 1989.The Latin American and Caribbean Network Against Domestic and Sexual Violence, formed in 1990, includes representation from twenty-one different countries and has been instrumental in increasing the visibility of VAW.&lt;ref&gt;Fried, Susana T. "Violence against Women". ''Health and Human Rights'' 6.2 (2003): 88.&lt;/ref&gt; In September 1999, the Heads of States of the Southern African Development Community (SADC) met and drafted the "Prevention and Eradication of Violence Against Women and Children", a document that condemned violence against women and children, and resolved a set of 13 methods of addressing it, reaching into the legal; social, economic, cultural, and political; social service; and education, training, and awareness building sectors.&lt;ref&gt;"The Prevention and Eradication of Violence against Women and Children". ''Review of African Political Economy'' 1999; 26(81): 415-17.&lt;/ref&gt;

On the transnational or regional level, the anti-violence movements also deploy different strategies based on the specificities of their cultures and beliefs in their particular regions. On this level, the activist movements are known as "transnational feminist networks" or TFNs.&lt;ref name="Htun"&gt;Htun, M., &amp; Weldon, S. L. (2012), pp. 9&lt;/ref&gt; The TFNs have a significant effect, like the autonomous movements on the national level, in shaping sets of policies as well pushing for the recognition and inclusion of language of VAW in the United Nations human rights mechanisms: the international human rights agreements.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author1=Htun, M.|author2=Weldon, S. L.|date=2012|title=The Civic Origins of Progressive Policy Change: Combating Violence against Women in Global Perspective, 1975–2005|journal=[[American Political Science Review]]|volume=1|pages= 1–22 |url=http://journals.cambridge.org/abstract_S0003055412000226 |accessdate=15 December 2013}}
&lt;/ref&gt; Their activities are ranging from lobbying the policy makers; organizing demonstrations on the local and regional levels; to creating institutional pressure that could push for changes in the international institutional measures.&lt;ref name="cambridge1"/&gt;

On the international level, the movements that advocate for women's rights and against VAW are the mixture of (civil society) actors from the domestic and regional levels. On this level, the objectives of VAW movements focus on "creating shared expectations" within the domestic and regional levels as well as "mobilizing numbers of domestic civil society" to create "standards in global civil society".&lt;ref name="Htun"/&gt; The global women's movement determine to transform numbers of international conventions and conferences to "a conference on women's rights" by pushing for a "stronger language and clearer recognition" of the VAW issues. In addition, the United Nations also plays a vital role in promoting and campaigning for the VAW movements on the international level. For instance, in 2008, Ban Ki-Moon, the UN Secretary General has initiated and launched the campaign called "UniTE To End Violence Against Women". This campaign "calls on governments, civil society, women's organizations, young people, the private sector, the media and the entire UN system to join forces in addressing the global pandemic of violence against women and girls".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.unwomen.org/en/what-we-do/ending-violence-against-women/take-action |title=Take action Say NO UNiTE |publisher=UN Women |date= |accessdate=2016-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; Moreover, this campaign also announces every 25th of the month to be "Orange Day" or "a day to take action to raise awareness and prevent violence against women and girls".&lt;ref&gt;Take action Say NO UNiTE | UN Women - Headquarters. (n.d.).
&lt;/ref&gt;

In conclusion, each level of activism is intertwined and has the common purpose to end violence against women. The activism on the local level can significantly affect the movements on the other levels: transnational and international levels. All in all, the effort on different levels lead to change that can perpetrate to all levels. In a scholarly article on ''Combating Violence Against Women'', the authors illustrated from their research analysis on how the norms of international society can shape and influence the policy making on the domestic or national level and vice versa. They argue that there are 'three' mechanisms, which have effects on the making of national policies as well as global agreements and conventions. Three of which are "1) the influence of global treaties and documents such as [[CEDAW]] on women's rights" - on the national policies "2) the influence of regional agreements on VAW (particularly after certain tipping points are reached)" - on both domestic policies and international conventions and "3) regional demonstration effects or pressure for conformity captured as diffusion within regions" - on the international norms and agreements.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author1=Htun, M.|author2=Weldon, S. L.|date=2012|title=The Civic Origins of Progressive Policy Change: Combating Violence against Women in Global Perspective, 1975–2005|journal=[[American Political Science Review]]|volume=1|pages= 1–22 |url=http://journals.cambridge.org/abstract_S0003055412000226 |accessdate=15 December 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Achievements of the VAW movements ===
On the global level:
* The first major document that highlights the recognition of violence against women as a human rights violation: the United Nations [[Declaration on the Elimination of Violence Against Women]] in Vienna, 1993.&lt;ref name="Brown Thompson 2002"&gt;Brown Thompson, Karen. 2002. "Women's Rights are Human Rights". In Restructuring World Politics: Transnational Social Movements, Networks, and Norms, eds. S. Khagram, J. V. Riker, and K. Sikkink. Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press, 96–122.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Elman, R. Amy. 2007. Sexual Equality in an Integrated Europe: Virtual Equality. Europe in Transition: The NYU European Studies Series. Basingstoke, UK: Palgrave Macmillan.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Weldon, S.L 2006"&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Weldon | first1 = S. L. | year = 2006 | title = Inclusion, Solidarity and Social Movements: The Global Movement on Gender Violence | url = | journal = Perspectives on Politics | volume = 4 | issue = 1| pages = 55–74 | doi=10.1017/s1537592706060063}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was a result of collective effort of global feminist movement to transform the Vienna conference from a general and mainstream human rights conference into the conference on women's rights. As before the other human rights organizations such as Amnesty International and Human Rights Watch did not focus on the issue of VAW and did not consider rape and domestic violence as violations of human rights despite of the fact that they also have agenda on women's rights.&lt;ref name="Htun"/&gt;
* The 1995 [[Fourth World Conference on Women]] in Beijing&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.un.org/womenwatch/daw/beijing/pdf/BDPfA%20E.pdf |format=PDF |title=Beijing Declaration and Platform for Action |publisher=United Nations |accessdate=2016-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; During the 4th Women Conference, VAW was emphasized and named as a critical concern. Also, the spillover effect was that this push highlighted the need for the development of "new international norms" that have often been used by activists and governments the proposition of legislation that provide other action to redress the acts of violence.&lt;ref name="Brown Thompson 2002"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Weldon, S.L 2006"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Fábián, Katalin, ed. 2010. Domestic Violence in Postcommunist States. Bloomington: Indiana University Press.&lt;/ref&gt;
* Subsequently, the push from the global feminist movement also push for the fully incorporation of the VAW issues into the "Committee on the Elimination of Discrimination Against Women" or [[CEDAW]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.un.org/womenwatch/daw/cedaw/committee.htm |title=Committee on the Elimination of Discrimination against Women |publisher=United Nations |date=2003-12-31 |accessdate=2016-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; whereas the "original text of [[CEDAW]] in 1979 did not explicitly mention violence against women"&lt;ref&gt;Htun, M., &amp; Weldon, S. L. (2012), pp. 9&lt;/ref&gt;
On the regional level:
* ''Americas'': the Inter-American Convention on Violence Against Women, which was formally announced and adopted by the [[Organization of American States]] (OAS) in 1994, immediately after the Vienna Conference&lt;ref name="Htun Weldon p. 10"&gt;Htun, M., &amp; Weldon, S. L. (2012), p. 10&lt;/ref&gt;
* ''Europe'': The [[European Union]] (EU)'s initiatives to combat violence against women after the 1990s: the 1997 resolution calling for a zero tolerance: specifically on UN human rights instruments of [[CEDAW]] and the [[Vienna Declaration and Programme of Action|Vienna Declaration]].
** The [[Council of Europe]] also developed "a series of initiatives" related to the issue of VAW: "the 2000 resolution on trafficking, the 2003 resolution on domestic violence, and the 2004 resolution on honor crimes" as well as promoted "the 2002 recommendation on the protection of women against violence and established its monitoring framework".&lt;ref&gt;Htun, M., &amp; Weldon, S. L. (2012), pp. 10&lt;/ref&gt;
* ''Africa'': 
** There emerged a series of regional meetings and agreements, which was triggered by the UN processes on the international level such as Third World Conference on Women in Nairobi, 1985; the 1993 Kampala Prep Com; the 1994 Africa-wide UN women's conference&lt;ref&gt;Tripp, Aili Mari, Isabel Casimiro, Joy Kwesiga, and Alice Mungwa. (2009). African Women's Movements: Changing Political Landscapes. New York: Cambridge University Press.&lt;/ref&gt; that led to the identification of VAW as a critical issue in the Southern African Women's Charter.&lt;ref name="Htun Weldon p. 10" /&gt;

==Access to justice for women victims of violence==

===International and regional instruments===
Efforts to fight violence against women can take many forms and access to justice, or lack thereof, for such violence varies greatly depending on the justice system. International and regional instruments are increasingly used as the basis for national legislation and policies to eradicate violence against women.

The Inter-American Convention to Prevent, Eradicate and Punish Violence Against Women – also known as the Belém do Parà Convention, for instance, has been applied by the Inter-American Commission on Human Rights (IACHR) in its first case of domestic violence to condemn Brazil in the Maria da Penha case. This led the Brazilian government to enact in 2006 the Maria da Penha Law, the country's first law against domestic violence against women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Spieler |first1=Paula |title=The Maria da Penha Case and the Inter-American Commission on Human Rights: Contributions to the Debate on Domestic Violence Against Women in Brazil |journal=Indiana Journal of Global Legal Studies |volume=18 |issue=1 |year=2011 |pages=121–43 |url=https://muse.jhu.edu/article/445824 }}&lt;/ref&gt; There is also, for instance, the South Asian Agreement on Regional Cooperation's (SAARC) Protocol to End Trafficking in Women and Children.&lt;ref name="FRIED, Susana T 2003"/&gt;

===Examples of measures put in place===
As violence is often committed by a family member, women first started by lobbying their governments to set up shelters for domestic violence survivors. The Julia Burgos Protected House established in Puerto Rico in 1979 was the first shelter in Latin America and the Caribbean for « battered women ». In 2003, 18 out of the 20 countries in the region had legislation on domestic or family violence, and 11 countries addressed sexual violence in their laws. Legislative measures to protect victims can include restraining orders, which can be found in Colombia, El Salvador, Guatemala, Paraguay, Venezuela, Turkey, the United States and many western European countries for instance.

Courts can also be allowed by law (Germany, 2001) to order the perpetrator to leave the home so that victims do not have to seek shelter. Countries were urged to repeal discriminatory legislation by 2005 following the review of the Beijing Declaration and Platform for Action in 2000. Egypt, for instance, abolished a law that exempted men from rape charges when marrying their victims. However, the goal of antiviolence legislation is often to keep the families together, regardless of the best interests of women, which perpetuate domestic violence.&lt;ref name="FRIED, Susana T 2003"&gt;Fried, Susana T, 'Violence against Women'. ''Health and Human Rights'', Vol. 6, No.2, Violence, Health, and Human Rights (2003)&lt;/ref&gt;

Innovative measures have been pioneered in a number of countries to end violence against women. In Brazil and Jordan, [[women's police stations]] have been introduced, and one-stop [[women's shelter]]s were created in Malaysia and Nicaragua.

[[Marital rape]] has been illegal in every American state and the District of Columbia since 1993, but is rarely prosecuted in America.&lt;ref name="rainn.org"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rainn.org/public-policy/sexual-assault-issues/marital-rape |title=Marital Rape |website=Rape, Abuse and Incest National Network |date= |accessdate=2016-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2013 the [[UN General Assembly]] passed its first resolution calling for the protection of defenders of women's human rights.&lt;ref name="Norway Post" /&gt; The resolution urges states to put in place gender-specific laws and policies for the protection of women's human rights defenders and to ensure that defenders themselves are involved in the design and implementation of these measures, and calls on states to protect women's human rights defenders from reprisals for cooperating with the UN and to ensure their unhindered access to and communication with international human rights bodies and mechanisms.&lt;ref name="awid.org"/&gt;

=== Challenges faced by women in accessing justice and limitations of measures ===
There can be a de jure or de facto acceptance of violent behaviors and lack of remedies for victims.&lt;ref name="FRIED, Susana T 2003"/&gt;

&lt;nowiki&gt;*&lt;/nowiki&gt; '''Lack of criminalization'''. In many places, acts of abuse, especially acts such as [[female genital mutilation]], [[marital rape]], [[forced marriage]] and [[child marriage]], are not criminalized, or are illegal but widely tolerated, with the laws against them being rarely enforced. There are instances where crimes against women are also categorized as minor offenses.

&lt;nowiki&gt;*&lt;/nowiki&gt;'''Lack of awareness of the existing laws'''. In many places, although there are laws against violence on the books, many women do not know of their existence. This is especially the case with marital rape - its criminalization being very recent in most countries.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.amnesty.org/en/library/asset/EUR27/002/2007/en/71da229c-d39d-11dd-a329-2f46302a8cc6/eur270022007en.pdf |title=Archived copy |accessdate=8 January 2013 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110608032444/http://www.amnesty.org/en/library/asset/EUR27/002/2007/en/71da229c-d39d-11dd-a329-2f46302a8cc6/eur270022007en.pdf |archivedate=8 June 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/6643727.stm | publisher=BBC News | title=Hungary law 'fails rape victims' | date=10 May 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |author=Patsy Moy |url=http://www.scmp.com/article/435610/publicity-urged-law-marital-rape |title=Publicity urged for law on marital rape |newspaper=South China Morning Post |date= 23 November 2003 |accessdate=2016-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;nowiki&gt;*&lt;/nowiki&gt; '''Challenges in making a case in court'''. The burden of proof can be placed on the victim. For instance in the Philippines, before a change in law in 1997, rape used to be described as a crime against chastity; and virginity played an important role in court. In various countries, such as [[Bangladesh]], a woman's past sexual experience continues to be very important in a case of rape. Bangladesh has received criticism for its employment of the "two-finger test" in rape investigations. This test consists in a physical examination of women who report rape during which a doctor inserts two fingers in the woman's vagina to determine whether the woman is "habituated to sex". This examination has its origin in the country's British colonial-era laws dating back to 1872. This deters many women from reporting rape. More than 100 experts, including doctors, lawyers, police, and women's rights activists had signed a joint statement in 2013 asking for the test, which they called "demeaning", to be abolished, as it "does not provide any evidence that is relevant to proving the offence". This test is also performed in several other countries in the region, including India.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.blast.org.bd/content/pressrelease/press-release-nc-2-2-2013.pdf |format=PDF |title=100 Experts Demand Change in Medical Evidence Laws and Justice For Rape Victims |publisher=Bangladesh Legal Aid Services Trust |accessdate=2016-04-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ndtv.com/article/world/bangladesh-activists-urge-ban-on-rape-victim-finger-test-326175 |title=Bangladesh activists urge ban on rape victim 'finger test' |publisher=NDTV |date=2013-02-04 |accessdate=2016-04-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Park |first=Madison |url=http://edition.cnn.com/2013/02/05/world/asia/rape-exam-india/index.html |title=Activists: Get rid of 'degrading' parts of India's sexual assault exam |publisher=CNN |date=2013-02-06 |accessdate=2016-04-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; It can also be difficult to make a case of sexual assault in court, when members of the judiciary expect evidence of severe struggle and injury as determinative evidence of non-consent. On the other hand, there are measures, such as the 2012 law in Brazil, that allow for cases to be filed even without the representation of the victim.

&lt;nowiki&gt;*&lt;/nowiki&gt; '''Existing laws are insufficient, conflicting, and have no effect in practice'''. Some laws on domestic violence, for instance, conflict with other provisions and ultimately contradict their goals. Legal frameworks can also be flawed when laws that integrate protection do so in isolation, notably in relation to immigration laws. Undocumented women in countries where they would have, in theory, access to justice, don't in practice for fear of being denounced and deported. The CEDAW Committee recommends that a State authority's obligation to report undocumented persons be repealed in national legislation.

&lt;nowiki&gt;*&lt;/nowiki&gt; '''The attitude of the police'''. Women who report acts of violence most often come into contact first with police workers. Therefore, police attitudes are crucial in facilitating a sense of safety and comfort for women who have been victimized.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1177/0886260506291653 |pmid=16940401 |title=Police Attitudes Toward Domestic Violence Offenders Journal of Interpersonal Violence |journal=Journal of Interpersonal Violence |volume=21 |issue=10 |pages=1365–74 |year=2016 |last1=Logan |first1=T K |last2=Shannon |first2=Lisa |last3=Walker |first3=Robert }}&lt;/ref&gt; When police officers have hostile attitudes towards victimized women, these women are prevented from obtaining justice.&lt;ref&gt;https://www.theguardian.com/society/2016/may/17/police-treatment-of-domestic-abuse-victims-to-be-investigated{{full}}&lt;/ref&gt; Recognizing these problems, some countries have enacted [[women's police station]], which are [[police station]]s that specialize in certain crimes, such as [[sexual violence]], [[harassment]], [[domestic violence]] committed against women.

Measures to address violence against women range from access to legal-aid to the provision of shelters and hotlines for victims. Despite advances in legislation and policies, the lack of implementation of the measures put in place prevents significant progress in eradicating violence against women globally. This failure to apply existing laws and procedures is often due to the persisting issue of gender stereotyping.&lt;ref&gt;CEDAW, ''General discussion on women and access to justice'', United Nations Office at Geneva, 18 February 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Relation with marriage laws==
[[File:Marriage_is_no_excuse_for_rape.png|thumb|Sign against justification of violence in marriage]] 
{{Further information|Criticism of marriage|Sexism#Coverture_and_other_marriage_regulations}}
The relation between violence against women and marriage laws, regulations and traditions has also been discussed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://citation.allacademic.com/meta/p_mla_apa_research_citation/0/4/1/2/5/p41259_index.html?phpsessid=f010300715dd72dcad0107c9ca4fd030 |title=Recognizing Marriage as a Symbolic Institution |publisher=American Political Science Association |date= |accessdate=2016-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=9mlFgjEBYWYC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=the+industrial+vagina&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=BVQ7UqTUN-Tl4gTIoYGADg&amp;redir_esc=y#v=onepage&amp;q=the%20industrial%20vagina&amp;f=false |title=The Industrial Vagina: The Political Economy of the Global Sex Trade |author=Sheila Jeffreys |via=Books.google.ro |date= |accessdate=2016-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; The US and English law subscribed until the 20th century to the system of [[coverture]], that is, a legal doctrine under which, upon marriage, a woman's legal rights were subsumed by those of her husband.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lonang.com/exlibris/blackstone/bla-115.htm |title=Husband And Wife - LONANG Institute |publisher=LONANG Institute |date= |accessdate=2016-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; Today, outside the West, many countries severely restrict the rights of married women: for example, in [[Yemen]], marriage regulations state that a wife must obey her husband and must not leave home without his permission.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www2.ohchr.org/english/bodies/hrc/docs/ngos/Yemen%27s%20darkside-discrimination_Yemen_HRC101.pdf |format=PDF |title=Yemen's Dark Side |publisher=[[Office of the United Nations High Commissioner for Human Rights]] |accessdate=2016-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Iraq]] husbands have a legal right to "punish" their wives. The criminal code states at Paragraph 41 that there is no crime if an act is committed while exercising a legal right; examples of legal rights include: "The punishment of a wife by her husband, the disciplining by parents and teachers of children under their authority within certain limits prescribed by law or by custom".&lt;ref&gt;[http://law.case.edu/saddamtrial/documents/Iraqi_Penal_Code_1969.pdf Grotian Moment Blog &gt; Frederick K. Cox International Law Center &gt; Case Western Reserve University School of Law&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20121021100954/http://law.case.edu/saddamtrial/documents/Iraqi_Penal_Code_1969.pdf |date=21 October 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In the West, married women faced discrimination until just a few decades ago: for instance, in [[France]], married women received the right to work without their husband's permission in 1965.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.tandf.co.uk/journals/explore/cmcf-vsi-women-in-france.pdf |format=PDF |title=Modern &amp; Contemporary France : Women in France |publisher=Tandf.co.uk |accessdate=2016-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.parisvoice.com/-archives-97-86/282-frances-leading-women-show-the-way |title=France's leading women show the way |publisher=Paris Voice |date= |accessdate=2016-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.womeninworldhistory.com/TWR-07.html|title=Lesson : The French Civil Code (Napoleonic Code) : Teaching Women's Rights From Past to Present|publisher=Women in World History Curriculum |accessdate=2016-04-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Spain]], during the Franco era, a married woman required her husband's consent (''permiso marital'') for nearly all economic activities, including employment, ownership of property and traveling away from home; the permiso marital was abolished in 1975.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://countrystudies.us/spain/43.htm |title=Spain - Social Values And Attitudes |publisher=Country Studies, Federal Research Division of the Library of Congress |date= |accessdate=2016-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; Concerns exist about violence related to marriage - both inside marriage (physical abuse, sexual violence, restriction of liberty) and in relation to marriage customs ([[dowry]], [[bride price]], [[forced marriage]], [[child marriage]], [[marriage by abduction]], violence related to female premarital [[virginity]]). Claudia Card, professor of Philosophy at the University of Wisconsin-Madison, writes:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://pol285.blog.gustavus.edu/files/2009/08/Card_Against_Marriage.pdf |format=PDF |title=Against Marriage and Motherhood |author=Claudia Card |publisher=Gustavus Adolphus College |accessdate=2016-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;
:"The legal rights of access that married partners have to each other's persons, property, and lives makes it all but impossible for a spouse to defend herself (or himself), or to be protected against torture, rape, battery, stalking, mayhem, or murder by the other spouse... Legal marriage thus enlists state support for conditions conducive to murder and mayhem."

==See also==

&lt;!-- New links in alphabetical order please --&gt;
*[[Bodily integrity]]
*[[Children's rights]]
*[[Eve teasing]]
*[[List of incidents of violence against women]], list of notable incidents of violence against women sorted by country and year
*[[Military sexual trauma]]
*[[Misogyny in horror films]]
*[[School-related gender-based violence (SRGBV)]]
*[[Sexism]]
*[[Sexual assault in the U.S. military]]
*[[United Nations Security Council Resolution 1325]]
*[[Violence against LGBT people]]
*[[Violence against men]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
*{{Cite journal | last1 = Durham | first1 = Meenakshi G. | authorlink1 = Meenakshi Gigi Durham | title = Vicious assault shakes Texas town: the politics of gender violence in The New York Times' coverage of a schoolgirl's gang rape | journal = Journalism Studies | volume = 14 | issue = 1 | pages = 1–12 | publisher = Taylor &amp; Francis Online | doi = 10.1080/1461670X.2012.657907 | date = February 2013 | ref = harv }}
*Bellemare, Marc F. [http://marcfbellemare.com/wordpress/2013/06/explaining-the-persistence-of-female-genital-cutting-in-the-gambia/ New Working Paper: Explaining the Persistence of Female Genital Cutting in The Gambia] 17 June 2013.
*Gerry Mackie, [http://dss.ucsd.edu/~gmackie/documents/FGCHarmlessPractice.pdf Female Genital Cutting: A harmless Practice?] Medical Anthropology Quarterly. 135-158p. 
*Jacqui True, "The Political Economy of Violence against Women". USA. 2012. {{ISBN|978-0-19-975591-2}}
*{{cite journal | last1 = James | first1 = S.M. | year = 1998 | title = Shades of Othering: Reflections on Female Circumcision/Genital Mutilation | url = | journal = Signs | volume = 23 | issue = 4| pages = 1031–1048 | doi=10.1086/495300}}
*{{cite journal | last1 = Jones | first1 = H. | last2 = Diop | first2 = N. | last3 = Askew | first3 = I. | last4 = Kabore | first4 = I. | year = 1999 | title = Female Genital Cutting Practices in Burkina Faso and Mali and Their Negative Health Outcomes | url = | journal = Studies in Family Planning | volume = 30 | issue = 3| pages = 219–230 | doi=10.1111/j.1728-4465.1999.00219.x}}
*{{cite journal | last1 = Jones | first1 = W.K. | last2 = Smith | first2 = B. Kieke Jr. | last3 = Wilcox | first3 = L. | year = 1997 | title = Female Genital Mutilation/Female Circumcision: Who Is at Risk in the US? | url = | journal = Public Health Reports | volume = 112 | issue = 5| pages = 368–377 }}
*Kwame Anthony Appiah, [https://web.archive.org/web/20131212131130/http://bigthink.com/videos/convincing-other-cultures-to-change Convincing Other Cultures to Change]. 21 September 2010, Big Think.
*{{cite journal | last1 = Kelly | first1 = Liz | date = 4–5 December 2005 | title = Inside Outsiders: Mainstreaming violence against women into human rights discourse and practice | url = | journal = International Feminist Journal of Politics | volume = | issue = | pages = 451–495 }}
*Lori L. Heise, Jacqueline Pitanguy and Adrienne Germain, "Violence against Women (World Bank, 1994): The Hidden Health Burden". World Bank Discussion Paper No. 255. The World Bank Washington, D.C.
*Nora Almosaed (2004), Violence against women: a cross-cultural perspective. Published online: 23 Jan, 2007. Journal of Muslim Minority Affairs.
*{{cite journal | last1 = Shell-Duncan | first1 = B. | last2 = Hernlund | first2 = Y. | year = 2006 | title = Are there 'Stages of Change' in the Practice of Female Genital Cutting? Qualitative Research Findings from Senegal and the Gambia | url = | journal = African Journal of Reproductive Health | volume = 10 | issue = 2| pages = 56–71 }}
*Skaine, R. (2005), Female Genital Mutilation: Legal, Cultural and Medical Issues, Jefferson, NC: McFarland &amp; Company, Inc.
*Wagner, N. (2013), "Why Female Genital Cutting Persist?", Working Paper, University of Rotterdam.
*{{cite journal | last1 = Wakabi | first1 = W | year = 2007 | title = Africa Battles to Make Female Genital Mutilation History | url = | journal = The Lancet | volume = 369 | issue = 9567| pages = 1069–70 | doi=10.1016/s0140-6736(07)60508-x | pmid=17405200}}
*{{cite journal | last1 = Williams | first1 = L. | last2 = Sobieszczyk | first2 = T. | year = 1997 | title = Attitudes Surrounding the Continuation of Female Circumcision in the Sudan: Passing the Tradition to the Next Generation | url = | journal = Journal of Marriage and the Family | volume = 59 | issue = 4| pages = 966–981 | doi=10.2307/353796}}

==External links==
*{{dmoz|Society/People/Women/Issues/Violence_and_Abuse}}
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20110516094651/http://www.echr.coe.int/NR/rdonlyres/39C38938-2E29-4151-9280-D5AC063DD02E/0/FICHES_Violence_femmes_EN.pdf Violence against women], a factsheet on [[ECtHR]] case law
* [http://www.endvawnow.org/ Virtual Knowledge Centre to End Violence against Women and Girls] (in English, French, and Spanish)
* [http://www.ohchr.org/EN/Issues/Women/SRWomen/Pages/SRWomenIndex.aspx UN Special Rapporteur on violence against women, its causes and consequences]
* [http://www.who.int/reproductivehealth/publications/fgm/en/index.html World Health Organization's reports on FGM], Health complications of female genital mutilation

{{abuse}}
{{Domestic violence}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Violence Against Women}}
[[Category:Violence against women| ]]
[[Category:Sex industry]]
[[Category:Feminism and health]]
[[Category:Gender-related violence]]
[[Category:Misogyny]]
[[Category:Crimes against women]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>