<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061110042014|86874062" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="3634424" pageid="3634424" ns="0" title="Violence against women"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-11-10T04:20:25Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{expand}}
{{Cleanup|September 2006}}
'''Violence against women''' ('''VAW''') is a [[term of art]] used to collectively refer to violent acts that are primarily or exclusively committed against [[female]]s.  Similar to a [[hate crime]], this type of [[violence]] targets a specific group with the victim's [[gender]] as a primary motive. The [[United Nations General Assembly]] defines "violence against women" as ''"any act of gender-based violence that results in, or is likely to result in, [[physical abuse|physical]], [[sexual abuse|sexual]] or [[mental abuse|mental]] harm or suffering to women, including threats of such acts, coercion or arbitrary deprivation of [[liberty]], whether occurring in public or in private life."'' The 1993 ''Declaration on the Elimination of Violence against Women'' noted that this violence could be perpetrated by assailants of either gender, family members and even the "State" itself. &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unhchr.ch/huridocda/huridoca.nsf/(Symbol)/A.RES.48.104.En?Opendocument United Nations General Assembly ''Declaration on the Elimination of Violence against Women'' (1993)]&lt;/ref&gt;. Worldwide governments and organizations actively work to combat violence against women through a variety of programs. A [[UN resolution]] designated November 25th as ''International Day for the Elimination of Violence against Women''. &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.un.org/womenwatch/daw/news/vawd.html UN Resolution 54/134-''International Day for the Elimination of Violence against Women'']&lt;/ref&gt;

==History of violence against women==
Some experts believe that the history of violence against women is tied to the history of women being viewed as property and a gender role assigned to be subservient to men and also other women. &lt;ref&gt; Penelope Harvey &amp; Peter Gow '' Sex and violence : issues in representation and experience''(1994)  pg 36 Routledge ISBN 0415057345 &lt;/ref&gt;. Feminist groups have contended that the advancement of women in society will curb the prevalance of violence against them. {{fact}}

==Female-on-female violence==

Very little research has been done into female-on-female lesbian relationship violence, so reliable source information is hard to come by. However, women have the capacity to be just as violent as men, so this form of violence could easily occur in lesbian relationships.

==Types of violence==
Studies have shown that violence is not always perpetrated as a form of physical violence but can also be psychological and [[verbal abuse|verbal]]. &lt;ref&gt;[http://diglib.tums.ac.ir/pub/magmng/pdf/119.pdf ''A Survey about Knowledge and Attitudes of People towards Violence against Women in Community Family Settings'' Iranian Public Health Journal Vol. 33, No. 2, pp.33-37, 2004]&lt;/ref&gt;  &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ojp.usdoj.gov/nij/vawprog/vaw_portfolio.pdf ''Violence &amp; Victimization Research Division's Compendium Of Research On Violence Against Women 1993-2005'' 1998-WT-VX-0014 pg 35, 1999-WT-VX-0014 pg 59] &lt;/ref&gt; Women are more likely to be victimized by someone that they are intimate with, commonly called "Intimate Partner Violence" or (IPV)&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.who.int/violence_injury_prevention/violence/world_report/factsheets/en/ipvfacts.pdf#search=%22most%20common%20Intimate%20Partner%20violence%22 WHO ''IPV Facts'']&lt;/ref&gt;. Instances of IPV tend not to be reported to police and thus many experts believe that the true magnitude of the problem is hard to estimate. &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cdc.gov/ncipc/factsheets/ipvfacts.htm CDC ''IPV Fact Sheet'']&lt;/ref&gt;

==Impact on society==
The [[World Health Organization]] reports that violence against women put an undue burden on [[health care]] services with women who have suffered violence being more likely to need health services and at higher costs. &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.who.int/mediacentre/factsheets/fs239/en/index.html WHO Factsheet ''Violence against women'']&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
&lt;div class="references-small"&gt;
&lt;references /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

==External links==
*[http://www.eagleforum.org/column/2006/sept06/06-09-13.html Laughing at Restraining Orders]
*[http://www.amnesty.org/actforwomen Stop Violence Against Women], [[Amnesty International]]
*[http://www.4woman.gov/violence/ U.S. Violence against women: Home Page]
*[http://www.aph.gov.au/library/intguide/SP/ViolenceAgainstWomen.htm Phillips, J. &amp; Park, M, ''Measuring violence against women: a review of the literature and statistics''] [[Australian Parliament House]] Library E-Briefs: Online only, issued 06 December 2004
*[http://www.usdoj.gov/ovw/ US Dept of Justice Office on Violence Against Women] 
*[http://www.homeoffice.gov.uk/rds/violencewomen.html UK Home Office ''Violence against women'']
*[http://www.un.org/rights/dpi1772e.htm United Nations Human Rights Commission ''Women and Violence'' ]
*[http://ec.europa.eu/justice_home/funding/daphne/funding_daphne_en.htm European Union ''Daphne Project'']
*[http://www.who.int/mediacentre/factsheets/fs239/en/index.html World Health Organization ''Violence against women'']
*[http://www.ncjrs.org/txtfiles1/nij/183781.txt ''Full report of the prevalence, incidence, and consequences of violence against women: Findings from the national violence against women survey.''] Publication No. NCJ183781
*[http://www.ojp.usdoj.gov/nij/pubs-sum/181867.htm ''Extent, nature, and consequences of intimate partner violence: findings from the National Violence Against Women Survey.''] Publication No. NCJ 181867

==See also==
*[[Violence Against Women Act]]
*[[Bride burning]]
*[[Domestic violence]]
*[[Domestic violence against men]]
*[[Men's Movement]]
*[[Female genital cutting]]
*[[Foot binding]]
*[[Infibulation]]
*[[Prostitution]]
*[[Rape]]
*[[Sati (practice)|Sati]]
*[[Sexual slavery]]

[[Category:Violence against women]]
[[Category:Sex trade]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>