<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20121110141737|522333789" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="3634424" pageid="3634424" ns="0" title="Violence against women"><revisions><rev timestamp="2012-11-10T14:21:26Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2012}}
{{pp-semi-sock|small=yes}}
{{Violence against women}}
'''Violence against women''' is a [[Technical terminology|technical term]] used to collectively refer to violent acts that are primarily or exclusively committed against [[woman|women]].  Similar to a [[hate crime]], this type of violence targets a specific group with the victim's [[gender]] as a primary motive.

The [[United Nations General Assembly]] defines "violence against women" as ''"any act of gender-based violence that results in, or is likely to result in, [[physical abuse|physical]], [[sexual abuse|sexual]] or [[emotional abuse|mental]] harm or suffering to women, including threats of such acts, coercion or arbitrary deprivation of [[liberty]], whether occurring in public or in private life."'' The 1993 [[Declaration on the Elimination of Violence Against Women]] noted that this violence could be perpetrated by assailants of either gender, family members and even the "State" itself.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unhchr.ch/huridocda/huridoca.nsf/(Symbol)/A.RES.48.104.En?Opendocument United Nations General Assembly ''Declaration on the Elimination of Violence against Women'' (1993)]&lt;/ref&gt;

Worldwide governments and organizations actively work to combat violence against women through a variety of programs. A [[UN resolution]] designated 25 November as ''[[International Day for the Elimination of Violence against Women]]''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.un.org/womenwatch/daw/news/vawd.html UN Resolution 54/134-'&amp;#39;International Day for the Elimination of Violence against Women'&amp;#39;]. Un.org.&lt;/ref&gt;

==History of violence against women==
[[File:Map3.1NEW Womens Physical Security 2011 compressed.jpg|right|thumb| 400px| A world map showing countries by women's physical security, 2011.]]
Some historians believe that the history of violence against women is tied to the history of women being viewed as property and a gender role assigned to be subservient to men and also other women.&lt;ref&gt;Penelope Harvey &amp; Peter Gow ''Sex and violence : issues in representation and experience'' (1994)  pg 36 Routledge ISBN 0-415-05734-5&lt;/ref&gt;

The UN Declaration on the Elimination of Violence against Women (1993) states that "violence against women is a manifestation of historically unequal power relations between men and women, which have led to domination over and discrimination against women by men and to the prevention of the full advancement of women, and that violence against women is one of the crucial social mechanisms by which women are forced into a subordinate position compared with men.”&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.un.org/documents/ga/res/48/a48r104.htm A/RES/48/104. Declaration on the Elimination of Violence against Women]. United Nations.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unfpa.org/rights/violence.htm Addressing Gender-Based Violence: Advancing Human Rights]. UNFPA.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 1870s courts in the United States stopped recognizing the common-law principle that a husband had the right to "physically chastise an errant wife".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Calvert R |year=1974 |chapter=Criminal and civil liability in husband-wife assaults |title=Violence in the family |pages=88–91 |editor=Steinmetz S, Straus M |publisher=Harper &amp; Row |location=New York}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the UK the traditional right of a husband to inflict moderate [[corporal punishment]] on his wife in order to keep her "within the bounds of duty" was removed in 1891.&lt;ref&gt;R. v. Jackson [1891]. 1 Q.B. 671&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Encyclopædia Britannica Eleventh Edition]], 1911. Article ''Corporal punishment''&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Quran]] verse [[An-Nisa, 34]] has been interpreted as supporting [[wife-beating]] (See [[Islam and domestic violence]]).&lt;ref name="autogenerated1"&gt;Yotam Feldner, Middle East Quarterly, December 2000, pp. 41–50,  http://www.meforum.org/50/honor-murders-why-the-perps-get-off-easy&lt;/ref&gt;

==Impact on society==
The [[World Health Organization]] reports that violence against women puts an undue burden on health care services with women who have suffered violence being more likely to need health services and at higher cost, compared to women who have not suffered violence.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.who.int/mediacentre/factsheets/fs239/en/index.html WHO Factsheet '&amp;#39;Violence against women'&amp;#39;]. World Health Organization (1 September 2011).&lt;/ref&gt;
Several studies have shown a link between poor treatment of women and international violence.  These studies show that one of the best predictors of inter- and intranational violence is the maltreatment of women in the society.&lt;ref&gt;Maffly, Brian (21 March 2009). [http://www.sltrib.com/ci_11967564 "BYU study links women's safety, nation's peace"]. ''The Salt Lake Tribune''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.womanstats.org/images/StearmerEmmettAPSA07.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

==Types of violence==

===Domestic violence===
{{main|Domestic violence}}
Women are more likely to be [[victimized]] by someone that they are intimate with, commonly called "Intimate Partner Violence" or (IPV). The impact of domestic violence in the sphere of total violence against women can be understood through the example that 40–70% of murders of women are committed by their husband or boyfriend.&lt;ref name="WHO"&gt;{{cite web
| year = 2002
| title = Intimate Partner Violence
| publisher = World Health Organization
| accessdate = 2007-09-04
| url = http://www.who.int/violence_injury_prevention/violence/world_report/factsheets/en/ipvfacts.pdf#search=%22most%20common%20Intimate%20Partner%20violence%22
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Studies have shown that violence is not always perpetrated as a form of physical violence but can also be psychological and [[verbal abuse|verbal]].&lt;ref name="IPH"&gt;{{cite journal
  | last =A Pourreza
  | coauthors =A Batebi; A Moussavi
  | title =A Survey about Knowledge and Attitudes of People towards Violence against Women in Community Family Settings
  | journal =Iranian Public Health Journal
  | volume =33
  | issue =2
  | pages =33–37
  | year =2004
  | url =http://diglib.tums.ac.ir/pub/magmng/pdf/119.pdf
  | id =
  | accessdate =2007-09-04  }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ojp.usdoj.gov/nij/vawprog/vaw_portfolio.pdf ''Violence &amp; Victimization Research Division's Compendium Of Research On Violence Against Women 1993–2005'' 1998-WT-VX-0014 pg 35, 1999-WT-VX-0014 pg 59]{{dead link|date=September 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In unmarried relationships this is commonly called [[dating violence]], whereas in the context of marriage it is called [[domestic violence]]. Instances of IPV tend not to be reported to police and thus many experts believe that the true magnitude of the problem is hard to estimate.&lt;ref name="CDC"&gt;{{cite web
| year = 2006
| title = Intimate Partner Violence: Overview
| publisher = Centers for Disease Control and Prevention
| accessdate = 2007-09-04
| url = http://www.cdc.gov/ncipc/factsheets/ipvfacts.htm
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Women are much more likely than men to be [[murdered]] by an intimate partner. In the United States, in 2005, 1181 women, in comparison with 329 men, were killed by their intimate partners.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cdc.gov/violencePrevention/intimatepartnerviolence/consequences.html CDC – Consequences – Intimate Partner Violence – Violence Prevention – Injury]. Cdc.gov.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.theduluthmodel.org/wheelgallery.php&lt;/ref&gt;  In [[England and Wales]] about 100 women are killed by partners or former partners each year while 21 men were killed in 2010.&lt;ref name=BBC&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-13058300 |title=All domestic abuse deaths to have multi-agency review |date=13 April 2011 |publisher=BBC |accessdate=14 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2008, in France, 156 women in comparison with 27 men were killed by their intimate partner.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.interieur.gouv.fr/sections/a_votre_service/aide_aux_victimes/violence-couple/downloadFile/attachedFile/morts_violentes_au_sein_couples.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

Though this form of violence is often portrayed as an issue within the context of heterosexual relationships, it also occurs in lesbian relationships,&lt;ref name="Girshick"&gt;Girshick, Lori B., "No Sugar, No Spice: Reflections on Research on Woman-to-Woman Sexual Violence." ''Violence Against Women'' Vol. 8 No. 12, December 2002, pgs. 1500–1520.&lt;/ref&gt; daughter-mother relationships, [[roommate]] relationships and other domestic relationships involving two women. Violence against women in lesbian relationships is about as common as violence against women in heterosexual relationships.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.musc.edu/vawprevention/lesbianrx/factsheet.shtml Fact Sheet: Lesbian Partner Violence]. Musc.edu.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Diagnosis planning====
The [[American Psychiatric Association]] planning and research committees for the forthcoming [[DSM-5]] (2013) have canvassed a series of new [[Relational disorder]]s which include ''Marital Conflict Disorder Without Violence'' or ''Marital Abuse Disorder (Marital Conflict Disorder With Violence)''.&lt;ref&gt;First, M.B., Bell, C.C., Cuthbert, B., Krystal, J.H., Malison, R., Offord, D.R., Riess, D., Shea, T., Widiger, T., Wisner, K.L., Personality Disorders and Relational Disorders, pp.164,166 Chapter 4 of Kupfer, D.J., First, M.B., &amp; Regier, D.A. [http://appi.org/book.cfm?id=2292 A Research Agenda For DSM-V]. Published by American Psychiatric Association (2002)&lt;/ref&gt; Couples with marital disorders sometimes come to clinical attention because the couple recognize long-standing dissatisfaction with their marriage and come to the [[clinician]] on their own initiative or are referred by an astute health care professional. Secondly, there is serious violence in the marriage which is -"usually the husband battering the wife".&lt;ref&gt;First, M.B., Bell, C.C., Cuthbert, B., Krystal, J.H., Malison, R., Offord, D.R., Riess, D., Shea, T., Widiger, T., Wisner, K.L., Personality Disorders and Relational Disorders, p.163, Chapter 4 of Kupfer, D.J., First, M.B., &amp; Regier, D.A.  [http://appi.org/book.cfm?id=2292 A Research Agenda For DSM-V]. Published by American Psychiatric Association (2002)&lt;/ref&gt; In these cases the emergency room or a legal authority often is the first to notify the [[clinician]]. Most importantly, marital violence "is a major risk factor for serious injury and even death and women in violent marriages are at much greater risk of being seriously injured or killed ([[National Advisory Council on Violence Against Women]] 2000)."&lt;ref name=autogenerated2&gt;First, M.B., Bell, C.C., Cuthbert, B., Krystal, J.H., Malison, R., Offord, D.R., Riess, D., Shea, T., Widiger, T., Wisner, K.L., Personality Disorders and Relational Disorders, p.166, Chapter 4 of Kupfer, D.J., First, M.B., &amp; Regier, D.A. [http://appi.org/book.cfm?id=2292 A Research Agenda For DSM-V]. Published by American Psychiatric Association (2002)&lt;/ref&gt; The authors of this study add that "There is current considerable controversy over whether male-to-female marital violence is best regarded as a reflection of male [[psychopathology]] and control or whether there is an empirical base and clinical utility for conceptualizing these patterns as relational."&lt;ref name=autogenerated2 /&gt; 

Recommendations for clinicians making a diagnosis of ''Marital Relational Disorder'' should include the assessment of actual or "potential" male violence as regularly as they assess the potential for suicide in depressed patients. Further, "clinicians should not relax their vigilance after a battered wife leaves her husband, because some data suggest that the period immediately following a marital separation is the period of greatest risk for the women. Many men will [[stalking|stalk]] and [[battery (crime)|batter]] their wives in an effort to get them to return or punish them for leaving. Initial assessments of the potential for violence in a marriage can be supplemented by standardized interviews and questionnaires, which have been reliable and valid aids in exploring marital violence more systematically."&lt;ref name=autogenerated2 /&gt;
 
The authors conclude with what they call "very recent information"&lt;ref name=autogenerated1&gt;First, M.B., Bell, C.C., Cuthbert, B., Krystal, J.H., Malison, R., Offord, D.R., Riess, D., Shea, T., Widiger, T., Wisner, K.L., Personality Disorders and Relational Disorders, p.167,168 Chapter 4 of Kupfer, D.J., First, M.B., &amp; Regier, D.A. [http://appi.org/book.cfm?id=2292 A Research Agenda For DSM-V]. Published by American Psychiatric Association (2002)&lt;/ref&gt; on the course of violent marriages which suggests that "over time a husband's battering may abate somewhat, but perhaps because he has successfully [[intimidate]]d his wife. The risk of violence remains strong in a marriage in which it has been a feature in the past. Thus, treatment is essential here; the clinician cannot just wait and watch."&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt; The most urgent clinical priority is the protection of the wife because she is the one most frequently at risk, and clinicians must be aware that supporting assertiveness by a battered wife may lead to more beatings or even death.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt;

===Mob violence===
In 2010 [[Amnesty International]] reported that [[Hassi Messaoud mob attacks against women|mob attacks]] against single women were taking place in [[Hassi Messaoud]], Algeria.&lt;ref name=Amnesty&gt;{{cite web|title=Algerian authorities must investigate and stop attacks against women|url=http://www.amnesty.org.au/news/comments/22931/|publisher=Amnesty International|accessdate=13 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to Amnesty International,  "some women have been sexually abused" and were targeted "not just because they are women, but because they are living alone and are economically independent."&lt;ref name=Amnesty/&gt;

===State violence===

====War and militarism====
[[File:Paul Jamin - Le Brenn et sa part de butin 1893.jpg|thumb|''"[[Brennus (4th century BC)|Brennus]] and His Share of the Spoils"'', by [[Paul Jamin]], 1893.]]

Militarism produces special environments that allow for increased violence against women. [[War rapes]] have accompanied warfare in virtually every known historical era.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last= Levinson |first=Bernard M |title= Gender and Law in the Hebrew Bible and the Ancient Near East |url=http://books.google.com/?id=2rZnXQwPX8gC&amp;dq=rape+in+warfare+ancient |page= 203 |year=2004 |isbn= 978-0-567-08098-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Rape in the course of war is mentioned multiple times in the Bible: "For I will gather all the nations against Jerusalem to battle, and the city shall be taken and the houses plundered and the women raped..." {{bibleref|Zechariah|14:2|ESV}} "Their little children will be dashed to death before their eyes. Their homes will be sacked, and their wives will be raped."{{bibleref|Isaiah|13:16|NLT}}

War rapes are rapes committed by soldiers, other combatants or civilians during armed conflict or war, or during military occupation, distinguished from sexual assaults and rape committed amongst troops in military service. It also covers the situation where women are forced into prostitution or [[sexual slavery]] by an occupying power. During World War II the Japanese military established brothels filled with "[[comfort women]]", girls and women who were forced into sexual slavery for soldiers, exploiting women for the purpose of creating access and entitlement for men. &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.inthesetimes.com/article/3848/ "Why Soldiers Rape – Culture of misogyny, illegal occupation, fuel sexual violence in military"]&lt;/ref&gt; 
&lt;ref name="bare_url"&gt;{{Citation
|url=http://www.japanfocus.org/-Tessa-Morris_Suzuki/2373
|title=Japan's 'Comfort Women': It's time for the truth (in the ordinary, everyday sense of the word)
|author=Tessa Morris-Suzuki
|date=March 8, 2007
|accessdate=2011-08-04
|publisher=[[The Asia-Pacific Journal: Japan Focus]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="definition"&gt;{{Harvnb|WCCW|2004}}.&lt;/ref&gt;
 
Another example of violence against women incited by militarism during war took place in the [[Kaunas Ghetto|Kovno Ghetto]]. Jewish male prisoners had access to (and used) Jewish women forced into camp brothels by the Nazis, who also used them.&lt;ref&gt;Dworkin, Andrea: ''Scapegoat: The Jews, Israel and Women's Liberation.'' pg. 316. Free Press, 2000. ISBN 0-684-83612-2&lt;/ref&gt;

Rape was committed during the [[Bangladesh Liberation War]] by members of the [[Pakistan Armed Forces|Pakistani military]] and the [[militia]]s that supported them. Over a period of nine months, hundreds of thousands of women were raped. [[Susan Brownmiller]], in her report on the [[1971 Bangladesh atrocities|atrocities]], said that girls from the age of eight to grandmothers of seventy-five suffered attacks.  (See also: [[Rape during the Bangladesh Liberation War]]) 

Rape used as a weapon of war was practiced during the [[Bosnian War]] where rape was used as a highly systematized instrument of war by Serb armed forces predominantly targeting women and girls of the Bosniak ethnic group for physical and moral destruction.  Estimates of the number of women raped during the war range from 50,000 to 60,000;  as of 2010 only 12 cases have been prosecuted.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.icty.org/x/file/About/Reports%20and%20Publications/AnnualReports/annual_report_1997_en.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;  (See also [[Rape during the Bosnian War]]). 

The 1998 [[International Criminal Tribunal for Rwanda]] recognized rape as a war crime.  Presiding judge [[Navanethem Pillay]] said in a statement after the verdict: "From time immemorial, rape has been regarded as spoils of war. Now it will be considered a war crime. We want to send out a strong message that rape is no longer a trophy of war."&lt;ref&gt;Quoted in citation for honorary doctorate, Rhodes University, April 2005 accessed at [http://www.ru.ac.za/academic/graduation/addresses_and_citations/2005/Judge_Pillay_citation.doc] March 23, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;  (See also: [[Rwandan Genocide]])

In 2006, five [[United States Army|U.S. troops]] from a six-man unit [[gang rape]]d and killed a 14-year-old girl in a village near the town of [[Mahmoudiyah, Iraq|Al-Mahmudiyah]], Iraq. After the rape the girl was shot in her head and the lower part of her body, from her stomach down to her feet, was set on fire.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cnn.com/2006/WORLD/meast/08/08/iraq.mahmoudiya/index.html |title=Soldier: 'Death walk' drives troops 'nuts' - Aug 8, 2006 |publisher=CNN.com |date= |accessdate=2012-11-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref name="greenNews"&gt;{{cite news|publisher=BBC News|date=2009-05-07|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/americas/8039257.stm|title=US ex-soldier guilty of Iraq rape}}&lt;/ref&gt; (See also: [[Mahmudiyah killings]])

A 1995 study of female war veterans found that 90 percent had been sexually harassed.   A 2003 survey found that 30 percent of female vets said they were raped in the military and a 2004 study of veterans who were seeking help for post-traumatic stress disorder found that 71 percent of the women said they were sexually assaulted or raped while serving.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=103844570 "The Nation: The Plight of Women Soldiers"]&lt;/ref&gt;

====Violence in empowerment systems====
When police officers misuse their power as agents of the state to physically and [[sexual harassment|sexually harass]] and assault victims, the survivors, including women, feel much less able to report the violence.&lt;ref name=FreshAir&gt;{{Cite episode
| title        = Covering 'Tainted Justice' And Winning A Pulitzer
| episodelink  = 
| url          = http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=126386819
| series       = Fresh Air
| serieslink   = Fresh Air
| credits      = Barbara Laker and Wendy Ruderman, hosted by [[Terry Gross]]
| network      = NPR
| station      = [[WHYY-FM|WHYY]]
| city         = Philedelphia
| airdate      = 3 May 2010
| began        = 
| ended        = 
| season       = 
| seriesno     =
| number       = 
| minutes      = 
| transcript   =  
| transcripturl= }}&lt;/ref&gt;  It is standard procedure for police to force entry into the victim's home even after the victim's numerous requests for them to go away.&lt;ref&gt;[[Jeannie Suk|Professor Jeannie Suk]], ''At Home in the Law: How the Domestic Violence Revolution Is Transforming Privacy,'' [[Yale University Press]], 27 October 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; Government agencies often disregard the victim's right to [[Freedom of association#Intimate association|freedom of association]] with their perpetrator.&lt;ref&gt;Cheryl Hanna, "No Right to Choose: Mandated Victim Participation in Domestic Violence Prosecutions," ''[[Harvard Law Review]]'', 1996, Vol. 109, pp.1850–1910.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Women's shelter|Shelter]] workers are often reduced themselves to contributing to violence against women by exploiting their [[vulnerability]] in exchange for a paying job.&lt;ref&gt;Koyama, Emi "Disloyal to feminism: Abuse of survivors within the domestic violence shelter system." in Smith A, Richie BE, Sudbury J, eds. ''The Color of Violence: INCITE! Anthology.'' Cambridge, Mass.: South End Press, 2006. ISBN 0-89608-762-X&lt;/ref&gt;

===Gender-based violence by male college athletes===

Violence against women is a topic of concern in the United States' collegiate athletic community. From the 2010 UVA lacrosse murder, in which a male athlete was charged guilty with second degree murder of his girlfriend, to the 2004 University of Colorado Football Scandal when players were charged with nine alleged sexual assaults,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Vaughan|first=Kevin|title=Colorado woman seeks justice in alleged sexual assault  Read more: Colorado woman seeks justice in alleged sexual assault|url=http://www.denverpost.com/firstinthepost/ci_12557039|work=denver Post|accessdate=17 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; studies suggest that athletes are at higher risk for committing sexual assault against women than the average student.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Brady|first=Jeff|title=Scandal Returns to University of Colorado Football|url=http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=105381707|work=NPR weekend edition|publisher=NPR|accessdate=12 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="chandler1999"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Chandler|first=Steve B|coauthors=JOHNSON, DEWAYNE J. CARROLL, PAMELA S.|title=Abusive Behaviors of College Athletes|journal=College Student Journal|date=12/01/1999|year=1999|month=December|volume=33|issue=4|accessdate=12 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is reported that one in three college assaults are committed by athletes.&lt;ref name="johnshopkins1"&gt;{{cite web|last=Mak|first=Stephanie|title=Are Athletes More Abusive Than the Rest of the Student Population?|url=http://web1.johnshopkins.edu/hurj/issue3/spotlight-mak.html|publisher=Hopkins Undergraduate Research Journal Online|accessdate=12 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Surveys suggest that male student athletes who represent 3.3% of the college population, commit 19% of reported sexual assaults and 35% of domestic violence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Statistics|url=http://www.ncava.org/Statistics.html|publisher=The National Coalition Against Violent Athletes|accessdate=12 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The theories that surround these statistics range from misrepresentation of the student-athlete to an unhealthy mentality towards women within the team itself.&lt;ref name="johnshopkins1"/&gt;

====Controversy over contributing factors====

Sociologist Timothy Curry, after conducting an observational analysis of two big time sports’ locker room conversations, deduced that the high risk of male student athletes for gender abuse is a result of the team’s subculture.&lt;ref name=Curry1991&gt;{{cite journal|last=Curry|first=Timothy Jon|title=Fraternal Bonding in the Locker Room: A Profeminist Analysis Of Talk About Competition And Women|journal=Sociology of Sport Journal|year=1991|volume=8|issue=2|pages=119–135|accessdate=12 March 2012|url=http://www.umt.edu/sociology/faculty_staff/ellestad/documents/275_Curry1991fraternalbondinginthelockerroom_s10.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; He states, "Their locker room talk generally treated women as objects, encouraged sexist attitudes toward women and, in its extreme, promoted rape culture."&lt;ref name=Curry1991/&gt; He proposes that this objectification is a way for the male to reaffirm his heterosexual status and hyper-masculinity. Claims have been made that the atmosphere changes when an outsider (especially women) intrude in the locker room. In the wake of the reporter [[Lisa Olson]] being harassed by a Patriots player in the locker room in 1990, she reflected, "We are taught to think we must have done something wrong and it took me a while to realize I hadn't done anything wrong."&lt;ref name=lisa&gt;{{cite journal|last=Disch|first=Lisa|coauthors=Kane, Mary Jo|title=When a Looker is Really a Bitch: Lisa Olson, Sport, and the Heterosexual Matrix|journal=Signs|year=1996|month=Winter|volume=21|issue=2|pages=278–308|url=http://www.jstor.org/stable/3175065|accessdate=17 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other female sports reporters (college and professional) have claimed that they often brush off the players' comments which leads to further objectification.&lt;ref name=lisa /&gt;  Other sociologists challenge this claim. Steve Chandler notes that because of their celebrity status on campus, “athletes are more likely to be scrutinized or falsely accused than non-athletes.”&lt;ref name="chandler1999"/&gt;  Another contender, Stephanie Mak, notes that, “if one considers the 1998 estimates that about three million women were battered and almost one million raped, the proportion of incidences that involve athletes in comparison to the regular population is relatively small."&lt;ref name="johnshopkins1"/&gt;

====Response to violence by male college athletes====

In response to the proposed link between college athletes and gender-based violence, and media coverage holding Universities as responsible for these scandals more universities are requiring athletes to attend workshops that promote awareness. For example, St. John's University holds sexual assault awareness classes in the fall for its incoming student athletes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Newsom|first=John|title=Share on emailShare on redditMore Sharing Services  Few Colleges Tackle Issue of Athlete Sex Assaults|url=http://articles.latimes.com/1992-03-22/news/mn-7249_1_sexual-assault|publisher=Los Angeles Times Online|accessdate=12 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Other groups, such as the National Coalition Against Violent Athletes, have formed to provide support for the victims as their mission statement reads, "The NCAVA works to eliminate off the field violence by athletes through the implementation of prevention methods that recognize and promote the positive leadership potential of athletes within their communities.  In order to eliminate violence, the NCAVA is dedicated to empowering individuals affected by athlete violence through comprehensive services including advocacy, education and counseling."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Mission|url=http://www.ncava.org/Mission.html|publisher=National Coalition Against Violent Athletes|accessdate=12 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Activism==
Many activists believe that working towards the elimination of domestic violence means working to eliminate a societal hierarchy enforced through sexism. [[INCITE! Women of Color Against Violence]] cited racism within the anti-violence movement and suggest that violence against women will not end until the anti-violence movement re-directs its goal from "ending violence against women" to "ending violence against women of color."&lt;ref&gt;[[INCITE! Women of Color Against Violence]]: ''Color of Violence: The INCITE! Anthology.'' pg 4. South End Press, 2006. ISBN 0-89608-762-X&lt;/ref&gt; The same conclusion can be drawn for other systems of oppression.

==See also==
*[[Acid attack]]
*[[Bride burning]]
*[[Domestic violence]]
*[[Female genital mutilation]]
*[[Foot binding]] (historical)
*[[Human trafficking]]
*[[Infibulation]]
*[[Lissette Ochoa's domestic violence case]]
*[[Murder of pregnant women]]
*[[Response based therapy]]
*[[Convention on preventing and combating violence against women and domestic violence]]
*[[Sati (practice)|Sati]]
*[[Sexual slavery]]
*[[Violence Against Women Act]]
*[[Widow inheritance]]
*[[Shows red card to abuser]]
*[[Violence against men]]

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
*{{dmoz|Society/People/Women/Issues/Violence_and_Abuse}}
* [http://www.echr.coe.int/NR/rdonlyres/39C38938-2E29-4151-9280-D5AC063DD02E/0/FICHES_Violence_femmes_EN.pdf Violence against women], a factsheet on [[ECtHR]] case law
* [http://www.endvawnow.org/ Virtual Knowledge Centre to End Violence against Women and Girls] (in English, French, and Spanish)
* [http://www.ohchr.org/EN/Issues/Women/SRWomen/Pages/SRWomenIndex.aspx UN Special Rapporteur on violence against women, its causes and consequences]

{{abuse}}
{{Domestic violence}}

&lt;references /&gt;

{{DEFAULTSORT:Violence Against Women}}
[[Category:Violence against women| ]]
[[Category:Sex industry]]
[[Category:Feminism and health]]
[[Category:Gender-based violence]]
[[Category:Misogyny]]

[[ar:العنف ضد المرأة]]
[[ca:Violència contra les dones]]
[[es:Violencia contra la mujer]]
[[eu:Emakumeen aurkako indarkeria]]
[[fa:خشونت علیه زنان]]
[[fr:Violence contre les femmes]]
[[it:Violenza contro le donne]]
[[he:אלימות נגד נשים]]
[[ne:महिला बिरूद्ध हुने हिंसा]]
[[no:Vold mot kvinner]]
[[pl:Przemoc wobec kobiet]]
[[pt:Violência contra a mulher]]
[[sk:Násilie voči ženám]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>