<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20031018233853|1589679" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="26316" pageid="26316" ns="0" title="Racial segregation"><revisions><rev timestamp="2003-10-19T06:07:30Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[de:Rassentrennung]]
'''Racial segregation''' is a kind of formalized or institutionalized [[racial discrimination|discrimination on the basis of race]], characterized by their separation from each other. The separation may be geographical, but is usually supported by providing services through separate institutions (such as schools) and through similar legal and social structures.

Societies have practiced racial segregation througout human history. 

== Nazi Germany==

During the 1930s and 40s, Jews and Gypsies were forced to wear yellow ribbons, and were discriminated against by the racial laws. Jewish doctors and professors were not allowed to teach [[Aryan]] pupils or cure [[Aryan]] patients.

During the WWII, Jews and  Gypsies were sent to the [[concentration camp]]s, solely on the basis of their race.


== USA==

Racial discrimination was regulated by the [[Jim Crow law]]s from the [[United States Civil War|Civil War]], especially (although not exclusively) in the [[U.S. Southern States]]. Such legal segregation lasted up to the [[1960s]]. Black people, Japanese and other "undesirables" had to use separate schools, public toilets, park benches etc.  "[[Miscegenation]]" laws prohibited people of different races from marrying. In some states, if a same restaurants admitted people of colour and caucasian "[[Aryan]]s", separate parts of the restaurant had to be arranged for each group; in other places it was forbidden for stores or restaurants to serve different races under the same roof.

During [[World War II]], Japanese people were sent to the [[concentration camp]]s, solely on the basis of their race.

Institutionalized racial segregation was ended by the efforts of such [[civil rights]] activists as [[Rosa Parks]] and [[Martin Luther King Jr.]], working during the period from the end of [[World War II]] through the passage of the [[Voting Rights Act]] and the [[Civil Rights Act]] supported by President [[Lyndon Johnson]]. Many of their efforts were acts of [[civil disobedience]] aimed at violating the racial segregation rules and laws, such as insisting on sitting at the front of the bus (Rosa Parks), or holding sit-ins at all-white diners. On [[January 26]], [[1948]] [[President of the United States|President]] [[Harry S Truman]] signed [[Executive Order 9981]], ending segregation in the [[United States Armed Forces]]. 

Althoug racial equality is, at least in theory, granted  to all citizens in USA today, some see the [[USA Patriots Act]] as an attempt for covert racial segregation of noncitizens. Arabs and Pakistanis, which have similar skin colour, are segregated at the airports and have to undergo humiliating procedures, solely on the basis of their national origin.

== South Africa==

[[Apartheid]] was a system which has existed in [[south]] [[Africa]] for almost as long as the segregation laws in the [[USA]]. It was abolished in the late 80s, after the victory of racial [[equality]], at least on [[paper]], in the [[USA]], and rapid change in public perception of racial segregation throughout the [[world]]. 

==Related issues==

Although not all advocates concede the validity of the concept of "race" as applied to human divisions, discrimination on color or other ethnic characteristics is often labelled "racist" (see [[race]], [[racism]]).</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>