<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20071113185453|171255199" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="26316" pageid="26316" ns="0" title="Racial segregation"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-11-14T22:31:58Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Segregation}}

'''Racial segregation''' characterised by separation of different [[race]]s in daily life, such as eating in a restaurant, drinking from a water fountain, using a rest room, attending school, going to the movies, or in the rental or purchase of a home.&lt;ref&gt;''Principles to Guide Housing Policy at the Beginning of the Millennium'', Michael Schill &amp; Susan Wachter, [[Cityscape]]&lt;/ref&gt; Segregation may be mandated by law or exist through social norms. Segregation may be maintained by means ranging from discrimination in hiring and in the rental and sale of housing to certain races to [[vigilante]] violence such as [[lynching]]s; a situation that arises when members of different races mutually prefer to associate and do business with members of their own race would usually be described as ''separation'' or ''de facto separation'' of the races rather than ''segregation''. Legal segregation in both South Africa and the U.S. was required and came with "[[anti-miscegenation laws]]" (prohibitions against [[interracial marriage]]) and laws against hiring people of the race that is the object of discrimination in any but menial positions.

Segregation in hiring practices contributes to [[economic inequality|economic imbalance]] between the races. Segregation, however, often allowed close contact in [[social hierarchy|hierarchical]] situations, such as allowing a person of one race to work as a servant for a member of another race. Segregation can involve [[spatial]] separation of the races, and/or mandatory use of different institutions, such as [[school]]s and hospitals by people of different races.

==Overview==
[[Image:Rex theatre.jpg|right|thumb|250px|The Rex Theatre for Colored People]]
Racial segregation differs from racial discrimination in a number of ways. Discrimination ranges from individual actions, to socially enforced discriminatory behavior, to legally mandated differences in status between members of different races. Segregation has, typically, harshly reinforced discrimination: if people of different races live in separate neighborhoods, attend different schools, receive different social services, etc., then people of the favored races can be largely insulated from societal neglect of people of other races.

==Historical cases==
===Indo-Aryan India===
Centuries ago, [[Indo-European]]-speaking nomadic groups invaded India and established the [[caste system]], an [[elitist]] form of social organization separating the light-skinned Indo-Aryan conquerors from the conquered aboriginal tribes thrlok[ough enforcement of racial [[endogamy]]. In this system, the [[Dravidian people|Dravidian]] [[Dalits|Untouchables]] and other aboriginal stocks were legally subject to rigorous segregation and bound to servile occupations. 

"If the whole of Sanskrit literature, sacred or profane, makes one thing clear, it is that there is one line no Hindu could cross, and that was the line which separated the Aryan in India from the non-Aryan. The two ethnic nouns even acquired moral connotations: to be ''Arya'' was to be noble and honourable, and to be ''Anarya'' was to be base and dishonourable. The non-Aryans were beyond the pale of Hindu society, and therefore untouchable. The Aryan Hindus regarded them with fear, hatred, contempt and disgust..." ([[Nirad C. Chaudhuri]], "Hinduism and the Aboriginals", ''Hinduism: A Religion to Live By'', Oxford University Press, USA; New Edition, 1997, p. 97).

===Ancient Sparta===
The [[Indo-European]] [[Dorian]] conquerors of [[Sparta]] established one of the harshest racially-based states in history. A tiny minority of Spartan masters lorded it over a large population of enserfed aboriginal [[Helots]], who had virtually no [[civil rights|civil]] or political rights. "Once a year, the Spartans declared war on the helots, so that their young men could kill any who seemed insubordinate without incurring the legal guilt of homicide" ([[Bertrand Russell]], ''A History of Western Philosophy'', Simon and Schuster, 1972, p. 95).

===Nazi Germany (1933-1945)===
A ban of interracial marriage was part of the [[Nuremberg Laws]] enacted by the [[Nazis]] in [[Germany]] against the German [[Jew]]ish community during the 1930s. The laws prohibited marriages between Jews and [[Aryan]] Germans, which were classified as different races. 

Under the [[General Government]] of occupied [[Poland]] in 1940, the population was divided into different groups, each with different rights, food rations, allowed strips in the cities, public transportation, and assigned  

*[[Ukraine|Ukrainians]],
*Highlanders ([[Goralenvolk]]) - an attempt to reverse the greater "Polish" identity
*[[Kashubians]] ([[Kaschobenvolk]]) - similar attempt like with Goralenvolk, but less successful
*[[Poland|Poles]], 
*[[Jew]]s 
*[[Homosexuals]]
*[[Roma people]]
*[[Jehovah's Witnesses]]

During the 1930s and 40s, Jews in Nazi-controlled states were made to wear yellow ribbons or stars of David, and were, along with [[Roma people|Romas]] (Gypsies) discriminated against by the racial laws. Jewish doctors and professors were not allowed to treat Aryan (effectively, [[gentile]]) patients or teach Aryan pupils, respectively. 
The Jews were also not allowed to use any public transportation, besides the ferry, and would only be able to shop from 3-5 in Jewish stores.  After [[Kristallnacht]] ("The Night of Broken Glass"), the Jews were fined 1,000,000 [[German reichsmark|marks]] for damages done by the Nazi troops and [[Schutzstaffel|SS]] members. Jews and Roma were subjected to genocide as "racial" groups in the [[Holocaust]]).

===Rhodesia (20th century)===

The British [[colony]] of [[Rhodesia]] (now [[Zimbabwe]]), under [[Ian Smith]], leader of the white minority government, declared unilateral independence in 1965.  For the next 15 years, Rhodesia operated under white minority rule until international sanctions forced Smith to hold multiracial elections, after a brief period of British rule in 1979.

Laws enforcing segregation had been around before 1965, although many institutions simply ignored them. One highly publicized legal battle occurred in 1960 involving the opening of a new [[Reps Theatre|Theatre]] that was to be open to all races, this incident was nicknamed [[Reps Theatre|"The Battle of the Toilets"]].

===South Africa (20th century)===
[[Image:DurbanSign1989.jpg|thumb|left|200px|"Petty apartheid": sign on Durban beach in English, [[Afrikaans]] and Zulu languages]]

{{main|History of South Africa in the Apartheid Era}}

[[History of South Africa in the apartheid era|Apartheid]] was a system which existed in [[South Africa]] for over forty years, although the term itself had a history going back to the 1910s and unofficially before that for many years. It was formalized in the years following the victory of the [[National Party (South Africa)|National Party]] in the all-white national election of 1948, increased in dominancy under the rule of Prime Minister [[Hendrik Frensch Verwoerd]] and remained law until 1994.  Examples of apartheid policy introduced are the [[Prohibition of Mixed Marriages Act]], [[1951]], which made it illegal for marriage between races.

Apartheid was abolished following a rapid change in public perception of racial segregation throughout the [[world]], and an economic [[boycott]] against South Africa which had crippled and threatened to destroy its economy.

===United States (19th-21st century)===
{{main|Racial segregation in the United States}}
After the [[Thirteenth Amendment]] abolished [[History of Slavery in the United States|slavery]] in America, racial discrimination became regulated by the so-called [[Jim Crow laws]], which mandated strict segregation of the races. Though such laws were instituted shortly after fighting ended in many cases, they only became formalized after the end of [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican]]-enforced [[Reconstruction]] in the 1870s and 80s during a period known as the [[nadir of American race relations]]. This legalized segregation lasted up to the 1960s, primarily through the deep and extensive power of [[Southern Democrats|Southern Democrats]]. 

While the majority in 1896 ''[[Plessy vs. Ferguson|Plessy]]'' overtly upheld only "separate but equal" facilities (specifically, transportation facilities), Justice [[John Marshall Harlan]] in his [[dissenting opinion|dissent]] protested that the decision was an expression of [[white supremacy]]; he predicted that segregation would "stimulate aggressions … upon the admitted rights of colored citizens," "arouse race hate" and "perpetuate a feeling of distrust between [the] races."&lt;ref&gt;http://www.thenation.com/doc/20040503/fonerkennedy&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!-- Eric Foner and Randall Kennedy, "Brown at 50", ''The Nation'', posted April 15, 2004 (May 3, 2004 issue)--&gt;

[[Image:Segregation Dallas.jpg|thumb|200px|right|A segregated facility in [[Dallas, Texas|Dallas]], [[Texas]]. Note the sign "Colored Waiting Room" at the top.]]Institutionalized racial segregation was ended as an official practice by the efforts of such [[American Civil Rights Movement (1955-1968)|civil rights]] [[Activism|activists]] as [[Clarence Mitchell, Jr.]], [[Rosa Parks]] and [[Martin Luther King Jr.]], working during the period from the end of World War II through the passage of the [[Voting Rights Act]] and the [[Civil Rights Act of 1964]] supported by President [[Lyndon B. Johnson]]. Many of their efforts were acts of [[non-violent]] [[civil disobedience]] aimed at disrupting the enforcement of racial segregation rules and laws, such as refusing to give up a seat in the black part of the bus to a white person (Rosa Parks), or holding [[sit-in]]s at all-white [[wiktionary:diner|diners]]. 

By 1968 all forms of segregation had been declared unconstitutional by the Supreme Court and by the 1970s, support for formal legal segregation had dissolved. Formal racial discrimination was illegal in school systems, businesses, [[military|American military]] and government. Separate bathrooms, water fountains and schools all disappeared and the civil rights movement had the public's support.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://encarta.msn.com/encyclopedia_761580651_3/Segregation_in_the_United_States.html|title=Encarta Encyclopedia|accessdate=2007-04-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Since then, African-Americans have played a significant role as mayors, governors, and state officials in both Southern and Northern states and on the national level have been on the Supreme Court, in the House of Representatives and the Senate, in presidential cabinets, and as head of the joint chiefs of staff.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://encarta.msn.com/encyclopedia_761580651_3/Segregation_in_the_United_States.html|title=Encarta Encyclopedia|accessdate=2007-04-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
[[Image:Governor George Wallace stands defiant at the University of Alabama.jpg|thumb|200px|left|Governor [[George Wallace]] attempts to block the enrollment of black students at the [[University of Alabama]].]]
Not all racial segregation laws have been repealed in the United States, although Supreme Court rulings have rendered them unenforceable and illegal to carry out. For instance, the [[Alabama Constitution]] still mandates that ''Separate schools shall be provided for white and colored children, and no child of either race shall be permitted to attend a school of the other race''.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.legislature.state.al.us/CodeOfAlabama/Constitution/1901/CA-245806.htm&lt;/ref&gt;  A proposal to repeal this provision was narrowly defeated in 2004.

Over the next twenty years, a succession of further court decisions and federal laws, including the ''[[Home Mortgage Disclosure Act]]'' and measure to end [[Mortgage Discrimination|mortgage discrimination]] in 1975, would completely invalidate ''de jure'' racial segregation and discrimination in the U.S., although ''de facto'' segregation and discrimination have proven more resilient.  According to the Civil Rights Project at [[Harvard University]], the actual de facto desegregation of U.S. public schools peaked in the late 1980s; since that time, the schools have, in fact, become more segregated mainly due to the ethnic segregation of the nation with whites dominating the suburbs and minorities the urban centers. As of 2005, the present proportion of black students at majority white schools "are a level lower than in any year since 1968."

==Contemporary segregation==
===Dominican Republic===
{{refimprove|section|date=October 2007}}
of [[Haiti]]an illegal inmigrants live without recognition of Dominican Nationality, where they do not have access to education and economic services based on their lack of legality in the country. According to multiple [[New York Times]], Human Rights Groups [http://hrw.org/reports/2002/domrep/domrep0402-02.htm]  and [[Amnesty International]] reports, birth certificates are not issued to children born to both parents of Haitian nationality and without legal residence in the Dominican Republic.&lt;Ref&gt; New York Times "No Papers, No Rights" 2005 &lt;/Ref&gt; Human rights worker [[Solange Pierre]] won the 2006 [[Robert F. Kennedy]] Human Rights Award for fighting to end this problem.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rfkmemorial.org/legacyinaction/2006_Winner/ "DOMINICAN BORN HAITIAN RIGHTS ACTIVIST WINS 2006 RFK HUMAN RIGHTS AWARD"] Press Release, RFK Memorial Center, accessed Sept. 28, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Tensions between both nationals in the Dominican Republic have been reported as well as periodic fights and acts of violence by Dominicans against the Haitians.&lt;Ref&gt; Amnesty International Dominican Republic Report 2006 &lt;/Ref&gt;  The practice of what is described as [[Antihaitianismo]] has been another factor, due to the tension between the Dominican Republic and its neighboring nation.&lt;Ref&gt; http://www.ling.upenn.edu/courses/Fall_2003/ling001/antihaitianismo.html&lt;/Ref&gt; &lt;Ref&gt;http://www.worldpress.org/Americas/2276.cfm &lt;/Ref&gt;  The documentary "The Price of Sugar" documents the current situation for Haitian workers living in the Dominican Republic. &lt;Ref&gt; http://www.thepriceofsugar.com &lt;/Ref&gt; In Europe there have been calls for a travel and economic boycott of the Dominican Republic. Smaller Non-Governmental organizations have called for similar boycotts in the United States.

Yet the president of Haiti and his ambassadors to the Dominican Republic and France have denied the accusations leveled by the film makers as propaganda. Since they have exposed that poor Dominicans of no Haitian ancestry or race live under the same conditions or worse than the Haitians at the Bateyes in the Dominican Republic.&lt;Ref&gt;http://dominicantoday.com/app/article.aspx?id=24051&lt;/Ref&gt; 

The film has been exposed as an orchestrated and manipulated tool to force the Dominican government to provide Citizenship to the over one million Haitians and their children that illegaly crossed the border looking for work and a better life to that they have in the impoverished Haiti. Since the Dominican government itself doesn't own any Sugar Mills anymore. 

So far the Dominican government has provided the issuance of Birth Certificates that will allow the Haitian parents to properly register the birth of the  children in the Haitian consulate at the country as well as allow the children to attend State funded public schools at the expense of the Dominican tax payer.

===[[Fiji]]===
{{refimprove|section|date=October 2007}}
[[Fiji coups of 1987|Two military coups]] in [[Fiji]] in 1987 removed from power a government that was led by an [[Fijian people|ethnic Fijian]], but was supported principally by the [[Indo-Fijian]] (ethnic Indian) electorate.  A new constitution was promulgated in 1990, establishing Fiji as a republic, with the offices of [[List of Presidents of Fiji|President]], [[List of Prime Ministers of Fiji|Prime Minister]], two-thirds of the [[Senate (Fiji)|Senate]], and a clear majority of the [[House of Representatives (Fiji)|House of Representatives]] reserved for ethnic Fijians, Ethnic Fijian ownership of the land was also entrenched in the constitution.

Fiji's case is a situation of defacto separation rather than racial segregation and has a long complex history with more than 3500 years as a divided Tribal nation, then united under the British and served as a Colony for 96 years and it was during that time other racial groups were introduced for various reasons through the Colonial authorities and then a mere 36 years as a modern democracy, the case here is more of an indigenous race trying to maintain and Govern the Land of their ancestors while trying to attain an inclusive and fair relationship with racial groups introduced in Fiji's recent History while finding its place as modern democracy and then working out a practical way forward.

===Malaysia=== 
{{refimprove|section|date=September 2007}}
[[Malaysia]] has an [[Article 153 of the Constitution of Malaysia|article in its constitution]] which distinctly segregates the [[Malay people|Malay]]s and other indigeneous peoples of Malaysia, or [[bumiputra]], from the non-Malays under the [[social contract (Malaysia)|social contract]], giving the indigeneous population special rights and privileges. This includes government-sponsored discounts and requiring even the [[private sector]] of the economy to preferentially treat bumiputras with economic privileges and penalising companies who do not have a certain quota of bumiputra in employment. Further more, any discussion of abolishing the article is prohibited with the justification that it is [[sedition|seditious]]. This form of state-sponsored racial segregation is claimed as apartheid to opponents of the article. Supporters of the policy maintain that this is [[affirmative action]] for the bumiputra who had suffered during the colonial era of the [[history of Malaysia]], using the concept of the [[Ketuanan Melayu]] that Malaysia belongs to the Malays.

===Yemen===

In Yemen, the Arabic elite practices an unofficial form of racial segregation: the population is implicitly divided into the higher-class Arabic stocks and the lower-class black Ethiopians, the Akhdam people [http://www.irinnews.org/report.aspx?reportid=25634].

===United States===
Black-White segregation is declining fairly consistently for most metropolitan areas in the US. Despite these pervasive  patterns, many changes for individual areas are small.&lt;ref&gt;''Inequality and Segregation''
R Sethi, R Somanathan - Journal of Political Economy, 2004&lt;/ref&gt;  Thirty years after the civil rights era, the United States remains a residentially segregated society in which Blacks and Whites inhabit different neighborhoods of vastly different quality.&lt;ref&gt;''SEGREGATION AND STRATIFICATION: A Biosocial Perspective'' Douglas S.  Massey Du Bois Review: Social Science Research on Race  (2004), 1: 7-25 Cambridge University Press&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Inequality and Segregation'' Rajiv Sethi and Rohini Somanathan ''Journal of Political Economy'', volume 112 (2004), pages 1296–1321 &lt;/ref&gt;

[[Redlining]] is the practice of denying or increasing the cost of services, such as [[banking]], [[insurance]], access to jobs,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.core.ucl.ac.be/services/psfiles/dp99/dp9913.pdf Racial Discrimination and Redlining in Cities]&lt;/ref&gt; access to health care,&lt;ref&gt;See: [[Race and health]]&lt;/ref&gt;  or even [[supermarkets]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.springerlink.com/content/ptc5hvexthe7wrye/ In poor health: Supermarket redlining and urban nutrition], Elizabeth Eisenhauer, [[GeoJournal]] 	Volume 53, Number 2 / February, 2001&lt;/ref&gt; to residents in certain, often racially determined,&lt;ref name="eastny"&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=TWo8OFJpFtAC How East New York Became a Ghetto] by Walter Thabit. ISBN 0814782671. Page 42.&lt;/ref&gt; areas. The most devastating form of redlining, and the most common use of the term, refers to [[Mortgage Discrimination|mortgage discrimination]].

Dan Immergluck writes that in 2002 small businesses in black neighborhoods still received fewer loans, even after accounting for businesses density, businesses size, industrial mix, neighborhood income, and the credit quality of local businesses.&lt;ref&gt;''Redlining Redux'' Urban Affairs Review, Vol. 38, No. 1, 22–41 (2002)&lt;/ref&gt; Gregory D. Squires wrote in 2003 that it is clear that race has long affected and continues to affect the policies and practices of the insurance industry.&lt;ref&gt;Racial Profiling, Insurance Style: Insurance Redlining and the Uneven Development of Metropolitan Areas Journal of Urban Affairs 25 (4), 391–410. &lt;/ref&gt; Workers living in American inner-cities have a harder time finding jobs than suburban workers.&lt;ref&gt;''Racial Discrimination and Redlining in Cities'' Yves Zenou and Nicolas Boccard 1999&lt;/ref&gt; 

The desire of many whites to avoid having their children attend integrated schools has been a factor in [[white flight]] to the suburbs.&lt;ref&gt; http://encarta.msn.com/encyclopedia_761580651_3/Segregation_in_the_United_States.html#s15&lt;/ref&gt; Recent studies in San Francisco showed that groups of homeowners tended to self-segregate in order to be with people of the same education level and race. &lt;ref&gt;[http://news.yahoo.com/s/livescience/20070910/sc_livescience/homeownersselfsegregatebyraceandeducation;_ylt=AlyjmsI5BA7s..hPZgWKnT0DW7oF Ap news article]&lt;/ref&gt; By 1990, the legal barriers enforcing segregation had been mostly replaced by decentralized racism, where whites pay more than blacks to live in predominantly white areas.&lt;ref name="vigdor"&gt;..&lt;/ref&gt; Today, many whites are willing, and are able, to pay a premium to live in a predominantly white neighborhood. Equivalent housing in white areas commands a higher rent.&lt;ref&gt;Kiel, K. A. and J. E. Zabel. "Housing Price Differentials in U.S. Cities: Household and Neighborhood Racial Effects." Journal of Housing Economics 5, 1996.&lt;/ref&gt;  By bidding up the price of housing, many white neighborhoods again effectively shut out blacks, because blacks are unwilling, or unable, to pay the premium to buy entry into white neighborhoods. Through the 1990s, residential segregation remained at its extreme and has been called "hypersegregation" by some sociologists or "American Apartheid"&lt;ref&gt;Massey, D. S. and N. A. Denton. American Apartheid. Cambridge: Harvard University Press, 1993. &lt;/ref&gt;

In February 2005 U.S. Supreme Court ruled in ''Johnson v. California'' (125 S. Ct. 1141) that the California Department of Corrections' unwritten practice of racially segregating prisoners in its prison reception centers — which California claimed was for inmate safety (gangs in California, as throughout the U.S., usually organize on racial lines)— is to be subject to [[strict scrutiny]], the highest level of constitutional review.

==Sociological research (''Brown v. Board of Education'')==

In the [[Brown v. Board of Education]] decision, Chief Justice [[Earl Warren]], writing for a unanimous court, said that "in the field of public education the doctrine of 'separate but equal' has no place. Separate educational facilities are inherently unequal... To separate them from others of similar age and qualifications solely because of their race generates a feeling of inferiority as to their status in the community that may affect their hearts and minds in a way unlikely ever to be undone."

The decision made clear that the justices were influenced in part by studies by [[Kenneth B. Clark]] showing that segregated education had a negative psychological effect upon black school children. Significant doubt was subsequently cast on these studies, especially Clark's "doll study." Black students in segregated schools were shown both black and white dolls and asked which one they liked better. A majority of black students preferred the white doll, which was believed by Clark to demonstrate lowered black self-esteem as a result of segregation. Clark, however, did not present to the court his own research which showed that black children in integrated schools were even more likely to choose the white doll than those in segregated schools. Though some blacks are even now socially aware that skin color does not matter in life decisions concerning enhancement (2006-2007).

In [[Toronto]], [[Canada]], racial segregation of “Black-only” public schools is currently being promoted by Canada's largest and most influential school board, the [[Toronto District School Board]]. [http://www.thestar.com/News/Ontario/article/274299] In 2005, controversy erupted when the Toronto District School Board's Equity Officer, [[Lloyd McKell]], who is black himself, spoke in favour of “Black-only schools”.  The proposal brought about a media backlash; the School Board claimed to have no plans to act on this proposal, however this has been proven incorrect as this very same school board is now taking a lead role in implementing this proposal [http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/LAC.20071107.SCHOOL07/TPStory/TPNational/Ontario/].  Similar controversy had taken place in the [[North York Board of Education]] in the 1980’s when the board attempted to turn [[Georges Vanier Secondary School]] into a black-only school. [http://www.torontosun.com/News/Columnists/MacDonald_Moira/2005/09/19/1223082.html]

==See also==

*[[Affirmative Action]]
*[[Al Wefaq]]
*[[Apartheid laws]]
*[[Bantustan]]
*[[Caste]]
*[[Eagle feather law]]
*[[Elitism]]
*[[Endogamy]]
*[[English as a Second Language]]
*[[Ethnic autonomous regions]]
*[[Forsyth County, Georgia v. The Nationalist Movement]]
*[[Genocide]]
*[[Ghetto]]
*[[Group Areas Act]]
*[[Jim Crow laws]]
*[[Judenhut]]
*[[Ku Klux Klan]]
*[[Mortgage Discrimination]]
*[[Muslim Mosque, Inc.]]
*[[Nation of Islam]]
*[[National Alliance (United States)|National Alliance]]
*[[Nuremberg laws]]
*[[Pass Law]]
*[[Redlining]]
*[[Religious segregation]]
*[[Second-class citizen]]
*[[Separate but equal]]
*[[Separatism]]
*[[Underground Railroad]]
*[[Xenophobia]]
*[[Yellow badge]]

==Notes ==
{{reflist}}

==References==

*Dobratz, Betty A. and Shanks-Meile, Stephanie L, ''White Power, White Pride: The White Separatist Movement in the United States'', Johns Hopkins University Press, 2001, 384 pages, ISBN 0-8018-6537-9.

* Stokes, DaShanne. (In Press) [http://www.geocities.com/eaglefeatherlaw/stokes.article.html "Legalized Segregation and the Denial of Religious Freedom"]

* ''Rural Face of White Supremacy: Beyond Jim Crow'', by Mark Schultz. University of Illinois Press, 2005, ISBN 0-252-02960-7.

==External links==
*[http://www.remembersegregation.org A site dedicated to the life of MLK]
*[http://www.skidmore.edu/~dkarp/Social%20Issues/E/history.html A study of segregation]
*[http://www.ericdigests.org/2003-2/race.html Constitutional Law and Race-Conscious Policies in K-12 Education]
*[http://www.geocities.com/eaglefeatherlaw Religious Freedom with Raptors] - details racism and segregation in Native American religious freedom.
*[http://www.alwefaq.org/ Website of Bahraini Islamists Al-Wefaq] (in Arabic)
{{Racism topics|state=collapsed}}
{{Types of Segregation}}
{{Discriminationfooter}}

[[Category:Racial segregation|*]]
[[Category:African-American history]]
[[Category:Antisemitism]]
[[Category:Core issues in ethics]]
[[Category:History of racial segregation in the United States]]
[[Category:Political theories]]
[[Category:Racism]]
[[Category:Politics and race]]
[[Category:Urban decay]]

[[da:Raceadskillelse]]
[[de:Rassentrennung]]
[[es:Segregación racial]]
[[fr:Ségrégation raciale]]
[[gl:Segregación racial]]
[[he:הפרדה גזעית]]
[[nl:Rassensegregatie]]
[[pl:Segregacja rasowa]]
[[pt:Segregação racial]]
[[simple:Racial Segregation]]
[[fi:Rotuerottelu]]
[[zh:種族隔離]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>