<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061111061206|87097740" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="26316" pageid="26316" ns="0" title="Racial segregation"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-11-13T15:47:55Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Ideology-small}}
[[Image:Rex theatre.jpg|right|thumb|250px|The Rex Theatre for Colored People, [[Leland, Mississippi]], June 1937]]
'''Racial segregation''' is characterized by separation of people of different [[race]]s in daily life when both are doing equal tasks, such as eating in a restaurant, drinking from a water fountain, using a rest room, attending school, going to the movies, or in the rental or purchase of a home. Segregation may be ''de jure'' ([[Latin language|Latin]], meaning "by law")&amp;mdash;mandated by law&amp;mdash;or ''de facto'' (also Latin, meaning "in fact"); ''de facto'' segregation may exist even illegally. A ''de facto'' a segregationist regime may be maintained by means ranging from [[racial discrimination]] in hiring and in the rental and sale of housing to [[vigilante]] violence such as [[lynching]]s; a situation that arises when members of different races mutually prefer to associate and do business with members of their own race would usually be described as ''separation''  or ''de facto separation'' of the races rather than ''segregation''.

Both [[South Africa]] in the ''[[apartheid]]'' era and the [[United States]]&amp;mdash;both during the [[History of slavery in the United States|slavery]] era (through 1865) and after the 1876 end of the [[Reconstruction]] that followed the [[United States Civil War]]&amp;mdash;passed laws requiring or permitting segregation of the [[race]]s in daily life. In 1896, the [[U.S. Supreme Court]] upheld, in ''[[Plessy v. Ferguson]]'' the right of [[U.S. state]]s and localities to mandate racial segregation. In 1913, President [[Woodrow Wilson]] ordered the segregation of the federal [[Civil Service]][http://teachingamericanhistory.org/library/index.asp?documentprint=1115]. In 1948, President [[Harry S. Truman]] ordered the [[desegregation]] of the U.S. military; in 1954 the Court, in ''[[Brown v. Board of Education]]'', largely reversed ''Plessy''; over the next eleven years, a succession of further court decisions and federal laws would completely invalidate ''de jure'' racial segregation and discrimination in the U.S., although ''de facto'' segregation and discrimination have proven more resilient.

''De jure'' segregation in both South Africa and the U.S. came with "[[miscegenation]] laws" (prohibitions against [[interracial marriage]]) and laws against hiring people of the race that is the object of discrimination in any but menial positions. Segregation in hiring practices contributed to [[economic inequality|economic imbalance]] between the races. Segregation, however, often allowed close contact in [[social hierarchy|hierarchical]] situations, such as allowing a person of one race to work as a servant for a member of another race. Segregation can involve [[spatial]] separation of the races, and/or mandatory use of different institutions, such as [[school]]s and hospitals by people of different races. 

==Overview==
Even though many societies throughout history have practiced racial segregation, it was by no means universal, and some multiracial societies such as the [[Roman Empire]] were notable for their rejection of racial segregation. Few modern societies officially practice racial segregation, and most officially frown upon racial discrimination. However, anxieties about racial, religious and cultural differences still find expression in other forms of political and social controversy, either as an official pretext for culturally accepted discrimination, or as a socially acceptable way to discuss cultural, religious and economic friction that results from racial discrimination. For example, [[immigration]] and religious controversies often mask concerns about the culture or racial composition of the immigrants. Issues of race relations also appear in seemingly race-neutral disputes, over such issues as poverty, healthcare, taxation, religion, enforcement of a particular set of cultural norms, and even fashion.

Racial segregation differs from racial discrimination in a number of ways. Discrimination ranges from individual actions, to socially enforced discriminatory behavior, to legally mandated differences in status between members of different races. Segregation has, typically, harshly reinforced discrimination: if people of different races live in separate neighborhoods, attend different schools, receive different social services, etc., then people of the favored races can be largely insulated from societal neglect of people of other races.

==Germanic apartheid system in 5th Century Britain==
Studies have suggested that small groups of invading [[Danes]], [[Saxons]], [[Angles]] and [[Jutes]] in the [[British Isles]] in the fifth century AD formed an apartheid system in what is now England stopping [[intermarriage]] with Britons although from about the 7th century AD such restrictions were removed and mixing began &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/science/nature/5192634.stm
|title=Britain 'had apartheid society'
|publisher=BBC News
|accessdate=2006-07-18 
}}&lt;/ref&gt;.

== Nazi Germany ==
An example of miscegenation laws was the [[Nuremberg Laws]] enacted by the [[Nazis]] in [[Germany]] against the large German [[Jew]]ish community during the [[1930s]]. The laws prohibited marriages between Jews (deemed as ''[[Untermensch]]en'' - "sub-humans") and German "[[Aryan#Racist connotations|Aryan]]s" (deemed the ''[[Herrenrasse]]'' - "master race").

Under the [[General Government]] of occupied [[Poland]] in [[1940]], the population was divided into different groups, each with different rights, food rations, allowed strips in the cities, public transportation, and assigned  
*[[Ukraine|Ukrainians]],
*Highlanders ([[Goralenvolk]]) - an attempt to split the Polish nation by using local collaborators
*[[Kashubians]] ([[Kaschobenvolk]]) - similar attempt like with Goralenvolk, but less successful
*[[Poland|Poles]], 
*[[Jew]]s (eventually sentenced to extermination as a category).
*[[Homosexuals]]

During the [[1930s]] and [[1940s|40s]], Jews in Nazi-controlled states were forced to wear yellow ribbons or stars of David, and were, along with [[Roma people|Romas]] (Gypsies) discriminated against by the racial laws. Jewish doctors and professors were not allowed to treat Aryan (effectively, [[gentile]]) patients or teach Aryan pupils, respectively. 
The Jews were also not allowed to use any public transportation, besides the ferry, and would only be able to shop from 3-5 in Jewish stores.  After [[Kristallnacht]] ("The Night of Broken Glass"), the Jews were fined 1,000,000 [[German reichsmark|marks]] for damages done by the Nazi troops and [[Schutzstaffel|SS]] members.

==United States==
{{main|Racial segregation in the United States}}

{{Mergeto|Racial segregation in the United States|date=September 2006}}

[[Image:1943 Colored Waiting Room Sign.jpg|thumb|200px|Sign for "Colored waiting room", [[Georgia (U.S. state)|Georgia]], 1943]]

After the [[Emancipation Proclamation]] abolished [[History of Slavery in the United States|slavery]] in the [[Southern United States|South]], racial discrimination became regulated by the so-called [[Jim Crow law]]s, which mandated strict segregation of the races. Though such laws were instituted shortly after fighting ended in many cases, they only became formalized after the end of [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican]]-enforced [[Reconstruction]] in the [[1870s]] and [[1880s|80s]] during a period known as the [[nadir of American race relations]]. This legalized segregation lasted up to the [[1960s]], primarily through the deep and extensive power of the [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democratic Party]] in the South. 

While the majority in 1896 ''[[Plessy vs. Ferguson|Plessy]]'' overtly upheld only "separate but equal" facilities (specifically, transportation facilities), Justice [[John Marshall Harlan]] in his [[dissenting opinion|dissent]] protested that the decision was an expression of [[white supremacy]]; he predicted that segregation would "stimulate aggressions … upon the admitted rights of colored citizens," "arouse race hate" and "perpetuate a feeling of distrust between [the] races."
[http://www.thenation.com/doc/20040503/fonerkennedy]&lt;!-- Eric Foner and Randall Kennedy, "Brown at 50", ''The Nation'', posted April 15, 2004 (May 3, 2004 issue)--&gt;

In the post-Civil War South, Democrats used the race issue to solidify their hold on Southern politics, playing on [[White (people)#Historic use of the term in the United States|white]] resentment of black political power. Democrats were the agents in passing segregation laws, as well as laws disenfranchising blacks (and sometimes poor whites) politically. In 1913, President [[Woodrow Wilson]] ordered the segregation of the federal [[Civil Service]][http://teachingamericanhistory.org/library/index.asp?documentprint=1115]. White and [[Black (people)|black people]] would sometimes be required to eat separately and use separate schools, public toilets, park benches, train and restaurant seating, etc. In some locales, in addition to segregated seating, it could be forbidden for stores or restaurants to serve different races under the same roof. 

Segregation was also pervasive in housing. State constitutions (for example, that of [[California Constitution|California]]) had clauses giving local jurisdictions the right to regulate where members of certain races could live.  White landowners often included [[restrictive covenant]]s in deeds through which they prevented blacks or [[Asian#'Asian' in other English-speaking countries|Asian]]s from ever purchasing their property from any subsequent owner.  In the [[1948]] case of ''[[Shelley v. Kraemer]]'', the [[Supreme Court of the United States|U.S. Supreme Court]] finally ruled that such covenants were unenforceable in a court of law.  However, residential segregation patterns had already become established in most American cities, and have often persisted up to the present (see [[white flight]]).

With the [[migration]] to the North of many black workers at the turn of the [[twentieth century]], and the friction that occurred with white and black workers during this time, segregation was and continues to be a phenomenon in northern cities as well as in the South. Whites generally allocate [[tenements]] as housing for the poorest blacks. It would be well to remember though, that while racism had to be legislated out of the South, many in the North, including Quakers and others who ran the [[Underground Railroad]], were ideologically opposed to southerners treatment of blacks. By the same token, many white southerners have a claim to closer relationships with blacks than wealthy northern whites, regardless of the latter's stated political persuasion. [http://www.skidmore.edu/~dkarp/Social%20Issues/E/history.html]

"[[Miscegenation]]" laws prohibited people of different races from marrying. As one of many examples of such state laws, [[Utah]]'s marriage law had an anti-miscegenation component that was passed in [[1899]] and repealed in [[1963]]. It prohibited marriage between a white and anyone considered a Negro, mulatto (half Negro), quadroon (one-quarter Negro), octoroon (one-eighth Negro), [[Mongols|Mongolian]], or member of the [[Malaysia|Malay]] race (presumably a [[Polynesia|Polynesian]] or [[Melanesia|Melanesian]]). No restrictions were placed on marriages between people that were not "white persons." (Utah Code, 40-1-2, C. L. 17, §2967 as amended by L. 39, C. 50; L. 41, Ch. 35.).

In [[World War I]], blacks served in the [[United States Armed Forces]] in segregated units. Black soldiers were often poorly trained and equipped. Still, the 93rd Division, fought alongside the [[French people|French]] &lt;!-- TODO: Figure out what this bit was trying to say (who needed troops, and with their use of [[Algeria]]n, [[Morocco|Moroccan]] --&gt;. The 369th Infantry (formerly 15th New York National Guard) Regiment distinguished themselves, and were known as the "[[Harlem]] Hellfighters". [http://www.worldwar1.com/dbc/detached.htm] [http://www.worldwar1.com/dbc/hhf.htm]

[[World War II]] saw the first black military pilots in the U.S., the Tuskegee Airmen, 99th Fighter Squadron, [http://www.smithsonianmagazine.com/issues/2004/may/interest.htm], and also saw the segregated 183rd Engineer Combat Battalion participate in the liberation of Jewish survivors at Buchenwald [http://members.aol.com/asargordon/encountr.htm].

During [[World War II]], people of [[Japanese people|Japanese]], [[Italian people|Italian]], and [[German people|German]] descent (whether citizens or not) were placed in [[internment camp]]s, on the basis of their ethnicity. However, the German Americans were not sent to internment camps to the same extent as the Japanese and Italian. See [[Japanese American internment]].

Pressure to end racial segregation in the [[Federal government of the United States|government]] grew among [[African American]]s and progressives after the end of World War II. On [[July 26]], [[1948]] [[President of the United States|President]] [[Harry S. Truman]] signed [[Executive Order 9981]], ending segregation in the United States Armed Forces. 

[[Image:Segregation_Dallas.jpg|thumb|200px|left|A segregated facility in [[Dallas, Texas|Dallas]], [[Texas]]. Note the sign "Colored Waiting Room" at the top.]]Institutionalized racial segregation was ended as an official practice by the efforts of such [[American Civil Rights Movement (1955-1968)|civil rights]] [[Activism|activists]] as [[Rosa Parks]] and [[Martin Luther King Jr.]], working during the period from the end of World War II through the passage of the [[Voting Rights Act]] and the [[Civil Rights Act of 1964]] supported by President [[Lyndon Johnson]]. Many of their efforts were acts of [[civil disobedience]] aimed at violating the racial segregation rules and laws, such as refusing to give up a seat in the black part of the bus to a white person (Rosa Parks), or holding [[sit-in]]s at all-white [[wiktionary:diner|diners]]. 

Not all racial segregation laws have been repealed in the United States, although Supreme Court rulings have rendered them unenforceable. For instance, the [[Alabama Constitution]] still mandates that ''Separate schools shall be provided for white and colored children, and no child of either race shall be permitted to attend a school of the other race''. [http://www.legislature.state.al.us/CodeOfAlabama/Constitution/1901/CA-245806.htm] &lt;!--  Professor H. Garlow has been a critical governmental influence on policies of legal desegregation. Thia may be true, and even useful, but it's uncited, and doesn't belong in the middle of this paragraph.--&gt; A proposal to repeal this provision was narrowly defeated in [[2004]]. However, in a different arena, the U.S. Supreme Court ruled in February [[2005]] in ''Johnson v. California'' (125 S. Ct. 1141) that the California Department of Corrections' unwritten practice of racially segregating prisoners in its prison reception centers — which California claimed was for inmate safety (gangs in California, as throughout the U.S., usually organize on racial lines)— is to be subject to [[strict scrutiny]], the highest level of constitutional review. Although the high court [[remanded]] the case back to the lower courts, it is likely{{citation needed}} that their decision will have the impact of forcing California to alter its practice of segregating by race in its reception centers.

A [[law]] need not stipulate ''de jure'' [[segregation]] in order to have the effect of ''de facto'' segregation. For example, the [[eagle feather law]], which governs the possession and [[religious]] use of [[eagle]] feathers, was officially written to protect then dwindling [[eagle]] populations while still protecting traditional [[Native Americans in the United States|Native American]] [[spiritual]] and [[religious]] customs, of which the use of eagles are central. The [[eagle feather law]] later met charges of promoting racial segregation due to the law’s provision authorizing the possession of eagle feathers to members of only one [[ethnic]] group, Native Americans, and forbidding Native Americans from including non-Native Americans in indigenous customs involving eagle feathers—a common modern practice dating back to the early 1500s.

Despite all of the legal changes of the past half-century, the United States remains a segregated society, with housing patterns, school enrollment, church membership, employment opportunities, and even college admissions all reflecting significant ''de facto'' segregation. Supporters of [[affirmative action]] argue that the persistence of such disparities reflects either racial discrimination or the persistence of its effects. 

[[Gates v. Collier]] was a case decided in federal court that brought an end to the trustee system and flagrant inmate abuse at the notorious [[Mississippi State Penitentiary]] at [[Parchman, Mississippi]]. In [[1972]] [[federal judge]], William C. Keady found that Parchman Farm violated modern standards of decency. He ordered an immediate end to all unconstitutional conditions and practices. Racial segregation of inmates was abolished. And the trustee system, which allow certain inmates to have power and control over others, was also abolished.&lt;ref name="hnet"&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.h-net.org/reviews/showrev.cgi?path=22500870194459
|title=Parchman Farm and the Ordeal of Jim Crow Justice
|publisher=
|accessdate=2006-08-28 
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the Civil Rights Project at [[Harvard University]], the actual desegregation of U.S. public schools peaked in [[1988]]; since that time the schools have, in fact, become more segregated. As of 2005, the present proportion of black students at majority white schools "a level lower than in any year since 1968." [http://www.thenation.com/doc/20051219/kozol] &lt;!-- Jonathan Kozol, [http://www.thenation.com/doc/20051219/kozol Overcoming Apartheid]. ''[[The Nation (U.S. periodical)|The Nation]]'', December 19, 2005. p. 26. --&gt;

==South Africa==
{{main|History of South Africa in the Apartheid Era}}
[[Image:DurbanSign1989.jpg|thumb|right|160px|"Petty apartheid": sign on Durban beach in English, Afrikaans and Zulu]]
[[History of South Africa in the apartheid era|Apartheid]] was a system which existed in [[South Africa]] for over forty years, although the term itself had a history going back to the [[1910s]] and unofficially before that for many years. It was formalized in the years following the victory of the [[National Party (South Africa)|National Party]] in the all-white national election of [[1948]], increased in dominancy under the rule of Prime Minister [[Hendrik Frensch Verwoerd]] and remained law until [[1990]]. Examples of apartheid policy introduced are the Prohibition of Mixed Marriages Act, [[1951]], which made it illegal for marriage between races. Apartheid was abolished following a rapid change in public perception of racial segregation throughout the [[world]], and an economic [[boycott]] against South Africa which had crippled and threatened to destroy its economy.

== Rhodesia ==

The British [[colony]] of [[Rhodesia]] (now [[Zimbabwe]]), under [[Ian Smith]], leader of the white minority government, declared unilateral independence in 1965.  For the next 15 years, Rhodesia operated under white minority rule until international sanctions forced Smith to hold multiracial elections, after a brief period of British rule in 1979.

Laws enforcing segregation had been around before 1965, although many institutions simply ignored them. One highly publicized legal battle occurred in [[1960]] involving the opening of a new [[Reps Theatre|Theatre]] that was to be open to all races, this incident was nicknamed [[Reps Theatre|"The Battle of the Toilets"]].

== Bahrain ==

After municipal elections in [[Bahrain]] in 2002 brought [[Islamist]] opposition party [[Al Wefaq|Al Wefaq Islamic Action]] to power in the capital [[Manama]], its newly installed mayor, [[Murthader Bader]] called for the introduction of racial segregation with the removal from the city of all non-Bahraini South Asian inhabitants and for the creation of a new township to house them. 

Mr Bader told the English language [http://www.gulf-daily-news.com/1yr_arc_Articles.asp?Article=87912&amp;Sn=BNEW&amp;IssueID=27131| Gulf Daily News] "It would cost a lot and we would have to find an area to accept them," he said. "A big question is where to build any new accommodation."

The government rejected the proposals.

==Israel and Israeli-occupied territories==
The Israeli human rights organisation [[B'Tselem]] criticises [[Israel]] for [[apartheid]]-like activities:
"Israel has established in the [[Occupied Territories]] a separation cum discrimination regime, in which it maintains two systems of laws, and a person’s rights are based on his or her national origin. This regime is the only of its kind in the world, and brings to mind dark regimes of the past, such as the [[Apartheid]] regime in [[South Africa]]." [http://www.btselem.org/english/settlements/index.asp]

Others argue that this comparison is ungrounded, maintaining that Israel has over one million [[Arab]] citizens, and they are given the same rights as the rest of the population. 

For example, Benjamin Pogrund, who was active in the South African anti-apartheid movement, wrote of the comparison:

::"... it isn't true. Anyone who knows what apartheid was, and who knows Israel today, is aware of that. Use of the apartheid label is at best ignorant and naïve and at worst cynical and manipulative." [http://www.mideastweb.org/israel_apartheid.htm]

Both [[Amnesty International]] and [[Human Rights Watch]] have expressed concern over human rights within Israel:

* From Human Rights Watch: 
::"Government-run Arab schools are a world apart from government-run Jewish schools. In virtually every respect, Palestinian Arab children get an education inferior to that of Jewish children, and their relatively poor performance in school reflects this." [http://hrw.org/english/docs/2001/12/05/isrlpa3399.htm]

*From Amnesty International:
::"In August the UN Committee on the Elimination of Racial Discrimination called for the revocation of the Citizenship and Entry into Israel Law, passed the previous year and extended for six months in July. The law institutionalized racial discrimination. It barred Israeli Arab citizens married to Palestinians from the Occupied Territories from living with their spouses in Israel, and forced families to either live apart or leave the country altogether." [http://web.amnesty.org/report2005/isr-summary-eng]

South African Archbishop emeritus [[Desmond Tutu]] has accused Israel of practising apartheid and said that "it reminded me so much of what happened to us black people in South Africa".[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/africa/1957644.stm]

==Fiji==
[[Fiji coups of 1987|Two military coups]] in [[Fiji]] in [[1987]] removed from power a government that was led by an [[Fijian people|ethnic Fijian]], but was supported principally by the [[Indo-Fijian]] (ethnic Indian) electorate, which then made up approximately half of the population.  A new constitution was promulgated in [[1990]], establishing Fiji as a republic, with the offices of [[List of Presidents of Fiji|President]], [[List of Prime Ministers of Fiji|Prime Minister]], two-thirds of the [[Senate (Fiji)|Senate]], and a clear majority of the [[House of Representatives (Fiji)|House of Representatives]] reserved for ethnic Fijians, despite the fact that ethnic Fijians then comprised less than half the population.  Ethnic Fijian ownership of the land (which was worked principally by Indo-Fijians) was also entrenched in the constitution.

World-wide condemnation of the [[1990]] constitution, and a [[Brain Drain|brain-drain]] of many Indo-Fijian professionals and business owners, caused the Fijian government to revise the [[Constitution of Fiji|constitution]] in [[1997]].  Amendments deleted most of the discriminatory provisions, and subsequent elections in [[1999]] brought a new government to power, with [[Mahendra Chaudhry]] as the country's first Indo-Fijian Prime Minister.  

[[Fiji coup of 2000|Another coup followed in 2000]], with [[George Speight]], supported by sympathetic officers in the Army and police force, seizing power, with the aim of ending Indo-Fijian influence in politics.  Democracy, and the moderate [[1997]] constitution, were eventually restored, however.

Current prime minister [[Laisenia Qarase]] has refused to adhere to the Constitution by not including members of the largely Indo-Fijian [[Fiji Labour Party]] in the government.(this article needs updating)

== Australia ==
From [[Federation of Australia|Australian federation]] (1901) up to the 1970s, what became known as the "[[White Australia Policy]]" officially discriminated against those who were not white and prevented them from immigrating to [[Australia]], by deliberately making their immigration tests too hard to pass. The history of this form of racial discrimination is described in a government fact sheet [http://www.immi.gov.au/facts/08abolition.htm]. The various government laws and acts that made up the Policy were amended or replaced over a course of twenty or so years, from the mid-fifties to the mid-seventies. See [[White Australia Policy]]. 

In the past, it was policy for [[Indigenous Australians|Aborigines]] to be taken to live on missions, the intention being for them to be "out of the way" for the expanding territory of the white settlers. In the early-to-mid 20th Century the official policy regarding half-Aboriginal children was one of ''assimilation'': they would be brought up on the missions to become part of white society and made to marry only white people, the intention being to "breed out" the Aboriginal traits by the third generation or so. Around the 1960s, the official policy regarding all indigenous Australians was changed to one of ''integration'': being able to live either in Western society, on missions or in traditional society.  

Despite the official stance being integration, a large percentage of indigenous Australians live away from the urban areas in comparatively poor socio-economic conditions, leaving them somewhat segregated from the rest of Australian society. A number of commentators and civil rights groups have characterised the situation as apartheid [http://www.unswpress.com.au/isbn/0868407194.htm][http://www.zmag.org/content/Race/pilger0127.cfm][http://www.hartford-hwp.com/archives/24/054.html] - in fact, Australia's government policies are viewed by some as the original impetus for the apartheid system in South Africa. [http://www.hartford-hwp.com/archives/24/177.html][http://www.jcu.edu.au/aff/history/articles/limb.htm][http://www.convictcreations.com/history/federation.htm]

== Malaysia == 
[[Malaysia]] has an [[Article 153 of the Constitution of Malaysia|article in its constitution]] which distinctly segregates the [[Malay people|Malay]]s and other indigeneous peoples of Malaysia from the non-Malays, or [[bumiputra]] under the [[social contract (Malaysia)|social contract]], giving them special rights and privileges. This includes government-sponsored discounts and requiring even the [[private sector]] of the economy to preferentially treat bumiputras with economic privileges and penalising companies who do not have a certain quota of bumiputra in employment. Furthermore, any discussion of abolishing the article is prohibited with the justification that it is [[sedition|seditious]]. This form of state-sponsored racial segregation is claimed as apartheid to opponents of the article. Supporters of the policy maintain that this is [[affirmative action]] for the bumiputra who had suffered during the colonial era of the [[history of Malaysia]], using the concept of the [[Ketuanan Melayu]] that Malaysia belongs to the Malays.

==Sociological research behind ''Brown v. Board''==

In the Brown v. Board decision, Chief Justice [[Earl Warren]], writing for a unanimous court, said that "in the field of public education the doctrine of 'separate but equal' has no place. Separate educational facilities are inherently unequal... To separate them from others of similar age and qualifications solely because of their race generates a feeling of inferiority as to their status in the community that may affect their hearts and minds in a way unlikely ever to be undone."

The decision made clear that the justices were influenced in part by studies by [[Kenneth B. Clark]] showing that segregated education had a negative psychological effect upon black school children. Significant doubt was subsequently cast on these studies, especially Clark's "doll study." Black students in segregated schools were shown both black and white dolls and asked which one they liked better. A majority of black students preferred the white doll, which was believed by Clark to demonstrate lowered black self-esteem as a result of segregation. Clark, however, did not present to the court his own research which showed that black children in integrated schools were even more likely to choose the white doll than those in segregated schools. 
Furthermore, when Asian children were segregated around the turn of the century, they consistently outperformed white children.

==See also==

*[[Ethnic autonomous regions]]
*[[Al Wefaq]]
*[[Apartheid]] laws
*[[Bantustan]]
*[[Eagle feather law]]
*[[Forsyth County, Georgia v. The Nationalist Movement]]
*[[Ghetto]]
*[[Group Areas Act]]
*[[Jim Crow laws]]
*[[Judenhut]]
*[[Ku Klux Klan]]
*[[National Alliance]]
*[[Nation of Islam]]
*[[Nuremberg laws]]
*[[Pass Law]]
*[[Religious segregation]]
*[[Second-class citizen]]
*[[Separate but equal]]
*[[Separatism]]
*[[Underground Railroad]]
*[[Xenophobia]]
*[[Yellow badge]]
*[[Muslim Mosque, Inc.]]

''Compare''
*[[Race]], [[racialism]], and [[racism]]
*[[Black supremacy]], [[Hispanic supremacy]], and [[White supremacy]] 
*[[Black pride]] and [[White pride]]
*[[Black Power]] and [[White Power]]
*[[Black nationalism]], [[Chicano nationalism]], and [[White nationalism]]

==References==
&lt;references/&gt;
*Dobratz, Betty A. and Shanks-Meile, Stephanie L, ''White Power, White Pride!: The White Separatist Movement in the United States'', Johns Hopkins University Press, 2001, 384 pages, ISBN 0-8018-6537-9.

* Stokes, DaShanne. (In Press) [http://www.geocities.com/eaglefeatherlaw/stokes.article.html ''Legalized Segregation and the Denial of Religious Freedom'']

*Rural Face of White Supremacy: Beyond Jim Crow, by Mark Schultz. University of Illinois Press, 2005, ISBN 0-252-02960-7.

==External links==
*[http://www.remembersegregation.org A site dedicated to the life of MLK]
* [http://www.skidmore.edu/~dkarp/Social%20Issues/E/history.html A study of segregation]
*[http://www.crusader.net/resources/election.html A white separatist FAQ]
* [http://www.ericdigests.org/2003-2/race.html Constitutional Law and Race-Conscious Policies in K-12 Education]
* [http://www.geocities.com/eaglefeatherlaw Religious Freedom with Raptors] - details racism and segregation in Native American religious freedom.
* [http://www.alwefaq.org/ Website of Bahraini Islamists Al-Wefaq] (in Arabic)

[[Category:Racial segregation|*]]
[[Category:African-American history]]
[[Category:Antisemitism]]
[[Category:Core issues in ethics]]
[[Category:History of racial segregation in the United States]]
[[Category:Political theories]]
[[Category:Racism]]
[[Category:Politics and race]]

[[da:Raceadskillelse]]
[[de:Rassentrennung]]
[[es:Segregación racial]]
[[gl:Segregación racial]]
[[he:הפרדה גזעית]]
[[nl:Rassensegregatie]]
[[pl:Segregacja rasowa]]
[[pt:Segregação racial]]
[[fi:Rotuerottelu]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>