<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20041105110150|7297382" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="26316" pageid="26316" ns="0" title="Racial segregation"><revisions><rev timestamp="2004-11-10T14:55:10Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Racial segregation''' is a kind of formalized or institutionalized [[racial discrimination|discrimination on the basis of race]], characterized by their separation from each other. The separation may be geographical, but is usually supported by providing services through separate institutions (such as schools) and through similar legal and social structures. See also: [[racism]].

== Introduction ==

Although many societies throughout history have practiced racial segregation, it was by no means universal, and societies such as the [[Roman Empire]] were notable for their rejection of racial segregation. Most modern societies reject racism (at least officially). However, anxieties about racial issues tend to be phrased in coded form as issues relating to [[immigration]].

In general, rationales for racial segregation can be divided into two classes:
* an attempt by a majority group to oppress or expel a minority group
* an attempt at self-determination by the minority group itself

== Nazi Germany==

A grotesque example of how [[miscegenation]] laws were enacted can be seen during the [[1930s]], when the racist and [[Anti-Semitism|Anti-Semitic]] [[Nuremberg Laws]] enacted by the [[Nazis]] in [[Germany]] against the large German [[Jew]]ish community, forbidding marriages between the Jews (deemed as ''[[Untermensch]]en'' - "lower people") and German "[[Aryan]]s" (deemed the ''[[Übermensch]]en'' - "higher people"). Many interfaith and intermarried couples committed suicide when these laws came into effect.

In the [[General Government]] in [[1940]] the population was divided on different groups. Each group had different rights, food ratios, allowed strips in the cities, public transportation and restricted restaurants. Listed from the most privilaged to the least:
*Germans from Germany (''Reichdeutsche'')
*Germans from outside, active ethnic Germans, Volksliste category 1 and 2 (see [[Volksdeutsche]])
*Germans from outside, passive Germans and members of families (this group included also many ethnic Poles), Volksliste category 3 and 4, 
*[[Ukraine|Ukrainians]],
*Highlanders (''Goralenvolk'') - an attempt to split Polish nation by using local collaborators  
*[[Poland|Poles]], 
*[[Jew|Jews]] (eventually sentenced to extermination as a category).

During the 1930s and 40s, Jews and Gypsies were forced to wear yellow ribbons, and were discriminated against by the racial laws. Jewish doctors and professors were not allowed to teach [[Aryan]] pupils or cure [[Aryan]] patients.


During the WWII, Jews and  Gypsies were sent to the [[concentration camp]]s, solely on the basis of their race.

== USA==

Racial discrimination was regulated by the so-called [[Jim Crow law]]s from the [[United States Civil War|Civil War]], primarily (although not exclusively) in the [[U.S. Southern States]]. Such legal segregation lasted up to the [[1960s]]. White and black people would sometimes be required to use separate schools, public toilets, park benches, train and restaurant seating, etc.  "[[Miscegenation]]" laws prohibited people of different races from marrying. In some locales, in addition to segregated seating, it could be forbidden for stores or restaurants to serve different races under the same roof.

During [[World War II]], people of Japanese descent (whether citizens or not) were [[Japanese American relocation|excluded]] from the [[West Coast of the United States|West Coast]] and placed in [[internment camp]]s, on the basis of their race.

Advocation to end government racial segregation grew amoung African Americans and progressives after the end of the World War. On [[January 26]], [[1948]] [[President of the United States|President]] [[Harry S. Truman]] signed [[Executive Order 9981]], ending segregation in the [[United States Armed Forces]]. 

Institutionalized racial segregation was ended by the efforts of such [[civil rights]] activists as [[Rosa Parks]] and [[Martin Luther King Jr.]], working during the period from the end of World War II through the passage of the [[Voting Rights Act]] and the [[Civil Rights Act of 1964]] supported by President [[Lyndon Johnson]]. Many of their efforts were acts of [[civil disobedience]] aimed at violating the racial segregation rules and laws, such as insisting on sitting at the front of the bus (Rosa Parks), or holding sit-ins at all-white diners. 

Although racial equality is, at least in theory, granted to all citizens in the US today, some see the [[USA Patriot Act]] as an attempt at covert racial segregation or discrimination against non-citizens. [[Arab]]s and [[Pakistan]]is, who have similar skin color, are allegedly subjected to different procedures that do not apply to others.  However, the US has strict rules against [[racial profiling]] to prevent such segregation.

== South Africa==

[[Apartheid]] was a system which existed in [[South Africa]] for over forty years, although the term itself had a history going back to the [[1910s]]. It was formalized in the years following the victory of the [[National Party (South Africa) | National Party]] in the (all-white) national election of [[1948]] and remained the law until [[1990]]. It was abolished following a rapid change in public perception of racial segregation throughout the [[world]], and an economic [[boycott]] against South Africa which had crippled and threatened to destroy its economy.

== Rhodesia ==
The British [[colony]] of Rhodesia (now [[Zimbabwe]]), under [[Ian Smith]], leader of the white minority government, declared unilateral independence in 1965.  For the next 15 years, Rhodesia operated under white minority rule until international sanctions forced Smith to hold multiracial elections, after a brief period of British rule in 1979.

== Israel ==
A number of organisations, including the [[Palestinian Society for the Protection of Human Rights|Palestinian Society for the Protection of Human Rights (LAW)]] and the [[Islamic Human Rights Commission]], believe that [[Israel]] is an apartheid state under the [[United Nations|UN]] definition. Recently some laws have been enacted in Israel to make it practically impossible to gain citizenship in the Jewish State by way of marriage. The paragraphs include special provisions which target Palestinians. The laws drew protests from the UN and the EU.

== Arab world ==
Institutionalized ethnic discrimination exists in many [[Arab]] countries. [[Jordan]] forbids Jews from becoming citizens. [[Palestinian]] refugees are generally treated as second-class citizens at best in their countries of refuge. 

Many [[Gulf states]] import large numbers of [[migrant workers]] from [[South Asia]] and other countries to do menial labour, who are often treated extremely poorly. Generally speaking, Arab countries recognize only Arabs as first-class citizens, though treatment of others ranges from tolerance to hostility in different places.

==Fiji==
[[Fiji coups of 1987|Two military coups]] in [[Fiji]] in [[1987]] removed from power a government that was led by an [[Fijian people|ethnic Fijian]], but was supported principally by the [[Indo-Fijian]] (ethnic Indian) electorate, which then made up approximately half of the population.  A new constitution was promulgated in [[1990]], establishing Fiji as a republic, with the offices of [[List of Presidents of Fiji|President]], [[List of Prime Ministers of Fiji|Prime Minister]], two-thirds of the [[Senate (Fiji)|Senate]], and a clear majority of the [[House of Representatives (Fiji)|House of Representatives]] reserved for ethnic Fijians, despite the fact that ethnic Fijians then comprised less than half the population.  Ethnic Fijian ownership of the land (which was worked principally by Indo-Fijians) was also entrenched in the constitution.

World-wide condemnation of the [[1990]] constitution, and a brain-drain of many Indo-Fijian professionals and businesspeople, caused the Fijian government to revise the [[Constitution of Fiji|constitution]] in [[1997]].  Amendments deleted most of the discriminatory provisions, and subsequent elections in [[1999]] brought a new government to power, with [[Mahendra Chaudhry]] as the country's first Indo-Fijian Prime Minister.  

[[Fiji coup of 2000|Another coup followed in 2000]], with [[George Speight]], supported by sympathetic offices in the Army and police force, seizing power, with the aim of ending Indo-Fijian influence in politics.  Democracy, and the moderate [[1997]] constitution, were eventually restored, however.

Current prime minister [[Laisenia Qarase]] has refused to adhere to the Constitution by not including members of the largely Indo-Fijian [[Fiji Labour Party]] in the government.

==Related issues==

Although not all advocates concede the validity of the concept of "race" as applied to human divisions, discrimination on color or other ethnic characteristics is often labelled "racist" (see [[race]], [[racism]]).

==White separatism==

'''White separatism''' is the belief that that those who are of [[Whites|white]] or [[Caucasian]] [[race]] should have separate institutions or even separate societies, territories, governments, and should not "breed" with those considered to be of non-white races. White separatists often label themselves as [[racialism|racialist]]s rather than [[racist]]s. White separatism is one among many forms of [[separatism]].

Many white separatists believe in [[white supremacy]], but some do not.  Some consider the segregationists of the [[Southern United States]] and the advocates of [[apartheid]] in [[South Africa]] as being white separatists as these advocates of segregationism and apartheid used the same language of separatism and denied that they were "White supremacists" despite evidence to the contrary. Both groups also had advanced a belief in the inherent "inferiority" of non-whites, whom they claimed are incapable of properly either governing themselves or any other races. Some segragationists put forward the proposition that "separation" doesn't necessarily mean superiority and thus endorsed the "separate but equal" proposition for educational segregation that the [[U.S. Supreme Court]] struck down in the case of [[Brown v. Board of Education]].

[[Kevin Alfred Strom]], on the [[National Alliance]]'s white separatist radio program ''[[American Dissident Voices]]'', defined the difference between white separatism and supremacy this way:

:"A supremacist&amp;mdash;of whatever race&amp;mdash;is distinct from a 'separatist.' A separatist may believe that his race is superior to other races in some or all characteristics, but this is not his essential belief. The separatist is defined by his wish for freedom and independence for his people. He wishes them to have their own society, to be led by their own kind, to have a government which looks out for their interests alone. The separatist does not wish to live in a multiracial society at all, so he naturally has no desire to rule over other races&amp;mdash;since such rule necessitates the multiracial society the separatist wants to avoid at all costs." [http://www.natvan.com/pub/012404.txt]

Sociologists [[Betty A. Dobratz]] and [[Stephanie Shanks-Meile]] contend that terms such as "white separatism" and "white nationalism" are [[euphemism]]s that have been adopted by what they refer to as [[neo-nazi]] and [[racist]] groups as a tactical move in order to make their views seem less extreme. The [[Center for Democratic Renewal]] likewise called the term "white separatist" a "media gloss." [http://gbgm-umc.org/umw/anti-hate/definitions.html] Proponents claim that their desire to remove themselves from [[Desegregation|integrated]] society and [[Racial segregation|segregate]] removes the possibility of subjagating other [[ethnicities]], and thus has no relation to supremacy at all. They often say they have no desire to intermingle with other races at all, neither to harm them nor to force them into [[slavery]] or other such conditions.

Light-skinned people are found among many ethnic groups, and the genetic basis of light pigmintation is not exclusive to any one particular racial category. Generally, white separatists claim genetic affiliation with Anglo-Saxon cultures, and sometimes to beliefs asserting ancestory with the Semitic peoples of the Christian bible. White separatists are often found among [[Christian Identity]] groups, some of whom refer to the United States as the "[[Zionist Occupation Government]]" and propose a "White" homeland in the northwestern corner of what is currently the [[United States|United States of America]].

The [[anti-racism|anti-racist]] group ''Turn it Down'', which campaigns against [[White Power]] music, defines the term "white separatist" as follows:

:"''white separatist'': a euphemism for white supremacist. The label has been adopted by individuals and organizations to obscure or present a more benevolent facade for the beliefs in racial segregation and/or neo-Nazism." [http://www.turnitdown.com/info/lexicon.html]

The [[National Alliance]], a white separatist group which is often accused of being white supremacist and [[neo-nazi]], has referred to [[Adolf Hitler]] in an editorial as being the "greatest man of our era" [http://www.nageorgia.com/articles_measure.html], but still claims not to be a white supremacist group and dismisses all criticism of this type as part of a "[[Jew]]ish plot" to suppress the "racial defense mechanisms" of white people by accusing those who believe in "white separatist ideals" as being "white supremacists". [http://www.natvan.com/pub/012404.txt].

The separation between separatism and supremacy continues to be unclear. A contemporary example which received press attention came during the campaign for the [[2004]] [[Arizona]] Proposition 200, [[Protect Arizona Now]] (the law restricts access by illegal aliens to services). National Advisory Board Chair Dr. [[Virginia Abernethy]] responded to a journalist's questions about her allegedly supremacist views by stating that she considers herself a separatist, not a supremacist. "''I'm in favor of separatism -- and that's different than supremacy. Groups tend to self-segregate. I know that I'm not a supremacist. I know that ethnic groups are more comfortable with their own kind.''" [http://www.eastvalleytribune.com/?sty=26431 East Valley Tribune: "Migrant foe tied to racism, news update", 11/5/04]  While this statement appears to show indifference to those of other races, Dr. Abernethy has written elsewhere that [[European-American]]s have made the greatest contributions to society and so they must strive to maintain adequate fertility to continue the race. [http://www.chroniclesmagazine.org/Chronicles/March2004/0304Abernethy.html Chronicles:"Homosexuality, In the Cards: Hanging Ourselves", 3/04] Abernethy is a leader in ethnic pride groups like the [[Council of Conservative Citizens]] that denigrate other minorities. This indicates that some self-described "separatists" still consider their race to be at least pre-eminent, if not supreme.

== Black separatism ==
Parallel to the white separatism, there also exists, particularly in the [[United States]], a similarly politically marginal '''black separatist''' movement. Black separatists generally hold that whites are racist oppressors of blacks and that there can be no remedy for black advancement within contemporary white-dominated society. They believe that the only solution for blacks is to break away and to create a separate, segregated black society.

The more specific goals were historically in flux and varied from group to group.
[[Martin Delaney]] in the 19th century and [[Marcus Garvey]] in the 1920s outspokenly called for African Americans to return to [[Africa]], by moving to [[Liberia]]. The [[Nation of Islam]] calls, much more quietly, for an independent black state on American soil. Much more mainstream views within black separatism hold that blacks would be better served by exclusively black schools and businesses, as well as by black local politicians and police.

The mainstream black separatism is sharply opposed by anti-segregationists and integrationists within the African American community. They generally hold that blacks can and should advance within the larger American society and call on them to work to achieve that through personal improvement, educational achievement, business involvement, and political action. [[Martin Luther King]], who led the political effort to overthrow segregation in 1960s, and [[Malcolm X]], a contemporary black separatist from the [[Nation of Islam]] may personify the opposition between the two views.

== Latino separatism ==
Some of the political groups among Latinos, or Americans of Mexican descent, in 1960s advocated racial separatism for the [[bronze race]] or the [[Chicanos]]. Some of them wanted to create an independent Chicano state in the south-west of [[United States]], on the territories that were won by America from [[Mexico]] after the [[Mexican-American War]] in 1848. Some of these views were reflected in the [[Plan Espiritual de Aztlan]] document which inspired Movimiento Estudiantil Chicano de Aztlan, [[MEChA]]. MEChA is a Chicano separatist movement whose ideologies run parallel to Hitler's Nazi Party including, the formation of a separate homeland only for Chicanos ("a bronze nation") and "...reclaiming the land of our birth...."

==See also==

*[[Apartheid]]
*[[Jim Crow]]
*[[National Alliance]]
*[[Race]]
*[[Racism]]
*[[White supremacy]]
*[[Xenophobia]]
*[[Anti-semitism]]
*[[Nation of Islam]]
*[[MEChA]]
*[[Plan Espiritual de Aztlan]]

==References==
*Dobratz, Betty A. and Shanks-Meile, Stephanie L, ''White Power, White Pride!: The White Separatist Movement in the United States'', Johns Hopkins University Press, 2001, 384 pages, ISBN 0801865379.

==External links==
* [http://www.crusader.net/resources/election.html A white separatist FAQ]
* [http://mumford1.dyndns.org U.S. Segregation over several decades]
*[http://www.ericdigests.org/2003-2/race.html Constitutional Law and Race-Conscious Policies in K-12 Education]

==Material regarding Israel ==
* [http://www.hrw.org/press/2001/12/SecondClass1205.htm Israeli Schools Separate, Not Equal]
* [http://web.amnesty.org/web/ar2002.nsf/mde/israel+and+the+occupied+territories+!Open Amnesty International report 2002 Israel and the occupied territories]	 
* [http://www.afsc.org/middleeast/peace/jerusalem/jeruhistory.htm Item on the history of Jerusalem] from the [[American Friends Service Committee]]
* [http://www.lawsociety.org/Apartheid/dibook.html LAW paper: "Israel's brand of apartheid: The Nakba continues"]
* [http://www.mediamonitors.net/mosaddeq11.html "Apartheid In the Holy Land"]:  full text of a paper presented by Nafeez Ahmed of the Islamic Human Rights Commission, at the 2001 [[UN Conference Against Racism]] in Durban
* [http://www.ihrc.org/ Islamic Human Rights Commission]
* [http://www.adl.org/durban/durban_083001.asp ADL statement on the anti-Israeli and anti-Semitic outcry at Durban]
* [http://www.israelnewsagency.com/mfa10.23.html Full text of Interview with Shimon Peres]
* [http://www.bitterlemons.org/previous/bl120802ed30.html Alon Liel, former director general of the Israel Foreign Ministry, on the question of apartheid]
* [http://www.aish.com/jewishissues/jewishsociety/An_Old_Story_Anti-Semitism3_Past_and_Present.asp Anti-Semitism - past and Present]. Claims anti-Semitic motives in some of the individuals who accuse Israel of Apartheid.
* [http://www.adl.org/durban/durban_083001.asp ADL statement on the anti-Israeli and anti-Semitic outcry at Durban]
* [http://oznik.com/words/021212.html Haaretz article about interreligious marriages in Israel] (omitted in the official English edition)

[[de:Rassentrennung]]

[[Category:Anti-Semitism]]
[[Category:Core issues in ethics]]
[[Category:Nazi Germany]]
[[Category:Neo-Nazi movements and concepts]]
[[Category:Political theories]]
[[Category:South Africa]]
[[Category:U.S. civil rights history]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>