<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20091116220937|326234387" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="26316" pageid="26316" ns="0" title="Racial segregation"><revisions><rev timestamp="2009-11-16T22:11:45Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Redirect|Segregationist|the short story by Isaac Asimov|Segregationist (short story)}}
[[File:Segregated cinema entrance3.jpg|thumb|250px|An [[African-American]] man climbs stairs to a theater's "colored" entrance, [[Mississippi]], 1939. The door on the ground level is marked "white men only".]]
{{Segregation}}
{{Discrimination sidebar}}
'''Racial segregation''' is the separation of different [[Race (classification of human beings)|racial group]]s in daily life, such as eating in a restaurant, drinking from a water fountain, using a [[washroom]], attending school, going to the movies, or in the rental or purchase of a home.&lt;ref&gt;''Principles to Guide Housing Policy at the Beginning of the Millennium'', Michael Schill &amp; Susan Wachter, [[Cityscape]]&lt;/ref&gt; Segregation may be mandated by law or exist through social norms. Segregation may be maintained by means ranging from [[discrimination]] in hiring and in the rental and sale of housing to certain races to [[vigilante]] violence (such as [[lynching]]s, e.g.) Generally, a situation that arises when members of different races mutually prefer to associate and do business with members of their own race would usually be described as ''separation'' or ''de facto separation'' of the races rather than ''segregation''. In the [[United States]], legal segregation  was required in some states and came with "[[anti-miscegenation laws]]" (prohibitions against [[interracial marriage]]).{{Citation needed|date=May 2008}}
There were laws passed against segregation in the USA in the 1960s. 

Segregation, however, often allowed close contact in [[social hierarchy|hierarchical]] situations, such as allowing a person of one race to work as a servant for a member of another race. Segregation can involve [[wiktionary:spatial|spatial]] separation of the races, and/or mandatory use of different institutions, such as schools and hospitals by people of different races.

==Historical cases==
Historically various conquerors—among them Asian [[Mongols]], African [[Bantu]], and American [[Aztec]]s—have practiced discrimination involving the segregation of subject races. Racial segregation has appeared in all parts of the world where there are multiracial communities.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/488135/racial-segregation Racial segregation]. Britannica Online Encyclopedia.&lt;/ref&gt; 

===Indo-Aryan India===
3,000–8,000 years ago, [[Indo-European]]-speaking nomadic groups from Europe, the Near East, Anatolia, and the Caucasus migrated to India. According to 19th century British historians, it was these "Aryans" who and established the [[caste system]], an [[elitist]] form of social organization that (according to the British) separated the "light-skinned" Indo-Aryan conquerors from the "conquered dark-skinned" indigenous [[Dravidian people|Dravidian]] tribes through enforcement of "racial [[endogamy]]". This claim was used by the British, defining themselves as "purely Aryan", to justify [[British Raj|British Rule in India]]. Much of this was simply [[conjecture]], fueled by [[British Empire|British]] [[imperialism]]&lt;ref name="NehruIndia"&gt;From [[Discovery of India]] by [[Jawaharlal Nehru]], reproduced from "History : Modern India" (p108) by S.N. Sen, New Age Publishers, ISBN 8122417744&lt;/ref&gt; British policies of [[divide and rule]] as well as enumeration of the population into rigid categories during the tenure of British rule in India contributed towards the hardening of these segregated caste identities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Corbridge |first=Staurt |coauthors=Harriss, John |title= Reinventing India: Liberalization, Hindu Nationalism and Popular Democracy|year=2000 |publisher= Polity press |page=8}}
&lt;/ref&gt;. Since the independence of [[South Asia]] from British rule, the British [[fantasy]] of an "Aryan Invasion and subjugation of the dark skinned Dravidians in India" has become a staple polemic in [[South Asia]]n geopolitics, including the propaganda of [[Indophobia]] in Pakistan&lt;ref&gt;[[Ayesha Jalal]]. (1995). [http://www.jstor.org/sici?sici=0020-7438(199502)27:1%3C73:CPHAOI%3E2.0.CO;2-0 Conjuring Pakistan: History as Official Imagining]. ''International Journal of Middle East Studies''. 27(1). pp. 73-89.&lt;/ref&gt;. There is no decisive theory as to the origins of the caste system in India, and globally renown historians and archaeologists like [[Jim Shaffer]], [[J.P. Mallory]], [[Edwin Bryant]], and others, have disputed the claim of "Aryan Invasion"&lt;ref&gt;
*[[Jim Shaffer]] - "Current archaeological data do not support the existence of an Indo-Aryan or European invasion into South Asia any time in the pre- or protohistoric periods. Instead, it is possible to document archaeologically a series of cultural changes reflecting indigenous cultural developments from prehistoric to historic periods"{{cite book|title = The Indo-Aryan Invasions : Cultural Myth and Archaeological Reality | author = Jim Shaffer}}
*[[J.P. Mallory]] - "... the extraordinary difficulty of making a case for expansions from Andronovo to northern India, and that attempts to link the Indo-Aryans to such sites as the Beshkent and Vakhsh cultures only gets the Indo-Iranian to Central Asia, but not as far as the seats of the Medes, Persians or Indo-Aryans". As quoted in Bryant (see below)
*[[Edwin Bryant]] - "India is not the only Indo-European-speaking area that has not revealed any archaeological traces of immigration."there is at least a series of archaeological cultures that can be traced approaching the Indian subcontinent, even if discontinuous, which does not seem to be the case for any hypothetical east-to-west emigration"
{{cite book| last =Bryant | first =Edwin | author-link =Edwin Bryant | year =2001 | title =[[The Quest for the Origins of Vedic Culture]]: The Indo-Aryan Migration Debate | publisher =Oxford University Press | isbn =0195137779}}.
{{cite book | year=2005 | editor-last=Bryant | editor-first=Edwin F. | editor-link=Edwin Bryant | editor2-last=Patton | editor2-first=Laurie L. | editor2-link= | title=The Indo-Aryan Controversy: Evidence and inference in Indian history | publication-place=London | publisher=Routledge | isbn=0-7007-1463-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some researchers from Europe and the U.S. claim that genetic similarities to Europeans were more common in members of the higher ranks. Their findings, published in ''[[Genome Research]]'', claimed the idea that members of higher castes are more closely related to Europeans than are the lower castes.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=scientists-connect-indian Scientists Connect Indian Castes and European Heritage]. [[Scientific American]]. May 15, 2001.&lt;/ref&gt;. However, other researchers have criticized and contradicted this claim.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal
 | last = Basu
 | first = Analabha
 | coauthors = Namita Mukherjee, Sangita Roy, Sanghamitra Sengupta, Sanat Banerjee, Madan Chakraborty, Badal Dey, Monami Roy, Bidyut Roy, Nitai P. Bhattacharyya, Susanta Roychoudhury and Partha P. Majumder
 | year = 2003
 | title = Ethnic India: A Genomic View, With Special Reference to Peopling and Structure
 | journal = Genome Research
 | volume = 13
 | issue = 10
 | pages = 2277–2290
 | pmid = 14525929
 | doi = 10.1101/gr.1413403
 | url = http://www.genome.org/cgi/reprint/13/10/2277
 | accessdate = 2007-09-09
}}&lt;/ref&gt; A study by Joanna L. Mountain et al. of [[Stanford University]] had concluded that there was "no clear separation into three genetically distinct groups along caste lines", although "an inferred tree revealed some clustering according to caste affiliation".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal
 | last = Mountain
 | first = Joanna L.
 | coauthors = J M Hebert, S Bhattacharyya, P A Underhill, C Ottolenghi, M Gadgil, and L L Cavalli-Sforza
 | month = April
 | year = 1995
 | title = Demographic history of India and mtDNA-sequence diversity
 | journal = [[American Journal of Human Genetics]]
 | volume = 56
 | issue = 4
 | pages = 979–992
 | issn = 0002-9297
 | pmid = 7717409
 | url = http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/picrender.fcgi?artid=1801212&amp;blobtype=pdf
 | accessdate = 2007-09-09
}}&lt;/ref&gt; A 2006 study by Ismail Thanseem et al. of [[Centre for Cellular and Molecular Biology]] (India) concluded that the "lower caste groups might have originated with the hierarchical divisions that arose within the tribal groups with the spread of [[Neolithic]] agriculturalists, much earlier than the arrival of Aryan speakers", and "the [[Indo-Aryans|Indo-Europeans]] established themselves as upper castes among this already developed caste-like class structure within the tribes."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal
 | last = Thanseem
 | first = Ismail
 | coauthors = Kumarasamy Thangaraj, Gyaneshwer Chaubey, Vijay Kumar Singh, Lakkakula VKS Bhaskar, B Mohan Reddy, Alla G Reddy, and Lalji Singh
 | month = August
 | year = 2006
 | title = Genetic affinities among the lower castes and tribal groups of India: inference from Y chromosome and mitochondrial DNA
 | journal = BMC Genetics
 | volume = 7
 | pages = 42
 | doi = 10.1186/1471-2156-7-42
 | url = http://www.biomedcentral.com/content/pdf/1471-2156-7-42.pdf
 | accessdate = 2007-09-09
|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt; A 2006 genetic study by the National Institute of Biologicals in India, testing a sample of men from 32 tribal and 45 caste groups, concluded that the Indians have acquired very few genes from [[Indo-European languages|Indo-European]] speakers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|title=India Acquired Language, Not Genes, From West, Study Says
|author=Brian Handwerk
|url=http://news.nationalgeographic.com/news/2006/01/0110_060110_india_genes.html
|publisher=National Geographic News
|date=2006-01-10
|accessdate=2006-12-08
}}&lt;/ref&gt; More recent studies have also debunked the British claims that so-called "Aryans" and "Dravidians" have a "racial divide". A study conducted by the [[Centre for Cellular and Molecular Biology]] in [[2009]] (in collaboration with [[Harvard Medical School]], [[Harvard School of Public Health]] and the [[Broad Institute of Harvard]] and [[MIT]]) analyzed half a million genetic markers across the genomes of 132 individuals from 25 ethnic groups from 13 states in India across multiple caste groups.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dnaindia.com/scitech/report_indians-are-one-people-descended-from-two-tribes_1292864 Indians are one people descended from two tribes]&lt;/ref&gt; The study establishes, based on the impossibility of identifying any genetic indicators across caste lines, that castes in South Asia grew out of traditional tribal organizations during the formation of Indian society, and was not the product of any mythical "Aryan Invasion" and "subjugation" of Dravidian people, unlike what British racial-[[revanchist]] and [[Historical revisionism (negationism)|revisionist]] claims would have one believe.&lt;ref&gt;[http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/news/india/Aryan-Dravidian-divide-a-myth-Study/articleshow/5053274.cms Aryan-Dravidian divide a myth: Study], [[Times of India]]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Anglo-Saxon England===
Segregation may have existed in early [[Timeline of Anglo-Saxon England|Anglo-Saxon England]], restricting intermarriage and resulting in the displacement of the native [[Brython|British]] population by [[Germanic peoples|Germanic]] incomers.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.nationalgeographic.com/news/2006/07/060721-england.html Ancient Britain Had Apartheid-Like Society, Study Suggests]&lt;/ref&gt; According to research led by the [[University College London]], Anglo-Saxon settlers enjoyed substantial social and economic advantages over [[Celt|Celtic Britons]].&lt;ref&gt;Thomas, Mark G. et al. [http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/articlerender.fcgi?artid=1635457 Evidence for a segregated social structure in early Anglo-Saxon England]. ''[[Proceedings of the Royal Society]] B: Biological Sciences'' 273(1601): 2651–2657.&lt;/ref&gt; However, [[Stephen Oppenheimer]] and [[Bryan Sykes]] argue that there was no population displacement, as the Anglo-Saxons had relatively little genetic impact on England.&lt;ref&gt;[http://scienceblogs.com/gnxp/2006/09/blood_of_the_british.php Gene Expression: Blood of the Wakas  Wakas&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.prospect-magazine.co.uk/article_details.php?search_term=oppenheimer&amp;id=7817 Special report: 'Myths of British ancestry' by Stephen Oppenheimer | Prospect Magazine October 2006 issue 127&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; In 2002, the [[BBC]] used the headline "English and Welsh are races apart" to report a genetic survey of test subjects from [[market town]]s in England and Wales.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/wales/2076470.stm "English and Welsh are Races Apart"], ''[[BBC]]'', 30 June, 2002&lt;/ref&gt;

===Jewish segregation===
[[Jew]]s in Europe generally were forced, by decree or by informal pressure, to live in highly segregated [[ghettos]] and [[shtetls]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Wirth, Louis]]. ''The Ghetto''. Transaction Publishers (1997), pp. 29–40. ISBN 1560009837.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1204 the papacy required Jews to segregate themselves from Christians and to wear distinctive clothing.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www2.kenyon.edu/projects/margin/jew.htm A Short History of the Jewish Tradition ]&lt;/ref&gt; Forced segregation of Jews spread throughout Europe during the 14th and 15th centuries.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/232679/ghetto Ghetto]. Encyclopædia Britannica.&lt;/ref&gt; In the [[Russian Empire]], Jews were restricted to the so-called [[Pale of Settlement]], the Western frontier of the Russian Empire corresponding roughly to the modern-day countries of Poland, Lithuania, Belarus and Ukraine.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.britannica.com/eb/article-215022/anti-Semitism Anti-Semitism in modern Europe]&lt;/ref&gt; By the early 20th century, the majority of European Jews lived in the Pale of Settlement.

Jewish population were confined to [[mellah]]s in [[Morocco]] beginning from the 15th century. In cities, a ''mellah'' was surrounded by a wall with a fortified gateway. In contrast, rural ''mellahs'' were separate villages inhabited solely by the Jews.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sefarad.org/publication/lm/017/morocco.html The Jews of Morocco, by Ralph G. Bennett]&lt;/ref&gt; 

In the middle of the 19th century, [[J. J. Benjamin]] wrote about the life  of [[History of Jews in Iran|Persian Jews]]: 
&lt;blockquote&gt;"…they are obliged to live in a separate part of town…; for they are considered as unclean creatures…  Under the pretext of their being unclean, they are treated with the greatest severity and should they enter a street, inhabited by Mussulmans, they are pelted by the boys and mobs with stones and dirt…  For the same reason, they are prohibited to go out when it rains; for it is said the rain would wash dirt off them, which would sully the feet of the Mussulmans…  If a Jew is recognized as such in the streets, he is subjected to the greatest insults.  The passers-by spit in his face, and sometimes beat him… unmercifully…  If a Jew enters a shop for anything, he is forbidden to inspect the goods… Should his hand incautiously touch the goods, he must take them at any price the seller chooses to ask for them... Sometimes the Persians intrude into the dwellings of the Jews and take possession of whatever please them. Should the owner make the least opposition in defense of his property, he incurs the danger of atoning for it with his life... If... a Jew shows himself in the street during the three days of the Katel (Muharram)…, he is sure to be murdered."&lt;ref&gt;Lewis (1984), pp. 181–183&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

===Qing dynasty China===
Following their conquest of [[China]] and establishment of the [[Qing]] dynasty in 1644, the [[Manchu]]s were keenly aware of their minority status. During the early eras of their reign, they implemented a strict policy of racial segregation between the Manchus and [[Mongol]]s on the one hand and the [[Han Chinese]] on the other. This ethnic segregation had cultural and economic reasons: intermarriage was forbidden to keep up the Manchurian heritage and minimize sinicization. In addition, in 1668 all Han Chinese were banned from settling in Manchuria (see ''[[Willow Palisade]]'').&lt;ref&gt;[http://darkwing.uoregon.edu/~inaasim/Mingqing04/Qing2.htm From Ming to Qing]&lt;/ref&gt; Since the beginning of the [[Qing dynasty]] in 1644, Han men in China had been required to wear a [[pigtail]] as a sign of submission to the ruling [[Manchus]]. The penalty for refusal was death.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Hair: Its Power and Meaning in Asian Cultures|author=Hiltebeitel, Alf et al.|publisher=[[State University of New York Press]]|date=1998|page=128}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The policy of segregation applied directly to the [[Eight Banners|banner]] garrisons, most of which occupied a separate walled zone within the cities in which they were stationed. (The Eight Banners formed the basic framework for the Manchu military organization.) Examples as in cities where there were limitations of space, such as in [[Qingzhou]] (青州), a new fortified town was purposely erected to house the Banner garrison and their families.  While the Manchus followed the governmental structure of the preceding [[Ming dynasty]], their ethnic policy dictated that appointments were split between Manchu noblemen and Han officials who had passed the highest levels of the [[Imperial examinations|state examinations]].

===Latin America===
Many women in [[Latin American]] countries had [[casta|caste systems]] based on classification by race and race mixture.  An entire nomenclature developed, including the familiar terms "[[Mulatto|mulato]]", "[[mestizo]]", and "[[zambo]]" (whence "[[Sambo (racial term)|sambo]]").  The caste system was imposed during colonial rule by the Spanish and Portuguese who had practiced a form of caste system in [[Hispania]] prior to the expulsion of the Jews and Muslims. While many Latin American countries have long since rendered the system officially illegal through legislation, usually at the time of independence, prejudice based on degrees of perceived racial distance from [[Europe]]an ancestry combined with one's socioeconomic status remain, an echo of the colonial caste system.&lt;ref&gt;Soong, Roland. [http://www.zonalatina.com/Zldata55.htm "Racial Classifications in Latin America"], 1999.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt; Cline, Howard F., [http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0002-8762(197112)76%3A5%3C1626%3ARACILA%3E2.0.CO%3B2-6 "Review"], ''The American Historical Review'', Vol. 76, No. 5 (Dec., 1971), 1626-1628.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Germany===
The ban of interracial marriage was part of the [[Nuremberg Laws]] enacted by the [[Nazis]] in [[Germany]] against the German [[Jew]]ish community during the 1930s. The laws prohibited marriages between Jews and [[Aryan]] Germans, which were classified as different races.&lt;ref&gt;The Laws for the Protection of German Blood and German Honour (September 15, 1935), section 1. "Marriages between Jews and citizens of German or kindred blood are forbidden. Marriages concluded in defiance of this law are void, even if, for the purpose of evading this law, they were concluded abroad."&lt;/ref&gt;

Under General Government of occupied [[Poland]] in 1940, the population was divided into different groups, each with different rights, food rations, allowed strips in the cities, public transportation, etc.
*[[Ukraine|Ukrainians]]
*[[Poland|Poles]]
*Highlanders ([[Goralenvolk]]) - an attempt to split the greater "Polish" identity
*[[Kashubians]] ([[Kaschobenvolk]]) - similar attempt like with Highlanders, but less successful
*[[Jew]]s 
*[[Homosexuals]] 
*[[Romani people]]
*[[Jehovah's Witnesses]]

During the 1930s and 1940s, Jews in Nazi-controlled states were made to wear yellow ribbons or stars of David, and were, along with [[Romani people|Romas]] (Gypsies) discriminated against by the racial laws. Jewish doctors and professors were not allowed to treat Aryan (effectively, [[gentile]]) patients or teach [[Aryan race|Aryan]] pupils, respectively. 
The Jews were also not allowed to use any public transportation, besides the ferry, and would only be able to shop from 3-5 in Jewish stores.  After [[Kristallnacht]] ("The Night of Broken Glass"), the Jews were fined 1,000,000 [[German reichsmark|marks]] for damages done by the Nazi troops and [[Schutzstaffel|SS]] members. Jews and Roma were subjected to [[genocide]] as "undesirable" "racial" groups in the [[Holocaust]]. 

[[Ghettos in occupied Europe 1939-1944|Ghetto]]s were established by the [[Nazism|Nazis]] to confine Jews and sometimes Romas into tightly packed areas of the cities of [[Eastern Europe]] turning them into ''de-facto'' [[concentration camp]]s. The [[Warsaw Ghetto]] was the largest of these [[Ghettos in occupied Europe 1939-1944|Ghettos]], with 400,000 people and the [[Łódź Ghetto]], the second largest, holding about 160,000.&lt;ref&gt;[http://fcit.usf.edu/HOLOCAUST/timeline/ghettos.htm Holocaust Timeline: The Ghettos]&lt;/ref&gt;

Between 1939 and 1945, at least 1.5 million [[Poland|Polish]] citizens were transported to the Reich for [[forced labour]], against their will (in all, about 12 million forced laborers were employed in the German war economy inside the [[Nazi Germany]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dw-world.de/dw/article/0,2144,1757323,00.html Final Compensation Pending for Former Nazi Forced Laborers]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://summeroftruth.org/enemy/barracks.html Forced Labor at Ford Werke AG during the Second World War]&lt;/ref&gt;). Although Nazi Germany also used forced laborers from [[Western Europe]], [[Poles]], along with other [[Eastern Europe]]ans viewed as racially inferior,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dac.neu.edu/holocaust/Hitlers_Plans.htm  Hitler’s Plans]&lt;/ref&gt; were subject to deeper discriminatory measures. They were forced to wear identifying purple tags with P's sewn to their clothing, subjected to a [[curfew]], and banned from [[public transportation]]. While the treatment of factory workers or farm hands often varied depending on the individual employer, Polish laborers as a rule were compelled to work longer hours for lower wages than Western Europeans — and, in many cities, they were forced to live in segregated barracks behind barbed wire. Social relations with [[Germans]] outside work were forbidden, and sexual relations ("racial defilement") were punishable by death.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.holocaust-trc.org/poles.htm Poles: Victims of the Nazi Era]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Italy===
In 1938, the [[fascism|fascist]] regime led by [[Benito Mussolini]] introduced a series of laws instituting an official segregationist policy in the [[Kingdom of Italy (1861–1946)|Italian Empire]], especially aimed against the [[Jew]]s. This policy enforced various segregationist norms, like the prohibition for Jews to teach or study in ordinary schools and universities, to own industries reputed of major national interest, to work as journalists, to enter the military, and to wed non-Jews.
Some of the immediate consequences of the introduction of the 'provvedimenti per la difesa della razza' (norms for the defence of the race) included many of the best Italian scientists leaving their job, or even Italy. Amongst these, world-renowned physicists [[Emilio Segrè]], [[Enrico Fermi]] (whose wife was Jewish), [[Bruno Pontecorvo]], [[Bruno Rossi]], [[Tullio Levi-Civita]] and mathematicians [[Federigo Enriques]] and [[Guido Fubini]]. [[Rita Levi-Montalcini]], who would successively win the [[Nobel Prize]] for medicine, was forbidden to work at the university. [[Albert Einstein]], upon approval of the racial law, resigned from honorary membership of the [[Accademia dei Lincei]].

Later, [[Fascist Italy]] participated actively in the persecution of the Italian Jews, arresting and handing over tens of thousands of Jews to [[Nazi Germany]]. The persecution of the Jews ended in southern Italy (controlled by the Kingdom of Italy) after the armistice with the Allies (September 8, 1943), while in central and northern Italy (controlled by the [[Italian Social Republic]], a puppet state of Nazi Germany led by Mussolini) the persecution continued until the definitive fall of Mussolini's regime (April 25, 1945).

===Rhodesia===
The British colony of [[Rhodesia]] (now [[Zimbabwe]]), under [[Ian Smith]], leader of the white minority government, declared unilateral independence in 1965.  For the next 15 years, Rhodesia operated under white minority rule until international sanctions forced Smith to hold multiracial elections, after a brief period of British rule in 1979.

[[File:DurbanSign1989.jpg|thumb|upright|right|"Petty apartheid": sign on Durban beach in English, [[Afrikaans]] and Zulu languages]]
Laws enforcing segregation had been around before 1965, although many institutions simply ignored them. One highly publicized legal battle occurred in 1960 involving the opening of a new [[Reps Theatre|Theatre]] that was to be open to all races, this incident was nicknamed [[Reps Theatre|"The Battle of the Toilets"]].

===South Africa===
{{Main|South Africa under apartheid}}

[[History of South Africa in the apartheid era|Apartheid]] was a system which existed in [[South Africa]] for over forty years, although the term itself had a history going back to the 1910s and unofficially before that for many years. It was formalized in the years following the victory of the [[National Party (South Africa)|National Party]] in the all-white national election of 1948, increased in dominancy under the rule of Prime Minister [[Hendrik Frensch Verwoerd]] and remained law until 1994.  Examples of apartheid policy introduced are the [[Prohibition of Mixed Marriages Act]], 1951, which made marriage between races illegal.

Apartheid was abolished following a rapid change in public perception of racial segregation throughout the world, and an economic [[boycott]] against South Africa which had crippled and threatened to destroy its economy.

===United States===
{{Main|Racial segregation in the United States}}

After the [[Thirteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Thirteenth Amendment]] abolished [[Slavery in the United States|slavery]] in America, racial discrimination became regulated by the so called [[Jim Crow laws]], which mandated strict segregation of the races. Though such laws were instituted shortly after fighting ended in many cases, they only became formalized after the end of [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican]]-enforced [[Reconstruction era of the United States|Reconstruction]] in the 1870s and 80s during a period known as the [[nadir of American race relations]]. This legalized segregation lasted up to the 1960s, primarily through the deep and extensive power of [[Southern Democrats]]. 

[[File:Segregation 1938b.jpg|thumb|left|thumb|An African-American youth at a drinking fountain in [[Halifax, North Carolina]], in 1938.]]
While the [[U.S. Supreme Court]] majority in 1896 ''[[Plessy vs. Ferguson|Plessy]]'' overtly upheld only "separate but equal" facilities (specifically, transportation facilities), Justice [[John Marshall Harlan]] in his [[dissenting opinion|dissent]] protested that the decision was an expression of [[white supremacy]]; he predicted that segregation would "stimulate aggressions … upon the admitted rights of colored citizens," "arouse race hate" and "perpetuate a feeling of distrust between [the] races. Feelings between whites and blacks were so tense, even the jails were segregated. "&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thenation.com/doc/20040503/fonerkennedy Brown at 50&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!-- Eric Foner and Randall Kennedy, "Brown at 50", ''The Nation'', posted April 15, 2004 (May 3, 2004 issue)--&gt;

Institutionalized racial segregation was ended as an official practice by the efforts of such [[American Civil Rights Movement (1955-1968)|civil rights]] [[Activism|activists]] as [[Clarence Mitchell, Jr.]], [[Rosa Parks]] and [[Martin Luther King Jr.]], working during the period from the end of World War II through the passage of the [[Voting Rights Act]] and the [[Civil Rights Act of 1964]] supported by President [[Lyndon B. Johnson]]. Many of their efforts were acts of [[non-violent]] [[civil disobedience]] aimed at disrupting the enforcement of racial segregation rules and laws, such as refusing to give up a seat in the black part of the bus to a white person ([[Rosa Parks]]), or holding [[sit-in]]s at all-white [[wiktionary:diner|diners]]. 

By 1968 all forms of segregation had been declared unconstitutional by the Supreme Court and by 1970, support for formal legal segregation had dissolved. Formal racial discrimination was illegal in school systems, businesses, the American military, other civil services and the government. Separate bathrooms, water fountains and schools all disappeared and the civil rights movement had the public's support.&lt;ref name="autogenerated1"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://encarta.msn.com/encyclopedia_761580651_3/Segregation_in_the_United_States.html|title=Encarta Encyclopedia|accessdate=2007-04-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Since then, African-Americans have played a significant role as mayors, governors, and state officials in both Southern and Northern states and on the national level have been on the Supreme Court, in the House of Representatives and the Senate, in presidential cabinets, as head of the joint chiefs of staff, and in 2009, the first black [[President of the United States]].&lt;ref name="autogenerated1" /&gt; 

[[Redlining]] is the practice of denying or increasing the cost of services, such as banking, insurance, access to jobs,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.core.ucl.ac.be/services/psfiles/dp99/dp9913.pdf Racial Discrimination and Redlining in Cities]&lt;/ref&gt; access to health care,&lt;ref&gt;See: [[Race and health]]&lt;/ref&gt;  or even [[supermarkets]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.springerlink.com/content/ptc5hvexthe7wrye/ In poor health: Supermarket redlining and urban nutrition], Elizabeth Eisenhauer, [[GeoJournal]] 	Volume 53, Number 2 / February, 2001&lt;/ref&gt; to residents in certain, often racially determined,&lt;ref name="eastny"&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=TWo8OFJpFtAC How East New York Became a Ghetto] by Walter Thabit. ISBN 0814782671. Page 42.&lt;/ref&gt; areas. The most devastating form of redlining, and the most common use of the term, refers to [[Mortgage Discrimination|mortgage discrimination]]. Over the next twenty years, a succession of further court decisions and federal laws, including the ''[[Home Mortgage Disclosure Act]]'' and measure to end [[Mortgage Discrimination|mortgage discrimination]] in 1975, would completely invalidate ''[[de jure]]'' racial segregation and discrimination in the U.S., although ''de facto'' segregation and discrimination have proven more resilient.  According to the Civil Rights Project at [[Harvard University]], the actual de facto desegregation of U.S. public schools peaked in the late 1980s; since that time, the schools have, in fact, become more segregated mainly due to the ethnic segregation of the nation with whites dominating the suburbs and minorities the urban centers. As of 2005, the present proportion of black students at majority white schools "are a level lower than in any year since 1968." 
{{Citation needed|date=December 2007}}

==Contemporary segregation==
===Middle East===
There is considerable racial segregation in [[Bahrain]] and the [[United Arab Emirates]], where there are areas that house large numbers of [[South Asian]] migrant workers (primarily from [[India]] and [[Pakistan]], but also from [[Bangladesh]]).[http://lib.ohchr.org/HRBodies/UPR/Documents/Session3/AE/Mafiwasta_ARE_UPR_S3_2008anx_EnforcingMigrantWorkersRightsinTheUnitedArabEmirates.pdf]. After municipal elections in [[Bahrain]] in 2002 brought [[Islamist]] opposition party [[Al Wefaq Islamic Action]] to power in the capital [[Manama]], its newly installed mayor, [[Murthader Bader]] called for the introduction of racial segregation with the removal from the city of all non-Bahraini [[South Asian]] inhabitants and for the creation of a new township to house them. In 2004, the head of Manama City Council, Al Wefaq’s Murthader Bader, called for the introduction of racial segregation &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gulf-daily-news.com/1yr_arc_Articles.asp?Article=87912&amp;Sn=BNEW&amp;IssueID=27131&amp;date=7/29/2004 Clashes spark call to relocate expats] Gulf Daily News, July 29 2004&lt;/ref&gt; in the city with the removal of South Asian nationals to other parts of the country.In 2006, the call was reiterated by Al Wefaq councillor Sadiq Rahma who said Asians 'make the neighbourhood dirty' &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gulf-daily-news.com/1yr_arc_Articles.asp?Article=133367&amp;Sn=BNEW&amp;IssueID=28309&amp;date=1-23-2006 'No go' rule for bachelor labourers] Gulf Daily News, January 23 2006&lt;/ref&gt;. The move has been criticised by Bahraini human rights groups as a 'a violation of basic human rights' &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gulf-daily-news.com/1yr_arc_Articles.asp?Article=133973&amp;Sn=BNEW&amp;IssueID=28316&amp;date=1-30-2006 Segregation of Asians slammed] Gulf Daily News, January 30, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;. After 2006’s elections, the party’s Abdullah Al A’ali used his parliamentary platform to call for legislation to restrict expatriate labour away from Bahraini families, saying "Labourers who now live in neighbourhoods with Bahraini families should be given a grace period to relocate before they face legal action." &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gulfnews.com/region/Bahrain/10110820.html Deputy calls for labour housing regulations], Gulf News, 13 March 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

===Fiji===
{{Refimprove|section|date=October 2007}}
[[Fiji coups of 1987|Two military coups]] in [[Fiji]] in 1987 removed from power a government that was led by an [[Fijian people|ethnic Fijian]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/asia-pacific/country_profiles/1300477.stm Country profile: Fiji]&lt;/ref&gt; but was supported principally by the [[Indo-Fijian]] (ethnic Indian) electorate.  A new constitution was promulgated in 1990, establishing Fiji as a republic, with the offices of [[List of Presidents of Fiji|President]], [[List of Prime Ministers of Fiji|Prime Minister]], two-thirds of the [[Senate (Fiji)|Senate]], and a clear majority of the [[House of Representatives (Fiji)|House of Representatives]] reserved for ethnic Fijians, Ethnic Fijian ownership of the land was also entrenched in the constitution.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lonelyplanet.com/worldguide/fiji/history Fiji: History]&lt;/ref&gt;

Fiji's case is a situation of de facto ethnic segregation.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rnzi.com/pages/news.php?op=read&amp;id=23319 UN seminar highlights concern in Fiji over ethnic segregation]&lt;/ref&gt;. Fiji has a long complex history with more than 3500 years as a divided Tribal nation. Unification under the British rule as a Colony for 96 years bought other racial groups, particularly immigrants from the Indian sub-continent.

Independent Fiji's young democracy has been troubled by some tension between the Indigenous Fijians and the Indo-Fijians at a Political level along with provincial differences also and this combined has caused some challenges with the Nation moving forward clearly.

===India===
Some activists consider that the [[Indian caste system]] is a form of [[racial discrimination]]&lt;ref name="npr"&gt;[http://www.npr.org/programs/specials/racism/010828.caste.html An Untouchable Subject?]&lt;/ref&gt;. The participants of the [[United Nations]] Conference Against Racism in [[Durban]], [[South Africa]] in March 2001, condemned discrimination due to the caste system, and tried to pass a resolution declaring that caste as a basis for the segregation and oppression of peoples in terms of their descent and occupation is a form of [[apartheid]]. However, no formal resolution was passed to that effect&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hri.ca/racism/Submitted/Theme/castedeclaration.shtml Final Declaration of the Global Conference Against Racism and Caste-based Discrimination]&lt;/ref&gt;

India's treatment of Dalits has been described by some authors as "India's hidden apartheid".&lt;ref&gt;Gopal Guru, with Shiraz Sidhva. [http://www.unesco.org/courier/2001_09/uk/doss22.htm India’s "hidden apartheid"]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Rajeev Dhavan. [http://www.hinduonnet.com/2001/08/24/stories/05242523.htm India's apartheid]&lt;/ref&gt; 

Such allegations have also been rejected by many sociologists such as [[Andre Béteille]], who writes that treating caste as a form of racism is "politically mischievous" and worse, "scientifically nonsense" since there is no discernible difference in the racial characteristics between [[Brahmins]] and [[Scheduled Castes]]. He writes that "Every social group cannot be regarded as a race simply because we want to protect it against prejudice and discrimination"&lt;ref&gt;[http://wcar.alrc.net/mainfile2.php/For+the+negative/14/ Race and caste] by [[Andre Beteille]]&lt;/ref&gt;.

[[Pakistan]]i-American sociologist [[Ayesha Jalal]] also rejects these allegations. In her book, "Democracy and Authoritarianism in [[South Asia]]", she writes that "As for [[Hinduism]], the hierarchical principles of the [[Brahmin|Brahmanical]] social order have always been contested from within Hindu society, suggesting that equality has been and continues to be both [[Hindu reform movements|valued and practiced]]."&lt;ref&gt;A. Jalal,Democracy and Authoritarianism in [[South Asia]]: A Comparative and Historical Perspective (Contemporary South Asia), Cambridge University Press (May 26, 1995), ISBN 0521478626&lt;/ref&gt;

===Malaysia===
{{Main|Bumiputra|Ketuanan Melayu}}
[[Malaysia]] has an [[Article 153 of the Constitution of Malaysia|article in its constitution]] which distinctly segregates the ethnic [[Malay people|Malay]]s and indigenous peoples of Malaysia—i.e [[bumiputra]]—from the non-Bumiputra such as the [[Chinese people|Chinese]] and the [[Person of Indian Origin|East Indian]]s under the [[social contract (Malaysia)|social contract]], of which by law would guarantee the former certain special rights and privileges. To question these rights and privileges however is strictly prohibited under the Internal Security Act, legalised by the 10th Article(IV) of the Constitution of Malaysia&lt;ref&gt;[[Constitution of Malaysia#Article_10|Constitution of Malaysia, Article 10]]&lt;/ref&gt;. The privileges mentioned herein covers—few of which—the economical and education aspects of Malaysians, e.g. the [[Malaysian New Economic Policy]]; an economic policy recently criticised by Thierry Rommel—who headed a European Commission's delegation to Malaysia—as an excuse for "significant protectionism"&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/asia-pacific/6237328.stm BBC News Asia-Pacific]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.infernalramblings.com/articles/Malaysian_Politics/496/ Infernal ramblings]&lt;/ref&gt; and a quota maintaining higher access of Malays into public universities. This system of segregation, seen as a form of apartheid by its opponent&lt;ref&gt;[http://blog.limkitsiang.com/2007/06/26/if-not-for-people-like-rommel-south-africa-would-still-have-apartheid/ blog entry 2007-06-26]&lt;/ref&gt;.

===Mauritania===
[[Slavery in Mauritania]] was finally criminalized in August 2007&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/6938032.stm Mauritanian MPs pass slavery law] by [[BBC News]]&lt;/ref&gt; It was already abolished in 1980 though it was still affecting the descendants of black Africans abducted into slavery before generations, who live now in Mauritania as "black [[Moors]]" or ''haratin'' and who partially still serve the "white Moors", or ''bidhan'' (the name means literally white-skinned people), as slaves. The number of slaves in the country was not known exactly, but is was estimated to be up to 600,000 men, women and children, or 20% of the population.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.saiia.org.za/modules.php?op=modload&amp;name=News&amp;file=article&amp;sid=1141 Mauritania made slavery illegal last month]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/worldservice/specials/1458_abolition/page4.shtml The Abolition season] on [[BBC World Service]]&lt;/ref&gt; 

For centuries, the so-called [[Haratin]] lower class, mostly poor black Africans living in rural areas, have been considered natural slaves by white Moors of Arab/Berber ancestry. Many descendants of the [[Arab]] and [[Berber people|Berber]] tribes today still adhere to the [[supremacist]] ideology of their ancestors. This ideology has led to oppression, discrimination and even enslavement of other groups in the region of [[Sudan]] and Western [[Sahara]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.irinnews.org/report.aspx?ReportId=70522 Fair elections haunted by racial imbalance]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.iabolish.org/slavery_today/in_depth/sudan-genocide.html War and Genocide in Sudan]&lt;/ref&gt; In certain villages in [[Mauritania]] there are [[mosque]]s for lighter-skinned nobles and mosques for black slaves, who are still buried in separate cemeteries.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.irinnews.org/Report.aspx?ReportId=75756 Mauritania: The real beginning of the end of slavery?]&lt;/ref&gt;  

===Yemen===
:''See also [[Caste#Castes_in_Yemen|Castes in Yemen]]''
In [[Yemen]], the [[Arab]] elite practices an unofficial form of discrimination against the lower class [[Akhdam]] people.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first= |last= |authorlink= |coauthors= |title=Yemen: Akhdam people suffer history of discrimination |url=http://www.irinnews.org/report.aspx?reportid=25634|work= |publisher=[[IRIN]] |date=November 1, 2005 |accessdate=2008-01-09 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===United States===
{{POV-check|date=December 2008}}
Rajiv Sethi, economist at Columbia University, writes that Black-white segregation is declining fairly consistently for most metropolitan areas in the US. Despite these pervasive  patterns, many changes for individual areas are small.&lt;ref&gt;''Inequality and Segregation''
R Sethi, R Somanathan - Journal of Political Economy, 2004&lt;/ref&gt; Racial segregation or separation can lead to social, economic and political tensions.&lt;ref name="Keating"&gt;Keating William Dennis ''The Suburban Racial Dilemma: Housing and Neighborhoods'' (1994) Temple University Press. ISBN 1566391474&lt;/ref&gt;  Thirty years after the civil rights era, the United States remains a residentially segregated society in which Blacks, Whites and [[Hispanics in the United States|Hispanics]] inhabit different neighborhoods of vastly different quality.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-srv/national/longterm/meltingpot/melt0222.htm Myth of the Melting Pot: America's Racial and Ethnic Divides]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Massey Douglas S. ''Segregation and stratification: A biosocial perspective'' Du Bois Review: Social Science Research on Race  (2004), 1: 7-25 Cambridge University Press&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Inequality and Segregation'' Rajiv Sethi and Rohini Somanathan ''Journal of Political Economy'', volume 112 (2004), pages 1296–1321&lt;/ref&gt;

Dan Immergluck writes that in 2002 small businesses in black neighborhoods still received fewer loans, even after accounting for businesses density, businesses size, industrial mix, neighborhood income, and the credit quality of local businesses.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title=Redlining Redux |journal=Urban Affairs Review |volume=38 |issue=1|pages=22–41 |year=2002}}&lt;/ref&gt; Gregory D. Squires wrote in 2003 that it is clear that race has long affected and continues to affect the policies and practices of the insurance industry.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title=Racial Profiling, Insurance Style: Insurance Redlining and the Uneven Development of Metropolitan Areas |journal=Journal of Urban Affairs |volume=25 |issue=4 |pages=391–410 |doi=10.1111/1467-9906.t01-1-00168 |year=2003 |author=Squires, Gregory D.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Workers living in American inner-cities have a harder time finding jobs than suburban workers.&lt;ref&gt;Zenou Yves, Boccard Nicolas ''Racial Discrimination and Redlining in Cities'' (1999)&lt;/ref&gt; 

The desire of many whites to avoid having their children attend integrated schools has been a factor in [[white flight]] to the suburbs.&lt;ref&gt; {{cite web |url=http://encarta.msn.com/encyclopedia_761580651_3/Segregation_in_the_United_States.html#s15 |title=VI  De Facto Segregation  |accessdate=2008-01-09 |format= |work=
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Recent studies in San Francisco showed that groups of homeowners of all races tended to self-segregate in order to be with people of the same education level and race.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.yahoo.com/s/livescience/20070910/sc_livescience/homeownersselfsegregatebyraceandeducation;_ylt=AlyjmsI5BA7s..hPZgWKnT0DW7oF ''Homeowners self segregate by race and education'' AP News 2007-09-10]&lt;/ref&gt; By 1990, the legal barriers enforcing segregation had been mostly replaced by decentralized racism, where whites pay more than blacks to live in predominantly white areas.&lt;ref name="vigdor"&gt;..&lt;/ref&gt; Today, many whites are willing, and are able, to pay a premium to live in a predominantly white neighborhood. Equivalent housing in white areas commands a higher rent.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Kiel K.A., Zabel J.E. |title=Housing Price Differentials in U.S. Cities: Household and Neighborhood Racial Effects |journal=Journal of Housing Economics |volume=5 |year=1996 |pages=143 |doi=10.1006/jhec.1996.0008}}&lt;/ref&gt;  By bidding up the price of housing, many white neighborhoods effectively shut out blacks, because blacks are unwilling, or unable, to pay the premium to buy entry into these expensive neighborhoods. Conversely, equivalent housing in black neighborhoods is far more affordable to those who are unable or unwilling to pay a premium to live in white neighborhoods. Through the 1990s, residential segregation remained at its extreme and has been called "hypersegregation" by some sociologists or "American Apartheid"&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Massey D.S., Denton N. A. |title=American Apartheid. |place=Cambridge |publisher=Harvard University Press |year=1993}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In February 2005, the U.S. Supreme Court ruled in ''Johnson v. California'' {{ussc|125|1141|2005}} that the California Department of Corrections' unwritten practice of racially segregating prisoners in its prison reception centers — which California claimed was for inmate safety (gangs in California, as throughout the U.S., usually organize on racial lines)— is to be subject to [[strict scrutiny]], the highest level of constitutional review.{{Citation needed|date=May 2008}}

There are [[List of historically black colleges of the United States|103 historically black colleges]] (HBCU) in the [[United States]] today, including public and private, two-year and four-year institutions, medical schools and community colleges.&lt;ref name="USDEd"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ed.gov/about/inits/list/whhbcu/edlite-list.html|title=List of HBCUs|work=White House Initiative on Historically Black Colleges and Universities|publisher=United States Department of Education|date=2007-08-17|accessdate=2008-02-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 2009 "Stimulus Bill" would include more than $1.3 billion for HBCU campuses.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.reuters.com/article/domesticNews/idUSTRE51F00B20090216 Recession hits black colleges hard]. ''Reuters.'' February 15, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Col-begin}}

{{Col-1-of-3}}
*[[Affirmative Action]]
*[[Apartheid laws]]
*[[Bantustan]]
*[[Caste]]
*[[Eagle feather law]]
*[[Elitism]]
*[[Endogamy]]
*[[English as a Second Language]]
*[[Ethnic autonomous regions]]
*[[Enclave]] 
*[[Forsyth County, Georgia v. The Nationalist Movement]]
{{Col-2-of-3}}
*[[Genocide]]
*[[Ghetto]]
*[[Group Areas Act]]
*[[Housing Segregation]]
*[[Jim Crow laws]]
*[[Judenhut]]
*[[Ku Klux Klan]]
*[[Mortgage Discrimination]]
*[[Multiculturalism]]
*[[Muslim Mosque, Inc.]]
*[[Nation of Islam]]
*[[National Alliance (United States)]]
*[[Nuremberg laws]]
{{Col-3-of-3}}
*[[Pass Law]]
*[[Paris Peace Conference, 1919#Japanese approach|Racial equality proposal]]
*[[Redlining]]
*[[Religious segregation]]
*[[Residential Segregation]]
*[[Second-class citizen]]
*[[Separate but equal]]
*[[Separatism]]
*[[Tejano]] and [[Chicano]]  
*[[Underground Railroad]]
*[[Xenophobia]]
*[[Yellow badge]]

{{Col-end}}

==Notes==
{{reflist|2}}

==References==
*Dobratz, Betty A. and Shanks-Meile, Stephanie L, ''White Power, White Pride: The White Separatist Movement in the United States'', Johns Hopkins University Press, 2001, 384 pages, ISBN 0-8018-6537-9.
*''Rural Face of White Supremacy: Beyond Jim Crow'', by Mark Schultz. University of Illinois Press, 2005, ISBN 0-252-02960-7.

==Further reading==
*{{cite book |title=Color-Blind Justice: Albion Tourgée and the Quest for Racial Equality from the Civil War to Plessy v. Ferguson |last=Elliott |first=Mark |authorlink= |coauthors= |year=2006 |publisher=[[Oxford University Press]] |location=New York |isbn=0195181395 |pages= }}
*{{cite book |title=I dissent: Great Opposing Opinions in Landmark Supreme Court Cases |last=Tushnet |first=Mark |authorlink= |coauthors= |year=2008 |publisher=Beacon Press |location=Boston |isbn=9780807000366 |pages=69&amp;ndash;80 }}
*{{cite book |title=Plessy v. Ferguson: A Brief History with Documents |last=Brook |first=Thomas |authorlink= |coauthors= |year=1997 |publisher=Bedford Books |location=Boston |isbn= |pages= }}
*{{cite book |title=Separate and Unequal: Homer Plessy and the Supreme Court Decision That Legalized Racism |last=Fireside |first=Harvey |authorlink= |coauthors= |year=2004 |publisher=Carroll &amp;amp; Graf |location=New York |isbn=0786712937 |pages= }}
*{{cite book |title=The Plessy Case: A Legal-Historical Interpretation.'' |last=Lofgren |first=Charles A. |authorlink= |coauthors= |year=1987 |publisher=Oxford University Press |location=New York |isbn= |pages= }}
*{{cite book |title=We As Freemen: Plessy v. Ferguson |last=Medley |first=Keith Weldon |authorlink= |coauthors= |year=2003 |publisher=Pelican |location=Gretna, LA |isbn=1589801202 |pages= }} [http://www.bsos.umd.edu/gvpt/lpbr/subpages/reviews/Medley1003.htm Review]
*{{cite journal | last = Chin | first = Gabriel J. | authorlink = | coauthors = | year = 1996 | month = | title = The ''Plessy'' Myth: Justice Harlan and the Chinese Cases | journal = Iowa Law Review | volume = 82 | issue = | pages = 151 | id = | url = http://ssrn.com/abstract=1121505 | accessdate = | quote =}}

==External links==
*[http://www.remembersegregation.org A site dedicated to the life of MLK]
*[http://www.skidmore.edu/~dkarp/Social%20Issues/E/history.html A study of segregation]
*[http://www.ericdigests.org/2003-2/race.html Constitutional Law and Race-Conscious Policies in K-12 Education]
*[http://www.nytimes.com/2009/05/24/magazine/24prom-t.html US racial segregation of proms continue]
{{Racism topics|state=collapsed}}
{{Segregation by type}}
{{Discrimination}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Racial Segregation}}
[[Category:Racial segregation| ]]
[[Category:African American history]]
[[Category:Antisemitism]]
[[Category:Core issues in ethics]]
[[Category:History of racial segregation in the United States]]
[[Category:Political theories]]
[[Category:Racism]]
[[Category:Politics and race]]
[[Category:Urban decay]]

[[ar:العزل العنصري]]
[[da:Raceadskillelse]]
[[de:Rassentrennung]]
[[es:Segregación racial]]
[[fr:Ségrégation raciale]]
[[gl:Segregación racial]]
[[it:Segregazione razziale]]
[[he:הפרדה גזעית]]
[[nl:Rassensegregatie]]
[[no:Raseadskillelse]]
[[pl:Segregacja rasowa]]
[[pt:Segregação racial]]
[[simple:Racial segregation]]
[[fi:Rotuerottelu]]
[[zh:种族隔离]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>