<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20171122173049|811596004" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="8536948" pageid="8536948" ns="0" title="National Organization for Women"><revisions><rev timestamp="2017-11-23T13:52:48Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox organization
| logo = [[File:National Organization for Women logo.png|200px]]
| type = [[501(c)#501(c)(3)|501(c)(3)]], [[501(c)#501(c)(4)|501(c)(4)]]
| key_people = [[Terry O'Neill (feminist)|Terry O'Neill]], President; Bonnie Grabenhoffer, Action Vice-President; [[Chitra Panjabi]], Membership Vice-President;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://now.org/about/officers/ |title=NOW Officers |publisher=National Organization for Women |accessdate=2013-10-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| name = National Organization for Women
| founded_date = {{start date and age|1966|6|30}}
| founder = 49 people, including [[Betty Friedan]] and [[Pauli Murray]]
| location = [[Washington, D.C.]], [[United States|U.S.]]
| focus = [[Women's rights]], [[feminism]], [[Equal Rights Amendment]], [[civil rights]], [[LGBT rights]], [[reproductive rights]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://now.org/issues/ |title=Issues |publisher=National Organization for Women |accessdate=2013-10-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| Non-profit_slogan = "Taking Action for Women's Equality Since 1966"
| homepage = [http://www.now.org/ NOW.org]
}}

The '''National Organization for Women''' ('''NOW''') is an American [[feminist]] organization founded in 1966. The organization consists of 550 chapters in all 50 [[U.S. state]]s and in [[Washington, D.C.]]&lt;ref&gt;"[http://www.now.org/organization/info.html Information about NOW.]" National Organization for Women. Retrieved 2011-01-13.&lt;/ref&gt; The organization is [[left-leaning]].&lt;ref name=“veconomist” &gt;{{cite news|author=E.M.|title=How daughters change the behaviour of influential men|url=https://www.economist.com/blogs/economist-explains/2017/10/economist-explains-4|work=[[The Economist]]|date=6 October 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Background==
The National Organization for Women (NOW) was founded in 1966 by 28 women at the Third National Conference of Commissions on the Status of Women in June (the successor to the [[Presidential Commission on the Status of Women]]), and another 21 women and men who became founders at the October 1966 NOW Organizing Conference, for a total of 49 founders.&lt;ref name="autogenerated3"&gt;{{cite web|author=February 9th, 2014 by Allyson Goldsmith. |url=http://now.org/about/history/honoring-our-founders-pioneers/ |title=Honoring Our Founders and Pioneers &amp;#124; National Organization for Women |publisher=Now.org |date=2014-02-09 |accessdate=2015-05-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; Both conferences were held in Washington, D.C.&lt;ref name="autogenerated3"/&gt; The 28 women who became founders in June were: Ada Allness, Mary Evelyn Benbow, Gene Boyer, [[Shirley Chisholm]], Analoyce Clapp, [[Kathryn F. Clarenbach]], Catherine Conroy, Caroline Davis, [[Mary Eastwood]], Edith Finlayson, [[Betty Friedan]], Dorothy Haener, Anna Roosevelt Halstead, Lorene Harrington, Mary Lou Hill, Esther Johnson, Nancy Knaak, Min Matheson, Helen Moreland, [[Pauli Murray]], Ruth Murray, Inka O’Hanrahan, Pauline A. Parish, Eve Purvis, Edna Schwartz, Mary-jane Ryan Snyder, Gretchen Squires, Betty Talkington and Caroline Ware.&lt;ref name="autogenerated3"/&gt; 

They were inspired by the failure of the [[Equal Employment Opportunity Commission]] to enforce Title VII of the [[Civil Rights Act of 1964]]; at the Third National Conference of State Commissions on the Status of Women they were prohibited from issuing a resolution that recommended the EEOC carry out its legal mandate to end sex discrimination in employment.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.feminist.org/research/chronicles/fc1966.html |title=The Feminist Chronicles, 1953–1993 – 1966 – Feminist Majority Foundation |publisher=Feminist.org |date= |accessdate=2015-05-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="makers1"&gt;{{cite web|author=MAKERS Team |url= http://www.makers.com/blog/nows-47th-anniversary-celebrating-its-founders-and-early-members |title=NOW's 47th Anniversary: Celebrating Its Founders and Early Members |publisher=MAKERS |date=2013-06-30 |accessdate=2015-05-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; They thus gathered in [[Betty Friedan]]’s hotel room to form a new organization.&lt;ref name="makers1"/&gt; On a paper napkin Friedan scribbled the acronym "NOW".&lt;ref name="makers1"/&gt; The 21 people who became founders in October were: Caruthers Berger, Colleen Boland, Inez Casiano, [[Carl Degler]], Elizabeth Drews, [[Mary Esther Gaulden Jagger|Mary Esther Gaulden]] (later Jagger), [[Muriel Fox]], Ruth Gober, Richard Graham, [[Anna Arnold Hedgeman]], Lucille Kapplinger (later Hazell), [[Bessie Margolin]], Margorie Palmer, [[Sonia Pressman Fuentes|Sonia Pressman]] (later Fuentes), [[Sister Mary Joel Read]], Amy Robinson, Charlotte Roe, [[Alice Rossi]], Claire R. Salmond, Morag Simchak and Clara Wells.&lt;ref name="autogenerated3"/&gt;

The founders were frustrated with the way in which the federal government was not enforcing the new anti-discrimination laws. Even after measures like the [[Equal Employment Opportunity Commission|Equal Employment Opportunity Commission (EEOC)]] and Title VII of the [[Civil Rights Act of 1964]], employers were still discriminating against women in terms of hiring women and unequal pay with men.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Feminism in Our Time: The Essential Writings, World War II to the Present|last = Schneir|first = Miriam|publisher = Vintage Books|year = 1994|isbn = |location = |pages = 95–102}}&lt;/ref&gt; Women’s rights advocates saw that these legal changes were not being enforced and worried that without a feminist pressure group, a type of “[[NAACP]] for women,”&lt;ref name="Schneir 1994 95"&gt;{{Cite book|title = Feminism in Our Time: The Essential Writings, World War II to the Present|last = Schneir|first = Miriam|publisher = Vintage Books|year = 1994|isbn = |location = |page = 95}}&lt;/ref&gt; women would not be able to combat discrimination. NOW was created in order to mobilize women, give women’s rights advocates the power to put pressure on employers and the government, and to promote full equality of the sexes. It hoped to increase the number of women attending colleges and graduate schools, employed in professional jobs instead of domestic or secretarial work, and appointed to federal offices.&lt;ref name="Schneir 1994 98"&gt;{{Cite book|title = Feminism in Our Time: The Essential Writings, World War II to the Present|last = Schneir|first = Miriam|publisher = Vintage Books|year = 1994|isbn = |location = |page = 98}}&lt;/ref&gt; NOW's Statement of Purpose,&lt;ref name="msu.edu"&gt;http://coursesa.matrix.msu.edu/~hst306/documents/nowstate.html&lt;/ref&gt; which was adopted at its organizing conference in Washington, D.C., on October 29, 1966, declares among other things that "the time has come to confront, with concrete action, the conditions that now prevent women from enjoying the equality of opportunity and freedom of choice which is their right, as individual Americans, and as human beings."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=National Organization for Women (NOW)|url=http://wax.lib.harvard.edu/collections/seed.do?seed=1498&amp;primColl=261&amp;lang=eng|publisher=Harvard University Library Web Archive Collection Service|accessdate=29 October 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; NOW was also one of the first women’s organizations to include the concerns of black women in their efforts.&lt;ref name="Schneir 1994 98"/&gt;

[[File:NOW women.jpg|thumb|left|&lt;!-- Billington, (unknown woman) --&gt; NOW founder and president [[Betty Friedan]] with, lobbyist [[Barbara Ireton]] (1932-1998) and feminist attorney [[Marguerite Rawalt]]]]
[[Betty Friedan]] and [[Pauli Murray]] wrote NOW's Statement of Purpose&lt;ref name="msu.edu"/&gt; in 1966; the original was scribbled on a napkin by Friedan.&lt;ref name="autogenerated1"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.now.org/history/purpos66.html |title=The National Organization for Women's 1966 Statement of Purpose |publisher=National Organization for Women |accessdate=2013-10-29 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110902232426/http://www.now.org/history/purpos66.html |archivedate=2011-09-02 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt; Also in 1966, [[Marguerite Rawalt]] became a member of NOW, and acted as their first legal counsel.&lt;ref name="hbio"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://oasis.lib.harvard.edu/oasis/deliver/~sch00250|title=Rawalt, Marguerite – Biography|year=2000|publisher=President and Fellows of Harvard College|accessdate=30 March 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; NOW's first Legal Committee consisted of [[Catherine East]], [[Mary Eastwood]], [[Phineas Indritz]], and Caruthers Berger; it was the first to sue on behalf of airline flight attendants claiming sex discrimination.&lt;ref name="now.org"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://now.org/about/history/honoring-our-founders-pioneers/|title=Honoring Our Founders and Pioneers – National Organization for Women|work=now.org|accessdate=11 May 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There were many influences contributing to the rise of NOW. Such influences included the President's Commission on the Status of Women, Betty Friedan's book ''[[The Feminine Mystique]]'', and passage and lack of enforcement of the [[Civil Right Act of 1964]] (prohibiting sexual discrimination).&lt;ref name="Lewis"&gt;{{cite web|last=Lewis|first=Jone Johnson|title=National Organization for Women – NOW|url=http://womenshistory.about.com/od/feminism/p/now.htm|publisher=About.com|accessdate=29 October 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The President's Commission on the Status of Women was established in 1961 by [[John F. Kennedy]], in hopes of providing a solution to female discrimination in education, work force, and Social Security. Kennedy appointed [[Eleanor Roosevelt]] as the head of the organization. The goal of action was to compromise those wanting to advance women's rights in the workforce (such as advocates of the [[Equal Rights Amendment]]) and those advocating women's domestic importance/role needing to be preserved (such as organized labor groups). The commission was in a way to settle the tension between opposing sides.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Lewis|first=Jone Johnson|title=President's Commission on the Status of Women|url=http://womenshistory.about.com/od/laws/a/status_women.htm|publisher=About.com|accessdate=29 October 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Betty Friedan wrote ''[[The Feminine Mystique]]'' in response to her own experiences. She was a feminist long before her book, by educating herself and deviating from the domestic female paradigm. The book's purpose was to fuel movement to a women's role outside of domestic environment. Acknowledging some satisfaction from raising children, cooking, rearranging house decor was not enough to suffice the deeper desire for women to achieve an education.&lt;ref name="Friedan interview"&gt;{{cite web|last=Wattenberg|first=Ben|title=Betty Friedan Interview|url=https://www.pbs.org/fmc/interviews/friedan.htm|work=The First Measured Century|publisher=PBS|accessdate=29 October 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; In an interview, Friedan specifically notes, "There was no activism in that cause when I wrote ''[[The Feminine Mystique|Feminine Mystique]]''. But I realized that it was not enough just to write a book. There had to be social change. And I remember somewhere in that period coming off an airplane [and] some guy was carrying a sign... It said, "The first step in revolution is consciousness." Well, I did the consciousness with [[The Feminine Mystique]]. But then there had to be organization and there had to be a movement. And I helped organize NOW, the National Organization for Women and the [[National Women's Political Caucus]] and [[NARAL]], the abortion rights [organization] in the next few years.”&lt;ref name="Friedan interview"/&gt;

In 1968 NOW issued a Bill of Rights,&lt;ref&gt;http://coursesa.matrix.msu.edu/~hst306/documents/nowrights.html&lt;/ref&gt; which they had adopted at their 1967 national conference, advocating the passage of the [[Equal Rights Amendment]], enforcement of the prohibitions against sex discrimination in employment under [[Title VII]] of the Civil Rights Act of 1964, [[maternity leave]] rights in employment and in Social Security benefits, tax deduction for home and child care expenses for working parents, child day care centers, equal and non-[[Single-sex education|gender-segregated education]], equal job training opportunities and allowances for women in poverty, and the right of women to control their reproductive lives.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://coursesa.matrix.msu.edu/~hst306/documents/nowrights.html |title=N.O.W. Bill of Rights, 1968 |publisher=National Organization for Women |accessdate=2013-10-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; The NOW bill of rights was included in the 1970 anthology ''[[Sisterhood is Powerful: An Anthology of Writings From The Women's Liberation Movement]]'', edited by [[Robin Morgan]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.worldcat.org/title/sisterhood-is-powerful-an-anthology-of-writings-from-the-womens-liberation-movement/oclc/96157 |title=Sisterhood is powerful : an anthology of writings from the women's liberation movement (Book, 1970) |publisher=[WorldCat.org] |date= |accessdate=2015-05-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1969 [[Ivy Bottini]], who was openly lesbian, designed the logo for NOW, which is still in use today.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Gendered Lives: Communication, Gender and Culture |last=Wood |first=Julia T. |year=2005 |edition=6th |publisher=Wadsworth/Thompson Learning |location=Belmont, California |isbn=0-534-63615-2 |pages=69–70}}&lt;/ref&gt; The first time lesbian concerns were introduced into NOW also occurred in 1969, when Bottini, who was then president of the New York chapter of NOW, held a public forum titled "Is Lesbianism a Feminist Issue?".&lt;ref name="bare_url_d"&gt;[[Barbara Love|Love, Barbara J.]] [https://books.google.com/books?id=kpNarH7t9CkC&amp;pg=PA51&amp;dq=1968+lesbian+ivy+bottini&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=4P7QT4ToGcXZ0QHIpdDqDw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=book-thumbnail&amp;resnum=7&amp;ved=0CFoQ6wEwBg#v=onepage&amp;q=1968%20lesbian%20ivy%20bottini&amp;f=false Feminists Who Changed America, 1963–1975]&lt;/ref&gt; However, NOW president [[Betty Friedan]] was against lesbian participation in the movement. In 1969 she referred to growing lesbian visibility as a "lavender menace" and fired openly lesbian newsletter editor [[Rita Mae Brown]], and in 1970 she engineered the expulsion of lesbians, including [[Ivy Bottini]], from NOW's New York chapter.&lt;ref&gt;Bonnie Zimmerman [https://books.google.com/books?id=0EUoCrFolGcC&amp;pg=PA134 Lesbian histories and cultures: an encyclopedia], Garland Pub., 2000 {{ISBN|0815319207}} p. 134&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Vicki Lynn Eaklor [https://books.google.com/books?id=qJZdHuZ0aM0C&amp;pg=PA145 Queer America: a GLBT history of the 20th century], ABC-CLIO, 2008 {{ISBN|0313337497}} p. 145&lt;/ref&gt; In reaction, at the 1970 Congress to Unite Women, on the first evening when all four hundred feminists were assembled in the auditorium, twenty women wearing T-shirts that read "Lavender Menace" came to the front of the room and faced the audience.&lt;ref name="google2"&gt;Flora Davis [https://books.google.com/books?id=ioM-8naFn60C&amp;pg=PA264 Moving the mountain: the women's movement in America since 1960], University of Illinois Press, 1999 {{ISBN|0-252-06782-7}} p. 264&lt;/ref&gt; One of the women then read their group's paper "[[The Woman-Identified Woman]]", which was the first major lesbian feminist statement.&lt;ref name="google2"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Cheshire Calhoun [https://books.google.com/books?id=7V73W75tGssC&amp;pg=PA27 Feminism, the Family, and the Politics of the Closet: Lesbian and Gay Displacement], Oxford University Press, 2003 {{ISBN|0-19-925766-3}} p. 27&lt;/ref&gt; The group, who later named themselves "Radicalesbians", were among the first to challenge the heterosexism of heterosexual feminists and to describe lesbian experience in positive terms.&lt;ref&gt;Carolyn Zerbe Enns [https://books.google.com/books?id=bIe7ZtOubc8C&amp;pg=PA105 Feminist theories and feminist psychotherapies: origins, themes, and diversity], Routledge, 2004 {{ISBN|078901808X}} p. 105&lt;/ref&gt; In 1971 NOW passed a resolution declaring “that a woman’s right to her own person includes the right to define and express her own sexuality and to choose her own lifestyle," as well as a conference resolution stating that forcing lesbian mothers to stay in marriages or to live a secret existence in an effort to keep their children was unjust.&lt;ref name="autogenerated2"&gt;[http://now.org/resource/now-leading-the-fight/ Leading the Fight | National Organization for Women]. NOW. Retrieved on 2014-07-25.&lt;/ref&gt; That year NOW also committed to offering legal and moral support in a test case involving child custody rights of lesbian mothers.&lt;ref name="autogenerated2"/&gt; In 1973 the NOW Task Force on Sexuality and Lesbianism was established.&lt;ref name="autogenerated2"/&gt;

[[Del Martin]] was the first open lesbian elected to NOW, and [[Del Martin and Phyllis Lyon]] were the first lesbian couple to join NOW.&lt;ref name="ABOUTMARTIN"&gt;{{cite news |last=Belge |first=Kathy |url= http://lesbianlife.about.com/cs/herstory/p/DelMartin.htm |title=Del Martin |publisher=About |date= |accessdate=2007-02-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Advocacy of the [[Equal Rights Amendment]] was also an important issue to NOW. The amendment had three primary objectives, which were:

“Section 1. Equality of Rights under the law shall not be denied or abridged by the United States or any state on account of sex.
Section 2. The Congress shall have the power to enforce, by appropriate legislation, the provisions of this article.
Section 3. This amendment shall take effect two years after the date of ratification.”&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Equal Rights Amendment|url=http://www.now.org/issues/economic/eratext.html|publisher=National Organization for Women|accessdate=29 October 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Efforts were proven successful when Congress passed the amendment in 1972. However, simply passing the amendment in the two houses of Congress did not mean the work was finished. NOW had to direct the efforts of getting the amendment ratified in at least three-fourths of the states (38 out of the 50 states).&lt;ref name="about1"&gt;{{cite web|last=Napikoski|first=Linda|title=Equal Rights Amendment: Constitutional Equality and Justice for All?|url=http://womenshistory.about.com/od/equalrightsamendment/a/equal_rights_amendment_overview.htm|accessdate=29 October 2013|publisher=About.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In response to opposing states denying the ratification of the amendment, NOW encouraged members to participate in marches and economic boycotts. “Dozens of organizations supported the ERA and the boycott, including the [[League of Women Voters]], the [[YWCA]] of the U.S., the Unitarian Universalist Association, the [[United Auto Workers]] (UAW), the [[National Education Association]] (NEA), and the [[Democratic National Committee]] (DNC).”&lt;ref name="about1"/&gt;

As strong as the support was, it was to no avail to the opposition from various groups. These groups included select religious collectives, business/ insurance interests, and most visibly was the STOP-ERA campaign led by antifeminist [[Phyllis Schlafly]]. Schlafly argued on the premise of creating equality in work force or anywhere else would hinder the laws that are instilled for the mere protection of these women. The safety of women was a higher priority than ensuring there is equality in financial and social scenarios. Interestingly enough, the predicament over the Equal Rights Amendment was not a fight between men and women who abhor men, but rather two groups of women advocating different perspectives on the nature of their lives. The rivalry was sparked in speeches, such as that of Schlafly who began her dialogue by thanking her husband for allowing her to participate in such an activity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=57c. The Equal Rights Amendment |url=http://www.ushistory.org/us/57c.asp |publisher=Ushistory.org |accessdate=29 October 2013 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130910050803/http://www.ushistory.org/us/57c.asp |archivedate=10 September 2013 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Even though efforts did not prove to be enough to have the amendment ratified, the organization remains active in lobbying legislatures and media outlets on feminist issues.

In 1972 NOW chose the [[Schlesinger Library]] as the archives for its records.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.radcliffe.harvard.edu/schlesinger-library/collection/records-national-organization-women |title=Records of the National Organization for Women &amp;#124; Radcliffe Institute for Advanced Study at Harvard University |publisher=Radcliffe.harvard.edu |date= |accessdate=2015-05-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Abortion being an individual woman's choice has come into the forefront since the Supreme Court case of ''[[Roe v. Wade]]'' in 1973. The decision of the court was that it ultimately was the woman's choice in reproduction. However, according to the National Organization for Women, decisions following the 1973 landmark case had substantially limited this right, which culminated their response to encourage the [[Freedom of Choice Act]]. The controversy over the landmark case ruling was initiated in the two cases, ''[[Gonzales v. Planned Parenthood]]'' and ''[[Gonzales v. Carhart]]''. These two cases consequently banned abortion methods after 12 weeks of pregnancy.&lt;ref name="prochoiceamerica1"&gt;{{cite web|title=Freedom of Choice Acts|url=http://www.prochoiceamerica.org/what-is-choice/fast-facts/foca.html|publisher=NARAL Pro-Choice America|accessdate=29 October 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''Gonzalez v. Planned Parenthood'' and ''Gonzalez v. Carhart'' both dealt with the question of whether the 2003 [[Partial-Birth Abortion Ban Act]] was unconstitutional by violating the [[Due Process Clause]] of the Fifth Amendment expressed in the ''Roe v. Wade'' case. This act ultimately meant that the “concept of partial-birth abortion as defined in the Act as any abortion in which the death of the fetus occurs when "the entire fetal head [...] or [...] any part of the fetal trunk past the navel is outside the body of the mother” is banned. The Supreme Court ultimately decided 5–4 that it was not unconstitutional and did not hinder a woman's right to an abortion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Gonzales v. Planned Parenthood|url=https://www.oyez.org/cases/2000-2009/2006/2006_05_1382|publisher=The Oyez Project|accessdate=29 October 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

National Organization for Women claimed it was a disregard to a basic principle stemming from ''Roe v. Wade'', which was to only have legislative restriction on abortion be justified with the intention of protecting women's health. Hence, the support for the Freedom of Choice Act (FOCA) which primary purpose was to safeguard a woman's access to abortions even if the ''Roe v. Wade'' ruling is further disregarded. As of 2013, there are seven states that have made the Freedom of Choice Act state law. FOCA will consequently supersede any other law prohibiting abortion in those seven states. They are: California, Connecticut, Hawaii, Maryland, Nevada, Wisconsin, Maine, and Washington. In addition, Maryland, Nevada, and Washington were the only three states to adhere via ballot initiative.&lt;ref name="prochoiceamerica1"/&gt;

Succeeding in the enactment of FOCA would ultimately mean fulfilment of three goals for the National Organization for Women. First, asserting a woman's reproductive right. Second, disseminate information to the public audience about threats posed in the two court cases mentioned above. Third, through the dissemination of information to the public, this in return would mobilize efforts to support female rights in multiple areas that will be presented in the future.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Freedom of Choice Act would Guarantee Roe Protections in U.S. Statutes|url=http://www.now.org/issues/abortion/070430foca.html|publisher=National Organization for Women|date=April 30, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Goals==
[[Betty Friedan]] and [[Pauli Murray]] wrote the organization's Statement of Purpose&lt;ref name="msu.edu"/&gt; in 1966. The statement described the purpose of NOW as "To take action to bring women into full participation in the mainstream of American society now, exercising all privileges and responsibilities thereof in truly equal partnership with men." The six core issues that NOW addresses are abortion and reproductive health services access, violence against women, constitutional equality, promoting diversity/ending racism, lesbian rights, and economic justice, with these issues having various sub-issues. The organization goes about creating these changes through laborious lobbying, rallies, marches, and conferences. NOW focuses on a variety of issues deploying multiple strategies, causing it to be an organization in which a comprehensive goal is envisaged and performed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Key Issues |url=http://www.now.org/issues/ |publisher=National Organization for Women |accessdate=2009-09-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Priorities mentioned above were pursued to ultimately secure constitutional amendments guaranteeing these rights. Even though discrimination on the basis of sex was illegal, the federal government was not taking an active role in enforcing the constitutional amendments and the new policies.&lt;ref name="Schneir 1994 95"/&gt; NOW sought to apply pressure to employers, local governments, and the federal government to uphold anti-discrimination policies. Through litigation, political pressure, and physical marches, NOW members held an authoritative stance leading to recognition in court cases, such as ''[[National Organization for Women v. Scheidler|NOW v. Scheidler]]'' and ''Weeks v. Southern Bell''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Tripp|first=Jennifer|title=National Organization for Women|url=http://learningtogive.org/papers/paper200.html|accessdate=29 October 2013|publisher=Grand Valley State University|work=Learning To Give}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''NOW v. Scheidler'' revolved around the issue of racketeering to gain support for anti-abortion groups. NOW was suing the groups for utilization of violence and the threat of violence for garnering support. The violence varied from physical barriers into entrances of abortion clinic to arson and bombings of those clinics. The plaintiff accused the Pro-Life Action Network (PLAN) for unethical seizing the right of women to make decisions about their own bodies, and that this right needed to be defended. The case was a success in terms of the class action suit “brought against terrorists by those they had terrorized”.&lt;ref&gt;[http://heinonline.org/HOL/LuceneSearch?terms=%2262%20Alb.%20L.%20Rev.%20%20967%22&amp;collection=journals&amp;searchtype=advanced&amp;submit=Go&amp;sections=any&amp;sections=external&amp;other_cols=yes&amp;cited_by=true&amp;sortby=cited_by 62 Alb. L. Rev. 967 (1998–1999) NOW v. Scheidler: Protecting Women's Access to Reproductive Health Services]; Clayton, Fay; Love, Sara N.&lt;/ref&gt;

However the case was dismissed based on the mere definition of racketeering because racketeering must have an economic inclination, and there was no evidence to prove PLAN had this financial intention. This does not mean it was not a significant case. It brought light and recognition to National Organization for Women and its goals. If anything, it galvanized the organization to strengthen its tactics.&lt;ref&gt;Oyez Project: [http://learningtogive.org/papers/paper200.html NATIONAL ORGANIZATION FOR WOMEN (NOW) v. SCHEIDLER]&lt;/ref&gt;

''Weeks v. Southern Bell'' had the same effect, but this is an example where those galvanized efforts proved beneficial. This concerned discriminatory practices against women in the workplace. [[Lorena Weeks]], employee of Southern Bell, claimed she was being discriminated against via exclusion to higher paying positions within the company. Sylvia Roberts acted as her attorney, supporting Week's grievances with the accusation of the company's violation of Title VII of the Civil Rights Act (1964). Title VII is enabled to "protect individuals against employment discrimination on the bases of race and color, as well as national origin, sex, and religion". With this premise, Weeks, with the aid of Sylvia Roberts, succeeded in 1969 after making an appeal. The trial not only served as the triumph of National Organization of Women, but brought to life legislation made to the intentions of organizations, such as NOW.&lt;ref&gt;[http://russelldoc.galib.uga.edu/russell/view?docId=ead/RBRL263LWSB-ead.xml;query=;brand=default Lorena Weeks Files related to Weeks v. Southern Bell], Richard B. Russell Library for Political Research and Studies, University of Georgia Libraries, Athens, Georgia, 30602-1641.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Presidents==
The following women have led the National Organization for Women:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Celebrating Our Presidents|url=http://www.now.org/history/past_presidents.html|publisher=National Organization for Women|accessdate=29 October 2013|deadurl=yes|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100121153357/http://www.now.org/history/past_presidents.html|archivedate=21 January 2010|df=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
# [[Betty Friedan]] (1966–1970)
# [[Aileen Hernandez]] (1970–1971)
# [[Wilma Scott Heide]] (1971–1974)
# [[Karen DeCrow]] (1974–1977)
# [[Eleanor Smeal]] (1977–1982)
# [[Judy Goldsmith]] (1982–1985)
# [[Eleanor Smeal]] (1985–1987)
# [[Molly Yard]] (1987–1991)
# [[Patricia Ireland]] (1991–2001)
# [[Kim Gandy]] (2001–2009)
# [[Terry O'Neill (feminist)|Terry O'Neil]] (2009–2017)
# [[Toni VanPelt]] (2017- )

==Criticism==
NOW has been criticized by various [[pro-life]], [[Conservatism in the United States|conservative]], and [[fathers' rights movement|fathers' rights]] groups.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://news.google.com/newspapers?id=pncqAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=BVkEAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=4576,2703172|title=NOW Seeking Abortion Summit|last=Cimons|first=Marlene|date=8 February 1979|work=The Pittsburgh Press|accessdate=28 October 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://news.google.com/newspapers?id=23wkAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=idsFAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=1850,6833582&amp;dq=national-organization-for-women+father%27s+rights&amp;hl=en|title=Women wary of man's bid to crash panel|last=Susman|first=Carolyn|date=30 July 1986|work=The Palm Beach Post|accessdate=28 October 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://news.google.com/newspapers?id=e6VOAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=OvsDAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=3552,2671261&amp;dq=national-organization-for-women+conservatives&amp;hl=en|title=Conservatives urge Reagan to deny 'leftists' grants|date=8 April 1982|work=Lakeland Ledger|accessdate=28 October 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; During the 1990s, NOW was criticized{{Who|date=September 2009}} for having a double standard when it refused to support [[Paula Jones]] in her sexual harassment suit against former [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democratic]] President [[Bill Clinton]], while calling for the resignation of [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican]] politician ([[Bob Packwood]]), who was accused of similar assault by 10 women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://articles.latimes.com/1998/apr/23/news/mn-42260|title=NOW Won't Back Paula Jones, Cites Her Backers|last=Jackson|first=Robert|date=23 April 1998|work=[[Los Angeles Times]]|accessdate=28 October 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Jones suit was later dismissed by U.S. District Judge [[Susan Webber Wright]], ruling that Mrs. Jones' allegations, even if true, wouldn't qualify as a case of sexual harassment. Jones appealed but later dropped her suit after reaching a settlement out of court for $850,000.  Judge Webber Wright later held President Clinton in contempt of court for giving "intentionally false" testimony about his relationship with Monica S. Lewinsky in the Paula Jones lawsuit, marking the first time that a sitting president has been sanctioned for disobeying a court order&lt;ref&gt;{{cite new|url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/1999/jan/13/clinton.usa1|title=Clinton pays Paula Jones $850,000|date=13 January 1999|work=The Guardian}}&lt;/ref&gt;.

NOW has also been criticized by feminists who claim it focuses on liberal agenda rather than women's rights. NOW has been criticized for not supporting pro-life feminists,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://yaledailynews.com/blog/2008/11/10/feminists-can-be-pro-life/|title=Feminists can be pro-life|last=Seager|first=Ilana|date=10 November 2008|publisher=Yale Daily News|accessdate=28 October 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ncregister.com/daily-news/meet-the-bold-new-feminists/|title=Meet the Bold ‘New Feminists'|last=Browder|first=Sue Ellen|date=1 August 2013|publisher=National Catholic Register|accessdate=28 October 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; as well as other liberal issues, and supporting the Iraq War.{{Citation needed|date=November 2009}} Some members, such as LA NOW chapter president [[Tammy Bruce]] left NOW, saying they oppose putting liberal and partisan policy positions above equality for all women. Tammy Bruce has attacked NOW for not doing enough to advocate for international women's rights, but instead attacking the [[George W. Bush]] [[White House]] for their conservative positions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.feministing.com/archives/009415.html |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2009-11-06 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://archive.is/20080828222719/http://www.feministing.com/archives/009415.html |archivedate=2008-08-28 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt; Accusations of putting politics above feminism began in 1982, the year the [[Equal Rights Amendment|ERA]] was defeated, when NOW, under President [[Judy Goldsmith]], fiercely opposed [[Reaganomics]], and endorsed [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican]] feminist Congresswoman [[Millicent Fenwick]]'s [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democratic]] [[Frank Lautenberg|opponent]] in a [[New Jersey]] Senate race due to her support of [[Ronald Reagan]]'s economic agenda.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://archives.nbclearn.com/portal/site/k-12/flatview?cuecard=2732|title=Views of NOW – The National Organization for Women|date=11 October 1982|publisher=NBC Today Show|accessdate=28 October 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/1984/06/28/us/the-rising-force-of-women-s-pacs.html|title=THE RISING FORCE OF WOMEN'S PACS|last=Salmans|first=Sandra|date=28 June 1984|work=The New York Times|page=22|accessdate=28 October 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://articles.chicagotribune.com/1985-11-29/news/8503220695_1_aurelia-pucinski-state-ticket-republican-women|title=Can`t The Women Play This Game?|last=Neal|first=Steve|date=29 November 1985|work=[[Chicago Tribune]]|accessdate=28 October 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Additionally, Deborah Watkins, who was once the President of the Dallas Chapter of NOW, left NOW in 2003 to found, in the same year, the Dallas-Fort Worth Chapter of the [[National Coalition for Men]], stating she grew tired of what she considered "hypocrisy" and "male bashing" at NOW.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ncfm.org/?page_id=138 History of the National Coalition for Men] "Both the Los Angeles, California and Dallas/Ft. Worth, Texas chapters were approved in 2003. Dallas/Ft. Worth was founded by Deborah Watkins, the former President of the Dallas chapter of the National Organization of Women who had grown tired of what she considered hypocrisy and male bashing by NOW."&lt;/ref&gt;

Moreover, the "National Organization for Women (NOW) has caused controversy by putting [[Little Sisters of the Poor]] on their “Dirty 100” list", a religious order that according to Fox News' [[Megyn Kelly]], "operate[s] homes in 31 countries where they provide care for over 13,000 needy, elderly persons, many of whom are dying".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://foxnewsinsider.com/2014/07/08/little-sisters-poor-named-now%E2%80%99s-%E2%80%98dirty-100%E2%80%99-list|title=Little Sisters of the Poor Named on NOW’s ‘Dirty 100’ List?!|date=8 July 2014|publisher=[[Fox News]]|accessdate=9 July 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 10 and 11 January 2016, the [[Daily Caller]] and the [[Washington Examiner]] published stories critical of NOW's continuing support of a [[A Rape on Campus|discredited University of Virginia rape accusation]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://dailycaller.com/2016/01/10/national-organization-for-women-defends-rolling-stone-gang-rape-fabricator/|title=National Organization For Women Defends Rolling Stone Gang Rape Fabricator|author=Ross, Chuck}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.washingtonexaminer.com/feminist-organization-still-defending-rolling-stone-rape-hoaxer/article/2580101|title= Feminist organization still defending Rolling Stone rape hoaxer|author=Schow, Ashe}}&lt;/ref&gt; The accusation had been published in [[Rolling Stone]], which later retracted the story.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Uberti |first=David |date=22 December 2014 |title=The worst journalism of 2014 |url=http://www.cjr.org/darts_and_laurels/the_worst_journalism_of_2014.php |newspaper=[[Columbia Journalism Review]] |location= |accessdate=23 December 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Although the accuser's story changed repeatedly and a police investigation found "no evidence" of rape, NOW referred to the accuser as a "survivor" of sexual assault.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://now.org/media-center/press-release/an-open-letter-to-uva-president-teresa-a-sullivan/|title=An open letter to UVA President Teresa Sullivan|author=O’Neill, Terry}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Feminism in the United States]]
* [[List of Presidents of the National Organization for Women]]
* [[National Organization for Women (NOW) Woman of Courage Award Winners|List of Woman of Courage Award Winners]]

==References==
{{reflist|33em}}

===Documentary===
The National Organization for Women and some of its founders [[Muriel Fox]], [[Jacqui Ceballos]] and [[Rita Mae Brown]] are part of the documentary [[She's Beautiful When She's Angry]], about the founders of the modern women's movement (from 1966 to 1971).

==External links==
{{commonscat|National Organization for Women (NOW)}}
* {{official|http://www.now.org/ }}
* [http://nrs.harvard.edu/urn-3:RAD.SCHL:sch00300 Records, 1959–2002 (inclusive), 1966–1998 (bulk).] [http://radcliffe.harvard.edu/schlesinger-library Schlesinger Library], Radcliffe Institute, Harvard University.
* [http://nrs.harvard.edu/urn-3:RAD.SCHL:sch01385 Additional Records of the National Organization for Women, 1970–2011.] [http://www.radcliffe.edu/schles Schlesinger Library], Radcliffe Institute, Harvard University.
* [http://www.lib.utexas.edu/taro/utsa/00173/utsa-00173.html Inventory of the Texas Chapter of the National Organization for Women Records], [[University of Texas at San Antonio Libraries (UTSA Libraries)]] Special Collections.
* [http://www.lib.utexas.edu/taro/utsa/00034/utsa-00034.html A Guide to the San Antonio Chapter of the National Organization for Women Records], [[University of Texas at San Antonio Libraries (UTSA Libraries)]] Special Collections.
* [http://asteria.fivecolleges.edu/findaids/sophiasmith/mnsss370_main.html National Organization for Women. Springfield (Mass.) Chapter], at Smith College.
* [http://digital.lib.washington.edu/findingaids/view?docId=LatourellElaine4587.xml Elaine Latourell Papers.] 1970–1977. 8.42 cubic feet (9 boxes). At the [http://lib.washington.edu/specialcollections/laws Labor Archives of Washington, University of Washington Libraries Special Collections.] Contains records from Latourell's service as a leader of the National Organization for Women between 1970 and 1980.

{{Women's lobbies, alliances and national committees}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:National Organization For Women}}
[[Category:National Organization for Women| ]]
[[Category:1966 establishments in Washington, D.C.]]
[[Category:Feminist organizations in the United States]]
[[Category:Liberal feminism]]
[[Category:Organizations based in Washington, D.C.]]
[[Category:Organizations established in 1966]]
[[Category:Pro-choice organizations in the United States]]
[[Category:Second-wave feminism]]
[[Category:Women's political advocacy groups in the United States]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>