<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20040803012041|4973942" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="8536948" pageid="8536948" ns="0" title="National Organization for Women"><revisions><rev timestamp="2004-08-03T01:24:08Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''National Organization for Women''' (NOW) is an American [[feminist]] group founded on [[June 30]], [[1966]] in Washington, D.C. by women attending the Third National Conference of the Commission on the Status of Women. Among the 28 founders were [[Betty Friedan]], author of ''[[The Feminine Mystique]]'' (1963), who became NOW's first president, and Rev. [[Pauli Murray]], the first African-American woman Episcopal priest. [[Molly Yard]] was president from [[1987]] to [[1991]]. During the [[1970s]] NOW promoted the [[Equal Rights Amendment]] to the [[U.S. Constitution]].

In [[Cincinnati, Ohio]], at its [[1989]] convention on [[July 23]], NOW delegates questioned the sanctity of the [[two-party system]] and broached the idea of forming a [[third party]]. The convention issued a "[[Declaration of Women's Political Independence]]." An exploratory commission was formed for the possibilities of expanding the [[United States Bill of Rights]] to include freedom from sexual discrimination, the right to a decent standard of living, the right to clean air, clean water and environmental protections, the right to be free from violence. The commission was chaired by former NOW president [[Eleanor Smeal]]. A month earlier, NOW launched a [[Commission for Responsive Democracy]], which included Smeal, [[John Bayard Anderson|John Anderson]], [[Toney Anaya]], [[Barry Commoner]] and [[Dee Barry]].

The group's original purpose (which Friedman scribbled on a napkin) remains "''to take action to bring women into full participation in the mainstream of American society now, exercising all privileges and responsibilities thereof in truly equal partnership with men''". The organization remains active in lobbying legislatures and media outlets on women's issues.  It also takes action to bring [[homosexual]]s "into full participation in the mainstream of American society."  This organization is also controversial in the [[masculism|male perspective]].

It claims 500,000 contributing members and 550 chapters in all 50 U.S. states and the District of Columbia.

==Opposing perspectives==

The National Organization for Women has been subject to criticism from many who claim to represent the [[masculism|male perspective]].  Many masculists accused the organization of promoting high rates of [[divorce]], alienation of the genders, disintegrating communities, [[female chauvinism]], and fatherless children.

==External links==
* [http://www.now.org/ National Organization for Women]


{{msg:stub}}
[[Category:Political advocacy groups in the U.S.]][[Category:U.S. history of women's rights]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>