<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20071108224703|170196782" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="8536948" pageid="8536948" ns="0" title="National Organization for Women"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-11-08T22:47:57Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[Image:logo-sign2.gif|right|250px]]
The '''National Organization for Women''' (NOW) is an [[United States|American]] [[feminist]] group, founded in [[1966]], claiming a membership of 500,000 people and 550 chapters in all 50 U.S. states and the [[Washington, D.C.|District of Columbia]].

==Background==
NOW was founded on [[June 30]], [[1966]] in [[Washington, D.C.]], by 28 women and men attending the Third National Conference of the Commission on the Status of Women, the successor to the [[Presidential Commission on the Status of Women]].  It had been three years since the Commission reported findings of women being discriminated against. However, the 1966 Conference delegates were prohibited by the administration's rules for the conference from even passing resolutions recommending that the Equal Employment Opportunity Commission (EEOC) enforce its legal mandate to end sex discrimination.

The founders included [[Betty Friedan]], the author of ''[[The Feminine Mystique]]'' (1963) and Rev. [[Pauli Murray]], the first African-American woman Episcopal priest. Betty Friedan became the organization's first president. 

During the [[1970s]] NOW promoted the [[Equal Rights Amendment]] to the [[U.S. Constitution]]. The organization's membership is not limited to women, and has included many men who support its goals. &lt;ref&gt;https://www.now.org/member.html&lt;/ref&gt;

The organization remains active in lobbying legislatures and media outlets on women's issues.

==Statement of purpose==
[[Betty Friedan]] and [[Pauli Murray]] wrote the organization's first Statement of Purpose in [[1966]] (the original was scribbled on a napkin by Friedan). The original statement described the purpose of NOW as "''to take action to bring women into full participation in the mainstream of American society now, exercising all privileges and responsibilities thereof in truly equal partnership with men''."

The current Statement reads, "Our purpose is to take action to bring women into full participation in society – sharing equal rights, responsibilities and opportunities with men, while living free from discrimination." Its current brochure also states "NOW is one of the few multi-issue progressive organizations in the United States. NOW stands against all oppression, recognizing that racism, sexism and homophobia are interrelated, that other forms of oppression such as classism and ableism work together with these three to keep power and privilege concentrated in the hands of a few." (From [http://www.now.org/about.html About NOW].)

==Current issues==
Its top priority issues are: 
*[http://www.now.org/issues/abortion/ Advancing Reproductive Freedom]
*[http://www.now.org/issues/diverse/ Promoting Diversity &amp; Ending Racism]
*[http://www.now.org/issues/violence/ Stopping Violence Against Women]
*[http://www.now.org/issues/economic/ Ensuring Economic Justice]
*[http://www.now.org/issues/lgbi/ Winning Lesbian Rights] 
*[http://www.now.org/issues/constitution/ Achieving Constitutional Equality] 	 

It also works on [http://www.now.org/issues/ other issues] of concern to women. 	 

==Structure and chapters==
From the [http://www.now.org/organization/faq.html#organize NOW FAQ]:
The ''membership'', meeting yearly in [http://www.now.org/conference Conference], is the supreme governing body of NOW. NOW draws its broad grassroots strength from a nationwide network of [http://www.now.org/chapters/ local chapters], which are chartered by national NOW and which engage in a wide variety of action programs in their communities.

''State organizations'' serve to develop chapters, coordinate statewide activities and provide resources to the chapters.

There are nine ''regions'' which, in Conference, elect members to the National Board of Directors, the body which governs the organization between national conferences.

The ''national level'' of the organization is led by four elected national [http://www.now.org/officers officers], by the national Board of Directors, and by national issues committees. These national leaders are responsible for implementing policy as formulated by the annual National Conference, for coordinating national actions, and for providing membership services. 

[[List of Presidents of the National Organization for Women|NOW has had ten national presidents]], beginning with Betty Friedan in [[1966]]. [[Kim Gandy]], the currently serving national president, was elected President on its 35th Anniversary, June 30, 2001 and reelected in 2005.

==Third-party explorations==
In [[Cincinnati, Ohio]], at its 1989 convention on [[July 23]], NOW delegates questioned the merits of the [[two-party system]] and broached the idea of forming a [[third political party|third party]]. 

The convention issued a "[[Declaration of Women's Political Independence]]." An exploratory commission was formed for the possibilities of amending the [[United States Constitution]] to include freedom from [[sexual discrimination]], the right to a decent [[standard of living]], the right to clean air, clean water and [[natural environment|environment]]al protections, and the right to be free from [[violence]]. 

The commission was chaired by former NOW president [[Eleanor Smeal]]. A month earlier, NOW launched a [[Commission for Responsive Democracy]], which included Smeal, [[John Bayard Anderson|John Anderson]], [[Toney Anaya]], [[Barry Commoner]] and [[Dee Barry]].

==ERA and CEA==

In 1995, the National Organization for Women voted to drop the [[Equal Rights Amendment]], "Equality of rights under the law shall not be denied or abridged by the United States or by any State on account of sex," from their platform. During that same conference NOW wrote their own constitutional amendment which would cover all of NOW's programs of reform, including abortion, lesbian and gay rights, affirmative action, etc . . . and labeled it the Constitutional Equality Amendment. 

Although NOW has given moral support to attempts to ratify the ERA, they continue to support the CEA as part of their official platform. 

The CEA has never been introduced into any session of Congress, and no significant action has been taken on it.



==See also==
* [[Feminism]]
* [[List of Presidents of the National Organization for Women]]
* [[National Organization for Women (NOW) Woman of Courage Award Winners|List of Woman of Courage Award Winners]]
* [[Feminist Majority Foundation]]

==External links==
* [http://www.now.org/ National Organization for Women]
* [http://www.now.org/chapters/ All NOW Chapters]
* [http://www.canow.org/ California Chapter of NOW]
* [http://www.marylandnow.org/ Maryland Chapter of NOW]
* [http://www.nevadanow.org/ Nevada Chapter of NOW]
* [http://www.nhnow.org/ New Hampshire Chapter of NOW]
* [http://www.nownys.org/ New York Chapter of NOW]

[[Category:1966 establishments]]
[[Category:Women's political advocacy groups in the United States]]
[[Category:Pro-choice organizations in the United States]]
[[Category:Feminist organizations]]

[[de:National Organization for Women]]
[[pt:Organização Nacional das Mulheres]]
[[sv:National Organization for Women]]

==References==
&lt;div class="references-small"&gt;
&lt;references /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>