<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20051103170453|27265911" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="8536948" pageid="8536948" ns="0" title="National Organization for Women"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-11-08T05:55:45Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">The '''National Organization for Women''' (NOW) is an [[United States|American]] [[feminist]] group founded on [[June 30]], [[1966]] in [[Washington, D.C.]], by women attending the Third National Conference of the Commission on the Status of Women. Among the 28 founders were [[Betty Friedan]], author of ''[[The Feminine Mystique]]'' (1963), who became NOW's first president, and Rev. [[Pauli Murray]], the first African-American woman Episcopal priest. [[Molly Yard]] was president from [[1987]] to [[1991]]. During the [[1970s]] NOW promoted the [[Equal Rights Amendment]] to the [[U.S. Constitution]]. In 1966 they introduced the "Statement of Purpose". In this document they outline the basic demands and  ideals of the American feminist movement of the time.  The organization's membership is not merely limited to women, and has had famous "male feminists" as members.

In [[Cincinnati, Ohio]], at its [[1989]] convention on [[July 23]], NOW delegates questioned the merits of the [[two-party system]] and broached the idea of forming a [[third political party|third party]]. The convention issued a "[[Declaration of Women's Political Independence]]." An exploratory commission was formed for the possibilities of amending the [[United States Constitution]] to include freedom from [[sexual discrimination]], the right to a decent [[standard of living]], the right to clean air, clean water and [[natural environment|environment]]al protections, and the right to be free from [[violence]]. The commission was chaired by former NOW president [[Eleanor Smeal]]. A month earlier, NOW launched a [[Commission for Responsive Democracy]], which included Smeal, [[John Bayard Anderson|John Anderson]], [[Toney Anaya]], [[Barry Commoner]] and [[Dee Barry]].

The group's original purpose (which Friedman scribbled on a napkin) remains "''to take action to bring women into full participation in the mainstream of American society now, exercising all privileges and responsibilities thereof in truly equal partnership with men''". The organization remains active in lobbying legislatures and media outlets on women's issues.  

It claims 500,000 contributing members and 550 chapters in all 50 U.S. states and the District of Columbia.  

At the present time, NOW works to eliminate discrimination and [[harassment]] in the workplace, schools, the justice system, and all other sectors of society; secure [[abortion]], [[birth control]] and [[reproductive rights]] for all women; end all forms of violence against women; eradicate [[racism]], [[sexism]] and [[homophobia]]; and promote equality and justice in our society.

Kim Gandy was elected President of the National Organization for Women (NOW) on its 35th Anniversary, June 30, 2001.

=== Criticism ===

The National Organization for Women has been subject to criticism from many whose belief systems differ from their agenda, in particular pro-life activists. Some critics, especially those claiming to represent the male perspective (such as articles in [[Men's News Daily]] by writer [[Robert F. Gay]]) say that NOW is anti-male.  The organization has been criticized by men's and father's rights groups for denouncing "deadbeat dads." NOW's support for "[[The Vagina Monologues]]" is another example of controversy.   Some critics said that  NOW's alleged support of former President [[Bill Clinton]] over [[Juanita Broddrick]], [[Kathleen Willey]], and [[Paula Jones]] indicated that NOW had lost the authority to lead a women's rights movement, suggesting that NOW only criticized Republicans and conservatives for women's issues.  However, it should be noted that NOW did not in fact support Bill Clinton, and in fact criticized him: http://www.now.org/issues/harass/clinton.html

Other critics point out that NOW usually only supports women with liberal-left positions, and women who have pro-life views on abortion feel as opposed by NOW as men. Critics question if NOW can claim to speak for all women.

==External link==
* [http://www.now.org/ National Organization for Women]

[[Category:U.S. history of women's rights]]
[[Category:Women by nationality]]
[[Category:Political advocacy groups in the United States]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>