<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20041025204610|7074882" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="437067" pageid="437067" ns="0" title="Hate group"><revisions><rev timestamp="2004-11-03T12:40:47Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">A '''hate group''' is a group or movement that advocates [[violence]] against or unreasonable [[hate]] or [[hostility]] toward those persons or organizations identified by their religion, race, national origin, gender, sexual orientation, or disability. A hate group includes organizations or individuals that disseminate historically inaccurate information with regards to these persons or organizations. This inaccurate information is used for vilification or may be the reason for hostility. Typically they prejudge each individual in the target group as "unworthy" or "inferior" and want to exclude or hurt them. A hate group commonly works to achieve its goals using [[fear]], hate, and [[intimidation]] as its ''modus operandi'' (or commonly used methods).
 
In the [[democracy|democratic]] West, organizations dedicated to the incitement of racial violence, including [[white supremacist]], [[black supremacist]], and [[neo-Nazi]] groups, are commonly described as hate groups. Typically these groups make no bones about it; they openly admit hating their targets.

Other groups are more controversial, and little or no consensus has developed as to whether political, religious or anti-religious movements deserve the label "hate group". Some advocates have applied it to some radical activists who engage in "questionable and often illegal" methods to achieve their goals, such as [[Operation Rescue]], the [[Animal Liberation Front]] and the [[Ex-premies]]. 

Two main elements are present in hate group literature and tactics:
*Dehumanizing or demonizing the target;
*Conspiracy theories, possibly not well backed up or referenced;

Some people claim, without referring to scholarly works, that there are two additional characterizations:
*Claiming to be a minority that speaks for a silent majority;
*Proclamation of pseudo-scientific support for their theories.

==Hate groups and new religious movements==
Some advocates who regard certain fringe religious organizations, [[new religious movement]]s or (controversially) "[[cult]]s" as spurious, and condemn their methods, also call them "hate groups". For example, the prominent [[Christian countercult movement|counter cult activist]] [[Anton  Hein]] considers [[scientology]] a hate group because that religious movement has, in his opinion, a long, documented history of hate and harassment activities[http://www.apologeticsindex.org/s04f.html], which&amp;#8212;along with lying and deception&amp;#8212;are condoned and encouraged in Scientology's own 'scriptures.' (See, for example, Scientology's Fair Game [http://www.apologeticsindex.org/f08.html] policy.) 

In turn, [[CESNUR]]&amp;#8217;s president [[Massimo Introvigne]], writes in his article "So many evil things: Anti-cult terrorism via the Internet"[http://www.cesnur.org/testi/anticult_terror.htm], that fringe and extreme [[anti-cult movement|anti-cult activism]] resort to tactics that may create a background favorable to extreme manifestations of [[discrimination]] and [[hate]] against individuals that belong to new religious movements. [[Elan Vital]], an organization that supports the work of [[Prem Rawat]], considers its vocal critics that call themselves ''ex-premies'' a hate group because Elan Vital believes that their behavior and literature contains aforementioned elements and characterizations. [http://elanvital.org.uk/faq/harass.htm]

==See also==
*[[Hate]]
*[[Hate crime]]
*[[Hate speech]]

==External links==
*[http://www.adl.org/poisoning_web/introduction.asp ''Poisoning the Web: Hatred Online, Internet Bigotry, Extremism and Violence'' - The Anti-defamation League]
*[http://www.bcpl.net/~rfrankli/hatedir.htm The Hate Directory]
*[http://ex-premie.org/ Ex-premie website, considered a hate group by Elan Vital]
*[http://www.evjcmg.bravehost.com/conspiracy/ Website made by Tom Gubler who according to Elan Vital belongs to the ex-premie hate group. Also contains a definition of a hate group.]
*[http://elanvital.com.au/faq/search.php?query=Gubler&amp;submit=Go Website of Elan Vital showing an affidavit signed by Tom Gubler in which he states that the ex-premies are a hate group]
*[http://mikefinch.com/mj/art/hg.htm Ex-premie Dr. Mike Finch answers the Elan Vital's hate group accusations on his personal website]
*[http://www.splcenter.org/intel/hatewatch/ Hatewatch]
*[http://www.religiousfreedomwatch.org/hategroups/ Religious Freedom Watch] (Church of Scientology page)
*[http://www.tolerance.org/maps/hate/ Tolerance.org. map of hate groups in the USA]
*[http://www.media-awareness.ca/english/issues/online_hate/index.cfm ''Online Hate'' - The Media Awareness Network]
**[http://www.media-awareness.ca/english/issues/online_hate/deconst_online_hate.cfm ''Deconstructing Hate Sites'']
*[http://www.religionnewsblog.com/category-cat=36.html Anton Hein's Apologetics Index weblog] - entry on hate groups</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>