<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20221027075936|1118488421" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="437067" pageid="437067" ns="0" title="Hate group"><revisions><rev timestamp="2022-11-26T18:58:08Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{globalize|date=October 2022}}
{{Short description|Collective united by hatred against others}}
[[Image:Drapeau_flag_nazi_waffen_ss_confédérés_confederate_croix_celtique_cetltic_cross_far_right_extreme_droite.png|thumb|Flags commonly used by hate groups include (clockwise from top-left): [[Celtic cross#White supremacy|Celtic cross]], [[Nazism|Nazi flag]], [[Schutzstaffel|SS flag]], and [[Modern display of the Confederate battle flag|Confederate battle flag]]]]
{{Discrimination sidebar}}
[[File:Symbolique-bonehead.jpg|thumb|187px|Examples of hate group symbols:{{ordered list|the white nationalist [[Celtic cross]]|the [[Odal rune]]|the [[White power]] raised [[Raised fist|fist]]|the [[Iron Cross]] with the Nazi swastika|the [[SS]] [[Sig runes]]|the SS ''[[Totenkopf]]''
}}]]

A '''hate group''' is a [[social group]] that advocates and practices [[hatred]], [[hostility]], or [[violence]] towards members of a [[race (human classification)|race]], [[Ethnic group|ethnicity]], [[nation]], [[religion]], [[gender]], [[gender identity]], [[sexual orientation]], or any other designated sector of [[society]]. According to the United States [[Federal Bureau of Investigation]] (FBI), a hate group's "primary purpose is to promote animosity, hostility, and malice against persons belonging to a race, religion, disability, sexual orientation, or ethnicity/national origin which differs from that of the members of the organization."&lt;ref&gt;"Hate Crime Data Collection Guidelines", ''Uniform Crime Reporting: Summary Reporting System: National Incident-Based Reporting System'', U.S. Department of Justice: Federal Bureau of Investigation, Criminal Justice Information Services Division, Revised October 1999.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Monitoring==
In the [[United States|US]], the [[Federal Bureau of Investigation|FBI]] does not publish a list of hate groups, and it also says that "investigations are only conducted when a threat or advocacy of force is made; when the group has the apparent ability to carry out the proclaimed act; and when the act would constitute a potential violation of federal law". The FBI maintains statistics on hate crimes.&lt;ref name=fbifaq&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.fbi.gov/about-us/faqs |title=Frequently Asked Questions |work=[[Federal Bureau of Investigation]] |access-date=May 30, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Two private American non-profit organizations that monitor intolerance and hate groups are the [[Anti-Defamation League]] (ADL)&lt;ref name="titleADL: Fighting Anti-Semitism, Bigotry and Extremism"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.adl.org/ |title=ADL: Fighting Anti-Semitism, Bigotry and Extremism |access-date=2008-04-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[Southern Poverty Law Center]] (SPLC).&lt;ref name="titleSPLCenter.org...forwarding to index.jsp"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.splcenter.org/ |title=SPLCenter.org...forwarding to index.jsp |access-date=2008-04-13 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190713171814/https://www.splcenter.org/ |archive-date=2019-07-13 |url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; They maintain lists of what they deem to be hate groups, supremacist groups and [[anti-Semitism|anti-Semitic]], anti-government or extremist groups that have committed [[hate crime]]s. The SPLC's definition of a "hate group" includes any group with beliefs or practices that attack or malign an entire class of people—particularly when the characteristics being maligned are immutable.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.splcenter.org/get-informed/hate-map Hate Map] – SPLC&lt;/ref&gt; However, at least for the SPLC, inclusion of a group in the list "does not imply a group advocates or engages in violence or other criminal activity."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.splcenter.org/get-informed/hate-map |title=Hate Map |access-date=2010-09-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to ''[[USA Today]]'', their list ranges from "white supremacists to black nationalists, neo-Nazis to neo-Confederates."&lt;ref name=usatoday2019&gt;Woodyard, Chris (February 20, 2019) [https://www.usatoday.com/story/news/nation/2019/02/20/hate-groups-white-power-supremacists-southern-poverty-law-center/2918416002/ "Hate group count hits 20-year high amid rise in white supremacy, report says"] ''[[USA Today]]''&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Canadian Anti-Hate Network]] is a nonprofit organization that monitors hate groups in [[Canada]].&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite web |title=Members of the Standing Committee on Public Safety and National Security |url=https://www.ourcommons.ca/Content/Committee/421/SECU/Brief/BR9919854/br-external/CanadianAntiHateNetwork-e.pdf |url-status=live |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180826211721/http://www.ourcommons.ca/Content/Committee/421/SECU/Brief/BR9919854/br-external/CanadianAntiHateNetwork-e.pdf |archive-date=2018-08-26 |access-date=2021-08-07 |website=[[Parliament of Canada]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{Cite news |last=Draaisma |first=Muriel |date=2018-05-08 |title=New anti-hate group aims to monitor 'growing threat' of far-right extremists in Canada |work=[[CBC News]] |url=https://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/toronto/canadian-anti-hate-network-forms-toronto-profiles-far-right-groups-1.4653148 |access-date=2021-08-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":2"&gt;{{Cite news |last=Pierce |first=Matthew |date=2021-01-12 |title=Canadian internet sleuths, anti-hate group helping to identify Capitol rioters |work=CBC News |url=https://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/canadians-help-track-down-rioters-capitol-1.5869389 |access-date=2021-08-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=Kestler-D'Amours |first=Jillian |date=2021-09-08 |title='What next?': Experts in Canada alarmed by anti-Trudeau protests |url=https://www.aljazeera.com/news/2021/9/8/what-next-experts-in-canada-alarmed-by-anti-trudeau-protests |url-status=live |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20210908161528/https://www.aljazeera.com/news/2021/9/8/what-next-experts-in-canada-alarmed-by-anti-trudeau-protests |archive-date=2021-09-08 |access-date=2022-01-04 |website=[[Al Jazeera]] |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Number of hate groups, by state, per million inhabitants..png|thumb|400px|right|Number of [[Southern Poverty Law Center|SPLC]] hate groups per million, as of 2013]]

According to the SPLC, from 2000 to 2008, hate group activity saw a 50 percent increase in the US, with a total of 926 active groups.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Katel |first=Peter |date=2009-05-08 |title=Hate Groups |volume=19 |issue=18 |pages=421–48 |publisher=[[CQ Researcher]]}} See "The Year in Hate" Southern Poverty Law Center, February 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; In 2019, the organization's report showed a total of 1,020 hate groups, the highest number in 20 years, and a 7% increase from 2017 to 2018. The previous high was 1,018 in 2011, and the recent low point was 2014, when the list included 784 groups.  A rise in [[white nationalism|white nationalist]] groups from 100 in 2017 to 148 in 2018 was the most significant increase in the 2019 report.&lt;ref name=usatoday2019 /&gt;

Since 2010 the term [[alt-right]], short for "alternative right," has come into usage.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last1=Lombroso, Daniel &amp; |first1=Applebaum, Yoni |title='Hail Trump!': White Nationalists Salute the President Elect |url=https://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2016/11/richard-spencer-speech-npi/508379/ |access-date=17 December 2016 |publisher=The Atlantic |date=21 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=Joseph |last=Goldstein |date=November 20, 2016 |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2016/11/21/us/alt-right-salutes-donald-trump.html |title=Alt-Right Exults in Donald Trump's Election With a Salute: 'Heil Victory' |newspaper=New York Times |access-date=November 21, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; This broad term includes a range of people who reject mainstream [[conservatism]] in favor of forms of conservatism that may embrace implicit or explicit [[racism]] or [[white supremacy]]. The alt-right is described as being "a weird mix of old-school [[Neo-Nazism|neo-Nazis]], conspiracy theorists, [[Anti-globalization movement|anti-globalists]], and young right-wing internet trolls—all united in the belief that white male identity is under attack by [[Multiculturalism|multicultural]], "[[Political correctness|politically correct]]" forces."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last1=Staff |title=The Rise of the alt-right |url=http://theweek.com/articles/651929/rise-altright |access-date=17 December 2016 |publisher=The Week |date=1 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Violence and hate crimes==
{{Further|Hate crime}}
Four categories which are associated with hate groups' propensity for [[violence]] are: organizational capacity, organizational constituency, strategic connectivity, and structural arrangement.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Chermak |first=S. |author2=Freilich, J. |author3=Suttmoeller, M. |title=The organizational dynamics of far-right hate groups in the United States: comparing violent to nonviolent organizations |journal=Studies in Conflict and Terrorism |date=2013 |volume=36 |issue=3 |pages=193–218 |doi=10.1080/1057610X.2013.755912 |s2cid=55870656}}&lt;/ref&gt; The larger an extremist group is and the longer it has existed, it is more prone to engage in violence.  Regionally, hate groups which are based in the [[Western United States|West]] and the [[Northeastern United States|Northeast]] are more likely to engage in violence than those hate groups which are based in the [[Southern United States|South]].  If a group has a charismatic leader, it is more likely to be violent.  Groups that share conflict-based relationships with other groups are more likely to engage in extreme violence.  The amount of ideological literature which a group publishes is linked to significant decreases in a group's violent behavior, with more literature linked to lower levels of violence.

The California Association for Human Relations Organizations (CAHRO) asserts that hate groups such as the [[Ku Klux Klan]] (KKK) and [[White Aryan Resistance]] (WAR) preach violence against racial, religious, sexual and other minorities in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.cahro.org/2011/08/freedom-from-fear-ending-californias-hate-violence-epidemic/ |title=Freedom From FearR: Ending California's Hate Violence Epidemic |publisher=CAHRO – California Association of Human Relations Organizations |website=Cahro.org |date=1992-01-07 |access-date=2013-09-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; Joseph E. Agne argues that hate-motivated violence is a result of the successes of the [[civil rights movement]], and he asserts that the KKK has resurfaced and new hate groups have formed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://gbgm-umc.org/advance/Church-Burnings/hategrup.html#consult |title=The Church's Response to Hate-Group Violence |publisher=Gbgm-umc.org |access-date=2013-09-14 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120224231637/http://gbgm-umc.org/advance/Church-Burnings/hategrup.html#consult |archive-date=2012-02-24 |url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; Agne argues that it is a mistake to underestimate the strength of the hate-violence movement, its [[apologist]]s and its silent partners.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://gbgm-umc.org/advance/Church-Burnings/hategrup.html |title=The Church's Response to Hate-Group Violence&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt; |access-date=2004-11-28 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120224231637/http://gbgm-umc.org/advance/Church-Burnings/hategrup.html#consult |archive-date=2012-02-24 |url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the US, crimes that "manifest evidence of prejudice based on race, religion, sexual orientation, or ethnicity, including the crimes of murder and nonnegligent manslaughter; forcible rape; robbery; aggravated assault; burglary; larceny-theft; motor vehicle theft; arson; simple assault; intimidation; and destruction, damage or vandalism of property", 
directed at the government, an individual, a business, or institution, involving hate groups and hate crimes, may be investigated as acts of domestic terrorism.&lt;ref&gt;The Uniform Crime Reporting (UCR) Program – Data Quality Guidelines for Statistics  [https://www.fbi.gov/ucr/guidelines/guidelines.htm#hatecrimehistory Appendix III – A Brief History of the Hate Crime Program]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Federal Bureau of Investigation – Civil Rights {{cite web |url=https://www.fbi.gov/hq/cid/civilrights/overview.htm |title=Federal Bureau of Investigation - Civil Rights - Hate Crime Overview |access-date=2016-07-28 |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160307005258/https://www2.fbi.gov/hq/cid/civilrights/overview.htm |archive-date=2016-03-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.fbi.gov/ucr/hc2006/index.html Hate Crime Statistics, 2006 Hate Crime Overview – The FBI's Role] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150717214828/https://www.fbi.gov/ucr/hc2006/index.html |date=2015-07-17 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;1999 Developing Hate Crime Questions for the National Crime Victim Survey (NCVS) p. 1 {{cite web |url=https://www.amstat.org/sections/srms/Proceedings/papers/1999_181.pdf |title=Sections &amp; Interest Groups |access-date=2008-01-04 |url-status=bot: unknown |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20030512103017/https://www.amstat.org/sections/srms/Proceedings/papers/1999_181.pdf |archive-date=May 12, 2003}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Hate speech==
{{Main|Hate speech}}

After [[WWII]], [[Germany]] found it necessary to criminalize [[Volksverhetzung]] ("incitement to hatred") to prevent resurgence of [[fascism]].

[[Counter-terrorism]] expert Ehud Sprinzak argues that verbal violence is "the use of extreme language against an individual or a group that either implies a direct threat that physical force will be used against them, or is seen as an indirect call for others to use it." Sprinzak argues that verbal violence is often a substitute for real violence, and that the verbalization of hate has the potential to incite people who are incapable of distinguishing between real and verbal violence to engage in actual violence.&lt;ref&gt;Sprinzak, Ehud, ''Brother against Brother: Violence and Extremism in Israeli Politics from Altalena to the Rabin Assassination'' (New York: The Free Press, 1999)&lt;/ref&gt;

People tend to judge the offensiveness of hate speech on a gradient depending on how public the speech is and what group it targets.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Cowan |first=G. |author2=Hodge, C. |title=Judgments of hate speech: the effects of target group, publicness, and behavioral responses of the target |journal=Journal of Applied Social Psychology |date=1996 |volume=26 |issue=4 |pages=355–71 |doi=10.1111/j.1559-1816.1996.tb01854.x}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although people's opinions of hate speech are complex, they typically consider public speech targeting ethnic minorities to be the most offensive.

Historian [[Daniel Goldhagen]], discussing [[Anti-semitism|antisemitic]] hate groups, argues that we should view verbal violence as "an assault in its own right, having been intended to produce profound damage—emotional, psychological, and social—to the dignity and honor of the Jews. The wounds that people suffer by ... such vituperation ... can be as bad as ... [a] beating."&lt;ref&gt;Goldhagen, Daniel Jonah, ''Hitler's Willing Executioners: Ordinary Germans the Holocaust'' (Knopf, 1996), p. 124.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the mid-1990s, the popularity of the Internet brought new international exposure to many organizations, including groups with beliefs such as [[white supremacy]], [[neo-Nazism]], [[homophobia]], [[Holocaust denial]] and [[Islamophobia]]. Several white supremacist groups have founded websites dedicated to attacking their perceived enemies. In 1996, the [[Simon Wiesenthal Center]] of Los Angeles asked Internet access providers to adopt a code of ethics that would prevent extremists from publishing their ideas online. In 1996, the [[European Commission]] formed the Consultative Commission on Racism and Xenophobia (CRAX), a pan-European group which was tasked to "investigate and, using legal means, stamp out the current wave of racism on the Internet."&lt;ref&gt;Newsbytes News Network (31 January 1996)&lt;/ref&gt;

==Religious hate groups==
{{See also|List of organizations designated by the SPLC as anti-LGBT hate groups}}

The [[Southern Poverty Law Center]] (SPLC) has designated several Christian groups as hate groups, including the [[American Family Association]], the [[Family Research Council]], [[Abiding Truth Ministries]], [[American Vision]], the [[Chalcedon Foundation]], the [[Dove World Outreach Center]], the [[Traditional Values Coalition]] and [[Westboro Baptist Church]]. Some conservatives have criticized the SPLC for its inclusion of certain Christian groups, such as the Family Research Council, on its list.&lt;ref name="Is the FRC really a hate group?"&gt;{{cite news |last=Sessions |first=David |title=Is the Family Research Council Really a Hate Group? |url=http://www.thedailybeast.com/articles/2012/08/16/is-the-family-research-council-really-a-hate-group.html |access-date=3 August 2014 |newspaper=[[The Daily Beast]] |date=16 August 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="SPLC-18-List"&gt;{{cite news |last=Waddington |first=Lynda |title=Groups that Helped Oust Iowa Judges Earn 'Hate Group' Designation; SPLC Adds American Family Association, Family Research Council to List |url=http://iowaindependent.com/47947/groups-that-helped-oust-iowa-judges-earn-hate-group-designation |access-date=25 November 2010 |newspaper=[[American Independent News Network|Iowa Independent]] |date=23 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="WaPo hate"&gt;{{cite news |last=Thompson |first=Krissah |title='Hate group' designation angers same-sex marriage opponents |url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2010/11/24/AR2010112405573.html |access-date=25 November 2010 |newspaper=Washington Post |date=24 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="The Southern Poverty Law Center (SPLC) and Its So-Called 'Hate Groups'"&gt;{{cite news |last=Sprigg |first=Peter |title=The Southern Poverty Law Center (SPLC) and Its So-Called 'Hate Groups' |url=http://www.frc.org/issuebrief/the-southern-poverty-law-center-splc-and-its-so-called-hate-groups |access-date=6 August 2014 |newspaper=The Family Research Council}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The SPLC classifies the [[Nation of Islam]] (NOI) as a hate group under the [[black separatist]] category&lt;ref name=jessup&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=1IL-RQcFjRsC&amp;pg=PA165 Jessup, Michael "The Sword of Truth in the Sea of Lies: The Theology of Hate"], in Priest, Robert J. and Alvaro L. Nieves, eds., ''This Side of Heaven'' (Oxford University Press US, 2006) {{ISBN|0-19-531056-X}},  pp. 165–66&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.splcenter.org/intel/map/type.jsp?DT=3 SPLC - Active U.S. Hate Groups in 2008: Black Separatist] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080314154401/http://www.splcenter.org/intel/map/type.jsp?DT=3 |date=2008-03-14 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[Israelite School of Universal Practical Knowledge]] (ISUPK) as a hate group under the [[black supremacist]] category.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.splcenter.org/intel/intelreport/article.jsp?aid=948 |title=God and the General. Leader Discusses Black Supremacist Group |date=Fall 2008 |work=Intelligence Report |location=[[Montgomery, Alabama]] |publisher=[[Southern Poverty Law Center]] |access-date=31 July 2020 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080907052245/http://www.splcenter.org/intel/intelreport/article.jsp?aid=948 |archive-date=2008-09-07 |url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.splcenter.org/fighting-hate/intelligence-report/2008/racist-black-hebrew-israelites-becoming-more-militant |title=Racist Black Hebrew Israelites becoming More Militant |date=Fall 2008 |work=Intelligence Report |location=[[Montgomery, Alabama]] |publisher=[[Southern Poverty Law Center]] |access-date=31 July 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.splcenter.org/fighting-hate/intelligence-report/2015/history-hebrew-israelism |title=History of Hebrew Israelism |date=2015 |work=Intelligence Report |location=[[Montgomery, Alabama]] |publisher=[[Southern Poverty Law Center]] |access-date=31 July 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt; Members of the NOI believe that a black scientist named [[Yakub (Nation of Islam)|Yakub]] created a race of {{wikt-lang|en|white devil|White devils}}, who are considered the progenitors of [[White people]], on the Greek island of [[Patmos]].&lt;ref name="Corbman 2020"&gt;{{cite journal |author-last=Corbman |author-first=Marjorie |date=June 2020 |title=The Creation of the Devil and the End of the White Man's Rule: The Theological Influence of the Nation of Islam on Early Black Theology |editor-last=Fletcher |editor-first=Jeannine H. |journal=[[Religions (journal)|Religions]] |location=[[Basel]] |publisher=[[MDPI]] |volume=11 |issue=6: ''Racism and Religious Diversity in the United States'' |page=305 |doi=10.3390/rel11060305 |doi-access=free |eissn=2077-1444}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Walker 2012"&gt;{{cite book |author-last=Walker |author-first=Dennis |year=2012 |origyear=1990 |chapter=The Black Muslims in American Society: From Millenarian Protest to Trans-Continental Relationships |chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=3CCYaHRKG-oC&amp;pg=PA343 |editor-last=Trompf |editor-first=G. W. |title=Cargo Cults and Millenarian Movements: Transoceanic Comparisons of New Religious Movements |location=[[Berlin]] and [[Boston]] |publisher=[[De Gruyter]] |series=Religion and Society |volume=29 |pages=343–390 |doi=10.1515/9783110874419.343 |isbn=9783110874419}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Berg 2011"&gt;{{cite book |author-last=Berg |author-first=Herbert |year=2011 |chapter=Elijah Muhammad’s Redeployment of Muḥammad: Racialist and Prophetic Interpretations of the Qurʾān |chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=J6V6oW6qdfkC&amp;pg=PA329 |editor1-last=Boekhoff-van der Voort |editor1-first=Nicolet |editor2-last=Versteegh |editor2-first=Kees |editor3-last=Wagemakers |editor3-first=Joas |title=The Transmission and Dynamics of the Textual Sources of Islam: Essays in Honour of Harald Motzki |location=[[Leiden]] |publisher=[[Brill Publishers]] |series=Islamic History and Civilization |volume=89 |pages=329–353 |doi=10.1163/9789004206786_017 |isbn=978-90-04-20678-6 |issn=0929-2403}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Hauser |first1=Thomas |title=Muhammad Ali: His Life and Times |date=15 June 1992 |publisher=Simon and Schuster |isbn=978-0-671-77971-9 |page=85 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=6aaV0p8jaeUC&amp;pg=PA85 |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; Historically a black-only group, White adherents now form a small part of the NOI membership.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Gibson |first1=Dawn-Marie |title=A History of the Nation of Islam: Race, Islam, and the Quest for Freedom |date=2012 |publisher=ABC-CLIO |isbn=978-0-313-39807-0 |page=163 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=nR-i0IuQM9AC&amp;pg=PA163 |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; Alongside the ISUPK,&lt;ref name="ADL 2020"&gt;{{cite web |author=&lt;!--Not stated--&gt; |url=https://www.adl.org/resources/backgrounders/extremist-sects-within-the-black-hebrew-israelite-movement |title=Extremist Sects Within the Black Hebrew Israelite Movement |date=September 2020 |website=Adl.org |location=[[New York City|New York]] |publisher=[[Anti-Defamation League]] |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20200924020157/https://www.adl.org/resources/backgrounders/extremist-sects-within-the-black-hebrew-israelite-movement |archive-date=24 September 2020 |url-status=live |access-date=4 November 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt; numerous other sects and organizations within the [[Black Hebrew Israelites|Black Hebrew Israelite movement]] expound extremist, [[Black supremacy|black supremacist]], [[Religious antisemitism|religious anti-Semitic]], and [[Racism|anti-White racist]] beliefs,&lt;ref name="ADL 2020"/&gt; as well as [[Homophobia|homophobic]], [[Transphobia|transphobic]], and [[Sexism|sexist]] beliefs.&lt;ref name="ADL 2020"/&gt;

The [[White supremacy|White supremacist]] religious group [[Creativity Movement]] (formerly the World Church of the Creator), led by [[Matthew F. Hale]], is associated with violence and [[bigotry]]. [[Aryan Nations]] is another religiously-based White supremacist hate group.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.splcenter.org/fighting-hate/extremist-files/group/creativity-movement |website=Southern Poverty Law Center |access-date=10 February 2017 |title=The Creativity Movement |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170729062216/https://www.splcenter.org/fighting-hate/extremist-files/group/creativity-movement |archive-date=July 29, 2017 |url-status=dead |df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Michael"&gt;{{cite book |last1=Michael |first1=George |year=2003 |title=Confronting Right Wing Extremism and Terrorism in the USA |url=https://archive.org/details/confrontingright00mich |url-access=limited |page=[https://archive.org/details/confrontingright00mich/page/n85 72] |publisher=Routledge |isbn=978-1134377619}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Westboro Baptist Church]] is considered a hate group by multiple sources&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Westboro Baptist Church |url=http://www.adl.org/learn/ext_us/WBC/default.asp?LEARN_Cat=Extremism&amp;LEARN_SubCat=Extremism_in_America&amp;xpicked=3&amp;item=WBC |publisher=Anti-Defamation League |access-date=June 20, 2010 |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100707223315/http://www.adl.org/learn/ext_us/WBC/default.asp?LEARN_Cat=Extremism&amp;LEARN_SubCat=Extremism_in_America&amp;xpicked=3&amp;item=WBC |archive-date=July 7, 2010 |df=mdy-all}}
* {{cite web |title=Hate Map KS |url=http://www.splcenter.org/get-informed/hate-map#s=KS |publisher=Southern Poverty Law Center |access-date=June 20, 2010}}
* {{cite news |title=Hate Group Targeted by Lawmakers |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/americas/5015552.stm |date=May 25, 2006 |first=Kathryn |last=Westcott |work=BBC News |location=Barre, Vermont |access-date=June 20, 2010}}
* {{cite news |title=Hate Group Protests at Hamilton H.S. |url=http://www.todaystmj4.com/news/local/45727977.html |date=May 21, 2009 |first=Katie |last=DeLong |publisher=WTMJ-TV |location=Milwaukee |access-date=June 20, 2010 |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110717070352/http://www.todaystmj4.com/news/local/45727977.html |archive-date=July 17, 2011 |df=mdy-all}}
* {{cite web |title=Anti-Gay Hate Group Targets Seattle Churches |url=http://www.seattlepi.com/local/article/Anti-gay-hate-group-targets-Seattle-churches-1304527.php |date=June 14, 2009 |first=Ray |last=Lane |work=Seattle Post-Intelligencer |access-date=June 20, 2010}}
* {{cite news |title=Kansas Hate Group Westboro Baptist Church Protest Brooklyn Synagogues |url=http://www.nydailynews.com/new-york/brooklyn/kansas-hate-group-westboro-baptist-church-protest-brooklyn-synagogues-article-1.405633 |date=September 27, 2009 |first1=Mike |last1=McLaughlin |work=Daily News |location=New York |first2=Erin |last2=Einhorn |name-list-style=amp |access-date=June 20, 2010}}
* {{cite news |title=Opponents Rally against Westboro Baptist Hate Group |url=http://www2.timesdispatch.com/rtd/news/local/article/HATE03_20100302-222805/327944/ |date=March 3, 2010 |first1=Reed |last1=Williams |work=Richmond Times-Dispatch |location=Richmond, Virginia |first2=Chris I. |last2=Young |name-list-style=amp |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100305025103/http://www2.timesdispatch.com/rtd/news/local/article/HATE03_20100302-222805/327944/ |archive-date=2010-03-05 |access-date=March 23, 2014}}
* {{cite news |title=Hate group protests this week |url=http://temple-news.com/2010/03/30/hate-group-protests-this-week/ |date=March 30, 2010 |work=[[The Temple News]] |publisher=Temple University |location=Philadelphia |access-date=June 30, 2010 |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100406033316/http://temple-news.com/2010/03/30/hate-group-protests-this-week/ |archive-date=April 6, 2010 |df=mdy-all}}
* {{cite news |title=Interview with Westboro Baptist Church: Hate in the Name of God |url=http://www.digitaljournal.com/article/293364 |date=June 16, 2010 |first=W.V. |last=Fitzgerald |work=DigitalJournal.com |access-date=June 20, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the WBC is monitored as such by the [[Anti-Defamation League]] and the [[Southern Poverty Law Center]]. The church has been involved in actions against gay people since at least 1991, when it sought a crackdown on homosexual activity at [[Gage Park, Topeka|Gage Park]] six blocks northwest of the church.&lt;ref&gt;Jones, K. Ryan (2008), ''Fall from Grace'' (documentary).&lt;/ref&gt; In addition to conducting [[Homophobia|anti-gay]] protests at military funerals, the organization pickets celebrity funerals and public events.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Wing |first=Nick |title=Elizabeth Edwards Funeral To Be Picketed By Westboro Baptist Church |url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2010/12/09/elizabeth-edwards-funeral-westboro-baptist-church_n_794333.html |newspaper=The Huffington Post |date=2010-12-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; Protests have also been held against [[American Jews|Jews]] and [[Catholic Church in the United States|Roman Catholics]], and some protests have included WBC members [[American flag desecration|stomping on the American flag or flying the flag upside down on a flagpole]]. The church also has made statements such as "thank God for dead soldiers," "God blew up the troops," and "God hates [[United States|America]]."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=About Westboro Baptist Church |url=http://www.godhatesfags.com/wbcinfo/aboutwbc.html |work=God Hates Fags |publisher=Westboro Baptist Church |access-date=June 18, 2017 |url-status=bot: unknown |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170618001055/http://www.godhatesfags.com/wbcinfo/aboutwbc.html |archive-date=June 18, 2017 |df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; The church has faced several accusations of [[brainwashing]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.huffingtonpost.com/2013/03/06/lauren-drain-westboro-baptist-brainwashed-piers-morgan_n_2823093.html |title=Lauren Drain, Former Westboro Baptist Member, Says Group 'Brainwashed' And 'Manipulated' Her (VIDEO) |date=March 7, 2013 |via=Huff Post}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.nydailynews.com/news/national/westboro-baptist-church-member-brainwashed-article-1.1257287 |title=Former Westboro Baptist Church member speaks out: 'I was brainwashed' - NY Daily News |first=Carol |last=Kuruvilla|website=[[New York Daily News]] }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.independent.ie/world-news/daughter-who-fled-westboro-baptist-church-tells-of-brainwashing-29054869.html |title=Daughter who fled Westboro Baptist Church tells of brainwashing - Independent.ie}}&lt;/ref&gt; and has been criticised as a [[cult]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.thegospelcoalition.org/article/9-things-you-should-know-about-fred-phelps-and-westboro-baptist-church/ |title=9 Things You Should Know About Fred Phelps and Westboro Baptist Church}}&lt;/ref&gt; because of its provocative stance against [[homosexuality]] and the [[United States]], and it has been condemned by many mainstream [[LGBT rights opposition|LGBT rights opponents]] as well as by [[LGBT rights|LGBT rights supporters]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.splcenter.org/intel/intelreport/article.jsp?aid=627 The year in hate 2005], [[Southern Poverty Law Center]].&lt;/ref&gt;

==Misogynistic hate groups==

[[Misogyny|Misogynist]] hate groups which target women, particularly those groups whose members mostly consist of young men who include [[pick-up artist]]s, [[incel]]s and hardline [[Antifeminist|anti-woman]] groups, are sources of concern to some experts. Using recruitment techniques which are similar to those which are used by [[Right-wing terrorism|far-right extremist]] groups, they target teenagers and vulnerable young men, their recruitment tactics include the use of methods which are akin to [[Abusive power and control|grooming]]. UK author [[Laura Bates]] believes that some of these groups should be classified as [[Misogynist terrorism|misogynist terrorist]] groups.&lt;ref &gt;{{cite web |last=Kelsey-Sugg |first=Anna |title=Misogynistic 'radicalisation' of boys online has these experts calling for change |website=ABC News |publisher=[[Australian Broadcasting Corporation]] |date=3 April 2021 |url=https://www.abc.net.au/news/2021-04-03/misogyny-anti-women-terrorism-extremist-groups-online/100031678 |access-date=5 April 2021 |series=[[Life Matters]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Proud Boys]], which, according to the [[Southern Poverty Law Center]] is known for its [[Misogyny|misogynistic]] rhetoric,&lt;ref&gt;Staff (ndg) [https://www.splcenter.org/fighting-hate/extremist-files/group/proud-boys "Proud Boys"] ''[[Southern Poverty Law Center]]''&lt;/ref&gt; has been designated as a [[Domestic terrorism|domestic terrorist]] group in Canada.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Jacobs |first1=Emma |title=Proud Boys Named 'Terrorist Entity' In Canada |url=https://www.npr.org/2021/05/02/992846086/proud-boys-named-terrorist-entity-in-canada |publisher=[[NPR]] |website=NPR.org |access-date=29 June 2021 |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Internet hate groups==

Traditionally, hate groups recruited members and spread extremist messages by word of mouth, or through the distribution of [[flyer (pamphlet)|flyer]]s and pamphlets. In contrast, the [[Internet]] allows hate group members from all over the world to engage in [[Online chat|real-time conversation]]s.&lt;ref name="Meddaugh and Kay 2009"&gt;Meddaugh and Kay (2009)&lt;/ref&gt; The Internet has been a boon for hate groups in terms of promotion, recruitment and expansion of their base to include younger audiences.&lt;ref&gt;Schafer and Navarro (2002); Williamson and Pierson (2003)&lt;/ref&gt; An Internet hate group does not have to be part of a traditional faction such as the [[Ku Klux Klan]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ibiblio.org/nmediac/summer2012/Articles/obama_facebook.htm Moody, M., "New Media-Same Stereotypes: An Analysis of Social Media Depictions of President Barack Obama and Michelle Obama", 'The Journal of New Media &amp; Culture'' (2012).]{{dead link|date=October 2017 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;

While many hate sites are explicitly antagonistic or violent, others may appear patriotic or benign, and this façade may contribute to the appeal of the groups.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=McNamee |first=L.G. |author2=Peterson, B.L. |author3=Pena, J. |title=A call to educate, participate, invoke, and indict: understanding the communication of online hate groups |journal=Communication Monographs |date=2010 |volume=77 |issue=2 |pages=257–80 |doi=10.1080/03637751003758227 |s2cid=143387827}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hate group websites work towards the following goals: to educate group members and the public, to encourage participation, to claim a divine calling and privilege, and to accuse out-groups (e.g. the government or the media).  Groups that work effectively towards these goals via an online presence tend to strengthen their sense of identity, decrease the threat levels from out-groups, and recruit more new members.

The [[Simon Wiesenthal Center]] (SWC), in its 2009 ''iReport'', identified more than 10,000 problematic hate and terrorist websites and other Internet postings. The report includes hate [[website]]s, [[social media|social networks]], [[blog]]s, [[newsgroup]]s, [[YouTube]] and other video sites. The findings illustrate that as the Internet continues to grow, extremists find new ways to seek validation of their hateful agendas and recruit members.

Creators of hate pages and groups on [[Facebook]] choose their target, set up their page or group, and then recruit members.&lt;ref&gt;Perry and Olsson (2009)&lt;/ref&gt; Anyone can create a Facebook group and invite followers to post comments, add pictures and participate in discussion boards. A Facebook page is similar, with the exception that one must "[[like button|like]]" the page in order to become a member. Because of the ease of creating and joining such groups, many so-called hate groups exist only in [[cyberspace]].&lt;ref name="Meddaugh and Kay 2009"/&gt;
[[United Patriots Front]], an internet-based [[Australia]]n [[far-right]] [[anti-immigration]] and [[neo-nazi]] organisation formed in 2015&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.smh.com.au/national/blair-cottrell-leader-of-aussie-patriots-upf-wanted-hitler-in-the-classroom-20151016-gkbbvz.html |title=New Aussie 'patriots' leader Blair Cottrell wanted Hitler in the classroom |first1=Michael |last1=Bachelard |author-link1=Michael Bachelard |first2=Luke |last2=McMahon |date=17 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; has been described as a hate group.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.bordermail.com.au/story/3361311/hostility-to-hit-albury/ |title=Hostility to hit Albury |first=Tahlia |last=McPherson |date=20 September 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{See also|Filter bubble|Echo chamber (media)|Deviancy amplification spiral|Terrorism and social media}}

==Psychology of hate groups==
Hateful intergroup conflict may be motivated by "[[in-group]] love," a desire to positively contribute to the group to which one belongs, or "[[Ingroups and outgroups|out-group]] hate," a desire to injure a foreign group.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Halevy |first=N. |author2=Weisel, O. |author3=Bornstein, G. |title="In-group love" and "out-group hate" in repeated interaction between groups |journal=Journal of Behavioral Decision Making |date=2012 |volume=25 |issue=2 |pages=188–95 |doi=10.1002/bdm.726}}&lt;/ref&gt; Both individuals and groups are more motivated by "in-group love" than "out-group hate," even though both motivations might advance a group's status.  This preference is especially salient when a group is not situated in a competitive position against another.  This partiality towards cooperative behavior suggests that intergroup conflict might decline if group members devoted more energy to positive in-group improvements than to out-group competition.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Halevy |first=N. |author2=Bornstein, G. |author3=Sagiv, L. |title="In-group love" and "out-group hate" as motives for individual participation in intergroup conflict |journal=Psychological Science |date=2008 |volume=19 |issue=4 |pages=405–11 |doi=10.1111/j.1467-9280.2008.02100.x |pmid=18399895 |s2cid=6869770}}&lt;/ref&gt; Groups formed around a set of moral codes are more likely than non-morality-based groups to exhibit "out-group hate" as a response to their especially strong sense of "in-group love."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Parker |first=M.T. |author2=Janoff-Bulman, R. |title=Lessons from morality-based social identity: the power of outgroup "hate," not just ingroup "love" |journal=Social Justice Research |date=2013 |volume=26 |pages=81–96 |doi=10.1007/s11211-012-0175-6 |s2cid=144523660}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Intergroup threat occurs when one group's interests threaten another group's goals and well-being.&lt;ref name="Stephan 2000 23–45"&gt;{{cite journal |last=Stephan |first=W.G. |author2=Stephan, C.W. |title=An integrated theory of prejudice |journal=Reducing Prejudice and Discrimination: The Claremont Symposium on Applied Social Psychology |date=2000 |pages=23–45}}&lt;/ref&gt; Intergroup threat theories provide a framework for intergroup biases and aggression.&lt;ref name="Riek 2006 336–353"&gt;{{cite journal |last=Riek |first=B.M. |author2=Mania, E.W. |author3=Gaertner, S.L. |title=Intergroup threat and outgroup attitudes: a meta-analytic review |journal=Personality and Social Psychology Review |date=2006 |volume=10 |pages=336–53 |doi=10.1207/s15327957pspr1004_4 |pmid=17201592 |issue=4 |s2cid=144762865}}&lt;/ref&gt;

One type of intergroup threat theory, [[Realistic conflict theory|realistic group conflict theory]], addresses competition between groups by positing that when two groups are competing for limited resources, one group's potential success is at odds with the other's interests, which leads to negative out-group attitudes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Sherif, M., &amp; Sherif, C.W. |title=Social psychology |date=1969 |publisher=Harper &amp; Row |location=New York |pages=221–66}}&lt;/ref&gt; If groups have the same goal, their interactions will be positive, but opposing goals will worsen intergroup relations.  Intergroup conflict may increase in-group unity, leading to a larger disparity and more conflict between groups.

[[Symbolic threat]] theory proposes that intergroup bias and conflict result from conflicting ideals, not from perceived competition or opposing goals.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=McConahay |first=J.B. |title=Self-interest versus racial attitudes as correlates of anti-busing attitudes in Louisville: Is it the buses or the blacks? |journal=Journal of Politics |volume=441 |pages=692–720}}&lt;/ref&gt; Biases based on symbolic threat tend to be stronger predictors of practical behavior towards out-groups than biases based on realistic threat.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Kinder |first=D.R. |author2=Sears, D.O. |title=Prejudice and politics: Symbolic racism versus racial threats to the good life |journal=Journal of Personality and Social Psychology |date=1981 |volume=40 |issue=3 |pages=414–31 |doi=10.1037/0022-3514.40.3.414}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Realistic group conflict theory and symbolic threat theory are, in some cases, compatible. [[Integrated-threat theory]] recognizes that conflict can arise from a combination of intergroup dynamics and classifies threats into four types: realistic threat, symbolic threat, [[intergroup anxiety]], and negative [[stereotypes]].&lt;ref name="Stephan 2000 23–45"/&gt; Intergroup threat theories provide a framework for intergroup biases and aggression.&lt;ref name="Riek 2006 336–353"/&gt; Intergroup anxiety refers to a felt uneasiness around members of other groups, which is predictive of biased attitudes and behaviors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Ho |first=C. |author2=Jackson, J.W. |title=Attitudes toward Asian Americans: Theory and measurement |journal=Journal of Applied Social Psychology |date=2001 |volume=31 |issue=8 |pages=1553–81 |doi=10.1111/j.1559-1816.2001.tb02742.x}}&lt;/ref&gt; Negative stereotypes are also correlated with these behaviors, causing threat based on negative expectations about an out-group.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Eagley |first=A.H. |author2=Mladinic, A. |title=Gender stereotypes and attitudes toward women and men |journal=Personality and Social Psychology Bulletin |date=1989 |volume=15 |issue=4 |pages=543–58 |doi=10.1177/0146167289154008 |s2cid=145550350}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the 7-stage hate model, a hate group, if unimpeded, passes through seven successive stages.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=2003 FBI Law Enforcement bulletin |url=https://www.fbi.gov/stats-services/publications/law-enforcement-bulletin/2003-pdfs/mar03leb.pdf/at_download/file |year=2003 |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130818015515/http://www.fbi.gov/stats-services/publications/law-enforcement-bulletin/2003-pdfs/mar03leb.pdf/at_download/file |archive-date=2013-08-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Schafer 2006 73–86"&gt;{{cite journal |last=Schafer |first=J.R. |title=The seven-stage hate model: the psychopathology of hate groups |journal=Cultic Studies Review |date=2006 |volume=5 |pages=73–86}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the first four stages, hate groups vocalize their beliefs and in the last three stages, they act on their beliefs.  Factors that contribute to a group's likelihood to act include the vulnerability of its members as well as its reliance on symbols and mythologies.  This model points to a transition period that exists between verbal violence and acting out that violence, separating hardcore haters from rhetorical haters. Thus, [[hate speech]] is seen as a prerequisite of [[hate crime]]s, and as a [[condition of possibility|condition of their possibility]].

Hate group intervention is most possible if a group has not yet passed from the speech to the action stage, and interventions on immature hate groups are more effective than those that are firmly established.&lt;ref name="Schafer 2006 73–86"/&gt; Intervention and rehabilitation is most effective when the one investigating a hate group can identify and deconstruct personal insecurities of group members, which in turn contribute to the weakness of the group.  Perhaps most critical to combating group hate is to prevent the recruitment of new members by supporting those who are most susceptible, especially children and youth, in developing a positive self-esteem and a humanized understanding of out-groups.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Sternberg |first=R.J. |title=The Psychology of Hate |date=2005 |publisher=American Psychological Association |location=Washington, D.C. |pages=61–63}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{col-begin|width=75%}}{{col-break}}
* [[Anti-Defamation League]]
* [[Antifeminism]]
* [[Ethnocentrism]]
* [[Far-right politics]]
* [[Far-right subcultures]]
* [[Fascism]]
* [[Fundamentalism]]
* [[Homophobia]]
{{col-break}}
* [[Incel]]
* [[List of fascist movements]]
* [[List of Ku Klux Klan organizations]]
* [[List of neo-Nazi organizations]]
* [[List of organizations designated by the Southern Poverty Law Center as hate groups]]
* [[List of white nationalist organizations]]
* [[Misogyny]]
{{col-break}}
* [[Misandry]]
* [[Nativism (politics)]]
* [[Nazism]]
* [[Neo-Confederates|Neo-Confederate]]
* [[Neo-Nazism]]
* [[Racism]]
* [[Religious terrorism]]
{{col-break}}
* [[Right-wing politics]]
* [[Right-wing populism]]
* [[Right-wing terrorism]]
* [[Sexism]]
* [[Supremacism]]
* [[Transphobia]]
* [[Xenophobia]]
{{col-end}}

==References==
'''Notes'''
{{Reflist}}

'''Further reading'''
* [[Dorothy E. Denning|Denning, Dorothy E.]] and [[Peter J. Denning]]. ''Internet Besieged: Countering Cyberspace Scofflaws.'' New York: ACM Press (1998)
*Dudley, J. Wayne, '"Hate" Organizations of the 1940s: The Columbians, Inc.', ''Phylon'', Vol. 42, No. 3 (3rd Qtr., 1981), pp.&amp;nbsp;262–274 ([https://www.jstor.org/pss/274923 JSTOR])
* Jessup, Michael ''The Sword of Truth in the Sea of Lies: The Theology of Hate'', [https://books.google.com/books?id=1IL-RQcFjRsC&amp;pg=PA165&amp;vq=hate+organizations&amp;dq=%22Hate+organizations%22&amp;source=gbs_search_s&amp;sig=ACfU3U3UPapDLm3h82CpppP_PmUVMLvKEg Google Print, p.165-p.166], in Robert J. Priest, Alvaro L. Nieves (ed.), ''This Side of Heaven'', Oxford University Press US, 2006, {{ISBN|0-19-531056-X}}
* {{cite journal |jstor=20832071 |title="Button-Down Terror": The Metamorphosis of the Hate Movement |author=Perry, Barbara |journal=Sociological Focus |date=May 2000 |volume=33 |issue=2 |pages=113–131 |doi=10.1080/00380237.2000.10571161 |s2cid=147010178 |author-link=Barbara A. Perry}}
* {{cite journal |url=http://www.au.af.mil/au/awc/awcgate/fbi/7stage_hate_model.htm |title=The seven-stage hate model: The psychopathology of hate groups |author=Schafer, John R. MA &amp; [[Navarro, Joe]], MA . |journal=[[FBI Law Enforcement Bulletin]] |date=March 2003}}

==External links==
* {{curlie|Society/Issues/Race-Ethnic-Religious_Relations/Hate/Hate_Groups|Hate Groups}}
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20040819224500/http://www.adl.org/poisoning_web/introduction.asp ''Poisoning the Web: Hatred Online, Internet Bigotry, Extremism and Violence'' - The Anti-defamation League]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20040630080104/http://www.splcenter.org/intel/hatewatch/ Hatewatch]
* [http://www.media-awareness.ca/english/issues/online_hate/index.cfm ''Online Hate'' - The Media Awareness Network] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20040603071644/http://www.media-awareness.ca/english/issues/online_hate/index.cfm |date=2004-06-03 }}
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20040603124745/http://www.media-awareness.ca/english/issues/online_hate/deconst_online_hate.cfm ''Deconstructing Hate Sites'']
* [http://www.ibiblio.org/rcip//sbh.html Survivor bashing - bias motivated hate crimes]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20070616232320/http://www.wickedness.net/Evil/Evil%208/chaturvedi%20paper.pdf Hate Communities in Cyber Space; Manjeet Chaturvedi, Ishan, Ishita]
* {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070927213531/http://www.simson.net/ref/leaderless/berlet_when_hate_went_online.pdf |date=September 27, 2007 |title="When Hate went Online" }}
* [https://www.splcenter.org/hate-map Active U.S. Hate Groups] – a map at The Southern Poverty Law Center

&lt;!--spacing--&gt;

{{Discrimination}}
{{Racism topics|state=collapsed}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Hate Group}}
[[Category:Prejudice and discrimination|Group]]
[[Category:Social groups]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>