<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20060519022006|53966228" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1079435" pageid="1079435" ns="0" title="Rankism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-06-26T16:16:05Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Rankism''' is a term coined by physicist, educationalist and [[Citizen diplomacy|citizen diplomat]] [[Robert W. Fuller]]. Fuller has defined rankism as: "abusive, discriminatory, or exploitative behavior towards people who have less power because of their lower rank in a particular hierarchy"[http://www.breakingranks.net/weblog/rankism]. Note this definition does not mean that rankism is a form of [[discrimination|social discrimination]] since it does not make a distinction between: 
* rank assigned on the basis of class or category and 
* rank assigned on the basis of individual merit

Fuller claims that rankism also describes the abuse of the power inherent in superior rank, with the view that rank-based abuse underlies many other phenomena such as [[bullying]], [[racism]], [[sexism]], and [[homophobia]]. 

The term ''rankism'' first appeared in print in the Oberlin Alumni Magazine for fall of 1997 in an article by Fuller. Fuller later wrote a book on the topic called ''Somebodies and Nobodies: Overcoming the Abuse of Rank'', which he began distributing on his web site as a free e-book in 2000. ''Somebodies and Nobodies'' was published in 2003. 

Fuller asserts that rankism involves:
* exploiting one's position within a hierarchy to secure unwarranted advantages and benefits, without regard to the deprivation of people deemed to be inferior;
* illegitimate use of rank (e.g., abusive parent or priest, corrupt CEO, bully boss, prisoner abuse, etc.);
* treating rank as a shield that permits one person to insult or humiliate others with impunity;
* using rank to perpetuate position long after it can be justified while quashing talented people who might challenge that position;
* exporting rank achieved in one sphere of activity to claim superior importance as a person;
* use of rank illegitimately acquired or held (as in situations resting on specious distinctions of social rank such as [[racism]], [[sexism]], etc.).

Fuller has also written that:
* victims of rankists may find themselves publicly humiliated or ignored and treated as invisible. 
* society facilitates the rankist liberty to insult when whole groups are stereotyped as weak and vulnerable{{ref|SomeNo}}. 
* the opponents of rankism believe that position and power should be used to serve the group over which one holds authority. 

Members of the Dignitarian Movement claim to apply the concept of rankism as the precise cause of indignity. For Dignitarians, indignity is a litmus test for rankism. The Dignitarian Movement asserts that their aim is to overcome rankism in the same way that the [[American Civil Rights Movement (1955-1968)|civil rights]] and [[feminist movement|women's movements]] target racism and sexism.

== References ==

*{{cite journal
 | first = Daniel
 | last = Berger
 | year = 2005
 | month = August
 | title = Book review: Somebodies and Nobodies: Overcoming the Abuse of Rank
 | journal = Journal of Nervous and Mental Disease
 | volume = 198
 | issue = 8
 | pages = 571
 | url = http://www.jonmd.com/pt/re/jnmd/abstract.00005053-200508000-00014.htm;jsessionid=EB3JeR6ML1B8J289h7dwXeWGIqiEFhsX6vsZHZxrbHNZS8nAyITE!-1738699248!-949856145!9001!-1
 }}
*{{note|SomeNo}} {{cite book
 | last = Fuller
 | first = Robert W.
 | year = 2003
 | title = Somebodies and Nobodies: Overcoming the Abuse of Rank
 | publisher = New Society Publishers
 | location = Gabriola Island, Canada
 | id = ISBN 0-86571-486-X
}}
*{{cite journal
 | first = Art
 | last = Kleiner
 | authorlink = 
 | year = 2004
 | title = Diversity and its discontents
 | journal = Strategy + Business
 | issue = Spring 2004
 }}
*{{cite journal
 | first = Robert
 | last = Knisely
 | year = 2003
 | month = April
 | title = Rank prejudice
 | journal = Washington Monthly
 | volume = 35 
 | issue = 4
 }}
*{{cite journal
 | first = Elaina
 | last = Richardson
 | year = 2003
 | month = April
 | title = Respect
 | journal = O Magazine
 }}
*{{cite journal
 | first = Connie
 | last = Schultz
 | date = January 14, 2006
 | title = Taking it out on the clerks
 | journal = The Cleveland Plain Dealer
 }}

*Further references can be found [http://www.breakingranks.net/weblog/bibliography/ here], [http://www.breakingranks.net/weblog/articles here], and [http://www.breakingranks.net/weblog/syllabi/ here].

== External links ==

* [http://www.breakingranks.net BreakingRanks.net] – '...the dignity movement'  (Robert W. Fuller's web site)
:* [http://www.breakingranks.net/weblog/ BreakingRanks.net] – 'Manifest Dignity:  Dignity is Not Negotiable' (blog)
* [http://www.digdi.org DigDi.org] - 'The Dignitarian Dialogues' (website that seeks to start a public discussion of rankism)
* [http://www.dignitarians.org Dignitarians.org] - 'The Dignitarian Foundation:  Protecting the dignity of others as you would your own' (foundation dedicated to developing training materials and advocacy tools to fight rankism)
* [http://right-rank.com/ Right-Rank.com] –  'Right-Rank is a tool for dealing with rankism, the abuse of rank within a hierarchy.  Respect for everyone, regardless of rank.' (integrates concept of rankism into a therapeutic practice)
* [http://www.somebodybook.com/ SomebodyBook.com] - ''I Feel Like Nobody When... I Feel Like a Somebody When...'' (children's book that introduces issues related to rankism), Stephanie Heuer (2005) 
* [http://www.yubanet.com/artman/publish/printer_33209.shtml YubaNet.com] - '"Executive" monkeys influenced by other executives, not subordinates', [[Duke University]] Medical Center (March 22, 2006)

[[Category:Sociology]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>