<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20090416214008|284291765" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1079435" pageid="1079435" ns="0" title="Rankism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2009-04-17T02:07:14Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Orphan|date=February 2009}}
'''Rankism''' is a term coined by physicist, educationalist and [[Citizen diplomacy|citizen diplomat]] [[Robert W. Fuller]]. Fuller has defined rankism as: "abusive, discriminatory, or exploitative behavior towards people who have less power because of their lower rank in a particular hierarchy"&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | last = Fuller
  | first = Robert
  | title = Rankism: A Social Disorder
  | url=http://www.breakingranks.net/weblog/rankism
  | accessdate = 2008-09-16
  }}
&lt;/ref&gt;. Fuller claims that rankism also describes the abuse of the power inherent in superior rank, with the view that rank-based abuse underlies many other phenomena such as [[bullying]], [[racism]], [[sexism]], and [[homophobia]]. 

==Characteristics==

Fuller asserts that rankism involves:
* exploiting one's position within a hierarchy to secure unwarranted advantages and benefits, without regard to the deprivation of people deemed to be inferior;
* illegitimate use of rank (e.g., abusive parent or priest, corrupt CEO, bully boss, prisoner abuse, etc.);
* treating rank as a shield that permits one person to insult or humiliate others with impunity;
* using rank to perpetuate position long after it can be justified while quashing talented people who might challenge that position;
* exporting rank achieved in one sphere of activity to claim superior importance as a person;
* use of rank illegitimately acquired or held (as in situations resting on specious distinctions of social rank such as [[racism]], [[sexism]], etc.).

Fuller has also written that:
* victims of rankists may find themselves publicly humiliated or ignored and treated as invisible;
* rankism can occur in any [[social hierarchy]], such as corporations, families, non-profit organizations, and universities;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | last = Fuller
  | first = Robert
  | title = Democracy's Next Step:  Building a Dignitarian Soceity
  | url=http://www.breakingranks.net/weblog/articles/democracy
  | accessdate = 2008-09-19
  }}
&lt;/ref&gt;. 
* the opponents of rankism believe that position and power should be used to serve the group over which one holds authority.

Julie Ann Wambach, author of ''Battles between Somebodies and Nobodies: Combat Abuse of Rank at Work and at Home'', writes that rankism happens when individuals misuse their rank by creating a class of somebodies and a class of nobodies.&lt;ref&gt;Wambach, Julie Ann (February 6, 2009). "Your Position Never Gives You the Right to Command."  http://www.greatleadershipbydan.com &lt;/ref&gt;
Once it has permeated a group, rankism feeds on itself.&lt;ref&gt; Wambach, Julie Ann (February 25, 2009). "Slow Leaders as 'Right-Rank'Leaders." http://www.slowleadership.org/blog/2009/02/slow-leaders-as-right-rank-leaders}} &lt;/ref&gt;


== Use of term ==
The term rankism first appeared in print in the Oberlin Alumni Magazine for fall of 1997.&lt;ref&gt; {{cite journal
 | last = Fuller
 | first = Robert
 | year = Fall 1997
 | title = Campus Activities (sidebar)
 | journal = Oberlin Alumni Magazine
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Fuller later wrote a book on the topic called ''Somebodies and Nobodies: Overcoming the Abuse of Rank'' which he began distributing on his web site as a free e-book in 2000 and published in print form in 2003.&lt;ref&gt; {{cite book
 | last = Fuller
 | first = Robert W.
 | year = 2003
 | title = Somebodies and Nobodies: Overcoming the Abuse of Rank
 | publisher = New Society Publishers
 | location = Gabriola Island, Canada
 | isbn = 0-86571-486-X
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Also in 2000, Fuller used the term in a series of op-ed pieces for the California newspaper [[The Berkeley Daily Planet]].&lt;ref&gt; {{cite web
 | last = Fuller
 | first = Robert
 | year = 2000
 | title = Front Page News: Rank-based discrimination is just as alive as other ‘isms’ 
 | url = http://www.berkeleydailyplanet.com/issue/2000-10-09/article/1573?headline=Rank-based-discrimination-is-just-as-alive-as-other-isms-
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Wambach, the concept of Somebodies and Nobodies is basic to understanding rankism because both come from the way a person is treated by others.  Somebodies are encouraged, respected, elevated, and loved.  Nobodies are dealt with as less than human, are overlooked, spurned, disrespected, disdained, and despised.&lt;ref&gt; Mullen, Leah (February 8, 2009). "Battles between Somebodies and Nobodies: Interview with Julie Ann Wambach, Part 1." http://www.bellaonline.com/articles/art60649.asp}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The first use of the term in a management journal occurred in 2001, when Fuller wrote an article for the [http://www.leadertoleader.org/ Leader to Leader Institute] (formerly the Peter F. Drucker Foundation for Nonprofit Management) about the abuse of rank in hierarchies.&lt;ref&gt; {{cite journal
 | last = Fuller
 | first = Robert W
 | month = Summer
 | year = 2001
 | title = A New Look at Hierarchy: How do we make sure that rank is exercised appropriately?
 | journal = Leader to Leader
 | volume = 21
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Fuller's second book on the subject, ''All Rise: Somebodies, Nobodies, and the Politics of Dignity'', was published in 2006.&lt;ref&gt; {{cite book
 | last = Fuller
 | first = Robert W.
 | year = 2006
 | title = All Rise: Somebodies, Nobodies, and the Politics of Dignity
 | publisher = Berrett-Koehler Publishers
 | isbn = 978-1576753859 
}}
&lt;/ref&gt; 
In 2008, Fuller and co-author Pamela A. Gerloff released an eighty-six page "action-oriented guide"&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
 | last = Fuller
 | first = Robert W.
 | coauthors = Pamela A. Gerloff
 | year = 2008
 | title = Dignity for All: How to Create a World Without Rankism
 | publisher = Berrett-Koehler Publishers
 | isbn = 978-1-57675-7895
 | nopp = true
 | page = back cover 
}}
&lt;/ref&gt; on the issue of rankism and the steps individuals can take to address it.

Wambach expanded Fuller's definition of rankism to include abuse of position within a hierarchy from both up and down the lines of power.  Rankists, according to Wambach, include anyone within a hierarchy who misuses a position for personal gain without concern for other persons within that framwork or the goals of the entity.&lt;ref&gt; Wambach, Julie Ann (2008). ''Battles between Somebodies and Nobodies: Combat Abuse of Rank at Work and At Home''. Brookside Press. ISBN 978-0-9814818-0-7 &lt;/ref&gt;

The term has also been extended to incorporate the idea of [[bullying]], as suggested by this quote from the website Canadian Living (http://www.canadianliving.com): 
"Basically, '''rankism is bullying someone of a lower rank.'''"&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 |last = Fisher
 | first = Diana
 | title = Rankism: Bullying someone of a lower rank at work
 | url = http://www.canadianliving.com/life/work/rankism_bullying_someone_of_a_lower_rank_at_work.php
 | accessdate = 2008-09-24
 }}
&lt;/ref&gt;

Wambach included twenty different styles of rankism, both overt and covert, that can be found among Somebody Rankists and Nobody Rankists.&lt;ref&gt; Wambach, Julie Ann (2008). ''Battles between Somebodies and Nobodies: Combat Abuse of Rank at Work and At Home''. Brookside Press. ISBN 978-0-9814818-0-7 &lt;/ref&gt;
The Human Dignity and Humiliation Studies (HumanDHS) network, of which Robert Fuller is a member, has also accepted the concept of rankism as core to their mission. They assert:  "...the mission we have undertaken at Human DHS is the confrontation of abuse, rankism and the humiliation endemic to it, on the historical scale." &lt;ref&gt; {{cite web
 | last = The Human DHS Team
 | title = Human Dignity and Humiliation Studies: Who We Are - A Brief Overview
 | url = http://www.humiliationstudies.org/whoweare/whoweare.php
 | accessdate = 2008-09-24
 }}
&lt;/ref&gt;

== Rankism and dignity ==
According to Fuller, the abuse of rank is experienced by victims as an affront to their dignity. He defines the term dignitarian as "a condition in which the dignity of all people is honored and protected." &lt;ref&gt; {{cite web
  | last = Fuller
  | first = Robert
  | title = Dignity: A Universal Right
  | url=http://www.breakingranks.net/weblog/dignity
  | accessdate = 2008-09-16
  }}
 &lt;/ref&gt; Fuller and his supporters have launched a new [[social movement]] to promote the creation of a dignitarian society.  The Dignitarian Movement asserts that their aim is to overcome rankism in the same way that the [[American Civil Rights Movement (1955-1968)|civil rights]] and [[feminist movement|women's movements]] target racism and sexism.

Wambach offers communication sklls the reader can use to achieve right-rank, the use of one's position, anywhere within a hierarchy, to better individuals and society by showing respect for the human dignity of everyone.&lt;ref&gt; Wambach, Julie Ann (2008). ''Battles between Somebodies and Nobodies: Combat Abuse of Rank at Work and At Home''. Brookside Press. ISBN 978-0-9814818-0-7 &lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Classism]]
*[[Discrimination]]
*[[Elitism]]

== References and notes ==
&lt;references /&gt;

== Further reading ==

*{{cite journal
 | first = Daniel
 | last = Berger
 | year = 2005
 | month = August
 | title = Book review: Somebodies and Nobodies: Overcoming the Abuse of Rank
 | journal = Journal of Nervous and Mental Disease
 | volume = 198
 | issue = 8
 | pages = 571
 | url = http://www.jonmd.com/pt/re/jnmd/abstract.00005053-200508000-00014.htm;jsessionid=EB3JeR6ML1B8J289h7dwXeWGIqiEFhsX6vsZHZxrbHNZS8nAyITE!-1738699248!-949856145!9001!-1
 | doi = 10.1097/01.nmd.0000172656.22250.24
 | format = {{dead link|date=April 2009}} &amp;ndash; &lt;sup&gt;[http://scholar.google.co.uk/scholar?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;q=author%3ABerger+intitle%3ABook+review%3A+Somebodies+and+Nobodies%3A+Overcoming+the+Abuse+of+Rank&amp;as_publication=Journal+of+Nervous+and+Mental+Disease&amp;as_ylo=2005&amp;as_yhi=2005&amp;btnG=Search Scholar search]&lt;/sup&gt;
 }}
*{{cite book
 | last = Ehrenreich
 | first = Barbara
 | year = 2008
 | title = This Land is Their Land
 | publisher = Metropolitan Books
 | location = New York, NY
 | isbn = 0-850-8840-7
}}
*{{cite journal
 | first = Art
 | last = Kleiner
 | authorlink = 
 | year = 2004
 | title = Diversity and its discontents
 | journal = Strategy + Business
 | issue = Spring 2004
 }}
*{{cite journal
 | first = Robert
 | last = Knisely
 | year = 2003
 | month = April
 | title = Rank prejudice
 | journal = Washington Monthly
 | volume = 35 
 | issue = 4
 }}
*{{cite journal
 | first = Elaina
 | last = Richardson
 | year = 2003
 | month = April
 | title = Respect
 | journal = O Magazine
 | doi = 10.1080/14786430310001599405
 | volume = 83
 | pages = 3549
 }}
*{{cite journal
 | first = Connie
 | last = Schultz
 | date = January 14, 2006
 | title = Taking it out on the clerks
 | journal = The Cleveland Plain Dealer
 }}
*{{cite book
 | first = Julie Ann
 | last = Wambach
 | year = 2008
 | title = Battles between Somebodies and Nobodies: Combat Abuse of Rank at Work and at Home
 | publisher = Brookside Press
 | isbn = 978-0-9814818-0-7
}}

== External links ==
* [http://www.aaup.org/AAUP/pubsres/academe/2006/SO/Feat/soanon.htm Academe Online] - Anonymous, (September/October 2006) "Class Issues Outside the Classroom"
* [http://blog.penelopetrunk.com/2006/08/07/battle-cry-against-power-tripping/ Brazen Careerist] - Penelope Trunk, (August 27, 2006) "Battle Cry Against Power Tripping" interview with Robert Fuller, at Brazen Careerist 
* [http://www.breakingranks.net/weblog/bibliography/ Breaking Ranks] - Bibliography on Fuller's website
* [http://www.breakingranks.net/weblog/articles/ Breaking Ranks] - Other articles by Fuller 
* [http://www.breakingranks.net/weblog/syllabi/ Branking Ranks] -Course syllabi on Fuller's website
* [http://www.canadianliving.com/life/work/rankism_bullying_someone_of_a_lower_rank_at_work.php/ Canadian Living] - Diana Fisher, "Rankism: Bullying someone of a lower rank at work"
* [http://www.digdi.org DigDi.org] - 'The Dignitarian Dialogues' (website that seeks to start a public discussion of rankism)
* [http://www.dignitarians.org Dignitarians.org] - 'The Dignitarian Foundation:  Protecting the dignity of others as you would your own' (foundation dedicated to developing training materials and advocacy tools to fight rankism)
* [http://www.humiliationstudies.org/ Human Dignity and Humiliation Studies] - an organization composed of over one thousand academics and practitioners from around the globe dedicated to confronting humiliation
* [http://knol.google.com/k/robert-fuller/rankism/2bdykvw4adkga/2# Rankism]- Knol article on rankism (expert summary)
* [http://right-rank.com/ Right-Rank.com] –  Right-rank is the use of communication skills by anyone within a hierarchy to promote respect for the dignity of everyone regardless of position.
* [http://www.somebodybook.com/ SomebodyBook.com] - ''I Feel Like Nobody When... I Feel Like a Somebody When...'' (children's book that introduces issues related to rankism), Stephanie Heuer (2005) 
* [http://www.yubanet.com/artman/publish/printer_33209.shtml YubaNet.com] - '"Executive" monkeys influenced by other executives, not subordinates', [[Duke University]] Medical Center (March 22, 2006)

[[Category:Sociology]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>