<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20031027085132|1632797" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="5097395" pageid="5097395" ns="0" title="Homophobia"><revisions><rev timestamp="2003-10-27T08:52:07Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Homophobia'''  is fear, hatred, aversion to, disapproval of, [[prejudice]] or discrimination against homosexual people.

Although the word was coined by a psychologist, homophobia is not a psychiatric term. There is no such thing as ''clinical homophobia'', though the phenomenon of homophobia continues to be studied by groups like the [[American Psychiatric Association]] and the [[American Psychological Association]]. New psychiatric studies have linked deep hatred towards homosexuality to repressed homosexual feelings. (see "[[#internalised homophobia|internalised homophobia]]", below). 

Homophobia has legal definitions in some countries, for example in the controversial [[gay panic defense]], a form of [[insanity defense]], or in [[hate crime]] legislation.

== Etymology ==
The word ''homophobia'' is a [[neologism]] coined by psychologist [[George Weinberg]] in his book ''Society and the Healthy Homosexual'' in [[1972]]. It can be broken down into the [[Greek language|Greek]] words ''homo'' meaning "the same" and ''phobia'' which means "fear". A precursor was ''homoerotophobia'', coined by Dr [[Wainwright Churchill]] in ''Homosexual Behavior Among Males'' in [[1967]].

== Usage of the term ==
The term ''homophobia'' means ''irrational hatred and fear'' of homosexuals or homosexuality itself. 

On one extreme, some people, including some [[gay rights]] activists tend to use the term to describe all disapproval of homosexuality, believing that it is all fundamentally based upon an irrational hatred and fear. For example, gay rights activist Scott Bidstrup states in a personal essay titled ''Homophobia: The Fear Behind The Hatred'':

: "If you look up ''homophobia'' in the dictionary, it will probably tell you that it is the fear of homosexuals. While many would take issue with that definition, it is nevertheless true that in many ways, it really is a fear of homosexuality or at least homosexuals, as we will see in this essay." [http://www.bidstrup.com/phobia.htm]

Others suggest that it is possible to have a rational aversion to homosexuality (by definition, this is not homophobia). For example, Niclas Berggren argues in the ''Independent Gay Forum'': 

: "It is usually not the case, for homophobic persons, that the basis of their attitudes towards homosexuality is rational reasoning, or intellectual argumentation. Such endeavors have, as a rule, been added afterwards, to try to give the homophobia a nicer and more respectable framing. However, these attempts to argue intellectually against homosexuality are utter failures." [http://www.indegayforum.org/articles/berggren41.html]

On the other extreme, some anti-gay rights activists tends cavil against any use of the term ''homophobe''. For example, Jarrod Carter wrote in [[1995]] in a letter to a [[student newspaper]]:

: "I'm not homophobic, for those homosexuals out there who still use that line of drivel. You can't explain it away that easily. The word homophobic means, by popular definition, fear of homosexuals or the event of becoming homosexual. I am not afraid of either. What I am, however, is fed up with the amount of limelight that the sexually deviant are receiving in this nation. Homosexuality is not cool, it is morally incorrect." [http://archives.thedaily.washington.edu/1995/102795/hp.html]

=== Semantic disputes ===
Opponents of the gay rights movement claim that the terms ''homophobia'' and ''homophobic'' are used emotively to "blur" the difference between those who actively fear and loathe homosexuals and those who claim to disapprove of homosexuality on principled or religious grounds, in order to shame the latter into abandoning their disapproval. They oppose comments equating rational and irrational opposition to homosexuality, saying that such comments are themselves irrational. Some advocates have cited this "blurring" as a reason for alienation from the gay rights movement.

Some [[gay]] activists respond that it is not believing homosexuality to be wrong which constitutes homophobia, but rather specific positions and actions such as opposing equal rights and protections for gay people. This contrasts with the views of Niclas Berggren, for example, who describes ''attitudes'' as homophobic in themselves.

Some researchers believe that a more accurate term for negative attitudes toward homosexuals would be "homosexual-prejudice", (or "homo-prejudice"), since the connotations for this prejudice are similar to that regarding race and gender.

==== Straight Supremacism ====

Some activists also call homophobia ''straight supremacism'' equating it to [[white supremacy|white supremacism]]. Anti-gay rights groups see this as an attempt to marginalize those who disapprove of homosexuality.

== Consequences of Homophobia ==

This part of the article discusses the mental illness, not the disapproval of homosexuality by traditional, religious or supposedly scientific reasons.

Consequences of homophobia may include ''internalised homophobia'', ''violence'', and ''discrimination''.

=== Internalised Homophobia ===

Homophobia directed against oneself, called ''internalised homophobia'' or ''ego-dystonic homophobia'', can result in lifelong suffering of [[Clinical depression|depression]], low self-esteem and a stunted love life and sexuality. Some psychologists and psychiatrists attribute the much higher incidence of [[suicide]] among gay teenagers as due to this. Others believe it is due to homophobic actions against them, as described below.

Homosexuals with internalised homophobia may discriminate or be violent towards other homosexuals in the same way and to the same extent as anyone else with homophobia. Some homosexuals with internalised homophobia may ''repress'' their homosexuality, so that they are not fully aware of it. Some people claim that most homophobes are repressed homosexuals.

Homosexuals who are opposed to homosexual behaviour may suffer many of the same effects, to a lesser extent, as those with internalised homophobia. Some choose [[chastity]] in order to avoid conflict between their homosexuality and their beliefs. Others may try to become heterosexual through [[reparative therapy]], though it is debated whether it is even possible to change [[sexual orientation]] (see [[causes of sexual orientation]]).

Sometimes homosexuals who are opposed to homosexual behaviour, particularly [[politician]]s, are forcibly [[The Closet|outed]] by campaign groups or newspapers. It is claimed that opposing homosexual behaviour while being homosexual is [[hypocrite|hypocritical]] and should be exposed. This is a controversial tactic.

=== Violence ===
Main article: [[gay-bashing]]

Extreme cases of homophobia have resulted in cases of [[murder]] in the [[United States]] (see [[hate crime]]) in which a person was killed because someone thought they were homosexual. In some of these cases, the defendant argued that their action was due to a moment of panic because they believed the victim was "coming on to them". This phenomenon is generally referred to as the "[[gay panic defense]]".

Murder is the most extreme manifestation of homophobia, and occurs relatively infrequently. Much more common are cases of non-fatal beatings, shootings, stabbings, and other assaults, including verbal assaults and bullying. Fear of physical violence is widespread among homosexuals, and many of them migrate to [[urban]] areas both for the safety and cultural advantages large gay communities offer them. Even urban environments are not always safe, as it is not unknown for gangs of youths to travel into gay communities in search of targets.

=== Discrimination ===

Most often, homophobia manifests itself in [[discrimination]]. Up until very recently, discrimination against homosexuals was a function of government in Western countries. The passage of many notable non-discrimination laws and the voluntary changing of policy by many employers has, to a certain extent, improved the situation for homosexuals. However, some anti-gay rights groups contend that many of these laws and policies have, in fact, discriminated against heterosexuals. Gay rights activists don't believe these claims and further state that there are still a great deal of subtle forms of anti-homosexual discrimination. Because of this, homosexuals still talk about their fear being fired from their jobs, denied housing, or harassed in various ways. (See [[fruit machine]].)

Homosexuals were one of the groups persecuted under the [[Nazi]] regime. As many as 600 000 homosexuals died in the [[Holocaust]]. See [[Homosexuals in Nazi Germany]], [[pink triangle]].

=== Causes of homophobia ===

The cause of homophobia in society has been widely debated. Homophobic beliefs and attitudes can be held by people independent of their sexual orientation.

Some [[gender theorist]]s interpret the fact that male/male activities or relationships often incite a stronger reaction in a homophobic person than female/female ([[lesbian]]) activities or relationships, as meaning that the homophobic person feels threatened by the perceived subversion of the [[gender paradigm]] in male/male sexual activity.

[[Psychoanalytic theory]] has long held that homophobia was the result of repressed homosexual desires.  Recent research has shown that homophobic heterosexual men showed signs of [[sexual arousal]] from being shown images of homosexual sex, when a control group of non-homophobic heterosexual men did not. [http://www.apa.org/releases/homophob.html] Similarly, so-called [[ex-gay]]s, who claim to have "walked away from homosexuality, have often used strong language to condemn the practice (and some have later returned to it). The group most likely to manifest homophobia is adolescent males.

Some groups or individuals have voiced disapproval of homosexuality, or actively oppose it, because of religious principles. These self-proclaimed ''principled advocates'' typically condemn violence toward homosexuals but vary in their opinion about the legal status of homosexuals. Some people believe that these approaches foster homophobia. See [[Religion and homosexuality]].

Some laws have been seen to encourage or legitimise homophobia, as in [[sodomy law]]s, [[Section 28]], and differing [[age of consent|ages of consent]] for homosexuals and heterosexuals.

== Opposition to homophobia ==

To combat homophobia, the [[Lesbian]]/[[Gay]]/[[Bisexual]]/[[Transgender]] (LGBT) community uses events such as [[pride parade]]s and [[political activism]]. See [[gay pride]].

Many religious organizations and denominations support gay rights and oppose homophobia. See [[Religion and homosexuality]].

Some laws have been made to oppose homophobia, as in [[hate speech]], [[hate crime]], and laws against [[discrimination]] on the basis of sexual orientation. Changes to the law are often made in response to pressure from the [[gay rights]] movement.

See also: [[Transphobia]], [[Xenophobia]], [[Heterosexism]], [[Heteronormativity]]

== External links ==
* [http://www.apa.org/releases/homophob.html New Study Links Homophobia with Homosexual Arousal]

[[de:Homophobie]]
[[fr:Homophobie]]
[[sv:Homofobi]]
[[zh:&amp;#23545;&amp;#21516;&amp;#24615;&amp;#24651;&amp;#30340;&amp;#24656;&amp;#24807;]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>