<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20051109160628|27829399" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="5097395" pageid="5097395" ns="0" title="Homophobia"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-11-10T22:00:12Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">The term '''"homophobia"''' is a [[portmanteau]] derived from the words [[homosexuality|homosexual]] and [[phobia]]. In current usage it is employed to refer to the aversion to, or disapproval of physical intimacy and sexual expression between individuals of the same sex and those who engage in such activities. This aversion may range from mild to intense.

==Etymology==

According to the [[Oxford English Dictionary]], the word ''homophobia'' in the meaning "fear or hatred of homosexuals and homosexuality" was first used in print in [[Time Magazine]] in [[1969]]. It was coined by clinical psychologist [[George Weinberg]], and popularized by his book ''Society and the Healthy Homosexual'' in [[1971]].  It combines the [[Greek language|Greek]] words ''phobos'', meaning "panic fear", with the prefix ''homo-'', which means "the same".  The "homo" in homophobia comes from the word [[homosexuality|homosexual]], not to be confused with the [[Latin]] ''homo'', meaning man (as in [[homo sapiens]]).

A possible precursor was ''homoerotophobia'', coined by Dr [[Wainwright Churchill]] in ''Homosexual Behavior Among Males'' in [[1967]].

==Dual associations and usage controversy==

Most people who discuss the idea of prejudice against [[LGBT]] people use the term "homophobia" as a parallel to [[racism]] or [[sexism]] (which refers to gender prejudice).  [[Heterosexism]] and [[sexualism]] have been proposed as alternatives which are more [[morphologically]] parallel, and which do not have the association with phobia.  The term "homosexualism" is a rarely-used synonym of [[homosexuality]].  [[Queer Theory]] uses the term [[heterocentric]] to refer to a similar [[ontological]] assumption, and the parallel term from [[critical theory]] is [[heteronormativity]]. [[Heterosexualism]] is an ambiguous term which is used either as a synomym for [[heterosexuality]] or [[heterosexism]] (prejudice against homosexuals). "Homoism" is not a term in widespread use.

Homophobia as a clinically diagnosed medical condition is quite uncommon, especially compared to the prevalence of political, personal, or moral disapproval of homosexuality in general.  Although not specifically listed in the [[Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders]], clinical homophobia might fall into the class of "specific phobias" or be associated with other disorders.  (See [[phobia]] and also [[homosexual panic]].)

For more information on medically diagnosed phobia, see [[phobia]].  For something that might be described as "medical homophobia", see [[homosexual panic]].

Some users of the term "homophobia" simply mean prejudice against homosexuals or LGBT people.  But others actually use the word to intentionally associate the idea of prejudice with fear.  One implication of this association would be that a lack of familiarity or comfort with openly LGBT people causes prejudice; some might even go so far as to claim that all prejudice arises from some kind of fear, possibly related to one or another "us vs. them" division.  

Just as some people intentionally use the term "homophobia" to stress the association between prejudice and a fear or medical disorder, others criticize it as being unnecessarily or even maliciously [[loaded term|loaded]] with those associations, and may avoid using it as a result.  Considerable cultural and political debate continues over whether anti-LGBT prejudice is right or wrong, whether it is a legitimate moral stance or indefensible discrimination, whether or not there are reasons other than fear and misunderstanding that might justify such an opinion, and even whether or not the arguments in support of such an opinion are rational or irrational.

As to the validity of the term, it is sometimes argued that the term suggests an irrational, instinctual fear, as other [[phobia]]s would, which they feel mischaracterizes "homophobes"' opposition to homosexuality in that it is often based on religious beliefs and/or reasoning as to the nature of sexual relationships. 

Gay-rights supporters, on the other hand, argue that homophobia does not stem from mere intellectual terms and therefore an aversion to homosexuality should validly be seen as sheer [[prejudice]] and unjustified aversion. However, a counter-argument would be that this is a similar attitude to the "choice" debate at the heart of homosexual persecution.

A minority argue that homophobia itself stems from a clinical condition, suggesting that the term should be taken literally as a medical definition of ill aversion to ''homosexuals'', for the state of individuals and their associated interactions with society. The scientific community, along with a vast majority of people are unsupportive as to this notion{{fn|1}}, though some still speculate on the pre-cultural roots of homophobia in today's society [http://uk.gay.com/headlines/8588 Study in the Journal of Personality and Social Psychology].The study claimed that ""Discrimination could be an after effect of the ancestral need to protect a group from danger." it went on to say that "key emotions were targeted at different minority groups, with gay men likely to elicit feelings of disgust." The study concluded that "the scientists behind the study say the hard-wiring of our brains should not act as an excuse for homophobia or prejudice, since we can now learn to "dampen down" our fears."


==Internalized homophobia==

''Internalized homophobia'' (or ''ego-dystonic homophobia'') usually refers to homophobia as a prejudice carried by homosexuals against themselves and others like them.  It includes a discomfort with or disapproval of one's own [[sexual orientation]].

Such a situation may cause extreme repression of homosexual desires. In other cases, a conscious internal struggle may occur for some time, often pitting deeply held religious or social beliefs against strong emotional desires and needs. This discordance often causes [[clinical depression]], and the unusually high [[suicide]] rate among homosexual teenagers may be partly attributed to this phenomenon (the opinions and actions of others is obviously also a factor in both).

Many people in this situation attempt to resolve it, at least for a period of time, through [[chastity]]. This is an attractive option because many belief systems are neutral or only mildly disapprove of, for example, homosexual feelings, but strongly disapprove of acting on those feelings. Advocates of the [[ex-gay]] movement believe that in addition to behavior, [[sexual orientation]] is a malleable attribute, and advocate attempting to change it (this is highly controversial, and most mental health professionals warn that such therapies have not been proven to be effective, and that they may be psychologically harmful).

The label of internalized homophobia is sometimes applied to conscious or unconscious behaviors which an observer feels the need to promote or conform to the expectations of [[heteronormativity]] or [[heterosexism]]. This might include making assumptions about the gender of a person's romatic partner, or about gender roles. Some also apply this label to LGBT persons who support "compromise" policies, such as those that find civil unions an acceptable alternative to same-sex marriage. Whether this is a tactical judgement call or the result of some kind of internal prejudice (whether in a cause-and-effect fashion, or definitionally) is a matter of some debate.

Some claim (including Sigmund Freud in his [[psychoanalytic theory]]) that some or most homophobes are repressed homosexuals, but this claim is highly controversial. The notion, however, suffers from a serious logical fallacy known as post hoc ergo propter hoc. In 1996, a controlled study of 64 heterosexual (by experience and self-reported orientation) men at the University of Georgia{{fn|2}} found the allegedly homophobic men (as measured by the Index of Homophobia{{fn|3}}) considerably more likely to experience more erectile response when exposed to homoerotic images than non-homophobic men. 

However, the homophobic men also tended to report more negative emotions in response to those particular images (not sexual arousal), and the researchers noted that general anxiety has been shown to enhance erectile response. There was no significant difference in results on the [[Homophobia#References|Aggression Questionnaire]]. The group recommended further research.

==Fear of being identified as a homosexual==

A component considered to play into homophobia, as considered by some theorists, such as [[Calvin Thomas]] and [[Judith Butler]], is an individual's fear of being identified as homosexual him or herself.

This notion suggests that when expressing homophobic viewpoints and emotions, the individual who does so is not only expressing his thoughts as to homosexuals, but also actively attempting to distance himself from this category and attributed social status. Therefore, by distancing him or herself from the people in question, he/she is reaffirming his/her role as a [[heterosexual]], within [[heteronormativity]], and contributing to the avoidance of his/her potential labelling and consequent treatment as a homosexual.

This interpretation plays into notions of violent opposition to "the Other" as a means of establishing one's identity as part of the majority and therefore, validated by society. This concept is also recurrent in interpretations of [[racism]] and [[xenophobia]].

==Homophobia as prejudice==

Whether viewed as unfounded prejudices or legitimate moral opinions, anti-LGBT attitudes have been reflected in [[:Category:Anti-gay rights legislation|legislation]] and have had a profound impact on political debates over [[:Category:LGBT civil rights|LGBT civil rights]] in general.  They have also result in [[Violence against gays, lesbians, bisexuals, and the transgendered|violence against LGBT people]], sometimes by individuals, sometimes state-sanctioned or organized.

Many social and religious attitudes toward homosexuality are negative, which some might describe as homophobic. See [[Societal attitudes towards homosexuality]] and [[Religion and homosexuality]].

[[Social Psychology|Psychology]] researchers have used the [[Social Dominance Orientation|SDO]] and [[Right_Wing_Authoritarianism|RWA]] measures to predict homophobic attitudes.

===Sexist beliefs===

Some [[gender theorist]]s interpret the fact that male-to-male relationships often incite a stronger reaction in a homophobic person than female-to-female ([[lesbian]]) as meaning that the homophobic person feels threatened by the perceived subversion of the [[gender paradigm]] in male-to-male sexual activity. According to such theorists as D.A. Miller, male heterosexuality is defined not only by the desire for women but also, and more importantly, by the denial of desire for men. Therefore, expressions of homophobia serve as a means of limiting those who they view as displaced in heteronormativity, and also of accenting their male nature, by isolating the threatening concept of their own potential feminity in gay men, and consequently belittling them, as not ''real'' males. They regard the reason male homosexuality is treated worse compared to female homosexuality as [[sexist]] in its underlying belief that men are superior to women and therefore for a man to ''"replace"'' a woman during intercourse with another man is his own subjection to (non-male) inferiority.

However, this view would imply that only the passive male partner in homosexual acts would be thought of as "offensive". Miller's specific claim that male heterosexuality does not require "desire for women" would seem to preclude the possibility of [[asexuality]] or [[bisexuality]]. Nor is it clear why male heterosexuals would "need" or even fear homosexuals in order to affirm maleness &amp;ndash; unless their sexuality was already experienced as threatened by some other cause.

===Opposition to homophobia===

To combat homophobia, the LGBT community uses events such as [[pride parade]]s and [[political activism]] (''See [[gay pride]]).'' Some parts of the festivities are criticized for reinforcing stereotypes about LGBT people (e.g. [[Dykes on Bikes]], the prominence of cross-dressing, a gay male fascination with musicals, the colour [[pink]], a sex-positive atmosphere that may seem to give endorsement to a promiscuous lifestyle which in turn relates to the problem of AIDS, etc). Other portions tend to challenge stereotypes, including the presence of religious organizations who support gay rights and oppose homophobia (''See [[Religion and homosexuality]]''), the families of LGBT people, and LGBT people with children. Much of the colour, glamour, and noise of pride parades can also be seen as a simple celebration of LGBT culture, or of life in general.

One form of organized resistance to homophobia is the [http://ilga.org/news_results_b.asp?FileID=329 International Day Against Homophobia (IDAHO)], first celebrated [[May]] 17, [[2005]] in related activities in more than 40 countries [http://www.emediawire.com/releases/2005/5/emw239185.htm].

Some activists also call homophobia ''straight supremacism'' equating it to [[white supremacy|white supremacism]]. Anti-gay groups see this as an attempt to marginalize those who disapprove of homosexuality.

Besides public expression, specific laws have been made to oppose homophobia, as in [[hate speech]], [[hate crime]], and laws against [[discrimination]] on the basis of sexual orientation.

Some argue that anti-LGBT prejudice is immoral or unwise above and beyond the effects on that class of people. [[Warren J. Blumenfeld]] argues that this emotion gains a dimension beyond itself, as a tool for extreme far-right conservative and religious groups and as a restricting factor on gender-relations as to the weight associated with performing each role accordingly. Furthermore, Blumenfeld in particular claimed:
:Anti-gay bias causes young people to engage in sexual behaviour earlier in order to prove that they are straight. Anti-gay bias contributed significantly to the spread of the AIDS epidemic. Anti-gay bias inhibits the ability of schools to create effective honest sexual education programs that would save children's lives and prevent STDs{{fn|4}}.

=="Homophobia" as a applied to opponents of political issues==
The term "homophobe" has also been used to describe opponents of laws considered favorable to gay rights causes. Opponents of [[same sex marriage]] legalization, child adoption by same-sex couples, and anti-gay hate crimes are often labeled "homophobes" when for not supporting this legislation.

Senator [[Rick Santorum]] was labeled a homophobe by critics for making a delclaration that he believed consenting adults do not have a constitutional right to privacy with respect to sexual acts. Santorum described the ability to regulate homosexual acts as comparable to the states' ability to regulate other sexual behaviors. (See [[Santorum Controversy]])

In some cases, it may be possible to oppose one or more of the pro-gay legislative issues listed above without it necessarily being due to visceral antipathy toward gay people, i.e. homophobia.

==Excerpts from discussions of the term==

Gay rights supporter Scott Bidstrup, in a personal essay titled ''Homophobia: The Fear Behind The Hatred'', emphasizes the association between prejudice and fear:
:If you look up ''homophobia'' in the dictionary, it will probably tell you that it is the fear of homosexuals. While many would take issue with that definition, it is nevertheless true that in many ways, it really is a fear of homosexuality or at least homosexuals{{fn|5}}.

Niclas Berggren, writing in the ''Independent Gay Forum'', argues that "homophobic" opinions are irrational:
:It is usually not the case, for homophobic persons, that the basis of their attitudes towards homosexuality is rational reasoning, or intellectual argumentation. Such endeavors have, as a rule, been added afterwards, to try to give the homophobia a nicer and more respectable framing. However, these attempts to argue intellectually against homosexuality are utter failures{{fn|6}}.

Christian commentator Gregory Koukl, in a personal essay titled ''Heterosexism'', objects to the medicalization of a moral position:
:The word homophobia has come to describe any kind of opposition to homosexuality of any sort, but its interesting that part of their ([[homosexuality|homosexuals]]') goal was to shift the emphasis from what many perceived to be a homosexual problem, away from the homosexual activity itself, and towards the attitude people have about homosexuality... They purposely did this to change the focus of the discussion from the morality of their activity and the social appropriateness of their lifestyle to the attitudinal bias of those who would judge them{{fn|7}}.

==Homophobia or Open Prejudice Against Homosexuals in popular culture==

* [[Eminem]] garnered a lot of controversy as he rose to success, because of what were seen as highly homophobic lyrics, which ultimately led to [[GLAAD]] actively receiving hate-mail from fans of his. This led to a number of reactions against him, in the forms of public manifestations and even a commercial specifically filmed for the night he played at the 2001 Grammys, with the mother of a homosexual teenager, [[Matthew Shepard]], who was beaten to death, speaking out to the general public as to the use of homophobic terms. Ironically, Eminem performed with openly gay artist [[Elton John]] that very night.

* In 2004 the reggae artist [[Sizzla]] cancelled his tours of the [[United Kingdom]] and [[France]] after protests over his anti-gay lyrics (popularly refered to as "homophobic"), and at one point the [[British government]] considered banning him from entry into the country [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/entertainment/music/3977791.stm].

* In 2001 the Russian pop-band ''Chugunnyi Skorokhod'' (Russian "Чугунный Скороход") (literally, "The fast-walker of pig-iron") released a song ''Pidory idut!'' (Russian "Пидоры идут"!) ("Fags are marching!"). The song is about how it is hard for a straight man to live in a world where gays rule (particularly, in fields of TV, show business, etc.). It contains lines like "You were born a man - you're trapped! There's no way if you are straight!" "Any hairdresser or stylist must be a homosexual! How can a straight man work, if gays want him immediately?" The reaction in the Russian society was mixed: while some gay magazines and web sites accused the authors of fascism, many people accepted it quite warmly.

==References==

# Carter, Jarrod, "''[http://archives.thedaily.washington.edu/1995/102795/hp.html What do you mean you're not homophobic?]''". Letter to the Editor.
# Bulter, Judith (). [http://www.theory.org.uk/but-int1.htm Interview by Peter Osborne and Lynne Segal, London, 1993. © Radical Philosophy Ltd, 1994].
# Herek, Gregory M., Ph.D., "Beyond 'Homophobia': Thinking About Sexual Prejudice and Stigma in the Twenty-First Century".  &lt;u&gt;Sexuality Research &amp; Social Policy&lt;/u&gt; (April, 2004) [http://www.narth.com/docs/creates.html summary].
# Thomas, Calvin, ed. (2000). "Straight with a Twist", ''Straight with a Twist: Queer Theory and the Subject of Heterosexuality'', p.27-8. University of Illinois Press.
# Aggression Questionnaire: A. H. Buss and M. Perry, 1992.

==Notes==

{{fnb|1}} [http://www.planetout.com/news/article-print.html?2002/06/13/3 Study: Homophobia is not a phobia], Gay.com U.K., June, 2002.

{{fnb|2}} "Is Homophobia Associated With Homosexual Arousal?" by Henry E. Adams, Ph.D., Lester W. Wright, Jr., Ph.D. and Bethany A. Lohr, University of Georgia (Athens), Department of Psychology. ''Journal of Abnormal Psychology'', Vol. 105, No. 3, pp 440-445. [http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=8772014 Abstract] at [[PubMed]]. Summarized in an [[American Psychological Association]] press release, August 1996: "[http://web.archive.org/web/20040202035152/www.apa.org/releases/homophob.html  New Study Links Homophobia with Homosexual Arousal]".

{{fnb|3}} Index of Homophobia: W. W. Hudson and W. A. Ricketts, 1980.

{{fnb|4}} Blumenfield, Warren J., "''Homophobia: How we all pay the price''" (1992).

{{fnb|5}} Bidstrup, Scott, "''[http://www.bidstrup.com/phobia.htm Homophobia: The Fear Behind The Hatred]''". An essay on the origin and nature of homophobia.

{{fnb|6}} Berggren, Niclas, "''[http://www.indegayforum.org/articles/berggren41.html Independent Gay Forum]''".

{{fnb|7}} Koukl, Gregory,"Stand to Reason" (radio program); "Heterosexism" [http://www.str.org/free/commentaries/homosexuality/heterose.htm].





==See also==

*[[National Day Against Homophobia]]
*[[Homophobic hate speech]]
*[[Violence against gays, lesbians, bisexuals, and the transgendered]]
*[[Anti-gay slogans]]
*[[Conformism]]
*[[List of sexual slurs]]
*[[Santorum controversy]]
*[[Religion and homosexuality]]

* Phobias as prejudice
**[[Afrophobia]]
**[[Heterophobia]]
**[[Islamophobia]]
**[[Transphobia]]
**[[Xenophobia]]


== External links ==
* [http://en.wikiquote.org/wiki/Homophobia Wikiquote - Quotes about Homophobia]
* [http://www.religioustolerance.org/hom_phob.htm Meanings of the word Homophobia]
* [http://www.glaad.org/media/archive_detail.php?id=142 GLAAD site: Nationwide Responses to Senator Lott's Homophobic Remarks]

[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Neologisms]]
[[Category:Phobias]]
[[Category:Prejudices]]
[[Category:Sexual orientation and society]]
[[Category:Pejorative political terms]]

[[bg:Хомофобия]]
[[de:Heterosexismus]]
[[es:Homofobia]]
[[fr:Homophobie]]
[[it:Omofobia]]
[[he:הומופוביה]]
[[nl:Homofobie]]
[[pl:Homofobia]]
[[pt:Homofobia]]
[[ru:Гомофобия]]
[[fi:Homofobia]]
[[sv:Homofobi]]
[[zh:同性恋恐惧症]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>