<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061022142214|83003917" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="5097395" pageid="5097395" ns="0" title="Homophobia"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-10-22T14:22:47Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{protected}}
{{npov}}
'''Homophobia''' is the fear of, aversion to, or discrimination against [[homosexuality]] or homosexuals.&lt;ref&gt;[http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/homophobia dictionary.reference.com]&lt;/ref&gt; It can also mean hatred, hostility, or disapproval of homosexual people, sexual behavior, or cultures, and is generally used to assert [[bigotry]].&lt;ref&gt;Merriam-Webster's Dictionary 2006 and 11th Collegiate Dictionary, 2005, American Heritage Dictionary.&lt;/ref&gt; 

The term ''homophobic'', meaning "prejudiced against homosexual people"&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thefreedictionary.com/homophobic]&lt;/ref&gt;, is [[pejorative]] in the same manner that [[bigotry|''bigoted'']] or [[prejudice|''prejudiced'']] is pejorative. Critics of the term argue that when it is applied to political opposition to particular goals of [[LGBT social movements]], it is a [[loaded language|loaded term]] intended to associate such political opposition with bigotry.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lifeway.com/lwc/article_main_page/0,1703,A%253D153888%2526M%253D150019,00.html "Just What Is 'Homophobia'?"], Kelly Boggs&lt;/ref&gt;

==Etymology and usage==

The word homophobia was used from 1920 to mean "fear of men, or aversion towards the male sex" ([[Oxford English Dictionary]]). However, from 1969 it has been more frequently used with its current connotation, first appearing (in print) in the American Time magazine, 31st October edition. It was utilized by clinical psychologist [[George Weinberg]], who claims to have first thought of it while speaking at a [[homosexuality|homophile]] group in 1965, and popularized by his book ''Society and the Healthy Homosexual'' in 1971. He combined the Greek term ''phobos'', meaning "fear" or "panic" and the root ''homo'' from the word "homosexual". When asked about the meaning of the word in a 2002 interview, he said:

:"Homophobia is just that: a phobia. A morbid and irrational dread which prompts irrational behavior flight or the desire to destroy the stimulus for the phobia and anything reminiscent of it."&lt;ref&gt;"[http://www.pflagdetroit.org/george_weinberg.htm George Weinberg: Love is Conspiratorial, Deviant &amp; Magical]"&lt;/ref&gt;

A possible etymological precursor was ''homoerotophobia'', coined by [[Wainwright Churchill]] in ''Homosexual Behavior Among Males'' in 1967.

The fact that "homophobia" etymologically implies an irrational fear can be in principle misleading, since it is commonly used to indicate any opposition to homosexuality on any basis. Moreover, "clinical homophobia" is not listed in the [[Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders]]. &lt;ref&gt;http://pheeds.com/American_Psychiatric_Association.html&lt;/ref&gt; Opponents object to the term, complaining that the connotation of mental illness is implicit.

Just as some people use the term "homophobia" to stress the association between prejudice and a fear or medical disorder, other terms such as [[sexism]], [[sexualism]], [[heterosexism]], [[heterosexualism]], and "homosexualism" have been proposed as alternatives which are more [[Morphology (linguistics)|morphologically]] parallel, and which do not have the association with [[phobia]].  [[Sexism]] refers to sexual discrimination and hatred, and may be extended to include discrimination and hatred based on both sex and sexuality (sexual-identity/sexual-orientation/hypersexuality).  [[Sexualism]] refers to hatred against [[homosexuals]] (gay men/lesbians) and [[bisexuals]].  [[Heterosexism]] refers to hatred against people who are not heterosexual.  [[Heterosexualism]] is an ambiguous term which is used either as a synomym for [[heterosexuality]] or [[heterosexism]].  The term "homosexualism" is a rarely-used synonym of [[homosexuality]].  [[Queer Theory]] and [[critical theory]] use the terms [[heterocentric]] and [[heteronormativity]] to refer to similar [[ontological]] assumptions.

As behaviors and thoughts that are frequently considered homophobic are often not fear based but instead reflect a disapproval of homosexuality, some recent psychological literature has suggested the term [[homonegativity]].

There is also considerable debate over the term's usage as a label for opponents of certain categories of social policy, with the debate centering upon the question of whether such opposition is a legitimate moral stance or indefensible discrimination, and whether or not there are reasons other than fear and misunderstanding that might justify such positions. As in cases such as the [[Santorum controversy]], many have alleged that the term is often used as a means of demonizing and silencing political opponents without regard to their actual motives; those on the other side of the debate argue that the motives in such cases are always connected with bigotry or fear.

Nonetheless, the term is often used collectively with other terms denoting of bigotry and discrimination. In a recent address, [[Coretta Scott King]] asserted that, ''Homophobia is like racism and anti-Semitism and other forms of bigotry in that it seeks to dehumanize a large group of people, to deny their humanity, their dignity and personhood.'' Likewise, George Yancey, writing in ''Christian Ethics Today'' associates "sexism, racism, class distinctions, or homophobia" and views them all as "varietes of discrimination."&lt;ref&gt;http://www.christianethicstoday.com/Issue/040/Is%20Homophobia%20The%20Same%20As%20Racism-Sexism%20By%20George%20Yancey_040__.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

==Measuring frequency of homophobic attitudes in the United States and United Kingdom==
Disapproval of homosexuality and of homosexuals &lt;!-- I assume?  What specific behaviors or beliefs were being measured by the study cited below? --&gt; is not evenly distributed throughout society, but is more or less pronounced according to age, sex, social class, education and religious status. {{cn}} According to UK HIV/AIDS charity [[AVERT]], low educational level and social status are strongly associated with such views.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.avert.org/hsexu3.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

One study of white adolescent males conducted at the University of Cincinnati by Janet Baker has been used to argue that negative feelings towards homosexuals are also associated with other [[discriminatory]] behaviors. The study claims to have found that hatred of homosexuals, &lt;!-- I assume?  Again, what behaviors or beliefs were being measured here, specifically? --&gt; anti semitism and racism are "likely companions",&lt;ref&gt;"[http://calbears.findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m1355/is_n10_v85/ai_14936859 Homophobia, racism likely companions, study shows]", ''Jet'', January 10, 1994&lt;/ref&gt; suggesting it is an abuse of power. &lt;!--  Additionally, there really needs to be an opposing view given to this rather than citing one vague study as uncontested fact --&gt;

The anxiety of non-gay individuals that others may identify them as gay, particularly among adolescents whose construction of heterosexual masculinity is factored in part on not being seen as gay,&lt;ref&gt;Epstein, D. (1995). "Keeping them in their place: Hetero/sexist harassment, gender and the enforcement of heterosexuality." In J. Holland&amp;L. Adkins (Eds.), ''Sex, sensibility and the gendered body.'' London: Macmillan.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Herek, G. (Ed.). (1998). Stigma and sexual orientation: Understanding prejudice against lesbians,
gay men and bisexuals. Newbury Park, CA: Sage.&lt;/ref&gt; has also been identified by [[Michael Kimmel]] and [[Matthew Mahler]] as an example of homophobia.&lt;ref&gt;Kimmel, M. (1994). Masculinity as homophobia: Fear, shame and silence in the construction of gender identity. In H. Brod &amp; M. Kaufman (Eds.), ''Theorizing masculinities'' (pp. 119-141). Newbury Park, CA: Sage&lt;/ref&gt; The gay-bashing of boys seen as eccentric (and who are not usually homosexual) is claimed to be endemic in rural and suburban American schools, and has been associated with risk-taking behavior and outbursts of violence (such as a spate of fatal school shootings) by boys seeking revenge or trying to assert their masculinity.&lt;ref&gt;MICHAEL S. KIMMEL and MATTHEW MAHLER, ''Adolescent Masculinity, Homophobia, and Violence: Random School Shootings, 1982-2001, [[State University of New York at Stony Brook]], in AMERICAN BEHAVIORAL SCIENTIST, Vol. 46 No. 10, June 2003 pp. 1439-1458&lt;/ref&gt;

==Types of homophobia==
Homophobia manifests in different forms, and a number of different types have been postulated, among which social homophobia, emotional homophobia, rationalized homophobia, internalized homophobia, and others. &lt;ref&gt;http://siba2.unile.it/ese/search/details.php?pubcat=&amp;recid=655&amp;recs=10&amp;single_pub=1&amp;pub_type=j&amp;pub_id=6&amp;id=60&amp;n_campo=contents&lt;/ref&gt;


===Internalized homophobia===
''Internalized homophobia'' (or ''ego-dystonic homophobia'') refers to homophobia as a prejudice carried by individuals against homosexual manifestations in themselves and others. It causes severe discomfort with or disapproval of one's own [[sexual orientation]].

Such a situation may cause extreme repression of homosexual desires. In other cases, a conscious internal struggle may occur for some time, often pitting deeply held religious or social beliefs against strong emotional desires and needs. This discordance often causes [[clinical depression]], and the unusually high [[suicide]] rate among homosexual teenagers (up to 30% of non-straight youth attempt suicide) has been attributed to this phenomenon.&lt;ref&gt;[http://66.151.111.132/pp2/portal/files/portal/medicalinfo/sexualhealth/article-sexual-orientation.xml Sexual Orientation and Gender Identity — Discrimination and Conflicts] from [[Planned Parenthood]] website (accessed 23 September 2006)&lt;/ref&gt;

The theory attributing higher incidences of depression, alchoholism and other self-destructive tendencies among homosexually oriented individuals to internalized homophobia has been put into question by groups such as [[NARTH]] that reject the validity of the studies behind the American Psychiatric Association's 1973 removal of homosexuality from the DSM. Studies of homosexuals in societies such as Sweden, New Zealand and the Netherlands where homosexuality is more socially accepted than in the United States found similar incidences of such behavior. A study conducted by the Christchurch School of Medicine and Health in Christchurch, New Zealand followed 1007 individuals since birth. It found that at age 21, the 28 subjects classified as gay, lesbian or bisexual were significantly more likely to have had mental-health problems than the 979 classed as heterosexual. &lt;ref&gt;http://www.chmeds.ac.nz/research/chds/publications/2005/264.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;


The Dutch study found, "Psychiatric disorders were more prevalent among homosexually active people compared with heterosexually active people. Homosexual men had a higher 12-month prevalence of mood disorders (odds ratio [OR] = 2.93; 95% confidence interval [CI] = 1.54-5.57) and anxiety disorders (OR = 2.61; 95% CI = 1.44-4.74) than heterosexual men. Homosexual women had a higher 12-month prevalence of substance use disorders (OR = 4.05; 95% CI = 1.56-10.47) than heterosexual women. Lifetime prevalence rates reflect identical differences, except for mood disorders, which were more frequently observed in homosexual than in heterosexual women (OR = 2.41; 95% CI = 1.26-4.63). The proportion of persons with 1 or more diagnoses differed only between homosexual and heterosexual women (lifetime OR = 2.61; 95% CI = 1.31-5.19). More homosexual than heterosexual persons had 2 or more disorders during their lifetimes (homosexual men: OR = 2.70; 95% CI = 1.66-4.41; homosexual women: OR = 2.09; 95% CI = 1.07-4.09)." 
&lt;ref&gt;"Same-Sex Sexual Behavior and Psychiatric Disorders:Findings From the Netherlands Mental Health Survey and Incidence Study (NEMESIS)" by Theo G. M. Sandfort, PhD; Ron de Graaf, PhD; Rob V. Bijl, PhD; Paul Schnabel, PhD. ''Archives of General Psychiatry'', Vol. 58 No. 1, January 2001, pp. 85-91. [http://archpsyc.ama-assn.org/cgi/content/abstract/58/1/85]&lt;/ref&gt;

J. Michael Bailey, researcher behind the New Zealand study warns a politicization of research into homosexuality has arisen in the name of preventing homophobia. Bailey argues "...it would be a shame if sociopolitical concerns prevented researchers from conscientious consideration of any reasonable hypothesis" regarding homosexuality. [http://www.narth.com/docs/risks.html]

Many people in this situation attempt to resolve it, at least for a period of time, through [[chastity]]. This is an attractive option because many belief systems are neutral or only mildly disapprove of, for example, homosexual feelings, but strongly disapprove of acting on those feelings. Advocates of the [[ex-gay]] movement believe that in addition to behavior, [[sexual orientation]] is a malleable attribute, and advocate attempting to change it (this is highly controversial, and many mental health professionals warn that such therapies have not been proven to be effective, and that they may be psychologically harmful).

The label of internalized homophobia is sometimes applied to conscious or unconscious behaviors which an observer feels the need to promote or conform to the expectations of [[heteronormativity]] or [[heterosexism]]. This might include making assumptions about the gender of a person's romantic partner, or about gender roles. Some also apply this label to LGBT persons who support "compromise" policies, such as those that find civil unions an acceptable alternative to same-sex marriage. Whether this is a tactical judgement call or the result of some kind of internal prejudice (whether in a cause-and-effect fashion, or definitionally) is a matter of some debate.

Some claim (including Sigmund Freud in his [[psychoanalytic theory]]) that some or most homophobics are repressed homosexuals, but this claim is somewhat controversial. In 1996, a controlled study of 64 heterosexual men (half claimed to be homophobic by experience and self-reported orientation) at the University of Georgia &lt;ref&gt;"Is Homophobia Associated With Homosexual Arousal?" by Henry E. Adams, Ph.D., Lester W. Wright, Jr., Ph.D. and Bethany A. Lohr, University of Georgia (Athens), Department of Psychology. ''Journal of Abnormal Psychology'', Vol. 105, No. 3, pp 440-445. [http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=8772014 Abstract] at [[PubMed]]. Summarized in an [[American Psychological Association]] press release, August 1996: "[http://web.archive.org/web/20040202035152/www.apa.org/releases/homophob.html  New Study Links Homophobia with Homosexual Arousal]".&lt;/ref&gt; found that the allegedly homophobic men (as measured by the Index of Homophobia)&lt;ref&gt;Index of Homophobia: W. W. Hudson and W. A. Ricketts, 1980.&lt;/ref&gt; were considerably more likely to experience more erectile responses when exposed to homoerotic images than non-homophobic men. 

However, the homophobic men also tended to report more negative emotions in response to those particular images (not sexual arousal), and the researchers noted that general anxiety has been shown to enhance erectile response. There was no significant difference in results on the ''Aggression Questionnaire''. The group recommended further research.

==Critics of the term==

Some critics of the term homophobia assert that their disapproval of homosexuality or opposition to certain goals of LGBT social movements ought not to be termed '''homophobia''', as they believe they have a moral, philosophical, or religious basis for their disapproval of homosexual sexual orientation.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lifeway.com/lwc/article_main_page/0,1703,A%253D153888%2526M%253D150019,00.html Just What Is 'Homophobia'?]&lt;/ref&gt;

They argue that defining their disapproval or opposition as homophobia is a [[loaded term]] intended to associate such political opposition with bigotry.

==Fear of being identified as a homosexual==
A component considered to play into homophobia, as considered by some theorists, such as [[Calvin Thomas]] and [[Judith Butler]], is an individual's fear of being identified as homosexual him or herself.

This notion suggests that when expressing homophobic viewpoints and emotions, the individual who does so is not only expressing his thoughts as to homosexuals, but also actively attempting to distance himself from this category and attributed social status. Therefore, by distancing him or herself from the people in question, he/she is reaffirming his/her role as a [[heterosexual]], within [[heteronormativity]], and contributing to the avoidance of his/her potential labeling and consequent treatment as a homosexual.

This interpretation plays into notions of violent opposition to "the Other" as a means of establishing one's identity as part of the majority and therefore, validated by society. This concept is also recurrent in interpretations of [[racism]] and [[xenophobia]].

==Homophobia as leading to a climate of prejudice==
Whether viewed as unfounded prejudices or legitimate moral opinions, attitudes frowning on LGBT orientations and lifestyles have been reflected in [[Homosexuality laws of the world|legislation]] and these attitudes have had a profound impact on political debates over [[:Category:LGBT civil rights|LGBT civil rights]] in general.  Some look at people holding negative attitudes about LGBT people and assign blame to them for a creating or perpetuating a climate of prejudice that has resulted in [[Violence against gays, lesbians, bisexuals, and the transgendered|violence against LGBT people]], by individuals, states or other organizations. 

Many social and religious attitudes toward homosexuality are negative, which some might describe as a form of prejudice. See [[Societal attitudes towards homosexuality]] and [[Religion and homosexuality]].

[[Social Psychology|Psychology]] researchers have used measures such as the [[Social Dominance Orientation|Social Dominance Orientation (SDO)]] and [[Right Wing Authoritarianism|Right Wing Authoritarianism (RWA)]] to predict homophobic attitudes. These measures are traditionally used to measure other forms of prejudice. 

===Sexist beliefs===
Some [[gender theorist]]s interpret the fact that male-to-male relationships often incite a stronger reaction in a homophobic person than female-to-female ([[lesbian]]) as meaning that the homophobic person feels threatened by the perceived subversion of the [[gender paradigm]] in male-to-male sexual activity. According to such theorists as D.A. Miller, male heterosexuality is defined not only by the desire for women but also, and more importantly, by the denial of desire for men. Therefore, expressions of homophobia serve as a means of limiting those who they view as displaced in heteronormativity, and also of accenting their male nature, by isolating the threatening concept of their own potential feminity in gay men, and consequently belittling them, as not ''real'' males. They regard the reason male homosexuality is treated worse compared to female homosexuality as [[sexist]] in its underlying belief that men are superior to women and therefore for a man to ''"replace"'' a woman during intercourse with another man is his own subjection to (non-male) inferiority.

However, this view would imply that only the receptive male partner in homosexual acts would be thought of as "offensive", which is the case in many cultures.  Miller's specific claim that male heterosexuality does not require "desire for women" would seem to preclude the possibility of [[asexuality]] or [[bisexuality]]. Nor is it clear why male heterosexuals would "need" or even fear homosexuals in order to affirm maleness &amp;ndash; unless their sexuality was already experienced as threatened by some other cause.

===Opposition to homophobia===
To combat homophobia, the LGBT community uses events such as [[pride parade]]s and [[political activism]] (''See [[gay pride]]).'' Some parts of the festivities are criticized for reinforcing stereotypes about LGBT people (e.g. [[Dykes on Bikes]], the prominence of cross-dressing, a gay male fascination with musicals, the colour [[pink]], a sex-positive atmosphere that may seem to give endorsement to a promiscuous lifestyle which in turn relates to the problem of AIDS, etc). Other portions tend to challenge stereotypes, including the presence of religious organizations who support gay rights and oppose homophobia (''See [[Religion and homosexuality]]''), the families of LGBT people, and LGBT people with children. Much of the colour, glamour, and noise of pride parades can also be seen as a simple celebration of LGBT culture, or of life in general.

One form of organized resistance to homophobia is the ''[http://www.idahomophobia.org/ International Day Against Homophobia (IDAHO)]'', &lt;ref&gt;[http://ilga.org/news_results_b.asp?FileID=329http://ilga.org/news_results_b.asp?FileID=329 "Towards an international Day against Homophobia"], [[April 10]], [[2004]]&lt;/ref&gt; first celebrated May 17, 2005 in related activities in more than 40 countries. &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.emediawire.com/releases/2005/5/emw239185.htm "1st Annual International Day Against Homophobia to be Celebrated in over 40 Countries on May 17"], [[May 12]], [[2005]]&lt;/ref&gt;

Some activists also call homophobia ''straight supremacism,'' equating it to [[white supremacy|white supremacism]]. Anti-gay groups see this as an attempt to marginalize those who disapprove of homosexuality.

Besides public expression, specific laws have been made to oppose homophobia, as in [[hate speech]], [[hate crime]], and laws against [[discrimination]] on the basis of sexual orientation.

Some argue that anti-LGBT prejudice is immoral or unwise above and beyond the effects on that class of people. [[Warren J. Blumenfeld]] argues that this emotion gains a dimension beyond itself, as a tool for extreme far-right conservative and religious groups and as a restricting factor on gender-relations as to the weight associated with performing each role accordingly. Furthermore, Blumenfeld in particular claimed:
:Anti-gay bias causes young people to engage in sexual behaviour earlier in order to prove that they are straight. Anti-gay bias contributed significantly to the spread of the AIDS epidemic. Anti-gay bias inhibits the ability of schools to create effective honest sexual education programs that would save children's lives and prevent STDs. &lt;ref&gt;Blumenfield, Warren J., "''Homophobia: How we all pay the price''" (1992).&lt;/ref&gt;

=="Homophobia" as applied to political figures==
The term "homophobe" has also been used to describe opponents of laws considered favorable to gay rights causes. Opponents of [[same-sex marriage]] legalization, child adoption by same-sex couples, and anti-gay hate crime laws are often accused of homophobia for not supporting this legislation.

The [[Concerned Women for America]], a [[conservatism|conservative]] lobby group, issued a press release following the [[Rick Santorum]] affair because they claimed that
:The Rick Santorum controversy has illuminated a serious problem in the Republican Party: Its leaders seem woefully ill-prepared to defend the pro-family position on homosexuality.

in their advice to "fellow Republicans," they issued several points, including #3:
:expose the deceptive terms, such as "sexual orientation", diversity and "homophobia", which are used by pro-"gay" proponents to confuse the issue and control the debate. This requires nothing but making them define their terms at the start of argument, then focusing the debate on clarifying the definitions and exposing their illogic and hypocrisy.

The press release goes on to say:
:Ask them to identify some examples of non-homophobic opposition to homosexuality. They can't do it because they define all opposition as "homophobic". Do they really believe that disapproval of [[sodomy]]/[[Anal-oral contact|rimming]]/[[fisting]]/[[Sadism and masochism|sadism]] is irrational bigotry? You get the idea. You'll find that this technique derails virtually every pro-"gay" argument because each one relies on deceptive rhetoric.&lt;ref&gt;"[http://www.cwfa.org/articles/3880/CFI/cfreport/ Santorum Crisis Exposes Republican Weakness]", Scott Lively, [[April 30]], [[2003]]&lt;/ref&gt;

Senator Rick Santorum was accused of homophobia by the [[Gay and Lesbian Medical Association]],&lt;ref&gt;"[http://www.sodomylaws.org/santorum/snnews030.htm GLMA Joins LGBT Civil Rights Groups in Condemning Homophobic Remarks by Santorum]", Gay and Lesbian Medical Association, [[April 22]], [[2003]]&lt;/ref&gt; for making a declaration that he believed consenting adults do not have a constitutional right to privacy with respect to sexual acts. Santorum described the ability to regulate homosexual acts as comparable to the states' ability to regulate sexual behaviors such as [[bestiality]], [[pedophilia]] and [[incest]]. (''See [[Santorum controversy]]'')

[[Alan Keyes]] was accused of homophobia by ''[[The Washington Blade]]'' correspondent [[Steve Koval]] in reference to Keyes' comments about Vice President [[Dick Cheney]]'s lesbian daughter when Keyes was running for the U.S. Senate.&lt;ref&gt;"[http://www.washblade.com/blog/index.cfm?blog_id=369 Blade outs Maya Keyes]"&lt;/ref&gt;

The term is likewise controversial when used in incidences such as the death threats made against Kamloops city councillor [[John DeCicco]] for objecting to a [[gay pride]] event. His opposition earned him the label of a "homophobe", with the phrase "Homophobia Die" being written on the door to his business, accompanied by letters expressing sentiments such as "I hope you rot in Hell". &lt;ref&gt;LifeSiteNews - [http://www.lifesite.net/ldn/2006/jun/06061602.html '"Homophobia Die" Scrawled on Door of City Councillor Who Opposed Gay Pride'] accessed 06 July 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

Usage of the term, and the climate it creates, has been alleged to have incited incidents such as the beating of the six-year old son of David Parker after the latter, a Christian, opposed the promotion of same-sex couples in the local elementary school curriculum. &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.traditionalvalues.org/modules.php?sid=2751 David Parker’s Son Beaten Up On Playground]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Excerpts from discussions of the term==
Gay rights supporter [[Scott Bidstrup]], in a personal essay titled ''Homophobia: The Fear Behind The Hatred'', emphasizes the association between prejudice and fear:
:If you look up ''homophobia'' in the dictionary, it will probably tell you that it is the fear of homosexuals. While many would take issue with that definition, it is nevertheless true that in many ways, it really is a fear of homosexuality or at least homosexuals.&lt;ref&gt;Bidstrup, Scott, "''[http://www.bidstrup.com/phobia.htm Homophobia: The Fear Behind The Hatred]''". An essay on the origin and nature of homophobia.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Niclas Berggren]], writing in the ''Independent Gay Forum'', argues that "homophobic" opinions are irrational:
:It is usually not the case, for homophobic persons, that the basis of their attitudes towards homosexuality is rational reasoning, or intellectual argumentation. Such endeavors have, as a rule, been added afterwards, to try to give the homophobia a nicer and more respectable framing. However, these attempts to argue intellectually against homosexuality are utter failures.&lt;ref&gt;Berggren, Niclas, "''[http://www.indegayforum.org/articles/berggren41.html Independent Gay Forum]''".&lt;/ref&gt;

Christian commentator [[Gregory Koukl]], in a personal essay titled ''[[Heterosexism]]'', objects to the medicalization of a moral position:
:The word homophobia has come to describe any kind of opposition to homosexuality of any sort, but its interesting that part of their ([[homosexuality|homosexuals]]') goal was to shift the emphasis from what many perceived to be a homosexual problem, away from the homosexual activity itself, and towards the attitude people have about homosexuality... They purposely did this to change the focus of the discussion from the morality of their activity and the social appropriateness of their lifestyle to the attitudinal bias of those who would judge them.&lt;ref&gt;Koukl, Gregory,"Stand to Reason" (radio program); [http://www.str.org/free/commentaries/homosexuality/heterose.htm "Heterosexism"].&lt;/ref&gt;

Kelly Boggs, writing for the conservative Christian website Lifeway, identifies "homophobe" as a "pejorative term" and says:
:I have grown weary of being accused of hating someone simply because I disagree with or oppose their behavior. While there are right-wing radicals that despise homosexuals and wish them harm, they represent only a tiny fraction of the conservative constituency. In fact, those who spout hate toward the homosexual community usually aren't overly thrilled with my belief that the God of the Bible loves homosexuals and wants to transform their lives.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lifeway.com/lwc/article_main_page/0,1703,A%253D153888%2526M%253D150019,00.html "Just What Is 'Homophobia'?"], Kelly Boggs&lt;/ref&gt;

==Homophobia in popular culture==
* [[Eminem]]'s lyrics, with their use of slurs (such as "fag") and violent imagery, were referred to as "homophobic" by such groups as [[GLAAD]], which opposed a duet he sang with [[Elton John]] at the 2001 [[Grammy Award]] presentation. &lt;ref&gt;[http://archives.cnn.com/2001/SHOWBIZ/Music/02/12/eminem.elton/ "Eminem and Elton John team up"], CNN, February 12, 2001&lt;/ref&gt;  The British [[gay rights]] activist [[Peter Tatchell]] commented that he could be a repressed homosexual who was seeking to distance himself from The Other.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.petertatchell.net/popmusic/iseminemqueer.htm "Is Eminem Queer?"] undated essay&lt;/ref&gt;

*The [[Guns N' Roses]] song "[[One in a Million]]" contains homophobic lyrics as well as prejudiced lyrics against blacks and immigrants. It used words such as "faggots", described as "spreading some [[AIDS|fuckin' disease]]". The band (mostly their singer, [[Axl Rose]]) were accused of homophobia. Rose denied this, arguing that he was an active fan of gay musicians like [[Freddie Mercury]], [[Elton John]] and [[Rob Halford]], as well as pointing out that his guitarist, [[Slash (musician)|Slash]], was half-black. The song, while not as popular in the US is quite popular in other countries. Rose would play "[[Bohemian Rhapsody]]" with Elton John at the [[Freddie Mercury Tribute Concert]].

* In 2004 the [[reggae]] artist [[Sizzla]] tour was cancelled in the [[United Kingdom]] and [[France]] after protests over his anti-gay lyrics (popularly referred to as "homophobic"), and at one point the [[British government]] considered banning him from entry into the country. &lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/entertainment/music/3977791.stm "Ban threat aborts Sizzla UK tour"], Bishop, Tom, [[November 4]], [[2004]]&lt;/ref&gt;

* In 2001 the Russian pop-band ''Chugunnyi Skorokhod'' ({{lang-ru|"Чугунный Скороход"}}) (literally, "The fast-walker of pig-iron") released a song "Пидоры идут!" (''Pidory idut!'') ("Fags are marching!"). The song is about how it is hard for a straight man to live in a world where gay men rule (particularly, in fields of TV, show business, etc.). It contains lines like "You were born a man - you're trapped! There's no way if you are straight!" "What's going on here and there? They suck each other right in clubs!" "Any hairdresser or stylist must be a homosexual! How can a straight man work, if gay men want him immediately?" "Try to make children with a faggot! You may try even for several days - there will be no children! The idea is corrupt, but you'll become a fag for sure!" The reaction in Russian society was mixed: while some gay magazines and web sites accused the authors of [[fascism]], many people accepted it quite warmly and some even viewed it as satire.

* Jamaican [[reggae]] artist [[Buju Banton]] has been openly criticized for the homophobic content featured in his rap lyrics. The song "Boom Bye Bye" includes lyrics inciting the murder of homosexuals, ("Batty boy get up and run, ah gunshot in ah head man"). Homosexuality is illegal under Jamaican law, and frequently carries prison sentences of up to ten years (''see [[LGBT rights in Jamaica]]'').

* [[Homer's Phobia]] a [[List of The Simpsons episodes#Season 8 (1996-1997)|season eight]] episode of The ''[[The Simpsons]]'' depicts [[Homer Simpson|Homer]] as a homophobic. At the end of the episode, however, he does renounce these views when his life is saved by a homosexual. The episode title itself is a word play of the word [[homophobia]].

==References==
&lt;references /&gt;

==See also==
{{gay rights}}
*[[Allophilia]]
*[[Biphobia]]
*''[[Family values]]''
*[[Glossary of sexual slurs]]
*[[Heterophobia]]
*[[Heterosexism]]
*[[Homonegativity]]
*[[Homosexuality and religion]]
*[[National Day Against Homophobia]]
*[[Sexualism]]
*[[Slogans of anti-gay ideology]]
*[[Violence against gays, lesbians, bisexuals, and the transgendered]]

== External links ==
* [http://en.wikiquote.org/wiki/Homophobia Wikiquote - Quotes about Homophobia]
* [http://www.religioustolerance.org/hom_phob.htm Meanings of the word Homophobia]
* [http://www.glaad.org/media/archive_detail.php?id=142 GLAAD site: Nationwide Responses to Senator Lott's Homophobic Remarks]
* [http://rci.rutgers.edu/~lcrew/pubd/homophobicimagination.html The Homophobic Imagination]
*[http://rockway.alliant.edu The Rockway Institute] for [[LGBT]] research in the public interest at [[Alliant International University]]

[[Category:NPOV disputes|Homophobia]]
[[Category:NPOV disputes from August 2006]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Neologisms]]
[[Category:Pejorative political terms]]
[[Category:Phobias]]
[[Category:Prejudices]]
[[Category:Sexual orientation and society]]

[[ar:رهاب المثلية]]
[[br:Homofobiezh]]
[[bg:Хомофобия]]
[[da:Homofobi]]
[[de:Heterosexismus]]
[[el:Ομοφοβία]]
[[es:Homofobia]]
[[fr:Homophobie]]
[[hr:Homofobija]]
[[it:Omofobia]]
[[he:הומופוביה]]
[[ka:ჰომოფობია]]
[[hu:Homofóbia]]
[[mk:Хомофобија]]
[[nl:Homofobie]]
[[ja:ホモフォビア]]
[[no:Homofobi]]
[[pl:Homofobia]]
[[pt:Homofobia]]
[[ro:Homofobie]]
[[ru:Гомофобия]]
[[fi:Homofobia]]
[[sv:Homofobi]]
[[tr:Homofobi]]
[[zh:同性恋恐惧症]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>