<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20081114210151|251839232" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="5097395" pageid="5097395" ns="0" title="Homophobia"><revisions><rev timestamp="2008-11-14T21:38:02Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Discrimination sidebar}}

'''Homophobia''' (from [[ancient Greek|Greek]] ''homós'': one and the same; ''phóbos'': fear, [[phobia]]) is an irrational fear of, aversion to, or discrimination against  [[homosexuality]].&lt;ref name=Webster&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.webster.com/dictionary/homophobia|title=webster.com|accessdate=2008-01-29|date=2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=dictionary.com&gt;{{cite web|url=http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/homophobia homophobial|title=Dictonary.com|accessdate=2008-01-29|date=2008|publisher=Dictonary.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=aol.com&gt;{{cite web|url=http://reference.aol.com/dictionary?dword=homophobia&amp;lookupbtn=Look+Up|title=aol.com|accessdate=2008-01-29|date=2008|publisher=aol.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some definitions lack the "irrational" component.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bartleby.com/61/90/H0259000.html The American Heritage Dictionary of the English Language: Fourth Edition.]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://oed.com/ The Oxford English Dictionary Online]&lt;/ref&gt; '''Homophobic''' is the [[adjective]] form of this term used to describe the qualities of these characteristics, while '''homophobe''' is the [[noun]] form given as a title to individuals labeled with homophobic characteristics.  
''Homophobia'' was first used with its modern meaning in [[1972]].  It has been criticized as a [[pejorative]] against those with differing debatable value positions, with several researchers proposing alternative words to describe prejudice and discrimination against gays and [[lesbian]]s.  The term "internalized homophobia" is used to describe a prejudice against one's own homosexuality.  

Sources of [[LGBT]]-based discrimination have been widely studied, and a focus of the LGBT community has been on countering such discrimination.

== Etymology and usage ==

[[Psychology|Psychologist]] and [[gay rights|gay activist]] [[George Weinberg (psychologist)|George Weinberg]] coined the term ''homophobia'' in his 1972 book ''Society and the Healthy Homosexual'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Weinberg|first=George|authorlink=George Weinberg (psychologist)|George Weinberg |title=Society and the Healthy Homosexual|year=1972|publisher=St. Martin's|location=New York|isbn=0901072168}}&lt;/ref&gt; published one year before the [[American Psychiatric Association]] voted to remove homosexuality from its list of [[mental disorder]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |title=Recalling APA's Historic Step |url=http://www.psych.org/pnews/00-09-01/recalling.html |first=Alfred M |last=Freedman |periodical=[[APA News]] |date=[[2000-09-01]] |accessdate=[[2007-05-04]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Weinberg's term became an important tool for gay and lesbian activists, advocates, and their allies.&lt;ref name="herek"&gt;{{cite journal |last=Herek|first=Gregory M.|year=2004|month=April|title=Beyond "Homophobia": Thinking About Sexual Prejudice
and Stigma in the Twenty-First Century|journal=Sexuality Research &amp; Social Policy|volume=1|issue=2|pages=2&amp;ndash;24|doi=10.1525/srsp.2004.1.2.6|accessdate=2007-09-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;  He describes the concept as a medical [[phobia]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Weinberg|first=George|authorlink=George Weinberg (psychologist)|George Weinberg |title=Society and the Healthy Homosexual|year=1972|publisher=St. Martin's|location=New York|isbn=0901072168}}&lt;/ref&gt;:

&lt;blockquote&gt;a phobia about homosexuals….It was a fear of homosexuals which seemed to be associated with a fear of contagion, a fear of reducing the things one fought for &amp;mdash; home and family. It was a religious fear and it had led to great brutality as fear always does.&lt;ref name="herek" /&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Conceptualizing prejudice against gays and lesbians as a social problem worthy of scholarly attention was not new, but Weinberg was the first to give it a name.&lt;ref name="herek" /&gt;

The construction of the word is comparable to [[xenophobia]], a much older term referring to individual or cultural hostility to foreigners or outsiders. It fails to make sense [[etymology|etymologically]], however, as the [[Greek language|Greek]] 'homo' means 'the same', so, literally, 'homophobia' means a fear of things that are the same.&lt;ref name="herek" /&gt; The word ''homophobia'' was also used early in the 20th century, albeit rarely. It then had the meaning of "fear or hatred of the male sex or humankind."  In this use, the word derived from the [[Latin]] root ''homo'' (Latin, "man" or "human") with the Greek ending [[-phobia]] ("fear").&lt;ref&gt;Oxford Shorter English Dictionary, 2002&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite its general shortcomings etymologically, the word can be used to describe the fear of a [[heterosexual]] that they will be approached romantically by someone of the same sex. It also can describe the apparently fear-based reactions of recoiling from unintentional close contact with another male or of being in close proximity to other males in certain situations such as while in the [[restroom]]. These are typically fear-based reactions, but the fear is usually that of the [[social stigma]] of being labelled homosexual. 

The word first appeared in print in an article written for the [[May 23]], [[1969]] edition of the American [[tabloid]] ''[[Screw magazine|Screw]]'', using the word to refer to straight men's fear that others might think they are gay.&lt;ref name="herek" /&gt; A possible etymological precursor was ''homoerotophobia'', coined by [[Wainwright Churchill]] in ''Homosexual Behavior Among Males'' in [[1967]].

It was first formally used in its modern sense in the press in [[1981]], when the ''[[The New York Times]]'' reported a [[General Synod]] vote where they refused to condemn homosexuality.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite newspaper|publisher=The Times|title=Homosexuality best seen as a handicap, Dr Runcie says|date=1981-2-28|author=Clifford Longley|quote=Let us recognize where the problem lies - in the dislike and distaste felt by many heterosexuals for homosexuals, a problem we have come to call ''homophobia''.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Criticism of the term ==

The term homophobia is often used collectively with other terms denoting bigotry and discrimination. In a 1998 address, [[Coretta Scott King]] asserted that, "Homophobia is like [[racism]] and [[anti-Semitism]] and other forms of bigotry in that it seeks to dehumanize a large group of people, to deny their humanity, their dignity and personhood." &lt;ref&gt; Chicago Defender, April 1, 1998, front page &lt;/ref&gt; Likewise, [[George Yancey]], writing in ''Christian Ethics Today'' associates "[[sexism]], racism, class distinctions, or homophobia" with one another and views them all as "varieties of discrimination," although he argues that they are not identical.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.christianethicstoday.com/Issue/040/Is%20Homophobia%20The%20Same%20As%20Racism-Sexism%20By%20George%20Yancey_040__.htm  Is Homophobia The Same As Racism/Sexism? By George Yancey, Assistant Professor]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1993, [[behavioral science|behavioral scientists]] William O'Donohue and Christine Caselles concluded that the usage of the term "as it is usually used, makes an illegitimately pejorative evaluation of certain open and debatable value positions, much like the former disease construct of homosexuality" itself, arguing that the term may be used as an ''[[ad hominem]]'' argument against those who advocate values or positions of which the speaker does not approve.  The [[social construct]] of [[masculinity]] is not defined by attraction to females alone but also by negative attraction to males. The addition of a fear of something unmasculine, given the terms scientific etymology, may be used illegitimately to imply that anyone with a different opinion is unmasculine. &lt;ref&gt;O'Donohue, William and Christine Caselles (September 1993). [http://www.springerlink.com/content/n0264m864t146585/ Homophobia: Conceptual, definitional, and value issues]. ''Journal of Psychopathology and Behavioral Assessment,'' 15 no. 3.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[National Association for Research &amp; Therapy of Homosexuality]], an organization affiliated with the [[ex-gay]] movement, describes the term homophobia as being "often used inaccurately to describe any person who objects to homosexual behavior on either moral, psychological or medical grounds." They claim that, "Technically, however, the terms actually denotes a person who has a phobia &amp;mdash; or irrational fear &amp;mdash; of homosexuality.  Principled disagreement, therefore, cannot be labeled 'homophobia.'"&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.narth.com/menus/positionstatements.html NARTH Position Statements,] [[National Association for Research &amp; Therapy of Homosexuality]], 27 February 2008 (accessed November 13, 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

Some researchers within the field have preferred other terms to "homophobia." For example, 
[[Gregory M. Herek]], a researcher at the [[University of California, Davis]], compared several related terms: "homophobia", "[[heterosexism]]", and "sexual prejudice". In preferring the latter term, he noted that "homophobia" was "probably more widely used and more often criticized", and observed that "Its critics note that homophobia implicitly suggests that antigay attitudes are best understood as an irrational fear and that they represent a form of individual [[psychopathology]] rather than a socially reinforced prejudice."  He preferred "sexual prejudice" as being descriptive and free of presumptions about motivations, and lacking in value judgments as to the irrationality or immorality of those so labeled.&lt;ref&gt;Herek, Gregory M. (2000). [http://psychology.ucdavis.edu/rainbow/html/Current_Directions_preprint.pdf The psychology of sexual prejudice]. ''Current Directions in Psychological Science, 9''&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1980 Hudson and Ricketts proposed the term "[[homonegativity]]," arguing that "homophobia" was unscientific in its presumption of motivation.&lt;ref&gt;Hudson, W. and Ricketts, W. (1980) A strategy for the measure of homophobia. ''Journal of Homosexuality, 5'', 357–372.&lt;/ref&gt;

Some recent psychological literature suggested the term homonegativity, reflecting the perspective that behaviors and thoughts that are frequently considered homophobic are not fear-based but instead reflect a disapproval of homosexuality.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.teachproject.org/homophobia/ Homophobia | TEACH Project]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.planetout.com/news/article-print.html?2002/06/13/3  Homophobia is a misnomer, according to a group of U.S. psychologists.]&lt;/ref&gt;

Similar terms, such as heterosexism, have been proposed as alternatives that are more [[Morphology (linguistics)|morphologically]] parallel, and which do not have the association with [[phobia]]. Heterosexism refers to the presumption that all people are heterosexual and/or to the privileging of heterosexuality over homosexuality.

Seeking to avoid both the focus on individual [[psychology]] of "homophobia" and the focus on collective cultural factors of "heterosexism", psychologist [[Gregory M. Herek]] has proposed the term "sexual prejudice" as referring to "all negative attitudes based on [[sexual orientation]], whether the target is homosexual, [[bisexual]], or heterosexual."&lt;ref&gt;Herek, G. M. (1990). The context of anti-gay violence: Notes on cultural and psychological heterosexism. Journal of Interpersonal Violence, 5, 316-333&lt;/ref&gt;

== Classification ==
[[Image:BenPhelps.JPG|thumb|Westboro Baptist Church picket signs with Ben Phelps, grandson of Fred Phelps]]

Homophobia manifests in different forms, and a number of different types have been postulated, among which are internalized homophobia, social homophobia, emotional homophobia, rationalized homophobia, and others.&lt;ref&gt;[http://allies.tamu.edu/Did%20You%20Know/riddle.htm The Riddle Homophobia Scale] from Allies Committee website, Department of Student Life, Texas A&amp;M University&lt;/ref&gt; There were also ideas to classify homophobia, racism, and sexism as an ''intolerant [[personality disorder]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Guindon, M.H., Green, A.G. &amp; Hanna, F.J. (2003). [http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sites/entrez?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids=12769238&amp;dopt=AbstractPlus Intolerance and Psychopathology: Toward a General Diagnosis for Racism, Sexism, and Homophobia]. ''American Journal of Orthopsychiatry, 73, 2,'' pp. 167&amp;ndash;176.&lt;/ref&gt;

Homophobia is not mentioned directly in any diseases classifications ([[Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders]] and [[International Statistical Classification of Diseases and Related Health Problems]]). For some, homophobia is a non-clinical term&lt;ref&gt;Paula A. Treichler, ''AIDS, Homophobia, and Biomedical Discourse: An Epidemic of Signification'', October, Vol. 43, AIDS: Cultural Analysis/Cultural Activism (Winter, 1987), pp. 31&amp;ndash;70.&lt;/ref&gt;.

=== Internalized homophobia ===
Internalized homophobia (or [[egodystonic]] homophobia) refers to homophobia as a prejudice carried by individuals against homosexual manifestations in themselves and others.&lt;ref&gt;http://psychology.ucdavis.edu/rainbow/html/JGLMApre.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; It causes severe discomfort with or disapproval of one's own [[sexual orientation]]. Internalized homophobia is thus a form of [[cognitive dissonance]]; the individual cannot reconcile the conflicting conscious or unconscious sexual desires with values and tenets gained from society, religion or upbringing.

Such a situation may cause extreme repression of homosexual desires.&lt;ref&gt;Adams, H.E., Wright, R.W. &amp; Lohr, B.A. (1996). "[http://www.oogachaga.com/downloads/homophobia_and_homosexual_arousal.pdf Is Homophobia Associated With Homosexual Arousal?]", ''Journal of Abnormal Psychology'', 105, no. 3, pp. 440–445.&lt;/ref&gt; In other cases, a conscious internal struggle may occur for some time, often pitting deeply held religious or social beliefs against strong sexual and emotional desires. This discordance often causes [[clinical depression]], and the unusually high [[suicide]] rate among gay teenagers (up to 30 percent of non-heterosexual youth attempt suicide) has been attributed to this phenomenon.&lt;ref&gt;[http://66.151.111.132/pp2/portal/files/portal/medicalinfo/sexualhealth/article-sexual-orientation.xml Sexual Orientation and Gender Identity — Discrimination and Conflicts] from [[Planned Parenthood]]&lt;/ref&gt;

The label of internalized homophobia is sometimes applied to conscious or unconscious behaviors which an observer feels the need to promote or conform to the expectations of [[heteronormativity]] or heterosexism. This can include extreme repression and denial coupled with forced outward displays of heteronormative behavior for the purpose of appearing or attempting to feel "normal" or "accepted". This might also include less overt behavior like making assumptions about the gender of a person's romantic partner, or about [[gender role]]s. Some also apply this label to [[LGBT]] persons who support "compromise" policies, such as those that find [[civil union]]s an acceptable alternative to [[same-sex marriage]]. Whether this is a tactical judgement call or the result of some kind of internal prejudice (whether in a cause-and-effect fashion, or definitionally) is a matter of some debate.

Some argue that some or most homophobes are repressed homosexuals, but this argument is somewhat controversial. In 1996, a controlled study of 64 heterosexual men (half claimed to be homophobic by experience and self-reported orientation) at the [[University of Georgia]] found that men who were found to be homophobic (as measured by the Index of Homophobia)&lt;ref&gt;Index of Homophobia: W. W. Hudson and W. A. Ricketts, 1980.&lt;/ref&gt; were considerably more likely to experience more [[erection|erectile]] responses when exposed to [[homoerotic]] images than non-homophobic men.&lt;ref&gt;"Is Homophobia Associated With Homosexual Arousal?" by Henry E. Adams, Lester W. Wright, Jr. and Bethany A. Lohr, University of Georgia (Athens), Department of Psychology. ''Journal of Abnormal Psychology'', Vol. 105, No. 3, pp 440-445. [http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=8772014 Abstract] at [[PubMed]]. Summarized in an [[American Psychological Association]] press release, August 1996: "[http://web.archive.org/web/20040202035152/www.apa.org/releases/homophob.html  New Study Links Homophobia with Homosexual Arousal]".&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Fear of being identified as gay (social homophobia) ===
Theorists including [[Calvin Thomas (critical theorist)|Calvin Thomas]] and [[Judith Butler]] have suggested that homophobia can be rooted in an individual's fear of being identified as gay.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.answers.com/topic/homophobia&lt;/ref&gt; At least one study indicates that homophobia in men is correlated with insecurity about masculinity.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.livescience.com/health/050802_masculinity.html Masculinity Challenged, Men Prefer War and SUVs]&lt;/ref&gt; 

They have argued that a person who expresses homophobic thoughts and feelings does so not only to communicate their beliefs about the class of gay people, but also to distance themselves from this class and its social status. Thus, by distancing themselves from gay people, they are reaffirming their role as a heterosexual in a [[heteronormative]] culture, thereby attempting to prevent themselves from being labelled and treated as a gay person.

This interpretation alludes to the idea that a person may posit violent opposition to "the Other" as a means of establishing their own identity as part of the majority and thus gaining social validation. This concept is also recurrent in interpretations of [[racism]] and [[xenophobia]].

Nancy J. Chodorow states that homophobia can be viewed as a method of protection of male masculinity.&lt;ref&gt;Nancy J. Chodorow. [http://www.cyberpsych.org/homophobia/chodorow.htm Statement in a public forum on homophobia by The American Psychoanalytic Foundation, 1999]&lt;/ref&gt;

Various [[psychoanalysis|psychoanalytic]] theories explain homophobia as a threat to an individual's own same-sex impulses, whether those impulses are imminent or merely hypothetical. This threat causes repression, denial or [[reaction formation]].&lt;ref&gt;West, D.J. ''Homosexuality re-examined.'' Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press, 1977. ISBN 0816608121&lt;/ref&gt;

===Anti-bourgeois and anti-Western homophobia===
[[Image:Lenin CL Colour.jpg|thumb|[[Vladimir Lenin]] thought that homosexuals were [[bourgeois]] [[class enemy|class enemies]].]]
Some left-wing thinkers have considered homosexuality a "[[Bourgeoisie|bourgeois]] disease", a right-wing movement or a "Western disease".&lt;ref name="left"&gt;Gay Men and the Sexual History of the Political Left By Gert Hekma, Harry Oosterhuis, James D. Steakley&lt;/ref&gt; According to Gert Hekma, Harry Oosterhuis and James D. Steakley, [[Vladimir Lenin]] considered sexual emancipation to be typical of [[Capitalism|capitalist]] societies and a symptom of bourgeois degeneracy."&lt;ref&gt;Hekma, Oosterhuis and Steakley (1995). p. 23. The authors also cite: Fannina W. Halle, ''Women in Soviet Russia'', translated by Margaret M. Green (New Yoork, Viking, 1933). pp. 112-114&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[North Korea]]n government condemns homosexuality as a vice caused by the decadence of capitalist society, and denounces Western [[gay culture]] as promoting consumerism, classism, and promiscuity.&lt;ref&gt;Global Gayz. ''[http://www.globalgayz.com/northkorea-news.html Gay North Korea News &amp; Reports 2005]''.  Retrieved May 5, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; In North Korea, "violating the rules of collective socialist life" can be punished with up to two years imprisonment.&lt;ref&gt;Spartacus International Gay Guide, page 1217. Bruno Gmunder Verlag, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Robert Mugabe]], the leader of [[Zimbabwe]], has waged a violent [[LGBT rights in Zimbabwe|campaign against homosexuals]], arguing that before colonisation, Zimbabweans did not engage in homosexual acts.&lt;ref name="HOMO"&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?vid=ISBN030647770X&amp;id=ezBvVdRnWKsC&amp;pg=PA213&amp;lpg=PA213&amp;ots=6IWk0seKwp&amp;dq=Mugabe+moral+campaign+homosexuality&amp;sig=tzSDUBuYv5c6Y8admBfF-Y-Azbo Page 213] ''Encyclopedia of Sex and Gender: Men and Women in the World's Cultures''&lt;/ref&gt; His first major public condemnation of homosexuality was in August 1995, during the Zimbabwe International Book Fair.&lt;ref name="ZIB"&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?vid=ISBN0773527516&amp;id=LvxMq2hNzm0C&amp;pg=PA180&amp;lpg=PA180&amp;ots=xI8D2NLVGn&amp;dq=Mugabe+moral+campaign+homosexuality&amp;sig=-81GDIVzFqwX10TbJjaRAXlT2TE#PPA180,M1 Page 180] ''Hungochani: The History of a Dissident Sexuality in Southern Africa''&lt;/ref&gt; He told an audience: "If you see people parading themselves as lesbians and gays, arrest them and hand them over to the police!"&lt;ref name="GAYRANT"&gt;[http://www.kaiwright.com/gayzimbabwe_more.php?id=101_0_25_0_M Under African Skies, Part I: 'Totally unacceptable to cultural norms'] Kaiwright.com&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt; In September 1995, Zimbabwe's parliament introduced legislation banning homosexual acts.&lt;ref name="ZIB"/&gt; In 1997, a court found [[Canaan Banana]], Mugabe's predecessor and the first President of Zimbabwe, guilty of 11 counts of sodomy and indecent assault.&lt;ref name="BANANAtrial"&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?vid=ISBN9042016264&amp;id=PFvYzAUheGkC&amp;pg=PA93&amp;lpg=PA93&amp;ots=0hbU6n9tV1&amp;dq=Canaan+Banana+homosexual&amp;sig=2cfQK_-ufIaV-egJ-ob6Wfu2kkQ Page 93] ''Body, Sexuality, and Gender v. 1''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="bananadeath"&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/zimbabwe/article/0,2763,1082496,00.html Canaan Banana, president jailed in sex scandal, dies] ''The Guardian''&lt;/ref&gt;

== Homophobia as leading to a climate of prejudice ==
=== Sexist beliefs ===
{{Unreferencedsection|date=June 2008}}
Some [[gender theorist]]s interpret the fact that male-to-male relationships often incite a stronger reaction in a homophobic person than female-to-female ([[lesbian]]) as meaning that the homophobic person feels threatened by the perceived subversion of the [[gender paradigm]] in male-to-male sexual activity. According to such theorists as D.A. Miller, male heterosexuality is defined not only by the desire for women but also, and more importantly, by the denial of desire for men. Therefore, expressions of homophobia serve as a means of limiting those who they view as displaced in heteronormativity, and also of accenting their male nature, by isolating the threatening concept of their own potential femininity in gay men, and consequently belittling them, as not ''real'' males. They regard the reason male homosexuality is treated worse compared to female homosexuality as [[sexist]] in its underlying belief that men are superior to women and therefore for a man to ''"replace"'' a woman during intercourse with another man is his own subjection to (non-male) inferiority.

However, this view would imply that only the receptive male partner in homosexual acts would be thought of as "offensive", which is the case in many cultures.  Miller's specific claim that male heterosexuality does not require "desire for women" would seem to preclude the possibility of [[asexuality]] or [[bisexuality]]. Nor is it clear why male heterosexuals would "need" or even fear gay people in order to affirm maleness{{ndash}} unless their sexuality was already experienced as threatened by some other cause.

Other theories of the difference in the reactions of homophobes to male-male versus female-female homosexual relationships simply have to do with a common sexual desire. A heterosexual man desires women. For a woman to desire women is thus more understandable than for a man to desire men, as a heterosexual man and homosexual woman share the same desire for women, but a heterosexual man cannot understand or identify with the attraction of one man to another man. Similarly, homosexual men desire men, and thus for a man to desire men is understandable to a woman who has the same desires. Even more simply, same-sex relationships can be more tolerable to members of the opposite sex simply because of the innate attraction of a heterosexual to the opposite sex, and the accompanying modification of emotion.

Lastly, a common sexual fantasy of heterosexual males, rooted in a desire to be virile and attractive to women, and also rooted in the traditional view of women as objects or possessions, is to engage in sex with multiple women. Thus a lesbian relationship can be seen as an opportunity to indulge in such a fantasy, regardless of any conscious realization of its implausibility.

=== Distribution/frequency of attitudes in the UK and US===
{{Expand-section|date=July 2008}}
{{globalize}}
Disapproval of homosexuality and of gay people &lt;!-- I assume?  What specific behaviors or beliefs were being measured by the study cited below? --&gt; is not evenly distributed throughout society, but is more or less pronounced according to age, ethnicity, race, sex, social class, education, partisan identification and religious status. According to UK HIV/AIDS charity [[AVERT]], lack of homosexual feelings or experiences, religious views, and lack of interaction with gay people are strongly associated with such views.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.avert.org/hsexu3.htm Prejudice &amp; Attitudes to Gay Men &amp; Lesbians]&lt;/ref&gt;

One study of white adolescent males conducted at the [[University of Cincinnati]] by Janet Baker has been used to argue that negative feelings towards gay people are also associated with other [[discriminatory]] behaviors. The study claims to have found that hatred of gay people, [[anti-Semitism]] and [[racism]] are "likely companions",&lt;ref&gt;"[http://calbears.findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m1355/is_n10_v85/ai_14936859 Homophobia, racism likely companions, study shows]," ''Jet'', January 10, 1994&lt;/ref&gt; suggesting it is an abuse of power. A study performed in 2007 in the [[UK]] for the charity Stonewall reports that 90 percent of the population support the ban on discrimination against gays and lesbians.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/gayrights/story/0,,2086335,00.html |title=Majority support gay equality rights, poll finds|date=[[2007-05-23]]|publisher=''Guardian''}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Social institutions can perpetuate homophobic attitudes. Such institutional sources in the [[black community]] include:
* Music and [[music video]]s&lt;ref&gt;After Elton: Because visibility matters, by Robert Urban, June 1, 2006 "Taking the Homophobia Out of Hip-Hop: A Progress Report" http://www.afterelton.com/archive/elton/music/2006/6/hiphop.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;"Beyond Beats and Rhymes" http://www.pbs.org/independentlens/hiphop/&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;"Issue Brief: Gender Violence and Homophobia" http://www.itvs.org/outreach/hiphop/resources/brief_gender.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
	
* Churches &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2006/01/21/national/21church.html Black Churches' Attitudes Toward Gay Parishioners Is Discussed at Conference - New York Times&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;"Obama takes on the black community's homophobia" http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2008/01/25/obama-takes-on-the-black-_n_83234.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.operationrebirth.com/ black gay christian church and homosexuality OPERATION: REBIRTH&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

Sources of homophobia in the white community include:
* Churches.  Pastor [[John Hagee]] said in 2006, "I believe that [[New Orleans]] had a level of [[sin]] that was offensive to God, and they were recipients of the judgment of God for that.   The newspaper carried the story in our local area, that was not carried nationally, that there was to be a [[gay rights parade|homosexual parade]] there on the Monday that the [[Hurricane Katrina|Katrina]] came."&lt;ref&gt;"Some hateful, radical ministers -- white evangelicals -- are acceptable" http://www.salon.com/opinion/greenwald/2008/02/28/hagee/index.html&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt;"ABC repeatedly noted controversial comments by Obama's "allies," but has yet to report comments by McCain endorsers" http://mediamatters.org/items/200803140013&lt;/ref&gt; This view was echoed by [[Fred Phelps]] and the [[Westboro Baptist Church]], who promote the view that virtually all wars and natural disasters affecting America are God's punishment for tolerating homosexuality.

Professional [[sports]] in many countries involves homophobic expressions by star athletes and by fans.  Examples in the United States include:
* Hockey fans. The homophobic chants and attitudes of certain fans, for example the labelling of one fan who frequently dances at games as "Homo Larry", have been protested by attendees of [[New York Rangers]] games and by [[New York City Council]] Speaker [[Christine Quinn]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2008/03/21/sports/hockey/21fans.html?em&amp;ex=1206244800&amp;en=5c641ada05d2c0a8&amp;ei=5087%0A When Tradition and Taunts Collide: Gay Hockey Fans Criticize Garden - New York Times&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Basketball players. All-Star [[National Basketball Association]] player [[Tim Hardaway]] drew criticism after he said on the "790 the Ticket" radio show, "Well, you know, I hate gay people. I let it be known I don’t like gay people. I don’t like to be around gay people. I’m homophobic. I don’t like it, it shouldn’t be in the world, in the United States, I don’t like it.”&lt;ref&gt;"Love and Basketball: Homophobia in Sports" http://blackademics.org/2007/02/18/love-and-basketball-homophobia-in-sports/&lt;/ref&gt;

The anxiety of heterosexual individuals that others may identify them as gay, particularly among adolescents whose construction of heterosexual masculinity is factored in part on not being seen as gay,&lt;ref&gt;Epstein, D. (1995). "Keeping them in their place: Hetero/sexist harassment, gender and the enforcement of heterosexuality." In J. Holland&amp;L. Adkins (Eds.), ''Sex, sensibility and the gendered body''. London: Macmillan.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Herek, G. (Ed.). (1998). Stigma and sexual orientation: Understanding prejudice against lesbians,
gay men and bisexuals. Newbury Park, CA: Sage.&lt;/ref&gt; has also been identified by [[Michael Kimmel]] as an example of homophobia.&lt;ref&gt;Kimmel, M. (1994). Masculinity as homophobia: Fear, shame and silence in the construction of gender identity. In H. Brod &amp; M. Kaufman (Eds.), ''Theorizing masculinities'' (pp. 119&amp;ndash;141). Newbury Park, CA: Sage&lt;/ref&gt; The taunting of boys seen as eccentric (and who are not usually gay) is claimed to be endemic in rural and [[suburb]]an American schools, and has been associated with risk-taking behavior and outbursts of violence (such as a spate of [[school shooting]]s) by boys seeking revenge or trying to assert their masculinity.&lt;ref&gt;Michael S. Kimmel and Matthew Mahler, "Adolescent Masculinity, Homophobia, and Violence: Random School Shootings", 1982&amp;ndash;2001, [[State University of New York at Stony Brook]], in ''American Behavioral Scientist'', Vol. 46 No. 10, June 2003 pp. 1439&amp;ndash;1458&lt;/ref&gt;

In the United States, attitudes about homosexuals may vary on the basis of partisan identification. [[U.S. Republican Party|Republicans]] are far more likely than [[U.S. Democratic Party|Democrats]] to have negative attitudes about gays and lesbians, according to surveys conducted by the [[National Election Studies]] in 2000 through 2004.
  
The disparity is shown in the graph, below, which is from a book published in 2008 by Joseph Fried. It should be noted that the tendency of Republicans to view gays and lesbians negatively could be based on homophobia, religious beliefs, or [[conservatism]] with respect to the traditional family.&lt;ref&gt;Fried, Joseph, ''Democrats and Republicans - Rhetoric and Reality'' (New York: Algora Publishing, 2008), 185.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Image:Fig. 148 - How do you feel about gays and lesbians.JPG|thumb|375px|left]]

===Combating homophobia===
[[Image:SOS Homophobie.JPG|thumb|An anti-homophobia protester at a demonstration in Paris, in 2005]]
To combat homophobia, the LGBT community uses events such as [[gay pride parade]]s and [[political activism]] (''See [[gay pride]]).'' This is criticized by some as counter-productive though, as gay pride parades showcase what could be seen as more "extreme" sexuality; fetish-based, and gender-variant aspects of LGBT culture. One form of organized resistance to homophobia is the [[International Day Against Homophobia]] (or IDAHO),&lt;ref&gt;"[http://ilga.org/news_results_b.asp?FileID=329 Towards an international Day against Homophobia]", [[April 10]], [[2004]]&lt;/ref&gt; first celebrated May 17, 2005 in related activities in more than 40 countries.&lt;ref&gt;"[http://www.emediawire.com/releases/2005/5/emw239185.htm 1st Annual International Day Against Homophobia to be Celebrated in over 40 Countries on May 17]", [[May 12]], [[2005]]&lt;/ref&gt;

In addition to public expression, legislation has been designed, controversially, to oppose homophobia, as in [[hate speech]], [[hate crime]], and laws against [[discrimination]] on the basis of sexual orientation.

Some argue that anti-LGBT prejudice is immoral and goes above and beyond the effects on that class of people. Warren J. Blumenfeld argues that this emotion gains a dimension beyond itself, as a tool for extreme right-wing conservatives and fundamentalist religious groups and as a restricting factor on gender-relations as to the weight associated with performing each role accordingly.&lt;ref&gt;Blumenfield, Warren J., "''Homophobia: How we all pay the price''" (1992).&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, Blumenfeld in particular claimed:
:''Anti-gay bias causes young people to engage in sexual behavior earlier in order to prove that they are straight. Anti-gay bias contributed significantly to the spread of the AIDS epidemic. Anti-gay bias prevents the ability of schools to create effective honest sexual education programs that would save children's lives and prevent [[Sexually transmitted disease|STD]]s.''

== See also ==

* [[Allophilia]]
* [[Biphobia]]
* [[Faggot (slang)]]
* [[Heterophobia]]
* [[Matthew Shepard]]
* [[Heterosexism]]
* [[Homosexual panic]]
* [[Lesbophobia]]
* [[Sissyphobia: Gay Men and Effeminate Behavior]]
* [[Iris Robinson]]

== References ==
{{reflist|2}}

== External links ==
{{commons}}
{{wikiquote}}
{{wiktionarypar|Homophobia}}

* [http://psychology.ucdavis.edu/rainbow/html/sexual_prejudice.html Sexual Prejudice: Understanding Homophobia and Heterosexism] 
* [http://rci.rutgers.edu/~lcrew/pubd/homophobicimagination.html ''The Homophobic Imagination''] - an essay by Rictor Norton and Louie Crew
* [http://rockway.alliant.edu The Rockway Institute] for [[LGBT]] research in the public interest at [[Alliant International University]]
* [http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/pages/frontline/shows/assault/etc/quiz.html  PBS] - "Frontline's" homophobia quiz
* [http://www.europarl.europa.eu/sides/getDoc.do?pubRef=-//EP//TEXT+TA+P6-TA-2006-0018+0+DOC+XML+V0//EN European Parliament] - resolution on homophobia in Europe

{{LGBT |culture=yes |rights=yes}}
{{Discrimination}}

[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Homophobia| ]]
[[Category:Hate]]
[[Category:Sexual orientation and society]]
[[Category:Sexual and gender prejudices]]

[[ar:رهاب المثلية]]
[[br:Homofobiezh]]
[[bg:Хомофобия]]
[[ca:Homofòbia]]
[[cs:Homofobie]]
[[cy:Homoffobia]]
[[da:Homofobi]]
[[de:Homophobie]]
[[et:Homofoobia]]
[[el:Ομοφοβία]]
[[es:Homofobia]]
[[fr:Homophobie]]
[[gl:Homofobia]]
[[hr:Homofobija]]
[[it:Omofobia]]
[[he:הומופוביה]]
[[ka:ჰომოფობია]]
[[lt:Homofobija]]
[[hu:Homofóbia]]
[[mk:Хомофобија]]
[[nl:Homofobie]]
[[ja:ホモフォビア]]
[[no:Homofobi]]
[[pl:Homofobia]]
[[pt:Homofobia]]
[[ro:Homofobie]]
[[ru:Гомофобия]]
[[simple:Homophobia]]
[[sk:Homofóbia]]
[[sl:Homofobija]]
[[sr:Хомофобија]]
[[fi:Homofobia]]
[[tr:Homofobi]]
[[zh:同性恋恐惧症]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>