<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20091115133816|325976063" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="5097395" pageid="5097395" ns="0" title="Homophobia"><revisions><rev timestamp="2009-11-15T19:05:41Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{fixbunching|beg}}
{{Discrimination sidebar}}
{{fixbunching|end}}

'''Homophobia''' (from [[ancient Greek|Greek]] ''homós'': one and the same; ''phóbos'': fear, [[phobia]]) is defined as an "irrational fear of, aversion to, or discrimination against [[homosexuality]] or homosexuals",&lt;ref name=Webster&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.webster.com/dictionary/homophobia|title=webster.com|accessdate=2008-01-29|date=2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; or individuals perceived to be homosexual; it is also defined as "unreasoning fear of or antipathy toward homosexuals and homosexuality",&lt;ref name=dictionary.com/&gt; "fear of or contempt for lesbians and gay men",&lt;ref name=dictionary.com/&gt; as well as "behavior based on such a feeling".&lt;ref name=dictionary.com&gt;{{cite web|url=http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/homophobia homophobia|title=Dictonary.com|accessdate=2008-01-29|date=2008|publisher=Dictonary.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; For the European Parliament ''"homophobia can be defined as an irrational fear of and aversion to homosexuality and to lesbian, gay, bisexual and transgender (LGBT) people based on prejudice and similar to racism, xenophobia, anti-semitism and sexism"''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.europarl.europa.eu/sides/getDoc.do?type=TA&amp;reference=P6-TA-2006-0018&amp;format=XML&amp;language=EN "European Parliament resolution on homophobia in Europe"], Texts adopted Wednesday, 18 January 2006 - Strasbourg Final edition- "Homophobia in Europe" at "A" point&lt;/ref&gt; It is defined by behavior (such as discrimination) as well as motivation (such as fear, antipathy or contempt).&lt;ref name=dictionary.com/&gt; '''Homophobic''' is the [[adjective]] form of this term used to describe the qualities of these characteristics, while '''homophobe''' is the [[noun]] form given as a title to individuals labeled with homophobic characteristics. ''Homophobia'' was first used with its modern meaning in 1971, although it was coined in the mid-[[1950s]]. Use of the word has been criticized as [[pejorative]] against those with differing value positions, with several researchers proposing alternative words to describe prejudice and discrimination against [[gay]] and [[lesbian]] people. The term "internalized homophobia" is used to describe a prejudice against one's own homosexuality.

== Etymology and usage ==

Kenneth Smith in 1971 was the first person to use ''homophobia'' as a personality profile to describe the psychological aversion to homosexuality.&lt;ref name=Smith1971 &gt;{{citation |last=Smith |first=Kenneth T |year=1971 |title=Homophobia: a tentative personality profile |journal=Psychological Reports |pages=1091-4 |volume=29.3 |issn=00332941 |oclc=100640283}}&lt;/ref&gt; The use was also adopted by [[Psychology|Psychologist]] and [[gay rights|gay activist]] [[George Weinberg (psychologist)|George Weinberg]] in his 1972 book ''Society and the Healthy Homosexual'',&lt;ref name=Weinberg1972 &gt;{{citation |title=Society and the healthy homosexual |last=Weinberg |first=George |year=1973 |publisher=Garden City, New York Anchor Press Doubleday &amp; Co |isbn=9780385050838 |url=http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/434538701 |origyear=1972 }}&lt;/ref&gt; published one year before the [[American Psychiatric Association]] voted to remove homosexuality from its list of [[mental disorder]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |title=Recalling APA's Historic Step |url=http://www.psych.org/pnews/00-09-01/recalling.html |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20021219211140/http://www.psych.org/pnews/00-09-01/recalling.html |archivedate=2002-12-19 |first=Alfred M |last=Freedman |periodical=[[APA News]] |date=September 01, 2000 |accessdate=2007-05-04 |issn=00332704}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Macionis2005 &gt;{{citation |last1=Macionis |first1=John J. |year=2005 |title=Sociology: a global introduction |first2=Kenneth |last2=Plummer |edition=3 |publisher=Pearson Education |isbn=9780131287464 |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=P4z3GgAgMFYC |page=332 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Weinberg's term became an important tool for gay and lesbian activists, advocates, and their allies.&lt;ref name="herek"&gt;{{cite journal |last=Herek|first=Gregory M.|year=2004|month=April|title=Beyond "Homophobia": Thinking About Sexual Prejudice and Stigma in the Twenty-First Century|journal=Sexuality Research &amp; Social Policy|volume=1|issue=2|pages=6&amp;ndash;24|doi=10.1525/srsp.2004.1.2.6|accessdate=2009-06-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; He describes the concept as a medical [[phobia]]:&lt;ref name=Weinberg1972/&gt;

{{quote|[A] phobia about homosexuals….It was a fear of homosexuals which seemed to be associated with a fear of contagion, a fear of reducing the things one fought for &amp;mdash; home and family. It was a religious fear and it had led to great brutality as fear always does.&lt;ref name="herek" /&gt;}}

Conceptualizing prejudice against people who are gay or lesbian as a [[social issues|social problem]] worthy of scholarly attention was not new, but Weinberg was the first to give it a name.&lt;ref name="herek" /&gt;

The construction of the word is comparable to [[xenophobia]], a much older term referring to individual or cultural hostility to foreigners or outsiders. Tracing the origin of the word to the [[Greek language|Greek]] 'homos'  fails to make sense [[etymology|etymologically]], because 'homo' means 'the same', which would render 'homophobia' to mean a fear of things that are the same.&lt;ref name="herek" /&gt;  Gay historian Boswell criticised the word on this basis, suggesting "homosexophobia" instead.&lt;ref name = BOS1980&gt;{{citation |title=Christianity, social tolerance, and homosexuality: Gay people in Western Europe from the beginning of the Christian era to the fourteenth century |first=John |last=Boswell |publisher=Chicago: University of Chicago Press |year=1980}}&lt;/ref&gt;  This interpretation of etymology has been challenged by arguing that as “homo” is derogatory slang for gay people,&lt;ref name = BOS1993&gt;
{{citation
|first=John
|last=Boswell
  | editor-last = Wolinsky
  | editor-first = M
  | editor2-last = Sherrill
  | editor2-first = K
|contribution=On the use of the term “homo” as a derogatory epithet
|title=Gays and the military: Joseph Steffan versus the United States
|year=1993
|pages=49-55
|publisher=Princeton University Press}}
&lt;/ref&gt;  most people will tend to see the “homo” in homophobia as referring to "homosexuals";&lt;ref name = MACD&gt;{{citation |title=Homophobia: Its roots and meanings |last=MacDonald |first=A.P., Jr. |journal=Homosexual Counseling Journal |volume=3 |issue=1 |year=1976 |pages=23-33}}&lt;/ref&gt; "a reasonable interpretation of homophobia is fear of 'homos,' that is, homosexuals".&lt;ref name = herek/&gt;

The word ''homophobia'' was also used early in the 20th century, albeit rarely. It then had the meaning of "fear or hatred of the male sex or humankind." In this use, the word derived from the [[Latin]] root ''homo'' (Latin, "man" or "human") with the Greek ending [[-phobia]] ("fear").&lt;ref&gt;Oxford Shorter English Dictionary, 2002&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite its general shortcomings etymologically, the word can be used to describe the fear of a [[heterosexual]] that they will be approached romantically by someone of the same sex. It also can describe the apparently fear-based reactions of recoiling from unintentional close contact with another male or of being in close proximity to other males in certain situations such as while in the [[restroom]]. These are typically fear-based reactions, but the fear is usually that of the [[social stigma]] of being labelled homosexual.

The word first appeared in print in an article written for the May 23, 1969, edition of the American [[tabloid]] ''[[Screw magazine|Screw]]'', using the word to refer to straight men's fear that others might think they are gay.&lt;ref name="herek" /&gt; A possible etymological precursor was ''homoerotophobia'', coined by Wainwright Churchill in ''Homosexual Behavior Among Males'' in 1967.

It was first formally used in its modern sense in the press in 1981, when the ''[[The New York Times]]'' reported that the [[General Synod]] of the Church of England voted to refuse to condemn homosexuality.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite newspaper|publisher=The Times|title=Homosexuality best seen as a handicap, Dr Runcie says|date=February 28, 1981|author=Clifford Longley|quote=Let us recognize where the problem lies - in the dislike and distaste felt by many heterosexuals for homosexuals, a problem we have come to call ''homophobia''.|url=http://archive.timesonline.co.uk/tol/viewArticle.arc?articleId=ARCHIVE-The_Times-1981-02-28-02-008&amp;pageId=ARCHIVE-The_Times-1981-02-28-02}} and {{cite news |title=New light on Archbishop of Canterbury's view on homosexuality |last=Gledhill |first=Ruth |date=August 7, 2008 |newspaper=The Times |url=http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/comment/faith/article4474226.ece}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The term homophobia is likened to and used alongside other terms denoting bigotry and discrimination. In a 1998 address, [[Coretta Scott King]] asserted that, "Homophobia is like [[racism]] and [[anti-Semitism]] and other forms of bigotry in that it seeks to dehumanize a large group of people, to deny their humanity, their dignity and personhood."&lt;ref&gt;Chicago Defender, April 1, 1998, front page&lt;/ref&gt; Likewise, [[George Yancey]], writing in ''Christian Ethics Today'' associates "[[sexism]], racism, class distinctions, or homophobia" with one another and views them all as "varieties of discrimination," although he argues that they are not identical.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.christianethicstoday.com/Issue/040/Is%20Homophobia%20The%20Same%20As%20Racism-Sexism%20By%20George%20Yancey_040__.htm Is Homophobia The Same As Racism/Sexism?] By George Yancey, Assistant Professor&lt;/ref&gt;

== Criticism of the term ==

[[Homonegativity]] is based on the term "homonegativism" used by Hudson and Ricketts in a 1980 paper; they coined the term for their research in order to avoid "homophobia", which they regarded as being unscientific in its presumption of motivation.&lt;ref name=Hudson1980 &gt;{{citation |title=A strategy for the measurement of homophobia. |last=Hudson |first=WW |last2=Ricketts |first2=WA |journal=Journal of Homosexuality |pages=357-72 |volume=5(4) |year=1980 |issn=00918369 |oclc=115532547}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other terms, such as heterosexism, have been proposed as alternatives that are more [[morphology (linguistics)|morphologically]] parallel, and which do not have the association with [[phobia]]. Heterosexism refers to the presumption that all people are heterosexual and/or to the privileging of heterosexuality over homosexuality.  [[Gregory M. Herek]], a researcher at the [[University of California, Davis]], compared several related terms: "homophobia", "[[heterosexism]]", and "sexual prejudice". In preferring the third term, he noted that "homophobia" was "probably more widely used and more often criticized", and observed that "Its critics note that homophobia implicitly suggests that antigay attitudes are best understood as an irrational fear and that they represent a form of individual [[psychopathology]] rather than a socially reinforced prejudice." He preferred "sexual prejudice" as being descriptive and free of presumptions about motivations, and lacking in value judgments as to the irrationality or immorality of those so labeled.&lt;ref&gt;Herek, G. M. (1990). The context of [[anti-gay]] violence: Notes on cultural and psychological heterosexism. Journal of Interpersonal Violence, 5, 316-333&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Herek, Gregory M. (2000). [http://psychology.ucdavis.edu/rainbow/html/Current_Directions_preprint.pdf The psychology of sexual prejudice]. ''Current Directions in Psychological Science, 9''&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1993, [[behavioral science|behavioral scientists]] William O'Donohue and Christine Caselles concluded that the usage of the term "as it is usually used, makes an illegitimately pejorative evaluation of certain open and debatable value positions, much like the former disease construct of homosexuality" itself, arguing that the term may be used as an ''[[ad hominem]]'' argument against those who advocate values or positions of which the speaker does not approve. The [[social construct]] of [[masculinity]] is not defined by attraction to females alone but also by negative attraction to males. The addition of a fear of something unmasculine, given the term's scientific etymology, may be used illegitimately to imply that anyone with a different opinion is unmasculine.{{Dubious|date=July 2009}}&lt;!-- The first part makes sense, but the last sentence makes no sense, and it is unclear how this enhances or relates to what came before it--&gt;&lt;ref&gt;O'Donohue, William and Christine Caselles (September 1993). [http://www.springerlink.com/content/n0264m864t146585/ Homophobia: Conceptual, definitional, and value issues]. ''Journal of Psychopathology and Behavioral Assessment,'' 15 no. 3.&lt;/ref&gt;  A group of psychologists from the University of Arkansas conducted research that showed that participants responses were not fear-based but reflected a disapproval of homosexuality that was due to other factors, such as disgust.&lt;ref&gt;[http://dailyheadlines.uark.edu/3240.htm University of Arkansas, Daily Headlines: "Disgust not fear drives homophobia, say UA psychologists" (June 07 2002)]&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[National Association for Research &amp; Therapy of Homosexuality]], an organization affiliated with the [[ex-gay]] movement, describes the term homophobia as being "often used inaccurately to describe any person who objects to homosexual behavior on either moral, psychological or medical grounds." They claim that, "Technically, however, the terms actually denotes a person who has a phobia &amp;mdash; or irrational fear &amp;mdash; of homosexuality. Principled disagreement, therefore, cannot be labeled 'homophobia.'"&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.narth.com/menus/positionstatements.html NARTH Position Statements], [[National Association for Research &amp; Therapy of Homosexuality]], 27 February 2008 . Retrieved November 13, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

Mormons have criticized the use of the term when used to describe people as 'homophobic', as they see this as a slur against those who disagree with homosexuality.&lt;ref&gt;[http://newsroom.lds.org/ldsnewsroom/eng/public-issues/same-gender-attraction Same-Gender Attraction - LDS Newsroom]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Classification ==
{{fixbunching|beg}}
[[Image:2008-09-27 Fagbug in Durham.jpg|thumb|A [[Volkswagen New Beetle|Volkswagen Beetle ("Bug")]] owner in response to ''[[faggot (slang)|fag]]'' [[graffiti]] spray-painted on her car christened it "The [[Fagbug]]" and embarked on a trans-[[United States|American]] [[road trip]] to raise awareness of homophobia and [[LGBT rights]].&lt;ref name=vanity&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.vanityfair.com/online/style/2009/01/fagbug.html#comments |title=The Heartwarming Story of Fagbug |last=Berk |first=Brett |date=January 8, 2009 |publisher=[[Vanity Fair (magazine)|Vanity Fair]]|accessdate=July 1, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=oscar&gt;{{cite web |url=http://blog.newsweek.com/blogs/current/archive/2007/12/19/driven-by-desire-and-her-fag-bug.aspx |title=Driven to Spread Awareness |last=Raymundo |first=Oscar |date=December 19, 2007 |publisher=[[Newsweek]]|accessdate=December 13, 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
{{fixbunching|end}}

Homophobia manifests in different forms, and a number of different types have been postulated, among which are internalized homophobia, social homophobia, emotional homophobia, rationalized homophobia, and others.&lt;ref&gt; [http://web.archive.org/web/20060904125724/http://allies.tamu.edu/Did+You+Know/riddle.htm The Riddle Homophobia Scale] from Allies Committee website, Department of Student Life, Texas A&amp;M University&lt;/ref&gt; There were also ideas to classify homophobia, racism, and sexism as an ''intolerant [[personality disorder]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Guindon, M.H., Green, A.G. &amp; Hanna, F.J. (2003). [http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sites/entrez?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids=12769238&amp;dopt=AbstractPlus Intolerance and Psychopathology: Toward a General Diagnosis for Racism, Sexism, and Homophobia]. ''American Journal of Orthopsychiatry, 73, 2,'' pp. 167&amp;ndash;176.&lt;/ref&gt;

Homophobia is not mentioned directly in any diseases classifications ([[Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders]] and [[International Statistical Classification of Diseases and Related Health Problems]]). For some, homophobia is a non-clinical term.&lt;ref&gt;Paula A. Treichler, ''AIDS, Homophobia, and Biomedical Discourse: An Epidemic of Signification'', October, Vol. 43, AIDS: Cultural Analysis/Cultural Activism (Winter, 1987), pp. 31&amp;ndash;70.  {{OCLC|17873405}}&lt;/ref&gt;

David Hall contrasts homophobia with [[heterosexism]], which he describes as a belief that heterosexuality is better than homosexuality, and deserving of distinct rights and privileges: "A phobia is an irrational fear. When you have a phobia, you either flee what you fear or attack and attempt to destroy what you fear", and cites [[Matthew Shepard]] and [[Lawrence "Larry" King|Lawrence King]] as victims of this. He explains that also, "people who are fired from their jobs for being lesbian, gay, bisexual, or transgender are victims of homophobia." &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.outandequal.org/Allies-At-Work Allies at Work: Creating a Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, and Transgender Inclusive Work Environment | Out &amp; Equal Workplace Advocates&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Internalized homophobia ===
Internalized homophobia (or [[egodystonic]] homophobia) refers to negative feeling towards oneself because of homosexuality.&lt;ref name=apa /&gt;&lt;ref name=Herek1998 &gt;{{citation |last=Herek |first=G M |year=1998 |title=Correlates of Internalized Homophobia in a Community Sample of Lesbians and Gay Men |last2=Cogan |first2=J C |last3=Gillis |first3=J R |last4=Glunt |first4=E K |journal=Journal - Gay And Lesbian Medical Association |pages=17-26 |volume=2.1 |issn=10907173 |oclc=206392016 |url=http://psychology.ucdavis.edu/rainbow/html/JGLMApre.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; This term has been criticized because holding negative attitudes does not necessarily involve a phobia, and the term "internalized stigma" is sometimes used instead.&lt;ref name=apa&gt;[http://www.apa.org/pi/lgbc/publications/therapeutic-response.pdf Appropriate Therapeutic Responses to Sexual Orientation]&lt;/ref&gt;  It causes severe discomfort with or disapproval of one's own [[sexual orientation]]. Internalized homophobia is thus a form of [[cognitive dissonance]]; the individual cannot reconcile the conflicting conscious or unconscious sexual desires with values and tenets gained from society, religion or upbringing.{{Citation needed|date=August 2009}}

Such a situation may cause extreme repression of homosexual desires.&lt;ref&gt;Adams, H.E., Wright, R.W. &amp; Lohr, B.A. (1996). "[http://web.archive.org/web/20080307094411/http://www.oogachaga.com/downloads/homophobia_and_homosexual_arousal.pdf Is Homophobia Associated With Homosexual Arousal?]", ''Journal of Abnormal Psychology'', 105, no. 3, pp. 440–445.&lt;/ref&gt; In other cases, a conscious internal struggle may occur for some time, often pitting deeply held religious or social beliefs against strong sexual and emotional desires. This discordance often causes [[clinical depression]], and the unusually high [[suicide]] rate among gay teenagers (up to 30 percent of non-heterosexual youth attempt suicide) has been attributed to this phenomenon.&lt;ref&gt; [http://66.151.111.132/pp2/portal/files/portal/medicalinfo/sexualhealth/article-sexual-orientation.xml Sexual Orientation and Gender Identity — Discrimination and Conflicts]{{Dead link|date=May 2009}} from [[Planned Parenthood]]&lt;/ref&gt;  Psychotherapy, such as [[gay affirmative psychotherapy]], and participation in a sexual-minority affirming group or an ex-gay group can help resolve the internal conflict between a religious and a sexual identity.&lt;ref name=apa /&gt;

The label of internalized homophobia is sometimes applied to conscious or unconscious behaviors which an observer feels the need to promote or conform to the expectations of [[heteronormativity]] or heterosexism. This can include extreme repression and denial coupled with forced outward displays of heteronormative behavior for the purpose of appearing or attempting to feel "normal" or "accepted". This might also include less overt behavior like making assumptions about the gender of a person's romantic partner, or about [[gender role]]s. Some also apply this label to [[LGBT]] persons who support "compromise" policies, such as those that find [[civil union]]s an acceptable alternative to [[same-sex marriage]]. Whether this is a tactical judgement call or the result of some kind of internal prejudice (whether in a cause-and-effect fashion, or definitionally) is a matter of some debate.{{Citation needed|date=August 2009}}

Some argue that some or most people who are homophobic have repressed their own homosexuality, but this argument is somewhat controversial. In 1996, a controlled study of 64 heterosexual men (half claimed to be homophobic by experience and self-reported orientation) at the [[University of Georgia]] found that men who were found to be homophobic (as measured by the Index of Homophobia)&lt;ref&gt;Index of Homophobia: W. W. Hudson and W. A. Ricketts, 1980.&lt;/ref&gt; were considerably more likely to experience more [[erection|erectile]] responses when exposed to [[homoerotic]] images than non-homophobic men.&lt;ref&gt;"Is Homophobia Associated With Homosexual Arousal?" by Henry E. Adams, Lester W. Wright, Jr. and Bethany A. Lohr, University of Georgia (Athens), Department of Psychology. ''Journal of Abnormal Psychology'', Vol. 105, No. 3, pp 440-445. [http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=8772014 Abstract] at [[PubMed]]. Summarized in an [[American Psychological Association]] press release, August 1996: "[http://web.archive.org/web/20040202035152/www.apa.org/releases/homophob.html New Study Links Homophobia with Homosexual Arousal]".&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Social homophobia ===
[[Image:BenPhelps.JPG|thumb|[[Westboro Baptist Church]] member Ben Phelps, grandson of [[Fred Phelps]]]]
The fear of being identified as gay can be considered as a form of social homophobia. Theorists including [[Calvin Thomas (critical theorist)|Calvin Thomas]] and [[Judith Butler]] have suggested that homophobia can be rooted in an individual's fear of being identified as gay.{{Citation needed|date=August 2009}} Homophobia in men is correlated with insecurity about masculinity.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.livescience.com/health/050802_masculinity.html Masculinity Challenged, Men Prefer War and SUVs]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=PBS&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pbs.org/independentlens/hiphop/gender.htm|title=Homophobia and Hip-Hop|publisher=PBS|accessdate=2009-03-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

They have argued that a person who expresses homophobic thoughts and feelings does so not only to communicate their beliefs about the class of gay people, but also to distance themselves from this class and its social status. Thus, by distancing themselves from gay people, they are reaffirming their role as a heterosexual in a [[heteronormative]] culture, thereby attempting to prevent themselves from being labeled and treated as a gay person.  This interpretation alludes to the idea that a person may posit violent opposition to "the Other" as a means of establishing their own identity as part of the majority and thus gaining social validation. This concept is also recurrent in interpretations of [[racism]] and [[xenophobia]].{{Citation needed|date=August 2009}}

Nancy J. Chodorow states that homophobia can be viewed as a method of protection of male masculinity.&lt;ref&gt;Nancy J. Chodorow. [http://www.cyberpsych.org/homophobia/chodorow.htm Statement in a public forum on homophobia by The American Psychoanalytic Foundation, 1999]&lt;/ref&gt;

Various [[psychoanalysis|psychoanalytic]] theories explain homophobia as a threat to an individual's own same-sex impulses, whether those impulses are imminent or merely hypothetical. This threat causes repression, denial or [[reaction formation]].&lt;ref&gt;West, D.J. ''Homosexuality re-examined.'' Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press, 1977. ISBN 0816608121&lt;/ref&gt;

== Political ideology ==
{{Main|LGBT rights in Russia|LGBT rights in Cuba|LGBT rights in North Korea|LGBT rights in Zimbabwe}}
{{See also|History of homosexual people in Nazi Germany and the Holocaust|Religion and homosexuality#Religious persecution of homosexuality}}
{{fixbunching|beg}}
[[Image:Joseph Stalin.jpg|thumb|120px|[[Joseph Stalin]] introduced Article 121, which remained in place until 1993.]]
{{fixbunching|end}}
The [[Soviet Union]] under [[Vladimir Lenin]] decriminalized homosexuality in 1922, long before many other European countries. The [[Communist Party of Russia|Russian Communist Party]] effectively legalized no-fault divorce, abortion and homosexuality, when they abolished all the old Tsarist laws and the initial Soviet criminal code kept these liberal sexual policies in place.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |title=Unity and diversity in socialist law |last=Hazard |first=John N |author2=Columbia University. Russian Institute |year=1965 |publisher=[New York] Russian Institute, School of International Affairs, Columbia University |oclc=80991633 }}&lt;/ref&gt; However, some left-wing figures have considered homosexuality a "[[bourgeoisie|bourgeois]] disease", a right-wing movement or a "Western disease".&lt;ref name="left"&gt;{{citation |title=Gay men and the sexual history of the political left |last=Hekma |first=Gert |last2=Oosterhuis |first2=Harry |last3=Steakley |first3=James D |year=1995 |publisher=Harrington Park Press |isbn=9781560230670 |url=http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/32923590 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Lenin's emancipation was reversed a decade later by [[Joseph Stalin]] and homosexuality remained illegal under Article 121 until the [[Boris Yeltsin|Yeltsin]] era.

In China homosexual behavior was outlawed in 1740.  When [[Mao]] came to power, the government thought of homosexuality as "social disgrace or a form of mental illness", and "[d]uring the [[cultural revolution]] (1966 - 76), people who were homosexual faced their worst period of persecution in Chinese history." Despite there being no law in the [[communist]] People's Republic against homosexuality, "police regularly rounded up gays and lesbians." Other laws were used to prosecute homosexual people and they were "charged with hooliganism or disturbing public order."&lt;ref&gt;"History of Chinese homosexuality" (2004-04-01) ''Shanghai Star'' Accessed July 3, 2009. [http://www.chinadaily.com.cn/english/doc/2004-04/01/content_319807.htm]&lt;/ref&gt;

The Communist regime in [[Cuba]] persecuted homosexual people throughout the 1960s and 1970s, but has taken a more tolerant position in recent years.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pinktriangle.org.uk/glh/213/cuba.html Gay and Lesbian Humanist – Gay Rights and Wrongs in Cuba&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[North Korea]]n government condemns Western [[gay culture]] as a vice caused by the decadence of [[capitalism|capitalist society]], and denounces it as promoting [[consumerism]], [[classism]], and promiscuity.&lt;ref&gt;Global Gayz. ''{{cite web |url=http://www.globalgayz.com/northkorea-news.html |title=Gay North Korea News &amp; Reports 2005 |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20051018160332/http://globalgayz.com/northkorea-news.html |archivedate=2005-10-18}}''. Retrieved May 5, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; In North Korea, "violating the rules of collective socialist life" can be punished with up to two years' imprisonment.&lt;ref&gt;Spartacus International Gay Guide, page 1217. Bruno Gmunder Verlag, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; However, according to the North Korean government, "As a country that has embraced science and rationalism, the DPRK recognizes that many individuals are born with homosexuality as a genetic trait and treats them with due respect. Homosexuals in the DPRK have never been subject to repression, as in many capitalist regimes around the world."

[[Robert Mugabe]], the leader of [[Zimbabwe]], has waged a violent [[LGBT rights in Zimbabwe|campaign against people who are homosexual]], arguing that before colonisation, Zimbabweans did not engage in homosexual acts.&lt;ref name="HOMO"&gt;{{citation |title=Encyclopedia of sex and gender : men and women in the world's cultures |last=Ember |first=Carol R |last2=Ember |first2=Melvin |year=2004 |publisher=Kluwer Academic/Plenum Publishers |isbn=9780306477706 |url=http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/54914021 |page=213 }}&lt;/ref&gt; His first major public condemnation of homosexuality was in August 1995, during the Zimbabwe International Book Fair.&lt;ref name="ZIB"&gt; {{citation |title=Hungochani : the history of a dissident sexuality in southern Africa |last=Epprecht |first=Marc |year=2004 |publisher=Montreal |isbn=9780773527515 |url=http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/54905608 |page=180 }}&lt;/ref&gt; He told an audience: "If you see people parading themselves as lesbians and gays, arrest them and hand them over to the police!"&lt;ref name="GAYRANT"&gt; [http://www.kaiwright.com/gayzimbabwe_more.php?id=101_0_25_0_M Under African Skies, Part I: 'Totally unacceptable to cultural norms'] Kaiwright.com&lt;/ref&gt;  In September 1995, Zimbabwe's parliament introduced legislation banning homosexual acts.&lt;ref name="ZIB"/&gt; In 1997, a court found [[Canaan Banana]], Mugabe's predecessor and the first President of Zimbabwe, guilty of 11 counts of sodomy and indecent assault.&lt;ref name="BANANAtrial"&gt;{{citation |last1=Veit-Wild |first1=Flora |year=2005 |title=Body, sexuality, and gender |first2=Dirk |last2=Naguschewski |publisher=Rodopi |isbn=9789042016262 |url=http://books.google.com/books?vid=ISBN9042016264 |page=93 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="bananadeath"&gt; [http://www.guardian.co.uk/zimbabwe/article/0,2763,1082496,00.html Canaan Banana, president jailed in sex scandal, dies] ''The Guardian''&lt;/ref&gt;

== Precursor to a climate of prejudice ==
=== Sexist beliefs ===
{{Unreferenced section|date=June 2008}}
Some [[gender theorist]]s interpret the fact that male-to-male relationships often incite a stronger reaction in homophobic people than female-to-female ([[lesbian]]) as meaning that people who are homophobic feel more threatened by the perceived subversion of the male-superior [[gender paradigm]]. According to such theorists as D.A. Miller, male heterosexuality is defined not only by the desire for women but also (and more importantly) by the denial of desire for men. Therefore, expressions of homophobia serve as a means of accenting their male nature by distancing themselves from the threatening concept of their own potential femininity, and consequently belittling gay men, as not being ''real'' males. According to this theory, the reason male homosexuality is treated worse compared to female homosexuality is [[sexist]] in its underlying belief that men are superior to women and therefore for a man to ''"replace"'' a woman during intercourse with another man necessarily degrades his own masculine status.

Miller's view implies that only the receptive or submissive role in a homosexual act is regarded as [[emasculation|emasculating]], as is the case in many cultures. His specific claim that male heterosexuality does not require a "desire for women" seems to preclude the possibility of [[asexuality]] or [[bisexuality]]. It is not made clear why heterosexual men would "need" to fear gay people in order to affirm maleness{{ndash}} unless they perceived that their sexuality was already threatened by another factor.

Other theories of the difference in homophobic reactions to male-male rather than female-female homosexual relationships simply have to do with a common sexual desire. A heterosexual man desires women. For a woman to desire women is thus more understandable than for a man to desire men, as a heterosexual man and homosexual woman share the same desire for women, but a heterosexual man cannot understand or identify with the attraction of one man to another man. Similarly, homosexual men desire men, and thus for a man to desire men is understandable to a woman who has the same desires.

=== Distribution of attitudes in the UK and US===
{{Expand section|date=July 2008}}
{{Globalize|date=October 2009}}
{{fixbunching|beg}}
[[Image:Fig. 148 - How do you feel about gays and lesbians.JPG|thumb|300px|right]]
{{fixbunching|end}}
Disapproval of homosexuality and of gay people &lt;!-- I assume? What specific behaviors or beliefs were being measured by the study cited below? --&gt; is not evenly distributed throughout society, but is more or less pronounced according to age, ethnicity, geographic location, race, sex, [[social class]], education, partisan identification and religious status. According to UK [[HIV]]/[[AIDS]] charity [[AVERT]], lack of homosexual feelings or experiences, religious views, and lack of interaction with gay people are strongly associated with such views.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.avert.org/hsexu3.htm Prejudice &amp; Attitudes to Gay Men &amp; Lesbians]&lt;/ref&gt;

The anxiety of heterosexual individuals (particularly adolescents whose construction of heterosexual masculinity is based in part on not being seen as gay) that others may identify them as gay&lt;ref&gt;Epstein, D. (1995). "Keeping them in their place: Hetero/sexist harassment, gender and the enforcement of heterosexuality." In J. Holland&amp;L. Adkins (Eds.), ''Sex, sensibility and the gendered body''. London: Macmillan.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Herek1998b &gt;{{citation |last=Herek |first=Gregory M |author2=Society for the Psychological Study of Lesbian and Gay Issues |year=1998 |title=Stigma and sexual orientation : understanding prejudice against lesbians, gay men, and bisexuals |publisher=Sage Publications |series=Psychological perspectives on lesbian and gay issues, v. 4 |isbn=9780803953857 |url=http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/37721264}}&lt;/ref&gt; has also been identified by [[Michael Kimmel]] as an example of homophobia.&lt;ref&gt;Kimmel, M. (1994). Masculinity as homophobia: Fear, shame and silence in the construction of [[gender identity]]. In H. Brod &amp; M. Kaufman (Eds.), ''Theorizing masculinities'' (pp. 119&amp;ndash;141). Newbury Park, CA: Sage&lt;/ref&gt; The taunting of boys seen as eccentric (and who are not usually gay) is claimed to be endemic in rural and [[suburb]]an [[Education in the United States|American schools]], and has been associated with risk-taking behavior and outbursts of violence (such as a spate of [[school shooting]]s) by boys seeking revenge or trying to assert their masculinity.&lt;ref name = Kimmel2003 &gt;{{citation
|last=Kimmel
|first=Michael S
|year=2003
|title=Adolescent Masculinity, Homophobia, and Violence: Random School Shootings, 1982-2001
|last2=Mahler
|first2=Matthew
|publisher=Sage Publications
|journal=American Behavioral Scientist
|pages=1439-1458
|volume=46.10
|issn=00027642
|oclc=437621566
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the United States, attitudes about people who are homosexual may vary on the basis of partisan identification. [[U.S. Republican Party|Republicans]] are far more likely than [[U.S. Democratic Party|Democrats]] to have negative attitudes about people who are gay and lesbian, according to surveys conducted by the [[National Election Studies]] in 2000 through 2004. 

Homophobia also varies by region, statistics show that the [[Southern United States]] has more reports of anti-gay prejudice than any other region in the US.&lt;ref name=APCJ2005&gt;{{citation|last=Lyons|first=P. M., Jr.|last2=Anthony|first2=C. M.|last3=Davis|first3=K. M.|last4=Fernandez|first4=K.|last5=Torres|first5=A. N.|last6=Marcus|first6=D. K.|year=2005|title=Police Judgements of Culpability and Homophobia|journal=Applied Psychology in Criminal Justice|volume=1.1|pages=1-14|url=http://www.apcj.org/journal/index.php?mode=view&amp;item=0}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The disparity is shown in the graph on the right, which is from a book published in 2008 by Joseph Fried. It should be noted that the tendency of Republicans to view gay and lesbian people negatively could be based on homophobia, religious beliefs, or [[conservatism]] with respect to the traditional family.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |title=Democrats and Republicans--rhetoric and reality : comparing the voters in statistics and anecdotes |last=Fried |first=Joseph |year=2008 |publisher=Algora Pub |isbn=0875866050 |url=http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/183179592 |page=185 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

One study of white adolescent males conducted at the [[University of Cincinnati]] by Janet Baker has been used to argue that negative feelings towards gay people are also associated with other [[discriminatory]] behaviors. The study claims to have found that hatred of gay people, [[anti-Semitism]] and [[racism]] are "likely companions",&lt;ref&gt; "[http://calbears.findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m1355/is_n10_v85/ai_14936859 Homophobia, racism likely companions, study shows]," ''Jet'', January 10, 1994&lt;/ref&gt; suggesting it is an abuse of power. A study performed in 2007 in the [[UK]] for the charity Stonewall reports that 90 percent of the population support [[Civil rights|anti-discrimination laws]] protecting gay and lesbian people.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/gayrights/story/0,,2086335,00.html |title=Majority support gay equality rights, poll finds|date=May 23, 2007|publisher=Guardian}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Social institutions can perpetuate homophobic attitudes. Such institutional sources in the [[black community]] include:
* Music and [[music video]]s&lt;ref&gt;After Elton: Because visibility matters, by Robert Urban, June 1, 2006 "Taking the Homophobia Out of Hip-Hop: A Progress Report" [http://www.afterelton.com/archive/elton/music/2006/6/hiphop.html]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;"Beyond Beats and Rhymes" http://www.pbs.org/independentlens/hiphop/&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.itvs.org/outreach/hiphop/resources/brief_gender.pdf "Issue Brief: Gender Violence and Homophobia"]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Churches&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2006/01/21/national/21church.html Black Churches' Attitudes Toward Gay Parishioners Is Discussed at Conference - New York Times&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2008/01/25/obama-takes-on-the-black-_n_83234.html "Obama takes on the black community's homophobia"]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.operationrebirth.com/ black gay christian church and homosexuality OPERATION: REBIRTH&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

Sources of homophobia in the white community include:
* Churches
:Pastor [[John Hagee]] said in 2006, "I believe that [[New Orleans]] had a level of [[sin]] that was offensive to God, and they were recipients of the judgment of God for that. The newspaper carried the story in our local area, that was not carried nationally, that there was to be a [[gay rights parade|homosexual parade]] there on the Monday that the [[Hurricane Katrina|Katrina]] came."&lt;ref&gt;"Some hateful, radical ministers -- white evangelicals -- are acceptable" [http://www.salon.com/opinion/greenwald/2008/02/28/hagee/index.html]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;"ABC repeatedly noted controversial comments by Obama's "allies," but has yet to report comments by McCain endorsers" [http://mediamatters.org/items/200803140013]&lt;/ref&gt; This view was echoed by [[Fred Phelps]] and the [[Westboro Baptist Church]], who promote the view that virtually all wars and natural disasters affecting America are God's punishment for tolerating homosexuality. The parade mentioned above was due to take place in the French Quarter of New Orleans, an area which escaped the terrible effects of Hurricane Katrina.{{Citation needed|date=September 2009}}

Professional [[sports]] in many countries involves homophobic expressions by star athletes and by fans. Examples in the United States include:
* Hockey fans
:The homophobic chants and attitudes of certain fans, for example the labelling of one fan who frequently dances at games as "Homo Larry", have been protested by attendees of [[New York Rangers]] games and by [[New York City Council]] Speaker [[Christine Quinn]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2008/03/21/sports/hockey/21fans.html?em&amp;ex=1206244800&amp;en=5c641ada05d2c0a8&amp;ei=5087%0A When Tradition and Taunts Collide: Gay Hockey Fans Criticize Garden - New York Times&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

* Basketball players
:All-Star [[National Basketball Association]] player [[Tim Hardaway]] drew criticism after he said on the "790 the Ticket" radio show, "Well, you know, I hate gay people. I let it be known I don’t like gay people. I don’t like to be around gay people. I’m homophobic. I don’t like it, it shouldn’t be in the world, in the United States, I don’t like it.”&lt;ref&gt;[http://blackademics.org/2007/02/18/love-and-basketball-homophobia-in-sports/ "Love and Basketball: Homophobia in Sports"]&lt;/ref&gt; 

However, the major professional sports leagues do not advocate homophobia, and regard the LGBT community a very important marketing base.&lt;ref&gt; [http://media.www.duclarion.com/media/storage/paper481/news/2005/04/05/Features/Homophobia.In.Professional.Sports-914733.shtml Homophobia in professional sports] - Features&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gaysports.com/page.cfm?Sectionid=1&amp;typeofsite=storydetail&amp;ID=1067&amp;storyset=yes |title=Gay and lesbian sports site, for sports enthusiasts and athletes worldwide |publisher=Gay Sports |accessdate=2009-08-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20080715145523/http://www.gaybaseballdays.com/ Archive 2008, gaybaseballdays.com]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Combating homophobia==
{{fixbunching|beg}}
[[Image:SOS Homophobie.JPG|thumb|120px|An anti-homophobia protester at a demonstration in Paris, in 2005]]
{{fixbunching|end}}

To combat homophobia, the LGBT community uses events such as [[gay pride parade]]s and [[political activism]] (''See [[gay pride]]).'' This is criticized by some{{Who|date=July 2009}} as counter-productive though, as gay pride parades showcase what could be seen as more "extreme" sexuality: fetish-based and gender-variant aspects of LGBT culture. One form of organized resistance to homophobia is the [[International Day Against Homophobia]] (or IDAHO),&lt;ref&gt; "[http://ilga.org/news_results_b.asp?FileID=329 Towards an international Day against Homophobia]", April 10, 2004&lt;/ref&gt; first celebrated May 17, 2005 in related activities in more than 40 countries.&lt;ref&gt; "[http://www.emediawire.com/releases/2005/5/emw239185.htm 1st Annual International Day Against Homophobia to be Celebrated in over 40 Countries on May 17]", May 12, 2005&lt;/ref&gt; The four largest countries of Latin America (Argentina, Brazil, Mexico and Colombia) developed mass media campaigns against homophobia since 2002.&lt;ref&gt; "{{cite web|publisher=Pan American Health Organization|title=Campaigns against Homophobia in Argentina, Brazil, Colombia, and Mexico	|url=http://new.paho.org/hq/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=346&amp;Itemid=355}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

In addition to public expression, legislation has been designed, controversially, to oppose homophobia, as in [[hate speech]], [[hate crime]], and laws against [[discrimination]] on the basis of sexual orientation.

Some argue that anti-LGBT prejudice is immoral and goes above and beyond the effects on that class of people. Warren J. Blumenfeld argues that this emotion gains a dimension beyond itself, as a tool for extreme right-wing conservatives and fundamentalist religious groups and as a restricting factor on gender-relations as to the weight associated with performing each role accordingly.&lt;ref name=Blumenfeld1992 &gt;{{citation |title=Homophobia : how we all pay the price |last=Blumenfeld |first=Warren J |year=1992 |publisher=Beacon Press |isbn=9780807079195 |url=http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/24544734}}&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, Blumenfeld in particular claimed:

{{quote|Anti-gay bias causes young people to engage in sexual behavior earlier in order to prove that they are straight. Anti-gay bias contributed significantly to the spread of the AIDS epidemic. Anti-gay bias prevents the ability of schools to create effective honest sexual education programs that would save children's lives and prevent [[Sexually transmitted disease|STD]]s.}}

==Contemporary death penalty==

In 2009, [[ILGA]] published a report based on research carried out by Daniel Ottosson at Södertörn University College, Stockholm, Sweden.  This research found that of the 80 countries around the world that continue to consider homosexuality illegal, five carry the [[Capital punishment|death penalty]] for homosexual activity, and two do in some regions of the country.  In the report, this is described as "State sponsored homophobia"&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ilga.org/http://www.ilga.org/statehomophobia/ILGA_State_Sponsored_Homophobia_2009.pdf ILGA: 2009 Report on State Sponsored Homophobia (2009)]{{Dead link|date=October 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;  This happens in [[Muslim|Islamic]] states, or in two cases regions under Islamic authority.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ilga.org/news_results.asp?LanguageID=1&amp;FileID=1111&amp;ZoneID=7&amp;FileCategory=50 ILGA:7 countries still put people to death for same-sex acts]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.religionfacts.com/homosexuality/islam.htm Homosexuality and Islam - ReligionFacts]&lt;/ref&gt;

* Countries that carry the death penalty:&lt;ref name = ILGAMAP/&gt;
** Iran
** Mauritania
** Saudi Arabia
** Sudan
** Yemen

* Countries where death penalty applies in some areas:&lt;ref name = ILGAMAP&gt;[http://www.ilga.org/Statehomophobia/ILGA_map_2009_A4.pdf ILGA: Lesbian and Gay Rights in the World (2009)]&lt;/ref&gt;
** Nigeria
** Somalia

In countries where homosexual activity carries the death penalty, it is enacted under [[Sharia Law]]; under which [[Homosexuality and Islam|Islam forbids homosexuality]], and it is treated as a crime in most [[Muslim world|Islamic countries]]. All major Islamic sects disapprove of homosexuality.  Homosexuality carried the death penalty in [[Afghanistan]] under the [[Taliban]]. The legal situation in the [[United Arab Emirates]] is unclear. In Saudi Arabia, the maximum punishment for homosexuality is public execution, but the government will use other punishments - e.g., fines, jail time, and [[whipping]] - as alternatives, unless it feels that people engaging in homosexual activity are challenging state authority by engaging in [[LGBT social movements]].&lt;ref name=Whitaker2005 &gt;{{cite news |title=Arrests at Saudi ’gay wedding’ |last=Whitaker |first=Brian |date=18 March 2005 |newspaper=The Observer |url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2005/mar/18/saudiarabia.gayrights |quote=Saudi executions are not systematically reported, and officials deny that the death penalty is applied for same-sex activity alone. }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Since the 1979 [[Iranian Revolution|Islamic revolution]] in Iran, the Iranian government has executed more than 4,000 people charged with homosexual acts.&lt;ref name=BBC20050728 &gt;{{cite news |title=Iran ’must stop youth executions’ |author=Steven Eke |date=28 July 2005 |newspaper=BBC News |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/middle_east/4725959.stm |quote=Human Rights Watch calls on Iran to end juvenile executions, after claims that two boys were executed for being gay.}}&lt;/ref&gt; In Afghanistan after the fall of the Taliban, homosexuality went from a capital crime to one that it punished with fines and prison sentence.

Most international [[human rights]] organizations, such as [[Human Rights Watch]] and [[Amnesty International]], condemn laws that make homosexual relations between consenting adults a crime.  Since 1994,  the [[United Nations]] [[Human Rights Committee]] has also ruled that such laws violated the right to privacy guaranteed in the [[Universal Declaration of Human Rights]] and the [[International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights]].  In 2008, the [[Roman Catholic Church]] issued a statement which "urges States to do away with criminal penalties against [homosexual persons]."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/roman_curia/secretariat_state/2008/documents/rc_seg-st_20081218_statement-sexual-orientation_en.html STATEMENT OF THE HOLY SEE DELEGATION AT THE 63rd SESSION OF THE GENERAL ASSEMBLY OF THE UNITED NATIONS ON THE DECLARATION ON HUMAN RIGHTS, SEXUAL ORIENTATION AND GENDER IDENTITY (18 DECEMBER 2008)]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2001, [[Al-Muhajiroun]], an international organization seeking the establishment of a global Islamic [[caliphate]], issued a [[fatwa]] declaring that all members of [[Al-Fatiha Foundation|The Al-Fatiha Foundation]] (which advances the cause of [[gay]], [[lesbian]], and [[transgender]] [[Muslim]]s) were ''[[murtadd]]'', or [[apostates]], and condemning them to death. Because of the threat and coming from conservative societies, many members of the foundation's site still prefer to be anonymous so as to protect their identity while continuing a tradition of secrecy.&lt;ref name=Aldrich2006 &gt;{{citation |last=Aldrich |first=Robert |year=2006 |title=Gay life and culture : a world history |publisher=Universe |isbn=9780789315113 |url=http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/74909268}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''See also: [[Mahmoud Asgari and Ayaz Marhoni]], [[Arsham Parsi]], [[Irshad Manji]]''

==See also==
{{multicol}}
* [[Allophilia]]
* [[Bernardino of Siena#Attacks on sodomy]]
* [[Biphobia]]
* [[Civil Rights Movement]]
* [[Corrective rape]]
* [[Faggot (slang)]]
* [[Hate crimes]]
* [[Heterophobia]]
* [[Heterosexism]]
* [[Homosexual panic]]
* [[Homosexuality and Citizenship in Florida]] (pamphlet)
{{multicol-break}}
{{portalpar|LGBT|Portal LGBT.svg}}
* [[Iris Robinson]]
* [[Lesbophobia]]
* [[LGBT rights opposition]]
* [[Fred Phelps]]
* [[Michael Savage (commentator)|Michael Savage]]
* [[Matthew Shepard]]
* [[Sissyphobia: Gay Men and Effeminate Behavior]]
* [[Transphobia]]
* [[Violence against LGBT people]]
* [[Lavender baiting]]
{{multicol-end}}

== References ==
{{reflist|2}}

== External links ==
{{commons}}
{{wikiquote}}
{{Wiktionary|Homophobia}}
* {{DMOZ|Society/Gay,_Lesbian,_and_Bisexual/Homophobia}}
&lt;!--========================({{No More Links}})============================
    | PLEASE BE CAUTIOUS IN ADDING MORE LINKS TO THIS ARTICLE. WIKIPEDIA  |
    | IS NOT A COLLECTION OF LINKS NOR SHOULD IT BE USED FOR ADVERTISING. |
    |                                                                     |
    |           Excessive or inappropriate links WILL BE DELETED.         |
    | See [[Wikipedia:External links]] &amp; [[Wikipedia:Spam]] for details.  |
    |                                                                     |
    | If there are already plentiful links, please propose additions or   |
    | replacements on this article's discussion page, or submit your link |
    | to the relevant category at the Open Directory Project (dmoz.org)   |
    | and link back to that category using the {{dmoz}} template.         |
    =======================({{No More Links}})=============================--&gt;
* [http://psychology.ucdavis.edu/rainbow/html/sexual_prejudice.html Sexual Prejudice: Understanding Homophobia and Heterosexism] 
* [http://rci.rutgers.edu/~lcrew/pubd/homophobicimagination.html ''The Homophobic Imagination''] - an essay by Rictor Norton and Louie Crew
* [http://rockway.alliant.edu/ The Rockway Institute] for [[LGBT]] research in the public interest at [[Alliant International University]]
* [http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/pages/frontline/shows/assault/etc/quiz.html PBS] - "Frontline's" homophobia quiz
* [http://www.europarl.europa.eu/sides/getDoc.do?pubRef=-//EP//TEXT+TA+P6-TA-2006-0018+0+DOC+XML+V0//EN European Parliament] - resolution on homophobia in Europe
* [http://new.paho.org/hq/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=346&amp;Itemid=355 An analysis of Campaigns against Homophobia in Argentina, Brazil, Colombia, and Mexico]
* [http://www.havanatimes.org/?p=8922 Homophobia Is the Problem, Not Gays-- photos from anti-homophobia event] By Irina Echarry, ''Havana Times'' May 19, 2009
* [http://www.lightapixel.com/Rainbow_Memorial Light a Pixel for the victims of the Tel Aviv Gay Center attack (2009)]

{{LGBT|social=expanded}}
{{Discrimination}}

[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Homophobia| ]]
[[Category:Hate]]
[[Category:Phobias]]
[[Category:Sexual orientation and society]]
[[Category:Sexual and gender prejudices]]

[[ar:رهاب المثلية]]
[[br:Homofobiezh]]
[[bg:Хомофобия]]
[[ca:Homofòbia]]
[[cs:Homofobie]]
[[cy:Homoffobia]]
[[da:Homofobi]]
[[de:Homophobie]]
[[et:Homofoobia]]
[[el:Ομοφοβία]]
[[es:Homofobia]]
[[fa:هوموفوبیا]]
[[fr:Homophobie]]
[[gl:Homofobia]]
[[ko:호모포비아]]
[[hr:Homofobija]]
[[it:Omofobia]]
[[he:הומופוביה]]
[[ka:ჰომოფობია]]
[[lt:Homofobija]]
[[hu:Homofóbia]]
[[mk:Хомофобија]]
[[arz:هوموفوبيا]]
[[nl:Homofobie]]
[[ja:ホモフォビア]]
[[no:Homofobi]]
[[pl:Homofobia]]
[[pt:Homofobia]]
[[ro:Homofobie]]
[[ru:Гомофобия]]
[[simple:Homophobia]]
[[sk:Homofóbia]]
[[sl:Homofobija]]
[[sr:Хомофобија]]
[[sh:Homofobija]]
[[fi:Homofobia]]
[[ta:தற்பால்சேர்க்கை வெறுப்பு]]
[[th:โฮโมโฟเบีย]]
[[tr:Homofobi]]
[[uk:Гомофобія]]
[[vi:Chứng ghê sợ đồng tính luyến ái]]
[[zh:同性恋恐惧症]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>