<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20071112194335|171021432" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="5097395" pageid="5097395" ns="0" title="Homophobia"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-11-14T19:34:30Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[Image:20051129 northlake-il5.jpg|right|thumb|160px|A protest by The [[Westboro Baptist Church]], a group identified by the [[Anti-Defamation League]] as "[[Virulence|virulently]] homophobic."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.adl.org/special_reports/wbc/default.asp Anti-Defamation League on the Westboro Baptist Church]&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.adl.org/special_reports/wbc/wbc_on_gays.asp Anti-homosexual quotes from WBC on ADL's website.]&lt;/ref&gt;]] 
'''Homophobia''' (from [[Greek language|Greek]] ὁμο ''[[homosexuality|homo(sexual)]]'', "same, equal" + φοβία (''[[phobia]]''), "fear") is a non-clinical term&lt;ref&gt;Paula A. Treichler, ''AIDS, Homophobia, and Biomedical Discourse: An Epidemic of Signification'', October, Vol. 43, AIDS: Cultural Analysis/Cultural Activism (Winter, 1987), pp. 31-70.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.psychiatryonline.com/index.aspx&lt;/ref&gt; used to describe the fear of, aversion to, or discrimination against [[homosexuality]] or [[homosexual]]s.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bartleby.com/61/90/H0259000.html The American Heritage® Dictionary of the English Language: Fourth Edition.]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.m-w.com/dictionary/homophobia&lt;/ref&gt; It can also mean [[hatred]], [[hostility]], disapproval of, or [[prejudice]] towards homosexuals, or homosexual behavior or cultures.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.m-w.com/dictionary/homophobia Merriam-Webster Online] and 11th Collegiate Dictionary, 2005, American Heritage Dictionary.&lt;/ref&gt; '''Homophobic''' is the adjective form of this term used to describe the qualities of these characteristics while '''homophobe''' is the noun form given as a title to individuals with "homophobic" characteristics.

Some believe any usage of ''homophobia'' is controversial&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.springerlink.com/content/n0264m864t146585/ William O'Donohue and Christine E. Caselles, "Homophobia: Conceptual, definitional, and value issues," Journal of Psychopathology and Behavioral Assessment (2005).]&lt;/ref&gt; and several dictionaries characterize this type of fear as irrational.&lt;ref&gt;http://mw1.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/homophobia&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/homophobia&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://reference.aol.com/dictionary?dword=homophobia&amp;lookupbtn=Look+Up&lt;/ref&gt; Homophobia in men is correlated with insecurity about masculinity.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.livescience.com/health/050802_masculinity.html Masculinity Challenged, Men Prefer War and SUVs]&lt;/ref&gt; 

== Etymology and usage ==
{{Discrimination2}}
=== Coinage ===

Psychologist [[George Weinberg (psychologist)|George Weinberg]] introduced the first scholarly use of the concept ''homophobia'' in his [[1972 in science|1972]] book ''Society and the Healthy Homosexual'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last= Weinberg|first= George|authorlink= George Weinberg (psychologist)|George Weinberg |title= Society and the Healthy Homosexual|year= 1972|publisher= St. Martin's|location= New York|isbn= 0901072168}}&lt;/ref&gt; published one year before the [[American Psychiatric Association]] voted to remove [[homosexuality]] from its list of mental disorders.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |title=Recalling APA's Historic Step |url=http://www.psych.org/pnews/00-09-01/recalling.html |first=Alfred M |last=Freedman |periodical=[[APA News]] |date=[[2000-09-01]] |accessdate=[[2007-05-04]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Weinberg's "term became an important tool for gay and lesbian activists, advocates, and their allies."&lt;ref name="herek"&gt;{{cite journal |last= Herek|first= Gregory M.|year= 2004|month= April|title= Beyond "Homophobia": Thinking About Sexual Prejudice
and Stigma in the Twenty-First Century|journal= Sexuality Research &amp; Social Policy|volume= 1|issue= 2|pages= 2-24|doi= 10.1525/srsp.2004.1.2.6|accessdate= 2007-09-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;  He describes the concept as:

&lt;blockquote&gt;a phobia about homosexuals….It was a fear of homosexuals which seemed to be associated with a fear of contagion, a fear of reducing the things one fought for—home and family.  It was a religious fear and it had led to great brutality as fear always does.&lt;ref name="herek" /&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Conceptualizing prejudice against gay and lesbian people as a social problem worthy of scholarly attention was not a new concept, but Weinberg was the first to give the problem a name.&lt;ref name="herek" /&gt;

The construction of the word is comparable to ''[[xenophobia]]'', a much older term referring to individual or cultural hostility to foreigners or outsiders.&lt;ref name="herek" /&gt;

The word ''homophobia'' was rarely used early in the twentieth century, and it meant "fear or hatred of the male sex or humankind."  In this use, the word derived from the Latin root ''homo'' (Latin, "man" or "human") with the Greek ending [[-phobia]] ("fear").&lt;ref&gt;Oxford Shorter English Dictionary, 2002&lt;/ref&gt;

The word first appeared in print in an article written for the American ''Screw'' tabloid, May 23, 1969 edition, using the word to refer to straight men's fear that others might think they are gay.&lt;ref name="herek" /&gt;  A possible etymological precursor was ''homoerotophobia'', coined by [[Wainwright Churchill]] in ''Homosexual Behavior Among Males'' in 1967.

=== Similar terms ===

Similar terms such as [[heterosexism]]  have been proposed as alternatives that are more [[Morphology (linguistics)|morphologically]] parallel, and which do not have the association with [[phobia]]. [[Heterosexism]] refers to the privileging of heterosexuality over homosexuality.

Some recent psychological literature suggested the term [[homonegativity]], reflecting the perspective that behaviors and thoughts that are frequently considered homophobic are not fear-based but instead reflect a disapproval of homosexuality.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.teachproject.org/homophobia/ Homophobia | TEACH Project]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.planetout.com/news/article-print.html?2002/06/13/3  Homophobia is a misnomer, according to a group of U.S. psychologists.]&lt;/ref&gt;

Seeking to avoid both the focus on individual psychology of "homophobia" and the focus on collective cultural factors of "heterosexism," psychologist [[Gregory Herek]] has proposed the term "sexual prejudice" as referring to "all negative attitudes based on sexual orientation, whether the target is homosexual, bisexual, or heterosexual."&lt;ref&gt;Herek, G. M. (1990). The context of anti-gay violence: Notes on cultural and psychological heterosexism. Journal of Interpersonal Violence, 5, 316-333&lt;/ref&gt;

The term homophobia is often used collectively with other terms denoting bigotry and discrimination. In a 1998 address, [[Coretta Scott King]] asserted that, "Homophobia is like racism and anti-Semitism and other forms of bigotry in that it seeks to dehumanize a large group of people, to deny their humanity, their dignity and personhood." Likewise, George Yancey, writing in ''Christian Ethics Today'' associates "sexism, racism, class distinctions, or homophobia" with one another and views them all as "varieties of discrimination," although he argues that they are not identical.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.christianethicstoday.com/Issue/040/Is%20Homophobia%20The%20Same%20As%20Racism-Sexism%20By%20George%20Yancey_040__.htm  Is Homophobia The Same As Racism/Sexism? By George Yancey, Assistant Professor]&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Defining Homophobia as 'Irrational' ===

{{sectstub}}
Neither the [[American Heritage Dictionary]] [http://www.bartleby.com/61/90/H0259000.html] nor the [[Oxford English Dictionary]] (OED) include the term "[[irrational]]" in the definition as fear of, aversion to, or discrimination against homosexuality or homosexuals. Footnote 4 of [[Merriam Webster]] dictionary's definition defines homophobia as "irrational fear".

=== Critics of the term ===

Some researchers within the field have preferred other terms to "homophobia." For example, 
[[Gregory M. Herek]], a researcher at the University of California, Davis, compared several related terms: "homophobia," "heterosexism," and "sexual prejudice." In preferring the latter term, he noted that "homophobia" was "probably more widely used and more often criticized," and observed that. "Its critics note that homophobia implicitly suggests that antigay attitudes are best understood as an irrational fear and that they represent a form of individual psychopathology rather than a socially reinforced prejudice."  He preferred "sexual prejudice" as being descriptive and free of presumptions about motivations, and lacking in value judgments as to the irrationality or immorality of those so labeled.&lt;ref&gt;Herek, Gregory M. (2000). [http://psychology.ucdavis.edu/rainbow/html/Current_Directions_preprint.pdf The psychology of sexual prejudice]. ''Current Directions in Psychological Science, 9''&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1980 Hudson and Ricketts proposed the term "[[homonegativity]]," arguing that "homophobia" was unscientific in its presumption of motivation.&lt;ref&gt;Hudson, W. and Ricketts, W. (1980) A strategy for the measure of homophobia. ''Journal of Homosexuality, 5'', 357–372.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1993, behavioral scientists William O'Donohue and Christine Caselles concluded that the usage of the term "as it is usually used, makes an illegitimately pejorative evaluation of certain open and debatable value positions, much like the former disease construct of homosexuality" itself, arguing that both homophobia and homosexuality are social constructions.&lt;ref&gt;O'Donohue, William and Christine Caselles (September 1993). [http://www.springerlink.com/content/n0264m864t146585/ Homophobia: Conceptual, definitional, and value issues]. ''Journal of Psychopathology and Behavioral Assessment,'' 15 no. 3.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Concerned Women for America]], a [[conservatism|conservative]] lobby group, has called homophobia a "deceptive term" which is "used by pro-gay proponents to confuse the issue and control the debate" by defining all opposition to [[homosexuality]] as irrational. CWA asserts that pro-gay proponents would not be able to identify any examples of non-homophobic opposition to homosexuality because they define all opposition as "homophobic" and "irrational bigotry."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cwfa.org/articles/3880/CFI/cfreport/ Santorum Crisis Exposes Republican Weakness]", Scott Lively, [[April 30]], [[2003]]&lt;/ref&gt; CWA calls this "deceptive rhetoric."  The [[National Association for Research &amp; Therapy of Homosexuality]], an organization affiliated with the [[ex-gay]] movement, describes the term homophobia as being "often used inaccurately to describe any person who objects to homosexual behavior on either moral, psychological or medical grounds." They claim that, "Technically, however, the terms actually denotes a person who has a phobia—or irrational fear—of homosexuality. Principled disagreement, therefore, cannot be labeled 'homophobia.'"&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.narth.com/menus/positionstatements.html N.A.R.T.H.]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Classification of homophobia ==

Homophobia manifests in different forms, and a number of different types have been postulated, among which are internalized homophobia, social homophobia, emotional homophobia, rationalized homophobia, and others.&lt;ref&gt;[http://allies.tamu.edu/Did%20You%20Know/riddle.htm The Riddle Homophobia Scale] from Allies Committee website, Department of Student Life, Texas A&amp;M University&lt;/ref&gt; There were also ideas to classify homophobia, racism, and sexism as an ''intolerant [[personality disorder]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Guindon, M.H., Green, A.G. &amp; Hanna, F.J. (2003). [http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sites/entrez?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids=12769238&amp;dopt=AbstractPlus Intolerance and Psychopathology: Toward a General Diagnosis for Racism, Sexism, and Homophobia]. ''American Journal of Orthopsychiatry, 73, 2,'' pp. 167-176.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Internalized homophobia ===

''Internalized homophobia'' (or ''[[ego-dystonic]] homophobia'') refers to homophobia as a prejudice carried by individuals against homosexual manifestations in themselves and others. It causes severe discomfort with or disapproval of one's own [[sexual orientation]].

Such a situation may cause extreme repression of homosexual desires.&lt;ref&gt;Adams, H.E., Wright, R.W. &amp; Lohr, B.A. (1996). [http://www.oogachaga.com/downloads/homophobia_and_homosexual_arousal.pdf Is Homophobia Associated With Homosexual Arousal?] ''Journal of Abnormal Psychology, 105, 3,'' pp. 440-445.&lt;/ref&gt; In other cases, a conscious internal struggle may occur for some time, often pitting deeply held religious or social beliefs against strong sexual and emotional desires. This discordance often causes [[clinical depression]], and the unusually high [[suicide]] rate among gay teenagers (up to 30% of non-heterosexual youth attempt suicide) has been attributed to this phenomenon.&lt;ref&gt;[http://66.151.111.132/pp2/portal/files/portal/medicalinfo/sexualhealth/article-sexual-orientation.xml Sexual Orientation and Gender Identity — Discrimination and Conflicts] from [[Planned Parenthood]] website (accessed 23 September 2006)&lt;/ref&gt;

The theory attributing higher incidences of depression, alcoholism and other self-destructive tendencies among homosexually oriented individuals to internalized homophobia has been put into question by groups such as [[NARTH]] that oppose the American Psychiatric Association's 1973 decision to remove of homosexuality from the DSM. Studies of gay people in societies such as Sweden, New Zealand and the Netherlands found similar incidences of such behavior.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.chmeds.ac.nz/research/chds/publications/2005/264.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;"Same-Sex Sexual Behavior and Psychiatric Disorders:Findings From the Netherlands Mental Health Survey and Incidence Study (NEMESIS)" by Theo G. M. Sandfort, PhD; Ron de Graaf, PhD; Rob V. Bijl, PhD; Paul Schnabel, PhD. ''Archives of General Psychiatry'', Vol. 58 No. 1, January 2001, pp. 85-91. [http://archpsyc.ama-assn.org/cgi/content/abstract/58/1/85]&lt;/ref&gt;

The label of internalized homophobia is sometimes applied to conscious or unconscious behaviors which an observer feels the need to promote or conform to the expectations of [[heteronormativity]] or [[heterosexism]]. This can include extreme repression and denial coupled with forced outward displays of [[heteronormative]] behavior for the purpose of appearing or attempting to feel "normal" or "accepted". This might also include less overt behavior like making assumptions about the gender of a person's romantic partner, or about gender roles. Some also apply this label to LGBT persons who support "compromise" policies, such as those that find civil unions an acceptable alternative to same-sex marriage. Whether this is a tactical judgment call or the result of some kind of internal prejudice (whether in a cause-and-effect fashion, or definitionally) is a matter of some debate.

Some claim that some or most homophobics are repressed homosexuals, but this claim is somewhat controversial. In 1996, a controlled study of 64 heterosexual men (half claimed to be homophobic by experience and self-reported orientation) at the University of Georgia&lt;ref&gt;"Is Homophobia Associated With Homosexual Arousal?" by Henry E. Adams, Ph.D., Lester W. Wright, Jr., Ph.D. and Bethany A. Lohr, University of Georgia (Athens), Department of Psychology. ''Journal of Abnormal Psychology'', Vol. 105, No. 3, pp 440-445. [http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=8772014 Abstract] at [[PubMed]]. Summarized in an [[American Psychological Association]] press release, August 1996: "[http://web.archive.org/web/20040202035152/www.apa.org/releases/homophob.html  New Study Links Homophobia with Homosexual Arousal]".&lt;/ref&gt; found that the allegedly homophobic men (as measured by the Index of Homophobia)&lt;ref&gt;Index of Homophobia: W. W. Hudson and W. A. Ricketts, 1980.&lt;/ref&gt; were considerably more likely to experience more erectile responses when exposed to homoerotic images than non-homophobic men.

== Fear of being identified as gay ==

{{Cleanup|date=September 2007}}
A component considered to play into homophobia, as considered by some theorists, such as [[Calvin Thomas (critical theorist)|Calvin Thomas]] and [[Judith Butler]], is an individual's fear of being identified as gay.

This notion suggests that when expressing homophobic viewpoints and emotions, the individual who does so is not only expressing his thoughts as to gay people, but also actively attempting to distance himself from this category and attributed social status. Therefore, by distancing him or herself from the people in question, he/she is reaffirming his/her role as a [[heterosexual]], within [[heteronormativity]], and contributing to the avoidance of his/her potential labeling and consequent treatment as a gay person.

This interpretation plays into notions of violent opposition to "the Other" as a means of establishing one's identity as part of the majority and therefore, validated by society. This concept is also recurrent in interpretations of [[racism]] and [[xenophobia]].

Nancy J. Chodorow states that homophobia can be viewed as method of protection of male masculinity.&lt;ref&gt;Nancy J. Chodorow. [http://www.cyberpsych.org/homophobia/chodorow.htm Statement in a public forum on homophobia by The American Psychoanalytic Foundation, 1999]&lt;/ref&gt;

Various psychoanalytic theories explain homophobia as a threat to an individual's own same-sex impulses or to a possibility of arising such impulses. This threat causes repression, denial or reaction formation.&lt;ref&gt;West, D.J. ''Homosexuality re-examined.'' Minneapolis: University of Minessota Press, 1977. ISBN 0816608121&lt;/ref&gt;

== Homophobia as leading to a climate of prejudice ==
=== Sexist beliefs ===

Some [[gender theorist]]s interpret the fact that male-to-male relationships often incite a stronger reaction in a homophobic person than female-to-female ([[lesbian]]) as meaning that the homophobic person feels threatened by the perceived subversion of the [[gender paradigm]] in male-to-male sexual activity. According to such theorists as D.A. Miller, male heterosexuality is defined not only by the desire for women but also, and more importantly, by the denial of desire for men. Therefore, expressions of homophobia serve as a means of limiting those who they view as displaced in heteronormativity, and also of accenting their male nature, by isolating the threatening concept of their own potential femininity in gay men, and consequently belittling them, as not ''real'' males. They regard the reason male homosexuality is treated worse compared to female homosexuality as [[sexist]] in its underlying belief that men are superior to women and therefore for a man to ''"replace"'' a woman during intercourse with another man is his own subjection to (non-male) inferiority.

However, this view would imply that only the receptive male partner in homosexual acts would be thought of as "offensive", which is the case in many cultures.  Miller's specific claim that male heterosexuality does not require "desire for women" would seem to preclude the possibility of [[asexuality]] or [[bisexuality]]. Nor is it clear why male heterosexuals would "need" or even fear gay people in order to affirm maleness &amp;ndash; unless their sexuality was already experienced as threatened by some other cause.

=== Distribution/frequency of attitudes in the US and UK ===

Disapproval of homosexuality and of gay people &lt;!-- I assume?  What specific behaviors or beliefs were being measured by the study cited below? --&gt; is not evenly distributed throughout society, but is more or less pronounced according to age, sex, social class, education and religious status. According to UK HIV/AIDS charity [[AVERT]], low educational level and social status, lack of homosexual feelings or experiences, religious views, and lack of interaction with gay people are strongly associated with such views.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.avert.org/hsexu3.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

One study of white adolescent males conducted at the University of Cincinnati by Janet Baker has been used to argue that negative feelings towards gay people are also associated with other [[discriminatory]] behaviors. The study claims to have found that hatred of gay people, [[anti-semitism]] and [[racism]] are "likely companions,"&lt;ref&gt;"[http://calbears.findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m1355/is_n10_v85/ai_14936859 Homophobia, racism likely companions, study shows]," ''Jet'', January 10, 1994&lt;/ref&gt; suggesting it is an abuse of power. &lt;!--  Additionally, there really needs to be an opposing view given to this rather than citing one vague study as uncontested fact --&gt;  A study performed in 2007 in the UK for the charity Stonewall reports that 90% of the population support the ban on discrimination against gays and lesbians.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.guardian.co.uk/gayrights/story/0,,2086335,00.html?gusrc=rss&amp;feed=11&lt;/ref&gt;

The anxiety of non-gay individuals that others may identify them as gay, particularly among adolescents whose construction of heterosexual masculinity is factored in part on not being seen as gay,&lt;ref&gt;Epstein, D. (1995). "Keeping them in their place: Hetero/sexist harassment, gender and the enforcement of heterosexuality." In J. Holland&amp;L. Adkins (Eds.), ''Sex, sensibility and the gendered body.'' London: Macmillan.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Herek, G. (Ed.). (1998). Stigma and sexual orientation: Understanding prejudice against lesbians,
gay men and bisexuals. Newbury Park, CA: Sage.&lt;/ref&gt; has also been identified by [[Michael Kimmel]] as an example of homophobia.&lt;ref&gt;Kimmel, M. (1994). Masculinity as homophobia: Fear, shame and silence in the construction of gender identity. In H. Brod &amp; M. Kaufman (Eds.), ''Theorizing masculinities'' (pp. 119-141). Newbury Park, CA: Sage&lt;/ref&gt; The taunting of boys seen as eccentric (and who are not usually gay) is claimed to be endemic in rural and suburban American schools, and has been associated with risk-taking behavior and outbursts of violence (such as a spate of fatal school shootings) by boys seeking revenge or trying to assert their masculinity.&lt;ref&gt;MICHAEL S. KIMMEL and MATTHEW MAHLER, ''Adolescent Masculinity, Homophobia, and Violence: Random School Shootings, 1982-2001, [[State University of New York at Stony Brook]], in AMERICAN BEHAVIORAL SCIENTIST, Vol. 46 No. 10, June 2003 pp. 1439-1458&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Combating homophobia ===
&lt;!--''This section is unclear: what exactly is being combatted? Prejudice and irrationality, or legitimate moral objections as well?''--&gt;

To combat homophobia, the LGBT community uses events such as [[pride parade]]s and [[political activism]] (''See [[gay pride]]).'' Many of these displays are criticized for reinforcing negative stereotypes about LGBT people (e.g. "dykes on bikes," the prominence of cross-dressing, a gay male fascination with musicals, the color [[pink]], antireligious sentiments). 

One form of organized resistance to homophobia is the [[International Day Against Homophobia]] (or IDAHO),&lt;ref&gt;[http://ilga.org/news_results_b.asp?FileID=329http://ilga.org/news_results_b.asp?FileID=329 "Towards an international Day against Homophobia"], [[April 10]], [[2004]]&lt;/ref&gt; first celebrated May 17, 2005 in related activities in more than 40 countries.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.emediawire.com/releases/2005/5/emw239185.htm "1st Annual International Day Against Homophobia to be Celebrated in over 40 Countries on May 17"], [[May 12]], [[2005]]&lt;/ref&gt;

Besides public expression, legislation has been designed, controversially, to oppose homophobia, as in [[hate speech]], [[hate crime]], and laws against [[discrimination]] on the basis of sexual orientation.

Some argue that anti-LGBT prejudice is immoral and goes above and beyond the effects on that class of people. Warren J. Blumenfeld argues that this emotion gains a dimension beyond itself, as a tool for extreme right-wing conservatives and fundamentalist religious groups and as a restricting factor on gender-relations as to the weight associated with performing each role accordingly.&lt;ref&gt;Blumenfield, Warren J., "''Homophobia: How we all pay the price''" (1992).&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, Blumenfeld in particular claimed:
:Anti-gay bias causes young people to engage in sexual behavior earlier in order to prove that they are straight. Anti-gay bias contributed significantly to the spread of the AIDS epidemic. Anti-gay bias prevents the ability of schools to create effective honest sexual education programs that would save children's lives and prevent STDs.&lt;ref&gt;Blumenfield, Warren J., "''Homophobia: How we all pay the price''" (1992).&lt;/ref&gt;

== References ==

{{reflist|2}}

== See also ==

{{wikiquote}}
{{wiktionary}}

* [[Allophilia]]
* [[Biphobia]]
* [[Gay panic defense]]
* [[Heterophobia]]
* [[Heterosexism]]
* [[Homonegativity]]
* [[Homosexual panic]]
* [[International Day Against Homophobia]]
* [[Latent homosexuality]]
* [[Slogans of anti-gay ideology]]
* [[Sissyphobia: Gay Men and Effeminate Behavior]]
* [[Violence against LGBT people]]

== External links ==

* [http://en.wikiquote.org/wiki/Homophobia Wikiquote - Quotes about Homophobia]
* [http://psychology.ucdavis.edu/rainbow/html/sexual_prejudice.html Sexual Prejudice: Understanding Homophobia and Heterosexism] 
* [http://www.religioustolerance.org/hom_phob.htm Meanings of the word Homophobia]
* [http://www.glaad.org/media/archive_detail.php?id=142 GLAAD site: Nationwide Responses to Senator Lott's Homophobic Remarks]
* [http://rci.rutgers.edu/~lcrew/pubd/homophobicimagination.html The Homophobic Imagination]
*[http://rockway.alliant.edu The Rockway Institute] for [[LGBT]] research in the public interest at [[Alliant International University]]
* [http://starjumps.net/modules/news/article.php?storyid=188 Homophobia in the media]
*[http://www.sod-work.co.uk Interactive guide to UK employment law regarding sexuality and homophobia and what you can do]
*[http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/pages/frontline/shows/assault/etc/quiz.html  PBS' "Frontline's" homophobia quiz]
*[http://www.europarl.europa.eu/sides/getDoc.do?pubRef=-//EP//TEXT+TA+P6-TA-2006-0018+0+DOC+XML+V0//EN European Parliament resolution on homophobia in Europe]

{{LGBT-footer|history=yes|culture=yes|rights=yes}}

[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Homophobia| ]]
[[Category:Hate]]
[[Category:Sexual orientation and society]]
[[Category:Sexual and gender prejudices]]

[[ar:رهاب المثلية]]
[[br:Homofobiezh]]
[[bg:Хомофобия]]
[[ca:Homofòbia]]
[[da:Homofobi]]
[[de:Homophobie]]
[[et:Homofoobia]]
[[el:Ομοφοβία]]
[[es:Homofobia]]
[[fr:Homophobie]]
[[gl:Homofobia]]
[[hr:Homofobija]]
[[it:Omofobia]]
[[he:הומופוביה]]
[[ka:ჰომოფობია]]
[[hu:Homofóbia]]
[[mk:Хомофобија]]
[[nl:Homofobie]]
[[ja:ホモフォビア]]
[[no:Homofobi]]
[[pl:Homofobia]]
[[pt:Homofobia]]
[[ro:Homofobie]]
[[ru:Гомофобия]]
[[sk:Homofóbia]]
[[sl:Homofobija]]
[[sr:Хомофобија]]
[[fi:Homofobia]]
[[sv:Homofobi]]
[[tr:Homofobi]]
[[zh:同性恋恐惧症]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>