<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20211015034947|1049991961" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="22648231" pageid="22648231" ns="0" title="Ageism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2021-11-03T11:15:24Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Stereotyping or discrimination due to age}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=December 2019}}
{{discrimination sidebar|General}}
[[File:Robert N. Butler 2004.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Robert N. Butler]] coined the term "ageism" in 1969]]
{{Wiktionary|Ageism}}'''Ageism''', also spelled '''agism''', is [[stereotyping]] and/or [[discrimination]] against individuals or groups on the basis of their age. This may be casual or systemic.&lt;ref name=":8"&gt;{{cite book |editor1-last=Nelson |editor1-first=T.D. |year=2002|title=Ageism: Stereotyping and Prejudice against Older Persons|publisher=[[MIT Press]]|isbn=978-0-262-64057-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Quadagno"&gt;Quadagno, J. (2008). The field of social gerontology. In E. Barrosse (Ed.), Aging &amp; the life course: An introduction to social gerontology (pp. 2–23). New York: McGraw-Hill.&lt;/ref&gt; The term was coined in 1969 by [[Robert Neil Butler]] to describe discrimination against [[Old age|seniors]], and patterned on [[sexism]] and [[racism]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Butler | first1 = R. N. | s2cid = 42442342 | year = 1969 | title = Age-ism: Another form of bigotry | journal = The Gerontologist | volume = 9 | issue = 4| pages = 243–246 | doi=10.1093/geront/9.4_part_1.243| pmid = 5366225 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Butler defined "ageism" as a combination of three connected elements. Originally it was identified chiefly towards older people, old age, and the [[Ageing|aging process]]; discriminatory practices against older people; and institutional practices and policies that perpetuate [[stereotype]]s about elderly people.&lt;ref&gt;Wilkinson J and Ferraro K, Thirty Years of Ageism Research. In Nelson T (ed). Ageism: Stereotyping and Prejudice Against Older Persons. Massachusetts Institute of Technology, 2002&lt;/ref&gt;

Although in the UK it was used (March 1983) in terms of discrimination against younger people by Councillor Richard Thomas at a meeting of Bracknell Forest Council, it has much later (February 2021) been used in regards to [[prejudice]] and discrimination against especially [[adolescents]] and [[children]], such as denying them certain rights usually reserved for adults such as the right to vote, run for political office, buy and use alcohol, tobacco, or cannabis, marry, own a gun, gamble, consent or refuse medical treatment, sign contracts, and so forth. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://freechild.org/discrimination-against-youth-voice/|title=Discrimination Against Youth Voice|date=7 January 2016|website=freechild.org}}&lt;/ref&gt; This can also include ignoring their ideas because they are considered "too young", or assuming that they should behave in certain ways because of their age. The elderly themselves can be deeply ageist, having internalized a lifetime of negative stereotypes about aging.&lt;ref&gt;[http://kingsreview.co.uk/magazine/theblog/2015/09/08/youthful-indiscretions/ "Youthful Indiscretions"] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160127232145/http://kingsreview.co.uk/magazine/theblog/2015/09/08/youthful-indiscretions/ |date=27 January 2016 }}. kingsreview.co.uk. Retrieved on 11 September 2015.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Fear of death]] and fear of disability and dependence are major causes of ageism; avoiding, segregating, and rejecting older people are [[coping mechanism]]s that allow people to avoid thinking about their own mortality.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2017/11/20/why-ageism-never-gets-old|title=Why Ageism Never Gets Old|last=Friend|first=Tad|date=13 November 2017|work=The New Yorker|access-date=2017-11-28|issn=0028-792X|df=dmy}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Classification==
===Distinction from other age-related bias===
Ageism in common parlance and age studies usually refers to negative discriminatory practices against old people, people in their middle years, teenagers and children. There are several forms of age-related bias. [[Adultism]] is a predisposition towards adults, which is seen as biased against children, youth, and all young people who are not addressed or viewed as adults.&lt;ref&gt;Lauter And Howe (1971) ''Conspiracy of the Young.'' Meridian Press.&lt;/ref&gt; This includes political candidacies, jobs, and cultural settings where the supposed greater vitality and/or [[Human physical appearance|physical beauty]] of youth is more appreciated than the supposed greater moral and/or [[Rigor|intellectual rigor]] of adulthood. [[Adultcentrism]] is the "exaggerated [[egocentrism]] of [[adults]]".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = De Martelaer | first1 = K. | last2 = De Knop | first2 = P. | last3 = Theeboom | first3 = M. | last4 = Van Heddegem | first4 = L. | year = 2000 | title = The UN Convention as a Basis for Elaborating Rights of Children in Sport | journal = Journal of Leisurability | volume = 27 | issue = 2| pages = 3–10 }}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Adultocracy'' is the [[Convention (norm)|social convention]] which defines "maturity" and "immaturity", placing adults in a dominant position over [[youth|young people]], both theoretically and practically.&lt;ref&gt;(n.d.) [http://www.zmag.org/0009.htm Youth Liberation] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070213202808/http://www.zmag.org/0009.htm |date=13 February 2007 }} ''Z'' magazine.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Gerontocracy]] is a form of oligarchical rule in which an entity is ruled by leaders who are significantly older than most of the adult population.&lt;ref&gt;Maddox, G. L. (1987). The Encyclopedia of aging (p. 284). New York: Springer Pub. Co..&lt;/ref&gt; [[Chronocentrism]] is primarily the belief that a certain state of humanity is superior to all previous and/or future times.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Lyon | first1 = P. | last2 = Pollard | first2 = D. | year = 1997 | title = Perceptions of the older employee: is anything really changing? | journal = Personnel Review | volume = 26 | issue = 4| pages = 245–257 [249] | doi=10.1108/00483489710172051}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Based on a conceptual analysis of ageism, a new definition of ageism was introduced by Iversen, Larsen, &amp; Solem in 2009. This definition constitutes the foundation for higher reliability and validity in future research about ageism and its complexity offers a new way of systemizing theories on ageism: "Ageism is defined as negative or positive stereotypes, prejudice and/or discrimination against (or to the advantage of) elderly people on the basis of their chronological age or on the basis of a perception of them as being 'old' or 'elderly'. Ageism can be implicit or explicit and can be expressed on a micro-, meso- or macro-level" (Iversen, Larsen &amp; Solem, 2009).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Iversen | first1 = T.N. | last2 = Larsen | first2 = L. | last3 = Solem | first3 = P.E. | year = 2009 | title = A conceptual analysis of ageism | journal = Nordic Psychology | volume = 61 | issue = 3| pages = 4–22 | doi=10.1027/1901-2276.61.3.4| s2cid = 145529534 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Other conditions of fear or aversion associated with age groups have their own names, particularly: paedophobia, the fear of infants and children; ephebiphobia, the fear of youth,&lt;ref&gt;Fletcher, A. (2006) ''Washington Youth Voice Handbook.'' CommonAction.&lt;/ref&gt; sometimes also referred to as an irrational fear of adolescents or a prejudice against teenagers;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.stop-discrimination.info/6423.0.html?&amp;no_cache=1&amp;mc_glossary%5Bcategories%5D=1 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20071017120531/http://stop-discrimination.info/6423.0.html?&amp;no_cache=1&amp;mc_glossary%5Bcategories%5D=1 |url-status=dead |archive-date=17 October 2007 |title=Stop Discrimination's Glossary (European Union) |work=stop-discrimination.info |access-date=17 April 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[gerontophobia]], the fear of elderly people.&lt;ref&gt;Branch, L., Harris, D. &amp; Palmore, E.B. (2005) ''Encyclopedia of Ageism.'' Haworth Press. {{ISBN|0-7890-1890-X}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Implicit ageism===
[[Implicature|Implicit]] ageism refers to thoughts, feelings, and judgements that operate without conscious awareness and automatically produce in everyday life.&lt;ref name=":8" /&gt; These may be a mixture of positive and negative thoughts and feelings, but gerontologist [[Becca Levy]] reports that they "tend to be mostly negative".&lt;ref name="Levy"&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Levy | first1 = B. R. | year = 2001 | title = Eradication of Ageism requires addressing the enemy within | journal = The Gerontologist | volume = 41 | issue = 5| pages = 578–579 | doi=10.1093/geront/41.5.578| pmid = 11574700 | doi-access = free }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Stereotyping===
[[stereotype|Stereotyping]] is a tool of cognition which involves categorizing into groups and attributing characteristics to these groups. Stereotypes are necessary for processing huge volumes of information which would otherwise overload a person and are generally accurate descriptors of group characteristics, though some stereotypes are inaccurate.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Stereotype Accuracy: Toward Appreciating Group Differences |publisher=American Psychological Association |date=September 1995 |isbn=978-1-55798-307-7 |editor=[[Yueh-Ting Lee]] |editor2=Lee J. Jussim |editor3=Clark R. McCauley}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, they can cause harm when the content of the stereotype is incorrect with respect to most of the group or where a stereotype is so strongly held that it overrides evidence which shows that an individual does not conform to it. For example, age-based stereotypes prime one to draw very different conclusions when one sees an older and a younger adult with, say, back pain or a limp. One might well assume that the younger person's condition is temporary and treatable, following an accident, while the older person's condition is chronic and less susceptible to intervention. On average, this might be true, but plenty of older people have accidents and recover quickly and very young people (such as infants, toddlers, and small children) can become permanently disabled in the same situation. This assumption may have no consequence if one makes it in the blink of an eye as one is passing someone in the street, but if it is held by a health professional offering treatment or managers thinking about occupational health, it could inappropriately influence their actions and lead to age-related discrimination.

Managers have been accused, by [[Erdman B. Palmore|Erdman Palmore]], as stereotyping older workers as being resistant to change, not creative, cautious, slow to make judgments, lower in physical capacity, uninterested in technological change, and difficult to train.&lt;ref&gt;Palmore, E. B. (1999).  Ageism: negative and positive (2nd ed., p. 108). New York: Springer Pub.&lt;/ref&gt; Another example is when people are rude to children because of their high pitched voice, even if they are kind and courteous. A review of the research literature related to age stereotypes in the workplace was recently{{when|date=December 2020}} published in the Journal of Management.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Posthuma | first1 = R. A. | last2 = Campion | first2 = M. A. | s2cid = 145727680 | year = 2009 | title = Age stereotyping in the workplace: Common stereotypes, moderators, and future research directions | journal = Journal of Management | volume = 35 | pages = 158–188 | doi=10.1177/0149206308318617}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Contrary to common and more obvious forms of stereotyping, such as racism and sexism, ageism is more resistant to change. For instance, if a child believes in an ageist idea against the elderly, fewer people correct them, and, as a result, individuals grow up believing in ageist ideas, even elders themselves.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite book|title = Invitation to the Life Span, Second Edition|last = Berger|first = Kathleen Stassen|publisher = Worth Publishers|year = 2014|location = New York}}&lt;/ref&gt; In other words, ageism can become a self-fulfilling prophecy.

Ageist beliefs against the elderly are commonplace in today's society. For example, an older person who forgets something could be quick to call it a "senior moment", failing to realize the ageism of that statement. People also often utter ageist phrases such as "dirty old man" or "second childhood", and elders sometimes miss the ageist undertones.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

In a classic study in 1994, researchers analyzed the effects of ageism among the elderly.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title = Aging free from stereotypes: Successful memory in China among the deaf|last1 = Levy|first1 = Becca|date = 1994|journal = Journal of Personality &amp; Social Psychology|last2 = Langer|first2 = Ellen|doi = 10.1037/0022-3514.66.6.989|pmid = 8046582|volume = 66|issue = 6|pages = 989–97}}&lt;/ref&gt; They performed memory tests on three selected groups: residents of China, deaf North Americans, and hearing North Americans. In the three groups, the Chinese residents were presumably the least exposed to ageism, with lifelong experience in a culture that traditionally venerates older generations. Lifelong deaf North Americans also faced less exposure to ageism in contrast to those with typical hearing, who presumably had heard ageist comments their whole life. The results of the memory tests showed that ageism has significant effects on memory.

The gap in the scores between the young and old North Americans with normal hearing were double those of the deaf North Americans and five times wider than those of the Chinese participants. The results show that ageism undermines ability through its self-fulfilling nature.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; The study was investigating the effect of the [[stereotype threat]], which has been explored as a possible reason for memory deficits,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1093/geronb/58.1.P3 |pmid=12496296 |title=The Impact of Stereotype Threat on Age Differences in Memory Performance |journal=The Journals of Gerontology Series B: Psychological Sciences and Social Sciences |volume=58 |issue=1 |pages=P3–11 |year=2003 |last1=Hess |first1=Thomas M. |last2=Auman |first2=Corinne |last3=Colcombe |first3=Stanley J. |last4=Rahhal |first4=Tamara A. |doi-access=free }}&lt;/ref&gt; though the stereotype threat has been criticized.&lt;ref name="Ganley2013"&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1037/a0031412 |pmid=23356523 |title=An examination of stereotype threat effects on girls' mathematics performance |journal=Developmental Psychology |volume=49 |issue=10 |pages=1886–97 |year=2013 |last1=Ganley |first1=Colleen M |last2=Mingle |first2=Leigh A |last3=Ryan |first3=Allison M |last4=Ryan |first4=Katherine |last5=Vasilyeva |first5=Marina |last6=Perry |first6=Michelle }}&lt;/ref&gt;

On the other hand, when elders show larger independence and control in their lives, defying ageist assumptions, they are more likely to be healthier, both mentally and physically, than other people their age.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

Research indicates that older people are stereotyped as scoring lower on measures of impulsivity, activism, antagonism and [[openness to experience|openness]] while younger people are stereotyped as scoring higher on these measures. This was found to be universal across cultures and was also found to be reasonably accurate (varying depending on how the accuracy was assessed and the type of stereotype), though differences were consistently exaggerated.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1037/a0029712 |pmid=23088227 |pmc=3514646 |title=Stereotypes of age differences in personality traits: Universal and accurate? |journal=Journal of Personality and Social Psychology |volume=103 |issue=6 |pages=1050–1066 |year=2012 |last1=Chan |first1=Wayne |last2=McCrae |first2=Robert R |last3=De Fruyt |first3=Filip |last4=Jussim |first4=Lee |last5=Löckenhoff |first5=Corinna E|author5-link= Corinna Löckenhoff |last6=De Bolle |first6=Marleen |last7=Costa |first7=Paul T |last8=Sutin |first8=Angelina R |last9=Realo |first9=Anu |last10=Allik |first10=Jüri |last11=Nakazato |first11=Katsuharu |last12=Shimonaka |first12=Yoshiko |last13=Hřebíčková |first13=Martina |last14=Graf |first14=Sylvie |last15=Yik |first15=Michelle |last16=Brunner-Sciarra |first16=Marina |last17=De Figueroa |first17=Nora Leibovich |last18=Schmidt |first18=Vanina |last19=Ahn |first19=Chang-kyu |last20=Ahn |first20=Hyun-nie |last21=Aguilar-Vafaie |first21=Maria E |last22=Siuta |first22=Jerzy |last23=Szmigielska |first23=Barbara |last24=Cain |first24=Thomas R |last25=Crawford |first25=Jarret T |last26=Mastor |first26=Khairul Anwar |last27=Rolland |first27=Jean-Pierre |last28=Nansubuga |first28=Florence |last29=Miramontez |first29=Daniel R |last30=Benet-Martínez |first30=Verónica |display-authors=29 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Ageism can also manifests itself in perceptions of how dateable one is, which has culminated in terms such as the ''sexpiration date'', indicating the age after which one is no longer appealing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Apt | first1 = Carol | last2 = Farley Hurlbert | first2 = David | year = 1994 | title = The sexual attitudes, behavior, and relationships of women with histrionic personality disorder | journal = Journal of Sex &amp; Marital Therapy | volume = 20 | issue = 2| pages = 125–134 | doi=10.1080/00926239408403423| pmid = 8035469 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Prejudice===
Ageist [[prejudice]] is a type of emotion which is often linked to the cognitive process of stereotyping. It can involve the expression of derogatory attitudes, which may then lead to the use of discriminatory behavior. Where older or younger contestants were rejected in the belief that they were poor performers, this could well be the result of stereotyping. But older people were also voted for on a stage in a game where it made sense to target the best performers. This can only be explained by a subconscious emotional reaction to older people; in this case, the prejudice took the form of distaste and a desire to exclude oneself from the company of older people.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |doi=10.1093/oxfordhb/9780195385052.001.0001 |first1=Richard A. |last1=Posthuma |first2=María Fernanda |last2=Wagstaff |first3=Michael A. |last3=Campion |chapter=Age Stereotypes and Workplace Age Discrimination: A Framework for Future Research |pages=298–312 |chapter-url={{Google books|OSBpAgAAQBAJ|page=298|plainurl=yes}} |editor1-first=Walter C. |editor1-last=Borman |editor2-first=Jerry W. |editor2-last=Hedge |title=The Oxford Handbook of Work and Aging |year=2012 |isbn=978-0-19-538505-2 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Stereotyping and prejudice against different groups in society does not take the same form. Age-based prejudice and stereotyping usually involves older or younger people being pitied, marginalized, or patronized. This is described as "'''benevolent prejudice"''' because the tendency to pity is linked to seeing older or younger people as "friendly" but "incompetent". [[Age Concern]]'s survey revealed strong evidence of "benevolent prejudice". 48% said that over-70s are viewed as friendly (compared to 27% who said the same about under-30s). Meanwhile, only 26% believe over-70s are viewed as capable (with 41% saying the same about under-30s).&lt;ref name="Loretto"&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Loretto | first1 = W. | last2 = Duncan | first2 = C. | last3 = White | first3 = P.J. | year = 2000 | title = Ageism and employment: Controversies, ambiguities, and younger people's perceptions | journal = Ageing &amp; Society | volume = 20 | issue = 3| pages = 279–302 | doi=10.1017/s0144686x00007741| s2cid = 54961733 | url = https://www.pure.ed.ac.uk/ws/files/11897989/DUNCAN_C_Ageism_and_Employment.pdf }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Digital ageism ===
Digital ageism refers to the prejudices faced by older adults in the digital world. A few examples of the subtle ways in which digital ageism operates in cultural representations, research, and everyday life: Generational segregation naturalizes youth as digitally adept and the old as digital dunces. There is no empirical evidence, though, for a digital divide between older and younger people, with the former never and the latter always capable to use digital media; a far more accurate description is that of a digital spectrum.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |author=Lenhart, A. |author2=Horrigan, J.B.|date=2003|title=Re-visualizing the digital divide as a digital spectrum|journal=IT &amp; Society|volume=1 |issue=5|pages=23–39}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":5"&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.15847/obsOBS612012513 |url=http://obs.obercom.pt/index.php/obs/article/view/513 |first1=Eugène |last1=Loos |title=Senior citizens: Digital immigrants in their own country? |journal=Observatorio |volume=6 |issue=1 |year=2012 |pages=1–23 |doi-broken-date=31 October 2021 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Loos, E. F., Haddon, L., &amp; Mante-Meijer, E. A. (Eds.) (2012). ''Generational Use of New Media.'' Farnham: Ashgate.{{page needed|date=November 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; The reason for the myth of declining capabilities of older people could be that many cultural representations have long histories reproducing images of the life cycle as a mountain, where we peak in middle age then decline{{clarify|date=June 2020}}&lt;ref name=":5" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Gee, E. &amp; G. Gutman, (eds.). (2000). The Overselling of Population Aging: Apocalyptic Demography, Intergenerational Challenges, and Social Policy. Don Mills, Ontario: Oxford University Press.{{page needed|date=November 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Gullette, M. M. (1997). Declining to Decline: Cultural combat: the politics of the midlife. Charlottesville, VA: University Press of Virginia.{{page needed|date=November 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Older adults' experiences are often excluded from research agendas on digital media, and ageism is ensconced within disciplines such as mass communication studies. For example, in a media diffusionist perspective,&lt;ref&gt;Rogers, E. (1995). Diffusion of Innovations. California: Stanford University Press.&lt;/ref&gt; the practices of seniors are depicted as either negligible or as lagging, and the equation of diffusion with individual ownership can hide practical 'workarounds' such as cell phone sharing or missed calls used by older couples on fixed incomes.&lt;ref&gt;Sawchuk, K. &amp; Crow, B. (2012). Seniors, Cell Phones, and Tactical Restriction, in Phillip Vannini et al. (eds.), technologies of Mobility in the Americas, (157-174). New York: Peter Lang Publishing.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.21018/rjcpr.2013.3.196 |title=Older People and Mobile Communication in Two European Contexts |journal=Romanian Journal of Communication and Public Relations |volume=15 |issue=3 |pages=83–98 |year=2016 |last1=Fernández-Ardèvol |first1=Mireia |last2=Ivan |first2=Loredana |doi-access=free }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Ageism in statistics===
Ageism is also inadvertently embedded in the ways statistics are collected. For example, data collected based on large age categories (e.g., '60+') foisting anyone over 60 into 'the grey zone' which obscures differences.&lt;ref&gt;Sawchuk, K., &amp; Crow, B. (2010). Into the grey zone: Seniors, cell phones and milieus that matter. In B. Poppinga (ed.), Observing the mobile user experience: Proceedings of the 1st international workshop held in conjunction with NordiCHI (pp. 17–20). Oldenburg, Germany: HaptiMap.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[dependency ratio]] has been criticized by the [[Office of the United Nations High Commissioner for Human Rights]] as being based on the ageist assumption that older people are always dependent on care from younger workers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Measure what you treasure: Ageism in Statistics |url=https://www.ohchr.org/Documents/Issues/OlderPersons/AgeismAgeDiscrimination/Submissions/UNs/UNFPA-2.pdf |website=OHCHR |access-date=5 October 2021 |date=2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Visual ageism ===
The term ''visual ageism'' was coined in 2018 by Loos and Ivan. They define ''visual ageism'' as "the social practice of visually underrepresenting older people or misrepresenting them in a prejudiced way".&lt;ref name=":6"&gt;Loos. E. F., &amp; Ivan, L. (2018). Visual Ageism in the Media. In: L. Ayalon &amp; C. Tesch-Roemer (Eds.), ''Contemporary perspectives on ageism'' (pp. 163-176)''.'' Berlin: Springer. [https://link.springer.com/content/pdf/10.1007%2F978-3-319-73820-8_11.pdf]&lt;/ref&gt; We are facing a shift from visual ageism characterized by underrepresentation and the negative representation of older people to a representation of older age characterized by images of stereotypically third age older adults (enjoying life and living their ''“[[:wikt:golden years|golden years]]”''), while older adults in their fourth age (inactive and unable to live independently) remain invisible. A review of empirical studies conducted since 1950 in Europe and North America&lt;ref name=":6" /&gt; reveals that print and television advertisements started this transition towards a more positive visual representation of older adults in their age during the last decade of the 20th century, followed by television programs some years later, while older adults in their fourth age remain invisible.

This is probably due to the increase in third age rhetoric in the media, picturing older people as healthy and as potential consumers, enjoying life and living their golden years. Media representations of older people have moved from visual under- and misrepresentation (negative images)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Atkins | first1 = T. | last2 = Jenkins | first2 = M. C. | last3 = Perkins | first3 = M. H. | year = 1990 | title = Portrayal of persons in television commercials age 50 and older | journal = Psychology: A Journal of Human Behaviour | volume = 27 | issue = 4| pages = 30–37 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Roy|first1=Abhik|last2=Harwood|first2=Jake|date=1 February 1997|title=Underrepresented, positively portrayed: Older adults in television commercials |journal=Journal of Applied Communication Research|volume=25|issue=1|pages=39–56|doi=10.1080/00909889709365464|issn=0090-9882}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Simcock|first1=Peter|last2=Lynn|first2=SudburyDr|date=1 January 2006|title=The invisible majority? Older models in UK television advertising |journal=International Journal of Advertising|volume=25|issue=1|pages=87–106|doi=10.1080/02650487.2006.11072953|s2cid=167032348|issn=0265-0487}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = van Selm | first1 = M. | last2 = Westerhof | first2 = G. J. | last3 = de Vos | first3 = B. | year = 2007 | title = Competent en veelzijdig | journal = [[Tijdschrift voor Gerontologie en Geriatrie]] | volume = 38 | issue = 2| pages = 51–58 | doi=10.1007/bf03074828| pmid = 23203008 | s2cid = 73372054 }}&lt;/ref&gt; to more positive depictions&lt;ref&gt;Vickers, K. (2007). Aging and the media: yesterday, today, and tomorrow. ''Californian Journal of Health Promotion'', ''5''(3'')'', 100-105.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Ylänne, V. (2015).  [null Representations of ageing in the media. In] J. Twigg, &amp; W. Martin (Eds.). (2015). ''Routledge Handbook of Cultural Gerontology'' (pp. 369-375). London: Routledge.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":6" /&gt; These days, visual ageism in the media tends to come wrapped in the guise of the positive attributes of third age representations of older people, while adults in their fourth age continue to be underrepresented. One possible explanation for this is that healthy third agers might prefer not to be associated with fourth agers, as they remind them too starkly of what lies ahead in their own near future. Although this discomfort or even fear about mortality is undeniably common, from a societal point of view this kind of (self)ageism is hurtful to fourth agers as a group and in a sense to third agers as well, as they risk to become fourth agers themselves one day.&lt;ref name=":6" /&gt;

==Discrimination==
{{See also|Age discrimination in the United States}}

Age [[discrimination]] is the result of actions taken to deny or limit opportunities to people based on age. These are usually actions taken as a result of one's ageist beliefs and attitudes. Age discrimination occurs on both a personal and institutional level.&lt;ref name="Quadagno" /&gt;

On a personal level, an older person may be told that he is too old to engage in certain physical activities, like an informal game of basketball between friends and family. A younger person may be told he is too young to get a job or help move the dining room table. On an institutional level, there are policies and regulations in place that limit opportunities to people of certain ages and deny them to all others. The law, for instance, requires that all people must be at least 16 years old to obtain a driver's license in the United States. There are also government regulations that determine when a worker may retire. Currently, in the US, a worker must be between 65 and 67 years old (depending upon his or her birth year) before becoming eligible for full Social Security retirement benefits (age 62 for 70% benefits) but some company pension plans begin benefits at earlier ages.{{citation needed|date=November 2017}}

A 2006/2007 survey done by the Children's Rights Alliance for England and the National Children's Bureau asked 4,060 children and young people whether they have ever been treated unfairly based on various criteria (race, age, sex, sexual orientation, etc.). A total of 43% of British youth surveyed reported experiencing discrimination based on their age, far eclipsing other categories of discrimination like sex (27%), race (11%), or sexual orientation (6%).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |first1=Carolyne |last1=Willow |first2=Anita |last2=Franklin |first3=Catherine |last3=Shaw |date=April 2007 |title=Meeting the obligations of the Convention on the Rights of the Child in England: children and young people's messages to government |url=http://dera.ioe.ac.uk/id/eprint/10935 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Consistently, a study based on the European Social Survey found that whereas 35% of Europeans reported exposure ageism, only 25% reported exposure to sexism and as few as 17% reported exposure to racism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Ayalon|first=Liat|title=Perceived Age, Gender, and Racial/Ethnic Discrimination in Europe: Results from the European Social Survey|journal=Educational Gerontology|year=2014|volume=40|issue=7|pages=499–517|doi=10.1080/03601277.2013.845490 |s2cid=143802599}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Ageism has significant effects in two particular sectors: employment and health care. Age discrimination has contributed to disparities in health between men and women. Reducing ageism and sexism would promote improved doctor-patient relationships and reduce ageist stereotypes in the healthcare industry.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1111/josi.12157 |title=Ageism can be Hazardous to Women's Health: Ageism, Sexism, and Stereotypes of Older Women in the Healthcare System |journal=Journal of Social Issues |volume=72 |issue=1 |pages=86–104 |year=2016 |last1=Chrisler |first1=Joan C |last2=Barney |first2=Angela |last3=Palatino |first3=Brigida }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Employment===
The concept of ageism was originally developed to refer to prejudice and discrimination against older people and middle aged people, but has expanded to include children and teenagers.&lt;ref name="Loretto"/&gt; Midlife workers, on average, make more than younger workers do, which reflects educational achievement and experiencd. The age-wage peak in the United States, according to Census data, is between 45 and 54 years of age. Seniority in general accords with respect as people age, lessening ageism.{{cn|date=October 2021}}

Younger female workers were historically discriminated against, in comparison with younger men, because it was expected that, as young women of childbearing years, they would need to leave the workforce permanently or periodically to have children.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |first1=Edmund S. |last1=Phelps |date=September 1972 |title=The Statistical Theory of Racism and Sexism |journal=The American Economic Review |volume=62 |issue=4 |pages=659–61 |jstor=1806107 |url=https://www.researchgate.net/publication/4728049}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, midlife female workers may also experience discrimination based on their appearance&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1016/j.scaman.2013.07.002 |title=Women managers, careers and gendered ageism |journal=Scandinavian Journal of Management |volume=30 |issue=2 |pages=175–85 |year=2014 |last1=Jyrkinen |first1=Marjut |hdl=10138/159757 |hdl-access=free }}&lt;/ref&gt; and may feel less visible and undervalued&lt;ref name=":7"&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1017/S0144686X07007003 |title=Visible and invisible ageing: Beauty work as a response to ageism |journal=Ageing and Society |volume=28 |issue=5 |pages=653–74 |year=2008 |last1=Clarke |first1=Laura Hurd |last2=Griffin |first2=Meridith |s2cid=145683403 }}&lt;/ref&gt; in a culture where emphasis is on maintaining an approved standard of beauty, e.g. 'thin, pretty, White, and young'.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1080/08952841.2015.1125698 |pmid=27471885 |title=There's a cream for that: A textual analysis of beauty and body-related advertisements aimed at middle-aged women |journal=Journal of Women &amp; Aging |volume=29 |issue=2 |pages=185–97 |year=2016 |last1=Del Rosso |first1=Teri |s2cid=32486881 }}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the same standard could have no effect on male colleagues of the same age.&lt;ref name=":7" /&gt;

The United States federal government restricts age discrimination under the [[Age Discrimination in Employment Act]] of 1967 (ADEA). That law provides certain employment protections to workers who are over the age of forty, who work for an employer who has twenty or more employees. For protected workers, the ADEA prohibits discrimination at all levels of employment, from recruitment and hiring, through the employment relationship, and through decisions for layoffs or termination of the employment relationship.&lt;ref name="auto1"&gt;{{cite web|last1=Larson|first1=Aaron|title=Age Discrimination Law|url=https://www.expertlaw.com/library/employment/age_discrimination.html|website=ExpertLaw|access-date=28 September 2017|date=25 July 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; An age limit may only be legally specified for protected workers in the circumstance where age has been shown to be a "[[bona fide occupational qualification]] [BFOQ] reasonably necessary to the normal operation of the particular business" (see {{usc|29|623(f)(1)}}). In practice, BFOQs for age are limited to the obvious (hiring a young actor to play a young character in a movie) or when public safety is at stake (for example, in the case of age limits for pilots and bus drivers). The ADEA does not stop an employer from favoring an older employee over a younger one, even when the younger one is over 40 years old.&lt;ref name="auto2"&gt;{{ussc|name=General Dynamics Land Sys., Inc. v. Cline|link=|volume=540|page=581|pin=|year=2004}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the UK, age discrimination against older people has been prohibited in employment since 2006.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=The Employment Equality (Age) Regulations 2006 |url=http://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2006/1031/contents/made |website=legislation.gov.uk |publisher=The National Archives |access-date=25 April 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt; Further refinements to anti-discrimination laws occurred in 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last1=Callahan |first1=Sheila |title=U.K.'s Willingness To Protect Younger Individuals From Age Discrimination Not Likely In U.S. |url=https://www.forbes.com/sites/sheilacallaham/2019/12/06/unlike-this-close-allys-willingness-to-protect-younger-workers-from-age-discrimination-us-not-likely-to-follow-suit/#17febb1b451a |access-date=25 April 2020 |agency=Forbes |date=6 December 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:EEOC Claim Process Infographic.png|thumb|Infographic showing the process of fililng an [[Equal Employment Opportunity Commission]] complaint, with age discrimintation being possible grounds for EEOC intervention]]
Age discrimination in hiring has been shown to exist in the United States. The [[Equal Employment Opportunity Commission]]'s first complainants were female flight attendants complaining of (among other matters) age discrimination.&lt;ref name="Collins2009"&gt;{{cite book|author= Gail Collins|author-link=Gail Collins|title=When Everything Changed: The Amazing Journey of American Women from 1960 to the Present|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=sQ1HhzuaYkEC&amp;pg=PT59|date=14 October 2009|publisher=Little, Brown|isbn=978-0-316-07166-6|pages=59}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1968, the [[EEOC]] declared age restrictions on flight attendants' employment to be illegal sex discrimination under [[Title VII of the Civil Rights Act of 1964]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=K Barry |url=http://femininityinflight.com/activism.html |title=Timeline of Discrimination |publisher=Femininity in Flight |access-date=6 August 2015 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160826083225/http://femininityinflight.com/activism.html |archive-date=26 August 2016 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; However, Joanna Lahey, professor at [[The Bush School of Government and Public Service]] at [[Texas A&amp;M]], found recently{{when|date=December 2020}} that firms are more than 40% more likely to interview a young adult job applicant than an older job applicant.&lt;ref&gt;Lahey, J. (2005) [https://ideas.repec.org/p/crr/issbrf/ib33.html Do Older Workers Face Discrimination?] Boston College.&lt;/ref&gt; In order to fulfill job postings with youthful staff, companies turn to recruitment companies to meet their needs. Many sources place blame on recruitment practices as it is the one way that age discrimination can go incognito at the hands of others. Sofica (2012) states "A study run in Washington in 1999 shows that 84% of the recruitment agencies are discriminating compared to only 29% of the companies that do their own.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Sofica | first1 = A | year = 2012 | title = The Social Network of Actors Influencing Age Discrimination in the Human Resources Recruiting Process | journal = Eastern Journal of European Studies | volume = 3 | issue = 1| pages = 169–88 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Dobson states that according to Weisbeck’s (2017) research, "People have a natural bias to hire people like themselves" (p.&amp;nbsp;3).&lt;ref&gt;Dobson, S.. "Older Tech Workers Face Ageism in Hiring." Canadian HR Reporter 30.18 (2017): 3-16. Web.&lt;/ref&gt; Lahey (2008) also stated within her research "Since it is more difficult for workers to determine why the failed to receive an interview than it is for workers to determine why they have been fired, firms that wish to retain only a certain type of worker without being sued would prefer to discriminate in the hiring state rather than at any point of the employment process" (p.&amp;nbsp;31).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Lahey | first1 = J | year = 2008 | title = Age, Women, and Hiring: An Experimental Study. (Report) | journal = Journal of Human Resources | volume = 43 | issue = 1| pages = 30–56 | doi = 10.3368/jhr.43.1.30 | doi-access = free }}&lt;/ref&gt; All states in the [[US]] prohibit youth under 14 from working with a handful of exceptions and prohibit youth under 18 from working in hazardous occupations. They are also paid a lower minimum wage and not allowed to work full-time.

Also in Europe, pervasive levels of age discrimination are found in [[Belgium]], [[England]], [[France]], Spain, and Sweden. Job candidates revealing older age are found to get 39% (in Belgium) to 72% (in France) less job interview invitations compared to equal candidates revealing a younger name.&lt;ref name="Baert et al 2016"&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1016/j.joep.2016.10.002 |title=Getting grey hairs in the labour market. An alternative experiment on age discrimination |journal=Journal of Economic Psychology |volume=57 |pages=86–101 |year=2016 |last1=Baert |first1=Stijn |last2=Norga |first2=Jennifer |last3=Thuy |first3=Yannick |last4=Van Hecke |first4=Marieke |hdl=10419/114164 |s2cid=38265879 |hdl-access=free }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Riach, P. A., Rich, J. (2006) [http://ftp.iza.org/dp2522.pdf An Experimental Investigation of Age Discrimination in the French Labour Market.] IZA Discussion Paper Series, 2522.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Riach, P. A., Rich, J. (2010) [https://www.jstor.org/stable/41219164 An Experimental Investigation of Age Discrimination in the English Labor Market.] Annals of Economics and Statistics, 99/100, 169–185.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Tinsley, M. (2012) [http://www.barrowcadbury.org.uk/wp-content/uploads/2012/07/Policy-Exchange-2012-Too-much-to-lose.pdf Too much to lose: Understanding and supporting Britain’s older workers.] London: Policy Exchange.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1080/09585192.2011.540160 |title=A field experiment to study sex and age discrimination in the Madrid labour market |journal=The International Journal of Human Resource Management |volume=22 |issue=2 |pages=351–375 |year=2011 |last1=Albert |first1=Rocío |last2=Escot |first2=Lorenzo |last3=Fernández-Cornejo |first3=José Andrés |s2cid=153806574 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Riach, P. A., Rich, J. (2007) [http://ftp.iza.org/dp2522.pdf An Experimental Investigation of Age Discrimination in the Spanish Labour Market.] IZA Discussion Paper Series, 2654.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1080/13504851.2011.581199 |title=Does age matter for employability? A field experiment on ageism in the Swedish labour market |journal=Applied Economics Letters |volume=19 |issue=4 |pages=403–406 |year=2012 |last1=Ahmed |first1=Ali M |last2=Andersson |first2=Lina |last3=Hammarstedt |first3=Mats |s2cid=154641862 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, In a survey for the [[University of Kent]], England, 29% of respondents stated that they had suffered from age discrimination. This is a higher proportion than for [[Sexism|gender]] or [[Racism|racial]] discrimination. [[Dominic Abrams]], [[social psychology]] professor at the university, concluded that ageism is the most pervasive form of prejudice experienced in the UK population.&lt;ref&gt;(2006) [http://www.ageconcern.org.uk/AgeConcern/media/how_ageist_is_britain.pdf How Ageist is Britain?] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20051027165812/http://www.ageconcern.org.uk/AgeConcern/media/how_ageist_is_britain.pdf |date=27 October 2005 }} London: Age Concern.&lt;/ref&gt; Discrimination is found to be heterogeneous by the activity older candidates undertook during their additional post-educational years. In Belgium, they are only discriminated if they have more years of inactivity or irrelevant employment.&lt;ref name="Baert et al 2016" /&gt;

According to Dr. Robert M. McCann, an associate professor of management communication at the [[University of Southern California]]'s [[Marshall School of Business]], denigrating older workers, even if only subtly, can have an outsized negative impact on employee productivity and corporate profits.{{citation needed|date=July 2017}} For American corporations, age discrimination can lead to significant expenses. In Fiscal Year 2006, the U.S. [[Equal Employment Opportunity Commission]] received nearly 17,000 charges of age discrimination, resolving more than 14,000 and recovering $51.5 million in monetary benefits. Costs from lawsuit settlements and judgments can run into the millions, most notably with the $250 million paid by the California Public Employees' Retirement System ([[CalPERS]]) under a settlement agreement in 2003.&lt;ref&gt;[http://newswise.com/articles/view/544169/ When Words Get Old: Ageist Language] Newswise, Retrieved on 9 September 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Harris, D. (2003 July–August) [http://www.aarpmagazine.org/lifestyle/a2003-05-21-mag-justice_age.html Simple justice. The story behind a record-setting age discrimination settlement and what it could mean in your workplace.] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080627184745/http://www.aarpmagazine.org/lifestyle/a2003-05-21-mag-justice_age.html |date=27 June 2008 }} ''AARP The Magazine''.  Retrieved on 25 October 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Hollywood ===
Ageism in [[Hollywood]], specifically in terms of women, is profound, from the way youth is praised to the lack of jobs for older actresses. The way youth is praised reflects directly on the way older women are presented in the media. President and CEO of the [[American Association of Advertising Agencies]], O. Burtch Drake, spoke in terms of older women's representation throughout the media stating "older women are not being portrayed at all; there is no imagery to worry about."&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;Kleyman, Paul. "Images of Aging." ''Encyclopedia of Aging''. Ed. David J. Ekerdt. Vol. 2. New York: Macmillan Reference USA, 2002. 679-685. ''Gale Virtual Reference Library''.&lt;/ref&gt; Women over fifty are not the center of attention and if an actress is older they are expected to act anything but their age.&lt;ref name=":4" /&gt; The standards set for women in film are fixated upon youth, sexuality, and beauty. Movies that portray older women acting their own age seem exaggerated and unrealistic because it does not fit the norms associated with women in film and media.&lt;ref name=":4" /&gt; As a result, older actresses face weaker employment opportunities.&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Being an Older Woman: A Study in the Social Production of Identity|last = Paoletti|first = Isabella|publisher = Lawrence Erlbaum Associates|year = 1998|isbn = 978-0-8058-2120-8|location = New Jersey|pages = [https://archive.org/details/beingolderwomans0000paol/page/47 47]|url = https://archive.org/details/beingolderwomans0000paol/page/47}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Because of the limited ages the film industry portrays and the lack of older actresses, society as a whole has a type of illiteracy about sexuality and those of old age. There is an almost inherent bias about what older women are capable of, what they do, and how they feel.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Gender, Social Inequalities, and Aging|last = Calasanti|first = Toni M.|publisher = AltaMira Press|year = 2001|isbn = 978-0-7591-0185-2|location = Walnut Creek|pages = [https://archive.org/details/gendersocialineq0000cala/page/79 79]|url = https://archive.org/details/gendersocialineq0000cala/page/79}}&lt;/ref&gt; Amongst all ages of actresses there is the attempt to look youthful and fitting to the beauty standards by altering themselves physically, many times under the hands of plastic surgeons.&lt;ref name=":4"&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Chivers | first1 = Sally | year = 2006 | title = Baby Jane Grew Up: The Dramatic Intersection of Age With Disability | journal = Canadian Review of American Studies | volume = 36 | issue = 2| pages = 211–227 | doi=10.1353/crv.2006.0039| s2cid = 161637817 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Women become frightful of what they will be seen as if they have wrinkles, cellulite, or any other signifier of aging.&lt;ref name=":2"&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Saucier | first1 = Maggi G | s2cid = 53617608 | year = 2004 | title = Midlife And Beyond: Issues For Aging Women | journal = Journal of Counseling &amp; Development | volume = 82 | issue = 4| pages = 420–425 | doi=10.1002/j.1556-6678.2004.tb00329.x}}&lt;/ref&gt; As women reach their forties and fifties, the pressure to adhere to societal beauty norms seen amongst films and media intensifies in terms of new cosmetic procedures and products that will maintain a "forever youthful" look.&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt; In terms of sexuality, older women are seen as unattractive, bitter, unhappy, and unsuccessful in films. With older women not being represented in the media and film industries, specifically in Hollywood, thoughts of underachievement, ugliness, and disgust crowd the thoughts of older women as they fail to meet beauty norms. This can cause depression, anxiety, and self-esteem issues in general.&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt; "In one survey, women reported feeling more embarrassed about their age than by their masturbation practices or same-gender sexual encounters."&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt;

When a woman is told she is old, she can start to believe that she is. A woman can start acting as if she is older than she believes because she internalizes what other people are saying and what they think about her.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = The Social World of Old Women: Management of Self-Identity|last = Matthews|first = Sarah H.|publisher = Sage Publication|year = 1979|isbn = 978-0-8039-1225-0|location = Beverly Hills, CA|pages = [https://archive.org/details/socialworldofold00matt/page/166 166]|url = https://archive.org/details/socialworldofold00matt/page/166}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In film the female body is depicted in different states of dress and portrayed differently depending on the age of the actress. Their clothing is used as an identity marker of the character. Young women are put into revealing and sexy costumes whereas older women often play the part of a mother or grandmother clad in a bonnet or apron.&lt;ref name=":3"&gt;{{Cite book|title = Aging Bodies:The Aging Female Body|last = Markson|first = Elizabeth|publisher = Rowman &amp; Littlefield Publishers, Inc.|year = 2003|isbn = 978-0-7591-0236-1|location = Lanham, Maryland|pages = 78, 79, 80–83}}&lt;/ref&gt; Aside from no longer representing the ideal female model, post-menopausal women are stereotyped as mentally unstable. "They become quarrelsome, vexatious and overbearing, petty and stingy; that is to say they exhibit typically sadistic and anal-erotic traits that they did not possess earlier...(Freud 1958,323-24)"&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt;

===Healthcare===
There is considerable evidence of discrimination against the elderly in health care.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.agediscrimination.info/News/Pages/ItemPage.aspx?Item=553 Complaints soar as 'age discrimination within NHS' leaves elderly neglected]. Agediscrimination.info (9 November 2011). Retrieved on 11 April 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.agediscrimination.info/News/Pages/ItemPage.aspx?Item=343 Poor treatment of older people in the NHS is an attitude problem]. Agediscrimination.info (15 February 2011). Retrieved on 11 April 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.agediscrimination.info/News/Pages/ItemPage.aspx?Item=364 The Department of Health says there is no place for age discrimination in the NHS, but a new report shows the middle-aged 'miss out' on life-saving cancer surgery]. Agediscrimination.info (18 March 2011). Retrieved on 11 April 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; This is particularly true for aspects of the physician-patient interaction, such as screening procedures, information exchanges, and treatment decisions. In the patient-physician interaction, physicians and other health care providers may hold attitudes, beliefs, and behaviors that are associated with ageism against older patients. Studies have found that some physicians do not seem to show any care or concern toward treating the medical problems of older people. Then, when interacting with these older patients on the job, the doctors sometimes view them with disgust and describe them in negative ways, such as "depressing" or "crazy".&lt;ref name="Nelson"&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Nelson | first1 = T. D. | s2cid = 10632570 | year = 2005 | title = Ageism: Prejudice against our feared future self | journal = Journal of Social Issues | volume = 61 | issue = 2| pages = 207–221 | doi=10.1111/j.1540-4560.2005.00402.x}}&lt;/ref&gt; For screening procedures, elderly people are less likely than younger people to be screened for cancers and, due to the lack of this preventive measure, less likely to be diagnosed at early stages of their conditions.&lt;ref name="Robb"&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Robb | first1 = C. | last2 = Hongbin | first2 = C. | last3 = Haley | first3 = W. E. | year = 2002 | title = Ageism in mental health and health care: A critical review | journal = Journal of Clinical Geropsychology | volume = 8 | issue = 1| pages = 1–12 | doi = 10.1023/A:1013013322947 | s2cid = 71024173 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

After being diagnosed with a disease that may be potentially curable, older people are further discriminated against. Though there may be surgeries or operations with high survival rates that might cure their condition, older patients are less likely than younger patients to receive all the necessary treatments. For example, health professionals pursue less aggressive treatment options in older patients,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Learning to be old: Gender, culture, and aging |edition=2nd |last = Cruikshank|first = Margaret|publisher = Rowman &amp; Littlefield|year = 2009|location = Lanham, MD}}&lt;/ref&gt; and fewer adults are enrolled in tests of new prescription drugs.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title = Disparate inclusion of older adults in clinical trials: Priorities and opportunities for policy and practice change|last = Herrera|first = Angelica P.|date = 2010|journal = American Journal of Public Health|doi = 10.2105/ajph.2009.162982 |pmid = 20147682|volume=100 |pages=S105–S112 |pmc=2837461}}&lt;/ref&gt; It has been posited that this is because doctors fear their older patients are not physically strong enough to tolerate the curative treatments and are more likely to have complications during surgery that may end in death.

Other research studies have been done with patients with heart disease, and, in these cases, the older patients were still less likely to receive further tests or treatments, independent of the severity of their health problems. Thus, the approach to the treatment of older people is concentrated on managing the disease rather than preventing or curing it. This is based on the stereotype that it is the natural process of aging for the quality of health to decrease, and, therefore, there is no point in attempting to prevent the inevitable decline of old age.&lt;ref name="Nelson" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Robb" /&gt;

Furthermore, caregivers further undermine the treatment of older patients by helping them too much, which decreases independence,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title = A primer on medication use in older adults for the non-clinician|last1 = Peron|first1 = Emily P.|date = 2011–2012|journal = Generations|last2 = Ruby|first2 = Christine M.}}&lt;/ref&gt; and by making a generalized assumption and treating all elderly as feeble.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

Differential medical treatment of elderly people can have significant effects on their health outcomes, a differential outcome which somehow escapes established protections.

In 2017, the [[European Court of Human Rights]] ruled in favor of Maria Ivone Carvalho Pinto de Sousa Morais, who had had an operation that was mishandled and rendered her unable to have sex. Portuguese judges had previously reduced damages to her in 2014, ruling then that the operation, which occurred when she was 50, had happened at "an age when sex is not as important as in younger years." The [[European Court of Human Rights]] rejected that decision, with the majority's ruling stating in part, "The question at issue here is not considerations of age or sex as such, but rather the assumption that sexuality is not as important for a 50-year-old woman and mother of two children as for someone of a younger age. That assumption reflects a traditional idea of female sexuality as being essentially linked to childbearing purposes and thus ignores its physical and psychological relevance for the self-fulfillment of women as people."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=SEWELL CHANJULY 25, 2017 |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2017/07/25/world/europe/sex-after-50-portugal-european-court.html |title=Sex for Women After 50 Is Important After All, European Court Rules - The New York Times |work=Nytimes.com |date=2017 |access-date=26 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Effects of ageism==
Ageism has significant effects on the elderly and young people. These effects might be seen within different levels: person, selected company, whole economy.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Prokurat|first=Sergiusz|date=2012|title=Age Management as a Tool for the Demographic Decline in the 21st Century: An Overview of its Characteristics|url=http://www.jemi.edu.pl/vol-8-issue-4-2012/age-management-as-a-tool-for-the-demographic-decline-in-the-21st-century-an-overview-of-its-characteristics|journal=Journal of Entrepreneurship, Management and Innovation|volume=8/2012|pages=83–96}}&lt;/ref&gt; The stereotypes and infantilization of older and younger people by patronizing language affects older and younger people's self-esteem and behaviors. After repeatedly hearing a stereotype that older or younger people are useless, older and younger people may begin to feel like dependent, non-contributing members of society. They may start to perceive themselves in terms of the [[looking-glass self]]—that is, in the same ways that others in society see them. Studies have also specifically shown that when older and younger people hear these stereotypes about their supposed incompetence and uselessness, they perform worse on measures of competence and memory.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Levy | first1 = B | s2cid = 14442482 | year = 1996 | title = Improving memory in old age by implicit self-stereotyping | journal = Journal of Personality and Social Psychology | volume = 71 | issue = 6| pages = 1092–1107 | doi=10.1037/0022-3514.71.6.1092}}&lt;/ref&gt; These stereotypes then become [[self-fulfilling prophecies]]. According to [[Becca Levy]]'s [[Stereotype embodiment theory|Stereotype Embodiment Theory]], older and younger people might also engage in self-stereotypes, taking their culture's age stereotypes—to which they have been exposed over the life course—and directing them inward toward themselves. Then this behavior reinforces the present stereotypes and treatment of the elderly.&lt;ref name="Levy" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Nelson" /&gt;

Many overcome these stereotypes and live the way they want, but it can be difficult to avoid deeply ingrained prejudice, especially if one has been exposed to ageist views in childhood or adolescence.

===Catholic Church===
In 1970 [[Pope Paul VI]] ruled that [[Cardinal (Catholic Church)|Cardinals]] who had reached the age of 80 years could not be part of the election of a new Pope. He also declared that year that upon reaching their 80th birthday Cardinals would no longer be members of administrative departments and other permanent Vatican institutions. He further stated that year that Cardinals in charge of departments of the [[Roman Curia]] and other permanent central church institutions should resign voluntarily when they reach 75 years old, and that the Pope would decide whether to accept each resignation on an individual basis.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Times|first=Paul Hofmann; Special to The New York|date=24 November 1970|title=Voting for Popes Is Barred to Cardinals Over 80 (Published 1970)|url=https://www.nytimes.com/1970/11/24/archives/voting-for-popes-is-barred-to-cardinals-over-80-prelates-over-80.html|via=NYTimes.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Africa ===

====Nigeria====
In November 2011, the [[House of Representatives (Nigeria)|Nigerian House of Representatives]] considered a bill which would outlaw age discrimination in employment.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|date=24 February 2012|title=Minister shelve ban on age discrimination|url=http://www.agediscrimination.info/News/Pages/ItemPage.aspx?Item=549}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== America ===

====Canada====
Section 15 (1) of the [[Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms]] states that "every individual is equal before and under the law and has the right to equal protection and equal benefit of the law without discrimination and, in particular, without discrimination based on{{Nbsp}}... age" (as well as other protected classes).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/Const/page-15.html|title=Consolidated federal laws of canada, Access to Information Act|first=Legislative Services|last=Branch|date=30 July 2015|website=laws-lois.justice.gc.ca|access-date=30 April 2018|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160110221331/http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/Const/page-15.html|archive-date=10 January 2016|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Canada, Article 718.2, clause (a)(i), of the [[Criminal Code]] defines as aggravating circumstances, among other situations, "evidence that the offence was motivated by{{Nbsp}}... age".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.laws.justice.gc.ca/en/showdoc/cs/C-46/bo-ga:l_XXIII-gb:s_718//en#anchorbo-ga:l_XXIII-gb:s_718 Canadian Criminal Code] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110706181639/http://www.laws.justice.gc.ca/en/showdoc/cs/C-46/bo-ga%3Al_XXIII-gb%3As_718//en |date=6 July 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.agediscrimination.info/international/Pages/Canada.aspx Canada] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120716080129/http://www.agediscrimination.info/international/Pages/Canada.aspx |date=16 July 2012 }}. Agediscrimination.info (12 December 2006). Retrieved on 11 April 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

Mandatory retirement was largely ended in Canada in December 2011,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.agediscrimination.info/News/Pages/ItemPage.aspx?Item=568 "Tories in Canada end forced retirement, decades of 'age discrimination{{'"}}] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120718004027/http://www.agediscrimination.info/News/Pages/ItemPage.aspx?Item=568 |date=18 July 2012 }}. Agediscrimination.info. Retrieved on 11 April 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; but 74% of Canadians still consider age discrimination to be a problem.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.agediscrimination.info/News/Pages/ItemPage.aspx?Item=657 Canadians believe employers discriminate against older applicants]. Agediscrimination.info (23 July 2012). Retrieved on 24 July 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

Retirement age for Canadian airline pilots is provided by each airline with some set to age 60, but changes to the [[Canadian Human Rights Act]] have restricted retirement age set by the airlines.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Vanessa Lu|url=https://www.thestar.com/business/2013/01/24/air_canada_pilots_can_continue_flying_past_age_60_under_new_rules.html|title=Air Canada pilots can continue flying past age 60 under new rules|newspaper=Toronto Star|date=January 24, 2013|access-date=November 5, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Colombia ====
Measures taken to prevent the spread of [[COVID-19 pandemic in Colombia|COVID-19]] were especially strict on older people in Colombia. The government prohibited anyone over 70 years of age from leaving their house.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite chapter | last1=Galeano | first1=E | last2=Zuluaga | first2=M | last3=Saldarriaga-Ruiz | first3=G | chapter=Envejecimiento y Covid-19: los debates que impone el confinamiento de los mayores a un mundo envejeciente 
|url=http://bibliotecadigital.udea.edu.co/bitstream/10495/17635/4/UribeAlejandro_2020_PolifoniaPensarPandemia.pdf |title=Polifonía para pensar una pandemia
|publisher=Universidad de Antioquia, Fondo Editorial FCSH de la Facultad de Ciencias Sociales y Humanas |year=2020|isbn=978-958-5157-17-0 |location=|pages=145–166}}&lt;/ref&gt; Amid public backlash, the restriction was taken to court and overturned.

====United States====
{{main|Age discrimination in the United States}}
In the United States, each [[List of states and territories of the United States|state]] has its own laws regarding age discrimination, and there are also federal laws.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.agediscrimination.info/international/Pages/USA.aspx USA]. Agediscrimination.info. Retrieved on 11 April 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; In California, the [[California Fair Employment and Housing Act of 1959|Fair Employment and Housing Act]] forbids unlawful discrimination against persons age 40 and older. The FEHA is the principal California statute prohibiting employment discrimination, covering employers, [[Trade union|labor organizations]], [[Employment agency|employment agencies]], apprenticeship programs and/or any person or entity who aids, abets, incites, compels, or coerces the doing of a discriminatory act. In addition to age, it prohibits employment discrimination based on race or color; religion; national origin or ancestry, [[disability]], mental type or medical condition; marital status; sex or sexual orientation; and pregnancy, childbirth, or related medical conditions.&lt;ref&gt;[http://finduslaw.com/california_fair_employment_and_housing_act_feha_government_code_12900_12996 California Fair Employment and Housing Act] FindLaw.&lt;/ref&gt; Although there are many protections for age-based discrimination against older workers (as shown above) there are less protections for younger workers.{{citation needed|date=January 2017}}

The [[District of Columbia]] and twelve states (California, Florida, [[Iowa]], Hawaii, [[Kansas]], [[Louisiana]], [[Maine]], [[Minnesota]], [[Nebraska]], [[New Mexico]], New York, and [[Vermont]]) define age as a specific motivation for hate crimes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Anti-Defamation League State Hate Crime Statutory Provisions (2005)|url=http://www.adl.org/learn/hate_crimes_laws/State_Hate_Crime_Statutory_Provisions_chart.pdf|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110629085842/http://www.adl.org/learn/hate_crimes_laws/State_Hate_Crime_Statutory_Provisions_chart.pdf|archive-date=29 June 2011|access-date=22 May 2009|df=dmy-all}}&amp;nbsp;{{small|(23.8&amp;nbsp;KB)}} (See page 1, section "Other", note 2) Retrieved on 21 May 2009&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Everyday Fears – A Survey of Violent Hate Crimes in Europe and North America|url=http://www.humanrightsfirst.org/discrimination/pdf/everyday-fears-080805.pdf|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20060112034643/http://www.humanrightsfirst.org/discrimination/pdf/everyday-fears-080805.pdf|archive-date=12 January 2006|access-date=22 May 2009|df=dmy-all}}&amp;nbsp;{{small|(1.96&amp;nbsp;MB)}} McClintock, Michael (See pages 84 and 122, Appendix 10, "Others", note 2) Retrieved on 21 May 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

The federal government restricts age discrimination under the [[Age Discrimination in Employment Act]] of 1967 (ADEA). That law provides certain employment protections to workers who are over the age of forty, who work for an employer who has twenty or more employees. For protected workers, the ADEA prohibits discrimination at all levels of employment, from recruitment and hiring, through the employment relationship, and through decisions for layoffs or termination of the employment relationship.&lt;ref name="auto1" /&gt; An age limit may only be legally specified for protected workers in the circumstance where age has been shown to be a "[[bona fide occupational qualification]] [BFOQ] reasonably necessary to the normal operation of the particular business" (see {{usc|29|623(f)(1)}}). In practice, BFOQs for age are limited to the obvious (hiring a young actor to play a young character in a movie) or when public safety is at stake (for example, in the case of age limits for pilots and bus drivers). The ADEA does not stop an employer from favoring an older employee over a younger one, even when the younger one is over 40 years old.&lt;ref name="auto2" /&gt;
[[File:Jimmy Carter participates in a bill signing ceremony - NARA - 178763.tif|thumb|President [[Jimmy Carter]] signing legislation against mandatory retirement in 1978]]
[[Mandatory retirement]] due to age is generally unlawful in the United States, except in certain industries and occupations that are regulated by law, and are often part of the government (such as military service and federal police agencies, such as the [[Federal Bureau of Investigation]]). [[Minnesota]] has statutorily established mandatory retirement for all judges at age 70 (more precisely, at the end of the month a judge reaches that age). The [[Minnesota Legislature]] has had the constitutional right to set judicial retirement ages since 1956, but did not do so until 1973, setting the age at 70.&lt;ref name="auto"&gt;{{cite news|last=Stassen-Berger|first=Rachel E.|date=July 7, 2015|title=Minnesota judges aren't making a fuss about retirement rule|newspaper=[[St. Paul Pioneer Press|Pioneer Press]]|location=[[Saint Paul, Minnesota|St. Paul, MN]]|url=http://www.twincities.com/politics/ci_28448632/rachel-stassen-berger-minnesota-judges-arent-making-fuss|access-date=December 28, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Federal Age Discrimination in Employment Act, which became law in 1986, ended mandatory age-related retirement at age 70 for many jobs, not including the Minnesota judiciary;&lt;ref name="auto" /&gt; another exception was all postsecondary institutions (colleges, etc.) This exception ended on December 31, 1993.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Weinberg|first1=Sharon L.|last2=Scott|first2=Marc A.|year=2013|title=The Impact of Uncapping of Mandatory Retirement on Postsecondary Institutions|url=https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/abs/10.3102/0013189X13497993|journal=Educational Researcher|volume=42|issue=6|pages=338–348|doi=10.3102/0013189X13497993|s2cid=13265704}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Sanjek, Roger (2009). Gray Panthers. Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Press, 185.&lt;/ref&gt; The Fair Treatment for Experienced Pilots Act (Public Law 110-135) went into effect on December 13, 2007, raising the mandatory retirement age for pilots to 65 from the previous 60.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release|url=http://www.faa.gov/news/press_releases/news_story.cfm?newsId=10072|title=FAA Statement on Pilot Retirement Age|date=14 December 2007|access-date=21 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In September 2016, California passed state bill AB-1687, an anti-ageism law taking effect on 1 January 2017, requiring "commercial online entertainment employment" services that allow paid subscribers to submit information and resumes (such as [[IMDB Pro]]), to honor requests to have their ages and birthdays removed. The bill was supported by [[SAG-AFTRA]]'s former and current presidents [[Ken Howard]] and [[Gabrielle Carteris]], who felt that the law would help to reduce ageism in the entertainment industry.&lt;ref name="thr-imdblaw"&gt;{{cite web|title=California Enacts Law Requiring IMDb to Remove Actor Ages on Request|url=https://www.hollywoodreporter.com/news/california-enacts-law-requiring-imdb-932330|access-date=15 November 2016|website=The Hollywood Reporter|date=24 September 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 23 February 2017, U.S. District Judge Vince Girdhari Chhabria issued a stay on the bill pending a further trial, claiming that it was "difficult to imagine how AB 1687 could not violate the [[First Amendment to the United States Constitution|First Amendment]]" because it inhibited the public consumption of factual information.&lt;ref name="thr-lawstruck"&gt;{{cite web|title=Judge Pauses Enforcement of IMDb Age Censorship Law|url=https://www.hollywoodreporter.com/thr-esq/judge-pauses-enforcement-imdb-age-censorship-law-978797|access-date=23 February 2017|website=The Hollywood Reporter|date=22 February 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; In February 2018, Girdhari ruled that the law was unconstitutional, arguing that the state of California "[had] not shown that partially eliminating one source of age-related information will appreciably diminish the amount of age discrimination occurring in the entertainment industry." The ruling was criticized by SAG-AFTRA, alleging that the court "incorrectly concluded there were no material disputed factual issues, while precluding the parties from acquiring additional evidence or permitting the case to go to trial". The ruling was eventually appealed, but the Ninth Circuit Court of Appeals upheld it in 2020.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|last=Pedersen|first=Erik|date=20 February 2018|title=California's IMDb Age Law Violates First Amendment, Federal Court Rules; SAG-AFTRA "Extremely Disappointed" – Update|language=en-US|work=Deadline|url=https://deadline.com/2018/02/imdb-age-law-violates-first-amendment-california-1202296413/|access-date=2018-02-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Asia ===

==== Australia ====
In regards to employment, discrimination on the basis of age is illegal in each of the states and territories of Australia. At the national level, Australia is party to a number of international treaties and conventions that impose obligations to eliminate age discrimination.&lt;ref name="bfr1"&gt;{{cite book|last1=Bittman|first1=Michael|url=http://www.jamesmahmudrice.info/SPRCR601.pdf|title=The Recruitment of Older Australian Workers: A Survey of Employers in a High Growth Industry|last2=Flick|first2=Mardi|last3=Rice|first3=James|publisher=Social Policy Research Centre, University of New South Wales|year=2001|isbn=978-0-7334-1908-9|location=Sydney|pages=14–15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Australian Human Rights Commission Act 1986 established the Australian Human Rights Commission and bestows on this Commission functions in relation to a number of international treaties and conventions that cover age discrimination.&lt;ref name="bfr1" /&gt;&lt;ref name="ahrc"&gt;{{cite web|title=Legislation &amp;#124; Australian Human Rights Commission|url=https://www.humanrights.gov.au/our-work/legal/legislation|access-date=27 April 2013|work=Australian Human Rights Commission}}&lt;/ref&gt; During 1998-1999, 15% of complaints received by the Commission under the Act were about discrimination on the basis of age.&lt;ref name="bfr1" /&gt;

Age discrimination laws at the national level were strengthened by the [[Age Discrimination Act 2004]], which helps to ensure that people are not subjected to age discrimination in various areas of public life, including employment, the provision of goods and services, education, and the administration of Australian government laws and programs. The Act, however, does provide for exemptions in some areas, as well as providing for positive discrimination, that is, actions which assist people of a particular age who experience a disadvantage because of their age.&lt;ref name="ahrc" /&gt;

In 2011, the position of Age Discrimination Commissioner was created within the Australian Human Rights Commission. The Commissioner's responsibilities include raising awareness among employers about the beneficial contributions that senior Australians as well as younger employees can make in the workforce.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.agediscrimination.info/News/Pages/ItemPage.aspx?Item=431 In Australia, new age discrimination laws have been passed by the Federal Parliament; a position of Age Discrimination Commissioner has been created in the Australian Human Rights Commission for the first time]. Agediscrimination.info (26 May 2011). Retrieved on 11 April 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; Every state in Australia has a probationary plate system for drivers. This is allowed because the Age Discrimination Act says that, in some circumstances, treating someone differently because of their age won't be against the law. This is known as an exemption and includes:

*things done in compliance with Commonwealth laws, including laws about taxation, social security and migration 
*things done in compliance with state and territory laws
*certain health and employment programmes
*youth wages or direct compliance with industrial agreements and awards.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.humanrights.gov.au/know-your-rights-age-discrimination When is age discrimination not against the law?] humanrights.gov.au Retrieved 7 March 2017&lt;/ref&gt;

====Philippines====
At least two bills have been filed before the [[16th Congress of the Philippines]] seeking to address age discrimination in employment in the country. The Blas Ople Policy Center, a non-government organization, asserts that responsibilities of making a livelihood in a household has shifted to younger members of the family due to bias against hiring people older than 30 years of age. The organization also added that age discrimination contributes to the unemployment rate and acts as a hurdle to [[inclusive growth]] in the country. [[Overseas Filipino Workers]] returning from abroad seeking to find work in the country were tagged as vulnerable to age discrimination.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Mateo|first1=Janvic|title=Law vs age discrimination in employment sought|url=http://www.philstar.com/headlines/2014/06/11/1333431/law-vs-age-discrimination-employment-sought|access-date=15 April 2015|work=The Philippine Star|date=11 June 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Lopez|first1=Ron|title=End age discrimination, Congress urged|url=http://www.mb.com.ph/end-age-discrimination-congress-urged/|access-date=15 April 2015|publisher=Manila Bulletin|date=8 May 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Europe===

====European Union====
The [[European Union|European]] citizenship provides the right to protection from discrimination on the grounds of age. According to Article 21-1 of the [[Charter of Fundamental Rights of the European Union|Charter of Fundamental Rights]] of the [[European Union]] [[s:Charter of Fundamental Rights of the European Union#CHAPTER III. EQUALITY]], "any discrimination based on any ground such as{{Nbsp}}… age, shall be prohibited".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.europarl.europa.eu/charter/pdf/text_en.pdf |title=Charter of Fundamental Rights of the European Union (official text) }}&amp;nbsp;{{small|(80.6&amp;nbsp;KB)}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Additional protection against age discrimination comes from the Framework Directive 2000/78/EC. It prohibits discrimination on grounds of age in the field of employment.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.agediscrimination.info/legislation/Pages/ECLegislation.aspx EC Legislation]. Agediscrimination.info. Retrieved on 11 April 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Germany====
On 18 August 2006, the General Equal Treatment Act (Allgemeines Gleichbehandlungsgesetz, AGG) came into force. The aim of the AGG is to prevent and abolish discrimination on various grounds including age.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.agediscrimination.info/international/Pages/Germany.aspx Germany]. Agediscrimination.info. Retrieved on 11 April 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

A recent{{when|date=December 2020}} study suggested that youths in Germany feel the brunt of age discrimination.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.agediscrimination.info/News/Pages/ItemPage.aspx?Item=580 Young in Germany feel brunt of age discrimination]. Agediscrimination.info (23 January 2012). Retrieved on 11 April 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

====France====
In France, Articles 225-1 through 225-4 of the [[Penal code|Penal Code]] detail the [[criminalization|penalization]] of Ageism, when it comes to an age discrimination related to the [[Consumption (economics)|consumption]] of a [[good (economics)|good]] or service, to the exercise of an economic activity, to the [[labour economics|labor market]] or an [[intern]]ship, except in the cases foreseen in Article 225-3.&lt;ref&gt;[http://195.83.177.9/code/liste.phtml?lang=uk&amp;c=33&amp;r=3716 French Penal Code (Legifrance)] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090817181231/http://195.83.177.9/code/liste.phtml?lang=uk&amp;c=33&amp;r=3716 |date=17 August 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.legifrance.gouv.fr/codes/id/LEGISCTA000006165298/2009-03-17/|title=Section 1 : Des discriminations (Articles 225-1 à 225-4) - Légifrance|website=www.legifrance.gouv.fr}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.agediscrimination.info/international/Pages/France.aspx France]. Agediscrimination.info. Retrieved on 11 April 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Belgium====
In [[Belgium]], the Law of 25 February 2003 "tending to fight discrimination" punishes Ageism when "a difference of treatment that lacks objective and reasonable justification is directly based on{{Nbsp}}... age". Discrimination is forbidden when it refers to providing or offering a good or service, to conditions linked to work or employment, to the appointment or [[promotion (rank)|promotion]] of an employee, and yet to the access or participation in "an economic, social, cultural or political activity accessible to the public" (Article 2nd, § 4). [[Incitement]] to discrimination, to [[hatred]] or to violence against a person or a group on the grounds of{{Nbsp}}... age (Article 6) is punished with [[incarceration|imprisonment]] and/or a [[fine (penalty)|fine]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.stop-discrimination.info/fileadmin/pdfs/Nationale_Inhalte/Belgium/Gesetz/25.02.2003.pdf |title=Belgium Law of 25 Feb 2003 against discrimination |language=fr}}&amp;nbsp;{{small|(76.5&amp;nbsp;KB)}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.agediscrimination.info/international/Pages/Belgium.aspx Belgium]. Agediscrimination.info. Retrieved on 11 April 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;
Nevertheless, employment opportunities are worsening for people in their middle years in many of these same countries, according to Martin Kohli ''et al.'' in ''Time for Retirement'' (1991).

====Sweden====
The Swedish Discrimination Act (2008:567) was enacted in 2008 and states that: "the purpose of the Act is to combat discrimination and in other ways promote equal rights and opportunities regardless of sex{{Nbsp}}... or age."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Official translation of the Swedish Discrimination Act |url=https://www.government.se/4a788f/contentassets/6732121a2cb54ee3b21da9c628b6bdc7/oversattning-diskrimineringslagen_eng.pdf |website=Government Offices of Sweden |access-date=14 October 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt; In Sweden, considering the increased proportion of older people, ageism is also discussed in the context of healthcare sector and health profession students such as nursing students.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title=Classic Tool, New Opportunities: A Psychometric Analysis of a Swedish Online Version of the Aging Semantic Differential Scale |journal=Research on Aging |year=2020 |doi=10.1177/0164027520963618 |last1=Holmberg |first1=Christopher |last2=Wolf |first2=Axel |last3=Eide |first3=Camilla |last4=Großschädl |first4=Franziska |last5=Schüttengruber |first5=Gerhilde |last6=Patel |first6=Harshida |last7=Heckemann |first7=Birgit |volume=43 |issue=9–10 |pages=378–387 |pmid=34524931 |doi-access=free }}&lt;/ref&gt;

====United Kingdom====
[[File:Barbara Robb c.1941.jpg|thumb|[[Barbara Robb]], founder of the [[Aid for the Elderly in Government Institutions]] pressure group]]
[[Barbara Robb]], founder of the British pressure group, [[Aid for the Elderly in Government Institutions]] (AEGIS), compiled ''Sans Everything: A Case to Answer'', a controversial book detailing the inadequacies of care provided for older people, which prompted a nationwide scandal in the UK in 1976. Although initially official inquiries into these allegations reported that they were "totally unfounded or grossly exaggerated",&lt;ref&gt;'Sans Everything (Reports of Inquiries)' ''Hansard'' HC Deb 9 July 1968 vol 768 cc213–6, 214&lt;/ref&gt; her campaigns led to revealing of other instances of ill treatment which were accepted and prompted the government to implement NHS policy changes.&lt;ref name="Anon 1974"&gt;Anon, 'Disturbing report on a hospital: health authorities to be asked to review standards of care' ''Times'', 16 May 1974, 16&lt;/ref&gt;

As noted above, Councillor Richard Thomas brought up the issue of age discrimination at an early stage at a meeting of Bracknell Forest Council in March 1983. He pointed out it is a double side process, with discrimination working against both older and younger citizens.

So, in the UK, laws against ageism are new. Age discrimination laws were only brought into force in October 2006,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.agediscrimination.info/legislation/Pages/IntheUK.aspx In the UK] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110326041717/http://www.agediscrimination.info/legislation/Pages/IntheUK.aspx |date=26 March 2011 }}. Agediscrimination.info. Retrieved on 11 April 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; and can now be found in the [[Equality Act 2010]]. This implements the Equal Treatment Framework Directive [[2000/78/EC]] and protects employees against direct discrimination, [[indirect discrimination]], [[harassment]] and [[victimisation]]. Pursuant to the [[Equality Act 2010]] it is generally unlawful to discriminate based upon age in the provision of goods and services.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Age discrimination - when discrimination is allowed in the provision of goods or services |url=https://www.citizensadvice.org.uk/consumer/discrimination-in-the-provision-of-goods-and-services/discrimination-in-the-provision-of-goods-and-services1/goods-and-services-what-are-the-different-types-of-discrimination/what-doesn-t-count-as-unlawful-discrimination-in-goods-and-services/age-discrimination-when-discrimination-is-allowed-in-the-provision-of-goods-or-services/ |website=Citizens Advice |access-date=27 April 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite the relatively recent{{when|date=December 2020}} prohibition on age discrimination, there have already been many notable cases and official statistics show a 37% increase in claims in 2009/10&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.agediscrimination.info/News/Pages/ItemPage.aspx?Item=218 37% rise in age discrimination claims]. Agediscrimination.info (8 July 2010). Retrieved on 11 April 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; and a further 31% increase in 2010/11.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.agediscrimination.info/News/Pages/ItemPage.aspx?Item=470 Age discrimination claims increase by 79%, Tribunal Service statistics show]. Agediscrimination.info (31 March 2011). Retrieved on 11 April 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; Examples include the case involving Rolls Royce,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.agediscrimination.info/cases/Pages/ItemPage.aspx?Item=93 ItemPage] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110721183803/http://www.agediscrimination.info/cases/Pages/ItemPage.aspx?Item=93 |date=21 July 2011 }}. Agediscrimination.info (14 May 2009). Retrieved on 11 April 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; the "Heyday" case brought by [[Age UK]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.agediscrimination.info/cases/Pages/ItemPage.aspx?Item=114 ItemPage] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110721183813/http://www.agediscrimination.info/cases/Pages/ItemPage.aspx?Item=114 |date=21 July 2011 }}. Agediscrimination.info (25 September 2009). Retrieved on 11 April 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; and the recent{{when|date=December 2020}} [[Miriam O'Reilly]] case against the [[BBC]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.agediscrimination.info/cases/Pages/ItemPage.aspx?Item=412 ItemPage] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110817013151/http://www.agediscrimination.info/cases/Pages/ItemPage.aspx?Item=412 |date=17 August 2011 }}. Agediscrimination.info (10 January 2011). Retrieved on 11 April 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

Recent{{when|date=December 2020}} research suggested that the number of age discrimination claims annually could reach 15,000 by 2015.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.agediscrimination.info/News/Pages/ItemPage.aspx?Item=476 Age discrimination claims will continue to rise and peak at nearly 15,000 a year by 2015]. Agediscrimination.info (7 July 2011). Retrieved on 11 April 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

The European Social Study survey in 2011 revealed that nearly two out of five people claim to have been shown a lack of respect because of their age. The survey suggested that the UK is riven by intergenerational splits, with half of the people admitting they do not have a single friend over 70; this compares with only a third of Portuguese, Swiss and Germans who say that they do not have a friend of that age or older.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.agediscrimination.info/News/Pages/ItemPage.aspx?Item=546 UK among Europe's worst countries for Ageism and age discrimination]. Agediscrimination.info (30 October 2011). Retrieved on 11 April 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; A Demos study in 2012 showed that three-quarters of people in the UK believed there to be not enough opportunities for older and younger people to meet and work together.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.agediscrimination.info/News/Pages/ItemPage.aspx?Item=637 Older people in Britain are more concerned about age discrimination than their European neighbours]. Agediscrimination.info (25 May 2012). Retrieved on 30 May 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

The "Grey Pride" campaign has been advocating for a Minister for Older People and its campaign has had some success, with Labour Leader [[Ed Miliband]] appointing [[Liz Kendall]] as Shadow Minister for Older People.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.agediscrimination.info/News/Pages/ItemPage.aspx?Item=555 Shadow minister for older people is a 'thorn in the side' of the coalition]. Agediscrimination.info (25 October 2011). Retrieved on 11 April 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

The artist Michael Freedman, an outspoken advocate against age discrimination within the art world says that "mature students, like me, come to art late in life, so why are we penalised and demotivated? Whatever happened to lifelong learning and the notion of a flexible workforce?"&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://www.michaelfreedman.co.uk/2011/12/ageism-in-the-art-world/|first = Michael|last = Freedman|title = Ageism in the Art World|date = 29 December 2011|url-status = dead|archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20140508205817/http://www.michaelfreedman.co.uk/2011/12/ageism-in-the-art-world/|archive-date = 8 May 2014|access-date = 15 April 2019|df = dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Advocacy against ageism==
[[File:Child Labor in United States 1910 working night shift.jpg|thumb|A 14-year-old newsboy in [[New York City]], 1910]]
The [[Newsboys Strike of 1899]] fought ageist employment practices targeted against youth by large newspaper syndicates in the [[Northeastern United States|Northeast]] of America. The strikers demonstrated across the city for several days, effectively stopping circulation of the two papers, along with the news distribution for many [[New England]] cities. The [[Strike action|strike]] lasted two weeks, causing Pulitzer's ''[[New York World]]'' to decrease its circulation from 360,000 papers sold per day to 125,000.&lt;ref&gt;Nasaw, David. (1999) "Ch. 3: Youse an' yer noble scrap: On strike with the Newsboy Legion in 1899." in ''Big Town, Big Time.'' New York: New York Daily News. p. 9.&lt;/ref&gt; Although the price of papers was not lowered, the strike was successful in forcing the ''World'' and ''Journal'' to offer full buybacks to their sellers, thus increasing the amount of money that newsies received for their work.&lt;ref&gt;Mott, F.L. (2000) ''American Journalism''. New York: Routledge. p. 598.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[American Youth Congress]], or AYC, was formed in 1935 to advocate for [[youth rights]] in U.S. politics. It ended in 1940.&lt;ref&gt;Black, A., Hopkins, J. ''et al.'' (2003) [http://www.nps.gov/archive/elro/glossary/american-youth-congress.htm "American Youth Congress,"] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20071019032029/http://www.nps.gov/archive/elro/glossary/american-youth-congress.htm |date=October 19, 2007 }} ''The Eleanor Roosevelt Papers.'' Teaching Eleanor Roosevelt. Hyde Park, New York: Eleanor Roosevelt National Historic Site. Retrieved 7/30/07.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:AARP Pride Booth Boston 2017.png|thumb|[[AARP]] booth at [[Boston]] Pride Festival, 2017]]
[[AARP]] was founded in 1958 by [[Ethel Percy Andrus]] (a retired educator from California) and Leonard Davis (later the founder of the [[Colonial Penn Life Insurance Company|Colonial Penn Group]] of insurance companies).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|work=Los Angeles Times|url=https://articles.latimes.com/2001/jan/23/local/me-15772|date=January 23, 2001|title=Local: Obituary}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://news.usc.edu/6078/Obituary-AARP-founder-philanthropist-Leonard-Davis-76/|work=USC News|title=AARP Founder: Philanthropist Leonard Davis, 76}}&lt;/ref&gt; Its stated mission is "to empower people to choose how they live as they age".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url= https://www.aarp.org/about-aarp/|title=About AARP|access-date=2018-11-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is an influential [[lobbying]] group in the United States focusing largely on issues affecting the elderly.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.thenonprofittimes.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/8-1-15_Top50PI.pdf|title=The 2015 Power &amp; Influence Top 50|date=August 31, 2015|website=The NonProfit Times|publisher=The NonProfit Times}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://thehill.com/business-a-lobbying/top-lobbyists/258317-top-lobbyists-2015-grassroots|title=Top Lobbyists 2015: Grassroots|last=Dickson|first=Rebecca|date=October 28, 2015|access-date=2016-09-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Aid for the Elderly in Government Institutions]] (AEGIS) was a British [[pressure group]] that campaigned to improve the care of older people in long-stay wards of [[National Health Service]] [[psychiatric hospitals]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://archives.lse.ac.uk/Record.aspx?src=CalmView.Catalog&amp;id=AEGIS|title=AEGIS - AEGIS (Aid to the Elderly in Government Institutions)|website=LSE Library Services|access-date=2016-05-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Whitewash"&gt;{{Cite news|title=Whitewash in the old folks' wards|last=Robinson|first=Anne|date=5 April 1970|work=Sunday Times}}&lt;/ref&gt; The group was founded by [[Barbara Robb]] in 1965,&lt;ref name="Whitewash" /&gt; and was active until her death in 1976.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=The patients' campaigner|date=25 June 1976|work=Hampstead and Highgate Express}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Gray Panthers]] was formed in 1970 by [[Maggie Kuhn]], with a goal of eliminating [[mandatory retirement]] in the United States; they now work on many [[social justice]] issues including eliminating ageism.&lt;ref&gt;Kuhn, M., Long, C. and Quinn, L. (1991) ''No Stone Unturned: the Life and Times of Maggie Kuhn.'' Ballantine Books.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.aarp.org/politics-society/history/champions-of-aging-photos/older-american-maggie-kuhn-gray-panthers.html|title=Maggie Kuhn - Champions of Aging|first=Patrick J.|last=Kiger|website=AARP}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.graypanthersnyc.org/about_us/ |title=About Us |publisher=Gray Panthers Nyc |date=2018-08-27 |access-date=2020-04-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Youth Liberation of Ann Arbor]] started in 1970 to promote youth and fight ageism.

[[Three O'Clock Lobby]] formed in 1976 to promote [[youth participation]] throughout traditionally ageist government structures in Michigan.

Old Lesbians Organizing for Change was founded in 1987; the mission of the organization is to "eliminate the oppression of ageism and to stand in solidarity against all oppressions" through “[the] cooperative community of Old Lesbian feminist activists from many backgrounds working for justice and the well-being of all old lesbians.”&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://oac.cdlib.org/findaid/ark:/13030/c8z89fjx/|title=Finding Aid for the Old Lesbians Organizing for Change records 1986-1992 LSC.2203|website=oac.cdlib.org}}&lt;/ref&gt; Their initial meeting was inspired by the publication of the book ''[https://archive.org/details/isbn_9781883523404 Look Me in the Eye: Old Women, Aging and Ageism]'' by [[Barbara Macdonald]] and Cynthia Rich in 1983.&lt;ref name="ref2"&gt;{{cite web
 | url=http://asteria.fivecolleges.edu/findaids/sophiasmith/mnsss547_bioghist.html
 | title=Old Lesbians Organizing for Change Records
 | access-date=27 March 2015
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Americans for a Society Free from Age Restrictions]] formed in 1996 to advance the civil and human rights of young people through eliminating ageist laws targeted against young people, and to help youth counter ageism in America.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|work=ASFAR |year=2006 |url=http://www.asfar.org/articles.php |title=Americans for a Society Free from Age Restrictions Articles of Incorporation |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070609192032/http://www.asfar.org/articles.php |archive-date=9 June 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:NYRA Berkeley voting age protest.jpg|thumb|[[National Youth Rights Association]] members protesting the [[Voting age#U|voting age]] in [[Berkeley, California]] (2004)]]
The [[National Youth Rights Association]] started in 1998 to promote awareness of the legal and human rights of young people in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|work=National Youth Rights Association|year=2001|url=http://www.youthrights.org/docs/nyraarticlesofinc.pdf|title=National Youth Rights Association Articles of Incorporation (Partial)}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Freechild Project]] was formed in 2001 in the United States to identify, unify and promote diverse opportunities for youth engagement in social change by fighting ageism.

===Related campaigns===
Director [[Paul Weitz (filmmaker)|Paul Weitz]] reported he wrote the 2004 film, ''[[In Good Company (2004 film)|In Good Company]]'', to reveal how ageism affects youth and adults.&lt;ref&gt;Hellerman, A. (2005) [http://www.wgaeast.org/features/2005/03/18/paul_weitz/index.html Working Solo in Good Company]{{Dead link|date=May 2019 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }} Writers Guild of America, East website.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2002 [[The Freechild Project]] created an information and training initiative to provide resources to youth organizations and schools focused on youth rights.&lt;ref&gt;(n.d.) [http://www.freechild.org/SNAYR/index.htm Survey of North American Youth Rights] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070206100316/http://www.freechild.org/SNAYR/index.htm |date=6 February 2007 }} The Freechild Project website.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2006 Lydia Giménez-LLort, an assistant professor of Psychiatry and researcher at the [[Autonomous University of Barcelona]] coined the term 'Snow White Syndrome' at the 'Congrés de la Gent Gran de Cerdanyola del Vallès' (Congress of the Elderly of Cerdanyola del Vallès, Barcelona, Spain) as a metaphor to define Ageism in an easier and more friendly way while developing a constructive spirit against it. The metaphor is based on both the auto-Ageism and adultocracy exhibited by the [[Queen (Snow White)|evil queen]] of the [[Snow White]] fairy tale as well as the social Ageism symbolized by the mirror.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.saberenvejecer.es/saberhacer_30.html|language=es|title=Envellir bé · Successful Ageing · Saber Envejecer website – Know-how.|access-date=13 May 2009|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090425094931/http://www.saberenvejecer.es/saberhacer_30.html|archive-date=25 April 2009|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Since 2008 'The Intergenerational Study' by Lydia Giménez-LLort and Paula Ramírez-Boix from the [[Autonomous University of Barcelona]] is aimed to find the basis of the link between grandparents and grandsons (positive family relationships) that can minimize the Ageism towards the elderly. Students of several Spanish universities have enrolled in this study which soon will be also performed in the US, Nigeria, Barbados, Argentina, and Mexico. The preliminary results reveal that 'The Intergenerational study questionnaire' induces young people to do a reflexive and autocritic analysis of their intergenerational relationships in contrast to those shown towards other unrelated old people which results very positive to challenge Ageism. A cortometrage about 'The International Study' has been directed and produced by Tomás Sunyer from [[Los Angeles City College]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.saberenvejecer.es/investigar_25.html|language=es|title=Envellir bé : Successful Ageing · Saber envejecer website – Research.|access-date=13 May 2009|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090423185650/http://www.saberenvejecer.es/investigar_25.html|archive-date=23 April 2009|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Votes at 16]] intends to lower the [[voting age]] in the United Kingdom to 16, reducing Ageism and giving 16-year-olds equal pay on the [[National Minimum Wage]]. The group claims that 16-year-olds get less money than older people for the same work, angering many 16-year-olds. They additionally postulate that 16-year-olds will have their voice listened to by older people more often.

Chilean director [[Sebastian Lelio]] created a U.S. version of his acclaimed 2013 film ''[[Gloria (2013 film)|Gloria]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.theatlantic.com/entertainment/archive/2017/11/will-a-us-adaptation-ruin-sebastian-lelios-gloria/543951/|title=Will a U.S. Adaptation Ruin Sebastian Lelio's Gloria?|last=Abbady|first=Tal|date=26 November 2017|website=The Atlantic|access-date=28 November 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; The original film challenges the notion that as women age they become culturally 'invisible';&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Isopahkala-Bouret|first=Ulpukka|date=2017|title="It's a great benefit to have gray hair!": The intersection of gender, aging, and visibility in midlife professional women's narratives|journal=Journal of Women &amp; Aging|volume=29|issue=3|pages=267–277|doi=10.1080/08952841.2016.1142773|pmid=27629496|s2cid=33967941}}&lt;/ref&gt; they may continue to be powerful, desirable, and sexually active. In the 2018 English [[remake]], titled ''[[Gloria Bell]]'', actress [[Julianne Moore]] portrayed the lead character.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.hollywoodreporter.com/news/cannes-julianne-moore-star-imagining-sebastian-lelios-gloria-1002948|title=Cannes: Julianne Moore to Star in Re-Imagining of Sebastian Lelio's 'Gloria'|last=Ford|first=Rebecca|date=12 May 2017|website=Hollywood Reporter|access-date=28 November 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last1=Dargis |first1=Manohla |title='Gloria Bell' Review: Love Is in the Air for a Transcendent Julianne Moore |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2019/03/07/movies/gloria-bell-review.html |access-date=29 July 2019 |work=The New York Times |date=7 March 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Accusations of ageism===
In a 2005 interview, actor [[Pierce Brosnan]] cited ageism as one of the contributing factors as to why he was not asked to continue his role as [[James Bond]] in the Bond film ''[[Casino Royale (2006 film)|Casino Royale]]'', released in 2006.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last = Cox|first = John|date = 5 November 2005|url = http://commanderbond.net/article/2994|title = Brosnan Bares All For Playboy|website = CommanderBond.net|url-status = dead|archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20060702020428/http://commanderbond.net/article/2994|archive-date = 2 July 2006|access-date = 15 April 2019|df = dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Also, successful singer and actress [[Madonna (entertainer)|Madonna]] spoke out in her 50s about ageism and her fight to defy the norms of society.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|date = 18 June 2008|url = http://www.carefair.com/html/Madonna_Not_Giving_In_to_Ageism_5301.html|title = Madonna not giving in to Ageism|publisher = Care Fair|url-status = dead|archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20081013071815/http://www.carefair.com/html/Madonna_Not_Giving_In_to_Ageism_5301.html|archive-date = 13 October 2008|access-date = 17 January 2009|df = dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2015, [[Radio 1 Madonna controversy|BBC Radio 1 were accused of ageism]] after the station did not add her new single to their playlist. Similarly, ''[[Sex and the City]]'' star [[Kim Cattrall]] has also raised the issue of ageism.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.agediscrimination.info/News/Pages/ItemPage.aspx?Item=382 Kim Cattrall's red carpet rant: "down with Ageism and age discrimination"]. Agediscrimination.info (5 April 2011). Retrieved on 11 April 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

A 2007 [[Pew Research Center]] study found that a majority of American voters would be less likely to vote for a President past a given age,{{which|date=November 2017}} with 45% saying that age would not matter.{{citation needed|date=November 2017}}

[[Margaret Morganroth Gullette]]'s 2017 book, ''Ending Ageism or How Not to Shoot Old People'', provides multiple examples to illustrate the pervasiveness of ageism and delivers a call to action.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url = https://www.wbur.org/artery/2017/08/15/ending-ageism |title = Who Are You Calling Old? Brandeis Scholar Argues For An End To Ageism |author = Erin Trahan |date = 15 August 2017 |publisher = The ARTery}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{cols|colwidth=20em}}
* [[Adultism]]
* [[Age discrimination in the United States]]
* [[Age stratification]]
* [[Aging brain]]
* [[Aging in the American workforce]] (related: the "[[The Silver Tsunami|silver tsunami]]" metaphor)
* [[Codename: Kids Next Door]]
* [[Elder rights]]
* [[Ephebiphobia]]
* [[Generation]]
* [[Gerontocracy]]
* [[Gerontophobia]]
* [[International Day of Older Persons]]
* [[Mandatory retirement]]
* [[Memory and aging]]
* [[OK boomer]]
* [[Pedophobia (social phenomena)|Pedophobia]]
* [[Power harassment]]
* [[Prejudice]]
* [[Rankism]]
* [[The Silver Tsunami]] (metaphor)
* [[You kids get off my lawn!]]
* [[Youth exclusion]]
* [[Youth rights]]
* [[Youth unemployment]]
{{colend}}

==References==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==External links==
{{Wiktionary|Ageism}}
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20181215174553/http://www.blackwell-synergy.com/toc/josi/61/2 2005 issue of the ''Journal of Social Issues''] Thematic journal issue devoted to empirical and theoretical research on Ageism.
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20091220050523/http://knol.google.com/k/solomon-tse/ageism/38s05w5hp4v3n/2 Ageism – Discrimination Against Age] A Knol examining Ageism and social attitudes against different age groups.
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20120625182547/http://www.agediscriminationatwork.com/ Age Discrimination at Work: Wellpoint/Blue Cross]
* [http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/business/5334972.stm Age discrimination laws by the BBC]
* [http://www.agediscrimination.info/statistics Age discrimination statistics for the UK, Europe and the world]
* [https://osha.europa.eu/en/themes/osh-management-context-ageing-workforce Ageing at work] [[EU-OSHA]]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20051130221014/http://mitpress.mit.edu/catalog/item/default.asp?ttype=2&amp;tid=10385 Ageism: Stereotyping and Prejudice Against Older Persons] Edited scholarly volume of the latest research and theory on Ageism.
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20180418210246/http://hrsbstaff.ednet.ns.ca/engramja/projects%26evals/sem2_mag1/chantellemag/chanceessay.htm Everyone deserves to be given a chance] An essay against Ageism towards teenagers, written by a Canadian adolescent.
* [https://web.archive.org/web/19980624160419/http://www.webster.edu/~woolflm/ageism.html An in-depth look at Ageism by Linda M. Woolfe, PhD, of Webster University]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20071016054502/http://www.luhs.org/depts/injprev/Transprt/tran3.htm#Older%20Drivers Article on Older Drivers].
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20120430000518/http://www.ilcusa.org/prj/ageism.htm Ageism In America] Detailed report on Ageism from the International Longevity Center.
* {{cite journal|last=Ayalon|first=Liat|title=Feelings towards Older vs. Younger Adults: Results from the European Social Survey|journal=Educational Gerontology|volume=39|issue=12|pages=888–901|doi=10.1080/03601277.2013.767620 |year=2013|s2cid=143103077}}
* [http://www.overfiftyandoutofwork.com/experts/susan-fiske-mike-north/ Interview] with social psychologists [[Susan Fiske]] and Mike North about common stereotypes of older people. ({{cite journal|last = Ayalon|first = Liat|title = Feelings towards Older vs. Younger Adults: Results from the European Social Survey|journal = Educational Gerontology|year = 2013|volume = 39|issue = 12|pages = 888–901|doi = 10.1080/03601277.2013.767620 |s2cid = 143103077}})
* {{cite journal|last=Ayalon|first=Liat|author2=Doron, I |author3=Bodner, E |author4=Inbar, N |title=Macro- and micro-level predictors of age categorization: results from the European Social Survey|journal=European Journal of Ageing|year=2014|volume=11|issue=1|pages=5–18 |doi=10.1007/s10433-013-0282-8|pmid=28804310 |pmc=5549183}}
* [http://www.oloc.org/ Old Lesbians Organizing for Change]
* {{cite journal|last=Yechezkel|first=Rachel|author2=Ayalon, Liat|title=Social Workers' Attitudes towards Intimate Partner Abuse in Younger vs. Older Women|journal=Journal of Family Violence|year=2013|volume=28|issue=4|pages=381–391 |doi=10.1007/s10896-013-9506-0|s2cid=21902989}}
* [https://www.usatoday.com/money/companies/management/2008-08-12-obama-mccain-age-ceos_N.htm USA Today article examining old and young CEOs about the ages of John McCain and Barack Obama]

== Further reading ==
{{refbegin|30em}}
* {{Cite book
         |last=Applewhite
         |first=Ashton
         |title=This Chair Rocks: A Manifesto Against Ageism |url=http://amzn.com/0996934707
         |year=2016
         |isbn=978-0996934701}}
*Ayalon, L., &amp; Tesch-Römer, C. (Eds.). (2018). ''[https://www.springer.com/gp/book/9783319738192 Contemporary perspectives on ageism]''. Springer International Publishing.
* {{Cite book
         |last=Barnes
         |first=Patricia G.
         |title=Betrayed: The Legalization of Age Discrimination in the Workplace |year=2014
         |isbn=978-0-9898708-1-8}}
* {{Cite book|last=Bergling|first=Tim|title=Reeling in the Years: Gay Men's Perspectives on Age and Ageism|year=2004|publisher=Southern Tier Editions, Harrington Park Press|location=New York, NY|isbn=978-1-56023-370-1|oclc=52166116}}
* {{Cite book|last=Bytheway|first=Bill|title=Ageism|year=1995|publisher=Open University Press|location=Buckingham; Bristol, PA|isbn=978-0-335-19176-5|oclc=30733778}}
* {{Cite book|last=Calasanti|first=Toni M. and Kathleen F. Slevin|title=Age Matters: Realigning Feminist Thinking|year=2006|publisher=Routledge|location=New York, NY|isbn=978-0-415-95223-1|oclc=65400440|url-access=registration|url=https://archive.org/details/agemattersrealig0000unse}}
* {{Cite book|last=Copper|first=Barbara|title=Ageism in the Lesbian Community|journal=Journal of Lesbian Studies|volume=19|issue=1|pages=7–12|year=1987|publisher=Crossing Press|location=Freedom, California|isbn=978-0895942364|oclc=16331354|pmid=25575317|doi=10.1080/10894160.2015.972303|s2cid=39302695}}
* {{Cite book|last=Cruikshank |first=Margaret|title=Learning to be Old: Gender, Culture, and Aging|year=2003|publisher=Rowman &amp; Littlefield Publishers|location=Lanham, MD|isbn=978-0-8476-9848-6|oclc=49566317}}
* {{Cite book|last=Eglit|first=Howard C.|title=Elders on Trial: Age and Ageism in the American Legal System|year=2004|publisher=University Press of Florida|location=Gainesville, FL|isbn=978-0-8130-2765-4|oclc=56482087}}
* {{Cite book|last=Gaster |first=Lucy|title=Past it at 40?: A Grassroots View of Ageism and Discrimination in Employment: A Report|year=2002|publisher=The Policy Press|location=Bristol, UK|isbn=978-1-86134-484-7|oclc=51802692}}
* {{Cite book|last=Glover |first=Ian and Mohamed Branine|title=Ageism in Work and Employment|year=2001|publisher=Ashgate|location=Aldershot, UK; Burlington, VT|isbn=978-1-84014-149-8|oclc=45487982}}
* {{Cite book|last=Gravagne|first=Pamela H.|title=The Becoming of Age: Cinematic Visions of Mind, Body and Identity in Later Life|year=2013|publisher=McFarland|location=Jefferson, NC|isbn=978-0-7864-7260-4}}
* {{Cite book|last=Gullette|first=Margaret Morganroth|title=Aged by Culture|year=2004|publisher=University of Chicago Press|location=Chicago, IL|isbn=978-0-226-31062-6|oclc=52514302}}
* {{Cite book|last=Gullette|first=Margaret Morganroth|title=Agewise: Fighting the New Ageism in America|year=2011|publisher=University of Chicago Press|location=Chicago, IL|isbn=978-0-226-31073-2}}
* {{Cite book|last=Gullette|first=Margaret Morganroth|title=Declining to Decline: Cultural Combat and the Politics of the Midlife|year=1997|publisher=University Press of Virginia|location=Charlottesville, VA|isbn=978-0-8139-1721-4|oclc=35986171}}
* {{cite journal | last1 = Kimmel | first1 = D.C. | year = 1988 | title = Ageism, psychology, and public policy | journal = American Psychologist | volume = 43 | issue = 3| pages = 175–178 | doi=10.1037/0003-066x.43.3.175| pmid = 3364853 }}
* {{cite journal | last1 = Kite | first1 = M.E. | last2 = Johnson | first2 = B.T. | year = 1988 | title = Attitudes towards older and younger adults: A meta-analysis | journal = Psychology and Aging | volume = 3 | issue = 3| pages = 232–244 | doi=10.1037/0882-7974.3.3.233}}
* {{Cite book|last=Lagacé |first=Martine, &amp; ''al.''|title=L'Âgisme: Comprendre et changer le regard social sur le vieillissement|year=2010|publisher=Presses de l'Université Laval (PUL)|location=Quebec city, Quebec, Canada|isbn=978-2-7637-8781-7|oclc=632095367}}
* {{Cite book|editor=[[Robin Morgan]]|title=Sisterhood Is Forever: The Women's Anthology for a New Millennium (specifically the piece "The Politics of Aging" by Barbara Macdonald)|year=2003|publisher=Washington Square Press|location=New York City, New York|isbn=978-0-7434-6627-1|oclc=760003303|url=https://archive.org/details/sisterhoodisfore00morg}}
* {{Cite book|editor=[[Robin Morgan]]|title=Sisterhood is Powerful: An Anthology of Writings From The Women's Liberation Movement (specifically the piece "It hurts to be alive and obsolete: the ageing woman" by Zoe Moss)|year=1970|publisher=Random House|location=New York City, New York|isbn=978-0-394-70539-2|oclc=96157|title-link=Sisterhood is Powerful: An Anthology of Writings From The Women's Liberation Movement}}
* {{Cite book|author=[[Barbara Macdonald]] and Cynthia Rich|title=Look Me in the Eye: Old Women, Aging and Ageism|year=2001|publisher=Spinsters Ink Books|location=Tallahassee, FL|isbn=978-1883523404|oclc=198557801|url=https://archive.org/details/isbn_9781883523404}}
* {{Cite book|last=Macnicol|first=John|title=Age Discrimination: An Historical and Contemporary Analysis|year=2006|publisher=Cambridge University|location=Cambridge|isbn=978-0-521-84777-3|oclc=61176543}}
* {{Cite book|last=Nelson |first=Todd D.|title=Ageism: Stereotyping and Prejudice Against Older Persons|year=2002|publisher=MIT Press|location=Cambridge, MA|isbn=978-0-262-14077-5|oclc=47863229}}
* {{cite journal | last1 = Nelson | first1 = T. D. | s2cid = 10632570 | year = 2005 | title = Ageism: Prejudice against our feared future self | journal = Journal of Social Issues | volume = 61 | issue = 2| pages = 207–221 | doi=10.1111/j.1540-4560.2005.00402.x}}
* Nelson, T. D. (2015). Ageism. In T. D. Nelson (Ed.), Handbook of Prejudice, Stereotyping, and Discrimination (2nd Ed.). New York: Psychology Press. 
* {{Cite book|editor-last=Palmore|editor-first=Erdman|editor2=Laurence Branch|editor3=Diana Harris|title=Encyclopedia of Ageism|year=2005|publisher=Haworth Pastoral Press: Haworth Reference Press|location=Binghamton, NY|isbn=978-0-7890-1889-2|oclc=55801014|url-access=registration|url=https://archive.org/details/encyclopediaofag0000unse_f4c1}}
* Prokurat S., Fabisiak J., ''Age Management as a Tool for the Demographic Decline in the 21st Century: An Overview of its Characteristics'', Journal of Entrepreneurship, Management and Innovation, 8/2012, p.&amp;nbsp;83-96.
* {{Cite book|last=Thompson |first=Neil|title=Anti-Discriminatory Practice|edition= 4th|year=2006|publisher=Palgrave Macmillan|location=Basingstoke, England; New York, NY|isbn=978-1-4039-2160-4|oclc=62302620}}
{{refend}}

{{Discrimination}}

[[Category:1969 neologisms]]
[[Category:Ageism| ]]
[[Category:Human rights by issue]]
[[Category:Prejudice and discrimination by type]]
[[Category:Youth rights]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>