<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20051104065726|27328128" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="22648231" pageid="22648231" ns="0" title="Ageism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-11-04T06:58:36Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Ageism''' is [[bias]] against a person or group on the grounds of [[aging|age]].  When that bias is the primary motivation behind acts of discrimination against that person or group, then those acts constitute '''age discrimination'''.

==The two most common forms==

Although ageism can refer to bias against any age group, ageism (and age discrimination) are usually focused on two targets: 
*[[Adolescence|Adolescents]] (Ageism against adolescents is also called "[[Adultism]]")
*The [[elderly]] (Just like Schyler)

==Examples==

===Ageism===

An example of ageism is thinking that all [[teenager]]s like rock music, are immature and insubordinate, use [[slang]] and [[profanity]], and watch R-rated movies; or that all elderly are slow, weak, demented and dependent.

===Age discrimination===

Although like all forms of discrimination, age discrimination has always been a problem, it is most severe at present in the entertainment and computer industries.  Many elderly actors, musicians, scriptwriters, programmers, and electrical engineers have all complained that it is difficult for them to find work, even though they are overwhelmingly well-qualified in terms of education and experience.
 
In a survey for the [[University of Kent]], [[England]], 29% of respondents stated that they had suffered from age discrimination.  This is a higher proportion than for [[Sexism|gender]] or [[Racism|race]] discrimination.  Dominic Abrams, Social Psychology professor at the University, concluded that ageism is the most pervasive form of prejudice experienced in the UK population.  [http://www.ageconcern.org.uk/AgeConcern/media/how_ageist_is_britain.pdf How Ageist is Britain?] - [[Age Concern]] survey (PDF).

==Responses==

===Grass-roots activism===

Many groups have been set up in various countries to combat age discrimination, including:
*[[United Kingdom]]
**[[Age Concern]]
**[[Help the Aged]]
*[[United States]]
**[[Americans for a Society Free from Age Restrictions]]
**[[Gray Panthers]]: In the early [[1970s]], [[Maggie Kuhn]] formed the Gray Panthers, an [[organization]] with a goal of eliminating ageism in all forms.
**[[National Youth Rights Association]]

===Unions===

Many unions have thrown themselves into the battle against age discrimination.  At present, the most prominent example is the Writers Guild of America West, which since [[2002]] has been waging a huge legal battle against much of the entertainment industry to get rid of the age discrimination commonly faced by elder scriptwriters.

===Laws===

There are many laws against age discrimination, including:

*[[United States]]
**[[Age Discrimination in Employment Act]]

==Further reading==
*[http://mitpress.mit.edu/catalog/item/default.asp?ttype=2&amp;tid=10385 Ageism: Stereotyping and Prejudice Against Older Persons] Edited scholarly volume of the latest research and theory on Ageism.
*[http://www.webster.edu/~woolflm/ageism.html An in-depth look at ageism by Linda M. Woolfe, Ph.D., of Webster University]
*[http://www.geocities.com/hatredsucks/upagainst.html Pro-Youth] A firm text against ageism towards teenagers, presenting a case of ageism committed by a jury. 
*[http://hrsbstaff.ednet.ns.ca/engramja/projects&amp;evals/sem2_mag1/chantellemag/chanceessay.htm Everyone deserves to be given a chance] An essay against ageism towards teenagers, written by a Canadian adolescent.

*[http://www.riamac.com "The Older Job Hunter's Guerilla Handbook"] A unique booklet that shows middle age men how to combat ageism in the job market. by Gunthar Manusson

==See also==
* [[Prejudice]]

[[Category:Aging]][[Category:prejudice and discrimination]]

[[de:Altersdiskriminierung]]
[[el:Ηλικιακές διακρίσεις]]
[[it:Razzismo generazionale]]
[[pl:Ageism]]
[[fi:Ikäsyrjintä]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>