<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20101113035401|396444781" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="22648231" pageid="22648231" ns="0" title="Ageism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2010-11-15T20:21:48Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Discrimination sidebar}}{{Wiktionary|ageism}}
'''Ageism''', also called '''age discrimination''' is [[stereotyping]] of and [[discrimination]] against individuals or groups because of their age. It is a set of beliefs, attitudes, norms, and values used to justify age based prejudice and discrimination. This may be casual or systematic.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Nelson|first=T. (Ed.)|year=2002|title=Ageism: Stereotyping and Prejudice against Older People|publisher=[[MIT Press]]|isbn=978-0-262-64057-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
  | last = Shepard
  | first = Jon
  | authorlink = Jon M. Shepard
  | coauthors = Robert W. Greene
  | title = Sociology and You
  | publisher = Glencoe McGraw-Hill
  | date = 2003u
  | location = Ohio
  | pages = A-22
  | url = http://www.glencoe.com/catalog/index.php/program?c=1675&amp;s=21309&amp;p=4213&amp;parent=4526
  | doi =
  | id =
  | isbn = 0078285763}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Quadagno"&gt;Quadagno, J. (2008). The field of social gerontology. In E. Barrosse (Ed.), Aging &amp; the life course: An introduction to social gerontology (pp. 2-23). New York: McGraw-Hill.&lt;/ref&gt;
The term was coined in 1968 by [[Robert Neil Butler]] to describe discrimination against [[Old age|seniors]], and patterned on [[sexism]] and [[racism]].&lt;ref&gt;Kramarae, C.  and Spender, D. (2000) ''Routledge International Encyclopedia of Women: Global Women's Issues and Knowledge.'' Routledge. p. 29.&lt;/ref&gt; Butler defined ageism as a combination of three connected elements. Among them were prejudicial attitudes towards older people, old age, and the [[Ageing|aging process]]; discriminatory practices against older people; and institutional practices and policies that perpetuate stereotypes about older people&lt;ref&gt;Wilkinson J and Ferraro K, Thirty Years of Ageism Research. In Nelson T (ed). Ageism: Stereotyping and Prejudice Against Older Persons. Massachusetts Institute of Technology, 2002&lt;/ref&gt; The term has also been used to describe prejudice and discrimination against [[adolescents]] and [[child]]ren, including ignoring their ideas because they are too young, or assuming that they should behave in certain ways because of their age.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youthrights.org/oppressed.php "Young and Oppressed" - youthrights.org]&lt;/ref&gt;

Ageism commonly refers to negative discriminatory practices, regardless of the age towards which it is applied. There are several subsidiary forms of ageism. [[Adultism]] is a predisposition towards adults, which is seen as biased against children, youth, and all young people who are not addressed or viewed as adults.&lt;ref&gt;Lauter And Howe (1971) ''Conspiracy of the Young.'' Meridian Press.&lt;/ref&gt; ''Jeunism'' is the discrimination against older people in favor of younger ones. This includes political candidacies, commercial functions, and cultural settings where the supposed greater vitality and/or [[Human physical appearance|physical beauty]] of youth is more appreciated than the supposed greater moral and/or [[Rigor|intellectual rigor]] of adulthood. [[Adultcentricism]] is the "exaggerated [[egocentrism]] of [[adults]]."&lt;ref&gt;De Martelaer, K., De Knop, P., Theeboom, M., and Van Heddegem, L. (2000) "The UN Convention as a Basis for Elaborating Rights of Children In Sport," ''Journal of Leisurability. 27''(2), pp. 3-10.&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Adultocracy]] is the [[Convention (norm)|social convention]] which defines "maturity" and "immaturity," placing adults in a dominant position over [[youth|young people]], both theoretically and practically.&lt;ref&gt;(n.d.) [http://www.zmag.org/0009.htm Youth Liberation] ''Z'' magazine.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Gerontocracy]] is a form of oligarchical rule in which an entity is ruled by leaders who are significantly older than most of the adult population.  [[Chronocentrism]] is primarily the belief that a certain state of humanity is superior to all previous and/or future times.

Ageism may also lead to the development of fears towards certain age groups, particularly: [[Pedophobia]], the fear of infants and children; [[Ephebiphobia]], the fear of youth,&lt;ref&gt;Fletcher, A. (2006) ''Washington Youth Voice Handbook.'' CommonAction.&lt;/ref&gt; sometimes also referred as an irrational fear of adolescents or a prejudice against teenagers;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.stop-discrimination.info/6423.0.html?&amp;no_cache=1&amp;mc_glossary%5Bcategories%5D=1 "Stop Discrimination"'s Glossary (European Union)]&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Gerontophobia]], the fear of elderly people.&lt;ref&gt;Branch, L., Harris, D. &amp; Palmore, E.B. (2005) ''Encyclopedia of Ageism.'' Haworth Press. ISBN 0-7890-1890-X&lt;/ref&gt;

==Forms and manifestations of ageism==
{{Original research|date=June 2008}}
There are several forms of ageism which fall under two general categories: prejudicial ageism, or the negative stereotyping of people on the basis of age, and discriminatory ageism, or denying people opportunities on the basis of age.&lt;ref name="Quadagno" /&gt;

====Implicit ageism====
Implicit ageism is the term used to refer to the implicit or unconscious thoughts, feelings, and behaviors one has about older or younger people. These may be a mixture of positive and negative thoughts and feelings, but gerontologist Becca Levy reports that they “tend to be mostly negative.” &lt;ref name="Levy"&gt;Levy, B. R. (2001). Eradication of ageism requires addressing the enemy within. The Gerontologist, 41(5), 578-579.&lt;/ref&gt;

One way that implicit or explicit ageism may manifest is through the use of patronizing language with older or younger people. The term "patronizing language" specifically describes two negative methods of communication: overaccommodation, which consists of a person being excessively courteous and speaking simple and short sentences very loudly and slowly to an older or younger person, with an exaggerated tone and high pitch; and baby talk, which involves practically the same uncomplicated speech with an exaggerated pitch and tone that one uses when talking to a baby, differing in the content of the speech. These tend to downplay the serious and thoughtful contributions of older or younger persons to society, while reinforcing a negative image of them as dependent people with deficiencies in intellect, cognitive and physical performance, and other areas required for autonomous, daily functioning. People who engage in this type of speech treat older members of society as if they have regressed to an infantile state, or treat younger members of society as if they have never progressed beyond an infantile state.&lt;ref name="Nelson"&gt;Nelson, T. D. (2005). Ageism: Prejudice against our feared future self. Journal of Social Issues, 61(2), 207-221.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Ageist stereotyping====
Ageist stereotyping is a tool of cognition which involves categorizing into groups and attributing characteristics to these groups.  Stereotypes are necessary for processing huge volumes of information which would otherwise overload a person, and they are often based on a "grain of truth" (for example, the association between aging and ill health).  However, they cause harm when the content of the stereotype is incorrect with respect to most of the group or where a stereotype is so strongly held that it overrides evidence which shows that an individual does not conform to it.  Stereotypes are used to interpret the world around us.  For example, age-based stereotypes prime one to draw very different conclusions when one sees an older and a younger adult with, say, back pain or a limp.  One might well assume that the younger person’s condition is temporary and treatable, following an accident, while the older person’s condition is chronic and less susceptible to intervention.  On average, this might be true, but plenty of older people have accidents and recover quickly.  This assumption may have no consequence if one makes it in the blink of an eye as one is passing someone in the street, but if it is held by a health professional offering treatment or managers thinking about occupational health, it could inappropriately influence their actions and lead to age-related discrimination. Another example is when people are rude to children because of their high pitched voice, even if they are kind and courteous.

====Ageist prejudice====
Ageist '''prejudice''' is a type of emotion which is often linked to the cognitive process of stereotyping. It can involve the expression of derogatory attitudes, which may then lead to the use of discriminatory behavior. Where older contestants were rejected in the belief that they were poor performers, this could well be the result of stereotyping.  But older people were also voted for at the stage in the game where it made sense to target the best performers.  This can only be explained by a subconscious emotional reaction to older people; in this case, the prejudice took the form of distaste and a desire to exclude oneself from the company of older people.

====Benevolent prejudice====
Stereotyping and prejudice against different groups in society does not take the same form.  Age-based prejudice and stereotyping usually involves older people being pitied, marginalized, or patronized.  This is described as "'''benevolent prejudice"''' because the tendency to pity is linked to seeing older people as "friendly" but "incompetent."  This is similar to the prejudice most often directed against women and disabled people.  [[Age Concern]]’s survey revealed strong evidence of "benevolent prejudice."  48% said that over-70s are viewed as friendly (compared to 27% who said the same about under-30s).  Meanwhile, only 26% believe over-70s are viewed as capable (with 41% saying the same about under-30s).&lt;ref name="Loretto"&gt;Loretto, W., Duncan, C., &amp; White, P.J. (2000). Ageism and employment: Controversies, ambiguities, and younger people’s perceptions. Ageing &amp; Society, 20(3), 279-302.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Hostile prejudice====
"'''Hostile prejudice'''" based on hatred, fear, or threat (which often characterizes attitudes linked to race, religion, and sexual orientation) is less common with respect to the elderly, though is very common with respect to youth.  An example of Hostile prejudice on the youth is when someone presumes that the youth committed a crime without any evidence.  But there are examples, including excessive rhetoric regarding intergenerational competition, and violence against vulnerable older people, which can be motivated by subconscious hostility or fear.  Equality campaigners are often wary of drawing comparisons between different forms of inequality.  But it is unquestionably true that abuse and neglect experienced by vulnerable older people (which is closely linked to hostile prejudice) kills more people each year than the shocking but relatively isolated cases of public violence motivated by race, religion, or sexual orientation.[citation needed]

The impact of "benevolent" and "hostile" prejudice can be equally severe but tends to be different.  The warmth felt towards older people means there is often public acceptance that they are deserving of preferential treatment—for example, concessionary travel.  But the perception of incompetence means older people can be seen as "not up to the job" or "a menace on the roads," when there is no evidence to support this.  Benevolent prejudice also leads to assumptions that it is "natural" for older people to have lower expectations, reduced choice and control, and less account taken of their views.

====Discrimination====
Age discrimination refers to the actions taken to deny or limit opportunities to people on the basis of age. These are usually actions taken as a result of one’s ageist beliefs and attitudes. Age discrimination occurs on both a personal and institutional level.&lt;ref name="Quadagno" /&gt;

On a personal level, an older person may be told that he or she is too old to engage in certain physical activities, like an informal game of basketball between friends and family, while a younger person may be told that he or she is too young to engage in certain social activities, like going to an unsupervised party.

On an institutional level, there are policies and regulations in place that limit opportunities to people of certain ages and deny them to all others. The law, for instance, requires that all young persons must be at least 16 years old in order to obtain a driver’s license in the United States. There are also government regulations that determine when a worker may retire. Currently, in the US, a worker must be 66 years and 2 months old before becoming eligible for normal retirement.&lt;ref&gt;Quadagno, J. (2008). The economics of aging. In E. Barrosse (Ed.), Aging &amp; the life course: An introduction to social gerontology (pp. 350-374). New York: McGraw-Hill.&lt;/ref&gt;

A 2006/2007 survey done by the Children's Rights Alliance for England and the National Children's Bureau asked 4,060 children and young people whether they have ever been treated unfairly based on various criteria (race, age, sex, sexual orientation, etc.).  A total of 43% of British youth surveyed reported experiencing discrimination based on their age, far eclipsing other categories of discrimination like sex (27%), race (11%), or sexual orientation (6%).&lt;ref&gt;Willow, C., Franklin, A. and Shaw, C. (2007).  Meeting the obligations of the Convention on the Rights of the Child in England. Children and young people's messages to Government. DCSF.&lt;/ref&gt;

Ageism has significant effects in two particular sectors: employment and health care.

=====Employment=====
The concept of ageism was originally developed to refer to prejudice and discrimination against older people. Over time, this association between discrimination and old age has been expanded by evidence that suggests prejudice and discrimination in employment can occur to a worker of any age.&lt;ref name="Loretto"/&gt;

Like [[racism|racial]] and [[gender discrimination]], age discrimination, at least when it affects younger workers, can result in unequal pay for equal work.  Unlike racial and gender discrimination, however, age discrimination in wages is often enshrined in law.  For example, in both the United States&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dol.gov/esa/minwage/q-a.htm Questions and Answers About the Minimum Wage], US Department of Labor&lt;/ref&gt; and the United Kingdom&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.agepositive.gov.uk/news/minimum_wage.asp Age Positive], [[Department for Work and Pensions]] in Sheffield and London&lt;/ref&gt; [[minimum wage]] laws allow for employers to pay lower wages to young workers.  Many state and local minimum wage laws mirror such an age-based, tiered minimum wage.  Outside of the law, older workers, on average, make more than younger workers do.  Firms may be afraid to offer older workers lower wages than they offer to younger workers.

Therefore, younger workers may face more [[statistical discrimination]] from employers than older workers. Statistical discrimination refers to limiting the employment opportunities of an individual based on stereotypes of a group to which the person belongs. Limited employment opportunities could come in the form of lower pay for equal work or jobs with little [[social mobility]]. Younger female workers may be more statistically discriminated against than older female workers, for example, because it is socially expected that, as young women of childbearing years, they will need to leave the work force periodically to have children.&lt;ref&gt;Phelps, E. S. (1972). "The statistical theory of racism and sexism". American Economic Review 62: 659–661.&lt;/ref&gt;

Labor regulations also limit the age at which people are allowed to work and how many hours and under what conditions they may work.  In the United States, a person must generally be at least 14 years old to seek a job, and workers face additional restrictions on their work activities until they reach age 16.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dol.gov/dol/topic/youthlabor/agerequirements.htm Youth &amp; Labor - Age Requirements], US Department of Labor&lt;/ref&gt; Many companies refuse to hire workers younger than 18.

Young workers over 18 may also have a hard time finding a [[White-collar worker|white-collar]] job because the maximum age for some professional occupations is set as low as 30 by employers. After these workers finish obtaining the necessary professional degrees, they may have only a few years, at most, to get into a position without being too old. The upward mobility in these same jobs starts to diminish once the workers reach the age of 40. A worker who gets a job at age 30 may only work about ten years before his chances of promotion begin to dwindle.&lt;ref name="Loretto" /&gt;

While older workers benefit more often from higher wages than do younger workers, they face barriers in promotions and hiring.  Employers may also encourage [[Retirement|early retirement]] or [[layoff]]s disproportionately more for older or more experienced workers.

Age discrimination in hiring has been shown to exist in the United States.  Joanna Lahey, professor at [[The Bush School of Government and Public Service]] at [[Texas A&amp;M]], found that firms are more than 40% more likely to interview a younger job applicant than an older job applicant.&lt;ref&gt;Lahey, J. (2005) [http://ideas.repec.org/p/crr/issbrf/ib33.html Do Older Workers Face Discrimination?] Boston College.&lt;/ref&gt;

In a survey for the [[University of Kent]], [[England]], 29% of respondents stated that they had suffered from age discrimination.  This is a higher proportion than for [[Sexism|gender]] or [[Racism|racial]] discrimination.  Dominic Abrams, [[social psychology]] professor at the university, concluded that ageism is the most pervasive form of prejudice experienced in the UK population.&lt;ref&gt;(2006) [http://www.ageconcern.org.uk/AgeConcern/media/how_ageist_is_britain.pdf How Ageist is Britain?] London: Age Concern.&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Dr. Robert M. McCann, an associate professor of management communication at the [[University of Southern California]]’s [[Marshall School of Business]], denigrating older workers, even if only subtly, can have an outsized negative impact on employee productivity and corporate profits. For American corporations, age discrimination can lead to significant expenses. In Fiscal Year 2006, the U.S. [[Equal Employment Opportunity Commission]] received nearly 17,000 charges of age discrimination, resolving more than 14,000 and recovering $51.5 million in monetary benefits. Costs from lawsuit settlements and judgments can run into the millions, most notably with the $250 million paid by the [[CalPERS|California Public Employees' Retirement System (CalPERS)]] under a settlement agreement in 2003.&lt;ref&gt;[http://newswise.com/articles/view/544169/ When Words Get Old: Ageist Language] Newswise, Retrieved on September 9, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Harris, D. (2003 July–August) [http://www.aarpmagazine.org/lifestyle/a2003-05-21-mag-justice_age.html Simple justice. The story behind a record-setting age discrimination settlement and what it could mean in your workplace.] ''AARP The Magazine''.  Retrieved on October 25, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the UK, age discrimination has been prohibited in employment since 2006. Since then, the number of age discrimination cases has risen dramatically. The laws protect the young as well as the old, and there were over 5,200 claims submitted to the Employment Tribunal in 2009/2010 compared to just 900 in 2006/2007 (immediately after the Regulations came in force).&lt;ref&gt;http://www.agediscrimination.info/&lt;/ref&gt;

=====Healthcare=====
There is considerable evidence of discrimination against the elderly in health care. This is particularly true for aspects of the physician-patient interaction, such as screening procedures, information exchanges, and treatment decisions. In the patient-physician interaction, physicians and other health care providers may hold attitudes, beliefs, and behaviors that are associated with ageism against older patients. Studies have found that physicians often do not seem to show any care or concern toward treating the medical problems of older people. Then, when actually interacting with these older patients on the job, the doctors sometimes view them with disgust and describe them in negative ways, such as "depressing" or "crazy."&lt;ref name="Nelson" /&gt;  For screening procedures, elderly people are less likely than younger people to be screened for cancers and, due to the lack of this preventative measure, less likely to be diagnosed at early stages of their conditions.&lt;ref name="Robb"&gt;Robb, C., Hongbin, C., &amp; Haley, W. E. (2002). Ageism in mental health and health care: A critical review. Journal of Clinical Geropsychology, 8(1), 1-12. [http://www.springerlink.com/content/gx05765126721755/fulltext.pdf]&lt;/ref&gt;

After being diagnosed with a disease that may be potentially curable, older people are further discriminated against. Though there may be surgeries or operations with high survival rates that might cure their condition, older patients are less likely than younger patients to receive all the necessary treatments. It has been posited that this is because doctors fear their older patients are not physically strong enough to tolerate the curative treatments and are more likely to have complications during surgery that may end in death. However, other studies have been done with patients with heart disease, and, in these cases, the older patients were still less likely to receive further tests or treatments, independent of the severity of their health problems. Thus, the approach to the treatment of older people is concentrated on managing the disease rather than preventing or curing it. This is based on the stereotype that it is the natural process of aging for the quality of health to decrease, and, therefore, there is no point in attempting to prevent the inevitable decline of old age.&lt;ref name="Nelson" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Robb" /&gt;

Such differential medical treatment of elderly people can have significant effects on their health outcomes.

==Effects of ageism==
Ageism has significant effects on the elderly. The stereotypes and infantilization of older people by patronizing language affects older people’s self-esteem and behaviors. After repeatedly hearing a stereotype that older people are useless, older people may begin to feel like dependent, non-contributing members of society. They may start to perceive themselves in terms of the [[looking-glass self]]--that is, in the same ways that others in society see them. Studies have also specifically shown that when older people hear these stereotypes about their supposed incompetence and uselessness, they perform worse on measures of competence and memory. These stereotypes then become [[self-fulfilling prophecies]]. Older people may also engage in self-stereotypes, or taking their culture’s age stereotypes to which they have been exposed over the life course and directing them inward toward themselves. Then this behavior reinforces the present stereotypes and treatment of the elderly.&lt;ref name="Levy" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Nelson" /&gt;

Many overcome these stereotypes and live the way they want, but it can be difficult to avoid deeply ingrained prejudice, especially if one has seen others express ageist views before growing older.

This is not to say, however, that it has no effect on the young. It too can have the same effects as ageism towards the elderly.

==Measuring ageism==
It is very difficult to measure ageism. Very few studies have been conducted on the topic, and those that have tend to leave out some forms of ageism, such as implicit ageism and self-stereotyped ageism. These two forms are particularly hard to conceptualize. Of the studies that have attempted to measure the concept of ageism, many have been met with significant scrutiny because there are several factors, such as the [[social desirability bias]], that may cloud the data.&lt;ref name="Levy" /&gt;

==Government responses to ageism==

In the US, each state has its own laws regarding age discrimination, and there are also federal laws.  In [[California]], the Fair Employment and Housing Act forbids unlawful discrimination against persons age 40 and older.  The FEHA is the principal California statute prohibiting employment discrimination, covering employers, [[Trade union|labor organizations]], [[Employment agency|employment agencies]], [[apprentice]]ship programs and/or any person or entity who aids, abets, incites, compels, or coerces the doing of a discriminatory act. In addition to age, it prohibits employment discrimination based on race or color; religion; national origin or ancestry, [[Disability|physical disability]]; mental disability or medical condition; marital status; sex or sexual orientation; and pregnancy, childbirth, or related medical conditions.&lt;ref&gt;[http://finduslaw.com/california_fair_employment_and_housing_act_feha_government_code_12900_12996 California Fair Employment and Housing Act] FindLaw.&lt;/ref&gt;

The federal government governs age discrimination under the [[Age Discrimination in Employment Act]] of 1967 (ADEA). The ADEA prohibits employment discrimination based on age with respect to employees 40 years of age or older as well.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.kmblegal.com/index.php/158/Legal_Protections_For_Older_Workers_Know_Your_Rights Federal Protections for Older Workers] 2008 KMB Legal&lt;/ref&gt;  The ADEA also addresses the difficulty older workers face in obtaining new employment after being displaced from their jobs, arbitrary age limits.&lt;ref&gt;[http://finduslaw.com/age_discrimination_in_employment_act_of_1967_adea_29_u_s_code_chapter_14 Age Discrimination in Employment Act of 1967] FindLaw website.&lt;/ref&gt; The ADEA applies even if some of the minimum 20 employees are overseas and working for a US corporation.&lt;ref&gt;[http://finduslaw.com/morelli_v_cedel_2nd_cir_1998_141_f3d_39_45 Morelli v. Cedel (2nd Cir. 1998) 141 F3d 39, 45] FindLaw website.&lt;/ref&gt;

The United States federal government has responded to issues of ageism in governance through several measures in the past. They include the creation of the 1970s-era [[National Commission on Resources for Youth]], which was created in the late 1960s as to promote [[youth participation]] throughout communities. Recently the federal government implemented the [[Tom Osborne Federal Youth Coordination Act]], aiming to curb redundancy among federal service providers to youth.

Other countries that have laws addressing ageism include Australia, Denmark, Ireland, and the [[Employment Equality (Age) Regulations 2006|United Kingdom]].

===Laws on ageism and hate crimes===

Some countries have enacted [[anti-discrimination law|anti-discriminatory laws]] against ageism, usually associating them with other [[hate crime]] motivations like [[racism]], [[homophobia|sexual orientation]] or [[religious intolerance]].

In the [[United States]], thirteen [[U.S. state|states]] define age as a specific motivation for hate crimes - [[California]], [[District of Columbia]], [[Florida]], [[Iowa]], [[Hawaii]], [[Kansas]], [[Louisiana]], [[Maine]], [[Minnesota]], [[Nebraska]], [[New Mexico]], [[New York]] and [[Vermont]].&lt;ref&gt;{{PDF|[http://www.adl.org/learn/hate_crimes_laws/State_Hate_Crime_Statutory_Provisions_chart.pdf Anti-Defamation League State Hate Crime Statutory Provisions (2005)]|23.8&amp;nbsp;KB}} (See page 1, section "Other", note 2) Retrieved on May-21-2009&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{PDF|[http://www.humanrightsfirst.org/discrimination/pdf/everyday-fears-080805.pdf Everyday Fears - A Survey of Violent Hate Crimes in Europe and North America]|1.96&amp;nbsp;MB}} McClintock, Michael (See pages 84 and 122, Appendix 10, "Others", note 2) Retrieved on May-21-2009&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[European Union|European]] citizenship provides the right to protection from discrimination on the grounds of age. According to Article 21-1 of the [[Charter of Fundamental Rights of the European Union|Charter of Fundamental Rights]] of the [[European Union]] [[s:Charter of Fundamental Rights of the European Union#CHAPTER III. EQUALITY]], “any discrimination based on any ground such as (…) age, shall be prohibited”.&lt;ref&gt;{{PDF|[http://www.europarl.europa.eu/charter/pdf/text_en.pdf Charter of Fundamental Rights of the European Union (official text)]|80.6&amp;nbsp;KB}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the [[Francophonie|Francophone]] world, discrimination based on age is often classified as a [[hate crime]] and/or legally deemed an [[aggravation (legal concept)|aggravating circumstance]].

In [[France]], Articles 225-1 thru 225-4 of the [[Penal code|Penal Code]] detail the [[criminalization|penalization]] of ageism, when it comes to an age discrimination related to the [[Consumption (economics)|consumption]] of a [[good (economics)|good]] or service, to the exercise of an [[Economics|economic]] activity, to the [[labour economics|labor market]] or an [[intern]]ship, except in the cases foreseen in Article 225-3.&lt;ref&gt;{{en}} [http://195.83.177.9/code/liste.phtml?lang=uk&amp;c=33&amp;r=3716 French Penal Code (Legifrance)]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{fr}} [http://www.legifrance.gouv.fr/affichCode.do?idArticle=LEGIARTI000006417831&amp;idSectionTA=LEGISCTA000006165298&amp;cidTexte=LEGITEXT000006070719&amp;dateTexte=20090317 Legifrance's Code pénal – original text]&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Canada]], Article 718.2, clause (a)(i), of the [[Criminal Code]] defines as aggravating circumstances, among other situations, “evidence that the offence was motivated by ....age”.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.laws.justice.gc.ca/en/showdoc/cs/C-46/bo-ga:l_XXIII-gb:s_718//en#anchorbo-ga:l_XXIII-gb:s_718 Canadian Criminal Code]&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Belgium]], the Law of Feb. 25, 2003 “tending to fight discrimination” punishes ageism when “a difference of treatment that lacks objective and reasonable justification is directly based on …. age”. Discrimination is forbidden when it refers to providing or offering a good or service, to conditions linked to work or [[employment]], to the appointment or [[promotion (rank)|promotion]] of an employee, and yet to the access or participation in “an economic, social, cultural or political activity accessible to the public” (Article 2nd, § 4). [[Incitement]] to discrimination, to [[hatred]] or to [[violence]] against a person or a group on the grounds of (…) age (Article 6) is punished with [[incarceration|imprisonment]] and/or a
[[fine (penalty)|fine]].&lt;ref&gt;{{fr}} {{PDF|[http://www.stop-discrimination.info/fileadmin/pdfs/Nationale_Inhalte/Belgium/Gesetz/25.02.2003.pdf Belgium Law of Feb. 25 2003 against discrimination]|76.5&amp;nbsp;KB}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Advocacy campaigns==

Many current and historical [[intergenerational equity|intergenerational]] and [[youth programs]] have been created to address the issue of ageism. Among the advocacy organizations created in the [[United Kingdom]] to challenge age discrimination are [[Age UK]] and the [[British Youth Council]].

In the [[United States]] there have been several historic and current efforts to challenge ageism. The earliest example may be the [[Newsboys Strike of 1899]], which fought ageist employment practices targeted against youth by large newspaper syndicates in the Northeast. During the [[Franklin D. Roosevelt]] Administration, [[First Lady]] [[Eleanor Roosevelt]] was active in the national [[youth movement]], including the formation of the [[National Youth Administration]] and the defense of the [[American Youth Congress]]. She made several statements on behalf of youth and against ageism. In one report entitled, "Facing the Problems of Youth," Roosevelt said of youth,

:"We cannot simply expect them to say, 'Our older people have had experience and they have proved to themselves certain things, therefore they are right.' That isn't the way the best kind of young people think. They want to experience for themselves. I find they are perfectly willing to talk to older people, but they don't want to talk to older people who are shocked by their ideas, nor do they want to talk to older people who are not realistic."&lt;ref&gt;Roosevelt, A.E. (1935) [http://newdeal.feri.org/er/er21.htm "Facing the Problems of Youth,"] ''National Parent-Teacher Magazine 29''(30). Retrieved 7/30/07.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Students for a Democratic Society (1960 organization)|Students for a Democratic Society]] formed in 1960 to promote democratic opportunities for all people regardless of age, and the [[Gray Panthers]] was formed in the early 1970s with a goal of eliminating ageism in all forms.&lt;ref&gt;Kuhn, M., Long, C. and Quinn, L. (1991) ''No Stone Unturned: the Life and Times of Maggie Kuhn.'' Ballentine Books.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Three O'Clock Lobby]] formed in 1976 to promote [[youth participation]] throughout traditionally ageist government structures in Michigan, while [[Youth Liberation of Ann Arbor]] started in 1970 to promote youth and fight ageism.

More recent U.S. programs include [[Americans for a Society Free from Age Restrictions]], which formed in 1996 to advance the civil and [[human rights]] of young people through eliminating ageist laws targeted against young people, and to help youth counter ageism in America.&lt;ref&gt;ASFAR (2006). [http://www.asfar.org/articles.php] Americans for a Society Free from Age Restrictions Articles of Incorporation.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[National Youth Rights Association]] started in 1998 to promote awareness of the legal and human rights of young people in the [[United States]],&lt;ref&gt;National Youth Rights Association (2001).[http://www.youthrights.org/docs/nyraarticlesofinc.pdf] National Youth Rights Association Articles of Incorporation (Partial)&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[Freechild Project]] was formed in 2001 to identify, unify and promote diverse opportunities for youth engagement in social change by fighting ageism.

===Related campaigns===

*In 2002 the [[Writers Guild of America, West]] has waged a legal battle within the entertainment industry to eliminate age discrimination commonly faced by elder scriptwriters.{{Citation needed|date=February 2007}}
*Director [[Paul Weitz (filmmaker)|Paul Weitz]] reported he wrote the 2004 film, ''[[In Good Company]]'' to reveal how ageism affects youth and adults.&lt;ref&gt;Hellerman, A. (2005) [http://www.wgaeast.org/features/2005/03/18/paul_weitz/index.html Working Solo in Good Company] Writers Guild of America, East website.&lt;/ref&gt;
*In 2002 [[The Freechild Project]] created an information and training initiative to provide resources to youth organizations and schools focused on youth rights.&lt;ref&gt;(n.d.) [http://www.freechild.org/SNAYR/index.htm Survey of North American Youth Rights] The Freechild Project website.&lt;/ref&gt;
*In 2006 Lydia Giménez-LLort,Ph.D. an assistant professor of Psychiatry and researcher at the [[Autonomous University of Barcelona]] coined the term 'Snow White Syndrome' at the 'Congrés de la Gent Gran de Cerdanyola del Vallès' (Congress of the Elderly of Cerdanyola del Vallès, Barcelona, Spain) as a metaphor to define ageism in a easier and more friendly way while developing a constructive spirit against it. The metaphor is based on both the auto-ageism and adultocracy exhibited by the queen of the [[Snow White]] fairy tale as well as the social ageism symbolized by the mirror &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.saberenvejecer.es/saberhacer_30.html] (Spanish) Envellir bé · Successful Ageing · Saber Envejecer website - Know-how.&lt;/ref&gt;
*Since 2008 'The Intergenerational Study' by Lydia Giménez-LLort and Paula Ramírez-Boix from the [[Autonomous University of Barcelona]] is aimed to find the basis of the link between grandparents and grandsons (positive family relationships) that are able to minimize the ageism towards the elderly. Students of several Spanish universities have enroled to this study which soon will be also performed in USA, Nigeria, Barbados, Argentina and Mexico. The preliminar results reveal that 'The Intergenerational study questionnaire' induces young people to do a reflexive and autocritic analysis of their intergenerational relationships in contrast to those shown towards other unrelated old people which results very positive to challenge ageism. A cortometrage about 'The International Study' has been directed and produced by Tomás Sunyer from [[Los Angeles City College]] &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.saberenvejecer.es/investigar_25.html] (Spanish) Envellir bé : Successful Ageing · Saber envejecer website - Research.&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Votes at 16]] intends to lower the [[voting age]] to 16, reducing ageism and giving 16 year olds equal pay on the [[National Minimum Wage]]. The group claims that 16 year olds get less money than older people for the same work, angering many 16 year olds. They additionally postulate that 16 year olds will have their voice listened to by older people more often.

===Accusations of ageism===

In a recent interview, actor [[Pierce Brosnan]] cited ageism as one of the contributing factors as to why he was not asked to continue his role as [[James Bond]] in the Bond film ''[[Casino Royale (2006 film)|Casino Royale]]'', released in 2006.&lt;ref&gt;Cox, J. (2006) [http://commanderbond.net/Public/Stories/2994-1.shtml Brosnan Bares All For Playboy]&lt;/ref&gt;

Also, successful singer and actress, [[Madonna (entertainer)|Madonna]] spoke out in her 50s about ageism and her fight to defy the norms of society.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.carefair.com/html/Madonna_Not_Giving_In_to_Ageism_5301.html "Madonna not giving in to ageism - Cafe Fair"]&lt;/ref&gt;

Had [[John McCain]] succeeded in his 2008 campaign for President, he would have been the oldest President in American history. Discussions about his age dogged McCain during his failed run, and whether or not the criticism of McCain qualified as unfair 'ageist' allegations or legitimate points of view was hotly debated.&lt;ref&gt;[http://blogs.usatoday.com/oped/2008/06/mccain-and-age.html McCain and age: An issue, not ageism]. By Kirsten Powers.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=unseen&gt;[http://www.newsweek.com/id/106672?from=rss McCain's Unseen Adversary: Ageism | Newsweek Voices - Michael Hirsh | Newsweek.com&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.minnpost.com/stories/2008/04/03/1364/considering_mccains_age_ageism_or_a_fair_question MinnPost - Considering McCain's age: ageism or a fair question?&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://blogs.abcnews.com/politicalpunch/2008/10/whats-the-diffe.html What's the Difference Between Ageism and Other Forms of Bias? Depends. - Political Punch&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://themoderatevoice.com/19761/ageism-and-john-mccain/ Ageism and John McCain | The Moderate Voice&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.huffingtonpost.com/sherman-yellen/ageism-and-john-mccain-a_b_94303.html Sherman Yellen: Ageism and John McCain: A Personal View&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://blog.washingtonpost.com/thefix/2008/05/mccains_age_and_the_power_of_a.html | work=The Washington Post}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="time1"&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.time.com/time/politics/article/0,8599,1779596,00.html | work=Time | title=How Healthy Is John McCain? | date=May 14, 2008 | accessdate=April 23, 2010 | first1=Michael | last1=Scherer | first2=Alice | last2=Park}}&lt;/ref&gt; McCain himself frequently made fun of the criticisms, in one instance pretending to fall asleep when asked about his age.&lt;ref name="time1"/&gt;

A 2007 [[Pew Research Center]] study found that a majority of American voters would be less likely to vote for a President past a given age, with only 45% saying that age would not matter.

==See also==

* [[Adultism]]
* [[Age of consent]]
* [[Aging brain]]
* [[Ephebiphobia]]
* [[Gerontocracy]]
* [[Gerontophobia]]
* [[Memory and aging]]
* [[Minor (law)]]
* [[Pedophobia]]
* [[Prejudice]]
* [[Youth rights]]

==References==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==External links==
{{Wiktionary|ageism}}
*[http://www.blackwell-synergy.com/toc/josi/61/2  2005 issue of the Journal of Social Issues] Thematic journal issue devoted to empirical and theoretical research on ageism.
*[http://osha.europa.eu/priority_groups/ageingworkers/ Ageing at work]  [[EU-OSHA]]
*[http://www.ilcusa.org/prj/ageism.htm Ageism In America] Detailed report on ageism from the International Longevity Center.
*[http://mitpress.mit.edu/catalog/item/default.asp?ttype=2&amp;tid=10385 Ageism: Stereotyping and Prejudice Against Older Persons] Edited scholarly volume of the latest research and theory on Ageism.
*[http://www.luhs.org/depts/injprev/Transprt/tran3.htm#Older%20Drivers Article on Older Drivers].
*[http://www.webster.edu/~woolflm/ageism.html An in-depth look at ageism by Linda M. Woolfe, Ph.D., of Webster University]
*[http://hrsbstaff.ednet.ns.ca/engramja/projects&amp;evals/sem2_mag1/chantellemag/chanceessay.htm Everyone deserves to be given a chance] An essay against ageism towards teenagers, written by a Canadian adolescent.
*[http://knol.google.com/k/solomon-tse/ageism/38s05w5hp4v3n/2# Ageism - Discrimination Against Age] A Knol examining ageism and social attitudes against different age groups.
*[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/business/5334972.stm Age discrimination laws by the BBC]
*[http://www.usatoday.com/money/companies/management/2008-08-12-obama-mccain-age-ceos_N.htm USA Today article examining old and young CEOs the ages of John McCain and Barack Obama]
*[http://www.carefair.com/html/Madonna_Not_Giving_In_to_Ageism_5301.html Article on singer Madonna and her views on ageism]
*[http://www.aginginalabama.com Issues and resources on aging in Alabama]

==Further reading==

{{refbegin}}

*{{Cite book
	|last=Bergling
	|first=Tim
	|title=Reeling in the Years: Gay Men's Perspectives on Age and Ageism
	|year=2004
	|publisher=Southern Tier Editions, Harrington Park Press
	|location=New York, NY
	|isbn=1560233702|oclc=52166116}}
*{{Cite book
	|last=Bytheway
	|first=Bill
	|title=Ageism
	|year=1995
	|publisher=Open University Press
	|location=Buckingham; Bristol, PA
	|isbn=0335191762|oclc=30733778}}
*{{Cite book
	|last=Calasanti |first=Toni M. and Kathleen F. Slevin
	|editor=
	|title=Age Matters: Realigning Feminist Thinking
	|edition=
	|year=2006
	|publisher=Routledge
	|location=New York, NY
	|isbn=0415952239 |oclc=65400440}}
*{{Cite book
	|last=Cruikshank |first=Margaret
	|editor=
	|title=Learning to be Old: Gender, Culture, and Aging
	|edition=
	|year=2003
	|publisher=Rowman &amp; Littlefield Publishers
	|location=Lanham, MD
	|isbn=0847698483|oclc=49566317}}
*{{Cite book
	|last=Eglit,
	|first=Howard C.
	|title=Elders on Trial: Age and Ageism in the American Legal System
	|year=2004
	|publisher=University Press of Florida
	|location=Gainesville, FL
	|isbn=0813027659|oclc=56482087}}
*{{Cite book
	|last=Gaster |first=Lucy
	|editor=
	|title=Past it at 40?: A Grassroots View of Ageism and Discrimination in Employment: A Report
	|edition=
	|year=2002
	|publisher=The Policy Press
	|location=Bristol, UK
	|isbn=1861344848|oclc=51802692}}
*{{Cite book
	|last=Glover |first=Ian and Mohamed Branine
	|editor=
	|title=Ageism in Work and Employment
	|edition=
	|year=2001
	|publisher=Ashgate
	|location=Aldershot, UK; Burlington, VT
	|isbn=1840141492|oclc=45487982}}
*{{Cite book
	|last=Gullette
	|first=Margaret Morganroth
	|title=Aged by Culture
	|year=2004
	|publisher=University of Chicago Press
	|location=Chicago, IL
	|isbn=0226310620|oclc=52514302}}
*{{Cite book
	|last=Gullette
	|first=Margaret Morganroth
	|title=Declining to Decline: Cultural Combat and the Politics of the Midlife
	|year=1997
	|publisher=University Press of Virginia
	|location=Charlottesville, VA
	|isbn=0813917212|oclc=35986171}}
* Kimmel, D.C. (1988). Ageism, psychology, and public policy. ''American Psychologist'', ''43''(3), 175-178.
* Kite, M.E., &amp; Johnson, B.T. (1988). Attitudes towards older and younger adults: A meta-analysis. ''Psychology and Aging'', ''3''(3), 232-244.
*{{Cite book
	|last=Lagacé |first=Martine, &amp; ''al.''
	|title=L'Âgisme: Comprendre et changer le regard social sur le vieillissement
	|year=2010
	|publisher=PUL (Presses de l'Université Laval
	|location=Quebec city, Quebec, Canada
	|isbn=2763787819|oclc=632095367}}
*{{Cite book
	|last=Macnicol
	|first=John
	|title=Age Discrimination: An Historical and Contemporary Analysis
	|year=2006
	|publisher=Cambridge University
	|location=Cambridge
	|isbn=052184777X|oclc=61176543}}
*{{Cite book
	|last=Nelson |first=Todd D.
	|editor=
	|title=Ageism: Stereotyping and Prejudice Against Older Persons
	|edition=
	|year=2002
	|publisher=MIT Press
	|location=Cambridge, MA
	|isbn=0262140772|oclc=47863229}}
*{{Cite book
	|last=Palmore |first=Erdman, Laurence Branch, and Diana Harris (editors)
	|editor=
	|title=Encyclopedia of Ageism
	|edition=
	|year=2005
	|publisher=Haworth Pastoral Press: Haworth Reference Press
	|location=Binhamton, NY
	|isbn=0789018896|oclc=55801014}}
*{{Cite book
	|last=Thompson |first=Neil
	|editor=
	|title=Anti-Discriminatory Practice
	|edition= 4th edition
	|year=2006
	|publisher=Palgrave Macmillan
	|location=Basingstoke, England; New York, NY
	|isbn=1403921601|oclc=62302620}}

{{refend}}

{{Discrimination}}

[[Category:Ageism| ]]
[[Category:Aging]]
[[Category:Prejudice and discrimination]]
[[Category:Youth rights]]
[[Category:Dispositional beliefs]]
[[Category:Human rights by issue]]

[[ar:تفرقة عمرية]]
[[bs:Starosna diskriminacija]]
[[bg:Възрастова дискриминация]]
[[cs:Ageismus]]
[[cy:Oedraniaeth]]
[[de:Altersdiskriminierung]]
[[el:Ηλικιακές διακρίσεις]]
[[fa:سن‌گرایی]]
[[fr:Âgisme]]
[[id:Diskriminasi usia]]
[[it:Ageismo]]
[[he:גילנות]]
[[lt:Diskriminacija dėl amžiaus]]
[[nl:Leeftijdsdiscriminatie]]
[[ja:年齢差別]]
[[pl:Ageizm]]
[[pt:Discriminação etária]]
[[ru:Дискриминация по возрасту]]
[[simple:Ageism]]
[[fi:Ikäsyrjintä]]
[[zh:年龄歧视]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>