<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20110808165340|443706922" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="28857185" pageid="28857185" ns="0" title="Racism in the Arab world"><revisions><rev timestamp="2011-08-17T17:17:58Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Orphan|date=March 2011}}
{{Merge to|Racism in the Middle East|date=August 2011}}

'''Racism in the Arab world''' covers an array of forms of intolerance against non-Arab groups, minorities in the middle east and Arab rule on Africans.

The previously forbidden topics of race and racism in the Arab world have been explored more since the rise of independent media. In one example, [[Al-Jazeera]]'s critical coverage of the [[Darfur crisis]] led to the arrest and conviction of its Khartoum bureau chief.&lt;ref&gt;''Middle East report'': Issues 234-235; Issues 237-241 , Middle East Research &amp; Information Project, 2005, p. 54, p 32&lt;/ref&gt;

==Racist attitudes==
[[The Guardian]]'s journalist [[Brian Whitaker]] wrote on ''the race taboo,'' an excerpt: &lt;blockquote&gt;Racism is a worldwide phenomenon. In some countries it's met with disapproval, in others with denial. The A to Z of ethnic and religious groups in the Middle East embraces Alawites, Armenians, Assyrians, Baha'is, Berbers, Chaldeans, Copts, Druzes, Ibadis, Ismailis, Jews, Kurds, Maronites, Sahrawis, Tuareq, Turkmen, Yazidis and Zaidis (by no means an exhaustive list), and yet serious discussion of ethnic/religious diversity and its place in society is a long-standing taboo.
If the existence of non-Arab or non-Muslim groups is acknowledged at all, it is usually only to declare how wonderfully everyone gets along.
&lt;ref&gt;Brian Whitaker: The existence of racist attitudes within some Arab countries is often denied, resulting in scandalous displays of prejudice against certain ethnic groups. Friday 8 September 2006, [[The Guardian]][http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/2006/sep/08/racisminthemiddleeast]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

[[Mona Edeltahawy]] is a columnist for [[Egypt]]'s Al Masry Al Youm and [[Qatar]]'s Al Arab wrote in the [[New York Times]] "'''Racism The Arab world's dirty secret'''" she cites witnessing to racist attacks by Arab Egyptians on blacks when no one objects to it, she admits:
''We are a racist people in Egypt and we are in deep denial about it. On my Facebook page, I blamed racism for my argument and an Egyptian man wrote to deny that we are racists and used as his proof a program on Egyptian Radio featuring Sudanese songs and poetry!
Our silence over racism not only destroys the warmth and hospitality we are proud of as Egyptians, it has deadly consequences''.

She concludes that nothing but [[racism]] is behind police cracking down on 5,000 [[Sudanese refugees]], or beating to death many of them including women and children and what she calls "bloody statistics in [[Egypt]].

She continues on her witnessing: "The racism I saw on the Cairo Metro has an echo in the Arab world at large, where the suffering in Darfur goes ignored because its victims are black and because those who are creating the misery in Darfur are not Americans or Israelis and we only pay attention when America and Israel behave badly."

Lamenting: "We love to cry 'Islamophobia' when we talk about the way Muslim minorities are treated in the West and yet we never stop to consider how we treat minorities and the most vulnerable among us."

She cited how instances in the United States, where Arabs/Muslims have been – rarely – treated bad, yet, most have interfered against this, whereas in Egypt (as well as in the Arab world) the racist deafening silence had been horrendously telling about the Arab racist society.&lt;ref name=mona&gt;Racism The Arab world's dirty secret, Mona Edeeltahawy, [[New York Times]], December 10, 2008 [http://www.nytimes.com/2008/12/10/opinion/10iht-edeltahawy.1.18556273.html]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Accusations against specific Arab governments==

According to [[Holly Burkhalter]] of [[Human Rights Watch]], in a statement made in testimony before the Congress of the United States, "It is fair to say that the Mauritanian government practices undeclared apartheid and severely discriminates on the basis of race."&lt;ref name="ChristopherWise"&gt; Yambo Ouologuem: postcolonial writer, Islamic militant, Christopher Wise, Lynne Rienner Publishers, 1999, p. 4.&lt;/ref&gt;

Beginning in 1991 elders of the [[Zaghawa people]] of Sudan complained that they were victims of an intensifying Arab apartheid campaign.&lt;ref name="Johnson"&gt; Hilde F. Johnson, Waging Peace in Sudan: The Inside Story of the Negotiations That Ended, Trans Pacific Press, 2011, p. 38.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Vukoni Lupa Lasaga]] has accused the Sudanese government of "deftly manipulat(ing) Arab solidarity" to carry out policies of apartheid and ethnic cleansing against non-Arabs in [[Darfur]].&lt;ref name="Lasaga"&gt; Vukoni Lupa Lasaga [http://webcache.googleusercontent.com/search?q=cache:Lfx5pFHQZbMJ:www.afrika.no/Detailed/12818.html+%22apartheid+in+sudan%22&amp;cd=1&amp;hl=en&amp;ct=clnk&amp;gl=us&amp;source=www.google.com] "The slow, violent death of '''apartheid''' in Sudan," 19 September 2006, Norwegian Council for Africa.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Alan Dershowitz]] has pointed to Sudan as an example of a government that deserves the appellation "apartheid,"&lt;ref name="Dershowitz"&gt; Alan Dershowitz, The Case Against Israel's Enemies:
Exposing Jimmy Carter and Others Who Stand in the Way of Peace, John Wiley and Sons, 2009, p. 24.&lt;/ref&gt; and former Canadian [[Minister of Justice (Canada)|Minister of Justice]] [[Irwin Cotler]] has also criticized Sudan in similar terms.&lt;ref name="Bauch"&gt; Hubert Bauch [http://www.canada.com/news/minister+speaks+against+Sudan+Bashir/1362904/story.html] "Ex-minister speaks out against Sudan's al-Bashir" Montreal Gazette, march 6, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Racist incidents by Arabs==
[[Lebanese people|Lebanese]] singer [[Haifa Wehbe]] released an album containing lyrics calling [[Nubian people|Nubian]] black people in Egypt "monkeys". Outraged Egyptian Nubians filed a lawsuit and claimed that it inspired an increase in Arab racism against Nubians in public, including schools.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Nubian fury at 'monkey' lyric of Arab pop star Haifa Wehbe|author=Jack Shenker|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2009/nov/17/nubian-fury-haifa-wehbe|newspaper=The Guardian|date=Tuesday 17 November 2009|accessdate=January 7, 2011|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Lebanon in June 2010, Lebanese Internal Security Forces crashed a Sudanese cancer fundraiser in [[Beirut]]. During the incident, the Lebanese Arabs called the Sudanese Arabs "animals" and "niggers", while physically hitting them with batons. They used extreme physical force and violence against the Sudanese and also used racial epithets. The Sudanese, who held citizenship of Sudan, were legally residing in Lebanon. While pressing their boots on the bodies of the Sudanese, the Lebanese made the Sudanese lie postrate with their stomachs touching the ground. The Lebanese inquired as to how the Sudanese could speak Arabic so well. When the Sudanese explained by saying that they were "Arabs from Sudan", the Lebanese believed that the Sudanese were "making fun of them" and replied by [[Corporal punishment|thrashing]] the Sudanese with physical force again. It was said that "Many people in Sudan accuse Lebanese of viewing them as underdogs and being racist against them because of their color."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Lebanon seeks to contain fallout from raid on Sudanese cancer fundraising event|author=(ST)|url=http://www.sudantribune.com/Lebanon-seeks-to-contain-fallout,35454|newspaper=SUDAN TRIBUNE|date=June 20, 2010|accessdate=January 7, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Relations between Sudan and Lebanon turn sour.|author=ASHARQ AL AWSAT|url=http://www.thefreelibrary.com/Relations+between+Sudan+and+Lebanon+turn+sour.-a0231714936|newspaper=The Middle East Reporter|year=2010|accessdate=January 7, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Gulf Arab countries, specfically Kuwait Arabs have behaved in a racist and violent manner towards Blacks, Kurds and South Asians like [[India]]ns, [[Pakistani people|Pakistani]]s, [[Bangladeshi people|Bangladeshi]]s, and other foreigners. Arab youth have engaged in violent attacks on Blacks and South Asian workers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Why Is There So Much Hate Inside Us?|author=Abdullah Al-Mutairi|url=http://archive.arabnews.com/?page=13&amp;section=0&amp;article=79830&amp;d=27&amp;m=3&amp;y=2006|newspaper=Al-Watan|date=Monday 27 March 2006|accessdate=January 7, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Dark-skinned Egyptian President [[Anwar Sadat]] faced insults of not looking "Egyptian enough" and "Nasser's black poodle."&lt;ref name=racismdivide&gt;{{cite news | url = http://www.npr.org/2011/02/07/133562448/the-root-egypts-race-problem | title = The Root: Race And Racism Divide Egypt | first = Sunni M. | last = Khalid |date = February 7, 2011 | work = npr.org | accessdate = March 3, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; An Egyptian Nubian soccer player Mahmoud Abdel Razek stopped playing football due to racist slurs by rival Egyptian fans during a game.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Shikabala ends Egypt career over racist taunts|agency=Associated Press|url=http://sports.yahoo.com/soccer/news?slug=ap-egypt-shikabala|newspaper=Yahoo! Sports|date=Dec 31 2010|accessdate=January 7, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Egyptian youth regularly attack, stab, and stone African migrants in Egypt, such as Sudanese, Somalians, Ethiopians, and Eritreans, due to their skin color. They use racial slurs like "oonga boonga". The worse the Egyptian economy gets, the more racist attacks there are.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=FEATURE-Egypt's African migrants dodge rocks, fight racism|author=Reuters|url=http://www.mafhoum.com/press3/103S21.htm|newspaper=|date=June 24|accessdate=January 7, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Black women are also targets of sexual harassment.&lt;ref name=racismdivide/&gt;

In March 2011, officials from the [[United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees]] confirmed allegations of discrimination by [[Tunisia]] against black Africans.&lt;ref name=tgam&gt;{{Cite news | url = http://www.theglobeandmail.com/news/world/africa-mideast/at-a-tense-border-crossing-a-systematic-effort-to-keep-black-africans-out/article1925955/ | title = At a Tense Border Crossing, a Systematic Effort To Keep Black Africans Out | first = Doug | last = Saunders |date = 1 March 2011 |work=The Globe and Mail |location=Canada  | accessdate = 3 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Ideology==
Author draws parallel between Arab nationalism and Turkish nationalism, both were "likewise evolving into the "racial" stage, the ideal being a great "Pan-Arab" empire, embracing not merely the ethnically Arab peninsula-homeland, [[Syria]], and [[Mesopotamia]], but also the Arabized regions of [[Egypt]], [[Tripoli]], [[France|French]] [[North Africa]] and the [[Sudan]]."
&lt;ref&gt;''The New World of Islam'' by Lothrop Stoddard, 2009, History, p. 201 [http://books.google.com/books?id=IDAnAQAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA201], ''The Middle East, abstracts and index,'' Part 4 about "Jihadi Movements Worldwide: Abstracts &amp; Documents", p. 1111, from Library Information and Research Service Published by Northumberland Press, 2004&lt;/ref&gt;

Author Tarek Fatah explained that&lt;blockquote&gt; the majority of the Arab constitutions declare the sharia as the basis of legislation, prevent&lt;nowiki&gt;[ing]&lt;/nowiki&gt; most of the countries that pretend to be Islamic States from living up to the standards set by the 1948 United Nations Declaration of Universal Human Rights. It also legitimizes the notion of racial and religious superiority, and allows for multiple levels of citizenship and widespread and systemic discrimination against racial and religious minorities living within a state's borders. Invariably, the human rights of the weak and dispossessed, the minorities and women, the disabled and the heretics, are trampled upon without the slightest sense of guilt or wrongdoing. Men and women are imprisoned, routinely tortured and often killed, while numbed citizens, fearful of offending Islam, unsure about their own rights, insecure about their own identities, allow these violations to continue. By looking the other way, the intelligentsia and middle classes have become complicit in these crimes. They justify their inaction as patriotism, where they stand in solidarity with the Islamic State, with the misguided idea that those who fight for universal human rights are somehow working for Western imperialism or represent the interests of Judeo-Christian civilization.
&lt;ref&gt;''Chasing a Mirage: The Tragic Illusion of an Islamic State,'' by Tarek Fatah [http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20090424.wbkdonnerexcerpt_fatah/BNStory/globebooks/home?cid=al_gam_mostemail]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

[[Christians of Iraq]] site published an extensive historic account on "the Foolishness of imposing Oppressive Arab Nationalism on Non Arabs, Non-Arab Muslim minorities such as the Amazigh, or Berbers, Kurds, and Turkmen found themselves officially out of favor. They faced the prospect of becoming "Arabized" or of being denied political and even civil rights. Groups that identified themselves as neither Arab nor Muslim had it even worse: Southern Sudanese, Copts, Jews, and Assyrians were plunged into a protracted nightmare that saw their communities ground into anonymity, forcing many to emigrate permanently. Even Maronites, whose retention of political power in Lebanon immunized them from utter marginalization, watched with alarm as Arab nationalist propaganda increasingly portrayed them as a foreign and sinister element in the heart of the Arab nation." &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.christiansofiraq.com/ArabismMar236.html |title=The Foolishness of imposing Oppressive Arab Nationalism on Non Arabs |publisher=Christiansofiraq.com |date= |accessdate=2011-04-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Dr. [[Walid Phares]] writes about Arabism's denial of identity of millions of indigenous non-Arab nations as an ethnic cleansing on a politico-cultural level.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.arabicbible.com/christian/intro_arab_christians.htm |title=Arab Christians - Who are they? |publisher=Arabicbible.com |date= |accessdate=2011-04-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A writer on the [[Durban]] conference regarding racism suggests: That stressing out that "Arabism is racism" would have been an interesting debating topic. Yet, he adds that "the [[OIC]]
countries were very clever in how they deflected the [[slavery]] issue that could so easily have been turned on them with a vengeance."&lt;ref&gt;''Out of step: life-story of a politician : politics and religion in a world at war'' by Jack Brian Bloom, Indiana University, p. 112&lt;/ref&gt;

Some [[Muslim]] activists have also expressed that, "Arabism is racism, pure and simple.",&lt;ref&gt;Africa events, Volume 7, published by Dar es Salaam Ltd., 1991, p. 21&lt;/ref&gt; There was Sheikh Mustafa al-Maraghi, who in a famous 1938 essay dismissed the goal of [pan] Arab unity as racist
,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=9casPE-sbXIC&amp;pg=PA29 |title=Radical Islam: medieval theology and ... - Google Books |publisher=Books.google.com |date= |accessdate=2011-04-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Arab]] [[Muslim]] authors in "Arab-[[Iran]]ian relations": &lt;blockquote&gt;Much ink has flowed on the issue of Arab nationalism. Some people believe it to be a racist movement, advocating the superiority of the Arabs.
&lt;ref&gt;Arab-Iranian relations By Khair el-Din Haseeb, K. Haseeb, Markaz Dirāsāt al-Waḥdah al-Arabīyah, Beirut, Lebanon, published by Centre for Arab Unity Studies, 1998, p. 368 [http://books.google.com/books?id=UaptAAAAMAAJ&amp;q=superiority]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; Islamic activist: talks about "the rise of Pan-Arab racism towards non-Arabized Black Africans that still reverberate through regions of the Sudan, Central Africa, Western and Northern Sahara and East Africa." &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.proudfleshjournal.com/issue5/bin-wahad.html ]{{dead link|date=April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
A [[Muslim]] scholar writes that "the Ba'th party, which sowed a Pan-Arabist ideology, was responsible for the genocide of Kurdish people in Iraq as well as the genocide of Shiite Arabs in Iraq. and that "Pan-Arabism does not recognize minorities living in the Arab world. Everybody in this "world" is an Arab."
&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.amislam.com/dream.htm |title=Arabs' Dream of Pan-Arabism |publisher=Amislam.com |date=2007-10-07 |accessdate=2011-04-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Ali A. Allawi]], the former [[Iraq]]i Minister of Defense and Finance, envisioning a peaceful Iraq: "Arabism, racism and sectarianism – would be dethroned. Iraq would be at peace with itself and with its region." &lt;ref&gt;Ali A. Allawi, ''The occupation of Iraq: winning the war, losing the peace'' p. 438 [http://books.google.com/books?id=Cwc3_TTqYhsC&amp;pg=PA438]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1960's, the [[France|French]] Comite d' Action de Defense De- mocratique published a pamphlet titled Racism and Pan-Arabism, it's introduction followed by an article by the well known [[France|French]] sociologist, anthropologist &amp; political leader: [[Jackes Soustelle]] to fight against all kinds of racism, this was followed by a paper by Shlomo Friedrich on "Pan-Arabism: A New Racist Menace?" who offered a sharp critique of [[Nasser]]'s book The Philosophy of the Revolution, and it terms it a mere pale imitation of [[Hitler]]'s [[Mein Kampf]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=Xt7f6WBEP0EC&amp;pg=PA187 |title=The myth of the Jewish race - Google Books |publisher=Books.google.com |date= |accessdate=2011-04-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[African Liberation Forces of Mauritania]] Speaking on Slavery and Genocide in the Sahel, said "those two governments" (Sudan &amp; Mauritania) "went to the same school—the school of Arabization. The professor was [[Saddam Hussein]], and the doctrine was developed in [[Egypt]] by [[Nasser]]. They follow the pattern of [[Ba'athism]] and [[Nasserism]]. implement a policy of Arabization in [[Mauritania]] and [[Sudan]]." &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://towardfreedom.com/home/content/view/902 |title=The African Liberation Forces of Mauritania Speak on Slavery and Genocide in the Sahel |publisher=Towardfreedom.com |date=2006-10-17 |accessdate=2011-04-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Racism – overview==

Jon Lewis (a Mid-East expert whose works on the Arab world's persecution of minorities have appeared in the [[Wall Street Journal]], [[The Forward|Forward]], In the National Interest, Middle East Quarterly and other prestigious publications) laments the media coverage of Darfur, its lack of historic context, clarifying that Darfur is but one example of Arab racism toward non-Arabs within the broader "Arab world."  he believes that the Darfur genocide, "must be viewed not solely as a case of an Islamic jihad, but also as a case of Arab racism", he also draws parallels to Saddam Hussein's genocide against Kurds and the [[Algeria]]n government's repression of the Kaybles."
He adds that without downplaying the Islamic Jihad aspect in both the [[Kurds]] and Kabyles who are primarily [[Sunni]] [[Muslims]], yet, "we cannot understand the violence in [[Darfur]] (and Iraq, for that matter) without examining the persistence of intra-Muslim ethnic conflict in the region and Arab racism."
&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.defenddemocracy.org/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=11773830&amp;Itemid=0 |title=Symposium: Darfur - Islam's Killing Fields |publisher=Defenddemocracy.org |date=2004-09-09 |accessdate=2011-04-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In an interview 'White Skin, Black Mask' the Tunisian-born, [[Alteria|Algerian]] author [[Kamel Riahi]] explained:
"It might come as a surprise to you to learn that Negro was the term people called my black grandfather. I consider myself as someone of a Negro decent, although I am not black. Perhaps my wide nose proves this theory. Therefore, I am sympathetic towards the blacks ideologically, by heritage and by history. We, the whites, will not be liberated until we liberate ourselves from the racist views we have of other races and religions."
He goes on in denouncing the massive common racism in the Arab world:

&lt;blockquote&gt;We still curse each other using "you’re Jewish" or "you’re Kurdish", this is also racial and religious discrimination. Watch any Egyptian sitcom and tell me about the image of the Sudanese character. Listen to the Tunisian jokes about the Libyans or jokes about people from Hums in Greater Syria. Listen to the debates regarding noble families and family lineage… even horses now are divided between what is considered "noble" and what is not. We are racists to the bones. Attempting to hide or silence this fact will not help with the matter because we are a sick society which still suffers from the complexes of color and race.&lt;ref&gt;White skin black mask interview with Kamel Riahi [http://beirut39.blogspot.com/2010/03/white-skin-black-mask-interview-with.html] [http://kamelriahi.elaphblog.com/Posts.aspx?U=1291&amp;A=44329]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Some charge that "ultra-Arabism and Jihadism have been responsible for widespread pesecution and genocide." such Saddam's using chemical weapons and gas against the [[Kurds]] during the bombings of Halabja in northern Iraq. "The Kurds, a non-Arab people whose language belongs to the Iranian group, have suffered from persecution under the Baath of Iraq and Syria, especially since the departure of British and French forces in the late 1940s." (Kurds are also claiming rights in Iran and Turkey.) The Berbers, the pre-Arab native peoples of have been victomized by the Arabs in North Africa.
&lt;ref&gt;''The Confrontation: Winning the War Against Future Jihad'', p. 109, by W. Phares, Macmillan, 2009. ISBN 0-230-61130-3, 978-0-230-61130-6  http://books.google.com/books?id=DTc2ACWFt18C&amp;pg=PA109&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Kurds]] decried 'Arab racism' against them,&lt;ref&gt;Yawar, Referendum and Arab racism Oct 15, 2004, EKurd http://www.ekurd.net/mismas/articles/misc/yawarreferendum.htm&lt;/ref&gt; and have charged that "The Arab League as a useless ideological racist Arabist institution"&lt;ref&gt;Kurdish Media: News about Kurds and Kurdistan http://www.kurdmedia.com/article.aspx?id=9285&lt;/ref&gt;

There're historic racial divisions,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.nytimes.com/1991/11/18/Fus/news-summary-273291.html | work=The New York Times | title=NEWS SUMMARY | date=November 18, 1991}}&lt;/ref&gt; racial and religious prejudices in [[Iraq]], including on Kurds, on Shia and the Marsh Arabs.&lt;ref&gt;John Burns Q and A: Ending the War in Iraq – NYTimes.com
Sep 29, 2009 [http://atwar.blogs.nytimes.com/2009/09/29/john-burns-q-and-a-ending-the-war-in-iraq/]&lt;/ref&gt;

Author Bat Yeor charges bigotry in the Arab Muslim middle east, including "the oppression of the Kurds in both [[Turkey]] and [[Iraq]], the discrimination against non-Muslims and women enforced by shari'a rules in Arab countries, as well as anti-Israel and anti-Western Arab racism."&lt;ref&gt;''Eurabia: the Euro-Arab axis'' p. 104, Bat Ye'or,  Fairleigh Dickinson Univ Press, 2005
ISBN 0-8386-4076-1, 978-0-8386-4076-0 [http://books.google.com/books?id=6nGivth3FqMC&amp;pg=PA104]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Affected victims==

Some of the persecuted victims of racism and discrimination in the Arab world include: [[Africans]] in [[Egypt]],&lt;ref name=mona /&gt; including on [[Eritreans]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://africa.reuters.com/wire/news/usnL26606518.html | work=Reuters}}&lt;/ref&gt; and oppressing [[Darfurian]] refugees,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.israeltoday.co.il/default.aspx?tabid=178&amp;nid=16830 |title=Egyptian troops execute another Darfur refugee |publisher=israel today |date=2008-08-06 |accessdate=2011-04-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Sudan]], [[Algeria]], [[Mauritania]] – fighting off racist policies in these countries,&lt;ref&gt;''The Journal of international studies'', Volumes 30-31 By Sophia University. Institute of International Relations p. 31&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Africa insight, Volumes 23-24, 1993, p. 45&lt;/ref&gt; in [[Iraq]] where blacks face racism &lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://latimesblogs.latimes.com/babylonbeyond/2008/08/baghdad-black-i.html | work=Los Angeles Times | title=IRAQ: Black Iraqis hoping for a Barack Obama win}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=96977550 |title=Black Iraqis In Basra Face Racism |publisher=NPR |date= |accessdate=2011-04-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; and in [[Libya]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEED81139F936A35755C0A96E948260 | work=The New York Times | first=James | last=Brooke | title=African Disputes Pit Arab Vs. Black | date=June 5, 1988}}&lt;/ref&gt; (among others), (including the 2000 anti-African racist violence &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.theperspective.org/oneafrica.html |title=Libya: Dreamland of "One Africa" Betrayed |publisher=Theperspective.org |date=2000-10-23 |accessdate=2011-04-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the current 2 million black African migrants in [[Libya]], quoted in the International Herald Tribune,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Slackman |first=Michael |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2009/03/23/world/africa/23libya.html |title=New Status in Africa Empowers an Ever-Eccentric Qaddafi |location=Libya;Africa |publisher=NYTimes.com |date=2009-03-22 |accessdate=2011-04-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;  to have said, they are treated like slaves and animals,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://europenews.dk/en/node/22151 |title=UN Watch Blasts Sudan on 'Racist Murder', Iran on Persecuting Gays &amp;#124; EuropeNews |publisher=Europenews.dk |date= |accessdate=2011-04-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.unwatch.org/cms.asp?id=741148&amp;campaign_id=63111 |title=UN Watch Turns Tables on Libyan Chair, Exposes Durban 2 Hypocrisy |publisher=Unwatch.org |date= |accessdate=2011-04-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Kurds]] in [[Syria]] and in [[Iraq]],&lt;ref&gt;''Autonomy, sovereignty, and and self-determination: the accommodation of conflicting rights,'' Hurst Hannum – 1996, p. 198 [http://books.google.com/books?id=gOq52_guRUoC&amp;pg=PA198]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Geographical abstracts: Human geography,'' Volume 14, Issues 5-8, published by  Elsevier/Geo Abstracts 2002, p. 852&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.khrw.org/advocate/2005/syrias_kurds_struggle_for_rights.htm ]{{dead link|date=April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ekurd.net/mismas/articles/misc2008/6/syriakurdistan142.htm |title=Kurdistan issues in press interviews: Dr Fuad Omar |publisher=Ekurd.net |date=2008-06-20 |accessdate=2011-04-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Copts]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://freecopts.net/english/index.php?Itemid=9&amp;id=935&amp;option=com_content&amp;task=view ]{{dead link|date=April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref&gt;''Minorities in the Middle East: a history of struggle and self-expression'' by Mordechai Nisan, pp 143–144 [http://books.google.com/books?id=keD9z1XWuNwC&amp;pg=PA144]&lt;/ref&gt;
it worsened Under [[pan-Arabism]] by [[Nasser]] and by empowering the [[Muslim Brotherhood]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.freecopts.net/forum/showthread.php?t=1687 |title=القردة الزانية - الأقباط الأحرار The Free Copts |publisher=Freecopts.net |date= |accessdate=2011-04-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.orderofmaltacolombia.org/news_files/en_News_faith_01.htm |title=A Test of Faith |publisher=Orderofmaltacolombia.org |date=1997-02-12 |accessdate=2011-04-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.netanyahu.org/strugaginemc.html |title=A Struggle Against Intolerance Embattled Coptic |publisher=Netanyahu.org |date= |accessdate=2011-04-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Al-Akhdam]] in [[Yemen]],&lt;ref&gt;''Social exclusion: rhetoric, reality, responses'', Gerry Rodgers, Charles G. Gore, José B. Figueiredo, International Institute for Labour Studies, United Nations Development Programme – Business &amp; Economics, p. 181&lt;/ref&gt; as well as slaves who fights the stigma of their status as 'slaves' in impoverished Yemen",&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=&lt;!--[if IE 6]&gt; &lt;![endif]--&gt; |url=http://www.alarabiya.net/articles/2010/07/21/114451.html |title=Slaves in impoverished Yemen dream of freedom |publisher=Alarabiya.net |date=2010-07-21 |accessdate=2011-04-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Persian people|Persians]] historic struggle against 'Arab supremacy'&lt;ref&gt;''Race and slavery in the Middle East: an historical enquiry'' by Bernard Lewis p. 32 http://books.google.com/books?id=WdjvedBeMHYC&amp;pg=PA32&lt;/ref&gt; [[Berbers]] in [[North Africa]] (Moroccos, Algeria, Tunisia),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.un.org/WCAR/e-kit/backgrounder4.htm |title=Press kit: Issues - Racism against Indigenous peoples - World Conference Against Racism |publisher=Un.org |date=1999-04-01 |accessdate=2011-04-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.foreignpolicy.com/story/cms.php?story_id=2765 |title=The Maghreb in Black and White - By Brian T. Edwards |publisher=Foreign Policy |date=2005-01-05 |accessdate=2011-04-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/worldservice/people/highlights/010423_berbers.shtml |title=Berbers: The Proud Raiders &amp;#124; BBC World Service |publisher=Bbc.co.uk |date= |accessdate=2011-04-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://oreneta.com/kalebeul/2004/06/13/berbers-attack-moroccan-state-racism ]{{dead link|date=April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.north-of-africa.com/article.php3?id_article=403&lt;/ref&gt; [[Asians]] (maids in the by the Gulf Arab nations),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=3NZonSikZPcC&amp;amp;pg=PA27 |title='&amp;#39;Race, Culture and Difference'&amp;#39; by James Donald, Ali Rattansi p 27 |publisher=Books.google.com |date= |accessdate=2011-04-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.middle-east-online.com/english/oman/?id=11601 ]{{dead link|date=April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Rabiya Parekh |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/blogs/worldhaveyoursay/2006/04/south_asian_workers_in_saudi.html |title=World Service - World Have Your Say: South Asian workers in Saudi |publisher=BBC |date=2006-04-04 |accessdate=2011-04-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.adnkronos.com/AKI/English/Religion/?id=3.0.2720941512 |title=Saudi Arabia: Asian immigrant forced to clean mosques for 'skipping prayers' - Adnkronos Religion |publisher=Adnkronos.com |date=2003-04-07 |accessdate=2011-04-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Jews]]. See: [[Antisemitism in the Arab world]], in a 2009 [[PEW]] poll, 90% of the Middle East were found to view Jews unfavorably.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Prusher |first=Ilene |url=http://www.jpost.com/MiddleEast/Article.aspx?id=168176 |title=Poll: 90% of ME views Jews unfavorably |publisher=Jpost.com |date=2009-06-16 |accessdate=2011-04-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==See also==
* [[Racism by country]]
* [[Racism in the Middle East]]
* [[Antisemitism in the Arab world]]
* [[Racism in Asia]]

{{Racism topics}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Racism and discrimination in the Arab world}}
[[Category:Racism by region|Arab]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>