<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20201018212941|984213225" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="28857185" pageid="28857185" ns="0" title="Racism in the Arab world"><revisions><rev timestamp="2020-11-22T12:33:16Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Racism in the Arab world''' covers an array of forms of intolerance against non-Arabs and the expat majority of the [[Arab states of the Persian Gulf]] coming from ([[Sri Lanka]], [[Pakistan]], [[India]] and [[Bangladesh]]) groups as well as Black and Asian groups that ''are'' Muslim; minorities such as [[Armenians]], [[Africans]], [[Latin Americans]], [[Southeast Asia]]ns, [[Jews]], [[Kurds]], and [[Coptic Christians]], [[Assyrian people|Assyrians]], [[Persians]] and other Iranic peoples, [[Turkish people|Turks]], and [[South Asians]] in Arab countries of the Middle East.

The previously forbidden topics of race and racism in the [[Arab world]] have been explored more since the rise of foreign, private and independent media. In one example, [[Al-Jazeera]]'s critical coverage of the [[Darfur crisis]] led to the arrest and conviction of its Khartoum bureau chief.&lt;ref&gt;''Middle East report'': Issues 234-235; Issues 237-241 , Middle East Research &amp; Information Project, 2005, p. 54, p 32&lt;/ref&gt;

==Racist attitudes==
''[[The Guardian]]''’s journalist, [[Brian Whitaker]], wrote on the race taboo in the Arab World; an excerpt:&lt;ref&gt;Brian Whitaker: The existence of racist attitudes within some Arab countries is often denied, resulting in scandalous displays of prejudice against certain ethnic groups. Friday 8 September 2006, [[The Guardian]][https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2006/sep/08/racisminthemiddleeast]&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;blockquote&gt;Racism is a worldwide phenomenon. In some countries it's met with disapproval, in others with denial. The A to Z of ethnic and religious groups in the Middle East embraces Alawites, [[Armenians]], [[Assyrian people|Assyrians]], [[Baháʼí Faith|Baháʼís]], [[Berbers]], [[Copts]], [[Druzes]], [[Ibadis]], [[Ismailis]], [[Jews]], [[Kurds]], [[Maronites]], [[Sahrawis]], [[Tuareg people|Tuareq]], [[Turkmens]], [[Yazidis]] and [[Zaidis]] and [[Nubians]] (by no means an exhaustive list), and yet serious discussion of ethnic/religious diversity and its place in society is a long-standing taboo.
If the existence of non-Arab or non-Muslim groups is acknowledged at all, it is usually only to declare how wonderfully everyone gets along.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

[[Mona Eltahawy]], a columnist for [[Egypt]]'s ''Al Masry Al Youm'' and [[Qatar]]'s ''Al Arab'', wrote in the ''[[New York Times]]'' an article titled, "Racism: The Arab world's dirty secret". She was a witness to racist attacks by Arab Egyptians on blacks and stated: "We are a racist people in Egypt and we are in deep denial about it. On my Facebook page, I blamed racism for my argument and an Egyptian man wrote to deny that we are racists and used as his proof a program on Egyptian Radio featuring Sudanese songs and poetry! Our silence over racism not only destroys the warmth and hospitality we are proud of as Egyptians, it has deadly consequences." She believed [[racism]] was behind a police crackdown on 5,000 [[Sudanese refugees]] and the beating to death of some women and children. She added: "The racism I saw on the Cairo Metro has an echo in the Arab world at large, where the suffering in Darfur goes ignored because its victims are black and because those who are creating the misery in Darfur are not Americans or Israelis and we only pay attention when America and Israel behave badly." She criticized the country's attitudes: "We love to cry 'Islamophobia' when we talk about the way Muslim minorities are treated in the West and yet we never stop to consider how we treat minorities and the most vulnerable among us." While noting that racist incidents are condemned in the United States, she said that in Egypt, as well as in the Arab world, there is a culture of silence toward racist incidents which reflects negatively on Arab society.&lt;ref name=mona&gt;Racism The Arab world's dirty secret, Mona Eltahawy, [[New York Times]], December 10, 2008 [https://www.nytimes.com/2008/12/10/opinion/10iht-edeltahawy.1.18556273.html]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Accusations against specific Arab governments==
===Iraq===
{{see also|Ba'athism|Racism in Iraq}}
In [[Ba'athist Iraq]], especially during the [[Iran–Iraq War]], [[Persia|Iran]] was presented as the age-old enemy of the [[Arabs]]. The Iraqi Ba'athists, according to [[Fred Halliday]], brought the ideas of [[Sati al-Husri]] to their full, official and racist, culmination.{{citation needed|date=June 2015}} For the Ba'athists, their [[pan-Arab]] ideology was laced with [[Anti-Iranian sentiment|anti-Iranian]] racism, it rested on the pursuit of anti-Iranian themes, over the decade and a half after coming to power, Baghdad organised the expulsion of Iraqis of Iranian origin, beginning with 40,000 Fayli Kurds, but totaling up to 200,000 or more, by the early years of the war itself. Such racist policies were reinforced by ideology: in 1981, a year after the start of the Iran–Iraq War, Dar al-Hurriya, the government publishing house,{{citation needed|date=November 2012}} issued ''Three Whom God Should Not Have Created: Persians, Jews, and Flies'' by the author, [[Khairallah Talfah]], the foster-father and father-in-law of Saddam Hussein. Halliday says that it was the Ba'athists too who, claiming to be the defenders of 'Arabism' on the eastern frontiers, brought to the fore the chauvinist myth of Iranian migrants and communities in the [[Persian Gulf]] region.{{sfn|Halliday|2000|pp=117–118}}

===Mauritania===
According to [[Holly Burkhalter]] of [[Human Rights Watch]], in a statement made in testimony before the Congress of the United States, "It is fair to say that the Mauritanian government practices undeclared apartheid and severely discriminates on the basis of race."&lt;ref name="ChristopherWise"&gt;Yambo Ouologuem: postcolonial writer, Islamic militant, Christopher Wise, Lynne Rienner Publishers, 1999, p. 4.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Sudan===
Beginning in 1991, elders of the [[Zaghawa people]] of Sudan complained that they were victims of an intensifying Arab apartheid campaign.&lt;ref name="Johnson"&gt;Hilde F. Johnson, Waging Peace in Sudan: The Inside Story of the Negotiations That Ended, Trans Pacific Press, 2011, p. 38.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Vukoni Lupa Lasaga]] has accused the Sudanese government of "deftly manipulat(ing) Arab solidarity" to carry out policies of apartheid and ethnic cleansing against non-Arabs in [[Darfur]].&lt;ref name="Lasaga"&gt;Vukoni Lupa Lasaga [http://www.afrika.no/Detailed/12818.html] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140901020033/http://www.afrika.no/Detailed/12818.html |date=2014-09-01 }} "The slow, violent death of '''apartheid''' in Sudan," 19 September 2006, Norwegian Council for Africa.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Alan Dershowitz]] has pointed to Sudan as an example of a government that deserves the appellation "apartheid",&lt;ref name="Dershowitz"&gt;Alan Dershowitz, The Case Against Israel's Enemies:
Exposing Jimmy Carter and Others Who Stand in the Way of Peace, John Wiley and Sons, 2009, p. 24.&lt;/ref&gt; and former Canadian [[Minister of Justice (Canada)|Minister of Justice]] [[Irwin Cotler]] has also criticized Sudan in similar terms.&lt;ref name="Bauch"&gt;Hubert Bauch [http://www.canada.com/news/minister+speaks+against+Sudan+Bashir/1362904/story.html] "Ex-minister speaks out against Sudan's al-Bashir" Montreal Gazette, march 6, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Egypt===
Dark-skinned Egyptian President [[Anwar Sadat]] faced insults of not looking "Egyptian enough" and "Nasser's black poodle".&lt;ref name=racismdivide&gt;{{cite news | url = https://www.npr.org/2011/02/07/133562448/the-root-egypts-race-problem | title = The Root: Race And Racism Divide Egypt | first = Sunni M. | last = Khalid |date = February 7, 2011 | work = npr.org | accessdate = March 3, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; An Egyptian [[Nubian people|Nubian]] soccer player [[Shikabala|Mahmoud Abdel Razek]] stopped playing football due to racist slurs by rival Egyptian fans during a game.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Shikabala ends Egypt career over racist taunts|work=usatoday.com|url=http://usatoday30.usatoday.com/sports/soccer/2010-12-31-1686152582_x.htm|date=Dec 31, 2010|accessdate=May 31, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the Egyptian Initiative for Personal Rights (EIPR), Black African immigrants to Egypt often face physical violence and verbal abuse at the hands of the general public and law enforcement officials. Refugees from Sudan are especially targeted, with racial slurs like "oonga boonga" and "samara" (meaning "black") constituting the most typical insults. The EIPR attributes the violence and abuse to both a lack of government efforts at disseminating information, raising awareness and dispelling myths with regard to the economic contributions made by the newcomers, and stereotyping on the part of the Egyptian media.&lt;ref name="EIPR"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://eipr.org/en/report/2010/03/06/635/639|title=III. Racist attitudes and Racially-Motivated Identity Checks and Detentions|publisher=|accessdate=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Black women are also targets of sexual harassment.&lt;ref name=racismdivide/&gt; As a remedy, the EIPR recommends that the Egyptian government "should intensify and accelerate efforts to combat racist xenophobic views towards migrant workers, especially those of Black African origin, and to promote awareness of their positive contribution to society. The government should train all personnel working in the field of criminal justice and law enforcement officials in the spirit of respect for human rights and non-discrimination on ethnic or racial grounds."&lt;ref name="EIPR"/&gt;

===Maghreb (Morocco, Tunisia, Algeria, and Libya)===
In March 2011, officials from the [[United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees]] confirmed allegations of discrimination by [[Tunisia]] against black Africans.&lt;ref name=tgam&gt;{{Cite news | url = https://www.theglobeandmail.com/news/world/africa-mideast/at-a-tense-border-crossing-a-systematic-effort-to-keep-black-africans-out/article1925955/ | title = At a Tense Border Crossing, a Systematic Effort To Keep Black Africans Out | first = Doug | last = Saunders |date = 1 March 2011 |work=The Globe and Mail |location=Canada  | accessdate = 3 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Black Africans were reportedly targeted by rebel forces during the [[2011 Libyan Civil War#Targeting of black Libyans and sub-Saharan Africans|Libyan civil war]] in 2011.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.unhcr.org/4e57d1cb9.html| title=UNHCR concerned as sub-Saharan Africans targeted in Libya|date=25 August 2011|accessdate=14 February 2012|work=UNHCR|location=Geneva}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/africa/rebels-settle-scores-in-libyan-capital-2344671.html| title=Rebels settle scores in Libyan capital|location=Tripoli|work=The Independent| first=Kim | last=Sengupta|date=27 August 2011|accessdate=14 February 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://edition.cnn.com/video/#/video/world/2011/08/31/robertson.libya.african.jails.cnn|title=Gadhafi Loyalists?|accessdate=14 February 2012|date=31 August 2011|work=CNN}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Ideology==
Author draws parallel between [[Arab nationalism]] and [[Turkish nationalism]], both were "likewise evolving into the "racial" stage, the ideal being a great "[[Pan-Arab]]" empire, embracing not merely the ethnically Arab peninsula-homeland, but also the regions of [[Mesopotamia]], [[The Levant]], [[Egypt]], [[Tripoli]], [[North Africa]] and the [[Sudan]]."&lt;ref&gt;''The New World of Islam'' by Lothrop Stoddard, 2009, History, p. 201 [https://books.google.com/books?id=IDAnAQAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA201], ''The Middle East, abstracts and index,'' Part 4 about "Jihadi Movements Worldwide: Abstracts &amp; Documents", p. 1111, from Library Information and Research Service Published by Northumberland Press, 2004&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Christians of Iraq]] site published an extensive historic account on "the Foolishness of imposing Oppressive Arab Nationalism on Non Arabs, Non-Arab Muslim minorities such as the Imazighen or Berbers, Kurds, and Turkmen found themselves officially out of favor. They faced the prospect of becoming 'Arabized' or of being denied political and even civil rights. Groups that identified themselves as neither Arab nor Muslim had it even worse. [[Maronites]], whose retention of political power in Lebanon immunized them from utter marginalization, watched with alarm as Arab nationalist propaganda increasingly portrayed them as a foreign and sinister element in the heart of the Arab nation."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.christiansofiraq.com/ArabismMar236.html |title=The Foolishness of imposing Oppressive Arab Nationalism on Non Arabs |publisher=Christiansofiraq.com |accessdate=2011-04-22 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110703075400/http://www.christiansofiraq.com/ArabismMar236.html |archivedate=2011-07-03 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Dr. [[Walid Phares]] writes about Arabism's denial of identity of millions of indigenous non-Arab nations as an ethnic cleansing on a politico-cultural level.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.arabicbible.com/for-christians/christians/1396-arab-christians-introduction.html |title=Arab Christians: An Introduction |publisher=Arabicbible.com |date= |accessdate=2015-05-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A writer on the [[Durban]] conference regarding racism suggests: That stressing out that "Arabism is racism" would have been an interesting debating topic. Yet, he adds that "the [[OIC]]
countries were very clever in how they deflected the [[slavery]] issue that could so easily have been turned on them with a vengeance."&lt;ref&gt;''Out of step: life-story of a politician : politics and religion in a world at war'' by Jack Brian Bloom, Indiana University, p. 112&lt;/ref&gt;

Some [[Muslim]] activists have also expressed that "Arabism is racism, pure and simple."&lt;ref&gt;Africa events, Volume 7, published by Dar es Salaam Ltd., 1991, p. 21&lt;/ref&gt; There was Sheikh Mustafa al-Maraghi, who in a famous 1938 essay dismissed the goal of [pan] Arab unity as racist.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=9casPE-sbXIC&amp;pg=PA29 |title=Radical Islam: medieval theology and ... - Google Books |date= 26 September 1990|isbn=0300049153 |accessdate=2011-04-22|last1=Sivan |first1=Emmanuel }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Arab Muslim authors in "Arab-Iranian relations": &lt;blockquote&gt;Much ink has flowed on the issue of Arab nationalism. Some people believe it to be a racist movement, advocating the superiority of the Arabs.&lt;ref&gt;Arab-Iranian relations By Khair el-Din Haseeb, K. Haseeb, Markaz Dirāsāt al-Waḥdah al-Arabīyah, Beirut, Lebanon, published by Centre for Arab Unity Studies, 1998, p. 368 [https://books.google.com/books?id=UaptAAAAMAAJ&amp;q=superiority]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

A Muslim scholar writes that "the Ba'th party, which sowed a Pan-Arabist ideology, was responsible for the genocide of Kurdish people in Iraq as well as the genocide of Shiite Arabs in Iraq, and that "Pan-Arabism does not recognize minorities living in the Arab world. Everybody in this "world" is an Arab."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://amislam.com/dream.htm|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20101119093545/http://amislam.com/dream.htm|archivedate=2010-11-19 |title=Arabs' Dream of Pan-Arabism |publisher=Amislam.com |date=2007-10-07 |accessdate=2014-07-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Ali A. Allawi]], the former [[Iraq]]i Minister of Defense and Finance, envisioning a peaceful Iraq: "Arabism, racism and sectarianism – would be dethroned. Iraq would be at peace with itself and with its region."&lt;ref&gt;Ali A. Allawi, ''The occupation of Iraq: winning the war, losing the peace'' p. 438 [https://books.google.com/books?id=Cwc3_TTqYhsC&amp;pg=PA438]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1960's, the [[France|French]] Comite d' Action de Defense De- mocratique published a pamphlet titled Racism and Pan-Arabism, its introduction followed by an article by the well known [[France|French]] sociologist, anthropologist &amp; political leader: [[Jackes Soustelle]] to fight against all kinds of racism, this was followed by a paper by Shlomo Friedrich on "Pan-Arabism: A New Racist Menace?" who offered a sharp critique of [[Nasser]]'s book The Philosophy of the Revolution, and it terms it a mere pale imitation of [[Hitler]]'s [[Mein Kampf]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Xt7f6WBEP0EC&amp;pg=PA187 |title=The myth of the Jewish race - Google Books |isbn=0814319483 |accessdate=2011-04-22|last1=Patai |first1=Raphael |last2=Patai |first2=Jennifer |year=1989 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[African Liberation Forces of Mauritania]] speaking on slavery and genocide in the Sahel, said "those two governments [Sudan and Mauritania] went to the same school—the school of Arabization. The professor was [[Saddam Hussein]], and the doctrine was developed in [[Egypt]] by [[Nasser]]. They follow the pattern of [[Ba'athism]] and [[Nasserism]]. In the color of their skin they may not be Arabs, they may be Black. But they want to be Arab, and they follow this policy of Arabization in Mauritania and Sudan."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.towardfreedom.com/30-archives/africa/857-the-african-liberation-forces-of-mauritania-speak-on-slavery-and-genocide-in-the-sahel |title=The African Liberation Forces of Mauritania Speak on Slavery and Genocide in the Sahel |publisher=Towardfreedom.com |date=2006-10-17 |accessdate=2015-05-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Racism – overview==

In an interview 'White Skin, Black Mask' the Tunisian-born, [[Algeria]]n author [[Kamel Riahi]] explained:
"It might come as a surprise to you to learn that Negro was the term people called my black grandfather. I consider myself as someone of a Negro descent, although I am not black. Perhaps my wide nose proves this theory. Therefore, I am sympathetic towards the blacks ideologically, by heritage and by history. We, the whites, will not be liberated until we liberate ourselves from the racist views we have of other races and religions."
He goes on in denouncing the massive common racism in the Arab world:

&lt;blockquote&gt;We still curse each other using "you’re Jewish" or "you’re Kurdish", this is also racial and religious discrimination. Watch any Egyptian sitcom and tell me about the image of the Sudanese character. Listen to the Tunisian jokes about the Libyans or jokes about people from Hums in Greater Syria. Listen to the debates regarding noble families and family lineage… even horses now are divided between what is considered "noble" and what is not. We are racists to the bones. Attempting to hide or silence this fact will not help with the matter because we are a sick society which still suffers from the complexes of color and race.&lt;ref&gt;White skin black mask interview with Kamel Riahi [http://beirut39.blogspot.com/2010/03/white-skin-black-mask-interview-with.html] [http://kamelriahi.elaphblog.com/Posts.aspx?U=1291&amp;A=44329]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Some charge that "ultra-Arabism and Jihadism have been responsible for widespread persecution and genocide." such Saddam's using chemical weapons and gas against the [[Kurds]] during the bombings of Halabja in northern Iraq. "The Kurds, a non-Arab people whose language belongs to the Iranian group, have suffered from persecution under the Baath of Iraq and Syria, especially since the departure of British and French forces in the late 1940s." (Kurds are also claiming rights in Iran and Turkey.) The Berbers, the pre-Arab native peoples of have been victomized by the Arabs in North Africa.&lt;ref&gt;''The Confrontation: Winning the War Against Future Jihad'', p. 109, by W. Phares, Macmillan, 2009. {{ISBN|0-230-61130-3}}, 978-0-230-61130-6  https://books.google.com/books?id=DTc2ACWFt18C&amp;pg=PA109&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Kurds]] decried 'Arab racism' against them,&lt;ref&gt;Yawar, Referendum and Arab racism Oct 15, 2004, EKurd http://www.ekurd.net/mismas/articles/misc/yawarreferendum.htm&lt;/ref&gt; and have branded "The Arab League as a useless ideological racist Arabist institution."&lt;ref&gt;Kurdish Media: News about Kurds and Kurdistan http://www.kurdmedia.com/article.aspx?id=9285&lt;/ref&gt;

There're historic racial divisions,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=https://www.nytimes.com/1991/11/18/Fus/news-summary-273291.html | work=The New York Times | title=NEWS SUMMARY | date=November 18, 1991}}&lt;/ref&gt; racial and religious prejudices in [[Iraq]], including on Kurds, on Shia and the Marsh Arabs.&lt;ref&gt;John Burns Q and A: Ending the War in Iraq – NYTimes.com
Sep 29, 2009 [http://atwar.blogs.nytimes.com/2009/09/29/john-burns-q-and-a-ending-the-war-in-iraq/]&lt;/ref&gt;

Author Bat Yeor charges bigotry in the Arab Muslim middle east, including "the oppression of the Kurds in both [[Turkey]] and [[Iraq]], the discrimination against non-Muslims and women enforced by shari'a rules in Arab countries, as well as anti-Israel and anti-Western Arab racism."&lt;ref&gt;''Eurabia: the Euro-Arab axis'' p. 104, Bat Ye'or,  Fairleigh Dickinson Univ Press, 2005
{{ISBN|0-8386-4076-1}}, 978-0-8386-4076-0 [https://books.google.com/books?id=6nGivth3FqMC&amp;pg=PA104]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Affected victims==
In [[Sudan]], including the [[Nuba Mountains]] and Blue Nile regions, from 1955 to 2005, it is estimated that nearly 4 million black people were killed or ethnically cleansed. During the [[Second Sudanese Civil War]], about 2.5 million people were killed in attacks widely regarded as racially motivated against black indigenous Africans.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jewishpost.com/news/Simon-Dengs-Speech.html|title=JewishPost.com - Remarkable Speech by Simon Deng, Once a Sudanese Slave, Addressing the Durban Conference in New York|publisher=|accessdate=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Racism has been documented in [[Libya]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=https://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEED81139F936A35755C0A96E948260 | work=The New York Times | first=James | last=Brooke | title=African Disputes Pit Arab Vs. Black | date=June 5, 1988}}&lt;/ref&gt; including the 2000 anti-African racist violence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.theperspective.org/oneafrica.html |title=Libya: Dreamland of "One Africa" Betrayed |publisher=Theperspective.org |date=2000-10-23 |accessdate=2011-04-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; They have reported facing racism in the country, with one witness reporting being called a "slave" and "animal."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Slackman |first=Michael |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2009/03/23/world/africa/23libya.html |title=New Status in Africa Empowers an Ever-Eccentric Qaddafi |location=Libya;Africa |publisher=NYTimes.com |date=2009-03-22 |accessdate=2011-04-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.unwatch.org/cms.asp?id=741148&amp;campaign_id=63111 |title=UN Watch Turns Tables on Libyan Chair, Exposes Durban 2 Hypocrisy |publisher=Unwatch.org |accessdate=2011-04-22 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20111122093840/http://www.unwatch.org/cms.asp?id=741148&amp;campaign_id=63111 |archivedate=2011-11-22 }}&lt;/ref&gt; From the start of [[2011 Libyan Civil War|Libyan Civil War]] in 2011, blacks were massacred for their skin color according to an [[Amnesty International]] report.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.csmonitor.com/World/Middle-East/2011/0829/In-Tripoli-African-mercenaries-at-risk |title=In Tripoli, African 'mercenaries' at risk |publisher=Csmonitor}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2012/feb/16/amnesty-widespread-torture-libyan-militias | work=The Guardian| title=Amnesty finds widespread use of torture by Libyan militias}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Algeria victims of racism include Sub-Saharan immigrants who suffer daily from verbal attacks and other forms of discrimination. Many Sub-Saharan immigrants find themselves on the street due to lack of public resources. The homeless immigrants often quote the Quran in an effort to appeal to the country's Muslim unity and divert attention from their race.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2016/05/03/opinion/kamel-daoud-black-in-algeria-then-youd-better-be-muslim.html|title=Opinion {{!}} Black in Algeria? Then You'd Better Be Muslim|last=Daoud|first=Kamel|date=2016-05-02|work=The New York Times|access-date=2018-12-08|language=en-US|issn=0362-4331}}&lt;/ref&gt; On the world stage the country has declared that members of its national football team must undergo a stricter selection process if they possess dual citizenship to ensure their loyalty to the country.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.middleeasteye.net/news/racism-algeria-targets-dual-nationality-football-players-2080075315|title=Video campaign tackles dual-national 'racism' in Algerian football|website=Middle East Eye|language=en|access-date=2018-12-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some of the persecuted victims of racism and discrimination in the Arab world include: Sub-Saharan [[Africans]] in [[Egypt]],&lt;ref name=mona /&gt; including on [[Eritreans]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.sudantribune.com/spip.php?article27664 |title=Egypt crackdown on African migrants hits Eritreans|work=Sudan Tribune}}&lt;/ref&gt; and oppressing [[Darfur]]ian refugees,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.israeltoday.co.il/default.aspx?tabid=178&amp;nid=16830 |title=Egyptian troops execute another Darfur refugee |publisher=israel today |date=2008-08-06 |accessdate=2011-04-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Algeria]], [[Mauritania]] – fighting off racist policies in these countries,&lt;ref&gt;''The Journal of international studies'', Volumes 30-31 By Sophia University. Institute of International Relations p. 31&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Africa insight, Volumes 23-24, 1993, p. 45&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.nytimes.com/2016/05/03/opinion/kamel-daoud-black-in-algeria-then-youd-better-be-muslim.html?_r=0 New York Times: "Black in Algeria? Then You’d Better Be Muslim" by KAMEL DAOUD MAY 2, 2016]&lt;/ref&gt; in [[Iraq]] where blacks face racism,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://latimesblogs.latimes.com/babylonbeyond/2008/08/baghdad-black-i.html | work=Los Angeles Times | title=IRAQ: Black Iraqis hoping for a Barack Obama win | date=2008-08-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=96977550 |title=Black Iraqis In Basra Face Racism |publisher=NPR |date= |accessdate=2011-04-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Kurds]] in [[Syria]] and in [[Iraq]],&lt;ref&gt;''Autonomy, sovereignty, and self-determination: the accommodation of conflicting rights,'' Hurst Hannum – 1996, p. 198 [https://books.google.com/books?id=gOq52_guRUoC&amp;pg=PA198]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Geographical abstracts: Human geography,'' Volume 14, Issues 5-8, published by  Elsevier/Geo Abstracts 2002, p. 852&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.voanews.com/content/a-13-2005-09-02-voa15-66937607/264610.html|date=28 October 2009|title=Syria's Kurds Struggle for Rights}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ekurd.net/mismas/articles/misc2008/6/syriakurdistan142.htm |title=Kurdistan issues in press interviews: Dr Fuad Omar |publisher=Ekurd.net |date=2008-06-20 |accessdate=2011-04-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Copts]],&lt;ref&gt;[https://archive.is/20090622230736/http://freecopts.net/english/index.php?Itemid=9&amp;id=935&amp;option=com_content&amp;task=view ]&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref&gt;''Minorities in the Middle East: a history of struggle and self-expression'' by Mordechai Nisan, pp 143–144 [https://books.google.com/books?id=keD9z1XWuNwC&amp;pg=PA144]&lt;/ref&gt;
it worsened under [[pan-Arabism]] by [[Nasser]] and with the empowerment of the [[Muslim Brotherhood]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.freecopts.net/forum/showthread.php?t=1687 |title=القردة الزانية - الأقباط الأحرار The Free Copts |publisher=Freecopts.net |date= |accessdate=2011-04-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.orderofmaltacolombia.org/news_files/en_News_faith_01.htm |title=A Test of Faith |publisher=Orderofmaltacolombia.org |date=1997-02-12 |accessdate=2011-04-22|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120523152826/http://www.orderofmaltacolombia.org/news_files/en_News_faith_01.htm|archivedate=23 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.netanyahu.org/strugaginemc.html |title=A Struggle Against Intolerance Embattled Coptic |publisher=Netanyahu.org |accessdate=2011-04-22 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20010128070600/http://www.netanyahu.org/strugaginemc.html |archivedate=2001-01-28 }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Al-Akhdam]] in [[Yemen]],&lt;ref&gt;''Social exclusion: rhetoric, reality, responses'', Gerry Rodgers, Charles G. Gore, José B. Figueiredo, International Institute for Labour Studies, United Nations Development Programme – Business &amp; Economics, p. 181&lt;/ref&gt; as well as slaves who fight the stigma of their status as 'slaves' in impoverished Yemen,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=&lt;!--[if IE 6]&gt; &lt;![endif]--&gt; |url=http://www.alarabiya.net/articles/2010/07/21/114451.html |title=Slaves in impoverished Yemen dream of freedom |publisher=Alarabiya.net |date=2010-07-21 |accessdate=2011-04-22 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120112103701/http://www.alarabiya.net/articles/2010/07/21/114451.html |archivedate=2012-01-12 }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Persian people|Persians']] historic struggle against the 'Arab supremacy,'&lt;ref&gt;''Race and slavery in the Middle East: an historical enquiry'' by Bernard Lewis p. 32 https://books.google.com/books?id=WdjvedBeMHYC&amp;pg=PA32&lt;/ref&gt; [[Berbers]] in [[North Africa]] (Moroccos, Algeria, Tunisia, Libya ),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.un.org/WCAR/e-kit/backgrounder4.htm |title=Press kit: Issues - Racism against Indigenous peoples - World Conference Against Racism |publisher=Un.org |date=1999-04-01 |accessdate=2011-04-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://foreignpolicy.com/2009/10/22/the-maghreb-in-black-and-white/ |title=The Maghreb in Black and White - By Brian T. Edwards |publisher=Foreign Policy |date=2005-01-05 |accessdate=2015-05-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/worldservice/people/highlights/010423_berbers.shtml |title=Berbers: The Proud Raiders &amp;#124; BBC World Service |publisher=Bbc.co.uk |date= |accessdate=2011-04-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://oreneta.com/kalebeul/2004/06/13/berbers-attack-moroccan-state-racism/|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20061028104319/http://oreneta.com/kalebeul/2004/06/13/berbers-attack-moroccan-state-racism/|title=kalebeul » Berbers attack Moroccan state racism|archivedate=28 October 2006|publisher=|accessdate=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://databank.isranet.org/article.asp?article=23721|title=Berber Leader Belkacem Lounes_ 'There Is No Worse Colonialism Than That of the Pan-Arabist Clan that Wants to Dominate Our People' - CIJR Databank|accessdate=31 May 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[South Asians]] and [[Southeast Asians]] (migrant workers and maids in the Gulf Arab nations),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=3NZonSikZPcC |title=''Race, Culture and Difference'' by James Donald, Ali Rattansi p 27 |date= 21 April 1992|isbn=9780803985803 |accessdate=2011-04-22|last1=Donald |first1=James |last2=Rattansi |first2=Ali }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.middle-east-online.com/english/?id=11601|title=Asian maids in Gulf face maltreatment|publisher=Middle East Online|date=10 October 2004|accessdate=31 May 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Rabiya Parekh |url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/blogs/worldhaveyoursay/2006/04/south_asian_workers_in_saudi.html |title=World Service - World Have Your Say: South Asian workers in Saudi |publisher=BBC |date=2006-04-04 |accessdate=2011-04-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.adnkronos.com/AKI/English/Religion/?id=3.0.2720941512 |title=Saudi Arabia: Asian immigrant forced to clean mosques for 'skipping prayers' - Adnkronos Religion |publisher=Adnkronos.com |date=2003-04-07 |accessdate=2011-04-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Jews]] (see: [[Antisemitism in the Arab world]], in a 2009 [[PEW]] poll, 90% of the Middle East were found to view [[Jews]] unfavorably).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Prusher |first=Ilene |url=http://www.jpost.com/MiddleEast/Article.aspx?id=168176 |title=Poll: 90% of ME views [ews unfavorably |publisher=Jpost.com |date=2009-06-16 |accessdate=2011-04-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although slavery was officially abolished in 1981, a 2012 [[CNN]] report suggested that 10% to 20% of the [[Mauritania]]n population was enslaved with a correlation with skin color – darker-skinned Mauritanians were often enslaved by lighter-skinned.&lt;ref name=cnnmauritania&gt;{{cite news | url = http://edition.cnn.com/interactive/2012/03/world/mauritania.slaverys.last.stronghold/index.html | title = Slavery's last stronghold | first = John D. | last = Sutter | date = March 2012 | work = [[CNN]] }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Wikiquote}}
* [[Antisemitism in the Arab world]]
* [[Racism by country]]
* [[Racism in the Middle East]]
* [[Racism in Asia]]
* [[Racism in Mauritania]]

==References==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

{{Racism topics}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Racism and discrimination in the Arab world}}
[[Category:Racism in the Arab world| ]]
[[Category:Arab world]]
[[Category:Racism by region|Arab]]
[[Category:Racism in the Middle East|Arab world]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>