<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20101030233634|393880452" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="338825" pageid="338825" ns="0" title="Toleration"><revisions><rev timestamp="2010-11-02T13:55:04Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Redirect|Tolerance}}
[[File:Minerva als Symbol der Toleranz.jpg|thumb|Minerva as a symbol of enlightened wisdom protects the believers of all religions ([[Daniel Chodowiecki]], 1791)]]

In general usage, '''tolerance''' is a fair, objective, and permissive attitude toward those whose beliefs or personal characteristics (race, religion, nationality, etc.), differ from one's own.

In [[sociology|social]], [[culture|cultural]] and [[religion|religious]] contexts, '''tolerance''' and '''toleration''' are terms used to describe attitudes which are "[[wiktionary:toleration|tolerant]]" (or ''moderately [[respect]]ful'') of practices or group memberships that may be disapproved of by those in the majority. 

In practice, "tolerance" indicates support for practices that prohibit ethnic and religious [[discrimination]]. Conversely, 'intolerance' may be used to refer to the discriminatory practices sought to be prohibited. Though developed to refer to the [[religious toleration]] of minority religious sects following the [[Protestant Reformation]], these terms are increasingly used to refer to a wider range of tolerated practices and groups, or of political parties or ideas widely considered objectionable.&lt;ref&gt;http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/Toleration&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
As a practical matter, governments have always had to consider the question of which groups and practices to tolerate and which to persecute. The [[Edicts of Ashoka]] issued by [[Ashoka the Great]] (269 – 231 BCE) during the [[Maurya Empire]] declared ethnic and religious tolerance. This fact, being Ashoka Buddhist, means also how the [[Buddhism]] was tolerant, referring to many other religions, especially monotheist. The later expanding [[Roman Empire]] faced the question of whether or to what extent practices or beliefs could be tolerated or vigorously persecuted. Practically, for Romans, were tolerated all religions not conflicting with Roman laws. Likewise, during the [[Middle Ages]], the rulers of [[Christendom|Christian Europe]] or the [[Islamic Golden Age|Muslim Middle East]] sometimes extended toleration to minority religious groups, and sometimes did not. Jews in particular suffered under [[Antisemitism|anti-Semitic]] persecutions in medieval [[Europe]].&lt;ref name="Vartan"&gt;Vartan Gregorian, "Islam: A Mosaic, Not a Monolith", Brookings Institution Press, 2003, pg 26-38 ISBN 0-8157-3283-X&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?artid=412&amp;letter=G&amp;search=Granada Granada] by Richard Gottheil, Meyer Kayserling, ''[[Jewish Encyclopedia]]''. 1906 ed.&lt;/ref&gt; A notable exception was [[Poland]], which served as a haven for European Judaism because of its relative tolerance - by the mid-sixteenth century, 80% of the world's Jews lived in Poland.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/vjw/Poland.html Jewish Virtual Library - Poland]&lt;/ref&gt;

An early champion of toleration in Europe was [[Pawel Wlodkowic]], who at the [[Council of Constance]] advocated the [[pagan]] nations' rights.&lt;ref&gt;[http://original.britannica.com/eb/article-28175/Poland#396759.hook Britannica Online - Poland: The rule of Jagielo]&lt;/ref&gt; However, the development of a body of theory on the subject of toleration didn't begin until the 16th and 17th centuries, in response to the [[Protestant Reformation]] and the [[European wars of religion|Wars of Religion]] and persecutions that followed the breaks with the [[Catholic Church]] instigated by [[Martin Luther]] and [[Huldrych Zwingli]] and others. In response to the theory of persecution that was used to justify wars of religion and the execution of persons convicted of [[heresy]] and [[witchcraft]], writers such as [[Sebastian Castellio]] and [[Michel de Montaigne]] questioned the morality of religious persecution, and offered arguments for toleration. By contrast, Poland, which had been uniquely tolerant and ethnically as well as religiously diverse, officially confirmed its status as "a place of shelter for heretics" in the [[Warsaw Confederation|Confederation of Warsaw of 1573]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://portal.unesco.org/ci/en/ev.php-URL_ID=7748&amp;URL_DO=DO_TOPIC&amp;URL_SECTION=201.html Portal UNESCO, Poland - The General Confederation of Warsaw]&lt;/ref&gt; the first toleration act in Europe.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.polityka.pl/archive/do/registry/secure/showArticle?id=945 Dzieje podzielone, Prof. Janusz Tazbir, Polityka 03-07-2004]&lt;/ref&gt;

A detailed and influential body of writing on the question of toleration was produced in [[Great Britain|Britain]] in the 17th century, during and after the destructive [[English Civil War]]s. [[John Milton]] and radical Parliamentarians such as [[Gerrard Winstanley]] argued that Christian and Jewish worship should be protected, and it was during the period that [[Oliver Cromwell]] allowed the return of Jews to England. These early theories of toleration were limited however, and did not extend toleration to [[Roman Catholics]] (who were perceived as disloyal to their country) or [[atheists]] (who were held to lack any moral basis for action). [[John Locke]], in his [[A Letter Concerning Toleration|Letter Concerning Toleration]] and [[Two Treatises of Government]] proposed a more detailed and systematic theory of toleration, which included a principle of [[separation of church and state]] that formed the basis for future constitutional democracies, but also did not extend toleration to Roman Catholics or atheists. The British [[Toleration Act of 1689]] was the political result of seventeenth century theorists and political exigency, which despite the limited scope of the toleration it granted was nevertheless a key development in the history of toleration, which helped produce greater political stability in the British Isles.

The philosophers and writers of the [[Age of Enlightenment|Enlightenment]], especially [[Voltaire]] and [[Gotthold Ephraim Lessing|Lessing]], promoted and further developed the notion of religious tolerance, which however was not sufficient to prevent the atrocities of the [[Reign of Terror]]. The incorporation by [[Thomas Jefferson]] and others of Locke's theories of toleration into the [[United States Constitution|U.S. Constitution]] was arguably more successful.

Discussions of toleration therefore often divided between those who view the term as a minimal and perhaps even historical virtue (perhaps today to be replaced by a more positive and robust appreciation of [[Pluralism (political philosophy)|pluralism]] or [[Multiculturalism|diversity]]), and those who view it as a concept with an important continuing vitality, and who are more likely to use the term in considering contemporary issues regarding discrimination on the basis of race, nationality, gender, sexuality, disability, and other reasons.

There are also debates with regard to the historical factors that produced the principle of toleration, as well as to the proper reasons toleration should be exercised, with some arguing that the growth of [[skepticism]] was an important or necessary factor in the development of toleration, and others arguing that religious belief or an evolving notion of respect for individual persons was or is the basis on which toleration was or should be practiced.

==Tolerance and monotheism==
One theory of the origins of religious intolerance, propounded by [[Sigmund Freud]] in ''Moses and Monotheism'', links intolerance to monotheism. More recently, [[Bernard Lewis]] and Mark Cohen have argued that the modern understanding of tolerance, involving concepts of national identity and equal citizenship for persons of different religions, was not considered a value by pre-modern Muslims or Christians, due to the implications of monotheism.&lt;ref&gt;Lewis (1997), p.321; (1984) p.65; Cohen (1995), p.xix&lt;/ref&gt; The historian [[Geoffrey Rudolph Elton|G.R. Elton]] explains that in pre-modern times, monotheists viewed such toleration as a sign of weakness or even wickedness towards God.&lt;ref&gt;quoted in Cohen (1995), p.xix&lt;/ref&gt; The usual definition of tolerance in pre-modern times as Bernard Lewis puts it was that:

{{cquote|I am in charge. I will allow you some though not all of the rights and privileges that I enjoy, provided that you behave yourself according to rules that I will lay down and enforce."&lt;ref name=LewisBrandeis1&gt;Lewis (2006), pp.25-36&lt;/ref&gt;}}

[[Mark R. Cohen|Mark Cohen]] states that it seems that all the monotheistic religions in power throughout the history have felt it proper, if not obligatory, to persecute nonconforming religions.&lt;ref name="Cohen1"&gt;Cohen (1995) p. xix&lt;/ref&gt; Therefore, Cohen concludes, [[Islamic Golden Age|Medieval Islam]] and [[Middle Ages|Medieval Christianity]] in power should have persecuted non-believers in their lands and "Judaism, briefly in power during the Hasmonean period (second century BCE) should have persecuted pagan Idumeans".&lt;ref name="Cohen1"/&gt; Cohen continues: "When all is said and done, however, the historical evidence indicates that the [[Golden age of Jewish culture in Spain|Jews of Islam]], especially during the formative and classical centuries (up to thirteenth century), experienced much less persecution than did the Jews of [[Christendom]]. This begs a more thorough and nuanced explanation than has hitherto been given."&lt;ref name="Cohen1"/&gt;

==Tolerating the intolerant==
{{see also|Paradox of tolerance}}
Philosopher [[Karl Popper]] asserted, in ''[[The Open Society and Its Enemies]]'' Vol. 1, that we are warranted in refusing to tolerate intolerance; illustrating that there are limits to tolerance.

Philosopher [[John Rawls]] devotes a section of his influential and controversial book ''[[A Theory of Justice]]'' to this problem; whether a just society should or should not tolerate the intolerant. He also addresses the related issue of whether or not the intolerant have any right to complain when they are not tolerated, within their society.

Rawls concludes that a just society must be tolerant; therefore, the intolerant must be tolerated, for otherwise, the society would then itself be intolerant, and thus unjust. However, Rawls qualifies this conclusion by insisting, like Popper, that society and its social institutions have a reasonable right of self-preservation that supersedes the principle of tolerance. In his words:

{{cquote|While an intolerant sect does not itself have title to complain of intolerance, its freedom should be restricted only when the tolerant sincerely and with reason believe that their own security and that of the institutions of liberty are in danger.&lt;ref name=Rawls1921&gt;{{Citation
 | title = A Theory of Justice
 | year = 1971
 | author = Rawls, John,
 | page = 220
}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
McNair (2009) describes the notion of tolerantism in his novel ''The Orchard''.  He states, 
{{cquote|Tolerantism, with its imposed value relativism and indiscriminate tolerance, is the rule of the day.  If you think there is anything other than value relativism and tolerance for everything, you are not tolerated. (however) The position falls in on itself.  How can a tree be tolerant, and claim to celebrate all forms of diversity, when positions contradict one another or are mutually exclusive.  How can these trees be tolerant of others who hold to a set of values, which say values are not relative, and that all kinds of diversity should not be tolerated let alone celebrated and at the same time claim to be tolerant of all positions?  These by themselves would be strange enough positions to hold.  Yet, followers of tolerantism then attempt to impose value relativism and total tolerance on trees who hold moral values.
&lt;ref name=McNair2009&gt;{{Citation
 | title = The Orchard
 | year = 2009
 | author = McNair, Jeff,
 | page = 78
}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

==Tolerance as a spiritual virtue==
[[Swami Tripurari]] states that the practice of tolerance leads to the ability to distinguish the [[jiva]] (soul) from the mind and body.&lt;ref&gt;[[Swami Tripurari]], "[http://www.swami.org/pages/sanga/1999/1999_3.php Tolerance: the Ornament of the Saints]", ''Sanga'', 1999.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the [[Bhagavad Gita]], [[Krishna]] says "... the nonpermanent appearance of happiness and distress, and their disappearance in due course, are like the appearance and disappearance of winter and summer seasons. They arise from sense perception ... and one must learn to tolerate them without being disturbed.&lt;ref&gt;[http://bhagavadgitaasitis.com/2/14/en1 Bhaktivedanta VedaBase: Bhagavad-gita As It Is 2.14]&lt;/ref&gt; The person who is not disturbed by happiness and distress and is steady in both is certainly eligible for [[Moksha|liberation]]."&lt;ref&gt;[http://bhagavadgitaasitis.com/2/15/en1 Bhaktivedanta VedaBase: Bhagavad-gita As It Is 2.15]&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Religious tolerance]]
*[[Religious intolerance]]
*[[Ideology]]
*[[Theocracy]]
* The Tolerance Webzine Tolerance.ca http://www.tolerance.ca/Default.aspx?L=en&amp;sc=1

==References==
{{reflist}}
*[http://www.annesullivan.cn/quotes-by-helen-adams-keller/quotes-by-helen-adams-keller-2 Quote about Tolerance by Helen Keller]

[[Category:Multiculturalism]]

[[ar:تسامح]]
[[bg:Толерантност]]
[[ca:Tolerància social]]
[[cs:Tolerance]]
[[da:Tolerance]]
[[de:Toleranz]]
[[et:Sallivus]]
[[es:Tolerancia social]]
[[eo:Toleremo]]
[[fa:تسامح]]
[[fr:Tolérance]]
[[gl:Tolerancia]]
[[ko:관용]]
[[hy:Հանդուրժողականություն]]
[[id:Toleransi]]
[[it:Tolleranza]]
[[he:סובלנות]]
[[ka:ტოლერანტობა]]
[[la:Tolerantia]]
[[lt:Tolerancija]]
[[hu:Tolerancia]]
[[arz:تسامح]]
[[nl:Tolerantie (maatschappij)]]
[[ja:寛容]]
[[no:Toleranse]]
[[nn:Toleranse]]
[[pl:Tolerancja (socjologia)]]
[[pt:Tolerância]]
[[ro:Toleranță]]
[[ru:Толерантность (социология)]]
[[simple:Toleration]]
[[sk:Tolerancia (znášanlivosť)]]
[[sl:Strpnost]]
[[sr:Трпељивост]]
[[fi:Suvaitsevuus]]
[[sv:Tolerans]]
[[tr:Hoşgörü]]
[[vls:Tolerantie]]
[[zh:寬容]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>