<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20041110144958|7297764" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1150894" pageid="1150894" ns="0" title="Victim blaming"><revisions><rev timestamp="2004-11-10T15:09:05Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Victim blaming''' is holding the [[victim]] of a [[crime]] or other misfortune to be in whole or in part responsible for what has happened to them.  

For example a motorist who leaves his/her car unlocked with the keys in the ignition may be held partly responsible if the car is stolen. A person who uses verbal abuse may be held partly responsible if they become a victim of a physical assault. 

In the context of [[rape]], this concept refers to popular attitudes that behaviour such as flirting or wearing sexually provocative clothing may encourage rape: that they are analagous to leaving ones car with the keys in the ignition or provoking an assault by "winding up" the assailant. In extreme cases victims are accused of "asking for it" by not behaving demurely. 

This idea can also apply to people who are victims of accidents, natural disasters, or other personal misfortunes. The victims of these misfortunes are typically blamed for not having the foresight to prevent or overcome their misfortune. Thus, for example, the poor are blamed for being feckless, and the victims of famine for not having the foresight to be prepared with stocks of food.

The theory depends on the view that either [[human nature]] or other facts of life ''should'' be known and acknowleged by the victim when making decisions. Thus a person is to blame if they act recklessly or with [[negligence]]. In law this  concept is acknowledged in some areas, for example when a driver ignores the rules of the road. However, victim blaming does not simply imply that the perpetrator was reckless, but that the victim should be responsible ''for'' the criminal. This implies that the victim creates [[temptation]] which tests the perpetrator's resolve.

It has been proposed that one cause of the phenomenon of victim blaming is the so-called '''Just World hypothesis''', where people who are inclined to believe that the world is a just place cannot accept a situation in which a person is hurt badly with no good reason. Therefore, they reason, people who are victims of misfortune must have done something to bring that misfortune upon them. This theory is very ancient, the most famous exploration of it being the [[Book of Job]]. 

Supporters of this view (once referred to as "Job's comforters") are forced to accept that to do otherwise would require them to give up their belief in a just world, and require them to believe in a world where bad things -- such as poverty, rape, starvation, and murder -- can happen to good people for no good reason. The [[cognitive dissonance]] in doing this is too great, and victim blaming is the result.

{{stub}} 

== External links ==
* [http://www.units.muohio.edu/psybersite/justworld/index.shtml Just World hypothesis]
* [http://www.scu.edu/ethics/publications/iie/v3n2/justworld.html The Just World hypothesis]

[[Category:Psychology]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>