<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20101101114724|394155409" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1150894" pageid="1150894" ns="0" title="Victim blaming"><revisions><rev timestamp="2010-11-05T01:25:27Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Refimprove|date=April 2009}}
'''Victim blaming''' (or '''blaming the victim''') is holding the victim (s) of a [[crime]], an [[accident]], or any type of [[abusive]] maltreatment to be entirely or partially responsible for the transgressions committed against them. Victim-blaming has traditionally emerged especially in [[Racism|racist]] and [[Sexism|sexist]] forms.&lt;ref&gt;Gregory Meyerson and Michael Joseph Roberto ''[http://richgibson.com/fascismcrisis.htm Fascism and the Crisis of Pax Americana]''&lt;/ref&gt; It is also about holding individuals responsible for their own personal distress or difficulties instead of attributing responsibility to the transgressors who caused it.

== History of the concept ==
The phrase "Blaming the victim" was coined by [[William Ryan (psychologist)|William Ryan]] in his 1976 classic book of the same title,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=George Kent|url=http://www.un.org/Pubs/chronicle/2003/issue3/0303p59.asp|title=Blaming the Victim, Globally|magazine=[[UN Chronicle]] online|publisher=United Nations Department of Public Information|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20031224033005/http://www.un.org/Pubs/chronicle/2003/issue3/0303p59.asp|archivedate=Dec 24, 2003|volume=XL|issue=3|year=2003}}&lt;/ref&gt; as a critique of [[Daniel Patrick Moynihan]]'s 1965 work ''The [[Negro]] Family:  The Case for National Action,'' usually simply referred to as the [[Moynihan Report]]. Moynihan's book summarized his theories about ghetto formation and intergenerational poverty.  Ryan's critique cast the Moynihan theories as subtle (and not so subtle) attempts to divert responsibility for poverty from social structural factors to the behaviors and cultural patterns of the poor.&lt;ref&gt;[http://lilt.ilstu.edu/gmklass/pos334/archive/ryan.htm Illinois state U. archives].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Ryan, William |title=Blaming the Victim |publisher=Vintage |year=1976 |isbn=0-394-72226-4 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  The phrase was quickly adopted by advocates for crime victims, in particular rape victims accused of abetting their victimization, although this usage is conceptually distinct from the sociological critique developed by Ryan.

== Just-world hypothesis ==
{{POV-section|date=November 2010}}
{{Unreferenced section|date=October 2010}}
{{Main|Just-world phenomenon}}
It has been proposed that one cause of victim-blaming is the "just-world phenomenon". People who believe that the world has to be fair may find it hard or impossible to accept a situation in which a person is unfairly and badly hurt. This leads to a sense that, somehow, the victim must have surely done 'something' to deserve their fate. Another theory entails the need to protect one's own sense of invulnerability. This inspires people to believe that rape only happens to those who deserve or provoke the assault (Schneider et al., 1994). This is a way of feeling safer. If the potential victim avoids the behaviors of the past victims then they themselves will remain safe and feel less vulnerable. A global survey of attitudes toward sexual violence by the [[Global Forum for Health Research]] shows that victim-blaming concepts are at least partially accepted in many countries. In some countries, victim-blaming is more common, and women who have been raped are sometimes deemed to have behaved improperly. Often, these are countries where there is a significant social divide between the freedoms and status afforded to men and women.

This idea dates from ancient times: the biblical [[Book of Job]] offers a refutation of the Just World Hypothesis, in which the main character, Job, maintains his faith through calamity after calamity, all of which are explicitly unrelated to his behavior, which remains devout.

Supporters of this view (once referred to as "[[Job's comforter]]s") must perforce accept that to do otherwise would require them to give up their belief in a just world, and require them to believe in a world where bad things – such as [[poverty]], [[rape]], [[starvation]], and [[murder]] – can happen to good men and women.
Though a form of attribution error, this incorrect attribution differs from the  "[[Fundamental Attribution Error]]" principally in its focus. Both concepts however center around a tendency to ignore situational contributors in favor of supposed internal failings on part of the subject being judged.  In the Just-World Hypothesis the subject's actions are not being scrutinized, but their situation; whereas those making the Fundamental Attribution Error tend to focus primarily on attributing actions to personal qualities and ignoring situational causes.  Crimes or other events that create a victim give opportunity for both attribution errors – in blaming the victim for "allowing" themselves to be victimized by crime as well as the inability to cope afterwards.  Despite their frequent simultaneity though, they remain two distinct attribution errors.

==Secondary victimization==
Rape is especially stigmatizing in cultures with strong customs and [[taboos]] regarding sex and sexuality. For example, a rape victim (especially one who was previously a [[virgin]]) may be viewed by society as being "damaged." Victims in these cultures may suffer [[solitude|isolation]], be disowned by friends and family, be prohibited from marrying, be divorced if already married, or even killed. This phenomenon is known as secondary victimization [http://www.nycagainstrape.org/survivors_factsheet_49.html#6].

Secondary victimization is the re-traumatization of the [[sexual assault]], [[abuse]], or [[rape]] victim through the responses of individuals and institutions. Types of secondary victimization include victim blaming and inappropriate post-assault behavior or language by medical personnel or other organizations with which the victim has contact.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Campbell R, Raja S |title=Secondary victimization of rape victims: insights from mental health professionals who treat survivors of violence |journal=Violence Vict |volume=14 |issue=3 |pages=261–75 |year=1999 |pmid=10606433 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Secondary victimization is especially common in cases of [[date rape drug|drug-facilitated]], [[date rape|acquaintance]], [[military sexual trauma]] and [[statutory rape]].

==Rape Shield Laws==
In the United States, rape is unique in that it is the only crime in which there are statutory protections designed in favor of the accuser (known as "[[rape shield law]]s"). These were enacted in response to the common defense tactic of "putting the accuser on trial". Typical rape shield laws prohibit cross-examination of the accuser (alleged victim) with respect to certain issues, such as his or her prior sexual history, or the manner in which he or she was dressed at the time of the rape. Most states and the federal rules, however, provide exceptions to the rape shield law where evidence of prior sexual history is used to provide an alternative explanation for physical evidence, where the defendant and the alleged victim had a prior consensual sexual relationship, and where exclusion of evidence would violate the defendant's constitutional rights.{{Citation needed|date=July 2008}}

==See also==
{{columns-list|2|
*[[Backlash (sociology)]]
*[[Blame]]
*[[Bullying]]
*[[Cognitive bias]]
*[[Demonization]]
*[[Exaggeration]]
*[[Labeling theory]]
*[[Negativity effect]]
*[[Victimology#Penal couple|Penal couple]]
*[[Psychological projection]]
*[[Scapegoating]]
*[[Shame]]
*[[Victim playing]]
*[[Victimisation]]
}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
*{{cite journal |doi=10.1016/0022-1031(85)90013-7 |author=Janoff-Bulman R, Timko C, Carli, LL |title=Cognitive biases in blaming the victim |journal=Journal of Experimental Social Psychology |volume=21 |issue=2 |pages=161–177 |year=1985 |month=March |url=http://www.sciencedirect.com/science?_ob=ArticleURL&amp;_udi=B6WJB-4D62HHD-52&amp;_user=10&amp;_coverDate=03%2F31%2F1985&amp;_rdoc=1&amp;_fmt=high&amp;_orig=search&amp;_sort=d&amp;_docanchor=&amp;view=c&amp;_searchStrId=1202081160&amp;_rerunOrigin=scholar.google&amp;_acct=C000050221&amp;_version=1&amp;_urlVersion=0&amp;_userid=10&amp;md5=6571d31cfa19e6b6d70418583854e9a7}}
*{{cite journal |author=Maes J |title=Blaming the victim: Belief in control or belief in justice? |journal=Social Justice Research |volume=7 |issue=1 |year=1994 |month=March |url=http://www.springerlink.com/content/n34574788578152m}}
*{{cite journal |doi=10.1111/j.1559-1816.1990.tb00375.x |author=McCaul, Kevin D.; Veltum, Lois G.; Boyechko, Vivian; Crawford, Jacqueline J. |title=Understanding attributions of victim blame for rape: Sex, violence, and foreseeability |journal=Journal of Applied Social Psychology |volume=20 |issue=1 |pages=1–26 |year=1990 |month=January |url=http://psycnet.apa.org/?fa=main.doiLanding&amp;uid=1990-17391-001}}
*{{cite journal |author=Summers, G; Feldman, NS |title=Blaming the victim versus blaming the perpetrator: An attributional analysis of spouse abuse |journal=Journal of Social &amp; Clinical Psychology |volume=2 |issue=4 |pages=339–347 |year=1984 |url=http://psycnet.apa.org/?fa=main.doiLanding&amp;uid=1986-01159-001}}

==External links==
* [http://www.zurinstitute.com/victimhood.html Ofer Zur - Rethinking 'Don't Blame the Victim': The Psychology of Victimhood]
* [http://www.ibiblio.org/rcip//vb.html Victim Blame and Sexual Assault]

{{Psychological manipulation}}
{{Sexual abuse}}
{{abuse}}
{{Bullying}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Victim Blaming}}
[[Category:Abuse]]
[[Category:Bullying]]
[[Category:Social psychology]]
[[Category:Victimology]]
[[Category:Human behavior]]
[[Category:Psychological abuse]]
[[Category:Diversionary tactics]]
[[Category:Injustice]]

[[es:Culpar a la víctima]]
[[it:Colpevolizzazione della vittima]]
[[nl:Blaming-the-victim]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>