<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20050523041356|16911115" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1150894" pageid="1150894" ns="0" title="Victim blaming"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-09-20T06:00:54Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Victim-blaming''' consists of holding [[victim]]s of [[crime]]s or other misfortunes wholly or partly [[responsibility|responsible]] for what has happened to them.  

For example: a motorist who leaves a car unlocked with the keys in the ignition may seem partly responsible if another party steals the car. Or persons who use verbal abuse may count as partly responsible if they suffer a physical assault. 

In the context of [[rape]], this concept refers to popular attitudes that behaviour such as [[flirting]] or wearing sexually provocative [[sociology of clothing|clothing]] may encourage rape: that such actions resemble leaving one's car with the keys in the ignition or provoking an assault by "winding up" the assailant. In extreme cases people may accuse victims of "asking for it" by not behaving demurely. 

The theory depends on the view that a prospective victim ''should'' know and acknowledge either [[human nature]] or other facts of life when making decisions. Thus persons may appear blame-worthy if they act recklessly or with [[negligence]]. Laws acknowledge this concept in some areas, for example when a driver ignores the rules of the road. However, victim-blaming does not simply imply that the perpetrator behaved recklessly, but that the victim should take responsibility ''for'' the criminal. This implies that the victim creates [[temptation]] which tests the perpetrator's resolve.

The idea of victim-blaming can also apply to people who become [[victim]]s of accidents, natural disasters, or other personal misfortunes. Commentators may blame the victims of these misfortunes for not succeeding in preventing or overcoming their misfortune. Thus, for example, the [[poverty|poor]] receive blame for their fecklessness, and the victims of [[famine]] for not having had the foresight to prepare stocks of food.

Some have proposed that one cause of the phenomenon of victim-blaming involves the [[Just-world phenomenon]], where people who tend to regard the world as a just place cannot accept a situation in which a person suffers for no good reason. Therefore, they reason, people who become victims of misfortune must have done something to bring that misfortune upon themselves. This theory dates from very ancient times: the biblical [[Book of Job]] offers a canonical exploration of it. 

Supporters of this view (once referred to as "[[Job's comforters]]") must perforce accept that to do otherwise would require them to give up their belief in a just world, and require them to believe in a world where bad things -- such as poverty, rape, [[starvation]], and [[murder]] -- can happen to good people for no good reason. The [[cognitive dissonance]] in doing this becomes too great, and results in victim-blaming.

== External links ==

* [http://www.units.muohio.edu/psybersite/justworld/index.shtml Just World hypothesis]
* [http://www.scu.edu/ethics/publications/iie/v3n2/justworld.html The Just World hypothesis]

[[Category:Social psychology]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>