<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20121101163126|520916912" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="34903083" pageid="34903083" ns="0" title="Gender representation in video games"><revisions><rev timestamp="2012-11-01T16:52:07Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Merge to|Portrayal of women in video games|date=March 2012}}
{{Essay|date=July 2012}}
{{NPOV|date=July 2012}}
{{rewrite|date=November 2012}}

[[Male|Males]] and [[Female|females]] are represented very differently in video games. Most do not reflect [[reality]]. Male characters are dramatically over represented relative to female characters.&lt;ref name=Burgess&gt;{{cite journal|last=Burgess|first=Melinda C. R.|coauthors=Steven Paul Stermer &amp; Stephen R. Burgess|title=Sex, Lies, and Video Games: The Portrayal of Male and Female Characters on Video Game Covers|journal=Sex Roles|date=30|year=2007|month=06|pages=419-433|accessdate=4/23/12}}&lt;/ref&gt; Males are often shown to have big [[Muscle|muscles]] and thus are [[masculine]]. Males are usually the main character portrayed as the "[[hero]] or [[Violence|violent]] perpetrator.”&lt;ref name="Dietz" /&gt; Young females are often shown to have [[Dress_code#Sexual_display|revealing clothing]] and [[Breast|big breasts]], thus they are [[Feminism|feminine]]. Females are often the [[damsel in distress]] and/or [[Hypersexuality|hypersexualized]].

==Depictions of women in games==
{{main|Portrayal of women in video games}}
Women are commonly depicted as having very large breasts, tiny waists, and full, pouting lips. Some examples of these images are [[Lara Croft]] from the [[Tomb Raider]] games and the female characters in [[Soul Calibur IV]].  There was a significant increase in the breast sizes of the female characters in [[Soul Calibur IV]] that was not there in in earlier versions. The female characters breasts in the earlier version of the game were already depicted as being larger than a real woman's breasts. The princess or damsel in distress, is portrayed as helpless, incapable of violence, and often wearing tightly fitted and revealing clothing that fails to contain her impossibly proportioned body.&lt;ref name="Dickerman" /&gt;

===Dead or Alive===
[[Team Ninja]], a Japanese video game development company, who is best known for their fighting game series [[Dead_or_Alive_(series)|Dead  or Alive]], created a spin-off to their fighting game called [[Dead or Alive Xtreme Beach Volleyball]]. A commercial for the game featured the commentary “Play with a friend.. or play with yourself”. At the end of the commercial, there was a play on words that called attention to the “X” in [[Xbox]] (the system on which the title was released), suggesting an “X” rating.&lt;ref name="Dickerman" /&gt;

Team Ninja has announced that their “female characters in [[Dead or Alive 5]] will be more realistic and high class.” Yosuke Hayashi, the company's head, said "In the series up to now we focused on some kind of… [[Sports Illustrated]] [aesthetic]. Like a magazine for high school kids, with women portrayed in that sense. We've always had the sex factor in the game; in the past, the female characters had to have big breasts, they had to have scanty dress. We're trying to focus on the real women that surround us; the voice of a female, the mannerisms. We are being realistic about it. We want to show something that's more high class, that adult males of our generation could look at a woman [character] and be impressed with her as a woman, not just as a pin-up.

The old team was known for making games that just had two primary elements: [[Sexual intercourse|Sex]] and [[violence]]. It was very obvious. The new team, we want to take it to a new level - to a direction that contains [[Emotion|emotional]] experiences that can move players. Rather than just having violence for the sake of violence and cheap thrill, we wanted to give meaning to violence: Why does this happen? We want to link emotion to violence. We wanted to make a game that is for mature audiences, that can make adults think.""&lt;ref name=nomas&gt;{{cite web|last=Nomas|first=Lee|title=Female characters in Dead or Alive 5 to be more realistic, high class|url=http://www.msxbox-world.com/news/article/18165/female-characters-in-dead-or-alive-5-to-be-more-realistic-high-class.html|accessdate=24 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Depictions of males in games==
[[Male|Males]] are shown to be big in all aspects. They are shown as being tall, having larger heads, and [[Muscle|muscles]] compared to a real man. Male character's have a [[chest]] size that is about 6% larger than the real man. The male character's  head is about 13 inches bigger, their chest is bigger by about 2 inches, their waist is 5 inches wider, and their hips are 7 inches wider .&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=N|first=Martins|coauthors=Williams DC, Ratan RA, Harrison K|title=Virtual muscularity: a content analysis of male video game characters|journal=Body Image|date=May, 3, 2012|year=2011|pages=43-51|doi=10.1016/j.bodyim.2010.10.002}}&lt;/ref&gt;   Male characters are generally depicted as possessing a lot of strength. In cases where the male character does not appear to be physically strong, other traits, such as superior intelligence or other superpowers are generally depicted.&lt;ref name=mk&gt;{{cite web|last=MK Design|title=Adolescent Male Masculinity and Video Games|url=http://voices.yahoo.com/adolescent-male-masculinity-video-6416946.html?cat=25|accessdate=25 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Men are also depicted as disposable, often with male soldiers and warriors dying by the hundreds in battle.

Many [[video games|games]] feature the common plot of [[hero]] rescuing a [[princess]] from the evil hands of a sorcerer, warlord or monster. This theme is most common in the legend or fairy tales genres, but it also can be found in other genres.  The hero in the game is usually a male and carries a large weapon, a sword or a gun. The main villain is a monster or a human who is usually male.&lt;ref name=Dickerman /&gt;  Both the [[hero]] and the villain are muscular, have some sort of scar on their bodies or another physical sign of past violence.

===Mitsurugi===
The character of [[Mitsurugi]], in the [[Soul (series)|Soul Series]],  is an example of a character that has gone through dramatic changes as the series has progressed. In the [[Soul Edge|first installment of the series]], he was dressed in [[cloth]] and was small. His facial expression is also simple and kind. In [[Soulcalibur|Soul Calibur]], he gains armor, a rope belt, and he grows in size. In [[Soulcalibur II|Soul Calibur II]], he gains more armor, his rope belt increases in size, and his weapon, his sword, is extremely larger than his original sword. In [[Soul Calibur III]], his amount of armor is reduced and his muscles are exposed in return. His rope belt is also reduced in size and his facial expression has a seriousness to it. In [[Soul Calibur IV]], even more of his [[Armour|armor]] is exchanged for [[muscle]]. His rope belt has doubled in size and is not proportional to his body. His head is reduced in size  to make his body bigger.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Tang|first=Wai Yen|title=manliness_evolution|url=http://vgresearcher.files.wordpress.com/2011/02/manliness_evolution.jpg|accessdate=25 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Sexualization for advertizing of games==
Sometimes the portrayal of women is associated with the marketing of the game. The game “[[Never_Winter_Nights|Neverwinter Nights]]” was featured  in a full page advertisement on [[GameSpy|Gamespy]] in 2003. The heading of the advertisement asks “Have you seen this girl?” and shows the image of a nearly naked woman, partially covered by seashells. Interestingly, this girl appears in the game but not she is not half naked.

In the game "[[Civilization_(video_game)|Civilization IV]]" the company producing the games ran an ad for an add-on feature to the games. The ad displayed a large-breasted Statue of Liberty and the world "CIV GOES BIG" despite the lack of anything overly sexual in the game.&lt;ref name="Dickerman" /&gt;

==Effect of video games==
===Impact on children===
Video game characters have the potential to shape players’ perceptions of gender roles. Through social comparison processes, players learn societal expectations of appearances, behaviors and roles.&lt;ref name=Dietz&gt;{{cite journal|last=Dietz|first=Tracy|title="An Examincation of Violence and Gender Role Portrayals in Video Games: Implications for Gender Socialization and Agressive Behavior|journal=Sex Roles|year=1998|volume=38|pages=425-442|accessdate=02/12/2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Girls may expect that they will continue to be victims and needy and that their responsibilities include maintaining beauty and sexual appeal while boys may determine that their role is to protect and defend women and to possess them even through the use of violence.&lt;ref name="Dietz" /&gt;

Thus, the roles internalized by the child, including gender, become for the child, and later for the adult, a basis for other roles and for action. The gender role that is internalized by the individual when she or he is young has a significant impact upon the perspective of that individual and the additional roles she or he assumes in later life. Feminine and masculine symbols become a part of a child’s identity. Boys and girls may come to see Barbie as a feminine symbol and [[Spider-Man]] as a [[Maculinity|masculine symbol]].&lt;ref name="Dietz" /&gt;

Men are characterized as either good guys or bad guys and aggressive behavior is exhibited and expected in either of these roles. At the same time, women are depicted in stereotypical roles that typically pertain to sexuality in which the woman focuses upon beauty/physical attractiveness and traditional family roles.&lt;ref name="Dietz" /&gt;

Parents fear the violent video games are influencing their children's view about violence. Studies have been conducted to proof the effects of violent video games on children and adolescents. Several of the studies apply [[Bandura_Study|Bandura's Social Modeling Theory]], which describes how individuals can learn behaviors merely by watching a model commit a behavior and be rewarded for it. With video games, the model is the main character, who gets rewarded with more points or advancement in the story, when he takes part in a violent act. There is a positive correlation, but research does not necessarily support the hypothesis that violent video games will cause increased levels of aggression.&lt;ref name=Dickerman&gt;{{cite journal|last=Dickerman|first=Charles|title=Big Breast and Bad Guys: Depictions of Gender and Race in Video Games|journal=Journal of Creativity in Mental Health|year=2008|volume=3|issue=1|accessdate=2012-02-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Impact on adults===
Women exposed to images of “the ideal woman”, aka thin, are reported to have increased levels of body dissatisfaction, negative moods and [[Depression_(mood)|depression]], and lower levels of [[self-esteem]]. The influence of the media on young women’s body image have led researchers to speculate that media might also play an important role in negative behaviors such as eating disorders. Males are affected by media images as well. Men who view images of “the ideal male”, aka, muscular, have been reported to  have more negative body images and are more likely to try to gain weight/muscle mass or use steroids. Thus, media images affect both males’ and females’ behavior, body image and self-perception.&lt;ref name=Miller&gt;{{cite journal|coauthors=Monica K. Miller &amp; Alicia Summers|title=Gender Differences in Video Game Characters’ Roles, Appearances, and Attire as Portrayed in Video Game Magazines|journal=Sex Roles|date=18|year=2007|month=September|accessdate=02/12/2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

[[Category:Gender and entertainment]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>