<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20161105213132|748019915" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="34903083" pageid="34903083" ns="0" title="Gender representation in video games"><revisions><rev timestamp="2016-11-05T22:03:38Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{redirect|Women in video games|women as video game developers and players|women and video games}}

The portrayal of men and women in [[video games]], as in other media, is a subject of research in [[gender studies]] and is discussed in the context of [[sexism in video gaming]]. Women in particular are significantly underrepresented as characters in mainstream games, and their portrayals often reflect traditional [[gender role]]s, [[sexual objectification]] or negative stereotypes, such as that of the "[[damsel in distress]]".

== Gamer demographics ==
{{Main article|Women and video games#Demographics of female players}}
[[File:Girl plays Pac Man.JPG|thumb|A young girl playing a video game]]

A 2008 Gallup poll indicated that half of all American video game players in 2014 were women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
| url = 
| title = Using Storytelling to Introduce Girls to Computer Programming
| last = Kelleher
| first = Caitlin
| date = 2008
| work = Beyond Barbie &amp; Mortal Kombat: New Perspectives on Gender and Gaming
| publisher = The MIT Press
| isbn = 978-0-262-11319-9
| editor-last = Kafai
| editor-first = Yasmin B.
| page = 247
| editor-last2 = Heeter
| editor-first2 = Carrie
| editor-last3 = Sun
| editor-first3 = Jennifer Y.
| accessdate = 
}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2014 in the UK and in Spain, women comprised 52% and 48% of video game players respectively.&lt;ref name=PlayGround&gt;{{cite web|title=Ellas también juegan, o por qué el machismo gamer no tiene ningún sentido|author=Natxo Medina|url=http://www.playgroundmag.net/articulos/reportajes/videojuegos-mujeres-gamer-feminismo_0_1396060382.html|accessdate=2014-09-29|date=2014-09-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Both men and women play video games, but studies suggest differences in platform and game genre preference.&lt;ref name=Joystiq&gt;{{cite web|title=LReport: Men play more MMOs, FPSes; women rule mobile, RPG|author=Jessica Conditt|url=http://www.joystiq.com/2014/10/27/report-men-play-more-mmos-fpses-women-rule-mobile-rpg|publisher=[[Joystiq]]|date=2014-09-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Entertainment Software Rating Board reports that in 2010, 80% of female console gamers played on Wii, 11% on Xbox360 and 9% on PS3. By comparison, 38% of male console gamers in the year 2014 played Xbox 360, 41% played Wii and 21% played PS3.&lt;ref name="Video Game Stats"&gt;{{cite web|title=How Much Do You Know About Video Games?|author=ESRB|url=http://www.esrb.org/about/video-game-industry-statistics.jsp|accessdate=2014-11-09|date=2014-09-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A 2013 study by [[Flurry (company)|Flurry]] looked at the different mobile gaming preferences between men and women. Women made up 60-80% of the solitaire, slots, social turn-based, match-three / bubble-shooter, management / simulation and quiz game markets. Men on the other hand, made up between 60-80% of the strategy, shooter, card battle, racing and action RPG markets.&lt;ref name="Furry App statistics"&gt;{{cite web|title=Love, Courtship and the Promiscuous Male Mobile Gamer|author=Dan Laughlin|url=http://www.flurry.com/bid/95605/Love-Courtship-and-the-Promiscuous-Male-Mobile-Gamer#.VIl21DGUfjU=2014-11-09|date=2014-09-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A 2014 SuperData Research study found that men and women enjoy video games, but some genres are attracting one gender more than the other: Women compose 57.8 percent of the mobile market, 53.6 percent of the RPG market and 50.2 percent of the PC market (including social games). The study found that men make up 66 percent of MMO players, 66 percent of FPS players and 63 percent of digital console players.&lt;ref name="Joystiq"/&gt; {{Clear}}

==Portrayal of women==
{{category see also|Video games featuring female protagonists}}
[[File:Cosplayers at Igromir 2011.jpg|thumb|upright|Two women [[cosplay|dressed up]] as video game characters]]

===As player characters===

====Prevalence====
Playable female characters were found to appear less frequently than male characters in reviews for popular games in a 2006 study from [[Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University]].&lt;ref&gt;Ivory, J. D. (2006). [http://filebox.vt.edu/users/jivory/JIvory2006MassCommunicationandSociety.pdf Still a man's game: Gender representation in online reviews of video games.] Mass Communication &amp; Society, 9(1), 103-114. The sample of reviews was taken from the "Top Rated" and "Most Popular" lists from [[GameSpot]] on March 26, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Miller, M. K., &amp; Summers, A. (2007). [http://www.easternct.edu/~lugow/courses/videogames/gender_videogames.pdf Gender differences in video game characters' roles, appearances, and attire as portrayed in video game magazines.] Sex roles, 57(9-10), 733-742.&lt;/ref&gt; A 2007 study by Melinda C. R. Burgess et al. found that men are featured much more often than women on the covers of console video games.&lt;ref name=Burgess&gt;{{cite journal|last=Burgess|first=Melinda C. R. |author2=Steven Paul Stermer |author3=Stephen R. Burgess|title=Sex, Lies, and Video Games: The Portrayal of Male and Female Characters on Video Game Covers|journal=Sex Roles|date=30 June 2007|pages=419–433|doi=10.1007/s11199-007-9250-0|volume=57|issue=5–6}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In a sample of 669 action, shooter, and role-playing games selected by EEDAR in 2012, 300 (45%) provided the option of playing as a female, but only 24 (4%) had an exclusively female protagonist. EEDAR found in 2010 that 10% of games did not have a protagonist with a discernible gender.&lt;ref name="escapistEEDAR"/&gt;

According to Madeline Messer writing in the ''[[Washington Post]]'' in 2015, among the top 50 [[Platform game#Endless running game|endless running]] games for mobile devices, 98% of those with gender-identifiable characters featured male protagonists, of which 90% were free to play. Only 46% of these games offered female characters, and only 15% offered them for free. Playing as a girl required, on average, an additional purchase of $7.53, much more than the games themselves cost.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Messer|first1=Madeline|title=I’m a 12-year-old girl. Why don’t the characters in my apps look like me?|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/posteverything/wp/2015/03/04/im-a-12-year-old-girl-why-dont-the-characters-in-my-apps-look-like-me/|accessdate=12 April 2015|date=4 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Evolution====
[[Samus Aran]], the heroine of ''[[Metroid (video game)|Metroid]]'' (1986) and its successors, is often cited as "the first playable human female character in a mainstream video game".&lt;ref name="Guinness2013"&gt;{{cite book | title=Guinness World Records 2013: Gamer's Edition | publisher=Guinness World Records Ltd | authorlink=Feature: Girl Power-Up | year=2012 | page=154 | isbn=9781904994954}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, other earlier games featured female player characters, such as Toby Masuyo ("Kissy") from ''[[Baraduke]]'' (1985).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.hardcoregaming101.net/namcoxcapcom/namcoxcapcom2.htm#tobymasuyo | title=Obscure Namco characters | publisher=Hardcore Gaming 101 | accessdate=6 October 2013 | author=Kurt Kalata}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.nintendolife.com/news/2009/10/nintendo_download_13_14_october_2009_japan | title=Nintendo Download: 13-14 October 2009 (Japan) | publisher=nintendolife.com | accessdate=6 October 2013 | author=Sean Aaron}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Studies of the prevalence of female characters in video games began to be conducted in sociological, educational, and cultural journals as early as the late 1970s and early 1980s. In 1979, researchers publishing in ''Psychological Record'' (Vol.29, No.1. Pp.&amp;nbsp;43–48) concluded from the results of a 201-person survey that 90% of male subjects and 85% of female subjects perceived the computer as masculine (in gameplay versus the computer).&lt;ref name=leroux&gt;Leroux, Yvan and Michel Pépin. "Jeu Sur Micro-Ordinateur et Différences Liées au Sexe". ''[[Revue des Sciences de l'Education]]''. Vol.XII, No.2. Pp.173-196. 1986. {{ISSN|0318-479X}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1983, professor [[Sara Kiesler]] et al. published a study in ''[[Psychology Today]]'' (Vol.17, No.3. Pp.&amp;nbsp;40–48.) finding that female characters appeared in video games at a frequency of 1 game in 7.&lt;ref name=leroux/&gt; Elizabeth Behm-Morawitz suggested that the reduced presence of female characters implies a secondary status for women in video games. When playable female characters do appear in video games, they are more often scantily dressed and [[oversexualized]] than men.&lt;ref&gt;Behm-Morawitz, Elizabeth, and Dana Mastro. "The Effects of the Sexualization of Female Video Game Characters on Gender Stereotyping and Female Self-Concept." Sex Roles 61.11 (2009): 808-823. ProQuest. Web. 22 April 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Lara Croft]], the protagonist of ''[[Tomb Raider (1996 video game)|Tomb Raider]]'' (1996), is among the best-known strong, fictional women in a variety of media.&lt;ref name="taylor"&gt;{{cite book | last1 = Egenfeldt-Nielsen | first1 = Simon | last2 = Smith | first2 = Jonas Heide | last3 = Pajares Tosca | first3 = Susana | title = Understanding video games: the essential introduction | chapter = Player culture | publisher = Taylor &amp; Francis | year = 2008 | page = 163 | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=31XHdVXlbt0C&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;dq=%22april%20ryan%22&amp;pg=PA163#v=onepage&amp;q=%22april%20ryan%22&amp;f=false | accessdate = 2011-07-03 | isbn = 978-0-415-97721-0 | quote = "Helen Kennedy [...] summarizes these arguments, and Lara Croft's ambivalent role as both an action heroine [...], and an eroticized object of the male gaze with a great deal of voyeuristic appeal".}}&lt;/ref&gt; Since her introduction in 1996, the character of Croft has been criticized for her "unrealistic" breast size; Lara was claimed to personify "an ongoing culture clash over gender, sexuality, empowerment, and objectification."&lt;ref name="gettingthegirl"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.1up.com/do/feature?cId=3137700 |author=Zoe Flower |title=Getting the Girl: The myths, misconceptions, and misdemeanors of females in games |publisher=[[1UP.com]] |accessdate=2007-09-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; In a 2008 Tomb Raider title, Croft was depicted in "hot pants" and "middriffs" and was said to look like she "was dressed by a male".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Tomb Raider Lara Croft now Battling Video Game Sterotypes|url=http://herocomplex.latimes.com/games/tomb-raider-lara-croft-now-battling-video-game-stereotypes/#/0|website=Hero Comles}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the game's creators maintain that she was not designed with marketing in mind, and have claimed to be rather surprised at her pinup-style adoration.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Lara Croft, the Bit Girl |author=N'gai Croal and Jane Hughes |publisher=[[Newsweek]] |date=1997-11-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; In ''[[Tomb Raider: Legend]]'', Lara underwent a radical redesign, ostensibly to make her less sexualized.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Lara's curves reduced to appeal to female gamers |date=2005-05-21 |publisher=[[The Sydney Morning Herald]] |url=http://www.smh.com.au/news/World/Real-appeal/2005/05/21/1116533572111.html |accessdate=2007-07-09 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20071015084057/http://www.smh.com.au/news/World/Real-appeal/2005/05/21/1116533572111.html |archivedate=October 15, 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[April Ryan (The Longest Journey)|April Ryan]] from ''[[The Longest Journey]]'' (1999) has been compared to Lara Croft, as she shows less prominent physical feminine attributes than Lara but more feminine psychological traits, as contrasted with Lara's masculine connotations like aggressiveness and force.&lt;ref name="merete"&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.csi.ensmp.fr/WebCSI/4S/download/download_page.php?file=lie.pdf | title = Lara Croft and her sisters | accessdate = 2011-07-03 | last = Lie | first = Merete | publisher = Norwegian University of Science and Technology | quote = "She is attractive, but no sex bomb"  "April may, however, appear as more feminine because even if she is tough and brave, she is depicted as both sensitive and vain"}}&lt;/ref&gt; Contrarily, [[Jade (Beyond Good &amp; Evil)|Jade]], the protagonist of ''[[Beyond Good &amp; Evil]]'' (2003), was widely recognized as a strong and confident female character lacking any overt sexualisation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Rougeau|first=Michael|url=http://www.complex.com/video-games/2013/01/the-50-greatest-heroines-in-video-game-history/jade|title=50 Greatest Heroines In Video Game History|publisher=Complex|date=March 4, 2013|accessdate=March 24, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Bayonetta: empowering or exploitative?|url=http://www.gamepro.com/article/features/213466/bayonetta-empowering-or-exploitative/ |publisher=[[GamePro]] |accessdate=2010-01-16|date=2010-01-06|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100109032922/http://www.gamepro.com/article/features/213466/bayonetta-empowering-or-exploitative/|archivedate=2010-01-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2014 the developers' choice to omit playable women in the latest iterations of the top-tier gaming franchises ''[[Assassin's Creed]]'' and ''[[Far Cry (series)|Far Cry]]'' became a focus of discussions in gaming media. This indicated, according to game industry professionals{{who|date=April 2015}} cited by ''[[Polygon (website)|Polygon]]'', a shift in the industry's attention towards issues of diversity in gaming, in conjunction with video games as a whole growing beyond their former core audience of younger men.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Crecente|first1=Brian|title=As game players diversify, developers start to rethink the stars of their games|url=http://www.polygon.com/2014/6/23/5834628/women-in-video-games-heroines-e3-2014|accessdate=23 June 2014|work=Polygon|date=23 June 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Women of Color or people of color as a whole are less likely to be represented by the popular games and more likely to be represented as a stereotype.&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{Cite book|title=Gender and Racial Stereotypes in Video Games|last=Peng|first=Mou|publisher=IGI Global|year=2009|isbn=|location=|pages=924}}&lt;/ref&gt; There is also a higher chance of people of color, especially women characters to be portrayed as villains.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;

===As supporting characters===
[[File:MCCC 15 - Princess Zelda (17906856280).jpg|thumb|278x278px|A woman dressed as [[Princess Zelda]], a notable supporting character from the ''[[The Legend of Zelda]]'']]
Female characters are often cast in the role of the [[damsel in distress]], with their rescue being the objective of the game.&lt;ref name="Tremblay2012"&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.gamasutra.com/blogs/KaitlinTremblay/20120601/171613/Intro_to_Gender_Criticism_for_Gamers_From_Princess_Peach_to_Claire_Redfield_to_FemSheps.php?print=1 | title=Intro to Gender Criticism for Gamers: From Princess Peach, to Claire Redfield, to FemSheps. | publisher=[[Gamasutra]] | date=1 June 2012 | accessdate=8 October 2013 | author=Kaitlin Tremblay}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://kotaku.com/shigeru-miyamoto-and-the-damsel-in-distress-520259897 | title=Shigeru Miyamoto and the Damsel In Distress | publisher=[[Kotaku]] | date=2013-06-20 | accessdate=8 October 2013 | author=Stephen Totilo}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Princess Zelda]] in the early ''[[The Legend of Zelda]]'' series and [[Princess Peach]] through much of the ''[[Mario (franchise)|Mario]]'' series are [[wikt:paradigm|paradigmatic]] examples. According to Salzburge Academy on Media and Global Change, in 1981 Nintendo offered game designer Shigeru Miyamoto to create a new video game for the American market. In the game the hero was Mario, and the objective of the game was to rescue a young princess named Peach. Peach was depicted as having a pink dress and blonde hair. The princess was kidnapped and trapped in a castle by the evil villain character Bowser, who is depicted as a turtle. Princess Peach appears in 14 of the main Super Mario games and is kidnapped in 13 of them. The only main game that Peach was not kidnapped in was in the North America release of ''[[Super Mario 2]]'', but she was a character that can be played. Zelda became playable in some later games of the Legend of Zelda series or had the pattern altered.&lt;ref name="Objectification of Women in Video Games"&gt;[http://www.salzburg.umd.edu/unesco/objectification-women-video-games "Objectification of Women in Video Games"], Retrieved 9 May 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;"In video games, the major stereotyped myths of women are typically the damsel in distress, hyper-sexualized villain (Sylvia Christel from ''[[No More Heroes (video game)|No More Heroes]]'') and the sexy/strong best friend ([[Tifa Lockhart|Tifa]] from ''[[Final Fantasy VII]]''). [...] In all of these instances, the female character is, more likely than not, in love with the male protagonist or trying desperately to bang him."&lt;ref name="Tremblay2012" /&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

A number of games feature a female character as an ally or [[sidekick]] to the male hero. Some of them, like [[Ada Wong]] of ''[[Resident Evil]]'' and [[Mona Sax]] of ''[[Max Payne (video game)|Max Payne]]'', were turned into [[player character]]s in later instances of their series. [[Alyx Vance]], a supporting protagonist of ''[[Half-Life 2]]'', was praised for her "stinging personality" and intelligence, developing a close bond with the player without simply being "eye candy".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ugo.com/games/video-game-hotties/?cur=alyx-vance&amp;morepics=17 Top 50 Videogame Hotties]. [[UGO.com]]. Retrieved on 2008-12-14&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ugo.com/games/gaming-girls/?cur=alyx-vance Top 11 Girls of Gaming]. [[UGO.com]]. Retrieved on 2008-12-28&lt;/ref&gt;

===As antagonists===
{{category see also|Video games featuring female antagonists}}

One of the first major female villains in video games was the [[Dark Queen (Battletoads)|Dark Queen]] in ''[[Battletoads]]'' (1991) and its sequels.&lt;ref&gt;Steven A. Schwartz, Janet Schwartz, ''The Parent's Guide to Video Games'', Prima Pub., 1994 (p.8)&lt;/ref&gt; [[SHODAN]], an artificial intelligence with a female voice and a female face, was the main villain of the game ''[[System Shock]]'' (1994), praised as one of the most recognizable female characters in gaming.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gamespot.com/features/tenspot_females/page9.html TenSpot: Ten Best Female Characters]. GameSpot. Elexis Sinclaire was also one of the first female villains featured in the FPS game called Sin, released in 1998. Retrieved on 19 November 2013&lt;/ref&gt; Another prominent female villain is [[Characters of Final Fantasy VIII#Ultimecia|Ultimecia]], the main antagonist in ''[[Final Fantasy VIII]]'' (1999). At [[Penny Arcade Expo|PAX]] Prime 2013, she was voted among the best female antagonists in video gaming history.&lt;ref name="ForbesPAXreport"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.forbes.com/sites/davidewalt/2013/08/31/are-these-the-top-women-game-characters-of-all-time/|title=Are These The Top Women Game Characters of All Time?|last=Ewalt|first=David M.|publisher=''[[Forbes]]''|date=2013-08-31|accessdate=2013-10-07|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131031081428/http://www.forbes.com/sites/davidewalt/2013/08/31/are-these-the-top-women-game-characters-of-all-time/ |archivedate=2013-10-31 |deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, [[GLaDOS]] from ''[[Portal (video game)|Portal]]'' (2007), an insane computer with a female voice, was praised by critics as one of the best new characters of the 2000s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=The 25 best new characters of the decade |url=http://www.gamesradar.com/f/the-25-best-new-characters-of-the-decade/a-20091221171910974007 |publisher=[[GamesRadar]] |accessdate=2010-01-04 |date=2009-12-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Sexualization===
The portrayal of women in video games has been the subject of academic study and controversy since the early 1980s. Recurring themes in articles and discussions on the topic include the [[sexual objectification]] and [[sexualization]] of female characters, done to appeal to a presumed male audience,&lt;ref name="Tremblay2012"/&gt; as well as the degree to which female characters are independent from their male counterparts within the same game. Research on exposure to sexualized media representations of women in television and magazines has asked whether it reduces male compassion toward women, and reduces women's perceptions of their desire and suitability for various vocations.&lt;ref name=Burgess/&gt;

====Prevalence====
In their 2005 study, Dill and Thill distinguish three major stereotypical depictions of women in gaming: (1) sexualized, (2) scantily clad, and (3) a vision of beauty. The study revealed that over 80% of women in video games represented one of these depictions. More than one quarter of female characters embodied all of the three stereotypical categories at once. Dill and Thill also note that another prevalent theme with which women were depicted was a combination of aggression and sex, referred to as "eroticized aggression".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Dill|first=Karen E.|author2=Thill K. P.|title=Video Game Characters and the Socialization of Gender Roles: Young People's Perceptions Mirror Sexist Media Depictions|journal=Sex Roles|year=2007|volume=57|pages=851–864|doi=10.1007/s11199-007-9278-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to sociology professor and researcher Tracy Dietz, women are often depicted in stereotypical roles that typically pertain to sexuality in which the woman focuses upon beauty/physical attractiveness.&lt;ref name="Dietz" /&gt; According to an analysis conducted by Downs and Smith, playable and plot relevant characters in the 60 best selling video games of 2003 were predominantly male. Females who were depicted were frequently sexualized. The female characters analyzed were depicted partially naked or with unrealistic proportions more often than the male characters were.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Downs|first1=Edward|last2=Smith|first2=Stacy L.|title=Keeping Abreast of Hypersexuality: A Video Game Character Content Analysis|journal=Sex Roles|date=2 September 2009|volume=62|issue=11-12|pages=721–733|doi=10.1007/s11199-009-9637-1|url=http://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s11199-009-9637-1|language=en|issn=0360-0025}}&lt;/ref&gt; A study of 225 video game covers found that both male and female character's physiques were over-exaggerated, but women were more "physically altered" (especially in the bust) than their male counterparts, and even more so if the female was the main character of the game.&lt;ref name=Burgess/&gt;

A 2016 study of 571 games released between 1984 and 2014&lt;ref name="Lynch et al. 2016"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Lynch|first1=Teresa|last2=Tompkins|first2=Jessica E.|last3=van Driel|first3=Irene I.|last4=Fritz|first4=Niki|title=Sexy, Strong, and Secondary: A Content Analysis of Female Characters in Video Games across 31 Years|journal=Journal of Communication|date=30 June 2016|doi=10.1111/jcom.12237}}&lt;/ref&gt; found that the sexualization of female characters was at its height between 1990 and 2005, and then began to significantly decline. It also determined that there was no significant difference in sexualization between games rated as "Teen" (for ages 13 and up) and "Mature" (18 and up) by the [[ESRB]], indicating that sexualized women in games are so prevalent that they are not thought of as objectionable to children. Less sexualization was found in [[Role-playing video game|RPGs]], which are played more often by women, than in action and fighting games.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Survey of 31 years of video games shows a decline in sexualized female characters|url=http://phys.org/news/2016-07-survey-years-video-games-decline.html|accessdate=31 July 2016|work=[[Phys.org]]|date=27 July 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===={{anchor|Women in scanty armor}}Forms====
[[File:DiabloCosplay1.jpg|thumb|Women costumed as scantily armored player characters from the video game [[Diablo III]]]]
Many early female video game characters (such as [[Ms. Pac-Man]]) are identical to an existing male character, except for a visual marker of their femininity, such as pink bows, lipstick and long eyelashes.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;Sarkeesian, Anita. "[http://www.feministfrequency.com/2013/11/ms-male-character-tropes-vs-women/ Tropes vs Women Ms. Male Character]". Feminist Frequency.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://kotaku.com/new-anita-sarkeesian-video-looks-at-gamings-ms-male-1466898678 | title=New Anita Sarkeesian Video Looks At Gaming's 'Ms. Male' Trope | publisher=Kotaku | accessdate=7 May 2014 | author=Patricia Hernandez}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Female video game characters have been criticized as having a tendency to be subjects of the "[[male gaze]]".&lt;ref name="maleprivilege"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://kotaku.com/5868595/nerds-and-male-privilege|title=Nerds and Male Privilege|author=Harris O'Malley|publisher=Kotaku}}&lt;/ref&gt; A print ad for the fighting game ''[[Soulcalibur V]]'' received some controversy for simply being a close up of female character [[Ivy Valentine]]'s breasts with a tagline.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.adweek.com/adfreak/videogame-ad-sets-new-low-objectifying-women-137421 | title=Videogame Ad Sets New Low for Objectifying Women | publisher=AdWeek | date=January 10, 2012 | accessdate=7 May 2014 | author=David Griner}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title = This is how to sell Soulcalibur V|url = http://www.gamesradar.com/how-sell-soulcalibur-v/|website = GamesRadar+|accessdate = 2015-12-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; In two sequels of fighting games ''[[Soulcalibur]]'' and ''[[Tekken]]'' that take place several years after the original issue, recurring male characters were all aged but all female characters were kept the same age or were replaced by their daughters.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.starcitygames.com/magic/misc/22786_To_My_Someday_Daughter.html|author=Geordie Tait|title=To My Someday Daughter}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the popular series of [[Lara Croft]]'s ''Tomb Raider'' (both the games and the movies), quite often it is shown that Lara Croft is a quick and intelligent character who performs daring acts and acts in a heroic manner. While this appeals to many fans it is quite possible that behind the story there is a bit more to the story. It is suggested by Helen Kennedy &lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Kennedy|first1=Helen|title=Lara Croft, feminist icon or cyberbimbo? On the limits of textual analysis|publisher=Game Studies}}&lt;/ref&gt; argues that "Lara Croft is shown as the equivalent of an avatar controlled by a man, as she is seen as acting out the will of her father and not the agent or originator of her own actions at all." This is but another example of the role that female characters play in video games, when even in a game named after them they still cannot be free to act on their own will. In almost every example of a female protagonist they have a driving motive that is not of their own accord.

A recurrent representation of [[Women in speculative fiction|women in fantasy setting]]s, originating in the 1960s, is the [[women warriors in literature and culture|female warrior]] dressed in scanty armor.&lt;ref name="Adweek 4 June 2013"&gt;{{cite news|last=Griner|first=David|title=Will the Fantasy Genre Ever Grow Up and Ditch the Chainmail Bikini? Industry bulletin's cover sets off firestorm|url=http://www.adweek.com/adfreak/will-fantasy-genre-ever-grow-and-ditch-chainmail-bikini-150004|accessdate=7 June 2013|newspaper=[[Adweek]]|date=4 June 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; They feature armor designs which have been described by such terms as "[[Bikini in popular culture|chainmail bikinis]]", largely consisting of small decorative plaques that reveal large portions of the body to the weather and expose vital organs, making them ineffective as protection.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://madartlab.com/2011/12/14/fantasy-armor-and-lady-bits/|title=Fantasy armor and lady bits|publisher=MadArtLab.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; The prevalence of this portrayal is presented as an instance of the common sexualization of women in the [[geek culture]] including video games, comic and movies.&lt;ref name="maleprivilege"/&gt; In reaction to this, the art blog "Women Fighters in Reasonable Armor"&lt;ref name="realisticarmor"&gt;[http://womenfighters.tumblr.com/ Women Fighters in Reasonable Armor]&lt;/ref&gt; compiles depictions of women fighters wearing "realistic" armor.&lt;ref name="io9realistic"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://io9.com/5834665/our-new-favorite-tumblr-women-fighters-in-reasonable-armor|title=Women Fighters in Reasonable Armor: An Idea Whose Time Has Come|author=Charlie Jane Anders|publisher=[[io9]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Violence against women===
Violence in video games is a hotly debated topic; some sources condemned video games for promoting [[violence against women]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |url=http://mediareporttowomen.com/issues/311.htm |title=Women's role in popular video games: Stripped down and killed off |journal=Media Report to Women |date=Winter 2003 |page=1 |volume=31 |issue=1 |accessdate=2007-09-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; For example, the 2013 game ''[[Dead Island: Riptide]]'' generated controversy when the special "zombie bait" edition of the game included a statue of a torso of a busty, dismembered woman in a skimpy bikini.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.polygon.com/2013/1/15/3878810/dead-island-riptides-bloody-torso-statue-sparks-anger-shock | title=Dead Island Riptide's bloody torso statue sparks anger, confusion | publisher=Polygon.com | date=January 15, 2013 | accessdate=7 May 2014 | author=Brian Crecente}}&lt;/ref&gt; While much of the [[Grand Theft Auto (series)|Grand Theft Auto]] franchise has had issues with claims of violence against women, [[Rockstar North]]'s ''[[Grand Theft Auto V]]'' was also surrounded in much criticism; so much so that the sale of it was banned by certain retailers in Australia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Makuch|first1=Eddie|title=GTA 5 "Violence Against Women" Criticisms Spur Ban from Australian Retailers|url=http://www.gamespot.com/articles/gta-5-violence-against-women-criticisms-spurs-ban-/1100-6423950/|website=GameSpot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The 1982 game ''[[Custer's Revenge]]'' was first noted for containing elements of rape and some Native American groups and the [[National Organization for Women]] have criticised this as well as alleged [[racism]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://archive.gamespy.com/top10/december02/shame/index4.shtml |title=Top Ten Shameful Games: 1. Custer's Revenge (Atari 2600) |publisher=[[GameSpy]] |date=2002-12-31 |accessdate=2007-07-09 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070630014928/http://archive.gamespy.com/top10/december02/shame/index4.shtml |archivedate=June 30, 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The 2013 reboot of ''[[Tomb Raider (2013 video game)|Tomb Raider]]'' series drew controversy when ''[[Kotaku]]'' claimed executive producer Ron Rosenberg said rape was utilized as a means for the eponymous character's development.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=You'll 'Want To Protect' The New, Less Curvy Lara Croft|url=http://kotaku.com/5917400/youll-want-to-protect-the-new-less-curvy-lara-croft |publisher=[[Kotaku]] |accessdate=2013-11-18 |date=2012-06-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Crystal Dynamics]] denied that the scene depicted an attempted rape.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Tomb Raider Creators Are No Longer Referring to Game's Attempted 'Rape' Scene As an Attempted Rape Scene|url=http://kotaku.com/5918193/tomb-raider-creators-are-no-longer-referring-to-games-attempted-rape-scene-as-an-attempted-rape-scene |publisher=[[Kotaku]] |accessdate=2013-11-18 |date=2012-06-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Tomb Raider Creators Say 'Rape' Is Not A Word In Their Vocabulary|url=http://kotaku.com/5922228/tomb-raider-creators-say-rape-is-not-a-word-in-their-vocabulary |publisher=[[Kotaku]] |accessdate=2013-11-18 |date=2012-06-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Portrayal of men==
Men are also often portrayed stereotypically in games. A recurring depiction of male sexuality is the ''Power Fantasy,'' where an apparent sexualization as an object of desire and [[hypermasculinity]] are overruled by the character's agency as the protagonist and  avatar for the player’s power within the game world.&lt;ref name=":2"&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.pastemagazine.com/articles/2016/04/the-three-modes-of-male-sexuality-in-videogames.html|title=The Three Modes of Male Sexuality in Videogames|access-date=2016-08-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

They tend to be shown as muscular and big. For instance, men in video games have chests that are about 2 inches (6%) larger, heads that are about 13 inches bigger, waists that are 5 inches wider, and hips that are 7 inches wider, than in reality.&lt;ref&gt;Martins, N., D.C. Williams, R.A. Ratan, and K. Harrison. 2011. "Virtual muscularity: A content analysis of male video game characters". ''Body Image.'' 8 (1): 43-51.&lt;/ref&gt; They are often characterized as overtly aggressive and violent.&lt;ref name="Dietz" /&gt; Following the releases of ''[[Grand Theft Auto V]]'', the developers were met with criticism regarding both the portrayal of women and torture, but also that of men. Two of the main characters, [[Trevor Philips]] and [[Michael De Santa]], have since been interpreted by some as portraying men as "liars, cheats, bad husbands and fathers, and psychopaths."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Tassi|first1=Paul|title=On Gender and 'GTA 5'|url=http://www.forbes.com/sites/insertcoin/2013/09/26/on-gender-and-gta-5/|accessdate=April 24, 2015|publisher=Forbes|date=2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[GamesRadar]] writer David Houghton, writing in an article on sexism in video games, was highly critical of many stereotypes that came with male protagonists, outlining them as "the primeval hunter/gatherer type [with] arm-cripplingly ripped biceps, necks too muscley to turn, emotion dials stuck on 'aggressive grimace' and a 50% lack of chest coverings."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gamesradar.com/are-video-games-really-sexist/?page=2|title=Are video games really sexist?|author=Houghton, David|publisher=[[GamesRadar]]|date=2012-06-23|accessdate=2014-02-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Jamin Warren]] on PBS Game/Show highlighted that video games could promote "unreasonable body expectations, or an inability to express emotion, or the pressure to 'man up' and be a leader." He also highlighted that the vast majority of characters who perform and experience violence in video games are men, while women and children are generally to be protected.&lt;ref name= GameShow&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mrActT_7X6U |title=Do Videogame Stereotypes Hurt Men? |accessdate=2014-09-29|date=2013-10-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Dante Douglas of [[Paste (magazine)|Paste magazine]] identifies this "power fantasy" alongside two other stereotypes, males as ''Gender Performance'' and as ''Fan Interpretation''.&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt;
* In the interpretation as gender performance under an heteronormative perspective, a male being sexy is seen as an opposite of masculinity. In this view, depictions of males as objects of desire are coded by including feminine traits, vanity and attention to personal attires, or [[queer]] codes, often depicted as humorous.&lt;ref name=":3"&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.your-critic.com/2011/06/gamers-gaze-part-1.html|title=Your Critic is in Another Castle: The Gamer's Gaze, part 1|website=www.your-critic.com|access-date=2016-08-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Bishōnen]] archetipe is an example of this portrayal, as well as characters like [[Vega (Street Fighter)|Vega]] from ''Street Fighter'', [[Mettaton]] from ''Undertale,'' [[Maxi (Soulcalibur)|Maxi]] and [[Raphael (Soulcalibur)|Raphael]] from ''Soul Calibur'', and [[Sephiroth (Final Fantasy)|Sephiroth]] from ''Final Fantasy VII''.&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt;
* A different way of sexualizing male characters is that performed by players and fans communities, in particular for characters open to their own emotions.&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt; Douglas identifies as traits of these characters the space dedicated in the game to show their personality, shown through their interactions with other characters, and their agency through those interactions rather than pure displays of strength and power. Because of these traits, this category of characters occurs most often with non-player characters.
Multiple critics point out at the [[male gaze]] theory as the reason why male characters are not overtly sexualized in the same way as females, mentioning the assumption in the video game industry that a majority of [[gamer]]s are heterosexual men, to whom companies cater.&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.popmatters.com/post/151713-on-mens-sexualization-in-video-games/|title=On Mens Sexualization in Video Games|access-date=2016-08-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Portrayal of LGBT characters==
{{main article|LGBT themes in video games|LGBT characters in video games}}

LGBT characters have been included in video games as early as the 1980s and 1990s.&lt;ref name=":rated m"&gt;{{Cite book|title=Rated M for Mature : Sex and Sexuality in Video Games|last=Wysocki|first=Matthew|last2=Lauteria|first2=Evan W.|publisher=Bloomsbury Publishing|year=2015|isbn=9781628925760|location=New York, NY|pages=42–57|quote=|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the [[history of video games]], LGBT content has been subject to changing rules and regulations, which are generally examples of [[heterosexism]], in that heterosexuality is normalized, while homosexuality is subject to additional [[censorship]] or ridicule. Companies [[Nintendo]], [[Sega]] and [[Maxis]] policed the content of games with content codes in which LGBT themes were toned down or erased.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Steltenpohl|first=Crystal|title=GLBT History in Video Games: 1990s|url=http://www.gamingbus.com/2012/06/12/glbt-history-video-games-1990s/|publisher=Gaming Bus|accessdate=9 May 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Phantasy"&gt;{{cite web|first=Mike|last=Ripplinger|year=2002|title=The Two Phantasy Stars  |url=http://www.camineet.net/camineet/theories/twophantasystars.asp|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080204060641/http://www.camineet.net/camineet/theories/twophantasystars.asp|archivedate=2008-02-04|publisher=Camineet|accessdate=2010-01-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="ModtheSims"&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20100128041935/http://www.modthesims.info/download.php?t=388170 "Autonomous Romantic Socials - Same Sex"], by werismyki&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Sims3"&gt;[http://forum.thesims3.com/jforum/posts/list/30/191458.page "Why is My Town Gay?"], by Srikandi&lt;/ref&gt; Some games, for instance, originally included trans characters, such as [[Birdo|Birdo from Super Mario Bros]], [[Poison (Final Fight)|Poison from the Final Fight series]], and Flea from Chrono Trigger. Due to adherence to Nintendo's quality standards and translations based on preserving gameplay rather than literal meaning, these characters' identities were altered or erased in translation.&lt;ref name=":rated m" /&gt;

Video games are a [[Heteronormativity|heteronormative]] media.&lt;ref name=":fairytale romances"&gt;{{Cite book|title=Hot Dates and Fairytale Romances: Studying Sexuality in Video Games|last=Consalvo|first=Mia|publisher=Routledge|year=2003|isbn=0415965780|location=New York, NY|pages=172–191|quote=|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":gay in games"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Shaw|first=Adrienne|date=2009-07-01|title=Putting the Gay in Games Cultural Production and GLBT Content in Video Games|url=http://gac.sagepub.com/content/4/3/228|journal=Games and Culture|language=en|volume=4|issue=3|pages=228–253|doi=10.1177/1555412009339729|issn=1555-4120}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to industry professionals interviewed by Shaw, reasons for this [[heteronormativity]] include the demographic of those who play games, the views of those who create games, the risk of backlash in the industry, and the storytelling limitations of the medium.&lt;ref name=":gay in games" /&gt;

Choice based LGBT content, such as optional same sex romance in Bioware games,&lt;ref name=":shepard in pink"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Krobová|first=Tereza|last2=Moravec|first2=Ondřej|last3=Švelch|first3=Jaroslav|title=Dressing Commander Shepard in pink: Queer playing in a heteronormative game culture|url=http://cyberpsychology.eu/view.php?cisloclanku=2015081905&amp;article=3|journal=Cyberpsychology: Journal of Psychosocial Research on Cyberspace|volume=9|issue=3|doi=10.5817/cp2015-3-3}}&lt;/ref&gt; is a low- risk &lt;ref name=":gay in games" /&gt; form of representation that occurs only in video games.&lt;ref name=":at the edge"&gt;{{Cite book|title=Gaming at the Edge: Sexuality and Gender at the Margins of Gamer Culture|last=Shaw|first=Adrienne|publisher=University of Minnesota Press|year=2014|isbn=978-0-8166-9315-3|location=Minneapolis, MN|pages=13–55}}&lt;/ref&gt;  When representation is included, it is often through these in-game choices, which place the responsibility for representation on players instead of developers.&lt;ref name=":at the edge" /&gt; Because they afford the most opportunity for player choice and in game romance, genres such as [[Role-playing video game|RPGs]] and [[Massively multiplayer online game|MMOs]] are the most LGBT representative.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.ign.com/articles/2012/01/25/a-gay-history-of-gaming|title=A Gay History of Gaming|last=MacDonald|first=Keza|date=2012-01-25|website=IGN|language=en-US|access-date=2016-10-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another low risk method of LGBT representation is "Gay window gaming," which is LGBT representation that is either subtle or avoidable in games that serves to appeal to LGBT players without alienating straight or homophobic players. This can occur in sandbox games such as [[The Sims (video game)|The Sims]].&lt;ref name=":fairytale romances" /&gt;

In games with LGBT characters or the option of an LGBT avatar, some aspects of marginalization that occur in contemporary culture are depicted despite the game's overall adherence to reality.&lt;ref name=":at the edge" /&gt; These real social constraints are imposed on a virtual world due to the way games are constructed and the community that inhabits them. Games are made using the same heteronormative basis seen in contemporary culture, and this shapes narrative and characters. In both reality and [[World of Warcraft]], LGBT people are silenced and viewed as abnormal by the rest of the community.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Pulos|first=Alexis|date=2013-03-01|title=Confronting Heteronormativity in Online Games A Critical Discourse Analysis of LGBTQ Sexuality in World of Warcraft|url=http://gac.sagepub.com/content/8/2/77|journal=Games and Culture|language=en|volume=8|issue=2|pages=77–97|doi=10.1177/1555412013478688|issn=1555-4120}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Both members of the industry &lt;ref name=":gay in games" /&gt; and LGBT players &lt;ref name=":shepard in pink" /&gt; prefer LGBT representation to be normalized in game narratives rather than made to seem abnormal or special. There are no games produced specifically to appeal to an LGBT audience.&lt;ref name=":id as a gamer"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Shaw|first=Adrienne|date=2012-02-01|title=Do you identify as a gamer? Gender, race, sexuality, and gamer identity|url=http://nms.sagepub.com/content/14/1/28|journal=New Media &amp; Society|language=en|volume=14|issue=1|pages=28–44|doi=10.1177/1461444811410394|issn=1461-4448}}&lt;/ref&gt; LGBT players prefer this so they can avoid marginalization in the gaming community.&lt;ref name=":gay in games" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":id as a gamer" /&gt;

LGBT gamers use queer readings of media to compensate for their lack of representation in it.&lt;ref name=":gay in games" /&gt; As concluded in a study by Moravec, this “imaginative play” is the most common method LGBT gamers use to relate to in game avatars&lt;ref name=":shepard in pink" /&gt; that are typically created for a presumed straight male player to relate to.&lt;ref name=":fairytale romances" /&gt;

[[Sexual orientation]] and [[gender identity]] have served a significant role in some video games, with the trend being toward greater visibility of LGBT identities.&lt;ref name="NeoSeeker"&gt;[http://www.neoseeker.com/news/11314-sunday-musing-homosexuality-in-video games/ "Homosexuality in Video Games"], by Lydia Sung&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Kotaku"&gt;[http://kotaku.com/5232808/how-not-to-address-homosexuality-in-gaming "How Not To Address Homosexuality In Gaming"], by Mike Fahey&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://i.joystiq.com/2007/02/26/gay-gamer-survey-results-with-large-hetero-inclusion/|title=Gay gamer survey results with large hetero inclusion|author=Alexander Sliwinski|publisher=[[Joystiq]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Speaking on the Ubisoft blog, Lucien Soulband, who is openly gay and was the writer for ''[[Far Cry 3: Blood Dragon]]'', said that openly gay or lesbian characters would not appear in video games for a long while as anything other than a one-off or something that was created through user choice as seen in the ''[[Mass Effect]]'' and ''[[Dragon Age]]'' games.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.polygon.com/2014/2/28/5456234/video-games-wont-feature-gay-protagonists-for-a-while-says-far-cry-3|title=Video games won't feature gay protagonists 'for a while,' says Far Cry 3 writer Lucien Soulban|author=Gera, Emily|publisher=[[Polygon (website)|Polygon]]|date=2014-02-28|accessdate=2014-02-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; The character of Dorian in [[Dragon Age: Inquisition]] was regarded as a significant development for the portrayal of gay characters in games, in that his homosexuality informs plot elements that occur regardless of whether the player decides to interact with him romantically.&lt;ref name="outDorian"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.out.com/popnography/2015/7/13/dorian-dragon-age-inquisition-why-gamings-breakout-gay-character-matters|last=Baume|first=Matt|work=[[Out (magazine)]]|title=Dorian of Dragon Age: Inquisition: Why Gaming's 'Breakout' Gay Character Matters|date=July 13, 2015|accessdate=October 26, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Dragon Age: Inquisition was also noted for its respectful portrayal of a transgender character.

==Effect of gender representation in games==

=== Effect on attitudes towards gender ===
A 2008 study found that males reported playing more violent video games than females. This exposure was negatively correlated with men's certainty in their judgements when presented with a scenario of possible sexual harassment selected for its ambiguity. The exposure to violent video games was also correlated with attitudes supportive of rape.&lt;ref&gt;Dill, Karen E., Brian P. Brown, and Michael A. Collins. "[http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022103108001005 Effects of exposure to sex-stereotyped video game characters on tolerance of sexual harassment]." Journal of Experimental Social Psychology 44.5 (2008): 1402-1408.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Effect on children===
Canadian non-profit [[MediaSmarts]] writes that "video games have the potential to influence how children perceive themselves and others", and despite their impact on the youth, "there is not a lot of research available in this area, and few of the existing studies stand up to critical examination. This lack of scrutiny means that we know very little about the effects that video games may have on children's development and socialization."&lt;ref name=MediaSmarts&gt;{{cite web|url=http://mediasmarts.ca/video-games/concerns-about-video-games |title=The Concerns About Video Games |accessdate=2014-09-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Dietz, video game characters have the potential to shape players' perceptions of gender roles. Through social comparison processes, players learn societal expectations of appearances, behaviors and roles.&lt;ref name=Dietz&gt;{{cite journal|last=Dietz|first=Tracy|title=An Examination of Violence and Gender Role Portrayals in Video Games: Implications for Gender Socialization and Aggressive Behavior|journal=Sex Roles|year=1998|volume=38|pages=425–442|doi=10.1023/A:1018709905920|issue=5/6}}&lt;/ref&gt; Girls may expect that they be dependent victims and that their responsibilities include maintaining beauty and sexual appeal, while boys may determine that their role is to protect and defend women.&lt;ref name="Dietz" /&gt; Thus, Dietz claims, the roles internalized by the child, including gender, become for the child, and later for the adult, a basis for other roles and for action. The gender roles internalized by young individuals have a significant impact upon their perspectives and the additional roles they assume in later life. Feminine and masculine symbols are supposed to become a part of a child's identity.&lt;ref name="Dietz" /&gt;

==Players' preferences==
Although games that included the option of selecting a female hero obtained better review scores, they sold fewer copies than games with exclusively male protagonists. [[Penny Arcade Report]] attributed the difference to larger marketing budgets for games with male heroes.&lt;ref name="PAR 21 November 2012"&gt;{{cite news|last=Kuchera|first=Ben|title=Games with exclusively female heroes don't sell (because publishers don't support them)|url=http://penny-arcade.com/report/editorial-article/games-with-female-heroes-dont-sell-because-publishers-dont-support-them|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130321064024/http://www.penny-arcade.com/report/article/games-with-female-heroes-dont-sell-because-publishers-dont-support-them||archivedate=21 March 2013|accessdate=21 November 2012|newspaper=Penny Arcade Report|date=21 November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Games with a female-only protagonist had, on average, only 50% of the marketing budget of female-optional games, and 40% of the marketing budget of games with male-only protagonists.&lt;ref name="PAR 21 November 2012" /&gt; Male-only games included popular sports and war franchises such as ''Madden'' and ''Call of Duty'', and EEDAR's Jesse Divnich stated in 2010, "The factors that drive sales are based more on brand licensing, marketing budgets, development budget and a thousand other factors that have little to do with the gender of playable avatars."&lt;ref name="escapistEEDAR"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.escapistmagazine.com/news/view/103045-EEDAR-Says-the-Chicks-Are-Alright|last=Chalk|first=Andy|work=The Escapist|title=EEDAR Says the Chicks Are Alright}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Polling in 2015 by Pew Research Center showed 16% of adults who play video games believe most games portray women poorly, compared to 26% who disagree, and 34% who say it depends on the game. Among those who do not play, 55% are unsure if games portray women poorly. Minimal differences were seen between male and female responses.&lt;ref name="pewGamer2015"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pewinternet.org/2015/12/15/attitudes-about-video-games/|last=Duggan|first=Maeve|publisher=Pew Research Center|title=Gaming and Gamers}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A 2015 survey of 1,583 U.S. students aged 11 to 18 by [[Rosalind Wiseman]] and [[Ashly Burch]] indicated that 60% of girls but only 39% of boys preferred to play a character of their own gender, and 28% of girls as opposed to 20% of boys said that they were more likely to play a game based on the character's gender. The authors interpreted this as meaning that the gaming industry's focus on male protagonists stifled sales to girls more than it promoted sales to boys.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Hall|first1=Charlie|title=The games industry is wrong about kids, gaming and gender|url=http://www.polygon.com/2015/3/5/8153213/the-games-industry-is-wrong-about-kids-gaming-and-gender|accessdate=8 March 2015|work=[[Polygon (website)|Polygon]]|date=5 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Video games|Gender studies|Feminism|Fictional characters}}
*[[Portrayal of women in American comics]]
*[[Sexual harassment in video gaming]]
*[[Media and gender]]
*[[Race and video games]]
{{Clear}}

==Footnotes==
{{reflist|30em}}

==References==
{{More footnotes|date=April 2015}}
*{{cite book|last=Brown|first=Jeffrey A.|title=Dangerous Curves: Action Heroines, Gender, Fetishism, and Popular Culture|year=2011|publisher=University Press of Mississippi|location=Jackson|isbn=160473714X}}
*{{cite journal|last=Dickerman|first=Charles|title=Big Breast and Bad Guys: Depictions of Gender and Race in Video Games|journal=Journal of Creativity in Mental Health|year=2008|volume=3|issue=1|doi=10.1080/15401380801995076|last2=Christensen|first2=Jeff|last3=Kerl-Mcclain|first3=Stella Beatríz|page=20}}
*{{cite journal |last=Jansz |first=Jeroen |author2=Martis, Raynel G.|title=The Lara Phenomenon: Powerful Female Characters in Video Games |journal=Sex Roles |location=New York |date=February 2007 |volume=56 |issue=3–4 |doi=10.1007/s11199-006-9158-0 |page=141}}
*{{cite journal|first=Nicole|last=Martins|author2=Williams, Dmitri C. |author3=Ratan, Rabindra A. |author4= Harrison, Kristen |title=Virtual muscularity: a content analysis of male video game characters|journal=Body Image|year=2011|doi=10.1016/j.bodyim.2010.10.002|volume=8|pages=43–51|pmid=21093394|issue=1}}

[[Category:Gender and video games]]
[[Category:Media issues]]
[[Category:Women and video games]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>