<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20141014203437|629622779" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="34903083" pageid="34903083" ns="0" title="Gender representation in video games"><revisions><rev timestamp="2014-11-08T20:33:32Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{redirect|Women in video games|women as video game developers and players|Women and video games}}
The portrayal of men and women in [[video games]], as in other media, is a subject of research in [[gender studies]] and is discussed in the context of [[sexism in video gaming]]. The way men and women are portrayed in games often reflects [[gender role]]s or popular stereotypes, such as that of the [[damsel in distress]] for women. Women are also significantly underrepresented as characters in mainstream games, particularly as protagonists.

==Gamer demographics ==
According to the Entertainment Software Association, 48% of all American video game players are women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=2014 Essential Facts About the Computer and Video Game Industry|date=April 2014|publisher=[[Entertainment Software Association]]|page=3|url=http://www.theesa.com/facts/pdfs/ESA_EF_2014.pdf|accessdate=23 June 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the UK and in Spain, women comprise 52% and 48% of video game players respectively.&lt;ref name=PlayGround&gt;{{cite web|title=Ellas también juegan, o por qué el machismo gamer no tiene ningún sentido|author=Natxo Medina|url=http://www.playgroundmag.net/articulos/reportajes/videojuegos-mujeres-gamer-feminismo_0_1396060382.html|accessdate=2014-09-29|date=2014-09-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Portrayal of women==
The portrayal of women in video games is the subject of academic study and controversy. Recurring themes in both include the level of independence of female characters from their male counterparts, as well as their [[sexual objectification]] and [[sexualization]].

Studies have shown that women who are exposed to stereotypical media representations of women identify with these stereotypes and base their appearance off of them. When unrealistic appearances shown cannot be achieved, this leads to issues with self-esteem and self-confidence.&lt;ref&gt;Burgess, Melinda C R, Steven Paul Stermer and Stephen R Burgess. “ Sex, Lies, and Video Games: The Portrayal of Male and Female Characters on Video Game Covers.” Sex Roles 57.5 (2007): 419-433. ProQuest. Web. 22 April 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Roles of women===

====Prevalence====

The vast majority of female characters have been found to be non-playable, meaning they cannot be played by the gamer. This suggests a female secondary status in video games. When playable female characters do appear in video games, it is most likely they are scantily dressed and over-sexualized in unrealistic ways.&lt;ref&gt;Behm-morawitz, Elizabeth, and Dana Mastro. “The Effects of the Sexualization of Female Video Game Characters on Gender Stereotyping and Female Self-Concept.” Sex Roles 61.11 (2009): 808-823. ProQuest. Web. 22 April 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;

According to data gathered by [[Electronic Entertainment Design and Research]] (EEDAR), few video games have exclusively female heroes. This is in part because, according to EEDAR, "there's a sense in the industry that games with female heroes won’t sell", which [[Penny Arcade]] attributed in part to these games receiving much smaller marketing budgets than games with male heroes.&lt;ref name="PAR 21 November 2012"&gt;{{cite news|last=Kuchera|first=Ben|title=Games with exclusively female heroes don’t sell (because publishers don’t support them)|url=http://penny-arcade.com/report/editorial-article/games-with-female-heroes-dont-sell-because-publishers-dont-support-them|accessdate=21 November 2012|newspaper=Penny Arcade Report|date=21 November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In a sample of 669 action, shooter, and role-playing games selected by EEDAR in 2012, only 24 (4%) had an exclusively female protagonist, and 300 (45%) provided the option of selecting one. Examining the sales data and review scores of these games, EEDAR found that the games that included the option of selecting a female hero obtained better scores, but the ones with male-only protagonists sold better than the others. However, games with a female-only protagonist had, on average, only 50% of the marketing budget of female-optional games, and 40% of the marketing budget of games with male-only protagonists.&lt;ref name="PAR 21 November 2012" /&gt;

A study by Burgess found that men are featured much more often than women on the covers of console video games.&lt;ref name=Burgess&gt;{{cite journal|last=Burgess|first=Melinda C. R.|coauthors=Steven Paul Stermer &amp; Stephen R. Burgess|title=Sex, Lies, and Video Games: The Portrayal of Male and Female Characters on Video Game Covers|journal=Sex Roles|date=30 June 2007|pages=419–433|doi=10.1007/s11199-007-9250-0|volume=57|issue=5–6}}&lt;/ref&gt;


====Evolution====
{{category see also|Video games featuring female protagonists}}
[[Samus Aran]], the heroine of ''[[Metroid (video game)|Metroid]]'' (1986) and its successors, is often cited as "the first playable human female character in a mainstream videogame".&lt;ref name="Guinness2013"&gt;{{cite book | title=Guinness World Records 2013: Gamer's Edition | publisher=Guinness World Records Ltd | authorlink=Feature: Girl Power-Up | year=2012 | page=154 | isbn=9781904994954}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, other earlier games featured female player characters, such as Toby Masuyo ("Kissy") from ''[[Baraduke]]'' (1985).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.hardcoregaming101.net/namcoxcapcom/namcoxcapcom2.htm#tobymasuyo | title=Obscure Namco characters | publisher=Hardcore Gaming 101 | accessdate=6 October 2013 | author=Kurt Kalata}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.nintendolife.com/news/2009/10/nintendo_download_13_14_october_2009_japan | title=Nintendo Download: 13-14 October 2009 (Japan) | publisher=nintendolife.com | accessdate=6 October 2013 | author=Sean Aaron}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Lara Croft]], the protagonist of ''[[Tomb Raider (1996 video game)|Tomb Raider]]'' (1996), is among the best-known strong, fictional women in a variety of media.&lt;ref name="taylor"&gt;{{cite book | last1 = Egenfeldt-Nielsen | first1 = Simon | last2 = Smith | first2 = Jonas Heide | last3 = Pajares Tosca | first3 = Susana | title = Understanding video games: the essential introduction | chapter = Player culture | publisher = Taylor &amp; Francis | year = 2008 | page = 163 | url = http://books.google.com/?id=31XHdVXlbt0C&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;dq=%22april%20ryan%22&amp;pg=PA163#v=onepage&amp;q=%22april%20ryan%22&amp;f=false | accessdate = 2011-07-03 | isbn = 978-0-415-97721-0 | quote = "Helen Kennedy [...] summarizes these arguments, and Lara Croft's ambivalent role as both an action heroine [...], and an eroticized object of the male gaze with a great deal of voyeuristic appeal".}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[April Ryan]] from ''[[The Longest Journey]]'' (1999) has been compared to Lara Croft in that respect, as she shows less prominent physical feminine attributes than Lara but more feminine psychological traits, as contrasted with Lara's masculine connotations like aggressiveness and force.&lt;ref name="merete"&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.csi.ensmp.fr/WebCSI/4S/download/download_page.php?file=lie.pdf | title = Lara Croft and her sisters | accessdate = 2011-07-03 | last = Lie | first = Merete | publisher = Norwegian University of Science and Technology | quote = "She is attractive, but no sex bomb"  "April may, however, appear as more feminine because even if she is tough and brave, she is depicted as both sensitive and vain"}}&lt;/ref&gt; Contrarily, [[Jade (Beyond Good &amp; Evil)|Jade]], the protagonist of ''[[Beyond Good &amp; Evil]]'' (2003), was widely recognized as a strong and confident female character lacking any overt sexualisation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Rougeau|first=Michael|url=http://www.complex.com/video-games/2013/01/the-50-greatest-heroines-in-video-game-history/jade|title=50 Greatest Heroines In Video Game History|publisher=Complex|date=March 4, 2013|accessdate=March 24, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Bayonetta: empowering or exploitative?|url=http://www.gamepro.com/article/features/213466/bayonetta-empowering-or-exploitative/ |publisher=[[GamePro]] |accessdate=2010-01-16|date=2010-01-06|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20100109032922/http://www.gamepro.com/article/features/213466/bayonetta-empowering-or-exploitative/|archivedate=2010-01-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2014 the developers' choice to omit playable women in the latest iterations of the top-tier gaming franchises ''[[Assassin's Creed]]'' and ''[[Far Cry]]'' became a focus of discussions in gaming media. This indicated, according to game industry professionals cited by ''[[Polygon (website)|Polygon]]'', a shift in the industry's attention towards issues of diversity in gaming, in conjunction with video games as a whole growing beyond their former core audience of younger men.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Crecente|first1=Brian|title=As game players diversify, developers start to rethink the stars of their games|url=http://www.polygon.com/2014/6/23/5834628/women-in-video-games-heroines-e3-2014|accessdate=23 June 2014|work=Polygon|date=23 June 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Female supporting characters====
A number of games feature a female character as an ally or [[sidekick]] to the male hero. Some of them, like [[Ada Wong]] and [[Mona Sax]], were turned into [[player character]]s in later instances of their series. [[Alyx Vance]], a supporting protagonist of ''[[Half-Life 2]]'', was praised for her "stinging personality" and intelligence, developing a close bond with the player without simply being "eye candy".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ugo.com/games/video-game-hotties/?cur=alyx-vance&amp;morepics=17 Top 50 Videogame Hotties]. [[UGO.com]]. Retrieved on 2008-12-14&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ugo.com/games/gaming-girls/?cur=alyx-vance Top 11 Girls of Gaming]. [[UGO.com]]. Retrieved on 2008-12-28&lt;/ref&gt;

However, female characters are often cast in the role of the [[damsel in distress]], with their rescue being the objective of the game.&lt;ref name="Tremblay2012"&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.gamasutra.com/blogs/KaitlinTremblay/20120601/171613/Intro_to_Gender_Criticism_for_Gamers_From_Princess_Peach_to_Claire_Redfield_to_FemSheps.php?print=1 | title=Intro to Gender Criticism for Gamers: From Princess Peach, to Claire Redfield, to FemSheps. | publisher=[[Gamasutra]] | date=06/01/12 | accessdate=8 October 2013 | author=Kaitlin Tremblay}} &lt;blockquote&gt;In video games, the major stereotyped myths of women are typically the damsel in distress, hyper-sexualized villain (Sylvia Christel from No More Heroes) and the sexy/strong best friend (Tifa from Final Fantasy VII). [...] In all of these instances, the female character is, more likely than not, in love with the male protagonist or trying desperately to bang him. &lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://kotaku.com/shigeru-miyamoto-and-the-damsel-in-distress-520259897 | title=Shigeru Miyamoto and the Damsel In Distress | publisher=[[Kotaku]] | date=2013-06-20 | accessdate=8 October 2013 | author=Stephen Totilo}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Princess Zelda]] in the early ''[[The Legend of Zelda]]'' series and [[Princess Peach]] through much of the ''[[Mario (series)|Mario]]'' series are [[wikt:paradigm|paradigmatic]] examples. Both of them, however, became playable in the later games of their series or had the pattern altered.

====Female antagonists====
{{category see also|Video games featuring female antagonists}}
The [[Dark Queen (Battletoads)|Dark Queen]] in ''[[Battletoads]]'' (1991) and its successors is one of the first major female villains in video games.&lt;ref&gt;Steven A. Schwartz, Janet Schwartz, ''The Parent's Guide to Video Games'', Prima Pub., 1994 (p.8)&lt;/ref&gt; [[SHODAN]], an artificial intelligence with a female voice and a female face, was the main villain of the game ''[[System Shock]]'' (1994), praised as one of the most recognizable female characters in gaming.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gamespot.com/features/tenspot_females/page9.html TenSpot: Ten Best Female Characters]. GameSpot. Retrieved on 19 November 2013&lt;/ref&gt; Another prominent female villain is [[Characters of Final Fantasy VIII#Ultimecia|Ultimecia]], the main antagonist in ''[[Final Fantasy VIII]]'' (1999). At [[Penny Arcade Expo|PAX]] Prime 2013, she was voted among the best female antagonists in video gaming history.&lt;ref name="ForbesPAXreport"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.forbes.com/sites/davidewalt/2013/08/31/are-these-the-top-women-game-characters-of-all-time/|title=Are These The Top Women Game Characters of All Time?|last=Ewalt|first=David M.|publisher=''[[Forbes]]''|date=2013-08-31|accessdate=2013-10-07|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20131031081428/http://www.forbes.com/sites/davidewalt/2013/08/31/are-these-the-top-women-game-characters-of-all-time/ |archivedate=2013-10-31 |deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, [[GLaDOS]] from ''[[Portal (video game)|Portal]]'' (2007), an insane computer with a female voice, was praised by critics as one of the best new characters of the 2000s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=The 25 best new characters of the decade |url=http://www.gamesradar.com/f/the-25-best-new-characters-of-the-decade/a-20091221171910974007 |publisher=[[GamesRadar]] |accessdate=2010-01-04 |date=2009-12-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Depiction of women===

====Objectification and sexualization====
{{See also|List of adult video games}}

Many recent games have increased the sexualized portrayal of women so as to appeal to a male audience.&lt;ref name="Tremblay2012"/&gt; In 2012, for instance, ''[[Dead or Alive (series)|Dead or Alive]]'' director, Yohei Shimbori, admitted the developers received complaints from fans who had played the [[Dead or Alive 5]] demo packaged with ''[[Ninja Gaiden 3]]''. According to Shimbori, "We actually got a lot of feedback from people who were playing it, saying, 'We want bigger breasts. Make the characters more like that.' That was kind of surprising."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Team Ninja learns to fear its fans|url=http://www.gamasutra.com/view/news/178358/Team_Ninja_learns_to_fear_its_fans.php#.UGVMR03A-RR |publisher=[[Gamasutra]] |accessdate=2013-03-15 |date=2012-09-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Female video game characters have been criticized as tending to suffer from a particularly extreme manifestation of the [[gaze|male gaze]].&lt;ref name="maleprivilege"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://kotaku.com/5868595/nerds-and-male-privilege|title=Nerds and Male Privilege|author=Harris O'Malley|publisher=Kotaku}}&lt;/ref&gt; A print ad for the fighting game [[Soul Calibur V]] received some controversy for simply being a close up of a female character's breasts with a tagline.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.adweek.com/adfreak/videogame-ad-sets-new-low-objectifying-women-137421 | title=Videogame Ad Sets New Low for Objectifying Women | publisher=AdWeek | date=January 10, 2012 | accessdate=7 May 2014 | author=David Griner}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Since her introduction in 1996, the character of [[Lara Croft]] from the ''[[Tomb Raider]]'' series in particular has been criticized for her unrealistic breast size; Lara was claimed to personify "an ongoing culture clash over gender, sexuality, empowerment, and objectification."&lt;ref name="gettingthegirl"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.1up.com/do/feature?cId=3137700 |author=Zoe Flower |title=Getting the Girl: The myths, misconceptions, and misdemeanors of females in games |publisher=[[1UP.com]] |accessdate=2007-09-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the game's creators maintain that she was not designed with marketing in mind, and have claimed to be rather surprised at her pinup-style adoration.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Lara Croft, the Bit Girl |author=N'gai Croal and Jane Hughes |publisher=[[Newsweek]] |date=1997-11-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; In ''[[Tomb Raider: Legend]]'', Lara underwent a radical redesign, ostensibly to make her less sexualized.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title= Lara's curves reduced to appeal to female gamers |date=2005-05-21 |publisher=[[The Sydney Morning Herald]] |url=http://www.smh.com.au/news/World/Real-appeal/2005/05/21/1116533572111.html |accessdate=2007-07-09}}{{dead link|date=June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In two sequels of fighting games [[Soul Calibur]] and [[Tekken]] that take place several years after the original issue, recurring male characters were allowed to age but all female characters were kept the same age or replaced by their daughters.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.starcitygames.com/magic/misc/22786_To_My_Someday_Daughter.html|author=Geordie Tait|title=To My Someday Daughter}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In their 2005 study, Dill and Thill distinguish three major stereotypical depictions of women in gaming: (1) sexualized, (2) scantily clad, and (3) a vision of beauty.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Dill|first=Karen E.|author2=Thill K. P.|title=Video Game Characters and the Socialization of Gender Roles: Young People’s Perceptions Mirror Sexist Media Depictions|journal=Sex Roles|year=2007|volume=57|pages=851–864|doi=10.1007/s11199-007-9278-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; The study revealed that over 80% of women in video games represented one of these depictions. More than one quarter of female characters embodied all of the three stereotypical categories at once. Dill and Thill also note that another prevalent theme with which women were depicted was a combination of aggression and sex, referred to as ''eroticized aggression''.

According to Dietz, women are often depicted in stereotypical roles that typically pertain to sexuality in which the woman focuses upon beauty/physical attractiveness.&lt;ref name="Dietz" /&gt;

====={{anchor|Women in scanty armor}}Women in scanty armor=====
A recurrent representation of [[Women in speculative fiction|women in fantasy setting]]s, originating in the 1960s, is the [[women warriors in literature and culture|woman warrior]] dressed in unrealistically scanty armor.&lt;ref name="Adweek 4 June 2013"&gt;{{cite news|last=Griner|first=David|title=Will the Fantasy Genre Ever Grow Up and Ditch the Chainmail Bikini? Industry bulletin's cover sets off firestorm|url=http://www.adweek.com/adfreak/will-fantasy-genre-ever-grow-and-ditch-chainmail-bikini-150004|accessdate=7 June 2013|newspaper=[[Adweek]]|date=4 June 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; They feature armor designs which have been described by such terms as [[Bikini in popular culture|chainmail bikinis]], largely consisting of small decorative plaques that reveal large portions of the body skin to the weather and that expose vital organs, thus being completely noneffective as protection.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://madartlab.com/2011/12/14/fantasy-armor-and-lady-bits/|title=Fantasy armor and lady bits|publisher=MadArtLab.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; The prevalence of this portrayal is an instance of the common sexualization of women in the [[geek culture]] including video games, comic and movies.&lt;ref name="maleprivilege"/&gt; In reaction to this, the art blog "Women Fighters in Reasonable Armor"&lt;ref name="realisticarmor"&gt;[http://womenfighters.tumblr.com/ Women Fighters in Reasonable Armor]&lt;/ref&gt; compiles depictions of women fighters wearing realistic armor.&lt;ref name="io9realistic"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://io9.com/5834665/our-new-favorite-tumblr-women-fighters-in-reasonable-armor|title=Women Fighters in Reasonable Armor: An Idea Whose Time Has Come|author=Charlie Jane Anders|publisher=[[io9]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====In comparison to male characters====
According to [[Anita Sarkeesian]], many early female video game characters (such as [[Ms. Pac-Man]]) are identical to an existing male character, except for a visual marker of their femininity, such as pink bows, lipstick and long eyelashes.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;Sarkeesian, Anita. "[http://www.feministfrequency.com/2013/11/ms-male-character-tropes-vs-women/ Tropes vs Women Ms. Male Character]". Feminist Frequency.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://kotaku.com/new-anita-sarkeesian-video-looks-at-gamings-ms-male-1466898678 | title=New Anita Sarkeesian Video Looks At Gaming's 'Ms. Male' Trope | publisher=Kotaku | accessdate=7 May 2014 | author=Patricia Hernandez}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In a study done in [[Southwestern Oklahoma State University]] comparing the appearances of male and female characters on video game covers, a few things were discovered. On covers, male characters were five times more likely to represented as the main character in the game, and women were merely portrayed as side kicks or accessories. Also, both male and female character's physiques were overexaggerated on video game covers; however, females were more physically altered (especially in the bust) than their male counterparts, and even more so if the female was the main character of the game.&lt;ref&gt;Burgess, Melinda C R, Steven Paul Stermer and Stephen R Burgess. [http://www.paulstermer.com/resources/SR.pdf "Sex, Lies, and Video Games: The Portrayal of Male and Female Characters on Video Game Covers.”] Sex Roles 57.5 (2007): 419-433. ProQuest. Web. 22 April 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Violence against women====

=====Sexual violence=====
The 1982 game ''[[Custer's Revenge]]'' was first noted for containing elements of [[rape]] and some Native American groups and the [[National Organization for Women]] have criticised this as well as alleged [[racism]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://archive.gamespy.com/top10/december02/shame/index4.shtml |title=Top Ten Shameful Games: 1. Custer's Revenge (Atari 2600) |publisher=[[GameSpy]] |date=2002-12-31 |accessdate=2007-07-09}} {{dead link|date=March 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The 2013 reboot of ''[[Tomb Raider]]'' series drew controversy when ''[[Kotaku]]'' claimed executive producer [[Ron Rosenberg]] said rape was utilized as a means for the eponymous character's development.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=You'll 'Want To Protect' The New, Less Curvy Lara Croft|url=http://kotaku.com/5917400/youll-want-to-protect-the-new-less-curvy-lara-croft |publisher=[[Kotaku]] |accessdate=2013-11-18 |date=2012-06-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Crystal Dynamics]] denied that the scene depicted an attempted rape.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Tomb Raider Creators Are No Longer Referring to Game's Attempted 'Rape' Scene As an Attempted Rape Scene|url=http://kotaku.com/5918193/tomb-raider-creators-are-no-longer-referring-to-games-attempted-rape-scene-as-an-attempted-rape-scene |publisher=[[Kotaku]] |accessdate=2013-11-18 |date=2012-06-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Tomb Raider Creators Say 'Rape' Is Not A Word In Their Vocabulary|url=http://kotaku.com/5922228/tomb-raider-creators-say-rape-is-not-a-word-in-their-vocabulary |publisher=[[Kotaku]] |accessdate=2013-11-18 |date=2012-06-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=====Non-sexual violence=====
Violence in video games is a hotly debated topic; some sources condemned video games for promoting violence against women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |url=http://mediareporttowomen.com/issues/311.htm |title=Women's role in popular video games: Stripped down and killed off |journal=Media Report to Women |date=Winter 2003 |page=p. 1 |volume=31 |issue=1 |accessdate=2007-09-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; For example, the 2013 game [[Dead Island: Riptide]] generated controversy when the special "zombie bait" edition of the game included a statue of a torso of a busty, dismembered woman in a skimpy bikini.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.polygon.com/2013/1/15/3878810/dead-island-riptides-bloody-torso-statue-sparks-anger-shock | title=Dead Island Riptide's bloody torso statue sparks anger, confusion | publisher=Polygon.com | date=January 15, 2013 | accessdate=7 May 2014 | author=Brian Crecente}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Portrayal of men==
{{Expand Section | date=January 2014}}
Men are also often portrayed stereotypically in games. They tend to be shown as muscular and big. For instance, men in video games have chests that are about 2 inches (6%) larger, heads that are about 13 inches bigger, waists that are 5 inches wider, and hips that are 7 inches wider, than in reality.&lt;ref&gt;Martins, N., D.C. Williams, R.A. Ratan, and K. Harrison. 2011. "Virtual muscularity: A content analysis of male video game characters". ''Body Image.'' 8 (1): 43-51.&lt;/ref&gt; They are often characterized as overtly aggressive and violent.&lt;ref name="Dietz" /&gt;

[[GamesRadar]] writer David Houghton, writing in an article on sexism in video games, was highly critical of many stereotypes that came with male protagonists, outlining them as "the primeval hunter/gatherer type [with] arm-cripplingly ripped biceps, necks too muscley to turn, emotion dials stuck on “aggressive grimace” and a 50% lack of chest coverings."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gamesradar.com/are-video-games-really-sexist/?page=2|title=Are video games really sexist?|author=Houghton, David|publisher=[[GamesRadar]]|date=2012-06-23|accessdate=2014-02-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Jamin Warren on PBS Game/Show highlighted that video games could promote "unreasonable body expectations, or an inability to express emotion, or the pressure to 'man up' and be a leader." He also highlighted that the vast majority of characters who perform and experience violence in video games are men, while women and children are generally to be protected.&lt;ref name= GameShow&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mrActT_7X6U |title=Do Videogame Stereotypes Hurt Men? |accessdate=2014-09-29|date=2013-10-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Portrayal of LGBT characters==
{{main|LGBT themes in video games}}
[[Lesbian]], [[gay]], [[Bisexuality|bisexual]], and [[transgender]] ([[LGBT]]) characters have been depicted in video games since the 1980s. Common depictions include comical gender confusion, transgender characters, gay characters in fighting and action games, and gay romance in role-playing games.

In the [[history of video games]], LGBT content has been subject to changing rules and regulations, which are generally examples of [[heterosexism]], in that heterosexuality is normalized, while homosexuality is subject to additional [[censorship]] or ridicule. Companies [[Nintendo]], [[Sega]] and [[Maxis]] policed the content of games with content codes in which LGBT themes were toned down or erased.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Steltenpohl|first=Crystal|title=GLBT History in Video Games: 1990s|url=http://www.gamingbus.com/2012/06/12/glbt-history-video-games-1990s/|publisher=Gaming Bus|accessdate=9 May 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Phantasy"&gt;{{cite web|first=Mike|last=Ripplinger|year=2002|title=The Two Phantasy Stars  |url=http://www.camineet.net/camineet/theories/twophantasystars.asp|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20080204060641/http://www.camineet.net/camineet/theories/twophantasystars.asp|archivedate=2008-02-04|publisher=Camineet|accessdate=2010-01-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="ModtheSims"&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20100128041935/http://www.modthesims.info/download.php?t=388170 "Autonomous Romantic Socials - Same Sex"], by werismyki&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Sims3"&gt;[http://forum.thesims3.com/jforum/posts/list/30/191458.page "Why is My Town Gay?"], by Srikandi&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Sexual orientation]] and [[gender identity]] have served a significant role in some [[video game]]s, with the trend being toward greater visibility of LGBT identities.&lt;ref name="NeoSeeker"&gt;[http://www.neoseeker.com/news/11314-sunday-musing-homosexuality-in-video games/ "Homosexuality in Video Games"], by Lydia Sung&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Kotaku"&gt;[http://kotaku.com/5232808/how-not-to-address-homosexuality-in-gaming "How Not To Address Homosexuality In Gaming"], by Mike Fahey&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://i.joystiq.com/2007/02/26/gay-gamer-survey-results-with-large-hetero-inclusion/|title=Gay gamer survey results with large hetero inclusion|author=Alexander Sliwinski|publisher=[[Joystiq]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Speaking on the Ubisoft blog, Lucien Soulband, who is openly gay and was the writer for ''[[Far Cry 3: Blood Dragon]]'', said that openly gay or lesbian characters would not appear in video games for a long while as anything other than a one-off or something that was created through user choice as seen in the ''[[Mass Effect]]'' and ''[[Dragon Age]]'' games.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.polygon.com/2014/2/28/5456234/video-games-wont-feature-gay-protagonists-for-a-while-says-far-cry-3|title=Video games won't feature gay protagonists 'for a while,' says Far Cry 3 writer Lucien Soulban|author=Gera, Emily|publisher=[[Polygon (website)|Polygon]]|date=2014-02-28|accessdate=2014-02-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Effect of gender representation in games==

===Effect on attitudes towards gender ===
According to [[Christina Hoff Sommers]], there is no evidence that video games make men [[misogynist]]: "In fact, all the data we have suggest that millennial males—and these are people born and raised in 'Video Game Nation'—are far less prone to ... prejudices than previous generations."&lt;ref name=CHS&gt;{{cite web|author=Christina Hoff Sommers|title=Are video games sexist?|work=AEI|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9MxqSwzFy5w|date=2014-09-06|accessdate=2014-09-29||}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Effect on children===
Canadian non-profit [[MediaSmarts]] writes that "video games have the potential to influence how children perceive themselves and others", and despite their impact on the youth, "there is not a lot of research available in this area, and few of the existing studies stand up to critical examination. This lack of scrutiny means that we know very little about the effects that video games may have on children's development and socialization."&lt;ref name=MediaSmarts&gt;{{cite web|url=http://mediasmarts.ca/video-games/concerns-about-video-games |title=The Concerns About Video Games |accessdate=2014-09-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Dietz, video game characters have the potential to shape players’ perceptions of gender roles. Through social comparison processes, players learn societal expectations of appearances, behaviors and roles.&lt;ref name=Dietz&gt;{{cite journal|last=Dietz|first=Tracy|title=An Examination of Violence and Gender Role Portrayals in Video Games: Implications for Gender Socialization and Aggressive Behavior|journal=Sex Roles|year=1998|volume=38|pages=425–442|doi=10.1023/A:1018709905920|issue=5/6}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Girls may expect that they be dependent victims and that their responsibilities include maintaining beauty and sexual appeal, while boys may determine that their role is to protect and defend women.&lt;ref name="Dietz" /&gt;{{verification needed|date=March 2014}}

Thus, Dietz claims, the roles internalized by the child, including gender, become for the child, and later for the adult, a basis for other roles and for action. The gender roles internalized by young individuals have a significant impact upon their perspectives and the additional roles they assume in later life. Feminine and masculine symbols are supposed to become a part of a child’s identity.&lt;ref name="Dietz" /&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Video games|Gender studies|Feminism|Fictional characters}}
*[[LGBT characters in video games]]
*[[Portrayal of women in comics]]
*[[Sexual harassment in video gaming]]
*''[[Tropes vs. Women in Video Games]]''
{{Clear}}

==Footnotes==
{{reflist|33em}}

==References==
*{{cite book|last=Brown|first=Jeffrey A.|title=Dangerous Curves: Action Heroines, Gender, Fetishism, and Popular Culture|year=2011|publisher=University Press of Mississippi|location=Jackson|isbn=160473714X}}
*{{cite journal|last=Dickerman|first=Charles|title=Big Breast and Bad Guys: Depictions of Gender and Race in Video Games|journal=Journal of Creativity in Mental Health|year=2008|volume=3|issue=1|doi=10.1080/15401380801995076|last2=Christensen|first2=Jeff|last3=Kerl-Mcclain|first3=Stella Beatríz|pages=20}}
*{{cite journal |last=Jansz |first=Jeroen |author2=Martis, Raynel G.|title=The Lara Phenomenon: Powerful Female Characters in Video Games |journal=Sex Roles |location=New York |date=February 2007 |volume=56 |issue=3–4 |doi=10.1007/s11199-006-9158-0 |pages=141}}
*{{cite journal|first=Nicole|last=Martins|author2=Williams, Dmitri C. |author3=Ratan, Rabindra A. |author4= Harrison, Kristen |title=Virtual muscularity: a content analysis of male video game characters|journal=Body Image|date=3 May 2012|year=2011|doi=10.1016/j.bodyim.2010.10.002|volume=8|pages=43–51|pmid=21093394|issue=1}}

==External links==
*"[http://adanewmedia.org/category/issue-no-2/ Feminist Game Studies]", the second issue of ''Ada''

[[Category:Media issues]]
[[Category:Female characters in video games| ]]
[[Category:Video games featuring female protagonists| ]]
[[Category:Male characters in video games| ]]
[[Category:LGBT characters in video games| ]]
[[Category:Video game characters by gender]]
[[Category:Gender and video games]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>