<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20131120221334|582588374" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="34903083" pageid="34903083" ns="0" title="Gender representation in video games"><revisions><rev timestamp="2013-11-20T22:16:18Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{redirect|Sexism in video games|sexism towards female gamers|Sexual harassment in video gaming}}
The portrayal of men and women in [[video games]], as in other media, is a subject of research in [[gender studies]]. Men are featured much more often in games than women.&lt;ref name=Burgess&gt;{{cite journal|last=Burgess|first=Melinda C. R.|coauthors=Steven Paul Stermer &amp; Stephen R. Burgess|title=Sex, Lies, and Video Games: The Portrayal of Male and Female Characters on Video Game Covers|journal=Sex Roles|date=30|year=2007|month=06|pages=419–433|doi=10.1007/s11199-007-9250-0|volume=57|issue=5–6}}&lt;/ref&gt; The way men and women are portrayed in games often reflects [[gender role]]s or popular stereotypes, such as that of the [[damsel in distress]] for women.

==Portrayal of women==
The portrayal of women in video games is the subject of academic study and controversy. Recurring themes in both include the level of independence of female characters from their male counterparts, as well as their [[sexual objectification]] and [[sexualization]].

Early video games typically presented women in subsidiary roles, dependent on male protagonists. Many more recent games include women in active and self-reliant attitudes, but some have also increased the sexualized portrayal of women so as to appeal to a male audience.&lt;ref name="Tremblay2012"/&gt; In 2012, for instance, ''[[Dead or Alive (series)|Dead or Alive]]'' director, Yohei Shimbori, admitted the developers received complaints from fans who had played the [[Dead or Alive 5]] demo packaged with ''[[Ninja Gaiden 3]]''. According to Shimbori, "We actually got a lot of feedback from people who were playing it, saying, 'We want bigger breasts. Make the characters more like that.' That was kind of surprising."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Team Ninja learns to fear its fans|url=http://www.gamasutra.com/view/news/178358/Team_Ninja_learns_to_fear_its_fans.php#.UGVMR03A-RR |publisher=[[Gamasutra]] |accessdate=2013-03-15 |date=2012-09-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; Controversy is generated by [[Gender inequality#Cultural stereotypes|cultural stereotypes]], [[sexism]] and [[violence towards women]] portrayed in games.

===Women as non-player characters===
{{seealsocat|Video games featuring non-playable female protagonists}}
Female characters are often cast in a role of [[damsel in distress]] and their rescue as the final objective of game.&lt;ref name="Tremblay2012"&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.gamasutra.com/blogs/KaitlinTremblay/20120601/171613/Intro_to_Gender_Criticism_for_Gamers_From_Princess_Peach_to_Claire_Redfield_to_FemSheps.php?print=1 | title=Intro to Gender Criticism for Gamers: From Princess Peach, to Claire Redfield, to FemSheps. | publisher=[[Gamasutra]] | date=06/01/12 | accessdate=8 October 2013 | author=Kaitlin Tremblay}} &lt;blockquote&gt;In video games, the major stereotyped myths of women are typically the damsel in distress, hyper-sexualized villain (Sylvia Christel from No More Heroes) and the sexy/strong best friend (Tifa from Final Fantasy VII). [...] In all of these instances, the female character is, more likely than not, in love with the male protagonist or trying desperately to bang him. &lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://kotaku.com/shigeru-miyamoto-and-the-damsel-in-distress-520259897 | title=Shigeru Miyamoto and the Damsel In Distress | publisher=[[Kotaku]] | date=6/20/13 | accessdate=8 October 2013 | author=Stephen Totilo}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Princess Zelda]] in the early ''[[The Legend of Zelda]]'' series and [[Princess Peach]] through much of the ''[[Mario (series)|Mario]]'' series are [[wikt:paradigm|paradigmatic]] examples. Both of them, however, became playable in the later games of their series.

A number of games will feature a female character as an ally or [[sidekick]] to the male hero. Some of them, like [[Ada Wong]] and [[Mona Sax]], were turned into [[player character]]s in later instances of their series. [[Alyx Vance]], a supporting protagonist of ''[[Half-Life 2]]'', was praised for her "stinging personality" and intelligence, developing a close bond with the player without simply being "eye candy".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ugo.com/games/video-game-hotties/?cur=alyx-vance&amp;morepics=17 Top 50 Videogame Hotties]. [[UGO.com]]. Retrieved on 2008-12-14&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ugo.com/games/gaming-girls/?cur=alyx-vance Top 11 Girls of Gaming]. [[UGO.com]]. Retrieved on 2008-12-28&lt;/ref&gt;

Some games feature female characters as major enemies or even main villains.&lt;ref name="Tremblay2012"/&gt; The [[Dark Queen (Battletoads)|Dark Queen]] in the ''[[Battletoads]]'' series is one of the first major female villains in video games.&lt;ref&gt;Steven A. Schwartz, Janet Schwartz, ''The Parent's Guide to Video Games'', Prima Pub., 1994 (p.8)&lt;/ref&gt; [[SHODAN]], an artificial intelligence with a female voice and a female face, was the main villain of the game ''[[System Shock]]'', praised as one of the most recognizable female characters in gaming.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gamespot.com/features/tenspot_females/page9.html TenSpot: Ten Best Female Characters]. GameSpot. Retrieved on 19 November 2013&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, [[GLaDOS]], an insane computer with a female voice, was widely praised by game critics and public as one of the best new characters of the decade.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=The 25 best new characters of the decade |url=http://www.gamesradar.com/f/the-25-best-new-characters-of-the-decade/a-20091221171910974007 |publisher=[[GamesRadar]] |accessdate=2010-01-04 |date=2009-12-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another recognized female villain is [[Characters of Final Fantasy VIII#Ultimecia|Ultimecia]], the main antagonist in ''[[Final Fantasy VIII]]''. At [[Penny Arcade Expo|PAX]] Prime 2013, she was voted among the best female antagonists in video gaming history.&lt;ref name="ForbesPAXreport"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.forbes.com/sites/davidewalt/2013/08/31/are-these-the-top-women-game-characters-of-all-time/|title=Are These The Top Women Game Characters of All Time?|last=Ewalt|first=David M.|publisher=''[[Forbes]]''|date=2013-08-31|accessdate=2013-10-07|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20131031081428/http://www.forbes.com/sites/davidewalt/2013/08/31/are-these-the-top-women-game-characters-of-all-time/ |archivedate=2013-10-31 |deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Women as player characters===
{{seealsocat|Female characters in video games|Video games featuring female protagonists}}

According to data gathered by [[Electronic Entertainment Design and Research]] (EEDAR), few video games have exclusively female heroes. This is in part because, according to EEDAR, "there's a sense in the industry that games with female heroes won’t sell", which [[Penny Arcade]] attributed in part to these games receiving much less marketing budget as games with male heroes.&lt;ref name="PAR 21 November 2012"&gt;{{cite news|last=Kuchera|first=Ben|title=Games with exclusively female heroes don’t sell (because publishers don’t support them)|url=http://penny-arcade.com/report/editorial-article/games-with-female-heroes-dont-sell-because-publishers-dont-support-them|accessdate=21 November 2012|newspaper=Penny Arcade Report|date=21 November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2013, for instance, [[Epic Games]] was lauded for the inclusion and portrayal of Anya and Samantha Byrne in ''[[Gears of War 3]]'', the series' first playable female characters.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Evans-Thirwell|first=Edwin|title=Epic: a female Gears of War star would be "tough to justify"|url=http://www.oxm.co.uk/50193/epic-a-female-gears-of-war-star-would-be-tough-to-justify/|accessdate=15 March 2013|newspaper=The Official Xbox Magazine|date=13 February 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Despite the positive response from female players who found her empowering, Epic Games believes that the video game market would not support a ''[[Gears of War]]'' title with women as the central protagonists, although they later clarified that this did not rule out a female protagonist at some point in the future.&lt;ref name= "GoWwomen"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://kotaku.com/5984112/its-too-bad-epic-games-considers-female-protagonists-tough-to-justify-in-gears-of-war|title=It's Too Bad Epic Games Considers Female Protagonists Tough To Justify In Gears of War [UPDATE]|author=Hernandez, Patricia|publisher=[[Kotaku]]|date=2011-02-15|accessdate=2013-11-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; During a talk at [[Game Developers Conference|GCD Next 2013]], Ubisoft Quebec's narrative designer, Jill Murry, pointed out that the basic reason for not putting women in leading roles in video games, because of a lack of real and historical examples, was invalid, citing historic and contemporary examples of strong or powerful women.&lt;ref name= "GDC Next"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gamasutra.com/view/news/204101/Want_interesting_women_in_video_games_There_are_binders_full_of_them.php|title=Want interesting women in video games? There are binders full of them|author=Ligman, Kris|publisher=[[Gamasutra]]|date=2013-11-06|accessdate=2013-11-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In a sample of 669 action, shooter, and role-playing games selected by EEDAR in 2012, only 24 (4%) had an exclusively female protagonist, and 300 (45%) provided the option of selecting one. Examining the sales data and review scores of these games, EEDAR found that the games that included the option of selecting a female hero obtained better scores, but the ones with male-only protagonists sold better than the others. However, games with a female-only protagonist had, on average, only 50% of the marketing budget of female-optional games, and 40% of the marketing budget of games with male-only protagonists.&lt;ref name="PAR 21 November 2012" /&gt; An example of this continued trend is found in ''[[Remember Me (video game)|Remember Me]]'', a 2013 video game featuring a mixed-race female protagonist.&lt;ref name="CAVGinterview"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.computerandvideogames.com/380545/remember-me-interview-can-capcoms-new-ip-prove-everyone-wrong/|title=Interview: Can Remember Me prove everyone wrong?|author=Rob Crossley|publisher=ComputerAndVideoGames.com|date=27-Nov-2012|accessdate=15-05-2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Because of these factors, many potential publishers were unwilling to take the game.&lt;ref name="RememberInspiration"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.penny-arcade.com/report/article/remember-mes-surprising-connection-to-facebook-and-why-its-protagonist-had|title=How Facebook inspired Remember Me to drop global warming, and why its protagonist had to be a woman|author=Sophie Prell|publisher=The Penny Arcade Report|date=3/18/13|accessdate=14-05-2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Nonetheless, a trend for women to appear as the sole [[protagonist]] in modern games has been identified.&lt;ref&gt;Jansz and Martis (2007), p. 141&lt;/ref&gt; [[Samus Aran]], the heroine of the ''[[Metroid]]'' franchise, is cited as a [[wikt:trailblazer|trailblazer]]. Players were unaware that Samus was a woman until the end of [[Metroid (video game)|the first ''Metroid'' game]] (1986), when she takes off the helmet of the armored suit that hides her sex during the game. Thus, her female characteristics are not emphasized over her viability as a character and are ultimately incidental in the plot of the series.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.1up.com/do/feature?cId=3152658 |title=One Girl vs. the Galaxy - The Woman Inside the Suit |publisher=[[1UP.com]] |author=Nadia Oxford |date=2006-08-07 |accessdate=2007-07-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although Samus is often cited as "the first playable human female character in a mainstream videogame",&lt;ref name="Guinness2013"&gt;{{cite book | title=Guinness World Records 2013: Gamer's Edition | publisher=Guinness World Records Ltd | authorlink=Feature: Girl Power-Up | year=2012 | page=154 | isbn=9781904994954}}&lt;/ref&gt; other earlier games featured human female characters; in particular Toby Masuyo ("Kissy") from [[Namco]]'s [[Baraduke|Alien Sector]] is a playable female human spacewoman similar to Samus, appearing one year earlier than Metroid.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.hardcoregaming101.net/namcoxcapcom/namcoxcapcom2.htm#tobymasuyo | title=Obscure Namco characters | publisher=Hardcore Gaming 101 | accessdate=6 October 2013 | author=Kurt Kalata}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.nintendolife.com/news/2009/10/nintendo_download_13_14_october_2009_japan | title=Nintendo Download: 13-14 October 2009 (Japan) | publisher=nintendolife.com | accessdate=6 October 2013 | author=Sean Aaron}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Lara Croft]] is among the best-known strong, fictional women in a variety of media that do not depend on men to achieve heroic deeds. The reception of their independence as action heroines and their eroticized portrayal has been ambivalent.&lt;ref name="taylor"&gt;{{cite book | last1 = Egenfeldt-Nielsen | first1 = Simon | last2 = Smith | first2 = Jonas Heide | last3 = Pajares Tosca | first3 = Susana | title = Understanding video games: the essential introduction | chapter = Player culture | publisher = Taylor &amp; Francis | year = 2008 | page = 163 | url = http://books.google.com/?id=31XHdVXlbt0C&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;dq=%22april%20ryan%22&amp;pg=PA163#v=onepage&amp;q=%22april%20ryan%22&amp;f=false | accessdate = 2011-07-03 | isbn = 978-0-415-97721-0 | quote = "Helen Kennedy [...] summarizes these arguments, and Lara Croft's ambivalent role as both an action heroine [...], and an eroticized object of the male gaze with a great deal of voyeuristic appeal".}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[April Ryan]], protagonist of ''[[The Longest Journey]]'', has been compared to Lara Croft in that respect, as she shows less prominent physical feminine attributes than Lara but more feminine psychological traits, as contrasted with Lara's masculine connotations like aggressiveness and force.&lt;ref name="merete"&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.csi.ensmp.fr/WebCSI/4S/download/download_page.php?file=lie.pdf | title = Lara Croft and her sisters | accessdate = 2011-07-03 | last = Lie | first = Merete | publisher = Norwegian University of Science and Technology | quote = "She is attractive, but no sex bomb"  "April may, however, appear as more feminine because even if she is tough and brave, she is depicted as both sensitive and vain"}}&lt;/ref&gt; Contrarily, [[Jade (Beyond Good &amp; Evil)|Jade]], the protagonist of ''[[Beyond Good &amp; Evil]]'', was widely recognized as a strong and confident female character lacking any overt sexualisation&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.thumbbandits.com/Oakley04.asp |title=Jade (Rebel with a Cause) |publisher=thumbbandits.com}}{{dead link|date=June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Chell (Portal)|Chell]], the main character of ''[[Portal (video game)|Portal]]'' was noted for the fact that she was neither in third-person or sexualised unlike most female characters in first-person shooters.&lt;ref name="Subversive"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.gamesradar.com/f/portal-is-the-most-subversive-game-ever/a-20071207115329881080 |title=Portal is the most subversive game ever |author=Joe McNeilly |date=7 December 2007 |work=[[GamesRadar]] |accessdate=27 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another example of a non-sexualised female character is ''Remember Me''{{'}}s protagonist Nilin. Her creator, Jean-Max Moris, stated: "You have to avoid the pitfalls of making [the character] just a damsel in distress or a sex bomb, because this is what you think would appeal most to the hordes of men that constitute your fan base."&lt;ref name="NilinConcept"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.vg247.com/2013/04/16/remember-me-dev-wanted-to-respect-gamers-with-a-strong-female-protagonist/|title=Remember Me dev wanted to "respect" gamers with a strong female protagonist|author=Brenna Hillier|publisher=VG24/7|date=April 16, 2013|accessdate=14-05-2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Objectification and sexualization===
{{See also|List of adult video games}}

Female video game characters tend to suffer from a particularly extreme manifestation of the [[gaze|male gaze]]&lt;ref name="maleprivilege"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://kotaku.com/5868595/nerds-and-male-privilege|title=Nerds and Male Privilege|author=Harris O'Malley|publisher=Kotaku}}&lt;/ref&gt; — even when not serving the male characters (be it as a [[plot device]], [[Damsel-in-distress|reward]], or something else), "the woman" will commonly find herself serving the male players through the systematic enforcement of [[sex appeal]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gamesradar.com/pc/f/top-20-overlooked-game-babes/a-20080708105437443047 Top 20 Overlooked Game Babes], [[GamesRadar]], July 8, 2008&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.complex.com/video-games/2010/11/the-50-hottest-women-in-video-games/ The 50 Hottest Women In Video Game], ''[[Complex (magazine)|Complex]]'', November 8, 2010&lt;/ref&gt; with rarely much regard to how gratuitous, out-of-place or [[out-of-character]] such appeal might be (e.g. [[high heels]] in armed combat). Another common feature often used for sex appeal is the use of "jiggle physics", when a female character's large breasts bounce, sway, and make various other random movements. [[Gender inequality#Gendered media|Like with many other media]], complaints have been made regarding a perceptible underlying implication that there is quite simply no point for a female character to even ''exist'' if her presence does not in some way entail the sexual pleasure of male consumers.

Since her introduction in 1996, the character of [[Lara Croft]] from the ''[[Tomb Raider]]'' series in particular has been criticized for her unrealistic breast size; Lara was claimed to personify "an ongoing culture clash over gender, sexuality, empowerment, and objectification."&lt;ref name="gettingthegirl"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.1up.com/do/feature?cId=3137700 |author=Zoe Flower |title=Getting the Girl: The myths, misconceptions, and misdemeanors of females in games |publisher=[[1UP.com]] |accessdate=2007-09-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the game's creators maintain that she was not designed with marketing in mind, and have claimed to be rather surprised at her pinup-style adoration;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Lara Croft, the Bit Girl |author=N'gai Croal and Jane Hughes |publisher=[[Newsweek]] |date=1997-11-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; in fact, it has been claimed that this [[fandom]] objectification is harmful to the character (in ''[[Tomb Raider: Legend]]'', Lara underwent a radical redesign, ostensibly to make her less sexualized&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title= Lara's curves reduced to appeal to female gamers |date=2005-05-21 |publisher=[[The Sydney Morning Herald]] |url=http://www.smh.com.au/news/World/Real-appeal/2005/05/21/1116533572111.html |accessdate=2007-07-09}}{{dead link|date=June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://film.guardian.co.uk/features/featurepages/0,,506934,00.html |title=The extraordinary life of Lara Croft |publisher=The Guardian |date=2001-06-15 |accessdate=2007-07-09 | location=London | first=Steven | last=Poole}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.gamedaily.com/games/tomb-raider-anniversary/playstation-2/game-features/the-man-behind-lara/5588/66813/ |title=The Man Behind Lara |publisher=[[GameDaily]] |author=Robin Yang |accessdate=2007-07-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Similarly, ''[[Dead or Alive Xtreme Beach Volleyball]]'' has been criticized as being more about [[wikt:eye candy|eye candy]] than it is about the sport of [[volleyball]], having been created merely for the purpose of displaying women's breasts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.gamecritics.com/review/doaxvolleyball/main.php | title=Dead or Alive: Xtreme Beach Volleyball |author=Brad Gallaway |publisher=GameCritics.com |date=2003-01-29 |accessdate=2006-12-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; In two sequels of fighting games [[Soul Calibur]] and [[Tekken]] that take place several years after the original issue, recurring male characters were allowed to age but all female characters were kept the same age or replaced by their daughters.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.starcitygames.com/magic/misc/22786_To_My_Someday_Daughter.html|author=Geordie Tait|title=To My Someday Daughter}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Sexualization is also an issue in game advertising. It may feature sexualized content that is not present in the games themselves. For instance, an advertisement for an add-on to the game ''[[Civilization IV]]'' featured a large-breasted [[Statue of Liberty]] with the text "CIV GOES BIG", although the game contains nothing overtly sexual.&lt;ref name="Dickerman" /&gt;

In their 2005 study, Dill and Thill distinguish three major stereotypical depictions of women in gaming: (1) sexualized, (2) scantily clad, and (3) a vision of beauty.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Dill|first=Karen E.|coauthors=Thill K. P.|title=Video Game Characters and the Socialization of Gender Roles: Young People’s Perceptions Mirror Sexist Media Depictions|journal=Sex Roles|date=2007|volume=57|pages=851–864}}&lt;/ref&gt; The study revealed that over 80% of women in video games represented one of these depictions. More than one quarter of female characters embodied all of the three stereotypical categories at once. Dill and Thill also note that another prevalent theme with which women were depicted was a combination of aggression and sex, referred to as ''eroticized aggression''.

==== {{anchor|Women in scanty armor}}Women in scanty armor ====
A recurrent representation of [[Women in speculative fiction|women in fantasy setting]]s, originating in the [[1960s]], is the [[woman warrior]] dressed in unrealistically scanty armor.&lt;ref name="Adweek 4 June 2013"&gt;{{cite news|last=Griner|first=David|title=Will the Fantasy Genre Ever Grow Up and Ditch the Chainmail Bikini? Industry bulletin's cover sets off firestorm|url=http://www.adweek.com/adfreak/will-fantasy-genre-ever-grow-and-ditch-chainmail-bikini-150004|accessdate=7 June 2013|newspaper=[[Adweek]]|date=4 June 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; They feature armor designs which have been described by such terms as [[Bikini in popular culture|chainmail bikinis]], largely consisting of small decorative plaques that reveal large portions of the body skin to the weather and that expose vital organs, thus being completely noneffective as protection.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://madartlab.com/2011/12/14/fantasy-armor-and-lady-bits/|title=Fantasy armor and lady bits|publisher=MadArtLab.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; The prevalence of this portrayal is an instance of the common sexualization of women in the [[geek culture]] including video games, comic and movies.&lt;ref name="maleprivilege"/&gt; In reaction to this, the art blog "Women Fighters in Reasonable Armor"&lt;ref name="realisticarmor"&gt;[http://womenfighters.tumblr.com/ Women Fighters in Reasonable Armor]&lt;/ref&gt; compiles depictions of women fighters wearing realistic armor.&lt;ref name="io9realistic"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://io9.com/5834665/our-new-favorite-tumblr-women-fighters-in-reasonable-armor|title=Women Fighters in Reasonable Armor: An Idea Whose Time Has Come|author=Charlie Jane Anders|publisher=[[io9]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Depiction of violence against women===

====Studies====
One investigation conducted at Lenior-Rhyne College examined the link between playing violent video games containing sexualized game characters and violence against women. Researchers hypothesized that being exposed to sexualized video game avatars (i.e. macho men, scantily-clad women) would make participants more condoning of sexual harassment and rape. Two research questions were also devised. The first of which speculated if the sex of the participants would shape their views towards sexual harassment and how they would react upon viewing the sexualized video game avatars. The second research question pondered how the sex of participants would influence their attitudes towards rape.

The experiment had one hundred and eighty one participants all of which were randomly assigned to either an experimental or control group. Individuals in the experimental group were given the task of viewing a [[PowerPoint]] presentation containing images of sexualized video game characters from games such as ''[[Resident Evil]]'', ''[[Gears of War]]'', and so on. In the control group, students were exposed to images of highly-respected individuals (US senators and congresspersons) such as Senator [[Mary Landrieu]]. Afterwards, both groups read about an actual account of sexual harassment that happened to a female student, taken from ''The Silent Treatment'' by [[Naomi Wolf]].

The results of the investigation supported hypothesis one, that participants would have an altered view on sexual harassment after short-term exposure to sexualized media content. Specifically, males were found to be more tolerant of the real-life case scenario of sexual harassment after they were exposed to the sexualized video game avatars. There was not sufficient evidence to support that the gender of the participants was the only significant factor in this analysis. Interestingly, as males became more tolerant of sexual harassment, females that viewed the same demeaning, stereotyped images of women became less tolerant. Even compared to the females that viewed images of respected and professional political figures, the females that viewed demeaning ones still had a lower tolerance for sexual harassment. It seems that, for these females, seeing women under-represented and overtly sexualized motivates them to advocate for the just treatment of women. In addition to these findings, a significant link between long-term exposure to violent video games and pro-violence attitudes towards women were found.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Dill|first=Karen E.|coauthors=Brown, Brian P.; Collins, Michael A.|title=Effects of exposure to sex-stereotyped video game characters on tolerance of sexual harassment|journal=Journal of Experimental Social Psychology|date=NaN undefined NaN|volume=44|issue=5|pages=1402–1408|doi=10.1016/j.jesp.2008.06.002}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to another study by Dietz, &lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Dietz|first=T. L.|title=An examination of violence and gender role portrayals in video games: Implications for gender socialization and aggressive behavior.|journal=Sex Roles|date=1998|volume=38|pages=425–442}}&lt;/ref&gt; about one fifth of analyzed games portrayed violence against women.

====Rape====
The 1982 game ''[[Custer's Revenge]]'' was first noted for containing elements of [[rape]] and some Native American groups and the [[National Organization for Women]] have criticised this as well as alleged [[racism]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://archive.gamespy.com/top10/december02/shame/index4.shtml |title=Top Ten Shameful Games: 1. Custer's Revenge (Atari 2600) |publisher=[[GameSpy]] |date=2002-12-31 |accessdate=2007-07-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; More recently, major controversies were sparked by some Japanese games such as ''[[RapeLay]]'' and ''[[Battle Raper]]''.

The 2013 reboot of ''[[Tomb Raider]]'' series drew controversy with a depiction of an attempted rape on its main protagonist. Executive producer [[Ron Rosenberg]] claimed rape was utilized as means of her "evolution" and character development.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=You'll 'Want To Protect' The New, Less Curvy Lara Croft|url=http://kotaku.com/5917400/youll-want-to-protect-the-new-less-curvy-lara-croft |publisher=[[Kotaku]] |accessdate=2013-11-18 |date=2012-06-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Crystal Dynamics]] later denied that the scene depicted an attempted rape, contradicting Rosenberg's earlier statement. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Tomb Raider Creators Are No Longer Referring to Game's Attempted 'Rape' Scene As an Attempted Rape Scene|url=http://kotaku.com/5918193/tomb-raider-creators-are-no-longer-referring-to-games-attempted-rape-scene-as-an-attempted-rape-scene |publisher=[[Kotaku]] |accessdate=2013-11-18 |date=2012-06-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Tomb Raider Creators Say 'Rape' Is Not A Word In Their Vocabulary|url=http://kotaku.com/5922228/tomb-raider-creators-say-rape-is-not-a-word-in-their-vocabulary |publisher=[[Kotaku]] |accessdate=2013-11-18 |date=2012-06-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Other violence====
Violence in video games is a hotly debated topic, especially with regards to the ''[[Grand Theft Auto (series)|Grand Theft Auto]]'' series; however, some sources have specifically condemned the series and similar games for promoting violence against women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |url=http://mediareporttowomen.com/issues/311.htm |title=Women's role in popular video games: Stripped down and killed off |journal=Media Report to Women |month=Winter |year=2003 |page=p. 1 |volume=31 |issue=1 |accessdate=2007-09-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Reactions===
{{see also|Women and video games}}
[[Ubisoft]] has formed a group of female gamers called the [[Frag Dolls]]; the intent is to create "role models for a whole legion of girls out there who may have been too intimidated to play games online - or even play at all".&lt;ref name="gettingthegirl"/&gt; Some game companies have attempted to make their games more "family friendly", allegedly to persuade female consumers to buy them for their male relatives or friends,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=Jennifer Kulpa |title=PC games are becoming kinder, gentler to attract females |url=http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m3374/is_8_23/ai_76335062 |publisher=Drug Store News |date=2001-06-25 |accessdate=2007-09-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; whereas some franchises, such as  ''[[Mass Effect]]'', reacted to studies suggesting over half of gamers are female&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.prnewswire.com/news-releases/new-study-gets-into-the-minds-of-women-who-game-online-134128328.html |title=New Study Gets Into the Minds of Women Who Game Online - SEATTLE, Nov. 18, 2011 /PRNewswire/ |location=Washington |publisher=Prnewswire.com |date= |accessdate=2012-08-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; by allowing complete customisation of the protagonist character, up to and including gender. ''Mass Effect'' in particular received praise for its minimal adapting of both script and armour for the different genders, allowing portrayal of a, "remarkably serious and capable-looking woman," which has been welcomed by some female gamers as an indication the gaming market is beginning to lose its record of using women solely to appeal to male gamers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Cook |first=Sarah |url=http://www.badreputation.org.uk/2012/01/09/found-feminism-mass-effect-3-pre-order-box/ |title=Found Feminism: Mass Effect 3 Pre-order Box |publisher=Bad Reputation |date= |accessdate=2012-08-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Portrayal of men==
Video games tend to show men as big in all aspects. They are portrayed as being tall, having larger heads, and more [[muscle]]s than real men. For instance, men in video games have [[chest]]s that are about 2 inches (6%) larger than in reality, heads that are about 13 inches bigger, waists that are 5 inches wider, and hips that are 7 inches wider.&lt;ref&gt;Martins, N., D.C. Williams, R.A. Ratan, and K. Harrison. 2011. "Virtual muscularity: A content analysis of male video game characters". ''Body Image.'' 8 (1): 43-51.&lt;/ref&gt;

Game heroes or protagonists are most often male and carry large weapons. The main villain is most often either a monster or a human man.&lt;ref name=Dickerman /&gt;

== Portrayal of LGBT characters ==
{{main|LGBT themes in video games}}
[[Lesbian]], [[gay]], [[Bisexuality|bisexual]], and [[transgender]] ([[LGBT]]) characters have been depicted in video games since the 1980s. Common depictions include comical gender confusion, transgender characters, gay characters in fighting and action games, and gay romance in role-playing games.

In the [[history of video games]], LGBT content has been subject to changing rules and regulations, which are generally examples of [[heterosexism]], in that heterosexuality is normalized, while homosexuality is subject to additional [[censorship]] or ridicule. Companies [[Nintendo]], [[Sega]] and [[Maxis]] policed the content of games with content codes in which LGBT themes were toned down or erased.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Steltenpohl|first=Crystal|title=GLBT History in Video Games: 1990s|url=http://www.gamingbus.com/2012/06/12/glbt-history-video-games-1990s/|publisher=Gaming Bus|accessdate=9 May 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Phantasy"&gt;{{cite web|first=Mike|last=Ripplinger|year=2002|title=The Two Phantasy Stars  |url=http://www.camineet.net/camineet/theories/twophantasystars.asp|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20080204060641/http://www.camineet.net/camineet/theories/twophantasystars.asp|archivedate=2008-02-04|publisher=Camineet|accessdate=2010-01-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="ModtheSims"&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20100128041935/http://www.modthesims.info/download.php?t=388170 "Autonomous Romantic Socials - Same Sex"], by werismyki&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Sims3"&gt;[http://forum.thesims3.com/jforum/posts/list/30/191458.page "Why is My Town Gay?"], by Srikandi&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Sexual orientation]] and [[gender identity]] have served a significant role in some [[video game]]s, with the trend being toward greater visibility of LGBT identities.&lt;ref name="NeoSeeker"&gt;[http://www.neoseeker.com/news/11314-sunday-musing-homosexuality-in-video games/ "Homosexuality in Video Games"], by Lydia Sung&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Kotaku"&gt;[http://kotaku.com/5232808/how-not-to-address-homosexuality-in-gaming "How Not To Address Homosexuality In Gaming"], by Mike Fahey&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://i.joystiq.com/2007/02/26/gay-gamer-survey-results-with-large-hetero-inclusion/|title=Gay gamer survey results with large hetero inclusion|author=Alexander Sliwinski|publisher=Joystiq}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Effect of gender representation in games==

===Impact on children===
Video game characters have the potential to shape players’ perceptions of gender roles. Through social comparison processes, players learn societal expectations of appearances, behaviors and roles.&lt;ref name=Dietz&gt;{{cite journal|last=Dietz|first=Tracy|title=An Examination of Violence and Gender Role Portrayals in Video Games: Implications for Gender Socialization and Aggressive Behavior|journal=Sex Roles|year=1998|volume=38|pages=425–442|doi=10.1023/A:1018709905920|issue=5/6}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Girls may expect that they will continue to be victims and needy and that their responsibilities include maintaining beauty and sexual appeal while boys may determine that their role is to protect and defend women and to possess them even through the use of violence.&lt;ref name="Dietz" /&gt;

Thus, the roles internalized by the child, including gender, become for the child, and later for the adult, a basis for other roles and for action. The gender role that is internalized by the individual when she or he is young has a significant impact upon the perspective of that individual and the additional roles she or he assumes in later life. Feminine and masculine symbols become a part of a child’s identity. Boys and girls may come to see Barbie as a feminine symbol and [[Spider-Man]] as a [[Maculinity|masculine symbol]].&lt;ref name="Dietz" /&gt;

Men are characterized as either good guys or bad guys and aggressive behavior is exhibited and expected in either of these roles. At the same time, women are depicted in stereotypical roles that typically pertain to sexuality in which the woman focuses upon beauty/physical attractiveness and traditional family roles.&lt;ref name="Dietz" /&gt;

Parents fear the violent video games are influencing their children's view about violence. Studies have been conducted to proof the effects of violent video games on children and adolescents. Several of the studies apply [[Bandura Study|Bandura's Social Modeling Theory]], which describes how individuals can learn behaviors merely by watching a model commit a behavior and be rewarded for it. With video games, the model is the main character, who gets rewarded with more points or advancement in the story, when he takes part in a violent act. There is a positive correlation, but research does not necessarily support the hypothesis that violent video games will cause increased levels of aggression.&lt;ref name=Dickerman&gt;Dickerman (2008)&lt;/ref&gt;

===Impact on adults===
====Females====
Women continuously exposed to extreme versions of the modern "ideal woman” (large breasted and slender, with longer-than-normal legs and breasts that defy gravity) are reported to have increased levels of body dissatisfaction, negative moods and [[Depression (mood)|depression]], and lower levels of [[self-esteem]] and [[self-worth]].&lt;ref&gt;http://web.ebscohost.com/ehost/pdfviewer/pdfviewer?sid=4e4f4fa6-d99b-4e09-87df-431e15c70ac2%40sessionmgr114&amp;vid=9&amp;hid=123&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, studies have found that females playing a highly sexualized characters, compared to a condition featuring no video game play, resulted in negative feelings of self-efficacy. The influence of the media on young women’s body image have led researchers to speculate that media might also play an important role in negative behaviors such as eating disorders. &lt;ref&gt;http://web.ebscohost.com/ehost/pdfviewer/pdfviewer?sid=4e4f4fa6-d99b-4e09-87df-431e15c70ac2%40sessionmgr114&amp;vid=5&amp;hid=123&lt;/ref&gt;

====Males====
Males are affected by media images as well. Men who view images of “the ideal male”  (muscular with very little body fat) have been reported to  have more negative body images and are more likely to try to gain weight/muscle mass or use steroids, as well as, more recently, increased risk of suffering from eating disorders.&lt;ref&gt;Miller, Monica K., and Alicia Summers. 2007. "Gender Differences in Video Game Characters' Roles, Appearances, and Attire as Portrayed in Video Game Magazines". ''Sex Roles''. 57 (9/10): 733-42.&lt;/ref&gt; Males who play games featuring highly sexualized characters reported less favorable attitudes towards female's cognitive capabilities, compared to those who don't.&lt;ref&gt;http://web.ebscohost.com/ehost/pdfviewer/pdfviewer?sid=4e4f4fa6-d99b-4e09-87df-431e15c70ac2%40sessionmgr114&amp;vid=5&amp;hid=123&lt;/ref&gt;Also, males who participated in games in which female characters were portrayed as sexual objects were then primed with thoughts of females as sex objects and are at a increased at self-reported tendency to sexually harass. &lt;ref&gt;http://web.ebscohost.com/ehost/pdfviewer/pdfviewer?sid=4e4f4fa6-d99b-4e09-87df-431e15c70ac2%40sessionmgr114&amp;vid=8&amp;hid=123&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Video games|Gender studies|Feminism|Fictional characters}}
*[[LGBT characters in video games]]
*[[Portrayal of women in comics]]
*[[Sexual harassment in video gaming]]
*''[[Tropes vs. Women in Video Games]]''
{{Clear}}

==Footnotes==
{{reflist|33em}}

==References==
*{{cite book|last=Brown|first=Jeffrey A.|title=Dangerous Curves: Action Heroines, Gender, Fetishism, and Popular Culture|year=2011|publisher=University Press of Mississippi|location=Jackson|isbn=160473714X}}
*{{cite journal|last=Dickerman|first=Charles|title=Big Breast and Bad Guys: Depictions of Gender and Race in Video Games|journal=Journal of Creativity in Mental Health|year=2008|volume=3|issue=1|doi=10.1080/15401380801995076|last2=Christensen|first2=Jeff|last3=Kerl-Mcclain|first3=Stella Beatríz|pages=20}}
*{{cite journal |last=Jansz |first=Jeroen |coauthors=Martis, Raynel G.|title=The Lara Phenomenon: Powerful Female Characters in Video Games |journal=Sex Roles |location=New York |month=February |year=2007 |volume=56 |issue=3–4 |doi=10.1007/s11199-006-9158-0 |pages=141}}
*{{cite journal|first=Nicole|last=Martins|coauthors=Williams, Dmitri C.; Ratan, Rabindra A.; Harrison, Kristen|title=Virtual muscularity: a content analysis of male video game characters|journal=Body Image|date=3 May 2012|year=2011|doi=10.1016/j.bodyim.2010.10.002|volume=8|pages=43–51|pmid=21093394|issue=1}}

==External links==
*"[http://adanewmedia.org/category/issue-no-2/ Feminist Game Studies]", the second issue of ''Ada''

[[Category:Gender and entertainment]]
[[Category:Media issues]]
[[Category:Female characters in video games| ]]
[[Category:Video games featuring female protagonists| ]]
[[Category:Male characters in video games| ]]
[[Category:LGBT characters in video games| ]]
[[Category:Video game characters by gender]]
[[Category:Video game culture]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>