<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20051111104820|28015589" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="2866512" pageid="2866512" ns="0" title="Anti-Masonry"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-11-11T15:28:52Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{mergefrom|Persecution of Freemasons}}

'''Anti-Freemasonry''' (alternatively called '''anti-masonry''') is hostility towards or [[prejudice]] against [[Freemasonry|Freemason]]s, which can range from individual [[hatred]] to institutionalized, violent [[persecution]]. The highly explicit [[ideology]] of [[Adolf Hitler]]'s [[National Socialism|Nazism]] was the most extreme historical example of the phenomenon. Anti-Freemasonry has historically taken different forms; in contemporary society anti-Freemasonry is common amongst new-age Christian sects or cults and conspiracy theorists.

The basis of most anti-masonic xenophobia is the fact that its rituals and modes of recognition are not publicised, but kept amongst its members exclusively.  Therefore the lack of understanding leads non-members to 'fill in the gaps' with theory often more than fact.

Because of the normally-secret nature of its rituals and activities, Freemasonry has long been suspected by both church and state of engaging in subversive activities.  What follows is some information on various claims made against the institution of Freemasonry, and various incidents involving or purporting to involve Masons in a negative manner.

==Historical Anti-Freemasonry advocates==

In 1736 the Roman Catholic Church began to investigate a Masonic Lodge in [[Florence]], [[Italy]]. The Lodge in question was condemned by the Chief [[Inquisitor]] in Rome on the 25th June 1737, and on the 9th May 1739 a physician in Florence by the name of Tommaso Crudeli as taken into custody and questioned about his masonic affiliation. The questioning was started on the 10th August 1739, and he was tortured in order to make him reveal the "secrets" of Freemasonry. After torture, Tommaso Crudeli was imprisoned and not released until April 1741. His health ruined by the torture and imprisionment, Tommaso Crudeli died on 27th January 1745{{ref|Crudeli}}

One of the oldest recorded cases of persecution of Freemasons involves John Custos, a native of Switzerland living in England. Arrested by the Inquisition in [[Portugal]], where he was traveling on business, he was tortured and questioned over a period of time before he was sentenced to the galleys. John Coustos was released in 1744 as a result of the intercession of George II of England. After his release and return to England, John Coustos wrote a book detailing his experiences in the hands of the Inquisition.{{ref|Coustos}}

In 1815, Francisco J. Mier y Campillo, the [[Inquisitor]]-General of Spain during some of the [[Spanish Inquisition]], suppressed Freemasonry and denounced the lodges as "societies which lead to sedition, to independence, and to all errors and crimes."  He then instituted a witch hunt during which Spaniards were arrested and imprisoned in the dungeons of the Inquisition on the charge of being "suspected of Freemasonry".

Hungary's [[Béla Kun]] proclaimed in 1919 the dictatorship of the proletariat in Hungary. This marked the start of raids by army officers on Masonic lodges, along with thefts and sometimes destruction of libraries, records, archives, paraphernalia, and works of art. Several Masonic buildings was seized and used for anti-Masonic exhibitions. A decree made in 1920 outlawed Masonry.

In Italy, [[Benito Mussolini]] decreed in 1924 that every member of his Fascist Party who was a Mason must abandon one or the other organization. In 1925, he dissolved Freemasonry in Italy, claiming that Italian Freemasonry was a political organisation. It is worth noting that General Cappello, one of the most prominent Fascists who had also been Deputy Grand Master of the Grande Oriente, Italy's leading Grand Lodge, gave up membership in Fascism rather than Masonry. He was later arrested and sentenced to 30 years in jail on false charges{{ref|Cappello}}.

The Spanish dictator [[Miguel Primo de Rivera]] ordered the abolition of Freemasonry in Spain. In September 1928, one of the two Grand Lodges in Spain was closed and many Masons were included among those arrested for allegedly plotting against the government.

The military goverment of pre-[[WWII]] [[Japan]] also attacked Freemasonry. In 1938, a Japanse representative to the [[Weltdienst]] congress stated, on behalf of Japan, that "Judeo-Masonry is forcing the Chinese to turn China into a spearhead for an attack on Japan, and thereby forcing Japan to defend herself against this threat. Japan is at war not with China but with Freemasonry, represented by General Chiang-Kai-shek, the successor of his master, the Freemason Sun-Yat-Sen.".{{ref|Japan1938}}

In [[Nazi Germany]], Freemasons were actively suppressed from the moment the Nazis seized power. [[Adolf Hitler]] banned Freemasonry soon after he rose to power, apperantly feeling that Germans who became Masons were "selling out" and that high degree Masons were willing members of "the Jewish conspiracy". The intense Nazi dislike for the Craft can partly by explained by the fact that the Nazis blamed Masons, among others, for causing Germany to lose [[WWI]].  [[Hermann Goering]] wrote in 1933 that "..in National Socialist Germany, there is no place for Freemasonry." This edict eventually affected all of the countries that were under Nazi control. In 1937, Dr. [[Joseph Goebbels]], the Reichsminister for Propaganda and National Enlightenment under Adolf Hitler and the Nazi regime, inaugurated an "Anti-Masonic Exposition" to display the treasures seized by the Gestapo. Similar exhibitions was held in several of the countries overrun by Nazi Germany during [[WWII]]. Dr. [[Alfred Rosenberg]], also a Nazi, wrote openly and virulently against Freemasonry. He was convicted of war crimes at Nürnberg and executed in 1946. The Ministry of Defence also passed a edict forbidding officers in the armed forces to become Freemasons. Officers who were already Masons were either sidelined or forced to give up their membership in the Lodges.{{ref|Nazi}}.

Despite the oppression, a number of Masons continued to practice the Craft in secret, and a number of them also strove to undermine Hitler in other ways. Hence, people would be arrested not for being Masons but for other activities like [[treason]].  However, it was frequently, if not always noted, that these people were Masons when their punishments was decided.

In Spain, under the dictator General [[Francisco Franco]], Freemasonry was outlawed on March 2, 1940. Being a Mason was automatically punishable by a jail term, up to six years for those holding degrees up to the 18th, and more for Masons with higher degrees. It was reported that Masons were shot, tortured and murdered in every town in Spain, although details are lacking. The oppression of Freemasons in Spain continued into the 1950's{{ref|Spain}}.

Freemasonry was also suppressed in Eastern Europe during the [[communist]] era. In communist Hungary, lodges were described as "meeting places of the enemies of the people's democratic republic, of capitalistic elements, and of the adherents of Western imperialism."{{ref|commie}}.

When Field-Marshal Paulus surrendered to the Soviet Union in 1943, he was denounced as being a "High-grade Freemason", despite the prohibition on Masons being in the German armed forces.

In 1991, [[Pat Robertson]], published a book in the U.S. called [[The New World Order]]. In it, he attempted to exonerate individual Masons, but condemned "the Masonic connection" with phrases such as "Masonic power", "dark side", "international conspiracy", "occult", "Rothschilds", "Jews", "wealth", "secret society", and "world power". Other individuals and organisations in the United States and elsewhere in the world continue to attack Masonry today, largely on religious grounds: allegedly promoting devil worship, leading religious men away from the "right" way to find God, or being inconsistent with the religious beliefs of certain denominations. They often attack Masonry with exaggerated language, and it has been pointed out that their use of language about Masonry is strikingly similar to that which was used by the Nazis and other attackers of Freemasonry in the past{{ref|today}}.  In fact, many times, modern anti-Masonic proponents use the same propaganda and false information published by the Nazis and other suppressors of the Craft in the past.

==The Morgan Affair==

{{main|William Morgan (anti-Mason)}}

In 1826, [[William Morgan (anti-Mason)|William Morgan]] disappeared after threatening to expose Freemasonry's secrets, causing some to claim that he had been murdered by Masons. 

Morgan's disappearance&amp;mdash;and the minimal punishment received by his kidnappers&amp;mdash;sparked a series of protests against the Freemasons throughout New York and the neighboring states. Under the leadership of [[Thurlow Weed]], an anti-masonic, anti-[[Andrew Jackson]] (Jackson was a Mason) movement became a [[Anti-Masonic Party|political party]] and even ran for the presidency in [[1828]], gaining the support of such notable politicians as [[William H. Seward]]. Its influence was such that other Jackson rivals, including [[John Quincy Adams]], denounced the Masons. Adams in 1847 wrote a widely distributed book titled "Letters on the Masonic Institution" that was highly critical of the Masons. In [[1832]], the party fielded [[William Wirt]] as it presidential candidate, though the party only received seven electoral votes. Three years later, the party had disbanded everywhere but [[Pennsylvania]], as other issues, such as [[slavery]], became the focus of national attention.

What exactly occurred has never been conclusively proven.

==Freemasonry and anticlericalism==

Historically, Freemasonry has been identified with 19th-century [[bourgeois]] [[liberalism]], and some Freemasons have regarded traditional [[Christianity]] as allied to [[reactionary]] powers defending the status quo against the advance of human [[freedom]].  Masonic Lodges of this period were often associated with [[anticlericalism]], and were part of a broader movement, as is pointed out by Ralph Gibson:  "The republican enemies of the Church did not simply attack it on the grounds of its political alignment, but also in terms of more positive ideologies: to the old traditions of the [[Age of Enlightenment|Enlightenment]] were added first [[positivism]], and then [[scientism]].  [[Science]] was supposed to be the key to the understanding of the universe, and even to enable men to grasp its essential meaning.  [[Social science]] was believed to be able to provide the basis for an [[Ethics|ethical system]].  This new faith was ardently preached under the [[French Third Republic|Third Republic]] in Masonic lodges and circles of ''libre pens&amp;eacute;e'', in learned journals, and in educated republican society in general" (''A Social History of French Catholicism, 1789-1914'' [London &amp; New York: Routledge, 1989], pp.237-38).

Controversies over the historical involvements of Freemasonry and anticlericalism reach a peak in attempting to understand the role of Freemasonry in the history of anticlericalism in [[Portugal]], [[Italy]], and [[Mexico]].  Freemasons were prominent in the foundation of the modern Mexican state and the [[Institutional Revolutionary Party]] (PRI) and the writing of its anticlerical constitution. Under the regime of [[Plutarco Elías Calles]], the enforcement of anticlerical laws provoked the [[Cristero War]]. These animosities persist. As recently as [[2004]], [http://www.catholic-hierarchy.org/bishop/brivera.html Norberto Cardinal Rivera] of Mexico at a conference in [[Mexico City]] denounced the influence of Freemasonry.


==Political conspiracy theories involving the Masons==
Freemasonry has been a long-time target of [[Conspiracy theories (a collection)|conspiracy theories]], which see it as an [[occult]] and [[evil]] power, often associated with the [[New World Order (conspiracy)|New World Order]] and other "agents," such as the [[Illuminati]] and Jews &amp;mdash; either bent on world domination, or already secretly in control of world politics.

The historical complaints that the Masons have secretly plotted to create a society based on their ideals of [[liberty]], [[social equality|equality]], [[fraternity]], and [[religious tolerance]] are not denied by Masons. In a post-Enlightenment society, many people have now accepted these core Masonic values (though as a set of overall social values), and persistent enemies of the Masons have been forced to come up with ever more sinister motives as to what Freemasons allegedly conspire to achieve.

==Allegations that Freemasonry is a new religion==

In a sectarian age many hold that Freemasonry is a new religion. Externally, to some at least, it has many similarities to a religion:

* it has an altar and a sacred book (VSL-The Volume of the Sacred Law, in most cases the Holy Bible)
* it has its own way of saying "[[amen]] " ("So mote it be," a literal translation of "Amen")
* it has far more developed rituals than many organized religions (a debatable point)
* some groups of Masons (especially the Scottish Rite) call their meeting places "temples", (a lodge is a group of Freemasons operating under a charter or dispensation. The place where they meet is often called a temple, but usually, several lodges use the same temple.)
* it has a large amount of iconography and symbolism.

==Criticisms of alleged Masonic cronyism==

Another criticism that may or may not have to do with the specific nature of Freemasonry, but may be applied generally to any type of organization or [[secret society]], is the practice of [[cronyism]], or giving favors to fellow members. For example, many people have the impression that one increases chances for employment by joining the Masons. This type of cronyism can be seen in the movie ''[[Gypsy: A Musical Fable| Gypsy]]'', where the general idea is alluded to.  Some Masons have been known to claim they can get out of driving tickets because of Masonic logos on their car. Again, this criticism can be easily applied to almost any fraternity, but the Masons are a target because they are the largest worldwide fraternal organization.

==Criticisms based on the moral faults of known Masons==

Although any institution with moral overtones, religious or secular, can be criticized for the moral faults of some of their members, Freemasonry is especially vulnerable to criticism because amongst its aims is the drive to improve its members' [[morality]] above and beyond whatever religion the individual member believes in.

A general fault ascribed to the Masons is that a Freemason would be charitable mainly to other Masons, an assumption which is made worse by the accusations of classism and racism sometimes leveled against Masonic Lodges. The phrase "[[charity]] begins at home" goes some way towards justifying this natural proclivity.  

Critics also attack what they perceive as a preoccupation with ritual minutiae and personal status within the hierarchy of the organization. Some critics also argue that the Freemasons are primarily a social club.

Masons respond to these criticisms by pointing out that there are many programs and initiatives sponsored by lodges that do give back to the community at large; e.g. blood drives, child identification programs, and other charitable funds. Neither the [[Shriners Hospitals for Children]] nor the [[Scottish Rite]] Learning Centers are restricted to Masons, and they provide their services free of charge to those who need them.


==Claims that Freemasonry worships Satan==

"THE MASONS FIRST FACE TO FACE ENCOUNTER WITH THE GOD OF THE LODGE, WITH LUCIFER, WITH EN SOPH, WILL TAKE PLACE IN THE THIRTIETH DEGREE" 

Mackey's ''Scotch Rite Masonry Illustrated''

:'''Response''' The quote is misattributed: the book in question is not by Mackey, but by J. Blanchard, and is available from many places such as  [http://www.kessingerpub.com/searchresults_orderthebook.php?Title=824 Kessinger Books], for example. More importantly, Art de Hoyos [http://www.srmason-sj.org/web/SRpublications/deHoyos-chapter2.htm informs us] that this book is actually an "expose" of Cerneauism, rather than any legitimate Masonic organization.


"One of the most hidden secrets involves the so-called fall of Angels. Satan and his rebellious host will thus prove to have become the direct Saviours and Creators of divine man. Thus Satan, once he ceases to be viewed in the superstitious spirit of the church, grows into the grandiose image. It is Satan who is the God of our planet and the only God. Satan (or Lucifer) represents the Centrifugal Energy of the Universe, this ever-living symbol of self-sacrifice for the intellectual independence of humanity." 

Sister H.P. Blavatsky 
''The Secret Doctrine''
Pages 215, 216, 220, 245, 255, 533

:'''Response:''' Blavatsky herself [http://freemasonry.bcy.ca/biography/esoterica/blavatsky_hp/blavatsky_hp.html freely admits] that she was not a member of what she called "Western Freemasonry". Besides this, the quote above does not appear to refer to Masonry, and is apparently put together from 5 different pages in that cited book, some widely separated.


"It (Satan) is that Angel who was proud enough to believe himself God; brave enough to buy his independence at the price of eternal suffering and torture; beautiful enough to have adored himself in full divine light; strong enough to still reign in darkness amidst agony, and to have made himself a throne out of this inextinguishable pyre." 

Brother Eliphas Levi 
''Historie de la Magie''
Pages 16-17

:'''Response:''': Levi, while he may have been a Mason, was also an occultist.  This may have been part of what attracted him to the symbolism of the Craft, but this book is about the history of magic, and as such has nothing to do with Masonry, nor does it appear to make such a connection.  In fact, this quote says nothing about Satan that you couldn't get from, e.g., [[Paradise Lost]].


"What is more absurd and more impious than to attribute the name of Lucifer to the devil, that is, to personified evil. The intellectual Lucifer is the spirit of intelligence and love; it is the paraclete, it is the Holy Spirit, while the physical Lucifer is the great agent of universal magnetism." 

Eliphas Levi
''The Mysteries of Magic''
page 428

:'''Response:''' Here, too, there is no connection made between what Levi is saying and Masonry.  One cannot consider the unrelated writings of an individual to speak for a group.


"First Conjuration Addressed to Emperor Lucifer. Emperor Lucifer, Master and Prince of Rebellious Spirits, I adjure thee to leave thine abode, in what-ever quarter of the world it may be situated and come hither to communicate with me. I command and I conjure thee in the Name of the Mighty Living God, Father, Son and Holy Ghost, to appear without noise and without ...." 

Arthur Edward Waite 33°
''The Book Of Black Magic''
page 244

:'''Response:''' This is also not a quote from a Masonic source.  Waite is not identified as a 33rd degree Mason in this book, as shown on the cover of the book [http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/0877282072/104-3876488-0413510 here], but rather as a person with interests in the occult.  Here again, there is no Masonic link whatsoever with this material besides the fact that a member of the Craft wrote it.


"I hereby promise the Great Spirit Lucifer, Prince of Demons, that each year I will bring unto him a human soul to do with as as it may please him, and in return Lucifer promises to bestow upon me the treasures of the earth and fulfil my every desire for the length of my natural life. If I fail to bring him each year the offering specified above, then my own soul shall be forfeit to him. Signed..... { Invocant signs pact with his own blood } " 

Manley Palmer Hall 33°
''The Secret Teachings of All Ages''
page CIV

:'''Response:'''Manley Palmer Hall was also an occultist, and according to [http://www.crucible.org/mphall.htm this page], was a well-established lecturer on the occult and other esoteric knowledge by the age of 20, prior to the age at which he could have become a Mason.  He is also not identified as a 33° anywhere in this book, and there seems to be no record of his reception of the 33° on any readily available source that does not include this same quote.


"When The Mason learns that the Key to the warrior on the block is the proper application of the dynamo of living power, he has learned the Mystery of his Craft. The seething energies of Lucifer are in his hands and before he may step onward and upward, he must prove his ability to properly apply this energy." 

Manley Palmer Hall 33°
''The Lost Keys Of Freemasonry''
page 48

:'''Response:'''  This quote does appear in Chapter 4 "The Fellowcraft" [http://altreligion.about.com/library/texts/bl_lostkeys5.htm here], but the meaning changes when it is put back into the context of the chapter it comes from, as it is part of a larger philosophical  discussion that can also be read to imply that the improper use of "energies" can make the Mason a tool of Satan.  Furthermore, even taken out of context, this passage does not refer to worshipping Satan, ''per se''. Most usefully, according to ''Is It True What They Say About Freemasonry?''[http://srmason-sj.org/web/SRpublications/DeHoyos.htm], which references the book directly, Hall did not become a Freemason until 1954, so his entire book was his personal opinion as a non-Mason.


"Lucifer represents..Life..Thought..Progress..Civilization.. Liberty..Independence..Lucifer is the Logos..the Serpent, the Savior." pages 171, 225, 255 (Volume II)

"It is Satan who is the God of our planet and the only God." pages 215, 216, 220, 245, 255, 533, (VI)

"The Celestial Virgin which thus becomes the Mother of Gods and Devils at one and the same time; for she is the ever-loving beneficent Deity...but in antiquity and reality Lucifer or Luciferius is the name. Lucifer is divine and terrestial Light, 'the Holy Ghost' and "Satan' at one and the same time." 

Helena Petrovna Blavatsky 32°
Ancient and Accepted Primitive Rite
Grand Orient of France
''The Secret Doctrine''

:'''Response:''' The Ancient and Accepted Primitive Rite, as well as the Grand Orient of France, are which are recognized by no regular Masonic Grand Lodge in the world.  They violate a number of the  Landmarks of Freemasonry, and as such, neither those bodies or nor anything pertaining to them has any bearing or relevance to regular Freemasonry whatsoever.


"If the buckler of Satan did not stay the flight of Michael's lance, the power of the Archangel would be lost in the void, or would necessarily display and manifest itself by an infinite destruction, directed from above to below.
"And if the foot of Michael did not arrest Satan in his ascent, Satan would go to dethrone God, or to lose himself in the abysses of height.

"Satan is then necessary to Michael, as the pedestal to the statue; and Michael to Satan, as the brake to the locomotive.

"In analogical and universal dynamics we rest only on that which resists.

"Wherefore, as we have said before, the Universe is balanced by two forces, which maintain it in equilibrium; and the force which attracts, and that which repels. This is the equilibrium of the mountain of gold, which the Gods on one side, and the Demons on the other, hold tied by the symbolic Serpent of India; and its scientific reality is demonstrated by the phenomena of Polarity, and by the universal law of Sympathies and Antipathies...."

Albert Pike 33°
''Legendas XIX° ~ XXX°''
Pg. 40 - 44.

:'''Response:''' ''Legendas'', as with most of Pike's other works, draws on other sources. In this case, Pike seeks to illustrate the sources of the material in the Scottish Rite degrees.  This passage seems to be an expansion on a New Testament passage, reflecting on the balance of good and evil, and thereby speaks more to how good (the archangel Michael) prevents evil (Satan), and is in balance with it, than any other possible interpretation.


'That which we must say to the crowd is -- We worship a God, but it is the God that one adores without superstition.' 

'To you, Sovereign Grand Inspectors General, we say this, that you may repeat it to the Brethren of the 32nd, 31st and 30th degrees -- The Masonic religion should be, by all of us initiates of the high degrees, maintained in the of purity of the Luciferian doctrine.'

'If Lucifer were not God, would Adonay whose deeds prove his cruelty, perfidy, and hatred of man, barbarism and repulsion for science, would Adonay and his priests, calumniate him?'

'Yes, Lucifer is God, and unfortunately Adonay is also God. For the eternal law is that there is no light without shade, no beauty without ugliness, no white without black, for the absolute can only exist as two Gods: darkness being necessary to light to serve as its foil as the pedestal is necessary to the statue, and the brake to the locomotive.' 

'In analogical and universal dynamics one can only lean on that which will resist. Thus the universe is balanced by two forces which maintain its equilibrium: the force of attraction and that of repulsion. These two forces exist in physics, philosophy and religion. And the scientific reality of the divine dualism is demonstrated by the phenomena of polarity and by the universal law of sympathies and antipathies. That is why the intelligent disciples of Zoroaster, as well as, after them, the Gnostics, the Manicheans and the Templars have admitted, as the only logical metaphysical conception, the system of the two divine principles fighting eternally, and one cannot believe the one inferior in power to the other.'

'Thus, the doctrine of Satanism is a heresy; and the true and pure philosophic religion is the belief in Lucifer, the equal of Adonay; but Lucifer, God of Light and God of Good, is struggling for humanity against Adonay, the God of Darkness and Evil.'"

Albert Pike 33°
"Instructions to the 23 Supreme Councils of the world"
Issued July 14, 1889

A. C. De La Rive in ''La Femme et l'Enfant dans la Franc-Maconnerie Universelle'' (page 588).

:'''Response:''' This letter has been demonstrated to be a forgery.  See [[Taxil hoax]].


As a general rule, the real problems with Anti-Masonic claims, especially with regard to Satan worship, is either a lack of comprehensive reading, a lack of understanding, or the usage of quotes outside of their context.  As has been clearly shown, sometimes a context is even invented - most of these works in fact have nothing to do with Masonry. they were written because these particular people, who also happened to be Masons for whatever reason, had an interest in esoterica.  Mackey, Hall, and many other Masonic writers of that generation were already interested in esoteric subjects before they became Masons, and merely applied their prior knowledge to a new area.   

As for the few books quoted above that are creditd to their proper authors and are furthermore definitely written about Masonry, those books are intended for those individuals who have gone though the degrees mentioned; there is never a discussion of process, because those books are designed to further one's knowledge of the symbolism in the degrees, either where it comes from, or where it can extend to, in a philosophical sense.

Notes:

#{{Note|Crudeli}} 'The Truth Is Stranger Than Fiction' by Alphonse Cerza, published by the Masonic Service Association in September, 1967
#{{Note|Coustos}} Ibid.
#{{note|Cappello}} Ibid.
#{{Note|Japan1938}} [http://bessel.org/naziartl.htm Bigotry and the Murder of Freemasonry], Paul M. Bessel, November 1994, Retrived 29 October 2005
#{{Note|Nazi}} Ibid.
#{{note|Spain}} Ibid.
#{{Note|commie}} Ibid.
#{{Note|today}} Ibid.

==See also==

* [[Anti-Masonic Party]]
* [[Gnosticism]]
* [[Taxil hoax]]
* [[Catholicism and Freemasonry]]
* [[Anti-Clericalism]]

==External links==
*[http://freemasonrywatch.org Freemasonry Watch] An Anti-Masonic site
*[http://www.conspiracyarchive.com/NWO/Freemasonry.htm Freemasonry: Midwife to an Occult Empire] Anti-Masonic study detailing the occult nature of Freemasonry
*[http://www.douknow.net/fm_FreemasonryandChristianity.htm Freemasonry &amp; Christianity]
*[http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/09771a.htm Catholic Encyclopedia]
*[http://www.godonthe.net/cme/links/masons.htm Freemasonry and the occult] by a conservative religious group accusing Masons of witchcraft
*[http://www.chick.com/reading/tracts/0093/0093_01.asp Masonry] [[Chick tract]] accusing Masons of Satanism (images, ~561Kb)
*[http://www.zone.ee/freemasons/sektist.htm Estonian Anti-Freemasons Movement]
*[http://www.saintsalive.com/freemasonry.html Saints Alive In Jesus Freemasonry Resource Files]
*[http://www.ephesians5-11.org Ephesians 5:11 Anti-Masonry organisation]
*[http://www.catholicherald.com/saunders/05ws/ws050922.htm Straight Answers: Catholics and Freemasonry] (Article by Fr. William P. Saunders of the Diocese of Arlington Virgina)
*[http://www.nytimes.com/2004/03/10/nyregion/10shot.html?ex=1128744000&amp;en=7258fd77249bb303&amp;ei=5070&amp;ex=1084766400&amp;en=91aa50721437061d&amp;ei=5070 A Ritual Gone Fatally Wrong Puts Light on Masonic Secrecy] (Article from New York Times, requires registration - about masons, but not about a masonic ritual)
[[Category:Freemasonry]]
*[http://bessel.org/naziartl.htm Bigotry and the Murder of Freemasonry] (the history of Anti-Freemasonry)
*[http://srmason-sj.org/web/SRpublications/DeHoyos.htm ''Is It True What They Say About Freemasonry?''] a look at how anti-Masonic argument functions.  While it is a book written by Masons, their research is cited.</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>