<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20231105202639|1183671384" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="2866512" pageid="2866512" ns="0" title="Anti-Masonry"><revisions><rev timestamp="2023-11-14T16:25:01Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|Opposition to Freemasonry}}
{{Freemasonry}}
{{Discrimination sidebar |expanded=Social}}

'''Anti-Masonry''' (alternatively called '''anti-Freemasonry''') is "avowed opposition to [[Freemasonry]]",&lt;ref name= "antimasonrydef"&gt;''Oxford English Dictionary'' (1979 ed.), p. 369.&lt;/ref&gt; which has led to multiple forms of [[religious discrimination]], [[Religious violence|violent]] [[Religious persecution|persecution]], and suppression in some countries as well as in various [[organized religion]]s (primarily [[Abrahamic religions]]).&lt;ref name="Ferrer-Benimeli 2014"&gt;{{cite book |author-last=Ferrer Benimeli |author-first=José A. |year=2014 |chapter=Freemasonry and Religion |chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=x033AwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA139 |editor1-last=Bogdan |editor1-first=Henrik |editor2-last=Snoek |editor2-first=Jan A. M. |title=Handbook of Freemasonry |location=[[Leiden]] and [[Boston]] |publisher=[[Brill Publishers]] |series=Brill Handbooks on Contemporary Religion |volume=8 |doi=10.1163/9789004273122_010 |pages=139–144 |isbn=978-9004273122 |issn=1874-6691 |lccn=2014009769 |s2cid=159127723}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, there is no homogeneous anti-Masonic movement. Anti-Masonry consists of radically differing criticisms from frequently incompatible political institutions and [[Religious intolerance|organized religions that oppose each other]], and are hostile to Freemasonry in some form.&lt;ref name="Ferrer-Benimeli 2014"/&gt;

==Early anti-Masonic documents==
The earliest known&lt;ref&gt;Morris, S. Brent; ''The Complete Idiot's Guide to Freemasonry'', Alpha books, 2006, p. 203&lt;/ref&gt; anti-Masonic document was a leaflet which was printed in 1698 by a [[Presbyterianism|Presbyterian minister]] who was named Winter. It reads:&lt;ref&gt;As quoted by Morris, S. Brent; ''The Complete Idiot's Guide to Freemasonry'', Alpha Books, 2006, p. 204&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Additional information on this pamphlet is available in ''Ars Quatuor Coronatorum'' 55 (1942)&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;TO ALL GODLY PEOPLE, In the Citie of London.
Having thought it needful to warn you of the Mischiefs and Evils practiced in the Sight of God by those called Freed Masons, I say take Care lest their Ceremonies and secret Swearings take hold of you; and be wary that none cause you to err from Godliness. For this devilish Sect of Men are Meeters in secret which swear against all without ther Following. They are the Anti Christ which was to come leading Men from Fear of God. For how should Men meet in secret Places and with secret Signs taking Care that none observed them to do the Work of GOD; are not these the Ways of Evil-doers?

Knowing how that God observeth privilly them that sit in Darkness they shall be smitten and the Secrets of their Hearts layed bare. Mingle not among this corrupt People lest you be found so at the World's Conflagration.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

== Political anti-Masonry ==
Freemasonry has been alleged to hold its members back from fully committing themselves to their nation.&lt;ref name= "cathencpat"&gt;"Another characteristic of Masonic law is that "treason" and "rebellion" against civil authorities are only declared political crimes, which affect the good standing of a Brother no more than heresy, and furnish no ground for a Masonic trial." [http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/09771a.htm Masonry (Freemasonry)] from the ''Catholic Encyclopedia'', partially quoting Mackey, ''Jurisprudence'', 509.&lt;/ref&gt; Critics claim that compared to [[Operative Masonry]]'s clear denunciations of treachery,&lt;ref name= "GLE"&gt;"2nd – You shall be true liegemen to the King of England without any treason or falsehood, and if you know of any that you amend it privily, if you may, or else warn the King and his Council of it by declaring it to his officers."&lt;/ref&gt; Speculative Masonry (Freemasonry after 1723) was far more ambiguous.&lt;ref name="charges"&gt;[http://freemasonry.bcy.ca/history/anderson/charges.html II. Of the CIVIL MAGISTRATES supreme and subordinate] "A Mason is a peaceable Subject to the Civil Powers, wherever he resides or works, and is never to be concern'd in Plots and Conspiracies against the Peace and Welfare of the Nation, nor to behave himself undutifully to inferior Magistrates; for as Masonry hath been always injured by War, Bloodshed, and Confusion, so ancient Kings and Princes have been much dispos'd to encourage the Craftsmen, because of their Peaceableness and Loyalty, whereby they practically answer'd the Cavils of their Adversaries, and promoted the Honour of the Fraternity, who ever flourish'd in Times of Peace. So that if a Brother should be a Rebel against the State he is not to be countenanc'd in his Rebellion, however he may be pitied as an unhappy Man; and, if convicted of no other Crime though the loyal Brotherhood must and ought to disown his Rebellion, and give no Umbrage or Ground of political Jealousy to the Government for the time being; they cannot expel him from the Lodge, and his Relation to it remains indefeasible."&lt;/ref&gt; The old ''[[Catholic Encyclopedia]]'' alleges that Masonic disapproval of treachery is not on moral grounds but on the grounds of inconvenience to other Masons.&lt;ref name="inconv"&gt;"The brotherhood ought to disown the rebellion, but only in order to preserve the fraternity from annoyance by the civil authorities." from the article [http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/09771a.htm Masonry (Freemasonry)] in the ''[[Catholic Encyclopedia]]''&lt;/ref&gt; It also argues&lt;ref name="CEFMCh"&gt;"Such language would equally suit every anarchistic movement." [http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/09771a.htm Masonry (Freemasonry)] in the ''Catholic Encyclopedia''&lt;/ref&gt; that the adage "Loyalty to freedom overrides all other considerations"&lt;ref name="FMch"&gt;"If we were to assert that under no circumstances had a Mason been found willing to take arms against a bad government, we should only be declaring that, in trying moments, when duty, in the masonic sense, to state means antagonism to the Government, they had failed in the highest and most sacred duty of a citizen. Rebellion in some cases is a sacred duty, and none, but a bigot or a fool, will say, that our countrymen were in the wrong, when they took arms against King James II. Loyalty to freedom in a case of this kind overrides all other considerations, and when to rebel means to be free or to perish, it would be idle to urge that a man must remember obligations which were never intended to rob him of his status of a human being and a citizen." "Freemason's Chronicle" 1875, I, 81, quoted as footnote [89] in [http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/09771a.htm Masonry (Freemasonry)] in the ''Catholic Encyclopedia''&lt;/ref&gt; justifies treason, and quotes [[Albert Mackey]], who said "... if treason or rebellion were masonic crimes, almost every mason in the United Colonies (America), in 1776, would have been subject to expulsion and every Lodge to a forfeiture of its warrant by the Grand Lodges of England and Scotland, under whose jurisdiction they were at the time".&lt;ref name= "cathencpat"/&gt;

Freemasonry, however, charges its members that: "In the state you are to be a quiet and peaceful subject, true to your government and just to your country; You are not to countenence disloyalty or rebellion, but patiently submit to legal authority and conform with cheerfulness to the government of the country in which you live."&lt;ref&gt;Webb, Thomas Smith; [https://books.google.com/books?id=7FrMR3dtgDwC&amp;q=Freemasonry+Webb ''Freemason's Monitor Or Illustrations of Freemasonry''] – Charge at initiation into the first degree, p. 43 (originally published 1818... republished by Kessinger Publishing, 1995 {{ISBN|978-1564595539}})&lt;/ref&gt;

With this charge in mind, American Freemasons are consistent advocates of the US Constitution, including the [[separation of church and state]],&lt;ref name="sepchustate"&gt;"Freemasonry Does Not Support any particular political position. It has long stood for separation of Church and State, and has been a champion of Free Public Education." From a [http://www.arkmason.com/didknow.htm speech given by Bill Jones] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20060215084757/http://www.arkmason.com/didknow.htm |date=2006-02-15}} Grand Master of Arkansas, 1996&lt;/ref&gt; which was seen by the [[Roman Catholic Church]] as a veiled attack on the Church's place in public life.&lt;ref name="etsi4"&gt;[[Pope Leo XIII]] [http://www.ewtn.com/library/ENCYC/L13ITL.HTM ''Etsi Nos'' (On Conditions in Italy)]&lt;/ref&gt;

Freemasonry was persecuted in all the communist countries.&lt;ref name="BatMoF"&gt;
{{Cite web
|url= http://bessel.org/naziartl.htm
|title= Bigotry and the Murder of Freemasonry
|author= Bessel, Paul M.
|date=November 1994
|access-date= 2011-10-19
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="communist"&gt;Whalen, W.J., "Freemasonry" [http://www.trosch.org/bks/freemasonry.html ''The New Catholic Encyclopedia'' (1967)] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130130040136/http://www.trosch.org/bks/freemasonry.html |date=2013-01-30 }} article hosted at ''trosch.org''. Retrieved 2011-10-19.&lt;/ref&gt; However, Freemasonry in Cuba continued to exist following the [[Cuban Revolution]], and according to Cuban [[folklore]], [[Fidel Castro]] is said to have "developed a soft spot for the Masons when they gave him refuge in a Masonic Lodge" in the 1950s. However, when in power, Castro was also said to have "kept them on a tight leash" as they were considered a [[subversive]] element in Cuban society and allegedly providing safe haven for dissidents.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rosslyntemplars.org.uk/CubanMasons.htm Cuba's muzzled mavericks find haven among Masons] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20061231131019/http://www.rosslyntemplars.org.uk/CubanMasons.htm |date=2006-12-31}}, by Gary Marx, published April 14, 2005&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine|last1=Stein|first1=Jeff|title=Bay of Piglets: How the Freemasons Got Caught in a Plot to Topple the Castros|url=http://www.newsweek.com/2014/04/18/bay-piglets-how-freemasons-got-caught-plot-topple-castros-248099.html|access-date=7 April 2015|magazine=[[Newsweek]]|date=7 April 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Fascism|Fascists]] treated Freemasonry as a potential source of opposition. Masonic writers state that the language used by the totalitarian regimes is similar to that used by other modern critics of Freemasonry.&lt;ref name= "bessel.tolalitarian"&gt;{{cite web|title=Bigotry and the Murder of Freemasonry|author=Paul M. Bessel|year=1994|url= http://bessel.org/naziartl.htm|quote=These people who attack Masonry with exaggerated language, and without accepting reasonable explanations of what Freemasonry really is, would probably say that their use of language about Masonry that is strikingly similar to that which was used by the Nazis and other vicious attackers of Freemasonry in the past does not mean that they are following in the footsteps of the Nazis.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== The United States ===
{{Main|William Morgan (anti-Mason)|Anti-Masonic Party}}
In 1826, [[William Morgan (anti-Mason)|William Morgan]] disappeared from the small town of [[Batavia, New York]]. He was alleged to be kidnapped by Freemasons&lt;ref&gt;Ridley, Jasper;''The Freemasons: A History of the World's Most Powerful Secret Society'', pp. 180–181 (Arcade Publishing 1999).&lt;/ref&gt; and murdered after threatening to expose Freemasonry's "secrets" by publishing its rituals.&lt;ref&gt;Finney, Charles Grandison; [http://onlinebooks.library.upenn.edu/webbin/book/lookupid?key=olbp33154 ''The Character, Claims, and Practical Workings of Freemasonry''].&lt;/ref&gt; Morgan's disappearance sparked a series of protests and suspicion against Freemasonry, which eventually spread to the political realm. Under the leadership of anti-Masonic [[Thurlow Weed]], an Anti-Jacksonist movement became (since [[Andrew Jackson|Jackson]] was a Mason) the [[Anti-Masonic Party]]. This political Party ran presidential candidates in 1828 and 1832, but by 1835 the party had disbanded everywhere except [[Pennsylvania]].{{citation needed|date=August 2015}} [[William A. Palmer]] of Vermont and [[Joseph Ritner]] of Pennsylvania were both elected governor of their respective states on anti-Masonic platforms.&lt;ref&gt;William Preston Vaughn, ''The Anti-Masonic Party in the United States, 1826–1843'' (University Press of Kentucky. 1983).&lt;/ref&gt;

[[John Quincy Adams]], President of the United States during the Morgan affair, objected to the oath of secrecy, particularly with regard to the keeping of undefined secrets and to the penalties for breaking the oath. He declared, "Masonry ought forever to be abolished. It is wrong – essentially wrong – a seed of evil which can never produce any good,"&lt;ref&gt;Adams, John Quincy [https://archive.org/details/lettersonmasoni00adamgoog Letters on the Masonic Institution], pp. 68–71, 1847
Press of T.R. Marvin&lt;/ref&gt; although he extended "the most liberal of tolerance" to Masons who joined the fraternity before the murder of William Morgan, saying that they were taken by surprise and that they took the Oaths "without reflecting upon what they imported, or sheltering their consciences under the great names which had gone before them."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=Adams |first=John Quincy |date=1 April 1833 |title=Autograph Letter Signed as Congressman, to Stephen Bates. Washington, D.C. |url=https://www.sethkaller.com/item/1697-23716-John-Quincy-Adams-Scathing-Anti-Masonic-Letter-After-the-Murder-of-a-Prominent-Anti-Mason-Who-Threatened-to-Reveal-their-Secrets&amp;from=12 |access-date=2022-05-21 |website=Seth Kaller, Inc.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Though few states passed laws directed at Freemasonry by name, laws regulating and restricting it were passed and many cases dealing with Freemasonry were seen in the courts.&lt;ref name="books.google.com"&gt;{{Cite book |last=Mackey |first=Albert Gallatin |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Shs3fYPy7V0C&amp;dq |title=Encyclopedia of Freemasonry 1909 |last2=Haywood |first2=Harry LeRoy |date=2003-03-01 |publisher=Kessinger Publishing |isbn=978-0-7661-4721-8 |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; Antimasonic legislation was passed in Vermont in 1833, including a provision by which the giving and willing taking of an unnecessary oath was made a crime. (Pub. Stat., sec. 5917),&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/15354b.htm Vermont] Catholic Encyclopedia, 1911, Accessed June 26, 2008&lt;/ref&gt; and the state of New York enacted a Benevolent Orders Law to regulate such organizations.&lt;ref name="books.google.com"/&gt;

=== Asia ===
In 1938, a Japanese representative to the [[Ulrich Fleischhauer|''Welt-Dienst'' / ''World-Service'']] congress hosted by [[Ulrich Fleischhauer]] stated, on behalf of [[Empire of Japan|Japan]], that "[[Judeo-Masonry]] is forcing the Chinese to turn [[Republic of China (1912–49)|China]] into a spearhead for an attack on Japan, and thereby forcing Japan to defend itself against this threat. Japan is at war not with China but with [[Freemasonry]] ([[Tiandihui]]), represented by General [[Chiang Kai-shek]], the successor of his master, the Freemason [[Sun Yat-sen]]."&lt;ref name="BatMoF"/&gt;

=== Europe ===
According to Simon Sarlin, and Dan Rouyer, intense denunciation of Freemasonry because of its supposed grip on society and government, became standard doctrine within counter-revolutionary thought and action in the 19th century.  A major event was The International Anti-Masonic Congress that took place in Trento, Italy in 1896. It was sponsored by [[Pope Leo XIII]] and the [[Franz Joseph I of Austria|Austro-Hungarian Emperor Francis-Joseph]], a Catholic. The Congress assembled 1,500 delegates and 300 journalists, as well as prominent Catholic bishops. Thousands of telegrams testified to support from the right worldwide.  It created a permanent body, the "Universal Anti-Masonic Union." The goal was to create a powerful centre for all anti-Masonic groups, strengthening their resolve and capabilities to battle the Freemasons nation by nation.  In practice the Union was too conspicuously Papal, and poorly organized. It proved ineffective in its grandiose expectations but its creation was a measure of bitter anger and frustration among the Catholic enemies of Freemasonry.&lt;ref&gt;Simon Sarlin and Dan Rouyer, "The Anti-Masonic Congress of Trento (1896): International Mobilization and the Circulation of Practices against Freemasonry." ''Contemporanea: Rivista di Storia dell'800 e del '900'' (July-Sep 2021, 24#3, pp. 517-536. &lt;/ref&gt;

====Soviet Union====
The Soviet Union outlawed Masonry, in 1918. At one of the [[Second International]] meetings, [[Grigory Zinoviev]] demanded to purge it of masons.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1&gt;{{cite web|url=http://samlib.ru/k/kac_a_s/protokoli.shtml|title=Кац Александр Семенович. Протоколы Сионских Мудрецов и Всемирный Жидомасонский Заговор|website=samlib.ru|access-date=23 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; Freemasonry did not exist in the Soviet Union or most other communist states. Post-war revivals of Freemasonry in Czechoslovakia and Hungary were suppressed in 1950.&lt;ref name="nce67"&gt;Whalen, W.J. [http://www.trosch.org/bks/freemasonry.html "Freemasonry"] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130130040136/http://www.trosch.org/bks/freemasonry.html |date=2013-01-30 }} ''The New Catholic Encyclopedia'' (1967), hosted at [[David Trosch]]'s website. Retrieved 2011-10-09.&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Fascist Italy ====
[[Benito Mussolini]] decreed in 1924 that every member of his [[Fascist Party]] who was a Mason must abandon either one or the other organization, and in 1925, he dissolved Freemasonry in Italy, claiming that it was a political organization. One of the most prominent Fascists, General [[Luigi Capello|Capello]], who had also been Deputy Grand Master of the Grande Oriente, Italy's leading [[Grand Lodge]], gave up his membership in the Fascist Party rather than in Masonry. He later took part in a failed attempt to murder Mussolini and was sentenced to 30 years in jail, though it was released after 9 years of prison.&lt;ref name="TTISTF"&gt;'The Truth Is Stranger Than Fiction', Alphonse Cerza, published by the Masonic Service Association, September 1967&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Hungary ====
In 1919, [[Béla Kun]]&lt;ref name="masonicinfo"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.masonicinfo.com/famousanti.htm|title="Famous" Anti-Masons|first=Edward L.|last=King|website=www.masonicinfo.com|access-date=14 August 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; proclaimed the [[dictatorship of the proletariat]] in Hungary and Masonic properties were taken into public ownership. After the fall of the dictatorship of the proletariat, leaders of the counter-revolution such as [[Miklós Horthy]] blamed the Hungarian freemasons for their First World War defeat and for the revolution. Masonry was outlawed by a decree in 1920. This marked the start of raids by army officers on Masonic lodges&lt;ref name="L. Nagy Zsuzsa"&gt;L. Nagy Zsuzsa: Szabadkőművesség a XX. században, Budapest, 1977, Kossuth Könyvkiadó; L. Nagy Zsuzsa: Szabadkőművesség, Budapest, 1988, Akadémiai kiadó&lt;/ref&gt; along with theft, and sometimes destruction, of Masonic libraries, records, archives, paraphernalia, and works of art. Several Masonic buildings were seized and used for anti-Masonic exhibitions. The masonic documents were archived, preserved and may still be used for research.

In post-war Hungary, lodges were re-established, but after five years,&lt;ref name="L. Nagy Zsuzsa"/&gt; the government described them as "meeting places of the enemies of the people's democratic republic, of capitalistic elements, and of the adherents of Western imperialism". They were banned again in 1950.&lt;ref name="BatMoF" /&gt;

==== Nazi Germany and occupied Europe ====
{{See also|The Holocaust|Liberté chérie}}
[[File:Posters11.jpg|thumb|Propaganda poster of the [[Grand Anti-Masonic Exhibition]] in [[Belgrade]] during the [[Nazi German]] [[Axis occupation of Serbia#German occupation|occupation of Serbia]]]]
[[File:Red triangle.svg|right|60px|The red triangle, the symbol used to mark Freemasons]]

Freemasons are consistently considered an ideological foe of [[Nazism]] in their world perception (''[[Weltauffassung]]''). The Nazis claimed that high-degree Masons were willing members of the Jewish conspiracy and that Freemasonry was one of the causes of Germany's defeat in [[World War&amp;nbsp;I]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Art DeHoyos and S. Brent Morris|title=Freemasonry in Context: History, Ritual, Controversy|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=hXq4lJeX_DUC&amp;pg=PA101|year=2004|pages=100–101|isbn=978-0739107812}}&lt;/ref&gt; In ''[[Mein Kampf]]'', [[Adolf Hitler]] wrote that Freemasonry has succumbed to the Jews and has become an excellent instrument to fight for their aims and to use their strings to pull the upper strata of society into their designs. He continued, "The general pacifistic paralysis of the national instinct of self-preservation begun by Freemasonry" is then transmitted to the masses of society by the press.&lt;ref&gt;[[Adolf Hitler]], ''Mein Kampf'', pp. 315, 320.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1933 [[Hermann Göring]], the [[Reichstag (Weimar Republic)|Reichstag]] President and one of the key figures in the process of ''[[Gleichschaltung]]'' ("[[synchronising|synchronization]]"), stated "in National Socialist Germany, there is no place for Freemasonry".&lt;ref name="mercury" /&gt;

The [[Enabling Act of 1933|Enabling Act]] (''Ermächtigungsgesetz'' in [[German language|German]]) was passed by Germany's parliament (the Reichstag) on March 23, 1933. Using the Act, on January 8, 1934, the [[Nazi Germany|German]] [[Ministry of the Interior]] ordered the disbandment of Freemasonry, and confiscation of the property of all Lodges; stating that those who had been members of Lodges when Hitler came to power, in January 1933, were prohibited from holding office in the [[Nazi party]] or its [[paramilitary]] arms, and were ineligible for appointment in public service.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nationalsozialismus.de/index.php? ''The Enabling Act''] Accessed February 23, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; Consistently considered an ideological foe of Nazism in their world perception (''Weltauffassung''), special sections of the Security Service ([[Sicherheitsdienst|SD]]) and later the Reich Security Main Office ([[RSHA]]) were established to deal with Freemasonry.&lt;ref name="mill-valley.freemasonry.biz"&gt;"[http://mill-valley.freemasonry.biz/persecution.htm Documented evidence from the U.S. Holocaust Memorial Museum pertaining to the persecution of the Freemasons] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20121210071945/http://mill-valley.freemasonry.biz/persecution.htm |date=2012-12-10}}" accessed 21 May 2006&lt;/ref&gt; Masonic concentration camp inmates were graded as political prisoners, and wore an inverted (point down) [[Nazi concentration camp badges|red triangle]].

On August 8, 1935, as [[Führer]] and [[Chancellor of Germany (German Reich)|Chancellor]], Adolf Hitler announced in the [[National Socialist German Workers Party|Nazi]] Party newspaper, ''[[Völkischer Beobachter]]'', the final dissolution of all Masonic Lodges in Germany. The article accused a conspiracy of the Fraternity and World Jewry of seeking to create a [[New World Order (conspiracy)|World Republic]].&lt;ref&gt;Bro. E Howe, ''Freemasonry in Germany'', Quatuor Coronati Lodge, No 2076 (UGLE), 1984 Yearbook.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1937 Joseph Goebbels inaugurated an "Anti-Masonic Exposition" to display objects seized by the state.&lt;ref name="mercury"&gt;[http://mill-valley.freemasonry.biz/amermerc.htm The American Mercury Newspaper, 1941] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120813052953/http://mill-valley.freemasonry.biz/amermerc.htm |date=2012-08-13}} accessed 21 May 2006&lt;/ref&gt; The Ministry of Defence forbade officers from becoming Freemasons, with officers who remained as Masons being sidelined.&lt;ref name="BatMoF"/&gt;

During the war, Freemasonry was banned by edict in all countries that were either allied with the Nazis or under Nazi control, including [[Norway]] and [[France]]. Anti-Masonic exhibitions were held in many occupied countries. [[Friedrich Paulus|Field-Marshal Friedrich Paulus]] was denounced as a "High-grade Freemason" when he surrendered to the Soviet Union in 1943.&lt;ref name="Denslow"&gt;Denslow, Freemasonry in the Eastern Hemisphere, at page 111, citing a letter from Otto Arnemann in 1947, cited as [http://www.bessel.org/naziartl.htm#N_22_ Note 22] in ''Bigotry and the Murder of Freemasonry'' by Paul M. Bessel&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1943, the Propaganda Abteilung, a delegation of Nazi Germany's propaganda ministry within [[occupied France]], commissioned the propaganda film ''[[Forces occultes]]''. The film virulently denounces Freemasonry, parliamentarianism and Jews as part of Vichy's drive against them and seeks to prove a Jewish-Masonic plot. The Freemasons was accused of conspiring with Jews and Anglo-American nations to encourage France into a war with Germany.

The preserved records of the [[RSHA]]—i.e., ''[[Reichssicherheitshauptamt]]'' or the Office of the High Command of Security Service, which pursued the racial objectives of the SS through the Race and Resettlement Office—document the persecution of Freemasons.&lt;ref name="mill-valley.freemasonry.biz"/&gt; The number of Freemasons from Nazi occupied countries who were killed is not accurately known, but it is estimated that between 80,000 and 200,000 Freemasons were murdered under the Nazi regime.&lt;ref name="holocaust2"&gt;{{cite book |last=Hodapp |first=Christopher |date=2013 |title=Freemasonry for Dummies|edition=2nd |publisher=Wiley Publishing Inc. |isbn=978-1118412084 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The Government of the [[United Kingdom]] established [[Holocaust Memorial Day (UK)|Holocaust Memorial Day]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.hmd.org.uk/resource/about-hmd-booklets/|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20071112004939/http://www.hmd.org.uk/about/|url-status=dead|title=Holocaust Memorial Day Trust |archivedate=November 12, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; to recognise all groups who were targets of the Nazi regime, and counter [[Holocaust denial]]. Freemasons are listed as being among those who were targeted.

==== Francoist Spain ====
It is claimed that the dictator [[Miguel Primo de Rivera]] ordered the abolition of Freemasonry in Spain.&lt;ref name="primo"&gt;
"In 1925, Spain's first dictator of this generation, General Primo de Rivera, ordered the abolition of Freemasonry in his country." [http://www.grandlodgescotland.com/glos/Literature/Articles/Annihilation-of-Freemasonry.htm The Anhilation of Freemasonry] by Sven G. Lunden by [[The American Mercury]] Newspaper, 1941. Hosted by the Grand Lodge of Antient Free and Accepted Masons of Scotland&lt;/ref&gt; In September 1928, one of the two Grand Lodges in Spain was closed and approximately two-hundred masons, most notably the Grand Master of the Grand Orient, were imprisoned for allegedly plotting against the government.&lt;ref name="freemasonrytoday.com"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.freemasonrytoday.com/29/p10.php |title=Freemasonry and the Spanish Civil War: Part I, the Path to War |first=Matthew |last=Scanlan |access-date=19 August 2009 |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100828085718/http://www.freemasonrytoday.com/29/p10.php |archive-date=28 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Following [[Spanish coup of July 1936|the military coup of 1936]], many Freemasons trapped in areas under Nationalist control were arrested and summarily killed in the [[White Terror (Spain)|White Terror]], along with members of left wing parties and trade unionists. It was reported that Masons were tortured, [[garrote]]d, shot, and murdered by organized death squads in every town in Spain. At this time one of the most rabid opponents of Freemasonry, Father [[Juan Tusquets Terrats]], began to work for the Nationalists with the task of exposing masons. One of his close associates was Franco's personal chaplain, and over the next two years, these two men assembled a huge index of 80,000 suspected masons, even though there were little more than 5,000 masons in Spain. The lodge building in Cordoba was burnt, the [[Masonic Temple of Santa Cruz de Tenerife]] in the [[Canary Islands]] was confiscated and transformed into the headquarters of the Falange, and another was shelled by artillery. In Salamanca thirty members of one lodge were shot, including a priest. Similar atrocities occurred across the country: fifteen masons were shot in Logrono, seventeen in Ceuta, thirty-three in Algeciras, and thirty in Valladolid, among them the Civil Governor. Few towns escaped the carnage as Freemasons in Lugo, Zamora, Cadiz and Granada were brutally rounded up and shot, and in Seville, the entire membership of several lodges were butchered. The slightest suspicion of being a mason was often enough to earn a place in a firing squad, and the blood-letting was so fierce that, reportedly, some masons were even hurled into working engines of steam trains. By 16 December 1937, according to the annual masonic assembly held in Madrid, all masons that had not escaped from the areas under nationalist control had been murdered.&lt;ref name="freemasonrytoday.com"/&gt;

After the victory of dictator General [[Francisco Franco]], Freemasonry was officially outlawed in Spain on 2 March 1940. Being a mason was automatically punishable by a minimum jail term of 12 years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.freemasons-freemasonry.com/franco.html|title=Freemasonry banned in Spain by General Franco|website=www.freemasons-freemasonry.com|access-date=14 August 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Masons of the 18º and above were deemed guilty of "Aggravated Circumstances", and usually faced the death penalty.&lt;ref name="ReferenceA"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.freemasonrytoday.com/30/p09.php|title="Freemasonry and the Spanish Civil War: Part II", by Matthew Scanlan retrieved 19 August 2009|access-date=14 August 2017|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110711034852/http://www.freemasonrytoday.com/30/p09.php|archive-date=11 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Francoists, the Republican Regime which Franco overthrew had a strong Masonic presence.{{citation needed|date=January 2010}} In reality Spanish Masons were present in all sectors of politics and the armed forces.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |url=https://archive.org/details/spainduringworld00bowe_0 |url-access=registration |quote=spain during wwII. |first=Wayne H. |last=Bowen |title=Spain during World War II |publisher= University of Missouri press |year=2006 |page=[https://archive.org/details/spainduringworld00bowe_0/page/249 249]|isbn=978-0826216588 }}&lt;/ref&gt; At least four of the Generals who supported Franco's rebellion were Masons, although many lodges contained fervent but generally conservative Republicans. Freemasonry was formally outlawed in the Law for the Repression of Freemasonry and Communism.&lt;ref name="Ruiz, Julius p. 25"&gt;Ruiz, Julius, [https://books.google.com/books?id=sNk61qkjop0C Franco's justice: repression in Madrid after the Spanish Civil War], p. 25 Oxford Univ. Press&lt;/ref&gt; After Franco's decree outlawing masonry, Franco's supporters were given two months to resign from any lodge they might be a member. Many masons chose to go into exile instead, including prominent monarchists who had whole-heartedly supported the Nationalist rebellion in 1936. The common components in Spanish Masonry seems to have been upper or middle class conservative liberalism and strong anti-clericism.&lt;ref&gt;Hugh Thomas, The Spanish Civil War, Penguin, 1965 pp. 47–48&lt;/ref&gt;

The Law for the Repression of Freemasonry and Communism was not abrogated until 1963.&lt;ref name="Ruiz, Julius p. 25"/&gt; References to a "Judeo-Masonic plot" are a standard component of Francoist speeches and propaganda and reveal the intense and paranoid obsession of the dictator with masonry. Franco produced at least 49 pseudonymous anti-masonic magazine articles and an anti-masonic book during his lifetime. According to Franco:&lt;ref name="ReferenceA" /&gt;
:The whole secret of the campaigns unleashed against Spain can be explained in two words: masonry and communism... we have to extirpate these two evils from our land.

==== United Kingdom ====
It was the [[Unlawful Societies Act]] of 1799 that saw the first statute "for the more effectual suppression of societies established for seditious and treasonable purposes"; once enacted it affected all societies whose members were required to take an oath not authorised by law, shall be deemed "unlawful combinations." It was as a result of the intervention of the Grand Master of the Antients, The 4th Duke of Atholl, and the Acting Grand Master of the Moderns, the earl of Moira that a special exempting clause was inserted into this legislation in favour of societies "held under the Denomination of Lodges of Freemasons" provided that they had been "usually held before the Act" and their names, places and times of meeting and the names of the members were annually registered with the local Clerk to the Justices of the Peace. This continued on until 1967 when this Act was repealed by a section of the Criminal Justice Act which meant that the annual returns of all the Lodges to the authorities ceased.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.freemasons-freemasonry.com/prescott15.html Pietre Stones] The Unlawful Societies Act of 1799, Dr Andrew Prescott, retrieved 13th July 2012&lt;/ref&gt;

In the United Kingdom, anti-Masonic sentiment grew following the publication of [[Martin Short (author)|Martin Short's]] 1989 book, ''Inside the Brotherhood (Further Secrets of the Freemasons)''.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.harpercollins.co.uk/Authors/5282/martin-short |title=Martin Short – HarperCollins |access-date=2013-12-15 |archive-date=2013-12-15 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20131215133522/http://www.harpercollins.co.uk/Authors/5282/martin-short |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; The allegations made by Short led several members of the British Government, since 1997, to propose laws requiring Freemasons who join the police or judiciary&lt;ref name="Newjudgesmustdeclaremasonicmembership"&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk/politics/57381.stm "New judges must declare masonic membership"], BBC, March 5, 1998, retrieved February 26, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; to declare their membership publicly to the government amid accusations of Freemasons performing acts of mutual advancement and favour-swapping. This movement was initially led by [[Jack Straw (politician)|Jack Straw]], [[Home Secretary]] from 1997 until 2001.&lt;ref name="Newjudgesmustdeclaremasonicmembership" /&gt; In 1999, the [[Welsh Assembly]] became the only body in the United Kingdom to place a legal requirement on membership declaration for Freemasons.&lt;ref name="Freemasonpolicyreviewdue"&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/wales/1699189.stm "Freemason policy review due"], BBC, December 8, 2001, retrieved February 26, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; Currently, existing members of the police and judiciary in England are asked to voluntarily admit to being Freemasons.&lt;ref name="HouseofCommonsresponce"&gt;[http://www.parliament.the-stationery-office.com/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/vo050721/text/50721w69.htm#50721w69.html_sbhd0 "House of Commons Hansard Written Answers for 21 July 2005 (pt 69)"] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120215024717/http://www.parliament.the-stationery-office.com/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/vo050721/text/50721w69.htm |date=15 February 2012}}, UK House of Commons, July 21, 2005, retrieved October 2, 2007&lt;/ref&gt; However, all first time successful judiciary candidates had to "declare their freemasonry status" before appointment until 2009, when – following a successful challenge in the European Court by Italian Freemasons – Jack Straw accepted that the policy was "disproportionate" and revoked it.&lt;ref name="HouseofCommonsresponce" /&gt; Conversely, new members of the police are not required to declare their status.&lt;ref name="HouseofCommonsresponce" /&gt;

In 2004, [[Rhodri Morgan]], the [[First Minister for Wales|First Minister of the Welsh Assembly]], said that he blocked Gerard Elias' appointment to counsel general because of links to hunting and Freemasonry,&lt;ref name="Morgancriticisedoverjobblocking"&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/wales/3557279.stm "Morgan criticised over job blocking"], BBC, March 22, 2004, retrieved February 26, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; although it was claimed by non-Labour politicians that the real reason was in order to have a Labour supporter, Malcolm Bishop, in the role.&lt;ref name="mbishop"&gt;"Mr Morgan wanted another QC, Malcolm Bishop, who has stood as a Labour candidate and is a close associate of former Lord Chancellor Derry Irvine." [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/wales/3530987.stm Morgan 'blocked' QC appointment]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Religious anti-Masonry ==
=== Muslim anti-Masonry ===
{{Further|Antisemitism in Islam|Antisemitism in the Arab world|Conspiracy theories in the Arab world|Conspiracy theories in Turkey|War on Islam controversy}}
[[File:Ahmad nami.jpg|thumb|[[Ottoman dynasty|Ottoman]] noble [[Ahmad Nami]] dressed in full Masonic attire in 1925]]

[[Islam]]ic criticism and opposition to Freemasonry has existed since the introduction of the latter in the [[Muslim world]] since the 19th century.&lt;ref name="Dumont 2005"&gt;{{cite journal |author-last=Dumont |author-first=Paul |date=July 2005 |title=Freemasonry in Turkey: A By-product of Western Penetration |editor-last=D'haen |editor-first=Theo |journal=[[European Review]] |location=[[Cambridge]] and [[New York City|New York]] |publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]] |volume=13 |issue=3 |pages=481–493 |doi=10.1017/S106279870500058X |s2cid=145551813 |issn=1474-0575}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Landau |first=Jacob M. |date=July 1996 |title=Muslim Opposition to Freemasonry |editor-last=Brunner |editor-first=Rainer |journal=[[Die Welt des Islams]] |location=[[Leiden]] and [[Boston]] |publisher=[[Brill Publishers]] |volume=36 |issue=2 |pages=186–203 |doi=10.1163/1570060962597481 |eissn=1570-0607 |issn=0043-2539 |jstor=3693461}}&lt;/ref&gt; After the condemnation of Freemasonry by [[Pope Clement XII]] in 1738, Sultan [[Mahmud I]] followed suit outlawing the organization and since that time Freemasonry was equated with [[atheism]] in the [[Ottoman Empire]] and the broader Islamic world.&lt;ref name=FitIW&gt;Layiktez, Cecil "[http://www.freemasons-freemasonry.com/layiktez1.html Freemasonry in the Islamic World]", Pietre-Stones Review of Freemasonry, 1996&lt;/ref&gt; The Islamic anti-Masonic opposition in the Muslim world has been reinforced by the [[Anticlericalism|anti-clerical]] and atheistic slant of the [[Grand Orient of France]].&lt;ref name=FitIW /&gt;

By the middle of the 19th century, Freemasonry and its semi-secret organizational structures were able to establish [[Masonic lodge|lodges]] predominantly among those populations living in the [[Ottoman Empire]] and [[Administrative divisions of the Ottoman Empire|its provinces]]&lt;ref name="Dumont 2005"/&gt; ([[Ottoman Egypt|Egypt]], [[History of Lebanon under Ottoman rule|Lebanon]], [[Ottoman Syria|Syria]], [[Ottoman Cyprus|Cyprus]], and [[History of North Macedonia#Ottoman period|Macedonia]]).&lt;ref name="Dumont 2005"/&gt; This began about 15 years after the declaration of [[Edict of Gülhane|1839 Reform Edicts]] and Freemasonry became successful in the Ottoman Empire under the reigns of sultans [[Abdulmejid I|Abdulmejid]] (1839–1861), [[Abdulaziz]] (1861–1876) and [[Abdul Hamid II]] (1876–1909).&lt;ref name="Dumont 2005" /&gt; During the 19th century, numerous prominent Muslim scholars, thinkers, and politicians, such as [[Emir Abdelkader|'Abd al-Qadir al-Jaza'iri]] (1808–1883), [[Jamal al-Din al-Afghani|Jamal al-Din Afghani]] (1839–1897), and [[Rıza Tevfik Bölükbaşı|Riza Tevfik]] (1869–1949) were active in Freemasonry.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=De Poli|first=Barbara|title=Freemansonry and the Orient: Esotericisms between the East and the West|publisher=Edizioni Ca' Foscari-Digital publishing|year=2019|isbn=978-8869693397|pages=75–86|chapter=6: Sufi and Freemasons in the Ottoman empire|quote="Summary 6.1 ʿAbd Al-Qādir Al-Jazāʾirī. – 6.2 Jamāl Al-Dīn Al-Afghānī. – 6.3 Rizā Tevfīk."}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other notable scholars, intellectuals, and politicians who became Freemasons included [[Saad Zaghloul|Sa'd Zaghlul]], [[Yaqub Sanu|Ya'qib Sannu']], [[Adib Ishaq]], [[Tewfik Pasha|Tawfiq Pasha]], and the influential [[Faqīh|Islamic jurist]] and [[Islamic theology|theologian]] [[Muhammad Abduh|Muhammad 'Abduh]].&lt;ref name="Kudsi-Zadeh 1972"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Kudsi-Zadeh|first=A. Albert|date=January–March 1972|title=Afghānī and Freemasonry in Egypt|journal=[[Journal of the American Oriental Society]]|publisher=[[American Oriental Society]]|volume=92|issue=1|pages=25–35|doi=10.2307/599645|issn=0003-0279|jstor=599645|lccn=12032032|oclc=47785421|quote="It traces Afghani's connections with Freemasonry and concludes that he attempted to use the brotherhood as a ready-made agency for political mobilization and agitation against the Khedive Isma'il and the increasing European intervention in the affairs of Egypt. Many of  his followers, such as Muhammad 'Abduh, Sa'd Zaghlul, Ya'qib Sannu' and Adib Ishaq, joined, as did some notables, army officers, and Isma'il's son, Tawfiq Pasha."}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Many contemporary Islamic anti-Masonic arguments are closely tied to both [[antisemitism]] and [[anti-Zionism]], though other reasons for the Muslim anti-Masonry have been formulated, such as linking Freemasonry to [[Masonic conspiracy theories|conspiracy theories]] and [[Islamic eschatology]], in particular to the eschatological figure of [[Masih ad-Dajjal|the Dajjal]] (the Islamic Antichrist).&lt;ref name="Litvak 2021"&gt;{{cite book |author-last=Litvak |author-first=Meir |year=2021 |editor1-last=Lange |editor1-first=Armin |editor2-last=Mayerhofer |editor2-first=Kerstin |editor3-last=Porat |editor3-first=Dina |editor4-last=Schiffman |editor4-first=Lawrence H. |title=An End to Antisemitism! – Volume 5: Confronting Antisemitism in Modern Media, the Legal and Political Worlds |chapter=Islamic Radical Movements and Antisemitism: Between Old and New |location=[[Berlin]] and [[Boston]] |publisher=[[De Gruyter]] |pages=133–148 |doi=10.1515/9783110671964-009 |doi-access=free |isbn=978-3110671964}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="SFMNAD"&gt;{{cite book|url=http://freemasonry.dept.shef.ac.uk/pdf/ovn.pdf?PHPSESSID=bf5645aae288a112e6c99cacdca85a90 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070317214300/http://freemasonry.dept.shef.ac.uk/pdf/ovn.pdf |url-status=dead |archive-date=2007-03-17 |format=pdf |title=The Study of Freemasonry as a New Academic Discipline |pages=13–14 |first=Andrew |last=Prescott |access-date=2006-05-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; During the early 20th century, the [[Syrians|Syrian]]-[[Egyptians|Egyptian]] Islamic theologian [[Rashid Rida|Mūhammād Rashīd Ridâ]] (1865–1935) played the crucial role in leading the opposition to Freemasonry across the Muslim world.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Rickenbacher|first=Daniel|date=6 December 2019|title=The 'War Against Islam': How a Conspiracy Theory Drove and Shaped the Islamist Movement|url=https://eeradicalization.com/the-war-against-islam-how-a-conspiracy-theory-drove-and-shaped-the-islamist-movement/|url-status=live|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20210818054514/https://eeradicalization.com/the-war-against-islam-how-a-conspiracy-theory-drove-and-shaped-the-islamist-movement/|archive-date=18 August 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt; Through his popular [[Pan-Islamism|pan-Islamic]] journal ''[[Al-Manār (magazine)|Al-Manār]]'', Rida spread anti-Semitic and anti-Masonic ideas which would directly influence the [[Muslim Brotherhood]] and subsequent [[Islamic extremism|radical Islamic]] and [[Islamism|Islamist]] movements, such as [[Hamas]] (see [[Hamas#Hamas Charter|Hamas Charter]]).&lt;ref name="Litvak 2021" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Rickenbacher 2019"&gt;{{cite web |last=Rickenbacher |first=Daniel |date=6 December 2019 |title=The 'War Against Islam': How a Conspiracy Theory Drove and Shaped the Islamist Movement |url=https://eeradicalization.com/the-war-against-islam-how-a-conspiracy-theory-drove-and-shaped-the-islamist-movement/ |url-status=live |website=www.eeradicalization.com |publisher=European Eye on Radicalization |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20210818054514/https://eeradicalization.com/the-war-against-islam-how-a-conspiracy-theory-drove-and-shaped-the-islamist-movement/ |archive-date=18 August 2021 |access-date=23 March 2023}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

{{Blockquote|text=The Egyptian newspaper ''[[Al-Manār (magazine)|Al-Manār]]'', belonging to [[Muhammad Rashid Rida]], played a critical role in spreading these [[conspiracy theories]]. Rida was the leading [[Pan-Islamism|pan-Islamic activist]] of that age, a significant intellectual influence on [[Hassan al-Banna]], the founder of the [[Muslim Brotherhood]]. In his articles, Rida maintained that [[International Jewish conspiracy|the Jews]] stood behind the [[Young Turk revolution]] in the [[Ottoman Empire]] in 1908 and had also orchestrated the [[French Revolution of 1789]] and the [[Russian Revolution (1905)|1905 rebellion in Russia]]. Rida also believed that the Jews were planning to take over [[Al-Aqsa Mosque]] and expel the Muslim and Christian inhabitants of the [[Holy Land]]. Rida’s mix of European conspiratorial thought and [[political Islam]] left a lasting mark.&lt;ref name="Rickenbacher 2019"/&gt;}}

Influenced by Rida,&lt;ref name="Rickenbacher 2019"/&gt; Muslim anti-Masonic propagandists [[Jewish conspiracy theories|argue that Freemasonry promotes the interests of the Jews around the world]] and that one of its aims is to rebuild the [[Temple of Solomon]] in [[Jerusalem]] after destroying [[Al-Aqsa]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.islamonline.net/servlet/Satellite?cid=1119503547288&amp;pagename=IslamOnline-English-Ask_Scholar%2FFatwaE%2FFatwaEAskTheScholar |title=Can a Muslim be a freemason? |access-date=2007-05-08 |format=asp |work=Islamonline.com |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20071016062746/https://wakeupfromyourslumber.com/node/4119 |archive-date=2007-10-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; In article 28 of its Charter, Hamas states that Freemasonry, [[Rotary International|Rotary]], and other similar groups "work in the interest of [[Zionism]] and according to its instructions...."&lt;ref&gt;''[[s:Hamas Covenant|Hamas Covenant of 1988]]''. Wikisource. Accessed 2 October 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; On July 15, 1978, the Islamic Jurisdictional College—one of the most influential entities that interpret ''[[Sharia]]'', or Islamic law—issued an opinion that deemed Freemasonry to be "dangerous" and "clandestine".&lt;ref name="FitIW" /&gt;

Many [[Muslim-majority countries|countries with a significant Muslim population]] do not allow Masonic establishments within their jurisdictions. After [[World War II]], while under the [[Mandatory Iraq|British Mandate]], Iraq used to have several Masonic lodges. This all changed with the [[14 July Revolution]] in 1958, however, with the abolition of the [[Hashemite monarchy]] and [[Iraqi Republic (1958–1968)|Iraq's declaration as a republic]]. The licenses permitting lodges to meet were rescinded, and later, laws were introduced banning any further meetings. This position was later reinforced under [[Saddam Hussein]]. In 1980, the Iraqi legal and penal code was changed, making it a [[felony]] to "promote or acclaim Zionist principles, including freemasonry, or who associate [themselves] with Zionist organizations."&lt;ref name="freemasonryinSHIraq"&gt;[http://www.washingtontimes.com/news/2004/jul/1/20040701-120129-6565r/?page=all "Saddam to be formally charged"], ''The Washington Times'', July 1, 2004. Retrieved 2011-10-09.&lt;/ref&gt; Also, Freemasonry was banned in [[Egypt]] in 1964 by the order of [[Gamal Abdel Nasser|President Nasser]] and in 1965 the [[Ba'athist Syria|Ba'athist government of Syria]] banned all lodges.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.syria.tv/استيقاظ-الماسونية-السورية|title=استيقاظ الماسونية السورية|date=September 9, 2019|website=تلفزيون سوريا}}&lt;/ref&gt;

However, a few countries such as [[Turkey]] and [[Morocco]] have allowed establishment of Grand Lodges&lt;ref&gt;Leyiktez, Celil. [http://www.freemasons-freemasonry.com/layiktez1.html "Freemasonry in the Islamic World"]. Accessed 2 October 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; while in countries such as [[Malaysia]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dglme.org/contacts/contacts.aspx DGLME.org – The District Grand Lodge of the Middle East&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20081206005838/http://www.dglme.org/contacts/contacts.aspx |date=2008-12-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Lebanon]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.nymasons.org/cms/districtsonline|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080705104458/http://www.nymasons.org/cms/districtsonline|url-status=dead|title=Districts Online &amp;#124; Grand Lodge F. &amp; A. M. State of New York&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;|archivedate=July 5, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; there are District Grand Lodges operating under a warrant from an established Grand Lodge. In addition, according to some sources, [[King of Jordan|King]] [[Hussein of Jordan]] was a Freemason himself.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.lodgeofunity.org.uk/extracts-from-the-minutes/famous-masons/|title=Famous Freemasons &amp;#124; The Lodge of Unity, Warwick|accessdate=8 June 2023}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://linfordresearch.info/fordownload/World%20of%20Fmy/Nairn%20Middle%20East.pdf |title=Extract from World of Freemasonry
|website=linfordresearch.info|access-date=8 June 2023}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Christian anti-Masonry ===
{{Main|Antisemitism in Christianity|Opposition to Freemasonry within Christianity}}
One of the first highly vocal Christian critics of freemasonry was [[Charles Finney]]. In his book ''The Character, Claims, and Practical Workings of Freemasonry'', Finney not only ridiculed the masons, he also explained why he viewed leaving the society as an essential act three years after he entered seminary.

A number of [[Protestant]] and [[Eastern Orthodox]] denominations discourage their congregants from joining Masonic lodges, but this practice differs in intensity according to the beliefs of the denomination. Some denominations simply express mild concern about Freemasonry because they do not believe that it is compatible with the teachings of Christianity while, at the other extreme, other denominations openly accuse the fraternity of [[Satanism|worshipping Satan]], by quoting the writings of [[Leo Taxil]] and [[Abel Clarin de la Rive]].&lt;ref&gt;"Is It True What They Say About Freemasonry?" Authors: de Hoyos, Arturo and Morris, S. Brent, 1988, 2nd edition, pp. 27–36, ''Leo Taxil: The Hoax of Luciferian Masonry'' {{ISBN|1590771532}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Since 1738, the [[Catholic Church|Roman Catholic Church]] has prohibited its members from joining Masonic organizations, citing political as well as religious reasons. Until 1983, the penalty for Catholics who joined the fraternity was [[excommunication]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/05678a.htm|title=Catholic Encyclopedia: Excommunication|website=www.newadvent.org|access-date=23 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; Since that time, the punishment has been an [[interdict]], barring the offender from receiving [[Holy Communion]]. Even though the canonical penalty was changed in 1983, the prohibition on membership has not been changed.&lt;ref&gt;Joseph Cardinal Ratzinger, Prefect. [https://www.vatican.va/roman_curia/congregations/cfaith/documents/rc_con_cfaith_doc_19831126_declaration-masonic_en.html ''Declaration on Masonic Associations''] Sacred Congregation for the Doctrine of the Faith, 26 November 1983. Accessed 2011-10-09. "Therefore the Church's negative judgment in regard to Masonic association[s] remains unchanged since their principles have always been considered irreconcilable with the doctrine of the Church and therefore membership in them remains forbidden. The faithful who enroll in Masonic associations are in a state of grave sin and may not receive Holy Communion. It is not within the competence of local ecclesiastical authorities to give a judgment on the nature of Masonic associations which would imply a derogation from what has been decided above..."&lt;/ref&gt;

== Conspiracy theories ==
{{Main|Masonic conspiracy theories}}
There have long been [[conspiracy theory|conspiracy theories]] concerning Freemasonry in which the organization is either bent on world domination or it is already covertly in control of world politics.&lt;ref&gt;Pawns in the Game, (4th Edition, April, 1962), William Guy Carr&lt;/ref&gt;

The earliest document which accused Freemasonry of being involved in a conspiracy was ''Enthüllungen des Systems der Weltbürger-Politik'' ("Disclosure of the System of Cosmopolitan Politics"), published in 1786.&lt;ref&gt;"Bereits um 1786, kurz zuvor waren die Illuminaten in Bayern verboten worden, kursierte das erste Pamphlet über die Freimaurer, das von einem anonymen Autor als "Enthüllungen des Systems der Weltbürger-Politik" veröffentlicht wurde." Transl. "As early as 1786, shortly before the banning of the Illuminati in Bavaria, the first pamphlet about Freemasonry arrived, the anonymously authored "Enthüllungen des Systems der Weltbürger – Politik"." [http://www.neue-freimaurer.com/freimaurerei.html Freimaurer im Wandel der Zeit – von der Gründung bis heute] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080925022152/http://www.neue-freimaurer.com/freimaurerei.html |date=2008-09-25}}, from the [http://www.neue-freimaurer.com/ Neue Freimaurer] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080925124409/http://www.neue-freimaurer.com/ |date=2008-09-25}} website.&lt;/ref&gt; The book claimed that Freemasons and [[Society of Jesus|Jesuits]] were plotting to foment a world revolution.&lt;ref name="Pfahl-Traughber"&gt;prof. Dr. Pfahl-Traughber: ''Der antisemitisch-antifreimaurerische Verschwörungsmythos''&lt;/ref&gt; During the 19th Century, this theory was repeated by many Christian counter-revolutionaries,&lt;ref name="EZW"&gt;Matthias Pöhlmann: ''Verschwiegene Männer'', Protestant Centre for Religious and Ideological Issues of the [[Evangelical Church in Germany]]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Biberstein"&gt;Dr. Johannes Rogalla von Biberstein, historian and librarian of the University of Bielefeld: ''Die These von der Verschwörung 1776–1945. Philosophen, Freimaurer, Juden, Liberale und Sozialisten gegen die Sozialordnung'', Flensburg 1992&lt;/ref&gt; who accused Freemasons of being behind every attack on the existing social system.&lt;ref name="EZW" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Biberstein" /&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Abel Clarin de la Rive]]
* [[Anti-clericalism]]
* [[Judeo-Masonic conspiracy theory]]
* [[Mormonism and Freemasonry]]
* ''[[Propaganda Due]]'' – The P2 pseudo-Masonic Lodge Scandal
* [[Secret society]]
* [[Taxil hoax]]

== References ==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
* Sarlin, Simon, and Dan Rouyer. "The Anti-Masonic Congress of Trento (1896): International Mobilization and the Circulation of Practices against Freemasonry." ''Contemporanea: Rivista di Storia dell'800 e del '900'' (Jul-Sep 2021), 24#3, pp. 517-536.

== External links ==
{{Commons category|Anti-Masonry}}

=== Critical of Freemasonry ===
* [http://www.conspiracyarchive.com/NWO/Freemasonry.htm www.conspiracyarchive.org] – Freemasonry: Midwife to an Occult Empire by Terry Melanson
* [http://www.masoncode.com/The%20Jewels%20of%20Freemasonry.htm www.masoncode.com] – The Jewels of Freemasonry
* [http://www.ephesians5-11.org www.ephesians 5-11.org] – How can you lead Masons away from the Masonic Lodge?
* [http://en.internationalism.org/node/3741 Workers' Movement: Marxism against Freemasonry]

=== Supportive of Freemasonry ===
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20051103003632/http://www.srmason-sj.org/web/SRpublications/DeHoyos.htm srmason-sj.org] – ''Is It True What They Say About Freemasonry?'' by Art DeHoyos
* [http://masonicinfo.com masonicinfo.com] – Masonic rebuttal to Anti-Masonic claims
* [http://www.freemasonry.bcy.ca/anti-masonry/anti-masonry_faq.html www.freemasonry.bcy.ca] – ''Anti-masonry Frequently Asked Questions''
* [http://www.freemasons-freemasonry.com/gazzo_antimasonry.html www/freemasons-freemasonry.com] – ''Anti-Masonry in the contemporary world''

'''Academic examinations of Anti-Masonry'''
* [http://scottishrite.org/about/media-publications/journal/article/current-interest-london-conference-on-anti-masonry/ Academic Conference on Anti-masonry]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20160222050920/http://ue.ucdavis.edu/explorations/2005/bruzas.pdf The New Anti-Masonic Movement in America, University California, Davis]

{{Freemasonry footer}}
{{Discrimination}}
{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Anti-Masonry| ]]
[[Category:Freemasonry]]
[[Category:Masonic organizations]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>