<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20041027205558|6988722" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="2866512" pageid="2866512" ns="0" title="Anti-Masonry"><revisions><rev timestamp="2004-10-30T19:22:25Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">The arguments against freemasonry thus far reviewed:


==Religious Tolerance==

Opinions about [[Freemasonry]] around the world may differ from place to place, but [[Freemasons]] always stress non dogmatism and tolerance (albeit often within certain defined limits). This openness has led to friction between Freemasonry and organizations which hold a negative view on [[ecumenism]], or are themselves intolerant towards other forms of belief and worship. Masons have been opposed throughout history by various biased religious groups, such as some [[Protestants]] and certain [[Muslims]].

The most vigorous opposition to the fraternity, however, has come from the [[Catholic Church]], but this body was also responsible for the [[Spanish inquisition]] and the attempt to convert Paganism (all these things were done for the same reason). Historically, Catholicism is by nature opposed to any movement it deems a threat to its attempt to monopolize state religion. Masonry by its nature is one such threat. 

The first papal condemnation of Freemasonry came in 1738 from [[Pope Clement XII]] in his papal bull "''Eminenti Apostolatus Specula''", repeated by several later popes, notably [[Pope Leo XIII]] in the "''encyclical Humanum Genus''" (1884).
 
The 1917 Code of [[Canon Law]] explicitly declares that joining [[Freemasonry]] entailed automatic [[excommunication]]; the revised Code issued in 1983 does not explicitly name Masonic orders among the secret societies condemned in canon 1374. 

However, in a letter to the [[United States]] Bishops from the [[Congregation for the Doctrine of the Faith|Office of the Sacred Congregation for the Doctrine of the Faith]], the interpretation was made clear&amp;mdash;the prohibition against [[Catholics]] joining Masonic orders remains. Many Catholic Masons in the US choose to rely on the letter of the law. Masons on the other hand do not exclude any view of a religious hierarchy so long as it is headed by a supreme being.

One reason the Free Methodist Church was founded in the 1860s was that its founders believed the [[Methodist Church]] was being influenced by Freemasons and members of [[secret societies]]. The Free [[Methodist]] Church continues to prohibit its members from also joining societies such as the Freemasons. Recently the Southern [[Baptist]] Convention, the largest association of Baptists in the United States, also stated that participation in Freemasonry is inconsistent with its beliefs.

This form of criticism has been markedly reduced since modern nation states like the [[USA]] and [[Europe]] in general are founded on religious tolerance, and many adherents of the religions that formally opposed Masons now believe in the main Masonic principles.

==Political conspiracy theories involving the Masons==

Nowadays, the main theme of anti-Masonic criticism involves the idea that Masons involve their organization in covert political activities. This assumption has been influenced by the assertion of Masons that many political figures in the past 300 years have been Masons. Opinions vary between opposing theories concerning this paradox. 

Some say the Masons constantly plot to increase their power and wealth, others say the Masonic Brotherhood is engaged in a plot to produce a new world order of a type different (usually more sinister) then the existing world order. These theories would be possible to describe almost any secret society (since a society with secret meetings allows secret coordination, the very essence of a conspiracy). Nevertheless, Masons have been the largest target because of their size and notable membership. 

The historical complaints that the Masons have secretly plotted to create society based on their ideals of [[liberty]], [[social equality|equality]], [[fraternity]], and [[religious tolerance]], are not denied by Masons. In an enlightened age many have now accepted the core Masonic values as stated, and persistent enemies of the society have been forced to come up with more sinister motives as to what Freemasons allegedly conspire to achieve.

==Criticisms of Masonic 'Cronyism'==

Another criticism that may or not have to do with the specific nature of Freemasonry, but may be applied generally to any type of organization or [[secret society]], is the practice of cronyism, or giving favors to fellow members. Anecdotely many have the impression that one increases chances for employment by joining the Masons. This type of cronyism can be seen in the movie "Gypsie", where possibly not talking about the Freemasons, but referencing fraternities like the Moose Lodge, the general idea is alluded to. Unscrupulous Masons have been known to claim they can get out of driving tickets because of Masonic logos on their car. Again, this criticism can be easily applied to almost any fraternity, but the Masons are a big target because they are not simply based in colleges, because they are the largest fraternity, and because they are worldwide.

==Criticisms based on the moral faults of known Masons==

Although an institution with religious overtones can be criticized for the moral faults of some of its members, Freemasonry is liable to criticism especially because amongst it aims is the drive to improve its members [[morality]], above and beyond whatever religion the individual member might profess his preference for. 

A general fault ascribed to the Masons is that he will be charitable mainly to other Masons, an assumption which is made worse by the class and racial inequalities sometimes leveled against in Masonic lodges. The phrase '[[charity]] begins at home' goes some way to justify this natural proclivity.

Critics attack what they perceive as a preoccupation ritual minutiae and personal status (ie. degree, a concept critics call similar to the thrill of an [[Role-playing game|RPG]] level) within the hierarchy of the organization. Some critics argue that the Freemasons are primarily a social club. All of these arguments however can be said to have the logical fallicy commonly applied to Christians, that if certain members of a group are bad the group in and of itself must be bad.

==Criticism that Freemasonry is a new religion==

In a sectarian age many hold that Freemasonry is a new religion. Externally it has many similarities to what many people consider to be a religion, it has its own version of the Bible, it has its own way of saying "amen" ("So mote it be", the literal translation of "amen"), it has far more developed rituals then most Protestant denominations, some groups of Masons (especially the Scottish rite) call their lodges "temples", and it has a large amount of iconography and symbolism. From the perspective of most religions, who feel that they have the perfect system of morality, any competing system of morality can be considered opposed to them&amp;mdash;and if not stricly another religion, then certainly an opponent.

Such ritual observances as practiced by Masons in private meetings should be seen in the same context as rituals maintained in the military services, in government and civil authorities. It has been argued that any organized system of morality (which the Masons claim to be) is a religion; the [[Green Party]] might thus qualify as such.

==Criticism that Freemasonry worships Satan==

While the practice of any given magical or mystical system is not particularly associated with Freemasonry (mainstream [[Masonry]] has always tended more to [[rationalism]] than to [[mysticism]]), there are some groups of Masons, such as Masonic [[Rosicrucian]]s, that may interpret Masonic ritual magically (or "hermetically"), which is their right as Masons, given the fraternity's non-dogmatic stance. 

The very existence of hermetic interpretations within Masonry has lead some reactionary Christians to label Freemasonry as "[[Satanic]]". This charge is commonly made about any hermetic society with practices beyond the understanding of uninformed critics (although paradoxically this can not be fully rectified due to the secret nature of such societies).

Many Anti-Masonic activists quote Albert Pike's ''Morals and Dogma'' to "prove" that Masons worship Lucifer. This is known as the [[Taxil hoax]]: the Pike book itself can be found easily, and does not contain the quote.

==Criticism of masonic blood oaths==

The traditional Masonic obligations, said to be undertaken by a candidate during the initiation ritual, are sometimes called "blood oaths", particularly by those critical of the fraternity. The candidate wishes severe physical punishment upon himself should he ever reveal the secrets of Freemasonry to a non-Mason. While many non-Masons are horrified by this, Masons defend the traditional obligations as no more literal than the commonplace childhood "blood oaths", like "cross my heart and hope to die"&amp;mdash;a very psychologically powerful way to express a serious bond or promise. 

In addition, some Masons argue that the bloody punishments mentioned in the obligations are, historically, references to the punishments that the state used to inflict on defenders of civil liberties and religious freedoms, such as Freemasons. But in spite of repeated attempts to defend them, by the early 1980s, the "blood oaths" had become quite problematic from a public relations standpoint, and most Masonic jurisdictions replaced them with more politically correct "bloodless oaths".

Certain conspiracy theorists look at certain historical killings and deduce that they were done as a fulfillment of the blood oath. In particular, [[Jack the Ripper]] is theorized by some to have been a Mason made psychotic for having to carry out a blood oath, and who then killed random people in the same fashion.
 
It should be noted that there are only 3 penalties that Masonry can impose on a member&amp;mdash;censure, suspension of membership and expulsion.

==Criticisms of the process of becoming a Freemason==

It is commonly held that individuals become Freemasons through invitation, patrimony, or other non-democratic means, officially an individual must ask freely and without persuasion to become a Freemason in order to join the fraternity. 

This arrangement is said to conflict with the Freemasons mission to "make good men better", on the basis that a hidden society can not promote itself publicly. If the society is secret, it is argued, how is good man supposed to be attracted to it? 

In practice, Freemasons have been known to not question the motives of anyone seeking to enter, but clearly members are going to prefer invitation to those individuals who can offer something of value to the group, and will thus indicate to potential members some clue, it is then incumbent upon the seeker to make the request.

The view that, in order to join the Society, one must "... be the son of a ... [Freemason]", is logical, such a method goes some way to explain how often membership is extended to newcomers. This method shadows the traditions of peerage. 

Many of these myths have taken hold in the imagination of "conspiracy buffs" partly because Freemasons, like government intelligence agencies and big business, understanding the value of misinformation, let the uninitiated argue amongst themselves, so that the truth remains private. Masons have only attempted in recent years to make their organization seem more open to public view, but remain non-committal beyond their own objectives of diverting government scrutiny and validating good public relations.

(see [1] (http://www.masonicinfo.com/ masonic info.com)).

==In defense of liberty==

It has been said that "''the Freemason builds his life around the moral principals that lie at the heart of the Craft, and becomes in his every word and deed the epitome of brotherly love, relief and truth ~ he will thus respect the rights of others to hold beliefs and attitudes that differ radically from his own, for he knows that tolerance is an essential part of brotherly love.''" 

''(Freemasonry, A Celebration of the Craft'~ 1993. Edited by Hamill &amp; Gilbert for Terry Allan)''.

The need for vigilance in the defense of human liberty is as great in society as it is said to be within the craft, yet by means of an increased compatibility with the common aims of human achievement the Freemasons have indisputably laid the foundations for very many of the cultural norms prevalent in the western World.
 
The duty of Masons to "give to the cause of Charity" was stressed by [[Preston_William|William Preston]], in his ''Illustrations of Masonry'' of 1772, when he wrote: "To relive the distressed is a duty incumbent on all men, but particularly on Freemasons, who are linked together by an indissoluble chain of sincere affection. 

"''To soothe the unhappy, to sympathize with their misfortunes, to compassionate their miseries and to restore their troubled minds, is the great aim we have in view.''"

A Mason's duty is also in his loyalty, as a peaceful subject, to the civil authority found wherever he resides or works, and it is on these grounds, restrained from pursuing any means of disrupting the established rule of law, that Freemasonry is itself a reformist institution, its members abstaining from any thought of association with rebellion, the cause of the common man, when oppressed. 

"Masonic Ritual" is reported as an aspect of the craft that reinforces its Spiritual dimension and is Biblical in origin, (but is claimed to derive from sources of a pre [[Christian]] age, whence evolved Cabalistic thought). A legend considered of great import to the Masonic Rite is that of the story of the building and reconstruction of [[King Solomon]]'s Temple&amp;mdash;as an allegory of the creation of a new, just and more tolerant society.</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>