<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20071114033254|171357827" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="2866512" pageid="2866512" ns="0" title="Anti-Masonry"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-11-14T03:33:12Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Freemasonry2}}
'''Anti-Masonry''' (alternatively called '''Anti-Freemasonry''') is defined as "Avowed opposition to [[Freemasonry]]".&lt;ref name="antimasonrydef"&gt;Oxford English Dictionary (1979 ed., p. 369).&lt;/ref&gt; However, there is no homogeneous anti-Masonic movement. Anti-Masonry consists of radically differing criticisms from sometimes incompatible groups who are hostile to Freemasonry in some form.

==Origin==
Matthias Pöhlmann of the Protestant Centre for Religious and Ideological Issues of the [[Evangelical Church in Germany]] refers&lt;ref name="EZW"&gt;Matthias Pöhlmann: ''Verschwiegene Männer'', Protestant Centre for Religious and Ideological Issues of the [[Evangelical Church in Germany]]&lt;/ref&gt; to the political scientist [[:de:Armin Pfahl-Traughber|prof. Dr. Armin Pfahl-Traughber]]&lt;ref name="Pfahl-Traughber"&gt;prof. Dr. Pfahl-Traughber: ''Der antisemitisch-antifreimaurerische Verschwörungsmythos''&lt;/ref&gt; for the claim that the first Anti-Masonic conspiracy myth was created in Germany.&lt;ref name="Pöhlmann"&gt;Matthias Pöhlmann referring to [[:de:Armin Pfahl-Traughber|Dr. Armin Pfahl-Traughber]]&lt;ref name="Pfahl-Traughber" /&gt;: „Der Freimaurer-Verschwörungsmythos wurde in Deutschland aufgebracht.“&lt;/ref&gt; According to Pöhlmann, an anonymous book titled ''Enthüllungen des Systems der Weltbürger-Politik'' (“Disclosure of the System of Cosmopolitan Politics”) was published in 1786. Its author was an employee of the Weimar city government, Ernst August von Göchhausen (1740–1824)&lt;ref name="Pfahl-Traughber" /&gt;. He described an alleged cosmopolitan conspiracy of Freemasons, Illuminati and Jesuits and predicts unavoidable world revolutions&lt;ref name="EZW" /&gt;. This was three years before the French Revolution, which seemed to confirm his prophecies, and the alleged Anti-Masonic conspiracy became a powerful weapon of propaganda&lt;ref name="EZW" /&gt;. Freemasons were accused to be the driving force behind the destruction of the existing social system and the alliance between Throne and Church&lt;ref name="EZW" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Biberstein"&gt;Dr. Johannes Rogalla von Biberstein, historian and librarian of the University of Bielefeld: ''Die These von der Verschwörung 1776–1945. Philosophen, Freimaurer, Juden, Liberale und Sozialisten gegen die Sozialordnung'', Flensburg 1992&lt;/ref&gt;. Supporters of the Anti-Masonic conspiracy theories were especially Christian counterrevolutionaries&lt;ref name="EZW" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Biberstein" /&gt; who saw Freemasons behind every force against the social system.&lt;ref name="EZW" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Biberstein" /&gt; Their main goal in the defamation campaign against Freemasonry was the expansion of Liberalism and Socialism, religious tolerance and the enlightening rationalism.&lt;ref name="EZW" /&gt; Until the 19th century this viewpoint dominated Anti-Masonic publications.

==Political Anti-Masonry==
===American Political Anti-Masonry (1830s-1850s)===
{{main|William Morgan (anti-Mason)|Anti-Masonic Party}}

In 1826, [[William Morgan (anti-Mason)|William Morgan]] disappeared from the small town of Batavia, New York, after threatening to expose Freemasonry's "secrets" by publishing its rituals.  His disappearance caused some Anti-masons to claim that he had been kidnapped, and murdered, by Masons. Morgan's disappearance sparked a series of protests against Freemasonry, which eventually spread to the political realm.  Under the leadership of anti-Masonic [[Thurlow Weed]], an [[Andrew Jackson|Anti-Jacksonist]] movement became (since Jackson was a Mason) the  [[Anti-Masonic Party]]. This political Party ran presidential candidates in [[1828]] and [[1832]], but by [[1835]] the party had disbanded everywhere except [[Pennsylvania]].

===British Political Anti-Masonry (1990s-current)===
Since 1997, several members of the British Government have attempted to pass laws requiring Freemasons who join the police or judiciary&lt;ref name="Newjudgesmustdeclaremasonicmembership"&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk/politics/57381.stm "New judges must declare masonic membership"], BBC, March 5, 1998, retrieved Feb 26, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; to declare their membership publicly to the government amid accusations of Freemasons performing acts of mutual advancement and favor-swapping. This movement was initially led by [[Jack Straw (politician)|Jack Straw]], [[Home Secretary]] from 1997 until 2001.&lt;ref name="Newjudgesmustdeclaremasonicmembership" /&gt; In 1999, the [[Welsh Assembly]] became the only body in the United Kingdom to place a legal requirement on membership declaration for Freemasons.&lt;ref name="Freemasonpolicyreviewdue"&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/wales/1699189.stm "Freemason policy review due
"], BBC, Dec 8, 2001, retrieved Feb 26, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; Currently, existing members of the police and judiciary in England are asked to voluntarily admit to being Freemasons.&lt;ref name="HouseofCommonsresponce"&gt; [http://www.parliament.the-stationery-office.com/pa/cm200506/cmhansrd/vo050721/text/50721w69.htm#50721w69.html_sbhd0 "House of Commons Hansard Written Answers for 21 Jul 2005 (pt 69) "], UK House of Commons, July 21, 2005, retrieved Oct 2, 2007&lt;/ref&gt; However, all first time successful judiciary candidates "must declare their freemasonry status" before appointment.&lt;ref name="HouseofCommonsresponce" /&gt; Conversely, new members of the police are not required to declare their status.&lt;ref name="HouseofCommonsresponce" /&gt;

In 2004, [[Rhodri Morgan]], the [[First Minister of Wales|First Minister of the Welsh Assembly]], said that he blocked Gerard Elias' appointment to counsel general because of links to hunting and freemasonry&lt;ref name="Morgancriticisedoverjobblocking"&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/wales/3557279.stm "Morgan criticised over job blocking"], BBC, March 22, 2004, retrieved Feb 26, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;, although it was claimed by non-Labour politicians that the real reason was in order to have a Labour supporter, Malcolm Bishop, in the role.&lt;ref name="mbishop"&gt;"Mr Morgan wanted another QC, Malcolm Bishop, who has stood as a Labour candidate and is a close associate of former Lord Chancellor Derry Irvine." [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/wales/3530987.stm Morgan 'blocked' QC appointment]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Persecution and Holocaust under Totalitarian Regimes===
{{main|Freemasonry under Totalitarian Regimes}}
{{see also|Freemasonry|Holocaust}}

In the [[twentieth century]] [[totalitarian]] regimes, both [[Fascist]] and [[Communist]], have treated Freemasonry as a potential source of opposition. Masonic writers state that the language used by the totalitarian regimes is similar to that used by some modern critics of Freemasonry.&lt;ref name="bessel.tolalitarian"&gt;Bigotry and the Murder of Freemasonry, Paul M. Bessel, 1994, [http://bessel.org/naziartl.htm 'Bigotry and the Murder of Freemasonry'] - "These people who attack Masonry with exaggerated language, and without accepting reasonable explanations of what Freemasonry really is, would probably say that their use of language about Masonry that is strikingly similar to that which was used by the Nazis and other vicious attackers of Freemasonry in the past does not mean that they are following in the footsteps of the Nazis."&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Image:Red triangle.svg|right|60px]]
Consistently considered an ideological foe of [[Nazism]] in their world perception (''Weltauffassung''), Freemasonic Concentration Camp inmates were graded as “Political” prisoners, and wore an inverted (point down) ''[[Nazi concentration camp badges|red triangle]]''. &lt;ref&gt;''The Encyclopedia of the Holocaust'', volume 2, page 531, citing Katz, ''Jews and Freemasons in Europe''.&lt;/ref&gt; 

The number of Freemasons from Nazi occupied countries who were killed is not accurately known,  but it is estimated that between 80,000 and 200,000 Freemasons perished under the Nazi regime. &lt;ref name="holocaust"&gt;Freemasons for Dummies, by [http://members.aol.com/brlodge/whymasons.html Christopher Hodapp], Wiley Publishing Inc., Indianapolis, 2005, p.85, sec. ''Hitler and the Nazi''&lt;/ref&gt;  The Government of the [[United Kingdom]] established [[Holocaust Memorial Day (UK)|Holocaust Memorial Day]] &lt;ref&gt;http://www.hmd.org.uk/about/&lt;/ref&gt; to recognise all groups who were targets of the Nazi regime, and counter [[Holocaust denial]].  Freemasons are listed as being among those who were targeted.

===Iraqi Baathist Anti-Masonry===
In 1980, the Iraqi legal and penal code was changed by [[Saddam Hussein]] and the ruling [[Ba'ath Party]], thereby making it a felony to "promote or acclaim [[Zionism|Zionist]] principles, including freemasonry, or who associate [themselves] with Zionist organizations."&lt;ref name="freemasonryinSHIraq"&gt;"Saddam to be formally charged", The Washington Times, 2004, retrieved March 1, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

===Freemasonry and Patriotism===
Freemasonry is often alleged to hold back its members from fully committing to their nation&lt;ref name"cathencpat"&gt;"Another characteristic of Masonic law is that "treason" and "rebellion" against civil authority are declared only political crimes, which affect the good standing of a Brother no more than heresy, and furnish no ground for a Masonic trial." [http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/09771a.htm Masonry (Freemasonry)] from the Catholic Encyclopedia, partially quoting Mackey, "Jurisprudence", 509.&lt;/ref&gt;. Critics claim that compared to Operative Masonry's clear denunciations of treachery&lt;ref name="GLE"&gt;"2nd -- You shall be true liegemen to the King of England without any treason or falsehood, and if you know of any that you amend it privily, if you may, or else warn the King and his Council of it by declaring it to his officers."&lt;/ref&gt; Masonry after 1723 (Speculative masonry) was far more ambiguous&lt;ref name="charges"&gt;[http://freemasonry.bcy.ca/history/anderson/charges.html II. Of the CIVIL MAGISTRATES supreme and subordinate] "A Mason is a peaceable Subject to the Civil Powers, wherever he resides or works, and is never to be concern'd in Plots and Conspiracies against the Peace and Welfare of the Nation, nor to behave himself undutifully to inferior Magistrates; for as Masonry hath been always injured by War, Bloodshed, and Confusion, so ancient Kings and Princes have been much dispos'd to encourage the Craftsmen, because of their Peaceableness and Loyalty, whereby they practically answer'd the Cavils of their Adversaries, and promoted the Honour of the Fraternity, who ever flourish'd in Times of Peace. So that if a Brother should be a Rebel against the State he is not to be countenanc'd in his Rebellion, however he may be pitied as an unhappy Man; and, if convicted of no other Crime though the loyal Brotherhood must and ought to disown his Rebellion, and give no Umbrage or Ground of political Jealousy to the Government for the time being; they cannot expel him from the Lodge, and his Relation to it remains indefeasible."&lt;/ref&gt;. It is alleged in the Catholic Encyclopedia that Masonic disapproval of treachery is not on moral grounds but on the grounds of inconvenience to other Masons.&lt;ref name="inconv"&gt;"The brotherhood ought to disown the rebellion, but only in order to preserve the fraternity from annoyance by the civil authorities." from the article [http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/09771a.htm Masonry (Freemasonry)] in the Catholic Encyclopedia&lt;/ref&gt; The ''Catholic Encyclopedia'' argues&lt;ref name="CEFMCh"&gt;"Such language would equally suit every anarchistic movement." [http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/09771a.htm Masonry (Freemasonry)] in the Catholic Encyclopedia&lt;/ref&gt; that the adage "Loyalty to freedom overrides all other considerations" &lt;ref name="FMch"&gt;"If we were to assert that under no circumstances had a Mason been found willing to take arms against a bad government, we should only be declaring that, in trying moments, when duty, in the masonic sense, to state means antagonism to the Government, they had failed in the highest and most sacred duty of a citizen. Rebellion in some cases is a sacred duty, and none, but a bigot or a fool, will say, that our countrymen were in the wrong, when they took arms against King James II. Loyalty to freedom in a case of this kind overrides all other considerations, and when to rebel means to be free or to perish, it would be idle to urge that a man must remember obligations which were never intended to rob him of his status of a human being and a citizen. ", "Freemason's Chronicle" 1875, I, 81, quoted as footnote [89] in [http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/09771a.htm Masonry (Freemasonry)] in the Catholic Encyclopedia&lt;/ref&gt; justifies treason.

American Freemasons are consistent advocates of the US Constitution in [[separation of church and state]]&lt;ref name="sepchustate"&gt;"Freemasonry Does Not Support any particular political position. It has long stood for separation of Church and State, and has been a champion of Free Public Education." From a [http://www.arkmason.com/didknow.htm speech given by Bill Jones] Grand Master of Arkansas, 1996&lt;/ref&gt;, which was seen especially by the Catholic church as a veiled attack on the Church's place in public life.&lt;ref name="etsi4"&gt;[[Pope Leo XIII]] [http://www.ewtn.com/library/ENCYC/L13ITL.HTM ETSI NOS (On Conditions in Italy)]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Modern conspiracy theories==
{{main|Masonic conspiracy theories}}
Due to its secretive nature Freemasonry has long been a target of [[Conspiracy theories (a collection)|conspiracy theories]] in which it is either bent on world domination or already secretly in control of world politics.

Historically, complaints have been made that the Masons have secretly plotted to create a society based on the revolutionary ideals of [[liberty]], [[social equality|equality]], [[Brotherhood|fraternity]], [[separation of church and state]] and (in Nazi Germany) a Jewish plot for [[Religious toleration|religious tolerance]].&lt;ref name="hitler.religioustolerance"&gt;Hitler, Adolf.  ''Mein Kampf: Volume One - A Reckoning''. "[Chapter XI: Nation and Race, http://www.adolfhitler.ws/lib/books/43kampf/kampf43.htm]" 1924, trans. 1943. - "Finally, the Jewish influence on economic affairs grows with terrifying speed through the stock exchange. He becomes the owner, or at least the controller, of the national labor force. To strengthen his political position he tries to tear down the racial and civil barriers which for a time continue to restrain him at every step. To this end he fights with all the tenacity innate in him for religious tolerance-and in Freemasonry, which has succumbed to him completely, he has an excellent instrument with which to fight for his aims and put them across. The governing circles and the higher strata of the political and economic bourgeoisie are brought into his nets by the strings of Freemasonry, and never need to suspect what is happening."&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, some Anti-Masons have claimed that Freemasonry is a Jewish front for world domination, or is at least controlled by Jews for this goal. An example of this is the notorious [[literary forgery]] ''[[The Protocols of the Elders of Zion]]''. Hitler outlawed Freemasonry partially for this reason.&lt;ref name="hitler.jewscontrolfreemasonry"&gt;Hitler, Adolf. ''Mein Kampf: Volume Two - The National Socialist Movement'',
"[Chapter XIII: German Alliance Policy after the War http://www.adolfhitler.ws/lib/books/43kampf/kampf43.htm]", 1924, trans. 1943. - "The fight which Fascist Italy waged against Jewry's three principal weapons, the profound reasons for which may not have been consciously understood (though I do not believe this myself) furnishes the best proof that the poison fangs of that Power which transcends all State boundaries are being drawn, even though in an indirect way. The prohibition of Freemasonry and secret societies, the suppression of the supernational Press and the definite abolition of Marxism, together with the steadily increasing consolidation of the Fascist concept of the State &amp;mdash; all this will enable the Italian Government, in the course of some years, to advance more and more the interests of the Italian people without paying any attention to the hissing of the Jewish world-hydra."&lt;/ref&gt; The covenant of the Palestinian Islamist movement [[Hamas]] claims that Freemasonry is a "secret society" founded as part of a Zionist plot to control the world.&lt;ref name="Hamas"&gt;[http://www.library.cornell.edu/colldev/mideast/hamas.htm 'The Covenant of the Islamic Resistance Movement (HAMAS)-Palestine'], Art. XVII, XXII, and XXVIII, 18 Aug 1988. Retrieved 29 October 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;

There are also many other religious and political conspiracy theories, most regarding the United States government, from claiming all the Presidents as Masons&lt;ref name="famous freemasons"&gt;[http://www.geocities.com/endtimedeception/famous.htm endtimedeception]&lt;/ref&gt;, and also that Masons were involved in the JFK assassination&lt;ref&gt;Downard, James Shelby, and Michael A. Hoffman II. [http://www.revisionisthistory.org/kingkill33.html "King-Kill/33°: Masonic Symbolism in the Assassination of John F. Kennedy]", 1987.  Website excerpt, 1998. Retrieved 16 July 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;), or that there are Masonic symbols in federal buildings and architecture.

==Religious Anti-Masonry==
===Christian anti-Masonry===
{{main|Christianity and Freemasonry}}
{{main|Catholicism and Freemasonry}}

A number of Protestant and Eastern Orthodox denominations discourage their congregants from joining Masonic lodges, although this differs in intensity according to the denomination.  Some simply express mild concern as to whether Freemasonry is compatible with Christianity while, at the other extreme, some accuse the fraternity of outright devil worship.  

The [[Roman Catholic Church]] has often been seen to be in conflict with Freemasonry, which it sees as tending to [[anticlericalism]] and [[deism]]. The Church [[Catholicism and Freemasonry#Ban on Membership|forbids]] [[Catholics]] from becoming Freemasons - until 1983 the penalty for joining was [[excommunication]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/05678a.htm newadvent.org] page on excommunication&lt;/ref&gt;.

In [[1983]], the [[Code of Canon Law]] was changed, and explicit reference to Freemasonry omitted. It reads: (Can. 1374) "a person who joins an association which plots against the Church is to be punished with a just penalty; one who promotes or takes office in such an association is to be punished with an [[interdict]]" (a penalty barring an offender from the Sacraments). 

This change caused some confusion among both Catholics and Freemasons.  Did it mean that membership was now allowed, so long as the Masonic Lodge did not plot against the Church?  The matter was quickly clarified in a declaration of the [[Congregation for the Doctrine of the Faith]], ''[[Quaesitum est]]'' (1983)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/roman_curia/congregations/cfaith/documents/rc_con_cfaith_doc_19831126_declaration-masonic_en.html text] of Quaestum Est&lt;/ref&gt;, which restated the traditional ban on Freemasonry. It reiterated that Catholic masons may not receive Holy Communion.

===Muslim anti-Masonry===
{{Further|[[Holocaust denial#In the Muslim world|Holocaust denial in the Muslim world]], [[Anti-Masonry#Iraqi Baathist Anti-Masonry|Iraqi Baathist Anti-Masonry]] and [[Hamas#The Covenant of Hamas|The Covenant of Hamas]]}}

[[Islamic]] anti-Masonry is closely tied with [[Anti-Semitism]] and [[Anti-Zionism]], though other criticisms are made.{{fact|date=November 2007}}

==Notes and references==
&lt;references/&gt;

==See also==
* [[Anti-Masonic Party]]
* [[Taxil hoax]]
* [[Catholicism and Freemasonry]]
* [[Anti-clericalism]]
* [[Propaganda Due]] - The P2 Masonic Lodge Scandal
* [[Secret society]] 
* [[Mormonism and Freemasonry]]

==External links==
===Critical of Freemasonry===
*[http://www.conspiracyarchive.com/NWO/Freemasonry.htm Conspiracy Archive] Masons and the Occult article.
*[http://www.masoncode.com/The%20Jewels%20of%20Freemasonry.htm The Jewels of Freemasonry - Unzipped] - an exposition of secret Masonic symbolism.
*[http://www.ephesians5-11.org An explanation of why Christians should lead people away from the Masonic Lodge]
*[http://www.islamqa.com/index.php?ref=34576&amp;ln=eng An Islamic view about Freemasonry ], and ruling on joining the Masons.

===Supportive of Freemasonry===
*[http://srmason-sj.org/web/SRpublications/DeHoyos.htm ''Is It True What They Say About Freemasonry?''] a look at how anti-Masonic argument functions. Written by freemasons, their research is cited.
*[http://masonicinfo.com masonicinfo.com]
*[http://www.freemasonry.bcy.ca/anti-masonry/anti-masonry_faq.html Anti-masonry Frequently Asked Questions]
*[http://www.freemasons-freemasonry.com/gazzo_antimasonry.html  Anti-Masonry in the contemporary world] Integralisms, Business and Media. A Report on the fighters of Freemasons' ideal of Liberty 

[[Category:Anti-Masonry]]

[[fr:Antimaçonnisme]]
[[nl:Anti-vrijmetselarij]]
[[pt:Antimaçonaria]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>