<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20161105022320|747903203" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="30101125" pageid="30101125" ns="0" title="Discrimination against people with HIV/AIDS"><revisions><rev timestamp="2016-11-15T03:35:36Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{merge from|HIV exceptionalism|date=May 2015}}
'''Discrimination against people living with [[HIV/AIDS]] ('PLHIV' or 'PLHA' or 'PLWHA')  )''' is the experience of prejudice against PLHIV which falls within the purview of the law. Discrimination is one manifestation of [[Social stigma|stigma]]. Stigmatizing, attitudes, and behaviors may fall under the rubric of discrimination depending on the legislation of a particular country.

{{Discrimination sidebar}}
HIV/AIDS stigma exists around the world in a lot of different ways, including [[shunning|ostracism]], [[Social rejection|rejection]], [[discrimination]] and avoidance. HIV testing without permission or security may be considered as wrongdoings towards those with HIV.  compulsory HIV testing without prior [[consent]] or protection of [[confidentiality]]; violence against HIV infected individuals or people who are perceived to be infected with HIV; the [[quarantine]] of HIV infected individuals&lt;ref name=UNAIDS2006Ch4&gt;{{Cite book
| publisher =[[Joint United Nations Programme on HIV/AIDS|UNAIDS]]
| year = 2006
| title = 2006 Report on the global AIDS epidemic
| chapter = The impact of AIDS on people and societies
| chapterurl = http://data.unaids.org/pub/GlobalantiReport/2006/2006_GR_CH04_en.pdf
| accessdate = 2006-06-14
| format= PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt; and, in some cases, the loss of property rights when a spouse dies.&lt;ref&gt;Huairou Commission http://www.huairou.org/sites/default/files/Women%20HIV%20LAND%20working%20draft%207-15-10%20-%20black%20and%20white%20version.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; Stigmas that are violence or the fear of violence stops a lot of individuals for getting tested for HIV, which does not aid in curing the virus. 

HIV/AIDS stigma has been further divided into the following three categories:

*''Instrumental AIDS stigma''—a reflection of the fear and apprehension that are likely to be associated with any deadly and transmissible illness.&lt;ref name=Herek1999&gt;{{Cite journal
|vauthors=Herek GM, Capitanio JP | journal=American Behavioral Scientist | year=1999
| url=http://psychology.ucdavis.edu/rainbow/html/abs99_sp.pdf
| format= PDF
| title=AIDS Stigma and sexual prejudice
| accessdate = 2006-03-27
| volume=42
| issue=7
| pages=1130–1147
| doi=10.1177/0002764299042007006

}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*''Symbolic AIDS stigma''—the use of HIV/AIDS to express attitudes toward the social groups or lifestyles perceived to be associated with the disease.&lt;ref name=Herek1999 /&gt;
*''Courtesy AIDS stigma''—stigmatization of people connected to the issue of HIV/AIDS or HIV- positive people.&lt;ref name=Snyder&gt;{{Cite journal|vauthors=Snyder M, Omoto AM, Crain AL |
title=Punished for their good deeds: stigmatization for AIDS volunteers |
journal=American Behavioral Scientist | year=1999 | pages=1175–1192 | volume=42 | issue=7 | doi=10.1177/0002764299042007009

}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Much HIV/AIDS stigma or discrimination involves [[homosexuality]], [[bisexuality]], [[promiscuity]], [[sex worker]]s, and [[Intravenous drug use (recreational)|intravenous drug use]].&lt;ref&gt;Understanding HIV/AIDS Stigma and Discrimination http://www.socialworkers.org/practice/hiv_aids/AIDS_Day2012.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

In many [[Developed country|developed countries]], there is a strong correlation between '''HIV/AIDS and male homosexuality''' or bisexuality (the CDC states, "(Gay, bisexual, and other men who have sex with men (MSM) represent approximately 2% of the United States population, yet are the population most severely affected by HIV."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cdc.gov/hiv/risk/gender/msm/facts/|title=CDC – Fact Sheet - Gay and Bisexual Men – Gender – Risk – HIV/AIDS|publisher=|accessdate=18 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;), and this association is correlated with higher levels of sexual prejudice such as [[homophobia|homophobic]] attitudes.&lt;ref name=Herek2002&gt;{{Cite journal
|vauthors=Herek GM, Capitanio JP, Widaman KF |title=HIV-related stigma and knowledge in the United States: prevalence and trends, 1991-1999
|journal=Am J Public Health
|volume=92
|issue=3
|pages=371–7
|year=2002
|pmid=11867313
|doi=10.2105/AJPH.92.3.371
|url=http://psychology.ucdavis.edu/rainbow/html/ajph2002.pdf
|accessdate=2008-03-10
|format=PDF
|pmc=1447082}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many people also believe that aids are related to homosexuality. An early name for AIDS, [[gay-related immune deficiency]] or GRID, shows this history. During the early 1980s, HIV/AIDS was "a disorder that appears to affect primarily male homosexuals".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author1=Lawrence K. Altman|title=New Homosexual Disorder Worries Health Officials|url=http://www.nytimes.com/1982/05/11/science/new-homosexual-disorder-worries-health-officials.html|accessdate=August 8, 2015|work=The New York Times|date=May 11, 1982}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some forms of serious discrimination can include: not being permitted for a job, being prohibited to buy a house, have to pay extra money when renting a housing, etc. People who have or may HIV/AIDS, face a tremendous amount of discrimination in different areas of life.  In the United States, disability laws prohibit HIV/AIDS discrimination in housing, employment, education, and access to health and social services. The [[U.S. Department of Housing and Urban Development]]'s [[Office of Fair Housing and Equal Opportunity]] enforces laws prohibiting housing discrimination based on actual or perceived&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://portal.hud.gov/hudportal/HUD?src=/program_offices/fair_housing_equal_opp/LGBT_Housing_Discrimination|title=FH_LGBT_PAGE|publisher=|accessdate=18 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; HIV/AIDS status.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://portal.hud.gov/hudportal/HUD?src=/program_offices/fair_housing_equal_opp/disabilities/inhousing|title=People with Disabilities - HUD|publisher=|accessdate=18 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Structural violence ==
{{Main article|Structural violence}}

Structural violence is an important factor in the treatment of people living with AIDS. Paul Farmer argues that social determinants affecting the lives of certain cultural groups alter their risk of infections and their ability to access treatment.&lt;ref name="Farmer2006"&gt;{{cite news|last=Farmer|first=Paul|author2=Bruce Nizeye|author3=Sara Stulac|author4=Salmaan Keshavjee|title=Structural Violence and Clinical Medicine|year=2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; For example, access to prophylaxis, access to antiretroviral therapy, and susceptibility to illness and malnutrition are all factors which change people's overall risk of illness due to HIV/AIDS. This causes large difference in the rate of illness due to HIV/AIDS in various social/cultural groups. Farmer also argues that social intervention may be key in altering the gap in treatment between these groups of people. Educating doctors on the interactions between social life and healthcare would help level out the injustices in healthcare.

==Research==
Current research has found that discrimination against people living with HIV is a contributing factor for delayed initiation of HIV treatment.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Pharris|title=Community patterns of stigma towards persons living with HIV: A population based latent class analysis from rural Vietnam|journal=BMC Public Health|year=2011|volume=11|page=705|display-authors=1|author2=&lt;Please add first missing authors to populate metadata.&gt;|doi=10.1186/1471-2458-11-705 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  As many as 20-40% of Americans who are HIV+ do not begin a care regimen within the first 6 months after diagnosis.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Mugavero|title=Improving engagement in HIV care: What can we do?|journal=Top HIV Med|year=2008|volume=16|pages=156–161|pmid=19106431|first1=MJ|issue=5}}&lt;/ref&gt;  When individuals begin treatment late in the progression of HIV (when CD4+ T cell counts are below 500 cells/µL), they have 1.94 times the risk of mortality compared to those whose treatment is initiated when CD4+ T cells are still about 500 cells/µL.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Panel on Antiretroviral Guidelines for Adults and Adolescents|title=Guidelines for the use of antiretroviral agents in HIV-1-infected adults and adolescents|newspaper=Department of Health and Human Services|date=October 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
In a 2011 study published in AIDS Patient Care and STDs (sample size 215), most of the barriers to care described involve stigma and shame.&lt;ref name="Pollini2011"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Pollini|first=Robin A.|author2=Estela Blanco|author3=Carol Crump|author4=Maria Zuniga|title=A community-based study of barriers to HIV care initiation|journal=AIDS Patient Care and STDs|year=2011|series=601-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The most common reasons of not seeking treatment are “I didn’t want to tell anyone I was HIV-positive”, “I didn’t want to think about being HIV-positive”, and “I was too embarrassed/ashamed to go”.&lt;ref name="Pollini2011" /&gt;  The presence and perpetuation of HIV stigma prevents many who are able to obtain treatment from feeling comfortable about addressing their health statue.&lt;ref name="Pollini2011" /&gt;

==See also==
*[[HIV exceptionalism]]
*[[Criminalization of HIV transmission]]

==References==
&lt;references/&gt;

{{Discrimination}}

People who are HIV positive have dealt with stigmas for the past 30 years, even though with the proper medication this can be manageable lifelong disease. It is now possible for a person who HIV + to have intimate relationship with someone who is HIV- and not pass the disease to them. It is also possible for a mother who is HIV + to not pass it to her child(Roth, Hrenchir and Pacheco 87-91. Though stigmas still continue and in third world countries people who are HIV + are discriminated against at work, school, their community and even in healthcare facilities(Cameron v de 5-8).. Discrimination is a killer it will not discourage those that are sick to not seek help until it to late, but will also increase the spread of HIV because fewer people will want to get tested
work cited
Roth Cheryl; Hrenchir Pauline F, and Pacheco Christine J. "HIV in Pregnancy." Nursing for Women Health (2016): 87-91. Nwhjournal.com. Web. 10 Apr. 2016 
Cameron, Sally; Jane Wilson, Julian Hows, Rodrigo Pascal, Jaime Todd-Gher, Liz Tremlett, Ann Stevens, and John Godwin. "People Living with HIV Stigma Index; Asia Pacific Regional Analysis 2011."(1-99). Joint United Nations Program, 2011.

{{DEFAULTSORT:Discrimination against people with HIV AIDS}}
[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Homophobia]]
[[Category:HIV/AIDS]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>