<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20130326061326|547027695" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="21985775" pageid="21985775" ns="0" title="Eliminationism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2013-07-27T03:55:04Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{About|a political ideology|the materialist position in the philosophy of mind|Eliminative materialism}}
{{Discrimination sidebar}}
'''Eliminationism''' is the belief that one's political opponents are "a [[cancer]] on the body politic that must be excised — either by separation from the public at large, through [[censorship]] or by outright [[mass murder|extermination]] — in order to protect the purity of the nation".&lt;ref name="Bernard 2009"&gt;{{cite paper| last = Bernard | first = Phyllis E. | title = Eliminationist Discourse In A Conflicted Society: Lessons For America From Africa? | date = June 12, 2009 | url = http://epublications.marquette.edu/mulr/vol93/iss1/12/ | quote = The phrase " eliminationist " has been used by David Neiwert, a journalist who has long covered right-wing discourse and action in the United States. Joshua Holland, The Terrorist Threat: Right-Wing Radicals and the Eliminationist Mindset, AlterNet (June 12, 2009), http://www.alternet.org/story/140578/. Niewert credits the phrase to DANIEL GOLDHAGEN, HITLER‘S WILLING EXECUTIONERS: ORDINARY GERMANS AND THE HOLOCAUST (1996). Holland, supra. The book explains the rhetorical mechanisms and socio-economic dynamics that led Germany‘s non-radical majority to acquiesce, then accept the race politics of the Nazi regime. See generally GOLDHAGEN, supra. "Eliminationism" claims a moral purpose, holding that political opponents are "a cancer on the body politic that must be excised—either by separation from the public at large, through censorship, or by outright extermination—in order to protect the purity of the nation." Joshua Holland, Dave Neiwert on the Roots of Right-Wing Terror, Daily Kos (June 12, 2009), http://www.dailykos.com/story/2009/6/12/741680/-Dave-Neiwert-on-the-Roots-of-Right-Wing-Terror. See generally DAVID NEIWERT, THE ELIMINATIONISTS: HOW HATE TALK RADICALIZED THE AMERICAN RIGHT 11 (2009). | accessdate = 2009-12-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Etymology==
The term ''eliminationism'' was coined by American political scientist [[Daniel Goldhagen]] in his 1996 book ''[[Hitler's Willing Executioners]]'' in which he posits that ordinary [[Germans]] not only knew about, but also supported, the [[Holocaust]] because of a unique and virulent "eliminationist antisemitism" in the German identity, which had developed in the preceding centuries.&lt;ref name="Bernard 2009"/&gt;

==Effects==
In his 2009 book ''Worse Than War: Genocide, Eliminationism, and the Ongoing Assault on Humanity'', Goldhagen argues that eliminationism is the root cause of every [[mass murder]] perpetrated in the 20th and 21st centuries, including:&lt;ref name="Gray 2009"&gt;{{cite paper| author = Gray, John | title = Worse Than War: Genocide, Eliminationism and the Ongoing Assault on Humanity By Daniel Jonah Goldhagen | date = 4 February 2010 | url = http://www.newstatesman.com/books/2010/02/genocide-goldhagen-mass | accessdate = 2010-03-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*[[War rape]] in [[War in Darfur|Darfur]] (2003–2010)
*[[Suicide attack]]s by [[Islamic terrorism|Islamic terrorists]]
*[[Rwandan Genocide]] (1994)
*[[Ethnic cleansing]] and [[genocide]] during the [[Yugoslav Wars]] (1991–1995)
*[[Cambodian Genocide]] (1975–1979)
*[[Operation Condor]] in [[Latin America]] (1973-1985)
*[[Atomic bombings of Hiroshima and Nagasaki]] (1945)
*[[Death marches (Holocaust)|Death marches]] from the [[Auschwitz concentration camp]] (1944–1945) 
*[[United Kingdom|British]] [[concentration camps]] for the [[Mau Mau]] following [[Mau Mau Uprising|their uprising]] in [[Kenya]] (1952–1960), and during the [[Boer Wars]] (1880–1881, 1899–1902)

American journalist [[David Neiwert]] argues that eliminationist rhetoric is becoming increasingly mainstream within the [[Conservatism in the United States|American right wing]], fueled in large part by the extremist discourse found on conservative [[blog]]s and [[talk radio]], which may provoke a resurgence of [[lone wolf (terrorism)|lone wolf terrorism]].&lt;ref name="Holland 2009"&gt;{{cite paper| author = Holland, Joshua | title = The Terrorist Threat: Right-Wing Radicals and the Eliminationist Mindset | date = 12 June 2009 | url = http://www.alternet.org/module/printversion/140578 | accessdate = 2009-07-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

American professor of law Phyllis E. Bernard argues that interventions in [[Rwanda]] and [[Nigeria]], which adapted American dispute prevention and [[dispute resolution|resolution]] methods to African media and dispute resolution traditions, may provide a better fit and forum for America to address eliminationist media messages and their impact on society.&lt;ref name="Bernard 2009"/&gt;

== References ==
{{reflist}}

[[Category:Censorship]]
[[Category:Human rights abuses]]
[[Category:Persecution]]
[[Category:Political theories]]
[[Category:Political repression]]
[[Category:Words coined in the 1990s]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>