<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20181025153218|865694010" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="44821234" pageid="44821234" ns="0" title="Pinkwashing (LGBTQ)"><revisions><rev timestamp="2018-10-25T22:25:24Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Use of the aesthetic of gay rights to promote organisations}}
{{Expand Serbo-Croatian|Pinkwashing|topic=hist|date=July 2015}}
{{Use British English Oxford spelling|date=November 2017}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=December 2014}}
'''Pinkwashing''' is a [[compound word]] modelled on term ''[[whitewash]]''. In the context of [[LGBT]] rights, it is used to describe a variety of marketing and political strategies aimed at promoting products, countries, people or entities through an appeal to [[gay friendly|gay-friendliness]], in order to be perceived as progressive, modern and tolerant. The phrase [[Pinkwashing (breast cancer)|was originally coined]] in 1992 by [[Breast Cancer Action]] to identify companies that claimed to support people with [[breast cancer]] while actually profiting from their illness.

== Immigration ==
In 2013, the [[Human Rights Campaign]] officially endorsed comprehensive immigration reform and committed to helping immigrants as they seek health and safety, asylum or citizenship.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Immigration |url=http://www.hrc.org/topics/immigration |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150201091142/http://www.hrc.org/topics/immigration |archivedate=February 1, 2015 |df=mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; The endorsement came days after an incident where a gay immigrant activist was prevented by HRC from discussing their legal status at a Supreme Court rally, mistreatment for which HRC later issued an apology.&lt;ref name="mistreat"&gt;{{cite web |title=HRC Apologizes for Mistreating Trans and Immigrant Activists at Supreme Court rally|url=http://transitiontransmission.com/post/46904132956/hrc-apologizes-for-mistreating-trans-and-immigrant|date=April 1, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[The Huffington Post]]'' described the HRC's actions as pinkwashing, "making immigration reform look pro-gay to garner LGBT support in order to mask the severe drawbacks of the legislation" – drawbacks such as funding to support enforcement, deportation, and further US militarization.&lt;ref name="hpost"&gt;{{cite news |author=Prerna Lal |author2=Justin Feldman |title=How Pinkwashing Masks the Retrograde Effects of Immigration Reform|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/prerna-lal/pinkwashing-immigration-reform_b_3070788.html|publisher=[[The Huffington Post]]|date=June 15, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2012, [[Jason Kenney]], Canada's Minister of Citizenship and Immigration, was accused of pinkwashing after an email titled "LGBT Refugees from Iran" was sent to thousands of Canadians. The message contained additional recent comments by [[John Baird (Canadian politician)|John Baird]], Minister of Foreign Affairs, about Canada's stand against the persecution and marginalization of gays and lesbian and women around the world. A group of activists claimed that it "is a poor attempt at 'pinkwashing' the Conservative government's obvious desire to encourage war with Iran."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Critics accuse Kenney of 'pinkwashing' in targeted emails|url=http://www.ctvnews.ca/politics/critics-accuse-kenney-of-pinkwashing-in-targeted-emails-1.970259|publisher=CTV News |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150515160614/http://www.ctvnews.ca/politics/critics-accuse-kenney-of-pinkwashing-in-targeted-emails-1.970259|archivedate=May 15, 2015 |deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==United States==
{{Expand section|date=February 2017}}
According to Omar G. Encarnación, a Professor of Political Studies at [[Bard College]], the [[Obama administration]] was accused by some critics of pinkwashing "to distract from other unsavory policies such as the deportation of millions of undocumented immigrants and the failure to prosecute those responsible for the human rights abuses of the Bush administration’s War on Terror."&lt;ref name="foreignaffairstrumpandgayrights"&gt;{{cite news|last1=Encarnación|first1=Omar G.|title=Trump and Gay Rights: The Future of the Global Movement|url=https://www.foreignaffairs.com/articles/2017-02-13/trump-and-gay-rights?cid=nlc-fatoday-20170213&amp;sp_mid=53412954&amp;sp_rid=dmljdG9yLnN0ZXBpZW5AZ21haWwuY29tS0|accessdate=February 14, 2017|work=Foreign Affairs|date=February 13, 2017|quote=There is even the cynical charge that Obama engaged in “pink washing,” or the use of the gay rights issue to distract from other unsavory policies such as the deportation of millions of undocumented immigrants and the failure to prosecute those responsible for the human rights abuses of the Bush administration’s War on Terror.}} {{subscription required|via=Foreign Affairs}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Israeli government public relations==
[[File:משפריצות פעולה ורודה 2.jpg|thumb|[[Anarcho-queer]] collective ''Mashpritzot'' hold a "[[die-in]]" protest against Israeli pinkwashing and the perceived [[homonormativity|homonormative]] priorities of the [[LGBT]] support centre in [[Tel Aviv]]]]
[[Sarah Schulman]], a writer and professor at the [[City University of New York]], claims Israeli [[Public diplomacy (Israel)|government public relations campaign]] exploits the idea of Israel being LGBT-friendly to promote public perception of Israel as a "modern democracy", a "safe and secured place for investment", and a "tourist destination with the sun and the sand".&lt;ref&gt;Avraham, Eli. (2009), "Marketing and managing nation branding during prolonged crisis: The case of Israel". Vol. 5, 3, pp. 202–212.&lt;/ref&gt; In August 2011, ''The Jerusalem Post'' reported the Foreign Ministry was promoting Gay Israel as part of its campaigns to counter the negative stereotypes that many liberal Americans and Europeans have of Israel.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |author=Tovah Lazaroff |date=October 26, 2006 |url=http://www.jpost.com/Israel/Foreign-Ministry-promoting-Gay-Israel |title=Foreign Ministry promoting Gay Israel |work=The Jerusalem Post |accessdate=March 22, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Critics of Israel like [[Jasbir Puar]], an associate professor of Women's and Gender Studies at [[Rutgers University]], cite the Israeli government's comparison of LGBT+ rights in Israel and in the [[occupied Palestinian territories]] as an example of pinkwashing. Citing WorldPride, which Jerusalem hosted in 2006, she wrote: "Within global gay and lesbian organising circuits, to be gay friendly is to be modern, cosmopolitan, developed, first-world, global north, and, most significantly, democratic."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2010/jul/01/israels-gay-propaganda-war |title=Israel's gay propaganda war |work=The Guardian |date=July 1, 2010 |first=Jasbir|last=Puar |accessdate=March 22, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Joseph Massad]], associate professor of modern Arab politics and intellectual history at [[Columbia University]], has written that the Israeli government "insist[s] on advertising and exaggerating its recent record on LGBT rights ... to fend off international condemnation of its violations of the rights of the Palestinian people."&lt;ref name=kaufman&gt;{{cite news |last=Kaufman|first=David|title=Is Israel Using Gay Rights to Excuse Its Policy on Palestine?|url=http://content.time.com/time/world/article/0,8599,2070415,00.html|newspaper=[[Time (magazine)|Time]] |date=May 13, 2011|accessdate=January 26, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |author=Morten Berthelsen |url=http://www.haaretz.com/news/stop-using-palestinian-gays-to-whitewash-israel-s-image-1.6887 |title='Stop using Palestinian gays to whitewash Israel's image' |work=[[Haaretz]] |date=October 1, 2009 |accessdate=January 26, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Others assert that pinkwashing allegations against Israel constitute a [[straw man]] argument, arguing that Israel's embrace of the LGBT community has never been used to justify or excuse the Israeli [[occupation of Palestine]], stating bluntly that the fact that Israel is generally tolerant towards LGBT individuals and groups on both state and individual levels is a factual contrast to the discriminatory and often-brutal treatment given to LGBT people by Arab and Muslim groups.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.haaretz.com/the-fallacy-of-the-pinkwashing-argument-1.422951|title=The Fallacy of the 'Pinkwashing' Argument|last=Kirchick|first=James|date=2012-04-06|newspaper=Haaretz|language=en|access-date=2016-05-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Mazzig |first=Hen |authorlink=Hen Mazzig |date=June 11, 2017 |title=The Dark Side of The Rainbow |url=http://www.jpost.com/Opinion/The-dark-side-of-the-rainbow-496560 |work=The Jerusalem Post }}&lt;/ref&gt; Ido Aharoni, former head of the Brand Israel project, responded to such criticism saying: "We are not trying to hide the conflict but broaden the conversation. We want to create a sense of relevance with other communities."&lt;ref name=kaufman/&gt; [[Alan Dershowitz]], a Harvard University law professor and a frequent defender of Israel, has said that the term ''pinkwashing'' is used against Israel by "some radical gay activists" who are [[antisemitic]] "bigots."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |author=[[Alan Dershowitz]] |date=March 1, 2013 |url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/alan-dershowitz/the-pinkwashing-campaign-_b_2790669.html |title=The Pinkwashing Campaign Against Israel: Another Conspiracy Theory |publisher=The Huffington Post |accessdate=March 22, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; He called the use of the term ''pinkwashing'' in this context as "nothing more than anti-Semitism with a pink face."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Dershowitz |first=Alan|url=https://nypost.com/2013/02/25/the-next-hate-fest/ |work=New York Post |title=The Next Hate Fest |accessdate=December 29, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |author=Zachary Lichaa |title=Trustee Blasts CUNY Anti-Israel 'Homonationalism and Pinkwashing' Conference |url=http://www.algemeiner.com/2012/06/08/trustee-blasts-cuny-anti-israel-homonationalism-and-pinkwashing-conference/ |newspaper=Algemeiner Journal |date=June 8, 2012 |accessdate=January 26, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Yair Qedar]], a gay Israeli filmmaker and civil rights activist, has said that Israel has a praiseworthy LGBT+ rights record and that failing to defend it "ultimately serves homophobia far more than dialogue and peace". He criticized Israeli LGBT+ groups for failing to oppose pinkwashing charges.&lt;ref name=kaufman/&gt; Shaul Ganon of the Israeli based LGBT+ rights group [[Israeli Gay, Lesbian, Bisexual and Transgender Association|Aguda]], assessed the dispute this way: "Each side is trying to gain some points. The truth is the only one who gets screwed by this is the Palestinian gays."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last1=Luongo |first1=Michael |title=Gay Palestinians caught in the middle of the conflict |url=http://www.globalpost.com/dispatch/news/regions/middle-east/israel-and-palestine/120607/gay-palestinians-lgbt-israel-conflict |date=June 8, 2012 |newspaper=[[Global Post]] |accessdate=January 25, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Corporate marketing ==
A campaign to develop public support for the [[Keystone Pipeline]], which would transport Canadian oil through the United States, has been accused of pinkwashing for its argument that the project deserves support based on a comparison of Canada's record on LGBT rights compared to that of other oil-producing nations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last1=Michaelson|first1=Jay|title=How Canadian Oilmen Pinkwash the Keystone Pipeline|url=http://www.thedailybeast.com/articles/2014/12/28/how-canadian-oilmen-pinkwash-the-keystone-pipeline.html |publisher=The Daily Beast |date=December 28, 2014 |accessdate=December 29, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; The campaign base at OpecHatesgays.com headlines its presentation: "Compare Canadian Ethical Oil to OPEC conflict oil".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Compare Canadian Ethical Oil to OPEC conflict oil.|url=http://opechatesgays.com/|publisher=OpenHatesGays|accessdate=December 29, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2014, BP launched "LGBT Careers Event", a move that was met with criticism as an attempt to pinkwash the conduct that led to [[Deepwater Horizon oil spill]], described as "the worst environmental disaster America has ever faced".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | work=Bright Green|title=BP reach for the pinkwash with 'LGBT Careers Event'|url=http://brightgreenscotland.org/index.php/2014/11/news-bp-pinkwash/ |date=November 11, 2014 | first=Naomi |last=Wilkins |accessdate=January 25, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Australia, concern has been raised about the commodification of gay rights by major corporations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.smh.com.au/national/pink-washing-marketing-stunt-or-corporate-revolution-20150605-ghhthh.html | title = "Pink washing": marketing stunt or corporate revolution? | last = Stark | first = Jill | date = June 7, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Anti-Islamic activists==
A coalition organized by several popular grassroots movements in Europe, including the [[English Defence League]] (EDL), mounted demonstrations in conjunction with LGBT Pride Week celebrations in Helsinki and Stockholm in July and August 2012.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|editor1-last=Deland|editor1-first=Mats|editor2-last=Minkenberg|editor2-first=Michael|editor3-last=Mays|editor3-first=Christin|title=In the Tracks of Breivik: Far Right Networks in Northern and Eastern Europe|date=2014|publisher=LIT Verlag|page=12}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="sverigesradio"&gt;{{cite news |title=Queers against Pinkwashing reject Counter Jihad|url=http://sverigesradio.se/sida/artikel.aspx?programid=2054&amp;artikel=5217586 |publisher=Radio Sweden|date=August 3, 2012 |accessdate=27 January 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; In an interview for Radio Sweden, the Swedish author and activist Lisa Bjurwald claimed that the EDL have exploited pride events in the United Kingdom by bringing attention to Islamic homophobia and that Queers against Pinkwashing (a group that protested against the Stockholm march) is opposed to talking about homophobia in Islam and label all such attempts as "pinkwashing" and a "divide and conquer tactic."&lt;ref name="sverigesradio" /&gt;

== Intersex movement ==
{{main|Intersex and LGBT}}
In June 2016, [[Organisation Intersex International Australia]] pointed to contradictory statements by Australian governments, suggesting that the dignity and rights of LGBT and intersex people are recognized while, at the same time, harmful practices on intersex children continue.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Submission: list of issues for Australia’s Convention Against Torture review | url = https://oii.org.au/30546/loi-cat-review/ | work = [[Organisation Intersex International Australia]] | date = June 28, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In August 2016, [[Zwischengeschlecht]] described actions to promote equality or civil status legislation without action on banning "intersex genital mutilations" as a form of pinkwashing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=seelenlos | title = 'Intersex legislation' that allows the daily mutilations to continue = PINKWASHING of IGM practices | url = http://stop.genitalmutilation.org/post/Intersex-politics-that-ignore-the-daily-mutilations-PINKWASHING-OF-IGM-PRACTICES | work = [[Zwischengeschlecht]] | date = August 28, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{RS|date=August 2017}} The organization has previously highlighted evasive government statements to UN Treaty Bodies that conflate intersex, transgender and LGBT issues, instead of addressing harmful practices on infants.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = TRANSCRIPTION &gt; UK Questioned over Intersex Genital Mutilations by UN Committee on the Rights of the Child - Gov Non-Answer + Denial | url = http://stop.genitalmutilation.org/post/UK-Questioned-over-Intersex-Genital-Mutilations-by-UN-Committee-on-the-Rights-of-the-Child | work = [[Zwischengeschlecht]] | date = May 26, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Country comparisons ==
Stephan Lefebvre of the [[Center for Economic and Policy Research]] has noted how the Obama administration, followed by the mainstream US media, has criticized Russia for its failure to provide basic civil liberties for its LGBT population. He contrasts that with the US government's failure to condemn the comparable record on LGBT issues on the part of US allies like Honduras, Saudi Arabia, and the United Arab Emirates, as well as the US government's failure to acknowledge progress on LGBT rights in Cuba. In his analysis, this constitutes pinkwashing, which he defines as "deliberately highlighting support for gay rights while ignoring or downplaying other relevant human rights issues".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Lefebvre |first1=Stephan |title=Foreign Policy Pinkwashing: Russia's New Law and Continuing Violence in Honduras|url=http://www.cepr.net/index.php/blogs/the-americas-blog/foreign-policy-pinkwashing-russias-new-law-and-continuing-violence-in-honduras|publisher=[[Center for Economic and Policy Research]]|date=August 16, 2013|accessdate=January 25, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Laurie Penny]], an author and feminist activist, contrasted those who criticized Russia's LGBT policies during the [[2014 Winter Olympics|Sochi Olympics]] with their silence on instances of homophobic treatment at their own countries' border crossings. She wrote:&lt;ref name=Guardian1&gt;{{cite news |title=Less homophobic than Russia? It's not something to give yourself a medal for|url=https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2014/feb/13/less-homophobic-russia-sochi-medal-lgbt|newspaper=[[The Guardian]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{quote|While western nations flap the rainbow flag defiantly in Russia's face, actual lesbian, gay, bisexual and transgender people are being harassed and abused at their borders when they arrive seeking safety. Supporting the rights of LGBT people worldwide is to be commended, but if that sentiment is more than pinkwashing, it should be backed up by action at home.&lt;ref name=Guardian1/&gt;}}

==See also==
{{Portal|LGBT}}
* [[Homonationalism]]
* [[Cause marketing]]
* [[LGBT marketing]]
* [[Pinkwashing (breast cancer)]]
* [[Greenwashing]]
* [[Pink capitalism]]
* [[Straightwashing]]
* [[Purplewashing]]

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
{{Wiktionary|pinkwashing}}
* [http://www.pinkwatchingisrael.com/ Pinkwatching Israel]
* [http://www.nopinkwashing.org.uk/ No to Pinkwashing]

[[Category:Sexual orientation and society]]
[[Category:LGBT and the economy|Marketing]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>