<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20241013180217|1250982739" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="44821234" pageid="44821234" ns="0" title="Pinkwashing (LGBTQ)"><revisions><rev timestamp="2024-11-30T19:00:18Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|Promotional use of LGBTQ rights}}
{{distinguish|Pinkwashing (breast cancer)}}
{{Use Oxford spelling|date=November 2017}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=December 2014}}
{{Unbalanced|date=May 2024}}
[[File:משפריצות פעולה ורודה 2.jpg|thumb|[[Anarcho-queer]] collective Mashpritzot hold a [[die-in]] protest against Israeli pinkwashing and the perceived [[homonormativity|homo-normative]] priorities of the [[LGBTQ]] support centre in [[Tel Aviv]]]]
{{LGBTQ sidebar|expanded=attitudes}}

'''Pinkwashing''', also known as '''rainbow-washing''',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url = https://rockcontent.com/blog/what-is-rainbow-washing/| title = What is Rainbow Washing? And Why You Should Prevent It During Pride Month| last = Rodríguez
| first = Ashley
| date = June 15, 2022
| work = rockcontent.com
| access-date = June 8, 2023
| archive-date = June 22, 2023
| archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20230622223123/https://rockcontent.com/blog/what-is-rainbow-washing/
| url-status = live
}}&lt;/ref&gt; is the strategy of deploying messages that are superficially sympathetic towards the [[LGBTQ community]] for ends having little or nothing to do with LGBTQ equality or inclusion,{{sfn|Russell|2019|p=182}} including [[LGBT marketing]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Profit From Pride – Pinkwashing as Part of Modern Marketing |url=https://www.pressrelations.com/blog/en/profit-from-pride-pinkwashing-as-part-of-modern-marketing |access-date=12 May 2022 |work=pressrelations Blog |date=27 August 2020 |archive-date=July 7, 2022 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20220707102642/https://www.pressrelations.com/blog/en/profit-from-pride-pinkwashing-as-part-of-modern-marketing |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Origin of the term==
In April 2010, Queers Undermining Israeli Terrorism (QUIT) in the Bay Area, used the phrase ''pinkwashing'' as a twist on ''[[greenwashing]]'', a practice where companies claim to be eco-friendly in order to make profit. Dunya Alwan was at a talk with Ali Abunimah, editor of [[Electronic Intifada]] in 2010, when he said "We won't put up with Israel whitewashing or greenwashing" and she thought "or pinkwashing!"&lt;ref&gt;{{cite thesis |last1=Ellison |first1=Joy |title=Recycled rhetoric: brand Israel 'pinkwashing' in historical context |url=https://via.library.depaul.edu/etd/149 |type=MA thesis |publisher=DePaul University |access-date=31 August 2022 |page=8 |date=2013 |archive-date=November 13, 2023 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20231113093056/https://via.library.depaul.edu/etd/149/ |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2011, [[Sarah Schulman]] used the term ''pinkwashing'' in a widely read ''[[The New York Times]]'' editorial arguing that Israel used the tactic in its public relations. Schulman saw pinkwashing as a manifestation of [[homonationalism]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Tziallas |first1=Evangelos |title=The new 'Porn Wars': representing gay male sexuality in the Middle East |journal=Psychology &amp; Sexuality |date=2015 |volume=6 |issue=1 |pages=93–110 |doi=10.1080/19419899.2014.983741|s2cid=145381763 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Ritchie |first1=Jason |title=Pinkwashing, Homonationalism, and Israel-Palestine: The Conceits of Queer Theory and the Politics of the Ordinary: Pinkwashing, Homonationalism, and Israel-Palestine |journal=Antipode |date=2015 |volume=47 |issue=3 |pages=616–634 |doi=10.1111/anti.12100|doi-access=free }}&lt;/ref&gt; the processes by which some powers selectively agree with the claims of [[sexual minorities]] and exploit them to justify [[racism]], [[xenophobia]] (rejection of foreign people), and [[aporophobia]] (rejection of the poor);&lt;ref name="homonationalism"&gt;{{Cite book |last=Puar |first=Jasbir K. |year=2007 |title=Terrorist Assemblages: Homonationalism in Queer Times |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=S-DlmHrJE6AC |publisher=Duke University Press |pages=83 |isbn=978-0-8223-4094-2 |access-date=January 27, 2022 |archive-date=December 4, 2023 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20231204051608/https://books.google.com/books?id=S-DlmHrJE6AC |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="heteronationalism"&gt;[http://www.publicseminar.org/2016/08/homonationalism-heteronationalism-and-lgbti-rights-in-the-eu/ Homonationalism, Heteronationalism and LGBTI Rights in the EU.] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180713174049/http://www.publicseminar.org/2016/08/homonationalism-heteronationalism-and-lgbti-rights-in-the-eu/ |date=July 13, 2018 }} Public Seminar. 31 August 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":2"&gt;{{Cite web |last1=Puar |first1=Jasbir |last2=Mikdashi |first2=Maya |date=9 August 2012 |title=Pinkwatching And Pinkwashing: Interpenetration and its Discontents |url=https://www.jadaliyya.com/Details/26818 |access-date=2022-01-20 |website=Jadaliyya - جدلية |archive-date=June 22, 2022 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20220622183637/https://www.jadaliyya.com/Details/26818 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt; in short, the intersection between gay identities and nationalist ideology.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=Nichols |first=James Michael |date=2016-10-05 |title=Understanding Homonationalism: Why Are There Gay People Supporting Trump? |url=https://www.huffpost.com/entry/gay-people-supporting-trump-homonationalism_n_57f3e545e4b01b16aaff4bff |access-date=2020-11-18 |website=HuffPost |archive-date=October 31, 2020 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20201031110323/https://www.huffpost.com/entry/gay-people-supporting-trump-homonationalism_n_57f3e545e4b01b16aaff4bff |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt; Homonationalism shaped the concept of pinkwashing and the two terms are often used together as tools to explain the actions of countries. [[Jasbir Puar]] writes in a later article, ''Rethinking Homonationalism'', that the two terms are not parallel but rather pinkwashing is able to exist because homonationalism exists.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Puar |first=Jasbir |date=2013 |title=Rethinking Homonationalism |url=https://www.jstor.org/stable/43302999 |journal=International Journal of Middle East Studies |volume=45 |issue=2 |pages=336–339 |doi=10.1017/S002074381300007X |jstor=43302999 |s2cid=232253207 |issn=0020-7438 |access-date=November 11, 2020 |archive-date=June 4, 2021 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20210604092310/https://www.jstor.org/stable/43302999 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;

By 2020, "pinkwashing" had become a popular term used by anti-occupation groups to describe the Israeli authorities' attitude towards LGBTQ Palestinians. That same year, Al-Qaws published "Beyond Propaganda: Pinkwashing as Colonial Violence," a paper detailing how the Israeli state and its supporters use the language of gay and trans rights to divert international attention away from the oppression of Palestinians.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=alQaws |date=2020-10-18 |title=This analysis paper explores a paradigm shift that alQaws has been exploring over the past decade of its grassroots community organizing, which centers the experiences of queer Palestinians. |url=https://www.alqaws.org/siteEn/print?id=86&amp;type=1 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==By country or region==

=== Canada ===
In 2012, [[Jason Kenney]], Canada's Minister of Citizenship and Immigration, was accused of pinkwashing, after an email titled "LGBT Refugees from Iran" was sent to thousands of Canadians. The message contained additional recent comments by [[John Baird (Canadian politician)|John Baird]], Minister of Foreign Affairs, about Canada's stand against the persecution and marginalization of gays and lesbian women around the world. A group of activists claimed that it "is a poor attempt at 'pinkwashing' the Conservative government's obvious desire to encourage war with Iran".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |date=25 September 2012 |title=Critics accuse Kenney of 'pinkwashing' in targeted emails |work=CTVNews |url=https://www.ctvnews.ca/politics/critics-accuse-kenney-of-pinkwashing-in-targeted-emails-1.970259 |access-date=3 December 2021 |archive-date=December 3, 2021 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20211203182350/https://www.ctvnews.ca/politics/critics-accuse-kenney-of-pinkwashing-in-targeted-emails-1.970259 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Europe ===
A coalition organized by several popular grassroots movements in Europe, including the [[English Defence League]] (EDL), mounted [[counter-jihad]] demonstrations in conjunction with LGBT Pride Week celebrations in Helsinki and Stockholm in July and August 2012.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=In the Tracks of Breivik: Far Right Networks in Northern and Eastern Europe |date=2014 |publisher=LIT Verlag |editor1-last=Deland |editor1-first=Mats |page=12 |editor2-last=Minkenberg |editor2-first=Michael |editor3-last=Mays |editor3-first=Christin}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="sverigesradio"&gt;{{cite news |date=August 3, 2012 |title=Queers against Pinkwashing reject Counter Jihad |publisher=Radio Sweden |url=http://sverigesradio.se/sida/artikel.aspx?programid=2054&amp;artikel=5217586 |access-date=27 January 2015 |archive-date=February 6, 2015 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150206222402/http://sverigesradio.se/sida/artikel.aspx?programid=2054&amp;artikel=5217586 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt; However, these movements inspired a counter demonstration by an LGBT rights group called "Queers against Pinkwashing", which claimed that the counter-jihad march against [[Muslim]]s was a clear example of pinkwashing and projected a fake support image for sexual minorities.&lt;ref name="sverigesradio" /&gt; In an interview for Radio Sweden, [[Lisa Bjurwald]], a Swedish journalist and expert on European [[right-wing]] ideology, criticized the EDL for allying with the wrong people, as "Queers against Pinkwashing" are in fact against singling out Islam as if it were the source of all the relevant problems because such attempts do not benefit the LGBTQ community.&lt;ref name="sverigesradio" /&gt;

==== Belgium ====
The Flemish nationalist party [[Vlaams Belang]] and [[Filip Dewinter]] shifted their stance on gay issues in the 2010s and began using pro-gay rhetoric to criticize Muslims and immigrants. According to Eric Louis Russell, Dewinter exploits homophobic violence in a similar way that pornography commodifies women's bodies; he argues "that this type of commodification of potential or real violence directed toward members of a society for political ends is a real, albeit [[wikt:subjacent|subjacent]] and deeply insidious form of homophobia".{{sfn|Russell|2019|pp=182, 256}}

==== France ====
[[Marine Le Pen]], president of the French [[far-right]] political party [[National Rally|National Front]], was gaining support from LGBT communities in the presidential election, despite the fact that [[Jean-Marie Le Pen]], her father and the founder of the party, once condemned homosexuality as "a biological and social anomaly".&lt;ref name="french1"&gt;{{Cite web |date=2017-04-07 |title='Pinkwashing' populism: Gay voters embrace French far-right |url=https://apnews.com/article/35ec96903d9444e9942396505d635981 |accessdate=2021-09-13 |website=APNews.com |archive-date=January 27, 2022 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20220127192156/https://apnews.com/article/35ec96903d9444e9942396505d635981 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt; After the [[Orlando nightclub shooting]], Marine Le Pen declared "how much homosexuality is attacked in countries that live under the Islamist jackboot".&lt;ref name="french1" /&gt; Facing these threats and receiving "sympathy" from Le Pen, some LGBT voters started to advocate for the far-right party, with one supporter stating that "they'll be the first victims of these barbarians, and only Marine is proposing radical solutions".&lt;ref name="french1" /&gt;

==== Ireland ====
According to Professor of Gender and Women's Studies Eithne Luibhéid, Ireland used its [[Thirty-fourth Amendment of the Constitution of Ireland|2015 same-sex marriage referendum]] "to pinkwash its migration regimes, thereby naturalizing harsh policies that reproduce gendered, sexual, racial, economic, and geopolitical inequalities".{{sfn|Luibhéid|2018|p=405}}

=== Israel ===
[[File:Europride2024.jpg|thumb|A participant in the 2024 EuroPride in Thessaloniki holding a picket that reads "NO PRIDE IN GENOCIDE".]]
The Israeli government's marketing strategy includes "Israel Beyond the Conflict", an attempt to promote aspects of Israeli life outside the [[Israeli–Palestinian conflict]]. According to Israeli gay rights activist [[Hagai El-Ad]], "In no other arena has that been used in a more cynical way than in the context of LGBT rights."{{sfn|Atshan|2020|p=80}} According to Palestinian anthropologist [[Sa'ed Atshan]],
{{blockquote|[Israeli] pinkwashing relies on a logic based on four pillars: 
#naming queer Israeli agency and eliding Israeli homophobia; 
#naming Palestinian homophobia and eliding queer Palestinian agency; 
#juxtaposing these contrasting queer experiences in Israeli and Palestinian societies as a civilizational discourse aimed at highlighting the superior humanity of the former and the subhumanity of the latter, who deserve to be dominated; and 
#representing Israel as a gay haven for Israelis, Palestinians, and internationals in order to attract tourism and other forms of solidarity and support.{{sfn|Atshan|2020|p=72}}}}

Opponents of the term pinkwashing in relation to Israel argue that Israeli society has seen [[LGBT rights in Israel|meaningful progress on LGBT rights]] that are better than those in neighbouring countries.{{sfn|Atshan|2020|p=92}} Others highlight the phenomenon of some gay Palestinians who live illegally in Israel;{{sfn|Atshan|2020|pp=99–100}} Israel has historically been against granting asylum to such individuals,{{sfn|Atshan|2020|pp=101–102}} but has changed this in recent years, with legal protections being established for LGBT+ Palestinians fleeing violence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Israel to Give Work Permits to LGBT Palestinians Granted Asylum Reversal|url=https://www.haaretz.com/israel-news/2022-06-20/ty-article/.premium/israel-to-give-work-permits-to-lgbt-palestinians-granted-asylum/00000181-803a-de72-afcb-a4feda4b0000|date=2022-06-20|access-date=February 12, 2024|newspaper=[[Haaretz]]|archive-date=June 23, 2022|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20220623072717/https://www.haaretz.com/israel-news/2022-06-20/ty-article/.premium/israel-to-give-work-permits-to-lgbt-palestinians-granted-asylum/00000181-803a-de72-afcb-a4feda4b0000|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Israeli Foreign Ministry Boasted LGBTQ Palestinian Asylum Ruling; Interior Minister Seeks Reversal|url=https://www.haaretz.com/israel-news/2024-02-07/ty-article/.premium/foreign-ministry-boasts-lgbtq-palestinian-asylum-ruling-interior-minister-seeks-reversal/0000018d-83fb-dfd5-adff-dbfbc7a00000|date=2024-02-07|access-date=February 12, 2024|newspaper=[[Haaretz]]|archive-date=February 7, 2024|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20240207164244/https://www.haaretz.com/israel-news/2024-02-07/ty-article/.premium/foreign-ministry-boasts-lgbtq-palestinian-asylum-ruling-interior-minister-seeks-reversal/0000018d-83fb-dfd5-adff-dbfbc7a00000|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; Pro-Israel writers also argue that the term is not always applied to other countries that use similar strategies.{{sfn|Atshan|2020|p=95–97}} [[Ido Aharoni]], former head of the [[Brand Israel]] project, responded to such criticism, saying: "We are not trying to hide the conflict, but broaden the conversation."&lt;ref name="kaufman" /&gt; [[Yair Qedar]], a gay Israeli filmmaker and civil rights activist, has said that Israel has a praiseworthy LGBT+ rights record, and that failing to defend it "ultimately serves homophobia far more than dialogue and peace". He criticized Israeli LGBT+ groups for failing to oppose pinkwashing charges.&lt;ref name="kaufman" /&gt; Shaul Ganon of the Israeli-based LGBT+ rights group [[Israeli Gay, Lesbian, Bisexual and Transgender Association|Aguda]], assessed the dispute this way: "Each side is trying to gain some points. The truth is the only one who gets screwed by this is the [[LGBT rights in the State of Palestine|Palestinian gays]]."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last1=Luongo |first1=Michael |title=Gay Palestinians caught in the middle of the conflict |url=http://www.globalpost.com/dispatch/news/regions/middle-east/israel-and-palestine/120607/gay-palestinians-lgbt-israel-conflict |date=June 8, 2012 |newspaper=[[Global Post]] |access-date=January 25, 2015 |archive-date=January 23, 2015 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150123102302/http://www.globalpost.com/dispatch/news/regions/middle-east/israel-and-palestine/120607/gay-palestinians-lgbt-israel-conflict |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt; According to Atshan, "the critiques leveled against [anti-pinkwashing activists] are often not well founded or ethically deployed. It is particularly disconcerting when supporters of Israel instead cast Israeli state sources of victimization as saviors of queer Palestinians."{{sfn|Atshan|2020|p=105}} He also argues that anti-pinkwashing can go too far when activists prioritize the struggle against [[Israeli occupation]] and only bring up LGBT issues in order to criticize Israel.{{sfn|Atshan|2020|p=110}}

After the 2011 [[Gaza Freedom Flotilla]], an Israeli actor created a hoax video in which he pretended to have been turned away from the flotilla because he was gay. The video was promoted by the Israeli prime minister's office.{{sfn|Atshan|2020|pp=79–80}}

[[Joseph Massad]], associate professor of modern Arab politics and intellectual history at [[Columbia University]], has written that the Israeli government "insist[s] on advertising and exaggerating its recent record on LGBT rights ... to fend off international condemnation of its violations of the rights of the Palestinian people".&lt;ref name="kaufman"&gt;{{cite news |last=Kaufman |first=David |title=Is Israel Using Gay Rights to Excuse Its Policy on Palestine? |url=http://content.time.com/time/world/article/0,8599,2070415,00.html |newspaper=[[Time (magazine)|Time]] |date=May 13, 2011 |access-date=January 26, 2015 |archive-date=May 18, 2019 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190518024759/http://content.time.com/time/world/article/0,8599,2070415,00.html |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt; Culture studies academic Nada Elia calls pinkwashing "the twenty-first century manifestation of the Zionist colonialist narrative of bringing civilisation to an otherwise backwards land".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Elia |first1=Nada |title=Gay Rights with a Side of Apartheid |journal=Settler Colonial Studies |date=2012 |volume=2 |issue=2 |pages=49–68 |doi=10.1080/2201473X.2012.10648841|s2cid=154917783|doi-access=free }}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the [[Israel–Hamas war]], queer Palestinians argued that Pride and the Pride flag had been co-opted by pro-Israeli group to justify and celebrate much of the resulting [[Gaza humanitarian crisis (2023–present)|Gaza humanitarian crisis]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |last=Graham-Harrison |first=Emma |date=2024-06-16 |title='No pride in occupation': queer Palestinians on 'pink-washing' in Gaza conflict |url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/article/2024/jun/16/queer-palestinians-lgbtq-israel-pride-flags-gaza-conflict-pink-washing |access-date=2024-07-06 |work=The Observer |language=en-GB |issn=0029-7712}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many [[Queer advocacy in the Israel–Hamas War|queer pro-Palestinian activists advocated against the war]], disrupting some [[Pride parade|Pride parades]] during 2024.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |date=2024-06-28 |title=Israel-Hamas war protests have disrupted Pride marches across the U.S. |url=https://www.nbcnews.com/nbc-out/out-news/lgbtq-pride-march-israel-hamas-war-protests-rcna156595 |access-date=2024-08-02 |website=NBC News |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Corporate marketing ==
{{further|LGBT marketing}}
Pinkwashing in the United States, according to author Stephan Dahl from the [[University of Hull]], is centered around pride merchandise created and sold by companies that do nothing for queer people.&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{cite news |last=Dahl |first=Stephan |title=The rise of pride marketing and the curse of 'pink washing' |url=http://theconversation.com/the-rise-of-pride-marketing-and-the-curse-of-pink-washing-30925 |access-date=November 12, 2020 |website=The Conversation |archive-date=November 11, 2020 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20201111235636/https://theconversation.com/the-rise-of-pride-marketing-and-the-curse-of-pink-washing-30925 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt; This encourages a "big business-small community" relationship and seems beneficial when in reality there is nothing changing legally for queer people through this practice.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;

A campaign to develop public support for the [[Keystone Pipeline]], which would transport Canadian oil through the United States, has been accused of pinkwashing for its argument that the project deserves support based on a comparison of Canada's record on LGBT rights compared to that of other oil-producing nations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last1=Michaelson |first1=Jay |title=How Canadian Oilmen Pinkwash the Keystone Pipeline |url=http://www.thedailybeast.com/articles/2014/12/28/how-canadian-oilmen-pinkwash-the-keystone-pipeline.html |publisher=The Daily Beast |date=December 28, 2014 |access-date=December 29, 2014 |archive-date=December 29, 2014 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20141229211818/http://www.thedailybeast.com/articles/2014/12/28/how-canadian-oilmen-pinkwash-the-keystone-pipeline.html |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Australia, concern has been raised about the commodification of gay rights by major corporations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.smh.com.au/national/pink-washing-marketing-stunt-or-corporate-revolution-20150605-ghhthh.html |title="Pink washing": marketing stunt or corporate revolution? |last=Stark |first=Jill |date=June 7, 2015 |accessdate=2016-09-04 |archive-date=October 28, 2016 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20161028221446/http://www.smh.com.au/national/pink-washing-marketing-stunt-or-corporate-revolution-20150605-ghhthh.html |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[LGBTQ Nation]] states that "many brands that engage in pinkwashing are guilty of using the LGBTQ community to boost their PR and incur capital from 'pink money', all while maintaining unjust labor practices, discriminatory hiring processes, and supporting anti-LGBTQ organizations".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=What is pinkwashing? |url=https://www.lgbtqnation.com/2022/07/what-is-pinkwashing/ |work=[[LGBTQ Nation]] |access-date=June 26, 2023 |archive-date=June 26, 2023 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20230626042547/https://www.lgbtqnation.com/2022/07/what-is-pinkwashing/ |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Intersex movement ==
{{main|Intersex and LGBT}}

In June 2016, [[Organisation Intersex International Australia]] pointed to contradictory statements by Australian governments, suggesting that the dignity and rights of LGBT and intersex people are recognized while, at the same time, harmful practices on intersex children continue.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Submission: list of issues for Australia's Convention Against Torture review | url = https://ihra.org.au/30546/loi-cat-review/ | work = [[Intersex Human Rights Australia]] | date = June 28, 2016 | access-date = August 13, 2022 | archive-date = September 20, 2019 | archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20190920150222/https://ihra.org.au/30546/loi-cat-review/ | url-status = live }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In August 2016, [[Zwischengeschlecht]] described actions to promote equality or civil status legislation without action on banning "intersex genital mutilations" as a form of pinkwashing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author = seelenlos | title = 'Intersex legislation' that allows the daily mutilations to continue = PINKWASHING of IGM practices | url = http://stop.genitalmutilation.org/post/Intersex-politics-that-ignore-the-daily-mutilations-PINKWASHING-OF-IGM-PRACTICES | work = [[Zwischengeschlecht]] | date = August 28, 2016 | access-date = September 4, 2016 | archive-date = September 19, 2016 | archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20160919050911/http://stop.genitalmutilation.org/post/Intersex-politics-that-ignore-the-daily-mutilations-PINKWASHING-OF-IGM-PRACTICES | url-status = live }}&lt;/ref&gt; The organization has previously highlighted evasive government statements to UN Treaty Bodies that conflate intersex, transgender and LGBT issues, instead of addressing harmful practices on infants.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = TRANSCRIPTION &gt; UK Questioned over Intersex Genital Mutilations by UN Committee on the Rights of the Child - Gov Non-Answer + Denial | url = http://stop.genitalmutilation.org/post/UK-Questioned-over-Intersex-Genital-Mutilations-by-UN-Committee-on-the-Rights-of-the-Child | work = [[Zwischengeschlecht]] | date = May 26, 2016 | access-date = September 4, 2016 | archive-date = September 19, 2016 | archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20160919045730/http://stop.genitalmutilation.org/post/UK-Questioned-over-Intersex-Genital-Mutilations-by-UN-Committee-on-the-Rights-of-the-Child | url-status = live }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Anti-pinkwashing==
Anti-pinkwashing or pinkwatching is the opposition to pinkwashing. Lynn Darwich and Hannen Maikay, in their article "The Road from Antipinkwashing Activism to the Decolonization of Palestine", allege that accusations of pinkwashing against Israel have led to an intersection of queer rights movements and Palestinian rights movements in Palestine and other countries, despite ongoing discrimination and abuse of LGBT individuals within Palestinian controlled territories. This is a strategy that has allowed the two activist groups to fight for one cause; however, it also places limits on both movements. Darwich and Maikay suggest that the anti-pinkwashing movement has to consider not only pinkwashing but also homonationalism, colonialism, and imperialism.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Darwich |first1=Lynn |last2=Maikey |first2=Haneen |date=2014 |title=The Road from Antipinkwashing Activism to the Decolonization of Palestine |url=https://www.jstor.org/stable/24365011 |journal=Women's Studies Quarterly |volume=42 |issue=3/4 |pages=281–285 |jstor=24365011 |issn=0732-1562 |access-date=November 11, 2020 |archive-date=November 12, 2020 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20201112200145/https://www.jstor.org/stable/24365011 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt; The Palestinian queer movement rejects pinkwashing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Lahiri |first1=Sukrita |title=Anti-Pinkwashing as Emerging Hope: Queering the Palestinian Liberation Movement in the Context of Institutionalised Neoliberalism |journal=International Journal of Critical Diversity Studies |date=2020 |volume=3 |issue=2 |doi=10.13169/intecritdivestud.3.2.0053}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Alqaisiya |first1=Walaa |title=Decolonial Queering: The Politics of Being Queer in Palestine |journal=Journal of Palestine Studies |date=2018 |volume=47 |issue=3 |pages=29–44 |doi=10.1525/jps.2018.47.3.29 |s2cid=158219919 |url=http://dro.dur.ac.uk/27262/1/27262.pdf |access-date=August 21, 2022 |archive-date=November 28, 2022 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20221128194447/https://dro.dur.ac.uk/27262/1/27262.pdf |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Cyril Ghosh, the argument against pinkwashing portraying Western countries as bastions of LGBT freedom while demonizing countries that lack LGBT rights protection has merit, but can fall into "Radical Theory Creep" when multiple strands of critique are combined in a way that lacks analytic rigor.{{sfn|Ghosh|2018|p=11}}

==See also==
* [[Queerbaiting]]
* [[Rainbow capitalism]]

== References ==

{{Reflist}}

==Sources==
*{{cite book |last1=Atshan |first1=Sa'ed |title=Queer Palestine and the Empire of Critique |date=2020 |publisher=Stanford University Press |isbn=978-1-5036-1240-2 |chapter=Global Solidarity and the Politics of Pinkwashing}}
*{{cite book |last1=Ghosh |first1=Cyril |title=De-Moralizing Gay Rights: Some Queer Remarks on LGBT+ Rights Politics in the US |date=2018 |publisher=Springer International Publishing |isbn=978-3-319-78840-1 |pages=11–41 |language=en |chapter=Radical Theory Creep}}
*{{cite journal |last1=Hartal |first1=Gilly |title=Touring and obscuring: how sensual, embodied and haptic gay touristic practices construct the geopolitics of pinkwashing |journal=Social &amp; Cultural Geography |date=2020 |volume=23 |issue=6 |pages=836–854 |doi=10.1080/14649365.2020.1821391|s2cid=224897595 }}
*{{cite journal |last1=Luibhéid |first1=Eithne |title=Same-sex marriage and the pinkwashing of state migration controls |journal=International Feminist Journal of Politics |date=2018 |volume=20 |issue=3 |pages=405–424 |doi=10.1080/14616742.2018.1442735|s2cid=148824463 }}
*{{cite book |last1=Russell |first1=Eric Louis |title=The Discursive Ecology of Homophobia |date=2019 |publisher=Multilingual Matters |isbn=978-1-78892-346-0 |chapter=Filip Dewinter: Pinkwashing, Populism and Nativism}}
*{{cite journal |last1=Wahab |first1=Amar |title=Affective Mobilizations: Pinkwashing and Racialized Homophobia in Out There |journal=Journal of Homosexuality |date=2021 |volume=68 |issue=5 |pages=849–871 |doi=10.1080/00918369.2019.1667158|pmid=31532347 |s2cid=202675700 }}

==Further reading==
{{Wiktionary|pinkwashing}}
*{{cite journal |last1=Bidaseca |first1=Karina |title=Sexualizar las fronteras: Pinkwashing y homonacionalismo en Palestina e Israel |journal=Horizontes Decoloniales / Decolonial Horizons |date=2020 |volume=6 |pages=121–140 |doi=10.13169/decohori.6.2020.0121 |s2cid=240825137 |issn=2422-6343}}
*{{cite journal |last1=Blackmer |first1=Corinne E. |title=Pinkwashing |journal=Israel Studies |date=2019 |volume=24 |issue=2 |pages=171 |doi=10.2979/israelstudies.24.2.14|s2cid=239402258 }}
*{{cite book |last1=Byrne |first1=Rachael |title=The Moral Panics of Sexuality |date=2013 |publisher=Palgrave Macmillan UK |isbn=978-1-137-35317-7 |pages=134–148 |chapter=Cyber Pinkwashing: Gay Rights under Occupation}}
*{{cite journal |last1=Dreher |first1=Tanja |title=Pinkwashing the past: gay rights, military history and the sidelining of protest in Australia |journal=Oñati Socio-Legal Series |volume=6 |issue=1 |date=2016 |pages=116–136 |url=https://ro.uow.edu.au/lhapapers/2608/ |ssrn=2724515 |issn=2079-5971}}
*{{cite book |last1=Lake |first1=Nadine |title=The Routledge International Handbook of Social Work and Sexualities |date=2021 |publisher=Routledge |isbn=978-0-429-34291-2 |chapter='Corrective Rape' and Black Lesbian Sexualities in South Africa: Negotiating the Tensions between 'Blackwashing' and 'Pinkwashing' Homophobia}}
*{{cite journal |last1=Ritchie |first1=Jason |title=Pinkwashing, Homonationalism, and Israel-Palestine: The Conceits of Queer Theory and the Politics of the Ordinary: Pinkwashing, Homonationalism, and Israel-Palestine |journal=Antipode |date=2015 |volume=47 |issue=3 |pages=616–634 |doi=10.1111/anti.12100|doi-access=free }}
*{{cite journal |last1=Shafie |first1=Ghadir |last2=Chávez |first2=Karma R. |title="Pinkwashing and the Boycott, Divestment, and Sanctions Campaign", May 25, 2016 |journal=Journal of Civil and Human Rights |date=2019 |volume=5/5 |pages=32–48 |doi=10.5406/jcivihumarigh.2019.0032 |s2cid=211353589 |issn=2378-4245}}
*{{cite book |last1=Koray Yılmaz-Günay &amp; Salih Alexander Wolter |title=The Queer Intersectional in Contemporary Germany |date=2018 |publisher=Psychosozial-Verlag |isbn=978-3-8379-2840-2 |chapter=Pinkwashing Germany? German Homonationalism and the "Jewish Card"}}

{{LGBTQ|social}}

[[Category:LGBTQ and society]]
[[Category:LGBTQ terminology]]
[[Category:Propaganda techniques]]
[[Category:Public relations terminology]]
[[Category:Phrases related to the Israeli-Palestinian conflict]]
[[Category:LGBTQ military history]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>