<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20171122215133|811631921" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="58164" pageid="58164" ns="0" title="Drag queen"><revisions><rev timestamp="2017-11-22T21:51:37Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Multiple issues|
  {{Refimprove|date=April 2017}}
  {{Original research|date=April 2017}}
}}
[[File:Logan Carter &amp; Roxanne Russell 1975.jpg|thumb|300px|alt=two panel photograph, the left panel is a man in a plaid shirt, the right panel is the same man wearing a fancy dress and radiant blond wig, appearing as a woman|Logan Carter (1954–1988) a.k.a. Roxanne Russell in [[Miami]] in 1975]]
{{Transgender sidebar}}
{{Crossdressing}}

A '''drag queen''' is a person, usually [[male]], who dresses in [[Drag (clothing)|clothing of the opposite sex]] and often acts with exaggerated [[femininity]] and in feminine [[gender role]]s for the purpose of entertainment or fashion. Often, they will exaggerate certain characteristics such as make-up and eyelashes for comic, dramatic, or satirical effect. While drag is very much associated with [[gay]] men and [[gay culture]], there are drag artists of all [[Human sexuality|sexualities]]. There are many kinds of drag artists and they vary greatly in dedication, from professionals who have starred in films to people who just try it once, or those who simply prefer clothing and makeup that is usually worn by the opposite sex in their culture. Drag queens can vary widely by class and culture. Other drag performers include [[drag king]]s, women who perform in male roles and attire, [[faux queen]]s, who are women who dress in an exaggerated style to emulate drag queens, and faux kings, who are men who dress to impersonate drag kings.

There are many reasons people do drag including self-expression, comfort, transvestic fetishism, and [[Two-Spirit|spiritual reasons]], as well as the higher-profile performing and entertaining. Drag can be a creative outlet, a means of self-exploration, and a way to make cultural statements. While the general public may be most familiar with the "high drag" of professional performance artists, drag is also part of regular life and street culture for many [[Gender bender|gender-nonconforming]] or [[Genderqueer|gender-variant]] people, who may or may not consider what they do, "drag."

Drag queen activities among stage and [[Street performance|street performers]] may include [[lip sync|lip-syncing]] performances, live singing, dancing, participating in events such as [[gay pride parade]]s, [[drag pageants]], or at venues such as [[cabaret]]s and [[discotheque]]s. Some drag artists also engage in mix-and-mingle or hosting work in night clubs, such as drag bingo, and at private parties and events.

== Terminology ==

===Etymology===

The [[etymology]] of the term "drag queen" is disputed. The term ''drag queen'' occurred in [[Polari]], a subset of English slang that was popular in some gay communities in the early part of the 20th century.{{citation needed|date=April 2017|reason=See Talk#Original research.}} The first recorded use of "drag" to refer to actors dressed in women's clothing is from 1870.&lt;ref name="González-2008"&gt;{{cite book |editor1=María de los Ángeles Gómez González |editor2=J. Lachlan Mackenzie |editor3=Elsa M. González Álvarez |author1=Felix Rodriguez Gonzales |title=Languages and Cultures in Contrast and Comparison |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=2Sk6AAAAQBAJ |series=Pragmatics &amp; beyond new series v 175 |date=26 June 2008 |publisher=John Benjamins Publishing Company |location=Philadelphia |page=231 |chapter=The feminine stereotype in gay characterization: A look at English and Spanish |chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=2Sk6AAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA221  |isbn=978-90-272-9052-6 |oclc=860469091 |accessdate=29 April 2017 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

A [[folk etymology]] is that ''drag'' is an [[acronym]] of "Dressed Resembling A Girl" in description of male theatrical [[transvestism]].{{citation needed|date=April 2017}} The film ''[[Connie and Carla]]'' also made a reference to this, though the acronym was slightly altered to men "Dressed as Girls."

'''Queen''' may refer to{{weasel inline|date=April 2017}} the trait of affected royalty found in the personalities of many who do drag (whether this is their normal personality or a character created for the stage).{{citation needed|date=April 2017|reason=Note that Glassman-2009 ({{ISBN|978-0-7864-3964-5}} p.34) is *not* a valid source as it quotes this Wikipedia article as a source}} It is also related to the Old English word ''[[wikt:quean|quean]]'' or ''{{lang|ang|[[wikt:cwene|cwene]]}}'', which originally simply meant "woman", then was later used as a label both for promiscuous women and gay men.&lt;ref&gt;see ''Oxford English Dictionary'' definition number 3 for "queen"&lt;/ref&gt; The Old English word appears derived from [[Middle Dutch]] ''{{lang|dum|quene}}'' ("old woman"), ultimately from [[Proto-Germanic]] *''{{lang|gem|kwenǭ}}'' ("woman"), from [[Proto-Indo-European]] *''{{PIE|gʷḗn}}'' ("woman").

===Female impersonator===
[[File:PantiBliss.jpg|thumb|left|Rory O’Neill as [[Panti Bliss]].]]

Another term for a drag queen is ''female impersonator.''&lt;ref&gt;When Cross Dressing was a crime http://www.advocate.com/arts-entertainment/books/2015/03/12/tbt-when-cross-dressing-was-crime?page=full&lt;/ref&gt; Although this is still used, it is sometimes regarded as inaccurate, because not all contemporary drag performers are attempting to [[Passing (gender)|pass]] as women. ''Female impersonation'' has been and continues to be illegal in some places, which inspired the drag queen [[José Sarria]] to hand out labels to his friends reading, "I am a boy," so he could not be accused of female impersonation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.glbtq.com/social-sciences/sarria_j.html |title=&gt;&gt; social sciences &gt;&gt; Sarria, José |publisher=glbtq |date=1923-12-12 |accessdate=2014-03-01 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131203005833/http://www.glbtq.com/social-sciences/sarria_j.html |archivedate=2013-12-03 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt; American drag queen [[RuPaul]] once said, "I do not impersonate females! How many women do you know who wear seven-inch heels, four-foot wigs, and skintight dresses?" He also said, "I don't dress like a woman; I dress like a drag queen!".

Some performers draw the distinction that a female impersonator seeks to emulate a specific female star or celebrity, while a drag queen only seeks to create a distinctive feminine persona of his or her own.

===Drag and transvestism===
{{Unreferenced section|date=May 2017}}
{{Original research|section|date=May 2017}}
[[File:2004-GayPrideBrazil-1.jpeg|thumb|left|180px|alt=4 individuals portraying women|Drag queens walking in a parade in [[São Paulo, Brazil]].]]

Drag queens are sometimes called [[transvestism|transvestites]], although that term also has many other connotations than the term "drag queen" and is not much favored by many drag queens themselves.&lt;ref&gt;Ford, Zack. "[https://thinkprogress.org/the-quiet-clash-between-transgender-women-and-drag-queens-297a9da4c5f6/ The Quiet Clash Between Transgender Women And Drag Queens]." ThinkProgress, 25 June 2014. Web. 9 September 2017.&lt;/ref&gt; This is because of the distinctions between drag queens and transvestic fetishists. "Drag queen" usually connotes cross-dressing for the purposes of entertainment and self-expression. It is not an accurate way to describe people who cross-dress for the fulfillment of [[transvestic fetishism|transvestic fetishes]] alone, i.e., people whose [[cross-dressing]] is primarily part of a private sexual activity or identity. Those whose motivation for transvestism is not primarily sexual, and who may go about their daily lives cross-dressed, often do not adopt the over-the-top drag queen look, at least not for daily wear; these individuals may or may not self-identify as drag queens.

===Alternative terms===
There are also performers who prefer to be called "gender illusionists" who do blur the line between transgender and drag queen. Generally transgender performers do not consider themselves to be drag queens and drag queens don't consider themselves to be illusionists, but, as with everything, there are exceptions. Often these distinctions are more generational, as laws and acceptance of individuality change and grow.{{original research inline|date=April 2017|reason=See Talk:Drag queen#Original research.}}

Many drag queens{{who|date=May 2017}} prefer to be referred to as "[[gender-specific pronoun|she]]" while in drag and desire to stay completely in character. Some performers object to being referred to as "he" or by their legal name while in character. Drag performer [[RuPaul]] is an exception, as he seems to be completely indifferent to which pronoun is used to refer to him. In his words, "You can call me he. You can call me she. You can call me Regis and Kathie Lee; I don't care!"&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|author=[[Rupaul]]|title=Lettin' It All Hang Out: An Autobiography|publisher=Hyperion Books|date=June 1995}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The term ''tranny'' has been adopted by some drag performers, notably RuPaul,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|first=Chris|last=Spargo |url=http://www.newnownext.com/rupaul-tranny-lance-bass-drag-race/01/2012/ |title=NEW: RuPaul's 'Tranny' Conroversy&lt;!--sic--&gt; |publisher=NewNowNext |date=2012-01-15 |accessdate=2013-10-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the gay male community&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Musto |first=Michael |url=http://blogs.villagevoice.com/dailymusto/2010/11/is_tranny_so_ba.php |title=Is "Tranny" So Bad? |publisher=Blogs.villagevoice.com |date=2010-11-12 |accessdate=2013-10-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; in the United States, but it is considered offensive to most transgender and transsexual people.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bilerico.com/2008/09/is_tranny_offensive.php |title=Is 'Tranny' Offensive? |publisher=The Bilerico Project |date=2008-09-09 |accessdate=2013-10-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the transgender community, it is taken as a degrading term along the lines of the highly offensive words "fag" and "faggot" in gay communities. This has caused the usage of the term to diminish.{{citation needed|date=April 2017}}

== History of drag ==

=== Europe ===

==== Pantomime dames ====
In the late 1800s to the mid-1900s, [[pantomime dame]]s became a popular form of female impersonation in Europe.&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt;  This was the first era of female impersonation in Europe to use comedy as part of the performance, as opposed to the serious [[Shakespeare's plays|Shakespearean]] tragedies and [[Italian opera]]s.&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt; The dame became a stock character with a range of attitudes from "charwoman" to "grande dame" that was mostly used for improvisation.&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt; The most famous and successful pantomime dame was [[Dan Leno]].  After the [[World War I|World]] [[World War II|Wars]], the theater and movie scenes were changing and the use of pantomime dames was on the decline.&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt;

=== Americas ===
[[File:Wench character 3.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Eugene d'Ameli]], a white man, dressed in [[blackface]] as an African American woman for a [[minstrel show]] in the late 19th century]]

==== Minstrel shows ====
Development of the drag queen in America started with the development of the [[blackface]] [[minstrel show]].&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{cite |last=Boyd |first=Nan Alamilla |title=Wide-Open Town |publisher=University of California Press |year=2003 |url=https://muse.jhu.edu/book/25351 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Originally the performers would only mock African American men, but as time went on they found it amusing to mock African American femininity as well.  They performed in comedic skits, dances, and "wench" songs.&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{cite |last=Bean |first=Annemarie |title=Female Impersonation in Nineteenth-Century American Blackface Minstrelsy |publisher=[[New York University]] |date=2001 |url=http://search.proquest.com/docview/304709304/abstract/21B0435A209F4C54PQ/1 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Far from the progressive freedom of modern drag, these minstrel shows and their "wench players," were used by white men to both mock and oppress both women and African Americans.&lt;ref name=":1"/&gt;

==== Vaudeville and female impersonators ====
[[File:Julian Eltinge (the fascinating widow).jpg|thumb|upright|[[Julian Eltinge]] as a female impersonator in the 1910s]]
The broad comedic stylings of the minstrel shows helped develop the [[vaudeville]] shows of the late 1800s to the early 1900s.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; With this shift, the "wench players" became "prima donnas", and became more elegant and refined, while still retaining their comedic elements.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;  While the "wenches" were purely American creations, the "prima donnas" were inspired by both America and European cross-dressing shows, like [[William Shakespeare|Shakespearean]] actors and [[castrato|castrati]].&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt; With the United States shifting demographics, including the shift from farms to cities, [[Great Migration (African American)|Great Migration]] of African Americans, and an influx of [[immigration to the United States|immigrants]], vaudeville's broad comedy and music expanded the audience from minstrelsy.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; With vaudeville becoming more popular, it allowed female impersonators to become popular as well.  Many female impersonators started with low comedy in vaudeville and worked their way up to perform as the prima donna.&lt;ref name=":2"&gt;Moore, F. Michael. ''Drag!: Male and Female Impersonators on Stage, Screen, and Television: An Illustrated World History''. Jefferson, N.C: McFarland &amp; Company, 1994.
&lt;/ref&gt; Famous female impersonator [[Julian Eltinge]] found success in this and eventually made his way to the [[Broadway theatre|broadway]] stage performing as a woman.&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt;  At this time being a female impersonator was seen as something for the straight white male, and any deviation was punished.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; Connection with [[sex work]] and [[homosexuality]] eventually lead to the decline of vaudeville during the [[Progressive Era]].&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; Both the minstrelsy and vaudeville eras of female impersonation led to an association with music, dance, and comedy that still lasts today.&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt;

==== Night clubs ====
In the early to mid-1900s, female impersonation had become tied to the [[LGBT community]]{{Dubious|reason=This cannot be right as stated; there was no LGBT community in the mid 1900s, that didn't form till later|date=May 2017}} and thus criminality, so it had to change forms and locations.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;  It moved from being popular mainstream entertainment to something done only at night in disreputable areas, such as San Francisco's [[Tenderloin, San Francisco|Tenderloin]].&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;  Here female impersonation started to evolve into what we today know as [[Drag (clothing)|drag]] and Drag Queens.&lt;ref name=":3"&gt;Baker, Roger. ''Drag: A History of Female Impersonation in the Performing Arts''. NYU Press, 1994.
&lt;/ref&gt;  Drag queens such as [[José Sarria]]&lt;ref&gt;"The Drag Times." ''Drag'', 1980. Archives of Sexuality.
&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Aleshia Brevard]]&lt;ref name="SMTimes-1961"&gt;{{cite news |author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt; |date=February 3, 1961 |title=Finocchio's 1961 Revue One of LaMonte's Best |url=https://www.newspapers.com/newspage/38985183/ |newspaper=The Times |location=San Mateo, California |page=23 |access-date=May 11, 2017 }}&lt;/ref&gt; first came to prominence in these clubs.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;  People went to these [[Gay nightclub|nightclubs]] to play with the boundaries of gender and sexuality and it became a place for the LBGT community, especially gay men, to feel accepted.  As [[LGBT culture]] has slowly become more accepted in American society, drag has also become more, though not totally, acceptable in today's society.&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt;

==== Protests ====
{{Main|Cooper Do-nuts Riot|Compton's Cafeteria riot|Stonewall riots|Invasion of the Pines}}
The [[Cooper Do-nuts Riot]] was a May 1959 incident in Los Angeles, in which drag queens, lesbians, transgender women, and gay men rioted; it was one of the first [[LGBT]] uprisings in the US.&lt;ref name="Out"&gt;{{cite news|last1=Moffitt|first1=Evan|title=10 Years Before Stonewall, There Was the Cooper's Donuts Riot|url=https://www.out.com/today-gay-history/2015/5/31/today-gay-history-10-years-stonewall-there-was-coopers-donuts-riot|accessdate=30 June 2017|work=Out Magazine|agency=Here Media Inc.|date=31 May 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1966 in San Francisco, the [[Compton's Cafeteria riot]], which involved drag queens and others, occurred.&lt;ref name="boyd"&gt;Boyd, Nan Alamilla (2004). "San Francisco" in the ''Encyclopedia of Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual and Transgendered History in America'', Ed. Marc Stein. Vol. 3. Charles Scribner's Sons. pp. 71–78.&lt;/ref&gt; It marked the beginning of [[transgender]] activism in San Francisco.&lt;ref name="boyd"/&gt;

On March 17, 1968, in [[Los Angeles]], to protest [[entrapment]] and harassment by the LAPD, two drag queens known as "The Princess" and "The Duchess" held a St. Patrick's Day party at [[Griffith Park]], a popular [[cruising for sex|cruising]] spot and a frequent target of police activity. More than 200 gay men socialized through the day.&lt;ref&gt;Witt, Lynn, Sherry Thomas and Eric Marcus (eds.) (1995). ''Out in All Directions: The Almanac of Gay and Lesbian America,'' pg. 210. New York, Warner Books. {{ISBN|0-446-67237-8}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

Drag queens were also involved in the [[Stonewall riots]], which were a series of spontaneous, violent demonstrations by members of the [[LGBT community]] against a [[police raid]] that took place in the early morning hours of June 28, 1969, at the [[Stonewall Inn]], located in the [[Greenwich Village]] neighborhood of [[Manhattan]], [[New York City]]. They are widely considered to constitute the single most important event leading to the [[gay liberation]] movement and the modern fight for [[LGBT rights in the United States]].&lt;ref name=diversity&gt;{{cite web |author=National Park Service |title=Workforce Diversity: The Stonewall Inn, National Historic Landmark National Register Number: 99000562 |url=http://www.nps.gov/diversity/stonewall.htm |publisher=US Department of Interior |year=2008 |accessdate=January 21, 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.northjersey.com/news/2012_Presidential_Election/Obama_inaugural_speech_references_Stonewall_riots.html |title=Obama inaugural speech references Stonewall gay-rights riots |publisher=North Jersey Media Group Inc |date=January 21, 2013 |accessdate=January 21, 2013 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130723025158/http://www.northjersey.com/news/2012_Presidential_Election/Obama_inaugural_speech_references_Stonewall_riots.html |archivedate=July 23, 2013 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the summer of 1976, a restaurant in [[Fire Island Pines, New York|Fire Island Pines]], [[New York (state)|New York]], denied entry to a visitor in drag named Terry Warren. When Warren's friends in Cherry Grove heard what had happened, they dressed up in drag, and, on [[United States Bicentennial|July 4, 1976]], sailed to the Pines by [[water taxi]]. This turned into a yearly event where drag queens go to the Pines, called the [[Invasion of the Pines]].

==== Story time in libraries ====
In December 2015, [[Radar Productions]] and [[Michelle Tea]] developed the concept of "Drag Queen Story Hour".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last1=Lamarche |first1=Una |title=Drag Queen Story Hour Puts the Rainbow in Reading |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2017/05/19/style/drag-queen-story-hour-puts-the-rainbow-in-reading.html |accessdate=22 June 2017 |work=[[The New York Times]] |date=19 May 2017 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Launched at the [[San Francisco Public Library]], Drag Queen Story Hour was adopted by the [[Brooklyn Public Library]] in the summer of 2016, and has since traveled to various libraries, museums, bookstores, and recreation centers, and parks across the United States, Canada, and the United Kingdom.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=About Drag Queen Story Hour|url=https://www.dragqueenstoryhour.org/#about|website=Drag Queen Story Hour -- drag queens reading stories to children in libraries, schools, and bookstores|publisher=Drag Queen Story Hour|accessdate=22 June 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Drag queen names ==
[[File:Eddie Valdez "José Maria González" Wild Side Story 1977.jpg|thumb|alt=Man reading a book in a store|José ''Maria'' Gonzalez reading about drag characters ''Consuelo'' and ''Obvióla'' sets the stage for the comedy plot of ''[[Wild Side Story]]'']]
Examples of drag queen names are Alexis Michelle, Roxanne Russell &lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://gaytoday.com/garchive/people/051997pe.htm |title=Logan Carter Remembered |last=Nichols |first=Jack |date=May 19, 1997 |work=Gay Today |archiveurl=https://www.webcitation.org/5ccMUseX7?url=http://gaytoday.com/garchive/people/051997pe.htm |archivedate=2008-11-26 |deadurl=yes |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Christer Lindarw|Zsa Zsa Shakespeer]].&lt;ref&gt;Kalle Westerling in ''La Dolce Vita'' {{ISBN|91-85505-15-3}} p 22&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Christina Kjellberg &amp; Christer Lindarw in ''This Is My Life'' {{ISBN|978-91-7424-533-2}} p 83&lt;/ref&gt; A drag queen may either pick or be given a drag name by a friend, sometimes called a {{anchor|drag mother}}"drag mother", the so named thus becoming known as a {{anchor|drag daughter}}"drag daughter".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.es/books?id=FsGxTL0gtZUC&amp;pg=PA168&amp;dq=%22drag+mother%22&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwibr5-hiL3TAhVMuxQKHXFpCPkQ6AEILzAC#v=onepage&amp;q=%22drag%20mother%22&amp;f=false|title=Drag Queens at the 801 Cabaret|last=Rupp|first=Leila J.|last2=Taylor|first2=Verta A.|date=2003-05-15|publisher=University of Chicago Press|year=|isbn=9780226731582|location=|pages=168|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; Drag mothers and drag daughters have a [[mentorship|mentor]] - apprentice relationship. [[Ball culture#Washington, D.C.|Drag families]] were part of [[ball culture]] and drag houses around 1960.&lt;ref name="dc"&gt;{{cite web
 |title=The Rainbow History Project: Drag in DC
 |publisher=Rainbow History Project
 |date=2000–2007
 |url=http://www.rainbowhistory.org/html/drag.html
 |accessdate=2007-10-20
 |deadurl=yes
 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140614052021/http://www.rainbowhistory.org/html/drag.html
 |archivedate=2014-06-14
 |df=
 }}&lt;/ref&gt;{{citation needed|date=April 2017}}

== Art of drag ==
[[File:ESC2014 - Austria 16.jpg|thumb|alt=man with long hair and a beard, wearing a radiant gold dress|[[Conchita Wurst]], the winner of the Eurovision Song Contest 2014]]
The process of getting into drag or into character can take hours. A drag queen may aim for a certain style, celebrity impression, or message with their look. Hair, make-up, and costumes are the most important essentials for drag queens.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dukechronicle.com/articles/2002/10/03/dude-diva-how-become-drag-queen |title=Dude to Diva: How to Become a Drag Queen &amp;#124; The Chronicle |publisher=Dukechronicle.com |date= |accessdate=2014-03-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Drag queens tend to go for a more exaggerated look with a lot more makeup than a typical feminine woman would wear.

With the complete look, drag queens often go out to clubs and bars, where they will typically perform an act which is called a "drag show."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|first=Mark|last=King |url=https://www.theguardian.com/money/2011/aug/12/drag-queen-cookie-monstar |title=A working life: the drag queen &amp;#124; Money |publisher=The Guardian |date= |accessdate=2014-03-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Many drag queens do dress up for money by doing different shows, but there are also drag queens that have full-time jobs but still enjoy dressing up in drag as a hobby.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/tom-bartolomei/10-myths-about-drag-queens_b_2979249.html |title=Tom Bartolomei: 10 Myths About Drag Queens |publisher=Huffingtonpost.com |date=2013-04-01 |accessdate=2014-03-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Many parts of the drag show, and of the drag queens’ other intellectual properties, cannot be protected by intellectual property law. To substitute the lack of legal protection, drag queens revert to social norms in order to protect their intellectual property.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Sarid|first1=Eden|title=Don’t Be a Drag, Just Be a Queen - How Drag Queens Protect their Intellectual Property without Law|journal=Florida International University Law Review|date=2014|volume=10|issue=1|url=http://ecollections.law.fiu.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1242&amp;context=lawreview|accessdate=8 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== In entertainment ==

=== Drag shows and venues ===
[[File:Lorellasukkiarini.jpg|thumb|alt=a drag queen putting on lip liner|Lorella Sukkiarini, an Italian drag queen, preparing stage make-up.]]
A '''drag show''' is an entertainment consisting of a variety of songs, [[monologue]]s or skits featuring either single performers or groups of performers in drag meant to entertain an audience. They range from amateur performances at small bars to elaborately staged theatrical presentations. Many drag shows feature performers singing or [[Lip sync|lip-synching]] to songs while performing a pre-planned [[pantomime]], or dancing. The performers often don elaborate costumes and makeup, and sometimes dress to imitate various famous female singers or personalities. Some events are centered around drag, such as [[Southern Decadence]] where the majority of festivities are led by the Grand Marshals, who are traditionally drag queens.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.southerndecadence.net |title=Southern Decadence Official Website |publisher=Southerndecadence.net |date=2013-09-03 |accessdate=2014-03-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== In film ===
* 1937 – ''[[Upstairs (film)|Upstairs]]'' ([[:pl:Piętro wyżej|Piętro wyżej]]), first drag queen style movie, starring [[Eugeniusz Bodo]] 
* 1953 – ''[[Glen or Glenda]]'', one of the most famous cult classics of [[Ed Wood]], starring himself as Glen and Glenda.
* 1954 – ''[[White Christmas (film)|White Christmas]]'',  classic of  [[Irving Berlin]], with [[Danny Kaye]] and [[Bing Crosby]] singing in "drag".
* 1959 – ''[[Some Like It Hot]]'', starring [[Marilyn Monroe]], [[Tony Curtis]] and [[Jack Lemmon]].
* 1967 – ''[[Thoroughly Modern Millie]]'', an American musical starring [[Julie Andrews]], [[James Fox (actor)|James Fox]], [[Mary Tyler Moore]], [[Carol Channing]], [[John Gavin]], and [[Beatrice Lillie]], notable where Fox's character dresses in drag in order to find out what happened to Tyler Moore's character.
* 1969 – ''[[Funeral Parade of Roses]]'' starring [[Peter (actor)|Peter]]
* 1972 – ''[[Pink Flamingos]]'' starring [[Divine (actor)|Divine]]
* 1975 – ''[[The Rocky Horror Picture Show]]'', with [[Tim Curry]] as a cross-dressing bi-sexual, [[Susan Sarandon]], [[Barry Bostwick]]
* 1977 – ''[[Outrageous!]]'', starring [[Craig Russell (Canadian actor)|Craig Russell]] as a fictionalized version of himself
* 1979 – ''[[The Rose (film)|The Rose]]'' starring [[Bette Midler]], notable for a scene in which Midler's character Mary Rose Foster performs a duet on stage in a drag club with a drag queen (played by Kenny Sacha) who is impersonating Midler as Foster.
* 1982 – ''[[Tootsie (film)|Tootsie]]'' starring [[Dustin Hoffman]], [[Jessica Lange]], and [[Teri Garr]]
* 1982 – ''[[Victor/Victoria]]'' starring [[Julie Andrews]]
* 1985 – ''[[Lust in the Dust]]'' starring [[Divine (actor)|Divine]]
* 1988 – ''[[Hairspray (1988 film)|Hairspray]]'' starring [[Divine (actor)|Divine]] (Remade [[Hairspray (2007 film)|in 2007]] starring [[John Travolta]])
* 1988 – ''[[Torch Song Trilogy (film)|Torch Song Trilogy]]'' starring [[Harvey Fierstein]], [[Anne Bancroft]] and [[Matthew Broderick]]
* 1990 – ''[[Paris Is Burning (film)|Paris Is Burning]]'' a documentary film directed by [[Jennie Livingston]]. It chronicles the ball culture of New York City and the gay and transgender community involved in it. It centers around African American and Latino drag culture surrounding communities such as Harlem in the 80s.
* 1991 – ''[[Vegas in Space]]'' starring [[Doris Fish]], [[Miss X (actress)|Miss X]], [[Ginger Quest]], and introducing 'Tippi'
* 1993 – ''[[Mrs. Doubtfire]]'' starring [[Robin Williams]], [[Sally Field]], and [[Pierce Brosnan]].
* 1994 – ''[[The Adventures of Priscilla, Queen of the Desert]]'' starring [[Terence Stamp]], [[Hugo Weaving]], and [[Guy Pearce]]
* 1995 – ''[[To Wong Foo, Thanks for Everything! Julie Newmar]]'' starring [[Wesley Snipes]], [[Patrick Swayze]], and [[John Leguizamo]] (cameo by [[RuPaul]])
* 1995 – ''[[Wigstock: The Movie]]'' documentary film focusing on the annual drag music festival that had been held in New York City's East Village during the 1980s and 1990s.  Includes appearances by [[Lady Bunny]], [[Crystal Waters]], [[Deee-Lite]], [[Jackie Beat]], [[Debbie Harry]], [[Leigh Bowery]], [[Joey Arias]] and the [[Tallulah Bankhead|Dueling Bankheads]]. The film also captures a performance by [[RuPaul]] at the height of his mainstream fame during the 1990s.
* 1996 – ''[[The Birdcage]]'' starring [[Robin Williams]], [[Nathan Lane]], [[Gene Hackman]] and [[Dianne Wiest]] (a remake of the 1978 film ''[[La Cage aux Folles (film)|La Cage aux Folles]]'', based on the 1973 play)
* 1996 – ''[[The Nutty Professor (1996 film)|The Nutty Professor]]'' starring [[Eddie Murphy]].
* 1998 – ''[[Midnight in the Garden of Good and Evil]]'' starring [[John Cusack]], [[Kevin Spacey]] and starring as herself [[Lady Chablis]]
* 1999 – ''[[Flawless (1999 film)|Flawless]]'' starring [[Philip Seymour Hoffman]] and [[Robert De Niro]]
* 2000 – ''[[Big Momma's House]]'' starring [[Martin Lawrence]]
* 2001 – ''[[Hedwig and the Angry Inch (film)|Hedwig and the Angry Inch]]'' starring [[John Cameron Mitchell]]
* 2002 - ''[[Sorority Boys]]''
* 2003 – ''[[Girls Will Be Girls (film)|Girls Will Be Girls]]'' directed by Richard Day, starring Miss Coco Peru (Clinton Leupp), Evie Harris (Jack Plotnick), and Varla Jean Merman (Jeffery Roberson).
* 2003 – ''[[Die, Mommie, Die!]]'' starring [[Charles Busch]], [[Jason Priestley]],  [[Philip Baker Hall]], and [[Natasha Lyonne]]
* 2004 – ''[[Connie and Carla]]'' starring [[Nia Vardalos]], [[Toni Collette]], and [[David Duchovny]]
* 2004 – ''[[White Chicks]]'' starring [[Shawn Wayans]] and [[Marlon Wayans]]
* 2005 – ''[[Kinky Boots (film)|Kinky Boots]]'' starring [[Joel Edgerton]], [[Chiwetel Ejiofor]], [[Sarah-Jane Potts]], and [[Nick Frost]]
* 2005 – ''[[Rent (film)|Rent]]''
* 2006 – ''[[The Curiosity of Chance]]'' starring [[Tad Hilgenbrink]] and [[Brett Chukerman]]
* 2006 – ''I Wanna Be a Republican'' starring [[The Kinsey Sicks]], America's Favorite Dragapella Beautyshop Quartet
* 2007 – ''[[A Shade Before Pink]]'' features cross dressing, drag queens and gender questioning. Starring Cary Woodworth and Rhoda Jordan, guest appearance by Jackie Beat.
* 2007 – ''[[St. Trinian's (film)|St. Trinian's]]'' starring [[Rupert Everett]] as Camilla Fritton, the headmistress of the school.
* 2008 – ''Slingbacks and Syrup'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.newenglandfilm.com/magazine/archives/2009/01/slingbacks |title=Burlington Beauties, Erin Trahan, New England Film, January 1, 2009 |publisher=Newenglandfilm.com |date= |accessdate=2014-03-01 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140308193548/http://www.newenglandfilm.com/magazine/archives/2009/01/slingbacks |archivedate=March 8, 2014 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Bourne |first=Kay |url=http://www.edgeboston.com/index.php?ch=entertainment&amp;sc=movies&amp;sc2=&amp;sc3=dvd&amp;id=84151 |title=Edge, Boston, MA, December 3, 2008 |publisher=Edgeboston.com |date=2008-12-03 |accessdate=2014-03-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vtiff.org/pastfilms/slingbacks-and-syrup VTIFF Website, 2008.]  {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100508062448/http://www.vtiff.org/pastfilms/slingbacks-and-syrup |date=May 8, 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=James |first=Megan |url=http://www.7dvt.com/2008viff-moves-palace-9 |title=VIFF Moves to Palace 9, Seven Days, October 15, 2008 |publisher=7dvt.com |date= |accessdate=2014-03-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; a documentary about the [[House of LeMay]] that held its world premiere at the [[Vermont]] International Film Festival.
* 2009 – ''Tamid oto chalom'', an [[Israel]]i TV miniseries about drag life in [[Tel Aviv]], based on the songs of Israeli songwriter [[Svika Pick]]
* 2010 – ''[[Yazima Beauty Salon the Movie]]'' featuring drag comedy/dance group [[Yazima Beauty Salon]]
* 2011 – ''[[Big Mommas: Like Father Like Son]]'' starring [[Martin Lawrence]] and [[Brandon T. Jackson]]
* 2012 - ''[[Albert Nobbs]]'' starring [[Glenn Close]] and [[Janet McTeer]]
* 2015 – ''[[Dressed As A Girl]]'' starring [[Jonny Woo (comedian)|Johnny Woo]]
* 2016 - ''[[Absolutely Fabulous: The Movie]]'' starring [[Joanna Lumley]] and [[Jennifer Saunders]], featuring [[Jodie Harsh]] and La Voix amongst others
* 2016 - ''[[Iru Mugan|Iru mugan]]'' (Indian Tamil movie) starring [[Vikram (actor)|Vikram]], [[Nayanthara]], [[Nithya Menen]] and [[Nassar|Nasser]] in the lead roles.
* 2016 - ''[[Hurricane Bianca]]'' starring [[Bianca Del Rio]], [[Willam Belli]], [[Shangela Laquifa Wadley]] and appearances by [[RuPaul]], [[Joslyn Fox]] and [[Alyssa Edwards]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.imdb.com/title/tt4007248/fullcredits?ref_=tt_ov_st_sm|title=Hurricane Bianca (2016)|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== In music ===
[[File:Miss Understood by David Shankbone.jpg|thumb|right|170px|alt=a drag queen, holding a guitar above her head. She has a bright pink wig on|[[Miss Understood]], who has appeared in several films and on television]]
While some male music celebrities wear exaggerated feminine clothing as part of their show, they are not necessarily drag queens. For example, [[Boy George]] wears drag queen style clothes and cosmetics but he once stated he was not a drag queen.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Fi6offnQQN0 |title=Boy George: "I'M Not A Dragqueen!" At Youtube |publisher=Youtube.com |date=2007-12-27 |accessdate=2014-03-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[RuPaul]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dragqueendiaries.com/rupaul.htm Rupaul Biography] Drag Queen Diaries&lt;/ref&gt; is a professional drag queen performer.

Examples of songs where lyrics refer to drag queens:
* "[[Lola (song)|Lola]]" by [[The Kinks]]
* "[[Walk on the Wild Side (Lou Reed song)|Walk on the Wild Side]]" by [[Lou Reed]]
* "[[Dude (Looks Like a Lady)]]" by [[Aerosmith]]
* "The Lady is a Vamp" by [[Spice Girls]]
* "[[Ballad of Cleo and Joe]]" by [[Cyndi Lauper]]
* "King for a Day" by [[Green Day]]
* "[[Cherry Lips]]" by [[Garbage (band)|Garbage]]
* "[[Born This Way (song)|Born This Way]]" by [[Lady Gaga]]
* "Verbatim" by [[Mother Mother]]
* "He's a Woman She's a Man" by [[Scorpions (band)|Scorpions]]
* "Pretty Lady" by [[Kesha|Ke$ha]] &amp; [[Detox (drag queen)|Detox Icunt]]
* "Andrew in Drag" by [[The Magnetic Fields]]
* "[[Rise Like a Phoenix]]" by [[Conchita Wurst]] (Represented [[Austria]] at the [[2014 Eurovision Song Contest]] and won)
* "Divine" by [[Antony and the Johnsons]]
* "World Top" by Bear Trap
* "The End." in the album ''[[The Black Parade]]'' by [[My Chemical Romance]]
* "Drag Queen" by [[The Strokes]]
* "LGBT" by [[Cupcakke|cupcaKke]]
* "C.L.A.T" by [[Aja (drag queen)|Aja]], [[Peppermint]], [[Sasha Velour]] and [[Alexis Michelle]]

== Societal reception ==
Drag has come to be a celebrated aspect of modern gay life.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Sarid|first1=Eden|title=Don ’t Be a Drag, Just Be a Queen—How Drag Queens Protect their Intellectual Property without Law|journal=Florida International University Law Review|date=2014|volume=10|issue=1|page=142|url=http://ecollections.law.fiu.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1242&amp;context=lawreview}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many gay bars and clubs around the world hold drag shows as special parties. Several "International Drag Day" holidays have been started over the years to promote the shows. In the U.S. drag is typically celebrated in early March.

A televised drag competition, ''[[RuPaul's Drag Race]]'', is the most successful program on the [[Logo (TV channel)|Logo]] television network. In 2016, RuPaul's Drag Race won an [[Emmy Award|Emmy]] award for "Outstanding Host for a Reality or Reality-Competition Program."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.emmys.com/shows/rupauls-drag-race|title=RuPaul's Drag Race|website=Television Academy|access-date=2016-09-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;  However, its winners and contestants have yet to receive the same level of recognition as mainstream reality show contestants.

Within the larger [[lesbian]], [[gay]], [[bisexual]], [[transgender]] ([[LGBT]]) community, drag queens are sometimes criticized for their participation in pride parades and other public events, believing that this projects a limited and harmful image of gay people and impedes a broader social acceptance. This attitude itself is criticized for limiting self-expression and encouraging the idea that there are "right" and "wrong" ways to be gay. In more recent years drag queens have been prominently featured at these same events.

A common criticism of drag queens is that they promote negative stereotypes of women, comparable to [[blackface]] (a racially offensive portrayal of [[black people]] by white performers that was popular throughout the 19th to early 20th century). Conversely, some feminists embrace drag as a skewering of traditional gender roles, defying the social norms of male and female appearance and behaviour and showing the artificiality of femininity and masculinity.

Drag queens are sometimes criticized by members of the transgender community — especially, but not exclusively, by many [[trans women]] — because of fears that they themselves may be stereotyped as drag queens. For example, the late [[Star Maris]], a Canadian transgender activist, wrote a song entitled "I'm Not A Fucking Drag Queen" which expresses her frustration and hurt at being mistaken for a drag queen. The song was featured in the film ''[[Better Than Chocolate]]'', performed by a trans woman on stage at a gay club. The transgender character, played by [[Peter Outerbridge]], struggles throughout the movie to fit in with [[cisgender]] women, and performs the song partially as an act of cathartic defiance and self-empowerment. Other trans women reject those criticisms in the broader context that drag queens, many of whom are [[gender-variant]] and sexuality minorities, are more of an ally for the cause of recognition and equality.

== See also ==
{{Commons|Drag queen}}
{{div col|colwidth=25em}}
* [[Ball culture]]
* ''[[Cover Girl (TV series)|Cover Girl]]''
* [[Cross-dressing]]
* [[Drag pageantry]]
* [[Finocchio's Club]]
* [[Imperial Court System]]
* [[Kiki and Herb|Kiki DuRane]]
* [[List of drag queens]]
* [[List of transgender-related topics]]
* [[Pansy Craze]]
* [[Sisters of Perpetual Indulgence]]
* [[Stonewall riots]]
* ''[[The Pink Mirror]]'', a film on Indian drag queens
* ''[[Tootsie]]'' &lt;!-- A film that showed drag techniques to mainstream audiences --&gt;
* ''[[Vegas in Space]]''
* [[Wanda Wisdom]]
* [[Wild Side Story]]
{{div col end}}

== Notes==
{{Reflist|30em}}

== External links ==
{{wiktionary|female impersonator}}
{{wiktionary|drag queen}}
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20140714215908/http://www.dragqueensonline.com/ Drag Social Network, community and portal]
* [http://www.queermusicheritage.com/drag.html Drag Artist Discography (information and discography with historical references and photos) of drag artists &amp; female impersonators]
* [http://www.solarispictures.com ''The Pink Mirror'' – a film on Indian drag queens]
* [http://www.queensoflasvegas.com Queens of Las Vegas drag show]
* [https://groups.yahoo.com/group/International_Drag_Queens_and_Friends/ International Drag Queens and Friends]
{{LGBT|culture=expanded}}

[[Category:Drag queens| ]]
[[Category:Transgender identities]]
[[Category:Cross-dressing]]
[[Category:Performance art]]
[[Category:Female impersonators]]
[[Category:Pop culture language]]
[[Category:Gender]]
[[Category:Sexuality-related lists]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>