<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20021029053355|411459" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="58164" pageid="58164" ns="0" title="Drag queen"><revisions><rev timestamp="2002-11-08T06:25:54Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[eo:Regxinjo]]'''Drag queen''', in current anglo-american [[Queer]] culture, is a person, typically a [[gay]] man or [[transgender]]ed woman, who performs in ''drag'': a costume of extremely gaudy dresses and shoes, large wigs, etc., or that imitates famous female film or pop-music stars. Drag queens sing or lip-synch, dance, and participate in shows, parades such as [[gay pride]] parades, cabarets, discotheques, and other celebrations.

'''Drag kings''' are the female equivalent of drag queens, that is to say, women who wear who perform hilariously exaggerated macho attitudes and characters in ostentatious mens' clothes. They are largely a phenomenon of [[lesbian]] culture.

"Drag queen" used to be a slang term for [[transvestite]] or [[transgender]]ed person. However, this usage is both dated and widely considered inappropriate (Canadian transgender activist Star Maris wrote a song entitled ''I'm Not A Fucking Drag Queen'' to express the difference.)

Drag queens (as the term is now used) were formerly called [[transvestite]]s. However, that term is now mostly used for someone with a [[fetish]] for the [[clothing]] of the opposite [[gender]]. Contrariwise, drag queens in general do not do drag for reasons of sexual pleasure. Furthermore, most transvestites are [[heterosexual]] men, whereas most drag queens are [[gay]] or [[transgender]]ed. (Indeed, there is a (small) community of straight women drag queens.)

Drag itself is often thought of as a subspecies of transgender, because it subverts gender roles. However, many drag queens are [[cisgendered]] gay men in the rest of their lives, whereas transgendered people remain so 24 hours a day. Drag is best thought of as a [[hobby]], profession, or [[art]] form rather than as a [[sexual orientation]] or [[gender identity]]. 

By courtesy, most drag queens are usually referred to as "she" while in drag.

Another term, "female impersonator," can be misleading. As the famous American drag queen [[RuPaul]] said, "I do not impersonate females! How many women do you know who wear seven inch heels, four foot wigs, and skintight dresses?" (See below.) 

"Female impersonation" used to be illegal in many places, which inspired the famous drag queen [[Silvia Rivera]] to suggest to her friends that they should wear buttons saying "I am a boy" so they couldn't be accused of female impersonation.

Drag is a part of Western [[gay culture]] - drag queens fought at the [[Stonewall riots]] in [[June]] [[1969]], and drag shows are traditional at [[pride parade]]s. Prominent drag queens in the Queer community of a city often serve as unofficial spokespersons, chroniclers, or community leaders.

The drag aesthetic is based on [[clown]]-like values like exaggeration, [[satire]], dirty [[joke]]s, putting on airs, and so forth. The idea of [[camp]] is also very important in drag.

Some members of the Queer community disdain drag queens; some [[feminism|feminists]] believe that drag consists in harmful stereotypes of women. A response is that drag is a very specific aesthetic (as RuPaul implies in the quotation above) and is not meant to satirize women in general. Furthermore, many gender theorists see drag as a subversive to [[gender roles]].

Some are distressed by the participation of drag queens for example in pride parades, believing that that projects a harmful image of the Queer community and impedes acceptance. However, others see this point of view as intolerant of the diversity in the community, and still others simply regard drag as traditional fun that needn't be politically analyzed.

Some of the more well-known drag performers include:

* [[RuPaul]]  www.rupaul.com
* [[Milton Berle]]
* [[Jolene Sugarbaker]] www.jolenestrailerpark.com
* [[Shirley Q Liquor]] www.shirleyqliquor.com
* [[The Lady Bunny]] 
* [[Pussy Tourette]]
* [[The Lady Chablis]]


External links:
* [http://dmoz.org/Society/Transgendered/Arts_and_Entertainment/Drag/Drag_Kings/ Open Directory category: Drag Kings]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>