<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20041108161833|7327182" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="58164" pageid="58164" ns="0" title="Drag queen"><revisions><rev timestamp="2004-11-11T04:43:42Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">&lt;table align=right width=296&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;[[image:Dragqueens.jpg]]
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;small&gt;''Drag queens Luc D'Arcy and Jerry Cyr and friend at Montreal's 2003 Divers-Cit&amp;eacute; pride parade''&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

'''Drag queens''' are performers - usually [[gay]] men, sometimes [[transgender]]ed women - who dress in ''drag'', clothing associated with the female [[gender role|gender]], usually highly exaggerated versions thereof. Drag queens often do drag to perform, singing or [[lip-synch]]ing and dancing, participating in events such as [[gay pride]] parades, cabarets, discotheques, and other celebrations and venues.

Female-bodied people who perform in usually exaggerated men's clothes and personae are called [[drag king]]s, though this term has a wider meaning than ''drag queen''. 

Drag is a part of Western [[gay culture]] - drag queens fought at the [[Stonewall riots]] in [[June]] [[1969]], and drag shows are traditional at [[pride parade]]s. Prominent drag queens in the [[lesbigay]] community of a city often serve as official or unofficial spokespersons, fundraisers, chroniclers, or community leaders.

Non-western cultures have traditions similar to drag, often existing among their [[GLBT]] communities; the western notion of drag is also becoming more common in non-western GLBT communities.

==Genres==

&lt;table align=right width=448&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;[[image:Mado.jpg]]
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;small&gt;''Drag queen Mado Lamotte performs at'' Mascara: La nuit des drags ''in Montreal''&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/table&gt; 

*High ''[[camp]]'' drag queens employ a drag aesthetic based on [[clown]]-like values like exaggeration, [[satire]], dirty [[joke]]s, "putting on airs," and so forth.  [[Divine]] is an example of a camp queen.

*Some drag queens, though not as outr&amp;eacute; as camp queens, employ highly exaggerated feminine personae. 

*Some drag queens exaggerate in the dimension of elegance and fashion, employing jewelry and beautiful gowns. [[The Lady Chablis]], who can be seen in the movie ''[[Midnight in the Garden of Good and Evil]]'' is an example of this type of performer. Many such drag queens impersonate specific actresses and other pop divas, such as [[Cher (singer)|Cher]], [[Madonna (singer)|Madonna]], [[Céline Dion]], and so forth.

*Some drag queens either do not perform or perform only rarely.  Their forte is participating in [[pageant]]s, hence the term ''pageant queen''.  Pageant queens gear their act toward winning titles and prizes in various contests and pageantry systems.  Some of these have grand prizes that rival those of pageants such as [[Miss America]].

==Terminology==

The term ''drag queen'' originates in [[Polari]], the language of gay men in England in the early part of the last century.  ''Drag'' meant "clothes", and was also theatre slang for a woman's costume worn by a male actor. A ''queen'' is an effeminate gay man.

Another term for drag queen, '''female impersonator''', is common in some areas, but considered dated in others. Drag queens are generally not literally  "female impersonators" in that they do not attempt to [[gay slang|pass]] as women. ''Female impersonation'', under that name, used to be illegal in many places, which inspired the famous drag queen [[José Sarria]] to hand out labels to his friends reading "I am a boy," so they could not be accused of female impersonation. [http://www.glbtq.com/social-sciences/sarria_j.html] American drag queen [[RuPaul]] famously said "I do not impersonate females! How many women do you know who wear seven-inch heels, four-foot wigs, and skintight dresses?" 

Most drag queens prefer to be referred to as "[[gender-specific pronoun|she]]" while in drag. Many performers protect their character quite vigorously and will be offended if they are referred to as "he" or by their legal name while they are in drag.

==Drag and transgender==

Most drag queens perform for fulfilment as a [[hobby]], a [[profession]], or an [[art]] form; as a way to be in the spotlight; or as a road to local or wider fame.

Drag queens are sometimes called '''transvestites''', however, [[transvestism]] is a word with many different meanings, most of which do not apply to or include Drag queens. Drag queens do not do drag for reasons of sexual pleasure, and are also not [[transvestic fetishism|transvestic fetishists]], people who have a sexual fetish for the [[clothing]] of another [[gender role]]. Furthermore, most people who are called or self-identify as [[transvestites]] are [[heterosexual]] men, whereas most drag queens are [[gay]] or [[transgender]]ed. 

Also, there is a (small) community of female-bodied drag queens, who may have one of several gender identities, with ''[[queer]]'' being rather common.

Drag itself is often thought of as part of [[transgender]]ism because it subverts gender roles. However, most drag queens are [[cisgender]]ed gay men (that is, they identify, appear, and are embodied as men) in the remainder of their lives when not in drag. 

Nevertheless, a number of people identifying as transgendered or [[transsexual]] women perform as drag queens, and a number of drag queens who do not identify as transgendered regard drag as being an important part of their understanding of their [[gender identity]].

== Opinions ==

Drag queens are often rejected by parts of the transgender community - especially, but not exclusively, by many [[transsexual]] women - because those people are afraid that they might be stereotyped as Drag Queens, too, which they are not. (Canadian transgender activist Star Maris wrote a song entitled ''I'm Not A Fucking Drag Queen'' to express her feelings on the subject.)

Some [[feminism|feminists]] believe that drag promotes harmful stereotypes of women. Most drag artists would respond that drag is a very specific aesthetic and is not meant to satirize women in general. Many gender theorists see drag as a subversion of gender roles.

Some members of the lesbigay community also disdain drag queens. Some are distressed by the participation of drag queens in pride parades, believing that this projects a harmful image of the lesbigay community and impedes acceptance. However, others see this point of view as intolerant of the diversity in the community, and still others simply regard drag as traditional fun that need not be politically analyzed.

==Famous drag queens==

Some of the more well-known drag performers include:

* [[Adora]]
* [[Enza Anderson|Enza "Supermodel" Anderson]]
* [[Shirley Temple Bar]] 
* [[Milton Berle]]
* [[Joan Jett Blakk]]
* [[Cookie Buffet]]
* [[Bugs Bunny]] (cartoon character frequently in drag)
* [[Lady Bunny|The Lady Bunny]] 
* [[Charles Busch]]
* [[The Lady Chablis]]
* [[Vaginal Davis]]
* [[Dame Edna]]
* [[Dreuxilla Divine]]
* [[Divine (Glen Milstead)|Divine]]
* [[Ethyl Eichelberger]]
* [[Julian Eltinge]]
* [[Harvey Fierstein]]
* [[Chyna Girl]]
* [[Power Infiniti]]
* [[Danny La Rue]]
* [[Mado Lamotte]]
* [[Elaine Lancaster]]
* [[Miss Shangay Lily]]
* [[Shirley Q Liquor]] 
* [[Charles Ludlam]]
* [[Brini Maxwell]]
* [[Kitty Meow]]
* [[Everett Quinton]]
* [[RuPaul]]
* [[José Sarria]]
* [[Steven St. Croix]] (cross-dresser)
* [[Jolene Sugarbaker]] 
* [[Pussy Tourette]]
* [[Pieter Dirk Uys]]
* [[Wanda]]
* [[Wanda Wisdom]]

==External links== 

* [http://www.wandawisdom.com Wanda Wisdom]
* [http://www.rupaul.com RuPaul]
* [http://www.hometown.aol.com/chyna777star Chyna Girl]
* [http://www.81x.com/tvsupermodel80/wanda Wanda]
* [http://www.jolenestrailerpark.com Jolene Sugarbaker]
* [http://www.rosepetalgalore.com Rose Petal]
* [http://www.shirleyqliquor.com Shirley Q Liquor]

''See also:'' [[List of transgender-related topics]]
[[de:Drag Queen]]
[[eo:Regxinjo]]
[[zh-cn:&amp;#25198;&amp;#35013;&amp;#30343;&amp;#21518;]]
[[Category:Transgender people and behavior]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>