<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061109152522|86726167" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="58164" pageid="58164" ns="0" title="Drag queen"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-11-09T21:16:58Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">&lt;!-- Unsourced image removed: [[Image:Rupa3.jpg|thumb|American drag performer [[RuPaul]].]] --&gt;
[[Image:Dragqueens.jpg|thumb|225px|right|Drag queens Luc D'Arcy and Jerry Cyr and friend at [[Montreal]]'s 2003 [[Divers/Cité]] [[pride parade]].]]

'''Drag queens''' are performers&amp;mdash;often, though not exclusively, [[gay]] men or [[transgender]] people—who dress in "[[drag (clothing)|drag]]," clothing associated with the female [[gender role|gender]] (see [[drag king]] for women who perform in males' clothing), often exaggerating certain characteristics for comic, dramatic or satirical effect. The term "drag queen" usually refers to people who dress in drag for the purpose of performing, whether singing or [[Lip sync|lip-sync]]ing, dancing, participating in events such as [[gay pride parade]]s, [[drag pageants]], or at venues such as [[cabaret]]s and [[discotheque]]s. In the [[United Kingdom]], alongside traditional drag work such as shows and performances, many drag queens engage in 'mix-and-mingle' or hosting work at night clubs or at private parties/events.

Drag is a part of Western [[Sexuality and gender identity-based cultures|gay culture]]; drag queens played a predominant role during the [[Stonewall riots]] in [[June 27]] [[1969]] in New York, and drag shows are traditional at pride parades. Prominent drag queens in the gay community of a city often serve as official or unofficial spokespersons, fund-raisers, chroniclers, or community leaders.

[[Image:Mado.jpg|225px|right|thumb|[[Mado Lamotte]] performs at'' Mascara: La nuit des drags ''in Montreal.]]

==Terminology==
&lt;!-- Unsourced image removed: [[Image:cloverhoneyred.JPG|thumb|National Television Personality [[Clover Honey]].]] --&gt;
The term ''drag queen'' originates in [[Polari]], a subset of English slang that was popular in some gay communities in the early part of the [[20th century]].  '''Drag''' meant "clothes", and was also theatre slang for a woman's costume worn by a male actor. '''Queen''' refers to the trait of affected royality found in many drag characters.

Another term for drag queen, ''female impersonator'', is still used—though it is often regarded as inaccurate, as many contemporary drag performers are not attempting to [[Passing (gender)|pass]] as women. ''Female impersonation'', under that name, used to be illegal in many places, which inspired the  drag queen [[José Sarria]] to hand out labels to his friends reading "I am a boy," so they could not be accused of female impersonation. [http://www.glbtq.com/social-sciences/sarria_j.html] American drag queen [[RuPaul]] once said "I do not impersonate females! How many women do you know who wear seven-inch heels, four-foot wigs, and skintight dresses?"  He also said, "I don't dress like a woman; I dress like a drag queen!"

Most drag queens prefer to be referred to as "[[gender-specific pronoun|she]]" while in drag and  desire to stay completely in character. Some performers may be offended if they are referred to as "he" or by their legal name while in character.  Drag performer RuPaul is one of the few exceptions to this rule, as he seems to be completely ambivalent to which pronoun is used to refer to him.  In his words, "You can call me he.  You can call me she.  You can call me Regis and Kathie Lee; I don't care!" {{fact}}

Some biological females perform as drag queens; they are referred to as [[bio queen]]s or faux queens.

==Drag and transvestism==
Most drag queens perform for fulfillment as a [[hobby]], a [[profession]], or an [[art]] form; as a way to be in the spotlight; or as a road to local or wider fame. There are a significant number of [[Heterosexuality|heterosexual]] men, who are generally actors, who perform in drag. There are also transgender or [[Transsexuality|transsexual]] people, as well as straight women, who perform as drag queens.

Drag queens are sometimes called [[transvestism|transvestites]], though that term has generally different connotations than "drag queen". "Drag queen" usually connotes cross-dressing for the purpose of entertainment or performance without necessarily aiming to [[Passing (gender)|pass]] as female and is not usually used to describe those who cross-dress for the fulfillment of [[transvestic fetishism|transvestic fetishes]] alone, or whose [[cross-dressing]] is primarily a part of a private sexual activity or identity.

==Drag shows and venues==
A drag show is an entertainment consisting of a variety of songs, [[monologue]]s or skits featuring either single performers or groups of performers in drag meant to entertain an audience. They range from amateur performances at small bars to elaborately staged theatrical presentations. Many drag shows feature performers singing or [[Lip sync|lip-sync]]ing to songs while performing a pre-planned [[pantomime]], or dancing. The performers often don elaborate costumes and makeup, and sometimes dress to imitate various famous female singers or personalities.

==Genres==
[[Image:Crossdressing at parade.jpg|thumb|215px|[[Camp (style)|Camp]] queen at [[Christopher Street Day]] in [[Berlin]].]] &lt;!-- Can't get this space to stay closed!--&gt;

* High ''[[Camp (style)|camp]]'' drag queens employ a drag aesthetic based on [[clown]]-like values like exaggeration, [[satire]], and [[ribaldry]].  [[Glen Milstead|Divine]], [[Miss Understood]], [[Jolene Sugarbaker]] and [[Rye Seronie]] are examples of camp queens.

* Some drag queens exaggerate in the dimension of elegance and fashion, employing elaborate jewelry and gowns. [[The Lady Chablis]], who can be seen in the movie ''[[Midnight in the Garden of Good and Evil]]'' is an example of this type of performer. Another example is drag pageant title holder [[Christine Mancini]]. Many such drag queens impersonate specific actresses and other pop divas, such as [[Cher]], [[Madonna (entertainer)|Madonna]], [[Celine Dion|Céline Dion]], and others.

* Some drag queens primarily perform in [[pageant]]s, hence the term ''pageant queen''.  Pageant queens gear their act toward winning titles and prizes in various contests and pageantry systems.  Some of these have grand prizes that rival those of pageants such as [[Miss America]].

*Post-modernist drag queens; an example would be The Divine David, who regularly performed in London during the 1990s in clubs such as Duckie, in South London. He used an extreme form of presentation, with make-up that was applied roughly and then smeared across his face. His act was designed to make the audience feel extremely uncomfortable about any preconcieved ideas of acceptable subject matter for a drag queen to tackle. One show included cutting up a pig's head and throwing the pieces into the audience. As such, the act bore close similarities to [[performance art]] of the 1970s.

== Criticism ==
[[Image:Monetdupreetina.jpg|150px|right|thumb|Drag performer [[Monet Dupree]] impersonates [[Tina Turner]].]]

Some members of the lesbian, gay, and bisexual community criticize drag queens and their participation in pride parades and other public events, believing that this projects a limited and harmful image of gay people and impedes a broader social acceptance. Others see this point of view as misplaced misogyny or an intolerance of the diversity and history of the gay community and the role drag queens played in kick starting the gay rights movement in the 1970s. Still others simply regard drag as traditional fun that need not be politically analyzed.

Some [[feminism|feminists]] believe that drag promotes harmful stereotypes of women, though others see drag as a critique or "subversion" of gender roles. Some drag performers may regard their acts as a satire of femininity, or as a form of social criticism. Others may view it as  entertainment, an art form, or simply fun.

Drag queens are sometimes rejected by parts of the transgender community—especially, but not exclusively, by many [[transsexual]] women—because of fears that they may be stereotyped as drag queens. Canadian transgender activist [[Star Maris]] wrote a song entitled "I'm Not A Fucking Drag Queen" which expresses this viewpoint.

&lt;!-- There's already a link in "see also"
==Famous drag queens==
Main article [[List of Drag Queens]]

Some of the more well-known drag performers include:

* [[Enza Anderson|Enza "Supermodel" Anderson]]
* [[Amber Wayves]]
* [[Shirley Temple Bar]]
* [[Panti]]
* [[Fabula DiBeaumarchais]]
* [[Milton Berle]]
* [[Miss Understood]]
* [[Sister Boom-Boom]]
* [[Cookie Buffet]]
* [[The Lady Bunny|Lady Bunny]]
* [[Charles Busch]]
* [[The Lady Chablis]]
* [[The Divine David]]
* [[Vaginal Creme Davis]]
* [[Glen Milstead|Divine]]
* [[Monet Dupree]]
* [[Julian Eltinge]]
* [[Dame Edna Everage]]
* [[Harvey Fierstein]]
* [[Clover Honey]]
* [[House of Diabolique]]
* [[Mado Lamotte]]
* [[Danny La Rue]]
* [[Miss Shangay Lily]]
* [[Charles Ludlam]]
* [[Lypsinka]] (John Epperson)
* [[Christine Mancini]]
* [[Brini Maxwell]]
* [[RuPaul]]
* [[Charles Pierce]]
* [[José Sarria]]
* [[Lily Savage]]
* [[Jolene Sugarbaker]]
* [[Pieter Dirk Uys]]
* [[Flo]] (John Koop)
 --&gt;

==See also==
{{Commons|Drag queen}} 
*[[Crossdressing]] 
*[[List of transgender-related topics]]
*[[List of drag queens]]
*[[Sisters of Perpetual Indulgence]]
*[[Stonewall riots]]
*[[Imperial Court System]]
*[[drag kings]]
*[[drag pageantry]]

==External links==
*[http://www.queermusicheritage.com/drag.html Comprehensive Drag Artist Information and Discography]
*[http://www.alexserpa.com Alex Serpa - Celebrity Female Impersonator]
*[http://one.revver.com/watch/90347/format/flv/affiliate/26948 ] Video from Halloween Street party at West Hollywood 
[[Category:Transgender people and behavior]]
[[Category:Drag queens|*]]

[[de:Drag Queen]]
[[es:Drag queen]]
[[eo:Reĝinjo]]
[[fr:Drag queen]]
[[it:Drag queen]]
[[he:דראג קווין]]
[[ka:დრაგ-ქუინი]]
[[nl:Travestiet]]
[[ja:ドラァグ・クイーン]]
[[pl:Drag queen]]
[[pt:Drag queen]]
[[ru:Драг-квин]]
[[sh:Drag queen]]
[[sv:Drag Queen]]
[[zh:扮装皇后]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>