<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20041108052824|7211229" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="8690" pageid="8690" ns="0" title="Don&#039;t ask, don&#039;t tell"><revisions><rev timestamp="2004-11-08T05:29:22Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Don't ask, don't tell''' is the common term for the current policy toward [[gay]]s in the [[United States armed forces]]. It was introduced in [[1993]] by President [[Bill Clinton]], although crafted by [[Colin Powell]], and has been maintained by Clinton's successor, [[George W. Bush]]. The policy requires that as long as homosexual men and women in the military don't volunteer their [[sexual orientation]], commanders won't try to find them out. The policy is widely seen as a failure and opposed by pro and anti-gay advocates.

*"Sexual orientation will not be a bar to service unless manifested by homosexual conduct. The military will discharge members who engage in homosexual conduct, which is defined as a homosexual act, a statement that the member is homosexual or bisexual, or a marriage or attempted marriage to someone of the same gender."
**quoted in "The Pentagon's New Policy Guidelines on Homosexuals in the Military", ''The New York Times'' (Judly 20, 1993), p.A14.

== History ==
Prejudice against homosexuals in military service is as old as the existence of military institutions themselves.  However, the levels with which this prejudice has been elevated to active attempts to segregate and then remove homosexuals from military service has varied greatly from time to time, especially at the official level.  Informally, homosexuals and suspected homosexuals were often the target of "blanket parties", in which several other service members during the night in the barracks first covered the face of the victim with a blanket so he could not see any of his attackers and then beat him, often quite severely and occasionally even fatally. The frequency of these occurrences is said to be related at least in part to whether a "command climate" indifferent or favorable to the harassment of suspected homosexuals exists. Formal efforts to remove homosexuals have varied in their level of emphasis and tenacity between services, and at one time seemed to be somewhat linked to whether personnel shortages existed, at which point there was sometimes more tolerance (up to a point), and whether there was an abundance of manpower, in which case there was often more pressure to remove all active and even suspected homosexuals.  This cannot be said to be true today, as the discharges of homosexual service members actually seems to be increasing at a time when personnel shortages are severe enough that the active duty tours of many enlisted service members are being involuntarily extended.

Homosexual acts have always technically been illegal in the U.S. military.  "[[Sodomy]]" has been one of the punitive articles (offenses) enumerated under the [[Uniform Code of Military Justice]] since its adoption in [[1951]], and before that was in its predecessor, the [[Articles of War]].  Justification for this has been in part based on the idea that homosexuals posed a security risk.  However, this "risk" has generally been based on the concept that homosexuals could easily be [[blackmail]]ed by an enemy or a potential enemy to perform [[treason]]able acts on the basis of the fear of their sexual orientation being exposed, which the current policy would seemingly heighten rather than lessen.  Another basis for separation of homosexuals from service is that their presence is found to be objectionable by many heterosexual service members.  Homosexual rights advocates respond that this was the basis for [[segregation]] in the services, as many [[Caucasian|white]] service members, especially initially, objected to the presence of [[African American|black]] and other minority members, and that cannot be a legal or moral basis for banning homosexuals from service.  All would admit that sexual harassment of any sort would be incompatible with the "good order and discipline" that military service demands, and homosexual rights activists stress that they are ''not'' advocating the tolerance of homosexual harassment, or any other form of harassment.

== Overview ==

Statistics on the number of persons discharged from the military in the years since the policy was first introduced ([[1993]]) show that more people are discharged now than were before.  Also, more of these people are given honorable discharges than was the case before.

&lt;table border="1" width=50%&gt;
&lt;caption&gt;''From Servicemembers Legal Defense Network - Annual Gay Discharges Under "Don't Ask, Don't Tell, Don't Pursue, Don't Harass"''&lt;/caption&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Year&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;[[United States Coast Guard|Coast Guard]]&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;[[United States Marine Corps|Marines]]&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;[[United States Navy|Navy]]&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;[[United States Army|Army]]&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;[[United States Air Force|Air Force]]&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Total&lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;[[1994]]&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;36&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;258&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;136&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;187&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;617&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;[[1995]]&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;15&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;69&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;269&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;184&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;235&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;772&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;[[1996]]&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;12&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;60&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;315&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;199&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;284&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;870&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;[[1997]]&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;78&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;413&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;197&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;309&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;1007&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;[[1998]]&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;14&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;77&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;345&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;312&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;415&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;1163&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;[[1999]]&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;12&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;97&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;314&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;271&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;352&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;1046&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;[[2000]]&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;19&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;104&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;358&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;573&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;177&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;1241&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;[[2001]]&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;?&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;?&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;?&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;?&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;?&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;1273&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;[[2002]]&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;?&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;?&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;?&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;?&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;?&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;906&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;[[2003]]&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;?&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;?&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;?&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;?&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;?&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;787&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

[[Judith Butler]] (1997) points out paranoid nature of the ban which conflates [[speech act|speech]] and conduct: "the statement, then, 'I am a homosexual,' is fabulously misconstrued...A claim that is, in the first instance, reflexive, that attributes a status to only oneself, is taken to be solicitous...to hear the utterance is to 'contract' the sexuality to which it refers...This is a statement construed as a solicitation; a constative taken as an interrogative; a self-ascription taken as an address." (p.113)

== Situation in Other Countries ==

Most other Western military forces have now removed bans on homosexuals (with
strict policies on [[sexual harassment]]). The U.K. armed forces lifted its ban on gay people in [[2000]].

==General==

More generally, '''"Don't ask, don't tell"''' is used to describe any instance where one person has a [[secret]], and another person would be uncomfortable knowing it, while also lying is undesirable. Applicable statements would be "I do not want to know", or after being told "I would rather not have known it". This is part of a more general tendency towards taking sexual identity ''as'' identity.

One general example of Don't Ask, Don't Tell is when a person purchases [[zig zag]] rolling papers for rolling plant material and smoking.  It is well known that a majority of zig zag users are [[marijuana]] smokers.  However, when one purchases them at any [[business]], they are not asked what they will be used for.  Similary, the purchaser will be sold the product without question, provided they do not confess to using the product as a means of breaking the law.  This may not be the best example, however, because it is known that the person purchasing the rolling papers will most likely be smoking marijuana.  If the marijuana-smoking purchaser were questioned, he/she would most likely lie and say it is for [[tobacco]] use.  Retailers who sell rolling papers avoid [[confrontation]], since it increases business and revenue.  Nonetheless, rolling paper sales are a general example of Don't Ask, Don't Tell.

==Source==
*Butler, Judith (1997). ''Excitable Speech: A Politics of the Performative''. New York: Routledge. ISBN 0415915880.

==External links==

* [http://www.california.com/~rathbone/links003.htm Chronology of Don't Ask, Don't Tell]
* [http://www.sldn.org Servicemembers Legal Defense Network]
* [http://www.gaymilitary.ucsb.edu/ Center for the Study of Sexual Minorities in the Military]

[[zh:%E4%B8%8D%E9%97%AE%EF%BC%8C%E4%B8%8D%E8%AF%B4]]

[[Category:United States military policies]][[Category:LGBT civil rights]]
[[Category:U.S. history of LGBT rights]]
[[Category:Political slogans]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>