<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20091109093314|324812726" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="8690" pageid="8690" ns="0" title="Don&#039;t ask, don&#039;t tell"><revisions><rev timestamp="2009-11-14T16:40:47Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Redirect|DADT|the television syndication company|Disney-ABC Domestic Television}}
{{Otheruses}}

{{LGBT rights}}
'''''Don't ask, don't tell''''' (DADT) is the common term for the policy regarding gays and lesbians serving [[closeted|openly]] in the U.S. military mandated by federal law {{USPL|103|160}} ({{usc|10|654}}). Unless one of the exceptions from {{uscsub|10|654|b}} applies, the policy prohibits anyone who "demonstrate(s) a propensity or intent to engage in homosexual acts" from serving in the [[Military of the United States|armed forces of the United States]], because "it would create an unacceptable risk to the high standards of morale, good order and discipline, and unit cohesion that are the essence of military capability." The act prohibits any [[homosexuality|homosexual]] or [[bisexuality|bisexual]] person from disclosing his or her [[sexual orientation]] or from speaking about any homosexual relationships, including marriages or other familial attributes, while serving in the [[United States armed forces]]. The "don't ask" part of the policy indicates that superiors should not initiate investigation of a service member's orientation in the absence of disallowed behaviors, though mere suspicion of homosexual behavior can cause an investigation. This policy has made the United States the only Western, rich, and industrialized nation that forbids gays from serving openly in the military.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.thefreelibrary.com/Why+It%27s+Good+that+the+USA+Is+Different-a01612027562&lt;/ref&gt; 

==Beginning of the policy==
The policy was introduced as a compromise measure in 1993 and approved by then President [[Bill Clinton]] who, while campaigning for the Presidency, had promised to allow all citizens regardless of sexual orientation to serve openly in the military, a departure from the then complete ban on those who are not [[heterosexual]].

{{quotation|Sexual orientation will not be a bar to service unless manifested by homosexual conduct. The military will discharge members who engage in homosexual conduct, which is defined as a homosexual act, a statement that the member is homosexual or bisexual, or a marriage or attempted marriage to someone of the same gender.|quoted in "The Pentagon's New Policy Guidelines on Homosexuals in the Military", ''[[The New York Times]]'' (July 20, 1993), p.A14.}}

==History==
During the [[American Revolutionary War]], the armed forces treated [[sodomy]] (then broadly defined as oral or anal sexual conduct){{Citation needed|date=May 2009}} as grounds for being dishonorably discharged. The first such recorded discharge was in 1778, when Lieutenant [[Frederick Gotthold Enslin]] was (with the approval of General [[George Washington]]&lt;ref&gt;Shilts, p. 11&lt;/ref&gt;) dishonorably discharged following a conviction of homosexual sodomy and [[perjury]]. The [[Articles of War]] maintained the crime of sodomy, but it was not until 1942 that the armed forces considered homosexual status (as assessed by the military through a process of recruitment screening or internal investigations) as grounds for nonselection or separation from the military. Thus, anyone in the armed forces labeled as gay or bisexual were subject to criminal sanctions under the sodomy prohibition, or could be given a [[blue discharge]] and returned to civilian life, where they were denied [[G.I. Bill]] benefits by the [[United States Department of Veterans Affairs|Veterans Administration]].&lt;ref name = berube230&gt;Bérubé, p. 230&lt;/ref&gt;

Blue discharges were discontinued in May 1947, with discharges that would formerly have been blue now falling under one of two new headings, "general" and "undesirable".&lt;ref&gt;Bérubé, p. 242&lt;/ref&gt; A general discharge was considered to be under honorable conditions – which is distinct from an "honorable discharge" – and an undesirable discharge was under conditions other than honorable – which, again, is distinct from a "dishonorable discharge".&lt;ref&gt;Jones, p. 2&lt;/ref&gt; At the same time, however, the Army changed its regulations to ensure that homosexuals would not qualify for general discharges.&lt;ref&gt;Bérubé, p. 243&lt;/ref&gt; Under this system, a servicemember found to be homosexual but who has not committed any homosexual acts while in service would receive an undesirable discharge. Those who were found guilty of engaging in homosexual conduct were dishonorably discharged.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news 
  | title = Homosexuals in Uniform
  | work = Newsweek
  | date = 1947-06-09
  | url = http://books.google.com/books?id=bjeJCGF5OiUC&amp;pg=PA164&amp;lpg=PA164&amp;dq=%22blue+discharge%22+%22military%22&amp;source=web&amp;ots=flRLjohGW_&amp;sig=8j6A9zHV_NTxfNShD6TldpusISM&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;resnum=20&amp;ct=result#PPA163,M1
  | accessdate = 2009-01- 04}}&lt;/ref&gt; By the 1970s, a gay servicemember who had not committed any homosexual acts while in service would tend to receive a general discharge, while those found to have engaged in homosexual conduct would tend to receive undesirable discharges.&lt;ref&gt;Jones, p. 3&lt;/ref&gt; However, the reality remained that gay servicemembers received a disproportionate percentage of undesirable discharges issued.&lt;ref&gt;Shilts, p. 163&lt;/ref&gt;

The success of the armed forces in pre-screening self-identified gay and bisexual people from the 1940s through 1981 remains in dispute; during the [[Vietnam War]], some men pretended to be gay in order to avoid the draft. However, a significant number of gay and bisexual men and women did manage to avoid the pre-screening process and serve in the military, some with special distinction. For example, in the 1950s and 1960s, the Navy medical doctor [[Thomas Anthony Dooley III|Tom Dooley]] received national fame for his anti-Communist and humanitarian efforts in Vietnam. His homosexuality was something of an open secret in the Navy, but eventually he was forced to resign; the Navy subsequently conducted the first official study on sexual orientation and the Navy regulations and rules. The 1957 report, titled ''Report of the Board Appointed to Prepare and Submit Recommendations to the Secretary of the Navy for the Revision of Policies, Procedures and Directives Dealing With Homosexuals'' (better known as the [[Crittenden Report]]) found that gay-identified people were no more likely to be a security risk than heterosexual-identified people, and found there was no rational basis for excluding gay people from the Navy, although it stopped short of recommending a change in the regulations because of social [[mores]].

Beyond the official regulations, gay people were often the target of various types of [[harassment]] by their fellow servicemen, designed to persuade them to resign from the military or turn themselves in to investigators. The most infamous type of such harassment was called a [[blanket party]]; during the night in the barracks, several service members first covered the face of the victim with a blanket and then committed assault, often quite severely and sometimes even fatally, as in the case of [[Allen R. Schindler, Jr.]]. When passing the DADT bill, President Clinton cited [[United States Navy|U.S. Navy]] [[Radioman]] [[Petty Officer Third Class|Third Class]] Schindler, who was brutally murdered by shipmate Terry M. Helvey (with the aid of an accomplice), leaving a "nearly-unrecognizable corpse".&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.palmcenter.org/press/dadt/in_print/abandoning_dont_ask_dont_tell_will_decrease_anti_gay_violence Belkin, Dr. Aaron. "Abandoning 'Don't Ask, Don't Tell' Will Decrease Anti-Gay Violence" Naval Institute: Proceedings Monthly. 1 May, 2005]&lt;/ref&gt;
The introduction of "Don't ask, don't tell" with the later amendment of "don't pursue, don't harass" has officially prohibited such behavior, but reports suggest that such harassment continues.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.palmcenter.org/publications/dadt/perceived_sexual_orientation_based_harrassment_in_military_and_civilian_contexts Moradi, Dr. Bonnie "Perceived Sexual-Orientation-Based Harassment in Military and Civilian Contexts" Military Psychology 2006, 18(1), 39-60]&lt;/ref&gt;

During the 1970s, several high-profile court challenges to the military's regulations on homosexuality occurred, with little success, and when such successes did occur it was when the plaintiff had been open about his homosexuality from the beginning or due to the existence of the "queen for a day" rule. In 1981, the [[United States Department of Defense|Department of Defense]] issued a new regulation on homosexuality that was designed to ensure withstanding a court challenge by developing uniform and clearly defined regulations and justifications that made homosexual status, whether self-applied or by the military, and conduct grounds for discharge (DOD Directive 1332.14 (Enlisted Administrative Separations), January, 1981):

{{quotation|Homosexuality is incompatible with military service. The presence in the military environment of persons who engage in homosexual conduct or who, by their statements, demonstrate a propensity to engage in homosexual conduct, seriously impairs the accomplishment of the military mission. The presence of such members adversely affects the ability of the armed forces to maintain discipline, good order, and morale; to foster mutual trust and confidence among service members; to ensure the integrity of the system of rank and command; to facilitate assignment and worldwide deployment of service members who frequently must live and work in close conditions affording minimal privacy; to recruit and retain members of the armed forces; to maintain the public acceptability of military service; and to prevent breaches of security.}}

The directive justified the policy and removed the "queen for a day" rule that had prompted some courts to rule against the armed forces. However, the intent of the policy had also been to treat homosexuality as being akin to a disability discharge and thus ensure that anyone found engaging in homosexual activity and/or identifying as gay, would be separated with an honorable discharge. The DOD policy has since withstood most court challenges, although the [[Supreme Court of the United States|United States Supreme Court]] has refused to weigh in on the constitutionality of the policy, preferring to allow lower courts and the [[United States Congress]] to settle the matter.

In the 1980s, many of the [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democratic Party]] presidential candidates expressed an interest in changing the regulations concerning homosexuality in the armed forces, and, as American social mores changed, public opinion began to express more sympathy with gay people in armed forces, at least to the extent that investigations into a serviceman or -woman's sexual behaviour and/or orientation were seen as a witch-hunt. "Gays in the military" became a political issue during the [[United States presidential election, 1992|1992 Presidential campaign]], when Clinton, the Democratic candidate, promised to lift the military's ban on homosexual and bisexual people.

In 1992, the United States General Accounting Office published a report entitled ''Defense Force Management: DOD's Policy on Homosexuality'', that outlined the DOD policy on homosexuality and the reasons for it. The report also included excerpts from a previously unpublished 1988 Defense Personnel Security Research and Education Center study on homosexuality that made similar conclusions as the 1957 Crittenden Report.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Defense Force Management: DOD's Policy on Homosexuality |author=United States General Accounting Office |year=1992|month=June|id=GAO/NSIAD-92-98 |url=http://archive.gao.gov/d33t10/146980.pdf|accessdate=2009-10-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Congressional opposition to lifting the ban on gay and bisexual people in the armed forces was led by [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democratic]] Senator [[Sam Nunn]] of [[Georgia (U.S. state)|Georgia]] who organized Congressional hearings that largely buffed the armed forces position that has remained unchanged since the 1981 directive. While Congressional support for reform was led by Democratic Congressman [[Barney Frank]] of [[Massachusetts]], who fought for a compromise, and retired [[Republican Party (US)|Republican]] Senator [[Barry Goldwater]], who argued for a complete repeal of the ban. After a large number of people flooded the Congressional phone lines with oppositions to lifting the ban, President Clinton soon backed off on his campaign promise to lift the ban on homosexual and bisexual people in the armed forces. Subsequently, Congress compromised, amending "Don't ask, don't tell" with "don't harass". Officially, the compromise dictates that the armed forces will no longer ask recruits about their sexual activity and/or orientation, will not investigate any serviceman or servicewoman's sexual activity and/or orientation without solid evidence (thus preventing witch-hunts), and self-identified homosexual servicemen and women agree that they will not engage in homosexual sex acts, or otherwise announce their homosexuality through public statements or open participation in a same-sex marriage.

[[Image:Congressman Marty Meehan joined by retired flag officers interested in repealling DADT.jpg|right|thumb|400px|In 2005, member of Congress [[Marty Meehan]] (third from left) unsuccessfully attempted to repeal the policy]]

In September 2005, the Center for the Study of Sexual Minorities in the Military – a [[think tank]] affiliated with the [[University of California, Santa Barbara]], and renamed the Michael D. Palm Center in October 2006 – issued a news release revealing the existence of a 1999 [[FORSCOM]] regulation (Regulation 500-3-3) that allowed the active duty deployment of Army Reservists and National Guard troops who say that they are gay or who are accused of being gay. U.S. Army Forces Command spokesperson Kim Waldron later confirmed the regulation and indicated that it was intended to prevent Reservists and National Guard members from pretending to be gay to escape combat.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=Chibbaro, Lou|year=2005|title=Out gay soldiers sent to Iraq - Regulation keeps straights from 'playing gay' to avoid war|work=Washington Blade |url=http://washblade.com/2005/9-23/news/national/outiraq.cfm |accessdate=2006-03-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

DADT has been upheld five times in federal court, and in a [[Supreme Court of the United States|Supreme Court]] case, ''Rumsfeld v. Forum for Academic and Institutional Rights, Inc.'' (2006), the Supreme Court unanimously held that the federal government could withhold funding in order to force universities to accept military recruiters in spite of their nondiscrimination policies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=Mears, Bill|year=2006|title=Justices uphold military recruiting on campuses|work=CNN Law Center |url=http://www.cnn.com/2006/LAW/03/06/scotus.recruiting/index.html |accessdate=2006-03-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1993, the National Defense Research Institute prepared a study for the Office of the Secretary of Defense published as ''Sexual Orientation and U.S. Military Personnel Policy: Options and Assessment''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rand.org/pubs/monograph_reports/MR323/ Rand Corporation, Santa Monica, CA, 1993. ISBN 0-8330-1441-2]&lt;/ref&gt; It concluded, in measured language, that "circumstances could exist under which the ban on homosexuals could be lifted with little or no adverse consequences for recruitment and retention"&lt;ref&gt;Ibid., 406.&lt;/ref&gt; if the policy were implemented with care, principally because many factors contribute to individual enlistment and re-enlistment decisions.

==Public opinion==
Polls have shown that a large majority of the American public favors allowing gay and lesbian people to serve openly in the U.S. military. A national poll conducted in May 2005 by the [[Boston Globe]] showed 79% of participants having nothing against openly gay people from serving in the military. In a 2008 ''[[Washington Post]]''–[[ABC News]] poll, 75% of Americans – including 80% of Democrats, 75% of independents, and 66% of conservatives – said that openly gay people should be allowed to serve in the military.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2008/07/18/AR2008071802561.html Acceptance of Gay People in Military Grows Dramatically - washingtonpost.com]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Military personnel opinion==
A 2006 [[Zogby International]] poll of military members found that 26% were in favor of gays and lesbians serving in the military, 37% opposed gays and lesbians serving, and 37% expressed no preference or were unsure.  72% of respondents who had experience with gays or lesbians in their unit said that the presence of gay or lesbian unit members had either no impact or a positive impact on their personal morale, while 67% said as much for overall unit morale.  Of those respondents uncertain whether they had served with gay or lesbian personnel, 51% thought that such unit members would have a neutral or positive effect on personal morale, while 48% thought that they would have a negative effect on unit morale. 73% of respondents said that they felt comfortable in the presence of gay and lesbian personnel.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.palmcenter.org/files/active/0/ZogbyReport.pdf Opinions of Military Personnel on Sexual Minorities in the Military]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Criticism from military personnel==
Former [[Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff]] Gen. [[John Shalikashvili]] (Ret.)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|first=Gordon|last=Lubold|title=Former JCS chairman: It's time to give 'don't ask, don't tell' policy another look|url=http://www.airforcetimes.com/issues/stories/0-AIRPAPER-2461638.php|publisher=Air Force Times|date=2007-01-15|accessdate=2007-01-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; and former [[United States Senate|Senator]] and [[Secretary of Defense]] [[William Cohen]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sldn.org/news/archives/former-defense-secretary-william-cohen-says-congress-should-re-visit-dont-a/|title=Former Defense Secretary William Cohen Says Congress Should Re-Visit “Don’t Ask, Don’t Tell”}}&lt;/ref&gt; spoke against the policy publicly in January 2007: "I now believe that if gay men and lesbians served openly in the United States military, they would not undermine the efficacy of the armed forces," General Shalikashvili wrote.  "Our military has been stretched thin by our deployments in the Middle East, and we must welcome the service of any American who is willing and able to do the job."&lt;ref name="newletter" /&gt;

In December 2007, 28 retired generals and admirals urged Congress to repeal the policy, citing evidence that 65,000 gay men and women are currently serving in the armed forces and that there are over 1,000,000 gay veterans.&lt;ref name="newletter"&gt;{{cite news |first=Tom|last=Shanker|coauthors=Healy, Patrick|title=A New Push to Roll Back 'Don't Ask, Don't Tell'|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2007/11/30/us/30military.html?_r=2&amp;oref=slogin&amp;oref=slogin|publisher=[[New York Times]]|date=2007-11-30|accessdate=2007-12-03 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="MSN-MilitaryView"&gt;{{cite news|author=Associated Press|title=Admirals, generals: Let gays serve openly|publisher=MSNBC|date=18 November 2008|url=http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/27774058/page/2/|accessdate=13 October 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; On November 17, 2008, 104 retired generals and admirals signed a similar statement.&lt;ref name="MSN-MilitaryView"/&gt;

On May 4, 2008, current Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, Adm. [[Mike Mullen]], when speaking to graduating cadets at [[United States Military Academy|West Point]], expressed the view "that Congress, and not the military, is responsible for [DADT]". Mullen's answer came in response to a cadet's question asking what would happen if the next administration were supportive of legislation allowing gays to serve openly. During his Senate confirmation hearing in 2007, Mullen told lawmakers, "I really think it is for the American people to come forward, really through this body, to both debate that policy and make changes, if that's appropriate." He went on to say, "I'd love to have Congress make its own decisions" with respect to considering repeal.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sldn.org/templates/press/record.html?section=2&amp;record=4798 SLDN Press Release - Admiral Mullen speaks at West Point]&lt;/ref&gt;

In an interview on CNN's ''State of the Union'' broadcast on July 5, 2009, Colin Powell said he thought that the policy was "correct for the time" but that "sixteen years have now gone by, and I think a lot has changed with respect to attitudes within our country, and therefore I think this is a policy and a law that should be reviewed." In the same program, Mike Mullen said the policy would continue to be implemented until the law was repealed, and that his advice was to "move in a measured way... At a time when we're fighting two conflicts there is a great deal of pressure on our forces and their families."&lt;ref name="July5_Powell_Mullen"&gt;[http://www.reuters.com/article/topNews/idUSTRE5641A920090705 Time to review policy on gays in U.S. military: Powell], July 5, [[Reuters]]&lt;/ref&gt;

Several gay service members have written novels and nonfiction works about life in the military under DADT. In 2005, [[Rich Merritt]] released his memoir ''Secrets of a Gay Marine Porn Star'',&lt;ref name="SAGPS"&gt;{{cite book|last1=Merritt|first1=Rich|title=[[Secrets Of A Gay Marine Porn Star]]|location=|publisher=[[Kensington Books|Kensington]]|date=7 June 2005|pages=480|isbn=0758209681}}&lt;/ref&gt; and in 2008 [[Brett Edward Stout]] released his first novel, ''Sugar-Baby Bridge''.&lt;ref name="SBB"&gt;{{cite book|last1=Stout|first1=Brett Edward|title=[[Sugar-Baby Bridge]]|location=|publisher=[[CreateSpace]]|date=6 October 2008|pages=360|isbn=1440433461}}&lt;/ref&gt; Openly gay service member [[Dan Choi]], who helped found [[West Point]]'s LBGT group [[Knight's Out]], made an appearance on the web-based [[documentary]] series ''[[In Their Boots]]'', criticizing the U.S. military's neglect of the partners of service members.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title='Silent partner' examines what happens when people 'don't tell' | url=http://www.latimes.com/news/local/la-me-gay-military18-2009jul18,0,848628.story | publisher=[[Los Angeles Times]] | date= 18 July 2009 | first=Alexandra | last=Zavis}}&lt;/ref&gt; As a linguist, Choi was among 59 gay Arabic speakers discharged by the military, along with 9 gay Farsi speakers discharged by the military up to June 2009,&lt;ref name="Guardian"&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2009/jun/29/gay-veteran-us-army-choi | title=Don't ask, don't tell: gay veteran of Iraq takes on US army | last=Nasaw | first=Daniel | newspaper=[[The Guardian]] | location = London | accessdate=6 November 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; despite a shortage of translators for these languages.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/08/opinion/08benjamin.html Don't Ask, Don't Translate] - New York Times opinion column&lt;/ref&gt;

In September 2009, Air Force Colonel Om Prakash sharply criticized the policy in an article published in ''[[Joint Force Quarterly]]''. He argued that it is unsound for numerous reasons, including the complete lack of any scientific basis for the proposition that unit cohesion is compromised by open homosexuals serving in the military.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Time to End 'Don’t Ask, Don’t Tell,' Official Writes|first=Elisabeth|last=Bumiller|authorlink=Elisabeth Bumiller|date=September 30, 2009|accessdate=October 1, 2009|newspaper=[[The New York Times]]|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2009/10/01/us/01pentagon.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Prakash |first=Om|year=2009|title=The Efficacy of "Don’t Ask, Don’t Tell"|journal=Joint Force Quarterly |volume=2009|issue=55|pages=88-94|url=http://www.ndu.edu/inss/Press/jfq_pages/editions/i55/14.pdf|doi= }}&lt;/ref&gt; The article won the Secretary of Defense National Security Essay competition for 2009.

==President Barack Obama's position==
During his presidential campaign, then-Senator [[Barack Obama]] advocated repeal of the policy to allow gay and lesbian people to serve openly in the armed forces, agreeing with General Shalikashvili and stating that the U.S. government has spent millions of dollars replacing troops expelled from the military, including language experts fluent in [[Arabic]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Barack Obama]] [http://www.barackobama.com/pdf/lgbt.pdf Barack Obama on LGBT RIGHTS: Barack Obama supports the LGBT community.] Retrieved from http://www.barackobama.com May 30, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.change.gov/agenda/civil_rights_agenda/&lt;/ref&gt; 

19 days after his election, Obama's advisers announced that plans to repeal the policy may be delayed until as late as 2010, because Obama "first wants to confer with the Joint Chiefs of Staff and his new political appointees at the Pentagon to reach a consensus, and then present legislation to Congress."&lt;ref name="scarborough"&gt;Rowan Scarborough.[http://www.washingtontimes.com/news/2008/nov/21/obama-to-delay-repeal-of-dont-ask-dont-tell/ "Obama to delay repeal of 'don't ask, don't tell': advisers see consensus building before lifting ban on gays] ''Washington Times'', November 21, 2008. Retrieved 2008-11-22.&lt;/ref&gt;

Obama's current position is that Congress has exclusive authority to lift the ban.{{Citation needed|date=September 2009}}  However, in May 2009, a committee of military law experts at the [[University of California at Santa Barbara]]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.palmcenter.org/files/active/0/Executive%20Order%20on%20Gay%20Troops%20-%20final.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; concluded that it is within the authority of the executive branch to discontinue the policy.&lt;ref&gt;“How to End Don’t Ask, Don’t Tell: A Roadmap of Political, Legal, Regulatory, and Organizational Steps to Equal Treatment,” was sponsored by the Palm Center at the University of California, Santa Barbara&lt;/ref&gt;

In July 2009, the White House and other Democrats allegedly pressured Florida Rep. [[Alcee Hastings]] to withdraw an amendment to the [[National Defense Authorization Act]] ({{USBill|111|H.R.|2647}}) that would have prevented the military from using money to carry out the provisions of DADT.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.miamiherald.com/news/politics/AP/story/1161451.html|title=Lawmaker backs off effort to fight Don't Ask, Don't Tell|last=Clark|first=Lesley|date=2009-07-28|publisher=Miami Herald|accessdate=2009-07-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In a major departure from his campaign promises, Obama's administration is defending the policy in court.&lt;ref&gt;[http://tpmdc.talkingpointsmemo.com/2009/05/obama-administration-punts-on-dont-ask-dont-tell.php Obama Administration Punts On Don't Ask, Don't Tell] talkingpointsmemo.com Brian Beutler - May 19, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/31168203/ Court rejects challenge to 'don't ask, don't tell'] Associated Press wire on msnbc.msn.com - June 8, 2009&lt;/ref&gt; Regarding the first reference, the government had argued before the Federal Appeals Court in San Francisco that the policy should have a blanket application, therefore negating a requirement for an expulsion review based on merit.  Obama administration lawyers let pass the May 3, 2009 deadline to appeal, and the case reverted to the district court.&lt;ref&gt;http://cqresearcherblog.blogspot.com/2009/09/gays-in-military.html CQ Researcher Blog&lt;/ref&gt;  In court documents, government lawyers agreed with the ruling of the Federal Appeals Court in Boston that DADT is "rationally related to the government's legitimate interest in military discipline and cohesion." An appeal of this case, ''Pietrangelo v. Gates 08-824'', was subsequently rejected by the U.S. Supreme Court.&lt;ref name="Guardian"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/feedarticle/8548225|title=Court rejects challenge to 'don't ask, don't tell'|last=Jakes|first=Lara|date=2009-06-08|publisher=Guardian|accessdate=2009-10-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="MSN"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/31168203|title=Court rejects challenge to 'don't ask, don't tell'|date=2009-06-08|publisher=MSN|accessdate=2009-10-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On the eve of the [[National Equality March]] in Washington, D.C., October 10, 2009, Barack Obama stated in a speech before the [[Human Rights Campaign]] that he will end the policy, but offered no timetable.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://abcnews.go.com/Politics/wireStory?id=8801328|title=Gays Question Obama 'Don't Ask, Don't Tell' Pledge|last=Simmons|first=Christine|date=2009-10-11|publisher=Associated Press|accessdate=2009-10-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.politico.com/news/stories/1009/28156.html|title=President Obama offers little new in speech to gay rights activists at HRC dinner|last=Gerstein|first=Josh|date=2009-10-10|publisher=Politico|accessdate=2009-10-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Statistics==
In the fiscal years since the policy was first introduced in 1993, the military has discharged over 13,000 troops from the military under DADT.&lt;ref name="MSN-MilitaryView"/&gt;&lt;ref name="ObamaEnd"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.stripes.com/article.asp?section=104&amp;article=60043|title=Stars and Stripes: Obama Wants to End “Don’t Ask, Don’t Tell” |last=Shane|first=Leo|date=January 16, 2009|work=[[Stars and Stripes (newspaper)|Stars and Stripes]]|publisher=[[U.S. Department of Defense]]|accessdate=2009-01-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.boston.com/news/nation/washington/articles/2009/05/20/continued_discharges_anger_dont_ask_dont_tell_critics/ Continued discharges anger 'don't ask, don't tell' critics: Gay-rights groups urge reversal now] Bryan Bender, Boston Globe; May 20, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; The number of discharges per year under DADT dropped sharply after the [[September 11 attacks]] and has remained relatively low since. Discharges exceed 600 each year. Statistics on the number of persons discharged per year:

{| class="wikitable sortable"
! Year
! [[United States Coast Guard|Coast Guard]]
! [[United States Marine Corps|Marines]]
! [[United States Navy|Navy]]
! [[United States Army|Army]]
! [[United States Air Force|Air Force]]
! Total
|-
| 1994  ||  0 ||  36 || 258 || 136 || 187 ||  617
|-
| 1995  || 15 ||  69 || 269 || 184 || 235 ||  772
|-
| 1996  || 12 ||  60 || 315 || 199 || 284 ||  870
|-
| 1997  || 10 ||  78 || 413 || 197 || 309 || 1,007
|-
| 1998  || 14 ||  77 || 345 || 312 || 415 || 1,163
|-
| 1999  || 12 ||  97 || 314 || 271 || 352 || 1,046
|-
| 2000  || 19 || 104 || 358 || 573 || 177 || 1,241
|-
| 2001* ||  — ||   — ||   — ||   — ||   — || 1,273
|-
| 2002* ||  — ||   — ||   — ||   — ||   — ||  906
|-
| 2003* ||  — ||   — ||   — ||   — ||   — ||  787
|-
| 2004  || 15 || 59  || 177 || 325 || 92  ||  668
|-
| 2005  || 16 || 75  || 177 || 386 || 88  ||  742
|-
| 2006* ||  — ||   — ||   — ||   — ||   — ||  623
|-
| 2007* ||  — ||   — ||   — ||   — ||   — ||  627
|-
| 2008* ||  — ||   — ||   — ||   — ||   — ||  619
|-
| '''Total''' || 113 || 655 || 2,626 || 2,583 || 2,139 || 12,961
|}
&lt;nowiki&gt;*&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;small&gt;Breakdown of discharges by service branch not available
*1994–2003, 2006, 2007 from [[Servicemembers Legal Defense Network]] - Annual Gay Discharges Under "Don't Ask, Don't Tell, Don't Pursue, Don't Harass"
*2004–2005 from [http://www.365gay.com/Newscon06/05/052406Military.htm 365Gay.com - Military Discharging Two Soldiers Per Day For Being Gay Despite War Group Says]
*2008 from [http://www.boston.com/news/nation/washington/articles/2009/05/20/continued_discharges_anger_dont_ask_dont_tell_critics/ Continued discharges anger 'don't ask, don't tell' critics] The Boston Globe,  Bryan Bender - May 20, 2009 
*Not accurate numbers of discharges under DADT due to some soldiers not disclosing their discharge. These statistics are only from those who came forward to the [[Servicemembers Legal Defense Network]].&lt;/small&gt;

==Financial impact of policy==
In February 2005, the [[Government Accountability Office]] released estimates on the cost of the policy. Cautioning that the amount may be too low, the GAO reported $95.4 million in recruiting costs and $95.1 million for training replacements for the 9,488 troops discharged from 1994 through 2003.&lt;ref name = "qkuldr"&gt;{{cite web |year=2006|title=Report: 'Don't Ask, Don't Tell' costs $363M|work=USA Today, Washington/Politics |url=http://www.usatoday.com/news/washington/2006-02-14-dont-ask-report_x.htm |accessdate=2007-05-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In February 2006, a [[University of California]] [[Blue Ribbon Commission]] including [[Lawrence Korb]], a former assistant defense secretary during the [[Ronald Reagan|Reagan]] administration, former [[Defense Secretary]] [[William Perry]], a member of the [[Bill Clinton|Clinton]] administration, and professors from the United States [[Military Academy]] at [[West Point]] concluded that figure should be closer to $363 million, including $14.3 million for "separation travel" once a service member is discharged, $17.8 million for training officers, $252.4 million for training enlistees and $79.3 million in recruiting costs.&lt;ref name = "qkuldr"/&gt; The commission report stated that the GAO didn't take into account the value the military lost from the departures.

==Military Readiness Enhancement Act==
{{Main|Military Readiness Enhancement Act}}
The Military Readiness Enhancement Act is a [[Bill (proposed law)|bill]] introduced to the [[United States House of Representatives|U.S. House of Representatives]] with the stated purpose "to amend [[Title 10 of the United States Code|title 10, United States Code]], to enhance the readiness of the [[United States armed forces|Armed Forces]] by replacing the current policy concerning [[homosexuality]] in the Armed Forces, referred to as 'Don't ask, don't tell,' with a policy of nondiscrimination on the basis of sexual orientation."

==Situation outside the United States==
{{Main|Sexual orientation and military service}}
Most Western military forces have now removed policies excluding individuals of sexual orientations other than heterosexual (with strict policies on [[sexual harassment]]). Of the 26 countries that participate militarily in [[NATO]], more than 22 permit gay people to serve; of the permanent members of the [[United Nations Security Council]], two (Britain, France) permit gay people to serve openly, and three (United States, Russia, China) do not. Besides [[Greece]], which bans homosexuals from serving, all other members of [[EU]] permit gay people to serve openly.  The Greek discrimination policy has become the object of criticism by the European Union, as EU law prohibits discrimination on the basis of sexual orientation.&lt;ref name="queer.de"&gt;[http://www.queer.de/detail.php?article_id=10083 Queer:Argentinien und die Philippinen beenden Homo-Verbot im Militär (german)]&lt;/ref&gt; In 2009, [[Argentina]], [[Uruguay]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|date=2009-05-18|accessdate=2009-10-10|publisher=[[Pink News]]|url=http://www.pinknews.co.uk/news/articles/2005-12486.html|title=Uruguay lifts military gay ban}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Philippines]] allowed gay men to serve openly in the military.&lt;ref name="queer.de"/&gt; [[Israel Defense Forces]] policies allow gay men and lesbians to serve openly and without discrimination or harassment due to actual or perceived sexual orientation, including special units.&lt;ref name="NYT"&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/02/opinion/02shalikashvili.html?_r=1 Second Thoughts on Gays in the Military], By JOHN M. SHALIKASHVILI, January 2, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Consul [[David Saranga]] at the Israeli Consulate in [[New York City]], stated, "It's a non-issue. You can be a very good officer, a creative one, a brave one, and be gay at the same time."&lt;ref name="Ynet"&gt;[http://www.ynetnews.com/articles/0,7340,L-3362505,00.html Follow Israel's example on gays in the military, US study says], by Itamar Eichner, February 8, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{portal|LGBT|Portal LGBT.svg}}
* [[Allen Schindler]] – sailor who was murdered by fellow sailors
* [[Barry Winchell]] – American soldier who was killed by other soldiers while serving because he was thought to be a homosexual
* [[Holmes v. California National Guard]]
* [[Margarethe Cammermeyer]] – retired colonel in the [[Washington National Guard]] and a gay rights activist
* [[Right to Serve Campaign]], an organized effort to bring attention to DADT
* [[Sexual orientation and military service]]
* [[Timothy R. McVeigh]] – first person to win a case against DADT

==Notes==
{{Reflist|2}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}
{{Refbegin}}
* Bérubé, Allan (1990). ''Coming Out Under Fire: The History of Gay Men and Women in World War Two''. New York, The Penguin Group.
* Jones, Major Bradley K. (January 1973). "The Gravity of Administrative Discharges: A Legal and Empirical Evaluation" ''[http://www.docstoc.com/docs/856136/The-Military-Law-Review-Vol-59-(Jan-73) The Military Law Review''] '''59''':1–26.
* Shilts, Randy (1993). ''Conduct Unbecoming: Gays &amp; Lesbians in the U.S. Military Vietnam to the Persian Gulf''. New York, St. Martin's Press. ISBN 031209261X
{{Refend}}

==Further reading==
{{Refbegin}}
* Belkin, Aaron (2008). [http://afs.sagepub.com/cgi/content/abstract/34/2/276 "'Don't Ask, Don't Tell': Does the Gay Ban Undermine the Military's Reputation?"] ''Armed Forces &amp; Society'', Jan 2008; vol. 34: pp.&amp;nbsp;276-291
* Bowling, Kirby L., Firestone, Juanita M., and Harris, Richard J. (2005). [http://afs.sagepub.com/cgi/content/abstract/31/3/411 "Analyzing Questions That Cannot Be Asked of Respondents Who Cannot Respond"] ''Armed Forces &amp; Society'', Apr 2005; vol. 31: pp.&amp;nbsp;411-437
* Carter, Chad C. and Kolenc, Antony B. (2005). {{PDFlink|[http://www.law.udayton.edu/lawreview/documents/31-1/Carter.pdf ''"Don't Ask, Don't Tell:" Has the Policy Met Its Goals?'']|157&amp;nbsp;[[Kibibyte|KiB]]&lt;!-- application/pdf, 161018 bytes --&gt;}} University of Dayton Law Review, Fall 2005.
* Donnelly, Elaine (2007).  [http://www.law.duke.edu/journals/cite.php?14+Duke+J.+Gender+L.+&amp;+Pol%2527y+815  "Constructing the Co-Ed Military,"] Duke University Journal of Gender Law and Policy, May 2007.
* Johansson, Warren and William A Percy. (1994). [http://williamapercy.com/pub-Outing.htm ''Outing: Shattering the Conspiracy of Silence.''] Harrington Park Press.
* Levy, Yagil (2007). [http://afs.sagepub.com/cgi/content/abstract/33/2/186 "The Right to Fight: A Conceptual Framework for the Analysis of Recruitment Policy toward Gays and Lesbians"] ''Armed Forces &amp; Society'', Jan 2007; vol. 33: pp.&amp;nbsp;186-202
* Zylbergold,Bonnie (2007). [http://nsrc.sfsu.edu/MagArticle.cfm?Article=751&amp;PageID=0  ''"The Key to Enlightenment: Semper-fi, a documentary about ex-marine Jeff Key, showcased at Frameline31"''], [[American Sexuality Magazine]]
{{Refend}}

==External links==
* [http://www.cmrlink.org Center for Military Readiness]
* {{usc|10|654}}– Policy concerning homosexuality in the armed forces
*[http://digital.library.unt.edu/govdocs/crs/search/?q=gays+and+u.s.+military+policy&amp;t=fulltext&amp;nlow=&amp;nhi=  Congressional Research Service (CRS) Reports regarding Gays and U.S. Military Policy]
* [http://www.hrc.org/legacyofservice  Human Rights Campaign]
* [http://www.sldn.org Servicemembers Legal Defense Network]
* [http://www.california.com/~rathbone/links003.htm Chronology of "Don't ask, don't tell"]
* [http://www.palmcenter.org/ Michael D. Palm Center]
* [http://www.blue-alliance.org/ Blue Alliance - LGBT Alumni of the US Air Force Academy]
* [http://knightsout.org/ Knights Out - LGBT Alumni of the US Military Academy]
* [http://usnaout.org/ USNA Out - LGBT Alumni of the US Naval Academy]
* [http://thomasson.info/index.html Thomasson v. Perry] - The first test of "Don't ask, don't tell" to reach the Supreme Court was turned down without comment and without setting a precedent
* [http://www.citizensforrepeal.com Citizens For Repeal of Don't Ask, Don't Tell] - a website dedicated to sharing stories of soldiers serving under DADT
{{LGBT|rights=yes}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Don't Ask, Don't Tell}}
[[Category:Clinton Administration initiatives]]
[[Category:Discrimination in the United States]]
[[Category:American political slogans]]
[[Category:Clinton administration controversies]]
[[Category:United States federal civil rights legislation]]
[[Category:United States federal defense and national security legislation]]
[[Category:1990s in LGBT history]]
[[Category:Sexual orientation and the United States military]]
[[Category:Homophobia]]
[[Category:LGBT rights in the United States]]

[[de:Don’t ask, don’t tell]]
[[es:No preguntar, no decir]]
[[fr:Don't ask, don't tell]]
[[he:לא נשאל, אל תספר]]
[[no:Don't ask, don't tell]]
[[pl:Don't ask, don't tell]]
[[ru:Не спрашивай, не говори]]
[[sv:Don't ask, don't tell]]
[[zh:不问，不说]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>