<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20101110230644|396025689" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="29555364" pageid="29555364" ns="0" title="Ableism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2010-11-10T23:08:15Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Disability}}
{{Discrimination sidebar}}
:''This article deals primarily with discrimination faced by those with physical disabilities. For details on the types of discrimination faced by those with [[mental illness|emotional issues]] and the like, see [[Mentalism (discrimination)]]. In [[British English]], the phenomenon of "ableism" is more often termed '''disablism'''.''
 
'''Ableism''' or '''disablism''' is a form of [[discrimination]] based on the physical ability, or lack thereof, of an individual's body and/or its functions.

An ''ableist'' or ''disablist'' society is said to be one based on the classic human assumption that [[able-bodied|non-disabled individuals]] are the [[normalization|standard of ‘normal living’]]. Even with the increased participation in many societies of individuals with disabilities, the tendency to view the world in this way has not always changed. Ableism is a [[dispositional belief]] but is gaining wider currency in [[social science]] circles: advocates say ableist tendencies are means by which mainstream society intentionally or unintentionally denigrates, devalues, and oppresses those with disabilities, and privileges those without disabilities.

Advocates of the concept contend that continued ableism/disablism is not just a social-discrimination matter; it physically results in public and private [[architectural]] structures, places, and even services, including education and [[social work]], that are built to serve 'standard', i.e. [[ambulatory]], people. In response, [[political activist]]s advocating inclusive and especially [[universal design]] structures and services — groups quite often themselves composed of disabled people — agitate and protest in a manner similar to [[anti-racist]] and anti-[[sexist]] activist movements.

[[Inclusion (disability rights)|Inclusion]] is ableism's opposite. Instead of tending towards [[accessibility|inaccessibility]], [[solitude|isolation]], [[pity]], [[paternalism]] and factors giving low [[self-esteem]] to people with disabilities, an inclusive society tends toward [[sociability]] and [[interdependency]] between the [[able-bodied]] and the disabled.

The [[United Kingdom]] favours the term ''disablism'' over ''ableism'' out of a perspective driven by the [[social model of disability]] which regards ''disability'' as discrimination experienced by a person as a response to their impairment, making ''disablist'' or ''disablism'' arguably the more logical terms to describe discrimination on the grounds of disability. However, from another logical perspective, most words employing the suffix "-ism" represent that the root of the word is that which is deemed privileged or superior in comparison with all other categories; therefore, ''ableism'' would logically mean a belief that those who are "able" are inherently superior to those who are not. Other [[English language|English]]-speaking nations may use either ''disablism'', ''ableism'', or both.

==Architectural issues==
{{Expand section|date=September 2010}}
The presumption that everyone (or at least everyone who matters) is non-disabled is said to encourage environments that are inaccessible to disabled people. For example, a building may be built with [[stairs]] but no [[elevator|lift]] or [[wheelchair accessible]] [[Wheelchair ramp|ramp]]s. Even if a disabled person who is ambulatory can and does use stairs, the stairs may not have [[Handrail|railings]] to hold on to, making the process of climbing and descending them either impossible or with serious [[Falling (accident)|risk of injury]]. Such practices can also make getting into [[public transportation]] such as [[metro system]]s difficult because many of these systems also do not have lifts, unless they are relatively newly-constructed or have had a major refurbishment.

==Ideological issues==
{{Expand section|date=September 2010}}
In extreme cases, morality, worth and intelligence may even be equated to being able-bodied or able-minded, while disability is [[conflated]] with immorality, stupidity, and worthlessness, and disabled lives may be devalued to the point that some in a society may believe that one is better off dead than living with disability.{{Citation needed|date=March 2008}}  The [[eugenics]] movement of the 19th and 20th centuries, which took its most extreme form in Nazi Germany with [[Action T4]], was a product of this belief, and some believe the ‘[[right to die]]’ movement is also an outgrowth of ableist beliefs&lt;ref name = "Teaching for diversity and social justice"&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://books.google.ca/books?id=1587Y2cwSjkC&amp;pg=PA354&amp;lpg=PA354&amp;dq=ableist+%27right+to+die%27&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=f37uibygvv&amp;sig=d3N3DWeMzkCLWwWnx_Nv6BUhTwg&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=-hPTSuiZMJHIlAeZh6GpCg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=8&amp;ved=0CBkQ6AEwBw#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false|author= "Maurianne Adams, Lee Anne Bell, Pat Griffin"|title=Teaching for diversity and social justice|date=last modified 2007|publisher=CRC Press|accessdate=2009-10-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; .

==Laws opposing ableist standards==
In the U.S., Section 504 of the Rehabilitation Act of 1973 and the [[Americans with Disabilities Act]] of 1990 (ADA) enacted into law certain [[Civil law (common law)|civil]] penalties for failing to make a public places comply with access codes known as the ADA Access Guidelines (ADAAG); this law also helped expand the use of certain adaptive devices, such as TTYs (phone systems for the deaf/speech impaired), some [[computer]]-related hardware and software, and [[ramps]] or lifts on [[public transportation]] [[bus]]es and private automobiles. In the UK, meanwhile, the [[Disability Discrimination Act 1995|1995 Disability Discrimination Act]] and [[Disability Discrimination Act 2005]] attempt the same.

However, neither of these laws requires all buildings constructed before the date of the Act to be modified to fit the physical directives of the Act. Government administration buildings regardless of age are required to do so {{Citation needed|date=September 2010}}, but generally, only newly-constructed or newly-refurbished buildings have these requirements according to the Act.

Sometimes, under their own power and for their own reasons, a business or service that does not have to modify its building structure to fit the accessibility requirements will modify it anyway. But other times, this does not happen, and any attempts to access the building by disabled individuals are ignored and shunned.

{{Expert-subject-multiple|Sociology|Discrimination|Disability|date=September 2010}}

==See also==
*[[ADAPT]]
*[[Audism]]
*[[Autism rights movement]]
*[[Custom employment]]
*[[Disability etiquette]]
*[[Disability hate crime]]
*[[Disability rights]]
*[[Disability studies]]
*[[Inclusion (disability rights)]]
*[[Intersectionality]]
*[[Kyriarchy]]
*[[List of disability rights activists]]
*[[Psychophobia]]
*[[Social criticism]]

==References==
{{No footnotes|date=June 2008}}
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.ataccess.org/ Alliance for Technology Access ]
* [http://www.equalemployment.org/publications/aguidetodisabilityrights.html Center for Disability Law and Policy ]
* [http://www.raggededgemagazine.com/1100/1100votestory.htm Ragged Edge Online ]
* [http://www.zmag.org/sustainers/content/2002-08/31russell.cfm "The Social Movement Left Out"] - ''[[Z Magazine]]'' article by Marta Russell
* [http://www.issuelab.org/closeup/Feb_2009 Nonprofit Research Collection on Disability &amp; Employment] Published on IssueLab
* [http://www.timetogetequal.org.uk/page.asp?section=37&amp;sectionTitle=Beating+disablism Beating Disablism]
* [http://www.demos.co.uk/publications/disablism Disablism]
* [http://www.milieu.it/DisabilityStudiesItaly/DisabilityStudiesItaly.html Disability Studies Italy]
* [http://www.disablism.co.uk Disablism UK]
* [http://www.disabled-world.com/disability/discrimination/ Disability Discrimination Information and News]

{{Discrimination}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Discrimination Against The Disabled}}
[[Category:Disability]]
[[Category:Sociology]]
[[Category:Political theories]]
[[Category:Social theories]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Disability rights]]
[[Category:Activism]]
[[Category:Dispositional beliefs]]

[[de:Behindertenfeindlichkeit]]
[[nl:Validisme]]
[[pl:Handicapizm]]
[[pt:Ableísmo]]
[[sv:Diskriminering av personer med funktionsnedsättning]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>