<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20070911005650|157051327" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="29555364" pageid="29555364" ns="0" title="Ableism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-09-29T19:04:45Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{discrimination2}}
'''Ableism''' is a [[neologism]] of [[United States|American]] coinage, since about [[1981]]. It is used to describe inherent [[discrimination]] against people with disabilities in favor of people who are not [[disabled]]. 

An ''ableist'' society is said to be one that treats non-disabled individuals as the standard of ‘normal living’, which results in public and private places and services, education, and social work that are built to serve 'standard' people, thereby inherently excluding those with various disabilities.

==Linguistic considerations==
Though the proper formation from the nominal stem would be ''abilitism'' (compare ''[[ageism]]'', a 1969 neologism, the correct Latinate form of which would be ''aetatism''), the term ''ableism'' is the term in use.

==Discrimination==
The presumption that everyone is non-disabled is said to be effectively discriminatory in itself, creating built environments which are inaccessible to disabled people. Advocates of the term argue that ''ableism'' is analogous to [[racism]] and [[sexism]] in that it is a system by which mainstream society denigrates, devalues, and thus oppresses those with disabilities, while privileging those without disabilities. 

In extreme cases, morality, worth and intelligence may even be equated to being ablebodied or ableminded, while disability is [[conflated]] with immorality, stupidity, and worthlessness and disabled lives may be devalued to the point that many in the society believe that one is better off dead than living with disability.  The eugenics movement of the 19th and 20th centuries, which took its most extreme form in Nazi Germany with [[Action T4]], was a product of this belief and many believe that the ‘right to die’ movement (also called the ‘better dead than disabled’ movement) is also an outgrowth of the ableist belief that living with disability is inherently undignified and unworthy.

===Laws against discrimination===
In the U.S., Section 504 of the Rehabilitation Act of 1973 and the [[Americans with Disabilities Act]] of 1990 (ADA) enacted into law certain [[Civil law (common law)|civil]] penalties for failing to make a public places comply with access codes known as the ADA Access Guidelines (ADAAG); this law also helped expand the use of certain adaptive devices, such as TTY’s (phone systems for the deaf/speech impaired), some [[computer]]-related hardware and software, and [[ramps]] or lifts on [[public transportation]] [[bus]]es and private automobiles. 

In the UK, meanwhile, the [[Disability Discrimination Act 1995|1995 Disability Discrimination Act]] and [[Disability Discrimination Act 2005]] attempts the same. 

However, these laws often concentrate mainly on the [[civil]] aspect of disability discrimination and, by their very nature as [[law]]-based papers, they often neglect the [[cultural]] dimensions that are integral to the [[social model of disability]].

==Inclusion==
''[[inclusion (disability rights)|Inclusion]]'', comparatively, means that all products, services, and societal opportunities and resources are fully accessible, welcoming, functional and usable for as many different types of abilities as reasonably possible. An ''ableist'' society tends towards [[isolation]], [[pity]], paternalism and low [[self-esteem]] among people with disabilities, whereas an ''inclusive'' society tends toward sociability and interdependency between the able-bodied and disabled. See [[Inclusion (disability rights)]] for more on this concept.

==References==
{{reflist}}
==See also==
*[[Inclusion (disability rights)]]
*[[Piss on pity]]
*[[Disability]]
*[[Social model of disability]]
*[[Disability etiquette]]
*[[List of disability rights activists]]
*[[Audism]]
*[[Social criticism]]

==External links==
* [http://www.aapd-dc.org/ American Association of People with Disabilities ]
* [http://www.ataccess.org/ Alliance for Technology Access ]
* [http://www.equalemployment.org/publications/aguidetodisabilityrights.html Center for Disability Law and Policy ]
* [http://www.raggededgemagazine.com/1100/1100votestory.htm Ragged Edge Online ]
* [http://www.zmag.org/sustainers/content/2002-08/31russell.cfm "The Social Movement Left Out"] - ''[[Z Magazine]]'' article by Marta Russell
{{Expand|date=April 2007}}
{{expert}}
{{Original research|date=September 2007}}

[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Disability rights]]
[[Category:Activism]]

[[de:Behindertenfeindlichkeit]]
[[nl:Validisme]]
[[pl:Handicapizm]]
[[pt:Ableismo]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>