<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20151121075951|691650709" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="29555364" pageid="29555364" ns="0" title="Ableism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2015-11-21T08:00:06Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{merge from|Handicapism|discuss=Talk:Ableism#Proposed merge with Handicapism|date=September 2014}}
{{globalize/Eng|date=August 2012}}
{{Discrimination sidebar}}
'''Ableism''' or '''ablism'''&lt;ref&gt;Oxford University Press, [http://www.oxforddictionaries.com/definition/english/ableism "Oxford Dictionaries Online: 'ableism'"], ''Oxford Dictionaries Online'', Retrieved 12 March 201h.&lt;/ref&gt; ({{IPAc-en|ˈ|eɪ|b|l|ɪ|z|əm}}) is a form of [[discrimination]] or social [[prejudice]] against people with disabilities. It may also be referred to as '''disability discrimination''', '''ablecentrism''',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://130.102.44.246/login?auth=0&amp;type=summary&amp;url=/journals/journal_of_womens_history/v015/15.3kafer.html|title=Project MUSE - Compulsory Bodies: Reflections on Heterosexuality and Able-bodiedness|work=44.246}}&lt;/ref&gt; '''physicalism''', '''handicapism''', and '''disability oppression'''.{{sfn|Griffin|Peters|Smith|2007|p=335}} It is also sometimes known as '''disablism''', although there is some dispute as to whether ableism and disablism are synonymous, and some people within [[Disability rights movement|disability rights]] circles find the latter term's use inaccurate. Discrimination faced by those who have or are perceived to have a [[mental disorder]] is sometimes called [[Mentalism (discrimination)|mentalism]] rather than ableism.

==Definition==
Similar to many of the assumptions underlying the [[medical model of disability]] amongst many [[clinicians]], the "ableist" societal world-view is that the [[able-bodied]] are the norm in society, and that people who have disabilities deviate from that norm. A disability is thus, something that must be overcome. The ableist worldview holds that disability is an error, a mistake, or a failing, rather than a simple consequence of human diversity, akin to [[race (classification of humans)|race]], [[Ethnic group|ethnicity]], [[sexual orientation]], or [[gender]].{{sfn|Marshak|Dandeneau|Prezant|L'Amoreaux|2009|p=50}}

Campbell draws a distinction between disablism and ableism.  Disablism, she notes, has been the traditional focus of study within the field of [[disability studies]].  Disablism promotes the unequal treatment of the (physically) disabled versus the able-bodied.  It marks the disabled as the [[Other]], and works from the perspective of the able-bodied.{{sfn|Campbell|2009|pp=3&amp;ndash;4}}

Campbell acknowledges that the concept of ableism is, as of 2009, not clearly defined in the literature and has "limited definitional or conceptual specificity".{{sfn|Campbell|2009|p=5}} She herself distinguishes between ableism and disablism, defining the former as:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
A network of beliefs, processes and practices that produces a particular kind of self and body (the corporeal standard) that is projected as the perfect, species-typical, and therefore essential and fully human.  Disability is then cast as a diminished state of being human.{{sfn|Campbell|2009|p=5}}{{sfn|Campbell|2001|p=44}}
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Other definitions of ableism include those of Chouinard, who defines it as "ideas, practices, institutions, and social relations that presume able-bodiedness, and by so doing, construct persons with disabilities as [[marginalization|marginalized]] &amp;#91;&amp;hellip;&amp;#93; and largely invisible 'others'"{{sfn|Campbell|2009|p=5}}{{sfn|Chouinard|1997|p=380}} and Amundson and Taira, who define it as "a doctrine that falsely treats impairments as inherently and naturally horrible and blames the impairments themselves for the problems experienced by the people who have them".{{sfn|Campbell|2009|p=5}}{{sfn|Amundson|Taira|2005|p=54}}

In many circles, there is disagreement as to how to refer to themselves and if referring to themselves as "disabled" counts as internalized ableism. These groups may prefer the terms non-neurotypical or neurodivergent for mental divergences, or non-common-bodied for physical divergences. For those that do call themselves disabled, most prefer being referred to as disabled people, rather than people with disabilities, because the latter uses person-first language that separates the person from their disability, rather than identity-first language. In effect, it denies that their disability is a part of who they are and thereby denies the ableism itself.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://autisticadvocacy.org/identity-first-language/|title=Identity-First Language|author=Autistic Self Advocacy Network|work=autisticadvocacy.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Harpur argues that the term ableism is a powerful label that has the capacity to ameliorate the use of negative stereotypes and facilitate cultural change by focusing attention on the discriminator rather than on the victim or impairment.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | last = Harpur | first = Paul | title = Sexism and Racism, Why not Ableism? Calling for a Cultural Shift in the Approach to Disability Discrimination | journal = Alternative Law Journal | volume = 34 | issue = 3 | pages = 163–167 | publisher = Legal Service Bulletin Co-operative Ltd | location = Melbourne | year = 2009 | url = http://www.altlj.org/index.php?option=Articles&amp;task=viewarticle&amp;artid=69#4 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;'From Disability to Ability:  Changing the Phrasing of the Debate' (2012) 27 Disability and Society 3, 325-337&lt;/ref&gt; An individual that expresses hostility towards disabled people is called an ''able-bodyist'' or ''ablecentrist''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Pelka|first1=Fred|title=The ABC-CLIO Companion to the Disability Rights Movement|date=1997|page=98}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;In Other Words: Writing As a Feminist - Page 50, Sigrid Nielsen - 2012&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legislation==

===United Kingdom===

In the UK, disability discrimination became unlawful as a result of the [[Disability Discrimination Act 1995]] and, later, the [[Disability Discrimination Act 2005]]. These were later repealed but the substantive law is replicated in the [[Equality Act 2010]]. Under the [[Equality Act 2010]] there are several types of discrimination that are prohibited. These are direct discrimination (s.13(1) [[Equality Act 2010]]), indirect discrimination (s.6 and s.19 [[Equality Act 2010]], [[harassment]] (s.26 [[Equality Act 2010]]), [[victimisation]] (s.27(2) [[Equality Act 2010]]), discrimination arising from disability (s.15(1) [[Equality Act 2010]]) and failure to make reasonable adjustments (s.20 [[Equality Act 2010]]).

The legal definition of disability is:

''"A person (P) has a disability if P has a physical or mental impairment, and the impairment has a substantial and long-term adverse effect on his ability to carry out normal day-to-day activities".'' (Section 6(1), [[Equality Act 2010]])

Some conditions (such as blindness, [[AIDS]] and cancer) are expressly included; others (such as drug and alcohol addictions) are expressly excluded.

Legal experts have suggested that this definition of disability may change as a result of a Danish case currently{{when?|date=May 2015}} before the [[European Court of Justice]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lewissilkin.com/Journal/2012/October/Dicing-with-disability.aspx|title=Lewis Silkin - Journal - Dicing with disability|author=Lewis Silkin|date=24 October 2012|work=lewissilkin.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===United States===
Until the 1970s, ableism in the [[United States]] was often codified into law. For example, in many jurisdictions, so-called "[[ugly law]]s" barred people from appearing in public if they had diseases or disfigurements that were considered unsightly.&lt;ref name="brown"&gt;Brown, Patricia Leigh (August 20, 2000). [http://www.accessmylibrary.com/coms2/summary_0286-29736932_ITM "Viewing Ahab and Barbie Through the Lens of Disability"]. ''[[The New York Times]]''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.accessmylibrary.com/coms2/summary_0286-29736932_ITM|title=Cengage Learning|work=accessmylibrary.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Section 504 and other sections of the [[Rehabilitation Act of 1973]] and the [[Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990]] (ADA) enacted into law certain [[civil law (common law)|civil]] penalties for failing to make public places comply with access codes known as the ADA Access Guidelines (ADAAG); this law also helped expand the use of certain adaptive devices, such as [[Telecommunications device for the deaf|TTYs]] (phone systems for the hearing/speech impaired), some [[computer]]-related hardware and software, [[wheelchair ramp]]s or lifts on [[public transportation]] and curb-cuts at intersections which allow wheelchairs and their users to safely move between sidewalks and crosswalks.  In addition these laws prohibit direct discrimination against disabled people in government programs, employment, public transit and public accommodations like stores and restaurants.

The building modification provisions of these directives apply to three general categories of buildings: existing government administration buildings and structures regardless of age; all newly constructed buildings and structures intended for use as public accommodations like stores and restaurants; significantly [[renovated]] and/or refurbished buildings and structures and any public accommodation where the cost of modification is slight when compared with the income it generates.  The US government also offered significant tax incentives to businesses to make these modifications.

The federal [[Fair Housing Act (United States)|Fair Housing Amendments Act]] of 1988 prohibits housing discrimination on the basis of disability and requires that newly constructed multi-family housing meet certain access guidelines while requiring landlords to allow disabled persons to modify existing dwellings for accessibility.

The Telecommunications Act, Individuals with Disabilities Education Act, Air Carriers Access Act, Voting Accessibility Act and others have codified the notion that persons with disabilities have some of the same rights and privileges as other citizens.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ada.gov/cguide.htm|title=A Guide to Disability Rights Laws|work=ada.gov}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===California===
In addition to the federal protections provided by the ADA, [[California]]'s [[California Fair Employment and Housing Act|Fair Employment and Housing Act]] (FEHA) provides additional protections to California employees. Notably, FEHA applies to employers with 5 or more employees and offers more extensive protection than the ADA.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://mybossstinks.com/disability_discrimination.html |title=Disability Discrimination |publisher=Mybossstinks.com |date= |accessdate=2012-10-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Empirical evidence==

In 2014, a large correspondence experiment to measure disability discrimination was conducted in Belgium by professor Stijn Baert of [[Ghent University]]. Two applications of graduates, identical except that one revealed a disability (blindness, deafness or autism), were both sent out to 768 vacancies for which the disabled candidates could be expected to be as productive as their non-disabled counterparts, based on the vacancy information. In addition, the researcher randomly disclosed the entitlement to a substantial wage subsidy in the applications of the disabled candidates. Disabled candidates had a 48% lower chance to receive a positive reaction from the employer side compared with the non-disabled candidates. Potentially due to the fear of the red tape, disclosing a wage subsidy did not affect the employment opportunities of disabled candidates.&lt;ref&gt;Baert, S. (Forthcoming) [http://link.springer.com/article/10.1007%2Fs10198-014-0656-7 Wage Subsidies and Hiring Chances for the Disabled: Some Causal Evidence.] European Journal of Health Economics.&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Disability|Discrimination}}
{{div col|cols=2}}
*[[ADAPT]]
*[[Atos]]
*[[Audism]]
*[[Autism rights movement]]
*[[Compulsory sterilization]]
*[[Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities]]
*[[Custom employment]]
*[[Disability abuse]]
*[[Disability etiquette]]
*[[Disability hate crime]]
*[[Disability rights]]
*[[Disfranchisement]]
*[[Eugenics]]
*[[Inclusion (disability rights)]]
*[[Intersectionality]]
*[[Kyriarchy]]
*[[List of disability rights activists]]
*[[Phillip Davies]]
*[[Psychiatric survivors movement]]
*[[Psychophobia]]
*[[Social criticism]]
*[[Social deprivation]]
*[[United Kingdom employment equality law]]
{{div col end}}

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

===Bibliography===
&lt;!-- alphabetically by last name of first author/editor --&gt;
{{refbegin|1}}
* {{cite journal|ref=harv
  |last1=Amundson|first1=Ron
  |first2=Gayle|last2=Taira
  |title=Our Lives and Ideologies: The Effects of Life Experience on the Perceived Morality of the Policy of Physician-Assisted Suicide
  |journal=Journal of Policy Studies
  |volume=16|issue=1
  |year=2005
  |pages=53&amp;ndash;57
  |url=http://uhh.hawaii.edu./~ronald/pubs/2005-Amundson-Taira.pdf
  |format=PDF |doi=10.1177/10442073050160010801
}}
* {{cite journal|ref=harv
  |first=Fiona A. Kumari|last=Campbell
  |year=2001
  |title=Inciting Legal Fictions: Disability Date with Ontology and the Ableist Body of the Law
  |journal=Griffith Law Review
  |volume=10
  |issue=1
  |pages=42&amp;ndash;62
}}
* {{cite book|ref=harv
  |title=Contours of Ableism: The Production of Disability and Abledness
  |first=Fiona A. Kumari|last=Campbell
  |publisher=Palgrave Macmillan
  |year=2009
  |isbn=978-0-230-57928-6
}}
* {{cite journal|ref=harv
  |last=Chouinard|first=Vera
  |title=Making Space for Disabling Difference: Challenges Ableist Geographies
  |journal=Environment and Planning D: Society and Space
  |volume=15
  |year=1997
  |pages=379&amp;ndash;387
}}
* {{cite book|ref=harv
  |title=Teaching for diversity and social justice
  |volume=1
  |editor1-first=Maurianne|editor1-last=Adams
  |editor2-first=Lee Anne|editor2-last=Bell
  |editor3-first=Pat|editor3-last=Griffin
  |chapter=Ableism Curriculum Design
  |first1=Pat|last1=Griffin
  |first2=Madelaine L.|last2=Peters
  |first3=Robin M.|last3=Smith
  |edition=2nd
  |publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis
  |year=2007
  |isbn=978-0-415-95199-9
}}
* {{cite book|ref=harv
  |title=The School Counselor's Guide to Helping Students with Disabilities
  |series=Jossey-Bass teacher
  |first1=Laura E.|last1=Marshak
  |first2=Claire J.|last2=Dandeneau
  |first3=Fran P.|last3=Prezant
  |first4=Nadene A.|last4=L'Amoreaux
  |publisher=John Wiley and Sons
  |year=2009
  |isbn=978-0-470-17579-8
}}
{{refend}}

== Further reading ==
* {{cite journal|ref=harv
  |url=http://journal.media-culture.org.au/index.php/mcjournal/article/viewArticle/46/0
  |journal=M/C Journal
  |volume=11|issue=3
  |year=2008
  |title=Refusing Able(ness): A Preliminary Conversation about Ableism
  |first=Fiona A. Kumari|last=Campbell
}}
* {{cite journal|ref=harv
  |last=Clear|first=Mike
  |title=The "Normal" and the Monstrous in Disability Research
  |journal=Disability &amp;amp; Society
  |volume=14|issue=4
  |year=1999
  |pages=435&amp;ndash;448
  |doi=10.1080/09687599926055
}}
* {{cite book|ref=harv
  |chapter=Eliminating Ableism in Education
  |first=Thomas|last=Hehir
  |title=Special education for a new century
  |volume=41
  |series=Harvard educational review
  |editor1-first=Lauren I.|editor1-last=Katzman
  |publisher=Harvard Educational Review
  |year=2005
  |isbn=&lt;!--091669044X--&gt;978-0-916690-44-1
}}
* {{cite journal|ref=harv
  |last1=Iwasaki|first1=Yoshitaka
  |first2=Jennifer|last2=Mactavish
  |title=Ubiquitous Yet Unique: Perspectives of People with Disabilities on Stress
  |journal=Rehabilitation Counselling Bulletin
  |volume=48|issue=4
  |year=2005
  |pages=194&amp;ndash;208
  |doi=10.1177/00343552050480040101
}}
* {{cite journal|ref=harv
  |last1=Watts|first1=Ivan Eugene
  |first2=Nirmala|last2=Erevelles
  |title=These Deadly Times: Reconceptualizing School Violence by Using Critical Race Theory and Disability Studies
  |journal=American Educational Research Journal
  |volume=41|issue=2
  |year=2004
  |pages=271&amp;ndash;299
  |jstor=3699367 |doi=10.3102/00028312041002271
}}

==External links==
* [http://www.ataccess.org/ Alliance for Technology Access ]
* [http://www.equalemployment.org/publications/aguidetodisabilityrights.html Center for Disability Law and Policy ]
* [http://www.raggededgemagazine.com/1100/1100votestory.htm Ragged Edge Online ]
* [http://www.zmag.org/sustainers/content/2002-08/31russell.cfm "The Social Movement Left Out"] - ''[[Z Magazine]]'' article by Marta Russell
* [http://www.issuelab.org/closeup/Feb_2009 Nonprofit Research Collection on Disability &amp; Employment] Published on IssueLab
* [http://www.demos.co.uk/publications/disablism Disablism]
* [http://www.disabled-world.com/disability/discrimination/ Disability Discrimination Information and News]
* [http://www.lewissilkin.com/Knowledge/2012/February/~/media/Knowledge%20PDFs/Employment/Disability%20discrimination.ashx Guide to UK disability discrimination law]
* [http://www.mlsemployment.co.uk/discrimination-equality.aspx Disability Discrimination] in the UK

{{Disability navbox}}
{{Discrimination}}

[[Category:Social theories]]
[[Category:Ablecentrism]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Activism]]
[[Category:Sociological terminology]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>