<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20241120014809|1258495663" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="29555364" pageid="29555364" ns="0" title="Ableism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2024-11-29T14:49:39Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|Discrimination on grounds of disability}}
{{Discrimination sidebar|expanded=Attributes}}
{{Disability sidebar|theory}}
'''Ableism''' ({{IPAc-en|ˈ|eɪ|b|əl|ɪ|z|əm}}; also known as '''ablism''', '''disablism''' (British English), '''anapirophobia''', '''anapirism''', and '''disability discrimination''') is [[discrimination]] and social [[prejudice]] against people with physical or mental [[Disability|disabilities]] (see also [[Sanism]]). Ableism characterizes people as they are defined by their disabilities and it also classifies disabled people as people who are inferior to non-disabled people.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Claiming Disability: Knowledge and Identity |url = https://archive.org/details/claimingdisabili00lint  |first1=Simi|last1=Linton|author-link1=Simi Linton|first2=Michael|last2=Bérubé|author-link2=Michael Bérubé|year=1998|page=9|isbn=9780814751343|publisher=[[New York University Press]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; On this basis, people are assigned or denied certain perceived abilities, skills, or [[character orientation]]s.

Although ableism and disablism are both terms which describe disability discrimination, the emphasis for each of these terms is slightly different. Ableism is discrimination in favor of non-disabled people, while disablism is discrimination against disabled people.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Disablism and ableism|url=https://www.scope.org.uk/about-us/disablism/|access-date=2020-11-21|website=[[Scope (charity)|Scope]]|language=en-gb}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There are stereotypes which are either associated with disability in general, or they are associated with specific impairments or chronic health conditions (for instance the presumption that all disabled people want to be cured, the presumption that wheelchair users also have an intellectual disability, or the presumption that blind people have some special form of insight).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://disability-studies.leeds.ac.uk/wp-content/uploads/sites/40/library/Sutherland-CHAPTER6.pdf|title=Sutherland, A.T. 'Disabled We Stand', Chapter 6 'Stereotypes of Disability', Souvenir Press, 1982}}&lt;/ref&gt; These [[stereotype]]s, in turn, serve as a justification for discriminatory practices, and reinforce discriminatory [[Attitude (psychology)|attitudes]] and [[behavior]]s toward people who are disabled.&lt;ref&gt;Wüllenweber, Ernst; Theunissen, Georg; Mühl, Heinz (2006). ''Pädagogik bei geistigen Behinderungen: ein Handbuch für Studium und Praxis (Education for intellectual disabilities: A manual for study and practice)'' (in German). [[Kohlhammer Verlag]]. p. 149. {{ISBN|3-17-018437-7}}. Retrieved January 17, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; Labeling affects people when it limits their options for action or changes their identity.&lt;ref&gt;"Geistige Behinderung{{snd}} Normtheorien nach Speck und Goffman". Heilpaedagogik-info.de. Retrieved 2014-05-12.&lt;/ref&gt;

In ableist societies, the lives of disabled people is considered less worth living, or disabled people less valuable, even sometimes expendable. The [[eugenics]] movement of the early 20th century is considered an expression of widespread ableism.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Powell |first=Robyn M. |date=2020–2021 |title=Confronting Eugenics Means Finally Confronting Its Ableist Roots |url=https://heinonline.org/HOL/Page?handle=hein.journals/wmjwl27&amp;id=645&amp;div=&amp;collection= |journal=William &amp; Mary Journal of Race, Gender, and Social Justice |volume=27 |pages=607}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Ableism can be further understood by reading literature which is written and published by those who experience disability and ableism first-hand. [[Disability studies]] is an academic discipline which is also beneficial when non-disabled people pursue it in order to gain a better understanding of ableism.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Ferguson |first1=Philip M. |last2=Nusbaum |first2=Emily |date=2012 |title=Disability Studies: What Is It and What Difference Does It Make? |journal=Research &amp; Practice for Persons with Severe Disabilities |volume=37 |issue=2 |pages=79–80}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Etymology==
Originating from ''-able'' (in disable, disabled) and ''[[-ism]]'' (in [[racism]], [[sexism]]); first recorded in 1981.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/ableism|title=Definition of ABLEISM|website=[[Merriam-Webster Online Dictionary]]|access-date=1 April 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Dictionary.com|ableism}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==
=== Canada ===
Ableism in Canada refers to a set of discourses, behaviors, and structures that express feelings of anxiety, fear, [[hostility]], and [[antipathy]] towards people with disabilities in [[Canadian people|Canada]].

The specific types of [[discrimination]] that have occurred or are still occurring in Canada include the inability to access important facilities such as infrastructure within the [[transportation|transport]] network, restrictive [[immigration policy|immigration policies]], [[involuntary sterilization]] to stop people with disabilities from having offspring, [[Employment discrimination|barriers to employment opportunities]], [[wage]]s that are insufficient to maintain a minimal [[standard of living]], and [[involuntary commitment|institutionalization]] of people with disabilities in substandard conditions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Policy on ableism and discrimination based on disability |url=http://www.ohrc.on.ca/en/policy-ableism-and-discrimination-based-disability |publisher=[[Ontario Human Rights Commission]] |access-date=26 August 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Austerity measure]]s implemented by the [[government of Canada]] have also at times been referred to as ableist, such as funding cuts that put people with disabilities at risk of [[Substandard housing|living in abusive arrangements]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://nationalpost.com/pmn/news-pmn/canada-news-pmn/austerity-left-people-with-disabilities-without-housing-n-s-inquiry-told|title='Ableist' bias left people with disabilities without housing, N.S. inquiry told|date=4 June 2018|website=[[National Post]]|access-date=26 August 2018|first=Michael|last=Tutton}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Nazi Germany ===
In July 1933, [[Adolf Hitler|Hitler]], along with the [[Government of Nazi Germany|Nazi Government]], implemented the [[Law for the Prevention of Hereditarily Diseased Offspring|Law for the Prevention of Progeny with Hereditary Diseased Offspring]]. Essentially, this law implemented sterilization practices for all people who had what were considered hereditary disabilities. For example, disabilities such as mental illness, blindness and deafness were all considered hereditary diseases; therefore, people with these disabilities were sterilized. The law also created propaganda against people with disabilities; people with disabilities were displayed as unimportant towards progressing the Aryan race.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=People with Disabilities — United States Holocaust Memorial Museum |url=https://www.ushmm.org/collections/bibliography/people-with-disabilities |access-date=2022-04-10 |website=www.ushmm.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1939 Hitler signed the secret euthanasia program decree [[Aktion T4]], which authorized the killing of selected patients diagnosed with chronic neurological and psychiatric disorders. This program killed about 70,000 disabled people before it was officially halted by Hitler in 1941 under public pressure, and it was unofficially continued out of the public eye, killing a total of 200,000 or more by the end of Hitler's reign in 1945.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.britannica.com/event/T4-Program|title=T4 Program{{snd}} Definition and History|website=[[Encyclopedia Britannica]]|access-date=1 April 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===United Kingdom===
[[File:Convicts Lunatics and Women! Have No Vote for Parliament, ca. 1907-1918.jpg|alt=A poster in gold colors and line art, showing three people: a large menacing man, a small frail man, and a woman in academic robes; the wording is "She. It is time I got out of this place. Where Shall I Find The Key? Convicts Lunatics and Women! Have no vote for Parliament"|thumb|A poster of the British suffrage movement, attacking the fact that women were placed next to "[[lunatics]]" and [[convicts]] in being unable to vote. Ableist and eugenicist ideas were often found in suffrage rhetoric.]]

In the UK, disability discrimination became unlawful as a result of the [[Disability Discrimination Act 1995]], and the [[Disability Discrimination Act 2005]]. These were later superseded, retaining the substantive law, by the [[Equality Act 2010]]. The Equality Act 2010 brought together protections against multiple areas of discriminatory behavior (disability, race, religion and belief, sex, sexual orientation, gender identity, age and pregnancy{{snd}} the so-called "protected characteristics").&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2010/15/notes/division/2/1|title=Equality Act 2010 - Explanatory Notes|website=[[legislation.gov.uk]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Under the Equality Act 2010, there are prohibitions addressing several forms of discrimination including direct discrimination (s.13), indirect discrimination (s.6, s.19), [[harassment]] (s.26), [[victimisation]] (s.27), discrimination arising from disability (s.15), and failure to make reasonable adjustments (s.20).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2010/15/contents|title=Equality Act 2010 (Contents)|website=[[legislation.gov.uk]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Part 2, chapter 1, section 6, of the Equality Act 2010 states that "A person (P) has a disability if (a) P has a physical or mental impairment, and (b) the impairment has a substantial and long-term adverse effect on P's ability to carry out normal day-to-day activities."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2010/15/section/6|title=Equality Act 2010 (Section 6)|website=[[legislation.gov.uk]]|access-date=9 August 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===United States===
Much like many minority groups, disabled Americans were often [[wikt:segregated|segregated]] and denied certain rights for a majority of American history.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://knightpoliticalreporting.syr.edu/?civilhistoryessays=a-civil-rights-history-americans-with-disabilities|title=A Civil Rights History: Americans with Disabilities|last=Faville|first=Andrea|website=[[Knight Foundation|Knight Chair in Political Reporting]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the 1800s, a shift from a religious view to a more scientific view took place and caused more individuals with disabilities to be examined.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://nccj.org/ableism|title=Ableism|website=[[National Conference for Community and Justice]] }}&lt;/ref&gt; Public stigma began to change after [[World War II]] when many Americans returned home with disabilities. In the 1960s, following the [[civil rights movement]] in America, the world began the [[Disability rights movement|disabled rights movement]]. The movement was intended to give all individuals with disabilities equal rights and opportunities. Until the 1970s, ableism in the United States was often codified into law. For example, in many jurisdictions, so-called "[[ugly law]]s" barred people from appearing in public if they had diseases or disfigurements that were considered unsightly.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://rootedinrights.org/the-ugly-laws-disability-in-public/|title=The Ugly Laws: Disability In Public — Galaxy Book Review|date=6 September 2011|website=rootedinrights.org|access-date=1 April 2019|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170118150635/https://rootedinrights.org/the-ugly-laws-disability-in-public/|archive-date=January 18, 2017|first=Shannon|last=Sommer}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== UN Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities ===
In May 2012, the [[UN]] Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities was ratified. The document establishes the inadmissibility of discrimination on the basis of disability, including in [[Employability|employment]]. In addition, the amendments create a legal basis for significantly expanding opportunities to protect the rights of persons with disabilities, including in the administrative procedure and in court. The law defined specific obligations that all owners of facilities and service providers must fulfill to create conditions for disabled people equal to the rest.&lt;ref&gt;[https://ria.ru/society/20160111/1357718226.html Дискриминация инвалидов запрещена в России с 1 января — РИА Новости (Discrimination of disabled people is prohibited in Russia since January 1] - [[Rossiya Segodnya|RIA News]])&lt;/ref&gt;

== Workplace ==
In 1990, the [[Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990|Americans with Disabilities Act]] was put in place to prohibit private employers, state and local government, employment agencies and labor unions from discrimination against qualified disabled people in job applications, when hiring, firing, advancement in workplace, compensation, training, and on other terms, conditions and privileges of employment.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.ada.gov/ada_title_I.htm|title=Employment (Title I)|website=[[Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990|ADA.gov]]|access-date=1 April 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; The U.S. [[Equal Employment Opportunity Commission]] (EEOC) plays a part in fighting against ableism by being responsible for enforcing federal laws that make it illegal to discriminate against a job applicant or an employee because of the person's race, color, religion, sex (including pregnancy, gender identity, and sexual orientation), national origin, age (40 or older), disability or genetic information.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.eeoc.gov/overview|title=About the EEOC: Overview|website=[[Equal Employment Opportunity Commission]]|access-date=1 April 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Similarly in the UK, the [[Equality Act 2010]] was put in place and provides legislation that there should be no workplace discrimination. Under the act, all employers have a duty to make reasonable adjustments for their disabled employees to help them overcome any disadvantages resulting from the impairment. Failure to carry out reasonable adjustment amounts to disability discrimination.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Employment Tribunal Claims |url=https://employmenttribunal.claims/employment-law/discrimination/disability-discrimination/ |access-date=2022-08-09 |website=www.employmenttribunal.claims}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Employers and managers are often concerned about the potential cost associated with providing accommodations to employees with disabilities.&lt;ref&gt;Bonaccio, S., Connelly, C.E., Gellatly, I.R., Jetha, A., &amp; Martin Ginis, K.A. (2020). [https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s10869-018-9602-5 The participation of people with disabilities in the workplace across the employment cycle: Employer concerns and research evidence.] [[Journal of Business and Psychology]], 35(2), 135-158.&lt;/ref&gt; However, many accommodations have a cost of $0 (59% in a survey of employers conducted by the [[Job Accommodation Network]] (JAN)&lt;ref&gt;[[Job Accommodation Network]] (Updated October 21, 2020). [https://askjan.org/topics/costs.cfm Workplace accommodations: Low cost, high impact]. Retrieved 06/16/2021.&lt;/ref&gt;), and accommodation costs may be offset by the savings associated with employing people with disabilities (higher performance, lower turnover costs).&lt;ref&gt;Fisher, S. L., &amp; Connelly, C. E. (2020). [https://cjds.uwaterloo.ca/index.php/cjds/article/view/669 Building the "Business Case" for Hiring People with Disabilities: A Financial Cost-Benefit Analysis Methodology and Example]. Canadian Journal of Disability Studies, 9(4), 71-88.&lt;/ref&gt; Moreover, organizational interventions that support workplace inclusion of the most vulnerable, such as [[Neurodiversity|neurodivergent]] individuals, are likely to benefit all employees.&lt;ref&gt;Praslova, Ludmila N. (2022) An Intersectional Approach to Inclusion at Work. https://hbr.org/2022/06/an-intersectional-approach-to-inclusion-at-work. Harvard Business Review, June 21, 2022.&lt;/ref&gt;
	
Idiosyncratic deals (''i''-deals), individually negotiated work arrangements (e.g., flexible schedules, working from home), can also serve as an important work accommodation for persons with disabilities.&lt;ref&gt;Brzykcy, A. Z., Boehm, S. A., &amp; Baldridge, D.C. (2019). [https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0001879119300272 Fostering sustainable careers across the lifespan: The role of disability, idiosyncratic deals and perceived work ability.] [[Journal of Vocational Behavior]], 112, 185-198.&lt;/ref&gt; ''I''-deals can create the conditions for long-term employment for people with disabilities by creating jobs that fit each employee's abilities, interests, and career aspirations.&lt;ref name="onlinelibrary.wiley.com"&gt;Ho, J. A., Bonaccio, S., Connelly, C. E., &amp; Gellatly, I.R. (2022). [https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/hrm.22118 Representative-negotiated ''i''-deals for people with disabilities.] [[Human Resource Management]], 61(6), 681-698.&lt;/ref&gt; Agents can represent people with disabilities and help them negotiate their unique employment terms, but successful ''i''-deals require resources and flexibility on the part of the employer.&lt;ref name="onlinelibrary.wiley.com"/&gt;

== Healthcare ==
Ableism is prevalent in the many different divisions of healthcare, whether that be in prison systems, the legal or policy side of healthcare, and clinical settings.&lt;ref name=":12"&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Iezzoni |first1=Lisa I. |last2=Rao |first2=Sowmya R. |last3=Ressalam |first3=Julie |last4=Bolcic-Jankovic |first4=Dragana |last5=Agaronnik |first5=Nicole D. |last6=Donelan |first6=Karen |last7=Lagu |first7=Tara |last8=Campbell |first8=Eric G. |date=2021-02-01 |title=Physicians' Perceptions Of People With Disability And Their Health Care |journal=Health Affairs |volume=40 |issue=2 |pages=297–306 |doi=10.1377/hlthaff.2020.01452 |issn=0278-2715 |pmc=8722582 |pmid=33523739}}&lt;/ref&gt; The following subsections will explore the ways in which ableism makes its way into these areas of focus through the inaccessibility of appropriate medical treatment.

=== Clinical settings ===
Just as in every other facet of life, ableism is present in clinical healthcare settings.&lt;ref name=":12" /&gt; A 2021 study of over 700 physicians in the United States found that only 56.5% "strongly agreed that they welcomed patients with disability into their practices."&lt;ref name=":12" /&gt; The same study also found that 82.4% of these physicians believed that people with a significant disability had a lower quality of life than those without disabilities.&lt;ref name=":12" /&gt; Data from the 1994–1995 National Health Interview Survey-Disability Supplement has shown that those with disabilities have lower life expectancies than those without them.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Forman-Hoffman |first1=Valerie L. |last2=Ault |first2=Kimberly L. |last3=Anderson |first3=Wayne L. |last4=Weiner |first4=Joshua M. |last5=Stevens |first5=Alissa |last6=Campbell |first6=Vincent A. |last7=Armour |first7=Brian S. |date=2015 |title=Disability Status, Mortality, and Leading Causes of Death in the United States Community Population |journal=Medical Care |volume=53 |issue=4 |pages=346–354 |doi=10.1097/MLR.0000000000000321 |issn=0025-7079 |pmc=5302214 |pmid=25719432}}&lt;/ref&gt; While that can be explained by a myriad of factors, one of the factors is the ableism experienced by those with disabilities in clinical settings. Those with disabilities may be more hesitant to seek care when needed due to barriers created by ableism such as dentist chairs that are not accessible or offices that are filled with bright lights and noises that can be triggering.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Kripke |first=Clarissa |date=2018-05-15 |title=Adults with Developmental Disabilities: A Comprehensive Approach to Medical Care |url=https://www.aafp.org/afp/2018/0515/p649.html |journal=American Family Physician |volume=97 |issue=10 |pages=649–656 |pmid=29763271 |issn=0002-838X}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In June 2020, near the start of the [[COVID-19 pandemic]], a 46-year-old quadriplegic in Austin, Texas named Michael Hickson was denied treatment for COVID-19, sepsis, and a urinary tract infection and died 6 days after treatment was withheld.&lt;ref name=":22"&gt;{{Cite journal |title=Misperceptions Of People With Disabilities Lead To Low-Quality Care: How Policy Makers Can Counter The Harm And Injustice {{!}} Health Affairs Forefront |url=https://www.healthaffairs.org/do/10.1377/forefront.20210325.480382/full/ |access-date=2022-04-15 |journal=Health Affairs Forefront |year=2021|doi=10.1377/forefront.20210325.480382|last1=Gallegos |first1=Andrés J. }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":32"&gt;{{Cite news |title=One Man's COVID-19 Death Raises The Worst Fears Of Many People With Disabilities |language=en |work=NPR |url=https://www.npr.org/2020/07/31/896882268/one-mans-covid-19-death-raises-the-worst-fears-of-many-people-with-disabilities |access-date=2022-04-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; His physician was quoted as having said that he had a "preference to treat patients who can walk and talk." The physician also had stated his belief that Hickson's brain injury made him have not much of a quality of life. Several complaints have since been filed with the Texas Office of Civil Rights and many disability advocacy groups have become involved in the case.&lt;ref name=":22" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":32" /&gt;

Several states, including Alabama, Arizona, Kansas, Pennsylvania, Tennessee, Utah, and Washington allow healthcare providers, in times of crisis, to triage based on the perceived quality of life of the patients, which tends to be perceived as lower for those with disabilities.&lt;ref name=":22" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":12" /&gt; In Alabama, a ventilator-rationing scheme put in place during the pandemic enabled healthcare providers to exclude patients with disabilities from treatment; such patients were those who required assistance with various [[activities of daily living]], had certain mental conditions (varying degrees of mental retardation or moderate-to-severe [[dementia]]) or other preexisting conditions categorized as disabilities.&lt;ref name=":22" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://adap.ua.edu/uploads/5/7/8/9/57892141/al-ocr-complaint_3.24.20.pdf|website=adap.ua.edu|title=Letter|access-date=7 May 2023|archive-date=4 January 2023|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20230104151106/http://adap.ua.edu/uploads/5/7/8/9/57892141/al-ocr-complaint_3.24.20.pdf|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Criminal justice settings ===
The provision of effective healthcare for people with disabilities in criminal justice institutions is an important issue because the percentage of disabled people in such facilities has been shown to be larger than the percentage in the general population.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=ADA: Access to Health Care in Detention and Correctional Facilities {{!}} Mid-Atlantic ADA Center |url=https://www.adainfo.org/content/ada-access-health-care-detention-and-correctional-facilities |access-date=2022-04-09 |website=www.adainfo.org}}&lt;/ref&gt; A lack of prioritization on working to incorporate efficient and quality medical support into prison structures endangers the health and safety of disabled prisoners.

Limited access to medical care in prisons consists of long waiting times to meet with physicians and to consistently receive treatment, as well as the absence of [[harm reduction]] measures and updated healthcare protocols. Discriminatory medical treatment also takes place through the withholding of proper diets, medications, and assistance (equipment and interpreters), in addition to failures to adequately train prison staff. Insufficient medical accommodations can worsen prisoners' health conditions through greater risks of [[Depression (mood disorder)|depression]], [[HIV/AIDS]] and [[Hepatitis C]] transmission, and unsafe drug injections.&lt;ref name=":02"&gt;{{Cite book |title=Disability incarcerated: imprisonment and disability in the United States and Canada |date=2014 |editor=Liat Ben-Moshe |editor2=Chris Chapman |editor3=Allison C. Carey | publisher=Palgrave Macmillan |isbn=978-1-322-04817-8 |location=New York |pages=163–184 |oclc=888360979}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Canada, the usage of prisons as psychiatric facilities may involve issues concerning inadequate access to medical support, particularly [[mental health]] counseling, and the inability of prisoners to take part in decision-making regarding their medical treatment. The usage of psychologists employed by the correctional services organization and the lack of confidentiality in therapeutic sessions also present barriers for disabled prisoners. That makes it more difficult for prisoners with disabilities to express discontentment about problems in the available healthcare since it may later complicate their release from the prison.&lt;ref name=":02" /&gt;

In the United States, the population of older adults in the criminal justice system is growing rapidly, but older prisoners' healthcare needs are not being sufficiently met.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Psick |first1=Zachary |last2=Simon |first2=Jonathan |last3=Brown |first3=Rebecca |last4=Ahalt |first4=Cyrus |date=2017-03-13 |title=Older and incarcerated: policy implications of aging prison populations |journal=International Journal of Prisoner Health |language=en |volume=13 |issue=1 |pages=57–63 |doi=10.1108/IJPH-09-2016-0053 |issn=1744-9200 |pmc=5812446 |pmid=28299972}}&lt;/ref&gt; One specific issue includes a lack of preparation for correctional officers to be able to identify geriatric disability.

Regarding that underrecognition of disability, further improvement is needed in training programs to allow officers to learn when and how to provide proper healthcare intervention and treatment for older adult prisoners.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Williams |first1=Brie A. |last2=Lindquist |first2=Karla |last3=Hill |first3=Terry |last4=Baillargeon |first4=Jacques |last5=Mellow |first5=Jeff |last6=Greifinger |first6=Robert |last7=Walter |first7=Louise C. |date=July 2009 |title=Caregiving Behind Bars: Correctional Officer Reports of Disability in Geriatric Prisoners: OFFICERS AND GERIATRIC PRISONER DISABILITY |url=https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/j.1532-5415.2009.02286.x |journal=Journal of the American Geriatrics Society |language=en |volume=57 |issue=7 |pages=1286–1292 |doi=10.1111/j.1532-5415.2009.02286.x|pmid=19582902 |s2cid=38602889 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Healthcare policy ===
Ableism has long been a serious concern in healthcare policy, and the COVID-19 pandemic has greatly exaggerated and highlighted the prevalence of this serious concern. Studies frequently show what a "headache" patients with disabilities are for the healthcare system. In a 2020 study, 83.6% of healthcare providers preferred patients without disabilities to those with disabilities.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |date=2021-11-08 |title=Ableism: Types, examples, impact, and anti-ableism |url=https://www.medicalnewstoday.com/articles/ableism |access-date=2022-04-18 |website=www.medicalnewstoday.com |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; This policy is especially concerning since according to the CDC, people with disabilities are at a heightened risk for contracting COVID-19.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=CDC |date=2021-10-26 |title=COVID-19 Information for People with Disabilities |url=https://www.cdc.gov/ncbddd/humandevelopment/covid-19/people-with-disabilities.html |access-date=2022-04-18 |website=Centers for Disease Control and Prevention |language=en-us}}&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, in the second wave of the COVID-19 pandemic in the UK, people with intellectual disabilities were told that they will not be resuscitated if they become ill with COVID-19.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |date=2021-02-13 |title=Fury at 'do not resuscitate' notices given to Covid patients with learning disabilities |url=http://www.theguardian.com/world/2021/feb/13/new-do-not-resuscitate-orders-imposed-on-covid-19-patients-with-learning-difficulties |access-date=2022-05-14 |website=the Guardian |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Education ==
Ableism often makes the world inaccessible to disabled people, especially in schools. Within education systems, the use of the [[medical model of disability]] and [[social model of disability]] contributes to the divide between students within [[special education]] and general education classrooms. Oftentimes, the medical model of disability portrays the overarching idea that disability can be corrected and diminished at the result of removing children from general education classrooms. This model of disability suggests that the impairment is more important than the person, who is helpless and should be separated from those who are not disabled.

The social model of disability suggests that people with impairments are disabled at the result of the way society acts. When students with disabilities are pulled out of their classrooms into receive the support that they need, that often leads their peers to socially reject them because they don't form relationships with them in the classroom. By using the social model of disability, inclusive schools where the social norm is not to alienate students can promote more teamwork and less division throughout their campuses.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite Q|Q109137763|author=Dolmage, Jay Timothy}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Implementing the social model within modern forms of inclusive education provides children of all abilities with the role of changing discriminatory attitudes within the school system. For example, a disabled student may need to read text instead of listening to a tape recording of the text. In the past, schools have focused on fixing the disability, but progressive reforms make schools now focused on minimizing the impact of a student's disability and giving support. Moreover, schools are required to maximize access to their entire community.&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{cite web |title=About IDEA - Individuals with Disabilities Education Act |url=https://sites.ed.gov/idea/about-idea/ |access-date=1 April 2019 |website=[[United States Department of Education]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2004, U.S. Congress made into law the [[Individuals with Disabilities Education Act]], which states that free and appropriate education is eligible to children with disabilities with insurance of necessary services.&lt;ref name=":2"&gt;{{cite web |title=Confronting Ableism{{snd}} Educational Leadership |url=http://www.ascd.org/publications/educational-leadership/feb07/vol64/num05/Confronting-Ableism.aspx |url-status=dead |access-date=1 April 2019 |website=[[Association for Supervision and Curriculum Development]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Congress later amended the law, in 2015, to include the [[Every Student Succeeds Act]], which guarantees equal opportunity for people with disabilities full participation in society, and the tools for overall independent success.

== Media ==
{{POV|date=May 2023}}
{{main|Disability in the media}}

These common ways of framing disability are heavily criticized for being dehumanizing and failing to place importance on the perspectives of disabled people.

=== Disabled villain ===
One common form of media depiction of disability is to portray villains with a mental or physical disability. Lindsey Row-Heyveld notes, for instance, "that villainous pirates are scraggly, wizened and inevitably kitted out with a peg leg, eye patch or hook hand, whereas heroic pirates look like [[Johnny Depp]]'s [[Jack Sparrow]]".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Row-Heyveld | first1 = Lindsey | year = 2015 | title = Reading Batman, Writing X-Men Superpowers and Disabilities in the First-Year Seminar | url = http://pedagogy.dukejournals.org/content/15/3/519.full.pdf | journal = Pedagogy: Critical Approaches to Teaching Literature, Language, Composition, and Culture | volume = 15| pages = 519–526| doi = 10.1215/15314200-2917105 | s2cid = 146299487 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The disability of the villain is meant to separate them from the average viewer and dehumanize the antagonist. As a result, stigma forms surrounding the disability and the individuals that live with it.

There are many instances in literature where the antagonist is depicted as having a disability or mental illness. Some common examples include [[Captain Hook]], [[Darth Vader]] and the [[Joker (character)|Joker]]. Captain Hook is notorious for having a hook as a hand and seeks revenge on [[Peter Pan]] for his lost hand. Darth Vader's situation is unique because [[Luke Skywalker]] is also disabled. Luke's prosthetic hand looks lifelike, whereas Darth Vader appears robotic and emotionless because his appearance does not resemble humans and takes away human emotions. The Joker is a villain with a mental illness, and he is an example of the typical depiction of associating mental illness with violence.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Misleading Media: Disabilities in Film and Television – UAB Institute for Human Rights Blog |url=https://sites.uab.edu/humanrights/2019/11/27/misleading-media-disabilities-in-film-and-television/ |access-date=2022-04-18 |website=sites.uab.edu}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Inspiration porn ===
[[File:070912 - Michelle Errichiello - 3b - 2012 Summer Paralympics (01).jpg|thumb|Australian Paralympic team member [[Michelle Errichiello]] (1024) at the [[2012 Summer Paralympics|2012 Summer Paralympic Games]] in London. Along with United States' Katy Sullivan (1418) and Germany's Vanessa Low (1181). Seen competing in the Women's 100-meter sprint.]]
[[Inspiration porn]] is the use of disabled people performing ordinary tasks as a form of inspiration.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Young|first=Stella|author-link=Stella Young|title=I'm not your inspiration, thank you very much|url=https://www.ted.com/talks/stella_young_i_m_not_your_inspiration_thank_you_very_much|language=en|access-date=2021-04-11|website=[[Ted Talk]]|date=9 June 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Criticisms of inspiration porn say that it distances disabled people from individuals who are not disabled and portrays disability as an obstacle to overcome or rehab.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last =Rakowitz|first= Rebecca|title = Inspiration porn: A look at the objectification of the disabled community |work= [[The Crimson White]]|publisher=[[University of Alabama]]|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20161202121955/https://cw.ua.edu/article/2016/12/inspiration-porn-a-look-at-the-objectification-of-the-disabled-community|archive-date=2 December 2016|date = 1 December 2016|url = https://cw.ua.edu/article/2016/12/inspiration-porn-a-look-at-the-objectification-of-the-disabled-community}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.huffpost.com/entry/on-inspiration-porn_b_596cedd0e4b05561da5a595e|title=On Inspiration Porn|date=July 17, 2017|website=[[HuffPost]]|first=Kate|last=Mitchell|access-date=5 March 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

One of the most common examples of inspiration porn includes the [[Paralympic Games|Paralympics]]. Athletes with disabilities often get praised as inspirational because of their athletic accomplishments. Critics of this type of inspiration porn have said, "athletic accomplishments by these athletes are oversimplified as 'inspirational' because they're such a surprise."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Athletes with disabilities are not 'inspiration porn' |url=https://www.sportsbusinessjournal.com/Journal/Issues/2021/08/23/Opinion/Tokyo-Paralympics.aspx |access-date=2022-04-18 |website=www.sportsbusinessjournal.com |date=23 August 2021 |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Pitied character ===
In many forms of media such as films and articles a disabled person is portrayed as a character who is viewed as less than able, different, and an "outcast." Hayes and Black (2003) explore Hollywood films as the discourse of pity towards disability as a problem of social, physical, and emotional confinement.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Hayes |first1=Michael |last2=Black |first2=Rhonda |title=Troubling Signs: Disability, Hollywood Movies and the Construction of a Discourse of Pity |journal=Disability Studies Quarterly |date=15 April 2003 |volume=23 |issue=2 |doi=10.18061/dsq.v23i2.419 |url=http://dsq-sds.org/article/view/419/585 |issn=2159-8371|doi-access=free }}&lt;/ref&gt; The aspect of pity is heightened through the storylines of media focusing on the individual's weaknesses as opposed to strengths and therefore leaving audiences a negative and ableist portrayal towards disability.

=== Supercrip stereotype ===
The supercrip narrative is generally a story of a person with an apparent disability who is able to "overcome" their physical differences and accomplish an impressive task. Professor Thomas Hehir's "Eliminating Ableism in Education" gives [[Erik Weihenmayer#Media and film appearances|the story of a blind man who climbs Mount Everest]], [[Erik Weihenmayer]], as an example of the supercrip narrative.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Hehir|first=Thomas|date=2002|title=Eliminating Ableism in Education|url=http://hepgjournals.org/doi/10.17763/haer.72.1.03866528702g2105|journal=[[Harvard Educational Review]]|language=en|volume=72|issue=1|pages=1–33|doi=10.17763/haer.72.1.03866528702g2105|issn=0017-8055}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Paralympic Games|Paralympics]] are another example of the supercrip stereotype since they generate a large amount of media attention and demonstrate disabled people doing extremely strenuous physical tasks. Although that may appear inspiring at face value, Hehir explains that many people with disabilities view those news stories as setting unrealistic expectations.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; Additionally, Hehir mentions that supercrip stories imply that disabled people are required to perform those impressive tasks to be seen as an equal and to avoid pity from those without disabilities.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

The disability studies scholar [[Alison Kafer]] describes how those narratives reinforce the problematic idea that disability can be overcome by an individual's hard work, in contrast to other theories, [[Social model of disability|which understand disability to be a result of a world that is not designed to be accessible]].&lt;ref name=":3"&gt;{{Cite book|last=Kafer|first=Alison|title=Feminist Queer Crip|publisher=Indiana University Press|year=2013|isbn=9780253009340|location=Bloomington|pages=129–148|language=English}}&lt;/ref&gt; Supercrip stories reinforce ableism by emphasizing independence, reliance on one's body, and the role of individual will in self-cure.&lt;ref name=":4"&gt;{{Cite book|last=Ray|first=Sarah Jaquette|title=The Ecological Other: Environmental Exclusion in American Culture|publisher=The University of Arizona Press|year=2013|isbn=9780816511884|location=Tucson|pages=1–82|language=English}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Other examples of the supercrip narrative include the stories of [[Rachael Scdoris]], the first blind woman to race in the Iditarod, and [[Aron Ralston]], who has continued to climb after the amputation of his arm.&lt;ref name=":4"/&gt;

=== Environmental and outdoor recreation media ===
Disability has often been used as a short-hand in environmental literature for representing distance from nature, in what Sarah Jaquette Ray calls the "disability-equals-alienation-from-nature trope."&lt;ref name=":4"/&gt; An example of this trope can be seen in ''[[Moby-Dick|Moby Dick]]'', as [[Captain Ahab]]'s lost leg symbolizes his exploitative relationship with nature.&lt;ref name=":4"/&gt; Additionally, in canonical environmental thought, figures such as [[Ralph Waldo Emerson]] and [[Edward Abbey]] wrote using metaphors of disability to describe relationships between nature, technology, and the individual.&lt;ref name=":4"/&gt;&lt;ref name=":3"/&gt;

Ableism in outdoor media can also be seen in promotional materials from the [[outdoor recreation]] industry: [[Alison Kafer]] highlighted a 2000 [[Nike, Inc.|Nike]] advertisement, which ran in eleven outdoor magazines promoting a pair of running shoes.&lt;ref name=":3"/&gt; Kafer alleged that the advertisement depicted a person with a [[spinal cord injury]] and a wheelchair user as a "drooling, misshapen, non-extreme-trail-running husk of [their] former self",&lt;ref name=":5" /&gt; and said that the advertisement promised non-disabled runners and hikers the ability to protect their bodies against disability by purchasing the pair of shoes.&lt;ref name=":3"/&gt; The advertisement was withdrawn after the company received over six hundred complaints in the first two days after its publication, and Nike apologized.&lt;ref name=":3"/&gt;&lt;ref name=":5"&gt;{{Cite news|last=Street Journal|first=Ann Grimes Staff Reporter of The Wall|date=2000-10-26|title=Nike Rescinds Advertisement, Apologizes to Disabled People|work=[[The Wall Street Journal]]|url=https://www.wsj.com/articles/SB972514389588597858|access-date=2022-01-23|issn=0099-9660}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Types of ableism ==
* Physical ableism is hate or discrimination based on physical disability.
* [[Sanism]], or mental ableism, is discrimination based on mental health conditions and cognitive disabilities.
* Medical ableism exists both interpersonally (as healthcare providers can be ableist) and systemically, as decisions determined by medical institutions and caregivers may prevent the exercise of rights from disabled patients like autonomy and making decisions. The [[medical model of disability]] can be used to justify medical ableism.
* Structural ableism is failing to provide accessibility tools: ramps, wheelchairs, special education equipments, etc.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://drc.arizona.edu/cultural-center/ableism-101-part-one-what-ableism-what-disability |title=Ableism 101 Part One: What is Ableism? What is Disability? &amp;#124; Disability Resources |website=University of Arizona | department=Disability Resource Center | location=Tucson | date=January 22, 2020 | archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20210923210654/https://drc.arizona.edu/cultural-center/ableism-101-part-one-what-ableism-what-disability  | archive-date=September 23, 2021 |access-date=10 January 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt; (Which is often also an example of [[Hostile architecture]].)
* Cultural ableism is behavioural, cultural, attitudinal and social patterns that may discriminate against disabled people, including by denying, dismissing or invisibilising disabled people, and by making accessibility and support unattainable.
* [[Internalised ableism]] is a disabled person discriminating against themself and other disabled people by holding the view that disability is something to be ashamed of or something to hide or by refusing accessibility or support. Internalised ableism may be a result of mistreatment of disabled individuals.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |chapter-url=https://doi.org/10.1057/9780230245181_2 |chapter=Internalised Ableism: The Tyranny Within |first=Fiona Kumari |last=Campbell |title=Contours of Ableism |date=2009 |publisher=Palgrave Macmillan UK |pages=16–29 |via=[[Springer-Link]] |doi=10.1057/9780230245181_2 |isbn=978-1-349-36790-0 |access-date=10 January 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Hostile ableism is a cultural or social kind of ableism where people are hostile towards symptoms of a disability or phenotypes of the disabled person.
* Benevolent ableism is when people treat the disabled person well but like a child ([[infantilization]]), instead of considering them full grown adults. Examples include ignoring disabilities (such as the [[RNIB]]'s "See the person" campaign&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www.rnib.org.uk/our-campaigns/see-differently-see-the-person |title=See the person, not the sight loss |access-date=29 October 2024}}&lt;/ref&gt;), not respecting the life experiences of the disabled person, [[microaggression]], not considering the opinion of the disabled person in important decision making, invasion of privacy or personal boundaries, forced corrective measures, unwanted help, not listening to the disabled person, etc.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |url=https://spssi.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1111/josi.12337 |title=Hostile, Benevolent, and Ambivalent Ableism: Contemporary Manifestations |first1=Michelle R. |last1=Nario-Redmond |first2=Alexia A. |last2=Kemerling |first3=Arielle |last3=Silverman |date=10 June 2019 |journal=[[Journal of Social Issues]] |volume=75 |issue=3 |pages=726–756 |via=Wiley Online Library |doi=10.1111/josi.12337 |s2cid=197736429 |access-date=10 January 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Ambivalent ableism can be characterized as somewhere in between hostile and benevolent ableism.

==Causes of ableism==
Ableism may have evolutionary and existential origins (fear of contagion, fear of death). It may also be rooted in belief systems ([[social Darwinism]], [[meritocracy]]), language (such as "suffering from" disability), or unconscious biases.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Disability Prejudice: Causes, Consequences, and Implications for Policymakers |url=https://www.spssi.org/index.cfm?fuseaction=document.viewdocument&amp;ID=3F28EB86AE4CA3BB2EE025BE0093BF0439AD904BE63A1C0C2BE50463F70F3B668A419D9A5BFC2C3737450814D3839CB6#:~:text=Ableism%20may%20have%20evolutionary%20and,disability)%2C%20and%20unconscious%20biases. | archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20211104215242/https://www.spssi.org/index.cfm?fuseaction=document.viewdocument&amp;ID=3F28EB86AE4CA3BB2EE025BE0093BF0439AD904BE63A1C0C2BE50463F70F3B668A419D9A5BFC2C3737450814D3839CB6 | archive-date=November 4, 2021 |date=December 2, 2019 |publisher=[[Society for the Psychological Study of Social Issues]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
{{Portal|Politics|Society}}
*[[Disability abuse]]
*[[Disability and poverty]]
*[[Disability hate crime]]
*[[Disability rights movement]]
*[[Inclusion (disability rights)]]
*[[Mentalism (discrimination)]]
*[[Medical–industrial complex|Medical industrial complex]]
*[[Violent behavior in autistic people]]
*[[Violence against people with disabilities]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

== Further reading ==
* {{cite book|last1=Adams|first1=Rachel |last2= Reiss|first2=Benjamin|last3=Serlin|first3=David |title=Keywords for Disability Studies|year=2015|publisher=NYU Press|isbn=978-1-4798-4115-8}}
* {{cite journal |last1=Amundson |first1=Ron |first2=Gayle |last2=Taira |title=Our Lives and Ideologies: The Effects of Life Experience on the Perceived Morality of the Policy of Physician-Assisted Suicide |journal=Journal of Policy Studies |volume=16 |issue=1 |year=2005 |pages=53&amp;ndash;57 |url=http://uhh.hawaii.edu./~ronald/pubs/2005-Amundson-Taira.pdf |doi=10.1177/10442073050160010801 |s2cid=143674103 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20101228114850/http://www.uhh.hawaii.edu/~ronald/pubs/2005-Amundson-Taira.pdf |archive-date=2010-12-28}}
* {{cite journal |first=Fiona A. Kumari|last=Campbell |year=2001 |title=Inciting Legal Fictions: Disability's Date with Ontology and the Ableist Body of the Law |url=https://core.ac.uk/download/pdf/143871776.pdf |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190412150956/https://core.ac.uk/download/pdf/143871776.pdf |archive-date=2019-04-12 |journal=Griffith Law Review |volume=10 |issue=1 |pages=42&amp;ndash;62}}
* {{cite journal |url=http://journal.media-culture.org.au/index.php/mcjournal/article/viewArticle/46/0 |journal=M/C Journal |volume=11|issue=3 |year=2008 |title=Refusing Able(ness): A Preliminary Conversation about Ableism |first=Fiona A. Kumari|last=Campbell |doi=10.5204/mcj.46 |doi-access=free|hdl=10072/21384 |hdl-access=free }}
* {{cite book |title=Contours of Ableism: The Production of Disability and Abledness |first=Fiona A. Kumari|last=Campbell |publisher=Palgrave Macmillan |year=2009 |isbn=978-0-230-57928-6}}
* {{cite journal |last=Chouinard|first=Vera |title=Making Space for Disabling Difference: Challenges Ableist Geographies |journal=Environment and Planning D: Society and Space |volume=15 |year=1997 |pages=379&amp;ndash;387 |doi=10.1068/d150379|s2cid=220082865|doi-access=free }}
* {{cite journal |last=Clear|first=Mike |title=The "Normal" and the Monstrous in Disability Research |journal=Disability &amp; Society |issn=0968-7599 |lccn=2007233711 |oclc=808984972 |publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis |volume=14|issue=4 |year=1999 |pages=435&amp;ndash;448 |doi=10.1080/09687599926055}}
* Fandrey, Walter: Krüppel, Idioten, Irre: zur Sozialgeschichte behinderter Menschen in Deutschland (Cripples, idiots, madmen: the social history of disabled people in Germany) {{in lang|de}} {{ISBN|978-3-925344-71-8}}
* {{cite book |title=Teaching for diversity and social justice |chapter-url= https://archive.org/details/teachingfordiver0000unse_j5k6/page/334/mode/2up?q=griffin |volume=1 |page= 335 |editor1-first=Maurianne|editor1-last=Adams |editor2-first=Lee Anne|editor2-last=Bell |editor3-first=Pat|editor3-last=Griffin |chapter=Ableism Curriculum Design |first1=Pat|last1=Griffin |first2=Madelaine L.|last2=Peters |first3=Robin M.|last3=Smith |edition=2nd |location=New York |publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis |url=https://archive.org/details/teachingfordiver0000unse_j5k6 |year=2007 |oclc =982668098 |isbn=978-0-415-95199-9}}
* {{cite book |chapter=Eliminating Ableism in Education |first=Thomas|last=Hehir |title=Special education for a new century |chapter-url=https://archive.org/details/specialeducation0000unse_f1t7/page/10/mode/2up?q=hehir |page=10 |volume=41 |series=Harvard educational review |editor1-first=Lauren I.|editor1-last=Katzman |publisher=Harvard Educational Review |year=2005 |oclc= 59553489 |isbn= 978-0-916690-44-1}}
* {{cite journal |last1=Iwasaki |first1=Yoshitaka |first2=Jennifer|last2=Mactavish |title=Ubiquitous Yet Unique: Perspectives of People with Disabilities on Stress |journal=Rehabilitation Counseling Bulletin |volume=48 |issue=4 |year=2005 |pages=194&amp;ndash;208 |doi=10.1177/00343552050480040101 |s2cid=144891563}}
* {{cite book |title=The School Counselor's Guide to Helping Students with Disabilities |series=Jossey-Bass teacher |first1=Laura E. |last1=Marshak |first2=Claire J.|last2=Dandeneau |first3=Fran P. |last3=Prezant |first4=Nadene A. |last4=L'Amoreaux |publisher=John Wiley and Sons |year=2009 |isbn=978-0-470-17579-8}}
* Schweik, Susan. (2009). [https://archive.org/details/uglylawsdisabili0000schw/mode/2up ''The Ugly Laws: Disability in Public'' (History of Disability)]. NYU Press.{{oclc|844342243}} {{JSTOR|j.ctt9qgf13}} {{ISBN|9780814740576}}
* Shaver, James P. (1981). [https://archive.org/details/handicapismequal0000shav Handicapism and Equal Opportunity: Teaching About the Disabled in Social Studies]. [[Library of Congress]] Card Catalog Number 80-70737 [[ERIC]] Number: ED202185 {{ISBN|978-0-939068-01-2}}
* {{Cite Q|Q56673362 |last1=Watts|first1=Ivan Eugene |first2=Nirmala |last2=Erevelles |jstor=3699367 |doi=10.3102/00028312041002271 |s2cid=144121049}}

==External links==
{{Wiktionary|ableism}}
{{Wiktionary|Wikisaurus:ableism}}
* [https://www.demos.co.uk/files/disablism.pdf Disablism: How to tackle the last prejudice] by [[Demos (UK think tank)|DEMOS]] (2004)
* {{cite web |title=Voting Accessibility |url=https://www.eac.gov/voters/voting-accessibility |publisher=U.S. Election Assistance Commission |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20220625190819/https://www.eac.gov/voters/voting-accessibility |archive-date=June 25, 2022 |date=2022}}
* {{cite news |title=Voters with disabilities face discrimination nationwide |url=http://www.raggededgemagazine.com/1100/1100votestory.htm |work=Ragged Edge |agency=Disability Rights Nation |date=2000 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20001212025400/http://www.raggededgemagazine.com/1100/1100votestory.htm |archive-date=December 12, 2000}}

{{Disability navbox|state=collapsed}}
{{Discrimination}}
{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Ableism| ]]
[[Category:Social theories]]
[[Category:Social concepts]]
[[Category:Prejudice and discrimination by type]]
[[Category:Disability rights]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>