<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20110715225927|439696240" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="4611451" pageid="4611451" ns="0" title="Gender nonconformity"><revisions><rev timestamp="2011-08-22T03:48:29Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Merge from|Atypical gender role|date=July 2010}}

'''Gender variance''', or '''gender nonconformity''', is behaviour or [[gender expression]] that does not conform to dominant [[gender norms]] of male and female.  People who exhibit gender variance may be called "gender variant", "gender non-conforming", or "gender atypical".&lt;ref&gt;Douglas C. Halderman (2000), ''Gender Atypical Youth: Clinical and Social Issues.'' School Psychology Review, v29 n2 p192-200 2000&lt;/ref&gt;

==Terminology==
The terms "gender variance" and "gender variant" are used by scholars of [[psychology]]&lt;ref&gt;Lynne Carroll, Paula J. Gilroy, Jo Ryan (2002), ''Counseling Transgendered, Transsexual, and Gender-Variant Clients'', Journal of Counseling &amp; Development, Volume 80, Number 2, Spring 2002, pp. 131 - 139&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Arlene Istar Lev, (2004) ''Transgender Emergence: Therapeutic Guidelines for Working With Gender-Variant People and Their Families.'' Haworth Press,  ISBN 9780789007087&lt;/ref&gt; and [[psychiatry]],&lt;ref&gt;Walter O. Bockting, Randall D. Ehrbar (2006), "Commentary: Gender Variance, Dissonance, or Identity Disorder?'' pp. 125 - 134 in "Sexual and Gender Diagnoses of the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual (DSM): A reevaluation'' edited by [[Dan Karasic]] and [[Jack Drescher]], 2006, Haworth Press, ISBN 0789032147 NB: Several articles in this book use the term "gender variance".&lt;/ref&gt; [[anthropology]],&lt;ref&gt;Serena Nanda (2000) ''Gender Diversity: Crosscultural Variations'', Illinois: Waveland Press, Inc., 2000 ISBN 157766 0749  NB: Nanda uses the term "gender variance" to encompass gender phenomena in different cultures.&lt;/ref&gt; and [[gender studies]], as well as advocacy groups of gender variant people themselves.&lt;ref&gt;"Gender Education and Advocacy (GEA) is a national [US] organization focused on the needs, issues and concerns of gender variant people in human society." Mission statement, available on the front page of the group's website: www.gender.org&lt;/ref&gt; 
The term "gender-variant" is deliberately broad, encompassing such specific terms as [[transsexual]], [[Butch and femme|butch]], [[Drag queen|queen]], [[sissy]], [[travesti]], [[Hijra (South Asia)|hijra]] or [[tomboy]].

The term "[[transgender]]" is sometimes used interchangeably with the term "gender-variant",&lt;ref&gt;After defining transgender as  primarily "an umbrella term to describe those who defy societal expectations and assumptions regarding femaleness and maleness" including people who are transsexual, intersexual or [[genderqueer]], as well as [[cross-dressing|crossdressers]], [[drag (clothing)|drag performers]], masculine women and feminine men, Serano goes on to state: "I will also sometimes use the synonymous term ''gender-variant'' to describe all people who are considered by others to deviate from societal norms of femaleness and maleness". (p. 25), Serano, Julia (2007), ''Whipping Girl: A Transsexual Woman on Sexism and the Scapegoating of Femininity,'' Seal Press, 2007. ISBN 978-1-58005-154-5, ISBN 1-58005-154-5&lt;/ref&gt; but usually has a narrower meaning and somewhat different connotations, including a non-identification with the [[sex assignment|gender assigned at birth]]. The Gay and Lesbian Alliance Against Defamation Media Reference Guide defines transgender as an "umbrella term for people whose gender identity and/or gender expression differs from the sex they were assigned at birth."&lt;ref&gt;Gay and Lesbian Alliance Against Defamation. [http://www.glaad.org/reference/transgender ‘’GLAAD Media Reference Guide, 8th Edition. Transgender Glossary of Terms”], ‘’[[GLAAD]]’’, USA, May 2010. Retrieved on 2011-03-02.&lt;/ref&gt; Not all gender variant people identify as transgender, and not all transgender people identify as gender variant--many identify simply as men or women.

Gender identity refers to one's internal sense of being male, female, both, or neither. Gender expression is the external manifestation of one's gender identity, usually through "masculine," "feminine," or gender variant presentation and/or behavior.&lt;ref&gt;Gay and Lesbian Alliance Against Defamation. [http://www.glaad.org/reference/transgender ‘’GLAAD Media Reference Guide, 8th Edition. Transgender Glossary of Terms”], ‘’[[GLAAD]]’’, USA, May 2010. Retrieved on 2011-03-02.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Childhood gender variance==
{{Main|Childhood gender nonconformity}}

Multiple studies have suggested a correlation between children who express gender non-conformity and their eventually coming out as [[homosexuality|gay, bisexual]] or [[transgender]].&lt;ref name="Friedman 2008" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Baumeister"&gt;{{cite book|last=Baumeister|first=Roy F.|title=Social Psychology and Human Sexuality: Essential Readings|year=2001|publisher=Psychology Press|isbn=978-1841690186|pages=201–2|url=http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=roychiRaM8gC&amp;pg=PA202&amp;dq=%22Childhood+Gender+Nonconformity%22&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=n0k4TNzJD4PQsAPOtqBR&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=3&amp;ved=0CDUQ6AEwAg#v=onepage&amp;q=%22Childhood%20Gender%20Nonconformity%22&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt; In some studies, a majority of those who identify as [[gay]] or [[lesbian]] self-report gender non-conformity as children. However, the accuracy of these studies have been questioned, especially within the academic community.&lt;ref name="Brookley"&gt;{{cite book|last=Brookley|first=Robert|title=Reinventing the Male Homosexual: The Rhetoric and Power of the Gay Gene|year=2002|publisher=Indiana University Press|isbn=978-0253340573|pages=60–65|url=http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=bZrXrqaDfwoC&amp;pg=PT54&amp;dq="Childhood+Gender+Nonconformity"&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=n0k4TNzJD4PQsAPOtqBR&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=5&amp;ved=0CD8Q66-}}&lt;/ref&gt; The therapeutic community is currently divided on the proper response to childhood gender non-conformity. One study suggested that childhood gender non-conformity is [[heritable]].&lt;ref name="Friedman 2008"&gt;{{cite book|last=Friedman |first=RC|title=Sexual Orientation and Psychodynamic Psychotherapy Sexual Science and Clinical Practice |year=2008|publisher=Columbia University Press |isbn=978-0231120579|pages=53–7|url=http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=mwtokhymV_4C&amp;pg=PA53&amp;dq=%22Childhood+Gender+Nonconformity%22&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=n0k4TNzJD4PQsAPOtqBR&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=4&amp;ved=0CDoQ6AEwAw#v=onepage&amp;q=%22Childhood%20Gender%20Nonconformity%22&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Social status for men vs. women==
{{Unreferenced section|date=July 2010}}
Gender nonconformity among males is usually more sensitively and violently [[gender policing|policed]] than is nonconformity in females. Many theorists believe this is because femaleness is inherently devalued in a [[patriarchy|patriarchal]] society, therefore a male seeking to be more feminine is actively reducing his [[social status]], yet a woman acting in a masculine way is tolerated and encouraged because her social status will be enhanced by the addition of the valuable attributes of maleness (e.g. physical power, assertiveness, ambition). The deep social pressure for those traditionally viewed as "male" to be masculine can be seen in the especially high levels of violence against transgender women.&lt;ref&gt;Gay and Lesbian Alliance Against Defamation. [http://glaadblog.org/2010/11/19/transgender-day-of-remembrance-honoring-the-lives-lost/ “Transgender Day of Remembrance: Honoring the Lives Lost”], ‘’GLAAD’’, USA, November 19, 2010. Retrieved on 2011-03-02.&lt;/ref&gt;

A fear of being labeled gay or feminine causes many men to overtly reject and devalue such gender non-conforming behaviours, even prosocial ones such as caring for another individual and emotional communication. Some researchers have suggested this self-suppression has a negative impact on men's [[mental health]]. As with female gender nonconformity, gay men may find it easier to reject traditional masculinity because the price for doing so has already been paid by being gay.

==Association with sexual orientation==
Behaviour such as expression of emotion, an inclination toward caring for and nurturing others, an interest in cooking or other domestic chores, self-grooming, and a desire to care for children are all aspects of male gender non-conformity. Men who exhibit such tendencies are often stereotyped as gay. One study did find a high incidence of gay males self-reporting gender-atypical behaviors in childhood, such as having little interest in athletics and rather playing with [[doll]]s.&lt;ref name="Bailey"&gt;[[J. Michael Bailey]], Joseph S. Miller, Lee Willerman; Maternally Rated Childhood Gender Nonconformity in Homosexuals and Heterosexuals, Archives of Sexual Behavior, Vol. 22, 1993.&lt;/ref&gt;  The same study found that mothers of gay males recalled such atypical behavior in their sons with greater frequency than mothers of heterosexual males.&lt;ref name="Bailey"/&gt; But while many gay and/or bisexual men exhibit traditionally feminine characteristics, many of them do not, and not all feminine men are necessarily gay or bisexual.

For women, adult gender non-conformity is often associated with lesbianism due to the limited identities women are faced with at adulthood. Notions of heterosexual womanhood often require a rejection of physically demanding activities, social submission to a male figure (husband or boyfriend), an interest in reproduction and homemaking, and an interest in making oneself look more attractive with appropriate clothing, make-up, hair styles and body shape. A rejection of any of these factors may lead to a woman being called a lesbian regardless of her actual sexual orientation. Therefore, attracting a male romantic or sexual partner can be a strong factor for an adult woman to suppress or reject her own desire to be gender variant. Lesbian and bisexual women, being less concerned with attracting men, may find it easier to reject traditional ideals of womanhood because social punishment for such transgression is not effective, or at least no more effective than the consequences of being openly gay or bisexual in a heteronormative society (which they already experience). This may help account for high levels of gender nonconformity self-reported by lesbians.

==Clothing==
{{Unreferenced section|date=July 2010}}
Among adults, the wearing of [[women's clothing]] by men is often socially stigmatized and [[sexual fetishism|fetishised]], or viewed as sexually abnormal. Yet, cross dressing is simply a form of gender expression and is not necessarily related to erotic activity. It is also not indicative of sexual orientation.&lt;ref&gt;Gay and Lesbian Alliance Against Defamation. [http://www.glaad.org/reference/transgender ‘’GLAAD Media Reference Guide, 8th Edition. Transgender Glossary of Terms”], ‘’[[GLAAD]]’’, USA, May 2010. Retrieved on 2011-03-01.&lt;/ref&gt; Other gender nonconforming males prefer to simply modify and stylise men's clothing as an expression of their interest in appearance and [[fashion]].

==See also==
* [[Atypical gender role]]
* [[Third gender]]
* [[Genderqueer]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

[[Category:Androgyny]]
[[Category:Genderqueer]]
[[Category:Gender studies]]
[[Category:Transgender]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>