<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20201029052725|985997096" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="4611451" pageid="4611451" ns="0" title="Gender nonconformity"><revisions><rev timestamp="2020-11-26T00:00:41Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Behavior by an individual that does not match masculine or feminine gender norms}}
{{Transgender sidebar}}
{{LGBT sidebar}}
'''Gender variance''', or '''gender nonconformity''', is behavior or [[gender expression]] by an individual that does not match masculine or feminine [[gender norms]]. People who exhibit gender variance may be called ''gender-variant'', ''gender-non-conforming'', ''gender-diverse,'' ''gender-atypical''{{thin space}}&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Haldeman |first=Douglas C. |date=2000-01-01 |title=Gender Atypical Youth: Clinical and Social Issues |url=https://www.researchgate.net/publication/254744524 |journal=School Psychology Review |volume=29 |issue=2 |pages=192–200|doi=10.1080/02796015.2000.12086007 |s2cid=142509837 }}&lt;/ref&gt; or ''[[non-binary]]'', and may be [[transgender]] or otherwise variant in their [[gender identity]]. In the case of transgender people, they may be perceived, or perceive themselves as, gender-nonconforming before transitioning, but might not be perceived as such after transitioning. Some [[intersex]] people may also exhibit gender variance.

==Terminology==

The terms ''gender variance'' and ''gender-variant'' are used by scholars of [[psychology]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Carroll |first1=Lynne |last2=Gilroy |first2=Paula J. |last3=Ryan |first3=Jo |date=2002 |title=Counseling Transgendered, Transsexual, and Gender-Variant Clients |journal=Journal of Counseling &amp; Development |volume=80 |issue=2 |pages=131–139 |doi=10.1002/j.1556-6678.2002.tb00175.x |issn=0748-9633}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |title=Transgender Emergence: Therapeutic Guidelines for Working with Gender-Variant People and their Families |last=Lev |first=Arlene Istar |authorlink=Arlene Istar Lev |date=2004 |publisher=The Haworth Clinical Practice Press |isbn=978-0789007087 |location=New York |oclc=51342468}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Stitt"&gt;{{Cite book |title=ACT For Gender Identity: The Comprehensive Guide |last=Stitt |first=Alex |date=2020 |publisher=Jessica Kingsley Publishers |isbn=978-1785927997 |location=London |oclc=1089850112}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[psychiatry]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |title=Sexual and gender diagnoses of the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual (DSM) : a reevaluation |date=2005 |publisher=Haworth Press |isbn=978-0789032133 |editor-last=Karasic |editor-first=Dan |location=New York |pages=125–134 |oclc=61859826 |editor-last2=Drescher |editor-first2=Jack}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[anthropology]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |title=Gender diversity: crosscultural variations |last=Nanda |first=Serena |author-link=Serena Nanda |publisher=Waveland Press, Inc. |year=2000 |isbn=978-1577660743 |location=Prospect Heights, Ill. |oclc=43190536 |url-access=registration |url=https://archive.org/details/genderdiversityc00nand_0}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[gender studies]], as well as advocacy groups of gender-variant people themselves.&lt;ref&gt;"Gender Education and Advocacy (GEA) is a national [US] organization focused on the needs, issues and concerns of gender-variant people in human society." Mission statement, available on the front page of the group's website: www.gender.org&lt;/ref&gt; The term ''gender-variant'' is deliberately broad, encompassing such specific terms as ''[[transsexual]]'', [[Butch and femme|''butch'' and ''femme'']], ''[[Drag queen|queen]]'', ''[[sissy]]'', ''[[tomboy]]'', ''[[Travesti (gender identity)|travesti]]'', or ''[[Hijra (South Asia)|hijra]]''. 

The word ''[[transgender]]'' usually has a narrower meaning and different connotations, including an identification that differs from the [[sex assignment|gender assigned at birth]]. [[GLAAD]] (formerly the Gay and Lesbian Alliance Against Defamation)'s Media Reference Guide defines ''transgender'' as an "umbrella term for people whose gender identity or gender expression differs from the sex they were assigned at birth."&lt;ref name="GLAAD"&gt;Gay and Lesbian Alliance Against Defamation. [http://www.glaad.org/reference/transgender ''GLAAD Media Reference Guide, 8th Edition. Transgender Glossary of Terms"], ''[[GLAAD]]'', USA, May 2010. Retrieved on 2011-03-02.&lt;/ref&gt; Not all gender-variant people identify as transgender, and not all transgender people identify as gender-variant—many identify simply as men or women.&lt;ref name="Stitt" /&gt; [[Gender identity]] is one's internal sense of their own [[gender]]; while most people have a gender identity of a boy or a man, or a girl or a woman, gender identity for other people is a more complex experience. 

Furthermore, gender expression is the external manifestation of one's gender identity, usually through "masculine", "feminine", or gender-variant presentation or behavior.&lt;ref name="GLAAD" /&gt;

In some countries, such as Australia, the term ''gender diverse'' or, historically, ''sex and/or gender diverse'', may be used in place of, or as well as, ''transgender''.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=Department of Health, Victoria, Australia |title=Transgender and gender diverse health and wellbeing |date=9 October 2014 |url=http://docs.health.vic.gov.au/docs/doc/Transgender-and-gender-diverse-health-and-wellbeing |accessdate=2014-12-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="lgbtiall" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=[[Australian Human Rights Commission]] |title=New Protection |date=1 August 2013 |url=http://www.humanrights.gov.au/new-protection |accessdate=2014-12-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Winter"&gt;{{cite journal |last=Winter |first=Sarah |title=Are human rights capable of liberation? The case of sex and gender diversity |journal=Australian Journal of Human Rights |year=2009 |volume=15 |issue=1 |pages=151–174 |url=http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/journals/AJHR/2009/13.pdf |accessdate=23 December 2011 |doi=10.1080/1323238X.2009.11910865|s2cid=158873691 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Culturally-specific gender diverse terms include ''sistergirls'' and ''brotherboys''.&lt;ref name="lgbtiguide" /&gt; Ambiguities about the inclusion or exclusion of [[intersex]] people in terminology, such as ''sex and/or gender diverse'', led to a decline in use of the terms ''sex and/or gender diverse'' and ''Diverse Sexes and Genders'' (DSG).&lt;ref name="lgbtiall"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://lgbtihealth.org.au/diversity |title=National LGBTI Health Alliance statement |last1=National LGBTI Health Alliance |date=2013 |publisher=[[National LGBTI Health Alliance]] |accessdate=2014-12-31|author1-link=National LGBTI Health Alliance }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="oiisgd"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://oii.org.au/21550/sex-and-gender-diverse-discussion-paper/ |title="Sex and Gender Diverse" discussion paper on terminology |last1=Organisation Intersex International Australia |date=9 January 2013 |publisher=[[Organisation Intersex International Australia]] |accessdate=2014-12-31|author1-link=Organisation Intersex International Australia }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="fpv"&gt;[http://www.fpv.org.au/assets/Family-Planning-Submission-re-ABS-gender_2.pdf Family Planning Victoria, February 2013, "ABS review of the sex standard / potential new gender standard, A submission by Family Planning Victoria in collaboration with Gay and Lesbian Health Victoria, [[Transgender Victoria]], Y Gender and the Zoe Belle Gender Centre"]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="tgv"&gt;[http://www.transgendervictoria.com/news/media/item/review-of-abs-standard-welcome Transgendervictoria.com] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20181226092813/https://transgendervictoria.com/news/media/item/review-of-abs-standard-welcome |date=2018-12-26}}, [[Transgender Victoria]]&lt;span&gt;, February 2013, "Review of ABS Standard Welcome"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; Current regulations providing for the recognition of trans and other gender identities use terms such as ''gender diverse'' and ''transgender''.&lt;ref name="agrecog"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ag.gov.au/Publications/Pages/AustralianGovernmentGuidelinesontheRecognitionofSexandGender.aspx |title=Australian Government Guidelines on the Recognition of Sex and Gender |last1=Attorney-General's Department (Australia) |date=June 2013 |publisher=[[Attorney-General's Department (Australia)]] |accessdate=2014-12-31|author1-link=Attorney-General's Department (Australia) }}]&lt;/ref&gt; In July 2013, the Australian [[National LGBTI Health Alliance]] produced a guide entitled "Inclusive Language Guide: Respecting people of intersex, trans and gender diverse experience" which clearly distinguishes between different bodily and identity groups.&lt;ref name="lgbtiguide"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://lgbtihealth.org.au/sites/default/files/Alliance%20Health%20Information%20Sheet%20Inclusive%20Language%20Guide%20on%20Intersex%2C%20Trans%20and%20Gender%20Diversity_0.pdf |title=Inclusive Language Guide: Respecting people of intersex, trans and gender diverse experience |last1=National LGBTI Health Alliance |date=July 2013 |publisher=[[National LGBTI Health Alliance]] |accessdate=2014-12-31|author1-link=National LGBTI Health Alliance }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==In childhood==
{{Main|Childhood gender nonconformity}}

Multiple studies have suggested a correlation between children who express gender nonconformity and their eventually coming out as [[homosexuality|gay]], [[bisexual]], or [[transgender]].&lt;ref name="Friedman 2008" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Baumeister"&gt;{{cite book |last=Baumeister |first=Roy F. |title=Social Psychology and Human Sexuality: Essential Readings |year=2001 |publisher=Psychology Press |isbn=978-1-84169-018-6 |pages=201–2 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=roychiRaM8gC&amp;q=%22Childhood+Gender+Nonconformity%22&amp;pg=PA202}}&lt;/ref&gt; In multiple studies, a majority of those who identify as gay or [[lesbian]] self-report gender nonconformity as children.&lt;ref name="Friedman 2008" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Baumeister" /&gt; However, the accuracy of some of these studies have been questioned.&lt;ref name="Brookley"&gt;{{cite book |last=Brookley |first=Robert |title=Reinventing the Male Homosexual: The Rhetoric and Power of the Gay Gene |year=2002 |publisher=Indiana University Press |isbn=978-0-253-34057-3 |pages=60–65 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=bZrXrqaDfwoC&amp;pg=PT54}}&lt;/ref&gt; The therapeutic community is currently divided on the proper response to childhood gender nonconformity.

One study suggested that childhood gender nonconformity is [[heritable]].&lt;ref name="Friedman 2008"&gt;{{cite book |last=Friedman |first=RC |title=Sexual Orientation and Psychodynamic Psychotherapy Sexual Science and Clinical Practice |year=2008 |publisher=Columbia University Press |isbn=978-0-231-12057-9 |pages=53–7 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=mwtokhymV_4C&amp;q=%22Childhood+Gender+Nonconformity%22&amp;pg=PA53}}&lt;/ref&gt; Studies have also been conducted about adults' attitudes towards nonconforming children. There are reportedly no significant generalized effects (with the exception of few outliers) on attitudes towards children who vary in gender traits, interests, and behavior.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |doi=10.1007/s10508-012-0023-7 |pmid=23150102 |title=Adults' Attitudes About Gender Nonconformity in Childhood |journal=Archives of Sexual Behavior |volume=42 |issue=3 |pages=399–412 |year=2013 |last1=Thomas |first1=Rachel N. |last2=Blakemore |first2=Judith E. Owen|s2cid=22230241 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Children who are gender-variant may struggle to conform later in life. As children get older and are not treated for the mismatch between their minds and bodily appearance, this leads to discomfort, and negative self-image and eventually may lead to [[Depression (mood)|depression]], [[suicide]], or [[self-doubt]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.apa.org/monitor/sep03/children.aspx |title=Understanding children's atypical gender behavior |last=Crawford |first=Nicole |date=2003 |website=American Psychological Association}}&lt;/ref&gt; If a child is nonconforming at a very young age, it is important to provide family support for positive impact to family and the child.&lt;ref&gt;Peate, I. (January 01, 2008). Understanding key issues in gender-variant children and young people. British Journal of Nursing (mark Allen Publishing), 17, 17, 25&lt;/ref&gt; Children who do not conform prior to age 11 tend to have an increased risk for depression, anxiety, and suicidal ideation as a young adult.&lt;ref name="Roberts, A. 2013"&gt;Roberts, A., Rosario, M., Slopen, N., et al. (2013). Childhood gender nonconformity, bullying victimization, and depressive symptoms across adolescence and early adulthood: an 11-year longitudinal study. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry, 52(2): 143-152&lt;/ref&gt; A 2012 study found that both children who will be heterosexual and children who will have a minority sexual orientation who expressed gender nonconformity before the age of 11 were more likely to experience [[physical abuse|abuse physically]], [[sexual abuse|sexually]], and [[psychological abuse|psychologically]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |first1=1Andrea L. |last1=Roberts |first2=Margaret |last2=Rosario |first3=Heather L. |last3=Corliss |first4=Karestan C. |last4=Koenen |first5=S. Bryn |last5=Austin |title=Childhood Gender Nonconformity: A Risk Indicator for Child Abuse and Posttraumatic Stress in Youth |journal=Pediatrics |date=March 2012 |volume=129 |issue=3 |pages=410–7 |doi=10.1542/peds.2011-1804 |pmid=22351893 |pmc=3289524}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Roberts et al. (2013) found that of participants in their study aged between 23 and 30, 26% of those who were gender nonconforming experienced some sort of depressive symptoms, versus 18% of those were gender-conforming.&lt;ref name="Roberts, A. 2013" /&gt; Treatment for gender identity disorders (GID) such as gender variance have been a topic of controversy for three decades.&lt;ref name="zach"&gt;Hill, D., Rozanski, C., Carfagnini, J., &amp; Willoughby, B. (January 01, 2007). Gender identity disorders (GID) in childhood and adolescence. International Journal of Sexual Health, 19, 1, 57-75&lt;/ref&gt; In the works of Hill, Carfagnini and Willoughby (2007), Bryant (2004), "suggests that treatment protocols for these children and adolescents, especially those based on converting the child back to a stereotypically gendered youth, make matters worse, causing them to internalize their distress." Treatment for GID in children and adolescents may have negative consequences.&lt;ref name="zach" /&gt; Studies suggest that treatment should focus more on helping children and adolescents feel comfortable living with GID. There is a feeling of distress that overwhelms a child or adolescent with GID that gets expressed through gender.&lt;ref name="zach" /&gt; Hill et al. (2007) states, "if these youth are distressed by having a condition deemed by society as unwanted, is this evidence of a disorder?" Bartlett and colleagues (2000) note that the problem determining distress is aggravated in GID cases because usually, it is not clear whether distress in the child is due to gender variance or secondary effects (e.g., due to ostracization or stigmatization).&lt;ref name="zach" /&gt; Hill et al. (2007) suggests, "a less controversial approach, respectful of increasing gender freedom in our culture and sympathetic to a child's struggle with gender, would be more humane."&lt;ref name="zach" /&gt;

==Social status for men vs. women==
Gender nonconformity among people assigned male at birth is usually more strictly, and sometimes violently, [[gender policing|policed]] in the West than is gender nonconformity among people assigned female at birth. However, a spectrum of types of gender nonconformity exists among boys and men. Some types of gender nonconformity, such as being a [[stay-at-home father]], may pass without comment whereas others, such as wearing lipstick and skirts, may attract stares, criticism, or questioning. Some geographical regions are more tolerant than others of such differences.{{Citation needed|date=January 2019}}

This is a comparatively recent development in historical terms, because the dress and careers of women used to be policed,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://ic.galegroup.com/ic/uhic/ReferenceDetailsPage/ReferenceDetailsWindow?query=&amp;prodId=UHIC&amp;displayGroupName=Reference&amp;limiter=&amp;disableHighlighting=true&amp;displayGroups=&amp;sortBy=&amp;zid=&amp;search_within_results=&amp;action=2&amp;catId=&amp;activityType=&amp;documentId=GALE%7CCX3468301237&amp;source=Bookmark&amp;u=sand55832&amp;jsid=ff1c546a17b62d2d1ce4007351b97724 |title=Working women in the 1930s |accessdate=21 Jan 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; and still are in countries like Iran and Saudi Arabia (where they are regulated by the law&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.theweek.co.uk/60339/nine-things-women-cant-do-in-saudi-arabia |title=Seven things women in Saudi Arabia cannot do |work=[[The Week]] UK |date=27 Sep 2016 |accessdate=21 Jan 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.gov.uk/foreign-travel-advice/iran/local-laws-and-customs |title=Iran travel advice |publisher=UK government |accessdate=21 Jan 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;). The success of [[second-wave feminism]] is the chief reason for the freedom of women in the West to wear traditionally-male clothing such as [[trousers]], or to take up traditionally-male occupations such as being a [[medical doctor]], etc. At the other extreme, some [[Communist]] regimes such as the Soviet Union made a point of pushing women into traditionally male occupations in order to advance the [[state feminism|feminist ideology of the state]] {{emdash}} for example, 58% of Soviet engineers were women in 1980 {{emdash}} but this trend went into reverse after the collapse of the Soviet Union, a reversal that some attribute to women becoming more free to follow their own interests.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite conference |url=http://www.asee.org/public/conferences/20/papers/6985/view |title=The Decline of Women in Russian Engineering Education |year=2013 |conference=ASEE Annual Conference &amp; Exposition |first1=Svetlana |last1=Barabanova |first2=Phillip |last2=Sanger |first3=Julia |last3=Ziyatdinova |first4=Anastasia |last4=Sokolova |first5=Vasiliy |last5=Ivanov}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Gender nonconforming transgender people in the United States have been demonstrated to have worse overall health outcomes than transgender individuals who identify as men or women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Lagos |first1=D. |date=2018 |title=Hearing Gender: Voice-Based Gender Classification Processes and Transgender Health Inequality |journal=Demography |volume=55 |issue=6 |pages=2097–2117 |doi=10.1007/s13524-018-0714-3 |pmid=30255426|s2cid=52822267 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Association with sexual orientation==
Gender norms vary by country and by culture, as well as across historical time periods within cultures. For example, in [[Pashtuns|Pashtun]] tribes in Afghanistan, adult men frequently hold hands, without being perceived as gay, whereas in the West this behavior would, in most circumstances, be seen as proof of a homosexual relationship. However, in many cultures, behaviors such as crying, an inclination toward caring for and nurturing others in an emotionally open way, an interest in domestic chores other than cooking, and self-grooming can all be seen as aspects of male gender nonconformity.&lt;ref name="Friedman 2008" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Baumeister" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Brookley" /&gt; Men who exhibit such tendencies are often stereotyped as gay. Studies found a high incidence of gay males self-reporting gender-atypical behaviors in childhood, such as having little interest in athletics and a preference for playing with dolls.&lt;ref name="Bailey"&gt;[[J. Michael Bailey]], Joseph S. Miller, Lee Willerman; Maternally Rated Childhood Gender Nonconformity in Homosexuals and Heterosexuals, Archives of Sexual Behavior, Vol. 22, 1993.&lt;/ref&gt; The same study found that mothers of gay males recalled such atypical behavior in their sons with much greater frequency than mothers of heterosexual males.&lt;ref name="Bailey" /&gt;

For women, adult gender nonconformity is often associated with lesbianism due to the limited identities women are faced with at adulthood.&lt;ref name="Friedman 2008" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Baumeister" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Brookley" /&gt; Notions of heterosexual womanhood often require a rejection of physically demanding activities, social submission to a male figure (husband or boyfriend), an interest in reproduction and homemaking, and an interest in making oneself look more attractive for men with appropriate clothing, make-up, hairstyles and body shape. A rejection of any of these factors may lead to a woman being called a lesbian regardless of her actual sexual orientation, or indeed to a man "crossing her off the list" as a potential romantic or sexual partner regardless of whether he actually believes she is a lesbian. Therefore, attracting a male romantic or sexual partner can be a strong factor for an adult woman to suppress or reject her own desire to be gender-variant.{{Citation needed|date=January 2019}}

Lesbian and bisexual women, being less concerned with attracting men, may find it easier to reject traditional ideas of womanhood because social punishment for such transgression is not effective, or at least no more effective than the consequences of being openly gay or bisexual in a [[Heteronormativity|heteronormative]] society (which they already experience). This may help account for high levels of gender nonconformity self-reported by lesbians.&lt;ref name="Friedman 2008" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Baumeister" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Brookley" /&gt;

Gender theorist [[Judith Butler]], in her essay ''Performative Acts and Gender Constitution: An Essay in Phenomenology and Feminist Theory'', states: "Discrete genders are part of what humanizes individuals within contemporary culture; indeed, those who fail to do their gender right are regularly punished. Because there is neither an 'essence' that gender expresses or externalizes nor an objective ideal to which gender aspires."&lt;ref name="auto"&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Butler |first=Judith |date=1988-01-01 |title=Performative Acts and Gender Constitution: An Essay in Phenomenology and Feminist Theory |journal=Theatre Journal |volume=40 |issue=4 |pages=519–531 |doi=10.2307/3207893 |jstor=3207893}}&lt;/ref&gt; Butler argues that gender is not an inherent aspect of identity, further stating, "...One might try to reconcile the gendered body as the legacy of sedimented acts rather than a predetermined or foreclosed structure, essence or fact, whether natural, cultural, or linguistic".&lt;ref name="auto" /&gt;

==Clothing==
Among adults, the [[cross-dressing|wearing of women's clothing by men]] is often socially stigmatized and [[sexual fetishism|fetishised]], or viewed as sexually abnormal. However, [[cross-dressing]] may be a form of gender expression and is not necessarily related to erotic activity, nor is it indicative of sexual orientation.&lt;ref&gt;Gay and Lesbian Alliance Against Defamation. [http://www.glaad.org/reference/transgender ''GLAAD Media Reference Guide, 8th Edition. Transgender Glossary of Terms"], ''[[GLAAD]]'', USA, May 2010. Retrieved on 2011-03-01.&lt;/ref&gt; Other gender-nonconforming men prefer to simply modify and stylise men's clothing as an expression of their interest in appearance and fashion.

==Gender-affirmative practices==
Gender-affirmative practices recognize and support an individual's unique gender self-identification and expression. Gender-affirmative practices are becoming more widely adopted in the mental and physical health fields in response to research showing that clinical practices that encourage individuals to accept a certain gender identity can cause psychological harm.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Bryant |first1=Karl |title=Making gender identity disorder of childhood: Historical lessons for contemporary debates |journal=Sexuality Research and Social Policy |date=September 2006 |volume=3 |issue=3 |pages=23–39 |doi=10.1525/srsp.2006.3.3.23|s2cid=144613679 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2015, the [[American Psychological Association]] published gender-affirmative practice guidelines for clinicians working with transgender and gender-nonconforming people. Preliminary research on gender-affirmative practices in the medical and psychological settings has primarily shown positive treatment outcomes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title=Guidelines for psychological practice with transgender and gender-nonconforming people. |journal=American Psychologist |date=2015 |volume=70 |issue=9 |pages=832–864 |doi=10.1037/a0039906 |pmid=26653312 |author1=American Psychological Association |s2cid=1751773 }}&lt;/ref&gt; As these practices become more widely used, longer-term studies and studies with larger sample sizes are needed to continue to evaluate these practices.

Research has shown that youth who receive gender-affirming support from their parents have better mental health outcomes than their peers who do not.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Ryan |first1=Caitlin |last2=Russell |first2=Stephen T. |last3=Huebner |first3=David |last4=Diaz |first4=Rafael |last5=Sanchez |first5=Jorge |title=Family Acceptance in Adolescence and the Health of LGBT Young Adults |journal=Journal of Child and Adolescent Psychiatric Nursing |date=November 2010 |volume=23 |issue=4 |pages=205–213 |doi=10.1111/j.1744-6171.2010.00246.x |pmid=21073595}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Gender-affirmative practices emphasize gender health. Gender health is an individual's ability to identify as and express the gender(s) that feels most comfortable without fear of rejection.&lt;ref name="ReferenceA"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Hidalgo |first1=Marco A. |last2=Ehrensaft |first2=Diane |last3=Tishelman |first3=Amy C. |last4=Clark |first4=Leslie F. |last5=Garofalo |first5=Robert |last6=Rosenthal |first6=Stephen M. |last7=Spack |first7=Norman P. |last8=Olson |first8=Johanna |title=The Gender Affirmative Model: What We Know and What We Aim to Learn |journal=Human Development |date=2013 |volume=56 |issue=5 |pages=285–290 |doi=10.1159/000355235 |doi-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt; Gender-affirmative practices are informed by the following premises:&lt;ref name="ReferenceA" /&gt;

* gender variance is not a psychological disorder or mental illness
* gender expressions vary across cultures
* gender expressions are diverse and may not be binary
* gender development is affected by biological, developmental, and cultural factors
* if pathology occurs, it is more often from cultural reactions rather than from within the individual

Mental health practitioners have begun integrating the gender-affirmative model into [[cognitive behavioral therapy]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Austin |first1=Ashley |last2=Craig |first2=Shelley L. |date=2015 |title=Transgender Affirmative Cognitive Behavioral Therapy: Clinical Considerations and Applications |journal=Professional Psychology: Research and Practice |volume=46 |issue=1 |pages=21–29 |doi=10.1037/a.0038642|doi-broken-date=2020-10-17 }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[person-centered therapy]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |title=Person-Centered Counselling for Trans and Gender Diverse People |last=Hope |first=Sam |date=2020 |publisher=Jessica Kingsley Publishers |isbn=978-1785925429 |location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[acceptance and commitment therapy]].&lt;ref name="Stitt"&gt;{{Cite book |title=ACT For Gender Identity: The Comprehensive Guide |last=Stitt |first=Alex |date=2020 |publisher=Jessica Kingsley Publishers |isbn=978-1785927997 |location=London |oclc=1089850112}}&lt;/ref&gt; While taking different approaches, each therapeutic modality may prove beneficial to gender-variant people looking to self-actualize, cope with minority stress, or navigate personal, social, and occupational issues across the lifespan.

==Atypical gender roles==
Gender expectations, like other [[social norms]], can vary widely by culture. A person may be seen as expressing an atypical [[gender role]] when their [[gender expression]] and activities differ from those usually expected in that culture. What is "typical" for one culture may be "atypical" for another. People from cultures who conceptualize gender as polar opposites on a binary, or having only two options, may see cultures with [[third gender]] people, or fluid gender expressions, and the people who live in these gender roles, as "atypical". 
Gender expressions that ''some'' cultures might consider "atypical" could include:

* ''[[Househusband]]s'': men from [[patriarchal]] cultures who stay at home to raise children and take care of the home while their partner goes to work. [[National Public Radio]] reported that by 2015 this had risen to 38%.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.npr.org/2015/02/08/384695833/what-happens-when-wives-earn-more-than-husbands |title=What Happens When Wives Earn More Than Husbands |publisher=[[National Public Radio]] |date=February 8, 2015 |accessdate=April 25, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; This would only be "atypical" in a culture where it is the norm for women to stay home.
* ''[[Androgynous]] people'': having a gender presentation that is either mixed or neutral in a culture that prizes highly binary presentations.&lt;ref name="Stitt" /&gt;
* ''[[Crossdresser]]'': a person who dresses in the clothing of, and otherwise assumes, "the appearance, manner, or roles traditionally associated with members of the opposite sex".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://medical-dictionary.thefreedictionary.com/Dual-role+transvestism |title=Dual-role transvestism |website=TheFreeDictionary.com |access-date=2019-05-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; Crossdressers may be cisgender, or they may be trans people who have not yet transitioned.
* ''[[Hijra (India)|Hijra]]'': a traditional third-gender person who is occasionally intersex, but most often considered male at birth. Many of the Hijra are [[eunuch]]s who have chosen to be ritually castrated in a dedication ceremony. They have a ceremonial role in several traditional South Asian cultures, often performing naming ceremonies and blessings. They dress in what is considered "women's" garments for that culture, but are seen as neither men nor women, but ''hijra''. 
* ''[[Khanith]]'': an effeminate gay male in [[Oman]]i culture who is allowed to associate with women. The clothing of these individuals must be intermediate between that of a male and a female.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first=Stephen O. |last=Murray |date=2002 |title=Homosexualities |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=GfH6Nc8HHFwC |publisher=University of Chicago Press |isbn=0-226-55194-6 |page=278}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Two-spirit|Two-Spirit]]: a modern, [[pan-Indian]], [[umbrella term]] used by some [[Indigenous peoples of the Americas|Indigenous North Americans]] to describe Native people in their communities who fulfill a traditional [[third gender|third-gender]] (or other gender-variant) social and ceremonial role in their cultures.&lt;ref name="de Vries 2009"&gt;{{cite book |last1=de Vries |first1=Kylan Mattias |editor1-last=O'Brien |editor1-first=Jodi |title=Encyclopedia of gender and society |date=2009 |publisher=SAGE |location=Los Angeles |isbn=9781412909167 |page=64 |chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=_nyHS4WyUKEC |accessdate=6 March 2015 |chapter=Berdache (Two-Spirit)}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Pember"&gt;{{cite web |url=https://rewire.news/article/2016/10/13/two-spirit-tradition-far-ubiquitous-among-tribes/ |title='Two Spirit' Tradition Far From Ubiquitous Among Tribes |publisher=[[Rewire (website)|Rewire]] |first=Mary Annette |last=Pember |date=Oct 13, 2016 |accessdate=October 17, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; The term ''two-spirit'' was created in 1990 at the Indigenous [[lesbian]] and [[gay]] international gathering in [[Winnipeg]], and "specifically chosen to distinguish and distance Native American/First Nations people from non-Native peoples."&lt;ref name="de Vries 2009" /&gt;
* Male spirit mediums in Myanmar: Biological men that are spirit mediums (''nat kadaw'') wear women's attire and wear makeup during religious ceremonies. The majority of male spirit mediums live their lives permanently as women.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Coleman |first1=Eli |last2=Allen |first2=Mariette Pathy |last3=Ford |first3=Jessie V. |date=2018-05-01 |title=Gender Variance and Sexual Orientation Among Male Spirit Mediums in Myanmar |journal=Archives of Sexual Behavior |volume=47 |issue=4 |pages=987–998 |doi=10.1007/s10508-018-1172-0 |pmid=29497915 |s2cid=4730569 |issn=1573-2800}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Transgender|LGBT}}
* [[Discrimination against non-binary gender people]]
* [[Gender binary]]
* [[Gender diversity]]
* [[Gender dysphoria]]
* [[Gender polarization]]
* [[Third gender]]
* [[Transphobia]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{Sexual identities}}
{{Drag performance}}

[[Category:Androgyny]]
[[Category:Gender nonconformity| ]]
[[Category:Non-binary gender]]
[[Category:Gender roles]]
[[Category:Transgender]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>