<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20221023013317|1117683791" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="6727352" pageid="6727352" ns="0" title="Anti-Black racism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2022-11-28T07:05:07Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|Fear, hatred or extreme aversion to Black people and Black culture}}
{{Redirect|Melanophobia|other uses of the word "Melano"|Melanoleuca (disambiguation)}}
{{pp-pc1}}
{{Discrimination sidebar}}
'''Negrophobia''' (also termed '''anti-Blackness''') is characterized by a fear, hatred or extreme aversion to [[black people]] and [[Black culture (disambiguation)|black culture]]&lt;!--intentional link to DAB page--&gt; worldwide. Caused amongst other factors by [[racism]] and traumatic events and circumstances, symptoms of this [[phobia]] include but are not limited to the attribution of negative characteristics to black people, the fear or the strong dislike of black men and the [[objectification]] of black women.&lt;ref name="Brooks"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Brooks|first1=Adia A.|date=2012|title=Black Negrophobia and Black Self-Empowerment: Afro-Descendant Responses to Societal Racism in São Paulo, Brazil|url=https://www.uwlax.edu/globalassets/offices-services/urc/jur-online/pdf/2012/brooks.adia.pdf|journal=UW-L Journal of Undergraduate Research|volume=XV|page=2|access-date=4 May 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Definitions ==

=== Lexicology ===

The [[hybrid word]] ''negrophobia'' consists of two components: ''negro'' and ''[[phobia]]''. As such, it literally derives from "Fear of black":

* From [[Spanish language|Spanish]] and [[Portuguese language|Portuguese]]: ''[[negro]]'', "Black color" 
* From Greek: φόβος, phóbos, "[[Fear]] of"

Other terms with similar meanings include ''antiblackness''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last=Rieger | first=Jeorg |title=Religion, Theology, and Class: Fresh Engagements after Long Silence | publisher=Palgrave Macmillan US | series=New Approaches to Religion and Power | year=2013 | isbn=978-1-137-33924-9 | url=https://books.google.com/books?id=_Z9EAgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA177 | access-date=5 July 2018 | page=177}}&lt;/ref&gt; and ''blackophobia''.&lt;ref&gt;''Afrasia: A Tale of Two Continents'' – Page 105, Ali A. Mazrui – 2013&lt;/ref&gt; However, some publishers have discouraged designating individuals as ''blackophobes'' or ''negrophobes'' and rather highlight the general epithet that is usually applied to racists.&lt;ref&gt;Lincoln: Political Writings and Speeches – Page xxvi,  Terence Ball – 2013&lt;/ref&gt;

Although ''melanophobia'' is sometimes confused with ''negrophobia'', the former term is more commonly applied to situations involving inanimate objects that are very dark or black.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Klaffke|first1=Pamela|title=Spree: A Cultural History of Shopping|url=https://archive.org/details/spree00pame|url-access=registration|date=2003|page=[https://archive.org/details/spree00pame/page/181 181]|isbn=9781551521435 }}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Negrophobia'' is also distinct from ''[[Afrophobia]]'', which is a perceived fear of the various cultures and peoples of [[Ethnic groups of Africa|Africa]] and the [[African diaspora]] irrespective of their racial origin. Unlike ''negrophobia'', ''Afrophobia'' is thus essentially a cultural rather than a racial phenomenon.&lt;ref name="Pwpa"&gt;{{cite book|author1=Kivuto Ndeti |author2=Kenneth R. Gray |author3=Gerard Bennaars |title=The second scramble for Africa: a response &amp; a critical analysis of the challenges facing contemporary sub-Saharan Africa|date=1992|publisher=Professors World Peace Academy|isbn=9966835733|page=127|url=https://www.google.com/books?id=ScsDAQAAIAAJ|access-date=10 December 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Debates over definitions===

There are differences in the senses that are applied to ''negrophobes'' or the noun ''Negrophobia''. Some senses use the term to describe a [[discriminatory]] sentiment towards people who may identify with the black race.&lt;ref&gt;Max Planck Yearbook of United Nations Law – Page 492,  Rüdiger Wolfrum – 1999&lt;/ref&gt; Accordingly, the latter sense adopts the notion that a person with ''Negrophobia'' believes that his or her race is superior to the black race through [[xenophobia]].&lt;ref&gt;Ubuntu, Migration and Ministry: Page 88, Elina Hankela – 2014&lt;/ref&gt; However, an alternative definition stays true to the original clinical meaning of the suffix phobia. Thereby, ''Negrophobia'' would be associated not with [[racism]], but rather with those who critically fear the black race.&lt;ref&gt;Black Soul, White Artifact: Fanon's Clinical Psychology and Social Theory
p 73, Jock McCulloch – 2002&lt;/ref&gt; In July 2010, a segment on ''Negrophobia'' was featured on ''[[The Rachel Maddow Show]]'' on [[MSNBC]].&lt;ref name="M"&gt;{{cite web|title=Scaring white people for fun and profit|url=http://www.msnbc.com/rachel-maddow-show/scaring-white-people-fun-and-profit|author=Maddow, Rachel|author-link=Rachel Maddow|date=July 21, 2010|work=[[MSNBC]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;"Negrophobia", published by St. Martin's Press and written by Darius James&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Negrophobia and Reasonable Racism: The Hidden Costs of Being Black in America, An academic book written through the New York University press.2&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Negrophobia: A Race Riot in 1906, by Mark Bauerlein with Encounter Press.3&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;American Heritage Dictionary 4&lt;/ref&gt;

== Overview ==

=== Historical context ===

In Europe, ''Negrophobia'' finds its roots in the 17th century due to its extensive historical [[Colonization|colonisation]] and [[slavery]].&lt;ref name="une"&gt;{{cite web|title=Négrophobie|url=http://une-autre-histoire.org/negrophobie/|last1=Une Autre Histoire|website=une-autre-histoire.org|date=13 January 2015 |access-date=6 May 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to certain sources, the term ''Negrophobia'' would have been forged on the model of the word ''Nigrophilism'', itself first appearing in 1802 in Baudry des Lozières’s ''Les égarements du nigrophilisme''.&lt;ref name="une" /&gt; It further reappeared in January 1927 in [[Lamine Senghor]]’s ''La voix des nègres'', a monthly anti-colonialist newspaper. The term was later popularised by [[Frantz Fanon]], especially in his works ''Peaux noires masques blancs'' and [[The Wretched of the Earth|&lt;nowiki&gt;''Les Damnés de la Terre''&lt;/nowiki&gt;]].&lt;ref name="une" /&gt; More recently in 2005, an anti-negrophobia brigade (BAN) was created in [[France]] to protest against increasing targeted acts and occurrences of [[police violence]].&lt;ref name="une" /&gt; The latter protest movements notably underwent severe police violence in the Jardin du Luxembourg in Paris during the 2011 and 2013 abolition of slavery commemorations.&lt;ref name="une" /&gt;

=== ''Negrophobia'' and identity ===

More specifically on Fanon's analysis of ''Negrophobia'', the psychiatrist was the first to introduce the concept of black ''Negrophobia'', pointing to the hatred of black people and black culture [[Self-hatred|by black people themselves]].&lt;ref name="Brooks" /&gt; Indeed, he asserts that ''Negrophobia'' is a form of "trauma for white people of the Negro".&lt;ref name="Alessandrini2005"&gt;{{cite book|author=Anthony C. Alessandrini|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Y6qGAgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA153|title=Frantz Fanon: Critical Perspectives|date=3 August 2005|publisher=Routledge|isbn=978-1-134-65657-8|page=153}}&lt;/ref&gt; Equivalent to internalised racism caused by the trauma of living in a culture defining black people as inherently evil, Fanon emphasises the slight existing cultural intricacies caused by the vast diversity of black people and cultures, as well as the nature of their colonisation by white [[Ethnic groups in Europe|Europeans]].&lt;ref name="Brooks" /&gt; The symptoms of such black ''Negrophobia'' include a rejection of their native or ethnic language in favour of [[Languages of Europe|European languages]], a marked preference for [[Culture of Europe|European cultures]] over black cultures, and a tendency to surround themselves with lighter skinned people rather than darker skinned ones.&lt;ref name="Brooks" /&gt; Similarly, the pattern further includes attributing negative characteristics to black people, culture, and things. [[Toni Morrison]]'s novel ''[[The Bluest Eye]]'' (1970) stands as an illustrative work on the destroying effects of ''Negrophobia'' among the [[black community]] on themselves.&lt;ref name="Blue"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Maleki, Nasser and Haj'jari and Mohammad-Javad|date=2015|title=Negrophobia and Anti-Negritude in Morrison's The Bluest Eye|url=https://www.researchgate.net/publication/291147460|journal=Epiphany: Journal of Transdisciplinary Studies|volume=8|page=69|access-date=7 May 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt; Indeed, the main character, Pecola Breedlove, through her non-reconciliation with her black identity, her black societal indifference and her craving for symbolic blue eyes, presents all the signs of an internalised ''Negrophobia''.&lt;ref name="Blue" /&gt; She develops an anti-black [[neurosis]] due to her feeling of non-existence both within the white and her own community.&lt;ref name="Blue" /&gt;

While the latter theoretical framework is academically debated, Fanon insists on the nature of ''Negrophobia'' as a socio-diagnosis, thus characterising not individuals but rather entire societies and their patterns.&lt;ref name="Brooks" /&gt; Fanon thereby implies that ''Negrophobia'' is a cross-disciplinary area of research, justifying that its analysis and understanding may not be confined to the [[psychological]] field.&lt;ref name="Brooks" /&gt;

=== ''Negrophobia'' and law ===

The notion of involuntary ''Negrophobia'' is highly debated in the academic and [[legal]] arenas, specifically opposing non [[Instrumentalism|instrumentalists]] and instrumentalists. The formers are favourable to the involuntary nature of a [[Posttraumatic stress disorder|post-traumatic stress disorder]], thereby defending the uncontrollable nature of a defendant’s actions.&lt;ref name="Armour"&gt;{{cite book|last1=Armour|first1=Jody David|title=Negrophobia and Reasonable Racism: The Hidden Costs of Being Black in America|date=1997|publisher=NYU Press|location=New York, London|page=64|jstor=j.ctt9qfpg3}}&lt;/ref&gt; This approach focusses on the personal culpability of the individual defendant,&lt;ref name="Armour" /&gt; thus disregarding any possible social implications. On the other hand, instrumentalists do consider such broader implications, viewing the [[law]] as an object of social change and claiming to promote the general [[welfare]] by refusing to recognise legal claims damaging the integrity of the legal.&lt;ref name="Armour5"&gt;{{cite book|last1=Armour|first1=Jody David|title=Negrophobia and Reasonable Racism: The Hidden Costs of Being Black in America|date=1997|publisher=NYU Press|location=New York, London|page=65|jstor=j.ctt9qfpg3}}&lt;/ref&gt; This view criticises non instrumentalists for equating ''Negrophobia'' with [[insanity]] by allowing a person’s racial fear to legally justify and even excuse violent behaviour.&lt;ref name="Armour5" /&gt; Following widespread claims that sane but guilty defendants may exploit the insanity defence to escape long [[prison sentence]]s,&lt;ref name="Armour6"&gt;{{cite book|last1=Armour|first1=Jody David|title=Negrophobia and Reasonable Racism: The Hidden Costs of Being Black in America|date=1997|publisher=NYU Press|location=New York, London|page=66|jstor=j.ctt9qfpg3}}&lt;/ref&gt; a similar skepticism with respect to defences invoking ''Negrophobia'' would result in significant distrust in the legal and [[criminal justice system]], thereby indirectly destroying the legitimacy of such courts.&lt;ref name="Armour6" /&gt;

=== AntiBlackness in Education and Organization Studies. ===
In response to BlackLivesMatter organizing contemporary scholars of Education, Human Resource Development, and Critical Management Studies have begun focusing on antiBlackness in schools and places of business.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Bell|first1=Myrtle P.|last2=Berry|first2=Daphne|last3=Leopold|first3=Joy|last4=Nkomo|first4=Stella|date=January 2021|title=Making Black Lives Matter in academia: A Black feminist call for collective action against anti‐blackness in the academy|url=https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/gwao.12555|journal=Gender, Work &amp; Organization|language=en|volume=28|issue=S1|pages=39–57|doi=10.1111/gwao.12555|s2cid=224844343 |issn=0968-6673}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Bohonos|first=Jeremy W|date=2021-06-03|title=Workplace hate speech and rendering Black and Native lives as if they do not matter: A nightmarish autoethnography|url=http://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.1177/13505084211015379|journal=Organization|language=en|pages=135050842110153|doi=10.1177/13505084211015379|s2cid=236294224 |issn=1350-5084}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Dumas|first=Michael J.|date=2016-01-02|title=Against the Dark: Antiblackness in Education Policy and Discourse|url=http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/00405841.2016.1116852|journal=Theory into Practice|language=en|volume=55|issue=1|pages=11–19|doi=10.1080/00405841.2016.1116852|s2cid=147252566 |issn=0040-5841}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Dumas|first1=Michael J.|last2=ross|first2=kihana miraya|date=April 2016|title="Be Real Black for Me": Imagining BlackCrit in Education|url=http://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.1177/0042085916628611|journal=Urban Education|language=en|volume=51|issue=4|pages=415–442|doi=10.1177/0042085916628611|s2cid=147319546 |issn=0042-0859}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Bohonos|first1=Jeremy W.|last2=Sisco|first2=Stephanie|date=June 2021|title=Advocating for social justice, equity, and inclusion in the workplace: An agenda for anti‐racist learning organizations|url=http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/ace.20428|journal=New Directions for Adult and Continuing Education|volume=2021|issue=170|pages=89–98|doi=10.1002/ace.20428|s2cid=240576110 |issn=1052-2891}}&lt;/ref&gt; These efforts build on established critical race discourses in their respective field and incorporate concepts from Afropessimism.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Wilderson|first=Frank|title=Afropessimism}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{div col}}
* [[Negrophilia]]
* [[Afrophobia]]
* [[Missing white woman syndrome]]
* [[Ethnocentrism]]
* [[List of phobias]]
* [[Racial bias in criminal news]]
* [[Racism in France#Racism against Sub-Saharan Africans|Racism against black people in France]]
* [[Racism against black Americans]]
* [[Stereotypes of African Americans]]
* [[Xenophobia]]
{{div col end}}

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{Racism topics}}

[[Category:Anti-black racism in the United States]]
[[Category:Racially motivated violence against African Americans| ]]
[[Category:Prejudice and discrimination by type]]
[[Category:Anti-black racism]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>