<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20161018144600|744968237" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="6727352" pageid="6727352" ns="0" title="Anti-Black racism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2016-11-11T12:15:36Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Redirect|Melanophobia|other uses of the word "Melano"|Melanoleuca (disambiguation)}}
{{Discrimination sidebar}}
'''Negrophobia''' is a fear of ''[[Negroid|negro]]'' peoples worldwide. It can be influenced by various things, such as [[racism]] or traumatic events and circumstances.

==Lexicology==
The term ''Negrophobia'' consists of two components: ''negro'' and ''phobia''. As such, it literally derives from "fear of black", from [[Spanish language|Spanish]] and [[Portuguese language|Portuguese]]: ''[[negro]]'', "black" and from Greek: φόβος, phóbos, "[[fear]]"). Other terms with similar meanings include antiblackness&lt;ref&gt;Religion, Theology, and Class: Fresh Engagements After Long Silence, p 177, Joerg Rieger – 2013&lt;/ref&gt; and blackophobia&lt;ref&gt;Afrasia: A Tale of Two Continents – Page 105, Ali A. Mazrui – 2013&lt;/ref&gt; However, some publishers have discouraged designating individuals as ''blackophobes'' or ''negrophobes'' and rather highlight the general epithet that is usually applied to racists.&lt;ref&gt;Lincoln: Political Writings and Speeches – Page xxvi,  Terence Ball – 2013&lt;/ref&gt;

Although ''melanophobia'' is sometimes confused with ''Negrophobia'', the term is more commonly applied to situations involving inanimate objects that are very dark or black.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Klaffke|first1=Pamela|title=Spree: A Cultural History of Shopping|date=2003|page=181}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Negrophobia'' is also distinct from ''[[Afrophobia]]'', which is a perceived fear of the various cultures and peoples of [[Ethnic groups of Africa|Africa]] and the [[African diaspora]] irrespective of racial origin. Unlike ''Negrophobia'', ''Afrophobia'' is thus essentially a cultural rather than a racial phenomenon.&lt;ref name="Pwpa"&gt;{{cite book|last1=Kivuto Ndeti, Kenneth R. Gray, Gerard Bennaars|title=The second scramble for Africa: a response &amp; a critical analysis of the challenges facing contempory sub-Saharan Africa|date=1992|publisher=Professors World Peace Academy|isbn=9966835733|page=127|url=https://www.google.com/books?id=ScsDAQAAIAAJ|accessdate=10 December 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Overview==
There are differences in the senses that are applied to negrophobes or the noun negrophobia. Some senses use the term to describe discriminatory sentiment towards people who may identify with the black race.&lt;ref&gt;Max Planck Yearbook of United Nations Law – Page 492,  Rüdiger Wolfrum – 1999&lt;/ref&gt; This sense adopts the notion that a person with negrophobia believes his or her race is superior over the black race with [[xenophobia]].&lt;ref&gt;Ubuntu, Migration and Ministry: Page 88, Elina Hankela – 2014&lt;/ref&gt; However an alternative definition stays true to the original clinical meaning of the suffix phobia. Thereby negrophobia is not associated with [[racism]], but rather is associated with those who fear the black race.&lt;ref&gt;Black Soul, White Artifact: Fanon's Clinical Psychology and Social Theory
p 73, Jock McCulloch – 2002&lt;/ref&gt; In July 2010, a segment on negrophobia was featured on ''[[The Rachel Maddow Show]]'' on [[MSNBC]].&lt;ref name=M&gt;{{cite web|work=[[MSNBC]]|url=http://www.msnbc.com/rachel-maddow-show/scaring-white-people-fun-and-profit|title=Scaring white people for fun and profit|date=July 21, 2010|authorlink=Rachel Maddow|author=Maddow, Rachel}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;"Negrophobia", published by St. Martin's Press and written by Darius James&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Negrophobia and Reasonable Racism: The Hidden Costs of Being Black in America, An academic book written through the New York University press.2&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Negrophobia: A Race Riot in 1906, by Mark Bauerlein with Encounter Press.3&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;American Heritage Dictionary 4&lt;/ref&gt;

Some, such as psychiatrist [[Frantz Fanon]], assert that negrophobia is a form of "trauma for white people of the Negro".&lt;ref name="Alessandrini2005"&gt;{{cite book|author=Anthony C. Alessandrini|title=Frantz Fanon: Critical Perspectives|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Y6qGAgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA153|date=3 August 2005|publisher=Routledge|isbn=978-1-134-65657-8|page=153}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Anglophobia]]
*[[Stereotypes of African-Americans]]
*[[Slavery in the United States]]
*[[Racism against black people in France]]
*[[Hispanophobia]]
*[[Lynching in the United States]]
*[[Racial bias in criminal news]]
*[[Xenophobia]]
*[[Ethnocentrism]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{Anti-cultural sentiment}}

[[Category:Anti-black racism in the United States]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Racially motivated violence against African Americans| ]]
[[Category:Racism]]
[[Category:Hatred]]
[[Category:Prejudices]]


{{socio-stub}}</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>