<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20201119064725|989483127" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="8587" pageid="8587" ns="0" title="Democide"><revisions><rev timestamp="2020-11-21T08:56:22Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Intentional killing of an unarmed or disarmed person by government agents acting in their authoritative capacity}}
'''Democide''' is a concept proposed by [[Rudolph Rummel]] since at least 1994 to describe "the intentional killing of an unarmed or disarmed person by government agents acting in their authoritative capacity and pursuant to government policy or high command."&lt;ref name="Harff 1996"&gt;Harff, Barbara (1996). "Death by Government by R. J. Rummel". ''The Journal of Interdisciplinary History''. '''27''' (1): 117–119. {{doi|10.2307/206491}}. {{jstor|206491}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Harff 2017"&gt;{{cite book|last=Harff|first=Barbara|year=2017|chapter-url=https://link.springer.com/content/pdf/10.1007%2F978-3-319-54463-2_12.pdf|chapter=The Comparative Analysis of Mass Atrocities and Genocide|editor-last=Gleditish|editor-first=N. P.|title=R.J. Rummel: An Assessment of His Many Contributions|volume=37|series=SpringerBriefs on Pioneers in Science and Practice|location=New York|publisher=Springer|pages=111–129|doi=10.1007/978-3-319-54463-2_12|doi-access=free|isbn=978-3-319-54463-2}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to Rummel, this definition covers a wide range of deaths, including forced labor and concentration camp victims; killings by unofficial private groups; extrajudicial summary killings; and mass deaths due to governmental acts of criminal omission and neglect such as in deliberate famines as well as killings by ''de facto'' governments, i.e. civil war killings.&lt;ref name="Harff 1996"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Harff 2017"/&gt; This definition covers any murder of any number of persons by any government.&lt;ref name="Harff 1996"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Harff 2017"/&gt;

Rummel created the term ''democide'' as an extended concept to include forms of government murder not covered by the term ''[[genocide]]''. According to Rummel, democide surpassed war as the leading cause of non-natural death in the 20th century.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://democraticpeace.wordpress.com/2009/07/01/democide-vs-other-causes-of-death/|title=Democide Vs. Other Causes of Death|author=R. J. Rummel|date=1 February 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=stats&gt;{{cite book|title=Statistics of Democide: Genocide and Mass Murder since 1900|author=R. J. Rummel|year=1998|isbn=978-3825840105|publisher=LIT Verlag}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to [[Raphael Lemkin]], the objectives of democide include the disintegration of the political and social institutions of culture, language, national feelings, religion and the economic existence of national groups as well as the destruction of the personal security, liberty, health, dignity and even the lives of the individuals belonging to such groups.&lt;ref&gt;Lemkin, Raphael (1944). ''Axis Rule in Occupied Europe''.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Definition ==
Democide is the murder of any person or people by their government, including genocide, politicide and mass murder. Democide is not necessarily the elimination of entire cultural groups but rather groups within the country that the government feels need to be eradicated for political reasons and due to claimed future threats.&lt;ref name="Harff 1996"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Harff 2017"/&gt;

According to Rummel, genocide has three different meanings. The ordinary meaning is murder by government of people due to their national, ethnic, racial or religious group membership. The legal meaning of genocide refers to the international treaty on genocide, the [[Convention on the Prevention and Punishment of the Crime of Genocide]]. This also includes nonlethal acts that in the end eliminate or greatly hinder the group. Looking back on history, one can see the different variations of democides that have occurred, but it still consists of acts of killing or mass murder. The generalized meaning of genocide is similar to the ordinary meaning but also includes government killings of political opponents or otherwise intentional murder. In order to avoid confusion over which meaning is intended, Rummel created the term ''democide'' for this third meaning.&lt;ref name="Genocide"&gt;[http://www.hawaii.edu/powerkills/GENOCIDE.HTM Genocide].&lt;/ref&gt;

In "How Many Did Communist Regimes Murder?", Rummel wrote:
&lt;blockquote&gt;First, however, I should clarify the term democide. It means for governments what murder means for an individual under municipal law. It is the premeditated killing of a person in cold blood, or causing the death of a person through reckless and wanton disregard for their life. Thus, a government incarcerating people in a prison under such deadly conditions that they die in a few years is murder by the state--democide--as would parents letting a child die from malnutrition and exposure be murder. So would government forced labor that kills a person within months or a couple of years be murder. So would government created famines that then are ignored or knowingly aggravated by government action be murder of those who starve to death. And obviously, extrajudicial executions, death by torture, government massacres, and all genocidal killing be murder. However, judicial executions for crimes that internationally would be considered capital offenses, such as for murder or treason (as long as it is clear that these are not fabricated for the purpose of executing the accused, as in communist show trials), are not democide. Nor is democide the killing of enemy soldiers in combat or of armed rebels, nor of noncombatants as a result of military action against military targets.&lt;ref name="Rummel 1993"/&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

== Estimates ==
In his estimates, [[Rudolph Rummel]] relied mostly on historical accounts, an approach that rarely provides accuracy compared with contemporary academic opinion. Rummel wrote "these figures amount to little more than informed guesses", but he thought that "there is enough evidence to at least indict these authoritarian regimes for megamurder."&lt;ref&gt;https://www.hawaii.edu/powerkills/SOD.CHAP11.HTM&lt;/ref&gt; In response to [[David Stannard]]'s figures about what he terms "the [[American Holocaust]]", Rummel estimated that over the centuries of European colonization about 2 million to 15 million American indigenous people were victims of democide, excluding military battles and unintentional deaths in Rummel's definition. Rummel wrote that "[e]ven if these figures are remotely true, then this still make this subjugation of the Americas one of the bloodier, centuries long, democides in world history."&lt;ref&gt;Cook on Stannard, p. 12. Rummel's quote and estimate from [http://www.hawaii.edu/powerkills/DBG.CHAP3.HTM his website], about midway down the page, after footnote 82. Rummel's estimate is presumably not a single democide, but is a total of multiple democides, since there were many different governments involved.&lt;/ref&gt;

Rummel's estimates, especially about Communist democide, typically included a wide range and cannot be considered determinative.&lt;ref name="Harff 1996"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Harff 2017"/&gt; Rummel calculates nearly 43 million deaths due to democide inside and outside the Soviet Union during Stalin's regime.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.hawaii.edu/powerkills/DBG.TAB1.4.GIF&lt;/ref&gt; This is much higher than an often quoted figure of 20 million, or a more recent figure of 9 million.&lt;ref&gt;Tymothy Snyder. Hitler vs. Stalin: Who was worse? ''The New York Review of Books'' January 27, 2011,[http://www.nybooks.com/daily/2011/01/27/hitler-vs-stalin-who-was-worse/]&lt;/ref&gt; Rummel responded that the 20 million estimate is based on a figure from  [[Robert Conquest]]'s ''[[The Great Terror]]'' and that Conquest's qualifier "almost certainly too low" is usually forgotten. For Rummell, Conquest's calculations excluded camp deaths before 1936 and after 1950, executions (1939–1953), the [[population transfer in the Soviet Union]] (1939–1953), the deportation within the Soviet Union of minorities (1941–1944) and those the Soviet [[Red Army]] and [[Cheka|secret police]] executed throughout Eastern Europe after their conquest during the 1944–1945 period. Moreover, the [[Holodomor]] that killed 5 million in 1932–1934 (according to Rummel) is also not included.&lt;ref&gt;[http://freedomspeace.blogspot.com/2005/04/how-many-did-stalin-really-murder.html "How Many Did Stalin Really Murder?"]&lt;/ref&gt; According to Rummel, forced labor, executions and concentration camps were responsible for over one million deaths in the [[Democratic People's Republic of Korea]] from 1948 to 1987.&lt;ref&gt;Rummel, Rudolph (1997). [http://www.hawaii.edu/powerkills/SOD.CHAP10.HTM "Statistics of North Korean Democide: Estimates, Calculations, and Sources"]. University of Hawaii Political Science Department. Retrieved 14 November 2020.&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Rummel, his research showed that the death toll from democide is far greater than the death toll from war. After studying over 8,000 reports of government-caused deaths, Rummel estimated that there have been 262 million victims of democide in the last century. According to his figures, six times as many people have died from the actions of people working for governments than have died in battle. One of his main findings was that liberal democracies have much less democide than authoritarian regimes.&lt;ref name="Miracle"&gt;[http://www.hawaii.edu/powerkills/MIRACLE.HTM Miracle].&lt;/ref&gt; Rummel argued that there is a relation between political power and democide. Political mass murder grows increasingly common as political power becomes unconstrained. At the other end of the scale, where power is diffuse, checked, and balanced, political violence is a rarity. According to Rummel, "[t]he more power a regime has, the more likely people will be killed. This is a  major reason for promoting freedom."&lt;ref&gt;https://www.hawaii.edu/powerkills/FREEMAN.INTERVIEW.HTM&lt;/ref&gt; Rummel argued that "concentrated political power is the most dangerous thing on earth."&lt;ref&gt;Totten, Samuel (2013). ''Pioneers of Genocide Studies''. Transaction Publishers. p. 170.&lt;/ref&gt;

Several other researchers have found similar results to Rummel's, with one noting that "[n]umerous researchers point out that democratic norms and political structures constrain elite decisions about the use of repression against their citizens whereas autocratic elites are not so constrained. Once in place, democratic institutions—even partial ones—reduce the likelihood of armed conflict and all but eliminate the risk that it will lead to geno/politicide."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cidcm.umd.edu/inscr/genocide/ Genocide] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20071030201259/http://www.cidcm.umd.edu/inscr/genocide/ |date=2007-10-30 }}.&lt;/ref&gt; Researchers often give widely different estimates of [[mass killing]]s or [[mass murder]]s. They use different definitions, methodology and sources, with some including battle deaths in their calculations. [[Klas-Göran Karlsson]] prefers using the term ''[[crimes against humanity]]'' to include "the direct mass killings of politically undesirable elements, as well as forced deportations and forced labour." Karlsson acknowledges that the term may be misleading in the sense that the Communist regimes targeted groups of their own citizens, but he considers it useful as a broad legal term which emphasizes attacks on civilian populations and because the offenses demean humanity as a whole.&lt;ref name="Karlsson &amp; Schoenhals 2008"&gt;Karlsson, Klas-Göran; Schoenhals, Michael (2008). [https://www.levandehistoria.se/sites/default/files/material_file/research-review-crimes-against-humanity.pdf ''Crimes Against Humanity under Communist Regimes'']. Stockholm: Forum for Living History. {{ISBN|9789197748728}}.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Michael Mann (sociologist)|Michael Mann]] and [[Jacques Sémelin]] believe that ''crimes against humanity'' is more appropriate than ''[[genocide]]'' or ''[[politicide]]'' when speaking of killings or violence by Communist regimes.&lt;ref&gt;Jaffrelot, Christophe; Semelin, Jacques, eds. (2009) ''Purify and Destroy: The Political Uses of Massacre and Genocide''. Translated by Schoch, Cynthia. CERI Series in Comparative Politics and International Studies. New York: Columbia University Press. pp. 318, 344. {{ISBN|978-0-231-14283-0}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Communist democide ===
Democide has been applied to [[Communist regime]]s.&lt;ref name="Rummel 1993"&gt;Rummel, Rudolph (November 1993). [http://www.hawaii.edu/powerkills/COM.ART.HTM "How Many Did Communist Regimes Murder?"] University of Hawaii Political Science Department. {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180825013702/http://www.hawaii.edu/powerkills/COM.ART.HTM|date=25 August 2018}}. Retrieved 14 November 2020.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Fein, Helen (1993). [https://books.google.com/books?id=n4TaAAAAMAAJ&amp;q=%22Soviet+and+Communist+Genocides%22 "Soviet and Communist Genocides and 'Democide'"]. In [https://books.google.it/books?id=n4TaAAAAMAAJ ''Genocide: A Sociological Perspective'']. Contextual and Comparative Studies I: Ideological Genocides. Thousand Oaks: SAGE Publications. pp. 75–78. {{ISBN|978-0-8039-8829-3}}.&lt;/ref&gt; According to [[Klas-Göran Karlsson]], discussion of Communist democide and the number of victims of Communist regimes has been "extremely extensive and ideologically biased."&lt;ref name="Karlsson &amp; Schoenhals 2008"/&gt; Any attempt to estimate a total number of Communist democide depends greatly on definitions,&lt;ref&gt;Dallin, Alexander (2000). "Reviewed Work(s): ''The Black Book of Communism: Crimes, Terror, Repression'' by Stéphane Courtois, Nicolas Werth, Jean-Louis Panné, Andrzej Paczkowski, Karel Bartošek, Jean-Louis Margolin, Jonathan Murphy and Mark Kramer". ''Slavic Review''. '''59''' (4): 882‒883. {{doi|10.2307/2697429}}. {{jstor|2697429}}.&lt;/ref&gt; ranging from a low of 10–20 millions to as high as 110 millions.&lt;ref&gt;Valentino, Benjamin (2005). ''Final Solutions: Mass Killing and Genocide in the Twentieth Century''. Cornell University Press. pp. 75, 91, 275. {{ISBN|9780801472732}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Nonetheless, attempts at documenting and estimating Communist democide have been made by several authors, scholars and [[anti-communist]] organizations. In 1994, [[Rudolph Rummel]]'s book ''Death by Government'' included about 110 million people, foreign and domestic, killed by Communist democide from 1900 to 1987.&lt;ref&gt;Rummel, Rudolph (1994). ''Death by Government''. New Brunswick: Transaction Publishers. p. 15, table 1.6. {{ISBN|978-1-56000-927-6}}.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1993, Rummel wrote: "Even were we to have total access to all communist archives we still would not be able to calculate precisely how many the communists murdered. Consider that even in spite of the archival statistics and detailed reports of survivors, the best experts still disagree by over 40 percent on the total [[The Holocaust#Victims and death toll|number of Jews killed by the Nazis]]. We cannot expect near this accuracy for the victims of communism. We can, however, get a probable [[Orders of magnitude (numbers)|order of magnitude]] and a relative approximation of these deaths within a most likely range."&lt;ref name="Rummel 1993"/&gt; Due to additional information about [[Mao Zedong]]'s culpability in the [[Great Chinese Famine]] according to ''[[Mao: The Unknown Story]]'', a 2005 book authored by [[Jon Halliday]] and [[Jung Chang]], Rummel revised upward his total for Communist democide to about 148 million, using their estimate of 38 million famine deaths.&lt;ref&gt;Rummel, Rudolph (10 October 2005). [https://democraticpeace.wordpress.com/2008/11/24/reevaluating-chinas-democide-to-73000000/ "Reevaluating China's Democide to 73,000,000"]. ''Democratic Peace''. Retrieved 14 November 2020.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Rummel, Rudolph (1 December 2005). [http://hawaiireporter.com/story.aspx?1c1d76bb-290c-447b-82dd-e295ff0d3d59 "Stalin Exceeded Hitler in Monstrous Evil; Mao Beat Out Stalin"]. University of Hawaii Political Science Department. {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090917001933/http://hawaiireporter.com/story.aspx?1c1d76bb-290c-447b-82dd-e295ff0d3d59|date=17 September 2009}}. Retrieved 14 November 2020.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1999, [[Stéphane Courtois]]'s introduction to ''[[The Black Book of Communism]]'' gave a "rough approximation, based on unofficial estimates" approaching 100 million killed.&lt;ref&gt;Courtois, Stéphane, ed. (1999). [https://books.google.com/books?id=H1jsgYCoRioC ''The Black Book of Communism: Crimes, Terror, Repression'']. Translated by Kraemer, Mark (consulting ed.); Murphy, Jonathan Murphy. Cambridge: Harvard University Press. p. 4. {{ISBN|978-0-674-07608-2}}.&lt;/ref&gt; In his foreword to the book, [[Martin Malia]] wrote that "a grand total of victims variously estimated by contributors to the volume at between 85 million and 100 million."&lt;ref&gt;Malia, Martin (1999). "Foreword: The Uses of Atrocity". In Courtois, Stéphane; Kramer, Mark (eds.). ''The Black Book of Communism: Crimes, Terror, Repression''. Cambridge: Harvard University Press. pp. ix–xx. {{ISBN|978-0-674-07608-2}}.&lt;/ref&gt; In 2005, [[Benjamin Valentino]] stated that Communist democide in the Soviet Union, People's Republic of China and Cambodia alone ranged from a low of 21 million to a high of 70 million. Citing Rummel and others, Valentino stated that the "highest end of the plausible range of deaths attributed to communist regimes" was "up to 110 million."&lt;ref&gt;Valentino, Benjamin (2005). [https://books.google.com/books?id=LQfeXVU_EvgC ''Final Solutions: Mass Killing and Genocide in the Twentieth Century'']. Ithaca: Cornell University Press. pp. 75, 91, 275. {{ISBN|978-0-801-47273-2}}.&lt;/ref&gt; In 2010, [[Steven Rosefielde]]'s book ''[[Red Holocaust (2009 book)|Red Holocaust]]'' argued that Communism's internal contradictions caused the democide of "approximately 60 million people and perhaps tens of millions more."&lt;ref&gt;Rosefielde, Steven (2010). [https://books.google.com/books?id=7_eMAgAAQBAJ ''Red Holocaust'']. London: Routledge. pp. 1, 7. {{ISBN|978-0-415-77757-5}}.&lt;/ref&gt; In 2011, [[Matthew White (historian)|Matthew White]] published his rough total of Communist democide at 70 million, including "people who died under communist regimes from execution, labor camps, famine, ethnic cleansing, and desperate flight in leaky boats", with 26 million people additionally dying in "Communist-inspired wars."&lt;ref&gt;White, Matthew (2011). [https://books.google.it/books?id=0-fQHlaIpR4C ''Atrocities: The 100 Deadliest Episodes in Human History'']. New York: W. W. Norton &amp; Company. pp. 455–456. {{ISBN|978-0-393-08192-3}}.&lt;/ref&gt; In 2014, Julia Strauss wrote that while there was the beginning of a scholarly consensus on figures of around 20 million killed in the Soviet Union and 2–3 million in Cambodia, there was no such consensus on numbers for China.&lt;ref&gt;Strauss, Julia (2014). "Communist Revolution and Political Terror". In Smith, S. A. (ed.) [https://books.google.it/books?id=ZMd7AgAAQBAJ&amp;redir_esc=y ''The Oxford Handbook of the History of Communism'']. Oxford: Oxford University Press. pp. 360–361. {{ISBN|978-0-191-66752-7}}.&lt;/ref&gt; In 2017, [[Stephen Kotkin]] wrote in ''[[The Wall Street Journal]]'' that Communist democide resulted in at least 65 million people between 1917 and 2017, stating: "Though communism has killed huge numbers of people intentionally, even more of its victims have died from starvation as a result of its cruel projects of social engineering."&lt;ref&gt;Kotkin, Stephen (3 November 2017). [https://www.wsj.com/articles/the-communist-century-1509726265 "Communism's Bloody Century"] ''The Wall Street Journal''. {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171103231659/https://www.wsj.com/articles/the-communist-century-1509726265|date=3 November 2017}}. Retrieved 14 November 2020.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Editorial Board (6 November 2017). [http://www.chicagotribune.com/news/opinion/editorials/ct-edit-communism-bolshevik-anniversary-putin-20171106-story.html "The legacy of 100 years of communism: 65 million deaths"] ''Chicago Tribune''. {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171107032519/http://www.chicagotribune.com/news/opinion/editorials/ct-edit-communism-bolshevik-anniversary-putin-20171106-story.html|date=7 November 2017}}. Retrieved 14 November 2020.&lt;/ref&gt;

The criticism of some of the estimates, especially those of Rummel and ''The Black Book of Communism'' which made use of Rummel's estimates and analysis, are mostly focused on three aspects, namely that the estimates were based on sparse and incomplete data when significant errors are inevitable; that the figures were skewed to higher possible values; and that those dying at war and victims of civil wars, Holodomor and other famines under Communist governments should not be counted.&lt;ref name="Harff 1996"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Kuromiya, Hiroaki (2001). "Review Article: Communism and Terror. Reviewed Work(s): ''The Black Book of Communism: Crimes, Terror, and Repression'' by Stephane Courtois; Reflections on a Ravaged Century by Robert Conquest". ''Journal of Contemporary History''. '''36''' (1): 191–201. {{doi|10.1177/002200940103600110}}. {{jstor|261138}}. {{S2CID|49573923}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Paczkowski, Andrzej (2001). "The Storm Over the Black Book". ''The Wilson Quarterly''. '''25''' (2): 28–34. {{jstor|40260182}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Weiner, Amir (2002). "Review. Reviewed Work: ''The Black Book of Communism: Crimes, Terror, Repression'' by Stéphane Courtois, Nicolas Werth, Jean-Louis Panné, Andrzej Paczkowski, Karel Bartošek, Jean-Louis Margolin, Jonathan Murphy, Mark Kramer". ''The Journal of Interdisciplinary History''. '''32''' (3): 450–452. {{doi|10.1162/002219502753364263}}. {{jstor|3656222}}. {{S2CID|142217169}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Dulić, Tomislav (2004). "Tito's Slaughterhouse: A Critical Analysis of Rummel's Work on Democide". ''Journal of Peace Research''. '''41''' (1): 85–102. {{doi|10.1177/0022343304040051}}. {{jstor|4149657}}. {{S2CID|145120734}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Harff, Barbara (2017), [https://link.springer.com/content/pdf/10.1007%2F978-3-319-54463-2_12.pdf "The Comparative Analysis of Mass Atrocities and Genocide"]. In Gleditsch, N. P., ed. ''R.J. Rummel: An Assessment of His Many Contributions''. '''37'''. SpringerBriefs on Pioneers in Science and Practice. pp. 111–129. {{doi|10.1007/978-3-319-54463-2_12}}. {{ISBN|9783319544632}}.&lt;/ref&gt; According to [[Anton Weiss-Wendt]], any attempts to develop a universally-accepted terminology describing mass killings of non-combatants was a complete failure.&lt;ref&gt;Weiss-Wendt, Anton (2008). "Problems in Comparative Genocide Scholarship". In Stone, Dan (eds). ''The Historiography of Genocide''. London: Palgrave Macmillan. p. 42. {{doi|10.1057/9780230297}}. {{ISBN|978-0-230-29778-4}}. "There is barely any other field of study that enjoys so little consensus on defining principles such as definition of genocide, typology, application of a comparative method, and timeframe. Considering that scholars have always put stress on prevention of genocide, comparative genocide studies have been a failure. Paradoxically, nobody has attempted so far to assess the field of comparative genocide studies as a whole. This is one of the reasons why those who define themselves as genocide scholars have not been able to detect the situation of crisis."&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Classicide]]
* [[Genocides in history]]
* [[Language death]]
* [[List of genocides by death toll]]
* [[Mass murder]]
* [[Policide]]
* [[Politicide]]

== References ==
{{reflist}}

== External links ==
* [http://www.hawaii.edu/powerkills Power Kills] – the website of Rudolph Rummel

[[Category:Crimes]]
[[Category:Genocide]]
[[Category:Human rights abuses]]
[[Category:Murder]]
[[Category:Political neologisms]]
[[Category:Violence]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>