<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20020827112044|177227" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="8587" pageid="8587" ns="0" title="Democide"><revisions><rev timestamp="2002-08-27T11:47:16Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Democide''' is a term coined by political scientist [[R. J. Rummel]] to describe the [[mass murder]] of persons by a government or its agents. It is distinct from [[genocide]], as the targeted group may not be chosen for reason of nationality or ethnicity. For example, government-sponsored killings for political reasons would be considered democide.

While of relatively recent origin, the word has been picked up for wider usage, particularly by activists for [[human rights]].  It should, however, be noted that the term is not yet considered to be generally accepted.

=== Accusations of Democide ===

Accusations of mass killings by a government are relatively common. Less common are well-documented cases with enough evidence to support the accusation.  Almost all accusations are disputed to some degree, although the evidence in some cases is stronger than in others.  For instance, many of the figures cited in ''Death by Government'', in which R.J. Rummel first coined the term,  have been criticized for not taking into account numbers of deaths caused by the absence of government by means such as anarchy, civil disorder, or foreign invasion. 

For example:
* The [[United States]] and [[Pakistan]] have been accused in collaborating in democide in [[Afghanistan]] during 2001, by the restricting access of humanitarian aid during a period of severe famine. [[Noam Chomsky]] has been one of the more prominent voices laying this accusation.   The number of deaths that can be attributed to the restriction is heavily disputed (numbers range from none to over a million deaths). Also significantly disputed are whether the restriction was used deliberately as a weapon of war.</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>