<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20051026212916|26561120" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="313075" pageid="313075" ns="0" title="Identity politics"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-11-11T14:48:10Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Identity politics''' is the [[political]] activity of various [[social movement]]s which represent and seek to advance the interests of particular groups in society, the members of which often share and unite around common experiences of actual or perceived [[social injustice]]. Such groups argue that they are in some way socially or politically disenfranchised, marginalized or disadvantaged relative to the wider society of which they form part. These movements seek to achieve better social and political outcomes for the members of such groups. In this way, the ''identity'' of the oppressed group gives rise to a ''political'' basis around which they then unite.

==Description==
Identity politics also encompasses the development of a [[identity (social science)|social identity]] for group members, such that references to “my people” gain currency, and a body of thought which may be used to challenge dominant [[stereotype]]s about group members. 

Identity politics may be based around [[race]], [[ethnicity]], [[sex]], [[religion]], [[caste]], [[sexual orientation]], [[disability rights movement|physical disability]] or some other assigned or perceived [[trait]]. Some groups have blended certain amounts of [[social class]] analysis and [[class consciousness]] into their beliefs (e.g., the [[Black Panther Party]]), but by and large, group identity is established by reference to identification with surface appearance or characteristics only.

Identity politics in the [[political left]] is based on the argument that the putatively [[oppression|oppressed]] group in question has its own problems to deal with before it can unite with the rest of the [[working class]] to confront what they consider to be the wider problem of [[capitalism]]. Identity politics essentially says that ''special oppression requires special liberation;'' i.e., that separate organizations or organizational strategies are needed for each oppressed group to deal with its special problem, rather than dealing with those problems as aspects of [[class society]].

The group identity will deal with and seek to alleviate injustices associated with real or perceived oppression against them based on that identity.  This may involve low-level social and legislative reform like [[affirmative action]] with the goal that people within the group can in this way achieve [[equality]]. It can also involve a [[separatist]] approach.  Particular focus in any form of identity politics is on the contrast between what is considered to be a social, political and occupational [[privilege]] of the dominant group(s) as compared to what is considered to be the [[discrimination]] faced by the oppressed group.

== Forms of identity politics ==

Ethnic nationalism may be regarded as a form of identity politics within the wider international community. Examples of identity politics within societies include, but are not limited to:

*[[nationalism]]
**[[Black nationalism]]
**[[Irish nationalism]]
**[[Hispanic nationalism]]
**[[White nationalism]]

*[[Autism rights movement|Autism rights]]
*[[Christian fundamentalism]]
*[[Disability rights movement|Disability rights]]
*[[Feminism]]
*[[Gay rights]]
*[[Transgendered rights]]
*[[Deaf culture]]
*[[Islamic fundamentalism]]
*[[Masculism]]
*[[Racism]]
*[[Zionism]]

==Criticism==
The [[political right]] tends to deem it inappropriate that a minority, in claiming an identity, expects an enumeration of unprecedented rights.  In the case of the enumeration of [[gay rights]], this opinion is underpinned by a general discouragement of homosexual activity by what are considered ahistorical religious texts, which greatly complicates the issue.

Another criticism of identity politics comes from the [[Radical Left]]. As noted above, this sector of the left considers identity politics detrimental to the [[working class]] culture they hope to see take the forefront upon revolution to overthrow [[capitalism]]. To these critics, identity politics unnecessarily divides the working class against one another. With the development of a political and social consciousness in the [[United States]] and [[Europe]] that overwhelmingly emphasizes [[individualism|individual liberty]] as opposed to the rights of [[social class|large groups]], the overarching [[socioeconomic]] problems with capitalism tend to be ignored in identity politics.  The result, identities pitted against identities, creates an ideal situation for the [[ruling class]]. Resources and organizational opportunities for deeply positive change are squandered in the relentless search for specific group identity.  The Radical Left would argue that capitalism created the circumstances of [[inequality]] whereby the formation of identities was deemed necessary in the first place. Thus, undertaking identity politics is like taking cough suppressant for a cold:  it attacks the symptoms of a problem, but not its cause.

Even given the above, some of those considering themselves Radical Left (socialist, communist and anarchist) have in recent years begun to [[opportunism|opportunistically]] support identity politics or aspects of identity politics in an attempt to appear more modern and open. This move has been denounced by other Radical Leftists.

==See also==

''[[White privilege (sociology)|White Skin Privilege]]''

==External links==
*[http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/identity-politics/ Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy entry on identity politics]

[[Category:Political terms]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>