<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20211128051314|1057530292" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="313075" pageid="313075" ns="0" title="Identity politics"><revisions><rev timestamp="2021-11-28T05:45:51Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|Politics based on one's identity}}
{{use dmy dates|date=August 2018}}
'''Identity politics''' is a political approach wherein people of a particular [[gender]], [[religion]], [[Race (human categorization)|race]], [[Socioeconomic status|social background]], [[social class|class]] or other identifying factors, develop political agendas that are based upon these identities. The term is used in a variety of ways to describe phenomena as diverse as [[multiculturalism]], [[women's movements]], [[civil rights]], [[LGBT movements|lesbian and gay movements]], and regional [[separatist movements]].&lt;ref name="Bernstein 2005 pp. 47–74"&gt;{{cite journal | last=Bernstein | first=Mary | title=Identity Politics | journal=Annual Review of Sociology | publisher=Annual Reviews | volume=31 | year=2005 | issn=03600572 | eissn=15452115 | jstor=29737711 | pages=47–74 | url=http://www.jstor.org/stable/29737711 | access-date=2021-11-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Many contemporary advocates of identity politics take an [[Intersectionality theory|intersectional perspective]], which accounts for the range of interacting systems of oppression that may affect their lives and come from their various identities. According to many who describe themselves as advocates of identity politics, it centers the lived experiences of those facing systemic oppression; the purpose is to better understand the interplay of racial, economic, sex-based, and gender-based oppression (among others) and to ensure no one group is disproportionately affected by political actions, present and future.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Garza|first=Alicia|title=Identity Politics: Friend of Foe?|url=https://belonging.berkeley.edu/identity-politics-friend-or-foe|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Smith|first=Barbara|title=It's Really Up To Us: Barbara Smith on Combahee, Coalitions and Dismantling White Supremacy|url=https://millennialsarekillingcapitalism.libsyn.com/its-really-up-to-us-barbara-smith-on-combahee-coalitions-and-dismantling-white-supremacy|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://monthlyreview.org/2019/01/01/a-black-feminist-statement/|title=A Black Feminist Statement|date=January 2019|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; Such contemporary applications of identity politics describe people of specific race, ethnicity, sex, [[gender identity]], [[sexual orientation]], age, economic class, disability status, education, religion, language, profession, political party, veteran status, and geographic location. These identity labels are not mutually exclusive but are in many cases compounded into one when describing hyper-specific groups. An example is that of [[African-American]], [[homosexual]], [[women]], who constitute a particular hyper-specific identity class.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|url=https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/15295030903015062|doi=10.1080/15295030903015062|title="Queer Nation is Dead/Long Live Queer Nation": The Politics and Poetics of Social Movement and Media Representation|year=2009|last1=Gray|first1=Mary L.|journal=Critical Studies in Media Communication|volume=26|issue=3|pages=212–236|s2cid=143122754}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Critics of identity politics have seen it as [[Political_particularism|particularist]], in contrast to the [[universalism]] of [[Liberalism|liberal]] perspectives, or argue that it detracts attention from non-identity based structures of oppression. Those who take an intersectional perspective, such as [[Kimberle Crenshaw]], criticise narrower forms of identity politics which over-emphasise inter-group differences and ignore intra-group differences and forms of oppression.

== Terminology ==
The term was coined by the [[Combahee River Collective]] in 1977.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Home Girls: A Black Feminist Anthology|publisher=Kitchen Table: Women of Color Press|year=1983|isbn=0-913175-02-1|editor-last=Smith|editor-first=Barbara|location=New York, NY|pages=xxxi-xxxii}}&lt;/ref&gt; The collective group of women saw identity politics as an analysis that introduced opportunity for Black women to be actively involved in politics, while simultaneously acting as a tool to authenticate Black women's personal experiences.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://www.worldcat.org/oclc/975027867|title=How we get free : Black feminism and the Combahee River Collective|others=Taylor, Keeanga-Yamahtta.|year=2017|isbn=978-1-60846-855-3|location=Chicago, Illinois|oclc=975027867}}&lt;/ref&gt; It took on widespread usage in the early 1980s,{{Clarify|reason=The citation mentions it first entered main political discourse in the 1990s, beforehand only being discussed in left-wing environments. What is 'widespread' defined as?|date=February 2021}} and in the ensuing decades has been employed in myriad cases with radically different connotations dependent upon the term's context.&lt;ref name="Wiarda-2016" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|url=http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/identity-politics/|title=Identity Politics|first=Cressida|last=Heyes|journal=Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy|publisher=Metaphysics Research Lab, [[Center for the Study of Language and Information|CSLI]], [[Stanford University]]|access-date=2012-11-11|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20060830015202/http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/identity-politics/|archive-date=30 August 2006|url-status=live|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; It has gained currency with the emergence of [[social activism]],{{Clarify|reason=Social activism has long preceded the 80's, what does "emergence" mean exactly?|date=July 2020}} manifesting in various dialogues within the [[feminist movement|feminist]], American [[civil rights movement|civil rights]], and [[LGBT]] movements, as well as multiple [[nationalist]] and [[postcolonial]] organizations.&lt;ref name=OB/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Gray|first=John|title=Divided we stand: identity politics and the threat to democracy|url=https://www.newstatesman.com/john-gray-identity-politics-contemporary-francis-fukuyama-lies-bind-kwame-anthony-appiah-review|access-date=2020-06-11|website=www.newstatesman.com|date=26 September 2018|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In academic usage, the term ''identity politics'' refers to a wide range of political activities and theoretical analyses rooted in experiences of injustice shared by different, often excluded social groups. In this context, identity politics aims to reclaim greater self-determination and political freedom for marginalized peoples through understanding particular [[paradigm]]s and lifestyle factors, and challenging externally imposed characterizations and limitations, instead of organizing solely around ''[[status quo]]'' belief systems or traditional party affiliations.&lt;ref name="Stanford"/&gt; ''Identity'' is used "as a tool to frame political claims, promote political ideologies, or stimulate and orient social and political action, usually in a larger context of inequality or injustice and with the aim of asserting group distinctiveness and belonging and gaining power and recognition."&lt;ref name="OB"&gt;{{cite encyclopedia|encyclopedia=Oxford Bibliographies|author=Vasiliki Neofotistos|title=Identity Politics|url=http://www.oxfordbibliographies.com/view/document/obo-9780199766567/obo-9780199766567-0106.xml|publisher=Oxford University Press|year=2013|access-date=18 February 2019|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20181027214156/http://www.oxfordbibliographies.com/view/document/obo-9780199766567/obo-9780199766567-0106.xml|archive-date=27 October 2018|url-status=live|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==
The term ''identity politics'' may have been used in political discourse since at least the 1970s.&lt;ref name="Wiarda-2016"&gt;{{cite book |last=Wiarda |first=Howard J. |title=Political Culture, Political Science, and Identity Politics: An Uneasy Alliance |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=1hHtCwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA150 |date=8 April 2016 |publisher=[[Routledge]] |location=[[Abingdon-on-Thames|Abingdon]] |isbn=978-1-317-07885-2 |oclc=982044314 |orig-year=1st pub. [[Ashgate]]:2014 |access-date=21 February 2018 |quote=There are disputes regarding the origins of the term 'identity politics' .... Almost all authors, even while disagreeing over who was the first to use the term, agree that its original usage goes back to the 1970s and even the 1960s. |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170819161909/https://books.google.com/books?id=1hHtCwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA150 |archive-date=19 August 2017 |url-status=live |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; The first known written appearance of the term is found in the April 1977 statement of the [[Black feminist]] [[Socialism|socialist]] group, [[Combahee River Collective]], which was originally printed in 1979's ''Capitalist Patriarchy and the Case for Socialist Feminism'',&lt;ref&gt;''[https://www.google.com/books/edition/Capitalist_Patriarchy_and_the_Case_for_S/4SqXDwAAQBAJ Capitalist Patriarchy and the Case for Socialist Feminism]'', ed. Zillah R. Eisenstein (New York: Monthly Review Press, 1979)&lt;/ref&gt; later in ''Home Girls: A Black Feminist Anthology,'' edited by [[Barbara Smith]], a founding member of the Collective,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Home Girls: A Black Feminist Anthology|publisher=Kitchen Table: Women of Color Press|year=1983|isbn=0-913175-02-1|editor-last=Smith|editor-first=Barbara|location=New York, NY|pages=275}}&lt;/ref&gt; who have been credited with coining the term.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Collier-Thomas|first1=edited by Bettye|last2=Franklin|first2=V.P.|title=Sisters in the struggle African American women in the civil rights-black power movement|date=2001|publisher=New York University Press|location=New York|isbn=978-0-8147-1603-8|page=39|edition=[Online-Ausg.].|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=iR6NVzFEntgC&amp;pg=PA194|access-date=11 October 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180617165603/https://books.google.com.au/books?id=iR6NVzFEntgC&amp;pg=PA194|archive-date=17 June 2018|url-status=live|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Harris |first=Duchess |chapter=From the Kennedy Commission to the Combahee Collective: Black Feminist Organizing, 1960–1980 |title=Sisters in the Struggle: African American Women in the Civil Rights-Black Power Movement |publisher=[[NYU Press]] |date=2001 |isbn=0-8147-1603-2 |page=300}}&lt;/ref&gt; In their terminal statement, they said:&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Home Girls: A Black Feminist Anthology|publisher=Kitchen Table: Women of Color Press|year=1983|isbn=0-913175-02-1|editor-last=Smith|editor-first=Barbara|edition=1st|location=New York, NY|pages=275}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Quote
| quote     = [A]s children we realized that we were different from boys and that we were treated different—for example, when we were told in the same breath to be quiet both for the sake of being 'ladylike' and to make us less objectionable in the eyes of white people. In the process of consciousness-raising, actually life-sharing, we began to recognize the commonality of our experiences and, from the sharing and growing consciousness, to build a politics that will change our lives and inevitably end our oppression....We realize that the only people who care enough about us to work consistently for our liberation are us. Our politics evolve from a healthy love for ourselves, our sisters and our community which allows us to continue our struggle and work. This focusing upon our own oppression is embodied in the concept of identity politics. We believe that the most profound and potentially most radical politics come directly out of our own identity, as opposed to working to end somebody else's oppression.
| author    = Combahee River Collective
| title     = "The Combahee River Collective Statement"&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://circuitous.org/scraps/combahee.html|title=The Combahee River Collective Statement|access-date=4 April 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170224021117/http://circuitous.org/scraps/combahee.html|archive-date=24 February 2017|url-status=live|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|source=|book=
}}
Identity politics, as a mode of categorizing, are closely connected to the ascription that some social groups are oppressed (such as women, [[ethnic minorities]], and [[sexual minorities]]); that is, the idea that individuals belonging to those groups are, by virtue of their identity, more vulnerable to forms of oppression such as [[cultural imperialism]], [[violence]], [[exploitation of labour]], [[marginalization]], or subjugation.&lt;ref name=Stanford&gt;{{cite web|last1=Heyes|first1=Cressida|title=Identity Politics|url=https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/identity-politics/|website=The Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy|publisher=Metaphysics Research Lab, Stanford University|access-date=3 May 2017|date=1 January 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170327180804/https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/identity-politics/|archive-date=27 March 2017|url-status=live|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; Therefore, these lines of social difference can be seen as ways to gain empowerment or avenues through which to work towards a more equal society.&lt;ref name=":0"/&gt; In the United States, identity politics is usually ascribed to these oppressed minority groups who are fighting discrimination. In Canada and Spain, identity politics has been used to describe [[Separatism|separatist]] movements; in Africa, Asia, and eastern Europe, it has described violent nationalist and ethnic conflicts. Overall, in Europe, identity politics are exclusionary and based on the idea that the [[silent majority]] needs to be protected from [[globalization]] and [[immigration]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|doi=10.1146/annurev-polisci-050718-033542|doi-access=free|title=Identity Politics and Populism in Europe|year=2020|last1=Noury|first1=Abdul|last2=Roland|first2=Gerard|journal=Annual Review of Political Science|volume=23|pages=421–439}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some groups have combined identity politics with [[Marxism|Marxist]] [[social class]] analysis and [[class consciousness]]—the most notable example being the [[Black Panther Party]]—but this is not necessarily characteristic of the form. Another example is the group [[MOVE (Philadelphia organization)|MOVE]], which mixed [[Black nationalism]] with [[anarcho-primitivism]] (a radical form of [[green politics]] based on the idea that civilization is an instrument of oppression, advocating the return to a [[hunter gatherer]] society).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=by Committee|title=Philadelphia Special Investigation Commission (MOVE) Records {{!}} Temple University Libraries|url=https://library.temple.edu/scrc/philadelphia-special-1|website=library.temple.edu|access-date=3 May 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170501205105/https://library.temple.edu/scrc/philadelphia-special-1|archive-date=1 May 2017|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=no attrib.|title=On a Move – Website of the MOVE Organization|url=http://onamove.com/|website=onamove.com|access-date=3 May 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170429085111/http://onamove.com/|archive-date=29 April 2017|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; Identity politics can be [[Left-wing politics|left-wing]] or [[Right-wing politics|right-wing]], with examples of the latter being [[Ulster Loyalism|Ulster Loyalist]], [[Islamism|Islamist]] and [[Christian Identity]] movements, and examples of the former being [[queer nationalism]] and [[black nationalism]].

During the 1980s, the politics of identity became very prominent and it was also linked to a new wave of social movement activism.&lt;ref name='Calhoun'&gt;{{cite book |last1=Calhoun |first1=Craig |author-link1=Craig Calhoun |title=Social Theory and the Politics of Identity|editor=Craig Calhoun|publisher=Blackwell |year=1994 |isbn=978-1-55786-473-4}}{{page needed|date=September 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Debates and criticism==
===Nature of the movement===
The term ''identity politics'' has been applied retroactively to varying movements that long predate its coinage. Historian [[Arthur Schlesinger Jr.]] discussed identity politics extensively in his 1991 book ''[[The Disuniting of America]]''.  Schlesinger, a strong supporter of liberal conceptions of [[civil rights]], argues that a [[liberal democracy]] requires a common basis for culture and society to function. Rather than seeing civil society as already fractured along lines of power and powerlessness (according to race, ethnicity, sexuality, etc.), Schlesinger suggests that basing politics on group marginalization is itself what fractures the civil polity, and that identity politics therefore works against creating real opportunities for ending marginalization. Schlesinger believes that "movements for civil rights should aim toward full acceptance and integration of marginalized groups into the mainstream culture, rather than … perpetuating that marginalization through affirmations of difference."&lt;ref&gt;M.A. Chaudhary &amp; Gautam Chaudhary, Global Encyclopaedia of Political Geography, New Delhi, 2009, {{ISBN|978-81-8220-233-7}}, p. 112&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Brendan O'Neill (journalist)|Brendan O'Neill]] has suggested that identity politics causes (rather than simply recognizing and acting on) political schisms along lines of [[social identity]]. Thus, he contrasts the politics of [[gay liberation]] and identity politics by saying: "[[Peter Tatchell|[Peter] Tatchell]] also had, back in the day, … a commitment to the politics of liberation, which encouraged gays to come out and live and engage. Now, we have the politics of identity, which invites people to stay in, to look inward, to obsess over the body and the self, to surround themselves with a moral forcefield to protect their worldview—which has nothing to do with the world—from any questioning."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Brendan|first1=O'Neill|title=Identity politics has created an army of vicious, narcissistic cowards|url=https://www.spectator.co.uk/article/identity-politics-has-created-an-army-of-vicious-narcissistic-cowards|work=The Spectator|access-date=28 June 2015|date=19 February 2015|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150630173221/http://blogs.spectator.co.uk/coffeehouse/2015/02/identity-politics-has-created-an-army-of-vicious-narcissists/|archive-date=30 June 2015|url-status=live|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{undue inline|Why is O'Neill noteworthy?|date=November 2021}}

Similarly in the United Kingdom, author [[Owen Jones (writer)|Owen Jones]] argues that identity politics often marginalize the [[working class]], saying:
{{quote|In the 1950s and 1960s, left-wing intellectuals who were both inspired and informed by a powerful labour movement wrote hundreds of books and articles on working-class issues. Such work would help shape the views of politicians at the very top of the Labour Party. Today, progressive intellectuals are far more interested in issues of identity. ... Of course, the struggles for the emancipation of women, gays, and ethnic minorities are exceptionally important causes. New Labour has co-opted them, passing genuinely progressive legislation on gay equality and women's rights, for example. But it is an agenda that has happily co-existed with the sidelining of the working class in politics, allowing New Labour to protect its radical flank while pressing ahead with Thatcherite policies.|Owen Jones|''[[Chavs: The Demonization of the Working Class]]''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Jones|first1=Owen|title=Chavs: The Demonization of the Working Class|url=https://archive.org/details/chavsdemonizatio00jone_371|url-access=limited|date=2012|publisher=Verso|location=London|isbn=978-1-84467-864-8|page=[https://archive.org/details/chavsdemonizatio00jone_371/page/n142 255]|edition=updated}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{undue inline|Why is Jones noteworthy?|date=November 2021}}}}

===LGBT issues===
{{See also|LGBT social movements|Queer nationalism|Political lesbianism|Bisexual politics}}
The [[gay liberation]] movement of the late 1960s through the mid-1980s urged [[lesbian]]s and [[gay men]] to engage in radical [[direct action]], and to counter societal shame with [[gay pride]].&lt;ref name=HoffmanIntro&gt;{{cite book|last=Hoffman|first= Amy |title=An Army of Ex-Lovers: My life at the Gay Community News |year=2007 |publisher=University of Massachusetts Press |isbn=978-1558496217 |pages=xi–xiii}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the [[feminism|feminist]] spirit of the personal being political, the most basic form of activism was an emphasis on [[coming out]] to family, friends and colleagues, and living life as an openly lesbian or [[gay]] person.&lt;ref name=HoffmanIntro/&gt; While the 1970s were the peak of "gay liberation" in New York City and other urban areas in the United States, "gay liberation" was the term still used instead of "gay pride" in more oppressive areas into the mid-1980s, with some organizations opting for the more inclusive, "lesbian and gay liberation".&lt;ref name=HoffmanIntro/&gt;&lt;ref name=Hoffman2007&gt;{{cite book|last=Hoffman|first= Amy |title=An Army of Ex-Lovers: My life at the Gay Community News |year=2007 |publisher=University of Massachusetts Press |isbn=978-1558496217 }}&lt;/ref&gt; While women and [[transgender]] activists had lobbied for more inclusive names from the beginning of the movement, the [[initialism]] [[LGBT]], or "[[Queer]]" as a counterculture shorthand for [[LGBT]], did not gain much acceptance as an umbrella term until much later in the 1980s, and in some areas not until the '90s or even '00s.&lt;ref name=HoffmanIntro/&gt;&lt;ref name=Hoffman2007/&gt;&lt;ref name=Hollibaugh&gt;{{cite web|author1=phoenix|title=Gay Rights Are Not Queer Liberation|url=http://www.autostraddle.com/gay-rights-are-not-queer-liberation-the-nation-interviews-amber-hollibaugh-140431/|website=autostraddle.com|date=29 June 2012|access-date=1 March 2015|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150402122449/http://www.autostraddle.com/gay-rights-are-not-queer-liberation-the-nation-interviews-amber-hollibaugh-140431/|archive-date=2 April 2015|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; During this period in the United States, identity politics were largely seen in these communities in the definitions espoused by writers such as self-identified, "black, dyke, feminist, poet, mother" [[Audre Lorde]]'s [[Audre Lorde#Personal identity|view]], that [[lived experience]] matters, defines us, and is the only thing that grants authority to speak on these topics; that, "If I didn't define myself for myself, I would be crunched into other people's fantasies for me and eaten alive."&lt;ref name=Zami&gt;{{Cite book|title=Zami: A New Spelling of My Name|last=Lorde|first=Audre|publisher=Crossing Press|year=1982|isbn=978-0-89594-123-7|location=New York|title-link=Zami: A New Spelling of My Name}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Kemp&gt;Kemp, Yakini B. (2004). "Writing Power: Identity Complexities and the Exotic Erotic in Audre Lorde's writing". ''Studies in the Literary Imagination''. '''37''': 22–36.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Leonard&gt;Leonard, Keith D. (28 September 2012). [https://muse.jhu.edu/article/486572 ""Which Me Will Survive": Rethinking Identity, Reclaiming Audre Lorde"] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20161220052903/https://muse.jhu.edu/article/486572 |date=20 December 2016 }}. ''Callaloo''. '''35''' (3): 758–77. {{doi|10.1353/cal.2012.0100}}. {{ISSN|1080-6512}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

By the 2000s, in some areas of [[postmodernism|postmodern]] [[queer studies]] (notably those around [[gender]]) the idea of "identity politics" began to shift away from that of naming and claiming lived experience, and authority arising from lived experience, to one emphasizing choice and performance.&lt;ref name=4-encylopedia&gt;{{cite encyclopedia|title=Queer Theory and the Social Construction of Sexuality|encyclopedia=Homosexuality|publisher=Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy|access-date=15 November 2011|url=http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/homosexuality/#QueTheSocConSex|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20111209062102/http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/homosexuality/#QueTheSocConSex|archive-date=9 December 2011|url-status=live|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some who draw on the work of authors like [[Judith Butler]] particularly stress this concept of remaking and unmaking performative identities.&lt;ref name=ButlerPerformative&gt;{{Cite journal|title = Performative Acts and Gender Constitution: An Essay in Phenomenology and Feminist Theory|last = Butler|first = Judith|date = 1988 |journal = Theatre Journal |volume=40 |issue=4 |pages=519–531|doi = 10.2307/3207893|jstor = 3207893}}&lt;/ref&gt; Writers in the field of [[Queer theory]] have at times taken this to the extent as to now argue that "queer", despite generations of specific use to describe a "non-heterosexual" sexual orientation,&lt;ref name="oed"&gt;{{cite encyclopedia  | year =2014 | title = queer | encyclopedia = Oxford English Dictionary | publisher = Oxford University Press}}&lt;/ref&gt; no longer needs to refer to any specific sexual orientation at all; that it is now only about "disrupting the mainstream", with author [[David M. Halperin]] arguing that straight people may now also self-identify as "queer".&lt;ref name=Halperin&gt;{{cite book |author=Halperin, David M. |title=One Hundred Years of Homosexuality: And Other Essays on Greek Love |publisher=Routledge |location=New York |year=1990 |isbn=978-0-415-90097-3 |title-link=One Hundred Years of Homosexuality }}&lt;/ref&gt; However, many LGBT people believe this concept of "[[queer heterosexuality]]" is an oxymoron and offensive form of [[cultural appropriation]] which not only robs gays and lesbians of their identities, but makes invisible and irrelevant the actual, lived experience of oppression that causes them to be marginalized in the first place.&lt;ref name="appropriation"&gt;{{cite news |last=Mortimer |first=Dora |date=9 February 2016 |title= Can Straight People Be Queer? - An increasing number of young celebrities are labeling themselves 'queer.' But what does this mean for the queer community? |url= https://www.vice.com/en_us/article/avy9vz/can-straight-people-be-queer-435 |website=[[Vice Media]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=4-encylopedia/&gt; "It desexualizes identity, when the issue is precisely about a sexual identity."&lt;ref name=Jagose&gt;[[Annamarie Jagose|Jagose, Annamarie]], 1996. ''Queer Theory: An Introduction''. New York: New York University Press.&lt;/ref&gt;

Some supporters of identity politics take stances based on [[Gayatri Chakravorty Spivak]]'s work (namely, "Can the Subaltern Speak?") and have described some forms of identity politics as [[strategic essentialism]], a form which has sought to work with [[Hegemony|hegemonic]] discourses to reform the understanding of "universal" goals.&lt;ref name=Spivak&gt;{{Cite book|title=Other Asias|last=Spivak|first=Gayatri Chakrovotry|publisher=Blackwell Publishing|year=2008|isbn=978-1405102070|location=Malden, M.A.|pages=260}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Abraham&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Abraham|first=Susan|year=2009|title=Strategic Essentialism in Nationalist Discourses: Sketching a Feminist Agenda in the Study of Religion|url=https://muse.jhu.edu/article/266799|journal=Journal of Feminist Studies in Religion|volume=25|issue=1|pages=156–161|via=Project Muse|doi=10.2979/fsr.2009.25.1.156|s2cid=143105193|access-date=17 December 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171018190808/https://muse.jhu.edu/article/266799|archive-date=18 October 2017|url-status=live|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Ritze&gt;G. Ritze/J. M. Ryan eds., ''The Concise Encyclopedia of Sociology'' (2010) p. 193&lt;/ref&gt; Others point out the erroneous logic and the ultimate dangers of reproducing strong identitarian divisions inherent in essentialism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Kurzwelly|first=J.|author2=Rapport, N.|author3=Spiegel, A. D.|title=Encountering, explaining and refuting essentialism|journal=Anthropology Southern Africa|year=2020|volume=43|issue=2|pages=65–81|doi=10.1080/23323256.2020.1780141|s2cid=221063562}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Critiques and criticisms of identity politics===

Those who criticize identity politics from the right see it as inherently [[Collectivism|Collectivist]] and [[Prejudice|prejudicial]], in contradiction to the ideals of [[Classical liberalism]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last1=Leadership|first1=Jonathan Haidt is the Thomas Cooley Professor of Ethical|last2=Institute|first2=NYU Stern School of Business This essay is an edited version of his Wriston Lecture for the Manhattan|last3=November 15|first3=delivered on|date=2017-12-17|title=The Age of Outrage|url=https://www.city-journal.org/html/age-outrage-15608.html|access-date=2021-03-08|website=City Journal|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; Those who criticize identity politics from the left see it as a version of [[bourgeois nationalism]], i.e. as a [[Divide and rule|divide and conquer]] [[strategy]] by the [[ruling class]]es to divide people by [[nationality]], [[Race (classification of human beings)|race]], [[ethnicity]], [[religion]], etc. so as to [[Distraction|distract]] the [[working class]] from uniting for the purpose of [[Class conflict|class struggle]].&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt;&lt;ref name="KišičekŽagar2013"&gt;{{cite book|author1=Gabrijela Kišiček|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=RlKaBQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA471|title=What Do We Know About the World?: Rhetorical and Argumentative Perspectives|author2=Igor Ž. Žagar|date=3 October 2013|publisher=University of Windsor|isbn=978-0-920233-70-2|page=471|quote=One of the most famous rallying cries of communism Workers of the world, unite!}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Niezen2008"&gt;{{cite book|author=Ronald Niezen|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=m8W6xPPdYLcC&amp;pg=PA129|title=A World Beyond Difference: Cultural Identity in the Age of Globalization|date=15 April 2008|publisher=John Wiley &amp; Sons|isbn=978-1-4051-3710-2|page=129|quote=The famous rallying cry from The Communist Manifesto, “workers of the world unite!” was meant only to hasten the [...]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Parenti"/&gt;

[[File:Anti-capitalism color— Restored.png|right|thumb|The [[Industrial Workers of the World]] poster "[[Pyramid of Capitalist System]]" (1911)]] Critics argue that groups based on a particular shared identity (e.g. race, or gender identity) can divert energy and attention from more fundamental issues, similar to the history of [[divide and rule]] strategies. [[Chris Hedges]] has criticized identity politics as one of the factors making up a form of "[[corporate capitalism]]" that only masquerades as a political platform, and which he believes "will never halt the rising social inequality, unchecked militarism, evisceration of civil liberties and omnipotence of the organs of security and surveillance."&lt;ref name=HedgesTD&gt;{{cite news |last=Hedges |first=Chris |date=5 February 2018 |title=The Bankruptcy of the American Left |url=https://www.truthdig.com/articles/bankruptcy-american-left/ |work=Truthdig |access-date=9 February 2018 |author-link=Chris Hedges |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180209135923/https://www.truthdig.com/articles/bankruptcy-american-left/ |archive-date=9 February 2018 |url-status=dead |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; Sociologist [[Charles Derber]] asserts that the American left is "largely an identity-politics party" and that it "offers no broad critique of the political economy of capitalism. It focuses on reforms for Blacks and women and so forth. But it doesn’t offer a contextual analysis within capitalism." Both he and [[David North (socialist)|David North]] of the [[Socialist Equality Party (United States)|Socialist Equality Party]] posit that these fragmented and isolated identity movements which permeate the left have allowed for a far-right resurgence.&lt;ref name=HedgesTD/&gt; [[Cornel West]] asserted that discourse on racial, gender and sexual orientation identity was "crucial" and "indispensable," but emphasized that it "must be connected to a moral integrity and deep political solidarity that hones in on a financialized form of predatory capitalism. A capitalism that is killing the planet, poor people, working people here and abroad."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |date=December 3, 2020 |title=Cornel West: "Bernie Was Crushed by Neoliberalism" |url=https://jacobinmag.com/2020/12/cornel-west-interview-bernie-black-lives-matter |work=[[Jacobin (magazine)|Jacobin]] |access-date=December 7, 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Critiques of identity politics have also been expressed by writers such as [[Eric Hobsbawm]],&lt;ref name=":2"&gt;{{cite web |last=Hobsbawm |first=Eric |date=2 May 1996 |url=http://banmarchive.org.uk/articles/1996%20annual%20lecture.htm |title=Identity Politics and the Left |website=Institute of Education |access-date=April 29, 2021 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170918013136/http://banmarchive.org.uk/articles/1996%20annual%20lecture.htm |archive-date=18 September 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Todd Gitlin]],&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.pbs.org/thinktank/transcript235.html PBS.org] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170804215455/http://www.pbs.org/thinktank/transcript235.html |date=4 August 2017 }}, Thinktank transcript 235&lt;/ref&gt; [[Michael Tomasky]], [[Richard Rorty]], [[Michael Parenti]],&lt;ref name="Parenti"&gt;{{citation|last=Parenti|first=Michael|title=Blackshirts and Reds: Rational Fascism and the Overthrow of Communism|year=1997|publisher=[[City Lights Bookstore|City Lights Books]]|location=San Francisco|isbn=978-0872863293|page=151|author-link=Michael Parenti|quote="Seizing upon anything but class, U.S. leftists today have developed an array of identity groups centering around ethnic, gender, cultural, and life-style issues. These groups treat their respective grievances as something apart from class struggle, and have almost nothing to say about the increasingly harsh politico-economic ''class'' injustices perpetrated against us all."}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Jodi Dean]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Dean|first=Jodi|author-link=Jodi Dean|date=2012|title=The Communist Horizon|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=kBghOq42S3YC&amp;pg=PA53|publisher=Verso|page=53|isbn=978-1844679546}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Sean Wilentz]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ppionline.org/ppi_ci.cfm?knlgAreaID=115&amp;subsecID=172&amp;contentID=2049|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100116130524/http://www.ppionline.org/ppi_ci.cfm?knlgAreaID=115&amp;subsecID=172&amp;contentID=2049 |archive-date=16 January 2010 |last=Sleeper |first=Jim |title=In Defense of Civic Culture |date=1 January 1993|publisher=[[Progressive Policy Institute]]. ppionline.org |access-date=4 September 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; and philosopher [[Slavoj Žižek]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=Slavoj|last=Žižek|author-link=Slavoj Žižek|title=Ein Plädoyer für die Intoleranz|year=2015|isbn=9783709201886|publisher= Passagen Verlag Ges.M.B.H |lang=German}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hobsbawm, as a Marxist,  criticized nationalisms and the principle of national self-determination adopted in many countries after 1919, since in his view national governments are often merely an expression of a ruling class or power, and their proliferation was a source of the wars of the 20th century. Hence, Hobsbawm argues that identity politics, such as [[queer nationalism]], [[Islamism]], [[Cornish nationalism]] or [[Ulster loyalism]] are just other versions of [[bourgeois nationalism]]. The view that identity politics (rooted in challenging racism, sexism, and the like) obscures class inequality is widespread in the United States and other Western nations. This framing ignores how class-based politics are identity politics themselves, according to [[Jeff Sparrow]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2016/nov/18/class-and-identity-politics-are-not-mutually-exclusive-the-left-should-use-this-to-its-benefit|title=Class and identity politics are not mutually exclusive. The left should use this to its benefit {{!}} Jeff Sparrow|last=Sparrow|first=Jeff|date=17 November 2016|website=the Guardian|language=en|access-date=2018-07-17|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180718030629/https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2016/nov/18/class-and-identity-politics-are-not-mutually-exclusive-the-left-should-use-this-to-its-benefit|archive-date=18 July 2018|url-status=live|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Intersectional critiques ===
In her journal article ''Mapping the Margins: Intersectionality, Identity Politics and Violence against Women of Color,'' [[Kimberle Crenshaw]] treats identity politics as a process that brings people together based on a shared aspect of their identity. Crenshaw applauds identity politics for bringing African Americans (and other non-white people), gays and lesbians, and other oppressed groups together in community and progress.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Crenshaw|first=Kimberle|author-link=Kimberle Crenshaw|date=1 January 1991|title=Mapping the Margins: Intersectionality, Identity Politics, and Violence against Women of Color|jstor=1229039|journal=Stanford Law Review|volume=43|issue=6|pages=1241–99|doi=10.2307/1229039|citeseerx=10.1.1.695.5934}}&lt;/ref&gt; But she critiques it because "it frequently conflates or ignores intragroup differences."&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;&amp;nbsp;Crenshaw argues that for Black women, at least two aspects of their identity are the subject of oppression: their race and their sex.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Demarginalizing the Intersection of Race and Sex: A Black Feminist Critique of Antidiscrimination Doctrine, Feminist Theory and Antiracist Politics|last=Crenshaw|first=Kimberle|publisher=University of Chicago Legal Forum|year=1989|pages=139–68|url=https://philpapers.org/archive/CREDTI.pdf?source=post_page---------------------------}}&lt;/ref&gt; Thus, although identity politics are useful, we must be aware of the role of&amp;nbsp;[[intersectionality]]. Nira Yuval-Davis supports Crenshaw's critiques&amp;nbsp;in ''Intersectionality and Feminist Politics''&amp;nbsp;and explains that "Identities are individual and collective narratives that answer the question 'who am/are I/we?"&amp;nbsp;&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Yuval-Davis|first=Nira|date=1 August 2006|title=Intersectionality and Feminist Politics|url=http://ejw.sagepub.com/content/13/3/193|journal=European Journal of Women's Studies|language=en|volume=13|issue=3|pages=193–209|doi=10.1177/1350506806065752|s2cid=145319810|issn=1350-5068|access-date=11 April 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20161103075104/http://ejw.sagepub.com/content/13/3/193|archive-date=3 November 2016|url-status=live|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In ''Mapping the Margins'', Crenshaw illustrates her point using the&amp;nbsp;[[Clarence Thomas Supreme Court nomination|Clarence Thomas]]/[[Anita Hill]] controversy. Anita Hill [[Clarence Thomas Supreme Court nomination#Anita Hill testimony|accused]] US Supreme Court Justice nominee Clarence Thomas of sexual harassment; Thomas would be the second African American judge on the Supreme Court. Crenshaw argues that Hill was then deemed anti-Black in the movement against racism, and although she came forward on the feminist issue of sexual harassment, she was excluded because when considering feminism, it is the narrative of white middle-class women that prevails.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; Crenshaw concludes that acknowledging intersecting categories when groups unite on the basis of identity politics is better than ignoring categories altogether.&lt;ref name=":0"/&gt;

== Examples ==
{{Main category|Identity politics}}

=== Racial and ethnocultural ===
{{Further|Ethnocultural politics in the United States}}

Ethnic, religious and racial identity politics dominated American politics in the 19th century, during the [[Second Party System]] (1830s–1850s)&lt;ref&gt;Daniel Walker Howe, "[https://academic.oup.com/jah/article-abstract/77/4/1216/850758 The Evangelical Movement and Political Culture in the North During the Second Party System]," ''Journal of American History'' (1991) 77#4 pp: 1216-1239.&lt;/ref&gt; as well as the [[Third Party System]] (1850s–1890s).&lt;ref&gt;Jon Gjerde, ''The Minds of the West: Ethnocultural Evolution in the Rural Middle West, 1830-1917'' (1999).&lt;/ref&gt; Racial identity has been the central theme in Southern politics since slavery was abolished.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |first=Harold D. |last=Woodman |url=https://www.jstor.org/stable/2211941 |title=Class, Race, Politics, and the Modernization of the Postbellum South |journal=The Journal of Southern History |volume=63 |issue=1 |date=February 1997 |pages=3–22 |doi=10.2307/2211941 |jstor=2211941 |access-date=May 6, 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Similar patterns appear in the 21st century are commonly referenced in popular culture,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.newsweek.com/2019/11/15/literary-influences-superstar-musician-david-bowie-1468145.html |title=The Literary Influences of Superstar Musician David Bowie|author=John O'Connell|quote=As the husband of a Muslim woman from Somalia, [[David Bowie|Bowie]] couldn't help but be highly attuned to racial identity politics.|date=31 October 2019|work=[[Newsweek]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; and are increasingly analyzed in media and social commentary as an interconnected part of politics and society.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://time.com/5444761/donald-trump-midterms-race-candidates/ |title=How President Trump Put Race at the Center of the Midterms|author=Tessa Berenson|quote=Some Republicans worry that Trump’s focus on racial identity politics so close to the election is undercutting their message to swing voters on subjects like the economy and health care.|date=6 November 2018|work=[[TIME]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.smh.com.au/national/opponents-on-the-left-pouring-gasoline-on-donald-trump-s-fires-20190818-p52i92.html |title=Opponents on the left pouring gasoline on Donald Trump's fires|author-link=James Kirchick|author=James Kirchick|quote=Trump’s game isn’t difficult to discern. He is practicing the same resentment-based, racial-identity politics that has fuelled his political rise since the earlier part of this decade, when he began expressing doubts that the first black American president was actually born in the United States.|date=19 August 2019|work=[[The Sydney Morning Herald]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Both a majority and minority group phenomenon, racial identity politics can develop as a reaction to the historical legacy of race-based oppression of a people&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Tamar Mayor|title=Gender Ironies of Nationalism: Sexing the Nation|date=2012|publisher=[[Routledge]]|isbn=978-0415162555|page=331|quote=For example, where a legacy of oppression based on race exists, an identity politics of race can be formed in opposition to that form of oppression, and can help to provide an occasion for racial pride and resistance to that oppression.}}&lt;/ref&gt; as well as a general group identity issue, as "racial identity politics utilizes racial consciousness or the group's collective memory and experiences as the essential framework for interpreting the actions and interests of all other social groups."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=James Jennings|title=Blacks, Latinos, and Asians in Urban America: Status and Prospects for Politics and Activism|date=1994|publisher=[[Praeger Publishing]]|isbn=978-0275949341|page=35|chapter=Building Coalitions}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Carol M. Swain]] has argued that non-white ethnic pride and an "emphasis on racial identity politics" is fomenting the rise of [[white nationalism]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Carol M. Swain|author-link1=Carol M. Swain|title=The New White Nationalism in America: Its Challenge to Integration|date=2004|publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]]|isbn=978-0521545587|page=xvi|chapter=Preface|quote=The continued emphasis on racial identity politics and the fostering of an ethnic group pride on the part of nonwhite minority groups.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Anthropologist [[Michael Messner]] has suggested that the [[Million Man March]] was an example of racial identity politics in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Michael A. Messner|author-link1=Michael Messner|title=Politics of Masculinities: Men in Movements|date=1997|publisher=[[SAGE Publications]]|isbn=978-0803955776|page=[https://archive.org/details/politicsofmascul00mess/page/79 79-80]|chapter=Racial and sexual identity politics|chapter-url=https://archive.org/details/politicsofmascul00mess/page/79}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Black feminist identity politics ====
{{See also|Black feminism|Combahee River Collective|Black women in American politics}}
Black feminist identity politics concern the identity-based politics derived from the lived experiences of struggles and oppression faced by Black women.&lt;ref name=":03"&gt;{{Cite book|last=Hooper|first=Cindy|title=Conflict: African American Women and the New Dilemma of Race and Gender Politics|publisher=ABC-CLIO|year=2012|location=California|pages=44–45}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1977, the [[Combahee River Collective]] (CRC) Statement argued that black women struggled with facing their oppression due to the sexism present within the [[Civil rights movement|Civil Rights Movement]] and the racism present within [[second-wave feminism]]. This statement—in which the CRC coined the term "identity politics"—gave black women in the U.S. a political foothold—both within radical movements and at large—from which they could confront the oppression they were facing. The CRC also claimed to expand upon the prior feminist adage that "the personal is political,"&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://www.worldcat.org/oclc/975027867|title=How we get free : Black feminism and the Combahee River Collective|others=Taylor, Keeanga-Yamahtta.|date=5 December 2012|isbn=978-1-64259-104-0|location=Chicago, Illinois|oclc=975027867}}&lt;/ref&gt; pointing to their own consciousness-raising sessions, centering of black speech, and communal sharing of experiences of oppression as practices that expanded the phrase's scope. As mentioned earlier K. Crenshaw, claims that the oppression of black women is illustrated in two different directions: race and sex.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|last=Crenshaw|first=Kimberle|title=Demarginalizing the Intersection of Race and Sex: A Black Feminist Critique of Antidiscrimination Doctrine, Feminist Theory, and Antiracist Politics [1989]|date=2018-02-19|url=http://dx.doi.org/10.4324/9780429500480-5|work=Feminist Legal Theory|pages=57–80|publisher=Routledge|doi=10.4324/9780429500480-5|isbn=978-0-429-50048-0|access-date=2020-10-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

In 1988, Deborah K. King coined the term [[Multiple jeopardy]], theory that expands on how factors of oppression are all interconnected. King suggested that the identities of gender, class, and race each have an individual prejudicial connotation, which has an incremental effect on the inequity of which one experiences&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=King|first=Deborah K.|date=1988-10-01|title=Multiple Jeopardy, Multiple Consciousness: The Context of a Black Feminist Ideology|url=https://www.journals.uchicago.edu/doi/10.1086/494491|journal=Signs: Journal of Women in Culture and Society|volume=14|issue=1|pages=42–72|doi=10.1086/494491|issn=0097-9740|s2cid=143446946}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1991, Nancie Caraway explained from a white feminist perspective that the politics of black women had to be comprehended by broader feminist movements in the understanding that the different forms of oppression that black women face (via race and gender) are interconnected, presenting a compound of oppression ([[Intersectionality]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Caraway|first=Nancie E.|date=1991|title=The Challenge and Theory of Feminist Identity Politics: Working on Racism|url=https://www.jstor.org/stable/3346851|journal=Frontiers: A Journal of Women Studies|volume=12|issue=2|pages=109–129|doi=10.2307/3346851|jstor=3346851}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Muslim identity politics ====
A ''[[Le Monde]]''/[[IFOP]] poll in January 2011 conducted in France and Germany found that a majority felt Muslims are "scattered improperly"; an analyst for ''IFOP'' said the results indicated something "beyond linking immigration with security or immigration with unemployment, to linking Islam with a threat to identity".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|date=6 January 2011|title=European Poll: An Islamic Threat?|work=[[Al Jazeera]]|url=http://www.aljazeera.com/indepth/features/2011/01/201116112228783789.html|url-status=live|access-date=19 October 2012|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20121014114808/http://www.aljazeera.com/indepth/features/2011/01/201116112228783789.html|archive-date=14 October 2012|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Arab identity politics ====
{{See also|Arab identity|Arab nationalism}}
Arab identity politics concerns the identity-based politics derived from the racial or ethnocultural consciousness of [[Arab people]]. In the [[Regionalism (international relations)|regionalism]] of the [[Middle East]], it has particular meaning in relation to the national and cultural identities of non-Arab countries, such as Turkey, Iran and North African countries .&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Arshin Adib-Moghaddam|title=Middle East Review (IDE-JETRO)|date=2010|publisher=[[Institute of Developing Economies]]|location=[[Japan External Trade Organization]]|isbn=978-0980415810|edition=Volume 7|chapter=The myth of "National Identity": Psycho-nationalism in Iran and the Arab world|quote=Iranian and Arab identity politics thwarted, perverted, and dismembered communitarian thinking for long periods in the twentieth century and the same applies to other forms of psycho-nationalism in Turkey}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Elizabeth Monier|title=[[Contemporary Politics (journal)|''Contemporary Politics'']]|chapter=The Arabness of Middle East regionalism: the Arab Spring and competition for discursive hegemony between Egypt, Iran and Turkey|date=2014|publisher=[[Taylor &amp; Francis]]|edition=Volume 20, No. 4|pages=421–434|quote=To explore the role played by Arab identity politics in regionalism with regard to the status of non-Arab states, this article presents a study of the competing hegemonic regional discourses employed by Turkey, Iran and Egypt}}&lt;/ref&gt; In their 2010 ''Being Arab: Arabism and the Politics of Recognition'', academics [[Christopher Wise]] and [[Paul James (academic)|Paul James]] challenged the view that, in the post-[[War in Afghanistan (2001–present)|Afghanistan]] and [[Iraq War|Iraq]] invasion era, Arab identity-driven politics were ending. Refuting the view that had "drawn many analysts to conclude that the era of Arab identity politics has passed", Wise and James examined its development as a viable alternative to [[Islamic fundamentalism]] in the Arab world.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Christopher Wise|author2=Paul James|author-link1=Christopher Wise|author-link2=Paul James (academic)|title=Being Arab: Arabism and the Politics of Recognition|date=2010|publisher=[[Arena (Australian publishing co-operative)|Arena Publications]]|isbn=978-0980415810}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to [[Marc Lynch]], the post-[[Arab Spring]] era has seen increasing Arab identity politics, which is "marked by state-state rivalries as well as state-society conflicts". Lynch believes this is creating a new [[Arab Cold War]], no longer characterized by Sunni-Shia sectarian divides but by a reemergent [[Arab identity]] in the region.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Lynch|first1=Mark|author-link=Marc Lynch|title=The Arab Uprisings Explained: New Contentious Politics in the Middle East|date=2019|publisher=[[Columbia University Press]]|isbn=978-0231158855|page=119}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Najla Said]] has explored her lifelong experience with Arab identity politics in her book ''Looking for Palestine''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.salon.com/2013/07/28/najla_said_my_arab_american_story_is_not_typical_in_any_way/|title=Najla Said: "My Arab-American story is not typical in any way"|work=[[Salon (website)]]|date=28 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Māori identity politics ====
{{See also|Māori identity|Māori nationalism}}
Due to somewhat competing tribe-based versus pan-Māori concepts, there is both an internal and external utilization of Māori identity politics in New Zealand.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Roger Maaka|author2=Augie Fleras|title=The Politics of Indigeneity: Challenging the State in Canada and Aotearoa New Zealand|date=2005|publisher=[[Otago University Press]]|isbn=978-1877276538|page=67|quote=The tensions created by the intersection of tribe as identity, versus tribe as organisation, are central to Maori identity politics.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Projected outwards, Māori identity politics has been a disrupting force in the [[politics of New Zealand]] and post-colonial conceptions of nationhood.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Tatiana Tökölyová|title=Journal of Nationalism, Memory &amp; Language Politics|date=2005|publisher=[[Walter de Gruyter]]|location=[[University of International and Public Relations Prague]]|page=67|edition=Volume 11, Edition 1|chapter=Transnationalism in the Pacific Region as a Concept of State Identity|quote=Maori identity politics have disrupted the colonially-inspired constructions of the New Zealand nation and state from a base of indigeneity.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Its development has also been explored as causing parallel ethnic identity developments in non-Māori populations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Hal B. Levine|title=Constructing collective identity: a comparative analysis of New Zealand Jews, Maori, and urban Papua New Guineans|date=1997|publisher=[[Peter Lang (publisher)|Peter Lang]]|isbn=978-3631319444|page=11|quote=The material on biculturalism particularly shows how ethnicity interdigitates with identity politics for Maori and stimulates parallel developments among non-Maori New Zealanders.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Academic [[Alison Jones]], in her co-written ''Tuai: A Traveller in Two Worlds'', suggests that a form of Māori identity politics, directly oppositional to [[Pākehā]] (white New Zealanders), has helped provide a "basis for internal collaboration and a politics of strength".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|editor1=Te Kawehau Hoskins|editor2=Alison Jones|title=Critical Conversations in Kaupapa Maori|date=2005|publisher=[[Huia Publishers]]|isbn=978-1775503286|quote=As Jones and Jenkins (2008) point out, an oppositional Māori identity politics has been the 'basis for internal collaboration and a politics of strength' (p.475).}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A 2009, [[Ministry of Social Development (New Zealand)|Ministry of Social Development]] journal identified Māori identity politics, and societal reactions to it, as the most prominent factor behind significant changes in self-identification from the 2006 New Zealand census.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |url=https://www.msd.govt.nz/about-msd-and-our-work/publications-resources/journals-and-magazines/social-policy-journal/spj36/36-in-search-of-ethnic-new-zealanders.html |author1=Tahu Kukutai |author2=Robert Didham |journal=Social Policy Journal of New Zealand |date=2009 |publisher=[[Ministry of Social Development (New Zealand)]] |title=In Search of Ethnic New Zealanders: National Naming in the 2006 Census |quote=Māori identity politics and Treaty settlements, as well as their reactions – the latter included challenges to historical settlements and so-called “race-based” funding. |access-date=May 6, 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== White identity politics ====
{{See also|White identity|White nationalism|White supremacy|White backlash|Identitarian movement}}

In 1998, political scientists [[Jeffrey Kaplan (academic)|Jeffrey Kaplan]] and Leonard Weinberg predicted that, by the late 20th-century, a "Euro-American radical right" would promote a trans-national [[White people|white]] identity politics, which would invoke populist grievance narratives and encourage hostility against non-white peoples and [[multiculturalism]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Jeffrey Kaplan|author-link1=Jeffrey Kaplan (academic)|author2=Leonard Weinberg|title=The Emergence of a Euro-American Radical Right|date=1998|publisher=[[Rutgers University Press]]|isbn=978-0813525648|page=18}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the United States, mainstream news has identified [[Donald Trump]]'s presidency as a signal of increasing and widespread utilization of white identity politics within the Republican Party and political landscape.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://apnews.com/c13df86fa32d4938b4d15f205531719a |title=Trump's America: Where politics dictate definition of racism|author1=Claire Galofaro|author2=Bill Barrow|quote=Bremner’s show carries just one current of the heated national debate on race that has been fanned by Trump’s unrepentant use of white identity politics|date=August 6, 2019|publisher=[[Associated Press]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Journalists [[Michael Scherer]] and [[David Smith (journalist)|David Smith]] have reported on its development since the mid-2010s.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2019/dec/07/kamala-harris-democratic-primary-whitewash-2020-debates |title=After Kamala: activists fear Democratic primary whitewash|author-link=David Smith (journalist)|author=David Smith|quote=Donald Trump’s Republican party has leaned into white identity politics.|date=December 8, 2019|work=[[The Guardian]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/white-identity-politics-drives-trump-and-the-republican-party-under-him/2019/07/16/a5ff5710-a733-11e9-a3a6-ab670962db05_story.html |title=White identity politics drives Trump, and the Republican Party under him|author-link=Michael Scherer|author=Michael Scherer|quote=Trump’s combustible formula of white identity politics already has reshaped the Republican Party, sidelining, silencing or converting nearly anyone who dares to challenge the racial insensitivity of his utterances.|date=July 16, 2019|work=[[The Washington Post]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Ron Brownstein]] believed that President Trump uses "White Identity Politics" to bolster his base and that this would ultimately limit his ability to reach out to non-[[White American]] voters for the [[2020 United States presidential election]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2019/08/trump-2020-democrats-racism/596155/ |title=The Limits of Trump's White Identity Politics|author-link=Ron Brownstein|author=Ron Brownstein|date=August 15, 2019|work=[[The Atlantic]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; A four-year [[Reuters]] and [[Ipsos]] analysis concurred that "Trump's brand of white identity politics may be less effective in the 2020 election campaign."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.reuters.com/article/us-usa-election-race-poll/for-trump-appeals-to-white-fears-about-race-may-be-a-tougher-sell-in-2020-reuters-ipsos-poll-idUSKCN1V90TX |title=For Trump, appeals to white fears about race may be a tougher sell in 2020: Reuters/Ipsos poll|author=Chris Kahn|date=August 19, 2019|work=[[Reuters]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Alternatively, examining the same poll, [[David Smith (journalist)|David Smith]] has written that "Trump’s embrace of white identity politics may work to his advantage" in 2020.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2019/jul/21/trump-race-charlottesville-democrats-ilhan-omar-2020 |title='It's a political civil war': Trump's racist tirades set tone for 2020 |author-link=David Smith (journalist)|author=David Smith|quote=Intentionally or not, Trump’s embrace of white identity politics may work to his advantage next year... A Reuters/Ipsos poll showed his net approval among Republicans rose by five points to 72%.|date=December 8, 2019|work=[[The Guardian]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; During the [[2020 Democratic Party presidential primaries|Democratic primaries]], presidential candidate [[Pete Buttigieg]] publicly warned that the president and his administration were using white identity politics, which he said was the most divisive form of identity politics.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author1=Maureen Groppe|title=Pete Buttigieg says Donald Trump's white 'identity politics' contributing to a 'crisis of belonging'  |url=https://eu.usatoday.com/story/news/politics/elections/2019/05/12/pete-buttigieg-says-donald-trump-divides-white-identity-politics/1151265001/|newspaper=[[USA Today]] |date=May 13, 2019}}
* {{cite news|title=Pete Buttigieg warns Democrats about lure of identity politics  |url=https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2019/may/12/pete-buttigieg-human-rights-campaign-trump|newspaper=[[The Guardian]] |date=May 12, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; Columnist [[Reihan Salam]] writes that he is not convinced that Trump uses "white identity politics" given the fact that he still has significant support from liberal and moderate Republicans – who are more favorable toward immigration and the legalization of undocumented immigrants – but believes that it could become a bigger issue as whites become a minority and assert their rights like other minority groups.&lt;ref name=Salam&gt;{{Cite news|first=Reihan  |last= Salam |title=Reihan Salam: Is 'white nationalism' rising?   |newspaper=[[Dallas Morning News]]|date= Sep 25, 2015 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Salam also states that an increase in "white identity" politics is far from certain given the very high rates of [[Interracial marriage in the United States|intermarriage]] and the historical example of the once Anglo-Protestant cultural majority embracing a more inclusive white cultural majority which included Jews, Italians, Poles, Arabs, and Irish.&lt;ref name=Salam /&gt;{{undue weight inline|date=February 2021}}

Columnist [[Ross Douthat]] has argued that it has been important to American politics since the [[Richard Nixon]]-era of the Republican Party,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2019/09/10/opinion/racism-republicans-trump.html |title=Can the Right Escape Racism?|author-link=Ross Douthat|author=Ross Douthat|date=September 10, 2019|work=[[The New York Times]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; and historian [[Nell Irvin Painter]] has analyzed [[Eric Kaufmann]]'s thesis that the phenomenon is caused by immigration-derived [[racial diversity]], which reduces the white majority, and an "anti-majority adversary culture".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine |url=https://www.foreignaffairs.com/reviews/review-essay/2019-10-15/what-white-america |title= What Is White America? The Identity Politics of the Majority |author-link=Nell Irvin Painter|author=Nell Irvin Painter|date=November 1, 2019|magazine=[[Foreign Affairs]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Writing in ''[[Vox Media|Vox]]'', political commentator [[Ezra Klein]] believes that demographic change has fueled the emergence of white identity politics.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.vox.com/policy-and-politics/2019/7/16/20695031/trump-ocasio-cortez-omar-pressley-tlaib-pelosi-squad |title=Trump vs. "the Squad"|author-link=Ezra Klein|author=Ezra Klein|quote=The other views American politics through the lens of demographic change and the white identity politics it triggers.|date=July 16, 2019|publisher=[[Vox Media]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Asian-American identity politics[edit] ====
In the political realm of the United States, according to Jane Junn and Natalie Masuoka, the possibilities for an Asian American vote are built upon the assumption that those broadly categorized as Asian share a sense of racial identity, and that this [[Group consciousness (political science)|group consciousness]] has political consequences. However, the idea of a monolithic Asian American bloc has been challenged as populations are diverse in terms of national origin and language—no one group is predominant—and scholars suggest that these many diverse groups favor their distinctive national origin groups over any [[Pan-Asianism|pan-ethnic racial identity]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Junn|first=Jane|last2=Masuoka|first2=Natalie|date=2008|title=Asian American Identity: Shared Racial Status and Political Context|url=https://www.jstor.org/stable/20446825|journal=Perspectives on Politics|volume=6|issue=4|pages=729–740|issn=1537-5927}}&lt;/ref&gt;. According to the 2000 Consensus, more than six national origin groups are classified collectively as Asian American, and these include: Chinese (23%), Filipino (18%), Asian Indian (17%), Vietnamese (11%), Korean (11%), and Japanese (8%), along with an “other Asian” category (12%). In addition, the definitions applied to racial categories in the United States are uniquely American constructs that Asian American immigrants may not adhere to upon entry.

Jun and Masuoka find that in comparison to blacks, the Asian American identity is more latent, and racial group consciousness is more susceptible to the surrounding context.

=== Gender ===
Gender identity politics is an approach that views politics, both in practice and as an academic discipline, as having a gendered nature and that gender is an identity that influences how people think.&lt;ref&gt;Celis, K.  Kantola, J. Waylen, G. Weldon, S. [https://www.oxfordhandbooks.com/view/10.1093/oxfordhb/9780199751457.001.0001/oxfordhb-9780199751457-e-34?print=pdf 'Introduction: Gender and Politics: A Gendered World, a Gendered Discipline'], The Oxford Handbook of Gender and Politics, 2013&lt;/ref&gt; Politics has become increasingly gender political as formal structures and informal 'rules of the game' have become gendered. How institutions affect men and women differently are starting to be analysed in more depth as gender will affect institutional innovation.&lt;ref&gt;[Mona L. Krook, Fiona Mckay] [https://ebookcentral.proquest.com/lib/uea/reader.action?docID=665680] [Gender, Politics ans Institutions] [2011 Palgrave Macmillan]&lt;/ref&gt;

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

== Further reading ==
* Christopher T. Stout. 2020. ''[https://www.google.com/books/edition/The_Case_for_Identity_Politics/PGnaDwAAQBAJ The Case for Identity Politics: Polarization, Demographic Change, and Racial Appeals]''. University of Virginia Press.
* Mike Gonzales. 2018. "[https://www.heritage.org/civil-society/commentary/it-time-debate-and-end-identity-politics It Is Time to Debate—and End—Identity Politics]". The Heritage Foundation.

==External links==
{{commons category}}
{{wikiquote}}
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20161206100016/http://belfercenter.ksg.harvard.edu/project/57/religion_in_international_affairs.html Initiative on Religion in International Affairs] at Harvard
*[http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/identity-politics/ "Identity politics"], ''[[Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy]]'', 16 July 2002
*Joan Mandel. [https://userpages.umbc.edu/~korenman/wmst/identity_pol.html "How Political Is the Personal?: Identity Politics, Feminism and Social Change"], [[University of Maryland, Baltimore County]]
*[https://www.seattleweekly.com/news/a-marxist-critiques-identity-politics/ "A Marxist Critiques Identity Politics"]. ''[[Seattle Weekly]]''. 25 April 2017.
*[https://www.jacobinmag.com/2017/08/identity-politics-gay-rights-neoliberalism-stonewall-feminism-race "Identity Politics Can Only Get Us So Far"]. ''[[Jacobin (magazine)|Jacobin]]''. 3 August 2017.
*[https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2018/jul/14/identity-politics-right-left-trump-racism "Why identity politics benefits the right more than the left"]. ''[[The Guardian]]''. 14 July 2018.

{{DEFAULTSORT:Identity politics}}
[[Category:Identity politics| ]]
[[Category:Intersectionality]]
[[Category:Human rights]]
[[Category:Political terminology]]
[[Category:Postmodernism]]
[[Category:Majority–minority relations]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>