<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061112190741|87378590" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="313075" pageid="313075" ns="0" title="Identity politics"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-11-12T19:11:34Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">&lt;div class="notice metadata" id="cleanup" style="margin: 1em 10%; text-align:center; background:white; border:2px solid #9F9FFF;"&gt;
{| style="background: transparent;"
| width=25px |[[Image:Information_icon.svg|32px]]
|'''This article is missing [[WP:CITE|citations]] and/or [[Wikipedia:Footnote|footnotes]]'''.  
To meet Wikipedia's [[:Category:Wikipedia style guidelines|style guidelines]] and conform to our policies regarding [[Wikipedia:Neutral point of view|NPOV]] and [[Wikipedia:Verifiability|verifiability]], please provide appropriate citations and/or footnotes.&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;small&gt;''For guidance in this area, see [[Wikipedia:Footnotes#How to use]].''&lt;/small&gt;
|}&lt;/div&gt;
'''Identity politics''' is the [[political]] activity of various [[social movement]]s for [[self-determination]]. It claims to represent and seek to advance the interests of particular groups in society, the members of which often share and unite around common experiences of actual or perceived [[social injustice]], relative to the wider society of which they form part. In this way, the ''identity'' of the oppressed group gives rise to a ''political'' basis around which they then unite.

Despite the purportedly overlapping definitions with [[social identity]] its adherents claim it possesses, such as encompassing the development of a [[identity (social science)|social identity]] for group members and providing a body of thought which may be used to challenge dominant [[stereotype]]s, ''identity politics'' means more than the sole recognition of social identity such as [[religion]], [[ethnicity]], or [[culture]]. Rather, identity politics seeks to carry this social identity forward, beyond mere self-identification, to a political framework based upon that identity. For example, [[black nationalists]] argue not only that blacks are (or should be) a community, but that they are a community with a "historical [political] struggle," and that when united, they can actually be a cohesive ''political force'' against [[racism]] and claim their own agency outside of "white-controlled" movements. [[Hispanic nationalism]] argues similarly, but in regard to the [[Hispanic]] population. The more extreme forms of [[feminism]] argue that women should unite as women against [[sexism]] outside of "man-controlled" movements. Modern [[Jewish]] [[Zionism]] was originally [[secular]] (and marginal) within the Jewish community, but became driven by its own form of identity politics upon the formation of the [[State of Israel]] in 1948. 

This framework is qualitatively different from identity itself, which does not necessarily have to evolve into identity politics. Identity politics has close parallels with concepts like [[white skin privilege]] and [[self-determination]], both of which heavily rely on the core of identity politics to advance their thought.

==Overview==

Identity politics may be based around [[race]], [[ethnicity]], [[sex]], [[religion]], [[caste]], [[sexual orientation]], [[disability rights movement|physical disability]] or some other assigned or perceived [[Trait (biological)|trait]] (see below for a more complete, but still non-exhaustive, list). Some groups have historically blended [[social class]] analysis and [[class consciousness]] into such beliefs — e.g., the [[Black Panther Party]] — but by and large, identity politics are based on surface and "[[bloodline]]" characteristics only.

Along the [[political spectrum]] identity politics are based on the argument that a putatively [[oppression|oppressed]] group can use their identity as a source of collective resistance to their commonly felt oppression, and that these particular problems must be dealt with separately, on their own self-contained level, before the specific group can unite with the wider [[working class]] to deal with overall [[social]] [[oppression]], such as that which is perceived by [[leftists]] to be the product of [[capitalism]]. Essentially, identity politics is based on the concept that ''special oppression requires special liberation'', i.e., special circumstances existing outside of the wider one of [[class consciousness]].

The group identity will deal with and seek to alleviate injustices associated with real or perceived oppression against them based on that identity.  This may involve social and legislative reform like [[affirmative action]] with the goal that people within the group can in this way achieve [[equality]]. It can also involve a [[separatist]] approach.  Particular focus in any form of identity politics is on the contrast between what is considered to be a social, political and occupational [[privilege]] of the dominant group(s) as compared to what is considered [[discrimination]] faced by the oppressed group. In this relationship the dominant, [[normative]] group is privileged as compared to the oppression of the nondominant group.

==Criticism==

====From the Right====

The [[political right]] considers it inappropriate that a minority, in claiming an identity, expects an [[enumeration]] of unprecedented rights. The [[individualist]] (or [[libertarian]]) ideology of the right makes the idea that rights be granted based only on race, religion, gender, sexual orientation, or culture a [[non sequitur (logic)|non sequitur]]. Particularly in [[Age of Enlightenment |Enlightenment]] [[liberal democratic]] theory, if a "right" is extended to only a portion of society, it is no longer a right but a privilege. Thus, from the point of view of the political right, identity politics is not demanding rights to which it is actually entitled, but instead is demanding special privileges.

====From the Left====

The [[Radical Left]] considers identity politics detrimental to the [[working class]] culture they hope to see take the forefront upon revolution to overthrow [[capitalism]]. To these critics, identity politics unnecessarily divides the working class against itself. With the development of a political and social consciousness in the [[United States]] and [[Europe]] that overwhelmingly emphasizes [[individualism|individual liberty]] as opposed to the collective entitlements of [[social class|large groups]], radical leftists say that the overarching [[socioeconomic]] problems with capitalism tend to be ignored in identity politics. According to this view, resources and organizational opportunities for deeply positive change are squandered in the relentless search for specific group identity.  The Radical Left would argue that [[capitalism]] created the circumstances of [[inequality]] whereby the formation of identities was deemed necessary in the first place. Thus, undertaking identity politics is like taking cough suppressant for a cold:  it attacks the symptoms of a problem, but not its cause.

Some [[GLBT]] rights [[activist]]s criticize the identity politics approach to [[gay rights]], particularly the approach based around the terms and concepts of [[queer]] and [[queer theory]].  Gay and lesbian activists work for full acceptance of gays and lesbians in the institutions and culture of mainstream society, but it is alleged that "queer" activists instead make a point of declaring themselves outside of the mainstream and having no desire to be accepted by or join it.  The former criticize the latter's attitude as counterproductive and as perpetuating discrimination and societal attitudes against LGBT people. [http://www.indegayforum.org/news/show/27067.html] [http://www.indegayforum.org/news/show/27052.html]

====From the Center====

[[Arthur Schlesinger, Jr.]] discussed identity politics extensively in his book ''The Disuniting of America''.  Schlesinger, a strong supporter of the [[civil rights movement]], argues that a liberal democracy requires a common basis for culture and society to function.   In his view, basing one's politics on self-identifying as part of a marginalized group perceived to be outside of the mainstream of society causes this common basis to break down, and therefore works against creating real opportunities for ending this marginalization.  

Schlesinger believes that movements for civil rights should aim toward full acceptance and integration of marginalized groups into the mainstream culture, not perpetuate that marginalization.  Another critic of identity politics from the center is former Colorado governor [[Richard Lamm]], who wrote an article in 2005 which was circulated on the Internet [http://www.snopes.com/politics/soapbox/lamm.asp].

Identity Independence, as discussed on the Internet on a site of that name [http://www.identityindependence.com], means the right of a free people to choose their own identity and culture.

== Forms of identity politics ==

Ethnic nationalism may be regarded as a form of identity politics within the wider international community, as well as within individual countries. The broader categories of identity politics are [[Separatism]], [[Irredentism]], [[Revanchism]], and [[Jingoism]].

Specific types of identity politics include, but are not limited to:

*[[Ethnic nationalism]]s such as:
**[[Irish nationalism]]
**[[Welsh self-government]]
**[[Black nationalism]]
***[[pan-Africanism]]
***[[Black Power]]
***[[Black separatism]]
**[[Hispanic nationalism]]
***[[Chicano nationalism]]
***[[pan-Americanism]]
**[[Dalit Nationalism(India)|Dalit Nationalism]]
**[[White nationalism]]
*[[Religious fundamentalism|Religion-based identities]] such as:
**[[Hindu nationalism]]
**[[Christian fundamentalism]]
**[[Islamic fundamentalism]]
**[[Jewish fundamentalism]]
**[[Zionism|Jewish nationalism]]
*[[Gender]] or [[human sexuality|sexuality]]-based identities such as:
**[[Gay community]]
**[[Radical feminism]]
**[[Masculism]]
**[[Transgender|Transgender rights]]
*[[Disability]]-based identities such as:
**[[Disability rights movement|Disability rights]]
**The National [[Allergic asthma|Asthma]] [[National Asthma Campaign|Campaign]]
**[[Autism rights movement|Autism rights]]
**[[Deaf culture]]
**[[Diabetes]]
**[[Fat acceptance]]
**[[Thalassaemia]]

==Books &amp; Articles==

* Walker Connor, "Ethnology and the Peace of South Asia," ''World Politics'', Vol. 22, No. 1 (October 1969), pp. 51–86.
* Monica Duffy Toft, ''The Geography of Ethnic Violence: Identity, Interests, and the Indivisibility of Territory'' (Princeton NJ: Princeton University Press, 2003). ISBN 0-691-12383-7.

==See also==

* [[Affinity politics]] (opposed to identity politics, by [[Donna Haraway]])
* [[Neofascism and religion]]
*''[[White privilege (sociology)|White Skin Privilege]]''
* [[Particularism]]

==External links==
*[http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/identity-politics/ Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy] (Entry on identity politics.)
*[http://whiteprivilege.com WhitePrivilege.com] - An anti-racism resource.
*[http://www.identityindependence.com/fordlindbergh.html A page of Identity Independence] - the defamation of Charles Lindbergh and Henry Ford to prepare the U.S. public for later aggressive wars
* http://vlib.iue.it/carrie/texts/carrie_books/paksoy-7/  IDENTITIES: How Governed, Who Pays? Full-text

[[Category:Political terms]]

[[ja:アイデンティティ政治]]
[[fr:Communautarisme identitaire]]
[[yi:זעלביקייט (פאליטיש)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>