<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20020919002904|366987" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1078" pageid="1078" ns="0" title="Antisemitism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2002-10-18T15:46:09Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[de:Antisemitismus]]
'''Anti-Semitism''' is hostility or violence toward people because of their [[Jew|Jewish ancestry]]. Although sometimes used literally for hatred of all [[Semitic people]]s, the word "anti-Semitism" was coined specifically to refer to hatred of Jews. There are numerous forms of anti-Semitism, originating in different trends in human society, but usually having the common ground of [[xenophobia]]. 

== Etymology of the word ==
The word was coined in Germany in 1873 by [[Wilhelm Marr]] as a more [[euphemism|euphonious]] way of saying "Judenhass" (Jew-hatred). This name was chosen because Marr and others believed in a now discredited theory that held that certain racial groups and linguistic groups coincide. Semites, at the time, were defined as natives of a group of Middle Eastern nations related in ethnicity, culture and language. Under this theory Semites would include: Jews, the various Arab groups, and ancient nationalities such as the Assyrians, Canaanites, Carthaginians, Aramaeans and Akkadians (one of the ancestors of the ancient Babylonians). The theory of Semitic races has long since been discredited. 

The only Semitic people found in significant numbers in Germany at the time the word was coined were Jews, and because of that, anti-Semitism was considered a convenient way to name the hatred of Jews without reminding of either hatred or Jews. 

Since the late twentieth century, some advocates have argued that since Arabs speak a Semitic language, they by definition cannot be "anti-Semitic". Jewish, Christian and moderate Muslim groups (as well as English usage dictionaries) generally consider this just a word game (see [[semantic dispute]]). Anti-Semitism, in its generally accepted meaning, means solely hatred of Jews. See also [[Anti-Arab]].

Similarly, some writers and speakers have used "anti-Semitism" to mean hatred of either Jews or Arabs, considering both groups as "Semites". This is highly controversial, and they have been accused of distorting the meaning of the word for propaganda purposes.

== Theological anti-Semitism ==
Theological anti-Semitism blames the entire Jewish people for the death of [[Jesus Christ]], and for wilfully and deliberately refusing to believe in the New Testament, despite the fact that all Jews "know" that Christianity is the one true faith. Theological anti-Semitism was created by the New Testament's replacement theology, which taught that with the coming of Jesus a new covenant has rendered obsolete and has superseded the religion of [[Judaism]].

Mere disagreement with the religion of Judaism, as such, does not constitute anti-Semitism in any way. However, teaching that Jews murdered God, or that that they literally ''choose to follow a faith that they actually know is false'' (as many Christian preachers have claimed) constitutes the oldest and perhaps most widely spread form of anti-Semitism. Theological anti-Semitism is referred to by some historians and scholars as anti-Judaism to emphasize its relationship to the Jewish religion.

== Mystical, or Demonic, anti-Semitism ==
From the medieval era to the 1900s many Christians believed that some (or all) Jews possessed magical powers; depending on the culture, people believed that the Jews gained these magical powers from making a deal with the devil.

* "The Satanizing of the Jews: Origin and Development of Mystical Anti-Semitism" Joel Carmichael, from, 1992

== Economic Anti-Semitism ==
From the medieval era to today, many people believed that Jewish people unfairly took away jobs and money from Christians.  

One historical theory for the growth of this sentiment points to the medieval Christian prohibition of [[usury]], then defined as the  practice of loaning money at interest.  Because there remained a demand for the receipt of loans, non-Christians were much more likely to practice moneylending. Furthermore, Christian restrictions on what positions could be held by Jews closed off many alternatives, leaving banking as one of the few areas open to them.  This connection became established as a [[social stereotype]] in many medieval minds, leading to unjustified resentment of "usurious" Jews.  These feelings may well have been fanned by the cynical efforts of debtors to escape their debts.  The play ''[[The Merchant of Venice]]'' by [[William Shakespeare]] contains a character that is an example of such a stereotype, and attitudes toward that character reflected by the play suggest the prevalence of this economic anti-Semitism in medieval and Renaissance Europe.  


More commonly, there is prejudice against Jews largely on account of the fact that Jews are often, in spite of what ethnic and religious differences they have with the population at large, in positions of power and prestige.  Hence, anti-Jewish prejudice is very often, by the defenders of Jews and Jewishness, ascribed to envy more than to any sort of religious concern.

== Racial Anti-Semitism ==
Racial anti-Semitism, the most modern form of anti-Semitism, is a type of [[racism]] mixed with [[religious persecution]].  Racial anti-Semites believe erroneously that the Jewish people are a distinct race, and that Jews are inherently inferior to people of other races.

In fact the Jews are an evolving religious civilization that started out as a nationality in exile.  Most historians, as well as most Jewish people, consider Jews to be an ethnic group with the religion of [[Judaism]] at its core.

== Anti-Semitism in the 20th and 21st century Middle East ==
There are two major causes of anti-Semitism in the modern Middle East: the religious and the nationalistic.

Some [[Muslim]]s resent Jews and Israel for religious reasons. Examples include followers of the [[Shi'ite]] movement of Iran and Lebanon, and followers of the [[Wahabi]] School of Saudi Arabia.  According to their tractation of the Islamic law, all lands fall into one of only two possible legal categories (A) Land currently under Islamic control, and (B) Land once controlled by Muslims, that all Muslims worldwide are bound to re-conquer; such lands, including the State of Israel and Spain, are termed "lands under the sword".

The second cause of anti-Semitism is nationalistic: as in many other countries (for instance the 19th century Russia), a rise in nationalism is accompanied by increased xenophobia. The grievances caused to Arabs during the Arab-Israeli conflict give these feelings a powerful boost; Israel and Jews are often demonized - up to the extent that [[blood libel]] theories are routinely revived by Arab television networks. Some advocates explain the bitterness of Palestinian Arabs as a natural response to what they call unfair expulsion from "their country", an argument which presumes that the land from which they were expelled was rightfully "theirs" (see [[Palestinian homeland]]).

From a sociological point of view, the origin of much modern day anti-Semitism in these nations is due to indoctrination of young children to hate Jewish people from an early age. 

* Palestinian television programs for kindergarten age children feature songs about becoming suicide-bombers, and drenching shopping malls with Jewish blood
* Syrian and Palestinian school textbooks deny the existence of the State of Israel.
* Sponsoring of [[Holocaust denial|Holocaust-denying]] material by official Palestinian structures.

Children who have grown up in this atmosphere don't see themselves as anti-Semitic. In the last few years American and European politicians and human rights groups have begun criticising the Palestinian Authority and other middle-eastern Arab nations for such television shows and textbooks; they are held to be violations of the Oslo accords. The Palestinians claim a new batch of PA textbooks, printed in 2000, is more tolerant towards Jews and Israel; however both television broadcasts and anti-Semitic books and meetings are allowed to persist.

== Anti-Zionism ==
[[Zionism|Zionists]], people who support the right of Jews to an independent state, accuse [[Anti-Zionism]] of being almost always antisemitic. See [[Anti-Zionism]] for more discussion.

== Occurrence of anti-Semitism ==
Anti-Semitic beliefs are often held by people of many different ethnicities. Anti-Semitism has a long history, including persecution of Jews in Europe, the Middle East and the Western world at large. (Can someone expand on this?) Relations between Christians and Jews have at times been horrible, other times bad, yet at other times peaceful. In recent years there has been much reconciliation between Jews and Christians.  In many nations there has been a remarkable decline in anti-Semitism.

One of the most damaging anti-Semitic tractates published is the infamous Russian hoax,  [[The Protocols of the Elders of Zion]].

Common occurrences of anti-Semitism:
* [[Arab anti-semitism]]
* [[Christian anti-semitism]]
* [[KKK anti-semitism]] (see [[KKK]])
* [[Nazi anti-semitism]] (see [[Nazism]])
* [[Nation of Islam anti-semitism]]

See also: 
*[[Anti-Zionism]]
*[[Unification Church and anti-semitism]]
*[[Middle East]], [[Israel]], [[Zionism]], [[holocaust]], [[nazi|nazism]], [[Anti-Arab]]
*[[White supremacy]], [[conspiracy theory]]
*[[Semitic]], [[Semitic languages]], [[Shem]]

==External link==

* [http://www.us-israel.org/jsource/anti-semitism/Christian.html Christian-Jewish relations]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>