<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20101117205009|397372548" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1078" pageid="1078" ns="0" title="Antisemitism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2010-11-17T20:58:38Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{pp-move-indef}}
{{Antisemitism}}
'''Antisemitism''' (also spelled '''anti-semitism''' or '''anti-Semitism''') is [[prejudice]] against or hostility towards [[Jew]]s, often rooted in [[hatred]] of their [[Jewish ethnic divisions|ethnic background]], [[Secular Jewish culture|culture]], and/or [[Judaism|religion]]. In its extreme form, it "attributes to the Jews an exceptional position among all other civilizations, defames them as an inferior group and denies their being part of the nation[s]" in which they reside.&lt;ref&gt;Pauley, B.F. ''From Prejudice to Persecution: A History of Austrian Anti-Semitism'' Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina Press, 2002. p. 1&lt;/ref&gt; A person who holds such views is called an "antisemite."

Antisemitism may be manifested in many ways, ranging from individual expressions of hatred and [[discrimination]] against individual Jews to organized [[pogroms|violent attacks]] by [[Ochlocracy|mobs]] or even [[state (polity)|state]], [[police]] or [[military]] attacks on entire Jewish communities. Extreme instances of [[persecution]] include the [[Persecution of Jews in the First Crusade|First Crusade]] of 1096, the [[Edict of Expulsion|expulsion from England]] in 1290, the [[Spanish Inquisition]], the [[Alhambra decree|expulsion from Spain]] in 1492, the [[Jews in Portugal|expulsion from Portugal]] in 1497, various [[pogroms]], the [[Dreyfus Affair]], and perhaps the most infamous, [[the Holocaust]] in [[Nazi Germany]].

While the term's [[etymology]] might suggest that antisemitism is directed against all [[Semitic#Ancient Semitic peoples|Semitic peoples]], the term was coined in the late 19th century in Germany as a more scientific-sounding term for ''Judenhass'' ("Jew-hatred"),&lt;ref name=Judenhass&gt;See, for example:
*Jerome A. Chanes. ''[[Antisemitism: A Reference Handbook]]'', [[ABC-CLIO]], 2004, p. 150.
*Ali Rattansi. ''Racism: a very short introduction'', [[Oxford University Press]], 2007, p. 5.
*Richard L. Rubenstein, John K. Roth. ''Approaches to Auschwitz: the Holocaust and its legacy'', Westminster John Knox Press, 2003, p. 30.
*William M. Johnston. ''The Austrian mind: an intellectual and social history, 1848-1938'', [[University of California Press]], 1983, p. 27.&lt;/ref&gt;
and that has been its normal use since then.&lt;ref name=Lewis_MEI1973&gt;"Antisemitism has never anywhere been concerned with anyone but Jews." [[Bernard Lewis|Lewis, Bernard]]. [http://middleeastinfo.org/library/lewis_antisemitism.html "Semites and Antisemites"], ''Islam in History: Ideas, Men and Events in the Middle East'', The Library Press, 1973.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=JustJews&gt;See, for example:
*"Anti-Semitism", ''Encyclopaedia Britannica'', 2006.
*[[Paul Johnson (writer)|Johnson, Paul]]. ''A History of the Jews'', HarperPerennial 1988, p 133 ff.
*[[Bernard Lewis|Lewis, Bernard]]. [http://hnn.us/blogs/entries/21832.html "The New Anti-Semitism"], ''The American Scholar'', Volume 75 No. 1, Winter 2006, pp. 25-36. The paper is based on a lecture delivered at [[Brandeis University]] on March 24, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Forms==
The [[Roman Catholic]] historian [[Edward Flannery]] distinguished four varieties of antisemitism:&lt;ref&gt;Flannery, Edward H. ''The Anguish of the Jews: Twenty-Three Centuries of Antisemitism'', Stimulus Books, first published 1965, this edition 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;

*political and economic antisemitism, giving as examples [[Cicero]] and [[Charles Lindbergh]];
*[[Religious antisemitism|theological or religious antisemitism]], sometimes known as anti-Judaism;
*nationalistic antisemitism, citing [[Voltaire]] and other [[Age of Enlightenment|Enlightenment]] thinkers, who attacked Jews for supposedly having certain characteristics, such as greed and arrogance, and for observing customs such as [[kashrut]] and [[Shabbat]];
*and [[racial antisemitism]], with its extreme form resulting in the [[The Holocaust|Holocaust]] by the [[Nazi]]s.
In addition, from the 1990s, some writers claim to have identified a [[new antisemitism]], a form of antisemitism coming simultaneously from the [[Left-wing politics|far left]], the [[far right]], and [[Islamism|radical Islam]], which tends to focus on opposition to [[Zionism]] and a Jewish homeland in the [[State of Israel]], and which may deploy traditional antisemitism motifs, including older motifs like the "[[Blood Libel]]".&lt;ref name="New-AS-List"&gt;
*[[Phyllis Chesler|Chesler, Phyllis]]. ''The New Antisemitism: The Current Crisis and What We Must Do About It'', Jossey-Bass, 2003, pp. 158-159, 181
*[[Warren Kinsella|Kinsella, Warren]]. [http://www.warrenkinsella.com/words_extremism_nas.htm The New antisemitism], accessed March 5, 2006
*[http://observer.guardian.co.uk/uk_news/story/0,6903,1278580,00.html "Jews predict record level of hate attacks: Militant Islamic media accused of stirring up new wave of antisemitism"], ''[[The Guardian]]'', August 8, 2004.
*Endelman, Todd M. "Antisemitism in Western Europe Today" in ''Contemporary Antisemitism: Canada and the World''. University of Toronto Press, 2005, pp. 65-79
*Matas, David. ''Aftershock: Anti-Zionism and antisemitism'', p.31. Dundurn Press, 2005.
&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Holocaust denial]] and [[List of conspiracy theories#Jewish world domination|Jewish conspiracy]] theories are also considered a form of antisemitism.&lt;ref name="hoax"&gt;Mathis, Andrew E. [http://www.holocaust-history.org/denial/abc-clio/ Holocaust Denial, a Definition], [[The Holocaust History Project]], July 2, 2004. Retrieved May 16, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Michael Shermer &amp; Alex Grobman. ''Denying History: : who Says the Holocaust Never Happened and why Do They Say It?'', University of California Press, 2000, ISBN 0-520-23469-3, p. 106.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tau.ac.il/Anti-Semitism/asw2000-1/usa.htm Antisemitism and Racism Country Reports: United States], [[Stephen Roth Institute]], 2000. Retrieved May 17, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Deborah Lipstadt]]. ''Denying the Holocaust -- The Growing Assault on Truth and Memory'', Penguin, 1993, ISBN 0-452-27274-2, p. 27.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="adl.org"&gt;[http://www.adl.org/holocaust/theory.asp Introduction: Denial as Anti-Semitism], "Holocaust Denial: An Online Guide to Exposing and Combating Anti-Semitic Propaganda", [[Anti-Defamation League]], 2001. Retrieved June 12, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="adl.org"/&gt;
&lt;ref&gt;Lawrence N. Powell, ''Troubled Memory: Anne Levy, the Holocaust, and David Duke's Louisiana'', University of North Carolina Press, 2000, ISBN 0-8078-5374-7, p. 445.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name="antisemitic"&gt;[http://fra.europa.eu/fraWebsite/material/pub/AS/AS-WorkingDefinition-draft.pdf ''Working Definition of Antisemitism'']|33.8&amp;nbsp;KB, [[European Fundamental Rights Agency]]&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref&gt;[[Deborah Lipstadt]], ''Denying the Holocaust'', ISBN 0-14-024157-4, p. 11.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref&gt;Roth, Stephen J. "Denial of the Holocaust as an Issue of Law" in the ''Israel Yearbook on Human Rights'', Volume 23, Martinus Nijhoff Publishers, 1993, ISBN 0-7923-2581-8, p. 215.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref&gt;Austin, Ben S. [http://www.mtsu.edu/~baustin/revision.htm "Deniers in Revisionists Clothing"], The Holocaust\Shoah Page, [[Middle Tennessee State University]]. Retrieved March 29, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jpr.org.uk/Reports/CS_Reports/no_3_2000/index.htm The nature of Holocaust denial: What is Holocaust denial?], JPR report #3, 2000. Retrieved May 16, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref&gt;Schweitzer, Frederick M. &amp; Perry, Marvin. ''Anti-Semitism: myth and hate from antiquity to the present'', Palgrave Macmillan, 2002, ISBN 0-312-16561-7, p. 3.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref&gt;Palgrave Macmillan, 2002, ISBN 0-312-16561-7, p. 10.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref&gt;Geoffrey Short, Carole Ann Reed. ''Issues in Holocaust Education'', Ashgate Publishing, 2004, ISBN 0-7546-4211-9, p. 71.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref&gt;Stephen Trombley, "antisemitism", ''The Norton Dictionary of Modern Thought'', W. W. Norton &amp; Company, 1999, ISBN 0-393-04696-6, p. 40.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref&gt;Howard K. Wettstein, ''Diasporas and Exiles: Varieties of Jewish Identity'', University of California Press, 2002, ISBN 0-520-22864-2, p. 169.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Etymology and usage==
===Usage===
Despite the use of the prefix ''anti-'', the terms ''Semitic'' and ''anti-Semitic'' are not directly opposed to each other. ''Antisemitism'' refers specifically to prejudice against [[Jew]]s alone and in general,&lt;ref name=Lewis_MEI1973/&gt;&lt;ref name=JustJews/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/antisemitism Antisemitism – Definition and More from the Merriam-Webster Dictionary]&lt;/ref&gt; despite the fact that there are other speakers of [[Semitic language]]s (e.g. [[Arab]]s, [[Ethiopians]], or [[Assyrian people|Assyrians]]) and that not all Jews speak a Semitic language.

The term ''anti-Semitic'' has been used on occasion to include bigotry against other Semitic-language peoples such as Arabs, but such usage is not widely accepted.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
|title=Aftershock: anti-zionism and anti-semitism
|first=David
|last=Matas
|authorlink=David Matas
|page=34
|publisher=Dundum Press
|year=2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
|title=Semites and anti-Semites
|first=Bernard
|last=Lewis
|authorlink=Bernard Lewis
|page=117
|year=1999
|unused_data=W. W. Norton}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Both terms ''anti-Semitism'' and ''antisemitism'' are in common use. Some scholars favor usage of the unhyphenated form ''antisemitism'' to avoid possible confusion involving whether the term refers specifically to [[Jews]], or to [[Semitic]]-language speakers as a whole.&lt;ref&gt;{{PDFlink|[http://www.facinghistory.org/campus/reslib.nsf/99ca830bb4f483948525717f005abfc7/2820f36c177cc758852571860065e8c2/$FILE/complete_antisemitism.pdf Antisemitism. The Power of Myth] (Facing History).|184&amp;nbsp;KB}} Accessed August 21, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Bauer&gt;[[Yehuda Bauer|Bauer, Yehuda]]. {{PDFlink|[http://humwww.ucsc.edu/jewishstudies/docs/YBauerLecture.pdf "Problems of Contemporary Antisemitism"]|196&amp;nbsp;KB}}. Retrieved March 12, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Bauer2&gt;Bauer, Yehuda. ''A History of the Holocaust'', Franklin Watts, 1982, p. 52. ISBN 0-531-05641-4&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Almog&gt;Almog, Shmuel. [http://sicsa.huji.ac.il/hyphen.htm "What's in a Hyphen?"], SICSA Report: Newsletter of the [[Vidal Sassoon International Center for the Study of Antisemitism]] (Summer 1989).&lt;/ref&gt; [[Emil Fackenheim]] supported the unhyphenated spelling, in order to "dispel[] the notion that there is an entity 'Semitism' which 'anti-Semitism' opposes."&lt;ref name=Fackenheim&gt;Cited in [[Dennis Prager|Prager, Dennis]]; [[Joseph Telushkin|Telushkin, Joseph]]. ''Why the Jews?: the reason for antisemitism'', [[Simon and Schuster]], 1983, p. 199.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Etymology===
[[Image:Bookcover-1880-Marr-German uber Juden.jpg|thumb|Cover page of Marr's ''The Way to Victory of Germanicism over Judaism'', 1880 edition]]
The word ''antisemitic'' (''{{lang|de|antisemitisch}}'' in German) was probably{{Vague|date=May 2010}} first used in 1860 by the [[Austria]]n Jewish [[scholar]] [[Moritz Steinschneider]] in the phrase "antisemitic prejudices" ({{lang-de|"antisemitische Vorurteile"}}).&lt;ref&gt;In: [[Alex Bein]]. ''The [[Jewish Question]]: Biography of a World Problem''. Fairleigh Dickinson University Press, 1990, Page 594. ISBN 0-8386-3252-1&lt;/ref&gt; Steinschneider used this phrase to characterize [[Ernest Renan]]'s ideas about how "[[Semitic]] races" were inferior to "[[Aryan]] races." These [[Pseudoscience|pseudo-scientific]] theories concerning race, civilization, and "progress" had become quite widespread in [[Europe]] in the second half of the 19th century, especially as [[Prussia]]n nationalistic historian [[Heinrich von Treitschke]] did much to promote this form of racism. In Treitschke's writings ''Semitic'' was [[synonym]]ous with ''Jewish'', in contrast to its usage by Renan and others.

In 1873 German journalist [[Wilhelm Marr]] published a pamphlet ''"The Victory of the Jewish Spirit over the Germanic Spirit. Observed from a non-religious perspective."'' (''"Der Sieg des Judenthums über das Germanenthum. Vom nicht confessionellen Standpunkt aus betrachtet."'') in which he used the word ''"Semitismus"'' interchangeably with the word "Judentum" to denote both "Jewry" (the Jews as a collective) and "jewishness" (the quality of being Jewish, or the Jewish spirit). Although he did not use the word "Antisemitismus" in the pamphlet, the coining of the latter word followed naturally from the word "Semitismus", and indicated either opposition to the Jews as a people, or else opposition to Jewishness or the Jewish spirit, which he saw as infiltrating German culture.&lt;ref&gt;Wilhelm Marr. [http://www.archive.org/details/DerSiegdesJudenthumsueberdasGermanenthum|Der Sieg des Judenthums über das Germanenthum. Vom nicht confessionellen Standpunkt aus betrachtet.] Rudolph Costenoble. 1879, 8th edition. Archive.org&lt;/ref&gt; In his next pamphlet, ''"The Way to Victory of the Germanic Spirit over the Jewish Spirit"'', published in 1880, Marr developed his ideas further and coined the related [[German language|German]] word ''Antisemitismus'' – ''antisemitism'', derived from the word "Semitismus" that he had earlier used.

The pamphlet became very popular, and in the same year he founded the ''"League of Antisemites"'' ("''Antisemiten-Liga''"), the first German organization committed specifically to combatting the alleged threat to Germany and German culture posed by the Jews and their influence, and advocating their [[population transfer|forced removal]] from the country.

So far as can be ascertained, the word was first widely printed in 1881, when Marr published ''"Zwanglose Antisemitische Hefte,"'' and [[Wilhelm Scherer]] used the term "''Antisemiten''" in the January issue of ''"Neue Freie Presse"''. The related word ''[[Philo-Semitism|semitism]]'' was coined around 1885.

===Definition===
[[Image:Antisemiticroths.jpg|thumb|right|Antisemitic caricature by C.Léandre (France, 1898)]]

Though the general definition of antisemitism is hostility or prejudice against [[Jew]]s, a number of authorities have developed more formal definitions. Holocaust scholar and [[City University of New York]] professor [[Helen Fein]] defines it as "a persisting latent structure of hostile beliefs towards Jews as a collective manifested in individuals as attitudes, and in culture as myth, [[ideology]], [[folklore]] and imagery, and in actions – social or legal discrimination, political mobilization against the Jews, and collective or state violence – which results in and/or is designed to distance, displace, or destroy Jews as Jews."

Professor Dietz Bering of the [[University of Cologne]] further expanded on Professor Fein's definition by describing the structure of antisemitic beliefs. To antisemites, "Jews are not only partially but totally bad by nature, that is, their bad traits are incorrigible. Because of this bad nature: (1) Jews have to be seen not as individuals but as a collective. (2) Jews remain essentially alien in the surrounding societies. (3) Jews bring disaster on their 'host societies' or on the whole world, they are doing it secretly, therefore the antisemites feel obliged to unmask the conspiratorial, bad Jewish character."

[[Bernard Lewis]] defines antisemitism as a special case of prejudice, hatred, or persecution directed against people who are in some way different from the rest. According to Lewis, antisemitism is marked by two distinct features: Jews are judged according to a standard different from that applied to others, and they are accused of "cosmic evil." Thus, "it is perfectly possible to hate and even to persecute Jews without necessarily being anti-Semitic" unless this hatred or persecution displays one of the two features specific to antisemitism.&lt;ref name="autogenerated1"&gt;[[Bernard Lewis|Lewis, Bernard]]. [http://hnn.us/blogs/entries/21832.html "The New Anti-Semitism"], ''The American Scholar'', Volume 75 No. 1, Winter 2006, pp. 25-36. The paper is based on a lecture delivered at [[Brandeis University]] on March 24, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;

There have been a number of efforts by international and governmental bodies to define antisemitism formally. The United States Department of State defines antisemitism in its 2005 Report on Global Anti-Semitism as "hatred toward Jews — individually and as a group — that can be attributed to the Jewish religion and/or ethnicity."&lt;ref name=USDS&gt;[http://www.state.gov/g/drl/rls/40258.htm "Report on Global Anti-Semitism"''], [[United States Department of State|U.S. State Department]], January 5, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2005, the [[European Monitoring Centre on Racism and Xenophobia]] (EUMC), then an agency of the [[European Union]], developed a more detailed discussion: "Antisemitism is a certain perception of Jews, which may be expressed as hatred toward Jews. Rhetorical and physical manifestations of antisemitism are directed toward Jewish or non-Jewish individuals and/or their property, toward Jewish community institutions and religious facilities. In addition, such manifestations could also target the [[state of Israel]], conceived as a Jewish collectivity. Antisemitism frequently charges Jews with conspiring to harm [[human]]ity, and it is often used to blame Jews for 'why things go wrong'."

The EUMC then listed "contemporary examples of antisemitism in public life, the media, schools, the workplace, and in the religious sphere." These included: "Making mendacious, dehumanizing, demonizing, or stereotypical allegations about Jews; accusing Jews as a people of being responsible for real or imagined wrongdoing committed by a single Jewish person or group; [[Holocaust denial|denying the Holocaust]]; and accusing Jewish citizens of being more loyal to Israel, or to the alleged priorities of Jews worldwide, than to the interests of their own nations. The EUMC provided a contraversial &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 |last=Bechler
 |first=Rosemary
 |title=A Commentary on the All-Party Parliamentary Inquiry into Antisemitism
 |url=http://www.ffipp-uk.org/AS_All-party_rpt_070317.doc
 |publisher=Faculty For Israeli-Palestinian Peace - UK
 |accessdate=24 July 2010
 |format=MS Word
 |month=March
 |year=2007}}

&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal
 |doi=10.1080/00313220500045253
 |last=Klug|first=Brian
 |title=Is Europe a lost cause? The European debate on antisemitism and the Middle East conflict
 |journal=[[Patterns of Prejudice]]
 |date=March 2005
 |volume=39
 |issue=1
 |pages=46–59
 |url=http://www.informaworld.com/smpp/content~content=a713722454&amp;db=all
 |accessdate=24 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
discussion of ways in which attacking Israel could be antisemitic, e.g.

*Denying the Jewish people the right to self-determination, e.g. by claiming that the existence of a state of Israel is a racist endeavor;
*Applying double standards by requiring of Israel a behavior not expected or demanded of any other democratic nation;
*Using the symbols and images associated with classic anti-Semitism (e.g. claims of Jews killing Jesus or blood libel) to characterize Israel or Israelis;
*Drawing comparisons of contemporary Israeli policy to that of the Nazis;
*Holding Jews collectively responsible for actions of the State of Israel.

However, the EUMC added that criticism of Israel cannot be regarded as antisemitism so long as it is "similar to that leveled against any other country."&lt;ref name=workingdef&gt;{{PDFlink|[http://fra.europa.eu/fraWebsite/material/pub/AS/AS-WorkingDefinition-draft.pdf "Working definition of antisemitism"]|33.8&amp;nbsp;KB}}, EUMC.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=EUMC&gt;[[European Monitoring Centre on Racism and Xenophobia]], {{PDFlink|[http://eumc.eu.int/eumc/material/pub/AS/AS-WorkingDefinition-draft.pdf "Working Definition of Antisemitism"]|33.8&amp;nbsp;KB}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Image:1889 French elections Poster for antisemitic candidate Adolf Willette.jpg|thumb|1889 Paris, France elections poster for self-described "candidat antisémite" [[Adolphe Willette]]: "The Jews are a different race, hostile to our own... Judaism, there is the enemy!" (see file for complete translation)]]

===Evolution of usage as a term===
In 1879, [[Wilhelm Marr]] founded the ''Antisemiten-Liga'' (Antisemitic League). Identification with antisemitism and as an antisemite was politically advantageous in Europe in the latter 19th century. For example, [[Karl Lueger]], the popular mayor of [[fin de siècle]] [[Vienna]], skillfully exploited antisemitism as a way of channeling public discontent to his political advantage.&lt;ref&gt;Richard S. Geehr. ''Karl Lueger, Mayor of Fin-de-Siècle Vienna'', Wayne State University Press, Detroit, 1989. ISBN 0-8143-2055-4&lt;/ref&gt; In its 1910 obituary of Lueger, ''The New York Times'' notes that Lueger was "Chairman of the Christian Social Union of the Parliament and of the Anti-Semitic Union of the Diet of Lower Austria.&lt;ref&gt;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=9404E7D91E30E333A25752C1A9659C946196D6CF Dr. Karl Lueger Dead; Anti-Semitic Leader and Mayor of Vienna Was 66 Years Old.] ''The New York Times'', March 11, 1910.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1895 [[A. C. Cuza]] organized the ''Alliance Anti-semitique Universelle'' in Bucharest. In the period before [[World War II]], when animosity towards Jews was far more commonplace, it was not uncommon for a person, organization, or political party to self-identify as an antisemite or antisemitic.

The early Zionist pioneer, [[Judah Leib Pinsker]], in a pamphlet written in 1882, said that antisemitism was an inherited predisposition:{{quote|Judeophobia is a psychic aberration. As a psychic aberration it is hereditary, and as a disease transmitted for two thousand years it is incurable.' ... 'In this way have Judaism and Anti-Semitism passed for centuries through history as inseparable companions.'... ...'Having analyzed Judeophobia as an hereditary form of demonopathy, peculiar to the human race, and having represented Anti-Semitism as proceeding from an inherited aberration of the human mind, we must draw the important conclusion that we must give' up contending against these hostile impulses as we must against every other inherited predisposition.&lt;ref&gt;[[Wikisource:Auto-Emancipation|''Auto-Emancipation'' by Judah Leib Pinsker]]&lt;/ref&gt;}}

In the aftermath of [[Kristallnacht]], [[Josef Goebbels|Goebbels]] announced: "The German people is anti-Semitic. It has no desire to have its rights restricted or to be provoked in the future by parasites of the Jewish race."&lt;ref&gt;''Daily Telegraph'', November 12, 1938. Cited in [[Martin Gilbert|Gilbert, Martin]]. ''Kristallnacht: Prelude to Destruction.'' Harper Collins, 2006, p. 142.&lt;/ref&gt;

After [[Hitler]]'s fall from power, and particularly after the extent of the [[Nazi]] [[genocide]] of Jews became known, the term "antisemitism" acquired [[pejorative]] connotations. This marked a full circle shift in usage, from an era just decades earlier when "Jew" was used as a pejorative term.&lt;ref&gt;Jacob Rader Marcus. ''United States Jewry, 1776-1985.'' Wayne State University Press, 1989, page 286. ISBN 0-8143-2186-0&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Alex Bein. ''The Jewish Question: Biography of a World Problem''. Fairleigh Dickinson University Press, 1990, Page 580. ISBN 0-8386-3252-1&lt;/ref&gt; Yehuda Bauer wrote in 1984: "There are no antisemites in the world... Nobody says, 'I am antisemitic.'" You cannot, after Hitler. The word has gone out of fashion."&lt;ref&gt;[[Yehuda Bauer]]: ''The Most Ancient Group Prejudice'' in Leo Eitinger (1984): ''The Anti-Semitism of Our Time''. Oslo. Nansen Committee. p.14. citing from: Jocelyn Hellig (2003): ''The Holocaust and Antisemitism: A Short History.'' Oneworld Publications. ISBN 1-85168-313-5. p.73&lt;/ref&gt;


===New antisemitism===
{{Main|New antisemitism}}
In recent years some scholars have advanced the concept of ''New antisemitism'', coming simultaneously from the [[Left-wing politics|left]], the [[Right-wing politics|right]], and [[Islamism|radical Islam]], which tends to focus on opposition to the creation of a Jewish homeland in the [[State of Israel]],&lt;ref name="New-AS-List" /&gt; and argue that the language of [[Anti-Zionism]] and criticism of [[Israel]] are used to attack the Jews more broadly. In this view, the proponents of the new concept believe that criticisms of Israel and [[Zionism]] are often disproportionate in degree and unique in kind, and attribute this to antisemitism.&lt;ref&gt;
Sources for the following are:
*[[Yehuda Bauer|Bauer, Yehuda]]. [http://web.archive.org/web/20030705131522/http://humanities.ucsc.edu/JewishStudies/docs/YBauerLecture.pdf "Problems of Contemporary Anti-Semitism"], 2003, retrieved April 22, 2006.
*[[Phyllis Chesler|Chesler, Phyllis]]. ''The New Anti-Semitism: The Current Crisis and What We Must Do About It'', Jossey-Bass, 2003, pp. 158-159, 181.
*Doward, Jamie. [http://observer.guardian.co.uk/uk_news/story/0,6903,1278580,00.html Jews predict record level of hate attacks: Militant Islamic media accused of stirring up new wave of anti-semitism], ''[[The Guardian]]'', August 8, 2004.
*[[Warren Kinsella|Kinsella, Warren]]. [http://www.warrenkinsella.com/words_extremism_nas.htm The New anti-Semitism], accessed March 5, 2006.
*[[Jonathan Sacks|Sacks, Jonathan]]. [http://israel.jcca.org/articles.htm?y=620051118152416 "The New Antisemitism"], Ha'aretz, September 6, 2002, retrieved on January 10, 2007.
*[[Mark Strauss (artist)|Strauss, Mark]]. [http://yaleglobal.yale.edu/display.article?id=2791 "Antiglobalism's Jewish Problem"] in Rosenbaum, Ron (ed). ''Those who forget the past: The Question of Anti-Semitism'', Random House 2004, p 272.&lt;/ref&gt; The concept has been criticized by those who argue it is used to stifle debate and deflect attention from legitimate criticism of the State of Israel, and, by associating anti-Zionism with antisemitism, is intended to taint anyone opposed to Israeli actions and policies.&lt;ref&gt;[[Brian Klug|Klug, Brian]]. [http://www.thenation.com/doc.mhtml?i=20040202&amp;s=klug The Myth of the New Anti-Semitism]. ''[[The Nation (U.S. periodical)|The Nation]]'', posted January 15, 2004 (February 2, 2004 issue), accessed January 9, 2006; and [[Michael Lerner (rabbi)|Lerner, Michael]]. [http://baltimorechronicle.com/2007/020207LERNER.shtml There Is No New Anti-Semitism], posted February 5, 2007. Retrieved February 6, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Current situation==
A report from the [[United States Department of State|U.S. State Department]] from March 14, 2008 detailed "an upsurge" across the world of antisemitism—hostility and discrimination toward Jewish people, accounting mostly from [[radical Islam]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Report: Anti-Semitism on the rise globally |url=http://edition.cnn.com/2008/US/03/14/anti-semitism/index.html |publisher=CNN |date=2008-03-14 |accessdate=2008-03-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In August 2005, the [[United States]] expressed 'serious concern' over anti-Christian and anti-Jewish passages in [[Pakistan Studies|Pakistani textbooks]] and termed them as "unacceptable and inciteful".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.expressindia.com/news/fullstory.php?newsid=53011 US shocked at Pak anti-Christian books]&lt;/ref&gt;

===United States===
{{Main|Antisemitism in the United States}}

[[Sami Al-Arian]], a Muslim leader in the U.S. who was later convicted of supporting a terrorist group, on September 29, 1991, said in a speech at a Chicago conference that "God cursed those who are the sons of Israel", and that [[Allah]] had made Jews "monkeys and swine", and damned them in this world and the afterworld.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2005/12/06/national/nationalspecial3/06cnd-terror.html?hp&amp;ex=1133931600&amp;en=cddfc36c6cad7591&amp;ei=5094&amp;partner=homepage Lichtblau, Eric, "4 in Florida Are Cleared on Many Terrorism Charges", ''The New York Times'', December 6, 2005, accessed March 8, 2010]&lt;/ref&gt;

On April 3, 2006, the [[U.S. Commission on Civil Rights]] announced its finding that incidents of antisemitism are a "serious problem" on college campuses throughout the United States. The Commission recommended that the [[U.S. Department of Education]]'s [[Office for Civil Rights]] protect college students from antisemitism through vigorous enforcement of ''Title VI'' of the [[Civil Rights Act of 1964]] and further recommended that [[United States Congress|Congress]] clarify that Title VI applies to discrimination against Jewish students.&lt;ref&gt;[[U.S. Commission on Civil Rights]]: {{PDFlink|[http://www.usccr.gov/pubs/050306FRUSCCRRCAS.pdf Findings and Recommendations Regarding Campus Antisemitism]|19.3&amp;nbsp;KB}}. April 3, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; ''

On July 28, 2006, [[Naveed Afzal Haq]] shot six women, one fatally, in the [[Seattle Jewish Federation shooting]] by Daniel Schwarz, an infamous leader of the Aryan Brotherhood who ordered the hit from the [[ADX Florence]].{{Citation needed|date=January 2010}} Police have classified the shooting as a [[hate crime]] based on Haq statements during a [[9-1-1]] call.&lt;ref name=LATimes&gt;Associated Press. [http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,206172,00.html=true "1 Killed, 5 Wounded in Seattle Jewish Center Shooting"], ''[[Fox News]]'', July 29, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

On September 19, 2006, [[Yale University]] founded [[The Yale Initiative for Interdisciplinary Study of Antisemitism]], the first North American university-based center for study of the subject, as part of its [[Institution for Social and Policy Studies]]. Director [[Charles A. Small|Charles Small]] of the Center cited the increase in antisemitism worldwide in recent years as generating a "need to understand the current manifestation of this disease".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.iht.com/articles/ap/2006/09/19/america/NA_GEN_US_Yale_Anti_Semitism.php Yale creates center to study antisemitism] Associated Press, September 19, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

According to an [[Anti-Defamation League]] survey 14 percent of U.S. residents had antisemitic views. The 2005 survey found "35 percent of foreign-born [[Hispanics]]" and "36 percent of [[African-American]]s hold strong antisemitic beliefs, four times more than the 9 percent for whites".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.adl.org/PresRele/ASUS_12/4680_12.htm ADL Survey: Anti-Semitism Declines Slightly in America; 14 Percent of Americans Hold 'Strong' Anti-Semitic Beliefs]&lt;/ref&gt;

A 2009 study published in ''[[Boston Review]]'' found that nearly 25% of non-Jewish Americans blamed Jews for the [[Global financial crisis of 2008–2009]], with a higher percentage among Democrats than Republicans.&lt;ref&gt;[http://bostonreview.net/BR34.3/malhotra_margalit.php State of the Nation: Anti-Semitism and the economic crisis by Neil Malhotra and Yotam Margalit in Boston Review]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Europe===
{{See|Antisemitism in Europe|New antisemitism|Islam in Europe}}
Antisemitism has increased significantly in Europe since 2000, with significant increases in verbal attacks against Jews and vandalism such as graffiti, fire bombings of Jewish schools, desecration of synagogues and cemeteries. According to a 2004 study, [[Germany]], [[France]], [[United Kingdom|Britain]] and [[Russia]] are the countries with the highest rate of anti-semitic incidents in Europe.&lt;ref name = "mgjmsp"&gt;[http://www.jcpa.org/phas/phas-urban-f04.htm Anti-Semitism In Germany Today: Its Roots And Tendencies – Susanne Urban]&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Netherlands]] and [[Sweden]] have also consistently had high rates of anti-semitic attacks since 2000.&lt;ref&gt;The 2005 U.S. State Department Report on Global Antisemitism.&lt;/ref&gt;

Much of the new European antisemitic violence can actually be seen as a spill over from the long running [[Arab-Israeli conflict]] since the majority of the perpetrators are from the [[Islam in Europe|large Muslim immigrant communities in European cities]]. However, compared to France, the United Kingdom and much of the rest of Europe, in Germany Arab and pro-Palestinian groups are involved in only a small percentage of antisemitic incidents.&lt;ref name = "mgjmsp"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Stephen Roth Institute, Tel Aviv University, http://www.tau.ac.il/Anti-Semitism/.&lt;/ref&gt; According to ''The Stephen Roth Institute for the Study of Contemporary Antisemitism and Racism'', most of the current antisemitism in Europe, with exceptions to [[Germany]], [[Austria]], and [[Sweden]], comes from militant Islamic and Muslim groups, and most Jews tend to be assaulted in countries where groups of young Muslim immigrants reside.&lt;ref name=roth&gt;[http://www.tau.ac.il/Antisemitism/asw2004/general-analysis.htm "Annual Reports: General Analysis, 2004"], The Steven Roth Institute for the Study of Contemporary Antisemitism and Racism, Tel Aviv University. Retrieved March 12, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Interior Minister of Germany, [[Wolfgang Schaeuble]], points out the official policy of Germany: "We will not tolerate any form of extremism, xenophobia or anti-Semitism."&lt;ref name=bbcwolfgang&gt;{{cite news
|title=Germans warned of neo-Nazi surge
|accessdate=2007-06-06
|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/5005472.stm
|date=May 22, 2006
| work=BBC News}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although the number of right-wing groups and organisations grew from 141 (2001)&lt;ref name=bundesamt1&gt;Bundesamt für Verfassungsschutz. Federal Office for the Protection of the Constitution. {{PDFlink|[http://www.verfassungsschutz.de/download/SHOW/vsbericht_2003.pdf Verfassungsschutzbericht 2003]}}. Annual Report. 2003, Page 29&lt;/ref&gt; to 182 (2006),&lt;ref name=bundesamt2&gt;[[Bundesamt für Verfassungsschutz]]. Federal Office for the Protection of the Constitution. {{PDFlink|[http://www.verfassungsschutz.de/download/de/publikationen/verfassungsschutzbericht/vsbericht_2006/vsbericht_2006.pdf ''Verfassungsschutzbericht 2006''. Annual Report]}}. 2006, Page 51&lt;/ref&gt; especially in the formerly communist East Germany,&lt;ref name=bbcwolfgang/&gt; Germany's measures against right wing groups and antisemitism are effective, despite Germany having the highest rates of antisemitic acts in Europe. According to the annual reports of the [[Bundesamt für Verfassungsschutz|Federal Office for the Protection of the Constitution]] the overall number of far-right extremists in Germany dropped during the last years from 49,700 (2001),&lt;ref name=bundesamt1/&gt; 45,000 (2002),&lt;ref name=bundesamt1/&gt; 41,500 (2003),&lt;ref name=bundesamt1/&gt; 40,700 (2004),&lt;ref name=bundesamt2/&gt; 39,000 (2005),&lt;ref name=bundesamt2/&gt; to 38,600 in 2006.&lt;ref name=bundesamt2/&gt; Germany provided several million Euros to fund "nationwide programs aimed at fighting far-right extremism, including teams of traveling consultants, and victims' groups."&lt;ref name=ihtassociated&gt;
[[The Associated Press]]. [http://www.iht.com/articles/ap/2006/10/22/europe/EU_GEN_Germany_Neo_Nazis.php "Berlin police say 16 arrested during neo-Nazi demonstration".] ''[[International Herald Tribune]]''. October 22, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; 

Despite these facts, Israeli Ambassador Shimon Stein warned in October 2006 that Jews in Germany feel increasingly "unsafe," stating that they "are not able to live a normal Jewish life" and that heavy security surrounds most synagogues or Jewish community centers.&lt;ref name=ihtassociated/&gt; Yosef Havlin, Rabbi at the Chabad Lubavitch Frankfurt does not agree with the Israeli Ambassador and states in an interview with ''[[Der Spiegel]]'' magazine in September 2007, that the German public does not support Nazis, instead he has personally experienced the support of Germans, as a Jew and Rabbi he "feels welcome in his (hometown) Frankfurt, he is not afraid, the city is no-go-area".&lt;ref&gt;''Der Spiegel''. [http://www.spiegel.de/politik/deutschland/0,1518,505159,00.html "Wir dürfen uns auf keinen Fall verstecken"]. ''[[Der Spiegel]]''. September 12, 2007&lt;/ref&gt; Despite this comment, on the 11th of September, 2007 an antisemitic incident occurred whereby Frankfurt Rabbi, Zalman Gurevitch, was stabbed repeatedly, the attacker subsequently threatening in German "I'll kill you, you (expletive) Jew."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Police: Anti-Semitic insult preceded Frankfurt rabbi stabbing|url=http://www.haaretz.com/hasen/spages/902882.html |publisher=[[Haaretz]] |date=2007-11-09 |accessdate=2008-02-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2005 the UK Parliament set up an all-party inquiry into antisemitism, which published its findings in 2006. The inquiry stated that "until recently, the prevailing opinion both within the Jewish community and beyond [had been] that antisemitism had receded to the point that it existed only on the margins of society." It found a reversal of this progress since 2000. It aimed to investigate the problem, identify the sources of contemporary antisemitism and make recommendations to improve the situation. It discussed the influence of the Israel-Palestine conflict and issues of anti-Israel sentiment versus antisemitism at length and noted "most of those who gave evidence were at pains to explain that criticism of Israel is not to be regarded in itself as antisemitic..The Israeli government itself may, at times, have mistakenly perceived criticism of its policies and actions to be motivated by antisemitism"&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Report of the All-Party Parliamentary Inquiry into Antisemitism|url=http://thepcaa.org/Report.pdf |month=September|year=2006|accessdate=14 February 2007|author=All-Party Parliamentary Group against Antisemitism (UK)|format=PDF|accessdate=2008-12-28}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

On January 1, 2006, Britain's chief [[rabbi]], Sir [[Jonathan Sacks]], warned that what he called a "[[tsunami]] of antisemitism" was spreading globally. In an interview with BBC's [[Radio Four]], Sacks said: "A number of my rabbinical colleagues throughout Europe have been assaulted and attacked on the streets. We've had synagogues desecrated. We've had Jewish schools burnt to the ground – not here but in France. People are attempting to silence and even ban Jewish societies on campuses on the grounds that Jews must support the state of Israel, therefore they should be banned, which is quite extraordinary because ... British Jews see themselves as British citizens. So it's that kind of feeling that you don't know what's going to happen next that's making ... some European Jewish communities uncomfortable."&lt;ref name=Gillan&gt;Gillan, Audrey. [http://www.guardian.co.uk/religion/Story/0,2763,1676509,00.html "Chief rabbi fears 'tsunami' of hatred"], ''Guardian'', January 2, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

France is home to [[Western Europe]]’s largest [[Muslim]] population ([[Islam in France|about 4 million]]) as well as the continent’s largest Jewish community (about 600,000). Jewish leaders decry an intensifying antisemitism in France, mainly among Muslims of [[Arab]] or [[African]] heritage, but also growing among [[Caribbean]] islanders from former French colonies.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.haaretz.com/hasen/spages/841445.html Jews for Le Pen] by Daniel Ben-Simon. Haaretz. 25/03/07&lt;/ref&gt; However, it is Muslims rather than Jews who can expect to suffer more from bigotry in France, stated Holocaust survivor and former French cabinet minister [[Simone Veil]]. "Let's not exaggerate," she said. While noting that radical Islamists are behind some violent incidents against Jews in certain French neighbourhoods, "[[Anti-Arabism|Anti-Arab]] sentiment is much stronger in France than anti-Semitism." France's Jewish community is much more integrated than its 5 to 6 million Muslims, she noted, claiming Muslim youth are moved by a militant and anti-Jewish hierarchy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=Irwin |last=Block |title=More hatred towards Muslims and Jews in France: Holocaust survivor |url=http://www.canada.com/montrealgazette/news/story.html?id=85ca8e66-a12c-40b0-9ce8-95823057df6c&amp;k=46226 |publisher=[[The Gazette (Montreal)|The Gazette]] |date=2007-10-13 |accessdate=2008-02-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; Former Interior Minister [[Nicolas Sarkozy]] denounced the killing of [[Ilan Halimi]] on 13 February 2006 as an antisemitic crime.

Independent voices, including leading Jewish philanthropist Baron [[Eric de Rothschild]] who received an honorary doctorate from [[Hebrew University]], suggest that the extent of antisemitism in Europe has been exaggerated. In an interview with the Jerusalem Post he says that "some of the complaints emanating from Israel about the treatment of French Jews amount to 'an element of [[schadenfreude]] (taking pleasure at another's misfortune) on the part of those who have already made aliya: When the cousins come over, they say, It's terrible [in France] – you have to come to Israel." About France he says: "People are in fact philo-Semitic in the government, mayors, to an extent which goes beyond pure electoral calculations" and "the one thing you can't say is that France is an anti-Semitic country."&lt;ref&gt;Krieger, Leila Hilary. [http://www.jpost.com/servlet/Satellite?pagename=JPost%2FJPArticle%2FShowFull&amp;cid=1150191582833 "Rothschild: France not anti-Semitic"]. ''[[Jerusalem Post]]'', June 15, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2010, the [[Norwegian Broadcasting Corporation]], after one year of research, revealed that [[anti-semitism]] was common among Norwegian [[Muslims]]. Teachers at schools with large shares of Muslims revealed that Muslim students often "praise or admire [[Adolf Hitler]] for his killing of [[Jews]]", that "Jew-hate is legitimate within vast groups of Muslim students" and that "Muslims laugh or command [teachers] to stop when trying to educate about the [[Holocaust]]". Additionally that "while some students might protest when some express support for [[terrorism]], none object when students express hate of Jews" and that it says in "the [[Quran]] that you shall kill Jews, all true Muslims hate Jews". Most of these students were said to be born and raised in Norway. One [[Jewish]] father also told that his child, after school, had been taken by a Muslim mob (though managed to escape), reportedly "to be taken out to the forest and [[lynching|hung]] because he was a Jew".&lt;ref&gt;{{citenews|url=http://www1.nrk.no/nett-tv/indeks/205057|work=NRK Lørdagsrevyen|title=Jødiske blir hetset|date=13 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Middle East===
{{See|Arabs and antisemitism}}

According to the [[Pew Global Attitudes Project]] released on August 14, 2005, high percentages of the populations of six Muslim-majority countries have negative views of Jews. To a questionnaire asking respondents to give their views of members of various religions along a spectrum from "very favorable" to "very unfavorable," 60% of [[Turkey|Turks]], 88% of [[Morocco|Moroccans]], 99% of [[Lebanon|Lebanese]] Muslims and 100% of [[Jordan]]ians checked either "somewhat unfavorable" or "very unfavorable" for Jews.&lt;ref&gt;
*[http://pewglobal.org/reports/display.php?ReportID=248 PEW Globel Attitudes Report] statistics on how the world views different religious groups
*{{Cite news |first=Meg |last=Bortin |title=Poll Finds Discord Between the Muslim and Western Worlds |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2006/06/23/world/23pew.html?ei=5090&amp;en=5b361ce4828f5847&amp;ex=1308715200&amp;adxnnl=1&amp;partner=rssuserland&amp;emc=rss&amp;pagewanted=all&amp;adxnnlx=1180479483-EJoZc0Poq7pWF1C9iBvPng |publisher=New York Times |date=June 23, 2006 |accessdate=2007-05-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to [[Newsweek]], "Indeed, anti-Semitism—the real stuff, not just bad-mouthing particular Israeli policies—is as much part of Arab life today as the hijab or the hookah. Whereas this darkest of creeds is no longer tolerated in polite society in the West, in the Arab world, Jew hatred remains culturally endemic."&lt;ref&gt;Anti-Semitism In Araby, Josef Joffe,
NEWSWEEK,
From the magazine issue dated March 9, 2009 [http://www.newsweek.com/id/186974]&lt;/ref&gt;

In the Middle East, anti-Zionist propaganda frequently adopts the terminology and symbols of the Holocaust to demonize Israel and its leaders.

In [[Egypt]], Dar al-Fadhilah published a translation of [[Henry Ford]]'s antisemitic treatise, ''[[The International Jew]]'', complete with distinctly antisemitic imagery on the cover.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.intelligence.org.il/eng/sib/4_04/as_egypt.htm Examples of anti-Semitism in the Arab and Muslim world] on intelligence.org.il, site of the Intelligence and Terrorism Information Center
at the Center for Special Studies (C.S.S), Israel. Retrieved 24 September 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

The website of the [[Saudi Arabia]]n [[Saudi Commission for Tourism &amp; Antiquities|Supreme Commission for Tourism]] initially stated that Jews would not be granted tourist visas to enter the country.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.sauditourism.gov.sa/sct/indexlist.php?catid=39&amp;maincat=Travel_Tips |title=Visa requirements |publisher=[[Saudi Commission for Tourism &amp; Antiquities|Supreme Commission for Tourism]] |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20040206173019/http://www.sauditourism.gov.sa/sct/indexlist.php?catid=39&amp;maincat=Travel_Tips |archivedate=2004-02-06 |quote=Visas will not be issued for the following groups of people:
* An Israeli passport holder or a passport that has an Israeli arrival/departure stamp.
* Those who don't abide by the Saudi traditions concerning appearance and behaviors.  Those under the influence of alcohol will not be permitted into the Kingdom.
* There are certain regulations for pilgrims and you should contact the consulate for more information.
* Jewish People}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.house.gov/apps/list/press/ny09_weiner/022604Saudi.html "Official Saudi Arabia Tourism Website: No Jews Allowed. 'Jewish People' May Not Receive Travel Visas Required To Travel Into The Kingdom"] by Congressman Anthony D. Weiner (D-Queens &amp; Brooklyn) February 26, 2004&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/3493448.stm "Jews barred in Saudi tourist drive"] (BBC) February 27, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;
It has since removed this statement, and apologized for posting "erroneous information". Members of religions other than Islam, including Jews, are not permitted to practice their religion publicly in Saudi Arabia.

Saudi Arabian government officials and state religious leaders often promote the idea that "the Jews" are conspiring to take over the entire world; as proof of their claims they publish and frequently cite ''[[The Protocols of the Elders of Zion]]'' as factual.&lt;ref name=CMIP-KSA2001&gt;[http://www.edume.org/reports/10/38.htm CMIP report: "The Jews in World History according to the Saudi textbooks"]. ''The Danger of World Jewry'', by Abdullah al-Tall, pp. 140–141 (Arabic). ''Hadith and Islamic Culture'', Grade 10, (2001) pp. 103–104.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{PDFlink|[http://www.freedomhouse.org/religion/pdfdocs/KSAtextbooks06.pdf 2006 ''Saudi Arabia's Curriculum of Intolerance'']}}, Report by Center for Religious Freedom of Freedom House. 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2001, Arab Radio and Television of Saudi Arabia produced a 30-part television miniseries entitled "Horseman Without a Horse", a dramatization of ''[[The Protocols of the Elders of Zion]]''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.adl.org/presrele/islme_62/4013_62.asp ADL]&lt;/ref&gt;

One Saudi Arabian government newspaper suggested that hatred of all Jews is justifiable.&lt;ref&gt;''Al-Riyadh'', Saudi government daily, April 15, 2002, Turki 'Abdallah as-Sudayri, ''All of History is against Them''&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Saudi-Arabian textbook controversy|Saudi textbooks]] vilify Jews (and Christians and non-[[Wahabi]] Muslims): according to the May 21, 2006 issue of ''[[The Washington Post]]'', Saudi textbooks claimed by them to have been sanitized of antisemitism still call Jews apes (and Christians swine); demand that students avoid and not befriend Jews; claim that Jews worship the devil; and encourage Muslims to engage in Jihad to vanquish Jews.&lt;ref&gt;Shea, Nina. [http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2006/05/19/AR2006051901769.html "This is a Saudi textbook. (After the intolerance was removed.)"], ''[[The Washington Post]]'', May 21, 2006, p. B01.&lt;/ref&gt;

Al-Manar recently aired a drama series, called ''The Diaspora'', which observers allege is based on historical antisemitic allegations. [[BBC]] reporters who watched the series said that correspondents who have viewed ''The Diaspora'' note that it quotes extensively from the ''Protocols of the Elders of Zion'', a notorious 19th century publication used by the Nazis among others to fuel race hatred.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/3581514.stm BBC NEWS|World|Europe|France offers 'hate TV' reprieve]&lt;/ref&gt;

Muslim clerics in the Middle East have frequently referred to Jews as descendants of apes and pigs, which are conventional epithets for Jews and Christians.&lt;ref&gt;Bernard Lewis. ''The Jews of Islam''. Princeton University Press, 1984, page 33.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Aluma Solnick. [http://memri.org/bin/articles.cgi?Area=sr&amp;ID=SR01102 ''Based on Koranic Verses, Interpretations, and Traditions, Muslim Clerics State: The Jews Are the Descendants of Apes, Pigs, And Other Animals''.] MEMRI Special Report – No. 11, November 1, 2002&lt;/ref&gt; [[Abdul Rahman Al-Sudais]] is the leading [[imam]] of the [[Masjid al-Haram|Grand mosque]] located in the Islamic holy city of [[Mecca]], [[Saudi Arabia]].&lt;ref&gt;
*Neil J. Kressel. [http://chronicle.com/free/v50/i27/27b01401.htm "The Urgent Need to Study Islamic Anti-Semitism"], ''The Chronicle of Higher Education'', ''The Chronical Review'', March 12, 2004.
*Tom Gross, [http://www.nationalreview.com/comment/gross200406181018.asp "Living in a Bubble: The BBC’s very own Mideast foreign policy".], ''[[National Review]]'', June 18, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[BBC]] aired a [[Panorama (TV series)|Panorama]] episode, entitled ''A Question of Leadership'', which reported that al-Sudais referred to Jews as "the scum of the human race" and "offspring of apes and pigs", and stated, "the worst [...] of the enemies of Islam are those [...] whom he [...] made monkeys and pigs, the aggressive Jews and oppressive [[Zionists]] and those that follow them [...] Monkeys and pigs and worshippers of false Gods who are the Jews and the Zionists."&lt;ref name="panorama"&gt;{{cite interview
 |last=Sacranie
 |first=Iqbal
|subjectlink = Iqbal Sacranie
|last2 = Abdul Bari
|first2 = Muhammad
|subjectlink2 = Muhammad Abdul Bari
|last3 = Kantharia
|first3 = Mehboob
|last4 = Siddiqui
|first4 = Ghayasuddin
|interviewer = John Ware
 |title=A Question of Leadership
 |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/programmes/panorama/4171950.stm
|program = ''[[Panorama (TV series)|Panorama]]''
|callsign = [[BBC]]
|city = [[London, England]]
 |date=August 21, 2005
 |accessdate=2007-03-30
}}&lt;/ref&gt; In another sermon, on April 19, 2002, he declared that Jews are "evil offspring, infidels, distorters of [others'] words, calf-worshippers, prophet-murderers, prophecy-deniers [...] the scum of the human race whom Allah cursed and turned into apes and pigs [...]"&lt;ref&gt;{{PDFlink|[http://arts.monash.edu.au/jewish-civilisation/visiting/kinberg-jews-koran.pdf "Jews In The Koran And Early Islamic Traditions"]}} by Dr. Leah Kinberg. Lecture delivered in May 2003, Monash University, Melbourne, quoting [http://www.alminbar.cc/alkhutab/khutbaa.asp?mediaURL=5544]&lt;/ref&gt;

On May 5, 2001, after [[Shimon Peres]] visited [[Egypt]], the Egyptian ''[[Al Akhbar (Egypt)|al-Akhbar]]'' internet paper stated that: "lies and deceit are not foreign to Jews[...]. For this reason, Allah changed their shape and made them into monkeys and pigs."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.adl.org/egyptian_media/media_2002/stereotypes.asp Anti-Semitism in the Egyptian Media: February 2001 – February 2002], "Classic Anti-Semitic Stereotypes", [[Anti Defamation League]]. Retrieved March 4, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

In Israel, Zalman Gilichenski has warned about the spread of antisemitism among [[History of the Jews in Russia#Russia today|immigrants from Russia]] in the last decade.&lt;ref&gt;See [http://pogrom.org.il/eng_articles.php?cat_id=1 his website] and by example [http://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/middle-east/israels-nightmare-homegrown-neonazis-in-the-holy-land-396392.html Israel's nightmare: Homegrown neo-Nazis in the Holy Land], [[The Independent]], London, 2007-10-09&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
{{Main|History of antisemitism}}

===Ancient world===
Examples of antipathy to [[Jews]] and [[Judaism]] during [[ancient world|ancient times]] are abundant. Statements exhibiting prejudice against Jews and their religion can be found in the works of many [[pagan]] [[ancient Greece|Greek]] and [[ancient Rome|Roman]] writers.&lt;ref&gt;Daniels. J,L, ''Anti-Semitism in the Hellenistic-Roman Period'' in JBL 98 (1979) pp.45–65&lt;/ref&gt; There are examples of [[Hellenistic]] rulers desecrating the [[Temple in Jerusalem|Temple]] and banning Jewish religious practices, such as [[circumcision]], [[Shabbat]] observance, study of Jewish religious books, etc. Examples may also be found in anti-Jewish riots in [[Alexandria]] in the 3rd century BCE. [[Philo of Alexandria]] described an attack on Jews in Alexandria in 38 CE in which thousands of Jews died.

The Jewish diaspora on the [[Nile River|Nile]] island [[Elephantine]], which was founded by mercenaries, experienced the destruction of its temple in 410 BCE.&lt;ref&gt;Colpe, Carsten (Berlin). "Anti-Semitism." Brill's New Pauly. Antiquity volumes edited by: Hubert Cancik and Helmuth Schneider. Brill, 2008. Brill Online. 28 April 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

Relationships between the Jewish people and the occupying [[Roman Empire]] were at first antagonistic and resulted in [[Jewish-Roman wars|several rebellions]]. According to [[Suetonius]], the emperor [[Tiberius]] expelled from Rome Jews who had gone to live there. The 18th century [[England|English]] historian [[Edward Gibbon]] identified a more tolerant period beginning in about 160 CE.

[[James P. Carroll|James Carroll]] asserted, "Jews accounted for 10% of the total population of the [[Roman Empire]]. By that ratio, if other factors such as [[pogrom]]s and [[forced conversion|conversion]]s had not intervened, there would be 200 million Jews in the world today, instead of something like 13 million."&lt;ref&gt;Carroll, James. ''[[Constantine's Sword]]'' (Houghton Mifflin, 2001) ISBN 0-395-77927-8 p.26&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.townhall.com/columnists/DennisPrager/2006/02/21/explaining_jews,_part_iii_a_very_insecure_people Explaining Jews, Part III: A very insecure people::By Dennis Prager]&lt;/ref&gt;

Quite interestingly, India has the unique distinction of no antisemitism in its history of Jewish settlements for at least 2000 years. Vibrant Jewish communities flourished in India since the ancient times till the mid 20th century when most of them, especially youths, decided to migrate to Israel as the economy of India was in shambles. Stephen Knapp states, "The Jewish people continued to suffer at the hands of their brothers, the people of the Books. It reached the peak during the second world war, when trains loaded with human cargo were sent into gas chambers. The Jewish race was nearly exterminated in Europe. The Jewish people in India were quite happy living among the Hindus."&lt;ref&gt;http://www.stephen-knapp.com/speaking_out_against_prejudice.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

===Persecutions in the Middle Ages===
{{Main|Jews in the Middle Ages}}{{Jews and Judaism sidebar|history}}
From the 9th century CE, the [[Islamic Golden Age|medieval Islamic world]] classified Jews (and Christians) as ''[[dhimmi]]'', and allowed them to practice their religion more freely than they could do in [[Middle Ages|medieval Christian Europe]]. Under [[Al-Andalus|Islamic rule]], there was a [[Golden age of Jewish culture in Spain]] that lasted until at least the 11th century,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|first=María Rosa|last=Menocal|author-link=María Rosa Menocal|title=The Ornament of the World: How Muslims, Jews and Christians Created a Culture of Tolerance in Medieval Spain|date=April 2003|publisher=Back Bay Books|isbn=0316168718}}&lt;/ref&gt; when several Muslim [[pogrom]]s against Jews took place in the [[Iberian Peninsula]]; those that occurred in [[Córdoba, Spain|Córdoba]] in 1011 and in [[1066 Granada massacre|Granada in 1066]].&lt;ref name="Schweitzer267-268"&gt;Schweitzer, Perry (2002) pp. 267-268.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?artid=412&amp;letter=G&amp;search=Granada Granada] by Richard Gottheil, Meyer Kayserling, ''[[Jewish Encyclopedia]]''. 1906 ed.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Harzig, Hoerder &amp; Shubert, 2003, p. 42.&lt;/ref&gt; Several decrees ordering the destruction of [[synagogue]]s were also enacted in [[Egypt]], [[Syria]], [[Iraq]] and [[Yemen]] from the 11th century. Despite the [[Qur'an]]'s prohibition, Jews were also forced to convert to Islam or face death in some parts of Yemen, [[Morocco]] and [[Baghdad]] several times between the 12th and 18th centuries.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/anti-semitism/Jews_in_Arab_lands_(gen).html The Treatment of Jews in Arab/Islamic Countries]&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Almohad dynasty|Almohads]], who had taken control of the [[Almoravid dynasty|Almoravids]]' [[Maghreb|Maghribi]] and Andalusian territories by 1147,&lt;ref name=islamicworldeb&gt;Islamic world. (2007). In Encyclopædia Britannica. Retrieved September 2, 2007, from [http://www.britannica.com/eb/article-26925 Encyclopædia Britannica Online].&lt;/ref&gt; were far more fundamentalist in outlook, and they treated the ''dhimmis'' harshly. Faced with the choice of either death or conversion, many Jews and Christians emigrated.&lt;ref name=frank&gt;Frank and Leaman, 2003, p. 137-138.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.myjewishlearning.com/history_community/Medieval/IntergroupTO/JewishMuslim/Almohads.htm The Almohads]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.theforgottenrefugees.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=66&amp;Itemid=39 The Forgotten Refugees]&lt;/ref&gt; Some, such as the family of [[Maimonides]], fled east to more tolerant Muslim lands,&lt;ref name=frank/&gt; while some others went northward to settle in the growing Christian kingdoms, where Jews were increasingly forced to convert to Christianity from the 13th century.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/Judaism/Sephardim.html Sephardim]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Kraemer, 2005, pp. 16-17.&lt;/ref&gt;

During the [[Middle Ages]] in Europe there was persecution against Jews in many places, with [[blood libel]]s, expulsions, [[forced conversion]]s and [[wiktionary:massacre|massacres]]. A main justification of prejudice against Jews in Europe was religious. The persecution hit its first peak during the [[Crusades]]. In the [[First Crusade]] (1096) flourishing communities on the [[Rhine]] and the [[Danube]] [[German Crusade, 1096|were destroyed]]. In the [[Second Crusade]] (1147) the Jews in Germany were subject to several massacres. The Jews were also subjected to attacks by the [[Shepherds' Crusade]]s of 1251 and 1320. The Crusades were followed by expulsions, including, in 1290, the banishing of all [[English people|English]] Jews; in 1396, the expulsion of 100,000 Jews in [[France]]; and in 1421, the expulsion of thousands from [[Austria]]. Many of the expelled Jews fled to [[Poland]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.holocaustcenterpgh.net/2-3.html Why the Jews? – Black Death]&lt;/ref&gt;

As the [[Black Death]] epidemics devastated Europe in the mid-14th century, annihilating more than half of the population, Jews were used as [[scapegoating#Psychology and sociology|scapegoats]]. Rumors spread that they caused the disease by deliberately poisoning wells. Hundreds of Jewish communities were destroyed. Although [[Pope Clement VI]] tried to protect them by the July 6, 1348, [[papal bull]] and an additional bull in 1348, several months later, 900 Jews were burned alive in [[Strasbourg]], where the plague had not yet affected the city.&lt;ref name="Black"/&gt;

===Seventeenth century===
During the mid-to-late 17th century the [[Polish-Lithuanian Commonwealth]] was devastated by several conflicts, in which the Commonwealth lost over a third of its population (over 3 million people), and Jewish losses were counted in hundreds of thousands. First, the [[Chmielnicki Uprising]] when [[Bohdan Khmelnytsky]]'s [[Cossack]]s massacred tens of thousands of [[History of Jews in Poland|Jews]] in the eastern and southern areas he controlled (today's [[Ukraine]]). The precise number of dead may never be known, but the decrease of the Jewish population during that period is estimated at 100,000 to 200,000, which also includes emigration, deaths from diseases and [[Slavery (Ottoman Empire)|captivity in the Ottoman Empire]], called ''jasyr''.&lt;ref&gt;"Bogdan Chmelnitzki leads Cossack uprising against Polish rule; 100,000 Jews are killed and hundreds of Jewish communities are destroyed." [http://www.cbsnews.com/htdocs/religion/judaism/timeline.html Judaism Timeline 1618-1770], ''[[CBS News]]''. Accessed May 13, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;"... as many as 100,000 Jews were murdered throughout the Ukraine by Bogdan Chmielnicki's Cossack soldiers on the rampage." [[Martin Gilbert]]. ''Holocaust Journey: Traveling in Search of the Past'', Columbia University Press, 1999, ISBN 0-231-10965-2, p. 219.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Eighteenth century===
In 1744, [[Frederick II of Prussia]] limited the number of Jews allowed to live in [[Breslau]] to only ten so-called "protected" Jewish families and encouraged a similar practice in other [[Prussia]]n cities. In 1750 he issued the ''Revidiertes General Privilegium und Reglement vor die Judenschaft'': the "protected" Jews had an alternative to "either abstain from marriage or leave Berlin" (quoting [[Simon Dubnow]]). In the same year, Archduchess of [[Austria]] [[Maria Theresa of Austria|Maria Theresa]] ordered Jews out of [[Bohemia]] but soon reversed her position, on the condition that Jews pay for their readmission every ten years. This [[extortion]] was known as ''malke-geld'' (queen's money). In 1752 she introduced the law limiting each Jewish family to one son. In 1782, [[Joseph II, Holy Roman Emperor|Joseph II]] abolished most of these persecution practices in his ''[[Toleranzpatent]]'', on the condition that [[Yiddish language|Yiddish]] and [[Hebrew language|Hebrew]] were eliminated from public records and that judicial autonomy was annulled. [[Moses Mendelssohn]] wrote that "Such a tolerance... is even more dangerous play in tolerance than open persecution."

In 1772, the empress of Russia [[Catherine II]] forced the Jews of the [[Pale of Settlement]] to stay in their [[shtetls]] and forbade them from returning to the towns that they occupied before the [[partition of Poland]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/vjw/Poland.html The Virtual Jewish History Tour By Rebecca Weiner]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Nineteenth century===
Historian [[Martin Gilbert]] writes that it was in the 19th century that the position of Jews worsened in Muslim countries. [[Benny Morris]] writes that one symbol of Jewish degradation was the phenomenon of stone-throwing at Jews by Muslim children. Morris quotes a 19th century traveler: "I have seen a little fellow of six years old, with a troop of fat toddlers of only three and four, teaching [them] to throw stones at a Jew, and one little urchin would, with the greatest coolness, waddle up to the man and literally spit upon his Jewish [[gaberdine]]. To all this the Jew is obliged to submit; it would be more than his life was worth to offer to strike a Mahommedan."&lt;ref name=Morris10/&gt;

In 1850 the [[Germany|German]] composer [[Richard Wagner]] published ''[[Das Judenthum in der Musik]]'' ("Jewishness in Music") under a [[pseudonym]] in the ''[[Neue Zeitschrift für Musik]]''. The essay began as an attack on Jewish composers, particularly Wagner's contemporaries (and rivals) [[Felix Mendelssohn]] and [[Giacomo Meyerbeer]], but expanded to accuse Jews of being a harmful and alien element in [[Culture of Germany|German culture]]. Antisemitism can also be found in many of the [[Grimms' Fairy Tales]] by [[Jacob Grimm|Jacob]] and [[Wilhelm Grimm]], published from 1812 to 1857. It is mainly characterized by Jews being the [[villain]] of a story, such as in “The Good Bargain (Der gute Handel)” and “The Jew Among Thorns (Der Jude im Dorn).”

The [[Dreyfus Affair]] was an infamous antisemitic event of the late 19th century and early 20th century. [[Alfred Dreyfus]], a Jewish artillery captain in the French army, was accused in 1894 of passing secrets to the Germans. As a result of these charges, Dreyfus was convicted and sentenced to [[life imprisonment]] at Devil's Island. The actual spy, Marie Charles Esterhazy, was acquitted. The event caused great uproar among the French, with the public choosing sides regarding whether Dreyfus was actually guilty or not. [[Émile Zola]] accused the army of polluting the French justice system. However, general consensus held that Dreyfus was guilty: eighty percent of the press in France condemned him. This attitude among the majority of the French population reveals the underlying antisemitism of the time period.&lt;ref&gt;Rapport, Michael. (2005) Nineteenth Century Europe. New York: Palgrave MacMillan.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Adolf Stoecker]] (1835–1909), the [[Lutheran]] court chaplain to [[Kaiser Wilhelm I]], founded in 1878 an antisemitic, [[antiliberal]] political party called The [[Christian Social Party (Germany)]]. However, this party did not attract as many votes as the Nazi party, which flourished in part because of [[The Great Depression]], which hit Germany especially hard during the early 1930s.&lt;ref&gt;Harold M. Green (2003). "Adolf Stoecker:Portrait of a Demagogue." ''Politics and Policy'''''31'''(1):106-129; D.A. Jeremy Telman (1995) "Adolf Stoecker: Anti-Semite with a Christian Mission." ''Jewish History'''''9'''(2):93-112&lt;/ref&gt;

===Twentieth century===
[[Image:1904 Russian Tsar-Stop your cruel oppression of the Jews-LOC hh0145s.jpg|thumb|right|360px|Russian Tsar-Stop your cruel oppression of the Jews! (1904)]]

In the first half of the 20th century, in the USA, Jews were discriminated against in employment, access to residential and resort areas, membership in clubs and organizations, and in tightened quotas on Jewish enrollment and teaching positions in colleges and universities. The [[Leo Frank]] lynching by a mob of prominent citizens in [[Marietta, Georgia|Marietta]], [[Georgia (U.S. state)|Georgia]] in 1915 turned the spotlight on antisemitism in the United States. The case was also used to build support for the renewal of the [[Ku Klux Klan]] which had been inactive since 1870.

In the beginning of 20th century, the [[Menahem Mendel Beilis|Beilis Trial]] in [[Russia]] represented incidents of blood libel in Europe. Allegations of Jews killing Christians were used as justification for killing of Jews by Christians.

Antisemitism in America reached its peak during the interwar period. The pioneer automobile manufacturer [[Henry Ford]] propagated antisemitic ideas in his newspaper ''[[The Dearborn Independent]]''. The radio speeches of [[Father Coughlin]] in the late 1930s attacked [[Franklin D. Roosevelt]]'s [[New Deal]] and promoted the notion of a Jewish financial conspiracy. Such views were also shared by some prominent politicians; [[Louis T. McFadden]], Chairman of the [[United States House Committee on Banking and Currency]], blamed Jews for Roosevelt's decision to abandon the [[gold standard]], and claimed that "in the United States today, the Gentiles have the slips of paper while the Jews have the lawful money."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Arad |first=Gulie Ne'eman |title=America, Its Jews, and the Rise of Nazism |year=2000 |publisher=Indiana University Press |location=Indianapolis |isbn=0253338093 |page=174}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:Nazi Anti-Semitic Propaganda by David Shankbone.jpg|thumb|left|Two depictions of Jews used for antisemitic propaganda during Nazi Germany, shown 2007 at [[Yad Vashem]]: on the left is a depiction as Capitalist/Communist ''Vermin'', in ''[[Der Stürmer]]'', September 1944; on the right is ''The Eternal [[Wandering Jew]]'' by [[Gustave Doré]] from 1852, shown at the exhibition ''[[Der Ewige Jude (exhibition)|Der Ewige Jude]]'', 1937– 1938]]

In the 1940s the [[aviator]] [[Charles Lindbergh]] and many prominent Americans led The [[America First Committee]] in opposing any involvement in the war against [[Fascism]]. During his July 1936 visit he wrote letters saying that there was “more intelligent leadership in Germany than is generally recognized.”

The [[German American Bund]] held parades in [[New York City]] during the late 1930s, where members wore [[Nazi]] uniforms and raised flags featuring [[swastika]]s alongside American flags. The U.S. [[House Committee on Un-American Activities]] (HUAC) was very active in denying the Bund's ability to operate. With the start of U.S. involvement in [[World War II]] most of the Bund's members were placed in [[internment camp]]s, and some were deported at the end of the war.

Sometimes, during race riots, as in [[Detroit]] in 1943, Jewish businesses were targeted for looting and burning.&lt;ref&gt;Capeci Jr., Dominic J. [http://books.google.com/books?id=BBzbA3HwmbkC&amp;pg=PA384 "Black–Jewish Relations in Wartime Detroit"], in Maurianne Adams, John H. Bracey. ''Strangers &amp; neighbors: relations between Blacks &amp; Jews in the United States'', [[University of Massachusetts Press]], 1999, p. 384.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:Buchenwald Corpses 60623.jpg|An American soldier stands near a wagon piled high with corpses outside the crematorium in the newly liberated [[Buchenwald concentration camp]]|thumb]]
&lt;!-- [[Image:Selection Birkenau ramp.jpg|right|thumb|200px|"Selection" on the ''Judenrampe'', [[Auschwitz concentration camp|Auschwitz]], May/June 1944. To be sent to the right meant slave labor; to the left, the [[gas chamber]]s. This image shows the arrival of [[Hungarian people|Hungarian]] Jews from [[Carpathian Ruthenia|Carpatho-Ruthenia]], many of them from the [[Berehove|Berehov]] ghetto. It was taken by Ernst Hofmann or Bernhard Walter of the [[SS]]. Courtesy of [[Yad Vashem]].&lt;ref name=AuschwitzAlbum&gt;[http://www1.yadvashem.org/exhibitions/album_auschwitz/home_auschwitz_album.html "The Auschwitz Album"], [[Yad Vashem]].&lt;/ref&gt; {{ifdc|1=Selection Birkenau ramp.jpg|log=2009 April 6}}]] --&gt;

In Germany, according to the historian [[Hans Mommsen]], there were three types of antisemitism. In a 1997 interview, Mommsen was quoted as saying:&lt;blockquote&gt;"One should differentiate between the cultural antisemitism symptomatic of the German conservatives — found especially in the German officer corps and the high civil administration — and mainly directed against the Eastern Jews on the one hand, and ''völkisch'' antisemitism on the other. The conservative variety functions, as Shulamit Volkov has pointed out, as something of a “cultural code.” This variety of German antisemitism later on played a significant role insofar as it prevented the functional elite from distancing itself from the
repercussions of racial antisemitism. Thus, there was almost no relevant protest against the Jewish persecution on the part of the generals or the leading groups within the ''Reich'' government. This is especially true with respect to Hitler's proclamation of the “racial annihilation war” against the Soviet Union.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt; Besides conservative antisemitism, there existed in Germany a rather silent anti-Judaism within the Catholic Church, which had a certain impact on immunising the Catholic population against the escalating persecution. The famous protest of the Catholic Church against the euthanasia program was, therefore, not accompanied by any protest against the Holocaust.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt; The third and most vitriolic variety of antisemitism in Germany (and elsewhere) is the so-called ''völkisch'' antisemitism or racism, and this is the
foremost advocate of using violence."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | last = Mommsen
  | first = Hans
  | authorlink = 
  | coauthors =
  | title = Interview with Hans Mommsen
  | work =
  | publisher = Yad Vashem
  |month=December 12 | year=1997| url = http://www1.yadvashem.org/odot_pdf/Microsoft%20Word%20-%203850.pdf 
  | doi =
  | accessdate = 2010-02-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;:&lt;/blockquote&gt;

In Germany the [[National Socialist]] regime of [[Adolf Hitler]], who came to power on 30 January 1933, instituted repressive legislation denying the Jews basic civil rights and instituted a pogrom on the night of 9–10 November 1938, dubbed [[Kristallnacht]], in which Jews were killed, their property destroyed and their synagogues torched.&lt;ref&gt;Ian Kershaw (2008) ''Fateful Choices'': 441-44&lt;/ref&gt; Antisemitic laws, agitation and propaganda were extended to Nazi occupied Europe, in the wake of conquest, often building on local antisemitic traditions. In the east Jews were forced into ghettos in [[Warsaw]], [[Krakow]], [[Lvov]], [[Lublin]] and [[Radom]].&lt;ref&gt;Martin Kitchen (2007) ''The Third Reich: A Concise History''. Tempus.&lt;/ref&gt; After the invasion of Russia in 1941 a campaign of mass murder, conducted by the [[Einsatzgruppen]], culminated, between 1942 to 1945, in systematic [[genocide]]: the Holocaust.&lt;ref name="saul1"&gt;Saul Friedlander (2008) The Years of Extermination: Nazi Germany and the Jews. London, Phoenix&lt;/ref&gt; Eleven million Jews were targeted for extermination by the Nazis, and some six million were eventually killed.&lt;ref name="saul1"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Wolfgang Benz in Dimension des Volksmords: Die Zahl der Jüdischen Opfer des Nationalsozialismus (Munich: Deutscher Taschebuch Verlag, 1991). Israel Gutman, ''Encyclopedia of the Holocaust,'' Macmillan Reference Books; Reference edition (October 1, 1995)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Lucy Dawidowicz|Dawidowicz, Lucy]]. ''The War Against The Jews, 1933–1945''. New York : Holt, Rinehart and Winston, 1975.&lt;/ref&gt;

Antisemitism was commonly used as an instrument for personal conflicts in [[USSR|Soviet Russia]], starting from conflict between [[Joseph Stalin]] and [[Leon Trotsky]] and continuing through numerous conspiracy theories spread by official propaganda. Antisemitism in the USSR reached new heights after 1948 during the campaign against the [[Rootless cosmopolitan|"rootless cosmopolitan"]] (euphemism for "Jew") in which numerous Yiddish-writing poets, writers, painters and sculptors were killed or arrested.&lt;ref name="jcws"&gt;{{cite journal|author=Konstantin Azadovskii and Boris Egorov| title=From Anti-Westernism to Anti-Semitism| journal=Journal of Cold War Studies| year=2002| volume=4:1| issue=Winter| pages=66–80| url=http://www.fas.harvard.edu/~hpcws/egorov.htm#REF31}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Myth"&gt;{{cite book|title=The Myth of the Jewish Race| coauthors=Raphael and Jennifer Patai| year=1989| page=178| publisher=Wayne State University Press| isbn=0814319483, 9780814319482}}&lt;/ref&gt; This culminated in the so-called [[Doctors' Plot]]. Similar [[anti-Semitic propaganda]] in Poland resulted in the flight of the Polish Jewish survivors out of the country.&lt;ref name="Myth" /&gt;

After the war, the [[Kielce pogrom]] and "[[March 1968 events]]" in communist [[Poland]] represented further incidents of antisemitism in Europe. The common theme behind the [[Anti-Jewish violence in Poland, 1944–1946|anti-Jewish violence in postwar Poland]] were [[blood libel]] rumours.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=4Iiw0KB31rgC&amp;pg=PA233&amp;ots=Se_CvAI3X6&amp;dq=Cracow+Kupa+synagogue+ritual+murder&amp;num=100&amp;sig=0t5WKlHjavg6aVgoL1ertcsPn9U]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=xZ5Ceq6l0M0C&amp;pg=PA74&amp;ots=VvcY2-LqLQ&amp;dq=blood+libel+kielce&amp;num=100&amp;sig=JY3EykCZ-dp3x3HoBc1jM2vFzks]&lt;/ref&gt;

The cult of [[Simon of Trent]] was disbanded in 1965 by [[Pope Paul VI]], and the shrine erected to him was dismantled. He was removed from the calendar, and his future veneration was forbidden, though a handful of extremists still promote the narrative as a fact.

==Christianity and antisemitism==
{{Main|Religious antisemitism}}
{{Main|Christianity and antisemitism}}

Religious antisemitism is also known as anti-Judaism. As the name implies, it was the practice of [[Judaism]] itself that was the defining characteristic of the antisemitic attacks. Under this version of antisemitism, attacks would often stop if Jews stopped practicing or changed their public faith, especially by [[Religious conversion|conversion]] to the official or right religion, and sometimes, liturgical exclusion of Jewish converts (the case of Christianized ''[[Marranos]]'' or Iberian Jews in the late 15th century and 16th century convicted of secretly practising Judaism or Jewish customs).&lt;ref&gt;See, for example, Flannery, Edward H. ''The Anguish of the Jews: Twenty-Three Centuries of Antisemitism'', Stimulus Books, first published 1985, this edition 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;

===New Testament and antisemitism===
{{Main|Antisemitism in the New Testament}}

Frederick Schweitzer and Marvin Perry write that the authors of the gospel accounts sought to place responsibility for the [[Crucifixion of Jesus]] and his death on Jews, rather than the Roman emperor or [[Pontius Pilate]].&lt;ref&gt;Schweitzer &amp; Perry (2002), pp. 27, 35.&lt;/ref&gt; As a result, Christians for centuries viewed Jews as "the Christ Killers".&lt;ref name=SchweitzerPerry2002p18&gt;Schweitzer &amp; Perry (2002), p. 18.&lt;/ref&gt; The destruction of the [[Second Temple]] was seen as judgment from God to the Jews for that death,&lt;ref&gt;Richardson (1986), p. 23&lt;/ref&gt; and Jews were seen as "a people condemned forever to suffer exile and degradation".&lt;ref name=SchweitzerPerry2002p18/&gt; According to historian [[Edward H. Flannery]], the [[Gospel of John]] in particular contains many verses that refer to Jews in a pejorative manner.&lt;ref&gt;Flannery (2004) p. 33.&lt;/ref&gt;

In {{bibleverse|1|Thessalonians|2:14-16|31}}, [[Paul (apostle)|Paul]] states that the Churches in Judea had been persecuted by the Jews who killed Jesus and that such people displease God, oppose all men, and had prevented Paul from speaking to the gentile nations concerning the New Testament message. Described by [[Hyam Maccoby]] as "the most explicit outburst against Jews in Paul's Epistles",&lt;ref name=Maccoby203&gt;[[Hyam Maccoby]], ''The Mythmaker: Paul and the Invention of Christianity'', [[Harper &amp; Row]], 1986, ISBN 0-06-015582-5, p. 203.&lt;/ref&gt; these verses have repeatedly been employed for antisemitic purposes. Maccoby views it as one of Paul's innovations responsible for creating Christian antisemitism, though he notes that some have argued these particular verses are later interpolations not written by Paul.&lt;ref name=Maccoby203/&gt; [[Craig Blomberg]] argues that viewing them as antisemitic is a mistake, but "understandable in light of [Paul's] harsh words". In his view, Paul is not condemning all Jews forever, but merely those he believed had specifically persecuted the prophets, Jesus, or the 1st century church. Blomberg sees Paul's words here as no different in kind than the harsh words the prophets of the Old Testament have for the Jews.&lt;ref&gt;[[Craig Blomberg]], ''From Pentecost to Patmos: An Introduction to Acts Through Revelation'', [[B&amp;H Publishing Group]], 2006, ISBN 9780805432480, p. 144.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Codex Sinaiticus]] contains two extra books in the New Testament – the [[Shepherd of Hermas]] and the [[Epistle of Barnabas]].&lt;ref name="bbc"&gt;{{cite news|title=The rival to the Bible |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/magazine/7651105.stm|publisher=BBC News|author=Roger Bolton|date=October 6, 2008|accessdate=January 1, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The latter emphasizes the claim that it was the Jews, not the Romans, who killed Jesus, and is full of antisemitism.&lt;ref name="bbc"/&gt; The Epistle of Barnabas was removed from later versions of the Bible; Professor [[Bart Ehrman]] has stated "the suffering of Jews in the subsequent centuries would, if possible, have been even worse had the Epistle of Barnabas remained".&lt;ref name="bbc"/&gt;

===Early Christianity===
A number of early and influential Church works — such as the dialogues of [[Justin Martyr]], the homilies of [[John Chrysostom]], and the testimonies of church father [[Cyprian]] — are strongly anti-Jewish.

During a discussion on the celebration of [[Easter]] during the [[First Council of Nicaea]] in 325 CE, Roman emperor [[Constantine I (emperor)|Constantine]] said, &lt;blockquote&gt; ...it appeared an unworthy thing that in the celebration of this most holy feast we should follow the practice of the Jews, who have impiously defiled their hands with enormous sin, and are, therefore, deservedly afflicted with blindness of soul. (...) Let us then have nothing in common with the detestable Jewish crowd; for we have received from our Saviour a different way.&lt;ref name=Eusebius&gt;[[Eusebius of Caesarea|Eusebius]]. [http://www.newadvent.org/fathers/25023.htm "Life of Constantine (Book III)"], 337 CE. Retrieved March 12, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Prejudice against Jews in the [[Roman Empire]] was formalized in 438, when the ''Code of [[Theodosius II]]'' established Christianity as the only legal religion in the Roman Empire. The [[Justinian Code]] a century later stripped Jews of many of their rights, and Church councils throughout the 6th and 7th century, including the Council of Orleans, further enforced anti-Jewish provisions. These restrictions began as early as 305, when, in Elvira, (now [[Granada]]), a Spanish town in [[Andalucia]], the first known laws of any church council against Jews appeared. Christian women were forbidden to marry Jews unless the Jew first converted to Catholicism. Jews were forbidden to extend hospitality to Catholics. Jews could not keep Catholic Christian [[concubine]]s and were forbidden to bless the fields of Catholics. In 589, in Catholic [[Iberian Peninsula|Iberia]], the [[Third Council of Toledo]] ordered that children born of marriage between Jews and Catholic be baptized by force. By the Twelfth Council of Toledo (681) a policy of forced conversion of all Jews was initiated (Liber Judicum, II.2 as given in Roth).&lt;ref name=Roth&gt;Roth, A. M. Roth, and Roth, Norman. ''Jews, Visigoths and Muslims in Medieval Spain'', Brill Academic, 1994.&lt;/ref&gt; Thousands fled, and thousands of others converted to Roman Catholicism.

===Medieval and Renaissance Europe===
{{Main|Jews in the Middle Ages|Antisemitism in Europe (Middle Ages)}}
Antisemitism was widespread in Europe during the [[Middle Ages]]. In those times, a main cause of prejudice against Jews in Europe was the religious one. Although not part of [[Roman Catholic]] [[dogma]], many Christians, including members of the [[clergy]], held the Jewish people [[collective guilt|collectively responsible]] for the death of Jesus, a practice originated by [[Melito of Sardis]].

Among socio-economic factors were restrictions by the authorities. Local rulers and church officials closed the doors for many professions to the Jews, pushing them into occupations considered socially inferior such as accounting, rent-collecting and [[moneylending]], which was tolerated then as a "[[consequentialism|necessary evil]]".&lt;ref name=Paley&gt;Paley, Susan and Koesters, Adrian Gibbons, eds. {{PDFlink|[http://moses.creighton.edu/JRS/pdf/ViewersGuide.pdf "A Viewer's Guide to Contemporary Passion Plays"]|74.4&amp;nbsp;KB}}. Retrieved March 12, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; During the [[Black Death]], Jews were accused as being the cause, and were often killed.&lt;ref name="Black"&gt;See Stéphane Barry and Norbert Gualde, ''La plus grande épidémie de l'histoire'' ("The greatest epidemics in history"), in ''[[L'Histoire]]'' magazine, n°310, June 2006, p.47 {{fr icon}}&lt;/ref&gt; There were expulsions of Jews from [[England]], [[France]], [[Germany]], [[Portugal]] and [[Spain]] during the Middle Ages as a result of antisemitism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Holocaust and Return to Zion: A Study in Jewish Philosophy of History |last=Spero |first=Shubert |year=2000 |publisher=KTAV Publishing House, Inc. |isbn=0881256366 |page=164}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:Judensau Frankfurt.jpg|thumb|left|18th century Frankfurt Judensau]]
[[German language|German]] for "Jews' sow", ''[[Judensau]]'' was the derogatory and dehumanizing imagery of Jews that appeared around the 13th century. Its popularity lasted for over 600 years and was revived by the Nazis. The Jews, typically portrayed in [[obscene]] contact with [[unclean animals]] such as [[pig]]s or [[owl]]s or representing a [[devil]], appeared on [[cathedral]] or [[church (building)|church]] ceilings, pillars, utensils, etchings, etc. Often, the images combined several antisemitic motifs and included derisive prose or poetry.
&lt;blockquote&gt;"Dozens of Judensaus... intersect with the portrayal of the Jew as a [[deicide|Christ killer]]. Various illustrations of the murder of [[Simon of Trent]] blended images of Judensau, the [[devil]], the murder of little Simon himself, and the [[Crucifixion]]. In the 17th-century engraving from Frankfurt&lt;ref&gt;Cohen's book includes an earlier variation of the same image.&lt;/ref&gt; ... a well-dressed, very contemporary-looking Jew has mounted the sow backward and holds her tail, while a second Jew sucks at her milk and a third eats her feces. The horned devil, himself wearing a [[Yellow badge|Jewish badge]], looks on and the butchered Simon, splayed as if on a cross, appears on a panel above."&lt;ref&gt;Jeremy Cohen (2007): ''Christ Killers: The Jews and the Passion from the Bible to the Big Screen.'' Oxford University Press. p.208 ISBN 0-19-517841-6&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

In [[William Shakespeare|Shakespeare]]'s ''"[[Merchant of Venice]]",'' considered to be one of the greatest romantic comedies of all time, the villain [[Shylock]] was a Jewish moneylender. By the end of the play he is mocked on the streets after his daughter elopes with a Christian. Shylock, then, compulsorily converts to Christianity as a part of a deal gone wrong. This has raised profound implications regarding Shakespeare and antisemitism.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.berens.org/tikkun.html On Beyond Shylock] by Bradley S. Berens&lt;/ref&gt;

During the Middle Ages, the story of Jephonias,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.christusrex.org/www1/ofm/pilgr/sources/TransVirginis.html#46 Transitus or Dormitio Virginis], the original 5th or 6th century text&lt;/ref&gt; the Jew who tried to overturn Mary's funeral bier, changed from his converting to Christianity into his simply having his hands cut off by an angel.&lt;ref&gt;[http://sicsa.huji.ac.il/99an2a.html Self-Description and the Antisemite: Denying Privileged Access]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:Descreationofhost.gif|thumb|right|A 15th century German woodcut showing an alleged host desecration.&lt;br/&gt;''1:'' the hosts are stolen&lt;br/&gt;''2:'' the hosts bleed when pierced by a Jew&lt;br/&gt;''3:'' the Jews are arrested&lt;br/&gt;''4:'' they are burned alive.]]
On many occasions, Jews were subjected to [[blood libel against Jews|blood libels]], false accusations of drinking the blood of Christian children in mockery of the Christian [[Eucharist]].
Jews were subject to a wide range of legal restrictions throughout the Middle Ages, some of which lasted until the end of the 19th century. Jews were excluded from many trades, the occupations varying with place and time, and determined by the influence of various non-Jewish competing interests. Often Jews were barred from all occupations but money-lending and peddling, with even these at times forbidden.

===19th and 20th century===
{{See also|Christianity and Judaism|Relations between Catholicism and Judaism}}
[[Image:proper hands.jpg|right|200px|thumb|[[Branford Clarke]] illustration in [[Heroes of the Fiery Cross]] by Bishop [[Alma White]] 1928 Published by the [[Pillar of Fire Church]] in [[Zarephath, NJ]]]]
Throughout the 19th century and into the 20th, the Roman Catholic Church still incorporated strong antisemitic elements, despite increasing attempts to separate anti-Judaism, the opposition to the Jewish religion on religious grounds, and racial antisemitism. [[Pope Pius VII]] (1800–1823) had the walls of the Jewish [[Ghetto]] in Rome rebuilt after the Jews were [[Napoleon and the Jews|released by Napoleon]], and Jews were restricted to the Ghetto through the end of the Papal States in 1870. 

Additionally, official organizations such as the [[Jesuits]] banned candidates "who are descended from the Jewish race unless it is clear that their father, grandfather, and great-grandfather have belonged to the Catholic Church" until 1946. Brown University historian [[David Kertzer]], working from the Vatican archive, has further argued in his book ''[[The Popes Against the Jews]]'' that in the 19th century and early 20th century the [[Roman Catholic Church]] adhered to a distinction between "good antisemitism" and "bad antisemitism". 

The "bad" kind promoted hatred of Jews because of their descent. This was considered un-Christian because the Christian message was intended for all of humanity regardless of ethnicity; anyone could become a Christian. The "good" kind criticized alleged Jewish conspiracies to control newspapers, banks, and other institutions, to care only about accumulation of wealth, etc. Many Catholic bishops wrote articles criticizing Jews on such grounds, and, when accused of promoting hatred of Jews, would remind people that they condemned the "bad" kind of antisemitism. Kertzer's work is not, therefore, without critics; scholar of Jewish-Christian relations [[Rabbi David G. Dalin]], for example, criticized Kertzer in the ''[[Weekly Standard]]'' for using evidence selectively.

The [[Second Vatican Council]], the [[Nostra Aetate]] document, and the efforts of [[Pope John Paul II]] have helped reconcile Jews and Catholicism in recent decades, however. According to Roman Catholic Holocaust scholar [[Michael Phayer]] the Church as a whole recognized its failings during the council when it corrected the traditional beliefs of the Jews having committed deicide and affirmed that they remained God's chosen people.&lt;ref&gt;"''Pius XII, The Holocaust and the Cold War''", Indiana University Press, p. 252, 2008, ISBN 978-0-253-34930-9&lt;/ref&gt;

The Nazis used [[Martin Luther]]'s book, ''[[On the Jews and Their Lies]]'' (1543), to [[Luther_and_antisemitism#Use by the Nazis|claim]] a moral righteousness for their ideology.  Luther even went so far as to advocate the murder of those Jews who refused to convert to Christianity, writing that "we are at fault in not slaying them"&lt;ref&gt;Luther, Martin. ''On the Jews and Their'' ''Lies'', cited in Robert.Michael. "Luther, Luther Scholars, and the Jews," ''Encounter'' 46 ( Autumn 1985) No.4.343-344&lt;/ref&gt; In 1994, the Church Council of the [[Evangelical Lutheran Church in America]], the largest [[Lutheran]] denomination in the United States and a member of the [[Lutheran World Federation]] publicly [[Luther and antisemitism#Recent Lutheran Church responses|rejected]] Luther's antisemitic writings. The controversial document [[Dabru Emet]] was issued by many American Jewish scholars in 2000 as a statement about Jewish-Christian relations. This document says, &lt;blockquote&gt;
"Nazism was not a Christian phenomenon. Without the long history of Christian anti-Judaism and Christian violence against Jews, Nazi ideology could not have taken hold nor could it have been carried out. Too many Christians participated in, or were sympathetic to, Nazi atrocities against Jews. Other Christians did not protest sufficiently against these atrocities. But Nazism itself was not an inevitable outcome of Christianity."
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

===Accusations of deicide===
{{Main|Jewish deicide}}

Though never a part of [[Christian]] [[dogma]], many Christians, including members of the [[clergy]], held the Jewish people under an [[antisemitic canard]] to be [[collective guilt|collectively responsible]] for [[deicide]], the [[Jewish deicide|killing of Jesus]], whom they believed to be the son of God.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/jubilee_2000/magazine/documents/ju_mag_01111997_p-31_en.html Nostra Aetate: a milestone – Pier Francesco Fumagalli]&lt;/ref&gt;

According to this interpretation, the Jews present at Jesus’ death as well as the Jewish people collectively and for all time had committed the sin of deicide, or God-killing. The accusation has been the most powerful warrant for antisemitism by Christians.&lt;ref&gt;Schweitzer, Perry (2002) pp. 26&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Passion play]]s are dramatic stagings representing the trial and death of [[Jesus]] and have historically been used in remembrance of Jesus' death during [[Lent]]. These plays historically blamed the Jews for [[deicide|the death of Jesus]] in a [[polemic]]al fashion, depicting a crowd of Jewish people condemning Jesus to [[crucifixion]] and a Jewish leader assuming eternal [[collective guilt]] for the crowd for the murder of Jesus, which, ''[[The Boston Globe]]'' explains, "for centuries prompted vicious attacks — or [[pogrom]]s — on Europe's Jewish communities".&lt;ref name=Sennott&gt;Sennott, Charles M. [http://www.boston.com/news/globe/living/articles/2004/04/10/in_poland_new_passion_plays_on_old_hatreds/ "In Poland, new 'Passion' plays on old hatreds"], ''[[The Boston Globe]]'', April 10, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Islam and antisemitism==
{{Main|Islam and antisemitism}}
{{See also|Arabs and antisemitism|History of the Jews under Muslim rule}}
Various definitions of antisemitism in the context of Islam are given. The extent of antisemitism among Muslims varies depending on the chosen definition:

*Scholars like [[Claude Cahen]] and [[Shelomo Dov Goitein]] define it to be the animosity specifically applied to Jews only and do not include discriminations practiced against Non-Muslims in general.&lt;ref name="Shelomo Dov Goitein"&gt;[[Shelomo Dov Goitein]], A Mediterranean Society: An Abridgment in One Volume, p. 293&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Cahen"&gt;"Dhimma" by Claude Cahen in [[Encyclopedia of Islam]]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="OxfordDic"&gt;The Oxford Dictionary of the Jewish Religion, ''Antisemitism''&lt;/ref&gt; For these scholars, antisemitism in Medieval Islam has been local and sporadic rather than general and endemic [Shelomo Dov Goitein],&lt;ref name="Shelomo Dov Goitein"/&gt; not at all present [Claude Cahen],&lt;ref name="Cahen"/&gt; or rarely present.&lt;ref name="OxfordDic"/&gt;

*According to [[Bernard Lewis]], antisemitism is marked by two distinct features: Jews are judged according to a standard different from that applied to others, and they are accused of "cosmic evil."&lt;ref&gt;Lewis, Bernard. "The New Anti-Semitism", The American Scholar, Volume 75 No. 1, Winter 2006, pp. 25-36. The paper is based on a lecture delivered at Brandeis University on March 24, 2004&lt;/ref&gt; For Lewis, from the late 19th century, movements appear among Muslims of which for the first time one can legitimately use the technical term antisemitic.&lt;ref&gt;Lewis(1984), p.184&lt;/ref&gt; However, he describes demonizing beliefs, anti-Jewish discrimination and systematic humiliations, as an "inherent" part of the traditional Muslim world, even if violent persecutions were relatively rare.&lt;ref&gt;Lewis(1984), p.8, 32-33, 41-45, etc.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Jews in Islamic texts===
[[Leon Poliakov]],&lt;ref name="EncJud"&gt;Poliakov&lt;/ref&gt; [[Walter Laqueur]],&lt;ref name="Laqueur192"/&gt; and [[Jane Gerber]],&lt;ref&gt;Gerber 78&lt;/ref&gt; suggest that later passages in the [[Qur'an]] contain very sharp attacks on Jews for their refusal to recognize [[Muhammad]] as a [[prophet]] of [[God]].&lt;ref name="EncJud"/&gt; There are also Qur'anic verses, particularly from the earliest Qur'anic [[surah]]s, showing respect for the Jews (e.g. see {{Quran-usc|2|47}}, {{Quran-usc|2|62}})&lt;ref name="Poliakov (1961), pg. 27"&gt;Poliakov (1961), pg. 27&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Glazov, Jamie, "Symposium: The Koran and Anti-Semitism", FrontPageMag.com, June 25, 2004. (retrieved May 3, 2006)&lt;/ref&gt; and preaching tolerance (e.g. see {{Quran-usc|2|256}}).&lt;ref name="Laqueur192"&gt;Laqueur 192&lt;/ref&gt; This positive view tended to disappear in the later Surahs. Taking it all together, the Qur'an differentiates between "good and bad" Jews, Poliakov states.&lt;ref name="Poliakov (1961), pg. 27"/&gt; Laqueur argues that the conflicting statements about Jews in the Muslim holy text has defined [[Arab]] and Muslim attitude towards Jews to this day, especially during periods of rising [[Islamic fundamentalism]].&lt;ref&gt;Laqueur 191&lt;/ref&gt;

During Muhammad's life, Jews lived in the [[Arabian Peninsula]], especially in and around [[Medina]]. They reportedly refused [[Muhammad]]'s offer for them to convert and accept him as the Prophet.&lt;ref&gt;F.E.Peters(2003), p.103&lt;/ref&gt; According to [[F.E. Peters]], they also began to secretly to conspire with Muhammad's enemies in [[Mecca]] to overthrow him (despite having been forced by their conquerors to sign a peace treaty.)&lt;ref name="Sameul"&gt;Samuel Rosenblatt, ''Essays on Antisemitism: The Jews of Islam'', p.112&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;F.E.Peters(2003), p.194&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;The Cambridge History of Islam (1977), pp.43-44&lt;/ref&gt; After each major battle, Muhammad accused one of the Jewish tribes of treachery and attacked it. Two Jewish tribes were expelled and the last one, the Banu Qura was wiped out after it threw itself on Muhammad's mercy.&lt;ref name="Laqueur192"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Esposito (1998), pp.10-11&lt;/ref&gt; Samuel Rosenblatt states that these incidents were not part of policies directed exclusively against Jews, and that Muhammad was more severe with Arab pagans than with Jews.&lt;ref name="Sameul"/&gt; 

The attitude towards Jews changed in the course of Muhammad's career, as expressed in more positive teachings in the earlier Qur'anic surahs, from the Mecca period, to increasingly hostile and negative ones, characterizing Jews as such, in Medina as the Jewish tribes there refused to submit completely to Muhammad's authority and claims. This distinction of periods is crucial to assess the weight of Qur'anic passages. According to traditional rules of Qur'anic exegesis stipulated in the Qur'an itself (Surah 2:106, from the later Medina period), the later passages must be taken as the last and binding final word from God, rendering earlier passages merely temporal expedients that no longer apply and are cancelled outright. Thus the negative characterizations have become the authoritative consensus. It may therefore be quite misleading to equate the earlier more positive statements with the later ones as some apologists do.

The words "humility" and "humiliation" occur frequently in the Qur'an and later Muslim literature in relation to Jews. According to Lewis, "This, in Islamic view, is their just punishment for their past rebelliousness, and is manifested in their present impotence between the mighty powers of Christendom and Islam." The standard Quranic reference to Jews is verse {{Quran-usc|2|61}}: "And remember ye said: "O [[Moses]]! we cannot endure one kind of food (always); so beseech thy Lord for us to produce for us of what the earth groweth, -its pot-herbs, and cucumbers, Its [[garlic]], [[lentil]]s, and [[onion]]s." He said: "Will ye exchange the better for the worse? Go ye down to any town, and ye shall find what ye want!" They were covered with humiliation and misery; they drew on themselves the wrath of Allah. This because they went on rejecting the Signs of Allah and slaying His Messengers without just cause. This because they rebelled and went on transgressing."&lt;ref name = "Lewis p128"&gt;Lewis (1999), p. 128&lt;/ref&gt; 

Two verses later we read: "And remember, Children of [[Israel]], when We made a covenant with you and raised [[Mount Sinai]] before you saying, "Hold tightly to what We have revealed to you and keep it in mind so that you may guard against evil." But then you turned away, and if it had not been for [[Allah]]'s grace and merecy, you surely would have been among the lost. And you know those among who sinned on the [[Shabbat|Sabbath]]. We said to them, "You will be transformed into despised apes." So we used them as a warning to their people and to the following generations, as well as a lesson for the Allah-fearing."(Qur'an {{Quran-usc|2|63}}) The accusation that Jews will ultimately be transformed into apes and pigs is traditionally understood literally and is derived from such Qur'anic and other early Muslim sources.

The Qur'an associates Jews above all with rejection of God's prophets including Jesus and Muhammad, thus explaining their resistance to him personally. (Cf. Surah 2:87-91; 5:59, 61, 70, and 82.) It states that they are, together with outright idolators, the worst and most inveterate enemies of Islam, and thus will not only suffer eternally in Hell but in this world will be the most degraded of the Peoples of the Book, below even Christians, everywhere. (Cf. Surah 5:82; 3:54-56.) It also asserts that Jews believe that they are the sole children of God (Surah 5:18), and that only they will achieve salvation (Surah 2:111). According to the Qur'an, Jews blasphemously claim that [[Ezra]] is the son of God, as [[Christians]] claim Jesus is, (Surah 9:30) and that God’s hand is fettered (Surah 5:64 – i.e., that they can freely defy God). Some of those who are Jews,&lt;ref name="Yahud"&gt;Here the Qur'an uses an Arabic expression ''alladhina hadu'' ("those who are Jewish"), which appears in the Qur'an ten times. "Yahud". ''Encyclopedia of Islam''&lt;/ref&gt; "pervert words from their meanings", (Surah 4:44), and because they have committed wrongdoing, God has "forbidden some good things that were previously permitted them", thus explaining Jewish commandments regarding food, Sabbath restrictions on work, and other rulings as a punishment from God (Surah 4:160). They listen for the sake of mendacity (Surah 5:41), twisting the truth, and practice forbidden usury, and therefore they will receive "a painful doom" (Surah 4:161).&lt;ref name="Yahud"/&gt; The Qur'an gives credence to the Christian claim of Jews scheming against Jesus, "...but God also schemed, and God is the best of schemers"(Surah 3:54). In the Muslim view, the [[crucifixion of Jesus]] was an illusion, and thus the supposed Jewish plots against him ended in complete failure.&lt;ref&gt;Lewis (1999), p. 120&lt;/ref&gt; In numerous verses (Surah 3:63, 71; 4:46, 160-161; 5:41-44, 63-64, 82; 6:92)&lt;ref&gt;Gerber (1986), p. 91&lt;/ref&gt; the Qur'an accuses Jews of deliberately [[tahrif|obscuring and perverting scripture]].&lt;ref name = "Gerber p78"&gt;Gerber (1986), p. 78&lt;/ref&gt;

===Differences with Christianity===
[[Bernard Lewis]] holds that Muslims were not antisemitic in the way Christians were for the most part because:
# The gospels are not part of the educational system in Muslim society and therefore Muslims are not brought up with the stories of [[Jewish deicide]]; on the contrary the notion of deicide is rejected by the Qur'an as a blasphemous absurdity.
# Muhammad and his early followers were not Jews and therefore they did not present themselves as the true Israel or feel threatened by survival of the old Israel.
# The Qur'an was not viewed by Muslims as a fulfillment of the [[Hebrew Bible]], but rather as a restorer of its original messages that had been distorted over time. Thus no clash of interpretations between Judaism and Islam could arise.
# Muhammad was not killed by the Jewish community and he was victorious in the clash with the Jewish community in Medina.
# Muhammad did not claim to have been Son of God or Messiah but only a prophet; a claim which Jews repudiated less.
# Muslims saw the conflict between Muhammad and the Jews as something of minor importance in Muhammad's career.&lt;ref&gt;Lewis (1999), p.117-118&lt;/ref&gt;

===Status of Jews under Muslim rule===
Traditionally Jews living in Muslim lands, known (along with Christians) as [[dhimmis]], were allowed to practice their religion and to administer their internal affairs but subject to certain conditions.&lt;ref name = "Gerber p10,20"&gt;Lewis (1984), pp.10,20&lt;/ref&gt; They had to pay the [[jizya]] (a per capita tax imposed on free adult non-Muslim males) to Muslims.&lt;ref name = "Gerber p10,20"/&gt; Dhimmis had an inferior status under Islamic rule. They had several social and legal [[Disabilities (Jewish)|disabilities]] such as prohibitions against bearing arms or giving testimony in courts in cases involving Muslims.&lt;ref&gt;Lewis (1987), p. 9, 27&lt;/ref&gt; Many of the disabilities were highly symbolic. The most degrading one was the requirement of [[Yellow badge|distinctive clothing]], not found in the Qur'an or hadith but invented in [[Early Middle Ages|early medieval]] [[Baghdad]]; its enforcement was highly erratic.&lt;ref&gt;Lewis (1999), p.131&lt;/ref&gt; Jews rarely faced martyrdom or exile, or forced compulsion to change their religion, and they were mostly free in their choice of residence and profession.&lt;ref&gt;Lewis (1999), p.131; (1984), pp.8,62&lt;/ref&gt;

The notable examples of massacre of Jews include the [[1066 Granada massacre]], when a Muslim mob stormed the royal palace in [[Granada]], [[crucifixion|crucified]] [[Jew]]ish [[vizier]] [[Joseph ibn Naghrela]] and massacred most of the Jewish population of the city. "More than 1,500 Jewish families, numbering 4,000 persons, fell in one day."&lt;ref name = "Gottheil-1906"&gt;[http://jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?artid=412&amp;letter=G&amp;search=Granada Granada] by Richard Gottheil, [[Meyer Kayserling]], ''[[Jewish Encyclopedia]]''. 1906 ed.&lt;/ref&gt; This was the first persecution of Jews on the Peninsula under Islamic rule. There was also the killing or forcibly conversion of them by the rulers of the [[Almohad]] dynasty in [[Al-Andalus]] in the 12th century.&lt;ref&gt;Lewis (1984), p. 52; Stillman (1979), p.77&lt;/ref&gt; Notable examples of the cases where the choice of residence was taken away from them includes confining Jews to walled quarters ([[mellah]]s) in Morocco beginning from the 15th century and especially since the early 19th century.&lt;ref&gt;Lewis (1984), p. 28&lt;/ref&gt; Most conversions were voluntary and happened for various reasons. However, there were some forced conversions in the 12th century under the [[Almohad]] dynasty of North Africa and [[al-Andalus]] as well as in Persia.&lt;ref&gt;Lewis (1984), pp.17,18,94,95; Stillman (1979), p.27&lt;/ref&gt;

===Pre-modern times===
The portrayal of the Jews in the early Islamic texts played a key role in shaping the attitudes towards them in the Muslim societies. According to [[Jane Gerber]], "the Muslim is continually influenced by the theological threads of anti-Semitism embedded in the earliest chapters of Islamic history."&lt;ref&gt;Gerber (1986), p. 82&lt;/ref&gt; In the light of the Jewish defeat at the hands of Muhammad, Muslims traditionally viewed Jews with contempt and as objects of ridicule. Jews were seen as hostile, cunning, and vindictive, but nevertheless weak and ineffectual. Cowardice was the quality most frequently attributed to Jews. Another stereotype associated with the Jews was their alleged propensity to trickery and deceit. While most anti-Jewish polemicists saw those qualities as inherently Jewish, [[Ibn Khaldun]] attributed them to the mistreatment of Jews at the hands of the dominant nations. For that reason, says ibn Khaldun, Jews "are renowned, in every age and climate, for their wickedness and their slyness".&lt;ref&gt;Lewis (1999), pp. 129–130&lt;/ref&gt;

Some Muslim writers have inserted racial overtones in their anti-Jewish polemics. [[Al-Jahiz]] speaks of the deterioration of the Jewish stock due to excessive inbreeding. [[Ibn Hazm]] also implies racial qualities in his attacks on the Jews. However, these were exceptions, and the racial theme left little or no trace in the medieval Muslim anti-Jewish writings.&lt;ref&gt;Lewis (1999), pp. 131–132&lt;/ref&gt;

Anti-Jewish sentiments usually flared up at times of the Muslim political or military weakness or when Muslims felt that some Jews had overstepped the boundary of humiliation prescribed to them by the Islamic law.&lt;ref&gt;Lewis (1999), p. 130; Gerber (1986), p. 83&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Al-Andalus|Moorish Iberia]], ibn Hazm and [[Abu Ishaq]] focused their anti-Jewish writings on the latter allegation. This was also the chief motivation behind the [[1066 Granada massacre]], when "[m]ore than 1,500 Jewish families, numbering 4,000 persons, fell in one day",&lt;ref name = "Gottheil-1906"/&gt; and in [[Fes, Morocco|Fez]] in 1033, when 6,000 Jews were killed.&lt;ref name=Morris10&gt;[[Benny Morris|Morris, Benny]]. ''Righteous Victims: A History of the Zionist-Arab Conflict, 1881-2001''. Vintage Books, 2001, pp. 10-11.&lt;/ref&gt; There were further massacres in Fez in 1276 and 1465.&lt;ref&gt;Gerber (1986), p. 84&lt;/ref&gt;

Islamic law does not differentiate between Jews and Christians in their status as dhimmis. According to [[Bernard Lewis]], the normal practice of Muslim governments until modern times was consistent with this aspect of [[sharia]] law.&lt;ref name = "Lewis p128"/&gt; This view is countered by Jane Gerber, who maintains that of all dhimmis, Jews had the lowest status. Gerber maintains that this situation was especially pronounced in the latter centuries, when Christian communities enjoyed protection, unavailable to the Jews, under the provisions of [[Capitulations of the Ottoman Empire]]. For example, in 18th century [[Damascus]], a Muslim noble held a festival, inviting to it all social classes in descending order, according to their social status: the Jews outranked only the peasants and prostitutes.&lt;ref&gt;Gerber (1986), pp. 84–85&lt;/ref&gt; In 1865, when the equality of all subjects of the Ottoman Empire was proclaimed, [[Ahmed Cevdet Pasha]], a high-ranking official observed: "whereas in former times, in the Ottoman State, the communities were ranked, with the Muslims first, then the Greeks, then the Armenians, then the Jews, now all of them were put on the same level. Some Greeks objected to this, saying: 'The government has put us together with the Jews. We were content with the supremacy of Islam.'"&lt;ref&gt;Lewis (1999), pp. 136–137; Gerber (1986), p. 86&lt;/ref&gt;

Some scholars have questioned the correctness of the term "antisemitism" to Muslim culture in pre-modern times.&lt;ref name="autogenerated1" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Cahen, Cl. "[http://www.brillonline.nl/subscriber/entry?entry=islam_SIM-1823 ḎH̲imma.]" Encyclopaedia of Islam. Edited by: P. Bearman, Th. Bianquis, C.E. Bosworth, E. van Donzel and W.P. Heinrichs. Brill, 2006. Brill Online.21 November 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Mark R. Cohen|Mark Cohen]] (1995) p. xvii&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Nissim Rejwan, ''Israel's Place in the Middle East: A Pluralist Perspective'', University Press of Florida, p.31&lt;/ref&gt; Robert Chazan and Alan Davies argue that the most obvious difference between pre-modern Islam and pre-modern Christendom was the "rich melange of racial, ethic, and religious communities" in Islamic countries, within which "the Jews were by no means obvious as lone dissenters, as they had been earlier in the world of polytheism or subsequently in most of medieval Christendom." According to Chazan and Davies, this lack of uniqueness ameliorated the circumstances of Jews in the medieval world of Islam.&lt;ref&gt;Encyclopedia of religion, anti-semitism article.&lt;/ref&gt; According to [[Norman Stillman]], antisemitism, understood as hatred of Jews as Jews, "did exist in the medieval Arab world even in the period of greatest tolerance".&lt;ref&gt;Stillman (1979), p. 63&lt;/ref&gt; Also see Bostom, Bat Ye'or, and the CSPI issued text, supporting Stillman and cited in the bibliography.

===Nineteenth century===
Historian [[Martin Gilbert]] writes that in the 19th century the position of Jews worsened in Muslim countries.{{Citation needed|date=May 2007}}

There was a massacre of Jews in [[Baghdad]] in 1828&lt;ref name=Morris10/&gt; and in 1839, in the eastern Persian city of [[Meshed]], a mob burst into the Jewish Quarter, burned the synagogue, and destroyed the [[Sefer Torah|Torah scrolls]]. It was only by forcible conversion that a massacre was averted.&lt;ref name=Gilbert179&gt;[[Martin Gilbert|Gilbert, Martin]]. ''Dearest Auntie Fori. The Story of the Jewish People''. HarperCollins, 2002, pp. 179-182.&lt;/ref&gt; There was another massacre in Barfurush in 1867.&lt;ref name=Morris10/&gt;

In 1840, the [[History of the Jews in Syria|Jews of Damascus]] were falsely accused of having murdered a Christian monk and his Muslim servant and of having [[blood libel|used their blood]] to bake [[Matzo|Passover bread]] or Matza. A Jewish barber was tortured until he "confessed"; two other Jews who were arrested died under torture, while a third converted to Islam to save his life. Throughout the 1860s, the [[History of the Jews in Libya|Jews of Libya]] were subjected to what Gilbert calls punitive taxation. In 1864, around 500 Jews were killed in [[Marrakech]] and [[Fes, Morocco|Fez]] in [[Morocco]]. In 1869, 18 Jews were killed in [[Tunis]], and an Arab mob looted Jewish homes and stores, and burned synagogues, on [[Djerba|Jerba Island]]. In 1875, 20 Jews were killed by a mob in [[Demnat]], Morocco; elsewhere in Morocco, Jews were attacked and killed in the streets in broad daylight. In 1891, the leading Muslims in [[Jerusalem]] asked the Ottoman authorities in [[Constantinople]] to prohibit the entry of Jews arriving from [[Russia]]. In 1897, synagogues were ransacked and Jews were murdered in [[Tripolitania]].&lt;ref name=Gilbert179/&gt;

[[Benny Morris]] writes that one symbol of Jewish degradation was the phenomenon of stone-throwing at Jews by Muslim children. Morris quotes a 19th century traveler: "I have seen a little fellow of six years old, with a troop of fat toddlers of only three and four, teaching [them] to throw stones at a Jew, and one little urchin would, with the greatest coolness, waddle up to the man and literally spit upon his Jewish [[gaberdine]]. To all this the Jew is obliged to submit; it would be more than his life was worth to offer to strike a Mahommedan."&lt;ref name=Morris10/&gt;

According to [[Mark R. Cohen|Mark Cohen]] in ''The Oxford Handbook of Jewish Studies'', most scholars conclude that Arab antisemitism in the modern world arose in the 19th century, against the backdrop of conflicting Jewish and Arab nationalism, and was imported into the Arab world primarily by nationalistically minded Christian Arabs (and only subsequently was it "Islamized").&lt;ref&gt;[[Mark R. Cohen|Mark Cohen]] (2002), p.208&lt;/ref&gt;

===Twentieth century===

{{See also|Jewish exodus from Arab lands}}
[[File:Death to Juice - illuminea.jpg|thumb|250px|Anti-Jewish demonstrations in New York]]
The massacres of Jews in Muslim countries continued into the 20th century. Martin Gilbert writes that 40 Jews were murdered in [[Taza]], Morocco in 1903. In 1905, old laws were revived in [[Yemen]] forbidding Jews from raising their voices in front of Muslims, building their houses higher than Muslims, or engaging in any traditional Muslim trade or occupation.&lt;ref name=Gilbert179/&gt; The Jewish quarter in Fez was almost destroyed by a Muslim mob in 1912.&lt;ref name=Morris10/&gt; There were [[Nazism|Nazi]]-inspired pogroms in [[Algeria]] in the 1930s, and massive attacks on the Jews in [[Iraq]] and [[Libya]] in the 1940s (see [[Farhud]]). Pro-Nazi Muslims slaughtered dozens of Jews in Baghdad in 1941.&lt;ref name=Morris10/&gt;

George Gruen attributes the increased animosity towards Jews in the [[Arab world]] to several factors, including the breakdown of the [[Ottoman Empire]] and traditional [[Islamic]] society; domination by Western [[colonialism|colonial powers]] under which Jews gained a disproportionately larger role in the commercial, professional, and administrative life of the region; the rise of [[Arab nationalism]], whose proponents sought the wealth and positions of local Jews through government channels; resentment against Jewish [[nationalism]] and the Zionist movement; and the readiness of unpopular [[regime]]s to [[scapegoat]] local Jews for political purposes.&lt;ref name=Gruen&gt;Gruen, George E. [http://www.jcpa.org/jl/jl102.htm "The Other Refugees: Jews of the Arab World"], ''The Jerusalem Letter'', [[Jerusalem Center for Public Affairs]], June 1, 1988.&lt;/ref&gt;

Antagonism and violence increased still further as resentment against [[Zionism|Zionist]] efforts in the [[British Mandate of Palestine]] spread. [[Anti-Zionism|Anti-Zionist]] propaganda in the Middle East frequently adopts the terminology and symbols of the Holocaust to [[Demonization|demonize]] Israel and its leaders. At the same time, Holocaust denial and Holocaust minimization efforts have found increasingly overt acceptance as sanctioned historical discourse in a number of Middle Eastern countries. Arabic- and Turkish-editions of Hitler's ''[[Mein Kampf]]'' and ''[[The Protocols of the Elders of Zion]]'' have found an audience in the region with limited critical response by local intellectuals and media. See [[International Conference to Review the Global Vision of the Holocaust]].

According to [[Robert Satloff]], Muslims and Arabs were involved both as rescuers and as perpetrators of the Holocaust during Italian and German Nazi occupation of Morocco, Tunisia and Libya.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.meforum.org/article/1073 Righteous Muslims. A briefing by Robert Satloff] by Rachel Silverman, ''Jewish Exponent'', December 14, 2006 ([[Middle East Forum]], December 11, 2006)&lt;/ref&gt;

Antisemitism has been reportedly found in Arab and Iranian media and schoolbooks. For example, the Center for Religious Freedom of [[Freedom House]] analyzed a set of Saudi Ministry of Education textbooks in use during the current academic year in Islamic studies courses for elementary and secondary school students. Among the statements and ideas found against non-Wahhabi Muslims and "non-believers" were those that teach Muslims to "hate" Christians, Jews, "polytheists" and other "unbelievers," including non-Wahhabi Muslims, though, incongruously, not to treat them "unjustly"; teach the infamous forgeries ''[[The Protocols of the Elders of Zion]]'', as historical fact and relate modern events to it; teach that "Jews and the Christians are enemies of the [Muslim] believers" and that "the clash" between the two realms is perpetual; instruct that "fighting between Muslims and Jews" will continue until Judgment Day, and that the Muslims are promised victory over the Jews in the end; cite a selective teaching of violence against Jews, while in the same lesson, ignoring the passages of the Qur'an and hadiths that counsel tolerance; include a map of the Middle East that labels Israel within its pre-1967 borders as "Palestine: occupied 1948"; discuss Jews in violent terms, blaming them for virtually all the "subversion" and wars of the modern world.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.freedomhouse.org/template.cfm?page=70&amp;release=379 freedomhouse.org: Press Release]&lt;/ref&gt; A {{PDFlink|[http://www.hudson.org/files/publications/CRF_SaudiReport_2006.pdf 38-page overview]|371&amp;nbsp;KB}} of Saudi Arabia's curriculum has been released to the press by the [[Hudson Institute]].

===Twenty-first century===
[[Image:Tomorrows Pioneers Assoud.JPG|right|250px|thumb|[[Tomorrow's Pioneers]], a children's program on the [[Hamas]] television station, [[Al-Aqsa TV]].]]

''[[New York Times]]'' critic-at-large [[Edward Rothstein]] compares the extent of antisemitic Islamic visions of Jews, "the historical distortions they codify and the readiness with which they are taught to children and are secularized into political action," with the [[Nazi propaganda]] that led to the Holocaust.&lt;ref&gt;''Nazis’ ‘Terrible Weapon,’ Aimed at Minds and Hearts,'' Edward Rothstein, February 23, 2009 [http://www.nytimes.com/2009/02/24/arts/design/24muse.html?ref=design&amp;pagewanted=all]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Brian Stelter]] of ''The Times'' has also noted how media pundits in the West such as [[Glenn Beck]] have been criticised for employing what have been called a "symphony of anti-semitic dog whistles", such as portraying prominent Jews as puppet masters.&lt;ref&gt;''Glenn Beck’s Attacks on George Soros Draw Heat,'' Brian Stelter, November 11, 2010 [http://www.nytimes.com/2010/11/12/us/12beck.html?scp=2&amp;sq=glenn%20beck&amp;st=cse]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Tesco Ireland]], the country's largest supermarket, apologised for allowing the ''[[Protocols of the Elders of Zion]]'' to be sold through its website. Sheikh Dr Shaheed Satardien, head of the Muslim Council of Ireland, said this was effectively "polluting the minds of impressionable young [Islamic] people with hate and anger towards the Jewish community"&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tribune.ie/archive/article/2006/may/21/tesco-apologises-and-withdraws-anti-jewish-literat/ Tesco apologises and withdraws anti-Jewish literature from sale]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Racial antisemitism==
{{Main|Racial antisemitism}}
[[Racial antisemitism]] is the idea that the Jews are a distinct and inferior race compared to their host nations. In the late 19th century and early 20th century, it gained mainstream acceptance as part of the [[eugenics]] movement, which categorized non-"Europeans" as inferior. It more specifically claims that the so-called Nordic Europeans are superior. Racial antisemites saw the Jews as part of a [[Semitic race]] and emphasized their "alien" extra-European origins and culture. They saw Jews as beyond redemption even if they converted to the majority religion. Anthropologists discussed whether the Jews possessed any Arabic-[[Armenoid]], African-[[Nubian]] or Asian-[[Turkic peoples|Turkic]] ancestries. Since [[World War II]] racial antisemitism has rarely appeared outside of [[Neo-Nazi]] and [[white supremacist]] movements.

Racial antisemitism replaced the hatred of Judaism with the hatred of Jews as a group. In the context of the [[Industrial Revolution]], following the [[Jewish Emancipation|emancipation of the Jews]], Jews rapidly urbanized and experienced a period of greater social mobility. With the decreasing role of religion in public life tempering religious antisemitism, a combination of growing [[nationalism]], the rise of [[eugenics]], and resentment at the socio-economic success of the Jews led to the newer, and more virulent, racist antisemitism.

==See also==
{{Colbegin|4}}
*[[1968 Polish political crisis]]
*[[Anti-globalization and antisemitism]]
*[[Anti-Jewish violence in Poland, 1944–1946]]
*[[Anti-Judaism]]
*''[[Anti-Semite and Jew]]''
*[[Anti-Zionism]]
*[[Antisemitic canard]]
*[[Antisemitism around the world]]
*[[Blood libel]]
*[[Criticism of Judaism]]
*[[Dreyfus affair]]
*[[Farhud]]
*[[General Order No. 11 (1862)]]
*[[History of antisemitism]]
*[[Holocaust denial]]
*[[Host desecration]]
*[[Jacob Barnet affair]]
*[[Judeo-Masonic conspiracy theory]]
*[[May Laws]]
*[[Nazi propaganda]]
*[[Persecution of Jews]]
*[[Racial policy of Nazi Germany]]
*[[Secondary antisemitism]]
*[[Semiticization]]
*[[Timeline of antisemitism]]
*[[Unification Church and anti-Semitism]]
*[[Three Whom God Should Not Have Created: Persians, Jews, and Flies]]
{{Colend}}

==Notes==
{{Reflist|2}}

==References==
*[[Yosef Bodansky|Bodansky, Yossef]]. ''Islamic Anti-Semitism as a Political Instrument'', Freeman Center For Strategic Studies, 1999.
*Carr, Steven Alan. ''Hollywood and anti-Semitism: A cultural history up to World War II'', Cambridge University Press 2001.
*Chanes, Jerome A. ''[[Antisemitism: A Reference Handbook]]'', ABC-CLIO, 2004.
*Cohn, Norman. ''Warrant for Genocide'', Eyre &amp; Spottiswoode 1967; Serif, 1996.
*{{Cite book |title=The Anguish of the Jews: Twenty-Three Centuries of Antisemitism |last=Flannery |first=Edward H. |year=2004 |publisher=Paulist Press |isbn=0809143240}}
*[[Avner Falk|Falk, Avner]]. ''Anti-Semitism: The History and Psychoanalysis of Contemporary Hatred''. Wesport, Connecticut, Praeger, 2008. ISBN 978-0-313-35384-0.
*Freudmann, Lillian C. ''Antisemitism in the New Testament'', University Press of America, 1994.
*[[Jane Gerber|Gerber, Jane S.]] (1986). "Anti-Semitism and the Muslim World". In ''History and Hate: The Dimensions of Anti-Semitism'', ed. David Berger. Jewish Publications Society. ISBN 0-8276-0267-7
*[[Raul Hilberg|Hilberg, Raul]]. ''[[The Destruction of the European Jews]]''. Holmes &amp; Meier, 1985. 3 volumes.
*[[Paul Johnson (writer)|Johnson, Paul]]: ''A History of the Jews'' (New York: HarperCollins Publishers, 1987) ISBN 0-06-091533-1
*[[Walter Laqueur|Laqueur, Walter]]. ''The Changing Face of Antisemitism: From Ancient Times To The Present Day''. Oxford University Press. 2006. ISBN 0-19-530429-2
*[[Bernard Lewis|Lewis, Bernard]] (1984). ''The Jews of Islam''. Princeton: Princeton University Press. ISBN 0-691-00807-8
*Lewis, Bernard (1999). ''Semites and Anti-Semites: An Inquiry into Conflict and Prejudice''. W. W. Norton &amp; Co. ISBN 0-393-31839-7
*[[Deborah Lipstadt|Lipstadt, Deborah]]. ''Denying the Holocaust: The Growing Assault on Truth and Memory'', Penguin, 1994.
*McKain, Mark. ''[[Anti-Semitism: At Issue (2005)|Anti-Semitism: At Issue]]'', Greenhaven Press, 2005.
*Michael, Robert and Philip Rosen. [http://www.scarecrowpress.com/ISBN/0810858622 Dictionary of Antisemitism], The Scarecrow Press, Inc., 2007
*Perry, Marvin and Frederick Schweitzer. ''Anti-Semitism: Myth and Hate from Antiquity to the Present.'' Palgrave Macmillan. 2002.
*[[Leon Poliakov|Poliakov, Leon]] (1997). "Anti-Semitism". ''[[Encyclopedia Judaica]]'' (CD-ROM Edition Version 1.0). Ed. [[Cecil Roth]]. Keter Publishing House. ISBN 965-07-0665-8
*Prager, Dennis, Telushkin, Joseph. ''Why the Jews? The Reason for Antisemitism''. Touchstone (reprint), 1985.
*{{Cite book |title=Anti-Judaism in Early Christianity |last=Richardson |first=Peter |year=1986 |publisher=Wilfrid Laurier University Press |isbn=0889201676}}
*Roth, Philip. [[The Plot Against America]], 2004
*Schweitzer, Frederick M. &amp; Perry, Marvin. ''Anti-Semitism: myth and hate from antiquity to the present'', Palgrave Macmillan, 2002, ISBN 0-312-16561-7
*Selzer, Michael (ed). ''"Kike!" : A Documentary History of Anti-Semitism in America'', New York 1972.
*Steinweis, Alan E. ''Studying the Jew: Scholarly Antisemitism in Nazi Germany''. Harvard University Press, 2006. ISBN 0-674-02205-X.
*[[Norman Stillman|Stillman, Norman]] (1979). ''The Jews of Arab Lands: A History and Source Book''. Philadelphia: Jewish Publication Society of America. ISBN 0-8276-0198-0
*Stillman, N.A. (2006). "Yahud". ''[[Encyclopaedia of Islam]]''. Eds.: P.J. Bearman, Th. Bianquis, C.E. Bosworth, E. van Donzel and W.P. Heinrichs. Brill. Brill Online
*[http://www.jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?artid=1603&amp;letter=A&amp;search=anti-semitism Anti-semitism] entry by Gotthard Deutsch in the [[Jewish Encyclopedia]], 1901-1906 ed.

==Further reading==
*[http://www.paulasays.com/articles/on_anti-semitism/2007_a_year_of_anti-semitism.html List of Anti-Semitic Attacks Worldwide in 2007]
*[http://www.paulasays.com/articles/on_anti-semitism/Anti-Semitism1.html List of Anti-Semitic Attacks Worldwide in 2006]
*[http://www.ajc.org/site/c.ijITI2PHKoG/b.2512779/k.66E6/Fighting_AntiSemitism.htm Anti-Semitism Multimedia] AJC Survey of Anti-Semitism, Roots and Responses
*[http://www.adl.org/main_Anti_Semitism_International/Default.htm Global Anti-Semitism] (ADL compilation of modern day anti-semitism happening around the world.)
*[http://www.jewishjournal.com/home/searchview.php?id=17335/ "Experts explore effects of Ahmadinejad anti-Semitism"], ''Jewish Journal of Greater Los Angeles'', March 9, 2007
*[http://www.adl.org/main_Arab_World/default.htm Arab Antisemitism]
*[http://www.aish.com/seminars/whythejews/ Why the Jews? A perspective on causes of anti-Semitism]
*Stav, Arieh (1999). ''Peace: The Arabian Caricature – A Study of Anti-semitic Imagery''. Gefen Publishing House. ISBN 965-229-215-X
*Falk, Avner. (2008). ''Anti-Semitism: The History and Psychoanalysis of Contemporary Hatred''. Wesport, Connecticut, Praeger, ISBN 978-0-313-35384-0
*[http://www.antisemitism.org.il/ Coordination Forum for Countering Antisemitism] (with up to date calendar of anti-semitism today)
*[http://har2.huji.ac.il:83/ALEPH/ENG/SAS/BAS/BAS/START Annotated bibliography of anti-Semitism] hosted by the Hebrew University of Jerusalem's Center for the Study of Antisemitism (SICSA)
*[http://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/antisem.html Anti-Semitism and responses]
*[http://www.tau.ac.il/Anti-Semitism/ The Stephen Roth Institute for the Study of Contemporary anti-Semitism and Racism] hosted by the Tel Aviv University – (includes an annual report)
*[http://www.shma.com/nov02/pierre.htm Jews, the End of the Vertical Alliance, and Contemporary Antisemitism]
*[http://www.freeman.org/m_online/dec04/plaut.php An Israeli point of view on antisemitism, by Steve Plaut]
*[http://www.coe.int/t/E/human_rights/ecri/1-ECRI/2-Country-by-country_approach/ Council of Europe, ECRI Country-by-Country Reports]
*[http://info-poland.buffalo.edu/classroom/J/ State University of New York at Buffalo, The Jedwabne Tragedy]
*[http://www.cyberroad.com/poland/jews_today.html Jews in Poland today]
*[http://www.adl.org/main_Anti_Semitism_International/Default.htm Anti-Defamation League's report on International Anti-Semitism]
*[http://memri.org/ The Middle East Media Research Institute] – documents antisemitism in Middle-Eastern media.
*[http://www.zionism-israel.com/his/judeophobia.htm Judeophobia: A short course on the history of anti-Semitism] at [http://www.zionism-israel.com] Zionism and Israel Information Center.
*[http://www.pinteleyid.com If Not Together, How?]: Research by April Rosenblum to develop a working definition of antisemitism, and related teaching tools about antisemitism, for activists.
*[http://www.vintagepostcards.com/mm5/merchant.mvc?Screen=CTGY&amp;Category_Code=ethnjua Vintage Postcards with an Anti-Jewish theme]
*[http://www.haaretz.com/hasen/spages/818365.html What makes an anti-Semite?] Dina Porat, ''Haaretz'', January 27, 2007
*[http://www.theaugeanstables.com/essays-on-judeophobia/anti-semitism-post-modern/ "Post Modern"]
*[http://www.theaugeanstables.com/2006/04/02/post-modern-anti-semitism-part-i/ Post-Modern Anti-Semitism: Part I]
*[http://www.theaugeanstables.com/reflections-from-second-draft/judeophobia-anti-judaism-anti-semitism-anti-zionism/ Judeophobia: Anti-Judaism, Anti-Semitism, Anti-Zionism]
*[http://www.azure.org.il/article.php?id=18&amp;page=all An Attempt to Identify the Root Cause of Antisemitism] by [[A.B. Yehoshua]], [http://www.azure.org.il Azure], Spring 2008.

==External links==
{{Sisterlinks}}
*The Journal for the Study of Antisemitism [http://jsantisemitism.org/]
*Why the Jews? Real Causes or mere excuses? [http://www.aish.com/seminars/whythejews/]
* [http://www1.yadvashem.org/yv/en/holocaust/about/01/antisemitism.asp?WT.mc_id=wiki Antisemitism] - About the Holocaust - Yad Vashem
*United States Holocaust Memorial Museum – [http://www.ushmm.org/museum/exhibit/focus/antisemitism/ Special Focus: Antisemitism]; and Encyclopedia [http://www.ushmm.org/wlc/article.php?lang=en&amp;ModuleId=10007170 1], [http://www.ushmm.org/wlc/article.php?lang=en&amp;ModuleId=10007167 2], [http://www.ushmm.org/wlc/article.php?lang=en&amp;ModuleId=10007171 3], [http://www.ushmm.org/wlc/article.php?lang=en&amp;ModuleId=10007173 4], [http://www.ushmm.org/wlc/article.php?lang=en&amp;ModuleId=10007166 5], [http://www.ushmm.org/wlc/article.php?lang=en&amp;ModuleId=10005175 6]
*[http://www.ushmm.org/museum/exhibit/focus/antisemitism/voices/ ''Voices on Antisemitism Podcast Series''] from the US Holocaust Memorial Museum
*[http://www.jewishaffairs.org Antisemitism and anti-Israelism]
*[http://www.antisemitism.org.il/eng/search/?country=63&amp;id_category=&amp;region= Antisemitism measuring]
*[http://www.simpletoremember.com/vitals/HistoryJewishPersecution.htm 2,000 Year Timeline of Jewish Persecution]
*[http://www.donmilligan.net What is Left Anti-Semitism?]
*[http://www.bl.uk/learning/histcitizen/voices/holocaust.html Voices of the Holocaust] – a learning resource from the British Library
*[http://www.zionism-israel.com/his/judeophobia.htm A course on Judeophobia]
*[http://www.tau.ac.il/Anti-Semitism/asw2005/serbia.htm Tel Aviv University on antisemitism]
*[http://www.thepcaa.org 2006 UK Parliamentary Inquiry into antisemitism]
*[http://omedia.org/Show_Article.asp?DynamicContentID=1853&amp;MenuID=719&amp;ThreadID=1014008 The New Anti-Judaism – according to Professor Irwin Cotler], Dr. Rivka Shafek Lissak
*[http://www.analitik.org.ua/author/46076f2011c07/ Antisemitism in modern Ukraine]
*[http://www.yale.edu/yiisa/ Yale Initiative for the Interdisciplinary Study of Antisemitism]
*[http://iibsa.org/cms/index.php?id=83&amp;L=1 International Institute for Education and Research on Antisemitism (Berlin/London)]
*[http://www.humanrightsfirst.org/discrimination/issues/antisemitism.asp Human Rights First Antisemitism Program]
*[http://www.h-net.org/~antis/ H-Antisemitism, H-Net Humanities &amp; Social Sciences OnLine]

{{Template group
|list =
{{Antisemitism topics|state=collapsed}}
{{Racism topics|state=collapsed}}
{{Jews and Judaism}}
{{Discrimination}}
}}

[[Category:Antisemitism| ]]
[[Category:Religious persecution]]
[[Category:Jewish political status]]
[[Category:Political terms]]
[[Category:Pejorative terms for people|Antisemite]]

&lt;!--Interwikis--&gt;
[[als:Antisemitismus]]
[[ar:معاداة السامية]]
[[az:Antisemitizm]]
[[bn:ইহুদি-বিদ্বেষ]]
[[bs:Antisemitizam]]
[[br:Enepyuzevegezh]]
[[bg:Антисемитизъм]]
[[ca:Antisemitisme]]
[[ceb:Antisemitismo]]
[[cs:Antisemitismus]]
[[cy:Gwrth-Semitiaeth]]
[[da:Antisemitisme]]
[[de:Judenfeindlichkeit]]
[[et:Antisemitism]]
[[el:Αντισημιτισμός]]
[[es:Antisemitismo]]
[[eo:Kontraŭjudismo]]
[[eu:Antisemitismo]]
[[fa:یهودستیزی]]
[[fr:Antisémitisme]]
[[gl:Antisemitismo]]
[[ko:반유대주의]]
[[hi:यहूदी विरोधवाद]]
[[hr:Antisemitizam]]
[[id:Antisemitisme]]
[[it:Antisemitismo]]
[[he:אנטישמיות]]
[[ka:ანტისემიტიზმი]]
[[la:Antisemitismus]]
[[lv:Antisemītisms]]
[[lb:Antisemitismus]]
[[lt:Antisemitizmas]]
[[hu:Antiszemitizmus]]
[[mk:Антисемитизам]]
[[arz:معاداة الساميه]]
[[ms:Antisemitisme]]
[[nl:Antisemitisme]]
[[ja:反ユダヤ主義]]
[[no:Antisemittisme]]
[[nn:Antisemittisme]]
[[pl:Antysemityzm]]
[[pt:Antissemitismo]]
[[ro:Antisemitism]]
[[ru:Антисемитизм]]
[[sq:Antisemitizmi]]
[[scn:Antisimitismu]]
[[simple:Antisemitism]]
[[sk:Antisemitizmus]]
[[sl:Antisemitizem]]
[[sr:Антисемитизам]]
[[fi:Antisemitismi]]
[[sv:Antisemitism]]
[[tl:Antisemitismo]]
[[th:ลัทธิความเป็นอคติต่อชาวเซมิติค]]
[[tr:Antisemitizm]]
[[uk:Антисемітизм]]
[[ur:ضد سامیت]]
[[vi:Chủ nghĩa bài Do Thái]]
[[yi:אנטיסעמיטיזם]]
[[zh:反犹太主义]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>