<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20031108125325|1706297" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1078" pageid="1078" ns="0" title="Antisemitism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2003-11-10T15:14:19Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[de:Antisemitismus]]  [[fr:Anti-sémitisme]] [[nl:Antisemitisme]] [[sv:Antisemitism]] 

''The neutrality of this article is [[Wikipedia:NPOV dispute|disputed]].

------

'''Anti-Semitism''' is either of the following: (1) hostility to Jews as a group which results from no legitimate cause or greatly exceeds any reasonable, ethical response to genuine provocation; or (2) a pejorative perception of Jewish physical or moral traits which is either utterly groundless or a result of irrational generalization and exaggeration"''

== Etymology and usage ==

[[Wilhelm Marr]] is credited with [[word coinage|coining]] the [[German language|German]] word ''Antisemitismus'' in [[1873]], at a time when [[racial science]] was fashionable in [[Germany]] but [[religion|religious]] hatred wasn't. So far as can be ascertained, the word was first printed in [[1880]]. In that year Marr published "Zwanglose Antisemitische Hefte," and [[Wilhelm Scherer]] used the term "Antisemiten" in the "Neue Freie Presse" of January. The related word ''[[semitism]]'' was coined around [[1885]].

&lt;!--- before editing this section, in particular before adding any text regards "anti-Semitism = hatred of semites", please read [[talk:Anti-Semitism/etymology]]. Thanks. ---&gt;

== [[Roots of anti-Semitism]] ==

There have been a number of motivating factors that spurred anti-Semitism, including social, economic, national, political, racial, and religious factors and any number of combinations of the above. In the twentieth century, the most visible forms of anti-Semitism were:
*[[Racism|Racist]] anti-Semitism. Some people perceive Jews as people of a racially distinct origin from other peoples, and claim that discrimination on the basis of such distinctness is valid.
* [[Religious]] anti-Semitism. Like other religions, [[Judaism]] has faced discrimination and violence from people of competing faiths and in countries that practice [[state atheism]].

[[Dennis Prager]] believes that the root cause of anti-Semitism is that Jews are socially and culturally different from the societies that they live in; in most eras Jews have not let themselves become [[Assimilation|assimilated]] into the majority culture.  This led to belief that the Jews believed themselves superior to others, resulting in hatred towards Jews.  Such phenomenon existed in ancient Egypt, ancient Persia, and in the ancient Roman Empire. While other conquered peoples assimilated and joined the religion of the majority, Jews did not. 

In consequence of their alien status, Jews were often excluded socially and politically from the societies in which they lived, or alternately, were forced to enter professions that were considered socially inferior (tax- and rent-collectors, money-lenders, etc.) Over time, these professions engendered animosity among the people who came into contact with Jews--peasants, who were forced to pay their taxes to Jews could personify Jews as the people taking their earnings, while remaining loyal to the lords on whose behalf the Jews worked.

== Early forms of anti-Semitism ==

Disdain of Jews can be traced back to the Graeco-Roman period and the rise of Hellenistic culture. Most Jews rejected efforts to assimilate them into the dominant Greek (and later Roman) culture, and their religious practices, which conflicted with established norms, were perceived as being backward and primitive. [[Gaius Cornelius Tacitus]], for example, writes disparagingly of many real and imagined practices of the Jews, while there are numerous accounts of [[circumcision]] being described as barbarous. 

Furthermore, throughout the [[Diaspora]], Jews tended to live in separate communities, in which they could practice their religion. This led to charges of elitism, as appear in the writings of [[Cicero]]. As an ethnic minority, Jews were also dependent on the goodwill of the ruling imperial power, though this was considered irksome to the indigenous population, which regarded any vestiges of autonomy among the local Jewish communities as reminders of their subject status to a foreign empire. Nevertheless, this did not always mean that opposition to Jewish involvement in local affairs was anti-Semitic. In 411 A.D. an Egyptian mob destroyed the Jewish temple at Elephantine in [[Egypt]], but many historians argue that this was provoked by anti-[[Persia]]n sentiment, rather than by anti-Semitism per se--the Jews, who were protected by the imperial power, were perceived as being its representatives. 

The enormous and influential Jewish community in the ancient Egyptian port city of [[Alexandria, Egypt|Alexandria]] saw manifestations of an unusual brand of anti-Semitism in which the local pagan populace rejected the biblical narrative of the [[Exodus]] as being anti-Egyptian. In response, a number of works were produced to provide an "Egyptian version" of what "really happened": the Jews were a group of sickly lepers that was expelled from Egypt. This was also used to account for Jewish practices--they were so sickly that they could not even wander in the desert for more than six days at a time, requiring a seventh day to rest, hence the origin of the Sabbath. It was these charges that led to [[Philo]]'s apologetic account of Judaism and Jewish history, which was so influential in the development of early church doctrine. 

Judaic traditions extend at least a thousand years [[BCE]] (before the common era), and are the historical predecessor for the religions of [[Christianity]] and [[Islam]], both of whom hold some Judaic traditions and texts as sacred, though differ in aspects that are central to each distinct branch of religion. 

Hence Judaism, Christianity, and Islam, each took different course in terms of beliefs, as well as traditional customs; each creating a separate and distinct culture, from the parent Judaism. Those who held to traditional Judaic belief were considered "deniers" of the newer beliefs and traditions, in much the same way that every religion considers people of other religions to be denying the truth.


While many more subtle manifestations of Church anti-Semitism can be traced to anti-Jewish sentiment in Egypt, these more blatant early accusations of anti-Egyptian sentiment and the rejection of the Exodus mythology were not coopted by the Church since they countered Christian doctrine.

== Medieval anti-Semitism, blood libels, the Black Death, and the Crusades ==

From the medieval era to the [[1900s]] there were Christians who believed that some (or all) Jews possessed magical powers; depending on the culture, people believed that the Jews gained these magical powers from making a deal with the [[devil]].

This was also often accompanied by beliefs that Jewish religious practice entailed devil worship, or "Satanic" actions, such as drinking the blood of Christian children in mockery of the Christian [[Eucharist]]; this idea is known as the [[blood libel]], the history of which is described in more detail in its own entry. Jews were also falsely accused of torturing consecrated host wafers in a re-enactment of the [[Crucifixion]]; this accusation was known as [[host desecration]].

[[Passion play]]s, dramatic stagings representing the trial and death of [[Jesus]], have been used in some Christian communities to arouse hatred of local Jews; the plays usually depict the entire Jewish people as condemning Jesus to [[crucifixion]] and being collectively guilty of deicide, murdering God.

== The Expulsion from England, France, Spain, Germany, and Spain ==
(''to be written'')

== The Chmielnicki Massacres == 

See [[Bohdan Chmielnicki]]

== Anti-Semitism and the Church (incl. Martin Luther, Ghettoes, etc.) ==
''Main article: [[Christianity and anti-Semitism]]''

Theological anti-Semitism has been particularly prevalent in [[Christianity]].  Until [[1965]], for instance, the [[Catholic Church]] preached that "the wicked Jews", as a people, were responsible for the death of [[Jesus Christ]]. This doctrine was repudiated as part of [[Vatican II]]. A small number of Protestant sects still teach it.  A number of Christian preachers, particularly in the Middle Ages and [[Renaissance]], additionally taught that religious Jews ''choose to follow a faith that they actually know is false'' out of a desire to offend God.  Christian theological anti-Semitism was created by the [[New Testament]]'s replacement theology, or [[supersessionism]], which taught that with the coming of Jesus a new covenant has rendered obsolete and has superseded the religion of [[Judaism]].

== The Enlightenment and the rise of racial anti-Semitism ==

Racial anti-Semitism, the most modern form of anti-Semitism, is a type of [[racism]] mixed with [[religious persecution]].  Racial anti-Semites believe erroneously that the Jewish people are a distinct race. They also believe that Jews are inherently inferior to people of other races.

Modern European anti-Semitism has its origin in the [[ethnology|ethnological]] theory that the Jewish people are a sub-group of Semitic peoples; Semitic people were thought by many Europeans to be entirely different from the [[Aryan]], or Indo-European, populations, and that they can never be amalgamated with them.  In this view, Jews are not opposed on account of their [[religion]], but on account of their supposed [[racial characteristics]]. As such are mentioned: greed, a special aptitude for money-making, aversion to hard work, clannishness and obtrusiveness, lack of social tact, and especially of [[patriotism]].

== The Pale of Settlement, pogroms, and the Protocols of the Elders of Zion ==

One of the most damaging anti-Semitic tractates published is the infamous Russian literary hoax,  [[The Protocols of the Elders of Zion]].

See [[Pale of Settlement]], [[Pogrom]]

== Dreyfus and the New Anti-Semitism ==

See [[Alfred Dreyfus]], [[Dreyfus affair]]

== The Holocaust ==

[[Holocaust]], [[Warsaw Ghetto]], 
An Anti-semite that oppose the holocaust [[Protest of Zofia Kossak-Szczucka]] etc...

== Anti-Semitism and anti-Zionism ==
''Main article: [[anti-Zionism#Anti-Zionism_and_anti-Semitism|Anti-Zionism and anti-Semitism]]''

== Modern anti-Semitism in America and Western Europe ==

* In the years leading up to America's entry into World War II, Father [[Charles Coughlin]], an anti-Semitic radio preacher, as well as many other prominent public figures, condemned "the Jews" because they were leading America into war. While most Jews in America supported the interventionist camp, not all did.
* Jews were condemned by populist politicians for their left-wing politics at the turn of the century. Many Jews were left-wing, but not most.
* Jews are condemned for their supposed "high level of participation" in the [[slave trade]].

== Anti-Semitism in the Communist Bloc ==
''Main article: [[History of the Jews in the Soviet Union]]''

== Anti-Semitism and Islam ==
''Main article: [[Islam and anti-Semitism]]''

[[Islam]] in and of itself is not Anti-Semitic, although the [[Qur'an]] criticizes both modern Jewish law for allegedly being corrupted, and a segment of the Jewish people for allegedly not adhering to what was revealed to [[Moses]]. [[Islam]] is similar and compatible with [[Judaism]], as both see themselves as descendants of [[Abraham]] and followers of the same [[prophet|prophets]]. Islamic scholars are quick to point out that [[Islam]] encourages toleration and respect for Jewish people, as they are considered "[[People of the Book]]", meaning they share common scriptures and prophets. Many people have produced [[hadith]] concerning Muhammad that showed how he did business with the Jewish tribes of his city and how he ordered Muslims to share food with Jewish neighbors.

Historically there has not been as much anti-Semitism from Muslim lands as from Christian lands, up until the Twentieth century. While many Jewish people were persecuted in Europe, they enjoyed relative political and religious freedom in Islamic societies. Moorish Spain was controlled by Muslims for approximately 700 years, and during that time, Jewish citizens had rights nearly equal to that of American citizens today. Jewish historians refer to that time period as "The Golden Age of Judaism."

Jewish people also gained prominence in the courts of Baghdad, Cairo, and Istanbul, performing the duties of palace physicians, finance officers, and even government ministers known as "viziers.' As a minority, Jewish people were exempt from Islamic law ([[Sharia]]), and the governments allowed them a degree of self-rule by appointing Jewish leaders to implement Jewish law for their communities. Important [[synagogue]]s dot the major cities of the Middle east, and relations between Muslims and Jewish people have been relatively calm for over a thousand years.

Anti-Semitism in the Muslim world rose greatly in the twentieth century. This can be traced to various sources; some of it can be traced to long-held prejudices and historical misunderstandings. The main reason for the rise of anti-Semitism in the past century may be due to the poor state of relations between [[Israel]], a Jewish-majority state, and the isolation from the neighboring Arab countries. Criticism of Israeli policy has led to distrust of Jewish people and anti-Semitism on the popular level.

== Anti-Semitism in the Arab World ==
''Main article: [[Arabs and anti-Semitism]]''

== Holocaust revisionism ==

[[Holocaust revisionism|Holocaust revisionists]] often claim that "the Jews" or a "Zionist conspiracy" is responsible for the exaggeration or wholesale fabrication of the events of the [[Holocaust]]. Critics of such revisionism point to an overwhelming amount of historical evidence that supports the mainstream historical view of the Holocaust. It should be noted that most academics also agree that there is no reliable evidence for any such conspiracy.

== Contemporary manifestations of anti-Semitism ==

In recent years some Jewish groups have noticed what they are describing as "the new anti-Semitism". The large increase in anti-Semitism over the last twenty years is taking on new forms that had not previously existed. Concern exists over anti-Semitism and anti-Zionism in the anti-Globalization movement, among many in the political left-wing, and among those who consider themselves anti-colonialist.

== Organizations dedicated to combatting anti-Semitism ==
[[Anti-Defamation League]]

== References ==

* ''The Holocaust Industry: Reflections on the Exploitation of Jewish Suffering'', Norman G. Finkelstein. Verso Books, 2001.
* ''Jewish History, Jewish Religion: The Weight of Three Thousand Years'', Israel Shahak. Pluto Press, 1994.
* ''The World Must Know: The History of the Holocaust As Told in the United States Holocaust Memorial Museum'', Michael Berenbaum. Little Brown &amp; Co, 1993.
* ''The War Against the Jews: 1933-1945'' Lucy S. Davidowicz. Bantam Doubleday Dell Pub, 1991. 
* ''Antisemitism in America'', Leonard Dinnerstein, Oxford Univ. Press, 1995.
* ''Antisemitism in the New Testament'', Lillian C. Freudmann, University Press of America, 1994.
* ''Jewish Self-Hatred: Anti-Semitism and the Hidden Language of the Jews'', Sander L. Gilman, Johns Hopkins University Press, 1990, ISBN 0801840635 
* ''The Destruction of the European Jews'' Raul Hilberg. Holmes &amp; Meier, 1985. 3 volumes
* ''Denying the Holocaust: The Growing Assault on Truth and Memory'' Deborah Lipstadt, 1994, Penguin. 
* ''Why the Jews? The Reasons for Antisemitism'' [[Dennis Prager]] and Joseph Telushkin, Simon &amp; Schuster, 1983
* ''Antisemitism: The Longest Hatred'', Robert S. Wistrich. Pantheon Books, 1992.

== External links ==

* [http://www.counterpunch.org/hamod07122003.html Semitic is a Language Group, Not a Race or Ethnic Group]
* [http://www.adl.org/adl.asp The Anti-Defamation League]
* [http://www.us-israel.org/jsource/anti-semitism/Christian.html Christian-Jewish relations]
* [http://www.tau.ac.il/Anti-Semitism/ The Stephen Roth Institute for the Study of Contemporary anti-Semitism and Racism] (includes an annual report)
* http://www.yahoodi.com/peace/selfhatred.html 
* [http://www.geocities.com/Athens/Cyprus/8815/ Response to anti-Semites' posting of Talmud "Quotes"]
* [http://www.tau.ac.il/Anti-Semitism/institute.html The Institute for the Study of Contemporary Anti-Semitism and Racism, Tel Aviv University]
* [[meta:Solution of the Israeli-Palestinian conflict]]
* [http://www.freeman.org/m_online/jan98/pipes.htm The New Anti-Semitism. Article by Daniel Pipes]
* [http://www.ajc.org/InTheMedia/Publications.asp?did=618 The New Anti-Semitism in Western Europe: American Jewish COngress]
* [http://www.adl.org/presrele/Islme_62/4040_62.asp The New Anti-Semitism in Europe and The Middle East: Anti-Defamation League]
* [http://christianactionforisrael.org/antiholo/new_anti2.html The New Anti-Semitism: Christian Action for Israel]
* [http://www.aish.com/jewishissues/middleeast/Anti-Globalization_The_New_Anti-Semitism.asp Anti-Globalization and the New Anti-Semitism: JewishWorld online magazine.]
* [http://www.commentarymagazine.com/sharansky.html On Hating the Jews by Natan Sharansky]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>