<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20101105144904|394993200" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="354224" pageid="354224" ns="0" title="Discrimination based on skin tone"><revisions><rev timestamp="2010-11-07T17:21:12Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Citations missing|date=November 2007}}
{{Globalize/USA|date=September 2010}}
{{Discrimination sidebar}}
'''Colourism''' is [[discrimination]] in which human beings are accorded differing social treatment based on skin colour. The preference often gets translated into economic status because of opportunities for work.  Colourism can be found across the world.  The term is generally used for the phenomenon of people discriminating within their own ethnic groups.

The term colourism refers to when lighter skin tones are preferred and darker skin is considered less desirable or darker skin tones are preferred and lighter skin is considered less desirable.  In the United States, the phenomenon also occurs in other populations, such as among [[Chicano]]s and other [[Latino]]s, [[India]]n immigrants and Caucasian Americans. While colourism still exists in the U.S.,{{Citation needed|date=May 2010}} it has diminished since the Civil Rights Movement.

The name '''pigmentocracy''' is given to a group-based [[social hierarchy]] based largely on colourism. Also labeled as colorism, which is more discussed than others, is the phenomenon of lighter-skinned people discriminating against darker tones within the same ethnic group.

Many historically favored and continue to favour lighter skin in women. In his foreword to [[Peter Frost (anthropologist)|Peter Frost]]'s 2005 ''Fair Women, Dark Men'', [[University of Washington]] sociologist Pierre L. van den Berghe writes:
"Although virtually all cultures express a marked preference for fair female skin, even those with little or no exposure to European imperialism, and even those whose members are heavily pigmented, many are indifferent to male pigmentation or even prefer men to be darker."&lt;ref&gt;see Steve Sailer, [http://vdare.com/sailer/050612_blondes.htm Blondes Have Deeper Roots] (2005)&lt;/ref&gt; A consequence of this is that, since higher-ranking men get to marry the more attractive women, the  upper classes of a society generally tend to develop a lighter complexion than the lower classes by [[sexual selection]] (see also [[Fisherian runaway]]).&lt;ref name="Frost"&gt;[[Peter Frost (anthropologist)|Peter Frost]] "Fair Women, Dark Men: The Forgotten Roots of Color Prejudice," (2005).&lt;/ref&gt;

==African-Americans in the United States==
{{Weasel|date=May 2010}}
[[File:WEB Du Bois 1946.jpg|thumb|right|Du Bois in 1946, photo by [[Carl Van Vechten]]]]
Colourism in the United States is a practice that began in times of slavery due to white slaveowners' assertion that any person black (African) or associated with blackness was inferior or lowly.  Common practices of the time were to allow the slaves with the lighter complexion (more commonly the offspring of the slave masters and their slaves) to engage in less strenuous usually domesticated duties, while the darker, more African looking slaves participated in hard labor, which was more than likely outdoors.&lt;ref name="Hill, Mark E 2002"&gt;Hill, Mark E. "Skin Color and the Perception of Attractiveness Among African Americans: Does Gender Make a Difference?" Social Psychology Quarterly 65.1 (2002): 77-91.&lt;/ref&gt; Scientific studies conclude natural human skin color diversity is highest in black/sub-saharan African  populations therefore many blacks/sub-saharan Africans or people of sub saharan African descent are naturally light skinned.&lt;ref&gt;Human skin color diversity is highest in sub-Saharan African or Black African populations {{harv|Relethford|2000}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

The "brown paper bag test" was a ritual once practiced by certain [[African-American]] and [[Creole peoples|Creole]] [[fraternities and sororities]] who discriminated against people who were "too dark." That is, these groups would not let anyone into the sorority or fraternity whose skin tone was darker than a paper lunch bag, in order to maintain a perception of standards.  [[Spike Lee]]'s film ''[[School Daze]]'' satirized this practice at historically black colleges and universities.

Along with the "Paper Bag Test," guidelines for acceptance among the lighter ranks included the "comb test", which tested the coarseness of one's hair, and the "flashlight test," which tested a person's profile, to make sure their features measured up, or were close enough to those of the Caucasian race.&lt;ref&gt;Kerr, Audrey E. "The Paper Bag Principle: Of the Myth and the Motion of Colorism." Journal of American Folklore 118.469 (205): 271-289.&lt;/ref&gt;

Colourism is prevalent in the [[application for employment|job application]] process as well; research shows that a light skinned African American male with a [[bachelors degree]] and mediocre experience is more likely to be hired for a typical job than a dark skinned man with a [[Masters in Business Administration]] and past experience in the field.&lt;ref&gt;Banerji, Shilpa. "Study: Darker-skinned Black Job Applicants Face More Obstacles." Diverse: Issues in Higher Education 23.16 (2006): 20.&lt;/ref&gt;

While stated less explicitly, colourism has been portrayed in episodes of the NBC drama ''[[Homicide: Life on the Street]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|url=http://www.encyclopedia.com/doc/1G1-115399891.html |title=Homicide: Life on the Street: progress in portrayals of African American men |last=Mascaro |first=Thomas A. |date=2004-03-22 |journal=Journal of Popular Film and Television | issn = 0195-6051 |id={{OCLC|4652347}} |accessdate=2007-09-23 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Lighter-skinned [[African American]] superior officers Deputy Commissioner of Operations [[James C. Harris]] and Colonel [[George Barnfather]] appear to discriminate against main character Baltimore Police Lieutenant [[Al Giardello]], a darker-skinned [[African American]]. Additionally, [[African American]] women have discriminated against Giardello on the grounds that his appearance is "too black".&lt;ref&gt;http://novemberrain.free.fr/GlossaireHLOTS.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

Along with the above example, a major issue in American society has been the fact the majority of media outlets (television, movies, advertising, etc.) choose to portray lighter skin people, because on average, that is the national preference. The (light to dark) hierarchy within the African American race is one that has existed since the time of slavery, but its problems and consequences are still very evident.  Darker skinned blacks are more likely to have negative relationships with the police, less likely to have higher education or income levels, and less likely to hold public office.  Darker skinned people are also considered less intelligent, less desirable (in women mostly), and are overall seen as a lesser people.  Studies have shown that when measuring education and family income, there is a positive sloping curve as the skin of families gets lighter. This does not prove that darker skinned people are discriminated against, but it provides insight as to why these statistics are recurring.  Lighter skinned people tend to have higher social standing, more positive networks, and more opportunities to succeed than those of a darker persuasion. Scientists believe this advantage is due to not only to ancestors benefits, but also skin color, which coincides with the belief of colorism affecting peoples lives from past to present.  In criminal sentencing, medium to dark-skinned African Americans are likely to receive sentences 2.6 longer than those of whites or light-skinned African Americans, and when a white victim is involved, those with more "black" features are likely to receive a much more severe punishment, reinforcing the idea that those of lighter complexion are of more "value."&lt;ref name="Hochschild, Jennifer L 2007"&gt;Hochschild, Jennifer L. "The Skin Color Paradox and the American Racial Order." Social Forces 86.2 (2007): 643-670.&lt;/ref&gt;

Colourism also adversely affects the relationships between African American men and women. Darker skinned African Americans are less likely to get married, and those that do are more likely to marry persons at a lower level of socioeconomic status than themselves, perpetuating the challenges that darker skinned blacks face.&lt;ref name="Hochschild, Jennifer L 2007"/&gt; Also, as education levels rise, the preferences in attraction also change,{{Citation needed|date=May 2010}} with most college{{Clarify|date=May 2010}} students believing that their lighter skinned racial counterparts are more attractive than darker skinned people. The preferences of children and adolescents were not that different, meaning education level is important.{{Citation needed|date=May 2010}}  This problem seems to be more evident when discussing the lives of African American women, seeing as they have more to overcome with the more pronounced differences in the body type, facial features, and hair.  The constant exposure to persons with White/European traits in American media, such as advertising, movies, television, or even children's dolls, provides an explanation as to why this comparison to Caucasian-like traits is perpetuated.  Those of lighter complexion are also known{{Citation needed|date=May 2010}} to have higher education and socioeconomic status, meaning their social skills are more "refined,"{{Citation needed|date=May 2010}} which can be seen{{Citation needed|date=May 2010}} as more attractive to other educated{{Clarify|date=May 2010}} people.  The idea that darker African American women do not stand up to their lighter counterparts may cause them to lose self confidence or esteem, which could in turn decrease their self worth, making them less likely to want to overcome the boundaries before them. Since the majority of a man's self worth is not related to their level of physical attractiveness,{{Citation needed|date=May 2010}} men are not as adversely affected as women.{{Citation needed|date=May 2010}}  The theory of the "sacred white womanhood"{{Clarify|date=May 2010}} also affects perceptions of attractiveness in that women whose complexion is closer to the "fair" skinned white female are considered{{Who|date=May 2010}} more desirable and at times{{Clarify|date=May 2010}} more attractive.{{Citation needed|date=May 2010}} This goes against the typical historical view of dark skinned women, which was that they were expected to be comparable to men in their ability to work, constantly looked at as dirty or as property, and in a sense eliminated their femininity.{{Citation needed|date=May 2010}} The backlash from these altering views is that African American women are forced{{Clarify|date=May 2010}} to imitate the actions and lifestyles of white women, by doing such things as bleaching their skin or straightening their hair, in order to gain affection of their male complements.

In the United States, light skin is seen as more attractive than tanned skin. Studies have shown that light skin is preferred in all cultures and races. [[Skin whitening]] products sales grew from $40 to $43 billion in 2008.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://news.medill.northwestern.edu/chicago/news.aspx?id=161243|title=Bleaching Creams: Fade to Beautiful?|publisher=Northwestern University|date=03-10-2010|accessdate=09-08-2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the [[African American]] community, light skin is considered more attractive than dark skin. During [[slavery]], light skin African Americans were perceived as intelligent, cooperative, and beautiful.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://northbysouth.kenyon.edu/2000/Beauty/goodlooks.htm|title=What Are "Good Looks"?|publisher=Kenyon College|accessdate=09-08-2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; They were more likely to work as house slaves. Light skin Blacks were also given preferential treatment by plantation owners and their henchmen. For example, they had a chance to get an education.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.sptimes.com/2003/08/31/Columns/The_paper_bag_test.shtml|title=The Paper Bag Test|publisher=St. Petersburg Times|date=08-31-2003|accessdate=09-08-2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Dark African Americans worked in the fields and did not get an education.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.npr.org/blogs/newsandviews/2007/10/for_lightskinned_only.html|title=For Light-Skinned Only?|date=08-16-2007|accessdate=09-08-2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Skin Colour Paradox===
The Skin Colour Paradox is an idea that deals with the issue of "being black," meaning how African Americans identify themselves, as well as others with the same experiences or lifestyles. A major issue in this paradox deals with the inconsistencies between a persons socio-economical and cultural preferences and their political preferences. Going along with the colourism issue, the paradox exists due to the fact that lighter skinned and darker skinned African Americans seem to have different experiences (socioeconomically and culturally), yet in the past, and theoretically in the future, will continue to have political preferences that benefit the African American race as a whole. Political scientists would suggest that skin color is a characteristic perhaps as equally important as religion, income, and education, which explains why the paradox is so surprising, but studies show that skin color (or shade) has no real implications on actual political preferences. Another issue with the paradox is the issue of Affirmative Action. Studies show that most African Americans that benefit Affirmative Action come from families that are better educated and more well off, and historically this means that the lighter-skinned portion of the black race is receiving the majority of the aid, making it appear as if the race as a whole is being benefited.&lt;ref name="Hochschild, Jennifer L 2007"/&gt;

===Americo Liberians===
In Liberia, descendants of African-American settlers (renamed [[Americo-Liberians]]) in part defined social class and standing by raising people with lighter skin above those with dark skin. The first Americo-Liberian presidents such as [[Joseph Jenkins Roberts]], [[James Spriggs-Payne]], and [[Alfred Francis Russell]] had considerable proportions of European ancestry.  Most may have been only one-quarter or one-eighth African American. Other aspects of their rising to power, however, likely related to their chances for having obtained education and work that provided good livings.

[[Edward Roye]] was the first representative of dark-skinned African-American settlers in [[Liberia]]. The light-skinned party was the [[Republican Party (Liberia)]] and the dark-skinned party was the [[True Whig Party]].

In addition to rivalries among descendants of African Americans, the Americans held themselves above the native Africans in Liberia. Thus, descendants of Americans held and kept power out of proportion to their representation in the population of the entire country, so there was a larger issue than color at work.

===The "Blue Vein Society"===
{{Unreferenced section|date=December 2007}}
Following the Emancipation, [[mulatto]] societies such as "The Blue Vein Society" came into prominence. Its members were often well-connected free-born or freed individuals of mixed African, [[Europe]]an, and occasionally of [[Native Americans in the United States|Native American]] blood. To be eligible for membership, one's skin color had to be pale enough that the "blue veins" on the underside of the arm were visible. Such restrictive organizations allowed its members and their offspring to meet, co-mingle and marry, thereby preserving what small privilege the mulatto elite had enjoyed before all slaves were set free. Uneducated, or economically disadvantaged mixed-race individuals, even those whose skin color was technically light enough to qualify them for admission, were rarely welcomed, demonstrating that there were more than color issues under consideration.

The original "Blue Veins" were said to have been organized in New England. Their primary objective was to establish and maintain "correct" social standards among people who had achieved some social, educational and economic standing.{{Citation needed|date=August 2008}}

==In Latin America==
[[Brazil]] has the largest population of African descendants (living outside of Africa) in the world.  This large number was a result of the African Slave trade. In [[Brazil]], skin color plays a large role in differences among the races.  [[Social status]]. Individuals with lighter skin and who are racially mixed generally have higher rates of [[social mobility]].&lt;ref name="Hernandez1"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Hernandez |first=Tanya K.|year=2006 |title=Bringing Clarity to Race Relations in Brazil
|journal=Diverse: Issues in Higher Education |volume=23|issue=18 |pages=85}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There are a disproportionate number of white elites{{Clarify|date=May 2010}} than those of African descent. There are large health, education and income disparities between the races in [[Brazil]].&lt;ref name="Santana1"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Santana, Almeida-Filho, Roberts, Cooper|first=Vilma, Naomar, Robert, Sharon P.|year=2007|title=Skin Colour, Perception of Racism and Depression among Adolescents in Urban Brazil|journal=Child &amp; Adolescent Mental Health |volume=12|issue=3 |pages=125–131|doi=10.1111/j.1475-3588.2007.00447.x |last2=Almeida-Filho |first2=Naomar |last3=Roberts |first3=Robert |last4=Cooper |first4=Sharon P.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Latin America, light skin is seen as more attractive.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.post-gazette.com/pg/06360/748295-51.stm|title=Documentary, Studies Renew Debate About Skin Color's Impact|publisher=Pittsburg Post Gazette|date=12-26-2006|accessdate=09-08-2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; In Mexico and in Brazil, light skin represents power. Light skin is seen as attractive.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://newsblogs.chicagotribune.com/race/2009/02/in-many-different-cultures-and-countries-around-the-world-skin-color-plays-a-huge-role-in-the-concept-of-beauty-lighter-ski/comments/page/2/|title=Is Light Skin Still Preferable to Dark?|publisher=Chicago Tribune|date=02-26-2010|accessdate=09-08-2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; A dark skinned person is more likely to be discriminated in Brazil.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.miamiherald.com/multimedia/news/afrolatin/part5/index.html|title=Racism Takes Many Hues|publisher=Miami Herald|date=08-24-2007|accessdate=09-08-2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Most South American actors and actresses have European features - blue eyes and pale skin. A light skinned person was considered to be more privileged and have a higher social status. A person with light skin is considered beautiful and it means that the person has more wealth. Skin color is such an obsession in these countries that specific words describe distinct skin tones from "hincha," Puerto Rican slang for "glass of milk" to "morena," literally "brown."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.boston.com/news/globe/living/articles/2004/08/19/pride_or_prejudice/?page=2|title=Pride or Prejudice?|publisher=Boston.com|date=08-19-2004|accessdate=09-08-2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Generally, those with dark skin and frizzy hair tend to be among the region's poorest and most disenfranchised.

==In South Asia==
Even prior to any interactions between [[Europe]]ans and [[South Asia]]ns, colorism has been an issue for South Asian cultures. According to Communist revisionist historians, color prejudice was introduced due to Aryans from Central Asia invading India in ancient times and subjugating the "dark" indigenous Indians. This form of negationist historical revisionism was part of the British colonial ideology. Much of these theories were simply conjecture fueled by European imperialism. This styling of an Aryan invasion by British colonial fantasies of racial supremacy was incorporated by Communist of duillean haywood revisionists as part of waging a [[Trotskyist]] [[permanent revolution]] in India between perceived "whites" and "darks", and has no basis in genetic or anthropological studies of South Asian populations. More recent studies have also debunked the British claims that so-called "Aryans" and "Dravidians" have a "racial divide". A study conducted by the [[Centre for Cellular and Molecular Biology]] in [[2009]] (in collaboration with [[Harvard Medical School]], [[Harvard School of Public Health]] and the [[Broad Institute of Harvard]] and [[MIT]]) analyzed half a million genetic markers across the genomes of 132 individuals from 25 ethnic groups from 13 states in India across multiple caste groups.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dnaindia.com/scitech/report_indians-are-one-people-descended-from-two-tribes_1292864 Indians are one people descended from two tribes]&lt;/ref&gt; The study establishes, based on the impossibility of identifying any genetic indicators across caste lines, that castes in South Asia grew out of traditional tribal organizations during the formation of Indian society, and was not the product of any mythical "Aryan Invasion" and "subjugation" of Dravidian people, unlike what British racial-[[revanchist]] and [[Historical revisionism (negationism)|revisionist]] claims would have one believe.&lt;ref&gt;[http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/news/india/Aryan-Dravidian-divide-a-myth-Study/articleshow/5053274.cms Aryan-Dravidian divide a myth: Study], [[Times of India]]&lt;/ref&gt;

The study does go on state that there were two different populations that originally settled India. They were the [[Ancestral North Indian]] (ANI) in the north and the [[Ancestral South Indian]] (ASI) in the south. Over time these groups mixed together.

Traditionally, Hinduism has never{{Citation needed|date=May 2010}} shown a preference for skin colour and dark skinned people can be found in all castes of Hindu society.&lt;!-- But can light colored people be found in all castes? --&gt; In the [[Mahabharata]], the character known as Krishnaa was of dark complexion but was an epitome of beauty. The incarnation of Vishnu, [[Krishna]] himself (widely revered by [[Vaishnavites]]), was said to be "as black as a full raincloud".

Individuals in South Asia have tended to see whiter skin as more beautiful. This was most clearly visible in [[British India]], where skin color served as a signal of high status for British. Thus, those individuals with fairer skin color enjoyed more privileges and opportunities than those with dark skin. Anglo-Indians with more European features were often more upwardly mobile and were considered{{Who|date=May 2010}} to have a more affluent status. These individuals gained preferences{{Clarify|date=May 2010}} in education and in employment. Darker skinned individuals were socially and economically disadvantaged due to their appearance. (Beyond the South Asian subcontinent,
persons who were dark-skinned, "black" or "colored" faced a disadvantage in most European-held colonies.)
Most Indian actors and actresses have light skin.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.newsweek.com/2008/07/02/blackout.html|title=Blackout|publisher=Newsweek|date=07-03-2008|accessdate=09-08-2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==In East Asia==
In eastern parts of Asia, including [[Southeast Asia]], a preference for lighter skin remains prevalent. In ancient China and Japan, for example, pale skin can be traced back to ancient drawings depicting women and goddesses with fair skin tones. In ancient China, Japan, and Southeast Asia, pale skin was seen as a sign of wealth.{{Citation needed|date=September 2010}} Thus, [[skin whitening]] cosmetic products are popular in East Asia.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://edition.cnn.com/2002/WORLD/asiapcf/east/05/13/asia.whitening/|title=Skin Deep: Dying to be White|publisher=CNN|date=05-15-2002|accessdate=09-08-2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; 4 out of 10 women surveyed in [[Hong Kong]], [[Malaysia]], the [[Philippines]] and [[South Korea]] used a skin-whitening cream, and more than 60 companies globally compete for Asia's estimated $18 billion market.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.pri.org/world/asia/skin-whitening-big-business-asia.html&lt;/ref&gt;

The perception of beauty can be influenced by racial stereotypes about skin color; the African American journalist [[Jill Nelson]] wrote that "to be both prettiest and black was impossible"&lt;ref name=tws6nov14/&gt; and elaborated:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
As a girl and young woman, hair, body, and color were society's trinity in determining female beauty and identity, the cultural and value-laden gang of three that formed the boundaries and determined the extent of women's visibility, influence, and importance. For the most part, they still are. We learn as girls that in ways both subtle and obvious, personal and political, our value as females is largely determined by how we look. As we enter womanhood, the pervasive power of this trinity is demonstrated again and again in how we are treated by the men we meet, the men we work for, the men who wield power, how we treat each other and, most of all, ourselves. For black women, the domination of physical aspects of beauty in women's definition and value render us invisible, partially erased, or obsessed, sometimes for a lifetime, since most of us lack the major talismans of Western beauty. Black women find themselves involved in a lifelong effort to self-define in a culture that provides them no positive reflection.&lt;ref name=tws6nov14&gt;{{Cite news
| author =  Jill Nelson
| title = Straight, No Chaser&amp;mdash;How I Became a Grown-Up Black Woman&amp;mdash; WHO'S THE FAIREST OF THEM ALL?
| quote = As a girl and young woman, hair, body, and color were society's trinity in determining female beauty and identity... We learn as girls that in ways both subtle and obvious, personal and political, our value as females is largely determined by how we look.
| publisher = New York Times
| year = 1997
| url = http://www.nytimes.com/books/first/n/nelson-straight.html
| accessdate = 2009-11-06
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==In the Arab world==
Arab culture beautifies the red color.&lt;ref name=colorism_Arabs&gt;{{Cite book|last=Al-Baqr al-Affif Mukhtar|title=The Crisis of Identity in Northern Sudan: The Dilemma of a Black People with a White Culture|publisher=in Fluehr-Lobban and Rhodes, Race and Identity in the Nile Valley|pages= 213–24.|year=2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; A popular phrase in [[Northern]] [[Sudan]] is "al-Husnu ahmar" (beauty is red)&lt;ref name=colorism_Arabs/&gt; reddishness is the ultimate standard color in most Arab societies. The second ranking is called "asmar" (brown), followed by "dhahabi" (golden), "gamhi" (wheatish), "khamri" (the color of wine), "akhdar" (light black/green). "Akhdhar" is used as a polite alternative of the word "black" in describing the color of a dark-skinned Arab. The early Arabs used the word "akhdar" (green) to describe people of unquestionable nobility whose color, for one reason or the other, was black. Last and least is azraq.&lt;ref name=colorism_Arabs/&gt;  which literally means "blue", but it is used interchangeably with aswad to mean "black".

==In Africa==
Skin bleaching is popular in Senegal and all across West Africa, especially among women.&lt;ref&gt;http://abcnews.go.com/International/story?id=6625808&amp;page=1&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Blackness (African-American subculture)|Blackness]]
* [[Black is beautiful]]
* [[Colonial mentality]]
* [[Human skin color]]
* [[Nordic theory|Nordicism]]
* [[One-drop rule]]
* [[Paper bag party]]
* [[Race (classification of human beings)|Race]]
* [[Racialism]]
* [[Racism]]
* [[Shadism]]
* [[Skin whitening]]
* [[Social interpretations of race]]
* [[Whiteness studies|Whiteness]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}
* Neal, Angela &amp; Wilson, Midge (1989). The role of skin color and features in the. Black community: Implications for black women and therapy. Clinical Psychology Review, Vol 9(3), 1989. pp.&amp;nbsp;323–333.
* Kerr, Audrey E. "The Paper Bag Principle: Of the Myth and the Motion of Colorism." Journal of American Folklore 118.469 (2005): 271-289.

==Further reading==
* ''The Color Complex'' by Kathy Russell &amp; Midge Wilson (ISBN 0-385-47161-0)
* ''Don't Play In the Sun'' by Marita Golden (ISBN 0-385-50786-0)
* ''[[The Bluest Eye]]'' by [[Toni Morrison]] (ISBN 0-452-28219-5)
* ''The Blacker the Berry'' by Wallace Thurman (ISBN 0-684-81580-X)
* ''Caucasia'' by [[Danzy Senna]]
* ''[http://books.google.com/books?id=t-JLtPfRjnEC&amp;printsec=frontcover Is Lighter Better?: Skin-Tone Discrimination Among Asian Americans]'' Joanne L. Rondilla, Paul R. Spickard ISBN 0742554945

==External links==
* [http://www.africaspeaks.com/leslie/051006.html Dealing with Colourism: A Step Towards the African Revolution]
* [http://www.africaspeaks.com/Black-African-Focus/ Black African Focus]
* {{Cite journal|url=http://www.encyclopedia.com/doc/1G1-115399891.html |title=Homicide: Life on the Street: progress in portrayals of African American men |last=Mascaro |first=Thomas A. |date=2004-03-22 |journal=Journal of Popular Film and Television | issn = 0195-6051 |id={{OCLC|4652347}} }}
* {{Cite web|url=http://students.ou.edu/M/Craig.A.Marroquin-1/colorism.html|title=The Face of Colorism |accessdate=2008-09-28 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080412133655/http://students.ou.edu/M/Craig.A.Marroquin-1/colorism.html &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2008-04-12}}
* [http://students.ou.edu/M/Craig.A.Marroquin-1/colorism.html Colorism]
* [http://www.colorismexposed.com Origin of Rainbows: Colorism Exposed Documentary]
* [http://abcnews.go.com/2020/GiveMeABreak/Story?id=548303&amp;page=1 abcnews.go.com]
* "''Light, Bright, Damn near White''" documentary film

{{DEFAULTSORT:Color Discrimination}}
[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Cultural studies]]
[[Category:Politics and race]]

[[cs:Kolorismus]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>