<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20071110101825|170522504" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="354224" pageid="354224" ns="0" title="Discrimination based on skin tone"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-11-10T11:58:21Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{globalize/USA}}
{{Discrimination2}}
'''Colorism''' is a form of [[discrimination]] where human beings are accorded differing social and/or economic status and treatment based on skin color. Colorism can be found across the world.  The term generally is applied to non-white peoples who discriminate against members of their own ethnic group.

With colorism, usually lighter skin tones are preferred and darker skin is considered less desirable although it is possible for the opposite to also be true. An example of this phenomenon in the United States occurs in [[African-American]] communities, where it is often called ''color consciousness''.  In the U.S., the phenomenon also occurs in other  populations, such as among [[Chicano]]s and other [[Latino]]s and [[India]]n immigrants.

Also labelled as colorism, but rarely discussed, is the phenomenon of darker skinned people discriminating against lighter tones within the same ethnic group. This most often occurs in [[African-American]] communities. It seems to stem from residual anger from perceived historical discrimination against those with darker skin tones by those lighter skin who were often favored by white people dating back to slavery. While colorism still exist in the U.S. it has greatly diminished since the [[black power]] movements.

==African-Americans==

The "brown paper bag test" was a ritual once practiced by certain [[African-American]] and [[Creole]] [[fraternities and sororities]] who discriminated against people who were "too dark." That is, these groups would not let anyone into the sorority or fraternity whose skin tone was darker than a paper lunch bag so as to maintain [[Mulatto]] and Creole cultural standards.[[Spike Lee]]'s film ''[[School Daze]]'' satirizes this practice. 

While stated less explicitly, Colorism can be seen in instances on the NBC drama ''[[Homicide: Life on the Street]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | url = http://www.encyclopedia.com/doc/1G1-115399891.html | title = Homicide: Life on the Street: progress in portrayals of African American men | last = Mascaro | first = Thomas A. | date = [[2004-03-22]] | journal = Journal of Popular Film and Television | issn = 0195-6051 | id = {{OCLC|4652347}} | accessdate = 2007-09-23 }}&lt;/ref&gt; On the show, a main character Baltimore Police Lieutenant [[Al Giardello]], a darker skinned [[African American]] officer is discrimated against by his lighter skinned [[African American]] superior officers Deputy Commissioner of Operations [[James C. Harris]] and Colonel [[George Barnfather]]. Additionally, Giardello is discriminated against by [[African American]] women as his appearance is "too black".&lt;ref&gt;http://novemberrain.free.fr/GlossaireHLOTS.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

==The "Blue Vein Society"==
Following the Emancipation, [[mulatto]] societies such as as "The Blue Vein Society" came into prominence. Its members were often well-connected free-born or freed individuals of mixed African, [[Europe]]an, and occasionally of [[Native Americans in the United States|Native American]] blood. To be eligible for membership, one's skin color had to be pale enough that the "blue veins" on the underside of the arm were visible. Such restrictive organizations allowed its members and their offspring to meet, co-mingle and marry, thereby preserving what small privilege the mulatto elite had enjoyed before all slaves were set free. Uneducated, or economically disadvantaged mixed race individuals, even those whose skin color was technically light enough to qualify them for admission, were still rarely welcomed.

The original "Blue Veins" were said to have been organized in New England. Their primary objective was to establish and maintain "correct" social standards amongst a people whose social condition, by virtue of their white bloodlines and powerful family connections. Today, social clubs such as Links and Jack and Jill are said to serve the same purpose for the [[Black middle class]]; however, in the late 20th century, economic standing, social position or professional affiliation often provide entry into these organizations to those who fit the physical criteria of having light skin.

==Books about colorism==
*''The Color Complex'' by Kathy Russell &amp; Midge Wilson (ISBN 0-385-47161-0)
*''Don't Play In the Sun'' by Marita Golden (ISBN 0-385-50786-0)
*''[[The Bluest Eye]]'' by [[Toni Morrison]] (ISBN 0-452-28219-5)&lt;br&gt; 
*''Flesh and the Devil'' by Kola Boof (ISBN 0-9712019-7-8)&lt;br&gt; 
*''The Blacker the Berry'' by Wallace Thurman (ISBN 0-684-81580-X)
*''Caucasia'' by [[Danzy Senna]]
*''[http://books.google.com/books?id=t-JLtPfRjnEC&amp;printsec=frontcover Is Lighter Better?: Skin-Tone Discrimination Among Asian Americans]''Joanne L. Rondilla  Paul R Spickard ISBN 0742554945

== Colorism outside the United States ==
{{unreferenced-section|date=September 2007}}
Colorism also occurs in many eastern cultures where fair people are considered to be more superior, affluent, and powerful then those of a darker skin tone. In some Latin American countries such as [[Brazil]], "race" is often more a matter of skin tone and social status than actual ancestry.

Colorism can be identified as a direct consequence of the social stratification of colonial societies, especially the ones affected by slavery.
The phenomenon can be identified in the Americas from United States to Caribbean countries to South America.

In the [[French West Indies]], new born children can be deemed as "sauvé" (saved) when their skin tone is light enough to represent a chance at better social status.

The same patterns that discriminate dark skin are also applied to other physical features that are directly linked to African heritage: hair, face features, etc.

== Colorism in Indian Society ==
{{unreferenced-section|date=September 2007}}

In the Indian Sub-continent, light skin is deemed more beautiful, in both men and women. Indian actors and actress almost always have milky white skin, or use lots of makeup to made to look lighter. Actress [[Bipasha Basu]] who has darker skin than most other Indian actresses, has been made to look lighter through makeup and her pictures are airbrushed for the same purpose. Indians have many skin colors, ranging from white to black and everything in between. Many Indians think it's natural to consider light skin to be more beautiful than dark skin. Historical Indian caste differences as well as a long history of invasion and colonization may play a part in this prejudice.

However in [[Sri Lanka]] colorism was historically absent. But there are indications that colorism might spread to Sri Lanka as Sri Lankans have started to watch a lot of Indian films and teledramas.

== See also ==
* [[Blackness]]
* [[Black is Beautiful]]
* [[Colonial mentality]]
* [[Skin whitening]]
* [[Human skin color]]
* [[Nordic theory|Nordicism]]
* [[Paper bag party]]
* [[Pigmentocracy]]
* [[One-drop rule]]
* [[Race]]
* [[Racialism]]
* [[Racism]]
* [[Social interpretations of race]]
* [[Whiteness studies|Whiteness]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.africaspeaks.com/leslie/051006.html Dealing with Colourism: A Step Towards the African Revolution]
* [http://www.sptimes.com/2003/08/31/Columns/The_paper_bag_test.shtml THE PAPER BAG TEST], an editorial by [[Bill Maxwell]] about blacks discriminating against blacks, ''St. Petersburg Times'', [[August 31]] [[2003]], discusses the history of the test.
* [http://proofmagazine.i8.com/contact.html AUTHENTIC BLACKNESS]...Magazine article inwhich Nigerian Scholar [[Chinweizu]] and Sudanese novelist [[Kola Boof]] document the African viewpoint of what is a "black" person and analyze colorism's effects on that criteria.
*[http://www.africaspeaks.com/Black-African-Focus/ Black African Focus]
* {{cite journal | url = http://www.encyclopedia.com/doc/1G1-115399891.html | title = Homicide: Life on the Street: progress in portrayals of African American men | last = Mascaro | first = Thomas A. | date = [[2004-03-22]] | journal = Journal of Popular Film and Television | issn = 0195-6051 | id = {{OCLC|4652347}} }}
* "The Face of Colorism (Black is beautiful....only if you're light-skinned)"  
* http://students.ou.edu/M/Craig.A.Marroquin-1/colorism.html
* Origin of Rainbows: Colorism Exposed Documentary (http://www.colorismexposed.com)

[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Cultural studies]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>