<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061111011635|87057271" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="354224" pageid="354224" ns="0" title="Discrimination based on skin tone"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-11-13T17:01:13Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{uncategorized|November 2006}}
'''Colorism''' is a form of [[discrimination]] that usually occurs in the [[United States]]. Colorism is also found in other countries and societies, such as the [[Caribbean]], [[Latin America]], and [[Asia]]. 

It is usually distinguished by where lighter skin tones are preferred, and darker skin tones are considered to be less desirable. There seems to be an implicit calculus behind this belief that makes the goodness of the individual inversely related to the darkness (or sometimes lightness) of his/her skin. An example of this phenomenon in the United States occurs in [[African-American]] communities.

Also labelled as colorism, but rarely discussed, is the discrimation of or hostility towards lighter skin tones in the same ethnic group. This most often occurs in [[African-American]] communities. It seems to stem from residual anger from perceived historical discrimination against those with darker skin tones.

==African-Americans==

The "brown paper bag test" was a ritual once practiced by certain [[African-American]] [[sororities and fraternities]] who discriminated against people who were "too dark." That is, these groups would not let anyone into the sorority or fraternity whose skin tone was darker than a paper lunch sack. [[Spike Lee]]'s film ''[[School Daze]]'' satirizes this practice.

==The "Blue Vein Society"==
Follwoing the Emancipation, [[mulatto]] societies such as as "[[The Blue Vein Society]]" came into prominence. Its members were often well-connected free-born or freed individuals of mixed African, [[European]], and ocassionally of [[Native Americans in the United States|Native American]] blood. To be eligible for membership, one's skin color had to be pale enough that the "blue veins" on the underside of the arm were visible. Such restrictive organizations allowed its members and their offspring to meet, co-mingle and marry, thereby preserving what small privilege the mulatto elite had enjoyed before all Blacks were set free. Uneducated, or economically disadvantaged mixed race individuals, even those whose skin color was technically light enough to qualify them for admission, were still rarely welcomed. Although these clubs may sound like an odd way to govern membership, in reality they simply mirrored the practices of upper-class [[WASP]] individuals who had their own restrictive country clubs that denied membership to Jews. 

The original "Blue Veins" were said to have been organized in New England. Their primary objective was to establish and maintain "correct" social standards amongst a people whose social condition, by virtue of their white bloodlines and powerful family connections. Today, social clubs such as Links and Jack and Jill are said to serve the same purpose for the Black middle class.

==Books about colorism==
*''The Color Complex'' by Kathy Russell &amp; Midge Wilson (ISBN 0-385-47161-0)
*''Don't Play In the Sun'' by Marita Golden (ISBN 0-385-50786-0)
*''The Bluest Eye'' by Toni Morrison (ISBN 0-452-28219-5)&lt;br&gt; 
*''Flesh and the Devil'' by Kola Boof (ISBN 0-9712019-7-8)&lt;br&gt; 
*''The Blacker the Berry'' by Wallace Thurman (ISBN 0-684-81580-X)

== Colorism outside the United States ==

Colorism also occurs in many eastern cultures where fair people are considered to be more superior, affluent, and powerful then those of a darker skin tone. In some Latin American countries such as [[Brazil]], "race" is often more a matter of skin tone and social status than actual ancestry.

Colorism can be identified as a direct consequence of the social stratification of colonial societies, especially the ones affected by slavery.
The phenomenon can be identified in the Americas from United States to Caribbean countries to South America.

In the [[French West Indies]], new born children can be deemed as "sové" (saved) when their skin tone is light enough to reprensent a chance at better social status.

The same patterns that discriminate dark skin are also applied to other physical features that are directly linked to African heritage: hair, face features, etc.

== See also ==
* [[Colonial mentality]]
* [[Skin whitening]]
* [[Hutu]] &amp; [[Tutsi]]
* [[Human skin color]]
* [[Blackness]]

==External links==

* [http://www.sptimes.com/2003/08/31/Columns/The_paper_bag_test.shtml THE PAPER BAG TEST], an editorial by Bill Maxwell about blacks discriminating against blacks, ''St. Petersburg Times'', [[August 31]] [[2003]], discusses the history of the test.

* [http://proofmagazine.i8.com/contact.html AUTHENTIC BLACKNESS]...Magazine article inwhich Nigerian Scholar Chinweizu and Sudanese novelist Kola Boof document the African viewpoint of what is a "black" person and analyze colorism's effects on that criteria.</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>