<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20110120013952|408893169" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="8868864" pageid="8868864" ns="0" title="Sexual orientation discrimination"><revisions><rev timestamp="2011-06-23T17:16:59Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">
{{refimprove|date=February 2009}}
{{Discrimination sidebar}} 
'''Sexualism''' refers to either discrimination based on [[human sexuality|sexuality]], or sexuality itself. Its most common form is [[heterosexism]].

== Sexual bias ==
'''Sexualism''' is discrimination against a person or group on the basis of their sexual orientation or sexual behaviour. It usually refers to a predisposition towards [[heterosexuality|heterosexual]] people, which is biased against [[lesbian]], [[gay]], [[bisexuality|bisexual]], and [[asexual]], people, among others. It can, however, also be against heterosexual people. A related term is '''Sexual Prejudice''', a negative attitude toward someone because of her or his sexual orientation.&lt;ref&gt;Matlin, Margaret W.,Ph.D., "The Psychology of Women", (2004)&lt;/ref&gt; 
This bias is not the same as [[Homophobia]], but rather is the discrimination towards or against certain sexual orientations. [[Heterosexism]] suggests that the basis for this bias is not found in the individual per se but rather has a broader cultural or biological basis that results in weighted attitudes towards heterosexuality over other sexual orientations. Heterosexism is one form of [[structural violence]].

An earlier definition of this term is:
Sexualism is a belief or argument that one sexual orientation or sexual behaviour is inherently superior to some or all others. Usually it comes in the form of [[heterosexuality]] being considered the only [[nature|natural]], [[normality (behavior)|normal]], or [[moral]] mode of sexual behavior, and is also used to refer to the effects of that
instinct. The word ''heterosexism'' has also been proposed to mean essentially the same thing as this form of sexualism.&lt;!--In The Dictionary of Psychology [1] ''heterosexism'' is defined as 
"An argument that male-female sexuality is the only correct, natural, proper, or moral mode of sexual activity. [Also proposed as] ''heterosexualism''. --&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Corsini, Raymond J., ''The Dictionary of Psychology'' (2001), ISBN 1-58391-328-9&lt;br&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; This word has been suggested as an alternative to [[homophobia]],&lt;ref&gt;Herek, Gregory M., Ph.D., " Beyond 'Homophobia': Thinking About Sexual Prejudice and Stigma in the Twenty-First Century."   Sexuality Research &amp; Social Policy (April, 2004)&lt;/ref&gt; in part because it uses a parallel structure to [[sexism]] or [[racism]]. The intent of heterosexism is the examination of the cultural bias towards non-heterosexuals rather than individual bias, which is the focus of homophobia.

Sexualism should not be confused with heterosexism, which is an (often subconscious) assumption that everyone is heterosexual, and the attitudes associated with that assumption.  In [[queer theory]], heterosexism is closely related to [[heteronormativity]].{{Citation needed|date=February 2007}}

== Sexuality / Sexual nature ==
The term '''sexualism''' has often been used in literature to refer to man's sexual nature.&lt;ref&gt;Coleman, Julie, 'Love, Sex and Marriage: A Historical Thesaurus' (1999)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Glicksberg, Charles Irving, 'The Sexual Revolution in Modern English Literature' (1973), etc.&lt;/ref&gt; The term [[Pansexuality|pansexualism]], seen especially in the field of early-20th century psychoanalysis&lt;!-- (Freud and "pan-sexualism")--&gt;,&lt;ref&gt;Malinowski, Bronislaw , ''[[Sex and Repression in Savage Society]]'' (1927)&lt;/ref&gt; was based on this usage. The terms [[homosexualism]] and [[bisexualism]] were also based on this usage, and were commonly used before the general adoption of the terms [[homosexuality]] and [[bisexuality]].&lt;ref&gt;Kodaigaku - 'Bi-sexualism in Buddhist Literature', by Kodaigaku Kyōkai (Japan)&lt;/ref&gt; The word sexualism is still in use, though often as part of a hyphenated compound word (for example, "anti-sexualism").&lt;!-- "Popularly written history of recent and present-day anti-sexualism in American health care and social/legal policy. Includes anti-masturbation theories ..." from --&gt;&lt;ref&gt;'For Sex Education, See Librarian: A Guide to Issues and Resources,' by Martha Cornog, Timothy Perper (1996)&lt;/ref&gt;

===Example usage===
Dr. C.G. Jung, in his book THE PSYCHOLOGY OF THE UNCONSCIOUS, wrote: 
&lt;blockquote&gt;''Just as the sexualism of neuroses is not to be taken literally but as regressive phantasy and symbolic compensation for a recent unachieved adaptation, so is the sexualism of the early infantile phantasy, especially the incest problem, a regressive product of the revival of the archaic modes of function, outweighing actuality.''&lt;ref name="jung"&gt;{{cite book|last=Jung|first=Carl Gustav|title=Psychology of the Unconscious: A Study of the Transformations and Symbolisms of the Libido, a Contribution to the History of the Evolution of Thought|publisher=Moffat, Yard and company|year=1916|pages=463|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=EXQRAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA464&amp;dq=&amp;ei=k36USYqmMYjcygTLzJSrBQ#PPA463,M1}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

== See also ==
*[[Antisexualism]]
*[[Heteronormativity]]
*[[Heterosexism]]
*[[Homophobia]]
*[[Sexualization]]
*[[Transphobia]]

== Notes ==
&lt;references /&gt;

==References==
*White, Chris, 'Nineteenth-century Writings on Homosexuality: a sourcebook' -ISBN 0-415-15305-0
*Wolman, Benjamin B., 'International Encyclopedia of Psychiatry, Psychology, Psychoanalysis &amp; Neurology' (1977)
*Fish, J. Heterosexism in Health &amp; Social Care. Basingstoke: Palgrave. (2006)

[[Category:Gender studies]]
[[Category:Queer theory]]
[[Category:Sexual and gender prejudices]]
[[Category:Sexual orientation and society]]

[[fr:Sexualisme]]
[[mk:Сексизам]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>