<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20091116074341|326125312" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="12343002" pageid="12343002" ns="0" title="Religious discrimination against modern pagans"><revisions><rev timestamp="2009-11-16T18:31:35Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[Neopaganism|Neopagans]] are a [[religious minority]] in every country where they exist,&lt;ref&gt;Consistently below 0.5%. Estimated ratios may approach 0.4% in [[Religion in Iceland|Iceland]] and the [[Religion in the United Kingdom|UK]]. In the [[USA]] and [[Canada]], Neopagans account for an estimated 0.2% of the population.&lt;/ref&gt; and have been subject to [[religious discrimination]]. The largest Neopagan communities are in [[North America]] and the [[United Kingdom]], and the issue of discrimination receives most attention in those locations, but there are also reports from [[Australia]] and [[Greece]] (the latter specifically concerning [[Hellenic Neopaganism]]).

==United States==
{{see|Neopaganism in the United States}}
According to [[Starhawk]] "[[religious discrimination]] against [[Pagans]] and [[Wiccans]] and [[indigenous religions]] is omnipresent in the U.S."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://newsweek.washingtonpost.com/onfaith/starhawk/2007/03/discrimination_against_pagans.html |title=Washington Post: Discrimination Against Pagans}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===In prisons===
{{see|Prisons in the United States|Religion in the United States' prisons|Dettmer v. Landon|Cutter v. Wilkinson}}
The 1985, Virginia prisoner Herbert Daniel Dettmer sued Robert Landon, the Director of the Virginia Department of Corrections, in federal court, to get access to objects he claimed were necessary for his Wiccan religious practice. The district court for the Eastern District of Virginia decided in Dettmer's favor, although on appeal the [[United States Court of Appeals for the Fourth Circuit]] ruled that, while Wicca was a religion, he was not being discriminated against. This case marked the first legal recognition of Wicca as a religion.

In 2004, a case involving five Ohio prison inmates (two followers of [[Ásatrú]], a minister of the [[Church of Jesus Christ Christian]], a [[Wicca]]n witch and a [[Satanist]]) protesting denial of access to ceremonial items and opportunities for group worship was brought before the Supreme Court.&lt;ref name="select.nytimes.com"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F60916FC355F0C708DDDA90994DC404482&amp;n=Top%2fReference%2fTimes%20Topics%2fOrganizations%2fS%2fSupreme%20Court%20 |title=NY Times: Justices Will Hear 2 Church-State Cases}}&lt;/ref&gt; Among the denied objects was instructions for runic writing requested by an Ásatrúer, which was initially denied when prison officials raised concerns that runic writing could be used for coded gang communication.

In an interview about the role of race-based [[gang]]s and other extremists in America's prisons, the historian [[Mark Pitcavage]] came to the conclusion that, "[n]''on-racist versions of Ásatrú and Odinism are pretty much acceptable religions in the prisons.''"&lt;ref&gt;Interview with Mark Pitcavage - [http://www.splcenter.org/intel/intelreport/article.jsp?sid=55 Behind the Walls]&lt;/ref&gt; But, materials from racist variants of these religions may be prohibited by corrections departments.

===In the armed forces===
In 1999, in response to a statement by Representative [[Bob Barr]] (R-GA, now [[Libertarian Party (United States)|Libertarian]]) regarding Wiccan gatherings on military bases, the [[Free Congress Foundation]] called for U.S. citizens to not enlist or re-enlist in the U.S. Army until the Army terminated the on-base freedoms of religion, speech and assembly for all Wiccan soldiers.&lt;ref name="SatanicArmy"&gt;{{cite press release |url=http://web.archive.org/web/20020617210538/http://www.freecongress.org/press/releases/990609.htm |title='Satanic' Army Unworthy of Representing United States |publisher=Free Congress Foundation |date=[[1999-06-09]] |accessdate=2007-07-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="RISwiccan"&gt;{{cite journal |url=http://web.archive.org/web/20070524174633/http://www.trincoll.edu/depts/csrpl/RINVol2No2/wicca.htm |title=Something Wiccan This Way Comes |journal=Religion in the News |first=Mark |last=Silk |month=Summer |year=1999 |volume=2 |issue=2 |issn=1525-7207}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="BarrProject"&gt;{{cite news |url=http://web.archive.org/web/20000229034145/http://www.lawstreet.com/journal/art991101wiccan.html |title=Barr's Witch Project: Lawmaker Wants to Ban Witches from the Military |work=LawStreet Journal |date=[[1999-11-01]] |accessdate=2007-07-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; Though this movement died a "quiet death", on [[24 June]] [[1999]], then-Governor [[George W. Bush]] stated on a television news program that "I don’t think witchcraft is a religion and I wish the military would take another look at this and decide against it."&lt;ref name="FortHoodsWiccans"&gt;{{cite conference |url=http://www.chasclifton.com/papers/hood.html |title=Fort Hood's Wiccans and the Problem of Pacifism |booktitle=Proceedings of the American Academy of Religion 2000 Meeting |first=Chas S |last=Clifton |date=[[2000-11-20]] |accessdate=2007-07-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="otherlinks1"&gt;Assortment of links regarding calls to ban Wicca from military establishments: [http://web.archive.org/web/20060613210914/http://www.firstamendmentcenter.org/news.aspx?id=9745], [http://web.archive.org/web/20060613210859/http://www.firstamendmentcenter.org/news.aspx?id=9729], [http://web.archive.org/web/20040328215008/http://www.firstamendmentcenter.org/news.aspx?id=9708], [http://web.archive.org/web/20060912005514/http://www.au.org/site/News2?JServSessionIdr012=2wta0ekcf1.app7b&amp;abbr=pr&amp;page=NewsArticle&amp;id=6192&amp;news_iv_ctrl=1479]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Emb-37.svg|thumb|left|80px|"Emblem of Belief"#37]]
[[United States Army Chaplain Corps|U.S. Army Chaplain]] Captain Don Larsen was dismissed from his post in [[Iraq]] in 2006 after changing his religious affiliation from [[Pentecostalism|Pentecostal Christianity]] to Wicca and applying to become the first Wiccan military chaplain. His potential new endorser, the Sacred Well Congregation based in Texas, was not yet an officially recognised endorsement organisation for the military, and upon hearing of his conversion, his prior endorser, the Chaplaincy of Full Gospel Churches, immediately revoked its endorsement. At this point, the U.S. Army was required to dismiss him from chaplaincy despite an exemplary service record.&lt;ref name="washpost20070218"&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2007/02/18/AR2007021801396_pf.html |title=For Gods and Country |work=The Washington Post |first=Alan |last=Cooperman |date=[[2007-02-19]] |accessdate=2007-06-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Prior to 2007, the [[United States Department of Veterans Affairs]] did not allow the use of the [[pentacle]] as an "emblem of belief" on tombstones in military cemeteries. This policy was changed following an out-of-court settlement on [[23 April]] following a series of lawsuits against the VA.&lt;ref name="SymbolsAllowed"&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.iht.com/articles/ap/2007/04/23/america/NA-GEN-US-Wiccan-Soldier.php |title=Wiccans symbols allowed on grave markers in government cemeteries |work=International Herald Tribune |author=Associated Press |date=[[2007-04-23]] |accessdate=2007-07-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="VAMustAccommodate"&gt;{{cite press release |url=http://www.au.org/site/News2?JServSessionIdr003=bg8nm5s6e1.app13a&amp;abbr=pr&amp;page=NewsArticle&amp;id=8269&amp;security=1002&amp;news_iv_ctrl=1241 |title=Veterans Affairs Department Must Accommodate Wiccan Symbol On Memorial Markers At Government Cemeteries, Says Americans United |publisher=Americans United (AU.org) |date=[[2006-06-08]] |accessdate=2007-07-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="ListofVASymbols"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.cem.va.gov/cem/hm/hmemb.asp |title=Available Emblems of Belief for Placement on Government Headstones and Markers |work=VA.gov |accessdate=2007-07-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''See [[Patrick Stewart (soldier)]].''

The United States Department of Veterans Affairs does not list any Ásatrú symbols as available emblems of belief for placement on government headstones and markers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.cem.va.gov/cem/hm/hmemb.asp |title=Available Emblems of Belief for Placement on Government Headstones and Markers&amp;nbsp;— Department of Veterans Affairs}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to federal guidelines, only approved religious symbols&amp;nbsp;— of which there are 39&amp;nbsp;— can be placed on government headstones or memorial plaques. [[Ásatrú Folk Assembly]] have demanded such a symbol.

===Wicca===
According to [[Gerald Gardner]], who popularised [[Wicca]] in the twentieth century, the religion is a survival of a European witch-cult that was persecuted during the [[witch trials]] (sometimes called the ''[[Witch-hunt#The Burning Times|Burning Times]]''), and the strong element of secrecy that traditionally surrounds the religion was adopted as a reaction to that persecution. Since then, [[Margaret Murray]]'s theory of an organised pan-European witch-cult has been discredited, and doubts raised about the age of Wicca; many Wiccans no longer claim this historical lineage. However, it is still common for Wiccans to feel solidarity with the victims of the witch trials and, being witches, to consider the witch-craze to have been a persecution against their faith.&lt;ref name="WitchcraftInside"&gt;{{cite book |title=Witchcraft From The Inside: Origins of the Fastest Growing Religious Movement in America |first=Raymond |last=Buckland |authorlink=Raymond Buckland |publisher=Llewellyn Publications |location=St. Paul, MN |date=[[2002-09-01]] |origyear=1971 |edition=3rd |isbn=1-56718-101-5 |oclc=31781774}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There has been confusion that Wicca is a form of [[Satanism]], despite important differences between these religions.&lt;ref name="Davis2003"&gt;{{cite book |title=New Religious Movements and Religious Liberty in America |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=up5fnY7Wp1wC&amp;pg=PA75&amp;sig=9NkPJ0x_PZBpvg7tJMC_zjKhx2c |publisher=Baylor University Press |location=[[Waco, Texas|Waco]] |author=Davis, Derek; Hankins, Barry |edition=2nd |year=2003 |pages=75 |isbn=0918954924 |oclc=52895492 |quote=Much to the chagrin of practitioners of Wicca, there has been confusion in the minds of many about their religion, which is often linked with Satanism, although there are important differences.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Due to negative connotations associated with witchcraft, many Wiccans continue the traditional practice of secrecy, concealing their faith for fear of persecution. Revealing oneself as Wiccan to family, friends or colleagues is often termed "coming out of the broom-closet".&lt;ref name="slate031204"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.slate.com/id/2090966/ |title=Witch Way |work=Slate.com |author='Bewitched' |date=2003-12-04 |accessdate=2008-05-16 |quote=Believe me, coming out of the "broom closet" is a one-way trip.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Wiccans have also experienced difficulties in administering and receiving prison ministry, although not in the UK of recent times.&lt;ref name="hmprison"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://psi.hmprisonservice.gov.uk/PSI_2005_33_paganism.doc |title=Practice of Paganism in Prison |work=HM Prison Service |first=Michael |last=Spurr |date=[[2005-08-31]] |accessdate=2007-07-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1985, as a result of ''[[Dettmer v. Landon]]'' [617 F. Supp. 592 (D.C. Va 1985)], the District Court of [[Virginia]] ruled that Wicca is a legally recognised religion and is afforded all the benefits accorded to it by law. This was affirmed a year later by Judge [[John D. Butzner, Jr.]] of the [[United States Court of Appeals for the Fourth Circuit]] [''Dettmer v. Landon'', 799 F. 2d 929 (4th Cir. 1986)]. Nevertheless, Wiccans are sometimes still stigmatised in America, and many remain secretive about their beliefs. In September 1985, [[Jesse Helms]] introduced legislation designed to take away the tax-exempt status of Wiccan religious institutions. This ultimately died with the close of the [[Ninety-ninth United States Congress|99th session of Congress]] in December 1986.&lt;ref name="WitchesPagansMedia"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.beliefnet.com/story/58/story_5812_2.html |title=Witches, Pagans, and the Media |work=BeliefNet.com |first=Margot |last=Adler |authorlink=Margot Adler |year=2000 |accessdate=2006-04-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Also in 1985, conservative legislators in the United States introduced three pieces of legislation designed to take away the tax-exempt status of Wiccans. The first one was House Resolution (H.R.) 3389, introduced on [[19 September]] [[1985]] by Congressman [[Robert Smith Walker|Robert S. Walker]] (R-Pennsylvania), which would have amended to the United States [[Internal Revenue Code]] that any organisation which promotes witchcraft would not be exempt from taxation. On the other side of Congress, Senator [[Jesse Helms]] (R-North Carolina ) added Amendment 705 to H.R. 3036, "The Treasury, Postal, and General Government Appropriations Bill for 1986", which similarly stated that organisations promoting witchcraft would not be eligible for tax-exempt status. After being ignored for a time, it was attached to H.R. 3036 by a unanimous voice vote of the senators. Congressman [[Richard T. Schulze]] (R-Pennsylvania) introduced substantially the same amendment to the Tax Reform Bill of 1985. When the budget subcommittee met on [[30 October]], the Helms Amendment was thrown out as it was not considered germane to the bill. Following this, Schulze withdrew his amendment from the Tax Reform Bill, leaving only H.R. 3389, the Walker Bill. [[Joe Barton]] (R-Texas) was attracted to become a co-sponsor of this bill on [[14 November]] [[1985]]. The [[United States House Committee on Ways and Means|Ways and Means Committee]] set aside the bill and quietly ignored it, and the bill was allowed to die with the close of the [[Ninety-ninth United States Congress|99th session of Congress]] in December 1986.&lt;ref name="99thCongress"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://soamc.dynu.com/tfh/FILES/Cults,%20Occult,%20Mysticism/Info%20on%20pagan%20rituals%20&amp;%20other%20info/index18.htm |title=Witch Busters: A Summary of Anti-Witchcraft Activity in the 99th Congress |work=soamc.dynu.com/tfh |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20070311074100/http://soamc.dynu.com/tfh/FILES/Cults,+Occult,+Mysticism/Info+on+pagan+rituals+&amp;+other+info/index18.htm |archivedate=2007-03-11 |accessdate=2007-07-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="WitchesMedia"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.beliefnet.com/story/58/story_5812_2.html |title=Witches, Pagans, and the Media |work=Beliefnet.com |first=Margot |last=Adler |accessdate=2007-07-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2002, Cynthia Simpson of [[Chesterfield County, Virginia]] submitted an application to be invited to lead prayer at the local Board of Supervisors meetings, but in a response was told that because the views of Wicca were not "consistent with the Judeo-Christian tradition," her application had been denied. After the Board reviewed and affirmed their policy, Simpson took the case to the [[United States District Court for the Eastern District of Virginia|U.S. District Court of Virginia]], which held that the Board had violated the [[Establishment Clause of the First Amendment|Establishment Clause]] by advancing limited sets of beliefs.&lt;ref name="simpedva"&gt;''[http://www.acluva.org/docket/pleadings/simpson_edvaopinion.pdf Simpson v. Chesterfield County Board of Supervisors]'', 292 F. Supp. 2d 805, 820 (E.D. Va. 2003)&lt;/ref&gt; The Board appealed to the [[United States Court of Appeals for the Fourth Circuit|Fourth Circuit Court of Appeals]], which in 2005 reversed the ruling based in part on the Board having modified its policy, directing clerics to avoid invoking the name of [[Jesus]].&lt;ref name="simp4cir"&gt;''[http://pacer.ca4.uscourts.gov/opinion.pdf/041045.P.pdf Simpson v. Chesterfield County Board of Supervisors]'', 404 F.3d 276 (4th Cir. 2005)&lt;/ref&gt; On [[October 11]], [[2005]], the [[United States Supreme Court]] rejected an appeal by Simpson,&lt;ref name="simpsupreme"&gt;''[http://www.supremecourtus.gov/orders/journal/jnl05.pdf Simpson v. Chesterfield County Board of Supervisors]'', 126 S. Ct. 426 (2005), p. 221&lt;/ref&gt; effectively ending the debate.&lt;ref name="lawrev0602"&gt;{{cite journal |url=http://www.harvardlawreview.org/issues/119/feb06/recent_cases/simpson_v_chesterfield.pdf |title=Fourth Circuit Holds That Local Government May Restrict the Leading of Its Invocations to Representatives of Judeo-Christian Religions |journal=Harvard Law Review |volume=119 |issue=4 |month=February |year=2006 |accessdate=2007-08-01|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="wp157"&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/articles/A55157-2005Apr14.html |title=Wiccan Bias Suit Against Va. County Dismissed |work=Washington Post |first=Jerry |last=Markon |date=[[2005-04-15]] |accessdate=2007-08-01 |pages=B03}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="cbs926"&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2005/10/11/supremecourt/main932926.shtml |title=High Court Grounds Broom Rider |work=CBS News |author=Associated Press |date=[[2005-10-11]] |accessdate=2007-08-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Ásatrú===
{{see|Ásatrú in the United States}}
The [[United States]] government does not officially endorse or recognize any religious group, but numerous Ásatrú groups have been granted [[Non-profit corporation|non-profit religious status]] going back to the 1970s.&lt;ref name= "Well of Mimir"&gt;{{cite paper| author =Linzie, Bil| title =Drinking at the Well of Mimir| version =| publisher =| year =2000| url =http://ragngautr-kindred.org/library/modern/drinking-at-the-well-of-mimir.pdf| format =[[PDF]]| accessdate =February 2007 |format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt;

An inmate of the "Intensive Management Unit" at [[Washington State Penitentiary]] alleges that adherents of Ásatrú in 2001 were deprived of their [[Mjolnir|Thor's Hammer]] medallions as well as denied religious literature, as well as complaints against the prison chaplain calling Ásatrú "'devil worship,' etc."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.prisonerlife.com/articles/articleID=3.cfm Walla Walla's Suppression of Religious Freedom]{{Verify credibility|date=July 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2007, a federal judge confirmed that Ásatrú adherents in US prisons have the right to possess a Thor’s Hammer pendant. An inmate sued the Virginia Department of Corrections after he was denied it while members of other religions were allowed their medallions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.firstamendmentcenter.org/news.aspx?id=18629 |title=First Amendment Center: Va. inmate can challenge denial of Thor's Hammer}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the Georgacarakos v. Watts case Peter N. Georgacarakos filed a pro se civil-rights complaint in the United States District Court for the District of Colorado against 19 prison officials for "interference with the free exercise of his Asatru religion" and "discrimination on the basis of his being Asatru".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.kscourts.org/CA10/cases/2005/08/05-1180.htm |title=Georgacarakos v. Watts}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Cutter v. Wilkinson]] case was partially about an adherent of Ásatrú being denied access to ceremonial items and opportunities for group worship.&lt;ref name="select.nytimes.com"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.spokesmanreview.com/breaking/story.asp?ID=3679|title=Spokesman Review: Sweet air of religious freedom could turn sour}}&lt;/ref&gt; The defendants on numerous occasions refused to answer or respond to letters, complaints, and requests for Ásatrú religious accommodations. They also refused to respond to complaints of religious discrimination. Ásatrú inmates were denied group worship and/or group study time as they did to other religions. They refused to hire a gothi to perform blots while providing priests for members of other religions. The Ásatrú inmates were also denied the right to have their own worship or study services.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.jus.state.nc.us/NCJA/07idetlegalport.doc |title=Portions of the Ásatrú Complaint}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In a join press release the [[Odinic Rite]], [[Ásatrú Alliance]] and [[Ásatrú Folk Assembly]] charged the [[FBI]] with violating its [[First Amendment to the United States Constitution|First Amendment]] rights to [[freedom of religion]], [[free speech]], and peaceful assembly by giving "False, misleading and deceptive information about our religion and its followers" in FBI's [[Project Megiddo]] report.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.cesnur.org/testi/FBI_007.htm |title=CESNUR&amp;nbsp;— Updates on FBI and Project Megiddo, November 10, 1999}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Anti-Defamation League]] publishes lists of [[fascist symbolism|symbols]] used by anti-Semitic groups.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.adl.org/hate_symbols/ |title=Hate On Display: A Visual Database of Extremist Symbols, Logos and Tattoos |publisher=ADL}}&lt;/ref&gt; Included in these publications are several [[Germanic paganism|Germanic pagan]] symbols that were sometimes used by the Nazis and some neo-Nazi groups, but have also always been used by non-racist pagan religions. Following an organised e-mail protest (mainly by the [[Odinic Rite]]), the ADL clarified that these symbols are not necessarily racist. It has since amended its publications to categorise these symbols as "pagan symbols co-opted by extremists".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.adl.org/hate_symbols/Pagan_graphics.asp |title=Hate On Display: A Visual Database of Extremist Symbols, Logos and Tattoos |publisher=ADL}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==United Kingdom==
{{main|Neopaganism in the United Kingdom}}
In the [[United Kingdom]], there have been occasional clashes between [[New Age travellers]] and authorities, such as the [[Battle of the Beanfield]] in 1985. There are also occasional charges of harassment against Neopagans such as the following examples.

In 1999, Dr Ralph Morse was appointed by the [[Pagan Federation]] as their first national youth manager. Following an article that appeared in the ''[[Independent on Sunday]]'' on 2 April 2000, Morse was summarily suspended from his post as Head of Drama, Theatre Arts and Media Studies at Shenfield High School in Essex.&lt;ref&gt;''Independent on Sunday'' articles dated 2 April and 9 April 2000 and The Foundation for Religious Freedom responding comment; CNS News Coverage (Foreign Bureaus)&lt;/ref&gt; Morse was subsequently fully investigated by the school and reinstated with a full retraction released to the media.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=New Religious Movements in the 21st Century |publisher=Routledge |location=New York |first=Phillip Charles |last=Lucas |coauthors=Robbins, Thomas |year=2004 |isbn=0415965764}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Modern Paganism in World Cultures: Comparative Perspectives |publisher=ABC-CLIO |location=[[Santa Barbara, California|Santa Barbara]] |first=Michael F |last=Strmiska |year=2005 |isbn=1851096086}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2006, members of "Youth 2000", a conservative Catholic organisation, on visit to Father Kevin Knox-Lecky of St Mary's church, [[Glastonbury]], attacked pagans by throwing salt at them and told them they "would burn in hell". Knox-Lecky apologized and said he would not invite the group again. The police warned two women and arrested one youth on suspicion of harassment.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.thesun.co.uk/article/0,,2-2006510299,00.html |title=Pagans are a-salt-ed |work=The Sun}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/religion/Story/0,,1939477,00.html |title=Catholic marchers turn on Glastonbury pagans |work=The Guardian}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2007, [[Brighton]] teaching assistant claiming she was fired for being a Wiccan.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.theargus.co.uk/news/generalnews/display.var.1272556.0.teaching_assistant_claims_she_was_sacked_for_being_a_witch.php The Argus: Teaching assistant claims she was sacked for being a witch]; [http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/england/sussex/6485487.stm BBC: White witch 'sacked for days off']; [http://www.thesun.co.uk/article/0,,2-2007130233,00.html The Sun: Sacked because I am a witch]; [http://www.personneltoday.com/Articles/2007/03/26/39888/pagan-teaching-assistant-brings-tribunal-claim-for-unfair.html Personnel Today: Pagan teaching assistant brings tribunal claim for unfair dismissal]; [http://education.guardian.co.uk/schools/story/0,,2040584,00.html The Guardian: Sacked witch 'told pupils she could teach them spells']. The case was settled out of court. [http://business.timesonline.co.uk/tol/business/law/article2047646.ece The Times: Weirdest workplace disputes]; [http://www.guardian.co.uk/uk_news/story/0,,2072045,00.html The Guardian: White witch settles job dispute with school]&lt;/ref&gt; A teacher at [[Shawlands Academy]] in [[Glasgow]] was denied time off with pay to attend Druid rites while members of other religions have their days of observance paid.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.pentaclemagazine.org/pn760/index.php?name=News&amp;file=article&amp;sid=1164 |title=Pentacle Magazine: I Want Pagan Holidays}}&lt;/ref&gt; A [[Neo-druidism|Neo-druid]] group from [[Weymouth, Dorset]] was molested by threats and abuse.&lt;ref&gt;Cited examples are a dead bird with a noose around its neck with an attached paper saying "Die Witches". [http://www.thisisdorset.net/display.var.1267293.0.pagans_suffer_ritual_abuse.php Dorset Echo: Pagans suffer ritual abuse]&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[University of St Andrews]] in [[Scotland]] have since 2006 allowed equal rights to The St Andrews Pagan Society, but under some strict rules.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/newspapers/sunday_times/scotland/article676124.ece |title=The Times: University allows pagans to hold rituals}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Greece==
In [[Separation of church and state#Greece|modern day Greece]], the [[Greek Orthodox Church]] has the status of [[state religion]], and consequently, alternative religions such as [[Hellenic Neopaganism]] may be subject to discrimination.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/main.jhtml?xml=/news/2004/05/08/wgods08.xml |title=The Telegraph: Modern Athenians fight for the right to worship the ancient Greek gods}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Greek Law No 1363/38, with amendment Law No. 1672/39: "Anyone engaging in [[proselytism]] shall be liable to imprisonment and a fine between 1,000 and 50,000 [[drachma]]s; he shall, moreover be subject to [[police]] supervision for a period of between six months and one year to be fixed by the court when convicting the offender." The second law requires anybody that is not an [[Eastern Orthodox Church|Orthodox]] Christian to obtain a "church license" from both the Ministry of Education and Religious Affairs and the local Orthodox bishops, but only the Orthodox Church, [[Judaism]] and [[Islam]] are recognized as "legal persons of public law." According to a press release from ''The Supreme Council of Gentile Hellenes'' there have been threats against the life of its members and a book store burning.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ysee.gr/index.php?type=d&amp;f=love&amp;lid=l4 |title=Χριστιανικοί διωγμοί κατά των Ελλήνων}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''The Greek Society of Attic Friends'', which state that it has 40,000 members, has been unsuccessful when they asked for recognition as a legal religion and were denied the right to build a temple in [[Athens]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.widdershins.org/vol10iss4/09.htm|title=Ongoing Persecution of Pagans in Modern Greece}}&lt;/ref&gt; and to use existing temples for worship.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.theage.com.au/news/travel/modern-pagans-worship-illegally-in-athens/2007/01/22/1169330798194.html |title=The Age: Modern pagans worship illegally in Athens}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2006 an Athens court ordered the worship of the old Greek gods to be unbanned. Father Eustathios Kollas, head of the community of Greek priests, said: "They are a handful of miserable resuscitators of a degenerate dead religion who wish to return to the monstrous dark delusions of the past." The followers of Ancient Greek religion now prepare to push for full recognition.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/international/story/0,,1767802,00.html |title=The Guardian: Greek gods prepare for comeback}}&lt;/ref&gt; So far they do not have the right to perform baptisms, marriages or funerals.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/6285397.stm |title=BBC: Ancient Greek gods' new believers}}&lt;/ref&gt; They are opposed by the Greek Orthodox church.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/g2/story/0,,2003096,00.html |title=The Guardian: By Zeus!}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.iht.com/articles/ap/2007/01/21/europe/EU-GEN-Greece-Ancient-Gods.php |title=International Herald Tribune: Zeus honored by modern pagans in ceremony in Athens}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Australia==
In 2003, Olivia Watts charged the mayor of the [[City of Casey]], [[Victoria (Australia)|Victoria]], Rob Wilson, as violating the [[Racial and Religious Tolerance Act 2001]] after he issued a press release in June of that year titled "Satanic cult out to take over Casey", in which Watts was mentioned by name. During a hearing on [[12 August]] [[2004]] in the [[Victorian Civil and Administrative Tribunal]], Watts said that after the press release, she suffered vandalism to her property and an assault at her home, in addition to general "hatred, contempt and revulsion". On [[13 August]], it was revealed in tribunal that the matter had been settled overnight, and Wilson read a statement acknowledging that Watts was not a Satanist and expressing "regret for any hurt felt by Ms Watts in consequence of his press release".&lt;ref name="age224"&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.theage.com.au/articles/2004/08/12/1092102595224.html |title=Tribunal hears claims of Satanic cult |work=The Age |first=Jamie |last=Berry |date=[[2004-08-13]] |accessdate=2007-08-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="ss279"&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.saltshakers.org.au/html/P/20/B/279/ |title=Rob Wilson VCAT case&amp;nbsp;— statement |work=Salt Shakers |first=Jenny |last=Stokes |date=[[2004-08-14]] |accessdate=2007-08-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==South Africa==
The [http://www.paganrightsalliance.org/ South Africa's Pagan Rights Alliance] (SAPRA) in [[South Africa]] have voiced objections to the proposed ''Witchcraft Suppression Bill''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://africa.reuters.com/wire/news/usnL20806502.html |title=Reuters: S.Africa witches fight for rights}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{portalpar|Wicca}}
* [[Cutter v. Wilkinson]]
* [[Dettmer v. Landon]]
* ''[[The Burning Times]]''
* [[Christian views on magic]]
* [[Witch-hunt]]

==References==
{{reflist|2}}
{{refbegin}}
*[[Mattias Gardell]], ''[[Gods of the Blood]]'' (2003).
{{refend}}

==External links==
* [http://www.rassias.gr/9011.html Christian Persecutions Against The Hellenes]
* [http://www.greekgodslegal.co.uk/ Campaign to De-Criminalize the Worship of the Greek Gods in Greece]

{{Neopaganism}}{{Religious persecution}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Neopaganism, Discrimination Against}}
[[Category:Neopaganism|Discrimination]]
[[Category:Minority rights]]
[[Category:Religion and politics]]
[[Category:Wicca|Discrimination]]
[[Category:Religious discrimination]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>