<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20151117180811|691104929" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="22041110" pageid="22041110" ns="0" title="Transgender rights movement"><revisions><rev timestamp="2015-11-22T17:05:22Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[File:A TransGender-Symbol Plain3.svg|thumb|A gender symbol commonly used to represent transgender people.]] [[File:Respect and Equality for All Trans People (4764133272) (2).jpg |thumb|Pride London, 3 July 2010.]] '''Transgender activism''' is generally determined to achieve antidiscrimination regarding housing, employment, and public accommodations, full access to education, health care, and appropriate identification documents, and open military service for trans individuals. This is by no means an exhaustive list. As social conditions evolve and public consciousness is raised, other concerns and issues emerge. As [[LGBT social movements]] gain momentum, it is important to recognize, for example, that not every Gay and Lesbian community recognizes the rights and needs of trans individuals.


==Statistics of Oppression==

In a survey conducted by [[National Center for Transgender Equality]] 
and [[National Gay and Lesbian Task Force]], called [[Injustice at Every Turn: A Report of the National Transgender Discrimination Survey]], respondents reported that 90% of them had experienced discrimination and harassment in the work place and at school. The trans community experiences rates of unemployment that are double the national average. Additionally, one out of every twelve trans women, and one out of every eight trans women of color, are violently murdered (the nature of these crimes is often perpetrated in such a way that attempts to dehumanize the victim).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Grant|first1=Jaime M.|last2=Mottet|first2=Lisa A.|last3=Tanis|first3=Justin|last4=Harrison|first4=Jack|last5=Herman|first5=Jody L.|last6=Keisling|first6=Mara|title=Injustice at Every Turn: A Report of the National Transgender  Discrimination Survey|url=http://www.thetaskforce.org/downloads/reports/reports/ntds_full.pdf|publisher=National Center for Transgender Equality  and National Gay and Lesbian Task Force}}&lt;/ref&gt; (For more details refer to [[Transgender inequality]]).


==History of the Movement==

Identifying the boundaries of a trans movement has been a matter of some debate. Conventionally, evidence of a codified political identity emerges in 1952, when Virginia Prince, a male [[crossdresser]], along with others, launched ''Transvestia: The Journal of the American Society for Equality in Dress.''&lt;ref name="glbtq1"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.glbtq.com/social-sciences/transgender_activism.html |title=&gt;&gt; social sciences &gt;&gt; Transgender Activism |publisher=glbtq |date= |accessdate=2009-11-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; This publication is considered by some to be the beginning of the transgender rights movement in the [[United States]].&lt;ref name="glbtq1"/&gt; In 1969, transgender and [[transsexual]] people played an integral part in the [[Stonewall Riots]], including [[Sylvia Rae Rivera]], a transsexual who was an instigator in the uprising. Rivera continued to be an advocate for transgender rights until her death in 2002.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.glbthistorymonth.com/glbthistorymonth/2006/bio.cfm?LeaderID=4 |title=GLBT History Month |publisher=GLBT History Month |date= |accessdate=2009-11-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; After Stonewall, awareness of transsexuality grew considerably. Support groups for male cross-dressers were common in the 1970s and 80s. In the 1980s female to male ([[transman|FTM]]) transsexuality became common.&lt;ref name="glbtq2"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.glbtq.com/social-sciences/transgender_activism,3.html |title=&gt;&gt; social sciences &gt;&gt; Transgender Activism |publisher=glbtq |date= |accessdate=2009-11-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
Contrary to these sociohistorical boundaries, [[Leslie Feinberg]] explodes the boundaries of trans activism by extending the history of the movement back to antiquity, and broadening the community to form partnerships with all people who are oppressed by the apparatus of capitalism. According to Feinberg, 

''As trans people, we have a history of resistance of which we should be proud. Trans warriors stood up to the slave-owners, the feudal landlords, and the capitalist bosses. Today, as trans warriors we are joining the movement for a just society in greater and greater numbers. By raising the demands of our trans movement within the larger struggle for change, we are educating people about our oppression, winning allies, and shaping the society we’re trying to bring into being.''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Feinberg|first1=Leslie|title=Transgender Warriors: Making History from Joan of Arc to RuPaul|date=1996|publisher=Beacon Press|location=Boston|page=128}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1992 Leslie Feinberg printed and circulated a pamphlet titled, [[“Transgender Liberation: A Movement Whose Time Has Come”]]. Feinberg’s pamphlet begins by calling on the trans community to compose their own definitions, invoking language as a tool that unites people divided by oppression. From here, Feinberg traces the emergence of oppression imposed by the ruling class by means of institutions. These institutions, run by the elite, enforce a gender binary at the expense of communal societies that encouraged liberal gender expression. Women were devalued and effeminacy was disparaged to promote patriarchal economic privilege. According to Feinberg, the gender binary is a contrivance of Western civilization. Having acknowledged this, Feinberg encourages all humans to reclaim the natural continuum of gender expression that identifies trans individuals as sacred. Feinberg concludes by empowering the working class to liberate themselves from the ruling class, which can be achieved by directing the labor of marginalized groups towards the common goal of revolution.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Feinberg|first1=Leslie|title=Transgender Liberation: A Movement Whose Time Has Come|date=1992|publisher=World View Forum}}&lt;/ref&gt; 


==Key Events==

[[File:Catlin - Dance to the berdache.jpg | thumb | Drawn while on the Great Plains, among the Sac and Fox Indians, the sketch depicts a ceremonial dance to celebrate the two-spirit person.  George Catlin (1796-1872), Dance to the Berdache. ]] In 1820s Rocky Mountains, a raid on a village of the Crow Indian tribe resulted in the death of a young man, and his sister, Pine Leaf, vowed that she would never marry until after she had killed a hundred of her enemies. Pine Leaf was recognized by her tribe as [[berdache]] or [[two-spirit]], a gender-variant individual who was often regarded with deep spiritual connections and tribal authority. She served on numerous war parties, and legend has it that one man, [[Jim Beckwourth]], a former slave, asked for her hand in marriage. She immediately declined, but upon being pressed further she responded that she would marry him just as soon as the pine leaves turn yellow.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Roscoe|first1=Will|title="Strange Country This: Images of Berdaches and Warrior Women," in Living the Spirit: A Gay American Indian Anthology|date=1988|publisher=St. Martin's Press|location=New York|page=(48-76), 67-69}}&lt;/ref&gt;


On December 31, 1993, a [[trans man]] [[Brandon Teena]] was murdered in [[Nebraska]] along with two of his friends. This murder was documented in the 1999 movie ''[[Boys Don't Cry (film)|Boys Don't Cry]]'' starring [[Hilary Swank]] as Brandon Teena.&lt;ref name="glbtq2"/&gt; In 2005, the movie ''[[Transamerica (film)|Transamerica]]'' told the story of a male to female transsexual preparing for gender reassignment surgery and traveling across the United States with her bisexual son. 

[[Transgender Day of Remembrance]], an annual ceremony to commemorate those who lost their lives due to their gender identity, was first held in 1999 following the murder of [[Rita Hester]] in 1998. The "Remembering our Dead" web project was also set up in 1999.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rememberingourdead.org/day/ |title=Transgender Day of Remembrance |publisher=Rememberingourdead.org |date=2005-11-20 |accessdate=2009-11-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In June of 2012 [[CeCe McDonald]] was wrongfully imprisoned for having defended herself against neo-nazi attackers with a pair of scissors, which resulted in the death of one of her assailants. Her story was publicized by a [[GLAAD Media Award]] winning article in [[Ebony.com]]. [[Laverne Cox]], openly trans actress on [[Orange Is the New Black]], launched a campaign to raise consciousness of cruel prison conditions for incarcerated trans individuals and rallied to free CeCe. After serving for 19 months, she was released January 2014.

[[File:Left OUT 04 HRC Betrayed all of us.jpg | thumb | Left OUT Party Two signs summarize the feelings of protestors. ]] On March 26-27, 2013, LGBT activists gathered at the Supreme Court in Washington, D.C. to support marriage equality, but in the midst of these demonstrations one speaker was asked to edit their proceedings to conceal their trans identity, and the trans community was asked to lower their pride flags. This incident follows years of tension between activist groups, namely [[Human Rights Campaign]] and the trans community, because the trans community is often neglected or blatantly excluded from events and political consideration. The incident resulted in a backlash and public criticism by the trans community. In response, activists groups apologized for the incident, and in 2014 HRC promised to energize efforts for promoting trans rights.

[[File:Pronouns.jpg | thumb | ]] In March of 2014 [[RuPaul’s Drag Race]] offended the trans community with a number of slurs, such as the phrase “You’ve got she-male” and “tranny,” as well as a segment that exploited trans issues and made a spectacle of [[passing]]. Trans activists asked RuPaul to redirect the show in a manner that is respectful of the trans community. This call for sensitivity was met with resistance as the issue was reframed as the result of people’s hypersensitivity and the unfair policing of language. Less than a decade prior to this incident, Leslie Feinberg explains in the landmark publication, which mentions RuPaul in the title, [[Transgender Warriors: Making History from Joan of Arc to RuPaul]], that “being ‘politically correct’ means using language that respects other peoples’ oppressions and wounds.”&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Leslie|first1=Feinberg|title=Transgender Warriors: Making History from Joan of Arc to RuPaul|date=1996|publisher=Beacon Press|location=Boston|page=ix}}&lt;/ref&gt; Two weeks later, [[Logo]] producers issued an apology.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Molloy|first1=Parker Marie|title=RuPaul's Drag Race, Logo TV Apologize for Transphobic Slur|url=http://www.advocate.com/politics/transgender/2014/04/14/rupauls-drag-race-logo-tv-apologize-transphobic-slur|website=Advocate.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; Since then, past contestants, [[Carmen Carrera]] and [[Monica Beverly-Hills]] have come out publicly about their ongoing struggles for acceptance and the damage that is perpetuated by oppressive terminology and insensitive use of pronouns.

In Florida in March of 2015, Representative Frank Artiles (R-Miami) proposed House Bill 583, which would ensure that individuals who enter public facilities such as bathrooms or locker rooms designated for those who are of the “other biological sex” could be jailed for up to 60 days. Artiles claims that it was proposed for the sake of public safety. Essentially, the bill would make it illegal for trans individuals to use public facilities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Wiesenthal|first1=Nicole|title=Controversial 'bathroom bill' leaves Florida transgender students, allies concerned|url=http://college.usatoday.com/2015/03/20/controversial-bathroom-bill-leaves-florida-transgender-students-allies-concerned/|website=USA Today}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== References ==
{{reflist}}

{{Transgender}}

[[Category:Activism]]
[[Category:LGBT history]]
[[Category:Transgender and transsexual culture]]
[[Category:Transgender rights]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>