<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20110901025155|447778746" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="22041110" pageid="22041110" ns="0" title="Transgender rights movement"><revisions><rev timestamp="2011-11-03T23:06:31Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">In 1952 Virginia Prince, a male-to-female [[transvestite]] (an outdated term for crossdresser, primarily used as a clinical diagnosis), along with other transgendered cross dressing people launched ''Transvestia: The Journal of the American society for Equality in Dress.''&lt;ref name="glbtq1"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.glbtq.com/social-sciences/transgender_activism.html |title=&gt;&gt; social sciences &gt;&gt; Transgender Activism |publisher=glbtq |date= |accessdate=2009-11-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; This publication was the beginning of the transgender rights movement in the [[United States]].&lt;ref name="glbtq1"/&gt; In 1969, transgendered and transsexual people played an integral part in the [[Stonewall Riots]], including [[Sylvia Rae Rivera]] a transsexual who was an instigator in the uprising. Rivera continued to be an advocate for transgender rights until her death in 2002.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.glbthistorymonth.com/glbthistorymonth/2006/bio.cfm?LeaderID=4 |title=GLBT History Month |publisher=GLBT History Month |date= |accessdate=2009-11-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; After Stonewall, awareness of transexuality grew considerably. Support groups for male cross-dressers were common in the 1970s and 80s. In the 1980s female to male ([[transman|FTM]]) transsexuality became common.&lt;ref name="glbtq2"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.glbtq.com/social-sciences/transgender_activism,3.html |title=&gt;&gt; social sciences &gt;&gt; Transgender Activism |publisher=glbtq |date= |accessdate=2009-11-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; Transsexual people have been victims of hate crimes. On December 31, 1993, a female to male transsexual [[Brandon Teena]] was murdered in [[Nebraska]] along with two of his friends. This murder was documented in the 2000 movie ''[[Boys Don't Cry (film)|Boys Don't Cry]]'' starring [[Hilary Swank]] as Brandon Teena.&lt;ref name="glbtq2"/&gt; In 2005, the movie ''[[Transamerica (film)|Transamerica]]'' told the story of a male to female transsexual preparing for sexual reassignment surgery and traveling across the United States with her bisexual son. The transgender day of remembrance to commemorate those who lost their lives due to their gender identity was first held in 1999 following the murder of Rita Hester in 1998. The "Remembering our Dead" web project was also set up in 1999.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rememberingourdead.org/day/ |title=Transgender Day of Remembrance |publisher=Rememberingourdead.org |date=2005-11-20 |accessdate=2009-11-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== References ==

{{reflist}}

[[Category:LGBT history]]
[[Category:Transgender]]


{{lgbt-stub}}</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>