<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20161120202659|750608211" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="22041110" pageid="22041110" ns="0" title="Transgender rights movement"><revisions><rev timestamp="2016-11-21T05:44:09Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[File:A TransGender-Symbol Plain3.svg|thumb|A gender symbol commonly used to represent transgender people.]] [[File:Respect and Equality for All Trans People (4764133272) (2).jpg |thumb|Pride London, 3 July 2010.]] The '''transgender rights movement''' is a movement determined to eliminate discrimination against [[transgender]] persons regarding housing, employment, public accommodations, education, and health care. It also seeks to eliminate violence against transgender persons. In some jurisdictions, transgender activism seeks to allow changes to identification documents to conform with a person's current [[gender identity]].

==Statistics of oppression==

In a survey conducted by [[National Center for Transgender Equality]]
and [[National Gay and Lesbian Task Force]], called "Injustice at Every Turn: A Report of the National Transgender Discrimination Survey", respondents reported that 90% of them had experienced discrimination and harassment in the work place and at school. The trans community experiences rates of unemployment that are double the national average. Additionally, one out of every twelve trans women, and one out of every eight trans women of color, are violently murdered (the nature of these crimes is often perpetrated in such a way that attempts to dehumanize the victim).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Grant|first1=Jaime M.|last2=Mottet|first2=Lisa A.|last3=Tanis|first3=Justin|last4=Harrison|first4=Jack|last5=Herman|first5=Jody L.|last6=Keisling|first6=Mara|title=Injustice at Every Turn: A Report of the National Transgender  Discrimination Survey|url=http://www.thetaskforce.org/downloads/reports/reports/ntds_full.pdf|publisher=National Center for Transgender Equality  and National Gay and Lesbian Task Force}}&lt;/ref&gt; (For more details refer to [[Transgender inequality]]).

==Oppression against people of color==

'''Transgender people of color''' often face an identity that is under speculation, suspicion, doubt, and policing. Those within the community are often left out  from the wealthy, able-bodied, American, and white experience that those in the non-trans community often focus on, and are subject to discrimination as a transgender and as a person of color.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title = What trans people of color fear after the Bruce Jenner media circus|url = http://fusion.net/story/125983/what-trans-people-of-color-fear-after-bruce-jenner-media-circus/|website = Fusion|accessdate = 2015-11-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some of the ways White transgender people have more [[White privilege|'''privilege''']] than those of their colored counterparts include racialized violence, better pay, better representation and benefits from the mainstream media movement. According to a National Transgender Discrimination survey, the combination of anti-transgender bias and individual racism results in transgender people of color being 6 times more likely to experience physical violence when interacting with the police compared to cisgender White people, two-thirds of LGBT homicide victims being transgender women of color, and a startling 78% attempt suicide.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title = 5 Ways White Transgender People Have Privilege Over Transgender People of Color|url = http://www.motherjones.com/politics/2015/06/transgender-women-disproportionately-targeted-violent-hate-crimes|website = BGD|accessdate = 2015-11-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title = Bustle|url = http://www.bustle.com/articles/87452-5-shocking-facts-about-transgender-suicide-and-violence-that-you-need-to-know|website = www.bustle.com|accessdate = 2015-11-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; The NCAVP survey also found that trans survivors were 1.7 times more likely to be the victims of sexual violence than cis-gender survivors.

According to the U.S. Current Population Survey and the National Committee on Pay Equity, Caucasian-Americans earn higher wages for the same work.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title = The Wage Gap by Gender &amp; Race Timeline History (White, Black, Hispanic, Men &amp; Women)|url = http://www.infoplease.com/ipa/A0882775.html|website = www.infoplease.com|accessdate = 2015-11-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; In " Beyond Stereotypes: Poverty in the LGBT Community," Brad Sears and Lee Badgett explain that transgender people are "four times as likely to have a household income under $10,000 and twice as likely to be unemployed" as most people in the U.S. Nearly a fifth of transgender people experience homelessness in their lifetimes, and 90 percent report having been discriminated against or harassed while on the job.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title = Bustle|url = http://www.bustle.com/articles/87452-5-shocking-facts-about-transgender-suicide-and-violence-that-you-need-to-know|website = www.bustle.com|accessdate = 2015-11-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; Transgender people of color are more likely to be poor, be homeless, or lack a college degree.&lt;ref name="BGD"/&gt;

The focus of the realms of trans visibility in pop culture and trans organizations has mostly been on white people, especially with [[Caitlyn Jenner]] joining the trans community.&lt;ref name="BGD"&gt;{{Cite web|title = 5 Ways White Transgender People Have Privilege Over Transgender People of Color|url = http://www.blackgirldangerous.org/2015/07/5-ways-white-transgender-people-have-privilege-over-transgender-people-of-color/|website = BGD|accessdate = 2015-11-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History of the movement==

Identifying the boundaries of a trans movement has been a matter of some debate. Conventionally, evidence of a codified political identity emerges in 1952, when Virginia Prince, a male [[crossdresser]], along with others, launched ''Transvestia: The Journal of the American Society for Equality in Dress.''&lt;ref name="glbtq1"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.glbtq.com/social-sciences/transgender_activism.html |title=&gt;&gt; social sciences &gt;&gt; Transgender Activism |publisher=glbtq |date= |accessdate=2009-11-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; This publication is considered by some to be the beginning of the transgender rights movement in the [[United States]].&lt;ref name="glbtq1"/&gt; In 1969, transgender and [[transsexual]] people played an integral part in the [[Stonewall Riots]], including [[Sylvia Rae Rivera]], a transsexual who was an instigator in the uprising. Rivera continued to be an advocate for transgender rights until her death in 2002.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.glbthistorymonth.com/glbthistorymonth/2006/bio.cfm?LeaderID=4 |title=GLBT History Month |publisher=GLBT History Month |date= |accessdate=2009-11-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; After Stonewall, awareness of transsexuality grew considerably. Support groups for male cross-dressers were common in the 1970s and 80s. In the 1980s female to male ([[transman|FTM]]) transsexuality became common.&lt;ref name="glbtq2"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.glbtq.com/social-sciences/transgender_activism,3.html |title=&gt;&gt; social sciences &gt;&gt; Transgender Activism |publisher=glbtq |date= |accessdate=2009-11-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Contrary to these sociohistorical boundaries, [[Leslie Feinberg]] explodes the boundaries of trans activism by extending the history of the movement back to antiquity, and broadening the community to form partnerships with all people who are oppressed by the apparatus of capitalism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Feinberg|first1=Leslie|title=Transgender Warriors: Making History from Joan of Arc to RuPaul|date=1996|publisher=Beacon Press|location=Boston|page=128}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1992 Leslie Feinberg printed and circulated a pamphlet titled "Transgender Liberation: A Movement Whose Time Has Come". Feinberg's pamphlet begins by calling on the trans community to compose their own definitions, invoking language as a tool that unites people divided by oppression. From here, Feinberg traces the emergence of oppression imposed by the ruling class by means of institutions. These institutions, run by the elite, enforce a gender binary at the expense of communal societies that encouraged liberal gender expression. Women were devalued and effeminacy was disparaged to promote patriarchal economic privilege. According to Feinberg, the gender binary is a contrivance of Western civilization. Having acknowledged this, Feinberg encourages all humans to reclaim the natural continuum of gender expression that identifies trans individuals as sacred. Feinberg concludes by empowering the working class to liberate themselves from the ruling class, which can be achieved by directing the labor of marginalized groups towards the common goal of revolution.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Feinberg|first1=Leslie|title=Transgender Liberation: A Movement Whose Time Has Come|date=1992|publisher=World View Forum}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Key events==
[[File:Beckwourth pine leaf11.jpg | thumb|Idealized illustration of "Pine Leaf", possibly identified with [[Woman Chief]], from [[James Beckwourth]]'s autobiography]] In the 1820s [[Rocky Mountains]], a raid{{by whom|date=April 2016}} on a village of the [[Crow Nation]] resulted in the death of a young man; his sibling, Pine Leaf, vowed that she would never marry until she had killed a hundred of her enemies. Pine Leaf was recognized by her tribe as [[two-spirit]], a gender-variant individual who may have spiritual gifts and the potential for authority and leadership in the community. She served in numerous war parties, and legend has it that one man, [[Jim Beckwourth]], a former slave, asked for her hand in marriage. She immediately declined, but upon being pressed further she responded that she would marry him just as soon as the pine leaves turn yellow.&lt;ref name=denig&gt;Edwin T. Denig: ''Five Indian Tribes at the Upper Missouri'', University of Oklahoma Press, Norman, 1961, p. 195–200&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Jenkins341&gt;{{cite encyclopedia|last=Jenkins |first= Jennifer L. |editor1-first= Gretchen M.|editor1-last=Bataille|editor2-first=Laurie |editor2-last=Lisa |encyclopedia=Native American Women: A Biographical Dictionary |title=Woman Chief |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=9eaSAgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA341&amp;dq=%22Woman+Chief%22+Crow&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=J0m0VKyXHMT6ggS7_YGQBA&amp;ved=0CBwQ6AEwADgK#v=onepage&amp;q=%22Woman%20Chief%22%20Crow&amp;f=false |access-date= January 12, 2014|year= 2001|publisher=Routledge|isbn= 1135955875 |page= 341}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On December 31, 1993, a [[trans man]] named [[Brandon Teena]] was murdered in [[Nebraska]] along with two of his friends. This murder was documented in the 1999 movie ''[[Boys Don't Cry (film)|Boys Don't Cry]]'' starring [[Hilary Swank]] as Brandon Teena.&lt;ref name="glbtq2"/&gt; In 2005, the movie ''[[Transamerica (film)|Transamerica]]'' told the story of a male to female transsexual preparing for gender reassignment surgery and traveling across the United States with her bisexual son.

[[Transgender Day of Remembrance]], an annual ceremony to commemorate those who lost their lives due to their gender identity, was first held in 1999 following the murder of [[Rita Hester]] in 1998. The "Remembering our Dead" web project was also set up in 1999.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rememberingourdead.org/day/ |title=Transgender Day of Remembrance |publisher=Rememberingourdead.org |date=2005-11-20 |accessdate=2009-11-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In June 2012 [[CeCe McDonald]] was wrongfully imprisoned for having defended herself against neo-nazi attackers with a pair of scissors, which resulted in the death of one of her assailants. Her story was publicized by a [[GLAAD Media Award]] winning article in [[Ebony.com]]. [[Laverne Cox]], openly trans actress on [[Orange Is the New Black]], launched a campaign to raise consciousness of cruel prison conditions for incarcerated trans individuals and rallied to free CeCe. After serving for 19 months, she was released January 2014.

[[File:Left OUT 04 HRC Betrayed all of us.jpg | thumb|Left OUT Party Two signs summarize the feelings of protestors.]] On March 26–27, 2013, LGBT activists gathered at the Supreme Court in Washington, D.C. to support marriage equality, but in the midst of these demonstrations one speaker was asked to edit their proceedings to conceal their trans identity, and the trans community was asked to lower their pride flags. This incident follows years of tension between activist groups, namely [[Human Rights Campaign]] and the trans community, because the trans community is often neglected or blatantly excluded from events and political consideration. The incident resulted in a backlash and public criticism by the trans community. In response, activists groups apologized for the incident, and in 2014 HRC promised to energize efforts for promoting trans rights.

In Florida in March 2015, Representative Frank Artiles (R-Miami) proposed House Bill 583, which would ensure that individuals who enter public facilities such as bathrooms or locker rooms designated for those who are of the "other biological sex" could be jailed for up to 60 days. Artiles claims that it was proposed for the sake of public safety. Essentially, the bill would make it illegal for trans individuals to use public facilities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Wiesenthal|first1=Nicole|title=Controversial 'bathroom bill' leaves Florida transgender students, allies concerned|url=http://college.usatoday.com/2015/03/20/controversial-bathroom-bill-leaves-florida-transgender-students-allies-concerned/|website=USA Today}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== In pop culture ==
Many celebrities have spoken out in support of transgender rights and often in conjunction with overall support for the LGBTQ community. Numerous celebrities voice such support for the Human Rights Campaign, including Archie Panjabi, Lance Bass, Tituss Burgess, Chelsea Clinton, George Clooney, Tim Cook, Jesse Tyler Ferguson, Sally Field, Lady Gaga, Whoopi Goldberg, Anne Hathaway, Jennifer Hudson, Caitlyn Jenner, Jazz Jennings, Elton John, Cyndi Lauper, Jennifer Lopez, Demi Lovato, Natasha Lyonne, Ellen Page, Brad Pitt, Geena Rocero, Bruce Springsteen, Jeffrey Tambor, Charlize Theron, Miley Cyrus, and Lana Wachowski.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.hrc.org/hrc-story/celebrity-supporters|title=Celebrity Supporters {{!}} Human Rights Campaign|last=Campaign|first=Human Rights|website=Human Rights Campaign|access-date=2016-11-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.looktothestars.org/charity/human-rights-campaign|title=Human Rights Campaign: Celebrity Supporters|website=Look to the Stars|access-date=2016-11-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.hrc.org/blog/watch-49-celebrities-honor-49-victims-of-orlando-tragedy-in-new-ryan-murphy|title=49 Celebrities Honor 49 Victims of Orlando Tragedy {{!}} Human Rights Campaign|last=Campaign|first=Human Rights|website=Human Rights Campaign|access-date=2016-11-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.hrc.org/resources/celebrities-come-out-for-equality-in-2015|title=Celebrities Come Out for Equality in 2015 {{!}} Human Rights Campaign|last=Campaign|first=Human Rights|website=Human Rights Campaign|access-date=2016-11-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Orange Is the New Black actress Laverne Cox has been particularly outspoken about the importance of transgender rights. Being transgender herself, Cox has experienced firsthand the issues that surround those who are transgender and often uses her own story to promote the movement for transgender rights.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://time.com/132769/transgender-orange-is-the-new-black-laverne-cox-interview/|title=TIME Cover Story: Interview With Trans Icon Laverne Cox|last=Steinmetz|first=Katy|website=TIME.com|access-date=2016-11-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; She sees her fame as an opportunity to bring awareness to causes that matter and that her unique position legitimizes the transgender rights movement.&lt;ref&gt;BREEN, M. LAVERNE COX: THE MAKING 0F AN ICON. ''Advocate''. 1074, 52, Aug. 2014. {{ISSN|0001-8996}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Particularly, she believes that transgender individuals have been historically overlooked and sidelined not just socially, but in the fight for civil rights as well.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.businessinsider.com/laverne-cox-says-this-is-how-to-get-equal-trans-rights-2015-9|title=Laverne Cox says this one simple change will help give trans people equal rights|newspaper=Business Insider|access-date=2016-11-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; Cox acknowledges the progress that has been made for Gay rights, but that it is important to focus on transgender rights separately, seeing as it has historically been grouped together with other causes and used as an umbrella term.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/nico-machlitt/the-transgender-movement-is-taking-over_b_5974198.html|title=The Next Civil Rights Frontier: How the Transgender Movement Is Taking Over|last=University|first=Nico Machlitt Sophomore at Hofstra|date=2014-10-14|website=The Huffington Post|access-date=2016-10-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2014, Glamour magazine named Cox Woman of the Year in recognition of her activism.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2014/11/05/laverne-cox-glamour-magazine_n_6109726.html|title=Laverne Cox Named One Of Glamour Magazine's Women Of The Year|last=Post|first=James Nichols The Huffington|date=2014-11-05|website=The Huffington Post|access-date=2016-11-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In April 2015, Olympic gold medalist and reality TV star Bruce Jenner came out as transgender.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2015/01/29/bruce-jenner-transgender_n_6570738.html|title=Bruce Jenner Comes Out As Transgender|last=Editor|first=Cavan Sieczkowski Senior|last2=Strategy|first2=Content|date=2015-04-24|website=The Huffington Post|access-date=2016-11-19|last3=Post|first3=The Huffington}}&lt;/ref&gt; The news had been speculated for months leading up to the announcement, but still shocked the public and received considerable attention.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://abcnews.go.com/Entertainment/bruce-jenner-im-woman/story?id=30570350|title=Bruce Jenner: 'I'm a Woman'|last=News|first=A. B. C.|date=2015-04-27|website=ABC News|access-date=2016-11-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; Jenner expressed the desire to transition and to be known as Caitlyn Jenner and introduced herself for the first time on the cover of Vanity Fair.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.vanityfair.com/hollywood/2015/06/caitlyn-jenner-bruce-cover-annie-leibovitz|title=Caitlyn Jenner: The Full Story|last=Bissinger|first=Buzz|newspaper=HWD|access-date=2016-11-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; Jenner's transition has been documented by the short-lived reality television series titled ''I am Cait.''&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.eonline.com/news/662536/caitlyn-jenner-starring-in-new-e-docu-series-i-am-cait|title=Watch the First Promo for Caitlyn Jenner's New Docu-Series on E!|newspaper=E! Online|language=en-US|access-date=2016-11-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; Jenner was determined to make a difference and bring awareness to transgender rights, believing that telling her story can do so. Jenner did increase transgender visibility, however, her commentary and series were criticized for misrepresenting the struggles of the majority the trans community, who are much less privileged than her and face deeper problems.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.cnn.com/2015/06/03/living/caitlyn-jenner-transgender-reaction-feat/index.html|title=What it's like to be transgender and not Caitlyn Jenner|last=CNN|first=Emanuella Grinberg|website=CNN|access-date=2016-11-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Other notable figures ==
Lili Elbe is noted as one of the first to undergo gender reassignment surgery.&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://oskicat.berkeley.edu/record=b20552215~S1|title=The transgender studies reader 2|date=2013-01-01|publisher=Routledge|isbn=9780415517720|editor-last=Stryker|editor-first=Susan|edition=1 Edition|location=New York, NY|editor-last2=Aizura|editor-first2=Aren Z.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Born in 1882, Elbe was a transgender painter from Denmark. Elbe had decided to commit suicide but decided against it when a doctor claimed that he could perform a gender reassignment surgery on Elbe. After undergoing four high risk experimental surgeries, Elbe died of post-op complications. Her story is depicted in the 2015 film, ''The Danish Girl''.&lt;ref name=":2"&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/2015/sep/28/gerda-einar-wergener-danish-girl-trans-painter|title=Gerda Wegener: 'The Lady Gaga of the 1920s'|last=Russell|first=Helen|date=2015-09-28|newspaper=The Guardian|language=en-GB|issn=0261-3077|access-date=2016-10-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":3"&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.biography.com/people/lili-elbe-090815|title=Lili Elbe Biography|last=|first=|date=|website=|publisher=|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/films/2016/04/14/the-tragic-true-story-behind-the-danish-girl/|title=The tragic true story behind The Danish Girl|newspaper=The Telegraph|access-date=2016-11-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Terminology ==
Terminology within the transgender community often changes and with it, connotations of certain terms can also change.

The broadest term used is "transgender," which typically refers to an individual who identifies with a gender different to the one assigned to them at birth. The term is used as an adjective and can be taken offensively is used as a noun. "Trans" is a shorthand for "transgender." The term "transgender man" refers to a transgender individual who identifies as a man and the term "transgender woman" refers to a transgender individual who identifies as a woman.&lt;ref name=":4"&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.transequality.org/issues/resources/transgender-terminology|title=Transgender Terminology|date=2015-01-23|newspaper=National Center for Transgender Equality|access-date=2016-10-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; These are acceptable and appropriate terms to use and many variations of the terms tend to have a negative connotation and are deemed offensive and even derogatory.&lt;ref name=":5"&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.glaad.org/reference/transgender|title=GLAAD Media Reference Guide - Transgender|date=2011-09-09|newspaper=GLAAD|access-date=2016-10-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":6"&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://ejce.berkeley.edu/geneq/resources/lgbtq-resources/definition-terms|title=Definition of Terms {{!}} Centers for Educational Justice &amp; Community Engagement|website=ejce.berkeley.edu|access-date=2016-10-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Significant backlash and controversy was generated when the term " trans* " was introduced into transgender terminology.&lt;ref name=":9"&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.pdxqcenter.org/bridging-the-gap-trans-what-does-the-asterisk-mean-and-why-is-it-used/|title=Bridging The Gap - Trans*:  What Does the Asterisk Mean and Why Is It Used?|date=2013-08-08|newspaper=Q Center|language=en-US|access-date=2016-10-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; The asterisk at the end of the term stems from the online practice wherein putting an asterisk at the end of a search subject includes search results that include any variation of the part before the asterisk. For example, if "trans*" were to be typed into a search engine, the search results would include topics such as ''transmission'', ''transfer'', ''transaction'', ''transgender'', etc.&lt;ref name=":7"&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.slate.com/blogs/outward/2014/01/10/trans_what_does_it_mean_and_where_did_it_come_from.html|title=What Does Trans* Mean, and Where Did It Come From?|last=Ryan|first=Hugh|date=2014-01-10|newspaper=Slate|language=en-US|issn=1091-2339|access-date=2016-10-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; The "trans*" term was intended to be an umbrella term to be more inclusive and encompass more identities within the transgender community. However, the term faced significant backlash for backfiring and being fundamentally oppressive. The criticism stems from the existence of an already inclusive term "transgender," and how many viewed the new "trans*" term as unnecessary given the preexisting inclusive term. Thus, many LGBTQ and particularly transgender rights activists denounce the use of the term&lt;ref name=":8"&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.transstudent.org/asterisk|title=Why We Used Trans* and Why We Don’t Anymore – Trans Student Educational Resources|website=www.transstudent.org|access-date=2016-10-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{Transgender}}

[[Category:Activism]]
[[Category:LGBT history]]
[[Category:Transgender and transsexual culture]]
[[Category:Transgender rights]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>