<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20041106113025|7290802" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="675582" pageid="675582" ns="0" title="New antisemitism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2004-11-10T09:40:34Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{NPOV}}

This article is concerned with '''Modern [[anti-Semitism]]''', roughly covering the period from right after World War II to the present.

== The Holocaust ==
The most horrific manifestation of anti-Semitism this century, subsequent to the rise of [[right wing|far-right]] ideologies in Europe, led to the "Jewish holocaust" during [[World War 2|World War II]], in which millions of Jews in Europe were systematically murdered. See [[Holocaust]], [[Warsaw Ghetto]], and [[Protest of Zofia Kossak-Szczucka]].

=== Holocaust denial ===
[[Holocaust revisionism|Holocaust revisionists]] often claim that "the Jews" or a "Zionist conspiracy" is responsible for the exaggeration or wholesale fabrication of the events of the [[Holocaust]]. Critics of such revisionism point to an overwhelming amount of physical and historical evidence that supports the mainstream historical view of the Holocaust. See the main article on [[Holocaust denial]].

== Anti-Semitism in modern-day nations ==
Anti-Semitism in the Eastern European countries is in decline recently. There are still
strong anti-semitic views in parts of the population, however the public anti-semitism is less frequent. In Russia it has been dominated by racism against people with darker skin from Caucasus region. In Poland one of leading anti-semitic priests: Henryk Jankowski has been removed from his office. In Poland and Germany ultra-right political parties has grown 
stronger however anti-semitism in their language has been replaced by generic xenophobia.

While in a decline since the 1940s, there is still anti-Semitism in the United States of America as well, although acts of violence are quite rare. The 2001 survey by the [[Anti-Defamation League]] reported 1432 acts of anti-Semitism in the United States that year. The figure included 877 acts of harassment, including verbal intimidation, threats and physical assaults ([http://www.adl.org/PresRele/ASUS_12/4057_12.asp]).

== The new anti-Semitism (Overview) ==
In recent years some scholars of religion and many Jewish groups, have noted what they describe as '''the new anti-Semitism.''' In this view, core themes of the new anti-Semitism include:
*Criticism of Zionism using terms that equate Jews with Nazis
*Editorial cartoons which portray Israelis in the same way that Nazi cartoonists portrayed Jews
*The censorship of works or participation by Jewish scholars from international conferences
*Harsh and repeated criticism of the State of Israel that is not made towards other nations for similar actions (an accusation of a double standard)
*Straw-man attacks, in which it is said that Jews claim that all criticism of Israel is anti-Semitism. This claim is then used to criticise Jewish groups as unreasonable. However, no Jewish groups hold such a position.

The term '''The New Antisemitism''' was first given to the wave of antisemitic attacks which bursted in [[Europe]] on [[2002]]. The attacks included hot verbal attacks against Israelis and Jews, delegitimation of Israel's right to exist and series of violent attacks (beating Rabbis, burning synagogues and vandalizing cemeteries) against Jews and supporters of Israel. Those attacks were explained on the ground of the [[Israeli-Palestinian conflict]], and many of them were commited by Muslim extremeists and [[Islamist]]s in Europe. The wave of New Antisemitism also included antisemitic [[cartoon]]s demonizing the Jews or Israel, and allegations on Israeli atrocities which later turned out to be false. The most notable case of false allegation was the [[Jenin massacre]] allegation which claimed that Israel massacred 500-3000 innocent Palestinians in [[Jenin]] during [[Operation Defensive Shield]]. Two weeks after the press was promoting the Jenin massacre allegation, [[Human rights]] group admited that no massacre took place in Jenin and lowered the death toll to 56 people, many of whom were militants. The Jenin massacre story sparked waves of anti-Israeli protests and violent attacks against Jews in Europe, and therefore regarded by many Jews as the first major [[blood libel]] of the New Antisemitism.

== Anti-Semitism and anti-Zionism ==
[[Anti-Zionism]] is a term that has been used to describe several very different political and religious points of view (both historically and in current debates) all expressing some form of opposition to [[Zionism]]. A large variety of commentators - politicians, journalists, academics and others - believe that criticisms of Israel and Zionism are often disproportionate in degree and unique in kind, and attribute this to anti-Semitism. In turn, critics of this view believe that associating anti-Zionism with anti-Semitism is intended to stifle debate, deflect attention from valid criticism, and taint anyone opposed to Israeli actions and policies. This subject is discussed in the main article on [[Anti-Zionism]].

== Manifestions of the New Antisemitism ==

=== Forms of discrimination ===
In his article [http://frontpagemag.com/Articles/ReadArticle.asp?ID=12191 Human Rights and the New Anti-Jewishness], [[Irwin Cotler]], the new Minister of Justice for Canada, writes:

:In a word, classical or traditional anti-Semitism is the discrimination against, or denial of, the right of Jews to live as equal members of a free society; the new anti-Semitism—incompletely, or incorrectly, [referred to] as "[[anti-Zionism]]"... —involves the discrimination against, denial of, or assault upon the right of the Jewish people to live as an equal member of the family of nations. What is intrinsic to each form of anti-Semitism—and common to both—is discrimination. All that has happened is that it has moved from discrimination against Jews as individuals—a classical anti-Semitism for which there are indices of measurement (e.g., discrimination against Jews in education, housing, or employment)—to discrimination against Jews as people—a new anti-Semitism—for which one has yet to develop indices of measurement.
[[Image:FrenchCemetery103004-01.jpg|thumb|300px|right|Neo-Nazi defacement of a Jewish cemetery in France]]
Cotler noted six categories and thirteen indices of modern anti-Semitism:

*Genocidal anti-Semitism
** the public call for the destruction of Israel and the Jewish people 
*Political anti-Semitism
** the discrimination against, denial of, or assault upon the Jewish people's right to self-determination
**discrimination against the Jews as a people
**the "demonizing" of Israel
*Theological anti-Semitism
**the convergence of state-sanctioned Islamic anti-Semitism, which characterizes Jews, Judaism, let alone Israel, as the perfidious enemy of Islam
**cultural anti-Semitism
**European "hierarchical" anti-Semitism
*Denying Israel equality before the law 
** the singling out of Israel for differential, if not discriminatory, treatment amongst the family of nations
** the disenfranchisement of Israel in the international arena
*Economic anti-Semitism
** the extra-territorial application by Arab countries of an international restrictive covenant against corporations conditioning their trade with Arab countries on their agreement not to do business with Israel (secondary boycott)
** not doing business with another corporation which may be doing business with Israel (tertiary boycott)
** conditioning the trade with such corporations on neither hiring nor promoting Jews within the corporation
*State-sanctioned anti-Semitism 
** the state-sanctioned "culture of hate"

=== The European Union ===
Groups monitoring hatespeech and violence in the European Union have noted an upswing in attacks on Jewish people and Jewish institutions in many European countries, especially in France. Jews have been attacked, stabbed, beaten and threatened in large numbers; synagogues have been vandalized, desecrated and burned. Jewish cemetaries have been vandalized.

A number of political and social leaders in the [[European]] Union have become concerned with this phenomeon. As such, a report on this phenomenon was written at the ''Center for Research on Anti-Semitism'', at the [[Technische Universität Berlin]], Germany. This report was written on behalf of the ''European Monitoring Centre on Racism and Xenophobia'' (EUMC.) The February 2003 version of this report is available online.

According to a study by Pew Research Center, in some European countries there has been a recent decrease in some forms of anti-Semitism.

==== France ====

The Interior Minister of [[France]] has announced that the number of [[anti-Semitic]] attacks in France in [[2004]] is more than double that of the same period in [[2003]]. [http://www.reuters.com/newsArticle.jhtml?type=worldNews&amp;storyID=6090896&amp;section=news  (Reuters)]

=== Canada ===

* [[David Ahenakew]]
* [[Malcolm Azania]]
* [[Doug Christie]]
* [[Ernst Zundel]]

=== The United Nations ===
Many Jewish groups have been disappointed with the role of the United Nations in regards to the treatment of Jews; many Jewish groups and writers have stated that the actions of the United Nations have often implicitly condoned, or encouraged, anti-Semitism. (''more to come''.)

In a recent development, [[United Nations]] Secretary-General [[Kofi Annan]] stated on June 21, 2004, that "It is hard to believe that 60 years after the tragedy of the Holocaust, anti-Semitism is once again rearing its head. But it is clear that we are witnessing an alarming resurgence of these phenomena in new forms and manifestations. This time the world must not, cannot, be silent." Anan then asked U.N. member states to adopt a resolution to fight anti-Semitism, and stated that the UN's Commission on Human Rights must study and expose anti-Semitism in the same way that it fights bias against Muslims. Anan stated "Are not Jews entitled to the same degree of concern and protection?"

[http://www.thestar.com/NASApp/cs/ContentServer?pagename=thestar/Layout/Article_Type1&amp;c=Article&amp;cid=1087855809804&amp;call_pageid=968332188854&amp;col=968350060724], [http://www.jpost.com/servlet/Satellite?pagename=JPost/JPArticle/ShowFull&amp;cid=1087787670464]

=== Straw-man anti-Semitism ===
One common form of anti-Semitism is the statement that Jews claim that all criticism of the State of Israel is anti-Semitism. This claim is then used to criticise Jewish groups as unreasonable. 

However, no Jewish groups hold such a position. This position has never been held, in any form, by any of the modern [[Jewish denominations]]. In fact, on numerous occasions many Jewish groups have publicly criticised the policies of different Israeli governments. Further, these Jewish groups are aware of many criticism by non-Jewish groups, and have not considered the majority of these criticisms as anti-Semitic. Public statements by leaders of many Jewish groups explicitly state that disagreement with a policy or government of the State of Israel is not, of itself anti-Semitic. One popular understanding of this issue can be found in a statement by the Anti-Defamation League:

:"Criticism of particular Israeli actions or policies in and of itself does not constitute anti-Semitism. Certainly the sovereign State of Israel can be legitimately criticized just like any other country in the world. However, it is undeniable that there are those whose criticism of Israel or of "Zionism" is used to mask anti-Semitism." (Anti-Defamation League website.) 

In his [http://www.frontpagemagazine.com/Articles/ReadArticle.asp?ID=13590 speech]) given at Berkeley University on April 29, 2004, Law Professor at Harvard University Law School [[Alan Dershowitz]] said, in particular: "Show me a single instance where a major Jewish leader or Israeli leader has ever said that criticizing a particular policy of Israeli government is anti-Semitic. That's just something made up by Israel's enemies."

== Views and position on the New Antisemitsm ==

=== Positions of Jewish groups on the new anti-Semitism ===
Tikkun magazine, an American Jewish magazine which is written from the perspective of the political left, ran a series of article on the resurgence of anti-Semitism across the world.
* [http://www.tikkun.org/magazine/index.cfm/action/tikkun/issue/tik0311/article/031111a.html The New Anti-Semitism, by Miriam Greenspan. Tikkun Magazine ]

The [[Anti-Defamation League]] stated that: "The events of September 11, the American campaign against terrorism and the Palestinian intifada against Israel have created a dangerous atmosphere in the Middle East and Europe, one that 'gives anti-Semitism and hate and incitement a strength and power of seduction that it has never before had in history.'"

=== Views of Natan Sharansky ===

Israeli political leader [[Natan Sharansky]] has suggested that anti-Semitism masquerading as anti-Zionism can be distinguished from legitimate criticism of Israel if it fails the "3D" test, as follows:

:The first D is the test of demonization. Whether it came in the theological form of a collective accusation of deicide or in the literary depiction of Shakespeare's Shylock, Jews were demonized for centuries as the embodiment of evil. Therefore, today we must be wary of whether the Jewish state is being demonized by having its actions blown out of all sensible proportion. For example, the comparisons of Israelis to Nazis and of the Palestinian refugee camps to Auschwitz -- comparisons heard practically every day within the "enlightened" quarters of Europe -- can only be considered anti-Semitic. Those who draw such analogies either do not know anything about Nazi Germany or, more plausibly, are deliberately trying to paint modern-day Israel as the embodiment of evil. 

:The second D is the test of double standards. For thousands of years a clear sign of anti-Semitism was treating Jews differently than other peoples, from the discriminatory laws many nations enacted against them to the tendency to judge their behavior by a different yardstick. Similarly, today we must ask whether criticism of Israel is being applied selectively. In other words, do similar policies by other governments engender the same criticism, or is there a double standard at work? It is anti-Semitism, for instance, when Israel is singled out by the United Nations for human rights abuses while tried and true abusers like China, Iran, Cuba, and Syria are ignored. Likewise, it is anti-Semitism when Israel's Magen David Adom, alone among the world's ambulance services, is denied admission to the International Red Cross. 

:The third D is the test of deligitimation. In the past, anti-Semites tried to deny the legitimacy of the Jewish religion, the Jewish people, or both. Today, they are trying to deny the legitimacy of the Jewish state, presenting it, among other things, as the last vestige of colonialism.  While criticism of an Israeli policy may not be anti-Semitic, the denial of Israel's right to exist is always anti-Semitic. If other peoples have a right to live securely in their homelands, then the Jewish people have a right to live securely in their homeland. 

=== Views of the Catholic Church ===
The International Catholic-Jewish Liaison Committee of the Catholic Church has recently spoken on this subject as well, stating that it embraces "the total rejection of anti-Semitism in all its forms, including [[anti-Zionism]] as a more recent manifestation of anti-Semitism. " [http://www.vatican.va/roman_curia/pontifical_councils/chrstuni/relations-jews-docs/rc_pc_chrstuni_doc_20040708_declaration-buenos-aires_en.html]


=== Books on the anti-Semitism ===
A number of book-length treatments about this subject have been published, including ''The New Anti-Semitism: The Current Crisis and What We Must Do About It'', Phyllis Chesler (Jossey-Bass, 2003); ''The Return of Anti-Semitism'' by Gabriel Schoenfeld, Encounter Books, 2003; and ''Never Again? The Threat of the New Anti-Semitism'' by Abraham Foxman, HarperSanFrancisco, 2003.

== References ==
* ''The World Must Know: The History of the Holocaust As Told in the United States Holocaust Memorial Museum'', Michael Berenbaum. Little Brown &amp; Co, 1993
* ''The War Against the Jews: 1933-1945'' Lucy S. Davidowicz. Bantam Doubleday Dell Pub, 1991
* ''Antisemitism in America'', Leonard Dinnerstein, Oxford Univ. Press, 1995
* Phyllis Chessler ''The New Anti-Semitism: The Current Crisis and What We Must Do About It'', Jossey-Bass, 2003
* ''The Holocaust Industry: Reflections on the Exploitation of Jewish Suffering'', Norman G. Finkelstein. Verso Books, 2001
*''Never Again? The Threat of the New Anti-Semitism'' by Abraham Foxman, HarperSanFrancisco, 2003
* ''Antisemitism in the New Testament'', Lillian C. Freudmann, University Press of America, 1994
* ''The Destruction of the European Jews'' Raul Hilberg. Holmes &amp; Meier, 1985. 3 volumes
* ''A New Antisemitism? Debating Judeophobia in 21st Century Britain'', Ed. Paul Iganski and Barry Kosmin. Profile Books, 2003
* ''Denying the Holocaust: The Growing Assault on Truth and Memory'' Deborah Lipstadt, 1994, Penguin
* Gabriel Schoenfeld ''The Return of Anti-Semitism'', Encounter Books, 2003
* ''Why the Jews? The Reasons for Antisemitism'' [[Dennis Prager]] and Joseph Telushkin, Simon &amp; Schuster, 1983
* ''Antisemitism: The Longest Hatred'', Robert S. Wistrich. Pantheon Books, 1992.

== External Links ==
* [http://www.adl.org/adl.asp The Anti-Defamation League]
* [http://www.ajc.org The American Jewish Committee]
* [http://www.ajcongress.org The American Jewish Congress]
* http://www.yahoodi.com/peace/selfhatred.html 
* [http://frontpagemag.com/Articles/ReadArticle.asp?ID=12191 Human Rights and the New Anti-Jewishness] by [[Irwin Cotler | Irwin Cotler, Minister of Justice for Canada]]
* [http://www.freeman.org/m_online/jan98/pipes.htm The New Anti-Semitism. Article by Daniel Pipes]
*[http://www.adl.org/presrele/Islme_62/4040_62.asp The New Anti-Semitism in Europe and The Middle East: Threat is "Potent and Very Real" ADL Leader Says in Major Address]
* [http://www.ajc.org/InTheMedia/Publications.asp?did=618 The New Anti-Semitism in Western Europe: American Jewish Committee]
* [http://www.adl.org/presrele/Islme_62/4040_62.asp The New Anti-Semitism in Europe and The Middle East: Anti-Defamation League]
* [http://christianactionforisrael.org/antiholo/new_anti2.html The New Anti-Semitism: Christian Action for Israel]
* [http://www.aish.com/jewishissues/middleeast/Anti-Globalization_The_New_Anti-Semitism.asp Anti-Globalization and the New Anti-Semitism: JewishWorld online magazine.]
* [http://www.thenation.com/doc.mhtml?i=20040202&amp;s=klug The Myth of the New Anti-Semitism by Brian Klug]
* [http://www.commentarymagazine.com/sharansky.html On Hating the Jews by Natan Sharansky]
* [http://www.us-israel.org/jsource/UN/unantisem.html Anti-Semitism in the United Nations by Morris B. Abram]
* [http://www.findarticles.com/cf_dls/m1061/6_113/87080283/p1/article.jhtml Israel and the anti-semites by Gabriel Schoenfeld]
* [http://www.antisemitism.org.il/myview/frontend/english/index.htm The Coordination Forum for Countering Anti-Semitism]
* [http://www.gush-shalom.org/archives/article286.html Anti-Semitism: A Practical Manual]
* [http://www.beitshalom.org/articulo.aspx?i=en-us&amp;c=54 "Anti-Semitism in the Church?"]
*[http://www.adl.org/presrele/Islme_62/4040_62.asp The New Anti-Semitism in Europe and The Middle East: Threat is "Potent and Very Real" ADL Leader Says in Major Address]
*[http://www.tikkun.org/magazine/index.cfm/action/tikkun/issue/tik0311/article/031111a.html The New Anti-Semitism, by Miriam Greenspan. Tikkun Magazine]

[[Category:Anti-Semitism]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>