<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20221119224823|1122814971" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="166029" pageid="166029" ns="0" title="Police brutality"><revisions><rev timestamp="2022-11-20T12:29:23Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|Use of excessive force by a police officer}}
{{Redirect|Excessive force}}
{{Multiple issues|
{{Very long|date=June 2020}}
{{Cleanup|date=April 2019|reason=Some entries are in broken English, lack specificity, or could use improvement in sentence structure or flow.}}
}}
[[File:Montreal police brutality protest.jpg|thumb|Police overuse of force at a Montreal protest.]]
{{Use dmy dates|date=November 2021}}
[[File:Police brutality in Egypt (4602240333).jpg|thumb|Nine police officers subduing a member of the public in Egypt]]
{{Police brutality topics sidebar|state=collapsed}}
'''Police brutality''' is the excessive and unwarranted [[use of force]] by [[law enforcement]] against an individual or a group. It is an extreme form of [[police misconduct]] and is a civil rights violation. Police brutality includes, but is not limited to, beatings, shootings, "improper takedowns, and unwarranted use of tasers."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Understanding Five Different Types of Police Brutality - Rhonda Hill Blog - Criminal Law |url=https://criminallaw.com/lawyer/rhonda-b-hill-chicago-il/blog/understanding-five-different-types-of-police-brutality |access-date=2022-05-01 |website=criminallaw.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Emesowum|first=Benedict|date=5 December 2016|title=Identifying Cities or Countries at Risk for Police Violence|journal=Journal of African American Studies|volume=21|issue=2|pages=269–281|doi=10.1007/s12111-016-9335-3|s2cid=151639366|issn=1559-1646}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{TOC limit|3}}

== History ==
The origin of modern policing can be traced back to 18th century [[France]]. By the 19th and early 20th centuries, many nations had established [[Police#History|modern police departments]]. Early records suggest that labor strikes were the first large-scale incidents of [[police brutality in the United States]], including events like the [[Great Railroad Strike of 1877]], the [[Pullman Strike]] of 1894, the [[Lawrence textile strike|Lawrence Textile Strike]] of 1912, the [[Ludlow massacre|Ludlow Massacre]] of 1914, the [[Steel strike of 1919|Great Steel Strike of 1919]], and the [[Hanapepe massacre|Hanapepe Massacre]] of 1924.

The term "police brutality" was first used in Britain in the mid-19th century, by ''[[The Puppet-Show]]'' magazine(a short-lived rival to ''[[Punch (magazine)|Punch]]'') in September 1848, when they wrote:&lt;blockquote&gt;Scarcely a week passes without their committing some offence which disgusts everybody but the magistrates. Boys are bruised by their ferocity, women insulted by their ruffianism; and that which brutality has done, perjury denies, and magisterial stupidity suffers to go unpunished. [...] And '''police brutality''' is becoming one of our most "venerated institutions!"&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite magazine |date=9 September 1848 |title=More Police Brutality |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=kbMOAAAAQAAJ&amp;pg=RA2-PA14 |magazine=The Puppet-Show |volume=2 |issue=27 |page=14}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The first use of the term in the American press was in 1872 when the ''[[Chicago Tribune]]''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |date=12 October 1872 |title=Police Brutality: A Prisoner was shamefully beaten by Officers, he was Kicked and Pounded in a Cell ---Probably Fatally Injured |work=Chicago Daily Tribune}}&lt;/ref&gt; reported the beating of a civilian who was under arrest at the Harrison Street Police Station.

In the United States, it is common for marginalized groups to perceive the police as [[oppression|oppressors]], rather than protectors or enforcers of the law, due to the statistically disproportionate number of minority incarcerations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Powers|first=Mary D.|editor=Winters, Paul A.|title=Policing the Police|year=1995|publisher=Greenhaven Press|location=San Diego|isbn=978-1-56510-262-0|pages=56–60|chapter=Civilian Oversight Is Necessary to Prevent Police Brutality}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Hubert Locke wrote:

&lt;blockquote&gt;When used in print or as the battle cry in a [[black power]] rally, police brutality can by implication cover several practices, from calling a citizen by his or her first name to death by a policeman's bullet. What the average citizen thinks of when he hears the term, however, is something midway between these two occurrences, something more akin to what the police profession knows as "alley court"—the wanton vicious beating of a person in custody, usually while [[handcuffs|handcuffed]], and usually taking place somewhere between the scene of the arrest and the [[Police station|station house]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|volume=44|publisher=J. Urb. L.|page=625|date=1966–1967|title=Police Brutality and Civilian Review Boards: A Second Look|author=Locke, Hubert G.|url=http://heinonlinebackup.com/hol-cgi-bin/get_pdf.cgi?handle=hein.journals/udetmr44&amp;section=45}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;!-- [[WP:NFCC]] violation: [[File:Kingbeating.jpg|thumb|Screenshots of [[Rodney King]] lying down and being beaten by [[Los Angeles Police Department|LAPD]] officers]] --&gt;
In March 1991, members of the [[Los Angeles Police Department]] (LAPD) beat an African American suspect, [[Rodney King]], during his arrest for drunk driving. A white civilian videotaped the assault. This incident led to extensive media coverage and criminal charges against several of the officers involved. In April 1992, hours after the four police officers involved were acquitted at trial, the [[Los Angeles riots of 1992]] commenced and resulted in 53 deaths, 2,383 injuries, more than 7,000 fires, damage to 3,100 businesses, and nearly $1 billion in financial losses. After facing a federal trial, two of the four officers were convicted and received 32-month prison sentences. The case was widely seen as a key factor in the reform of the Los Angeles Police Department.

== Examples ==
{{Main|List of cases of police brutality}}

=== Africa ===
[[File:Protesters at the endSARS protest in Lagos, Nigeria 74.jpg|thumb|[[End SARS]] is a decentralised social movement, and series of mass protests against police brutality in [[Nigeria]].]]

====Uganda====

Under president [[Idi Amin]], many Ugandan people were killed, including minority groups. Many others were tortured.{{Citation needed|date=June 2022}}

==== South Africa ====
{{See also|Marikana killings}}
Incidents of police brutality skyrocketed by 312% from 2011 to 2012 compared to 2001 to 2002, with only 1 in 100 cases leading to a conviction. There were also 720 deaths in police custody due to police action from 2011 to 2012.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Smith|first=David|date=22 August 2013|title=South Africa reports of police brutality more than tripled in the last decade|newspaper=[[The Guardian]]|url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/aug/22/south-africa-police-brutality-increase}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2015, as a result of police officers being accused of crimes such as rape, torture, and murder, the cost of civil liabilities claims were so great that there was concern the costs would strain the [[South African Police Service]] national budget. The police commissioner at the time, Riah Phiyega, blamed the large number of claims "on a highly litigious climate".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|date=1 October 2015|title=Police Brutality on Rise in South Africa: Officers Accused of Killing, Raping Citizens|website=[[International Business Times]]|url=http://www.ibtimes.com/police-brutality-rise-south-africa-officers-accused-killing-raping-citizens-2122712}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Police brutality has spread throughout [[Soweto]]. Nathaniel Julius was killed in Soweto by police officers from the El Dorado police station. He was a 16 year old boy with [[Down Syndrome]], and was shot because he didn't respond to the police officer calling him. This action was not warranted because Nathaniel didn't have any weapons on him and he was just walking from the store after buying biscuits. Two police officers were arrested over Julius' death on murder charges, after mass protests against this in the area. South African police are commonly accused of excessive force, with ten deaths attributed to police the same year (2020).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|date=29 August 2020|title=Nathaniel Julius: South Africa police arrested for killing teen|website=[[BBC News]]|url=https://www.bbc.com/news/world-africa-53958570}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Ethiopia ====
{{excerpt|Police brutality in Ethiopia}}
==== Egypt ====
Police brutality was a major contribution to the [[2011 Egyptian revolution]] and [[Khaled Said]]'s death, though little has changed since.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=What happened to reform? |newspaper=The Economist |url=https://www.economist.com/news/middle-east-and-africa/21574017-police-are-rotten-ever-what-happened-reform}}&lt;/ref&gt; One of the "demands" around which people decided to take to the streets in Egypt was "purging the Ministry of Interior" for its brutality and torture practices. After six months of reporting gang rape, a woman in Egypt is still seeking justice not only for herself, but also those who were witnesses in her favor and are jailed, tortured in pretrial custody. The lack of investigation into the Fairmont Hotel rape case of 2014 has also put the Egyptian authorities under condemnation. Reportedly, the prime witnesses of the case have been subjected to drug testing, virginity tests and publicly defamed, while their families suffer trauma.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.hrw.org/news/2021/02/08/justice-stalled-egypts-fairmont-rape-case|title=Justice Stalled in Egypt's 'Fairmont' Rape Case|access-date=8 February 2021|website=Human Rights Watch|date=8 February 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.reuters.com/article/us-egypt-rape-idUSKBN2962C5|title=Witness detentions cast shadow over Egyptian 'MeToo' movement|access-date=1 January 2021|website=Reuters|date=January 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Asia ===
==== Bangladesh ====

In May 2017, a man named Shamim Reja was killed by police in the [[Sonargaon]] police station. The victim's father claimed that his son was tortured in the police station as the police wanted [[Bangladeshi Taka]] (BDT) 600,000. Police investigated and the officer-in-charge Arup Torofar, SI Paltu Ghush, and ASP Uttam Prashad were found guilty as charged.&lt;ref name="bangladesh"&gt;{{cite web|title=Police Brutality and Corruption on Steep Rise|url=http://progressbangladesh.com/police-brutality-and-corruption-on-steep-rise/|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160304214455/http://progressbangladesh.com/police-brutality-and-corruption-on-steep-rise/|archive-date=4 March 2016|access-date=21 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 
In Shahbag, Bangladesh on 26 January 2017, hundreds of protesters against the Bangladesh India Friendship Power Company were taken into custody with extreme force by police officers. The protesters were struck by police officers and had a water cannon, tear gas, and baton charges used on them.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Khan Chandan|first1=Md Shahnawaz |date=2 February 2017 |title=Our Silence on Police Brutality |url=https://www.thedailystar.net/star-weekend/opinion/our-silence-police-brutality-1355386 |access-date=1 November 2018 |website=thedailystar.net}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====India====
{{See also|List of cases of police brutality in India}}
During India's independence struggle, protestors and activists were subject to Lathi charges and shootings. One such incident is recalled as the [[Jallianwala Bagh massacre]], where a crowd gathered to protest the [[Rowlatt act]] were indiscriminately fired at, on the orders of a British Officer, General Dyer with 200 causalities. &lt;ref&gt;{{Citation |title=9. The Roots and Resonance of the Jallianwala Bagh Massacre |date=1977-12-31 |url=http://dx.doi.org/10.1515/9780824887179-012 |work=Imperial Crime and Punishment |pages=168–190 |publisher=University of Hawaii Press |access-date=2022-11-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

During [[the emergency of 1975-1977]], several cases of Police Brutality were recorded, including the [[Rajan case]] on 31 March 1976.

On 23 January 2017, [[2017 pro-jallikattu protests|a pro-jallikattu silent protest]] in [[Tamil Nadu]] turned violent. The [[National Human Rights Commission]] consolidated reports that the police used violent methods without prior warning, including beatings and damaging private property, to disperse protesters in [[Chennai]]. There were widespread social media reports of police setting vehicles on fire.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Police excesses on jallikattu supporters in Chennai: NHRC issues notice to Tamil Nadu govt &amp;#124; Chennai News-Times of India|url=https://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/city/chennai/police-excesses-on-jallikattu-supporters-in-chennai-nhrc-issues-notice-to-tamil-nadu-govt/articleshow/56761447.cms|website=The Times of India}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|date=25 January 2017|title=Jallikattu: NHRC notice to Tamil Nadu government, police for 'excesses&amp;#8217|url=http://indianexpress.com/article/india/jallikattu-nhrc-notice-to-tamil-nadu-government-police-for-excesses/}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Jallikattu: Kamal Haasan, Others Tweet Video of Cop Setting An Auto on Fire|url=http://www.ndtv.com/tamil-nadu-news/video-of-cop-setting-auto-on-fire-allegedly-in-chennai-goes-viral-1651853|access-date=29 January 2017|publisher=Ndtv.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 15 December 2019 police authorities baton-charged students who were protesting against the controversial Citizenship Amendment Act at University Library of Jamia Milia University, New Delhi.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Yamunan|first=Sruthisagar|title=Delhi Police were 'uncontrollable' as they unleashed violence at Jamia Millia Islamia, students say|url=https://scroll.in/article/946933/delhi-police-were-uncontrollable-as-they-unleashed-violence-at-jamia-millia-islamia-students-say|access-date=29 August 2021|website=Scroll.in|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=India: Footage appears to show police attack on Jamia students|url=https://www.aljazeera.com/news/2020/2/16/india-footage-appears-to-show-police-attack-on-jamia-students|access-date=29 August 2021|website=www.aljazeera.com|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[baton charge|Lathi Charge]] is very well known in India for excessive use of force done by police during mass protests or riots.

==== Indonesia ====
[[Islamic extremists]] in Indonesia have been targeted by police as terrorists in the country. In many cases, they are either captured or killed. There are cases of police corruption involving hidden bank accounts and retaliation against journalists investigating these claims; one example occurred in June 2012 when Indonesian magazine ''[[Tempo (Indonesian magazine)|Tempo]]'' had journalist activists beaten by police. Separately, on 31 August 2013 police officers in Central Sulawesi province fired into a crowd of people protesting the death of a local man in police custody; five people were killed and 34 injured. The police's history of violence goes back to the military-backed [[Suharto]] regime (1967–1998) when Suharto seized power during an alleged coup and instituted an [[Indonesian killings of 1965–1966|anti-Communist purge]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Cop killers|newspaper=The Economist|url=http://www.economist.com/node/17419881}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Criminal investigations into human rights violations by the police are rare, punishments are light, and Indonesia has no independent national body to deal effectively with public complaints. [[Amnesty International]] has called on Indonesia to review police tactics during arrests and public order policing to ensure that they meet international standards.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Indonesia|url=https://www.amnesty.org/en/news/indonesia-must-end-impunity-police-violence-2012-04-25|access-date=2 October 2015|publisher=Amnesty International|archive-date=26 January 2013|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130126171319/http://www.amnesty.org/en/news/indonesia-must-end-impunity-police-violence-2012-04-25|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Malaysia====
During the [[Bersih]] protests, Malaysian police attacked protesters and killed one. Malaysian police also cane prisoners for several offences, including theft, drug dealing and molestation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.corpun.com/singfeat.htm|title=WORLD CORPORAL PUNISHMENT RESEARCH: JUDICIAL CANING IN SINGAPORE, MALAYSIA AND BRUNEI|website=www.corpun.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Philippines====
The discussions of police brutality in the Philippines were revived on 21 December 2020 when a civilian [[Philippine National Police|police]] officer Jonel Nuezca [[2020 Tarlac shooting|shot his two unarmed neighbors]] following an argument over an improvised noise maker known locally as [[PVC cannon|boga]] set up by the victim a day earlier.&lt;ref name=jn0024&gt;{{cite news|access-date=22 December 2020 |title= Cop in viral shooting video surrenders to Rosales police|url= https://www.pna.gov.ph/articles/1125332|work=[[Philippine News Agency]] }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=jn00012&gt;{{cite news|access-date=21 December 2020 |title=Cop shoots unarmed mother, son over 'boga' in Tarlac |url= https://www.rappler.com/nation/cop-shoots-unarmed-mother-son-over-boga-improvised-noisemaker-in-tarlac-december-2020|work= Rappler|quote=The shooting happened at 5:10 pm then was reported to the Paniqui police station at 5:30 pm. Nearly an hour later, at 6:19 pm, Nuezca surrendered to the Rosales police station in Pangasinan province. Paniqui police picked up Nuezca and now have him in their custody.}}&lt;/ref&gt; The incident sparked nationwide outrage and most news organizations linked the incident to the [[Philippine drug war|war on drugs]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|access-date=21 December 2020 |title= Rage and fury over cop's killing of mother and son: 'No license to kill'|url=https://www.rappler.com/nation/netizens-reaction-tarlac-cop-killing-december-2020 |work= Rappler}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|access-date=21 December 2020 |title= Maine Mendoza, Agot Isidro other celebrities concerned over cop's slaying of mother, son|url=https://mb.com.ph/2020/12/21/maine-mendoza-agot-isidro-other-celebrities-concerned-over-cops-slaying-of-mother-son/ |work= Manila Bulletin}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|access-date=22 December 2020 |title=A Brazen Police Shooting Caught on Video Sparks Anger in the Philippines |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2020/12/21/world/asia/philippines-police-shooting-video.html |work=[[The New York Times]]|author=Gutierrez, Jason|date=21 December 2020 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Prior to the incident, [[President of the Philippines|Philippine president]] [[Rodrigo Duterte]] had made remarks on ordering the police to shoot-to-kill but Duterte "denied" it to "shoot" on civilians.&lt;ref name="ts2020"&gt;{{cite news |title='How many were not filmed?': Calls to end police brutality renewed after cop killed mother and son in Tarlac |url=https://interaksyon.philstar.com/politics-issues/2020/12/21/182391/how-many-were-not-filmed-calls-to-end-police-brutality-renewed-after-cop-killed-mother-and-son-in-tarlac/ |access-date=6 March 2021 |work=The Philippine Star |publisher=Interaksyon |date=21 December 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Singapore ====

In Singapore, people [[Public demonstrations in Singapore|cannot protest]]. Police have also caned people for vandalism and other offences.

==== United Arab Emirates ====
The [[Gulf Cooperation Council]] (GCC) member states have seen many cases of brutality, with some even involving senior figures. For example, [[Issa bin Zayed Al Nahyan]], a [[United Arab Emirates]] (UAE) sheikh, was involved in the torture of many business associates. He often recorded some of the abuse. Issa was eventually arrested but a court found him not guilty and released him.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=ABC News |date=23 April 2009 |title=ABC News |website=[[ABC News]] |url=https://abcnews.go.com/Blotter/story?id=7402099 |access-date=2 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Amnesty International reported that a UAE worker was subjected to a wide array of torture methods during his time in jail, including beatings and sleep deprivation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Error |date=28 August 2015 |url=https://www.amnesty.org/en/latest/news/2015/08/uae-foreign-national-tortured-in-custody-and-detained-without-charge-for-a-year/ |access-date=2 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; UAE prisoners are also treated poorly and tortured.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.theguardian.com/world/2016/feb/26/uae-torture-prisoners-beatings-electrocution|title=UAE beat foreign prisoners and gave them electric shocks, evidence shows|date=26 February 2016|website=The Guardian}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Saudi Arabia ====
Authorities in Saudi Arabia have also been filmed lashing civilians for different reasons.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |date=12 February 2014 |title=Saudi Religious Police Don't Like Being Filmed Beating People Up |url=https://www.vice.com/en_uk/read/saudi-religious-police-dont-like-artists-who-harass-the-godly-self-and-have-long-hair |access-date=2 October 2015 |work=VICE}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Jamal Khashoggi]] was a Saudi-American activist and his death inside a Saudi Embassy drew widespread criticism. In October 2018, he went into the Embassy in Turkey. On that same day, a group of Saudi authorities entered the country and intercepted him at the Embassy and killed him soon after. They disposed of his body and then returned to Saudi Arabia.

==== Bahrain ====
In Bahrain, police and military personnel manhandled and shot dead many Arab Spring protesters.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.bbc.com/news/world-middle-east-12975832 |title=Police brutality turns Bahrain into 'island of fear' |first=Bill | last=Law |work=BBC News |date=7 April 2011 |access-date=6 July 2020 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Iraq ====
During the Gulf war, the Iraqis pillaged Kuwait and killed or tortured many people. A number of men and women were also raped. At the end of the war, some troops deliberately [[Kuwaiti oil fires|set fire to Kuwaiti oil fields]]. Before that, [[Saddam Hussein]] used the police to arrest any one who opposed him.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/1991/02/28/world/war-gulf-torture-freed-kuwaitis-tell-iraqi-abuse-including-some-cases-torture.html|title=WAR IN THE GULF: Torture; Freed Kuwaitis Tell of Iraqi Abuse Including Some Cases of Torture|newspaper=The New York Times|date=28 February 1991|last1=Hedges|first1=Chris}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite magazine|url=https://newrepublic.com/article/76724/rape-rescue-kuwait-iraq-saddam-hussein|title = The Rape and Rescue of Kuwaiti City|magazine = The New Republic|date = 24 March 1991|last1 = Kelly|first1 = Michael}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.latimes.com/archives/la-xpm-1990-10-11-mn-2801-story.html?_amp=true|title = Witnesses Tell of Iraqi Atrocities in Kuwait : Congress: Members are shaken by what they hear. Kuwait's ambassador warns that 'time is running out.'|website = [[Los Angeles Times]]|date = 11 October 1990}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Iran ====
Iranian authorities routinely harass women if they are not wearing a hijab or if they show too much skin. The authorities have also harassed minorities, especially Baháʼí and Kurdish people.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2018/apr/19/video-of-iran-morality-police-wrestling-with-woman-sparks-outrage|title=Video of Iran 'morality police' wrestling with woman sparks outrage|website=[[TheGuardian.com]]|date=19 April 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1979, authorities stormed the US embassy in Tehran and held many of the workers hostage.

[[2009 Iranian presidential election|The 2009 Iranian Presidential election]] protests over the victory of [[Mahmoud Ahmadinejad|Mahmoud Ahmeninejad]], the police and paramilitary forces used excessive force against protestors, injuring and killing many. &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |date=2009-07-15 |title=Death Toll Apparently Far Exceeds Government Claims |url=https://iranhumanrights.org/2009/07/deathtoll/ |access-date=2022-11-19 |website=Center for Human Rights in Iran}}&lt;/ref&gt;Many detentions, injuries and deaths of protestors, including children, were also reported on the [[2019–2020 Iranian protests|2019-2020 protests]]. &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=New Evidence Shows At Least 23 Children Killed in Iran by Security Forces During November Protests |url=https://www.amnestyusa.org/press-releases/at-least-23-children-killed-in-iran-by-security-forces-during-november-protests-new-evidence/ |access-date=2022-11-19 |website=Amnesty International USA |language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On September 13, 2022, [[Mahsa Amini]], a Kurdish woman was deatined by authorities. She was announced dead on September 16, 2022, allegdly due to cardiac arrest. However, it was likely due to injuries acquired due to the brutality she encountered. This incident sparked massive protests, and women burning the mandatory headscarf. &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=Hoog |first=Niels de |last2=Morresi |first2=Elena |title=Mapping Iran’s unrest: how Mahsa Amini’s death led to nationwide protests |url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/ng-interactive/2022/oct/31/mapping-irans-unrest-how-mahsa-aminis-death-led-to-nationwide-protests |access-date=2022-11-19 |website=the Guardian |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Pakistan ====
{{See also|List of cases of police brutality in Pakistan}}
Pakistan's law enforcement is divided into multiple tiers, including forces under provincial and federal government control. The law strictly prohibits any physical abuse of suspected or convicted criminals; however, due to deficiencies during the training process, there have been reported instances of suspected police brutality. Reported cases are often investigated by police authorities as well as civil courts leading to mixed outcomes.

A recent case includes the purported extra judicial killing of a man named Naqeebullah by an ex-officer named "Rao Anwar". Taking notice of the matter, the Supreme Court issued arrest and detention warrants in the case to arrest the accused.{{citation needed|date=March 2020}}

In October 2019, the People National Alliance organised a rally to free Kashmir from Pakistani rule. As a result of the police trying to stop the rally, 100 people were injured.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Shams |first1=Shamil |title=Why calls for independence are getting louder in Pakistani Kashmir |url=https://www.dw.com/en/why-calls-for-independence-are-getting-louder-in-pakistani-kashmir/a-50949454 |website=[[Deutsche Welle]] |access-date=6 December 2020 |date=23 October 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Hong Kong SAR ====
{{main|Controversies of the Hong Kong Police Force|Police misconduct allegations during the 2019 Hong Kong protests}}
[[File:HK police storm Prince Edward station and attack civilians 20190831 11pm.webm|thumb|[[Hong Kong Police Force|Hong Kong police]] storm [[Prince Edward station]] and attack civilians on 31 August 2019.]]
During the [[2014 Hong Kong protests]], there were numerous instances of police brutality. Seven police officers were caught on video kicking and beating a prominent political activist who was already handcuffed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Claims of Police Brutality Threaten to Escalate the Hong Kong Protests?|magazine=TIME|url=http://time.com/3508857/ken-tsang-hong-kong-police-brutality-occupy-central/}}&lt;/ref&gt; There had also been more than hundreds of incidents of police beating passers-by with batons. Pictures on local TV and social media show demonstrators being dragged behind police lines, circled by police officers so that onlookers' views were blocked, and in some cases, re-emerging with visible injuries. An officer-involved, retired police officer Frankly Chu King-wai was sentenced to three months in prison for causing serious bodily harm.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Hong Kong: Heavy-handed policing will only inflame protests|work=Amnesty International|url=https://www.amnesty.org/en/for-media/press-releases/hong-kong-heavy-handed-policing-will-only-inflame-protests-2014-11-28|access-date=4 December 2016|archive-date=3 January 2015|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150103122058/http://www.amnesty.org/en/for-media/press-releases/hong-kong-heavy-handed-policing-will-only-inflame-protests-2014-11-28|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|date=27 March 2017|title=Retired police officer charged with assault at Occupy protest, 853 days after incident|url=https://www.hongkongfp.com/2017/03/27/former-police-inspector-charged-misconduct-occupy-protests/}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the [[2019–20 Hong Kong protests]] which gained extensive international coverage,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Graham-Harrison|first1=Emma|last2=Yu|first2=Verna|date=16 June 2019|title='Fighting for our freedom': protesters flood on to Hong Kong's streets|url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2019/jun/16/hong-kong-protests-carrie-lam-china|url-status=live|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190617112851/https://www.theguardian.com/world/2019/jun/16/hong-kong-protests-carrie-lam-china|archive-date=17 June 2019|access-date=27 June 2019|work=The Guardian|issn=0261-3077|oclc=60623878}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|date=16 June 2019|title=Hong Kong Protest Live Updates: Nearly 2 Million People Took Part in Rally, Organizers Say|work=The New York Times|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2019/06/16/world/asia/hong-kong-protests.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|date=16 June 2019|title=Hong Kong protest sees thousands call for city's leader to step down: live updates|work=CNN|url=https://edition.cnn.com/asia/live-news/hong-kong-protests-june-16-intl-hnk/index.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|date=16 June 2019|title=Nearly 2 million march in Hong Kong to protest extradition bill, organizers say|work=CNN|url=https://edition.cnn.com/2019/06/16/asia/hong-kong-protest-carrie-lam-china-extradition-intl-hnk/index.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; complaints of police brutality increased substantially and broke previous records of complaints.{{Citation needed|date=May 2020}}

Cases that have caused outrage include the police's mauling and intentional head-shooting of protesters by [[plastic bullet|rubber bullets]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Hong Kong police declare China extradition protest 'a riot' as rubber bullets and tear gas fired at crowd|date=12 June 2019 |url=https://edition.cnn.com/2019/06/12/asia/hk-protests-extradition-intl-hnk/index.html|access-date=12 June 2019|publisher=CNN}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Hong Kong police fire rubber bullets as extradition bill protests turn to chaos|work=Reuters|url=https://www.reuters.com/article/us-hongkong-extradition/hong-kong-police-fire-rubber-bullets-as-protests-turn-to-violent-chaos-idUSKCN1TC1WR|access-date=12 June 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Hong Kong extradition: Police fire rubber bullets at protesters|work=BBC News|date=12 June 2019|url=https://www.bbc.com/news/world-asia-china-48591001|access-date=12 June 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; and rapid tear-gassing of a surrounded crowd.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|date=19 June 2019|title=Video: Hong Kong security chief apologises over extradition debacle, as lawmakers slam police use of force|work=Hong Kong Free Press|url=https://www.hongkongfp.com/2019/06/19/video-hong-kong-security-chief-apologises-extradition-debacle-lawmakers-slam-police-use-force/}}&lt;/ref&gt; Numerous were critically wounded. Many Hong Kong citizens accuse the police of attempting to [[murder]] protesters to deter the people from exercising their [[freedom of expression]].

[[Amnesty International]] released a report on 21 June 2019 denouncing the role of the Hong Kong police in the 12 June protest that ended up in bloodshed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Verified: Hong Kong police violence against peaceful protesters|work=[[Amnesty International]]|url=https://www.amnesty.org/en/latest/news/2019/06/hong-kong-police-violence-verified/}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Several street conflicts continued in Hong Kong throughout July 2019. Instances of police striking journalists with batons to obstruct their live reporting have been filmed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=警察上水瘋狂鎮壓立法議員被打額頭起包法新社女記者混亂中受傷|work=[[Radio France Internationale|RFI]] Chinese|url=http://trad.cn.rfi.fr/%E6%B8%AF%E6%BE%B3%E5%8F%B0/20190714-%E8%AD%A6%E5%AF%9F%E4%B8%8A%E6%B0%B4%E7%98%8B%E7%8B%82%E9%8E%AE%E5%A3%93%E7%AB%8B%E6%B3%95%E8%AD%B0%E5%93%A1%E8%A2%AB%E6%89%93%E9%A1%8D%E9%A0%AD%E8%B5%B7%E5%8C%85%E6%B3%95%E6%96%B0%E7%A4%BE%E5%A5%B3%E8%A8%98%E8%80%85%E6%B7%B7%E4%BA%82%E4%B8%AD%E5%8F%97%E5%82%B7|access-date=13 July 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=【逃犯條例】新聞界靜默遊行 楊健興：警對記者用暴力超社會接受程度|work=[[Ming Pao]]|url=https://news.mingpao.com/ins/%E6%B8%AF%E8%81%9E/article/20190714/s00001/1563073755965/%E3%80%90%E9%80%83%E7%8A%AF%E6%A2%9D%E4%BE%8B%E3%80%91%E6%96%B0%E8%81%9E%E7%95%8C%E9%9D%9C%E9%BB%98%E9%81%8A%E8%A1%8C-%E6%A5%8A%E5%81%A5%E8%88%88-%E8%AD%A6%E5%B0%8D%E8%A8%98%E8%80%85%E7%94%A8%E6%9A%B4%E5%8A%9B%E8%B6%85%E7%A4%BE%E6%9C%83%E6%8E%A5%E5%8F%97%E7%A8%8B%E5%BA%A6|access-date=14 July 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On the night of 31 August 2019, more than 200 riot police officers entered the [[Prince Edward station|Prince Edward MTR station]] and attacked suspects in a train compartment on the [[Tsuen Wan line]] with batons and pepper spray. Many suspects sustained head injuries.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Violence erupts across Hong Kong as police fire 'warning shots,' MTR closes 5 lines and officers storm train carriage|work=[[Hong Kong Free Press]]|url=https://www.hongkongfp.com/2019/09/01/violence-erupts-across-hong-kong-police-fire-warning-shots-mtr-closes-5-lines-officers-storm-train-carriage/|access-date=31 August 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=警衝入太子站列車 噴胡椒揮警棍拘多人 市民車廂跪地求饒照被噴|work=[[Stand News]]|url=https://thestandnews.com/politics/%E8%AD%A6%E8%A1%9D%E5%85%A5%E5%A4%AA%E5%AD%90%E7%AB%99%E5%88%97%E8%BB%8A-%E5%99%B4%E8%83%A1%E6%A4%92%E6%8F%AE%E8%AD%A6%E6%A3%8D%E6%8B%98%E5%A4%9A%E4%BA%BA-%E5%B8%82%E6%B0%91%E8%BB%8A%E5%BB%82%E8%B7%AA%E5%9C%B0%E6%B1%82%E9%A5%92%E7%85%A7%E8%A2%AB%E5%99%B4/|access-date=31 August 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|date=31 August 2019|title=Video: 831蒙面武裝分子太子站無差別襲擊市民|url=https://www.facebook.com/Pakkin.Cousin/videos/vb.168187426856933/652549298568774/?type=2&amp;theater|publisher=[[Pakkin Leung@Rice Post]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=【逃犯條例．831．圖輯】警登港鐵列車亂棍毆市民 (00:43)|work=[[Ming Pao]]|url=https://news.mingpao.com/ins/%e6%b8%af%e8%81%9e/article/20190901/s00001/1567268192038/%e3%80%90%e9%80%83%e7%8a%af%e6%a2%9d%e4%be%8b-831-%e5%9c%96%e8%bc%af%e3%80%91%e8%ad%a6%e7%99%bb%e6%b8%af%e9%90%b5%e5%88%97%e8%bb%8a%e4%ba%82%e6%a3%8d%e6%af%86%e5%b8%82%e6%b0%91|access-date=31 August 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; Until November 2019, several alleged cases of sexual violence, "disappearings", and falling deaths were found to have been directly involved with Hong Kong police brutality, and massive attacks on campus and streets have been also occurring with the concurrent deterioration of the city.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=郭文貴爆驚人事實：美國議員、政界人士看到陳彥霖的照片哭了|url=https://www.cmmedia.com.tw/home/articles/18121|access-date=12 November 2019|website=www.cmmedia.com.tw}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=科大生周梓樂留院第5日 今晨8時不治|url=https://hk.news.appledaily.com/breaking/realtime/article/20191108/60243318|access-date=12 November 2019|website=Apple Daily 蘋果日報}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=香港警察已成人類文明的惡夢 {{!}} 甄拔濤 {{!}} 立場新聞|url=https://thestandnews.com/politics/%E9%A6%99%E6%B8%AF%E8%AD%A6%E5%AF%9F%E5%B7%B2%E6%88%90%E4%BA%BA%E9%A1%9E%E6%96%87%E6%98%8E%E7%9A%84%E6%83%A1%E5%A4%A2/|access-date=12 November 2019|website=立場新聞 Stand News|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|date=9 November 2019|title=港網憤傳少女遭港警輪姦墮胎 警方啟動調查|url=http://www.rfi.fr/tw/%E4%B8%AD%E5%9C%8B/20191109-%E6%B8%AF%E7%B6%B2%E6%86%A4%E5%82%B3%E5%B0%91%E5%A5%B3%E9%81%AD%E6%B8%AF%E8%AD%A6%E8%BC%AA%E5%A7%A6%E5%A2%AE%E8%83%8E-%E8%AD%A6%E6%96%B9%E5%95%9F%E5%8B%95%E8%AA%BF%E6%9F%A5|access-date=12 November 2019|website=RFI - 法國國際廣播電台|language=zh-Hant}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|date=11 November 2019|title=正在香港採訪的德國記者在美國社群媒體發文：香港警察比IS更可怕|url=http://www.rfi.fr/tw/20191111-%E6%AD%A3%E5%9C%A8%E9%A6%99%E6%B8%AF%E6%8E%A1%E8%A8%AA%E7%9A%84%E5%BE%B7%E5%9C%8B%E8%A8%98%E8%80%85%E5%9C%A8%E7%BE%8E%E5%9C%8B%E7%A4%BE%E7%BE%A4%E5%AA%92%E9%AB%94%E7%99%BC%E6%96%87%E9%A6%99%E6%B8%AF%E8%AD%A6%E5%AF%9F%E6%AF%94is%E6%9B%B4%E5%8F%AF%E6%80%95|access-date=12 November 2019|website=RFI - 法國國際廣播電台|language=zh-Hant}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|date=14 November 2019|title=Police Misconduct in 2019 Hong Kong Democratic Movement|url=https://tl.hkrev.info/en/police-timeline/|access-date=14 November 2019|website=2019 Hong Kong Democratic Movement|language=en|archive-date=14 November 2019|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20191114004510/https://tl.hkrev.info/en/police-timeline/|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Mainland China ====
[[Protest and dissent in China|Politically motivated riots and protests]] have occurred historically in China, notably with the [[Tiananmen Square protests of 1989]]. Associations such as [[Falun Gong]] have objected against the [[Chinese Communist Party]] (CCP) and which are dispersed by riot police. Chinese protesters have been able to systematize powerful group mobilizations with the use of social media and informal mass communication like [[Twitter]] and its Chinese counterparts [[Microblogging in China|Weibo]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|date=9 May 2012|title=Chinese censors block news on blind activist's escape – CNN.com|work=CNN|url=http://articles.cnn.com/2012-04-30/asia/world_asia_china-chen-internet_1_sina-weibo-chinese-censors-chen-guangcheng?_s=PM:ASIA|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120614224358/http://articles.cnn.com/2012-04-30/asia/world_asia_china-chen-internet_1_sina-weibo-chinese-censors-chen-guangcheng?_s=PM:ASIA|archive-date=14 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Xintang, Canton Province ([[Guangzhou]]), protests over allegations of corruption and abuse of power abound in the country – they are the principal cause of discontent in the CCP the then-[[General Secretary of the Chinese Communist Party|CCP General Secretary]] [[Xi Jinping]]. The Xintang region, Canton Province (Guangzhou), is an influential textile hub, attracting thousands of workers from all over the country, and what lit the fuse was a complaint of mistreatment against a pregnant migrant worker. Protests on 20 February{{what year|date=October 2020}} used a website to urge participants not to shout more anti-government slogans, but to go outside for a quiet walk in the places where they had been deciding to continue the protest. After a brutal police response, the authorities installed corrugated metal fences outside the restaurant and the home of dissident and Nobel Peace Prize winner [[Liu Xiaobo]].{{citation needed|date=October 2020}} Hundreds of uniformed and plainclothes security officers and volunteers with red armbands, pre-emptively positioned in Wangfujing. This presence interrupted the orderly operation of the shops.

====Thailand====

In 1976, Thai police, military personnel and others, were seen shooting at protesters at [[Thammasat University]]. Many were killed and many survivors were abused.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://secretsiam.news/p/october-6|title = 6ตุลา}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Turkey====
[[File:Gezi Parkı Müdahale 2013-06-11 (46).jpg|thumb|A protester shows his wounded eye. Police brutality was one of the main issues arising from the [[2013 protests in Turkey]].]]
[[Turkey]] has a history of police brutality, including [[Torture in Turkey|the use of torture]] particularly between 1977 and 2002. Police brutality featured excessive use of tear gas (including targeting protesters with tear gas canisters),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Tear gas as a dangerous weapon|newspaper=The Economist|url=https://www.economist.com/blogs/charlemagne/2013/07/aftermath-unrest-turkey}}&lt;/ref&gt; pepper spray, and water cannons. Physical violence against protesters has been observed, for example, in the suppression of Kurdish protests and [[International Workers' Day#Turkey|May Day demonstrations]]. The [[2013 protests in Turkey]] were in response to the brutal police suppression of an environmentalist sit-in protesting the removal of [[Taksim Gezi Park]].

In 2012 several officials received prison sentences for their role in the death in custody of the political activist [[Engin Çeber]].

The European Court of Human Rights has noted the failure of the Turkish investigating authorities to carry out effective investigations into allegations of ill-treatment by law enforcement personnel during demonstrations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=CASE OF İZCİ v. TURKEY - Judgment|url=http://hudoc.echr.coe.int/sites/eng/Pages/search.aspx#{%22itemid%22:[%22001-122885%22]}|access-date=2 October 2015|publisher=European Court of Human Rights}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2021, the [[General Directorate of Security (Turkey)|General Directorate of Security]] issued a circular banning all audio-visual recordings of law enforcement officers at protests.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Turkey Bans Citizens From Filming Police at Protests |url=https://balkaninsight.com/2021/04/30/turkey-bans-citizens-from-filming-police-at-protests/ |work=Balkan Insight |date=30 April 2021 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20210522005016/https://balkaninsight.com/2021/04/30/turkey-bans-citizens-from-filming-police-at-protests/ |archive-date=22 May 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Europe ===

====Austria====
In Vienna, there is an association made between Vienna's drug problem and the city's African migrants, which have led to African migrants being racially profiled.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Reactions to Police Brutality|url=http://www.viennareview.net/news/austria/reactions-to-police-brutality|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160818090904/http://www.viennareview.net/news/austria/reactions-to-police-brutality|archive-date=18 August 2016|access-date=22 July 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There have been several highly publicized incidents in Austria where police have either tortured, publicly humiliated, or violently beaten people{{emdash}}in some cases, to the point of death. While the most notorious of these incidents occurred in the late 1990s, incidents as recent as 2019 are being investigated by the Vienna Police Department for Special Investigations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://civicspacewatch.eu/austria-five-questions-on-possible-police-violence-in-vienna/|title=Freedom of assembly - AUSTRIA: Five questions on possible police violence in Vienna}}&lt;/ref&gt;
:'''24 April 1996:''' Nicola Jevremović, a Serbian Romani man, tried to pay a friend's parking fine and was harassed by police. He escaped and a group of 25 to 40 police officers entered his home without a warrant. The police officers violently beat him and his wife, Violetta Jevremović, in front of their children and then arrested the couple. The couple were made to wait outside for half an hour in front of their neighbours, allegedly to humiliate them. Nicola Jevremović was initially fined for a misdemeanor and found guilty in 1997 of "resisting arrest". Violetta Jevremović was found guilty of "suspicion of resisting arrest".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Romani Couple Beaten by Police in Austria - ERRC.org|url=http://www.errc.org/article/romani-couple-beaten-by-police-in-Austria/1494|access-date=22 July 2016|website=www.errc.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Viennese Court Refuses to Counter Police Testimony - ERRC.org|url=http://www.errc.org/roma-rights-journal/viennese-court-refuses-to-counter-police-testimony|access-date=7 June 2020|website=www.errc.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Cahn|first=Claude|url=http://www.errc.org/uploads/upload_en/file/00/26/m00000026.pdf#page=20|title=Divide and Deport: Roma &amp; Sinti in Austria|publisher=European Roma Rights Centre|year=1996|isbn=963046988X|editor-last=Petrova|editor-first=Dimitrina|pages=19–23}}&lt;/ref&gt;
:'''November 1998:''' Dr. C, a black Austrian citizen, was stopped by police after reversing his car into a one-way street and asked, "Why are you driving the wrong way, nigger?". He was beaten unconscious and handcuffed. Police continued beating him after he regained consciousness. After he was arrested, he spent 11 days recovering in the hospital.&lt;ref name=":14"&gt;{{Cite news|date=24 March 2000|title=Austria: Incidents of police brutality continue|url=https://www.amnesty.org/download/Documents/136000/eur130072000en.pdf|access-date=7 June 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;
:'''May 1999:''' [[Marcus Omofuma]], a Nigerian asylum-seeker, was being deported from Vienna when the officers taped him to his chair "like a mummy" and stuck tape over his mouth. He suffocated whilst in police custody.&lt;ref name=":14" /&gt;
:'''1 January 2015:''' A 47-year-old woman was beaten and taken into custody after refusing to take a breathalyzer test while walking home on New Year's Eve. She suffered a fractured coccyx, and severe bruising to her head and knees. She filed a complaint and received no response. The case was re-examined by the prosecutor only after she found CCTV footage.&lt;ref name=":16"&gt;{{cite web|date=13 March 2015|title=Video of police arrest shows 'orgy of violence'|url=http://www.thelocal.at/20150313/video-of-police-arrest-shows-orgy-of-violence|access-date=22 July 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Wie die Polizei eine Frau verletzte und dann falsch beschuldigte|url=https://www.falter.at/zeitung/20150310/wie-die-polizei-eine-frau-verletzte-und-dann-falsch-beschuldigte|url-status=live|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150419112740/http://www.falter.at/falter/2015/03/10/wie-die-polizei-eine-frau-verletzte-und-dann-falsch-beschuldigte|archive-date=19 April 2015|access-date=7 June 2020|website=www.falter.at|language=de}}&lt;/ref&gt;
:'''28 July 2015:''' A 27-year-old man, suspected of being a pickpocket, was handcuffed and violently thrown to the ground while in police custody. Police said that the man had been injured while "pressing his head against the wall". Video evidence showed him being passive and compliant before the altercation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|date=11 August 2015|title=Video shows alleged police violence in Vienna|url=http://www.thelocal.at/20150811/video-shows-alleged-police-violence-in-vienna|access-date=22 July 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.falter.at/zeitung/20150811/polizei-luegen-und-ein-video|title=Polizei, Lügen und ein Video|website=www.falter.at}}&lt;/ref&gt;
There has been a notable lack of commitment to addressing the violation of civilians' rights in Austria, with Amnesty International reporting that in 1998–1999 very few people who violated human rights were brought to justice. This was worsened by the fact that many people who made a complaint against police were brought up on counter-charges such as resisting arrest, defamation, and assault.&lt;ref name=":14" /&gt;

From 2014 to 2015, 250 accusations of police misconduct were made against officers in Vienna with none being charged, though 1,329 people were charged with "civil disorder" in a similar time period.&lt;ref name=":16" /&gt; The Council of Europe's Committee for the Prevention of Torture (CPT)'s 2014 report included several complaints of police using excessive force with detainees and psychiatric patients. The culture of excusing police officers for their misconduct has continued into the present day, and any complaints of mistreatment are often met with inadequate investigations and judicial proceedings.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Austria|url=http://www.amnestyusa.org/our-work/countries/europe/austria|access-date=22 July 2016|website=Amnesty International USA}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Austria 2015/2016|url=https://www.amnesty.org/en/countries/europe-and-central-asia/austria/report-austria/|access-date=22 July 2016|website=www.amnesty.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Austria has legislation that criminalizes hate speech against anyone's race, religion, nationality, or ethnicity.&lt;ref name=":17"&gt;{{cite web|title=Austria 2015 Human Rights Report|url=https://2009-2017.state.gov/documents/organization/253033.pdf|publisher=United States Bureau of Democracy and Labor}}&lt;/ref&gt; Laws like this discourage discrimination, help with altering public perceptions of different ethnic and cultural groups, and subsequently reduce the number of racially motivated incidents of police brutality. Austria has several [[non-governmental organization|NGO]]s that are trying to implement broad programs that encourage positive cross-cultural relations and more targeted programs such as racial sensitivity training for police. The Austrian police are formulating their policies to prevent police brutality and to make prosecuting police misconduct fairer.&lt;ref name=":17" /&gt; In January 2016, Austrian police forces started a trial of wearing body cameras to document civilian—police interactions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|date=17 August 2015|title=Austria to test police body cameras|url=http://www.thelocal.at/20150817/austria-to-test-police-body-cameras|access-date=22 July 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

However, it appears that incidents of police brutality are still occurring.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Amnesty international report : the state of the world's human rights.|publisher=Amnesty International|year=2016|isbn=978-0-86210-492-4|location=New York|page=75|oclc=946693257}}&lt;/ref&gt; Amnesty International suggested that more work needs to be done by the government to reduce negative stereotypes that lead to prejudice, racial profiling, hatred, and police brutality. One suggestion was to disband the ''Bereitschaftspolizei'', Vienna's riot police, as they have frequently been involved with human rights violations and situations of police brutality.&lt;ref name=":16" /&gt; Amnesty International also proposed that the Austrian government adopt a National Action Plan against Racism, something which they had previously refused to do. Such a plan was required by the [[World Conference against Racism 2001|2001 Durban Declaration and Programme of Action]].&lt;ref name="amnestyusa1"&gt;{{cite web|title=Annual Report: Austria 2013|url=http://www.amnestyusa.org/research/reports/annual-report-austria-2013|access-date=22 July 2016|website=Amnesty International USA}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Belarus ====
In May 2021, authorities stopped [[Ryanair Flight 4978]] in Belarusian airspace. A Belarusian journalist and activist, [[Roman Protasevich]] was taken off the plane and detained by authorities.

==== Belgium ====
[[Law of Belgium|Belgian law]] enforcement changed to two police forces operating on a federal and local level in 2001 after a three-tier police system. While the two services remain independent, they integrate common training programs and recruitment. The change was prompted by a national parliamentary report into a series of pedophile murders which proved police negligence and severely diminished public confidence. Currently, approximately 33,000 local police and 900 civilians work across 196 regional police forces.&lt;ref name=":10"&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Benoît|first1=Majerus|last2=Xavier|first2=Rousseaux|date=1 January 2004|title=The World Wars and their Impact on the Belgian Police Systems|language=en|hdl-access=free|hdl=10993/1824}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The United Nations (UN) Basic Principles on the Use of Force and Firearms by Law Enforcement Officials (1990) are replicated in Belgian law through The Criminal Code and the Police Functions Act.&lt;ref name=":10" /&gt; These principles dictate that the use of force should be proportionate, appropriate, reported, and delivered on time; however, the UN Human Rights Committee reported complaints of ill-treatment against property and people by police escalated between 2005 and 2011, most commonly involving assault against persons no longer posing danger.&lt;ref name=":11"&gt;{{cite web|title=POLIS – Country Profiles of Participating and Partner States|url=http://polis.osce.org/countries/details?item_id=8|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160517164252/http://polis.osce.org/countries/details?item_id=8|archive-date=17 May 2016|access-date=22 July 2016|website=polis.osce.org}}&lt;/ref&gt; Belgian judicial authorities were found to also have failed to notify national police watchdog, Committee P, of criminal convictions against police, which is both a direct breach of Belgian judicial procedure and a failure to comply with Article 40 of the International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights.&lt;ref name=":11" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Treaty bodies Search|url=http://tbinternet.ohchr.org/_layouts/treatybodyexternal/TBSearch.aspx?Lang=En&amp;CountryID=17&amp;ctl00_PlaceHolderMain_radResultsGridChangePage=4|access-date=22 July 2016|website=tbinternet.ohchr.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;

An extreme instance in January 2010 led to the death of Jonathan Jacob in Mortsel. He was apprehended by local Mortsel police for behaving strangely under the influence of amphetamines. The footage depicted eight officers from Antwerp police's Special Intervention Unit restraining and beating Jacob after he had been injected with a sedative sparked public outrage. Jacob died from internal bleeding following the incident, but police claimed they did not make any mistakes and "acted carefully, respecting the necessary precautions".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|date=22 February 2013|title=Police brutality video sends shock wave through Belgium|url=http://deredactie.be/cm/vrtnieuws.english/News/1.1555242|access-date=22 July 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2013, the Grand Chamber of the European Court of Human Rights (ECtHR) convicted Belgium of human rights violations in an appeal on the treatment of two brothers in custody who had been slapped by an officer. The Grand Chamber voiced its concern that "a slap inflicted by a law-enforcement officer on an individual who is entirely under his control constitutes a serious attack on the individual's dignity".&lt;ref name=":12"&gt;{{cite web|last=Platform|first=European Liberties|title=Belgium Slapped for Police Slapping|url=http://www.liberties.eu/en/news/ecthr-belgium-slapping-case-police-violence|access-date=22 July 2016|website=Liberties.eu}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Belgian League of Human Rights (LDH) monitored police brutality through the Observatory of Police Violence (OBSPOL) after Belgium downplayed cases.&lt;ref name=":13"&gt;{{cite web|last=cressot|first=nicolas|title=ObsPol – Observatoire des violences policières en Belgique|url=http://www.obspol.be/|access-date=22 July 2016|website=www.obspol.be}}&lt;/ref&gt; OBSPOL was formed in 2013 and collects testimonies on its website, informs police brutality victims of their rights, and strongly advocating public policy being adapted in of favor victim protection.&lt;ref name=":12" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":13" /&gt;

Several other instances of police violence can be noted in Belgium. In 2014, Mawda, a four-year-old child was killed in an encounter with a truck used to carry migrants across the border. A police officer shot on the moving car, despite knowing a child was in it.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|date=24 May 2018|title=La mort de Mawda, une Kurde de 2 ans tuée par un policier : on vous résume l'affaire qui bouleverse la Belgique|url=https://www.francetvinfo.fr/monde/europe/migrants/la-mort-de-mawda-une-kurde-de-2-ans-tuee-par-un-policier-on-vous-resume-l-affaire-qui-bouleverse-la-belgique_2765741.html|access-date=16 February 2021|website=Franceinfo|language=fr-FR}}&lt;/ref&gt; The case got widespread media attention, but the police officer only ended up with a 400€ fine and one year of suspended prison sentence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|date=12 February 2021|title=Jugement Mawda : le conducteur fautif (4 ans) mais le policier aussi (1 an avec sursis), il ne devait pas sortir son arme estime le tribunal|url=https://www.rtbf.be/info/belgique/detail_affaire-mawda-le-conducteur-fautif-mais-le-policier-aussi-il-ne-devait-pas-sortir-son-arme-estime-le-tribunal?id=10696476|access-date=16 February 2021|website=RTBF Info|language=fr}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2018, Lamine Bangoura was killed in his own apartment by eight policemen because he had not paid rent. In the attempt to evict him out of his flat, the policemen used unwarranted brutality which resulted in Lamine's death.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|date=10 November 2020|title=L'affaire des policiers poursuivis pour le décès de "Lamine" traitée en février|url=https://www.7sur7.be/belgique/l-affaire-des-policiers-poursuivis-pour-le-deces-de-lamine-traitee-en-fevrier~a30e1770/|access-date=7 March 2021|website=7sur7.be|language=fr}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2019, Mehdi, 17-year-old Moroccan boy was run over by a police car on patrol.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|date=8 October 2020|title=Décès du jeune Mehdi : les policiers qui conduisaient la voiture ne sont pas inculpés|url=https://bx1.be/bruxelles-ville/deces-du-jeune-mehdi-les-policiers-qui-conduisaient-la-voiture-ne-sont-pas-inculpes/|access-date=16 February 2021|website=BX1|language=fr-FR}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2020, Adil, a 19-year-old Moroccan boy was chased by a police car for not respecting the Coronavirus curfew. He was hit by a police car to stop him in his chase, which killed him on impact. Sources say it was on purpose, even though he was on a scooter. Both these cases had been filed as dismissed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|date=26 November 2020|title=Décès du jeune Adil à Anderlecht : le parquet demande le non-lieu à l'encontre des policiers|url=https://www.rtbf.be/info/societe/detail_deces-du-jeune-adil-a-anderlecht-le-parquet-demande-le-non-lieu-a-l-encontre-des-policiers?id=10640320|access-date=16 February 2021|website=RTBF Info|language=fr}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2021, Ibrahima was arrested. He was filming a police control. The authorities however, said he was arrested for not respecting the curfew, which starts at 10pm, even though his arrest happened at 6pm. He died in police custody, in unknown circumstances. His death prompted a lot of reaction from the public, who organized a protest a few days after his killing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|date=11 January 2021|title=Bruxelles : il filme la police puis est déclaré mort (VIDÉO)|url=https://cite24.com/bruxelles-il-filme-la-police-puis-est-declare-mort-video/|access-date=16 February 2021|website=Cité 24|language=fr-FR}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Croatia ====
The Constitution of [[Croatia]] prohibits torture, mistreatment, and cruel and degrading punishment under Article 17, and accords arrested and convicted persons humane treatment under Article 25 of the OHCHR.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The Constitution|url=http://www.hr-eu.net/article.php?lang=2&amp;id=25&amp;t=The%20Constitution|access-date=12 August 2019|website=www.hr-eu.net}}&lt;/ref&gt; Croatia has a centralised police force under the command of the Ministry of the Interior with approximately 20,000 police officers.&lt;ref&gt;Interpol 2016, Croatia, viewed 19 July 2016, http://www.interpol.int/Member-countries/Europe/Croatia&lt;/ref&gt;

From 1991 to 1995, the Croatian police, in addition to their regular police tasks, were a militarised force charged with the role of defending the country while seceding from Yugoslavia.&lt;ref name="Ivkovic 2005, pp. 546"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Ivkovic|first1=S|year=2005|title=Police (mis)behaviour: a cross-cultural study of corruption seriousness|journal=Policing: An International Journal of Police Strategies &amp; Management|volume=28|issue=3|pages=546–566|doi=10.1108/13639510510614609}}&lt;/ref&gt; Military training taught police officers to use firearms before exhausting other procedures, which has affected the philosophy and behaviour of police officers in using excessive force.&lt;ref name="Ivkovic, S 2000, pp. 194"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Ivkovic|first1=S|last2=Haberfeld|first2=M|year=2000|title=Transformation from militia to police in Croatia and Poland – A comparative perspective|journal=Policing: An International Journal of Police Strategies &amp; Management|volume=23|issue=2|pages=194–217|doi=10.1108/13639510010333831}}&lt;/ref&gt; Developments were made to achieve democratic policing as a modern, professional force that is also accountable to the public.&lt;ref name="Ivkovic, S 2000, pp. 194" /&gt; However, citizen complaints of violent police behaviour suggest that the [[police militarization|militarization of the police force]] in the early 1990s continues to influence the level of force accepted as legitimate and reasonable by Croatian police officers.&lt;ref name="Ivkovic 2005, pp. 546" /&gt;

The European Court of Human Rights has found that Croatian police authorities have failed to fulfill their obligations, on numerous occasions, under Article 3 of the European Convention on Human Rights and Fundamental Freedoms by failing to carry out effective investigations to protect its citizens and tourists from violent attacks.&lt;ref name="irb-cisr.gc.ca"&gt;{{cite web|last=Canada|first=Immigration and Refugee Board of|date=5 June 2018|title=Responses to Information Requests|url=https://irb-cisr.gc.ca:443/en/country-information/rir/Pages/index.aspx?doc=455395&amp;pls=1|access-date=13 August 2019|website=irb-cisr.gc.ca|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2009, the European Court of Human Rights condemned Croatian police authorities for ignoring requests to starting an investigation into perpetrators who violently attacked a Croatian citizen.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Court Condemns Croatia for Failing to Fulfill Its Positive Obligations under Article 3 of the ECHR|url=http://www.errc.org/cikk.php?cikk=3041|access-date=12 August 2019|website=European Roma Rights Centre|language=HU}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Croatian police have a history of discriminatory abuse and failing to recognise violence against the [[Romani people|Romani]] minority living in Croatia. The European Commission against Racism and Intolerance noted that Croatian police abuse against minority groups including Romani were continually reported;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Refugees|first=United Nations High Commissioner for|title=Refworld {{!}} Croatia: Treatment of minority groups, including Roma, Serbs, Bosnians, and Romanians; state protection available in cases of violence and discrimination, including legislation (2012-June 2015)|url=https://www.refworld.org/docid/55bf4ac04.html|access-date=12 August 2019|website=Refworld|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; police authorities are reluctant to take violence against Romani people seriously.&lt;ref name="irb-cisr.gc.ca" /&gt; Police investigations into black market selling in Croatia have been excessively violent towards Romani vendors, with reports of physical violence and abusive racism being directed at them.&lt;ref name="errc.org"&gt;{{cite web|title=Police Beat Pregnant Romani Woman in Croatia|url=http://www.errc.org/cikk.php?cikk=1582|access-date=13 August 2019|website=European Roma Rights Centre|language=HU}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Romani women's association, "Better Future", reported that police had beaten a pregnant Romani woman who attempted to evade arrest for black market selling in 2002.&lt;ref name="errc.org" /&gt;

The Croatian police violence has been used to intimidate refugees travelling from Serbia into Croatia.&lt;ref name="moving-europe.org"&gt;{{cite web|title=Report on Push-backs and Police violence at the Serbo-Croatian border – Moving Europe|url=http://moving-europe.org/report-on-push-backs-and-police-violence-at-the-serbo-croatian-border-2/|access-date=13 August 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; This included segregating nationalities, with Syrian, Iraqi, and Afghani nationals gaining entry to Croatia as refugees more easily than other nationalities.&lt;ref name="moving-europe.org" /&gt; An unaccompanied sixteen-year-old from Morocco recounted his experience trying to gain asylum in Croatia after lying about being a Syrian national: "We had to get into a police car [...] They told us this is Slovenia, but then it was Serbia [...] One of my friends tried to run away, but the Croatian police caught [sic] him and beat him."&lt;ref name="moving-europe.org" /&gt;

==== Denmark ====
The [[Police of Denmark]] has a force of approximately 11,000 officers and they serve in the 12 police districts and the two Danish overseas territories.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=About the Police: Organisation|url=https://www.politi.dk/en/About_the_police/organisation/|access-date=18 July 2016|website=Politi|archive-date=19 November 2018|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20181119214341/https://www.politi.dk/en/About_the_police/organisation/|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Danish Independent Police Complaints Authority ({{lang|da|Den Uafhængige Politiklagemyndighed}}) (the Authority) handles the investigation of police misconduct allegations.&lt;ref name="politiklagemyndigheden.dk"&gt;{{cite web|title=Independent Police Complaints Authority|url=http://politiklagemyndigheden.dk/english|access-date=18 July 2016|website=Den Uafhængige Politiklagemyndighed}}&lt;/ref&gt; Annual statistics released by the Authority revealed a reduction in the number of complaints against police from 2012 to 2015.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Adfaerdsklager|url=http://politiklagemyndigheden.dk/udgivelser-og-tal/politikredsstatistik/adfaerdsklager|access-date=18 July 2016|website=Den Uafhængige Politiklagemyndighed|language=da|archive-date=17 August 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160817073208/http://politiklagemyndigheden.dk/udgivelser-og-tal/politikredsstatistik/adfaerdsklager|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2012, the Authority received 726 conduct complaints from across Denmark; in 2015, the number of complaints fell to 509, representing approximately 0.05 complaints per officer. A majority of complaints stem from general misconduct, such as traffic violations and unprofessional behaviour (e.g., swearing).&lt;ref name="politiklagemyndigheden1"&gt;{{cite web|title=Arsberetning 2015|url=http://politiklagemyndigheden.dk/media/15820/a_rsberetning_2015_netversion.pdf|access-date=18 July 2016|publisher=Den Uafhængige Politiklagemyndighed (Independent Police Complaints Authority)|language=da|archive-date=17 August 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160817055124/http://politiklagemyndigheden.dk/media/15820/a_rsberetning_2015_netversion.pdf|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

However, the 2015 Annual Report identifies some instances where the Police of Denmark used excessive force.&lt;ref name="politiklagemyndigheden1" /&gt; For example, the Authority investigated a complaint made about alleged violence against an arrested person in Christianshavn on 15 March 2016.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Politiklagemyndigheden søger vidner til en episode på Christianshavn, hvor en polititjenestemand er anmeldt for vold|url=http://politiklagemyndigheden.dk/nyheder/pressemeddelelser-nyheder/2016/4/politiklagemyndigheden-soeger-vidner-til-en-episode-paa-christianshavn,-hvor-en-polititjenestemand-er-anmeldt-for-vold|access-date=18 July 2016|website=Den Uafhængige Politiklagemyndighed|date=18 April 2016|language=da}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another investigation looked into the alleged use of force against a 16-year-old boy on 28 June 2016,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Polititjenestemænd sigtet for vold begået mod en 16-årig dreng|url=http://politiklagemyndigheden.dk/nyheder/pressemeddelelser-nyheder/2016/6/polititjenestemaend-sigtet-for-vold-begaaet-mod-en-16-aarig-dreng|access-date=18 July 2016|website=Den Uafhængige Politkilagemyndighed|date=28 June 2016|language=da}}&lt;/ref&gt; which resulted in charges being laid against the two offending police officers from the Sydsjællands- and Lolland-Falster police department. Although examples of police brutality are not common, highly publicised incidents have been reported.

* In 2002, 21-year-old Jens Arne Orskov Mathiason died while in police custody on the way to prison.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|date=15 June 2006|title=Denmark: Jens Arne Ørskov's death in custody: A mother's quest for justice|url=http://www.refworld.org/docid/44c610894.html|access-date=18 July 2016|website=refworld|publisher=Amnesty International|pages=1–6}}&lt;/ref&gt; The incident raised concerns over the behaviour of the officers involved, the thoroughness of the subsequent investigation, and the willingness of the Director of Public Prosecutions to hold the officers accountable for their alleged failings. As a result, [[Amnesty International]] called for the establishment of new policies to investigate human rights violations and enforce compliance under the [[European Convention on Human Rights]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|date=15 June 2006|title=Denmark: Jens Arne Ørskov's death in custody: A mother's quest for justice|url=http://www.refworld.org/docid/44c610894.html|access-date=18 July 2016|website=refworld|publisher=Amnesty International|page=6}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In January 2016, a man died in police custody after being arrested by seven Copenhagen Police officers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|date=8 January 2016|title=Man died while in custody of Danish police|agency=The Local DK|url=http://www.thelocal.dk/20160108/man-died-while-in-custody-of-danish-police|access-date=18 July 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In August 2009, police in Copenhagen were heavily criticised for their response to an attempt to remove Iraqi refugees who were living in a city church.&lt;ref name="nytimes.com"&gt;{{cite news|author1=Matthew Saltmarsh|author2=Catherine Contiguglia|date=14 August 2009|title=Raid in Denmark to Dislodge Iraqi Refugees Leads to Protests and Hunger Strike|newspaper=The New York Times |agency=New York Times|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2009/08/15/world/europe/15denmark.html|access-date=18 July 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Video allegedly showed the police using violence against the refugees and their supporters. Between 12,000 and 20,000 people subsequently protested against these actions.&lt;ref name="nytimes.com" /&gt;
* In 2012, the [[Courts of Denmark|Danish Court of Appeal]] concluded that the Danish Police had violated Article 3 (against abusive treatment and torture) and Articles 5, 10, and 11 (dealing with the right to liberty, the right to information about the accusation, and the freedom of peaceful assembly) of the European Convention of Human Rights for the 2009 mass arrest made during protests at the [[2009 United Nations Climate Change Conference]] in Copenhagen.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|date=22 April 2012|title=Police found guilty of violating European Convention on Human Rights|agency=SocialistWorld.net|url=http://www.socialistworld.net/doc/5713|access-date=18 July 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

To ensure that police are well-trained and to mitigate the risk of police brutality, police recruits undergo approximately three years of training; at the National Police College, recruits learn about police theory, the Road Traffic Act, criminal law, physical training, other legislation, first aid, radio communication, securing evidence, identifying drugs, preventing crime, management, human rights, and cultural sociology to name a few.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=About the Police: How to become a police officer|url=https://www.politi.dk/en/About_the_police/admission/|access-date=18 July 2016|website=Politi|publisher=Politi|archive-date=17 June 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160617060530/https://www.politi.dk/en/About_the_police/admission/|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; After this training period, recruits are promoted to the position of a police constable. By comparison, US police academies provide an average of 19 weeks of classroom instruction.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author1=Paul Hirschfield|date=30 November 2015|title=Why American Cops Kill So Many Compared To European Cops|agency=Huffington Post|url=https://www.huffingtonpost.com/entry/american-cops-lethal_us_565cde59e4b079b2818b8870|access-date=18 July 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; The prolonged training in Denmark was observed to increase the ability of police to effectively de-escalate conflicts and enact their duties professionally and responsibly.

To keep police officers accountable and to ensure that they perform their duties in compliance with Danish, European and international laws, the Independent Police Complaints Authority has the power to handle criminal investigations against police officers and determine complaints of police misconduct.&lt;ref name="politiklagemyndigheden.dk" /&gt; This body is independent of both the police and prosecutors. For example, police

{{Blockquote|text="[...] may use force only if necessary and justified and only by such means and to such extent as are reasonable relative to the interest which the police seek to protect. Any assessment of the justification of such force must also take into account whether the use of force involves any risk of bodily harm to third parties."|author=''Act on Police Activities'' (2004)|source=&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author1=Frode Z. Olsen|title=The Use of Police Firearms in Denmark|url=https://www.politi.dk/NR/rdonlyres/20DE43AF-33F4-48C5-A710-6A58457E35D2/0/Engelskresum%C3%A9afendeligrapport.pdf|website=Politi|publisher=Politi|access-date=18 July 2016|page=2|language=en|date=2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

Therefore, police in Denmark are held to high standards and will face consequences if they breach their obligations to encourage compliance. Victims of police misconduct are encouraged to lodge a report with the Authority.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Do you want to complain about the police?|url=http://politiklagemyndigheden.dk/media/6447/1._korr_pm_pjece_uk.pdf|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160305062856/http://politiklagemyndigheden.dk/media/6447/1._korr_pm_pjece_uk.pdf|archive-date=5 March 2016|access-date=18 July 2016|publisher=Den Uafhængige Politiklagemyndighed (Independent Police Complaints Authority)|pages=1–14|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Estonia ====
The [[Estonian Police]] force was temporarily dissolved in 1940 when [[Estonia]] lost its independence to the Soviet Union after it was occupied, before the Police Act passed in 1990 dissolved the Soviet [[militsiya]] and re-established it.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=POLIS – Country Profiles of Participating and Partner States|url=http://polis.osce.org/countries/details?item_id=16|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160816074034/http://polis.osce.org/countries/details?item_id=16|archive-date=16 August 2016|access-date=22 July 2016|website=polis.osce.org}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2010, the Public Order Police, Police Board, Central Criminal Police, Border Guard, Citizenship, and Migration Board merged into the Police and Border Guard Board.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Estonia / Europe / Member countries / Internet / Home – INTERPOL|url=http://www.interpol.int/Member-countries/Europe/Estonia|access-date=22 July 2016|website=www.interpol.int}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is the largest state agency in Estonia with over 5000 people in employment. The main objectives for this organisation are to maintain security and public order, crime prevention, detection and investigation, securing the European Union (EU) border, citizenship and identity documentation administration.

The Estonian Ministry of Justice reports that crime figures dropped by 10% from 2013 to 2015.&lt;ref name=":9"&gt;{{cite web|title=Estonia 2015 Crime and Safety Report|url=https://www.osac.gov/pages/ContentReportDetails.aspx?cid=17447|access-date=22 July 2016|website=www.osac.gov}}&lt;/ref&gt; They instruct that those who find themselves detained by the police should comply with their instructions and those who experience a language barrier are allowed to "request the presence of an interpreter and should not sign any documents or reports until they are confident that the document's contents are consistent with the details of the incident or the victim's statement".&lt;ref name=":9" /&gt;

Incidents of police abuse are very rare. Although uncommon, powers are sometimes abused which leads to police brutality, such as the 2007 Bronze Soldier riots.

===== Bronze Night =====
{{See also|Bronze Night}}
[[File:Bronze Soldier of Tallinn, 2007.jpg|thumb|The Bronze Soldier of Tallinn in its new location]]The Bronze Night occurred from 26 to 29 April 2007, when riots broke out over the Bronze Soldier of Tallinn being relocated. The government wanted to relocate the statue and rebury the associated remains near the Tallinn Military Cemetery; the response was heavily negative among the country's [[Geographical distribution of Russian speakers|Russophone]] population, but for Estonians historically the Bronze Soldier served as a symbol of Soviet occupation and repression.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Johnston|first=Anthony|title=The Memory Remains|url=http://www.russiaprofile.org/page.php?pageid=Culture+%26+Living&amp;articleid=a1230646924|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100812073257/http://www.russiaprofile.org/page.php?pageid=Culture%2B&amp;%2BLiving&amp;articleid=a1230646924|archive-date=12 August 2010|access-date=20 July 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; For Russian citizens, it represented Soviet Russia's victory over Germany in World War II and their claim to equal rights in Estonia.
One Russian rioter was killed and other protesters were arrested. Due to the overcrowded detention centres, many of the detainees were taken to cargo terminals in Tallinn's seaport. Then-chairman of the [[Constitution Party (Estonia)|Constitution Party]] Andrei Zarenkov stated "people were forced to squat for hours or lie on the concrete floor with their hands tied behind their backs. The police used plastic handcuffs which caused great pain. The police selectively beat the detainees including women and teenagers. We have pictures of a toilet which is stained with the blood of the injured".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|date=1 May 2007|title=Interfax-Religion|website=Ethnic Russians quit Estonian police to stay away from violence – public figure|agency=Interfax|url=http://www.interfax-religion.com/?act=news&amp;div=2975|access-date=20 July 2016|quote=Paragraph 6 -7}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The police department denied all claims made against them. On 22 May 2007, the Office of Prosecutor General of Estonia&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ejtn.eu/About-us/Members/Estonia-Office-of-the-Prosecutor-General/|title=Estonia: Office of the Prosecutor General - EJTN Website|website=www.ejtn.eu}}&lt;/ref&gt; received more than fifty complaints on the police brutality that occurred during Bronze Night and opened seven criminal cases against them. In November 2007, the [[United Nations Committee against torture|United Nations Committee Against Torture]] expressed concerns over the use of excessive force and brutality by law enforcement personnel in regards to Bronze Night.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Human Rights Committee considers report of Estonia|url=https://newsarchive.ohchr.org/EN/NewsEvents/Pages/DisplayNews.aspx?NewsID=10206&amp;LangID=E|access-date=5 July 2019|website=newsarchive.ohchr.org}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Council of Europe]] published in its report that those detained were not granted all the fundamental safeguards, including the right to a doctor or a lawyer, and to inform a relative or a third party of their arrest. It was later discovered that the accused were only allowed outside contact and lawyer assistance when brought before a judge. Several detainees were denied access to a doctor while in police custody despite displaying visible injuries.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=agencies|first=staff and|date=28 April 2007|title=500 held in fresh Estonia riots|url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/1549981/500-held-in-fresh-Estonia-riots.html |archive-url=https://ghostarchive.org/archive/20220112/https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/1549981/500-held-in-fresh-Estonia-riots.html |archive-date=12 January 2022 |url-access=subscription |url-status=live|access-date=22 July 2016}}{{cbignore}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== France ====
The policing structure of the nineteenth century [[France]] has been linked to the outcomes of France's reorganisation during the [[French Revolution]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine|date=1 January 1982|title=The French Police in the 19th Century|url=http://www.historytoday.com/clive-emsley/french-police-19th-century|magazine=History Today|access-date=28 January 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; There have been multiple instances of violent enforcement stemming from issues around racial and geographic differences throughout France's history.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|date=20 June 2014|title="Police Brutality Is a Hollow Term": On the Current Policing Violence in France|url=http://thefunambulist.net/2016/05/31/police-brutality-is-a-hollow-term-on-current-violence-in-france/|access-date=28 January 2017|work=The Funambulist}}&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, the Human Rights Watch and Amnesty International reported human rights violations by France including physical and psychological abuse as a result of excessive force towards Muslims when undertaking house raids.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|date=4 February 2016|title=French police 'abuse' Muslims under emergency laws|url=http://www.aljazeera.com/news/2016/02/french-police-abuse-muslims-emergency-laws-160204035243925.html|access-date=28 January 2017|publisher=Al Jazeera English}}&lt;/ref&gt;

France's police ombudsman is currently dealing with 48 judicial inquiries into police brutality against its citizens, in which 1,000 individuals have been arrested within three months.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Angelique Chrisafis in Paris|title=French police watchdog looks into violence at labour protests |newspaper=The Guardian|url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2016/jun/07/french-police-violence-labour-law-protests-watchdog|access-date=28 January 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; There have been several high-profile cases of alleged police brutality which have gained media attention, including the death of Lamine Dieng on 17 June 2007, who died after suffocating in a police van while he was constrained.&lt;ref name="ceasefiremagazine.co.uk"&gt;{{cite web|author=Ali Meziane|title=Stolen Lives: A new generation rises up against French police violence|url=https://ceasefiremagazine.co.uk/stolen-lives-generation-rises-french-police-violence/|access-date=28 January 2017|publisher=Ceasefire Magazine}}&lt;/ref&gt; The investigation of Lamine's death is ongoing. Grey areas around [[police accountability]] have come to light, including questions over how his body was covered in bruises and whether or not [[carotid restraint]] (which involves constricting the carotid arteries) was used against him.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Ari Vidali|date=30 January 2014|title=Reconsidering Carotid Control - Article - POLICE Magazine|url=http://www.policemag.com/channel/patrol/articles/2014/01/reconsidering-carotid-control.aspx|access-date=28 January 2017|publisher=Policemag.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; The European Court of Human Rights condemned France in 1998 for their apparent use of carotid constriction.&lt;ref name="ceasefiremagazine.co.uk" /&gt; This same method of restraint was seen to be used against Hakim Ajimi who died of [[positional asphyxia]] as a result of overwhelming pressure being placed on his chest and neck by police.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|date=20 January 2012|title=Suspended sentences for Grasse police &amp;#124; Riviera Insider|url=http://www.riviera-press.fr/insider/node/24360|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160807141941/http://www.riviera-press.fr/insider/node/24360|archive-date=7 August 2016|access-date=28 January 2017|publisher=Riviera-press.fr}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:2019-02-09 14-28-06 manif-GJ-Montbéliard.jpg|thumb|[[Yellow vests movement|Yellow vests]] protesters holding a sign referring to victims of police violence, 9 February 2019]]
Recent protests over disputed [[labor laws]] have revealed the extreme nature of police brutality in France, as many videos have surfaced in the media depicting police using disproportionate force on protesters. French officials have forced these aggressive videos to be destroyed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Labor law protests shadowed by police brutality in France before Euro 2016|newspaper=Daily Sabah|url=http://www.dailysabah.com/europe/2016/05/29/labor-law-protests-shadowed-by-police-brutality-in-france-before-euro-2016|access-date=28 January 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A group known as the Stolen Lives Collective formed in response to the increased number of cases of police brutality in French communities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://ceasefiremagazine.co.uk/stolen-lives-generation-rises-french-police-violence/|title=Stolen Lives: A new generation rises up against French police violence &amp;#124; Ceasefire Magazine|website=ceasefiremagazine.co.uk}}&lt;/ref&gt; It represents families of those who have been affected by police brutality. The group strongly demands the government to act against police brutality and to reduce racism present across the police force in France.&lt;ref name="ceasefiremagazine.co.uk" /&gt;

On 14 December 2018, [[Amnesty International]] reported police brutality during the [[yellow vests movement]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Police must end use of excessive force against protesters and high school children in France|url=https://www.amnesty.org/en/latest/news/2018/12/police-must-end-use-of-excessive-force-against-protesters-and-high-school-children-in-france/|access-date=5 July 2019|website=www.amnesty.org|date=14 December 2018|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; France's yellow vests protests began against an increased fuel tax made by President [[Emmanuel Macron]]. Participation in the weekly protests diminished due to violence, particularly due to the loss of eyes and hands, and the development of neurological disorders caused by police [[Blast ball|blast balls]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |date=13 November 2019 |title=Reconstruction et quête de vérité : l'autre combat des gilets jaunes mutilés |url=https://www.lexpress.fr/actualite/societe/reconstruction-et-quete-de-verite-l-autre-combat-des-gilets-jaunes-mutiles_2106795.html |access-date=4 July 2021 |website=LExpress |language=fr}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Dehimi |first1=Mathilde |date=2 June 2019 |title=Ces gilets jaunes ont perdu un œil ou une main lors de manifestations et appellent à interdire grenades et LBD |url=https://www.franceinter.fr/societe/ces-gilets-jaunes-ont-perdu-un-oeil-ou-une-main-lors-de-manifestations-et-appellent-a-interdire-grenades-et-lbd |access-date=4 July 2021 |website=France Inter |language=fr}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Etancelin |first1=Valentin |date=1 February 2019 |title=Ces gilets jaunes ont "perdu un œil", qu'est-ce que cela veut dire exactement? |url=https://www.huffingtonpost.fr/2019/02/01/ces-gilets-jaunes-ont-perdu-un-oeil-quest-ce-que-cela-veut-dire-exactement_a_23658310/ |access-date=4 July 2021 |website=[[HuffPost|Le Huffington Post]] |language=fr}}&lt;/ref&gt; The protests eventually stopped due to the [[COVID-19 pandemic]] but continued again after health restrictions lifted.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |date=12 September 2020 |title=French police use teargas at gilets jaunes protest in Paris |work=The Guardian |url=http://www.theguardian.com/world/2020/sep/12/french-police-use-teargas-at-gilet-jaunes-protest-in-paris}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Finland ====
Historically, police brutality was commonplace during the 1920s and 1930s following the [[Finnish Civil War]]. Some local sections of the secret police ([[Etsivä Keskuspoliisi]]) routinely beat up arrested communists.{{According to whom|date=October 2021}}

In 2006, there were 7,700 police officers in Finland.&lt;ref name="uta.fi"&gt;{{cite web|title=Poliisien tekemät rikokset – normien valvojat normien rikkojina|url=http://tampub.uta.fi/handle/10024/93527|access-date=2 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; That police force was seen to be more law-abiding than firemen;&lt;ref name="uta.fi" /&gt; however, a few dozen cases each year involved police officers being convicted of crimes committed while on duty, 5 to 10 percent of the hundreds of similar crimes prosecuted annually. The number of these crimes were shown to increase annually.&lt;ref name="uta.fi" /&gt; Police officers are most often suspected of traffic-related crimes (endangering road safety, vehicular collisions, etc.) which constitute approximately 50% of all cases. These types of cases were the most likely to be dismissed before proceeding to the prosecutor for consideration.&lt;ref name="uta.fi" /&gt; The second-highest category (approximately 20%) involving police is the use of excessive force which, except for of some off-duty petty assaults (which includes a slap on the cheek), proceed to the prosecutor without fail.&lt;ref name="uta.fi" /&gt;

In 2006, a 51-year-old police constable lured a 16-year-old girl to his house by showing her his badge, where he got her drunk and raped her twice. The constable was fired and sentenced to a two-year suspended sentence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|date=3 February 2010|title=Poliisi raiskasi 16-vuotiaan – selvisi ehdollisella|url=http://www.iltasanomat.fi/kotimaa/poliisi-raiskasi-16-vuotiaan---selvisi-ehdollisella/art-1288335053979.html|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130928022350/http://www.iltasanomat.fi/kotimaa/poliisi-raiskasi-16-vuotiaan---selvisi-ehdollisella/art-1288335053979.html|url-status=dead|archive-date=28 September 2013|access-date=21 May 2016|work=Ilta-Sanomat}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2007, an Iranian-born immigrant, Rasoul Pourak, was beaten in a cell at Pasila Police Station, Helsinki, inflicting bruises all over Pourak's body, an open wound over his eyebrow, and a fractured skull. Facial bones were also broken and he was left permanently damaged. One guard participating in the assault was sentenced to an 80-day suspended prison sentence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=IL: Turvakameran dramaattinen tallenne – mies hakattiin julmasti Pasilan poliisiputkassa|url=http://takku.net/article.php/200710022319038|access-date=2 October 2015|work=Takku}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Putkat vailla tallentavia kameroita|url=http://blogit.mtv3.fi/kolmevarttia/2007/10/10/putkat-vailla-tallentavia-kameroita|access-date=2 October 2015|work=Kolme varttia}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2010, two police officers assaulted a man in a wheelchair in connection with an arrest. The police twisted the man's hands and pushed him backward and broke a femur in the process.&lt;ref&gt;Iltasanomat 5 June 2010 Poliisi pahoinpiteli vammaisen&lt;/ref&gt; In 2013, two policemen were sentenced to 35 [[day-fine]]s for assault and breach of duty in connection with stomping on a [[Romani people|Romani]] man's head onto the asphalt three times. According to the police, he had resisted, contrary to eyewitness accounts. A third officer testified that the event was captured on surveillance video, which was stored but accidentally destroyed. The officer also stated that they had seen the footage and claimed that the video did not show any resistance on the part of the victim, but also that the assault happened out of the camera's view.&lt;ref name="HS.fi"&gt;{{cite web|date=23 September 2013|title=MTV3: Romanimiehen päätä poljettiin asvalttiin, poliiseille sakot|url=http://www.hs.fi/kotimaa/MTV3+Romanimiehen+p%C3%A4%C3%A4t%C3%A4+poljettiin+asvalttiin+poliiseille+sakot/a1379902738575?ref=hs-art-top-7|access-date=21 May 2016|work=HS.fi|archive-date=19 February 2014|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140219082241/http://www.hs.fi/kotimaa/MTV3+Romanimiehen+p%C3%A4%C3%A4t%C3%A4+poljettiin+asvalttiin+poliiseille+sakot/a1379902738575?ref=hs-art-top-7|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Poliisi polki romanimiehen päätä asfalttiin|url=http://www.mtv3.fi/uutiset/rikos.shtml/2013/09/1809380/poliisi-polki-romanimiehen-paata-asfalttiin|access-date=2 October 2015|work=mtv.fi}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Germany ====
Germany is sensitive towards its history in implementing policing practices, though this has not stopped international bodies from identifying a clear pattern of police ill-treatment of foreigners and members of ethnic minorities.&lt;ref name="ReferenceC"&gt;{{cite web|date=14 January 2004|title=Document &amp;#124; Amnesty International|url=https://www.amnesty.org/en/documents/eur23/001/2004/en/|access-date=28 January 2017|publisher=Amnesty.org}}&lt;/ref&gt; Every year, around 2,000 complaints of police brutality are reported, though it is highly suspected that the actual number of cases is under-reported.&lt;ref name="dw.com"&gt;{{cite web|date=24 January 2017|title=Preventing police brutality in Germany &amp;#124; Germany &amp;#124; DW.COM &amp;#124; 03.03.2013|url=http://www.dw.com/en/preventing-police-brutality-in-germany/a-16641839|access-date=28 January 2017|publisher=DW.COM}}&lt;/ref&gt; As high-profile cases like the 2014 Cologne New Year's Eve incident become more prevalent, racist and xenophobic attitudes have been reflected in instances of police brutality.&lt;ref name="bloomberg.com"&gt;{{cite news|title=German Police Are Too Soft, Really - Bloomberg View|url=https://www.bloomberg.com/view/articles/2016-01-08/german-police-are-too-soft-really|access-date=28 January 2017|newspaper=Bloomberg.com|date=8 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; High profile cases of police brutality have been reported to occur as far back as the 1960s:
*'''2 June 1967''': [[Benno Ohnesorg]] was shot and killed by a policeman during a demonstration against the state visit of the Shah of Iran, [[Mohammad Reza Pahlavi]].
*'''28 May 1999''': Sudanese national Aamir Ageeb died of asphyxia during his forced deportation from Frankfurt. Before departure, Ageeb was forcibly restrained by tape and rope. During take-off, police officers allegedly forced his head and upper body between his knees.&lt;ref name="ReferenceC" /&gt;
*'''8 December 2000''': Josef Hoss was accused by his neighbour (a police officer) of harbouring firearms; he was ambushed, beaten, and handcuffed near his home. He woke up in the police station with a cloth bag over his head and sustained multiple injuries that prevented him from working or being able to financially support his family. No firearms were found during the investigation.&lt;ref name="ReferenceC" /&gt;
*'''May 2002''': Stephan Neisius was repeatedly kicked and hit by a group of police officers while he was handcuffed on the floor of a police station. He spent 13 days in hospital on life support before dying. Although the Cologne District Court convicted all six police officers of bodily harm resulting in death, none of the accused served prison sentences.&lt;ref name="ReferenceC" /&gt;
*'''2012''': Teresa Z. called the police after a fight with her boyfriend got out of hand but was quickly arrested. She was punched by police officer Frank W. and received a broken nose and eye socket while in detention. Frank W. spent ten months in jail and was forced to pay a fine of 3,000 euros.&lt;ref name="dw.com" /&gt;

As law enforcement is vested solely with the states of Germany, each state's police force (or "Land" police) follows a different system of law. Accordingly, there is an absence of a federal comprehensive register, compiling and publishing regular, uniform, and comprehensive figures on complaints about police ill-treatment.&lt;ref name="ReferenceC" /&gt; Even though Germany is bound to obligate its many international treaties and conventions, Amnesty International (2002) highlights the authorities failed to protect a range of human rights as guaranteed by international human rights law and standards.&lt;ref name="ReferenceC" /&gt;
A study conducted in 2019 on police brutality in Germany found that it led to complaints in only 9%, and trials in only 13% of the cases. The study was conducted by the Ruhr-University of Bochum and was the biggest study at the time to be conducted on police brutality in Germany. The study found that the low number of complaints was likely due to a low expectation of success.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|date=17 September 2019 |title=Polizeiliche Gewaltanwendungen aus Sicht der Betroffenen |url=https://kviapol.rub.de/images/pdf/KviAPol_Zwischenbericht.pdf |access-date=20 May 2020 |publisher=Körperverletzung im Amt durch Polizeibeamt*innen |pages=68–69}}&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, most German states do not require their police force to carry identification, making it difficult for victims to lodge complaints against individuals.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Plarre|first=Plutonia |date=19 April 2017 |title=Berliner Polizisten: Individuum zu sein ist keine Nachteil |newspaper=Die Tageszeitung: Taz |url=https://taz.de/!5398584/ |via=taz.de}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Reuter|first=Markus |date=17 September 2019 |title=Nie Täter, immer Opfer: Die Polizei muss endlich lernen, mit Kritik umzugehen |url=https://netzpolitik.org/2019/nie-taeter-immer-opfer-die-polizei-muss-endlich-lernen-mit-kritik-umzugehen/}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Watchdog organizations have also criticized the lack of independent institutions for investigations into police violence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |date=20 August 2015|title=Polizisten nur selten vor Gericht |url=https://correctiv.org/aktuelles/justiz-polizei/2015/08/20/polizisten-nur-selten-vor-gericht/}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Mehr Verantwortung bei der Polizei |url=https://www.amnesty.de/mehr-verantwortung-bei-der-polizei |website=www.amnesty.de}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite this objective lack of accountability for policing practice, public levels of trust in police remain among the highest in the EU only behind Scandinavian countries and Switzerland.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Confidence data|url=https://www.cepol.europa.eu/sites/default/files/03-confidence-police.pdf|access-date=12 November 2019|publisher=cepol.europa.eu}}&lt;/ref&gt; This allows Germany to maintain one of the lowest levels of public order and safety spending in the EU, at 1.5 percent of gross domestic profit, compared to the EU average of 1.8 percent.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Government expenditure on public order and safety - Statistics Explained |url=http://ec.europa.eu/eurostat/statistics-explained/index.php/Government_expenditure_on_public_order_and_safety |access-date=28 January 2017 |publisher=Ec.europa.eu}}&lt;/ref&gt; As a result, Germany has a police force of only 300 officers per 100,000 of its population. Lower numbers exist in Scandinavian countries and the UK,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=File:Police officers, average per year, 2007–09 and 2010–12 (per 100 000 inhabitants) YB14.png - Statistics Explained |url=https://ec.europa.eu/eurostat/statistics-explained/index.php/File:Police_officers,_average_per_year,_2007%E2%80%9309_and_2010%E2%80%9312_(per_100_000_inhabitants)_YB14.png |access-date=5 July 2019 |website=ec.europa.eu}}&lt;/ref&gt; suggesting that Germany is attempting to build the impression of having a more [[laissez-faire]] approach to policing, despite instances of police brutality.{{clarify|reason=Probably just a matter of improved wording, but this sentence is a minor trainwreck.|date=May 2020}} German police officers rarely use their guns; as of August 2017, 109 deaths by service weapons since 1998 were reported, and only 8 fatalities in the two years before the report.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Why German police officers rarely reach for their guns &amp;#124; Germany &amp;#124; DW.COM &amp;#124; 27.08.2014 |url=http://www.dw.com/en/why-german-police-officers-rarely-reach-for-their-guns/a-17884779 |access-date=28 January 2017 |publisher=DW.COM}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Greece ====
The Greek Police, known officially as the [[Hellenic Police]], assumed their current structure in 1984 as a result of merging the Gendarmerie (Chorofylaki) and the Urban Police Forces (Astynomia Poleon).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Greece / Europe / Member countries / Internet / Home - INTERPOL|url=http://www.interpol.int/Member-countries/Europe/Greece|access-date=22 July 2016|website=www.interpol.int}}&lt;/ref&gt; Composed of central and regional departments, the Hellenic Police have a relatively long history of police brutality. One of the first documented incidents dates back to 1976, where 16-year-old activist Sideris Isidoropoulos was killed by police while he put up campaign posters on a public building. In 1980, during a demonstration commemorating the [[Athens Polytechnic uprising]], 20-year-old protester Stamatina Kanelopoulou and 24-year-old Iakovos Koumis [[Athens Polytechnic March of 1980|were beaten to death]] by the Greek police. The protests still occur to this day for protesters to commemorate the 1973 uprising. The protests are still commonly affected by police brutality around the time of the event.&lt;ref name="huffingtonpost.co.uk"&gt;{{cite web|date=7 February 2013|title=Growing Police Brutality in Greece: The Hidden Face of the Crisis|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.co.uk/fragkiska-megaloudi/growing-police-brutality-in-greece_b_2636529.html|access-date=22 July 2016|website=The Huffington Post|language=en-GB}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 17 November 1985 another protestor, 15-year-old [[Michalis Kaltezas]], was murdered by the police during the demonstration commemorating the Polytechnic uprising.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |date=2019-12-06 |title=Μιχάλης Καλτεζάς: Οταν από σφαίρα αστυνομικού χάθηκε ακόμη ένα παιδί |url=https://www.tanea.gr/2019/12/06/people/dolofonia-kalteza-otan-apo-sfaira-astynomikou-xathike-akomi-ena-paidi/ |access-date=2022-07-24 |website=ΤΑ ΝΕΑ |language=el}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The level and severity of police brutality in Greece over the last few years have been profound. Due to the recent financial crisis, many austerity measures have been enforced, resulting in many individuals and families struggling to survive. Greek citizens opposed these austerity measures from the beginning and showed their disapproval with strikes and demonstrations. In response, police brutality has significantly increased, with consistent reports on the use of tear gas, severe injuries inflicted by the police force, and unjustified detention of protesters.&lt;ref name="huffingtonpost.co.uk" /&gt;

In 2013 Greek police allegedly tortured four young men believed to be bank robbery suspects following their arrest. It was claimed that the men were hooked and severely beaten in detention. The media published photos of the men, all with severe bruising, though the police's press release showed digitally manipulated photos of the four without injuries. The Greek minister of citizen protection{{emdash}}[[Nikos Dendias]]{{emdash}}supported the police and claimed that they needed to use Photoshop to ensure the suspects were recognisable.&lt;ref name="huffingtonpost.co.uk" /&gt; In October 2012, 15 anti-fascist protesters were arrested in Athens when they clashed with supporters of the fascist party (and later criminal organization) "[[Golden Dawn (Greece)|Golden Dawn]]". Victims claimed they were tortured while being held at the Attica General Police Directorate and stated that police officers slapped them, spat on them, burnt their arms with cigarette lighters, and kept them awake with flashlights and lasers. Dendias countered by accusing the British newspaper that published the details of these crimes of libel. It was proven by forensic examination that the torture had taken place. The two Greek journalists who commented on ''The Guardian'' report the next day were fired.&lt;ref name="huffingtonpost.co.uk" /&gt;

Police brutality in Greece today predominantly manifests itself in the form of unjustified and extreme physical violence towards protesters and journalists. Amnesty International highlights that the continued targeting of journalists is concerning as it infringes on the right to freedom of expression. According to a recent Amnesty International report, there have been multiple instances in which police have used excessive brutal force, misused less-lethal weapons against protesters, attacked journalists, and subjected bystanders to ill-treatment, particularly over the course of the anniversary of the Athens Polytechnic uprising, which took place on 17 November 2014.&lt;ref name="thetoc.gr"&gt;{{cite web|date=21 November 2014|title=Amnesty International condemns Greek police brutality {{!}}thetoc.gr|url=http://www.thetoc.gr/eng/news/article/amnesty-international-condemns-greek-police-brutality|access-date=22 July 2016|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt; Allegations against police have emerged specifically concerning their use of unprovoked brutal force towards journalists documenting the demonstration and against many students who partook in a peaceful protest. Police allegedly sprayed protesters with chemical irritants from close range – in one instance a 17-year-old girl with asthma had been treated in the hospital after this attack and when she informed police of her condition they laughed.&lt;ref name="thetoc.gr" /&gt;

Video footage confirmed that on 13 November 2014, riot police began to strike students who attempted to run away from the grounds of Athens Polytechnic. Media reports suggest that around 40 protesters had to seek subsequent medical attention to injuries sustained from brutal police beatings.&lt;ref name="thetoc.gr" /&gt; Amnesty International called for action to prosecute those who were behind the assaults, stating that within the Greek police there is a culture of "abuse and impunity" which remains as authorities have taken very little action to address the root of the problem.&lt;ref name="thetoc.gr" /&gt;

A German exchange student said he was beaten randomly by riot police in the Exarheia district, stating his only reason for being there was that he was eating with other students. The student gave a horrifying description of the violence he endured and cowered in a corner when he saw police because a few weeks before he had witnessed police beating a man they had arrested. He claimed that upon spotting him, about six police officers began assaulting him with their batons, and when they left they were replaced by another group of police.&lt;ref name="thetoc.gr" /&gt; The student was unarmed and posed no threat but the police were ruthlessly brutal in their actions. It has been indicated that riot police left beaten and gravely injured individuals without any medical assistance. Amnesty International urges Greece to effectively and promptly investigate these crimes against civilians, which violate human rights, and hold perpetrators accountable.&lt;ref name="thetoc.gr" /&gt;
*'''May 2011''': student Yannis Kafkas suffered an almost fatal head injury after a police officer hit him with a fire extinguisher. Kafkas spent 20 days in intensive care.&lt;ref name="huffingtonpost.co.uk" /&gt;
*'''June 2011''': Manolis Kipraios, journalist, was covering protests against austerity measures when a member of the riot police fired a stun grenade at him and caused him to suffer from permanent hearing loss.&lt;ref name="huffingtonpost.co.uk" /&gt;
*'''February 2012''': photojournalist Marios Lolos had to have surgery done after being beaten in the head by police at a protest. The day before this attack another journalist Rena Maniou was allegedly severely beaten by security forces. Dimitris Trimis, the head of The Greek Journalist Association (ESEA) broke his arm after he was violently pushed and kicked by police.&lt;ref name="huffingtonpost.co.uk" /&gt;

There have been instances where protesters were used as human shields – a photo of a female protester in handcuffs ahead of policeman as people threw rocks at the police has gained considerable media attention.&lt;ref name="huffingtonpost.co.uk" /&gt;

None of the cases of police brutality above resulted in any prosecution of police force members. One case that sparked nationwide riots was the death of 15-year-old Alexis Grigoropoulos, who was shot dead by a police officer in December 2008 during demonstrations in Athens, sparkling [[2008 Greek riots|large riots against police brutality]]. Unlike other cases, the police officer responsible was convicted of murder.&lt;ref name="huffingtonpost.co.uk" /&gt;

==== Hungary ====
{{Main|2006 protests in Hungary}}
In 2008 when Hungary's two law enforcement bodies, the police ([[Rendőrség]]) and the [[Border guard|Border Guards]] merged when the nation signed the [[Schengen Agreement]]; Border Guards became police officers. The police force in Hungary consists of the National Bureau of Investigation and the Operational Police, who respectively deal with investigating severe crimes and riot suppression. A third police group, Terrorelhárítási Központ, which deals mainly with counter-terrorism nationwide, also exists. 44,923 employees make up the Rendőrség force in Hungary. Brutality and corruption exist within Rendőrség.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees|title=Hungary: Police corruption, including complaints mechanisms available to report instances of corruption; police effectiveness, including response to complaints submitted by Roma (2013-June 2015)|url=http://www.refworld.org/docid/55bf50df4.html|access-date=28 January 2017|publisher=Refworld}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The 1998 Human Rights Watch World Report revealed that the Roma minority in Hungary were continually discriminated against.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=HRW World Report 1999: Hungary:Human Rights Developments|url=https://www.hrw.org/legacy/worldreport99/europe/hungary.html|access-date=28 January 2017|publisher=Hrw.org}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was evident in the police force, with reports of police mistreatment and brutality.

The 2006 protests in response to Prime Minister [[Ferenc Gyurcsány]]'s speech where he said that the Socialist Party lied their way into office demonstrated the disproportionate measures police took particularly police brutality on non-violent civilians. Police threw gas grenades and used rubber bullets to shoot protesters. Protesters and non-violent civilians passing by were targeted, tackled, and injured by the police. Police broke the fingers of a handcuffed man and raided restaurants and bars to find radical demonstrators. Police brutality ranged from offensive language to physically attacking protesters. Reports show that brutality extended to bypassers, tourists, news reporters, and paramedics.

Hungarian Spectrum blogger Eva S. Bologh suggest that rather than acting reactively, Hungary should work to improve their police training programs and work to provide ongoing training and assessments to ensure that police officers in the Rendőrség, are competent and fair in their ethical judgements when it comes to the proportionality of a crime or situation and the use of force. The requirements to become a police officer in Hungary are to graduate from high school, pass a matriculation exam, and complete two years in the police academy.&lt;ref name="hungarianspectrum.org"&gt;{{cite web|date=March 2009|title=The Hungarian police force – Hungarian Spectrum|url=http://hungarianspectrum.org/2009/03/01/the-hungarian-police-force/|access-date=28 January 2017|publisher=Hungarianspectrum.org}}&lt;/ref&gt; Compared to other countries around the world, the two-year program is shorter than Denmark's (3-year program), and longer than Australia's (33-week program) and the United States' (18 weeks).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=About the Role &amp;#124; Police Members &amp;#124; Victoria Police|url=http://www.policecareer.vic.gov.au/police/about-the-role/becoming-a-police-officer|access-date=28 January 2017|publisher=Policecareer.vic.gov.au|archive-date=25 August 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160825232420/http://www.policecareer.vic.gov.au/police/about-the-role/becoming-a-police-officer|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|date=18 March 2008|title=Police recruit training and academy summary|url=http://discoverpolicing.org/what_does_take/?fa=training_academy_life|access-date=29 January 2017|publisher=Discover Policing}}&lt;/ref&gt; The current two-year program is quite lengthy, however, time is not the issue. Most of what the Hungarian police academy teaches is academic theory and not much on practice.&lt;ref name="hungarianspectrum.org" /&gt; If practical work was given more attention in the Hungarian police academy, the number of police brutality incidents will likely decrease.

==== Ireland ====
===== Northern Ireland (UK) =====
[[File:Anti-police pin from Northern Ireland.jpg|thumb|A pin from [[Northern Ireland]] that reads "Help the Police, beat yourself up."]]
Police brutality has been a long-standing issue in Northern Ireland due to unsavoury police procedures used during [[the Troubles]] to obtain admissions of guilt. The Troubles in Northern Ireland lasted from 1968 until 2007 and were essentially a civil war between those who wanted Northern Ireland to remain in the United Kingdom (unionists/loyalists, predominantly Protestants) and those who did not (Irish nationalists/republicans, predominantly Catholics). During this time as many as 50,000 people were physically maimed or injured, some by the Police Service of Northern Ireland (PSNI, previously called Royal Ulster Constabulary).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=History - The Troubles|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/history/troubles|access-date=29 January 2017|publisher=BBC}}&lt;/ref&gt; Instances of Northern Irish Police brutality were confirmed by the 1978 report from the [[European Court of Human Rights]], which concluded that five interrogation techniques used by the police, which included wall standing, deprivation of food, drink or sleep, subjection to noise, and forcing detainees to remain in the same position for hours, were instances of [[Cruel and unusual punishment|cruel and degrading treatment]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|date=12 September 2013|title=Document &amp;#124; Amnesty International|url=https://www.amnesty.org/en/documents/EUR45/004/2013/en/|access-date=29 January 2017|publisher=Amnesty International}}&lt;/ref&gt; Such brutality was not recognized by domestic courts until 2010, where 113 people, some of them minors, came forward to have their complaints heard.

At present Northern Ireland still faces policing issues, though not to the extent during the Troubles. There are concerns about harassment by police against children aged 14–18 in low socio-economic areas of Northern Ireland which have led to a deep level of mistrust between the youth and the police.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|date=2003|title=Young people|url=http://conflictresearch.org.uk/reports/policing/NIPB-PONI-Young-People-April-2003.pdf|access-date=12 November 2019|publisher=conflictresearch.org}}&lt;/ref&gt; Catholics in Northern Ireland find that they are treated differently by police due to the police force being largely Protestant. 48% of Catholics that were surveyed in Northern Ireland reported harassment by the police. Instances of harassment include police officials spitting on individuals or enforcing laws in a discriminatory fashion.&lt;ref&gt;McVeigh, Robbie
[http://cain.ulst.ac.uk/issues/police/docs/mcveigh.html' It's Part of Life Here … The Security Forces and Harassment in Northern Ireland']{{dead link|date=March 2018|bot=InternetArchiveBot|fix-attempted=yes}} ''[[Cain Web Service]]'', Belfast, Accessed 18 July 2016&lt;/ref&gt; The PSNI has moved away from police brutality given the focus on accountability for the past and the significant decrease in the use of the baton amongst police members (guns are rarely used);&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|date=30 September 2016|title=Statistics on Police Use of Force|url=https://www.psni.police.uk/inside-psni/Statistics/statistics-on-police-use-of-force/|access-date=29 January 2017|publisher=Police Service of Northern Ireland}}&lt;/ref&gt; however, harassment continues to be a key issue for Northern Ireland.

===== Republic of Ireland =====
The Republic of Ireland's police force is called the [[Garda Síochána]] (Garda) and employs around 14,500 staff.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=About Us - An Garda Síochána - Ireland's National Police Service|url=http://garda.ie/Controller.aspx?Page=5416|access-date=29 January 2017|publisher=An Garda Síochána}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ireland's criminal laws allow "reasonable force" to be used by the police with regard to all the circumstances, which eludes to officers actions being proportionate in the circumstances. Excessive use of force is unlawful, though section 76(7) of the Criminal Justice and Immigration Act 2008 allows the following considerations when deciding on what force is reasonable.
A person acting for a legitimate purpose may not be able to weigh up the exact necessary action at the time or may act instinctively but honestly – in these instances, the use of force may be considered reasonable.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|date=23 October 2013|title=Police use of force|url=https://www.app.college.police.uk/app-content/public-order/core-principles-and-legislation/police-use-of-force/#the-criminal-law-act-1967-the-police-and-criminal-evidence-act-1984-common-law-and-the-criminal-justice-and-immigration-act-2008|access-date=29 January 2017|publisher=College of Policing}}&lt;/ref&gt;

This is acknowledged by the Garda, who state: "Unfortunately, even in the most civilised democratic jurisdictions, tragedies resulting from police use of force will continue to devastate families and communities".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Incident info|url=http://www.justice.ie/en/JELR/GInspBarricadeIncidents.pdf/Files/GInspBarricadeIncidents.pdf|access-date=12 November 2019|publisher=justice.ie}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The use of force by Irish Police officers has been of international concern, when the European Committee for the Prevention of Torture reported on this issue in the Republic three times within a decade. Incidents that prompted this concern centred around the death of John Carty, a man suffering from mental illness who was shot and killed by police; the prosecution of seven Garda police members due to assaults on protesters in 2002 and in 2005; and a fifteen-year-old boy who died after spending time in Garda custody. Given this state of events, the Garda engaged independent Human Rights experts to conduct a review of the force who found numerous deficiencies. The government responded by implementing new procedures based on this report. These include a new complaints procedure available against the Garda (Ombudsman Commission), disciplinary procedures and whistle-blowing protections.&lt;ref&gt;Conway, V &amp; Walshe, D  'Current Developments in Police Governance and Accountability in Ireland [[Crime, Law and Social Change]], Published online, 9 February 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Italy ====
The use of excessive violence by police officers has been a major concern in Italy since the 2000s. Beatings and violence are commonly used during demonstrations, and several murders have been carried out.
The following incidents caused concern in the country:
*On 11 July 2001, 23-year-old student [[Death of Carlo Giuliani|Carlo Giuliani]] was killed by police officers when they opened fire on a group of protesters during the [[27th G8 summit#Protests|anti-globalization demonstration outside the July 2001 G8 summit]]. 25-year-old police officer Mario Placanica was considered to be responsible for Giuliani's death but was not charged. Placanica asserted that he was being used as a scapegoat to cover up for the responsible parties and that other officers caused Giuliani's death, shooting at Giuliani from a nearby location. Nobody was arrested for Giuliani's murder.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.ilfattoquotidiano.it/2019/07/19/g8-di-genova-quello-che-lo-stato-non-dice-neppure-18-anni-dopo/5336982/|title=Blog &amp;#124; G8 di Genova, quello che lo Stato non dice. Neppure 18 anni dopo|date=19 July 2019|website=Il Fatto Quotidiano}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*On 11 July 2003, Marcello Lonzi, aged 29, was beaten and tortured to death in his cell. Lonzi was arrested in the city of [[Livorno]] four months prior, as he was suspected of carrying out an attempted theft. Although his death was considered to be caused by "a heart attack after a fall", signs of torture were found on his body. Nobody was arrested for Lonzi's death.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.fanpage.it/attualita/mio-figlio-come-cucchi-morto-in-carcere-per-un-pestaggio-voglio-giustizia/|title=Mio figlio come Cucchi: morto in carcere per un pestaggio, voglio giustizia|website=Fanpage}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*On 25 September 2005 in [[Ferrara]], at around 5 a.m., a woman called police claiming that she saw "a strange man walking around". The man, 18-year-old Federico Aldrovandi, who had spent the night in [[Bologna]] before returning to Ferrara, was stopped by four policemen. The four officers then began to beat and torture Aldrovandi, killing him at the scene. The officers were arrested and sentenced to three years and six months in prison.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.reti-invisibili.net/aldrovandi/|title=Federico Aldrovandi|website=www.reti-invisibili.net}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*On 27 October 2007 in [[Trieste]], 34-year-old [[schizophrenic]] Riccardo Rasman was launching firecrackers to celebrate his recent employment as a waste collector. Police were called by a resident as he heard suspected shots (which were the firecrackers' noise). Four police officers stormed the house, beating Rasman. The man was hit with iron objects and gagged. The officer pressed their knee on his neck and back, causing Rasman to die of [[asphyxia]]. The four officers were sentenced to just six months of prison.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.crimeblog.it/post/978/riccardo-rasman-ucciso-da-4-poliziotti-dopo-due-anni-il-processo|title=Riccardo Rasman: ucciso da 4 poliziotti, dopo due anni il processo|date=5 July 2008|website=Crimeblog.it}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*On 14 October 2007 in [[Pietralunga]], 44-year-old carpenter Aldo Bianzino and his wife, Roberta Radici, were arrested for a handful of marijuana plants at their home. Bianzino stated that the plants were for personal use. When the couple arrived at a police station, they were separated. Two days later, an officer approached Radici in her cell and asked her if her husband has heart problems. Radici responded that Aldo never had health issues and was in good condition, and demanded to know why the officer had asked her the question. The officer responded that Aldo Bianzino had been brought to the hospital in serious condition. Three hours later, Radici was freed from her cell and inquired as to when she could see Aldo. The officer callously responded: "after the autopsy." During Bianzino's autopsy, several signs of violence emerged, including broken ribs, damage to the liver and spleen, and several bruises. A policeman was sentenced in 2015 to a year in prison for lack of assistance. Roberta Radici died of cancer in 2008.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.fanpage.it/attualita/vittime-del-carcere-quando-aldo-bianzino-moriva-in-cella-con-il-fegato-spappolato/|title=Aldo Bianzino, arrestato per qualche piantina di cannabis e tornato a casa in una bara|website=Fanpage}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*On 11 November 2007 near [[Arezzo]], a group of five friends, including 27-year-old Gabriele Sandri, were in a car headed to a football match between [[Inter Milan|Inter]] and [[S.S. Lazio]]. The five men, supporters of S.S. Lazio, were stopped by a car of [[Juventus]] supporters, and a fight erupted. Policeman Luigi Spaccarotella intervened and opened fire, killing Gabriele Sandri with a single gunshot wound to his neck. The policeman was sentenced to nine years and five months in prison.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ilfattoquotidiano.it/2012/08/01/omicidio-sandri-cassazione-spaccarotella-consapevole-dei-rischi/313226/|title=Omicidio Sandri, la Cassazione: "Spaccarotella consapevole dei rischi"|date=1 August 2012|website=Il Fatto Quotidiano}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, he was freed in 2017 with semi-liberty.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.lanazione.it/arezzo/cronaca/arezzo-spaccarotella-gabbo-sandri-1.3512569|title=Il poliziotto Spaccarotella in semilibertà: "E' tornato anche ad Arezzo"|first=La|last=Nazione|date=5 November 2017|website=La Nazione}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*On 14 June 2008 in [[Varese]], Giuseppe Uva was stopped along with his friend Alberto Bigigoggero by two police officers, who demanded to see the two men's documents. Uva refused, angrily kicking at the door of a nearby house. Other police officers arrived at the scene and arrested Uva and Bigigoggero. Uva died the next morning. Signs of violence were on Uva's body, and Bigigoggero confirmed that Uva had been tortured. Attorney general Massimo Gaballo asked for ten years of imprisonment for each of the eight officers involved in Uva's death. However, none of the officers were charged. Uva's sister insisted that her brother was murdered, receiving support from [[Luigi Manconi]], who promised to fight for the truth.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://tg24.sky.it/cronaca/2019/07/08/morte-giuseppe-uva-cassazione-conferma-assoluzioni|title=Morte Uva, Cassazione conferma assoluzione poliziotti e carabinieri|first=Sky|last=TG24|website=tg24.sky.it}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*On 15 October 2009 in [[Rome]], 31-year-old Stefano Cucchi was stopped by five policemen after they had seen him selling transparent packaging to a man in exchange for money. Cucchi was arrested and brought to a police station, where officers found cocaine and hashish in his pocket, along with medicine for [[epilepsy]], as Cucchi was affected by the disease. Cucchi was described by officers as "a homeless foreigner", but he was an Italian who resided regularly at a home in Rome. Cucchi was beaten before his trial, which led him to walk with fatigue and with evident punch-inflicted injuries to his eyes. A week later, his condition worsened, as he continued to be tortured in custody, resulting in several fractures and a stay in the hospital. Cucchi died at the hospital on 22 October. Stefano's sister Ilaria became an activist since her brother's death, bringing national attention to the case and continuing to fight for justice. In 2019, two officers, Alessio di Bernardo and Raffaele d'Alessandro were sentenced to twelve years in jail for manslaughter.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2019/nov/14/italian-police-officers-jailed-12-years-2009-custody-death|title=Italian police officers jailed for 12 years over 2009 custody death|first=Lorenzo|last=Tondo|date=14 November 2019|via=www.theguardian.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*On 22 July 2020 in [[Piacenza]], seven [[Carabinieri]] were arrested after being accused of drug trafficking, receiving stolen goods, extortion, illegal arrest, torture, grievous bodily harm, embezzlement, abuse of office, and fraud. The "leader" of the group, officer Montella, arrested and charged people with fake proof of crimes that the detainees never committed, placing in the pockets of the people in custody the drugs that he smuggled.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.corriere.it/cronache/20_luglio_27/piacenza-carabinieri-arrestati-maresciallo-orlando-sentito-gip-in-30-anni-non-mai-avuta-sanzione-f9929098-cff2-11ea-b6b4-c1fd88d9cdd9.shtml|title=Piacenza, lo sfogo del maresciallo Orlando: "In 30 anni non ho mai avuto una sanzione"|first=Giuseppe|last=Guastella|date=27 July 2020|website=Corriere della Sera}}&lt;/ref&gt; A [[Morocco|Moroccan]] man was illegally arrested by the seven officers; the man accused Montella of punching him several times while in custody and reported that the officer laughed during the torture. Montella later admitted that he carried out the torture after initially trying to accuse only his colleagues.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://tg.la7.it/cronaca/parla-il-marocchino-vittima-dei-cc-di-piacenza-mi-misero-la-droga-in-tasca-26-07-2020-152176|title=Parla il marocchino vittima dei cc di Piacenza: 'Mi misero la droga in tasca'|website=TGLA7}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, many other cases of torture inside the police station and outside during arrests were reported, as in the case of a [[Nigeria]]n man who was approached by Montella; a photo of the man was taken during the arrest, showing him covered with blood. Montella claimed that the man "had a fall" during the arrest; however, prosecutors did not believe Montella's version of the events.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.ilmessaggero.it/italia/carabinieri_piacenza_cosa_succede_falanga_soldi_nigeriano_ultime_notizie_news-5367405.html|title=Carabinieri Piacenza, Falanga: "Soldi vinti al Gratta e vinci. Il nigeriano pestato? Cadde da solo"|website=www.ilmessaggero.it|date=25 July 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt; A [[Brazil]]ian woman accused marshal Orlando, one of the charged officers, of being forced to have sex with him through blackmail and intimidation, as the marshal threatened to have her deported back to Brazil. The woman was also beaten at the police station by Orlando; she reported that the seven officers consumed cocaine inside the police station several times, and orgies with prostitutes happened there; Orlando was the one who brought the drugs inside the station. Several prostitutes were also beaten and threatened by the officers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://tg24.sky.it/cronaca/2020/07/26/caserma-piacenza-trans-brasiliana|title=Caserma Piacenza, una trans brasiliana: 'Minacce e botte in caserma'|first=Sky|last=TG24|website=tg24.sky.it}}&lt;/ref&gt; The seven officers were sentenced between three and twelve years in prison.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.quotidiano.net/cronaca/carabinieri-caserma-levante-condanne-1.6545402|title=Carabinieri caserma Levante di Piacenza: 12 anni all'appuntato Montella. Tutte le condanne|date=July 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*On 1 July 2021, 52 prison guards were arrested and suspended on the charges of aggravated torture, aggravated ill-treatment and causing multiple injuries to a group of prisoners, who had demanded better [[Coronavirus]] protections, at the Santa Maria Capua Vetere prison in [[Caserta]] on 6 April 2020. A video footage emerged in which there were shocking scenes of prisoners being kicked, slapped and beaten with truncheons. This happened after a riot erupted in the prison as inmates demanded face masks and Covid-19 tests in reaction to an outbreak of the virus. The inmates were allegedly made to strip, kneel and be beaten by guards who wore helmets to conceal their identity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2021/jul/01/italian-prisons-under-fire-as-video-footage-shows-guards-beating-inmates|title = Italian prisons under fire as video footage shows guards beating inmates|website = [[TheGuardian.com]]|date = July 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Latvia ====
[[Latvia]] became an independent republic in 1918 and attempted to develop an effective and accepted police force, moving away from the untrusted [[Russian Empire|Russian Tsarist administration]]. Despite positive post-independence aims to reform the police system and to maintain public order and security, the [[State Police (Latvia)|Latvian police]] were underfunded and under-resourced. The [[Aizsargi|National Militia]] was created in response, consisting of a group of volunteers to protect public order.&lt;ref&gt;Melnis, E, Garonskis, A &amp; Matvejevs, A 2006, 'Development of the Policing in Latvia', ''Jurisprudencija''&lt;/ref&gt; Policing during this period was quite successful and was assimilated to what is today referred to as community policing.

From 1940 to 1991, [[Soviet occupation of Latvia in 1940|Latvia was occupied by the Soviet Union]], and all previous regulations and practices were overruled by the Communist regime, which brought in the Soviet [[militsiya]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Melnis|first1=E|last2=Garonskis|first2=A|last3=Matvejevs|first3=A|year=2006|title=Development of the Policing in Latvia|journal=Jurisprudencija|volume=1|issue=79|pages=72–84}}&lt;/ref&gt; Due to Soviet ideals on policing that considered criminals to be the enemy, a high level of institutional secrecy existed and meant that there was no independent review of policing. More significantly, the approach of community policing was replaced with a militarised authority based on Marxist ideologies. During this time, an imbalance existed between police actions and citizens' rights. Despite the lack of statistics, it is clear that police brutality was a major issue, as ustrated by the case where the former nominal head of the militsiya (in practice - the secret police of [[Committee for State Security of the Latvian Soviet Socialist Republic|the KGB of the Latvian SSR]]) [[Alfons Noviks]] was sentenced to life imprisonment in this time period for genocide against the Latvian people.&lt;ref&gt;Jeffries, I 2004, ''The countries of the former Soviet Union at the turn of the twenty-first century the Baltic and European states in transition'', Routledge, London, p. 190.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1991, the independence of the state of Latvia was restored, which saw another change in the police system with the implementation of the ''Law on Police'' on 5 June. This restructured the police into State, Security, and Local Government levels. The ''Law on Police'' reiterated ethical requirements, where police officers were prohibited from performing or supporting acts relating to "torture or other cruel, inhuman or demeaning treatment or punishment". However, despite these reforms, issues regarding police brutality arose among the Russian population living in Latvia; in 1998, police forces were accused of dispersing a rally of predominately Russian pensioners through the use of excessive force and brutality.&lt;ref&gt;Jeffries, I 2004, ''The countries of the former Soviet Union at the turn of the twenty-first century the Baltic and European states in transition'', Routledge, London, p. 192.&lt;/ref&gt; This hostility towards Russians remained in the following years, and despite lack of official statistics, police brutality continued to be an issue after Latvia's independence.

In 2005, the [[Latvian Centre for Human Rights|Latvian Center for Human Rights and Ethnic Studies]] (LCHRES) found some instances of brutality and "severe abuse" within police authorities, especially on persons in custody.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Latvia|url=https://2009-2017.state.gov/j/drl/rls/hrrpt/2005/61658.htm|access-date=15 August 2019|website=U.S. Department of State}}&lt;/ref&gt; Reports showed high levels of corruption within Latvian law enforcement authorities, with 42 members convicted of corruption offences between 2003 and 2004.&lt;ref name="autogenerated2006"&gt;U.S Department of State: Diplomacy in Action, 2006, Latvia, accessed 19 July 2016 &lt;nowiki&gt;[https://2009-2017.state.gov/j/drl/rls/hrrpt/2005/61658.htm United States Department of State]&lt;/nowiki&gt;.&lt;/ref&gt; For the Latvian community, this meant that should an incident of police brutality occur, they may not have an independent body to report to nor is it guaranteed to be handled impartially without corruption.

Reports from Latvian prisons illustrate cases where police batons were used to inflict serious harm to inmates, including causing broken ribs, which often were not medically assessed for up to two days. To address levels of police brutality, LCHRES conducted a study where it set up an anonymous hotline.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Prevention of Torture {{!}} Latvian Centre for Human Rights|url=http://cilvektiesibas.org.lv/en/projects/prevention-of-torture/|access-date=15 August 2019|website=cilvektiesibas.org.lv}}&lt;/ref&gt; During this four-day study, LCHRES received almost 300 calls and written complaints regarding police brutality and misconduct. This identifies fundamental flaws in the Latvian police authorities.

Since joining the [[European Union]] in 2004, the European Committee for the Prevention of Torture (CPT) has assessed the Latvian criminal justice system several times. While the CPT gives appropriate authorities recommendations for improvements such as a review board for ill-treatment, they found that in 2011, Latvian authorities did not enact any of their 2007 recommendations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Latvia should address ill-treatment by police and improve detention conditions|url=https://www.coe.int/en/web/portal/news-2013/-/asset_publisher/TEHtOeUO1Ozc/content/latvia-should-address-ill-treatment-by-police-and-improve-detention-conditions|access-date=15 August 2019|website=www.coe.int|language=en-GB}}&lt;/ref&gt; Their 2011 report outlined some cases of police brutality within the prison system, with allegations such as punching, kicking and a few cases of misuse of police batons and excessively tight handcuffing. This was alleged to occur mostly while being apprehended or at the police station (including during questioning).

Despite the flaws within the Latvian Police system, CPT has found that the number of allegations for poor treatment is decreasing over the years. The Latvian Police force operates under the Professional Ethics and Conduct Code of the State Police Personnel, which states "a police officer shall use force, special facilities or weapon only in the cases stipulated by due course of law and to attain a legal aim. The use of spontaneous or -intentioned force, special facilities or weapon shall not be justified",&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Valsts policija -|url=http://www.vp.gov.lv/?id=205&amp;said=205&amp;r=1|access-date=15 August 2019|website=www.vp.gov.lv}}&lt;/ref&gt; recognising that the authorities are conscious of police brutality, and given more time, it is likely that the figures will continue to decrease.

==== Luxembourg ====
The Luxembourg Police force has 1,603 officers and is known as the "Grand Ducal Police". The Grand Ducal Police is the primary law enforcement agency in Luxembourg and has been operating since 1 January 2000, when the Grand Ducal Gendarmerie (previous Luxembourg military) merged with the police force.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|date=1 January 1958|title=Luxembourg &amp;#124; Partners &amp; Agreements &amp;#124; Member States &amp;#124; Europol|url=https://www.europol.europa.eu/content/memberpage/luxembourg-779|access-date=29 January 2017|publisher=Europol}}&lt;/ref&gt; Due to Luxembourg's relatively small population of approximately 500,000 people, the Grand Ducal Police are in charge of several duties that are often separated by jurisdictions such as Border Control and Internal Military operations.&lt;ref name="police.public.lu"&gt;{{cite web|date=22 April 2016|title=L'inspecteur de police - Portail de la Police Grand-Ducale - 1000 métiers en 1|url=http://www.police.public.lu/fr/police-se-presente/1000-metiers/inspecteur/index.html|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170110204044/http://www.police.public.lu/fr/police-se-presente/1000-metiers/inspecteur/index.html|archive-date=10 January 2017|access-date=29 January 2017|publisher=Luxembourg police}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Police brutality is not perceived to be a serious threat to society in Luxembourg. The European Union's 2014 Anti-Corruption report placed Luxembourg, along with Denmark and Finland, as having the lowest incidents of reported police brutality within the European Union.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release|url=http://europa.eu/rapid/press-release_IP-14-86_en.htm|title=Commission unveils first EU Anti-Corruption Report|publisher=European Commission|date=3 February 2014|access-date=29 January 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Due to many positive characteristics of their society, such as freedom of media, the encouragement of public participation in the legal system, and transparency mechanisms, the public also have a deep trust in the Grand Ducal police force.

Laws in Luxembourg specifically distinguish between coercion and force in the 1973 Act on Regulating the Use of Force.&lt;ref name="books.google.it"&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=YGbNgL-m20AC|title=Schengen Investigated: A Comparative Interpretation of the Schengen ... - Chantal Joubert, Hans Bevers|date=3 June 1996|publisher=Martinus Nijhoff Publishers|isbn=978-9041102669|access-date=29 January 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; This Act regulates the use of police weapons and specific technical means of physical force used by police. However, this Act does not cover other forms of physical coercion by police officers such as the use of handcuffs as these are seen as basic police measures that do not require specific legislation. The officer must be legitimately executing his duty and his actions and must be compatible under the principles of proportionality, subsidiarity, reasonability, and measure to use force.&lt;ref name="books.google.it" /&gt; To ensure the Grand Ducal Police do not engage in police brutality, numerous safeguards and prevention methods are implemented. The police inspector (the term used for a common officer) must undergo legal and tactical training lasting an intensive 26 months followed by further training at an allocated police station.&lt;ref name="police.public.lu" /&gt; By way of comparison, the Victoria Police Academy only provides 33 weeks of tactical and legal training.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|date=25 May 2005|title=Victoria Police - Delivering a Safer Victoria|url=http://www.police.vic.gov.au/content.asp?Document_ID=2|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130409041623/http://www.police.vic.gov.au/content.asp?Document_ID=2|archive-date=9 April 2013|access-date=29 January 2017|publisher=Victoria Police (Australia)}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 2015 Human Rights Report on Government practices by the United States indicated no cases of police brutality in Luxembourg, suggesting that the Grand Ducal Police have effective mechanisms in place to investigate and punish potential abuse and corruption.

Although police brutality is almost nonexistent in Luxembourg, there are effective procedures in place for the investigation and punishment of any potential misconduct by the Grand Ducal Police.

==== Malta ====
Malta's Police Force (MPF) is one of the oldest in Europe, with the Maltese government taking over the force in 1921 following the grant of self-governance. There are approximately 1,900 members in the Force.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Malta police force|url=https://www.gov.mt/en/Services-And-Information/Business-Areas/Law%20Enforcement/Pages/Malta-Police-Force.aspx|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160703125311/http://gov.mt/en/Services-And-Information/Business-Areas/Law%20Enforcement/Pages/Malta-Police-Force.aspx|archive-date=3 July 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Under the Police Act of 1961, Part V deals with the use of force, where"police officers may use such moderate and proportionate force as may be necessary [...]" (Article 96);&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{cite web|url=https://legislation.mt/|title=LEĠIŻLAZZJONI MALTA|website=legislation.mt}}&lt;/ref&gt; however, according to Article 100, "It shall be considered as an offence against discipline if a police officer uses force for considerations extraneous to those permitted by law and the circumstances of the case".&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; As such, Malta recognizes the illegality of police brutality and can prosecute offending officials on these grounds.

Malta is expected to abide by the 2001 European Code of Ethics as a member of the [[European Union]], where "the police may use force only when strictly necessary and only to the extent required to obtain a legitimate objective."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://search.coe.int/cm/Pages/result_details.aspx?ObjectID=09000016805e297e|title=Council of Europe}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Similarly, the Council of Europe (of which Malta is a member) follows the five principles developed by the [[European Court of Human Rights]], where definition 16 states that police officers "may use reasonable force when lawfully exercising powers".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Hammarberg|first=Council of Europe, Commissioner for Human Rights, Mandate 2006–2012, Thomas|title=Commissioner for Human Rights – Opinion of the Commissioner for Human Rights, Thomas Hammarberg, concerning independent and effective determination of complaints against the police|url=https://wcd.coe.int/ViewDoc.jsp?p=&amp;id=1417857&amp;Site=COE&amp;BackColorInternet=DBDCF2&amp;BackColorIntranet=FDC864&amp;BackColorLogged=FDC864&amp;direct=true|access-date=18 July 2016|website=wcd.coe.int}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2008, Lawrence Gonzi (The Minister for Justice and Home Affairs) called upon Martin Scicluna, a former civil servant and currently an expert on security issues at the Prime Minister's Office, to conduct an independent inquiry into 24 March 2008 police brutality incident. The inquiry required the investigation of "allegations of beatings carried out on detainees at Safi Detention Centre by members of the Detention Service on 24 March 2008 and to make any recommendations necessary in the light of [his] findings".&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.coe.int/en/web/cpt/home|title=European Committee for the Prevention of Torture and Inhuman or Degrading Treatment or Punishment (CPT)|website=www.coe.int}}&lt;/ref&gt; Following the results of the inquiry of Scicluna, made public by the [[Government of Malta|Maltese Government]], it was concluded that "excessive force was used by Detention Service Personnel".&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;

Scicluna made recommendations that "appropriate [action] should be taken to reprimand the Detention Service officers involved in this operation and the relevant Senior NCOs for the acts of 25 excessive force used by some personnel in their charge".&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt; Simultaneously, Home Affairs Minister Carm Mifsud Bonnici said "95 percent of the members of the police force were doing their duties, but the remainder needed to be addressed",&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Ltd|first=Allied Newspapers|title=Police violence will not be tolerated – minister|url=http://www.timesofmalta.com/articles/view/20080706/local/cmb.215356|access-date=18 July 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; which led to the establishment of the Internal Affairs Unit (IAU) to "maintain and safeguard the integrity of the Malta Police Force through an internal system of investigation that is objective, fair, equitable, impartial and just",&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Malta Police Force Portal|url=http://www.pulizija.gov.mt/en-us/internalaffairs.aspx|access-date=18 July 2016|website=www.pulizija.gov.mt}}&lt;/ref&gt; where complaints or allegations on the use of force can be monitored and responded to.

Although Malta has attempted to tackle the police brutality through the implementation of independent systems such as the Internal Affairs Unit (IAU), the [[United States Department of State|US Department of State]] 2010 report on Malta's human rights found that "authorities detained irregular immigrants under harsh conditions for up to 18 months during the review of their protected status."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Malta|url=http://m.state.gov/md154438.htm|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160719085153/http://m.state.gov/md154438.htm|archive-date=19 July 2016|access-date=18 July 2016|website=m.state.gov}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, the 2013 US Department of State report found that although there were no government reports on the use of brutality in detention centers, on 2 December 2013 media reported the sentencing of two former prison guards to five years in prison and another two guards to three months in prison after finding them guilty of beating an escaped prisoner in 2008, illustrating the gradual development of the IAU in limiting the use of police brutality.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://2009-2017.state.gov/documents/organization/220518.pdf|title=MALTA 2013 HUMAN RIGHTS REPORT}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After the IAU was implemented, the [[United Nations Human Rights Committee|Human Rights Committee]] has raised questions on the use of force by state officials with respect to the countering of detention center riots, where police were accused of punching and striking detainees. An inquiry was consequently conducted in 2011 and 2012 following riots, resulting in criminal proceedings against the law enforcement officials responsible.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Human Rights Committee considers report of Malta|url=http://www.ohchr.org/en/NewsEvents/Pages/DisplayNews.aspx?NewsID=15167&amp;LangID=E|access-date=18 July 2016|website=www.ohchr.org}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, Giacomo Santini and Tina Acketoft (The Chairs of the Migration and Equality Committees of the Parliamentary Assembly of the [[Council of Europe]]) expressed "grave concern at an increasing number of incidents of state violence against migrants and refugees". They called upon Maltese authorities to conduct a rapid investigation emphasising the need to forbid violence against migrants and refugees, whether by state parties or by individuals.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=PACE: News|url=http://assembly.coe.int/nw/xml/News/News-View-EN.asp?newsid=4044&amp;lang=2|access-date=22 July 2016|website=assembly.coe.int}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Committee on the Elimination of Racial Discrimination]], concerning the conditions of migrants in detention, recommended that the "State party take appropriate measures to improve detention conditions and refrain from resorting to excessive use of force to counter riots by immigrants in detention centers, and also to avoid such riot".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www2.ohchr.org/english/bodies/cerd/docs/A.66.18.pdf|title=The Committee on the Elimination of Racial Discrimination}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===== List of alleged cases =====
{| class="wikitable sortable"
|-
!Date
!Persons Involved
!Description
!Resolution
|-
|October 2014
|David Calleja&lt;ref name=":7"&gt;{{cite web|title=Lawyer of man accused of biting constable claims his client was victim of police brutality – The Malta Independent|url=http://www.independent.com.mt/articles/2014-10-27/local-news/Lawyer-of-man-accused-of-biting-constable-claims-his-client-was-victim-of-police-brutality-6736124499|access-date=22 July 2016|website=www.independent.com.mt}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|"Ta' Xbiex resident David Calleja, a financial advisor, was driving in the Sliema Strand when he was stopped by police who deemed him to be driving recklessly.
The Malta Police Force issued a statement detailing what had happened, in which it claimed that Mr. Calleja acted aggressively, refused to take a breathalyser test, ignored police orders, and used foul language.

He was subsequently arrested and taken to a police squad car, but according to the police statement, he kicked the driver, tried to escape and banged his head repeatedly against the car window. The police added that he even spit blood at police officers and bit a constable's arm, tearing off part of his skin.

When asked to state his client's plea, Dr. Abela declared "absolutely not guilty," before accusing the police of grossly distorting the truth.

Mr. Calleja's nose was bandaged, and Dr. Abela presented a medical certificate showing that it had been broken as evidence. The lawyer also presented his client's blood-stained clothes – prosecuting inspector Jason Sultana originally objected, but relented after Dr. Abela said that this objection was due to the fact that the clothes helped confirm the injuries Mr. Calleja sustained."&lt;ref name=":7" /&gt;
|"Magistrate Marse-Ann Farrugia ultimately granted bail against a €10,000 personal guarantee, with Mr Calleja's father acting as his guarantor."&lt;ref name=":7" /&gt;
|-
|January 2015
|Not mentioned
|"The Commissioner of Police has referred a complaint of police brutality to the Duty Magistrate after a parent wrote to him saying his son was beaten while in police custody.
The man said his son was in a bar in Paceville when police went up to him because he was smoking. The man claimed that the police roughly manhandled his son, handcuffed him and threw him into a van where he was beaten up and suffered from lacerations to the head as well as bruised ribs and muscles."&lt;ref name="timesofmalta1"&gt;{{cite web|last=Ltd|first=Allied Newspapers|title=Commissioner refers alleged police brutality case to the duty magistrate|url=http://www.timesofmalta.com/articles/view/20150105/local/commissioner-refers-alleged-police-brutality-case-to-the-duty.550770|access-date=22 July 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|Ongoing inquiry&lt;ref name="timesofmalta1" /&gt;
|-
|March 2015
|Mifsud Grech
|"The police were called in and the customer left the restaurant as soon as he was ordered to. However, once on the pavement, he and two policemen, who in the meantime had been joined by others from the nearby station, were involved in what witnesses called a "commotion".
The customer ended up on the ground beneath several officers who were trying to arrest him.

He was subsequently charged with threatening the two officers while carrying out their duties, breaching the peace and refusing to give his particulars. He was cleared of the charges."&lt;ref name="timesofmalta2"&gt;{{cite web|last=Ltd|first=Allied Newspapers|title=Police take action against sergeant|url=http://www.timesofmalta.com/articles/view/20120813/local/Police-take-action-against-sergeant.432623|access-date=22 July 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|"In handing down judgment, Magistrate Depasquale said the court was "convinced" that the incident had not happened in the way that the police had alleged. He further noted that the police "may have used excessive force".&lt;ref name="timesofmalta2" /&gt;
|-
|May 2015
|Jean Paul Aquilina, 24-year-old Mosta man
|Aquilina, accused of assaulting policemen after he was pulled over for dangerous driving, struggled to explain how Aquilina suffered severe facial bruising and scratches to his body during the course of his arrest.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Dangerous driving case turns into police brutality investigation|url=http://www.maltatoday.com.mt/news/court_and_police/53475/drunk_driving_case_turns_into_police_brutality_investigation#.V5HTpFewGJU|access-date=22 July 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|Not mentioned
|-
|February 2016
|20-year-old Lee Michael Robertson from Xemxija&lt;ref name=":8"&gt;{{cite web|title=Paceville brawler alleges police brutality|url=http://www.maltatoday.com.mt/news/court_and_police/62317/paceville_brawler_alleges_police_brutality#.V5HMp1ewGJU|access-date=22 July 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|"Robertson had been attacked whilst at the bar, and had injured his hand. He rushed to the police station, she said, but once he arrived he had been told to clear out of the station and wipe the blood off his hand before going back in.
In the ensuing verbal exchange the officer, Defence lawyer Rachel Tua said, made offensive remarks about the accused's father. Robertson was then allegedly thrown to the ground by the officer, who slammed the man's head on the ground, the lawyer said, also claiming that the accused had his injured arm cruelly twisted while he was being handcuffed. She denied the prosecution's assertion that Robertson had assaulted police, adding that his friends had witnessed the incident and would be summoned to testify. Tua told magistrate Vella that the police refused to allow Robertson to speak to her during his arrest, instead of holding him overnight and taking a statement the next morning – with the police officer who allegedly delivered the beating present in the interrogation room. The police had not even told him why he was being arrested, she said."&lt;ref name=":8" /&gt;
|"The court ruled that the arrest was not illegal and granted Robertson bail against a personal deposit of €1,200 and a personal guarantee of €8,000, also ordering him to sign a bail book once a week and observe a curfew".&lt;ref name=":8" /&gt;
|}

==== Netherlands ====
{{Unbalanced section|date=March 2017}}
The Netherlands is signatory to the [[European Convention on Human Rights]]&lt;ref name="rightsinfo.org"&gt;{{cite web|date=19 April 2015|title=What Is The European Convention on Human Rights?|url=https://rightsinfo.org/the-rights-in-the-European-convention/|access-date=15 August 2019|website=RightsInfo|language=en-GB|archive-date=15 August 2019|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190815074931/https://rightsinfo.org/the-rights-in-the-european-convention/|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; detailing the limits and responsibilities of police powers, and as such demonstrates a public commitment to the restricted legal use of police powers. These powers include the use of reasonable force to enable the effective discharge of duties, with the stipulation force be used proportionately and only as a last resort&lt;ref name="rightsinfo.org" /&gt;

The police force of the Netherlands is divided into 25 regional forces and one central force. A Regional Police Board, made up of local mayors and the chief public prosecutor, heads each regional force, with a chief officer placed in charge of police operations. Police accountability procedures include mandatory reporting of any on-duty incident that requires the use of force. The Rijksrecherche is the national agency responsible for the investigation of serious breaches of police conduct resulting in death or injury. In 2007 the Rijksrecherche conducted 67 inquiries related to police officers, 21 of which were related to shootings.&lt;ref&gt;Lamboo, T 2010, "Police Misconduct: accountability of internal investigations" ''International Journal of Public Sector management,'' vol. 23, iss. 7, pp. 613-631.&lt;/ref&gt;

While Dutch society has a history of support for liberal values, it has been subject to practicing racial profiling and increased levels of police violence towards racial minorities. Van der Leun writes that suspicion and mistrust of some racial groups is evident and perpetuated by police attitudes at all levels of command.&lt;ref name="Leun, J. P 2011"&gt;van der Leun, J. P &amp; van der Woude, M. A. H 2011, 'Ethnic Profiling in the Netherlands? A reflection on expanding preventative powers, ethnic profiling and a changing social and political context', ''Policing and Society'', Vol. 21, No. 4, December 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; This trend in police behaviour has drawn comment from Amnesty International, where a 2015 report describes Dutch law enforcement officers as having a tendency to correlate suspicious criminal behaviour with specific ethnic characteristics, most notably those typical of persons of Moroccan heritage.&lt;ref&gt;Amnesty International 2015, 'Stop and Search Powers Pose Risk to Human Rights: Acknowledging and tackling ethnic profiling in the Netherlands', viewed online 19 July 2016 at {{cite web|title=Archived copy|url=https://www.amnesty.nl/sites/default/files/public/amnesty_stopandsearchpowersposearisktohumanrights.pdf|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20141005115357/http://www.amnesty.nl/sites/default/files/public/amnesty_stopandsearchpowersposearisktohumanrights.pdf|archive-date=5 October 2014|access-date=20 July 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Current political discourse in the Netherlands often supports the notion of inferiority of some cultures and is evidenced by the growth in support for far-right political ideologies in recent decades.&lt;ref name="Leun, J. P 2011" /&gt;

A notable case in racial profiling and the use of police force occurred in June 2015 with the death of Aruban man [[Mitch Henriquez]]. Henriquez died of asphyxiation while in police custody after being suspected of carrying a firearm and being arrested at a music festival in [[The Hague]]. The first anniversary of his death in June 2019 provided a catalyst for protests against police brutality in The Hague, an area with a significant proportion of residents of non-European background. Eleven protesters were arrested for failing to comply with instructions from the Mayor to limit protest to certain areas of the city, which led some protesters to claim authorities were attempting to criminalize the right to peaceful protest. The five officers alleged to be involved in Hendriquez's death have been suspended but have yet to be charged.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|date=27 June 2016|title=Police chokehold death protesters blocked from Hague neighborhood|url=https://nltimes.nl/2016/06/27/police-chokehold-death-protesters-blocked-hague-neighborhood|access-date=15 August 2019|website=NL Times|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Poland ====
[[File:Stan wojenny w Polsce - 1981-1983 - 08.JPG|thumb|right|260px|Polish [[ZOMO]] squads with [[baton (law enforcement)|police batons]] during [[martial law in Poland]], 1981–1983. The [[sarcasm|sarcastic]] caption reads "outstretched hands of understanding" or "outstretched hands for agreement".]]
The Polish police (''[[Policja]]'') force aims to "serve and protect the people, and to maintain public order and security".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.policja.pl/pol/english-version/4889,Polish-National-Police.html|title=Polish National Police|first=Polska|last=Policja|website=Policja.pl}}&lt;/ref&gt; Polish laws prohibit torture or degrading treatment and set out punishment for police officers including demotion and removal from the police force.&lt;ref name=":2"&gt;{{cite web|url=https://2009-2017.state.gov/documents/organization/220529.pdf|title=Poland 2013 Human Rights Report}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===== History =====
A key factor influencing the levels of police brutality in [[Poland]] has been the move from a communist state to a democracy. Force was particularly used by the [[ZOMO]] squads, which were elite units of [[Citizens' Militia|Citizens' Militia (MO)]] during the [[Polish People's Republic]].&lt;ref name="zomo-3"&gt;{{cite web|author=Michał Kępiński, pres.|date=2007|title=ZOMO|url=http://www.milicja.waw.pl/?zomo,3|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150406141101/http://www.milicja.waw.pl/?zomo,3|archive-date=6 April 2015|access-date=8 October 2013|work=Historia Milicji Obywatelskiej at Milicja.waw.pl|publisher=Fundacja Edukacji Historycznej}}&lt;/ref&gt; As a result, the opposition branded ZOMO with the nickname "Communist [[Gestapo]]". It is argued that Poland's transition has resulted in a more transparent system, reducing levels of police brutality.&lt;ref name=":3"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Krasnokutski|first=Shannon|date=2001|title=Human Rights in Transition: The success and Failure of Polish and Russian Criminal Justice Reform|url=http://scholarlycommons.law.case.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1469&amp;context=jil|journal=Case Western Reserve Journal|volume=33|issue=1}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although police brutality exists within Poland cases are much more likely to be handled by the criminal justice system with a greater chance for resolution through the courts.&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt;

While there are still instances of police brutality, trust in the police has steadily increased in Poland from 62% to 75% between 2002 and 2008,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite thesis|type=Master's thesis|last=Walker|first=Tabitha|date=2009|title=The Distrust Paradox: Trust and Distrust in the Polish Online Press, Cross National Data Reports and Public Opinion Surveys 2002–2008|url=https://cdr.lib.unc.edu/indexablecontent/uuid:10615342-c372-4fd1-ac0f-71850ef328c2|publisher= University of North Carolina}}&lt;/ref&gt; demonstrating the improvement in trust between the police and the general public.

Although there is a more open police force within Poland, many organizations still have issues against police brutality. The 2013 United States Department of State report on Poland raised several concerns of police brutality;&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt; The report cited a case of police officers using violence to acquire a confession for armed robbery in 2012,&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt; though it also noted that these police officers were eventually indicted for police brutality.&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt;

In year 2020 [[2020 women's strike protests in Poland|Polish women started protesting against new restrictions in abortion law]]. In response Polish police started arresting, use of gas against protesters and even beating them on the streets. Government states that use of force was necessary, even though there was no reported example of aggression on the side of protesters.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.euronews.com/2020/11/24/police-using-excessive-violence-against-peaceful-protesters-in-poland|title=Poland: Police using 'excessive violence' against peaceful protesters|first=Emma|last=Beswick|date=24 November 2020|website=euronews}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===== Issues with sports fans =====
{{See also|2015 Knurów riots|1998 Słupsk street riots}}
In recent years one of the main sources of controversy concerning Polish police brutality has been the use of rubber bullets to disperse uncooperative crowds at sporting events.

In 1998, [[1998 Słupsk street riots|major riots]] occurred when a young basketball fan was killed by the police. In 2004, a man was killed and a woman injured in a riot when Polish police accidentally shot live ammunition instead of rubber bullets into the crowd after an association football game.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://2009-2017.state.gov/j/drl/rls/hrrpt/2007/100578.htm|title=Poland|website=U.S. Department of State}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[2015 Knurów riots|Another set of riots]] occurred in 2015 in response to a [[pitch invasion]] during a football match. Although rubber bullets were used, one man was hit in the neck and later died at the hospital.&lt;ref name=":4"&gt;{{cite web|title=Football Fan Death Sparks Riots|url=http://www.newpolandexpress.pl/pdf_copies/newpolandexpress_305_2015-05-08.pdf|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20161003180859/http://www.newpolandexpress.pl/pdf_copies/newpolandexpress_305_2015-05-08.pdf|archive-date=3 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; A former police officer justified the use of weapons as a means to combat [[football hooliganism]].&lt;ref name=":4" /&gt; Protesters have characterized the detainment of sports fans protesting against the government as unfair and undemocratic.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Kibice Jagiellonii zatrzymani za protest|url=http://www.polskieradio.pl/43/265/Artykul/370212,Kibice-Jagiellonii-zatrzymani-za-protest|access-date=29 January 2017|publisher=Polskie Radio}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===== Issues with Roma =====
The Polish police also have a history of police brutality within the [[Roma in Poland|Roma community]].&lt;ref name=":5"&gt;{{cite web|title=OSCE Metting Statement on Roma in Poland|url=http://www.errc.org/article/osce-meeting-statement-on-roma-in-poland/285|publisher=European Roma Rights Centre}}&lt;/ref&gt; There are multiple cases of police beatings and other discriminatory acts against the Roma by the police.&lt;ref name=":5" /&gt; The European Roma Rights Centre argues that investigations into police brutality cases are seldom carried out and that the police brutality against the Roma minority is systematic.&lt;ref name=":5" /&gt;

One particular case of police brutality against the Romani people occurred in 1998 when the police took four Roma men to a field and beat them.&lt;ref name=":6"&gt;{{cite news|title=Police Beat four Roma near Ciechocinek, Poland|url=http://www.errc.org/article/police-beat-four-roma-near-ciechocinek-poland/1558|newspaper=European Roma Rights Centre}}&lt;/ref&gt; The men that were beaten were hospitalised for broken bones and other injuries; they were charged with vulgar words and behavior in public.

==== Portugal ====
[[Portugal]] is ranked the fourth most heavily policed country in the world.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=McCarthy|first=Niall|date=24 November 2014|title=• Chart: The most heavily policed countries in the world|url=https://www.statista.com/chart/2987/the-most-heavily-policed-countries-in-the-world/|access-date=29 January 2017|publisher=Statista}}&lt;/ref&gt; The police force is divided into five main organisations, with the [[Polícia de Segurança Pública]] (PSP) having the most prominent urban presence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|date=20 October 1945|title=Police in Portugal|url=http://www.safecommunitiesportugal.com/police-in-portugal/|access-date=29 January 2017|publisher=Safe Communities Portugal}}&lt;/ref&gt; The PSP has a diverse range of duties and responsibilities, which include protecting the rights of citizens and ensuring democratic legality.

The use of weapons by Portuguese police is permitted only when:

{{Blockquote|text=[...] absolutely necessary and when less dangerous means have proved ineffective, and provided that their use is proportionate to the circumstances.|author=Decreto-Lei No. 457/99 Art. 2(1) |source=&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pgdlisboa.pt/leis/lei_mostra_articulado.php?nid=1558&amp;tabela=leis |title=::: DL n.º 457/99, de 05 de Novembro |publisher=Procuradoria-Geral Distrital de Lisboa |date= 1999-11-05|access-date=2017-01-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; }}

This is restrictive on multiple counts; for example, police are not permitted to use their firearms when an offender is running away.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Rodrigues|first1=Ezequiel|last2=Faria|first2=Paula|last3=Santos|first3=Agostinho|last4=Fraga|first4=Sílvia|year=2015|title=Police shootings against civilians in Portugal: Contextual, forensic medical and judicial characterization|journal=Journal of Forensic and Legal Medicine|volume=33|pages=50–55|doi=10.1016/j.jflm.2015.04.008|pmid=26048497|hdl-access=free|hdl=10216/114703}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===== Football hooliganism =====
Portuguese police have adopted an aggressive position in combating football hooliganism. Despite their means being considered disproportionate, the police view the heavy-handed nature of their tactics as a necessary and successful approach towards protecting the community and maintaining social order.

In 2015, a viral video showed a Benfica fan being heavily beaten in front of his two children outside a football stadium. The footage, filmed by a local television station, showed Jose Magalhaes leaving the football match early with his children and elderly father before being confronted by police officers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|date=19 May 2015|title=Portugal police filmed hitting football fan in front of children|newspaper=BBC News|url=https://www.bbc.com/news/world-europe-32793901|access-date=29 January 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although the family appeared calm, Magalhaes was tackled to the ground by police and repeatedly hit with a metal baton, while his father was punched in the face twice.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|date=20 May 2015|title=Outrage in Portugal over police beating of man in front of his children |newspaper=The Guardian|agency=Associated Press|url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2015/may/20/outrage-in-portugal-over-police-beating-of-man-in-front-of-his-children|access-date=29 January 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; More police rushed to the scene to shield the children aged nine and thirteen.

A statement released by the PSP acknowledged the controversial incident and announced that an investigation was launched against the officer responsible for initiating the attack.&lt;ref name="safecommunitiesportugal.com"&gt;{{cite web|title=Public Statement by PSP Police concerning football violence at Guimarães and Lisbon {{!}} Safe Communities Portugal|url=http://www.safecommunitiesportugal.com/public-statement-by-psp-police-concerning-football-violence-at-guimar%C3%A3es-and-lisbon/|access-date=15 August 2019|website=www.safecommunitiesportugal.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; The officer was later suspended for 90 days by the Ministry of Internal Affairs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Officer caught beating Benfica fan suspended for 90 days|url=http://www.theportugalnews.com/news/officer-caught-beating-benfica-fan-suspended-for-90-days/35214|access-date=29 January 2017|publisher=The Portugal News}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The statement also defended policing the large crowds in the aftermath of the football match. Riot police had clashed with supporters the following day in Lisbon as fans celebrated Benfica's title victory. The harsh approach was described as sufficient, justified, and necessary to prevent the social disorder from escalating.&lt;ref name="safecommunitiesportugal.com" /&gt;

In a similar incident in 2016, another football club, Sporting Lisbon, complained about "barbaric" police assaults on their fans.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|date=19 May 2016|title=Sporting Lisbon complain of 'barbaric' assault by riot police on fans|url=http://www.espnfc.com.au/sporting-cp/story/2876295/sporting-lisbon-complain-of-barbaric-assault-by-riot-police-on-fans|access-date=29 January 2017|work=[[ESPN FC]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===== Racism =====
{{Update|section|date=March 2020}}
There have been suggestions of institutionalised racism within the Portuguese police force, with activists claiming that discrimination is the deep-rooted cause of police brutality in Portugal.&lt;ref name="bbc.comThey hate"&gt;{{cite news|last1=Fletcher|first1=James|date=23 April 2015|title=They hate black people|newspaper=BBC News|url=https://www.bbc.com/news/magazine-32419952|access-date=29 January 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; In its 2015/2016 annual report on Portugal, Amnesty International condemned the excessive force used by police against migrant and minority communities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Portugal 2015/2016 &amp;#124; Amnesty International|url=https://www.amnesty.org/en/countries/europe-and-central-asia/portugal/report-portugal/|access-date=29 January 2017|publisher=Amnesty International}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite a good record in migrant integration, historical parallels can be drawn between Portugal's colonial past and modern police racism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Marshall|first=Andrew|date=29 May 1961|title=Portugal: A Determined Empire|journal=The World Today|volume=17|issue=3|pages=95–101|jstor=40394108}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to activists, police have killed 14 young black men since 2001; however, no police officer has been held responsible for the deaths.&lt;ref name="bbc.comThey hate" /&gt;

Racially-influenced police actions are illustrated by the violence in Cova de Moura, a low socio-economic area housing a significant migrant population. Notably, during an incident in February 2015, a young man named Bruno Lopes was aggressively searched and physically abused.&lt;ref name="bbc.comThey hate" /&gt; When bystanders protested the excessive force, police responded by firing shotguns loaded with rubber bullets at the witnesses.&lt;ref name="bbc.comThey hate" /&gt;

On the same day, two human rights workers and five youth entered the [[Alfragide]] police station requesting information on Lopes' situation. Upon arrival, the group was allegedly attacked by police officers shouting racist slurs.&lt;ref name="bbc.comThey hate" /&gt; The policemen dragged and kept the young men in the police station, where they detained, mistreated, and mocked them for two days.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Reis|first1=Marta|title=Esquadra de Alfragide. MP fala de tortura e outros "tratamentos cruéis, degradantes ou desumanos"|url=https://ionline.sapo.pt/571713|access-date=1 November 2018|website=iOnline - Sapo}}&lt;/ref&gt;

17 police officers from the Alfragide police station were eventually sent to trial on a variety of charges, including physical aggression, torture, document forging, and aggravated kidnapping.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Costa|first1=Cátia|title=Juíza leva a julgamento 17 dos 18 polícias acusados de agressões|url=https://www.sabado.pt/portugal/detalhe/juiza-leva-a-julgamento-17-dos-18-policias-acusados-de-agressoes?ref=DET_relacionadas_portugal|access-date=1 November 2018|website=Sábado}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt; {{Update}} As of October 2018, the trial is ongoing, with victims being heard in court.&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Henriques|first1=Joana|title=Os polícias davam socos, pontapés. Estavam a gostar. Parecia o inferno|url=https://www.publico.pt/2018/09/21/sociedade/noticia/os-policias-davam-socos-pontapes-estavam-a-gostar-daquilo-parecia-o-inferno-1844823|access-date=1 November 2018|website=Público}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[European Commission against Racism and Intolerance]] (ECRI) has raised concerns about police mistreatment of minorities in Portugal in all of its reports on the country.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=ECRI - Country monitoring in Portugal|url=https://www.coe.int/en/web/European-commission-against-racism-and-intolerance/portugal|access-date=1 November 2018|website=CoE}}&lt;/ref&gt; In its fifth country report of 2018, ECRI mentions the Alfragide case in connection to the failure of IGAI ([[Inspeção-Geral da Admnisitração Interna|Inspeção-Geral da Administração Interna]]) or officers higher up in the chain of command to stop the abuses.&lt;ref name="Council of Europe"&gt;{{cite book|url=https://rm.coe.int/fifth-report-on-portugal/16808de7da|title=ECRI REPORT ON PORTUGAL (fifth monitoring cycle)|date=19 June 2018|publisher=Council of Europe|location=Strasbourg|page=26|access-date=1 November 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; IGAI is currently the body responsible for scrutinizing police activities in the country, but it is part of the Ministry of the Interior like the police forces.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Apresentação|url=https://www.igai.pt/quem-somos/apresentacao|access-date=1 November 2018|website=IGAI}}&lt;/ref&gt; In its 2018 report, ECRI recommended that such work should be carried out by the country's [[Ombudsman]], an equality body, or by a new and (entirely) independent body that can be created for that purpose.&lt;ref name="Council of Europe" /&gt;

Portuguese people of [[Romani people|Roma]] descent have also been victims of police harassment and brutality in the country. There are several examples publicized by the media: one case from 2007 involved a Roma man and his son. The two walked to the [[Nelas]] police station in [[Porto]] to get some information, but the police allegedly ended up abusing them. Two officers were convicted in 2011 for physically assaulting the father.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Lusa|title=Dois agentes da PSP condenados por agressão a cigano|url=https://www.dn.pt/portugal/norte/interior/dois-agentes-da-psp-condenados-por-agressao-a-cigano-1876502.html|access-date=1 November 2018|website=Diário de Notícias}}&lt;/ref&gt;

An example of police brutality that occurred in 2012 is the night raid of a Roma campsite by the GNR ([[Guarda Nacional Republicana]]), in [[Cabanelas]], [[Vila Verde]]. Some of the people living in the camp, including children and women, were reportedly attacked by GNR officers. Six Roma that were detained in the operation allege that they were later tortured and humiliated in the GNR station of [[Amares]]; the GNR denied the accusations, while [[SOS Racismo]] promised to file a complaint against the force.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Silva|first1=Samuel|title=GNR acusada de "torturar" ciganos detidos numa rusga em Vila Verde|url=https://www.publico.pt/2012/09/27/local/noticia/gnr-acusada-de-torturar-ciganos-detidos-numa-rusga-em-vila-verde-1564830|access-date=1 November 2018|website=Público}}&lt;/ref&gt; The last remnant of overt institutional racism, in Portugal, is article 81 of GNR's regulation law, which provides for an increased policing of nomadic people, who in general are known to be mostly Roma; the regulation's constitutionality was unsuccessfully challenged in the 1980s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Mendes|first1=Maria|title=Identidades, Racismo e Discriminação: Ciganos da AML|date=2012|publisher=Caleidoscópio|isbn=978-989-658-160-2|location=Lisbon|pages=83, 84}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Russia ====
Russian protests have gained media attention with the reelection of [[Vladimir Putin]] in 2012. More attention has been given to the frequency of police brutality shown on posted videos online. Then-president [[Dmitry Medvedev]] initiated reforms of the police force in an attempt to minimize the violence by firing the Moscow police chief and centralising police powers. Police divisions in Russia are often based on loyalty systems that favor bureaucratic power among political elites. Phone tapping and business raids are common practice in the country, and often fail to give [[due process]] to citizens. Proper investigations into police officials are still considered insufficient by Western standards.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Cops for hire|newspaper=The Economist|url=http://www.economist.com/node/15731344}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2012, Russia's top investigative agency investigated charges that four police officers had tortured detainees under custody. Human rights activists claim that Russian police use torture techniques to extract [[false confessions]] from detainees. Police regulations require officers to meet quotas for solving crimes, which encourages false arrests to meet their numbers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|date=29 March 2012|title=Russian Police Charged With Torture in Deadly Rape, Death of Detainee|work=Huffington Post|url=https://www.huffingtonpost.com/2012/03/29/russia-police-torture_n_1387421.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2022, during the Russian invasion of Ukraine, Russian police were seen attacking protesters.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://m.youtube.com/watch?v=z34pnK2l3pw |title=Censorship, arrests, shutdowns: Putin crushes Russian media &amp;#124; The Listening Post - YouTube |publisher=M.youtube.com |date=2022-03-12 |accessdate=2022-05-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the early days, when Russia was part of the Soviet Union, the secret police and authorities used to detain people and send certain people to the gulags.

==== Slovakia ====
Police brutality in Slovakia is systematic and widely documented, but is almost exclusively enacted on the Romani minority. The nation-state itself has particularly racist attitudes toward the Romani minority dating back to before the split of Czechoslovakia. It is widely known that the government practiced forced sterilisation of Romani women and the segregation of the Romani into walled-off settlements;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|date=20 October 2015|title=Slovakia Internationally Criticized For Forced Sterilisation, Police Impunity Against Roma|work=Romea|url=http://www.romea.cz/en/news/world/slovakia-internationally-criticized-for-forced-sterilization-police-impunity-for-brutality-against-roma-position-on-refugee}}&lt;/ref&gt; these forms of discrimination have filtered down to the police force. Excessive use of force against the Romani minority by police has been publicly criticised by the United Nations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Slovakia 2015/2016|work=Amnesty International|url=https://www.amnesty.org/en/countries/europe-and-central-asia/slovakia/report-slovakia/}}&lt;/ref&gt; The police force has been repeatedly condemned by several organisations for lengthy pre-trial detention and its treatment of suspects in custody.&lt;ref&gt;Cox, T (2013) 'Reflections on 1989 in Eastern Europe'  p 227, Routledge, {{ISBN|1-317-98039-5}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2001, a 51-year-old Romani man died as a result of abuse in police custody at the hands of the Mayor of Magnezitovce and his son who works as a police officer. The victim, Karol Sendrei, was allegedly chained to a radiator and fatally beaten after being forcefully removed from his home.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Comparative Criminology|work=San Diego State University|url=http://www-rohan.sdsu.edu/faculty/rwinslow/europe/slovakia.html|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160415144947/http://www-rohan.sdsu.edu/faculty/rwinslow/europe/slovakia.html|archive-date=15 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; While the mayor's son was immediately removed from the police force and the mayor was suspended from his position, the latter was reinstated four months later. In response to this incident, the Minister for Internal Affairs attempted to establish new measures to prevent police brutality by including mandatory psychological testing for law enforcement and better training around the effective use of coercion. However, police brutality toward the Roma minority remains a serious issue.

Video footage shot by law enforcement officers in 2009 shows 6 Romani boys aged between 6-16 being forced to strip naked, kiss, and slap each other. It is alleged that the boys were then set upon by [[police dog]]s, with at least two sustaining serious injuries. Officers attempted to justify their behaviour because the boys were suspected of theft against an elderly citizen; however, [[cruel]], [[inhuman or degrading treatment|inhuman, or degrading treatment]] by police, regardless of whether a crime has been suspected or committed, is prohibited under international law.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|date=29 April 2016|title=Slovakia: Roma exclusion and the dark side of democracy|work=Open Democracy|url=https://www.opendemocracy.net/can-europe-make-it/bernard-rorke/slovakia-roma-exclusion-and-dark-side-of-democracy}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 10 law enforcement officers involved have since been acquitted after the judge ruled the video inadmissible in court as it was obtained illegally. As the footage was the main piece of evidentiary support for the crime, without it a conviction could not be passed down.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|date=28 February 2016|title=Slovakia: Scandalous verdict acquits police of torturing Romani children|work=Romea|url=http://www.romea.cz/en/news/slovakia-scandalous-verdict-acquits-police-of-torturing-romani-children}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Human rights watchdog organisations have raised concerns around police selectivity in making recordings of raids after a raid in the settlement of Vrbica in 2015; the police claimed to have not thought the settlement would be problematic; this raid involved 15 men being seriously injured.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|date=15 July 2015|title=Slovak ombud says police raid on Roma settlement was unnecessary|work=Romea|url=http://www.romea.cz/en/news/world/slovak-ombud-says-police-raid-on-roma-settlement-was-unnecessary}}&lt;/ref&gt;

It is often the experience of the Roma in regards to pressing charges for police brutality, a counter charge is often threatened by law enforcement in an attempt to pressure the alleged victim into dropping the charges. It is generally an effective move as the hostile attitude toward the Roma in Slovakia is so entrenched that lawyers are often reluctant to represent Romani victims.&lt;ref&gt;Goldman, M (1999) 'Slovakia Since Independence: A Struggle for Democracy' p.137, Greenwood Publishing Group&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Slovenia ====
Minority groups in Slovenia, particularly the Roma and any residents from the former Yugoslav Republic face discrimination and sometimes brutality by Slovenian police.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Tyler|first=Tom R.|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=-AEXAwAAQBAJ&amp;q=police+brutality+slovenia&amp;pg=PA103|title=Legitimacy and Criminal Justice: An International Perspective|date=25 October 2007|publisher=Russell Sage Foundation|isbn=9781610445412|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Roma are major targets because of their being stereotyped as an inherently criminal population.&lt;ref name="Lobnikar 191–209"&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Lobnikar|first1=Branko|last2=Hozjan|first2=Urška|last3=Šuklje|first3=Tina|last4=Banutai|first4=Emanuel|date=3 April 2014|title=Policing a multicultural community: a case study of the Roma community in northeastern Slovenia|journal=International Journal of Comparative and Applied Criminal Justice|volume=38|issue=2|pages=191–209|doi=10.1080/01924036.2013.819025|s2cid=143516241|issn=0192-4036}}&lt;/ref&gt; They often live in illegal settlements in very low socio-economic conditions, which contributes to their discrimination and their reputation as criminals.&lt;ref name="Lobnikar 191–209" /&gt; They are one of the ethnic minorities from former Yugoslavic states known as "the erased" who, after Slovenia declared of independence in 1991, lost all legal status, social, civil, and political rights.&lt;ref name=":15"&gt;{{cite web|title=Slovenia|url=http://www.amnestyusa.org/our-work/countries/europe/slovenia#|access-date=22 July 2016|website=Amnesty International USA}}&lt;/ref&gt; This made them particularly vulnerable to police brutality. Their rights have not been fully restored yet.&lt;ref name=":15" /&gt; Due to their lack of rights and legal status, it is difficult to hold police officers accountable for offences committed against the Romani.

The police have been known to occasionally use excessive force against detainees in prisons, as well as foreigners and other minority groups, though no police officer has ever been arrested or charged.&lt;ref name="Lobnikar 191–209" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":15" /&gt; It is argued that authorities turn a blind eye to any allegations that arise because the victims are often from ethnic minorities, and there is a culture of racism within parts of the police force.&lt;ref name="Lobnikar 191–209" /&gt; When investigations are made, they are often ineffective.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=European Court of Human Rights, Slovenia|url=http://www.echr.coe.int/Documents/CP_Slovenia_ENG.pdf|access-date=22 July 2016|publisher=European Court of Human Rights}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The worst case of police brutality was the November 2012 protests; political dissatisfaction spurred a series of protests in Maribor, Slovenia. For the most part, the protests were peaceful;&lt;ref name="Why Slovenia is content no more"&gt;{{cite news|last1=Cain|first1=Phil|date=4 December 2012|title=Why Slovenia is content no more|work=BBC News|url=https://www.bbc.com/news/world-europe-20591820|access-date=22 July 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; the crowds chanted and behaved non-violently for about two hours on 26 November 2012 (also known as, "the second Maribor uprising").&lt;ref name="Why Slovenia is content no more" /&gt; However, the violence began when crowds moved towards an area with a heavy police presence.&lt;ref name="dnevnik.si"&gt;{{cite web|title=Last in Maribor interior minister also flew when they are blasted by Kramberger (In Slovenian)|url=https://www.dnevnik.si/1042565173/slovenija/zadnjic-je-v-maribor-notranji-minister-tako-priletel-ko-so-pocili-krambergerja/|access-date=22 July 2016|website=dnevnik}}&lt;/ref&gt; Police used excessive force to disperse the crowds, including tear gas, dragging and beating protesters, police dogs, and mounted police who indiscriminately charged into the crowd.&lt;ref name="dnevnik.si" /&gt; Civilians, protesters, and journalists were all targeted.&lt;ref name="dnevnik.si" /&gt; Authorities attempted to justify the use of force by claiming protesters were violent and the use of force was necessary and not excessive. Slovenian media sources reported that the protest only turned violent after the police started using physical force.&lt;ref name="dnevnik.si" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Why Slovenia is content no more|url=http://www.mladina.si/118142/vinko-gorenak-demonstracije-so-ilegalne-niso-prijavljene-in-niso-dovoljene/|access-date=22 July 2016|website=mladina}}&lt;/ref&gt; This level of violence was unprecedented and entirely unexpected in Slovenia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Cain|first1=Phil|date=4 December 2012|title=Vinko Gorenak: Demonstrations are illegal, not registered and are not allowed|work=BBC News|url=https://www.bbc.com/news/world-europe-20591820|access-date=22 July 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Since 2003, Slovenian authorities have attempted to rectify this discrimination by introducing a two-day training programme on policing in a multi-ethnic community.&lt;ref name="Pliceand Minority Groups"&gt;{{cite web|title=Pliceand Minority Groups|url=https://www.amnesty.nl/sites/default/files/public/ainl_police_and_minority_groups__eng_0.pdf6|access-date=22 July 2016|website=Amnesty International USA}}{{dead link|date=November 2017|bot=InternetArchiveBot|fix-attempted=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt; The programme involved teaching the police about Roma culture and their language which helped to break down some of the stereotypes that caused tension.&lt;ref name="Pliceand Minority Groups" /&gt; The Roma were made aware of their rights, and the police were educated about national and international standards regarding the treatment of minorities.&lt;ref name="Pliceand Minority Groups" /&gt; It also helped to build trust between the Roma community and the police.&lt;ref name="Pliceand Minority Groups" /&gt; Tensions still exist between the two groups, especially concerning police who have not participated in this programme; however, they have been greatly reduced.&lt;ref name="Pliceand Minority Groups" /&gt;

==== Spain ====
[[File:Demonstration in front of the headquarters of the Spanish National Police in Barcelona.png|thumb|[[2017 Catalan general strike]] against police brutality]]
Two notable demonstrations were the ones that occurred in Barcelona on 27 May 2011, and in Madrid on 25 September 2012. Video footage published online showed the use of force by police against peaceful demonstrators on both occasions. Images show officers using handheld batons to repeatedly hit peaceful demonstrators (some of them in the face and neck), rubber bullets, pepper spray, and the injuries caused.&lt;ref name="amnesty.org"&gt;{{cite web|title=Spain 2015/2016|url=https://www.amnesty.org/en/countries/europe-and-central-asia/spain/report-spain|access-date=22 June 2016|website=Amnesty International}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite public outrage, the Spanish government did not make any attempt to reform policing and police mistreatment of the public; the opposite happened instead: in July 2016, new reforms to the law on Public Security and the Criminal Code were enforced which limited the right to freedom of assembly and gave police officers the broad discretion to fine people who show a "lack of respect" towards them.&lt;ref name="amnesty.org" /&gt; The Law on Public Security also includes an offence of spreading images of police officers in certain cases. The UN Human Rights Commission has expressed concern at the impact this legislation could have on human rights and police accountability.&lt;ref name="amnesty.org" /&gt; Fines for insulting a police officer can be up to €600 and as much as €30,000 for spreading damaging photos of police officers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Spain's New Public Safety Law Has Its Challengers| newspaper=The New York Times | date=30 June 2015 |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2015/07/01/world/europe/spains-new-public-safety-law-has-its-challengers.html?_r=1|access-date=22 June 2016| last1=Minder | first1=Raphael }}&lt;/ref&gt; Amnesty International identifies three main areas of concern about police action during demonstrations and assemblies: excessive use of force and inappropriate use of riot equipment, excessive use of force when arresting demonstrators, and poor treatment of detainees in police custody.&lt;ref name="amnesty.org" /&gt;

[[File:Intervenció policial a Institut Pau Claris de Barcelona l'1 d'octubre de 2017.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Spanish National Police]] storm polling station during the [[2017 Catalan independence referendum]].]]
Amnesty International and ACODI (Acción Contra la Discriminación) have both called out Spain for racial profiling and ethnic discrimination.&lt;ref name="https"&gt;{{cite web|title=Spain: Discrimination condoned by the authorities|url=https://www.amnesty.org/en/latest/news/2011/12/spain-discrimination-condoned-authorities/|access-date=22 June 2016|website=Amnesty International|date=14 December 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="opensocietyfoundations.org"&gt;{{cite web|title=Case Watch: Challenging Police Abuse in Spain|url=https://www.opensocietyfoundations.org/voices/case-watch-challenging-police-abuse-spain|access-date=22 June 2016|website=Open Society Foundations}}&lt;/ref&gt;
ACODI documented 612 cases of racial discrimination in a single year, emphasising that many of these did not lead to official complaints because victims feared police retaliation or believed their complaints would be ignored.&lt;ref name="opensocietyfoundations.org" /&gt; This belief is not unfounded; in 2005, Beauty Solomon, an African American immigrant working as a prostitute, filed two criminal complaints against Spanish policemen for repeated harassment and physical assault. Despite eyewitness testimony and medical reports confirming her injuries the Spanish Courts dismissed her claims on the grounds of insufficient evidence.&lt;ref name="opensocietyfoundations.org" /&gt; Solomon then took her case to the European Court of Human Rights, who unanimously ruled in her favour that Spain had violated Article 3 (prohibition of inhuman and degrading treatment) and Article 14 (prohibition of discrimination) of the European Convention of Human Rights. They also condemned Spain for failing to investigate both Solomon's assault and other racist and sexist acts of violence by police officers.&lt;ref name="opensocietyfoundations.org" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Beauty Solomon vs. Spain, discrimination based on race, gender and social status|url=http://www2.womenslinkworldwide.org/wlw/new.php?modo=detalle_proyectos&amp;dc=26&amp;lang=en|access-date=22 June 2016|website=Women's Link Worldwide|archive-date=17 August 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160817075950/http://www2.womenslinkworldwide.org/wlw/new.php?modo=detalle_proyectos&amp;dc=26&amp;lang=en|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Under Spanish law, the police have the right to check the identity of anyone in a public space when there is a security concern. However, African and Latin American immigrants are most frequently targeted, often without a legitimate security concern. "People who do not 'look Spanish' can be stopped by police as often as four times a day," said Izza Leghtas, an Amnesty International researcher.&lt;ref name="https" /&gt;

==== Sweden ====
{{POV section|date=April 2020}}
According to David Grobgeld of the [[Center for a Stateless Society]], since the REVA (Legally Certain and Efficient Enforcement) project had been applied in Sweden in an attempt to deport illegal immigrants, it had exposed the brutal and illegal methods used by police. Officers have been shown to harass and racially profile non-white Swedes who often live in segregated suburbs. The marginalised such as the poor, homeless, people of colour, users of illicit drugs, and the mentally ill are facing Sweden as a Police State. This has resulted in social disobedience with ordinary people in Sweden updating others on Twitter and Facebook on the whereabouts of police.&lt;ref name="Grobgeld"&gt;{{cite web|title=Swedish Police, Racism And Resistance|url=https://c4ss.org/content/22562|access-date=20 July 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===== Examples =====
In 2013 police shot a man in his own home in front of his wife in the town of Husby, a suburb of Stockholm. The police alleged the man had been wielding a machete and threatening them with it. The Stockholm riots were set off after the Husby shooting, where more than 100 cars were torched. When the police showed up they had stones thrown at them. People said the police called them "monkeys" and used batons against them in the clash.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|date=22 May 2013|title=Riots grip Stockholm suburbs after police shooting – BBC News|language=en-GB|work=BBC News|url=https://www.bbc.com/news/world-europe-22622909|access-date=20 July 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In another incident in 2013, an African-born Swede was refused entry into a local club in [[Malmö]] for wearing traditional African clothes. The police picked him up and in the process of his arrest broke his arm and locked him in a cell for nearly six hours with no medical aid. Socially excluded groups have been targeted and the result of police investigations often means the police officers are not deemed to be at fault.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Sweden punishes its rioters and its police very differently|website=[[TheGuardian.com]]|date=27 May 2013 |url=https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2013/may/27/sweden-punishes-rioters-police-stockholm-riots|access-date=20 July 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Grobgeld, the common denominator for people on a special police list is being or married to a [[Romani people|Romani person]]. A register of 4029 Romani people is kept by police. The police say the document is a register of criminals and their associates and is used to fight crime in [[Skåne County]] despite people being on it that have no connection with Skåne or any association with criminal people.&lt;ref name="Grobgeld"/&gt; According to Grobgeld, police target apparent ethnicity at Stockholm subways for ID-checks to see if they are illegal immigrants. The police claim that they are "following orders", the "rule of law" and "democratic process".&lt;ref name="Grobgeld"/&gt;

In February 2016, a nine-year-old was accused of not paying for a railway ticket in Malmö. The police ordered the local security guards to stop the child. One guard tackled him to the ground and sat on him. He then pushed the child's face into the pavement hard and covered his mouth. The child can be heard screaming and gasping on the video that has gone viral on the internet. The police then put him in handcuffs.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=Guards investigated after child 'assault' in Malmö|work=[[The Local]]|url=http://www.thelocal.se/20150209/station-guards-accused-of-violent-assault-on-boy-9|access-date=20 July 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Switzerland ====
*1999, Zurich: Khaled Abuzarifa died of suffocation after being bound and gagged by his police escort at the Zurich airport.&lt;ref name=":19" /&gt;
*November 2016, Bex: Hervé Mandundu was shot several times and killed by police, who claim he tried to attack him with a knife. This account is disputed by his neighbors.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=Bex : Il y a un an, Hervé mourrait sous les balles de la police !|url=https://renverse.co/infos-locales/Bex-Il-y-a-un-an-Herve-mourrait-sous-les-balles-de-la-police-1291|access-date=10 June 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*October 2017, Lausanne: Lamin Fatty was mistaken for another person with the same name and detained. He was found dead in his jail cell the following day.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=Manifestation à Lausanne contre la violence policière|language=fr|work=24 heures|url=https://www.24heures.ch/vaud-regions/lausanne-region/manifestation-lausanne-jeune-decede-cellule/story/22298144|access-date=10 June 2020|issn=1424-4039}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*February 2018, Lausanne: Mike Ben Peter was held to the ground by police for six minutes. He then collapsed and died of cardiac arrest twelve hours later. There were reports that he was repeatedly kicked by the police in his genital area, and an autopsy confirmed severe bruising in this region. The police officers involved were not suspended, but have been charged with negligent homicide in an ongoing case.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=Auch die Schweiz hat einen "George Floyd"-Fall|url=https://www.blick.ch/news/schweiz/tod-nach-polizeigewalt-in-lausanne-auch-die-schweiz-hat-einen-george-floyd-fall-id15921105.html|access-date=10 June 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*May 2001, Valais: Samson Chukwu died of suffocation as a police officer put his weight on the back of a face-down Chukwu. Authorities originally claimed he died of a heart attack, but an autopsy later showed that postural asphyxiation led to Chukwu's death.&lt;ref name=":19"&gt;{{cite web|title=Swiss deportation measures to be changed|url=https://www.swissinfo.ch/eng/swiss-deportation-measures-to-be-changed/2651980|access-date=10 June 2020|website=SWI swissinfo.ch|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|date=9 May 2001|title=Le Nigérian décédé en Valais n'est pas mort d'une crise cardiaque ordinaire|language=fr|work=Le Temps|url=https://www.letemps.ch/suisse/nigerian-decede-valais-nest-mort-dune-crise-cardiaque-ordinaire|access-date=10 June 2020|issn=1423-3967}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*2001, Bern: Cemal Gomec was attacked by police officers with batons to the head, irritant gas, a shock grenade, rubber bullets. A sedative is said to have led to cardiac arrest which led to his death a few days later.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=Herschkowitz war Arzt im Fall Cemal G.|language=de|work=Tages-Anzeiger|url=https://www.tagesanzeiger.ch/schweiz/standard/herschkowitz-war-arzt-im-fall-cemal-g/story/12742781|access-date=10 June 2020|issn=1422-9994}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== United Kingdom ====
{{See also|#Northern Ireland (UK)|List of cases of police brutality in the United Kingdom}}
In 2015 the [[United Kingdom]] employed approximately 126,818 police officers in the 43 police forces of England, Wales and the [[British Transport Police]], the lowest number since March 2002.&lt;ref name="gov.uk"&gt;{{cite web|title=Police workforce, England and Wales: 31 March 2015|url=https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/police-workforce-england-and-wales-31-march-2015/police-workforce-england-and-wales-31-march-2015|access-date=29 January 2017|publisher=Home Office}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===== Legislation and treaties =====
The 1967 Criminal Law Act, the 2008 Common Law and the Criminal Justice and Immigration Act, the 1984 Police and Criminal Evidence Act, and the [[European Convention on Human Rights]] (ECHR) set out the law and acceptable use of force in the UK. The use of unnecessary physical force is in principle an infringement of ECHR Article 3.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|date=23 October 2013|title=Police use of force|url=https://www.app.college.police.uk/app-content/public-order/core-principles-and-legislation/police-use-of-force/|access-date=29 January 2017|publisher=College of Policing}}&lt;/ref&gt; The use of force should be "reasonable" in the circumstances. Physical force is considered appropriate if:
*it is absolutely necessary for a purpose permitted by law, and
*the amount of force used is reasonable and proportionate
This requires a consideration of the degree of force used. Any excessive use of force by a police officer is unlawful and an officer could be prosecuted under criminal law.

===== Findings and statistics =====
Since 2004/05, the Independent Police Complaints Commission (IPCC) published complaint statistics reports for England and Wales. In the 2014/15 annual report, the IPCC reported that there were 17 deaths in or following police custody and only one fatal police shooting from 2014 to 2017.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|date=23 July 2015|title=Annual report on deaths during or following police contact in 2014/15 published &amp;#124; Independent Police Complaints Commission|url=https://www.ipcc.gov.uk/news/annual-report-deaths-during-or-following-police-contact-201415-published|access-date=29 January 2017|publisher=Independent Police Complaints Commission}}&lt;/ref&gt; These figures more than doubled when the IPCC was first erected. The annual report for 2015/16 was published on 26 July 2016. A total of 37,105 complaints were recorded in 2014/15, marking a 6% increase to the previous year, and a 62% overall increase since 2004/05.&lt;ref name="ipcc.gov.uk"&gt;{{cite web|title=Police complaints - Statistics for England and Wales 2013/14 and 2012/13|url=https://www.ipcc.gov.uk/sites/default/files/Documents/research_stats/complaints_statistics_2014_15.pdf|access-date=29 January 2017|archive-date=27 October 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20161027043046/http://www.ipcc.gov.uk/sites/default/files/Documents/research_stats/complaints_statistics_2014_15.pdf|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; Allegations of "neglect or failure in duty" accounted for 34% of all allegations recorded while "other assault" and "oppressive conduct" or harassment made up only 8% and 6% respectively.&lt;ref name="ipcc.gov.uk" /&gt;

===== Public dissatisfaction and discrimination =====
Despite an average reduction in deaths in custody since 2004, a 2014 Public Confidence Survey revealed that public satisfaction following contact with the police was falling and that there was a greater willingness to file a complaint.&lt;ref name="ipcc.gov.uk" /&gt; The Metropolitan Police, who operate in some of the most ethnically diverse parts of the UK, received the greatest number of complaints in 2014/15 at 6,828 claims. However, young people and people from black or minority ethnic groups were much less likely to come forward with complaints.&lt;ref name="ipcc.gov.uk" /&gt;

While instances of police brutality in the UK is comparatively less than its US counterpart, there are nonetheless high profile incidents that have received wide media coverage.{{citation needed|date=July 2019}}

===== Examples =====
In May 2013, 21-year-old Julian Cole was arrested outside a nightclub in [[Bedford]] by six police officers. The altercation left Cole in a vegetative state due to a severed spinal cord. Expert evidence indicated that Cole was struck with considerable force on his neck whilst his head was pulled back.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Vikram Dodd|date=26 January 2015|title=Julian Cole family hit out at IPCC over police brutality allegations &amp;#124; UK news|newspaper=The Guardian|url=https://www.theguardian.com/uk-news/2015/jan/26/julian-cole-ipcc-police-brutality-allegations|access-date=29 January 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Despite calls by the IPCC to suspend the officers, Bedfordshire chief constable Colette Paul refused to place the six police officers on restricted duties despite being under criminal investigation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Vikram Dodd|date=11 February 2015|title=Suspend officers involved in broken neck incident, family tells police chief &amp;#124; UK news|newspaper=The Guardian|url=https://www.theguardian.com/uk-news/2015/feb/11/suspend-offcers-involved-in-broken-neck-incident-family-tells-police-chief|access-date=29 January 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Bedfordshire police denied allegations that the use of excessive force on Cole was race-related.

On 20 February 2014, [[Bedfordshire Police]] Constables Christopher Thomas and Christopher Pitts, chased Faruk Ali before allegedly knocking him over and punching him in the face outside his family home. Ali was described as an autistic man who had the mental age of a five-year-old.&lt;ref name="ReferenceB"&gt;{{cite news|date=7 April 2016|title=Faruk Ali case: Bedfordshire Police officers sacked for gross misconduct|work=BBC News|url=https://www.bbc.com/news/uk-england-beds-bucks-herts-35987385|access-date=29 January 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; The police officers, who were accused of laughing throughout the ordeal, were cleared of misconduct in public office by the [[Aylesbury Crown Court]]. Following an investigation by the IPCC, the officers were fired following breaches of standards of professional conduct including standards of honesty, integrity, authority, equality, and diversity.&lt;ref name="ReferenceB" /&gt;

On 13 July 2016, 18-year-old Mzee Mohammed died in police custody after being detained by Merseyside police at a Liverpool shopping centre. Officers were called to the scene after Mzee was allegedly behaving aggressively and erratically while armed with a knife. After successfully detaining Mzee, the police called an ambulance after Mzee suffered a "medical episode" and was pronounced dead.&lt;ref name="theguardian.com"&gt;{{cite news|last1=Reporter|first1=Frances Perraudin North of England|date=18 July 2016|title=Mzee Mohammed death: Liverpool mayor promises transparent inquiry &amp;#124; UK news|newspaper=The Guardian|url=https://www.theguardian.com/uk-news/2016/jul/18/mzee-mohammed-death-liverpool-mayor-transparent-inquiry|access-date=29 January 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Video evidence surfaced showing Mohammed surrounded by officers and paramedics, seemingly fully unconscious while being placed face down with his hands handcuffed behind his back. Questions remain about how appropriate medical condition could have been administered given how the handcuffs would restrict breathing.&lt;ref name="theguardian.com" /&gt; Mohammed is the 21st black person to die in police custody in six years.{{citation needed|date=December 2020}}

=== North America ===
==== Canada ====
{{Main|List of cases of police brutality in Canada}}
There have been several high-profile cases of alleged police brutality, including the [[2010 G20 Toronto summit protests]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Medics at G20 protests speak out against police brutality|url=http://rabble.ca/news/2010/07/medics-g20-protests-speak-out-against-police-brutality-0|access-date=2 October 2015|work=rabble.ca|date=5 July 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt; the [[2012 Quebec student protests]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Police violence on the rise in Montreal|url=http://rabble.ca/news/2012/03/police-violence-rise-montreal|access-date=2 October 2015|work=rabble.ca|date=23 March 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt; the [[Killing of Robert Dziekański|Robert Dziekański Taser incident]], and the [[shooting of Sammy Yatim]]. The public incidents in which police judgments or actions have been called into question raised concerns about police accountability and governance.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|date=25 May 2014|title=Police Investigating Police: A Critical Analysis of the Literature &amp;#124; Civilian Review and Complaints Commission for the RCMP|url=https://www.crcc-ccetp.gc.ca/en/police-investigating-police-critical-analysis-literature|access-date=29 January 2017|publisher=Civilian Review and Complaints Commission for the RCMP}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 16 March 2014, 300 people were arrested in Montreal at a protest against police brutality.{{citation needed|date=December 2020}}

==== United States ====
{{Main|Police brutality in the United States}}
[[File:Wattsriots-policearrest-loc.jpg|thumb|upright|LAPD officers restrain a man during the [[Watts Riots]], August 1965.]]
In the United States, major political and social movements have involved excessive force by police, including the [[civil rights movement]] of the 1960s, anti-war demonstrations, the [[War on Drugs]], and the [[Global War on Terrorism]]. In 2014, the UN Committee against Torture condemned police brutality and excessive use of force by law enforcement in the US, and highlighted the "frequent and recurrent police shootings or fatal pursuits of unarmed black individuals".&lt;ref&gt;Stephanie Nebehay (28 November 2014). [https://www.reuters.com/article/us-usa-un-torture-idUSKCN0JC1BC20141128 U.N. torture watchdog urges U.S. crackdown on police brutality] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20151123034857/https://www.reuters.com/article/2014/11/28/us-usa-un-torture-idUSKCN0JC1BC20141128 |date=23 November 2015 }}. ''Reuters''. Retrieved 19 March 2015.&lt;/ref&gt; The United Nations' Working Group of Experts on People of African Descent's 2016 report noted that "contemporary police killings and the trauma that they create are reminiscent of the past racial terror of [[Lynching in the United States|lynching]]."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Tharoor|first=Ishaan|date=27 September 2016|title=U.S. owes black people reparations for a history of 'racial terrorism,' says U.N. panel|newspaper=[[The Washington Post]]|url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/worldviews/wp/2016/09/27/u-s-owes-black-people-reparations-for-a-history-of-racial-terrorism-says-u-n-panel/|access-date=1 May 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Seven members of the United States Maryland military police were convicted for the [[Abu Ghraib torture and prisoner abuse]] incidents in Iraq.&lt;ref name=":18"&gt;{{Cite news|date=10 April 2017|title=Iraq Prison Abuse Scandal Fast Facts|work=CNN|url=http://www.cnn.com/2013/10/30/world/meast/iraq-prison-abuse-scandal-fast-facts/index.html|access-date=26 September 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Detainees were abused within the prison by being forced to jump on their naked feet, being videotaped in sexually exploitative positions, having chains around their neck for photos, and being kept naked for days.&lt;ref name=":18" /&gt;

The United States has developed a notorious reputation for cases of police brutality. The United States has a far higher number of police killings compared to other Western countries.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|date=17 December 2015|title=American police shoot and kill far more people than their peers in other countries|language=en|work=Vox|url=https://www.vox.com/cards/police-brutality-shootings-us/us-police-shootings-statistics|access-date=17 August 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|last=Hirschfield|first=Paul|title=Why do American cops kill so many compared to European cops?|language=en|work=The Conversation|url=https://theconversation.com/why-do-american-cops-kill-so-many-compared-to-European-cops-49696|access-date=17 August 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; U.S. police killed 1,093 people in 2016 and 1,146 people in 2015.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The Counted: People Killed by Police in the US|url=https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/ng-interactive/2015/jun/01/the-counted-police-killings-us-database|access-date=3 November 2019|website=[[The Guardian]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Mass shootings in the United States|Mass shootings]] have killed 339 people since 2015, whereas police shootings over the same time span claimed the lives of 4,355 people.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Fassler|first=Ella|date=14 July 2019|title=Presidential Candidates Can't Discuss Gun Deaths Without Discussing Cops|url=https://truthout.org/articles/presidential-candidates-cant-discuss-gun-deaths-without-discussing-cops/|access-date=14 July 2019|website=[[Truthout]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; An FBI homicide report from 2012 observed that while black people represent 13% of the US population, they amounted to 31% of those killed by police,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|date=17 December 2015|title=There are huge racial disparities in how US police use force|language=en|work=Vox|url=https://www.vox.com/cards/police-brutality-shootings-us/us-police-racism|access-date=17 August 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; and were responsible for 48% of police murdered. It was found through Kaiser Family Foundation research that almost half of Black Americans believe they have been victimized by law enforcement.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title=Protest Structures: Responses from Nigerians in the United States to Police Brutality and #BlackLivesMatter Protests|journal=Journal of Language and Social Psychology |url=https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/abs/10.1177/0261927X211049473|access-date=2022-02-18|date=January 2022 |volume=41 |issue=1 |pages=29–48 |doi=10.1177/0261927X211049473|s2cid=240338987|last1=Acheme |first1=Doris E. |last2=Cionea |first2=Ioana A. }}&lt;/ref&gt; The FBI 2019 Law Enforcement Officers Killed and Assaulted report, Table 42 reports that black persons were responsible for 37% of all officers killed from 2012 through 2019.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://ucr.fbi.gov/leoka/2019/tables/table-42.xls|title = Table 42}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to a 2021 study published in ''[[The Lancet]]'', more than 30,000 people were [[Police use of deadly force in the United States|killed by police in the United States]] between 1980 and 2018.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Sharara |first1=Fablina |last2=Wool |first2=Eve E |display-authors=etal. |date=2 October 2021 |title=Fatal police violence by race and state in the USA, 1980–2019: a network meta-regression |journal=The Lancet |volume=398 |issue=10307 |pages= 1239–1255|doi=10.1016/S0140-6736(21)01609-3 |pmid=34600625 |pmc=8485022 |quote=Across all races and states in the USA, we estimate 30 800 deaths (95% uncertainty interval [UI] 30 300–31 300) from police violence between 1980 and 2018; this represents 17 100 more deaths (16 600–17 600) than reported by the NVSS.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Around 2,500 of those killed by police from 2015 to 2022 were fleeing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Levin|first=Sam|date=July 28, 2022 |title='Hunted': one in three people killed by US police were fleeing, data reveals|url=https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2022/jul/28/hunted-one-in-three-people-killed-by-us-police-were-fleeing-data-reveals|work=The Guardian |location= |access-date=September 2, 2022}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Black Lives Matter (50054644917).jpg|thumb|In June 2020, the "[[defund the police]]" slogan gained widespread popularity during the [[George Floyd protests]].]]

==== Examples ====

[[Shooting of Breonna Taylor|Breonna Taylor]] was killed at the age of 26 when police forced entry into the apartment as part of an investigation into drug dealing operations. Officers said that they announced themselves as police before forcing entry, but Walker said he did not hear any announcement, thought the officers were intruders, and fired a warning shot at them and hit Mattingly in the leg, and the officers fired 32 shots in return. Walker was unhurt but Taylor was hit by six bullets and died. On 23 September, a state grand jury found the shooting of Taylor justified but indicted officer Hankison on three counts of wanton endangerment for endangering Taylor's neighbors with his shots.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|date=28 December 2020|title=How the Police Killed Breonna Taylor|language=en-GB|work=The New York Times|url=https://www.nytimes.com/video/us/100000007348445/breonna-taylor-death-cops.html|access-date=6 January 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|date=23 September 2020|title=Breonna Taylor: Police officer charged but not over death|language=en-GB|work=BBC News|url=https://www.bbc.com/news/world-us-canada-54273317|access-date=6 January 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 25 May 2020, [[George Floyd]], an unarmed African American man, was murdered by a Minneapolis police officer, [[Derek Chauvin]], who knelt on his neck for over nine minutes ([[Nine minutes 29 seconds|9:29 seconds]]) while three other officers appeared to restrain his back and legs. In the video, it appears George Floyd screaming "You are going to kill me man!" Chauvin was charged with [[2nd degree murder|2nd-degree murder]]; his three colleagues stand accused of [[aiding and abetting]]. The colleagues of Derek Chauvin include Alexander Kueng, Thomas Lane, and Tou Thao. Floyd's murder, captured on video, triggered [[George Floyd protests|protests]] against racial discrimination across the US and the world.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|date=30 May 2020|title=The last 30 minutes of George Floyd's life|language=en-GB|work=BBC News|url=https://www.bbc.com/news/world-us-canada-52861726|access-date=14 June 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Levenson|first=Eric|title=Former officer knelt on George Floyd for 9 minutes and 29 seconds -- not the infamous 8:46|url=https://www.cnn.com/2021/03/29/us/george-floyd-timing-929-846/index.html|website=CNN}}&lt;/ref&gt; In June 2021, former officer Chauvin was [[Trial of Derek Chauvin|found guilty]] of three counts of murder and manslaughter and received a sentence of 22.5 years in prison.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Forliti|first1=Amy|last2=Karnowski|first2=Steve|date=26 June 2021|title=Chauvin gets 22 1/2 years in prison for George Floyd's death|url=https://apnews.com/article/derek-chauvin-sentencing-23c52021812168c579b3886f8139c73d|work=Associated Press|access-date=5 September 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Karnowski |first1=Steve |title=Trial for 3 ex-cops charged in Floyd's death pushed to March |url=https://apnews.com/article/death-of-george-floyd-officer-trial-pushed-back-af28560436091238b6554e41be3c9da3 |website=AP |date=13 May 2021 |access-date=6 December 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== South America ===
==== Brazil ====
{{main cat|Police brutality in Brazil}}
{{Further|Law enforcement in Brazil#Misconduct}}
The police in [[Brazil]] have a history of violence against the lower classes.&lt;ref name="Cavallaro US Helsinki watch committee Manuel Human Rights Watch/Americas 1997 p."&gt;{{cite book | last=Cavallaro | first=J. | author2=US Helsinki watch committee | last3=Manuel | first3=A. | author4=Human Rights Watch/Americas | author5=Americas | title=Police Brutality in Urban Brazil | publisher=Human Rights Watch | series=Americas Series | year=1997 | isbn=978-1-56432-211-1 | url=https://books.google.com/books?id=sUnhN-gnmhMC | access-date=22 June 2020 }}&lt;/ref&gt; It dates back to the nineteenth century when it primarily served as an instrument to control slaves.&lt;ref&gt;Holloway, Thomas H. "Policing Rio De Janeiro: Repression and Resistance in a 19Th-Century City" Stanford University Press, 1993. {{ISBN|0804720568}} - Chapter Two.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Graden, D. Torston. "From Slavery to Freedom in Brazil: Bahia, 1835–1900" University of New Mexico Press, 2006. {{ISBN|9780826340511}} - Chapters Two &amp; Three.&lt;/ref&gt; In a mostly rural country, the police forces were heavily influenced by local large landowners known as "colonels".&lt;ref&gt;Koonings, K. &amp; Kruijt D. "Armed Actors, Organised Violence and State Failure in Latin America" Zed Books, 1988. {{ISBN|1842774441}} - Page 41.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the latter half of the twentieth century, the country was heavily urbanized, while over [[Brazilian military government|its last military dictatorship]] state governments became responsible for Brazilian police forces experiencing which became heavily [[Military Police (Brazil)|militarized]].&lt;ref&gt;Andrade, John. "World Police &amp; Paramilitary Forces" Mstockton Press, Macmillan Publishers Ltd, 1985. {{ISBN|9781349077847}} - Pages 28-29.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Heinz, W.S. &amp; Frühling, h. "Determinants of Gross Human Rights Violations by State and State Sponsored Actors in Brazil, Uruguay, Chile, And Argentina 1960–1990" Martinus Nijhoff Publishers, 1999. {{ISBN|9041112022}} - Chapter 5.&lt;/ref&gt;

The militarist approach to dealing with social issues led the country to its highest violence levels and in 2015 Brazil had more violent deaths than the [[Syrian Civil War]],&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/americas/brazil-deaths-violent-crime-syria-police-brutality-report-brazilian-forum-for-public-security-a7386296.html Article] at [[The Independent]], 29 October 2016.&lt;/ref&gt; with most people fearing the police.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www1.folha.uol.com.br/cotidiano/2015/07/1662655-maioria-da-populacao-diz-ter-medo-da-policia-militar-aponta-datafolha.shtml Article] at "Folha de São Paulo" {{in lang|pt}}, 31 July 2015.&lt;/ref&gt; More than 6,160 people were killed by the Brazilian police in 2018.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|date=9 July 2019|title=Violent crime has undermined democracy in Latin America|work=Financial Times|url=https://www.ft.com/content/7bbc9228-a09f-11e9-a282-2df48f366f7d}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2019, the state of [[Rio de Janeiro (state)|Rio de Janeiro]] alone registered 1,814 killings by members of the police force in 2019, setting a new record. A significant portion of the officers involved had already been charged for crimes previously.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Andreoni|first1=Manuela|last2=Londoño|first2=Ernesto|date=18 May 2020|title='License to Kill': Inside Rio's Record Year of Police Killings|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2020/05/18/world/americas/brazil-rio-police-violence.html|access-date=20 May 2020|work=The New York Times}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Research released by the Forum Brasileiro de Segurança Pública (Brazilian Public Security Forum)&lt;ref name="Relatórios"&gt;{{cite web|title=Relatórios|url=http://observatorioseguranca.com.br/produtos/relatorios/|access-date=2021-12-05|website=Rede de Observatórios de Segurança|language=pt-BR}}&lt;/ref&gt; in partnership with São Paulo University showed that the Brazilian police killed approximately 6,416 people in 2020. Black and Brown people are 78% of the dead - 5,000 people, most of them men, poor, and aged 14 to 30 years old. It is what Brazilian Black Movement name the genocide of Black Brazilian youth. Rio de Janeiro is the city with the highest rates. According to Rio's Public Security Institute (ISP),&lt;ref name="Relatórios"/&gt; in 2019, where 1,814 people were killed in legal police interventions, 1,423 were Black or Brown. The COVID-19 pandemic did not stop or diminish the killings, which increased 27,9% compared to 2019. An ISP report states that Rio's police killed 741 people from January to May – the highest rate in 22 years.

The ISP research reveals the disparities between the number of COVID-19 mitigating actions (36) and police encounters (120) in the first months of the pandemic. Due to this absence of public health politics and the increase of lethal operations in favelas, 17 organizations from the Black movement, human rights, and favelas organizations joined a political party towards entered a petition called ADPF (Arguição de Descumprimento de Preceito Fundamental) 635, known as "ADPF das Favelas" (Favela's ADPF) in Brazil's Supreme Court (Supremo Tribunal Federal – STF)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|date=2020-07-25|title=Brazil Supreme Court Considers Landmark Case on Police Operations in Rio's Favelas, Part I|url=https://www.rioonwatch.org/?p=60813|access-date=2021-12-05|website=RioOnWatch|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt; demanding actions towards minimizing police terror in the communities. In May 2020, they asked for the immediate suspension of police operations during the pandemic, indicating that continuing such operations would threaten life and dignity. In addition, they cited mortality rates, power abuse cases, and the propriety damages caused by the police raids during a deadly pandemic in poor neighborhoods.

On May 18, 2020, João Pedro Pinto, a 14 years old boy, was killed inside his family's house. According to a witness, he lived in a place with a pool and a barbecue area, where he was with his cousins and friends when the police raid started. According to the survivors, the boys went to the covered area when they noticed that the police helicopter started to shoot. Moments later, the police invaded the place, which the boys informed: “There are only children here.” The police response was throwing two grenades that made the boys run into the house to protect themselves. João Pedro was shot in his belly by a rifle, his body was transported to a place 27 miles away from the crime scene, and the family had access to him after 17 hours. According to the reports and TV news, it was possible to count more than 70 bullet marks inside João Pedro's house. This murder led people to protest in the streets and was the main argument for the ADPF 635&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=ADPF 635|url=http://www.mprj.mp.br/adpf-635|access-date=2021-12-05|website=MPRJ|language=pt-BR}}&lt;/ref&gt; petition, supported by Supreme Courts Minister Edson Fachin in August of the same year.

Afterward, the Court unanimously voted to maintain the decision, which would only authorize operations in "absolutely exceptional" cases that needed to be justified for the Public Ministry of the State of Rio de Janeiro. The Supreme Court also stated that in case of authorized operations in the pandemic, "Exceptional care should be taken, duly identified in writing by the competent authority, so as not to put in risk population' provision of public health services and the humanitarian aid activities." Even after the pandemic, it has prohibited using helicopters as a platform for shooting and terror, conducting operations near schools and hospitals, and using them as police operational bases. The crime scene must be preserved and must avoid body remotion (by the excuse of supposed rescue). The technical-scientific police must document evidence, reports, and autopsy exams to ensure the possibility of independent review; Investigations must meet the Minnesota Protocol requirements. It must be fast, effective, and complete well as independent, impartial, and transparent.

The decision was celebrated by the group as a mark in the history of justice and lives in favela's struggle. The organizations that joined the political party (PSB – Socialist Brazilian Party) were Rio de Janeiro Public Defense, Fala Akari, Papo Reto Collective, Rede de Comunidades e Movimentos Contra a Violência, Mães de Manguinhos, Redes da Maré, Movimento Negro Unificado, Educafro, Iniciativa Direito à Memória e Justiça Racial, ISER, Justiça Global, Conectas e National Human Rights Concil. Other organizations as Observatório de Favelas, Maré Vive, Instituto Marielle Franco, Cesec, Grupo de Estudo dos Novos Legalismos/UFF e Fogo Cruzado contributed to the lawsuit.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Vitória do povo negro e das favelas!|url=https://www.adpfdasfavelas.org/|access-date=2021-12-05|website=www.adpfdasfavelas.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In August 2020, the research group named “Grupo de Estudos dos Novos Ilegalismos” (GENI)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Em um ano de restrição às operações policiais no RJ, número de mortes e tiroteios cai no estado, diz relatório|url=https://g1.globo.com/rj/rio-de-janeiro/noticia/2021/06/07/em-um-ano-de-restricao-as-operacoes-policiais-no-rj-numero-de-mortes-e-tiroteios-cai-no-estado-diz-relatorio.ghtml|access-date=2021-12-05|website=G1|language=pt-br}}&lt;/ref&gt; from Federal Fluminense University in Rio de Janeiro with other civil organizations, stated that after the suspension of police operations by the STF, the mortality rates decreased to 72.5%. Furthermore, the criminality rates also decreased: a  reduction of 47.7% in crimes against life, 37.9% in willful murder homicides, 39% in reduction in crimes against patrimonies, and less 32,1% in vehicle robbery. Nevertheless, the STF decision was not very well received by Rio de Janeiro's police, who complained and accused the decision to make their work more difficult, even with the decrease of criminality. They also did not always obey the order and did raid without the requirements the law demanded. According to the organization Rede de Observatórios, in the first two months of the year, police killed 47 people, 20% more than the same period of 2020.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|date=2021-09-03|title=Sixth Annual Black July Discusses the 'ADPF of the Favelas,' Its Political Impact and Social Struggles|url=https://rioonwatch.org/?p=67183|access-date=2021-12-05|website=RioOnWatch|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On May 6, 2021, Rio de Janeiro police killed 28 people in Jacarezinho Favela&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|date=2021-05-08|title=Stop Killing Us! Jacarezinho Experiences Worst Massacre in Rio History #VoicesFromSocialMedia|url=https://rioonwatch.org/?p=65697|access-date=2021-12-05|website=RioOnWatch|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt; in a raid that was considered a success by police forces and the state of Rio's government. Immediately after the slaughter, human rights activists denounced illegal actions as alteration of the crime scene, invasion of houses, in addition to non-compliance with the protocol demanded by the STF. It is considered the biggest slaughter in the history of the city and is still under investigation. One month later, on June 08th, a young pregnant Black woman was killed by the police in another favela. Kathlen Romeu, 24 years old,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|date=2021-06-15|title=In Rio's Favelas, the Fight Against Police Brutality Begins in the Womb|url=https://rioonwatch.org/?p=66133|access-date=2021-12-05|website=RioOnWatch|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt; four months pregnant, was walking with her grandmother when a police officer shot her. According to the Brazilian Bar Association's Humans Rights Commission (OAB), the operation that killed Kathlen was illegal, and the police officer was hiding in a neighbor's house to ambush criminals. According to the ISP and GENI Group, from January to September 2021, Rio de Janeiro police killed 811 people during their raids.

==== Colombia ====
[[2020 Colombian protests (disambiguation)|Protests]] against police brutality started in [[Bogotá]], the country's capital, following the death of Javier Ordóñez while in police custody on 9 September 2020. The unrest has since spread to many cities throughout Colombia. {{As of|2020|9|12}}, 13 people have died and over 400 have been injured as part of the protests.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Rahman|first=Khaleda|date=10 September 2020|title=Bogota riots as police killing of unarmed man sparks violent unrest in Colombia|url=https://www.newsweek.com/bogota-riots-police-killing-unarmed-man-sparks-violent-unrest-colombia-1530914|website=[[Newsweek]]|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Colombia: Protests against police brutality leave 13 dead, over 400 injured |url=https://www.dw.com/en/colombia-protests-against-police-brutality-leave-13-dead-over-400-injured/a-54902653 |work=Deutsche Welle |date=12 September 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Chile ====
In recent years, [[Chile]]'s police force [[Carabineros de Chile]] has been under investigation because of various cases of power abuse and police brutality, particularly towards students participating in riots for better education and the indigenous [[Mapuche]] people; countless cases of violence were enacted on this group for allegedly committing crimes; it was later discovered that some Carabineros officers were responsible for these crimes and blamed Mapuches.

One of the recent cases involving the Mapuche was [[Shooting of Camilo Catrillanca|Camilo Catrillanca's death]]. The first reports of his death came from the Carabineros who claimed that Camilo shot at a police officer and others while being investigated for allegedly stealing three cars. The Carabineros special forces team Comando Jungla was in the [[Araucanía Region]] searching for terrorists. After seeing Camilo "attacking" policemen with a gun in an attempt to escape, the Carabineros shot Camilo in the head and killed him. It was later discovered that this was not what happened; a partner of the police officer that killed Camilo showed the video of the policeman killing him while he drove a tractor. Carabineros was asked why they did not have a recording of the officer being shot at by Camilo. The institution responded the officer destroyed the SD card because it had private photos and videos of his wife; most people were not satisfied with the answer. The policeman was later discharged and prosecuted.&lt;ref&gt;[[Rodrigo Acuña]]. [https://www.redpepper.org.uk/killing-of-indigenous-activist-in-chile-provokes-widespread-protests/ "Killing of an indigenous activist in Chile provokes widespread protests"], ''[[Red Pepper (magazine)|Red Pepper]]'', London, 27 November 2018. Retrieved on 29 November 2018.&lt;/ref&gt;

During the [[2019–20 Chilean protests]], Carabineros de Chile has caused hundreds of [[Eye injuries in the 2019–2020 Chilean protests|eye mutilations]] on protesters and random civilians with hardened rubber bullets and tear gas canisters.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2019/11/19/world/americas/chile-protests-eye-injuries.html|title=A Bullet to the Eye Is the Price of Protesting in Chile (Published 2019)|first=Brent|last=McDonald|newspaper=The New York Times|date=19 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; The most notorious cases are of the victims with complete loss of vision Gustavo Gatica&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.eldinamo.cl/nacional/2020/06/24/gustavo-gatica-caabineros-ocultamiento-de-informacion/|title=Gustavo Gatica: Carabineros responde a posible ocultamiento de información}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Fabiola Campillai.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.indh.cl/indh-se-querella-por-homicidio-frustrado-contra-carabineros-en-favor-de-trabajadora-que-habria-perdido-vision-de-ambos-ojos/|title=INDH se querella por homicidio frustrado contra Carabineros en favor de trabajadora que habría perdido visión de ambos ojos|date=28 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Venezuela ====
{{Main|Human rights in Venezuela}}
During the [[2014 Venezuelan protests]], multiple human rights organizations condemned the Venezuelan government for its handling of the protests as security forces had reportedly gone beyond typical practices of handling protests, with methods ranging from the use of rubber pellets and tear gas to instances of live ammunition and torture of arrested protestors, according to organizations like Amnesty International&lt;ref name="AIabuses"&gt;{{cite news |title=Amnesty Reports Dozens of Venezuela Torture Accounts |newspaper=Bloomberg |url=https://www.bloomberg.com/news/2014-04-01/amnesty-reports-dozens-of-venezuela-torture-accounts.html |url-status=live |access-date=13 April 2014 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140414145726/http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2014-04-01/amnesty-reports-dozens-of-venezuela-torture-accounts.html |archive-date=14 April 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Human Rights Watch]].&lt;ref name="HRWpfp"&gt;{{cite web |title=Punished for Protesting |url=https://www.hrw.org/sites/default/files/reports/venezuela0514_reportcover_web.pdf |url-status=live |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140513223338/http://www.hrw.org/sites/default/files/reports/venezuela0514_reportcover_web.pdf |archive-date=13 May 2014 |access-date=6 May 2014 |publisher=Human Rights Watch}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hundreds of Venezuelans were tortured when detained by Venezuelan authorities.&lt;ref name="UN22oct"&gt;{{cite web |title=Venezuela: UN rights chief calls for immediate release of opposition leader, politicians |url=https://www.un.org/apps/news/story.asp?NewsID=49120 |url-status=live |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20141021131739/http://www.un.org/apps/news/story.asp?NewsID=49120#.VEc4WZPF8Q5 |archive-date=21 October 2014 |access-date=22 October 2014 |publisher=United Nations}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="REUT26feb"&gt;{{cite news |last1=Gupta |first1=Girish |date=26 February 2014 |title=Venezuela government faces brutality accusations over unrest |work=Reuters |url=https://www.reuters.com/article/us-venezuela-protests-allegations-idUSBREA1P1AF20140226 |url-status=live |access-date=22 October 2014 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20141026110449/http://www.reuters.com/article/2014/02/26/us-venezuela-protests-allegations-idUSBREA1P1AF20140226 |archive-date=26 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

During the [[2017 Venezuelan protests]], the [[United Nations Human Rights Office]] denounced "widespread and systematic use of excessive force" against demonstrators, saying security forces and pro-government groups were responsible for the deaths of at least 73 protesters. The UN Human Rights Office described "a picture of widespread and systematic use of excessive force and arbitrary detentions against demonstrators in Venezuela". "Witness accounts suggest that security forces, mainly the national guard, the national police and local police forces, have systematically used disproportionate force to instil fear, crush dissent and to prevent demonstrators from assembling, rallying and reaching public institutions to present petitions".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |date=8 August 2017 |title=Venezuela: UN rights chief decries excessive force used against protesters |work=[[The Guardian]] |url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2017/aug/08/venezuela-un-rights-chief-decries-excessive-force-used-against-protesters |url-status=live |access-date=13 August 2017 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170813111410/https://www.theguardian.com/world/2017/aug/08/venezuela-un-rights-chief-decries-excessive-force-used-against-protesters |archive-date=13 August 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{external media|width=260px|video1={{YouTube|id=hHVOf9RTSPs|title=National Guardsman firing live ammunition at protesters on 19 June, [[Killing of Fabián Urbina|killing Fabián Urbina]]}}}}
[[File:David_Vallenilla_shot.webm|right|thumb|250x250px|Venezuelan protester David Vallenilla being shot dead by a security agent]]
The majority of individuals killed during protests died from gunshot wounds, with many resulting from the repression by Venezuelan authorities and assisting pro-government [[Colectivo (Venezuela)|colectivos]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |date=5 June 2017 |title=Venezuela's New Government Approach to Crowd Control: Robbery |work=[[Latin American Herald Tribune]] |url=http://www.laht.com/article.asp?ArticleId=2437675&amp;CategoryId=10717 |url-status=live |access-date=6 June 2017 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170614202224/http://laht.com/article.asp?CategoryId=10717&amp;ArticleId=2437675 |archive-date=14 June 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; A report by [[Human Rights Watch]] and [[Foro Penal]] documented at least six cases in which Venezuelan security forces raided residential areas and apartment buildings in Caracas and in four different states, usually near barricades built by residents; according to testimonies, officials bursted into houses without warrants, stealing personal belongings and food from residents, as well as beating and arresting them.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Human Rights Watch |title=Crackdown on Dissent. Brutality, Torture, and Political Persecution in Venezuela |author2=Foro Penal |year=2017 |isbn=978-1-62313-549-2 |page=61 |language=en |chapter=5 |author-link=Human Rights Watch |author-link2=Foro Penal |chapter-url=https://www.hrw.org/sites/default/files/report_pdf/venezuela1117web_0.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A report of the [[Office of the United Nations High Commissioner for Human Rights]] specified that non-lethal weapons were used systematically to cause unnecessary injuries, explaining that security forces had fired tear gas canisters directly against protesters at short distances.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |date=31 August 2017 |title=Informe: En Venezuela los manifestantes fueron víctimas de vulneraciones y abusos de derechos humanos |language=es |agency=Office of the United Nations High Commissioner for Human Rights |url=http://www.ohchr.org/SP/NewsEvents/Pages/ReportProtestorsinVenezuelaHumanRightsViolations.aspx |url-status=live |access-date=10 April 2018 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180411030004/http://www.ohchr.org/SP/NewsEvents/Pages/ReportProtestorsinVenezuelaHumanRightsViolations.aspx |archive-date=11 April 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Mónica Kräuter]], a chemist and teacher of the [[Simón Bolívar University (Venezuela)|Simón Bolívar University]] who has studied over a thousand tear gas canisters since 2014, has stated that security forces have fired expired tear gas which, according to her, "breaks down into [[cyanide]] oxide, [[Phosgene|phosgenes]] and [[Nitrogen|nitrogens]] that are extremely dangerous".&lt;ref name="LPteargas"&gt;{{cite news |date=8 April 2017 |title=Bombas lacrimógenas que usa el gobierno están vencidas y emanan cianuro (+ recomendaciones) |language=es-ES |work=[[La Patilla]] |url=https://www.lapatilla.com/site/2017/04/10/bombas-lacrimogenas-que-usa-el-gobierno-estan-vencidas-y-emanan-cianuro-recomendaciones/ |url-status=live |access-date=24 April 2017 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170424175448/https://www.lapatilla.com/site/2017/04/10/bombas-lacrimogenas-que-usa-el-gobierno-estan-vencidas-y-emanan-cianuro-recomendaciones/ |archive-date=24 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Groups such as the Venezuelan Observatory of Health have denounced the use of tear gas fired directly or nearby health centers and hospitals, as well as houses and residential buildings.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |date=28 April 2017 |title=Observatorio Venezolano de la Salud alerta sobre uso de gases lacrimógenos |language=ES |publisher=Observatorio Venezolano de Violencia |agency=Observatorio Venezolano de la Salud |url=https://observatoriodeviolencia.org.ve/observatorio-venezolano-de-la-salud-alerta-sobre-uso-de-gases-lacrimogenos/ |url-status=live |access-date=10 April 2018 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180716165600/https://observatoriodeviolencia.org.ve/observatorio-venezolano-de-la-salud-alerta-sobre-uso-de-gases-lacrimogenos/ |archive-date=16 July 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In a 15 June statement, [[Human Rights Watch]] stated that high levels officials of the government, such as José Antonio Benavides Torres, the head of the Bolivarian National Guard; [[Vladimir Padrino López]], the defense minister and the strategic operational commander of the Armed Forces; [[Néstor Reverol]], the interior minister, Carlos Alfredo Pérez Ampueda, director of the Bolivarian National Police; [[Gustavo González López]], the national intelligence director, and Siria Venero de Guerrero, the military attorney general, were responsible for the human rights violations and abuses performed by Venezuelan security forces during the protests. Venezuelan officials have praised authorities for their actions and denied any wrongdoing.&lt;ref name="HRWjun15"&gt;{{cite web |date=15 June 2017 |title=Venezuela: Senior Officials' Responsibility for Abuses |url=https://www.hrw.org/news/2017/06/15/venezuela-senior-officials-responsibility-abuses |access-date=17 June 2017 |publisher=[[Human Rights Watch]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{external media|width=260px|video1={{YouTube|id=8YiQi32ihig|title=Human Rights Watch multimedia report on abuses}}|float=right}}
Human rights groups have stated that Venezuelan authorities have used force to gain confessions. [[Amnesty International]] maintains that the government has a "premeditated policy" to commit violent and lethal acts against protesters, stating that there is "a planned strategy by the government of President Maduro to use violence and illegitimate force against the Venezuelan population to neutralize any criticism". ''[[The Wall Street Journal]]'' reported that a young men had already been [[Torture|tortured]] at an army base when soldiers piled them into two jeeps and transported them to a wooded area just outside the [[Venezuela|Venezuelan]] capital.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.wsj.com/articles/venezuelas-brutal-crime-crackdown-executions-machetes-and-8-292-dead-1513792219 Venezuela's Brutal Crime Crackdown: Executions, Machetes and 8,292 Dead]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Foro Penal]] stated that "most of the detainees are beaten once they are arrested, while they are being transferred to a temporary detention site where they are to be brought before a judge", giving one instance with "a group of 40 people arrested for alleged looting, 37 reported that they were beaten before their hair was forcefully shaved off their heads". In other examples of abuses, "15 reported that they were forced to eat pasta with grass and [[excrement]]. The regime's officials forced dust from tear gas canisters up their noses to pry open their mouths. They then shoved the pasta with excrement in their mouths and made them swallow it".&lt;ref name="PAPtorture"&gt;{{cite news |last1=Martín |first1=Karina |date=16 May 2017 |title=Venezuelan Regime Steps up Torture against Protesters, Forces Them to Eat Excrement |work=[[PanAm Post]] |url=https://panampost.com/karina-martin/2017/05/16/venezuelan-regime-steps-up-torture-against-protesters-forces-them-to-eat-excrement/ |url-status=live |access-date=18 May 2017 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170612161455/https://panampost.com/karina-martin/2017/05/16/venezuelan-regime-steps-up-torture-against-protesters-forces-them-to-eat-excrement/ |archive-date=12 June 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

== Causes ==
[[File:Ian Tomlinson remonstrates with police.jpg|thumb|right|[[Ian Tomlinson]] after being pushed to the ground by police in [[London]] (2009). He collapsed and died soon after.]]
[[File:Citizens protest police terror.jpg|thumb|Protest against police brutality after the eviction of unemployed demonstrators occupying the Post Office in [[Vancouver]], Canada, 1938]]
The persistence of police brutality in many nations can be linked to a collective failure of the criminal justice system. Governments enacting "hard on crime" policies, poor police training, and a lack of legal repercussions for officers who use excessive force against civilians all increase the likelihood of police brutality occurring. Additionally, social issues like racial discrimination and poverty can exacerbate the brutality and its effects on marginalized communities.

=== Hard on Drugs Campaigns ===
In nations with a reputation for having a high number of drug-related issues, including gang violence, drug trafficking, and overdose deaths, one common solution that government will enact is a collective campaign against drugs that spans the entirety of the state's establishment. Changes to address these issues encompass education, bureaucracy, and, most notably, law enforcement policy and tactics. Law enforcement agencies expand and receive more funding to attack the drug problems in communities. Acceptance of harsher policing tactics grows as well, as an "any means necessary" philosophy develops within the law enforcement community and the militarization of local police forces.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.cato.org/blog/police-violence-racist-drug-war |access-date=2022-05-17 |website=www.cato.org}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, many studies have concluded that these efforts are in vain, as the drug market has grown in such nations despite anti-drug policies. For example, in the United States, critics of the War on Drugs waged by the American government have been very vocal about the ineffectiveness of the policy, citing an increase in drug-related crimes and overdoses since President Nixon first introduced this policy.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Cooper |first=Hannah LF |date=2015 |title=War on Drugs Policing and Police Brutality |journal=Substance Use &amp; Misuse |volume=50 |issue=8–9 |pages=1188–1194 |doi=10.3109/10826084.2015.1007669 |issn=1082-6084 |pmc=4800748 |pmid=25775311}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Legal System ===
A type of government failure that can result in the normalization of police brutality is a lack of accountability and repercussions for officers mistreating civilians. While it is currently commonplace for civilians to hold officers accountable by recording them, the actual responsibility of police oversight rests heavily on the criminal justice system of a given nation, as police represent the enforcement of the law. One method of increasing police accountability that has become more common is the employment of body cameras as a part of police uniforms.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Zepcam |title=Growing Number of European Police Forces use Bodycam |url=https://www.prnewswire.com/news-releases/growing-number-of-european-police-forces-use-bodycam-892044220.html |access-date=2022-05-19 |website=www.prnewswire.com |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the effectiveness of body cameras has been called into question due to the lack of transparency shown in police brutality cases where the footage is withheld from the public. In many cases of police brutality, the criminal justice system has no policy in place to condemn or prohibit police brutality. Certain nations have laws that permit lawful, violent treatment of civilians, like qualified immunity, which protects officers from being sued for their use of violence if their actions can be justified under the law.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Qualified Immunity |url=https://eji.org/issues/qualified-immunity/ |access-date=2022-05-19 |website=Equal Justice Initiative |language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Police officers are legally permitted to use force. [[Jerome Herbert Skolnick]] writes in regards to dealing largely with disorderly elements of the society, some people{{who|date=July 2020}} working in law enforcement may gradually develop an attitude or sense of authority over society, particularly under traditional reaction-based policing models; in some cases, the police believe that they are above the law.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Skolnick|first=Jerome H.|author2=Fyfe, James D.|editor=Winters, Paul A.|title=Policing the Police|year=1995|publisher=Greenhaven Press|location=San Diego|isbn=978-1-56510-262-0|pages=45–55|chapter=Community-Oriented Policing Would Prevent Police Brutality}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There are many reasons why police officers can sometimes be excessively aggressive. It is thought that psychopathy makes some officers more inclined to use excessive force than others. In one study, police psychologists surveyed officers who had used excessive force. The information obtained allowed the researchers to develop five unique types of officers, only one of which was similar to the [[Bad apples|bad apple]] stereotype. These include personality disorders; previous traumatic job-related experience; young, inexperienced, or authoritarian officers; officers who learn inappropriate patrol styles; and officers with personal problems. Schrivers categorized these groups and separated the group that was the most likely to use excessive force.&lt;ref&gt;Scrivner, 1994: 3–6&lt;/ref&gt; However, this "bad apple paradigm" is considered by some to be an "easy way out". A broad report commissioned by the Royal Canadian Mounted Police on the causes of misconduct in policing calls it "a simplistic explanation that permits the organization and senior management to blame corruption on individuals and individual faults – behavioural, psychological, background factors, and so on, rather than addressing systemic factors."&lt;ref name="RCMP Review"&gt;{{cite web|last=Loree|first=Don|title=Corruption in Policing: Causes and Consequences; A Review of the Literature|work=Research and Evaluation Community, Contract and Aboriginal Policing Services Directorate|publisher=Royal Canadian Mounted Police|year=2006|url=http://dsp-psd.pwgsc.gc.ca/Collection/PS64-27-2006E.pdf|access-date=1 September 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The report continues to discuss the systemic factors, which include:
* Pressures to conform to certain aspects of "police culture", such as the [[Blue Code of Silence]], which can "sustain an oppositional criminal subculture protecting the interests of police who violate the law"&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|doi=10.1080/15614260290011309|last=Skolnick|first=Jerome H.|title=Corruption and the Blue Code of Silence|journal=Police Practice and Research|volume=3|year=2002|page=7|issue=1|s2cid=144512106}}&lt;/ref&gt; and a "'we-they' perspective in which outsiders are viewed with suspicion or distrust"&lt;ref name="RCMP Review" /&gt;
* Command and control structures with a rigid hierarchical foundation ("results indicate that the more rigid the authoritarian hierarchy, the lower the scores on a measure of ethical decision-making" concludes one study reviewed in the report);&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Owens|first=Katherine M. B.|author2=Jeffrey Pfeifer|title=Police Leadership and Ethics: Training and Police Recommendations|journal=The Canadian Journal of Police and Security Services|volume=1|page=7|year=2002|issue=2}}&lt;/ref&gt; and
* Deficiencies in internal accountability mechanisms (including internal investigation processes).&lt;ref name="RCMP Review" /&gt;

The use of force by police officers is not kept in check in many jurisdictions by the issuance of a [[use of force continuum]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Stetser|first=Merle|title=The Use of Force in Police Control of Violence: Incidents Resulting in Assaults on Officers|year=2001|publisher=LFB Scholarly Publishing L.L.C.|location=New York|isbn=978-1-931202-08-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; which describes levels of force considered appropriate in direct response to a suspect's behavior. This power is granted by the government, with few if any limits set out in [[statutory law]] as well as [[common law]].

Violence used by police can be excessive despite being lawful, especially in the context of political repression. Police brutality is often used to refer to violence used by the police to achieve politically desirable ends (terrorism) and, therefore, when none should be used at all according to widely held values and cultural norms in the society (rather than to refer to excessive violence used where at least some may be considered justifiable).

Studies show that there are officers who believe the legal system they serve is failing and that they must pick up the slack. This is known as "vigilantism", where the officer-involved may think the suspect deserves more punishment than what they may have to serve under the court system.&lt;ref&gt;Chevigny, P. (2008). "Police Brutality", In Encyclopedia of Violence, Peace and Conflict. oxford: Elsevier Science and Technology, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

During high-speed pursuits of suspects, officers can become angry and filled with adrenaline, which can affect their judgment when they finally apprehend the suspect. The resulting loss of judgment and heightened emotional state can result in inappropriate use of force. The effect is colloquially known as "high-speed pursuit syndrome".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Kevin Mullen |url=http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/e/a/1996/04/05/EDITORIAL9376.dtl |title=The high-speed chase syndrome |work=SFGate |date=5 April 1996 |access-date=12 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Effects of police brutality in the United States ===
{{Original research section|date=December 2017}}
{{POV section|date=March 2020}}
{{More citations needed section|date=November 2020}}
Police brutality is the misuse of power by the police force to intentionally harm individuals.{{citation needed|date=June 2020}} The excessive force imposed by police officers has increased&lt;ref name=":20"&gt;{{cite web|title=Mapping Police Violence|url=https://mappingpoliceviolence.org/|access-date=22 September 2021|website=Mapping Police Violence|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt; over the past decade and caused social misinterpretations of the role that police officers play in the community.

In 2015, the percentage of people who have confidence in the police hit its lowest since 1993 at 52 percent.&lt;ref name="ReferenceD"&gt;Citation error. See inline comment how to fix. {{verify source |date=September 2019 |reason=This ref was deleted Special:Diff/869571971 by a bug in VisualEditor and later identified by a bot. The original cite can be found at Special:Permalink/869571739 (or in a rev close to it) as cite #137 - find and verify the cite and replace this template with it (2). [[User:GreenC bot/Job 18]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Of this 52 percent, Democrats saw the biggest drop in confidence. Democrats' confidence in police dropped to 42% from 2017–2018 compared with 2012–2013, a larger change than for any other subgroup. Over the same period, Independents' (51%) and Republicans' (69%) confidence in the police has not changed.&lt;ref name="ReferenceD"/&gt; The number of black people that trust the police in 2017–2018 averaged 30 percent, well below the national average of 53% and much lower than for any other subgroup.{{citation needed|date=September 2020}}

==== Firearms usage ====

Individual state statutes and police department policies generally say that police officers are legally allowed to shoot in the instance that they feel the need to protect their lives or an innocent life{{citation needed|date=May 2020}} or to prevent the suspect from escaping and posing a dangerous threat to bystanders in society.{{citation needed|date=May 2020}} The Supreme Court Decision of [[Tennessee v. Garner]] made it possible to shoot a fleeing suspect only if they may cause harm to innocent people to prevent officers from shooting every suspect that tries to escape.

==== Stereotypes ====
Lorie Fridell, Associate Professor of Criminology at University of South Florida, states that "racial profiling was the number one issue facing police [in the 1990s]", which led her to two conclusions: "bias in policing was not just a few officers in a few departments and, overwhelmingly, the police in this country are well-intentioned." According to a Department of Justice report, "Officers, like the rest of us, have an implicit bias linking blacks to crime. So the black crime implicit bias might be implicated in some of the use of deadly force against African-Americans in our country".&lt;ref name="BBC News"&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.bbc.com/news/world-us-canada-32740523|title=Why do US police keep killing black men?|date=26 May 2015|work=BBC News|access-date=23 October 2018|language=en-GB}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A 2014 experiment conducted on white undergraduate female students showed that there was a higher degree of fear of racial minorities. The paper concluded that people with a higher fear of racial minorities and dehumanization had "a lower threshold for shooting Black relative to White and East Asian targets".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://psycnet.apa.org/record/2015-41947-001|title=PsycNET|website=psycnet.apa.org|language=en|access-date=5 July 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Justice for Jamar Response Action (22627979078).jpg|thumb|Protest march in response to the [[Shooting of Jamar Clark|Jamar Clark shooting]], Minneapolis, Minnesota]]
High-profile police deaths of black men like Eric Garner in New York City, Tamir Rice in Cleveland, and Freddie Gray in Baltimore have increased distrust in the black community towards the police.{{citation needed|date=June 2020}} High-profile police killings have led to the creation of social organizations, such as the [[Black Lives Matter]] movement founded in 2013.{{citation needed|date=November 2021}}

While the Justice Department reported that Cleveland police officers used "excessive deadly force, including shootings and head strikes with impact weapons; unnecessary, excessive, and retaliatory force, including Tasers, chemical sprays, and their fists" on the victim, there was no real repercussions from their actions.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Hines|first=Sandra|date=21 September 2017|chapter=Detroit Coalition Against Police Brutality|publisher=Policy Press|doi=10.1332/policypress/9781447327868.003.0019|isbn=9781447327868|title=Why Detroit Matters}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Black Americans and the US police ====
[[File:Protest march against police violence - Justice for George Floyd (49941871086).jpg|thumb|right|Protesters in [[Minneapolis]] on 26 May 2020, the day after the [[murder of George Floyd]]]]
In a report released concerning the [[shooting of Michael Brown]] in [[Ferguson, Missouri]], the Justice Department admitted to the Ferguson's police department's pattern of racial bias. The department argued that it is typically an effort to ticket as many low-income black residents as possible in an attempt to raise local budget revenue through fines and court fees. The Justice Department explained police encounters could get downright abusive when the person being questioned by the police officers becomes disrespectful or challenges their authority.{{citation needed|date=June 2020}}

The Department of Justice also released a statement that confronted police officers' susceptibility to implicit bias: One of the things they looked at was "threat perception failure", where an officer may believe that the person was armed and it turned out not to be the case. These failures were observed to occur more frequently when the suspect was black.{{citation needed|date=June 2020}}

==== Statistics ====

Data released by the US Bureau of Justice Statistics (2011) showed that from 2003 to 2009 at least 4,813 people died while being arrested by local police. Of the deaths classified as [[law enforcement]] homicides, there were 2,876 deaths; of those, 1,643 or 57.1% of the deaths were "people of color".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Kappeler|first=Victor |title=Being Arrested can be Hazardous to your Health, Especially if you are a Person of Color |date=18 February 2014 |url=http://plsonline.eku.edu/insidelook/being-arrested-can-be-hazardous-your-health-especially-if-you-are-person-color}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the police violence tracking website fatalencounters.org showed the records of over 29,000 people were killed in police interactions across the US since 2000.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://fatalencounters.org/our-visualizations/|title=Our visualizations – Fatal Encounters}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2016, police killed 574 [[White Americans]], 266 [[African Americans]], 183 [[Hispanic and Latino Americans|Hispanics]], 24 [[Native Americans in the United States|Native Americans]], and 21 Asians. However, for every million in population, police killed 10.13 Native Americans, 6.66 African Americans, 3.23 Hispanics, 2.9 White Americans, and 1.17 Asians.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=The Counted: People killed by police in the US |url=https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/ng-interactive/2015/jun/01/the-counted-police-killings-us-database |work=The Guardian}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the 2020 Police Violence Report, 1,126 people were killed by police, of which in 16 cases police officers were charged with a crime. 620 of the deaths began with police officers responding to reports of non-violent offenses or no crime. 81 people killed by the police were unarmed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://policeviolencereport.org/|title=2020 Police Violence Report|website=policeviolencereport.org|language=en|access-date=3 October 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Sam Sinyangwe, founder of the Mapping Police Violence project, stated in 2015 that "black people are three times more likely to be killed by police in the United States than white people. More unarmed black people were killed by police than unarmed white people last year, even though only 14% of the population are black people."&lt;ref name="BBC News"/&gt; According to the Mapping Police Violence project, in 2019, there were only 27 days where police in the United States didn't kill someone.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Mapping Police Violence|url=https://mappingpoliceviolence.org/|access-date=18 June 2020|website=Mapping Police Violence|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Critics of police brutality also note that sometimes this abuse of force or power can extend to police officer civilian life as well. For example, critics note that women in around 40% of police officer families have experienced domestic violence&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Rafaqat |first1=Cheema|date=July 2016|title=Black and Blue Bloods: Protecting Police Officer Families from Domestic Violence|url=https://scholarlycommons.law.hofstra.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1009&amp;context=hofstra_law_student_works|journal=Scholarly Commons at Hofstra Law|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; and that police officers are convicted of misdemeanors and felonies at a rate of more than six times higher than [[concealed carry]] weapon (CCW) permit holders.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite ssrn|last1=Lott|first1=John R.| date=29 August 2018|title=Concealed Carry Permit Holders Across the United States: 2018| ssrn=3233904}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Global prevalence ==
[[File:NSW police use illegal pain hold on activist at University of Sydney.JPG|thumb|[[Australia]]n police use illegal pain hold on activist at [[University of Sydney]].]]
* The [[Amnesty International]] 2007 report on human rights also documented widespread police misconduct in many other countries, especially countries with [[authoritarian]] regimes.&lt;ref name="Amnesty 2007"&gt;{{cite web|title=Amnesty International Report 2007|url=http://thereport.amnesty.org/eng/Homepage|publisher=Amnesty International|year=2007|access-date=8 August 2007|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070807192225/http://thereport.amnesty.org/eng/Homepage &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt;|archive-date=7 August 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In the UK, the reports into the death of New Zealand teacher and anti-racism campaigner [[Death of Blair Peach|Blair Peach]] in 1979 was published on the Metropolitan Police website on 27 April 2010. They concluded that Peach was killed by a police officer, but that the other police officers in the same unit had refused to cooperate with the inquiry by lying to investigators, making it impossible to identify the actual killer.{{citation needed|date=January 2011}}
* In the UK, [[Death of Ian Tomlinson|Ian Tomlinson]] was filmed by an American tourist being hit with a baton and pushed to the floor as he was walking home from work during the [[2009 G-20 London summit protests]]. Tomlinson then collapsed and died. Although he was arrested on suspicion of manslaughter, the officer who allegedly assaulted Tomlinson was released without charge. He was later dismissed for [[gross misconduct]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title = Ian Tomlinson case: PC Simon Harwood sacked for gross misconduct|date = 17 September 2012|url = https://www.theguardian.com/uk/2012/sep/17/simon-harwood-sacked-gross-misconduct|last = Walker|first = Peter|newspaper = The Guardian|access-date = 6 August 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In the UK, in 2005, a young Brazilian man was arrested and shot by Metropolitan Police in Central London. The man, Jean Charles Menezes, died later.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dispatch.co.za/2005/08/23/Foreign/amendez.html |title=Dispatch Online - Your premier Eastern Cape news site |date= |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090109143617/http://www.dispatch.co.za/2005/08/23/Foreign/amendez.html |accessdate=2022-05-20|archive-date=9 January 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In Serbia, police brutality occurred in numerous cases during protests against [[Slobodan Milošević]], and has also been recorded at protests against governments since Milošević lost power.{{citation needed|date=June 2011}} The most recent case was recorded in July 2010, when five people, including two girls, were arrested, handcuffed, beaten with clubs, and mistreated for one hour. Security camera recordings of the beating were obtained by the media and public outrage when released.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.b92.net/info/vesti/index.php?yyyy=2010&amp;mm=07&amp;dd=06&amp;nav_category=16&amp;nav_id=443501|title=Policija brutalno tukla i devojke|work=B92.net|access-date=2 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.blic.rs/Vesti/Hronika/197194/Policija-nas-tukla--bez-razloga|title=Blic Online – Policija nas tukla bez razloga|work=Blic Online|access-date=2 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Police officials, including [[Ivica Dačić]], the Serbian minister of internal affairs, denied this sequence of events and accused the victims "to have attacked the police officers first". He also publicly stated that "police [aren't] here to beat up citizens", but that it is known "what one is going to get when attacking the police".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.b92.net/info/vesti/index.php?yyyy=2010&amp;mm=07&amp;dd=07&amp;nav_id=443903|title=Dačić: Policija nije tu da bije|work=B92.net|access-date=2 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Some recent{{when|date=November 2021}} episodes of police brutality in India include the [[Rajan case]], the death of Udayakumar,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.hindu.com/2005/10/04/stories/2005100419970300.htm|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20121110190836/http://www.hindu.com/2005/10/04/stories/2005100419970300.htm|url-status=dead|archive-date=10 November 2012|location=Chennai, India|work=[[The Hindu]]|title=Police question forensic experts|date=4 October 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; and of Sampath.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.hindu.com/2011/05/17/stories/2011051755890500.htm|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110521225829/http://www.hindu.com/2011/05/17/stories/2011051755890500.htm|url-status=dead|archive-date=21 May 2011|location=Chennai, India|work=[[The Hindu]]|title=Sampath case: 4 police officers to turn approvers|date=17 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Police violence episodes against peaceful demonstrators appeared during the [[2011 Spanish protests]].&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/may/27/spanish-protesters-clash-with-police Spanish police clash with protesters over clean-up] – ''The Guardian''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.publico.es/espana/378668/los-mossos-d-esquadra-desalojan-a-palos-la-plaza-de-catalunya Los Mossos d'Esquadra desalojan a palos la Plaza de Catalunya] – Público {{in lang|es}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{YouTube|id=Geg_6Xoy04s|title=Indignats – Desallotjament de la Plaça Catalunya}}&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, on 4 August 2011, Gorka Ramos, a journalist of ''Lainformacion'' was beaten by police and arrested while covering 15-M protests near the Interior Ministry in Madrid.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/aug/05/spanish-police-clash-austerity-protesters Spanish riot police clash in Madrid with anti-austerity protesters] – ''The Guardian''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.elmundo.es/elmundo/2011/08/05/comunicacion/1312558334.html Los periodistas, detenidos y golpeados al cubrir las manifestaciones del 15-M] – El Mundo {{in lang|es}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.publico.es/espana/390284/doce-policias-para-detener-a-un-periodista Doce policías para detener a un periodista] – Público {{in lang|es}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://videos.lainformacion.com/asuntos-sociales/gorka-ramos-me-tiraron-al-suelo-me-patearon-y-luego-me-detuvieron_mKeinSMbGcQSEzMAbwP8V/ Gorka Ramos: "Me tiraron al suelo, me patearon y luego me detuvieron"] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130512095239/http://videos.lainformacion.com/asuntos-sociales/gorka-ramos-me-tiraron-al-suelo-me-patearon-y-luego-me-detuvieron_mKeinSMbGcQSEzMAbwP8V/ |date=12 May 2013 }} – Lainformación {{in lang|es}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.elpais.com/videos/espana/policia/detiene/periodista/Gorka/Ramos/elpvidnac/20110805elpepunac_1/Ves/ La policía detiene al periodista Gorka Ramos] – El País {{in lang|es}}&lt;/ref&gt; A freelance photographer, Daniel Nuevo, was beaten by police while covering demonstrations against the Pope's visit in August 2011.&lt;ref&gt;[https://archive.today/20130423183742/http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/religion/the-pope/8711224/Spanish-police-officer-slaps-g--~~~~irl-during-Pope-protests.html Spanish police officer slaps girl during Pope protests] – ''The Telegraph''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.publico.es/espana/392134/la-policia-golpea-a-un-fotografo-y-a-una-joven La policía golpea a un fotógrafo y a una joven] – Público {{in lang|es}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*In Brazil, incidents of police violence have been very well-reported and Brazil has one of the highest prevalences of police brutality in the world today.
*South Africa from apartheid to today has had incidents of police brutality, though police violence is not as prevalent as during the apartheid years.
*There have been several instances of police brutality towards protesters in the [[2019–20 Hong Kong protests]].

== Investigation ==
In [[England and Wales]], an independent organization known as the [[Independent Police Complaints Commission]] (IPCC) investigates reports of police misconduct. They automatically investigate any deaths caused by or thought to be caused by, police action.

A similar body known as the [[Police Investigations and Review Commissioner]] (PIRC) operates in Scotland. In Northern Ireland, the [[Police Ombudsman for Northern Ireland]] has a similar role to that of the IPCC and PIRC.

In Africa, there exist two such bodies: one in South Africa and another one in Kenya known as the Independent Policing Oversight Authority.

In the United States, more police are wearing body cameras after the [[death of Michael Brown]]. The US Department of Justice has made a call to action for police departments across the nation to implement body cameras into their departments so further investigation will be possible.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=Investigation of the Ferguson Police Department|date=2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Measurement ==
Police brutality is measured based on the accounts of [[Crime victim|people who have experienced]] or [[Witness|seen it]], as well as the juries who are present for trials involving police brutality cases, as there is no objective method to quantify the use of excessive force for any particular situation.

In addition to this, police brutality may also be filmed by [[police body camera]]s, worn by police officers. Whereas body cams could be a tool against police brutality (by prevention, and by increasing accountability). However according to Harlan Yu, executive director from Upturn, for this to occur, it needs to be embedded in a broader change in culture and legal framework. In particular, the [[Open access|public's ability to access the body camera footage]] can be an issue.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite magazine|url=https://www.wired.com/story/body-cameras-stopped-police-brutality-george-floyd/|title=Body Cameras Haven't Stopped Police Brutality. Here's Why|magazine=Wired|via=www.wired.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://progressive.org/api/content/f8f69360-0ce1-11eb-948e-1244d5f7c7c6/|title=Why Police Body Cameras Haven't Stopped Police Brutality|first=Andrew|last=Lee|date=13 October 2020|website=Progressive.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.theverge.com/21378159/police-brutality-protests-body-cameras-video-surveillance-black-lives-matter|title=Police body cameras don't tell the whole story. This experiment shows it.|first=William|last=Poor|date=31 August 2020|website=The Verge}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1985, only one out of five people thought that police brutality was a serious problem. Police brutality is relative to a situation: it depends on if the suspect is resisting. Out of the people who were surveyed about their account of the police brutality in 2008, only about 12% felt as if they had been resisting.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Bureau of Justice Statistics|title=Use of Force|url=http://www.bjs.gov/index.cfm?ty=tp&amp;tid=703|website=Bureau of Justice Statistics|publisher=Office of Justice Programs|access-date=15 November 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although the police force itself cannot be quantified, the opinion of brutality among various races, genders, and ages can. African Americans, women, and younger people are more likely to have negative opinions about the police than Caucasians, men and middle-aged to elderly individuals.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Jefferis|first1=Eric|last2=Butcher|first2=Fredrick|last3=Hanley|first3=Dena|title=Measuring perceptions of police use of force|journal=Police Practice and Research|date=2012|volume=13|issue=6|pages=81–96}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Independent oversight ==
Various community groups have criticized police brutality. These groups often stress the need for oversight by independent [[civilian review board]]s and other methods of ensuring accountability for police action.

Umbrella organizations and justice committees usually support those affected. [[Amnesty International]] is a non-governmental organization focused on human rights with over 3 million members and supporters around the world. The stated objective of the organization is "to conduct research and generate action to prevent and end grave abuses of human rights, and to demand justice for those whose rights have been violated".

Tools used by these groups include video recordings, which are sometimes broadcast using websites such as [[YouTube]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=YouTube.com prompts police beating probe |url=https://abcnews.go.com/US/wireStory?id=2645350&amp;CMP=OTC-RSSFeeds0312 |agency=Associated Press |last=Veiga |first=Alex |date=11 November 2006 |access-date=12 November 2006 |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20061130233223/https://abcnews.go.com/US/wireStory?id=2645350&amp;CMP=OTC-RSSFeeds0312 |archive-date=30 November 2006 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Civilians have begun independent projects to monitor police activity to try to reduce violence and misconduct. These are often called "Cop Watch" programs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Policing the Police: Civilian Video Monitoring of Police Activity|url=http://theglobaljournal.net/group/global-minds/article/643/|publisher=[[The Global Journal]]|last=Krupanski|first=Marc|date=7 March 2012|access-date=13 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Authoritarian personality]]
* [[Civil liberties]]
* [[Civil rights]]
* [[Death squad]]
* [[Suicide by cop]]
* [[International Day Against Police Brutality]] (15 March)
* [[Law enforcement agency]]
* [[Law enforcement and society]]
* [[Legal observer]]
* [[List of cases of police brutality]]
* [[List of killings by law enforcement officers in the United States]]
* [[List of killings by law enforcement officers in Canada]]
* [[Militarization of police]]
* [[Photography is Not a Crime]]
* [[Police misconduct]]
* [[Police riot]]
* [[Prisoner abuse]]
* [[Rough ride (police brutality)|Rough ride]]
* [[Use of force continuum]]

===US specific===
* [[Christopher Commission]]
* [[Copwatch]]
* [[Pitchess motion]]
*[[Police brutality in the United States|Police Brutality in the United States]]

== References ==

{{reflist}}

== Further reading ==
* {{Cite book|editor-last=della Porta|editor-first=Donatella|editor-link=Donatella della Porta|title=The policing of transnational protest|date=2006|publisher=Ashgate|editor-last2=Peterson|editor-first2=Abby|editor-last3=Reiter|editor-first3=Herbert}}
* {{Cite book|last=della Porta|first=Donatella|title=Policing protest : the control of mass demonstrations in Western democracies|date=1998|publisher=Univ. of Minnesota Press|isbn=0-8166-3063-1}}
* {{Cite book|last=Donner|first=Frank J.|title=Protectors of privilege : red squads and police repression in urban America|date=1990|publisher=University of California Press|isbn=0-520-05951-4|location=Berkeley}}
* {{cite journal | last1 = Earl | first1 = Jennifer S. | last2 = Soule | first2 = Sarah A. | year = 2006 | title = Seeing Blue: A Police-Centered Explanation of Protest Policing | journal = Mobilization | volume = 11 | issue = 2| pages = 145–164 | doi = 10.17813/maiq.11.2.u1wj8w41n301627u }}
* {{cite journal | last1 = Oliver | first1 = P | year = 2008 | title = Repression and Crime Control: Why Social Movements Scholars Should Pay Attention to Mass Incarceration Rates as a Form of Repression | journal = Mobilization | volume = 13 | issue = 1| pages = 1–24 | doi = 10.17813/maiq.13.1.v264hx580h486641}}
* {{Cite book|last=Ross|first=J.I.|title=Making news of police violence a comparative study of Toronto and New York City|date=2000|publisher=Praeger|isbn=0-275-96825-1}}
* {{Cite book|last1=Zwerman|first1=G.|title=Repression and mobilization|last2=Steinhoff|first2=P.|date=2005|publisher=University of Minnesota Press|editor-last=Davenport|editor-first=C.|location=Minneapolis|pages=85–107|language=English|chapter=When activists ask for trouble: state-dissident interactions and the new left cycle of resistance in the United States and Japan|editor-last2=Johnston|editor-first2=H.|editor-last3=Mueller|editor-first3=C.}}
* {{Cite book|last=Hessbruegge|first=Jan Arno|title=Human rights and personal self-defense in international law|date=2017|isbn=978-0-19-065503-7|edition=First|location=New York, NY}}

== External links ==
{{Commons category}}
{{Wiktionary}}
{{Library resources box|onlinebooks=yes}}
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20150510011129/http://copcrisis.com/ Police Brutality Statistics]
* [http://www.policebrutality.info/ Worldwide Police Brutalities archive]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20070612152202/http://members.fortunecity.com/brutalitycanada/names.html Names of Victims of Police Brutality In Canada]
* [http://theglobaljournal.net/group/global-minds/article/643/ Policing the Police: Civilian Video Monitoring of Police Activity]
* [https://www.politicalgraphics.org/to-protect-and-serve To Protect and Serve?: Five Decades of Posters Protesting Police Violence]

{{Abuse}}
{{Discrimination}}
{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Police brutality| ]]
[[Category:1870s neologisms]]
[[Category:Abuse]]
[[Category:Articles containing video clips]]
[[Category:Human rights abuses]]
[[Category:Political repression]]
[[Category:Protests against police brutality| ]]
[[Category:Terrorism]]
[[Category:Violence]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>