<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20071112175437|170998487" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="166029" pageid="166029" ns="0" title="Police brutality"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-11-12T17:55:04Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[Image:1919 Battle of George Square - David Kirkwood on the ground after being struck by police batons.jpg|thumb|right|300px|January 31 [[1919]]: [[David Kirkwood]] on the ground after being struck by batons of the [[Glasgow]] police]]

'''Police brutality''' is a term used to describe the excessive use of physical force, [[assault]], verbal attacks, and threats by [[police officer]]s and other law enforcement officers. The term may also be used to apply to such behavior when used by [[prison officer]]s.  Widespread, systematic police brutality exists in many countries, even those which prosecute it.&lt;ref name="Amnesty 2007"&gt;{{cite web | title = Amnesty International Report 2007  | url = http://thereport.amnesty.org/eng/Homepage | publisher = Amnesty International |date= 2007 | accessdate - 2007-08-08 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Brutality is one of several forms of [[police misconduct]] which include [[false arrest]], [[intimidation]], [[racial profiling]], [[political repression]], [[surveillance abuse]], [[sexual abuse]], and [[police corruption]]. 

==History==
Throughout history, efforts to police societies have been marred by brutality to some degree.  In the ancient world, policing entities actively cultivated an atmosphere of terror, and abusive treatment was meted out in the quest for subjugation and control.  For example, the [[New Testament]] records many incidents in which [[Military of ancient Rome|Roman guards]] inflicted unwarranted violence on members of the growing [[Early Christianity|Christian]] minority.

In the English-speaking world, most modern police departments were first established in the  nineteenth century, and in the early days cases of police brutality were frequent.  In her book ''Street Justice: A History of Police Violence in New York City'', researcher Marilynn S. Johnson describes "the routine bludgeoning of citizens by patrolmen armed with nightsticks or blackjacks.".&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite book | last = Johnson | first = Marilynn S. | editor = Johnson | title = Street Justice: A History of Police Violence in New York City | year = 2004 | publisher = Beacon Press | id = ISBN 0807050237 | pages = 365}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Large-scale incidents of brutality were often associated with labor unrest, such as the [[Great Railroad Strike of 1877]], the [[Pullman Strike]] of 1894, the [[Lawrence textile strike]] of 1912, the [[Ludlow massacre]] of 1914, the [[Steel strike of 1919]], and the [[Hanapepe massacre]] of [[1922]].
[[Image:Bloody Sunday-Alabama police attack.jpeg|right|250px|thumb|March 7 [[1965]]: Alabama police attack Selma-to-Montgomery Marchers ([[Federal Bureau of Investigation]] photograph)]]
[[Image:Rk910303.jpg|right|250px|thumb| March 3, [[1991]]: [[Rodney King]] beaten by [[LAPD]] officers]] 
[[Image:ftaapolice.png|250px|right|thumb|April 21 [[2001]]: Police fire [[CS gas]] at protesters during the [[Quebec City Summit of the Americas]]. The Commission for Public Complaints against the RCMP later concluded the use of tear gas against demonstrators at the summit constituted "excessive and unjustified force."]]

In the United States, the passage of the [[Volstead Act]] (popularly known as the National Prohibition Act) in [[1919]] had a long-term negative impact on policing practices.  By the mid-1920s, crime was growing dramatically in response to the demand for illegal alcohol.  Undermanned and with limited resources, many law enforcement agencies stepped up the use of unlawful practices.  By the time of the [[Herbert Clark Hoover|Hoover]] administration ([[1929]]-[[1932]]), the issue had risen to national concern and a National Committee on Law Observation and Enforcement (popularly known as the [[Wickersham Commission]]) was formed to look into the situation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Wicker shambles |url = http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,740911-3,00.html | publisher = Time Magazine | date =1931-02-02 | accessdate = 2007-09-05 }}&lt;/ref&gt;   The resulting [[Wickersham report|"Report on Lawlessness in Law Enforcement"]] ([[1931]]) concluded that "[t]he [[third degree]]--that is, the use of physical brutality, or other forms of cruelty, to obtain involuntary confessions or admissions--is widespread."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title =  Records of the Wickersham Commission on Law Observance and Enforcement |url = http://www.lexisnexis.com/academic/guides/jurisprudence/wickersham.asp | publisher = LexisNexis | author = University Publications of America | date = 1997-12 | accessdate = 2007-09-05 }}&lt;/ref&gt;   In the years following the report, landmark legal judgements such as [[Brown v. Mississippi]] helped to cement a legal obligation to respect the [[due process]] clause of the [[Fourteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Fourteenth Amendment]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=[[United States Supreme Court]] |title=BROWN et al. v. STATE OF MISSISSIPPI. |url=http://www.injusticeline.com/brown.html |work= |publisher=www.injusticeline.com |date=1936-02-17 |accessdate=2007-09-05 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 1960s, the [[African-American Civil Rights Movement]] had to overcome numerous incidents of police brutality in its struggle for justice and racial equality, notably during the [[Birmingham campaign]] of 1963-64 and during the [[Selma to Montgomery marches]] of [[1965]].  Media coverage of the brutality sparked national outrage, and public sympathy for the movement grew rapidly as a result.

During the Vietnam War, anti-war demonstrations were sometimes quelled through the use of billy-clubs and [[CS gas]], commonly known as tear gas. The most notorious of these assaults took place during the August [[1968 Democratic National Convention]] in [[Chicago]]. The actions of the police were later described as a "[[police riot]]" in the Walker Report to the [[US National Commission on the Causes and Prevention of Violence]].&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite book | last = Walker | first = Daniel | editor = Johnson | title = Rights in Conflict: The violent confrontation of demonstrators and police in the parks and streets of Chicago during the week of the Democratic National Convention of 1968. A report submitted by Daniel Walker, director of the Chicago Study Team, to the National Commission on the Causes and Prevention of Violence. 
| year = 1968 | publisher = Braceland Brothers | pages = 233}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As was the case with [[Prohibition]] during the 1920s and 1930s, the "[[War on Drugs]]" initiated by President [[Richard M. Nixon]] in [[1969]] has been marked by increased [[police misconduct]].  Critics contend that a "[[holy war]]" mentality&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | title = Has the Drug War Created an Officer Liars' Club? |url = http://www.druglibrary.org/schaffer/debate/mcn/mcn6.htm | publisher = Los Angeles Times | author = Joseph D. McNamara | date = 1996-02-11 | accessdate = 2007-09-06 }}&lt;/ref&gt; has helped to nurture a "new militarized style of policing" where "confrontation has replaced investigation.".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | title = Kill Zone |url = http://www.worldnetdaily.com/news/article.asp?ARTICLE_ID=39486 | publisher = WorldNetDaily.com | author = Joel Miller | date = 2004-07-17 | accessdate = 2007-09-06 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  

In the United States, race and police brutality continue to be closely linked, and the phenomenon has sparked a string of [[race riots]] over the years.  Especially notable among these incidents was the uprising caused by the arrest and beating of [[Rodney King]] on [[March 3]], [[1991]] by officers of the [[Los Angeles Police Department]].  The atmosphere was particularly volatile because the brutality had been videotaped by a bystander and widely broadcast afterwards.   When the four law enforcement officers charged with assault and other charges were acquitted, the [[1992 Los Angeles Riots]] broke out.

In recent years,  police brutality has often flared at global summits where protesters have sought to challenge the legitimacy of various institutions of economic globalization such as the [[World Trade Organization|WTO]], the [[World Bank]], the [[International Monetary Fund|IMF]], the [[G8]], and international trade regimes such as the [[North American Free Trade Agreement|NAFTA]] and the [[Free Trade Area of the Americas|FTAA]].  [[Crowd control]] efforts at these events are often characterized by the use of "less-than-lethal" means of force, such as [[CS gas]], [[Plastic bullet]]s, [[Taser]]s, and [[police dog]]s.

Numerous [[human rights]] observers have raised concerns about increased police brutality in the wake of the [[September 11, 2001 attacks]] on the [[World Trade Center]].  An extensive report prepared for the [[United Nations Human Rights Committee]] tabled in [[2006]] states that in the [[United States]], the "[[War on Terror]]" has "created a generalized climate of impunity for law enforcement officers, and contributed to the erosion of what few accountability mechanisms exist for civilian control over law enforcement agencies. As a result, police brutality and abuse persist unabated and undeterred across the country."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = In the Shadows of the War on Terror: Persisitent Police Brutality and Abuse in the United States |url = http://www.ohchr.org/english/bodies/hrc/docs/ngos/law%20enforcement%20shadow%20rpt%20final.pdf | publisher = United Nations Committee on Human Rights | format=[[PDF]] date = 2006-06 | accessdate = 2007-09-11 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Incidence==
An extensive [[U.S. Department of Justice]] report on police use of force released in [[2001]] indicates that in [[1999]], "approximately 422,000 people 16 years old and older were estimated to have had contact with police in which force or the threat of force was used." &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Contacts between Police and the Public: Findings from the 1999 National Survey  | url = http://www.ojp.usdoj.gov/bjs/pub/press/cpp99.htm | publisher = Bureau of Justice Statistics  |date= 2001-03-21 | accessdate - 2007-08-27 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Another Department of Justice report issued in [[2006]] shows that out of 26,556 citizen complaints about excessive use of police force among large U.S. agencies (representing 5% of agencies and 59% of officers) in [[2002]], about 2000 were sustained.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Citizen Complaints about Police Use of Force  | url = http://www.ojp.usdoj.gov/bjs/abstract/ccpuf.htm | publisher = Bureau of Justice Statistics | author = Matthew Hickman |date= 2006-06-26 | accessdate - 2007-08-27 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

However, other studies have shown that most police brutality goes unreported. In [[1982]], the federal government funded a "Police Services Study" in which over 12,000 randomly selected citizens were interviewed in three metropolitan areas. The study found that 13 percent of those surveyed had been victims of police brutality the previous year. Yet only 30 percent of those who acknowledged such brutality filed formal complaints.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Fighting Police Abuse: A Community Action Manual  | url = http://www.aclu.org/police/gen/14614pub19971201.html | publisher = American Civil Liberties Union |date= 1997-12-1 | accessdate - 2007-08-06 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  A [[1998]] [[Human Rights Watch]] report stated that in all 14 precincts which it examined, the process of filing a complaint was "unnecessarily difficult and often intimidating."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Shielded from Justice: Police Brutality and Accountability in the United States  | url = http://www.hrw.org/reports98/police/uspo20.htm | publisher = Human Rights Watch |date= June, 1998 | accessdate - 2007-08-08 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Police brutality is often associated with the phenomenon of [[racial profiling]]. Differences in [[race]], [[religion]], [[politics]], and [[socioeconomics|socioeconomic status]] between police and the citizenry can contribute to the creation of a relationship in which some police officers may view the population (or a particular subset thereof) as generally deserving punishment while these portions of the population view the police as [[oppression|oppressors]]. In addition, there is a perception that victims of police brutality often belong to relatively powerless groups, such as minorities, the young, and the poor.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite book | last = Powers | first = Mary D. | editor = Winters, Paul A. | title = Policing the Police | year = 1995 | publisher = Greenhaven Press | location = San Diego | id = ISBN 1-56510-262-2 | pages = 56–60 | chapter = Civilian Oversight Is Necessary to Prevent Police Brutality }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Recent [[Amnesty International]] and [[Human Rights Watch]] reports confirm that prison guard brutality is especially rife within the U.S.  A 2006 [[Human Rights Watch]] watch report entitled "Cruel and Degrading: The Use of Dogs for Cell Extractions in U.S. Prisons" revealed that five state prison systems permit the use of aggressive, unmuzzled dogs to terrify and even attack prisoners as part of cell removal procedures.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Cruel and Degrading: The Use of Dogs for Cell Extractions in U.S. Prisons | url = http://hrw.org/reports/2006/us1006/ | publisher = Human Rights Watch |date= 2006 | accessdate - 2007-08-08 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Amnesty International]] 2007 report on human rights also documents widespread police misconduct in many other countries.&lt;ref name="Amnesty 2007"/&gt;

==Causes==
In dealing largely with disorderly elements of the society, some people working in law enforcement may gradually develop an attitude or sense of authority over society, particularly under traditional reaction-based policing models; in some cases the police believe that they are above the law.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Skolnick | first = Jerome H. | coauthors = Fyfe, James D. | editor = Winters, Paul A. | title = Policing the Police | year = 1995 | publisher = Greenhaven Press | location = San Diego | id = ISBN 1-56510-262-2 | pages = 45–55 | chapter = Community-Oriented Policing Would Prevent Police Brutality }}&lt;/ref&gt;

However the "bad apple paradigm" is considered to be often used as an "easy way out". A broad RCMP-commissioned report on the causes of misconduct in policing calls it "a simplistic explanation that permits the organization and senior management to blame corruption on individuals and individual faults – behavioural, psychological, background factors, and so on, rather than addressing systemic factors."&lt;ref name="RCMP Review"&gt;{{cite web | last = Loree | first = Don | title = Corruption in Policing: Causes and Consequences; A Review of the Literature | work = Research and Evaluation Community, Contract and Aboriginal Policing Services Directorate  | publisher = Royal Canadian Mounted Police | date = [[2006]] | url = http://dsp-psd.pwgsc.gc.ca/Collection/PS64-27-2006E.pdf | format = [[PDF]] | accessdate = 2007-09-01 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  The report goes on to discuss the systemic factors, which include 
* pressures to conform to certain aspects of "police culture", such as the [[Blue Code of Silence]] which can "sustain an oppositional criminal subculture protecting the interests of police who violate the law"&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last = Skolnick | first = Jerome H. | title = Corruption and the Blue Code of Silence | journal = Police Practice and Research  | volume = 3(1) | page = 7 | date = [[2002]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; and a "'we-they' perspective in which outsiders are viewed with suspicion or distrust"&lt;ref name="RCMP Review"/&gt;;
* command and control structures with a rigid hierarchical foundation ("results indicate that the more rigid the hierarchy, the lower the scores on a measure of ethical decision-making" concludes one study reviewed in the report);&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last = Owens | first = Katherine M. B. | coauthors = Jeffrey Pfeifer | title = Police Leadership and Ethics: Training and Police Recommendations | journal = The Canadian Journal of Police and Security Services | volume = 1(2) | pages = 7 | date = [[2002]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; and
* deficiencies in internal accountability mechanisms (including internal investigation processes).&lt;ref name="RCMP Review"/&gt;

Some members of the public may in fact perceive the use of force by police as excessive even when the force used is not only reasonable, but is also appropriate under the circumstances. Police use of force is kept in check in many jurisdictions by the issuance of a [[use of force continuum]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Stetser | first = Merle | title = The Use of Force in Police Control of Violence: Incidents Resulting in Assaults on Officers |date= 2001 | publisher = LFB Scholarly Publishing L.L.C. | location = New York | id = ISBN 1-931202-08-7 }}&lt;/ref&gt; A use of force continuum sets levels of force considered appropriate in direct response to a subject's behavior. This power is granted by the civil government, with limits set out in [[statutory law]] as well as [[common law]].

==Investigation==
In the [[United States]], investigation of cases of police brutality has often been left to internal police commissions and/or [[district attorney]]s (DAs). Internal police commissions have often been criticized for a lack of accountability and for bias favoring officers, as they frequently declare upon review that the officer(s) acted within the department's rules, or according to their training.  For instance, a study focussing on the [[Chicago Police Department]] which was conducted in April [[2007]] found that out of more than 10,000 complaints of police abuse that were filed between 2002 and 2004, only 19 resulted in meaningful disciplinary action. The study charges that the police department’s oversight body allows officers with "criminal tendencies to operate with impunity," and argues that the [[Chicago Police Department]] should not be allowed to police itself.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | title = Study: Police abuse goes unpunished |url = http://news.medill.northwestern.edu/chicago/news.aspx?id=6125 | publisher = Medill School, Northwestern University, Chicago | author = Ryan Gallagher | date = 2007-04-04 | accessdate = 2007-09-04 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  

The ability of district attorneys to investigate police brutality has also been called into question, as DAs depend on help from police departments to bring cases to trial.  It was only in the 1990s that serious efforts began to be made to transcend the difficulties of dealing with systemic patterns of misconduct in police departments. 

Beyond police departments and DAs, other mechanisms of government oversight have gradually evolved.  The [[Rodney King]] case triggered the creation of the [[Independent Commission on the Los Angeles Police Department]], informally known as the [[Christopher Commission]], in 1991.  The commission, mandated to investigate the practices of the [[Los Angeles Police Department|LAPD]], uncovered disturbing patterns of misconduct and abuse, but the reforms it  recommended were put on hold.  Meanwhile, media reports revealed a frustration in dealing with systemic abuse in other jurisdictions as well, such as New York and Pittsburgh.  Selwyn Raab of the [[New York Times]] wrote about how the "[[Blue Code of Silence]] among police officers helped to conceal even the most outrageous examples of misconduct."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | title = The Dark Blue Code of Silence |url = http://www.nytimes.com/books/98/02/08/home/15700.html | publisher = New York Times | author = Selwyn Raab | date = 1993-5-2 | accessdate = 2007-08-27 }}&lt;/ref&gt; 

It was within this climate that the police misconduct provision of the [[Violent Crime Control and Law Enforcement Act]] of [[1994]] was created, authorizing the [[Attorney General]] to "file lawsuits seeking court orders to reform police departments engaging in a pattern or practice of violating citizens' federal rights."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Conduct of Law Enforcement Agencies |url = http://www.usdoj.gov/crt/split/police.htm | publisher = U.S. Department of Justice | author = Civil Rights Division | date = 2007-08-16 | accessdate = 2007-08-27 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  As of January 31 [[2003]], the [[Department of Justice]] has used this provision to negotiate reforms in eleven jurisdictions across the U.S. ([[Pittsburgh]] Bureau of Police, [[Steubenville]] Police Department, [[New Jersey State Police]], [[Los Angeles Police Department]], [[District of Columbia]] Metropolitan Police Department, [[Highland Park]] Police Department, [[Cincinnati]] Police Department, [[Columbus Police Department]], [[Buffalo, New York|Buffalo]] Police Department, [[Mount Prospect]] Police Department, and the [[Montgomery County]] Police Department).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Department of Justice Police Misconduct Pattern or Practice Program |url = http://www.usdoj.gov/crt/split/faq.htm#pppmp.htm | publisher = U.S. Department of Justice | author = Civil Rights Division | date = 2003-01-1 | accessdate = 2007-08-27 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the [[United Kingdom]], an independent organization known as the [[Independent Police Complaints Commission]] investigates reports of police misconduct. They automatically investigate any deaths caused by, or thought to be caused by, police action.

==Prevention and redress==

===Independent oversight===
Various community groups have criticized police brutality. These groups often stress the need for oversight by independent citizen review boards and other methods of ensuring accountability for police action. 

[[Copwatch]] is a [[U.S.]]-based network of organizations that actively monitors and videotapes the police to prevent police brutality. Umbrella organizations and justice committees (often named after a deceased individual or those victimized by police violence) usually engage in a solidarity of those affected. [[Amnesty International]] is another organization active in the issue of police brutality.

Tools used by these groups include video recordings, which are sometimes broadcast using websites such as [[YouTube]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | title = YouTube.com prompts police beating probe | url = http://abcnews.go.com/US/wireStory?id=2645350&amp;CMP=OTC-RSSFeeds0312 | publisher = [[Associated Press]] | last = Veiga | first = Alex |date= November 11, 2006 | accessdate = 2006-11-12 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Legislation protecting against police brutality===

====Canada====
*[[Section Seven of the Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms]] - protects an individual's autonomy and legal rights and guarantees [[due process]]
*[[Section Eight of the Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms]] - protects against unreasonable [[searches and seizures]]
*[[Section Nine of the Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms]] - against arbitrary detainment and imprisonment. The provision is invoked in the criminal law context generally where a police officer who stops, detains, arrests or otherwise restrains a suspect without reasonable grounds.
*[[Section Ten of the Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms]] - specifies rights upon arrest or detention, including the rights to consult a lawyer and the right to [[habeas corpus]].

====United States====
*[[Fourth Amendment to the United States Constitution]] - protects against unreasonable [[searches and seizures]]
*[[Fourteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution]] - includes the [[Due Process]] and [[Equal Protection]] clauses 
*[[Civil Rights Act of 1871]] - this has evolved into a key U.S. law in brutality cases (see: "[http://www.constitution.org/brief/forsythe_42-1983.htm A guide to civil rights liability under 42 U.S.C. § 1983]" for a detailed analysis of the section which is now of central relevance in excessive force lawsuits)
*[[Federal Tort Claims Act]] - key U.S. law in brutality cases (particularly those which hinge upon  negligence claims)


== Notable cases of police brutality ==
See: [[List of cases of police brutality]]

==See also==
*[[Police misconduct]]
*[[Police riot]]
*[[Prisoner abuse]]
*[[State terrorism]]
*[[Christopher Commission]]
*[[Copwatch]]
*[[COINTELPRO]]
*[[Racism]]
*[[International Day Against Police Brutality]] (March 15)
*[[Civil rights]]
*[[Civil liberties]]

==References==
&lt;div class="references-small"&gt;
&lt;references/&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

==External links==
*[http://web.amnesty.org/report2005/index-eng Amnesty International 2005 World Report]
*[http://PoliceCrimes.com PoliceCrimes.com: News on police brutality and other police misconduct]
*[http://copbrutality.com Bringing awareness of Excessive Force, Malicious Prosecution and Police Brutality.]
*[http://BadCopNews.com Bad Cop News: Extensive archives on police misconduct]
*[http://members.fortunecity.com/brutalitycanada/names.html Names of Victims of Police Brutality In Canada]
*[http://www.geocities.com/CapitolHill/6174/polbrutality2001.html Police Misconduct, Brutality and Use of Force in Canada - 2001] - includes links to lists for Canadian brutality victims in years going back to 1975
*[http://www.october22.org/StolenLivesProject.html Stolen Lives Project] - project documenting cases of killings by U.S. law enforcement
*[http://www.copwatch.org/ Copwatch Project] Includes the Copwatch Database: a permanent, searchable repository of complaints filed against police officers.

[[Category:Human rights abuses]]
[[Category:Law enforcement]]
[[Category:Alleged police brutality| ]]

[[es:Brutalidad policíaca]]
[[fr:Violence policière]]
[[no:Politivold]]
[[sv:Polisbrutalitet]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>