<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061113152000|87547896" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="166029" pageid="166029" ns="0" title="Police brutality"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-11-13T15:20:57Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{abuse}}
[[Image:1919 Battle of George Square - David Kirkwood on the ground after being struck by police batons.jpg|thumb|[[David Kirkwood]] on the ground after being struck by police batons]]
'''Police brutality''' is a term used to describe the excessive use of physical force, [[assault]], verbal attacks, and threats by [[police officer]]s and other law enforcement officers. The term may also be used to apply to such behavior when used by [[prison officer]]s.  Widespread, systematic police brutality exists in many countries, even those which prosecute it. Brutality is one of several forms of [[police misconduct]] which include; [[false arrest]], [[intimidation]], [[racial profiling]], [[political repression]], [[surveillance abuse]], [[sexual abuse]], and [[police corruption]]. 

==Alleged Corruption==
Use of force and authority by police to some groups can be — or be perceived to be — disproportionate. Differences in [[race]], [[religion]], [[politics]], and [[socioeconomics|socioeconomic status]] between police and the citizenry can contribute to the creation of a relationship in which some police officers may view the population (or a particular subset thereof) as generally deserving punishment while these portions of the population view the police as [[oppression|oppressors]]. 

Police are employed by society to maintain order, but by dealing largely with disorderly elements of the society, some people working in law enforcement may gradually develop an attitude or sense of authority over society. The growing number of cases of police brutality is usually attributed not to increased awareness within police ranks, but merely to more widespread use of [[video camera]]s.

Alternatively, some members of the public may in fact perceive the use of force by police as excessive, even when the force used is not only reasonable, but is also appropriate under the circumstances.  Police use of force is kept in check in many jurisdictions by the issuance of a [[use of force continuum]].  A use of force continuum sets levels of force considered appropriate in direct response to a subject's behavior.  This power is granted by the civil government, with limits set out in [[statutory law]] as well as [[common law]].

===Investigation===
In the [[United States]], cases of police brutality are investigated by internal police commissions, [[district attorney]]s (DAs) and the [[Federal Bureau of Investigation]] (FBI). Internal police commissions are often criticized for bias to the officers as they frequently declare upon review that the officer(s) acted within the department's rules, or according to their training. Additionally, the ability of district attorneys to investigate police brutality is called into question, as DAs depend on help from Police Departments to bring cases to trial. In contrast, the FBI is believed by many to be objective in its work in this area, but it investigates only a fraction of suspect cases of police brutality.

In the [[United Kingdom]], an independent organization known as the [[Independent Police Complaints Commission]] investigates reports of police misconduct. They automatically investigate any deaths caused by, or thought to be caused by, police action.

===Politics===
In some cases the police can be seen as siding with or against a government on political issues. For example during the [[Quebec City Summit of the Americas]] in 2001, it was believed by the anti-globalists that the police were defending the [[capitalist]] objectives of the summit participants, yet many people viewed those anti-globalists' actions as unreasonable and destructive.  Another example is when, in March 2006, masked Kenyan police attacked a media outlet during the midst of a government [[Political corruption|corruption]] scandal; see [[Corruption in Kenya]] for details.

==Human Rights==
The [[Amnesty International]] 2005 report on human rights alleges widespread police misconduct in many countries. Some notable countries include [[Canada]], the [[United Kingdom]], [[France]], the [[United States]], [[Germany]], [[Austria]], [[Switzerland]] and [[Brazil]].

==Community Response==
Various community groups have criticized police brutality. These groups often stress the need for oversight by independent citizen review boards and other methods of ensuring accountability for police action. 

[[Copwatch]] is a [[U.S.]]-based network of organizations that actively monitors and videotapes the police to prevent police brutality. Umbrella organizations and justice committees (often named after a deceased individual or those victimized by police violence) usually engage in a solidarity of those affected. [[Amnesty International]] is another organization active in the issue of police brutality.

Tools used by these groups include video recordings, which are sometimes broadcast using websites such as [[YouTube]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | title = YouTube.com prompts police beating probe | url = http://abcnews.go.com/US/wireStory?id=2645350&amp;CMP=OTC-RSSFeeds0312 | publisher = [[Associated Press]] | last = Veiga | first = Alex | date = November 11, 2006 | accessdate = 2006-11-12 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Self-described police monitoring organizations have themselves sometimes been the target of criticism. For example, some have interpreted the response of such groups to police shootings as calls to retaliate against the police, even when not explicitly stated as such.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Portland's crazed leftists / Arissa / Rose City Copwatch | publisher =  Willamette Week Online | url = http://www.wweek.com/editorial/3024/4997 | date = April 14 | year = 2004 | accessdate = 2006-10-08 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Selected Cases of Police Brutality ==
&lt;!-- Do not add new names or items to this list without first (a) verifying the information through a reliable neutral source, and (b) posting it on the talk page first for discussion. --&gt;

*[[Martin Lee Anderson]] died in [[2006]] at a [[Florida]] juvenile detention facility after allegedly suffering a beating by as many as eight guards, recorded by videotape. An investigation is ongoing. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = FDLE Investigates Death of Martin Lee Anderson | url = http://www.fdle.state.fl.us/press_releases/20060110_Martin_Anderson.html | publisher = Florida Department of Law Enforcement | date = 2006-01-10 | accessdate - 2006-08-05 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Anthony Baez]] died in a confrontation with [[New York City]] police in which a chokehold was used on him.  Police officer Francis Livoti was indicted and acquitted, but was later convicted in federal court of perjury.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Mayor Giuliani signs bill that names Bronx street after Anthony Baez | url = http://www.nyc.gov/html/om/html/2000a/pr135-00.html | format = Press release | publisher = City of New York | date = 2000-04-17 | accessdate = 2006-08-07 }} &lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Every Mother's Son - About the film | publisher = Public Broadcasting System | url = http://www.pbs.org/pov/pov2004/everymothersson/about.html | accessdate = 2006-08-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Steve Biko]] was allegedly killed by police as a result of anti-[[apartheid]] demonstrations in [[South Africa]] in [[1977]]. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.sahistory.org.za/pages/people/biko,s.htm | title = Stephen Bantu Biko | work = South African History Online | accessdate = 2006-08-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Oscar Elías Biscet]] is a [[Cuba]]n political prisoner, arrested in December [[2002]], who is reportedly not allowed to have food or medicines brought to him by his wife, a situation which has caused his health to deteriorate.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | format = Press release | title = Treatment of Oscar Elias Biscet and Other Cuban Political Prisoners | url = http://www.state.gov/r/pa/prs/ps/2004/34570.htm | accessdate = 2006-08-07 | date = 2004-07-21 | last = Boucher | first = Richard | publisher = United States Department of State }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Robert Davis (New Orleans)|Robert Davis]] was filmed in an altercation with New Orleans police officers in October 2005. Two officers were later fired and charged with battery as a result of the incident.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | title = New Orleans policemen suspended |url = http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/americas/4325574.stm | publisher = BBC News | author = Alistair Leithead | date = 2005-10-10 | accessdate = 2006-08-10 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Amadou Diallo]] was shot and killed in February 1999 by New York City police officers while unarmed after the officers claimed they believed he was reaching for a gun. Four officers were indicted for second-degree murder but later acquitted.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Officers acquitted of all charges in Diallo shooting | url = http://www.courttv.com/trials/diallo/verdict.html | publisher = Courtroom Television Network (Court TV) | date = 2000-02-25 | accessdate = 2006-08-11 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Johnny Gammage]] was a black motorist who died in a scuffle with white police officers. Three officers were charged with involuntary manslaughter, although at least one was acquitted.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url = http://www.cnn.com/US/9611/13/verdict/ | title = White officer acquitted in death of black motorist | publisher = CNN | date = 1996-11-13 | accessdate = 2006-08-13 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Frank Jude Jr.]] was beaten while unarmed by three off-duty police officers, who were charged but acquitted.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last = Grinburg | first = Emanuella | title = Off-duty Milwaukee officers cleared in beating of unarmed man | url = http://www.courttv.com/trials/jude/041406_verdict_ctv.html | publisher = Courtroom Television Network (Court TV) | date = 2006-04-20 | accessdate = 2006-08-14 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Abner Louima]] was sexually abused by New York City police officers in 1997. A number of officers were convicted in the case.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | publisher = CBS Worldwide | title = Louima Cop Sentenced | url = http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2000/06/27/national/main209867.shtml | date = 2000-06-27 | accessdate = 2006-08-11 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Benno Ohnesorg]], a German university student, was shot dead by police officer [[Karl-Heinz Kurras]] during a demonstration in [[Berlin]] on 2 June 1967. Kurras was charged with manslaughter but acquitted.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Thomas | first= Nick | title = Protest Movements in 1960s West Germany: A Social History of Dissent and Democracy |location = Oxford | publisher = Berg |year = 2003}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last = Seifert| first = Jurgen | coauthors = ''et al.'' | title = Defining the Enemy of the State: Political Policies of West Germany | year = 1976 | journal = New German Critique | volume = 8 | pages = 42-53}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Corruption in Kenya]]
*[[Human rights abuses by Hong Kong police]]
*[[Paris massacre of 1961]]
*[[Police riot]]
*[[Prisoner abuse]]
*[[State terrorism]]
*''[[Training Day]]''
*''[[Strip Search]]'', a film that deals with brutality.
*[[Tompkins Square Park Police Riot]]
*[[Vel'd'hiv raid]] in [[Vichy France]] on July 16, 1942
*[[Stonewall Riots]] on June 28, 1969

==References==
&lt;div class="references-small"&gt;
&lt;references/&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
==External links==
*[http://web.amnesty.org/report2005/index-eng Amnesty International 2005 World Report]

[[Category:Human rights abuses]]
[[Category:Law enforcement]]

[[fr:Violence policière]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>