<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20191126035213|928000529" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="26410" pageid="26410" ns="0" title="Conversion therapy"><revisions><rev timestamp="2019-11-26T03:54:13Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{pp-pc1}}
{{short description|Pseudoscientific attempts to change sexual orientation}}
{{LGBT rights sidebar}}
'''Conversion therapy''' is the [[pseudoscience|pseudoscientific]] practice of trying to change an individual's [[sexual orientation]] from [[homosexual]] or [[bisexual]] to [[heterosexual]] using psychological or spiritual interventions. There is no reliable evidence that sexual orientation can be changed and medical bodies warn that conversion therapy practices are ineffective and potentially harmful.&lt;ref name="DrescherandZucker"&gt;{{Harvnb|Drescher|Zucker|2006|pp=126, 175}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Ford|2001}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Cruz" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Yoshino" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Haldeman|1991|p=149}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="YouthCrosshairs"&gt;{{Cite web |last1=Cianciotto |first1=Jason |last2=Cahill |first2=Sean |title=Youth in the Crosshairs: the Third Wave of Ex-gay Activism |date=2006 |url=http://www.thetaskforce.org/downloads/reports/reports/YouthInTheCrosshairs.pdf |website=[[National LGBTQ Task Force]] |publisher=National LGBTQ Task Force Policy Institute |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070605183318/http://www.thetaskforce.org/downloads/reports/reports/YouthInTheCrosshairs.pdf |archive-date=June 5, 2007 |url-status=dead |access-date=January 14, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Haldeman1"&gt;{{cite journal|url = http://drdoughaldeman.com/doc/Pseudo-Science.pdf|title = The Pseudo-science of Sexual Orientation Conversion Therapy|volume = 4|issue = 1|journal = Angles: The Policy Journal of the Institute for Gay and Lesbian Strategic Studies|date = December 1999|accessdate = March 16, 2018|last = Haldeman|first = Douglas C.|pages = 1–4}}&lt;/ref&gt; Medical, scientific, and government organizations in the United States and United Kingdom have expressed concern over the validity, efficacy and ethics of conversion therapy.&lt;ref name="Psych"&gt;{{cite web|title=Position Statement on Therapies Focused on Attempts to Change Sexual Orientation (Reparative or Conversion Therapies)|url=http://www.psych.org/Departments/EDU/Library/APAOfficialDocumentsandRelated/PositionStatements/200001.aspx|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110110120228/http://www.psych.org/Departments/EDU/Library/APAOfficialDocumentsandRelated/PositionStatements/200001.aspx |archive-date=January 10, 2011|accessdate=August 28, 2007|date=May 2000|author=American Psychiatric Association|publisher=[[American Psychiatric Association]]|quote=In December of 1998, the Board of Trustees issued a position statement that the American Psychiatric Association opposes any psychiatric treatment, such as "reparative" or conversion therapy, which is based upon the assumption that homosexuality per se is a mental disorder or based upon the a priori assumption that a patient should change his/her sexual homosexual orientation. ... The validity, efficacy and ethics of clinical attempts to change an individual's sexual orientation have been challenged. To date, there are no scientifically rigorous outcome studies to determine either the actual efficacy or harm of "reparative" treatments. (references omitted)|author-link=American Psychiatric Association}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="APA" /&gt;&lt;ref name="NewAPA"&gt;{{citation |url=http://www.apa.org/pi/lgbt/resources/therapeutic-response.pdf |title=Report of the American Psychological Association Task Force on Appropriate Therapeutic Responses to Sexual Orientation |accessdate=2009-09-24 |first=JM |last=Glassgold |publisher=[[American Psychological Association]] |date=2009-08-01 |display-authors=etal}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Memorandum"&gt;{{citation|url=http://www.psychotherapy.org.uk/UKCP_Documents/policy/MoU-conversiontherapy.pdf|title=Memorandum of Understanding on Conversion Therapy in the UK|accessdate=2015-01-19|date=January 2015|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150123004221/http://www.psychotherapy.org.uk/UKCP_Documents/policy/MoU-conversiontherapy.pdf|archivedate=2015-01-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="GMC"&gt;{{citation|url=http://www.gmc-uk.org/news/26043.asp|title=General Medical Council supports Memorandum on conversion therapy in the UK|accessdate=2015-01-19|date=January 2015|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170923011704/http://www.gmc-uk.org/news/26043.asp|archive-date=2017-09-23|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="PSA"&gt;{{citation|url=http://www.professionalstandards.org.uk/footer-pages/news-and-media/latest-news/news-article?id=db1f5a9e-2ce2-6f4b-9ceb-ff0000b2236b |archive-url=http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20150505175118/http://www.professionalstandards.org.uk/footer-pages/news-and-media/latest-news/news-article?id=db1f5a9e-2ce2-6f4b-9ceb-ff0000b2236b |url-status=dead |archive-date=2015-05-05 |title=Professional Standards Authority supports action by Accredited Registers on Conversion Therapy |accessdate=2015-01-19 |date=January 2015 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Various jurisdictions around the world have passed laws against conversion therapy.

The [[American Psychiatric Association]] (APA) opposes psychiatric treatment "based upon the assumption that [[homosexuality]] ''per se'' is a mental disorder or based upon the ''[[A priori and a posteriori|a priori]]'' assumption that a patient should change his/her sexual homosexual orientation"&lt;ref name="Psych" /&gt; and describes attempts to change sexual orientation by practitioners as [[Medical ethics|unethical]].&lt;ref name="YouthCrosshairs" /&gt; It also states that debates over the [[Social integration|integration]] of gay and lesbian people have obscured science "by calling into question the motives and even the character of individuals on both sides of the issue"&lt;ref name="Psych" /&gt; and that the advancement of conversion therapy may cause social harm by disseminating unscientific views about sexual orientation.&lt;ref name="APA"/&gt; In 2001, [[Surgeon General of the United States|United States Surgeon General]] [[David Satcher]] issued a report stating that "there is no valid scientific evidence that sexual orientation can be changed".&lt;ref name="SurgeonGeneral"&gt;{{citation |url=http://www.surgeongeneral.gov/library/sexualhealth/call.htm#III |title="The Surgeon General's call to Action to Promote Sexual Health and Responsible Sexual Behavior", A Letter from the Surgeon General U.S. Department of Health and Human Services |accessdate=2007-03-29 |publisher=U. S. Department of Health and Human Services |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070220184835/http://www.surgeongeneral.gov/library/sexualhealth/call.htm#III |archivedate=2007-02-20 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The highest-profile advocates of conversion therapy today tend to be [[Christian fundamentalism|fundamentalist Christian]] groups and other organizations which use a religious justification for the therapy rather than speaking of homosexuality as "a disease".&lt;ref name="Yoshino"&gt;{{Harvnb|Yoshino|2002}}&lt;/ref&gt; The main organization advocating conversion therapy is the [[National Association for Research &amp; Therapy of Homosexuality]] (NARTH), which, although notionally secular, often partners with religious groups.&lt;ref name="Yoshino" /&gt;

Techniques used in conversion therapy in the United States and Western Europe have included ice-pick [[Lobotomy|lobotomies]];&lt;ref name=Cruz&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Cruz|first1=David B.|title=Controlling Desires: Sexual Orientation Conversion and the Limits of Knowledge and Law|journal=Southern California Law Review|date=1999|volume=72|page=1297|url=http://www-bcf.usc.edu/~usclrev/pdf/072502.pdf|accessdate=25 November 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170919071205/http://www-bcf.usc.edu/~usclrev/pdf/072502.pdf|archive-date=19 September 2017|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Yoshino /&gt;&lt;ref name="Homosexuality and Biology"&gt;{{cite news|last1=Burr|first1=Chandler|title=Homosexuality and Biology|url=https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/1997/06/homosexuality-and-biology/304683/|accessdate=25 November 2016|publisher=The Atlantic Magazine|date=June 1997}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Internet Movie Database"&gt;{{cite web|last1=Harrison|first1=James|title=Changing Our Minds: The Story of Dr. Evelyn Hooker|url=https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0103938/combined|website=imdb|publisher=Internet Movie Database|accessdate=25 November 2016|format=Documentary Film}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Rieber|first1=Inge|last2=Sigusch|first2=Volkmar|title=Psychosurgery on Sex Offenders and Sexual "Deviants" in West Germany|journal=Archives of Sexual Behavior|date=1979|volume=8|issue=6|pages=523–527|doi=10.1007/bf01541419}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Dieckmann|first1=G.|last2=Horn|first2=H.J. |last3=Schneider|first3=H. |editor1-first=E.R.|editor1-last=Hitchcock|editor2-first=H.T.|editor2-last=Ballantine|editor3-first=B.A.|editor3-last=Meyerson|title=Long-term Results of Anterior Hypothalamotomy in Sexual Offences|journal=Modern Concepts in Psychiatric Surgery|date=1979|pages=187–195}}&lt;/ref&gt; chemical castration with hormonal treatment;&lt;ref name="APA-myth"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Milar|first1=Katherine S.|title=The myth buster|journal=Monitor on Psychology|date=February 2011|volume=42|issue=2|page=24|url=http://www.apa.org/monitor/2011/02/myth-buster.aspx|accessdate=25 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Aversion therapy|aversive treatments]], such as "the application of electric shock to the hands and/or genitals"; "nausea-inducing drugs ... administered simultaneously with the presentation of homoerotic stimuli"; and [[masturbation|masturbatory]] reconditioning. More recent clinical techniques used in the United States have been limited to counseling, visualization, social skills training, [[Psychoanalysis|psychoanalytic therapy]], and spiritual interventions such as "prayer and group support and pressure",&lt;ref name="haldeman2"&gt;{{Citation|last=Haldeman|first=Douglas C.|title=Gay Rights, Patient Rights: The Implications of Sexual Orientation Conversion Therapy|date=June 2002|postscript=.|journal=Professional Psychology: Research and Practice|volume=33 |issue=3|pages=260–264| doi=10.1037/0735-7028.33.3.260|url=http://www.drdoughaldeman.com/doc/GayRightsPatientRights.pdf|citeseerx=10.1.1.506.1394}}&lt;/ref&gt; though there are some reports of aversive treatments through unlicensed practice as late as the early 2000s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Wareham|first1=Hannah Clay|title=Survivor: MIT grad student Samuel Brinton remembers 'ex-gay' therapy|url=http://www.lgbtqnation.com/2011/08/survivor-mit-grad-student-samuel-brinton-remembers-ex-gay-therapy/|website=lgbtqnation.com|accessdate=6 May 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name =Lyn_Duff /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Brinton|first1=Sam|title=I Was Tortured in Gay Conversion Therapy. And It’s Still Legal in 41 States.|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2018/01/24/opinion/gay-conversion-therapy-torture.html|accessdate=18 November 2019}} {{Subscription required}}&lt;/ref&gt; The term '''reparative therapy''' has been used as a synonym for conversion therapy in general,&lt;ref name="Psych" /&gt; but it has been argued that strictly speaking it refers to a specific kind of therapy associated with the psychologists [[Elizabeth Moberly]] and [[Joseph Nicolosi]].&lt;ref name="Drescher1998" /&gt;
{{TOC limit|3}}

==History==

The history of conversion therapy can be divided broadly into three periods: an early Freudian period; a period of mainstream approval of conversion therapy, when the mental health establishment became the "primary superintendent" of sexuality; and a post-[[Stonewall riots|Stonewall]] period where the mainstream medical profession disavowed conversion therapy.&lt;ref name="Yoshino" /&gt;

During the earliest parts of psychoanalytic history, analysts granted that homosexuality was non-pathological in certain cases, and the ethical question of whether it ought to be changed was discussed. By the 1920s analysts assumed that homosexuality was pathological and that attempts to treat it were appropriate, although psychoanalytic opinion about changing homosexuality was largely pessimistic. Those forms of homosexuality that were considered perversions were usually held to be incurable. Analysts' tolerant statements about homosexuality arose from recognition of the difficulty of achieving change. Beginning in the 1930s and continuing for roughly twenty years, major changes occurred in how analysts viewed homosexuality, which involved a shift in the rhetoric of analysts, some of whom felt free to ridicule and abuse their gay patients.&lt;ref name="Lewes"&gt;{{Harvnb|Lewes|1988}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Europe===

====Sigmund Freud====
{{Main|Sigmund Freud's views on homosexuality}}
[[Image:Sigmund Freud, by Max Halberstadt (cropped).jpg|thumb|upright|Freud (1856–1939) was skeptical of the possibility of therapeutic conversion.]]

[[Sigmund Freud]] was a physician and the founder of psychoanalysis. Freud stated that homosexuality could sometimes be removed through hypnotic suggestion,&lt;ref name="SigmundFreudOnSexuality"&gt;{{Harvnb|Freud|1991|p=51}}&lt;/ref&gt; and was influenced by [[Eugen Steinach]], a [[Vienna|Viennese]] endocrinologist who transplanted [[testicle]]s from straight men into gay men in attempts to change their sexual orientation,&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|LeVay|1996|p=74,109}}&lt;/ref&gt; stating that his research had "thrown a strong light on the organic determinants of homo-eroticism".&lt;ref name="SigmundFreudOnSexualityP58"&gt;{{Harvnb|Freud|1991|p=58}}&lt;/ref&gt; Freud cautioned that Steinach's operations would not necessarily make possible a therapy that could be generally applied, arguing that such transplant procedures would be effective in changing homosexuality in men only in cases in which it was strongly associated with physical characteristics typical of women, and that probably no similar therapy could be applied to lesbianism.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Freud|1991|pp=58–59}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Freud|1991|p=400}}&lt;/ref&gt; Steinach's method was doomed to failure because the [[immune system]] rejects transplanted glands, and was eventually exposed as ineffective and often harmful.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|LeVay|1996|pp=32–33}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Freud's main discussion of female homosexuality was the 1920 paper "The Psychogenesis of a Case of Homosexuality in a Woman", which described his analysis of a young woman who had entered therapy because her parents were concerned that she was a [[lesbian]]. Her father wanted this condition changed. In Freud's view, the prognosis was unfavourable because of the circumstances under which she entered therapy, and because homosexuality was not an illness or neurotic conflict. Freud wrote that changing homosexuality was difficult and possible only under unusually favourable conditions, observing that "in general to undertake to convert a fully developed homosexual into a heterosexual does not offer much more prospect of success than the reverse".&lt;ref name="SigmundFreudCaseHistoriesIIP376"&gt;{{Harvnb|Freud|1991|p=376}}&lt;/ref&gt; Success meant making heterosexual feeling possible, not eliminating homosexual feelings.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Freud|1991|p=375}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Gay people could seldom be convinced that heterosexual sex would provide them with the same pleasure they derived from homosexual sex. Patients often wanted to become heterosexual for reasons Freud considered superficial, including fear of social disapproval, an insufficient motive for change. Some might have no real desire to become heterosexual, seeking treatment only to convince themselves that they had done everything possible to change, leaving them free to return to homosexuality after the failure they expected.&lt;ref name="OconnorandRyan"&gt;{{Harvnb|O'Connor|Ryan|1993|pp=30–47}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="SigmundFreudCaseHistoriesII"&gt;{{Harvnb|Freud|1991|pp=371–400}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="LewesP34"&gt;{{Harvnb|Lewes|1988|p=34}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1935, a mother asked Freud to treat her son. Freud replied in a letter that later became famous:&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Lewes|1988|p=32}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|I gather from your letter that your son is a homosexual. ... it is nothing to be ashamed of, no vice, no degradation; it cannot be classified as an illness; we consider it to be a variation of the sexual function, produced by a certain arrest of sexual development. ... By asking me if I can help [your son], you mean, I suppose, if I can abolish homosexuality and make normal heterosexuality take its place. The answer is, in a general way we cannot promise to achieve it. In a certain number of cases we succeed in developing the blighted germs of heterosexual tendencies, which are present in every homosexual; in the majority of cases it is no more possible. It is a question of the quality and the age of the individual. The result of treatment cannot be predicted.&lt;ref name="ErnstLFreud"&gt;{{Harvnb|Freud|1992|pp=423–424}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

====Sándor Ferenczi====
[[Sándor Ferenczi]] was an influential psychoanalyst. Ferenczi hoped to cure some kinds of homosexuality completely, but was content in practice with reducing what he considered gay men's hostility to women, along with the urgency of their homosexual desires, and with helping them to become attracted to and potent with women. In his view, a gay man who was confused about his sexual identity and felt himself to be "a woman with the wish to be loved by a man" was not a promising candidate for cure. Ferenczi believed that complete cures of homosexuality might become possible in the future when psychoanalytic technique had been improved.&lt;ref name="Lewes" /&gt;&lt;ref name="ErnestJonesVol2"&gt;{{Harvnb|Jones|1955|p=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="MartinStanton"&gt;{{Harvnb|Stanton|1991|p=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Anna Freud====
Daughter of Sigmund Freud, Anna Freud became an influential psychoanalytic theorist in the UK.&lt;ref name="Young-Bruehl" /&gt;

[[Anna Freud]] reported the successful treatment of homosexuals as neurotics in a series of unpublished lectures. In 1949 she published "Some Clinical Remarks Concerning the Treatment of Cases of Male Homosexuality" in the ''[[International Journal of Psychoanalysis]]''. In her view, it was important to pay attention to the interaction of passive and active homosexual fantasies and strivings, the original interplay of which prevented adequate identification with the father. The patient should be told that his choice of a passive partner allows him to enjoy a passive or receptive mode, while his choice of an active partner allows him to recapture his lost masculinity. She claimed that these interpretations would reactivate repressed [[castration complex|castration anxieties]], and childhood narcissistic grandiosity and its complementary fear of dissolving into nothing during heterosexual intercourse would come with the renewal of heterosexual potency.&lt;ref name="Lewes" /&gt;

Anna Freud in 1951 published "Clinical Observations on the Treatment of Male Homosexuality" in ''[[The Psychoanalytic Quarterly]]'' and "Homosexuality" in the ''[[American Psychoanalytic Association]] (APsaA) Bulletin''. In these articles, she insisted on the attainment of full object-love of the opposite sex as a requirement for cure of homosexuality. In 1951 she gave a lecture about treatment of homosexuality which was criticised by [[Edmund Bergler]], who emphasised the oral fears of patients and minimized the importance of the phallic castration fears she had discussed.&lt;ref name="Lewes" /&gt;

Anna Freud recommended in 1956 to a journalist who was preparing an article about psychoanalysis for ''[[The Observer]]'' of London that she not quote Freud's letter to the American mother, on the grounds that "nowadays we can cure many more homosexuals than was thought possible in the beginning. The other reason is that readers may take this as a confirmation that all analysis can do is to convince patients that their defects or 'immoralities' do not matter and that they should be happy with them. That would be unfortunate."&lt;ref name="Young-Bruehl"&gt;{{Harvnb|Young-Bruehl|1988|p=327}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Melanie Klein====
[[Melanie Klein]] was a pupil of Ferenczi. Her seminal book ''The Psycho-Analysis of Children'', based on lectures given to the [[British Psychoanalytical Society]] in the 1920s, was published in 1932. Klein claimed that entry into the [[Oedipus Complex]] is based on mastery of primitive anxiety from the oral and anal stages. If these tasks are not performed properly, developments in the Oedipal stage will be unstable. Complete analysis of patients with such unstable developments would require uncovering these early concerns. The analysis of homosexuality required dealing with paranoid trends based on the oral stage. ''The Psycho-Analysis of Children'' ends with the analysis of Mr. B., a gay man. Klein claimed that he illustrated pathologies that enter into all forms of homosexuality: a gay man idealizes "the good penis" of his partner to allay the fear of attack he feels due to having projected his paranoid hatred onto the imagined "bad penis" of his mother as an infant. She stated that Mr. B.'s homosexual behaviour diminished after he overcame his need to adore the "good penis" of an idealized man. This was made possible by his recovering his belief in the good mother and his ability to sexually gratify her with his good penis and plentiful [[semen]].&lt;ref name="Lewes" /&gt;

==== Vote by European parliament in March 2018 ====
In March 2018, a majority of 435 against 109 representatives in the [[European Parliament|European parliament]] passed a resolution condemning conversion therapy and urging [[European Union]] member states to ban the practice.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.queer.de/detail.php?article_id=30751|title=EU-Parlament stärkt LGBTI-Grundrechte|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://schwulissimo.de/politik/245183/EuropaeischesParlamentverurteiltdieHeilungvonHomosexuellen.htm|title=Schwulissimo - Europäisches Parlament verurteilt die "Heilung" von Homosexuellen|website=schwulissimo.de|access-date=2018-03-02|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180303050904/http://schwulissimo.de/politik/245183/EuropaeischesParlamentverurteiltdieHeilungvonHomosexuellen.htm|archive-date=2018-03-03|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.pinknews.co.uk/2018/03/01/european-parliament-condemns-gay-cure-therapy-and-tells-eu-member-states-to-ban-it/|title=European Parliament condemns gay 'cure' therapy and tells EU member states to ban it|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===United States===

====20th century====
Psychoanalysis started to receive recognition in the United States in 1909, when Sigmund Freud delivered a series of lectures at [[Clark University]] in [[Massachusetts]] at the invitation of [[G. Stanley Hall]].&lt;ref name="PGay1998"&gt;{{Harvnb|Gay|2006|p=}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1913, [[Abraham Brill]] wrote "The Conception of Homosexuality", which he published in the ''[[JAMA (journal)|Journal of the American Medical Association]]'' and read before the [[American Medical Association]]'s annual meeting. Brill criticised physical treatments for homosexuality such as bladder washing, [[rectum|rectal]] massage, and castration, along with [[hypnosis]], but referred approvingly to Freud and Sadger's use of psychoanalysis, calling its results "very gratifying".&lt;ref name=KatzP149&gt;{{Harvnb|Katz|1976|p=149}}&lt;/ref&gt; Since Brill understood curing homosexuality as restoring heterosexual potency, he claimed that he had cured his patients in several cases, even though many remained homosexual.&lt;ref name="Lewes" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Katz"&gt;{{Harvnb|Katz|1976}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Wilhelm Stekel]], an Austrian, published his views on treatment of homosexuality, which he considered a disease, in the American ''[[National Psychological Association for Psychoanalysis#Current ideology|Psychoanalytic Review]]'' in 1930. Stekel believed that "success was fairly certain" in changing homosexuality through psychoanalysis provided that it was performed correctly and the patient wanted to be treated. In 1932, ''The Psychoanalytic Quarterly'' published a translation of [[Helene Deutsch]]'s paper "On Female Homosexuality". Deutsch reported her analysis of a lesbian, who did not become heterosexual as a result of treatment, but who managed to achieve a "positive libidinal relationship" with another woman. Deutsch indicated that she would have considered heterosexuality a better outcome.&lt;ref name="Katz" /&gt;

[[Edmund Bergler]] was the most important psychoanalytic theorist of homosexuality in the 1950s.&lt;ref name="Lewes" /&gt; He was vociferous in his opposition to [[Alfred Kinsey]]. Kinsey's work, and its reception, led Bergler to develop his own theories for treatment, which were essentially to "[[blame the victim]]", in the evaluation of Jennifer Terry, associate professor of Woman's Studies.&lt;ref name="Terry"/&gt; Bergler claimed that if gay people wanted to change, and the right therapeutic approach was taken, then they could be cured in 90% of cases.&lt;ref name="BerglerTime"&gt;{{Harvnb|Bergler|1956}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bergler used confrontational therapy in which gay people were punished in order to make them aware of their masochism. Bergler openly violated professional ethics to achieve this, breaking patient confidentiality in discussing the cases of patients with other patients, bullying them, calling them liars and telling them they were worthless.&lt;ref name="Terry"&gt;{{Harvnb|Terry|1999|pp=308–314}}&lt;/ref&gt; He insisted that gay people could be cured. Bergler confronted Kinsey because Kinsey thwarted the possibility of cure by presenting homosexuality as an acceptable way of life, which was the basis of the gay rights activism of the time.&lt;ref name="Terry"/&gt; Bergler popularised his views in the United States in the 1950s using magazine articles and books aimed at non-specialists.&lt;ref name="Terry" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Bergler"&gt;{{Harvnb|Bergler|1962}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1951, the mother who wrote to Freud asking him to treat her son sent Freud's response to the ''American Journal of Psychiatry'', in which it was published.&lt;ref name="Lewes" /&gt; The 1952 first edition of the American Psychiatric Association's [[Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders]] (DSM-I) classified homosexuality as a mental disorder.&lt;ref name="RonaldBayer" /&gt;

During the three decades between Freud's death in 1939 and the [[Stonewall riots]] in 1969, conversion therapy received approval from most of the psychiatric establishment in the United States.&lt;ref name="Drescher"&gt;{{Harvnb|Drescher|1998|pp=19–42}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1962, [[Irving Bieber]] ''et al.'' published ''[[Homosexuality: A Psychoanalytic Study of Male Homosexuals]]'', in which they concluded that "although this change may be more easily accomplished by some than by others, in our judgment a heterosexual shift is a possibility for all homosexuals who are strongly motivated to change".&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Bieber|1962|p=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There was a [[Stonewall riots|riot]] in 1969 at the Stonewall Bar in New York after a police raid. The Stonewall riot acquired symbolic significance for the gay rights movement and came to be seen as the opening of a new phase in the struggle for gay liberation. Following these events, conversion therapy came under increasing attack. Activism against conversion therapy increasingly focused on the DSM's designation of homosexuality as a psychopathology.&lt;ref name="RonaldBayer" /&gt; In 1973, after years of criticism from gay activists and bitter dispute among psychiatrists, the American Psychiatric Association removed homosexuality as a mental disorder from the ''Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders''. Supporters of the change used evidence from researchers such as Kinsey and [[Evelyn Hooker]]. Psychiatrist Robert Spitzer, a member of the APA's Committee on Nomenclature, played an important role in the events that led to this decision. Critics argued that it was a result of pressure from gay activists, and demanded a referendum among voting members of the Association. The referendum was held in 1974 and the APA's decision was upheld by a 58% majority.&lt;ref name="RonaldBayer"&gt;{{Harvnb|Bayer|1987|p=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The APA removed [[Ego-dystonic sexual orientation|ego-dystonic homosexuality]] from the DSM-III-R in 1987 and opposes the diagnosis of either homosexuality or ego-dystonic homosexuality as any type of disorder.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |url=http://www.apa.org/pi/lgbc/policy/diagnoses.html |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070929104523/http://www.apa.org/pi/lgbc/policy/diagnoses.html |archivedate=2007-09-29 |title=APA Policy Statement: Use of Diagnoses "Homosexuality" &amp; "Ego-Dystonic Homosexuality" |accessdate=2007-08-28 |author=APA Council of Representatives |date=1987-08-30 |publisher=American Psychological Association}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Joseph Nicolosi]] had a significant role in the development of conversion therapy as early as the 1990s, publishing his first book ''[[Reparative Therapy of Male Homosexuality]]'' in 1991.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|url=http://lgbtphysicists.org/files/GLAAD_MediaRefGuide_7thEdition.pdf|title=GLAAD Media Reference Guide, 7th Edition |author=Gay &amp; Lesbian Alliance Against Defamation (GLAAD)|date=September 2006|access-date=25 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Nicolosi"&gt;{{cite book|last1=Nicolosi|first1=Joseph|title=Reparative Therapy of Male Homosexuality: A New Clinical Approach|date=1997|publisher=Jason Aronson|isbn=9780765701428}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1992, Nicolosi, with [[Charles Socarides]] and Benjamin Kaufman, founded the [[National Association for Research &amp; Therapy of Homosexuality]] (NARTH), an organization that opposes the mainstream medical view of homosexuality and aims to "make effective psychological therapy available to all homosexual men and women who seek change".&lt;ref name="NARTH"&gt;{{citation |url=http://narth.com/menus/goals.html |title=NARTH What We Offer |accessdate=2009-05-25 |publisher=NARTH |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090413091827/http://narth.com/menus/goals.html |archivedate=2009-04-13 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1998, [[Christian right]] groups including the [[Family Research Council]] and the [[American Family Association]] spent $600,000 on advertising promoting conversion therapy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2015/04/how-christians-turned-against-gay-conversion-therapy/390570/|title=How Christians Turned Against Gay Conversion Therapy|first=Jonathan |last=Merritt |date=15 Apr 2015 |accessdate=29 November 2016 |work=[[The Atlantic]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[John Paulk]] and his then wife Anne featured in full-page newspaper spreads.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.newsweek.com/ex-ex-gay-pride-249282 |title=Ex-Ex-Gay Pride | first1=Zoë |last1=Schlanger |first2=Elijah |last2=Wolfson |work=[[Newsweek]] |date=1 May 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====21st century====

[[Surgeon General of the United States|United States Surgeon General]] [[David Satcher]] in 2001 issued a report stating that "there is no valid scientific evidence that sexual orientation can be changed".&lt;ref name="SurgeonGeneral"/&gt; The same year, a study by [[Robert Spitzer (psychiatrist)|Robert Spitzer]] concluded that some highly motivated individuals whose orientation is predominantly homosexual can become predominantly heterosexual with some form of reparative therapy.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |title=Can Some Gay Men and Lesbians Change Their Sexual Orientation? |volume = 32 |issue = 5 |year = 2001|doi=10.1023/A:1025647527010 |pmid=14567650 |journal=Arch Sex Behav |pages=403–17; discussion 419–72 | last1 = Spitzer | first1 = RL}}&lt;/ref&gt; Spitzer based his findings on structured interviews with 200 self-selected individuals (143 males, 57 females). He told ''[[The Washington Post]]'' that the study "shows some people can change from gay to straight, and we ought to acknowledge that".&lt;ref name="Ritter"&gt;{{cite news|title= Study: Some Gays Can Go Straight| url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-srv/aponline/20010509/aponline013921_000.htm |first=Malcolm |last=Ritter |work=[[The Washington Post]] |date = 9 May 2001 |accessdate=29 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Spitzer's study caused controversy and attracted media attention.&lt;ref name="DrescherandZucker" /&gt; Spitzer recanted his study in 2012,&lt;ref name=spitzer1 /&gt; and apologized to the gay community for making unproven claims of the efficacy of reparative therapy,&lt;ref name=spitzer3 /&gt; calling it his only professional regret.&lt;ref name=spitzer4 /&gt;

The American Psychoanalytic Association spoke against NARTH in 2004, stating "that organization does not adhere to our policy of nondiscrimination and ... their activities are demeaning to our members who are gay and lesbian".&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |last=Crow |first=C. |date=2004-11-20 |title=Irate reader's expert on gays has drawn fire from his peers |publisher=[[San Antonio Express-News]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; The same year, a survey of members of the [[American Psychological Association]] rated reparative therapy as "certainly discredited", though the authors warn that the results should be interpreted carefully as an initial step, not a final word.&lt;ref name="NorcrossKoocherandGarofalo"&gt;{{Harvnb|Norcross|Koocher|Garofalo|2006|pp=512–522}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The American Psychological Association in 2007 convened a task force to evaluate its policies regarding reparative therapy.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |url=http://www.washingtontimes.com/news/2007/jul/11/gay-reparative-therapy-under-scrutiny/ |title=Gay reparative therapy under scrutiny |publisher=Washington Times |location=New York |date=July 11, 2007 |accessdate=2009-02-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2008, the organizers of an APA panel on the relationship between religion and homosexuality canceled the event after gay activists objected that "conversion therapists and their supporters on the religious right use these appearances as a public relations event to try and legitimize what they do".&lt;ref name="Plowman"&gt;{{Harvnb|Plowman|2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Johnson"&gt;{{Harvnb|Johnson|2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2009, American Psychological Association stated that it "encourages mental health professionals to avoid misrepresenting the efficacy of sexual orientation change efforts by promoting or promising change in sexual orientation when providing assistance to individuals distressed by their own or others' sexual orientation and concludes that the benefits reported by participants in sexual orientation change efforts can be gained through approaches that do not attempt to change sexual orientation".&lt;ref name=Apa2009&gt;American Psychological Association: [http://www.apa.org/about/policy/sexual-orientation.aspx Resolution on Appropriate Affirmative Responses to Sexual Orientation Distress and Change Efforts]&lt;/ref&gt;

The ethics guidelines of major mental health organizations in the United States vary from cautionary statements to recommendations that ethical practitioners refrain from practicing conversion therapy (American Psychiatric Association) or from referring patients to those who do ([[American Counseling Association]]).&lt;ref name="Psych" /&gt;&lt;ref name="ACA News" /&gt; In a letter dated February 23, 2011 to the Speaker of the U.S. House of Representatives, the Attorney General of the United States stated "while sexual orientation carries no visible badge, a growing scientific consensus accepts that sexual orientation is a characteristic that is immutable".&lt;ref name="DOMA2011"&gt;[http://www.justice.gov/opa/pr/2011/February/11-ag-223.html Letter from the Attorney General of the United States to the Speaker of the U.S. House of Representatives, RE: DOMA, 23rd February 2011]. "Second, while sexual orientation carries no visible badge, a growing scientific consensus accepts that sexual orientation is a characteristic that is immutable."&lt;/ref&gt;

Gay rights groups and groups concerned with mental health fear reparative therapy can make depression and suicide more likely. President [[Barack Obama]] expressed opposition to the practice in 2015.&lt;ref name="BBC-4-2015"&gt;{{cite news|title=Obama calls for end to 'gay conversion therapies' |url=https://www.bbc.com/news/world-us-canada-32227353 |author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt; |work=[[BBC News]] |date=9 April 2015 |accessdate=29 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Theories and techniques==
{{Wikinews|Dr. Joseph Merlino on sexuality, insanity, Freud, fetishes and apathy}}

===Behavioral modification===
{{Main|Behavior modification}}

Before the American Psychological Association's 1973 decision to remove homosexuality from the [[Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders|DSM]], practitioners of conversion therapy employed [[Aversion therapy|aversive conditioning techniques]], involving electric shock and nausea-inducing drugs during presentation of same-sex erotic images. Cessation of the aversive stimuli was typically accompanied by the presentation of opposite-sex erotic images, with the objective of strengthening heterosexual feelings. In "Aversion therapy for sexual deviation: a critical review", published in 1966, M. P. Feldman claimed a 58% cure rate, but [[Douglas Haldeman]] is skeptical that such stressful methods permit feelings of sexual responsiveness, and notes that Feldman defined success as suppression of homosexuality and increased capacity for heterosexual behavior.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Haldeman|1991|p=152}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Another method used was the covert sensitization method, which involves instructing patients to imagine vomiting or receiving electric shocks, writing that only single case studies have been conducted, and that their results cannot be generalized. Haldeman writes that behavioral conditioning studies tend to decrease homosexual feelings, but do not increase heterosexual feelings, citing Rangaswami's "Difficulties in arousing and increasing heterosexual responsiveness in a homosexual: A case report", published in 1982, as typical in this respect.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Haldeman|1991|pp=152–153}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Haldeman concludes that such methods can be called [[torture]], besides being ineffective. He writes that "Individuals undergoing such treatments do not emerge heterosexually inclined; rather they become shamed, conflicted, and fearful about their homosexual feelings."&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Haldeman|1991|p=153}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Ex-gay ministry===
[[Image:One by One booth.jpg|thumb|right|[[OneByOne]] booth at a [[Love Won Out]] conference]]
{{Main|Ex-gay}}

Some sources describe ex-gay ministries as a form of conversion therapy, while others state that ex-gay organizations and conversion therapy are distinct methods of attempting to convert gay people to heterosexuality.&lt;ref name="DrescherandZucker" /&gt;&lt;ref name="APA"&gt;{{citation |url=http://www.apa.org/pi/lgbt/resources/just-the-facts.pdf |title=Just the Facts About Sexual Orientation &amp; Youth: A Primer for Principals, Educators and School Personnel |accessdate=2010-05-14 |year=1999 |publisher=Just the Facts Coalition}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Haldeman|1991|pp=149,156–159}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="JonesandYarhouse"&gt;{{Harvnb|Jones|Yarhouse|2007|p=374}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ex-gay ministries have also been called transformational ministries.&lt;ref name="APA"/&gt; Some state that they do not conduct clinical treatment of any kind.&lt;ref name=ExodusStatement /&gt; [[Exodus International]] once believed reparative therapy could be a beneficial tool.&lt;ref name=ExodusStatement&gt;{{citation |url=http://exodus.to/content/view/34/117/ |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070928010931/http://exodus.to/content/view/34/117/ |archivedate=2007-09-28 |title=Exodus International Policy Statements |accessdate=2007-08-28 |publisher=Exodus International}}&lt;/ref&gt; The umbrella organization in the United States ceased activities in June 2013, and the three member board issued a statement which repudiated its aims and apologized for the harm their pursuit has caused to [[LGBT]] people.&lt;ref name=Change&gt;{{citation |url=http://exodusinternational.org/2013/06/i-am-sorry |first=Alan |last=Chambers |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130623013409/http://exodusinternational.org/2013/06/i-am-sorry |archivedate=2013-06-23 |title=I Am Sorry |accessdate=2013-06-22 |publisher=Exodus International}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ministries that had been members formed a new organization, [[Restored Hope Network]], and continue to operate as before with a renewed emphasis on spiritual conversion and therapy.{{citation needed|date=October 2017}}

===Psychoanalysis===
{{Main|Psychoanalysis}}

Haldeman writes that psychoanalytic treatment of homosexuality is exemplified by the work of Irving Bieber ''et al.'' in ''Homosexuality: A Psychoanalytic Study of Male Homosexuals''. They advocated long-term therapy aimed at resolving the unconscious childhood conflicts that they considered responsible for homosexuality. Haldeman notes that Bieber's methodology has been criticized because it relied upon a clinical sample, the description of the outcomes was based upon subjective therapist impression, and follow-up data were poorly presented. Bieber reported a 27% success rate from long-term therapy, but only 18% of the patients in whom Bieber considered the treatment successful had been exclusively homosexual to begin with, while 50% had been bisexual. In Haldeman's view, this makes even Bieber's unimpressive claims of success misleading.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Haldeman|1991|pp=150–151}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Haldeman discusses other psychoanalytic studies of attempts to change homosexuality. Curran and Parr's "Homosexuality: An analysis of 100 male cases", published in 1957, reported no significant increase in heterosexual behavior. Mayerson and Lief's "Psychotherapy of homosexuals: A follow-up study of nineteen cases", published in 1965, reported that half of its 19 subjects were exclusively heterosexual in behavior four and a half years after treatment, but its outcomes were based on patient self-report and had no external validation. In Haldeman's view, those participants in the study who reported change were bisexual at the outset, and its authors wrongly interpreted capacity for heterosexual sex as change of sexual orientation.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Haldeman|1991|pp=151, 256}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Reparative therapy===

The term "reparative therapy" has been used as a synonym for conversion therapy generally, but according to Jack Drescher it properly refers to a specific kind of therapy associated with the psychologists [[Elizabeth Moberly]] and [[Joseph Nicolosi]].&lt;ref name="Drescher1998" /&gt; The term ''reparative'' refers to Nicolosi's postulate that same-sex attraction is a person's unconscious attempt to "self-repair" feelings of inferiority.&lt;ref name=Hicks_1999&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Hicks|first1=Karolyn Ann|title="Reparative Therapy": Whether Parental Attempts to Change a Child's Sexual Orientation Can Legally Constitute Child Abuse|journal=American University Law Review|date=1999|volume=49|issue=2|pages=505–547|url=http://digitalcommons.wcl.american.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1288&amp;context=aulr|accessdate=28 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Nicolosi|first1=Joseph|title=What Is Reparative Therapy? Examining the Controversy|url=http://josephnicolosi.com/what-is-reparative-therapy-exa/|accessdate=28 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Bright"&gt;{{Harvnb|Bright|2004|pp=471–481}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Most mental health professionals and the [[American Psychological Association]] consider reparative therapy discredited, but it is still practiced by some.&lt;ref name="Yoshino" /&gt; In 2014 the Republican Party of Texas endorsed "counseling, which offers reparative therapy and treatment" in their party platform.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Report of Permanent Committee on Platform and Resolutions As Amended and Adopted by the 2014 State Convention of the Republican Party of Texas|url=http://www.texasgop.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/06/2014-Platform-Final.pdf#page=14|website=texasgop.org|publisher=Republican Party of Texas|accessdate=28 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Exodus International]] regarded reparative therapy as a useful tool to eliminate "unwanted same-sex attraction"&lt;ref name=ExodusStatement/&gt; but ceased activities in June 2013 and issued a statement repudiating its aims and apologizing for the harm the organization had caused to [[LGBT]] people.&lt;ref name=Change /&gt; Psychoanalysts critical of Nicolosi's theories have offered gay-affirmative approaches as an alternative to reparative therapy.&lt;ref name="Drescher1998"&gt;{{Harvnb|Drescher|1998|p=152}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="DomeniciandLesser"&gt;{{Harvnb|Domenici|Lesser|1995|p=119}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Sex therapy===
{{Main|Masters and Johnson}}

Haldeman has described [[Masters and Johnson|William Masters' and Virginia Johnson]]'s work on sexual orientation change as a form of conversion therapy.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Haldeman|1991|pp=149, 154}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In ''Homosexuality in Perspective'', published in 1979, Masters and Johnson viewed homosexuality as the result of blocks that prevented the learning that facilitated heterosexual responsiveness, and described a study of 54 gay men who were dissatisfied with their sexual orientation. The original study did not describe the treatment methodology used, but this was published five years later. John C. Gonsiorek criticized their study on several grounds in 1981, pointing out that while Masters and Johnson stated that their patients were screened for major psychopathology or severe neurosis, they did not explain how this screening was performed, or how the motivation of the patients to change was assessed. Nineteen of their subjects were described as uncooperative during therapy and refused to participate in a follow-up assessment, but all of them were assumed without justification to have successfully changed.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Haldeman|1991|p=154}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Haldeman writes that Masters and Johnson's study was founded upon heterosexist bias, and that it would be tremendously difficult to replicate. In his view, the distinction Masters and Johnson made between "conversion" (helping gay men with no previous heterosexual experience to learn heterosexual sex) and "reversion" (directing men with some previous heterosexual experience back to heterosexuality) was not well founded. Many of the subjects Masters and Johnson labelled homosexual may not have been homosexual, since, of their participants, only 17% identified themselves as exclusively homosexual, while 83% were in the predominantly heterosexual to bisexual range. Haldeman observed that since 30% of the sample was lost to the follow-up, it is possible that the outcome sample did not include any people attracted mainly or exclusively to the same sex. Haldeman concludes that it is likely that, rather than converting or reverting gay people to heterosexuality, Masters and Johnson only strengthened heterosexual responsiveness in people who were already bisexual.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Haldeman|1991|p=155}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Lobotomy===
{{main|Lobotomy}}

In the 1940s and 1950s, U.S. neurologist [[Walter Jackson Freeman II|Walter Freeman]] popularized the [[Lobotomy#Transorbital lobotomy|ice-pick lobotomy]] to treat homosexuality. He personally performed as many as 3,439&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=He was bad, so they put an ice pick in his brain|url=https://www.theguardian.com/science/2008/jan/13/neuroscience.medicalscience|author=Elizabeth Day|date=13 Jan 2008|website=www.theguardian.com|accessdate=26 December 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; lobotomy surgeries in 23 states, of which 2,500 used his ice-pick procedure,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Top 10 Fascinating And Notable Lobotomies|url=http://listverse.com/2009/06/24/top-10-fascinating-and-notable-lobotomies/|date=June 24, 2009|website=listverse.com|accessdate=26 December 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; despite the fact that he had no formal surgical training.&lt;ref name="rowland"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Rowland|first=Lewis|date=April 2005|title=Walter Freeman's Psychosurgery and Biological Psychiatry: A Cautionary Tale|url=http://journals.lww.com/neurotodayonline/Fulltext/2005/04000/Walter_Freeman_s_Psychosurgery_and_Biological.18.aspx|journal=Neurology Today|volume=5|issue=4|pages=70–72|doi=10.1097/00132985-200504000-00020|accessdate=July 9, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Up to 40% of Freeman's patients were gay individuals subjected to a lobotomy&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Stone|first1=Gene|title=The Tiger Cure|journal=New York Magazine|date=September 2013|url=http://nymag.com/news/features/sex-surrogate-2013-9/index1.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; in order to change their homosexual orientation, leaving most of these individuals severely disabled for the rest of their lives.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Scot|first1=Jamie|title=Shock the Gay Away: Secrets of Early Gay Aversion Therapy Revealed|url=https://www.huffingtonpost.com/jamie-scot/shock-the-gay-away-secrets-of-early-gay-aversion-therapy-revealed_b_3497435.html|work=Huffington Post|date=28 June 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; While promoted at the time as a treatment for various psychoses, the effectiveness of lobotomy in changing sexual orientation was already the subject of critical research in 1948 when a single case was investigated by Joseph Friedlander and Ralph Banay.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1= Friedlander |first1= Joseph W. |last2=Banay |first2=Ralph |title= Psychosis Following Lobotomy in a Case of Sexual Psychopathy |journal= Archives of Neurology &amp; Psychiatry |date= 1948 |volume= 59 |issue=3 |pages= 302–321 |doi= 10.1001/archneurpsyc.1948.02300380031003}}&lt;/ref&gt; A video depicting the "ice-pick lobotomy" of a homosexual man was featured in the documentary film, ''[[Changing Our Minds: The Story of Dr. Evelyn Hooker]]''.&lt;ref name=Yoshino /&gt;&lt;ref name="Homosexuality and Biology"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Internet Movie Database"/&gt;

==Studies of conversion therapy==

==="Can Some Gay Men and Lesbians Change Their Sexual Orientation?"===
In May 2001, [[Robert Spitzer (psychiatrist)|Robert Spitzer]] presented "Can Some Gay Men and Lesbians Change Their Sexual Orientation? 200 Participants Reporting a Change from Homosexual to Heterosexual Orientation", a study of attempts to change homosexual orientation through ex-gay ministries and conversion therapy, at the American Psychiatric Association's convention in New Orleans. The study was partly a response to the APA's 2000 statement cautioning against clinical attempts at changing homosexuality, and was aimed at determining whether such attempts were ever successful rather than how likely it was that change would occur for any given individual. Spitzer wrote that some earlier studies provided evidence for the effectiveness of therapy in changing sexual orientation, but that all of them suffered from methodological problems.&lt;ref name="DrescherandZucker" /&gt;

In 2012, Spitzer renounced&lt;ref name="Zimmerman"&gt;{{cite news | url= | title=Echoes of an intolerant past | date=May 30, 2012 | agency=Philadelphia Inquirer | author=Zimmerman, Jonathan | location=Philadelphia, PA | quote=prominent psychiatrist Robert Spitzer renounced his famous 2001 study claiming that some gays could become straight via so-called reparative therapy.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Besen"&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/wayne-besen/2012-many-celebrations-few-setbacks_b_2388887.html | title=2012: Many Celebrations, Few Setbacks | date=January 2, 2013 | agency=Huffington Post | accessdate=January 3, 2013 | author=Besen, Wayne | quote=Spitzer renounced his infamous 2001 study that said that some highly motivated homosexuals could change from gay to straight.}}&lt;/ref&gt; and retracted this study, stating "I was quite wrong in the conclusions that I made from this study. The study does not provide evidence, really, that gays can change. And that's quite an admission on my part."&lt;ref name="spitzer1"&gt;{{cite news| url=http://prospect.org/article/my-so-called-ex-gay-life| work=The American Prospect | title=My So-Called Ex-Gay Life| date=April 11, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Robert Spitzer, Psychiatrist Behind Retracted 'Ex-Gay' Study, Apologizes To Gay Community, Patients|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2012/04/25/robert-spitzer-ex-gay-psychiatrist-apology_n_1453570.html|accessdate=4 January 2013|newspaper=Huffington Post|date=April 25, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="spitzer_reassessed"&gt;{{Citation| author=Robert L. Spitzer | title=Spitzer Reassesses His 2003 Study of Reparative Therapy of Homosexuality | volume=41 | issue=4 | pages=757 | work=Arch Sex Behav | date=2012-05-24 | doi=10.1007/s10508-012-9966-y | pmid=22622659 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="spitzer2"&gt;{{cite web|last=Besen|first=Wayne|title=TWO Exclusive Video: Interview with Dr. Robert Spitzer Who Discusses Retracting His Infamous 'Ex-Gay' Study|url=http://www.truthwinsout.org/blog/2012/05/25725/|publisher=[[Truth Wins Out]]. truthwinsout.org|accessdate=30 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; He also apologized to the gay community for making unproven claims of the efficacy of reparative therapy,&lt;ref name="spitzer3"&gt;{{cite web|last=Becker|first=John M.|title=EXCLUSIVE: Dr. Robert Spitzer Apologizes to Gay Community for Infamous 'Ex-Gay' Study|url=http://www.truthwinsout.org/news/2012/04/24542/|publisher=truthwinsout.org|accessdate=May 26, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; calling it his only professional regret.&lt;ref name="spitzer4"&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2012/05/19/health/dr-robert-l-spitzer-noted-psychiatrist-apologizes-for-study-on-gay-cure.html|title=Psychiatry Giant Sorry for Backing Gay 'Cure'|last=Carey|first=Benedict|date=May 18, 2012|newspaper=nytimes.com|accessdate=May 26, 2012|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120525070851/http://www.nytimes.com/2012/05/19/health/dr-robert-l-spitzer-noted-psychiatrist-apologizes-for-study-on-gay-cure.html|archive-date=May 25, 2012|url-status=bot: unknown}}archived here .&lt;/ref&gt; Spitzer has requested that all "ex-gay" therapy organizations such as [[National Association for Research &amp; Therapy of Homosexuality|NARTH]], [[Parents and Friends of Ex-Gays and Gays|PFOX]], [[American College of Pediatricians]], and [[Focus on the Family]] stop citing his study as evidence for conversion therapy.&lt;ref name="spitzer2" /&gt;

===Analysis of the May 2001 Spitzer report===
The study results were based solely on interviews with the patients and not on any objective observed results. This made it possible and likely that the report was reporting what the patients wanted their results to be rather than the actual results.

Spitzer reported that after intervention, 66% of the men and 44% of the women had achieved "Good Heterosexual Functioning", which he defined as requiring five criteria (being in a loving heterosexual relationship during the last year, overall satisfaction in emotional relationship with a partner, having heterosexual sex with the partner at least a few times a month, achieving physical satisfaction through heterosexual sex, and not thinking about having homosexual sex more than 15% of the time while having heterosexual sex). He found that the most common reasons for seeking change were lack of emotional satisfaction from gay life, conflict between same-sex feelings and behavior and religious beliefs, and desire to marry or remain married.&lt;ref name="DrescherandZucker" /&gt;&lt;ref name="SpitzerStudy"&gt;{{Harvnb|Spitzer|2003|pp=403–417}}&lt;/ref&gt; This paper was widely reported in the international media and taken up by politicians in the United States, Germany, and Finland, and by conversion therapists.&lt;ref name="DrescherandZucker" /&gt;

In 2003, Spitzer published the paper in the ''[[Archives of Sexual Behavior]]''. Spitzer's study has been criticized on numerous ethical and methodological grounds, and "press releases from both [[NGLTF]] and [[Human Rights Campaign|HRC]] sought to undermine Spitzer's credibility by connecting him politically to right-wing groups that had backed the [[ex-gay movement]]".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://books.google.com/?id=EGMEAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=PA30&amp;lpg=PA30&amp;q=spitzer+besen+political|title=The Advocate|date=19 June 2001|publisher=Here Publishing|accessdate=13 July 2017|via=Google Books}}&lt;/ref&gt; Gay activists argued that the study would be used by conservatives to undermine gay rights.&lt;ref name="DrescherandZucker" /&gt; Spitzer acknowledged that the study sample consisted of people who sought treatment primarily because of their religious beliefs (93% of the sample), served in various church-related functions, and who publicly spoke in favor of changing homosexual orientation (78%), and thus were strongly motivated to overreport success. Critics felt he dismissed this source of bias, without even attempting to measure [[deception]] or [[self-deception]] (a standard practice in self-reporting psychological tests like [[MMPI-2]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Drescher|Zucker|2006|pp=97}}&lt;/ref&gt; That participants had to rely upon their memories of what their feelings were before treatment may have distorted the findings. It was impossible to determine whether any change that occurred was due to the treatment because it was not clear what it involved and there was no control group.&lt;ref name="DrescherandZucker" /&gt; Spitzer's own data showed that claims of change were reflected mostly in changes in self-labelling and behavior, less in attractions, and least in the homoerotic content during the masturbatory fantasies; this particular finding was consistent with other studies in this area.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Drescher|Zucker|2006|pp=98}}&lt;/ref&gt; Participants may have been bisexual before treatment. Follow-up studies were not conducted.&lt;ref name="DrescherandZucker" /&gt; Spitzer stressed the limitations of his study. Spitzer said that the number of gay people who could successfully become heterosexual was likely to be "pretty low",&lt;ref&gt;Goode, Erica (May 9, 2001). [https://www.nytimes.com/2001/05/09/us/study-says-gays-can-shift-sexual-orientation.html Study Says Gays Can Shift Sexual Orientation]. New York Times (retrieved 2011).&lt;/ref&gt; and conceded that his subjects were "unusually religious".&lt;ref name="Ucdavis"&gt;{{citation |url=http://psychology.ucdavis.edu/rainbow/html/facts_changing.html |title=Attempts To Change Sexual Orientation |accessdate=2007-08-28 |publisher=[[University of California, Davis]] Department of Psychology}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==="Changing Sexual Orientation: A Consumer's Report"===

Ariel Shidlo and Michael Schroeder found in "Changing Sexual Orientation: A Consumer's Report", a peer-reviewed study of 202 respondents&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Shidlo|Schroeder|2002b}}&lt;/ref&gt; published in 2002, that 88% of participants failed to achieve a sustained change in their sexual behavior and 3% reported changing their orientation to heterosexual. The remainder reported either losing all sexual drive or attempting to remain celibate, with no change in attraction. Some of the participants who failed felt a sense of shame and had gone through conversion therapy programs for many years. Others who failed believed that therapy was worthwhile and valuable. Many respondents felt harmed by the attempt to change, and reported depression, [[suicidal ideation]] and [[Failed suicide attempt|attempts]], [[hypervigilance]] of gender-deviant mannerisms, social isolation, fear of being a child abuser and poor self-esteem. Of the 8 respondents (out of a sample of 202) who reported a change in sexual orientation, 7 worked as ex-gay counselors or group leaders.&lt;ref name="ShidloandSchroeder2002a"&gt;{{Harvnb|Shidlo|Schroeder|2002a}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Medical, scientific and legal views==
{{further|Biology and sexual orientation|Environment and sexual orientation|Timeline of sexual orientation and medicine|Homosexuality and psychology}}

===Legal status===
[[File:Countries banning conversion therapy.svg|thumb|400px|center|Map of countries that have bans on sexual orientation and gender identity change efforts with minors.
{{legend|Navy|Ban on conversion therapy on the basis of sexual orientation and gender identity}}
{{legend|#0000ff|''[[De facto]]'' ban on conversion therapy}}
{{legend|#00ffff|Case-by-case bans}}
{{legend|Gold|Ban on conversion therapy pending or proposed}}
{{legend|LightGrey|No ban on conversion therapy}}]]
{| class="wikitable sortable" style="width:100%; margin:auto;"
|-
! width=10%| Country !! Details
|-
| {{flag|Argentina}} || '''Nationwide ban:''' Since 2010, no diagnosis can be made in the field of mental health on the exclusive basis of "sexual choice or identity".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://servicios.infoleg.gob.ar/infolegInternet/verNorma.do?id=175977 |title=Law 26,657, Article 3-C |website=InfoLEG}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ban only applies to registered [[health professional]]s.
|-
| {{flag|Australia}} || '''Banned in [[States and territories of Australia|one state]]:''' In February 2016, the Government of [[Victoria (Australia)|Victoria]] announced it would promptly introduce legislation to crack down on conversion therapy.&lt;ref name = Moret1&gt;{{cite web|url=http://gaynewsnetwork.com.au/news/gay-conversion-therapy-to-be-banned-in-victoria-20303.html|title=Gay conversion therapy to be banned in Victoria|work=Gay News Network|date=9 February 2016|author=Glen Moret|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160825194841/http://gaynewsnetwork.com.au/news/gay-conversion-therapy-to-be-banned-in-victoria-20303.html|archivedate=25 August 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = Moret2 /&gt; On 9 February 2016, a legislative bill was introduced to the lower house of the [[Parliament of Victoria|Victorian Parliament]]. The bill created a Health Complaints Commissioner with increased powers to take action against groups performing conversion therapy; these powers ranging from issuing public warnings to banning them from practicing in Victoria. It passed the lower house on 25 February 2016, passed the upper house on 14 April 2016 with minor amendments and passed the lower house with the attached amendments on 27 April 2016. [[Royal assent]] was granted on 5 May 2016.&lt;ref name = VicLaw /&gt; The law, known as the ''Health Complaints Act 2016'',&lt;ref&gt;[https://hcc.vic.gov.au/sites/default/files/healthcomplaintsact2016.pdf Health Complaints Act 2016]&lt;/ref&gt; went into effect on 1 February 2017. [[Western Australia]] and the [[Australian Capital Territory]] are also considering enacting laws to crack down on conversion therapy.&lt;ref name = Hack /&gt;

In April 2018, Health Minister [[Greg Hunt]] confirmed that the Australian Government does not support conversion therapy.&lt;ref&gt;[http://thebigsmoke.com.au/2018/05/29/libs-and-labor-vow-to-crack-down-but-not-ban-gay-conversion-therapy/ Libs and Labor vow to crack down (but not ban) gay conversion therapy]&lt;/ref&gt; 
|-
| {{flag|Brazil}} || '''Nationwide ban:''' In 1999, the Federal Council of Psychology issued two provisions which state that "psychologists shall not collaborate in events or services offering treatment and cure for homosexuality", and that "psychologists will neither pronounce nor participate in public speeches, in the mass media, reinforcing social prejudice related to homosexuals as pursuing any kind of psychological disorder".&lt;ref name="brazil"&gt;{{cite news|title=Resolução CFP 01/1999|url=https://site.cfp.org.br/wp-content/uploads/1999/03/resolucao1999_1.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; Brazil thus became the first country in the world to ban conversion therapy.&lt;ref name="Brazil"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.politicalresearch.org/2013/06/28/brazilian-evangelical-lawmakers-push-gay-conversion-therapy-bill/|title=Brazilian Evangelical Lawmakers Push Gay Conversion Therapy Bill|first=Tyler|last=Murphy|date=28 June 2013|publisher=|accessdate=13 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2013, the Commission for Human Rights of Brazil's lower house of Congress, headed by an evangelical Christian man, approved legislation that would nullify the Council's provisions and legalize conversion therapy.&lt;ref name="Brazil"/&gt; The bill subsequently died without any more legislative action. In September 2017, a federal judge in [[Brasília]] approved the use of conversion therapy by a psychologist to "cure" people of homosexuality, overruling the 1999 decision.&lt;ref name="guardian-19sep2017"&gt;{{cite news|last1=Phillips|first1=Dom|title=Brazilian judge approves 'gay conversion therapy', sparking national outrage|url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2017/sep/19/brazilian-judge-approves-gay-conversion-therapy|accessdate=September 19, 2017|newspaper=[[The Guardian]]|date=September 19, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, in December 2017, the same judge changed his decision, keeping the "treatment" banned.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Juiz Federal altera decisão que liberou 'cura gay' e reafirma normas do Conselho de Psicologia|url=https://g1.globo.com/df/distrito-federal/noticia/juiz-federal-do-df-altera-decisao-que-liberou-cura-gay-e-restabelece-normas-do-conselho-de-psicologia.ghtml}}&lt;/ref&gt; In January 2018, the Federal Psychology Council established norms of performance for psychologists in relation to transsexual and transvestite people, also banning any conversion therapy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Resolução CFP 01/2018|url=http://site.cfp.org.br/wp-content/uploads/2018/01/Resolução-CFP-01-2018.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| {{flag|Canada}} || '''Banned in [[Provinces and territories of Canada|three provinces]] and one city:''' Conversion therapy is banned in the province of [[Manitoba]] (since 2015),&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/manitoba/manitoba-works-to-ban-conversion-therapy-for-lgbt-youth-1.3083611 Manitoba works to ban conversion therapy for LGBT youth]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.gov.mb.ca/health/conversion_therapy.html Position on Conversion Therapy]&lt;/ref&gt; for minors in [[Ontario]] (since 2015),&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.ola.org/en/legislative-business/bills/parliament-41/session-1/bill-77 Bill 77, Affirming Sexual Orientation and Gender Identity Act, 2015]&lt;/ref&gt; for people of all ages and across all settings in the city of [[Vancouver]] (since 2018),&lt;ref&gt;[http://council.vancouver.ca/20180605/documents/motionB3.pdf Business Prohibition By-law No. 5156]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.thestar.com/vancouver/2018/06/06/vancouver-bans-conversion-therapy.html Vancouver council votes unanimously to ban conversion therapy]&lt;/ref&gt; and for minors (though allowed for "mature minors" between the ages of 16 and 18 if they consent) in [[Nova Scotia]] (since 2018).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Bill 16 - Sexual Orientation and Gender Identity Protection Act - RA |url=https://nslegislature.ca/legc/bills/63rd_2nd/3rd_read/b016.htm |website=Nova Scotia Legislature |language=en |date=12 October 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/nova-scotia/conversion-therapy-ban-lgbtq-bill-manitoba-ontario-1.4838311|work=CBC News|title=Bill passes banning conversion therapy in Nova Scotia|last=Gorman|first=Michael|accessdate=28 September 2018|date=25 September 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; In March 2019, the federal government initially rejected a petition calling for a nationwide conversion therapy ban,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/the-national-conversion-therapy-federal-petition-1.5066899/|title=Ottawa rejects plea for nationwide conversion therapy ban|date=March 23, 2019|publisher=CBC News|accessdate=May 2, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; but announced in July of that year it would move forward with a change to the criminal code to outlaw the procedure across all of Canada, and called on the provinces to take urgent action as well.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.cbc.ca/news/politics/conversion-therapy-criminal-code-1.5204919|title=Ottawa looking at Criminal Code reforms to deter 'shameful' conversion therapy|work=[[Canadian Broadcasting Company|CBC]]|date=9 July 2019|accessdate=11 July 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
|-
| {{flag|Chile}} || In February 2016, the Chilean Ministry of Health expressed their opposition to conversion therapy. The statement said: "We consider that practices known as conversion therapies represent a grave threat to health and well-being, including the life, of the people who are affected."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.washingtonblade.com/2016/02/19/chilean-officials-conversion-therapy-is-a-grave-threat/|title=Chilean officials: Conversion therapy is a 'grave threat'|date=19 February 2016|publisher=|accessdate=26 June 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In October 2017, the [[Chamber of Deputies of Chile|Chamber of Deputies]] passed a bill, known as the ''Proyecto de Ley Sobre Protección de la Salud Mental'' ("Mental Health Protection Bill"), which states in its article 6 that "a mental health diagnosis can not be made based solely on criteria related to sexual orientation or identity." The bill is currently being discussed in the Senate Health Committee.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Proyecto de Ley sobre protección de la salud mental |url=https://www.camara.cl/pley/pley_detalle.aspx?prmID=10987&amp;prmBoletin=10563-11 |website=www.camara.cl |publisher=Cámara de Diputados de Chile |accessdate=27 September 2018 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180928003331/https://www.camara.cl/pley/pley_detalle.aspx?prmID=10987&amp;prmBoletin=10563-11 |archive-date=28 September 2018 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| {{flag|China}} || '''Case-by-case ban:''' In China, courts have ruled instances of conversion therapy to be illegal on two occasions; however, legal precedents in China are not enforceable in future cases. In December 2014, a [[Beijing]] court ruled in favor of a gay man in a case against a conversion therapy clinic. The court ruled that such treatments are illegal and ordered the clinic to apologize and pay monetary compensation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2014/dec/19/chinese-court-gay-straight-conversion-clinic|title=Chinese court rules 'gay cure' treatments illegal|first=Jonathan|last=Kaiman|date=19 December 2014|publisher=|accessdate=13 July 2017|via=The Guardian}}&lt;/ref&gt; In June 2016, a man from [[Henan|Henan Province]] sued a hospital in the city of [[Zhumadian]] for forcing him to undergo conversion therapy,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2016/jun/14/gay-man-sues-chinese-psychiatric-hospital-over-sexuality-correction|title=Gay man sues Chinese psychiatric hospital over 'sexuality correction'|first=Tom|last=Phillips|date=14 June 2016|publisher=|accessdate=13 July 2017|via=The Guardian}}&lt;/ref&gt; and was also awarded a public apology and compensation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.bbc.com/news/world-asia-40490946|title=Gay Chinese man wins legal battle over forced conversion therapy|date=4 July 2017|publisher=[[BBC]]|accessdate=26 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Following these two successful rulings, LGBT groups are now calling on the Chinese Health Ministry to ban conversion therapy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine|url=http://www.sixthtone.com/news/1000883/hospital-drops-appeal-in-gay-mans-involuntary-treatment-case |title=Hospital Drops Appeal in Gay Man's Involuntary Treatment Case |magazine=Sixth Tone |date=20 September 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, as of April 2019, no measure has been taken by the government to ban conversion therapy, and such treatments are still in fact being actively promoted throughout the country.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine|url=https://www.sixthtone.com/news/1003870/conversion-therapy-still-promoted-in-china%2C-investigation-finds |title=Conversion Therapy Still Promoted in China, Investigation Finds |magazine=Sixth Tone |date=19 April 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| {{flag|Ecuador}} || '''Nationwide ban:''' In Ecuador, the Government's view is that conversion therapy is proscribed by a 1999 law banning anti-gay discrimination.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.theguardian.com/global-development-professionals-network/2016/feb/09/electrocution-and-submersion-gay-cures-and-the-fight-to-end-them|title=Electric shocks, rape and submersion: 'gay cures' and the fight to end them|work=[[The Guardian]]|accessdate=26 February 2018|date=9 February 2016|first=Matthew|last=Jenkins}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, Article 151 of the 2014 Penal Code prohibits conversion therapy, equating it to torture, and provides 10 years' imprisonment for those practicing it.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www.justicia.gob.ec/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/c%C3%B3digo_org%C3%A1nico_integral_penal_-_coip_ed._sdn-mjdhc.pdf |title=Código Orgánico Integral Penal |access-date=2018-08-05 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180219062146/http://www.justicia.gob.ec/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/c%C3%B3digo_org%C3%A1nico_integral_penal_-_coip_ed._sdn-mjdhc.pdf |archive-date=2018-02-19 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In January 2012, the Ecuadorian Government raided three conversion therapy clinics in [[Quito]], rescued dozens of women who were abused and tortured in an effort to "cure their homosexuality", and promised to shut down every such clinic in the country.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gaystarnews.com/article/ecuador-promises-shut-down-all-gay-cure-clinics/|title=Ecuador promises to shut down all 'gay cure' clinics|date=31 January 2012|publisher=|accessdate=13 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| {{flag|Fiji}} || '''Nationwide ban:''' The ''Mental Health Decree 2010'' states that people are not to be considered mentally ill if they refuse or fail to express a particular sexual orientation, and prohibits any conversion therapy in the field of mental health.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.paclii.org/fj/promu/promu_dec/mhd2010141.rtf Mental Health Decree 2010]&lt;/ref&gt; The ban only applies to registered health professionals.
|-
| {{flag|Germany}} || In 2008, the German Government declared itself completely opposed to conversion therapy.&lt;ref&gt;{{de icon}} [http://dip21.bundestag.de/dip21/btd/16/080/1608022.pdf Antwort der Bundesregierung auf die Kleine Anfrage der Abgeordneten Volker Beck (Köln), Josef Philip Winkler, Hans-Christian Ströbele, weiterer Abgeordneter under der Fraktion BÜNDNIS 90/DIE GRÜNEN]&lt;/ref&gt;

In February 2019, German Health Minister [[Jens Spahn]] said he will seek to ban conversion therapies that claim to change sexual orientation.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.theguardian.com/world/2019/feb/15/german-minister-calls-ban-gay-conversion-therapy German minister calls for ban on conversion therapy]&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| {{flag|India}} || In February 2014, the [[Indian Psychiatric Society]] (IPS) issued a statement, in which it stated that there is no evidence to prove that homosexuality is unnatural: "Based on existing scientific evidence and good practice guidelines from the field of psychiatry, the Indian Psychiatric Society would like to state that there is no evidence to substantiate the belief that homosexuality is a mental illness or a disease."&lt;ref name="india"&gt;{{cite web|url = http://orinam.net/indian-psychiatric-society-homosexual-not-mental-illness/|title = Indian Psychiatric Society official statement: homosexuality is not a mental illness|date = February 6, 2014|website = [[Orinam]]|accessdate = February 6, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| {{flag|Ireland}} || {{as of|2018|May}}, the ''Prohibition of Conversion Therapies Bill 2018'' has passed second reading in the [[Seanad Éireann]] (Irish Senate). It currently awaits a third reading in that chamber, and passage in the [[Dáil Éireann]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.thejournal.ie/seanad-conversion-therapy-bill-3991347-May2018/ |title='A deceptive practice': Bill to ban LGBTQ conversion therapies passes second stage of Seanad |newspaper=TheJournal.ie |date=2 May 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| {{flag|Israel}} || In October 2014, the Ministry of Health issued a statement announcing that it considers conversion therapy to "create false impressions of scientific recognition even though there is no scientific evidence that it is at all successful. It may also cause harm to the individual."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jpost.com/Israel-News/Health/Health-Ministry-warns-against-conversion-therapy-for-homosexuals-378122|title=Health Ministry warns against conversion therapy for homosexuals|publisher=|accessdate=13 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In February 2016 and in March 2017, the [[Knesset]] rejected bills introduced by former Health Minister [[Yael German]] that would have banned conversion therapy in Israel for minors. The bills were rejected 37–45 and 26–38, respectively.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.timesofisrael.com/day-after-marking-lgbt-rights-knesset-nixes-5-gender-equality-bills/|title=Day after marking LGBT rights, Knesset nixes 5 gender equality bills|publisher=|accessdate=13 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| {{flag|Lebanon}} || In 2013, the Lebanese Psychiatric Society stated that conversion therapy seeking to "convert" gays and bisexuals into straights has no scientific backing and asked health professionals to rely only on science when giving opinion and treatment in this matter.&lt;ref name="lebanon"&gt;Dan Littauer. [http://www.huffingtonpost.co.uk/dan-littauer/gay-treatment-lebanon_b_3585192.html "Lebanon Says: Being Gay Is Not a Disease and Needs No Treatment"]. ''Huffington Post'', 11 September 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| {{flag|Malaysia}} || '''Legal and state-backed:''' In February 2017, the Malaysian Government endorsed conversion therapy, claiming homosexuality can be "cured" through extensive training.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.newnownext.com/malaysia-conversion-therapy/02/2017/|title=The Goverment &amp;#91;sic&amp;#93; Of Malaysia Endorses Gay Conversion Therapy|author=Cody Gohl |date=Feb 16, 2017|publisher=www.newnownext.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; In June 2017, the Health Ministry began a film competition to find the best way to "cure" and prevent homosexuality. The competition was later cancelled, following massive outrage.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://news.sky.com/story/anger-over-malaysias-prevent-homosexuality-film-competition-10903201|title=Anger over Malaysia's 'prevent' homosexuality film competition|publisher=news.sky.com|author=Greg Heffer|date=3 June 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- 
| {{flag|Malta}} || '''Nationwide ban:''' In December 2016, the [[Parliament of Malta]] unanimously approved the ''Affirmation of Sexual Orientation, Gender Identity and Gender Expression Act'', becoming the first country in the [[European Union]] to ban conversion therapy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Benjamin|first=Butterworth|title=Malta just became the first country in Europe to ban 'gay cure' therapy|url=http://www.pinknews.co.uk/2016/12/06/malta-just-became-the-first-country-in-europe-to-ban-gay-cure-therapy/|newspaper=[[Pink News]]|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20161206160701/http://www.pinknews.co.uk/2016/12/06/malta-just-became-the-first-country-in-europe-to-ban-gay-cure-therapy/|archivedate=6 December 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://inewsmalta.com/article.php?ID1=43953|title=L-MCP dwar il-kriminalizzazzjoni tal-Gay Conversion Therapy|date=28 November 2016|publisher=iNews Malta|location=[[Marsa, Malta|Marsa]]|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20161129021735/https://inewsmalta.com/article.php?ID1=43953|archivedate=29 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| {{flag|Netherlands}} || Organizations offering conversion therapy in the [[Netherlands]] are not eligible for subsidies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Dirks |first1=Bart |title=Christelijke stichting verliest toch homo-subsidie |url=https://www.volkskrant.nl/nieuws-achtergrond/christelijke-stichting-verliest-toch-homo-subsidie~bd7f062f/ |website=de Volkskrant |language=nl-NL}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, since June 2012, conversion therapies have been blocked from coverage by healthcare insurance.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=De Wever |first1=Robin |title=Alleen stoppen met vergoeding homotherapie is niet genoeg |url=https://www.trouw.nl/home/-alleen-stoppen-met-vergoeding-homotherapie-is-niet-genoeg-~a778a901/ |website=Trouw |language=nl-NL}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| {{flag|New Zealand}} || In August 2018, Justice Minister [[Andrew Little (New Zealand politician)|Andrew Little]] announced that a conversion therapy ban could be considered as part of a reform to the ''Human Rights Act 1993''.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.radionz.co.nz/news/national/363321/conversion-therapy-ban-could-be-considered-justice-minister Conversion therapy ban could be considered - Justice Minister]&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| {{flag|Norway}} || In 2000, the Norwegian Psychiatric Association overwhelmingly voted for the position statement that "homosexuality is no disorder or illness, and can therefore not be subject to treatment. A 'treatment' with the only aim of changing sexual orientation from homosexual to heterosexual must be regarded as ethical malpractice, and should have no place in the health system".&lt;ref name=norway&gt;{{cite journal
 | last = Kjær
 | first = Reider
 | year = 2003
 | title = Look to Norway? Gay Issues and Mental Health Across the Atlantic Ocean
 | journal = Journal of Gay &amp; Lesbian Psychotherapy
 | volume = 7
 | issue = 1/2
 | pages = 55–73
 | doi = 10.1300/J236v07n01_05
 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| {{flag|Samoa}} || '''Nationwide ban:''' The ''Mental Health Act 2007'' states that people are not to be considered mentally ill if they refuse or fail to express a particular sexual orientation, and prohibits any conversion therapy in the field of mental health.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.paclii.org/ws/legis/num_act/mha2007128.rtf Mental Health Act 2007]&lt;/ref&gt; The ban only applies to registered health professionals.
|-
| {{flag|South Africa}} || The South African Society of Psychiatrists states that "there is no scientific evidence that reparative or conversion therapy is effective in changing a person's sexual orientation. There is, however, evidence that this type of therapy can be destructive".&lt;ref name="south africa"&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.sasop.co.za/Statements/Homosexuality_State |title=POSITION STATEMENTS HOMOSEXUALITY - POSITION STATEMENT |access-date=2016-12-12 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180420080900/https://www.sasop.co.za/Statements/Homosexuality_State |archive-date=2018-04-20 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In February 2015, owners of a conversion therapy camp were found guilty of murder, child abuse and assault with intent to do grievous bodily harm after three teens were found dead at the camp. The teens were beaten with spades and rubber pipes, chained to their beds, not allowed to use the toilet at any time and forced to eat soap and their own feces, all with the aim of "curing" their homosexuality.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.metroweekly.com/2015/02/gay-cure-camp-in-south-africa-guilty-of-murdering-teen/|title=Gay "cure" camp in South Africa guilty of murdering teen - Metro Weekly|website=www.metroweekly.com|accessdate=13 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| {{flag|Spain}} || '''Banned in [[Autonomous communities of Spain|four autonomies]]:''' Conversion therapy has been banned in the autonomous communities of [[Region of Murcia|Murcia]] (since 2016),&lt;ref&gt;{{es icon}} [http://noticias.juridicas.com/base_datos/CCAA/576023-l-8-2016-de-27-may-ca-murcia-igualdad-social-de-lesbianas-gais-bisexuales.html Ley 8/2016, de 27 de mayo, de igualdad social de lesbianas, gais, bisexuales, transexuales, transgénero e intersexuales, y de políticas públicas contra la discriminación por orientación sexual e identidad de género en la Comunidad Autónoma de la Región de Murcia.]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Community of Madrid|Madrid]] (since 2017),&lt;ref&gt;{{es icon}} [https://www.boe.es/buscar/pdf/2016/BOE-A-2016-11096-consolidado.pdf Ley 3/2016, de 22 de julio, de Protección Integral contra LGTBIfobia y la Discriminación por Razón de Orientación e Identidad Sexual en la Comunidad de Madrid]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Valencian Community|Valencia]] (since 2017),&lt;ref&gt;{{es icon}} [http://noticias.juridicas.com/base_datos/CCAA/595124-l-8-2017-de-7-abr-ca-valenciana-integral-del-reconocimiento-del-derecho-a.html Ley 8/2017, de 7 de abril, de la Generalitat, integral del reconocimiento del derecho a la identidad y a la expresión de género en la Comunitat Valenciana]&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Andalusia]] (since 2018).&lt;ref&gt;{{es icon}} [noticias.juridicas.com/base_datos/CCAA/612536-l-8-2017-de-28-dic-ca-andalucia-garantia-de-los-derechos-la-igualdad-de.html Ley 8/2017, de 28 de diciembre, para garantizar los derechos, la igualdad de trato y no discriminación de las personas LGTBI y sus familiares en Andalucía]&lt;/ref&gt; The specifics vary by jurisdiction. For instance, in Murcia, the ban only applies to registered [[health professional]]s, but the Madrid ban applies to everyone including religious groups.

The Spanish Psychological Association states that there is no evidence to support conversion therapy. "On the contrary, there is evidence that conversion therapy leads to anxiety, depression and suicide".&lt;ref name="spain"&gt;[https://www.redaccionmedica.com/secciones/otras-profesiones/rechazo-total-de-los-psicologos-a-las-terapias-de-conversion-homosexual--4869 Rechazo total de los psicólogos a las 'terapias de conversión homosexual']&lt;/ref&gt;

In April 2019, following an exposé of conversion therapy in Spain, the Spanish health minister Maria Luisa Carcedo  said the Spanish government would consider legislating to stamp out the practice.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.reuters.com/article/us-spain-lgbt-politics/spains-health-minister-calls-for-end-to-gay-conversion-therapy-idUSKCN1RF2IR|work=Reuters|accessdate=11 July 2019|date=3 April 2019|title=Spain's health minister calls for end to gay 'conversion therapy'|last1=Savage|first1=Rachel|last2=Davies|first2=Sophie}}&lt;/ref&gt;

|-
| {{flag|Switzerland}} || '''''De facto'' ban:''' In Switzerland, it is unlawful for a medical professional to carry out conversion therapy. In 2016, the [[Swiss Federal Council]] wrote in response to a parliamentary [[Interpellation (politics)|interpellation]] that in its view, conversion therapies are "ineffective and cause significant suffering to young people subject to them", and would constitute a breach of professional duties on the part of any care professional undertaking them. As such, in the Government's view, any care professional undertaking such therapies is liable to be sanctioned by the cantonal authorities. Whether such therapies also constitute a criminal offense is to be determined by the criminal courts in the individual case, according to the Federal Council.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Interpellation 16.3073: Verbot und Unterstrafestellung von Therapien zur "Heilung" von Homosexualität bei Minderjährigen|url=https://www.parlament.ch/en/ratsbetrieb/suche-curia-vista/geschaeft?AffairId=20163073|website=www.parlament.ch|accessdate=12 November 2017|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Reports emerged in summer 2018 of a therapist claiming to be able to "cure" homosexuality through [[homoeopathy]]. He was promptly fired, and an investigation was opened with the Geneva Ministry of Health.&lt;ref&gt;{{fr icon}} [https://www.neonmag.fr/un-medecin-propose-de-soigner-lhomosexualite-par-lhomeopathie-515166.html Un médecin propose de « soigner » l’homosexualité par l’homéopathie]&lt;/ref&gt; According to the Ministry, believing that homosexuality is an illness is sufficient enough to open an investigation. The ''Association des Médecins du Canton de Genève'' describes conversion therapy as a form of [[charlatan]]ism.
|-
| {{flag|Taiwan}} || '''Nationwide ban:''' On 13 May 2016, the Health Bureau of the [[Taichung City Government]] announced that medical institutions in [[Taichung]] are prohibited from engaging in conversion therapy. According to Shader Liu, a member of Taichung's Gender Equality Committee, any group—medical, civil or religious—that practices the treatment is violating the Taiwanese ''Physicians Act'' and ''Psychologists Act''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.taipeitimes.com/News/feat/archives/2016/08/28/2003654009|title=Taipei Watcher: The call is loud and clear - Taipei Times|website=www.taipeitimes.com|accessdate=13 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Regulations banning conversion therapy were expected to bypass [[Legislative Yuan|Parliament]] in late January 2017 and take effect in March 2017.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|first=George|last=Liao|title=Conversion therapy to be prohibited by regulation|url=https://www.taiwannews.com.tw/en/news/3062115|work=Taiwan News|date=20 January 2017|accessdate=13 April 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Benedict|first=R.S.|title=Taiwan is Getting Closer to Banning Gay Conversion Therapy|url=http://www.taiwannews.com.tw/en/news/3062115|work=Hornet|date=30 January 2017|accessdate=13 April 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to the ''Physicians Act'', doctors who engage in prohibited treatments are subject to fines of between NT$100,000 (US$3,095) to NT$500,000 (US$15,850) and may be suspended for one month to one year.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|first=Joe|last=Morgan|title=Taiwan publishes bill to ban 'gay cure' therapy|url=http://www.gaystarnews.com/article/taiwan-publishes-bill-ban-gay-cure-therapy/|work=Gay Star News|date=3 January 2017|accessdate=13 April 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the proposed regulations were stalled by fierce resistance from anti-LGBT groups.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|first=驛淵|last=黃|script-title=zh:【獨家】反同攻進國發會公共平台　衛福部「禁性傾向扭轉」2度觸礁|trans-title=[Exclusive] Anti-LGBT group attacks MoHW's proposed ban on sexual orientation conversion on National Development Council's Public Policy Online Participation Platform|url=https://www.upmedia.mg/news_info.php?SerialNo=30633|language=Chinese|date=7 December 2017|accessdate=13 April 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Instead of pushing ahead legal amendments or new regulations, on 22 February 2018, the [[Ministry of Health and Welfare (Taiwan)|Ministry of Health and Welfare]] issued a letter to all local health authorities on the matter, which effectively banned conversion 'therapy'.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=|script-title=zh:衛生福利法規檢索系統 - 衛部醫字第1071660970號|trans-title=Health and Welfare law and regulation search engine - Wei-Bu-Yi 1071660970|url=http://mohwlaw.mohw.gov.tw/FINT/FINTQRY04.aspx?starDate=00000000&amp;endDate=99991231&amp;no=&amp;n1=&amp;n2=1071660970&amp;kt=&amp;kw=&amp;kw2=&amp;kw3=&amp;kw4=&amp;type=etype_&amp;RowNo=1|website=Ministry of Health and Welfare|language=Chinese|date=22 February 2018}}{{Dead link|date=July 2019 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt; In the letter, the Ministry states that sexual orientation conversion is not regarded as a legitimate healthcare practice and that any individual performing the so-called therapy is liable to prosecution under the [[Law of Taiwan|Criminal Code]] or the ''Protection of Children and Youths Welfare and Rights Act'', depending on the circumstances.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Shanghaiist|url=https://medium.com/shanghaiist/taiwan-finalizes-conversion-therapy-ban-adb417e5ff44|title=Taiwan finalizes conversion therapy ban|publisher=Medium|date=24 February 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| {{flag|United Kingdom}} || In 2007, the [[Royal College of Psychiatrists]], the main professional organisation of psychiatrists in the UK, issued a report stating that: "Evidence shows that LGB people are open to seeking help for mental health problems. However, they may be misunderstood by therapists who regard their homosexuality as the root cause of any presenting problem such as depression or anxiety. Unfortunately, therapists who behave in this way are likely to cause considerable distress. A small minority of therapists will even go so far as to attempt to change their client's sexual orientation. This can be deeply damaging. Although there are now a number of therapists and organisations in the USA and in the UK that claim that therapy can help homosexuals to become heterosexual, there is no evidence that such change is possible."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.thinkinganglicans.org.uk/uploads/rcp.html |title=Thinking Anglicans |date=13 September 2008 |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After reports of a [[Liverpool]] church starving individuals for three days as a means to "cure" their homosexuality, the [[Church of England]] announced it considers conversion therapy "fundamentally wrong" and demanded the Government ban it.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1 = Parry|first1 = Josh|title = ECHO goes undercover at gay 'cure' church offering 'dangerous' starvation therapy|url = https://www.liverpoolecho.co.uk/news/liverpool-news/echo-goes-undercover-gay-cure-13468107|accessdate = March 9, 2018|newspaper = [[Liverpool Echo]]|publisher = [[Trinity Mirror]]|date = September 5, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url = https://www.theguardian.com/world/2017/jul/08/church-of-england-demands-ban-on-conversion-therapy|title = Church of England demands ban on conversion therapy|newspaper = [[The Guardian]]|date = 8 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Groups such as [[Stonewall (charity)|Stonewall]] and [[Humanists UK]] have also long called for it to be banned. On 3 July 2018, the UK Government announced it would work towards a total ban on conversion therapy across medical, non-medical, and religious settings.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://humanism.org.uk/2018/07/03/government-commits-to-banning-conversion-therapy-and-other-major-lgbt-protections-in-action-plan/|title=Government commits to banning 'conversion therapy' and other major LGBT protections in action plan|work=Humanists UK|date=3 July 2018|accessdate=3 July 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://humanism.org.uk/campaigns/human-rights-and-equality/conversion-therapy/|title=Conversion therapy|work=[[Humanists UK]]|accessdate=12 June 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; Stonewall notes that "in the UK, all major counselling and psychotherapy bodies, as well as the NHS, have concluded that conversion therapy is dangerous and have condemned it by signing a Memorandum of Understanding".&lt;ref&gt;https://www.stonewall.org.uk/campaign-groups/conversion-therapy&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| {{flag|United States}} || {{main|List of U.S. jurisdictions banning conversion therapy for minors}}

'''Banned in 18 states, 2 territories, and local counties/municipalities:''' {{as of|2019|May}}, 18 [[U.S. state]]s, the [[Washington, D.C.|District of Columbia]], [[Puerto Rico]], and some counties and municipalities in the United States have passed laws banning the practice of conversion therapy on minors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://vtdigger.org/2016/05/25/ban-on-anti-gay-therapy-hailed-as-step-against-hatred/|title=Ban on anti-gay 'therapy' hailed as step against hatred|date=25 May 2016|website=VTDigger|accessdate=13 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Lieu, Ma|title=SB-1172 Sexual orientation change efforts.(2011-2012)|url=https://leginfo.legislature.ca.gov/faces/billNavClient.xhtml?bill_id=201120120SB1172|publisher=State of California, Legislative Counsel|accessdate=6 May 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lgbtqnation.com/2015/08/illinois-enacts-gay-conversion-therapy-ban-for-young-people/ "Illinois enacts gay conversion therapy ban for young people"]. ''LGBTQ Nation'', August 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.oregonlive.com/politics/index.ssf/2015/05/bill_to_ban_conversion_therapy.html|title=Bill to ban conversion therapy for LGBT youth sent to Kate Brown's desk|publisher=Oregon Live|date=May 7, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.usatoday.com/story/news/nation-now/2015/12/09/cincinnati-bans-gay-conversion-therapy/77075540/ "Cincinnati bans gay 'conversion' therapy"]. ''USA Today'', 9 December 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;https://www.usatoday.com/story/news/nation-now/2018/07/24/conversion-therapy-banned-lgbt-youth-delaware/829410002/&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|work=[[New York Times]]|last=Gold|first=Michael|date=January 21, 2019|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2019/01/21/nyregion/conversion-therapy-ban.html|title=New York Passes a Ban on 'Conversion Therapy' After Years-Long Efforts}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|work=[[The Hill (newspaper)|The Hill]]|last=Anapol|first=Avery|date=April 8, 2019|url=https://thehill.com/homenews/state-watch/437925-massachusetts-gop-governor-signs-bill-banning-gay-conversion-therapy}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is also banned in major cities like [[Miami]] and [[Cincinnati]].

Subsequently, legal challenges against [[New Jersey]]'s and [[California]]'s conversion therapy bans were filed. United States District Court Judge [[Freda L. Wolfson]] rejected the claim of New Jersey parents that it violated their rights by keeping them from treating their child for same-sex attraction. In ''Doe v. Christie'', Wolfson wrote: "Surely, the fundamental rights of parents do not include the right to choose a specific medical or mental health treatment that the state has reasonably deemed harmful or ineffective." Wolfson added, "To find otherwise would create unimaginable and unintentional consequences." On February 10, 2015, a New Jersey Superior Court judge ruled that offering conversion services on the basis of a description of homosexuality as abnormal or a mental illness is a violation of the ''New Jersey Consumer Fraud Act''.&lt;ref name="gallagher"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.njlawjournal.com/this-weeks-news/id=1202717571907/Judge-Says-Gay-Conversion-Therapy-is-Consumer-Fraud?mcode=1202617207189&amp;curindex=0|title=Gay 'Conversion Therapy' Consumer Fraud Ruling First in U.S.|author=Mary Pat Gallagher|work=New Jersey Law Journal|accessdate=5 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; An article about the ruling on the New Jersey Law Journal web site said the decision is "believed to be the first of its kind in the U.S."&lt;ref name="gallagher"/&gt; On August 29, 2013, in the case of ''[[Pickup v. Brown and Welch v. Brown]]'', the United States Court of Appeals for the Ninth Circuit upheld California's ban.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://equalityontrial.com/2013/08/29/ninth-circuit-court-of-appeals-upholds-california-law-banning-lgbt-conversion-therapy/|title=Ninth Circuit Court of Appeals upholds California law banning LGBT conversion therapy|date=August 29, 2013|publisher=Equality On Trial}}&lt;/ref&gt; In August 2016, the Ninth Circuit again upheld the state's ban, finding that legislation prohibiting conversion therapy is not unconstitutional.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.courthousenews.com/2016/08/23/gay-conversion-therapy-ban-upheld-by-9th-circ.htm|title=CNS - Gay Conversion Therapy Ban Upheld by 9th Circ.|website=www.courthousenews.com|accessdate=13 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Supreme Court of the United States|U.S. Supreme Court]] has repeatedly dismissed challenges against conversion therapy bans.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2017-05-01/gay-conversion-therapy-ban-survives-as-high-court-rejects-appeal |title=Gay-Conversion Therapy Ban Survives as Supreme Court Rejects Appeal |publisher=Bloomberg |date=May 1, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The states of [[New Jersey]] (2013), [[California]] (2013), [[Oregon]] (2015), [[Illinois]] (2016), [[Vermont]] (2016), [[New Mexico]] (2017), [[Connecticut]] (2017), [[Rhode Island]] (2017), [[Nevada]] (2018), [[Washington (state)|Washington]] (2018), [[Hawaii]] (2018), [[Delaware]] (2018), [[Maryland]] (2018), [[New Hampshire]] (2019), [[New York (state)|New York]] (2019), [[Massachusetts]] (2019),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.masslive.com/news/2019/04/massachusetts-bans-conversion-therapy-for-minors.html|title=Massachusetts bans conversion therapy for minors|date=April 8, 2019|work=[[MassLive.com]]|accessdate=April 9, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Maine]] (2019),&lt;ref&gt;https://www.gaystarnews.com/article/maine-bans-conversion-therapy/#gs.ffub68&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Colorado]] (2019),&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.denverpost.com/2019/05/31/conversion-therapy-ban-lgbt-colorado/ Conversion therapy for gay youth banned in Colorado]&lt;/ref&gt; as well as the [[District of Columbia]] (2015) and [[Puerto Rico]] (2019) ban the use of conversion therapy on minors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.nbcnews.com/feature/nbc-out/new-york-become-15th-state-ban-gay-conversion-therapy-n958761|title=New York to become 15th state to ban 'gay conversion therapy'|author=|date=|website=www.nbcnews.com|accessdate=April 1, 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Opinion polls have found that conversion therapy bans enjoy popular support among the American population. As of 2019, no nationwide opinion poll has been carried out, though surveys in three states ([[Florida]], [[New Mexico]] and [[Virginia]]) show support varying between 60% and 75%. According to a 2014 national poll, only 8% of Americans believed conversion therapies to be successful.&lt;ref&gt;[https://williamsinstitute.law.ucla.edu/wp-content/uploads/Conversion-Therapy-LGBT-Youth-Jan-2018.pdf Conversion Therapy and LGBT Youth], the Williams Institute, January 2018&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| {{flag|Uruguay}} || '''Nationwide ban:''' Adopted in 2017, the ''Ley de Salud Mental'' ("Mental Health Law") states that in no case a diagnosis can be made in the field of mental health on the exclusive basis of sexual orientation and gender identity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Ley N° 19529 de Salud Mental |url=https://www.impo.com.uy/bases/leyes/19529-2017 |accessdate=27 September 2018 |language=es}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|}

===Legal status by US state===
 {{main|List of U.S. jurisdictions banning conversion therapy for minors}}
Although no national ban exists, several US states and individual counties ban therapy attempting to change sexual orientation as shown in the map below.
[[File:US states banning conversion therapy for minors.svg|thumb|400px|center|Map of U.S. states and counties that have bans on sexual orientation and gender identity change efforts with minors.
{{legend|Blue|Ban on conversion therapy for minors on the basis of sexual orientation and gender identity}}
{{legend|LightGrey|No ban on conversion therapy for minors}}]]

===Status by health organizations===

Many health organizations around the world have denounced and criticized sexual orientation change efforts.&lt;ref name="UK" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Lambda" /&gt;&lt;ref name="HRC" /&gt; National health organizations in the United States have announced that there has been no scientific demonstration of conversion therapy's efficacy in the last forty years.&lt;ref name="APA"/&gt;&lt;ref name="APA-Answers"&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.apa.org/topics/lgbt/orientation.aspx | title=Answers to Your Questions: For a Better Understanding of Sexual Orientation and Homosexuality | publisher=American Psychological Association | date=2008 | accessdate=January 31, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name =APA_Position/&gt;&lt;ref name="PsychNews"&gt;{{citation |last=H. |first=K |title=APA Maintains Reparative Therapy Not Effective |url=http://www.psychiatricnews.org/pnews/99-01-15/therapy.html |publisher=Psychiatric News (news division of the American Psychiatric Association) |date=1999-01-15 |accessdate=2007-08-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;
They find that conversion therapy is ineffective, risky and can be harmful. Anecdotal claims of cures are counterbalanced by assertions of harm, and the American Psychiatric Association, for example, cautions ethical practitioners under the [[Hippocratic oath]] to do no harm and to refrain from attempts at conversion therapy.&lt;ref name=APA_Position&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.psych.org/Departments/EDU/Library/APAOfficialDocumentsandRelated/PositionStatements/200001a.aspx |title=Therapies Focused on Attempts to Change Sexual Orientation |publisher=Psych.org |accessdate=2011-07-18 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080910045820/http://www.psych.org/Departments/EDU/Library/APAOfficialDocumentsandRelated/PositionStatements/200001a.aspx |archivedate=2008-09-10 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Mainstream medical bodies state that conversion therapy can be harmful because it may exploit guilt and anxiety, thereby damaging self-esteem and leading to depression and even suicide.&lt;ref name="nytconversion"&gt;{{citation |last=Luo |first=Michael |title=Some Tormented by Homosexuality Look to a Controversial Therapy |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2007/02/12/nyregion/12group.html |work=The New York Times |page=1 |date=2007-02-12 |accessdate=2007-08-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; There is also concern in the mental health community that the advancement of conversion therapy can cause social harm by disseminating inaccurate views about sexual orientation and the ability of gay and bisexual people to lead happy, healthy lives.&lt;ref name="APA"/&gt;

====List of health organizations critical of conversion therapy====
Major health organizations critical of conversion therapy include:

=====Multi-national health organizations=====
* The [[World Psychiatric Association]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=WPA Position Statement on Gender Identity and Same-Sex Orientation, Attraction, and Behaviours|url=http://www.wpanet.org/detail.php?section_id=7&amp;content_id=1807|website=wpanet.org|publisher=World Psychiatric Association|date=March 2016|quote=There is no sound scientific evidence that innate sexual orientation can be changed. Furthermore, so-called treatments of homosexuality can create a setting in which prejudice and discrimination flourish, and they can be potentially harmful. The provision of any intervention purporting to 'treat' something that is not a disorder is wholly unethical. ... WPA considers same-sex attraction, orientation, and behaviour as normal variants of human sexuality. It recognises the multi-factorial causation of human sexuality, orientation, behaviour, and lifestyle. It acknowledges the lack of scientific efficacy of treatments that attempt to change sexual orientation and highlights the harm and adverse effects of such 'therapies'.|access-date=2017-12-16|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160417131725/http://www.wpanet.org/detail.php?section_id=7&amp;content_id=1807|archive-date=2016-04-17|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Lace-Evans|first1=Olivia|title=Global health group takes on gay conversion therapy|url=https://www.bbc.com/news/magazine-35893729|work=BBC News|publisher=British Broadcasting Company|date=30 March 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[Pan American Health Organization]] regional office of the [[World Health Organization]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title='Therapies' to change sexual orientation lack medical justification and threaten health|url=http://www.paho.org/hq/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=6803&amp;Itemid=1|website=paho.org|publisher=Pan American Health Organization of the World Health Organization}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[International Society of Psychiatric-Mental Health Nurses]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Powell|first1=Lois|last2=Hein|first2=Laura|title=Position Statement On Reparative Therapy|url=http://www.ispn-psych.org/docs/PS-ReparativeTherapy.pdf|website=ispn-psych.org|publisher=International Society of Psychiatric-Mental Health Nurses|quote=In fact 'reparative or conversion therapies' have not supported authentic change in sexual orientation itself. ... There is no conclusive evidence that 'reparative therapy' is beneficial to patients. ... Harmful sequelae of reparative therapy reported in the literature include anxiety, depression, avoidance of intimacy, sexual dysfunction, PTSD, loss of self-confidence and self-efficacy, shame/guilt, self-destructive behavior, and suicidality.|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20170517042600/http://www.ispn-psych.org/docs/PS-ReparativeTherapy.pdf|archivedate=2017-05-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=====US health organizations=====
* The [[American Medical Association]]&lt;ref name="AmericanMedicalAssociation"&gt;{{citation |url=http://www.ama-assn.org/ama/pub/about-ama/our-people/member-groups-sections/glbt-advisory-committee/ama-policy-regarding-sexual-orientation.shtml |title=American Medical Association policy regarding sexual orientation |accessdate=2007-07-30 |date=2007-07-11 |publisher=American Medical Association}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[American Psychiatric Association]]&lt;ref name="Lambda"&gt;{{cite web|title=Health and Medical Organization Statements On Sexual Orientation, Gender Identity/Expression and 'Reparative Therapy'|url=https://www.lambdalegal.org/publications/health-and-med-orgs-stmts-on-sex-orientation-and-gender-identity|website=lambdalegal.org|publisher=Lambda Legal}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="HRC" /&gt;
* The [[American Psychological Association]]&lt;ref name="Lambda" /&gt;&lt;ref name="HRC" /&gt;
* The [[American Association for Marriage and Family Therapy]]&lt;ref name="McGeorgeCarlson2015"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=McGeorge|first1=Christi R.|last2=Carlson|first2=Thomas Stone|last3=Toomey|first3=Russell B.|title=An Exploration of Family Therapists' Beliefs about the Ethics of Conversion Therapy: The Influence of Negative Beliefs and Clinical Competence With Lesbian, Gay, and Bisexual Clients|journal=Journal of Marital and Family Therapy|volume=41|issue=1|year=2015|pages=42–56|issn=0194-472X|doi=10.1111/jmft.12040|pmid=24750074}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[American Counseling Association]]&lt;ref name="Lambda" /&gt;&lt;ref name="HRC" /&gt;
* The [[National Association of Social Workers]]&lt;ref name="Lambda" /&gt;&lt;ref name="HRC" /&gt;
* The [[American Academy of Pediatrics]]&lt;ref name="Aap"&gt;{{citation |author=Committee on Adolescence |title=Homosexuality and Adolesence |year=1993 |journal=Pediatrics |volume=92 |pages=631–634 |url=http://pediatrics.aappublications.org/cgi/reprint/92/4/631.pdf |accessdate=2007-08-28 |issue=4}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[American Academy of Physician Assistants]]&lt;ref name="APA"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|url=http://www.spiritindia.com/health-care-news-articles-10085.html |title=Physician Assistants vote on retail clinics, reparative therapy |accessdate=2007-08-28 |publisher=SpiritIndia.com |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070701171455/http://www.spiritindia.com/health-care-news-articles-10085.html |archivedate=2007-07-01 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[American Association of Sexuality Educators, Counselors and Therapists]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Position on Sexual Orientation and Reparative Therapy|url=https://www.aasect.org/position-sexual-orientation-and-reparative-therapy|website=aasect.org|publisher=American Association of Sexuality Educators, Counselors and Therapists|accessdate=9 February 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=====UK health organizations=====
* The [[National Association of School Psychologists]]&lt;ref name="UK"&gt;{{cite web|title=Conversion Therapy: Consensus Statement|url=https://www1.bps.org.uk/system/files/Public%20files/conversion_therapy_final_version.pdf|website=bps.org.uk|publisher=UK Council for Psychotherapy|page=2|access-date=2017-12-16|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170517093445/http://www.bps.org.uk/system/files/Public%20files/conversion_therapy_final_version.pdf|archive-date=2017-05-17|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[UK Council for Psychotherapy]]&lt;ref name="UK" /&gt;
* The [[British Association for Counselling and Psychotherapy]]&lt;ref name="UK" /&gt;
* The [[British Psychological Society]]&lt;ref name="UK" /&gt;
* The [[British Psychoanalytic Council]]&lt;ref name="UK" /&gt;
* The [[Royal College of Psychiatrists]]&lt;ref name="UK" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Memo" /&gt;
* The [[British Association for Behavioural and Cognitive Psychotherapies]]&lt;ref name="Memo"&gt;{{cite web|title=Memorandum of Understanding on Conversion Therapy in the UK|url=https://www.psychotherapy.org.uk/wp-content/uploads/2016/09/Memorandum-of-understanding-on-conversion-therapy.pdf|website=psychotherapy.org.uk|publisher=UK Department of Health|date=November 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[Association of Christian Counsellors]]&lt;ref name="Memo" /&gt;
* The [[National Counselling Society]]&lt;ref name="Memo" /&gt;
* The [[NHS Scotland|Scottish National Health Service]]&lt;ref name="Memo" /&gt;
* The [[National Health Service (England)|English National Health Service]]&lt;ref name="Memo" /&gt;
* The [[Royal College of General Practitioners]]&lt;ref name="Memo" /&gt;

=====Australian health organizations=====
*The [[Australian Medical Association]]&lt;ref name = AMA1&gt;{{cite web|title = AMA Position Statement – Sexual Diversity and Gender Identity (2002): A submission to the Australian Human Rights Commission Inquiry "Same-Sex: Same Entitlements"|date = June 21, 2007|accessdate = March 17, 2018|url = https://www.humanrights.gov.au/sites/default/files/content/human_rights/samesex/inquiry/submissions/314.doc|author = Australian Medical Association|quote = The AMA opposes the use of "reparative" or "conversion" therapy that is based upon the assumption that homosexuality is a mental disorder and that the patient should change his or her sexual orientation.|publisher = [[Australian Human Rights Commission]]|url-status = live|archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20151222113334/https://www.humanrights.gov.au/sites/default/files/content/human_rights/samesex/inquiry/submissions/314.doc|archive-date = December 22, 2015|author-link = Australian Medical Association}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = AMA2&gt;{{cite web|title = AMA Position Statement – Marriage Equality|date = May 20, 2017|accessdate = March 17, 2018|url = https://ama.com.au/position-statement/marriage-equality-2017|author = Australian Medical Association|quote = There are real and significant mental and physiological health impacts arising from structural discrimination, and the AMA supports moves to eliminate it in all of its forms. All Australian doctors should offer sensitive, non-discriminatory care to all of their patients, regardless of their sexual orientation or gender identity.|archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20170706213258/https://ama.com.au/position-statement/marriage-equality-2017|url-status = live|archive-date = July 6, 2017|author-link = Australian Medical Association}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*The [[Australian Psychological Society]]&lt;ref name = AustPsychSocPosSt&gt;{{cite web|author = Australian Psychological Society|year = 2015|title = APS Position Statement on the use of psychological practices that attempt to change sexual orientation|publisher = [[Australian Psychological Society]]|quote = (emphases in original) '''APS strongly opposes any approach to psychological practice or research that treats lesbians, gay men, and bisexual people as disordered. The APS also strongly opposes any approach to psychological practice or research that attempts to change an individual's sexual orientation.'''&lt;br /&gt;'''There is no peer-reviewed empirical psychological research objectively documenting the ability to 'change' an individual’s sexual orientation. Furthermore, there is no peer-reviewed empirical psychological research demonstrating that homosexuality or bisexuality constitutes a disorder.''' In addition to the lack of empirical support for the claim that sexual orientation can be changed, empirical evidence indicates that attempts at changing sexual orientation can be harmful.|accessdate = March 17, 2018|url = https://www.psychology.org.au/getmedia/95cfcca4-009c-4a75-a0e7-597d68e5a55c/Position_statement_on_psychological_practices_that_attempt_to_change_sexual_orientation_members.pdf|url-status = live|archive-date = March 17, 2018|archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20180317021307/https://www.psychology.org.au/getmedia/95cfcca4-009c-4a75-a0e7-597d68e5a55c/Position_statement_on_psychological_practices_that_attempt_to_change_sexual_orientation_members.pdf|author-link = Australian Psychological Society}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*The [[National LGBTI Health Alliance]]&lt;ref name = NationalLGBTIHealthAlliance&gt;{{cite book|first = Gabi|last = Rosenstreich|title = LGBTI People: Mental Health and Suicide|edition = 2nd|year = 2013|publisher = [[National LGBTI Health Alliance]]|location = Sydney|page = 10|quote = Experiences of LGBTI people include violence, refusal or reluctance to treat or if treating to acknowledge a health concern directly related to their sexual orientation, gender identity or intersex status. They also include homophobic and transphobic treatment paradigms, for example, pathologising LGBTI identity as a symptom of mental ill-health and using conversion therapies for same-sex attracted people (also known as reparative therapy). This practice claims to change sexual orientation and has been condemned the Australian Psychological Society and numerous other Australian and international professional associations as not only not working (as it is based on false premises) but also as unethical and harmful to the wellbeing of those who undergo it.|url = https://www.beyondblue.org.au/docs/default-source/default-document-library/bw0258-lgbti-mental-health-and-suicide-2013-2nd-edition.pdf|accessdate = March 17, 2018|url-status = live|archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20150420195927/https://www.beyondblue.org.au/docs/default-source/default-document-library/bw0258-lgbti-mental-health-and-suicide-2013-2nd-edition.pdf|archive-date = April 20, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*The [[Royal Australian College of General Practitioners]] operates a unit titled "Sex, sexuality, gender diversity and health" as part of its curriculum for aspiring general practitioners and for [[professional development]], which is intended to foster the provision of "non-judgemental holistic care that is affirming and positive when disclosure occurs and based on sound knowledge of any mental or physical health risks and requirements for screening, because like many others in the Australian population, many sex, sexuality and gender diverse individuals do not want to be solely defined by their gender or sexual identity."&lt;ref name = RACGP&gt;{{cite web|author = Royal Australian College of General Practitioners|year = 2016|accessdate = March 17, 2018|url = https://www.racgp.org.au/Education/Curriculum/Sex,-sexuality,-gender-diversity-and-health|title = SG16 – Sex, sexuality, gender diversity and health contextual unit|quote = [G]eneral practitioners (GPs) [must] have a good understanding of the diversity of sex, sexuality and gender in Australia, and to approach every individual in a holistic and non-judgemental way, minimise discrimination and obstacles to care access, and optimise the quality of healthcare that they provide. The title of this contextual unit is intentionally broad to encompass individuals who may identify as lesbian, gay, bisexual, transgender, intersex, queer (LGBTIQ), asexual, pansexual, those who do not identify with any particular gender or sexual orientation, and those who prefer not to be categorised. The purpose of this unit is to challenge the 'binary' approach to provision of healthcare by GPs, in which assumptions and judgements are made about an individual's sex, sexuality and/or gender based on appearances and/or what is considered by the individual GP to be 'normal.' This approach is essentially flawed and typically impacts the quality of care that can be provided. ... GPs have an important role to play in advocating to reduce discrimination and in creating meaningful therapeutic relationships with LGBTIQ individuals to improve healthcare access. The establishment of high-quality therapeutic relationships and delivery of quality care to these individuals draws on the core skills in The Royal Australian College of General Practitioners' (RACGP's) 2016 curriculum.|archive-date = April 23, 2017|url-status = live|archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20170423063409/https://www.racgp.org.au/Education/Curriculum/Sex,-sexuality,-gender-diversity-and-health|author-link = Royal Australian College of General Practitioners}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Dr Catherine Yelland, President of the [[Royal Australasian College of Physicians]], stated in a press release issued by the College that "[g]ay conversion therapy is unethical, harmful and not supported by medical evidence."&lt;ref name = Hack&gt;{{cite news|title = 'Ludicrous practice' of gay conversion therapy to be scrutinised|date = September 21, 2017|first = Shalailah|last = Medhora|url = http://www.abc.net.au/triplej/programs/hack/gay-conversion-therapy-to-be/8969414|work = [[Hack (radio program)|Hack]], [[Triple J]]|publisher = [[Australian Broadcasting Corporation]]|accessdate = March 17, 2018|quote = Medical groups like the Australian Medical Association and the Royal Australasian College of Physicians have slammed gay conversion therapy.|url-status = live|archive-date = September 22, 2017|archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20170922233942/http://www.abc.net.au/triplej/programs/hack/gay-conversion-therapy-to-be/8969414}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = RACP&gt;{{cite press release|last1 = Bell|first1 = Melissah|first2 = Genevieve|last2 = Costiga|date = September 18, 2017|title = Doctors criticise gay conversion therapy remarks in marriage equality debate|url = https://www.racp.edu.au/docs/default-source/default-document-library/doctors-criticise-gay-conversion-therapy-remarks-in-marriage-equality-debate.pdf|publisher = [[Royal Australasian College of Physicians]] jointly with the [[Royal Australian and New Zealand College of Psychiatrists]]|archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20180317113837/https://www.racp.edu.au/docs/default-source/default-document-library/doctors-criticise-gay-conversion-therapy-remarks-in-marriage-equality-debate.pdf|archive-date = March 17, 2018|url-status = live|accessdate = March 17, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*The [[Royal Australian and New Zealand College of Psychiatrists]]&lt;ref name = RANZCP1&gt;{{cite web|author = Committee for Therapeutic Interventions and Evidence-Based Practice, Royal Australian and New Zealand College of Psychiatrists|authorlink = Royal Australian and New Zealand College of Psychiatrists|date = June 2015|accessdate = March 17, 2018|title = Position Statement 60 – Sexual orientation change efforts|url = https://www.ranzcp.org/Files/Resources/College_Statements/Position_Statements/PS-60-PS-Sexual-Orientation-Change-Efforts-(Ju-(1).aspx|archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20180117011907/https://www.ranzcp.org/Files/Resources/College_Statements/Position_Statements/PS-60-PS-Sexual-Orientation-Change-Efforts-(Ju-(1).aspx|publisher = [[Royal Australian and New Zealand College of Psychiatrists]]|url-status = live|archive-date = January 17, 2018|quote = The harm such therapies can cause to individuals, the contribution they make to the misrepresentation of homosexuality as a mental disorder, and the prejudice and discrimination that can flourish through the use of such therapies has led all major medical organisations to oppose the use of sexual orientation change efforts.&lt;br /&gt;'''Recommendations'''&lt;br /&gt;* The RANZCP does not support the use of sexual orientation change efforts of any kind&lt;br /&gt;* Mental health workers must avoid misrepresenting the efficacy of sexual orientation change efforts when providing assistance to people distressed by their own or others' sexual orientation&lt;br /&gt;* Mental health workers should assist people distressed by their sexual orientation by care and treatment approaches that involve acceptance, support, and identity exploration. These should aim to reduce the stigma associated with homosexuality and respect the person’s religious beliefs.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = RANZCP2&gt;{{cite web|author = Board, Royal Australian and New Zealand College of Psychiatrists|authorlink = Royal Australian and New Zealand College of Psychiatrists|publisher = [[Royal Australian and New Zealand College of Psychiatrists]]|date = March 2016|title = Position Statement 83 – Recognising and addressing the mental health needs of people identifying as LGBTI|accessdate = March 17, 2018|url = https://www.ranzcp.org/Files/Resources/College_Statements/Position_Statements/PS-83-LGBTI-mental-health-2016.aspx|archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20171001074818/https://www.ranzcp.org/Files/Resources/College_Statements/Position_Statements/PS-83-LGBTI-mental-health-2016.aspx|url-status = live|archive-date = October 1, 2017|quote = [S]exual orientation change efforts, or often non-consensual therapies intended to change the sexual orientation of a person, are now broadly understood to be harmful and unethical}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=====Other health organizations=====
* The Austrian Society for Public Health&lt;ref&gt;https://oeph.at/sites/default/public/files/Statements/Gemeinsame%20Stellungnahme%20der%20%C3%96GPH_Kompetenzgruppen_FINAL.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[Canadian Psychological Association]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=CPA Policy Statement on Conversion/Reparative Therapy for Sexual Orientation|url=http://www.cpa.ca/docs/File/Position/SOGII%20Policy%20Statement%20-%20LGB%20Conversion%20Therapy%20FINALAPPROVED2015.pdf|website=cpa.ca|publisher=Canadian Psychological Association|date=2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[Public Health Agency of Canada]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Questions and Answers: Sexual Orientation in Schools – What do we know?|url=https://www.canada.ca/en/public-health/services/infectious-diseases/sexual-health-sexually-transmitted-infections/reports-publications/questions-answers-schools/questions-answers-sexual-schools.html|website=canada.ca|publisher=Government of Canada|quote=A student's sexual orientation is not a 'lifestyle' choice and under no circumstances should a student be counselled to change or attempt to 'repair' their sexual orientation. These kinds of 'conversion' or 'reparative' therapies have been criticized and discouraged by the American Psychological Association and by many teacher associations across Canada. Clinical research has demonstrated that these approaches are largely ineffective, ignore the impact of social stigmatization on mental health, and in some cases, can be extremely dangerous, particularly for vulnerable youth. Instead of attempting to change a student's sexual orientation, educators, administrators, and health care professionals should focus on helping the youth and their family to develop active coping mechanisms to address issues related to internalized homophobia, stigma, prejudice and discrimination.|date=2014-03-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [http://legeforeningen.no/norskpsykiatri Norwegian Psychiatric Association]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal| last = Kjær| first = Reider| year = 2003| title = Look to Norway? Gay Issues and Mental Health Across the Atlantic Ocean| journal = Journal of Gay &amp; Lesbian Psychotherapy| volume = 7| issue = 1/2| pages = 55–73| doi = 10.1300/J236v07n01_05|quote=In October 2000, the General Assembly [of the Norwegian Psychiatric Association] voted overwhelmingly (about 90%) in favor of the following statement ... Homosexuality is no disorder or illness, and can therefore not be subject to treatment. A 'treatment' with the only aim of changing sexual orientation from homosexual to heterosexual must be regarded as ethical malpractice, and has no place in the health system.}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The Chilean College of Psychologists&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Posición del Colegio de Psicólogos de Chile acerca de las terapias reparativas para curar la homosexualidad |url=http://colegiopsicologos.cl/wp-content/uploads/2018/02/Referencias-Tecnicas-Terapias-Reparativas-Revision-final-04-Junio-2015.pdf |publisher=Colegio de Psicólogos de Chile |accessdate=27 September 2018 |language=es}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The Brazilian Federal Council of Psychology&lt;ref name="brazil"/&gt;
* The [[Indian Psychiatric Society]]&lt;ref name="india"/&gt;
* The Lebanese Psychiatric Society&lt;ref name="lebanon"/&gt;
* The South African Society of Psychiatrists&lt;ref name="south africa"/&gt;
* The Spanish Psychological Association&lt;ref name="spain"/&gt;
* The [[Israel Medical Association]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.haaretz.com/israel-news/israeli-doctors-ban-conversion-therapy-for-gay-people-1.6828815|title=Israeli Doctors Ban 'Conversion Therapy' for Gay People|work=Haaretz|date=10 January 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[Psychological Society of Ireland]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.thejournal.ie/psi-condemn-conversion-therapy-4574903-Apr2019/|title='No place in any modern society': Psychologists condemn LGBT conversion therapies|work=TheJournal.ie|date=3 April 2019|access-date=5 April 2019|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190404153502/https://www.thejournal.ie/psi-condemn-conversion-therapy-4574903-Apr2019/|archive-date=4 April 2019|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[Hong Kong College of Psychiatrists]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.starobserver.com.au/news/2012/01/19/gay-not-disorder/69763|title=News on Announcement from Hong Kong College of Psychiatrists|date=2012-01-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The Hong Kong Psychological Society&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.hkps.org.hk/padmin/upload/wpage1_26download2_Position%20Paper%20on%20LGB.pdf |title=Position Paper for Psychologists Working with Lesbians, Gays, and Bisexual (LGB) Individuals |access-date=2019-07-23 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140106185246/http://www.hkps.org.hk/padmin/upload/wpage1_26download2_Position%20Paper%20on%20LGB.pdf |archive-date=2014-01-06 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The Hong Kong Association of Doctors in Clinical Psychology

====APA taskforce study====

The American Psychological Association undertook a study of the peer-reviewed literature in the area of [[sexual orientation change efforts]] (SOCE) and found a myriad of issues with the procedures used in conducting the research. The taskforce did find that some participants experienced a lessening of same sex attraction and arousal, but that these instances were "rare" and "uncommon". The taskforce concluded that, "given the limited amount of methodically sound research, claims that recent SOCE is effective are not supported".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.apa.org/pi/lgbt/resources/therapeutic-response.pdf Appropriate Therapeutic Responses to Sexual Orientation] Page 2&lt;/ref&gt; Two issues with SOCE claims are that conversion therapists falsely assume that homosexuality is a mental disorder and that their research focuses almost exclusively on gay men and rarely includes lesbians.&lt;ref name="Haldeman1" /&gt;&lt;ref name="APA"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Bright" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Ucdavis" /&gt;&lt;ref name="HRC"&gt;{{cite web|title=Policy and Position Statements on Conversion Therapy|url=http://www.hrc.org/resources/policy-and-position-statements-on-conversion-therapy|website=Human Rights Campaign|publisher=Human Rights Campaign|accessdate=12 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Self-determination===

The [[American Psychological Association]]'s code of conduct states that "Psychologists respect the dignity and worth of all people, and the rights of individuals to privacy, confidentiality, and self-determination", but also that "Psychologists are aware that special safeguards may be necessary to protect the rights and welfare of persons or communities whose vulnerabilities impair autonomous decision making."&lt;ref name="apacode"&gt;{{cite web
|url = http://www.apa.org/ethics/code2002.html#principle_e
|archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20070807183620/http://www.apa.org/ethics/code2002.html
|archivedate=August 7, 2007 |title = Ethical Principles of Psychologists and Code of Conduct
|accessdate = 2007-08-28
|date = 2003-06-01
|publisher = American Psychological Association
}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[American Counseling Association]] says that "it is of primary importance to respect a client's autonomy to request a referral for a service not offered by a counselor".&lt;ref name="ACA News"&gt;{{citation |url=http://www.counseling.org/PressRoom/NewsReleases.aspx?AGuid=b68aba97-2f08-40c2-a400-0630765f72f4 |last1=Whitman |first1=Joy S. |last2=Glosoff |first2=Harriet L. |last3=Kocet |first3=Michael M. |last4=Tarvydas |first4=Vilia |title=Ethical issues related to conversion or reparative therapy |accessdate=2007-08-28 |date=2006-05-22 |publisher=American Counseling Association |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070927030302/http://www.counseling.org/PressRoom/NewsReleases.aspx?AGuid=b68aba97-2f08-40c2-a400-0630765f72f4 |archivedate=2007-09-27 }}&lt;/ref&gt; They said that no one should be forced to attempt to change their sexual orientation against their will, including children being forced by their parents.&lt;ref name=apa1997&gt;{{Citation |url=http://www.apa.org/pi/sexual.html |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090324034818/http://www.apa.org/pi/sexual.html |archivedate=2009-03-24 |title=Resolution on Appropriate Therapeutic Responses to Sexual Orientation |accessdate=2007-08-28 |date=1997-08-14 |publisher=American Psychological Association}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Supporters of SOCE focus on patient self-determination when discussing whether therapy should be available. Mark Yarhouse, of [[Pat Robertson]]'s [[Regent University]], wrote that "psychologists have an ethical responsibility to allow individuals to pursue treatment aimed at curbing experiences of same-sex attraction or modifying same-sex behaviors, not only because it affirms the client's rights to dignity, autonomy, and agency, as persons presumed capable of freely choosing among treatment modalities and behavior, but also because it demonstrates regard for diversity".&lt;ref name=Right2Choose&gt;{{Citation
 | doi = 10.1037/h0087753
 | last = Yarhouse
 | first = Mark
 |date=Summer 1998
 | title = When Clients Seek Treatment for Same-Sex Attractions: Ethical Issues in the "Right to Choose" Debate
 | journal = Psychotherapy: Theory, Research, Practice, Training
 | volume = 35
 | issue = 2
 | pages = 248–259
 | postscript = .
 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Yarhouse and Throckmorton, of the private Christian school [[Grove City College]], argue that the procedure should be available out of respect for a patient's values system and because they find evidence that it can be effective.&lt;ref name="EthicalIssues"&gt;{{Harvnb|Yarhouse|Throckmorton|2002|pp=66–75}}&lt;/ref&gt; Haldeman similarly argues for a client's right to access to therapy if requested from a [[Informed consent|fully informed]] position: "For some, religious identity is so important that it is more realistic to consider changing sexual orientation than abandoning one's religion of origin ... and if there are those who seek to resolve the conflict between sexual orientation and spirituality with conversion therapy, they must not be discouraged."&lt;ref name="haldeman2"/&gt;

In response to Yarhouse's paper, Jack Drescher argued that "any putative ethical obligation to refer a patient for reparative therapy is outweighed by a stronger ethical obligation to keep patients away from mental health practitioners who engage in questionable clinical practices".&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Drescher|2001}}&lt;/ref&gt; Chuck Bright wrote that refusing to endorse a procedure that "has been deemed unethical and potentially harmful by most medical and nearly every professional psychotherapy regulating body cannot be justifiably identified as prohibiting client self-determination".&lt;ref name="Bright" /&gt; Some commentators, recommending a hard stand against the practice, have found therapy inconsistent with a psychologist's ethical duties because "it is more ethical to let a client continue to struggle honestly with her or his identity than to collude, even peripherally, with a practice that is discriminatory, oppressive, and ultimately ineffective in its own stated ends".&lt;ref name=PurpleMenace&gt;{{Citation
 | last = Tozer
 | first = Erinn E.
 | author2 = McClanahan, Mary K.
 | year = 1999
 | title = Treating the Purple Menace: Ethical Considerations of Conversion Therapy and Affirmative Alternatives
 | journal = The Counseling Psychologist
 | volume = 27
 | issue = 5
 | pages = 722–742
 | doi = 10.1177/0011000099275006
 | postscript = .
 }}&lt;/ref&gt; They argue that clients who request it do so out of social pressure and internalized homophobia, pointing to evidence that rates of depression, anxiety, alcohol and drug abuse and suicidal feelings are roughly doubled in those who undergo therapy.&lt;ref name="ShidloandSchroeder2002a"/&gt;

Haldeman argues that, due to concern for people whose "spiritual or religious concerns" may assume priority over their sexual orientation, mental health organizations do not ban conversion therapy outright.&lt;ref name="haldeman2"/&gt;

===Ethics guidelines===
In 1998, the [[American Psychiatric Association]] issued a statement opposing any treatment which is based upon the assumption that homosexuality is a mental disorder or that a person should change their orientation, but did not have a formal position on other treatments that attempt to change a person's sexual orientation. In 2000, they augmented that statement by saying that as a general principle, a therapist should not determine the goal of treatment, but recommends that ethical practitioners refrain from attempts to change clients' sexual orientation until more research is available.&lt;ref name="Psych" /&gt;

The [[American Counseling Association]] has stated that they do not condone any training to educate and prepare a counselor to practice conversion therapy. Counselors who do offer training in conversion therapy must inform students that the techniques are unproven. They suggest counselors do not refer clients to a conversion therapist or to proceed cautiously once they know the counselor fully informs clients of the unproven nature of the treatment and the potential risks. However, "it is of primary importance to respect a client's autonomy to request a referral for a service not offered by a counselor". A counselor performing conversion therapy must provide complete information about the treatment, offer referrals to gay-affirmative counselors, discuss the right of clients, understand the client's request within a cultural context, and only practice within their level of expertise.&lt;ref name="ACA News"/&gt;

[[NARTH]] stated in 2012 that refusing to offer therapy aimed at change to a client who requests it, and telling them that their only option is to claim a gay identity, could also be considered ethically unacceptable.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://narth.com/2012/01/narth-statement-on-sexual-orientation-change |title=Statement on Sexual Orientation Change |publisher=NARTH |accessdate=2012-07-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2012 the [[British Psychological Society]] issued a position statement opposing any treatments that are based on an assumption that non-heterosexual orientations are pathological.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://www.bps.org.uk/system/files/images/therapies_attempting_to_change_sexual_orientation.pdf|title = Position Statement: Therapies Attempting to Change Sexual Orientation|date = |accessdate = |website = |publisher = |last = British Psychological Society}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A 2013 article by the Committee on Adolescence of the [[American Academy of Pediatrics]] stated "Referral for 'conversion' or 'reparative therapy' is never indicated; therapy is not effective and may be harmful to LGBTQ individuals by increasing internalized stigma, distress, and depression."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Office-Based Care for Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, Transgender, and Questioning Youth|journal=Pediatrics|volume=132|issue=1|year=2013|pages=198–203|issn=0031-4005|doi=10.1542/peds.2013-1282|pmid=23796746|author1=Committee On Adolescence}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The Health of Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, and Transgender People: Building a Foundation for Better Understanding|date=March 31, 2011|url=http://books.nap.edu/openbook.php?record_id=13128&amp;page=146|page=146|publisher=[[Institute of Medicine]]/[[National Academies Press]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2014, the [[American Association of Christian Counselors]] amended its code of ethics to eliminate the promotion of conversion therapy for homosexuals and encouraged them to be [[celibacy|celibate]] instead.&lt;ref name="religionnews1"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.religionnews.com/2014/08/04/gay-christian-celibate-changing-face-homosexuality-debate/ |title=Gay, Christian and ... celibate: The changing face of the homosexuality debate - Religion News Service |publisher=Religionnews.com |date= |accessdate=2015-07-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; An article in the [[American Medical Association]]'s Journal of Ethics argues that if a pediatrician learns that parents of a 12-year-old patient seek conversion therapy, the pediatrician can advise against "the ineffective and potentially harmful intervention" while being [[Cultural competence in health care|culturally sensitive]] of their religious objections to homosexuality. The authors argue that the doctor's [[medical ethics]] means they should place the interests of the patient above the cultural sensitivities of the parents, and [[Confidentiality#Medical confidentiality|confidentially]] counsel the patient about resources for LGBT youth facing bullying, and advise the parents about resources for parents of LGBT children.&lt;ref name="pmid25397646"&gt;{{cite journal|vauthors=Zachariah P, Blaschke GS, Weddle M | title=A request for "conversion therapy". | journal=Virtual Mentor | year= 2014 | volume= 16 | issue= 11 | pages= 877–83 | pmid=25397646 | doi=10.1001/virtualmentor.2014.16.11.ecas2-1411 | pmc= }}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2014, major therapy professional bodies in the United Kingdom issued a joint consensus statement opposing conversion therapy. Professional bodies supporting the statement included the [[United Kingdom Council for Psychotherapy|UK Council for Psychotherapy]], the [[British Psychoanalytic Council]], the [[Royal College of Psychiatrists]], the [[British Association for Counselling and Psychotherapy]], the [[British Psychological Society]] and the National Counselling Society.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url =http://www.psychotherapy.org.uk/UKCP_Documents/policy/Conversion%20therapy.pdf|title =Conversion therapy: a consensus statement|url-status =dead|archiveurl =https://web.archive.org/web/20160209095649/http://www.psychotherapy.org.uk/UKCP_Documents/policy/Conversion%20therapy.pdf|archivedate =2016-02-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2015, with support of the UK Government's [[Department of Health (United Kingdom)|Department of Health]], a wide range of UK organisations signed a memorandum of understanding (MoU) setting out an agreed framework for activities by parties concerned to help address the issues raised by the practice of conversion therapy in the UK. In addition to many of the professional bodies that previously issued the consensus statement, signatories included the UK Association of Christian Counsellors, the [[Royal College of General Practitioners]], [[NHS England]] and [[NHS Scotland]]. The signatory organisations recognised a shared commitment to protecting the public from the risks of conversion therapy. They committed to raise awareness among healthcare professionals and psychological therapists of ethical issues involved in conversion therapy and to provide training to enable therapists to support clients in distress in an appropriate way.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url =http://www.psychotherapy.org.uk/UKCP_Documents/policy/MoU-conversiontherapy.pdf|title =Memorandum of Understanding on conversion therapy in the UK|url-status =dead|archiveurl =https://web.archive.org/web/20150123004221/http://www.psychotherapy.org.uk/UKCP_Documents/policy/MoU-conversiontherapy.pdf|archivedate =2015-01-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===International medical views===
{{See also|LGBT rights in the United Kingdom}}
The [[World Health Organization]]'s [[ICD-10]], which along with the [[Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders|DSM-IV]] is widely used internationally, states that "sexual orientation by itself is not to be regarded as a disorder". It lists [[ego-dystonic sexual orientation]] as a disorder instead, which it defines as occurring where "the gender identity or sexual preference (heterosexual, homosexual, bisexual, or prepubertal) is not in doubt, but the individual wishes it were different because of associated psychological and behavioural disorders, and may seek treatment in order to change it".&lt;ref name="icd"&gt;{{citation |url=http://www.who.int/classifications/apps/icd/icd10online/?gf60.htm+f661 |title=ICD-10, Chapter V: Mental and behavioural disorders: Disorders of adult personality and behaviour |year=2007 |accessdate=2007-08-28 |publisher=World Health Organization}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2012, the [[Pan American Health Organization]] (the North and South American branch of the World Health Organization) released a statement cautioning against services that purport to "cure" people with non-heterosexual sexual orientations as they lack medical justification and represent a serious threat to the health and well-being of affected people, and noted that the global scientific and professional consensus is that homosexuality is a normal and natural variation of [[human sexuality]] and cannot be regarded as a pathological condition. The Pan American Health Organization further called on governments, academic institutions, professional associations and the media to expose these practices and to promote respect for diversity. The World Health Organization affiliate further noted that gay minors have sometimes been forced to attend these "therapies" involuntarily, being deprived of their liberty and sometimes kept in isolation for several months, and that these findings were reported by several [[United Nations]] bodies. Additionally, the Pan American Health Organization recommended that such practices be denounced and subject to sanctions and penalties under national legislation, as they constitute a violation of the ethical principles of health care and violate [[human rights]] that are protected by international and regional agreements.&lt;ref name=PAHO&gt;{{cite web |title="Therapies" to change sexual orientation lack medical justification and threaten health |url=http://new.paho.org/hq/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=6803&amp;Itemid=1926 |publisher=Pan American Health Organization |accessdate=May 26, 2012 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120523040848/http://new.paho.org/hq/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=6803&amp;Itemid=1926 |archivedate=May 23, 2012 }} archived here .&lt;/ref&gt;

The development of theoretical models of sexual orientation in countries outside the United States that have established mental health professions often follows the history within the U.S. (although often at a slower pace), shifting from pathological to non-pathological conceptions of homosexuality.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |title=Special Issue on the Mental Health Professions and Homosexuality |year=2003 |journal=Journal of Gay &amp; Lesbian Psychotherapy |volume=7 |issue=1/2 }}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Request quotation|date=November 2010}}

====Australia====
Major medical and psychological bodies in Australia uniformly prohibit conversion therapy practices,&lt;ref name = Hack /&gt;&lt;ref name = NationalLGBTIHealthAlliance /&gt; with published statements having come from peak bodies representing psychologists,&lt;ref name = AustPsychSocPosSt /&gt; psychiatrists,&lt;ref name = RANZCP1 /&gt;&lt;ref name = RANZCP2 /&gt; and medical practitioners.&lt;ref name = AMA1 /&gt;&lt;ref name = AMA2 /&gt; In a statement issued jointly with the College of Psychiatrists,&lt;ref name = RACP /&gt; Royal Australasian College of Physicians President Catherine Yelland summarised the view of the Australian medical community: "[g]ay conversion therapy is unethical, harmful and not supported by medical evidence."&lt;ref name = Hack /&gt; The approaches taken by peak medical bodies is exemplified by the 2015 Australian Psychological Society Position Statement, which declares (emphasis in original) that the:
:"'''APS strongly opposes any approach to psychological practice or research that treats lesbians, gay men, and bisexual people as disordered. The APS also strongly opposes any approach to psychological practice or research that attempts to change an individual's sexual orientation.'''"&lt;ref name = AustPsychSocPosSt /&gt;
The Position Statement supports this position by reference to the Society's Code of Ethics, which were adopted in 2007&lt;ref name = AustPsychSocCoE&gt;{{cite web|author = Australian Psychological Society|title = APS Code of Ethics|publisher = [[Australian Psychological Society]]|date = September 27, 2007|accessdate = March 17, 2018|quote = The Australian Psychological Society Limited (the Society) adopted this Code of Ethics (the Code) at its Forty-First Annual General Meeting held on 27 September 2007. ... Reprinted October 2016|url = https://www.psychology.org.au/getmedia/67370669-e701-4b1d-9ef9-c5b8e0011da8/Code-of-Ethics-APS.pdf|url-status = live|archive-date = March 12, 2018|archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20180312020600/https://www.psychology.org.au/getmedia/67370669-e701-4b1d-9ef9-c5b8e0011da8/Code-of-Ethics-APS.pdf|author-link = Australian Psychological Society}}&lt;/ref&gt; and mandated as the Code of Ethics for Australian psychologists in 2010 by the [[Psychology Board of Australia]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title = Codes, guidelines and policies|publisher = [[Psychology Board of Australia]]|accessdate = March 17, 2018|date = January 29, 2018|url = http://www.psychologyboard.gov.au/Standards-and-Guidelines/Codes-Guidelines-Policies.aspx|url-status = live|archive-date = March 13, 2018|archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20180313133259/http://www.psychologyboard.gov.au/Standards-and-Guidelines/Codes-Guidelines-Policies.aspx|quote = The Board has adopted the Australian Psychological Society Code of Ethics for the profession.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title = APS Code of Ethics|publisher = [[Australian Psychological Society]]|accessdate = March 17, 2018|year = 2018|url = https://www.psychology.org.au/About-Us/What-we-do/ethics-and-practice-standards/APS-Code-of-Ethics|quote = In 2010 the Psychology Board of Australia adopted the APS Code of Ethics for the profession.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Under the Code, psychologists are required to "avoid discriminating unfairly against people on the basis of age, religion, sexuality, ethnicity, gender, disability, or any other basis proscribed by law" and mandates that they
:"(a) communicate respect for other people through their actions and language;
:(b) do not behave in a manner that, having regard to the context, may reasonably be perceived as coercive or demeaning;
:(c) respect the legal rights and moral rights of others; and
:(d) do not denigrate the character of people by engaging in conduct that demeans them as persons, or defames, or harasses them."&lt;ref name = AustPsychSocCoE /&gt;
The Position Statement explicitly states that this ethical "requirement not to discriminate and to respect clients' moral rights does not equate to a justification to treat homosexuality or bisexuality as a disorder requiring treatment,"&lt;ref name = AustPsychSocPosSt /&gt; relying on the Code of Ethics' section on propriety: "psychologists only provide psychological services within the boundaries of their professional competence [which] includes but is not restricted to ... basing their service on established knowledge of the discipline and profession of psychology".&lt;ref name = AustPsychSocCoE /&gt; Regarding the knowledge base relating to conversion therapy, the statement is unequivocal (emphasis in original):
:"'''There is no peer-reviewed empirical psychological research objectively documenting the ability to 'change' an individual's sexual orientation. Furthermore, there is no peer-reviewed empirical psychological research demonstrating that homosexuality or bisexuality constitutes a disorder.''' In addition to the lack of empirical support for the claim that sexual orientation can be changed, empirical evidence indicates that attempts at changing sexual orientation can be harmful."&lt;ref name = AustPsychSocPosSt /&gt;
The Society's position concludes by noting that it "is, of course, appropriate for psychologists to provide clinical services to clients who experience distress in regards to their sexual orientation ... [but this practice] should seek to understand ''the reasons for'' distress and how it may be alleviated. Evidence-based strategies to alleviate distress do not include attempts at changing sexual orientation, but could include challenging negative stereotypes, seeking social support, and self-acceptance, among others."&lt;ref name = AustPsychSocPosSt /&gt;

The [[Government of Victoria]] announced in 2016 that it would be legislating to ban all LGBTQI conversion therapy.&lt;ref name = Moret1 /&gt;&lt;ref name = Moret2&gt;{{cite news|url = http://gaynewsnetwork.com.au/news/gay-conversion-therapy-to-be-banned-in-victoria-20303.html|work = [[SX News]]|title = Gay conversion therapy to be banned in Victoria|date = February 9, 2016|first = Glen|last = Morét|accessdate = February 12, 2016|archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20160825194841/http://gaynewsnetwork.com.au/news/gay-conversion-therapy-to-be-banned-in-victoria-20303.html|url-status = dead|archive-date = August 25, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url = http://www.abc.net.au/news/2016-02-09/government-to-ban-gay-conversion-therapy-health-providers/7151016|title = Gay conversion therapy, fake doctors to be banned in Victoria|date = February 9, 2016|work = [[ABC News (Australia)|ABC News]]|accessdate = July 13, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; The new law began operating in February 2017&lt;ref name = VicLaw&gt;{{cite Legislation AU|Vic|num_act|hca201622o2016227|Health Complaints Act}}&lt;/ref&gt; and allows the Health Complaints Commissioner to act against any health professional engaged in practices that are "found to be making false claims and to be acting in a manner that puts people's physical, mental or psychological health, safety or welfare at risk"—and in a world first, this law applies to conversion therapy for adults as well as for minors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title = Washington state to ban 'gay conversion' therapy|date = March 5, 2018|accessdate = March 17, 2018|first = Evan|last = Young|work = [[SBS News]]|url = https://www.sbs.com.au/news/washington-state-to-ban-gay-conversion-therapy}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title = Will the new health watchdog stop gay conversion therapy?|url = http://www.abc.net.au/triplej/programs/hack/will-the-new-health-watchdog-stop-gay-conversion-therapy/8235942|date = February 2, 2017|work = [[Hack (radio program)|Hack]], [[Triple J]]|publisher = [[Australian Broadcasting Corporation]]|accessdate = July 13, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Western Australia]] and the [[Australian Capital Territory]] announced in September 2017 that they are investigating similar laws.&lt;ref name = Hack /&gt; Advocates for a ban on conversion therapy argued that reviews need to go beyond the practices of health professionals and into activities of religious groups&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title = 'I was suicidal every day': Gay conversion Australia's secret shame|first = Emma|last = Reynolds|date = February 2, 2017|accessdate = March 17, 2018|website = [[news.com.au]]|publisher = [[News Corp Australia]]|url = http://www.news.com.au/lifestyle/relationships/sex/i-was-suicidal-every-day-gay-conversion-australias-secret-shame/news-story/23873ec688b6ac2bdbff846843ebab00}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the unregulated (non-medical) counselling sector.&lt;ref name = Hack /&gt;

A [[Fairfax Media]] investigation in 2018 reported that "across Australia, organisations who believe that LGBTI people can or should change are hard at work. Conversion practices are hidden in evangelical churches and ministries, taking the form of exorcisms, prayer groups or counselling disguised as pastoral care. They're also present in some religious schools or practised in the private offices of health professionals. They're pushed out through a thriving network of courses and mentors in the borderless world of cyberspace, cloaked in the terminology of 'self improvement' or 'spiritual healing.'"&lt;ref name = Farrah1&gt;{{cite news|title = 'I am profoundly unsettled': inside the hidden world of gay conversion therapy|first = Farrah|last = Tomazin|url = https://www.theage.com.au/national/i-am-profoundly-unsettled-inside-the-hidden-world-of-gay-conversion-therapy-20180227-p4z1xn.html|date = March 9, 2018|accessdate = March 17, 2018|newspaper = [[The Age]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; A study of [[Pentecostalism in Australia|Pentecostal-Charismatic Churches]] found that LGBTI parishioners were faced with four options: remain closeted, come out but commit to remaining celibate, undergo conversion therapy, or leave the church... the majority took the last option, though typically only after "agonising attempts to reconcile their faith and their sexuality."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title = Impossible Subjects: LGBTIQ Experiences in Australian Pentecostal-Charismatic Churches|first = Mark A. C.|last = Jennings|journal = Religions|year = 2018|volume = 9|issue = 2|at = article 53|doi = 10.3390/rel9020053|doi-access = free}}&lt;/ref&gt; The study provides corroboration that conversion therapy remains practiced within religious communities.

Following the Fairfax investigation, [[Premier of Victoria|Victorian Premier]] [[Daniel Andrews]] called on [[Prime Minister of Australia|Prime Minister]] [[Malcolm Turnbull]] to support outlawing conversion therapy as part of the national mental health strategy. Federal [[Minister for Health (Australia)|Health Minister]] [[Greg Hunt]] declared that the issue is one for the states as no Commonwealth funding goes to sexual orientation change efforts—though "gay conversion ideology has been quietly pushed in schools as part of the [[National School Chaplaincy Programme|federal government's chaplaincy program]]."&lt;ref name="Farrah2"&gt;{{cite news|url = https://www.theage.com.au/politics/victoria/victoria-urges-turnbull-to-help-states-crack-down-on-gay-conversion-20180316-p4z4o4.html|title = Victoria urges Turnbull to help states crack down on gay 'conversion'|first = Farrah|last = Tomazin|newspaper = [[The Age]]|date = March 16, 2018|accessdate = March 17, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; The report noted that the Victorian law applies only to people offering health services&lt;ref name="Farrah1" /&gt; and so does not catch religious groups and charities "who say they are helping same-sex attracted people to live in accordance with their faith."&lt;ref name="Farrah2" /&gt;

Chris, a survivor of conversion therapy, joined Andrews in calling for the Federal Government to outlaw conversion therapy, declaring that "praying the gay away nearly killed me."&lt;ref name="PinkNews"&gt;{{cite news|title = Man launches petition to put an end to gay 'cure' therapy: 'praying the gay away nearly killed me'|first = Meka|last = Beresford|date = March 16, 2018|accessdate = March 17, 2018|work = [[PinkNews]]|url = https://www.pinknews.co.uk/2018/03/16/man-launches-petition-to-put-an-end-to-gay-cure-therapy-praying-the-gay-away-nearly-killed-me/}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="QNews"&gt;{{cite news|title = Call For Australian Government To Ban Dangerous 'Gay Conversion' Therapy|first = Jordan|last = Hirst|work = [[QNews Magazine]]|date = March 13, 2018|accessdate = March 17, 2018|url = https://www.qnews.com.au/call-for-australian-government-to-ban-dangerous-gay-conversion-therapy/}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.smh.com.au/politics/federal/greg-hunt-must-condemn-gay-conversion-therapy-not-protect-it-20180418-p4zabx.html|title=Greg Hunt must condemn gay conversion therapy, not protect it|last=Csabs|first=Chris|date=2018-04-18|website=The Sydney Morning Herald|language=en|access-date=2018-04-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; He established a petition calling on Turnbull and Hunt to act to outlaw conversion therapy, declaring: "I prayed to God asking him to either heal me, or kill me. I was so depressed, I wanted to die."&lt;ref name="QNews" /&gt; In April 2018, Shadow Health Minister Catherine King wrote a response to the petition: "I'm writing to let you know that Labor stands with you, Chris Csabs and the medical experts in opposing gay conversion therapy...two Turnbull Government ministers—the Acting Prime Minister and the Health Minister—have now failed to condemn the practice when given the chance."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.starobserver.com.au/news/national-news/shadow-health-minister-gay-conversion/168189|title=Shadow health minister calls out the Liberal party over gay 'conversion' therapy - Star Observer|website=www.starobserver.com.au|language=en-US|access-date=2018-04-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; Shortly after Catherine King's response, Health Minister for Queensland Dr Steven Miles voiced his concerns over the practise and stated that the Federal Health Minister should be working with the states to enact change.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.dailytelegraph.com.au/news/national/queensland-could-follow-victorias-lead-and-become-the-second-jurisdiction-in-australia-to-ban-gay-conversion-therapy/video/d72a6352b58d9fb7a17e74cfe741adca|title=Queensland could join Victoria in banning gay conversion therapy {{!}} Daily Telegraph|language=en|access-date=2018-04-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; In May 2018, the Victorian Health Minister [[Jill Hennessy (politician)|Jill Hennessy]] called for an inquiry into gay conversion therapies. In an unprecedented move, the state government indicated it would not only investigate health professionals but will focus on religious and faith-based ministries propagating Gay Conversion ideologies.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.sbs.com.au/news/vic-crackdown-on-gay-conversion-therapy|title=Vic crackdown on 'gay conversion therapy'|work=SBS News|access-date=2018-05-22|language=en-GB}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.theage.com.au/politics/victoria/victoria-urges-turnbull-to-help-states-crack-down-on-gay-conversion-20180316-p4z4o4.html|title=Victoria urges Turnbull to help states crack down on gay 'conversion'|last=Tomazin|first=Farrah|date=2018-03-16|website=The Age|language=en|access-date=2018-05-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; The following day, Health Minister for the Australian Capital Territory Meegan Fitzharris followed Catherine King's lead by also responding to the petition, stating that, "The ACT government will ban gay conversion therapy. It is abhorrent and completely inconsistent with the inclusive values of Canberrans."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://amp.canberratimes.com.au/politics/act/chris-underwent-gay-conversion-therapy-in-a-canberra-church-now-the-act-will-ban-it-20180516-p4zflj.html|title=Chris underwent gay conversion therapy in a Canberra church. Now, the ACT will ban it|website=amp.canberratimes.com.au|language=en|access-date=2018-05-23|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180518033559/https://amp.canberratimes.com.au/politics/act/chris-underwent-gay-conversion-therapy-in-a-canberra-church-now-the-act-will-ban-it-20180516-p4zflj.html|archive-date=2018-05-18|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Legal views===
{{For|the legal status of conversion therapy and other sexual orientation change efforts|Sexual orientation change efforts#Legal status}}
On June 25, 2015, a New Jersey jury found the Jewish conversion therapy organization JONAH guilty of consumer fraud in the case [[Ferguson v. JONAH|Ferguson v JONAH]] for promising to be able to change its clients' sexual urges and determined its commercial practices to be unconscionable.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Livio|first1=Susan K.|title=Group claiming to turn gay men straight committed consumer fraud, N.J. jury says|url=http://www.nj.com/politics/index.ssf/2015/06/gay_conversion_therapy_fraud_trial_verdict.html|website=NJ.com True Jersey|publisher=New Jersey On-Line LLC|accessdate=23 September 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In a 1997 U.S. case, the [[Ninth Circuit]] addressed conversion therapy in the context of an asylum application. A Russian citizen "had been apprehended by the Russian militia, registered at a clinic as a 'suspected lesbian', and forced to undergo treatment for lesbianism, such as 'sedative drugs' and hypnosis. ... The Ninth Circuit held that the conversion treatments to which Pitcherskaia had been subjected constituted mental and physical torture." The court rejected the argument that the treatments to which Pitcherskaia had been subjected did not constitute persecution because they had been intended to help her, not harm her, and stated "human rights laws cannot be sidestepped by simply couching actions that torture mentally or physically in benevolent terms such as 'curing' or 'treating' the victims".&lt;ref name="Gans"&gt;{{citation |last=Gans |first=Laura A. |title=Inverts, Perverts, and Converts: Sexual Orientation Conversion Therapy and Liability |date=Winter 1999 |journal=The Boston University Public Interest Law Journal |volume=8}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1993, the Superior Court of San Francisco's Family Court placed 15-year-old lesbian [[Lyn Duff]] under the guardianship of a foster couple after her mother committed her to Rivendell Psychiatric Center in West Jordan, Utah, where she allegedly endured physical abuse under the guise of conversion therapy. Lyn Duff's petition to leave her mother was granted without court opinion.&lt;ref name=Lyn_Duff&gt;{{cite web|last1=Ocamb|first1=Karen|title=Shannon Minter on NARTH Lawsuit Against Psychological Child Abuse Law |url=http://www.bilerico.com/2012/11/shannon_minter_on_narth_lawsuit_against_psychologi.php |publisher=The Bilerico Project|accessdate=25 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Molnar1997"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Molnar|first1=Beth E.|title=Juveniles and Psychiatric Institutionalization: Toward Better Due Process and Treatment Review in the United States|journal=[[Health and Human Rights]]|volume=2|issue=2|year=1997|pages=98–116|url=http://www.hhrjournal.org/wp-content/uploads/sites/13/2014/03/8-Molnar.pdf|accessdate=29 November 2016|issn=1079-0969|jstor=4065274|doi=10.2307/4065274|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150924030043/http://www.hhrjournal.org/wp-content/uploads/sites/13/2014/03/8-Molnar.pdf|archive-date=24 September 2015|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Duff|first1=Lyn|title=I was a teenage test case|journal=California Lawyer Magazine|date=May 1996|page=46}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Orly&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Rachmilovitz|first1=Orly|title=Masters of Their Own Destiny: Children's Identities, Parents' Assimilation Demands, and State Intervention|journal=Boston University School of Law, Dissertation|date=13 August 2013|volume=Public Law and Legal Theory Paper No. 13-35|url=http://www.bu.edu/law/faculty/scholarship/workingpapers/documents/RachmilovitzO081313.pdf|accessdate=29 November 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20151222121648/http://www.bu.edu/law/faculty/scholarship/workingpapers/documents/RachmilovitzO081313.pdf|archive-date=22 December 2015|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[LGBT rights opposition]]
*[[Ole Ivar Lovaas]]—a psychologist who attempted to perform gay conversion therapy.
*[[Sexual orientation change efforts]]
*[[Ex-ex-gay|Ex-ex-gay people]]—those who participated in the ex-gay movement and later publicly stated they do not identify as heterosexual

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Bibliography==
*{{citation |last=Bayer |first=Ronald |title=Homosexuality and American Psychiatry: The Politics of Diagnosis |year=1987 |publisher=Princeton University Press |location=Princeton |isbn=978-0-691-02837-8 |url-access=registration |url=https://archive.org/details/homosexualityame00bayerich }}
*{{citation |last=Bergler |first=Edmund |title=Curable Disease? |journal=Time |date=10 Dec 1956 |url=http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,808760-2,00.html}}
*{{citation |last=Bergler |first=Edmund |title=Homosexuality: disease or way of life? |year=1962 |publisher=Collier Books}}
*{{citation |last=Bieber |first=Irving |title=Homosexuality: A Psychoanalytic Study of Male Homosexuals |publisher=Basic Books Inc |year=1962}}
*{{citation |last=Bright |first=Chuck |title=Deconstructing Reparative Therapy: An Examination of the Processes Involved When Attempting to Change Sexual Orientation |date=December 2004 |journal=Clinical Social Work Journal |volume=32 |issue=4 |doi=10.1007/s10615-004-0543-2 |pages=471–481}}
*{{citation |last=Cruz |first=David B. |title=CONTROLLING DESIRES: SEXUAL ORIENTATION CONVERSION AND THE LIMITS OF KNOWLEDGE AND LAW |date=1999 |journal=Southern California Law Review |volume=72 |url=http://www-bcf.usc.edu/~usclrev/pdf/072502.pdf |page=1297 |access-date=2015-05-20 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170919071205/http://www-bcf.usc.edu/~usclrev/pdf/072502.pdf |archive-date=2017-09-19 |url-status=dead }}
*{{citation |last1=Domenici |first1=Thomas |last2=Lesser |first2=Ronnie C. |title=Disorienting Sexuality: Psychoanalytic Reappraisals of Sexual Identities |year=1995 |publisher=Routledge |location=New York |isbn=978-0-415-91198-6}}
*{{citation |last=Drescher |first=Jack |title=I'm Your Handyman: A History of Reparative Therapies |date=June 1998 |journal=Journal of Homosexuality |pmid=9670099 |volume=36 |issue=1 |pages=19–42 |doi=10.1300/J082v36n01_02}}
*{{Citation |last=Drescher |first=Jack |year=2001 |title=Ethical Concerns Raised When Patients Seek to Change Same-Sex Attractions |journal=Journal of Gay &amp; Lesbian Psychotherapy |volume=5 |issue=3/4 |page=183 |doi=10.1300/j236v05n03_11}}
*{{citation |editor-last=Drescher |editor-first=Jack |editor2-last=Zucker |editor2-first=Kenneth |title=Ex-Gay Research: Analyzing the Spitzer Study and Its Relation to Science, Religion, Politics, and Culture |year=2006 |publisher=Harrington Park Press |location=New York |isbn=978-1-56023-557-6}}
*{{citation |last=Drescher |first=Jack |title=Psychoanalytic Therapy and the Gay Man |year=1998 |publisher=The Analytic Press |location=Hillsdale, New Jersey |isbn=978-0-88163-208-8}}
*{{citation |last=Ellis |first=Albert |title=Homosexuality: Its Causes and Cure |year=1965 |publisher=Lyle Stuart Inc. |location=New York |lccn=65-12351}}
*{{citation |last1=Ford|first1=Jeffry G.|title=Healing homosexuals: A psychologist's journey through the ex-gay movement and the pseudo-science of reparative therapy |journal=Journal of Gay &amp; Lesbian Psychotherapy |volume=5 |issue= 3–4 |year=2001 |pages=69–86 |doi= 10.1300/J236v05n03_06}}
*{{citation |last=Freud |first=Sigmund |title=On Sexuality: Volume 7 |year=1991 |publisher=Penguin Books |location=London |isbn=978-0-14-013797-2}}
*{{citation |last=Freud |first=Ernst L. |title=Letters of Sigmund Freud |year=1992 |publisher=Dover Publications, Inc |location=New York |isbn=978-0-486-27105-7}}
*{{citation |last=Gay |first=Peter |title=Freud: A Life for Our Time |year=2006 |publisher=Papermac |location=London |isbn=978-0333486382}}
*{{citation |last=Haldeman |first=Douglas C. |contribution=Sexual orientation conversion therapy for gay men and lesbians: A scientific examination |editor1-last=Gonsiorek |editor1-first=John |editor2-last=Weinrich |editor2-first=James |title=Homosexuality: Research Implications for Public Policy |year=1991 |publisher=Sage Publications, Inc |location=Newbury Park, California |isbn=978-0-8039-3764-2 |contribution-url=http://www.drdoughaldeman.com/doc/ScientificExamination.pdf}}
*{{citation |last=Haldeman |first=Douglas C. |title=Gay Rights, Patient Rights: The Implications of Sexual Orientation Conversion Therapy |date=June 2002 |journal=Professional Psychology: Research and Practice |volume=33 |issue=3 |pages= 260–264|doi=10.1037/0735-7028.33.3.260 |url=http://www.drdoughaldeman.com/doc/GayRightsPatientRights.pdf|citeseerx=10.1.1.506.1394 }}
*{{citation |last=Hooker |first=Evelyn |date=March 1957 |title=The Adjustment of the Male Overt Homosexual |journal=Journal of Projective Techniques |volume=21 |issue=1 |pages=18–31 |pmid=13417147|doi=10.1080/08853126.1957.10380742 }}
*{{citation |last=Jones |first=Ernest |title=The Life and Work of Sigmund Freud, Volume 2 |year=1955 |publisher=Basic Books |location=New York |isbn=&lt;!-- Not given --&gt;}}
*{{citation |last1=Jones|first1= S. L.|last2=Yarhouse |first2=A. M. |year=2007 |title=Ex‐gays? A longitudinal study of religiously mediated change in sexual orientation |location=Downers Grove, IL |publisher= [[InterVarsity Press]] }}
*{{citation |last=Johnson |first=Chris |title=Robinson backs out of symposium on "ex-gays" |publisher=Washington Blade |url=http://www.washblade.com/thelatest/thelatest.cfm?blog_id=18015 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080502044844/http://washblade.com/thelatest/thelatest.cfm?blog_id=18015 |archivedate=2008-05-02 |date=2008-05-12 |format=}}
*{{citation |last=Katz |first=Jonathan |authorlink=Jonathan Ned Katz |title=Gay American History: Lesbians and Gay Men in the U.S.A. |year=1976 |publisher=Crowell |location=New York |isbn=978-0690005103|title-link=Gay American History: Lesbians and Gay Men in the U.S.A. }}
*{{citation |last=Kirby |first=Michael |authorlink=Michael Kirby (judge) |date=December 2003 |title=The 1973 deletion of homosexuality as a psychiatric disorder: 30 years on |journal=Australian &amp; New Zealand Journal of Psychiatry |volume=37 |issue=6 |pages=18–31, 674–677 |doi=10.1111/j.1440-1614.2003.01269.x}}
*{{citation |last=Marmor |first=Judd |title=Sexual Inversion: The Multiple Roots of Homosexuality |year=1965 |publisher=Basic Books |location=New York |lccn=65-13343}}
*{{citation |last1=Norcross |first1=John C. |last2=Koocher |first2=Gerald P. |last3=Garofalo |first3=Ariele |title=Discredited Psychological Treatments and Tests: A Delphi Poll |date=October 2006 |journal=Professional Psychology: Research and Practice |volume=37 |issue=5 |pages=515–522 |doi=10.1037/0735-7028.37.5.515}}
*{{citation |last1=LeVay |first1=Simon |title=Queer Science: The Use and Abuse of Research into Homosexuality |year=1996 |publisher=MIT Press |location=Cambridge |isbn=978-0-262-12199-6 |url-access=registration |url=https://archive.org/details/queerscienceusea00leva }}
*{{citation |last1=Lewes |first1=Kenneth |title=The Psychoanalytic Theory of Male Homosexuality|year=1988 |publisher=Simon &amp; Schuster |location=New York |isbn=978-0-671-62391-3}}
*{{citation |last1=Lewes |first1=Kenneth |title=A special oedipal mechanism in the development of male homosexuality |journal=Psychoanalytic Psychology |volume=15 |issue=3 |year=1998 |pages=341–359 |doi=10.1037/0736-9735.15.3.341}}
*{{citation |last1=O'Connor |first1=Noreen |last2=Ryan |first2=Joanna |title=Wild Desires and Mistaken Identities: Lesbianism and Psychoanalysis |year=1993 |publisher=Virago |location=London |isbn=978-1-85381-303-0}}
*{{citation |last=Plowman |first=William |title=Homosexuality Panel Squelched by Gay Activists |date=2008-05-12 |url=https://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=90365869 |publisher=NPR}}
*{{citation |last1=Shidlo |first1=Ariel |last2=Schroeder |first2=Michael |title=Changing Sexual Orientation: A Consumers' Report |date=2002a|journal=Professional Psychology: Research and Practice |volume=33 |issue=3 |doi=10.1037/0735-7028.33.3.249 |pages=249–259}}
*{{citation |last1=Shidlo |first1=Ariel |last2=Schroeder |first2=Michael |title=Sexual conversion therapy: ethical, clinical, and research perspectives |date=2002b |page=137 |url=https://books.google.com/?id=1jYuientrGoC&amp;pg=PA137&amp;lpg=PA137&amp;q=Shidlo%20and%20Schroeder%20gay%20sample | accessdate = 2011-05-17 | isbn = 978-0-7890-1911-0}}
*{{citation |last=Socarides |first=Charles |title=The Overt Homosexual |year=1968 |publisher=Grune &amp; Stratton |location=New York |isbn=978-0808904373}}
*{{citation |last=Spitzer |first=Robert L. |title=Can Some Gay Men and Lesbians Change Their Sexual Orientation? 200 Participants Reporting a Change from Homosexual to Heterosexual Orientation |date=October 2003 |journal=Archives of Sexual Behavior |volume=32 |issue=5 |pmid=14567650 |doi=10.1023/A:1025647527010 |pages=403–17; discussion 419–72}}
*{{citation |last=Stanton |first=Martin |title=Sandor Ferenczi: Reconsidering Active Intervention |year=1991 |publisher=Jason Aronson Inc |location=Northvale |isbn=978-0-87668-569-3}}
*{{citation |last=Terry |first=Jennifer |title=An American Obsession: Science, Medicine and the Place of Homosexuality in Modern Society |year=1999 |publisher=Chicago University Press |location=Chicago |isbn=978-0226793665}}
*{{citation |last=Waidzunas |first=Tom |title=The Straight Line: How the Fringe Science of Ex-Gay Therapy Reoriented Sexuality |year=2016 |publisher=University of Minnesota Press |location=Minneapolis |isbn=9780816696154}}
*{{citation |last=Young-Bruehl |first=Elisabeth |title=Anna Freud |year=1988 |publisher=Summit Books |location=New York |isbn=978-0-671-68751-9}}
*{{citation |last1=Yarhouse |first1=Mark A. |last2=Throckmorton |first2=Warren |title=Ethical Issues in Attempts to Ban Reorientation Therapies |year=2002 |journal=Psychotherapy: Theory, Research, Practice, Training |volume=39 |issue=1 |doi=10.1037/0033-3204.39.1.66 |pages=66–75}}
*{{citation |last=Yoshino |first=Kenji |title=Covering |year=2002 |journal=Yale Law Journal |volume=111 |issue=4 |pages=769–939 |url=http://www.yalelawjournal.org/article/covering|doi=10.2307/797566 |jstor=797566 }}

==External links==
{{wikiquote}}
* [https://www.thetrevorproject.org/50-bills-50-states/ The Trevor Project's 50 Bills 50 States Campaign]
* [http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=homosexuality-cure-masters-johnson Article by Thomas Maier about Masters and Johnson]
* [http://psychology.ucdavis.edu/rainbow/html/facts_changing.html Facts About Changing Sexual Orientation: Dr. Gregory M. Herek] ''[[University of California, Davis]]''
* {{YouTube|id=gIifMxPcRnI |title= Interview with Dr. Robert Spitzer, M.D. (retracting his study on conversion therapy)}}
* [https://www.independent.co.uk/news/uk/this-britain/the-exgay-files-the-bizarre-world-of-gaytostraight-conversion-1884947.html Investigation into Conversion Therapy] ''[[The Independent]]'' ([https://web.archive.org/web/20120615050519/http://www.independent.co.uk/news/uk/this-britain/the-exgay-files-the-bizarre-world-of-gaytostraight-conversion-1884947.html Archive])
* [https://www.nytimes.com/2012/05/19/health/dr-robert-l-spitzer-noted-psychiatrist-apologizes-for-study-on-gay-cure.html Psychiatry Giant Sorry for Backing Gay 'Cure'] ''[[The New York Times]]''
* [http://whatweknow.law.columbia.edu/topics/lgbt-equality/what-does-the-scholarly-research-say-about-whether-conversion-therapy-can-alter-sexual-orientation-without-causing-harm/ What does the scholarly research say about whether conversion therapy can alter sexual orientation without causing harm?] on the [http://whatweknow.law.columbia.edu/ "What We Know" Project (Columbia University)]

{{LGBT |orientation=yes}}
{{Pseudoscience |orientation=yes}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Conversion Therapy}}
[[Category:Conversion therapy]]
[[Category:Medical controversies]]
[[Category:Sexual orientation and medicine]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>