<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20020912131855|357508" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="26410" pageid="26410" ns="0" title="Conversion therapy"><revisions><rev timestamp="2002-10-14T09:21:19Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Reparative therapy''' is the controversial practice of helping a person transition voluntarily from [[homosexuality]] to [[heterosexuality]]. Some organizations, such as [[NARTH]] and the [[International Healing Foundation]], which advocate the idea that [[sexual orientation]] is not fixed by genetic factors, support reparative therapy. Many other organizations advocate the idea that [[sexual orientation]] is fixed by genetic factors or otherwise unchangeable in adults and thus adamantly oppose reparative therapy. 

The issue of changing sexual orientation has become a highly politicized topic in western countries, especially the United States. Both the theory and practice have come under heavy criticism from [[gay rights]] groups, doctors, [[American Psychiatric Association]] and other organizations. 

== Position of the American Psychiatric Association ==
The [[American Psychiatric Association]] (APA) voted in 1973 that homosexuality is not a mental illness and states that there are no scientifically rigorous studies to indicate the actual "efficacy or harm of 'reparative' treatments" and that "reparative" therapists have yet to produce "any rigorous scientific research to substantiate their claims of cure."  The APA position statement on reparative therapy states that "recent publicized efforts to repathologize homosexuality by claiming that it can be cured are often guided not by rigorous scientific or psychiatric research, but sometimes by religious and political forces opposed to full civil rights for gay men and lesbians." The APA position statement ends with a recommendation to ethical practitioners to "refrain from attempts to change individuals' sexual orientation, keeping in mind the medical dictum to first, do no harm." 

See also: [[International Healing Foundation]] (IHF)

==External Links==
*[http://www.narth.com NARTH ] advocates right of patients to seek therapy to re-orient from homosexuality to heterosexuality.
*The [http://www.gaytostraight.org IHF ] has pioneered a form of reparative therapy "for those who wish to change".
*[http://religioustolerance.org/hom_repar.htm religioustolerance.org] -- strongly criticizes reparative therapy as "useless and probably harmful".
*[http://www.psych.org/pract_of_psych/copptherapyaddendum83100.cfm American Psychiatric Association: Position Statement on Therapies Focused on Attempts to Change Sexual Orientation]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>