<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20221126161602|1123953340" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="26410" pageid="26410" ns="0" title="Conversion therapy"><revisions><rev timestamp="2022-11-28T11:07:57Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|Pseudoscientific&lt;!-- DO NOT remove or change to "scientific" without talk page consensus --&gt; intervention}}
{{pp-pc1}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2020}}
{{LGBT rights sidebar}}
'''Conversion therapy''' is the [[pseudoscientific]]&lt;!-- DO NOT remove or change to "scientific" without talk page consensus --&gt; practice of attempting to change an individual's [[sexual orientation]], [[gender identity]], or [[gender expression]] to align with [[heterosexual]] and [[cisgender]] norms.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|date=October 2015 |title=Ending Conversion Therapy: Supporting and Affirming LGBTQ Youth |url=https://store.samhsa.gov/sites/default/files/d7/priv/sma15-4928.pdf |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20211014164244/https://store.samhsa.gov/sites/default/files/d7/priv/sma15-4928.pdf |archive-date=14 October 2021 |access-date=26 December 2021 |publisher=Substance Abuse and Mental Health Services Administration|quote=Efforts to change an individual's sexual orientation, gender identity, or gender expression through behavioral health or medical interventions. Any effort with an ''a priori'' goal of a gender expression that aligns with stereotypical norms, cisgender identity, and/or heterosexual orientation, identity, and sexual behaviors.}}&lt;/ref&gt; In contrast to [[evidence-based medicine]] and clinical guidance, such practices typically view [[homosexuality]] and [[gender variance]] as unnatural or unhealthy. There is a scientific consensus that conversion therapy is ineffective at changing a person's sexual orientation or gender identity and that it frequently causes significant, long-term psychological harm in individuals who undergo it.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

Common methods of conversion therapy are counseling, visualization, social skills training, [[Psychoanalysis|psychoanalytic therapy]], and spiritual interventions. Other methods that have been used include ice-pick [[Lobotomy|lobotomies]];&lt;ref name=Cruz&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Cruz|first1=David B.|title=Controlling Desires: Sexual Orientation Conversion and the Limits of Knowledge and Law|journal=Southern California Law Review|date=1999|volume=72|issue=5|pages=1297–400|pmid=12731502|url=http://www-bcf.usc.edu/~usclrev/pdf/072502.pdf|access-date=25 November 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170919071205/http://www-bcf.usc.edu/~usclrev/pdf/072502.pdf|archive-date=19 September 2017|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Yoshino"&gt;{{Harvnb|Yoshino|2002}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Homosexuality and Biology"&gt;{{cite news |last1=Burr |first1=Chandler |date=June 1997 |title=Homosexuality and Biology |work=[[The Atlantic]] |publisher= |url=https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/1997/06/homosexuality-and-biology/304683/ |access-date=25 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Rieber|first1=Inge|last2=Sigusch|first2=Volkmar|title=Psychosurgery on Sex Offenders and Sexual "Deviants" in West Germany|journal=Archives of Sexual Behavior|date=1979|volume=8|issue=6|pages=523–527|doi=10.1007/bf01541419|pmid=391177|s2cid=41463669}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Dieckmann|first1=G.|last2=Horn|first2=H.J. |last3=Schneider|first3=H. |editor1-first=E.R.|editor1-last=Hitchcock|editor2-first=H.T.|editor2-last=Ballantine|editor3-first=B.A.|editor3-last=Meyerson|title=Long-term Results of Anterior Hypothalamotomy in Sexual Offences|journal=Modern Concepts in Psychiatric Surgery|date=1979|pages=187–195}}&lt;/ref&gt; chemical castration with hormonal treatment;&lt;ref name="APA-myth"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Milar|first1=Katherine S.|title=The myth buster|journal=Monitor on Psychology|date=February 2011|volume=42|issue=2|page=24|url=http://www.apa.org/monitor/2011/02/myth-buster.aspx|access-date=25 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Aversion therapy|aversive treatments]], such as "the application of electric shock to the hands and/or genitals" and "nausea-inducing drugs{{nbsp}}[...] administered{{nbsp}}[...] with the presentation of homoerotic stimuli", and [[masturbation|masturbatory]] reconditioning or [[hypnosis]].

An increasing number of jurisdictions around the world have passed [[laws against conversion therapy]].&lt;ref name="Drescher" /&gt; Conversion therapy may constitute [[fraud]] and has been described by experts as [[torture]], [[cruel, inhuman, or degrading treatment]], and contrary to [[human rights]] norms.

==Terminology ==
Medical professionals and activists consider "conversion therapy" a misnomer, as it does not constitute a legitimate form of [[therapy]].{{sfn|Haldeman|2022|p=4}}  Alternative terms include sexual orientation change efforts (SOCE), gender identity change efforts (GICE)—together, sexual orientation and gender identity change efforts (SOGICE)&lt;ref name="SOGICESurvivor"/&gt;—and LGBTQA+ conversion practices.&lt;ref name="SOGICESurvivor"&gt;Csabs, C., Despott, N., Morel, B., Brodel, A., Johnson, R. '[http://socesurvivors.com.au/wp-content/uploads/2020/12/Survivor-Statement-A4-Doc-v1-2-Digital.pdf The SOGICE Survivor Statement]', 2018.&lt;/ref&gt; "Reparative therapy" may refer to conversion therapy in general, or to [[#Reparative therapy|a subset thereof]].&lt;ref name="Drescher1998"/&gt;

==History==
{{main|History of conversion therapy}}

=== Sexual Orientation Change Efforts (SOCE) ===
The term ''[[homosexual]]'' was coined by German-speaking Hungarian writer [[Karl Maria Kertbeny]] and was in circulation by the 1880s.{{sfn|Whisnant|2016|p=20}}&lt;ref name=Drescher&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Drescher |first1=Jack |last2=Schwartz |first2=Alan |last3=Casoy |first3=Flávio |last4=McIntosh |first4=Christopher A. |last5=Hurley |first5=Brian |last6=Ashley |first6=Kenneth |last7=Barber |first7=Mary |last8=Goldenberg |first8=David |last9=Herbert |first9=Sarah E. |last10=Lothwell |first10=Lorraine E. |last11=Mattson |first11=Marlin R. |last12=McAfee |first12=Scot G. |last13=Pula |first13=Jack |last14=Rosario |first14=Vernon |last15=Tompkins |first15=D. Andrew |title=The Growing Regulation of Conversion Therapy |journal=Journal of Medical Regulation |date=2016 |volume=102 |issue=2 |pages=7–12 |doi=10.30770/2572-1852-102.2.7|pmid=27754500 |pmc=5040471 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Into the middle of the twentieth century, competing views of homosexuality were advanced by [[psychoanalysis]] versus academic [[sexology]]. [[Sigmund Freud]], the founder of psychoanalysis, viewed homosexuality as a form of [[arrested development]]. Later psychoanalysts followed [[Sandor Rado]], who argued that homosexuality was a "phobic avoidance of heterosexuality caused by inadequate early parenting".&lt;ref name=Drescher/&gt; This line of thinking was popular in psychiatric models of homosexuality based on the prison population or homosexuals seeking treatment. In contrast, sexology researchers such as [[Alfred Kinsey]] argued that homosexuality was a normal variation in human development. In 1970, gay activists confronted the [[American Psychiatric Association]], persuading the association to reconsider whether homosexuality should be listed as a disorder. The APA delisted homosexuality in 1973, which contributed to shifts in public opinion on homosexuality.&lt;ref name=Drescher/&gt;

Despite their lack of scientific backing, some [[social conservative|socially]] or [[religious conservatism|religiously]] conservative activists continued to argue that if one person's sexuality could be changed, homosexuality was not a fixed class such as [[Race (human categorization)|race]]. Borrowing from discredited psychoanalytic ideas about the cause of homosexuality, some of these individuals offered conversion therapy.&lt;ref name=Drescher/&gt; In 2001, conversion therapy attracted attention when [[Robert L. Spitzer]] published a non-peer-reviewed study asserting that some homosexuals could change their sexual orientation. Many researchers made methodological criticisms of the study, which Spitzer later repudiated.&lt;ref name=Drescher/&gt;

=== Gender Identity Change Efforts (GICE) ===
Many cultures throughout history have had validating attitudes towards transgender and nonbinary people. Systemic institutionalized [[transphobia]] present in Western and U.S.-based medical-model narratives historically favored binary gender and pathologized gender diversity. This aided the development and proliferation of GICE, which is based on considering gender identity discordant with assigned sex at birth disordered.&lt;ref name="GICE_summary"&gt;{{Cite book |last1=Rivera |first1=David P. |url=http://content.apa.org/books/17244-003 |title=The case against conversion "therapy": Evidence, ethics, and alternatives. American Psychological Association |last2=Pardo |first2=Seth T. |publisher=American Psychological Association |year=2022 |isbn=978-1-4338-3711-1 |editor-last=Haldeman |editor-first=Douglas C. |location=Washington |pages=51–68 |language=en |chapter=Gender identity change efforts: A summary |doi=10.1037/0000266-003|s2cid=243776563 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Early interventions were rooted in psychoanalytic hypotheses. [[Robert Stoller]] advanced the theory that cross-gender presentation and behavior in children assigned male at birth was due to an overly close relationship with their mother. [[Richard Green (sexologist)|Richard Green]] continued his research into [[social engineering (political science)|social engineering]]. His methods include augmenting contact with fathers, including stereotypical masculine activities, requesting the mother the step back, and having both parents praise traditional "masculine" behaviors and shame effeminate or cross-gender behavior. These methods did more harm than good, resulting in depression and feelings of betrayal (from parents) that the goals of the "treatment" were impossible.&lt;ref name="GICE_summary" /&gt;

Green's methods were adopted by [[Kenneth Zucker]], but modified so the focus was primarily preventing the child from developing an eventual transgender identity. His methods include behavioral modifications of cross-gender play interests, encouraging the same-sex parent to engage more and the other to engage less, and treating the child with psychodymanic therapy. The province of Ontario subsequently banned therapeutic programs based on this approach.&lt;ref name="GICE_summary" /&gt;

==Theories and techniques==
===Aversion therapy===
{{see also|Behavior modification}}

[[Aversion therapy]] used on homosexuals included electric shock and nausea-inducing drugs during presentation of same-sex erotic images. Cessation of the aversive stimuli was typically accompanied by the presentation of opposite-sex erotic images, with the objective of strengthening heterosexual feelings.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Haldeman|1991|p=152}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another method used was the covert sensitization method, which involves instructing patients to imagine vomiting or receiving electric shocks, writing that only single case studies have been conducted, and that their results cannot be generalized. Haldeman writes that behavioral conditioning studies tend to decrease homosexual feelings, but do not increase heterosexual feelings, citing Rangaswami's "Difficulties in arousing and increasing heterosexual responsiveness in a homosexual: A case report", published in 1982, as typical in this respect.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Haldeman|1991|pp=152–153}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Aversion therapy was developed in [[Czechoslovak Socialist Republic|Czechoslovakia]] between 1950 and 1962 and in the Commonwealth from 1961 into the mid-1970s. In the context of the Cold War, Western psychologists ignored the poor results of their Czechoslovak counterparts, who had concluded that aversion therapy was not effective by 1961 and recommended [[decriminalization of homosexuality]] instead.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Davison |first1=Kate |title=Cold War Pavlov: Homosexual aversion therapy in the 1960s |journal=History of the Human Sciences |date=2021 |volume=34 |issue=1 |pages=89–119 |doi=10.1177/0952695120911593|s2cid=218922981 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Some men in the United Kingdom were offered the choice between prison and undergoing aversion therapy. It was also offered to a few British women, but was never the standard treatment for either homosexual men or women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Spandler |first1=Helen |last2=Carr |first2=Sarah |title=Lesbian and bisexual women's experiences of aversion therapy in England |journal=History of the Human Sciences |date=2022 |volume=35 |issue=3–4 |pages=218–236 |doi=10.1177/09526951211059422|pmid=36090521 |pmc=9449443 |s2cid=245753251 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Bioenergetics===
{{main|Bioenergetics}}
'''Bioenergetics''' is a therapeutic technique developed by [[Alexander Lowen]] and [[John Pierrakos]], who were students of [[Wilhelm Reich]]. It has been used to attempt to convert gay people to heterosexuality by [[Richard A. Cohen|Richard Cohen]], who has been called one of America's leading practitioners of conversion therapy.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.abc.net.au/foreign/content/2006/s1732241.htm Transcript of "USA - Gay Conversion] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100513171123/http://www.abc.net.au/foreign/content/2006/s1732241.htm |date=2010-05-13 }}, [[ABC Television (Australian TV network)|ABC TV]] Foreign Correspondent, 08-22-2006. Retrieved 04-07-2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Cohen holds male patients in his lap with the patient curled into the fetal position, and also advocates methods involving shouting or slamming a pillow with a tennis racket.&lt;ref name="Cohen"&gt;{{Harvnb|Cohen|2000|p=152,176}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Ex-gay/ex-trans ministry===
[[File:One by One booth.jpg|thumb|right|[[OneByOne]] booth at a [[Love Won Out]] conference]]
{{Main|Ex-gay}}

Some sources{{which|date=July 2022}} describe ex-gay and ex-trans ministries as a form of conversion therapy, while others{{which|date=July 2022}} state that ex-gay organizations and conversion therapy are distinct methods of attempting to convert gay people to heterosexuality.&lt;ref name="DrescherandZucker"&gt;{{Harvnb|Drescher|Zucker|2006|pp=126, 175}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="APA"&gt;{{citation |url=http://www.apa.org/pi/lgbt/resources/just-the-facts.pdf |title=Just the Facts About Sexual Orientation &amp; Youth: A Primer for Principals, Educators and School Personnel |access-date=14 May 2010 |year=1999 |publisher=Just the Facts Coalition}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Haldeman|1991|pp=149,156–159}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="JonesandYarhouse"&gt;{{Harvnb|Jones|Yarhouse|2007|p=374}}&lt;/ref&gt; The umbrella organization [[Exodus International]] in the United States ceased activities in June 2013, and the three member board issued a statement which repudiated its aims and apologized for the harm their pursuit has caused to [[LGBT]] people.&lt;ref name=Change&gt;{{citation |url=http://exodusinternational.org/2013/06/i-am-sorry |first=Alan |last=Chambers |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130623013409/http://exodusinternational.org/2013/06/i-am-sorry |archive-date=23 June 2013 |title=I Am Sorry |access-date=22 June 2013 |publisher=Exodus International}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{bsn|date=July 2022}} Ex-gay/ex-trans organizations often overlap and portray being trans as inherently sinful or against God's design, or pathologize gender variance as due to trauma, social contagion, or "[[gender ideology]]."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Robinson |first1=Christine M. |last2=Spivey |first2=Sue E. |date=2019-06-17 |title=Ungodly Genders: Deconstructing Ex-Gay Movement Discourses of "Transgenderism" in the US |journal=Social Sciences |language=en |volume=8 |issue=6 |pages=191 |doi=10.3390/socsci8060191 |issn=2076-0760|doi-access=free }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Jones |first1=Tiffany |last2=Jones |first2=Timothy W. |last3=Power |first3=Jennifer |last4=Pallotta-Chiarolli |first4=Maria |last5=Despott |first5=Nathan |date=2021-10-12 |title=Mis-education of Australian Youth: exposure to LGBTQA+ conversion ideology and practises |url=https://doi.org/10.1080/14681811.2021.1978964 |journal=Sex Education |volume=22 |issue=5 |pages=595–610 |doi=10.1080/14681811.2021.1978964 |s2cid=241018465 |issn=1468-1811}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Hypnosis ===
Hypnosis was used in conversion therapy since the 19th century by [[Richard von Krafft-Ebing]] and [[Albert von Schrenck-Notzing]]. In 1967, Canadian psychiatrist Peter Roper published a case study of treating 15 homosexuals (some of which would probably be considered bisexuals by modern standards) with hypnosis. Allegedly, 8 showed "marked improvement" (they reportedly lost sexual attraction towards the same sex altogether), 4 mild improvements (decrease of "homosexual tendencies"), and 3 no improvement after hypnotic treatment; he concluded that "hypnosis may well produce more satisfactory results than those obtainable by other means", depending on the [[hypnotic susceptibility]] of the subjects.&lt;ref&gt;Roper P. (1967). The effects of hypnotherapy on homosexuality. C''anadian Medical Association journal'', 96(6), 319–327.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Psychoanalysis===
{{Main|Psychoanalysis}}

Haldeman writes that psychoanalytic treatment of homosexuality is exemplified by the work of Irving Bieber ''et al.'' in ''Homosexuality: A Psychoanalytic Study of Male Homosexuals''. They advocated long-term therapy aimed at resolving the unconscious childhood conflicts that they considered responsible for homosexuality. Haldeman notes that Bieber's methodology has been criticized because it relied upon a clinical sample, the description of the outcomes was based upon subjective therapist impression, and follow-up data were poorly presented. Bieber reported a 27% success rate from long-term therapy, but only 18% of the patients in whom Bieber considered the treatment successful had been exclusively homosexual to begin with, while 50% had been bisexual. In Haldeman's view, this makes even Bieber's unimpressive claims of success misleading.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Haldeman|1991|pp=150–151}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Haldeman discusses other psychoanalytic studies of attempts to change homosexuality. Curran and Parr's "Homosexuality: An analysis of 100 male cases", published in 1957, reported no significant increase in heterosexual behavior. Mayerson and Lief's "Psychotherapy of homosexuals: A follow-up study of nineteen cases", published in 1965, reported that half of its 19 subjects were exclusively heterosexual in behavior four and a half years after treatment, but its outcomes were based on patient self-report and had no external validation. In Haldeman's view, those participants in the study who reported change were bisexual at the outset, and its authors wrongly interpreted capacity for heterosexual sex as change of sexual orientation.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Haldeman|1991|pp=151, 256}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Reparative therapy===

The term "reparative therapy" has been used as a synonym for conversion therapy generally, but according to [[Jack Drescher]] it properly refers to a specific kind of therapy{{clarify|date=July 2022}} associated with the psychologists [[Elizabeth Moberly]] and [[Joseph Nicolosi]].&lt;ref name="Drescher1998"&gt;{{Harvnb|Drescher|1998b|p=152}}&lt;/ref&gt; The term ''reparative'' refers to Nicolosi's postulate that same-sex attraction is a person's unconscious attempt to "self-repair" feelings of inferiority.&lt;ref name=Hicks_1999&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Hicks|first1=Karolyn Ann|title="Reparative Therapy": Whether Parental Attempts to Change a Child's Sexual Orientation Can Legally Constitute Child Abuse|journal=American University Law Review|date=1999|volume=49|issue=2|pages=505–547|url=http://digitalcommons.wcl.american.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1288&amp;context=aulr|access-date=28 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Nicolosi|first1=Joseph|title=What Is Reparative Therapy? Examining the Controversy|url=http://josephnicolosi.com/what-is-reparative-therapy-exa/|access-date=28 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Bright"&gt;{{Harvnb|Bright|2004|pp=471–481}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Lobotomy===
{{Main|Lobotomy}}

In the 1940s and 1950s, U.S. neurologist [[Walter Jackson Freeman II|Walter Freeman]] popularized the [[Lobotomy#Transorbital lobotomy|ice-pick lobotomy]] as a treatment for homosexuality. He personally performed as many as 3,439&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=He was bad, so they put an ice pick in his brain|url=https://www.theguardian.com/science/2008/jan/13/neuroscience.medicalscience|author=Elizabeth Day|date=13 January 2008|website=www.theguardian.com|access-date=26 December 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; lobotomy surgeries in 23 states, of which 2,500 used his ice-pick procedure,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Top 10 Fascinating And Notable Lobotomies|url=http://listverse.com/2009/06/24/top-10-fascinating-and-notable-lobotomies/|date=24 June 2009|website=listverse.com|access-date=26 December 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; despite the fact that he had no formal surgical training.&lt;ref name="rowland"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Rowland|first=Lewis|date=April 2005|title=Walter Freeman's Psychosurgery and Biological Psychiatry: A Cautionary Tale|journal=Neurology Today|volume=5|issue=4|pages=70–72|doi=10.1097/00132985-200504000-00020}}&lt;/ref&gt; Up to 40% of Freeman's patients were gay individuals subjected to a lobotomy&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine|last1=Stone|first1=Gene|title=The Tiger Cure|magazine=New York Magazine|date=September 2013|url=https://nymag.com/news/features/sex-surrogate-2013-9/index1.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; in order to change their homosexual orientation, leaving most of these individuals severely disabled for the rest of their lives.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Scot|first1=Jamie|title=Shock the Gay Away: Secrets of Early Gay Aversion Therapy Revealed|url=https://www.huffingtonpost.com/jamie-scot/shock-the-gay-away-secrets-of-early-gay-aversion-therapy-revealed_b_3497435.html|work=HuffPost|date=28 June 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Marriage therapy===
{{See also|Relationship counseling}}
Previous editions of the [[World Health Organization]]'s ICD included "[[sexual relationship disorder]]", in which a person's sexual orientation or gender identity makes it difficult to form or maintain a relationship with a sexual partner. The belief that their sexual orientation has caused problems in their relationship may lead some people to turn to a marriage therapist for help to change their sexual orientation.&lt;ref name="Rosik-2003"&gt;{{cite journal |last=Rosik |first=Christopher H |title=Motivational, ethical, and epistemological foundations in the treatment of unwanted homoerotic attraction |journal=Journal of Marital and Family Therapy |issn=0194-472X |volume=29 |issue=1 |pages=13–28 |date=January 2003 |pmid=12616795 |doi=10.1111/j.1752-0606.2003.tb00379.x |oclc=5154888155}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sexual orientation disorder was removed from the most recent ICD, [[ICD-11]], after the Working Group on Sexual Disorders and Sexual Health determined that its inclusion was unjustified.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Reed |first1=Geoffrey M. |last2=Drescher |first2=Jack |last3=Krueger |first3=Richard B. |last4=Atalla |first4=Elham |last5=Cochran |first5=Susan D. |last6=First |first6=Michael B. |last7=Cohen‐Kettenis |first7=Peggy T. |last8=Arango‐de Montis |first8=Iván |last9=Parish |first9=Sharon J. |last10=Cottler |first10=Sara |last11=Briken |first11=Peer |date=2016 |title=Disorders related to sexuality and gender identity in the ICD‐11: revising the ICD‐10 classification based on current scientific evidence, best clinical practices, and human rights considerations |journal=World Psychiatry |volume=15 |issue=3 |pages=205–221 |doi=10.1002/wps.20354 |issn=1723-8617 |pmc=5032510 |pmid=27717275}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Nazi human experimentation===
{{further|Persecution of homosexuals in Nazi Germany}}
Homosexual prisoners were a preferred target of [[Nazi human experimentation]] during the last years of Nazi rule. The best-known experiments involving homosexual men were attempts by endocrinologist [[Carl Vaernet]] to change prisoners' sexual orientations by implanting a pellet that released [[testosterone]]. Most of the victims, non-consenting prisoners at Buchenwald, died shortly thereafter.{{sfn|Whisnant|2016|p=223}}{{sfn|Weindling|2015|pp=183–184}}

==Effects==
{{expand section|date=June 2022}}
There is a scientific consensus that conversion therapy is ineffective at changing a person's sexual orientation and can cause significant, long-term psychological harm.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Higbee |first1=Madison |last2=Wright |first2=Eric R. |last3=Roemerman |first3=Ryan M. |title=Conversion Therapy in the Southern United States: Prevalence and Experiences of the Survivors |journal=Journal of Homosexuality |date=2022 |volume=69 |issue=4 |pages=612–631 |doi=10.1080/00918369.2020.1840213|pmid=33206024 |s2cid=227039714 }}&lt;/ref&gt; This includes significantly higher rates of [[Major depressive disorder|depression]], [[substance abuse]], and other mental health issues in individuals who have undergone conversion therapy than their peers who did not,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=Christensen |first=Jen |date=2022-03-08 |title=Conversion therapy is harmful to LGBTQ people and costs society as a whole, study says |url=https://www.cnn.com/2022/03/07/health/conversion-therapy-personal-and-financial-harm/index.html |access-date=2022-11-05 |website=CNN |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt; including a suicide attempt rate nearly twice that of those who did not.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=thisisloyal.com |first=Loyal {{!}} |title=LGB people who have undergone conversion therapy almost twice as likely to attempt suicide |url=https://williamsinstitute.law.ucla.edu/press/lgb-suicide-ct-press-release/ |access-date=2022-11-05 |website=Williams Institute |language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A 2022 study estimated that conversion therapy of youth in the United States cost $650.16 million annually with an additional $9.5 billion in associated costs such as increased suicide and substance abuse.&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Forsythe |first1=Anna |last2=Pick |first2=Casey |last3=Tremblay |first3=Gabriel |last4=Malaviya |first4=Shreena |last5=Green |first5=Amy |last6=Sandman |first6=Karen |title=Humanistic and Economic Burden of Conversion Therapy Among LGBTQ Youths in the United States |journal=JAMA Pediatrics |date=2022 |volume=176 |issue=5 |pages=493–501 |doi=10.1001/jamapediatrics.2022.0042|pmid=35254391 |pmc=8902682 |s2cid=247252995 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Public opinion==
A 2020 survey carried out on US adults found majority support for banning conversion therapy for minors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Flores |first1=Andrew R. |last2=Mallory |first2=Christy |last3=Conron |first3=Kerith J. |title=Public attitudes about emergent issues in LGBTQ rights: Conversion therapy and religious refusals |journal=Research &amp; Politics |date=2020 |volume=7 |issue=4 |pages=205316802096687 |doi=10.1177/2053168020966874|s2cid=229001894 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

A 2022 [[YouGov]] poll found majority support in England, Scotland, and Wales for a conversion therapy ban for both sexual orientation and gender identity, with opposition ranging from 13 to 15 percent.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=The majority of Welsh people support a ban on trans conversion therapy in Wales {{!}} YouGov |url=https://yougov.co.uk/topics/politics/articles-reports/2022/05/03/majority-welsh-people-support-ban-trans-conversion |website=yougov.co.uk |access-date=30 June 2022 |language=en-gb}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legal status==
{{main|Legality of conversion therapy}}
[[File:Countries banning conversion therapy.svg|thumb|upright=1.3|Map of jurisdictions that have bans on sexual orientation and gender identity change efforts with minors.
{{legend|Navy|Criminal prohibition against conversion therapy on the basis of sexual orientation and gender identity}}
{{legend|#0000ff|Only medical professionals are banned from performing conversion therapy}}
{{legend|#00ffff|Conversion therapy is banned only in some subnational jurisdictions}}
{{legend|Gold|Ban on conversion therapy pending or proposed}}
{{legend|LightGrey|No ban on conversion therapy}}]]
Some jurisdictions have criminal bans on the practice of conversion therapy, including Malta, France, Germany, Albania, Mexico and Canada.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=Branch |first=Legislative Services |date=2022-01-10 |title=Consolidated federal laws of canada, An Act to amend the Criminal Code (conversion therapy) |url=https://laws.justice.gc.ca/eng/annualstatutes/2021_24/page-1.html |access-date=2022-07-06 |website=laws.justice.gc.ca}}&lt;/ref&gt; In other countries, including Brazil, Ecuador, and Taiwan, medical professionals are barred from practicing conversion therapy.&lt;ref name=Trispiotis/&gt;

In some states, lawsuits against conversion therapy providers for [[fraud]] have succeeded, but in other jurisdictions those claiming fraud must prove that the perpetrator was intentionally dishonest. Thus, a provider who genuinely believes conversion therapy is effective could not be convicted.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Purshouse |first1=Craig |last2=Trispiotis |first2=Ilias |title=Is 'conversion therapy' tortious? |journal=Legal Studies |date=2022 |volume=42 |issue=1 |pages=23–41 |doi=10.1017/lst.2021.28 |s2cid=236227920 |url=https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/legal-studies/article/is-conversion-therapy-tortious/6C8C4EDF829BE722AB7A7184E0CE6EBD |language=en |issn=0261-3875}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Conversion therapy on minors may amount to [[child abuse]].&lt;ref name=irct/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Canady |first1=Valerie |title=New report calls for an end to 'conversion therapy' for youth |journal=The Brown University Child and Adolescent Behavior Letter |date=2015 |volume=31 |issue=12 |pages=3–4 |doi=10.1002/cbl.30088}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Lee |first1=Cory |title=A Failed Experiment: Conversion Therapy as Child Abuse |journal=Roger Williams University Law Review |date=2022 |volume=27 |issue=1 |url=https://docs.rwu.edu/rwu_LR/vol27/iss1/3/ |issn=1090-3968}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Human rights===
In 2020 the [[International Rehabilitation Council for Torture Victims]] released an official statement that conversion therapy is torture.&lt;ref name=irct&gt;{{cite web |title=Conversion Therapy is Torture |url=https://irct.org/media-and-resources/latest-news/article/1027 |website=International Rehabilitation Council for Torture Victims |access-date=31 May 2021 |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; The same year, UN Independent Expert on sexual orientation and gender identity, [[Victor Madrigal-Borloz]], said that conversion therapy practices are "inherently discriminatory, that they are [[cruel, inhuman and degrading treatment]], and that depending on the severity or physical or mental pain and suffering inflicted to the victim, they may amount to torture". He recommended that it should be banned across the world.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.ohchr.org/EN/NewsEvents/Pages/ConversionTherapy_and_HR.aspx |title='Conversion therapy' Can Amount to Torture and Should be Banned says UN Expert |date=July 13, 2020 |website=United Nations Human Rights: Office of the High Commissioner |access-date=July 20, 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2021 Ilias Trispiotis and Craig Purshouse argue that conversion therapy violates the prohibition against degrading treatment under [[Article 3 of the European Convention on Human Rights]], leading to a state obligation to prohibit it.&lt;ref name=Trispiotis&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Trispiotis |first1=Ilias |last2=Purshouse |first2=Craig |title='Conversion Therapy' As Degrading Treatment |journal=Oxford Journal of Legal Studies |date=2021 |volume=42 |issue=1 |pages=104–132 |doi=10.1093/ojls/gqab024|pmid=35264896 |pmc=8902017 |doi-access=free }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Nugraha |first1=Ignatius Yordan |title=The compatibility of sexual orientation change efforts with international human rights law |journal=Netherlands Quarterly of Human Rights |date=2017 |volume=35 |issue=3 |pages=176–192 |doi=10.1177/0924051917724654|s2cid=220052834 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Medical views==
{{main|Medical views of conversion therapy}}Many health organizations around the world have denounced and criticized sexual orientation and gender identity change efforts.&lt;ref name="Lambda"&gt;{{cite web|title=Health and Medical Organization Statements on Sexual Orientation, Gender Identity/Expression and 'Reparative Therapy'|url=https://www.lambdalegal.org/publications/health-and-med-orgs-stmts-on-sex-orientation-and-gender-identity|website=lambdalegal.org|publisher=Lambda Legal}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="HRC"&gt;{{cite web|title=Policy and Position Statements on Conversion Therapy|url=http://www.hrc.org/resources/policy-and-position-statements-on-conversion-therapy|website=Human Rights Campaign|publisher=Human Rights Campaign|access-date=12 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="UK"&gt;{{cite web|title=Conversion Therapy: Consensus Statement|url=https://www1.bps.org.uk/system/files/Public%20files/conversion_therapy_final_version.pdf|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170517093445/http://www.bps.org.uk/system/files/Public%20files/conversion_therapy_final_version.pdf|archive-date=17 May 2017|access-date=16 December 2017|website=bps.org.uk|publisher=UK Council for Psychotherapy|page=2}}&lt;/ref&gt; National health organizations in the United States have announced that there has been no scientific demonstration of conversion therapy's efficacy in the last forty years.&lt;ref name="APA"/&gt;&lt;ref name="APA-Answers"&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.apa.org/topics/lgbt/orientation.aspx | title=Answers to Your Questions: For a Better Understanding of Sexual Orientation and Homosexuality | publisher=American Psychological Association | date=2008 | access-date=31 January 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name =APA_Position/&gt;&lt;ref name="PsychNews"&gt;{{citation |title=APA Maintains Reparative Therapy Not Effective |url=http://www.psychiatricnews.org/pnews/99-01-15/therapy.html |publisher=Psychiatric News (news division of the American Psychiatric Association) |date=15 January 1999 |access-date=28 August 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; They find that conversion therapy is ineffective, risky and can be harmful. Anecdotal claims of cures are counterbalanced by assertions of harm, and the American Psychiatric Association, for example, cautions ethical practitioners under the [[Hippocratic oath]] to do no harm and to refrain from attempts at conversion therapy.&lt;ref name=APA_Position&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.psych.org/Departments/EDU/Library/APAOfficialDocumentsandRelated/PositionStatements/200001a.aspx |title=Therapies Focused on Attempts to Change Sexual Orientation |publisher=Psych.org |access-date=18 July 2011 |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080910045820/http://www.psych.org/Departments/EDU/Library/APAOfficialDocumentsandRelated/PositionStatements/200001a.aspx |archive-date=10 September 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Mainstream medical bodies state that conversion therapy can be harmful because it may exploit guilt and anxiety, thereby damaging self-esteem and leading to depression and even suicide.&lt;ref name="nytconversion"&gt;{{citation |last=Luo |first=Michael |title=Some Tormented by Homosexuality Look to a Controversial Therapy |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2007/02/12/nyregion/12group.html |work=The New York Times |page=1 |date=12 February 2007 |access-date=28 August 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; There is also concern in the mental health community that the advancement of conversion therapy can cause social harm by disseminating inaccurate views about gender identity, sexual orientation, and the ability of LGBTQ people to lead happy, healthy lives.&lt;ref name="HRC" /&gt;

Some medical bodies prohibit their members from practicing conversion therapy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Albania becomes third European country to ban gay 'conversion therapy' |url=https://www.france24.com/en/20200516-albania-becomes-third-european-country-to-ban-gay-conversion-therapy |access-date=30 June 2022 |work=France 24 |date=16 May 2020 |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==

* [[Christianity and homosexuality]]
* [[Recovering from Religion]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Bibliography==
*{{citation |last=Bright |first=Chuck |title=Deconstructing Reparative Therapy: An Examination of the Processes Involved When Attempting to Change Sexual Orientation |date=December 2004 |journal=Clinical Social Work Journal |volume=32 |issue=4 |doi=10.1007/s10615-004-0543-2 |pages=471–481|s2cid=189871877 }}
*{{citation |last=Cruz |first=David B. |title=Controlling desires: Sexual orientation conversion and the limits of knowledge and law |date=1999 |journal=Southern California Law Review |volume=72 |issue=5 |pages=1297–400 |url=http://www-bcf.usc.edu/~usclrev/pdf/072502.pdf |pmid=12731502 |access-date=20 May 2015 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170919071205/http://www-bcf.usc.edu/~usclrev/pdf/072502.pdf |archive-date=19 September 2017 |url-status=dead }}
*{{citation |last=Drescher |first=Jack |title=I'm Your Handyman: A History of Reparative Therapies |date=June 1998a |journal=Journal of Homosexuality |pmid=9670099 |volume=36 |issue=1 |pages=19–42 |doi=10.1300/J082v36n01_02}}
*{{Citation |last=Drescher |first=Jack |year=2001 |title=Ethical Concerns Raised When Patients Seek to Change Same-Sex Attractions |journal=Journal of Gay &amp; Lesbian Psychotherapy |volume=5 |issue=3/4 |page=183 |doi=10.1300/j236v05n03_11|s2cid=146736819 }}
*{{citation |editor-last=Drescher |editor-first=Jack |editor2-last=Zucker |editor2-first=Kenneth |title=Ex-Gay Research: Analyzing the Spitzer Study and Its Relation to Science, Religion, Politics, and Culture |year=2006 |publisher=Harrington Park Press |location=New York |isbn=978-1-56023-557-6}}
*{{citation |last=Drescher |first=Jack |title=Psychoanalytic Therapy and the Gay Man |journal=American Journal of Psychoanalysis |year=1998b |volume=60 |issue=2 |pages=191–6 |publisher=The Analytic Press |location=Hillsdale, New Jersey |doi=10.1023/a:1001968909523 |pmid=10874429 |isbn=978-0-88163-208-8}}
*{{citation |last=Haldeman |first=Douglas C. |contribution=Sexual orientation conversion therapy for gay men and lesbians: A scientific examination |editor1-last=Gonsiorek |editor1-first=John |editor2-last=Weinrich |editor2-first=James |title=Homosexuality: Research Implications for Public Policy |year=1991 |publisher=Sage Publications, Inc |location=Newbury Park, California |isbn=978-0-8039-3764-2 |contribution-url=http://www.drdoughaldeman.com/doc/ScientificExamination.pdf |access-date=30 May 2010 |archive-date=6 February 2018 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180206023332/http://www.drdoughaldeman.com/doc/ScientificExamination.pdf |url-status=dead }}
*{{citation |last=Waidzunas |first=Tom |title=The Straight Line: How the Fringe Science of Ex-Gay Therapy Reoriented Sexuality |year=2016 |publisher=University of Minnesota Press |location=Minneapolis |isbn=9780816696154}}
*{{cite book |last1=Weindling |first1=Paul|author-link=Paul Weindling |title=Victims and Survivors of Nazi Human Experiments: Science and Suffering in the Holocaust |date=2015 |publisher=[[Bloomsbury Academic]] |isbn=978-1-4411-7990-6 |language=en}}
*{{cite book |last1=Whisnant |first1=Clayton J.|author-link=Clayton J. Whisnant |title=Queer Identities and Politics in Germany: A History, 1880–1945 |date=2016 |publisher=[[Columbia University Press]] |isbn=978-1-939594-10-5 |language=en}}
*{{citation |last=Yoshino |first=Kenji |title=Covering |year=2002 |journal=Yale Law Journal |volume=111 |issue=4 |pages=769–939 |url=http://www.yalelawjournal.org/article/covering|doi=10.2307/797566 |jstor=797566 }}

==Further reading==
*{{cite book |last1=Haldeman |first1=Douglas C. |title=Sexual Orientation and Gender Identity Change Efforts: Evidence, Effects, and Ethics |date=2021 |publisher=Columbia University Press |isbn=978-1-939594-36-5 |language=en}}
*{{cite book |last1=Haldeman |first1=Douglas C. |title=The Case Against Conversion Therapy: Evidence, Ethics, and Alternatives |date=2022 |publisher=American Psychological Association |isbn=978-1-4338-3711-1 |language=en}}

{{LGBT |orientation=yes}}
{{Pseudoscience|orientation=yes}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Conversion Therapy}}
[[Category:Conversion therapy]]
[[Category:Gender identity]]
[[Category:Human rights abuses]]
[[Category:Medical controversies]]
[[Category:Pseudoscience]]
[[Category:Religion and mental health]]
[[Category:Religion and science]]
[[Category:Sexual orientation and medicine]]
[[Category:Violence against LGBT people]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>