<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20161120042852|750505390" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="26410" pageid="26410" ns="0" title="Conversion therapy"><revisions><rev timestamp="2016-11-20T04:58:16Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Conversion therapy''' is psychological treatment or spiritual counseling designed to change a person's [[sexual orientation]] from homosexual or bisexual to heterosexual. Such treatments are controversial&lt;ref name="DrescherandZucker"&gt;{{Harvnb|Drescher|Zucker|2006|pp=126, 175}}&lt;/ref&gt; and are a form of [[pseudoscience]].&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Ford|2001}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name =Cruz /&gt;&lt;ref name=Yoshino /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Haldeman|1991|p=149}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="YouthCrosshairs" /&gt;&lt;ref name=Haldeman1&gt;{{cite web | url=http://drdoughaldeman.com/doc/Pseudo-Science.pdf | title=The Pseudo-science of Sexual Orientation Conversion Therapy | publisher=Institute for Gay and Lesbian Strategic Studies | work=Angles | date=December 1999 | accessdate=January 31, 2015| author=Haldeman, Douglas C.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Medical, scientific, and government organizations in the United States and Britain have expressed concern over conversion therapy and consider it potentially harmful.&lt;ref name="Psych"&gt;{{citation |url=http://www.psych.org/Departments/EDU/Library/APAOfficialDocumentsandRelated/PositionStatements/200001.aspx |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110110120228/http://www.psych.org/Departments/EDU/Library/APAOfficialDocumentsandRelated/PositionStatements/200001.aspx |archivedate=2011-01-10 |title=Position Statement on Therapies Focused on Attempts to Change Sexual Orientation (Reparative or Conversion Therapies) |accessdate=2007-08-28 |date=May 2000 |publisher=[[American Psychiatric Association]] |format=PDF}} archived from [http://www.psych.org/Departments/EDU/Library/APAOfficialDocumentsandRelated/PositionStatements/200001a.aspx the original]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="APA"/&gt;&lt;ref name="NewAPA"&gt;{{citation |url=http://www.apa.org/pi/lgbt/resources/therapeutic-response.pdf |format=PDF |title=Report of the American Psychological Association Task Force on Appropriate Therapeutic Responses to Sexual Orientation |accessdate=2009-09-24 |first=JM |last=Glassgold |publisher=[[American Psychological Association]] |date=2009-08-01 |display-authors=etal}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Memorandum"&gt;{{citation|url=http://www.psychotherapy.org.uk/UKCP_Documents/policy/MoU-conversiontherapy.pdf|title=Memorandum of Understanding on Conversion Therapy in the UK|accessdate=2015-01-19|date=January 2015|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="GMC"&gt;{{citation|url=http://www.gmc-uk.org/news/26043.asp|title=General Medical Council supports Memorandum on conversion therapy in the UK|accessdate=2015-01-19|date=January 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="PSA"&gt;{{citation|url=http://www.professionalstandards.org.uk/footer-pages/news-and-media/latest-news/news-article?id=db1f5a9e-2ce2-6f4b-9ceb-ff0000b2236b|title=Professional Standards Authority supports action by Accredited Registers on Conversion Therapy|accessdate=2015-01-19|date=January 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[American Psychiatric Association]] opposes psychiatric treatment "based upon the assumption that [[homosexuality]] ''per se'' is a mental disorder or based upon the ''[[A priori and a posteriori|a priori]]'' assumption that a patient should change his/her sexual homosexual orientation"&lt;ref name="Psych" /&gt; and describes attempts to change sexual orientation by practitioners as unethical.&lt;ref name="YouthCrosshairs"&gt;Jason Cianciotto and Sean Cahill (2006). [http://www.thetaskforce.org/downloads/reports/reports/YouthInTheCrosshairs.pdf Youth in the crosshairs: the third wave of ex-gay activism]. New York: National Gay and Lesbian Task Force Policy Institute.&lt;/ref&gt; It also states that debates over the [[Social integration|integration]] of gay and lesbian people have obscured science "by calling into question the motives and even the character of individuals on both sides of the issue"&lt;ref name="Psych" /&gt; and that the advancement of conversion therapy may cause social harm by disseminating unscientific views about sexual orientation.&lt;ref name="APA"/&gt; [[Surgeon General of the United States|United States Surgeon General]] [[David Satcher]] in 2001 issued a report stating that "there is no valid scientific evidence that sexual orientation can be changed".&lt;ref name="SurgeonGeneral"&gt;{{citation  |url=http://www.surgeongeneral.gov/library/sexualhealth/call.htm#III |title="The Surgeon General's call to Action to Promote Sexual Health and Responsible Sexual Behavior", A Letter from the Surgeon General U.S. Department of Health and Human Services |accessdate=2007-03-29 |publisher=U. S. Department of Health and Human Services}}&lt;/ref&gt; The highest-profile advocates of conversion therapy today tend to be [[Christian fundamentalism|fundamentalist Christian]] groups and other organizations which use a religious justification for the therapy rather than speaking of homosexuality as "a disease".&lt;ref name="Yoshino"&gt;{{Harvnb|Yoshino|2002}}&lt;/ref&gt; The main organization advocating secular forms of conversion therapy is the [[National Association for Research &amp; Therapy of Homosexuality]] (NARTH), which often partners with religious groups.&lt;ref name="Yoshino" /&gt;

Techniques used in conversion therapy prior to 1981 in the United States and Western Europe included ice-pick [[Lobotomy|lobotomies]]&lt;ref name=Cruz&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Cruz|first1=David B.|title=Controlling Desires: Sexual Orientation Conversion and the Limits of Knowledge and Law|journal=Southern California Law Review|date=1999|volume=72|page=1297|url=http://www-bcf.usc.edu/~usclrev/pdf/072502.pdf|accessdate=May 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Yoshino /&gt;&lt;ref name="Homosexuality and Biology"&gt;{{cite news|last1=Burr|first1=Chandler|title=Homosexuality and Biology|url=http://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/1997/06/homosexuality-and-biology/304683/|accessdate=May 2015|publisher=The Atlantic Magazine|date=June 1997}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Internet Movie Database"&gt;{{cite web|last1=Harrison|first1=James|title=Changing Our Minds: The Story of Dr. Evelyn Hooker|url=http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0103938/combined|website=imdb|publisher=Internet Movie Database|accessdate=May 2015|format=Documentary Film}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Rieber, Inge and Sigusch, Volkmar|title=Psychosurgery on Sex Offenders and Sexual "Deviants" in West Germany|journal=Archives of Sexual Behavior|date=1979|volume=8|issue=6|pages=523–527|url=http://rd.springer.com/article/10.1007%2FBF01541419#page-1|accessdate=May 2015|doi=10.1007/bf01541419}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Dieckmann, G., Horn, H.-J. &amp; Schneider, H.|editor1-last=E. R. Hitchcock, H. T. Ballantine, Jr &amp; B. A. Meyerson|title=Long-term Results of Anterior Hypothalamotomy in Sexual Offences|journal=Modern Concepts in Psychiatric Surgery|date=1979|pages=187–195|publisher=Elsevier/ North Holland Biomedical Press}}&lt;/ref&gt; and chemical castration with hormonal treatment,&lt;ref name=APA-myth&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Milar|first1=Katherine S.|title=The myth buster|journal=Monitor on Psychology, the American Psychological Association|date=February 2011|volume=42|issue=2|page=24|url=http://www.apa.org/monitor/2011/02/myth-buster.aspx|accessdate=May 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Aversion therapy|aversive treatments]], such as "the application of electric shock to the hands and/or genitals," and "nausea-inducing drugs...administered simultaneously with the presentation of homoerotic stimuli," and [[masturbation|masturbatory]] reconditioning. More recent clinical techniques used in the United States have been limited to counseling, visualization, social skills training, [[Psychoanalysis|psychoanalytic therapy]], and spiritual interventions such as "prayer and group support and pressure,"&lt;ref name="haldeman2"&gt;{{Citation|last=Haldeman|first=Douglas C.|title=Gay Rights, Patient Rights: The Implications of Sexual Orientation Conversion Therapy|date=June 2002|postscript=.|journal=Professional Psychology: Research and Practice|volume=33|issue=3|pages=260–264|doi=10.1037/0735-7028.33.3.260}}&lt;/ref&gt; though there are some reports of aversive treatments through unlicensed practice as late as the 1990s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Wareham|first1=Hannah Clay|title=Survivor: MIT grad student Samuel Brinton remembers 'ex-gay' therapy|url=http://www.lgbtqnation.com/2011/08/survivor-mit-grad-student-samuel-brinton-remembers-ex-gay-therapy/|website=lgbtqnation.com|accessdate=6 May 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name =Lyn_Duff /&gt; The term '''reparative therapy''' has been used as a synonym for conversion therapy in general,&lt;ref name="Psych" /&gt; but it has been argued that strictly speaking it refers to a specific kind of therapy associated with [[Elizabeth Moberly]] and [[Joseph Nicolosi]].&lt;ref name="Drescher1998" /&gt;

==History==

The history of conversion therapy can be divided broadly into three periods: an early Freudian period; a period of mainstream approval of conversion therapy, when the mental health establishment became the "primary superintendent" of sexuality; and a post-[[Stonewall riots|Stonewall]] period where the mainstream medical profession disavowed conversion therapy.&lt;ref name="Yoshino" /&gt;

During the earliest parts of psychoanalytic history, analysts granted that homosexuality was non-pathological in certain cases, and the ethical question of whether it ought to be changed was discussed. By the 1920s analysts assumed that homosexuality was pathological and that attempts to treat it were appropriate, although psychoanalytic opinion about changing homosexuality was largely pessimistic. Those forms of homosexuality that were considered perversions were usually held to be uncurable. Analysts‘ tolerant statements about homosexuality arose from recognition of the difficulty of achieving change. Beginning in the 1930s and continuing for roughly twenty years, major changes occurred in how analysts viewed homosexuality, which involved a shift in the rhetoric of analysts, some of whom felt free to ridicule and abuse their gay patients.&lt;ref name="Lewes"&gt;{{Harvnb|Lewes|1988}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Europe===

====Sigmund Freud====
{{Main article|Sigmund Freud's views on homosexuality}}
[[Image:Sigmund Freud LIFE.jpg|thumb|Freud (1856–1939) was skeptical of the possibility of therapeutic conversion.]]

[[Sigmund Freud]] was a physician and the founder of psychoanalysis. Freud stated that homosexuality could sometimes be removed through hypnotic suggestion,&lt;ref name="SigmundFreudOnSexuality"&gt;{{Harvnb|Freud|1991|p=51}}&lt;/ref&gt; and was influenced by [[Eugen Steinach]], a [[Vienna|Viennese]] endocrinologist who transplanted [[testicle]]s from straight men into gay men in attempts to change their sexual orientation,&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|LeVay|1996|p=74,109}}&lt;/ref&gt; stating that his research had “thrown a strong light on the organic determinants of homo-eroticism”.&lt;ref name="SigmundFreudOnSexualityP58"&gt;{{Harvnb|Freud|1991|p=58}}&lt;/ref&gt; Freud cautioned that Steinach's operations would not necessarily make possible a therapy that could be generally applied, arguing that such transplant procedures would be effective in changing homosexuality in men only in cases in which it was strongly associated with physical characteristics typical of women, and that probably no similar therapy could be applied to lesbianism.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Freud|1991|pp=58–59}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Freud|1991|p=400}}&lt;/ref&gt; Steinach’s method was doomed to failure because the [[immune system]] rejects transplanted glands, and was eventually exposed as ineffective and often harmful.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|LeVay|1996|pp=32–33}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Freud‘s main discussion of female homosexuality was the 1920 paper “The Psychogenesis of a Case of Homosexuality in a Woman“, which described his analysis of a young woman who had entered therapy because her parents were concerned that she was a [[lesbian]]. Her father wanted this condition changed. In Freud‘s view, the prognosis was unfavourable because of the circumstances under which she entered therapy, and because homosexuality was not an illness or neurotic conflict. Freud wrote that changing homosexuality was difficult and possible only under unusually favourable conditions, observing that “in general to undertake to convert a fully developed homosexual into a heterosexual does not offer much more prospect of success than the reverse.”&lt;ref name="SigmundFreudCaseHistoriesIIP376"&gt;{{Harvnb|Freud|1991|p=376}}&lt;/ref&gt; Success meant making heterosexual feeling possible, not eliminating homosexual feelings.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Freud|1991|p=375}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Gay people could seldom be convinced that heterosexual sex would provide them with the same pleasure they derived from homosexual sex. Patients often wanted to become heterosexual for reasons Freud considered superficial, including fear of social disapproval, an insufficient motive for change. Some might have no real desire to become heterosexual, seeking treatment only to convince themselves that they had done everything possible to change, leaving them free to return to homosexuality after the failure they expected.&lt;ref name="OconnorandRyan"&gt;{{Harvnb|O'Connor|Ryan|1993|pp=30–47}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="SigmundFreudCaseHistoriesII"&gt;{{Harvnb|Freud|1991|pp=371–400}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="LewesP34"&gt;{{Harvnb|Lewes|1988|p=34}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1935, a mother asked Freud to treat her son. Freud replied in a letter that later became famous:&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Lewes|1988|p=32}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|"I gather from your letter that your son is a homosexual. [...] it is nothing to be ashamed of, no vice, no degradation; it cannot be classified as an illness; we consider it to be a variation of the sexual function, produced by a certain arrest of sexual development. [...] By asking me if I can help [your son], you mean, I suppose, if I can abolish homosexuality and make normal [[heterosexuality]] take its place. The answer is, in a general way we cannot promise to achieve it. In a certain number of cases we succeed in developing the blighted germs of heterosexual tendencies, which are present in every homosexual; in the majority of cases it is no more possible. It is a question of the quality and the age of the individual. The result of treatment cannot be predicted."&lt;ref name="ErnstLFreud"&gt;{{Harvnb|Freud|1992|pp=423–424}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

====Sándor Ferenczi====
[[Sándor Ferenczi]] was an influential psychoanalyst. Ferenczi hoped to cure some kinds of homosexuality completely, but was content in practice with reducing what he considered gay men's hostility to women, along with the urgency of their homosexual desires, and with helping them to become attracted to and potent with women. In his view, a gay man who was confused about his sexual identity and felt himself to be “a woman with the wish to be loved by a man” was not a promising candidate for cure. Ferenczi believed that complete cures of homosexuality might become possible in the future when psychoanalytic technique had been improved. Melanie Klein was a pupil of Ferenczi.&lt;ref name="Lewes" /&gt;&lt;ref name="ErnestJonesVol2"&gt;{{Harvnb|Jones|1955|p=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="MartinStanton"&gt;{{Harvnb|Stanton|1991|p=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Anna Freud====
Daughter of Sigmund Freud, Anna Freud became an influential psychoanalytic theorist in the UK.&lt;ref name="Young-Bruehl" /&gt;

[[Anna Freud]] reported the successful treatment of homosexuals as neurotics in a series of unpublished lectures. In 1949 she published “Some Clinical Remarks Concerning the Treatment of Cases of Male Homosexuality” in the ''[[International Journal of Psychoanalysis]]''. In her view, it was important to pay attention to the interaction of passive and active homosexual fantasies and strivings, the original interplay of which prevented adequate identification with the father. The patient should be told that his choice of a passive partner allows him to enjoy a passive or receptive mode, while his choice of an active partner allows him to recapture his lost masculinity. She claimed that these interpretations would reactivate repressed [[castration complex|castration anxieties]], and childhood narcissistic grandiosity and its complementary fear of dissolving into nothing during heterosexual intercourse would come with the renewal of heterosexual potency.&lt;ref name="Lewes" /&gt;

Anna Freud in 1951 published “Clinical Observations on the Treatment of Male Homosexuality” in ''[[The Psychoanalytic Quarterly]]'' and “Homosexuality” in the ''American Psychoanalytic Association Bulletin.'' In these articles, she insisted on the attainment of full object-love of the opposite sex as a requirement for cure of homosexuality. In 1951 she gave a lecture about treatment of homosexuality which was criticised by [[Edmund Bergler]], who emphasised the oral fears of patients and minimized the importance of the phallic castration fears she had discussed.&lt;ref name="Lewes" /&gt;

Anna Freud recommended in 1956 to a journalist who was preparing an article about psychoanalysis for the London ''[[The Observer|Observer]]'' that she not quote Freud‘s letter to the American mother, on the grounds that “...nowadays we can cure many more homosexuals than was thought possible in the beginning. The other reason is that readers may take this as a confirmation that all analysis can do is to convince patients that their defects or ‘immoralities‘ do not matter and that they should be happy with them. That would be unfortunate.”&lt;ref name="Young-Bruehl"&gt;{{Harvnb|Young-Bruehl|1988|p=327}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Melanie Klein====
[[Melanie Klein]]'s seminal book ''The Psycho-Analysis of Children'', based on lectures given to the [[British Psychoanalytical Society]] in the 1920s, was published in 1932. Klein claimed that entry into the [[Oedipus Complex]] is based on mastery of primitive anxiety from the oral and anal stages. If these tasks are not performed properly, developments in the Oedipal stage will be unstable. Complete analysis of patients with such unstable developments would require uncovering these early concerns. The analysis of homosexuality required dealing with paranoid trends based on the oral stage. ''The Psycho-Analysis of Children'' ends with the analysis of Mr. B., a gay man. Klein claimed that he illustrated pathologies that enter into all forms of homosexuality: a gay man idealizes “the good penis” of his partner to allay the fear of attack he feels due to having projected his paranoid hatred onto the imagined “bad penis“ of his mother as an infant. She stated that Mr. B.’s homosexual behaviour diminished after he overcame his need to adore the “good penis” of an idealized man. This was made possible by his recovering his belief in the good mother and his ability to sexually gratify her with his good penis and plentiful [[semen]].&lt;ref name="Lewes" /&gt;

===United States===

====20th century====
Psychoanalysis started to receive recognition in the United States in 1909, when Sigmund Freud delivered a series of lectures at Clark University in Massachusetts at the invitation of G. Stanley Hall.&lt;ref name="PGay1998"&gt;{{Harvnb|Gay|2006|p=}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1913, [[Abraham Brill]] wrote “The Conception of Homosexuality”, which he published in the ''Journal of the American Medical Association'' and read before the American Medical Association’s annual meeting. Brill criticised physical treatments for homosexuality such as bladder washing, [[rectum|rectal]] massage, and castration, along with [[hypnosis]], but referred approvingly to Freud and Sadger's use of psychoanalysis, calling its results “very gratifying.“&lt;ref name=KatzP149&gt;{{Harvnb|Katz|1976|p=149}}&lt;/ref&gt; Since Brill understood curing homosexuality as restoring heterosexual potency, he claimed that he had cured his patients in several cases, even though many remained homosexual.&lt;ref name="Lewes" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Katz"&gt;{{Harvnb|Katz|1976}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Wilhelm Stekel]], an Austrian, published his views on treatment of homosexuality, which he considered a disease, in the American ''Psychoanalytic Review'' in 1930. Stekel believed that “success was fairly certain“ in changing homosexuality through psychoanalysis provided that it was performed correctly and the patient wanted to be treated. In 1932, the ''Psychoanalytic Quarterly'' published a translation of [[Helene Deutsch]]'s paper “On Female Homosexuality“. Deutsch reported her analysis of a lesbian, who did not become heterosexual as a result of treatment, but who managed to achieve a "positive libidinal relationship" with another woman. Deutsch indicated that she would have considered heterosexuality a better outcome.&lt;ref name="Katz" /&gt;

[[Edmund Bergler]] was the most important psychoanalytic theorist of homosexuality in the 1950s.&lt;ref name="Lewes" /&gt; He was vociferous in his opposition to [[Alfred Kinsey]]. Kinsey's work, and its reception, led Bergler to develop his own theories for treatment, which were essentially to 'blame the victim,' in the evaluation of Jennifer Terry, associate professor of Woman's Studies.&lt;ref name="Terry"/&gt; Bergler claimed that if gay people wanted to change, and the right therapeutic approach was taken, then they could be cured in 90% of cases.&lt;ref name="BerglerTime"&gt;{{Harvnb|Bergler|1956}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bergler used confrontational therapy in which gay people were punished in order to make them aware of their masochism. Bergler openly violated professional ethics to achieve this, breaking patient confidentiality in discussing the cases of patients with other patients, bullying them, calling them liars and telling them they were worthless.&lt;ref name="Terry"&gt;{{Harvnb|Terry|1999|pp=308–314}}&lt;/ref&gt; He insisted that gay people could be cured. Bergler confronted Kinsey because Kinsey thwarted the possibility of cure by presenting homosexuality as an acceptable way of life, which was the basis of the gay rights activism of the time.&lt;ref name="Terry"/&gt;  Bergler popularised his views in the United States in the 1950s using magazine articles and books aimed at non-specialists.&lt;ref name="Terry" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Bergler"&gt;{{Harvnb|Bergler|1962}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1951, the mother who wrote to Freud asking him to treat her son sent Freud's response to the ''American Journal of Psychiatry'', in which it was published.&lt;ref name="Lewes" /&gt; The 1952 first edition of the American Psychiatric Association's [[Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders]] (DSM-I) classified homosexuality as a mental disorder.&lt;ref name="RonaldBayer" /&gt;

During the three decades between Freud's death in 1939 and the [[Stonewall riots]] in 1969, conversion therapy received approval from most of the psychiatric establishment in the United States.&lt;ref name="Drescher"&gt;{{Harvnb|Drescher|1998|pp=19–42}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1962, [[Irving Bieber]] ''et al.'' published ''[[Homosexuality: A Psychoanalytic Study of Male Homosexuals]]'', in which they concluded that "although this change may be more easily accomplished by some than by others, in our judgment a heterosexual shift is a possibility for all homosexuals who are strongly motivated to change."&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Bieber|1962|p=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There was a [[Stonewall riots|riot]] in 1969 at the Stonewall Bar in New York after a police raid. The Stonewall riot acquired symbolic significance for the gay rights movement and came to be seen as the opening of a new phase in the struggle for gay liberation. Following these events, conversion therapy came under increasing attack. Activism against conversion therapy increasingly focused on the DSM's designation of homosexuality as a psychopathology.&lt;ref name="RonaldBayer" /&gt; In 1973, after years of criticism from gay activists and bitter dispute among psychiatrists, the American Psychiatric Association removed homosexuality as a mental disorder from the ''Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders''. Supporters of the change used evidence from researchers such as Kinsey and [[Evelyn Hooker]]. Psychiatrist Robert Spitzer, a member of the APA's Committee on Nomenclature, played an important role in the events that led to this decision. Critics argued that it was a result of pressure from gay activists, and demanded a referendum among voting members of the Association. The referendum was held in 1974 and the APA’s decision was upheld by a 58% majority.&lt;ref name="RonaldBayer"&gt;{{Harvnb|Bayer|1987|p=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The APA removed ego-dystonic homosexuality from the DSM-III-R in 1987 and opposes the diagnosis of either homosexuality or ego-dystonic homosexuality as any type of disorder.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |url=http://www.apa.org/pi/lgbc/policy/diagnoses.html |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070929104523/http://www.apa.org/pi/lgbc/policy/diagnoses.html |archivedate=2007-09-29 |title=APA Policy Statement: Use of Diagnoses "Homosexuality" &amp; "Ego-Dystonic Homosexuality" |accessdate=2007-08-28 |author=APA Council of Representatives |date=1987-08-30 |publisher=American Psychological Association}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Joseph Nicolosi had a significant role in the development of conversion therapy as early as the 1990s, publishing his first book ''Reparative Therapy of Male Homosexuality'' in 1991.&lt;ref name="GLAAD" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Jason Aronson"&gt;{{cite book|last1=Nicolosi|first1=Joseph|title=Reparative Therapy of Male Homosexuality: A New Clinical Approach|date=1997|publisher=Jason Aronson|isbn=9780765701428}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1992, Nicolosi, with [[Charles Socarides]] and Benjamin Kaufman, founded the [[National Association for Research &amp; Therapy of Homosexuality]] (NARTH), an organization that opposes the mainstream medical view of homosexuality and aims to "make effective psychological therapy available to all homosexual men and women who seek change."&lt;ref name="NARTH"&gt;{{citation |url=http://narth.com/menus/goals.html |title=NARTH What We Offer |accessdate=2009-05-25 |publisher=NARTH}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1998, [[Christian right]] groups including the [[Family Research Council]] and the [[American Family Association]] spent $600,000 on advertising promoting conversion therapy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2015/04/how-christians-turned-against-gay-conversion-therapy/390570/|title=How Christians Turned Against Gay Conversion Therapy|author=Jonathan Merritt|date=15 Apr 2015|work=The Atlantic}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[John Paulk]] and his then wife Anne featured in full-page newspaper spreads.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.newsweek.com/ex-ex-gay-pride-249282|title=Ex-Ex-Gay Pride|work=Newsweek|date=1 May 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====21st century====

[[Surgeon General of the United States|United States Surgeon General]] [[David Satcher]] in 2001 issued a report stating that "there is no valid scientific evidence that sexual orientation can be changed".&lt;ref name="SurgeonGeneral"/&gt; The same year, a study by [[Robert Spitzer (psychiatrist)|Robert Spitzer]] concluded that some highly motivated individuals whose orientation is predominantly homosexual can become predominantly heterosexual with some form of reparative therapy.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |url=http://www.springerlink.com/content/rk67865783602411/ |title=Can Some Gay Men and Lesbians Change Their Sexual Orientation? |publisher=Archive of Sexual Behavior |volume = 32 |issue = 5 |year = 2001|format= |doi=10.1023/A:1025647527010 |pmid=14567650 |journal=Arch Sex Behav |pages=403–17; discussion 419–72}}&lt;/ref&gt; Spitzer based his findings on structured interviews with 200 self-selected individuals (143 males, 57 females). He told ''[[The Washington Post]]'' that the study "shows some people can change from gay to straight, and we ought to acknowledge that."&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-srv/aponline/20010509/aponline013921_000.htm |title=Study: Some Gays Can Go Straight |publisher=The Washington Post |date = May 9, 2001}}&lt;/ref&gt; Spitzer's study caused controversy and attracted media attention.&lt;ref name="DrescherandZucker" /&gt; Spitzer recanted his study in 2012,&lt;ref name=spitzer1 /&gt; and apologized to the gay community for making unproven claims of the efficacy of reparative therapy,&lt;ref name=spitzer3 /&gt; calling it his only professional regret.&lt;ref name=spitzer4 /&gt;

The American Psychoanalytic Association (APsaA) spoke against NARTH in 2004, stating "that organization does not adhere to our policy of nondiscrimination and ... their activities are demeaning to our members who are gay and lesbian."&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |last=Crow |first=C. |date=2004-11-20 |title=Irate reader's expert on gays has drawn fire from his peers |publisher=[[San Antonio Express-News]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; The same year, a survey of members of the [[American Psychological Association]] rated reparative therapy as "certainly discredited", though the authors warn that the results should be interpreted carefully as an initial step, not a final word.&lt;ref name="NorcrossKoocherandGarofalo"&gt;{{Harvnb|Norcross|Koocher|Garofalo|2006|pp=512–522}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[American Psychological Association]] in 2007 convened a task force to evaluate its policies regarding reparative therapy.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |url=http://www.washingtontimes.com/news/2007/jul/11/gay-reparative-therapy-under-scrutiny/ |title=Gay reparative therapy under scrutiny |publisher=Washington Times |location=New York |date=July 11, 2007 |accessdate=2009-02-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2008, the organizers of an APA panel on the relationship between religion and homosexuality canceled the event after gay activists objected that "conversion therapists and their supporters on the religious right use these appearances as a public relations event to try and legitimize what they do."&lt;ref name="Plowman"&gt;{{Harvnb|Plowman|2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Johnson"&gt;{{Harvnb|Johnson|2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2009, American Psychological Association stated that it "encourages mental health professionals to avoid misrepresenting the efficacy of sexual orientation change efforts by promoting or promising change in sexual orientation when providing assistance to individuals distressed by their own or others’ sexual orientation and concludes that the benefits reported by participants in sexual orientation change efforts can be gained through approaches that do not attempt to change sexual orientation".&lt;ref name=Apa2009&gt;American Psychological Association: [http://www.apa.org/about/policy/sexual-orientation.aspx Resolution on Appropriate Affirmative Responses to Sexual Orientation Distress and Change Efforts]&lt;/ref&gt;

The ethics guidelines of major mental health organizations in the United States vary from cautionary statements to recommendations that ethical practitioners refrain from practicing conversion therapy (American Psychiatric Association) or from referring patients to those who do ([[American Counseling Association]]).&lt;ref name="Psych" /&gt;&lt;ref name="ACA News" /&gt; In a letter dated February 23, 2011 to the Speaker of the U.S. House of Representatives, the Attorney General of the United States stated "while sexual orientation carries no visible badge, a growing scientific consensus accepts that sexual orientation is a characteristic that is immutable".&lt;ref name="DOMA2011"&gt;[http://www.justice.gov/opa/pr/2011/February/11-ag-223.html Letter from the Attorney General of the United States to the Speaker of the U.S. House of Representatives, RE: DOMA, 23rd February 2011],"Second, while sexual orientation carries no visible badge, a growing scientific consensus accepts that sexual orientation is a characteristic that is immutable."&lt;/ref&gt;

Gay rights groups and groups concerned with mental health fear reparative therapy can make depression or even suicide more likely.  [[Barack Obama|President Obama]] opposes the practise.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-us-canada-32227353 Obama calls for end to 'gay conversion therapies']&lt;/ref&gt;

==Theories and techniques==
{{Wikinews|Dr. Joseph Merlino on sexuality, insanity, Freud, fetishes and apathy}}

===Behavioral modification===
{{Main article|Behavior modification}}

Before the American Psychological Association's 1973 decision to remove homosexuality from the [[Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders|DSM]], practitioners of conversion therapy employed [[Aversion therapy|aversive conditioning techniques]], involving electric shock and nausea-inducing drugs during presentation of same-sex erotic images. Cessation of the aversive stimuli was typically accompanied by the presentation of opposite-sex erotic images, with the objective of strengthening heterosexual feelings. In "Aversion therapy for sexual deviation: a critical review", published in 1966, M. P. Feldman claimed a 58% cure rate, but Douglas Haldeman is skeptical that such stressful methods permit feelings of sexual responsiveness, and notes that Feldman defined success as suppression of homosexuality and increased capacity for heterosexual behavior.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Haldeman|1991|p=152}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Another method used was the covert sensitization method, which involves instructing patients to imagine vomiting or receiving electric shocks, writing that only single case studies have been conducted, and that their results cannot be generalized. Haldeman writes that behavioral conditioning studies tend to decrease homosexual feelings, but do not increase heterosexual feelings, citing Rangaswami's "Difficulties in arousing and increasing heterosexual responsiveness in a homosexual: A case report", published in 1982, as typical in this respect.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Haldeman|1991|pp=152–153}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Haldeman concludes that such methods can be called [[torture]], besides being ineffective.  He writes that "Individuals undergoing such treatments do not emerge heterosexually inclined; rather they become shamed, conflicted, and fearful about their homosexual feelings."&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Haldeman|1991|p=153}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Aversion therapy|Aversive treatments]] sometimes involved the application of electric shock to the hands and/or genitals, or nausea-inducing drugs, administered simultaneously with the presentation of homoerotic stimuli, while other methods included masturbatory reconditioning, visualization, and social skills training. All of these methods were based on the idea that homosexuality is a learned behavior that can be reconditioned.&lt;ref name="haldeman2"/&gt;

===Ex-gay ministry===
[[Image:One by One booth.jpg|thumb|right||[[OneByOne]] booth at a [[Love Won Out]] conference]]
{{Main article|Ex-gay}}

Some sources describe ex-gay ministries as a form of conversion therapy, while others state that ex-gay organizations and conversion therapy are distinct methods of attempting to convert gay people to heterosexuality.&lt;ref name="DrescherandZucker" /&gt;&lt;ref name="APA"&gt;{{citation |url=http://www.apa.org/pi/lgbt/resources/just-the-facts.pdf |title=Just the Facts About Sexual Orientation &amp; Youth: A Primer for Principals, Educators and School Personnel |accessdate=2010-05-14 |year=1999 |publisher=Just the Facts Coalition}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Haldeman|1991|pp=149,156–159}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="JonesandYarhouse"&gt;{{Harvnb|Jones|Yarhouse|2007|p=374}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ex-gay ministries have also been called transformational ministries.&lt;ref name="APA"/&gt; Some state that they do not conduct clinical treatment of any kind.&lt;ref name=ExodusStatement /&gt;  [[Exodus International]] once believed reparative therapy could be a beneficial tool,&lt;ref name=ExodusStatement&gt;{{citation |url=http://exodus.to/content/view/34/117/ |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070928010931/http://exodus.to/content/view/34/117/ |archivedate=2007-09-28 |title=Exodus International Policy Statements |accessdate=2007-08-28 |publisher=Exodus International}}&lt;/ref&gt; but ceased activities in June 2013, issuing a statement which repudiated its aims and apologized for the harm their pursuit has caused to [[LGBT]] people.&lt;ref name=Change&gt;{{citation |url=http://exodusinternational.org/2013/06/i-am-sorry |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130623013409/http://exodusinternational.org/2013/06/i-am-sorry |archivedate=2013-06-23 |title=I am sorry |accessdate=2013-06-22 |publisher=Exodus International}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Psychoanalysis===
{{Main article|Psychoanalysis}}

Haldeman writes that psychoanalytic treatment of homosexuality is exemplified by the work of Irving Bieber and his colleagues in ''Homosexuality: A Psychoanalytic Study of Male Homosexuals''. They advocated long-term therapy aimed at resolving the unconscious childhood conflicts that they considered responsible for homosexuality. Haldeman notes that Bieber's methodology has been criticized because it relied upon a clinical sample, the description of the outcomes was based upon subjective therapist impression, and follow-up data were poorly presented. Bieber reported a 27% success rate from long-term therapy, but only 18% of the patients in whom Bieber considered the treatment successful had been exclusively homosexual to begin with, while 50% had been bisexual. In Haldeman's view, this makes even Bieber's unimpressive claims of success misleading.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Haldeman|1991|pp=150–151}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Haldeman discusses other psychoanalytic studies of attempts to change homosexuality. Curran and Parr's "Homosexuality: An analysis of 100 male cases", published in 1957, reported no significant increase in heterosexual behavior. Mayerson and Lief's "Psychotherapy of homosexuals: A follow-up study of nineteen cases", published in 1965, reported that half of its 19 subjects were exclusively heterosexual in behavior four and a half years after treatment, but its outcomes were based on patient self-report and had no external validation. In Haldeman's view, those participants in the study who reported change were bisexual at the outset, and its authors wrongly interpreted capacity for heterosexual sex as change of sexual orientation.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Haldeman|1991|pp=151, 256}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Reparative therapy===

The term ''reparative therapy'' has been used as a synonym for conversion therapy generally, but Jack Drescher writes that strictly speaking it refers to a specific kind of therapy associated with [[Elizabeth Moberly]] and [[Joseph Nicolosi]].&lt;ref name="Drescher1998" /&gt; Nicolosi's ''Reparative Therapy of Male Homosexuality'' was published in 1991.&lt;ref name="GLAAD"&gt;{{citation |url=http://216.235.201.198/Page.aspx?pid=373|title=GLAAD Media Reference Guide |author=GLAAD |accessdate=September 2006|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The term ''reparative'' refers to Nicolosi's postulate that same-sex attraction is a person's rational and unconscious attempt to “self-repair” feelings of inferiority.&lt;ref name=Hicks_1999&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Hicks|first1=Karolyn Ann|title="Reparative Therapy": Whether Parental Attempts to Change a Child's Sexual Orientation Can Legally Constitute Child Abuse|journal=American University Law Review|date=1999|volume=49|issue=2|pages=505–547|url=http://digitalcommons.wcl.american.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1288&amp;context=aulr|accessdate=May 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Nicolosi|first1=Joseph|title=What Is Reparative Therapy?  Examining the Controversy|url=http://josephnicolosi.com/what-is-reparative-therapy-exa/|accessdate=April 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Bright"&gt;{{Harvnb|Bright|2004|pp=471–481}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Most mental health professionals and the [[American Psychological Association]] consider reparative therapy discredited, but it is still practiced by some.&lt;ref name="Yoshino" /&gt; In 2014 the Republican Party of Texas endorsed "...counseling, which offers reparative therapy and treatment..." in their party platform.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Report of Permanent Committee on Platform and Resolutions As Amended and Adopted by the 2014 State Convention of the Republican Party of Texas|url=http://www.texasgop.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/06/2014-Platform-Final.pdf#page=14|website=texasgop.org|publisher=Republican Party of Texas|accessdate=May 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Psychoanalysts critical of Nicolosi's theories have offered gay-affirmative approaches as an alternative to reparative therapy.&lt;ref name="Drescher1998"&gt;{{Harvnb|Drescher|1998|p=152}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="DomeniciandLesser"&gt;{{Harvnb|Domenici|Lesser|1995|p=119}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Exodus International]] regarded reparative therapy as a useful tool to eliminate "unwanted same-sex attraction"&lt;ref name=ExodusStatement/&gt; but ceased activities in June 2013 and issued a statement repudiating its aims and apologizing for the harm the organization had caused to [[LGBT]] people.&lt;ref name=Change /&gt;

===Sex therapy===
{{Main article|Masters and Johnson}}

Haldeman has described [[Masters and Johnson|William Masters' and Virginia Johnson]]'s work on sexual orientation change as a form of conversion therapy.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Haldeman|1991|pp=149, 154}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In ''Homosexuality in Perspective'', published in 1979, Masters and Johnson viewed homosexuality as the result of blocks that prevented the learning that facilitated heterosexual responsiveness, and described a study of 54 gay men who were dissatisfied with their sexual orientation. The original study did not describe the treatment methodology used, but this was published five years later. John C. Gonsiorek criticized their study on several grounds in 1981, pointing out that while Masters and Johnson stated that their patients were screened for major psychopathology or severe neurosis, they did not explain how this screening was performed, or how the motivation of the patients to change was assessed. Nineteen of their subjects were described as uncooperative during therapy and refused to participate in a follow-up assessment, but all of them were assumed without justification to have successfully changed.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Haldeman|1991|p=154}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Haldeman writes that Masters and Johnson's study was founded upon heterosexist bias, and that it would be tremendously difficult to replicate. In his view, the distinction Masters and Johnson made between "conversion" (helping gay men with no previous heterosexual experience to learn heterosexual sex) and "reversion" (directing men with some previous heterosexual experience back to heterosexuality) was not well founded. Many of the subjects Masters and Johnson labelled homosexual may not have been homosexual, since, of their participants, only 17% identified themselves as exclusively homosexual, while 83% were in the predominantly heterosexual to bisexual range. Haldeman observed that since 30% of the sample was lost to the follow-up, it is possible that the outcome sample did not include any people attracted mainly or exclusively to the same sex. Haldeman concludes that it is likely that, rather than converting or reverting gay people to heterosexuality, Masters and Johnson only strengthened heterosexual responsiveness in people who were already bisexual.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Haldeman|1991|p=155}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Lobotomy===
{{main article|Lobotomy}}

While promoted at the time as a treatment for various psychoses, the effectiveness of lobotomy in changing sexual orientation was already the subject of critical research in 1948 when a single case was investigated by Joseph Friedlander and Ralph Banay.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=FRIEDLANDER JW, BANAY RS.|title=PSYCHOSIS FOLLOWING LOBOTOMY IN A CASE OF SEXUAL PSYCHOPATHY: Report of a Case.|journal=Arch Neurol Psychiatry|date=1948|volume=59|issue=3|pages=302–321|url=http://archneurpsyc.jamanetwork.com/article.aspx?articleid=650572|accessdate=May 2015|doi=10.1001/archneurpsyc.1948.02300380031003}}&lt;/ref&gt;  A video graphically depicting the [[Lobotomy#Transorbital lobotomy|"ice-pick lobotomy"]] of a homosexual man was featured in the documentary film, ''[[Changing Our Minds: The Story of Dr. Evelyn Hooker]]''.&lt;ref name=Yoshino /&gt;&lt;ref name="Homosexuality and Biology"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Internet Movie Database"/&gt;

==Studies of conversion therapy==

==="Can Some Gay Men and Lesbians Change Their Sexual Orientation?"===
In May 2001, [[Robert Spitzer (psychiatrist)|Robert Spitzer]] presented "Can Some Gay Men and Lesbians Change Their Sexual Orientation?" 200 Participants Reporting a Change from Homosexual to Heterosexual Orientation", a study of attempts to change homosexual orientation through ex-gay ministries and conversion therapy, at the American Psychiatric Association's convention in New Orleans. The study was partly a response to the APA's 2000 statement cautioning against clinical attempts at changing homosexuality, and was aimed at determining whether such attempts were ever successful rather than how likely it was that change would occur for any given individual. Spitzer wrote that some earlier studies provided evidence for the effectiveness of therapy in changing sexual orientation, but that all of them suffered from methodological problems.&lt;ref name="DrescherandZucker" /&gt;

In 2012, Spitzer renounced&lt;ref name="Zimmerman"&gt;{{cite news | url= | title=Echoes of an intolerant past | date=May 30, 2012 | agency=Philadelphia Inquirer | author=Zimmerman, Jonathan | location=Philadelphia, PA | quote=prominent psychiatrist Robert Spitzer renounced his famous 2001 study claiming that some gays could become straight via so-called reparative therapy.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Besen"&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/wayne-besen/2012-many-celebrations-few-setbacks_b_2388887.html | title=2012: Many Celebrations, Few Setbacks | date=January 2, 2013 | agency=Huffington Post | accessdate=January 3, 2013 | author=Besen, Wayne | quote=Spitzer renounced his infamous 2001 study that said that some highly motivated homosexuals could change from gay to straight.}}&lt;/ref&gt; and retracted this study, stating "I was quite wrong in the conclusions that I made from this study. The study does not provide evidence, really, that gays can change. And that’s quite an admission on my part."&lt;ref name="spitzer1"&gt;{{cite news| url=http://prospect.org/article/my-so-called-ex-gay-life| work=The American Prospect | title=My So-Called Ex-Gay Life| date=April 11, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Robert Spitzer, Psychiatrist Behind Retracted 'Ex-Gay' Study, Apologizes To Gay Community, Patients|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2012/04/25/robert-spitzer-ex-gay-psychiatrist-apology_n_1453570.html|accessdate=4 January 2013|newspaper=Huffington Post|date=April 25, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="spitzer_reassessed"&gt;{{Citation| author=Robert L. Spitzer | url=http://link.springer.com/content/pdf/10.1007%2Fs10508-012-9966-y | format=PDF| title=Spitzer Reassesses His 2003 Study of Reparative Therapy of Homosexuality | volume=41 | issue=4 | pages=757 | work=Arch Sex Behav | date=2012-05-24 | accessdate=2013-01-03| doi=10.1007/s10508-012-9966-y }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="spitzer2"&gt;{{cite web|last=Besen|first=Wayne|title=TWO Exclusive Video: Interview with Dr. Robert Spitzer Who Discusses Retracting His Infamous ‘Ex-Gay’ Study|url=http://www.truthwinsout.org/blog/2012/05/25725/?utm_source=Exclusive+TWO+Video%3A+Dr.+Spitzer+Retracts+Ex-Gay+Study+and+Slams+Anti-Gay+Groups&amp;utm_campaign=Cleveland+Radio+Host|publisher=[[Truth Wins Out]]. ''truthwinsout.org''|accessdate=30 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; He also apologized to the gay community for making unproven claims of the efficacy of reparative therapy,&lt;ref name="spitzer3"&gt;{{cite web|last=Becker|first=John M.|title=EXCLUSIVE: Dr. Robert Spitzer Apologizes to Gay Community for Infamous ‘Ex-Gay’ Study|url=http://www.truthwinsout.org/news/2012/04/24542/|publisher=truthwinsout.org|accessdate=May 26, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; calling it his only professional regret.&lt;ref name="spitzer4"&gt;{{cite news|last=Carey|first=Benedict|title=Psychiatry Giant Sorry for Backing Gay ‘Cure’|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2012/05/19/health/dr-robert-l-spitzer-noted-psychiatrist-apologizes-for-study-on-gay-cure.html?pagewanted=3&amp;_r=1|accessdate=May 26, 2012|newspaper=nytimes.com|date=May 18, 2012}} archived here [http://www.webcitation.org/67xWBOdwX].&lt;/ref&gt; Spitzer has requested that all "ex-gay" therapy organizations such as [[National Association for Research &amp; Therapy of Homosexuality|NARTH]], [[Parents and Friends of Ex-Gays and Gays|PFOX]], [[American College of Pediatricians]], and [[Focus on the Family]] stop citing his study as evidence for conversion therapy.&lt;ref name="spitzer2" /&gt;

===Analysis of the May 2001 Spitzer report===
The study results were based solely on interviews with the patients and not on any objective observed results.  This made it possible and likely that the report was reporting what the patients wanted their results to be rather than the actual results.

Spitzer reported that after intervention, 66% of the men and 44% of the women had achieved "Good Heterosexual Functioning", which he defined as requiring five criteria (being in a loving heterosexual relationship during the last year, overall satisfaction in emotional relationship with a partner, having heterosexual sex with the partner at least a few times a month, achieving physical satisfaction through heterosexual sex, and not thinking about having homosexual sex more than 15% of the time while having heterosexual sex). He found that the most common reasons for seeking change were lack of emotional satisfaction from gay life, conflict between same-sex feelings and behavior and religious beliefs, and desire to marry or remain married.&lt;ref name="DrescherandZucker" /&gt;&lt;ref name="SpitzerStudy"&gt;{{Harvnb|Spitzer|2003|pp=403–417}}&lt;/ref&gt; This paper was widely reported in the international media and taken up by politicians in the United States, Germany, and Finland, and by conversion therapists.&lt;ref name="DrescherandZucker" /&gt;

In 2003, Spitzer published the paper in the [[Archives of Sexual Behavior]]. Spitzer's study has been criticized on numerous ethical and methodological grounds, and "press releases from both [[NGLTF]] and [[Human Rights Campaign|HRC]] sought to undermine Spitzer's credibility by connecting him politically to right-wing groups that had backed the [[ex-gay movement]]."&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=EGMEAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=PA30&amp;lpg=PA30&amp;dq=spitzer+besen+political&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=LG_lH9nv20&amp;sig=lT8CyIGi5cq2Rn4F3nHJKarnsA0&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=ourKTYbIEaXg0QHRjJWTCQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=4&amp;ved=0CDQQ6AEwAw#v=onepage&amp;q=spitzer%20besen%20political&amp;f=false The Advocate - Jun 19, 2001]&lt;/ref&gt; Gay activists argued that the study would be used by conservatives to undermine gay rights.&lt;ref name="DrescherandZucker" /&gt; Spitzer acknowledged that the study sample consisted of people who sought treatment primarily because of their religious beliefs (93% of the sample), served in various church-related functions, and who publicly spoke in favor of changing homosexual orientation (78%), and thus were strongly motivated to overreport success. Critics felt he dismissed this source of bias, without even attempting to measure [[deception]] or [[self-deception]] (a standard practice in self-reporting psychological tests like [[MMPI-2]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Drescher|Zucker|2006|pp=97}}&lt;/ref&gt; That participants had to rely upon their memories of what their feelings were before treatment may have distorted the findings. It was impossible to determine whether any change that occurred was due to the treatment because it was not clear what it involved and there was no control group.&lt;ref name="DrescherandZucker" /&gt; Spitzer's own data showed that claims of change were reflected mostly in changes in self-labelling and behavior, less in attractions, and least in the homoerotic content during the masturbatory fantasies; this particular finding was consistent with other studies in this area.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Drescher|Zucker|2006|pp=98}}&lt;/ref&gt; Participants may have been bisexual before treatment. Follow-up studies were not conducted.&lt;ref name="DrescherandZucker" /&gt; Spitzer stressed the limitations of his study. Spitzer said that the number of gay people who could successfully become heterosexual was likely to be "pretty low",&lt;ref&gt;Goode, Erica (May 9, 2001). [http://www.nytimes.com/2001/05/09/us/study-says-gays-can-shift-sexual-orientation.html?scp=2&amp;sq=robert%2Bspitzer&amp;st=nyt Study Says Gays Can Shift Sexual Orientation]. New York Times (retrieved 2011).&lt;/ref&gt; and conceded that his subjects were "unusually religious."&lt;ref name="Ucdavis"&gt;{{citation |url=http://psychology.ucdavis.edu/rainbow/html/facts_changing.html |title=Attempts To Change Sexual Orientation |accessdate=2007-08-28 |publisher=[[University of California, Davis]] Department of Psychology}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==="Changing Sexual Orientation: A Consumer's Report"===

Ariel Shidlo and Michael Schroeder found in "Changing Sexual Orientation: A Consumer's Report", a peer-reviewed study of 202 respondents&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Shidlo|Schroeder|2002b}}&lt;/ref&gt; published in 2002, that 88% of participants failed to achieve a sustained change in their sexual behavior and 3% reported changing their orientation to heterosexual. The remainder reported either losing all sexual drive or attempting to remain celibate, with no change in attraction. Some of the participants who failed felt a sense of shame and had gone through conversion therapy programs for many years. Others who failed believed that therapy was worthwhile and valuable. Many respondents felt harmed by the attempt to change, and reported depression, [[suicidal ideation]] and [[Failed suicide attempt|attempts]], [[hypervigilance]] of gender-deviant mannerisms, social isolation, fear of being a child abuser and poor self-esteem. Of the 8 respondents (out of a sample of 202) who reported a change in sexual orientation, 7 worked as ex-gay counselors or group leaders.&lt;ref name="ShidloandSchroeder2002a"&gt;{{Harvnb|Shidlo|Schroeder|2002a}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Medical, scientific and legal views==
{{further information|Biology and sexual orientation|Environment and sexual orientation|Timeline of sexual orientation and medicine|Homosexuality and psychology}}

===United States===

[[File:US states banning conversion therapy.svg|thumb|500px|Map of U.S. cities and counties that have bans on sexual orientation and gender identity change efforts with minors.
{{legend|Purple|Ban on conversion therapy for minors on the basis of sexual orientation and gender identity}}
{{legend|Blue|Ban on conversion therapy for minors on the basis of sexual orientation}}
{{legend|LightGrey|No ban on conversion therapy for minors on the basis of sexual orientation}}]]

====Legal status====

Use of conversion therapy on minors is banned in the states of [[Vermont]],&lt;ref&gt;[https://vtdigger.org/2016/05/25/ban-on-anti-gay-therapy-hailed-as-step-against-hatred/]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.metroweekly.com/2016/05/vermont-governor-signs-conversion-therapy-ban-law/]&lt;/ref&gt; [[California]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Lieu, Ma|title=SB-1172 Sexual orientation change efforts.(2011-2012)|url=https://leginfo.legislature.ca.gov/faces/billNavClient.xhtml?bill_id=201120120SB1172|publisher=State of California, Legislative Counsel|accessdate=6 May 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[New Jersey]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://www.livescience.com/38987-gay-conversion-therapy-facts.html|title = Gay Conversion Therapy: What You Should Know|date = August 19, 2013|accessdate = December 19, 2014|website = Gay Conversion Therapy: What You Should Know|publisher = livescience.com|last = Pappas|first = Stepjanie}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=P.L. 2013, c.150 (A3371)|url=http://www.njleg.state.nj.us/2012/Bills/PL13/150_.HTM|publisher=New Jersey Legislature|accessdate=10 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Illinois]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lgbtqnation.com/2015/08/illinois-enacts-gay-conversion-therapy-ban-for-young-people/ Illinois enacts gay conversion therapy ban for young people] LGBTQ Nation.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lgbtqnation.com/2015/08/illinois-republican-governor-signs-two-more-pro-equality-bills/Illinois Republican governor signs two more pro-equality bills] LGBTQ Nation.&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Oregon]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.oregonlive.com/politics/index.ssf/2015/05/bill_to_ban_conversion_therapy.html|title=Bill to ban conversion therapy for LGBT youth sent to Kate Brown's desk|publisher=Oregon Live|date=May 7, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://olis.leg.state.or.us/liz/2015R1/Measures/Overview/HB2307 HB2307], Oregon Legislature&lt;/ref&gt; as well as the [[District of Columbia]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title= D.C. Act 20-530: Conversion Therapy for Minors Prohibition Act of 2014 |work= Council of the District of Columbia |date= December 22, 2014 |url= http://www.dcregs.dc.gov/Gateway/NoticeHome.aspx?noticeid=5259066 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In December 2015, following the death of transgender teenager [[Leelah Alcorn]], [[Cincinnati, Ohio]] by a vote of 7-2, became the first city within the [[United States]] to outlaw all therapy designed to change sexual orientation or gender identity.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usatoday.com/story/news/nation-now/2015/12/09/cincinnati-bans-gay-conversion-therapy/77075540/ Cincinnati bans gay 'conversion' therapy]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.advocate.com/health/2015/12/09/cincinnati-approves-ex-gay-therapy-ban Cincinnati Approves 'Ex-Gay' Therapy Ban]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cincinnati.com/story/news/politics/2015/12/09/7-2-vote-imposes-ban-conversion-therapy-cincinnati/76993924/ Council votes to ban gay 'conversion' therapy in Cincinnati]&lt;/ref&gt; On June 8, 2016, [[Miami Beach, Florida|Miami Beach]] voted to ban therapies designed to change sexual orientation or gender identity. The ban was sponsored by Commissioner John Elizabeth Alemàn and was unanimously approved by the city commission. Miami Beach thus became the first city in Florida to ban the use of conversion therapy on LGBT minors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.miamiherald.com/news/local/community/miami-dade/miami-beach/article82644677.html |title=Miami Beach says no more conversion therapy for youths under 18 |publisher=[[Miami Herald]] |date=June 8, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://health.wusf.usf.edu/post/miami-beach-bans-conversion-therapy-minors |author=Ramos, Lisann |title=Miami Beach Bans Conversion Therapy For Minors |publisher=Health News Florida |date=June 10, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; On August 1, 2016 [[Seattle, Washington|Seattle]] voted unanimously by all nine commissioners to ban therapy designed to change the sexual orientation or gender identity of minors, becoming the third city in the United States to do so.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.seattlepi.com/local/article/Seattle-bans-gay-conversion-therapy-9009149.php]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://seattle.legistar.com/View.ashx?M=F&amp;ID=4614366&amp;GUID=3D567C88-EFC9-4A60-917C-37A03881B956 Signed Ord 125000]&lt;/ref&gt;

Legal challenges against the ban in New Jersey were defeated: The Federal court in New Jersey upheld the state's ban on conversion therapy for minors. United States District Court Judge [[Freda L. Wolfson]] rejected the claim of New Jersey parents that it violated their rights by keeping them from treating their child for same-sex attraction.  In ''Does v. Christie'', Wolfson wrote: "Surely, the fundamental rights of parents do not include the right to choose a specific medical or mental health treatment that the state has reasonably deemed harmful or ineffective." Wolfson added, "To find otherwise would create unimaginable and unintentional consequences."

On February 10, 2015, a New Jersey Superior Court judge ruled that the offering of conversion services on the basis of a description of homosexuality as abnormal or a mental illness is a violation of the New Jersey Consumer Fraud Act.&lt;ref name="gallagher"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.njlawjournal.com/this-weeks-news/id=1202717571907/Judge-Says-Gay-Conversion-Therapy-is-Consumer-Fraud?mcode=1202617207189&amp;curindex=0|title=Gay 'Conversion Therapy' Consumer Fraud Ruling First in U.S.|author=Mary Pat Gallagher|work=New Jersey Law Journal|accessdate=5 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; An article about the ruling on the New Jersey Law Journal web site said the decision is "believed to be the first of its kind in the U.S."&lt;ref name="gallagher"/&gt;

====Status by Health organizations====
National health organizations in the United States have announced that there has been no scientific demonstration of conversion therapy's efficacy in the last forty years.&lt;ref name="APA"/&gt;&lt;ref name=APA-Answers&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.apa.org/topics/lgbt/orientation.aspx | title=Answers to Your Questions: For a Better Understanding of Sexual Orientation and Homosexuality | publisher=American Psychological Association | date=2008 | accessdate=January 31, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name =APA_Position/&gt;&lt;ref name="PsychNews"&gt;{{citation |last=H. |first=K |title=APA Maintains Reparative Therapy Not Effective |url=http://www.psychiatricnews.org/pnews/99-01-15/therapy.html |publisher=Psychiatric News (news division of the American Psychiatric Association) |date=1999-01-15 |accessdate=2007-08-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;
They find that conversion therapy is ineffective, risky and can be harmful. Anecdotal claims of cures are counterbalanced by assertions of harm, and the American Psychiatric Association, for example, cautions ethical practitioners under the [[Hippocratic oath]] to do no harm and to refrain from attempts at conversion therapy.&lt;ref name =APA_Position&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.psych.org/Departments/EDU/Library/APAOfficialDocumentsandRelated/PositionStatements/200001a.aspx |title=Therapies Focused on Attempts to Change Sexual Orientation |publisher=Psych.org |accessdate=2011-07-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Mainstream medical bodies state that conversion therapy can be harmful because it may exploit guilt and anxiety, thereby damaging self-esteem and leading to depression and even suicide.&lt;ref name="nytconversion"&gt;{{citation |last=Luo |first=Michael |title=Some Tormented by Homosexuality Look to a Controversial Therapy |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2007/02/12/nyregion/12group.html?_r=2&amp;oref=slogin&amp;oref=slogin |publisher=''The New York Times'' |page=1 |date=2007-02-12 |accessdate=2007-08-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; There is also concern in the mental health community that the advancement of conversion therapy can cause social harm by disseminating inaccurate views about sexual orientation and the ability of gay and bisexual people to lead happy, healthy lives.&lt;ref name="APA"/&gt;

Mainstream health organizations critical of conversion therapy include the [[American Medical Association]],&lt;ref name="AmericanMedicalAssociation"&gt;{{citation |url=http://www.ama-assn.org/ama/pub/about-ama/our-people/member-groups-sections/glbt-advisory-committee/ama-policy-regarding-sexual-orientation.shtml |title=American Medical Association policy regarding sexual orientation |accessdate=2007-07-30 |date=2007-07-11 |publisher=American Medical Association}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[American Psychiatric Association]], the [[American Psychological Association]], the [[American Association for Marriage and Family Therapy]],&lt;ref name="McGeorgeCarlson2015"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=McGeorge|first1=Christi R.|last2=Carlson|first2=Thomas Stone|last3=Toomey|first3=Russell B.|title=An Exploration of Family Therapists' Beliefs about the Ethics of Conversion Therapy: The Influence of Negative Beliefs and Clinical Competence With Lesbian, Gay, and Bisexual Clients|journal=Journal of Marital and Family Therapy|volume=41|issue=1|year=2015|pages=42–56|issn=0194-472X|doi=10.1111/jmft.12040}}&lt;/ref&gt; the [[American Counseling Association]], the [[National Association of Social Workers]], the [[American Academy of Pediatrics]], the [[National Association of School Psychologists]], and the American Academy of Physician Assistants.&lt;ref name="APA"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Aap"&gt;{{citation |author=Committee on Adolescence |title=Homosexuality and Adolesence |year=1993 |journal=Pediatrics, Official Journal of the American Academy of Pediatrics |volume=92 |pages=631–634 |url=http://pediatrics.aappublications.org/cgi/reprint/92/4/631.pdf |accessdate=2007-08-28 |format=PDF |issue=4}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |url=http://www.spiritindia.com/health-care-news-articles-10085.html |title=Physician Assistants vote on retail clinics, reparative therapy |accessdate=2007-08-28 |publisher=SpiritIndia.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The American Psychological Association undertook a study of the peer-reviewed literature in the area of [[sexual orientation change efforts]] (SOCE) and found a myriad of issues with the procedures used in conducting the research. The taskforce did find that some participants experienced a lessening of same sex attraction and arousal, but that these instances were "rare" and "uncommon." The taskforce concluded that, "given the limited amount of methodically sound research, claims that recent SOCE is effective are not supported.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.apa.org/pi/lgbt/resources/therapeutic-response.pdf Appropriate Therapeutic Responses to Sexual Orientation] Page 2&lt;/ref&gt; Two issues with SOCE claims are that conversion therapists falsely assume that homosexuality is a mental disorder and that their research focuses almost exclusively on gay men and rarely includes lesbians.&lt;ref name="Haldeman1" /&gt;&lt;ref name="APA"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Bright" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Ucdavis" /&gt;

===Self-determination===

The [[American Psychological Association]]'s code of conduct states: "Psychologists respect the dignity and worth of all people, and the rights of individuals to privacy, confidentiality, and self-determination," but also: "Psychologists are aware that special safeguards may be necessary to protect the rights and welfare of persons or communities whose vulnerabilities impair autonomous decision making."&lt;ref name="apacode"&gt;{{cite web
|url = http://www.apa.org/ethics/code2002.html#principle_e
|archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20070807183620/http://www.apa.org/ethics/code2002.html
|archivedate=August 7, 2007 |title = Ethical Principles of Psychologists and Code of Conduct
|accessdate = 2007-08-28
|date = 2003-06-01
|publisher = American Psychological Association
}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[American Counseling Association]] says that "it is of primary importance to respect a client's autonomy to request a referral for a service not offered by a counselor."&lt;ref name="ACA News"&gt;{{citation |url=http://www.counseling.org/PressRoom/NewsReleases.aspx?AGuid=b68aba97-2f08-40c2-a400-0630765f72f4
|last1=Whitman |first1=Joy S. |last2=Glosoff |first2=Harriet L. |last3=Kocet |first3=Michael M. |last4=Tarvydas |first4=Vilia |title=Ethical issues related to conversion or reparative therapy |accessdate=2007-08-28 |date=2006-05-22 |publisher=American Counseling Association}}&lt;/ref&gt;  No one should be forced to attempt to change their sexual orientation against their will, including children being forced by their parents.&lt;ref name=apa1997&gt;{{Citation |url=http://www.apa.org/pi/sexual.html |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090324034818/http://www.apa.org/pi/sexual.html |archivedate=2009-03-24 |title=Resolution on Appropriate Therapeutic Responses to Sexual Orientation |accessdate=2007-08-28 |date=1997-08-14 |publisher=American Psychological Association}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Supporters of SOCE focus on patient self-determination when discussing whether therapy should be available. Mark Yarhouse, of [[Pat Robertson]]'s [[Regent University]], wrote that "psychologists have an ethical responsibility to allow individuals to pursue treatment aimed at curbing experiences of same-sex attraction or modifying same-sex behaviors, not only because it affirms the client's rights to dignity, autonomy, and agency, as persons presumed capable of freely choosing among treatment modalities and behavior, but also because it demonstrates regard for diversity."&lt;ref name=Right2Choose&gt;{{Citation
 | doi = 10.1037/h0087753
 | last = Yarhouse
 | first = Mark
 |date=Summer 1998
 | title = When Clients Seek Treatment for Same-Sex Attractions: Ethical Issues in the "Right to Choose" Debate
 | journal = Psychotherapy: Theory, Research, Practice, Training
 | volume = 35
 | issue = 2
 | pages = 248–259
 | postscript = .
 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Yarhouse and Throckmorton, of the private Christian school [[Grove City College]], argue that the procedure should be available out of respect for a patient’s values system and because they find evidence that it can be effective.&lt;ref name="EthicalIssues"&gt;{{Harvnb|Yarhouse|Throckmorton|2002|pp=66–75}}&lt;/ref&gt; Haldeman similarly argues for a client's right to access to therapy if requested from a [[Informed consent|fully informed]] position: "For some, religious identity is so important that it is more realistic to consider changing sexual orientation than abandoning one's religion of origin... and if there are those who seek to resolve the conflict between sexual orientation and spirituality with conversion therapy, they must not be discouraged."&lt;ref name="haldeman2"/&gt;

In response to Yarhouse's paper, Jack Drescher argued that "any putative ethical obligation to refer a patient for reparative therapy is outweighed by a stronger ethical obligation to keep patients away from mental health practitioners who engage in questionable clinical practices."&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Drescher|2001}}&lt;/ref&gt; Chuck Bright wrote that refusing to endorse a procedure that "has been deemed unethical and potentially harmful by most medical and nearly every professional psychotherapy regulating body cannot be justifiably identified as prohibiting client self-determination."&lt;ref name="Bright" /&gt;  Some commentators, recommending a hard stand against the practice, have found therapy inconsistent with a psychologist's ethical duties because "it is more ethical to let a client continue to struggle honestly with her or his identity than to collude, even peripherally, with a practice that is discriminatory, oppressive, and ultimately ineffective in its own stated ends."&lt;ref name=PurpleMenace&gt;{{Citation
 | last = Tozer
 | first = Erinn E.
 | author2 = McClanahan, Mary K.
 | year = 1999
 | title = Treating the Purple Menace: Ethical Considerations of Conversion Therapy and Affirmative Alternatives
 | journal = The Counseling Psychologist
 | volume = 27
 | issue = 5
 | pages = 722–742
 | doi = 10.1177/0011000099275006
 | postscript = .
 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  They argue that clients who request it do so out of social pressure and internalized homophobia, pointing to evidence that rates of depression, anxiety, alcohol and drug abuse and suicidal feelings are roughly doubled in those who undergo therapy.&lt;ref name="ShidloandSchroeder2002a"/&gt;

Haldeman argues that, due to concern for people whose "spiritual or religious concerns" may assume priority over their sexual orientation, mental health organizations do not ban conversion therapy outright.&lt;ref name="haldeman2"/&gt;

===Ethics guidelines===
In 1998, the [[American Psychiatric Association]] issued a statement opposing any treatment which is based upon the assumption that homosexuality is a mental disorder or that a person should change their orientation, but did not have a formal position on other treatments that attempt to change a person's sexual orientation. In 2000, they augmented that statement by saying that as a general principle, a therapist should not determine the goal of treatment, but recommends that ethical practitioners refrain from attempts to change clients' sexual orientation until more research is available.&lt;ref name="Psych" /&gt;

The [[American Counseling Association]] has stated that they do not condone any training to educate and prepare a counselor to practice conversion therapy. Counselors who do offer training in conversion therapy must inform students that the techniques are unproven. They suggest counselors do not refer clients to a conversion therapist or to proceed cautiously once they know the counselor fully informs clients of the unproven nature of the treatment and the potential risks. However, "it is of primary importance to respect a client's autonomy to request a referral for a service not offered by a counselor." A counselor performing conversion therapy must provide complete information about the treatment, offer referrals to gay-affirmative counselors, discuss the right of clients, understand the client's request within a cultural context, and only practice within their level of expertise.&lt;ref name="ACA News"/&gt;

[[NARTH]] stated in 2012 that refusing to offer therapy aimed at change to a client who requests it, and telling them that their only option is to claim a gay identity, could also be considered ethically unacceptable.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://narth.com/2012/01/narth-statement-on-sexual-orientation-change |title=Statement on Sexual Orientation Change |publisher=NARTH |accessdate=2012-07-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2012 the [[British Psychological Society]] issued a position statement opposing any treatment that are based on an assumption that non-heterosexual orientations are pathological.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://www.bps.org.uk/system/files/images/therapies_attempting_to_change_sexual_orientation.pdf|title = Position Statement: Therapies Attempting to Change Sexual Orientation|date = |accessdate = |website = |publisher = |last = British Psychological Society}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A 2013 article by the Committee on Adolescence of the [[American Academy of Pediatrics]] stated "Referral for “conversion” or “reparative therapy” is never indicated; therapy is not effective and may be harmful to LGBTQ individuals by increasing internalized stigma, distress, and depression."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Office-Based Care for Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, Transgender, and Questioning Youth|journal=Pediatrics|volume=132|issue=1|year=2013|pages=198–203|issn=0031-4005|doi=10.1542/peds.2013-1282}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The Health of Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, and Transgender People: Building a Foundation for Better Understanding|date=March 31, 2011|url=http://books.nap.edu/openbook.php?record_id=13128&amp;page=146|page=146|publisher=[[Institute of Medicine]]/[[National Academies Press]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2014 the [[American Association of Christian Counselors]] amended its code of ethics to eliminate the promotion of conversion therapy for homosexuals and encouraged them to be [[celibacy|celibate]] instead.&lt;ref name="religionnews1"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.religionnews.com/2014/08/04/gay-christian-celibate-changing-face-homosexuality-debate/ |title=Gay, Christian and ... celibate: The changing face of the homosexuality debate - Religion News Service |publisher=Religionnews.com |date= |accessdate=2015-07-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; An article in the [[American Medical Association]]'s Journal of Ethics argues that if a pediatrician learns that parents of a 12 year old patient seek conversion therapy, the pediatrician can advise against "the ineffective and potentially harmful intervention" while being [[Cultural competence in health care|culturally sensitive]] of their religious objections to homosexuality. The authors argue that the doctor's [[medical ethics]] means they should place the interests of the patient above the cultural sensitivities of the parents, and [[Confidentiality#Medical confidentiality|confidentially]] counsel the patient about resources for LGBT youth facing bullying, and advise the parents about resources for parents of LGBT children.&lt;ref name="pmid25397646"&gt;{{cite journal|vauthors=Zachariah P, Blaschke GS, Weddle M | title=A request for "conversion therapy". | journal=Virtual Mentor | year= 2014 | volume= 16 | issue= 11 | pages= 877–83 | pmid=25397646 | doi=10.1001/virtualmentor.2014.16.11.ecas2-1411 | pmc= | url=http://journalofethics.ama-assn.org/2014/11/ecas2-1411.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2014 major therapy professional bodies in the United Kingdom issued a joint consensus statement opposing conversion therapy. Professional bodies supporting the statement included the [[United Kingdom Council for Psychotherapy|UK Council for Psychotherapy]], the [[British Psychoanalytic Council]], the [[Royal College of Psychiatrists]], the [[British Association for Counselling and Psychotherapy]], the [[British Psychological Society]] and the National Counselling Society.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://www.psychotherapy.org.uk/UKCP_Documents/policy/Conversion%20therapy.pdf|title = Conversion therapy: a consensus statement|date = |accessdate = |website = |publisher = }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2015, with support of the UK Government's [[Department of Health (United Kingdom)|Department of Health]] a wide range of UK organisations signed a memorandum of understanding (MoU) setting out an agreed framework for activities by parties concerned to help address the issues raised by the practice of conversion therapy in the UK. In addition to many of the professional bodies that previously issued the consensus statement, signatories included the UK Association of Christian Counsellors, the [[Royal College of General Practitioners]], [[NHS England]] and [[NHS Scotland]]. The signatory organisations recognised a shared commitment to protecting the public from the risks of conversion therapy. They committed to raise awareness among healthcare professionals and psychological therapists of ethical issues involved in conversion therapy and to provide training to enable therapists to support clients in distress in an appropriate way.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://www.psychotherapy.org.uk/UKCP_Documents/policy/MoU-conversiontherapy.pdf|title = Memorandum of Understanding on conversion therapy in the UK|date = |accessdate = |website = |publisher = }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===International medical views===
{{See also|LGBT rights in the United Kingdom}}
The [[World Health Organization]]'s [[ICD-10]], which along with the [[DSM-IV]] is widely used internationally, states that "sexual orientation by itself is not to be regarded as a disorder". It lists [[ego-dystonic sexual orientation]] as a disorder instead, which it defines as occurring where "the gender identity or sexual preference (heterosexual, homosexual, bisexual, or prepubertal) is not in doubt, but the individual wishes it were different because of associated psychological and behavioural disorders, and may seek treatment in order to change it."&lt;ref name="icd"&gt;{{citation |url=http://www.who.int/classifications/apps/icd/icd10online/?gf60.htm+f661 |title=ICD-10, Chapter V: Mental and behavioural disorders: Disorders of adult personality and behaviour |year=2007 |accessdate=2007-08-28 |publisher=World Health Organization}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2012, the [[Pan American Health Organization]] (the North and South American branch of the World Health Organization) released a statement cautioning against services that purport to "cure" people with non-heterosexual sexual orientations as they lack medical justification and represent a serious threat to the health and well-being of affected people, and noted that the global scientific and professional consensus is that homosexuality is a normal and natural variation of [[human sexuality]] and cannot be regarded as a pathological condition. The Pan American Health Organization further called on governments, academic institutions, professional associations and the media to expose these practices and to promote respect for diversity. The World Health Organization affiliate further noted that gay minors have sometimes been forced to attend these "therapies" involuntarily, being deprived of their liberty and sometimes kept in isolation for several months, and that these findings were reported by several [[United Nations]] bodies. Additionally, the Pan American Health Organization recommended that such practices be denounced and subject to sanctions and penalties under national legislation, as they constitute a violation of the ethical principles of health care and violate [[human rights]] that are protected by international and regional agreements.&lt;ref name=PAHO&gt;{{cite web|title="Therapies" to change sexual orientation lack medical justification and threaten health|url=http://new.paho.org/hq/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=6803&amp;Itemid=1926|publisher=Pan American Health Organization|accessdate=May 26, 2012}} archived here [http://www.webcitation.org/67xKQyixE].&lt;/ref&gt;

The development of theoretical models of sexual orientation in countries outside the United States that have established mental health professions often follows the history within the U.S. (although often at a slower pace), shifting from pathological to non-pathological conceptions of homosexuality.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |title=Special Issue on the Mental Health Professions and Homosexuality |year=2003 |journal=Journal of Gay &amp; Lesbian Psychotherapy |volume=7 |issue=1/2 |publisher= Haworth Medical Press}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Request quotation|date=November 2010}}

===Legal views===
{{Hatnote|For the legal status of conversion therapy and other sexual orientation change efforts, see [[Sexual orientation change efforts#Legal status]].}}
On June 25, 2015 a New Jersey jury found the Jewish conversion therapy organization, JONAH, guilty of consumer fraud for promising to be able to change its client’s sexual urges and determined its commercial practices to be unconscionable.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Livio|first1=Susan K.|title=Group claiming to turn gay men straight committed consumer fraud, N.J. jury says|url=http://www.nj.com/politics/index.ssf/2015/06/gay_conversion_therapy_fraud_trial_verdict.html|website=NJ.com True Jersey|publisher=New Jersey On-Line LLC|accessdate=23 September 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In a 1997 U.S. case, the [[Ninth Circuit]] addressed conversion therapy in the context of an asylum application. A Russian citizen "had been apprehended by the Russian militia, registered at a clinic as a 'suspected lesbian,' and forced to undergo treatment for lesbianism, such as 'sedative drugs' and hypnosis.... The Ninth Circuit held that the conversion treatments to which Pitcherskaia had been subjected constituted mental and physical torture. The court rejected the argument that the treatments to which Pitcherskaia had been subjected did not constitute persecution because they had been intended to help her, not harm her, and stated "human rights laws cannot be sidestepped by simply couching actions that torture mentally or physically in benevolent terms such as 'curing' or 'treating' the victims."&lt;ref name="Gans"&gt;{{citation |last=Gans |first=Laura A. |title=Inverts, Perverts, and Converts: Sexual Orientation Conversion Therapy and Liability |date=Winter 1999 |journal=The Boston University Public Interest Law Journal |volume=8}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1993, the Superior Court of San Francisco - Family Court placed 15-year old lesbian [[Lyn Duff]] under the guardianship of a foster couple after her mother committed her to Rivendell Psychiatric Center in West Jordan, Utah, where she allegedly endured physical abuse under the guise of conversion therapy.  Lyn Duff's petition to leave her mother was granted without court opinion.&lt;ref name=Lyn_Duff&gt;{{cite web|last1=Ocamb|first1=Karen|title=Shannon Minter on NARTH Lawsuit Against Psychological Child Abuse Law|url=http://www.bilerico.com/2012/11/shannon_minter_on_narth_lawsuit_against_psychologi.php|website=www.bilerico.com|publisher=The Bilerico Project|accessdate=May 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Molnar&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Molnar|first1=Beth|title=JUVENILES AND PSYCHIATRIC INSTITUTIONALIZATION: Toward Better Due Process and Treatment Review in the United States|journal=Health and Human Rights (Harvard College)|volume=2|issue=2|pages=98–116|url=http://www.hhrjournal.org/wp-content/uploads/sites/13/2014/03/8-Molnar.pdf|accessdate=May 2015|doi=10.2307/4065274}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Duff|first1=Lyn|title=I was a teenage test case|journal=California Lawyer Magazine|date=May 1996|page=46}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Orly&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Rachmilovitz|first1=Orly|title=Masters of Their Own Desiny: Children's Identities, Parents' Assimilation Demands, and State Intervention|journal=Boston University School of Law, Dissertation|date=August 13, 2013|volume=Public Law and Legal Theory Paper No. 13-35|url=http://www.bu.edu/law/faculty/scholarship/workingpapers/documents/RachmilovitzO081313.pdf|accessdate=May 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[LGBT rights opposition]]
*[[Sexual orientation change efforts]]

==Notes==
{{reflist|2}}

==Bibliography==
*{{citation |last=Bayer |first=Ronald |title=Homosexuality and American Psychiatry: The Politics of Diagnosis |year=1987 |publisher=Princeton University Press |location=Princeton |isbn=0-691-02837-0}}
*{{citation |last=Bergler |first=Edmund |title=Curable Disease? |journal=Time |date=10 Dec 1956 |url=http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,808760-2,00.html}}
*{{citation |last=Bergler |first=Edmund |title=Homosexuality: disease or way of life? |year=1962 |publisher=Collier Books}}
*{{citation |last=Bieber |first=Irving |title=Homosexuality: A Psychoanalytic Study of Male Homosexuals |publisher=Basic Books Inc |year=1962}}
*{{citation |last=Bright |first=Chuck |title=Deconstructing Reparative Therapy: An Examination of the Processes Involved When Attempting to Change Sexual Orientation |date=December 2004 |journal=Clinical Social Work Journal |volume=32 |issue=4 |doi=10.1007/s10615-004-0543-2 |pages=471–481}}
*{{citation |last=Cruz |first=David B. |title=CONTROLLING DESIRES: SEXUAL ORIENTATION CONVERSION AND THE LIMITS OF  KNOWLEDGE AND LAW|date=1999 |journal=Southern California Law Review|volume=72 |url=http://www-bcf.usc.edu/~usclrev/pdf/072502.pdf|page=1297}}
*{{citation |last1=Domenici |first1=Thomas |last2=Lesser |first2=Ronnie C. |title=Disorienting Sexuality: Psychoanalytic Reappraisals of Sexual Identities |year=1995 |publisher=Routledge |location=New York |isbn=0-415-91198-2}}
*{{citation |last=Drescher |first=Jack |title=I'm Your Handyman: A History of Reparative Therapies |date=June 1998 |journal=Journal of Homosexuality |pmid=9670099 |volume=36 |issue=1 |pages=19–42 |doi=10.1300/J082v36n01_02}}
*{{Citation |last=Drescher |first=Jack |year=2001 |title=Ethical Concerns Raised When Patients Seek to Change Same-Sex Attractions |journal=Journal of Gay &amp; Lesbian Psychotherapy |volume=5 |issue=3/4 |page=183 |publisher= Haworth Press |doi=10.1300/j236v05n03_11}}
*{{citation |editor-last=Drescher |editor-first=Jack |editor2-last=Zucker |editor2-first=Kenneth |title=Ex-Gay Research: Analyzing the Spitzer Study and Its Relation to Science, Religion, Politics, and Culture |year=2006 |publisher=Harrington Park Press |location=New York |isbn=1-56023-557-8}}
*{{citation |last=Drescher |first=Jack |title=Psychoanalytic Therapy and the Gay Man |year=1998 |publisher=The Analytic Press |location=Hillsdale, New Jersey |isbn=0-88163-208-2}}
*{{citation |last=Ellis |first=Albert |title=Homosexuality: Its Causes and Cure |year=1965 |publisher=Lyle Stuart Inc. |location=New York |lccn=65-12351}}
*{{citation |last1=Ford|first1=Jeffry G.|title=Healing homosexuals: A psychologist's journey through the ex-gay movement and the pseudo-science of reparative therapy |journal=Journal of Gay &amp; Lesbian Psychotherapy |volume=5 |issue= 3–4 |year=2001 |pages=69–86 |doi= 10.1300/J236v05n03_06}}
*{{citation |last=Freud |first=Sigmund |title=On Sexuality: Volume 7 |year=1991 |publisher=Penguin Books |location=London |isbn=0-14-013797-1}}
*{{citation |last=Freud |first=Ernst L. |title=Letters of Sigmund Freud |year=1992 |publisher=Dover Publications, Inc |location=New York |isbn=0-486-27105-6}}
*{{citation |last=Gay |first=Peter |title=Freud: A Life for Our Time |year=2006 |publisher=Papermac |location=London |isbn=0333486382}}
*{{citation |last=Haldeman |first=Douglas C. |contribution=Sexual orientation conversion therapy for gay men and lesbians: A scientific examination |editor1-last=Gonsiorek |editor1-first=John |editor2-last=Weinrich |editor2-first=James |title=Homosexuality: Research Implications for Public Policy |year=1991 |publisher=Sage Publications, Inc |location=Newbury Park, California |isbn=0-8039-3764-4 |contribution-url=http://www.drdoughaldeman.com/doc/ScientificExamination.pdf}}
*{{citation |last=Haldeman |first=Douglas C. |title=Gay Rights, Patient Rights: The Implications of Sexual Orientation Conversion Therapy |date=June 2002 |journal=Professional Psychology: Research and Practice |volume=33 |issue=3 |pages= 260–264|doi=10.1037/0735-7028.33.3.260 |url=http://www.drdoughaldeman.com/doc/GayRightsPatientRights.pdf}}
*{{citation |last=Hooker |first=Evelyn |date=March 1957 |title=The Adjustment of the Male Overt Homosexual |journal=Journal of projective techniques |volume=21 |issue=1 |pages=18–31 |pmid=13417147|doi=10.1080/08853126.1957.10380742 }}
*{{citation |last=Jones |first=Ernest |title=The Life and Work of Sigmund Freud, Volume 2 |year=1955 |publisher=Basic Books |location=New York |isbn=&lt;!-- Not given --&gt;}}
*{{citation |last1=Jones|first1= S. L.|last2=Yarhouse |first2=A. M. |year=2007 |title=Ex‐gays? A longitudinal study of religiously mediated change in sexual orientation |location=Downers Grove, IL |publisher= [[InterVarsity Press]] }}
*{{citation |last=Johnson |first=Chris |title=Robinson backs out of symposium on "ex-gays" |publisher=Washington Blade |url=http://www.washblade.com/thelatest/thelatest.cfm?blog_id=18015 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080502044844/http://washblade.com/thelatest/thelatest.cfm?blog_id=18015 |archivedate=2008-05-02 |date=2008-05-12 |format=}}
*{{citation |last=Katz |first=Jonathan |authorlink=Jonathan Ned Katz |title=Gay American history: lesbians and gay men in the U.S.A.: a documentary anthology |year=1976 |publisher=Crowell |location=New York |isbn=0690005105}}
*{{citation |last=Kirby |first=Michael |date=December 2003 |title=The 1973 deletion of homosexuality as a psychiatric disorder: 30 years on |journal=Australian &amp; New Zealand Journal of Psychiatry  |volume=37 |issue=6 |pages=18–31, 674–677 |doi=10.1111/j.1440-1614.2003.01269.x}}
*{{citation |last=Marmor |first=Judd |title=Sexual Inversion: The Multiple Roots of Homosexuality |year=1965 |publisher=Basic Books |location=New York |lccn=65-13343}}
*{{citation |last1=Norcross |first1=John C. |last2=Koocher |first2=Gerald P. |last3=Garofalo |first3=Ariele |title=Discredited Psychological Treatments and Tests: A Delphi Poll |date=October 2006 |journal=Professional Psychology: Research and Practice |volume=37 |issue=5 |pages=515–522 |doi=10.1037/0735-7028.37.5.515}}
*{{citation |last1=LeVay |first1=Simon |title=Queer Science: The Use and Abuse of Research into Homosexuality|year=1996 |publisher=MIT Press |location=Cambridge |isbn=0-262-12199-9}}
*{{citation |last1=Lewes |first1=Kenneth |title=The Psychoanalytic Theory of Male Homosexuality|year=1988 |publisher=Simon &amp; Schuster |location=New York |isbn=0-671-62391-5}}
*{{citation |last1=Lewes |first1=Kenneth |title=A special oedipal mechanism in the development of male homosexuality |journal=Psychoanalytic Psychology |volume=15 |issue=3 |year=1998 |pages=341–359 |doi=10.1037/0736-9735.15.3.341}}
*{{citation |last1=O'Connor |first1=Noreen |last2=Ryan |first2=Joanna |title=Wild Desires and Mistaken Identities: Lesbianism and Psychoanalysis |year=1993 |publisher=Virago |location=London |isbn=1-85381-303-6}}
*{{citation |last=Plowman |first=William |title=Homosexuality Panel Squelched by Gay Activists |date=2008-05-12  |url=http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=90365869 |publisher=NPR}}
*{{citation |last1=Shidlo |first1=Ariel |last2=Schroeder |first2=Michael |title=Changing Sexual Orientation: A Consumers’ Report |date=2002a|journal=Professional Psychology: Research and Practice |volume=33 |issue=3 |doi=10.1037/0735-7028.33.3.249 |pages=249–259}}
*{{citation |last1=Shidlo |first1=Ariel |last2=Schroeder |first2=Michael |title=Sexual conversion therapy: ethical, clinical, and research perspectives |date=2002b |page=137 |url=https://books.google.com/?id=1jYuientrGoC&amp;pg=PA137&amp;lpg=PA137&amp;dq=Shidlo+and+Schroeder+gay+sample#v=onepage&amp;q=Shidlo%20and%20Schroeder%20gay%20sample&amp;f=false | accessdate = 2011-05-17 | isbn = 978-0-7890-1911-0}}
*{{citation |last=Socarides |first=Charles |title=The Overt Homosexual |year=1968 |publisher=Grune &amp; Stratton |location=New York |isbn=080890437X}}
*{{citation |last=Spitzer |first=Robert L. |title=Can Some Gay Men and Lesbians Change Their Sexual Orientation? 200 Participants Reporting a Change from Homosexual to Heterosexual Orientation |date=October 2003 |journal=Archives of Sexual Behavior |volume=32 |issue=5 |pmid=14567650 |doi=10.1023/A:1025647527010 |pages=403–17; discussion 419–72}}
*{{citation |last=Stanton |first=Martin |title=Sandor Ferenczi: Reconsidering Active Intervention |year=1991 |publisher=Jason Aronson Inc |location=Northvale |isbn=0-87668-569-6}}
*{{citation |last=Terry |first=Jennifer |title=An American Obsession: Science, Medicine and the Place of Homosexuality in Modern Society |year=1999 |publisher=Chicago University Press |location=Chicago |isbn=0226793664}}
*{{citation |last=Waidzunas |first=Tom  |title=The Straight Line: How the Fringe Science of Ex-Gay Therapy Reoriented Sexuality |year=2016 |publisher=University of Minnesota Press |location=Minneapolis |isbn=9780816696154}}
*{{citation |last=Young-Bruehl |first=Elisabeth |title=Anna Freud |year=1988 |publisher=Summit Books |location=New York |isbn=0-671-68751-4}}
*{{citation |last1=Yarhouse |first1=Mark A. |last2=Throckmorton |first2=Warren |title=Ethical Issues in Attempts to Ban Reorientation Therapies |year=2002 |journal=Psychotherapy: Theory/Research/Practice/Training |volume=39 |issue=1 |doi=10.1037/0033-3204.39.1.66 |pages=66–75}}
*{{citation |last=Yoshino |first=Kenji |title=Covering |year=2002 |journal=Yale Law Journal |volume=111 |issue=4 |url=http://www.yalelawjournal.org/article/covering}}

==External links==
* [http://www.independent.co.uk/news/uk/this-britain/the-exgay-files-the-bizarre-world-of-gaytostraight-conversion-1884947.html Investigation into Conversion Therapy] ''[[The Independent]]'' ([http://www.webcitation.org/683h7AYsv Archive])
* [http://www.nytimes.com/2012/05/19/health/dr-robert-l-spitzer-noted-psychiatrist-apologizes-for-study-on-gay-cure.html?pagewanted=all Psychiatry Giant Sorry for Backing Gay 'Cure'] ''[[The New York Times]]''
* {{YouTube|id=gIifMxPcRnI |title= Interview with Dr. Robert Spitzer, M.D. (retracting his study on conversion therapy)}}
* [http://psychology.ucdavis.edu/rainbow/html/facts_changing.html Facts About Changing Sexual Orientation: Dr. Gregory M. Herek] ''[[University of California, Davis]]''
* [http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=homosexuality-cure-masters-johnson Article by Thomas Maier about Masters and Johnson]
* [http://whatweknow.law.columbia.edu/topics/lgbt-equality/what-does-the-scholarly-research-say-about-whether-conversion-therapy-can-alter-sexual-orientation-without-causing-harm/ What does the scholarly research say about whether conversion therapy can alter sexual orientation without causing harm?] on the [http://whatweknow.law.columbia.edu/ “What We Know” Project (Columbia University)]

{{LGBT |orientation=yes}}
{{Pseudoscience |orientation=yes}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Conversion Therapy}}
[[Category:Conversion therapy]]
[[Category:Pseudoscience]]
[[Category:Medical controversies]]
[[Category:Sexual orientation and medicine]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>