<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20030729161314|1255438" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="26410" pageid="26410" ns="0" title="Conversion therapy"><revisions><rev timestamp="2003-08-07T15:40:02Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Reparative therapy''', or '''conversion therapy''' refers to any of several controversial techniques for transitioning a person from [[homosexuality]] to [[heterosexuality]]. These therapies assume that homosexuality is [[mental disorder]], and not a fixed [[sexual orientation]], and should thus be repathologized as such. 

Some organizations, such as [[Exodus International]], [[NARTH]] and the [[International Healing Foundation]], which advocate the idea that [[sexual orientation]] is not fixed by genetic factors, support the belief that reparative therapy is genuine. 

Many people oppose these therapies, usually on the grounds that there is nothing wrong with homosexuality. Most scientific organizations furthermore believe that [[sexual orientation]] is fixed by genetic factors or otherwise unchangeable in adults and thus believe reparative therapy is misleading and potentially damaging. 

Reparative therapy uses a number of techniques, including [[counselling]], [[aversion therapy]], male bonding, fasting, reading scripture, and prayer. Generally, reparative therapy can be divided into two categories: secular and religious. Secular reparative therapy seeks to distance itself from religion, although it typically originates from religious thinking.

Conversion therapy is not a new idea and, in fact, harks back to the start of [[psychology]] itself. Until revealing research in the [[1950s]], researchers such as [[Irving Bieber]], [[Lawrence Hatterer]] and [[Sigmund Freud]] believed that homosexuality could be 'cured' through a variety of techniques, including &amp;quot;[[aversion therapy]], nausea producing drugs, [[castration]], [[electric shock]], [[brain surgery]], [[breast amputations]], etc.&amp;quot;[http://www.religioustolerance.org/hom_exod.htm]. Modern reparative therapy is a re-reading of this research and stems from the clinical work and theories of [[Elizabeth Moberly]], a British Christian [[theologian]]. In her book, '[[Homosexuality: A new Christian ethic]]', she states that homosexuality is purely a result of environmental factors, primarily a failure to bond with the subject's father as opposed to the domineering mother theory in Freudian psychoanalysis.

Initially, reparative therapy was welcomed by many 'Ex-Gay' and homosexual Christian groups who saw it as a means of reconciling their beliefs with their sexuality and as a way of gaining greater acceptance in their respective churches or ministries. Latterly, it has been adopted by much larger, mainstream religious groups, particularly in the [[USA]]. Many in these mainstream groups see it as a kinder way of approaching the 'homosexual problem'. It has also been used by some of these groups to influence public opinion and sway legislators &amp;quot;from supporting [[equal rights,]] domestic partnership and [[hate crime]] legislation.&amp;quot;[http://jgford.homestead.com/Fordessay.html]

Reparative therapy has had mixed results and a conclusive, peer-reviewed study is yet to be made. In general, whilst some conversions appear successful some are not permanent or only partially successful, i.e. subjects still have some homosexual feelings/attractions. 

== Political and Professional views ==

The issue of changing sexual orientation has become a highly politicized topic in western countries, especially the United States. Both the theory and practice have come under heavy criticism from [[gay rights]] groups, doctors, the [[American Psychiatric Association]], the [[American Academy of Pediatrics]], the [[American Medical Association]], the [[American Psychological Association]], the [[American Counseling Association]], and the [[National Association of Social Workers]], the [[Royal College of Nursing]] and other organizations. 

The [[American Psychiatric Association]] (APA) concluded in 1973 that homosexuality is not a mental illness and states that there are no scientifically rigorous studies to indicate the actual "efficacy or harm of 'reparative' treatments" and that "reparative" therapists have yet to produce "any rigorous scientific research to substantiate their claims of cure."  The APA position statement on reparative therapy states that "recent publicized efforts to repathologize homosexuality by claiming that it can be cured are often guided not by rigorous scientific or psychiatric research, but sometimes by religious and political forces opposed to full civil rights for gay men and lesbians." The APA position statement ends with a recommendation to ethical practitioners to "refrain from attempts to change individuals' sexual orientation, keeping in mind the medical dictum to first, do no harm." 

==External Links==
*[http://www.narth.com/ NARTH ] advocates right of patients to seek therapy to re-orient from homosexuality to heterosexuality.
*The [http://www.gaytostraight.org/ IHF ] advocates a form of reparative therapy "for those who wish to change".
*[http://religioustolerance.org/hom_repar.htm religioustolerance.org] -- strongly criticizes reparative therapy as "useless and probably harmful".
*[http://www.psych.org/pract_of_psych/copptherapyaddendum83100.cfm American Psychiatric Association: Position Statement on Therapies Focused on Attempts to Change Sexual Orientation]
*[http://www.exodus-international.org/ Exodus International] is an interdenominational Christian organization advocating reparative therapy and repentance for homosexuals.
*The [http://www.courage.org.uk/ Courage Trust] is a nonprofit, UK Christian Ministry &amp;quot;offering understanding and support for homosexual people&amp;quot; that no longer offers conversion therapy.
* [http://members.aol.com/exgaynomad/ NOMAD] Ex-ex-gay movement information site.</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>