<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20240811050838|1239731945" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="75418984" pageid="75418984" ns="0" title="Social identity threat"><revisions><rev timestamp="2024-11-01T14:48:56Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|Theory in social psychology}}
{{Discrimination sidebar}}

'''Social identity threat''' is a theory in [[social psychology]] derived from [[social identity theory]] to explain the different types of [[threat]]s that arise from [[Collective identity|group identity]] being threatened as opposed to [[personal identity]].&lt;ref name="Branscombe-1999"&gt;{{Cite book |last1=Branscombe |first1=N.R. |title=Social identity: Context, commitment, content: The context and content of social identity threat |last2=Ellemers |first2=N. |last3=Spears |first3=R. |last4=Doosje |first4=E.J. |publisher=Oxford: Blackwell |year=1999 |isbn= |pages=35–55}}&lt;/ref&gt; This theory distinguishes between four distinct types of social identity threats: categorization threat, distinctiveness threat, threats to the value of social identity, and acceptance threat''.'' Each type is associated with particular social contexts that make the threats more or less likely to occur. This theory emphasizes how the level of commitment with the social identity shapes the nature of the threat experienced.

== Components of the theory ==
The four components of social identity threat were developed by Nyla R. Branscombe, [[Naomi Ellemers]], Russell Spears, and Bertjan Doosje (1999).&lt;ref name="Branscombe-1999" /&gt; Each threat is experienced differently depending on the level of identification with the group identity.

=== Categorization threat ===
Categorization threat happens when individuals are involuntarily assigned stereotypical characteristics or judged on the basis of their group membership.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Lemyre |first1=Louise |last2=Smith |first2=Philip M. |date=September 1985 |title=Intergroup discrimination and self-esteem in the minimal group paradigm. |url=http://doi.apa.org/getdoi.cfm?doi=10.1037/0022-3514.49.3.660 |journal=Journal of Personality and Social Psychology |language=en |volume=49 |issue=3 |pages=660–670 |doi=10.1037/0022-3514.49.3.660 |issn=1939-1315}}&lt;/ref&gt; This theory suggests that there are certain social contexts where people want to be seen as unique individuals who have their own personal characteristics or accomplishments, and if instead, they are categorized in accordance with a group membership such as [[gender]], [[ethnicity]], or [[Political identity|political orientation]], then they would be resistant to the identity and feel as if they are being treated unfairly.

This resistance to categorization is especially pronounced when the assigned membership seems irrelevant or inappropriate to the situation at hand (even if the identity is normally one which they strongly identify with) such as gender in the workforce.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Young |first1=Heather |last2=Knippenberg |first2=Ad van |last3=Ellemers |first3=Naomi |last4=Vries |first4=Nanne de |date=July 1999 |title=The Asymmetrical Perception of Men and Women |url=http://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.1177/1368430299023004 |journal=Group Processes &amp; Intergroup Relations |language=en |volume=2 |issue=3 |pages=259–278 |doi=10.1177/1368430299023004 |issn=1368-4302}}&lt;/ref&gt; Individuals might even opt to hide stigmatized group membership in order to avoid the possible consequences of being categorized. Other identities like gender or ethnicity cannot be concealed, thus making it impossible to prevent others from categorizing them in specific ways.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Crocker |first1=Jennifer |last2=Major |first2=Brenda |date=October 1989 |title=Social stigma and self-esteem: The self-protective properties of stigma. |url=http://doi.apa.org/getdoi.cfm?doi=10.1037/0033-295X.96.4.608 |journal=Psychological Review |language=en |volume=96 |issue=4 |pages=608–630 |doi=10.1037/0033-295X.96.4.608 |issn=1939-1471}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Since individuals have a multitude of identities they can be categorized as, the theory suggests that people might prefer identities that they have self-selected rather than identities in which they are given.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Doosje |first1=Bertjan |last2=Branscombe |first2=Nyla R. |last3=Spears |first3=Russell |last4=Manstead |first4=Antony S. R. |date=October 1998 |title=Guilty by association: When one's group has a negative history. |url=http://doi.apa.org/getdoi.cfm?doi=10.1037/0022-3514.75.4.872 |journal=Journal of Personality and Social Psychology |language=en |volume=75 |issue=4 |pages=872–886 |doi=10.1037/0022-3514.75.4.872 |issn=1939-1315}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Ellemers |first1=Naomi |last2=Kortekaas |first2=Paulien |last3=Ouwerkerk |first3=Jaap W. |date=March 1999 |title=Self-categorisation, commitment to the group and group self-esteem as related but distinct aspects of social identity |url=https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/(SICI)1099-0992(199903/05)29:2/33.0.CO;2-U |journal=European Journal of Social Psychology |language=en |volume=29 |issue=2–3 |pages=371–389 |doi=10.1002/(SICI)1099-0992(199903/05)29:2/3&lt;371::AID-EJSP932&gt;3.0.CO;2-U |issn=0046-2772}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the authors argue that willingness to identify with an identity is determined most by the level of commitment towards an identity versus another competing identity. The authors recommended further research be conducted exploring the specific conditions that lead to identification with one identity over another. Regardless, based on principles from [[social identity theory]] and [[self-categorization theory]] theorizing that identities which are assigned can still determine how individuals see and define themselves, the researchers believed in the importance of examining both self-selected and socially assigned identities.

People who do not identify strongly with an identity are most likely to resist categorization threat, especially when the categorization is involuntarily imposed on them. When identity is emphasized, these low-identifiers distance themselves from the group, emphasize their individual identity, and might even demean ingroup members.&lt;ref name="Doosje-1995"&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Doosje |first1=Bertjan |last2=Ellemers |first2=Naomi |last3=Spears |first3=Russell |date=1995-09-01 |title=Perceived Intragroup Variability as a Function of Group Status and Identification |url=https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022103185710189 |journal=Journal of Experimental Social Psychology |volume=31 |issue=5 |pages=410–436 |doi=10.1006/jesp.1995.1018 |issn=0022-1031}}&lt;/ref&gt; High-performing individuals placed into a group with low status are likelier to disidentify because they view the group membership as threatening to their reputation and high self-esteem.&lt;ref name="van Prooijen 63–77"&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=van Prooijen |first1=Jan-Wiliem |last2=van Knippenberg |first2=Daan |date=January 2000 |title=Individuation or Depersonalization: The Influence of Personal Status Position |url=http://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.1177/1368430200031004 |journal=Group Processes &amp; Intergroup Relations |language=en |volume=3 |issue=1 |pages=63–77 |doi=10.1177/1368430200031004 |issn=1368-4302}}&lt;/ref&gt; Low-identifying members experience negative affective emotions such as anger, low self-esteem, or depression.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Koper |first1=Gerda |last2=Van Knippenberg |first2=Daan |last3=Bouhuijs |first3=Francien |last4=Vermunt |first4=Riel |last5=Wilke |first5=Henk |date=May 1993 |title=Procedural fairness and self-esteem |url=https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/ejsp.2420230307 |journal=European Journal of Social Psychology |language=en |volume=23 |issue=3 |pages=313–325 |doi=10.1002/ejsp.2420230307 |issn=0046-2772}}&lt;/ref&gt; Also, involuntary categorization into groups which are not valued or negatively stereotyped can lead to the individual emphasizing the shared qualities between groups and the heterogeneity in the in-group.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Doosje |first1=Bertjan |last2=Spears |first2=Russell |last3=Ellemers |first3=Naomi |last4=Koomen |first4=Willem |date=January 1999 |title=Perceived Group Variability in Intergroup Relations: The Distinctive Role of Social Identity |url=http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/14792779943000017 |journal=European Review of Social Psychology |language=en |volume=10 |issue=1 |pages=41–74 |doi=10.1080/14792779943000017 |issn=1046-3283}}&lt;/ref&gt; People who are stereotyped into groups expected to perform badly on a task actually do end up performing worse. This has been more commonly documented as [[stereotype threat]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Spencer |first1=Steven J. |last2=Logel |first2=Christine |last3=Davies |first3=Paul G. |date=2016-01-04 |title=Stereotype Threat |url=https://www.annualreviews.org/doi/10.1146/annurev-psych-073115-103235 |journal=Annual Review of Psychology |language=en |volume=67 |issue=1 |pages=415–437 |doi=10.1146/annurev-psych-073115-103235 |pmid=26361054 |issn=0066-4308}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Distinctiveness threat ===
Distinctiveness threat occurs when individuals are concerned about not having a unique social identity or having an identity that is indistinguishable from other comparable groups. According to research done by Tajfel and colleagues, individuals rely on distinct identities as a way to find meaning and define themselves in the world.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=TAJFEL |first1=HENRI |last2=WILKES |first2=A. L. |date=May 1963 |title=Classification and Quantitative Judgement |url=http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.2044-8295.1963.tb00865.x |journal=British Journal of Psychology |volume=54 |issue=2 |pages=101–114 |doi=10.1111/j.2044-8295.1963.tb00865.x |pmid=13980241 |issn=0007-1269}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Tajfel |first=Henri |date=1969 |title=Cognitive aspects of prejudice |url=http://dx.doi.org/10.1017/s0021932000023336 |journal=Journal of Biosocial Science |volume=1 |issue=S1 |pages=173–191 |doi=10.1017/s0021932000023336 |issn=0021-9320}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Tajfel-1974"&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Tajfel |first=Henri |date=April 1974 |title=Social identity and intergroup behaviour |url=http://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.1177/053901847401300204 |journal=Social Science Information |language=en |volume=13 |issue=2 |pages=65–93 |doi=10.1177/053901847401300204 |issn=0539-0184}}&lt;/ref&gt; After a distinct identity is formed, social comparison with similar groups can pose a potential threat to group distinctiveness. In other words, because humans desire to have a unique personal identity, they pursue a distinct group identity in order to distinguish themselves from others.

In the context of distinctiveness threat, discrimination against other groups only occur when the differences between the groups are unclear or minimal. The [[minimal group paradigm]] suggest that people favor in-group members and discriminate against out-group members based on arbitrary group assignments like painter preferences. Some researchers demonstrated that when individuals were given meaningful reasons between the differentiation (i.e. people who like painter A are more extroverted than painter B), discrimination decreased because individuals were presumably more secure and certain about their identity.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Mullin |first1=Barbara-Ann |last2=Hogg |first2=Michael A. |date=September 1998 |title=Dimensions of subjective uncertainty in social identification and minimal intergroup discrimination |url=http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.2044-8309.1998.tb01176.x |journal=British Journal of Social Psychology |volume=37 |issue=3 |pages=345–365 |doi=10.1111/j.2044-8309.1998.tb01176.x |issn=0144-6665}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some studies also demonstrate that people are more likely to choose a distinct identity over a positive identity. For example, Polish students would rather embrace some stereotypically negative traits of their nation than emphasize the similarities between all European countries.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=MLICKI |first1=PAWEL P. |last2=ELLEMERS |first2=NAOMI |date=January 1996 |title=Being different or being better? National stereotypes and identifications of Polish and Dutch students |url=http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/(sici)1099-0992(199601)26:1&lt;97::aid-ejsp739&gt;3.0.co;2-f |journal=European Journal of Social Psychology |volume=26 |issue=1 |pages=97–114 |doi=10.1002/(sici)1099-0992(199601)26:1&lt;97::aid-ejsp739&gt;3.0.co;2-f |issn=0046-2772|hdl=1871/17737 |hdl-access=free }}&lt;/ref&gt; While research demonstrates the importance of having distinctive identities over ones with positive traits, the embrace of negative traits are more common among people who strongly identify with the group rather than low-identifiers'''.'''

People are likelier to identify with groups that are numerically smaller versus majority groups.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=McGuire |first1=William J. |last2=McGuire |first2=Claire V. |last3=Child |first3=Pamela |last4=Fujioka |first4=Terry |date=1978 |title=Salience of ethnicity in the spontaneous self-concept as a function of one's ethnic distinctiveness in the social environment. |url=http://content.apa.org/journals/psp/36/5/511 |journal=Journal of Personality and Social Psychology |language=en |volume=36 |issue=5 |pages=511–520 |doi=10.1037/0022-3514.36.5.511 |pmid=671213 |issn=0022-3514}}&lt;/ref&gt; People also seek belonging in groups, which tend to be found in smaller tight-knit groups than larger groups.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Brewer |first=Marilynn B. |date=October 1991 |title=The Social Self: On Being the Same and Different at the Same Time |url=http://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.1177/0146167291175001 |journal=Personality and Social Psychology Bulletin |language=en |volume=17 |issue=5 |pages=475–482 |doi=10.1177/0146167291175001 |issn=0146-1672}}&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, individuals identify more with minority groups relative to majority groups because there are distinct cultures found in minority groups that may not be present in majority groups,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Simon |first1=Bernd |last2=Hamilton |first2=David L. |date=1994 |title=Self-stereotyping and social context: The effects of relative in-group size and in-group status. |url=http://doi.apa.org/getdoi.cfm?doi=10.1037/0022-3514.66.4.699 |journal=Journal of Personality and Social Psychology |language=en |volume=66 |issue=4 |pages=699–711 |doi=10.1037/0022-3514.66.4.699 |pmid=8189347 |issn=1939-1315}}&lt;/ref&gt; despite the politically and economically disadvantages of minority groups in society.

Once the group identity is established, social comparison with other similar groups may cause conflict and lead to differentiation.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Jetten |first1=Jolanda |last2=Spears |first2=Russell |last3=Manstead |first3=Antony S. R. |date=June 1998 |title=Defining dimensions of distinctiveness: Group variability makes a difference to differentiation. |url=http://dx.doi.org/10.1037/0022-3514.74.6.1481 |journal=Journal of Personality and Social Psychology |volume=74 |issue=6 |pages=1481–1492 |doi=10.1037/0022-3514.74.6.1481 |issn=1939-1315}}&lt;/ref&gt; People who strongly identify with the group will engage in differentiation while low-identifiers are not as threatened and might prefer to identify as individuals or in categories involving both groups.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last1=Jetten |first1=Jolanda |title=Group Distinctiveness and Intergroup Discrimination |last2=Spears |first2=Russell |last3=Manstead |first3=Antony S.R. |publisher=Blackwell Publishers |year=199}}&lt;/ref&gt;

While direct differentiation between groups is one strategy when faced with distinctiveness threat, it may be unrealistic in cases where the two groups are actually quite similar. So, those who strongly identify with the group will engage in other responses like identifying with the group even more by [[self-stereotyping]].&lt;ref name="Ellemers-1997"&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Ellemers |first1=Naomi |last2=Spears |first2=Russell |last3=Doosje |first3=Bertjan |date=1997 |title=Sticking together or falling apart: In-group identification as a psychological determinant of group commitment versus individual mobility. |url=http://doi.apa.org/getdoi.cfm?doi=10.1037/0022-3514.72.3.617 |journal=Journal of Personality and Social Psychology |language=en |volume=72 |issue=3 |pages=617–626 |doi=10.1037/0022-3514.72.3.617 |issn=1939-1315}}&lt;/ref&gt; The authors emphasize how the concept of distinctiveness threat demonstrates that groups discriminate against out-groups, not necessarily because distinctiveness is threatened, but rather in order to achieve or maintain the distinctiveness between the two groups. When resolving distinctiveness conflict among groups, a common result is to acknowledge that the other group has some positive traits while also acknowledging that their own group has positive traits, allowing for members of both groups to keep their positive distinct self-image.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Ellemers |first1=Naomi |last2=van Knippenberg |first2=Ad |last3=Wilke |first3=Henk |date=September 1990 |title=The influence of permeability of group boundaries and stability of group status on strategies of individual mobility and social change |url=https://bpspsychub.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/j.2044-8309.1990.tb00902.x |journal=British Journal of Social Psychology |language=en |volume=29 |issue=3 |pages=233–246 |doi=10.1111/j.2044-8309.1990.tb00902.x |pmid=2224425 |issn=0144-6665}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Value threat ===
Value threat refers to when the group value is undermined by a source of threat ranging from outgroups, neutral sources, or even ingroup members on dimensions such as competence or morality. When one's social identity is being explicitly attacked by an outgroup member (e.g. verbally insulted), then this can result in outgroup derogation.&lt;ref name="Bourhis-1979"&gt;{{Cite book |last1=Bourhis |first1=R.Y. |title=Psycholinguistic Distinctiveness: Language Divergence in Belgium: Language and Social Psychology |last2=Giles |first2=H. |last3=Leyens |first3=J.P. |last4=Tajfel |first4=H. |publisher=Blackwell |year=1979 |pages=158–185}}&lt;/ref&gt; Perceptions of discrimination based on group membership (e.g. the more Black Americans felt discriminated based on their race) can also result in increased hostility.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Branscombe |first1=Nyla R. |last2=Schmitt |first2=Michael T. |last3=Harvey |first3=Richard D. |date=July 1999 |title=Perceiving pervasive discrimination among African Americans: Implications for group identification and well-being. |url=http://doi.apa.org/getdoi.cfm?doi=10.1037/0022-3514.77.1.135 |journal=Journal of Personality and Social Psychology |language=en |volume=77 |issue=1 |pages=135–149 |doi=10.1037/0022-3514.77.1.135 |issn=1939-1315}}&lt;/ref&gt;

When high-identifiers are faced with value threats, they tend to both self-affirm the value of their identity and [[Self-stereotyping|self-stereotype]] themselves to be prototypical of the group.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Ellemers |first1=Naomi |last2=Wilke |first2=Henk |last3=van Knippenberg |first3=Ad |date=1993 |title=Effects of the legitimacy of low group or individual status on individual and collective status-enhancement strategies. |url=http://doi.apa.org/getdoi.cfm?doi=10.1037/0022-3514.64.5.766 |journal=Journal of Personality and Social Psychology |language=en |volume=64 |issue=5 |pages=766–778 |doi=10.1037/0022-3514.64.5.766 |issn=1939-1315}}&lt;/ref&gt; Moreover, if members of a group believe that their group has been unjustly persecuted resulting in their stigmatized group status, then their ingroup affiliation will increase, as well as their out-group derogation.

The source of the threat could also be [[Symbolic threat|symbolic]] and still invoke similar reactions as threats from out-groups. In a study by Branscombe and Wann (1994), they found that simply watching a video where a Russian boxer beat an American boxer invoked reductions in self esteem among people who strongly identified as American (there was no effect for people who did not strongly identify as American).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Branscombe |first1=Nyla R. |last2=Wann |first2=Daniel L. |date=November 1994 |title=Collective self-esteem consequences of outgroup derogation when a valued social identity is on trial |url=https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/ejsp.2420240603 |journal=European Journal of Social Psychology |language=en |volume=24 |issue=6 |pages=641–657 |doi=10.1002/ejsp.2420240603 |issn=0046-2772}}&lt;/ref&gt; Reductions in self-esteem were also directed linked to outgroup derogation. Level of identification with the group is a significant factor in determining the impact of the threat and subsequent reactions to the threat.

Besides direct outgroup derogation, when the ingroup is depicted as inferior to a competing outgroup, other defensive responses may occur. In situations where the status-dimension is taken into account and social reality is hard to dispute (e.g. sports team losing), then direct in-group favoritism is not effective. Only high identifiers are likely to reinforce or demonstrate their commitment to the group by actions like perceiving the ingroup as homogenous, taking on prototypical group traits, and stereotyping the group on other dimensions.&lt;ref name="Doosje-1995" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Ellemers-1997" /&gt;

As identification with the group becomes stronger, ingroup members will protect the group in the moral dimension of value threats as well. This response can occur in both low-status and high-status groups. For instance, high-identifying White Americans who are reminded of the privileges they have due to their race score higher on a racism scale compared to low-identifying White Americans.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Branscombe |first1=N.R. |last2=Wann |first2=D.L. |date=1998 |title=Effects of thinking about White privilege or disadvantage and degree of White racial identification for feelings about the ingroup and outgroup |journal=Unpublished Manuscript}}&lt;/ref&gt; To resolve the dissonance from having pride in being White and the history of racism perpetrated by White Americans, high-identifying White Americans engage in out-group derogation, while low-identifying white Americans experience no such increase in out-group hostility and instead experience a decrease in self-esteem. The authors argue that strong identification with a group leads to feelings of linked fate, where one experiences emotions based on the group despite not necessarily being involved in the group's past or future decisions.

The strength of identification with a group also affects how one evaluates feedback from the out-group versus the in-group. In a study examining the effects of identity threat (whether the person is rated as positively or negatively as a result of their group membership) on self-esteem, participants received either positive or negative feedback from in-group or outgroup members.&lt;ref name="Branscombe-1999" /&gt; Positive feedback was generally more well-received than negative, but feedback from an in-group member was always deemed as more reliable than an out-group member regardless of the content. In-group members' opinions may be seen as more value because they are an important part of one's identity and are supposed to be accepting of the individual.&lt;ref name="Bourhis-1979" /&gt; Additionally, those who were low-identifying suffered more self-esteem loss from negative feedback compared to high-identifying individuals.

=== Acceptance threat ===
Acceptance threat deals with whether one is accepted by their own in-group. Many social groups like jobs, sororities or fraternities, or churches have various requirements to entry. These requirements allow the organization to see whether the member is suitable for entry and may increase the member's commitment once they are accepted into the group.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Aronson |first1=Elliot |last2=Mills |first2=Judson |date=September 1959 |title=The effect of severity of initiation on liking for a group. |url=http://doi.apa.org/getdoi.cfm?doi=10.1037/h0047195 |journal=The Journal of Abnormal and Social Psychology |language=en |volume=59 |issue=2 |pages=177–181 |doi=10.1037/h0047195 |issn=0096-851X}}&lt;/ref&gt; The authors argue that while acceptance threat may present similarly like the other threats (i.e. outgroup derogation), the internal processes are different. Taking from self-categorization theory which implies that people act strategically in ways that indicate who they want to align themselves with, individuals who have multiple conflicting identities have to choose which identity to publicly align with.&lt;ref name="Tajfel-1974" /&gt; After choosing an identity, members must try and prove their allegiance, and they may do so by devaluing the other group.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Ethier |first1=Kathleen A. |last2=Deaux |first2=Kay |date=August 1994 |title=Negotiating social identity when contexts change: Maintaining identification and responding to threat. |url=http://doi.apa.org/getdoi.cfm?doi=10.1037/0022-3514.67.2.243 |journal=Journal of Personality and Social Psychology |language=en |volume=67 |issue=2 |pages=243–251 |doi=10.1037/0022-3514.67.2.243 |issn=1939-1315}}&lt;/ref&gt;

People who have or feel insecure about their place in group are most likely to engage in behaviors that are prototypical of the group. While these behaviors may manifests itself differently depending on the group that one wants to gain entry for, individuals just desire to be accepted into the in-group they favor.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Noel |first1=Jeffrey G. |last2=Wann |first2=Daniel L. |last3=Branscombe |first3=Nyla R. |date=1995 |title=Peripheral ingroup membership status and public negativity toward outgroups. |url=http://doi.apa.org/getdoi.cfm?doi=10.1037/0022-3514.68.1.127 |journal=Journal of Personality and Social Psychology |language=en |volume=68 |issue=1 |pages=127–137 |doi=10.1037/0022-3514.68.1.127 |pmid=7861310 |issn=1939-1315}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some experiments have demonstrated that people engage in in-group favoritism and out-group derogation when faced with uncertainty, with people who are more insecure about their group standing strongly supporting leaders who are biased towards their in-group rather than leaders who are equitable.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Platow |first1=Michael J. |last2=Hoar |first2=Stephanie |last3=Reid |first3=Scott |last4=Harley |first4=Keryn |last5=Morrison |first5=Dianne |date=July 1997 |title=Endorsement of distributively fair and unfair leaders in interpersonal and intergroup situations |url=https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/(SICI)1099-0992(199707)27:43.0.CO;2-8 |journal=European Journal of Social Psychology |language=en |volume=27 |issue=4 |pages=465–494 |doi=10.1002/(SICI)1099-0992(199707)27:4&lt;465::AID-EJSP817&gt;3.0.CO;2-8 |issn=0046-2772}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The reactions of people who are seeking entry to a group are similar to the reactions of individuals who are faced with the possibility for being excluded from the group, or at the very least, demoted. If the individual cares about the identity, then they will engage in the aforementioned behaviors to try and maintain their status.&lt;ref name="Branscombe-1999" /&gt; They will even evaluate a person who is more prototypical of the group more favorably than someone who is more similar to themselves to preserve the distinctiveness of the group.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Schmitt |first1=Michael T. |last2=Branscombe |first2=Nyla R. |date=2001-11-01 |title=The Good, the Bad, and the Manly: Threats to One's Prototypicality and Evaluations of Fellow In-Group Members |url=https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022103101914763 |journal=Journal of Experimental Social Psychology |volume=37 |issue=6 |pages=510–517 |doi=10.1006/jesp.2001.1476 |issn=0022-1031}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, for individuals who are low-identifying, they will not try to stay in the group's good graces because they already expect to be negatively perceived by the group. Interestingly, their self-categorization of themselves as low-identifying will be validated by the group's perception of them as non-prototypical.&lt;ref name="van Prooijen 63–77"/&gt;

Whether the group's elite members recognize the individual's commitment to the group is another way in which one can gain acceptance from the group. Since rejection by an ingroup is seen as distressing to those who are high-identifying, they might over-compensate by adhering strictly to all of the expectations associated with the group. Meanwhile, if the individual seems to value themselves over the group (forsaking the group when it becomes disadvantageous to them), then the group elites might have a negative impression of them.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last1=Spears |first1=Russell |title=Commitment and the Context of Social Perception |last2=Doosje |first2=Bertjan |last3=Ellemers |first3=Naomi |publisher=Blackwell |year=1999 |pages=59–83}}&lt;/ref&gt; People who act in this way tend to be low-identifying, so these people may be rejected by those who are highly committed to the group.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Branscombe |first1=Nyla R. |last2=Wann |first2=Daniel L |last3=Noel |first3=Jeffrey G. |last4=Coleman |first4=Jason |date=August 1993 |title=In-Group or Out-Group Extemity: Importance of the Threatened Social Identity |url=http://dx.doi.org/10.1177/0146167293194003 |journal=Personality and Social Psychology Bulletin |volume=19 |issue=4 |pages=381–388 |doi=10.1177/0146167293194003 |issn=0146-1672}}&lt;/ref&gt; This pattern of low-identifying individuals being rejected by the group, therefore they do not try to fit in, may become a cycle, where a subgroup might come to believe that they do not belong in the group in the first place.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Vorob’ev |first=D. N. |date=2022-12-01 |title=From the Origins to the Present-Day Relationships between the African American Community and the Republican Party |url=https://doi.org/10.1134/S1019331622210237 |journal=Herald of the Russian Academy of Sciences |language=en |volume=92 |issue=15 |pages=S1412–S1419 |doi=10.1134/S1019331622210237 |issn=1555-6492 |pmc=10052273}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== References ==
{{reflist}}

{{Discrimination}}
[[Category:Social psychology]]
[[Category:Self]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>