<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20241130230813|1260469939" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="256025" pageid="256025" ns="0" title="Abortion debate"><revisions><rev timestamp="2024-11-30T23:10:28Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Debate about whether and under which circumstances a fetus should be allowed to be aborted}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=December 2023}}
{{Redirect-distinguish|Pro-birth|Natalism}}
The '''abortion debate''' is a longstanding and contentious discourse that touches on the moral, legal, medical, and religious aspects of induced [[abortion]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |author-link=Thomas Groome |last=Groome |first=Thomas |url= https://www.nytimes.com/2017/03/27/opinion/to-win-again-democrats-must-stop-being-the-abortion-party.html |title=To Win Again, Democrats Must Stop Being the Abortion Party |work=[[The New York Times]] |date=27 March 2017 |access-date=3 May 2022}}&lt;/ref&gt; In [[English-speaking countries]], the debate has two major sides, commonly referred to as the "[[Abortion-rights movements|pro-choice]]" and "[[Anti-abortion movements|pro-life]]" movements. Generally, supporters of ''pro-choice'' argue for the right to choose to terminate a pregnancy. They take into account various factors such as the stage of fetal development, the health of the woman, and the circumstances of the conception. By comparison, the supporters of ''pro-life'' generally argue that a fetus is a human being with [[Natural rights and legal rights|inherent rights]] and [[Intrinsic value (ethics)|intrinsic value]], and thus, cannot be overridden by the woman's choice or circumstances and that abortion is morally wrong in most or all cases. Both the terms ''pro-choice'' and ''pro-life'' are considered [[loaded word]]s in mainstream media, which tend to prefer terms such as "[[Abortion-rights movement|abortion rights]]" or "anti-abortion" as more neutral and avoidant of [[bias]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Hyperbole |volume=23 |issue=1 |url= https://blogs.wsj.com/styleandsubstance/2010/01/31/vol-23-no-1/|newspaper=[[The Wall Street Journal]]|access-date=4 November 2011|date=31 January 2010 |archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20210421132158/https://www.wsj.com/articles/vol-23-no-1-hyperbole-01557859513?tesla=y |archive-date=21 April 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Each movement has had varying results in influencing public opinion and attaining legal support for its position. Supporters and opponents of abortion often argue that it is essentially a [[morality|moral]] issue, concerning the [[beginning of human personhood]], [[Fetal rights|rights of the fetus]], and [[Bodily integrity#Women's rights|bodily integrity]]. Additionally, some argue that government involvement in abortion-related decisions, particularly through public funding, raises [[Ethics|ethical]] and political questions. [[Libertarianism|Libertarians]], for example, may oppose taxpayer funding for abortion based on [[Principle|principles]] of limited government and personal responsibility, while holding [[Libertarian perspectives on abortion|diverse views]] on the legality of the procedure itself.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=Staff |date=2019-05-17 |title=Libertarians: Abortion is a matter for individual conscience, not public decree |url=https://www.lp.org/libertarians-abortion-is-a-matter-for-individual-conscience-not-public-decree/ |access-date=2024-09-23 |website=Libertarian Party |language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt; The debate has become a political and legal issue in some countries with those who oppose abortion seeking to enact, maintain, and expand [[Abortion law|anti-abortion laws]], while those who support abortion seek to repeal or ease such laws and expand access to the procedure. Abortion laws vary considerably between jurisdictions, ranging from outright prohibition of the procedure to public funding of abortion. The availability of abortion procedures considered safe also varies across the world and exists mainly in places that legalize abortion.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Cates |first1=Willard Jr. |last2=Grimes |first2=David A. |last3=Schulz |first3=Kenneth F. |title=The Public Health Impact of Legal Abortion: 30 Years Later |date=1 January 2003 |journal=Perspectives on Sexual and Reproductive Health |volume=35 |pages=25–28 |url= https://www.guttmacher.org/journals/psrh/2003/01/public-health-impact-legal-abortion-30-years-later |via=Guttmacher.org |doi=10.1363/3502503 |issue=1 |doi-broken-date=18 November 2024 |pmid=12602754}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Overview==
In ancient times, issues such as abortion and [[infanticide]] were evaluated by [[Patriarchy|patriarchies]] within the contexts of [[family planning]], gender selection, population control, and property rights.&lt;ref&gt;See generally, "The Kindness of Strangers: The Abandonment of Children in Western Europe from Late Antiquity to the Renaissance", John BosLik {{ISBN|978-0-226-06712-4}} Nov 1998, Intro.&lt;/ref&gt; The rights of the prospective mother and child were typically not central to these considerations.&lt;ref&gt;See generally Spivack, Carla, ''To Bring Down the Flowers: The Cultural Context of Abortion Law in Early Modern England''. Available at SSRN: [http://ssrn.com/abstract=1132482] Introduction&lt;/ref&gt; Ancient discourse often expressed the concerns on the [[Human nature|nature of humankind]], the existence of a [[soul]], when life begins, and the [[beginning of human personhood]], issues that are still relevant even today.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first=A. O. |last=Echekwube |title=Contemporary Ethics: History, Theories and Issues |location=Lagos |publisher=Spero Books |date=1999 |page=188 |isbn=97830897-4-9}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Discussion of the presumed [[personhood]] of a fetus may be complicated by the current legal status of children. Similar to minors, fetuses and embryos lack certain legal capacities. In many legal systems, a fetus or an embryo does not have the same legal status as a person. They have not reached the age of majority and deemed not able to enter into contracts and to sue or be sued.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Rodham |first=Hillary |author-link=Hillary Clinton |title=Children under the law |journal=Harvard Educational Review |date=1973 |volume=43 |issue=4 |pages=487–514 |doi=10.17763/haer.43.4.e14676283875773k}}&lt;/ref&gt; Since the 1860s, they have been treated as persons for the limited purposes of [[offence against the person]] law in the UK including Northern Ireland, although this treatment was amended by the [[Abortion Act 1967|Abortion Act of 1967]] in England, Scotland, and Wales.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=The law and ethics of abortion: BMA views |work=BMA.org.uk |publisher=Ethics Department, [[British Medical Association]] |date=March 2023 |orig-date=2014, 2020 |page=5 |url= https://www.bma.org.uk/media/3307/bma-the-law-and-ethics-of-abortion-report-march-2023-final-web.pdf |access-date=16 December 2023}}&lt;/ref&gt; In America, there have been logistical challenges in considering a fetus as a person. Some legal interpretations have argued that if a fetus is considered a person, then it is only under certain conditions as it relies on the body of another person and is usually not the object of direct action by another person.&lt;ref&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20110714155021/http://www.napil.com/PersonalInjuryCaseLawDetail40130/Page2.htm ''State v Loce''] 6 September 1991&lt;/ref&gt; In the current debate, proposals range from prohibitions on abortion in all cases, even when the woman's life is at risk, to calls for complete legalization with provisions for public funding.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=Nicholas |last=Kristof |url= https://www.nytimes.com/2010/05/27/opinion/27kristof.html?&amp;emc=rss |title=Sister Margaret's Choice |work=[[The New York Times]] |date=27 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Reingold |first=Rebecca |date=June 5, 2019 |title=State Abortion Restrictions and the New Supreme Court: Women's Access to Reproductive Health Services |url=https://scholarship.law.georgetown.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3187&amp;context=facpub |journal=[[American Medical Association]]|volume=322 |issue=1 |pages=21–22 |doi=10.1001/jama.2019.8437 |pmid=31166573 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Terminology==
Many of the terms used in the debate are seen as [[Framing (social sciences)|political framing]]: terms used to validate one's stance while invalidating the opposition's.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Harrington |first=Erin |title=Women, Monstrosity and Horror Film: Gynaehorror |url= https://books.google.com/books?id=aF8wDwAAQBAJ |date=2017 |publisher=[[Taylor &amp; Francis]] |isbn=978-1-134-77933-8 |page=[https://books.google.com/books?id=aF8wDwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT97&amp;dq=%22The%20terms%20pro–life%20and%20pro–choice%20are%20themselves%20acts%20of%20political%20framing%22 97]}}&lt;/ref&gt; For example, the labels [[pro-choice and pro-life|"pro-choice" and "pro-life"]] imply widely held values such as [[liberty]] or the [[right to life]], while suggesting that the opposition must be "anti-choice" or "anti-life".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |url=https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/book/10.1002/9781118896877 |title=The International Encyclopedia of Human Sexuality |date=2015-04-10 |publisher=Wiley |isbn=978-1-4051-9006-0 |editor-last=Bolin |editor-first=Anne |edition=1 |language=en |doi=10.1002/9781118896877.wbiehs376 |editor-last2=Whelehan |editor-first2=Patricia}}&lt;/ref&gt; Terms used in the debate to describe their opponents consist of "pro-abortion", "pro-abort"; however, these terms do not always reflect a political view or fall along a binary. Seven in ten Americans described themselves as "pro-choice" while almost two-thirds described themselves as "pro-life".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |url=https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/book/10.1002/9781118896877 |title=The International Encyclopedia of Human Sexuality |date=2015-04-10 |publisher=Wiley |isbn=978-1-4051-9006-0 |editor-last=Bolin |editor-first=Anne |edition=1 |language=en |doi=10.1002/9781118896877.wbiehs376 |editor-last2=Whelehan |editor-first2=Patricia}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another identifier in the debate is "abolitionist", which harks back to the 19th-century struggle against human [[slavery]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |first=Andrea |last=Grimes |url= http://rhrealitycheck.org/article/2014/04/11/portrait-anti-abortion-abolitionist/ |title=Portrait of an Anti-Abortion 'Abolitionist' |quote=It is no accident that Ragon both calls himself an "abolitionist" and that his group uses these so-called disturbing images. He sees himself as carrying on the tradition of 19th-century anti-slavery activists, who he says similarly tried to shock their fellow Americans into action. |access-date=26 May 2015 |date=11 April 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |first=Irin |last=Carmon |url= http://www.msnbc.com/melissa-harris-perry/meet-the-rebels-the-anti-abortion-movement |title=Meet the rebels of the anti-abortion movement |quote=AHA activists disdain the phrase "pro-life" altogether. They prefer 'abolitionists', with all slavery comparisons explicitly intended, and they want to push the larger movement to abide by their uncompromising positions. |access-date=26 May 2015 |date=8 March 2014 |website=[[MSNBC]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Appeals are often made in the abortion debate to the [[rights]] of the [[fetus]], pregnant woman, or other parties. Such appeals can generate confusion if the ''type'' of rights is not specified (whether [[Civil rights|civil]], [[Natural rights|natural]], or otherwise) or if it is simply ''assumed'' that the right appealed to takes precedence over all other competing rights (an example of [[begging the question]]). The appropriate terms to designate the human organism before birth are also debated. Some anti-abortion supporters regard the technical terminology "[[embryo]]" and "[[fetus]]" as [[dehumanization|dehumanizing]],&lt;ref&gt;Brennan 'Dehumanizing the vulnerable' 2000&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |journal=Princeton Progressive Review |date=February 1996 |url= http://groups.csail.mit.edu/mac/users/rauch/nvp/consistent/naomi_wolf.html |last1=Getek |first1=Kathryn |last2=Cunningham |first2=Mark |title=A Sheep in Wolf's Clothing – Language and the Abortion Debate}}&lt;/ref&gt; whereas some abortion rights proponents regard ordinary terms such as "[[Infant|baby]]" or "[[child]]" as emotion-inducing.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Fineman |first=Martha |date=1988 |title=Dominant Discourse, Professional Language, and Legal Change in Child Custody Decisionmaking |url= https://www.jstor.org/stable/1341172 |journal=Harvard Law Review |volume=101 |issue=4 |pages=727–774 |doi=10.2307/1341172|jstor=1341172}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The use of the term "baby" to describe the unborn human organism is seen by some scholars as part of an effort to assign the organism agency, functioning to further the construction of [[fetal personhood]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Petchesky |first=Rosalind Pollack |author-link=Rosalind P. Petchesky |date=1987 |title=Fetal Images: The Power of Visual Culture in the Politics of Reproduction |journal=Feminist Studies |volume=13 |issue=2 |pages=263–292 |jstor=3177802 |doi=10.2307/3177802 |s2cid=41193716|hdl=2027/spo.0499697.0013.203 |hdl-access=free }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Murray |first=Thomas H. |title=The Worth of a Child |url= https://books.google.com/books?id=tRTMbjvUrS0C |date=1996 |publisher=University of California Press |isbn=978-0-520-91530-5 |page=[https://archive.org/details/worthofchild0000murr/page/149 139]&lt;!-- quote="rhetorical tactics", "unborn baby". --&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; Anti-abortion activists occasionally use the term the "Silent Holocaust" or "the American genocide" about the [[Abortion statistics in the United States|number of abortions that have been performed in the United States]] since 1973.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Wyler |first=Grace |title=The New Face of the Anti-Abortion Movement |url= https://www.vice.com/en_us/article/exmngz/the-new-face-of-the-anti-abortion-movement |access-date=3 September 2020 |work=[[Vice (magazine)|Vice]] |date=26 November 2013 |quote=Armed with images of fully developed, dismembered fetuses and a sign christening Albuquerque as 'America's Auschwitz,' they set up camp in front of the city's modest Holocaust and Intolerance Museum and demanded a new exhibit to commemorate the victims of what they call 'the silent holocaust,' or 'the American genocide'—or the roughly 50 million abortions performed in the United States since the Supreme Court's Roe vs. Wade ruling in 1973.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Political debate==
There is abundant debate regarding the extent of abortion regulation by the government. Supporters of abortion rights may argue against the government regulation of abortions, and rather it be treated as routine medical practice.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.bccla.org/positions/privateoff/72abortion.html |title=Abortion |access-date=24 May 2007 |work=Positions |publisher=British Columbia Civil Liberties Association |quote=rights call for complete legal freedom to secure an abortion, in the sense that the legal status of abortion should be the same as that of other medical services that a doctor provides to a patient |archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20070926232717/http://www.bccla.org/positions/privateoff/72abortion.html |archive-date=26 September 2007 |url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; From a [[Compromise|compromising]] perspective, both sides may support the permission of the government to prohibit elective abortions after the 20th week, [[Point of fetal viability|viability]], or the second [[wiktionary:trimester|trimester]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |url= http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/pagerender.fcgi?artid=1455357&amp;pageindex=2 |title=Abortion |volume=119 |issue=6 |pages=42–59 |access-date=24 May 2007 |date=December 1973|journal=Where We Stand—CMA Position Papers |quote=Good medical practice indicates that abortion should not be performed after the 20th week of pregnancy}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.amwa-doc.org/index.cfm?objectId=0A5BF4D4-D567-0B25-58C7E8584C98D43B |title=Abortion |access-date=24 May 2007 |date=2000 |work=Positions |publisher=American Medical Women's Association |quote=The 1973 Supreme court decision ''Roe v. Wade'' struck a fair balance between the responsibility of the state to protect a woman's right to make personal medical decisions and the responsibility of the state to protect the potentially viable third-trimester fetus |archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20070920172711/http://www.amwa-doc.org/index.cfm?objectId=0A5BF4D4-D567-0B25-58C7E8584C98D43B |archive-date=20 September 2007 |url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.kent.ac.uk/sspssr/research/papers/legalpro.pdf |title=Abortion issues today – a position paper |access-date=24 May 2007 |last1=Lee |first1=Ellie |first2=Ann |last2=Furedi |date=February 2002 |work=Legal Issues for Pro-Choice Opinion – Abortion Law in Practice |publisher=University of Kent, Canterbury, CT2 7NY, UK |page=2 |quote=While most people have no difficulty accepting the legality of abortion at early stages of pregnancy, fewer are so sure about their position as pregnancy progresses – especially when the fetus is perceived to be 'viable' |archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20070926143428/http://www.kent.ac.uk/sspssr/research/papers/legalpro.pdf |archive-date=26 September 2007 |url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; Religion has also played a role in the debate. For example, some Christian denominations and groups [[Christianity and abortion|generally oppose abortion]], believing it more aligns with their [[Hermeneutics|interpretation]] of the [[Bible]], and because of this may support the prohibition of some or all abortions, starting from conception.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.johnstonsarchive.net/baptist/rptbgctc.html |title=Evaluation of the BGCT Christian Life Commission's "Abortion and the Christian Life" |access-date=2 September 2016 |last=Johnston |first=William Robert |date=24 December 2002 |work=Committee Report |publisher=First Baptist Church, Brownsville, Texas |quote=the unique value that human life has, as a gift from God, regardless of stage of development or physical health, from the point of conception to the point of physical death| archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20070411224102/http://www.johnstonsarchive.net/baptist/rptbgctc.html| archive-date= 11 April 2007 |url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt; Those who oppose abortion rights may argue against the procedures and nature of [[abortion]]. The two sides of the political debate represent the contentious moral principles in the “sanctity of life” versus “the woman's right to choose.” &lt;ref name="Mucciaroni 2018"&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Mucciaroni |first1=Gary |last2=Ferraiolo |first2=Kathleen |last3=Rubado |first3=Meghan E. |date=27 October 2018 |title=Framing morality policy issues: state legislative debates on abortion restrictions |url= http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s11077-018-9336-2 |journal=Policy Sciences |volume=52 |issue=2 |pages=171–189 |doi=10.1007/s11077-018-9336-2 |s2cid=254898447 |issn=0032-2687}}&lt;/ref&gt; Abortion debates differ from other public health issues due to complex ethical and legal considerations.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Lantz |first=M. |date=2019 |title="State Laws Restricting Abortion: The Need to Document Their Impact." |url= https://deepblue.lib.umich.edu/bitstream/handle/2027.42/151887/milq12401.pdf?sequence=2 |journal=The Milbank Quarterly  |volume=97}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In popular culture, the American romantic drama dance [[film]] ''[[Dirty Dancing]]'' (1987) was a clear and unapologetic argument for reproductive choice, called by abortion rights advocates the "golden standard" for cinematic portrayals of abortion.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=Rooney |first=Daniel Fienberg,Lovia Gyarkye,Angie Han,Sheri Linden,David |date=2022-05-03 |title=Abortion in Film: THR Critics Recommend 12 Movies to Revisit |url=https://www.hollywoodreporter.com/movies/movie-reviews/12-movies-about-abortion-1235022140/ |access-date=2024-11-19 |website=The Hollywood Reporter |language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=Herold |first=Steph |date=2017-02-28 |title='Dirty Dancing' Led the Way in Depicting Abortion—If Only Other Media Would Follow |url=https://rewirenewsgroup.com/2017/02/28/dirty-dancing-led-way-depicting-abortion-media-follow/ |access-date=2024-11-19 |website=Rewire News Group |language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last1=Tzioumakis |first1=Yannis |title=The time of our lives: Dirty dancing and popular culture |last2=Lincoln |first2=Siân |date=2013 |publisher=Wayne State University Press |isbn=978-0-8143-3624-3 |series=Contemporary approaches to film and media series |location=Detroit, Michigan}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Debates in North America ==
=== United States ===
==== The ''Dobbs'' decision ====
As an example of political decisions concerning the abortion debate, in the recent years following the [[Dobbs v. Jackson Women's Health Organization|''Dobbs'']] ruling, state governments have been granted political authority over abortion access and resources. The [[Framing (social sciences)|issue-framing]] and [[Policy making|policy-making]] aspects vary from each perspective and interest but ultimately form the strategic decisions for legislators for support or opposition to their efforts.&lt;ref name="Mucciaroni 2018" /&gt;

The ''[[Dobbs v. Jackson Women's Health Organization|Dobbs]]'' decision allows other debates to form over several different concepts in other state legislature concerning the terms "privacy" and "liberty interests"&lt;ref name="Lazzarini 2022"&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Lazzarini |first=Zita |date=4 August 2022 |title=The End of ''Roe v. Wade'' — States' Power over Health and Well-Being |journal=New England Journal of Medicine |volume=387 |issue=5 |pages=390–393 |doi=10.1056/nejmp2206055 |pmid=35830684 |issn=0028-4793|doi-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt; Which those cases have determined the foundation of [[Doctor–patient relationship|clinician-patient]] relationships and private medical decisions. Abortion decisions bring focus onto other state efforts corresponding to abortion, such as limiting access to medication abortions, preventing third parties from assisting anyone seeking an abortion, or punishing women who end their pregnancies.&lt;ref name="Lazzarini 2022" /&gt; While evaluating the ''Dobbs'' ruling, the Court had determined the importance of the opposing factors of "respect for and preservation of prenatal life at all stages...; the protection of maternal health and safety; the elimination of particularly gruesome or barbaric medical procedures;... integrity of the medical profession; the mitigation of fetal pain, and the prevention of discrimination based on race, sex, or disability."&lt;ref name="Lazzarini 2022" /&gt;

====Privacy====
In the United States, the debate has been framed as an aspect of privacy. Even though the [[Privacy law|right to privacy]] is not explicitly stated in many constitutions of sovereign nations, many people see it as foundational to a functioning democracy. In general, the right to privacy can be found to rest on the provisions of ''[[habeas corpus]]'', which first found official expression under Henry II in 11th century England, but has precedent in Anglo-Saxon law. This provision guarantees the right to freedom from arbitrary government interference, as well as due process of law.{{cn|date=September 2024}} This conception of the right to privacy is established in all countries which have adopted [[English common law]] through Acts of Reception.{{cn|date=September 2024}} The [[law of the United States]] rests on English common law by this means.

''[[Time (magazine)|Time]]'' has stated that the issue of bodily [[privacy]] is "the core" of the abortion debate.&lt;ref name="Time"&gt;{{cite news |url= http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,903358,00.html|archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20071014175809/http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,903358,00.html?promoid=googlep|url-status=dead|archive-date=14 October 2007|title=Abortion and Privacy|access-date=25 May 2007 |date=13 March 1972|magazine=[[Time (magazine)|Time]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Time'' defined privacy, concerning abortion, as the ability of a woman to "decide what happens to her own body".&lt;ref name="Time" /&gt; In political terms, privacy can be understood as a condition in which one is not observed or disturbed by government.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.askoxford.com/concise_oed/privacy?view=uk |archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20070929141702/http://www.askoxford.com/concise_oed/privacy?view=uk |url-status=dead |archive-date=29 September 2007 |title=Privacy |access-date=24 May 2007 |work=Compact Oxford English Dictionary |publisher=AskOxford.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Traditionally, American courts have located the [[Privacy laws of the United States|right to privacy]] in the [[Fourth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Fourth Amendment]], [[Ninth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Ninth Amendment]], [[Fourteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Fourteenth Amendment]], as well as the penumbra of the [[United States Bill of Rights|Bill of Rights]]. The landmark decision ''[[Roe v Wade]]'' relied on the 14th Amendment, which guarantees that federal rights shall be applied equally to all persons born in the United States. The 14th Amendment has given rise to the doctrine of [[Substantive due process]], which is said to guarantee various privacy rights, including the right to [[bodily integrity#Women's rights|bodily integrity]].

While governments are allowed to invade the privacy of their citizens in some cases, they are expected to protect privacy in all cases lacking a [[strict scrutiny|compelling state interest]]. In the US, the compelling state interest test has been developed per the standards of strict scrutiny. In ''Roe v Wade'', the Court decided that the state has an "important and legitimate interest in protecting the potentiality of human life" from the point of viability on, but that before viability, the woman's fundamental rights are more compelling than that of the state.

[[Image:Roevwade.jpg|thumb|[[Albert Wynn]] and [[Gloria Feldt]] at the [[Supreme Court of the United States|U.S. Supreme Court]] to rally in support of ''Roe v. Wade'']]

====Aftermath of U.S. judicial involvement====
{{main|Abortion in the United States}}
''[[Roe v. Wade]]'' struck down state laws banning abortion in 1973. Over 20 [[:Category:United States abortion case law|cases]] have addressed abortion law in the [[Abortion in the United States|United States]], all of which upheld ''Roe v. Wade''. Since ''Roe'', abortion has been legal throughout the country, but states have placed varying regulations on it, from requiring [[Minors and abortion|parental involvement]] in a minor's abortion to restricting [[late-term abortion]]s.

After the court ruling, controversies continued, sometimes passionately. [[Judith Blake (sociologist)|Judith Blake]], for example, even before the ruling, predicted a backlash in attitudes about abortion in "Abortion and Public Opinion" (1971). &lt;ref name="Abortion"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Blake |first1=Judith |title=Abortion and Public Opinion: The 1960-1970 Decade |journal=Science |date=12 February 1971 | volume=171|issue=3971 |pages=540–549 | doi=10.1126/science.171.3971.540 |pmid=5539717 |bibcode=1971Sci...171..540B |url=https://www.science.org/doi/pdf/10.1126/science.171.3971.540 |access-date=27 October 2021 |language=EN}}&lt;/ref&gt; After the ruling, her research indicated a considerable discrepancy between the views of the Court and those of the public at large. Meanwhile, philosophers and theologians (including Roger Wertheimer and Edmund Pincoffs) debated questions such as whether there is any rational basis for deciding whether a zygote, embryo, or fetus must be considered to be a human being. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Boyle |first=Joseph |url=http://epublications.marquette.edu/lnq/vol46/iss2/17 |title=Book Review of Abortion: New Directions for Policy Studies, ed. by Edward Manier and others   |journal=The Linacre Quarterly |date=May 1979 |volume=46 |issue=2 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Legal criticisms of the ''Roe'' decision address many points, among them are several suggesting that it is an overreach of judicial powers,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |first=William |last=Saletan |author-link=William Saletan |url= http://www.legalaffairs.org/issues/May-June-2005/feature_saleton_mayjun05.msp |title= Unbecoming Justice Blackmun |journal=Legal Affairs |date=May–June 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; or that it was not properly based on the Constitution,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Ely |first=John Hart |author-link=John Hart Ely |date=1973 &lt;!--access-date= 4 Oct 9--&gt; |title=The Wages of Crying Wolf: A Comment on Roe v. Wade |url= http://www.timothypcarney.com/wages-wolf.htm |url-status=dead |journal=[[Yale Law Journal]] |volume=82 |issue=5 |pages=920–49 |archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20070625170521/http://www.timothypcarney.com/wages-wolf.htm |archive-date=25 June 2007|doi=10.2307/795536 |jstor=795536 |pmid=11663374}}&lt;/ref&gt; or that it is an example of [[judicial activism]] and that it should be overturned so that abortion law can be decided by legislatures.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url= http://www.boston.com/yourlife/health/women/articles/2005/07/26/why_i_vetoed_contraception_bill/ |title=Why I Vetoed Contraception Bill |access-date=24 May 2007 |last=Romney |first=Mitt |author-link=Mitt Romney |date=26 July 2005 |newspaper=[[The Boston Globe]] |quote=avoiding the bitter battles engendered by 'one size fits all' judicial pronouncements. A [[federalist]] approach would allow such disputes to be settled by the citizens and elected representatives of each state, and appropriately defer to democratic governance| archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20070429111010/http://www.boston.com/yourlife/health/women/articles/2005/07/26/why_i_vetoed_contraception_bill/| archive-date= 29 April 2007 |url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt; Justice [[Potter Stewart]], who joined with the majority, viewed the ''Roe'' opinion as "legislative" and asked that more consideration be paid to state legislatures.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://members.aol.com/abtrbng2/roememos.txt |title=Testimony of Douglas W. Kmiec |access-date=24 May 2007 |last=Kmiec |first=Douglas W. |date=22 April 1996 |publisher=Judiciary Committee, U.S. House of Representatives}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Candidates competing for the Democratic nomination for the 2008 presidential election cited ''[[Gonzales v. Carhart]]'' as judicial activism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url= https://www.nytimes.com/ref/washington/ABORTIONPOSITIONS.html#democrats |title=The Presidential Candidates on Abortion |access-date=23 May 2007 |last1=Hossain |first1=Farhana |first2=Ben |last2=Werschkul |date=2007 |work=[[The New York Times]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; In upholding the [[Partial-Birth Abortion Ban Act]], ''Carhart'' is the first judicial opinion upholding a legal barrier to a specific abortion procedure.

{{blockquote|Where, in the performance of its judicial duties, the Court decides a case in such a way as to resolve the sort of intensely divisive controversy reflected in ''Roe'' and those rare, comparable cases, its [505 U.S. 833, 867] decision has a dimension that the resolution of the normal case does not carry. It is the dimension present whenever the Court's interpretation of the Constitution calls the contending sides of a national controversy to end their national division by accepting a common mandate rooted in the Constitution&amp;nbsp;... [W]hatever the premises of opposition may be, only the most convincing justification under accepted standards of precedent could suffice to demonstrate that a later decision overruling the first was anything but a surrender to political pressure and an unjustified repudiation of the principle on which the Court staked its authority in the first instance.|[[Majority opinion]] of ''[[Planned Parenthood v. Casey]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first=Thomas R. |last=Kearns |url= https://books.google.com/books?id=J_9YVh0QmUQC&amp;pg=PA8 |publisher= University of Michigan Press |title= History, Memory, and the Law| isbn= 978-0-472-08899-7| page= 340| date= August 2002}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Find1"&gt;{{cite court |litigants=[[Planned Parenthood v. Casey]] |vol=505 |reporter=U.S. |opinion=833 |date=1992 |url= http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/scripts/getcase.pl?navby=CASE&amp;court=US&amp;vol=505&amp;page=833}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
{{blockquote|Quite to the contrary, by foreclosing all democratic outlets for the deep passions this issue arouses, by banishing the issue from the political forum that gives all participants, even the losers, the satisfaction of a fair hearing and an honest fight, by continuing the imposition of a rigid national rule instead of allowing for regional differences, the Court merely prolongs and intensifies the anguish [over abortion].|Justice [[Antonin Scalia]], "concurring in the judgment in part and dissenting in part".&lt;ref name="Find1" /&gt;}}

''[[Dobbs v. Jackson]]'' overturned the ''Roe'' decision on 24 June 2022. This was a Supreme Court decision about Mississippi's law stopping abortions after 14 weeks. 

Although there is a general presumption against a state's ability to regulate extraterritorially (i.e., beyond its borders), legal authority suggests that the Constitution does not prohibit a state from regulating abortion travel.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |date=2023-10-16 |title=The Constitutionality of Banning Interstate Travel for Abortion - Bill of Health |url=https://blog.petrieflom.law.harvard.edu/2023/10/16/the-constitutionality-of-banning-interstate-travel-for-abortion/ |access-date=2024-05-03 |website=blog.petrieflom.law.harvard.edu |language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Canada===
{{Main|Abortion in Canada}}
[[File:Supreme Court of Canada Building - Winter2012.JPG|thumb|Supreme Court of Canada in Ottawa]]

With ''[[R v. Morgentaler]]'', a 5–2 majority of the Supreme Court of Canada held that the abortion provisions of the Criminal Code were unconstitutional. The majority of the Court held that the abortion provisions infringed the rights of pregnant women, contrary to the [[Section 7 of the Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms|security of the person clause]] of the [[Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms]], and could not be justified. The only laws currently governing abortion in Canada are those that govern medical procedures in general, such as those regulating the licensing of facilities, the training of medical personnel, and the like. [[Legal protection of access to abortion#Laws in Canada|Laws also exist]] which are intended to prevent anti-abortion activists from interfering with staff and patient access to hospitals and clinics, for instance by creating buffer zones around them.

Because the courts did not establish abortion as a constitutional right, Parliament continues to have jurisdiction to legislate concerning abortion. The Progressive Conservative government of [[Brian Mulroney]] twice attempted to do. The first bill, introduced in 1988, was defeated in the [[House of Commons of Canada|House of Commons]]. The next year, in 1989, the Mulroney government introduced a bill that would allow abortion only if two doctors certified that the woman's health was in danger. This bill passed the House of Commons but was defeated by a tie vote in the [[Senate of Canada|Senate]]. There have not been any further government attempts to enact legislation relating to abortion in Parliament since then.

Although the courts have not ruled on the question of fetal personhood as a matter of constitutional law, the question has been raised in two cases, ''[[Tremblay v. Daigle]]'' and ''[[R. v. Sullivan]]''. Both cases relied on the [[born alive rule]], part of Canadian common law and Quebec civil law, to determine that the fetus was not a person by law.

Two further cases are notable: ''[[Dobson (Litigation Guardian of) v. Dobson]]'', and ''Winnipeg Child &amp; Family Services (Northwest Area) v G.(D.F.)'',&lt;ref&gt;[1997] SCR 925.&lt;/ref&gt; which dismissed fetal abuse claims.

== Worldwide stances ==
{{main|Abortion law}}

=== Countries that refuse abortions ===
As of 2016, six countries completely outlaw abortion: [[El Salvador]], [[Malta]], [[Vatican City]], the [[Dominican Republic]], [[Philippines]], and [[Nicaragua]]. This prohibits a woman from having an abortion for any reason (underage, fetal impairment, [[rape]]/[[incest]]), even if it might mean saving her life.&lt;ref name="Gorman 2016"&gt;{{Cite news |last=Gorman |first=Andree |date=15 December 2016 |url= http://www.businessinsider.com/countries-strictest-abortion-laws-2016-12/#el-salvador-has-a-complete-ban-on-abortions-and-the-strictest-reproductive-rights-laws-in-the-world-1 |title=The 9 countries with the most draconian abortion laws in the world |work=Business Insider |access-date=7 December 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url= http://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2015/10/06/how-abortion-is-regulated-around-the-world/ |title=How abortion is regulated around the world |date=6 October 2015 |work=Pew Research Center |access-date=7 December 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Penalties include jail time. For example, in El Salvador, abortions are punishable with up to 50 years in prison.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=https://elpais.com/sociedad/2023-03-26/el-giro-de-bukele-con-el-aborto-de-defenderlo-a-calificarlo-de-genocidio.html?outputType=amp | title=El giro de Bukele con el aborto: De defenderlo a calificarlo de "genocidio" | date=26 March 2023 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Countries with strict laws ===
[[File:02020 0557 (2) Protest against abortion restriction in Kraków, October 2020.jpg|thumb|The [[October 2020 Polish protests]] were caused by severe changes to abortion laws.]] [[Argentina]] allowed abortion only in case of rape or if the woman's health was at risk. In December 2020, the [[Argentine Senate]] passed a bill to legalize abortion. Also in 2020, the [[Constitutional Tribunal (Poland)|Constitutional Tribunal]] ended almost all legal [[abortion in Poland]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Wilczek|first=Maria|date=22 October 2020|title=Constitutional court ends almost all legal abortion in Poland|url= https://notesfrompoland.com/2020/10/22/constitutional-court-ruling-ends-almost-all-legal-abortion-in-poland/|access-date=29 October 2020|website=Notes From Poland}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[China]] has a free abortion policy but some studies show that its government also uses [[forced abortion]] to enforce strict limits on how many children each family can have.&lt;ref name="Gorman 2016" /&gt; In the United States, there are increasing efforts to limit access to abortion by states in the wake of the 2022 reversal of Roe v Wade (1973) which allowed for a constitutional right to abortion.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Abortion Laws by State |url=https://reproductiverights.org/maps/abortion-laws-by-state/ |access-date=2024-04-22 |website=Center for Reproductive Rights |language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Effects of legalization/illegalization===
Abortion rights advocates argue that outlawing abortion increases the rate of [[unsafe abortion]]s, as the availability of professional abortion services decreases, and leads to increased [[maternal mortality]]. According to a global study collaboratively conducted by the [[World Health Organization]] and the [[Guttmacher Institute]], most unsafe abortions occur [[abortion law|where abortion is illegal]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |last=Rosenthal |first=Elisabeth |date=October 2007 |title=Legal or Not, Abortion Rates Compare |work=[[The New York Times]] |url= https://www.nytimes.com/2007/10/12/world/12abortion.html |access-date=30 June 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Withholding access to safe abortions results in 30,000 abortion-related deaths per year. Women may also choose suicide when abortion is illegal.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url= https://www.theatlantic.com/health/archive/2018/10/how-many-women-die-illegal-abortions/572638/ |title=When Abortion is Illegal, Women Rarely die. But They Still Suffer |website=[[The Atlantic]] |date=11 October 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Legalized abortion and crime effect|effect on crime of legalized abortion]] is a subject of controversy, with proponents of the theory generally arguing that "unwanted children" are more likely to become criminals and that an inverse correlation is observed between the availability of abortion and subsequent crime.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Helfgott|first=Jacqueline B.|title=Criminal Behavior: Theories, Typologies and Criminal Justice|url= https://books.google.com/books?id=-kSUlHgB2m4C|date=2008|publisher=SAGE|isbn=978-1-4129-0487-2|page=[https://books.google.com/books?id=-kSUlHgB2m4C&amp;pg=PA26n 26]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Economist [[George Akerlof]] has argued that the legalization of abortion in the United States contributed to a declining sense of paternal duty among biological fathers and to a decline in [[shotgun wedding]]s, even when women chose childbirth over abortion, and thus to an increase rather than a decrease in the rate of children born to unwed mothers.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |doi=10.2307/2946680 |last1=Akerlof |first1=George A. |last2=Yellen |first2=Janet |author-link2=Janet Yellen |last3=Katz |first3=Lawrence F. |s2cid=11777041 |author-link3=Lawrence F. Katz |name-list-style=amp |date=1996 |title=An analysis on out-of-wedlock childbearing in the United States |journal=Quarterly Journal of Economics |volume=111 |issue=2 |pages=277–317 |jstor=2946680}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |doi=10.1111/1468-0297.00288 |last=Akerlof |first=George A. |date=1998 |title=Men without children |journal=[[The Economic Journal]] |volume=108 |issue=447 |pages=287–309 |jstor=2565562|doi-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt;

KFF conducted a nationally representative survey of office-based OBGYNs in the U.S. Since Dobbs, 42% of OBGYNs report that they are very or somewhat concerned about their own legal risk when making decisions about patient care and abortion. This could greatly affect how many OBGYNs will continue to practice.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last1=Frederiksen |first1=Brittni |last2=Ranji |first2=Usha |last3=Gomez |first3=Ivette |last4=Published |first4=Alina Salganicoff |date=21 June 2023 |title=A National Survey of OBGYNs' Experiences After Dobbs |url= https://www.kff.org/womens-health-policy/report/a-national-survey-of-obgyns-experiences-after-dobbs/ |access-date=16 December 2023 |website=KFF}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Personhood==
{{Main article|Beginning of human personhood}}
There are differences of opinion as to whether a zygote/embryo/fetus [[Beginning of human personhood|acquires "personhood"]] or was always a "person". If "personhood" is acquired, opinions differ about when this happens.

Traditionally, the concept of [[personhood]] entailed the [[Soul (spirit)|soul]], a [[metaphysics|metaphysical]] concept referring to a non-corporeal or extra-corporeal dimension of [[human being]]. Today, the concepts of [[subjectivity]] and [[intersubjectivity]], [[person]]hood, [[mind]], and [[self]] have come to encompass several aspects of human beings previously considered the domain of the "soul".&lt;ref&gt;[[Charles Taylor (philosopher)|Charles Taylor]], ''Sources of the Self: The Making of Modern Identity'', Harvard University Press, 1992.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Michel Foucault]], ''The Hermeneutics of the Subject'', New York: Picador, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; Thus, while the historical question has been: when does the [[ensoulment|soul enter the body]], in modern terms, the question could be put instead: at what point does the developing individual develop personhood or selfhood?&lt;ref&gt;The question could also be put historically. The concept of "personhood" is of fairly recent vintage, and cannot be found in the 1828 edition of [http://1828.mshaffer.com/ 1828 edition of Webster's American Dictionary of the English Language], nor even as late as [http://machaut.uchicago.edu/websters 1913] {{webarchive|url= https://archive.today/20120710101105/http://machaut.uchicago.edu/websters |date=10 July 2012}}. A search in dictionaries and encyclopedias for the term "personhood" generally redirects to "person". The American Heritage Dictionary at Yahoo has: "The state or condition of being a person, especially having those qualities that confer distinct individuality."&lt;/ref&gt;

Since human development occurs continuously, identifying a precise time when a human being becomes a person could lead to an instance of the [[Sorites paradox]] (also known as ''the paradox of the heap'').&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Kerckhove |first1=Lee F. |last2=Waller |first2=Sara |title=Fetal Personhood and the Sorites Paradox |journal=The Journal of Value Inquiry |date=June 1998 |volume=32 |issue=2 |pages=175–189 |pmid=15295850 |doi=10.1023/a:1004375726894 |s2cid=37563125}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Related issues attached to the question of the beginning of human personhood include the legal status, and subjectivity of the pregnant woman&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Bordo |first=Susan |author-link=Susan Bordo |chapter=Are Mothers Persons? |title=Unbearable Weight: Feminism, Western Culture and the Body |location=Berkeley / Los Angeles |publisher=[[University of California Press]] |date=2003 |pages=71–97}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the philosophical concept of "natality" (i.e. "the distinctively human capacity to initiate a new beginning", which a new human life embodies).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Kompridis |first=Nikolas |author-link=Nikolas Kompridis |chapter=The Idea of a New Beginning: A romantic source of normativity and freedom |title=Philosophical Romanticism |location=New York |publisher=[[Routledge]] |date=2006 |pages=48–49}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 1973 US judgment ''Roe v. Wade'', the opinion of the justices included the following statement:
{{blockquote|We need not resolve the difficult question of when life begins. When those trained in the respective disciplines of medicine, philosophy, and theology are unable to arrive at any consensus, the judiciary, at this point in the development of man's knowledge, is not in a position to speculate as to the answer.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite court |litigants=Roe v. Wade |vol=410 |reporter=U.S. |opinion=113 |pinpoint=Section IX |court=S. Ct. |date=1973 |url= https://www.law.cornell.edu/supct/html/historics/USSC_CR_0410_0113_ZO.html |access-date=13 November 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

===Fetal pain===
{{See also|Prenatal perception}}A 2005 multidisciplinary systematic review in ''[[Journal of the American Medical Association|JAMA]]'' in the area of fetal development found that a fetus is unlikely to feel pain until after the sixth month of pregnancy.&lt;ref name="S. J. Lee et al. 2005"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Lee |first1=S. J. |last2=Ralston |first2=H. J. |last3=Drey |first3=E. A. |last4=Partridge |first4=J. C. |last5=Rosen |first5=M. A. |title=Fetal pain: a systematic multidisciplinary review of the evidence |journal=JAMA |volume=294 |issue=8 |pages=947–954 |date=2005 |pmid=16118385 |doi=10.1001/jama.294.8.947|doi-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="MSNBC pain"&gt;{{cite news |url= https://www.nbcnews.com/id/wbna9053416 |title=Study: Fetus feels no pain until third trimester |agency=Associated Press |work=NBC News |date=24 August 2005 |access-date=13 April 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Developmental [[neurobiology|neurobiologists]] suspect that the establishment of [[Human thalamus|thalamocortical]] connections (at about 26 weeks) may be critical to fetal perception of pain.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Johnson |first1=Martin |last2=Everitt |first2=Barry |url= https://archive.org/details/essentialreprodu0000john_p2q3 |url-access=registration |quote=emerging consensus among developmental neurobiologists that the establishment. |page=[https://archive.org/details/essentialreprodu0000john_p2q3/page/215 215] |title=Essential reproduction |publisher=Wiley |access-date=21 February 2007 |isbn=978-0632042876 |date=20 January 2000}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, legislation was proposed by anti-abortion advocates that would require abortion providers to tell a woman that the fetus may feel pain during an abortion procedure if the woman's proposed abortion was at least 20 weeks after fertilization.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |author=Weisman, Jonathan |url= https://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2006/12/04/AR2006120401089.html |title=House to Consider Abortion Anesthesia Bill |newspaper=[[The Washington Post]] |date=5 December 2006|access-date=6 February 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The ''JAMA'' review concluded that data from dozens of medical reports and studies indicate that fetuses are unlikely to feel pain until the [[third trimester]] of pregnancy.&lt;ref name="S. J. Lee et al. 2005"/&gt; However several medical critics have since disputed these conclusions.&lt;ref name="MSNBC pain" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Lowery |first1=C. L. |last2=Hardman |first2=M. P. |last3=Manning |first3=N. |last4=Hall |first4=R. W. |last5=Anand |first5=K. J. |s2cid=16909188 |title=Neurodevelopmental changes of fetal pain |journal=Seminars in Perinatology |volume=31 |issue=5 |pages=275–282 |date=2007 |doi=10.1053/j.semperi.2007.07.004 |pmid=17905181}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other researchers such as Anand and Fisk have challenged the idea that pain cannot be felt before 26 weeks, positing instead that pain can be felt at around 20 weeks.&lt;ref name="NYT pain"&gt;{{cite news |last=Paul |first=Annie |url= https://www.nytimes.com/2008/02/10/magazine/10Fetal-t.html |title=The First Ache |work=[[The New York Times Magazine]]|date=10 February 2008 |access-date=21 March 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Anand's suggestion is disputed in a March 2010 report on fetal awareness published by a working party of the [[Royal College of Obstetricians and Gynaecologists|Royal College of Obstetricians and Gynaecologists (RCOG)]], citing a lack of evidence or rationale.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.rcog.org.uk/fetal-awareness-review-research-and-recommendations-practice |title=Fetal Awareness |publisher=Royal College of Obstetricians and Gynaecologists |archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20101014111725/http://www.rcog.org.uk/fetal-awareness-review-research-and-recommendations-practice |archive-date=14 October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Page 20 of the report definitively states that the fetus cannot feel pain before week 24. Because pain can involve sensory, emotional and cognitive factors, leaving it "impossible to know" when painful experiences are perceived, even if it is known when thalamocortical connections are established.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Johnson |first1=Martin |last2=Everitt |first2=Barry |url= https://archive.org/details/essentialreprodu0000john_p2q3 |url-access=registration |page=[https://archive.org/details/essentialreprodu0000john_p2q3/page/216 216]|title=Essential reproduction |publisher=Blackwell |date=2000 |quote=The multidimensionality of pain perception, involving sensory, emotional, and cognitive factors may in itself be the basis of conscious, painful experience, but it will remain difficult to attribute this to a fetus at any particular developmental age. |access-date=21 February 2007|isbn=9780632042876}}&lt;/ref&gt; In December 2022, the RCOG conducted a review of the existing literature surrounding fetal pain awareness, and concluded, "To date, evidence indicates that the possibility of pain perception before 28 weeks of gestation is unlikely."&lt;ref&gt;"[https://www.rcog.org.uk/guidance/browse-all-guidance/other-guidelines-and-reports/fetal-awareness-updated-review-of-research-and-recommendations-for-practice/ Fetal Awareness: Updated review of Research and Recommendations for Practice]". Royal College of Obstetricians and Gynaecologists. Archived from the [https://www.rcog.org.uk/media/gdtnncdk/rcog-fetal-awareness-evidence-review-dec-2022.pdf original] on January 4, 2024.&lt;/ref&gt;

Wendy Savage—former press officer, Doctors for a Woman's Choice on Abortion—considered the question to be irrelevant. In a 1997 letter to the ''[[British Medical Journal]]'',&lt;ref&gt;Wendy Savage, [http://www.bmj.com/content/314/7088/1201.1.extract Letter to the British Medical Journal], April 1997.&lt;/ref&gt; she noted that the majority of surgical abortions in Britain were performed under general anesthesia which affects the fetus, and considers the discussion "to be unhelpful to women and to the scientific debate". Others caution against the unnecessary use of fetal anesthetic during abortion, as it poses potential health risks to the pregnant woman.&lt;ref name="S. J. Lee et al. 2005" /&gt; David Mellor and colleagues have noted that the fetal brain is already awash in naturally occurring chemicals that keep it sedated and anesthetized until birth.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Mellor |first1=D. J. |last2=Diesch |first2=T. J. |last3=Gunn |first3=A. J. |last4=Bennet |first4=L. |date=2005 |title=The importance of 'awareness' for understanding fetal pain |pmid=16269314 |journal=Brain Research Reviews |volume=49 |issue=3| pages=455–71 |doi=10.1016/j.brainresrev.2005.01.006| s2cid=9833426}}&lt;/ref&gt; At least one anesthesia researcher has suggested the fetal pain legislation may make abortions harder to obtain because abortion clinics lack the equipment and expertise to supply fetal anesthesia. Anesthesia is administered directly to fetuses only while they are undergoing surgery.&lt;ref name="NYT pain" /&gt;

===Fetal personhood debate===
{{Main|Beginning of human personhood}}
Although the two main sides of the abortion debate tend to agree that a human fetus is biologically and genetically human (that is, of the human species), they often differ in their view on whether or not a human fetus is, in any of various ways, a ''[[person]]''. Anti-abortion supporters argue that abortion is morally wrong on the basis that a fetus is an innocent [[human]] [[person]]&lt;ref name="Warren 1991"&gt;Warren 1991.&lt;/ref&gt; or because a fetus is a potential life that will, in most cases, develop into a fully functional human being.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url= http://www.str.org/site/News2?page=NewsArticle&amp;id=5187 |title=Creating a Potential Life? |first=Gregory |last=Koukl |date=1999 |work=Stand to Reason |access-date=22 March 2010 |archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20100412093804/http://www.str.org/site/News2?page=NewsArticle&amp;id=5187 |archive-date=12 April 2010 |url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; They believe that a fetus is a person upon conception. Others reject this position by distinguishing between ''human being'' and ''human person'', arguing that while the fetus is ''innocent'' and ''biologically human'', it is not a ''person'' with a ''right to life''.&lt;ref&gt;Warren 1991. See also Tooley 1972: 40–43; Singer 2000: 126–28 and 155–156; and [[Consciousness#Consciousness as the basis of personal identity|John Locke]]. The term ''person'' may be used to denote a ''psychological'' property (being rational and self-conscious), a ''moral'' property (having a right to life), or both.&lt;/ref&gt; In support of this distinction, some propose a list of criteria as markers of [[personhood]]. For example, [[Mary Ann Warren]] suggests [[consciousness]] (at least the capacity to feel pain), [[reasoning]], self-motivation, the ability to [[Communication|communicate]], and [[self-awareness]].&lt;ref name="Warren 1991"/&gt; According to Warren, a being need not exhibit all of these criteria to qualify as a person with a right to life, but if a being exhibits ''none'' of them (or perhaps only one), then it is certainly not a person. Warren concludes that as the fetus satisfies only one criterion, consciousness (and this only after it becomes [[fetal pain|susceptible to pain]]),&lt;ref name="Warren 1991"/&gt; the fetus is not a person and abortion is therefore morally permissible. Other philosophers apply similar criteria, concluding that a fetus lacks a right to life because it lacks [[Neural oscillation|brain waves]] or higher brain function,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Jones |first=D. G. |title=The problematic symmetry between brain birth and brain death |doi=10.1136/jme.24.4.237 |journal=Journal of Medical Ethics |volume=24 |issue=4 |pages=237–242 |date=1998 |pmid= 9752625 |pmc=1377672}}&lt;/ref&gt; self-consciousness,&lt;ref&gt;Tooley 1972: 44.&lt;/ref&gt; rationality,&lt;ref&gt;Singer 2000: 128 and 156–157.&lt;/ref&gt; and autonomy.&lt;ref&gt;McMahan 2002: 260&lt;/ref&gt; These lists diverge over precisely {{em|which}} features confer a right to life,&lt;ref&gt;It is similarly unclear which features one must have a natural capacity for, to have a right to life (cf. Schwarz 1990: 105–109), or which features constitute a "future like ours".&lt;/ref&gt; but tend to propose various {{em|developed}} psychological or physiological features not found in fetuses.

Critics of this typically argue that some of the proposed criteria for personhood would disqualify two classes of ''born'' human beings – reversibly [[comatose]] patients, and human infants – from having a right to life, since they, like fetuses, are not self-conscious, do not communicate, and so on.&lt;ref&gt;Marquis 1989: 197; Schwarz 1990: 89&lt;/ref&gt; Defenders of the proposed criteria may respond that the reversibly comatose ''do'' satisfy the relevant criteria because they "retain all their ''unconscious'' mental states".&lt;ref&gt;Stretton 2004: 267, original emphasis; see also Singer 2000: 137; Boonin 2003: 64–70&lt;/ref&gt; or at least some higher brain function (brain waves). Warren concedes that infants are not "persons" by her proposed criteria,&lt;ref name="Warren 1991"/&gt; and on that basis, she and others, including the moral philosopher [[Peter Singer]], conclude that [[infanticide]] could be morally acceptable under some circumstances (for example if the infant is severely disabled&lt;ref&gt;Singer 2000: 186–193&lt;/ref&gt; or to save the lives of several other infants.&lt;ref&gt;McMahan 2002: 359–360&lt;/ref&gt;

An alternative approach is to base personhood or the right to life on a being's ''natural'' or ''inherent'' capacities. On this approach, a being [[Essential property|essentially]] has a right to life if it has a ''natural capacity'' to develop the relevant psychological features; and, since human beings do have this natural capacity, they essentially have a right to life beginning at [[Conception (biology)|conception]] (or whenever they come into existence).&lt;ref&gt;P. Lee 1996 and 2004: Schwarz 1990: 91–93.&lt;/ref&gt; Critics of this position argue that mere genetic potential is not a plausible basis for respect (or for the right to life), and that basing a right to life on natural capacities would lead to the counterintuitive position that [[anencephaly|anencephalic]] infants, irreversibly comatose patients, and brain-dead patients kept alive on a [[medical ventilator]], are all persons with a right to life.&lt;ref&gt;Stretton 2004: 274–281.&lt;/ref&gt; Respondents to this criticism argue that the noted human cases in fact would not be classified as persons as they do not have a natural capacity to develop any psychological features.&lt;ref&gt;Schwarz 1990: 52.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.prolifeadvocate.us/persnbw2.html |title=Christian Research Journal, Summer 1991, page 28 – When Does a Human Become a Person?|access-date=18 February 2010 |last=Beckwith |first=Francis J. |date=1991}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= https://www.cedarville.edu/~/media/Files/PDF/Center-for-Bioethics/conception.pdf |title=Ethics &amp; Medicine, volume 19:1 – The conception view of personhood: a review |access-date=1 April 2014 |last=Sullivan|first=Dennis M. |date=2003}}&lt;/ref&gt; Also, in a view that favors benefiting even unconceived but [[potential person|potential future persons]], it has been argued as justified to abort an [[unintended pregnancy]] in favor for conceiving a new child later in better conditions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Savulescu |first1=J. |date=2002 |title=Abortion, embryo destruction and the future of value argument |journal=J Med Ethics |volume=28 |issue=3| pages=133–135 |doi=10.1136/jme.28.3.133 |pmid=12042393 |pmc=1733572}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Image:Pro-Life Demonstration at Supreme Court.jpg|thumb|Members of [[Bound4LIFE]] in [[Washington, D.C.]] symbolically cover their mouths with red tape.]]

Philosophers such as [[Aquinas]] use the concept of [[individuation]]. They argue that abortion is not permissible from the point at which individual human identity is realized. [[Anthony Kenny]] argues that this can be derived from everyday beliefs and language and one can legitimately say "if my mother had had an abortion six months into her pregnancy, she would have killed me" then one can reasonably infer that at six months the "me" in question would have been an existing person with a valid claim to life. Since division of the zygote into twins through the process of [[twins|monozygotic twinning]] can occur until the fourteenth day of pregnancy, Kenny argues that individual identity is obtained at this point and thus abortion is not permissible after two weeks.&lt;ref&gt;A. Kenny, ''Reason and Religion: Essays in Philosophical Theology'' (Oxford: Basil Blackwell), 1987&lt;/ref&gt;

===Arguments for abortion rights that do not depend on fetal non-personhood===

====Bodily rights====
An argument first presented by [[Judith Jarvis Thomson]] in her 1971 paper "A Defense of Abortion" states that {{em|even if}} the fetus is a person and has a right to life, abortion is morally permissible because a woman has a right to control her own body and its life-support functions (i.e. the right to life does not include the right to be kept alive by another person's body). Thomson's variant of this argument draws an analogy between forcing a woman to continue an unwanted pregnancy and forcing a person to allow his body to be used to maintain blood [[homeostasis]] (as a [[Kidney dialysis|dialysis]] machine is used) for another person with [[kidney failure]]. It is argued that just as it would be permissible to "unplug" and thereby cause the death of the person who is using one's kidneys, so it is permissible to abort the fetus (who similarly, it is said, has no right to use one's body's life-support functions against one's will).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Jarvis Thomson |first=Judith |title=A Defense of Abortion |journal=Philosophy &amp; Public Affairs|date=1971|volume=1|issue=1|quote=let me ask you to imagine this. You wake up in the morning and find yourself back to back in bed with an unconscious violinist. A famous unconscious violinist. He has been found to have a fatal kidney ailment, and the Society of Music Lovers has canvassed all the available medical records and found that you alone have the right blood type to help. They have therefore kidnapped you, and last night the violinist's circulatory system was plugged into yours, so that your kidneys can be used to extract poisons from his blood as well as your own. The director of the hospital now tells you, 'Look, we're sorry the Society of Music Lovers did this to you—we would never have permitted it if we had known. But still, they did it, and the violinist is now plugged into you. To unplug you would be to kill him. But never mind, it's only for nine months. By then he will have recovered from his ailment, and can safely be unplugged from you.' Is it morally incumbent on you to accede to this situation?|pages=47–66|url= http://spot.colorado.edu/~heathwoo/Phil160,Fall02/thomson.htm|access-date=9 November 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Critics of this argument generally argue that there are morally relevant disanalogies between abortion and the kidney failure scenario. For example, it is argued that the fetus is the woman's child as opposed to a mere stranger;&lt;ref&gt;Schwarz 1990; McMahan 2002&lt;/ref&gt; that abortion ''kills'' the fetus rather than merely letting it die;&lt;ref&gt;Schwarz 1990; McMahan 2002; P. Lee 1996&lt;/ref&gt; and that in the case of pregnancy arising from voluntary intercourse, the woman has either tacitly consented to the fetus using her body,&lt;ref name="Warren 1991"/&gt; or has to allow it to use her body since she is responsible for its need to use her body.&lt;ref&gt;McMahan 2002&lt;/ref&gt; Some writers defend the analogy against these objections, arguing that the disanalogies are morally irrelevant or do not apply to abortion in the way critics have claimed.&lt;ref&gt;Boonin 2003: ch 4&lt;/ref&gt;

Alternative scenarios have been put forth as more accurate and realistic representations of the moral issues present in abortion. [[John T. Noonan Jr.|John Noonan]] proposes the scenario of a family who was found to be liable for frostbite finger loss suffered by a dinner guest whom they refused to allow to stay overnight, although it was very cold outside and the guest showed signs of being sick. Noonan argues that just as it would not be permissible to refuse temporary accommodation for the guest to protect him from physical harm, it would not be permissible to refuse temporary accommodation for a fetus.&lt;ref&gt;''The Morality of abortion: legal and historical perspectives'' John T. Noonan, Harvard University Press, 1970 {{ISBN|0-674-58725-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Other critics claim that there is a difference between artificial and extraordinary means of preservation, such as medical treatment, kidney dialysis, and blood transfusions, and normal and natural means of preservation, such as gestation, childbirth, and breastfeeding. They argue that if a baby was born into an environment in which there was no replacement available for her mother's breast milk, and the baby would either breastfeed or starve, the mother would have to allow the baby to breastfeed. But the mother would never have to give the baby a blood transfusion, no matter what the circumstances were. The difference between breastfeeding in that scenario and blood transfusions is the difference between using one's body as a kidney dialysis machine, and gestation and childbirth.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |url= http://www.equipresources.org/atf/cf/%7B9C4EE03A-F988-4091-84BD-F8E70A3B0215%7D/JAA025.pdf |journal=Christian Research Journal |volume=30 |issue=4 |title=Suffer the violinist: Why the pro-abortion argument from bodily autonomy fails |access-date=25 October 2009 |last=Poupard |first=Richard J. |date=2007 |archive-date=16 July 2011 |archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20110716152144/http://www.equipresources.org/atf/cf/%7B9C4EE03A-F988-4091-84BD-F8E70A3B0215%7D/JAA025.pdf |url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Koukl |first1=G. |last2=Klusendorf |first2=S. |title=Making Abortion Unthinkable: The Art of Pro-Life Persuasion |publisher=STR Press |date=2001 |page=86}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Nathanson |first1=Bernard |last2=Ostling |first2=Richard |title=Aborting America |publisher=[[Doubleday (publisher)|Doubleday]] |location=Garden City |date=1979 |isbn=978-0-385-14461-2 |url= https://archive.org/details/abortingamerica00bern}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video |last=Boonin |first=David |title='Is Abortion Morally Justifiable in a Free Society?' Public debate at Yale University |medium=Audio |date=2005 |url= http://www.isi.org/lectures/lectures.aspx?SBy=search&amp;SSub=title&amp;SFor=Is%20Abortion%20Morally%20Justifiable%20in%20a%20Free%20Society |access-date=9 October 2009 |archive-date=7 August 2011 |archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20110807091051/http://www.isi.org/(S(b1ig3iuvnweg1d55poegw5vy))/lectures/lectures.aspx?SBy=search&amp;SSub=title&amp;SFor=Is%20Abortion%20Morally%20Justifiable%20in%20a%20Free%20Society|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Arthur |first=John |title=The Unfinished Constitution: Philosophy and Constitutional Practice |url= https://archive.org/details/unfinishedconsti0000arth |url-access=registration |publisher=Wadsworth |date=1989 |pages=[https://archive.org/details/unfinishedconsti0000arth/page/198 198]–200|isbn=9780534100148}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|url= http://homepage.mac.com/francis.beckwith/Thomson.pdf |journal=International Philosophical Quarterly |volume=32 |issue=1 |title=Personal Bodily Rights, Abortion, and Unplugging the Violinist |access-date=10 October 2009 |last=Beckwith |first=Francis |date=March 1992 |pages=105–118 |doi=10.5840/ipq199232156 |pmid=11656685 |url-status=dead |archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20100816072853/http://homepage.mac.com/francis.beckwith/Thomson.pdf |archive-date=16 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Freedom and equality====
[[Margaret Sanger]] wrote: "No woman can call herself free until she can choose consciously whether she will or will not be a mother." From this perspective, the right to abortion can be construed to be necessary for women to achieve equality with men whose freedom is not nearly so restricted by having children.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url= https://www.bbc.co.uk/ethics/abortion/mother/for_1.shtml#h4 |title=BBC - Ethics - Abortion: Arguments in favour of abortion}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Although freedom and equality are [[Subjective logic|subjective]] or based on one's perspectives in some contexts regarding politics, reproductive rights in policy are classified as fundamental freedoms for multiple reasons. Several reasons include but are not limited to the necessary proper analysis of public interests and policy, legislative violations when criminalizing abortion, utilizing humanitarian efforts, equality of resources and medical access, etc.&lt;ref name="Lantz 2019"&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Lantz |first=Paula M. |date=25 June 2019 |title=State Laws Restricting Abortion: The Need to Document Their Impact |url= http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/1468-0009.12401 |journal=The Milbank Quarterly |volume=97 |issue=3 |pages=645–648 |doi=10.1111/1468-0009.12401 |pmid=31237024 |pmc=6739611 |hdl=2027.42/151887 |issn=0887-378X}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The regulation of the [[Fundamental rights|population's fundamental rights]] disregards several policy-making purposes: assessing the burdens, opportunity costs, and unintended consequences of public policies.&lt;ref name="Lantz 2019" /&gt; Prioritization of such assessments benefits the essential understanding of trends regarding abortion rates and depicts an accurate evaluation of the status of women's reproductive freedoms and equality overall.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Beckman |first=Linda J. |date=February 2017 |title=Abortion in the United States: The continuing controversy |url= http://dx.doi.org/10.1177/0959353516685345 |journal=Feminism &amp; Psychology |volume=27 |issue=1 |pages=101–113 |doi=10.1177/0959353516685345 |s2cid=151395674 |issn=0959-3535}}&lt;/ref&gt; The right to abortion is consequently determined by referring to either the policy method of life versus choice.

==== Impacts of criminalization ====
Some activists and academics, such as [[Andrea Smith (academic)|Andrea Smith]], argue that the criminalization of abortion furthers the marginalization of oppressed groups such as poor women and women of color. Sending these women into the prison system would do nothing to address the social/political/economic problems that marginalize these women or, sometimes, cause them to require abortions.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Smith |first=Andrea |date=Spring 2005 |title=Beyond Pro-Choice versus Pro-Life: Women of Color and Reproductive Justice |jstor=4317105 |journal=NWSA Journal |volume=17 |issue=1 |pages=119–140 |doi=10.2979/NWS.2005.17.1.119 |doi-broken-date=1 November 2024 |citeseerx=10.1.1.552.2054 |s2cid=3760837}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some argue that race and sex-based abortions being prohibited further marginalizes oppressed groups by criminalizing those aspects of abortions. The Susan B. Anthony and Frederick Douglas Prenatal Nondiscrimination Act, proposed in Arizona in 2011, prohibited race and sex-based abortions and allowed punishment for those who perform abortions based on that criteria.&lt;ref name="Denbow 2016"&gt;Denbow 2016.&lt;/ref&gt; The bill characterized sex-based abortions as sex-based infanticide, and abortions based on the race of the fetus, or the race of the parent of the fetus, were seen as a practice that reinforces aspects of racial discrimination.&lt;ref name="Denbow 2016" /&gt; Laws like these can be seen as heightening the racialization of certain issues surrounding abortion.&lt;ref name="Denbow 2016" /&gt;

According to the [[World Health Organization|WHO]], criminalization can have a major negative impact on "the provision of quality care" by preventing medical personnel from acting out of fear of retaliation or punishment.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Halliday |first1=Samantha |last2=Romanis |first2=Elizabeth Chloe |last3=de Proost |first3=Lien |last4=Verweij |first4=E. Joanne |date=30 May 2023 |title=The (mis)use of fetal viability as the determinant of non-criminal abortion in the Netherlands and England and Wales |journal=Medical Law Review |volume=31 |issue=4 |pages=538–563 |doi=10.1093/medlaw/fwad015 |pmid=37253391 |pmc=10681352 |issn=0967-0742|doi-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 2022 LTP Evaluation found that doctors were unwilling to conduct late abortions even when the legislation allowed them, preferring to refer pregnant women to clinics abroad out of anxiety for the possibility of exposing themselves to criminal culpability.

This worry even extends to an unfounded fear of being prosecuted for sending their patient to a clinic in a different country where late abortion is permitted.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |date=25 August 2022 |title=State Abortion Bans Will Harm Women and Families' Economic Security Across the U.S. |url= https://www.americanprogress.org/article/state-abortion-bans-will-harm-women-and-families-economic-security-across-the-us/ |access-date=14 August 2023 |website=Center for American Progress}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The criminalization of abortion in certain states has forced women to cross state lines for abortion care. It was found that women living in states with more hostile abortion laws were traveling out of state for abortion care in greater percentages than women living in states with protected abortion access.&lt;ref name="M. H. Smith et al. 2022"&gt;M. H. Smith et al. 2022.&lt;/ref&gt; This also brought about the term "abortion deserts", which are locations or counties that have no abortion facilities.&lt;ref name="M. H. Smith et al. 2022" /&gt;

People traveling interstate for abortions decrease their home state's abortion rates, but it increases the percentages of women who will need to travel across state lines to get access to abortion care.&lt;ref name="Moseson et al. 2023"&gt;Moseson et al. 2023.&lt;/ref&gt; The travel also comes with other costs, such as transportation, insurance costs, missing work, childcare, etc. that impact the people who need this abortion care.&lt;ref name="Moseson et al. 2023" /&gt; These burdens tend to disproportionately affect people of color and impoverished people in need of reproductive healthcare.&lt;ref name="Moseson et al. 2023" /&gt;

Abortion criminalization also affects abortion providers by placing strict regulations and requirements on the providers. Targeted Regulation of Abortion Provider laws (TRAP laws) are state laws that impose annual licensing fees, personnel or facility mandates, etc. on facilities that want to continue to be abortion providers; these regulations are not imposed on other similar clinics or facilities.&lt;ref name="Medoff 2010"&gt;Medoff 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; Some criticize these laws as excessive, with many of the regulations seeming excessive. Some states have requirements for room sizes and ceiling heights, room temperatures, procedure supervision, etc. that may make it harder for facilities to acquire licensure or hard for physicians to perform the procedure.&lt;ref name="Medoff 2010" /&gt;

==== Inefficacy of abortion bans on reducing abortion ====
Research has been conducted exploring whether banning abortion reduces abortion rates. Researchers from the Guttmacher Institute, the World Health Organization, and the University of Massachusetts concluded that, in countries where abortions were restricted, the number of unintended pregnancies increased.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Bearak |first1=Jonathan |last2=Popinchalk |first2=Anna |last3=Ganatra |first3=Bela |last4=Moller |first4=Ann-Beth |last5=Tunçalp |first5=Özge |last6=Beavin |first6=Cynthia |last7=Kwok |first7=Lorraine |last8=Alkema |first8=Leontine |date=1 September 2020 |title=Unintended pregnancy and abortion by income, region, and the legal status of abortion: Estimates from a comprehensive model for 1990–2019 |journal=The Lancet Global Health |volume=8 |issue=9 |pages=e1152–e1161 |doi=10.1016/S2214-109X(20)30315-6 |issn=2214-109X |pmid=32710833 |doi-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt; The following table taken from their research shows these findings in greater detail:

'''Table: Rates of unintended pregnancy and abortion, and proportion of unintended pregnancies ending in abortion, by legal status of abortion for years 2015–19'''
{| class="wikitable"
!
!
! colspan="4" |Unintended pregnancy rate per 1000 women aged between 15 and 49 years
! colspan="4" |Abortion rate per 1000 women aged between 15 and 49 years
! colspan="4" |Unintended pregnancies ending in abortion (%)
|-
!
!
!1990–94 (80% UI)
!2015–19 (80% UI)
!Change from 1990–94 to 2015–19 (80% UI)
!Probability of change (%)
!1990–94 (80% UI)
!2015–19 (80% UI)
!Change from 1990–94 to 2015–19 (80% UI)
!Probability of change (%)
!1990–94 (80% UI)
!2015–19 (80% UI)
!Change from 1990–94 to 2015–19 (80% UI)
!Probability of change (%)
|-
| colspan="2" |Abortion broadly legal
|72 (66 to 80)
|58 (53 to 66)
|−19% (−28 to −9)
|99%
|44 (39 to 49)
|40 (36 to 47)
|−8% (−20 to 9)
|73%
|61 (56 to 65)
|70 (65 to 73)
|15% (8 to 23)
|100%
|-
|
|Abortion broadly legal (excluding India and China)
|76 (72 to 80)
|50 (46 to 54)
|−34% (−39 to −29)
|100%
|46 (43 to 50)
|26 (24 to 30)
|−43% (−49 to −36)
|100%
|61 (59 to 63)
|53 (50 to 56)
|−13% (−18 to −8)
|100%
|-
| colspan="2" |Abortion restricted
|91 (86 to 97)
|73 (68 to 79)
|−20% (−25 to −14)
|100%
|33 (28 to 38)
|36 (32 to 42)
|12% (−4 to 30)
|82%
|36 (32 to 39)
|50 (46 to 53)
|39% (27 to 53)
|100%
|-
|
|Abortion prohibited altogether
|110 (100 to 123)
|80 (70 to 91)
|−27% (−35 to −19)
|100%
|35 (27 to 48)
|40 (31 to 51)
|11% (−14 to 40)
|70%
|32 (27 to 39)
|50 (44 to 55)
|52% (30 to 78)
|100%
|-
|
|Abortion permitted to save the woman's life
|86 (80 to 93)
|70 (63 to 77)
|−19% (−26 to −12)
|100%
|31 (27 to 38)
|36 (30 to 43)
|15% (−3 to 35)
|85%
|36 (33 to 41)
|52 (48 to 56)
|41% (28 to 57)
|100%
|-
|
|Abortion permitted to preserve health
|92 (86 to 99)
|75 (70 to 81)
|−18% (−24 to −12)
|100%
|33 (28 to 38)
|36 (31 to 41)
|8% (−8 to 27)
|73%
|36 (32 to 39)
|47 (44 to 51)
|32% (20 to 47)
|100%
|}
UI = uncertainty interval.

====Abortion safety====

Even where abortions are illegal, they continue to take place, however, they are generally done unsafely, both because the need for secrecy tends to be more important than the woman's safety, and due to the lack of training and experience the person performing the abortion. When done correctly by properly trained doctors, abortion is generally safe. Where laws restrict abortion rights, abortions are less safe and result in the deaths of 30,000 women each year.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url= https://www.theatlantic.com/health/archive/2018/10/how-many-women-die-illegal-abortions/572638/|title=When Abortion is Illegal, Women Rarely die. But They Still Suffer|website=[[The Atlantic]]|date=11 October 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Population planning====

It has been suggested that access to abortion can [[Human population planning|help reduce]] human [[human overpopulation|overpopulation]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author1-link=Stephen Douglas Mumford |first1=Stephen |last1=Mumford |first2=Elton |last2=Kessel |title=Role of Abortion in Control of Global Population Growth|journal=Clinics in Obstetrics and Gynaecology|url= https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/3709011/|date=March 1986|volume=13|issue=1|pages=19–31|doi=10.1016/S0306-3356(21)00150-3|pmid=3709011|access-date=29 November 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt; which is shown to be harmful to the [[natural environment]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |first=Richard A. |last=Schwartz |title=The Social Effects of Legal Abortion |journal=[[American Journal of Public Health]] |volume=62 |page=1332 |date=October 1972 |issue=10 |doi=10.2105/AJPH.62.10.1331 |pmid=4561771 |pmc=1530462}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Arguments against abortion===

====Discrimination====
The book ''Abortion and the Conscience of the Nation'' (1983) presented the argument that abortion involves unjust [[discrimination]] against the unborn. According to this argument, those who deny that fetuses have a right to life do not value {{em|all}} human life, but instead, select arbitrary characteristics (such as particular levels of physical or psychological development) as giving some human beings more value or rights than others.&lt;ref&gt;Reagan et al. 1983.&lt;/ref&gt;{{page needed|date=December 2023}}

In contrast, philosophers who define the right to life by reference to particular levels of physical or psychological development typically maintain that such characteristics are morally relevant,&lt;ref&gt;Singer 2000: 217–18; McMahan 2002: 242–3; Boonin 2003: 126&lt;/ref&gt; and reject the assumption that all human life necessarily has value (or that membership in the species ''[[Homo sapiens]]'' is in itself morally relevant).&lt;ref&gt;, Singer 2000: 221–2; McMahan 2002: 214; Boonin 2003: 25&lt;/ref&gt;

Some abortion opponents have argued for, and promoted legislation for, a ban on the abortion of fetuses that have been diagnosed with [[Down syndrome]] on the basis that such abortions unfairly discriminate against [[disabled]] people.&lt;ref name="Hoban 2021"&gt;{{cite web |last=Hoban |first=Rose |title=In debate over Down syndrome/abortion bill, disability groups struggle with how to respond |url= https://www.northcarolinahealthnews.org/2021/06/08/disability-groups-struggle-to-respond-to-latest-abortion-bill/ |website=North Carolina Health News |date=8 June 2021 |access-date=21 January 2022}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Better source needed|reason=The current source is insufficiently reliable ([[WP:NOTRS]]).|date=January 2022}}&lt;ref name="Kolbi-Molinas Mizner 2020"&gt;{{Cite web |last1=Kolbi-Molinas |first1=Alexa |last2=Mizner |first2=Susan |date=14 January 2020 |title=The Offensive Hypocrisy of Banning Abortion for a Down Syndrome Diagnosis |url= https://www.aclu.org/news/disability-rights/the-offensive-hypocrisy-of-banning-abortion-for-a-down-syndrome-diagnosis/ |url-status=live|access-date=15 December 2021 |work=ACLU.org |publisher=[[American Civil Liberties Union]] |quote=Proponents of these bans claim that their goal is to protect the rights of people with disabilities. Such attempts to co-opt the mantle of disability rights to ban abortion are not only hypocritical but also deeply offensive. |archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20200430122942/https://www.aclu.org/news/disability-rights/the-offensive-hypocrisy-of-banning-abortion-for-a-down-syndrome-diagnosis/ |archive-date=30 April 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt; Critics of these measures charge that they are hypocritical since many of their proponents appear to be unconcerned with addressing the needs of living disabled persons.&lt;ref name="Kolbi-Molinas Mizner 2020" /&gt; In response to one such proposed measure in North Carolina, a spokesperson for Disability Rights North Carolina commented, "We would never think of using limits on someone's bodily autonomy to protect our rights."&lt;ref name="Hoban 2021" /&gt;{{Better source needed|reason=The current source is insufficiently reliable ([[WP:NOTRS]]).|date=January 2022}}

====Deprivation====
{{further|Deprivation argument}}
[[Image:March for Women's Lives detail.jpg|thumb|The 2004 [[March for Women's Lives]] near the [[Washington Monument]]]]
The argument of deprivation states that abortion is morally wrong because it deprives the fetus of a valuable future.&lt;ref&gt;Marquis 1989. See also Stone 1987.&lt;/ref&gt; On this account, killing an adult human being is wrong because it deprives the victim of a "future like ours"—a future containing highly valuable or desirable experiences, activities, projects, and enjoyments.&lt;ref&gt;Marquis 1989: 189–190&lt;/ref&gt; If a being has such a future, then killing that being would seriously harm the fetus and hence would be seriously wrong.&lt;ref name="Marquis 1989: 190"&gt;Marquis 1989: 190. The type of wrongness appealed to here is presumptive or ''[[prima facie]]'' wrongness, and it may be overridden in exceptional circumstances.&lt;/ref&gt; According to the argument, since a fetus does have such a future, the "overwhelming majority" of deliberate abortions are placed in the "same moral category" as killing an innocent adult human being.&lt;ref&gt;Marquis 1989: 183.&lt;/ref&gt; Not all abortions are unjustified according to this argument; abortion would be justified if the same justification could be applied to killing an adult human.&lt;ref name="Marquis 1989: 190" /&gt;

Criticism of this line of reasoning follows several threads. Some reject the argument on grounds relating to [[personal identity]], holding that the fetus is "not the same entity" as the adult into which it will develop, and thus that the fetus does not have a "future like ours" in the required sense.&lt;ref&gt;McMahan 2002: ch 1.&lt;/ref&gt; Others grant that the fetus has a "future like ours" but argue that being deprived of this future is not significant harm or a significant wrong to the fetus because there are relatively few "psychological connections" (continuations of memory, belief, desire, and the like) between the fetus as it is now and the adult into which it will develop.&lt;ref&gt;McMahan 2002: 271; Stretton 2004: 171–179&lt;/ref&gt; Another criticism is that the argument creates inequalities in the wrongness of killing;&lt;ref&gt;Stretton 2004: 250–260; see also McMahan 2002: 234–235 and 271&lt;/ref&gt; as the futures of some people appear to be far more valuable or desirable than the futures of other people, the argument appears to entail that some killings are far more wrong than others, or that some people have a far stronger right to life than others—a conclusion that is taken to be counterintuitive or unacceptable.{{Citation needed|date=January 2022}}

====Argument from uncertainty====
Some anti-abortion supporters argue that if there is uncertainty as to whether the fetus has a right to life, then having an abortion is equivalent to consciously taking the risk of killing another. According to this argument, if it is not known for certain whether something (such as the fetus) has a right to life, then it is reckless and morally wrong to treat that thing as if it ''lacks'' a right to life (for example by killing it).&lt;ref&gt;Schwarz 1990: 58–59; Beckwith 2007: 60–61; Reagan et al. 1983.{{page needed|date=December 2023}}&lt;/ref&gt; This would place abortion in the same moral category as [[manslaughter]] (if it turns out that the fetus has a right to life) or certain forms of [[criminal negligence]] (if it turns out that the fetus does not have a right to life).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Kreeft |first=Peter |title=Three Approaches to Abortion: A Thoughtful and Compassionate Guide to Today's Most Controversial Issue |date=2002 |publisher=[[Ignatius Press]] |isbn=0-89870-915-6}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{page needed|date=December 2023}}

David Boonin replies that if this kind of argument were correct, then the killing of nonhuman animals and plants would also be morally wrong because Boonin contends it is not known for certain that such beings lack a right to life.&lt;ref&gt;Boonin 2003: 314–15&lt;/ref&gt; Boonin also argues that arguments from uncertainty fail because the mere fact that one might be mistaken in finding certain arguments persuasive (for example, arguments for the claim that the fetus lacks a right to life) does not mean that one should act contrary to those arguments or assume them to be mistaken.&lt;ref&gt;Boonin 2003: 323&lt;/ref&gt;

====Slippery slope ====

A primary [[slippery slope argument]] used against the practice of abortion claims that the continuity of human life from conception onward requires that we do not arbitrarily deny life prior to any particular developmental milestone. For otherwise, it would be a slippery slope to the denial of adult human being's right to life because there would only be an arbitrary difference between the two cases. Thus the argument concludes that the only non-arbitrary and fair point at which to distinguish when human life has a stringent right to life and when it does not is at conception.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last= Boonin| first=David |author-link= David Boonin |date=2003 |title=A Defense of Abortion |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ISBN0521520355|publication-date=2003 |location=New York, New York |publisher= Cambridge University Press |page=36 |isbn=0521520355}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Another argument used by anti-abortion activists is the slippery slope argument, that normalizing abortion may lead to the normalization of other practices such as [[euthanasia]].&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite book |last1=Dowbiggin |first1=Ian Robert |author-link1=Ian Dowbiggin |date=2005 |title=A Concise History of Euthanasia: Life, Death, God, and Medicine |url= https://books.google.com/books?id=CNigO7gMGkUC |series=Critical Issues in World and International History Series |location=Lanham, Maryland |publisher=Rowman &amp; Littlefield |publication-date=2007 |page=133 |isbn=9780742531116 |access-date=1 May 2019 |quote=A deep respect for the sanctity of human life meant that many right-to-life activists saw euthanasia and abortion as similar crimes against innocent life. Indeed, euthanasia ranked second only to abortion within the pro-life movement as a topic of concern.&lt;br /&gt;Right-to-life activists were highly effective at linking euthanasia and abortion.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Mental health ====
{{Main|Abortion and mental health}}
Some anti-abortion activists argue that having an abortion can cause long-term harm to a woman's emotional and physical health.&lt;ref name="BBC against"&gt;{{Cite web |title=Ethics Guide: Arguments against abortion – Women's rights arguments against abortion |url= https://www.bbc.co.uk/ethics/abortion/mother/against_1.shtml |access-date=20 September 2022 |website=BBC.co.uk |publisher=[[BBC]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Religious beliefs====
{{Main|Religion and abortion}}
Views from different religions can often be in direct opposition to each other.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url= http://www.patheos.com/Resources/Additional-Resources/Topic-Page-Abortion.html|archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20100129003803/http://www.patheos.com/Resources/Additional-Resources/Topic-Page-Abortion.html|url-status=dead|title=Resources for Religious Views on Abortion on Patheos|archive-date=29 January 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Muslims typically cite the Quranic verse 17:31 which states that a fetus should not be aborted out of fear of poverty.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.bbc.co.uk/religion/religions/islam/islamethics/abortion_1.shtml Sanctity of life] retrieved 17 October 2013&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.islamicstudies.info/tafheem.php?sura=17&amp;verse=31&amp;to=40|title= Surah Al-Isra 17:31-40|publisher=islamicstudies.info}}&lt;/ref&gt; Christians who oppose abortion support their views with Scripture references such as that of [[Luke 1|Luke 1:15]]; [[Jeremiah 1|Jeremiah 1:4–5]]; [[Genesis 25|Genesis 25:21–23]]; [[Matthew 1|Matthew 1:18]]; and [[Psalm 139|Psalm 139:13–16]].{{citation needed|date=September 2022}} The [[Roman Catholic Church]], [[Eastern Orthodox Church]] and [[Oriental Orthodox Churches]], constituting approximately 70% of Christians worldwide, believe that human life begins at conception, as does the right to life; thus, abortion is considered immoral.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= https://www.vatican.va/archive/ccc_css/archive/catechism/p3s2c2a5.htm |title= Article 5: The Fifth Commandment |access-date=7 June 2011 |work=Catechism of the Catholic Church| archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20110514012545/https://www.vatican.va/archive/ccc_css/archive/catechism/p3s2c2a5.htm| archive-date= 14 May 2011 |url-status= dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=Church |first=Saint John |date=2021-09-21 |title=The Orthodox Church's View on Abortion |url=https://www.saintjohnchurch.org/orthodox-church-view-of-abortion/ |access-date=2024-01-20 |website=Saint John the Evangelist Orthodox Church |language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=admin |date=2017-02-05 |title=What's wrong with Abortion? |url=https://copticorthodoxanswers.org/social/why-is-the-church-against-abortion/ |access-date=2024-01-20 |website=Coptic Orthodox Answers |language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt; Most [[Evangelical Christians]] also consider abortion to be immoral. The [[Church of England]] also considers abortion to be morally wrong, though their position admits abortion when "the continuance of a pregnancy threatens the life of the mother".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= https://www.bbc.co.uk/religion/religions/christianity/christianethics/abortion_1.shtml |title= Abortion: the Church of England view |access-date=3 August 2009 |work=Religion &amp; Ethics}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Feminist arguments ====
Some feminists have argued that abortion does not liberate women, but gives society an excuse to not allow women who are mothers to access financial and social services that would benefit them more, such as better access to childcare, workplaces acknowledging the needs of mothers, and state support to help women reintegrate into the workplace. Further, they argue that if women did not have easy access to abortions, governments would be forced to invest more money into supporting mothers.&lt;ref name="BBC against" /&gt;

Other feminists oppose abortion because it distracts from other women's issues. Writer Megan Clancy argued that:&lt;ref name="BBC against" /&gt;
{{Blockquote|text=There are women who are raped and become pregnant; the problem is that they were raped, not that they are pregnant. There are women who are starving who become pregnant; the problem is that they are starving, not that they are pregnant. There are women in abusive relationships who become pregnant; the problem is that they are in abusive relationships, not that they are pregnant.}}
Some feminists have argued that abortion is inconsistent with feminist principles of justice and opposition to discrimination and violence. [[Feminists for Life]], an anti-abortion feminist organization, argued that:&lt;ref name="BBC against" /&gt;
{{Blockquote|text=We believe in a woman's right to control her body, and she deserves this right no matter where she lives, even if she's still living inside her mother's womb.}}
Some feminists see abortion as an excuse for men to not take responsibility for sexually exploiting women because abortion prevents men from having to take care of any children the woman has as a result of the sexual intercourse.&lt;ref name="BBC against" /&gt;

===Other factors===

====Mexico City policy====
{{Main|Mexico City policy}}
The Mexico City policy is a U.S. federal government policy requiring any [[non-governmental organization]] that is based outside the U.S. and receives U.S. government funding to refrain from performing or promoting abortion services.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite book |last=Rodgers |first=Yana |date=2018 |title=The Global Gag Rule and Women's Reproductive Health: Rhetoric Versus Reality |url=https://academic.oup.com/book/5138 |archive-url= |archive-date= |access-date=2024-10-10 |website=Oxford Academic |publisher=Oxford University Press |language=en-US |publication-date=2018 |isbn=9780190876128}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is known by critics as the "global gag rule".&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; Kelly Lifchez and Beatriz Maldonado cite studies showing that "the policy results in higher abortion rates, more unwanted births, higher maternal mortality, worse health status for unwanted children, and substantial reductions in the provision of family planning services in countries that rely on U.S. funding for family planning."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Lifchez |first1=Kelly |last2=Maldonado |first2=Beatriz |date=2022 |title=Health consequences of the Mexico City policy. |url=http://accessecon.com/Pubs/EB/2022/Volume42/EB-22-V42-I3-P105.pdf |journal=Economics Bulletin |volume=42 |issue=3 |pages=1249–1256 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20240826003004/http://accessecon.com/Pubs/EB/2022/Volume42/EB-22-V42-I3-P105.pdf |archive-date=2024-08-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Mexico City policy was instituted under [[Ronald Reagan|President Reagan]], suspended under [[Bill Clinton|President Clinton]], reinstated by [[George W. Bush|President George W. Bush]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Reproductive Rights in a Global Context |last=Knudsen |first=Lara |date=2006 |publisher= Vanderbilt University Press |isbn=978-0-8265-1528-5 |page=[https://archive.org/details/reproductiverigh0000knud/page/7 7] |url= https://archive.org/details/reproductiverigh0000knud |url-access=registration |quote=reproductive rights.}}&lt;/ref&gt; suspended again by [[Barack Obama|President Barack Obama]] on 24 January 2009&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url= http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/americas/7847651.stm |title=Obama lifts ban on abortion funds |access-date=24 January 2009 |work=BBC News |date=24 January 2009 |archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20090123205526/http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/americas/7847651.stm| archive-date= 23 January 2009 |url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt; and re-instated once again by [[President Donald Trump]] on 23 January 2017.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= https://www.federalregister.gov/documents/2017/01/25/2017-01843/the-mexico-city-policy|title=The Mexico City Policy – Memorandum for the Secretary of State[,] the Secretary of Health and Human Services[, and] the Administrator of the United States Agency for International Development|date=25 January 2017|publisher=Federal Register}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url= http://www.cnn.com/2017/01/23/politics/trans-pacific-partnership-trade-deal-withdrawal-trumps-first-executive-action-monday-sources-say/index.html|title=TPP withdrawal Trump's first executive action Monday, sources say |first1=Jeremy |last1=Diamond |author1-link=Jeremy Diamond (journalist) |first2=Dana |last2=Bash |author2-link=Dana Bash |website=CNN |access-date=23 January 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |last=Sengupta |first=Somini |url= https://www.nytimes.com/2017/01/23/world/trump-ban-foreign-aid-abortions.html |title=Trump Revives Ban on Foreign Aid to Groups That Give Abortion Counseling |date=23 January 2017 |newspaper=[[The New York Times]] |issn=0362-4331 |access-date=24 January 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2021, President Biden rescinded the Mexico City policy.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |last1=Lucey |first1=Catherine |last2=Peterson |first2=Kristina |date=28 January 2021 |title=Biden Targets Abortion Restrictions as Fight Looms in Congress |work=Wall Street Journal |url= https://www.wsj.com/articles/biden-to-reverse-abortion-rule-known-as-mexico-city-policy-11611835467 |access-date=28 January 2021 |issn=0099-9660}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Public opinion====
{{Main|Societal attitudes towards abortion}}{{update|section|date=March 2023}}

A number of opinion polls around the world have explored public opinion regarding the issue of abortion. Results have varied from poll to poll, country to country, and region to region, while varying with regard to different aspects of the issue.

In North America, a December 2001 poll surveyed [[Abortion in Canada#Opinion polls|Canadian opinion on abortion]], asking in what circumstances they believe abortion should be permitted; 32% responded that they believe abortion should be legal in all circumstances, 52% that it should be legal in certain circumstances, and 14% that it should be legal in no circumstances. A similar poll in April 2009 surveyed people in the United States about [[Abortion in the United States#Public opinion|U.S. opinion on abortion]]; 18% said that abortion should be "legal in all cases", 28% said that abortion should be "legal in most cases", 28% said abortion should be "illegal in most cases" and 16% said abortion should be "illegal in all cases".&lt;ref&gt;''[http://pewresearch.org/pubs/1212/abortion-gun-control-opinion-gender-gap Pew Research Center] {{Webarchive|url= https://web.archive.org/web/20100615042040/http://pewresearch.org/pubs/1212/abortion-gun-control-opinion-gender-gap |date=15 June 2010}}''. (2009). Retrieved 2 May 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; A November 2005 poll in Mexico found that 73.4% think abortion should not be legalized while 11.2% think it should be.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Mexicans Support Status Quo on Social Issues |publisher=[[Angus Reid Global Monitor]] |date=1 December 2005 |url= http://www.angus-reid.com/polls/view/10042 |access-date=9 December 2008 |archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20090103231252/http://www.angus-reid.com/polls/view/10042 |archive-date=3 January 2009 |url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A May 2005 survey examined attitudes toward abortion in 10 European countries, asking respondents whether they agreed with the statement, "If a woman doesn't want children, she should be allowed to have an abortion". The highest level of approval was 81% (in the Czech Republic); the lowest was 47% (in Poland).&lt;ref&gt;TNS Sofres. (May 2005). [http://www.thebrusselsconnection.be/tbc/upload/attachments/European%20Values%20Overall%20EN.pdf European Values] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070619211339/http://www.thebrusselsconnection.be/tbc/upload/attachments/European%20Values%20Overall%20EN.pdf|date=19 June 2007}}. Retrieved 11 January 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; In 2019, 58% of Poles supported abortion on request up to the 12th week of pregnancy.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |date=28 October 2020 |title=Sondaż: Rośnie poparcie dla aborcji na żądanie do 12. tygodnia ciąży |url=https://www.newsweek.pl/polska/spoleczenstwo/sondaz-rosnie-poparcie-dla-aborcji-na-zadanie-do-12-tygodnia-ciazy/bf2lwyy |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://archive.today/20201028185205/https://www.newsweek.pl/polska/spoleczenstwo/sondaz-rosnie-poparcie-dla-aborcji-na-zadanie-do-12-tygodnia-ciazy/bf2lwyy |archive-date=28 October 2020 |access-date=29 October 2020 |website=archive.vn}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A 2021 study showed that abortion providers faced discrimination and termination in the workplace, death threats, harassment, and impacts to their private and personal lives for them and their families. The same study shows that the providers continue to work in the field due to their commitment to women's health and pro-choice cause.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Chowdhary |first1=Pari |last2=Newton-Levinson |first2=Anna |last3=Rochat |first3=Roger |date=1 June 2022 |title="No One Does This for the Money or Lifestyle": Abortion Providers' Perspectives on Factors Affecting Workforce Recruitment and Retention in the Southern United States |url= https://doi.org/10.1007/s10995-021-03338-6 |journal=Maternal and Child Health Journal |volume=26 |issue=6 |pages=1350–1357 |doi=10.1007/s10995-021-03338-6 |issn=1573-6628 |pmc=9132807 |pmid=34997437}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As of 2022, after the overturn of ''Roe vs Wade'' by the Supreme Court, a ''Wall Street Journal'' poll conducted in March showed that 60% of voters believed that abortion should be legal in most cases, an increase of 5% earlier in the year. 29% of participates believed it should be illegal in most cases, except for endangerment of the woman, rape, or incest. Lastly, 6% said it should be illegal in all cases, down from 11% earlier that same year.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=Lucey |first=Catherine |date=September 3, 2022 |title=Support for Legalized Abortion Grows Since Dobbs Ruling, WSJ Poll Shows |url=https://www.wsj.com/articles/support-for-legalized-abortion-grows-since-dobbs-ruling-wsj-poll-shows-11662210020 |website=Wall Street Journal}}&lt;/ref&gt; A 2024 Pew Research Center poll reported 63% of Americans believed abortion should be legal in all or most cases. The poll found that the share of Americans living in states with abortion bans or restrictions who believe abortions should be easier to access has increased by 12%.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=Nadeem |first=Reem |date=2024-05-13 |title=Broad Public Support for Legal Abortion Persists 2 Years After Dobbs |url=https://www.pewresearch.org/politics/2024/05/13/broad-public-support-for-legal-abortion-persists-2-years-after-dobbs/ |access-date=2024-08-04 |website=Pew Research Center |language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt; This poll found little difference based on gender (61% of men generally supportive vs 64% of women) with education and especially religious affiliation being better predictive factors. It also shows that younger people tend to be more positive towards abortion with the 50-64 group being the most negative.

African countries have different views based on region and cultural influences. In Kenya, both male and female opinions show that abortion is frowned upon, due to embedded social norms that stem from religious and cultural beliefs. While younger generations are starting to normalize abortions, limited access to procedure, high costs, and lack of information still leads to unsafe abortion practices.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Community perception of abortion, women who abort and abortifacients in Kisumu and Nairobi counties, Kenya. - Document - Gale In Context: Opposing Viewpoints |url= https://link.gale.com/apps/doc/A608456645/OVIC?u=nebraska_scc&amp;sid=bookmark-OVIC&amp;xid=fdf35e6a |access-date=14 March 2023 |website=link.gale.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; In Nigeria, the abortion laws are even stricter. Rather than being ostracized by the community, abortion in Nigeria can lead to life imprisonment for both the abortion seekers and those who assist them. The country's government has outlawed abortion in all cases except to save the life of the pregnant person. In a survey of women, many cited religion, incomplete abortion, future infertility, and death as a fear when seeking abortion in Nigeria.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title="I just have to hope that this abortion should go well": Perceptions, fears, and experiences of abortion clients in Nigeria. - Document - Gale In Context: Opposing Viewpoints |url= https://link.gale.com/apps/doc/A692322820/OVIC?u=nebraska_scc&amp;sid=bookmark-OVIC&amp;xid=d5aa2c2a |access-date=14 March 2023 |website=link.gale.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Of attitudes in South America, a December 2003 survey found that 30% of Argentines thought that [[abortion in Argentina]] should be allowed "regardless of situation", 47% that it should be allowed "under some circumstances", and 23% that it should not be allowed "regardless of situation".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Argentines Assess Abortion Changes |publisher=[[Angus Reid Global Monitor]] |date=4 March 2004 |url= http://www.angus-reid.com/polls/view/2029 |access-date=9 December 2008 |archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20090103190525/http://www.angus-reid.com/polls/view/2029 |archive-date=3 January 2009 |url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; A more recent poll now suggest that 45% of Argentinians are in favor of abortion for any reason in the first twelve weeks. This same poll conducted in September 2011 also suggests that most Argentinians favor abortion being legal when a woman's health or life is at risk (81%), when the pregnancy is a result of rape (80%) or the fetus has severe abnormalities (68%).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Views on Changing the Law on Abortion in Argentina |publisher=Belden Russonello Strategists |date=October 2011 |url= http://www.catholicsforchoice.org/news/pr/2011/documents/ArgentinaSurveyEnglish3.pdf |access-date=22 November 2011 |url-status=dead |archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20120524022054/http://www.catholicsforchoice.org/news/pr/2011/documents/ArgentinaSurveyEnglish3.pdf |archive-date=24 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; A March 2007 poll regarding the [[Abortion in Brazil|abortion law in Brazil]] found that 65% of Brazilians believe that it "should not be modified", 16% that it should be expanded "to allow abortion in other cases", 10% that abortion should be "decriminalized", and 5% were "not sure".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Brazilians Want to Keep Abortion as Crime |publisher=[[Angus Reid Global Monitor]] |date=12 April 2007 |url= http://www.angus-reid.com/polls/view/15370 |access-date=9 December 2008 |archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20090103192744/http://www.angus-reid.com/polls/view/15370 |archive-date=3 January 2009 |url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; Later a poll made in September 2022 found that the 70% of Brazilians where against abortions, 20% where in favor of it, 8% where neither in favor or against it, and 2% didn't know what to answer.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |date=13 September 2022 |title=Ipec: 70% dos brasileiros dizem ser contra a legalização do aborto |url= https://g1.globo.com/politica/noticia/2022/09/13/ipec-70percent-dos-brasileiros-dizem-ser-contra-a-legalizacao-do-aborto.ghtml |access-date=19 September 2023 |website=G1 |language=pt-br}}&lt;/ref&gt; A July 2005 poll in [[Colombia]] found that 65.6% said they thought that abortion should remain illegal, 26.9% that it should be made legal, and 7.5% that they were unsure.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Colombians Reject Legalizing Abortion |publisher=[[Angus Reid Global Monitor]] |date=2 August 2005 |url= http://www.angus-reid.com/polls/view/8333 |access-date=9 December 2008 |archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20090103185722/http://www.angus-reid.com/polls/view/8333 |archive-date=3 January 2009 |url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The attitudes in Asia vary. More secular parts of Asia such as Japan and Taiwan are more likely to favor abortion, and more religious parts such as Pakistan and Indonesia are more likely to oppose abortion. Other countries, such as China, are in between but still slightly favoring abortion. A worldwide survey conducted in 2022 reported that 14% of Chinese thought that [[abortion in China]] should be "legal in all cases", 34% that it should be "legal in most cases", 20% that it should be "illegal in most cases", and 13% that it should be "illegal in all cases", with 20% that did not respond. The same survey reported that 17% of Japanese thought that [[abortion in Japan]] should be "legal in all cases", 32% that it should be "legal in most cases", only 7% that it should be "illegal in most cases", and a very small minority of 2% that it should be "illegal in all cases", with an overwhelming 43% that did not respond. The survey also reported that 14% of Malaysians thought that [[abortion in Malaysia]] should be "legal in all cases", 18% that it should be "legal in most cases", 25% that it should be "illegal in most cases", and 20% that it should be "illegal in all cases", with 23% that did not respond, amounting to almost half the population with a negative view of abortion.&lt;ref&gt;https://www.ipsos.com/sites/default/files/ct/news/documents/2022-07/Global%20Advisor-Global%20Opinion%20on%20Abortion%202022-Graphic%20Report.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

According to global surveys in 2023 and 2024, the right to access legal abortion is widely supported. There is particularly strong widespread support for legal abortion in Europe.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=Clancy |first=Janell Fetterolf and Laura |date=2024-05-15 |title=Support for legal abortion is widespread in many countries, especially in Europe |url=https://www.pewresearch.org/short-reads/2024/05/15/support-for-legal-abortion-is-widespread-in-many-countries-especially-in-europe/ |access-date=2024-07-07 |website=Pew Research Center |language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Effect upon crime rate====
{{Main|Legalized abortion and crime effect}}

A theory attempts to draw a correlation between the United States' unprecedented nationwide decline of the overall crime rate during the 1990s and the decriminalization of abortion 20 years prior.

The suggestion was brought to widespread attention by a 1999 academic paper, ''[[The Impact of Legalized Abortion on Crime]]'', authored by the economists [[Steven Levitt|Steven D. Levitt]] and John Donohue. They attributed the drop in crime to a reduction in individuals said to have a higher statistical probability of committing crimes: unwanted children, especially those born to mothers who are African American, impoverished, [[teenage pregnancy|adolescent]], uneducated, and [[single parent|single]]. The change coincided with what would have been the adolescence, or peak years of potential criminality, of those who had not been born as a result of ''Roe v Wade'' and similar cases. Donohue and Levitt's study also noted that states which legalized abortion before the rest of the nation experienced the lowering crime rate pattern earlier, and those with higher abortion rates had more pronounced reductions.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |first1=John J. |last1=Donohue |last2=Levitt |first2=Steven D. |date=May 2001 |title=The Impact of Legalized Abortion on Crime |journal=[[Quarterly Journal of Economics]] |volume=116 |issue=2 |pages=379–420 |doi=10.1162/00335530151144050 |title-link=The Impact of Legalized Abortion on Crime}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Fellow economists Christopher Foote and Christopher Goetz criticized the methodology in the Donohue-Levitt study, noting a lack of accommodation for statewide yearly variations such as cocaine use, and recalculating based on incidence of crime per capita; they found no [[statistically significant]] results.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Foote |first1=Christopher L. |last2=Goetz |first2=Christopher F. |date=February 2008|title=The Impact of Legalized Abortion on Crime: Comment |journal=[[Quarterly Journal of Economics]] |volume=123 |issue=1 |pages=407–423 |doi=10.1162/qjec.2008.123.1.407 |citeseerx=10.1.1.575.497}}&lt;/ref&gt; Levitt and Donohue responded to this by presenting an adjusted [[data set]] which took into account these concerns and reported that the data maintained the statistical significance of their initial paper.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Donohue |first1=John J. |last2=Levitt |first2=Steven D. |date=February 2008|title=Measurement Error, Legalized Abortion, and the Decline in Crime: A Response to Foote and Goetz |journal=[[Quarterly Journal of Economics]] |volume=123 |issue=1 |pages=425–440 |doi=10.1162/qjec.2008.123.1.425 |s2cid=11532713 |url= http://www.nber.org/papers/w11987.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Such research has been criticized by some as being [[utilitarianism|utilitarian]], discriminatory as to race and socioeconomic class, and as promoting [[eugenics]] as a solution to crime.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Crime-Abortion Study Continues to Draw Pro-life Backlash |date=11 August 1999 |publisher=The Pro-Life Infonet |url= http://ohioroundtable.org/library/articles/life/crimeabortion.html |work=Ohio Roundtable Online Library |access-date=6 December 2008 |archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20050228041848/http://www.ohioroundtable.org/library/articles/life/crimeabortion.html |archive-date=28 February 2005 |url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=J. B. F. |url= http://www.americancatholic.org/Messenger/Jan2000/Editorial.asp |title=Abortion and the Lower Crime Rate |date=January 2000|work=St. Anthony Messenger |access-date=6 December 2008| archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20081205054847/http://www.americancatholic.org/Messenger/Jan2000/editorial.asp |archive-date= 5 December 2008 |url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; Levitt states in his book ''[[Freakonomics]]'' that they are neither promoting nor negating any course of action—merely reporting data as economists.

====Breast cancer hypothesis====
{{Main|Abortion–breast cancer hypothesis}}
The abortion–breast cancer hypothesis posits that induced abortion may increase the risk of developing breast cancer.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Russo |first1=J. |last2=Russo |first2=I. H. |title=Susceptibility of the mammary gland to carcinogenesis. II. Pregnancy interruption as a risk factor in tumor incidence |journal=The American Journal of Pathology |volume=100 |issue=2 |pages=505–506 |date=August 1980 |pmid=6773421 |pmc=1903536 |quote=In contrast, abortion is associated with increased risk of carcinomas of the breast. The explanation for these epidemiologic findings is not known, but the parallelism between the DMBA-induced rat mammary carcinoma model and the human situation is striking.&amp;nbsp;... Abortion would interrupt this process, leaving in the gland undifferentiated structures like those observed in the rat mammary gland, which could render the gland again susceptible to carcinogenesis.}}&lt;/ref&gt; This 1980's paper actually contrasts with other scientific data that abortion is not related causality with breast cancer occurrence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= https://www.who.int/mediacentre/factsheets/fs240/en/index.html |title=Induced abortion does not increase breast cancer risk |date=June 2000 |access-date=24 December 2007 |publisher=[[World Health Organization]] |archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20071214064635/http://www.who.int/mediacentre/factsheets/fs240/en/index.html |archive-date=14 December 2007 |url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |title=The Care of Women Requesting Induced Abortion |orig-date=2000 |url= http://www.rcog.org.uk/resources/Public/pdf/induced_abortionfull.pdf |archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20080227213507/http://www.rcog.org.uk/resources/Public/pdf/induced_abortionfull.pdf |archive-date=27 February 2008 |access-date=5 December 2008 |series=Evidence-based Clinical Guideline Number 7 |date=September 2004 |publisher=[[Royal College of Obstetricians and Gynaecologists]] |isbn=978-1-904752-06-6 |oclc=263585758 |page=43}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://oversight.house.gov/features/politics_and_science/example_breast_cancer.htm |title=Breast Cancer Risks |access-date=14 April 2008 |publisher=[[United States House Committee on Oversight and Government Reform]] |archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20080327055020/http://oversight.house.gov/features/politics_and_science/example_breast_cancer.htm |archive-date=27 March 2008 |url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The hypothesis suggests that during early pregnancy, levels of [[estrogen]] increase, leading to breast growth in preparation for [[lactation]], and if this process is interrupted by an abortion&amp;nbsp;– before full maturity in the third trimester&amp;nbsp;– then more relatively vulnerable immature cells could be left than there were prior to the pregnancy, resulting in a greater potential risk of breast cancer. The hypothesis mechanism was explored in rat studies conducted in the 1980s, from the same lab, so it lacks any scientific validation.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Russo |first1=J. |last2=Russo |first2=I. H. |title=Susceptibility of the mammary gland to carcinogenesis. II. Pregnancy interruption as a risk factor in tumor incidence |journal=The American Journal of Pathology |volume=100 |issue=2 |pages=497–512 |date=August 1980 |pmid=6773421 |pmc=1903536}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Russo |first1=J. |last2=Tay |first2=L. |last3=Russo |first3=I. H. |title=Differentiation of the mammary gland and susceptibility to carcinogenesis |journal=Breast Cancer Research and Treatment |volume=2 |issue=1 |pages=5–73 |date=1982 |pmid=6216933 |doi=10.1007/BF01805718|s2cid=22657169}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Russo |first1=J. |last2=Russo |first2=I. H. |title=Biological and molecular bases of mammary carcinogenesis |journal=Laboratory Investigation |volume=57 |issue=2 |pages=112–137 |date=1987 |pmid=3302534 |issn=0023-6837}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Minors ====
{{Main|Minors and abortion}}
Many states require an unmarried minor to have parental consent or notification before an abortion is allowed to happen.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Haas-Wilson |first=Deborah |date=1993 |title=The Economic Impact of State Restrictions on Abortion: Parental Consent and Notification Laws and Medicaid Funding Restrictions |url= https://www.jstor.org/stable/3325303 |journal=Journal of Policy Analysis and Management |volume=12 |issue=3 |pages=498–511 |doi=10.2307/3325303|jstor=3325303|pmid=10127357 }}&lt;/ref&gt; These are known as [[Parental involvement (abortion)|parental involvement]] laws. The parents or guardians of the pregnant person must be consulted before an abortion is to be induced legally. States with these laws generally have different degrees of involvement and enforcement. A judge can be consulted to overrule a parent in the event the pregnant person is denied abortion services.

Studies have shown that these the required notification laws have not affected the probability that teenagers will engage in sexual activity or the demand for abortion.&lt;ref name="Medoff 2013"&gt;Medoff 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; The rate of abortions for minors decreases in states with parental involvement laws by nearly 13 to 22 percent, however, it raises the rate for out-of-state abortions such in the case of Mississippi and Missouri.&lt;ref name="Medoff 2013" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Medoff 2010" /&gt;

Teenagers are shown to seek abortion across state lines to areas with less restrictive abortion laws to bypass these preventative methods. In the United States, 37 states require the parent to have knowledge while only 21 of those states need one parent to consent.&lt;ref name="Guttmacher 2016"&gt;{{Cite news |url= https://www.guttmacher.org/state-policy/explore/parental-involvement-minors-abortions |title=Parental Involvement in Minors' Abortions |date=14 March 2016 |work=Guttmacher.org |publisher=[[Guttmacher Institute]] |access-date=7 December 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Certain states have an alternative answer to the involvement of the parent by getting the judicial system involved with a judicial bypass. In those states, minors can get permission from the judge if parents are not willing to do so or if they are absent from their lives.&lt;ref name="Guttmacher 2016" /&gt;

There are different guidelines for minors and abortions in every country. In most of Europe, all persons that are capable of judgment enjoy [[medical privacy]] and can decide medical matters on their own. The capability of judgment does not come at a defined age, however, and is dependent on how well the person is able to understand the decision and its consequences. For most medical procedures, the capability of judgment usually sets in at ages 12 to 14.

Parental involvement is one of the most common methods of restricting abortion, along with Medicaid funding restrictions, mandatory delay laws, licensing fees for abortion providers, and mandatory counseling laws.&lt;ref name="Medoff 2010" /&gt;

Economist [[Marshall Medoff]] has argued that parental involvement laws are largely ineffective at reducing abortion demands. One cause could be that some states do not require parental involvement, so out-of-state abortions could meet the demands.&lt;ref name="Medoff 2013" /&gt;

==See also==
{|
|- valign="top"
|
* [[Abortion: New Directions for Policy Studies]]
* [[Legal protection of access to abortion|Bubble zone laws]]
* [[Conscience clause (medical)]]
* [[Consistent life ethic]]
* [[Stem cell controversy|Embryonic stem cell research]]
* [[Equal Protection Clause]]
* [[Paper Abortion]]
|
* [[Feticide]]
* [[Opposition to the legalization of abortion]]
* [[Reproductive rights]]
* [[Roe effect]]
* [[Support for the legalization of abortion]]
* [[Philosophical aspects of the abortion debate]]
|}

==Notes==
{{Reflist}}

==References==
*{{Cite book |last=Boonin |first=David |title=A Defense of Abortion |series=Cambridge Studies in Philosophy and Public Policy |date=2003 |publisher=University of Colorado |location=Boulder |isbn=978-0-521-52035-5}}
*{{Cite book |last=Lee |first=Patrick |title=Abortion and Unborn Human Life |date=1996 |publisher=Catholic University of America Press |isbn=978-0-8132-0846-6}}
*{{Cite journal |last=Lee |first=Patrick |s2cid=31160912 |date=June 2004|title=The Pro-Life Argument from Substantial Identity: A Defense |journal=Bioethics |volume=18 |issue=3 |doi=10.1111/j.1467-8519.2004.00393.x |pmid=15341038 |pages=249–63}}
*{{Cite journal |last=Marquis |first=Don |author-link=Don Marquis (philosopher) |date=April 1989 |title=Why Abortion is Immoral |journal=[[The Journal of Philosophy]] |volume=86 |issue=4 |pages=183–202 |doi=10.2307/2026961 |pmid=11782094 |jstor=2026961 |s2cid=12645264}}
*{{Cite book |last=McMahan |first=Jeff |author-link=Jeff McMahan (philosopher) |title=The Ethics of Killing: Problems at the Margins of Life |series=Oxford Ethics Series |date=2002 |publisher=Oxford University Press |location=New York |isbn=978-0-19-516982-9}}
*{{Cite journal |last=Medoff |first=Marshall H. |author-link=Marshall Medoff |date=2010 |title=State Abortion Policies, Targeted Regulation of Abortion Provider Laws, and Abortion Demand |journal=Review of Policy Research |volume=27 |issue=5 |pages=577–594 |doi=10.1111/j.1541-1338.2010.00460.x |url= https://web.pdx.edu/~nwallace/AHP/StateAbortion.pdf |via=Portland State University}}
*{{Cite journal |last=Medoff |first=Marshall H. |author-link=Marshall Medoff |date=25 September 2013 |title=Social Policy and Abortion: A Review of the Research |url= http://benthamopen.com/ABSTRACT/TODEMOJ-6-18 |journal=The Open Demography Journal |volume=6 |issue=1 |pages=18–27 |issn=1874-9186 |doi=10.2174/1874918601306010018|doi-access=free }}
*{{Cite journal |last1=Moseson |first1=Heidi |first2=Mikaela H. |last2=Smith |first3=Payal |last3=Chakraborty |first4=Hilary J. |last4=Gyuras |first5=Abigail |last5=Foster |first6=Danielle |last6=Bessett |first7=Tracey |last7=Wilkinson |first8=Alison |last8=Norris |date=2023 |title=Abortion-Related Laws and Concurrent Patterns in Abortion Incidence in Indiana, 2010-2019 |journal=American Journal of Public Health |volume=113 |issue=4 |pages=429–437 |doi=10.2105/AJPH.2022.307196| pmid=36795983 |pmc=10003501}}
*{{cite book |last1=Reagan |first1=Ronald |author-link=Ronald Reagan |first2=William P. |last2=Clark |author2-link=William P. Clark Jr. |first3=Brian P. |last3=Johnston |first4=Wanda |last4=Franz |author4-link=Wanda Franz |title=Abortion and the Conscience of the Nation |date=1983 |publisher=[[Regency Enterprises|New Regency Publishing]] |isbn=0-9641125-3-1}}
*{{Cite book |last=Schwarz |first=Stephen D. |title=The Moral Question of Abortion |date=1990 |publisher=Loyola University Press |location=Chicago |isbn=978-0-8294-0623-8}}
*{{Cite book |last=Singer |first=Peter |author-link=Peter Singer |title=Writings on an Ethical Life |date=2000 |publisher=Ecco (HarperCollins) |isbn=978-0-06-019838-1 |url= https://archive.org/details/writingsonethica00sing}}
*{{Cite journal |last=Stone |first=Jim |date=December 1987 |title=Why Potentiality Matters |journal=Canadian Journal of Philosophy |volume=17 |issue=4 |pages=815–830 |doi=10.1080/00455091.1987.10715920 |s2cid=147106418}}
*{{Cite journal |last=Stretton |first=Dean |date=June 2004 |title=Essential Properties and the Right to Life: A Response to Lee |journal=Bioethics |volume=18 |issue=3 |pages=264–282 |doi=10.1111/j.1467-8519.2004.00394.x |pmid=15341039}}
*{{Cite journal |last=Tooley |first=Michael |date=1972 |title=Abortion and Infanticide |journal=Philosophy and Public Affairs |volume=2 |issue=1 |pages=37–65 |jstor=2264919}}
*{{Cite book |last=Warren |first=Mary Anne |author-link=Mary Anne Warren |date=1991 |orig-year=1973, 1982 |contribution=On the Moral and Legal Status of Abortion |title=Biomedical Ethics |edition=2nd |editor1-first=Thomas A. |editor1-last=Mappes |editor2-first=Jane S. |editor2-last=Zembaty |location=New York |publisher=[[McGraw-Hill]] |isbn=9780070401266 |pages=438–444 |url= https://archive.org/details/biomedicalethics3ed00unse_z2q9 |via=Internet Archive |url-access=registration}}
*{{Cite journal |first=Jennifer M. |last=Denbow |date=2016 |title=Abortion as Genocide: Race, Agency, and Nation in Prenatal Nondiscrimination Bans |journal=Signs: Women in Culture and Society |volume=41 |issue=3 |pages=603–626 |doi=10.1086/684239 |s2cid=147059771}}
*{{Cite journal |last1=Smith |first1=Mikaela H. |first2=Zoe |last2=Muzyczka |first3=Payal |last3=Chakraborty |first4=Elaina |last4=Johns-Wolfe |first5=Jenny |last5=Higgins |first6=Danielle |last6=Bessett |first7=Alison H. |last7=Norris |date=2022 |title=Abortion Travel Within the United States: An Observational Study of Cross-State Movement to Obtain Abortion Care in 2017 |journal=The Lancet Regional Health – Americas |volume=10 |doi=10.1016/j.lana.2022.100214 |pmid=36777689 |pmc=9903901 |url= https://www.thelancet.com/pdfs/journals/lanam/PIIS2667-193X(22)00031-X.pdf}}

==External links==
&lt;!--======================== {{No more links}} ============================
 |   PLEASE BE CAUTIOUS IN ADDING MORE LINKS TO THIS ARTICLE. Wikipedia   |
 |   is not a collection of links nor should it be used for advertising.  |
 |                                                                        |
 |           Excessive or inappropriate links WILL BE DELETED.            |
 |                                                                        |
 |   See [[Wikipedia:External links]] &amp; [[Wikipedia:Spam]] for details.   |
 |                                                                        |
 |   If there are already plentiful links, please propose additions or    |
 |   replacements on this article's discussion page, or submit your link  |
 |   to the relevant category at the Open Directory Project (dmoz.org)    |
 |   and link back to that category using the {{dmoz}} template.          |
 ======================= {{No more links}} =============================--&gt;
{{Wikiquote}}
*[http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/scripts/getcase.pl?court=US&amp;vol=410&amp;invol=113 Findlaw: full text of ''Roe v. Wade'' decision, plus discussion]
*[http://www.rsrevision.com/Alevel/ethics/abortion/index.htm Abortion and Ethics], RSRevision.com - Case studies, Christian and non-Christian responses and resources for students
*[http://webarchive.loc.gov/all/20041022184522/http://www.agi-usa.org/pubs/journals/2411798.html Reasons why women have induced abortions, evidence from 27 countries], August 1998, AGI-USA.org
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20110717003552/http://www.thehist.com/index.php?option=com_docman&amp;task=cat_view&amp;gid=65&amp;limit=5&amp;limitstart=0&amp;order=date&amp;dir=ASC&amp;Itemid=713 Recordings] of the College Historical Society debate on abortion featuring Professor William Binchy, Frances Kissling, and Rebecca Gomperts
*[https://www.bbc.co.uk/ethics/abortion/religion/religion.shtml Religious perspectives on abortion], BBC.co.uk
*[https://www.britannica.com/story/pro-and-con-abortion Pro and Con: Abortion], Britannica.com
*[https://abortion.procon.org/ Should Abortion Be Legal?], ProCon.org by Britannica
*[https://www.kialo.com/pro-life-vs-pro-choice-should-abortion-be-legal-5637 Pro-Life vs Pro-Choice: Should Abortion be Legal?], interactive [[argument map]] of the abortion debate at [[Kialo.com]]
*[[Wikiversity:Should abortion be legal?|Should abortion be legal?]] – Wikidebate at Wikiversity

{{Abortion}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Abortion Debate}}
[[Category:Abortion debate| ]]
[[Category:Personhood]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>