<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20091115212412|326043135" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="256025" pageid="256025" ns="0" title="Abortion debate"><revisions><rev timestamp="2009-11-15T21:25:05Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{globalize}}
{{Weasel|date=March 2009}}


The '''abortion debate''' refers to discussion and controversy surrounding the moral and legal status of [[abortion]]. The two main groups involved in the abortion debate are the [[pro-choice]] movement, and the [[pro-life]] movement.  Each movement has, with varying results, sought to influence public opinion and to attain legal support for its position.  In [[Abortion in Canada|Canada]], for example, abortion is available on demand,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://dictionary.reference.com/search?q=abortion-on-demand&amp;r=66 |title=abortion on demand |accessdate=2007-05-01 |work=Dictionary.com |quote=(1) the right of a woman to have an abortion during the first six months of a pregnancy; (2) an abortion performed on a woman solely at her own request}}&lt;/ref&gt; while in [[Abortion in Nicaragua|Nicaragua]] abortions are illegal.&lt;ref&gt;http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/health/7041048.stm&lt;/ref&gt; In some cases, the abortion debate has led to the use of [[Abortion-related violence|violence]].

==Terminology==
Many of the terms used in the debate are seen as [[Framing (social sciences)|political framing]]: terms used to validate one's own stance while invalidating the opposition's.  For example, the labels "pro-choice" and "pro-life" imply endorsement of widely held values such as [[liberty]] and [[Freedom (political)|freedom]], while suggesting that the opposition must be "''anti''-choice" or "''anti''-life" (alternatively "pro-''coercion''" or "pro-''death''").&lt;ref&gt;Handbook of Constructionist Research, Holstein and Gubrium, Guilford Press, 2008&lt;/ref&gt;  Such terms gloss over the underlying issue of ''which'' choice or life is being considered and ''whose'' choice or ''what kind'' of life is deemed most important.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ordinary-gentlemen.com/2009/06/ah-abortion/ Retrieved 15 June 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

Appeals are often made in the abortion debate to the [[rights]] of the fetus, pregnant woman, or other parties.  Such appeals can generate confusion if the ''type'' of rights is not specified (whether [[Civil rights|civil]], [[Natural rights|natural]], or otherwise) or if it is simply ''assumed'' that the right appealed to takes precedence over all other competing rights (an example of [[begging the question]], defined as, "when a proposition which requires proof is assumed without proof").&lt;ref name="Welton279"&gt;James Welton. [http://books.google.com/books?id=v3sZAAAAYAAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=James+Welton#v=onepage&amp;q=when%20a%20proposition%20which%20requires%20proof%20is%20assumed%20without%20proof&amp;f=false A Manual of Logic]. (1905), p. 279.&lt;/ref&gt;

The appropriate terms with which to designate the human organism prior to birth are also debated. The medical terms "[[embryo]]" and "[[fetus]]" are seen by pro-life advocates as [[dehumanization|dehumanizing]]&lt;ref&gt;Brennan 'Dehumanizing the vulnerable' 2000&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Princeton Progressive Review 1986 http://groups.csail.mit.edu/mac/users/rauch/nvp/consistent/naomi_wolf.html&lt;/ref&gt;. The terms "[[Infant|baby]]" and "unborn child" are seen by pro-choice advocates as [[emotionalism|emotionalized]]. Similarly, there is debate between use of the terms "[[woman]]" and "[[mother]]".

==Political debate==
[[Politics]] refers to the processes, defined and limited through legal documents, by which decisions ([[laws]]) are made in [[governments]].  In politics, [[Civil rights|rights]] are the protections and privileges legally granted to [[citizens]] by the government.  Regarding [[abortion law]], the political debate usually surrounds a right to [[privacy]], and when or how a government may [[Regulation|regulate]] abortion.  For example, there is abundant debate regarding the extent of abortion regulation.  Some pro-choice advocates argue that it should be illegal for governments to regulate abortion any more than other medical practices.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.bccla.org/positions/privateoff/72abortion.html |title=Abortion |accessdate=2007-05-24 |work=Positions |publisher=British Columbia Civil Liberties Association |quote=…rights call for complete legal freedom to secure an abortion, in the sense that the legal status of abortion should be the same as that of other medical services that a doctor provides to a patient}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Some pro-life advocates argue that governments should be permitted to regulate abortions after the 20th week,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/pagerender.fcgi?artid=1455357&amp;pageindex=2 |title=Abortion |accessdate=2007-05-24 |year=1973 |month=December |work=Where We Stand—CMA Position Papers |publisher=California Medical Association |pages=43 |quote=Good medical practice indicates that abortion should not be performed after the 20th week of pregnancy}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Fetus#Viability|viability]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.kent.ac.uk/sspssr/research/papers/legalpro.pdf |title=Abortion issues today - a position paper |accessdate=2007-05-24 |last=Lee |first=Ellie |coauthors=Ann Furedi |year=2002 |month=February |format=PDF |work=Legal Issues for Pro-Choice Opinion - Abortion Law in Practice |publisher=University of Kent, Canterbury, CT2 7NY, UK |pages=2 |quote=While most people have no difficulty accepting the legality of abortion at early stages of pregnancy, fewer are so sure about their position as pregnancy progresses – especially when the fetus is perceived to be 'viable'
}}&lt;/ref&gt; or the second [[trimester]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.amwa-doc.org/index.cfm?objectId=0A5BF4D4-D567-0B25-58C7E8584C98D43B |title=Abortion |accessdate=2007-05-24 |year=2000 |work=Positions |publisher=American Medical Women's Association |quote=The 1973 Supreme court decision Roe v. Wade struck a fair balance between the responsibility of the state to protect a woman's right to make personal medical decisions and the responsibility of the state to protect the potentially viable third trimester fetus}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Some want to regulate all abortions, starting from conception.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.johnstonsarchive.net/baptist/rptbgctc.html |title=Evaluation of the BGCT Christian Life Commission's "Abortion and the Christian Life" |accessyear=May 2007 |last=Johnston |first=Wm. Robert |date=2002-12-24 |work=Committee Report |publisher=First Baptist Church, Brownsville, Texas |quote=…the unique value that human life has, as a gift from God, regardless of stage of development or physical health, from the point of conception to the point of physical death}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Privacy===
''[[Time (magazine)|Time]]'' has stated that the issue of bodily [[privacy]] is "the core" of the abortion debate.&lt;ref name="Time"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,903358,00.html?promoid=googlep|title=Abortion and Privacy|accessdate=2007-05-25 |date=1972-03-13|publisher=TIME}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In political terms, privacy can be understood as a condition in which one is not observed or disturbed by government.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.askoxford.com/concise_oed/privacy?view=uk |title=Privacy |accessdate=2007-05-24 |work=Compact Oxford English Dictionary |publisher=AskOxford.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Privacy, in relation to abortion, is defined as the ability of a woman to "decide what happens to her own body".&lt;ref name="Time"/&gt;

While [[governments]] are allowed to invade the privacy of their citizens in some cases, they are expected to protect privacy in all cases lacking a [[Strict scrutiny|compelling state interest]].  Abortions are recognized as being private, but are criticized for involving the loss of human life.  The pro-life position argues that abortion regulation is valid because the state interest in protecting prenatal life is compelling.  The pro-choice position argues either that there is no state interest in regulating abortion, or that the woman's privacy is a ''more'' compelling interest.

[[Image:Roevwade.jpg|thumb|right|200px|[[Albert Wynn]] and [[Gloria Feldt]] at the [[Supreme Court of the United States|U.S. Supreme Court]] to rally in support of ''[[Roe v. Wade]].'']]

===U.S. judicial involvement===
''[[Roe v. Wade]]'' struck down state laws banning abortion in 1973. Over 20 [[:Category:United States abortion case law|cases]] have addressed abortion law in the [[Abortion in the United States|United States]], all of which upheld Roe v. Wade. Since ''Roe'', abortion has been legal throughout the country, but states have placed varying regulations on it, from requiring [[Minors and abortion|parental involvement]] in a minor's abortion to restricting [[late-term abortion]]s.
  
Legal criticisms of the ''Roe'' decision address many points, among them are several suggesting that it is an overreach of judicial powers,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal| author= William Saletan |url= http://www.legalaffairs.org/issues/May-June-2005/feature_saleton_mayjun05.msp |title= Unbecoming Justice Blackmun |work= Legal Affairs |date= May/June 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; or that it was not properly based on the Constitution,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal| author= Ely, John Hart. |url= http://www.timothypcarney.com/wages-wolf.htm |title= The Wages of Crying Wolf |publisher= [[Yale Law Journal]] |date= 1973  &lt;!--accessdate= 4 Oct 09--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; or that it is an example of [[judicial activism]] and that it should be overturned so that abortion law can be decided by legislatures.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.boston.com/yourlife/health/women/articles/2005/07/26/why_i_vetoed_contraception_bill/ |title=Why I Vetoed Contraception Bill |accessdate=2007-05-24 |last=Romney |first=Mitt |authorlink=Mitt Romney |date=2005-07-26 |publisher=The Boston Globe |quote=…avoiding the bitter battles engendered by 'one size fits all' judicial pronouncements. A [[federalist]] approach would allow such disputes to be settled by the citizens and elected representatives of each state, and appropriately defer to democratic governance}}&lt;/ref&gt; Justice [[Potter Stewart]], who joined with the majority, viewed the ''Roe'' opinion as  "legislative" and asked that more consideration be paid to state legislatures.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://members.aol.com/abtrbng2/roememos.txt |title=Testimony of Douglas W. Kmiec |accessdate=2007-05-24 |last=Kmiec |first=Douglas W. |date=1996-04-22 |publisher=Judiciary Committee, U.S. House of Representatives}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Candidates competing for the Democratic nomination for the 2008 Presidential election cited ''[[Gonzales v. Carhart]]'' as judicial activism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.nytimes.com/ref/washington/ABORTIONPOSITIONS.html#democrats |title=The Presidential Candidates on Abortion |accessdate=2007-05-23 |last=Hossain |first=Farhana |coauthors=Ben Werschkul |date=2007 |publisher=New York Times}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In upholding the [[Partial-Birth Abortion Ban Act]], ''Carhart'' is the first judicial opinion upholding a legal barrier to a specific abortion procedure.

{{quotation|"Where, in the performance of its judicial duties, the Court decides a case in such a way as to resolve the sort of intensely divisive controversy reflected in Roe and those rare, comparable cases, its [505 U.S. 833, 867] decision has a dimension that the resolution of the normal case does not carry. It is the dimension present whenever the Court's interpretation of the Constitution calls the contending sides of a national controversy to end their national division by accepting a common mandate rooted in the Constitution [...W]hatever the premises of opposition may be, only the most convincing justification under accepted standards of precedent could suffice to demonstrate that a later decision overruling the first was anything but a surrender to political pressure and an unjustified repudiation of the principle on which the Court staked its authority in the first instance." -[[Majority opinion]] of [[Planned Parenthood v. Casey]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| author= Thomas R. Kearns | url= http://books.google.com/books?id=J_9YVh0QmUQC&amp;pg=PA8&amp;dq=History,+memory,++controversy+to+end+their+national+division&amp;lr=#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false | publisher= University of Michigan Press | title= History, Memory, and the Law}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Find1&gt;{{cite court|litigants=[[Planned Parenthood v. Casey]] |vol=505 |reporter=U.S. |opinion=833 |date=1992 |url=http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/scripts/getcase.pl?navby=CASE&amp;court=US&amp;vol=505&amp;page=833}}&lt;/ref&gt;,&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Quite to the contrary, by foreclosing all democratic outlet for the deep passions this issue arouses, by banishing the issue from the political forum that gives all participants, even the losers, the satisfaction of a fair hearing and an honest fight, by continuing the imposition of a rigid national rule instead of allowing for regional differences, the Court merely prolongs and intensifies the anguish [over abortion]. - Justice [[Antonin Scalia]], "concurring in the judgment in part and dissenting in part"&lt;ref name=Find1/&gt;}}

[[Image:BentoXVI-37-10052007.jpg|thumb|right|250px|"No to abortion" at a 2007 meeting with [[Pope Benedict XVI]] in [[São Paulo]], [[Brazil]]. The crowd have both arms raised in a [[orans|prayer gesture]].]]

==Ethical debate==
{{POV-check|date=January 2009}}
{{Main|Ethical aspects of abortion|Philosophical aspects of the abortion debate|}}
[[Ethics]] refers to "[[moral]] [[philosophy]]", or the study of [[values]] and the analysis of [[right and wrong]]. The ethical debate over abortion usually surrounds the issues of whether a fetus has [[rights]], in particular a [[right to life]], and whether the pregnant woman's rights over her own body justify abortion ''even if'' the fetus has a right to life.  For many, there is a strong correlation between [[Religion and abortion|religion and abortion ethics]].

===Personhood===
{{Main|Beginning of human personhood}}
Pro-life supporters argue that abortion is morally wrong on the basis that a fetus is an innocent [[human being]].&lt;ref&gt;Warren, 1973&lt;/ref&gt; Others reject this position by drawing a distinction between ''human being'' and ''human person'', arguing that while the fetus is ''innocent'' and ''biologically human'', it is not a ''person'' with a ''right to life''.&lt;ref&gt;Warren 1973: 457.  See also Tooley 1972: 40-43; Singer 2000: 126-28 and 155-156; and [[Consciousness#Consciousness as the basis of personal identity|John Locke]].  The term ''person'' may be used to denote a ''psychological'' property (being rational and self-conscious), a ''moral'' property (having a right to life), or both.&lt;/ref&gt;  In support of this distinction, some propose a list of criteria as markers of [[personhood]].  For example, [[Mary Ann Warren]] suggests [[consciousness]] (at least the capacity to feel pain), [[reasoning]], [[self motivation]], the ability to [[Communication|communicate]], and [[self-awareness]].&lt;ref&gt;Warren 1973: 458.&lt;/ref&gt;  According to Warren, a being need not exhibit all of these criteria to qualify as a person with a right to life, but if a being exhibits ''none'' of them (or perhaps only one), then it is certainly not a person.  Warren concludes that as the fetus satisfies only one criterion, consciousness (and this only after it becomes [[fetal pain|susceptible to pain]]),&lt;ref&gt;Warren 1973: 458-459&lt;/ref&gt; the fetus is not a person and abortion is therefore morally permissible.  Other philosophers apply similar criteria, concluding that a fetus lacks a right to life because it lacks self-consciousness,&lt;ref&gt;Tooley 1972: 44.&lt;/ref&gt; rationality,&lt;ref&gt;Singer 2000: 128 and 156-157.&lt;/ref&gt; and autonomy.&lt;ref&gt;McMahan 2002: 260&lt;/ref&gt; These lists diverge over precisely ''which'' features confer a right to life,&lt;ref&gt;It is similarly unclear ''which'' features one must have a natural capacity for, in order to have a right to life (cf Schwarz 1990: 105-109), or ''which'' features constitute a "future like ours".&lt;/ref&gt; but tend to propose various ''developed'' psychological features not found in fetuses.

Critics of this position typically argue that the proposed criteria for personhood would disqualify two classes of ''born'' human beings — reversibly [[comatose]] patients, and human [[infant]]s — from having a right to life, since they, like fetuses, are not self-conscious, do not communicate, and so on.&lt;ref&gt;Marquis 1989: 197; Schwarz 1990: 89&lt;/ref&gt;  Defenders of the proposed criteria may respond that the reversibly comatose ''do'' satisfy the relevant criteria because they "retain all their ''unconscious'' mental states".&lt;ref&gt;Stretton 2004: 267, original emphasis; see also Singer 2000: 137; Boonin 2003: 64-70&lt;/ref&gt;  Warren concedes that infants are not "persons" by her proposed criteria,&lt;ref&gt;Warren 1982&lt;/ref&gt; and on that basis she and others concede that [[infanticide]] could be morally acceptable under some circumstances (for example if the infant is severely disabled&lt;ref&gt;Singer 2000: 186-193&lt;/ref&gt; or in order to save the lives of several other infants&lt;ref&gt;McMahan 2002: 359-360&lt;/ref&gt;).  Critics may see such concessions as an indication that the right to life cannot be adequately defined by reference to developed psychological features.

An alternative approach is to base personhood or the right to life on a being's ''natural'' or ''inherent'' capacities.  On this approach, a being [[Essential property|essentially]] has a right to life if it has a genetic propensity or ''natural capacity'' to develop the relevant psychological features; and, since human beings do have this natural capacity, they essentially have a right to life beginning at [[Conception (biology)|conception]] (or whenever they come into existence).&lt;ref&gt;Lee 1996 and 2004: Schwarz 1990: 91-93.&lt;/ref&gt;  Critics of this position argue that mere genetic potential is not a plausible basis for respect (or for the right to life), and that basing a right to life on natural capacities would lead to the counterintuitive position that [[anencephaly|anencephalic]] infants, irreversibly comatose patients, and brain-dead patients kept alive on a [[medical ventilator]], are all persons with a right to life.&lt;ref&gt;Stretton 2004: 274-281.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Image:Pro-Life Demonstration at Supreme Court.jpg|thumb|right|250px|Members of [[Bound4LIFE]] in [[Washington, D.C.]] symbolically cover their mouths with red tape.]]

Philosophers such as [[Aquinas]] use the concept of [[individuation]]. They argue that abortion is not permissible from the point at which individual human identity is realised. [[Anthony Kenny]] argues that this can be derived from everyday beliefs and language and one can legitimately say "if my mother had had an abortion six months into her pregnancy, she would have killed me" then one can reasonably infer that at six months the "me" in question would have been an existing person with a valid claim to life. Since division of the zygote into twins through the process of [[twins|monozygotic twinning]] can occur until the fourteenth day of pregnancy, Kenny argues that individual identity is obtained at this point and thus abortion is not permissible after two weeks. &lt;ref&gt;A. Kenny, Reason and Religion: Essays in Philosophical Theology (Oxford: Basil Blackwell), 1987&lt;/ref&gt;

===Argument from uncertainty===
Some pro-life supporters argue that if there is uncertainty as to whether the fetus has a right to life, then having an abortion is equivalent to consciously taking the risk of killing another.  According to this argument, if it is not known for certain whether something (such as the fetus) has a right to life, then it is reckless, and morally wrong, to treat that thing as if it ''lacks'' a right to life (for example by killing it).&lt;ref&gt;Schwarz 1990: 58-9; Beckwith 2007: 60-1; "Abortion and the Conscience of the Nation" (1983), by Ronald Reagan, William P. Clark, Brian P. Johnston, Wanda Franz. New Regency Pub, ISBN 0964112531&lt;/ref&gt;  This would place abortion in the same moral category as [[manslaughter]] (if it turns out that the fetus has a right to life) or certain forms of [[criminal negligence]] (if it turns out that the fetus does not have a right to life).&lt;ref&gt;"Three approaches to abortion" (2002), by Peter Kreeft, ISBN 0898709156&lt;/ref&gt;

David Boonin replies that if this kind of argument were correct, then the killing of nonhuman animals and plants would also be morally wrong, because (Boonin contends) it is not known for certain that such beings lack a right to life.&lt;ref&gt;Boonin 2003: 314-15&lt;/ref&gt;  Boonin also argues that arguments from uncertainty fail because the mere fact that one might be mistaken in finding certain arguments persuasive (for example, arguments for the claim that the fetus lacks a right to life) does not mean that one should act contrary to those arguments or assume them to be mistaken.&lt;ref&gt;Boonin 2003: 323&lt;/ref&gt;

===Discrimination===

The book ''Abortion and the Conscience of the Nation'' presents the argument that abortion involves unjust [[discrimination]] against the unborn.  According to this argument, those who deny that fetuses have a right to life do not value ''all'' human life, but instead select arbitrary characteristics (such as particular levels of physical or psychological development) as giving some human beings more value or rights than others.&lt;ref&gt;"Abortion and the Conscience of the Nation" (1983), by Ronald Reagan, William P. Clark, Brian P. Johnston, Wanda Franz. New Regency Pub, ISBN 0964112531&lt;/ref&gt;

In contrast, philosophers who define the right to life by reference to particular levels of physical or psychological development typically maintain that such characteristics are morally relevant,&lt;ref&gt;Singer 2000: 217-18; McMahan 2002: 242-3; Boonin 2003: 126&lt;/ref&gt; and reject the assumption that all human life necessarily has value (or that membership in the species ''[[Homo sapiens]]'' is in itself morally relevant).&lt;ref&gt;Singer 2000: 221-2; McMahan 2002: 214; Boonin 2003: 25&lt;/ref&gt;

===Deprivation===
The argument of deprivation states that abortion is morally wrong because it deprives the fetus of a valuable future.&lt;ref&gt;Marquis 1989.  See also Stone 1987.&lt;/ref&gt;  On this account, killing an ''adult'' human being is wrong because it deprives the victim of a ''future like ours''—a future containing highly valuable or desirable experiences, activities, projects, and enjoyments.&lt;ref&gt;Marquis 1989: 189-190&lt;/ref&gt; If a being has such a future, then (according to the argument) killing that being would seriously harm it and hence would be seriously wrong.&lt;ref&gt;Marquis 1989: 190.  The type of wrongness appealed to here is presumptive or [[prima facie]] wrongness: it may be overridden in exceptional circumstances.&lt;/ref&gt; But since a fetus does have such a future, the "overwhelming majority" of deliberate abortions are placed in the "same moral category" as killing an innocent adult human being.&lt;ref&gt;Marquis 1989: 183.&lt;/ref&gt;  Not ''all'' abortions are unjustified according to this argument: abortion would be justified if the same justification could be applied to killing an adult human.

Criticism of this line of reasoning follows several threads.  Some reject the argument on grounds relating to [[Personal identity (philosophy)|personal identity]], holding that the fetus is ''not the same entity'' as the adult into which it will develop, and thus that the fetus does not have a "future like ours" in the required sense.&lt;ref&gt;McMahan 2002: ch 1.&lt;/ref&gt; Others grant that the fetus has a future like ours, but argue that being deprived of this future is not a significant harm or a significant wrong to the fetus, because there are relatively few ''psychological connections'' (continuations of memory, belief, desire and the like) between the fetus as it is now and the adult into which it will develop.&lt;ref&gt;McMahan 2002: 271; Stretton 2004: 171-179&lt;/ref&gt;  Another criticism is that the argument creates inequalities in the wrongness of killing:&lt;ref&gt;Stretton 2004: 250-260; see also McMahan 2002: 234-235 and 271&lt;/ref&gt; as the futures of some people (for example the young, bright and healthy) appear to be far more valuable or desirable than the futures of other people (for example the old, depressed and sick), the argument appears to entail that some killings are far more ''wrong'' than others, or that some people have a far stronger ''right to life'' than others—a conclusion that is taken to be counterintuitive or unacceptable.  Finally, some argue that as [[gametes]] have a similar potential to the fetus, the argument would entail that [[contraception]] is as wrong as the killing of an adult human being—a conclusion that is similarly taken to be counterintuitive or unacceptable.

[[Image:March for Women's Lives detail.jpg|thumb|right|250px|The 2004 [[March for Women's Lives]] near the [[Washington Monument]].]]

===Bodily rights===
{{Further|[[A Defense of Abortion]]}}
An argument first presented by [[Judith Jarvis Thomson]] states that ''even if'' the fetus has a right to life, abortion is morally permissible because a woman has a right to control her own body.  Thomson's variant of this argument draws an analogy between forcing a woman to continue an unwanted [[pregnancy]] and forcing a person's body to be used as a [[dialysis]] machine for another person suffering from [[kidney failure]].  It is argued that just as it would be permissible to "unplug" and thereby cause the death of the person who is using one's kidneys, so it is permissible to abort the fetus (who similarly, it is said, has no right to use one's body against one's will).

Critics of this argument generally argue that there are morally relevant disanalogies between abortion and the kidney failure scenario.  For example, it is argued that the fetus is the woman's child as opposed to a mere stranger;&lt;ref&gt;Schwarz 1990; McMahan 2002&lt;/ref&gt; that abortion ''kills'' the fetus rather than merely letting it die;&lt;ref&gt;Schwarz 1990; McMahan 2002; Lee 1996&lt;/ref&gt; and that in the case of pregnancy arising from voluntary intercourse, the woman has either tacitly consented to the fetus using her body,&lt;ref&gt;Warren 1973&lt;/ref&gt; or has a duty to allow it to use her body since she herself is responsible for its need to use her body.&lt;ref&gt;McMahan 2002&lt;/ref&gt; Some writers defend the analogy against these [[Objection (argument)|objections]], arguing that the disanalogies are morally irrelevant or do not apply to abortion in the way critics have claimed.&lt;ref&gt;Boonin 2003: ch 4&lt;/ref&gt;

Alternative scenarios have been put forth as more accurate and realistic representations of the moral issues present in abortion. [[John Noonan]] proposes the scenario of a family who was found to be liable for frostbite finger loss suffered by a dinner guest whom they refused to allow to stay overnight, although it was very cold outside and the guest showed signs of being sick. It is argued that just as it would not be permissible to refuse temporary accommodation for the guest to protect them from physical harm, it would not be permissible to refuse temporary accommodation of a foetus.&lt;ref&gt;"The Morality of abortion: legal and historical perspectives" John T. Noonan, Harvard University Press, 1970 ISBN: 0674587251&lt;/ref&gt;

Other critics claim that there is a difference between artificial and extraordinary means of preservation, such as medical treatment, kidney dialysis, and blood transfusions, and normal and natural means of preservation, such as gestation, childbirth, and breastfeeding. They argue that if a baby was born into an environment in which there was no replacement available for her mother's breast milk, and the baby would either breastfeed or starve, the mother would have to allow the baby to breastfeed.  But the mother would never have to give the baby a blood transfusion, no matter what the circumstances were.  The difference between breastfeeding in that scenario and blood transfusions is the difference between using your body as a kidney dialysis machine, and gestation and childbirth.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.equipresources.org/atf/cf/%7B9C4EE03A-F988-4091-84BD-F8E70A3B0215%7D/JAA025.pdf |title=Christian Research Journal, volume 30, number 4 - Suffer the violinist: Why the pro-abortion argument from bodily autonomy fails |accessdate=2009-10-25 |last=Poupard|first=Dr Richard J|date=2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;G Koukl &amp; S Klusendorf, "Making Abortion Unthinkable: The Art of Pro-Life Persuasion" STR Press, California (2001) p. 86.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bernard Nathanson &amp; Richard Ostling "Aborting America". Double Day &amp; Company, Inc.: Garden City, 1979 (ISBN 0-385-14461-X)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video | people = [[Peter Kreeft]], David Boonin | title = "Is Abortion Morally Justifiable in a Free Society?" Public debate at [[Yale University]] | medium = Audio | publisher = [[Intercollegiate Studies Institute]] | location = http://www.isi.org/lectures/lectures.aspx?SBy=search&amp;SSub=title&amp;SFor=Is%20Abortion%20Morally%20Justifiable%20in%20a%20Free%20Society? | year2 = 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;John Arthur 'The Unfinished Constitution: Philosophy and Constitutional Practice', Wadsworth, 1989, p198-200.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://homepage.mac.com/francis.beckwith/Thomson.pdf |title=International Philosophical Quarterly Vol 32 Issue 1 - Personal Bodily Rights, Abortion, and Unplugging the Violinist |accessdate=2009-10-10 |last=Beckwith |first=Francis |date=March 1992}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Religious Beliefs===
	 
{{Main|Religion and abortion}}
	 
Some pro-life Christians support their views with Scripture references such as that of Luke 1:15; Jeremiah 1:4-5; Genesis 25:21-23; Matthew 1:18; and Psalm 139:13-16.  [[Roman Catholicism|Roman Catholics]] in particular recognize that human life begins at conception as well as the right to life, so abortion is considered immoral and a violation of the Fifth Commandment: "You shall not kill" (Exodus 20:13).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.vatican.va/archive/catechism/p3s2c2a5.htm |title= Article 5: The Fifth Commandment |accessdate=3 August 2009 |work=Catechism of the Catholic Church}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Church of England also considers abortion to be morally wrong, though their position is not as firm as that of Roman Catholicism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/religion/religions/christianity/christianethics/abortion_1.shtml |title= Abortion: the Church of England view |accessdate=3 August 2009 |work=Religion &amp; Ethics}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{col-start}}
{{col-break}}
*[[Legal protection of access to abortion|Bubble zone laws]]
*[[Conscience clause (medical)]]
*[[Stem cell controversy|Embryonic stem cell research]]
{{col-break}}
*[[Feticide]]
*[[Legalized abortion and crime effect]]
*[[Post-abortion syndrome]]
{{col-break}}
*[[Pregnancy options counseling]]
*[[Roe effect]]
*[[Sex-selective abortion]]
*[[Societal attitudes towards abortion]]
{{col-end}}

==Notes==
{{reflist|colwidth=20em}}

==References==
*{{cite book |last=Boonin |first=David |title=A Defense of Abortion |series=Cambridge Studies in Philosophy and Public Policy |year=2003 |publisher=University of Colorado |location=Boulder |isbn=0521520355  }}
*{{cite book |last=Lee |first=Patrick |title=Abortion and Unborn Human Life |year=1996 |publisher=Catholic University of America Press |isbn=0813208467 }}
*{{cite journal |last=Lee |first=Patrick |year=2004 |month=June |title=The Pro-Life Argument from Substantial Identity: A Defense |journal=Bioethics |volume=18 |issue=3 |pages=249 |doi=10.1111/j.1467-8519.2004.00393.x | laysummary = http://www.blackwell-synergy.com/doi/abs/10.1111/j.1467-8519.2004.00393.x?cookieSet=1&amp;journalCode=biot | laysource = Blackwell Synergy | laydate = 2007-05-25}}
*{{cite book |last=Mappes  |first=Thomas A. |coauthors=David DeGrazia |title=Biomedical Ethics |year=2001 |publisher=McGraw-Hill |isbn=0072303654 }}
*{{cite journal |last=Marquis |first=Don |year=1989 |month=April |title=Why Abortion is Immoral |journal=The Journal of Philosophy |volume=86 |issue=4 |pages=183–202 |doi=10.2307/2026961 | laysummary = http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0022-362X(198904)86%3A4%3C183%3AWAII%3E2.0.CO%3B2-T | laysource = JSTOR | laydate = 2007-05-25}}
*{{cite book |last=McMahan |first=Jeff |authorlink=Jeff McMahan (philosopher) |title=The Ethics of Killing: Problems at the Margins of Life | series=Oxford Ethics Series |year=2002 |publisher=Oxford University Press |location=New York |isbn=0195169824 }}
*{{cite conference |first=Mary Ann |last=Warren |authorlink=Mary Ann Warren |year=1973 |title=On the Moral and Legal Status of Abortion | booktitle = Biomedical Ethics |editor=Thomas A. Mappes |others=David DeGrazia |publisher=McGraw-Hill |pages=456-461}}
*{{cite conference |first=Mary Ann |last=Warren |authorlink=Mary Ann Warren |year=1982 |title=Postscript on Infanticide | booktitle = Biomedical Ethics |editor=Thomas A. Mappes |others=David DeGrazia |publisher=McGraw-Hill |pages=461-463}}
*{{cite book |last=Schwarz |first=Stephen D. |title=The Moral Question of Abortion |year=1990 |publisher=Loyola University Press |location=Chicago |isbn=0829406239}}
*{{cite book |last=Singer |first=Peter |authorlink=Peter Singer |title=Writings on an Ethical Life |year=2000 |publisher=Ecco (HarperCollins) |isbn=0060198389 }}
*{{cite journal |last=Stone |first=Jim |year=1987 |month=December |title=Why Potentiality Matters |journal=Canadian Journal of Philosophy |volume=17 |issue=4 |pages=815–830}}
*{{cite journal |last=Stretton |first=Dean |year=2004 |month=June |title=Essential Properties and the Right to Life: A Response to Lee |journal=Bioethics |volume=18 |issue=3 |pages=264–282 |doi=10.1111/j.1467-8519.2004.00394.x | laysummary = http://www.blackwell-synergy.com/doi/abs/10.1111/j.1467-8519.2004.00394.x?journalCode=biot | laysource = Blackwell Synergy | laydate = 2007-05-25}}
*{{cite journal |last=Tooley |first=Michael |year=1972 |title=Abortion and Infanticide |journal=Philosophy and Public Affairs |volume=2 |issue=1 |pages=37–65 | laysummary = http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0048-3915(197223)2%3A1%3C37%3AAAI%3E2.0.CO%3B2-K | laysource = JSTOR | laydate = 2007-05-25}}

==External links==
&lt;!--========================({{No More Links}})============================
    | PLEASE BE CAUTIOUS IN ADDING MORE LINKS TO THIS ARTICLE. WIKIPEDIA  |
    | IS NOT A COLLECTION OF LINKS NOR SHOULD IT BE USED FOR ADVERTISING. |
    |                                                                     |
    |           Excessive or inappropriate links WILL BE DELETED.         |
    | See [[Wikipedia:External links]] &amp; [[Wikipedia:Spam]] for details.  |
    |                                                                     |
    | If there are already plentiful links, please propose additions or   |
    | replacements on this article's discussion page, or submit your link |
    | to the relevant category at the Open Directory Project (dmoz.org)   |
    | and link back to that category using the {{dmoz}} template.         |
    =======================({{No More Links}})=============================--&gt;
*[http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/scripts/getcase.pl?court=US&amp;vol=410&amp;invol=113 Findlaw: full text of Roe V Wade decision, plus discussion]
*[http://www.rsrevision.com/Alevel/ethics/abortion/index.htm Abortion and Ethics] Case studies, Christian and non-Christian responses and resources for students
*[http://www.agi-usa.org/pubs/journals/2411798.html Reasons why women have induced abortions, evidence from 27 countries]
*[http://www.thehist.com/index.php?option=com_docman&amp;task=cat_view&amp;gid=65&amp;limit=5&amp;limitstart=0&amp;order=date&amp;dir=ASC&amp;Itemid=713 Recordings] of [[College Historical Society]] debate on abortion featuring [[William Binchy|Professor William Binchy]], [[Frances Kissling]] and [[Rebecca Gomperts]]
*[http://debategraph.org/Flash/fv.aspx?r=585&amp;d=2&amp;i=1 Interactive map of the Abortion debate]
*[http://www.bbc.co.uk/ethics/abortion/religion/religion.shtml Religious perspectives on abortion]
{{Abortion}}
[[Category:Abortion debate]]
[[Category:Controversies]]

[[it:Dibattito sull'aborto]]
[[pt:Debate sobre o aborto]]
[[ru:Полемика вокруг проблемы аборта]]
[[sv:Abortfrågan]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>