<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20020817121107|303011" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="7257" pageid="7257" ns="0" title="Caste"><revisions><rev timestamp="2002-09-21T13:46:10Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Caste''' is derived from the Portuguese word for "chaste," and originally used to refer to a social division in [[Hindu]] society.  [[cultural anthropology | Anthropologists]] use the term more generally to refer to a social group that is endogamous and occupationally specialized; such groups are common in highly stratified societies with a very low degree of social mobility.  Broadly understood, Apartheid [[South Africa]] and parts of the United States before the Civil Rights movement, were caste-based societies.

The caste system in [[India]] is based on four "varnas" -- Brahmans, Kshatriyas, Vaishyas, and Shudras -- each of which corresponds to an occupational category -- priests, warriors, merchants and craftsmen, and menial workers.  Each varna is further subdivied into subcastes, or "jatis," which are more specific occupational categories.  Each varna has its appropriate rules of conduct, or "dharma," including [[taboo]]s regarding marriage, eating, and physical proximity.  (see Louis Dumont's ''Homo Hierarchicus'')

Much of what we know of the caste system in India was documented and codified during the period of [[British Empire|British]] occupation and rule (e.g. Herbert Risley's ''The Tribes and Castes of [[Bengal]]'', published in 1892).  Some scholars suggest that the resulting depiction of the caste system was as much a product of European [[race|racialist]] theories, and the interests of colonial rule, rather than Indian cultural realities.  They further suggest that prior to the colonial era, castes were much more open and flexible.

In [[social insect]]s such as [[ant]]s, [[bee]]s and [[termite]]s, a caste is a specific sub-type of an insect species which is specialized in a certain task. A common example is the "queen" and the "worker", in which queens are specialized in reproduction and the workers are specialized in feeding and protecting the queens.</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>