<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20121118200029|523720591" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="7257" pageid="7257" ns="0" title="Caste"><revisions><rev timestamp="2012-11-18T20:00:36Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Other uses}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2012}}
[[File:India1909PrevailingRaces.JPG|thumb|right|An example of a now discredited "ethnographic" map of India from the ''[[Imperial Gazetteer of India]]'', 1909, purporting to show the different "races" (in coloured regions), and castes (in labels).  The map was based on the 1901 Census of India in which questions about caste and sub-caste were asked of the respondents, the most explicit in the census's history.  A key figure behind the census was [[Herbert Hope Risley]], best known for the now discounted attribution of all differences in caste to varying proportions of seven racial types.  Critics, then and since, have questioned the accuracy of the data so garnered.]]
'''Caste''' is a form of [[social stratification]] characterized by [[endogamy]], hereditary transmission of a style of life which often includes an occupation, ritual status in a hierarchy, and customary social interaction and exclusion based on cultural notions of purity and pollution.&lt;ref name=OxfordDictionarySociology&gt;{{citation|last1=Scott|first1=John|last2=Marshall|first2=Gordon|title=A Dictionary of Sociology|chapter=caste|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=id8iAQAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA66|location=Oxford, UK; New York, NY|accessdate=10 August 2012|year=2005|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=978-0-19-860987-2|page=66}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=winthrop-1991&gt;{{citation|last=Winthrop|first=Robert H.|chapter=Caste|title=Dictionary of Concepts in Cultural Anthropology|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=3xoB_3C5N5QC&amp;pg=PA27|accessdate=10 August 2012|year=1991|publisher=Greenwood Press|location=New York, NY|isbn=978-0-313-24280-9|pages=27–30}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Its paradigmatic  ethnographic example is the division of India's [[Hinduism|Hindu]] society into rigid social groups, with roots in India's ancient history and persisting until today.  However, the economic significance of the [[caste system in India]] has been declining as a result of urbanization and affirmative action programs. A subject of much scholarship by sociologists and anthropologists, the Hindu caste system is sometimes used as an analogical basis for the study of caste-like social divisions existing outside Hinduism and India.

==Etymology==
The English word "caste" derives from the Spanish and Portuguese ''casta'', which the [[Oxford English Dictionary]] quotes [[John Minsheu]]'s Spanish dictionary (1599) to mean, "race, lineage, or breed."&lt;ref name=oed-caste&gt;{{cite web|publisher = Oxford English Dictionary|year = 1989|title=Caste, n|url=http://www.oed.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;  When the Spanish colonized the New World, they used the word to mean a "clan or lineage."   However, it was the Portuguese who employed ''casta'' in the primary modern sense when they applied it to the many in-marrying hereditary Hindu social groups  they encountered upon their arrival in India in 1498.&lt;ref name=oed-caste/&gt;&lt;ref name=pitt-rivers&gt;{{citation|last=Pitt-Rivers|first=Julian|editor=T O Beidelman|title=The translation of culture essays to E.E. Evans-Pritchard|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=f509AAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=231|year=1971|publisher=Tavistock|location=London, UK|pages=231–256|chapter=On the word 'caste'|id=GGKEY:EC3ZBGF5QC9}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The use of the spelling "caste," with this latter meaning, is first attested to in English in 1613.&lt;ref name=oed-caste/&gt;

==Caste system of India==
{{expand section|date=October 2012}}
{{Main|Caste system in India|History of the Indian caste system}}
[[File:Kurmi sowing.jpg|thumb|right|An early 20th century "ethnographic" photograph of men and women from the [[Kurmi]] caste&amp;mdash;famed as cultivators and market gardeners&lt;ref name="Bayly1988-p478"&gt;{{cite book|last=Bayly|first=C. A.|authorlink=Christopher Bayly|title=Rulers, Townsmen and Bazaars: North Indian Society in the Age of British Expansion, 1770-1870|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=xfo3AAAAIAAJ|accessdate=25 August 2011|year=1988|publisher=CUP Archive|isbn=978-0-521-31054-3|page=478}}&lt;/ref&gt;&amp;mdash;sowing their field.&lt;ref&gt;From {{cite book|last=Russell|first=Robert Vane|title=The Tribes and Castes of the Central Provinces of India: volume IV. Descriptive articles on the principal castes and tribes of the Central Provinces|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=xGXhAAAAMAAJ|year=1916|publisher=Macmillan and Co.|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
Historically, the caste system in India consisted of four well known categories (the [[Varna (Hinduism)|Varnas]]):&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Closed Social Stratification in India|author=F.G. Bailey|date=1 May 1963|volume=4|pages=107–124|doi=10.1017/S0003975600000710|journal=European Journal of Sociology}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* [[Brahmin]] (priests)
* [[Kshatriyas]] (warriors)
* [[Vaishyas]] (traders)
* [[Shudras]] (workmen)

Some people were left out from these four caste classifications, and were called panchama (literally, the fifth). Regarded as outcastes or [[Dalit|untouchables]], these were shunned and ostracized. The ''varnas'' themselves have been further subdivided into thousands of ''jatis''.&lt;ref name=dirks&gt;{{cite book|url=http://press.princeton.edu/titles/7191.html|author=Nicholas B. Dirks|title=Castes of Mind: Colonialism and the Making of New India|year=2001|isbn=978-0-691-08895-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 
Ancient Indian text on laws, such as [[Manusmṛti]] suggest a caste system was part of Indian society. These laws in ancient India discriminated between castes. For example, the laws of Manusmṛti declare sexual relationships between men and women of different castes as illegal.&lt;ref&gt;See William Jones translation of Manusmṛti, available online as [http://books.google.com/books?id=4caNTgBa6oEC&amp;dq=william+jones+manu&amp;printsec=frontcover#PPP1,M1 ''The Institutes of Hindu Law: Or, The Ordinances of Manu''], Calcutta: Sewell &amp; Debrett, 1796.&lt;/ref&gt; 

Upon independence from the British rule, the Indian Constitution listed 1,108 castes across the country as Scheduled Castes in 1950, for [[affirmative action]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://lawmin.nic.in/ld/subord/rule3a.htm The Constitution (Scheduled Castes) Order 1950]&lt;/ref&gt; The Scheduled Castes are sometimes called as [[Dalit]] in contemporary literature.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Scaling Caste Walls With Capitalism’s Ladders in India|publisher=The New York Times|author=Lydia Polgreen|date=21 December 2011|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/12/22/world/asia/indias-boom-creates-openings-for-untouchables.html?pagewanted=all}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2001, the proportion of [[Dalit]] population was 16.2 percent of India's total population.&lt;ref name=censtat01&gt;{{cite web|title=Scheduled castes and scheduled tribes population: Census 2001|year=2004|publisher=Government of India|url=http://censusindia.gov.in/Census_Data_2001/India_at_glance/scst.aspx}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Caste in rest of South Asia==

===Nepal===
{{Main|Nepalese caste system|Ethnicity and caste in Nepal}}
The [[Nepal]]ese caste system resembles that of the Indian [[Jāti]] system with numerous Jāti divisions with a Varna system superimposed for a rough equivalence. But since the culture and the society is different some of the things are different. Inscriptions attest the beginnings of a caste system during the Lichchhavi period.  Jayasthiti Malla (1382–95) categorized Newars into 64 castes (Gellner 2001). A similar exercise was made during the reign of Mahindra Malla (1506–75). The Hindu social code was later set up in Gorkha by Ram Shah (1603–36).

===Sri Lanka===
{{Main|Caste system in Sri Lanka}}
The Caste system in Sri Lanka is a division of society into strata,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Caste as a social category and identity in colonial Lanka|author=John Rogers| doi=10.1177/001946460404100104| journal=Indian Economic Social History Review| date= February 2004|volume=41|number=1|pages=51–77}}&lt;/ref&gt; influenced by the classic Aryan Varnas of North India and the Dravida Jāti system found in South India. Ancient Sri Lankan texts such as the Pujavaliya, Sadharmaratnavaliya and Yogaratnakaraya and inscriptional evidence show that the above hierarchy prevailed throughout the feudal period. The repetition of the same caste hierarchy even as recently as the 18th century, in the British / Kandyan period Kadayimpoth - Boundary books as well, indicates the continuation of the tradition right up to the end of Sri Lanka's monarchy.

===Pakistan===
{{Main|Caste system among South Asian Muslims}}

Religious, historical and socio-cultural factors have helped define the bounds of endogamy for Muslims in some parts of [[Pakistan]]. There is a preference for endogamous marriages based on the clan-oriented nature of the society, which values and actively seeks similarities in social group identity based on several factors, including religious, sectarian, ethnic, and tribal/clan affiliation. Religious affiliation is itself multi-layered and includes religious considerations other than being Muslim, such as sectarian identity (e.g. Shia or Sunni, etc.) and religious orientation within the sect (Isnashari, Ismaili, Ahmedi, etc.). Both ethnic affiliation (e.g. Sindhi, Baloch, Punjabi, etc.) and membership of specific biraderis or zaat/quoms are additional integral components of social identity.&lt;ref name="barth"&gt;{{cite book | last = Barth | first = Fredrik | editor = E. R. Leach | title = The System Of Social Stratification In Swat, North Pakistan (Aspects of Caste in South India, Ceylon, and North-West Pakistan) | url= http://www.questia.com/PM.qst?a=o&amp;d=2995517 | publisher = Cambridge University Press | page = 113 | year =  1962 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Within the bounds of endogamy defined by the above parameters, close consanguineous unions are preferred due to a congruence of key features of group- and individual-level background factors as well as affinities. McKim Marriott claims a social stratification that is hierarchical, closed, endogamous and hereditary is widely prevalent, particularly in western parts of Pakistan. [[Frederik Barth]] in his review of this system of social stratification in Pakistan suggested that these are castes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Ecologic Relationships of Ethnic Groups in Swat, North Pakistan|author=Fredrick Barth|journal=American Anthropologist|doi=10.1525/aa.1956.58.6.02a00080|volume=58|issue=6|pages=1079–1089|date=December 1956}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The New Wind: Changing Identities in South Asia (Editor: Kenneth David)|author=Zeyauddin Ahmed|pages=337–354|isbn=90-279-7959-6|publisher=Aldine Publishing Company|year=1977}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Caste ranking and community structure in five regions of India and Pakistan|author=McKim Marriott|year=1960|url=http://www.worldcat.org/title/caste-ranking-and-community-structure-in-five-regions-of-india-and-pakistan/oclc/186146571}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Caste-like stratification outside South Asia==

===South-east Asia===
[[File:COLLECTIE TROPENMUSEUM Een soedra een man uit de laagste kaste van Bali. TMnr 60002169.jpg|thumb|upright|A Sudra caste man from [[Bali]]. Photo from 1870, courtesy of Tropenmuseum, Netherlands]]

====Myanmar====
[[Karen people|Karen]] are people from the [[Burma]]-[[Thailand]] border region. They were claimed by Christian missionaries and British colonialists as people who were treated by the ethnic majority as ''low-caste people'' or ''dirty-feeders''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Hobson-Jobson|author=Yule and Burnell|year=1903|page=163|url=http://dsal.uchicago.edu/cgi-bin/philologic/getobject.pl?c.0:1:413.hobson}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Bali====
{{Main|Balinese caste system}}
[[Bali]]nese caste structure has been described in early 20th century European literature to be based on three categories &amp;ndash; triwangsa (thrice born) or the nobility, dwijati (twice born) in contrast to ekajati (once born) the low folks. Four statuses were identified in these sociological studies, spelled a bit differently than the caste categories for India:&lt;ref name=boon&gt;{{cite book|title=The Anthropological Romance of Bali 1597-1972: Dynamic Perspectives in Marriage and Caste, Politics and Religion|author=James Boon|year=1977|isbn=0-521-21398-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Brahmanas - priest
*Satrias - knighthood
*Wesias - commerce
*Sudras - servitude

The Brahmana caste was further subdivided by these Dutch ethnographers into two: Siwa and Buda. The Siwa caste was subdivided into five &amp;ndash; Kemenuh, Keniten, Mas, Manuba and Petapan. This classification was to accommodate the observed marriage between higher caste Brahmana men with lower caste women. The other castes were similarly further sub-classified by these 19th-century and early-20th-century ethnographers based on numerous criteria ranging from profession, endogamy or exogamy or polygamy, and a host of other factors in a manner similar to [[casta]]s in Spanish colonies such as Mexico, and caste system studies in British colonies such as India.&lt;ref name=boon/&gt;

===East Asia===

====Japan====
{{Main|Feudal Japan hierarchy}}
[[File:Samurai and servant.jpg|thumb|170px|Japanese samurai of importance and servant.]]
In Japan's history, social strata based on inherited position rather than personal merits, was rigid and highly formalized. At the top were the Emperor and Court nobles ([[kuge]]), together with the Shogun and daimyo. Below them the population was divided into four classes in a system known as ''mibunsei'' (身分制). These were: [[samurai]], peasants, craftsmen and merchants. Only the samurai class was allowed to bear arms. A samurai had a right to kill any peasants and other craftsmen and merchants whom he felt were disrespectful. Craftsmen produced products, being the third, and the last merchants were thought to be as the meanest class because they did not produce any products. The castes were further sub-divided; for example, the peasant caste were labelled as ''furiuri'', ''tanagari'', ''mizunomi-byakusho'' amongst others. The castes and sub-classes, as in Europe, were from the same race, religion and culture.

Howell, in his review of [[Japan]]ese society notes that if a Western power had colonized Japan in the 19th century, they would have discovered and imposed a rigid four-caste hierarchy in Japan.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Geographies of identity in nineteenth-century Japan|author=David L. Howell|publisher=University of California Press|isbn=0-520-24085-5|year=2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;

DeVos and Wagatsuma observe that a systematic and extensive caste system was part of the Japanese society. They also discuss how alleged caste impurity and alleged racial inferiority, concepts often quickly assumed to be slightly different, are superficial terms, two faces of identical inner psychological processes, which expressed themselves in Japan and other countries of the world.&lt;ref name=gdvhw&gt;{{cite book|title=Japan's invisible race: caste in culture and personality|author=George DeVos and Hiroshi Wagatsuma|publisher=University of California Press|year=1966|isbn=978-0-520-00306-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Endogamy was common because marriage across caste lines was socially unacceptable.&lt;ref name=gdvhw/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Japanese Fashion: A Cultural History|author=Toby Slade|publisher=Berg|isbn=978-1-84788-252-3|year=2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Japan]] had its own untouchable caste, shunned and ostracized, historically referred to by the insulting term ''Eta'', now called ''Burakumin''. While modern law has officially abolished the class hierarchy, there are reports of discrimination against the [[Buraku]] or [[Burakumin]] underclasses.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hrdc.net/sahrdc/hrfeatures/HRF39.htm Class, Ethnicity and Nationality: Japan Finds Plenty of Space for Discrimination&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; The Burakumin are regarded as "ostracised."&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite journal
| author = William H. Newell
| year = 1961
| month = December
| title = The Comparative Study of Caste in India and Japan
| journal = Asian Survey
| volume = 1
| issue = 10
| pages = 3–10
| doi = 10.1525/as.1961.1.10.01p15082
| jstor=3023467
}}
&lt;/ref&gt; The burakumin are one of the main [[demographics of Japan|minority groups in Japan]], along with the [[Ainu people|Ainu]] of [[Hokkaidō]] and those of [[Zainichi Korean|residents of Korean]] and [[Chinese in Japan|Chinese]] descent.

===Africa===
{{Main|Caste system in Africa}}

Various sociologists have reported caste systems in Africa.&lt;ref name=Obinna1&gt;{{cite journal|title=Contesting identity: the Osu caste system among Igbo of Nigeria|author=Elijah Obinna|pages=111–121|journal=African Identities|volume=10|issue=1|year=2012|doi=10.1080/14725843.2011.614412}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Caste as a Form of Acculturation|author=James B. Watson|journal=Southwestern Journal of Anthropology|volume=19|number= 4|date= Winter, 1963|pages=356–379}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=tamari1/&gt; The specifics of the caste systems have varied in ethnically and culturally diverse Africa, however the following features are common - it has been a closed system of social stratification, the social status is inherited, the castes are hierarchical, certain castes are shunned while others are merely endogamous and exclusionary.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Caste discrimination in Africa|author=Leo Igwe|publisher=International Humanist and Ethical Union|date=21 August 2009|url=http://www.iheu.org/caste-discrimination-africa}}&lt;/ref&gt; In some cases, concepts of purity and impurity by birth have been prevalent in Africa. In other cases, such as the ''Nupe'' of Nigeria, the ''Beni Amer'' of East Africa, and the ''Tira'' of Sudan, the exclusionary principle has been driven by evolving social factors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Caste and government in primitive society|author=SF Nadel|journal=Journal of Anthropological Society|volume=8|pages=9–22|year=1954}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====West Africa====
[[File:GriotFête.jpg|thumb|upright|A [[Griot]], who have been described as an endogamous caste of West Africa who specialize in oral story telling and culture preservation. They have been also referred to as the bard caste.]] 
[[File:NSRW Africa Midgan.png|thumb|upright|A [[Madhiban]], also known as Midgan or Medigan or Boon or Gaboye, specialize in leather occupation. They have been listed as one of three occupational castes discriminated in East Africa. Austrian Red Cross reports that they, along with ''Tumal'' and ''Yibir'' people are locally known collectively as ''sab'', meaning low caste people.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Ethiopia: Treatment of Madhiban/Midgan/Medigan minority clan|publisher=ACCORD|date=20 May 2009|url=http://www.unhcr.org/refworld/country,,ACCORD,,ETH,,4a16a50b2,0.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
Among the Igbo of [[Nigeria]] - especially [[Enugu State|Enugu]], [[Anambra State|Anambra]], [[Imo State|Imo]], [[Abia State|Abia]], [[Ebonyi State|Ebonyi]], [[Edo State|Edo]] and [[Delta state|Delta]] states of the country - Obinna finds Osu caste system has been and continues to be a major social issue. The Osu caste is determined by one's birth into a particular family irrespective of the religion practised by the individual. Once born into Osu caste, this Nigerian person is an outcast, shunned and ostracized, with limited opportunities or acceptance, regardless of his or her ability or merit. Obinna discusses how this caste system-related identity and power is deployed within government, Church and indigenous communities.&lt;ref name=Obinna1/&gt;

The ''osu'' class systems of eastern [[Nigeria]] and southern [[Cameroon]] are derived from indigenous religious beliefs and discriminate against the "Osus" people as "owned by deities" and outcasts.
The Songhai economy was based on a caste system. The most common were metalworkers, fishermen, and carpenters. Lower caste participants consisted of mostly non-farm working immigrants, who at times were provided special privileges and held high positions in society. At the top were noblemen and direct descendants of the original Songhai people, followed by freemen and traders.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.africankingdoms.com African Kingdoms Songhai Class System&lt;/ref&gt;

In a review of social stratification systems in Africa, Richter reports that the term caste has been used by French and American scholars to many groups of West African artisans. These groups have been described as inferior, deprived of all political power, have a specific occupation, are hereditary and sometimes despised by others. Richter illustrates caste system in [[Cote d'lvoire]], with six sub-caste categories. Unlike other parts of the world, mobility is sometimes possible within sub-castes, but not across caste lines. Farmers and artisans have been, claims Richter, distinct castes. Certain sub-castes are shunned more than others. For example, exogamy is rare for women born into families of woodcarvers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Further considerations of caste in West Africa: The Senufo|author=Dolores Richter|journal=Africa|date= January 1980|volume=50|pages=37–54|doi=10.2307/1158641}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Similarly, the [[Mandé peoples|Mandé]] societies in [[Gambia]], [[Ghana]], [[Guinea]], [[Ivory Coast]], [[Liberia]], [[Senegal]] and [[Sierra Leone]] have social stratification systems that divide society by ethnic ties. The Mande class system regards the ''jonow'' slaves as inferior. Similarly, the [[Wolof people|Wolof]] in Senegal is divided into three main groups, the ''geer'' (freeborn/nobles), ''jaam'' (slaves and slave descendants) and the underclass ''neeno''. In various parts of West Africa, [[Fula people|Fulani]] societies also have class divisions. Other castes include ''Griots'', ''Forgerons'', and ''Cordonniers''.

Tamari has described endogamous castes of over fifteen West African peoples, including the Tukulor, Songhay, Dogon, Senufo, Minianka, Moors, Manding, Soninke, Wolof, Serer, Fulani, and Tuareg. Castes appeared among the ''Malinke'' people no later than 14th century, and was present among the ''Wolof'' and ''Soninke'', as well as some ''Songhay'' and ''Fulani'' populations, no later than 16th century. Tamari claims that wars, such as the ''Sosso-Malinke'' war described in the ''Sunjata'' epic, led to the formation of blacksmith and bard castes among the people that ultimately became the Mali empire. As West Africa evolved over time, sub-castes emerged that acquired secondary specializations or changed occupations. Endogamy was prevalent within a caste or among a limited number of castes, yet castes did not form demographic isolates according to Tamari. Social status according to caste was inherited by off-springs automatically; but this inheritance was paternal. That is, children of higher caste men and lower caste or slave concubines would have the caste status of the father.&lt;ref name=tamari1&gt;{{cite journal|journal=The Journal of African History|year=1991|volume=32|pages=221–250|doi=10.1017/S0021853700025718|title=The Development of Caste Systems in West Africa|author=Tal Tamari}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Central Africa====
Albert in 1960 claimed that the societies in [[Central Africa]] were caste-like social stratification systems.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Socio-Political Organization and Receptivity to Change: Some Differences between Ruanda and Urundi|author=Ethel M. Albert|journal=Southwestern Journal of Anthropology|volume=16|number= 1|date= Spring, 1960|pages=46–74}}&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, in 1961, Maquet notes that the society in [[Rwanda]] and [[Burundi]] can be best described as castes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The Premise of Inequality in Ruanda: A Study of Political Relations in a Central African Kingdom|author= Jacques J. Maquet|year=1962|pages=135–171|publisher=Oxford University Press, London|isbn=978-0-19-823168-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Tutsi]], noted Maquet, considered themselves as superior, with the more numerous [[Hutu]] and the least numerous [[Twa]] regarded, by birth, as respectively, second and third in the hierarchy of Rwandese society. These groups were largely endogamous, exclusionary and with limited mobility.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Power in Ruanda|author=Helen Codere|journal=Anthropologica|volume=4|number=1|year=1962|pages=45–85|jstor=25604523}}&lt;/ref&gt; Maquet's theories have been controversial.

====East Africa====
In a review published in 1977, Todd reports that numerous scholars report a system of social stratification in different parts of Africa that resembles some or all aspects of caste system. Examples of such caste systems, he claims, are to be found in Rwanda and Ethiopia in communities such as the ''Gurage'' and ''Konso''. He then presents the ''Dime'' of South-West Ethiopia, amongst whom there operates a system which Todd claims can be unequivocally labelled as caste system. The ''Dime'' have seven castes whose size varies considerably. Each broad caste level is a hierarchical order that is based on notions of purity, non-purity and impurity. It uses the concepts of defilement to limit contacts between caste categories and to preserve the purity of the upper castes. These caste categories have been exclusionary, endogamous and the social identity inherited.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=LA CASTE EN AFRIQUE? (Caste in Africa?)|author=D. M. Todd|journal=Africa|date=October 1977|volume=47 |pages= 398–412|url=http://journals.cambridge.org/action/displayAbstract?fromPage=online&amp;aid=7903506}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Borana Oromo]] of southern [[Ethiopia]] in the [[Horn of Africa]] also have a class system, where the Watta, an acculturated [[Bantu peoples|Bantu]] group, represent the poorest class.

The traditionally [[nomad]]ic [[Somali people]] are divided into clans, wherein the [[Rahanweyn]] agro-pastoral clans and the occupational clans such as the [[Madhiban]] are sometimes treated as outcasts.&lt;ref&gt;I. M. Lewis, ''A pastoral democracy: a study of pastoralism and politics among the Northern Somali of the Horn of Africa'', (LIT Verlag Berlin-Hamburg-Münster: 1999), pp.13-14&lt;/ref&gt;

===Europe===

====France====
For centuries, through the modern times, the majority regarded [[Cagot]]s of western France and northern Spain as an inferior caste, the untouchables. While they had the same skin color and religion as the majority, in the Churches, they had to use segregated doors, drink from segregated fonts, receive communion on the end of long wooden spoons. It was a closed social system. The socially isolated Cagots were endogamous, and chances of social mobility non-existent.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=The last untouchable in Europe|author=Sean Thomas|date=28 July 2008|publisher=The Independent, United Kingdom|url=http://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/europe/the-last-untouchable-in-europe-878705.html|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Hansson1996"&gt;{{cite book|author=Anders Hansson|title=Chinese Outcasts: Discrimination and Emancipation in Late Imperial China|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=4Ibp1RTW0AoC&amp;pg=PA15|year=1996|publisher=BRILL|isbn=978-90-04-10596-6|pages=15–16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
*[[Caste system in India]]
*[[Rajput]]
*[[Maratha]]
*[[Rajputana]]
*[[Maratha Empire]]
*[[Caste system in Africa]]
*[[Burakumin]]
*[[Al-Akhdam]]

== Notes ==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==Secondary sources==

==Scholarly tertiary sources==
*{{citation|last=Das|first=Veena|authorlink=Veena Das|editor=Neil J. Smelser|others=Paul B. Baltes|title=International encyclopedia of the social and behavioral sciences|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=5pYYAAAAIAAJ|accessdate=25 September 2012|year=2001|publisher=Pergamon; Elsevier|location=Oxford, UK|isbn=978-0-08-043076-8|pages=1529–1532|chapter=Caste}}
*{{citation|editor=Doniger, Wendy|title=Merriam-Webster's Encyclopedia of World Religions|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=ZP_f9icf2roC&amp;pg=PA186|accessdate=24 September 2012|year=1999|publisher=Merriam-Webster|location=Springfield, MA|isbn=978-0-87779-044-0|page=186|chapter=Caste}}
*{{citation|last=Gupta|first=Dipankar|chapter=Caste|editor-last=Schaefer|editor-first=Richard T.|title=Encyclopedia of Race, Ethnicity, and Society|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=YMUola6pDnkC&amp;pg=PA246|location=Thousand Oaks|accessdate=5 August 2012|year=2008|publisher=SAGE|isbn=978-1-4129-2694-2|pages=246–250}}
*{{citation|last=Kannabiran|first=Kalpana|editor1-last=Kramarae|editor1-first=Cheris|editor2-last=Spender|editor2-first=Dale|chapter=Caste|title=Routledge international encyclopedia of women: global women's issues and knowledge|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=TfrzBcycB-4C&amp;pg=PA142|accessdate=5 August 2012|year=2000|publisher=Routledge|location=New York, NY|isbn=978-0-415-92088-9|pages=142–144}}
*{{citation|last=Lindholm|first=Charles|editor=Thomas Barfield|title=The Dictionary of Anthropology|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=V5dkKYyHclwC&amp;pg=PA50|year=2002|publisher=Oxford, UK: Blackwell; New York, NY: Wiley|isbn=978-1-57718-057-9|pages=50–51|chapter=caste, caste societies}}
*{{citation|last1=Madan|first1=T. N.|authorlink1=T. N. Madan|last2=Editors|fist2= |title=caste|publisher= Encyclopæida Britannica Online|url=http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/98395/caste|year=2012}}
*{{citation|last=Morris|first=Mike|title=Concise Dictionary of Social and Cultural Anthropology|chapter=caste|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=5lTQRZru1SQC&amp;pg=PA33|accessdate=10 August 2012|date=27 March 2012|publisher=John Wiley &amp; Sons|isbn=978-1-4443-3209-4|page=33}}
*{{citation|last=Ramu|first=G. N.|editor=William A. Darity|title=International Encyclopedia of the Social Sciences|url=http://www.encyclopedia.com/topic/caste.aspx#2|accessdate=24 September 2012|series=(Macmillan social science library)|year=2008|publisher=Macmillan Reference USA|location=Detroit, MI|isbn=978-0-02-865967-1|chapter=Caste}}
*{{citation|last=Roberts|first=Nathaniel P.|editor=William A. Darity|title=International Encyclopedia of the Social Sciences|url=http://www.encyclopedia.com/doc/1G2-3045300290.html|accessdate=24 September 2012|series=(Macmillan social science library)|year=2008|publisher=Macmillan Reference USA|location=Detroit, MI|isbn=978-0-02-865967-1|chapter=Anthropology of Caste}}
*{{citation|last1=Scott|first1=John|last2=Marshall|first2=Gordon|title=A Dictionary of Sociology|chapter=caste|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=id8iAQAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA66|accessdate=10 August 2012|year=2005|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=978-0-19-860987-2|page=66}}
*{{citation|last=Sonnad|first=Subhash R. |editor1-last=Christensen|editor1-first=Karen|editor2-last=Levinson|editor2-first=David|title=Encyclopedia of Community: From the Village to the Virtual World|chapter=Caste|pages=115&amp;ndash;121|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=t1geOjQ6R0MC&amp;pg=PA115|accessdate=5 August 2012|year=2003|publisher=SAGE|location=Thousand Oaks, CA|isbn=978-0-7619-2598-9}}
*{{citation|last=Sooryamoorthi|first=Radhamany|editor-last=Leonard|editor-first=Thomas M. (editor)|chapter=Caste Systems|title=Encyclopedia of the Developing World|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=3mE04D9PMpAC&amp;pg=PA252|accessdate=5 August 2012|year=2006|location=New York, NY|publisher=Routledge|isbn=978-0-415-97662-6|pages=252–}}

==Further reading==
* ''Spectres of Agrarian Territory'' by David Ludden 11 December 2001
* "Early Evidence for Caste in South India", p.&amp;nbsp;467-492 in ''Dimensions of Social Life: Essays in honor of David G. Mandelbaum'', Edited by Paul Hockings and Mouton de Gruyter, Berlin, New York, Amsterdam, 1987.

== External links ==
* [http://socserv.mcmaster.ca/econ/ugcm/3ll3/comte/Philosophy3.pdf Auguste Comte on why and how castes developed across the world - in The Positive Philosophy, Volume 3 (see page 55 onwards)]
* [http://sciencepolicy.colorado.edu/students/envs_5110/merton_sociology_science.pdf Robert Merton on Caste and The Sociology of Science]
* [http://www.cambridge.org/gb/knowledge/isbn/item1168367/?site_locale=en_GB Caste, Society and Politics in India from the Eighteenth Century to the Modern Age - Susan Bayly]
* [http://www.countercurrents.org/hr-marguerite250404.htm Class In Yemen] by Marguerite Abadjian (Archive of the Baltimore Sun)
* [http://web.archive.org/web/20091026134948/http://geocities.com/lamberdar/_caste.html Hindu Caste System &amp; Hinduism: Vedic vocations (Hindu castes) were not related to heredity (birth)]
* [http://idsn.org/ International Dalit Solidarity Network: An international advocacy group for Dalits]
{{Segregation by type|state=collapsed}}
{{Discrimination}}

[[Category:Caste| ]]
[[Category:Portuguese loanwords]]
[[Category:Social status]]

[[be:Каста]]
[[bg:Каста]]
[[ca:Casta]]
[[cs:Kastovní systém]]
[[da:Kaste]]
[[de:Kaste]]
[[et:Kastisüsteem]]
[[el:Κάστα]]
[[es:Casta]]
[[eo:Kasto]]
[[eu:Kasta]]
[[fa:نظام طبقاتی]]
[[fr:Caste]]
[[ko:카스트]]
[[hr:Kaste]]
[[io:Kasto]]
[[id:Kasta]]
[[it:Casta]]
[[he:קאסטה]]
[[kk:Касталар]]
[[ky:Касталар]]
[[lb:Kast]]
[[lt:Kasta]]
[[ms:Sistem kasta]]
[[nl:Kastenstelsel]]
[[ja:カースト]]
[[no:Kaste]]
[[nn:Kaste]]
[[uz:Kasta]]
[[pl:Kasta]]
[[pt:Casta]]
[[ru:Каста]]
[[simple:Caste]]
[[sk:Kasta]]
[[sr:Каста]]
[[sh:Kaste]]
[[fi:Kastilaitos]]
[[sv:Kast]]
[[ta:சாதி]]
[[th:วรรณะทางสังคม]]
[[tr:Kast sistemi]]
[[uk:Каста]]
[[ur:ذات پات]]
[[zh:种姓制度]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>