<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20171123044838|811674543" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="7257" pageid="7257" ns="0" title="Caste"><revisions><rev timestamp="2017-11-23T04:49:26Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Other uses}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2012}}
[[File:Basor Dalit caste.jpg|thumb|The ''[[Basor]]'' weaving bamboo baskets in a 1916 book. The ''Basor'' are a [[Hindu]] caste found in the state of [[Uttar Pradesh]] in India.]]
{{Political anthropology|expanded=Basic concepts}}

{{Political anthropology}}

'''Caste''' is a form of [[social stratification]] characterized by [[endogamy]], hereditary transmission of a lifestyle which often includes an occupation, status in a hierarchy, and customary social interaction and exclusion.{{Sfn|Scott|Marshall|2005|p=66}}{{Sfn|Winthrop|1991|pp=27–30}} Although caste systems exist in various regions, its paradigmatic ethnographic example is the division of Indian society into rigid social groups, with roots in India's ancient history and persisting until today.{{Sfn|Béteille|2002|p=66}} However, the economic significance of the [[caste system in India]] has been declining as a result of urbanization and [[affirmative action]] programs.  A subject of much scholarship by sociologists and anthropologists, the Indian caste system is sometimes used as an analogical basis for the study of caste-like social divisions existing outside India.  In biology, the term is applied to role stratification in [[eusocial]] animals like ants and termites, though the analogy is imperfect as these also involve extremely stratified [[queen ant|reproduction]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last= Wilson |first= E. O. |year= 1979 |title= The Evolution of Caste Systems in Social Insects |journal= Proceedings of the American Philosophical Society |volume= 123 |number=4 |pages= 204–210 |jstor= 986579}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Etymology==
The origins of the term 'caste' are attributed to the Spanish and Portuguese ''[[casta]]'', which, according to the [[John Minsheu]]'s Spanish dictionary (1599), means "race, lineage, or breed".&lt;ref name=oed-caste&gt;{{cite web|publisher = Oxford English Dictionary|year = 1989|title=Caste, n|url=http://www.oed.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;  When the Spanish colonized the [[New World]], they used the word to mean a "clan or lineage". However, it was the Portuguese who employed ''casta'' in the primary modern sense when they applied it to the thousands of endogamous, hereditary Indian social groups they encountered upon their arrival in India in 1498.&lt;ref name=oed-caste/&gt;&lt;ref name=pitt-rivers&gt;{{citation|last=Pitt-Rivers|first=Julian|editor=T O Beidelman|title=The translation of culture essays to E.E. Evans-Pritchard|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=f509AAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=231|year=1971|publisher=Tavistock|location=London, UK|pages=231–256|chapter=On the word 'caste'|id=GGKEY:EC3ZBGF5QC9}}&lt;/ref&gt; The use of the spelling "caste", with this latter meaning, is first attested to in English in 1613.&lt;ref name=oed-caste/&gt;

==In South Asia==

=== India===
{{Main|Caste system in India}}
{{commons category|Castes in India}}
Modern India's caste system is based on the social groupings called ''[[jāti]]'' and the  theoretical ''[[varna (Hinduism)|varna]]''. The system of ''varnas'' appears in Hindu texts dating back to 1000 BCE and envisages the society divided into four classes: [[Brahmins]] (teachers, scholars and priests), [[Kashatriya]]s (warriors and nobles), [[Vaishyas]] (farmers, traders and artisans) and [[Shudras]] (labourers/service providers). The texts do not mention any separate, untouchable category in ''[[varna (Hinduism)|varna]]'' classification. Scholars believe that the system of ''varnas'' was a theoretical classification envisioned by the Brahmins, but never truly operational in the society. The practical division of the society had always been in terms of ''jātis'' (birth groups), which are not based on any specific principle, but could vary from ethnic origins to occupations. The ''jātis'' have been endogamous groups without any fixed hierarchy but subject to vague notions of rank articulated over time based on lifestyle and social, political or economic status. In many instances, as in Bengal, historically the kings and rulers had been called upon, when required, to mediate on the ranks of ''jātis'', which might number in thousands all over the subcontinent and vary by region. In practice, the ''jātis'' may or may not fit into the ''varna'' classes and many prominent ''jatis'', for example the Jats and Yadavs, straddled two varnas i.e. Kshatriyas and Vaishyas, and the ''varna'' status of ''jātis'' itself was subject to articulation over time.

Starting with the British colonial Census of 1901 led by [[Herbert Hope Risley]], all the ''jātis'' were grouped under the theoretical ''varnas'' categories.&lt;ref name=dirks&gt;{{cite book|url=http://press.princeton.edu/titles/7191.html|author=Nicholas B. Dirks|title=Castes of Mind: Colonialism and the Making of New India|year=2001|isbn=978-0-691-08895-2}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to political scientist [[Lloyd Rudolph]], Risley believed that ''varna'', however ancient, could be applied to all the modern castes found in India, and "[he] meant to identify and place several hundred million Indians within it."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=3vnsnma5nW4C |title=The Modernity of Tradition: Political Development in India |first=Lloyd I. |last=Rudolph |authorlink=Lloyd I. Rudolph |others=[[Susanne Hoeber Rudolph|Rudolph, Susanne Hoeber]] |year=1984 |publisher=University of Chicago Press |pages=116–117 |isbn=0-226-73137-5}}&lt;/ref&gt; The terms ''varna'' (conceptual classification based on occupation) and ''jāti'' (groups) are two distinct concepts: while ''varna'' is the idealised four-part division envisaged by the [[Dvija|Twice-Borns]], ''jāti'' (community) refers to the thousands of actual endogamous groups prevalent across the subcontinent. The classical authors scarcely speak of anything other than the ''varnas'', as it provided a convenient shorthand; but a problem arises when even Indologists sometimes confuse the two.&lt;ref name="Chicago"&gt;{{citation |author=Dumont, Louis |title=Homo hierarchicus: the caste system and its implications |publisher=University of Chicago Press |location=Chicago |year=1980 |pages=66–67 |isbn=0-226-16963-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Upon independence from Britain, the Indian Constitution listed 1,108 castes across the country as Scheduled Castes in 1950, for positive discrimination.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://lawmin.nic.in/ld/subord/rule3a.htm |title=The Constitution (Scheduled Castes) Order 1950 |publisher=Lawmin.nic.in |date= |access-date=2013-11-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Untouchable communities are sometimes called ''[[Scheduled Castes]]'', ''[[Dalit]]'' or ''[[Harijan]]'' in contemporary literature.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Scaling Caste Walls With Capitalism’s Ladders in India|publisher=The New York Times|author=Lydia Polgreen|date=21 December 2011|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2011/12/22/world/asia/indias-boom-creates-openings-for-untouchables.html?pagewanted=all}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2001, Dalits were 16.2% of India's population.&lt;ref name=censtat01&gt;{{cite web|title=Scheduled castes and scheduled tribes population: Census 2001|year=2004|publisher=Government of India|url=http://censusindia.gov.in/Census_Data_2001/India_at_glance/scst.aspx}}&lt;/ref&gt; Most of the 15 million bonded child workers are from the lowest castes.&lt;ref&gt;"[http://www.unicef.org/pon95/chil0016.html Children pay high price for cheap labour]". [[UNICEF]].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | author=ZAMA COURSEN-NEFF | date=30 January 2003 | title=For 15 million in India, a childhood of slavery | url=https://www.nytimes.com/2003/01/30/opinion/30iht-edzama_ed3__0.html | work=[[The New York Times]] | access-date=22 March 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Independent India has witnessed [[Caste-related violence in India|caste-related violence]]. India's National Crime Records Bureau (NCRB) records crimes against scheduled castes and scheduled tribes – the most disadvantaged groups - in a separate category. In 2005, government recorded approximately 110,000 cases of reported violent acts, including rape and murder, against Dalits &lt;ref&gt;"[http://www.cbc.ca/world/story/2007/03/02/india-dalits.html UN report slams India for caste discrimination]". CBC News. 2 March 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; For 2012, the government recorded 651 murders, 3,855 injuries, 1,576 rapes, 490 kidnappings, and 214 cases of arson.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.com/news/world-asia-india-27774908 "Viewpoint: India must stop denying caste and gender violence]". BBC News. 11 June 2014&lt;/ref&gt;

The socio-economic limitations of the caste system are reduced due to urbanization and [[affirmative action]]. Nevertheless, the caste system still exists in [[endogamy]] and [[Property|patrimony]], and thrives in the politics of democracy, where caste provides ready made constituencies to politicians. The globalization and economic opportunities from foreign businesses has influenced the growth of India's middle-class population. Some members of the Chhattisgarh Potter Caste Community (CPCC) are middle-class urban professionals and no longer potters unlike the remaining majority of traditional rural potter members. The co-existence of the middle-class and traditional members in the CPCC has created [[intersectionality]] between caste and class.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Natrajan|first1=Balmurli|title=Caste, class, and community in india: An ethnographic approach|journal=Ethnology|date=2005|volume=4|issue=3|pages=227–241}}&lt;/ref&gt; There is persistence of caste in Indian politics. Caste associations have evolved into caste-based political parties. Political parties and the state perceive caste as an important factor for mobilization of people and policy development. It is not politics that gets caste-ridden; it is caste that gets politicized.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Sen|first1=Ronojoy.|title=The persistence of caste in indian politics|journal=Pacific Affairs|date=2012|volume=85|issue=2|pages=363–369|doi=10.5509/2012852363}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Seventy-two Specimens of Castes in India (62).jpg|thumb|A page from the manuscript ''Seventy-two Specimens of Castes in India'', which consists of 72 full-color hand-painted images of men and women of various religions, occupations and ethnic groups found in [[Madurai|Madura, India]] in 1837, which confirms the popular perception and nature of caste as Jati, before the British made it applicable only to Hindus grouped under the ''[[Varna (Hinduism)|varna]]'' categories from the 1901 census onwards.]]

===Nepal===
{{Main|Caste system in Nepal}}
The [[Nepal]]ese caste system resembles that of the Indian ''jāti'' system with numerous ''jāti'' divisions with a ''varna'' system superimposed for a rough equivalence. But since the culture and the society is different some of the things are different. Inscriptions attest the beginnings of a caste system during the [[Licchavi (kingdom)|Licchavi]] period.  Jayasthiti Malla (1382–95) categorized Newars into 64 castes (Gellner 2001). A similar exercise was made during the reign of Mahindra Malla (1506–75). The Hindu social code was later set up in Gorkha by Ram Shah (1603–36).

===Pakistan===
{{Main|Caste system among South Asian Muslims}}

Religious, historical and sociocultural factors have helped define the bounds of endogamy for Muslims in some parts of [[Pakistan]]. There is a preference for endogamous marriages based on the clan-oriented nature of the society, which values and actively seeks similarities in social group identity based on several factors, including religious, sectarian, ethnic, and tribal/clan affiliation. Religious affiliation is itself multilayered and includes religious considerations other than being Muslim, such as sectarian identity (e.g. Shia or Sunni, etc.) and religious orientation within the sect (Isnashari, [[Isma'ilism|Ismaili]], [[Ahmadiyya|Ahmedi]], etc.).{{citation needed|date=March 2015}}

Both ethnic affiliation (e.g. [[Pashtuns|Pathan]], [[Sindhis|Sindhi]], [[Baloch people|Baloch]], [[Punjabis|Punjabi]], etc.) and membership of specific biraderis or zaat/quoms are additional integral components of social identity.&lt;ref name="barth"&gt;{{cite book | last = Barth | first = Fredrik | editor = E. R. Leach | title = The System Of Social Stratification In Swat, North Pakistan (Aspects of Caste in South India, Ceylon, and North-West Pakistan) | url= https://www.questia.com/PM.qst?a=o&amp;d=2995517 | publisher = Cambridge University Press | page = 113 | year = 1962 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Within the bounds of endogamy defined by the above parameters, close consanguineous unions are preferred due to a congruence of key features of group- and individual-level background factors as well as affinities. McKim Marriott claims a social stratification that is hierarchical, closed, endogamous and hereditary is widely prevalent, particularly in western parts of Pakistan. Frederik Barth in his review of this system of social stratification in Pakistan suggested that these are castes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Ecologic Relationships of Ethnic Groups in Swat, North Pakistan|author=Fredrick Barth|journal=American Anthropologist|doi=10.1525/aa.1956.58.6.02a00080|volume=58|issue=6|pages=1079–1089|date=December 1956}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The New Wind: Changing Identities in South Asia (Editor: Kenneth David)|author=Zeyauddin Ahmed|pages=337–354|isbn=90-279-7959-6|publisher=Aldine Publishing Company|year=1977}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Caste ranking and community structure in five regions of India and Pakistan|author=McKim Marriott|year=1960|url=http://www.worldcat.org/title/caste-ranking-and-community-structure-in-five-regions-of-india-and-pakistan/oclc/186146571}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Sri Lanka===
{{Main|Caste system in Sri Lanka}}
The caste system in Sri Lanka is a division of society into strata,&lt;ref name="John Rogers 51–77"&gt;{{cite journal|title=Caste as a social category and identity in colonial Lanka|author=John Rogers| doi=10.1177/001946460404100104| journal=Indian Economic Social History Review| date= February 2004|volume=41|number=1|pages=51–77}}&lt;/ref&gt; influenced by the textbook ''varnas'' and ''jāti'' system found in India. Ancient Sri Lankan texts such as the Pujavaliya, Sadharmaratnavaliya and Yogaratnakaraya and inscriptional evidence show that the above hierarchy prevailed throughout the feudal period. The repetition of the same caste hierarchy even as recently as the 18th century, in the British/Kandyan period Kadayimpoth - Boundary books as well, indicates the continuation of the tradition right up to the end of Sri Lanka's monarchy.

==Caste-like stratification outside South Asia==

===Southeast Asia===
[[File:COLLECTIE TROPENMUSEUM Een soedra een man uit de laagste kaste van Bali. TMnr 60002169.jpg|thumb|upright|A Sudra caste man from [[Bali]]. Photo from 1870, courtesy of [[Tropenmuseum]], [[Netherlands]].]]

====Indonesia====
{{Main|Balinese caste system}}
[[Bali]]nese caste structure has been described in early 20th-century European literature to be based on three categories – triwangsa (thrice born) or the nobility, ''dwijāti'' (twice born) in contrast to ''ekajāti'' (once born) the low folks. Four statuses were identified in these sociological studies, spelled a bit differently from the caste categories for India:&lt;ref name=boon&gt;{{cite book|title=The Anthropological Romance of Bali 1597-1972: Dynamic Perspectives in Marriage and Caste, Politics and Religion|author=James Boon|year=1977|isbn=0-521-21398-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Brahmanas - priest
*Satrias - knighthood
*Wesias - commerce
*Sudras - servitude

The Brahmana caste was further subdivided by these Dutch ethnographers into two: Siwa and Buda. The Siwa caste was subdivided into five &amp;ndash; Kemenuh, Keniten, Mas, Manuba and Petapan. This classification was to accommodate the observed marriage between higher caste Brahmana men with lower caste women. The other castes were similarly further sub-classified by these 19th-century and early-20th-century ethnographers based on numerous criteria ranging from profession, endogamy or exogamy or polygamy, and a host of other factors in a manner similar to ''castas'' in Spanish colonies such as Mexico, and caste system studies in British colonies such as India.&lt;ref name=boon/&gt;

===East Asia===

====China and Mongolia====

During the period of [[Yuan Dynasty]], ruler [[Kublai Khan]] enforced a ''Four Class System'', which was a legal caste system. The order of four classes of people was maintained by the information of the descending order were:-
* [[Mongols|Mongolian]]
* [[Semu]] people
* [[Han Chinese|Han]] people (in the northern areas of China)
* Southerners (people of the former Southern [[Song dynasty]])

Some scholars notes that it was a kind of psychological indication that the earlier they submitted to Mongolian people, the higher social status they would have. The 'Four Class System' and its people received different treatment in political, legal, and military affairs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.travelchinaguide.com/intro/history/yuan/four-class-system.htm |title='Four-Class System' of Yuan Dynasty |publisher=Travelchinaguide.com |date= |accessdate=2013-11-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;"The Cambridge History of China: Volume 6, Alien Regimes and Border States, 710-1368", by Denis C. Twitchett, Herbert Franke, John King Fairbank, p. 610&lt;/ref&gt;

Today, the [[Hukou system]] is considered by various sources as the current caste system of [[China]].&lt;ref&gt;"Chinese Society: Change, Conflict and Resistance", by Elizabeth J. Perry, Mark Selden, page [https://books.google.com/books?id=JqZyQCZmrRAC&amp;pg=PA90 90]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;"China's New Confucianism: Politics and Everyday Life in a Changing Society", p. 86, by Daniel A. Bell&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;"Trust and Distrust: Sociocultural Perspectives", p. 63, by Ivana Marková, Alex Gillespie&lt;/ref&gt;

There is also significant controversy over the [[social classes of Tibet]], especially with regards to the [[serfdom in Tibet controversy]].

====Japan====
{{Main|Edo society}}
[[File:Samurai and servant.jpg|thumb|Japanese [[samurai]] of importance and servant.]]

In Japan's history, social strata based on inherited position rather than personal merit, was rigid and highly formalized in a system called ''mibunsei'' (身分制). At the top were the Emperor and Court nobles ([[kuge]]), together with the Shogun and daimyo. Below them, the population was divided into [[Four occupations|four classes]]: [[samurai]], peasants, craftsmen and merchants. Only samurai were allowed to bear arms. A samurai had a right to kill any peasants, craftsman or merchant who he felt were disrespectful. Merchants were the lowest caste because they did not produce any products. The castes were further sub-divided; for example, peasants were labelled as ''furiuri'', ''tanagari'', ''mizunomi-byakusho'' among others. As in Europe, the castes and sub-classes were of the same race, religion and culture.

Howell, in his review of [[Japan]]ese society notes that if a Western power had colonized Japan in the 19th century, they would have discovered and imposed a rigid four-caste hierarchy in Japan.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Geographies of identity in nineteenth-century Japan|author=David L. Howell|publisher=University of California Press|isbn=0-520-24085-5|year=2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;

De Vos and Wagatsuma observe that Japanese society had a systematic and extensive caste system. They discuss how alleged caste impurity and alleged racial inferiority, concepts often  assumed to be different, are superficial terms, and are due to identical inner psychological processes, which expressed themselves in Japan and elsewhere.&lt;ref name=gdvhw&gt;{{cite book|title=Japan's invisible race: caste in culture and personality|author=George De Vos and Hiroshi Wagatsuma|publisher=University of California Press|year=1966|isbn=978-0-520-00306-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Endogamy was common because marriage across caste lines was socially unacceptable.&lt;ref name=gdvhw/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Japanese Fashion: A Cultural History|author=Toby Slade|publisher=Berg|isbn=978-1-84788-252-3|year=2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Japan]] had its own untouchable caste, shunned and ostracized, historically referred to by the insulting term ''Eta'', now called ''[[Burakumin]]''. While modern law has officially abolished the class hierarchy, there are reports of discrimination against the [[Buraku]] or [[Burakumin]] underclasses.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hrdc.net/sahrdc/hrfeatures/HRF39.htm |title=Class, Ethnicity and Nationality: Japan Finds Plenty of Space for Discrimination |publisher=Hrdc.net |date=2001-06-18 |accessdate=2013-11-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Burakumin are regarded as "ostracised."&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite journal
| author = William H. Newell
|date=December 1961
| title = The Comparative Study of Caste in India and Japan
| journal = Asian Survey
| volume = 1
| issue = 10
| pages = 3–10
| doi = 10.1525/as.1961.1.10.01p15082
| jstor=3023467
}}
&lt;/ref&gt; The burakumin are one of the main [[demographics of Japan|minority groups in Japan]], along with the [[Ainu people|Ainu]] of [[Hokkaidō]] and those of [[Zainichi Korean|residents of Korean]] and [[Chinese in Japan|Chinese]] descent.

====Korea====
[[File:Korea-History-Goban Game in Seoul Korea 1904 (LOC).jpg|thumbnail|A typical Yangban Family Scene from 1904.  The Yoon Family had an enduring presence in Korean politics from the 1800s until the 1970s.]]

The [[baekjeong]] (백정) were an “untouchable” outcaste of Korea. The meaning today is that of butcher. It originates in the [[Goryeo-Khitan Wars|Khitan invasion of Korea]] in the 11th century. The defeated [[Khitans]] who surrendered were settled in isolated communities throughout Goryeo to forestall rebellion.  They were valued for their skills in hunting, herding, butchering, and making of leather, common skill sets among nomads.  Over time, their ethnic origin was forgotten, and they formed the bottom layer of Korean society.

In 1392, with the foundation of the Confucian [[Joseon dynasty]], Korea systemised its own native class system. At the top were the two official classes, the [[Yangban]], which literally means "two classes." It was composed of scholars (''munban'') and warriors (''muban''). Scholars had a significant social advantage over the warriors. Below were the ''jung-in'' (중인-中人: literally "middle people". This was a small class of specialized professions such as medicine, accounting, translators, regional bureaucrats, etc. Below that were the ''sangmin'' (상민-常民: literally 'commoner'), farmers working their own fields. Korea also had a [[serf]] population known as the ''nobi''. The nobi population could fluctuate up to about one-third of the population, but on average the nobi made up about 10% of the total population.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Rodriguez|first1=Junius P.|title=The Historical Encyclopedia of World Slavery|publisher=ABC-CLIO|isbn=9780874368857|page=392|url=https://books.google.com/?id=ATq5_6h2AT0C&amp;pg=RA1-PA392&amp;dq=%2210+percent+of+the+total+population+on+average,+but+it+could+rise+up+to+one-third+of+the+total%22#v=onepage&amp;q=%2210%20percent%20of%20the%20total%20population%20on%20average%2C%20but%20it%20could%20rise%20up%20to%20one-third%20of%20the%20total%22&amp;f=false|accessdate=14 February 2017|language=en|year=1997}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1801, the vast majority of government nobi were emancipated,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Kim|first1=Youngmin|last2=Pettid|first2=Michael J.|title=Women and Confucianism in Choson Korea: New Perspectives|publisher=SUNY Press|isbn=9781438437774|page=141|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=UwgUa6WWFBMC&amp;pg=PA141#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|accessdate=14 February 2017|language=en|date=2011-11-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; and by 1858 the nobi population stood at about 1.5 percent of the total population of Korea.&lt;ref name="nobi"&gt;{{cite book|last1=Campbell|first1=Gwyn|title=Structure of Slavery in Indian Ocean Africa and Asia|publisher=Routledge|isbn=9781135759179|page=163|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=J0iRAgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA163#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|accessdate=14 February 2017|language=en|date=2004-11-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; The hereditary nobi system was officially abolished around 1886–87 and the rest of the nobi system was abolished with the [[Gabo Reform]] of 1894,&lt;ref name="nobi" /&gt; but traces remained until 1930.

The opening of Korea to foreign Christian missionary activity in the late 19th century saw some improvement in the status of the ''baekjeong.'' However, everyone was not equal under the Christian congregation, and even so protests erupted when missionaries tried to integrate ''baekjeong'' into worship, with non-''baekjeong'' finding this attempt insensitive to traditional notions of hierarchical advantage.{{Citation needed|date=September 2007}} Around the same time, the ''baekjeong'' began to resist open social discrimination.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|chapter=In Search of Human Rights: The Paekchŏng Movement in Colonial Korea|title=Colonial Modernity in Korea|first=Joong-Seop|last=Kim|editor=Gi-Wook Shin and Michael Robinson|year=1999|pages=326|isbn=0-674-00594-5}}&lt;/ref&gt; They focused on social and economic injustices affecting them, hoping to create an [[egalitarianism|egalitarian]] Korean society. Their efforts included attacking social discrimination by upper class, authorities, and "commoners," and the use of degrading language against children in public schools.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The Korean Paekjŏng under Japanese rule: the quest for equality and human rights|first=Joong-Seop|last=Kim|year=2003|pages=147}}&lt;/ref&gt;

With the [[Gabo reform]] of 1896, the class system of Korea was officially abolished. Following the collapse of the [[Enlightenment Party|Gabo government]], the new cabinet, which became the Gwangmu government after the establishment of the Korean Empire, introduced systematic measures for abolishing the traditional class system. One measure was the new household registration system, reflecting the goals of formal [[social equality]], which was implemented by the loyalists’ cabinet. Whereas the old registration system signified household members according to their hierarchical social status, the new system called for an occupation.&lt;ref name="proper"&gt;Hwang, Kyung Moon (2004), University of Southern California. ''Citizenship, Social Equality and Government Reform: Changes in the Household Registration System in Korea, 1894-1910''&lt;/ref&gt;

While most Koreans by then had surnames and even [[bongwan]], although still substantial number of [[cheonmin]], mostly consisted of [[serfs]] and slaves, and [[Untouchability|untouchables]] did not. According to the new system, they were then required to fill in the blanks for surname in order to be registered as constituting separate households. Instead of creating their own family name, some cheonmins appropriated their masters’ surname, while others simply took the most common surname and its bongwan in the local area. Along with this example, activists within and outside the Korean government had based their visions of a new relationship between the government and people through the concept of citizenship, employing the term ''inmin'' ("people") and later, ''kungmin'' ("citizen").&lt;ref name="proper"/&gt;

=====North Korea=====
{{Main|Songbun}}

Committee for Human Rights in [[North Korea]] reported that "Every North Korean citizen is assigned a heredity-based class and socio-political rank over which the individual exercises no control but which determines all aspects of his or her life."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=06 Jun 2012 |url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/asia/northkorea/9313174/North-Korea-caste-system-underpins-human-rights-abuses.html |title=North Korea caste system 'underpins human rights abuses' |publisher=Telegraph.co.uk |date=2012-06-06 |accessdate=2013-11-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; Regarded as '''Songbun''', [[Barbara Demick]] describes this "class structure" as an updating of the hereditary "caste system", combining Confucianism and Stalinism.&lt;ref&gt;Barbara Demick, ''Nothing to Envy: Love, Life and Death in North Korea,'' Fourth Estate, London, 2010, pp 26-27.&lt;/ref&gt;  She claims that a bad family background is called "tainted blood", and that by law this "tainted blood" lasts for three generations.&lt;ref&gt;Demick, pp 28, 197, 202.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Tibet====
{{See also|Social classes of Tibet}}

Heidi Fjeld has put forth the argument that pre-1950s Tibetan society was functionally a caste system, in contrast to previous scholars who defined the Tibetan social class system as similar to European feudal serfdom, as well as non-scholarly western accounts which seek to romanticize a supposedly 'egalitarian' ancient Tibetan society.

===West Asia===
{{main|Yazidi}}

[[Yezidi]] society is hierarchical. The secular leader is a hereditary [[emir]] or prince, whereas a chief [[sheikh]] heads the religious hierarchy. The Yazidi are strictly [[Endogamy|endogamous]]; members of the three Yazidi castes, the [[murid]]s, sheikhs and [[Islam Pir|pir]]s, marry only within their group.

====Iran====

Pre-Islamic [[Sassanid]] society was immensely complex, with separate systems of social organization governing numerous different groups within the empire.&lt;ref name="Nicolle, p. 11"&gt;Nicolle, p. 11&lt;/ref&gt; Historians believe society comprised four&lt;ref&gt;
These four are the three common "Indo-Euoropean" [[Trifunctional hypothesis|social tripartition]] common among ancient Iranian, Indian and Romans with one extra Iranian element (from Yashna xix/17). cf. Frye, p. 54.
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The Persian Night: Iran under the Khomeinist Revolution|page=1982|author=Amir Taheri|publisher=Encounter books}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Why the Middle East Lagged Behind: The Case of Iran|page=72|author=Kāẓim ʻAlamdārī|publisher=University Press of America}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[social class]]es:

# Priests ({{lang-fa|Asravan}})
# Warriors ({{lang-fa|Arteshtaran}})
# Secretaries ({{lang-fa|Dabiran}})
# Commoners ({{lang-fa|Vastryoshan}})

====Yemen====
{{main|Al-Akhdam}}
In [[Yemen]] there exists a hereditary caste, the [[Africa]]n-descended [[Al-Akhdam]] who are kept as perennial manual workers. Estimates put their number at over 3.5 million residents who are discriminated, out of a total Yemeni population of around 22 million.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ireport.cnn.com/docs/DOC-999239|title=Yemen’s Al-Akhdam face brutal oppression|website=CNN iReport|accessdate=22 October 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Africa===
{{Main|Caste system in Africa}}

Various sociologists have reported caste systems in Africa.&lt;ref name=Obinna1&gt;{{cite journal|title=Contesting identity: the Osu caste system among Igbo of Nigeria|author=Elijah Obinna|pages=111–121|journal=African Identities|volume=10|issue=1|year=2012|doi=10.1080/14725843.2011.614412}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="James B. Watson 356–379"&gt;{{cite journal|title=Caste as a Form of Acculturation|author=James B. Watson|journal=Southwestern Journal of Anthropology|volume=19|number= 4|date= Winter 1963|pages=356–379}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=tamari1/&gt; The specifics of the caste systems have varied in ethnically and culturally diverse Africa, however the following features are common - it has been a closed system of social stratification, the social status is inherited, the castes are hierarchical, certain castes are shunned while others are merely endogamous and exclusionary.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Caste discrimination in Africa|author=Leo Igwe|publisher=International Humanist and Ethical Union|date=21 August 2009|url=http://www.iheu.org/caste-discrimination-africa}}&lt;/ref&gt; In some cases, concepts of purity and impurity by birth have been prevalent in Africa. In other cases, such as the ''Nupe'' of Nigeria, the ''Beni Amer'' of East Africa, and the ''Tira'' of Sudan, the exclusionary principle has been driven by evolving social factors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Caste and government in primitive society|author=SF Nadel|journal=Journal of Anthropological Society|volume=8|pages=9–22|year=1954}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====West Africa====
[[File:GriotFête.jpg|thumb|upright|left|A [[Griot]], who have been described as an endogamous caste of West Africa who specialize in oral story telling and culture preservation. They have been also referred to as the bard caste.]]
Among the Igbo of [[Nigeria]] - especially [[Enugu State|Enugu]], [[Anambra State|Anambra]], [[Imo State|Imo]], [[Abia State|Abia]], [[Ebonyi State|Ebonyi]], [[Edo State|Edo]] and [[Delta state|Delta]] states of the country - Obinna finds Osu caste system has been and continues to be a major social issue. The Osu caste is determined by one's birth into a particular family irrespective of the religion practised by the individual. Once born into Osu caste, this Nigerian person is an outcast, shunned and ostracized, with limited opportunities or acceptance, regardless of his or her ability or merit. Obinna discusses how this caste system-related identity and power is deployed within government, Church and indigenous communities.&lt;ref name=Obinna1/&gt;

The ''osu'' class systems of eastern [[Nigeria]] and southern [[Cameroon]] are derived from indigenous religious beliefs and discriminate against the "Osus" people as "owned by deities" and outcasts.

The Songhai economy was based on a caste system. The most common were metalworkers, fishermen, and carpenters. Lower caste participants consisted of mostly non-farm working immigrants, who at times were provided special privileges and held high positions in society. At the top were noblemen and direct descendants of the original Songhai people, followed by freemen and traders.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.africankingdoms.com|title=AFRICAN KINGDOMS - Kingdoms of Ancient African History|website=www.africankingdoms.com|accessdate=22 October 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In a review of social stratification systems in Africa, Richter reports that the term caste has been used by French and American scholars to many groups of West African artisans. These groups have been described as inferior, deprived of all political power, have a specific occupation, are hereditary and sometimes despised by others. Richter illustrates caste system in [[Ivory Coast]], with six sub-caste categories. Unlike other parts of the world, mobility is sometimes possible within sub-castes, but not across caste lines. Farmers and artisans have been, claims Richter, distinct castes. Certain sub-castes are shunned more than others. For example, exogamy is rare for women born into families of woodcarvers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Further considerations of caste in West Africa: The Senufo|author=Dolores Richter|journal=Africa|date= January 1980|volume=50|pages=37–54|doi=10.2307/1158641|jstor=1158641}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Similarly, the [[Mandé peoples|Mandé]] societies in [[Gambia]], [[Ghana]], [[Guinea]], [[Ivory Coast]], [[Liberia]], [[Senegal]] and [[Sierra Leone]] have social stratification systems that divide society by ethnic ties. The Mande class system regards the ''jonow'' slaves as inferior. Similarly, the [[Wolof people|Wolof]] in Senegal is divided into three main groups, the ''geer'' (freeborn/nobles), ''jaam'' (slaves and slave descendants) and the underclass ''neeno''. In various parts of West Africa, [[Fula people|Fulani]] societies also have class divisions. Other castes include ''Griots'', ''Forgerons'', and ''Cordonniers''.

Tamari has described endogamous castes of over fifteen West African peoples, including the Tukulor, Songhay, Dogon, Senufo, Minianka, Moors, Manding, Soninke, Wolof, Serer, Fulani, and Tuareg. Castes appeared among the ''Malinke'' people no later than 14th century, and was present among the ''Wolof'' and ''Soninke'', as well as some ''Songhay'' and ''Fulani'' populations, no later than 16th century. Tamari claims that wars, such as the ''Sosso-Malinke'' war described in the ''Sunjata'' epic, led to the formation of blacksmith and bard castes among the people that ultimately became the Mali empire.

As West Africa evolved over time, sub-castes emerged that acquired secondary specializations or changed occupations. Endogamy was prevalent within a caste or among a limited number of castes, yet castes did not form demographic isolates according to Tamari. Social status according to caste was inherited by off-springs automatically; but this inheritance was paternal. That is, children of higher caste men and lower caste or slave concubines would have the caste status of the father.&lt;ref name=tamari1&gt;{{cite journal|journal=The Journal of African History|year=1991|volume=32|issue=2|pages=221–250|doi=10.1017/S0021853700025718|title=The Development of Caste Systems in West Africa|author=Tal Tamari}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Central Africa====
Ethel M. Albert in 1960 claimed that the societies in [[Central Africa]] were caste-like social stratification systems.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Socio-Political Organization and Receptivity to Change: Some Differences between Ruanda and Urundi|author=Ethel M. Albert|journal=Southwestern Journal of Anthropology|volume=16|number= 1|date= Spring 1960|pages=46–74}}&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, in 1961, Maquet notes that the society in [[Rwanda]] and [[Burundi]] can be best described as castes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The Premise of Inequality in Ruanda: A Study of Political Relations in a Central African Kingdom|author= Jacques J. Maquet|year=1962|pages=135–171|publisher=Oxford University Press, London|isbn=978-0-19-823168-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Tutsi]], noted Maquet, considered themselves as superior, with the more numerous [[Hutu]] and the least numerous [[Twa]] regarded, by birth, as respectively, second and third in the hierarchy of Rwandese society. These groups were largely endogamous, exclusionary and with limited mobility.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Power in Ruanda|author=Helen Codere|journal=Anthropologica|volume=4|number=1|year=1962|pages=45–85|jstor=25604523}}&lt;/ref&gt; Maquet's theories have been controversial.

====Horn of Africa====
[[File:NSRW Africa Midgan.png|thumb|upright|The [[Madhiban]] (Midgan) specialize in leather occupation. Along with the Tumal and Yibir, they are collectively known as ''sab''.&lt;ref name="Lewis"/&gt;]]
In a review published in 1977, Todd reports that numerous scholars report a system of social stratification in different parts of Africa that resembles some or all aspects of caste system. Examples of such caste systems, he claims, are to be found in Ethiopia in communities such as the [[Gurage people|Gurage]] and [[Konso people|Konso]]. He then presents the Dime of Southwestern Ethiopia, amongst whom there operates a system which Todd claims can be unequivocally labelled as caste system. The Dime have seven castes whose size varies considerably. Each broad caste level is a hierarchical order that is based on notions of purity, non-purity and impurity. It uses the concepts of defilement to limit contacts between caste categories and to preserve the purity of the upper castes. These caste categories have been exclusionary, endogamous and the social identity inherited.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=LA CASTE EN AFRIQUE? (Caste in Africa?)|author=D. M. Todd|journal=Africa|date=October 1977|volume=47 |issue=4|pages= 398–412|url=http://journals.cambridge.org/action/displayAbstract?fromPage=online&amp;aid=7903506|doi=10.2307/1158345|jstor=1158345}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Alula Pankhurst]] has published a study of caste groups in SW Ethiopia.&lt;ref&gt;Pankhurst, Alula. 1999. ‘“Caste” in Africa: the evidence from south-western Ethiopia reconsidered’. ''Africa'' 69(4), pp.485-509.&lt;/ref&gt;

Among the [[Kingdom of Kafa|Kafa]], there were also traditionally groups labeled as castes. "Based on research done before the Derg regime, these studies generally presume the existence of a social hierarchy similar to the caste system. At the top of this hierarchy were the Kafa, followed by occupational groups including blacksmiths (Qemmo), weavers (Shammano), bards (Shatto), potters, and tanners (Manno). In this hierarchy, the Manjo were commonly referred to as hunters, given the lowest status equal only to slaves."&lt;ref&gt;p. 299. Sayuri Yoshida. Why did the Manjo convert to Protestant? Social Discrimination and Coexistence in Kafa, Southwest Ethiopia? ''Proceedings of the 16th International Conference of Ethiopian Studies'', ed. by Svein Ege, Harald
Aspen, Birhanu Teferra and Shiferaw Bekele, Trondheim 2009. p. 299-309.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Borana Oromo]] of southern [[Ethiopia]] in the [[Horn of Africa]] also have a class system, wherein the Wata, an acculturated hunter-gatherer group, represent the lowest class. Though the Wata today speak the [[Oromo language]], they have traditions of having previously spoken another language before adopting Oromo.&lt;ref name="Westermann"&gt;{{cite book|last=Diedrich Westermann|first=Edwin William Smith, Cyril Daryll Forde|title=Africa|year=1981|publisher=Oxford University Press|page=853}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The traditionally nomadic [[Somali people]] are divided into clans, wherein the [[Rahanweyn]] agro-pastoral clans and the occupational clans such as the [[Madhiban]] were traditionally sometimes treated as outcasts.&lt;ref&gt;I. M. Lewis, ''A pastoral democracy: a study of pastoralism and politics among the Northern Somali of the Horn of Africa'', (LIT Verlag Berlin-Hamburg-Münster: 1999), pp.13-14&lt;/ref&gt; As Gabboye, the Madhiban along with the [[Yibir]] and Tumaal (collectively referred to as ''sab'') have since obtained political representation within [[Somalia]], and their general social status has improved with the expansion of urban centers.&lt;ref name="Lewis"&gt;{{cite book|last=Lewis|first=I.M.|title=Understanding Somalia and Somaliland: Culture, History, Society|year=2008|publisher=Columbia University Press|isbn=0231700849|pages=8}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Europe===
Medieval Europe had a social stratification similar to that on the Indian subcontinent, that is:-
# Nobility/Royalty
# Knights/Squires/Clergy
# Artisans
# Peasants/serfs

====France and Spain====
For centuries, through the modern times, the majority regarded [[Cagot]]s of western [[France]] and northern [[Spain]] as an inferior caste, the untouchables. While they had the same skin color and religion as the majority, in the churches they had to use segregated doors, drink from segregated fonts, and receive communion on the end of long wooden spoons. It was a closed social system. The socially isolated Cagots were endogamous, and chances of social mobility non-existent.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=The last untouchable in Europe|author=Sean Thomas|date=28 July 2008|publisher=The Independent, United Kingdom|url=https://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/europe/the-last-untouchable-in-europe-878705.html|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Hansson1996"&gt;{{cite book|author=Anders Hansson|title=Chinese Outcasts: Discrimination and Emancipation in Late Imperial China|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=4Ibp1RTW0AoC&amp;pg=PA15|year=1996|publisher=BRILL|isbn=978-90-04-10596-6|pages=15–16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====United Kingdom====
In July 2013, the UK government announced its intention to amend the [[Equality Act 2010]] to "introduce legislation on caste, including any necessary exceptions to the caste provisions, within the framework of domestic discrimination law".&lt;ref&gt;Government Equalities Office, [https://www.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/225658/130726-Caste-Discrimination.pdf Caste legislation introduction – programme and timetable], accessed 2 June 2016&lt;/ref&gt; Section 9(5) of the Equality Act 2010 provides that "a [[Minister (government)|Minister]] may by [[Statutory order|order]] amend the statutory definition of race to include caste and may provide for exceptions in the Act to apply or not to apply to caste". 

From September 2013 to February 2014, [[Meena Dhanda]] led a project on ‘Caste in Britain’ for the UK [[Equality and Human Rights Commission]] (EHRC).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.equalityhumanrights.com/en/publication-download/research-report-91-caste-britain-socio-legal-review|title=Research report 91: Caste in Britain: Socio-legal Review {{!}} Equality and Human Rights Commission|website=www.equalityhumanrights.com|access-date=2017-10-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Estates of the realm]]
*[[Kamaiya]]
*[[Propiska in the Soviet Union|Propiska]]
*[[Social exclusion]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Sources==
{{refbegin}}
*{{citation|last=Béteille
|first =André|editor-last=Barnard|editor-first=Alan|editor2-last=Spencer|editor2-first=Jonathan|chapter=Caste|title=Encyclopedia of Social and Cultural Anthropology|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=o1VpdrbH3BUC&amp;pg=PA136|year=2002|location=New York, NY; London, UK|publisher=Routledge|isbn=978-0-415-28558-2|pages=136–137}}
*{{citation|editor-last=Doniger
|editor-first=Wendy|title=Merriam-Webster's Encyclopedia of World Religions|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ZP_f9icf2roC&amp;pg=PA186|accessdate=24 September 2012|year=1999|publisher=Merriam-Webster|location=Springfield, MA|isbn=978-0-87779-044-0|page=186|chapter=Caste}}
*{{citation|last=Gupta
|first=Dipankar|chapter=Caste|editor-last=Schaefer|editor-first=Richard T.|title=Encyclopedia of Race, Ethnicity, and Society|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=YMUola6pDnkC&amp;pg=PA246|location=Thousand Oaks|accessdate=5 August 2012|year=2008|publisher=SAGE|isbn=978-1-4129-2694-2|pages=246–250}}
*{{citation|editor-last=Lagasse
|editor-first=Paul|title=The Columbia Encyclopedia|chapter=Caste|url=http://www.encyclopedia.com/topic/caste.aspx#3|accessdate=24 September 2012|year=2007|publisher=Columbia University Press|location=New York, NY|isbn=978-0-231-14446-9}}
*{{citation|last1=Madan
|first1=T. N.|authorlink1=T. N. Madan|last2=Editors|fist2= |title=caste|publisher= Encyclopæida Britannica Online|url=http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/98395/caste|date=2012}}
*{{citation|last=Mitchell
|first=Geoffrey Duncan|title=A New Dictionary of the Social Sciences|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=-a4vvdBrSVgC&amp;pg=PA194|accessdate=10 August 2012|date=2006|publisher=Aldine Transaction Publishers|isbn=978-0-202-30878-4|pages=194–195|chapter=Castes (part of SOCIAL STRATIFICATION)|location=New Brunswick, NJ}}
*{{citation|last=Morris
|first=Mike|title=Concise Dictionary of Social and Cultural Anthropology|chapter=caste|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=5lTQRZru1SQC&amp;pg=PA33|accessdate=10 August 2012|date= 2012|publisher=John Wiley &amp; Sons|isbn=978-1-4443-3209-4|location=Malden, MA|page=33}}
*{{citation|last=Nagar
|first=Richa|authorlink=Richa Nagar|editor=Derek Gregory|others=Ron Johnston, Geraldine Pratt, Michael Watts, Sarah Whatmore|title=The Dictionary of Human Geography|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=5gCHckKszz0C&amp;pg=PA72|accessdate=10 August 2012|year=2011|publisher=John Wiley &amp; Sons|isbn=978-1-4443-5995-4|page=72|chapter=caste}}
*''[[Oxford English Dictionary]]'' ({{citation|chapter=caste, n.|title  = Oxford English Dictionary, Second edition; online version June 2012|publisher = Oxford University Press|location=Oxford, UK|url=http://www.oed.com/view/Entry/28546|accessdate =5 August 2012|year = 1989}}) Quote: '''caste, n.''' 2a. spec. One of the several hereditary classes into which society in India has from time immemorial been divided; ... ''This is now the leading sense, which influences all others.''
*{{citation|last=Parry
|first = Jonathan| editor1-last=Kuper|editor1-first=Adam|editor2-last=Kuper|editor2-first=Jessica|chapter=Caste|title=Social Science Encyclopedia|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=IKXj9sQ3aqIC&amp;pg=PA131|year=2003|location=London and New York|publisher=Routledge|isbn=978-0-415-28560-5|page=131}}
*{{citation|last=Pavri
|first=Firooza|editor=Tim Forsyth|title=Encyclopedia of International Development|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=93OsjK8GjE0C&amp;pg=PA63|year=2004|publisher=Routledge|location=Abingdon, Oxon, OX ; New York, NY |isbn=978-0-415-25342-0|pages=63–|chapter=Caste}}
*{{citation|last=Ramu
|first=G. N.|editor=William A. Darity|title=International Encyclopedia of the Social Sciences|url=http://www.encyclopedia.com/topic/caste.aspx#2|accessdate=24 September 2012|series=(Macmillan social science library)|year=2008|publisher=Macmillan Reference USA|location=Detroit, MI|isbn=978-0-02-865967-1|chapter=Caste}}
*{{citation|last=Roberts
|first=Nathaniel P.|editor=William A. Darity|title=International Encyclopedia of the Social Sciences|url=http://www.encyclopedia.com/doc/1G2-3045300290.html|accessdate=24 September 2012|series=(Macmillan social science library)|year=2008|publisher=Macmillan Reference USA|location=Detroit, MI|isbn=978-0-02-865967-1|chapter=Anthropology of Caste}}
*{{citation|last=Salamone
|first=Frank A.|editor-first=Junius P. |editor-last=Rodriguez|chapter=Caste|title=The Historical Encyclopedia of World Slavery, Volume 1|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ATq5_6h2AT0C&amp;pg=PA133|location=Santa Barbara, CA; Oxford, UK|accessdate=5 August 2012|year=1997|publisher=ABC-CLIO|isbn=978-0-87436-885-7|page=133}}
*{{citation|last1=Scott
|first1=John|last2=Marshall|first2=Gordon|title=A Dictionary of Sociology|chapter=caste|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=id8iAQAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA66|location=Oxford, UK; New York, NY|accessdate=10 August 2012|year=2005|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=978-0-19-860987-2|page=66}}
*{{citation|last=Sonnad
|first=Subhash R. |editor1-last=Christensen|editor1-first=Karen|editor2-last=Levinson|editor2-first=David|title=Encyclopedia of Community: From the Village to the Virtual World|chapter=Caste|pages=115&amp;ndash;121|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=t1geOjQ6R0MC&amp;pg=PA115|accessdate=5 August 2012|year=2003|publisher=SAGE|location=Thousand Oaks, CA|isbn=978-0-7619-2598-9}}
*{{citation|last=Sooryamoorthi
|first=Radhamany|editor-last=Leonard|editor-first=Thomas M. (editor)|chapter=Caste Systems|title=Encyclopedia of the Developing World|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=3mE04D9PMpAC&amp;pg=PA252|accessdate=5 August 2012|year=2006|location=New York, NY|publisher=Routledge|isbn=978-0-415-97662-6|pages=252–}}
*{{citation|last=Winthrop
|first=Robert H.|title=Dictionary of Concepts in Cultural Anthropology|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=3xoB_3C5N5QC&amp;pg=PA27|accessdate=10 August 2012|year=1991|publisher=ABC-CLIO|isbn=978-0-313-24280-9|pages=27–30}}
{{refend}}

==Further reading==
* ''Spectres of Agrarian Territory'' by David Ludden 11 December 2001
* "Early Evidence for Caste in South India", p.&amp;nbsp;467-492 in ''Dimensions of Social Life: Essays in honor of David G. Mandelbaum'', Edited by Paul Hockings and Mouton de Gruyter, Berlin, New York, Amsterdam, 1987.

==External links==
* [http://socserv.mcmaster.ca/econ/ugcm/3ll3/comte/Philosophy3.pdf Auguste Comte on why and how castes developed across the world - in The Positive Philosophy, Volume 3 (see page 55 onwards)]
* [http://sciencepolicy.colorado.edu/students/envs_5110/merton_sociology_science.pdf Robert Merton on Caste and The Sociology of Science]
* [http://www.cambridge.org/gb/knowledge/isbn/item1168367/?site_locale=en_GB Caste, Society and Politics in India from the Eighteenth Century to the Modern Age - [[Susan Bayly]]]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20061105095243/http://www.countercurrents.org/hr-marguerite250404.htm Class In Yemen] by Marguerite Abadjian (Archive of the Baltimore Sun)
* [http://idsn.org/ International Dalit Solidarity Network: An international advocacy group for Dalits]

{{Segregation by type|state=collapsed}}
{{Discrimination}}
{{Social class}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Caste| ]]
[[Category:Social status]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>