<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20071109034153|170251370" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="7257" pageid="7257" ns="0" title="Caste"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-11-11T18:44:55Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Caste Systems''' are traditional, [[hereditary]] systems of social classification, that evolved due to the enormous diversity in India (where all three primary races met, not by forced slavery but by immigration). This classification is based on [[endogamy]], [[wikt:occupation|occupation]], economic status, and [[ethnicity]]. 

In Hinduism, it it believed that there are multiple incarnations of God at various times to rescue earthly living-beings from the evil. In fact, there is freedom to worship any form of God to become Hindu. Likewise, there is no need to believe in caste-oriented classification to be a Hindu. This is proof enough to delink caste from Hinduism as a religion. It is just that many Hindus tend to conceive themselves in a caste-mold
(as well as in an econmic class mode as well as other inclusivistic molds and exclusivistic modes). So, caste is associated with Hindus but not with Hinduism. Caste is also associated with Christians and Muslims especially in Pakistan where less than 1% of the population is Hindu.

==Definitions==
{{Copyedit|section|date=August 2007}}
Caste is described by the Oxford English Dictionary as both, "each of the hereditary classes of Hindu society, distinguished by relative degrees of ritual purity or pollution and of social status," and, "any exclusive social class".&lt;ref&gt;http://www.askoxford.com/concise_oed/caste?view=uk&lt;/ref&gt; 

Although Hinduism is often now associated with the word caste, it was first used by the Portuguese to describe inherited class status in their own European society. 

Vedas and other Indian scriptures speak of 'Varna', classification of the human society in general based on 'guna', or personality traits, and 'Jati', or tribe. In "A New History of India," by Stanley Wolpert, "[s]uch a process of expansion, settled agricultural production, and pluralistic integration of new peoples led to the development of India's uniquely complex system of social organization, which was mistakenly labeled the caste system by the Portuguese. For what the Portuguese [...] called "caste" in the sixteenth century was, in fact the Rig Vedic "class" (varna) system of Brahmanas (priests), Kshastriyas (warriors), Vaishyas (merchants), and Shudras (artisans), whereas what Indians mean by caste is really a much more narrowly limited, endogamous group related by "birth" (jati)." It should be noted that the Vedic classification of a society is universal and is not limited to India. Further, the Vedic classification (varna categorization of society based on nature or profession) is actually non-hereditary, individual, and can be changed by learning or practice. The word jati (tribe) is used to describe any community, and not specific to any one religion. A person's jati (community or  tribe or caste) is the social group (with its own culture, religious practices, traditions, language, customs, regional origin, etc...) one is born into, and is hereditary. There are countless castes or communities (jatis) in India. Many communities were known for certain occupations. Before universal education, as in the rest of the world, job skills were often transferred within families and communities.  Those communities (jatis) known for a particular occupation or related occupations that could be categorized into one of the four varnas (priest, warrior, merchant/agriculturist, or artisan), were over time known as belonging to one of the four varnas. However, it should be noted that there are many Hindu religions in which animal sacrifices are common. The priests in those non-Brahminical temples, Christian churches and Islamic mosques do not belong to the vedic priest (Brahmin) class.  

A Caste's, or Jati's, association with a profession, or varna, can change with the chosen professions of it's members. Due to tribal, racial, religious and ethnic affiliations, one almost always married within the community one was born into. Each community governs itself without proselytizing, interfering or imposing their values on other communities, and this live and let live attitude is the main reason why so many communities were able to maintain their diversity while living among other communities in India. It should be noted that the word for Religion is "matam" in many Indian Languages including Sanskrit and Tamil. "Matam" means opinion. And Hinduism gave the right to opinion to everyone. This "live and let live attitude" is a direct result of the Hindu concept of "right to opinion/Matam" as are the numerous versions of God and the numerous religious texts some which even question the existence of God.

[[Cultural anthropology|Anthropologists]] use the term "caste" more generally, to refer to a social group that is [[Endogamy|endogamous]] and [[Profession|occupationally]] specialized; such groups are common in highly stratified societies with a very low degree of social mobility;{{Fact|date=January 2007}} that is to say, a caste system is one in which an individual's occupation and marriage prospects are determined by his or her birth and heritage. In its broadest sense, examples of caste-based societies include colonial [[Latin America]] under [[Spain|Spanish]] and [[Portugal|Portuguese]] rule (see [[Casta]]).
India was occupied by Islamic invaders from about 1000AD to  about 1700AD. They were replaced by European invaders,
mainly British, from about 1700AD to 1947AD. During that millennium no Muslim or European ruler ever enforced any privileges to the so called upper castes. They of course enforced special privileges to their own kind: Muslim invaders to Muslims and European invaders to Europeans.  Even after 700 years of Islamic suppression of India, India was one of the richest countries accounting for about 25% of world trade. India's current state of poverty was aggravated by the mercantilist economic model followed during much of Britain's rule, which saw little development of domestic industry. The caste system was in some ways reinforced under British rule as a means of stability and control, in other aspects it was suppressed. Today even many Hindus have come to believe that the Indian poverty is because of caste suppression and every caste demands reservation. 

==The Estates in Europe==
In medieval Europe, the [[estates of the realm]] were a caste system.

The population was divided into [[nobility]], [[clergy]], and the commoners. In some regions, the commoners were divided into burghers, peasants or [[serfs]], and the estateless.

Although originally based on occupation, one's estate was eventually inherited, because of low social mobility.

==Castes in Africa==
{{main|Caste system in Africa}}

Countries in Africa who have societies with caste systems within their borders include [[Mali]], [[Mauritania]], [[Senegal]], [[Gambia]], [[Guinea]], [[Guinea-Bissau]], [[Ivory Coast]], [[Niger]], [[Burkina Faso]], [[Cameroon]], [[Ghana]], [[Liberia]], [[Sierra Leone]], [[Algeria]], [[Nigeria]], [[Chad]], [[Ethiopia]] and [[Somalia]].

The Osu caste system in Nigeria and southern Cameroon are derived from indigenous religious beliefs and discriminate against the "Osus" people as "owned by deities" and outcasts.

Similarly, the Mande societies in Senegal, Gambia, Guinea, Sierra Leone, Liberia, Ivory Coast and Ghana have caste systems that divide society by occupation and ethnic ties.The Mande caste system regards the "Jonow" slave castes as inferior. Similarly, the Wolof caste system in Senegal is divided into three main groups, the Geer (freeborn/nobles), jaam (slaves and slave descendents) and the outcasted neeno (people of caste).

Other caste systems in Africa include the Borana caste system of NE [[Kenya]] with the Watta as the lowest caste, the "Ubuhake" castes in Rwanda and Burundi, and the [[Hutu]] undercastes in Rwanda who committed genocide on the [[Tutsi]] overlords in the now infamous [[Rwandan Genocide]].

==Balinese caste system==
{{main|Balinese caste system}}

The caste system in [[Bali]] is similar to the Indian caste system; however, India's caste system is far more complicated than Bali's, and there are only four Balinese castes:

*Sudras - peasants making up more than 90% of Bali's population 
*Wesias - the caste of merchants 
*Satrias - the warrior caste, it also included some nobility and kings 
*Brahmans - holy men and priests 

Different dialects of the [[Balinese language]] are used to address members of a different caste. 

The Balinese caste system has completely dissipated and is no longer in use due to the untouchable rebellion of 1649. Nonetheless, even though it is not written in law, most people still belong to the caste system.

==Castes in India==
{{main|Indian caste system|Reservations in India|Caste system among South Asian Muslims|Caste system among Indian Christians}}

===Caste system among Hindus===
{{main|Indian caste system}}

Caste in India mistakenly links two categories - the [[varna]] (class/group) and the [[jati]] ([[tribe]]). Prior to European colonization by Portugal and Britain, the Portuguese word caste was not used to describe the Hindu term Varna and the Indian term Jati in India. [[Varna]] as enunciated in the Hindu sacred scriptures of [[Vedas]] and the non-sacred [[Manusmriti]] text, seems to have categorised the people in the Indian society based on qualities and occupation.  It formed ideologies of identity and status and may have been open to a changing process of the coming and going of groups. Broadly speaking, the [[varnas]] are [[Brahmins]] (priests, scholars and teachers), [[Kshatriya]] (warriors and rulers), [[Vaisya]] (traders and agriculturists), and [[Sudra]] (manual workers) and the Untouchables. Brahmins have usually been described by the western orientalists as the priestly class, but this may not be very accurate. A temple priest need not have been a Brahmin, but a [[Yajna]] priest always was. The Greeks and the Muslims showed a better understanding when they described Brahmins as the Philosophers. The people who fell outside the four varna included the [[Dalit]]s (originally a part of Varna but fell out because they did not abide by the rules of soceity), [[adivasi]]s (because they were not a part of mainstream society), and foreigners (all were called Mlechhas), probably because they did not subscribe to Vedas and the rules and values of the Vedic society.
There were also the low class called the Untouchables.
Over time, it is thought, influenced by economic and social factors, the social ranking became a traditional, hereditary system of [[social stratification]]. It operated through thousands of endogamous groups,  termed ''[[jāti]]''. Though there were several kinds of variations across the breadth of India, the jati was the effective community within which one married and spent most of one's personal life. Often it was the community (jati) which one turned to for support and also the community (jati) which one sought to promote. The community (jati/tribe) system, usually with politically and economically derived hierarchies, has been followed across the Indian continent with regional variations across [[India]], [[Pakistan]], [[Bangladesh]] and [[Nepal]]. Different religious denominations have traditionally followed different kinds of community (jati) stratification that has nothing to do with their respective religion. With the assertion of "caste" identities under the British empire, communities (jatis) sought to place themselves within varna and mobility in reference to it was not uncommon. [[Sanskritization]] is an example of this. While the prevalence of the community (jati) social ranking has declined significantly over the course of the twentieth century, remote and rural areas of the subcontinent continue to subscribe to community ranking. Contrary to popular belief, historically there was a great deal of mobility and intermingling between Indian communities, and among Hindu varna categories, other than Brahmins, largely based on economic or political status of the concerned group. While community (jati) endogamy remains quite strong and though a diverse and rich range of communities is healthy and valuable, ongoing linking of communities to a particular social status is perhaps the biggest obstacle to the process of dissolution of inherited social status. However, one significant blow to inherited social status in India came about with the abolition of royalty when India gained its independence from the British Empire. Ironically, India is in this regard ahead of several democratic European countries that still have kings, queens, princes, princesses, including its former colonial master Britain. The remaining struggle in India is to separate the rest of the communities regardless of the religion they follow from any social rank, while allowing for the uniqueness of each community.

The Vedic priests were enjoined by their scriptures and texts, including the [[Manusmriti]], to live in poverty and to shun possessions and temporal power and to instead devote themselves to the study and teaching of scriptures and other knowledge, to pure conduct, and to spiritual growth. In fact, they usually subsisted on alms from the rest of the society, including from those in the Shudra varna. This is an important point in understanding the difference between caste and class, which are usually equated in the westernised mind, with concepts of economic hierarchies and dominating power structures deeply embedded in its world-view and belief systems&lt;ref name="Ghurye"&gt; G.S. Ghurye (1969)-Caste and Race in India, Popular Prakashan, Mumbai 1969 (1932)and Dirk "Castes of Mind" [http://press.princeton.edu/titles/7191.html online]&lt;/ref&gt; 

"Caste" became an important element of Indian politics after the British imperialists used "caste"-based classifications as the basis of classifying the colonized Indian population, especially the Hindus, in the population censuses of late 19th Century. This became more specific in the 1901 Census, because the Indian population, not being aware of what the Brahmins thought of them, by and large did not understand what was meant by "caste" and gave their occupation, religion, education, etc. as their "caste".&lt;ref name="Ghurye"/&gt;. This time the census enumerators insisted on slotting the population into the four varna categories, even if it meant a loose fit. Thus the British succeeded in melding the empirical reality of jatis (communities) with the Brahmin's theoretical construct of varna (categorization of occupations), as "caste"(inherited social status), causing the popular modern perception of Indian society having been "always" divided into the four "hereditary" "caste" groups from "time immemorial".

Some activists consider that the "caste" (tribes and jatis) is a form of [[racial discrimination]].&lt;ref name="npr"&gt;[http://www.npr.org/programs/specials/racism/010828.caste.html An Untouchable Subject?]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hri.ca/racism/Submitted/Theme/castedeclaration.shtml Final Declaration of the Global Conference Against Racism and Caste-based Discrimination]&lt;/ref&gt; This allegation has been rejected by many sociologists such as [[Andre Béteille]], who writes that treating caste as a form of racism is "politically mischievous" and worse, "scientifically nonsense" since there is no discernible difference in the racial characteristics between [[Brahmins]] and [[Scheduled Castes]] such as the [[jatav]]. He writes that "Every social group cannot be regarded as a race simply because we want to protect it against prejudice and discrimination".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hinduonnet.com/2001/06/03/stories/13030611.htm Discrimination that must be cast away],''The Hindu''&lt;/ref&gt;

The Indian government denies the claims of equivalency between Caste and Racial discrimination, pointing out that the issues of social status is essentially intra-racial and intra-cultural.The view of the "caste" system as "static and unchanging" has been disputed. Sociologists describe how the perception of the "caste" system as a static and textual stratification has given way to the perception of the "caste" system as a more processual, emprical and contextual stratification. Others have applied theoretical models to explain mobility and flexibility in the "caste system" in India.&lt;ref name="Silverberg Paper"&gt;{{cite journal
|author = James Silverberg
|date = November 1969
|year = 1969
|month = Nov
|title = Social Mobility in the Caste System in India: An Interdisciplinary Symposium
|journal = The American Journal of Sociology
|volume = 75
|issue = 3
|pages = 443-444
}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to these scholars, groups of lower-caste individuals could seek to elevate the status of their caste by attempting to emulate the practices of higher castes.

Sociologist [[M. N. Srinivas]] has also debated the question of rigidity in Caste.&lt;ref&gt;Srinivas, M.N, Religion and Society among the Coorgs of South India by MN Srinivas, Page 32 (Oxford, 1952)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Caste in Modern India; And other essays: Page 48. (Media Promoters &amp; Publishers Pvt. Ltd, Bombay; First Published: 1962, 11th Reprint: 1994)&lt;/ref&gt; For details see [[sanskritization]].

In the Chandogya Upanishad, Satyakama (the illegitimate, varnasankra, son of a Shudra woman who did not even remember who her son's father was) went on to be accepted and educated for as a Brahmin (the Gita: Ch. 18 - verse 42). This shows that the people (including the Shudra and of unknown lineage) had the choice of pursuing any occupation (even that of a Brahmin). 

In the Mahabharata, Satyavati (a Shudra-girl whose father was a fisherman), when presented with a marriage proposal from king Shantanu, married him only after he accepted her pre-nuptial agreement. Her own children, in stead of another older heir to the throne, went on to inherit the Kshatriya kingdom as was demanded in the pre-nuptial agreement. This indicates that the intercaste marriages and exchanges were quite prevalent; and that the women and Shudras could make free choices even when there was royalty involved. 

For more such incidences see http://www.geocities.com/lamberdar/_caste.html

===Caste system among Indian Christians===
{{main|Caste system among Indian Christians}}
That some converts to Christianity have retained the old caste practices establishes that caste system is inherent to no religion in particular but rather a socio-economic demarcation with potential discriminatory practices.  In particular, [[Catholic]] [[Dalit]] Christians in certain parts of India are regarded as an undercaste by upper-caste [[Catholic]] Christian clergy, nuns, and Hindus and are discriminated against in society. 

In fact even non-converts are segregated in Christianity. In the United States (where like in India all three primary races Mangoloids, Caucusoids and Negroids met), the historically suppressed Blacks still go to separate Black Churches.

=== Modern status of the caste system ===

The inherited social status is gradually relaxing, especially in metropolitan and other major urban areas, due to higher penetration of high education, co-existence of all communities and lesser knowledge about caste system due to alienation with rural roots of people.  But in the countryside and small towns, this system is still very rigid. However, the total elimination of caste system seems distant, if ever possible, due to [[caste politics in India|caste politics]].

The [[Government of India]] has officially documented castes and subcastes, primarily to determine those deserving [[Reservation in India|reservation]] ([[positive discrimination]] in education and jobs) through the [[census]].  The Indian reservation system relies entirely on [[quotas]]. The Government lists consist of Scheduled Castes, Scheduled Tribes and [[Other Backward Classes]]:

;Scheduled castes (SC)
:[[Scheduled castes]] generally consist of former "untouchables" (the term "[[Dalit]]" is now preferred). Present population is 16% of total population of India i.e. around 160 million. For example, the Delhi state has 49 castes listed as SC.&lt;ref name="DelhiGovt"&gt;[http://www.delhigovt.nic.in/dept/district/anx25.pdf List of Scheduled Castes] Delhi Govt.&lt;/ref&gt;

;Scheduled tribes (ST)
:[[Scheduled tribes]] generally consist of tribal groups. Present population is 8% of total population of India i.e. around 80 million.

;Other Backward Classes (OBC)
:The [[Mandal Commission]] covered more than 3000 castes under OBC Category and stated that OBCs form around 52% of the Indian population. However, the National Sample Survey puts the figure at 32%.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tribuneindia.com/2006/20060611/main2.htm Reply to SC daunting task for government], ''Tribune India''&lt;/ref&gt; There is substantial debate over the exact number of OBCs in India. It is generally estimated to be sizable, but many believe that it is lower than the figures quoted by either the Mandal Commission and the National Sample Survey.&lt;ref&gt;[http://in.news.yahoo.com/060524/43/64i2a.html What is India's population of other backward classes?],''Yahoo News''&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Reservation in India|caste-based reservations]] in India has led to wide-spread protests, with many complaining of [[reverse discrimination]] against the forward castes.

=== Caste politics ===
{{main|Caste politics in India}}

[[Mahatma Gandhi]], [[B. R. Ambedkar]] and [[Jawaharlal Nehru]] had radically different approaches to caste esp. over constitutional politics and the status of "untouchables".&lt;ref name="caste_aditya_nigam"&gt;{{cite web
|title=Book review of Caste, Society and Politics in India: From the Eighteenth Century to the Modern Age
|author=Danny Yee
|url=http://dannyreviews.com/h/Caste_India.html
|accessdate=2006-12-11
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Till the mid-[[1970s]], the politics of independent India was largely dominated by economic issues and questions of corruption.  But since the [[1980s]],  caste has emerged as a major issue in the [[Politics of India]].&lt;ref name="caste_aditya_nigam"&gt;{{cite web
|title=Caste Politics in India
|author=Aditya Nigam
|url=http://www.southasianmedia.net/Magazine/Journal/castepolitics_india.htm
|accessdate=2006-12-11
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Mandal Commission]] was established in 1979 to "identify the socially or educationally backward",&lt;ref name="Bhattacharya"&gt; Bhattacharya, Amit. {{cite web|url=http://www.theotherindia.org/caste/who-are-the-obcs.html|title="Who are the OBCs?"|accessdate=2006-04-19}} ''Times of India'', April 8, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; and to consider the question of [[Reservation in India|seat reservations and quotas]] for people to redress caste discrimination.  In [[1980]], the commission's report affirmed the [[affirmative action]] practice under Indian law whereby members of lower castes were given exclusive access to a certain portion of government jobs and slots in public universities.  When [[V. P. Singh]] Government tried to implement the recommendations of the [[Mandal Commission]] in 1989, massive protests were held throughout the country.  Many alleged that the politicians were trying to benefit personally from caste-based reservations for purely pragmatic electoral purposes.

Many political parties in [[India]] have openly indulged in caste-based [[votebank]] politics. Parties such as [[Bahujan Samaj Party]] (BSP), the [[Samajwadi Party]] and the [[Janata Dal]] claim that they are representing the backward castes, and rely primarily on OBC support, often in alliance with Dalit and Muslim support to win the elections.&lt;ref name="country_studies_caste"&gt;{{cite web
|title=Caste-Based Parties
|url=http://countrystudies.us/india/116.htm
|publisher= Country Studies US
|accessdate=2006-12-12
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Castes in Japan==
{{main|Burakumin}}

Japan historically subscribed to a feudal caste system. While modern law has officially abolished the caste hierarchy, there are reports of discrimination against the [[Buraku]] or [[Burakumin]] undercastes, historically referred to by the insulting term "Eta".&lt;ref&gt;http://www.hrdc.net/sahrdc/hrfeatures/HRF39.htm&lt;/ref&gt; Studies comparing the caste systems in India and Japan have been performed, with similar discriminations against the Burakumin as the [[Dalit]]s. The Burakumin are regarded as "ostracized".&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite journal
 | author = William H. Newell
 | year = 1961
 | month = December
 | title = The Comparative Study of Caste in India and Japan 
 | journal = Asian Survey
 | volume = 1
 | issue = 10
 | pages = 3-10
 | url = http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0004-4687(196112)1%3A10%3C3%3ATCSOCI%3E2.0.CO%3B2-F
 }}
&lt;/ref&gt; The burakumin are one of the main [[demographics of Japan|minority groups in Japan]], along with the [[Ainu people|Ainu]] of [[Hokkaidō]] and [[Zainichi Korean|residents of Korean]] and [[Chinese in Japan|Chinese]] descent.

==Castes in Korea==
With the unification of the three kingdoms in the seventh century and the foundation of the Koryo dynasty in the Middle Ages, Koreans systemized its own native caste system.  At the top was the two official classes, the YANGBAN.  Yangban means "two classes".  It was composed of scholars (Munban) and warriors (Muban). Within the Yangban class, the Scholars (Munban) enjoyed a significant social advantage over the warrior (Muban) class, until the Muban Rebellion in 1170. Muban ruled Korea under successive Warrior Leaders until the Mongol Conquest in 1253.  SAM BYUL CHO, the private Army of the ruling Choe dynasty, carried on the struggle against the Mongols until 1273, when they were finally wiped out to the last man in Chejudo.  With the destruction of the warrior class, the Munban gained ascendancy.  In 1392, with the foundation of Joseon dynasty, the full ascendancy of munban over muban was final.  With the establishment of Confucianism as the state philosophy of Joseon, the Muban would never again gain its former social standing in Korean society.

Beneath the Yangban class were the Jung-in. They were the technicians.  They served in lower level government bureaucracy.  They were literate, yet were unable to rise into full bureaucratic positions despite passing the gwageo (central government entrance) exam.  This class was small and specialized.

Beneath the Jung-in were the Chun min.  They were the landless peasants.  These people composed the majority of Korean society until the 1600s.  They were illiterate, and forbidden from marrying into the Yangban class.  During the Japanese invasion of 1592, as many government genealogical record was burnt, many of them fabricated their social origin and moved into the Yangban class.  With the Manchu invasion in the 1627 and 1637 and numerous peasant rebellions that followed, the ranks of Yangban families swelled up to more than 60% of the whole country by the late 1800s.

Beneath the Chun min were the Sang min, also called Ssangnom in the vernacular. These were the servant class.   

Underneath them all were the Baekjeong.  The meaning today is that of butcher.  They originate from the Khitan invasion of Korea in the 900s.  As they were defeated, instead of sending them back to Manchuria, The Goryeo government retianed them as warriors, spread out throughout Korea.  As they were nomads skilled in hunting and tanning of leather, their skill was initially valued by Koreans.  Over the centuries, their foreign origins were forgotten, and were only remembered as butchers and tanners.

With Gabo reform of 1896, the caste system of Korea was officially abolished.  However, the Yangban families carried on traditional education and formal mannerisms into the 20th century.  With the "democratization" of 1990s in South Korea, remnant of such mannerisms and classism is now heavily frowned upon in the South Korean society, replaced by the myth of egalitarianism.  However, with rampant capitalism, a new aristocracy is slowly developing, caused by a major gap in income among the people of Korea, with the resulting differences in education and mannerism.

{{main|Baekjeong}}
The ''baekjeong'' were an "[[untouchable]]" outcaste group of [[Korea]], often compared with the [[burakumin]] of [[Japan]] and the [[dalit (outcaste)|dalit]]s of [[India]] and [[Nepal]]. The term ''baekjeong'' itself means "a butcher", but later changed into "common citizens" to change the caste system so that the system would be without untouchables. In the early part of the [[Goryeo]] period (918 - 1392), the outcaste groups were largely settled in fixed communities. However, the Mongol invasion left Korea in disarray and [[anomie]], and these groups began to become [[nomad]]ic. Other subgroups of the baekjeong are the ''chaein'' and the ''hwachae''.{{Fact|date=September 2007}} During the Joseon dynasty, they were specific professions like basket weaving and performing executions. They were also considered in moral violation of Buddhist principles, which lead Koreans to see work involving meat as polluting and sinful, even if they saw the consumption as acceptable.

The opening of Korea to foreign Christian missionary activity in the late 19th century saw some improvement in the status of the ''baekjeong''; However, everyone was not equal under the Christian congregation, and protests erupted when missionaries attempted to integrate them into worship services, with non-''baekjeong'' finding such an attempt insensitive to traditional notions of hierarchical advantage.{{Fact|date=September 2007}} Also around the same time, the baekjeong began to resist the open social discrimination that existed against them.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|chapter=In Search of Human Rights: The Paekchŏng Movement in Colonial Korea|title=Colonial Modernity in Korea|first=Joong-Seop|last=Kim|editor=Gi-Wook Shin and Michael Robinson|year=1999|pages=326}}&lt;/ref&gt; hey focused on social and economic injustices affecting the baekjeong, hoping to create an [[egalitarianism|egalitarian]] Korean society. Their efforts included attacking social discrimination by the upper class, authorities, and "commoners" and the use of degrading language against children in public schools.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The Korean Paekjŏng under Japanese rule: the quest for equality and human rights|first=Joong-Seop|last=Kim|year=2003|pages=147}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Castes in Latin America==
{{main|Casta}}
{{Expand-section|date=January 2007}}
Many [[Latin American]] countries have caste systems based on classification by race and race mixture.  An entire nomenclature developed, including the familiar terms "mulato", "[[mestizo]]", and "zambo" (whence "[[Sambo (racial term)|sambo]]").  The caste system was imposed during colonial rule by the Spanish who had practiced a form of caste system in Spain prior to the expulsion of the Jews and Muslims. While many Latin American countries have long since rendered the system officially illegal through legislation, usually at the time of independence from Spain, prejudice based on degrees of perceived racial distance from Spanish ancestry combined with one's socioeconomic status remain, an echo of the colonial caste system. The United States and many Caribbean countries also share similar caste hierarchies based on race and race mixture. &lt;ref&gt;http://www.zonalatina.com/Zldata55.htm &lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0002-8762(197112)76%3A5%3C1626%3ARACILA%3E2.0.CO%3B2-6 &lt;/ref&gt;

==Nepalese caste system==
{{main|Nepalese caste system}}
The Nepalese caste system resembles that of the Indian [[Jāti]] system with numerous Jāti divisions with a Varna system superimposed.

==Caste system in Pakistan==
{{main|Caste system among South Asian Muslims}}
{{Expand-section|date=February 2007}}
A caste system similar to that in [[Indian caste system#Caste System among Indian Muslims|India]] is practiced in [[Pakistan]], although with wide variability since the concept of caste is not actually recognized in [[Islam]]. In the absence of "classical" castes, typically the proxies used are ethnic background ([[Sindhi people|Sindhi]], [[Punjabi]], [[Pusthun]], [[Balochi]], Mohajir etc.), tribal affiliations and religious denominations or sects (Sunni, Shia, Ahmadiyya, Ismaili, Christian, Hindu etc.).

While caste/social stratification information can be found relating to specific areas in Pakistan, it is not known if any studies have compared how relatively prevalent such attitudes are amongst the various ethnic groups, religious sects and geographies. Also, it is not known if any tracking studies have documented changes in these social attitudes.

Anecdotal evidence seems to suggest that there are quite significant differences in how social stratification is practised within, and between, the various ethnic/religious groups in Pakistan.
 
The social stratification among Muslims in the "Swat" area of North Pakistan has been meaningfully compared to the Caste system in India. The society is rigidly divided into subgroups where each Quom (meaning tribe or nation) is assigned a profession. Different Quoms are not permitted to intermarry or live in the same community.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite book
  | last = Leach
  | first = Edmund Ronald
  | authorlink = E.R. Leach 
  | title = Aspects of Caste in South India, Ceylon and North-West Pakistan (Pg 113)
  | publisher =  Cambridge University Press
  | date = [[November 24]], [[1971]]
  }}
&lt;/ref&gt;
These Muslims practice a ritual-based system of social stratification. The Quoms who deal with human emissions are ranked the lowest.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
  | last = Leach
  | first = Edmund Ronald
  | authorlink = E.R. Leach 
  | title = Aspects of Caste in South India, Ceylon and North-West Pakistan (Pg 113)
  | publisher =  Cambridge University Press
  | date = [[November 24]], [[1971]]
  }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Caste system in Pakistan creates sectarian divides and strong issues along similar lines to those divides seen in [[India]]. Lower castes are often severely persecuted by the upper castes. Lower castes are denied privileges in many communities and violence is committed against them. A particularly infamous example of such incidents is that of [[Mukhtaran Mai]] in Pakistan, a low caste woman who was gang raped by upper caste men.&lt;ref&gt;http://archives.cnn.com/2002/WORLD/asiapcf/south/08/31/pakistan.gang.rape/ &lt;/ref&gt; In addition, educated Pakistani women from the lower castes are often persecuted by the higher castes for attempting to break the shackles of the restrictive system (that traditionally denied education to the lower castes, particularly the women). A recent example of this is the case of Ghazala Shaheen, a low caste Muslim woman in Pakistan who, in addition to getting a higher education, had an uncle who eloped with a woman of a high caste family. She was accosted and gang-raped by the upper-caste family. The chances of any legal action are low due to the Pakistani Government's inability to repeal the [[Hudood ordinance]] against women in Pakistan,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.timesonline.co.uk/article/0,,2089-2372124,00.html Pakistani graduate raped to punish her low-caste family] The Sunday Times - September 24, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; though, in [[2006]], Pakistan president [[Pervez Musharraf]] proposed laws against Hudood making rape a punishable offense,&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/south_asia/6178214.stm Pakistan senate backs rape bill],''BBC''&lt;/ref&gt; which were ratified by the Pakistani senate. The law is meeting considerable opposition from the [[Islamist]] parties in Pakistan, who insist that amending the laws to make them more civilized towards women is against the mandate of Islamic religious law.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/south_asia/6152520.stm Strong feelings over Pakistan rape laws],''BBC''&lt;/ref&gt; 

The late [[Nawab Akbar Bugti]] a freedom-fighter for the [[Balochistan Liberation Army]] fighting for secession from Pakistan, criticised Punjabi attitudes to women when he said, "What respect we give to a woman, irrespective of her caste, religion or ethnicity, no Punjabi can understand."&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.atimes.com/atimes/South_Asia/GA15Df07.html Tribals looking down a barrel in Balochistan] &lt;/ref&gt;

==Sri Lankan caste system==
{{main|Caste in Sri Lanka}}

==Castes in Yemen==

In [[Yemen]] there exists a caste like system that keeps [[Al-Akhdam]] [[social group]] as the perennial manual workers for the society through practices that mirror untouchability.&lt;ref name="ymirror"&gt;[http://www.yemenmirror.com/index.php?action=showDetails&amp;id=136 Akhdam: Ongoing suffering for lost identity ''Yemen Mirror'']&lt;/ref&gt; Al-Akhdam (literally "servants" with Khadem as plural) is the lowest rung in the Yemeni caste system and by far the poorest. According to official estimates in Yemen, the total number of Khadem countywide is in the neighbourhood of 500,000, some 100,000 of which live in the outskirts of the capital Sana'a. The remainder are dispersed mainly in and around the cities of Aden, Taiz, Lahj, Abyan, Hodeidah and Mukalla.&lt;ref name="irin"&gt;[http://www.irinnews.org/report.asp?ReportID=49867&amp;SelectRegion=Middle_East&amp;SelectCountry=YEMEN YEMEN: Akhdam people suffer history of discrimination],'''irinnews.org'''&lt;/ref&gt;

===Origins===
The Khadem are not members of the three castes--Bedouin (nomads), fellahin (villagers), and hadarrin (townspeople)--that comprise mainstream Arab society.&lt;ref name="irin"/&gt;They are believed to be of Ethiopian ancestry. Some sociologists theorize that the Khadem are descendants of Ethiopian soldiers who had occupied Yemen in the 5th century but were driven out in the 6th century. According to this theory the al-Akhdham are descended from the soldiers who stayed behind and were forced into menial labor as a punitive measure.&lt;ref name="irin"/&gt;

===Discrimination===
The Khadem live in small shanty towns and are marginalized and shunned by mainstream society in Yemen. The Khadem slums exist mostly in big cities, including the capital, Sana'a. Their segregated communities have poor housing conditions. As a result of their low position in society, very few children in the Khadem community are enrolled in school&lt;ref name="irin"/&gt; and often have little choice but to beg for money and intoxicate themselves with crushed glass.&lt;ref name="Abadjian"&gt;[http://www.countercurrents.org/hr-marguerite250404.htm Caste In Yemen] by Marguerite Abadjian,''Countercurrents.org'' archive of ''The Baltimore Sun''&lt;/ref&gt; A traditional [[Arabic]] saying in the region goes: "Clean your plate if it is touched by a dog, but break it if it's touched by a Khadem".&lt;ref name="irin"/&gt; Though conditions have improved somewhat over the past few years, the Khadem are still stereotyped by mainstream Yemenese society, considering them lowly, dirty, ill-mannered and immoral.&lt;ref name="Abadjian"/&gt;

Many NGO's and charitable organizations from other countries such as CARE International are working towards their emancipation. The Yemenese government denies that there is any discrimination against the Khadem.&lt;ref name="ymirror"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.yementimes.com/99/iss01/l&amp;d.htm ''Yemen Times'']&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Elitism]]
*[[Social stratification]]
*[[Feudal society]]
*[[Class society]]
*[[Reservations in India]]
*[[Forward Castes]]
*[[Backward-caste Hindu Saints]]
*[[Backward-caste Hindu Warriors]]
*[[Varnas|Varna]]
*[[Water Dynasty]]

==Notes==
{{reflist}}

==References==
* ''Spectres of Agrarian Territory'' by David Ludden [[December 11]], [[2001]]
* "Early Evidence for Caste in South India", p. 467-492 in ''Dimensions of Social Life: Essays in honor of David G. Mandelbaum'', Edited by Paul Hockings and Mouton de Gruyter, Berlin, New York, Amsterdam, 1987.

==External links==
*[http://usjesus.com/jesusindia.aspx] Caste System in 2007
*[http://www.shastras.org a Hindu group eliminating Caste discrimination]
*[http://www.hinduwisdom.info/Caste_System.htm Caste system in India.]
*[http://www.anti-caste.org/ '''The Anti-Caste Information Page'''///] On caste, communalism, and class struggle.
*[http://www.tamilnation.org/caste/ Caste &amp; the Tamil Nation - Brahmins, Non Brahmins &amp; Dalits]
* [http://www.murnis.com/culture/articlenamestitlesandcaste.htm Caste system in Bali]
*[http://www.imadr.org/tokyo/ishikawareport.html Rights Activists and Rights Violations:  the Burakumin case in Japan]
*[http://www.hrdc.net/sahrdc/hrfeatures/HRF39.htm Caste, Ethnicity and Nationality]:Japan Finds Plenty of Space for Discrimination
*[http://jbe.gold.ac.uk/7/alldritt001.html The Burakumin] The Complicity of Japanese Buddhism in Oppression and an Opportunity for Liberation
*[http://www.irinnews.org/report.asp?ReportID=49867&amp;SelectRegion=Middle_East&amp;SelectCountry=YEMEN YEMEN: Akhdam people suffer history of discrimination]IRIN News.org
*[http://www.countercurrents.org/hr-marguerite250404.htm Caste In Yemen] by Marguerite Abadjian (Archive of the Baltimore Sun)
*[http://www.indiatogether.org/society/caste.htm India Together on Caste]
*[http://www.breakingranks.net/weblog/rankism Rankism: A Social Disorder]
*[http://www.hindu-international.org/books/articles/varna_jaati_or_caste.pdf Varna Ashram and Hindu Scriptures (pdf)]
* [http://codesign.scu.edu/hinduism/ The Caste System in India]
* [http://atributetohinduism.com/Caste_System.htm Jati system in India]
*''Articles on Caste by [[Koenraad Elst]]:'' [http://koenraadelst.bharatvani.org/books/wiah/ch1.htm#16a Caste in India], [http://koenraadelst.bharatvani.org/books/wiah/ch11.htm#49a Buddhism and Caste], [http://koenraadelst.bharatvani.org/books/wiah/ch9.htm#78a Indian tribals and Caste],
* [http://koenraadelst.bharatvani.org/books/ait/ch49.htm Physical anthropology and Caste], [http://koenraadelst.bharatvani.org/books/ait/ch48.htm#68a Etymology of Varna]	 	
*[http://www.epw.org.in/showArticles.php?root=2003&amp;leaf=11&amp;filename=6474&amp;filetype=html Is Caste System Intrinsic to Hinduism?]
*[http://www.tamilnation.org/caste/ Caste &amp; the Tamil Nation - Brahmins, Non Brahmins &amp; Dalits]
*[http://www.geocities.com/lamberdar/_caste.html Hindu Caste System &amp; Hinduism: Vedic vocations (Hindu castes) were not related to heredity (birth)] 	 	
*[http://india.krishna.org/Articles/2000/07/00057.html ISKCON view of caste and behavior]
*[http://padmanayakavelama.googlepages.com Information about Velama Caste]	
*[http://www.maanojrakhit.com/e_book11_varn_system_text.htm These documented Results of 4-Varn system can make you Proud of your Hindu heritage]
*[http://velamahistoricleaders.googlepages.com/velama Historic Leaders of Velama Caste]

[[Category:Caste|*]]
[[Category:Sociology]]
[[Category:Social divisions]]

[[bg:Каста]]
[[cs:Kastovní systém]]
[[de:Kaste]]
[[es:Casta (hinduismo)]]
[[eo:Kasto]]
[[fa:کاست]]
[[fr:Caste]]
[[hr:Kaste]]
[[id:Kasta]]
[[it:Casta]]
[[he:קאסטה]]
[[lt:Varna (luomas)]]
[[ms:Sistem kasta]]
[[nl:Kaste]]
[[ja:カースト]]
[[no:Kaste]]
[[nn:Kaste]]
[[pl:System kastowy]]
[[pt:Casta]]
[[ru:Каста]]
[[sr:Каста]]
[[sh:Kaste]]
[[fi:Kastilaitos]]
[[sv:Kast]]
[[ta:சாதி]]
[[tr:Kast sistemi]]
[[zh:种姓制度]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>