<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20041106021402|7251276" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="7257" pageid="7257" ns="0" title="Caste"><revisions><rev timestamp="2004-11-09T08:22:50Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{merge}} [[Varna (caste)]]

'''''Caste''''' is derived from a [[Portuguese language|Portuguese]] word for lineage, breed or race, ''casta''.  The term caste when used in human [[culture]] is usually in conjunction with the social division in [[Hindu]] society, particularly in [[India]].  This term is also used in [[entomology]] to describe [[social insect]]s species who have a specific sub-type of which is specialised in a certain task.  For example, social insects like [[ant]]s [[bee]]s and [[termite]]s have caste divisions of queen {specilization in reproduction) and worker (specialization in food gathering).

[[cultural anthropology|Anthropologists]] use the term more generally to refer to a social group that is [[Endogamy|endogamous]] and [[Profession|occupationally]] specialised; such groups are common in highly stratified societies with a very low degree of social mobility.  Broadly understood, [[South Africa]] during the era of [[apartheid]], the practice of [[slavery]] in the [[antebellum]] South of the [[United States]] through the [[American Civil Rights Movement|Civil Rights movement]], colonial [[Latin America]] under [[Spain|Spanish]] and Portuguese rule, and [[India]] prior to 1947 were all caste-based societies.

==Primary Hindu Castes==

The caste system, although not officially sanctioned by their governments, is used by [[Hindu]]s in [[India]] and [[Nepal]].  It is based on four ''[[Varna (caste)|varnas]]'' (meaning "colours"):

*'''''[[Brahmin]]s''''' ([[white]]), [[priest]]s

*'''''[[Kshatriya]]s''''' ([[red]]), [[warrior]]s

*'''''[[Vaishya]]s''''' ([[yellow]]), [[merchant]]s/[[Craftsman|craftsmen]]

*'''''[[Shudra]]s''''' ([[blue]]), [[worker]]s

The varna system is based on division on labor. The colors are based upon the daily activities of each group. The Brahmin wears white because he performs various sacrifices and has to be clean. Any impurities will show on the white clothing. The Kshatriya warriors wear red because they see a lot of blood and wounds as they practice their daily warrior routines. The Vaishya traders handle items like turmeric and other spices and they wear yellow because it masks the colour. The Shudras wear blue because the color blue was more appropriate for the work environment.

== Caste and its origins ==
Indian texts also speak of [[jati]], which are communities. Each varna is further subdivided into many jatis. Each varna has its appropriate rules of conduct, or "dharma", including rules regarding [[marriage]], [[Food|eating]], and physical proximity. The four varnas are psychological categories that are supposed to be present in each individual. 

In the ''[[Manusmriti]]'' it is asserted that there are only four varnas, which leads one to the conclusion that the formation of the ''outcaste'' groups may have been a consequence of the [[Buddhist]] [[injunction]] against professions dealing with animal-killing. Support for this view comes from the fact that similar [[outcaste]] groups have existed in [[Japan]], [[Korea]], and [[China]]. However, this seems a stretched comparison to some since the Manusmriti itself condemns the eating of animal flesh, stating that non-[[vegetarian]]s will come back in later lives to be killed by the very beings they killed and ate in former lives.

The caste system originated in nomenclature and was changed through the influence of a powerful elite into an enforced system. Indeed, the [[Dharmashastra]]s (which are collections of Hindu codes and laws) say that caste is not determined by birth but by action in [[life]]. One must also keep in mind that since the dawn of [[Vedanta]] and with the increase of [[Tantric]]s of the [[Shiva]]-[[Shakti]] variety many [[Vedic]]-rooted people (i.e. Hindus) rejected the stratified and corrupted version of [[varna-ashram]] that became caste. On the other hand, caste still retained a significant influence on modern Hindu society. 

Brahmin (priest), Kshatriya (warrior, [[nobility]]), Vaishya (large group of ordinary workers, merchants, [[businessmen]], etc.) and Shudras ([[menial worker]]s, [[janitor]]s, sweepers, etc.) were the four varnas. Each varna was said to possess certain characteristics: i.e. the shudra was often someone with a violent temper, crude tongue, given to [[intoxicant]]s, not loving of [[God]]; the Vaishya was hardworking, dutiful but given to avarice and while believing in God, was not spiritually inclined. The Kshatriya was noble, learned and beyond all, selfless, his or her duty being the administration of the people and fighting of [[battle]]s against intruders; often very spiritually inclined. The Brahmin was kind, loving, was the society's storehouse (especially when scriptures were memorized) of the ancient scriptures, the performer of rituals, a lover of God and the most spiritually advanced member of a community. 

Thus, one sees that the original conception of caste was that people who acted a certain way, fell into a certain category. If one were born into a Brahmin family, but drank and had no respect for one's fellow living beings and God, one was simply not a Brahmin. This view is supported by a reading of the Bhagavad Gita which held that caste was a function of practice, rather than based on birth. It is worthy to note that all three acharayas, [[Sankara]], [[Ramanuja]], and [[Madhva]] all subscribed to this view. The lives of great Vaishnavite saints such as [[Kanaka Dasa]] and [[Tukaram]] demonstrated that single-minded devotion to God was the sole criteria for Him, not birth.

Regarding caste, the ''Indian History Sourcebook'' writes:

:43. But in consequence of the omission of the sacred rites, and of their not consulting Brahmanas, the following tribes of Kshatriyas have gradually sunk in this world to the condition of Sudras; 

:44. (Viz.) the Paundrakas, the Kodas, the Dravidas, the Kambogas, the Yavanas, the Sakas, the Paradas, the Pahlavas, the Kinas, the Kiratas, and the Daradas.) 

:''Indian History Sourcebook: The Laws of Manu'', c. 1500 BCE, translated by G. Buhler

It was considered highly auspicious if someone had the good fortune to be born into a Brahmin family and then, following the family tradition, established oneself as a Brahmin by actually living the life of a Brahmin. Hence, the term twice-born, or dvija. Clearly it is far easier to move down than up the ladder of caste. 

One sees in scriptural descriptions of caste another motivation: it was a way of explaining the natural inequalities into which all human societies are necessarily born. It was the unhappy truth that some people were born into poor families, or in the [[slum]]s, and others into the families of holy men. Explaining to people in clear terms that the natural processes of life and [[death]], [[reincarnation]], led to certain circumstances with which one was confronted. Thus, the varnas were a good way of helping people who had no chance of being warriors or priests, due to their upbringing or native intelligence/ability, to live happily within their life and feel good about attaining God through proper adherence to their own dharma (overall duties). 

Over and over again, the [[Upanishad]]s and other great texts spoke to the nature of caste being a mere name and not defining who one was. Calling someone a Vaishya was supposed to be like calling someone a blue-collar worker today. There is the Upanishadic story of a boy who went to a [[guru]] to learn the Hindu scriptures. His guru asked him what his caste was. Consulting his mother, who was actually a [[prostitute]] and didn't really know what her caste by birth was, the boy returned to the guru and responded that he was all castes. He worshipped the Gods, thus fulfilling the duties that are ordinarily a Brahmin's, he earned his keep like a Vaishya, took care of cleaning the house, like a Shudra, and protected his family's interest like a Kshatriya. The guru was pleased and told the boy he was fit to be taught and initiated into the Brahmin's life. However the very fact that the boy had to refer to his birth to determine his caste as a first step indicates that caste was determined by birth even from the most ancient of times. The default caste of a person was always determined by birth.

The established Brahmins, whose duty it was to act as gurus (teachers) for new generations of Brahmins, by culling those worthy of Brahminhood from all the young boys of the society, began discriminating based on caste. This practice began to become more ingrained, and social mobility became a thing of the past but for in a few areas of India. Even today, however, in the most traditional of circles, sanyassis (renunciates of the world) are given the utmost respect, as it is said that by leaving human society, they leave behind their distinctive social characteristics, including caste. 

The Hindu tantrics are a part of Hinduism whose scriptural texts, the Agamic strand known collectively as the [[Tantra]]s, assert their descent from the [[Veda]]s, especially the [[Atharva-Veda]]. Claiming that the Vedic rituals no longer applied to [[Kali Yuga]], the fourth and final age of humanity in Hinduism that sees morality ebb to complete dissolution until the end of the earth, the Tantrics see themselves as natural continuations of the Vedas through Hindu [[Yoga|yogic]] practices. Among other progressions from Vedic Hinduism, the Tantrics spoke of the caste system as it had evolved as unfounded and inapplicable to humanity and spiritual growth. 

Many Hindu yogins and sages have, over the centuries, constantly denounced enforced caste as an aberration of any faith in God. The great non-dualist, Vedantic jnana-yogin (Yogin of discrimination) [[Shankara|Shri Adi Shankaracharya]] ([[8th century]] [[Common Era|CE]]), denounced caste as but one more indication of one's weak, ego-driven self and the flouting of [[Brahman]] (the impersonal, ultimate monist basis of Hindu belief). [[Chaitanya|Shri Chaitanya Mahaprabhu]] ([[15th century]] CE), the powerful bhakti (loving devotee) of Brahman in its manifestations of [[Vishnu]], also denounced caste. But like most societies across the world, the tenets of the [[religion]] were completely ignored in the face of personal gain and the corruption of power. The strongly cemented and oppressive caste hierarchy was so ingrained in the Indian consciousness that it was all but indestructible.

== Modern perceptions of caste ==

The caste system was perhaps first exposed to the Western world during the [[British Empire|British]] occupation and rule. Herbert Risley's ''The Tribes and Castes of [[Bengal]]'', published in [[1892]], was one of the first works on this practice by a Western scholar. Some scholars suggest that the resulting depiction of the caste system was as much a product of European [[racist]] theories, and the interests of colonial rule, rather than Indian cultural realities. Certainly the color hierarchy from "white" to "black" was typically interpreted at this time in racial terms. Modern scholars further suggest that prior to the [[British Raj|colonial era]], castes were much more open and flexible. There are several passages in the Vedas which indicate that the four varnas were initially based on professions and not simply determined by birth. It was during a later period that the current rigid caste system came into place. 

In any case, the Vedas are said to talk about only four castes. Contemporary India however, has numerous castes and sub-castes, many of which are officially documented (primarily to determine those deserving [[reservation]], an [[affirmative action]] process similar to the [[United States|US]] system) through the [[census]], and these divisions have fragmented the Indian [[society]]. Caste-based [[politics]] have strong roots in many Indian states. Sometimes, converts to other religions like [[Christianity]], or [[Islam]], retain their caste identity, often due to the economic benefits it carries, and also to retain their ties with the community for social reasons.

The embracement of the lower castes into the mainstream community was brought about by [[Mahatma Gandhi]] who called them "[[Harijan]]s" (people of God).

Presently, India has tough laws against individual discrimination on the basis of caste. There is a policy for the socio-economic upliftment of the erstwhile lower castes, by the provision of free [[education]] till graduation, reservation of admission seats in institutions for higher education, a 50% [[quota]] in [[government]] jobs with faster promotions. (The state of [[Tamil Nadu]] reserves 69% of its college admission seats instead of 50% as mandated by the Central Government). In spite of these affirmative actions, identification and discrimination based on castes is quite common in the Indian society. Matrimony between members of different castes is still looked down upon and not very popular. Casteist [[atrocity|atrocities]] are still fairly common in many economically backward states and isolated rural districts.

These [[affirmative action]]s have often been challenged in courts, and through mass protests. Anti-reservation activists allege that the divisions are artificially fostered by the process, which they suspect is fuelled by political gains. A few allege that in the process of categorizing people "who need reservation", casteist identities become firmly entrenched in the Indian [[psyche]]. Many also allege that the progress of the meritorious is cramped by the reservation system, which has not been set any deadline by the [[Constitution of India]]. Pro-reservation activists allege that the system helps in upliftment of the long-suppressed masses and needs to be in place until all sections achieve an equal status in the Indian society. There is a third viewpoint which suggests that reservations should be continued but based on the [[financial]] plight of an individual rather than on his/her caste. This debate has raged on for the last two decades in India.

== Some Indian Castes ==

* [[Adi Dravida]]
* [[Agarwal]]
* [[Anavil Brahmin]]
* [[Arora]]
* [[Arya Samaj]]
* [[Arya Vysya]]
* [[Audichya Brahmin]]
* [[Bahi]]
* [[Balija Naidu]]
* [[Baniya]]
* [[Bengali Brahmin]]
* [[Bhandari]]
* [[Billava]]
* [[Brahmin]]
* [[Brahmin Bhumihar]]
* [[Brahmin Goswami]]
* [[Madhva]]
* [[Madhva Deshasta|Madhva Deshasta]]
* [[Brahmin Kanyakubja]]
* [[Chettiar]]
* [[Dalit]]
* [[Iyengar]]
* [[Iyer]]
* [[Kamma]]
* [[Kayastha]]
* [[Kokanastha]]
* [[Maharashtrian Karhade Brahmins]]
* [[Maharashtrian Deshastha Brahmins]]
* [[Maharashtrian Konkanastha Brahmins]]
* [[Maharashtrian Saraswat Brahmins]]
* [[Maharashtrian Devrukhe Brahmins]]
* [[Mudaliar]]
* [[Nadar(caste)|Nadar]]
* [[Naidu]]
* [[Niyogi]]
* [[Punjabi Khatri]]
* [[Pillai]]
* [[Reddiar]]
* [[Smartha]]
* [[Valmiki]]
* [[Yadav]]

== Notable people ==
* [[Ambedkar]]
* [[Savitri Devi]] saw Brahmins as the bearers of Aryan culture to India, and admired the separation they kept between themselves and the Dravidians.
* [[Mahatma Gandhi]] coined Harijan, a euphemistic word for ''untouchable''
* [[Thanthai Periyar]], famous [[Tamil people|Tamil]] [[rationalist]] fought against the caste practice of Brahmins and Hinduism

== See also ==
* [[Balinese caste system]]
* [[Brahmin]]
* [[Ethnic conflict in India]]
* [[List of ethnic slurs]]
* [[Racism]]
* [[Untouchable|Untouchability]]

== External links ==

*[http://www.murnis.com/culture/articlenamestitlesandcaste.htm Murni's in Bali: Names, Titles and Castes]

* [http://codesign.scu.edu/hinduism/ The Caste System in India]
* ''Annihilation of Caste with a Reply to Mahatma Gandhi'' [http://wcar.alrc.net/mainfile.php/Documents/76/ Part I] &amp; [http://wcar.alrc.net/mainfile.php/Documents/77/ Part II] by ''[[Babasaheb Ambedkar|Dr.B.R.Ambedkar]]''

[[de:Kaste]] 
[[fr:Caste]] 
[[id:kasta]] 
[[ja:&amp;#12459;&amp;#12540;&amp;#12473;&amp;#12488;]] 
[[sv:Kast]] 
[[zh:&amp;#31181;&amp;#22995;&amp;#21046;&amp;#24230;]]

[[Category:Social groups of India]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>