<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20031025194803|1624438" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="7257" pageid="7257" ns="0" title="Caste"><revisions><rev timestamp="2003-10-25T19:49:23Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[de:Kaste]] [[fr:Caste]] [[ja:&amp;#12459;&amp;#12540;&amp;#12473;&amp;#12488;]] [[sv:Kast]] [[zh:&amp;#31181;&amp;#22995;&amp;#21046;&amp;#24230;]]

'''''Caste''''' is derived from the [[Portuguese language|Portuguese]] word for "chaste," and originally used to refer to a social division in [[Hindu]] society.  [[cultural anthropology | Anthropologists]] use the term more generally to refer to a social group that is endogamous and occupationally specialized; such groups are common in highly stratified societies with a very low degree of social mobility.  Broadly understood, [[South Africa]] during the era of [[Apartheid]], the practice of slavery in the southern colonies of the [[United States]] before the Civil Rights movement, and the British occupation of India before its independence were caste-based societies.

The caste system in [[India]] was based on four ''varnas'' (meaning "colors") -- [[Brahmin| Brahmins]] (white), [[Kshatriya| Kshatriyas]] (red), [[Vaishya| Vaishyas]] (yellow), and [[Shudra| Shudras]] (black) -- each of which corresponded to an occupational class -- priests, warriors, merchants/craftsmen, and workers. Indian texts also speak of [[jati]], which are communities. Each varna is further subdivied into many jatis. Each varna has its appropriate rules of conduct, or "dharma," including rules regarding marriage, eating, and physical proximity.   In the ''[[Manusmriti]]'' it is asserted that there are only four varnas, which leads one to the conclusion that the formation of the ''outcaste'' groups may have been a consequence of the Buddhist injunction against professions dealing with animal-killing. Support for this view comes from the fact that similar outcaste groups have existed in Japan, Korea, and China.

Much of what we know of the caste system in India was documented and codified during the period of [[British Empire|British]] occupation and rule (e.g. Herbert Risley's ''The Tribes and Castes of [[Bengal]]'', published in 1892).  Some scholars suggest that the resulting depiction of the caste system was as much a product of European [[racist]] theories, and the interests of colonial rule, rather than Indian cultural realities. Certainly the color hierarchy from 'white' to 'black' was typically interpreted at this time in racial terms. Modern scholars further suggest that prior to the colonial era, castes were much more open and flexible. There are several passages in the Vedas which indicate that the four varnas were initially based on professions and not simply determined by birth. It was during a later period that the current rigid caste system came into place. 

In any case, the vedas talk about only four castes. Today, we find numerous
castes and subcastes in India which have fragmented the society. Presently, India has tough laws against discrimination on the basis of caste. There is a policy for the socio-economic upliftment of the erstwhile lower castes, by the provision of free education till graduation, reservation of admission seats in institutions for higher education, a 50% quota in government jobs with faster promotions.
-----------

In [[social insect]]s such as [[ant]]s, [[bee]]s and [[termite]]s, a caste is a specific sub-type of an insect species which is specialized in a certain task. A common example is the "queen" and the "worker", in which queens are specialized in reproduction and the workers are specialized in feeding and protecting the queens.</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>