<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061113203226|87603693" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="7257" pageid="7257" ns="0" title="Caste"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-11-13T20:33:35Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{expert}}
'''Caste''' systems are traditional, hereditary systems of [[social stratification]], such as [[clans]], [[gentes]], or the [[Indian caste system]].

==Etymology of the English word ''caste''==
The word ''caste'' is derived from the Romance word ''casta'' (seen in [[Portuguese language|Portuguese]], [[Spanish language|Spanish]], and [[Italian language|Italian]]), which (in addition to representing the same concept as English ''caste'') can mean "lineage" or "race". It comes from Romance ''casto,'' which can mean "pure" or "chaste" [the word ''chaste'' itself is ultimately cognate]. ''Casto'' is derived from Latin ''castus'', which also meant "pure" or "chaste".&lt;ref&gt;American Heritage Dictionary of the English Language, 4th ed. Boston, Houghton Mifflin, 2000, entry ''caste''.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Definitions==
Caste as a religious concept is recognized by Oxford Dictionary as "each of the hereditary classes of Hindu society, distinguished by relative degrees of ritual purity or pollution and of social status." and as " any exclusive social class."[http://www.askoxford.com/concise_oed/caste?view=uk]
[[cultural anthropology|Anthropologists]] use the term more generally, to refer to a social group that is [[Endogamy|endogamous]] and [[Profession|occupationally]] specialized; such groups are common in highly stratified societies with a very low degree of social mobility{{fact}}. In its broadest sense, examples of caste-based societies include colonial [[Latin America]] under [[Spain|Spanish]] and [[Portugal|Portuguese]] rule (see [[Casta]]), apart from [[India]] prior to 1947.

==Castes in India==
{{main|Indian caste system|Reservations in India}}
The traditional hereditary system of social stratification of India, in which all social classes exist in thousands of endogamous groups is termed as Jāti. The Jati system, usually with politically and economically derived hierarchies, has been followed across the Indian Subcontinent with regional variations across [[India]],[[Pakistan]],[[Bangladesh]] and [[Nepal]].Different religious denominations have traditionally followed different kinds of Jati stratification. While the prevalence of the Jati system has reduced significantly over the course of the twentieth century, remote and rural areas of the subcontinent continue to subscribe to Jati and Jati segregation. 

Caste, on the other hand is a theoretical construct of the Brahmin scholars to describe and categorise (Varna) the complex social arrangement of which they were themselves a part. In the absence of any other better word, Varna was translated as Caste by the Europeans, with its connotations of racial purity. Contrary to popular belief, historically there was a great deal of mobility and intermingling within Indian castes, other than Brahmins, largely based on economic or political status of the concerned group. 

The Brahmins were enjoined by their scriptures and texts, including the Manusmriti, to live in poverty and to shun possessions and temporal power and instead devote themselves to study and teaching of scriptures and other knowledge, pure conduct and spiritual growth. In fact, they usually subsisted on alms from the rest of the society, including the so called backward caste of "Shudras". This is an important point in understanding the difference between Caste and Class. 

Caste became an important element of Indian politics after the British used the entirely theoretical construct of Varna, now Caste, as the basis of classifying the Indian population, especially the Hindus, in the Population Censuses of late 19th Century. This became more specific in the 1901 Census, because the Indian population, not being aware of what the Brahmins thought of them, by and large did not understand what was meant by "Caste" and gave their occupation, religion, education etc as their "Caste". In the 1901 Census, the people were asked to slot themselves, or were slotted by enumerators, as members of the specific castes of Brahmin, Khshatriya, Vaishya ,Shudra etc . This was ostensibly done to simplify an otherwise difficult to slot society, with subtle hierarchies, for the purposes of better statistical manipulation. 

Thus,a purely theoretical construct of "Varna" or "Caste" now became a living entity and got embedded in the minds of intellectuals and common people alike as an "ancient" system of social segregation. 

It did not take much time to become a significant political issue in India and members of certain castes often form [[Votebank]]s that subscribe to special interest political parties.

===Caste system among Hindus===
{{Citecheck}}
{{Moresources}}
The Indian caste system, prevalent also among local Muslims and Christians, exhibits some differences from those of other countries. Elsewhere, the separation between one group and the other is usually along racial lines{{cn}}. Within India, that is not so. Nor is there any discernable dichotomy (white/black or high/low) because the caste system forms a continuum that defies such ready definition. While many lower-caste people live in conditions of great poverty and social disadvantage, many upper-caste Brahmins too are poor and now disadvantaged politically. Efforts by the Indian government to emancipate the lower castes with affirmative action like reservations in education, jobs and promotions have achieved some success, although the benefits have tended to be cornered by the well-off "Creamy Layer" of lower castes.

The concept of 'upper' and 'lower' caste is therefore a matter of social standing and assimilation rather than anything based on wealth or influence {{fact}}. Even in this age, some castes do not allow other caste members, whom they consider to be "lower" to touch them, and would have washed themselves or their possessions if they had been touched by someone from a "lower" caste {{fact}}. In some parts of India, there was the practice of defining the physical distance one should keep from persons of another caste. As a result of this, children who attended a school where children of lower castes were present had to bathe in running water before returning home. In some parts of the world, as well as in India, such discrimination still exists, though it is punishable by law and unconstitutional in India. The Indian constitution was drafted by [[Ambedkar]], himself of low-caste origins, who is regarded as an emancipator of the [[Dalit]]s.

Loss of caste could occur if individuals strayed from the norms of behavior expected of them; for instance, if one married a person belonging to another caste{{fact}}. Despite the prosletysing efforts of Christian missionaries, the fact is that converts rarely achieve emancipation from the caste system to gain an equal social standing with people of privilege. Even among converts, matrimony between members of different castes is rare, although it is not unknown.

A detailed analysis of the caste system, ''Castes in India: Their Mechanism, Genesis and Development in India''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ambedkar.org/ambcd/01.Caste%20in%20India.htm |title=Castes in India: Their Mechanism, Genesis and Development in India|accessdate=2006-07-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; was presented by Dr. [[B. R. Ambedkar]] in his doctoral paper at the Columbia University.
====Mythical Origin of Castes====
{{Main|Purusha sukta}} 
This is a unique verse as it is the only one in the ancient Brahminical Veda scriptures that has a mention of Varna. This may seem rather strange, given the preponderence of caste in India. But once we recognise that the Indian society was Jati based and the Varna system was a later Brahminical interpretation of that society, this anomaly becomes understandable.

In the [[Purana]]s, it is said{{fact}} that the creative force of the universe, [[Brahma]], created some humans from his mouth — they became reciters of the [[Veda]] and became the [[Brahmin]]s. Then he created other humans from his arms, they became the [[Kshatriyas]], bearers of arms, the warrior and ruling class. Brahma then created some from his abdomen, who became the [[Vaishya]]s or merchants. Finally, Brahma created humans from his feet. They served the other castes even as the feet serve the man; they came to become the [[Sudras]] (manual labourers and artisans). Thus, the whole universe is held to be one organic entity, the body of the almighty.

Most scholars are agreed that the caste system was not rigid, including in the early vedic times{{fact}}. Change of one's caste could be effected by all except Brahmins, by changing one's vocation and acquiring new skills, or gaining economic or political power{{fact}}. 

====Jāti====
{{main|Jāti}}
Major castes were subdivided into hundreds of sub-castes or ''jāti''s. Castes were based on occupation {{fact}}. Endogamous marriage (including polyandry) and other association within caste was strongly enforced. 
*Sub-castes within a group of ''jat'' ("birth" as opposed to ''varna'') were called ''jāti'' {{fact}}
*''Jāti'' members were allowed to marry only with their ''jāti'' {{fact}}.
*People were born into their ''jāti''; this status couldn't be changed, unless through marriage or under rare circumstances. {{fact}}
*Each ''jāti'' was part of a local system of interdependence with other groups, involving occupational specialization, and was linked in complex ways with networks that stretched across regions.
For example, in [[Tamil Nadu]] and [[Kerala]], states of [[South India]], castes based on occupation would include: ''asari'' (carpenters), ''thattar'' (goldsmiths), ''muusaari'' (coppersmiths), ''karuvar'' (ironsmiths), ''ambattar'' (clothes-washers), ''[[parayar]]'' (cobblers) and so on.

====Modern developments====
{{Original research}} 
With rapid urbanization and education of India's largely rural, agrarian population, the significance of caste has diminished, except in government mediated interventions in the form of quotas and reservations in education, jobs and promotions for the socially "lower", but numerous and thus politically important, castes. 

The caste system and its attendant practices have been outlawed and declared punishable offenses, but these laws are difficult to implement. There are occasional violations of human rights of [[Dalit (outcaste)|Dalit]]s (outcastes - also called untouchables) by the higher castes, including forcing Dalits into their traditional professions. Dalits in rural areas have often been victimized by other castes, many a times themselves politically powerful "Shudras"or "lower castes". The government of India provides freeships, scholarships, reservations for government jobs and of university seats in programs of higher education (undergraduate and above) for people hailing from [[Scheduled Castes and Tribes|Scheduled caste]]s, [[Scheduled tribe]]s and [[Other Backward Castes]]; see [[Reservation in India]]. Upper caste Hindus and several secular elements counter-argue that unmeritorious Dalits, especially those from the well off "Creamy Layer"  are exploiting this constitutionally obligatory discrimination to their unfair advantage and meritorious candidates are being sidelined. The site [[Dalitstan]] (presently taken down), once banned by the [[India]]n government, is an example of [[anti-Brahmin]] and [[anti-Hindu]] rhetoric by Dalit extremists, allegedly supported by [[Christian mission]]s {{fact}}.

===Caste system among Indian Muslims===
:''Main article: [[Indian caste system#Caste System among Indian Muslims|Caste System among Indian Muslims]]''

There is also several caste systems among some Muslims in India. They are broadly divided into two castes, Ashraf and Ajlaf, or ''oonchi zaat'' (high caste) and ''niichi zaat'' (low caste). The Muslim Caste system in India was analyzed by [[Ambedkar]], who had a very dim view of the rampant discrimination of the Ajlaf castes by the Ashraf castes&lt;ref&gt;Ambedkar, Bhimrao. Pakistan or the Partition of India. Thackers Publishers.[http://www.columbia.edu/itc/mealac/pritchett/00ambedkar/ambedkar_partition/410.html online]&lt;/ref&gt;.In addition to the Ashraf and Ajlaf castes, there exist the ''Arzal'' under-caste or the [[Dalit]] Muslims who are regarded by the Ashraf and the Ajlaf as ritually impure and are relegated to professions regarded as "menial" such as scavenging and the carrying of night soil.

In addition, Muslims in [[Bengal]] organize their society according to social strata called "Quoms", where division of labor is granted by birth, rather than by economic status. Professions perceived as "lowly" are provided to people of certain ostracized Quoms and higher Quoms get professions perceived as superior&lt;ref&gt;[http://sociology.ucdavis.edu/dgokamoto/soc230/pdf/race_caste_stratification.pdf Race, Caste, and Other Invidious Distinctions in Social Stratification] - UC DavisDept. of Sociology&lt;/ref&gt;. The Quoms are rigidly segregated with little or no intermarriage or cohabitation.

===Caste system among Indian Christians===
:''Main article: [[Indian caste system#Caste System among Indian Christians|Caste System among Indian Christians]]''
Converts to Christianity have retained the old caste practices. In particular, [[Dalit]] Christians are regarded as an undercaste by upper caste Christian clergy and nuns and are discriminated against in society.

==Caste System in Pakistan==
The same caste system practiced by [[Indian caste system#Caste System among Indian Muslims|Indian Muslims]] is practiced in [[Pakistan]], with divisions into tribes such as the [[Pushtun]], [[Pathan]], as well as divisions by religious denomination such as [[Ahmadiyya]], Mojahir etc.Pogroms against Ahmadiyya Muslims and Mojahir Muslims in Pakistan have occurred. Gang-rapes of lower caste women such as [[Mukhtaran Mai]] by upper caste men have also occurred in Pakistan. The ethnic [[Balochi]] in Pakistan are often discriminated against by the Punjabi and [[Sindhi]] people in Pakistan, leading to an armed separatist insurgency in [[Balochistan]] formerly led by the late [[Nawab Akbar Bugti]].

The social stratification among Muslims in the "Swat" area of North Pakistan has been meaningfully compared to the Caste system in India. The society is rigidly divided into subgroups where each Quom is assigned a profession. Different Quoms are not permitted to intermarry or live in the same community&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite book
  | last = Leach
  | first = Edmund Ronald
  | authorlink = E.R. Leach 
  | title = Aspects of Caste in South India, Ceylon and North-West Pakistan (Pg 113)
  | publisher =  Cambridge University Press
  | date = November 24, 1971
  }}
&lt;/ref&gt;.
These Muslims practice a ritual-based system of social stratification. The Quoms who deal with human emissions are ranked the lowest. 
{{cite book
  | last = Leach
  | first = Edmund Ronald
  | authorlink = E.R. Leach 
  | title = Aspects of Caste in South India, Ceylon and North-West Pakistan (Pg 113)
  | publisher =  Cambridge University Press
  | date = November 24, 1971
  }}

The Caste system in Pakistan creates sectarian divides and strong issues along similar lines to those divides seen in [[India]]. Lower castes are often severely persecuted by the upper castes. Lower castes are denied privileges in many communities and violence is committed against them. A particularly infamous example of such incidents is that of [[Mukhtaran Mai]] in Pakistan, a low caste woman who was gang raped by upper caste men. In addition, educated Pakistani women from the lower castes are often persecuted by the higher castes for attempting to break the shackles of the restrictive system (that traditionally denied education to the lower castes, particularly the women). A recent example of this is the case of Ghazala Shaheen, a low caste Muslim woman in Pakistan who, in addition to getting a higher education, had an uncle who eloped with a woman of a high caste family. She was accosted and gang-raped by the upper-caste family. The chances of any legal action are low due to the Pakistani Government's inability to repeal the [[Huddood]] ordinance &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.timesonline.co.uk/article/0,,2089-2372124,00.html Pakistani graduate raped to punish her low-caste family] The Sunday Times - September 24, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;.

==Nepalese caste system==
{{main|Nepalese caste system}}

The Nepalese caste system resembles that of the Indian [[Jāti]] system with numerous Jāti divisions with a Varna system superimposed.

==Sri Lankan caste system==
{{main|Caste in Sri Lanka}}

The Sri Lankan system resembles the South Indian [[Jāti]] system with numerous Jāti divisions without a Varna system superimposition. Furthermore, the Sri Lankan Tamils see themselves as superior to Tamils of Indian background.

==Balinese caste system==
{{main|Balinese caste system}}

The Balinese caste system resembles the Indian system with a four-fold division of society. [[Shudra]]s make up 97% of the society.

==Castes in Yemen==

In [[Yemen]] there exists a caste like system that keeps [[Al-Akhdam]] [[social group]] as the perennial manual workers for the society through practices that mirror untouchability&lt;ref name="ymirror"&gt;[http://www.yemenmirror.com/index.php?action=showDetails&amp;id=136 Akhdam: Ongoing suffering for lost identity ''Yemen Mirror'']&lt;/ref&gt;. Al-Akhdam (literally "servants" with Khadem as plural) is the lowest rung in the Yemeni caste system and by far the poorest. According to official estimates in Yemen, the total number of Khadem countywide is in the neighbourhood of 500,000, some 100,000 of which live in the outskirts of the capital Sana’a. The remainder are dispersed mainly in and around the cities of Aden, Taiz, Lahj, Abyan, Hodeidah and Mukalla&lt;ref name="irin"&gt;[http://www.irinnews.org/report.asp?ReportID=49867&amp;SelectRegion=Middle_East&amp;SelectCountry=YEMEN YEMEN: Akhdam people suffer history of discrimination],'''irinnews.org'''&lt;/ref&gt;.

===Origins===
The Khadem are not members of the three tribes (Bedouin, Berber, and Rif) that comprise mainstream Arab society&lt;ref name="irin"/&gt;.They are believed to be of Ethiopian ancestry.
Some sociologists theorize that the Khadem are descendants of Ethiopian soldiers who had occupied Yemen in the 5th century but were driven out in the 6th century. According to this theory the al-Akhdham are descended from the soldiers who stayed behind and were forced into menial labor as a punitive measure&lt;ref name="irin"/&gt;.

===Discrimination===
The Khadem live in small shanty towns and are marginalized and shunned by mainstream society in Yemen. The Khadem slums exist mostly in big cities, including the capital, Sana’a. Their segregated communities have poor housing conditions. As a result of their low position in society, very few children in the Khadem community are enrolled in school&lt;ref name="irin"/&gt; and often have little choice but to beg for money and intoxicate themselves with crushed glass&lt;ref name="Abadjian"&gt;[http://www.countercurrents.org/hr-marguerite250404.htm Caste In Yemen] by Marguerite Abadjian,''Countercurrents.org'' archive of ''The Baltimore Sun''&lt;/ref&gt;. A traditional [[Arabic]] saying in the region goes: “Clean your plate if it is touched by a dog, but break it if it’s touched by a Khadem" &lt;ref name="irin"/&gt;. Though conditions have improved somewhat over the past few years, the Khadem are still stereotyped by mainstream Yemenese society, considering them lowly, dirty,ill-mannered and immoral&lt;ref name="Abadjian"/&gt;.

Many NGO's and charitable organizations from other countries such as CARE International are working towards their emancipation. The Yemenese government denies that there is any discrimination against the Khadem&lt;ref name="ymirror"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.yementimes.com/99/iss01/l&amp;d.htm ''Yemen Times'']&lt;/ref&gt;.

==Castes in Africa==
{{main|Caste system in Africa}}

Countries in Africa who have societies with caste systems within their borders include Mali, Mauritania, Senegal, Gambia, Guinea, Guinea-Bissau, Ivory Coast, Niger, Burkina Faso, Cameroon, Ghana, Liberia, Sierra Leone, Algeria, Nigeria, Chad, Ethiopia and Somalia.

The Osu caste system in Nigeria and southern Cameroon are derived from indegenous religious beliefs and discriminate against the "Osus" people as "owned by deities" and outcastes.

Caste systems in Somalia mandate non-Arab descended "outcastes" such as Midgan-Madhiban, Yibir, Tumal and other groups deemed to be impure and are ostracized from society. Similarly, the Mande societies in Senegal, Gambia, Guinea, Sierra leone, Liberia, Ivory Coast and Ghana have caste systems that divide society by occupation and ethnic ties.The Mande caste system regards the "Jonow" slave castes as inferior. Similarly, the Wolof caste system in Senegal is divided into three main groups, the Geer (freeborn/nobles), jaam (slaves and slave descendents) and the outcasted neeno (people of caste).

Other caste systems in Africa include the Borana caste system of NE [[Kenya]] with the Watta as the lowest caste, the "Ubuhake" castes in Rwanda and Burundi, and the "Hutu" undercastes in Rwanda who committed genocide on the "Tutsi" overlords in the now infamous [[Rwandan Genocide]].

==Castes in Latin America==
{{main|Casta}}
{{Expand-section}}
:The word "Caste" is Portuguese in origin, from the word [[Casta]]. Many [[Latin American]] countries have caste systems based on classification by race and inter-ethnic marriages. The caste system was imposed during colonial rule by the Spanish. While many Latin American countries have rendered the system officially illegal through legislation, societal prejudices against lower castes still remain.[http://www.zonalatina.com/Zldata55.htm][http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0002-8762(197112)76%3A5%3C1626%3ARACILA%3E2.0.CO%3B2-6]

==Castes in Korea==
{{main|Baekjeong}}
The '''baekjeong''' (백정) were an “[[untouchable]]” outcaste group of [[Korea]], often compared with the [[burakumin]] of [[Japan]] and the [[dalit (outcaste)|dalit]]s of [[India]] and [[Nepal]].The term ''baekjeong'' itself means “common people”. In the early part of the [[Goryeo]] period (918 - 1392), the outcaste groups were largely settled in fixed communities. However the Mongol invasion left Korea in disarray and [[anomie]], and these groups began to become [[nomad]]ic.Other subgroups of the baekjeong are the ''chaein'' and the ''hwachae''.

===History===
Before the [[Mongol invasions of Korea|Mongol invasions]] in mid-13th century the outcastes in Korea, called the ''[[kolisuchae]]'', were divided very lightly into two camps; the ''[[hwachae]]'' or ''suchae'', who hunted and butchered, and were seen as crude; and the ''[[chaein]]'', who were principally [[actor]]s, [[entertainer]]s, [[minstrel]]s, [[prostitute]]s, and so on, and were sometimes described as “frivolous”. Near the end of the [[Goryeo]] era the term ''hwachae-suchae'' replaced ''kolisuchae'' to refer to the outcastes, before the groups were divided into separate classes altogether, the ''hwachae'' and the ''chaein'', who were then seen as distinct groups. Initial attempts by [[Sejong the Great of Joseon|King Sejong]] to assimilate the outcastes of Korea were a failure, and they were forced to live in [[ghettos]] outside mainstream habitations 

===Discrimination and emancipation attempts===
Throughout the history of the Choson empire, the baekjeong were forced into specific professions like basket weaving and performing executions. They were also considered in moral violation of Buddhist principles, which lead Koreans to see work involving meat as polluting and sinful, even if they saw the consumption as acceptable.
The group had long suffered severe social [[discrimination]] in [[Culture of Korea|Korean society]]. The baekjeong were seen as a contemptible and polluted people that others feared and avoided meeting. By the end of the Choson dynasty, legal reforms were underway to emancipate the status of the baekjeong.However, this legal equality did not equate to social equality. Many remain segregated from larger society, and conditions have worsened in some respects.

Towards the end of the [[19th century]], there was an increasing impetus on [[human dignity]] and [[liberalization]]. Of particular importance was the growth of certain religions supportive of change. 
However, the baekjeong had benefited much less from these changes than other groups, such as the slaves. The other major religious influence on human rights came through Christianity. Some [[missionary|missionaries]] had success converting baekjeong to [[Christianity]], emphasizing that everyone has equal rights under [[God]]. However, everyone was not equal under the Christian congregation, and protests erupted when missionaries attempted to integrate them into worship services, with non-baekjeong finding such an attempt insensitive to traditional notions of hierarchical advantage.

Beginning in the late 19th and early 20th centuries, the baekjeong began to resist the open social discrimination that existed against them.The [[Hyŏngp'yŏngsa]] was launched in Chinju on [[23 April]] [[1923]] through the alliance of wealthy or educated baekjeong and non-baekjeong proponents of change, advocating for “the abolition of classes and of contemptuous appellations, the enlightenment of members, and the promotion of mutual friendship among members.” &lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|chapter=In Search of Human Rights: The Paekchŏng Movement in Colonial Korea|title=Colonial Modernity in Korea|first=Joong-Seop|last=Kim|editor=Gi-Wook Shin and Michael Robinson|year=1999|pages=326}}&lt;/ref&gt; It advocated both for individual civil rights as well as communal fellowship. Thus, the  Hyŏngp'yŏngsa pursued both an equality of human rights and the right to assimilate into the broader public, even as it worked to forge a common identity.They focused on social and economic injustices affecting the baekjeong, hoping to create an [[egalitarianism|egalitarian]] Korean society. Their efforts included attacking social discrimination by the upper class, authorities, and “commoners” and the use of degrading language against children in public schools. In 1927 a number of members of the Hyŏngp'yŏngsa were arrested for their involvement in the creation of an underground nationalist organization. 

The growing power of the radical wing divided the movement, and much of the economic support provided by wealthier baekjeong was pulled, particularly under the strain of the [[Great Depression]], which had negatively impacted the meat and leather trades. The young socialists in the  Hyŏngp'yŏngsa forged connections with other movements, attempting to broaden the movement and work towards “the reconstitution of Korea as a whole.” &lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The Korean Paekjŏng under Japanese rule: the quest for equality and human rights|first=Joong-Seop|last=Kim|year=2003|pages=147}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

At the 1931 national conference, they stirred controversy within the movement by introducing a dissolution proposal, feeling that the organization had abandoned its original aims in favor of those of the bourgeois [[intellectual]]s directing it. It was their belief that dissolution would better serve their interests as it was replaced by [[trade union]]s. The dissolution proposal failed, but not without further alienating more conservative members of the movement, who would already financially strapped from broader economic conditions in Korea.

==Castes in Japan==
{{main|Burakumin}}

'''Burakumin''' ({{lang|ja|部落民}}: ''buraku'', community or hamlet + ''min'', people),  or '''hisabetsu buraku''' ({{lang|ja|被差別部落}} "discriminated communities / discriminated hamlets") are a [[Japanese people|Japanese]] social [[minority group]]. The burakumin are one of the main [[demographics of Japan|minority groups in Japan]], along with the [[Ainu people|Ainu]] of [[Hokkaido]] and [[Zainichi Korean|residents of Korean]] and [[Han Chinese|Chinese]] descent. 

Japan has historically subscribed to a feudal caste system. While modern law has officially abolished the caste hierarchy, there are reports of discrimination against the [[Buraku]] or [[Burakumin]] undercastes, historically referred to by the insulting term "Eta".[http://www.hrdc.net/sahrdc/hrfeatures/HRF39.htm] Studies comparing the caste systems in India and Japan have been performed, with similar discriminations against the Burakumin as the [[Dalit]]s. The Burakumin  are regarded as "ostracized".&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite journal
 | author = William H. Newell
 | year = 1961
 | month = December
 | title = The Comparative Study of Caste in India and Japan 
 | journal = Asian Survey
 | volume = 1
 | issue = 10
 | pages = 3-10
 | url = http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0004-4687(196112)1%3A10%3C3%3ATCSOCI%3E2.0.CO%3B2-F
 }}
&lt;/ref&gt;

===Discrimination against the Burakumin===
While nearly all Japanese Buddhist sects have discriminated against the burakumin, the case of the [[Jōdo Shinshu]] [[Honganji]] Sect is a particularly notable one. The imperial state also forced all people to belong to a specific Buddhist temple according to the formula:
&lt;blockquote&gt;"the imperial family is in [[Tendai]], the peerage is in [[Shingon]], the nobility is in [[Pure Land Buddhism|Jōdo]] (Honen's followers), the Samurai is in [[Zen]], the beggar is in [[Nichiren]], and [[Jōdo Shinshu|Shin]] Buddhists (Shinran's followers) are at the bottom." (Kasahara 1996)&lt;/blockquote&gt;
In consequence the Honganji, which under [[Rennyo]]'s leadership had defiantly accepted the derogatory label of 'the dirty sect' (see Rennyo's letters known as the [[Ofumi]] / [[Gobunsho]]) now began to discriminate against its own burakumin members as it jostled for political and social status.

The fact of religious discrimination against the burakumin was commonly denied until the late twentieth century.  For example, in 1979 the Director-General of the [[Soto]] Sect of Buddhism made a speech at the "3rd World Conference on Religion and Peace" claiming that there was no longer any discrimination against burakumin in Japan.[http://blhrri.org/blhrri_e/blhrri/Q&amp;A.htm]

Finally in 1969 the Honganji began to recognise its mistreatment of burakumin and appears to be beginning to address the problem.[http://www.shindharmanet.com/writings/burakumin.htm]

===Burakumin rights movement===

As early as [[1922]], leaders of the hisabetsu buraku organized a movement, the "Levelers Association of Japan" (''Suiheisha''), to advance their rights.  The Declaration of the Suiheisha encouraged the Burakumin to unite in resistance to discrimination, and sought to frame a positive identity for the victims of discrimination, insisting that the time had come to be "proud of being ''eta''.The Levelers Association remained active until the late 1930s.

After [[World War II]], the National Committee for Burakumin Liberation was founded, changing its name to the [[Buraku Liberation League]] (''Buraku Kaihou Doumei'') in the 1950s. The league, with the support of the [[Japan Socialist Party|socialist]] and [[Japan Communist Party|communist]] parties, pressured the government into making important concessions in the late 1960s and 1970s. One concession was the passing of the ''Special Measures Law for Assimilation Projects'', which provided financial aid for the discriminated communities. 

Even into the early 1990s, however, discussion of the 'liberation' of these discriminated communities, or even their existence, was taboo in public discussion. In the 1960s, [[the Sayama incident]] (狭山事件), which involved a murder conviction of a member of the discriminated communities based on circumstantial evidence, focused public attention on the problems of the group. In the 1980s, some educators and local governments, particularly in areas with relatively large ''hisabetsu buraku'' populations, began special education programs, which they hoped would encourage greater educational and economic success for young members of the group and decrease the discrimination they faced.

Branches of burakumin rights groups exist today in all parts of Japan except for [[Hokkaido]] and [[Okinawa]]. 

"Human Rights Promotion Centers" (人権啓発センター) have been set up across the country by prefectural governments and local authorities; these, in addition to promoting ''burakumin'' rights, campaign on behalf of a wide range of groups such as women, the disabled, ethnic minorities, foreign residents and released prisoners. (The term "human rights" (人権 ''jinken'') usually has a different meaning in Japan as it does in the English speaking world. Where in English the term is most often used in reference to protecting people against violations by, for example, the criminal justice system or an oppressive regime, in Japan it is most often used in reference to equality and discrimination issues.)

The [[Buraku Liberation League]] is considered one of the most militant among burakumin's rights groups. Their legality is still disputed, but to this date the authorities have mostly turned a blind eye to them except in the more extreme cases. 

The other major buraku activist group is the All Japan Federation of Buraku Liberation Movements (全国部落解放運動連合会 ''zenkoku buraku kaihō undō rengōkai'', or '''Zenkairen'''), affiliated to the [[Japanese Communist Party]](JCP), formed by ex-BLL activists.

==See also==
*[[Social stratification]]
*[[Feudal society]]
*[[Class society]]
*[[Reservations in India]]
*[[Forward Castes]]
*[[Backward-caste Hindu Saints]]
*[[Backward-caste Hindu Warriors]]
*[[Caste system]]
*[[Varna]]
==Notes==
&lt;div class="references-small"&gt;
&lt;references /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

==References==
*Spectres of Agrarian Territory by David Ludden December 11, 2001
* Early Evidence for Caste in South India, p. 467-492 in Dimensions of Social Life: Essays in honor of David G. Mandelbaum, Edited by Paul Hockings and Mouton de Gruyter, Berlin, New York, Amsterdam, 1987.

==External links==
'''Sites'''
*http://www.idsn.org International Dalit Solidarity Network
*http://www.dalits.org National Campaign on Dalit Human Rights
*http://www.dalits.nl Dalit Network Netherlands
*[http://www.anti-caste.org/ Anti-Caste Information Page] On caste, communalism, and class struggle.
*[http://www.tamilnation.org/caste/ Caste &amp; the Tamil Nation - Brahmins, Non Brahmins &amp; Dalits]

'''Articles'''
*[http://www.imadr.org/tokyo/ishikawareport.html Rights Activists and Rights Violations:  the Burakumin case in Japan]
*[http://www.hrdc.net/sahrdc/hrfeatures/HRF39.htm Caste, Ethnicity and Nationality]:Japan Finds Plenty of Space for Discrimination
*[http://jbe.gold.ac.uk/7/alldritt001.html The Burakumin] The Complicity of Japanese Buddhism in Oppression and an Opportunity for Liberation
*[http://www.irinnews.org/report.asp?ReportID=49867&amp;SelectRegion=Middle_East&amp;SelectCountry=YEMEN YEMEN: Akhdam people suffer history of discrimination]IRIN News.org
*[http://www.countercurrents.org/hr-marguerite250404.htm Caste In Yemen] by Marguerite Abadjian (Archive of the Baltimore Sun)
*[http://www.indiatogether.org/society/caste.htm India Together on Caste]	 	
*[http://www.breakingranks.net/weblog/rankism Rankism: A Social Disorder]
*[http://www.hindu-international.org/books/articles/varna_jaati_or_caste.pdf Varna Ashram and Hindu Scriptures (pdf)]	
*[http://www.anti-caste.org/muslim_question/caste/caste_one.html Muslims and Caste]
*[http://www.anti-caste.org/diamond_reply/jared_diamond_one.html On the Social Function of Caste: A Reply to Jared Diamond]
*[http://www.anti-caste.org/letters/tsunami.html On discrimination against untouchable survivors of the South Asian tsunami]
*[http://www.anti-caste.org/suj_book/suj_book_index.html Personal family history of an untouchable writer from Andhra]
*''[[New Internationalist]]'', July 2005, "combating Caste"
* [http://codesign.scu.edu/hinduism/ The Caste System in India]
* [http://atributetohinduism.com/Caste_System.htm Jati system in India]
*''Articles on Caste by [[Koenraad Elst]]:'' [http://koenraadelst.bharatvani.org/books/wiah/ch1.htm#16a Caste in India], [http://koenraadelst.bharatvani.org/books/wiah/ch11.htm#49a Buddhism and Caste], [http://koenraadelst.bharatvani.org/books/wiah/ch9.htm#78a Indian tribals and Caste], [http://koenraadelst.bharatvani.org/books/ait/ch49.htm Physical anthropology and Caste], [http://koenraadelst.bharatvani.org/books/ait/ch48.htm#68a Etymology of Varna]	 	
*[http://www.epw.org.in/showArticles.php?root=2003&amp;leaf=11&amp;filename=6474&amp;filetype=html Is Caste System Intrinsic to Hinduism?]	 
*[http://www.tamilnation.org/caste/ Caste &amp; the Tamil Nation - Brahmins, Non Brahmins &amp; Dalits]
*[http://www.geocities.com/lamberdar/_caste.html Hindu Caste System &amp; Hinduism: Vedic vocations (Hindu castes) were not related to heredity (birth)] 	 	
*[http://india.krishna.org/Articles/2000/07/00057.html ISKCON view of caste and behavior]	
*[http://www.maanojrakhit.com/e_book11_varn_system_text.htm These documented Results of 4-Varn system can make you Proud of your Hindu heritage]
*[http://www.anti-caste.org/news/news_index.html News on caste, communalism, and class struggle in South Asia] from the [http://www.anti-caste.org/ Anti-Caste Information Page]

[[Category:Caste|*]]
[[Category:Sociology]]
[[Category:Social divisions]]

[[bg:Каста]]
[[de:Kaste]]
[[es:Casta]]
[[eo:Kasto]]
[[fr:Caste]]
[[hr:Kaste]]
[[id:Kasta]]
[[it:Casta]]
[[he:קאסטה]]
[[lt:Varna (luomas)]]
[[ms:Sistem kasta]]
[[nl:Kaste]]
[[ja:カースト]]
[[nn:kaste]]
[[pl:System kastowy]]
[[pt:Casta]]
[[ru:Каста]]
[[sh:Kaste]]
[[fi:Kastilaitos]]
[[sv:Kast]]
[[ta:சாதி]]
[[tr:Kast sistemi]]
[[zh:种姓制度]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>