<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20081110235103|250987115" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1853472" pageid="1853472" ns="0" title="Dog whistle (politics)"><revisions><rev timestamp="2008-11-10T23:51:21Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">:''This article is specifically about the use of "code words" in politics, for the concept generally, see [[Code word (figure of speech)]]''

'''Dog-whistle politics''', also known as the use of '''code words''', is a type of political campaigning or speechmaking employing coded language that appears to mean one thing to the general population but has a different or more specific meaning for a targeted subgroup of the audience. The term is usually used pejoratively by those that do not approve of the tactics. According to blogger Ian Welsh,

&lt;blockquote&gt;When you speak in code(...), most of the time the only people who hear and understand what you just said are the intended group, who have an understanding of the world and a use of words that is not shared by the majority of the population.&lt;ref&gt;[http://agonist.org/ian_welsh/20060925/just_a_comma_dog_whistle_politics Just A Comma: Dog Whistle Politics | The Agonist&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The term is an analogy to [[dog whistle]]s built in such a way that humans cannot hear them due to their high [[frequency]], but dogs can.

==Origin in Australia==
The term originated in [[Australian politics]] in the mid 1990s. One notable example was its use to describe the [[John Howard|Howard Government's]] policy to crack down on illegal immigration. The Australian Government took a strong stand against illegal immigration, which was highly popular amongst a segment of voters on both sides of the usual political divide, and which contributed to the [[Australian federal election, 2001|winning of the 2001 Australian Federal Election]].  In response to this political success, some commentators have argued that the stand was playing to racist segments of the community, despite the Government's avoidance of ''overtly'' racist terminology. The Howard Government has used dog whistling as a technique to send a message of support to voters with racist leanings while avoiding criticism from those opposed to prejudice. The key to its use is to maintain the option of "[[plausible deniability]]".&lt;ref&gt;http://www.tai.org.au/documents/downloads/DP96.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; An example is the publicity of the citizenship test in 2007 &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.citizenship.gov.au/test/index.htm Overview of the citizenship test&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;. It has been argued that the test may appear reasonable at face value, but is really intended to appeal to those opposing immigration from some regions.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.smh.com.au/news/editorial/no-question-about-a-citizenship-test/2006/12/12/1165685675052.html No question about a citizenship test - Editorial - Opinion - smh.com.au&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

==United Kingdom==
The term was introduced to the [[United Kingdom]] by [[Matthew Parris]] in ''[[The Times]]'' on October 31, 2003 in an article about [[Michael Howard]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/uk/article1005337.ece|title=He is not a rotter and I wish him well (warily)|first=Matthew|last=Parris|publisher=The Times|date=2003-10-31|accessdate=2008-02-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;.  After the phrase caught on in the UK, [[Matthew Parris]] wrote in ''[[The Spectator]]'' on April 30, 2005 about having introduced it.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.spectator.co.uk/the-magazine/cartoons/13599/only-the-tories-can-cut-the-state-down-to-size.thtml|title=Only the Tories can cut the state down to size|first=Matthew|last=Parris|publisher=The Spectator|date=2005-04-30|accessdate=2008-02-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==United States==
Dog-whistle politics is a separate strategy from the less nuanced approach of [[wedge politics]] often employed in the [[United States]]. Still, several examples of "dog whistle politics" are thought to exist in American politics.

One group of American code words is claimed to appeal to racism of the intended audience. The phrase "[[states' rights]]", although literally referring to powers of individual state governments in the United States, has been described as a code word for institutionalized segregation and racism.&lt;ref&gt;David Greenburg, "[http://www.slate.com/id/2178379/pagenum/2/ Dog-Whistling Dixie]", Slate,  Nov. 20, 2007. Accessed April 4, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; Other terms that some people say are used to indicate alleged veiled racism are "crime in the streets" and "welfare queens". &lt;ref&gt;
David Hogberg, "[http://www.spectator.org/dsp_article.asp?art_id=6384 Outsourcing Bigotries]", American Spectator, April 5, 2005. Accessed April 16, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

President [[George W. Bush]] is claimed to use coded language in his speeches to send messages to his supporters among the [[Christian right|religious right]] that will be ignored by other parts of the U.S. population. Examples include his frequent use of biblical phrases and the veiled mention of the [[Dred Scott v. Sandford|''Dred Scott'']] Supreme Court decision in the 2004 Presidential debates.  The latter refers to overturning ''[[Roe v. Wade]]'', which is likened to the ''Dred Scott'' case by some of its critics. &lt;ref&gt;Timothy Noah, "[http://www.slate.com/id/2108083/ Why Bush Opposes Dred Scott], Slate, Oct. 11, 2004. Accessed April 8, 2008. National Right To Life, [http://www.nrlc.org/news/1999/NRL699/slave.html Court Blunders on Slavery and Abortion]. Accessed April 8, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

David Gergen claimed that John McCain's 2008 presidential campaign against [[Barack Obama]] used dog whistle tactics targeting racists, while retaining plausible deniability. &lt;ref&gt;[http://video.google.com/videoplay?docid=6194119833937526436&amp;q=gergen+uppity&amp;ei=fhqWSIsgh5SvAvC8wJsN&amp;hl=en Gergen Calls Out Racial "Signals" of McCain Ads]&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Code word (figure of speech)]]
*[[Framing (social sciences)]]
*[[Loaded language]]
*[[Newspeak]]
*[[Shibboleth]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*"[http://agonist.org/ian_welsh/20060925/just_a_comma_dog_whistle_politics Just a Comma]" by Ian Welsh at The Agonist, September 25, 2006
*"[http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2006/10/04/AR2006100401707.html 'Just a Comma' Becomes Part of Iraq Debate]" by Peter Baker, ''Washington Post'', Thursday, October 5, 2006,  page A19
*[http://www.doubletongued.org/index.php/dictionary/dog_whistle_politics/ Etymology] from the Double-Tongued Dictionary
*"[http://www.tai.org.au/documents/downloads/DP96.pdf Under the Radar : Dog-whistle politics in Australia]" by Josh Fear, [[The Australia Institute]], September 2007

{{Propaganda}}

[[Category:Political campaign techniques]]
[[Category:Propaganda techniques]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>