<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20100716222244|373880896" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="2189751" pageid="2189751" ns="0" title="Cultural pluralism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2010-09-04T06:46:56Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{About|the concept of cultural pluralism|other uses of the term|Pluralism (disambiguation)}}
'''Cultural pluralism''' is a term used when smaller groups within a larger society maintain their unique cultural identities, and their values and practices are accepted by the wider culture.

One example is [[Lebanon]] where 18 different religious communities co-exist on a land of 10,452&amp;nbsp;km². In a pluralist culture, unique groups not only co-exist side by side, but also consider qualities of other groups as traits worth having in the dominant culture.

The current [[contemporary art]] world in the 21st century is an example of cultural pluralism. For another example, a community center in the United States may offer classes in Indian [[yoga]], Chinese [[calligraphy]], and Latin [[salsa dancing]]. That community may also have one or more [[synagogue]]s, [[mosque]]s, [[mandir]]s, [[gurudwara]]s, and/or [[Buddhist temple]]s, as well as several churches of various [[Christian]] denominations.

The existence of such institutions and practices are possible if the cultural communities responsible for them are protected by law and/or accepted by the larger society in a pluralist culture.
 
The idea of cultural pluralism in America has its roots in the [[transcendentalist]] movement and was developed by [[pragmatist]] philosophers such as [[William James]] and [[John Dewey]], and later thinkers such as [[Horace Kallen]] and [[Randolph Bourne]].  One of the most famous articulations of cultural pluralistic ideas can be found in Bourne's 1916 essay "Trans-National America" .&lt;ref&gt;Science Encyclopedia [http://science.jrank.org/pages/10750/Pluralism-Cultural-Pluralism.html Cultural Pluralism] Retrieved on May 31, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==See also==
*[[Multiculturalism]]

[[Category:Pluralism|Pluralism]]
[[Category:Social theories]]


{{Culture-stub}}
{{Socio-stub}}

[[el:Πολιτιστική πολυμορφία]]
[[es:Pluralismo cultural]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>