<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20160229161503|707565391" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="39623516" pageid="39623516" ns="0" title="Feminist art movement"><revisions><rev timestamp="2016-05-08T19:49:05Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{About|worldwide phenomenon|the article specific to the United States|Feminist art movement in the United States}}
{{Feminism sidebar}}
The '''feminist art movement''' refers to the efforts and accomplishments of [[feminism|feminists]] internationally to produce [[feminist art|art that reflects women's lives and experiences]], as well as to change the foundation for the production and reception of contemporary art. It also sought to bring more visibility to women within [[art history]] and art practice. Corresponding with general developments within [[feminism]], and often including such self-organizing tactics as the consciousness-raising group, the movement began in the 1960s and flourished throughout the 1970s as an outgrowth of the so-called [[Second-wave feminism|second wave of feminism]]. It has been called "the most influential international movement of any during the postwar period."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2007/04/20/AR2007042000400.html Jeremy Strick], director of the Museum of Contemporary Art in Los Angeles in the ''Washington Post'', 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
The 1960s was period of civil rights and [[LGBT rights by country or territory|gay and lesbian rights]] movements and protests against war. It was also a period when women artists wanted to gain equal rights as men within the established art world, influenced by modernist movements "utopian ideals," and to create [[feminist art]], often in non-traditional ways, to help "change the world."&lt;ref name="Art Story"&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.theartstory.org/movement-feminist-art.htm# | title=Feminist art movement | publisher=The Art Story Foundation | accessdate=13 January 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Louise Bourgeois]] (1911-2010) and German-American [[Eva Hesse]] (1936-1970) explore some of the themes in [[feminist art]], like domestic life, personal experience and the women's body.&lt;ref name="Art Story" /&gt;

On 20 July 1964 [[Yoko Ono]], an avant-garde artist, singer, and activist, presented ''Cut Piece'' at the Yamaichi Concert Hall, Kyoto, Japan where she sat still as parts of her clothing were cut off of her, which meant to protest violence against women. She performed it again at [[Carnegie Hall]] in 1965.&lt;ref name="CBS Yoko Ono"&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.cbsnews.com/news/crowd-cuts-yoko-onos-clothing-off/ | title=Crowd Cuts Yoko Ono's Clothing Off | work=CBS News | date=16 October 2003 | accessdate=12 January 2014 | author=Jarett Murphy}}&lt;/ref&gt; Her son, Sean, participated in the artist performance on 15 September 2013 at the Théâtre le Ranelagh in Paris.  ''[[The Guardian]]'''s Jonathan Jones considered it "one of the 10 most shocking performance artworks ever."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.theguardian.com/artanddesign/2013/nov/11/scrotum-top-10-shocking-performance-art | title=The 10 most shocking performance artworks ever | publisher=The Guardian | date=11 November 2013 | accessdate=12 January 2014 | author=Jonathan Jones}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Women artists, motivated by [[feminist theory]] and the [[feminist movement]], began the feminist art movement in the 1970s. Feminist art represented a shift away from [[modernism]], where art made by women was put in a different class to works made by men. Or, as Griselda Pollock and Roszika Parker put it—a separation of Art with a capital "A" from art made by women produced a "feminine stereotype".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Roszika Parker|author2=Griselda Pollock| title=Old Mistresses: Women, Art and Ideology |publisher=Pandora, RKP|year=1981}}&lt;/ref&gt;

This demand for equality in representation was codified in the [[Art Workers' Coalition]]'s (AWC) Statement of Demands, which was developed in 1969 and published in definitive form in March 1970. The AWC was set up to defend the rights of artists and force museums and galleries to reform their practices. While the coalition sprung up as a protest movement following Greek kinetic sculptor [[Takis|Panagiotis "Takis" Vassilakis]]'s physical removal of his work Tele-Sculpture(1960) from a 1969 exhibition at the [[Museum of Modern Art]], New York, it quickly issued a broad list of demands to 'art museums in general'.{{citation needed|date=March 2015}}

Alongside calls for free admission, better representation of ethnic minorities, late openings and an agreement that galleries would not exhibit an artwork without the artist's consent, the AWC also demanded that museums 'encourage female artists to overcome centuries of damage done to the image of the female as an artist by establishing equal representation of the sexes in exhibitions, museum purchases and on selection committees'.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Harrison|first1=Charles|title=Art in theory|date=2000|publisher=Blackwell|location=Oxford [u.a.]|isbn=0-631-16575-4|pages=901–2|edition=Repr.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There are also feminist forms of [[postmodernism]] which emerged in the 1980s. The feminist art movement grew out of the struggle to find a way to express sexual, material, social and political aspects of life—and to femininity—in a new way.&lt;ref name="Kramarae pp. 92-93"&gt;Entry on feminist art practice by Katy Deepwell in {{cite book|editor1=Cheris Kramarae|editor2=Dale Spender|title=Routledge International Encyclopedia of Women: Global Women's Issues and Knowledge|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=TfrzBcycB-4C&amp;pg=PA92|date=1 December 2000|publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis|isbn=978-0-415-92088-9|pages=92–93}}&lt;/ref&gt; Feminist art movements emerged in [[Feminist art movement in the United States|the United States]];  Europe,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Gislind Nabakowski|author2=Peter Gorsen|author3=Sander Helke| title=Frauen in der Kunst(2 Vols.)|publisher=Frankfurt,Suhrkamp|year=1980}}&lt;/ref&gt; including Spain;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mav.org.es/cronologiaMAV/cronologia.html  Mujeres en les Artes Visuales, Women in the Visual Arts, Spanish chronology]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Australian feminist art timeline|Australia]]; Canada;&lt;ref&gt;Marie  Rose Arbour  ''Art et Feminisme'' Exhibition catalogue. Canada: Quebec, Musée d'Art Contemporain, Montreal &amp; Ministere des Affaires Culturelles. 1982&lt;/ref&gt; and Latin America in the 1970s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Catriona Moore|title=Dissonance: Feminism and the Arts, 1970-1990| publisher=Allen and Unwin and Artspace| year=1994}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;see Andrea Giunta's, ''[http://cral.in2p3.fr/artelogie/spip.php?article271 Feminist Disruptions in Mexican Art]'', 1975-1987 in Number 5 .(c) ''Artelogie'', October 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;

Since then, there are women's art movements in Sweden, Denmark and Norway, Russia, and Japan.&lt;ref&gt;Hindsbo, Karen. ''The Beginning is Always Today: Scandinavian feminist art from the last 20 years''. SKMU, Sørlandets Kunstmuseum, 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Kokatsu, Reiko.''Women In-Between: Asian Women Artists 1984-2012''. Japan, Fukuoka Asian Art Museum, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; Women artists from Asia, Africa and particularly Eastern Europe emerged in large numbers onto the international art scene in the late 1980s and 1990s as [[contemporary art]] became popular worldwide.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.erstestiftung.org/gender-check/ Gender Check: Masculinity and Femininity in the Art in Eastern Europe],&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Huangfu, Binghui.(ed).''Text and Sub-Text''(Singapore: Lasalle-SIA University, 2000.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Dike, Paul Chike and Oyelola, Patricia. ''Nigerian Women in Visual Art''. National Gallery of Art, Lagos, Nigeria, 2004&lt;/ref&gt;

Major exhibitions of contemporary women artists include ''[[WACK! Art and the Feminist Revolution]]'' curated by Connie Butler, SF MOMA, 2007, ''Global Feminisms'' curated by [[Linda Nochlin]] and Maura Reilly at the Brooklyn Museum, 2007,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.brooklynmuseum.org/exhibitions/global_feminisms/  Global Feminisms]&lt;/ref&gt; ''Rebelle'', curated by Mirjam Westen at MMKA, Arnheim, 2009, ''Kiss Kiss Bang Bang! 45 Years of Art and Feminism'' curated by Xavier Arakistan at Bilbao Fine Arts Museum, 2007,&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.museobilbao.com/in/exposiciones/kiss-kiss-bang-bang-89 Kiss Kiss Bang Bang! 45 Years of Art and Feminism]&lt;/ref&gt; ''Elles at Centre Pompidou'' in Paris (2009-2011), which also toured to Seattle Art Museum.&lt;ref&gt;[http://seattleartmuseum.org/elles/elles_pompidou.html Elles Pompidou.] Seattle Art Museum&lt;/ref&gt; have been increasingly international in their selection. This shift is also reflected in journals set up in the 1990s like ''[[n.paradoxa]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Connor, Maureen|url=http://www.jstor.org/discover/10.2307/778180?uid=3738032&amp;uid=2129&amp;uid=2&amp;uid=70&amp;uid=4&amp;sid=21103432225961|title=Working Notes: Conversation with Katy Deepwell|journal=Art Journal|volume=61|number=2|date=Summer 2002|jstor=778180|pages=32–43}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Div col}}
* [[Australian Feminist Art Timeline]]
* [[Cyberfeminism]]
* [[Feminism in 1950s Britain]]
* [[Feminist art]]
* [[Feminist art criticism]]
* [[Feminist art movement in the United States]]
* [[Historiography]]
* [[List of 20th century women artists]]
* [[n.paradoxa]]
* [[Postmodern feminism]]
*[[Timeline of the Feminist art movement in New Zealand]]
* [[Women Artists]]
{{Div col end}}

== References ==
{{reflist}}

===Further reading===
* 
* Juan Vicente Aliaga ''Gender Battle/A Battala dos Xeneros'' Spain, Santiago de Compostela, 2007.
* Juan Aliaga and Maria Laura Rosa ''Recuperar la Memoria: Experiencias feministas desde el Arte, Argentina y Espana, Ana Navarette and Mujeres Publicas'' Centro Cultural de Espana, Buenos Aires and CCEBE, Sede Parana, 2013. 
* L. Anderson, A. Livion Ingvarsson, M. Jensner, A. Nystrom, B.Werkmeister, N. Ostlind (eds.) ''Konstfeminism'' Helsingborg, Sweden, Dunkers Kulturhaus and Lilevalch Konsthall, 2004. 
* Kathy Battista ''Re-Negotiating the Body: Feminist Art in 1970s'' London, I B Tauris, 2011.    
* Carla Bianpoen, Farah Wardani, Wulan Dirgantoro ''Indonesian Women Artists'' Jakarta: Yayasan Semirupa Indonesia:2007.
* Katy Deepwell (ed) ''New Feminist Art Criticism: Critical Strategies'' UK, Manchester, Manchester University Press, 1995.
* Sylvia Eiblmayr ''Die Frau als Bild: Der weibliche Körper in der Kunst des 20 Jahrhunderts'' Berlin, Dietrich Reimer, 1993.
* Isabelle  Graw  ''Die bessere Hälfte: Künstlerinnen des 20. und 21. Jahrhunderts'' Cologne, du Mont Verlag, 2003.
* Karen Hindsbo ''The Beginning is Always Today': Scandinavian feminist art from the last 20 years'' Norway: Saarlandets Kunstmuseum, 2013.
* Johanna  Householder and Tanya Mars (eds) ''Caught in the Act: an Anthology of Performance Art by Canadian Women''  Toronto:YYZ Books, 2003.  
* Lucy Lippard ''From the Center:Feminist Essays on Women's Art'' New York. Dutton, 1976.
* Roszika Parker and Griselda Pollock ''Framing Feminism: Art and the Women's Movement, 1970-1985'' London. Pandora/RKP, 1987.
* Bojana Pejic (ed) ''The Gender Check Reader'' Vienna, MUMOK and Erste Foundation, 2010
* Griselda Pollock (ed) ''Generations and Geographies'' London, Routledge, 1996.
* Helena Reckitt (ed) ''Art and Feminism'' London, Phaidon, 2001 
* Hilary Robinson (ed) ''Visibly Female'' London, Camden Press, 1987
* Hilary Robinson (ed)  ''Feminism – Art – Theory: An Anthology, 1968-2000'' Oxford. Blackwells, 2001.
* Araceli Barbosa Sanchez  ''Arte Feminista en los ochenta en Mexico: una perspectiva de genero'' Mexico: Casa Juan Pablos Centro Cultural, Universidad Autonoma de Estado de Morelos, 2008.
* Ella Shohat (ed) ''Talking Visions: Multicultural Feminism in a Transnational Age'' Cambridge, Mass, MIT:1998  
* Bridget Tracy Tan ''Women Artists in Singapore''  Singapore, Select Books and Singapore Art Museum, 2011.
* Jayne  Wark  ''Radical Gestures: Feminism and Performance Art in North America''  Montreal: McGill-Queen's University Press, 2006. 
* Women Down the Pub (a.k.a. N.Debois Buhl, L.Strombeck, A.Sonjasdotter)  ''Udsight – Feministiske Strategier i Dansk Billedkunst / View – Feminist Strategies in Danish Visual Art''  Denmark, Informations Vorla, 2004.

{{Feminism}}
{{Westernart}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Feminist Art Movement}}
[[Category:Art movements]]
[[Category:Contemporary art]]
[[Category:Feminist theory]]
[[Category:Feminist artists]]
[[Category:Feminist theatre]]
[[Category:Feminism and the arts]]
[[Category:Political art]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>