<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20101111213113|396199713" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="40786" pageid="40786" ns="0" title="Bias"><revisions><rev timestamp="2010-11-11T21:31:15Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{For|other meanings of '''Bias'''|Bias (disambiguation)}}
Bias is an inclination to present or hold a partial perspective at the expense of (possibly equally valid) alternatives. Bias can come in many forms.

==In statistics==
{{Main|Bias (statistics)}}
In statistics, bias is systematic favoritism present in data collection, analysis or reporting of [[quantitative research]].

==In judgment and decision making==
{{Main|Cognitive bias}}
A cognitive bias is the human tendency to make systematic errors in certain circumstances based on [[cognitive]] factors rather than evidence. Such biases can result from information-processing shortcuts called ''[[heuristics]]''. They include errors in judgment, [[social attribution]], and memory. Cognitive biases are a common outcome of human thought, and often drastically skew the reliability of [[anecdotal evidence|anecdotal]] and [[evidence (law)|legal evidence]]. It is a phenomenon studied in [[cognitive science]] and [[social psychology]].

==In the media==
{{main|Media bias}}
Media bias refers to the bias of [[journalist]]s and [[news producer]]s within the [[mass media]], in the selection of which events and stories are reported and how they are covered.  The term "media bias" implies a pervasive or widespread bias contravening [[Journalism ethics and standards|the standards of journalism]], rather than the perspective of an individual journalist or article. The direction and degree of media bias in various countries is widely disputed.

Practical limitations to media neutrality include the inability of journalists to report all available stories and facts, and the requirement that selected facts be linked into a coherent narrative (Newton 1989).  Since it is impossible to report everything, selectivity is inevitable. [[Government]] influence, including overt and covert [[censorship]], biases the media in some countries. Market forces that result in a biased presentation include the [[ownership]] of the news source, [[concentration of media ownership]], the selection of [[Employment|staff]], the [[preference]]s of an intended [[audience]], and pressure from [[advertiser]]s.

Political bias has been a feature of the mass media since its birth with the invention of the [[printing press]]. The expense of early printing equipment restricted media production to a limited number of people. Historians have found that publishers often served the interests of powerful social groups.&lt;ref&gt;Ann Heinrichs, ''The Printing Press (Inventions That Shaped the World)'', p. 53, Franklin Watts, 2005, ISBN 0-531-16722-4, ISBN 978-0-531-16722-9&lt;/ref&gt;

==Other aspects==
* Economic: When People/Government interpret a law/contract in their favor for economic reasons.
* [[Cultural bias|Cultural]]: interpreting and judging phenomena in terms particular to one's own culture.
* [[Racism]], [[regionalism (politics)|regionalism]] and [[tribalism]].
* [[Inductive bias]] in machine learning.
* [[Sexism]], [[homophilia]] and [[heteronormativity]].
* [[Sensationalism|Sensationalist]]: favoring the exceptional over the ordinary. This includes emphasizing, distorting, or fabricating exceptional news to boost commercial ratings.
* [[Funding bias]] in scientific studies.
* Medical bias is also known as a physician having a [[conflict of interest]].&lt;ref&gt;Cain, D.M. and Detsky, A.S. [http://jama.ama-assn.org/cgi/content/extract/299/24/2893| Everyone's a Little Bit Biased (Even Physicians)] ''JAMA'' 2008;299(24):2893-289.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Biasing]] or ''bias'' in electrical engineering: force applied as a reference level in order to operate a device. Bias as in prejudice.

==See also==
{{Portal|Psychology}}
* [[Prejudice]]
* [[Impartiality]]
* [[List of cognitive biases]]
* [[Scholarly method]]
* [[Source criticism]]
* [[Weasel word]]
* [[Detection theory]]
* [[Experimenter's bias]]
* [[Social desirability bias]]
* [[Political Correctness]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{Wikiquote}}
{{Wiktionary}}
{{Biases}}

[[Category:Bias|*]]
[[Category:Psychological attitude]]
[[Category:Critical thinking]]

[[ar:انحياز]]
[[da:Bias (psykologi)]]
[[de:Bias]]
[[es:Sesgo]]
[[he:נטאי]]
[[no:Bias]]
[[pt:Viés]]
[[simple:Bias]]
[[sr:Биас]]
[[sv:Metodfel]]
[[ta:பக்கசார்பு]]
[[tr:Ön yargı]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>