<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061010212720|80690781" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="5686076" pageid="5686076" ns="0" title="Christian feminism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-10-29T23:56:06Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{POV}}
'''Christian feminism''' is a branch of [[feminist theology]] that seeks to interpret and understand [[Christianity]] in the scope of the equality of women and men morally, socially, and in leadership. Because this equality has been historically ignored, feminists believe their contributions are necessary for a complete understanding of Christianity. As with all feminists, Christian feminists  vary greatly in belief; most agree that God does not discriminate the roles of leadership and earning wages. Feminists views tend to overlap with secular feminism. The major issues are the [[ordination of women]], male dominance in marriage, and the moral deficiency of women compared to men. Feminists are also concerned with many other issues such as the balance of parenting between mothers and fathers and the treatment of women in the [[Torah]]. Many Christians are uncomfortable with the term ''feminism'' because of extreme feminists such as [[Mary Daly]], while still sympathizing with feminist ideas; they may use the term [[egalitarianism]].

==Issues==

===Women in church leadership===
{{main|ordination of women}}

===Women as morally deficient===
Understanding whether women are morally deficient to men partly hinges on whether women are morally equipped to teach;  The following passages also relate to whether women are inherently as moral as men.

*[[Genesis]] 3.16 God makes Eve to desire her husband. Non-feminists may interpret it as a template for females.
*[[Genesis]] 2.20 Hebrew word for "help" can mean "military rescue" as well. 
*[[Epistle to Galatians|Galatians]] 3.28 "There is neither . . . male nor female for all are one in Christ Jesus."

===Women submitting to husbands===
The following passages relate to whether wives must submit to their husbands.

*[[Eishes Chayil|Proverbs 31]] 10, 29 Wives are commended when they are mighty.
*[[Epistle to the Romans|Romans]] 16.3 [[Priscilla (Christian)|Priscilla]] is listed as above her husband, [[Aquila (bible)|Aquila]]
*[[Epistle to the Ephesians|Ephesians]] 5.21 Husbands and wives are told to submit to each other.
*[[Ephesians]] 5.22 Women are told to submit to their husbands.

===Head Coverings===
Historically, Christian women have covered their head as a sign of their husband's authority over them in accordance with [[1 Corinthians 11]]:3-16. All feminists reject that women should still cover their heads, but disagree as to the exact meaning of the passage.

==The Bible==
The deep controvery with Christian Feminism is with its interpretation and understanding of the Bible. For the same passages that one denomination takes to say that women may not preach, a Christian Feminist might interpret otherwise. An important factor that influences a Christian Feminist's understanding of a passage is the specific cultural setting and circumstance of the time that the passage was written. Another factor is simply Christian Feminist's translation of the original text. For example, the word "help" or "helper" (in Hebrew ezer (ay'-zer)) that is often understood as a word meaning "servant" in Genesis 2:20 can be otherwise viewed to mean "military rescue" in reference to the context in which the same word is used in other passages in the bible. It is also used in Gen 49:25, Ps 33:20 to describe God's gracious assistance to those he loves.  "Military rescue" would not be a rational translation of the Hebrew word in the context of Genesis 2:20.


===Problematic Passages===
A large variety of biblical passages are used as authority to eliminate women from leadership roles, primarily in marriage and priesthood/pastorship. Some feminists reject the passages altogether while more conservatives believe they can be reconciled with feminism.

*[[Genesis]] 3:16 God makes Eve to desire her husband as a template for females; man's authority over woman reaffirmed. 
*[[Acts of the Apostles]] 1:21 Criteria for apostleship include being male.
*[[1 Corinthians]] 11:3-16 Women are commanded to cover their heads in worship to show they recognize their husband's authority (man created first).
*[[1 Corinthians]] 14:34-35 Women are told to be silent in church.
*[[Ephesians]] 5:22 Women are told to submit to their husbands.
*[[First Epistle to Timothy|1 Timothy]] 2:11-12 Women are told to be quiet in church because man was created first, and woman was deceived and sinned first.

===Supportive Passages===
*[[Genesis]] 2.20 Hebrew word for "help" means "military rescue," not a servant. 
*[[Genesis]] 3.15 The [[Messiah]] is promised to woman.

*[[Book of Exodus|Exodus]] 15:20 [[Miriam]] is called a [[prophet|prophetess]].
*[[Book of Judges|Judges]] 4 Deborah leads the nation of [[Israel]].
*[[Eishes Chayil|Proverbs 31]] 10, 29 Women are commended when they are mighty.
*[[Book of Nehemiah|Nehemiah]] 6:14 The prophetess [[Noadiah]] is mentioned.
*[[Book of Isaiah|Isaiah]] 8.3 An anonymous prophetess is mentioned.
*[[Book of Joel]] 2:28, 29 Prophesy that women and men will prophesy alike.
*[[Gospel]]s Jesus shows no distinction between women and men to the denial of cultural norms.
*[[Acts of the Apostles]] 2:4 [[Mary, the mother of Jesus]], and other women prophesy.
*[[Acts of the Apostles]]16:14-15 [[Lydia of Thyatira]] is presented as of forceful character.
*[[Epistle to the Romans|Romans]] 16:1 A woman, [[Phoebe]], is called a "diakonos", a word which usually (e.g. Mt 20:26, 23:11; Mk 9:35; Jn 12:26; Col 1:23, 25) means a servant, but which some interpret as here meaning a [[deacon]].
*[[Epistle to the Romans|Romans]] 16:3 [[Priscilla (Christian)|Priscilla]] is listed as above her husband, [[Aquila (bible)|Aquila]].
*[[Epistle to the Romans|Romans]] 16:7 A woman, [[Junias]], is identified as an apostle.
*[[Epistle to Galatians|Galatians]] 3:28 "There is neither . . . male nor female for all are one in Christ Jesus."
*[[Epistle to the Ephesians|Ephesians]] 5:21 Husbands and wives are told to submit to each other.

==Bibliography==

* [[Pamela Sue Anderson]], ''A feminist philosophy of religion: the rationality and myths of religious belief'' (Oxford; Malden, Mass.: Blackwell, 1998) 
* [[Pamela Sue Anderson]] and Beverley Clack, eds., ''Feminist philosophy of religion: critical readings'' (London: Routledge, 2004)
* [[John Temple Bristow]], ''What Paul Really Said About Women: An Apostle's Liberating Views on Equality in Marriage, Leadership and Love'' (San Francisco: Harper &amp; Row, 1988)

[[Category:Religious feminism]]


{{sociology-stub}}</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>