<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20071111080123|170708819" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="5686076" pageid="5686076" ns="0" title="Christian feminism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-11-13T13:41:16Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{NPOV}}

{{Feminism}}

'''Christian feminism''', a branch of [[feminist theology]], seeks to interpret and understand [[Christianity]] in the scope of the [[sexual equality|equality]] of [[men]] and [[women]] morally, socially, spiritually and in leadership. Christian [[feminist]]s believe their contributions are necessary for a complete understanding of Christianity. While there is no standard set of beliefs among Christian feminists, most agree that [[God]] does not [[discriminate]] on the basis of biologically-determined characteristics such as gender. Their major issues are the [[ordination of women]], male dominance in Christian [[marriage]], and claims of spiritual deficiency and inferiority of the abilities of women to interpret and exposit scripture compared to men. They also are concerned with issues such as the balance of [[parenting]] between [[mother]]s and [[father]]s and the overall treatment of women in the church. 

Certain Christians who sympathize with women's issues are uncomfortable with the term ''feminism''. One reason for this discomfort is the claim by some conservatives that Christian feminists are theological descendants of radical secular feminists such as [[Mary Daly]], [[Betty Friedan]], and [[Daphne Hampson]].{{Fact|date=June 2007}} However, Christian feminists appeared on the scene much earlier than secular feminists (see "History" below). Increasingly, the term [[Christian egalitarianism]] is preferred by those advocating gender equality and equity among Christians. 

==History==

The Greek philosopher [[Aristotle]] had taught that women are intrinsically inferior. Aristotle's discriminatory view was taken over the far more egalitarian views of [[Plato]] and [[Socrates]] by notable theologians such as [[Tertullian]], [[Augustine of Hippo|Augustine]], [[Chrysostom]], and [[Thomas Aquinas]].{{Fact|date=May 2007}} Protestant reformers [[John Calvin]] and [[John Knox]] also believed that men were spiritually and morally superior to women. Others, such as [[Margaret Fell]] and [[Sojourner Truth]], were women. 
In the early 1800s some Christians began to teach that women are not innately inferior. Between 1808 and 1930, there appeared printed arguments in support of women's ministries. Thus emerged the first wave of feminists. They advocated that the theology of gender and justice should be based on a whole-Bible approach rather than "proof texting" of isolated passages. Some notable first-wave Christian feminists:
*[[Fredrik Franson]] (1852–1908). Founded the Evangelical Alliance Mission.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.wheaton.edu/bgc/archives/GUIDES/087.htm (1) July 10, 1888—''Evangelistkurs''. Franson's announcement of Evangelist Course in Oslo beginning July 10, 9 a.m. He recounts blessings received through those who have worked as Evangelists, especially in the inland districts, since last winter—and especially so through the women evangelists. (2) Spring 1892—Franson's announcement concerning the founding and work of "The Scandinavian-American Women's Alliance Mission to Dark Places." (3) April 1896—''Profeterande Dottrar'' by Franson and [English] Prophesying Daughters by Franson—concerning women's' position in regard to evangelization.&lt;/ref&gt; 
*[[Adoniram Judson Gordon|A. J. Gordon]] (1836–1895). The founder and first president of Gordon College.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.gcts.edu/studentlife/ethos.php#women A.J. Gordon was a well-known advocate, in his day, of the preaching ministry of women.&lt;/ref&gt; "'Dr. A. J. Gordon stood by me steadily,' Frances Willard recalled."&lt;ref&gt;http://www.historycooperative.org/journals/jga/3.3/blum.html Blum, Edward (Baylor University).''Paul Has Been Forgotten: Women, Gender, and Revivalism during the Gilded Age.''&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Katharine Bushnell]] (1856–1946). Medical doctor, scholar, missionary, activist.
*[[Catherine Booth]] (1829–1890). Co-founder with her husband of the Salvation Army.
*[[Frances Willard (suffragist)|Frances Willard]] (1839–1898). Preached at D. L. Moody revivals. President of Women's Christian Temperance Union.

==Issues==
===Women in church leadership===
{{main|Ordination of women}}
Feminism has affected many aspects of [[religion]]. In liberal branches of [[Protestant Christianity]] (and, notably, in some theologically conservative denominations, such as [[Assemblies of God]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| date=[[1990-08-14]] |url=http://ag.org/top/beliefs/position_papers/pp_downloads/pp_4191_women_ministry.pdf |title=The Role of Women in Ministry |format=[[PDF]] |pages=7 |publisher=The General Council of the Assemblies of God}}&lt;/ref&gt;) women are ordained as [[clergy]], and in [[Reform Judaism|Reform]], [[Conservative Judaism|Conservative]] and [[Reconstructionist Judaism|Reconstructionist]] [[Judaism]], women are ordained as [[rabbi]]s and [[Hazzan|cantor]]s. Within these [[Christianity|Christian]] and [[Judaism|Jewish]] groups, women have gradually obtained more positions of power; their perspectives now have greater influence in developing new statements of belief.

The leadership of women in religious matters continues to be restricted by many denominations. The [[Roman Catholic]] church, and [[Fundamentalist Christianity|fundamentalist]] Protestant traditions such as the (American) Southern [[Baptist]] convention&lt;ref&gt;http://www.sbc.net/aboutus/pswomen.asp&lt;/ref&gt;, and the American "[[non-denominational]]" movement (that includes the [[Church of Christ]] and [[megachurch]]es)&lt;ref&gt;http://www.jstor.org/view/0034673x/ap060107/06a00020/1?frame=noframe&amp;userID=83d82910@unlv.edu/01cc99331400501c40fcb&amp;dpi=3&amp;config=jstor&lt;/ref&gt; generally exclude women from entering the priesthood and other clerical positions, limiting women to the roles of nuns or laypeople.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.springerlink.com/content/l5p31j7w2q316882/&lt;/ref&gt;

===Women as spiritually deficient===
Understanding whether women are spiritually deficient to men partly hinges on whether women are equipped spiritually with discernment to teach. The following passages also relate to whether women are inherently spiritually discerning as men:
*{{bibleref|Galatians|3:28}}. "There is neither…male nor female for all are one in Christ Jesus."
* '''Deborah''' of the [[Old Testament]] was a prophetess and "judge of Israel"&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.amit.org.il/learning/english/JW/Deborah.htm Deborah the Prophetess]&lt;/ref&gt;
*{{bibleref|Genesis|2:20}}. The word translated "help" or "helper" is the same Hebrew word, "ēzer," which the Old Testament uses 17 times to describe the kind of help that God brings to His people in times of need; e.g., "Thou art my help (ēzer} and my deliverer," and "My help (ēzer) comes from the Lord."
*{{bibleref|Genesis|3:16}}. "To the woman he (God) said, 'I will greatly increase your pains in childbearing; in pain you shall bring forth children, yet your desire shall be for your husband, and he shall rule over you.'"

===Reproduction, sexuality and religion===
In the United States, conservative religious groups are often at philosophical odds with feminist and liberal religious groups over abortion and the use of birth control.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.plannedparenthood.org/news-articles-press/politics-policy-issues/abortion-access/antichoice-organizations-6127.htm&lt;/ref&gt; These philosophical oppositions are manifest in courtroom and legislative battles, even making their way to the [[United States Supreme Court]].&lt;ref&gt;http://pewforum.org/news/display.php?NewsID=10051&lt;/ref&gt;
Scholars like sociologist Flann Campbell have noted that conservative religious denominations tend to restrict male and female sexuality&lt;ref&gt;http://www.jstor.org/view/00324728/di980713/98p0182w/0?frame=noframe&amp;userID=83d82910@unlv.edu/01cc99331400501c40fcb&amp;dpi=3&amp;config=jstor&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://books.google.com/books?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;id=yUWz24sVu54C&amp;oi=fnd&amp;pg=PP13&amp;dq=women+southern+baptist+convention&amp;ots=2zoqp_H0w-&amp;sig=4Jj4aGKdQ_Y98aJrpSg5vM5O8W8#PPA10,M1&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt;http://scholar.google.com/scholar?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;q=%22Flann+Campbell%22&amp;btnG=Search&amp;as_subj=soc&lt;/ref&gt;by prohibiting or limiting birth control use&lt;ref&gt;http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/paul_vi/encyclicals/documents/hf_p-vi_enc_25071968_humanae-vitae_en.html&lt;/ref&gt;, and condemning abortion as a [[sin]] likely punished by damnation to [[hell]] by [[God]]. &lt;ref&gt;http://www.johnstonsarchive.net/baptist/sbcabres.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.bible-knowledge.com/Sin-of-Abortion.html&lt;/ref&gt; As a result of these religious claims, mainline Protestant denominations (e.g. the [[Episcopal Church in the United States of America|Episcopalian]], [[Presbyterian]], [[Methodist]], [[United Church of Christ]], [[Unitarian Universalist]], and the [[Evangelical Lutheran Church of America]] traditions), as well as [[Jewish]] denominations and the group [[Catholics for a Free Choice]] have formed the [[Religious Coalition for Reproductive Choice]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.rcrc.org/about/members.cfm&lt;/ref&gt; The RCRC often works as a feminist organization and in conjunction with other American feminist organizations&lt;ref&gt;http://www.nwlc.org/details.cfm?id=1223&amp;section=Reproductive%20Rights%3A%20General%20Materials&lt;/ref&gt;

===Women submitting to husbands===
The following passages relate to whether wives must submit to their husbands:
*{{bibleref|Ephesians|5:22}} Women are told to submit to their husbands.
*{{bibleref|1 Peter|3:6}} Sarah obeyed Abraham and called him lord

===Head coverings===
In {{bibleref|1Corinthians|11:3–17}}, women are commanded to cover their heads in worship to show they recognize their husband's authority coming from the fact that man was created first and that he was created in God's image. Most Christians today apply a cultural exemption to this verse to agree that women no longer need to cover their heads when praying or prophesying.

==The Bible==
A major concern to Christian Feminism is how people interpret the [[Bible]], particularly the influence of one's set of presuppositions on understanding the Bible. The same passages that one [[Christian denomination|denomination]] takes to say that women may not [[preach]], a Christian feminist might interpret otherwise. An important factor that influences a Christian feminist's understanding of a passage is taking into account the specific [[cultural]] setting and circumstance of the time that the passage was written. 

===Some problematic passages===
A variety of biblical passages are used as authority to prohibit women from having leadership roles, primarily in marriage and the church. 

*{{bibleref|Acts|1:21}}. Criteria for apostleship include being male.
*{{bibleref|1Corinthians|11:3–16}}. Women are commanded to cover their heads in worship to show they recognize their husband's authority coming from the fact that man was created first and that man was created in Gods' image.
*{{bibleref|1Corinthians|14:34–35}}. Women are told to be silent in church.
*{{bibleref|Ephesians|5:22}} Women are told to submit to their husbands. 
*{{bibleref|1Timothy|2:11–12}}. Women are told to be quiet in church because man was created first, and woman was deceived and sinned first.
Revelation 2:20 The church of Thyatira was rebuked for letting a women teach that the Lord referred to as Jezebel.
Genesis 3:17 The first sin Adam committed was that he listened to his wife.
Job 2:10 Job rebukes his wife for speaking as foolish women.

===Supportive passages===

*{{bibleref|Exodus|15:20}}. [[Miriam]] is called a [[prophet]]ess.
*[[Eishes Chayil|Proverbs 31]] 10, 29. Women are commended when they are virtuous.
*{{bibleref|Nehemiah|6:14}}. The prophetess [[Noadiah]] is mentioned. A false prophet who antagonized Nehemiah.
*{{bibleref|Isaiah|8:3}}. An anonymous prophetess is mentioned.
*{{bibleref|Joel|2:28–29}}. A prophetic forecast that women and men alike will prophesy.
* Acts 9:36. A woman, Tabitha, Dorcas in Greek, is called a disciple. Who was full of good works and alms deeds.
*{{bibleref|Romans|16:1}}. A woman, [[Phoebe]], is called a "diakonos," 
*{{bibleref|Galatians|3:28}}. "There is neither…male nor female for all are one in Christ Jesus."

==Bibliography==

* Patricia M. Berliner, Ph.D., ''Touching Your Lifethread and Revaluing the Feminine'' Cloverdale Books (2007) ISBN 978-1-929569-20-5 [http://www.cloverdalebooks.com/CloverdaleBooks/TYL_RTF.html]
* Mimi Haddad, Ph.D., "Egalitarian Pioneers: Betty Friedan or Catherine Booth?" ''Priscilla Papers,'' Vol. 20, No. 4 (Autumn 2006)
* [[Pamela Sue Anderson]], ''A feminist philosophy of religion: the rationality and myths of religious belief'' (Oxford; Malden, Mass.: Blackwell, 1998) 
* [[Pamela Sue Anderson]] and Beverley Clack, eds., ''Feminist philosophy of religion: critical readings'' (London: Routledge, 2004)
* John Temple Bristow, ''What [[Paul]] Really Said About Women: An Apostle's Liberating Views on Equality in Marriage, Leadership and Love'' (San Francisco: Harper &amp; Row, 1988)

==References==
&lt;references/&gt;

==See also==
*[[Christian egalitarianism]]
*[[Christian views about women]]
*[[Christian views of marriage]]
*[[Complementarian]]

==External links==
* [http://www.users.csbsju.edu/~eknuth/xpxx/ Christian Feminist articles and books]

[[Category:Christian theology]]
[[Category:Feminist theory]]
[[Category:Liberation theology]]
[[Category:Religious feminism]]
[[Category:Genesis]]

[[hr:Kršćanski feminizam]]
[[pl:Chrześcijaństwo feministyczne]]
[[sh:Kršćanski feminizam]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>