<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20150709105913|670660958" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="5686076" pageid="5686076" ns="0" title="Christian feminism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2015-08-14T05:17:09Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Feminism sidebar |variants}}

'''Christian feminism''' is an aspect of [[feminist theology]] which seeks to advance and understand the [[sexual equality|equality]] of [[men]] and [[women]] morally, socially, spiritually, and in leadership from a [[Christian]] perspective. Christian [[feminist]]s argue that contributions by women in that direction are necessary for a complete understanding of Christianity.&lt;ref&gt;Harrison, Victoria S. "Modern Women, Traditional Abrahamic Religions and Interpreting Sacred Texts." ''Feminist Theology: The Journal of the Britain &amp; Ireland School of Feminist Theology'' 15.2 (2007):145-159.&lt;/ref&gt; Christian feminists believe that [[God]] does not [[discriminate]] on the basis of biologically-determined characteristics such as sex and race.&lt;ref&gt;McPhillips, Kathleen. "Theme: Feminisms, Religions, Cultures, Identities." ''Australian Feminist Studies'' 14.30 (1999).&lt;/ref&gt; Their major issues include the [[ordination of women]], male dominance in Christian [[marriage]], recognition of equal spiritual and moral abilities, reproductive rights, and the search for a feminine or gender-transcendent divine.&lt;ref&gt;Daggers, Jenny. "Working for Change in the Position of Women in the Church." ''Feminist Theology: The Journal of the Britain &amp; Ireland School of Feminist Theology'' 26 (2001)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;McEwan, Dorothea. "The Future of Christian Feminist Theologies--As I Sense It: Musings on the Effects of Historiography and Space."&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;McIntosh, Esther. "The Possibility of a Gender-Transcendent God: Taking Macmurray Forward." ''Feminist Theology: The Journal of the Britain &amp; Ireland School of Feminist Theology'' 15 (2007): 236-255.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Polinska, Wioleta. "In Woman's Image: An Iconography for God." ''Feminist Theology'' 13.1 (2004):40-61&lt;/ref&gt; Christian feminists often draw on the teachings of other religions and ideologies in addition to biblical evidence.&lt;ref&gt;Clack, Beverly. "Thealogy and Theology: Mutually Exclusive or Creatively Interdependent? ''Feminist Theology: The Journal of the Britain &amp; Ireland School of Feminist Theology'' 21 (1999):21-38.&lt;/ref&gt;

The term [[Christian egalitarianism]] is often preferred by those advocating gender equality and equity among Christians who do not wish to associate themselves with the feminist movement.&lt;ref&gt;Groothuis, Rebecca M., Ronald Pierce and Gordon Fee (eds.), [http://www.christianethicstoday.com/CET/CET/CETJournal.pdf Feminism Goes to Seed]&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==

Some Christian feminists believe that the principle of egalitarianism was present in the teachings of [[Jesus]] and the early Christian movements, but this is a highly contested view. These interpretations of Christian origins have been criticized for "anachronistically projecting contemporary ideals back into the first century."&lt;ref&gt;Beavis, Mary Ann. "Christian Origins, Egalitarianism, and Utopia." ''Journal of Feminist Studies in Religion'' 23.2 (2007): 27-49&lt;/ref&gt; In the [[Middle Ages]] [[Julian of Norwich]] and [[Hildegard of Bingen]] explored the idea of a divine power with both masculine and feminine aspects.&lt;ref&gt;Bauerschmidt, Frederick Christian. "Seeing Jesus: Julian of Norwich and the Text of Christ's Body." ''Journal of Medieval and Early Modern Studies'' 27.2 (1997):189-214.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Boyce-Tillman, June. "Hildegard of Bingen: A Woman for our Time." ''Feminist Theology'' 22 (1999):25-41.&lt;/ref&gt; Feminist works from the fifteenth to seventeenth centuries addressed objections to women learning, teaching and preaching in a religious context.&lt;ref&gt;McEwan, Dorothea. "The Future of Christian Feminist Theologies--As I Sense It: Musings on the Effects of Historiography and Space." 79-92.&lt;/ref&gt; One such proto-feminist was [[Anne Hutchinson]] who was cast out of the [[Puritan]] colony of [[Massachusetts]] for teaching on the dignity and rights of women.&lt;ref&gt;Ellsberg, Robert. ''All Saints: Daily Reflections on Saints, Prophets, and Witnesses from Our Time''&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[First-wave feminism|first wave]] of feminism in the nineteenth and early twentieth centuries included an increased interest in the place of women in religion. Women who were campaigning for their rights began to question their inferiority both within the church and in other spheres justified by church teachings.&lt;ref&gt;Capitani, Diane. "Imagining God in Our Ways: The Journals of Frances E. Willard." ''Feminist Theology: The Journal of the Britain &amp; Ireland School of Feminist Theology'' 12.1 (2003):57-88.&lt;/ref&gt; Some Christian feminists of this  period were [[Marie Maugeret]], [[Katharine Bushnell]], [[Catherine Booth]], [[Frances Willard (suffragist)|Frances Willard]], and [[Elizabeth Cady Stanton]].

== Issues ==
{{Christianity and gender|positions}}

=== Women in church leadership ===
{{main|Ordination of women}}

In both mainline and liberal branches of [[Protestantism|Protestant Christianity]], women are ordained as [[clergy]]. Even some theologically conservative denominations, such as [[Assemblies of God]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|date=1990-08-14 |url=http://ag.org/top/beliefs/position_papers/pp_downloads/pp_4191_women_ministry.pdf |title=The Role of Women in Ministry |format=[[Portable Document Format|PDF]] |pages=7 |publisher=The General Council of the Assemblies of God}}&lt;/ref&gt; ordain women as pastors. However, the [[Roman Catholic Church]], the [[Orthodox Church]], the [[Southern Baptist Convention]] (the largest Protestant denomination in the U.S.),&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sbc.net/aboutus/pswomen.asp SBC Position Statements - Women in Ministry]&lt;/ref&gt; as well as [[The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]] (LDS Church), and most churches in the American [[Evangelicalism|Evangelical]] movement prohibit women from entering clerical positions.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.springerlink.com/content/l5p31j7w2q316882/ SpringerLink - Journal Article ]&lt;/ref&gt; Some Christian feminists believe that as women have greater opportunity to receive theological training, they will have greater influence on how scriptures are interpreted by those that deny women the right to become ministers.&lt;ref&gt;Harrison, Victoria S. "Modern Women, Traditional Abrahamic Religions and Interpreting Sacred Texts." ''Feminist Theology: The Journal of the Britain &amp; Ireland School of Feminist Theology'' 15.2 (2007):145-159&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Women as spiritually deficient ===

Understanding whether women are spiritually deficient to men partly hinges on whether women are equipped spiritually with discernment to teach. The following passages also relate to whether women are inherently spiritually discerning as men:

* {{Bibleref2|Galatians|3:28}}. "There is neither…male nor female for all are one in Christ Jesus."
* [[Deborah]] of the [[Old Testament]] was a [[prophetess]] and "judge of Israel"&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.amit.org.il/learning/english/JW/Deborah.htm Deborah the Prophetess]&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{Bibleref2|Genesis|2:20}}. The word translated "help" or "helper" is the same Hebrew word, "ēzer," which the Old Testament uses more than 17 times to describe the kind of help that God brings to His people in times of need; e.g., "Thou art my help (ēzer) and my deliverer," and "My help ''(ēzer)'' comes from the Lord." Never once in all these references is the word used to indicate subordination or servitude to another human being.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.godswordtowomen.org/ezerkenegdo.htm "Ezer Kenegdo" Word Study. God's Word to Women, 2011]&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{Bibleref2|Genesis|3:16}}. "To the woman he (God) said, 'I will greatly increase your pains in childbearing; in pain you shall bring forth children, yet your desire shall be for your husband, and he shall rule over you.{{' "}}
* {{Bibleref2|Timothy|2:12}}. "But I suffer not a woman to teach, nor to usurp authority over the man, but to be in silence."
* {{Bibleref2|1 Corinthians|11:7-9}}. "For a man ought not to cover his head, since he is the image and glory of God, but woman is the glory of man. For man was not made from woman, but woman from man. Neither was man created for woman, but woman for man."
* {{Bibleref2|1 Corinthians|14:34}}. "The women should keep silent in the churches. For they are not permitted to speak, but should be in submission, as the Law also says."
* {{Bibleref2|Colossians|3:18}}. "Wives, submit to your husbands, as is fitting in the Lord."
* {{Bibleref2|1 Peter|3:1}}. "Likewise, wives, be subject to your own husbands, so that even if some do not obey the word, they may be won without a word by the conduct of their wives."

=== Reproduction, sexuality and religion ===
{{See also|Christianity and abortion}}

Conservative religious groups are often at philosophical odds with many feminist and liberal religious groups over [[abortion]] and the use of [[birth control]]. Scholars like sociologist Flann Campbell have argued that conservative religious denominations tend to restrict [[male]] and [[female]] sexuality&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jstor.org/view/00324728/di980713/98p0182w/0?frame=noframe&amp;userID=83d82910/01cc99331400501c40fcb&amp;dpi=3&amp;config=jstor Birth Control and Christian Churches]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=yUWz24sVu54C&amp;pg=PP13 Ordaining Women: Culture and Conflict in Religious Organizations]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jstor.org/view/00324728/di980713/98p0182w/0 Birth Control and Christian Churches]&lt;/ref&gt; by prohibiting or limiting birth control use,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/paul_vi/encyclicals/documents/hf_p-vi_enc_25071968_humanae-vitae_en.html Paul VI - Humanae Vitae&lt;!-- Bot-generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; and condemning abortion as [[sin]]ful [[murder]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.johnstonsarchive.net/baptist/sbcabres.html Southern Baptist Convention Resolutions on Abortion&lt;!-- Bot-generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bible-knowledge.com/Sin-of-Abortion.html Sin of Abortion and the Reasons Why&lt;!-- Bot-generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Some Christian feminists (like [[Teresa Forcades]]) contend that a woman's "right to control her [[pregnancy]] is bounded by considerations of her own well-being" and that restricted access to birth control and abortion disrespect her God-given [[choice|free will]].&lt;ref&gt;Colker, Ruth. "Feminism, Theology, and Abortion: Toward Love, Compassion, and Wisdom." ''California Law Review'' 77 (1989):1011-1075.&lt;/ref&gt;

A number of socially [[Christian left|progressive]] mainline Protestant denominations as well as certain [[Jew]]ish organizations and the group [[Catholics for Choice|Catholics for a Free Choice]] have formed the [[Religious Coalition for Reproductive Choice]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rcrc.org/about/members.cfm RCRC—Member Organizations&lt;!-- Bot-generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; The RCRC often works as a liberal feminist organization and in conjunction with other American feminist groups to oppose conservative religious denominations which, from their perspective, seek to suppress the natural reproductive rights of women.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nwlc.org/details.cfm?id=1223&amp;section=Reproductive%20Rights%3A%20General%20Materials National Women's Law Center&lt;!-- Bot-generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Feminine or Gender-transcendent God ===

Some Christian feminists believe that gender equality within the church cannot be achieved without rethinking the portrayal and understanding of [[God]] as a [[masculinity|masculine]] being.&lt;ref&gt;Kim, Grace. "Revisioning Christ." ''Feminist Theology: The Journal of the Britain &amp; Ireland School of Feminist Theology'' 28 (2001):82-91.&lt;/ref&gt; The theological concept of [[Sophia (wisdom)|Sophia]], usually seen as replacing the [[Holy Spirit]] in the [[Trinity]], is often used to fulfill this desire for symbols which reflect women's religious experiences. How Sophia is configured is not static, but usually filled with emotions and individual expression.&lt;ref&gt;McEwan, Dorothea. "The Future of Christian Feminist Theologies--As I Sense It: Musings on the Effects of Historiography and Space." 79-92.&lt;/ref&gt; For some Christian feminists, the Sophia concept is found in a search for women who reflect contemporary feminist ideals in both the Old and New Testament. Some figures used for this purpose include the [[Virgin Mary]], [[Mary Magdalene]],&lt;ref&gt;Winkett, Lucy. "Go Tell! Thinking About Mary Magdalene." ''Feminist Theology: The Journal of the Britain &amp; Ireland School of Feminist Theology'' 29 (2002):19-31.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Eve]],&lt;ref&gt;Isherwood, Lisa. "The British Christian Women's Movement: A Rehabilitation of Eve." ''Feminist Theology: The Journal of the Britain &amp; Ireland School of Feminist Theology'' 15.1 (2006): 128-129.&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Esther]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Esther Fuchs|Fuchs, Esther]]. "Reclaiming the Hebrew Bible for Women." ''Journal of Feminist Studies in Religion'' 24.2 (2008):45-65.&lt;/ref&gt; Others see God as entirely gender-transcendent.&lt;ref&gt;McIntosh, Esther. "The Possibility of a Gender-Transcendent God: Taking Macmurray Forward." ''Feminist Theology: The Journal of the Britain &amp; Ireland School of Feminist Theology'' 15 (2007):236-255.&lt;/ref&gt; or focus on the feminine aspects of God and [[Jesus]].&lt;ref&gt;Kim, Grace. "Revisioning Christ." ''Feminist Theology: The Journal of the Britain &amp; Ireland School of Feminist Theology'' 28 (2001):82-91.&lt;/ref&gt; Some Christian feminists use and promote gender neutral and/or feminine language and imagery to describe God and/or Christ. The [[United Church of Christ]] describes its [[New Century Hymnal]], published in 1995, as "the only hymnal released by a Christian church that honors in equal measure both male and female images of God." &lt;ref&gt;http://www.ucc.org/about-us/old-firsts.html&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!-- ===Women submitting to husbands===
The following passages relate to whether wives must submit to their husbands:

* {{Bibleref2|Ephesians|5:22}} Women are told to submit to their husbands.

=== Head coverings ===

In {{Bibleref|1Corinthians|11:3–17}}, women are commanded to cover their heads in worship to show they recognize their husband's authority coming from the fact that man was created first and that he was created in God's image. However, one interpretation of this passage points out that Paul goes on to note that this was not necessary and that it was merely a cultural phenomenon, and whether women covered their heads or not was unimportant and not explicitly required.{{Fact|date=October 2008}}

== The Bible ==
{{Original research|date=April 2008}}

A major fundamental of Christian Feminism is how people interpret the [[Bible]], particularly the influence of one's set of presuppositions on understanding the Bible. The same passages that one [[Christian denomination|denomination]] takes to say that women may do all sorts of very important things, but not preach to adult men, a Christian feminist might interpret otherwise. An historical approach can influence a Christian feminist's understanding of a passage by taking into account the specific [[cultural]] setting and circumstance of the time that the passage was written.

=== Some problematic passages ===

A variety of biblical passages are used as authority to encourage women to not want leadership roles, exclusively in marriage and the pastorate.

* {{Bibleref|Job|2:10}} Job rebukes his wife for speaking as a foolish woman. The Bible also mentions men being foolish in many places.
* {{Bibleref|Ecclesiastes|7:27-28}}{{Clarifyme|date=October 2008}}

* {{Bibleref|Acts|1:21}} In English, being male appears as a prerequisite for apostlehood but in Greek{{Fact|date=June 2008}} the word encompasses both genders.
* {{Bibleref|1Corinthians|11:3–16}} In some interpretations, women are commanded to cover their heads in worship to show they recognize their husband's authority coming from the fact that man was created first.
* {{Bibleref|1Corinthians|14:34–35}} Women are told to be quiet in church.
* {{Bibleref|Ephesians|5:22}} Women are told to submit to their husbands.
* {{Bibleref|1Timothy|2:11–12}} Women are told to be quiet in church because man was created first, and woman was deceived and sinned first.
* {{Bibleref|Revelation|2:20}} The church of Thyatira is rebuked for letting a women teach. But this is not to be considered as against women. The problem here is the teacher is leading people to sexual sins.{{Fact|date=October 2008}}

=== Supportive passages ===

* {{Bibleref|Exodus|15:20}} [[Miriam]] is called a [[prophet]]ess.
* {{Bibleref|Judges|4:4}} [[Deborah]], a prophetess, the wife of Lappidoth, leads Israel at as a Judge and a General.
* [[Eishes Chayil|Proverbs 31]] 10, 29 Women are commended when they are virtuous and valued as breadwinners. The 'virtuous woman' is described as a manager of financial affairs.
* {{Bibleref|Isaiah|8:3}} An anonymous prophetess is mentioned.
* {{Bibleref|Joel|2:28–29}} A prophetic forecast that women and men alike will prophesy.
* {{Bibleref|Luke|2:34–38}} Anna the prophetess is present for the [[male genital mutilation|circumcision]] of baby Jesus.
* Acts 9:36 A woman, Tabitha (Dorcas in Greek) is called a disciple "full of good works and almsdeeds".
* {{Bibleref|Romans|16:1}} A woman, [[Phoebe]], is called a "diakonos," a Greek word meaning "one who serves", from which the English word "deacon" came.
* {{Bibleref|Galatians|3:28}} "There is neither…male nor female for all are one in Christ Jesus."

--&gt;

== See also ==
{{multicol}}
* [[Anti-pornography feminism]]
* [[Biblical patriarchy]]
* [[Christian egalitarianism]]
* [[Christian humanism]]
* [[Christianity and abortion]]
* [[Christian views of marriage]]
{{multicol-break}}
* [[Complementarianism]]
* [[Evangelical and Ecumenical Women's Caucus]]
* [[Feminist theology]]
* [[Gender roles in Christianity]]
* [[HerChurch]]
* [[Liberation theology]]
{{multicol-break}}
* [[Ordination of women]]
* [[Political theology]]
* [[Progressive Christianity]]
* [[Sacred feminine]]
* [[Women in the Bible]]
* [[Women in Church history]]
{{multicol-end}}

== References ==
{{div col}}
&lt;references/&gt;
{{div col end}}

== Further reading ==

* [[Rosemary Radford Ruether]], ''Feminist Theologies: Legacy and Prospect'' (Minneapolis, MN: Fortress Press, 2007)
* Patricia M. Berliner, Ph.D., ''Touching Your Lifethread and Revaluing the Feminine'' Cloverdale Books (2007) ISBN 978-1-929569-20-5 [http://www.cloverdalebooks.com/CloverdaleBooks/TYL_RTF.html]
* Mimi Haddad, Ph.D., "Egalitarian Pioneers: Betty Friedan or Catherine Booth?" ''Priscilla Papers,'' Vol. 20, No. 4 (Autumn 2006)
* Eryl W. Davies, ''The Dissenting Reader: Feminist Approaches to the Hebrew Bible'' (Burlington, VT: Ashgate, 2003)
* [[Pamela Sue Anderson]], ''A feminist philosophy of religion: the rationality and myths of religious belief'' (Oxford; Malden, Mass.: Blackwell, 1998)
* [[Pamela Sue Anderson]] and Beverley Clack, eds., ''Feminist philosophy of religion: critical readings'' (London: Routledge, 2004)
* [[Letty M. Russell]], ''Church in the Round'' (Westminster John Knox Press, 1993)
* John Temple Bristow, ''What Paul Really Said About Women: An Apostle's Liberating Views on Equality in Marriage, Leadership and Love'' (San Francisco: Harper &amp; Row, 1988)
* Patricia Wilson-Kastner, ''Faith, Feminism, and the Christ'' (Philadelphia: Fortress Press, 1983).

== Journals ==

* Journal of Feminist Studies in Religion. [http://www.fsrinc.org/jfsr/]
* The Woman's Pulpit.

== External links ==
* [http://www.users.csbsju.edu/~eknuth/xpxx/ Christian Feminist articles and books]
* [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9fszLvrWGko Radio Interview with Dr. Rosemary Radford Ruether on Ecofeminism and Christianity], University of Toronto, 16 February 2007.

{{Christianity and politics}}
{{Relpolnav}}
{{Theology}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Christian Feminism}}
[[Category:Christian feminism| ]]
[[Category:Christianity and women]]
[[Category:Christian theological movements]]
[[Category:Feminist theology]]
[[Category:Feminist theory]]
[[Category:Liberation theology]]
[[Category:Women's rights in religious movements]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>