<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20031004203913|1525362" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="26636309" pageid="26636309" ns="0" title="Progressivism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2003-10-04T20:39:54Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Progressive''' is a term often used by those on the political left to describe their beliefs.  This term is preferred by many over the more traditional label in American politics, [[liberal]], because of the association of '[[liberal]]' with the centrist politics of many Democratic Party politicians (such as Al Gore) in recent years.  The term "progressive" is thus used to avoid confusion between the politicized term "[[liberal]]" and genuine philosophical views focused on social change.

"Progressive" is used in place of ''liberal'' to best describe philosophical ideals that are opposite and contrasted to those held by [[conservatism|conservatives]]. Political ideas that advocate rapid social change, are likely to be &lt;b&gt;progressive&lt;/b&gt;, while conservative ideas tend to reflect an adherence to established norms and support for (or furtherance of) status quo interests. Continuing logically, by this spectrum, a philosophy that advocated reversing course to previous standards would be ''regressive'', though this term is rarely used.  Instead, the term ''[[reactionary]]'' is more frequently used to describe those who wish to adhere to established convention.

This is particularly useful when dealing with philosophical positions, since the liberal tradition has very particular and fixed [[the Enlightenment|Enlightenment]] connotations that may not necessarily have any useful meaning in the Left political scene.

The term has its origin in American politics in the early part of the twentieth century.  During this period, known as the [[Progressive Era]], many reforms were enacted.  Some third-party presidential candidates ran for office during this time under the Progressive Party label, notably [[Robert M. La Follette, Sr.]].  The [[Progressive Party of Canada]] also briefly rose to prominence in the [[1920s]].


This term is also used in [[Canada]], since many liberals are not Liberals, i.e. do not support the centrist [[Liberal Party of Canada]]. Not to be confused with the [[Progressive Conservative Party|Progressive Conservatives.]]

=== External links and references ===
* [http://www.libertyforums.com/ LibertyForums] - Classical Liberal, Libertarian &amp; Objectivist Discussion Board</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>