<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20051106041433|27502797" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="26636309" pageid="26636309" ns="0" title="Progressivism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-11-11T19:47:09Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Progressivism}}

'''Political Progressivism''' or simply '''Progressivism''' is an [[ideology]] and [[political philosophy]] whose adherents promote policies that they believe would reform a country's government, economy, or society. As a broad characterization of political leanings, political progressivism can refer to [[Left-wing politics|left]] or [[antiestablishmentarianism]], in which case it may be right or left, as long as the platform is [[reformist]].The term can be used by economic liberals, who are generally placed on the "right" of the political spectrum. An example of this is in Ireland (See below) Progressivism may also mean prefering moderate change, oppose to mimimal or maximum change. In this sense, it is contrasted with [[Reactionary]], [[Conservative]], as well as [[radical]] ideology. 

==Around the world==

===United States===
''See main article - [[Progressivism in the United States]]

Progressives in the US were strong in the early parts of the 20th century. Today it is equated to movements on the left ranging from [[liberalism|liberal]] to [[democratic socialist]].

===Australia===
The term ''progressive'' is popular in [[Australia]], since many on the left usually support either the [[Australian Labor Party|Labor Party]], the [[Australian Democrats|Democrats]] or the [[Australian Greens|Greens]], opposed to the right-wing [[Liberal Party of Australia]].

===Canada===
The term ''progressive'' is also popular in [[Canada]], since many are further left than the [[Liberal Party of Canada]].  Most supporters of the old [[Progressive Conservative Party of Canada]] did not consider themselves progressive although arguments have been made that the Mulroney government implemented progressive environmental policies. The David Orchard wing of the old PC Party was progressive in nature while the Red Tory faction, which included former Prime Minister Joe Clark, was less so. The [[New Democratic Party]] often considers itself progressive, and attempts to appeal to progressive voters.

The [[Progressive Party of Canada]] briefly rose to prominence in the [[1920s]]. The [[Progressive Canadian Party]], composed mostly of anti-merger Progressive Conservatives, was formed several months prior to the [[Canadian federal election, 2004|2004 general election]].

===Ireland===
In Ireland The [[Progressive Democrats]] (in Irish An Páirtí Daonlathach, literal back-translation: The Democratic Party) is a free market liberal party in the [[Republic of Ireland]] founded in 1985.

The Progressive Democrats’ economic policies are based on liberal economics. They support a free enterprise, low tax and pro-competition policy base.


The party is often described as [[right wing]] by supporters and critics alike, but they have several policies which are closer to the [[left wing]].
768

===New Zealand===
[[Jim Anderton]] formed the [[New Zealand Progressive Party]] by splitting from the [[Alliance (New Zealand political party)]].

The [[Progressive Green Party (New Zealand)|Progressive Green Party]] was formed in [[1995]] but has now disbanded.

Progressive voters also support the [[Green Party of Aotearoa New Zealand]] and the [[New Zealand Labour Party]].

==See also==
* [[Progressive Party (United States)|Progressive Party]], which refers to 3 different parties of different periods, to see how the term progressive has been used in political campaigns in the past.
* [[Progressive Christianity]]
* [[Reform movement]]
* [[Social democracy]]
* [[real movment]]
* [[Techno-progressivism]]

==References==

[[George Lakoff]]. ''Don't Think of an Elephant: Know Your Values and Frame the Debate''. Chelsea Green Publishing, 2004. ISBN 1-931498-71-7

==External links==
*[http://www.commondreams.org/headlines04/0630-20.htm A list of popular Progressive websites] - From CommonDreams.org
*[http://www.airamericaradio.com Air America Radio] - Progressive radio network
*[http://www.americanprogress.org/ The Center for American Progress] - A self-styled progressive think tank in Washington, DC
*[http://acthere.com/ America Coming Together] - Political Action Committee mobilizing progressive voters
*[http://www.prospect.org The American Prospect] - Progressive magazine and non-profit think-tank.
*[http://www.dailykos.com Daily Kos] - Web log, or blog, and online discussion of progressive events
*[http://www.democrats.org/ Democratic National Committee]
*[http://www.democraticunderground.com Democratic Underground] - Progressive news views and active progressive message boards
*[http://www.gp.org Green Party of the United States] - Third party considered by some to be the modern equivalent to a Progressive Party 
*[http://www.moveon.org MoveOn.org] - Progressive political action organization
*[http://www.pdamerica.org Progressive Democrats of America]
*[http://www.progressivedepot.com Progressive Depot] - Online mall contributing profits to progressive organizations
* [http://www.progressivetexan.com Progressive Texan] - Web log, or blog, about progressive issues affecting Texas
*[http://www.rockridgeinstitute.org Rockridge Institute] - Progressive think-tank
*[http://www.talkingpointsmemo.com Talking Points Memo] - Web log, or blog, offering progressive political opinion
*[http://www.alternet.org/wiretap/23706/ "What Is Progressive?"], [http://www.alternet.org/ ''AlterNet''] opinion piece, July 25th 2005
*[http://www.ourfuture.org/ Campaign for America's Future] A progressive non-profit thinktank
*[http://www.cybartv.org European progressive media

===Resources for Studying Progressivism===
*[http://www.progressiveu.org Progressive U]

[[ko:진보주의]]
[[ja:革新]]
[[nl:Progressivisme]]
[[Category:Political theories]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>