<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20141101015403|631963321" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="26636309" pageid="26636309" ns="0" title="Progressivism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2014-11-01T02:16:29Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{other uses}}
{{verification|date=October 2014}}
{{Progressivism}}
'''Progressivism''' is a broad [[philosophy]] based on the [[Idea of Progress]], which asserts that advancement in science, technology, [[economic development]], and [[social organization]] are vital to improve the [[human condition]]. Progressivism became highly significant during the [[Age of Enlightenment]] in [[Europe]], out of the belief that Europe was demonstrating that societies could progress in civility from barbaric conditions to civilization through strengthening the basis of [[empirical evidence|empirical knowledge]] as the foundation of society.&lt;ref name="Harold Mah 1914. p157"&gt;Harold Mah. Enlightenment Phantasies: Cultural Identity in France and Germany, 1750-1914. Cornell University. (2003). p157.&lt;/ref&gt; Figures of the Enlightenment believed that progress had [[Universal (metaphysics)|universal]] application to all societies and that these ideas would spread across the world from Europe.&lt;ref name="Harold Mah 1914. p157"/&gt; Sociologist [[Robert Nisbet]] finds that "No single idea has been more important than ... the Idea of Progress in Western civilization for three thousand years" and defines five "crucial premises" of the Idea of Progress as being: value of the past, nobility of Western civilization, worth of economic/technological growth, faith in reason and scientific/scholarly knowledge obtained through reason, intrinsic importance and worth of life on earth.&lt;ref&gt;Nisbet, Robert (1980). History of the Idea of Progress. New York: Basic Books. p. 4.&lt;/ref&gt; Beyond this, the meanings of progressivism have varied over time and from different perspectives.

==History==
The Progressive Movement, historically associated with [[left-wing politics]], began in the late 19th and early 20th centuries in cities with settlement workers and reformers who were interested in helping those facing harsh conditions at home and at work. The reformers spoke out about the need for laws regulating tenement housing and child labor. They also called for better working conditions for women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Women's Trade Union League of Chicago Collection: An inventory of its records at the University of Illinois at Chicago|url=http://www.uic.edu/depts/lib/specialcoll/services/rjd/findingaids/WTULb.html|publisher=University of Illinois at Chicago|accessdate=13 June 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; It also contributed to the development of [[progressive education]].

Political parties such as the [[Progressive Party 1912 (United States)|Progressive Party]] were organized at the start of the 20th century, and progressivism was embraced in the administrations of American presidents [[Theodore Roosevelt]], [[Woodrow Wilson]], [[Franklin Delano Roosevelt]] and [[Lyndon Baines Johnson]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last = | first = | authorlink = | coauthors = | url=http://www.bartleby.com/65/pr/progrsvsm.html | title =Progressivism | work = | publisher =The Columbia Encyclopedia, Sixth Edition. 2001-05. | accessdate =2006-11-18}}{{Dead link|date=June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Moreover, in [[Europe]] and [[Canada]], the term "progressive" has occasionally been used by groups not particularly left-wing. The [[Progressive Democrats]] in the [[Republic of Ireland]] took the name "progressivism" despite being considered centre-right or [[Classical liberalism|classical liberal]]. The [[European Progressive Democrats]] was a mainly heterogeneous political group in the [[European Union]].

==Philosophy==
[[Immanuel Kant]] identified progress as being a movement away from barbarism towards civilization. Eighteenth century philosopher and political scientist [[Marquis de Condorcet]] pre­dicted that political progress would involve the disappearance of slavery, the rise of literacy, the lessening of in­equalities between the sexes, reforms of harsh prisons and the decline of poverty.&lt;ref&gt;Nisbet, Robert (1980). History of the Idea of Progress. New York: Basic Books. ch 5&lt;/ref&gt; "[[Modernity]]" or "modernization" was a key form of the idea of progress as promoted by [[Classical liberalism|classical liberals]] in the 19th and 20th centuries, who called for the rapid modernization of the economy and society to remove the traditional hindrances to [[free market]]s and [[Freedom of movement|free movements]] of people.&lt;ref&gt;Joyce Appleby, Lynn Hunt, and Margaret Jacob, ''Telling the Truth about History'' (1995) p. 78&lt;/ref&gt; German philosopher [[Georg Wilhelm Friedrich Hegel]] was influential in promoting the [[Idea of Progress]] in European philosophy by emphasizing a linear-progressive conception of history and rejecting a cyclical conception of history. [[Karl Marx]] applied the [[Hegelianism|Hegelian]] conception of linear-progressive history, the modernization of the economy through industrialization, and criticisms of the social class structure of industrial capitalist societies, to develop the ideology of [[communism]]. As industrialization grew, concerns over its effects grew beyond [[Marxism|Marxist]] and other radical critiques and became mainstream.

==Political Progressivism==
The contemporary political conception of progressivism in the [[Western culture|culture of the Western world]] emerged from the vast [[social change]]s brought about by [[industrialization]] in the Western world in the late 19th century, particularly out of the view that progress was being stifled by vast [[economic inequality]] between the rich and the poor, minimally regulated ''[[laissez-faire]]'' [[capitalism]] with out-of-control [[monopoly|monopolistic]] [[corporation]]s, intense and often violent conflict between workers and capitalists, and a need for measures to address these problems.&lt;ref name="nugent"&gt;{{cite book | title=Progressivism: A Very Short Introduction | publisher=Oxford University Press | author=Nugent, Walter | year=2010 | isbn=9780195311068| pages=2}}&lt;/ref&gt; Progressivism has influenced various political movements. [[social liberalism|Modern liberalism]] was influenced by [[Liberalism|liberal]] philosopher [[John Stuart Mill]]'s conception of people being "progressive beings".&lt;ref&gt;Alan Ryan. ''The Making of Modern Liberalism''. P. 25.&lt;/ref&gt; British Prime Minister [[Benjamin Disraeli]] developed [[progressive conservatism]] under "[[One nation conservatism|One Nation]]" [[Toryism]].&lt;ref&gt;Patrick Dunleavy, Paul Joseph Kelly, Michael Moran. ''British Political Science: Fifty Years of Political Studies''. Oxford, England, UK; Malden, Massachusetts, USA: Wiley-Blackwell, 2000. Pp. 107-108.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Robert Blake. Disraeli. Second Edition. London, England, UK: Eyre &amp; Spottiswoode (Publishers) Ltd, 1967. Pp. 524.&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly in Germany, Chancellor [[Otto von Bismarck]] enacted various progressive social welfare measures out of conservative motivations to distance workers from the socialist movement and as humane ways to assist in maintaining the industrial revolution.&lt;ref&gt;Union Contributions to Labor Welfare Policy and Practice: Past, Present and Future. Routledge, 16, 2013. P172.&lt;/ref&gt; Proponents of [[social democracy]] have identified themselves as promoting the progressive cause.&lt;ref&gt;Henning Meyer, Jonathan Rutherford. The Future of European Social Democracy: Building the Good Society. Palgrave Macmillan, 2012. P108.&lt;/ref&gt;  The [[Catholic Church]] encyclical ''[[Rerum novarum]]'' issued by [[Pope Leo XIII]] in 1891, condemned the exploitation of labour and urged support for labour unions, government regulation of businesses in the interests of social justice, while upholding the rights of private property and criticizing socialism.&lt;ref&gt;Faith Jaycox. The Progressive Era. New York, New York: Infobase Publishing, 2005. P85.&lt;/ref&gt; A [[Protestantism|Protestant]] progressive outlook called the [[Social Gospel]] emerged in North America that focused on challenging economic exploitation and poverty, and by the mid-1890s the Social Gospel was common in many Protestant theological seminaries in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;Faith Jaycox. The Progressive Era. New York, New York: Infobase Publishing, 2005. P84.&lt;/ref&gt;

In America, progressivism began as a social movement in the late 19th and early 20th centuries and grew into a political movement, in what was known as the [[Progressive Era]]. American progressives rejected [[Social Darwinism]], believing that the problems society faced (poverty, violence, greed, racism, class warfare) could best be addressed by providing good education, a safe environment, and an efficient workplace. Progressives lived mainly in the cities, were college educated, and believed that government could be a tool for change.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gwu.edu/~erpapers/teachinger/glossary/progressive-era.cfm he Progressive Era (1890 - 1920)], The Eleanor Roosevelt Papers Project (retrieved 31 September 2014).&lt;/ref&gt; American President [[Theodore Roosevelt]] of the US [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican Party]] and later the US [[Progressive Party (United States, 1912)|Progressive Party]] declared that he "always believed that wise progressivism and wise conservatism go hand in hand".&lt;ref&gt;Jonathan Lurie. William Howard Taft: The Travails of a Progressive Conservative. New York, New York, USA: Cambridge University Press, 2012. p. 196.&lt;/ref&gt; American President [[Woodrow Wilson]] was also a member of the American progressive movement within the [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democratic Party]].

Progressive stances have evolved over time. In the late 19th century, for example, certain progressives argued for [[scientific racism]] on the grounds that it had a scientific basis.&lt;ref name="nugent"&gt;{{cite book | title=Progressivism: A Very Short Introduction | publisher=Oxford University Press | author=Nugent, Walter | year=2010 | isbn=9780195311068| pages=54}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Imperialism]] was a controversial issue within progressivism in the late 19th and early 20th centuries, particularly in the United States where some progressives supported [[American imperialism]] while others opposed it.&lt;ref name="nugent"&gt;{{cite book | title=Progressivism: A Very Short Introduction | publisher=Oxford University Press | author=Nugent, Walter | year=2010 | isbn=9780195311068| pages=33}}&lt;/ref&gt; In response to [[World War I]], progressive American President Woodrow Wilson's [[Fourteen Points]] established the concept of national [[self-determination]] and criticized imperialist competition and colonial injustices; these views were supported by [[Anti-imperialism|anti-imperialists]] in areas of the world that were resisting imperial rule.&lt;ref&gt;Reconsidering Woodrow Wilson: Progressivism, Internationalism, War, and Peace. P. 309.&lt;/ref&gt; During the period of acceptance of economic [[Keynesianism]], there was acceptance of a large role for state intervention in the economy, however with the rise of [[neoliberalism]] and challenges to state [[Interventionism (politics)|interventionist]] policies, [[centre-left]] progressive movements responded by creating the [[Third Way]] that emphasized a major role for the [[market economy]].&lt;ref&gt;Jane Lewis, Rebecca Surender. ''Welfare State Change: Towards a Third Way?''. Oxford University Press, 2004. Pp. 3-4, 16.&lt;/ref&gt; In the aftermath of the arising of the [[Great Recession]], economic policies established or influenced by neoliberalism have faced scrutiny and criticism in mainstream politics. There have been [[Social democracy|social democrats]] who have called for the social democratic movement to move past Third Way.&lt;ref&gt;After the Third Way: The Future of Social Democracy in Europe. I.B. Taurus, 2012. p. 47.&lt;/ref&gt; Prominent progressive conservative elements in the British Conservative Party have criticized neoliberalism.&lt;ref&gt;Hugh Bochel. The Conservative Party and Social Policy. The Policy Press, 2011. P. 108.&lt;/ref&gt;

==By country==

===Australia===
The term "progressive" is sometimes used to describe political organisations or policies in Australia, typically associated with left of centre politics. The [[Australian Labor Party]] is a member of the 
[[Progressive Alliance (political international)|Progressive Alliance]], and its official think tank, the [[Chifley Research Centre]], researches and promotes progressive policies and values. Third party [[Australian Greens|The Australian Greens]]&lt;ref&gt;http://greens.org.au/structure-charter&lt;/ref&gt; and activist group [[GetUp!]] also identify progressive change as key goals.

===Canada===
Western Canada began to receive an influx of political ideas at the end of the 19th century. The [[Progressive Party of Canada]] was founded in 1920 by [[Thomas Crerar]], a former [[Minister of Agriculture (Canada)|Minister of Agriculture]] in the [[Unionist Party (Canada)|Unionist]] government of [[Robert Borden]]. Crerar quit the Borden cabinet in 1919 because Minister of Finance Thomas White introduced a budget that Crerar felt did not pay sufficient attention to farmers' issues. Crerar became the first leader of the Progressive Party, and he led it to win 65 seats in the [[Canadian federal election, 1921|1921 general election]], placing second (ahead of the well-established Conservative Party).  The Progressives also had a close alignment with the provincial [[United Farmers of Canada|United Farmers]] parties in several provinces.  However, the Progressives were not able to hold their caucus together well, and progressive-leaning MPs and voters soon deserted the Progressives for the [[Liberals (Canada)|Liberals]] and the [[Co-operative Commonwealth Federation]] (later the [[New Democratic Party of Canada|New Democratic Party]]).{{citation needed|date=February 2012}}

Dating back to 1854, Canada's oldest political party was the [[Conservative Party of Canada (historical)|Conservative Party]].  Following that party's disastrous showing in the [[Canadian federal election, 1935|1935 election]] during the depths of the [[Great Depression in Canada|Great Depression]], the party was leaderless and lacked new ideas.  The party drafted [[Manitoba]] [[Premier (Canada)|Premier]] [[John Bracken]], a long-time leader of that province's progressive "United Farmers" party, who agreed to become leader of the Conservatives on condition that the party add ''Progressive'' to its name.  The party adopted the name "[[Progressive Conservative Party of Canada|Progressive Conservative]]", which it kept until its dissolution in 2003.  Despite the name change, most former Progressives continued to support other parties.{{citation needed|date=February 2012}}

During the debate over the merger of the Progressive Conservatives and the Alliance (2003), the meaning of the word caused contention again.  Since the Tories have stopped using the word "progressive" in their name federally, it has been used as a synonym for "centrist and centre left".  This has been apparent in the debate on a possible coalition between the NDP and the Liberals,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Heath|first=Jamey|title=NDP must cooperate with all progressive forces|url=http://www.thestar.com/opinion/editorialopinion/2012/03/08/ndp_must_cooperate_with_all_progressive_forces.html|newspaper=Toronto Star|date=Mar 8, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; or in discussions of strategic voting among leftist voters.

At the provincial level in [[Alberta]], the "progressive" element of the PCs was used in advertisements by [[Allison Redford]]'s leadership to attack the allegedly "regressive" nature of the [[Wildrose Party]] in the [[Alberta general election, 2012|2012 election]]. Liberal leader [[Raj Sherman]] challenged the PC's right to use the label.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Cryderman|first=Kelly|title=Sherman calls Redford’s "progressive" cred into question|url=http://blogs.calgaryherald.com/2012/04/12/sherman-calls-redfords-progressive-cred-into-question/|newspaper=Calgary Herald|date=April 12, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===India===
{{Unreferenced section|date=May 2014}}

In [[India]], there are a large number of state and national political parties. The [[National Democratic Alliance (India)|National Democratic Alliance]] (NDA) and the [[United Progressive Alliance]] (UPA) are the two political alliances in India, previously composed of leftist political parties that lean toward [[socialism]] and/or [[communism]], but since economic reforms took place in 1991 both national parties have established themselves as right wing reformists which lean toward more [[capitalism]]. Thus, the definition of "progressivism" may be interpreted differently in India, as communism was not a branch of thought that played any major role in the original western progressive movement. Furthermore, on a social level, the leftist parties in India do not espouse policies that would be considered progressive in the West, though policies in regards to the caste system, worker's rights, and women's rights are far more progressive than the non-progressive Indian parties. The [[Bharatiya Janata Party]] and the [[Indian National Congress]] are currently the chief members of the NDA and UPA coalitions respectively.{{citation needed|date=February 2012}}

===New Zealand===
The [[New Zealand Progressive Party]], led by [[Jim Anderton]], focused on the creation of jobs, full employment, the environment, free education, free healthcare and raising the legal age of alcohol consumption to 20.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last = | first = | authorlink = | coauthors = | year = | url =http://www.progressive.org.nz/Policy/poilcy.html | title =Policies | work = | publisher =New Zealand Progressive Party | accessdate =2010-03-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; The party was a junior member of the governing coalition in New Zealand from 2005 to 2008 during the second and third term of the [[fifth Labour Government of New Zealand]], and the coalition continued in opposition after the [[New Zealand general election, 2008|2008 election]].&lt;ref name="NZ_Herald_10543865"&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.nzherald.co.nz/nz-election-2008/news/article.cfm?c_id=1501799&amp;objectid=10543865 |title=Anderton to stay with Labour, even in opposition |date=November 19, 2008 |agency=[[NZPA]] |work=[[The New Zealand Herald]] |accessdate=November 4, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The party disbanded in 2012.

The [[Progressive Green Party (New Zealand)|Progressive Green Party]] was formed in 1995 as an economically [[right-wing]] "[[Blue Greens|blue-green]]" environmentalist party. After a poor showing in the [[New Zealand general election, 1996|1996 election]], the Party did not contest any further elections. It is now disbanded.

===Ukraine===
{{Unreferenced section|date=May 2014}}
&lt;!-- Image with inadequate rationale removed: [[File:Vitrenkoposter.jpeg|thumb| [[Nataliya Vitrenko]]'s 2004 election poster.]] --&gt;
The [[Progressive Socialist Party of Ukraine]] (''Prohresivna Sotsjalistychna Partiya Ukrayiny/Progressivnaya Sotsialističeskaja Partiya Ukrajiny'', Прогресивна соціалістична партія України) is a [[political party]] in [[Ukraine]], created by [[Nataliya Vitrenko]], a flamboyant former member of the [[Socialist Party of Ukraine]] in 1995. The Progressive Socialist Party of Ukraine is a radical left-wing populist party that supports integration with [[Russia]] and [[Belarus]] as an alternative to the [[European Union]]. PSPU traditionally campaigns on an anti-NATO, anti-IMF and pro-Russian platform. During the [[Ukrainian parliamentary election, 1998|1998 parliamentary elections]] the party got 4% of the vote, and its candidate for the [[Ukrainian presidential election, 1999|1999 presidential elections]], Nataliya Vitrenko, came in fourth. She received 10.97% of the vote in the first round.{{citation needed|date=February 2012}}

In the [[legislative]] [[Ukrainian parliamentary election, 2002|2002 parliamentary election]], the party established the Nataliya Vitrenko Bloc alliance, including the ''Partija Osvitjan Ukrajiny''. It received 3.22% of the votes, below the 4% threshold needed to enter the [[Verkhovna Rada]]. PSPU was a vocal opponent of President [[Leonid Kuchma]] but supported [[Viktor Yanukovych]], Ukrainian prime minister since 2002, during the [[Ukrainian presidential election, 2004|2004 presidential elections]]. After the [[Orange Revolution]] of 2004, the party joined the opposition to the new president [[Viktor Yushchenko]] in a coalition with the "[[Derzhava (Ukrainian party)|Derzhava]]" (State) party led by former Ukrainian prosecutor [[Gennady Vasilyev]].{{citation needed|date=February 2012}}

In the [[Ukrainian parliamentary election, 2006|2006 parliamentary elections]], the party again failed to gain seats in the parliament, participating as [[People's Opposition Bloc of Natalia Vitrenko]]. At the [[Ukrainian parliamentary election, 2007|2007 parliamentary elections]] the party failed once more to enter the parliament.{{citation needed|date=February 2012}}

===United Kingdom===
In the UK there are several parties who claim to be progressive, including the [[Labour Party (UK)|Labour Party]], the [[Liberal Democrats]], the [[Scottish National Party]], [[Plaid Cymru]] and the [[Green Party of England and Wales]]. The current coalition between the [[Conservative Party (UK)|Conservatives]] and the [[Liberal Democrats]] also claims to be progressive.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-politics-11785483 So what exactly is 'progressive' in politics?]&lt;/ref&gt;

====Scotland====
{{See also|Politics of Scotland}}

{{Unreferenced section|date=May 2014}}

The [[Progressives (Scotland)|Progressive Party]] was the name of a defunct municipal political organisation that operated in [[Scottish local government]] in the 20th century based around the [[Unionist Party (Scotland)|Unionist Party]], [[Scottish Liberals]] and [[Independent (politician)|Independents]].  The [[Scottish Progressives]], a party with the same registered name as the defunct party, was also established in 2007.{{citation needed|date=February 2012}}

National political parties were rarely active in local politics, but the rise of the [[Labour Party (UK)|Labour Party]] led to a process of party [[politicisation]] of private government. At first Labour were opposed by the Progressives before other national political parties entered local government elections on a significant scale.{{citation needed|date=February 2012}}

The Progressives formed as a loose alliance of unofficial [[Liberal Party (UK)|Liberals]], [[Unionism in Scotland|Unionists]] and independents. Apart from a distinct focus on their urban localities, the essence of the Progressive groupings was opposition to Labour policies and control, plus a desire to avoid splitting the anti-Labour vote.{{citation needed|date=February 2012}}

Progressive groupings formed in [[Edinburgh]] in 1928 and [[Glasgow]] in 1936 before spreading to other cities and towns. Their members were mainly drawn from [[small business]]men opposed to the introduction of what they saw as [[municipal socialism]] and Labour control. They dominated Scottish local politics for almost 50 years and as late as 1972 [[Edinburgh Council|Edinburgh council]] was made up of 21 Progressives, 9 Conservatives, 33 Labour and 5 Liberals.{{citation needed|date=February 2012}}

===United States===
{{Main|Progressivism in the United States}}
[[File:President Theodore Roosevelt, 1904.jpg|thumb|160px|[[Theodore Roosevelt]] (1858-1919) was a leader in the [[Progressive Era]].]]
In the [[United States]] there have been several periods where progressive political parties have developed. The first of these was around the start of the 20th century.&lt;ref&gt;Catherine Cocks, Peter C. Holloran and Alan Lessoff. ''Historical Dictionary of the Progressive Era'' (2009)&lt;/ref&gt; This period notably included the emergence of the [[Progressive Party 1912 (United States)|Progressive Party]], founded in 1912 by former President Theodore Roosevelt. This Progressive Party was the most successful third party in modern American history.&lt;!-- Populists with W.B. Jennings? --&gt; The [[Progressive Party 1924 (United States)|Progressive Party founded in 1924]] and the [[Progressive Party 1948 (United States)|Progressive Party founded in 1948]] were less successful than the 1912 version. There are also two notable state progressive parties: the [[Wisconsin Progressive Party]] and the [[Vermont Progressive Party]]. The latter is still in operation and currently has several positions in state government.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=A Legacy of Progressive Leadership|url=http://www.progressiveparty.org/organize/legacy|publisher=The Vermont Progressive Party|accessdate=13 June 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Today, members of the [[Green Party of the United States]] are most likely to self-identify as liberal progressives. In the U.S. Congress, the [[Congressional Progressive Caucus]] is the most liberal wing of the Democratic Party, and it is often in opposition to the more [[centrist]] or conservative Democrats who form the [[Blue Dog Coalition|Blue Dogs]] caucus. It is also in near-continuous opposition to the [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican Party]].{{citation needed|date=February 2012}}

==Relation to other political ideologies==

===Liberalism===
{{globalize|date=October 2013}}
{{Refimprove section|date=May 2014}}

The term "progressive" is today often used in place of "[[Liberalism|liberal]]". Although the two are related in some ways, they are separate and distinct political ideologies. In the U.S. in particular, the term "[[Progressivism in the United States|progressive]]" tends to have the same value as the European term [[Social democracy|social democrat]], which is scarcely used in American political language.

The reason for this confusion in the U.S. might partly be rooted in the political spectrum being two-dimensional; [[social liberalism]] is a tenet of modern progressivism, whereas [[economic liberalism]] (and its associated [[deregulation]]) is not. According to John Halpin, senior advisor on the staff of the center-left [[Center for American Progress]], "Progressivism is an orientation towards politics. It's not a long-standing ideology like liberalism, but an historically-grounded concept ... that accepts the world as dynamic."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last = | first = | authorlink = | coauthors = | year = | url =http://www.alternet.org/wiretap/23706/?comments=view&amp;cID=25252&amp;pID=22606 | title =What Is Progressivism? | format = | work = | publisher =Andrew Garib | accessdate =2006-11-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Cultural liberalism]] is ultimately founded on the belief that the major purpose of the government is to protect rights. Liberals are often called "[[left-wing]]", in contrast to "[[right-wing]]" conservatives. The progressive school, as a unique branch of contemporary political thought, tends to advocate certain center-left or left-wing views that may conflict with mainstream liberal views, despite the fact that modern liberalism and progressivism may still both support many of the same policies (such as the concept of war as a general last resort).{{citation needed|date=February 2012}}

American progressives tend to advocate [[progressive taxation]] and oppose what they describe as the growing and negative influence of large corporations. Progressives are typically in agreement on an international scale with left-liberalism in that they support organized labor and [[trade union]]s, they usually wish to introduce a [[living wage]], and they often support the creation of a [[universal health care]] system. In the United States, liberals and progressives are often conflated, and in general are the primary voters of the [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democratic Party]] which has a "large tent" policy, combining similar if not congruent ideologies into large voting blocs.  Many progressives also support the [[Green Party (United States)|Green Party]] or local parties such as the [[Vermont Progressive Party]].  In [[Canada]], liberals usually support the national [[Liberal Party (Canada)|Liberal Party]] while progressives usually support the [[New Democratic Party of Canada|New Democratic Party]], which traditionally has had provincial electoral success in Manitoba, Saskatchewan, British Columbia and, since the recent federal election, in Quebec.{{citation needed|date=September 2013}}

==See also==
*[[Centre-left]]
*[[Constitutional economics]]
*[[Political economy]]
*[[Rule according to higher law]]
*[[Independent Media Center]]
*[[Progressive education]]
*[[Social democracy]]
*[[Welfare state]]

==Notes==
{{refimprove|date=February 2012}}
{{Reflist}}

==References==
*[[George Tindall|Tindall, George]] and [[David E. Shi|Shi, David E.]]. ''America: A Narrative History''. W W Norton &amp; Co Inc (Np); Full Sixth edition, 2003. ISBN 0-393-92426-2
*[[George Lakoff|Lakoff, George]]. ''Don't Think of an Elephant: Know Your Values and Frame the Debate''. Chelsea Green Publishing, 2004. ISBN 1-931498-71-7
*[[William J. Kelleher|Kelleher, William J.]]. ''Progressive Logic: Framing A Unified Field Theory of Values For Progressives''.  The Empathic Science Institute, 2005.  ISBN 0-9773717-1-9
*[[Arthur S. Link|Link, Arthur S.]] and [[Richard L. McCormick|McCormick, Richard L.]]. ''Progressivism (American History Series)''. Harlan Davidson, 1983. ISBN 0-88295-814-3
*[[James T. Kloppenberg|Kloppenberg, James T.]]. ''Uncertain Victory: Social Democracy and Progressivism in European and American Thought, 1870-1920''. Oxford University Press, USA, 1988. ISBN 0-19-505304-4
* [[Michael McGerr|McGerr, Michael]] ''A Fierce Discontent: The Rise and Fall of the Progressive Movement in America, 1870-1920'' (2003)
*[[Aaron Schutz|Schutz, Aaron]]. ''Social Class, Social Action, and Education: The Failure of Progressive Democracy''. Palgrave, Macmillan, 2010. ISBN 978-0-230-10591-1 [http://educationaction.org introduction]

==External links==
* [http://cpc.grijalva.house.gov/index.cfm?sectionid=71&amp;sectiontree=2,71 United States Congressional Progressive Caucus Membership Rosters]
* [http://www.startguide.org/orgs/orgs00.html 500 Leading U.S. Progressive Organizations]
* [http://www.commondreams.org/headlines04/0630-20.htm A list of popular Progressive websites] from [[Common Dreams]]
* [http://www.alternet.org/wiretap/23706/ "What Is Progressive?"], [[AlterNet]] opinion piece, July 25, 2005
* The Fifty Most Influential Progressives of the Twentieth Century:  [http://www.thenation.com/slideshow/154631/slide-show-fifty-most-influential-progressives-twentieth-century-part-1 Part I],&amp;nbsp; [http://www.thenation.com/slideshow/154744/slide-show-fifty-most-influential-progressives-20th-century-2 Part II],&amp;nbsp; [http://www.thenation.com/slideshow/154792/slide-show-fifty-most-influential-progressives-twentieth-century-3 Part III] — slideshows by ''[[The Nation]]''
{{Philosophy of education sidebar |expanded}}
{{Political ideologies}}

[[Category:Progressivism| ]]
[[Category:Political ideologies]]
[[Category:Political movements]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>