<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061110045428|86878585" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="26636309" pageid="26636309" ns="0" title="Progressivism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-11-10T04:56:06Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Progressivism}}

'''Progressivism''' is a term that refers to a broad school of contemporary international social and [[political philosophy|political philosophies]]. As a political term, '''progressive''' was first widely used in late [[19th century]] North America, in reference to a general branch of political thought opposed to traditional [[conservative|conservatism]]. Political parties such as the American [[Progressive Party 1912 (United States)|Progressive Party]] formed at the start of the [[20th century]], and progressivism made great strides throughout the early 1900's.

There are at least three distinct meanings of the word "progressive", as it is used today. Ordered from the most vague to the most specific, they are as follows:

#In the broadest sense, the label "progressive" may be used in self-description of anyone who advocates any kind of change in a society, or in any part of the [[political spectrum]].
#In a somewhat more restricted sense, "progressive" is a term used within [[left-wing politics]] to distinguish left-wingers who advocate [[moderate]] or gradual social change - often called either "progressives" or "reformists" - from those who advocate larger and more rapid changes - called "revolutionaries" or "radicals".
#Finally, in the most specific sense, there is the continuation of the political movement/ideology that began in the late 19th century. This ideology is mostly adhered to by the political [[left-wing]], but not every liberal is a progressive. Progressives support the continual advancement of [[workers' rights]] and [[social justice]]. The first progressives were some of the earliest proponents of [[antitrust|anti-trust laws]] and the regulation of large corporations and [[monopoly|monopolies]]. They were also among the first advocates of government-funded [[environmentalism]], and the creation of [[National Park]]s and [[National Wildlife Refuge|Wildlife Refuges]]. It is this meaning of progressivism that will be covered more extensively in the rest of the article below.

==Tenets of Early Progressivism==
In the beginning of the original progressive movement, most of the principles that were laid out by early [[20th century]] [[United States of America|American]] progressives continue to be the hallmarks of contemporary progressive politics. The following are some of those early tenets. 

===Democracy===
Many progressives hoped to make government in the U.S. more responsive to the direct voice of the American people by instituting the following institutional reforms: 

*''Ballot Initiative'' - A procedure whereby citizens could [[vote]] directly on whether to approve proposed laws. 
*''[[Initiative]]'' - A procedure whereby ordinary citizens could propose laws for consideration by their [[state legislature]]s or by the voters directly. 
*''[[Direct primary]]'' - A procedure whereby political party nominations for public office were made directly by a vote of rank-and-file members of the party rather than by party bosses. 
*''[[Direct election]] of U.S. [[Senator]]s'' - A procedure to allow the citizens in each state to directly elect their Senators. Previously, Senators were chosen by the state legislatures. Direct election of Senators was achieved with the addition of the [[Seventeenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Seventeenth Amendment to the U.S. Constitution]] (1913). 
*''[[Referendum]]'' - A procedure whereby citizens could vote directly to rescind a law which was passed by the legislature. 
*''[[Recall]]'' - A procedure by which a public official could be removed from office by a direct vote of the citizens. 
*''[[Secret Ballot]]'' - A procedure by which citizens could keep their votes secret. Previously, voting was a public act witnessed by others. The voting records of individual citizens were recorded and made public. Many progressives argued that public voting allowed for voter intimidation. An employer, for instance, might require his employees to vote for certain candidates on pain of losing their jobs. 
*''[[Women's Suffrage]]'' - Granting to women the right to vote. Women's Suffrage was achieved with the addition of the [[Nineteenth Amendment to the U.S. Constitution]] (1920). 

The progressives achieved their greatest and most enduring successes in the effort to make governments more democratic.

===Efficiency===
Many progressives hoped to make American governments better able to serve the people's needs by making governmental operations and services more efficient and rational. Reforms included: 

*''Professional [[Administration|administrator]]s''-Many progressives argued that governments would function better if they were placed under the direction of trained, professional administrators. One example of progressive reform was the rise of the city manager system, in which paid, professional administrators ran the day-to-day affairs of city governments under guidelines established by elected [[city council]]s. 
*''[[Centralization]] of decision-making process''-Many progressives sought to make government more rational through centralized decision-making. Governments were reorganized to reduce the number of officials and to eliminate overlapping areas of authority between departments. City governments were reorganized to reduce the power of local wards within the city and to increase the powers of the city council. Governments at every level began developing budgets to help them plan their expenditures (rather than spending money haphazardly as needs arose and revenue became available). The drive for centralization was often associated with the rise of professional administrators. 
*''Movements to eliminate governmental corruption''-Corruption represented a source of waste and inefficiency in government. Many progressives worked to cleanup local governments by eliminating the power of machine politicians and urban political bosses. Often this was associated with the effort to restructure the ward system. Power was transferred from urban bosses to professional administrators. 
Note that the progressives' quest for efficiency was sometimes at odds with the progressives' quest for democracy. Taking power out of the hands of elected officials and placing that power in the hands of professional administrators reduced the voice of the people in government. Centralized decision-making and reduced power for local [[ward]]s made government more distant and isolated from the people it served. Progressives who emphasized the need for efficiency sometimes argued that an elite class of administrators knew better what the people needed than did the people themselves. 

===Regulation of Large Corporations and Monopolies===
Many progressives hoped that by regulating large [[corporation]]s that they could liberate human energies from the restrictions imposed by industrial [[capitalism]]. Yet the progressive movement was split over which of the following four solutions should be used to regulate corporations:

*''[[Trust-busting]]''-Some progressives argued that industrial [[monopoly|monopolies]] were unnatural economic institutions which suppressed the competition which was necessary for progress and improvement. The [[federal government]] should intervene by breaking up monopolies into smaller companies, thereby restoring competition. The government should then withdraw and allow marketplace forces once again to regulate the economy. 
*''Regulation''-Some progressives argued that in a modern [[economy]], large corporations and even monopolies were both inevitable and desirable. With their massive resources and economies of scale, large corporations offered the U.S. advantages which smaller companies could not offer. Yet, these large corporations might abuse their great power. The federal government should allow these companies to exist but regulate them for the public interest. 
*''[[Socialism]]''-Some progressives believed that privately owned companies could never be made to serve the public interest. Therefore, the federal government should acquire ownership of large corporations and operate them for the public interest.
*''[[Laissez-Faire]]''-Some progressives argued that marketplace forces were the best regulators of all. A company which paid low wages or maintained an unsafe work environment would be forced to change its policies by the loss of workers. A company which made an unsafe product would eventually lose customers and go [[bankruptcy|bankrupt]]. In the long run, a [[free market]] would best protect the public interest.
 
The laissez-faire and socialist approaches were less popular among American progressives than the trust-busting and regulatory approaches.

===Social Justice===
Many progressives supported both private and governmental action to help people in need (such action is called [[social justice]]). Social justice reforms included:

*''Development of professional [[social worker]]s'' - The idea that [[welfare]] and charity work should be undertaken by professionals who are trained to do the job. (Notice again the progressives' concern for efficiency through professionalism.) 
*''The building of [[Settlement movement|Settlement Houses]]'' - These were residential, community centers operated by social workers and volunteers and located in inner city slums. The purpose of the settlement houses was to raise the standard of living of urbanites by providing schools, [[day care]] centers, and cultural enrichment programs. 
*''The enactment of [[child labor]] laws'' - Child labor laws were designed to prevent the overworking of children in the newly emerging industries. The goal of these laws was to give [[working-class]] children the opportunity to go to school and to mature more naturally, thereby liberating the potential of humanity and encouraging the advancement of humanity. 
*''Support for the goals of [[organized labor]]'' - Progressives often supported such goals as the eight-hour work day, improved safety and health conditions in factories, [[workers compensation]] laws, [[minimum wage]] laws, and [[unionization]]. 
*''[[Prohibition]] laws'' - Progressives adopted the cause of prohibition. They claimed the consumption of [[alcohol]] limited mankind's potential for advancement. Progressives achieved success in this area with the enactment of the [[Eighteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Eighteenth Amendment to the U.S. Constitution]] in 1919.&lt;ref&gt;http://spider.georgetowncollege.edu/htallant/courses/his225/progmovt.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

===Environmentalism===
During the term of the progressive President [[Theodore Roosevelt]] (1901 – 1909), the largest government-funded environmentalism-related projects in U.S. history were undertaken:

* On March 14, 1903, President Roosevelt created the first National Bird Preserve, (the beginning of the Wildlife Refuge system), on Pelican Island, [[Florida]]. In all, by 1909, the Roosevelt administration had created an unprecedented 42 million acres of [[national forest]]s, 53 [[national wildlife refuge]]s and 18 areas of "special interest", including the [[Grand Canyon]]. This environmental record was unequaled until President [[Bill Clinton]]'s term, 90 years later.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.runet.edu/~wkovarik/envhist/5progressive.html&lt;/ref&gt;

==Progressivism Worldwide==
{{ Expandsection }}
The precise definition of what constitutes "Progressivism" varies somewhat worldwide. Most of the above tenets still apply, with the most notable divide being in regards to economic principles. The issues pertaining to government economic intervention, such as corporate regulation, split the early progressive movement into two major branches. The branch of progressivism which adheres to a less [[radical]] policy of intervention through [[trust-busting]] and regulation is more predominate in North America, while the more interventionist [[social-democrats|social-democratic]] branch is more predominate in parts of South America and Asia. Europe has a fairly even representation of both schools.

==Americas==
In North America, Green and other progressive parties have a small but fairly consistent following. The [[Federation of Green Parties of the Americas]] is a coalition of progressive environmentalist parties from the U.S., Canada, and parts of South America.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.broadleft.org/greens.htm&lt;/ref&gt;  The progressive movement in South America more commonly advocates moderate socialism or social-democracy as an economic reform option, and is currently experiencing an upswing in popularity, as recent elections in Venezuela, Mexico, Chile, Peru, and other parts of Latin America show. The [[Latin American Socialist Coordination]] (Coordinación Socialista Latinoamericana) is an organization of social-democratic parties with progressive policies in South America.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.broadleft.org/leftsoc.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

===Canada===
The term ''progressive'' is also popular in [[Canada]], since many are further left than the [[Liberal Party of Canada]].  Most supporters of the old [[Progressive Conservative Party of Canada]] did not consider themselves progressive although arguments have been made that the Mulroney government implemented progressive environmental policies. The David Orchard wing of the old PC Party was progressive in nature while the Red Tory faction, which included former Prime Minister Joe Clark, was less so. The [[New Democratic Party]] embraces certain progressive stances, and attempts to appeal to progressive voters.

Some of the New Democrats' more progressive stances are:
* [[Gay rights]] and gender equality.
* Fully socialized [[healthcare]].
* More progressive taxes.
* Greater [[welfare]] benefits.
* [[Electoral reform]].
* Environmental protection.
* Labor and Aboriginal rights.
* The elimination of [[child poverty]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ndp.ca/workingfamiliesfirst&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Progressive Party of Canada]] briefly rose to prominence in the 1920s. The [[Progressive Canadian Party]], composed mostly of anti-merger Progressive Conservatives, was formed several months prior to the [[Canadian federal election, 2004|2004 general election]].

===United States===
{{main|Progressivism in the United States}}

Progressive political parties were created in the United States on three different occasions. The first of these - the [[Progressive Party 1912 (United States)|Progressive Party]], founded in 1912 by President [[Theodore Roosevelt]] - was the most successful third party in modern American history. The other two were the [[Progressive Party 1924 (United States)|Progressive Party founded in 1924]] and the [[Progressive Party 1948 (United States)|Progressive Party founded in 1948]], which were less successful.

From the [[New Deal]] to the [[1960s]], the progressive movement was largely subsumed into [[modern American liberalism]]. After the 1960s, however, progressives grew increasingly unhappy with the direction of the liberal movement and the leadership of the [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democratic Party]]. On the one hand, progressives agreed with many of the concerns of the [[New Left]], such as environmental [[conservation]]. On the other hand, they preserved their commitment to the original progressive issues, such as [[workers' rights]], which liberals grew less interested in. And finally, progressives also began advocating entirely new ideas - for example [[electoral reform]] (including [[proportional representation]]) and [[campaign finance reform]]. As many American progressives felt disenfranchised from the contemporary American liberal movement, they sought to establish their own separate political organizations. Two prominent examples are the [[Vermont Progressive Party]], and the environmentalist [[Green Party (United States)|Green Party]].

==Asia==
==Europe==
In Europe there is a large but varied progressive movement, mostly in the form of center-left [[social-democrat]]s, and Green parties. The [[European Federation of Green Parties]] is a multinational organization of progressive environmental parties. The [[Socialist International]] is comprised of social-democratic parties.

===Ireland===
In Ireland, the [[Progressive Democrats]] (in Irish ''An Páirtí Daonlathach'', literal back-translation: The Democratic Party) is a free market liberal party in the [[Republic of Ireland]] founded in 1985.

The party is often described as [[right wing]] by supporters and critics alike, but they have several policies which may be considered progressive:
*They have been strong supporters of overseas development aid. Liz O’Donnell of the Progressive Democrats, then Minister of State in the Department of Foreign Affairs, threathened to resign if aid wasn’t increased. As a result, it was doubled. 
*The former PD leader, Mary Harney, introduced Ireland's first [[minimum wage]] in [[2000]] while she was [[Irish Minister for Enterprise, Trade &amp; Employment|Minister for Enterprise, Trade and Employment]]. At the time, it was the highest minimum wage in the EU.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.progressivedemocrats.ie/about_us/achievements_in_government/&lt;/ref&gt;
*They support the social partnership agreements on taxation, wages and conditions negotiated between unions, government and employers.
*Their election programmes have included the intention to significantly increase welfare spending in key areas, including children's allowance, unemployment benefit and old age pensions.
*They support free university education..&lt;ref&gt;http://www.progressivedemocrats.ie/our_policies/&lt;/ref&gt;

===United Kingdom===
In the UK, the [[Liberal Democrats (UK)|Liberal Democrats]] tend to favor more progressive causes than the center-left [[Labour Party]], though both have at times embraced the progressive movement. The [[RESPECT The Unity Coalition|Respect Party]], while leaning more towards socialism, is one of the more progressive parties in the region. The [[Scottish Green Party]] and the [[Green Party of England and Wales]] are progressive environmental parties.

The Liberal Democrats more progressive policies are:
*Recently the party has adopted a strong sense of environmentalist values - favouring taxing high polluters.
*The party has supported higher taxes on high earners, and higher levels of government spending.
*They are supportive of a multilateral foreign policy, and opposed to British participation in the War in Iraq.
* They support more open government, including substantial reforms to increase parliamentary oversight of the [[executive (government)|executive]].
* They support anti-discrimination laws. 25 Lib Dem MPs signed [http://edmi.parliament.uk/EDMi/EDMDetails.aspx?EDMID=29000 EDM710] calling on the government to extend the protections for religious groups, in respect of discrimination in the provisions of goods, facilities and services, to lesbians and [[gay]] men. 
* They are in favour of [[proportional representation]] for elections to the [[British House of Commons|House of Commons]], preferably by the [[Single Transferable Vote|STV]] system.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.libdems.org.uk/party/policy/manifesto.html&lt;/ref&gt;

Some of the Respect Party's policies are:
* Opposition to the privatisation of the [[National Health Service]] and the [[education system]], including opposition to university tuition fees and support for pensions increases linked to average earnings.
* Raising the [[minimum wage]] to the [[European Union]]'s "decency threshold" of £7.40 an hour.
* The defence of the rights of refugees and other asylum-seekers.
* Support for the [[Conservation in the United Kingdom|British environmental movement]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.respectcoalition.org/index.php?sec=39&lt;/ref&gt;

==Pacific==
===Australia===
The term ''progressive'' is popular in [[Australia]], and most progressives tend to support either the [[Australian Labor Party|Labor Party]], the [[Australian Democrats|Democrats]] or the [[Australian Greens|Greens]], opposed to the right-wing neo-liberal [[Liberal Party of Australia]].

The Australian Democrats' have many progressive agendas, including:
* [[economic interventionism|Interventionist economic]] policies.
* Commitment to environmental causes.
* Support for [[reconciliation]] with Australia's [[Indigenous Australians|indigenous population]] through such mechanisms as formal treaties.
* [[pacifism|Pacifist]] approaches to international relations.
* Open government and constitutional reform.
* Progressive approaches to social issues such as sexuality and drugs.
* Strong support for [[human rights]] and civil liberties. 
* Support of [[proportional representation]] and [[citizen initiated referendum|citizens' initated referenda]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.democrats.org.au/policies/&lt;/ref&gt;

The party also explicitly targets voters who seek a brake on the powers of the government of the day to change things, with their long-term hold on the Senate balance of power. Many important internal issues (such as electoral preselection and leadership) are decided by direct postal ballot of the membership. Although policies are theoretically set in a similar fashion, Democrat parliamentarians have extensive freedom in interpreting them.

The Australian [[Green Party (Australia)|Green Party]] is a progressive environmentalist party.

===New Zealand===
The current Prime Minister of New Zealand - Helen Clark, leader of the Labour Party - announced in 2005 that she had come to a complex arrangement that led to a formal coalition consisting of the Labour Party and [[Jim Anderton]], the [[New Zealand Progressive Party]]'s  MP. A further arrangement has been made with the Green Party, which has given a commitment not to vote against the government on confidence and supply.

[[Jim Anderton]] formed the Progressive Party after splitting from the [[Alliance (New Zealand political party)]] Party. The Progressive Party states a particular focus on the creation of jobs, and has said that it is committed to achieving full employment. They seek to raise the legal age of alcohol consumption to 20. They are pro-environment, and list free education and free healthcare as other policy objectives.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.progressive.org.nz/modules.php?name=Content&amp;pa=showpage&amp;pid=111&lt;/ref&gt;

Progressive voters also support the [[Green Party of Aotearoa New Zealand]]. The Greens focus primarily on environmental issues. In recent times, they have expressed particular concerns about [[genetic engineering]], which they strongly oppose using. They have also spoken out against the [[military]] operations conducted by the [[United States|United States of America]] and other countries in [[Afghanistan]] and [[Iraq]]. In its [[Economics|economic]] policies, the Green Party stresses factors such as [[sustainability]] and "[[fair trade]]". It also states that measuring economic success should concentrate on [[measuring well-being]] rather than analysing economic indicators.

The [[Progressive Green Party (New Zealand)|Progressive Green Party]] was formed in [[1995]] but has now disbanded.

==Progressivism in relation to other political ideologies==
===Liberalism===
The term "progressive" is now often used in place of "[[liberalism|liberal]]". Although the two are related, they are really distinct political ideologies. According to John Halpin, senior advisor on the staff of the [[Center for American Progress]], ''"Progressivism is an orientation towards politics, It's not a long-standing ideology like liberalism, but an historically-grounded concept ... that accepts the world as dynamic."'' Progressives see progressivism as an attitude towards the world of politics that is far less black-and-white than conservatism vs. liberalism, and as an attempt to break free from that false and divisive dichotomy.&lt;ref&gt;Andrew Garib, [http://www.alternet.org/wiretap/23706/?comments=view&amp;cID=25252&amp;pID=22606 "What Is Progressivism?"]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Untergeek.com,  [http://www.untergeek.com/?p=396 "Progressive versus Liberal"]&lt;/ref&gt;

Liberalism is ultimately founded on a concept of [[natural rights]] and [[civil liberties]], and the belief that the major purpose of the government is to protect those rights. Liberals are often called "[[left-wing]]", as opposed to "[[right-wing]]" conservatives. The progressive school, as a unique branch of contemporary political thought, tends to advocate certain center-left or left-wing views that may conflict with mainstream liberal views, despite the fact that modern liberalism and progressivism may still both support many of the same policies (such as the concept of [[war]] as a general last resort). 

American progressives tend to support liberal economics: they advocate [[income redistribution]], and they oppose the growing influence of corporations. Conversely, European and Australian progressives tend to be more pro-business, and will often have policies that are soft on taxation of large corporations.  Progressives are in agreement on an international scale with liberalism in that they support organized labor and [[trade union]]s, they usually wish to introduce a [[living wage]], and they often support the creation of a [[universal health care]] system. Yet progressives tend to be more concerned with environmentalism than mainstream liberals, and are often more skeptical of the government, positioning themselves as [[whistleblowers]] and advocates of governmental reform. Finally, liberals are more likely to support the [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democratic Party]] in America and the [[Labour party]] in Europe and Australia, while progressives tend to feel disillusioned with any two-party system, and vote more often for third-party candidates.

===Conservatism and libertarianism===
Some views in opposition to progressivism are [[conservatism]], and [[libertarianism]]. 

Conservatives, by definition, advocate [[tradition]] and social stability. They are skeptical of notions of "progress" and social change - in any direction - believing that it is best to retain social relations that have been proven stable by past experience. 

Libertarians, on the other hand, advocate their own brand of social change, which is in many ways opposed to the kind of change advocated by progressives. For this reason, libertarians claim that "they" are the true promoters of progress, and that the policies of progressivism are actually "regressive". A notable supporter of this view is [[Brink Lindsey]], an economist working with the [[Cato Institute]]. Lindsey believes that by terming themselves progressives, [[American liberalism|American liberals]] and social democrats have put a positive spin on what he claims to be regressive economic tendencies. Being a libertarian, he argues in favor of free market capitalism and believes that progressive economic policies (such as [[minimum wage]]s, [[income tax]]es, [[payroll tax]]es, most social safety nets and [[trade barrier]]s) help to increase unemployment among the poor and unskilled, as well as increase costs for all members of society.

Progressives counter that free market capitalism can be demonstrated to be regressive due to negative social consequences caused by its rejection or mitigation of labor policies to improve corporate efficiency, and the fact that it is often at odds with fair trade and other movements that argue for [[labor rights]] and [[social justice]] in international relations and economics. They further argue that the kind of policies advocated by libertarians like Brink Lindsey would and have created severe poverty, widened the gap between rich and poor and allowed those who are already rich to gain an excessively high amount of both wealth and power over the rest of society.

===Socialism===
[[Socialism]] (in the strict or radical sense) aims to establish a fundamentally different society from the one that currently exists in most countries. While there are different schools of socialism, which often tend to have differing views of the ideal socialist society, some general examples of socialist concepts are: The desire to abolish capitalism, to place the [[means of production]] under the collective ownership of the people, and to achieve a very high degree of economic and political equality. Socialists argue that capitalism [[exploitation|exploits]] the [[working class]], and they desire for workers to play a vital role in moving society from capitalism to socialism (either by rising up in a [[proletarian revolution|revolution]] or [[general strike]], or by voting ''en masse'' for socialist political parties).

In contrast, by definition progressivism aims to achieve gradual social change, and most progressives are outright opposed to any form of radical revolution. When the progressive movement split on economic principles, some progressives moved towards the socialist camp, advocating a [[planned economy]]. Other progressives moved towards the regulated [[mixed economy]] camp, with both public and private ownership of companies. Between these two extremes is [[social democracy]] (not a term in popular U.S. usage), a branch of socialism that became increasingly moderate and moved towards the [[centrism|political center]]. Regulated-capitalism progressives and socialist progressives still tend to support similar progressive social policies, outside of economic principles.

However, the relationship between progressivism and socialism as described here has often been a tense one. An example of this tension can be seen in the conflict between the [[Progressive Party (United States, 1912)|Progressive Party]] of [[Theodore Roosevelt]] and the [[Socialist Party of America|Socialist Party]] of [[Eugene V. Debs]] in the United States.

==List of progressive groups==
'''See also:''' [[List of progressive organizations]]

* [[Australian Democrats]] [http://www.democrats.org.au/]
* [[Australian Greens]] [http://www.greens.org.au/]
* [[European Federation of Green Parties]]
* [[Federation of Green Parties of the Americas]]
* [[Green Party of Aotearoa New Zealand]] [http://greens.org.nz/]
* [[Green Party of England and Wales]] [http://www.greenparty.org.uk/]
* [[Green Party (United States)|Green Party of the United States]] [http://www.gp.org/]
* [[Liberal Democrats (UK)|Liberal Democrats]] - U.K. [http://www.libdems.org.uk/]
* [[New Zealand Progressive Party]] [http://www.progressive.org.nz/]
* [[New Democratic Party]] - Canada [http://www.ndp.ca/]
* [[Progressive Democrats]] - Ireland [http://www.progressivedemocrats.ie/]
* [[Progressive Democrats of America]]
* [[Progressive Party (United States)|Progressive Party]], which now refers to 3 different parties of different periods in the U.S.
* [[Scottish Green Party]] [http://www.scottishgreens.org.uk/]

==List of progressive advocates==
{{col-begin}}
{{col-2}}      
*[[Jane Addams]]
*[[Eric Alterman]]
*[[Susan B. Anthony]] 
*[[Louis Brandeis]]
*[[Alan Brinkley]]
*[[Peter Camejo]]
*[[Noam Chomsky]]
*[[John Dewey]]
*[[Russ Feingold]]
*[[Thomas Frank]]
*[[George Galloway]]
*[[Amy Goodman]]
*[[David Goodman]]
*[[Stephen Jay Gould]]
*[[Edward S. Herman]]
*[[Alfie Kohn]]
*[[Dennis Kucinich]]
*[[Robert M. La Follette, Sr.]]
{{col-2}}
*[[Robert McChesney]]
*[[David McReynolds]]
*[[Ralph Nader]]
*[[John B. Oakes]]
*[[Greg Palast]]
*[[Christian Parenti]]
*[[John Pilger]]
*[[Walter Rauschenbusch]]
*[[Franklin Delano Roosevelt]]
*[[Theodore Roosevelt]]
*[[Bernie Sanders]]
*[[Margaret Sanger]]
*[[Norman Solomon]]
*[[Elizabeth Cady Stanton]]
*[[Ida M. Tarbell]]
*[[James Ward]]
*[[Ida B. Wells]]
*[[Woodrow Wilson]]
{{col-end}}

==References ==
&lt;references/&gt;

*[[George Tindall|Tindall, George]] and [[David E. Shi|Shi, David E.]]. ''America: A Narrative History''. W W Norton &amp; Co Inc (Np); Full Sixth edition, 2003. ISBN 0-3939242-6-2
*[[George Lakoff|Lakoff, George]]. ''Don't Think of an Elephant: Know Your Values and Frame the Debate''. Chelsea Green Publishing, 2004. ISBN 1-931498-71-7
*[[William J. Kelleher|Kelleher, William J.]]. ''Progressive Logic: Framing A Unified Field Theory of Values For Progressives''.  The Empathic Science Institute, 2005.  ISBN 0-9773717-1-9
*[[Arthur S. Link|Link, Arthur S.]] and [[Richard L. McCormick|McCormick, Richard L.]]. ''Progressivism (American History Series)''. Harlan Davidson, 1983. ISBN 0-8829581-4-3
*[[James T. Kloppenberg|Kloppenberg, James T.]]. ''Uncertain Victory: Social Democracy and Progressivism in European and American Thought, 1870-1920''. Oxford University Press, USA, 1988. ISBN 0-1950530-4-4

==External links==
*[http://www.commondreams.org/headlines04/0630-20.htm A list of popular Progressive websites] - From CommonDreams.org
*[http://encarta.msn.com/encyclopedia_1741500823_23/United_States_(History).html#s123 American Progressivism and Reform] - online article from [[Encarta]]
*[http://www.airamericaradio.com Air America Radio] - Progressive radio network
*[http://www.prospect.org American Prospect] - Progressive magazine and non-profit think-tank
*[http://www.commondreams.org/ Breaking News &amp; Commentary for the Progressive Community]
*[http://www.ourfuture.org/ Campaign for America's Future] A progressive non-profit thinktank
*[http://www.americanprogress.org/ Center for American Progress] - A progressive think tank in Washington, DC
*[http://www.comw.org/pssp Progressive Strategy Studies Project] - effort to systematically study and catalog progressive strategic thinking
*[http://www.rockridgeinstitute.org Rockridge Institute] - Think-tank dedicated to better presenting progressive ideas
*[http://rooseveltinstitution.org Roosevelt Institution] Progressive student think tank
*[http://www.alternet.org/wiretap/23706/ "What Is Progressive?"], [http://www.alternet.org/ ''AlterNet''] opinion piece, July 25th 2005
*[http://www.indymedia.org/en/index.shtml IMC, the Independent Media Center]
*[http://www.umpaonline.org University of Montevallo Progressive Alliance] - Progressive Students

[[Category:Progressivism| ]]
[[Category:Social democracy]]
[[Category:Liberalism]]
[[Category:Political ideologies]]
[[Category:Political movements]]

&lt;!-- interwiki --&gt;
[[da:Progressivisme]]
[[es:Progresismo]]
[[fr:Progressisme]]
[[ko:진보주의]]
[[hr:Progresivizam]]
[[it:Progressismo]]
[[nl:Progressivisme]]
[[ja:革新]]
[[pt:Progressismo]]
[[zh:進步主義]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>