<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20041101232251|7092430" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="26636309" pageid="26636309" ns="0" title="Progressivism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2004-11-04T07:54:26Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Progressivism''' or '''political progressivism''' is any of several historically related [[political philosophy|political philosophies]] or political ideologies. There are also a number of Progressive political parties in various countries. All of these are primarily (though not necessarily exclusively) identified with the [[Left-wing politics|political left]].

==Beliefs==

'''Basic Progressive Vision'''

The basic Progressive vision is of community — as family, a caring, responsible family. Progressives envision a community where people care about each other, not just themselves, and act responsibly with strength and effectiveness for each other.


'''Progressive Principles'''

''Equity''

What citizens and nations owe each other. If you work hard; play by the rules; and serve your family, community, and nation, then the nation should provide a decent standard of living, as well as freedom, security, and opportunity.

''Equality''

Do everything possible to guarantee political equality and avoid imbalances of political power.

''Democracy''

Maximize citizen participation; minimize concentrations of political, corporate, and media power. Maximize journalistic standards. Establish publicly financed elections, Invest in public education. Bring corporations under stakeholder control, not just stockholder control.

''Government for a Better Future''

Government does what the future requires and what the private sector cannot do or is not doing effectively, ethically, or at all. it is the job of government to promote and, if possible, provide sufficient protection, greater democracy, more freedom, a better environment, broader prosperity, better health, greater fulfillment in life, less violence, and the building and maintaining of public infrastructure.

''Ethical Business''

In the course of making money by providing products and services, businesses should not adversely affect the public good, as defined by the above values.

''Values-based Foreign Policy''

The same values governing domestic policy should apply to foreign policy whenever possible.

==History==

===United States===
In the [[United States]], the term ''liberal'' has for many decades (at least since the [[New Deal]]) been used to describe the political left, and ''conservative'' the [[Right-wing politics|right]]. Since at least the late 1990s, the term ''progressive'' has been employed to describe certain leftist views of one form or another, for at least two reasons.

The first is to create a contrast between center-left and farther-left politics.  For example, [[John Kerry]], [[Al Gore]], and the [[United States Democratic Party|Democratic Party]] are more likely to be described as or to describe themselves as ''liberal'', whereas [[Howard Dean]] (a Democrat), [[Ralph Nader]] (endorsed by the Green Party in 2000) and the [[United States Green Party|Green Party]] are more likely to be described as or to describe themselves as ''progressive''. In addition to ''progressive'' [[Third party (United States)|third parties]] like the [[United States Green Party|Greens]], there is also a [[Progressive Caucus]] in the [[United States House of Representatives|House of Representatives]], made up of Democrats and an independent Congressman.  (Note that the Democratic and Republican parties have not always represented the left and the right.  The modern alignment has been strongest since the 1970s.)

The second is to find a term with positive connotations.  The intuitive opposite of ''liberal'' is ''conservative'', which some people are proud to consider themselves.  The intuitive opposite of ''progressive'' is ''regressive'', a label with which hardly any person or political ideology would want to be associated.  Critics of leftist politics often use the term ''liberals'' to describe their opponents, so distancing oneself from that term can be a rhetorical device to distance oneself from that criticism.  (Both ''liberal'' and ''conservative'' can be quite [[pejorative]] when used by their critics on the opposite side.)  ''Progressive'' connotes ''progress'', a notion which is both positive and intuitively orthogonal to a left-right axis.

''Progressive'' and ''conservative'' are also intuitive opposites; the former represents change, the other, tradition.  This replaces the distinction between large and small government (especially with regard to government spending) evoked by the pairing of ''liberal'' / ''conservative''.  These distinctions are, however, controversial and often inaccurate in predicting how either side feels about any given issue.

Avoidance of the term ''liberal'' has the benefit of being less ambiguous.  In other countries, the terms ''liberal'' and ''conservative'' may have slightly different or even completely opposite meanings than in the United States.  ''Liberal'' can also mean ''free'', as in ''freedom'' and ''free country''.  See the article on [[Liberalism]] for a full explanation.

For more historical perspective, see the articles on  the [[Progressive Era]] and the [[United States Progressive Party|Progressive Party]] (which actually refers to several different parties of different periods).

===Australia===
The term ''progressive'' is also popular in [[Australia]], since many on the left are not supporters of the (centre-right) [[Liberal Party of Australia]]. ''Progressives'' usually support either the [[Australian Labor Party|Labor Party]], the [[Australian Democrats|Democrats]] or the [[Australian Greens|Greens]].

===Canada===
The term ''progressive'' is also popular in [[Canada]], since some on the left do not support the centrist [[Liberal Party of Canada]].  They should not, however, be confused with supporters of the old [[Progressive Conservative Party|Progressive Conservatives]]. 

The [[Progressive Party of Canada]] briefly rose to prominence in the [[1920s]]. The [[Progressive Canadians Party]], composed mostly of anti-merger [[Tories]], was formed several months prior to the 2004 general election.

===New Zealand===
[[Jim Anderton]] formed the [[New Zealand Progressive Party]] by splitting from the [[Alliance (New Zealand political party)]].

The [[Progressive Green Party (New Zealand)|Progressive Green Party]] was formed in [[1995]] but has now disbanded.

==See also==
*[[Reform movement]]

==References==

[[George Lakoff]]. ''Don't Think of an Elephant: Know Your Values and Frame the Debate''. Chelsea Green Publishing, 2004. ISBN 1-931498-71-7

==External links==
*[http://www.commondreams.org/headlines04/0630-20.htm A list of popular Progressive websites]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>