<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20040815031802|5214207" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="360876" pageid="360876" ns="0" title="Supremacism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2004-08-15T03:19:58Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Supremacism''' is the belief that one's [[race]] or [[religion]] is the supreme, and that those of other distinctions are (by various arbitrary criteria) unfit for [[social]] or religious interaction, and [[sexual reproduction]].  

Current notions of "supremacy" are generally related to [[xenophobia]], and descended from [[eugenics]] theory&amp;mdash;where the emerging sciences of [[breeding]] and [[evolutionary anthropology]] influenced social thinking toward the direction of believing in a racial self-[[identity]], and subsequently [[protectionism]] and exclusion of [[foreign]] influences.

The [[Nazi]]s were considered an supremacist group and held that the [[ethnic Germans]] and other "[[Aryan race|Aryans]]" were the "[[master race]]" &amp;mdash;superior to others. This social self-identity was resonant at the time and led to [[Hitler]]'s popular rise to [[political power | power]], and later, to state policy ending in the [[holocaust]]. The Nazis are seen by many as an archetype of supremacism.

==Supremacist groups==

*[[Ku Klux Klan]]
*[[Nazi]]s
*[[Neo-Nazism]]
*[[Nation of Islam]]
*[[German-American Bund]]

==Religious groups==
The three [[Abrahamic]] [[religion]]s can each be referred to as supremacist, a characteristic not shared by eastern religions such as [[Hinduism]], [[Buddhism]], or [[Taoism]]. Of course one must also recognize that that [[western society]] no longer openly promotes religious supremacism, the current war in [[Iraq]] being a good example. A great deal of care was made in order not to allow anti-[[Saddam Hussein|Saddam]] propaganda to include an anti-[[Islamic]] focus. On the other hand, the [[Crusades]], [[Islamism]] and the [[Jewish ethnocentrism]] all contain examples of supremacist interpretations of the respective religions [[philosophy|philosophies]].

==Supremacists and Terrorist organizations==

Although not specifically considered to be supremacist groups.  [[Terrorist]] organizations such as [[Al-Qaeda]] and groups occasionally associated with terrorism such as the [[Palestinian Liberation Organization]] display traits often associated with supremacist groups.  Examples of these traits are the spreading of [[Anti-Semitic]] propaganda and violent attacks based on race.</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>