<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20081110041000|250801457" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="360876" pageid="360876" ns="0" title="Supremacism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2008-11-15T17:09:18Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{unreferenced|date=May 2008}}
{{distinguish|suprematism}}

'''Supremacism''' is the belief that a particular [[Race (classification of human beings)|race]], [[religion]], [[gender]], [[Belief|belief system]] or [[culture]] is superior to others and entitles those who identify with it to dominate, control or rule those who do not. Examples include supremacism based on [[Ethnic group|ethnic]] or [[Anthropology|anthropological]] origins ([[white supremacy]], [[black supremacy]], [[ethnocentrism]]), [[human sexuality|sexuality]] (male supremacy, female supremacy) and [[religion]] (see below).

== Beliefs and ideas ==
If someone believes something is true whilst someone else believes it is false, each will probably regard the evidence and [[reasoning]] for his or her belief to be superior (more informed, more considered) than that of the other. For instance, if person X believes the [[Flat Earth|Earth is flat]] whilst person Y believes it isn't, X would probably consider the evidence and reasoning for his or her belief to be superior to that of Y.

Supremacism, however, goes much further. A supremacist not only holds that any evidence and reasoning for his or her beliefs is superior to any other, but that those holding such beliefs have rights over those who do not. For example:
"American leadership is good both for America and for the world" -  [[Project for the New American Century|New American Century Project]][http://www.newamericancentury.org/index.html]

== Attempts at justification ==
Following the development of theories such as [[evolution]] and [[eugenics]], supremacists have sought [[Science|scientific]] justification for their views through notions such as [[Social Darwinism]].

== Historical examples ==
[[Adolf Hitler]]'s [[Nazism|Nazi]] Party was perhaps the best-known and documented organization in history with fundamental principles of racial supremacy. They believed in the establishment of an [[Aryan#Racist connotations|Aryan]] empire throughout [[Europe]] and [[Russia]], where all people who were not of the Proto-European (Aryan) [[master race]] were to be below them. These beliefs resulted in [[World War II]] and [[The Holocaust]].

Following the [[American Civil War]], southern whites and former [[Confederate States of America|Confederates]] formed the secret society known as the [[Ku Klux Klan]]. They preached Anglo Protestant supremacy over all other races, as well as over [[Jew]]s and [[Catholic]]s.

During the first part of the [[Shōwa era]], the propaganda of the [[Empire of Japan]] used the old concept of [[hakko ichiu]] to support the idea that the [[Yamato]] was a superior race, destined to rule Asia and the Pacific. Many documents such as ''[[Kokutai no Hongi]]'', ''[[Shinmin no Michi]]'' and ''[[An Investigation of Global Policy with the Yamato Race as Nucleus]]'' referred to this concept of racial supremacy. 

Certain sectors of Jamaican-born religion of [[Rastafarianism]] preaches the supremacy of the black race and the need for Exodus back to Africa ([[Ethiopia]]).

Racial supremacy differs from [[racism]] in that, racism is the dislike or disrespect for a particular ethnic group. Racial Supremacy is the belief that one's own race is superior, dominant, chosen, smarter, more civilized, or more productive than any other race.

== Hierarchy of Races ==
Some supremacists believe in the existence of a "hierarchy of races," in which certain races are more or less "evolved" than others.  White supremacists believe they are more evolved than Blacks while certain Asians (particularly those of East Asian descent) believe they are the most superior race based on factors such as [[IQ]], educational attainment, low rates of crime and violence, and wealth (e.g., the [[model minority]], cognitive elitism).

== See also ==
* [[Biphobia]]
* [[Black supremacy]]
* [[Chauvinism]]
* [[Cognitive elite]]
* [[Heteronormative]]
* [[Heterophobia]]
* [[Heterosexism]]
* [[Homophobia]]
* [[Jewish supremacy]]
* [[Malay supremacy]]
* [[Misandry]]
* [[Misanthropy]]
* [[Misogyny]]
* [[Model minority]]
* [[Triumphalism]]
* [[White supremacy]]

{{Discrimination}}
{{Racism topics|state=collapsed}}

&lt;!--Categories--&gt;
[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Ethnic supremacy]]
[[Category:Political theories]]
[[Category:Prejudices]]
[[Category:Racism]]

&lt;!--Other languages--&gt;
[[it:Supremazismo]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>