<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20051019101235|25907806" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="360876" pageid="360876" ns="0" title="Supremacism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-10-19T16:04:01Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Supremacism''' is the belief that a particular [[race]], [[religion]], [[belief system]] or [[culture]] is superior to others and entitles those who identify with it to dominate, control or rule those who do not. Examples include supremacism based on [[ethnic]] or [[anthropological]] origins ([[white supremacism]], [[black supremacism]], [[ethnocentrism]]) and [[gender]] or [[sexuality]] (male supremacy, female supremacy, or "[[straight supremacism]]").

==Beliefs and ideas==
There is a distinction to be made between supremacism and the holding of beliefs. If someone believes something is true whilst someone else believes it is false, they will probably regard the evidence and [[reasoning]] for their belief to be superior (more informed, more considered) than that of the other person. For instance, if I believe the [[Flat Earth|Earth is flat]] whilst you believe it isn't, you would probably consider the evidence and reasoning for your belief to be superior to mine.

Supremacism, however, goes much further than this. A supremacist not only holds that any evidence and reasoning for their beliefs is superior to any other, but that they and others holding such beliefs have rights over those who do not.

Unlike [[Eastern]] religions such as [[Hinduism]], [[Buddhism]] and [[Taoism]], the three major [[Abrahamic religion]]s ([[Judaism]], [[Christianity]] and [[Islam]]) have been described as supremacist. This is largely because each have been associated not only with a set of religious beliefs and ideas but also with a race or a culture, for instance [[Christendom]].

==Recent justifications==
After the work of [[Charles Darwin]], proponents of supremacy sought scientific justification via concepts such as "[[social Darwinism]]".  The most notorious example of this is during the early [[20th century]] and the rise of [[Nazism|German National Socialism]], which posited a "[[master race]]", superior to others and therefore entitled to rule over others. This social self-identity led to [[Hitler]]'s popular rise to [[political power|power]], and later to state policy ending in the [[holocaust]]. The Nazis are seen by many as an archetype of modern supremacism.

Minority views consider more recent belief systems to be supremacist, such as:
#The [[Neoconservatism (United States)|neoconservative]] belief that Western political and economic structures should be introduced throughout the world and that doing so by force is justified.  
#The United Nations' [http://www.un.org/Overview/rights.html The Universal Declaration of Human Rights] wherein self-determination is not a right extended to "all peoples" if the identity of those "peoples" can be described as "racial".

==Supremacist groups==
The following groups qualify as supremacist organisations. 

===Racial supremacist groups===
*[[Ku Klux Klan]] (white, anti-Jewish and anti-Catholic racist and supremacist)
*[[Nazi]]s (white racist and supremacist)
*[[Neo-Nazism|Neo-Nazis]] (white racist and supremacist)
*[[German-American Bund]] (white racist and supremacist)
*[[Creativity Movement]] (worships the "white race", white supremacist)

===Religious supremacist groups===
*[[Shiv Sena]] (Hindu supremacist)	 	
*[[Vishwa Hindu Parishad]] (Hindu supremacist)	 
*[[Jewish Agency for Israel]] (Jewish land supremacist)	 
*[[Moledet]]/[[National Union]]/[[Tkuma]]/[[Herut: The National Movement]]/[[Yisrael Beytenu]] (Jewish supremacist)	 
*[[Jewish Defense League]]/[[Jewish Task Force]]/[[Chayil Party]]  ([[Kahanist]] Jewish supremacist)	 
*[[Lehi (group)]]/[[Irgun]] (Jewish supremacist terrorist groups)	 
*[[Christian Identity]] groups (white anti-Semitic Christian racist and supremacist)
*[[National Liberation Front of Tripura]] (Christian anti-Hindu supremacist)
*[[Takfir wal Hijra]] ([[Takfiri]] Islamic supremacist)
*[[Al Qaeda]]/[[GSPC]]/[[Saudi Arabia]] government ([[Salafi]] Islamic supremacist)
*[[Nation of Islam]]/[[Nation of Gods and Earths]]  (black Islamic supremacist)
*[[Hizb ut-Tahrir]] ([[Sunni]] Islamic supremacist)
*[[Al-Muhajiroun]] (Islamic supremacist)
*[[Hezbollah]]/[[Iran]] government ([[Shi'ite]] Islamic supremacist)
*[[Muslim Brotherhood]] in different national incarnations (Sunni Islamic supremacist)
*[[Hamas]]/[[Al Aqsa Martyrs Brigade]]/[[Islamic Jihad]] (Palestinian Islamic supremacist)

==See also==
*[[Black supremacy]]
*[[White supremacy]]

[[Category:Political theories]]
[[Category:Prejudices]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>