<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20031109164403|1700361" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="360876" pageid="360876" ns="0" title="Supremacism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2003-11-09T16:45:00Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">A '''Supremacist''' is a person whom believes that their [[race]], [[gender]], [[species]] or [[religion]] is the supreme race, gender species or religion. A person whom believes that a particular race, gender, species or religion is inferior to the rest could also be considered a supremacist.

Generally speaking people and groups that believe this have a hard time fitting into society and on occasion are known to do terrible things to groups they dislike.  For example, the [[Nazi]]s were an [[Aryan Race]] Supremacist group and held that the Germans were the '[[master race]]'.  They then set out to murder or enslave everyone else. See: [[holocaust]].

'''Supremacist Groups'''

*[[Ku Klux Klan]]
*[[Nazi]]s
*[[Neo-Nazism]]
*[[Nation of Islam]]
*[[German-American Bund]]

'''Supremacists and Terrorist organizations'''

Although not specifically considered to be supremacist groups.  Terrorist Organizations such as [[Al-Qaeda]] and groups occasionally associated with Terrorism such as the [[Palestinian Liberation Organization]] display traits often associated with Supremacist groups.  Examples of these traits are the spreading of [[Anti-Semitic]] propaganda and advocacy of religious states.

However sometimes groups such as these try to hide behind political causes.  Making them difficult to identify as supremacist groups.</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>