<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20071015215522|164816008" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="360876" pageid="360876" ns="0" title="Supremacism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-10-24T05:59:13Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Merge|chauvinism|Talk:Supremacism#Supremacism and chauvinism|date=May 2007}}  
{{distinguish|suprematism}}
{{Discrimination2}}
'''Supremacism''' is the belief that a particular [[race]], [[religion]], [[gender]], [[Belief|belief system]] or [[culture]] is superior to others and entitles those who identify with it to dominate, control or rule those who do not. Examples include supremacism based on [[Ethnic group|ethnic]] or [[Anthropology|anthropological]] origins ([[white supremacy]], [[black supremacy]], [[ethnocentrism]]), [[human sexuality|sexuality]] (male supremacy, female supremacy) and [[religion]] (see below).

== Beliefs and ideas ==
If someone believes something is true whilst someone else believes it is false, each will probably regard the evidence and [[reasoning]] for his or her belief to be superior (more informed, more considered) than that of the other. For instance, if person X believes the [[Flat Earth|Earth is flat]] whilst person Y believes it isn't, X would probably consider the evidence and reasoning for his or her belief to be superior to that of Y.

Supremacism, however, goes much further. A supremacist not only holds that any evidence and reasoning for his or her beliefs is superior to any other, but that those holding such beliefs have rights over those who do not.

== Attempts at justification ==
Following the development of theories such as [[evolution]] and [[eugenics]], supremacists have sought [[Science|scientific]] justification for their views through notions such as [[Social Darwinism]]. The most notorious and far-reaching example is probably the [[Nazism|Nazi]] belief in an [[Aryan#Racist connotations|Aryan]] [[master race]], which ultimately led to [[the Holocaust]].

== Historical examples ==
[[Adolf Hitler]]'s Nazi Party was perhaps the best-known and documented organization in history with fundamental principles of racial supremacy. They believed in the establishment of an Aryan empire throughout [[Europe]] and [[Russia]], where all people who were not of the Proto-European (Aryan) race were to be below them. Following the U.S. Civil War, southern whites and former [[Confederates]] formed the secret society known as the [[Ku Klux Klan]]. They preached Anglo Protestant Supremacy over all other races, as well as over [[Jew]]s and [[Catholic]]s.

[[Japan]]'s military leaders during [[World War II]] repeatedly told the Japanese population that they were a superior race, destined to rule [[Asia]] and the Pacific.

The Jamaican-born religion of [[Rastafarianism]] preaches the supremacy of the black race and the need for Exodus back to Africa (Ethiopia).

Racial Supremacy differs from [[racism]] in that, racism is the dislike or disrespect for a particular ethnic group. Racial Supremacy is the belief that one's own race is superior, dominant, chosen, smarter, more civilized, or more productive than any other race.

== Hierarchy of Races ==
There are also beliefs from supremacists, most commonly Aryans, people with Aryan blood, or North Europeans, of a hierarchy of races. This also relating to the theory of how races are higher up on a pyramid scale and more evolved than others.

== See also ==
* [[Chosen People]]
* [[Misanthropy]]
* [[Heterosexism]]
* [[Homophobia]]
* [[Black supremacy]]
* [[White supremacy]]
* [[Triumphalism]]
* [[Ketuanan Melayu]], racist belief that the Malay people are the "tuan" (masters) of Malaysia or Malaya

{{Racism topics|state=collapsed}}

&lt;!--Categories--&gt;
[[Category:Prejudices]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Racism]]
[[Category:Ethnic supremacy]]
[[Category:Political theories]]

&lt;!--Other languages--&gt;
[[it:Supremazismo]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>