<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20091116091315|326132833" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="48990" pageid="48990" ns="0" title="Social justice"><revisions><rev timestamp="2009-11-16T14:27:24Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{For|the Israeli political party|Social Justice (political party)}}
{{Intro-rewrite|date=September 2009}}
'''Social justice''' is the concept in which [[justice]] is achieved in every aspect of society, rather than the administration of law. It involves a greater degree of [[economic egalitarianism]] through [[progressive tax]]ation, [[income redistribution]], or even [[property redistribution]], policies aimed toward achieving that which developmental economists refer to as [[Equal opportunity|equality of opportunity]] and [[equality of outcome]].

The term "social justice" was coined by the [[Jesuit]] [[Luigi Taparelli]] in the 1840s and is described in much of [[John Rawls]]' writing. It is a part of [[Catholic social teaching]] and is one of the [[Four Pillars of the Green Party]] upheld by the [[worldwide green parties]]. Some tenets of social justice have been adopted by those on the left of the political spectrum. Social justice is also a concept that some use to describe the movement towards a socially just world. In this context, social justice is based on the concepts of [[human rights]] and [[social equality|equality]].

== Theories of Social Justice ==
=== Rawls ===

{{Main|John Rawls}}
The political philosopher [[John Rawls]] draws on the [[utilitarian]] insights of [[Jeremy Bentham|Bentham]] and [[John Stuart Mill|Mill]], the [[social contract]] ideas of [[John Locke|Locke]], and the [[categorical imperative]] ideas of [[Kant]]. His first statement of principle was made in ''A Theory of Justice'' (1971) where he proposed that, "Each person possesses an inviolability founded on justice that even the welfare of society as a whole cannot override. For this reason justice denies that the loss of freedom for some is made right by a greater good shared by others." (at p3). A [[deontological]] proposition that echoes Kant in framing the moral good of justice in [[Moral absolutism|absolutist]] terms. His views are definitively restated in ''Political Liberalism'' (1993), where society is seen, "as a fair system of co-operation over time, from one generation to the next." (at p14).

All societies have a basic structure of social, economic, and political institutions, both formal and informal. In testing how well these elements fit and work together, Rawls based a key test of legitimacy on the theories of [[social contract]]. To determine whether any particular system of collectively enforced social arrangements is legitimate, he argued that one must look for agreement by the people who are subject to it, but not necessarily to an objective notion of justice based on coherent ideological grounding. Obviously, not every citizen can be asked to participate in a poll to determine his or her consent to every proposal in which some degree of coercion is involved, so one has to assume that all citizens are [[reasonable]]. Rawls constructed an argument for a two-stage process to determine a citizen's hypothetical agreement:
*the citizen agrees to be represented by X for certain purposes; to that extent, X holds these powers as a [[trustee]] for the citizen; 
*X agrees that a use of enforcement in a particular social context is legitimate; the citizen, therefore, is bound by this decision because it is the function of the trustee to represent the citizen in this way. 
This applies to one person representing a small group (e.g. to the organiser of a social event setting a dress code) as equally as it does to national [[government]]s which are the ultimate trustees, holding representative powers for the benefit of all citizens within their territorial boundaries, and if those governments fail to provide for the [[social welfare|welfare]] of their citizens according to the principles of justice, they are not legitimate. To emphasise the general principle that justice should rise from the people and not be dictated by the law-making powers of governments, Rawls asserted that, "There is . . . a general presumption against imposing legal and other restrictions on conduct without sufficient reason. But this presumption creates no special priority for any particular liberty." (at pp291–292) This is support for an unranked set of liberties that reasonable citizens in all states should respect and uphold — to some extent, the list proposed by Rawls matches the normative [[human rights]] that have international recognition and direct enforcement in some nation states where the citizens need encouragement to act in way that fixes a greater degree of [[equality of outcome]].

'''The basic liberties according to Rawls'''
*Freedom of thought;
*Liberty of conscience as it affects social relationships on the grounds of religion, philosophy, and morality;
*Political liberties (e.g. representative democratic institutions, freedom of speech and the press, and freedom of assembly);
*Freedom of association;
*Freedoms necessary for the liberty and integrity of the person (viz: freedom from slavery, freedom of movement and a reasonable degree of freedom to choose one's occupation); and
*Rights and liberties covered by the rule of law.

=== Criticism ===
Many authors criticize the idea that there exists an objective standard of social justice.  [[moral relativism|Moral relativists]] deny that there is any kind of objective standard for justice in general.  [[non cognitivism|Non-cognitivists]], [[moral skepticism|moral skeptics]], [[moral nihilism|moral nihilists]], and most [[logical positivism|logical positivists]] deny the epistemic possibility of objective notions of justice. [[cynicism|Cynics]] (such as [[Niccolò Machiavelli]]) believe that any ideal of social justice is ultimately a mere justification for the [[status quo]].  Supporters of [[social darwinism]] believe that social justice assists the least fit to reproduce, sometimes labeled as [[dysgenics]], and hence should be opposed. [http://encarta.msn.com/encyclopedia_761579584/social_darwinism.html] 

Many other people accept some of the basic principles of social justice, such as the idea that all human beings have a basic level of value, but disagree with the elaborate conclusions that may or may not follow from this. One example is the statement by [[H. G. Wells]] that all people are "equally entitled to the respect of their fellow-men."{{Cite quote|date=October 2007}}

On the other hand, some scholars reject the very idea of social justice as meaningless, religious, self-contradictory, and ideological, believing that to realize any degree of social justice is unfeasible, and that the attempt to do so must destroy all liberty. The most complete rejection of the concept of social justice comes from [[Friedrich Hayek]] of the [[Austrian School]] of economics: 
&lt;blockquote&gt;There can be no test by which we can discover what is 'socially unjust' because there is no subject by which such an injustice can be committed, and there are no rules of individual conduct the observance of which in the market order would secure to the individuals and groups the position which as such (as distinguished from the procedure by which it is determined) would appear just to us.  [Social justice] does not belong to the category of error but to that of nonsense, like the term `a moral stone'.&lt;ref&gt;"Law, legislation, and liberty, Volume 2, The Mirage of Social Justice", F.A. Hayek, Routledge, 1973&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

== Social Justice from Religious Traditions ==
=== Jewish social teaching ===
{{Main|Tikkun olam}}

In ''To Heal a Fractured World: The Ethics of Responsibility'', Rabbi [[Jonathan Sacks]] describes how social justice has a central place in [[Judaism]].  One of Judaism’s most distinctive and challenging ideas is its ethics of responsibility reflected in the concepts of [[simcha]] ("gladness" or "joy"), [[tzedakah]] ("the religious obligation to perform charity and philanthropic acts"), chesed ("deeds of kindness"), and [[tikkun olam]] ("repairing the world").

=== Catholic social teaching ===
{{Main|Catholic social teaching}}
Catholic social teaching comprises those aspects of Roman Catholic  doctrine which relate to matters dealing with the collective aspect of humanity. A distinctive feature of Catholic social teaching is its concern for the poorest members of society. Two of the seven key areas&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20070608113958/http://www.usccb.org/sdwp/projects/socialteaching/excerpt.htm Seven Key Themes of Catholic Social Teaching]&lt;/ref&gt; of Catholic social teaching are pertinent to social justice:

*'''Life and dignity of the human person:''' The foundational principle of all Catholic Social Teaching is the sanctity of all human life and the inherent dignity of every human person. Human life must be valued above all material possessions. 
*'''Preferential option for the poor and vulnerable:''' Jesus taught that on the [[Day of Judgement]] God will ask what each person did to help the poor and needy: "Amen, I say to you, whatever you did for one of these least brothers of mine, you did for me."&lt;ref&gt;[[Gospel of Matthew|Matthew]] 25:40.&lt;/ref&gt; The Catholic Church teaches that through words, prayers and deeds one must show solidarity with, and compassion for, the poor. When instituting public policy the "preferential option for the poor" should always be kept at the forefront.  The moral test of any society is "how it treats its most vulnerable members. The poor have the most urgent moral claim on the conscience of the nation. People are called to look at public policy decisions in terms of how they affect the poor."&lt;ref&gt;Option for the Poor, [http://www.osjspm.org/cst/themes.htm Major themes from Catholic Social Teaching], Office for Social Justice, Archdiocese of St. Paul and Minneapolis.&lt;/ref&gt;

Even before it was propounded in the Catholic social teachings, Social Justice appeared regularly in the history of the Catholic Church:
*The term "social justice" was coined by the [[Jesuit]] [[Luigi Taparelli]] in the 1840s, based on the teachings of [[Thomas Aquinas]]. He wrote extensively in his journal ''Civiltà Cattolica'', engaging both [[capitalism|capitalist]] and [[socialist]] theories from a [[natural law]] viewpoint. His basic premise was that the rival economic theories, based on subjective [[René Descartes|Cartesian]] thinking, undermined the unity of society present in [[Thomism|Thomistic]] [[metaphysics]]; neither the liberal capitalists nor the communists concerned themselves with public [[ethics|moral]] [[philosophy]]. 
*[[Pope Leo XIII]], who studied under Taparelli, published in 1891 the [[encyclical]], ''[[Rerum Novarum]]'' (On the Condition of the Working Classes), rejecting both socialism and capitalism, while defending labor unions and private property. He stated that society should be based on cooperation and not [[class conflict]] and [[competition]]. In this document, Leo set out the Catholic Church's response to the social instability and labor conflict that had arisen in the wake of industrialization and had led to the rise of socialism. The Pope taught that the role of the State is to promote social justice through the protection of rights, while the Church must speak out on social issues in order to teach correct social principles and ensure class harmony.
*The encyclical ''[[Quadragesimo Anno]]'' (On Reconstruction of the Social Order, literally "in the fortieth year") of 1931 by [[Pope Pius XI]], encourages a [[living wage]], [[subsidiarity (Catholicism)|subsidiarity]], and teaches that social justice is a personal [[virtue]] as well as an attribute of the social order: society can be just only if individuals and institutions are just.
*[[Pope Benedict XVI]]'s encyclical ''[[Deus Caritas Est]]'' ("God is Love") of 2006 teaches that justice is the defining  concern of the state and the central concern of politics, and not of the church, which has charity as its central social concern. The laity has the specific responsibility of pursuing social justice in civil society. The church's active role in social justice should be to inform the debate, using reason and [[natural law]], and also by providing moral and spiritual formation for those involved in politics.
*The official Catholic doctrine on social justice can be found in the book ''Compendium of the Social Doctrine of the Church'', published in 2004 and updated in 2006, by the [[Pontifical Council for Justice and Peace|Pontifical Council ''Iustitia et Pax'']].

== Social Justice Movements ==
Social justice is also a concept that is used to describe the movement towards a socially just world, ie. the [[Global Justice Movement]]. In this context, social justice is based on the concepts of human rights and equality, and can be defined as ''"the way in which human rights are manifested in the everyday lives of people at every level of society"''.&lt;ref&gt; Just Comment - Volume 3 Number 1, 2000 &lt;/ref&gt;.

There are a number of [[social movement|movements]] that are working to achieve social justice in society.&lt;ref&gt;[http://socialjustice.ccnmtl.columbia.edu/index.php/Main_Page Main Page - Social Justice Wiki&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20070522080239/http://philebus.tamu.edu/~cmenzel/justice.html Social Justice and Social Justice Movements]&lt;/ref&gt; These movements are working towards the realization of a world where all members of a society, regardless of background or procedural justice, have basic human rights and equal access to the benefits of their society.

==== The Green Party ====
{{Main|Green party}}
Social Justice (sometimes "Social and Global Equality and Economic Justice") is one of the [[Four Pillars of the Green Party]] and is sometimes referred to as "Social and Global Equality" or "Economic Justice". The Canadian party defines the principle as the "equitable distribution of resources to ensure that all have full opportunities for personal and social development".&lt;ref&gt;http://www.greenparty.ca/en/about-us&lt;/ref&gt; As one of the 10 key values of the party in the United States, social justice is described as the right and opportunity  of all people "to benefit equally from       the resources afforded us by society and the environment."&lt;ref&gt;http://www.gp.org/tenkey.shtml  &lt;/ref&gt;

====Social Justice in Bioethics====

Social justice has more recently made its way into the field of bioethics. Discussion involves topics such as affordable access to health care, especially for low income households and family. The discussion also raises questions such as whether society should burden healthcare costs for low income families, whether the global marketplace is a good thing to deal with healthcare etc. etc. [[Ruth Faden]] and Madison Powers of the [[Johns Hopkins Berman Institute of Bioethics]] focus their analysis of social justice on which inequalities matter the most. The develop a social justice theory that answers some of these questions in concrete settings.

== Periodicals or Publications ==
''Social Justice'' was also the name of a periodical published by [[Father Coughlin]] in the 1930s and early 1940s.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,795777,00.html Crackdown on Coughlin]&lt;/ref&gt; Coughlin's organization was known as the National Union for Social Justice and he frequently used the term social justice in his radio broadcasts. In 1935 Coughlin made a series of broadcasts in which he outlined what he termed "the Christian principles of social justice" as an alternative to both [[capitalism]] and [[communism]].

== Social Justice and the Internet ==
In 2009, the website [http://www.onlinesocialjustice.com Onlinesocialjustice.com] emerged as a response to questions of how the internet is changing social justice concepts and practices.  With a scholarly focus, the site is set to potentially grow into a key hub for socially-conscious practitioners of Web 2.0 and beyond.  Its founder, David Toews, a Professor at the University of Windsor in Canada and affiliate of Windsor's Social Justice Centre, published his views of A Socially-Just Internet in 2008 in [http://ojs.uwindsor.ca/ojs/leddy/index.php/SSJ/article/viewArticle/669 an article in Studies in Social Justice].

== See also ==
{{MultiCol}} 
*[[Altruism]]
*[[Black theology]]
*[[Centre for Social Justice]]
*[[Counselors for Social Justice]]
*[[Distributism]]
*[[Equality of outcome]]
*[[Equal opportunity]]
*[[Equity (economics)]]
*[[Global Greens Charter]]
*[[Global justice]]
*[[Grassroots]]
{{ColBreak}}
*[[Justice (economics)]] 
*[[Liberation theology]]
*[[Progressivism]]
*[[Rule of law]]
*[[Spatial justice]]
*[[Social action]]
*[[Social criticism]]
*[[Social injustice]]
*[[Teaching for social justice]]
{{EndMultiCol}}

== References ==
{{reflist}}

== Further reading ==
*Novak, Michael, [http://www.firstthings.com/article/2007/01/defining-social-justice-29 Defining Social Justice], ''First Things''
* [[Anthony Atkinson|Atkinson, A.B.]] (1982). ''Social Justice and Public Policy.'' [http://books.google.com/books?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;id=UiZ2HdkNHBAC&amp;oi=fnd&amp;pg=PP11&amp;dq=%22Social+Justice+and+Public+Policy%22&amp;ots=-6iPmku71A&amp;sig=yACP-Kt6h174KR5dh3lsPDfGX64#PPP1,M1 Contents &amp; chapter previews.]
* [[Thomas Nixon Carver|Carver, Thomas Nixon]] (1915). ''Essays in Social Justice''. Chapter  [http://books.google.com/books?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;id=kE0tAAAAYAAJ&amp;oi=fnd&amp;pg=PA3&amp;dq=zDo9sLfoyZ&amp;sig=PvrKeGno0zH1SBhr39xLwbPfm2g#PPP13,M1 links.]
*[[Carroll Quigley|Quigley, Carroll]]. (1961). ''The Evolution Of Civilizations: An Introduction to Historical Analysis''. Second edition 1979. Indianapolis, IN: Liberty Fund. ISBN 0-913966-56-8
*Faden, Ruth &amp; Powers, Madison. "Social Justice: The Moral Foundations of Public Health and Health Policy [http://www.amazon.com/dp/0195189264]", New York, USA: Oxford University Press  
*Rawls, John. (1971). ''[[A Theory of Justice]]'', Cambridge, MA: Belknap Press of Harvard University Press. ISBN 0-674-88010-2
*Rawls, John. (1993). ''[[Political Liberalism]]''. New York: Columbia University Press (''The John Dewey Essays in Philosophy, 4''). ISBN 0-231-05248-0
*For an analysis of justice for non-ruling communities, see: [[Gad Barzilai]], Communities and Law: Politics and Cultures of Legal Identities. Ann Arbor: University of Michigan Press.
*For perspectives from Christian-informed contexts, see Philomena Cullen, Bernard Hoose &amp; Gerard Mannion (eds.), Catholic ''Social Justice: Theological and Practical Explorations'', (T. &amp;. T Clark/Continuum, 2007) and J. Franklin (ed.), ''Life to the Full: Rights and Social Justice in Australia'' (Connor Court, 2007).
*Powers, M. and Faden, R. "Inequalities in health, inequalities in health care: four generations of discussion about justice and cost-effectiveness analysis," Kennedy. Inst.Ethics J. 10 (2):109-127, 2000.
*Madison Powers and Ruth Faden,“Racial and Ethnic Disparities in Health Care: An Ethical Analysis of When and How They Matter,” in Unequal Treatment: Confronting Racial and Ethnic Disparities in Health Care, Washington, DC: National Academy of Sciences, Institute of Medicine, 2002: 722-38
*Faden, R.R., Dawson, L., Bateman-House, A.S., Agnew, D.M., Bok, H., Brock, D.W., Chakravarti, A, Gao, X-J., Greene, M., Hansen, J.A., King, P.A., O'Brien, S.J., Sachs, D.H., Schill, K.E., Siegel, A., Solter, D., Suter, S. M., Verfaillie, C.M., Walters, L.B., Gearhart, J.D.,  "Public stem cell banks: Considerations of justice in stem cell research and therapy."  Hastings Center Report, 33(6), November-December 2003.

{{Social work}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Social Justice}}
[[Category:Justice]]
[[Category:Political philosophy]]
[[Category:Practical theology]]
[[Category:Social ethics]]
[[Category:Social work]]

[[ar:عدالة اجتماعية]]
[[ca:Justícia social]]
[[de:Soziale Gerechtigkeit]]
[[es:Justicia social]]
[[eo:Socia justeco]]
[[fr:Justice sociale]]
[[hr:Socijalna pravda]]
[[id:Keadilan sosial]]
[[he:צדק חברתי]]
[[hu:Társadalmi igazságosság]]
[[nl:Sociale rechtvaardigheid]]
[[pt:Justiça social]]
[[ru:Социальная справедливость (хартия Зелёных)]]
[[sr:Социјална правда]]
[[sh:Socijalna pravda]]
[[fi:Oikeudenmukaisuus]]
[[zh:社會正義]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>