<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20201019065743|984279175" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="79942" pageid="79942" ns="0" title="Crime of apartheid"><revisions><rev timestamp="2020-11-12T00:45:01Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{About|the crime of Apartheid as defined in international law|the system of racial segregation that formerly existed in South Africa|Apartheid|other uses|Apartheid (disambiguation)}}
{{Jus in bello}}{{Discrimination sidebar|state=collapsed}}
The '''crime of Apartheid''' is defined by the 2002 [[Rome Statute of the International Criminal Court]] as inhumane acts of a character similar to other [[crimes against humanity]] "committed in the context of an institutionalized regime of systematic [[oppression]] and [[Dominance hierarchy|domination]] by one [[Race (classification of human beings)|racial group]] over any other racial group or groups and committed with the intention of maintaining that regime".

On November 30, 1973, the [[United Nations General Assembly]] opened for signature and ratification '''[[The International Convention on the Suppression and Punishment of the Crime of Apartheid]]'''.&lt;ref name="ICSPCA"&gt;[http://legal.un.org/avl/ha/cspca/cspca.html International Convention on the Suppression and Punishment of the Crime of Apartheid], retrieved on 10 October 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; It defined the crime of apartheid as "inhuman acts committed for the purpose of establishing and maintaining domination by one racial group of persons over any other racial group of persons and systematically oppressing them".&lt;ref name="text_ICSPCA"&gt;[http://www.un.org/en/genocideprevention/documents/atrocity-crimes/Doc.10_International%20Convention%20on%20the%20Suppression%20and%20Punishment%20of%20the%20Crime%20of%20Apartheid.pdf Text of the ''International Convention on the Suppression and Punishment of the Crime of Apartheid'']&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
{{International opposition to Apartheid}}
The term ''[[Wiktionary:apartheid|apartheid]]'', from [[Afrikaans]] for "apartness," was the official name of the [[History of South Africa in the apartheid era|South African system of racial segregation]] which existed after 1948. The use of Apartheid which amounts to a large collection of laws and the implementation thereof is a Dutch loan word. This use of Dutch in Legal English is unique both in the fact that it is not of Latin origin and denotes a code of laws. Complaints about the system were brought to the United Nations as early as 12 July 1948 when Dr. Padmanabha Pillai, the representative of [[India]] to the United Nations, circulated a letter to the Secretary-General expressing his concerns over treatment of ethnic Indians within the [[Union of South Africa]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.anc.org.za/show.php?id=4968
|title=Letter from the representative of India to the Secretary-General concerning the treatment of Indians in South Africa
|last=Pillai
|first=Padmanabha
|date=12 July 1948
|accessdate=10 October 2011
|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120603164112/http://www.anc.org.za/show.php?id=4968
|archive-date=3 June 2012
|url-status=dead
}}&lt;/ref&gt; As it became more widely known, South African apartheid was condemned internationally as unjust and [[racist]] and many decided that a formal legal framework was needed in order to apply international pressure on the South African government.

In 1971, the [[Soviet Union]] and [[Guinea]] together submitted early drafts of a convention to deal with the suppression and punishment of apartheid.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
|title=Southern Africa Vol. 1: United Nations-Organization of African Unity Conference Oslo 9–14 April 1973
|editor=Olav Stokke and Carl Widstrand
|year=1973
|publisher=Scandinavian Institute of African Studies}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1973, the [[UN General Assembly|General Assembly of the United Nations]] agreed on the text of the International Convention on the Suppression and Punishment of the Crime of Apartheid (ICSPCA).&lt;ref name="ICSPCA"/&gt; The Convention has 31 signatories and 107 parties.
The convention came into force in 1976 after 20 countries had ratified it. They were: Benin, Bulgaria, Belarus, Chad, Czechoslovakia, Ecuador, the German Democratic Republic (East Germany), Guinea, Hungary, Iraq, Mongolia, Poland, Qatar, Somalia, Syria, Ukraine, the USSR, the United Arab Emirates, Tanzania, Yugoslavia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=https://treaties.un.org/doc/Publication/UNTS/Volume%201015/v1015.pdf
|title=Treaties and international agreements registered or filed and recorded with the Secretariat of the United Nations
|series=VOLUME 1015
|at=p.244
|date=1976
|accessdate=13 June 2019
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

"As such, apartheid was declared to be a [[crime against humanity]], with a scope that went far beyond South Africa. While the crime of apartheid is most often associated with the racist policies of South Africa after 1948, the term more generally refers to racially based policies in any state."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
|title=The International Law Commission of the United Nations
|first=Jeffrey S.
|last=Morton
|year=2000
|publisher=University of South Carolina Press
|isbn=1-57003-170-3
|pages=27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Seventy-six other countries subsequently signed on, but a number of nations, including western democracies, have neither signed nor ratified the ICSPCA, including Canada, France, Germany, Israel, Italy, the Netherlands, the United Kingdom, Australia, New Zealand and the United States.&lt;ref&gt;[http://treaties.un.org/Pages/ViewDetails.aspx?src=TREATY&amp;mtdsg_no=IV-7&amp;chapter=4&amp;lang=en List of signatories to the ICSPCA] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120718122932/http://treaties.un.org/Pages/ViewDetails.aspx?src=TREATY&amp;mtdsg_no=IV-7&amp;chapter=4&amp;lang=en |date=July 18, 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  In explanation of the US vote against the convention, Ambassador [[Clarence Clyde Ferguson Jr.]] said: "[W]e cannot...accept that apartheid can in this manner be made a crime against humanity. Crimes against humanity are so grave in nature that they must be meticulously elaborated and strictly construed under existing international law..."&lt;ref&gt;Statement by Ambassador Clarence Clyde Ferguson Jr. before General Assembly in explanation of vote on Apartheid Convention, 30 November 1973. Review of the U.N. Commission on Human Rights: Hearings before the Subcommittee on International Organizations and Movements of the House Foreign Affairs Committee (1974) p.58&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1977, Addition Protocol 1 to the Geneva Conventions designated apartheid as a grave breach of the Protocol and a war crime. There are 169 parties to the Protocol.&lt;ref&gt;See Article 85(4) and 85(5) of Additional Protocol 1, dated 8 June 1977 [http://www.icrc.org/ihl.nsf/7c4d08d9b287a42141256739003e636b/f6c8b9fee14a77fdc125641e0052b079]&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[International Criminal Court]] provides for individual criminal responsibility for crimes against humanity,&lt;ref&gt;''Encyclopædia Britannica'', "[http://www.britannica.com/eb/article-233522 Nonstate actors in international law]".  Retrieved on 12 June 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; including the crime of apartheid.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.un.org/law/icc/statute/99_corr/2.htm Article 7] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080113100723/http://www.un.org/law/icc/statute/99_corr/2.htm |date=January 13, 2008 }} of the [[Rome Statute of the International Criminal Court]] specifically lists the "crime of apartheid" as one of eleven recognized crimes against humanity.&lt;/ref&gt;

The International Criminal Court (ICC) came into being on 1 July 2002, and can only prosecute crimes committed on or after that date.  The Court can generally only exercise jurisdiction in cases where the accused is a national of a state party, the alleged crime took place on the territory of a state party, or a situation is referred to the Court by the [[United Nations Security Council]]. The ICC exercises complimentary jurisdiction. Many of the member states have provided their own national courts with universal jurisdiction over the same offenses and do not recognize any statute of limitations for crimes against humanity.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.nottingham.ac.uk/law/hrlc/international-criminal-justice-unit/implementation-database.php |title=Database of National Implementing Legislation |access-date=2009-07-04 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080706002816/http://www.nottingham.ac.uk/law/hrlc/international-criminal-justice-unit/implementation-database.php |archive-date=2008-07-06 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; As of July 2008, 106 countries are [[States Parties to the Rome Statute of the International Criminal Court|states parties]] (with [[Suriname]] and [[Cook Islands]] set to join in October 2008), and a further 40 countries have signed but not yet ratified the treaty.&lt;ref name=untreaty&gt;United Nations.  ''Multilateral treaties deposited with the Secretary-General: [http://untreaty.un.org/ENGLISH/bible/englishinternetbible/partI/chapterXVIII/treaty11.asp Rome Statute of the International Criminal Court'']. Accessed 16 July 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;  However, many of the world's most populous nations, including [[China]], [[India]], the [[United States]], [[Indonesia]], and [[Pakistan]] are not parties to the Court and therefore are not subject to its jurisdiction, except by Security Council referral.

==ICSPCA definition of the crime of apartheid==
[[File:ICSPCA-members.PNG|thumb|upright=1.5|Signatories to the 1973 International Convention on the Suppression and Punishment of the Crime of Apartheid: parties in dark green, signed but not ratified in light green, non-members in grey]]
Article II of the ICSPCA defines the crime of apartheid as below:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;div style="text-align: center;&gt;'''International Convention on the Suppression and Punishment of the Crime of Apartheid,'''&lt;br /&gt;
'''Article II'''&lt;ref name="ICSPCA"/&gt;&lt;ref name="text_ICSPCA"/&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;

For the purpose of the present Convention, the term 'the crime of apartheid', which shall include similar policies and practices of [[racial segregation]] and discrimination as practiced in [[southern Africa]], shall apply to the following [[inhumane]] acts committed for the purpose of establishing and maintaining domination by one [[Race (classification of human beings)|racial group]] of persons over any other racial group of persons and systematically oppressing them:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
{{ordered list|type=lower-alpha
| 1 = Denial to a member or members of a racial group or groups of the [[right to life]] and [[liberty]] of person
{{ordered list|type=lower-roman
  | 1 = By murder of members of a racial group or groups;
  | 2 = By the infliction upon the members of a racial group or groups of serious [[bodily harm|bodily]] or [[Psychological trauma|mental harm]], by the infringement of their freedom or dignity, or by subjecting them to [[torture]] or to cruel, inhuman or degrading treatment or punishment;
  | 3 = By [[arbitrary arrest and detention|arbitrary arrest]] and illegal imprisonment of the members of a racial group or groups;
  }}
| 2 = Deliberate imposition on a racial group or groups of living conditions calculated to cause its or their [[Genocide|physical destruction]] in whole or in part;
| 3 = Any legislative measures and other measures calculated to prevent a racial group or groups from participation in the political, social, economic and cultural life of the country and the deliberate creation of conditions preventing the full development of such a group or groups, in particular by denying to members of a racial group or groups basic human rights and freedoms, including the [[right to work]], the right to form recognised [[trade unions]], the right to education, the [[Illegal emigration|right to leave]] and [[Right of return|to return]] to their country, the [[Nationality law|right to a nationality]], the right to [[freedom of movement]] and residence, the right to [[freedom of expression|freedom of opinion and expression]], and the right to [[Freedom of assembly|freedom of peaceful assembly]] and [[Freedom of association|association]];
| 4 = Any measures including legislative measures, designed to divide the population along racial lines by the creation of separate reserves and [[ghetto]]s for the members of a racial group or groups, the prohibition of [[Interracial marriage|mixed marriage]]s among members of various racial groups, the [[Nationalization|expropriation]] of landed property belonging to a racial group or groups or to members thereof;
| 5 = Exploitation of the labour of the members of a racial group or groups, in particular by submitting them to [[forced labour]];
| 6 = [[Persecution]] of organizations and persons, by depriving them of fundamental rights and freedoms, because they oppose [[apartheid]].
}}&lt;/blockquote&gt;

===Definition of racial discrimination===
According to the [[United Nations]] [[Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Racial Discrimination]],
{{quote|the term "racial discrimination" shall mean any distinction, exclusion, restriction or preference based on [[Race (classification of human beings)|race]], colour, [[Cultural heritage|descent]], or national or [[ethnicity|ethnic]] origin which has the purpose or effect of nullifying or impairing the recognition, enjoyment or exercise, on an equal footing, of [[human rights]] and fundamental freedoms in the political, economic, social, cultural or any other field of public life.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hri.org/docs/ICERD66.html UN International Convention on the Elimination of All of Racial Discrimination], New York 7 March 1966&lt;/ref&gt;}}

This definition does not make any difference between discrimination based on [[ethnicity]] and [[Race (classification of human beings)|race]], in part because the distinction between the two remains debatable among [[Anthropology|anthropologists]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |first=A. |last=Metraux |year=1950 |title=United nations Economic and Security Council Statement by Experts on Problems of Race |journal=[[American Anthropologist]] |volume=53 |issue=1 |pages=142–145 |doi=10.1525/aa.1951.53.1.02a00370 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, in British law the phrase ''racial group'' means "any group of people who are defined by reference to their race, colour, nationality (including citizenship) or ethnic or national origin".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.cps.gov.uk/publications/prosecution/rrpbcrbook.html |title=Racist and Religious Crime – CPS Prosecution Policy |publisher=The CPS |accessdate=2010-05-23 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100119032241/http://www.cps.gov.uk/publications/prosecution/rrpbcrbook.html |archive-date=2010-01-19 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==ICC definition of the crime of apartheid==
Article 7 of the [[Rome Statute of the International Criminal Court]] defines crimes against humanity as:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
;Article 7
;Crimes against humanity
{{ordered list
|1 = For the purpose of this Statute, 'crime against humanity' means any of the following acts when committed as part of a widespread or systematic attack directed against any civilian population, with knowledge of the attack:
{{ordered list|type=lower-alpha
  |1 = Murder;
  |2 = Extermination;
  |3 = Enslavement;
  |4 = Deportation or forcible transfer of population;
  |5 = Imprisonment or other severe deprivation of physical liberty in violation of fundamental rules of international law;
  |6 = [[Torture]];
  |7 = Rape, sexual slavery, enforced prostitution, forced pregnancy, enforced sterilization, or any other form of sexual violence of comparable gravity;
  |8 = Persecution against any identifiable group or collectivity on political, racial, national, ethnic, cultural, religious, gender as defined in paragraph 3, or other grounds that are universally recognized as impermissible under international law, in connection with any act referred to in this paragraph or any crime within the jurisdiction of the Court;
  |9 = Enforced disappearance of persons;
  |10 = The crime of apartheid;
  |11 = Other inhumane acts of a similar character intentionally causing great suffering, or serious injury to body or to mental or physical health.&lt;ref name="rome_art7"&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://legal.un.org/icc/statute/99_corr/2.htm
|title=Rome Statute of the International Criminal Court, Part 2, Article 7
|author=United Nations
|year=2002
|accessdate=21 July 2007
|archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20070712204433/http://www.un.org/law/icc/statute/99_corr/2.htm#art.7 &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 12 July 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 }}
}}&lt;/blockquote&gt;
Later in Article 7, the crime of apartheid is defined as:
&lt;blockquote&gt;The 'crime of apartheid' means inhumane acts of a character similar to those referred to in paragraph 1, committed in the context of an institutionalised regime of systematic oppression and domination by one racial group over any other racial group or groups and committed with the intention of maintaining that regime.&lt;ref name="rome_art7"/&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==Accusations of apartheid by country==

===China===

The privileging of the [[Han people]] in ethnic minority areas outside of [[China proper]], such as the [[Uyghurs|Uyghur]]-majority [[Xinjiang]] and the central government's [[Chinese settlements in Tibet|policy of settlement]] in [[Tibet]], and the alleged erosion of indigenous religion, language and culture through repressive measures (such as the Han [[Bingtuan]] militia in Xinjiang) and [[sinicization]] have been likened to "cultural genocide" and apartheid by some activists.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last1=Seytoff |first1=Alim A |title=China's Uighurs claim cultural 'genocide' |url=https://www.aljazeera.com/indepth/opinion/2014/06/china-uighurs-claim-cultural-gen-20146165946224857.html |accessdate=14 August 2018 |work=Al Jazeera |date=2 June 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Apartheid with Chinese characteristics: China has turned Xinjiang into a police state like no other |url=https://www.economist.com/briefing/2018/05/31/china-has-turned-xinjiang-into-a-police-state-like-no-other |accessdate=14 August 2018 |work=The Economist |date=31 May 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; With regards to [[Chinese settlements in Tibet]], in 1991 the [[Tenzin Gyatso, 14th Dalai Lama|Dalai Lama]] declared:

&lt;blockquote&gt; The new Chinese settlers have created an alternate society: a Chinese apartheid which, denying Tibetans equal social and economic status in our own land, threatens to finally overwhelm and absorb us.&lt;ref name=Dalai&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/asia-pacific/1347735.stm "Profile: The Dalai Lama"], ''[[BBC News]]'', April 25, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;United States Congressional Serial Set, United States Government Printing Office, 1993, p. 110.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Additionally, the traditional residential system of ''[[hukou]]'' has been likened to apartheid due to its classification of 'rural' and 'urban' residency status,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=The rural-urban divide: Ending apartheid |url=https://www.economist.com/special-report/2014/04/19/ending-apartheid |accessdate=14 August 2018 |work=The Economist|url-access=subscription  |date=19 April 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=China rethinks peasant 'apartheid' |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/asia-pacific/4424944.stm |accessdate=14 August 2018 |work=BBC News |date=10 November 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; and is sometimes likened to a form of [[caste]] system.&lt;ref&gt;"Chinese Society: Change, Conflict and Resistance", by Elizabeth J. Perry, Mark Selden, page [https://books.google.com/books?id=JqZyQCZmrRAC&amp;pg=PA90 90]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;"China's New Confucianism: Politics and Everyday Life in a Changing Society", p. 86, by Daniel A. Bell&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;"Trust and Distrust: Sociocultural Perspectives", p. 63, by Ivana Marková, Alex Gillespie&lt;/ref&gt; In recent years, the system has undergone reform, with an expansion of urban residency permits in order to accommodate more migrant workers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last1=Lu |first1=Rachel |title=China Is Ending Its 'Apartheid.' Here's Why No One Is Happy About It |url=https://foreignpolicy.com/2014/07/31/china-is-ending-its-apartheid-heres-why-no-one-is-happy-about-it/ |accessdate=14 August 2018 |work=Foreign Policy |date=31 July 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last1=Sheehan |first1=Spencer |title=China's Hukou Reforms and the Urbanization Challenge |url=https://thediplomat.com/2017/02/chinas-hukou-reforms-and-the-urbanization-challenge/ |accessdate=14 August 2018 |work=The Diplomat |date=22 February 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Israel===
{{main|Israel and the apartheid analogy}}
Critics have accused Israel of committing the crime of apartheid; In a 2007 report, United Nations Special Rapporteur for Palestine John Dugard stated that "elements of the [state of Israel's] occupation constitute forms of colonialism and of apartheid, which are contrary to international law." and suggested that the "legal consequences of a prolonged occupation with features of colonialism and apartheid" be put to the [[International Court of Justice]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Dugard|first=John|title=Implementation of General Assembly resolution 60/251 of 15 March 2006 entitled "Human Rights Council": Report of the Special Rapporteur on the situation of human rights in the Palestinian territories occupied since 1967, John Dugard|url=http://www.unhcr.org/refworld/pdfid/461e52b12.pdf|page=3|quote=The international community has identified three regimes as inimical to human rights – colonialism, apartheid and foreign occupation. Israel is clearly in military occupation of the OPT. At the same time elements of the occupation constitute forms of colonialism and of apartheid, which are contrary to international law. What are the legal consequences of a regime of prolonged occupation with features of colonialism and apartheid for the occupied people, the occupying Power and third States? It is suggested that this question might appropriately be put to the International Court of Justice for a further advisory opinion.|postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2007, the Department of Foreign Affairs of the South African Government commissioned the [[Human Sciences Research Council]] of South Africa to investigate whether Israel was practicing apartheid in the occupied Palestinian territories. For this purpose, the HSRC assembled an international team of scholars specializing in international human rights law, with HSRC researcher [[Virginia Tilley]] serving as project leader. In 2009, the HSRC team submitted a 180,000-word report finding that Israeli policies in the occupied Palestinian territories were consistent with apartheid as defined in international law.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.alhaq.org/attachments/article/236/Occupation_Colonialism_Apartheid-FullStudy.pdf Tilley, V., ed., "Occupation, Colonialism, Apartheid? A Reassessment of Israel's Practices in the Occupied Palestinian Territories under International Law"] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170510115026/http://www.alhaq.org/attachments/article/236/Occupation_Colonialism_Apartheid-FullStudy.pdf |date=2017-05-10 }}.&lt;/ref&gt; 

In 2010, Richard Falk, the UN Special Rapporteur for Palestine said that this "general structure of apartheid that exists in the Occupied Palestinian Territories ... makes the allegation increasingly credible despite the differences between the specific characteristics of South African apartheid and that of the Occupied Palestinian Territories regime".&lt;ref&gt;[https://unispal.un.org/DPA/DPR/UNISPAL.NSF/5ba47a5c6cef541b802563e000493b8c/69bec99af727eac2852577c3004aad8a?OpenDocument Richard Falk Report to the UN General Assembly, 30 August 2010, paragraph. 5] accessdate= 19.12.2010, paragraph 5&lt;/ref&gt; In 2017, Tilley and Falk authored a report commissioned by the [[United Nations Economic and Social Commission for Western Asia]], then chaired by Dr. [[Rima Khalaf]]. According to Khalaf, the report was prepared at the request of ESCWA member states (ESCWA is composed of eighteen Arab states in Western Asia). The report found that Israel has established an apartheid regime impacting the Palestinian people as a whole, including Palestinians in the occupied territories, Palestinian citizens of Israel, Palestinians holding Jerusalem residency and Palestinian refugees. The report further urged governments to take all measures stipulated in international law to end this apartheid regime, including support for BDS (Boycott, Divest, and Sanction) policies. US Ambassador [[Nikki Haley]] issued a statement saying the UN Secretariat must "withdraw the report altogether". The Israeli foreign ministry compared the report to the Nazi propaganda paper ''[[Der Stürmer]]''. A UN spokesman stated that "the report as it stands does not reflect the views of the secretary-general", and that it only reflects the opinion of its authors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |agency=Reuters |title=Israel imposes 'apartheid regime' on Palestinians: U.N. report |url=https://www.reuters.com/article/us-israel-palestinians-report-idUSKBN16M2IN |location=Beirut, Lebanon |date=15 March 2017 |access-date=10 July 2018 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The report was withdrawn from the ESCWA website on the instructions of Secretary-General [[António Guterres]], and Rima Khalaf resigned in protest from her position as ESCWA chair.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2017/03/17/world/middleeast/un-rima-khalaf-quits-israel-apartheid.html?_r=0|title=U.N. Diplomat Behind Report Accusing Israel of Apartheid Quits|date=March 17, 2017|website=www.nytimes.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.reuters.com/article/us-un-israel-report-resignation-idUSKBN16O24X Senior U.N. official quits after 'apartheid' Israel report pulled], Reuters, 17 March 2017&lt;/ref&gt;

[[South Africa]]n Judge [[Richard Goldstone]], head of the Report of the United Nations Fact Finding Mission on the Gaza Conflict, also known as the [[Goldstone Report]], writing in [[The New York Times]] in October 2011, said that "in Israel, there is no apartheid. Nothing there comes close to the definition of apartheid under the 1998 Rome Statute." Goldstone noted that [[Arab citizens of Israel]] are allowed to vote, have political parties, and hold seats in the [[Knesset]] and other positions, including one on the [[Supreme Court of Israel|Israeli Supreme Court]]. Goldstone wrote that the situation in the West Bank was more complex, but that there is no attempt to maintain "an institutionalized regime of systematic oppression and domination by one racial group", and claimed that the seemingly oppressive measures taken by Israel were taken to protect its own citizens from attacks by Palestinian militants.&lt;ref name="Goldstone2011"&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2011/11/01/opinion/israel-and-the-apartheid-slander.html |title=Israel and the Apartheid Slander |first=Richard J. |last=Goldstone |newspaper=[[The New York Times]] |date=October 31, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; However the Goldstone Report does not contain any reference to charges of apartheid, whether supported or not.&lt;ref&gt;http://www2.ohchr.org/english/bodies/hrcouncil/docs/12session/A-HRC-12-48.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; With regard to associated issue of positive findings of Israeli war crimes in the report, Goldstone has argued for a redaction. However the other three authors of the Goldstone Report have publicly rejected this arguing Goldstone has "misrepresented facts in an attempt to delegitimise the [Goldstone Report's] findings and to cast doubts on its credibility".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2011/apr/14/goldstone-report-statement-un-gaza | location=London | work=The Guardian | first1=Hina | last1=Jilani | first2=Christine | last2=Chinkin | first3=Desmond | last3=Travers | title=Goldstone report: Statement issued by members of UN mission on Gaza war | date=14 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Myanmar===
Since Myanmar's transition to relative democratic rule beginning in 2010, the government's response to the [[Rohingya genocide]] has been widely condemned, and has been described as an [[ethnic cleansing]] by the [[United Nations]], [[International Criminal Court|ICC]] officials, and other governments.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.cbsnews.com/news/myanmar-mass-graves-latest-rohingya-slaughter-genocide-ap/|title=AP finds mass graves, latest evidence of Rohingya genocide in Myanmar|accessdate=10 April 2018|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180411174445/https://www.cbsnews.com/news/myanmar-mass-graves-latest-rohingya-slaughter-genocide-ap/|archive-date=11 April 2018|url-status=live|publisher=CBS News}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.latimes.com/world/la-fg-myanmar-rohingyas-20180313-story.html|title=U.N. genocide advisor: Myanmar waged 'scorched-earth campaign' against the Rohingya|accessdate=10 April 2018|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180411174500/http://www.latimes.com/world/la-fg-myanmar-rohingyas-20180313-story.html|archive-date=11 April 2018|url-status=live|work=Los Angeles Times}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.cnn.com/2018/03/12/asia/myanmar-rohingya-un-violence-genocide-intl/index.html|title=UN official convinced of Myanmar Rohingya 'genocide'|access-date=10 April 2018|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180411174221/https://www.cnn.com/2018/03/12/asia/myanmar-rohingya-un-violence-genocide-intl/index.html|archive-date=11 April 2018|url-status=live|publisher=CNN}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.amnestyusa.org/press-releases/un-security-council-end-disgraceful-inaction-on-myanmars-rohingya-crisis/|title=UN Security Council: End disgraceful inaction on Myanmar's Rohingya crisis|publisher=Amnesty International|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180411174225/https://www.amnestyusa.org/press-releases/un-security-council-end-disgraceful-inaction-on-myanmars-rohingya-crisis/|archive-date=11 April 2018|url-status=dead|accessdate=10 April 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.cnn.com/2017/11/22/politics/tillerson-myanmar-ethnic-cleansing/index.html|title=Tillerson: Myanmar clearly 'ethnic cleansing' the Rohingya|accessdate=10 April 2018|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180410132738/https://www.cnn.com/2017/11/22/politics/tillerson-myanmar-ethnic-cleansing/index.html|archive-date=10 April 2018|url-status=live|publisher=CNN}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Guardian"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Burma-Mass-Destruction"&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.hrw.org/news/2017/10/17/burma-new-satellite-images-confirm-mass-destruction|title=Burma: New Satellite Images Confirm Mass Destruction|date=17 October 2017|publisher=[[Human Rights Watch]]|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180106003237/https://www.hrw.org/news/2017/10/17/burma-new-satellite-images-confirm-mass-destruction|archive-date=6 January 2018|url-status=live|access-date=14 January 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Myanmar's current policies towards the [[Rohingya]] population include ethnic segregation, limited access to resources (comparable to the bantustan system), a lack of civil rights, ID card and special permit systems without any guarantee of citizenship (akin to the [[pass laws]]), restrictions on movement, and even institutionalized racial definitions, with the Rohingya being officially labelled as "Bengali races".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Myanmar: Rohingya trapped in dehumanising apartheid regime |url=https://www.amnesty.org/en/latest/news/2017/11/myanmar-rohingya-trapped-in-dehumanising-apartheid-regime/ |website=Amnesty International |accessdate=11 May 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, the UN has explicitly condemned Myanmar over creating an apartheid state, threatening to withdraw aid from the country.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last1=McCarthy |first1=Joe |title=UN Accuses Myanmar of Creating ‘Apartheid State’ and Threatens to Withhold Aid |url=https://www.globalcitizen.org/en/content/rohingya-myanmar-apartheid/ |accessdate=11 May 2020 |publisher=Global Citizen |date=17 June 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===North Korea===
[[File:Demilitarized Zone of Korea 03.JPG|thumb|Pro-[[Korean unification|unification]] propaganda on the [[Korean Demilitarized Zone]].]]
Some commentators have compared modern-day [[North Korea]] to apartheid South Africa. In an anonymous [[News24]] opinion piece, the [[African National Congress Youth League]] was criticized for its praise of former North Korean leader [[Kim Jong-il]] after his [[Death and state funeral of Kim Jong-il|death]] (the North Koreans provided support to the [[African National Congress]] and other anti-apartheid movements). Parallels were made between North Korea and apartheid South Africa, including institutionalized ideas of racial purity, the heavy restrictions on letting foreign citizens live in the country, and the living conditions in North Korea outside of [[Pyongyang]] being compared to South Africa's [[bantustan]] system.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=North Korea an 'Apartheid' State |url=https://www.news24.com/MyNews24/North-Korea-an-Apartheid-State-20111228 |website=News24.com |publisher=Naspers Limited |accessdate=2 April 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other points of comparison have included the ''[[songbun]]'' system being equivalent to the [[Population Registration Act, 1950|Population Registration Act]], both states having developed nuclear weapons for self-defense purposes, international isolation, and the proliferation of race myths in national history.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Noland |first1=Marcus |title=Myers, Apartheid, and Engagement with North Korea |url=https://www.piie.com/blogs/north-korea-witness-transformation/myers-apartheid-and-engagement-north-korea |website=Pierson Institute for International Economics |accessdate=2 April 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Saudi Arabia===
[[Image:Christian Bypass.jpg|thumb|right|280px|Road sign on a highway into Mecca, stating that one direction is "Muslims only" while another direction is "obligatory for non-Muslims". [[Committee for the Promotion of Virtue and the Prevention of Vice (Saudi Arabia)|Religious police]] are stationed beyond the turnoff on the main road to prevent non-Muslims from proceeding into Mecca and Medina.&lt;ref name=mackeymecca&gt;[[Sandra Mackey]]'s account of her attempt to enter Mecca in {{cite book|last=Mackey|first=Sandra|title=The Saudis: Inside the Desert Kingdom|year=1987|pages=63–64|publisher=W. W. Norton &amp; Company|isbn=0-393-32417-6}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
{{main|Saudi Arabia and the apartheid analogy}}
Saudi Arabia's treatment of religious minorities has been described by both Saudis and non-Saudis as "[[apartheid]]" and "religious apartheid".&lt;ref&gt;Saudi Institute (2001).&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Alan Dershowitz]] wrote in 2002, "in Saudi Arabia apartheid is practiced against non-Muslims, with signs indicating that Muslims must go to certain areas and non-Muslims to others."&lt;ref&gt;Alan M. Dershowitz, [http://www.jewishworldreview.com/1102/alien_visit.asp Treatment of Israel strikes an alien note], Jewish World Review, November 8, 2002.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2003, [[Amir Taheri]] quoted a Shi'ite businessman from [[Dhahran]] as saying "It is not normal that there are no Shi'ite army officers, ministers, governors, mayors and ambassadors in this kingdom. This form of religious apartheid is as intolerable as was apartheid based on race."&lt;ref&gt;Taheri (2003).&lt;/ref&gt;

Testifying before the [[Tom Lantos Human Rights Commission|U.S. Congressional Human Rights Caucus]] on June 4, 2002, in a briefing entitled "Human Rights in Saudi Arabia: The Role of Women", Ali Al-Ahmed, Director of the Saudi Institute, stated:
&lt;blockquote&gt;Saudi Arabia is a glaring example of religious apartheid. The religious institutions from government clerics to judges, to religious curricula, and all religious instructions in media are restricted to the [[Wahhabism|Wahhabi]] understanding of [[Islam]], adhered to by less than 40% of the population. The Saudi government communized Islam, through its monopoly of both religious thoughts and practice. Wahhabi Islam is imposed and enforced on all Saudis regardless of their religious orientations. The Wahhabi sect does not tolerate other religious or ideological beliefs, Muslim or not. Religious symbols by Muslims, [[Christianity|Christians]], [[Judaism|Jews]] and other believers are all banned. The Saudi embassy in Washington is a living example of religious apartheid. In its 50 years, there has not been a single non-Sunni Muslim diplomat in the embassy. The branch of [[Imam Mohamed Bin Saud University]] in Fairfax, Virginia instructs its students that [[Shia Islam]] is a Jewish conspiracy.&lt;ref&gt;Congressional Human Rights Caucus (2002).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

On December 14, 2005, [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican]] [[United States House of Representatives|Representative]] [[Ileana Ros-Lehtinen]] and [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democratic]] Representative [[Shelley Berkley]] introduced a bill in Congress urging American divestiture from Saudi Arabia, and giving as its rationale (among other things) "Saudi Arabia is a country that practices religious apartheid and continuously subjugates its citizenry, both Muslim and non-Muslim, to a specific interpretation of Islam."&lt;ref&gt;[http://thomas.loc.gov/cgi-bin/query/z?c109:H.R.4543.IH: To express the policy of the United States to ensure the divestiture...] 109th CONGRESS, 1st Session, H. R. 4543.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Freedom House]] showed on its website, on a page tiled "Religious apartheid in Saudi Arabia", a picture of a sign showing Muslim-only and non-Muslim roads.&lt;ref&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20060221180044/http://www.freedomhouse.org/religion/country/Saudi%20Arabia/religious%20apartheid%20in%20sa.htm Religious Apartheid in Saudi Arabia], [[Freedom House]] website. Retrieved July 11, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

===South Africa===
{{main|Apartheid in South Africa}}
[[File:Nelson Mandela statue.jpg|thumb|Nelson Mandela successfully fought against apartheid in South Africa. ]]
The name of the crime comes from a system of racial segregation in South Africa enforced through legislation by the National Party (NP), the governing party from 1948 to 1994. Under apartheid, the rights, associations, and movements of the majority black inhabitants and other ethnic groups were curtailed, and white minority rule was maintained.

===Sudan===
{{see|Sudan and the apartheid analogy}}
In early 1991, non-Arabs of the Zaghawa tribe of Sudan attested that they were victims of an intensifying Arab [[apartheid]] campaign, segregating Arabs and non-Arabs.&lt;ref name="Johnson2011"&gt;{{cite book|first=Hilde F. |last=Johnson|title=Waging Peace in Sudan: The Inside Story of the Negotiations that Ended Africa's Longest Civil War|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=WhlarBGyoQQC|year=2011|publisher=Sussex Academic Press|isbn=978-1-84519-453-6 |page=38}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sudanese Arabs, who controlled the government, were widely referred to as practicing apartheid against Sudan's non-Arab citizens. The government was accused of "deftly manipulat(ing) Arab solidarity" to carry out policies of apartheid and ethnic cleansing.&lt;ref name="Lasaga"&gt;Vukoni Lupa Lasaga, "The slow, violent death of apartheid in Sudan," 19 September 2006, Norwegian Council for Africa.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[American University]] economist [[George Ayittey]] accused the Arab government of Sudan of practicing acts of racism against black citizens.&lt;ref&gt;George Ayittey, Africa and China, [[The Economist]], 19 February 2010&lt;/ref&gt; According to Ayittey, "In Sudan... the Arabs monopolized power and excluded blacks – Arab apartheid."&lt;ref&gt;"How the Multilateral Institutions Compounded Africa's Economic Crisis", George B.N. Ayittey; Law and Policy in International Business, Vol. 30, 1999.&lt;/ref&gt; Many African commentators joined Ayittey in accusing Sudan of practising Arab apartheid.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Koigi wa Wamwere|title=Negative Ethnicity: From Bias to Genocide|url=https://archive.org/details/negativeethnicit0000koig|url-access=registration|year=2003|publisher=Seven Stories Press|isbn=978-1-58322-576-9 |page= [https://archive.org/details/negativeethnicit0000koig/page/152 152]}}&lt;br/&gt;{{cite book|author=George B.N. Ayittey|title=Africa in Chaos: A Comparative History|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=5HtUn_dUmSYC|date=15 January 1999|publisher=Palgrave Macmillan|isbn=978-0-312-21787-7 |page= 50}}&lt;br/&gt;{{cite book|author=George B. N. Ayittey|title=Indigenous African Institutions|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ltMjAQAAIAAJ|year=2006|publisher=Transnational Publishers|isbn=978-1-57105-337-4}}&lt;br/&gt;{{cite journal|first=Garba |last=Diallo |title=Mauritania, the other apartheid? |url=http://www.isn.ethz.ch/Digital-Library/Publications/Detail/?ots783=0c54e3b3-1e9c-be1e-2c24-a6a8c7060233&amp;lng=en&amp;id=104909 |issue=16 |journal=Current African Issues |publisher=Nordiska Afrikainstitutet |year=1993}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Alan Dershowitz]] labeled Sudan an example of a government that "actually deserve(s)" the appellation "apartheid".&lt;ref name="Dershowitz2008"&gt;{{cite book|author=Alan Dershowitz|title=The Case Against Israel's Enemies: Exposing Jimmy Carter and Others Who Stand in the Way of Peace|url=https://archive.org/details/caseagainstisrae0000ders|url-access=registration|date=3 November 2008|publisher=John Wiley &amp; Sons|isbn=978-0-470-44745-1 |page= [https://archive.org/details/caseagainstisrae0000ders/page/24 24]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Former Canadian Minister of Justice [[Irwin Cotler]] echoed the accusation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| first=Hubert |last=Bauch |title=Ex-minister speaks out against Sudan's al-Bashir |url=http://www.canada.com/news/minister+speaks+against+Sudan+Bashir/1362904/story.html |newspaper=Montreal Gazette |date=6 March 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Racial segregation]]
* [[Racial segregation in the United States]]
* [[Human rights in Myanmar]]
* [[Human rights in North Korea]]
* [[Human rights in South Africa]]
* [[Human rights in Sudan]]
* [[Human rights in Zimbabwe]]
* [[White Australia Policy]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
* [http://legal.un.org/avl/ha/cspca/cspca.html Introductory note] by [[John Dugard]] on the International Convention on the Suppression and Punishment of the Crime of Apartheid in the [http://legal.un.org/avl/historicarchives.html Historic Archives of the United Nations Audiovisual Library of International Law]
* [http://legal.un.org/avl/ha/cspca/cspca.html Procedural history] of the International Convention on the Suppression and Punishment of the Crime of Apartheid in the [http://legal.un.org/avl/historicarchives.html Historic Archives of the United Nations Audiovisual Library of International Law]

==External links==
{{wiktionary|apartheid}}
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20170510115026/http://www.alhaq.org/attachments/article/236/Occupation_Colonialism_Apartheid-FullStudy.pdf Human Sciences Research Council: Occupation, Colonialism, Apartheid? A re-assessment of Israel’s practices in the occupied Palestinian territories under international law. Cape Town 2009]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20101123003904/http://www.middleeastmonitor.org.uk/downloads/other_reports/report-of-the-special-rapporteur-on-the-situation-of-human-rights-in-the-palestinian-territories-occupied-since-1967.pdf Richard Falk:Report of the Special Rapporteur on the situation of human rights in the Palestinian territories occupied since 1967, Report to the UN General Assembly, 30.August 2010, sec. 5]
* [https://www.hrw.org/node/95061 Human Rights Watch Report: Separate and Unequal. Israel’s Discriminatory Treatment of Palestinians in the Occupied Palestinian Territories, December 19 2010]

{{International Criminal Law}}
{{Racism topics|state=collapsed}}
{{International human rights legal instruments}}

[[Category:Racial segregation]]
[[Category:International criminal law|Apart]]
[[Category:International opposition to apartheid in South Africa]]
[[Category:Crimes against humanity|Apart]]
[[Category:Apartheid]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>