<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20081111060406|251046828" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="79942" pageid="79942" ns="0" title="Crime of apartheid"><revisions><rev timestamp="2008-11-11T06:05:04Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{about|the crime of apartheid as defined in international law|the system of racial segregation that formerly existed in [[South Africa]]|South Africa under apartheid|other uses|Apartheid (disambiguation)}}
The '''crime of apartheid''' is defined by the 2002 [[Rome Statute of the International Criminal Court]] which established the [[International Criminal Court]] as inhumane acts of a character similar to other [[crimes against humanity]] "committed in the context of an institutionalised regime of systematic [[oppression]] and [[Dominance hierarchy|domination]] by one [[Race (classification of human beings)|racial group]] over any other racial group or groups and committed with the intention of maintaining that regime." It lists such crimes as [[murder]], [[slavery|enslavement]], deprivation of physical [[liberty]], [[forced relocation]], [[sexual violence]], and [[collective persecution]].&lt;ref name="rome_art5"&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.un.org/law/icc/statute/99_corr/2.htm#art.5
|title=Rome Statute of the International Criminal Court, Part 2, Article 5
|author=United Nations
|year=2002
|accessdaymonth=21 July
|accessyear=2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 30 November 1973, the [[United Nations]] [[United Nations General Assembly|General Assembly]] opened for signature and ratification the '''International Convention on the Suppression and Punishment of the Crime of Apartheid''' (ICSPCA)&lt;ref name="ICSPCA"&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.unhchr.ch/html/menu3/b/11.htm
|title=International Convention on the Suppression and Punishment of the Crime of ''Apartheid''
|author=United Nations
|date=30 November 2006
|accessdaymonth=8 October
|accessyear=2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; It defined the crime of apartheid as "inhuman acts committed for the purpose of establishing and maintaining domination by one racial group of persons over any other racial group of persons and systematically oppressing them."

==History==
{{FixBunching|beg}}
{{International opposition to Apartheid}}
{{FixBunching|mid}}
[[Image:ICSPCA-members.PNG|thumb|right|400px|Signatories to the International Convention on the Suppression and Punishment of the Crime of Apartheid: parties in dark green, signed but not ratified in light green, non-members in grey]]
{{FixBunching|end}}
The term ''[[Wiktionary:apartheid|apartheid]]'', from [[Afrikaans language|Afrikaans]] for "apartness," was the official name of the [[History of South Africa in the apartheid era|South African system of racial segregation]] which existed after 1948. Complaints about the system were brought to the United Nations as early as 12 July 1948 when Dr. Padmanabha Pillai, the representative of [[India]] to the United Nations, circulated a letter to the Secretary-General expressing his concerns over treatment of ethnic Indians within the [[Union of South Africa]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.anc.org.za/un/undocs1a.html#2
|title=Letter from the representative of India to the Secretary-General concerning the treatment of Indians in South Africa
|last=Pillai
|first=Padmanabha
|date=12 July 1948
|accessdaymonth=17 July
|accessyear=2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; As it became more widely known, South African apartheid was condemned internationally as unjust and [[racist]] and many{{Who|date=August 2007}} decided that a formal legal framework was needed in order to apply international pressure on the South African government.

In 1971, the [[Union of Soviet Socialist Republics]] and [[Guinea]] together submitted early drafts of a convention to deal with the suppression and punishment of apartheid.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
|title=Southern Africa Vol. 1: United Nations-Organization of African Unity Conference Oslo 9-14 April 1973
|editor=Olav Stokke and Carl Widstrand
|year=1973
|publisher=Scandinavian Institute of African Studies}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1973, the [[UN General Assembly|General Assembly of the United Nations]] agreed on the text of the International Convention on the Suppression and Punishment of the Crime of Apartheid (ICSPCA).&lt;ref name="ICSPCA"/&gt; The Convention has 31 signatories and 107 parties.

"As such, apartheid was declared to be a [[crime against humanity]], with a scope that went far beyond South Africa. While the crime of apartheid is most often associated with the racist policies of South Africa after 1948, the term more generally refers to racially based policies in any state."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
|title=The International Law Commission of the United Nations
|first=Jeffrey S.
|last=Morton
|year=2000
|publisher=University of South Carolina Press
|isbn=1570031703
|pages=27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Seventy-six other countries subsequently signed on, but a number of nations have neither signed nor ratified the ICSPCA, including Canada, France, Germany, Israel, Italy, the Netherlands, the United Kingdom and the United States.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ohchr.org/english/countries/ratification/7.htm]&lt;/ref&gt; In explanation of the US vote against the convention, Ambassador [[Clarence Clyde Ferguson Jr.]] said: "[W]e cannot...accept that apartheid can in this manner be made a crime against humanity. Crimes against humanity are so grave in  nature that they must be meticulously elaborated and strictly construed under existing international law..."&lt;ref&gt;Statement by Ambassador Clarence Clyde Ferguson Jr. before General Assembly in explanation of vote on Apartheid Convention, 30 November 1973. Review of the U.N. Commission on Human Rights: Hearings before the Subcommittee on International Organizations and Movements of the House Foreign Affairs Committee (1974) p.58&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[International Criminal Court]] provides for individual criminal responsibility for crimes against humanity,&lt;ref&gt;''Encyclopædia Britannica'', "[http://www.britannica.com/eb/article-233522 Nonstate actors in international law]".  Retrieved on 12 June 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; including the crime of apartheid.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.un.org/law/icc/statute/99_corr/2.htm Article 7] of the [[Rome Statute of the International Criminal Court]] specifically lists the "crime of apartheid" as one of eleven recognized crimes against humanity.&lt;/ref&gt;

The International Criminal Court (ICC) came into being on 1 July 2002, and can only prosecute crimes committed on or after that date.  The Court can generally only exercise jurisdiction in cases where the accused is a national of a state party, the alleged crime took place on the territory of a state party, or a situation is referred to the Court by the [[United Nations Security Council]].  As of July 2008, 106 countries are [[States Parties to the Rome Statute of the International Criminal Court|states parties]] (with [[Suriname]] and [[Cook Islands]] set to join in October 2008), and a further 40 countries have signed but not yet ratified the treaty.&lt;ref name=untreaty&gt;United Nations.  ''Multilateral treaties deposited with the Secretary-General: [http://untreaty.un.org/ENGLISH/bible/englishinternetbible/partI/chapterXVIII/treaty11.asp Rome Statute of the International Criminal Court'']. Accessed 16 July 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;  However, many of the world's most populous nations, including [[China]], [[India]], the [[United States]], [[Indonesia]], and [[Pakistan]] are not parties to the Court and therefore are not subject to its jurisdiction, except by Security Council referral.

==ICSPCA definition of the crime of apartheid==
Article II of the ICSPCA defines the crime of apartheid as follows:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;div style="text-align: center;&gt;'''International Convention on the Suppression and Punishment of the Crime of Apartheid,'''&lt;br /&gt;
'''Article II'''&lt;ref name="ICSPCA"/&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
For the purpose of the present Convention, the term 'the crime of apartheid', which shall include similar policies and practices of [[racial segregation]] and discrimination as practiced in [[southern Africa]], shall apply to the following [[inhuman]] acts committed for the purpose of establishing and maintaining domination by one [[Race (classification of human beings)|racial group]] of persons over any other racial group of persons and systematically oppressing them:&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;ol style="list-style-type: lower-alpha"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Denial to a member or members of a racial group or groups of the [[right to life]] and [[liberty]] of person
&lt;ol style="list-style-type: lower-roman"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;By murder of members of a racial group or groups;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;By the infliction upon the members of a racial group or groups of serious [[bodily harm|bodily]] or [[Psychological trauma|mental harm]], by the infringement of their freedom or dignity, or by subjecting them to [[torture]] or to cruel, inhuman or degrading treatment or punishment;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;By arbitrary arrest and illegal imprisonment of the members of a racial group or groups;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deliberate imposition on a racial group or groups of living conditions calculated to cause its or their [[ethnic clensing|physical destruction]] in whole or in part;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Any legislative measures and other measures calculated to prevent a racial group or groups from participation in the political, social, economic and cultural life of the country and the deliberate creation of conditions preventing the full development of such a group or groups, in particular by denying to members of a racial group or groups basic human rights and freedoms, including the [[right to work]], the right to form recognised [[trade unions]], the right to education, the [[Illegal emigration|right to leave]] and [[Right of return|to return]] to their country, the [[Nationality law|right to a nationality]], the right to [[freedom of movement]] and residence, the right to [[freedom of expression|freedom of opinion and expression]], and the right to [[Freedom of assembly|freedom of peaceful assembly]] and [[Freedom of association|association]];&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Any measures including legislative measures, designed to divide the population along racial lines by the creation of separate reserves and [[ghetto]]s for the members of a racial group or groups, the prohibition of [[mixed marriage]]s among members of various racial groups, the [[expropriation]] of landed property belonging to a racial group or groups or to members thereof;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Exploitation of the labour of the members of a racial group or groups, in particular by submitting them to [[forced labour]];&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[[Persecution]] of organizations and persons, by depriving them of fundamental rights and freedoms, because they oppose [[apartheid]].&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==ICC definition of the crime of apartheid==
Article 7 of the [[Rome Statute of the International Criminal Court]] defines crimes against humanity as:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
;Article 7
;Crimes against humanity
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For the purpose of this Statute, 'crime against humanity' means any of the following acts when committed as part of a widespread or systematic attack directed against any civilian population, with knowledge of the attack:
&lt;ol style="list-style-type: lower-alpha;"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Murder;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Extermination;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enslavement;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deportation or forcible transfer of population;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Imprisonment or other severe deprivation of physical liberty in violation of fundamental rules of international law;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Torture;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rape, sexual slavery, enforced prostitution, forced pregnancy, enforced sterilization, or any other form of sexual violence of comparable gravity;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Persecution against any identifiable group or collectivity on political, racial, national, ethnic, cultural, religious, gender as defined in paragraph 3, or other grounds that are universally recognized as impermissible under international law, in connection with any act referred to in this paragraph or any crime within the jurisdiction of the Court;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enforced disappearance of persons;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The crime of apartheid;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Other inhumane acts of a similar character intentionally causing great suffering, or serious injury to body or to mental or physical health.&lt;ref name="rome_art7"&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.un.org/law/icc/statute/99_corr/2.htm#art.7
|title=Rome Statute of the International Criminal Court, Part 2, Article 7
|author=United Nations
|year=2002
|accessdaymonth=21 July
|accessyear=2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
Later in Article 7, the crime of apartheid is defined as:
&lt;blockquote&gt;The 'crime of apartheid' means inhumane acts of a character similar to those referred to in paragraph 1, committed in the context of an institutionalised regime of systematic oppression and domination by one racial group over any other racial group or groups and committed with the intention of maintaining that regime.&lt;ref name="rome_art7"/&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==See also==
* [[Racial segregation]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

&lt;br&gt;
{{International Criminal Law}}
{{Racism topics|state=collapsed}}
{{Human rights}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Apartheid, crime of}}
[[Category:Racial segregation]]
[[Category:Human rights instruments]]
[[Category:International criminal law]]
[[Category:International opposition to apartheid in South Africa]]
[[Category:Crimes against humanity]]
[[Category:Apartheid]]

[[sr:Злочин апартхејда]]
[[sh:Zločin aparthejda]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>