<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20111117151053|461118804" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="79942" pageid="79942" ns="0" title="Crime of apartheid"><revisions><rev timestamp="2011-11-17T20:31:47Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{About|the crime of apartheid as defined in international law|the system of racial segregation that formerly existed in South Africa|South Africa under apartheid|other uses|Apartheid (disambiguation)}}
[[Image:ICSPCA-members.PNG|thumb|right|400px|Signatories to the 1973 International Convention on the Suppression and Punishment of the Crime of Apartheid: parties in dark green, signed but not ratified in light green, non-members in grey]]
The '''crime of apartheid''' is defined by the 2002 [[Rome Statute of the International Criminal Court]] as inhumane acts of a character similar to other [[crimes against humanity]] "committed in the context of an institutionalized regime of systematic [[oppression]] and [[Dominance hierarchy|domination]] by one [[Race (classification of human beings)|racial group]] over any other racial group or groups and committed with the intention of maintaining that regime."

On 30 November 1973, the [[United Nations]] [[United Nations General Assembly|General Assembly]] opened for signature and ratification the '''International Convention on the Suppression and Punishment of the Crime of Apartheid'''.&lt;ref name="ICSPCA"&gt;[http://untreaty.un.org/cod/avl/ha/cspca/cspca.html International Convention on the Suppression and Punishment of the Crime of Apartheid], retrieved on 10 October 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; It defined the crime of apartheid as "inhuman acts committed for the purpose of establishing and maintaining domination by one racial group of persons over any other racial group of persons and systematically oppressing them."

==History==
{{International opposition to Apartheid}}
The term ''[[Wiktionary:apartheid|apartheid]]'', from [[Afrikaans]] for "apartness," was the official name of the [[History of South Africa in the apartheid era|South African system of racial segregation]] which existed after 1948. Complaints about the system were brought to the United Nations as early as 12 July 1948 when Dr. Padmanabha Pillai, the representative of [[India]] to the United Nations, circulated a letter to the Secretary-General expressing his concerns over treatment of ethnic Indians within the [[Union of South Africa]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.anc.org.za/show.php?id=4968
|title=Letter from the representative of India to the Secretary-General concerning the treatment of Indians in South Africa
|last=Pillai
|first=Padmanabha
|date=12 July 1948
|accessdate=10 October 2011
}}&lt;/ref&gt; As it became more widely known, South African apartheid was condemned internationally as unjust and [[racist]] and many decided that a formal legal framework was needed in order to apply international pressure on the South African government.

In 1971, the [[Union of Soviet Socialist Republics]] (more commonly known as the Soviet Union or USSR) and [[Guinea]] together submitted early drafts of a convention to deal with the suppression and punishment of apartheid.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
|title=Southern Africa Vol. 1: United Nations-Organization of African Unity Conference Oslo 9–14 April 1973
|editor=Olav Stokke and Carl Widstrand
|year=1973
|publisher=Scandinavian Institute of African Studies}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1973, the [[UN General Assembly|General Assembly of the United Nations]] agreed on the text of the International Convention on the Suppression and Punishment of the Crime of Apartheid (ICSPCA).&lt;ref name="ICSPCA"/&gt; The Convention has 31 signatories and 107 parties.

"As such, apartheid was declared to be a [[crime against humanity]], with a scope that went far beyond South Africa. While the crime of apartheid is most often associated with the racist policies of South Africa after 1948, the term more generally refers to racially based policies in any state."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
|title=The International Law Commission of the United Nations
|first=Jeffrey S.
|last=Morton
|year=2000
|publisher=University of South Carolina Press
|isbn=1570031703
|pages=27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Seventy-six other countries subsequently signed on, but a number of nations have neither signed nor ratified the ICSPCA, including Canada, France, Germany, Israel, Italy, the Netherlands, the United Kingdom, Australia, New Zealand and the United States.&lt;ref&gt;[http://treaties.un.org/Pages/ViewDetails.aspx?src=TREATY&amp;mtdsg_no=IV-7&amp;chapter=4&amp;lang=en List of signatories to the ICSPCA]&lt;/ref&gt;  In explanation of the US vote against the convention, Ambassador [[Clarence Clyde Ferguson Jr.]] said: "[W]e cannot...accept that apartheid can in this manner be made a crime against humanity. Crimes against humanity are so grave in  nature that they must be meticulously elaborated and strictly construed under existing international law..."&lt;ref&gt;Statement by Ambassador Clarence Clyde Ferguson Jr. before General Assembly in explanation of vote on Apartheid Convention, 30 November 1973. Review of the U.N. Commission on Human Rights: Hearings before the Subcommittee on International Organizations and Movements of the House Foreign Affairs Committee (1974) p.58&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1977, Addition Protocol 1 to the Geneva Conventions designated apartheid as a grave breach of the Protocol and a war crime. There are 169 parties to the Protocol.&lt;ref&gt;See Article 85(4) and 85(5) of Additional Protocol 1, dated 8 June 1977 [http://www.icrc.org/ihl.nsf/7c4d08d9b287a42141256739003e636b/f6c8b9fee14a77fdc125641e0052b079]&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[International Criminal Court]] provides for individual criminal responsibility for crimes against humanity,&lt;ref&gt;''Encyclopædia Britannica'', "[http://www.britannica.com/eb/article-233522 Nonstate actors in international law]".  Retrieved on 12 June 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; including the crime of apartheid.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.un.org/law/icc/statute/99_corr/2.htm Article 7] of the [[Rome Statute of the International Criminal Court]] specifically lists the "crime of apartheid" as one of eleven recognized crimes against humanity.&lt;/ref&gt;

The International Criminal Court (ICC) came into being on 1 July 2002, and can only prosecute crimes committed on or after that date.  The Court can generally only exercise jurisdiction in cases where the accused is a national of a state party, the alleged crime took place on the territory of a state party, or a situation is referred to the Court by the [[United Nations Security Council]]. The ICC exercises complimentary jurisdiction. Many of the member states have provided their own national courts with universal jurisdiction over the same offenses and do not recognize any statute of limitations for crimes against humanity.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nottingham.ac.uk/law/hrlc/international-criminal-justice-unit/implementation-database.php Database of National Implementing Legislation]&lt;/ref&gt; As of July 2008, 106 countries are [[States Parties to the Rome Statute of the International Criminal Court|states parties]] (with [[Suriname]] and [[Cook Islands]] set to join in October 2008), and a further 40 countries have signed but not yet ratified the treaty.&lt;ref name=untreaty&gt;United Nations.  ''Multilateral treaties deposited with the Secretary-General: [http://untreaty.un.org/ENGLISH/bible/englishinternetbible/partI/chapterXVIII/treaty11.asp Rome Statute of the International Criminal Court'']. Accessed 16 July 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;  However, many of the world's most populous nations, including [[China]], [[India]], the [[United States]], [[Indonesia]], and [[Pakistan]] are not parties to the Court and therefore are not subject to its jurisdiction, except by Security Council referral.

==ICSPCA definition of the crime of apartheid==
Article II of the ICSPCA defines the crime of apartheid as follows:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;div style="text-align: center;&gt;'''International Convention on the Suppression and Punishment of the Crime of Apartheid,'''&lt;br /&gt;
'''Article II'''&lt;ref name="ICSPCA"/&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
For the purpose of the present Convention, the term 'the crime of apartheid', which shall include similar policies and practices of [[racial segregation]] and discrimination as practiced in [[southern Africa]], shall apply to the following [[inhumane]] acts committed for the purpose of establishing and maintaining domination by one [[Race (classification of human beings)|racial group]] of persons over any other racial group of persons and systematically oppressing them:&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;ol style="list-style-type: lower-alpha"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Denial to a member or members of a racial group or groups of the [[right to life]] and [[liberty]] of person
&lt;ol style="list-style-type: lower-roman"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;By murder of members of a racial group or groups;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;By the infliction upon the members of a racial group or groups of serious [[bodily harm|bodily]] or [[Psychological trauma|mental harm]], by the infringement of their freedom or dignity, or by subjecting them to [[torture]] or to cruel, inhuman or degrading treatment or punishment;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;By arbitrary arrest and illegal imprisonment of the members of a racial group or groups;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deliberate imposition on a racial group or groups of living conditions calculated to cause its or their [[ethnic clensing|physical destruction]] in whole or in part;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Any legislative measures and other measures calculated to prevent a racial group or groups from participation in the political, social, economic and cultural life of the country and the deliberate creation of conditions preventing the full development of such a group or groups, in particular by denying to members of a racial group or groups basic human rights and freedoms, including the [[right to work]], the right to form recognised [[trade unions]], the right to education, the [[Illegal emigration|right to leave]] and [[Right of return|to return]] to their country, the [[Nationality law|right to a nationality]], the right to [[freedom of movement]] and residence, the right to [[freedom of expression|freedom of opinion and expression]], and the right to [[Freedom of assembly|freedom of peaceful assembly]] and [[Freedom of association|association]];&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Any measures including legislative measures, designed to divide the population along racial lines by the creation of separate reserves and [[ghetto]]s for the members of a racial group or groups, the prohibition of [[Interracial marriage|mixed marriage]]s among members of various racial groups, the [[Nationalization|expropriation]] of landed property belonging to a racial group or groups or to members thereof;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Exploitation of the labour of the members of a racial group or groups, in particular by submitting them to [[forced labour]];&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[[Persecution]] of organizations and persons, by depriving them of fundamental rights and freedoms, because they oppose [[apartheid]].&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

===Definition of racial discrimination===
According to the [[United Nations]] [[Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Racial Discrimination]],
&lt;blockquote&gt;''the term "racial discrimination" shall mean any distinction, exclusion, restriction or preference based on [[Race (classification of human beings)|race]], colour, [[Cultural heritage|descent]], or national or [[ethnicity|ethnic]] origin which has the purpose or effect of nullifying or impairing the recognition, enjoyment or exercise, on an equal footing, of [[human rights]] and fundamental freedoms in the political, economic, social, cultural or any other field of public life.''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hri.org/docs/ICERD66.html UN International Convention on the Elimination of All of Racial Discrimination], New York 7 March 1966&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

This definition does not make any difference between discrimination based on  [[ethnicity]] and [[Race (classification of human beings)|race]], in part because the distinction between the two remains debatable among [[Anthropology|anthropologists]].&lt;ref&gt;A. Metraux (1950) "United nations Economic and Security Council Statement by Experts on Problems of Race" in ''American Anthropologist 53(1): 142–145)&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, in British law the phrase ''racial group'' means "any group of people who are defined by reference to their race, colour, nationality (including citizenship) or ethnic or national origin".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cps.gov.uk/publications/prosecution/rrpbcrbook.html |title=Racist and Religious Crime – CPS Prosecution Policy |publisher=The CPS |date= |accessdate=2010-05-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==ICC definition of the crime of apartheid==
Article 7 of the [[Rome Statute of the International Criminal Court]] defines crimes against humanity as:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
;Article 7
;Crimes against humanity
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For the purpose of this Statute, 'crime against humanity' means any of the following acts when committed as part of a widespread or systematic attack directed against any civilian population, with knowledge of the attack:
&lt;ol style="list-style-type: lower-alpha;"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Murder;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Extermination;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enslavement;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deportation or forcible transfer of population;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Imprisonment or other severe deprivation of physical liberty in violation of fundamental rules of international law;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[[Torture]];&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rape, sexual slavery, enforced prostitution, forced pregnancy, enforced sterilization, or any other form of sexual violence of comparable gravity;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Persecution against any identifiable group or collectivity on political, racial, national, ethnic, cultural, religious, gender as defined in paragraph 3, or other grounds that are universally recognized as impermissible under international law, in connection with any act referred to in this paragraph or any crime within the jurisdiction of the Court;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enforced disappearance of persons;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The crime of apartheid;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Other inhumane acts of a similar character intentionally causing great suffering, or serious injury to body or to mental or physical health.&lt;ref name="rome_art7"&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.un.org/law/icc/statute/99_corr/2.htm#art.7
|title=Rome Statute of the International Criminal Court, Part 2, Article 7
|author=United Nations
|year=2002
|accessdate=21 July 2007
|archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070712204433/http://www.un.org/law/icc/statute/99_corr/2.htm#art.7 &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 12 July 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
Later in Article 7, the crime of apartheid is defined as:
&lt;blockquote&gt;The 'crime of apartheid' means inhumane acts of a character similar to those referred to in paragraph 1, committed in the context of an institutionalised regime of systematic oppression and domination by one racial group over any other racial group or groups and committed with the intention of maintaining that regime.&lt;ref name="rome_art7"/&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==Allegations against Israel==
{{POV|date=April 2011}}
{{Merge to|Israel and the apartheid analogy|date=January 2011}}
{{main|Israel and the apartheid analogy}}
Activists for Palestinian rights have accused Israel of committing the crime of apartheid.&lt;ref name="MacAllister2008"&gt;{{Cite document|last=MacAllister|first=Karine|title=Applicability of the Crime of Apartheid to Israel|work=al-Majdal|issue=BDS and the Global Anti-Apartheid Movement|publisher=BADIL|year=2008|url=http://www.badil.org/al-majdal/item/72-applicability-of-the-crime-of-apartheid-to-israel|postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; For example, in 2006, at the UN-sponsored International Conference of Civil Society in Support of the Palestinian People, Phyllis Bennis, co-chair of the International Coordinating Network on Palestine alleged that "Once again, the crime of apartheid [is] being committed by a United Nations Member State [Israel]."&lt;ref name="Stopthewall2006"&gt;{{cite web|title=UN CIVIL SOCIETY CONFERENCE SLAMS 'ISRAELI APARTHEID': Worldwide Activism, Palestinian Grassroots Anti-Apartheid Wall Campaign|date=10 September 2006|accessdate=2007-08-31|url=http://stopthewall.org/worldwideactivism/1300.shtml}}"The reference is to ''The International Conference of Civil Society in Support of the Palestinian People''&lt;/ref&gt;  Zahir Kolliah has written that "In South Africa and in Palestine the indigenous populations live under apartheid regimes 'settler colonies' as described by the International Convention on the Suppression and Punishment of the Crime of Apartheid".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.caiaweb.org/southafricanconnection|title=The South African Connection|last=Kolliah|first=Zahir|date=25 February 2007|publisher=Coalition Against Israeli Apartheid|accessdate=3 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hazeem Jamjoum states in a 2009 article that "In terms of law, describing Israel as an apartheid state does not revolve around levels of difference and similarity with the policies and practices of the South African Apartheid regime" because apartheid is a universal crime under international law.&lt;ref name="Jamjoum"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.caiaweb.org/node/1315|title=Not an Analogy: Israel and the Crime of Apartheid|last=Jamjoum|first=Hazeem|date=5 April 2009|publisher=Coalition Against Israeli Apartheid|accessdate=3 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Such accusations have recently been picked up in documents of the United Nations. In a 2007 report, United Nations Special Rapporteur for Palestine John Dugard stated that "elements of the Israeli occupation constitute forms of colonialism and of apartheid, which are contrary to international law" and suggested that the "legal consequences of a prolonged occupation with features of colonialism and apartheid" be put to the [[International Court of Justice]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Dugard|first=John|title=Report of the Special Rapporteur on the situation of human rights in the Palestinian territories occupied since 1967, John Dugard|url=http://daccess-dds-ny.un.org/doc/UNDOC/GEN/G07/105/44/PDF/G0710544.pdf?OpenElement|page=3|quote=The international community has identified three regimes as inimical to human rights – colonialism, apartheid and foreign occupation. Israel is clearly in military occupation of the OPT. At the same time elements of the occupation constitute forms of colonialism and of apartheid, which are contrary to international law. What are the legal consequences of a regime of prolonged occupation with features of colonialism and apartheid for the occupied people, the occupying Power and third States? It is suggested that this question might appropriately be put to the International Court of Justice for a further advisory opinion.|postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; South Africa's statutory research agency the [[Human Sciences Research Council (South Africa)|Human Sciences Research Council]] (HSRC) stated in a 2009 report that "the State of Israel exercises control in the [Occupied Palestinian Territories] with the purpose of maintaining a system of domination by Jews over Palestinians and that this system constitutes a breach of the prohibition of apartheid."&lt;ref name="HSRC2009"&gt;{{Cite document|author=Middle East Project of the Democracy and Governance Programme, Human Sciences Research Council of South Africa|date=May 2009|title=Occupation, Colonialism, Apartheid? A re-assessment of Israel’s practices in the occupied Palestinian territories under international law|place=Cape Town, South Africa|publisher=Human Sciences Research Council|url=http://www.hsrc.ac.za/Document-3227.phtml|accessdate=2010-04-24|pages=17–22|quote=... practices in South Africa are not the test or benchmark for a finding of apartheid elsewhere, as the principal instrument which provides this test lies in the terms of the Apartheid Convention itself.|postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; Based on these findings, [[Richard Falk]], the successor of John Dugard as UN Special Rapporteur for Palestine has detailed some of the indicators of apartheid in the occupied territories &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.middleeastmonitor.org.uk/downloads/other_reports/report-of-the-special-rapporteur-on-the-situation-of-human-rights-in-the-palestinian-territories-occupied-since-1967.pdf Richard Falk:Report of the Special Rapporteur on the situation of human rights in the Palestinian territories occupied since 1967, Report to the UN General Assembly, 30.August 2010, paragraph. 5] accessdate= 19.12.2010&lt;/ref&gt;:
* preferential citizenship, visitation and residence laws and practices that prevent Palestinians who reside in the West Bank or Gaza from reclaiming their property or from acquiring Israeli citizenship, as contrasted to a Jewish right of return that entitles Jews anywhere in the world with no prior tie to Israel to visit, reside and become Israeli citizens;
* differential laws in the West Bank and East Jerusalem favouring Jewish settlers who are subject to Israeli civilian law and constitutional protection, as opposed to Palestinian residents, who are governed by military administration;
* dual and discriminatory arrangements for movement in the West Bank and to and from Jerusalem; discriminatory policies on land ownership, tenure and use; extensive burdening of Palestinian movement, including checkpoints applying differential limitations on Palestinians and on Israeli settlers, and onerous permit and identification requirements imposed only on Palestinians;
* punitive house demolitions, expulsions and restrictions on entry and exit from all three parts of the Occupied Palestinian Territories.

The Special Rapporteur concludes that this "general structure of apartheid that exists in the Occupied Palestinian Territories ... makes the allegation increasingly credible despite the differences between the specific characteristics of South African apartheid and that of the Occupied Palestinian Territories regime".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.middleeastmonitor.org.uk/downloads/other_reports/report-of-the-special-rapporteur-on-the-situation-of-human-rights-in-the-palestinian-territories-occupied-since-1967.pdf Richard Falk Report to the UN General Assembly, 30.August 2010, paragraph. 5] accessdate= 19.12.2010, paragraph 5&lt;/ref&gt;

Judge [[Richard Goldstone]], writing in [[The New York Times]] in October 2011, said that "in Israel, there is no apartheid. Nothing there comes close to the definition of apartheid under the 1998 Rome Statute."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2011/11/01/opinion/israel-and-the-apartheid-slander.html?_r=1&amp;ref=opinion Israel and the Apartheid Slander]&lt;/ref&gt;.

==See also==
* [[Racial segregation]]
* [[Israel and the apartheid analogy]]
* [[Human rights in Myanmar]]
* [[Human rights in North Korea]]
* [[Human rights in Saudi Arabia]]
* [[Human rights in South Africa]]
* [[Human rights in Sudan]] &amp;ndash; events here led to the secession of [[South Sudan]]
* [[Human rights in Zimbabwe]]
* [[Nazi Germany]]
* [[White Australia Policy]]

== External links ==
{{wiktionary|apartheid}}
* [http://www.hsrc.ac.za/Document-3227.phtml Human Sciences Research Council: Occupation, Colonialism, Apartheid? A re-assessment of Israel’s practices in the occupied Palestinian territories under international law. Cape Town 2009]
* [http://www.middleeastmonitor.org.uk/downloads/other_reports/report-of-the-special-rapporteur-on-the-situation-of-human-rights-in-the-palestinian-territories-occupied-since-1967.pdf Richard Falk:Report of the Special Rapporteur on the situation of human rights in the Palestinian territories occupied since 1967, Report to the UN General Assembly, 30.August 2010, sec. 5]
* [http://www.hrw.org/node/95061 Human Rights Watch Report: Separate and Unequal. Israel’s Discriminatory Treatment of Palestinians in the Occupied Palestinian Territories, December 19 2010]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

&lt;br&gt;
{{International Criminal Law}}
{{Racism topics|state=collapsed}}
{{International human rights legal instruments}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Apartheid, Crime Of}}
[[Category:Racial segregation]]
[[Category:Human rights instruments]]
[[Category:International criminal law]]
[[Category:International opposition to apartheid in South Africa]]
[[Category:Crimes against humanity]]
[[Category:Apartheid]]

[[de:Apartheid (Recht)]]
[[es:Crimen de apartheid]]
[[fr:Crime d'apartheid]]
[[sr:Злочин апартхејда]]
[[sh:Zločin aparthejda]]
[[sv:International Convention on the Suppression and Punishment of the Crime of Apartheid (ICSPCA)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>