<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20021019050118|370552" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="68493" pageid="68493" ns="0" title="Roe v. Wade"><revisions><rev timestamp="2002-10-20T03:15:58Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">&lt;i&gt;'''Roe v. Wade'''&lt;/i&gt; was the caption of the lawsuit in which a 1973 [[U.S. Supreme Court]] ruling recognized [[abortion]] as a constitutional right, over-turning individual states' laws against abortion.

The case originated in [[Texas]] in March 1970: A pregnant woman, the pseudonymous Jane Roe, headed a [[class action]] against the state of Texas's anti-abortion laws, claiming that the laws were unconstitutionally vague and abridged her rights under the First, Fourth, Fifth, Ninth, and Fourteenth Amendments to the [[United States Constitution]]. It was argued in the Supreme Court on December 13, 1971, and reargued on October 11, 1972, with the court issuing its opinion on [[January 22]], [[1973]], with a majority of four, and two concurring and two dissenting.

The opinion of the court was that the right to an abotion fell under the [[right to privacy]] derived from the [[Fifth Amendment|Fifth]] Amendment and the [[Due Process Clause]] of the [[Fourteenth Amendment]] (the latter extending the protections in the Bill of Rights to state as well as federal action). Justice [[Harry Blackmun]]'s majority decision holds that "the right of personal privacy includes the abortion decision, but that this right is not unqualified". The right to an abortion is unlimited within the first trimester of pregnancy; under ''Roe'', states can pass laws regulating second- and third-trimester abortions.

In an interesting turn of events, "Jane Roe", whose real name is [[Norma McCorvey]], later became a member of the [[pro-life]] movement and is now fighting to make abortion illegal. In her own words, McCorvey became the pawn of two young and ambitious lawyers who were looking for a plaintiff with whom they could use to challenge the [[Texas]] state law prohibiting abortion. Every year on the anniversary of the decision, protestors still demonstrate outside the Supreme Court Building in [[Washington, D.C.]]; some justices seem to make a practice of not coming to work that day.

See also ''[[Griswold v. Connecticut]]'', ''[[Doe v. Bolton]]'', ''[[Webster v. Reproductive Health Services]]'', and ''[[Planned Parenthood v. Casey]]''.

External link: [http://www.roenomore.org/ Norman McCorvey's website]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>