<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20041108145256|7221543" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="68493" pageid="68493" ns="0" title="Roe v. Wade"><revisions><rev timestamp="2004-11-08T15:31:55Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[Image:sarah_weddington.jpg|thumb|right|Roe's attorney, Sarah Weddington]]
'''''Roe v. Wade''''', 410 U.S. 113 ([[1973]]) was the [[landmark case|landmark]] [[Supreme Court of the United States|United States Supreme Court]] decision that recognized [[abortion]] as a constitutional right, overturning individual states' laws against abortion. The [[Supreme Court of Canada|Canadian Supreme Court]] case entitled [[Morgentaler et. al. v. Her Majesty The Queen]] would decide the same issue there some 15 years later.

==History of the case==

The case originated in [[Texas]] in March [[1970]].  It started when a pregnant woman named [[Norma McCorvey]], using the pseudonym "Jane Roe," headed a [[class action]] lawsuit against the state of Texas's anti-abortion laws, claiming that the laws were unconstitutionally vague and abridged her rights under the [[First Amendment to the United States Constitution|First]], [[Fourth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Fourth]], [[Fifth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Fifth]], [[Ninth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Ninth]], and [[Fourteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Fourteenth Amendment]]s to the [[United States Constitution]]. [[Dallas]] district attorney [[Henry Wade]] was the defendant in the case. Roe's attorney, [[Sarah Weddington]], was a young University of Texas law student who played the leading role in pursuing the case. She argued the case twice in front of the Supreme Court, once after the case was put over for reargument.
The trial court denied "Jane Roe" relief but on appeal the lower court's decision was overturned and finally it was argued in the Supreme Court on [[December 13]], [[1971]], and then reargued on [[October 11]], [[1972]]. The court issued its opinion, backed by a 7-2 majority on [[January 22]], 1973 with Justices [[Byron White|White]] and [[William Rehnquist|Rehnquist]] dissenting.  On the same day, the same 7-2 majority issued a similar ruling in the lesser-known case of ''[[Doe v. Bolton]]'', 410 U.S. 179 (1973), involving [[Georgia (U.S. state)|Georgia]]'s abortion laws.

==The Bench==
The makeup of the Supreme Court and their opinions were:

===Opinion===
&lt;u&gt;Written by&lt;/u&gt;: [[Associate Justice of the Supreme Court of the United States|Justice]] [[Harry Blackmun]]
:*''Joined by'': [[Chief Justice of the United States|Chief Justice]] [[Warren E. Burger]] and Justices [[William O. Douglas]], [[William J. Brennan]], [[Potter Stewart]], [[Thurgood Marshall]] and [[Lewis Franklin Powell, Jr.]]

===Concurring Opinions===
#&lt;u&gt;Written by&lt;/u&gt;: Chief Justice Burger
#&lt;u&gt;Written by&lt;/u&gt;: Justice Douglas
#&lt;u&gt;Written by&lt;/u&gt;: Justice Stewart

===Dissenting===
#&lt;u&gt;Written by&lt;/u&gt;: Justice [[William H. Rehnquist]]
#&lt;u&gt;Written by&lt;/u&gt;: Justice [[Byron White]]
:*''Joined by'': Justice Rehnquist

==Supreme Court decision==

The majority opinion notes that criminalization of abortion did not occur until the nineteenth century and that restrictive laws emerged as a result of three concerns: (1) women who can receive an abortion are likely to be more sexually promiscuous, (2) abortion mortality was high until the turn of the twentieth century, and (3) the State has an interest in protecting prenatal life.   In the Court's opinion, the first two justifications for outlawing abortion are obsolete, and a woman's right to privacy supersedes the third.  According to Justice Blackmun, the [[right to privacy]] is implicit in the [[Due Process Clause]] of the [[Fourteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Fourteenth Amendment]]. Justice [[Harry Blackmun]]'s majority decision held that "the right of personal privacy includes the abortion decision, but that this right is not unqualified." Thus, the decision established a system of trimesters, whereby the State cannot restrict a woman's right to an abortion during the first trimester, the State can regulate the abortion procedure during the second trimester "in ways that are reasonably related to maternal health," and in the third trimester, demarcating the viability of the [[fetus]], a State can choose to restrict or even to [[proscribe]] abortion as it sees fit.

In dissent, Justice Byron White, joined by Justice [[William H. Rehnquist]], criticized the Court's decision as having no foundation in the Constitution:

"I find nothing in the language or history of the Constitution to support the Court's judgment. The Court simply fashions and announces a new constitutional right for pregnant mothers and, with scarcely any reason or authority for its action, invests that right with sufficient substance to override most existing state abortion statutes. The upshot is that the people and the legislatures of the 50 States are constitutionally disentitled to weigh the relative importance of the continued existence and development of the fetus, on the one hand, against a spectrum of possible impacts on the mother, on the other hand. As an exercise of raw judicial power, the Court perhaps has authority to do what it does today; but in my view its judgment is an improvident and extravagant exercise of the power of judicial review that the Constitution extends to this Court."

== Aftermath==

The Roe decision sparked massive nationwide protest, including a massive letter-writing campaign to the Supreme Court. Many Americans, including many Catholics and evangelical Protestants, believe that abortion is morally equivalent to infanticide, or rather that abortion is in itself infanticide.  Widespread protest over the decision resulted in the creation of the [[Pro-Life]] Movement, which organized large protest rallies outside the Supreme Court.  Pro-Life protesters frequently picket abortion clinics, distribute literature and other forms of persuasion to women considering abortion, and have promoted adoption efforts to steer women away from abortion.  More extreme variants of the movement have also developed.  Abortion doctors have been the targets of harassment and even murder by pro-life zealots who claim that by taking the life of an abortion doctor they are actually saving many fetus' lives.  Many abortion opponents have claimed that there exists a link between abortion and breast cancer, and Texas has enacted a law requiring literature advancing this theory be distributed to women considering abortion; more credibly, abortion has been linked to persistent guilt feelings and other [[psychological]] problems, and to a higher risk of future infertility.  Every year on the anniversary of the decision, protesters continue to demonstrate outside the Supreme Court Building in [[Washington, D.C.]] 

The Pro-Life Movement successfully convinced several states to enact many laws limiting the right of abortion, including laws requiring parental consent for minors to obtain abortions, parental notification laws, spousal consent laws, spousal notification laws, laws requiring abortions to be performed in hospitals, not clinics, laws barring state funding for abortions, laws banning the [[partial-birth abortion]] procedure, where the baby is partially delivered before being destroyed, laws requiring waiting periods before abortion, laws mandating that women read certain types of literature before choosing an abortion, and many more.  The United States Congress in the 1970s passed the Hyde Amendment, barring federal funding for abortion.  Abortions are currently prohibited in overseas military hospitals, among other places, and the U.S. is barred from aiding international family planning organizations that might advise abortions.  The Supreme Court struck down several state restrictions on abortions in a long series of cases stretching from the mid-1970s to the late 1980s, but consistently upheld restrictions on funding, including the Hyde Amendment, in the case of Harris v. McRae (1980). 

Many academics also criticized the decision.  In his 1973 article in the Yale Law Review, "The Wages of Crying Wolf," Professor [[John Hart Ely]] criticized Roe as a decision which "is not constitutional law and gives almost no sense of an obligation to try to be."

Opposition to Roe on the bench grew as Ronald Reagan, who supported legislative restrictions on abortion, controversially made abortion his "litmus test" for judicial appointments.  In addition to White and Rehnquist, Reagan appointee Sandra Day O'Connor began dissenting from the Court's abortion cases, arguing that the "trimester system" devised by the Court was arbitrary.  Shortly before his retirement from the bench, Chief Justice [[Warren Burger]] suggested that Roe be "reexamined," and Burger's replacement, Justice [[Antonin Scalia]], was a vigorous opponent of Roe.  Concerns over Roe's overturning played a major role in the defeat of [[Robert Bork]]'s nomination to the Court, and the man eventually appointed to replace Roe supporter [[Lewis Franklin Powell]], [[Anthony M. Kennedy]], was seen as a potential anti-Roe vote.  In a 5-4 decision in 1989's ''Webster vs. Reproductive Health Services'', Chief Justice Rehnquist, writing for the Court, declined to explicitly overrule Roe, but did uphold several abortion restrictions and substantially modified Roe's trimester framework.  In a concurring opinion, Justice O'Connor pointedly refused to reconsider Roe.  Justice Antonin Scalia, in a concurring opinion, refused to join the plurality's opinion because it refused to overrule ''Roe'', which he believed should be overruled, and criticized O'Connor's ambiguous position on the matter.  Justice [[Harry Blackmun]], by now a passionate defender of his Roe opinion, dissented angrily, arguing that the plurality opinion signaled doom for the abortion right.

With the retirement of ''Roe'' supporters [[William J. Brennan]] and [[Thurgood Marshall]], and their replacement by "conservative" judges appointed by President [[George Herbert Walker Bush]], many predicted the demise of Roe.  The Supreme Court, however, in ''[[Planned Parenthood v. Casey]]'', 505 U.S. 833 ([[1992]]), reexamined ''Roe'' and explicitly upheld its validity by a 5-4 vote.  A plurality of Reagan-Bush appointees, O'Connor, Kennedy, and [[David H. Souter]], reaffirmed that the Constitution protects a right of abortion.  Rehnquist and Scalia filed biting dissenting opinions.  During the 1990s, attempts were made at the state level to ban "partial-birth" abortions, which were struck down, again by a 5-4 vote, in ''[[Stenberg v. Carhart]]'', 530 U.S. 914 ([[2000]]), with Justice Kennedy, co-author of the ''Casey'' decision, among the dissenters.  Subsequently, Congress passed a law banning third trimester abortions, which is currently tied up in litigation.  [[George W. Bush]] has proposed an amendment to the constitution that would ban third trimester abortions.

==Roe switches sides==

In an interesting turn of events, "Jane Roe," whose real name is [[Norma McCorvey]], became a member of the [[pro-life]] movement following her conversion to Christianity, and now fights to make abortion illegal. McCorvey claims that she was the "pawn" of young, ambitious lawyers who were looking for a [[plaintiff]] so that they could challenge the [[Texas]] state law prohibiting abortion. Using her prerogative as a party to the original litigation, she sought to reopen the case in a U.S. District Court in Texas and have it overturned. Her new stance is based on claims made since the decision, including evidence of emotional and other harm suffered by many women who have had abortions, increased resources for the care of unwanted children, and additional evidence of the humanity of the fetus.  On [[June 19]], [[2003]], Judge [[David Godbey]] ruled that the motion was not made within a "reasonable time."  McCorvey's lawyer maintains that no time limit exists for such motions, and an appeal seems likely.

==External links==
* [http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/scripts/getcase.pl?court=us&amp;vol=410&amp;invol=113 Text of the decision from Findlaw]
* [http://www.oyez.org/oyez/resource/case/334/argument.mp3 Listen to first of two audio recordings of the Roe V. Wade debates at www.oyez.org]

[[Category:U.S. Supreme Court cases]][[Category:U.S. abortion rights case law]][[Category:U.S. history of women's rights]][[Category:Abortion]][[Category:Fourteenth Amendment case law]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>