<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20181106200828|867603957" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="68493" pageid="68493" ns="0" title="Roe v. Wade"><revisions><rev timestamp="2018-11-17T19:56:18Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{About||the 1989 television film|Roe vs. Wade (film)}}
{{pp-move-indef}}
{{pp-semi-indef}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=September 2018}}
{{Infobox SCOTUS case
|Litigants=Roe v. Wade
|ArgueDate=December 13
|ArgueYear=1971
|ReargueDate=October 11
|ReargueYear=1972
|DecideDate=January 22
|DecideYear=1973
|FullName=[[Norma McCorvey|Jane Roe]], et al. v. [[Henry Wade]], District Attorney of Dallas County
|ParallelCitations=93 S. Ct. 705; 35 [[L. Ed. 2d]] 147; [https://www.lexis.com/research/slft?cite=3139373320552E532E204C455849532020313539&amp;keyenum=15451&amp;keytnum=0 1973 U.S. LEXIS 159]
|USVol=410
|USPage=113
|Prior=''Judgment for plaintiffs, injunction denied'', 314 [[F. Supp.]] [https://law.justia.com/cases/federal/district-courts/FSupp/314/1217/1472349/ 1217] ([[N.D. Tex.]] 1970); ''probable jurisdiction noted'', {{ussc|402|941|1971|el=no}}; ''set for reargument'', {{ussc|408|919|1972|el=no}}
|Subsequent=''Rehearing denied'', {{ussc|410|959|1973|el=no}}
|Holding=Texas law making it a crime to assist a woman to get an abortion violated her due process rights. [[U.S. District Court for the Northern District of Texas]] affirmed in part, reversed in part.
|OralArgument=https://www.oyez.org/cases/1970-1979/1971/1971_70_18/argument/
|OralReargument=https://www.oyez.org/cases/1970-1979/1971/1971_70_18/reargument/
|SCOTUS=1972–1975
|Majority=Blackmun
|JoinMajority=Burger, Douglas, Brennan, Stewart, Marshall, Powell
|Concurrence=Burger
|Concurrence2=Douglas
|Concurrence3=Stewart
|Dissent=White
|JoinDissent=Rehnquist
|Dissent2=Rehnquist
|LawsApplied=[[Fourteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|U.S. Const. Amend. XIV]]; [[Texas abortion statutes (1961)|Tex. Code Crim. Proc. arts. 1191–1194, 1196]]
}}

'''''Roe v. Wade''''', 410 U.S. 113 (1973),&lt;ref&gt;{{ussc|name=Roe v. Wade|410|113|1973}}.&lt;/ref&gt; is a [[List of landmark court decisions in the United States|landmark decision]] issued in 1973 by the [[Supreme Court of the United States|United States Supreme Court]] on the issue of the constitutionality of laws that [[abortion law|criminalized or restricted]] access to [[abortion]]s.  The Court ruled 7–2 that a right to [[Privacy#Privacy law|privacy]] under the [[Due Process Clause]] of the [[Fourteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|14th Amendment]] extended to a woman's decision to have an abortion, but that this right must be balanced against the state's interests in regulating abortions: protecting women's health and protecting the potentiality of human life.&lt;ref&gt;''See Roe'', 410 U.S. at 162 ("We repeat, however, that the State does have an important and legitimate interest in preserving and protecting the health of the pregnant woman, whether she be a resident of the State or a non-resident who seeks medical consultation and treatment there, and that it has still another important and legitimate interest in protecting the potentiality of human life.").&lt;/ref&gt; Arguing that these state interests became stronger over the course of a pregnancy, the Court resolved this [[balancing test]] by tying state regulation of abortion to the third [[Trimester (pregnancy)#Physiology|trimester of pregnancy]].

Later, in ''[[Planned Parenthood v. Casey]]'' (1992),&lt;ref name="Casey"&gt;{{ussc|name=Planned Parenthood v. Casey|volume=505|page=833|pin=|year=1992}}.&lt;/ref&gt; the Court rejected ''Roe''{{'}}s trimester framework while affirming its central holding that a woman has a right to abortion until [[fetal viability]].&lt;ref&gt;"[https://www.pbs.org/wgbh/pages/frontline/clinic/wars/cases.html Roe v. Wade and Beyond]", [[Frontline (U.S. TV series)|Frontline]], [[Public Broadcasting Service|PBS]] (January 19, 2006): "while reaffirming the central holding of ''Roe v. Wade'', the court rejected 'Roe's rigid trimester framework'...."&lt;/ref&gt; The '' Roe'' decision defined "viable" as "potentially able to live outside the mother's womb, albeit with artificial aid."&lt;ref&gt;Wood, Mary and Hawkins, Lisa. "State Regulation of Late Abortion and the Physician's Duty of Care to the Viable Fetus", 45 Mo. L. Rev. 394 (1980).&lt;/ref&gt;  Justices in ''[[Planned Parenthood v Casey|Casey]]'' acknowledged that viability may occur at 23 or 24 weeks, or sometimes even earlier, in light of medical advances.&lt;ref&gt;''Casey'', 505 U.S. at 860.&lt;/ref&gt;

In disallowing many [[state law|state]] and [[federal law|federal]] restrictions on [[abortion in the United States]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | first = William | last = Mears | first2 = Bob | last2 = Franken | url = http://www.cnn.com/2003/LAW/01/21/roevwade.overview/ | title = 30 years after ruling, ambiguity, anxiety surround abortion debate | publisher = CNN | date = January 22, 2003 | quote = In all, the Roe and Doe rulings impacted laws in 46 states.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Greenhouse|2005|p=72}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Roe v. Wade'' prompted a [[abortion debate|national debate]] that continues today about issues including whether, and to what extent, abortion should be legal, who should decide the legality of abortion, what methods the Supreme Court should use in constitutional [[adjudication]], and what the role should be of [[First Amendment to the United States Constitution#Establishment of religion|religious]] and [[morality|moral]] views in the political sphere. ''Roe v. Wade'' reshaped national politics, dividing much of the United States into [[pro-life]] and [[pro-choice]] camps, while activating [[grassroots]] movements on both sides.

''Roe'' received significant criticism in the legal community,&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite book|title=Limits: The Role of the Law in Bioethical Decision Making|last=Dworkin|first=Roger|publisher=[[Indiana University Press]]|year=1996|isbn=978-0253330758|location=[[United States]]|pages=28-36}}&lt;/ref&gt; with the decision being widely seen as an extreme form of [[judicial activism]].&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt; In a highly cited 1973 article in the ''[[Yale Law Journal]]'',&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{harvnb|Greenhouse|2005|pp=135–136}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[John Hart Ely]] criticized ''Roe'' as a decision that "is not constitutional law and gives almost no sense of an obligation to try to be."&lt;ref&gt;Ely, John Hart. "[http://www.timothypcarney.com/wages-wolf.htm The Wages of Crying Wolf] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070625170521/http://www.timothypcarney.com/wages-wolf.htm|date=2007-06-25}}", 82 ''Yale Law Journal'' 920 (1973). Retrieved January 23, 2007. Professor Ely "supported the availability of abortion as a matter of policy." See Liptak, Adam. [https://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E2DF1131F934A15753C1A9659C8B63 "John Hart Ely, a Constitutional Scholar, Is Dead at 64"], ''New York Times'' (2003-10-27). Ely is generally regarded as having been a "liberal constitutional scholar." Perry, Michael (1999). {{Google books|ka8ajkxQWxkC|We the People: The Fourteenth Amendment and the Supreme Court}}{{cite web|url=http://www.timothypcarney.com/wages-wolf.htm|title=Archived copy|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070625170521/http://www.timothypcarney.com/wages-wolf.htm|archivedate=June 25, 2007|deadurl=bot: unknown|accessdate=October 5, 2009|df=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ely added: "What is frightening about ''Roe'' is that this super-protected right is not inferable from the language of the Constitution, the framers’ thinking respecting the specific problem in issue, any general value derivable from the provisions they included, or the nation's governmental structure." Professor [[Laurence Tribe]] had similar thoughts: "One of the most curious things about ''Roe'' is that, behind its own verbal smokescreen, the substantive judgment on which it rests is nowhere to be found."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Tribe|first=Laurence|year=1973|title=The Supreme Court, 1972 Term – Foreword: Toward a Model of Roles in the Due Process of Life and Law|journal=[[Harvard Law Review]]|volume=87|issue=1|pages=1 [p. 7]|doi=10.2307/1339866|jstor=1339866}} Quoted in {{cite journal|last=Morgan|first=Richard Gregory|year=1979|title=''Roe v. Wade'' and the Lesson of the Pre-''Roe'' Case Law|journal=[[Michigan Law Review]]|volume=77|issue=7|pages=1724–1748|doi=10.2307/1288040|jstor=1288040}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Background==

===History of abortion laws in the United States===
According to the Court, "the restrictive criminal abortion laws in effect in a majority of States today are of relatively recent vintage." Providing a historical analysis on abortion, Justice [[Harry Blackmun]] noted that abortion was "resorted to without scruple" in Greek and Roman times.&lt;ref&gt;''Roe'', 410 U.S. at 130.&lt;/ref&gt; Blackmun also addressed the permissive and restrictive abortion attitudes and laws throughout history, noting the disagreements among leaders (of all different professions) in those eras and the formative laws and cases.&lt;ref&gt;''Roe'', 410 U.S. at 131–136, 143.&lt;/ref&gt; In the United States, in 1821, Connecticut passed the first state statute criminalizing abortion. Every state had abortion legislation by 1900.&lt;ref&gt;Cole, George; Frankowski, Stanislaw. ''[https://books.google.com/?id=-ujuOMTNAQAC&amp;pg=PA20 Abortion and protection of the human fetus : legal problems in a cross-cultural perspective]'', p. 20 (1987): "By 1900 every state in the Union had an anti-abortion prohibition." Via Google Books. Retrieved (April 8, 2008).&lt;/ref&gt; [[Abortion in the United States|In the United States, abortion]] was sometimes considered a [[common law]] crime,&lt;ref&gt;[[James Wilson|Wilson, James]], "[http://teachingamericanhistory.org/library/index.asp?document=831 Of the Natural Rights of Individuals]" (1790–1792): "In the contemplation of law, life begins when the infant is first able to stir in the womb." Also see [[William Blackstone|Blackstone, William]]. [http://press-pubs.uchicago.edu/founders/documents/amendIXs1.html Commentaries] (1765): "Life ... begins in contemplation of law as soon as an infant is able to stir in the mother's womb."&lt;/ref&gt; though Justice Blackmun would conclude that the criminalization of abortion did not have "roots in the English common-law tradition."&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Greenhouse|2005|p=92}}&lt;/ref&gt; Rather than arresting the women having the abortions, legal officials were more likely to interrogate these women to obtain evidence against the abortion provider in order to close down that provider's business.&lt;ref name="Paltrow 17–21"&gt;{{Cite journal |title=Roe v Wade and the New Jane Crow: Reproductive Rights in the Age of Mass Incarceration |journal=American Journal of Public Health |volume=103 |issue=1 |last=Paltrow |first=Lynn M. |date=January 2013  |pages=17–21 |doi=10.2105/AJPH.2012.301104 |pmc=3518325 |pmid=23153159 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=When Abortion Was a Crime: Women, Medicine, and Law in the United States 1867–1973|last=Reagan|first=LJ|publisher=University of California Press|year=1997|isbn=|location=|pages=|quote=|via=}}{{Page needed|date=December 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== History of the case ===
In June 1969, 21-year-old [[Norma McCorvey]] discovered she was pregnant with her third child. She returned to [[Dallas]], Texas, where friends advised her to assert falsely that she had been raped in order to obtain a legal abortion (with the understanding that Texas law allowed abortion in cases of rape and incest). However, this scheme failed because there was no police report documenting the alleged rape. In any case, the Texas statute allowed abortion only ”for the purpose of saving the life of the mother”. She attempted to obtain an [[Illegal abortion]], but found that the unauthorized facility had been closed down by the police. Eventually, she was referred to attorneys [[Linda Coffee]] and [[Sarah Weddington]].&lt;ref&gt;McCorvey, Norma and Meisler, Andy. ''I Am Roe: My Life, Roe V. Wade, and Freedom of Choice'' (Harper Collins 1994).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Contemporary Cases in Women's Rights|last = Friedman Goldstein|first = Leslie|publisher = The University of Wisconsin|year = 1994|isbn = |location = Madison|page = 15}}&lt;/ref&gt; (McCorvey would end up giving birth before the case was decided, and the child was put up for adoption.)&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |last1=Rourke |first1=Mary |last2=Reyes |first2=Emily Alpert |date=February 18, 2017 |title=Norma McCorvey, once-anonymous plaintiff in 'Roe vs. Wade,' dies at 69 |url=http://www.latimes.com/local/obituaries/la-me-norma-mccorvey-snap-story.html |work=Los Angeles Times |access-date=February 19, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1970, Coffee and Weddington filed suit in the [[United States District Court for the Northern District of Texas]] on behalf of McCorvey (under the alias [[John Doe|Jane Roe]]). The defendant in the case was [[Dallas County District Attorney]] [[Henry Wade]], who represented the State of Texas. McCorvey was no longer claiming her pregnancy was a result of rape, and later acknowledged that she had lied about having been raped.&lt;ref&gt;[[Richard Ostling]]. [http://www.texnews.com/1998/texas/roe1019.html "A second religious conversion for 'Jane Roe' of Roe vs. Wade"] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080220145810/http://www.texnews.com/1998/texas/roe1019.html |date=February 20, 2008 }}, Associated Press (October 19, 1998): "She confessed that her tale of rape a decade before had been a lie; she was simply an unwed mother who later gave the child up for adoption."&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="testimony"&gt;McCorvey, Norma. [https://books.google.com/?id=4b0TAAAAIAAJ Testimony to the Senate Subcommittee on the Constitution, Federalism and Property Rights] (January 21, 1998), [http://www.parliament.wa.gov.au/hansard/hans35.nsf/(ATT)/A4C48AF367A417A84825661A007776E1/$file/C0520006.PDF also quoted in the parliament of Western Australia (PDF)] (1998-05-20): "The affidavit submitted to the Supreme Court didn’t happen the way I said it did, pure and simple." Retrieved January 27, 2007&lt;/ref&gt; "Rape" is not mentioned in the judicial opinions in the case.&lt;ref name="dist"&gt;{{cite court |litigants=Roe v. Wade |vol=314 |reporter=F. Supp. |opinion=1217 |pinpoint=1221 |court=N.D. Tex. |date=1970 |url=https://law.justia.com/cases/federal/district-courts/FSupp/314/1217/1472349/ |accessdate=May 16, 2018 |quote=On the merits, plaintiffs argue as their principal contention that the Texas Abortion Laws must be declared unconstitutional because they deprive single women and married couple of their rights secured by the Ninth Amendment to choose whether to have children. We agree.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On June 17, 1970, a three-judge panel of the District Court, consisting of Northern District of Texas Judges [[Sarah T. Hughes]], [[William McLaughlin Taylor Jr.]] and [[United States Court of Appeals for the Fifth Circuit|Fifth Circuit Court of Appeals]] Judge [[Irving Loeb Goldberg]], unanimously&lt;ref name="dist"/&gt; declared the Texas law unconstitutional, finding that it violated the right to privacy found in the [[Ninth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Ninth Amendment]]. In addition, the court relied on Justice [[Arthur Goldberg]]'s 1965 concurrence in ''[[Griswold v. Connecticut]]''. The court, however, declined to grant an [[injunction]] against enforcement of the law.&lt;ref&gt;O'Connor, Karen. Testimony before U.S. Senate Judiciary Committee, "[https://web.archive.org/web/20080731061027/http://judiciary.senate.gov/testimony.cfm?id=1553&amp;wit_id=4399 The Consequences of Roe v. Wade and Doe v. Bolton]", via archive.org (June 23, 2005). Retrieved January 30, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1971, Shirley Wheeler was charged with manslaughter after Florida hospital staff reported her illegal abortion to the police. She received a sentence of two years' probation and, under her probation, had to move back into her parents' house in North Carolina.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Paltrow|first=Lynn|year=2013|title=Roe V. Wade and the New Jane Crow: Reproductive Rights in the Age of Mass Incarceration|pmc=3518325|journal=American Journal of Public Health|volume=103|issue=1|pages=17–21|via=|doi=10.2105/AJPH.2012.301104|pmid=23153159|url=https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3518325/pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Boston Women's Abortion Coalition held a rally for Wheeler in Boston to raise money and awareness of her charges as well as had staff members from the Women's National Abortion Action Coalition (WONAAC) speak at the rally.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |title=Rally Today Supports Wheeler |url=http://www.thecrimson.com/article/1971/10/21/rally-today-supports-wheeler-pthe-boston/ |website=The Harvard Crimson |location=Cambridge, Mass. |access-date=November 29, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Wheeler was possibly the first woman to be held criminally responsible for submitting to an abortion.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/1971/12/04/archives/shes-fighting-conviction-for-aborting-her-child.html|title=She's Fighting Conviction For Aborting Her Child|last=Nordheimer|first=Jon|date=December 4, 1971|newspaper=The New York Times|language=en-US|accessdate=December 15, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Her conviction was overturned by the Florida Supreme Court.&lt;ref name="Paltrow 17–21"/&gt;

== Before the Supreme Court ==
''Roe v. Wade'' reached the Supreme Court on appeal in 1970. The justices delayed taking action on ''Roe'' and a closely related case, ''[[Doe v. Bolton]]'', until they had decided ''[[Younger v. Harris]]'' (because they felt the appeals raised difficult questions on judicial jurisdiction) and ''[[United States v. Vuitch]]'' (in which they considered the constitutionality of a [[Washington D.C.|District of Columbia]] statute that criminalized abortion except where the mother's life or health was endangered). In ''Vuitch'', the Court narrowly upheld the statute, though in doing so, it treated abortion as a medical procedure and stated that physicians must be given room to determine what constitutes a danger to (physical or mental) health. The day after they announced their decision in ''Vuitch'', they voted to hear both ''Roe'' and ''Doe''.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Greenhouse|2005|pp=77–79}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Arguments were scheduled by the full Court for December 13, 1971. Before the Court could hear the oral arguments, Justices [[Hugo Black]] and [[John Marshall Harlan II]] retired. [[Chief Justice of the United States|Chief Justice]] [[Warren Burger]] asked Justice [[Potter Stewart]] and Justice Blackmun to determine whether ''Roe'' and ''Doe'', among others, should be heard as scheduled. According to Blackmun, Stewart felt that the cases were a straightforward application of ''Younger v. Harris'', and they recommended that the Court move forward as scheduled.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Greenhouse|2005|p=80}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In his opening argument in defense of the abortion restrictions, attorney Jay Floyd made what was later described as the "worst joke in legal history."&lt;ref name="salon"&gt;Sant, Geoffrey. "[http://www.salon.com/2013/07/26/8_horrible_courtroom_jokes_and_their_ensuing_legal_calamity 8 horrible courtroom jokes and their ensuing legal calamities]", ''Salon.com'' (July 27, 2013): "The title of Worst Joke in Legal History belongs to one of history's highest-profile cases. Defending Texas's abortion restrictions before the Supreme Court, attorney Mr. Jay Floyd decided to open oral argument with a sexist joke. Arguing against two female attorneys, Floyd begins: 'It's an old joke, but when a man argues against two beautiful ladies like this, they are going to have the last word.'" Retrieved 2010-08-10.&lt;/ref&gt; Appearing against two female lawyers, Floyd began, "Mr. Chief Justice and may it please the Court. It's an old joke, but when a man argues against two beautiful ladies like this, they are going to have the last word." His remark was met with cold silence; one observer thought that Chief Justice Burger "was going to come right off the bench at him. He glared him down."&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Malphurs|2010|p=48}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Garrow|1994|p=526}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After a first round of arguments, all seven justices tentatively agreed that the Texas law should be struck down, but on varying grounds.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Greenhouse|2005|p=81}}&lt;/ref&gt; Burger assigned the role of writing the Court's opinion in ''Roe'' (as well as ''Doe'') to Blackmun, who began drafting a preliminary opinion that emphasized what he saw as the Texas law's vagueness.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Schwartz|1988|p=103}}&lt;/ref&gt; (At this point, Black and Harlan had been replaced by Justices [[William Rehnquist]] and [[Lewis F. Powell Jr.]], but they arrived too late to hear the first round of arguments.) But Blackmun felt that his opinion did not adequately reflect his liberal colleagues' views.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Greenhouse|2005|pp=81–88}}&lt;/ref&gt; In May 1972, he proposed that the case be reargued. Justice [[William O. Douglas]] threatened to write a dissent from the reargument order (he and the other liberal justices were suspicious that Rehnquist and Powell would vote to uphold the statute), but was coaxed out of the action by his colleagues, and his dissent was merely mentioned in the reargument order without further statement or opinion.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Garrow|1994|p=556}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Greenhouse|2005|p=89}}&lt;/ref&gt; The case was reargued on October 11, 1972. Weddington continued to represent ''Roe'', and Texas Assistant Attorney General Robert C. Flowers replaced Jay Floyd for Texas.{{Citation needed|date=January 2017}}&lt;!--Probably in {{harvnb|Garrow|1994|pp=569–570}} but if not why not say "...Texas Assistant Attorney General [[Robert C. Flowers]] represented Wade."--&gt;

Blackmun continued to work on his opinions in both cases over the summer recess, even though there was no guarantee that he would be assigned to write them again. Over the recess, he spent a week researching the history of abortion at the [[Mayo Clinic]] in Minnesota, where he had worked in the 1950s. After the Court heard the second round of arguments, Powell said he would agree with Blackmun's conclusion but pushed for ''Roe'' to be the lead of the two abortion cases being considered. Powell also suggested that the Court strike down the Texas law on privacy grounds. Justice [[Byron White]] was unwilling to sign on to Blackmun's opinion, and Rehnquist had already decided to dissent.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Greenhouse|2005|pp=93–95}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Supreme Court decision ==
[[File:US Supreme Court Justice Harry Blackmun, detail.jpg|thumb|right|[[Harry Blackmun]] wrote the Court's opinion.]]
The Court issued its decision on January 22, 1973, with a 7-to-2 majority vote in favor of Roe. Justices Burger, Douglas, and Stewart filed concurring opinions, and Justice White filed a dissenting opinion in which Justice Rehnquist joined. Burger's, Douglas's, and White's opinions were issued along with the Court's opinion in ''[[Doe v. Bolton]]'' (announced on the same day as ''Roe v. Wade''). The Court deemed abortion a [[fundamental right]] under the [[United States Constitution]], thereby subjecting all laws attempting to restrict it to the standard of [[strict scrutiny]].&lt;ref&gt;Although abortion is still considered a fundamental right under current jurisprudence, [[#Role in subsequent decisions and politics|subsequent cases]], notably ''[[Planned Parenthood v. Casey]]'', ''[[Stenberg v. Carhart]]'', and ''[[Gonzales v. Carhart]]'' have affected the legal standard.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Right to privacy ===
The Court declined to adopt the district court's [[Ninth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Ninth Amendment]] rationale, and instead asserted that the "right of privacy, whether it be founded in the [[Fourteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Fourteenth Amendment]]'s concept of personal liberty and restrictions upon state action, as we feel it is, or, as the district court determined, in the Ninth Amendment's reservation of rights to the people, is broad enough to encompass a woman's decision whether or not to terminate her pregnancy."&lt;ref&gt;Chase, H. et al. (1975). ''Supplement to Edward S. Corwin's The constitution and what it means today: Supreme Court decisions of 1973, 1974, and 1975'', p. 36. Princeton University Press: "The abortion cases afforded the Supreme Court another opportunity to caress the Ninth Amendment without embracing it."&lt;/ref&gt; Douglas, in his concurring opinion in the companion case, Doe, stated more emphatically, "The Ninth Amendment obviously does not create federally enforceable rights."&lt;ref&gt;Devins, Neal and Watson, Wendy (1995). ''Judicial Nominations'', p. 225.&lt;/ref&gt;

Justice Blackmun's majority opinion explicitly rejected a fetal "right to life" argument.&lt;ref&gt;''Roe'', 410 U.S. at 156–159.&lt;/ref&gt; The Court instead recognized the right to an abortion as a fundamental right included within the guarantee of personal privacy.&lt;ref&gt;''Roe'', 410 U.S. at 153 ("This right of privacy, whether it be founded in the Fourteenth Amendment's concept of personal liberty and restrictions upon state action, as we feel it is, or, as the District Court determined, in the Ninth Amendment's reservation of rights to the people, is broad enough to encompass a woman's decision whether or not to terminate her pregnancy.").&lt;/ref&gt; As a result, regulations limiting abortion had to be justified by a "compelling state interest," and legislative enactments regulating abortion had to be narrowly tailored to meet the compelling interests; in other words, Justice Blackmun applied a strict scrutiny analysis to abortion regulations.&lt;ref&gt;''Roe'', 410 U.S. at 155.&lt;/ref&gt;

While acknowledging that the right to abortion was not unlimited, Justice Blackmun, speaking for the Court, created a trimester framework to balance the fundamental right to abortion with the government's two legitimate interests: protecting the mother's health and protecting the "potentiality of human life." The trimester framework addressed when a woman's fundamental right to abortion would be absolute, and when the state's interests would become compelling. In the first trimester, when it was believed that the procedure was [[Abortion#Safety|safer than childbirth]], the Court left the decision to abort completely to the woman and her physician.&lt;ref&gt;''Roe'', 410 U.S. at 163.&lt;/ref&gt; From approximately the end of the first trimester until [[fetal viability]], the state's interest in protecting the health of the mother would become "compelling."&lt;ref name="Id. at 163"&gt;''Roe'', 410 U.S. at 163.&lt;/ref&gt; At that time, the state could regulate the abortion procedure if the regulation "reasonably relate[d] to the "preservation and protection of maternal health."&lt;ref name="Id. at 163"/&gt; At the point of viability, which the Court believed to be in the third trimester, the state's interest in "potential life" would become compelling, and the state could regulate abortion to protect "potential life."&lt;ref name="Id. at 163"/&gt; At that point, the state could even forbid abortion so long as it made an exception to preserve the life or health of the mother.&lt;ref&gt;''Roe'', 410 U.S. at 163–164 ("If the State is interested in protecting fetal life after viability, it may go so far as to proscribe abortion during that period, except when it is necessary to preserve the life or health of the mother.").&lt;/ref&gt; The Court added that the primary right being preserved in the ''Roe'' decision was that of the physician to practice medicine freely absent a compelling state interest – not women's rights in general.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Greenhouse|2005|pp=98–99}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1992, however, the plurality of Justices [[Sandra Day O'Connor]], [[David Souter]], and [[Anthony Kennedy]] made a subtle move away from the physician's-rights approach of ''Roe'' and toward a patient's-rights approach in ''Planned Parenthood of Southeastern Pennsylvania v. Casey''. The plurality in ''Casey'', explicitly confirming that women had a constitutional right to abortion and further upholding the "essential holding" of ''Roe'', stated that women had a right to choose abortion before viability and that this right could not be unduly interfered with by the state.&lt;ref name=Casey846&gt;''Casey'', 505 U.S. at 846.&lt;/ref&gt; They asserted that this right was rooted in the Due Process Clause of the Fourteenth Amendment.&lt;ref name=Casey846/&gt;

Prior to the decision, the justices discussed the trimester framework at great length. Justice Powell had suggested that the point where the state could intervene be placed at viability, which Justice [[Thurgood Marshall]] supported as well.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Greenhouse|2005|pp=96–97}}&lt;/ref&gt; In an internal memo to the other justices before the majority decision was published, Justice Blackmun wrote: "You will observe that I have concluded that the end of the first trimester is critical. This is arbitrary, but perhaps any other selected point, such as [[quickening]] or viability, is equally arbitrary."&lt;ref&gt;Woodward, Bob. "[http://swiss.csail.mit.edu/~rauch/nvp/roe/woodward.html The Abortion Papers]", ''Washington Post'' (January 22, 1989). Retrieved 2007-02-03.&lt;/ref&gt; Roe supporters are quick to point out, however, that the memo only reflects Blackmun's uncertainty about the timing of the trimester framework, not the framework or the holding itself.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=Kate |last=Michelman |first2=Dawn |last2=Johnsen |title=The Abortion Papers (Op-Ed) |work=The Washington Post |date=February 4, 1989 |url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/archive/opinions/1989/02/04/the-abortion-papers/68042f1b-db7b-4e06-8c74-5425d67ef615/ }}&lt;/ref&gt; In his opinion, Blackmun also clearly explained how he had reached the trimester framework – scrutinizing history, common law, the [[Hippocratic Oath]], medical knowledge, and the positions of medical organizations.&lt;ref&gt;''Roe'', 410 U.S. at 129–147.&lt;/ref&gt; Justice Blackmun's trimester framework was later rejected by the O'Connor–Souter–Kennedy plurality in ''Casey'', in favor of the "undue burden" analysis still employed by the Court.&lt;ref&gt;''See'' 505 U.S. at 873–874.&lt;/ref&gt; Contrary to Blackmun, Justice Douglas preferred the first-trimester line.&lt;ref name="Greenhouse 97"&gt;{{harvnb|Greenhouse|2005|p=97}}&lt;/ref&gt; Justice Stewart said the lines were "legislative" and wanted more flexibility and consideration paid to state legislatures, though he joined Blackmun's decision.&lt;ref&gt;Kmiec, Douglas. "[http://members.aol.com/abtrbng2/roememos.txt Testimony Before Subcommittee on the Constitution, Judiciary Committee, U.S. House of Representatives]" (April 22, 1996), via the "Abortion Law Homepage". Retrieved 2007-01-23.&lt;/ref&gt; Justice [[William J. Brennan Jr.]] proposed abandoning frameworks based on the age of the fetus and instead allowing states to regulate the procedure based on its safety for the mother.&lt;ref name="Greenhouse 97" /&gt;

The majority opinion allowed states to protect fetal life after viability even though a fetus is not a person within the meaning of the Fourteenth Amendment.&lt;ref&gt;Charles H. Baron. [http://lawdigitalcommons.bc.edu/lsfp/130/ "The Concept of Person in the Law."] ''The Journal of Law, Medicine &amp; Ethics'' 11, (1985): 52–63.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Justiciability ===
An aspect of the decision that attracted comparatively little attention was the Court's disposition of the issues of [[Standing (law)|standing]] and [[mootness]]. Under the traditional interpretation of these rules, Jane Roe's appeal was "moot" because she had already given birth to her child and thus would not be affected by the ruling; she also lacked "standing" to assert the rights of other pregnant women.&lt;ref&gt;Abernathy, M. et al. (1993), ''[https://books.google.com/?id=tHhlYpWokFIC Civil Liberties Under the Constitution]''. U. South Carolina, p. 4. Retrieved February 4, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; As she did not present an "actual [[case or controversy]]" (a grievance and a demand for relief), any opinion issued by the Supreme Court would constitute an [[advisory opinion]].

The Court concluded that the case came within an established exception to the rule: one that allowed consideration of an issue that was "capable of repetition, yet evading review."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Federal Jurisdiction |series=Introduction to Law |first=Erwin |last=Chemerinsky |authorlink=Erwin Chemerinsky |edition=4th |publisher=Aspen Publishers |year=2003 |isbn=978-0-7355-2718-8 |page=132 |url=https://books.google.com/?id=wgpGAQAAIAAJ}}&lt;/ref&gt; This phrase had been coined in 1911 by Justice [[Joseph McKenna]] in ''[[Southern Pacific Terminal Co. v. ICC]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{ussc|name=Southern Pacific v. Interstate Commerce Commission|volume=219|page=498|pin=|year=1911}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Blackmun's opinion quoted McKenna and noted that pregnancy would normally conclude more quickly than an appellate process: "If that termination makes a case moot, pregnancy litigation seldom will survive much beyond the trial stage, and appellate review will be effectively denied."&lt;ref&gt;''Roe'', 410 U.S. at 125; see also {{harvnb|Schwartz|1988|pp=108–109}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Dissents ==
[[File:Justice White Official.jpg|thumb|right|[[Byron White]] was the senior dissenting justice.]]
Justices White and Rehnquist wrote emphatic dissenting opinions. White wrote:
{{quote|I find nothing in the language or history of the Constitution to support the Court's judgment. The Court simply fashions and announces a new constitutional right for pregnant women and, with scarcely any reason or authority for its action, invests that right with sufficient substance to override most existing state abortion statutes. The upshot is that the people and the legislatures of the 50 States are constitutionally disentitled to weigh the relative importance of the continued existence and development of the fetus, on the one hand, against a spectrum of possible impacts on the woman, on the other hand. As an exercise of raw judicial power, the Court perhaps has authority to do what it does today; but, in my view, its judgment is an improvident and extravagant exercise of the power of judicial review that the Constitution extends to this Court.&lt;ref name="Doe" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Potts, Malcolm et al. ''Abortion'', p. 347 (1977).&lt;/ref&gt;}}

White asserted that the Court "values the convenience of the pregnant mother more than the continued existence and development of the life or potential life that she carries." Though he suggested that he "might agree" with the Court's values and priorities, he wrote that he saw "no constitutional warrant for imposing such an order of priorities on the people and legislatures of the States." White criticized the Court for involving itself in the issue of abortion by creating "a constitutional barrier to state efforts to protect human life and by investing mothers and doctors with the constitutionally protected right to exterminate it." He would have left this issue, for the most part, "with the people and to the political processes the people have devised to govern their affairs."

Rehnquist elaborated on several of White's points, asserting that the Court's historical analysis was flawed:
{{quote|To reach its result, the Court necessarily has had to find within the scope of the Fourteenth Amendment a right that was apparently completely unknown to the drafters of the Amendment. As early as 1821, the first state law dealing directly with abortion was enacted by the Connecticut Legislature. By the time of the adoption of the Fourteenth Amendment in 1868, there were at least 36 laws enacted by state or territorial legislatures limiting abortion. While many States have amended or updated their laws, 21 of the laws on the books in 1868 remain in effect today.&lt;ref name="Roe"&gt;''Roe'', 410 U.S. at 174–177 (Rehnquist, J., dissenting).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Currie |first=David |title=The Constitution in the Supreme Court: The Second Century, 1888–1986|volume=2|page=470|publisher=University of Chicago Press|year=1994}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;"[http://www.economist.com/node/4134124 Rehnquist's legacy]", ''[[The Economist]]'' (June 30, 2005).&lt;/ref&gt;}}

From this historical record, Rehnquist concluded, "There apparently was no question concerning the validity of this provision or of any of the other state statutes when the Fourteenth Amendment was adopted." Therefore, in his view, "the drafters did not intend to have the Fourteenth Amendment withdraw from the States the power to legislate with respect to this matter."

== Reception ==

===Political===
A  statistical evaluation of the relationship of political affiliation to pro-choice and anti-abortion issues shows that public opinion is much more nuanced about when abortion is acceptable than is commonly assumed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Analysis {{!}} How America feels about abortion|url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/politics/wp/2017/04/24/how-america-feels-about-abortion/?wpisrc=nl_draw&amp;wpmm=1|accessdate=April 25, 2017|work=Washington Post}}&lt;/ref&gt;
The most prominent organized groups that mobilized in response to ''Roe'' are the [[NARAL Pro-Choice America|National Abortion Rights Action League]] and the [[National Right to Life Committee]].

====Support====
{{multiple image
|direction = vertical
|width = 200
|align=right
|image1 = Roevwade.jpg
|caption = [[Albert Wynn]] and [[Gloria Feldt]] at a 2003 rally for ''Roe v. Wade''}}

Advocates of ''Roe'' describe it as vital to the preservation of [[women's rights]], personal freedom, bodily integrity, and privacy. Advocates have also reasoned that access to safe abortion and reproductive freedom generally are fundamental rights. Some scholars (not including any member of the Supreme Court) have equated the denial of abortion rights to compulsory motherhood, and have argued that abortion bans therefore violate the [[Thirteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Thirteenth Amendment]]:

{{quote|When women are compelled to carry and bear children, they are subjected to 'involuntary servitude' in violation of the Thirteenth Amendment….[E]ven if the woman has stipulated to have consented to the risk of pregnancy, that does not permit the state to force her to remain pregnant.&lt;ref name="Koppelman" /&gt;}}

Supporters of ''Roe'' contend that the decision has a valid constitutional foundation in the Fourteenth Amendment, or that the fundamental right to abortion is found elsewhere in the Constitution but not in the articles referenced in the decision.&lt;ref name="Koppelman"&gt;Koppelman, Andrew. [http://www.law1.northwestern.edu/faculty/fulltime/koppelman/forcedlabor.pdf "Forced Labor: A Thirteenth Amendment Defense of Abortion"] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090225130324/http://www.law1.northwestern.edu/faculty/fulltime/koppelman/forcedlabor.pdf |date=February 25, 2009 }}, ''Northwestern Law Review'', Vol. 84, p. 480 (1990).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Balkin"&gt;''[https://books.google.com/?vid=ISBN0814799183&amp;id=Us-277i9ZJYC&amp;pg=PP1 What Roe v. Wade Should Have Said; The Nation's Top Legal Experts Rewrite America's Most Controversial decision]'', Jack Balkin Ed. (NYU Press 2005). Retrieved January 26, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

====Opposition====

{{multiple image
|direction = vertical
|width = 200
|align=right
|image1 = AntiObamaBiden.jpg
|caption1 = [[Protest]]ors at the 2009 [[March for Life (Washington, D.C.)|March for Life]] rally against ''Roe v. Wade''
}}

Every year, on the anniversary of the decision, opponents of abortion march up [[Constitution Avenue]] to the [[United States Supreme Court Building|Supreme Court Building]] in [[Washington, DC]], in the [[March for Life (Washington, D.C.)|March for Life]].&lt;ref&gt;Shimron, Yonat. [http://www.newsobserver.com/news/story/1372074.html "Democratic Gains Spur Abortion Foes into Action,"] ''[[The News &amp; Observer]]'' (January 18, 2009): "The annual March for Life procession is already among Washington's largest rallies, drawing an estimated 200,000 people."&lt;/ref&gt;  Around 250,000 people attended the march until 2010.&lt;ref&gt;Harper, Jennifer. [http://washingtontimes.com/news/2009/jan/22/pro-life-rally-yearns-for-media-spotlight/ "a marchers lose attention,"] ''[[Washington Times]]'' (January 22, 2009): "the event has consistently drawn about 250,000 participants each year since 2003."&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Johnston, Laura. [http://www.cleveland.com/news/plaindealer/index.ssf?/base/cuyahoga/1232271195211520.xml&amp;coll=2 "Cleveland's first March for Life anti-abortion event draws 200,"] ''[[The Plain Dealer]]'' (January 18, 2009): "the Washington March for Life…draws 200,000 annually on the anniversary of the Roe v. Wade decision."&lt;/ref&gt; Estimates put the 2011 and 2012 attendances at 400,000 each,&lt;ref name="zenit2011"&gt;{{cite web|title=Youth Turnout Strong at US March for Life|date=January 25, 2011|publisher=Zenit.org|website=Catholic.net|url=http://www.zenit.org/en/articles/youth-turnout-strong-at-us-march-for-life|accessdate=February 9, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the 2013 March for Life drew an estimated 650,000 people.&lt;ref name="MonroeNews"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.monroenews.com/news/2013/feb/10/newport-650000-march-life/ |title=Newport: 650,000 In March For Life |last=Portteus |first=Danielle |date=February 10, 2013 |website=[[MonroeNews]] |publisher=MonroeNews |accessdate=April 14, 2013 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140213230423/http://www.monroenews.com/news/2013/feb/10/newport-650000-march-life/ |archivedate=February 13, 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Opponents of ''Roe'' assert that the decision lacks a valid constitutional foundation.&lt;ref name="Childress1984"&gt;{{cite book|author=James F. Childress|title=Bioethics Reporter|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=S8keAQAAMAAJ|accessdate=August 2, 2013|year=1984|publisher=University Publications of America|page=463|quote=Roe v. Wade itself provided abortion rights with an unstable foundation.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Like the dissenters in ''Roe'', they maintain that the Constitution is silent on the issue, and that proper solutions to the question would best be found via state legislatures and the legislative process, rather than through an all-encompassing ruling from the Supreme Court.&lt;ref name="Locay2008"&gt;{{cite book|author=Alex Locay|title=Unveiling the Left|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=X9hr6zWiPhIC&amp;pg=PA187|accessdate=August 2, 2013|date=January 2008|publisher=Xulon Press|isbn=978-1-60266-869-0|page=187|quote=To justify their decision the Court made up a new "right", not found in the Constitution: the right to privacy. The founders of course never intended for such rights to exists, as we know privacy is limited in many ways.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A prominent argument against the ''Roe'' decision is that, in the absence of consensus about when meaningful life begins, it is best to avoid the risk of doing harm.&lt;ref&gt;Reagan, Ronald. ''[http://www.worldcatlibraries.org/oclc/10456929?tab=holdings Abortion and the Conscience of the Nation]'', (Nelson 1984): "If you don't know whether a body is alive or dead, you would never bury it. I think this consideration itself should be enough for all of us to insist on protecting the unborn." Retrieved January 26, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

In response to ''Roe v. Wade'', most states enacted or attempted to enact laws limiting or regulating abortion, such as laws requiring [[parental consent]] or parental notification for minors to obtain abortions; spousal mutual consent laws; [[Paternal rights and abortion|spousal notification]] laws; laws requiring abortions to be performed in hospitals, not clinics; laws barring state funding for abortions; laws banning [[intact dilation and extraction]], also known as partial-birth abortion; laws requiring waiting periods before abortions; and laws mandating that women read certain types of literature and watch a fetal ultrasound before undergoing an abortion.&lt;ref&gt;Guttmacher Institute, "[http://www.guttmacher.org/statecenter/spibs/spib_OAL.pdf State Policies in Brief, An Overview of Abortion Laws (PDF)]", published January 1, 2007. Retrieved 2007-01-26.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1976, Congress passed the [[Hyde Amendment]], barring federal funding of abortions (except in cases of rape, incest, or a threat to the life of the mother) for poor women through the [[Medicaid]] program. The Supreme Court struck down some state restrictions in a long series of cases stretching from the mid-1970s to the late 1980s, but upheld restrictions on funding, including the Hyde Amendment, in the case of ''[[Harris v. McRae]]'' (1980).&lt;ref&gt;{{ussc|name=Harris v. McRae|volume=448|page=297|pin=|year=1980}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

Some opponents of abortion maintain that [[personhood]] begins at [[fertilization]] or [[Conception (biology)|conception]], and should therefore be protected by the Constitution;&lt;ref name="Balkin" /&gt; the dissenting justices in ''Roe'' instead wrote that decisions about abortion "should be left with the people and to the political processes the people have devised to govern their affairs."&lt;ref name="Doe"&gt;{{ussc|name=Doe v. Bolton|volume=410|page=179|pin=|year=1973}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

Perhaps the most notable opposition to ''Roe'' comes from Roe herself: In 1995, Norma L. McCorvey revealed that she had become [[pro-life]], and from then until her death in 2017, she was a vocal opponent of abortion.&lt;ref&gt;McCorvey, Norma, with Andy Meisler (1994). ''I Am Roe: My Life, Roe v. Wade, and Freedom of Choice.'' New York: Harper-Collins.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Legal ===
Justice Blackmun, who authored the ''Roe'' decision, stood by the analytical framework he established in ''Roe'' throughout his career.&lt;ref name=Blackmun&gt;''Casey'', 505 U.S. at 930–934 (Blackmun, J., concurring in part and dissenting in part) ("In sum, ''Roe''&lt;nowiki/&gt;'s requirement of strict scrutiny as implemented through a trimester framework should not be disturbed.").&lt;/ref&gt;  Despite his initial reluctance, he became the decision's chief champion and protector during his later years on the Court.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Greenhouse|2005|pp=183–206, 250}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Modern liberalism in the United States|Liberal]] and [[feminist]] legal scholars have had various reactions to ''Roe'', not always giving the decision unqualified support. One argument is that Justice Blackmun reached the correct result but went about it the wrong way.&lt;ref&gt;[[Jack Balkin|Balkin, Jack]]. [http://www.yalelawjournal.org/pdf/110-8/balkin.pdf Bush v. "Gore and the Boundary Between Law and Politics"] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080227213608/http://www.yalelawjournal.org/pdf/110-8/balkin.pdf |date=February 27, 2008 }}, 110 ''Yale Law Journal'' 1407 (2001): "Liberal and feminist legal scholars have spent decades showing that the result was correct even if Justice Blackmun's opinion seems to have been taken from the Court's [[cubism|Cubist]] period."&lt;/ref&gt; Another is that the end achieved by ''Roe'' does not justify its means of [[judicial fiat]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Richard Cohen (Washington Post columnist)|Cohen, Richard]]. [https://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2005/10/19/AR2005101901974.html "Support Choice, Not Roe",] ''Washington Post'', (October 19, 2005): "If the best we can say for it is that the end justifies the means, then we have not only lost the argument – but a bit of our soul as well." Retrieved 2007-01-23.&lt;/ref&gt;

Justice [[John Paul Stevens]], while agreeing with the decision, has suggested that it should have been more narrowly focused on the issue of privacy. According to Stevens, if the decision had avoided the trimester framework and simply stated that the right to privacy included a right to choose abortion, "it might have been much more acceptable" from a legal standpoint.&lt;ref&gt;Rosen, Jeffrey. [https://www.nytimes.com/2007/09/23/magazine/23stevens-t.html "The Dissenter"], ''[[The New York Times Magazine]]'' (September 23, 2007). Rosen notes that Stevens is "the oldest and arguably most liberal justice."&lt;/ref&gt; Justice [[Ruth Bader Ginsburg]] had, before joining the Court, criticized the decision for ending a nascent movement to liberalize [[abortion law]] through legislation.&lt;ref&gt;Ginsburg, Ruth. "[http://www.blogdenovo.org/archives/63_N_C_L_Rev_375.doc Some Thoughts on Autonomy and Equality in Relation to Roe v. Wade]", 63 ''North Carolina Law Review'' 375 (1985): "The political process was moving in the early 1970s, not swiftly enough for advocates of quick, complete change, but majoritarian institutions were listening and acting. Heavy-handed judicial intervention was difficult to justify and appears to have provoked, not resolved, conflict." Retrieved January 23, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Ginsburg has also faulted the Court's approach for being "about a doctor's freedom to practice his profession as he thinks best.... It wasn't woman-centered. It was physician-centered."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Bullington|first=Jonathan|title=Justice Ginsburg: Roe v. Wade not 'woman-centered'|url=http://www.chicagotribune.com/news/local/breaking/chi-justice-ginsburg-roe-v-wade-not-womancentered-20130511,0,3079568.story|newspaper=Chicago Tribune|date=May 11, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Watergate scandal|Watergate]] prosecutor [[Archibald Cox]] wrote: "[''Roe''{{'}}s] failure to confront the issue in principled terms leaves the opinion to read like a set of hospital rules and regulations.... Neither historian, nor layman, nor lawyer will be persuaded that all the prescriptions of Justice Blackmun are part of the Constitution."&lt;ref&gt;Cox, Archibald. ''[https://books.google.com/?id=ZrYdAAAAMAAJ The Role of the Supreme Court in American Government]'', 113–114 (Oxford U. Press 1976), via Google Books. Retrieved January 26, 2007. [[Stuart Taylor Jr.|Stuart Taylor]] has argued that "''Roe v. Wade'' was sort of conjured up out of very general phrases and was recorded, even by most liberal scholars like Archibald Cox at the time, John Harvey Link – just to name two Harvard scholars – as kind of made-up constitutional law." See [[Stuart Taylor Jr.]], [https://www.pbs.org/newshour/bb/law/july-dec00/scotus_7-13.html Online News Hour], ''PBS'' 2000-07-13.&lt;/ref&gt;

In a highly cited 1973 article in the ''[[Yale Law Journal]]'',&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Greenhouse|2005|pp=135–136}}&lt;/ref&gt; Professor [[John Hart Ely]] criticized ''Roe'' as a decision that "is not constitutional law and gives almost no sense of an obligation to try to be."&lt;ref&gt;Ely, John Hart. "[http://www.timothypcarney.com/wages-wolf.htm The Wages of Crying Wolf] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070625170521/http://www.timothypcarney.com/wages-wolf.htm |date=2007-06-25 }}", 82 ''Yale Law Journal'' 920 (1973). Retrieved January 23, 2007. Professor Ely "supported the availability of abortion as a matter of policy." See Liptak, Adam. [https://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E2DF1131F934A15753C1A9659C8B63 "John Hart Ely, a Constitutional Scholar, Is Dead at 64"], ''New York Times'' (2003-10-27). Ely is generally regarded as having been a "liberal constitutional scholar." Perry, Michael (1999). {{Google books|ka8ajkxQWxkC|We the People: The Fourteenth Amendment and the Supreme Court}}{{cite web|url=http://www.timothypcarney.com/wages-wolf.htm |title=Archived copy |accessdate=October 5, 2009 |deadurl=bot: unknown |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070625170521/http://www.timothypcarney.com/wages-wolf.htm |archivedate=June 25, 2007 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt; Ely added: "What is frightening about ''Roe'' is that this super-protected right is not inferable from the language of the Constitution, the framers’ thinking respecting the specific problem in issue, any general value derivable from the provisions they included, or the nation's governmental structure." Professor [[Laurence Tribe]] had similar thoughts: "One of the most curious things about ''Roe'' is that, behind its own verbal smokescreen, the substantive judgment on which it rests is nowhere to be found."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Tribe |first=Laurence |year=1973|title=The Supreme Court, 1972 Term – Foreword: Toward a Model of Roles in the Due Process of Life and Law |journal=[[Harvard Law Review]] |volume=87|issue=1 |pages=1 [p. 7] |doi=10.2307/1339866|jstor=1339866 }} Quoted in {{cite journal |last=Morgan |first=Richard Gregory|year=1979 |title=''Roe v. Wade'' and the Lesson of the Pre-''Roe'' Case Law |journal=[[Michigan Law Review]] |volume=77 |issue=7 |pages=1724–1748|doi=10.2307/1288040 |jstor=1288040}}&lt;/ref&gt; Liberal law professors [[Alan Dershowitz]],&lt;ref&gt;Dershowitz, Alan. ''Supreme Injustice: How the High Court Hijacked Election 2000'' (Oxford U. Press 2001): "Judges have no special competence, qualifications, or mandate to decide between equally compelling moral claims (as in the abortion controversy)...." quoted by Green, "[https://books.google.com/?id=JW9LdM2nxsQC Bushed and Gored: A Brief Review of Initial Literature]", in ''The Final Arbiter: The Consequences of Bush V. Gore for Law And Politics'', ed. Banks C, Cohen D &amp; Green J., editors, p. 14 (SUNY Press 2005), via Google Books. Retrieved January 26, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Cass Sunstein]],&lt;ref&gt;Sunstein, Cass. Quoted by McGuire, ''[http://www.nysun.com/article/23046 New York Sun]'' (November 15, 2005): "What I think is that it just doesn't have the stable status of ''[[Brown v. Board of Education|Brown]]'' or ''[[Miranda v. Arizona|Miranda]]'' because it's been under internal and external assault pretty much from the beginning....As a constitutional matter, I think Roe was way overreached." Retrieved 2007-01-23. Sunstein is a "liberal constitutional scholar." See Herman, Eric. [http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qn4155/is_20050711/ai_n14852520 "Former U of C law prof on everyone's short court list"], ''Chicago Sun-Times'' (2005-07-11). {{dead link|date=August 2016|bot=medic}}{{cbignore|bot=medic}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Kermit Roosevelt III|Kermit Roosevelt]]&lt;ref&gt;Roosevelt, Kermit. "[https://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/washingtonpost/access/279325011.html?dids=279325011:279325011&amp;FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS=ABS:FT&amp;fmac=&amp;date=Jan+22%2C+2003&amp;author=Kermit+Roosevelt&amp;desc=Shaky+Basis+for+a+Constitutional+%27Right%27 Shaky Basis for a Constitutional ‘Right’]", ''Washington Post'', (January 22, 2003): "[I]t is time to admit in public that, as an example of the practice of constitutional opinion writing, Roe is a serious disappointment. You will be hard-pressed to find a constitutional law professor, even among those who support the idea of constitutional protection for the right to choose, who will embrace the opinion itself rather than the result….This is not surprising. As constitutional argument, Roe is barely coherent. The court pulled its fundamental right to choose more or less from the constitutional ether. It supported that right via a lengthy, but purposeless, cross-cultural historical review of abortion restrictions and a tidy but irrelevant refutation of the straw-man argument that a fetus is a constitutional ‘person’ entitled to the protection of the 14th Amendment....By declaring an inviolable fundamental right to abortion, Roe short-circuited the democratic deliberation that is the most reliable method of deciding questions of competing values." Retrieved 2007-01-23. {{cite web|url=https://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/washingtonpost/access/279325011.html?dids=279325011%3A279325011&amp;FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS=ABS%3AFT&amp;fmac=&amp;date=Jan%2022%2C%202003&amp;author=Kermit%20Roosevelt&amp;desc=Shaky%20Basis%20for%20a%20Constitutional%20%27Right%27 |title=Archived copy |accessdate=May 8, 2017 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070319014511/https://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/washingtonpost/access/279325011.html?dids=279325011%3A279325011&amp;FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS=ABS%3AFT&amp;fmac=&amp;date=Jan+22%2C+2003&amp;author=Kermit+Roosevelt&amp;desc=Shaky+Basis+for+a+Constitutional+%27Right%27 |archivedate=March 19, 2007 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt; have also expressed disappointment with ''Roe''.

[[Jeffrey Rosen]]&lt;ref&gt;Rosen, Jeffrey. "[https://web.archive.org/web/20030309173117/http://www.tnr.com/doc.mhtml?i=20030224&amp;s=rosen022403 Why We’d Be Better off Without Roe: Worst Choice]", ''The New Republic'' via Archive.org (February 24, 2003): "In short, 30 years later, it seems increasingly clear that this pro-choice magazine was correct in 1973 when it criticized ''Roe'' on constitutional grounds. Its overturning would be the best thing that could happen to the federal judiciary, the pro-choice movement, and the moderate majority of the American people." Retrieved 2007-01-23.&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Michael Kinsley]]&lt;ref&gt;Kinsley, Michael. "Bad choice", ''The New Republic'' (June 13, 2004): "Against all odds (and, I'm afraid, against all logic), the basic holding of Roe v. Wade is secure in the Supreme Court....[A] freedom of choice law would guarantee abortion rights the correct way, democratically, rather than by constitutional origami." Retrieved 2007-01-23.&lt;/ref&gt; echo Ginsburg, arguing that a legislative movement would have been the correct way to build a more durable consensus in support of abortion rights. [[William Saletan]] wrote, "Blackmun's [Supreme Court] papers vindicate every indictment of ''Roe'': invention, overreach, arbitrariness, textual indifference."&lt;ref&gt;Saletan, William. [http://www.legalaffairs.org/issues/May-June-2005/feature_saleton_mayjun05.msp "Unbecoming Justice Blackmun",] ''Legal Affairs'', May/June 2005. Retrieved January 23, 2007. Saletan is a self-described liberal. See Saletan, William. [http://www.slate.com/id/2170311/ "Rights and Wrongs: Liberals, progressives, and biotechnology"], ''Slate'' (2007-07-13).&lt;/ref&gt; [[Benjamin Wittes]] has written that ''Roe'' "disenfranchised millions of conservatives on an issue about which they care deeply."&lt;ref&gt;Wittes, Benjamin. "[https://www.theatlantic.com/doc/200501/wittes Letting Go of Roe]", ''The Atlantic Monthly'', Jan/Feb 2005. Retrieved January 23, 2007. Wittes also said, "I generally favor permissive abortion laws." He has elsewhere noted, "In their quieter moments, many liberal scholars recognize that the decision is a mess." See Wittes, Benjamin. [http://www.tnr.com/politics/story.html?id=30f9cb45-53e4-4e16-b447-968c6ea52e2a "A Little Less Conversation"], ''The New Republic'' November 29, 2007&lt;/ref&gt; And [[Edward Lazarus]], a former Blackmun clerk who "loved ''Roe''{{'}}s author like a grandfather," wrote: "As a matter of constitutional interpretation and judicial method, ''Roe'' borders on the indefensible.... Justice Blackmun's opinion provides essentially no reasoning in support of its holding. And in the almost 30 years since ''Roe'''s announcement, no one has produced a convincing defense of ''Roe'' on its own terms."&lt;ref&gt;Lazarus, Edward. "[http://writ.corporate.findlaw.com/lazarus/20021003.html The Lingering Problems with Roe v. Wade, and Why the Recent Senate Hearings on Michael McConnell's Nomination Only Underlined Them]", ''Findlaw's Writ'' (October 3, 2002). Retrieved 2007-01-23.&lt;/ref&gt;

The assertion that the Supreme Court was making a legislative decision is often repeated by opponents of the ruling.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| last =Forsythe| first =Clarke| title =Abuse of Discretion: The Inside Story of Roe v. Wade| publisher =Encounter Books| date =2013| pages =496| url =http://www.encounterbooks.com/books/abuse-of-discretion-the-inside-story-of-roe-v-wade/| isbn =978-1594036927}}&lt;/ref&gt; The "viability" criterion is still in effect, although the point of viability has changed as medical science has found ways to help premature babies survive.&lt;ref&gt;Stith, Irene. ''[http://www.law.umaryland.edu/marshall/crsreports/crsdocuments/95-1101_SPR.pdf Abortion Procedures, CRS Report for Congress (PDF)]'' (November 17, 1997). Retrieved 2007-02-02.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Public opinion ===
{{See also|Abortion in the United States#Public opinion|l1=Abortion in the United States: Public opinion}}
A [[Gallup poll]] conducted in May 2014 indicates that 50% of Americans believe that abortions should be legal under certain circumstances, 28% believe abortion should be legal under any circumstances, and 21% believe that abortion should be illegal in all circumstances.&lt;ref&gt;Saad, Lydia. [http://www.gallup.com/poll/170249/split-abortion-pro-choice-pro-life.aspx U.S. Still Split on Abortion: 47% Pro-Choice, 46% Pro-Life], Gallup (May 22, 2014).&lt;/ref&gt;

A [[Gallup poll]] conducted in May 2009 indicates that 53% of Americans believe that abortions should be legal under certain circumstances, 23% believe abortion should be legal under any circumstances, and 22% believe that abortion should be illegal in all circumstances. However, in this poll, more Americans referred to themselves as "Pro-Life" than "Pro-Choice" for the first time since the poll asked the question in 1995, with 51% identifying as "Pro-Life" and 42% identifying as "Pro-Choice".&lt;ref&gt;Saad, Lydia. [http://www.gallup.com/poll/118399/More-Americans-Pro-Life-Than-Pro-Choice-First-Time.aspx More Americans "Pro-Life" Than "Pro-Choice" for First Time], Gallup (May 15, 2009).&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, an April 2009 [[Pew Research Center]] poll showed a softening of support for legal abortion in all cases compared to the previous years of polling. People who said they support abortion in all or most cases dropped from 54% in 2008 to 46% in 2009.&lt;ref&gt;[http://people-press.org/report/513/ "Public Takes Conservative Turn on Gun Control, Abortion Americans Now Divided Over Both Issues"], [[Pew Research Center]] (April 30, 2009).&lt;/ref&gt;

In contrast, an October 2007 [[Harris Insights &amp; Analytics|Harris]] poll on ''Roe v. Wade'' asked the following question:
{{quote|In 1973, the U.S. Supreme Court decided that states laws which made it illegal for a woman to have an abortion up to three months of pregnancy were unconstitutional, and that the decision on whether a woman should have an abortion up to three months of pregnancy should be left to the woman and her doctor to decide. In general, do you favor or oppose this part of the U.S. Supreme Court decision making abortions up to three months of pregnancy legal?&lt;ref name="Lowest" /&gt;}}

In reply, 56 percent of respondents indicated favour while 40 percent indicated opposition. The Harris organization concluded from this poll that "56 percent now favours the U.S. Supreme Court decision." Anti-abortion activists have disputed whether the Harris poll question is a valid measure of public opinion about ''Roe''{{'}}s overall decision, because the question focuses only on the first three months of pregnancy.&lt;ref&gt;Franz, Wanda. [http://www.nrlc.org/news/2007/NRL06/PresidentColumn.html "The Continuing Confusion About Roe v. Wade"] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080512081340/http://www.nrlc.org/news/2007/NRL06/PresidentColumn.html |date=May 12, 2008 }}, ''NRL News'' (June 2007).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Adamek, Raymond. [https://www.jstor.org/stable/2748305 "Abortion Polls"], ''[[Public Opinion Quarterly]]'', Vol. 42, No. 3 (Autumn, 1978), pp. 411–413. Dr. Adamek is pro-life. [http://www.prolifetechnology.org/proceedings/2004/bio/adamek.html Dr Raymond J Adamek, PhD] ''Pro-Life Science and Technology Symposium.''&lt;/ref&gt; The Harris poll has tracked public opinion about ''Roe'' since 1973:&lt;ref name="Lowest"&gt;Harris Interactive, (November 9, 2007). "[http://www.harrisinteractive.com/harris_poll/index.asp?PID=830 Support for Roe v. Wade Increases Significantly, Reaches Highest Level in Nine Years]." Retrieved 2007-12-14.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Harris Interactive. [https://online.wsj.com/public/resources/documents/info-harris0503.html 'U.S. Attitudes Toward Roe v. Wade".] ''The Wall Street Journal Online'', (May 4, 2006). Retrieved 2007-02-03.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:roevwade.png|center]]

Regarding the ''Roe'' decision as a whole, more Americans support it than support overturning it.&lt;ref name="Angus"&gt;[http://www.angus-reid.com/uppdf/Ayres.pdf Ayres McHenry Poll Results on ''Roe v. Wade''] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20081013001848/http://www.angus-reid.com/uppdf/Ayres.pdf |date=October 13, 2008 }} via [[Angus Reid Global Monitor]] (2007).&lt;/ref&gt; When pollsters describe various regulations that ''Roe'' prevents legislatures from enacting, support for ''Roe'' drops.&lt;ref name="Angus" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Gallagher, Maggie. [http://www.realclearpolitics.com/articles/2007/05/prolife_voters_are_crucial_com.html "Pro-Life Voters are Crucial Component of Electability"], Realclearpolitics.com (May 23, 2007).&lt;/ref&gt;

== Role in subsequent decisions and politics ==
Opposition to ''Roe'' on the bench grew when President Reagan, who supported legislative restrictions on abortion, began making federal judicial appointments in 1981. Reagan denied that there was any [[litmus test (politics)|litmus test]]: "I have never given a litmus test to anyone that I have appointed to the bench…. I feel very strongly about those social issues, but I also place my confidence in the fact that the one thing that I do seek are judges that will interpret the law and not write the law. We've had too many examples in recent years of courts and judges legislating."&lt;ref&gt;Reagan, Ronald. ''[http://www.reagan.utexas.edu/archives/speeches/1986/62386e.htm Interview With Eleanor Clift, Jack Nelson, and Joel Havemann of the Los Angeles Times]'' (June 23, 1986). Retrieved 2007-01-23.&lt;/ref&gt;

In addition to White and Rehnquist, Reagan appointee [[Sandra Day O'Connor]] began dissenting from the Court's abortion cases, arguing in 1983 that the trimester-based analysis devised by the ''Roe'' Court was "unworkable."&lt;ref&gt;{{ussc|name=City of Akron v. Akron Center for Reproductive Health|volume=462|page=416|pin=|year=1983}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Shortly before his retirement from the bench, Chief Justice Warren Burger suggested in 1986 that ''Roe'' be "reexamined";&lt;ref name="Thornburgh"&gt;{{ussc|name=Thornburgh v. American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists|volume=476|page=747|pin=|year=1986}}.&lt;/ref&gt; the associate justice who filled Burger's place on the Court – Justice [[Antonin Scalia]] – vigorously opposed ''Roe''. Concern about overturning ''Roe'' played a major role in the defeat of [[Robert Bork]]'s nomination to the Court in 1987; the man eventually appointed to replace ''Roe''-supporter Lewis Powell was [[Anthony Kennedy]].

The [[Supreme Court of Canada]] used the rulings in both ''Roe'' and ''[[Doe v. Bolton]]'' as grounds to find Canada's federal law restricting access to abortions unconstitutional. That Canadian case, ''[[R. v. Morgentaler]]'', was decided in 1988.&lt;ref&gt;''[http://scc.lexum.umontreal.ca/en/1988/1988rcs1-30/1988rcs1-30.html R. v. Morgentaler] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20081023093534/http://scc.lexum.umontreal.ca/en/1988/1988rcs1-30/1988rcs1-30.html |date=October 23, 2008 }}'' 1 S.C.R. 30 (1988).&lt;/ref&gt;

=== ''Webster v. Reproductive Health Services'' ===
{{Main article|Webster v. Reproductive Health Services}}
In a 5–4 decision in 1989's ''[[Webster v. Reproductive Health Services]]'', Chief Justice Rehnquist, writing for the Court, declined to explicitly overrule ''Roe'', because "none of the challenged provisions of the Missouri Act properly before us conflict with the Constitution."&lt;ref name="Webster"&gt;{{ussc|name=Webster v. Reproductive Health Services|volume=492|page=490|pin=|year=1989}}.&lt;/ref&gt; In this case, the Court upheld several abortion restrictions, and modified the ''Roe'' trimester framework.&lt;ref name="Webster"/&gt;

In concurring opinions, O'Connor refused to reconsider ''Roe'', and Justice [[Antonin Scalia]] criticized the Court and O'Connor for not overruling ''Roe''.&lt;ref name="Webster"/&gt; Blackmun – author of the ''Roe'' opinion – stated in his dissent that White, Kennedy and Rehnquist were "callous" and "deceptive," that they deserved to be charged with "cowardice and illegitimacy," and that their [[Plurality (voting)|plurality]] opinion "foments disregard for the law."&lt;ref name="Webster"/&gt; White had recently opined that the majority reasoning in ''Roe v. Wade'' was "warped."&lt;ref name="Thornburgh"/&gt;

=== ''Planned Parenthood v. Casey'' ===
{{Main article|Planned Parenthood v. Casey}}

During initial deliberations for ''[[Planned Parenthood v. Casey]]'' (1992), an initial majority of five Justices (Rehnquist, White, Scalia, Kennedy, and Thomas) were willing to effectively overturn ''Roe''. [[Anthony Kennedy|Kennedy]] changed his mind after the initial conference,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Totenberg|first=Nina|authorlink=Nina Totenberg|url=https://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=1745254|title=Documents Reveal Battle to Preserve 'Roe'; Court Nearly Reversed Abortion Ruling, Blackmun Papers Show|publisher=NPR|work=Morning Edition|date=March 4, 2004|accessdate=January 30, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; and O'Connor, Kennedy, and Souter joined Blackmun and Stevens to reaffirm the central holding of ''Roe'',&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Greenhouse|2005|pp=203–206}}&lt;/ref&gt; saying, "Our law affords constitutional protection to personal decisions relating to marriage, procreation, contraception, family relationships, child rearing, and education. [...] These matters, involving the most intimate and personal choices a person may make in a lifetime, choices central to personal dignity and autonomy, are central to the liberty protected by the Fourteenth Amendment. At the heart of liberty is the right to define one's own concept of existence, of meaning, of the universe, and of the mystery of human life."&lt;ref&gt;''Casey'', 505 U.S. at 851.&lt;/ref&gt; Only Justice Blackmun would have retained ''Roe'' entirely and struck down all aspects of the statute at issue in ''Casey''.&lt;ref name=Blackmun/&gt;

Scalia's dissent acknowledged that abortion rights are of "great importance to many women", but asserted that it is not a liberty protected by the Constitution, because the Constitution does not mention it, and because longstanding traditions have permitted it to be legally proscribed. Scalia concluded: "[B]y foreclosing all democratic outlet for the deep passions this issue arouses, by banishing the issue from the political forum that gives all participants, even the losers, the satisfaction of a fair hearing and an honest fight, by continuing the imposition of a rigid national rule instead of allowing for regional differences, the Court merely prolongs and intensifies the anguish."&lt;ref&gt;''Casey'', 505 U.S. at 1002 (Scalia, J., dissenting).&lt;/ref&gt;

=== ''Stenberg v. Carhart'' ===
{{Main article|Stenberg v. Carhart}}
During the 1990s, the state of [[Nebraska]] attempted to ban a certain second-trimester abortion procedure known as [[intact dilation and extraction]] (sometimes called [[partial birth abortion]]). The Nebraska ban allowed other second-trimester abortion procedures called [[dilation and evacuation]] abortions. Ginsburg (who replaced White) stated, "this law does not save any fetus from destruction, for it targets only 'a method of performing abortion'."&lt;ref name="Stenberg"&gt;{{ussc|name=Stenberg v. Carhart|volume=530|page=914|pin=958–59|year=2000}} ("The fetus, in many cases, dies just as a human adult or child would: It bleeds to death as it is torn from limb from limb. The fetus can be alive at the beginning of the dismemberment process and can survive for a time while its limbs are being torn off.").&lt;/ref&gt; The Supreme Court struck down the Nebraska ban by a 5–4 vote in ''[[Stenberg v. Carhart]]'' (2000), citing a right to use the safest method of second trimester abortion.

Kennedy, who had co-authored the 5-4 ''Casey'' decision upholding ''Roe'', was among the dissenters in ''Stenberg'', writing that Nebraska had done nothing unconstitutional.&lt;ref name="Stenberg"/&gt; In his dissent, Kennedy described the second trimester abortion procedure that Nebraska was not seeking to prohibit, and thus argued that since this dilation and evacuation procedure remained available in Nebraska, the state was free to ban the other procedure sometimes called "partial birth abortion."&lt;ref name="Stenberg"/&gt;

The remaining three dissenters in ''Stenberg'' – Rehnquist, Scalia, and Thomas – disagreed again with ''Roe'': "Although a State may permit abortion, nothing in the Constitution dictates that a State must do so."

=== ''Gonzales v. Carhart'' ===
{{unreferenced|section|date=January 2018}}
{{Main article|Gonzales v. Carhart}}
In 2003, Congress passed the [[Partial-Birth Abortion Ban Act]], which led to a lawsuit in the case of ''[[Gonzales v. Carhart]]''. The Court had previously ruled in ''[[Stenberg v. Carhart]]'' that a state's ban on "partial birth abortion" was unconstitutional because such a ban did not have an exception for the health of the woman. The membership of the Court changed after ''Stenberg'', with [[John Roberts]] and [[Samuel Alito]] replacing Rehnquist and O'Connor, respectively. Further, the ban at issue in ''Gonzales v. Carhart'' was a clear federal statute, rather than a relatively vague state statute as in the ''Stenberg'' case.

On April 18, 2007, the Supreme Court handed down a 5 to 4 decision upholding the constitutionality of the Partial-Birth Abortion Ban Act. Kennedy wrote the majority opinion, asserting that Congress was within its power to generally ban the procedure, although the Court left the door open for as-applied challenges. Kennedy's opinion did not reach the question of whether the Court's prior decisions in ''Roe v. Wade'', ''[[Planned Parenthood v. Casey]]'', and ''Stenberg v. Carhart'' remained valid, and instead the Court stated that the challenged statute remained consistent with those past decisions whether or not those decisions remained valid.

Chief Justice [[John Roberts]], Scalia, Thomas, and Alito joined the majority. Justices Ginsburg, Stevens, Souter, and Breyer dissented, contending that the ruling ignored Supreme Court abortion precedent, and also offering an equality-based justification for abortion precedent. Thomas filed a concurring opinion, joined by Scalia, contending that the Court's prior decisions in ''Roe v. Wade'' and ''Planned Parenthood v. Casey'' should be reversed, and also noting that the Partial-Birth Abortion Ban Act possibly exceeded the powers of Congress under the [[Commerce Clause]].

=== ''Whole Woman's Health v. Hellerstedt'' ===
{{Main article|Whole Woman's Health v. Hellerstedt}}

In the case of ''[[Whole Woman's Health v. Hellerstedt]]'', the most significant [[abortion]] rights case before the Supreme Court since ''[[Planned Parenthood v. Casey]]'' in 1992,&lt;ref name=Atlantic&gt;{{cite news|last1=Green|first1=Emma|title=A New Supreme Court Challenge: The Erosion of Abortion Access in Texas|url=https://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2015/11/a-new-supreme-court-challenge-the-erosion-of-abortion-access-in-texas/415929/|accessdate=January 26, 2016|work=Atlantic|date=November 13, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="20160627Reuters"&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.reuters.com/article/us-usa-court-abortion-idUSKCN0ZC0JL|title=Supreme Court firmly backs abortion rights, tosses Texas law|last=Hurley|first=Lawrence|date=June 28, 2016|website=Reuters|accessdate=June 29, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="20160627CNN"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://edition.cnn.com/2016/06/27/politics/supreme-court-abortion-texas/|title=Supreme Court strikes down Texas abortion access law|date=June 27, 2015|work=|publisher=CNN|author= Ariane de Vogue, Tal Kopan and Dan Berman|accessdate=June 29, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; the Supreme Court in a 5–3 decision on June 27, 2016, swept away forms of state restrictions on the way abortion clinics can function. The Texas legislature enacted in 2013 restrictions on the delivery of abortions services that created an undue burden for women seeking an abortion by requiring abortion doctors to have difficult-to-obtain "admitting privileges" at a local hospital and by requiring clinics to have costly hospital-grade facilities. The Court struck down these two provisions "facially" from [[Texas House Bill 2|the law at issue]] – that is, the very words of the provisions were invalid, no matter how they might be applied in any practical situation. According to the Supreme Court the task of judging whether a law puts an unconstitutional burden on a woman's right to abortion belongs with the courts and not the legislatures.&lt;ref name="20160627SCOTUSDenniston"&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.scotusblog.com/2016/06/opinion-analysis-abortion-rights-reemerge-strongly/|title=Whole Woman's Health v. Hellerstedt – Opinion analysis: Abortion rights reemerge strongly|last=Denniston|first=Lyle|date=June 27, 2016|website=SCOTUSblog|accessdate=June 29, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Activities of Norma McCorvey ===
[[Norma McCorvey]] became a member of the anti-abortion movement in 1995; she supported making abortion illegal until her death in 2017.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-us-canada-39016181 |title=Roe v Wade: Woman in US abortion legal test case dies |website=bbc.co.uk |date=February 18, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1998, she testified to Congress:
{{quote|It was my pseudonym, Jane Roe, which had been used to create the "right" to abortion out of legal thin air. But Sarah Weddington and Linda Coffee never told me that what I was signing would allow women to come up to me 15, 20 years later and say, "Thank you for allowing me to have my five or six abortions. Without you, it wouldn't have been possible." Sarah never mentioned women using abortions as a form of birth control. We talked about truly desperate and needy women, not women already wearing maternity clothes.&lt;ref name="testimony"/&gt;}}

As a party to the original litigation, she sought to reopen the case in [[United States district court|U.S. District Court]] in Texas to have ''Roe v. Wade'' overturned. However, the [[Fifth Circuit]] decided that her case was moot, in ''[[McCorvey v. Hill]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite court |litigants=McCorvey v. Hill |vol=385 |reporter=F.3d |opinion=846 |pinpoint= |court=5th Cir. |date=2004 |url=https://law.justia.com/cases/federal/appellate-courts/F3/385/846/582508/ |accessdate=May 17, 2018 |quote=}}&lt;/ref&gt; In a concurring opinion, Judge [[Edith Jones]] agreed that McCorvey was raising legitimate questions about emotional and other harm suffered by women who have had abortions, about increased resources available for the care of unwanted children, and about new scientific understanding of fetal development, but Jones said she was compelled to agree that the case was moot. On February 22, 2005, the Supreme Court refused to grant a [[certiorari|writ of certiorari]], and McCorvey's appeal ended.

=== Activities of Sarah Weddington ===
After arguing before the Court in ''Roe v. Wade'' at the age of 26, [[Sarah Weddington]] went on to be a representative in the Texas House of Representatives for three terms.&lt;ref name=Lapinski&gt;Valerie Lapinski, ''Winning Roe v. Wade: Q&amp;A with Sarah Weddington'', ''Time''  (January 22, 2013), ''available at'' http://nation.time.com/2013/01/22/winning-roe-v-wade-qa-with-sarah-weddington/.&lt;/ref&gt; Weddington has also had a long and successful career as General Counsel for the United States Department of Agriculture, Assistant to President Jimmy Carter, lecturer at Texas Wesleyan University, and speaker and adjunct professor at the University of Texas at Austin.&lt;ref name=Lapinski/&gt;

=== Presidential positions ===
President [[Richard Nixon]] did not publicly comment about the decision.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| last=Reeves| first=Richard | authorlink=Richard Reeves (American writer) |url=https://books.google.com/?id=AdBdPvGxdaIC&amp;pg=PA563 | title= President Nixon: Alone in the White House| page=563 |year=2001| isbn=978-0-684-80231-2| publisher=[[Simon &amp; Schuster]] |edition=1st |quote=The President did not comment directly on the decision.}}&lt;/ref&gt; In private conversation later revealed as part of the [[Nixon tapes]], Nixon said "There are times when an abortion is necessary,... ."&lt;ref name="nyt2009tapes"&gt;{{cite news | url=https://www.nytimes.com/2009/06/24/us/politics/24nixon.html | title=On Nixon Tapes, Ambivalence Over Abortion, Not Watergate | newspaper=The New York Times |last=Savage| first=Charlie |authorlink=Charlie Savage |date= June 23, 2009 | accessdate=July 18, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Harnden, Toby. [https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/northamerica/usa/5626338/President-Richard-Nixon-said-it-was-necessary-to-abort-mixed-race-babies-tapes-reveal.html "President Richard Nixon Said it Was 'Necessary' to Abort Mixed-Race Babies, Tapes Reveal,"] ''[[The Daily Telegraph]]'' (June 24, 2009).&lt;/ref&gt; However, Nixon was also concerned that greater access to abortions would foster "permissiveness," and said that "it breaks the family."&lt;ref name="nyt2009tapes"/&gt;

Generally, presidential opinion has been split between major party lines. The ''Roe'' decision was opposed by [[President of the United States|Presidents]] [[Gerald Ford]],&lt;ref&gt;Ford, Gerald. [http://www.presidency.ucsb.edu/ws/print.php?pid=6320 Letter to the Archbishop of Cincinnati], published online by The American Presidency Project. Santa Barbara, CA: University of California (September 10, 1976).&lt;/ref&gt; [[Ronald Reagan]],&lt;ref&gt;Reagan, Ronald. [[q:Ronald Reagan#Abortion and the Conscience of the Nation (1983)|Abortion and the Conscience of the Nation]] (Nelson 1984).&lt;/ref&gt; and [[George W. Bush]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Kornblut|first=Anne E.|url=http://graphics.boston.com/news/politics/campaign2000/news/Bush_tells_addicts_he_can_identify+.shtml|title=Bush Tells Addicts He Can Identify|newspaper=Boston Globe|page=A12|date=January 22, 2000}}&lt;/ref&gt; President [[George H.W. Bush]] also opposed ''Roe'', though he had supported abortion rights earlier in his career.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Fritz|first=Sara|url=http://articles.latimes.com/1992-08-18/news/mn-5874_1_abortion-rights-advocates/3|title='92 Republican Convention: Rigid Anti-Abortion Platform Plank OKd Policy|quote=President George Bush supported abortion rights until 1980, when he switched sides after Ronald Reagan picked Bush as his running mate.|newspaper=[[Los Angeles Times]]|date=August 18, 1992}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bush, George Herbert Walker.[http://www.presidency.ucsb.edu/ws/index.php?pid=16617 Remarks to Participants in the March for Life Rally] (January 23, 1989): "I think the Supreme Court's decision in Roe versus Wade was wrong and should be overturned."&lt;/ref&gt;

President [[Jimmy Carter]] supported legal abortion from an early point in his political career, in order to prevent birth defects and in other extreme cases; he encouraged the outcome in ''Roe'' and generally supported abortion rights.&lt;ref&gt;Carter, James Earl. ''Larry King Live'', CNN, [http://transcripts.cnn.com/TRANSCRIPTS/0602/01/lkl.02.html Interview With Jimmy Carter] (February 1, 2006). Also see [[Peter Bourne|Bourne, Peter]], ''Jimmy Carter: A Comprehensive Biography from Plains to Postpresidency'': "Early in his term as governor, Carter had strongly supported family planning programs including abortion in order to save the life of a woman, birth defects, or in other extreme circumstances. Years later, he had written the foreword to a book, ''Women in Need'', that favored a woman's right to abortion. He had given private encouragement to the plaintiffs in a lawsuit, ''Doe v. Bolton'', filed against the state of Georgia to overturn its archaic abortion laws."&lt;/ref&gt; ''Roe'' was also supported by President [[Bill Clinton]].&lt;ref&gt;Clinton, Bill. ''[[My Life (Bill Clinton autobiography)|My Life]]'', p. 229 (Knopf 2004).&lt;/ref&gt; President [[Barack Obama]] has taken the position that "Abortions should be legally available in accordance with ''Roe v. Wade''."&lt;ref&gt;Obama, Barack. [https://web.archive.org/web/20080922231441/http://www.votesmart.org/npat.php?old=true&amp;can_id=BS030017&amp;npatform_id=69 "1998 Illinois State Legislative National Political Awareness Test"], Project Vote Smart, via archive.org. Retrieved on January 21, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; 

President [[Donald Trump]] has publicly opposed the decision, vowing to appoint pro-life justices to the Supreme Court.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = https://www.cnn.com/2018/06/29/politics/abortion-roe-v-wade-supreme-court/index.html | title = The plan to overturn Roe v. Wade at the Supreme Court is already in motion | first=  Clare | last= Foran | date = June 29, 2018 | accessdate = June 29, 2018 | website = [[CNN]] }}{{dead link|date=October 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; Upon Justice Kennedy's retirement in 2018, Trump [[Brett Kavanaugh Supreme Court nomination|nominated]] [[Brett Kavanaugh]] to replace him, and he was confirmed by Congress in October 2018. A central point of Kavanaugh's appointment hearings was his stance on ''Roe V. Wade'', of which he said to Senator [[Susan Collins]] that he would not "overturn a long-established precedent if five current justices believed that it was wrongly decided".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = https://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2018/10/susan-collins-brett-kavanaugh-roe-v-wade/572344/ | title= Susan Collins Gambles With the Future of Roe v. Wade | first = Emma | last = Green | date = October 10, 2018 | accessdate = October 25, 2018 | work = [[The Atlantic]] }}&lt;/ref&gt; Despite Kavanaugh's statement, there is concern that with the Supreme Court having a strong conservative majority, that ''Roe v. Wade'' will be overturned given an appropriate case to challenge it. Pro-abortion organizations like Planned Parenthood are planning on how they will operate should ''Roe v. Wade'' be overturned.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = https://www.thenewamerican.com/culture/faith-and-morals/item/30443-planned-parenthood-prepares-for-overturning-of-roe-v-wade | title = Planned Parenthood Prepares for Overturning of Roe v. Wade | first = Lisa | last = Shaw | date = October 24, 2018 | accessdate = October 25, 2018 | work = [[The New American]] }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== State laws regarding ''Roe'' ===
[[File:Guttmacher Abortion Restrictions.SVG|thumb|upright=1.1|Since 2010 there has been an increase in state restrictions on abortion.]]

Several states have enacted so-called [[trigger law]]s which would take effect in the event that ''Roe v. Wade'' is overturned, with the effect of outlawing abortions on the state level. Those states include Arkansas, Illinois, Kentucky, Louisiana, Mississippi, North Dakota and South Dakota.&lt;ref name="Vestal"&gt;Vestal, Christine. [http://www.pewtrusts.org/en/research-and-analysis/blogs/stateline/2006/06/22/states-probe-limits-of-abortion-policy "States probe limits of abortion policy"], Stateline.org (June 11, 2007).&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, many states did not repeal pre-1973 statutes that criminalized abortion, and some of those statutes could again be in force if ''Roe'' were reversed.&lt;ref&gt;Marcus, Frances Frank. [https://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE5D71738F93BA35754C0A96F948260 "Louisiana Moves Against Abortion"], ''[[New York Times]]'' (July 8, 1989).&lt;/ref&gt;

Other states have passed laws to maintain the legality of abortion if ''Roe v. Wade'' is overturned. Those states include California, Connecticut, Hawaii, Maine, Maryland, Nevada and Washington.&lt;ref name="Vestal" /&gt;

The Mississippi Legislature has attempted to make abortion unfeasible without having to overturn ''Roe v. Wade''. The Mississippi law as of 2012 was being challenged in federal courts and was temporarily blocked.&lt;ref&gt;LZ Granderson [http://www.cnn.com/2012/07/11/opinion/granderson-mississippi-abortion/index.html?hpt=hp_c1 "Mississippi's end run around abortion"], ''[[CNN]]'' (July 12, 2012).&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[List of United States Supreme Court cases, volume 410]]

== Footnotes ==
{{Reflist}}

== References ==
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite book |last=Garrow |first=David J. |authorlink=David Garrow|title=Liberty and Sexuality: The Right to Privacy and the Making of Roe v. Wade |year=1994 |publisher=Macmillan |location=New York |isbn=978-0-02-542755-6 |ref=harv|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=9MlWAAAAIAAJ }}
* {{cite book |last=Greenhouse |first=Linda |authorlink=Linda Greenhouse |title=Becoming Justice Blackmun: Harry Blackmun's Supreme Court Journey |isbn=978-0-8050-7791-9 |year=2005 |publisher=[[Times Books]] |location=New York |ref=harv|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=NfqUtsNqx0MC }}
* {{cite journal |last=Malphurs |first=Ryan A. |year=2010 |title="People Did Sometimes Stick Things in my Underwear": The Function of Laughter at the U.S. Supreme Court |journal=Communication Law Review |volume=10 |issue=2 |pages=48–75 |doi= |url=http://commlawreview.org/Archives/CLRv10i2/The%20Function%20of%20Laughter%20at%20the%20U.S.%20Supreme%20Court%20CLR%20v10i2.pdf |accessdate=August 10, 2013 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Schwartz |first=Bernard |url=https://books.google.com/?id=gUMrsFFZtrQC&amp;pg=PA103| title=The Unpublished Opinions of the Burger Court |year=1988 |publisher=Oxford University Press |isbn=978-0-19-505317-3 |ref=harv}}
{{refend}}

==Further reading==
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite book |last=Critchlow |first=Donald T. |authorlink=Donald T. Critchlow |title=The Politics of Abortion and Birth Control in Historical Perspective |year=1996 |publisher=Pennsylvania State University Press |location=University Park, PA |isbn=978-0-271-01570-5|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=tMnznQEACAAJ }}
* {{cite book |last=Critchlow |first=Donald T.|title=Intended Consequences: Birth Control, Abortion, and the Federal Government in Modern America |year=1999 |publisher=Oxford University Press |location=New York |isbn=978-0-19-504657-1|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=krSRAAAAIAAJ}}
* {{cite book |last=Hull |first=N. E. H.|title=The Abortion Rights Controversy in America: A Legal Reader |year=2004 |publisher=University of North Carolina Press |location=Chapel Hill |isbn=978-0-8078-2873-1}}
* {{cite book |last=Hull |first=N. E. H.|author2=Peter Charles Hoffer  |title=Roe v. Wade: The Abortion Rights Controversy in American History |year=2001 |publisher=University Press of Kansas |location=Lawrence, KS |isbn=978-0-7006-1143-0|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=-MyPAAAAMAAJ}}
* {{cite book |last=Mohr |first=James C. |title=Abortion in America: The Origins and Evolution of National Policy, 1800–1900 |year=1979 |publisher=Oxford University Press |location=Oxford |isbn=978-0-19-502616-0|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=rnllmAEACAAJ }}
* {{cite book |last=Rubin |first=Eva R. [ed.] |title=The Abortion Controversy: A Documentary History |year=1994 |publisher=Greenwood |location=Westport, CT |isbn=978-0-313-28476-2|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=SU2QAAAAMAAJ }}
* {{cite book |last=Staggenborg |first=Suzanne |title=The Pro-Choice Movement: Organization and Activism in the Abortion Conflict |year=1994 |publisher=Oxford University Press |location=New York |isbn=978-0-19-506596-1 }}
{{refend}}

== External links ==
{{Spoken Wikipedia|Roe_vs_wade.ogg|2005-07-16}}
* {{Wikisource-inline|Roe v. Wade|''Roe v. Wade''}}
* {{caselaw source
 | case = ''Roe v. Wade'', {{ussc|410|113|1973|el=no}}
 | cornell =https://www.law.cornell.edu/supremecourt/text/410/113
 | courtlistener =https://www.courtlistener.com/opinion/108713/roe-v-wade/
 | findlaw = https://caselaw.findlaw.com/us-supreme-court/410/113.html
 | googlescholar = https://scholar.google.com/scholar_case?case=12334123945835207673
 | justia =https://supreme.justia.com/cases/federal/us/410/113/case.html
 | loc =http://cdn.loc.gov/service/ll/usrep/usrep410/usrep410113/usrep410113.pdf
 }}{{clarify span|text=.|explain=That link to Cornell seems to show no text of the case, whether viewed using any of 4 different types of browser.|date=July 2018}}
* The concurring opinions of Burger and Douglas, as well as White's dissenting opinion, were issued along with ''Doe v. Bolton'' and may be found at:
** [https://www.law.cornell.edu/supct/html/historics/USSC_CR_0410_0179_ZC1.html Cornell LLI]
* [https://www.oyez.org/sites/default/files/audio/cases/1971/70-18_19711213-argument.mp3 Audio of oral argument at www.oyez.org]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20121022102151/http://www.lawnix.com/cases/roe-wade.html Summary of ''Roe v. Wade'' at Lawnix.com]
* [http://constitution.laws.com/supreme-court-decisions/major-decisions-roe-v-wade Major Decisions-''Roe v Wade'']
* [http://landmarkcases.c-span.org/Case/12/Roe-V-Wade "Supreme Court Landmark Case ''Roe v. Wade''"] from [[C-SPAN]]'s ''[[Landmark Cases: Historic Supreme Court Decisions]]''

{{US14thAmendment|Due Process}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Roe V. Wade}}
[[Category:United States Supreme Court cases]]
[[Category:United States Supreme Court cases of the Burger Court]]
[[Category:United States abortion case law]]
[[Category:Right to abortion under the United States Constitution]]
[[Category:History of women's rights in the United States]]
[[Category:United States substantive due process case law]]
[[Category:1973 in United States case law]]
[[Category:American Civil Liberties Union litigation]]
[[Category:United States mootness case law]]
[[Category:Judicial activism]]
[[Category:Medical lawsuits]]
[[Category:United States privacy case law]]
[[Category:Right to privacy under the United States Constitution]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>