<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20171025183652|807072748" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="55313644" pageid="55313644" ns="0" title="Vegaphobia"><revisions><rev timestamp="2017-11-12T15:34:22Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{original research|date=September 2017}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2017}}
'''Vegaphobia''' (or '''vegephobia'''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://yves-bonnardel.info/fr/brochure-la-vegephobie|title=Brochure «La végéphobie...»  - Yves Bonnardel|author=|date=|website=yves-bonnardel.info}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.vice.com/fr/article/bnqd3d/report-veggie-pride-paris|title=Les végétariens de France se battent contre « l’holocauste animal »|author=|date=23 May 2014|website=vice.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://jolacora.wordpress.com/2014/01/13/vegephobia-article/|title=Vegephobia is Speciesism|author=|date=13 January 2014|website=wordpress.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;) is the aversion to and discrimination against vegetarian and [[vegan]] people.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/j.1468-4446.2010.01348.x/abstract|title=Vegaphobia: derogatory discourses of veganism and the reproduction of speciesism in UK national newspapers1|first1=Matthew|last1=Cole|first2=Karen|last2=Morgan|date=1 March 2011|publisher=|journal=The British Journal of Sociology|volume=62|issue=1|pages=134–153|via=Wiley Online Library|doi=10.1111/j.1468-4446.2010.01348.x}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.veggiepride.it/index.php/documenti/127-repetita|title=Repetita juvant: cos'è la vegefobia|author=|date=|website=www.veggiepride.it}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://ar-conference.org/2013/details.php?id=44|title=Vegephobia, what is it? Why is it important to fight it? (Jola Cora) [IARC2013]|author=|date=|website=ar-conference.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==

Some of the oldest episodes of aversion can be found in the 3rd and 4th centuries when [[Ancient Greek comedy|Greek comedies]] are written where [[Pythagoras]] is despised of his choice of not eating meat.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.researchgate.net/publication/241657832_Fish_Flesh_and_Foul_The_Anti-Vegetarian_Animus|title=Fish, Flesh, and Foul: The Anti-Vegetarian Animus|author=|date=|website=ResearchGate}}&lt;/ref&gt;

They then have episodes of persecution of vegetarians in China in the twelfth century as well as in the [[Middle Ages|European medieval]], where they were branded as [[heretics]] and persecuted by the [[Holy Inquisition]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.researchgate.net/publication/303439414_Resolving_the_Meat-Paradox_A_Motivational_Account_of_Morally_Troublesome_Behavior_and_Its_Maintenance|title=Resolving the Meat-Paradox: A Motivational Account of Morally Troublesome Behavior and Its Maintenance|author=|date=|website=ResearchGate}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.researchgate.net/publication/273833620_Meat_traditions_The_co-evolution_of_humans_and_meat|title=Meat traditions. The co-evolution of humans and meat|author=|date=|website=ResearchGate}}&lt;/ref&gt; These persecutions are also detailed in the essay Pythagora's Supper by Erica Joy Mannucci.

In recent times, [[Nazi Germany]] became the protagonist of the vegetarian persecution. When he came to power in 1933, [[Hitler]] infiltrated all vegetarian associations in Germany, detained executives, and closed the main vegetarian magazines published in [[Frankfurt]]. Nazi persecution forced vegetarians to leave the country or enter into secret. A German vegetarian, [[Edgar Kupfer-Koberwitz]], fled to Paris and then to Italy where he was arrested by the [[Gestapo]] and sent to the [[Dachau]] [[concentration camp]]. During the war, Nazi Germany banned all vegetarians in the territories occupied by it, though vegetarian diets could have contributed to alleviating the famine of the war time.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ilgiornale.it/news/cronache/hitler-e-carne-evitava-faceva-arrestare-i-vegetariani-1132601.html|title=Hitler e la carne: la evitava ma faceva arrestare i vegetariani|author=|date=|website=ilgiornale.it}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Using the term ===

It is in the 21st that it began to frame the phenomenon in the sociological sphere and makes its appearance "vegaphobia". In 2007, a survey called "Vegaphobia: disproportionate talk about [[veganism]] in British national newspapers" took place in the United Kingdom, which examined 397 articles containing the terms "vegan", "vegans" and "veganism". That's what the researchers found was that 74.3% of the items are classified as "negatives"; 20.2% "neutral" and only 5.5% "positive". Negative items were in order of frequency: ridiculing veganism; characterize veganism as [[asceticism]]; affirming that veganism is difficult or impossible to sustain; describe veganism as a fashion; portray vegans as sentimentalists; defining vegans as hostile.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thescavenger.net/social-justice-sp-24912/animals/738-vegaphobia-media-eats-veganism.html|title=Vegaphobia: media eats veganism|author=|date=|website=thescavenger.net}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2010, the book "Some we love, some who hate, some who eat: because it is so hard to think directly about animals" is published by Hal Herzog. The fourth chapter focuses on vegaphobia entitled "Veganism, veganorexia and vegaphobia: women, choice, and eating policy".&lt;ref name="google1"&gt;{{cite web|url=https://books.google.it/books/about/Some_We_Love_Some_We_Hate_Some_We_Eat.html?id=5yjzWUckNIMC&amp;redir_esc=y|title=Some We Love, Some We Hate, Some We Eat: Why It's So Hard to Think Straight About Animals|first=Hal|last=Herzog|date=9 August 2011|publisher=Harper Collins|via=Google Books}}&lt;/ref&gt; The chapter's analysis is also reported in the book of 2015 "The Vegan Studies Project: Food, Animals and Gender in the Eternal of Terror "by Laura Wright.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://books.google.it/books?hl=it&amp;lr=&amp;id=gwPaCgAAQBAJ&amp;oi=fnd&amp;pg=PR11&amp;dq=vegaphobia+-derogatory&amp;ots=4Yy4d6Rz1d&amp;sig=nZJ4vw-Li7w1BMz2xEJj9Ku-wms#v=onepage&amp;q=vegaphobia&amp;f=false|title=The Vegan Studies Project: Food, Animals, and Gender in the Age of Terror|first=Laura|last=Wright|date=1 October 2015|publisher=University of Georgia Press|via=Google Books}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Other uses of the term vegaphobia can be found mainly in Europe during conferences such as that held in August 2011 by Sara Fergé, titled "Social Violence against Vegetarianism for Animals and Vegaphobia Analysis" during the "Summer Animal Issues" "held in Marlhes de [[la Loire]], France.&lt;ref&gt;http://brigitte-bardot.over-blog.net/archive/2011-07/5&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2012 Christophe Traïni in the scientific text "Between disgust and moral indignation: the socio-genesis of a practicing activist" speaks of [[vegans]] and anti-peoples become an "oppressed minority" rebelled against vegephobia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.cairn-int.info/article-E_RFSP_624_0559--between-disgust-and-moral-indignation.htm|title=Between disgust and moral indignation|first1=Christophe|last1=Traïni|first2=Katharine|last2=Throssell|date=|via=cairn-int.info|journal=Revue française de science politique|volume=Vol. 62|issue=4}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the same year he also talks about Kay Peggs in the book "Animal Consumption".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1057/9780230377271_6|title=Animals and Sociology|first=Kay|last=Peggs|date=6 October 2017|publisher=Palgrave Macmillan, London|pages=90–106|via=link.springer.com|doi=10.1057/9780230377271_6}}&lt;/ref&gt;

At the Animal Rights Conference in [[Luxembourg]] in 2013, actress and producer Jola Cora, organizer of the first Vega International, exposed the phenomenon in an intervention called "Vegaphobia, what is it?"&lt;ref name="youtube1"&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Tucw3cCzjLc|title=Vegephobia, what is it? Jola Cora at IARC 2013 Luxembourg|first=|last=VeganKanal|date=12 September 2013|publisher=|via=YouTube}}&lt;/ref&gt; Also in the same year spoke French philosopher Yves Bonnardel in his speech titled "Vegaphobia" at [[Veggie Pride]] International in [[Genoa]], Switzerland.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.veggiepride.it/index.php/news|title=News|author=|date=|website=www.veggiepride.it}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2014 they talk about Andrea Romeo and Ivonne Citarella in the text "The Network and the Spread of Anti-Species Culture" describing the phenomenon of vegaphobia as the "superficial and derisory" attitude of those who focus on vegan lifestyle rather than real motivations that lead to this choice. " It can also be noted that proliferation of "anti-veg" groups is called "specist".&lt;ref name="google2"&gt;{{cite web|url=https://books.google.it/books?id=aIkmBAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT47&amp;lpg=PT47&amp;dq=vegephobia&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=MyG2e-kbyF&amp;sig=u40WhEZDboQRxoOjeu4A1IL21ls&amp;hl=it&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwjpxaSW3anWAhWDvhQKHQWvCmY4FBDoAQg1MAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=vegefobia&amp;f=false|title=La rete e la diffusione della cultura antispecista|first1=Andrea|last1=Romeo|first2=Ivonne|last2=Citarella|date=1 August 2014|publisher=goWare|via=Google Books}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the same year, Queer Vegan Manifesto was published, where Rasmus R. Simonsen argues that vegaphobia is linked to [[homophobia]] because "homophobic speech feeds vegaphobia, since the choice of eating differently, for males in particular, is linked to 'effeminacy and lack of virility'.&lt;ref name="bepress1"&gt;https://works.bepress.com/rasmus_simonsen/3/download/&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2016 [[Radio Radicale]] was broadcasting an interview with Silvia Molè on censorship of [[antispecism]] and vegephobia by Cristiana Pugliese.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.radioradicale.it/scheda/485397/intervista-a-silvia-mole-sulla-censura-verso-lantispecismo-e-sulla-vegefobia|title=Intervista a Silvia Molè sulla censura verso l'antispecismo e sulla vegefobia|first=Radio|last=Radicale|date=5 September 2016|website=radioradicale.it}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the same year, always in Italy, he also spoke of vegefobia also Radio Onda Rossa.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.ondarossa.info/tag/vegefobia|title=vegefobia - Radio Onda Rossa|author=|date=|website=www.ondarossa.info}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2017, the "[[Plant-based diet |Plant-Based Nutrition]]: An Essential Component of [[Cardiovascular Disease]] Prevention and Management" research is published where vegaphobia is described as the stereotypical attitude of vegans as "[[ascetics]], fashionists, sentimentalists, and in some cases hostile [[extremists]]" .&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s11886-017-0909-z|title=Plant-Based Nutrition: An Essential Component of Cardiovascular Disease Prevention and Management|first1=Hena|last1=Patel|first2=Sonal|last2=Chandra|first3=Sarah|last3=Alexander|first4=Jeffrey|last4=Soble|first5=Kim Allan|last5=Williams|date=1 October 2017|publisher=|journal=Current Cardiology Reports|volume=19|issue=10|pages=104|via=link.springer.com|doi=10.1007/s11886-017-0909-z|pmid=28887684}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Episodes of Vegaphobia==


===Italy===
One of the most striking episodes of vegafobia in Italy was staged by chef Gianfranco Vissani, guest in "In Onda" on La7, saying: "Vegans are a sect. I'll kill them all." &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ilgiornale.it/news/cronache/gianfranco-vissani-i-vegani-sono-setta-li-ammazzerei-tutti-1297604.html|title=Gianfranco Vissani: "I vegani sono una setta. Li ammazzerei tutti"|author=|date=|website=ilgiornale.it}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The conductor Alessandro Cecchi Paone stated during the episode of 10 April 2017 of the TV show "Quinta Colonna" that those who grow without eating meat become "fat and ugly". This appears to be scientifically false and discriminatory, contradicting the positions of the [[Academy of Nutrition and Dietetics]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.eatrightpro.org/resource/practice/position-and-practice-papers/position-papers/vegetarian-diets|title=Vegetarian Diets|author=|date=|website=www.eatrightpro.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;

MP Maurizio Bianconi during the ECG Region format stated on Radio Cusano Campus: "Vegans are ill if I had a vegan grandchild kicks her parents."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.meteoweb.eu/2016/03/show-del-deputato-bianconi-i-vegani-sono-malati-se-avessi-un-nipotino-vegano-prenderei-a-calci-i-suoi-genitori/660024/|title=Show del deputato Bianconi: "I vegani sono malati, se avessi un nipotino vegano prenderei a calci i suoi genitori"|first=Filomena|last=Fotia|date=30 March 2016|website=meteoweb.eu}}&lt;/ref&gt; The statement is intended to define anyone who follows a plant diet and contradicts the [[science|scientific]] positions already cited as it proves that the [[vegan]] diet is not intrinsically harmful. There is also an incitement to hatred and violence against other people.

Anna Oliverio Ferraris, a professor of psychology at [[La Sapienza University]] in Rome, said during an interview that veganism can be considered a "[[mental disorder]]". The motivation is that it causes "fractures among people" while the allegation to vegans is that they "feel pure and often despise those who do not like them."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wired.it/lifestyle/food/2014/04/18/la-psicologia-del-vegetariano|title=La psicologia del vegetariano - Wired|author=|date=18 April 2014|website=wired.it}}&lt;/ref&gt; This seems to be an obvious simplification of the phenomenon and a generalization not supported by any scientific data, which results in discrimination of those who follow a vegan diet.

A woman in [[Grosseto]] was physically assaulted by her daughter's classmates' parents because she was accused of bad influence, precisely because of the diet followed by her mother and daughter. In fact, the latter explained to his companions the ethical reasons of his diet, triggering the reaction of their parents.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://iltirreno.gelocal.it/grosseto/cronaca/2017/03/23/news/una-mamma-denuncia-io-aggredita-perche-mia-figlia-e-vegetariana-1.15077669|title=Una mamma denuncia: Io, aggredita perché mia figlia è vegetariana  - Cronaca - il Tirreno|author=|date=23 March 2017|website=gelocal.it}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Rome, a woman who opened a vegan activity at the open market in [[Testaccio]] was physically assaulted by butchers and fisherman and her banquet was overthrown.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.romatoday.it/cronaca/aggressione-vegana-mercato-testaccio-banco.html|title=Mercato Testaccio: "Io aggredita perché ho un banco vegano"|author=|date=|website=romatoday.it}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://roma.repubblica.it/cronaca/2015/11/06/news/la_lav_al_mercato_di_testaccio_una_banchista_vegana_aggredita_da_una_pescivendola_-126783897/|title=La Lav: "Al mercato di Testaccio una banchista vegana aggredita da una pescivendola"|author=|date=6 November 2015|website=repubblica.it}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2016, a politician proposed a decree to ban the vegan diet to children and arrest their parents.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.com/news/world-europe-37034619|title=Vegan parents targeted by Italy bill|author=|date=10 August 2016|publisher=|via=www.bbc.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===France===
A decree was issued to ban the children from eating [[vegan]]. The decree was severely criticized by the animalist associations and the singing [[Paul McCartney]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.icdv.info/index.php?post/2011/12/02/Déclaration-de-Paul-McCartney-au-sujet-du-décret-français&lt;/ref&gt;  The reasons given for the protection of children's health contradict scientific positions on the absence of intrinsic harmfulness of the vegan diet.

In October 2008, MEP Yves Cochet, proposing to the National Assembly for measures to reduce the consumption of meat, felt compelled to reassure the interlocutors by saying, "I am not a vegetarian integralist."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://2007-2012.nosdeputes.fr/seance/466|title=Séance en hémicycle du 9 octobre 2008 à 21h45 : NosDeputes.fr|author=|date=|website=2007-2012.nosdeputes.fr}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2013, a child of only 7 months was taken away from his parents by social services because his mother is vegan.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.millebabords.org/spip.php?article24035|title=« Moi Joachim, 7 mois, condamné à la détention, privé de mes parents depuis le 11 juin car ma mère est végétarienne - Mille Babords|author=|date=|website=www.millebabords.org}}&lt;/ref&gt; The case created a great stir in France and started petitions. It was also reported by actress and producer Jola Cora during the Animal Rights Conference of 2013 held in [[Luxembourg]] during the "Vegafobia, what is it?".&lt;ref name="youtube1"/&gt; Once again, action is generated by the ignorance of scientific positions about it, fueling the commonplace that sees the vegan diet as intrinsically damaging.

===United Kingdom===
In [[Hatfield, Hertfordshire|Hatfield]], a 12-year-old [[vegan]] student who has been bullied has committed [[suicide]]. His companions insulted him by throwing him on pieces of [[meat]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mirror.co.uk/news/uk-news/schoolboy-12-found-hanged-after-11255073.amp|title=Schoolboy found hanged after 'class bullies threw meat at him for being vegan'|author=|date=28 September 2017|website=mirror.co.uk}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Greece===
A couple on the island of [[Crete]] was prevented from adopting a baby because of their vegetarian diet.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.news.com.au/lifestyle/real-life/vegetarian-couple-barred-from-adopting-in-greece/news-story/d5f44aeed78306a996acd0cf9150ca50|title=Vegetarian couple barred from adopting|author=|date=|website=news.com.au}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Georgia===
In [[Tiblisi]] was destroyed a vegan restaurant. Employees, who were beaten, said: "The fact of not eating meat is considered out of the world."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.it/2016/06/01/caffe-vegano-assalto-sals_n_10236044.html|title=Attacco a colpi di salsiccia a un caffè vegano di Tbilisi, in Georgia. "Sono neonazisti, ci considerano fuori dal mondo"|author=|date=1 June 2016|website=huffingtonpost.it}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Poland===
Foreign Minister Witold Waszczykowski said: "Vegetarians are the [[symbol]] of a marching Europe against which we must fight."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://wroclawuncut.com/2016/01/04/foreign-minister-in-cyclists-vegetarians-slur/|title=Foreign Minister In "Cyclists &amp; Vegetarians" Slur|author=|date=|website=wroclawuncut.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.economist.com/news/europe/21685201-new-law-lets-government-purge-public-broadcaster-polandu2019s-new-government-dislikes|title=Poland’s new government dislikes critical media, vegetarians and cyclists|author=|date=|website=economist.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Australia===
One student in [[Melbourne]] was forced to leave the campus after repeated harassment. They left her a horse's heart in front of the door, spread the chicken on the window and dumped raw meat in her room while she slept.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-4951930/Vegan-student-raw-meat-thrown-her.html&lt;/ref&gt;

== Bibliography ==
*{{cite book| first=Lorenzo | last=Guadagnucci | title=Restiamo animali | date=2012 | publisher=Terre di mezzo | isbn= 978-88-6189-224-8 }}
* {{cite book|author=Charles Patterson|title=Un'eterna Treblinka. Il massacro degli animali e l'Olocausto|publisher=Editori Riuniti|date=2003|isbn= 978-8835953241}}
*{{cite book | last=Mannucci | first=Erica Joy | title=La cena di Pitagora. Storia del vegetarianismo dall'antica Grecia a Internet  | publisher=Carocci editore| date=2008 | isbn =978-88-430-4574-7 }}
*{{cite book | last=Cole | first=Matthew | title=Vegafobia: discorsi dispregiativi sul veganismo nei giornali nazionali britannici  | date=2011  }}
*{{cite book | last=Sigler | first=Pierre | title=L'exploitation animale est une question de société   }}
*{{cite book | last=Oliver | first=David | title=Vegephobia is Speciesism   }}
*{{cite book | last=Romeo | first=Andrea | title=La rete e la diffusione della cultura antispecista| date=2014  }}&lt;ref name="google2"/&gt;
*{{cite book| first=Christophe | last=Traïni | title=Between disgust and moral indignation: The socio-genesis of an activist practice | date=2012 | publisher=Presses de Sciences Po | isbn=978-27-2463-260-6 }}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.cairn-int.info/resume.php?ID_ARTICLE=E_RFSP_624_0559|title=Between disgust and moral indignation|first1=Christophe|last1=Traïni|first2=Katharine|last2=Throssell|date=|journal=Revue française de science politique|volume=Vol. 62|issue=4}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*{{cite book| first=Hal | last=Herzog | title=Some We Love, Some We Hate, Some We Eat: Why It's So Hard to Think Straight About Animals | date=2011 | publisher=HarperCollins | isbn= 978-00-6173-085-6 }}&lt;ref name="google1"/&gt;
*{{cite book| first=Massimo | last=Filippi | title=Manifesto Queer Vegan | date=2014 | publisher=Ortica Editrice }}&lt;ref name="bepress1"/&gt;

== References ==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

{{Animal rights}}
{{Discrimination}}

[[Category:Hatred]]
[[Category:Phobias]]
[[Category:Prejudices]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>