<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20111019173143|456383933" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="102866" pageid="102866" ns="0" title="Gay bashing"><revisions><rev timestamp="2011-10-29T19:32:55Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Discrimination sidebar}}
'''Gay bashing''' and '''gay bullying''' is [[verbal abuse|verbal]] or [[physical abuse]] against a person who is perceived to be  [[gay]], [[lesbian]], [[bisexual]], or [[transgender]] ([[LGBT]]). Such abuse is used also to [[bullying|bully]] [[heterosexual]] persons and persons of non-specific or unknown [[sexual orientation]].

A "bashing" may be a specific incident, and one could also use the verb ''to bash'' (e.g. "I was gay bashed."). A verbal gay bashing might use sexual slurs, expletives, intimidation, or threats of violence. It also might take place in a political forum and include one or more common [[anti-gay slogan]]s.

Gay bullying involves intentional and unprovoked actions toward the victim, repeated negative actions by one or more people against another person, and an imbalance of physical or psychological power.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|publisher=US Dept of Education|title=Bullying Myths and Facts|accessdate=Oct 2 2010|url=http://www2.ed.gov/admins/lead/safety/training/bullying/bullying_pg3.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; Similar terms such as ''lesbian bullying'', ''[[queer]] bullying'', and ''queer bashing'' may also be formed.

==Historical incidents==
{{Expand section|date=December 2010}}
Gay bashing has occurred worldwide for many decades and continues today.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|first=Thomas|last=Rogers|url=http://www.salon.com/life/lgbt/index.html?story=/books/feature/2010/12/12/lgbt_bullying_interview|title=Explaining American schools' gay bullying epidemic|publisher=Salon.com|accessdate=12 December 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Homophobia]] in the [[United States]] was especially serious in the late 1940s and early 1950s, when many gay people were forced out of government by boards set up by presidents [[Harry S. Truman]] and [[Dwight Eisenhower]]. As historian David K. Johnson explains:&lt;ref name="uchicago"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.press.uchicago.edu/Misc/Chicago/404811in.html|publisher=University of Chicago Press|title=An interview with David K. Johnson}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|The [[Lavender Scare]] helped fan the flames of the [[Red Scare]]. In popular discourse, [[communist]]s and homosexuals were often conflated. Both groups were perceived as hidden [[subculture]]s with their own meeting places, literature, cultural codes, and bonds of loyalty. Both groups were thought to recruit to their ranks the psychologically weak or disturbed. And both groups were considered immoral and godless. Many people believed that the two groups were working together to undermine the government.}}

Johnson concludes that Senator [[Joe McCarthy]], notorious for his attacks on alleged Communists in government, was often pressured by his allies to denounce homosexuals in government, but he resisted and did not do so.&lt;ref name="uchicago" /&gt; Using rumors collected by [[Drew Pearson (journalist)|Drew Pearson]], one [[Nevada]] publisher wrote in 1952 that both McCarthy and his chief counsel, [[Roy Cohn]], were homosexuals.&lt;ref group="note"&gt;After McCarthy called him an ex-Communist, [[Hank Greenspun]] wrote: "It is common talk among homosexuals in [[Milwaukee]] who rendezvous in the White Horse Inn that Senator Joe McCarthy has often engaged in homosexual activities." [[Las Vegas Sun]], October 25, 1952. McCarthy later explained he meant to call Greenspun an ex-convict (which was true), rather than an ex-Communist (which was false).&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Washington Post]]'' editor [[Benjamin C. Bradlee]] said, "There was a lot of time spent investigating" these allegations, "although no one came close to proving it."  No reputable McCarthy biographer has accepted it as probable.&lt;ref group="note"&gt;The allegations are specifically rejected in Richard Rovere, ''Senator Joe McCarthy'' (1969), p. 68; see also Robert D. Dean, ''Imperial Brotherhood: Gender and the Making of Cold War Foreign Policy'' (2001) p. 149 (includes Bradlee quote); Kyle A. Cuordileone, ''Manhood and American Political Culture in the Cold War'' (2003), p. 94; Thomas Patrick Doherty, ''Cold War, Cool Medium: Television, McCarthyism, and American Culture,'' (2003), p. 228. Geoff Schumacher, ''Sun, Sin &amp; Suburbia: An Essential History of Modern Las Vegas'' (2004), p. 144, concludes, "Greenspun descended into mud-spewing rhetoric that would make the [[National Enquirer]] blanch."&lt;/ref&gt;

==Statistics and examples==
Teens faced harassment, threats, and violence. In the US, students heard anti-gay slurs such as “homo”, “faggot” and “sissy” about 26 times a day on average, or once every 14 minutes, according to a 1998 study by [[Mental Health America]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Mental Health American, Bullying and Gay Youth|url=http://www.nmha.org/go/information/get-info/children-s-mental-health/bullying-and-gay-youth|publisher=[[National Mental Health Association]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

About two-thirds of gay and lesbian students in [[United Kingdom|Britain]]’s schools have suffered from gay bullying, a survey by the Schools Health Education Unit found.  Almost all that had been bullied had experience verbal attacks, 41 percent had been physically attacked, and 17 percent had received death threats.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|publisher=BBC News|title=Gay Bullying in Schools Common|date=June 26, 2007|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/6239098.stm}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There is a high rate of [[suicide]] [[suicide among LGBT youth|among gay men and lesbian women]]. According to a 1979 Jay and Young study, 40 percent of gay men and 39 percent of gay women in the US had attempted or seriously thought about suicide.&lt;ref name="ncmh" /&gt; In 1985, F. Paris estimated that suicides by gay youth may comprise up to 30 percent of all youth suicides in the US.&lt;ref name="ncmh"&gt;{{cite web |title=Gay Male and Lesbian Youth Suicide |year=1989 |url=http://www.ncmhjj.com/resource_kit/pdfs/Special%20Issues/References/GayMaleLesSuic.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[American Foundation for Suicide Prevention]] has found that gay, lesbian and bisexual youth attempt suicide at a rate three to six times that of similar-age heterosexual youth.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|publisher=[[American Foundation for Suicide Prevention]]|accessdate=Oct 2 2010|url=http://www.afsp.org/index.cfm?fuseaction=home.viewPage&amp;page_ID=CF7F9E5B-BF4B-52F3-4D4079E9991163DC|title=Statistics}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Cases===
* In 1996, Jamie Nabozny won a landmark lawsuit against officials at his former public high school in [[Ashland, Wisconsin]] over their refusal to intervene in the "relentless antigay verbal and physical abuse by fellow students" to which he had been subjected and which had resulted in his hospitalization.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|publisher=[[Lambda Legal]]|url=http://www.lambdalegal.org/in-court/cases/nabozny-v-podlesny.html|title=Nabozny v. Podlesny|accessdate=12 December 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* [[Damilola Taylor]] was attacked by a local gang of youths on 27 November 2000 in Peckham, south London; he bled to death after being stabbed with a broken bottle in the thigh, which severed the femoral artery. The BBC, Telegraph, Guardian and Independent newspapers reported at the time that during the weeks between arriving in the UK from [[Nigeria]] and the attack he had been subjected to bullying and beating, which included homophobic remarks by a group of boys at his school. "The bullies told him that he was gay."&lt;ref name="BBCDAM"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/africa/1048449.stm|title=Damilola's grieving father speaks out|publisher=BBC News|date=30 Nov 2000}}&lt;/ref&gt; He "may not have understood why he was being bullied at school, or why some other children taunted him about being 'gay' – the word meant nothing to him."&lt;ref name="GUADAM" /&gt; He had to ask his mother what 'gay' meant, she said "Boys were swearing at him, saying lots of horrible words. They were calling him names."&lt;ref name="GUADAM"&gt;{{Cite news|last=Hopkins|first=Nick|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/uk/2000/nov/29/ukcrime.nickhopkins|title=Death of a schoolboy|newspaper=The Guardian|date=29 Nov 2000}}&lt;/ref&gt; His mother had spoken about this bullying, but the teachers failed to take it seriously. "She said pupils had accused her son of being gay and had beaten him last Friday."&lt;ref name="INDAM"&gt;{{Cite news|last=Bennetto|first=Jason|url=http://www.independent.co.uk/news/uk/home-news/his-mother-told-teachers-he-was-being-bullied-now-she-must-bury-him-622144.html|title=His mother told teachers he was being bullied. Now she must bury him| newspaper=Independent|date=29 Nov 2000}}&lt;/ref&gt; Six months after the murder, his father said, "I spoke to him and he was crying that he was being bullied and being called names. He was being called 'gay'."&lt;ref name="TELDAM"&gt;{{Cite news|last=Steele|first=John|url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/uknews/1377304/Damilolas-father-attacks-loss-of-values.html|title=Damilola's father attacks loss of values|newspaper=[[The Daily Telegraph|The Telegraph]]|date=19 June 2001}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the New Statesman two years later, when there had still been no convictions for the crime, Peter Tatchell, gay human rights campaigner, said, "In the days leading up to his murder in south London in November 2000, he was subjected to vicious homophobic abuse and assaults,"&lt;ref name="NSDAM"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Tatchell|first=Peter|url=http://www.newstatesman.com/200301130014|title=A victim of homophobia?|journal=New Statesman|date=13 Jan 2003}}&lt;/ref&gt; and asked why the authorities had ignored this before and after his death.

* In 2009, Carl Joseph Walker Hoover, an 11-year old boy in [[Springfield, Massachusetts]], hanged himself with an electrical cord.  His mother said his classmates at his middle school had bullied and called him “gay” on a daily basis.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|publisher=WCVB TV, Boston|title=Hoover|accessdate=Oct 20 2010|url=http://www.thebostonchannel.com/r/19137836/detail.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* In 2010, a gay man from [[Cameroon]], an [[Africa]]n nation, was granted asylum in the [[United Kingdom]] after reporting that he had been attacked by an angry mob in Cameroon after they saw him kissing his male partner. The Communications Minister of Cameroon, Issa Tchiroma, denied the allegation of persecution of homosexuals.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|publisher=BBC News|title=Cameroon Denies Homosexuals Face Persecution|date=July 8, 2010|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/10550576}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* [[Tyler Clementi]] committed suicide on September 22, 2010, after his roommate at [[Rutgers University]] filmed him having a sexual encounter with another male and posted the footage online.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Hu|first=Winnie|date=October 1, 2010|title=Debate Over Charges in Rutgers Student’s Suicide|publisher=The New York Times|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2010/10/02/nyregion/02suicide.html|accessdate=2010-10-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* A 32-year old man in Paisley, [[Scotland]] was bullied and harassed by his employer a [[Glasgow]] publishing firm, before he was fired.  He later sued the company and won a £120,000 award.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|publisher=BBC News|title=Harassed gay man’s  £120,000 award|date=Oct 2, 2010|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/scotland/glasgow_and_west/6353609.stm}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* On October 14, 2011, Canadian teenager Jamie Hubley, the son of [[Ottawa]] city councillor [[Allan Hubley]], committed suicide after having [[blog]]ged for a month about the anti-gay bullying he was facing at school.&lt;ref name=lonely&gt;[http://www.ottawacitizen.com/sports/year+Jamie+Hubley+documented+heartbreaking+need+acceptance/5559352/story.html "15-year-old Jamie Hubley's lonely cry for acceptance"]. ''[[Ottawa Citizen]]'', October 17, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; The bullying had begun as early as Grade 7, with students on Jamie's bus attempting to stuff [[Battery (electricity)|batteries]] in his mouth because he preferred [[figure skating]] over [[ice hockey|hockey]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thestar.com/news/canada/article/1072227--mallick-meet-the-boy-the-bullies-broke?bn=1 "Mallick: Meet the boy the bullies broke"]. ''[[Toronto Star]]'', October 18, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legislation==
{{Expand section|date=December 2010}}
The state of [[Illinois]] passed a law (SB3266) in June 2010 that prohibits gay bullying and other forms of bullying in schools.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=SB3266 Text|url=http://www.ilga.gov/legislation/fulltext.asp?DocName=&amp;SessionId=76&amp;GA=96&amp;DocTypeId=SB&amp;DocNum=3266&amp;GAID=10&amp;LegID=51081&amp;SpecSess=&amp;Session=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Support==
In response to growing awareness of gay bashing and bullying, a number of support groups have been founded to help LGBT persons cope with their abuse.{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}} In Europe [[Stonewall UK]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|publisher=Uk gay news|title=Stonewall, Mayor of London Launch Anti-Homophobic Bullying DVD|accessdate=Aug 21 2011|url=http://www.ukgaynews.org.uk/archive/2006july/0401.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt; BeLonG To LGBT organisation&lt;ref&gt;http://www.belongto.org/pro/default.aspx&lt;/ref&gt;{{Failed verification|date=August 2011}} and Anti-Bullying Network&lt;ref&gt;http://www.antibullying.net/homophobicinfo3.htm&lt;/ref&gt; are active in the [[UK]], while [[Russia]] has the [[Russian LGBT network]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|publisher=Ilga|title=The Russian LGBT Network|accessdate=Aug 21 2011|url=http://ilga-europe.org/home/how_we_work/developing/projects/russian_project/the_russian_lgbt_network}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Failed verification|date=August 2011}}

Notable in the [[US]] is the [[It Gets Better Project]], for which celebrities and ordinary LGBT people make [[YouTube]] videos and share messages of hope for gay teens.&lt;ref name="CNET"&gt;{{cite web|publisher=CNET|title=CBS employees join the It Gets Better Project|accessdate=Aug 21 2011|url=http://news.cnet.com/8301-1023_3-20072421-93/cbs-employees-join-the-it-gets-better-project/}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="MTV"&gt;{{cite web|publisher=MTV|title=Adam Lambert Revamps 'Aftermath' for The Trevor Project|accessdate=Aug 21 2011|url=http://act.mtv.com/posts/adam-lambert-revamps-aftermath-for-the-trevor-project/}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="NPR"&gt;{{cite web|publisher=NPR|title=Dan Savage: For Gay Teens, Life 'Gets Better'|accessdate=Aug 21 2011|url=http://www.npr.org/2011/03/23/134628750/dan-savage-for-gay-teens-life-gets-better}}&lt;/ref&gt; The organization works with USA, The Trevor Project&lt;ref name="MTV"/&gt; and the [[Gay, Lesbian and Straight Education Network]].&lt;ref name="NPR"/&gt; The Safe Schools Coalition provides resources for teachers and students where bullying is a problem. Egale Canada works with LGBT [[Canadian]] citizens.&lt;ref name="City news"&gt;{{cite web|publisher=City news|title=Gay Rights Organization Egale Canada Applauds Decision On Dire Straits Song|accessdate=Aug 21 2011|url=http://www.citytv.com/toronto/citynews/entertainment/news/article/107785--gay-rights-organization-egale-canada-applauds-decision-on-dire-straits-song}}&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Brazil]], the Gay Group of Bahia (Grupo Gay da Bahia) provides support.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ggb.org.br/ggb-ingles.html&lt;/ref&gt;{{Failed verification|date=August 2011}} LGBT [[South African]]s can turn to the South African Human Rights Commission.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.sahrc.org.za/home/index.php?ipkContentID=1&amp;ipkMenuID=28&lt;/ref&gt;{{Failed verification|date=August 2011}}

==See also==
{{Portal box|LGBT}}
* [[Abuse]]
* [[Bullying]]
* [[Cyberbullying]]
* [[Bash Back!]]
* [[List of LGBT rights organizations]]
* [[School bullying]]
* [[Anti-LGBT slogans]]
* [[Hate crime]]
* [[Trans bashing]]
* [[Violence against LGBT people]]

==Notes==
&lt;references group="note" /&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

==Further reading==
* {{cite book |title=Sexual Bullying: Gender Conflict and Pupil Culture in Secondary Schools |last=Duncan |first=Neil |coauthors= |year=2001 |publisher=Routledge |location=UK }}
* {{cite book |title=Gender, Bullying, and Harassment: Strategies to End Sexism and Homophobia in Schools |last=Meyer |first=Elizabeth |year=2009 |publisher=Teacher’s College Press |location=USA }}
* {{cite book |title=Cyberbullying and the LGBT Community |publisher=Human Rights Campaign |location=USA |url=http://www.hrc.org/issues/parenting/schools/9682.htm }}
* {{cite book |title="You Have to Be Strong to Be Gay": Bullying and Educational Attainment in LGB New Zealanders |year=2008 |publisher=Journal of Gay and Lesbian Social Services |location=New Zealand}}
* {{cite book |title=Traversing the Margins: Intersectionalities in the Bullying of Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual and Transgender Youth |year=2008 |publisher=Journal of Gay and Lesbian Social Services |location=New Zealand }}
* {{cite book |title=Homophobic Bullying and Same-Sex Desire in Anglo-American Schools: An Historical Perspective |year=2008 |publisher=Journal of Gay and Lesbian Social Services |location=New Zealand }}
* {{cite book |title=Christianity, Social Tolerance, and Homosexuality: Gay People in Western Europe from the Beginning of the Christian Era to the Fourteenth Century |last=Boswell |first=John |year=1980 |publisher= |location= |isbn=9780226067117 }}
* {{cite journal |last1=Cuordileone |first1=K. A. |last2= |first2= |year=2000 |title='Politics in an Age of Anxiety': Cold War Political Culture and the Crisis in American Masculinity |journal=Journal of American History |volume=87 |issue=2 |pages=515–45 }}
* {{cite book |last1=D'Emilio |first1=John |editor1-first=Kathy |editor1-last=Peiss |editor2-first=Christina |editor2-last=Simmons |title=Passion and Power: Sexuality in History |year=1989 |publisher=Temple University Press |pages=226–40 |chapter=The Homosexual Menace: The Politics of Sexuality in Cold War America }}
* {{cite book |title=Toward Stonewall: Homosexuality and Society in the Modern Western World |last=Edsall |first=Nicholas C. |year=2003 |publisher=U. of Virginia Press |location= |isbn=9780813925431 |pages=384 }}
* {{cite book |title=Intimate Matters: A History of Sexuality in America, Second Edition |last1=D'Emilio |first1=John |last2=Freedman |first2=Estelle B. |year=1997 |isbn=9780226142647 }}
* {{cite book |title=Homophobia: A History |last=Fone |first=Byrne |year=2001 |isbn=9780312420307 }}
* {{cite book |title=The Gilded Age Construction of Modern American Homophobia |last=Hatheway |first=Jay |year=2003 |publisher=Palgrave Macmillan |isbn=9780312234928 }}
* {{cite book |title=Handbook of Lesbian and Gay Studies |chapter=Anti-Gay and Lesbian Violence and Its Discontents |last1=Jenness |first1=Valerie |last2=Richman |first2=Kimberly D. |editor1-first=Diane |editor1-last=Richardson |editor2-first=Steven |editor2-last=Seidman |year=2002 |pages=403+}}
* {{cite book |title=Making Hate a Crime: From Social Movement to Law Enforcement |last1=Jenness |first1=Valerie |last2=Grattet |first2=Ryken |year=2001 |isbn=9780871544094}}
* {{cite book |title=The Lavender Scare: The Cold War Persecution of Gays and Lesbians in the Federal Government |last=Johnson |first=David K. |year=2004 |publisher=University of Chicago Press |isbn=9780226401904}}
* {{cite book |title=Homophobia: Description, Development, and Dynamics of Gay Bashing |last=Kantor |first=Martin |year=1998 |isbn=9780275955304}}
* {{cite book |title=Departing from Deviance: A History of Homosexual Rights and Emancipatory Science in America |last=Minton |first=Henry L. |year=2002 |publisher=U. of Chicago Press |isbn=9780226530444|pages=344 }}

{{bullying}}
{{abuse}}
{{LGBT|social=expanded}}
{{Discrimination}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Gay Bashing}}
[[Category:Homophobic violence]]
[[Category:Sexual orientation and society]]
[[Category:Pejoratives]]
[[Category:Persecution of homosexuals]]
[[Category:Abuse]]
[[Category:LGBT terms]]
[[Category:Persecution]]

[[simple:Gay-bashing]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>