<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20051007161328|24985011" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="102866" pageid="102866" ns="0" title="Gay bashing"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-10-26T19:46:56Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Gay-bashing''', '''dyke-bashing''', '''bi-bashing''', '''trans-bashing''', and '''queer-bashing''' are pejorative terms used to describe verbal confrontation with, denigration of, or physical violence against allegedly [[gay]], [[lesbian]], [[bisexuality|bisexual]], or [[transgender]]ed people, collectively [[LGBT]] or [[queer]], because of their apparent sexuality. Similar terms may be formed from other words describing these various sexual or gender minorities, like "lesbian bashing". A "bashing" may be a specific incident, or one could also use the verb "to bash" e.g. "I was gay bashed". The term [[gay]] may be used to refer to homosexuals of either sex and bisexuals, or all LGBT people. Thus gay-bashing may also refer to an incident involving any of these groups.

As detection methods are often sloppy, people are likely to fall victims even if they are not LGBT at all.  Likewise, gay-bashing is strictly acts directed at persons and must not be extended to mean bashing conducts or thoughts that suggest someone is LGBT. Taken this way, most religious authorities oppose gay-bashing.

Please see the article [[violence against gays, lesbians, bisexuals, and the transgendered]] for information on that topic.

A verbal gay-bashing might take place on any street corner and use sexual slurs, expletives, intimidation, or threats of violence &amp;mdash; or, it might take place in a political forum and include one or more common [[anti-gay slogan]]s. Passionate invective fits more closely into the general idea of gay bashing than does a calm, intellectual justification for anti-LGBT attitudes or policies. However, some people would include (firmly or otherwise) any expression of anti-LGBT sentiment in one or another category of "bashing".

==See also==
* [[Hate crime]]

[[Category:LGBT]]
[[Category:Pejoratives]]

[[simple:Gay-bashing]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>