<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061026113709|83825066" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="507981" pageid="507981" ns="0" title="Religious antisemitism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-11-10T22:03:46Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[Image:Iudaism bez prikras 63-7.gif|right|thumb|An example of state-sponsored atheist anti-Judaism. The [[Soviet Union|Soviet]] book ''"Judaism Without Embellishments"'' published by the Academy of Sciences of the [[Ukrainian SSR]] in 1963 shows typical antisemitic imagery and allegations: "It is in the teachings of Judaism, in the [[Old Testament]], and in the [[Talmud]], that the [[Israel]]i militarists find inspiration for their inhuman deeds, racist theories, and expansionist designs..."]]

{{dablink|This article deals with opposition to Judaism. For scholarly criticism of Judaism, please see [[Criticism of Judaism]].}}

'''Anti-Judaism''' is hostility to the [[Jew]]ish religion ([[Judaism]]) and those who practice it. This hostility may be of varying degrees of intensity and can be expressed in discrimination or even violence.  Anti-Judaism is a form of "[[Antisemitism]]," which is the more commonly used umbrella term, defined in the [[Merriam-Webster Dictionary]] as: "hostility toward or discrimination against Jews as a religious, ethnic, or racial group."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.m-w.com/cgi-bin/dictionary?va=anti-Semitism Merriam-Webster Dictionary: Anti-Semitism]&lt;/ref&gt; Sometimes, when it becomes an obsession, Anti-Judaism is described as "[[Judeophobia]]."

==Christian anti-Judaism==
Christian anti-Judaism is a Christian [[Theology|theological]] position denigrating [[Jew]]ish belief and practice. It emerged out of the [[Schism (religion)|schism]] between early Christian "[[Judaizers]]" &amp;mdash;those who insisted that in order to be Christian one must first become Jewish and observe [[Halakha|Jewish law]]s and religious practices such as [[circumcision]], and "universalizers"&amp;mdash;those who insisted that the nascent faith was open to everyone. Anti-Judaism was adopted by early Christian theologians to distinguish themselves from their Jewish kin. 

Anti-Judaism is sometimes distinguished from antisemitism based upon [[race|racial]] or [[ethnicity|ethnic]] grounds. "The dividing line was the possibility of effective conversion . . . a Jew ceased to be a Jew upon baptism." However, with racial antisemitism, "Now the assimilated Jew was still a Jew, even after baptism ... . From the [[Age of Enlightenment |Enlightenment]] onward, it is no longer possible to draw clear lines of distinction between religious and racial forms of hostility towards Jews... Once Jews have been emancipated and secular thinking makes its appearance, without leaving  behind the old Christian hostility towards Jews, the new term antisemitism becomes almost unavoidable, even before explicitly racist doctrines appear."&lt;ref&gt;Nichols, William: ''Christian Antisemitism, A History of Hate'' (1993) p.314&lt;/ref&gt; 

===History of Christian anti-Judaism===
{{Antisemitism}}
The fact that the vast majority of [[first century]] Jews did not believe [[Jesus]] was the [[Messiah]], nor the claims of his followers that he was [[Trinity|God]], led to the eventual parting of the ways between Christians and Jews. "To the question, Was Jesus God or man?, the Christians therefore answered: both. After 70 AD, their answer was unanimous and increasingly emphatic. This made a complete breach with Judaism inevitable."&lt;ref&gt;[[Paul Johnson (journalist)|Johnson, Paul]]: ''A History of the Jews'' (1987), p.144&lt;/ref&gt;

The Jewish/Christian debate and dialogue moved from polemic to bitter verbal and written attacks one against the other. [[Justin Martyr|St. Justin Martyr's]] ''Dialogue with Trypho the Jew''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ccel.org/fathers/ANF-01/just/justtryindex.html ''Dialogue with Trypho the Jew'']&lt;/ref&gt; was a polemical debate giving the Christian assertions for the Messiahship of Jesus especially by making use of Jewish Scripture (the [[Old Testament]]). In the ''Dialogue'', Justin makes use of a fictional figure called Trypho on which to construct his [[apologetics|apologetic]] arguments (a traditional rhetorical and literary device in the ancient world, finding its origins in Socratic philosophy). This ''Dialogue'' is one of the first apologetic works in the early Church to address Judaism.

[[John Chrysostom|St. John Chrysostom]], [[Archbishop of Constantinople]] ([[4th century|4th]]/[[5th century|5th]] century) is equally negative in his treatment of Judaism, though much more [[Hyperbole|hyperbolic]] in expression.&lt;ref&gt;Saint John Chrysostom: [http://www.fordham.edu/halsall/source/chrysostom-jews6.html ''Eight Homilies Against the Jews'']&lt;/ref&gt; While St. Justin's ''Dialogue'' is a philosophical treatise, St. Chrysostom's eight [[homily|homilies]] ''Against the Judaizers'' are a more informal and rhetorically forceful set of sermons preached in church.  Delivered while Chrysostom was still a [[priest]] in [[Antioch]], his homilies deliver a scathing critique of Jewish religious and civil life. The primary scholarly explanation for this was that he wished to warn Christians not to have any contact with Judaism because of the attraction that some Christians felt towards the [[synagogue]], and his purpose was not primarily to attack the Jews, but rather to keep Christians away from the rival religion's festivals, apparently an ongoing pastoral problem in Antioch.  Additionally, it was common during that period to make use of an exaggerated [[straw man]] argument in order to make one's point.

[[Martin Luther]] has been accused of antisemitism, primarily in relation to his statements about [[Jew]]s in his book ''[[On the Jews and their Lies]]'', which describes the Jews in extremely harsh terms, excoriating them, and providing detailed recommendation for a [[pogrom]] against them and their permanent oppression and/or expulsion.  According to [[Paul Johnson (journalist)|Paul Johnson]], it "may be termed the first work of modern anti-Semitism, and a giant step forward on the road to [[the Holocaust]]."&lt;ref&gt;Johnson, Paul: ''A History of the Jews'' (1987), p.242&lt;/ref&gt; In contrast, [[Roland Bainton]], noted church historian and Luther biographer, wrote "One could wish that Luther had died before ever this tract was written. His position was entirely religious and in no respect racial"&lt;ref&gt;Bainton, Roland: ''Here I Stand'', (Nashville: Abingdon Press, New American Library, 1983), p. 297&lt;/ref&gt;. See also [[Martin Luther and the Jews]].

At several points in the history of Christianity, Chrysostom and Luther's writings have been used to justify anti-Semitism and anti-Judaism, whatever their original intentions may have been. Contemporary examples include the 1980 statement by Bailey Smith (then-president of the [[Southern Baptist Convention]]) that "God Almighty does not hear the prayer of a Jew," and Baptist minister and televangelist [[Jerry Falwell]]'s assertion in his book, ''Listen, America!'', that Jews "are spiritually blind and desperately in need of their Messiah and Savior."

Elsewhere in Christianity, efforts have been made to counteract the effects of anti-Judaism, especially as many Christian leaders seek to have an [[ecumenical]] rapport with their Jewish counterparts.

==Blood libel against Jews==
[[Blood libel against Jews|Blood libels]] are accusations that Jews use human blood in religious [[rituals]]. Historically these are accusations that the blood of [[Christian]] children is especially coveted. In many cases, blood libels served as the basis for a blood libel [[cult]], in which the alleged victim of human sacrifice was elevated to the status of martyr, and in some cases, [[canonized]]. Although the first known instance of blood libel is found in the writings of [[Apion]], who claimed that the Jews sacrificed [[Greeks|Greek]] victims in the Temple, no further incidents are recorded until the 12th century, when blood libels began to proliferate. These libels have persisted from then through the 20th century.

== Notes ==
&lt;div class="references-small"&gt;&lt;references /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

==See also==
* [[Christianity and antisemitism]]
* [[Christian opposition to antisemitism]]
* [[Schisms among the Jews]]
* [[Islam and antisemitism]]
* [[Amal Saad-Ghorayeb]]
* [[History of the Jews in Russia and the Soviet Union]]
* [[Criticism of Judaism]]

==External links==
{{Commons2|Anti-Judaism}}
* [http://www.chrysostom.org/jews.html Was St. John Chrysostom Anti-Semitic?]
* [http://www.findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m1058/is_10_121/ai_n6159172/print Anti-Semitism or anti-Judaism?]
* [http://www.icjs.org/scholars/bachfred.html The Gospel of John and Christian Anti-Judaism]


[[Category:Ancient Roman Christianity]]
[[Category:Antisemitism]]
[[Category:Christian and Jewish interfaith topics]]


[[de:Antijudaismus im Mittelalter]]
[[hu:Antijudaizmus]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>