<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20051111174426|28041284" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="507981" pageid="507981" ns="0" title="Religious antisemitism"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-11-11T17:57:40Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Anti-Judaism''' is a [[Christian]] [[Theology|theological]] position denigrating [[Jew]]ish belief and practice. It emerged out of the [[schism]] between early Christian [[Judaizers]]&amp;mdash;those who insisted that in order to be Christian one must first become Jewish and observe [[Halakha|Jewish law]]s and religious practices such as [[circumcision]], and "universalizers"&amp;mdash;those who insisted that the nascent faith was open to everyone. Anti-Judaism was adopted by early Christian theologians to distinguish themselves from their Jewish kin. 

[[Anti-Semitism]] is hostility towards, or prejudice against, Jews.  While some consider anti-Judaism to be a manifestation or type of anti-Semitism, others distinguish between anti-Judaism (which is emnity towards the practice of, and practitioners of, Judaism), and modern anti-Semitism (emnity towards Jews as an [[ethnicity|ethnic]] or [[race|racial]] group).

==History==

The fact that the vast majority of the [[first century]] Jews did not believe [[Jesus]] was the Messiah, nor the claims of his followers that he was [[Trinity|God]], led to the eventual parting of the ways between Christians and Jews. 

The Jewish/Christian debate and dialogue moved from polemic to bitter verbal and written attacks one against the other. [[Justin Martyr|St. Justin Martyr's]] ''Dialogue with Trypho the Jew'' [http://www.ccel.org/fathers/ANF-01/just/justtryindex.html] was a polemical debate giving the Christian assertions for the Messiahship of Jesus especially by making use of Jewish Scripture (the [[Old Testament]]). In the ''Dialogue'', Justin makes use of a fictional figure called Trypho on which to construct his [[apologetics|apologetic]] arguments (a traditional rhetorical and literary device in the ancient world, finding its origins in Socratic philosophy). This ''Dialogue'' is one of the first apologetic works in the early Church to address [[Judaism]].

[[John Chrysostom|St. John Chrysostom]], [[Archbishop of Constantinople]] ([[4th century|4th]]/[[5th century|5th]] century) is equally negative in his treatment of Judaism, though much more [[Hyperbole|hyperbolic]] in expression. [http://www.fordham.edu/halsall/source/chrysostom-jews6.html] While St. Justin's ''Dialogue'' is a philosophical treatise, St. Chrysostom's eight [[homily|homilies]] ''Against the Judaizers'' are a more informal and rhetorically forceful set of sermons preached in church.  Delivered while Chrysostom was still a [[priest]] in [[Antioch]], his homilies deliver a scathing critique of Jewish religious and civil life. The primary scholarly explanation for this was that he wished to warn Christians not to have any contact with Judaism because of the attraction that some Christians felt towards the [[synagogue]], and his purpose was not primarily to attack the Jews, but rather to keep Christians away from the rival religion's festivals, apparently an ongoing pastoral problem in Antioch.  Additionally, it was common during that period to make use of an exaggerated [[straw man]] argument in order to make one's point.

[[Martin Luther]] has been accused of [[Anti-Semitism]] primarily in relation to his statements about [[Jew]]s in his book ''[[On the Jews and their Lies]]'', which describes the Jews in extremely harsh terms, excoriating them, and providing detailed recommendation for a [[pogrom]] against them and their permanent oppression and/or expulsion.  According to [[Paul Johnson (journalist)|Paul Johnson]], it "may be termed the first work of modern anti-Semitism, and a giant step forward on the road to [[the Holocaust]]." (''A History of the Jews'', 1987, p.242)  In contrast, [[Roland Bainton]], noted church historian and Luther biographer, wrote "One could wish that Luther had died before ever this tract was written. His position was entirely religious and in no respect racial" (''Here I Stand'', [Nashville: Abingdon Press, New American Library, 1983], p. 297). See also [[Martin Luther and Antisemitism]].

At several points in the history of Christianity, Chrysostom and Luther's writings have been used to justify anti-Semitism and anti-Judaism, whatever their original intentions may have been. Contemporary examples include the 1980 statement by Bailey Smith (then-president of the [[Southern Baptist Convention]]) that "God Almighty does not hear the prayer of a Jew," and Baptist minister and televangelist [[Jerry Falwell]]'s assertion in his book, ''Listen, America!'', that Jews "are spiritually blind and desperately in need of their Messiah and Savior."

Elsewhere in Christianity, efforts have been made to counteract the effects of anti-Judaism, especially as many Christian leaders seek to have an [[ecumenical]] rapport with their Jewish counterparts.

==See also==
* [[Christianity and anti-Semitism]]
* [[Christian opposition to anti-Semitism]]
* [[Martin Luther and Antisemitism]]

==External links==
{{Commons2|Anti-Judaism}}
* [http://www.chrysostom.org/jews.html Was St. John Chrysostom Anti-Semitic?]
* [http://www.simpletoremember.com/vitals/jewsandjesus.htm Why Jews Don't Believe In Jesus]
* [http://www.findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m1058/is_10_121/ai_n6159172/print Anti-Semitism or anti-Judaism?]
* [http://www.icjs.org/scholars/bachfred.html The Gospel of John and Christian Anti-Judaism]

[[Category:Jewish Christian topics]]
[[Category:Ancient Roman Christianity]]
[[Category:Anti-Semitism]]

[[de:Antijudaismus im Mittelalter]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>