<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20121107133958|521823113" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="720902" pageid="720902" ns="0" title="Compulsory sterilization"><revisions><rev timestamp="2012-11-09T14:50:53Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Cleanup-link rot|date=February 2012}}
{{Discrimination sidebar}}

'''Compulsory sterilization''', also known as  '''forced sterilization''',  programs are government policies which attempt to force people to undergo surgical [[Human sterilization (surgical procedure)|sterilization]]. In the first half of the 20th century, several such programs were instituted in countries around the world, usually as part of [[eugenics]] programs intended to prevent the reproduction and multiplication of members of the population considered to be carriers of defective [[Genetics|genetic]] traits. Widespread or systematic forced sterilization has been recognized as a [[crime against humanity]]  by the [[Rome Statute of the International Criminal Court|Rome Statute]] in the Explanatory Memorandum. This memorandum also defines the jurisdiction of the [[International Criminal Court]].&lt;ref name="Horton"&gt;As quoted by Guy Horton in ''[http://www.ibiblio.org/obl/docs3/Horton-2005.pdf Dying Alive - A Legal Assessment of Human Rights Violations in Burma]'' April 2005, co-Funded by The Netherlands Ministry for Development Co-Operation. See section "12.52 Crimes against humanity", Page 201. He references RSICC/C, Vol. 1 p. 360&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://untreaty.un.org/cod/icc/statute/romefra.htm |title=Rome Statute of the International Criminal Court |publisher=Untreaty.un.org |date= |accessdate=2012-07-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; Despite international agreement concerning the inhumanity and illegality of forced sterilization, it has been suggested that Government of Uzbekistan continues to pursue such programs.&lt;ref name=bbc-news-2012-04-12 /&gt;

==By country==

===Canada===
{{Main|Compulsory sterilization in Canada}}
Two Canadian provinces (Alberta and British Columbia) performed compulsory sterilization programs with eugenic aims. Canadian compulsory sterilization operated via the same overall mechanisms of [[institutionalization]], [[judgment]], and [[surgery]] as the American system.{{why?|date=November 2010}} However, one notable difference is in the treatment of non-insane criminals. Canadian legislation never allowed for punitive sterilization of inmates.

===Czechoslovakia and the Czech Republic===
[[Czechoslovakia]] carried out a policy to sterilize some [[Roma (Romani subgroup)|Roma]] women, starting in 1973. In various cases the sterilization was agreed upon, often in exchange for social welfare benefits or was given by the lack of education.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/6409699.stm Sterilized Roma accuse Czechs], [[BBC]], March 12, 2007 {{en icon}}&lt;/ref&gt; The dissidents of the [[Charter 77]] denounced it in 1977–78 as a "[[genocide]]", but the practice continued through the [[Velvet Revolution]] of 1989.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newsdesk.org/archives/003850.html For Gypsies, Eugenics is a Modern Problem - Czech Practice Dates to Soviet Era], [[Newsdesk]], June 12, 2006 {{en icon}}&lt;/ref&gt; A 2005 report by the Czech government's independent ombudsman, [[Otakar Motejl]], identified dozens of cases of coercive sterilization between 1979 and 2001, and called for criminal investigations and possible prosecution against several health care workers and administrators.&lt;ref name=Czech /&gt;

===Germany===&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[January 1]] --&gt;
{{Main|Nazi eugenics}}
[[File:Wir stehen nicht allein.png|thumb|left|250px|"We do not stand alone": Nazi poster from 1936 with flags of other countries with compulsory sterilization legislation]]

One of the first acts by [[Adolf Hitler]] after achieving total control over the [[Germany|German]] state was to pass the [[Law for the Prevention of Hereditary Diseased Offspring]] (''Gesetz zur Verhütung erbkranken Nachwuchses'') in July 1933. The law was signed in by Hitler himself, and over 200 eugenic courts were created specifically as a result of the law. Under the German law, all doctors in the Reich were required to report patients of theirs who were [[mentally retarded]], [[mentally ill]] (including [[schizophrenia]] and [[manic depression]]), [[epilepsy|epileptic]], blind, deaf, or physically deformed, and a steep monetary penalty was imposed for any patients who were not properly reported. Individuals suffering from [[alcoholism]] or [[Huntington's disease|Huntington's Disease]] could also be sterilized. The individual's case was then presented in front of a court of [[Nazism|Nazi]] officials and public health officers who would review their medical records, take testimony from friends and colleagues, and eventually decide whether or not to order a sterilization operation performed on the individual, using force if necessary. Though not explicitly covered by the law, 400 mixed-race "[[Rhineland Bastard]]s" were also sterilized beginning in 1937.&lt;ref&gt;Robert Proctor, ''Racial hygiene: Medicine under the Nazis'' (Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press, 1988), and Gisela Bock, "Nazi sterilization and reproductive policies" in Dieter Kuntz, ed., ''Deadly medicine: creating the master race'' (Washington, D.C.: United States Holocaust Memorial Museum, 2004).&lt;/ref&gt;

By the end of [[World War II]], over 400,000 individuals were sterilised under the German law and its revisions, most within its first four years of being enacted. When the issue of compulsory sterilisation was brought up at the [[Nuremberg trials]] after the war, many Nazis defended their actions on the matter by indicating that it was the United States itself from whom they had taken inspiration. The Nazis had many other eugenics-inspired [[racial policy of Nazi Germany|racial policies]], including their [[T-4 Euthanasia Programme|"euthanasia" programme]] in which around 70,000 people institutionalised or suffering from birth defects were killed.&lt;ref&gt;[[Ian Kershaw]], ''Hitler: A Profile in Power'', Chapter VI, first section (London, 1991, rev. 2001)&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Japan ===
{{Further|Eugenics in Showa Japan}}

In the first part of the [[Showa era]], Japanese governments promoted increasing the number of healthy Japanese, while simultaneously decreasing the number of people suffering mental retardation, disability, genetic disease and other conditions that led to inferiority in the Japanese gene pool.&lt;ref&gt;"The National Eugenic Law" The 107th law that Japanese Government promulgated in 1940　(国民優生法) 第一条　本法ハ悪質ナル遺伝性疾患ノ素質ヲ有スル者ノ増加ヲ防遏スルト共ニ健全ナル素質ヲ有スル者ノ増加ヲ図リ以テ国民素質ノ向上ヲ期スルコトヲ目的トス, Kimura, Jurisprudence in Genetics, http://www.bioethics.jp/licht_genetics.html&lt;/ref&gt;

The ''Leprosy Prevention laws'' of 1907, 1931 and 1953, permitted the segregation of patients in sanitariums where forced abortions and sterilization were common and authorized punishment of patients "disturbing peace".&lt;ref&gt;''Hansen's sanitarium were houses of horrors,'' http://search.japantimes.co.jp/cgi-bin/nn20050128a1.html, ''Abolition of leprosy isolation policy in Japan'', http://goliath.ecnext.com/coms2/summary_0199-1556743_ITM&lt;/ref&gt; Under the colonial Korean ''Leprosy prevention ordinance'', Korean patients were also subjected to hard labor.&lt;ref&gt;''Korean Hansens patients seek redress'', http://search.japantimes.co.jp/cgi-bin/nn20040226a4.html&lt;/ref&gt;

The ''Race Eugenic Protection Law'' was submitted from 1934 to 1938 to the Diet. After four amendments, this draft was promulgated as a ''National Eugenic Law''  in 1940 by the [[Fumimaro Konoe|Konoe]] government.&lt;ref&gt;"The Eugenic Protection Law" (国民優生法)The 107th law that Japanese Government promulgated in 1940　(国民優生法) 第二条　本法ニ於テ優生手術ト称スルハ生殖ヲ不能ナラシムル手術又ハ処置ニシテ命令ヲ以テ定ムルモノヲ謂フ , http://www.res.otemon.ac.jp/~yamamoto/be/BE_law_04.htm&lt;/ref&gt; According to Matsubara Yoko, from 1940 to 1945, sterilization was done to 454 Japanese persons under this law.&lt;ref&gt;[http://tateiwa.kir.jp/1990/971100my.htm 「優生問題を考える（四）──国民優生法と優生保護法] Matsubara Yoko - Research of Eugenics problem
(Professor of [[Ritsumeikan University]], researcher of Gender-blind and Eugenics.)&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the ''Eugenic Protection Law'' (1948), sterilization could be enforced on criminals "with genetic predisposition to commit crime", patients with genetic diseases such as total color-blindness, [[hemophilia]], [[albinism]] and [[ichthyosis]], and mental affections such as [[schizophrenia]], [[manic-depression]] and [[epilepsy]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.soshiren.org/shiryou/yuseihogohou.html |title=SOSHIREN / 資料・法律−優生保護法 |publisher=Soshiren.org |date= |accessdate=2012-07-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; The mental sicknesses were added in 1952.
{{further|LGBT rights in Japan}}
The right to legal sex change in case of transsexual has been approved by legislation in 2004. The legislation only allows the person who has no children in addition to having undergone the [[sex reassignment surgery]]. The condition is amended in 2008 to "those who has no child under 20 years old", but still sterilization and sex reassignment surgery is compulsory to legal sex change.

===India===
India's state of emergency [[The Emergency (India)|between 1975 and 1977]] included a family planning initiative that began in April 1976 through which the government hoped to lower India's ever increasing population.  This program used propaganda and monetary incentives to convince citizens to get sterilized.  People who agreed to get sterilized would receive land, housing, and money or loans.&lt;ref name=Relyingonhardandsoftsells&gt;''Relying on Hard and Soft Sells India Pushes Sterilization'', New York Times, June 22, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;  Because of this program, thousands of men received vasectomies and even more women received tubal ligations.  However, the program focused more on sterilizing women than men.  An article in The New York Times titled “For Sterilization, Target Is Women” states, “There were 114,426 vasectomies in India in 2002-03, and 4.6 million tubal ligations, the analogous operation on women, though ligation is a more complicated operation.” &lt;ref name=Forsterilizationtargetiswomen&gt;''For Sterilization Target is Women'', New York Times, November 7, 2003.&lt;/ref&gt;  Despite the fact that sterilizing men is a more simple procedure, the government still chose to focus on sterilizing women instead.&lt;ref name=Relyingonhardandsoftsells&gt;{{cite news|title=Relying on Hard and Soft Sells India Pushes Sterilization|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2001/06/22/world/relying-on-hard-and-soft-sells-india-pushes-sterilization.html?src=pm|publisher=New York Times|accessdate=February 13, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Forsterilizationtargetiswomen&gt;{{cite news|title=For Sterilization Target is Women|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2003/11/07/world/for-sterilization-target-is-women.html?src=pm|publisher=New York Times|accessdate=February 13, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Son of the Prime Minister at the time [[Indira Gandhi]], [[Sanjay Gandhi]] was largely blamed for what turned out to be a failed program.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news | title=The Indira enigma | date=May 11, 2001 | accessdate=July 28, 2006 | publisher=[[Frontline (US TV series)|Frontline]] | url=http://www.hinduonnet.com/fline/fl1809/18090740.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt; A strong backlash against any initiative associated with family planning followed the highly controversial program, which continues into the 21st century.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news | title=Male involvement and contraceptive methods for men |date = September 1996| accessdate=July 28, 2006 | publisher=[[Frontline (US TV series)|Frontline]] | url=http://www.malecontraceptives.org/articles/ringheim_article.php}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===China===

[[File:Puning city china river bank houses.jpg|thumb|River bank houses in [[Puning]]]]

In 1978, Chinese authorities became concerned with the possibility of a baby boom that the country could not handle, and they initialized the one-child policy. In order to effectively deal with the complex issues surrounding childbirth, the Chinese government placed great emphasis on family planning.  Because this was such an important matter, the government felt it needed to be standardized and so to this end laws were introduced in 2002.&lt;ref name="Amnesty International"&gt;{{Cite news | title=Thousands at risk of forced sterilization in China | date=April 22, 2010 | accessdate=April 9, 2012 | publisher=[[Amnesty International]] | url=http://www.amnesty.org/en/news-and-updates/thousands-risk-forced-sterilization-china-2010-04-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;  These laws uphold the basic tenets of what was previously put into practice, outlining the rights of the individuals and outlining what the Chinese government can and cannot do to enforce policy. 

However, recently accusations have been raised from groups such as [[Amnesty International]], who have claimed that practices of compulsory sterilization have been occurring for people who have already reached their one child quota.  These practices run contrary to the stated principles of the law, and seem to differ on a local level. An especially egregious example, according to Amnesty International, has been occurring in Puning City, [[Guangdong Province]]. The stated goal of the sterilization drive in this city in China was to meet with family planning targets that were outlined by the government in the Population and Family Planning Law of 2002. This drive, also known as the [[Iron Fist Campaign]],  also is said to have used coercive methods in order to ensure that close to 10,000 women were sterilized, including detaining elderly family members.&lt;ref name="Amnesty International"/&gt;

The Chinese Government does not seem to be unaware of these discrepancies in policy implementation on a local level.  For example, The National Population and Family Planning Commission put forth in a statement that, “Some persons concerned in a few counties and townships of Linyi did commit practices that violated law and infringed upon legitimate rights and interests of citizens while conducting family planning work.”  This statement comes in reference to some charges of forced sterilization and abortions in Linyi city of Shandong Province.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news | title=China acts on forced abortion | date=September 20, 2005 | accessdate=April 9, 2012 | publisher=BBC | url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/asia-pacific/4262890.stm}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, it remains unclear to what extent the government has prosecuted or disciplined the officials in charge of family planning in the country.

===Peru===
In [[Peru]], President [[Alberto Fujimori]] (in office from 1990–2000) has been accused of [[genocide]] and [[crimes against humanity]] as a result of a sterilization program put in place by his administration.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/americas/2148793.stm Mass sterilization scandal shocks Peru], [[BBC]], July 24, 2002&lt;/ref&gt; Peru put in place a program of forced sterilizations against indigenous people (essentially the  [[Quechuas]] and the [[Aymaras]]), in the name of a "[[public health]] plan", presented July 28, 1995. The plan was principally financed using funds from [[USAID]] (36 million dollars), the [[Nippon Foundation]], and later, the [[United Nations Population Fund]] (UNFPA).&lt;ref name=Diplo&gt;[http://www.monde-diplomatique.fr/2004/05/BARTHELEMY/11190 Stérilisations forcées des Indiennes du Pérou], ''[[Le Monde diplomatique]]'', May 2004&lt;/ref&gt; On September 9, 1995, Fujimori presented a Bill that would revise the "General Law of Population", in order to allow sterilization. Several contraceptive methods were also legalized, all measures that were strongly opposed by the Roman Catholic Church, as well as the Catholic organization [[Opus Dei]]. In February 1996, the [[World Health Organization]] (WHO) itself congratulated Fujimori for his plan to control demographic growth.&lt;ref name=Diplo/&gt;

On February 25, 1998, a representative for [[USAID]] testified before the U.S. government's House International Relations Committee, to address controversy surrounding Peru's program. He indicated that the government of Peru was making important changes to the program, in order to:

* Discontinue their campaigns in tubal ligations and vasectomies.
* Make clear to health workers that there are no provider targets for voluntary surgical contraception or any other method of contraception.
* Implement a comprehensive monitoring program to ensure compliance with family planning norms and informed consent procedures.
* Welcome Ombudsman Office investigations of complaints received and respond to any additional complaints that are submitted as a result of the public request for any additional concerns.
* Implement a 72 hour "waiting period" for people who choose tubal ligation or vasectomy. This waiting period will occur between the second counseling session and surgery.
* Require health facilities to be certified as appropriate for performing surgical contraception as a means to ensure that no operations are done in makeshift or substandard facilities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=USAID Testimony: House International Relations Committee, Subcommittee on International Operations and Human Rights, 2/25/98|url=http://www.usaid.gov/press/spe_test/testimony/1998/test079.htm|publisher=USAID|accessdate=August 23, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In September 2001, Minister of Health [[Luis Solari]] launched a special commission into the activities of the Voluntary Surgical Contraception, initiating a Parliamentary commission tasked with inquiring into the "irregularities" of the program, and to put it on an acceptable footing. In July 2002, its Final Report ordered by the Minister of Health revealed that between 1995 and 2000, 331,600 women were sterilized, while 25,590 men submitted to vasectomies.&lt;ref name="Diplo"/&gt; The plan, which had the objective of diminishing the number of births in areas of poverty within Peru, was essentially directed at the indigenous people living in deprived areas (areas often involved in internal conflicts with the Peruvian government, as with the [[Shining Path]] guerilla group). Deputy [[Dora Núñez Dávila]] made the accusation in September 2003 that 400,000 indigenous people were sterilized during the 1990s. Documents proved that President Fujimori was informed, each month, of the number of sterilizations done, by his former Ministers of Health, [[Eduardo Yong Motta]] (1994–96), [[Marino Costa Bauer]] (1996–1999) and [[Alejandro Aguinaga]] (1999–2000).&lt;ref name=Diplo/&gt; A study by sociologist Giulia Tamayo, ''Nada Personal'' (in English: Nothing Personal), showed that doctors were required to meet quotas. According to ''[[Le Monde diplomatique]]'', "tubal ligation festivals" were organized through program publicity campaigns, held in the ''[[pueblos jóvenes]]'' (in English: shantytowns). In 1996 there were, according to official statistics, 81,762 tubal ligations performed on women, with a peak being reached the following year, with 109,689 ligatures, then only 25,995 in 1998.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news | title=Mass sterilization scandal shocks Peru | date=July 24, 2002 | accessdate=April 30, 2006 | publisher=BBC News | url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/americas/2148793.stm}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On October 21, 2011, Peru’s Attorney General [[José Bardales]] decided to reopen an investigation into the cases, which had been halted in 2009 under the statute of limitations, after the  [[Inter-American Commission on Human Rights]] ruled that Peru’s sterilization program involved [[crimes against humanity]], which are not time-limited.&lt;ref&gt;[http://impunitywatch.com/?p=21794 Thousands of Forced Sterilization Cases Reopened in Peru] Impunity Watch, published November 14, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

===Russia===
In 2008, the [[Perm Krai]] [[ombudswoman]] [[Tatyana Margolina]] reported that 14 women with disabilities were subjected to compulsory medical sterilization in Ozyorskiy psychoneurological nursing home whose director was Grigory Bannikov.&lt;ref name="Сизова"&gt;{{ru icon}} {{cite news|last=Сизова|first=Марина|title=Пельмешки из психушки|url=http://www.beriki.ru/2011/02/02/pelmeshki-iz-psikhushki|accessdate=25 April 2012|newspaper=Пермские новости|date=2 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The sterilizations were performed not on the basis mandatory court decision appropriate for them, but only on the basis of the application by the guardian Bannikov.&lt;ref name="Богданов"&gt;{{ru icon}} {{cite news|last=Богданов|first=Владимир|title=Непорочное сиротство: Девушек-воспитанниц интерната директор распорядился принудительно стерилизовать|url=http://www.rg.ru/2010/07/20/internat.html|accessdate=25 April 2012|newspaper=[[Rossiyskaya Gazeta]] - Федеральный выпуск № 5237 (158)|date=20 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 2 December 2010, the court has not found [[corpus delicti]] in the compulsory medical sterilizations performed by his consent.&lt;ref name="Сизова"/&gt; The order by the [[health minister]] of the [[Russian Federation]] that issued in 1993 and neatly determined the procedure of forced abortion and sterilization of women with disabilities was repealed by the head of [[Ministry of Health and Social Development of the Russian Federation]] [[Tatyana Golikova]] in 2009.&lt;ref name="Сизова"/&gt; Therefore, now women can be subjected to compulsory sterilization without court decision, according to Tatyana Margolina.&lt;ref name="Сизова"/&gt; In Russia, one of supporters of preventive [[eugenics]] is the president of the [[Independent Psychiatric Association of Russia]] [[Yuri Savenko]], who justifies forced sterilization of women, which is practiced in Moscow psychoneurological nursing homes, and states that “one needs a more strictly adjusted and open control for the practice of preventive eugenics, which, in itself, is, in its turn, justifiable.”&lt;ref name="Лишённые"&gt;{{ru icon}} {{cite news|title=Лишённые наследства. Законно ли запрещают рожать пациенткам психоневрологических интернатов?|url=http://2005.novayagazeta.ru/nomer/2005/93n/n93n-s26.shtml|accessdate=23 April 2012|newspaper=[[Novaya Gazeta]]|date=12 December 2005}} Савенко: «…Необходим более строго выверенный и открытый контроль за практикой предупредительной евгеники, которая сама по себе, в свою очередь, оправданна».&lt;/ref&gt;

===Sweden===
[[Jan Guillou]] brought up [[eugenics]] in the TV-program Rekordmagazinet in the 1980s, at which time this was still a topic largely unknown to the people, but it wasn't until 1997, following the publication of articles by [[Maciej Zaremba]] in the ''[[Dagens Nyheter]]'' daily, widespread attention was given to the fact that [[Sweden]] once operated a strong sterilization program, which was active primarily from the mid 1930s until the 1970s. A governmental commission was set up, and finished its inquiry in 2000.&lt;ref name=Czech /&gt;

The eugenistic legislation was enacted in 1934 and was formally abolished in 1976. According to the 2000 governmental report, 21,000 were estimated to have been forcibly sterilized, 6,000 were coerced into a 'voluntary' sterilization while the nature of a further 4,000 cases could not be determined.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.regeringen.se/content/1/c4/28/64/212fc81a.pdf Steriliseringsfrågan i Sverige 1935 - 1975], SOU 2000:20, in Swedish with an English summary.&lt;/ref&gt; However, the 40,000 or so socio-medical cases are contested, and Zaremba and others argue that they were more in the interest of society than individual women. The Swedish state subsequently paid out damages to victims who contacted the authorities and asked for compensation.

The program included all known criteria for sterilization, including a loosely phrased "social" indiciation. In 1922 the [[Statens institut för rasbiologi|State Institute of Racial Biology]] was founded in Uppsala and in 1927 Parliament began to deal with the first legal provisions on sterilisation.&lt;ref name=Czech&gt;[http://www.ochrance.cz/en/dokumenty/dokument.php?doc=400 Final Statement of the Public Defender of Rights in the Matter of Sterilisations Performed in Contravention of the Law and Proposed Remedial Measures], Czech government, 2005 {{en icon}}&lt;/ref&gt; A new draft was produced in 1932, already taking into account sterilization for general socio-prophylactic reasons, and even without the consent of the person concerned.&lt;ref name=Czech /&gt; The draft was adopted in 1934.&lt;ref name=Czech /&gt; Another law, passed in 1941, was more far reaching, included a social indication and did not include any age of consent limit.

From 1950, the number of eugenic sterilizations under the 1941 legal provisions gradually decreased.&lt;ref name=Czech /&gt;
It is possible but not proven that the Swedish sterilizations targeted travelers. These were sometimes viewed as a separate race or ethnic group. The [[Swedish Racial Hygiene Society]] had been founded in Stockholm in 1909, and the 1934 works by [[Alva Myrdal|Alva]] and [[Gunnar Myrdal]] was very significant in promoting the eugenic tendencies in practical politics.&lt;ref name=Czech /&gt; The authors theorized that the best solution for the Swedish welfare state ("[[Folkhemmet|folkhem]]") was to prevent at the outset the hereditary transfer of undesirable characteristics that caused the individual affected to become sooner or later a burden on society. The authors therefore proposed a "corrective social reform” under which sterilization was to prevent "nonviable individuals” from spreading their undesirable traits.&lt;ref name=Czech /&gt;

In Sweden, sterilization is only compulsory before [[sex change]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thelocal.se/38466/20120112/ Sweden keeps sex-change sterilization law], [[The Local]], January 12, 2012&lt;/ref&gt; This last compulsory sterilization has been criticized by several political parties in Sweden and since 2011 the [[Parliament of Sweden]] is expected to change the law since no party is formally supporting it.

===Switzerland===
In October 1999, [[Margrith von Felten]] suggested to the [[National Council of Switzerland]] in the form of a general proposal to adopt legal regulations that would enable reparation for persons sterilized against their will. According to the proposal, reparation was to be provided to persons who had undergone the intervention without their consent or who had consented to sterilization under coercion. According to Margrith von Felten:
{{cquote|The history of eugenics in Switzerland remains insufficiently explored. Research programmes are in progress. However, individual studies and facts are already available. For example:

The report of the Institute for the History of Medicine and Public Health "Mental Disability and Sexuality. Legal sterilization in the [[Vaud]] Canton between 1928 and 1985" points out that coercive sterilizations took place until the 1980s. The act on coercive sterilizations of the Vaud Canton was the first law of this kind in the European context.

Hans Wolfgang Maier, head of the Psychiatric Clinic in Zurich pointed out in a report from the beginning of the century that 70% to 80% of [[abortion|terminations]] were linked to sterilization by doctors. In the period from 1929 to 1931, 480 women and 15 men were sterilized in Zurich in connection with termination.

Following agreements between doctors and authorities such as the 1934 "Directive For Surgical Sterilization" of the Medical Association in Basle, eugenic indication to sterilization was recognized as admissible.

A statistical evaluation of the sterilizations performed in the Basle women's hospital between 1920 and 1934 shows a remarkable increase in sterilizations for a psychiatric indication after 1929 and a steep increase in 1934, when a coercive sterilization act came into effect in nearby National Socialist Germany.

A study by the Swiss Nursing School in Zurich, published in 1991, documents that 24 mentally-disabled women aged between 17 and 25 years were sterilized between 1980 and 1987. Of these 24 sterilizations, just one took place at the young woman's request.

Having evaluated sources primarily from the 1930s (psychiatric files, official directives, court files, etc.), historians have documented that the requirement for free consent to sterilization was in most of cases not satisfied. Authorities obtained the "[[Informed consent|consent]]" required by the law partly by persuasion, and partly by enforcing it through coercion and threats. Thus the recipients of social benefits were threatened with removal of the benefits, women were exposed to a choice between placement in an institution or sterilization, and abortions were permitted only when women simultaneously consented to sterilization.

More than fifty years after ending the National Socialist dictatorship in Germany, in which racial murder, euthanasia and coerced sterilizations belonged to the political programme, it is clear that eugenics, with its idea of "[[life unworthy of life]]" and "racial purity" permeated even democratic countries. The idea that a "healthy nation" should be achieved through targeted medical/social measures was designed and politically implemented in many European countries and in the U.S.A in the first half of this century. It is a policy incomparable with the inconceivable horrors of the Nazi rule; yet it is clear that authorities and the medical community were guilty of the methods and measures applied, i.e. coerced sterilizations, prohibitions of marriages and child removals – serious violations of human rights.&lt;ref name=Czech /&gt;}}

Switzerland refused, however, to vote a reparations Act.

===United States===
{{See also|Eugenics in the United States}}
[[File:Sterilization states.jpg|250px|thumb|right|A poster from a 1921 [[eugenics]] conference displays the U.S. states that had implemented sterilization legislation by then]]

The United States was the first country to concertedly undertake compulsory sterilization programs for the purpose of eugenics.&lt;ref&gt;Eugenics And Its Relevance To Contemporary Health Care, Rachel Iredale, Nursing Ethics 2000 7 (3), 0969-7330(00)NE346OA © 2000 Arnold&lt;/ref&gt; The heads of the program were avid believers in eugenics and frequently argued for their program. It was shut down due to ethical problems. The principal targets of the American program were the [[mental retardation|mentally retarded]] and the [[mental illness|mentally ill]], but also targeted under many state laws were the deaf, the blind, people with [[epilepsy]], and the physically deformed. According to the activist [[Angela Davis]], [[Indigenous people of the United States|Native Americans]], as well as African-American women&lt;ref&gt;[[Angela Davis]], ''Women, Race and Class'' (1981) ISBN 0-394-71351-6&lt;/ref&gt; were sterilized against their will in many states, often without their knowledge while they were in a hospital for other reasons (e.g. childbirth). Other Native American activists such as Dr. Pinkerman concluded some 25,000 Native American women were forcibly sterilized against their will. Fortunately, these cases, as common mathematics would prove, were exaggerated [http://www.straightdope.com/columns/read/2384/were-40-of-native-american-women-forcibly-sterilized-in-the-1970s]. 

Some sterilizations took place in prisons and other penal institutions, targeting [[criminality]], but they were in the relative{{Citation needed|date=December 2009}} minority. In the end, over 65,000 individuals were sterilized in 33 states under state compulsory sterilization programs in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;An overview of U.S. eugenics and sterilization is in ..&lt;/ref&gt;]&lt;ref name="Open WorldCat"&gt;{{cite book|last=Kevles|first=Daniel|title=In the name of eugenics: Genetics and the uses of human heredity|publisher=Knopf|location=New York|isbn=0-394-50702-9|edition=1st|date=April 12, 1985}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

The first state to introduce a compulsory sterilization bill was [[Michigan]], in 1897, but the proposed law failed to garner enough votes by legislators to be adopted. Eight years later [[Pennsylvania]]'s state legislators passed a sterilization bill that was vetoed by the governor. [[Indiana]] became the first state to enact sterilization legislation in 1907,&lt;ref&gt;The Indiana Supreme Court overturned the law in 1921 in ''Williams v. Smith'', 131 NE 2 (Ind.), 1921, text at [http://www.bioethics.iupui.edu/Eugenics/SMith%20vs%20Williams.pdf]&lt;/ref&gt; followed closely by [[Washington (U.S. state)|Washington]] and [[California]] in 1909. Sterilization rates across the country were relatively low (California being the sole exception) until the 1927 [[Supreme Court of the United States|Supreme Court]] case ''[[Buck v. Bell]]'' which legitimized the forced sterilization of patients at a [[Virginia]] home for the [[mental retardation|mentally retarded]]. The number of sterilizations performed per year increased until another Supreme Court case, ''[[Skinner v. Oklahoma]]'', 1942, complicated the legal situation by ruling against sterilization of criminals if the equal protection clause of the constitution was violated. That is, if sterilization was to be performed, then it could not exempt [[White-collar crime|white-collar criminals]].&lt;ref&gt;On the legal history of eugenic sterilization in the U.S., see Paul Lombardo, "Eugenic Sterilization Laws", essay in the [http://www.eugenicsarchive.org Eugenics Archive], available online at http://www.eugenicsarchive.org/html/eugenics/essay8text.html.&lt;/ref&gt;

Most sterilization laws could be divided into three main categories of motivations: ''eugenic'' (concerned with heredity), ''therapeutic'' (part of an even-then obscure medical theory that sterilization would lead to vitality), or ''punitive'' (as a punishment for criminals), though of course these motivations could be combined in practice and theory (sterilization of criminals could be both punitive and eugenic, for example). ''[[Buck v. Bell]]'' asserted only that eugenic sterilization was constitutional, whereas ''[[Skinner v. Oklahoma]]'' ruled specifically against punitive sterilization. Most operations only worked to prevent reproduction (such as severing the ''[[vas deferens]]'' in males), though some states ([[Oregon]] and [[North Dakota]] in particular) had laws which called for the use of [[castration]]. In general, most sterilizations were performed under ''eugenic'' statutes, in state-run psychiatric hospitals and homes for the mentally disabled.&lt;ref&gt;Philip Reilly, ''The surgical solution: a history of involuntary sterilization in the United States'' (Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press, 1991).&lt;/ref&gt; There was never a federal sterilization statute, though eugenicist [[Harry H. Laughlin]], whose state-level "Model Eugenical Sterilization Law" was the basis of the statute affirmed in ''Buck v. Bell'', proposed the structure of one in 1922.&lt;ref&gt;A copy of Harry Laughlin's "Model Eugenical Sterilization Law" (including the federal proposal) is available online at: http://www.people.fas.harvard.edu/~wellerst/laughlin/.&lt;/ref&gt;

After [[World War II]], public opinion towards eugenics and sterilization programs became more negative in the light of the connection with the [[genocide|genocidal]] policies of [[Nazi Germany]], though a significant number of sterilizations continued in a few states until the early 1960s. The [[Oregon]] Board of Eugenics, later renamed the Board of Social Protection, existed until 1983,&lt;ref name=oregonapology&gt;Governor John Kitzhaber, December 2, 2002. Proclamation of Human Rights Day, and apology for Oregon's forced sterilization of institutionalized patients, Salem, Oregon. [http://archivedwebsites.sos.state.or.us/Governor_Kitzhaber_2003/governor/speeches/s021202.htm]&lt;/ref&gt; with the last forcible sterilization occurring in 1981.&lt;ref&gt;Julie Sullivan. (2002). "[http://news.google.com/newspapers?id=ZFBWAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=jesDAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=6596,4132204 State will admit sterilization past]", ''Portland Oregonian'', November 15, 2002. (Mirrored in ''Eugene Register-Guard'', November 16, 2002, at [[Google News]].)&lt;/ref&gt;  The U.S. [[Commonwealth (U.S. insular area)|commonwealth]] [[Puerto Rico]] had a sterilization program as well. Some states continued to have sterilization laws on the books for much longer after that, though they were rarely if ever used. California sterilized more than any other state by a wide margin, and was responsible for over a third of all sterilization operations. Information about the California sterilization program was produced into book form and widely disseminated by eugenicists [[E.S. Gosney]] and [[Paul B. Popenoe]], which was said by the government of [[Adolf Hitler]] to be of key importance in proving that large-scale compulsory sterilization programs were feasible.&lt;ref&gt;On California sterilizations and their connection to the Nazi program, see: Stefan Kühl, ''The Nazi connection: Eugenics, American racism, and German National Socialism'' (New York: Oxford University Press, 1994); Alexandra Stern, ''Eugenic nation: faults and frontiers of better breeding in modern America'' (Berkeley: University of California Press, 2005); and Wendy Kline, ''Building a better race: gender, sexuality, and eugenics from the turn of the century to the baby boom'' (Berkeley: University of California Press, 2001).&lt;/ref&gt;
In recent years, the governors of many states have made public apologies for their past programs beginning with Virginia and followed by Oregon&lt;ref name=oregonapology/&gt; and California. None have offered to compensate those sterilized, however, citing that few are likely still living (and would of course have no affected offspring) and that inadequate records remain by which to verify them. At least one compensation case, ''[[Poe v. Lynchburg Training School &amp; Hospital]]'' (1981), was filed in the courts on the grounds that the sterilization law was unconstitutional. It was rejected because the law was no longer in effect at the time of the filing. However, the petitioners were granted some compensation as the stipulations of the law itself, which required informing the patients about their operations, had not been carried out in many cases.

The 27 states where sterilization laws remained on the books (though not all were still in use) in 1956 were: [[Arizona]], [[California]], [[Connecticut]], [[Delaware]], [[Georgia (U.S. state)|Georgia]], [[Idaho]], [[Indiana]], [[Iowa]], [[Kansas]], [[Maine]], [[Michigan]], [[Minnesota]], [[Mississippi]], [[Montana]], [[Nebraska]], [[New Hampshire]], [[North Carolina]], [[North Dakota]], [[Oklahoma]], [[Oregon]], [[South Carolina]], [[South Dakota]], [[Utah]], [[Vermont]], [[Virginia]], [[West Virginia]], [[Wisconsin]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.toolan.com/hitler/append1.html |title=Note that this is not a comprehensive list of states which had sterilization laws on the books at any given time (some states had their laws overturned in courts very early on) nor an indication of when states' laws were active (some ceased to be used much earlier) |publisher=Toolan.com |date= |accessdate=2012-07-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As of January 2011, discussions are underway regarding compensation for the victims of forced sterilization under the authorization of the [[Eugenics Board of North Carolina]]. Governor Bev Perdue formed the NC Justice for Sterilization Victims Foundation in 2010  in order "to provide justice and compensate victims who were forcibly sterilized by the State of North Carolina".&lt;ref&gt;North Carolina Department of Administration. NC Justice for Sterilization Victims Foundation. http://www.sterilizationvictims.nc.gov/&lt;/ref&gt; As of April 13, 2012, victims of forced sterilization in North Carolina have yet to be compensated.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=JOURNALNOW STAFF |title=Editorial: Planners of sterilization compensation should make process fast, smooth. Winston-Salem Journal|date=April 13, 2012 |url=http://www2.journalnow.com/news/opinion/2012/apr/13/wsopin01-editorial-planners-of-sterilization-compe-ar-2156521/ |publisher=Journalnow.com |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Governor Bev Perdue recommended providing each living victim with $50,000. However, Gov. Perdue and others are awaiting approval for the compensation and are working towards writing a bill. Discussions have yet to begin regarding compensation for victims of forced sterilization in other states. Other countries have yet to compensate victims of forced sterilization.

===Uzbekistan===
According to reports, as of 2012, forced and coerced sterilization are current Government policy in [[Uzbekistan]] for women with two or three children as a means of imposing [[Human population control|population control]] and to improve maternal mortality rates.&lt;ref name=bbc-news-2012-04-12&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/magazine-17612550 BBC News: Uzbekistan's policy of secretly sterilizing women] [[BBC]], published 2012-04-12, accessed 2012-04-12&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=bbc-cc-2012-04-12&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b01fjx63 Crossing Continents: Forced Sterilization in Uzbekistan] [[BBC]], published 2012-04-12, accessed 2012-04-12&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=moscow-2010-03-10&gt;[http://www.themoscowtimes.com/news/article/uzbeks-face-forced-sterilization/401279.html Uzbeks Face Forced Sterilization] [[The Moscow Times]] published 2010-03-10, accessed 2012-04-12&lt;/ref&gt; In November 2007, a report by the [[United Nations Committee Against Torture]] reported that "the large number of cases of forced sterilization and removal of reproductive organs of women at reproductive age after their first or second pregnancy indicate that the Uzbek government is trying to control the birth rate in the country" and noted that such actions were not against the national Criminal Code &lt;ref&gt;[http://www2.ohchr.org/english/bodies/cat/docs/ngos/omctuzbekistan39.pdf Shadow Report: UN Committee Against Torture] [[United Nations]], authors Rapid Response Group and OMCT, published November 2007, accessed 2012-04-12&lt;/ref&gt; in response to which the Uzbek delegation to the associated conference was "puzzled by the suggestion of forced sterilization, and could not see how this could be forced."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unhchr.ch/huricane/huricane.nsf/view01/DDAD7F2786699CA7C12573910072F598?opendocument Press Release: Committee Against Torture Hears Response of Uzbekistan] [[United Nations]], published 2007-10-12, accessed 2012-04-12&lt;/ref&gt;

Reports of forced sterilizations, [[Hysterectomy|hysterectomies]] and [[Intrauterine device|IUD]] insertions first emerged in 2005,&lt;ref name=bbc-news-2012-04-12 /&gt;&lt;ref name=bbc-cc-2012-04-12 /&gt;&lt;ref name=moscow-2010-03-10 /&gt;&lt;ref name=iwpr-2005-11-18&gt;[http://iwpr.net/report-news/birth-control-decree-uzbekistan Birth Control by Decree in Uzbekistan] [[Institute for War and Peace Reporting|IWPR Institute for War &amp; Peace Reporting]], published 2005-11-18, accessed 2012-04-12&lt;/ref&gt; although it is reported that the practice originated in the late 1990s,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/asia/uzbek-women-accuse-state-of-mass-sterilizations-2028987.html Uzbek women accuse state of mass sterilizations] [[The Independent]], published 2010-07-17, accessed 2012-04-12&lt;/ref&gt; with reports of a secret degree dating from 2000.&lt;ref name=iwpr-2005-11-18 /&gt; The current policy was allegedly instituted by [[Islam Karimov]] under Presidential [[Decree]] PP-1096, "on additional measures to protect the health of the mother and child, the formation of a healthy generation"&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.eurasianet.org/node/64549 Uzbekistan: Presidential Decree on Birth Rate Leads to Increased Sterilization | EurasiaNet.org] published 2011-11-14, accessed 2012-04-12&lt;/ref&gt; which came into force in 2009.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ourkids.uz/ Our Kids: EU Parliamentarians Applaud MCH Project in Uzbekistan], published 2010-10-28, accessed 2012-04-12&lt;/ref&gt; In 2005 Deputy Health Minister Assomidin Ismoilov confirmed that doctors in Uzbekistan were being held responsible for increased birth rates.&lt;ref name=iwpr-2005-11-18 /&gt;

Based on a report by journalist Natalia Antelava, doctors reported that the Ministry of Health told doctors they must perform surgical sterilizations on women. One doctor reported, “It's ruling number 1098 and it says that after two children, in some areas after three, a woman should be sterilized.”&lt;ref name="theworld.org"&gt;{{cite web |last=Hackel |first=Joyce |title=Doctors in Uzbekistan Say Government Forcibly Sterilizing Women |work=PRI's The World |date=April 12, 2012 |url=http://www.theworld.org/2012/04/doctors-in-uzbekistan-say-government-forcibly-sterilizing-women/ |publisher=Theworld.org |accessdate= }}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2010, the Ministry of Health passed a decree stating all clinics in Uzbekistan should have sterilization equipment ready for use. The same report also states that sterilization is to be done on a voluntary basis with the informed consent of the patient.&lt;ref name="theworld.org"/&gt; In the 2010 Human Rights Report of Uzbekistan, there were many reports of forced sterilization of women along with allegations of the government pressuring doctors to sterilize women in order to control the population.&lt;ref&gt;U.S. Department of State.Bureau of Democracy,Human Rights, and Labor. 2010 Country Reports on Human Rights Practices. April 2011.http://www.state.gov/j/drl/rls/hrrpt/2010/sca/154489.htm&lt;/ref&gt; Doctors also reported to Antelava that there are quotas they must reach every month on how many women they need to sterilize. These orders are passed on to them through their bosses and, allegedly, from the government.&lt;ref name="theworld.org"/&gt;

On May 15, 2012, during a meeting with the Russian president [[Vladimir Putin]] in [[Moscow]] the Uzbek president Islam Karimov said: "we are doing everything in our hands to make sure that the population growth rate [in Uzbekistan] does not exceed 1.2-1.3"&lt;ref name=RFE/RL&gt;{{cite news|title="Akhborot" censors Karimov|url=http://www.ozodlik.org/content/article/24584171.html|accessdate=17 May 2012|newspaper=[[RFE/RL]]'s Uzbek Service|date=17 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Uzbek version of [[RFE/RL]] reported that with this statement Karimov indirectly admitted that forced sterilization of women is indeed taking place in Uzbekistan.&lt;ref name=RFE/RL /&gt; The main Uzbek television channel, O'zbekiston, cut out Karimov's statement about the population growth rate while broadcasting his conversation with Putin.&lt;ref name=RFE/RL /&gt;

===Puerto Rico===
The United States, the Puerto Rican government, and the medical community began a program for the mass sterilization of women in [[Puerto Rico]].

Puerto Rico was first Claimed by Christopher Columbus in 1493 for Spain. Puerto Rico remained under Spanish control for the next 400 years although the Netherlands, France, and England made various attempts to control the island. Under the [[Treaty of Paris (1898)]] during the [[Spanish-American War]], Spain gave the island to the United States. In 1917, Puerto Ricans became United States citizens and the United States Congress began controlling a large amount of life in Puerto Rico.&lt;ref&gt;Puerto Rico. http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Puerto_Rico#Religion.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Puerto Rican government and population was suffering from economic problems, high unemployment rate, and poverty during the 1920s. The United States blamed overpopulation for these problems.&lt;ref name=Hoerlein&gt;{{cite web|last=Hoerlein|first=Sara|title=Female Sterilization in Puerto Rico|url=http://www.libertadlatina.org/US_Puerto_Rico_Forced_Sterilization_1.htm|accessdate=25 April 2012|year=2001}}&lt;/ref&gt; Contraception was illegal in the Puerto Rican colony which was largely due to the main religion of Puerto Rico: [[Catholicism]]. The [[Catholic Church]] teachings state that contraception and sterilization are sins against nature. Therefore, any form of contraception was illegal in Puerto Rico before the late 1930s.&lt;ref name=Maguire&gt;{{cite web|last=Maguire|first=Daniel|title=The Moderate Roman Catholic Position on Contraception and Abortion|url=http://www.religiousconsultation.org/News_Tracker/moderate_RC_position_on_contraception_abortion.htm|accessdate=25 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1937, the United States made contraceptives legal, initiating their plan for population control.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=U.S. eugenics policy evident in Puerto Rico as well as Guatemala |author=Melanie, Charlotte |date=October 15, 2010 |url= http://www.speroforum.com/site/article.aspidCategory=34&amp;idsub=127&amp;id=41704&amp;t=U.S.+eugenics+policy+evident+in+Puerto+Rico+as+well+as+Guatemala |publisher=Speroforum.com |accessdate= }}&lt;/ref&gt; 

The United States began governing Puerto Rico in 1898 and were immediately aware of the large, and ever increasing, population. A demographer from Puerto Rico reported in 1968 that women in the United States were ten time less likely to be sterilized than women from Puerto Rico. The U.S. began to worry about overpopulation of the small island that could potentially lead to a major decline socially and economically. Therefore, the U.S. began to enforce public policies in order to control the rapidly increasing population.&lt;ref name=Krase&gt;{{cite news|last=Krase|first=Katherine|title=The Politics of Women's Health: Sterilization Abuse|url=http://www.ourbodiesourselves.org/book/companion.asp?id=31&amp;compID=55|accessdate=25 April 2012|newspaper=Newsletter of the National Women’s Health Network|date=January/February 1996}}&lt;/ref&gt;

By 1965, demographer [[Harriet Presser]] reported, 34% of Puerto Rican mothers ages 20–49 had been sterilized, the highest rate ever documented for a population.&lt;ref&gt;Presser, Harriet B. 1969. "The Role of Sterilization in Controlling Puerto Rican Fertility." Population Studies 23(3).[http://www.jstor.org/stable/2172875]&lt;/ref&gt; Sterilization was so common that Puerto Rican women labeled it "la operacion", or the operation.&lt;ref name="Louis de Malave"&gt;{{cite web|last=Louis de Malave|first=Florita|title=Sterilizayion of Puerto Rican Women: A Selected, Partially Annotated Bibliography.|url=http://womenst.library.wisc.edu/bibliogs/puerwom.htm|accessdate=25 April 2012|month=May|year=1999}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many Puerto Rican women also began having "la operacion" due to healthcare worker visits whom advocated sterilization and already sterilized women whom were receiving favoritism in the work industry after their sterilization.&lt;ref name="Krase"/&gt; The government continued with their plan as stated in a report dated November 1973. The report, entitled "Opportunities for Education, Employment, and Training", was written by an economic policy group backed by the governor of Puerto Rico. This report explains alternatives for decreasing the Puerto Rican working class and a high unemployment rate was noted in the report as Puerto Rico's main problem.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=35% of Puerto Rican Women Sterilized|url=http://www.uic.edu/orgs/cwluherstory/CWLUArchive/puertorico.html|accessdate=25 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

A private organization opened twenty-three birth control clinics in 1937 and a bill was signed eliminating the laws making the advertisement of contraceptives and pregnancy prevention services a felony. Another 160 private and public birth control clinics were opened after another bill was signed authorizing the "Commissioner of Health in Puerto Rico to regulate the teaching and dissemination of eugenic principles, including contraception, to health centers and maternal hospitals".&lt;ref name=Hoerlein/&gt; Soon after, the United States government passed Law #136 which made sterilization legal for other than strictly medical reasons and advocated picking out the "unfit".&lt;ref name=Hoerlein/&gt;

In addition to the forced sterilization Puerto Rican women endured, they were also used as test subjects for birth control pills. In 1954 and 1955, two researchers, Gregory Pincus and John Rock, chose Puerto Rico as the site for large-scale human trials for an oral contraceptive. They had already achieved success in the human trials in Boston; however, in order to get the oral contraceptive in the market, they would need a larger trial. During that time, anti-birth control laws were non-existent in Puerto Rico and many birth control clinics were already riddled everywhere on the island. Also, with Puerto Rico being one of the most densely populated areas in the world during the 1950s, U.S. officials greatly supported birth control as a way to control the growing population.&lt;ref name="pbs.org"&gt;People and Events: The Puerto Rico Pill Trials. 2001. http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/amex/pill/peopleevents/e_puertorico.html&lt;/ref&gt;

Many women were eager to try the new drug that helped prevent pregnancy and the large population on the small island made it easier for Pincus and Rock to monitor the trials. Another factor in choosing Puerto Rican women as test subjects was the fact that they were all poor and uneducated. If uneducated women in Puerto Rico could follow the regimen for the oral contraceptive then an educated woman somewhere else in the world would be able to as well. Also, the success of the trials would prove that the use of the oral contraceptives would not be too complicated for women to use in other developing nations as well as the slums of some U.S. cities.&lt;ref name="pbs.org"/&gt;

The drug trials began in Rio Piedras in April 1965. The maximum amount of people needed immediately reached capacity once the trials began. Pincus and Rock immediately opened more trial locations. Rock chose a high dose of synthetic oral progesterone, Enovid, which was G.D Searle's name brand, the pharmaceutical company providing the drug. Later, synthetic estrogen was added to the pill due to its efficacy. Dr. Edris Rice-Wray, the medical director of Puerto Rico Family Planning Association and a Puerto Rico Medical School faculty member, headed the trials. She reported 100% efficacy rate of the pills a year after the study began but also reported "that 17% of the women in the study complained of nausea, dizziness, headaches, stomach pain and vomiting".&lt;ref name="pbs.org"/&gt; However, Pincus and Rock did not listen to Dr. Rice-Wray and the Pill was placed on the market.

The Puerto Rican women involved in the study were not told they were part of a drug trial. Researchers informed them that they would be receiving a drug that prevented pregnancy. They were not informed of the dangerous side effects that may occur or that taking the pill was experimental. Pincus, Rock, and the researchers and doctors involved in the drug trials have since been "accused of deceit, colonialism and the exploitation of poor women of color".&lt;ref name="pbs.org"/&gt;

===Other countries===
Eugenics programs including forced sterilization existed in most Northern European countries, as well as other more or less Protestant countries. Some programs, such as Canada's and Sweden's, lasted well into the 1970s. Other countries that had notably active sterilisation programmes include [[Denmark]], [[Norway]], [[Finland]], [[Estonia]], [[Switzerland]], [[Iceland]], and some countries in [[Latin America]] (including [[Panama]]).&lt;ref&gt;[[Gunnar Broberg]] and [[Nils Roll-Hansen]], eds., ''Eugenics And the Welfare State: Sterilization Policy in Denmark, Sweden, Norway, and Finland'' (Michigan State University Press, 2005).&lt;/ref&gt; In the [[United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland|United Kingdom]], [[Home Secretary]] [[Winston Churchill]] introduced a bill that included forced sterilisation. Writer [[G. K. Chesterton]] led a successful effort to defeat that clause of the 1913 Mental Deficiency Act. 

According to some testimonies, the [[Soviet Union]] allegedly imposed forced sterilisation on female workers deported from [[Romania]] to Soviet labour camps. This is said to have occurred after [[World War II]], when [[Romania]] was supposed to supply a reconstruction workforce (according to the armistice convention).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jurnalul.ro/index.php?section=rubrici&amp;article_id=29282 A link to the testimony of such a deportee] (in [[Romanian language|Romanian]]).&lt;/ref&gt; However, no court decisions or formal investigations of these allegations are known for the moment.

==See also==
{{Portal|Genocide}}
* [[Chemical castration]]
* [[Eugenics]]
* [[Medical law]]
* [[Nazism]]
* [[Reproductive rights]]
* [[The Yogyakarta Principles]]
* [[Forced pregnancy]]

==References==
{{Cleanup-link rot|date=July 2012}}
{{Reflist|colwidth=35em}}

== Further reading ==
* "B.C. faces forced sterilization lawsuit". ''CBC News''. February 7, 2003. Canadian Broadcasting Corporation. Accessed April 13, 2006.
* Clarke, Nic. "Sacred Daemons: Exploring British Columbian Society's Perceptions of 'Mentally Deficient' Children, 1870-1930." ''BC Studies'' 144 (2004/2005): 61-89.
* Dowbiggin, Ian Robert. ''Keeping America Sane: Psychiatry and Eugenics in the United States and Canada 1880-1940''. Ithaca: Cornell University Press, 2003.
* Grekul, Jana., Krahn, H., Odynak, D.. "Sterilizing the 'Feeble-minded': Eugenics in Alberta, Canada, 1929-1972." ''J. Hist. Sociol.'' 17:4 (2004): 358-384.
* Manitoba Law Reform Commission. ''Discussion Paper on Sterilization of Minors and Mentally Incompetent Adults''. Winnipeg: 1990.
* Manitoba Law Reform Commission. ''Report on Sterilization and Legal Incompetence''. Winnipeg: 1993.
* McLaren, Angus. ''Our Own Master Race: Eugenics in Canada, 1885-1945''. Toronto: McClelland &amp; Stewart, 1990.
* Rosen, Christine. ''Preaching Eugenics: Religious Leaders and the American Eugenics Movement''. Oxford [England]; New York: Oxford University Press, 2004.
*{{Cite book |title=Defending the Master Race: Conservation, Eugenics, and the Legacy of Madison Grant |last=Spiro |first=Jonathan P. |publisher=Univ. of Vermont Press |year=2009 |isbn=978-1-58465-715-6 |laysummary=http://www.upne.com/1-58465-715-4.html |laydate=September 29, 2010 |ref=harv }}
*{{Cite book |title=The funding of Scientific Racism: Wickliffe Draper and the Pioneer Fund |last=Tucker |first=William H. |authorlink=William H. Tucker |publisher=[[University of Illinois Press]] |year=2007 |isbn=978-0-252-07463-9 |laysummary=http://www.press.uillinois.edu/books/catalog/65rwe7dm9780252074639.html |laydate=September 4, 2010 |ref=harv }}
* Wahlsten, Douglas. "Leilani Muir versus the Philosopher Kings: Eugenics on trial in Alberta." ''Genetica'' 99 (1997): 195-198.
* "Nine women sterilized in B.C. have lawsuits settled for $450,000". ''The Vancouver Sun'''. December 21, 2005.

==External links==
*[http://www.webster.edu/~woolflm/forcedsterilization.html Forced Sterilization]
*[http://www.healthsystem.virginia.edu/internet/library/historical/eugenics/index.cfm "Three Generations, No Imbeciles: Virginia, Eugenics, and ''Buck v. Bell''"] (USA)
*[http://www.eugenicsarchive.org/eugenics/ Eugenics Archive] (USA)
*[http://www.ushmm.org/museum/exhibit/online/deadlymedicine/ "Deadly Medicine: Creating the Master Race"] (United States Holocaust Memorial Museum exhibit) (Germany, USA)
*[http://home.earthlink.net/~thetabus/eugenics/ Eugenics - A Psychiatric Responsibility] (History of Eugenics in Germany)
*[http://www.catholicculture.org/docs/doc_view.cfm?recnum=615 "Sterilization Law in Germany"] (includes text of 1933 German law in appendix)
*[http://www.crin.org/docs/resources/treaties/crc.12/China_CFT2_NGO_Report.pdf "Genocide in Tibet - Children of Despair"](NGO Group for the Convention on the Rights of the Child)

{{DEFAULTSORT:Compulsory Sterilization}}
[[Category:Birth control]]
[[Category:Disability in law]]
[[Category:Eugenics]]
[[Category:History of psychiatry]]
[[Category:Penology]]
[[Category:Punishments]]
[[Category:Reproductive rights]]
[[Category:Sterilization]]

[[ca:Esterilització forçosa]]
[[de:Sterilisationsgesetze]]
[[es:Esterilización forzosa]]
[[fr:Stérilisation contrainte]]
[[he:עיקור כפוי]]
[[ja:断種]]
[[pl:Przymusowa sterylizacja]]
[[pt:Esterilização compulsiva]]
[[ru:Принудительная стерилизация]]
[[simple:Compulsory sterilization]]
[[sv:Tvångssterilisering]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>