<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20101115095422|396878485" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="720902" pageid="720902" ns="0" title="Compulsory sterilization"><revisions><rev timestamp="2010-11-17T19:40:46Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Discrimination sidebar}}

'''Compulsory sterilization''' (or '''sterilisation''')  also known as  '''forced sterilization'''  programs are government policies which attempt to force people to undergo surgical [[sterilization (surgical procedure)|sterilization]]. In the first half of the twentieth century, many such programs were instituted in countries around the world, usually as part of [[eugenics]] programs intended to prevent the reproduction and multiplication of members of the population considered to be carriers of defective [[Genetics|genetic]] traits. Forced sterilization has been recognized as [[crime against humanity]] if the action is part of a widespread or systematic practice by the [[Rome Statute of the International Criminal Court|Rome Statute]] Explanatory Memorandum, which defines the jurisdiction of the [[International Criminal Court]].&lt;ref name="Horton"&gt;As quoted by Guy Horton in ''[http://www.ibiblio.org/obl/docs3/Horton-2005.pdf Dying Alive - A Legal Assessment of Human Rights Violations in Burma]'' April 2005, co-Funded by The Netherlands Ministry for Development Co-Operation. See section "12.52 Crimes against humanity", Page 201. He references RSICC/C, Vol. 1 p. 360&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://untreaty.un.org/cod/icc/statute/romefra.htm Rome Statute of the International Criminal Court&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

==By country==
===Canada===
{{Main|Compulsory sterilization in Canada}}
Although less well-known{{Says who|date=November 2010}} than other eugenic sterilization programs, two Canadian provinces (Alberta and British Columbia) performed compulsory sterilization programs with eugenic aims. Canadian compulsory sterilization operated via the same overall mechanisms of [[institutionalization]], [[judgement]], and [[surgery]] as the American system{{why?|date=November 2010}}. One notable difference is in the treatment of non-insane criminals. Canadian legislation never allowed for punitive sterilization of inmates.

===Czechoslovakia, Czech Republic===
[[Czechoslovakia]] carried out a policy of sterilization of [[roma (Romani subgroup)|Roma]] women, starting in 1973.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/6409699.stm Sterilised Roma accuse Czechs], [[BBC]], 12 March 2007 {{en icon}}&lt;/ref&gt; The dissidents of the [[Charter 77]] denounced it in 1977-78 as a "[[genocide]]", but the practice continued through the [[Velvet Revolution]] of 1989.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newsdesk.org/archives/003850.html For Gypsies, Eugenics is a Modern Problem - Czech Practice Dates to Soviet Era], [[Newsdesk]], June 12, 2006 {{en icon}}&lt;/ref&gt; A 2005 report by the Czech government's independent ombudsman, [[Otakar Motejl]], identified dozens of cases of coercive sterilization between 1979 and 2001, and called for criminal investigations and possible prosecution against several health care workers and administrators.&lt;ref name=Czech /&gt;

===Germany===&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[January 1]] --&gt;
{{Main|Nazi eugenics}}
[[File:Wir stehen nicht allein.jpg|thumb|left|250px|"We do not stand alone": Nazi poster from 1936 with flags of other countries with compulsory sterilization legislation.]]

The most infamous sterilization program of the 20th century took place under the [[Third Reich]]. One of the first acts by [[Adolf Hitler]] after achieving total control over the [[Germany|German]] state was to pass the [[Law for the Prevention of Hereditarily Diseased Offspring]] (''Gesetz zur Verhütung erbkranken Nachwuchses'') in July 1933. The law was signed in by Hitler himself, and over 200 eugenic courts were created specifically as a result of the law. Under the German law, all doctors in the Reich were required to report patients of theirs who were [[mentally retarded]], [[mentally ill]] (including [[schizophrenia]] and [[manic depression]]), [[epilepsy|epileptic]], blind, deaf, or physically deformed, and a steep monetary penalty was imposed for any patients who were not properly reported. Individuals suffering from [[alcoholism]] or [[Huntington's disease|Huntington's Disease]] could also be sterilized. The individual's case was then presented in front of a court of [[Nazism|Nazi]] officials and public health officers who would review their medical records, take testimony from friends and colleagues, and eventually decide whether or not to order a sterilization operation performed on the individual, using force if necessary. Though not explicitly covered by the law, 400 mixed-race "[[Rhineland Bastard]]s" were also sterilized beginning in 1937.&lt;ref&gt;Robert Proctor, ''Racial hygiene: Medicine under the Nazis'' (Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press, 1988), and Gisela Bock, "Nazi sterilization and reproductive policies" in Dieter Kuntz, ed., ''Deadly medicine: creating the master race'' (Washington, D.C.: United States Holocaust Memorial Museum, 2004).&lt;/ref&gt;

By the end of [[World War II]], over 400,000 individuals were sterilized under the German law and its revisions, most within its first four years of being enacted. When the issue of compulsory sterilization was brought up at the [[Nuremberg trials]] after the war, many Nazis defended their actions on the matter by indicating that it was the United States itself from whom they had taken inspiration. The Nazis had many other eugenics-inspired [[racial policy of Nazi Germany|racial policies]], including their [[T-4 Euthanasia Program|"euthanasia" program]] in which around 70,000 people institutionalized or suffering from birth defects were murdered.&lt;ref&gt;[[Ian Kershaw]], ''Hitler: A Profile in Power'', Chapter VI, first section (London, 1991, rev. 2001)&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Japan ===
{{See|Eugenics in Showa Japan}}

In the first part of the [[Showa era]], Japanese governments promoted increasing the number of healthy Japanese, while simultaneously decreasing the number of people suffering mental retardation, disability, genetic disease and other conditions that led to inferiority in the Japanese gene pool.&lt;ref&gt;"The National Eugenic Law" The 107th law that Japanese Government promulgated in 1940　(国民優生法) 第一条　本法ハ悪質ナル遺伝性疾患ノ素質ヲ有スル者ノ増加ヲ防遏スルト共ニ健全ナル素質ヲ有スル者ノ増加ヲ図リ以テ国民素質ノ向上ヲ期スルコトヲ目的トス, Kimura, Jurisprudence in Genetics, http://www.bioethics.jp/licht_genetics.html&lt;/ref&gt;

The ''Leprosy Prevention laws'' of 1907, 1931 and 1953, permitted the segregation of patients in sanitariums where forced abortions and sterilization were common and authorized punishment of patients "disturbing peace".&lt;ref&gt;''Hansen's sanitarium were houses of horrors,'' http://search.japantimes.co.jp/cgi-bin/nn20050128a1.html, ''Abolition of leprosy isolation policy in Japan'', http://goliath.ecnext.com/coms2/summary_0199-1556743_ITM&lt;/ref&gt; Under the colonial Korean ''Leprosy prevention ordinance'', Korean patients were also subjected to hard labor.&lt;ref&gt;''Korean Hansens patients seek redress'', http://search.japantimes.co.jp/cgi-bin/nn20040226a4.html&lt;/ref&gt;

The ''Race Eugenic Protection Law'' was submitted from 1934 to 1938 to the Diet. After four amendments, this draft was promulgated as a ''National Eugenic Law''  in 1940 by the [[Konoe]] government.&lt;ref&gt;"The Eugenic Protection Law" (国民優生法)The 107th law that Japanese Government promulgated in 1940　(国民優生法) 第二条　本法ニ於テ優生手術ト称スルハ生殖ヲ不能ナラシムル手術又ハ処置ニシテ命令ヲ以テ定ムルモノヲ謂フ , http://www.res.otemon.ac.jp/~yamamoto/be/BE_law_04.htm&lt;/ref&gt; According to Matsubara Yoko, from 1940 to 1945, sterilization was done to 454 Japanese persons under this law.&lt;ref&gt;[http://tateiwa.kir.jp/1990/971100my.htm 「優生問題を考える（四）──国民優生法と優生保護法] Matsubara Yoko - Research of Eugenics problem
(Professor of [[Ritsumeikan University]], researcher of Gender-blind and Eugenics.)&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the ''Eugenic Protection Law'' (1948), sterilization could be enforced on criminals "with genetic predisposition to commit crime", patients with genetic diseases such as total color-blindness, [[hemophilia]], [[albinism]] and [[ichthyosis]], and mental affections such as [[schizophrenia]], [[manic-depression]] and [[epilepsy]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.soshiren.org/shiryou/yuseihogohou.html SOSHIREN / 資料・法律−優生保護法&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; The mental sicknesses were added in 1952.

===India===
India's state of emergency [[The Emergency (India)|between 1975 and 1977]] included an infamous family planning initiative beginning April 1976, which involved the vasectomy of thousands of men and tubal ligation of women, either for payment or under coercive conditions. The son of then-Prime Minister [[Indira Gandhi]], [[Sanjay Gandhi]], was largely blamed for what turned out to be a failed program.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news | title=The Indira enigma | date=May 11, 2001 | accessdate=2006-07-28 | publisher=[[Frontline (US TV series)|Frontline]] | url=http://www.hinduonnet.com/fline/fl1809/18090740.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt; A strong backlash against any initiative associated with family planning followed the highly controversial program, which continues into the 21st century.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news | title=Male involvement and contraceptive methods for men |date = September 1996| accessdate=2006-07-28 | publisher=[[Frontline (US TV series)|Frontline]] | url=http://www.malecontraceptives.org/articles/ringheim_article.php}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===China===
Coercive sterilization to enforce the [[one child policy]] has occurred in China. This is not permitted by the law, and some local officials have been jailed for their actions.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news | title=China acts on forced abortion | date=September 20, 2005 | accessdate=2008-07-08 | publisher=[[BBC]] | url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/asia-pacific/4262890.stm}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2010, [[Amnesty International]] accused authorities in [[Puning]] of compelling people to be sterilized by imprisoning their elderly relatives.&lt;ref&gt;[[The Independent]], [http://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/asia/chinese-state-holds-parents-hostage-in-sterilisation-drive-1947236.html "Chinese state holds parents hostage in sterilisation drive"], 17 April 2010&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news | title=China To Sterilise 10,000 To Curb Births | date=April 23, 2010 | accessdate=2010-05-09 | publisher=[[Sky News]] | url=http://news.sky.com/skynews/Home/World-News/China-Authorities-Plan-To-Sterilise-10000-People-To-Ensure-They-Meet-Family-Planning-Targets/Article/201004415613125?f=rss}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Sweden===
In 1997, following the publication of articles by [[Maciej Zaremba]] in the ''[[Dagens Nyheter]]'' daily, widespread attention was given to the fact that [[Sweden]] once operated a strong sterilization program, which was active primarily from the late 1930s until the mid 1950s. A governmental commission was set up, and finished its inquiry in 2000.&lt;ref name=Czech /&gt;

The eugenistic legislation was enacted in 1934 and was formally abolished in 1976. According to the 2000 governmental report, 21,000 were estimated to have been forcibly sterilized, 6,000 were coerced into a 'voluntary' sterilization while the nature of a further 4,000 cases could not be determined.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.regeringen.se/content/1/c4/28/64/212fc81a.pdf Steriliseringsfrågan i Sverige 1935 - 1975], SOU 2000:20, in Swedish with an English summary.&lt;/ref&gt; The Swedish state subsequently paid out damages to many of the victims.

The program was meant primarily to prevent mental illness and disease. In 1922 the [[Statens institut för rasbiologi|State Institute of Racial Biology]] was founded in Uppsala and in 1927 Parliament began to deal with the first legal provisions on sterilisation.&lt;ref name=Czech&gt;[http://www.ochrance.cz/en/dokumenty/dokument.php?doc=400 Final Statement of the Public Defender of Rights in the Matter of Sterilisations Performed in Contravention of the Law and Proposed Remedial Measures], Czech government, 2005 {{en icon}}&lt;/ref&gt; A new draft was produced in 1932, already taking into account sterilisation for general socio-prophylactic reasons, and even without the consent of the person concerned.&lt;ref name=Czech /&gt; The draft was adopted in 1934.&lt;ref name=Czech /&gt; Another law, passed in 1941, did not include any age of consent limit.

From 1950, the number of eugenic sterilisations under the 1935 legal provisions gradually decreased and between 1960 and 1970 voluntary sterilisations based on the wishes and in the interest of the persons concerned prevailed.&lt;ref name=Czech /&gt;
As in Canada and the US, racial politics also became involved, as there was a strong belief in the connection between race and genetic integrity among leading scientists and those carrying out the sterilizations. The [[Swedish Racial Hygiene Society]] had been founded in Stockholm in 1909, and the 1934 works by [[Alva Myrdal|Alva]] and [[Gunnar Myrdal]] was very significant in promoting the eugenic tendencies in practical politics.&lt;ref name=Czech /&gt; The authors theorized that the best solution for the Swedish welfare state ("[[Folkhemmet|folkhem]]") was to prevent at the outset the hereditary transfer of undesirable characteristics that caused the individual affected to become sooner or later a burden on society. The authors therefore proposed a "corrective social reform” under which sterilisation was to prevent "unviable individuals” from spreading their undesirable traits.&lt;ref name=Czech /&gt; In the later decades it was primarily the mentally ill who were forcibly sterilized.

===Switzerland===
In October 1999, [[Margrith von Felten]] suggested to the [[National Council of Switzerland]] in the form of a general proposal to adopt legal regulations that would enable reparation for persons sterilised against their will. According to the proposal, reparation was to be provided to persons who had undergone the intervention without their consent or who had consented to sterilisation under coercion. According to Margrith von Felten:
{{cquote|The history of eugenics in Switzerland remains insufficiently explored. Research programmes are in progress. However, individual studies and facts are already available. For example:

The report of the Institute for the History of Medicine and Public Health "Mental Disability and Sexuality. Legal Sterilisation in the [[Vaud]] Canton between 1928 and 1985" points out that coercive sterilisations took place until the 1980s. The act on coercive sterilisations of the Vaud Canton was the first law of this kind in the European context.

Hans Wolfgang Maier, head of the Psychiatric Clinic in Zurich pointed out in a report from the beginning of the century that 70% to 80% of [[abortion|terminations]] were linked to sterilisation by doctors. In the period from 1929 to 1931, 480 women and 15 men were sterilised in Zurich in connection with termination.

Following agreements between doctors and authorities such as the 1934 "Directive For Surgical Sterilisation" of the Medical Association in Basle, eugenic indication to sterilisation was recognised as admissible.

A statistical evaluation of the sterilisations performed in the Basle women's hospital between 1920 and 1934 shows a remarkable increase in sterilisations for a psychiatric indication after 1929 and a steep increase in 1934, when a coercive sterilisation act came into effect in nearby National Socialist Germany.

A study by the Swiss Nursing School in Zurich, published in 1991, documents that 24 mentally-disabled women aged between 17 and 25 years were sterilised between 1980 and 1987. Of these 24 sterilisations, just one took place at the young woman's request.

Having evaluated sources primarily from the 1930s (psychiatric files, official directives, court files, etc.), historians have documented that the requirement for free consent to sterilisation was in most of cases not satisfied. Authorities obtained the "[[Informed consent|consent]]" required by the law partly by persuasion, and partly by enforcing it through coercion and threats. Thus the recipients of social benefits were threatened with removal of the benefits, women were exposed to a choice between placement in an institution or sterilisation, and abortions were permitted only when women simultaneously consented to sterilisation.

More than fifty years after ending the National Socialist dictatorship in Germany, in which racial murder, euthanasia and coerced sterilisations belonged to the political programme, it is clear that eugenics, with its idea of "[[life unworthy of life]]" and "racial purity" permeated even democratic countries. The idea that a "healthy nation" should be achieved through targeted medical/social measures was designed and politically implemented in many European countries and in the U.S.A in the first half of this century. It is a policy incomparable with the inconceivable horrors of the Nazi rule; yet it is clear that authorities and the medical community were guilty of the methods and measures applied, i.e. coerced sterilisations, prohibitions of marriages and child removals – serious violations of human rights.&lt;ref name=Czech /&gt;}}

Switzerland refused, however, to vote a reparations Act.

===United States===
[[File:Sterilization states.jpg|250px|thumb|right|A poster from a 1921 [[eugenics]] conference displays which U.S. states had by then implemented sterilization legislation.]]

The United States was the first country to concertedly undertake compulsory sterilization programs for the purpose of eugenics.&lt;ref&gt;Eugenics And Its Relevance To Contemporary Health Care, Rachel Iredale, Nursing Ethics 2000 7 (3), 0969-7330(00)NE346OA © 2000 Arnold&lt;/ref&gt; The heads of the program were avid believers in eugenics and frequently argued for their program. It was shut down due to ethical problems. The principal targets of the American program were the [[mental retardation|mentally retarded]] and the [[mental illness|mentally ill]], but also targeted under many state laws were the deaf, the blind, people with [[epilepsy]], and the physically deformed. According to the activist [[Angela Davis]], [[Indigenous people of the United States|Native Americans]], as well as African-American women&lt;ref&gt;[[Angela Davis]], ''Women, Race and Class'' (1981) ISBN 0-394-71351-6&lt;/ref&gt; were sterilized against their will in many states, often without their knowledge while they were in a hospital for other reasons (e.g. childbirth). However, citing a [[Government Accountability Office]] investigation which found no evidence to support Davis's claims, [[The Chicago Reader]] also noted that the rate of sterilizations for all American women (or their partners) was 41% as of 1995,{{Citation needed|date=June 2010}} compared to only "at least 25%" of Native American women receiving sterilization as shown by the activist and physician Connie Redbird Uri Pinkerman, whose work prompted the GAO investigation;{{Citation needed|date=June 2010}} The Chicago Reader also claimed that overall, "Accounts in the medical journals suggest that surgical sterilization rates for Native Americans rose during this period but were lower than for the general population. (IHS data for 1975 indicates that the tubal ligation rate was about the same as for the non-Native American population, while the hysterectomy rate was much lower)".&lt;ref&gt;http://www.straightdope.com/columns/read/2384/were-40-of-native-american-women-forcibly-sterilized-in-the-1970s&lt;/ref&gt; Some sterilizations took place in prisons and other penal institutions, targeting [[criminality]], but they were in the relative{{Citation needed|date=December 2009}} minority. In the end, over 65,000 individuals were sterilized in 33 states under state compulsory sterilization programs in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;An overview of U.S. eugenics and sterilization is in [[Daniel Kevles]], ''In the name of eugenics: Genetics and the uses of human heredity'' (New York: Knopf, 1985).&lt;/ref&gt;

The first state to introduce a compulsory sterilization bill was [[Michigan]], in 1897 but the proposed law failed to garner enough votes by legislators to be adopted. Eight years later [[Pennsylvania]]'s state legislators passed a sterilization bill that was vetoed by the governor. [[Indiana]] became the first state to enact sterilization legislation in 1907,&lt;ref&gt;The Indiana Supreme Court overturned the law in 1921 in ''Williams v. Smith'', 131 NE 2 (Ind.), 1921, text at [http://www.bioethics.iupui.edu/Eugenics/SMith%20vs%20Williams.pdf]&lt;/ref&gt;  followed closely by [[Washington (U.S. state)|Washington]] and [[California]] in 1909. Sterilization rates across the country were relatively low (California being the sole exception) until the 1927 [[Supreme Court of the United States|Supreme Court]] case ''[[Buck v. Bell]]'' which legitimized the forced sterilization of patients at a [[Virginia]] home for the [[mental retardation|mentally retarded]]. The number of sterilizations performed per year increased until another Supreme Court case, ''[[Skinner v. Oklahoma]]'', [[1942]], complicated the legal situation by ruling against sterilization of criminals if the equal protection clause of the constitution was violated. That is, if sterilization was to be performed, then it could not exempt [[White-collar crime|white-collar criminals]].&lt;ref&gt;On the legal history of eugenic sterilization in the U.S., see Paul Lombardo, "Eugenic Sterilization Laws", essay in the [http://www.eugenicsarchive.org Eugenics Archive], available online at http://www.eugenicsarchive.org/html/eugenics/essay8text.html.&lt;/ref&gt;

Most sterilization laws could be divided into three main categories of motivations: ''eugenic'' (concerned with heredity), ''therapeutic'' (part of an even-then obscure medical theory that sterilization would lead to vitality), or ''punitive'' (as a punishment for criminals), though of course these motivations could be combined in practice and theory (sterilization of criminals could be both punitive and eugenic, for example). ''[[Buck v. Bell]]'' asserted only that eugenic sterilization was constitutional, whereas ''[[Skinner v. Oklahoma]]'' ruled specifically against punitive sterilization. Most operations only worked to prevent reproduction (such as severing the ''[[vas deferens]]'' in males), though some states ([[Oregon]] and [[North Dakota]] in particular) had laws which called for the use of [[castration]]. In general, most sterilizations were performed under ''eugenic'' statutes, in state-run psychiatric hospitals and homes for the mentally disabled.&lt;ref&gt;Philip Reilly, ''The surgical solution: a history of involuntary sterilization in the United States'' (Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press, 1991).&lt;/ref&gt; There was never a federal sterilization statute, though eugenicist [[Harry H. Laughlin]], whose state-level "Model Eugenical Sterilization Law" was the basis of the statute affirmed in ''Buck v. Bell'', proposed the structure of one in 1922.&lt;ref&gt;A copy of Harry Laughlin's "Model Eugenical Sterilization Law" (including the federal proposal) is available online at: http://www.people.fas.harvard.edu/~wellerst/laughlin/.&lt;/ref&gt;

After [[World War II]], public opinion towards eugenics and sterilization programs became more negative in the light of the connection with the [[genocide|genocidal]] policies of [[Nazi Germany]], though a significant number of sterilizations continued in a few states until the early 1960s. The [[Oregon]] Board of Eugenics, later renamed the Board of Social Protection, existed until 1983, with the last forcible sterilization occurring in 1981.&lt;ref&gt;Julie Sullivan, "State will admit sterilization past", ''Portland Oregonian'' (November 15, 2002). Available online at http://www.people1.org/eugenics/eugenics_article_6.htm. {{Dead link|date=November 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The U.S. [[Commonwealth (U.S. insular area)|commonwealth]] [[Puerto Rico]] had a sterilization program as well. Some states continued to have sterilization laws on the books for much longer after that, though they were rarely if ever used. California sterilized more than any other state by a wide margin, and was responsible for over a third of all sterilization operations. Information about the California sterilization program was produced into book form and widely disseminated by eugenicists [[E.S. Gosney]] and [[Paul B. Popenoe]], which was said by the government of [[Adolf Hitler]] to be of key importance in proving that large-scale compulsory sterilization programs were feasible.&lt;ref&gt;On California sterilizations and their connection to the Nazi program, see: Stefan Kühl, ''The Nazi connection: Eugenics, American racism, and German National Socialism'' (New York: Oxford University Press, 1994); Alexandra Stern, ''Eugenic nation: faults and frontiers of better breeding in modern America'' (Berkeley: University of California Press, 2005); and Wendy Kline, ''Building a better race: gender, sexuality, and eugenics from the turn of the century to the baby boom'' (Berkeley: University of California Press, 2001).&lt;/ref&gt;
In recent years, the governors of many states have made public apologies for their past programs beginning with Virginia and followed by Oregon and California. None have offered to compensate those sterilized, however, citing that few are likely still living (and would of course have no affected offspring) and that inadequate records remain by which to verify them. At least one compensation case, ''[[Poe v. Lynchburg Training School &amp; Hospital]]'' (1981), was filed in the courts on the grounds that the sterilization law was unconstitutional. It was rejected because the law was no longer in effect at the time of the filing. However, the petitioners were granted some compensation as the stipulations of the law itself, which required informing the patients about their operations, had not been carried out in many cases.

The 27 states where sterilization laws remained on the books (though not all were still in use) in 1956 were: [[Arizona]], [[California]], [[Connecticut]], [[Delaware]], [[Georgia (U.S. state)|Georgia]], [[Idaho]], [[Indiana]], [[Iowa]], [[Kansas]], [[Maine]], [[Michigan]], [[Minnesota]], [[Mississippi]], [[Montana]], [[Nebraska]], [[New Hampshire]], [[North Carolina]], [[North Dakota]], [[Oklahoma]], [[Oregon]], [[South Carolina]], [[South Dakota]], [[Utah]], [[Vermont]], [[Virginia]], [[West Virginia]], [[Wisconsin]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.toolan.com/hitler/append1.html. Note that this is not a comprehensive list of states which had sterilization laws on the books at any given time (some states had their laws overturned in courts very early on) nor an indication of when states' laws were active (some ceased to be used much earlier).&lt;/ref&gt;

===Other countries===
Eugenics programs including forced sterilization existed in most Northern European countries, as well as other more or less Protestant countries. Some programs, such as Canada's and Sweden's, lasted well into the 1970s. Other countries that had notably active sterilization programs include [[Australia]], [[Norway]], [[Finland]], [[Estonia]], [[Switzerland]], [[Iceland]], and some countries in [[Latin America]] (including [[Panama]]).&lt;ref&gt;[[Gunnar Broberg]] and [[Nils Roll-Hansen]], eds., ''Eugenics And the Welfare State: Sterilization Policy in Denmark, Sweden, Norway, and Finland'' (Michigan State University Press, 2005).&lt;/ref&gt; In the [[United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland|United Kingdom]], [[Home Secretary]] [[Winston Churchill]] introduced a bill that included forced sterilization. Writer [[G. K. Chesterton]] led a successful effort to defeat that clause of the 1913 Mental Deficiency Act. In [[Peru]], former president [[Alberto Fujimori]] (1990–2000) pressured 200,000 indigenous people in rural areas (mainly [[Quechuas]] and [[Aymara]]s) into being sterilized.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news | title=Mass sterilisation scandal shocks Peru | date=July 24, 2002 | accessdate=2006-04-30 | publisher=[[BBC News]] | url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/americas/2148793.stm}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to some testimonies, the [[Soviet Union]] allegedly imposed forced sterilization on female workers deported from [[Romania]] to Soviet labor camps. This is said to have occurred after [[World War II]], when [[Romania]] was supposed to supply a reconstruction workforce (according to the armistice convention).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jurnalul.ro/index.php?section=rubrici&amp;article_id=29282 A link to the testimony of such a deportee] (in [[Romanian language|Romanian]]).&lt;/ref&gt; However, no court decisions or formal investigations of these allegations are known for the moment.

A Dutch Labour Party MP has recently proposed ''temporary (two year) compulsory contraception'', (not sterilization), of women who have a legally proven history of child abuse. The method would be via injection of anti-conception medicinal drugs, every six months. If the woman or parents have shown progress during that time, this would be reversed.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EuKG1VHEugw&amp;feature=PlayList&amp;p=7B5B009BA35FFF2F&amp;index=0&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.nrc.nl/international/Features/article2251634.ece/Should_drug-addicted_mothers_be_stopped_from_having_children&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Genocide}}
* [[Chemical castration]]
* [[Medical law]]
* [[Nazism]]
* [[Reproductive rights]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
* Clarke, Nic. "Sacred Daemons: Exploring British Columbian Society's Perceptions of 'Mentally Deficient' Children, 1870-1930." ''BC Studies'' 144 (2004/2005): 61-89.
* Dowbiggin, Ian Robert. ''Keeping America Sane: Psychiatry and Eugenics in the United States and Canada 1880-1940''. Ithaca: Cornell University Press, 2003.
* Grekul, Jana., Krahn, H., Odynak, D.. "Sterilizing the 'Feeble-minded': Eugenics in Alberta, Canada, 1929-1972." ''J. Hist. Sociol.'' 17:4 (2004): 358-384.
* Manitoba Law Reform Commission. ''Discussion Paper on Sterilization of Minors and Mentally Incompetent Adults''. Winnipeg: 1990.
* Manitoba Law Reform Commission. ''Report on Sterilization and Legal Incompetence''. Winnipeg: 1993.
* McLaren, Angus. ''Our Own Master Race: Eugenics in Canada, 1885-1945''. Toronto: McClelland &amp; Stewart, 1990.
* Rosen, Christine. ''Preaching Eugenics: Religious Leaders and the American Eugenics Movement''. Oxford [England]; New York: Oxford University Press, 2004.
* Wahlsten, Douglas. "Leilani Muir versus the Philosopher Kings: Eugenics on trial in Alberta." ''Genetica'' 99 (1997): 195-198.
* "B.C. faces forced sterilization lawsuit". ''CBC News''. February 7, 2003. Canadian Broadcasting Corporation. Accessed April 13, 2006.
* "Nine women sterilized in B.C. have lawsuits settled for $450,000". ''The Vancouver Sun'''. December 21, 2005.

==External links==
*[http://www.healthsystem.virginia.edu/internet/library/historical/eugenics/index.cfm "Three Generations, No Imbeciles: Virginia, Eugenics, and ''Buck v. Bell''"] (USA)
*[http://www.eugenicsarchive.org/eugenics/ Eugenics Archive] (USA)
*[http://www.ushmm.org/museum/exhibit/online/deadlymedicine/ "Deadly Medicine: Creating the Master Race"] (United States Holocaust Memorial Museum exhibit) (Germany, USA)
*[http://home.earthlink.net/~thetabus/eugenics/ Eugenics - A Psychiatric Responsibility] (History of Eugenics in Germany)
*[http://www.catholicculture.org/docs/doc_view.cfm?recnum=615 "Sterilization Law in Germany"] (includes text of 1933 German law in appendix)
*[http://www.crin.org/docs/resources/treaties/crc.12/China_CFT2_NGO_Report.pdf "Genocide in Tibet - Children of Despair"](NGO Group for the Convention on the Rights of the Child)

{{DEFAULTSORT:Compulsory Sterilization}}
[[Category:Eugenics]]
[[Category:Disability legislation]]
[[Category:Sterilization]]
[[Category:Birth control]]
[[Category:Reproductive rights]]
[[Category:Disability rights]]

[[ca:Esterilització forçosa]]
[[de:Sterilisationsgesetze]]
[[es:Esterilización forzosa]]
[[fr:Programmes de stérilisations contraintes]]
[[he:עיקור כפוי]]
[[ja:断種]]
[[pl:Przymusowa sterylizacja]]
[[pt:Esterilização compulsiva]]
[[ru:Принудительная стерилизация]]
[[simple:Compulsory sterilization]]
[[sv:Tvångssterilisering]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>