<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20161113063311|749238276" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="47275784" pageid="47275784" ns="0" title="Intersex human rights"><revisions><rev timestamp="2016-11-13T06:46:27Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Intersex sidebar}}
[[File:Third International Intersex Forum.jpg|thumb|300px|Participants at the third [[International Intersex Forum]], Malta, in December 2013]]
'''[[Intersex]]''' people are born with [[sex]] characteristics, such as [[chromosome]]s, [[gonad]]s, or [[genital]]s that, according to the UN [[Office of the High Commissioner for Human Rights]], "do not fit typical binary notions of [[male]] or [[female]] bodies".&lt;ref name="unfe-fact"&gt;{{Cite web| author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt; | publisher = United Nations [[Office of the High Commissioner for Human Rights]] | title = Free &amp; Equal Campaign Fact Sheet: Intersex| date = 2015| url = https://unfe.org/system/unfe-65-Intersex_Factsheet_ENGLISH.pdf | access-date = 28 March 2016 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Intersex infants and children, such as those with ambiguous outer genitalia, may be surgically and/or hormonally altered to fit perceived more socially acceptable sex characteristics. However, this is considered controversial, with no firm evidence of good outcomes.&lt;ref name="apeg2013"&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.aph.gov.au/DocumentStore.ashx?id=aafe43f3-c6a2-4525-ad16-15e4210ee0ac&amp;subId=16191 | title = Submission 88 to the Australian Senate inquiry on the involuntary or coerced sterilisation of people with disabilities in Australia | work = Australasian Paediatric Endocrine Group (APEG) | date = 27 June 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Such treatments may involve sterilization. Adults, including elite female athletes, have also been subjects of such treatment.&lt;ref name="jysk"&gt;{{cite journal |author=[[Rebecca Jordan-Young]], Peter Sonksen, [[Katrina Karkazis]]|title= Sex, health, and athletes |journal=[[BMJ]]|volume=2014|issue=348|pages=g2926|year=2014 |doi=10.1136/bmj.g2926|url=http://www.bmj.com/content/348/bmj.g2926 |pmid=24776640}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Chand&gt;{{cite news|last1=Macur|first1=Juliet|title=Fighting for the Body She Was Born With|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2014/10/07/sports/sprinter-dutee-chand-fights-ban-over-her-testosterone-level.html|accessdate=9 February 2015|publisher=[[The New York Times]]|date=6 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Increasingly these issues are recognized as human rights abuses, with statements from UN agencies,&lt;ref name="untorture" /&gt;&lt;ref name="jointun" /&gt; the Australian parliament,&lt;ref name="SenateOnSterilisation" /&gt; and German and Swiss ethics institutions.&lt;ref name="swissnek"&gt;{{Cite book| last = Swiss National Advisory Commission on Biomedical Ethics NEK-CNE| title = On the management of differences of sex development. Ethical issues relating to "intersexuality".Opinion No. 20/2012| location = Berne| series = 2012| date = November 2012| url = http://www.nek-cne.ch/fileadmin/nek-cne-dateien/Themen/Stellungnahmen/en/NEK_Intersexualitaet_En.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Intersex civil society organizations|Intersex organizations]] have also issued joint statements over several years, including as part of an [[International Intersex Forum]].

Implementation of human rights protections in legislation and regulation has been slower. In 2011, [[Christiane Völling]] won the first successful case brought against a surgeon for non-consensual surgical intervention.&lt;ref name="voll" /&gt; In 2015, the [[Council of Europe]] recognized, for the first time, a right for intersex persons to ''not'' undergo sex assignment treatment.&lt;ref name="coe" /&gt; In April 2015, [[Malta]] became the first country to outlaw non-consensual medical interventions to modify sex anatomy, including that of intersex people.&lt;ref name="nyt-2015"&gt;{{Cite news| last = Reuters| title = Surgery and Sterilization Scrapped in Malta's Benchmark LGBTI Law| work = The New York Times| date = 1 April 2015| url = http://www.nytimes.com/reuters/2015/04/01/world/europe/01reuters-gay-rights-malta.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="star-2015"&gt;{{Cite news| last = Star Observer| title = Malta passes law outlawing forced surgical intervention on intersex minors| work = Star Observer| date = 2 April 2015| url = http://www.starobserver.com.au/news/international-news-news/malta-passes-law-outlawing-forced-surgical-intervention-on-intersex-minors/134800}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Other human rights and legal issues include the right to life, protection from discrimination, access to justice and reparations, access to information, and legal recognition.&lt;ref name="coe" /&gt;&lt;ref name="afp2016" /&gt; Few countries so far protect intersex people from discrimination, or provide access to reparations for harmful practices.&lt;ref name="coe" /&gt;&lt;ref name="afp2016" /&gt;

{{TOC limit|3}}

==Intersex and human rights==
Research indicates a growing consensus that diverse intersex bodies are normal—if relatively rare—forms of human biology,&lt;ref name=Zderic&gt;{{cite book|first=  Stephen |last = Zderic|title=Pediatric gender assignment : a critical reappraisal ; [proceedings from a conference ... in Dallas in the spring of 1999 which was entitled "pediatric gender assignment - a critical reappraisal"]|year=2002|publisher=Kluwer Acad. / Plenum Publ.|location=New York, NY [u.a.]|isbn=0306467593}}&lt;/ref&gt; and human rights institutions are placing increasing scrutiny on medical practices and issues of discrimination against intersex people. A 2013 first international pilot study. [[Human Rights between the Sexes]], by Dr. [[Dan Christian Ghattas]],&lt;ref name="ghattas"&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.boell.de/sites/default/files/endf_human_rights_between_the_sexes.pdf | title = Human Rights Between the Sexes | first1 = Dan Christian | last1 = Ghattas | authorlink1 = Dan Christian Ghattas | last2 = [[Heinrich Böll Foundation]] | date = September 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://oiieurope.org/a-preliminary-study-on-the-life-situations-of-inter-individuals/ | title = A preliminary study on the life situations of inter* individuals | work = [[OII Europe]] | date = 4 November 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; found that intersex people are discriminated against worldwide:
{{quotation|Intersex individuals are considered individuals with a «disorder» in all areas in which Western medicine prevails. They are more or less obviously treated as sick or «abnormal», depending on the respective society.}}

The [[Council of Europe]] highlights several areas of concern:

* unnecessary "normalising" treatment of intersex persons, and unnecessary pathologisation of variations in sex characteristics.
* unnecessary medicalisation is said to also impact a right to life.
* inclusion in equal treatment and hate crime law; facilitating access to justice and reparations.
* access to information, medical records, peer and other counselling and support.
* respecting self-determination in gender recognition, through expeditious access to official documents.&lt;ref name="coe"&gt;{{Citation| last1 = [[Council of Europe]]| last2 = Commissioner for Human Rights| title = Human rights and intersex people, Issue Paper| date = April 2015| url = https://wcd.coe.int/ViewDoc.jsp?Ref=CommDH/IssuePaper(2015)1&amp;Language=lanEnglish&amp;Ver=original}}&lt;/ref&gt;

However, the implementation, codification and enforcement of intersex human rights remains slow. These actions take place through legislation, regulation and court cases, detailed below.

=== "Pinkwashing" ===

Multiple organizations have highlighted appeals to LGBT rights recognition that fail to address the issue of unnecessary "normalising" treatments on intersex children, using the portmanteau term "[[Pinkwashing (LGBT)|pinkwashing]]". In June 2016, [[Organisation Intersex International Australia]] pointed to contradictory statements by Australian governments, suggesting that the dignity and rights of LGBTI (LGBT and intersex) people are recognized while, at the same time, harmful practices on intersex children continue.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Submission: list of issues for Australia’s Convention Against Torture review | url = https://oii.org.au/30546/loi-cat-review/ | work = [[Organisation Intersex International Australia]] | date = June 28, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In August 2016, [[Zwischengeschlecht]] described actions to promote equality or civil status legislation without action on banning "intersex genital mutilations" as a form of [[Pinkwashing (LGBT)|pinkwashing]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = "Intersex legislation" that allows the daily mutilations to continue = PINKWASHING of IGM practices | url = http://stop.genitalmutilation.org/post/Intersex-politics-that-ignore-the-daily-mutilations-PINKWASHING-OF-IGM-PRACTICES | work = [[Zwischengeschlecht]] | date = August 28, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; The organization has previously highlighted evasive government statements to UN Treaty Bodies that conflate intersex, transgender and LGBT issues, instead of addressing harmful practices on infants.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = TRANSCRIPTION &gt; UK Questioned over Intersex Genital Mutilations by UN Committee on the Rights of the Child - Gov Non-Answer + Denial | url = http://stop.genitalmutilation.org/post/UK-Questioned-over-Intersex-Genital-Mutilations-by-UN-Committee-on-the-Rights-of-the-Child | work = [[Zwischengeschlecht]] | date = May 26, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Protection from non-consensual medical interventions ==
{{main|Intersex medical interventions}}
[[File:Protection of intersex children from harmful practices.svg|thumb|right|452px|
{{legend|#002255|Legal prohibition of non-consensual medical interventions}}
{{legend|#0066FF|Regulatory suspension of non-consensual medical interventions}}]]
Non-consensual medical interventions to modify the sex characteristics of intersex people take place in all countries where the human rights of intersex people have been explored.&lt;ref name="ghattas" /&gt; Such interventions have been criticized by the World Health Organization, other UN bodies such as the Office of the High Commissioner for Human Rights, and an increasing number of regional and national institutions.

Several rights have been stated as affected by involuntary or coerced medical treatment, particularly that on minors:
* the [[right to life]].&lt;ref name="coe" /&gt;
* the [[right to privacy]], including a right to personal [[autonomy]] or self-determination regarding medical treatment.&lt;ref name="SenateOnSterilisation" /&gt;&lt;ref name="swissnek" /&gt;
* prohibitions against [[torture]] and other cruel, inhuman and degrading treatment.&lt;ref name="untorture" /&gt;&lt;ref name="SenateOnSterilisation" /&gt;
* a right to physical integrity&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite conference| publisher = United Nations| last1 = United Nations| last2 = [[Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities|Committee on the Rights of Persons with Diabilities]] | title = Concluding observations on the initial report of Germany (advance unedited version)| location = Geneva| date = April 17, 2015| url = http://tbinternet.ohchr.org/_layouts/treatybodyexternal/Download.aspx?symbolno=CRPD%2FC%2FDEU%2FCO%2F1&amp;Lang=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; and/or bodily autonomy.&lt;ref name="star-2015" /&gt;&lt;ref name="gate-malta"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://transactivists.org/2015/04/08/making-depathologization-a-matter-of-law-a-comment-from-gate-on-the-maltese-act-on-gender-identity-gender-expression-and-sex-characteristics/ |title=Making depathologization a matter of law. A comment from GATE on the Maltese Act on Gender Identity, Gender Expression and Sex Characteristics |last1= Cabral |first1= Mauro |author-link= Mauro Cabral |date=April 8, 2015 |website= |publisher=[[Global Action for Trans Equality]] |access-date=2015-07-03 |quote=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* additionally, the best interests of the child may not be served by surgeries aimed at familial and social integration.&lt;ref name="swissnek" /&gt;

These issues have been addressed by a rapidly increasing number of international institutions including, in 2015, the Council of Europe, the United Nations [[Office of the United Nations High Commissioner for Human Rights]] and the [[World Health Organization]]. In April 2015, [[Malta]] became the first country to outlaw such interventions.&lt;ref name="nyt-2015" /&gt;&lt;ref name="star-2015" /&gt; In the same year, the Council of Europe became the first institution to state that intersex people have the right ''not'' to undergo sex affirmation interventions.&lt;ref name="coe" /&gt;

===Constitutional Court of Colombia===

Although not many cases of children with intersex conditions are available, a case taken to the [[Constitutional Court of Colombia]] led to changes in their treatment.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Curtis|first=Skyler|title=Reproductive Organs and Differences of Sex Development: The Constitutional Issues Created by the Surgical Treatment of Intersex Children|journal=McGeorge Law Review|year=2010–2011|volume=42|page=863|url=http://heinonline.org/HOL/Page?handle=hein.journals/mcglr42&amp;div=66&amp;g_sent=1&amp;collection=journals|accessdate=15 November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The case significantly reduced the power of doctors and parents to decide surgical procedures on the children's ambiguous genitalia. Due to the decision of the Constitutional Court of Colombia on Case 1 Part 1 (SU-337 of 1999), doctors are obligated to inform parents on all the aspects of the intersex child. Parents can only consent to surgery if they have received accurate information, and cannot give consent after the child reaches the age of five. By then the child will have, supposedly, realized their gender identity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Corte Constitucional de Colombia: Sentencia T-1025/02|url=http://www.corteconstitucional.gov.co/relatoria/2002/t-1025-02.htm|accessdate=2 December 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The court case has led to setting legal guidelines for doctors' surgical practice on intersex children.

===Maltese legislation===

In April 2015, [[Malta]] became the first country to outlaw non-consensual medical interventions in a ''Gender Identity Gender Expression and Sex Characteristics Act''.&lt;ref name="nyt-2015" /&gt;&lt;ref name="star-2015" /&gt; The Act recognizes a right to bodily integrity and physical autonomy, explicitly prohibiting modifications to children's sex characteristics for social factors:

{{quotation|14. (1) It shall be unlawful for medical practitioners or other professionals to conduct any sex assignment treatment and/or surgical intervention on the sex characteristics of a minor which treatment and/or intervention can be deferred until the person to be treated can provide informed consent: Provided that such sex assignment treatment and/or surgical intervention on the sex characteristics of the minor shall be conducted if the minor gives informed consent through the person exercising parental authority or the tutor of the minor.
(2) In exceptional circumstances treatment may be effected once agreement is reached between the Interdisciplinary Team and the persons exercising parental authority or tutor of the minor who is still unable to provide consent: Provided that medical intervention which is driven by social factors without the consent of the minor, will be in violation of this Act.&lt;ref name="gigesc"&gt;{{Citation| last = Malta| title = Gender Identity, Gender Expression and Sex Characteristics Act: Final version| date = April 2015| url = http://justiceservices.gov.mt/DownloadDocument.aspx?app=lp&amp;itemid=26805&amp;l=1}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

The Act was widely welcomed by civil society organizations.&lt;ref name="gate-malta" /&gt;&lt;ref name="oiieu-malta"&gt;{{Cite web| last = OII Europe| title = OII-Europe applauds Malta's Gender Identity, Gender Expression and Sex Characteristics Act. This is a landmark case for intersex rights within European law reform| date = April 1, 2015| url = http://oiieurope.org/press-release-oii-europe-applauds-maltas-gender-identity-gender-expression-and-sex-characteristics-act/|access-date=2015-07-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="oiiau-malta"&gt;{{cite web |url=https://oii.org.au/28592/we-celebrate-maltese-protections-for-intersex-people/ |title=We celebrate Maltese protections for intersex people |last1=Carpenter |first1=Morgan | author-link= Morgan Carpenter |date=April 2, 2015 |website= |publisher= [[Organisation Intersex International Australia]] |access-date=2015-07-03 |quote=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Chile===

In January 2016, the [[Ministry of Health (Chile)|Ministry of Health]] of [[LGBT rights in Chile|Chile]] ordered the suspension of unnecessary normalization treatments for intersex children, including irreversible surgery, until they reach an age when they can make decisions on their own.&lt;ref&gt;https://www.outrightinternational.org/content/chilean-government-stops-normalization-intersex-children&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.washingtonblade.com/2016/01/11/chilean-officials-oppose-normalization-surgery-for-intersex-children/&lt;/ref&gt;

==Right to life==

[[Preimplantation genetic diagnosis]] (PGD or PIGD) refers to [[Genetics|genetic]] testing of [[embryo]]s prior to [[Implantation (human embryo)|implantation]] (as a form of [[embryo profiling]]), and sometimes even of [[oocyte]]s prior to [[Fertilisation|fertilization]]. PGD is considered in a similar fashion to [[prenatal diagnosis]]. When used to screen for a specific genetic condition, the method makes it highly likely that the baby will be free of the condition under consideration. PGD thus is an adjunct to [[assisted reproductive technology]], and requires [[In vitro fertilisation|in vitro fertilization]] (IVF) to obtain [[oocytes]] or [[embryo]]s for evaluation. The technology allows discrimination against those with [[intersex]] traits.

[[Georgiann Davis]] argues that such discrimination fails to recognize that many people with intersex traits led full and happy lives.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal| doi = 10.1080/15265161.2013.828119| issn = 1526-5161| volume = 13| issue = 10| pages = 51–53| last = Davis| first = Georgiann| author-link=Georgiann Davis|title = The Social Costs of Preempting Intersex Traits| journal = The American Journal of Bioethics| accessdate = 2014-10-21| date = October 2013| url = http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/15265161.2013.828119| pmid=24024811}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Morgan Carpenter]] highlights the appearance of several intersex variations in a list by the UK [[Human Fertilisation and Embryology Authority]] of "serious" "genetic conditions" that may be de-selected, including [[5 alpha reductase deficiency]] and [[androgen insensitivity syndrome]], traits evident in elite women athletes and "the world's first openly [[Tony Briffa|intersex mayor]]".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal| last = Carpenter| first = Morgan| author-link=Morgan Carpenter |title = Morgan Carpenter at LGBTI Human Rights in the Commonwealth conference| location = Glasgow| date = July 18, 2014| url = http://oii.org.au/27467/lgbti-human-rights-in-the-commonwealth/}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Organisation Intersex International Australia]] has called for the Australian [[National Health and Medical Research Council]] to prohibit such interventions, noting a "close entanglement of intersex status, gender identity and sexual orientation in social understandings of sex and gender norms, and in medical and medical sociology literature".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite report| publisher = Organisation Intersex International Australia| last1 = Carpenter| first1 = Morgan| last2 = [[Organisation Intersex International Australia]]| title = Submission on the Review of Part B of the Ethical Guidelines for the Use of Assisted Reproductive Technology in Clinical Practice and Research, 2007| location = Sydney| date = April 30, 2014| url = http://oii.org.au/25621/submission-ethics-genetic-selection-intersex-traits/}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2015, the [[Council of Europe]] published an Issue Paper on ''Human rights and intersex people'', remarking:

{{quotation|Intersex people’s right to life can be violated in discriminatory “sex selection” and “preimplantation genetic diagnosis, other forms of testing, and selection for particular characteristics”. Such de-selection or selective abortions are incompatible with ethics and human rights standards due to the discrimination perpetrated against intersex people on the basis of their sex characteristics.&lt;ref name="coe" /&gt;}}

In 2015, it was reported that an intersex Kenyan adolescent, Muhadh Ishmael, was mutilated and later died. He had previously been described as a curse on his family.&lt;ref name="76crimes"&gt;{{Cite web| last = Odero| first = Joseph| title = Intersex in Kenya: Held captive, beaten, hacked. Dead.| work = 76 CRIMES| accessdate = 2016-10-01| date = December 23, 2015| url = http://76crimes.com/2015/12/23/intersex-in-kenya-held-captive-beaten-hacked-dead/}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Protection from discrimination ==
[[File:Inclusion of sex characteristics in anti-discrimination law.svg|thumb|right|452px|
{{legend|#002255|Explicit protection on grounds of sex characteristics}}
{{legend|#0066FF|Explicit protection on grounds of intersex status}}
{{legend|#9FCFFF|Explicit protection on grounds of intersex within attribute of sex}}]]
{{main|Discrimination against intersex people}}
A handful of jurisdictions so far provide explicit protection from discrimination for intersex people. [[South Africa]] was the first country to explicitly add intersex to legislation, as part of the attribute of 'sex'.&lt;ref name="zagaz"&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.justice.gov.za/legislation/acts/2005-022.pdf | title = Judicial Matters Amendment Act, No. 22 of 2005, Republic of South Africa, Vol. 487, Cape Town | date = 11 January 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Australia]] was the first country to add an independent attribute, of 'intersex status'.&lt;ref name="com law"&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.comlaw.gov.au/Details/C2013A00098 | title = Sex Discrimination Amendment (Sexual Orientation, Gender Identity and Intersex Status) Act 2013, No. 98, 2013, C2013A00098 | work = ComLaw | date = 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Malta]] was the first to adopt a broader framework of 'sex characteristics', through legislation that also ended modifications to the sex characteristics of minors undertaken for social and cultural reasons.&lt;ref name="gate-malta" /&gt;  [[Bosnia-Herzegovina]] listed as "sex characteristics"&lt;ref name="ilga-europe.org"&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.ilga-europe.org/resources/news/latest-news/anti-discrimination-law-updated-bosnia-herzegovina | title = Anti-discrimination Law Updated in Bosnia-Herzegovina | work = [[ILGA-Europe]] }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="lezbelib.com"&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.lezbelib.com/europe-news/lgbti-people-are-now-better-protected-in-bosnia-and-herzegovina | title = LGBTI people are now better protected in Bosnia and Herzegovina}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Greece]] prohibits discrimination and hate crimes based on "sex characteristics", since 24 December 2015.&lt;ref name="et.gr"&gt;{{el icon}} {{cite web | url = http://www.et.gr/idocs-nph/search/pdfViewerForm.html?args=5C7QrtC22wE4q6ggiv8WTXdtvSoClrL8RZsdmVE36E95MXD0LzQTLWPU9yLzB8V68knBzLCmTXKaO6fpVZ6Lx9hLslJUqeiQ7YD-s2g-TGFc-ieGHzbhl8d9JIy5q3gnKRFHKgyKzGY | title = NOMOΣ ΥΠ’ ΑΡΙΘ. 3456 Σύμφωνο συμβίωσης, άσκηση δικαιωμάτων, ποινικές και άλλες διατάξεις}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Πρώτη φορά, ίσοι απέναντι στον νόμο"&gt;{{el icon}}{{cite web | url = http://www.efsyn.gr/arthro/proti-fora-isoi-apenanti-ston-nomo | title = Πρώτη φορά, ίσοι απέναντι στον νόμο}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Education ===
An Australian survey of 272 persons born with atypical sex characteristics, published in 2016, found that 18% of respondents (compared to an Australian average of 2%) failed to complete secondary school, with early school leaving coincident with pubertal medical interventions, bullying and other factors.&lt;ref name="jones2016ed"&gt;{{Cite journal| doi = 10.1080/14681811.2016.1149808| issn = 1468-1811 | pages = 1–17| last = Jones| first = Tiffany| title = The needs of students with intersex variations| journal = Sex Education| accessdate = 2016-05-28| date = March 11, 2016 | url = http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/14681811.2016.1149808}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Employment ===
A 2015 Australian survey of people born with atypical sex characteristics found high levels of poverty, in addition to very high levels of early school leaving, and higher than average rates of disability.&lt;ref name="jonesbk2016"&gt;{{Cite book| publisher = Open Book Publishers| isbn = 978-1-78374-208-0 | last1 = Jones| first1 = Tiffany| last2 = Hart| first2 = Bonnie| last3 = Carpenter| first3 = Morgan| last4 = Ansara| first4 = Gavi| last5 = Leonard| first5 = William| last6 = Lucke| first6 = Jayne| title = Intersex: Stories and Statistics from Australia| location = Cambridge, UK| accessdate = 2016-02-02| date = February 2016 | url = http://oii.org.au/wp-content/uploads/key/Intersex-Stories-Statistics-Australia.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; An ''Employers guide to intersex inclusion'' published by Pride in Diversity and [[Organisation Intersex International Australia]] also discloses cases of discrimination in employment.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book| publisher = Pride in Diversity and [[Organisation Intersex International Australia]] | isbn = 978-0-646-92905-7| last1 = Carpenter| first1 = Morgan| last2 = Hough| first2 = Dawn| author1-link = Morgan Carpenter | title = Employers' Guide to Intersex Inclusion| location = Sydney, Australia| date = 2014| url = http://oii.org.au/employer}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Healthcare ===
Discrimination protection intersects with involuntary and coercive medical treatment. Maltese protections on grounds of [[sex characteristics]] provides explicit protection against unnecessary and harmful modifications to the sex characteristics of children.&lt;ref name="star-2015" /&gt;&lt;ref name="gate-malta" /&gt;

In May 2016, the [[United States Department of Health and Human Services]] issued a statement explaining Section 1557 of the [[Affordable Care Act]] stating that the Act prohibits "discrimination on the basis of intersex traits or atypical sex characteristics" in publicly-funded healthcare, as part of a prohibition of discrimination "on the basis of sex".&lt;ref name="interact"&gt;{{Cite web| last = [[Interact Advocates for Intersex Youth|interACT]]| title = Federal Government Bans Discrimination Against Intersex People in Health Care| work = interactadvocates| accessdate = 2016-05-27| url = http://interactadvocates.org/federal-government-bans-discrimination-against-intersex-people-in-health-care/}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Sport ===
{{main article|Sex verification in sports}}
In 2013, it was disclosed in a medical journal that four unnamed elite female athletes from developing countries were subjected to gonadectomies (sterilization) and partial clitoridectomies ([[female genital mutilation]]) after [[Sex verification in sports|testosterone testing]] revealed that they had an intersex condition.&lt;ref name="jcem2013" /&gt;&lt;ref name="bmj2014" /&gt; Testosterone testing was introduced in the wake of the [[Caster Semenya]] case, of a South African runner subjected to testing due to her appearance and vigor.&lt;ref name="jcem2013"&gt;{{Cite journal| doi = 10.1210/jc.2012-3893| issn = 0021-972X | volume = 98| issue = 6| pages = –1055-E1059| last1 = Fénichel| first1 = Patrick| last2 = Paris| first2 = Françoise| last3 = Philibert| first3 = Pascal| last4 = Hiéronimus| first4 = Sylvie| last5 = Gaspari| first5 = Laura| last6 = Kurzenne| first6 = Jean-Yves| last7 = Chevallier| first7 = Patrick| last8 = Bermon| first8 = Stéphane| last9 = Chevalier| first9 = Nicolas| last10 = Sultan| first10 = Charles| title = Molecular Diagnosis of 5α-Reductase Deficiency in 4 Elite Young Female Athletes Through Hormonal Screening for Hyperandrogenism| journal = The Journal of Clinical Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism| accessdate = 2016-05-28| date = June 2013| url = http://press.endocrine.org/doi/abs/10.1210/jc.2012-3893}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="bmj2014"&gt;{{Cite journal| doi = 10.1136/bmj.g2926| issn = 1756-1833| volume = 348| issue = apr28 9| pages = –2926-g2926| last1 = Jordan-Young| first1 = R. M.| last2 = Sonksen| first2 = P. H.| last3 = Karkazis| first3 = K.| author-link1= Rebecca Jordan-Young | author-link3= Katrina Karkazis |title = Sex, health, and athletes| journal = BMJ| access-date = 2016-05-21 | date = April 2014 | url = http://www.bmj.com/cgi/doi/10.1136/bmj.g2926}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/sport1/hi/athletics/8210471.stm|title=Semenya told to take gender test  |publisher=[[BBC Sport]]|date=19 August 2009|accessdate=19 August 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="nyt2008"&gt;{{cite news | title = A Lab is Set to Test the Gender of Some Female Athletes. | work = [[New York Times]] | date = 30 July 2008 | url = http://www.nytimes.com/2008/07/30/sports/olympics/30gender.html?_r=2&amp;ref=olympics&amp;oref=slogin&amp;oref=slogin }}&lt;/ref&gt; There is no evidence that innate hyperandrogenism in elite women athletes confers an advantage in sport.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal| doi = 10.1210/jc.2014-1391| issn = 0021-972X | pages = –2014-1391| last1 = Bermon| first1 = Stéphane| last2 = Garnier| first2 = Pierre Yves| last3 = Lindén Hirschberg| first3 = Angelica| last4 = Robinson| first4 = Neil| last5 = Giraud| first5 = Sylvain| last6 = Nicoli| first6 = Raul| last7 = Baume| first7 = Norbert| last8 = Saugy| first8 = Martial| last9 = Fénichel| first9 = Patrick| last10 = Bruce| first10 = Stephen J.| last11 = Henry| first11 = Hugues| last12 = Dollé| first12 = Gabriel| last13 = Ritzen| first13 = Martin| title = Serum Androgen Levels in Elite Female Athletes| journal = The Journal of Clinical Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism| accessdate = 2016-05-28| date = August 2014 | url = http://press.endocrine.org/doi/abs/10.1210/jc.2014-1391}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="IAAF ruling"&gt;{{cite news|last1=Branch|first1=John|title=Dutee Chand, Female Sprinter With High Testosterone Level, Wins Right to Compete|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2015/07/28/sports/international/dutee-chand-female-sprinter-with-high-male-hormone-level-wins-right-to-compete.html|accessdate=22 May 2016|work=The New York Times|date=27 July 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; While Australia protects intersex persons from discrimination, the Act contains an exemption in sport.

== Access to justice and reparations ==

Access to reparation appears limited, with a scarcity of legal cases.

=== Christiane Völling case, Germany ===
{{main article|Christiane Völling}}
In Germany in 2011, [[Christiane Völling]] won what may be the first successful case against her medical treatment. The surgeon was ordered to pay €100,000 in damages&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://zwischengeschlecht.org/pages/Hermaphrodite-wins-damage-claim |title=Christiane Völling: Hermaphrodite wins damage claim over removal of reproductive organs |last1=[[Zwischengeschlecht]] |date=August 12, 2009 |website= |publisher= |access-date=2015-07-20 |quote=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="local" /&gt; after a legal battle that began in 2007, thirty years after the removal of her reproductive organs.&lt;ref name="voll"&gt;{{Cite web| last = | title = German Gender-Assignment Case Has Intersexuals Hopeful | publisher= [[Deutsche Welle]] | date=12 December 2007| work = DW.COM| accessdate = 2015-12-21| url = http://www.dw.com/en/german-gender-assignment-case-has-intersexuals-hopeful/a-3000902}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| last = DW Staff| title = Christiane Völling | publisher= [[German Ethics Council]] | date=August 2010| work = | accessdate = 2015-12-21| url = http://diskurs.ethikrat.org/christiane-volling/}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== M.C. case, USA ===
In the United States the "M.C." legal case, advanced by [[Advocates for Informed Choice]] with the [[Southern Poverty Law Centre]] was brought before the courts in 2013.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.splcenter.org/get-informed/news/groundbreaking-splc-lawsuit-accuses-south-carolina-doctors-and-hospitals-of-unnece |title= Groundbreaking SLPC Lawsuit Accuses South Carolina Doctors and Hospitals of Unnecessary Surgery on Infant |last1=[[Southern Poverty Law Centre]] |date=May 14, 2013 |website= |publisher= |access-date=2015-07-20 |quote=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://nursingclio.org/2013/05/17/do-no-harm-intersex-surgeries-and-the-limits-of-certainty/ |title= Do No Harm: Intersex Surgeries and the Limits of Certainty |last1=Reis |first1=Elizabeth  |date=May 17, 2013 |website=Nursing Clio |publisher= |access-date=2015-07-20 |quote=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.theatlantic.com/health/archive/2013/05/when-to-do-surgery-on-a-child-with-both-genitalia/275884/ |title= When to Do Surgery on a Child With 'Both' Genitalia |last1=Dreger |first1=Alice  |date=May 16, 2013 |website=[[The Atlantic]] |publisher= |access-date=2015-07-20 |quote=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Michaela Raab case, Germany ===
In 2015, Michaela Raab sued doctors in Nuremberg, Germany who failed to properly advise her. Doctors stated that they "were only acting according to the norms of the time - which sought to protect patients against the psychosocial effects of learning the full truth about their chromosomes."&lt;ref name="local"&gt;{{Cite web| last = [[The Local]]| title = Intersex person sues clinic for unnecessary op| date = February 27, 2015| accessdate = 2015-12-21| url = http://www.thelocal.de/20150227/intersex-person-sues-doctors-for-unwanted-op}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 17 December 2015, the Nuremberg State Court ruled that the [[University of Erlangen-Nuremberg]] Clinic must pay damages and compensation.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| last = Zwischengeschlecht| title = Nuremberg Hermaphrodite Lawsuit: Michaela "Micha" Raab Wins Damages and Compensation for Intersex Genital Mutilations!| accessdate = 2015-12-21| date = December 17, 2015 | url = http://stop.genitalmutilation.org/post/Nuremberg-Hermaphrodite-Lawsuit-Damages-and-Compensation-for-Intersex-Genital-Mutilations}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Access to information ==

With the rise of modern medical science in Western societies, many intersex people with ambiguous external genitalia have had their genitalia surgically modified to resemble either female or male genitals. Surgeons pinpointed the birth of intersex babies as a "social emergency".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Coran|first1=Arnold G.|last2=Polley|first2=Theodore Z.|title=Surgical management of ambiguous genitalia in the infant and child|journal=Journal of Pediatric Surgery|date=July 1991|volume=26|issue=7|pages=812–820|doi=10.1016/0022-3468(91)90146-K|pmid=1895191}}&lt;!--|accessdate=30 November 2014--&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; A secrecy-based model was also adopted, in the belief that this was necessary to ensure “normal” physical and psychosocial development.&lt;ref name="swissnek" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| last = Holmes| first = Morgan| authorlink=Morgan Holmes |title = Is Growing up in Silence Better Than Growing up Different?| work = Intersex Society of North America| url = http://www.isna.org/node/743}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| last = [[Intersex Society of North America]]| title = What's wrong with the way intersex has traditionally been treated?| url = http://www.isna.org/faq/concealment#fn2}}&lt;/ref&gt; Disclosure also included telling people that they would never meet anyone else with the same condition.&lt;ref name="SenateOnSterilisation" /&gt; Access to medical records has also historically been challenging.&lt;ref name="coe" /&gt; Yet the ability to provide free, informed consent depends on the availability of information.

The [[Council of Europe]]&lt;ref name="coe" /&gt; and [[World Health Organization]]&lt;ref name="who2015" /&gt; acknowledge the necessity for improvements in information provision, including access to [[medical record]]s.

Some intersex organizations claim that secrecy-based models have been perpetuated by a shift in clinical language to [[Disorders of sex development]]. [[Morgan Carpenter]] of [[Organisation Intersex International Australia]] quotes the work of [[Miranda Fricker]] on "hermeneutical injustice" where, despite new legal protections from discrimination on grounds of intersex status, "someone with lived experience is unable to even make sense of their own social experiences" due to the deployment of clinical language and "no words to name the experience".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite conference| publisher = Organisation Intersex International Australia| last = Carpenter| first = Morgan| title = Intersex and ageing| date = February 3, 2015 | url = https://oii.org.au/28385/intersex-and-ageing/}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Gender identities and legal recognition ==
{{main article|Legal recognition of intersex people}}
Like all individuals, some intersex individuals may be raised as a particular sex (male or female) but then identify with another later in life, while most do not.&lt;ref name="Money"&gt;{{cite book|last=Money |first=John |author2=Ehrhardt, Anke A. |title=Man &amp; Woman Boy &amp; Girl. Differentiation and dimorphism of gender identity from conception to maturity |year=1972|publisher=The Johns Hopkins University Press |location=USA |isbn=0-8018-1405-7 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Dreger"&gt;{{cite book |last=Domurat Dreger |first=Alice |title=Hermaphrodites and the Medical Invention of Sex |year=2001 |publisher=Harvard University Press |location=USA |isbn=0-674-00189-3 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="maranon"&gt;{{cite book |last=Marañón |first=Gregorio |title=Los estados intersexuales en la especie humana |year=1929 |publisher=Morata |location=Madrid }}&lt;/ref&gt; Like non-intersex people, some intersex individuals may not identify themselves as either exclusively female or exclusively male. A 2012 clinical review suggests that between 8.5-20% of persons with intersex conditions may experience [[gender dysphoria]],&lt;ref name="furtado"&gt;{{cite journal | author = Furtado P. S.| year = 2012 | title = Gender dysphoria associated with disorders of sex development | url = | journal = Nat. Rev. Urol. | volume = 9 | issue = | pages = 620–627 | doi = 10.1038/nrurol.2012.182 |display-authors=etal}}&lt;/ref&gt; while sociological research in Australia, a country with a third 'X' sex classification, shows that 19% of people born with atypical sex characteristics selected an "X" or "other" option, while 52% are women, 23% men and 6% unsure.&lt;ref name="jonesbk2016" /&gt;&lt;ref name="oiiaudemo"&gt;{{Citation| last = Organisation Intersex International Australia| title = Demographics| date = July 28, 2016| url = https://oii.org.au/demographics/ | accessdate = 2016-09-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Depending on the jurisdiction, access to any birth certificate may be an issue,&lt;ref name="Reuters"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.reuters.com/article/2014/12/05/us-kenya-intersex-idUSKCN0JJ1M120141205|title=Kenya takes step toward recognizing intersex people in landmark ruling|work=Reuters}}&lt;/ref&gt; including a birth certificate with a sex marker.&lt;ref name="adv-de"&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.advocate.com/commentary/2013/11/06/op-ed-germany’s-third-gender-law-fails-equality | first = Hida | last = Viloria | work = The Advocate | title = Op-ed: Germany’s Third-Gender Law Fails on Equality | date = November 6, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Asia Pacific Forum]] of [[National Human Rights Institutions]] states that:
{{quotation|Recognition before the law means having legal personhood and the legal protections that flow from that. For intersex people, this is neither primarily nor solely about amending birth registrations or other official documents. Firstly, it is about intersex people who have been issued a male or a female birth certificate being able to enjoy the same legal rights as other men and women&lt;ref name="afp2016" /&gt;}}

Access to a birth certificate with a correct sex marker may be an issue for people who do not identify with their sex assigned at birth,&lt;ref name="coe" /&gt; or it may only be available accompanied by surgical requirements.&lt;ref name="afp2016" /&gt;

The passports and identification documents of Australia and some other nationalities have adopted "X" as a valid third category besides "M" (male) and "F" (female), at least since 2003.&lt;ref name="Science as Culture"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/09505430802280784?journalCode=csac20|first=Ingrid | last = Holme | title = Hearing People's Own Stories | journal = Science as Culture | volume = 17 | issue = 3 | doi = 10.1080/09505430802280784 | date = 2008|publisher=|accessdate=6 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="nzpass"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.passports.govt.nz/Transgender-applicants|title=New Zealand Passports - Information about Changing Sex / Gender Identity|publisher=|accessdate=6 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2013, Germany became the first European nation to allow babies with characteristics of both sexes to be registered as ''indeterminate gender'' on birth certificates, amidst opposition and skepticism from intersex organisations who point out that the law appears to mandate exclusion from male or female categories.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.dw.de/third-sex-option-on-birth-certificates/a-17193869 | title = Third sex option on birth certificates | work = [[Deutsche Welle]] | date = 1 November 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://oiieurope.org/bluff-package-for-inter-leaving-sex-entry-open-is-not-an-option/ | title = Sham package for Intersex: Leaving sex entry open is not an option | work = [[OII Europe]] | date = 15 February 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="rt"&gt;{{cite web | url = http://rt.com/news/germany-allows-third-gender-062/ | title = ‘X’ gender: Germans no longer have to classify their kids as male or female | work = [[RT (TV network)|RT]] | date = 3 November 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Council of Europe acknowledged this approach, and concerns about recognition of third and blank classifications in a 2015 Issue Paper, stating that these may lead to "forced outings" and "lead to an increase in pressure on parents of intersex children to decide in favour of one sex."&lt;ref name="coe" /&gt; The Issue Paper argues that "further reflection on non-binary legal identification is necessary":

{{quotation|[[Mauro Cabral]], [[Global Action for Trans Equality]] (GATE) Co-Director, indicated that any recognition outside the “F”/”M” dichotomy needs to be adequately planned and executed with a human rights point of view, noting that: “People tend to identify a third sex with freedom from the gender binary, but that is not necessarily the case. If only trans and/or intersex people can access that third category, or if they are compulsively assigned a third sex, then the gender binary gets stronger, not weaker”&lt;ref name="coe" /&gt;}}

== Human rights investigations and statements ==

===San Francisco Human Rights Investigation, 2005===

The 2005 ''Human Rights Investigation into the Medical "Normalization" of Intersex People, by the Human Rights Commission of the City and County of San Francisco'' is thought "likely to be the first human rights report into the treatment of intersex people, certainly in the English language."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://oii.org.au/22613/third-submission-senate-inquiry-sterilisation/ | title = Third submission to Senate Inquiry on involuntary sterilisation | work = [[Organisation Intersex International Australia]] | date = 6 June 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="sanfran"&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.aph.gov.au/DocumentStore.ashx?id=2bbf04f0-66c8-4dd9-9c20-2cdb1c936f79 | title = Human Rights Investigation into the Medical "Normalization" of Intersex People | work = Human Rights Commission of the City and County of San Francisco | date = 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://oii.org.au/23387/august-submission-senate-inquiry-sterilisation/ | title = Concluding submission to the Senate Inquiry on involuntary or coerced sterilisation | work = [[Organisation Intersex International Australia]] | date = 12 September 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; The report found that:

{{quotation|
#Infant genital surgeries and sex hormone treatments that are not performed for the treatment of physical illness, such as improving urinary tract or metabolic functioning, and have not been shown to alleviate pain or illness (hereafter referred to as "normalizing" interventions) are unnecessary and are not medical or social emergencies.
#"Normalizing" interventions done without the patient's informed consent are inherent human rights abuses.
#"Normalizing" interventions deprive intersex people of the opportunity to express their own identity and to experience their own intact physiology.
#It is unethical to disregard a child's intrinsic human rights to privacy, dignity, autonomy, and physical integrity by altering genitals through irreversible surgeries for purely psychosocial and aesthetic rationales. It is wrong to deprive a person of the right to determine their sexual experience and identity. ...
#It is ethically wrong to treat people differently or unfairly because they are perceived by others to be "monsters" or "oddities."|Human Rights Commission of the City and County of San Francisco&lt;ref name="sanfran" /&gt;}}

===Yogyakarta Principles, 2006===

The 2006 '''[[Yogyakarta Principles]] on the Application of International Human Rights Law in relation to Sexual Orientation and Gender Identity''' is a set of principles relating to [[sexual orientation]] and [[gender identity]], intended to apply international human rights law standards to address the abuse of the human rights of lesbian, gay, bisexual and transgender ([[LGBT]]) people. It briefly mentions intersex, influenced by the [[Declaration of Montreal]] which first demanded prohibition of unnecessary post-birth surgery to reinforce gender assignment until a child is old enough to understand and give [[informed consent]]. The [[Yogyakarta Principles]] detail this in the context of existing UN declarations and conventions under Principle 18, which called on states to:

{{Quotation|
B. Take all necessary legislative, administrative and other measures to ensure that no child's body is irreversibly altered by medical procedures in an attempt to impose a gender identity without the full, free and informed consent of the child in accordance with the age and maturity of the child and guided by the principle that in all actions concerning children, the best interests of the child shall be a primary consideration;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
C. Establish child protection mechanisms whereby no child is at risk of, or subjected to, medical abuse;|The Yogyakarta Principles}}

===Report of Swiss National Advisory Council on Biomedical Ethics, 2012===

In late 2012, the Swiss National Advisory Commission on Biomedical Ethics reported on intersex. The Commission report makes a strong case against medical intervention for "psychosocial" reasons:&lt;ref name="swissnek" /&gt;

{{quotation|Especially delicate are those cases where a psychosocial indication is used to justify the medical urgency of surgical sex assignment in children who lack capacity. Here, there is a particularly great risk of insufficient respect being accorded to the child's (future) self-determination and its physical integrity...

Decisions on sex assignment interventions are to be guided by the questions of what genitalia a child actually requires at a given age (apart from a functional urinary system) and how these interventions will affect the physical and mental health of the child and the future adult. Treatment needs to be carefully justified, especially since – in functional, aesthetic and psychological respects – surgically altered genitalia ... are not comparable to natural male or female genitalia.
Decisions are to be guided, above all, by the child's welfare...

The harmful consequences may include, for example, loss of fertility and sexual sensitivity, chronic pain, or pain associated with dilation (bougienage) of a surgically created vagina, with traumatizing effects for the child. If such interventions are performed solely with a view to integration of the child into its family and social environment, then they run counter to the child's welfare. In addition, there is no guarantee that the intended purpose (integration) will be achieved.|Swiss National Advisory Commission on Biomedical Ethics&lt;ref name="swissnek" /&gt;}}

The report is notable for making a clear apology for damage done to intersex people in the past, and up until the present. It recommends deferring all "non-trivial" surgeries which have "irreversible consequences". The report also recommended criminal sanction for non-medically necessary genital surgeries.

===Report of UN Special Rapporteur on Torture, 2013===

On 1 February 2013, [[Juan E. Méndez]], the UN Special Rapporteur on torture and other cruel, inhuman or degrading treatment or punishment, issued a statement condemning non-consensual surgical intervention on intersex people. His report states:&lt;ref name="untorture"&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.ohchr.org/Documents/HRBodies/HRCouncil/RegularSession/Session22/A.HRC.22.53_English.pdf | title = Report of the UN Special Rapporteur on Torture | work = [[Office of the UN High Commissioner for Human Rights]] | date = February 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="wash"&gt;{{Cite book| publisher = Center for Human Rights &amp; Humanitarian Law| last1 = Center for Human Rights &amp; Humanitarian Law| last2 = Washington College of Law| last3 = American University| title =  Torture in Healthcare Settings: Reflections on the Special Rapporteur on Torture's 2013 Thematic Report| location = Washington, DC| date = 2014| url = http://antitorture.org/torture-in-healthcare-publication/}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quotation|76. … There is an abundance of accounts and testimonies of persons being denied medical treatment, subjected to verbal abuse and public humiliation, psychiatric evaluation, a variety of forced procedures such as sterilization, State-sponsored forcible … hormone therapy and genital-normalizing surgeries under the guise of so called "reparative therapies". These procedures are rarely medically necessary, can cause scarring, loss of sexual sensation, pain, incontinence and lifelong depression and have also been criticized as being unscientific, potentially harmful and contributing to stigma (A/HRC/14/20, para. 23).

77. Children who are born with atypical sex characteristics are often subject to irreversible sex assignment, involuntary sterilization, involuntary genital normalizing surgery, performed without their informed consent, or that of their parents, "in an attempt to fix their sex", leaving them with permanent, irreversible infertility and causing severe mental suffering…

79. The mandate has noted that "members of sexual minorities are disproportionately subjected to torture and other forms of ill-treatment because they fail to conform to socially constructed gender expectations.|UN Special Rapporteur on Torture&lt;ref name="untorture" /&gt;}}

===Resolution by the Council of Europe, 2013===

In October 2013, the [[Council of Europe]] adopted a resolution 1952, 'Children's right to physical integrity'. It calls on member states to&lt;ref name="coe1952"&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.assembly.coe.int/nw/xml/XRef/Xref-XML2HTML-en.asp?fileid=20174&amp;lang=en | title = Resolution 1952/2013, Provision version, Children’s right to physical integrity | work = [[Council of Europe]] | date = 1 October 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{quotation|undertake further research to increase knowledge about the specific situation of intersex people, ensure that no-one is subjected to unnecessary medical or surgical treatment that is cosmetic rather than vital for health during infancy or childhood, guarantee bodily integrity, autonomy and self-determination to persons concerned, and provide families with intersex children with adequate counselling and support|Resolution 1952/2013, Council of Europe&lt;ref name="coe1952" /&gt;}}

===Senate Committee inquiry, Australia, 2013===

In October 2013, the [[Australian Senate]] published a report entitled ''Involuntary or coerced sterilisation of intersex people in Australia''.&lt;ref name="SenateOnSterilisation"&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.aph.gov.au/Parliamentary_Business/Committees/Senate/Community_Affairs/Involuntary_Sterilisation/Sec_Report/index | title = Involuntary or coerced sterilisation of intersex people in Australia | last = [[Australian Senate]] Community Affairs Committee | date = October 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="oiiausen"&gt;{{cite web | url = http://oii.org.au/24058/statement-senate-report-involuntary-or-coerced-sterilisation-intersex-people/ | title = Statement on the Senate report ''Involuntary or coerced sterilisation of intersex people in Australia'' | work = [[Organisation Intersex International Australia]] | date = 29 October 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.abc.net.au/news/2013-11-15/carpenter-its-time-to-defend-intersex-rights/5093966 | title = It's time to defend intersex rights | first = Morgan | last = Carpenter | work = [[Australian Broadcasting Corporation]] | date = 15 November 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.gaystarnews.com/article/australian-parliament-committee-releases-intersex-rights-report281013 | title = Australian Parliament committee releases intersex rights report | work = [[Gay Star News]] | date = 28 October 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://gaynewsnetwork.com.au/news/intersex-advocates-address-findings-of-senate-committee-into-involuntary-sterilisation-12237.html | title = Intersex advocates address findings of Senate Committee into involuntary sterilisation | work = Gay News Network | date = 28 October 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Senate found that "normalising" surgeries are taking place in Australia, often on infants and young children, with preconceptions that it described as "disturbing": "Normalising appearance goes hand in hand with the stigmatisation of difference".&lt;ref name="SenateOnSterilisation" /&gt;

They commented: "...normalisation surgery is more than physical reconstruction. The surgery is intended to deconstruct an intersex physiology and, in turn, construct an identity that conforms with stereotypical male and female gender categories" and: "Enormous effort has gone into assigning and 'normalising' sex: none has gone into asking whether this is necessary or beneficial. Given the extremely complex and risky medical treatments that are sometimes involved, this appears extremely unfortunate."&lt;ref name="SenateOnSterilisation" /&gt;

The report makes 15 recommendations, including ending cosmetic genital surgeries on infants and children and providing for legal oversight of individual cases.&lt;ref name="SenateOnSterilisation" /&gt;

[[Organisation Intersex International Australia]] welcomed the report, saying that, 
{{quotation|At a first view, many of the headline conclusions and recommendations are positive – accepting our recommendations on minimising genital surgery, concern over the lack of adequate data, insufficient psychosocial support, and concern that decision making on cancer risk is insufficiently disentangled from wider concerns about a person's intersex status itself; we also broadly welcome the recommendations relating to the prenatal use of Dexamethasone ... The distinction between therapeutic and non-therapeutic treatment has failed many intersex people in Australia. We welcome the recommendation for the proper oversight of individual cases.|Organisation Intersex International Australia&lt;ref name="oiiausen" /&gt;}}

===World Health Organization and UN interagency report, 2014===

In May 2014, the [[World Health Organization]] issued a joint statement on '''Eliminating forced, coercive and otherwise involuntary sterilization, An interagency statement''' with the [[OHCHR]], [[UN Women]], [[UNAIDS]], [[UNDP]], [[UNFPA]] and [[UNICEF]]. The report references the involuntary surgical "sex-normalising or other procedures" on "intersex persons". It questions the medical necessity of such treatments, patients' ability to consent, and a weak evidence base.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://oii.org.au/27189/who-and-other-un-agencies-issues-statement-on-involuntary-or-coerced-sterilisation/ | title = WHO/UN interagency statement on involuntary or coerced sterilisation | work = Organisation Intersex International Australia | date = 30 May 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; The report recommends a range of guiding principles for medical treatment, including ensuring patient autonomy in decision-making, ensuring non-discrimination, accountability and access to remedies.&lt;ref name="jointun"&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.who.int/reproductivehealth/publications/gender_rights/eliminating-forced-sterilization/en/ | title = Eliminating forced, coercive and otherwise involuntary sterilization, An interagency statement | work = [[World Health Organization]] | date = May 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Council of Europe Issue Paper, 2015===
In a wide-ranging first detailed analysis on intersex health and human rights issues by an international institution, the [[Council of Europe]] published an ''Issue Paper'' entitled ''Human rights and intersex people'' in May 2015. The document highlighted an historic lack of attention to intersex human rights, stating that current social and biomedical understandings of sex and gender make intersex people "especially vulnerable" to human rights breaches. The report cited previous reports from San Franscisco,&lt;ref name="sanfran" /&gt; the Swiss National Advisory Commission on Biomedical Ethics&lt;ref name="swissnek" /&gt; and the [[Australian Senate]].&lt;ref name="SenateOnSterilisation" /&gt; The [[Commissioner for Human Rights]] made eight recommendations. For this first time, these recognized a right to ''not'' undergo sex assignment treatment.&lt;ref name="coe" /&gt;

===UN Office of the High Commissioner for Human Rights report, 2015===

In 2015, the UN [[Office of the High Commissioner for Human Rights]] (OHCHR) described human rights violations against intersex people:

{{quotation|53. Many intersex children, born with atypical sex characteristics, are subjected to medically unnecessary surgery and treatment in an attempt to force their physical appearance to align with binary sex stereotypes. Such procedures are typically irreversible and can cause severe, long-term physical and psychological suffering.&lt;ref name="ohchr2015" /&gt;}}

The OHCHR acknowledged Australia and Malta as "the first countries to expressly prohibit discrimination against intersex persons," and Malta as "the first State to prohibit sex-assignment surgery or treatment on intersex minors without their informed consent." It called on UN member states to protect intersex persons from discrimination, and address violence by: 
* "Banning “conversion” therapy, involuntary treatment, forced sterilization and forced genital and anal examinations;"
* "Prohibiting medically unnecessary procedures on intersex children"&lt;ref name="ohchr2015"&gt;{{Citation| last = United Nations High Commissioner for Human Rights| title = Discrimination and violence against individuals based on their sexual orientation and gender identity| date = May 4, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===WHO report, "Sexual health, human rights and the law", 2015===

In June 2015, the [[World Health Organization]] published a major report on sexual and reproductive rights and the law. Section 3.4.9, on intersex people, identifies discrimination and stigma within health systems (citations omitted):&lt;ref name="who2015"&gt;{{Cite book| publisher = World Health Organization| isbn = 9789241564984| last = [[World Health Organization]]| title = Sexual health, human rights and the law| location = Geneva| date = 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quotation|Intersex people may face discrimination and stigma in the health system, in many cases being subjected to lack of quality of care, institutional violence and forced interventions throughout their lifetime.

A major concern for intersex people is that so-called sex normalizing procedures are often undertaken during their infancy and childhood, to alter their bodies, particularly the sexual organs, to make them conform to gendered physical norms, including through repeated surgeries, hormonal interventions and other measures. As a result, such children may be subjected to medically unnecessary, often irreversible, interventions that may have lifelong consequences for their physical and mental health, including irreversible termination of all or some of their reproductive and sexual capacity.&lt;ref name="who2015" /&gt;}}

The report stated that intersex persons are entitled "to access health services on the same basis as others, free from coercion, discrimination and violence", with the ability offer free and informed consent. The report also called for the education and training of medical and psychological professionals on "physical, biological and sexual diversity and integrity".&lt;ref name="who2015" /&gt;

===Asia Pacific Forum of NHRIs manual, 2016===

In 2016, the [[Asia Pacific Forum]] of [[National Human Rights Institutions]] (AFP) manual on Promoting and Protecting Human Rights in relation to [[Sexual Orientation]], [[Gender Identity]] and [[Sex characteristics|Sex Characteristics]].&lt;ref name="afp2016"&gt;{{Cite book| publisher = [[Asia Pacific Forum|Asia Pacific Forum of National Human Rights Institutions]]| isbn = 978-0-9942513-7-4| last = Asia Pacific Forum of National Human Rights Institutions| title = Promoting and Protecting Human Rights in relation to Sexual Orientation, Gender Identity and Sex Characteristics| date = June 2016| url = http://www.asiapacificforum.net/resources/manual-sogi-and-sex-charactersitics/}}&lt;/ref&gt; The document provides an analysis of human rights issues, including the rights to physical integrity, non-discrimination, effective remedies and redress, and recognition before the law. The report states:

{{quotation|Intersex people often experience human rights violations because their bodies are different. These include so-called ‘sex-normalising’ surgeries or hormone treatment on infants and children, that are medically unnecessary and typically performed when a child is too young to be involved in the decision-making process. These practices violate the right to physical integrity and have been described by human rights bodies as forms of torture or ill-treatment and as harmful practices. Fear and discrimination can never justify human rights abuses, including forced medical treatment. States have a duty to combat harmful stereotypes and discrimination against intersex people.&lt;ref name="afp2016" /&gt;}}

=== UN and regional experts statement, 2016 ===

For [[Intersex Awareness Day]], October 26, UN experts including the [[United Nations Convention against Torture#Committee against Torture| Committee against Torture]], the [[Committee on the Rights of the Child]] and the [[Committee on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities]], along with the Council of Europe [[Commissioner for Human Rights]], the [[Inter-American Commission on Human Rights]] and [[United Nations Special Rapporteur]]s called for an urgent end to human rights violations against intersex persons, including in medical settings. The experts also called for the investigation of human rights abuses, access to reparations, and the implementation of anti-discrimination measures.&lt;ref name="un-2016"&gt;{{Cite| last = Office of the High Commissioner for Human Rights| authorlink = Office of the United Nations High Commissioner for Human Rights |title = End violence and harmful medical practices on intersex children and adults, UN and regional experts urge| date = October 24, 2016| url = http://www.ohchr.org/EN/NewsEvents/Pages/DisplayNews.aspx?NewsID=20739&amp;LangID=E}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="radcliffe-2016"&gt;{{Cite web| last = Radcliffe| first = Charles| title = Intersex Ed at the UN| work = [[The Huffington Post]]| accessdate = 2016-10-26| date = October 24, 2016| url = http://www.huffingtonpost.com/charles-radcliffe/intersex-ed-at-the-un_b_12613864.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quotation|States must, as a matter of urgency, prohibit medically unnecessary surgery and procedures on intersex children. They must uphold the autonomy of intersex adults and children and their rights to health, to physical and mental integrity, to live free from violence and harmful practices and to be free from torture and ill-treatment. Intersex children and their parents should be provided with support and counselling, including from peers.&lt;ref name="un-2016" /&gt;}}

The [[Office of the United Nations High Commissioner for Human Rights|United Nations Office of the High Commissioner for Human Rights]] also launched a website, ''United Nations for Intersex Awareness''.&lt;ref name="unfe-2016"&gt;{{cite web|url = http://unfe.org/intersex-awareness|title = United Nations for Intersex Awareness | date = October 2016 | last = Office of the High Commissioner for Human Rights| authorlink = Office of the United Nations High Commissioner for Human Rights }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Disorders of Sex Development]]
*[[Intersex surgery]]
*[[Legal recognition of intersex people]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist|30em}}

{{Human rights}}
{{Discrimination|state=collapsed}}

[[Category:Gender studies]]
[[Category:Queer theory]]
[[Category:Intersex rights|Human rights]]
[[Category:Human rights by issue]]
[[Category:Medical ethics]]
[[Category:Minority rights]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>