<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20211110010221|1054434127" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1890864" pageid="1890864" ns="0" title="Guttmacher Institute"><revisions><rev timestamp="2021-11-11T07:53:03Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox organization
|name         = Guttmacher Institute
|image        =
|image_border =
|size         =
|caption      =
|map          =
|msize        =
|mcaption     =
|abbreviation =
|motto        =
|formation    = {{start date and age|1968}} (as Center for Family Planning Program Development)
|extinction   =
|type         = NGO
|status       =
|purpose      = [[reproductive health]], [[birth control]]
|headquarters =
|location     =
|region_served = United States and globally
|membership   =
|language     =
|leader_title =
|leader_name  =
|main_organ   =
|parent_organization =
|affiliations =
|num_staff    =
|num_volunteers =
|budget       = $19 million
|website      = [http://www.guttmacher.org www.guttmacher.org]
|remarks      =
}}
The '''Guttmacher Institute''' is a [[Abortion-rights movements|pro-choice]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.economist.com/united-states/2019/07/20/abortion-laws-get-more-attention-in-the-culture-wars|title=Abortion laws get more attention in the culture wars|work=The Economist|access-date=2020-03-10|issn=0013-0613|quote=the Guttmacher Institute, a pro-choice think-tank}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.buzzfeednews.com/article/emaoconnor/abortion-rights-decade-bans-trump-kavanaugh-planned|title=The Decade That Dismantled Abortion Rights|website=BuzzFeed News|language=en|access-date=2020-03-10|quote=reproductive rights group Guttmacher Institute}}&lt;/ref&gt; research organization started in 1968 that works to study, educate, and advance sexual and reproductive health and rights.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Bass|first=Hannah|date=2012-01-25|title=Guttmacher Institute|url=https://www.bmj.com/content/344/bmj.e623|journal=BMJ|language=en|volume=344|pages=e623|doi=10.1136/bmj.e623|issn=0959-8138|pmid=22279095|s2cid=5319414}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.benefunder.com/life-science-causes/guttmacher-institute/the-guttmacher-institute-the-scientific-backbone-of-the-reproductive-health-community|title=The Guttmacher Institute: The Scientific Backbone of the Reproductive Health Community {{!}} Benefunder|website=www.benefunder.com|language=en|access-date=2018-10-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; The organization works mainly in the United States but also focuses on developing countries.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt; The Guttmacher Institute uses studies to help support policy making and program reform.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt; The Institute is named after [[Obstetrics and gynaecology|obstetrician-gynocologist]] and former president of [[Planned Parenthood]] [[Alan Frank Guttmacher|Alan F. Guttmacher]].&lt;ref name=":2"&gt;{{Cite news|title=Guttmacher Institute|last=Valentine|first=Barbara|work=College &amp; Research Libraries News}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Guttmacher Institute has many sources of funding nationally and internationally.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt; One of the Institute's biggest projects is keeping a running list of the reproductive health laws and policies throughout the United States.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;

== History ==
Founded in 1968, the Guttmacher Institute was originally called the Center for Family Planning Program Development and was a branch of [[Planned Parenthood]].&lt;ref name=":2"/&gt; After Alan Guttmacher’s death, the Center for Family Planning Program Development was renamed and became an independent [[Nonprofit organization|non-profit organization.]]&lt;ref name=":2"/&gt; In 2007, the organization officially split from Planned Parenthood.&lt;ref name=":0"/&gt;

== Activities ==
The Guttmacher Institute continually updates its analysis of state and national laws and policies about contraception and abortion.  The Institute keeps a record of the restrictions on reproductive health that different states have put in place. The organization also keeps data about how teens are affected by pregnancy and the number of teens who use contraception.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt; Internationally, the Guttmacher Institute uses methodologies to give an approximation of abortions in places where the data is not as accessible or the abortions happen outside of the health care setting.&lt;ref name=":1"/&gt;

In 2013, it was awarded a Population Center grant by the US [[National Institutes of Health]] in support of the Guttmacher Center for Population Research Innovation and Dissemination.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt; The Guttmacher Institute has received [[Charity Navigator]]’s highest 4-star rating annually since 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.charitynavigator.org/index.cfm?bay=search.summary&amp;orgid=3226#.V0N1h-IrJD8|title=Charity Navigator - Rating for Guttmacher Institute|website=Charity Navigator|access-date=2016-05-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2011 and 2013, the Institute was named the number one organization in the field of reproductive health by Philanthropedia.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.myphilanthropedia.org/top-nonprofits/national/reproductive-health-rights-justice/2010/guttmacher-institute|title=Guttmacher Institute|website=Philanthropedia|access-date=2016-05-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Funding ==

The Institute was first started in 1968 as part of Planned Parenthood, which was its sole source of funding.&lt;ref name=":0"/&gt; After the Guttmacher Institute became independent from Planned Parenthood in 2007, the organization received less than 1% of its funding from Planned Parenthood in 2010.&lt;ref name=":0"/&gt; Now, most of the funding is gained through private foundations based in the United States. Other funding does come from international organizations such as the [[World Health Organization]] and the [[World Bank]].&lt;ref name=":1"/&gt;  The Guttmacher Institute was awarded $3.9 million between 1986 and 2015 by the [[MacArthur Foundation]], including 13 grants in population and reproductive health.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title = Guttmacher Institute - MacArthur Foundation| access-date = 2020-05-15| url = https://www.macfound.org/grantees/356/}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Bias ==
The Guttmacher Institute is not affiliated with a political party, and so it is nonpartisan in the strict sense of the word. It is true that the group does work to "ensure that all women are able to exercise their reproductive rights and responsibilities," which puts them among advocates of abortion rights. However, according to Factcheck.org, Guttmacher "provides the most highly respected statistics on the sexual health of women and men. Its figures on abortion are widely cited by the media as well as by groups on both sides of the political aisle."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.factcheck.org/2010/04/factcheck-mailbag-week-of-april-6-april-12/|title=FactCheck Mailbag, Week of April 6-April 12 - FactCheck.org|date=2010-04-13|work=FactCheck.org|access-date=2018-10-26|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Sharon Camp]], former CEO

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.guttmacher.org Official website]
* [https://findingaids.smith.edu/repositories/2/resources/964 Guttmacher Institute records] at the [https://www.smith.edu/libraries/special-collections Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College]

{{authority control}}

[[Category:Dupont Circle]]
[[Category:Medical research institutes in the United States]]
[[Category:Non-profit organizations based in Washington, D.C.]]
[[Category:Scientific organizations established in 1968]]
[[Category:Abortion-rights organizations]]
[[Category:Planned Parenthood]]
[[Category:1968 establishments in the United States]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>