<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20071102161723|168752657" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1890864" pageid="1890864" ns="0" title="Guttmacher Institute"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-11-02T21:10:11Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">The '''Guttmacher Institute''' is a [[non-profit organization]] which works to advance [[reproductive health]] as defined by the [[World Health Organization]]. The institute operates in the [[United States]] and globally "through an interrelated program of social science research, policy analysis and public education."&lt;ref name="mission"&gt;[http://www.guttmacher.org/about/mission.html "Mission: The Guttmacher Institute’s Future"] ''guttmacher.org'' Retrieved November 1, 2007&lt;/ref&gt; According to their mission statement, this program aims to "generate new ideas, encourage enlightened public debate, promote sound policy and program development and, ultimately, inform individual decision making."&lt;ref name="mission"/&gt;

The Guttmacher Institute has played a leading role in the movement for women's sexual and reproductive rights since the institute's inception in 1968, when it was founded as the "Center for Family Planning Program Development", a semiautonomous division of The [[Planned Parenthood]] Federation of America. The Center was renamed in memory of [[Alan Guttmacher]], an [[Obstetrics and gynaecology|Ob/Gyn]] and former president of Planned Parenthood, and the Guttmacher Institute became an independent, not-for-profit corporation in 1977.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guttmacher.org/about/history.html The History of the Guttmacher Institute]&lt;/ref&gt; Guttmacher's nearly four decades of experience claims to demonstrate that scientific evidence &amp;mdash; when reliably collected and analyzed, compellingly presented and systematically disseminated &amp;mdash; can make a difference in policies, programs, and medical practice.

The institute has offices in both [[New York City]] and [[Washington, D.C.]] As of 2005, it has an annual revenue of $7.9 million and expenses of $9.1 million, with an asset reserve of $15.6 million dollars.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guttmacher.org/about/2006/06/22/AnnualReport2005.pdf Progress Through Partnership: Annual Report of the Guttmacher Institute]&lt;/ref&gt; The institute produces two [[peer review]]ed periodicals, ''International Family Planning Perspectives'' and ''Perspectives on Sexual and Reproductive Health'', in addition to a third periodical on public policy, ''The Guttmacher Policy Review''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guttmacher.org/journals/aboutper.html "Guttmacher Institute Periodicals"]. ''guttmacher.org'' Retrieved November 1, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.guttmacher.org/ Guttmacher Institute] official page

[[Category:Research institutes in the United States]]
[[Category:Birth control]]
[[Category:Pro-choice organizations]]

{{abortion-stub}}
{{sci-org-stub}}

[[fr:Guttmacher Institute]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>