<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20181029160053|866310219" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1890864" pageid="1890864" ns="0" title="Guttmacher Institute"><revisions><rev timestamp="2018-10-29T16:08:22Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Primary sources|date=March 2009}}
{{Infobox Organization
|name         = Guttmacher Institute
|image        =
|image_border =
|size         =
|caption      =
|map          =
|msize        =
|mcaption     =
|abbreviation =
|motto        =
|formation    = {{start date and age|1968}} (as Center for Family Planning Program Development)
|extinction   =
|type         = NGO
|status       =
|purpose      = [[reproductive health]], [[birth control]]
|headquarters =
|location     =
|region_served = United States and globally
|membership   =
|language     =
|leader_title =
|leader_name  =
|main_organ   =
|parent_organization =
|affiliations =
|num_staff    =
|num_volunteers =
|budget       = $17.5 million
|website      = [http://www.guttmacher.org www.guttmacher.org]
|remarks      =
}}
The Guttmacher Institute is a research organization started in 1968 that works to study, educate, and advance sexual and reproductive health and rights.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Bass|first=Hannah|date=2012-01-25|title=Guttmacher Institute|url=https://www.bmj.com/content/344/bmj.e623|journal=BMJ|language=en|volume=344|pages=e623|doi=10.1136/bmj.e623|issn=0959-8138|pmid=22279095}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.benefunder.com/life-science-causes/guttmacher-institute/the-guttmacher-institute-the-scientific-backbone-of-the-reproductive-health-community|title=The Guttmacher Institute: The Scientific Backbone of the Reproductive Health Community {{!}} Benefunder|website=www.benefunder.com|language=en|access-date=2018-10-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;The organization works mainly in the United States but also focuses on developing countries.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;The Guttmacher Institute uses studies to help support policy making and program reform. &lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;The Institute is named after [[Obstetrics and gynaecology|obstetrician-gynocologist]] and the former president of [[Planned Parenthood]], [[Alan Frank Guttmacher|Alan F. Guttmacher]]. &lt;ref name=":2"&gt;{{Cite news|title=Guttmacher Institute|last=Valentine|first=Barbara|date=|work=College &amp; Research Libraries News|access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;The Guttmacher Institute has many sources of funding nationally and internationally.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;One of the Institute's biggest projects is keeping a running list of the reproductive health laws and policies throughout the United States. &lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;


== History ==
Founded in 1968, the Guttmacher Institute was originally called the Center for Family Planning Program Development and was a branch of [[Planned Parenthood]].&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt;After Alan Guttmacher’s death, the Center for Family Planning Program Development was renamed and became an independent [[Nonprofit organization|non-profit organization.]]&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt;In 2007, the organization officially split from Planned Parenthood. &lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

== Activities ==
The Guttmacher Institute continually updates its analysis of state and national laws and policies about contraception and abortion.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt; The Institute keeps a record the restrictions that different states have put in place for reproductive health. The organization also keeps data about how teens are affected by pregnancy and the number of teens who use contraception.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt; Internationally, the Guttmacher Institute uses methodologies to give an approximation of abortions in places where the data is not as accessible or the abortions happen outside of the health care setting. &lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;

In 2013, it was awarded a Population Center grant by the US [[National Institutes of Health]] in support of the Guttmacher Center for Population Research Innovation and Dissemination.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt; The Guttmacher Institute has received [[Charity Navigator]]’s highest 4-star rating annually since 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.charitynavigator.org/index.cfm?bay=search.summary&amp;orgid=3226#.V0N1h-IrJD8|title=Charity Navigator - Rating for Guttmacher Institute|website=Charity Navigator|access-date=2016-05-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2011 and 2013, the Institute was named the number one organization in the field of reproductive health by Philanthropedia.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.myphilanthropedia.org/top-nonprofits/national/reproductive-health-rights-justice/2010/guttmacher-institute|title=Guttmacher Institute|website=Philanthropedia|access-date=2016-05-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Funding ==
When the Institute was first started in 1968 as part of [[Planned Parenthood]], its funding was solely from Planned Parenthood.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;Once the Guttmacher Institute was no longer connected to Planned Parenthood in 2007, the organization only received less than 1% of its funding from Planned Parenthood in 2010&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;. Now, most of the funding is gained through private foundations based in the United States. Other funding does come from international organizations such as the [[World Health Organization]]&lt;nowiki/&gt;and the [[World Bank]].&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;Over the last 25 years, the [[MacArthur Foundation]] has provided funding so that the Guttmacher Institute can conduct studies internationally on the abortion rates and reproductive health of women. &lt;ref name=":4"&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.macfound.org/grantees/356/|title=Guttmacher Institute - MacArthur Foundation|website=www.macfound.org|language=en|access-date=2018-10-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;



== Bias ==
The Guttmacher Institute has no political affiliation. Although their mission supports reproductive health, which also includes abortion, the organization is [[Nonpartisanism|nonpartisan]]. The data released by the Guttmacher institute are respected, considered accurate, and used in media and by supporters of different political ideologies.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.factcheck.org/2010/04/factcheck-mailbag-week-of-april-6-april-12/|title=FactCheck Mailbag, Week of April 6-April 12 - FactCheck.org|date=2010-04-13|work=FactCheck.org|access-date=2018-10-26|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
[[Sharon Camp]], former CEO

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.guttmacher.org Official website]
* [http://asteria.fivecolleges.edu/findaids/sophiasmith/mnsss558_main.html Records, 1960-2013]
* [https://www.smith.edu/libraries/special-collections Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College]


[[Category:Dupont Circle]]
[[Category:Medical research institutes in the United States]]
[[Category:Non-profit organizations based in Washington, D.C.]]
[[Category:Organizations established in 1968]]
[[Category:Pro-choice organizations]]
[[Category:Planned Parenthood]]
[[Category:1968 establishments in the United States]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>