<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20240501180020|1221735160" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="56481836" pageid="56481836" ns="0" title="Taste-based discrimination"><revisions><rev timestamp="2024-08-12T03:00:02Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Economic model of discrimination}}
{{Discrimination sidebar|expanded=Forms}}
'''Taste-based discrimination''' is an economic model of [[labor market]] [[discrimination]] which argues that employers' [[prejudice]] or dislikes in an [[Organizational culture|organisational culture]] rooted in [[prohibited grounds]] can have negative results in hiring [[Minority group|minority workers]], meaning that they can be said to have a '''taste for discrimination'''. The model further posits that employers discriminate against minority applicants to avoid interacting with them, regardless of the applicant's productivity, and that employers are willing to pay a financial penalty to do so. It is one of the two leading theoretical explanations for labor market discrimination, the other being [[Statistical discrimination (economics)|statistical discrimination]].&lt;ref name=letters&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Baert |first1=Stijn |last2=Pauw |first2=Ann-Sophie De |title=Is ethnic discrimination due to distaste or statistics? |journal=Economics Letters |volume=125 |issue=2 |pages=270–273 |doi=10.1016/j.econlet.2014.09.020|hdl=1854/LU-5704419 |year=2014 |s2cid=154444808 |url=https://biblio.ugent.be/publication/5704419 |hdl-access=free }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2002/12/12/business/economic-scene-sticks-stones-can-break-bones-but-wrong-name-can-make-job-hard.html |title=Economic Scene; Sticks and stones can break bones, but the wrong name can make a job hard to find. |last=Krueger |first=Alan B. |date=2002-12-12 |work=The New York Times |access-date=2018-02-03 |language=en-US |issn=0362-4331}}&lt;/ref&gt; The taste-based model further supposes that employers' preference for employees of certain groups is unrelated to their preference for more productive employees.&lt;ref name=from/&gt; According to this model, employees that are members of a group that is discriminated against may have to work harder for the same wage or accept a lower wage for the same work as other employees.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://economics.mit.edu/files/553 |title=Lecture Note: The Economics of Discrimination — Theory |last=Autor |first=David |date=2003-11-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Taste-based discrimination can be observed from the side of employers, customers or co-workers. In the case of an employer's "taste for discrimination", the employer aims to avoid non-monetary costs and does so often based on his own preferences. In the case of co-workers and customers, they may not want to interact with people belonging to a certain group, which the employer considers during the hiring process.

==History==
The taste-based discrimination model was first proposed by [[Gary Becker]] in 1957 in his book ''The economics of discrimination''.&lt;ref name=from&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Neilson |first1=William |last2=Ying |first2=Shanshan |title=From taste-based to statistical discrimination |journal=Journal of Economic Behavior &amp; Organization |volume=129 |pages=116–128 |doi=10.1016/j.jebo.2016.06.001|year=2016 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Becker argued that the reasons for such discrimination should be determined by psychologists and sociologists, not by economists, and he sought only to determine the consequences of discrimination as manifested in economic decision-making.&lt;ref name=iess&gt;{{Cite encyclopedia |title=Discrimination, Taste For  |encyclopedia=International Encyclopedia of the Social Sciences  |url=http://www.encyclopedia.com/social-sciences/applied-and-social-sciences-magazines/discrimination-taste |date=2008 |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; The early version of this model was criticized for failing to explain the continued existence of discriminating firms, because it predicts that these firms will be less profitable than their non-discriminating counterparts.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Siddique |first=Zahra |title=Evidence on Caste Based Discrimination |journal=Labour Economics |volume=18 |pages=S146–S159 |doi=10.1016/j.labeco.2011.07.002|year=2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Nevertheless, the taste-based model has since become the predominant economic explanation for discriminatory practices.&lt;ref name=iess/&gt;

==Distinguishing from statistical discrimination==
It is difficult for economists to distinguish between taste-based and statistical discrimination.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Moser |first=Petra |title=Taste-based discrimination: evidence from a shift in ethnic preferences after WWI |journal=Explorations in Economic History |volume=49 |issue=2 |pages=167–188 |doi=10.1016/j.eeh.2011.12.003|year=2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt; A paper in 2008 studied the effect [[World War I]] had on German Americans as traders at the [[New York Stock Exchange]]. &lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; The German Americans were discriminated against as a consequence of the war and were considered an ethnic minority, creating opportunity for taste-based discrimination in the trade market. The results showed that the discrimination indeed had an effect on the German Americans in the NYSE, where the rates of their rejection doubled. However, the discrimination had no effects on the price of NYSE seats.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

In 2014, researchers from the [[Center for Economic and Policy Research]] conducted a study of the [[Fantasy Premier League]], which is an online game where players choose their 15 players from 20 participant [[Premier League]] teams. Since this is a virtual game, the players are able to discriminate without  real life consequences. There are no real customers and the "workers" (players) do not interact. This allowed the research team to control for statistical discrimination, because all information about potential employees' productivity is publicly disclosed. The results showed that the research subjects were choosing players based on their performance, which is measured in points, and the race of the players did not play a role. The research was done over a period of three years and no evidence of taste-based discrimination was found.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://voxeu.org/article/there-taste-discrimination |title=Is there a 'taste for discrimination'? |last1=Bryson |first1=Alex |last2=Chevalier |first2=Arnaud |date=2014-08-15 |website=VoxEU.org |access-date=2018-02-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist}}
==External links==
*[http://www.dictionaryofeconomics.com/article?id=pde2009_T000251 Entry] in ''[[The New Palgrave Dictionary of Economics]]''

{{Discrimination}}

[[Category:Employment discrimination]]
[[Category:Labour economics]]
[[Category:Economic theories]]
[[Category:Sociological theories]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>