<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20231127143724|1187107161" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="67529786" pageid="67529786" ns="0" title="Racism against African Americans"><revisions><rev timestamp="2023-11-28T16:33:44Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|none}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=September 2022}}

[[File:Rc17739 04.jpg|alt=Black and white photograph of segregationists fighting on a beach|thumb|White segregationists (foreground) trying to prevent Black people from swimming at a "White only" beach in St. Augustine, Florida in 1964]]
{{Discrimination sidebar|state=collapsed}}
In the context of [[racism in the United States]], '''racism against African Americans''' dates back to the [[Colonial history of the United States|colonial era]], and it continues to be a persistent issue in [[Society of the United States|American society]] in the 21st century.

From the arrival of the first Africans in early colonial times until after the [[American Civil War]], most [[African Americans]] were [[Slavery in the United States|enslaved]]. Even free African Americans have faced restrictions on their political, social, and economic freedoms, being subjected to [[lynching]]s, [[Racial segregation in the United States|segregation]], [[Black Codes (United States)|Black Codes]], [[Jim Crow laws]], and other forms of discrimination, both before and after the Civil War. Thanks to the [[civil rights movement]], formal racial discrimination was gradually outlawed by the [[Federal government of the United States|federal government]], and gradually came to be perceived as socially and morally unacceptable by large elements of American society. Despite this, racism against Black Americans remains widespread in the U.S., and it continues to be [[Racial inequality in the United States|reflected in socioeconomic inequality]].{{efn|In his 2009 visit to the US, the [UN] Special Rapporteur on Racism noted that "Socio-economic indicators show that poverty, [[Race (human categorization)|race]] and [[Ethnic group|ethnicity]] continue to overlap in the United States. This reality is a direct legacy of the past, in particular, it is a direct legacy of slavery, segregation and the forcible resettlement of Native Americans, which was confronted by the United States during the [[civil rights movement]]. However, whereas the country managed to establish equal treatment and non-discrimination in its laws, it has yet to redress the socioeconomic consequences of the historical legacy of racism."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author = CERD Task Force of the US Human Rights Network |title = Universal Periodic Review Joint Reports: United States of America |chapter = From Civil Rights to Human Rights: Implementing US Obligations Under the International Convention on the Elimination of All forms of Racial Discrimination (ICERD) |date = August 2010 |page = 44 }}&lt;/ref&gt;}}&lt;ref&gt;Henry, P. J., David O. Sears. Race and Politics: The Theory of Symbolic Racism. University of California, Los Angeles. 2002.&lt;/ref&gt; In recent years research has uncovered extensive evidence of racial discrimination in various sectors of modern U.S. society, including the [[#Criminal justice system|criminal justice]] system, [[#Business|businesses]], the [[Economic discrimination|economy]], [[#Housing and land|housing]], [[#Health|health care]], the [[#Media|media]], and [[#Politics|politics]]. In the view of the United Nations and the [[US Human Rights Network]], "[[discrimination in the United States]] permeates all aspects of life and extends to all [[people of color|communities of color]]."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title = Universal Periodic Review Joint Reports: United States of America |author = U.S. Human Rights Network |date = August 2010 |page = 8 |chapter = The United States of America: Summary Submission to the UN Universal Periodic Review }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Citizenship and voting rights==
The [[Naturalization Act of 1790]] set the first uniform rules for the granting of [[Citizenship of the United States|United States citizenship]] by [[naturalization]], which limited naturalisation to "free white person[s]", thus excluding from citizenship Native Americans, [[Indentured servitude|indentured servants]], [[History of slavery|slaves]], [[Free Negro|free Blacks]], and later [[Asian Americans|Asians]]. Citizenship and the lack of it had special impact on various legal and political rights, most notably [[Voting rights in the United States|suffrage rights]] at both the federal and state level, as well as the right to hold certain government offices, jury duty, military service, and many other activities, besides access to government assistance and services. The second [[Militia Act of 1792]] also provided for the [[conscription]] of every "free able-bodied white male citizen".&lt;ref&gt;[[s:United States Statutes at Large/Volume 1/2nd Congress/1st Session/Chapter 33|second Militia Act of 1792]]&lt;/ref&gt; Tennessee's 1834 Constitution included a provision: “the free white men of this State have a right to Keep and bear arms for their common defense.”&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://cdm15138.contentdm.oclc.org/cdm/compoundobject/collection/tfd/id/495/rec/2 |title=Tennessee Constitution, 1834 |access-date=2018-02-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Citizenship, however, did not guarantee any particular rights, such as the right to vote. Black Americans, for example, who gained formal US citizenship by 1870, were soon [[Disfranchisement after the Reconstruction era|disenfranchised]]. For example, after 1890, less than 9,000 of Mississippi's 147,000 eligible African-American voters were registered to vote, or about 6%. Louisiana went from 130,000 registered African-American voters in 1896 to 1,342 in 1904 (about a 99% decrease).{{cn|date=August 2021}} They were also subjected to [[Black Codes (United States)|Black Codes]] and discriminated against in the Southern states by [[Jim Crow laws]]. [[Voter suppression in the United States|Voter suppression]] efforts around the country, though mainly motivated by political considerations, often effectively disproportionately affect African Americans and other minorities. In 2016, one in 13 African-Americans of voting age was disenfranchised, more than four times greater than that of non-African-Americans. Over 7.4% of adult African-Americans were disenfranchised compared to 1.8% of non-African-Americans. [[Felony disenfranchisement in Florida]] disqualifies over 10% of its citizens for life and over 23% of its African-American citizens.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=6 Million Lost Voters: State-Level Estimates of Felony Disenfranchisement, 2016 |url=https://felonvoting.procon.org/wp-content/uploads/sites/48/sentencing-project-felony-disenfranchisement-2016.pdf |website=ProCon.org |publisher=The Sentencing Project |access-date=September 22, 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Antebellum period==
{{see|Colonial history of the United States|History of the United States (1789–1849)|History of the United States (1849–1865)|Antebellum South}}

[[Slavery]], as a form of [[Forced labour|forced labor]], has existed in many cultures, dating back to [[Cradle of civilization|early human civilizations]]. Slavery is not inherently racial ''per se.'' In the United States, however, [[Slavery in the United States|slavery]], having [[Slavery in the colonial history of the United States|been established]] in the [[Colonial history of the United States|colonial era]], became [[Racial hierarchy|racialized]] by the time of the [[American Revolutionary War|American Revolution]] (1775–1783), when slavery was widely institutionalized as a racial caste system which was based on African ancestry and [[Discrimination based on skin color|skin color]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |url= http://www.slate.com/articles/life/the_history_of_american_slavery/2015/05/why_america_adopted_race_based_slavery.html |title= The Birth of Race-Based Slavery |last=Wood |first=Peter |date=2003 |journal=Slate |id= (May 19, 2015): Reprinted from "Strange New Land: Africans in Colonial America" by Peter H. Wood with permission from Oxford University Press. ©1996, 2003}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Slavery===
{{main|Slavery in the United States}}
{{further|Atlantic slave trade|The 1619 Project}}
[[File:Slave Auction Ad.jpg|thumb|right|Reproduction of a handbill advertising a slave auction in [[Charleston, South Carolina]], in 1769]]

The [[Atlantic slave trade]] prospered, with more than 470,000 persons forcibly transported from Africa between 1626 and 1860 to what is now the United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Eltis|first=David|title=Extending the Frontiers: Essays on the New Transatlantic Slave Trade Database |url=https://archive.org/details/extendingfrontie00elti |url-access=limited |year=2008 |publisher=Yale University Press|location=New Haven|isbn=978-0300134360| page=[https://archive.org/details/extendingfrontie00elti/page/n47 31]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Eltis |first=David |title=Estimates |url=http://www.slavevoyages.org/tast/assessment/estimates.faces |access-date=October 19, 2013 |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20131027021745/http://www.slavevoyages.org/tast/assessment/estimates.faces |archive-date=October 27, 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Prior to the [[American Civil War|Civil War]], eight serving presidents were slaveholders, and slavery was protected by the [[Constitution of the United States|U.S. Constitution]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Calore|first1=Paul|title=The Causes of the Civil War: The Political, Cultural, Economic and Territorial Disputes between North and South|date=2008|publisher=McFarland|page=10}}&lt;/ref&gt; Creating wealth for the White elite, approximately one in four [[Southern United States|Southern]] families held Black people in slavery prior to the Civil War. According to the 1860 U.S. census, there were about 385,000 slave owners out of a White population of approximately 7 million in the slave states.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fpri.org/articles/2008/08/teaching-about-slavery|title=Teaching about Slavery|work=Foreign Policy Research Institute}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Alonzo L. Hamby]], George Clack, and Mildred Sola Neely. [http://usinfo.state.gov/products/pubs/historybrf/index.htm "Outline of US History"] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080405170847/http://usinfo.state.gov/products/pubs/historybrf/index.htm |date=April 5, 2008 }}. US Department of State.&lt;/ref&gt; White European Americans who participated in the slave industry tried to justify their economic exploitation of [[Black people]] by creating a [[Scientific racism|"scientific" theory of White superiority and Black inferiority]].&lt;ref name=Boggs&gt;{{cite journal |jstor=41202851 |title=Uprooting Racism and Racists in the United States |last=Boggs |first=James |author-link=James Boggs (activist) |journal=The Black Scholar |publisher=Paradigm Publishers |date=October 1970 |volume=2 |number=2 |pages=2–5|doi=10.1080/00064246.1970.11431000 }}&lt;/ref&gt; One such slave owner was [[Thomas Jefferson]], and it was his call for science to determine the obvious "inferiority" of Blacks that is regarded as "an extremely important stage in the evolution of scientific racism."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Garrod |first1=Joel Z.|title=A Brave Old World: An Analysis of Scientific Racism and BiDil |journal=McGill Journal of Medicine |volume=9|issue=1|pages=54–60|pmc=2687899|year=2006|pmid=19529811}}&lt;/ref&gt; He concluded that Blacks were "inferior to the whites in the endowments of body and mind."&lt;ref&gt;Paul Finkelman (November 12, 2012). [https://www.nytimes.com/2012/12/01/opinion/the-real-thomas-jefferson.html?pagewanted=all "The Monster of Monticello"]. ''The New York Times''. Retrieved July 14, 2020.&lt;/ref&gt;

Groups of armed White men, who were called [[slave patrol]]s, were formed to monitor enslaved Black people.&lt;ref name="Policing"/&gt; First established in South Carolina in 1704 and later established in other [[Slave states and free states|slave states]], their function was to police slaves, especially runaways. Slave owners feared that slaves might organize revolts or rebellions, so state militias were formed to provide a military command structure and discipline within the slave patrols so they could be used to detect, encounter, and crush any organized slave meetings which might lead to revolts or rebellions.&lt;ref name="Policing"&gt;{{Cite web|date=July 10, 2019|title=Slave Patrols: An Early Form of American Policing|url=https://lawenforcementmuseum.org/2019/07/10/slave-patrols-an-early-form-of-american-policing/|access-date=2020-06-16|website=National Law Enforcement Museum|language=en-US|archive-date=June 9, 2020|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20200609091807/https://lawenforcementmuseum.org/2019/07/10/slave-patrols-an-early-form-of-american-policing/|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Loewen, James W. Lies Across America: What Our Historic Sites Get Wrong. The New Press, 2013. Print.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Controlling free Blacks===
[[File:Scourged back by McPherson &amp; Oliver, 1863, retouched.jpg|thumb|right|A photograph of [[Gordon (slave)|Gordon]] showing the scars accumulated from whipping during his enslavement]]

During the 1820s and 1830s, the solution of the [[American Colonization Society]] (ACS) to the presence of [[Free Negro|free Blacks]] was to persuade them to emigrate to Africa.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fcnl.org/issues/item.php?item_id=731&amp;issue_id=75 |title=Background on conflict in Liberia |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110108042234/http://www.fcnl.org/issues/item.php?item_id=731&amp;issue_id=75 |archive-date=January 8, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1821, the ACS established the colony of [[Liberia]], and persuaded thousands of former slaves and free Black people to move there. Some slaves were [[Manumission|manumitted]] (set free) on condition that they emigrate. The slave states made no secret that they wanted to get rid of free Blacks, who they believed threatened their investment, the slaves, encouraging escapes and revolts. The support for the ACS was primarily Southern. The founder of the ACS, [[Henry Clay]] of Kentucky, stated that because of "unconquerable prejudice resulting from their color, they never could amalgamate with the free whites of this country. It was desirable, therefore, as it respected them, and the residue of the population of the country, to drain them off".&lt;ref name=ATH&gt;Maggie Montesinos Sale (1997). ''The slumbering volcano: American slave ship revolts and the production of rebellious masculinity''. p. 264. Duke University Press, 1997. {{ISBN|0822319926}}&lt;/ref&gt; Thousands of Black people were resettled in Liberia, where they formed an American English speaking enclave which could not assimilate back into African life and as a result, most of them died of tropical diseases.

White supremacist American governments emphasized the importance of the subjugation and control of other racial populations. In 1824 the [[South Carolina Senate|Senate of South Carolina]] enacted a resolution echoing the wording of the [[Supremacy Clause]] of the [[Constitution of the United States]], declaring that the paramount objective of its government was to prevent the insubordination of black citizens and any possible [[:Category:Slave rebellions in the United States|slave rebellions]] as well as any social or political causes which might instrumentally lead to such insubordination or insurrection, and declaring that this purpose was paramount over all other laws, constitutions, and domestic or international agreements:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|editor-surname=Ames|editor-given=Herman Vandenburg|editor-link=Herman Vandenburg Ames|year=1904|chapter=103. Resolutions of the Senate of South Carolina|chapter-url={{fullurl:iarchive:statedocumentson05ames/page/15/mode/1up}}|title=State Documents on Federal Relations: The States and the United States|volume=5, Slavery and the Constitution, 1789–1845|location=New York|publisher=Longmans, Green &amp; Co.|page=207|lccn=09023351|oclc=797288287}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{quote|''Resolved'', That it is as much the duty of the state to guard against insubordination or insurrection among our colored population, or to control and regulate any cause which might excite or produce it, as to guard against any other evil, political or physical, which might assail us. This duty is paramount to all ''laws'', all ''treaties'', all ''constitutions''. It arises from the supreme and permanent law of nature, the law of self-preservation; and will never, by this state, be renounced, compromised, controlled or participated with any power whatever.}}

===Domestic slave trade===
{{main|Slave trade in the United States}}
[[File:Ashley's Sack (Slave Sack c. mid-19th century).jpg|thumb|right|[[Ashley's Sack]], a cloth that recounts a slave sale separating a mother and her daughter. The sack belonged to a nine-year-old girl, Ashley. It was a parting gift from her mother, Rose, after Ashley had been sold. Rose filled the sack with a dress, braid of her hair, pecans, and "my love always".]]

The importation of slaves into the United States was outlawed by federal law from 1808, but smuggling continued, the last known ship to bring enslaved Africans to the United States being the [[Clotilda (slave ship)|Clotilda]] in 1859 or 1860. The [[Slavery in the United States#Domestic slave trade and forced migration|domestic trade in human beings]] continued to be a major economic activity.&lt;ref name="CUP"&gt;{{Cite book |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=mhJcsiydNe8C&amp;pg=PA20 |page=20|title=Language, Discourse and Power in African American Culture |isbn=978-0521001496 |date= 2002 |last1=Morgan |first1=Marcyliena}}&lt;/ref&gt; Maryland and Virginia, for example, would export surplus slaves to the south. (See [[Franklin and Armfield Office]].) Enslaved family members could be split up (ie., sold off) never to see or hear of each other again.&lt;ref name="CUP" /&gt; Between 1830 and 1840, nearly 250,000 slaves were taken across state lines.&lt;ref name="CUP" /&gt; In the 1850s, more than 193,000 were transported, and historians estimate nearly one million in total were traded.&lt;ref name="CUP" /&gt;

The historian [[Ira Berlin]] called this forced migration of slaves the "Second Middle Passage", because it reproduced many of the same horrors as the [[Middle Passage]] (the name given to the transportation of slaves from Africa to North America). These sales of slaves broke up many families, with Berlin writing that whether slaves were directly uprooted or lived in fear that they or their families would be involuntarily moved, "the massive deportation traumatized black people".&lt;ref&gt;Berlin, ''Generations of Captivity'', pp. 161–62.&lt;/ref&gt; Individuals lost their connection to families and clans. Added to the earlier colonists combining slaves from different tribes, many ethnic Africans lost their knowledge of varying tribal origins in Africa. Most were descended from families who had been in the U.S. for many generations.&lt;ref name="CUP" /&gt;

==Civil War and emancipation==
[[File:Crowe-Slaves Waiting for Sale - Richmond, Virginia.jpg|thumb|left|''Slaves Waiting for Sale: Richmond, Virginia'', 1853]]

During the [[American Civil War]], the [[Militia Act of 1862]], for the first time, allowed African Americans to serve in the Union militias as soldiers. However, Black members were discriminated against in pay, with Black members being paid half of White members. Besides discrimination in pay, colored units were often disproportionately assigned laborer work, rather than combat assignments.&lt;ref name=McPherson&gt;James McPherson, ''"The Negro's Civil War"''.&lt;/ref&gt;{{Rp|198}} General [[Daniel Ullman]], commander of the [[United States Colored Troops]], remarked "I fear that many high officials outside of Washington have no other intention than that these men shall be used as diggers and drudges."&lt;ref&gt;Official Record Ser. III Vol. III p. 1126&lt;/ref&gt; Black members were organized into [[United States Colored Troops|colored regiments]]. By the end of that war, in April 1865, there were 175 colored regiments constituting about one-tenth of the [[Union Army]]. About 20 percent of colored soldiers died, their death toll being about 35 percent higher than that of white Union troops. The 1862 Militia Act, however, did not open military service to all races, only to Black Americans. In the [[Confederate States of America|Confederate]] army, non-white men were not permitted to serve as soldiers.

President [[Abraham Lincoln]]'s [[Emancipation Proclamation]], which took effect on January 1, 1863, marked a change in the federal government's position on slavery. (Up to that time, the federal government had never even taken a limited pro-emancipation stance, and it could do so only in 1862 because of the 1861 departure of almost all of the Southern members of Congress). Though the proclamation was welcomed by abolitionists, its application was limited. It did not apply, for example, to the nearly 500,000 slaves in the slave-holding [[Border states (American Civil War)|border states]] of [[Delaware]], [[Kentucky]], [[Maryland]], [[Missouri]], and the new state of [[West Virginia]], and it also did not apply in parts of [[Louisiana]] and [[Virginia]] that were occupied by Union forces. In those states, slavery remained legal until abolished by state action or by the ratification of the [[Thirteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Thirteenth Amendment]] in December 1865.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.yale.edu/lawweb/avalon/amend1.htm#13 XIII – Slavery Abolished] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160819194412/http://www.yale.edu/lawweb/avalon/amend1.htm |date=August 19, 2016 }} The Avalon Project&lt;/ref&gt;

While personally opposed to slavery (see [[Abraham Lincoln and slavery]]), Lincoln accepted the federal consensus that the Constitution did not give Congress the power to end it.&lt;ref&gt;[[James Oakes (historian)|Oakes, James]], ''The Crooked Path to Abolition: Abraham Lincoln and the Antislavery Constitution'', W. W. Norton &amp; Company, 2021, p. 55.&lt;/ref&gt; But he was also Commander in Chief of the Army and Navy. An action based on military necessity, against states that were in rebellion, would be appropriate as a step towards their defeat. The South of course interpreted the Emancipation Proclamation as a hostile act, but it allowed Lincoln to abolish slavery to a limited extent, without igniting resistance from anti-abolitionist forces in the Union. The slaves were not immediately affected by the proclamation, but advancing Union armies freed them.

About four million Black slaves were freed in 1865. Ninety-five percent of Black people lived in the South, comprising one-third of its total population, while only five percent of Black people lived in the North, comprising only one percent of its total population. Consequently, fears of eventual emancipation were much greater in the South than in the North.&lt;ref&gt;James McPherson, Drawn with the Sword, page 15&lt;/ref&gt; Based on 1860 census figures, eight percent of males who were aged 13 to 43 died in the Civil War, including six percent in the North and eighteen percent in the South.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.harvardmagazine.com/on-line/050155.html |title=The Deadliest War |magazine=Harvardmagazine.com |access-date=2013-02-16 |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070927225020/http://www.harvardmagazine.com/on-line/050155.html |archive-date=September 27, 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Though the Thirteenth Amendment formally abolished slavery throughout the United States, some Black Americans became subjected to revised forms of involuntary labor, particularly in the South, through the use of [[Black Codes (United States)|Black Codes]] that restricted African Americans' freedom and compelled them to work for low wages, and through the use of the exception in the Thirteenth Amendment, which permitted slavery "as a punishment for crime". They were also subject to [[White supremacy|White supremacist]] violence and selective enforcement of statutes.

==Reconstruction Era to World War II==
{{Main|Nadir of American race relations}}
{{Further|Lynching in the United States|Mass racial violence in the United States}}

===Reconstruction era===
[[File:Lynching-of-will-james.jpg|thumb|The mob-style [[lynching in the United States|lynching]] of [[William "Froggie" James|Will James]], Cairo, Illinois, 1909. A crowd of thousands watched the lynching.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Black Woman Reformer: Ida B. Wells, Lynching, &amp; Transatlantic Activism |url=https://archive.org/details/blackwomanreform0000silk |url-access=registration |date=2015 |publisher=University of Georgia Press |page=[https://archive.org/details/blackwomanreform0000silk/page/n18 1]|isbn=978-0820345574 }}&lt;/ref&gt;]]

After the Civil War, on December 6, 1865, the [[Thirteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|13th Amendment]], formally abolishing slavery, was ratified. The next year, Congress passed the [[Civil Rights Act of 1866]], which provided a range of civil rights and granted them to all persons who were born in the United States. Despite this, the emergence of [[Black Codes (United States)|Black Codes]] sanctioned acts of subjugation against Blacks and continued to bar African Americans from exercising their [[Civil and political rights|civil rights]]. The [[Naturalization Act of 1790]] had granted U.S. citizenship only to whites, and in 1868 the effort to broaden civil rights was underscored by the passage of the [[Fourteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|14th Amendment]], which granted citizenship to "[a]ll persons born or naturalized in the United States", regardless of race.&lt;ref name="Schultz"&gt;{{cite book |last=Schultz|first=Jeffrey D.|title=Encyclopedia of Minorities in American Politics: African Americans and Asian Americans|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=WDV40aK1T-sC&amp;q=African+Americans+discriminated+by+Naturalization+Act+of+1790&amp;pg=PA284|page=284|year=2002|access-date=2015-09-14|isbn=978-1573561488}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Civil Rights Act of 1875]] followed, which was eliminated in a decision that undermined federal power to thwart private racial discrimination.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Estreicher|first=Samuel|title=Federal Power to Regulate Private Discrimination: The Revival of the Enforcement Clauses of the Reconstruction Era Amendments|journal=Columbia Law Review|year=1974|volume=74|issue=3|pages=452–454|jstor=112176|doi=10.2307/1121764}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nonetheless, the last of the [[Reconstruction Era]] amendments, the [[Fifteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|15th Amendment]] promised [[voting rights]] to African American men (previously only white men of property could vote), and these cumulative federal efforts, African Americans began taking advantage of enfranchisement. They began voting, seeking office positions, and getting a [[public education]].

By the end of Reconstruction in the mid 1870s, violent white supremacists came to power via [[paramilitary group]]s such as the [[Red Shirts (Southern United States)|Red Shirts]] and the [[White League]] and imposed [[Jim Crow laws]] which deprived African-Americans of voting rights by instituting systemic and discriminatory policies of unequal [[racial segregation]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Klarman|first=Michael|title=The Plessy Era|journal=The Supreme Court Review|volume=1998|year=1998|pages=307–308|jstor=3109701|doi=10.1086/scr.1998.3109701|s2cid=147074451}}&lt;/ref&gt; Segregation, which began with slavery, continued with the passage and enforcement of Jim Crow laws, along with the posting of signs which were used to show Blacks where they could legally walk, talk, drink, rest, or eat.&lt;ref name="Leon Litwack 2004"&gt;Leon Litwack, ''Jim Crow Blues'', Magazine of History (OAH Publications, 2004)&lt;/ref&gt; For those places that were racially mixed, non-Whites had to wait until all White customers were dealt with.&lt;ref name="Leon Litwack 2004"/&gt; Segregated facilities extended from White-only schools to White-only graveyards.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-us-canada-38536668 "Barack Obama legacy: Did he improve US race relations?"]. BBC. Retrieved August 9, 2017&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Anti-miscegenation laws in the United States|Anti-miscegenation laws]], which forbade marriage and even sex between whites and non-whites (which typically covered Blacks but in some cases also Indians and Asians),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |ssrn=283998 |title=Preserving Racial Identity: Population Patterns and the Application of Anti-Miscegenation Statutes to Asian Americans, 1910–1950 |date=April 14, 2011| last1=Karthikeyan| first1=Hrishi| last2=Chin|first2=Gabriel Jackson}}&lt;/ref&gt; existed in most of the states well into the 20th century, even after emancipation and even in states that advocated the abolition of slavery. Such anti-miscegenation laws existed in many states until 1967, when the [[United States Supreme Court]] unanimously ruled in ''[[Loving v. Virginia]]'' that such laws were [[unconstitutional]].

===Post-Reconstruction era===
[[File:Ota Benga at Bronx Zoo.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Ota Benga]] was exhibited in the Monkey House of the [[Bronx Zoo]], New York in 1906]]

The new century saw a hardening of [[institutionalized racism]] and legal discrimination against citizens of African descent in the United States. Throughout the post Civil War period, [[racial stratification]] was informally and systemically enforced, to solidify the pre-existing social order. Although they were technically able to vote, [[poll tax (United States)|poll taxes]], pervasive acts of [[terrorism]] such as [[Lynching in the United States|lynchings]] (often perpetrated by [[hate group]]s such as the reborn [[Ku Klux Klan]], founded in the Reconstruction South), and discriminatory laws such as [[grandfather clauses]] kept Black Americans (and many [[Poor White]]s) disenfranchised particularly in the South. Furthermore, the discrimination was extended to state legislation which "allocated vastly unequal financial support" for Black and White schools. In addition to this, county officials sometimes redistributed resources which were earmarked for Blacks to White schools, further undermining educational opportunities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Beck|first=E.M.|author2=Tolnay, Stewart |title=Black Flight: Lethal Violence and the Great Migration, 1900–1930|journal=Social Science History|year=1990|volume=14|issue=3|pages=347–370|doi=10.2307/1171355|jstor=1171355}}&lt;/ref&gt; In response to [[de jure]] racism, protest and lobbyist groups emerged, most notably, the [[NAACP]] (National Association for the Advancement of Colored People) in 1909.&lt;ref&gt;Kwame Anthony Appiah, Henry Louis Gates, Jr., eds. ''Africana: The Encyclopedia of the African and African American Experience'', in articles "Civil Rights Movement" by Patricia Sullivan (pp. 441–455) and "National Association for the Advancement of Colored People" by Kate Tuttle (pp. 1, 388–381, 391). {{ISBN|0465000711}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:TulsaRaceRiot-1921.png|thumb|left|During the 1921 [[Tulsa race massacre]] thousands of Whites rampaged through the Black community, killing men and women, burning and looting stores and homes. It's estimated that 300 people were killed.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |author=Oklahoma Commission to Study the Tulsa Race Riot of 1921 |contribution=Final Report |title=Tulsa Race Riot Oklahoma Commission to Study the Tulsa Race Riot of 1921 |place=[[Tulsa, Oklahoma]] |date=February 28, 2001 |contribution-url=https://www.okhistory.org/research/forms/freport.pdf |access-date=April 10, 2016 |url-status=live |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20210326235611/https://www.okhistory.org/research/forms/freport.pdf |archive-date=March 26, 2021 }}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
This era is sometimes referred to as the [[nadir of American race relations]] because racism, [[Racial segregation in the United States|segregation]], [[racial discrimination]], and expressions of White supremacy all increased. So did anti-Black violence, including [[Mass racial violence in the United States|race riots]] such as the [[Atlanta race riot]] of 1906, the [[Elaine massacre]] of 1919, the [[Tulsa race massacre]] of 1921, and the [[Rosewood massacre]] of 1923. The Atlanta riot was characterized as a "racial massacre of negroes" by the French newspaper ''[[Le Petit Journal (newspaper)|Le Petit Journal]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last= |first= |date=September 24, 1906 |title=Un lynchage monstre |url=https://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/bpt6k6176609/f3.image |url-status=live |work=[[Le Petit Journal (newspaper)|Le Petit Journal]] |location= |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20210225115030/https://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/bpt6k6176609/f3.image |archive-date=February 25, 2021 |access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Charleston ''[[The Post and Courier|News and Courier]]'' wrote in response to the Atlanta riots: "Separation of the races is the only radical solution of the negro problem in this country. There is nothing new about it. It was the Almighty who established the bounds of the habitation of the races. The negroes were brought here by compulsion; they should be induced to leave here by persuasion."&lt;ref&gt;[https://timesmachine.nytimes.com/timesmachine/1906/09/30/101799831.pdf "DEPORTING THE NEGROES"] (September 30, 1906) ''[[The New York Times]]''&lt;/ref&gt;

===Great Migration===
[[Image:Omaha courthouse lynching.jpg|thumb|252px|A group of White men pose for a 1919 photograph as they stand over the body of the Black lynching victim Will Brown before they decide to mutilate and burn it during the [[Omaha race riot of 1919]] in [[Omaha, Nebraska]]. Photographs and postcards of lynchings were popular souvenirs in the U.S.&lt;ref&gt;Moyers, Bill. [https://www.pbs.org/moyers/journal/11232007/profile2.html "Legacy of Lynching"]. PBS. Retrieved July 28, 2016&lt;/ref&gt;]]

In addition, racism, which had been viewed as a problem which primarily existed in the [[Southern United States|Southern states]], burst onto the nation's consciousness following the [[Great Migration (African American)|Great Migration]], the relocation of millions of African Americans from their roots in the rural Southern states to the industrial centers of the North and West between 1910 and 1970, particularly in cities such as [[Boston]], [[St. Louis]], Chicago, Detroit, New York City ([[Harlem]]), [[Cleveland]], Los Angeles, [[Oakland, California|Oakland]], [[Seattle]], [[Phoenix, Arizona|Phoenix]], and [[Denver]]. Within Chicago, for example, between 1910 and 1970, the population fraction of African-Americans leapt from 2.0 percent to 32.7 percent.&lt;ref name="Tolnay 2003 209–232"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Tolnay|first=Stewart|title=The African American 'Great Migration' and Beyond|journal=Annual Review of Sociology|year=2003|volume=29|pages=209–232|doi=10.1146/annurev.soc.29.010202.100009|jstor=30036966}}&lt;/ref&gt; The demographic patterns of Black migrants and external economic conditions are largely studied stimulants regarding the Great Migration.&lt;ref name="Tolnay 2003 209–232"/&gt; For example, migrating Blacks (between 1910 and 1920) were more likely to be literate than Blacks who remained in the South. Known economic push factors played a role in migration, such as the emergence of a split labor market and agricultural distress which resulted from the [[boll weevil]] destruction of the cotton economy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Beck|first=E.M.|author2=Tolnay, Stewart |title=Black Flight: Lethal Violence and the Great Migration, 1900–1930|journal=Social Science History|year=1990|volume=14|issue=3|pages=351–352|doi=10.2307/1171355|jstor=1171355}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:We want white tenants.jpg|thumb|left|White tenants seeking to prevent Blacks from moving into the [[Public housing in Detroit|housing project]] erected this sign. Detroit, 1942.]]
Southern migrants were often treated in accordance with pre-existing racial stratification. The rapid influx of Blacks into the North and West disturbed the racial balance within cities, exacerbating hostility between both Black and White residents in the two regions. Stereotypic schemas of Southern Blacks were used to attribute issues in urban areas, such as crime and disease, to the presence of African-Americans. Overall, African-Americans in most Northern and Western cities experienced systemic discrimination in a plethora of aspects of life. Within employment, economic opportunities for Blacks were routed to the lowest-status and restrictive in potential mobility. In 1900 Reverend Matthew Anderson, speaking at the annual [[Hampton Negro Conference]] in Virginia, said that "...the lines along most of the avenues of wage earning are more rigidly drawn in the North than in the South. There seems to be an apparent effort throughout the North, especially in the cities to debar the colored worker from all the avenues of higher remunerative labor, which makes it more difficult to improve his economic condition even than in the South."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Annual Report of the Hampton Negro Conference|chapter=The Economic Aspect of the Negro Problem|first=Anderson|last=Matthew|series=Hampton bulletinno. 9–10, 12–16|editor1-last=Browne |editor1-first=Hugh |editor2-last=Kruse |editor2-first=Edwina |editor4-last=Moton |editor3-last=Walker |editor3-first=Thomas C. |editor4-first=Robert Russa |editor4-link=Robert Russa Moton |editor5-last=Wheelock |editor5-first=Frederick D. |publisher=Hampton Institute Press|location=[[Hampton, Virginia]]|chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=gkQ9AQAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PA39|hdl=2027/chi.14025588?urlappend=%3Bseq=43|volume=4|year=1900|page=39}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite report|title=Occupational Changes Among Negroes in Chicago|first=Estelle Hill|last=Scott|publisher=[[Works Progress Administration|Work Projects Administration]]|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=XHQG6Tdfr1QC&amp;pg=PA91|hdl=2027/uiug.30112046302813?urlappend=%3Bseq=137|year=1939|page=91| df=mdy-all}} [https://archive.org/details/occupationalchan00unit/page/n217/mode/1up Alt URL]&lt;/ref&gt; Within the housing market, stronger discriminatory measures were used in correlation to the influx, resulting in a mix of "targeted violence, [[restrictive covenants]], [[redlining]] and racial steering".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Tolnay|first=Stewart|title=The African American 'Great Migration' and Beyond|journal=Annual Review of Sociology|year=2003|volume=29|pages=218–221|doi=10.1146/annurev.soc.29.010202.100009|jstor=30036966}}&lt;/ref&gt; A club central to the [[Harlem Renaissance]] in the 1920s, the [[Cotton Club]] in Harlem, New York City, was a whites-only establishment, with Black acts allowed to perform, but to a White audience.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Ella Fitzgerald |date=1989 |publisher=Holloway House Publishing |page=27}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Image:chicago-race-riot.jpg|thumb|right|A White gang looking for Blacks during the [[Chicago race riot of 1919]]]]
Throughout this period, racial tensions exploded, most violently in Chicago, and [[lynching in the United States|lynchings]]—mob-directed hangings, usually racially motivated—increased dramatically in the 1920s. Urban riots—Whites attacking Blacks—became a northern and western problem.&lt;ref&gt;Michael O. Emerson, Christian Smith (2001). "Divided by Faith: Evangelical Religion and the Problem of Race in America". p. 42. Oxford University Press&lt;/ref&gt; Many Whites defended their space with violence, intimidation, or legal tactics toward African Americans, while many other Whites migrated to more racially homogeneous suburban or exurban regions, a process known as [[White flight]].&lt;ref name="Migration"&gt;{{cite book|last=Seligman|first=Amanda|title=Block by block : neighborhoods and public policy on Chicago's West Side|year=2005|publisher=University of Chicago Press|location=Chicago|isbn=978-0226746630|pages=213–214}}&lt;/ref&gt; Racially restrictive housing covenants were ruled unenforceable under the [[Fourteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Fourteenth Amendment]] in the 1948 landmark [[Supreme Court of the United States|Supreme Court]] case ''[[Shelley v. Kraemer]]''.&lt;ref&gt;''Shelley v. Kraemer'', 334 U.S. 1 (1948)&lt;/ref&gt;

[[1912 United States presidential election|Elected in 1912]], President [[Woodrow Wilson]] [[Woodrow Wilson and race#Segregating the federal bureaucracy|authorized the practice of racial segregation]] throughout the federal government's bureaucracy.&lt;ref&gt;Michael Kazin, Rebecca Edwards, Adam Rothman (2009). "The Princeton Encyclopedia of American Political History". p. 245. Princeton University Press&lt;/ref&gt; In [[World War I]], Blacks who served in the [[United States Armed Forces]] served in [[Racial segregation in the United States Armed Forces|segregated units]]. Black soldiers were often poorly trained and equipped, and they were often put on the frontlines and forced to go on [[suicide mission]]s. The U.S. military was still heavily segregated during [[World War II]]. In addition, no African-American was awarded the [[Medal of Honor]] during the war, and sometimes, Black soldiers who traveled on trains had to give their seats up to Nazi prisoners of war.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nydailynews.com/news/national/forgotten-details-heroism-black-soldiers-wwii-article-1.2419211 "Forgotten' details heroism of black soldiers in WWII"]. New York Daily News. Retrieved August 5, 2017&lt;/ref&gt;

==World War II to the civil rights movement==
[[File:Segregation 1938b.jpg|thumb|300px|A Black youth at a [[Racial segregation|segregated]] ("colored") drinking fountain in [[Halifax, North Carolina]], in 1938]]

The [[Jim Crow laws]] were state and local laws which were enacted in the [[Southern United States|Southern]] and [[Border states (Civil War)|border states]] of the United States and enforced between 1876 and 1965. They mandated "[[separate but equal]]" status for Blacks. In reality, this led to treatment and accommodations that were almost always inferior to those which were provided to Whites. The most important laws required that public schools, public places and public transportation, like trains and buses, have separate facilities for Whites and Blacks. State-sponsored school segregation was declared unconstitutional by the [[Supreme Court of the United States]] in 1954 in ''[[Brown v. Board of Education]]''. One of the first federal court cases which challenged segregation in schools was [[Mendez v. Westminster]] in 1946.

[[File:Emmett Till's funeral - mourners.jpg|thumb|190px|left|[[Emmett Till]]’s mother Mamie (middle) at her son's funeral in 1955. He was killed by White men after a White woman accused him of offending her in her family's grocery store.]]
By the 1950s, the [[Civil Rights Movement]] was gaining momentum. Membership in the NAACP increased in states across the U.S. A 1955 lynching that sparked public outrage about injustice was that of [[Emmett Till]], a 14-year-old boy from Chicago. Spending the summer with his relatives in [[Money, Mississippi]], Till was killed for allegedly having [[wolf-whistle]]d at a White woman. Till had been badly beaten, one of his eyes was gouged out, and he was shot in the head before being thrown into the [[Tallahatchie River]], his body weighed down with a {{convert|70|lbs|kg|adj=on}} [[cotton gin]] fan tied around his neck with barbed wire. David Jackson writes that [[Mamie Till]], Emmett's Mother, "brought him home to Chicago and insisted on an open casket. Tens of thousands filed past Till's remains, but it was the publication of the searing funeral image in ''Jet'', with a stoic Mamie gazing at her murdered child's ravaged body, that forced the world to reckon with the brutality of American racism."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=How The Horrific Photograph of Emmett Till Helped Energize The Civil Rights Movement|url=http://100photos.time.com/photos/emmett-till-david-jackson|access-date=2017-07-29|website=100 Photographs {{!}} The Most Influential Images of All Time}}&lt;/ref&gt; News photographs were circulated around the country, and they drew an intense public reaction. The visceral response to his mother's decision to have an open-casket funeral mobilized the Black community throughout the U.S.&lt;ref name="Atlantic"&gt;{{Cite news|last=II|first=Vann R. Newkirk|title=How 'The Blood of Emmett Till' Still Stains America Today|work=The Atlantic|url=https://www.theatlantic.com/entertainment/archive/2017/02/how-the-blood-of-emmett-till-still-stains-america-today/516891/|access-date=2017-07-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; Vann R. Newkirk wrote "the trial of his killers became a pageant illuminating the tyranny of White supremacy".&lt;ref name="Atlantic" /&gt; The state of Mississippi tried two defendants, Roy Bryant and J.W. Milam, but they were speedily acquitted by an [[all-White jury]].&lt;ref&gt;Whitfield, Stephen (1991). ''A Death in the Delta: The story of Emmett Till''. pp. 41–42. JHU Press.{{ISBN?}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:US Marshals with Young Ruby Bridges on School Steps.jpg|thumb|Due to threats and violence against her, U.S. Marshals escorted six-year-old [[Ruby Bridges]] to and from the previously–whites-only [[William Frantz Elementary School]] in New Orleans, 1960. As soon as Bridges entered the school, White parents pulled their children out.]]
In response to heightening discrimination and violence, non-violent acts of protest began to occur. For example, in February 1960, in [[Greensboro, North Carolina]], four young African American college students entered a Woolworth store and sat down at the counter but were refused service. The men had learned about non-violent protest in college, and continued to sit peacefully as Whites tormented them at the counter, pouring ketchup on their heads and burning them with cigarettes. The [[Greensboro sit-ins]] contributed to the formation of the [[Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee]]. Many more [[sit-in]]s took place to non-violently protest against racism and inequality. Sit-ins continued throughout the South and spread to other areas. Eventually, after many sit-ins and other non-violent protests, including marches and boycotts, places began to agree to desegregate.&lt;ref&gt;Carol Berkin, Christopher Miller, Robert Cherny, James Gormly (2011). "Making America: A History of the United States, Volume 2: From 1865". p. 749. Cengage Learning&lt;/ref&gt;

In June 1963, civil rights activist and [[NAACP]] member [[Medgar Evers]] was assassinated by [[Byron De La Beckwith]], a member of the [[White Citizens' Council]]. In his trials for murder De La Beckwith evaded conviction via all-White juries (both trials ended with hung juries).

[[File:Rosa Parks being fingerprinted by Deputy Sheriff D.H. Lackey after being arrested for refusing to give up her seat for a white passenger on a segregated municipal bus in Montgomery, Alabama.jpg|thumb|left|[[Rosa Parks]] being fingerprinted after being arrested for not giving up her seat on the bus so that a single white passenger could have an entire row of seats with no Black person sitting across the aisle]]
The [[16th Street Baptist Church bombing]] marked a turning point during the civil rights era. On Sunday, September 15, 1963, with a stack of dynamite hidden on an outside staircase, Ku Klux Klansmen destroyed one side of the Birmingham church. The bomb exploded in proximity to twenty-six children who were preparing for choir practice in the basement assembly room. The explosion killed four Black girls, Carole Robertson (14), Cynthia Wesley (14), Denise McNair (11) and Addie Mae Collins (14).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Ravitz|first=Jessica|title=Siblings of the bombing: Remembering Birmingham church blast 50 years on|url=http://www.cnn.com/2013/09/14/us/birmingham-church-bombing-anniversary-victims-siblings/|access-date=October 20, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Birmingham Church Bombed|url=http://www.cinema.ucla.edu/la-rebellion/timeline/birmingham-church-bombed-0|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20131015055957/http://www.cinema.ucla.edu/la-rebellion/timeline/birmingham-church-bombed-0|archive-date=October 15, 2013|access-date=October 20, 2013|publisher=L.A. Rebellion: Film &amp; Television Archive}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Bayard Rustin NYWTS 3.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Bayard Rustin]] (left) and [[Cleveland Robinson]] (right), organizers of the March, on August 7, 1963]]
With the bombing occurring only a couple of weeks after [[Martin Luther King Jr.]]'s [[March on Washington for Jobs and Freedom]], it became an integral aspect of transformed perceptions of conditions for Blacks in America. It influenced the passage of the [[Civil Rights Act of 1964]] (that banned discrimination in public accommodations, employment, and labor unions) and [[Voting Rights Act of 1965]] which overruled remaining Jim Crow laws. Nonetheless, neither had been implemented by the end of the 1960s as civil rights leaders continued to strive for political and social freedom.

The first [[Anti-miscegenation laws in the United States|anti-miscegenation law]] was passed by the [[Maryland General Assembly]] in 1691, criminalizing [[Interracial marriage in the United States|interracial marriage]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Eugenics, Race, and Marriage|website=Facing History.org|url=https://www.facinghistory.org/resource-library/eugenics-race-and-marriage|access-date=February 23, 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt; By the late 1800s, 38 US states had anti-miscegenation statutes, and by 1924 it was still in force in 29 states. In 1958, officers in [[Virginia]] entered the home of [[Loving v. Virginia#Plaintiffs|Richard and Mildred Loving]] and dragged them out of bed for living together as an interracial couple, on the basis that “any white person intermarry with a colored person"— or vice versa—each party "shall be guilty of a felony" and face prison terms of five years. The law was ruled unconstitutional in 1967 by the U.S. Supreme Court in ''[[Loving v. Virginia]]''.

[[File:WhiteTradeOnlyLancasterOhio.jpg|thumb|left|"We Cater to White Trade Only" sign on a restaurant window in [[Lancaster, Ohio]] in 1938. In 1964 [[Martin Luther King Jr.]] was arrested and spent a night in jail for attempting to eat at a White-only restaurant in [[St. Augustine, Florida]].]]
Segregation continued even after the demise of the Jim Crow laws. Data on house prices and attitudes towards integration suggest that in the mid-20th century, segregation was a product of collective actions taken by Whites to exclude Blacks from their neighborhoods.&lt;ref name="vigdor"&gt;''The Rise and Decline of the American Ghetto'' David M. Cutler, Edward L. Glaeser, Jacob L. Vigdor ''The Journal of Political Economy'', Vol. 107, No. 3 (Jun. 1999), pp. 455–506&lt;/ref&gt; Segregation also took the form of [[redlining]], the practice of denying or increasing the cost of services, such as banking, insurance, access to jobs,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Racial Discrimination and Redlining in Cities|url=http://www.core.ucl.ac.be/services/psfiles/dp99/dp9913.pdf|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20071130210614/http://www.core.ucl.ac.be/services/psfiles/dp99/dp9913.pdf|archive-date=November 30, 2007|access-date=2013-02-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; access to health care,&lt;ref&gt;See: [[Race and health]]&lt;/ref&gt; or even supermarkets&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Eisenhauer|first1=Elizabeth|year=2001|title=In poor health: Supermarket redlining and urban nutrition|journal=GeoJournal|volume=53|issue=2|pages=125–133|doi=10.1023/A:1015772503007|s2cid=151164815}}&lt;/ref&gt; to residents in certain, often racially determined,&lt;ref name="eastny"&gt;{{Cite book|last1=Thabit|first1=Walter|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=TWo8OFJpFtAC|title=How East New York Became a Ghetto|year=2003|isbn=978-0814782675|page=42}}&lt;/ref&gt; areas. Although in the U.S. informal discrimination and segregation have always existed, redlining began with the [[National Housing Act of 1934]], which established the [[Federal Housing Administration]] (FHA). The practice was fought first through passage of the [[Fair Housing Act of 1968]] (which prevents redlining when the criteria for redlining are based on race, religion, gender, familial status, disability, or ethnic origin), and later through the [[Community Reinvestment Act]] of 1977, which requires banks to apply the same lending criteria in all communities.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last1=Grogan|first1=Paul|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ISBN0813339529|title=Comeback Cities: A Blueprint for Urban Neighborhood Revival|last2=Proscio|first2=Tony|date=2001|isbn=978-0813339528|page=114|quote=The goal was not to relax lending restrictions but rather to get banks to apply the same criteria in the inner-city as in the [[suburbs]].}}{{Dead link|date=November 2023 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt; Although redlining is illegal some argue that it continues to exist in other forms.

[[File:Mr &amp; Mrs Sammy Davis Jnr 2 Allan Warren.jpg|thumb|upright|Although the [[Anti-miscegenation laws|ban on interracial marriage]] ended in California in 1948, entertainer [[Sammy Davis Jr.]] faced a backlash for his involvement with a White woman in 1957.]]
Up until the 1940s, the full revenue potential of what was called "the Negro market" was largely ignored by White-owned manufacturers in the U.S. with advertising focused on Whites.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|date=January 9, 2016|title=How Pepsi Opened Door to Diversity|newspaper=Wall Street Journal|url=https://www.wsj.com/articles/SB116831396726171042}}&lt;/ref&gt; Blacks were also denied commercial deals. On his decision to take part in exhibition races against racehorses in order to earn money, Olympic champion [[Jesse Owens]] stated, "People say that it was degrading for an Olympic champion to run against a horse, but what was I supposed to do? I had four gold medals, but you can't eat four gold medals."&lt;ref name="espn1"&gt;{{cite web|last=Schwartz|first=Larry|title=Owens Pierced a Myth|url=http://espn.go.com/sportscentury/features/00016393.html|access-date=April 30, 2009|publisher=ESPN}}&lt;/ref&gt; On the lack of opportunities, Owens added, "There was no television, no big advertising, no endorsements then. Not for a black man, anyway."&lt;ref&gt;Entine, Jon (2000). Taboo: Why Black Athletes Dominate Sports and why We are Afraid to Talk about it. PublicAffairs. p. 187.&lt;/ref&gt; In the reception to honor his Olympic success Owens was not permitted to enter through the main doors of the [[Waldorf Astoria New York]] and instead forced to travel up to the event in a freight elevator.&lt;ref name="schwartz"&gt;{{cite web|last=Schwartz|first=Larry|year=2007|title=Owens pierced a myth|url=http://espn.go.com/sportscentury/features/00016393.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; The first Black Academy Award recipient [[Hattie McDaniel]] was not permitted to attend the premiere of ''[[Gone with the Wind (film)|Gone with the Wind]]'' with Georgia being racially segregated, and at the Oscars ceremony in Los Angeles she was required to sit at a segregated table at the far wall of the room; the hotel had a strict no-Blacks policy, but allowed McDaniel in as a favor.&lt;ref name="LA segregation"&gt;{{cite news|last=Abramovitch|first=Seth|date=February 19, 2015|title=Oscar's First Black Winner Accepted Her Honor in a Segregated 'No Blacks' Hotel in L.A.|work=[[The Hollywood Reporter]]|url=https://hollywoodreporter.com/features/oscars-first-black-winner-accepted-774335|access-date=August 10, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Her final wish to be buried in [[Hollywood Forever Cemetery|Hollywood Cemetery]] was denied because the graveyard was restricted to Whites only.&lt;ref name="LA segregation" /&gt;

As the civil rights movement and the dismantling of Jim Crow laws in the 1950s and 1960s deepened existing racial tensions in much of the Southern U.S, a Republican Party electoral strategy—the [[Southern strategy]]—was enacted to increase political support among White voters in the South by appealing to racism against African Americans.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Boyd|first=James|date=May 17, 1970|title=Nixon's Southern strategy: 'It's All in the Charts'|work=The New York Times|url=https://www.nytimes.com/packages/html/books/phillips-southern.pdf|access-date=August 2, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Carter, Dan T. ''From George Wallace to Newt Gingrich: Race in the Conservative Counterrevolution, 1963–1994.'' p. 35.&lt;/ref&gt; Republican politicians such as presidential candidate [[Richard Nixon]] and Senator [[Barry Goldwater]] developed strategies that successfully contributed to the political realignment of many White, conservative voters in the South who had traditionally supported the Democratic Party rather than the Republican Party.&lt;ref name="Apple"&gt;{{cite news|last=Apple|first=R.W. Jr.|date=September 19, 1996|title=G.O.P. Tries Hard to Win Black Votes, but Recent History Works Against It|work=The New York Times|url=https://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E2DA1F3AF93AA2575AC0A960958260|url-status=live|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20220612002448/https://www.nytimes.com/1996/09/19/us/gop-tries-hard-to-win-black-votes-but-recent-history-works-against-it.html?pagewanted=all&amp;src=pm|archive-date=June 12, 2022}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1971, angered by African delegates at the UN siding against the U.S. in a vote to admit China and expel [[Taiwan]], then Governor of California [[Ronald Reagan]] stated in a phone call to president Nixon, "To see those... those monkeys from those African countries – damn them, they're still uncomfortable wearing shoes!"&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-us-canada-49177034 "Ronald Reagan called Africans at UN 'monkeys', tapes reveal"]. BBC. Retrieved July 31, 2019&lt;/ref&gt; Nixon adopted Reagan's offensive language to complain about "cannibals jumping up and down" after the vote passed. Recorded conversations from Nixon’s time in office further revealed his bigoted views of minorities, commenting on African Americans: "I know they're not going to make it for 500 years. They aren't. You know it, too. The Mexicans are a different cup of tea. They have a heritage. At the present time they steal, they're dishonest, but they do have some concept of family life. They don't live like a bunch of dogs, which the Negroes do live like."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Edmondson |first1=Christina Barland |last2=Brennan |first2=Chad |title=Faithful Antiracism: Moving Past Talk to Systemic Change |date=2022 |publisher=InterVarsity Press}}&lt;/ref&gt; The perception that the Republican Party had served as the "vehicle of white supremacy in the South", particularly post 1964, made it difficult for the Party to win back the support of Black voters in the South in later years.&lt;ref name="Apple" /&gt;

In 1973, African American baseball legend [[Hank Aaron]] received hundreds of thousands of hate mail letters from fans, angry at him for trying to break the all-time homerun record at the time set by [[Babe Ruth]]. Aaron would eventually break Ruth's homerun record by hitting his 715th homerun on April 8, 1974. That same year, the [[U.S. Postal Service]] confirmed that Hank Aaron set the [[Guinness World Record]] for most mail received by any private citizen in one year, receiving over 900,000 letters with a third of them being letters of hate.&lt;ref&gt;[https://people.com/sports/hank-aaron-used-hate-mail-for-inspiration-before-breaking-babe-ruth-record/ "Hank Aaron Used Record Setting Hate Mail for Inspiration Before Breaking Babe Ruth Record"]. People. Retrieved January 22, 2021&lt;/ref&gt;

==1980s to the 2000s==
[[File:Emanuel African Methodist Episcopal (AME) Church Corrected.jpg|thumb|The [[Emanuel African Methodist Episcopal Church]] where nine Black church-goers, including the pastor, were killed by [[Dylann Roof|a White man]] in the 2015 [[Charleston church shooting]]. The church had been rebuilt after one of its co-founders, [[Denmark Vesey]], was suspected of planning a [[slave rebellion]] in Charleston in 1822; 35 people, including Vesey, were hanged and the church was burned down.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Wade|first1=Richard C.|year=1964|title=The Vesey Plot: A Reconsideration|journal=The Journal of Southern History|volume=30|issue=2|pages=143–161|doi=10.2307/2205070|jstor=2205070}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]

While substantial gains were made in the succeeding decades through middle class advancement and public employment, [[African-American poverty|Black poverty]] and lack of education continued in the context of de-industrialization.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=JBHE Statistical Shocker of the Year|url=http://www.jbhe.com/latest/122905_statistical_shocker2005.html|access-date=2013-02-16|publisher=Jbhe.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Takaki-CivRights"&gt;Ronald Takaki, ''A Different Mirror: A History of Multicultural America'' (New York: Little, Brown &amp; Co., 1993), 400–414.&lt;/ref&gt; Despite gains made after the [[16th Street Baptist Church bombing]], some violence against Black churches has also continued—145 fires were set to churches around the South in the 1990s,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Booth|first1=William|date=June 19, 1996|title=In Church Fires, a Pattern but No Conspiracy|newspaper=[[The Washington Post]]|url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-srv/national/longterm/churches/churches.htm|access-date=2015-06-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; and a [[Charleston church shooting|mass shooting in Charleston, South Carolina]] was committed in 2015 at the historic [[Emanuel African Methodist Episcopal Church|Mother Emanuel Church]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Whitman|first=Elizabeth|date=June 23, 2015|title=Charleston Church Shooting: South Carolina Racism Will Not Change After Killings, Black Residents Say|url=http://www.ibtimes.com/charleston-church-shooting-south-carolina-racism-will-not-change-after-killings-black-1979391|work=International Business Times}}&lt;/ref&gt;

From 1981 to 1997, the [[United States Department of Agriculture]] discriminated against tens of thousands of Black American farmers, denying loans that were provided to White farmers in similar circumstances. The discrimination was the subject of the ''[[Pigford v. Glickman]]'' lawsuit brought by members of the [[National Black Farmers Association]], which resulted in two settlement agreements of $1.06&amp;nbsp;billion in 1999 and of $1.25&amp;nbsp;billion in 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|last=Southall|first=Ashley|date=May 25, 2010|title=Bias Payments Come Too Late for Some Farmers|work=The New York Times|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2010/05/26/us/26farmers.html?scp=1&amp;sq=black%20farmers&amp;st=cse|access-date=2010-05-26|issn=0362-4331}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Numerous authors, academics, and historians have asserted that the [[War on Drugs]] has been racially and politically motivated. As the [[crack epidemic]] spread across the country in the mid 1980s, Congress would pass the [[Anti-Drug Abuse Act of 1986]]. Under these sentencing guidelines, five grams of [[crack cocaine]], often sold by and to African-Americans, carried a mandatory five-year prison sentence. However, for powder cocaine, often sold by and to White Americans, it would take one hundred times that amount, or 500 grams, for the same sentence, leading many to criticize the law as discriminatory. The 100:1 sentencing disparity was reduced to 18:1 in 2010 by the [[Fair Sentencing Act]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Fair Sentencing Act|url=https://www.aclu.org/issues/criminal-law-reform/drug-law-reform/fair-sentencing-act|website=American Civil Liberties Union}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to the [[National Security Archive]], during the 1980s, US officials, including [[Oliver North]], collaborated with and protected known drug traffickers as part of efforts to fund the [[Central Intelligence Agency]] funded right-wing [[Nicaraguan Contra]] rebels. In 1989, the [[Kerry Committee]] report concluded the Contra drug links included... "Payments to drug traffickers by the U.S. State Department of funds authorized by the Congress for humanitarian assistance to the Contras, in some cases after the traffickers had been indicted by federal law enforcement agencies on drug charges, in others while traffickers were under active investigation by these same agencies". In 1996, journalist [[Gary Webb]] wrote the [[Dark Alliance series]] for the [[San Jose Mercury News]] where he asserted that the CIA-backed Contras played a major role in the crack epidemic.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=The Contras, Cocaine, and U.S. Covert Operations|url=https://nsarchive2.gwu.edu/NSAEBB/NSAEBB2/index.html|website=nsarchive2.gwu.edu}}&lt;/ref&gt; The series caused outrage in the African-American community, particularly in [[South Central Los Angeles]], where Congresswoman [[Maxine Waters]] served, and subsequently praised the series.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | author=Schou, Nick | title=Kill the Messenger: How the CIA's Crack Cocaine Controversy Destroyed Gary Webb |page=115 | publisher=Nation Books | year=2006 | isbn=1560259302 | url=https://archive.org/details/killmessenger00scho }}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the 1980s and '90s, a number of riots occurred that were related to longstanding racial tensions between police and minority communities. The [[1980 Miami riots]] were catalyzed by the killing of an African-American motorist by four White [[Miami-Dade Police]] officers. They were subsequently acquitted on charges of manslaughter and evidence tampering. Similarly, the six-day [[1992 Los Angeles riots]] erupted after the acquittal of four White [[Los Angeles Police Department|LAPD]] officers who had been filmed beating [[Rodney King]], an African-American motorist. [[Khalil Gibran Muhammad]], the Director of the Harlem-based [[Schomburg Center for Research in Black Culture]] has identified more than 100 instances of mass racial violence in the United States since 1935 and has noted that almost every instance was precipitated by a police incident.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Hannah-Jones|first1=Nikole|date=March 4, 2015|title=Yes, Black America Fears the Police. Here's Why.|url=https://www.propublica.org/article/yes-black-america-fears-the-police-heres-why|access-date=2015-03-05|website=[[ProPublica]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Curriculum===
The curriculum in U.S. schools has also contained racism against non-white Americans, including Native Americans, African Americans, Mexican Americans, and Asian Americans.&lt;ref name=":20" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":10" /&gt; Particularly during the 19th and early 20th centuries, school textbooks and other teaching materials emphasized the biological and social inferiority of Black Americans, consistently portraying Black people as simple, irresponsible, and oftentimes, in situations of suffering that were implied to be their fault (and not the effects of slavery and other oppression).&lt;ref name=":20"&gt;Elson, Ruth Miller (1964). ''Guardians of Tradition: American Schoolbooks of the Nineteenth Century''. Lincoln, Nebraska: University of Nebraska Press.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":10"&gt;Au, Wayne, 1972–. Reclaiming the multicultural roots of U.S. curriculum : communities of color and official knowledge in education. Brown, Anthony Lamar, Aramoni Calderón, Dolores, Banks, James A. New York. {{ISBN|978-0807756782}}. {{OCLC|951742385}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Black Americans were also depicted as expendable and their suffering as commonplace, as evidenced by a poem about "Ten Little Nigger Boys" dying off one by one that was circulated as a children's counting exercise from 1875 to the mid-1900s.&lt;ref name=":10" /&gt; Historian [[Carter G. Woodson]] analyzed the American curriculum as completely lacking any mention of Black Americans' merits in the early 20th century. Based on his observations of the time, he wrote that American students, including Black students, who went through U.S. schooling would come out believing that Black people had no significant history and had contributed nothing to human civilization.&lt;ref&gt;Woodson, Carter G. (Carter Godwin) (1993). ''The mis-education of the Negro''. Internet Archive. Trenton, NJ: AfricaWorld Press. {{ISBN|978-0865431713}}{{page needed|date=December 2022}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==2008 to the present==
Some Americans saw the presidential candidacy of [[Barack Obama]], who served as president of the United States from 2009 to 2017 and was the nation's first [[Black people|Black]] president, as a sign that the nation had entered a new, [[Post-racial America|post-racial era]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=A New, 'Post-Racial' Political Era in America|url=https://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=18489466|access-date=2016-01-02|website=NPR.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":02"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Dawson|first1=Michael C.|last2=Bobo|first2=Lawrence D.|year=2009|title=One Year Later and the Myth of a Post-Racial Society|url=https://dash.harvard.edu/handle/1/10347165|journal=Du Bois Review|volume=6|issue=2|page=247|doi=10.1017/S1742058X09990282|access-date=2016-01-01|doi-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt; The election of President [[Donald Trump]] in 2016, who was a chief proponent of the racist [[birther movement]] in the US (which argued that Obama was not born in the United States) and ran a racially tinged campaign, has been viewed by some commentators as a [[White backlash|racist backlash]] against the election of Barack Obama.&lt;ref name=":2"&gt;{{cite journal|last=Coates|first=Ta-Nehisi|author-link=Ta-Nehisi Coates|date=October 2017|title=The First White President|url=https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2017/10/the-first-white-president-ta-nehisi-coates/537909/|journal=The Atlantic|access-date=June 29, 2018|quote=It is often said that Trump has no real ideology, which is not true—his ideology is White supremacy, in all its truculent and sanctimonious power.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Before and after the election, Trump has had a history of speech and actions that have been [[Racial views of Donald Trump|widely viewed as racist or racially charged]]. During the mid-2010s, American society has seen a resurgence of high levels of racism and discrimination. One new phenomenon has been the rise of the [[Alt-right|"alt-right" movement]]: a [[White nationalism|White nationalist]] coalition which seeks the expulsion of [[Sexual minority|sexual]] and [[Minority group|racial minorities]] from the United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Lozada|first=Carlos|date=November 3, 2017|title=Where the alt-right wants to take America — with or without Trump|url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/amphtml/news/book-party/wp/2017/11/03/where-the-alt-right-wants-to-take-america-with-or-without-trump/|access-date=April 3, 2018|newspaper=[[Washington Post]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Since the mid-2010s, the [[United States Department of Homeland Security|Department of Homeland Security]] and the [[Federal Bureau of Investigation]] have identified White supremacist violence as the leading threat of [[domestic terrorism in the United States]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Winter|first=Jana|date=August 14, 2017|title=FBI and DHS Warned of Growing Threat From White Supremacists Months Ago|url=https://foreignpolicy.com/2017/08/14/fbi-and-dhs-warned-of-growing-threat-from-white-supremacists-months-ago/|access-date=April 19, 2018|website=Foreign Policy}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|date=May 10, 2017|title=White Supremacist Extremism Poses Persistent Threat of Lethal Violence|url=https://www.documentcloud.org/documents/3924852-White-Supremacist-Extremism-JIB.html|access-date=April 19, 2018|website=FBI Intelligence Bulletin}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Many cite the [[2008 United States presidential election]] as a step forward in race relations: White Americans played a role in electing [[Barack Obama]], the country's first Black president.&lt;ref&gt;[https://latimes.com/news/printedition/asection/la-na-assess5-2008nov05,0,6354926.story White Americans play major role in electing the first black president], ''Los Angeles Times''&lt;/ref&gt; In fact, Obama received a greater percentage of the White vote (43%),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|date=November 5, 2008|title=Inside Obama's Sweeping Victory|url=http://pewresearch.org/pubs/1023/exit-poll-analysis-2008|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110509200438/http://pewresearch.org/pubs/1023/exit-poll-analysis-2008|archive-date=May 9, 2011|access-date=April 21, 2011|publisher=Pew Research Center}}&lt;/ref&gt; than did the previous Democratic candidate, [[John Kerry]] (41%).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=U.S. President: National: Exit Poll|publisher=CNN|url=http://www.cnn.com/ELECTION/2004/pages/results/states/US/P/00/epolls.0.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; Racial divisions persisted throughout the election; wide margins of Black voters gave Obama an edge during the presidential primary, where 8 out of 10 African-Americans voted for him in the primaries, and an [[MSNBC]] poll found that race was a key factor in whether a candidate was perceived as being ready for office. In South Carolina, for instance, "Whites were far likelier to name [[Hillary Clinton|Clinton]] than Obama as being most qualified to be commander in chief, likeliest to unite the country and most apt to capture the White House in November. Blacks named Obama over Clinton by even stronger margins—two- and three-to one—in all three areas."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|date=January 26, 2008|title=Strong black vote gives Obama big boost|url=http://www.nbcnews.com/id/22859978|access-date=2013-02-16|work=NBC News}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Sociologist Russ Long stated in 2013 that there is now a more subtle racism that associates a specific race with a specific characteristic.&lt;ref&gt;Long, Russ. [http://dmc122011.delmar.edu/socsci/rlong/problems/chap-08.htm "How to Think about Racial and Ethnic Inequality"] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170826153922/http://dmc122011.delmar.edu/socsci/rlong/problems/chap-08.htm|date=August 26, 2017}}.&lt;/ref&gt; In a 1993 study conducted by Katz and Braly, it was presented that "blacks and whites hold a variety of stereotypes towards each other, often negative".&lt;ref name="Leonard 1993"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Leonard|first1=Rebecca|last2=Locke|first2=Don C|year=1993|title=Communication Stereotypes: Is Interracial Communication Possible?|journal=Journal of Black Studies|volume=23|issue=3|pages=332–343|doi=10.1177/002193479302300303|s2cid=143963032}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Katz and Braley study also found that African-Americans and Whites view the traits that they identify each other with as threatening, interracial communication between the two is likely to be "hesitant, reserved, and concealing".&lt;ref name="Leonard 1993" /&gt; Interracial communication is guided by stereotypes; stereotypes are transferred into personality and character traits which then have an effect on communication. Multiple factors go into how stereotypes are established, such as age and the setting in which they are being applied.&lt;ref name="Leonard 1993" /&gt; For example, in a study done by the Entman-Rojecki Index of Race and Media in 2014, 89% of Black women in movies are shown swearing and exhibiting offensive behavior while only 17% of White women are portrayed in this manner.&lt;ref&gt;Orbe, Mark P., and Tina M. Harris. "Interracial Communication: Theory Into Practice."Google Books. Sage Publications, n.d. Web. February 2, 2014&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2012, [[Trayvon Martin]], a seventeen-year-old teenager, was [[Killing of Trayvon Martin|fatally shot]] by [[George Zimmerman]] in [[Sanford, Florida]]. Zimmerman, a neighborhood-watch volunteer, claimed that Martin was being suspicious and called the Sanford police to report him.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Saloman|first=Larry|title=Timeline of Race, Racism, Resistance and Philanthropy 1992–2014|url=http://racialequity.org/docs/CIF5Timeline.pdf|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20181221144927/http://racialequity.org/docs/CIF5Timeline.pdf|archive-date=December 21, 2018|website=Racial Equity}}&lt;/ref&gt; While on the call to police, Zimmerman began following Martin. Between ending his call with police and their arrival, Zimmerman fatally shot Martin outside of the townhouse he was staying at following an altercation. Zimmerman was injured in the altercation and claimed self-defense. The incident caused national outrage after Zimmerman was not charged over the shooting. The national coverage of the incident lead Sandford police to arrest Zimmerman and charge him with second-degree murder, but he was found not guilty at [[Trial of George Zimmerman|trial]]. Public outcry followed the acquittal, leading to the creation of the [[Black Lives Matter]] movement.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.cbsnews.com/news/alicia-garza-on-the-origin-of-black-lives-matter/|title=Alicia Garza on the origin of Black Lives Matter|author=Alicia Garza|website=cbsnews.com|date=October 18, 2020|access-date=2021-06-30|quote=While many might remember first hearing the phrase "Black Lives Matter" during the 2014 protests in Ferguson, Missouri, the movement actually began a year earlier, the day George Zimmerman was found not guilty of murdering 17-year-old Trayvon Martin in Florida.}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

[[File:DSC 0008 (50283939071).jpg|thumb|left|Reverend [[Al Sharpton]] speaking at the [[Commitment March: Get Your Knee Off Our Necks]] in August 2020]]
In 2014, the police [[shooting of Michael Brown]], an African American, in Ferguson, Missouri led to widespread [[Ferguson unrest|unrest]] in the town. In the years following, mass media has followed other high profile police shootings of African-Americans, often with video evidence from police [[Body worn video (police equipment)|body-worn]] cameras. Amongst 15 high-profile police shooting deaths of African-Americans, only one officer faced prison time.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|last=Lee|first=Jasmine|date=December 7, 2017|title=In 15 High-Profile Cases Involving Deaths of Blacks, One Officer Faces Prison Time|work=[[The New York Times]]|url=https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2017/05/17/us/black-deaths-police.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[U.S. Justice Department]] launched the National Center for Building Community Trust and Justice in 2014.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Saloman|first=Larry|date=June 2014|title=Timeline of Race, Racism, Resistance and Philanthropy 1992–2014|url=http://racialequity.org/docs/CIF5Timeline.pdf|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20181221144927/http://racialequity.org/docs/CIF5Timeline.pdf|archive-date=December 21, 2018|website=Racial Equity}}&lt;/ref&gt; This program collects data concerning racial profiling to create change in the criminal justice system concerning implicit and explicit racial bias towards African-Americans as well as other minorities.

In August 2017, the [[International Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Racial Discrimination#Committee on the Elimination of Racial Discrimination|UN Committee on the Elimination of Racial Discrimination]] issued a rare warning to the US and its leadership to "unequivocally and unconditionally" condemn racist speech and crime, following violence in Charlottesville during a rally organized by [[White nationalists]], White supremacists, [[Klansmen]], [[neo-Nazis]] and various right-wing militias in August.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=UN issues rare warning over 'alarming' racism in US|url=https://www.aljazeera.com/news/2017/08/issues-rare-warning-alarming-racism-170823225952827.html|access-date=August 24, 2017|publisher=Al Jazeera}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=United Nations issues 'racism warning' over growing US tensions|date=August 23, 2017 |url=https://www.thejournal.ie/un-racism-warning-to-us-3560646-Aug2017/|access-date=August 23, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On June 17, 2015, a white man [[Charleston church shooting|killed nine people during a Bible study]] at [[Emanuel African Methodist Episcopal Church]] in Charleston, South Carolina. All victims were African Americans, including senior pastor and state senator [[Clementa C. Pinckney]]. The perpetrator later confessed that he committed the shooting in hopes of igniting a race war.

White women calling the police on Black people has become more publicized in recent years. In a 2020 article in ''The New York Times'' titled ''How White Women Use Themselves as Instruments of Terror'', Black columnist [[Charles M. Blow]] wrote, "historically, White women have used the violence of White men and the institutions these men control as their own muscle. Untold numbers of lynchings were executed because White women had claimed that a black man raped, assaulted, talked to or glanced at them. This exercise in racial extremism has been dragged into the modern era through the weaponizing of [[9-1-1]], often by White women, to invoke the power and force of the police who they are fully aware are hostile to black men“.&lt;ref name="Terror"&gt;{{cite news|title=How White Women Use Themselves as Instruments of Terror|newspaper=The New York Times|date=May 28, 2020 |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2020/05/27/opinion/racism-white-women.html|access-date=June 4, 2020|last1=Blow |first1=Charles M. }}&lt;/ref&gt; White women in the U.S. who used their White privilege as a weapon have been given a [[Karen (pejorative)#Origin|different name over the centuries]] by Black people, with [[Karen (pejorative)|Karen]] a contemporary name.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last = Tiffany |first = Kaitlyn |date = May 6, 2020 |title = How 'Karen' Became a Coronavirus Villain |url = https://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2020/05/coronavirus-karen-memes-reddit-twitter-carolyn-goodman/611104/ |access-date = May 20, 2020 |magazine = [[The Atlantic]] |language = en-US }}&lt;/ref&gt; In May 2020, a White woman calling the police on a [[Central Park birdwatching incident|Black man bird-watching in Central Park, New York]] received wide publicity after it was caught on film. After he had asked her to put her dog on a leash (as per the rules in an area of the park to protect other wildlife), she approached him, to which he responded “Please don't come close to me", before she yelled, "I'm taking a picture and calling the cops. I'm going to tell them there's an African American man threatening my life." During her phone call, with the man standing a distance away from her and recording her, she spoke in an audibly distraught voice, "There's a man, African American, he is.. threatening me and my dog. Please send the cops immediately!".&lt;ref name="Terror" /&gt; Other examples of White women calling the police on Black people include reporting an eight-year-old girl for selling bottles of water without a permit in San Francisco, reporting a Black family barbecuing in a park in [[Oakland, California]], blocking a Black man from entering an apartment building in [[St. Louis, Missouri]] where he is a resident before calling the police, and a woman accusing a boy of groping her in a store in Brooklyn, New York, which was disproven by surveillance.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=From 'BBQ Becky' to 'Golfcart Gail,' list of unnecessary 911 calls made on blacks continues to grow|agency=ABC|url=https://abcnews.go.com/US/bbq-becky-golfcart-gail-list-unnecessary-911-calls/story?id=58584961|access-date=June 4, 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=California woman threatens to call police on eight-year-old black girl for selling water|work=The Guardian|url=https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2018/jun/25/permit-patty-eight-year-old-selling-water-san-francisco-video|access-date=June 4, 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On May 25, 2020, [[George Floyd]], a 46-year-old Black man, was [[Murder of George Floyd|murdered]] by a White [[Minneapolis Police Department]] officer, [[Derek Chauvin]], who forced his knee on Floyd's neck for a total of [[8 minutes and 46 seconds|9 minutes and 29 seconds]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|first1=Amy|last1=Forliti|first2=Steve|last2=Karnowski|first3=Tammy|last3=Webber|title=Police chief: Kneeling on Floyd's neck violated policy|date=April 5, 2021|agency=Associated Press|newspaper=Star Tribune|url=https://www.startribune.com/police-chief-kneeling-on-floyds-neck-violated-policy/600042283/|access-date=April 8, 2021|archive-date=April 10, 2021|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20210410114811/https://www.startribune.com/police-chief-kneeling-on-floyds-neck-violated-policy/600042283/|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|last=Levenson|first=Eric|date=March 29, 2021|title=Former officer knelt on George Floyd for 9 minutes and 29 seconds – not the infamous 8:46|work=CNN|url=https://www.cnn.com/2021/03/29/us/george-floyd-timing-929-846/index.html|url-status=live|access-date=March 29, 2021|archive-date=March 29, 2021|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20210329194620/https://www.cnn.com/2021/03/29/us/george-floyd-timing-929-846/index.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{efn|name=9:30 not 8:46|The initial criminal complaint gave the duration as 8:46, which came to be [[Eight minutes 46 seconds|often cited by protesters and the media]]. Prosecutors revised this about three weeks later to 7:46.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last1=Bogel-Burroughs |first1=Nicholas |title=8 Minutes, 46 Seconds Became a Symbol in George Floyd's Death. The Exact Time Is Less Clear. |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2020/06/18/us/george-floyd-timing.html |access-date=June 23, 2020 |work=The New York Times |date=June 18, 2020 |quote=Yet the revised time provided by prosecutors conflicts with videotapes obtained by The New York Times after the May 25 killing along a Minneapolis street. The videos show Mr. Chauvin’s knee on Mr. Floyd’s neck for at least eight minutes and 15 seconds. |archive-date=August 13, 2020 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20200813125726/https://www.nytimes.com/2020/06/18/us/george-floyd-timing.html |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=latimes_20200618_derek&gt;{{cite news |title=Prosecutors say officer had knee on George Floyd's neck for 7:46 rather than 8:46 |date=June 18, 2020 |newspaper=Los Angeles Times |agency=Associated Press |url=https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2020-06-18/derek-chauvin-had-knee-george-floyd-neck-746-rather-than-846 |access-date=June 23, 2020|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20200623084616/https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2020-06-18/derek-chauvin-had-knee-george-floyd-neck-746-rather-than-846|archive-date=June 23, 2020|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; In August, police body camera footage was publicly released, which showed the duration to be about 9:30.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Willis|first1=Haley|last2=Hill|first2=Evan|last3=Stein|first3=Robin|last4=Triebert|first4=Christiaan|last5=Laffin|first5=Ben|last6=Jordan|first6=Drew|date=August 11, 2020|title=New Footage Shows Delayed Medical Response to George Floyd|newspaper=The New York Times|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2020/08/11/us/george-floyd-body-cam-full-video.html|access-date=August 14, 2020|archive-date=August 15, 2020|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20200815122140/https://www.nytimes.com/2020/08/11/us/george-floyd-body-cam-full-video.html|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=XiongAugust3rd&gt;{{cite news|last=Xiong|first=Chao|date=August 3, 2020|title=Daily Mail publishes leaked bodycam footage of George Floyd arrest, killing|newspaper=Star Tribune|url=https://www.startribune.com/daily-mail-publishes-leaked-bodycam-footage-of-george-floyd-arrest-killing/571995372/|access-date=August 14, 2020|quote=Prosecutors have said Chauvin knelt on Floyd's neck for nearly 8 minutes, but Kueng's video showed that it was about 9 minutes and 30 seconds.|archive-date=August 14, 2020|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20200814071032/https://www.startribune.com/daily-mail-publishes-leaked-bodycam-footage-of-george-floyd-arrest-killing/571995372/|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|date=August 11, 2020|title=Two police bodycam videos in killing of George Floyd released|newspaper=Tampa Bay Times|agency=Associated Press|url=https://www.tampabay.com/news/2020/08/10/two-police-bodycam-videos-in-killing-of-george-floyd-released/|access-date=August 14, 2020|archive-date=August 19, 2020|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20200819211514/https://www.tampabay.com/news/2020/08/10/two-police-bodycam-videos-in-killing-of-george-floyd-released/|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
All four police officers present were fired the next day,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title='I Can't Breathe': 4 Minneapolis Officers Fired After Black Man Dies in Custody|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2020/05/26/us/minneapolis-police-man-died.html|access-date=May 26, 2020|newspaper=The New York Times|date=May 26, 2020|last1=Hauser|first1=Christine|last2=Taylor|first2=Derrick Bryson|last3=Vigdor|first3=Neil}}&lt;/ref&gt; and later arrested.&lt;ref name="cnn.com"&gt;{{Cite web|author1=Josh Campbell|author2=Sara Sidner|author3=Eric Levenson|title=All four former officers involved in George Floyd's killing now face charges|url=https://www.cnn.com/2020/06/03/us/george-floyd-officers-charges/index.html|access-date=2020-06-25|website=CNN|date=June 3, 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt; Chauvin was charged with and later convicted of second-degree murder, and the other three officers were charged with aiding and abetting second-degree murder.&lt;ref name="cnn.com" /&gt; Floyd's murder sparked a [[George Floyd protests|wave of protests]] across the United States and worldwide.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |last1=Burch |first1=Audra D. S. |last2=Cai |first2=Weiyi |last3=Gianordoli |first3=Gabriel |last4=McCarthy |first4=Morrigan |last5=Patel |first5=Jugal K. |date=June 13, 2020 |title=How Black Lives Matter Reached Every Corner of America |work=The New York Times |url=https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2020/06/13/us/george-floyd-protests-cities-photos.html|access-date=February 19, 2022 |issn=0362-4331}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A white male gunman identified as [[Payton S. Gendron]] of [[Conklin, New York]] shot and killed 10 black people in the [[2022 Buffalo shooting]]. He believed [[White Americans]] were being replaced by blacks.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=https://www.nytimes.com/live/2022/05/14/nyregion/buffalo-shooting | title=Gunman Kills 10 at Buffalo Supermarket in Racist Attack | newspaper=The New York Times | date=May 14, 2022 | last1=McKinley | first1=Jesse | last2=Traub | first2=Alex | last3=Closson | first3=Troy }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2023, a white man shot and killed 3 black people inside a [[Dollar General]] in [[Jacksonville, Florida]]. He shot them to death with a Glock handgun and an AR-15 semi-automatic rifle. One of the guns were painted with a swastika.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.pbs.org/newshour/amp/nation/white-man-fatally-shoots-3-black-people-at-a-florida-store-in-a-hate-crime-officials-say|title=White man fatally shoots 3 Black people at a Florida store in a hate crime, officials say|website=[[PBS]] }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Afrophobia]]
* [[List of unarmed African Americans killed by law enforcement officers in the United States]]

==Notes==
{{notelist}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
* {{cite book|last1=Bell|first1=Derrick|author-link1=Derrick Bell|title=Faces at the Bottom of the Well: The Permanence of Racism|url=https://archive.org/details/facesatbottomofw00bell|url-access=registration|date=1992|publisher=Basic Books|location=New York|isbn=978-0465068173}}
* {{cite book|first=Ibram X.|last=Kendi|author-link=Ibram X. Kendi|title-link=Stamped from the Beginning|title=Stamped from the Beginning: The Definitive History of Racist Ideas in America|place=New York|publisher=Nation Books|year=2016|isbn=978-1568584645}}
* Raffel, Jeffrey. ''Historical dictionary of school segregation and desegregation: The American experience'' (Bloomsbury, 1998) [https://books.google.com/books?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;id=2a7OEAAAQBAJ&amp;oi=fnd&amp;pg=PR7&amp;dq=HISTORICAL+DICTIONARY+OF+SCHOOL+SEGREGATION+AND+DESEGREGATION&amp;ots=FNVMhQhrqU&amp;sig=IpyhybKlG5BpZFJxVxtOMfHU_q4 online]

{{African American topics}}
{{Americas topic|Racism in}}
{{Demographics of the United States}}
{{United States topics}}
{{Racism topics|state=collapsed}}

[[Category:Anti-black racism in the United States| ]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>