<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20230923194810|1176754355" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="50528637" pageid="50528637" ns="0" title="High heel policy"><revisions><rev timestamp="2023-09-23T21:33:11Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|Regulation or law about the wearing of high heels}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=April 2018}}
[[File:No Heels.jpg |thumb|right |High heels have been restricted by law and policy in various places such as schools, museums, and localities such as [[Mobile, Alabama]].&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=0LY7AwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT338 |title=Fashion and Fetishism |first=David |last=Kunzle |publisher=The History Press |year=2013 |isbn=9780752495453}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In this case, the sign forbids them on [[Stearns Wharf]] in [[Santa Barbara, California]].]]
[[File:Stilettos-heels-b.JPG|thumb|A pair of [[court shoe|pumps/court shoes]] with {{convert|12|cm|frac=4|abbr=in}} stiletto heels]]
A '''high heel policy''' is a regulation or law about the wearing of [[high heels]], which may be required or forbidden in different places and circumstances.

Historically in the West high heels were associated with [[aristocrats]] for cosmetic reasons, to emphasize social status among an elite who could afford to wear impractical footwear, to raise their height, or to keep feet and long dresses clean.  The style was then subject to [[sumptuary law|sumptuary]] laws.  In more modern times, [[stiletto heels]] have been restricted when they might damage the floor surface or cause accidents.

Some [[dress code]]s, however, require women to wear high heels so that they appear to be taller and more attractive.  Such footwear may be painful and damage the feet, and there have been repeated protests by women workers against such policies.  In 2016, a British receptionist was dismissed for not wearing high heels and she then started a petition which attracted sufficient support to be considered by the UK Parliament.

== Regulations preventing the wearing of high heels ==
===In history===
In 1430, ''[[chopine]]s'' were {{convert|30|in|cm|0}} high, at times. [[Republic of Venice|Venetian]] law then limited the height to three inches—but this regulation was widely ignored.&lt;ref name="DeMello2009"&gt;{{cite book|author=Margo DeMello|title=Feet and Footwear: A Cultural Encyclopedia|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=5QdKSxajwP0C&amp;pg=PA311|year=2009|publisher=Greenwood Press/ABC-CLIO|isbn=978-0-313-35714-5|page=311}}&lt;/ref&gt; A 17th-century law in [[Massachusetts]] announced that women would be subjected to the same treatment as witches if they lured men into marriage via the use of high-heeled shoes.&lt;ref name=demello323&gt;{{cite book|author=Margo DeMello|title=Feet and Footwear: A Cultural Encyclopedia|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=LKTACQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA323|date=10 September 2009|publisher=ABC-CLIO|isbn=978-0-313-35715-2|page=323}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1770, an act was introduced into the [[Parliament of Great Britain|British parliament]] which would have applied the same penalties as witchcraft to the use of high heels and other cosmetic devices.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |title=Manners and Customs of the English Nation |author=John Brookes |pages=261–262 |publisher=James Blackwood |year=1859 |quote=In the year 1770 an act was introduced into Parliament against hoops, false hair, high heels...}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Floor surface and safety concerns===
The pressure under a stiletto heel is greater (per unit of the very small area) than that under the feet of an elephant.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://hypertextbook.com/facts/2003/JackGreen.shtml|title=Pressure Under High Heels|last=Green|first=Jack|year=2003|accessdate= 20 December 2012|publisher= The Physics Factbook}}&lt;/ref&gt; Thus, as  the very narrow [[stiletto heel]] became more widespread in the 1950s, the owners of many types of buildings became concerned about the effects of large numbers of such heels on their floors, especially in historic and high-traffic public buildings. Specifically, there was concern that the heels would either damage certain types of floor covering or cause minor accidents through heels getting jammed in floor-grills, the gaps in planking, or uneven surfaces. Soft outdoor ground also caused problems, affecting both the surface and the wearer.   Wood flooring was the most vulnerable, but carpets, [[linoleum]], and mosaic floors were also considered at risk of damage.  Signs were frequently posted attempting to ban stiletto heels, though they were generally ineffective. A 1963 article in a US building maintenance magazine stated, "Replacement of floors is estimated to have cost at least half a billion dollars throughout the country since the advent of the stiletto heel fashion."&lt;ref&gt;''Modern Sanitation and Building Maintenance'', Volume 15, 1963&lt;/ref&gt; The [[United States Department of Agriculture|U.S. Department of Agriculture]] [[United States Forest Service|Forest Service]] claimed in 1963 that "with style changes the stiletto-heel problem has diminished".&lt;ref&gt;''United States Department of Agriculture Forest Service, research note, Forest Products Laboratory'', 1963&lt;/ref&gt; In 2023, a gay club called Bunker opened in Washington, D.C., and it banned high heels, as well as open-toed shoes and flip flops, "for customer safety." However, this ban on high heels was dropped within a month, with the club's website stating instead of an outright ban, "Bunker welcomes the attire of all gender identities and expressions. However, Bunker is a dimly lit, underground dance club with concrete floors and steps. As a safety precaution, we strongly discourage the wearing of high heels. Open-toed shoes are prohibited."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://dcist.com/story/23/03/08/dc-new-gay-bar-bunker-drops-no-high-heel-dress-code-after-public-pushback/|title=D.C.'s New Gay Bar And Club, Bunker, Drops 'No High Heels' Dress Code After Pushback}}&lt;/ref&gt;

High heels can represent [[contributory negligence]] by the [[plaintiff]] in American [[personal injury]] cases involving [[slip and fall]] accidents.&lt;ref&gt;Gary M. Bakken, H. Harvey Cohen, Jon R. Abele, ''Slips, Trips, Missteps, and Their Consequences'', p. 170, Lawyers &amp; Judges Publishing Company, 2007, {{ISBN|1933264012}}, 9781933264011, [https://books.google.com/books?id=aWatvfoR7vQC&amp;pg=PA170 google books]&lt;/ref&gt;  Many high heel policies in the US are related to concerns over the potential for legal claims.{{Citation needed|date = June 2016}}

== Regulations requiring the wearing of high heels ==
=== In media and fashion ===
Some women have challenged the expectation that women should wear high heels in formal social situations. In 2015, a group of women were turned away from a film première at the [[Cannes Film Festival]] in France for wearing flat shoes, including a woman physically unable to wear heels due to an operation on one of her feet.&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/film/cannes-festival/emily-blunt-cannes-heel-row/|title=Emily Blunt on Cannes heels row: 'everybody should wear flats'|newspaper=The Telegraph|language=en-GB|access-date=16 May 2016|date=19 May 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; The women complained that this was a sexist policy which forced women into a stereotyped appearance; festival organisers later responded that "the rumour that the festival requires high heels for the women on the steps [was] baseless."&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.yahoo.com/news/cannes-denies-high-heel-rule-women-red-carpet-173653799.html?ref=gs|title=Cannes denies high-heel rule for women on red carpet|website=www.yahoo.com|access-date=16 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===In workplaces===
Some dress codes require women to wear high heels, and some medical organizations have called for a ban on such dress codes.&lt;ref name=2016_review&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Barnish |first1=MS |last2=Barnish |first2=J |title=High-heeled shoes and musculoskeletal injuries: a narrative systematic review. |journal=BMJ Open |date=13 January 2016 |volume=6 |issue=1 |pages=e010053 |doi=10.1136/bmjopen-2015-010053 |pmid=26769789|pmc=4735171 }}&lt;/ref&gt; There have been repeated protests by women workers against such policies. Laws regarding dress codes that require women to wear high heels in the workplace. Some women, however, consider the ban on high heels sexist.

It has been argued that high heels in the workplace should be subject to a health and safety assessment.&lt;ref name=Unions/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/uknews/6193823/High-heels-should-be-banned-at-work.html|title=High heels 'should be banned at work'|work=The Telegraph|date=2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Canada====
Guidelines on acceptable [[dress code]]s in the workplace are permitted by Canadian law in order to ensure that employees are able to complete their work safely and effectively.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.millerthomson.com/en/blog/canadian-labour-employment-law-blog/high-heels-in-the-workplace-could-be-high|title=Canadian Labour &amp; Employment Law Blog {{!}} High Heels in the Workplace could be High Risk for Employers {{!}} Miller Thomson|website=www.millerthomson.com|access-date=16 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; However the inclusion of the wearing of high heels in these guidelines has created controversy. Some workplace studies show that women in the hospitality industry who wear high heels have suffered injuries after tripping, falling, or slipping.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; In addition, requirements for an appearance that differs for male and female employees have the potential to be considered discriminatory.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

In 2014, waitresses at three restaurant chains in [[Calgary|Calgary, Alberta]], Canada, claimed that they were required to wear high heels at work despite complaining of pain and injury. Management responded that there was no written policy on wearing high heels.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://globalnews.ca/news/2052233/original-joes-boston-pizza-servers-claim-mandatory-high-heel-policies/ |title=Original Joe's, Boston Pizza servers claim mandatory high heel policies |last=Hart |first=Danielle |website=Global News |access-date=16 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In April 2017, the Canadian province of [[British Columbia]] amended workplace legislation to prevent employers from requiring women to wear high heels at work. British Columbia premier [[Christy Clark]] stated that the government was "changing this regulation to stop this unsafe and discriminatory practice."&lt;ref name="guardian-8apr2017"&gt;{{cite news|last1=Collig|first1=Pádraig|title=Canadian province makes it illegal to require women to wear high heels|url=https://www.theguardian.com/fashion/2017/apr/08/canadian-province-makes-it-illegal-to-require-women-to-wear-high-heels|accessdate=8 April 2017|newspaper=[[The Guardian]]|date=8 April 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other Canadian provinces followed suit.&lt;ref name="2018_bans"&gt;{{cite news |title=Alberta takes steps to ban mandatory high heels in the workplace {{!}} National Post |url=https://nationalpost.com/news/canada/alberta-takes-steps-to-ban-mandatory-high-heels-in-the-workplace |accessdate=11 November 2019 |work=National Post |date=30 November 2018 |language=en-CA}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===United States===
During the mid-1990s, several US-based airlines required female [[flight attendants]] to wear shoes with heels. Minimum heel heights ranged from one-half inch to the two inches mandated by [[USAir]].&lt;ref name=marc&gt;{{cite web |url=http://ir.uiowa.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1007&amp;context=law_pubs |author=Marc Linder |title=Smart Women, Stupid Shoes, and Cynical Employers |publisher=[[University of Iowa]] |date=1 January 1997 |accessdate=24 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Flight attendants at times avoided censure by changing into more comfortable shoes during flights, since their supervisors were less likely to be present there.&lt;ref name="Banaszak-HollLevitsky2010"&gt;{{cite book |author1=Jane C. Banaszak-Holl |author2=Sandra R. Levitsky |author3=Mayer N. Zald |title=Social Movements and the Transformation of American Health Care |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=OePEMr_9l0wC&amp;pg=PA294 |date=24 June 2010 |publisher=Oxford University Press |isbn=978-0-19-974214-1 |page=294}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Policies that force women to wear heels have been challenged in a number of locations. In 2001, [[cocktail waitress]]es in [[Las Vegas]] organized a "Kiss My Foot" campaign which was successful in getting casinos to relax their requirement to wear high heels.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |page=43 |title=Casino Women: Courage in Unexpected Places |first1=Susan |last1=Chandler |first2=Jill |last2=Jones |publisher=Cornell University Press |year=2011 |isbn=9780801450143}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===United Kingdom===
In 2009, the UK [[Society of Chiropodists and Podiatrists]] released a report outlining the dangers of wearing high heels for extended periods and approached unions and employers to collaborate on measures to ensure risk assessments would be completed on women's footwear, and to offer alternatives to high heels where these were deemed unhealthy.&lt;ref name=Unions&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.reuters.com/article/us-britain-shoes-heels-idUSTRE58F3WL20090916|title=UK unions spark debate over high heels at work|date=16 September 2009|newspaper=Reuters|access-date=16 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Similar policies were tested again in the UK in 2016 when a [[temporary work|temporary receptionist]], [[Nicola Thorp]], was sent home unpaid after she refused to follow the dress code at the office of accountants [[PricewaterhouseCoopers]]. Outsourcing firm Portico stated that Thorp "had signed the appearance guidelines" but after Thorp launched an online petition—"Make it illegal for a company to require women to wear high heels at work"—the firm changed their policy. The new guideline states that all female employees "can wear plain flat shoes or plain court shoes as they prefer."&lt;ref name="Guard-1"&gt;{{cite news |last1=Johnston |first1=Chris |title=Woman's high-heel petition receives 100,000-plus signatures |url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2016/may/12/nicola-thorp-high-heel-petition-receives-100000-plus-signatures|accessdate=13 May 2016|work=the Guardian|date=12 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; The petition gained widespread support from public figures such as Scotland's First Minister [[Nicola Sturgeon]] and [[Member of Parliament|MPs]] [[Caroline Dinenage]], [[Margot James]] and [[Tulip Siddiq]].&lt;ref name="McIntosh"&gt;{{cite news|last=McIntosh|first=Lindsay|url=http://www.thetimes.co.uk/article/heel-loving-sturgeon-steps-into-shoe-debate-vv2nlh825 |title=Heel-loving Sturgeon steps into shoe debate |work=The Times|location=London |date=16 May 2016|accessdate=7 March 2017}} {{subscription required}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Tele-1"&gt;{{cite news|last1=Yorke|first1=Harry|url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/2016/05/12/firm-accused-of-sexism-in-high-heels-row-forced-to-change-its-dr/ |title=MPs back temp worker's campaign to end 'sexist' high heel policy |work=The Daily Telegraph |date=12 May 2016 |accessdate=13 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Two parliamentary committees in January 2017 decided that Portico had broken the law; the company had already changed its terms of employment.&lt;ref name="McIntosh"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Bilefsky"&gt;{{cite news|last=Bilefsky|first=Dan|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2017/03/06/world/europe/uk-parliament-nicola-thorp-heels.html?smid=tw-nytimes&amp;smtyp=cur&amp;_r=0|title=British Woman's Revolt Against High Heels Becomes a Cause in Parliament|work=The New York Times|date=6 March 2017|accessdate=7 March 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The petition gained over 130,000 signatures, sufficient for a debate in the British parliament.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |last=Kaur Grewal |first=Herpreet |url=http://www.fm-world.co.uk/news/fm-industry-news/temps-high-heels-petition-heads-for-parliament/ |title=Temp's 'high heels' petition heads for Parliament |date=17 May 2016 |journal=FM World |access-date=22 May 2016 |archive-date=13 February 2017 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170213083153/http://www.fm-world.co.uk/news/fm-industry-news/temps-high-heels-petition-heads-for-parliament/ |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; This took place on 6 March 2017, when MPs decided the UK government should change the law to prevent the demand being made by employers.&lt;ref name="Bilefsky"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Hansard"&gt;{{cite hansard |jurisdiction=United Kingdom |title=Workplace Dress Codes (High Heels) |url=https://hansard.parliament.uk/commons/2017-03-06/debates/58CDA5AC-D655-43F4-BDD8-3D1370BCB076/WorkplaceDressCodes%28HighHeels%29 |house=[[Westminster Hall]] |date= 6 March 2017 |column_start=198WH |column_end=216WH |speaker=[[Helen Jones]] |position=the [[British Members of Parliament|MP]] for [[Warrington North (UK Parliament constituency)|Warrington North]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, this was rejected by the government in April 2017 as they stated that existing legislation was "adequate".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-39667912|title=High heels row: Petition for work dress code law rejected|date=21 April 2017|work=BBC News|access-date=21 April 2017|language=en-GB}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The government clarified in a document published in May 2018 that high heel policies likely constituted direct discrimination, even if the men's shoes were required to "look smart," and potentially also indirect discrimination against those with mobility or vision problems.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Dress codes and sex discrimination: what you need to know |url=https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/dress-codes-and-sex-discrimination-what-you-need-to-know |access-date=2022-05-30 |website=GOV.UK |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Israel===

In 2015, the Israeli airline [[El Al]] introduced a requirement that female flight attendants wear high heels until passengers had been seated.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://globalnews.ca/news/2063591/i-dont-think-the-girls-thought-they-could-question-it-high-heels-policy-study-author/|title='I don't think the girls thought they could question it': high heels policy study author |last=Tucker |first=Erika |website=Global News |access-date=16 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; The airline's workers' union stated that the requirement would endanger the health and safety of the flight attendants and instructed its members to ignore the rule. Later that year the requirement was removed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Yedidyah Ben Or, 10/09/15 12:26 |url=http://www.israelnationalnews.com/News/News.aspx/200542 |title=El Al Flight Attendants Say Goodbye to High Heels |publisher=Israel National News |date= 10 September 2015|accessdate=2019-06-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Philippines===

Also in 2017, the [[Philippines]] forbade companies from mandating that female employees wear high heels at work.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news | url=https://www.reuters.com/article/philippines-women/philippines-bans-mandatory-high-heels-at-work-idUSL8N1M637F |title = Philippines bans mandatory high heels at work|newspaper = Reuters|date = 25 September 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Japan===

In 2019, a petition against mandatory high heels was started in Japan with the hashtag [[KuToo movement|#KuToo]], blending the [[MeToo movement|#MeToo movement]] with the Japanese words for shoes (''kutsu'') and pain (''kutsuu'').&lt;ref name=BBC&gt;{{citation |url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-48504490 |publisher=BBC News |title=Thousands back Japan high heels campaign |date=3 June 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Japanese Minister of Labor has stated that it is acceptable for companies and others to require women to wear high heels as long as it is necessary and appropriate for the job, with reference to socially accepted norms.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://kokkai.ndl.go.jp/#/detail?minId=119804260X02220190605&amp;current=1|title=No198 Japanese House of Representatives Session minutes remark No.059,No.063,No.069|date=2019-06-03|access-date=10 February 2023}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.asahi.com/articles/ASM6566MNM65ULFA04B.html|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20220520053937/https://www.asahi.com/articles/ASM6566MNM65ULFA04B.html|script-title=ja:職場でハイヒール強制「業務上必要なら」 厚労相が容認|language=ja|publisher=[[The Asahi Shimbun]]|date=5 June 2019|archive-date=20 May 2022|access-date=10 February 2023}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Cosmetics policy]]
* [[Foot Emancipation Society]]
* [[Hijabophobia]]
* [[KuToo movement]]
* ''[[Price Waterhouse v. Hopkins]]''
* [[Right to sit]]

==References==
{{reflist|30em}}

==External links==
* [http://www.parliament.uk/petitions-committee/heels-at-work-inquiry High heels and workplace dress codes inquiry] of the UK Petitions Committee
* [http://www.parliament.uk/business/committees/committees-a-z/commons-select/petitions-committee/inquiries/parliament-2015/high-heels-workplace-dress-codes-inquiry-16-17/high-heels-and-work-place-dress-codes-web-forum--/ High heels and work place dress codes web forum] – oral evidence for the Commons Select Committee

[[Category:Clothing controversies]]
[[Category:Discrimination in the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Dress codes (legal)]]
[[Category:High-heeled footwear]]
[[Category:Labour law]]
[[Category:Sexism]]
[[Category:Women's rights]]
[[Category:Working conditions]]
[[Category:Workwear]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>