<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20170223060920|766971657" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="28359484" pageid="28359484" ns="0" title="Statistical discrimination (economics)"><revisions><rev timestamp="2017-08-23T18:19:04Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Statistical discrimination''' is an [[economics|economic]] theory of racial or gender [[Economic inequality|inequality]] based on [[stereotypes]]. According to this theory, inequality may exist and persist between demographic groups even when economic agents (consumers, workers, employers, etc.) are rational and non-prejudiced. This type of preferential treatment is labeled "statistical" because stereotypes may be based on the discriminated group's [[average]] behavior.

The theory was pioneered by [[Kenneth Arrow]] and [[Edmund Phelps]] &lt;ref&gt;Fang, Hanming and Andrea Moro, 2011, "Theories of Statistical Discrimination and Affirmative Action: A Survey," in Jess Benhabib, Matthew Jackson and Alberto Bisin, eds: Handbook of Social Economics, Vol. 1A, Chapter 5, The Netherlands: North Holland, 2011, pp. 133-200. Available as [http://ideas.repec.org/p/nbr/nberwo/15860.html NBER Working Papers 15860], National Bureau of Economic Research, Inc.&lt;/ref&gt;
The theory posits that in the absence of direct information about a certain fact of ability, a decision maker would substitute group averages. For instance, labor market discrimination may exist because employers don't know with certainty workers' ability, therefore they may resort to basing employment decisions on the workers' visible features, such as group identity, as long as these features [[Correlation and dependence|correlate]] with some desirable but more difficult to measure trait. The result is that atypical individuals from the disadvantaged group suffer unfair discrimination.&lt;ref name="Tobler2005"&gt;{{cite book|author=Christa Tobler|title=Indirect Discrimination: A Case Study Into the Development of the Legal Concept of Indirect Discrimination Under EC Law|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ePRKaU0k3nIC&amp;pg=PA55|year=2005|publisher=Intersentia nv|isbn=978-90-5095-458-7|page=55}}&lt;/ref&gt; This type of discrimination can result in a self-reinforcing [[vicious circle]] over time, as the atypical individuals from the discriminated group are discouraged from participating in the market,&lt;ref name="Rodgers2009"&gt;{{cite book|author=William M. Rodgers|title=Handbook on the Economics of Discrimination|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=RiVATAL4Om0C&amp;pg=PA223|year=2009|publisher=Edward Elgar Publishing|isbn=978-1-84720-015-0|pages=223}}&lt;/ref&gt; or improving their skills as their (average) return on investment (education etc.) is less than for the non-discriminated group.&lt;ref name="Dau-Schmidt2009"&gt;{{cite book|author=K. G. Dau-Schmidt|title=Labor and Employment Law and Economics|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=NE5AK4P6kWsC&amp;pg=PA304|year=2009|publisher=Edward Elgar Publishing|isbn=978-1-78195-306-8|pages=304}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A related form of (theorized) statistical discrimination is based on group [[variance]]s, assuming equal averages. For discrimination to occur in this scenario, the decision maker needs to be [[risk averse]]; such a decision maker will prefer the group with the lower variance.&lt;ref name="England1992"&gt;{{cite book|author=Paula England|title=Comparable Worth: Theories and Evidence|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=JFLk3v19b0gC&amp;pg=PA58|year=1992|publisher=Transaction Publishers|isbn=978-0-202-30348-2|pages=58–60}}&lt;/ref&gt; Even assuming two theoretically identical group distributions (in all respects, including average and variance), a risk averse decision maker will prefer the group for which a measurement (test) exists that minimizes the [[error term]].&lt;ref name="England1992"/&gt; For example, if two groups, A and B, have theoretically identical distributions of test scores well above the average for the entire population, but group A's estimate is considered more reliable because a large amount of data may be available for group A in comparison to group B, then if two people, one from A and one from B apply for a job, using statistical discrimination, A is hired, because it is perceived that his group score is a more reliable estimate, so a risk-averse decision maker sees group B's group score as more likely to be luck. Conversely, if the two groups are below average, B is hired, because group A's negative score is believed to be a better estimate.

Statistical discrimination is often used and tolerated, for example, when older people are charged more for life insurance, or when a college diploma is required for a job (because it is believed that college graduates perform, on average, better). Some well-documented instances of statistical discrimination for involuntary group membership also do exist and are tolerated. For example, many countries allow auto insurance companies to charge men and women with identical driving records different rates (or factor in gender when deciding whether to deny coverage). The same society may not tolerate statistical discrimination when it is applied to protected groups. For example, it has been suggested that home mortgage lending discrimination against [[African Americans]], which is illegal in the [[United States]], may be partly caused by statistical discrimination.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.clevelandfed.org/Research/Commentary/1995/1100.pdf Rooting Out Discrimination in Home Mortgage Lending -]&lt;/ref&gt;

Market forces are expected to penalize some forms of statistical discrimination; for example, a company capable and willing to test its job applicants on relevant metrics is expected to do better than one that relies only on group averages for employment decisions.&lt;ref name="Nechyba2010"&gt;{{cite book|author=Thomas J. Nechyba|title=Microeconomics: An Intuitive Approach|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=zsV-cHg96RsC&amp;pg=PA514|year=2010|publisher=Cengage Learning|isbn=0-324-27470-X|pages=514}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, this assumption does not take into account the economic cost of testing itself, which may not be feasible in some scenarios like predicting the future likelihood that an employee will quit for personal reasons.&lt;ref name="University2004"&gt;{{cite book|author=Anne L. Alstott|title=No Exit: What Parents Owe Their Children and What Society Owes Parents|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Mnqza00w-SEC&amp;pg=PA149|year=2004|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=978-0-19-534749-4|page=149}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== References ==
{{reflist}}

==Further reading==
{{refbegin}}
* Arrow, K. J. (1973), "The Theory of Discrimination", in O. Ashenfelter and A. Rees (eds.), ''Discrimination in Labor Markets'', Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press.
* Coate, Steven and Glenn Loury, 1993, Will affirmative-action policies eliminate negative stereotypes?,The American Economic Review, 1220–1240.
* [[Glenn Loury]], ''The Anatomy of Racial Inequality'', Princeton University Press. Informally illustrates the theory in the context of [[United States]]' racial differences. 
* {{cite journal | author=[[Edmund Phelps|Phelps, Edmund S.]] | title=The Statistical Theory of Racism and Sexism | journal=American Economic Review| year=1972 | volume=62 | pages=659–661}}
{{refend}}

[[Category:Employment discrimination]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>