<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20211203144358|1058440052" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="28359484" pageid="28359484" ns="0" title="Statistical discrimination (economics)"><revisions><rev timestamp="2022-11-27T13:21:48Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Theorized behavior in economics}}

'''Statistical discrimination''' is a [[economic theory|theorized]] behavior in which racial or gender [[Economic inequality|inequality]] results when economic agents (consumers, workers, employers, etc.) have imperfect information about individuals they interact with.&lt;ref name="Principle of Economics"&gt;{{cite book |last1=Mankiw |first1=N. Gregory |title=Principle of Economics |date=2020 |publisher=Cengage Learning |isbn=9780357133804 |pages=392–393 |edition=9 |url=https://www.google.com/books/edition/Principles_of_Economics/KQfFDwAAQBAJ?hl=en&amp;gbpv=0 |access-date=19 September 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to this theory, inequality may exist and persist between demographic groups even when economic agents are rational and non-prejudiced. It stands in contrast with [[taste-based discrimination]] which uses racism, sexism and the likes to explain different labour market outcomes of groups.

The theory of statistical discrimination was pioneered by [[Kenneth Arrow]] (1973) and [[Edmund Phelps]] (1972).&lt;ref&gt;Fang, Hanming and Andrea Moro, 2011, "Theories of Statistical Discrimination and Affirmative Action: A Survey," in Jess Benhabib, Matthew Jackson and Alberto Bisin, eds: Handbook of Social Economics, Vol. 1A, Chapter 5, The Netherlands: North Holland, 2011, pp. 133-200. Available as [http://ideas.repec.org/p/nbr/nberwo/15860.html NBER Working Papers 15860], National Bureau of Economic Research, Inc.&lt;/ref&gt; The name "statistical discrimination" relates to the way in which employers make employment decisions. Since their information on the applicants' productivity is imperfect, they use statistical information on the group they belong to in order to infer productivity. If the minority group is less productive initially (due to historic discrimination or having navigated a bad equilibrium), each individual in this group will be assumed to be less productive and discrimination arises.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Lang, Lehmann|date=2012|title=Racial Discrimination in the Labour Market: Theory and Empirics|journal=Journal of Economic Literature|volume=50|issue=4|pages=959–1006|jstor=23644909|doi=10.1257/jel.50.4.959|url=http://www.nber.org/papers/w17450.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; This type of discrimination can result in a self-reinforcing [[vicious circle]] over time, as the atypical individuals from the discriminated group are discouraged from participating in the market,&lt;ref name="Rodgers2009"&gt;{{cite book|author=William M. Rodgers|title=Handbook on the Economics of Discrimination|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=RiVATAL4Om0C&amp;pg=PA223|year=2009|publisher=Edward Elgar Publishing|isbn=978-1-84720-015-0|pages=223}}&lt;/ref&gt; or from improving their skills as their (average) return on investment (education etc.) is less than for the non-discriminated group.&lt;ref name="Dau-Schmidt2009"&gt;{{cite book|author=K. G. Dau-Schmidt|title=Labor and Employment Law and Economics|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=NE5AK4P6kWsC&amp;pg=PA304|year=2009|publisher=Edward Elgar Publishing|isbn=978-1-78195-306-8|pages=304}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A related form of (theorized) statistical discrimination is based on differences in the signals that applicants send to employers. These signals report the applicant's productivity, but they are noisy. 
Discrimination can occur if groups differ on means, even if applicants have identical nominal above-average signals: [[regression to the mean]] will imply that a member of a higher-mean group will regress less as they are more likely to have a higher true value, while the lower-mean group member will regress more and the signal will overestimate their value if the group membership is ignored ("Kelley's paradox"&lt;ref&gt;Wainer &amp; Brown 2006, [https://www.gwern.net/docs/statistics/bayes/2006-wainer.pdf "Three Statistical Paradoxes in the Interpretation of Group Differences: Illustrated with Medical School Admission and Licensing Data"]&lt;/ref&gt;). Discrimination can also occur on group [[variance]]s in the signals (i.e. in how noisy the signal is), even assuming equal averages. For variance-based discrimination to occur, the decision maker needs to be [[risk averse]]; such a decision maker will prefer the group with the lower variance.&lt;ref name="England1992"&gt;{{cite book|author=Paula England|title=Comparable Worth: Theories and Evidence|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=JFLk3v19b0gC&amp;pg=PA58|year=1992|publisher=Transaction Publishers|isbn=978-0-202-30348-2|pages=58–60}}&lt;/ref&gt; Even assuming two theoretically identical groups (in all respects, including average and variance), a risk averse decision maker will prefer the group for which a measurement (signal, test) exists that minimizes the signal [[error term]].&lt;ref name="England1992"/&gt; For example, assume two individuals, A and B, have theoretically identical test scores well above the average for the entire population, but individual A's estimate is considered more reliable because a large amount of data may be available for their group in comparison to the group of B. Then if two people, one from A and one from B, apply for the same job, A is hired, because it is perceived that their score is a more reliable estimate, so a risk-averse decision maker sees B's score as more likely to be luck. Conversely, if the two groups are below average, B is hired, because group A's negative score is believed to be a better estimate. This generates differences in employment chances, but also in the average wages of different groups - a group with a lower signal precision will be disproportionately employed to lower paying jobs.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Phelps|first=Edmund|date=1972|title=The Statistical Theory of Racism and Sexism|journal=The American Economic Review|volume=62|issue=4|pages=659–661|jstor=1806107}}&lt;/ref&gt;

It has been suggested that home mortgage lending discrimination against [[African Americans]], which is illegal in the [[United States]], may be partly caused by statistical discrimination.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.clevelandfed.org/Research/Commentary/1995/1100.pdf Rooting Out Discrimination in Home Mortgage Lending -]&lt;/ref&gt;

Market forces are expected to penalize some forms of statistical discrimination; for example, a company capable and willing to test its job applicants on relevant metrics is expected to do better than one that relies only on group averages for employment decisions.&lt;ref name="Nechyba2010"&gt;{{cite book|author=Thomas J. Nechyba|title=Microeconomics: An Intuitive Approach|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=zsV-cHg96RsC&amp;pg=PA514|year=2010|publisher=Cengage Learning|isbn=978-0-324-27470-7|pages=514}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{verify-inline|date=October 2018}}

According to a 2020 study, managers who had experience with statistical discrimination theory were more likely to believe in the accuracy of stereotypes, accept stereotyping, and engage in gender discrimination in hiring. When managers were informed of criticisms against statistical discrimination, these effects were reduced.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Tilcsik|first=András|date=2020-12-11|title=Statistical Discrimination and the Rationalization of Stereotypes|journal=American Sociological Review|volume=86|language=en|pages=93–122|doi=10.1177/0003122420969399|issn=0003-1224|doi-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==

* [[Coate-Loury model]]

== References ==
{{reflist}}

==Further reading==
{{refbegin}}
* Arrow, K. J. (1973), "The Theory of Discrimination", in O. Ashenfelter and A. Rees (eds.), ''Discrimination in Labor Markets'', Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press. {{ISBN|0-691-04170-9}}
* Coate, Steven and Glenn Loury, 1993, Will affirmative-action policies eliminate negative stereotypes?, The American Economic Review, 1220–1240. {{JSTOR|2117558}}
* [[Glenn Loury]], ''The Anatomy of Racial Inequality'', Princeton University Press. Informally illustrates the theory in the context of [[United States]]' racial differences. 
* {{cite journal | author=Phelps, Edmund S. | title=The Statistical Theory of Racism and Sexism | journal=American Economic Review| year=1972 | volume=62 | issue=4 | pages=659–661|jstor=1806107| author-link=Edmund Phelps }}
{{refend}}

[[Category:Employment discrimination]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>