<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20121112004643|522563058" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="7079135" pageid="7079135" ns="0" title="Forced conversion"><revisions><rev timestamp="2012-11-13T07:51:21Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">A '''forced conversion''' is the [[religious conversion]] or acceptance of a philosophy against the will of the subject, often with the threatened consequence of earthly penalties or harm. These consequences range from job loss and social isolation to incarceration, torture or death.

== Christianity==
{{see also|Christianization}}

===End of Roman empire===
Forced conversion was a major means in the Christianization of the Roman Empire. In 392 A.D. the emperor [[Theodosius I]] instituted a law making Christianity the only legal religion of the empire, and forbidding Pagan practices by law as a means to stabilize the declining empire:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
It is Our will that all the peoples who are ruled by the administration of Our Clemency shall practice that religion which the divine Peter the Apostle transmitted to the Romans....The rest, whom We adjudge demented and insane, shall sustain the infamy of heretical dogmas, their meeting places shall not receive the name of churches, and they shall be smitten first by divine vengeance and secondly by the retribution of Our own initiative''" ([[Codex Theodosianus]] XVI 1.2.).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://penelope.uchicago.edu/~grout/encyclopaedia_romana/greece/paganism/paganism.html |title=Paganism and Rome |publisher=Penelope.uchicago.edu |date= |accessdate=2012-11-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
This law led to the destruction of most pagan temples in the empire.

===Medieval era===
During the [[Saxon Wars]], [[Charlemagne]], [[King of the Franks]], forcibly Christianized the [[Saxons]] from their native [[Germanic paganism]] by way of warfare and law upon conquest. Examples include the [[Massacre of Verden]] in 782, during which Charlemagne reportedly had 4,500 captive Saxons massacred upon rebelling against conversion, and the ''[[Capitulatio de partibus Saxoniae]]'', a law imposed on conquered Saxons in 785 which prescribes death to those that refuse to convert to Christianity.&lt;ref name="CHARLEMAGNE"&gt;For the Massacre of Verden, see Barbero, Alessandro (2004). ''Charlemagne: Father of a Continent'', page 46. [[University of California Press]]. For the ''Capitulatio de partibus Saxoniae'', see Riché, Pierre (1993). ''The Carolingians''. [[University of Pennsylvania Press]]. ISBN 978-0-8122-1342-3.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Pope Innocent III]] pronounced in 1201 that even if torture and intimidation had been employed in receiving the sacrament, one nevertheless:
&lt;blockquote&gt;...does receive the impress of Christianity and may be forced to observe the Christian Faith as one who expressed a conditional willingness though, absolutely speaking, he was unwilling. ... [For] the grace of Baptism had been received, and they had been [[confirmation (sacrament)|anointed with the sacred oil]], and had [[eucharist|participated in the body of the Lord]], they might properly be forced to hold to the faith which they had accepted perforce, lest the name of the Lord be blasphemed, and lest they hold in contempt and consider vile the faith they had joined.&lt;ref&gt;Grayzel, Solomon, ''The Church and the Jews in the Thirteenth Century'', rev. ed., New York: Hermon, 1966, p. 103&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

From The Crusades, by Bernard Hamilton&lt;ref&gt;The Crusades, by Bernard Hamilton, 1998, Sutton Publishing, United Kingdom, Chapter 9: Later Crusades, page 87)&lt;/ref&gt;   “In 1309 the Teutonic Order moved its headquarters to Marienburg in Prussia.  It had a papal license to wage perpetual war against the pagans and used this to launch annual crusades against Lithuania.  These expeditions were very popular the nobility of northern Europe: campaigns were held twice a year, in the summer and in the winter when the order laid on special Christmas festivities for visiting crusaders.”“The excuse for men who enjoyed fighting and to lay waste large parts of Lithuania in the name of Christ was removed in 1386 when the King of Lithuania, Ladislas Jagiello, married Queen Jadwiga of Poland and received Catholic baptism.  The two kingdoms were united under Christian rulers and the Teutonic Knights no longer had any justification for crusading against pagans there.”

Lithuania was not the first country that fell victim to a campaign of lethal military force, for the purpose of forced conversion to Christianity.  Three entire European nationalities became victims of genocide because they refused to become Christians:“...the Vandals, Ostogoths, and Heruli.  The last three were destroyed by the Pope of Rome because they refused to become ‘Christian.’  The armies of Emperor Justinian, in cooperation with the Pope, thrust the Ostrogoths out of the city of Rome. They have become extinct.”&lt;ref&gt;2. National Sunday Law, A. Jan Marcussen, 1983, page 11)

 
&lt;/ref&gt;

===Spanish Inquisition===
After the end of the [[Al-Andalus|Islamic control of Spain]], Muslims and Jews were murdered and expelled from Spain in 1492 and from Portugal in 1497.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.home.earthlink.net/~benven/annivers.html 500 ANNIVERSARY OF THE FORCED CONVERSION OF THE JEWS OF PORTUGAL&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; After the [[Reconquista]], so called "[[New Christian]]s" were those inhabitants ([[Sephardi]]c Jews or [[Mudéjar]] Muslims) during the Middle Ages and the Early Modern Era who were baptized under coercion and in the face of murder, becoming forced converts from Islam ([[Morisco]]s, [[Converso]]s and ''secret Moors'') and forced converts from [[Judaism]] ([[Converso]]s, [[Crypto-Judaism|Crypto-Jews]] and [[Marrano]]s). 
Then the [[Spanish Inquisition]] targeted primarily forced converts from Judaism who came under suspicion of either continuing to adhere to their old religion or of having fallen back into it. Jewish conversos still resided in Spain and often hiddenly (cryptically) practiced Judaism and were suspected by the "Old Christians" of being [[Crypto-Jew]]s. The Spanish Inquisition generated much wealth and income for the church and individual inquisitors by confiscating the property of the persecutees or selling them into slavery. The end of the [[Al-Andalus]] and the expulsion of the Sephardic Jews from the Iberian Peninsula went hand in hand with the increase of Spanish-Portugal influence in the world, as exemplified in the Christian conquest of the Americas and their aboriginal Indian population. The Ottoman empire and the Netherlands both absorbed much of the Jewish refugees.

===Goa Inquisition===
Religious persecution took place by the Portuguese in [[Goa]], India from 16th to the 17th century. The natives of Goa, most of them Hindus were subjected to [[Goa Inquisition|severe torture and oppression]] by the zealous Portuguese rulers and missionaries and forcibly converted to Christianity.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.co.in/books?id=RS1uAAAAMAAJ Of umbrellas, goddesses, and dreams: essays on Goan culture and society‎] Robert Samuel Newman, 2001&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[The Goa Inquisition (book)|The Goa Inquisition, Being a Quatercentenary Commemoration Study of the Inquisition in India]] by Anant Priolkar, Bombay University Press&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.co.in/books?id=hSnn_kDUI6AC&amp;pg=PA69 Everyday Nationalism: Women of the Hindu Right in India‎] Kalyani Devaki Menon, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.co.in/books?id=ftS1AAAAIAAJ Journal of the Asiatic Society of Bombay] 1967&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;M. D. David (ed.), Western Colonialism in Asia and Christianity, Bombay, 1988, p.17&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.co.in/books?id=INWSqBXundYC&amp;pg=PA137 Between ethnography and fiction: Verrier Elwin and the tribal question in India‎] Tanka Bahadur Subba, Sujit Som, K. C. Baral, North Eastern Hill University. Dept. of Anthropology - Social Science&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1567, the campaign of destroying temples in Bardez met with success. At the end of it 300 Hindu temples were destroyed. Enacting laws, prohibition was laid from 4 December 1567 on rituals of Hindu marriages, sacred thread wearing and cremation. All the persons above 15 years of age were compelled to listen to Christian preaching, failing which they were punished. In 1583 Hindu temples at Assolna and Cuncolim were destroyed through army action. The fathers of the Church forbade the Hindus under terrible penalties the use of their own sacred books, and prevented them from all exercise of their religion. They destroyed their temples, and so harassed and interfered with the people that they abandoned the city in large numbers, refusing to remain any longer in a place where they had no liberty, and were liable to imprisonment, torture and death if they worshipped after their own fashion the gods of their fathers." wrote Filippo Sassetti, who was in India from 1578 to 1588. An order was issued in June 1684 for suppressing the Konkani language and making it compulsory to speak the Portuguese language. The law provided for dealing toughly with anyone using the local language. Following that law all the non-Christian cultural symbols and the books written in local languages were sought to be destroyed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.scribd.com/doc/28411503/Goa-Inquisition-for-Colonial-Disciplining |title=Goa Inquisition for Colonial Disciplining |publisher=Scribd.com |date=2010-03-15 |accessdate=2012-11-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Methods such as repressive laws, demolition of temples and mosques, destruction of holy books, fines and the forcible conversion of orphans were used.&lt;ref&gt;Mascarenhas-Keyes, Stella (1979), Goans in London: portrait of a Catholic Asian community, Goan Association (U.K.)&lt;/ref&gt;

===Native American Boarding Schools===
The government paid religious societies to provide education to Native American children on reservations. In the late 19th and early 20th centuries, the [[Bureau of Indian Affairs]] (BIA) founded additional boarding schools based on the assimilation model of the [[Carlisle Indian Industrial School]].
 
Children were usually immersed in European-American culture through appearance changes with haircuts, were forbidden to speak their native languages, and traditional names were replaced by new European-American names. The experience of the schools was often harsh, especially for the younger children who were separated from their families. In numerous ways, they were encouraged or forced to abandon their Native American identities and cultures.&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20050829051045/http://sacbee.com/static/archive/news/projects/native/day2_main.html "Long-suffering urban Indians find roots in ancient rituals". California's Lost Tribes]&lt;/ref&gt; Archived from the original on August 29, 2005. Retrieved February 8, 2006. The number of Native American children in the boarding schools reached a peak in the 1970s, with an estimated enrollment of 60,000 in 1973. Especially through investigations of the later twentieth century, there have been many documented cases of sexual, physical and mental abuse occurring at such schools.&lt;ref&gt;"Developmental and learning disabilities". PRSP Disabilities. Retrieved February 8, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.amnestyusa.org/news/newsletter"Soul Wound: The Legacy of Native American Schools". Amnesty International USA. Retrieved February 8, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; Since those years, tribal nations have increasingly insisted on community-based schools and have also founded numerous tribally controlled colleges. Community schools have also been supported by the federal government through the BIA and legislation. The largest boarding schools have closed. In some cases, reservations or tribes were too small or poor to support independent schools and still wanted an alternative for their children, especially for high school. By 2007, the number of Native American children in boarding schools had declined to 9,500.

==Judaism==

Forced conversions are rare, but are reported to have happened under the [[Hasmonean dynasty|Hasmonean Empire]]. The Gentile Galileans, Samaritans and Idumaens were forced to convert to Judaism, (either by threats of exile, or threats of death, depending on the source.)
For the forced conversion of the Idumaeans under [[John Hyrcanus]], see Flavius Josephus Antiquities 13.257-258. For the forced conversion of the Ituraeans under [[Aristobulus I|Aristobulus]], see Flavius Josephus Antiquities 13.319.  
In Eusebíus, Christianity, and Judaism  Harold W. Attridge  says that “there is reason to think that Josephus’ account of their conversion is substantially accurate.”  He also writes, “That these were not isolated instances but that forced conversion was a national policy is clear from the fact that Alexander Jannaeus (ca 80 BCE) demolished the city of Pella in Moab, “because the inhabitants would not agree to adopt the national custom of the Jews.”  Josephus, Antiquities. 13.15.4, 397&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |url=http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=jVyzbHAJ_hAC&amp;pg=PA374&amp;dq=Ituraeans+forced+conversion&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=dNUATu3BAciv8QORmPTHDQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=2&amp;ved=0CC4Q6AEwATgK#v=onepage&amp;q=Ituraeans%20forced%20conversion&amp;f=false |accessdate=2011-06-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Maurice Sartre has written of the "policy of forced Judaization adopted by [[John Hyrcanus|Hyrcanos]], [[Aristobulus I]] and [[Jannaeus]]”, who offered "the conquered peoples a choice between expulsion or conversion,”&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |url=http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=9y7nTpFcN3AC&amp;pg=PA15&amp;lpg=PA15&amp;dq=Ituraeans+forced+conversion&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=hxTELYx1Vd&amp;sig=_EhvKuhvcja0F7ZTkGcW6ET6nG8&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=lMwATsfQOcmn8QO41syeDQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=7&amp;ved=0CD8Q6AEwBg#v=onepage&amp;q=Ituraeans%20forced%20conversion&amp;f=false |accessdate=2011-06-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

And in 'The early Roman period, Volume 2', William David Davies has written that. “The evidence is best explained by postulating that an existing small Jewish population in Lower Galilee was massively expanded by the forced conversion in c.104 BCE of their Gentile neighbours in the north.”&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |url=http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=MA-4VX5gWS4C&amp;pg=PA599&amp;dq=Ituraeans+forced+conversion&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=f9MATobdEMiW8QPYpqyTDQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=6&amp;ved=0CEMQ6AEwBQ#v=onepage&amp;q=Ituraeans%20forced%20conversion&amp;f=false accessdate=2011-20-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Islam==
{{See also|Islamization|Safavid conversion of Iran from Sunnism to Shiism}}

Most scholars have argued that early Islamic scripture and law forbids forced conversion in theory,&lt;ref name="W53"&gt;Waines (2003) "An Introduction to Islam" ''Cambridge University Press''. p. 53&lt;/ref&gt; In opposition to forced Islamization, verse of the [[Qur'an]] ({{cite quran|2|256|expand=no|style=nosup}}) is frequently cited, reading "let there be no compulsion in religion".&lt;ref&gt;Sir Thomas W. Arnold, ''The Preaching of Islam''{{pageneeded|date=November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Marshall G. Hodgson, ''The Venture of Islam''{{pageneeded|date=November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Albert Hourani, ''A History of the Arab Peoples''{{pageneeded|date=November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Ira Lapidus, ''History of Islamic Societies''{{pageneeded|date=November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;L.S. Starorianos, ''A Global History, the Human Heritage''{{pageneeded|date=November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Muhammed and his followers never practice forced conversion of the Pagan Arabs during Muhammad's conquest of Arabia. None of the Quraish was forced to become Muslim, but Muhammad’s victory convinced some of his most principled opponents, such as Abu Sufyan, that the old religion had failed.&lt;ref&gt;Islam - A Short History, Karen Armstrong, Phoenix Press, 2001, p20&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Haykal, M.H. (1933) The Life of Muhammad, translated by Isma'il Razi A. al-Faruqi. The Supreme Council of Islamic Affairs, Cairo, Egypt &amp; the University of Chicago.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Husayn, M.J. - Biography Of Imam `Ali Ibn Abi-Talib, Translation of Sirat Amir Al-Mu'minin, Translated By: Sayyid Tahir Bilgrami, Ansariyan Publications, Qum, Islamic Republic of Iran&lt;/ref&gt;

However, forced conversions have occurred during Islamic history and rarely has it been official government policy.&lt;ref name="W53"/&gt;&lt;ref name="conseq"&gt;Lewis (1984), p. 17, 18, 94, 95.&lt;/ref&gt; Noted cases include the conversion of [[Samaritan]]s to Islam at the hands of the rebel Ibn Firāsa,&lt;ref&gt;M. Levy-Rubin,  "New evidence relating to the process of Islamization in Palestine in the Early Muslim Period - The Case of Samaria", in: ''Journal of the Economic and Social History of the Orient'', 43 (3), p. 257-276, 2000, [[Springer Science+Business Media|Springer]]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Fattal, A.(1958) ''Le statut légal des non-Musulman en pays d'Islam'', Beyrouth: Imprimerie Catholique, p. 72-73.&lt;/ref&gt; conversions in the 12th century under the [[Almohad]] dynasty of North Africa and [[al-Andalus|Andalusia]], as well as in [[Persia]] under the [[Safavid]] dynasty where [[Sunni]]s were converted to [[Shi'ism]]&lt;ref name="conseq" /&gt; and Jews were converted to Islam.&lt;ref name="JadidAlIslam"&gt;{{cite web|author=Jaleh Pirnazar |url=http://www.fis-iran.org/en/irannameh/volxix/mashhad-jewish-community |title=The "Jadid al-Islams" of Mashhad &amp;#124; Foundation for Iranian Studies |publisher=Fis-iran.org |date= |accessdate=2012-11-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; A form of forced conversion became institutionalized during the [[Ottoman Empire]] in the practice of [[devşirme]], a human levy in which Christian boys were seized and collected from their families (usually in the Balkans), enslaved, converted to Islam, and then trained for high ranking service to the sultan.&lt;ref&gt;'''Conversion''', Tijana Krstić, ''Encyclopedia of the Ottoman Empire'', Ed. Gábor Ágoston and Bruce Alan Masters, (InfoBase Publishing, 2009), 145-146;"''As a part of their education, devşirme children underwent compulsory conversion to Islam, which is the only documented forced form of conversion organized by the Ottoman state.''".&lt;/ref&gt;

There is dispute amongst scholars as to whether the famous Jewish philosopher [[Maimonides]] converted to Islam in order to freely escape from Almohad territory, and then reconverted back to Judaism in either the Levant or in Egypt.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nysun.com/arts/the-great-rambam-joel-kramers-maimonides/86437/ |title=The Great Rambam: Joel Kraemer's 'Maimonides' - The New York Sun |publisher=Nysun.com |date=2008-09-24 |accessdate=2012-11-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; Maimonides wrote a book on [[apostasy]] wherein he advocated accepting forced conversion rather than suffer martydom, and to then seek refuge afterward at a place where it was safe. The dispute also extended to the allegedly forced conversion of [[Sabbatai Zevi]], an Ottoman Jew from Smyrna. In reality, at the beginning of 1666, the [[Ottoman Sultan]] in [[Constantinople]] ordered Sabbatai, who had many followers and had claimed to be the long-awaited [[Jewish messiah]], to be imprisoned. When Sabbatai was later taken to Adrianople, the Sultan's physician, a former Jew, advised him to convert to Islam. The following day he converted before the Sultan, who happily rewarded Sabbatai by conferring the title (Mahmed) ''Effendi'', and appointing him as his doorkeeper with a high salary. A number of Sabbatai's followers also went over to Islam and about 300 families converted and were known as dönmeh (converts).&lt;ref name="tnr.com"&gt;[http://www.tnr.com/book/review/the-other-secret-jews?utm_source=TNR+Books+%26+Arts&amp;utm_campaign=4866964be0-TNR_BA_021810&amp;utm_medium=email Adam Kirsch, "The Other Secret Jews", review of Marc David Baer, ''The Dönme: Jewish Converts, Muslim Revolutionaries, and Secular Turks''], ''The New Republic'', 15 Feb 2010, accessed 20 Feb 2010&lt;/ref&gt; The sultan's officials ordered Sabbatai to take an additional wife to demonstrate his conversion.

Mughal ruler [[Aurangzeb]] cherished the ambition of converting India into a land of [[Islam]]. For this, he encouraged forced religious conversions and destroyed thousands of Hindu temples during his reign.&lt;ref name="bb3"&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/religion/religions/islam/history/mughalempire_1.shtml#h5] Intolerant ruler: Aurangzeb (bbc.co.uk)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="bbc6"&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/religion/religions/sikhism/people/teghbahadur.shtml] Guru Tegh Bahadur (BBC.CO.UK)&lt;/ref&gt; 

During the [[Moplah Riots]] of 1921 in [[Kerala]], Muslim [[Mappila]]s forcibly converted thousands of Hindus to Islam&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | title = Hindu culture during and after Muslim rule: survival and subsequent challenges| publisher = M.D. Publications Pvt. Ltd.| year = 1994| page = 103| url = http://books.google.co.in/books?id=wVr_f_gXOX4C&amp;pg=PA103| isbn = 978-81-85880-26-6}}&lt;/ref&gt; and killed all those who refused to apostatise.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
 | last = Besant
 | first = Annie
 | authorlink = Annie Besant
 | title = The Future Of Indian Politics: A Contribution To The Understanding Of Present-Day Problems P252
 | publisher = Kessinger Publishing, LLC
 | isbn = 1-4286-2605-0
 }}&lt;/ref&gt; During the [[Noakhali genocide]] of [[Hindu]]s in 1946, several thousand Hindus were forcibly converted to Islam by Muslim mobs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Fatal flaw in communal violence bill |author= |url=http://www.rediff.com/news/column/fatal-flaw-in-communal-violence-bill/20110602.htm |newspaper=Rediff.com |date=2 July 2011 |accessdate=2 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="makhan"&gt;{{cite book |title=Islamic Jihad: A Legacy of Forced Conversion, Imperialism and Slavery |last=Khan |first=M.A. |year=2009 |publisher=iUniverse |location=Bloomington |isbn=978-1-4401-1846-3 |page=232}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[1998 Prankote massacre]], 26 Kashmiri Hindus were beheaded by Islamist militants after their denial of converting into Islam. The militants struck when the villagers refused demands from the gunmen to convert to Islam and prove their conversion by eating beef.&lt;ref name="jk9"&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/1998/06/20/world/gunmen-kill-25-hindus-in-kashmir-attacks.html] 26 Hindus beheeaded by Islamist militants in Kashmir&lt;/ref&gt;

==Twenty-first century allegations==

===Buddhism===
Forced conversion is not permitted in Buddhism and is rarely if ever attempted for religious reasons. However, in Burma in recent years the military dictatorship has strongly encouraged the conversion of ethnic minorities, often by force, as part of its campaign of assimilation.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.co.in/books?id=O3KwXCBdE_kC&amp;pg=PA120 Burma at the turn of the twenty-first century p.120] Monique Skidmore&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://books.google.co.in/books?id=-bm19c5kqrMC&amp;pg=PA29 |title=Buddhism: Webster's Quotations, Facts and Phrases - Google Books |publisher=Books.google.co.in |date= |accessdate=2012-11-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A Christian aid group revealed that students from Myanmar's Chin ethic minority were being forced to shave their heads and convert to Buddhism, despite the president's insistence that religious freedom is protected in the South Asian nation.{{citation needed|date=September 2012}}&lt;ref name="christianpost.com"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.christianpost.com/news/christian-students-in-myanmar-forced-to-shave-heads-convert-to-buddhism-81211/ |title=Christian Students in Myanmar Forced to Shave Heads, Convert to Buddhism |publisher=Christianpost.com |date=2012-09-06 |accessdate=2012-11-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

"President Thein Sein's government claims that religious freedom is protected by law but in reality Buddhism is treated as the de facto state religion," said Salai Ling, Program Director of the Chin Human Rights Organization (CHRO).&lt;ref name="christianpost.com"/&gt;

Richard Chilvers reports on the human rights abuses committed against Christians by the Burmese junta, that children from Christian families in Burma between the ages of five and 10 have been lured from their homes and placed in Buddhist monasteries. Their heads are shaved and they are trained as novice monks, never to see their parents again.{{citation needed|date=September 2012}}&lt;ref name="archive.catholicherald.co.uk"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://archive.catholicherald.co.uk/article/9th-april-2004/5/christian-children-forced-to-convert-to-buddhism-i |title=Christian Children Forced To Convert To Buddhism In Burma - from the Catholic Herald Archive |publisher=Archive.catholicherald.co.uk |date= |accessdate=2012-11-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In a visit to Chin and Kachin refugees in New Delhi and Mizoram State, India, Christian Solidarity Worldwide (CSW) heard accounts of cultural genocide and religious persecution and discrimination.{{citation needed|date=September 2012}}&lt;ref name="archive.catholicherald.co.uk"/&gt;

Burmese forces offer incentives to impoverished villagers to convert from Christianity to Buddhism in Chin state, an area which is 90 per cent Christian.&lt;ref name="archive.catholicherald.co.uk"/&gt;

From 2002-2004, extremist Buddhists have attacked at least 160 churches in [[Sri Lanka]]. An estimated 140 churches have closed as a result of violence and intimidation, and in some places Christians are forced to worship in secret — in the middle of the night — for fear of being discovered and attacked.Many of the incidents of anti-Christian violence have been incited by monks, and in some places the monks have themselves beaten up pastors. Nagarajah Solomon leads a church outside [[Kandy]], in the center of the country. Last year a Buddhist monk led a mob of 15 people to capture two church workers and take them to the temple. The Christians were locked up for several hours in the temple, where six monks beat them with fists and sticks. Then the monks summoned more than 200 villagers to announce that these Christians were destroying the community and their culture. When Pastor Solomon arrived at the temple to plead for the release of his church workers, he too was locked up and interrogated by the monks, with the angry mob waiting outside. "They asked me to instruct my congregation to come to the temple, renounce their Christian faith and return to Buddhism," Pastor Solomon told me. "But I told them I could not do that. Their faith was a matter for them. At that, the monks continued to beat me." Finally, the monks brought the pastor out to the assembled crowd, and told the people: "These are fundamentalists. You should not tolerate them. You should immediately attack them."&lt;ref name="catholicculture.org"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.catholicculture.org/culture/library/view.cfm?recnum=6395 |title=Library : Buddha's Fist |publisher=Catholic Culture |date= |accessdate=2012-11-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some of the attacks are not only violent and destructive but deliberately crude and insulting as well. In one village in southern Sri Lanka, a church was burned down, and when the congregation moved to another building, local Buddhists, incited by a monk, threw buckets of human excrement at the house and then doused it with engine oil. In another village, a mob of 30 drunken Buddhists attacked a church, assaulted the church workers, attempted to rape three Christian women, and then dragged them off through the streets, claiming they had captured some prostitutes working in a brothel. In the first week of November, a pastor's family was attacked, his wife beaten, and his furniture, documents, and books burned. The attackers then took a sword and cut off the long hair of the pastor's wife — a deliberate act of humiliation.&lt;ref name="catholicculture.org"/&gt;

===Christianity===
The [[Baptist]] Church of Tripura is alleged to have supplied the [[NLFT]] with arms and financial support and to have encouraged the murder of Hindus, particularly infants, as a means to depopulate the region of all Hindus.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | first =Subhir | last =Bhaumik |title = 'Church backing Tripura rebels'| url =http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/south_asia/717775.stm | publisher =BBC News |accessdate =2006-08-26  | date=April 18, 2000}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2009, the Assam Times reported that about fifteen armed [[Hmar people|Hmar]] militants, members of Manmasi National Christian Army, tried to force Hindu residents of Bhuvan Pahar, [[Assam]] to convert to Christianity.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.assamtimes.org/social/3112.html Christianity threat looms over Bhuvan Pahar] Assam Times - June 23, 2009&lt;/ref&gt; A Few Christian evangelists in India have been accused forced conversion of Hindus, and some of them have been jailed for forcefully converting.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bosnewslife.com/12022-india-pastor-jailed-for-converting-hindus India Pastor Jailed For Converting Hindus, Corpse Exhumed]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.persecution.org/suffering/newsdetail.php?newscode=8289 Indian couple detained on forced conversion charges]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Bernard Blasius Moras|Archbishop Moras]], refuting these allegation of forced conversions and the charges of conversions against the Christian missionaries, said ''"We do not believe in forced conversions"'' ''"It is easy to charge people with wrong allegations but difficult to stop evil powers that are working against Christians"''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://mangalorean.com/news.php?newstype=broadcast&amp;broadcastid=98889 Satisfied with govt action- Archbishop Moras]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Hinduism===
Indian Christians have alleged that "radical Hindu groups" in [[Orissa]], India have forced Christian converts from Hinduism to "revert"&lt;ref name="revert"&gt;the word ''revert'' is used in this context; not ''convert''; see [http://www.jstor.org/stable/4413900 Older than the Church: Christianity and Caste in The God of Small Things India] by A sekhar;[http://www.washingtontimes.com/news/2010/mar/11/proselytism-on-the-table Washington post article]&lt;/ref&gt; to Hinduism. These "religious riots" were largely between two tribal groups in [[Orissa]], one of which was predominantly Hindu and another predominantly Christian, over the [[Murder of Swami Lakshmanananda|assassination]] of a Hindu leader named [[Swami Lakshmanananda]] by Christian [[Maoists]] operating as terrorist groups in India (see [[Naxalite]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hindujagruti.org/news/5576.html |title=We killed Swami Laxmananda: Christian Maoist leader - Attack |publisher=hindujagruti.org |date=2008-10-06 |accessdate=2012-11-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the aftermath of the violence, American Christian evangelical groups have claimed that Hindu groups are "forcibly reverting" Christians converts from Hinduism back to Hinduism.&lt;ref name="revert" /&gt; However, some local Christian groups have dismissed these allegations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url= http://news.rediff.com/report/2009/aug/14/orissa-christian-leaders-disagree-with-us-report.htm|title= Orissa: Christian leaders disagree with US panel's report|date= 2009-08-14|publisher=Rediff News}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Father Jebamalai told UCA News the "induced and forced" conversion of 2000 tribal Christians in [[Gujarat]] was aimed at creating "a sense of fear among Christians and prevent missioners from working in the area".{{citation needed|date=September 2012}}Christian leaders in the state say that Hindu radicals fear tribal and lower-caste people receiving an education because it may lead them not only to stop slaving for upper-caste Hindus but also to question the idea of high-caste superiority.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.christiantoday.com/article/hindu.extremists.convert.2000.christians.in.india/15965.htm |title=Hindu extremists convert 2,000 Christians in India &amp;#124; Christian News on Christian Today |publisher=Christiantoday.com |date=2008-01-03 |accessdate=2012-11-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some 40 Hindu radicals attacked some Tribal Christian Rabha in the village of Deuphani ([[Assam]]). After showering them with insults, death threats and beatings, they forced the victims to abjure their Christian faith.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Gheddo |first=Piero |url=http://www.asianews.it/news-en/Assam:-tribal-Christians-beaten-and-forced-to-convert-to-Hinduism-25003.html |title=INDIA Assam: tribal Christians beaten and forced to convert to Hinduism - Asia News |publisher=Asianews.it |date= |accessdate=2012-11-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Nandapeda is the only village with majority Muslim population in the Dangs district, considered the poorest district in the whole of India. The government has been pressurizing the Muslims to convert to the Hindu religion or face eviction from their land. Some of the residents of this village moved the Gujarat High Court against the government's pressure of converting and changing their religion. The families have been living in the village for over 100 years. On June 13, 2008 a senior officer had called a meeting in [[Ahwa]] and asked them to change their religion or vacate the land.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.countercurrents.org/hashmi170908.htm |title=Forced Conversion In Gujarat By Shabnam Hashmi |publisher=Countercurrents.org |date= |accessdate=2012-11-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Islam===

====Indonesia====
In 2001 the [[Indonesia]]n army evacuated hundreds of Christian refugees from the remote [[Kesui]] and [[Teor]] islands in [[Maluku (province)]] after the refugees stated that they had been forced to convert to Islam. According to reports, some of the men had been circumcised against their will, and a paramilitary group involved in the incident confirmed that circumcisions had taken place while denying any element of coercion.&lt;ref&gt;Maluku refugees allege forced circumcision, BBC News Online, Wednesday, 31 January 2001 [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/asia-pacific/1146224.stm]&lt;/ref&gt;

====Middle-East====
In 2004 [[Coptic Christian]]s in [[Egypt]] occupied the main Coptic cathedral in [[Cairo]] for several days, angry at the disappearance of a priest's wife in a village in the [[Nile delta]], who, they alleged, had been forced to convert to Islam. The [[BBC]] reported that allegations of forced conversions of Copts to Islam surface every year in Egypt.&lt;ref&gt;Heba Saleh (BBC News, Cairo), 'Conversion' sparks Copt protest. BBC News Online 9 December 2004.
[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/4080777.stm]&lt;/ref&gt;

Other notables among these have been the cases of Iraq's [[Mandaeans]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/6412453.stm Iraq's Mandaeans 'face extinction']&lt;/ref&gt; Egypt's [[Copt|Coptic Orthodox Christians]], Christians of Pakistan&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,273075,00.html Taliban Tells Pakistani Christians: Convert or Die]&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Assyrian Christians]] of Iraq&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.abc.net.au/rn/religionreport/stories/2007/1937124.htm Christian Minorities in the Islamic Middle East : Rosie Malek-Yonan on the Assyrians]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.iht.com/articles/2007/05/08/opinion/edisaac.php The assault on Assyrian Christians]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aina.org/news/20070518111715.htm Told to Convert or Die, 21 Assyrian Families Seek Shelter in Baghdad Churches]&lt;/ref&gt; who have faced coercion to convert to Islam.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/asia-pacific/1146224.stm | work=BBC News | title=Maluku refugees allege forced circumcision | date=2001-01-31 | accessdate=2010-05-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/4080777.stm 'Conversion' sparks Copt protest]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2006 two journalists of the Fox News Network had been kidnapped and forced to convert to Islam at gunpoint. After conversion they were made to read statements on videotape proclaiming that they had converted, after which they were released by their captors.&lt;ref&gt;[http://edition.cnn.com/2006/WORLD/meast/08/27/fox.journalists/index.html Kidnapped Fox journalists released]&lt;/ref&gt; 

There have been numerous reports of Islamic attempts to forcibly convert religious minorities in Iraq.  In Baghdad, Christians have been told to convert to Islam, pay the [[jizya]] or die.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aina.org/news/20070518111715.htm Told to Convert or Die, 21 Assyrian Families Seek Shelter in Baghdad Churches&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.iht.com/articles/2007/05/08/opinion/edisaac.php The assault on Assyrian Christians - International Herald Tribune&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.abc.net.au/rn/religionreport/stories/2007/1937124.htm The Religion Report - 30 May 2007 - Christian Minorities in the Islamic Middle East : Rosie Malek-Yonan on the Assyrians&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; In March 2007 the BBC reported that people in the [[Mandaean]] religious minority in [[Iraq]] alleged that they were being targeted by [[Islamist]] insurgents, who offered them the choice of conversion or death.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/6412453.stm BBC News on-line 7 March 2007]&lt;/ref&gt;

====India====
In Jammu &amp; Kashmir, the [[Ladakh Buddhist Association]] has said: "There is a deliberate and organised design to convert Kargil's Buddhists to Islam.  In the last four years, about 50 girls and married women with children were taken and converted from village Wakha alone.  If this continues unchecked, we fear that Buddhists will be wiped out from Kargil in the next two decades or so.  Anyone objecting to such allurement and conversions is harassed."&lt;ref&gt;Tundup Tsering and Tsewang Nurboo, in: ''Ladakh visited'', Pioneer, 4/12/1995.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tribuneindia.com/2000/20000113/j&amp;k.htm#2 ''The Tribune'', Chandigarh, India - Jammu &amp; Kashmir&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

====Pakistan====
Around 25 Hindu girls are abducted every month and converted to Islam forcibly in Pakistan, as reported by Pakistani media.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thenews.com.pk/TodaysPrintDetail.aspx?ID=231616&amp;Cat=4&amp;dt=3/31/2010] 25 Hindu girls abducted every month, claims HRCP official] The News, Tuesday, March 30, 2010&lt;/ref&gt; In May 2007, members of the Christian community of [[Charsadda]] in the [[Khyber Pakhtunkhwa|North West Frontier Province]] of Pakistan, close to the border of [[Afghanistan]], reported that they had received letters threatening bombings if they did not convert to Islam, and that the police were not taking their fears seriously.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,273075,00.html Report on Fox News, from AP]&lt;/ref&gt;  In June 2009, [[International Christian Concern]] (ICC) reported the rape and killing of a Christian man in Pakistan, for refusing to convert to Islam.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,526126,00.html |title=Christian Man Raped, Murdered for Refusing to Convert to Islam, Family Says |publisher=FOX News |date=June 13, 2009 |author=Nora Zimmett|accessdate=June 11, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Rinkle Kumari, a 19&amp;nbsp;year Pakistani student, Dr. Lata Kumari, and Asha Kumari, a Hindu working in a beauty parlor, were allegedly forced to convert from Hindu to Islam.&lt;ref name="fridaytimesrinkle"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thefridaytimes.com/beta2/tft/article.php?issue=20120413&amp;page=9 |title=Opinion: Rinkle Kumari - the new Marvi of Sindh by Marvi Sirmed |publisher=Thefridaytimes.com |date= |accessdate=2012-06-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://pakobserver.net/detailnews.asp?id=151043 |title=SC orders release of Rinkal Kumari, others |publisher=Pakobserver.net |date= |accessdate=2012-06-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; Their cases were appealed all the way to the [[Supreme Court of Pakistan]] where they said that they wanted to live with their parents and not their 'so called' husbands.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dailytimes.com.pk/default.asp?page=2012\04\19\story_19-4-2012_pg7_3 |title=Leading News Resource of Pakistan |publisher=Daily Times |date=2012-04-19 |accessdate=2012-06-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; The court issued a verdict that they had decided to stay with her husband.

====Somalia====
In August 2009, ICC reported that four Christians working to help orphans in Somalia were beheaded by Islamist extremists when they refused to convert to Islam.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,539129,00.html |title=Al Shabaab Reportedly Beheads 4 Christians, Rips Gold Teeth From Locals' Mouths |publisher=FOX News |date=August 12, 2009 |author= |accessdate=June 11, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[State atheism]]
* [[Coercion]]
* [[Covenant of Umar I]]
* [[Crypto-Paganism]]
* [[Religious conversion]]
* [[Religious intolerance]]

==References==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

{{Religious persecution}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Forced Conversion}}
[[Category:Religious persecution]]
[[Category:Religious conversion]]
[[Category:Persecution]]

[[ja:強制改宗]]
[[ru:Принудительное обращение]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>