<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20131026174737|578848498" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="7079135" pageid="7079135" ns="0" title="Forced conversion"><revisions><rev timestamp="2013-11-20T05:00:44Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Use mdy dates|date=March 2013}}
A '''forced conversion''' is the [[religious conversion]] or acceptance of a philosophy against the will of the subject, often with the threatened consequence of earthly penalties or harm. These consequences range from job loss and social isolation to incarceration, torture or death. It is a form of [[religious cleansing]]. 

== Christianity==
{{see also|Christianization}}

===End of Roman empire===
Forced conversion was a major way for the [[Christianization]] of the [[Roman Empire]]. In 392 Emperor [[Theodosius I]] decreed that Christianity was the only legal religion of the Roman Empire, and forbidding pagan practices by law:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
It is Our will that all the peoples who are ruled by the administration of Our Clemency shall practice that religion which the divine Peter the Apostle transmitted to the Romans....The rest, whom We adjudge demented and insane, shall sustain the infamy of heretical dogmas, their meeting places shall not receive the name of churches, and they shall be smitten first by divine vengeance and secondly by the retribution of Our own initiative''" ([[Codex Theodosianus]] XVI 1.2.).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://penelope.uchicago.edu/~grout/encyclopaedia_romana/greece/paganism/paganism.html |title=Paganism and Rome |publisher=Penelope.uchicago.edu |date= |accessdate=2012-11-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

===Medieval era===
During the [[Saxon Wars]], [[Charlemagne]], [[King of the Franks]], forcibly Roman Catholicized the [[Saxons]] from their native [[Germanic paganism]] by way of warfare and law upon conquest. Examples include the [[Massacre of Verden]] in 782, during which Charlemagne reportedly had 4,500 captive Saxons massacred upon rebelling against conversion, and the ''[[Capitulatio de partibus Saxoniae]]'', a law imposed on conquered Saxons in 785 which prescribes death to those that refuse to convert to Christianity.&lt;ref name="CHARLEMAGNE"&gt;For the Massacre of Verden, see Barbero, Alessandro (2004). ''Charlemagne: Father of a Continent'', page 46. [[University of California Press]]. For the ''Capitulatio de partibus Saxoniae'', see Riché, Pierre (1993). ''The Carolingians''. [[University of Pennsylvania Press]]. ISBN 978-0-8122-1342-3.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Pope Innocent III]] pronounced in 1201 that even if torture and intimidation had been employed in receiving the sacrament, one nevertheless:
&lt;blockquote&gt;...does receive the impress of Christianity and may be forced to observe the Christian Faith as one who expressed a conditional willingness though, absolutely speaking, he was unwilling. ... [For] the grace of Baptism had been received, and they had been [[confirmation (sacrament)|anointed with the sacred oil]], and had [[eucharist|participated in the body of the Lord]], they might properly be forced to hold to the faith which they had accepted perforce, lest the name of the Lord be blasphemed, and lest they hold in contempt and consider vile the faith they had joined.&lt;ref&gt;Grayzel, Solomon, ''The Church and the Jews in the Thirteenth Century'', rev. ed., New York: Hermon, 1966, p. 103&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

From ''The Crusades'', by Bernard Hamilton&lt;ref&gt;''The Crusades'', by Bernard Hamilton, 1998, Sutton Publishing, United Kingdom, Chapter 9: Later Crusades, p. 87.&lt;/ref&gt;   “In 1309 the [[Teutonic Order]] moved its headquarters to Marienburg in Prussia.  It had a papal license to wage perpetual war against the pagans and used this to launch annual crusades against [[Lithuania]].  These expeditions were very popular with the nobility of northern Europe: campaigns were held twice a year, in the summer and in the winter when the order laid on special Christmas festivities for visiting crusaders.” “The excuse for men who enjoyed fighting and to lay waste large parts of Lithuania in the name of Christ was removed in 1386 when the [[King of Lithuania]], [[Jagiello]], married [[Queen Jadwiga of Poland]] and received Catholic baptism.  The two kingdoms were united under Christian rulers and the Teutonic Knights no longer had any justification for crusading against pagans there.”

===Spanish Inquisition===
After the end of the [[Al-Andalus|Islamic control of Spain]], Muslims and Jews were murdered and expelled from Spain in 1492 and from Portugal in 1497.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.home.earthlink.net/~benven/annivers.html 500 ANNIVERSARY OF THE FORCED CONVERSION OF THE JEWS OF PORTUGAL&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; After the [[Reconquista]], so called "[[New Christian]]s" were those inhabitants ([[Sephardi]]c Jews or [[Mudéjar]] Muslims) during the Middle Ages and the Early Modern Era who were baptized under coercion and in the face of murder, becoming forced converts from Islam ([[Morisco]]s, [[Converso]]s and ''secret Moors'') and forced converts from [[Judaism]] ([[Converso]]s, [[Crypto-Judaism|Crypto-Jews]] and [[Marrano]]s). 
Then the [[Spanish Inquisition]] targeted primarily forced converts from Judaism who came under suspicion of either continuing to adhere to their old religion or of having fallen back into it. Jewish conversos still resided in Spain and often hiddenly (cryptically) practiced Judaism and were suspected by the "Old Christians" of being [[Crypto-Jew]]s. The Spanish Inquisition generated much wealth and income for the church and individual inquisitors by confiscating the property of the persecutees or selling them into slavery. The end of the [[Al-Andalus]] and the expulsion of the Sephardic Jews from the Iberian Peninsula went hand in hand with the increase of Spanish-Portugal influence in the world, as exemplified in the Christian conquest of the Americas and their aboriginal Indian population. The Ottoman empire, the Netherlands, and the New World absorbed much of the Jewish refugees.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thejerusalemconnection.us/news-archive/tag/inquisition 3000 Years of Sephardic History] Jerusalem Connection Writers Archives&lt;/ref&gt;

===Goa Inquisition===
Religious persecution took place by the Portuguese in [[Goa]], India from 16th to the 17th century. The natives of Goa, most of them Hindus were subjected to [[Goa Inquisition|severe torture and oppression]] by the zealous Portuguese rulers and missionaries and forcibly converted to Christianity.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.co.in/books?id=RS1uAAAAMAAJ Of umbrellas, goddesses, and dreams: essays on Goan culture and society] Robert Samuel Newman, 2001&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[The Goa Inquisition (book)|The Goa Inquisition, Being a Quatercentenary Commemoration Study of the Inquisition in India]] by Anant Priolkar, Bombay University Press&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.co.in/books?id=hSnn_kDUI6AC&amp;pg=PA69 Everyday Nationalism: Women of the Hindu Right in India] Kalyani Devaki Menon, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.co.in/books?id=ftS1AAAAIAAJ Journal of the Asiatic Society of Bombay] 1967&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;M. D. David (ed.), Western Colonialism in Asia and Christianity, Bombay, 1988, p.17&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.co.in/books?id=INWSqBXundYC&amp;pg=PA137 Between ethnography and fiction: Verrier Elwin and the tribal question in India] Tanka Bahadur Subba, Sujit Som, K. C. Baral, North Eastern Hill University. Dept. of Anthropology – Social Science&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1567, the campaign of destroying temples in Bardez met with success. At the end of it 300 Hindu temples were destroyed. Enacting laws, prohibition was laid from December 4, 1567 on rituals of Hindu marriages, sacred thread wearing and cremation. All the persons above 15 years of age were compelled to listen to Christian preaching, failing which they were punished. In 1583 Hindu temples at Assolna and Cuncolim were destroyed through army action. The fathers of the Church forbade the Hindus under terrible penalties the use of their own sacred books, and prevented them from all exercise of their religion. They destroyed their temples, and so harassed and interfered with the people that they abandoned the city in large numbers, refusing to remain any longer in a place where they had no liberty, and were liable to imprisonment, torture and death if they worshipped after their own fashion the gods of their fathers." wrote Filippo Sassetti, who was in India from 1578 to 1588. An order was issued in June 1684 for suppressing the Konkani language and making it compulsory to speak the Portuguese language. The law provided for dealing toughly with anyone using the local language. Following that law all the non-Christian cultural symbols and the books written in local languages were sought to be destroyed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.scribd.com/doc/28411503/Goa-Inquisition-for-Colonial-Disciplining |title=Goa Inquisition for Colonial Disciplining |publisher=Scribd.com |date=2010-03-15 |accessdate=2012-11-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Methods such as repressive laws, demolition of temples and mosques, destruction of holy books, fines and the forcible conversion of orphans were used.&lt;ref&gt;Mascarenhas-Keyes, Stella (1979), Goans in London: portrait of a Catholic Asian community, Goan Association (U.K.)&lt;/ref&gt;

===Native American Boarding Schools===
The government paid religious societies to provide education to Native American children on reservations. In the late 19th and early 20th centuries, the [[Bureau of Indian Affairs]] (BIA) founded additional boarding schools based on the assimilation model of the [[Carlisle Indian Industrial School]].
 
Children were usually immersed in European-American culture through appearance changes with haircuts, were forbidden to speak their native languages, and traditional names were replaced by new European-American names. The experience of the schools was often harsh, especially for the younger children who were separated from their families. In numerous ways, they were encouraged or forced to abandon their Native American identities and cultures.&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20050829051045/http://sacbee.com/static/archive/news/projects/native/day2_main.html "Long-suffering urban Indians find roots in ancient rituals". California's Lost Tribes] Archived from the original on August 29, 2005. Retrieved February 8, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; The number of Native American children in the boarding schools reached a peak in the 1970s, with an estimated enrollment of 60,000 in 1973. Especially through investigations of the later twentieth century, there have been many documented cases of sexual, physical and mental abuse occurring at such schools.&lt;ref&gt;"Developmental and learning disabilities". PRSP Disabilities. Retrieved February 8, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.amnestyusa.org/news/newsletter"Soul Wound: The Legacy of Native American Schools". Amnesty International USA. Retrieved February 8, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; Since those years, tribal nations have increasingly insisted on community-based schools and have also founded numerous tribally controlled colleges. Community schools have also been supported by the federal government through the BIA and legislation. The largest boarding schools have closed. In some cases, reservations or tribes were too small or poor to support independent schools and still wanted an alternative for their children, especially for high school. By 2007, the number of Native American children in boarding schools had declined to 9,500.

==Judaism==

Forced conversions are rare, but are reported to have happened under the [[Hasmonean dynasty|Hasmonean Empire]]. The Idumaens were forced to convert to Judaism, (either by threats of exile, or threats of death, depending on the source.)&lt;ref&gt;Flavius Josephus Antiquities 13.257–258&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Aristobulus I|Aristobulus]]&lt;/ref&gt; 
In Eusebíus, Christianity, and Judaism  Harold W. Attridge  claims that “there is reason to think that Josephus’ account of their conversion is substantially accurate.”  He also writes, “That these were not isolated instances but that forced conversion was a national policy is clear from the fact that Alexander Jannaeus (ca 80 BCE) demolished the city of Pella in Moab, “because the inhabitants would not agree to adopt the national custom of the Jews.”  Josephus, Antiquities. 13.15.4, 397&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |url=http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=jVyzbHAJ_hAC&amp;pg=PA374&amp;dq=Ituraeans+forced+conversion&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=dNUATu3BAciv8QORmPTHDQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=2&amp;ved=0CC4Q6AEwATgK#v=onepage&amp;q=Ituraeans%20forced%20conversion&amp;f=false |accessdate=2011-06-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Maurice Sartre has written of the "policy of forced Judaization adopted by [[John Hyrcanus|Hyrcanos]], [[Aristobulus I]] and [[Jannaeus]]”, who offered "the conquered peoples a choice between expulsion or conversion,”&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |url=http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=9y7nTpFcN3AC&amp;pg=PA15&amp;lpg=PA15&amp;dq=Ituraeans+forced+conversion&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=hxTELYx1Vd&amp;sig=_EhvKuhvcja0F7ZTkGcW6ET6nG8&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=lMwATsfQOcmn8QO41syeDQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=7&amp;ved=0CD8Q6AEwBg#v=onepage&amp;q=Ituraeans%20forced%20conversion&amp;f=false |accessdate=2011-06-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

And in 'The early Roman period, Volume 2', William David Davies has written that. “The evidence is best explained by postulating that an existing small Jewish population in Lower Galilee was massively expanded by the forced conversion in c.104 BCE of their Gentile neighbours in the north.”&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |url=http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=MA-4VX5gWS4C&amp;pg=PA599&amp;dq=Ituraeans+forced+conversion&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=f9MATobdEMiW8QPYpqyTDQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=6&amp;ved=0CEMQ6AEwBQ#v=onepage&amp;q=Ituraeans%20forced%20conversion&amp;f=false |accessdate=2011-06-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Islam==
{{See also|Islamization|Safavid conversion of Iran from Sunnism to Shiism}}

Many scholars have argued that early Islamic scripture and law forbids forced conversion,&lt;ref name="W53"&gt;Waines (2003) "An Introduction to Islam" ''Cambridge University Press''. p. 53&lt;/ref&gt; while other scholars contest this claim with historical examples.&lt;ref&gt;Klein, Martin A. "Social and economic factors in the Muslim revolution in Senegambia." Journal of African History 13.3 (1972): 419-441&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Rodney Stark (2001) "One True God: Historical Consequences of Monotheism, Princeton University Press&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Arzi, Donna E. "Role of Compulsion in Islamic Conversion: Jihad, Dhimma and Ridda, The." Buff. Hum. Rts. L. Rev. 8 (2002): 15&lt;/ref&gt;

One particular  verse of the [[Qur'an]] ({{cite quran|2|256|expand=no|style=nosup}}) is frequently cited, reading "let there be no compulsion in religion".&lt;ref&gt;Sir Thomas W. Arnold, ''The Preaching of Islam''{{page needed|date=November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Marshall G. Hodgson, ''The Venture of Islam''{{page needed|date=November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Albert Hourani, ''A History of the Arab Peoples''{{page needed|date=November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Ira Lapidus, ''History of Islamic Societies''{{page needed|date=November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;L.S. Starorianos, ''A Global History, the Human Heritage''{{page needed|date=November 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another cited verse of the Qur'an ({{cite quran|9|5|expand=no|style=nosup}}), reads "And when the sacred months have passed, then kill the polytheists (pagan) wherever you find them and capture them and besiege them and sit in wait for them at every place of ambush. But if they should repent, establish prayer, and give zakah, let them go on their way."&lt;ref&gt;http://quran.com/9/5 Qur'an Surat At-Tawbah&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;London, Herbert. "Fighting a War for Survival." Temp. Pol. &amp; Civ. Rts. L. Rev. 14 (2004): 385&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Safa, Reza F. "Winning Souls." Islam and Christianity: A Revealing Contrast (2009): 263-265&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Alawneh, Shafiq Falah. "Human motivation: an Islamic perspective." American Journal of Islamic Social Sciences 15.4 (1998): 19-39&lt;/ref&gt;

Some scholars suggest Muhammed and his followers never practiced forced conversion of the Pagan Arabs during Muhammad's conquest of Arabia.&lt;ref&gt;Haykal, M.H. (1933) The Life of Muhammad, translated by Isma'il Razi A. al-Faruqi. The Supreme Council of Islamic Affairs, Cairo, Egypt &amp; the University of Chicago.&lt;/ref&gt;{{Failed verification|date=July 2013}}{{Page needed|date=July 2013}}&lt;ref&gt;Husayn, M.J. – Biography Of Imam `Ali Ibn Abi-Talib, Translation of Sirat Amir Al-Mu'minin, Translated By: Sayyid Tahir Bilgrami, Ansariyan Publications, Qum, Islamic Republic of Iran&lt;/ref&gt; Other scholars, point to sunnah, described in multiple [[Hadith]], which suggest use of violence by Muhammed and his followers to achieve forced religious conversion. [[Sahih al-Bukhari]], for example, describes Muhammed asking his followers, "fight against the people until they testify that none has the right to be worshipped but Allah and that Muhammad is Allah's Apostle, and offer the prayers perfectly and give the obligatory charity, so if they perform that, then they save their lives and property from me except for Islamic laws and then their reckoning (accounts) will be done by Allah."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usc.edu/org/cmje/religious-texts/hadith/bukhari/002-sbt.php#001.002.025 University of Southern California translation of the hadith, Sahih al-Bukhari, Book 2]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Khan, M. Muhsin. Sahih Bukhari. Peace Vision, 1986; see Ibn 'Umar at Volume 1, Book 2, Number 24&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Ahmedov, Aibek. "Religious Minorities and Apostasy in Early Islamic States: Legal and Historical Analysis of Sources." J. Islamic St. Prac. Int'l L. 2 (2006): 1.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Al-Hilali, Muhammad Taqi-ud-Din, and Muhammad Muhsin Khan. Translation of the Meanings of the Noble Quran in the English Language. IslamKotob, 2009; see page 40, translation at footnote 3.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Sahih Muslim]] similarly, in Book 19, describes Muhammed asking his followers, "You see the ruffians and the lowly followers of the (pagan) Quraish. And he indicated by striking one of his hands over the other that they should be killed."&lt;ref&gt;{{Hadith-usc|usc=yes|muslim|19|4395}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hadithcollection.com/sahihmuslim/147-Sahih%20Muslim%20Book%2019.%20Jihad%20and%20Expedition/12706-sahih-muslim-book-019-hadith-number-4395.html Sahih Muslim Book 019, Hadith Number 4395, Jihad and Expedition]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Mogler, Christian. The Rise of Islam: How could this small religious movement become within centuries the dominant religion of the Mediterranean, and why was Christianity not able to stop it. GRIN Verlag, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

Historians suggest that forced conversions have occurred during Islamic history.&lt;ref name="W53"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hourani, Albert (2010), ''A History of the Arab Peoples: Updated Edition'', Faber &amp; Faber, ISBN 978-0674058194&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Khan, M.A. (2009), ''Islamic Jihad: A Legacy of Forced Conversion, Imperialism, and Slavery'', iUniverse, ISBN 978-1440118463&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Robinson, Francis, ed. (1996) The Cambridge illustrated history of the Islamic world. Cambridge University Press, ISBN 978-0521669931&lt;/ref&gt; Noted cases include the conversion of [[Samaritan]]s to Islam at the hands of the rebel Ibn Firāsa,&lt;ref&gt;M. Levy-Rubin,  "New evidence relating to the process of Islamization in Palestine in the Early Muslim Period – The Case of Samaria", in: ''Journal of the Economic and Social History of the Orient'', 43 (3), p. 257-276, 2000, [[Springer Science+Business Media|Springer]]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Fattal, A.(1958) ''Le statut légal des non-Musulman en pays d'Islam'', Beyrouth: Imprimerie Catholique, p. 72-73.&lt;/ref&gt; conversions in the 12th century under the [[Almohad]] dynasty of North Africa and [[al-Andalus|Andalusia]], as well as in [[Persia]] under the [[Safavid]] dynasty where [[Sunni]]s were converted to [[Shi'ism]]&lt;ref&gt;Lewis, Bernard (1984). The Jews of Islam. Princeton: Princeton University Press. ISBN 0-691-00807-8&lt;/ref&gt; and Jews were converted to Islam.&lt;ref name="JadidAlIslam"&gt;{{cite web|first=Jaleh |last=Pirnazar |url=http://www.fis-iran.org/en/irannameh/volxix/mashhad-jewish-community |title=The "Jadid al-Islams" of Mashhad |work=[http://fis-iran.org/en Foundation for Iranian Studies] |location=Bethesda, MD, USA |publisher=[[Foundation for Iranian Studies]] |accessdate=2012-11-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; A form of forced conversion became institutionalized during the [[Ottoman Empire]] in the practice of [[devşirme]], a human levy in which Christian boys were seized and collected from their families (usually in the Balkans), enslaved, converted to Islam, and then trained for high-ranking service to the sultan.&lt;ref&gt;'''Conversion''', Tijana Krstić, ''Encyclopedia of the Ottoman Empire'', Ed. Gábor Ágoston and Bruce Alan Masters, (InfoBase Publishing, 2009), 145–146;"''As a part of their education, devşirme children underwent compulsory conversion to Islam, which is the only documented forced form of conversion organized by the Ottoman state.''".&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Jizya]] (poll tax) was the most important factor in the mass conversion to Islam, the tax paid by all non-Muslims ([[Dhimmis]]) in Islamic empires.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ucalgary.ca/applied_history/tutor/islam/empires/ottoman/bosnia.html University of Calgary - The Islamisation of Bosnia, the fourth text paragraph]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="BBC"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Britannica"/&gt;&lt;ref name="mtholyoke"/&gt; In the 8th century, under administration of the [[Muslim conquest of Egypt|Muslim Arabs]], heavy taxation moves large numbers of [[Copts|Coptic Christians]] to convert to Islam in [[North Africa]].&lt;ref name="BBC"&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/worldservice/specials/1624_story_of_africa/page96.shtml BBC – Charting major events in Africa's history across millenia, ''717 – Heavy taxation moves large numbers of Coptic Christians to convert to Islam'']&lt;/ref&gt; And also with the [[Zoroastrians]] living under [[Muslim conquest of Persia|Muslim's rule]] in ancient [[Persia]],&lt;ref name="Britannica"&gt;"The Zoroastrians who remained in Persia (modern Iran) after the Arab–Muslim conquest (7th century CE) had a long history as outcasts. Although they purchased some toleration by paying the jizya (poll tax), not abolished until 1882, they were treated as an inferior race, had to wear distinctive garb, and were not allowed to ride horses or bear arms."[http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/223068/Gabar Gabars Gabars], [[Encyclopædia Britannica]]. 2007. Britannica Concise Encyclopedia. 29 May 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Arabs]] came to conquer [[Sindh]] under command of [[Muhammad bin Qasim]] in 711 CE. This was an easy task, as the people of Sindh had been practicing [[Buddhism]] and [[Hindu]] [[ahimsa]] (non-violence) for many years, and battle was sinful.&lt;ref&gt;Levy, Robert I. Mesocosm: Hinduism and the Organization of a Traditional Newar City in Nepal. Berkeley: University of California Press, c1990 1990.&lt;/ref&gt; The Arab Muslims quickly destroyed the Sindhi forts and conquered Sindh. Many Hindus chose to flee Sindh and move to [[Punjab]] and [[Kutch]].&lt;ref name="Mcleod"&gt;''McLeod, John, "The History of India", Greenwood Press (2002), ISBN 0-313-31459-4, pp. 41–42.&lt;/ref&gt; Those that stayed behind were asked to convert to Islam. For those that did not comply to this request, heavy taxes were levied on them and their properties were taken from them.&lt;ref name="mtholyoke"&gt;[http://www.mtholyoke.edu/~agha20e/polit116/musliminvasion.html Muslim Invasion]&lt;/ref&gt; 

There is dispute amongst scholars as to whether the famous Jewish philosopher [[Maimonides]] converted to Islam in order to freely escape from Almohad territory, and then reconverted back to Judaism in either the Levant or in Egypt.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nysun.com/arts/the-great-rambam-joel-kramers-maimonides/86437/ |title=The Great Rambam: Joel Kraemer's 'Maimonides' – The New York Sun |publisher=Nysun.com |date=2008-09-24 |accessdate=2012-11-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; Maimonides wrote a book on [[apostasy]] wherein he advocated accepting forced conversion rather than suffer martydom, and to then seek refuge afterward at a place where it was safe. The dispute also extended to the allegedly forced conversion of [[Sabbatai Zevi]], an Ottoman Jew from Smyrna. In reality, at the beginning of 1666, the [[Ottoman Sultan]] in [[Constantinople]] ordered Sabbatai, who had many followers and had claimed to be the long-awaited [[Jewish messiah]], to be imprisoned. When Sabbatai was later taken to Adrianople, the Sultan's physician, a former Jew, advised him to convert to Islam. The following day he converted before the Sultan, who happily rewarded Sabbatai by conferring the title (Mahmed) ''Effendi'', and appointing him as his doorkeeper with a high salary. A number of Sabbatai's followers also went over to Islam and about 300 families converted and were known as dönmeh (converts).&lt;ref name="tnr.com"&gt;[http://www.tnr.com/book/review/the-other-secret-jews?utm_source=TNR+Books+%26+Arts&amp;utm_campaign=4866964be0-TNR_BA_021810&amp;utm_medium=email Adam Kirsch, "The Other Secret Jews", review of Marc David Baer, ''The Dönme: Jewish Converts, Muslim Revolutionaries, and Secular Turks''], ''The New Republic'', Feb 15, 2010, accessed Feb 20, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

Mughal ruler [[Aurangzeb]] cherished the ambition of converting India into a land of Islam. For this, he encouraged forced religious conversions and destroyed thousands of Hindu temples during his reign.&lt;ref name="bb3"&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/religion/religions/islam/history/mughalempire_1.shtml#h5] Intolerant ruler: Aurangzeb (bbc.co.uk)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="bbc6"&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/religion/religions/sikhism/people/teghbahadur.shtml] Guru Tegh Bahadur (BBC.CO.UK)&lt;/ref&gt; During [[Tipu Sultan]]'s invasion of [[Malabar Coast|Malabar]] in the late 18th century, he forcefully converted over 400,000 Hindus to Islam.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | last = Goel| first = Sita| title = Tipu Sultan: villain or hero? : an anthology| publisher = Voice of India| year = 1993| page = 38| url = http://books.google.co.in/books?ei=TYMYTPfXCse0rAf8-62tCg| isbn = 978-81-85990-08-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | last = Sharma| first = Hari| title = The real Tipu: a brief history of Tipu Sultan| publisher = Rishi publications| year = 1991| page = 112| url = http://books.google.co.in/books?ei=TYMYTPfXCse0rAf8-62tCg}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | last = Purushottam | title = Must India go Islamic?| publisher = P.S. Yog| url = http://books.google.co.in/books?ei=TYMYTPfXCse0rAf8-62tCg&amp;ct=result&amp;id=MLvXAAAAMAAJ&amp;dq=tipu+hindu+malabar+4+lakh&amp;q=%22over+4+lakh+Hindus%22}}&lt;/ref&gt;
During the [[Moplah Riots]] of 1921 in [[Kerala]], Muslim [[Mappila]]s forcibly converted thousands of Hindus to Islam&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | title = Hindu culture during and after Muslim rule: survival and subsequent challenges| publisher = M.D. Publications Pvt. Ltd.| year = 1994| page = 103| url = http://books.google.co.in/books?id=wVr_f_gXOX4C&amp;pg=PA103| isbn = 978-81-85880-26-6}}&lt;/ref&gt; and killed all those who refused to apostatise.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
 | last = Besant
 | first = Annie
 | authorlink = Annie Besant
 | title = The Future Of Indian Politics: A Contribution To The Understanding Of Present-Day Problems P252
 | publisher = Kessinger Publishing, LLC
 | isbn = 1-4286-2605-0
 }}&lt;/ref&gt; During the [[Noakhali genocide]] of [[Hindu]]s in 1946, several thousand Hindus were forcibly converted to Islam by Muslim mobs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Fatal flaw in communal violence bill |author= |url=http://www.rediff.com/news/column/fatal-flaw-in-communal-violence-bill/20110602.htm |newspaper=Rediff.com |date=July 2, 2011 |accessdate=August 2, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="makhan"&gt;{{cite book |title=Islamic Jihad: A Legacy of Forced Conversion, Imperialism and Slavery |last=Khan |first=M.A. |year=2009 |publisher=iUniverse |location=Bloomington |isbn=978-1-4401-1846-3 |page=232}}&lt;/ref&gt;
In [[Bangladesh]], the [[International Crimes Tribunal (Bangladesh)|International Crimes Tribunal]] tried and convicted several leaders of the Islamic [[Razakars (Pakistan)|Razakar]] militias, as well as [[Bangladesh Jamaat-e-Islami]] ([[Delwar Hossain Sayeedi]]), of [[war crimes]] committed against Hindus during the [[1971 Bangladesh atrocities]]. The charges included forced conversion of [[Bengali Hindu]]s to Islam.&lt;ref&gt;
*{{cite news |title= Bangladesh Islamist's death sentence sparks deadly riots|author= Anis Ahmed|url=http://www.reuters.com/article/2013/02/28/us-bangladesh-tribunal-idUSBRE91R0AN20130228 |newspaper= [[Reuters]] |date= February 28, 2013 |accessdate=March 1, 2013}} 
*{{cite news |title= Clashes Kill 35 in Bangladesh After Islamist Sentenced to Hang|author1= [[Arun Devnath]] |author2= [[Andrew MacAskill]]|url= http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2013-02-28/bangladesh-sentences-islamist-leader-to-death-amid-dhaka-protest.html|newspaper=[[Bloomberg L.P.]] |date=March 1, 2013 |accessdate=March 1, 2013}} 
*{{cite news |title= Death Toll From Bangladesh Unrest Reaches 44 |author1= [[Julfikar Ali Manik]]|author2= [[Jim Yardley]] |url= http://www.nytimes.com/2013/03/02/world/asia/death-toll-from-bangladesh-unrest-hits-42.html?_r=0|newspaper= [[New York Times]]|date= March 1, 2013|accessdate=March 1, 2013}} 
&lt;/ref&gt; In the [[1998 Prankote massacre]], 26 Kashmiri Hindus were beheaded by Islamist militants after their denial of converting into Islam. The militants struck when the villagers refused demands from the gunmen to convert to Islam and prove their conversion by eating beef.&lt;ref name="jk9"&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/1998/06/20/world/gunmen-kill-25-hindus-in-kashmir-attacks.html] 26 Hindus beheeaded by Islamist militants in Kashmir&lt;/ref&gt;

==Atheism==
Under the [[state atheism]] of the [[U.S.S.R.]], there was a "government-sponsored program of forced conversion to atheism."&lt;ref&gt;The Ukrainian Quarterly - Volume 21, Page 177. Ukrainian Congress Committee of America, 1965.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Religion and the State in Russia and China: Suppression, Survival, and Revival, by Christopher Marsh, page 47. Continuum International Publishing Group, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Inside Central Asia: A Political and Cultural History, by Dilip Hiro. Penguin, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Twenty-first century allegations==

===Buddhism===
Forced conversion is not permitted in Buddhism and is rarely if ever attempted for religious reasons. However, in Burma in recent years the military dictatorship has strongly encouraged the conversion of ethnic minorities, often by force, as part of its campaign of assimilation.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.co.in/books?id=O3KwXCBdE_kC&amp;pg=PA120 Burma at the turn of the twenty-first century p.120] Monique Skidmore&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.co.in/books?id=-bm19c5kqrMC&amp;pg=PA29 |title=Buddhism: Webster's Quotations, Facts and Phrases – Google Books |publisher=Books.google.co.in |date= |accessdate=2012-11-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Christianity===
The [[Baptist]] Church of Tripura is alleged to have supplied the [[NLFT]] with arms and financial support and to have encouraged the murder of Hindus, particularly infants, as a means to depopulate the region of all Hindus.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | first =Subhir | last =Bhaumik |title = 'Church backing Tripura rebels'| url =http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/south_asia/717775.stm | publisher =BBC News |accessdate =2006-08-26  | date=April 18, 2000}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2009, the Assam Times reported that about fifteen armed [[Hmar people|Hmar]] militants, members of Manmasi National Christian Army, tried to force Hindu residents of Bhuvan Pahar, [[Assam]] to convert to Christianity.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.assamtimes.org/social/3112.html Christianity threat looms over Bhuvan Pahar] Assam Times – June 23, 2009&lt;/ref&gt; A Few Christian evangelists in India have been accused forced conversion of Hindus, and some of them have been jailed for forcefully converting.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bosnewslife.com/12022-india-pastor-jailed-for-converting-hindus India Pastor Jailed For Converting Hindus, Corpse Exhumed]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.persecution.org/suffering/newsdetail.php?newscode=8289 Indian couple detained on forced conversion charges]&lt;/ref&gt;

====Roman Catholicism====
[[Bernard Blasius Moras|Archbishop Moras]], refuting allegations of forced conversions and the charges of conversions against the Christian missionaries, said ''"We do not believe in forced conversions"'' ''"It is easy to charge people with wrong allegations but difficult to stop evil powers that are working against Christians"''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://mangalorean.com/news.php?newstype=broadcast&amp;broadcastid=98889 Satisfied with govt action- Archbishop Moras]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Hinduism===
Indian Christians have alleged that "radical Hindu groups" in [[Orissa]], India have forced Christian converts from Hinduism to "revert"&lt;ref name="revert"&gt;the word ''revert'' is used in this context; not ''convert''; see [http://www.jstor.org/stable/4413900 Older than the Church: Christianity and Caste in The God of Small Things India] by A sekhar;[http://www.washingtontimes.com/news/2010/mar/11/proselytism-on-the-table Washington post article]&lt;/ref&gt; to Hinduism. These "religious riots" were largely between two tribal groups in [[Orissa]], one of which was predominantly Hindu and another predominantly Christian, over the [[Murder of Swami Lakshmanananda|assassination]] of a Hindu leader named [[Swami Lakshmanananda]] by Christian [[Maoists]] operating as terrorist groups in India (see [[Naxalite]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hindujagruti.org/news/5576.html |title=We killed Swami Laxmananda: Christian Maoist leader – Attack |publisher=hindujagruti.org |date=2008-10-06 |accessdate=2012-11-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the aftermath of the violence, American Christian evangelical groups have claimed that Hindu groups are "forcibly reverting" Christians converts from Hinduism back to Hinduism.&lt;ref name="revert" /&gt; However, some local Christian groups have dismissed these allegations and forced conversion is not what Jesus Christ preached.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url= http://news.rediff.com/report/2009/aug/14/orissa-christian-leaders-disagree-with-us-report.htm|title= Orissa: Christian leaders disagree with US panel's report|date= 2009-08-14|publisher=Rediff News}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Islam===
United Nations Refugee Agency and other global human rights groups have published several reports describing forced conversion to Islam in nations with majority Islamic and regionally large Islamic populations.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.refworld.org/docid/510f8b832.html Pakistan - Religious conversions, UNHCR January 2013 report]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hrw.org/sites/default/files/reports/indonesia0213_ForUpload_0.pdf In Religion's Name: Abuses against Religious Minorities in Indonesia]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.state.gov/j/drl/rls/irf/religiousfreedom/index.htm?year=2012&amp;dlid=208232 Religious Freedom Report for 2012 - Indonesia]&lt;/ref&gt; Some examples are described below.

====Indonesia====
In 2012, over 1000 Catholic children in East Timor, removed from their families, were reported to being held in Indonesia without consent of their parents, forcibly converted to Islam, educated in Islamic schools and naturalized.&lt;ref&gt;[http://vaticaninsider.lastampa.it/en/world-news/detail/articolo/indonesia-12401/ Indonesia: thousands of Catholic children kidnapped and forced to convert to Islam, Vatican (Rome)]&lt;/ref&gt; Other reports claim forced conversion of minority Ahmadiyya sect Muslims to Sunni sect Muslim, with the use of violence.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thejakartapost.com/news/2012/11/06/sampang-shiites-forced-convert-sunni-kontras.html Sampang Shiites forced to convert to Sunni, November 2012, The Jakarta Post]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2011/feb/07/indonesia-inquiry-ahmadiyah-muslims-killed Indonesian president condemns mob killing of Ahmadiyah Muslims, The Guardian, London, February 2011]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.law.unimelb.edu.au/files/dmfile/crouch_final_website1.pdf Indonesia, Militant Islam and Ahmadiya, Melissa Crouch (2010), University of Melbourne, Australia]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2005,  three Indonesian Christian women were charged with attempting to convert Muslim children to Christianity in 2005. They were sentenced to three years' imprisonment. The punishment was upheld by the Supreme Court of Indonesia upon appeal.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.refworld.org/cgi-bin/texis/vtx/rwmain?page=printdoc&amp;docid=45f1474911 UNHCR 2006 Report on religious conversions in Indonesia]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[Reuters. 7 September 2005. Achmad Sukarsono. "Appeal Deadline Looms for Jailed Indonesia Christians."]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2001 the [[Indonesia]]n army evacuated hundreds of Christian refugees from the remote [[Kesui]] and [[Teor]] islands in [[Maluku (province)|Maluku]] after the refugees stated that they had been forced to convert to Islam. According to reports, some of the men had been circumcised against their will, and a paramilitary group involved in the incident confirmed that circumcisions had taken place while denying any element of coercion.&lt;ref&gt;Maluku refugees allege forced circumcision, BBC News Online, Wednesday, January 31, 2001 [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/asia-pacific/1146224.stm]&lt;/ref&gt;

====Middle-East====
In 2013, [[Inter Press Service]] reported more than 500 Christian girls have been abducted in [[Egypt]], over the last two years, with a growing number of cases involving girls between the ages of 13 and 17.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ipsnews.net/2013/04/missing-christian-girls-leave-trail-of-tears/ Missing Christian girls leave a trail of tears, Cam McGrath, Inter Press Agency (April 16 2013)]&lt;/ref&gt; In 2012, a 14-year old Coptic Christian girl was kidnapped, forcibly converted to Islam and married in Al Dab'a Egypt, even though Egyptian laws criminalize child marriage and prohibit the conversion of minors.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.refworld.org/docid/519dd4ca61.html United Nations Refugee Agency, 2012 Report on International Religious Freedom - Egypt]&lt;/ref&gt;

Egypt's largest newspaper [[Al-Ahram]] has reported a number of kidnapping and forced conversion of Coptic Christian girls to Islam, followed by marriage against their will to Muslim men.&lt;ref&gt;[http://weekly.ahram.org.eg/2009/963/eg7.htm Coptic Swan Song, Al Ahram Weekly, Issue 963 (September 2009)]&lt;/ref&gt; Similar claims of forced conversion have been reported by other independent organizations.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.state.gov/j/drl/rls/irf/2009/127346.htm The State Department of the United States, International Religious Freedom Report - Egypt (2009)]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://csi-int.org/pdfs/csi_coptic_report.pdf The Disappearance, Forced Conversions, and Forced Marriages of Coptic Christian Women in Egypt (November 2009)]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2004 [[Coptic Christian]]s in Egypt occupied the main Coptic cathedral in [[Cairo]] for several days, angry at the disappearance of a priest's wife in a village in the [[Nile delta]], who, they alleged, had been forced to convert to Islam. The [[BBC]] reported that allegations of forced conversions of Copts to Islam surface every year in Egypt.&lt;ref&gt;Heba Saleh (BBC News, Cairo), 'Conversion' sparks Copt protest. BBC News Online December 9, 2004.
[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/4080777.stm]&lt;/ref&gt;

Other notables among these have been the cases of Iraq's [[Mandaeans]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/6412453.stm Iraq's Mandaeans 'face extinction']&lt;/ref&gt; Egypt's [[Copt|Coptic Orthodox Christians]], Christians of Pakistan&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,273075,00.html Taliban Tells Pakistani Christians: Convert or Die]&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Assyrian Christians]] of Iraq&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.abc.net.au/rn/religionreport/stories/2007/1937124.htm Christian Minorities in the Islamic Middle East : Rosie Malek-Yonan on the Assyrians]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.iht.com/articles/2007/05/08/opinion/edisaac.php The assault on Assyrian Christians]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aina.org/news/20070518111715.htm Told to Convert or Die, 21 Assyrian Families Seek Shelter in Baghdad Churches]&lt;/ref&gt; who have faced coercion to convert to Islam.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/asia-pacific/1146224.stm | work=BBC News | title=Maluku refugees allege forced circumcision | date=2001-01-31 | accessdate=2010-05-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/4080777.stm 'Conversion' sparks Copt protest]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2006 two journalists of the Fox News Network had been kidnapped and forced to convert to Islam at gunpoint. After conversion they were made to read statements on videotape proclaiming that they had converted, after which they were released by their captors.&lt;ref&gt;[http://edition.cnn.com/2006/WORLD/meast/08/27/fox.journalists/index.html Kidnapped Fox journalists released]&lt;/ref&gt;

There have been numerous reports of Islamic attempts to forcibly convert religious minorities in [[Iraq]].  In Baghdad, Christians have been told to convert to Islam, pay the [[jizya]] or die.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aina.org/news/20070518111715.htm Told to Convert or Die, 21 Assyrian Families Seek Shelter in Baghdad Churches&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.iht.com/articles/2007/05/08/opinion/edisaac.php The assault on Assyrian Christians – International Herald Tribune&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.abc.net.au/rn/religionreport/stories/2007/1937124.htm The Religion Report – 30 May 2007 – Christian Minorities in the Islamic Middle East : Rosie Malek-Yonan on the Assyrians&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; In March 2007 the BBC reported that people in the [[Mandaean]] religious minority in [[Iraq]] alleged that they were being targeted by [[Islamist]] insurgents, who offered them the choice of conversion or death.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/6412453.stm BBC News on-line 7 March 2007]&lt;/ref&gt;

In several Middle East countries, force of law has been used to prevent and punish [[apostasy]] and religious conversions. For example, in 2008, sharia courts of [[Jordan]] have used Islamic law to judge religious conversion. People who convert from Islam to other religions lose their civil and property rights, their marriages are annulled, and their Muslims relatives gain custody of their children.&lt;ref&gt;[http://lib.ohchr.org/HRBodies/UPR/Documents/Session4/JO/ECLJ_JOR_UPR_S4_2009_EuropeanCentreforLawandJustice_upr.pdf United Nations Office of Human Rights Commission, RELIGIOUS FREEDOM IN THE HASHEMITE KINGDOM OF JORDAN (2008)]&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Saudi Arabia]], on December 17, 2012, the Jeddah District Court, hearing charges against [[Raif Badawi]] for the crime of apostasy (leaving Islamic faith), demanded that the defendant "repent to God" in the court. Badawi refused. The judge then referred the sentence of death penalty to a higher court.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hrw.org/news/2012/12/22/saudi-arabia-website-editor-facing-death-penalty Saudi Arabia, Website editor faces death penalty (2012)]&lt;/ref&gt;

====Maldives====
A Maldivian man, Mohammed Nazim,&lt;ref&gt;[http://iheu.org/story/maldavian-faces-death-“failure-believe” Maldavian faces death for “failure to believe”, June 2010]&lt;/ref&gt; was assaulted in 2010, after he attended a conference on religion, and during the question and answer session, asked questions on Islam, while confessing that he was born to Muslim parents, has read a translation of Qur'an, but does not believe in religion, that he is atheist. The conference gathering of about 11,000 demanded that the atheist be attacked and killed. Maldives' constitution stipulates Maldives citizens must be Muslims. The Maldivian man was arrested, given a chance to return to Islam or face criminal charges with death penalty. In prison, he agreed to return to Islam.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.haveeru.com.mv/news/30405 Maldivian renounces Islam, gets attacked by Zakir Naik audience, Haveeru Daily, May 30 2010]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://iheu.org/story/atheist-kills-himself-escape-100-percent-muslim-nation Atheist kills himself to escape "100 percent Muslim" nation, International Humanist and Ethical Union (15 July 2010)]&lt;/ref&gt;

====India====
In Jammu &amp; Kashmir, the [[Ladakh Buddhist Association]] has said: "There is a deliberate and organised design to convert Kargil's Buddhists to Islam.  In the last four years, about 50 girls and married women with children were taken and converted from village Wakha alone.  If this continues unchecked, we fear that Buddhists will be wiped out from Kargil in the next two decades or so.  Anyone objecting to such allurement and conversions is harassed."&lt;ref&gt;Tundup Tsering and Tsewang Nurboo, in: ''Ladakh visited'', Pioneer, 4/12/1995.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tribuneindia.com/2000/20000113/j&amp;k.htm#2 ''The Tribune'', Chandigarh, India – Jammu &amp; Kashmir&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

====Pakistan====
In 2003 a six year old Sikh girl was kidnapped by a member of the [[afridi]] tribe in Northwest Frontier Province, he also claimed the girl had converted to Islam and therefore could not be returned to her family.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Annual Report on International Religious Freedom|year=2005|publisher=State Dept (U S ), Senate (U S ) Committee on Foreign Relations|page=667|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=04dlwzB2SvcC&amp;pg=PA667}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A 2013 report published by United Nations Refugee Agency finds at least 700 Christian girls are kidnapped and forced to convert to Islam every year, in Pakistan. Additionally, the report claims 15 to 20 Hindu kidnapping cases are reported each month to the Hindu Council in Karachi alone, widespread complaints of forced conversions and forced child marriages of Hindu girls to Muslim men in Sindh province of Pakistan. The Human Rights Council of Pakistan has reported that cases of forced conversion are increasing.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.refworld.org/docid/51826ef842.html  USCIRF Annual Report 2013 - Countries of Particular Concern: Pakistan]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.irb-cisr.gc.ca:8080/RIR_RDI/RIR_RDI.aspx?id=454343&amp;l=e Government Research Directorate, Immigration and Refugee Board of Canada, Pakistan: Religious conversion, including treatment of converts and forced conversions (2009-2012)]&lt;/ref&gt;

In prior years too, around 25 Hindu girls have been reported to be abducted every month and converted to Islam forcibly in Pakistan, as reported by Pakistani media.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thenews.com.pk/TodaysPrintDetail.aspx?ID=231616&amp;Cat=4&amp;dt=3/31/2010] 25 Hindu girls abducted every month, claims HRCP official] The News, Tuesday, March 30, 2010&lt;/ref&gt; In May 2007, members of the Christian community of [[Charsadda]] in the [[Khyber Pakhtunkhwa|North West Frontier Province]] of Pakistan, close to the border of [[Afghanistan]], reported that they had received letters threatening bombings if they did not convert to Islam, and that the police were not taking their fears seriously.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,273075,00.html Report on Fox News, from AP]&lt;/ref&gt;  In June 2009, [[International Christian Concern]] (ICC) reported the rape and killing of a Christian man in Pakistan, for refusing to convert to Islam.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,526126,00.html |title=Christian Man Raped, Murdered for Refusing to Convert to Islam, Family Says |publisher=FOX News |date=June 13, 2009 |author=Nora Zimmett|accessdate=June 11, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Rinkle Kumari, a 19&amp;nbsp;year Pakistani student, Dr. Lata Kumari, and Asha Kumari, a Hindu working in a beauty parlor, were allegedly forced to convert from Hindu to Islam.&lt;ref name="fridaytimesrinkle"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thefridaytimes.com/beta2/tft/article.php?issue=20120413&amp;page=9 |title=Opinion: Rinkle Kumari – the new Marvi of Sindh by Marvi Sirmed |publisher=Thefridaytimes.com |date= |accessdate=2012-06-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://pakobserver.net/detailnews.asp?id=151043 |title=SC orders release of Rinkal Kumari, others |publisher=Pakobserver.net |date= |accessdate=2012-06-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; Their cases were appealed all the way to the [[Supreme Court of Pakistan]] where they said that they wanted to live with their parents and not their 'so called' husbands.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dailytimes.com.pk/default.asp?page=2012\04\19\story_19-4-2012_pg7_3 |title=Leading News Resource of Pakistan |publisher=Daily Times |date=2012-04-19 |accessdate=2012-06-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; The court issued a verdict that they had decided to stay with their husbands.

====Somalia====
In August 2009, ICC reported that four Christians working to help orphans in Somalia were beheaded by Islamist extremists when they refused to convert to Islam.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,539129,00.html |title=Al Shabaab Reportedly Beheads 4 Christians, Rips Gold Teeth From Locals' Mouths |publisher=FOX News |date=August 12, 2009 |author= |accessdate=June 11, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====United Kingdom====
According to the [[Daily Mail]], in 2007, commissioner of police, Sir [[Ian Blair]] stated the police were targeting extremist members of the Muslim community who were allegedly forcing vulnerable girls to convert to Islam in response to claims made by the Hindu Forum.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Police protect girls forced to convert to Islam |url=http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-437871/Police-protect-girls-forced-convert-Islam.html|publisher=Daily Mail|accessdate=19 August 2013|date=22 February 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2007 a Sikh girl's family claimed that she had been forcibly converted to Islam, and they received a police guard after being attacked by an armed gang, although the "Police said no one was injured in the incident".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Cowan|first=Mark|title=Police guard girl 'forced to become Muslim' |url=http://icbirmingham.icnetwork.co.uk/mail/news/tm_headline=police-guard-girl--forced-to-become-muslim-%26method=full%26objectid=19253457%26siteid=50002-name_page.html|publisher=Birmingham Mail|accessdate=19 August 2013|date=Jun 6 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In response to these news stories, an open letter to Sir Ian Blair, signed by ten Hindu academics, argued that claims that Hindu and Sikh girls were being forcefully converted were "part of an arsenal of myths propagated by right-wing Hindu supremacist organisations in India".&lt;ref&gt;http://www.pickledpolitics.com/archives/1045&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Muslim Council of Britain]] issued a press release pointing out there is a lack of evidence of any forced conversions and suggested it is an underhand attempt to smear the British Muslim population.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.mcb.org.uk/media/presstext.php?ann_id=242&lt;/ref&gt; Sheikh Musa Admani, an imam, said Islamic extremist groups may be evading university bans on groups such as [[Hizb ut Tahrir]] and [[Al-Muhajiroun]] &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=‘Hindu girls targeted by extremists’|url=http://metro.co.uk/2007/02/22/hindu-girls-targeted-by-extremists-108990/|publisher=http://metro.co.uk|date=22 Feb 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

An academic paper by Katy Sian published in the journal ''South Asian Popular Culture'' in 2011 explored the question of how "'forced' conversion narratives" arose around the [[Sikhism in the United Kingdom|Sikh diaspora in the United Kingdom]].&lt;ref name=Forced&gt;{{cite journal | url = http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/pdf/10.1080/14746681003798060 | title = ‘Forced’ conversions in the British Sikh diaspora | first = Katy P. |last = Sian |date = 6 July 2011 | journal = South Asian Popular Culture}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sian, who reports that claims of conversion through courtship on campuses are widespread in the UK, indicates that rather than relying on actual evidence they primarily rest on the word of "a friend of a friend" or on personal [[anecdote]]. According to Sian, the narrative is similar to accusations of "[[white slavery]]" lodged against the Jewish community and foreigners to the UK and the US, with the former having ties to [[anti-semitism]] that mirror the [[Islamophobia]] betrayed by the modern narrative. Sian expanded on these views in 2013's ''Mistaken Identities, Forced Conversions, and Postcolonial Formations''.&lt;ref name="Sian2013"&gt;{{cite book|author=Katy P. Sian|title=Unsettling Sikh and Muslim Conflict: Mistaken Identities, Forced Conversions, and Postcolonial Formations|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=-9AZ2atcd-kC&amp;pg=PA127|accessdate=15 June 2013|date=4 April 2013|publisher=Rowman &amp; Littlefield|isbn=978-0-7391-7874-4|pages=55–71}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Love Jihad]]
*[[State atheism]]
* [[Coercion]]
* [[Covenant of Umar I]]
* [[Crypto-Paganism]]
* [[Religious conversion]]
* [[Religious intolerance]]

==References==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

{{Religious persecution}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Forced Conversion}}
[[Category:Religious persecution]]
[[Category:Religious conversion]]
[[Category:Persecution]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>