<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20101109010142|395651473" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="7079135" pageid="7079135" ns="0" title="Forced conversion"><revisions><rev timestamp="2010-11-09T01:03:15Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">A '''forced conversion''' is the [[religious conversion]] or acceptance of a philosophy against the will of the subject, often with the threatened consequence of earthly penalties or harm. These consequences range from job loss and social isolation to incarceration, torture or death. Typically, such a conversion entails the repudiation of former religious or philosophical convictions.{{Citation needed|date=October 2007}}

==Christianity==
There is no support in the [[Bible]] for forced conversion{{Citation needed|date=September 2010}}, but there have been historical attempts by Christians to force the religious conversion of individuals, groups, and entire populations.

[[Pope Innocent III]], who denounced forced conversions{{Citation needed|date=September 2010}}, pronounced in 1201 that even if torture and intimidation had been employed in receiving the sacrament, one nevertheless:
&lt;blockquote&gt;...does receive the impress of Christianity and may be forced to observe the Christian Faith as one who expressed a conditional willingness though, absolutely speaking, he was unwilling. ... [For] the grace of Baptism had been received, and they had been [[confirmation (sacrament)|anointed with the sacred oil]], and had [[eucharist|participated in the body of the Lord]], they might properly be forced to hold to the faith which they had accepted perforce, lest the name of the Lord be blasphemed, and lest they hold in contempt and consider vile the faith they had joined.&lt;ref&gt;Grayzel, Solomon, ''The Church and the Jews in the Thirteenth Century'', rev. ed., New York: Hermon, 1966, p. 103&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The "[[New Christian]]s" were inhabitants of the [[Iberian Peninsula]] ([[Sephardi]]c Jews or [[Mudéjar]] Muslims) during the Middle Ages and the Early Modern Era who were baptized under coercion, becoming [[Converso]]s or [[Morisco]]s. In spite of their new faith, they were suspected by the "Old Christians" of being [[Crypto-Jew]]s or [[crypto-Islam|Crypto-Muslim]]s. Jews were expelled from Spain in 1492 and from Portugal in 1497.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.home.earthlink.net/~benven/annivers.html 500 ANNIVERSARY OF THE FORCED CONVERSION OF THE JEWS OF PORTUGAL&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

Religious persecution took place by the Portuguese in [[Goa]], India from 16th to the 17th century. The natives of Goa, most of them Hindus were subjected to [[Goa Inquisition|severe torture and oppression]] by the zealous Portuguese rulers and missionaries and forcibly converted to Christianity.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.co.in/books?id=RS1uAAAAMAAJ Of umbrellas, goddesses, and dreams: essays on Goan culture and society‎] Robert Samuel Newman, 2001&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[The Goa Inquisition (book)|The Goa Inquisition, Being a Quatercentenary Commemoration Study of the Inquisition in India]] by Anant Priolkar, Bombay University Press&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.co.in/books?id=hSnn_kDUI6AC&amp;pg=PA69 Everyday Nationalism: Women of the Hindu Right in India‎] Kalyani Devaki Menon, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.co.in/books?id=ftS1AAAAIAAJ Journal of the Asiatic Society of Bombay] 1967&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;M. D. David (ed.), Western Colonialism in Asia and Christianity, Bombay, 1988, p.17&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.co.in/books?id=INWSqBXundYC&amp;pg=PA137 Between ethnography and fiction: Verrier Elwin and the tribal question in India‎] Tanka Bahadur Subba, Sujit Som, K. C. Baral, North Eastern Hill University. Dept. of Anthropology - Social Science&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Charlemagne]] regarded the repelling of pagan invaders and their absorption and conversion as part of his obligation as defender of the faith and he forced the [[Saxon]]s and [[Frisians]] to convert to Christianity.&lt;ref name="Sandler2002"&gt;{{cite book|author=Stanley Sandler|title=Ground warfare: an international encyclopedia|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=L_xxOM85bD8C&amp;pg=PA173|accessdate=30 August 2010|date=1 July 2002|publisher=ABC-CLIO|isbn=9781576073445|pages=173–}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The economic conquest of the Americas by various European forces coincided with and depended on conversion of the natives. Some of these conversions were forced.{{Citation needed|date=June 2010}}

==Islam==
{{See also|Conversion of non-Muslim places of worship into mosques|Safavid conversion of Iran from Sunnism to Shiism}}

===Teachings===
Early Islamic scripture and law forbids forced conversion.&lt;ref name="W53"&gt;Waines (2003) "An Introduction to Islam" ''Cambridge University Press''. p. 53&lt;/ref&gt; A verse of the [[Qur'an]] ({{cite quran|2|256|expand=no|style=nosup}}) is frequently cited: "''Let there be no compulsion in religion''".&lt;ref&gt;Sir Thomas W. Arnold, ''The Preaching of Islam''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Marshall G. Hodgson, ''The Venture of Islam''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Albert Hourani, ''A History of the Arab Peoples''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Ira Lapidus, ''History of Islamic Societies''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;L.S. Starorianos, ''A Global History, the Human Heritage''&lt;/ref&gt; [[Karen Armstrong]] asserts that after [[Muhammad]]'s death, nobody in the [[Caliphate|Islamic empire]] was forced to accept the Islamic faith.&lt;ref name="arm2"&gt;Armstrong, A History of God: from Abraham to the Present: the 4000-year Quest for God, 1993, p. 185.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Practice===
{{POV|date=July 2010}}
In practice, forced conversions have been very common throughout all Islamic history, although it was but rarely official government policy.&lt;ref name="W53"/&gt;&lt;ref name="conseq"&gt;Lewis (1984), p. 17, 18, 94, 95.&lt;/ref&gt; Noted cases include the conversion of [[Samaritan]]s to Islam at the hands of the rebel Ibn Firāsa,&lt;ref&gt;M. Levy-Rubin,  "New evidence relating to the process of Islamization in Palestine in the Early Muslim Period - The Case of Samaria", in: ''Journal of the Economic and Social History of the Orient'', 43 (3), p. 257-276, 2000, [[Springer Science+Business Media|Springer]]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Fattal, A.(1958) ''Le statut légal des non-Musulman en pays d'Islam'', Beyrouth: Imprimerie Catholique, p. 72-73.&lt;/ref&gt; conversions in the 12th century under the [[Almohad]] dynasty of North Africa and [[al-Andalus|Andalusia]], as well as in [[Persia]] under the [[Safavid]] dynasty where [[Sunni]]s were converted to [[Shi'ism]]&lt;ref name="conseq" /&gt; and Jews were converted to Islam.&lt;ref name="JadidAlIslam"&gt;http://www.fis-iran.org/en/irannameh/volxix/mashhad-jewish-community&lt;/ref&gt; A form of forced conversion became institutionalized during the [[Ottoman Empire]] in the practice of [[devşirme]], a human levy in which Christian boys were seized and collected from their families (usually in the Balkans), enslaved, converted to Islam, and then trained for high ranking service to the sultan.

There is dispute amongst scholars as to whether the famous Jewish philosopher [[Maimonides]] converted to Islam in order to freely escape from Almohad territory, and then reconverted back to Judaism in either Israel or in Egypt.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.nysun.com/arts/the-great-rambam-joel-kramers-maimonides/86437/&lt;/ref&gt; Maimonides wrote a book on [[apostasy]] wherein he advocated accepting forced conversion rather than suffer martydom, and to then seek refuge afterward at a place where it was safe. [[Sabbatai Zevi]], an Ottoman Jew from Smyrna, was forced to convert to Islam,
and had no opportunity to return to Judaism. Sabbatai, a charismatic figure, had many followers,and ultimately claimed to be the messiah. He went to Constantinople where the Sultan placed him in a prison in Abydos. He gained his freedom by accepting Islam, along with his wife, and was then further forced to take a second wife to verify his true conversion.

[[K. S. Lal]], alleged in his book ''[[Growth of Muslim Population in Medieval India]]'' that between the years 1000 and 1500 the population of Hindus decreased by 80 million in the [[Indian Subcontinent]] due to forced conversion to Islam and widespread slaughter of Hindus who resisted conversion. Although [[Simon Digby]] criticized the book in a review in "Bulletin of the School of Oriental and African Studies",&lt;ref&gt;[[Growth of Muslim Population in Medieval India#Criticism|Simon Digby's Criticism of Mr. K. S. Lal's book]]&lt;/ref&gt; saying that even though Mr. Lal was a very competent historian of medieval India, the available information and the number of variables involved was far too great for any such account to be accurate.

During [[Tipu Sulthan]]'s invasion of [[Malabar]] in the late 18th century, he forcefully converted over 400,000 Hindus to Islam.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | last = Goel| first = Sita| title = Tipu Sultan: villain or hero? : an anthology| publisher = Voice of India| year = 1993| page = 38| url = http://books.google.co.in/books?ei=TYMYTPfXCse0rAf8-62tCg| isbn = 9788185990088}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | last = Sharma| first = Hari| title = The real Tipu: a brief history of Tipu Sultan| publisher = Rishi publications| year = 1991| page = 112| url = http://books.google.co.in/books?ei=TYMYTPfXCse0rAf8-62tCg}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | last = Purushottam | title = Must India go Islamic?| publisher = P.S. Yog| url = http://books.google.co.in/books?ei=TYMYTPfXCse0rAf8-62tCg&amp;ct=result&amp;id=MLvXAAAAMAAJ&amp;dq=tipu+hindu+malabar+4+lakh&amp;q=%22over+4+lakh+Hindus%22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Twenty-first century allegations==
===Buddhism===
Forced conversion is not permitted in Buddhism and is rarely if ever attempted for religious reasons. However, in Burma in recent years the military dictatorship has strongly encouraged the conversion of ethnic minorities, often by force, as part of its campaign of assimilation.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.co.in/books?id=O3KwXCBdE_kC&amp;pg=PA120 Burma at the turn of the twenty-first century p.120] Monique Skidmore&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.co.in/books?id=-bm19c5kqrMC&amp;pg=PA29]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Christianity===
The [[Baptist]] Church of Tripura is alleged to have supplied the NLFT with arms and financial support and to have encouraged the murder of Hindus, particularly infants, as a means to depopulate the region of all Hindus.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | first =Subhir | last =Bhaumik |title = 'Church backing Tripura rebels'| url =http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/south_asia/717775.stm | publisher =[[BBC News]] |accessdate =2006-08-26  | date=April 18, 2000}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2009, the Assam Times reported that about fifteen armed [[Hmar people|Hmar]] militants, members of Manmasi National Christian Army, tried to force Hindu residents of Bhuvan Pahar, [[Assam]] to convert to Christianity.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.assamtimes.org/social/3112.html Christianity threat looms over Bhuvan Pahar] Assam Times - June 23, 2009&lt;/ref&gt; Few Christian evangelists in India have been accused forced conversion of Hindus.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bosnewslife.com/12022-india-pastor-jailed-for-converting-hindus India Pastor Jailed For Converting Hindus, Corpse Exhumed]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.persecution.org/suffering/newsdetail.php?newscode=8289 Indian couple detained on forced conversion charges]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Bernard Blasius Moras|Archbishop Moras]], refuting these allegation of forced conversions and the charges of conversions against the Christian missionaries, said ''"We do not believe in forced conversions"'' ''"It is easy to charge people with wrong allegations but difficult to stop evil powers that are working against Christians"''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://mangalorean.com/news.php?newstype=broadcast&amp;broadcastid=98889 Satisfied with govt action- Archbishop Moras]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Hinduism===
There has been a great controversy in India in the past few years about the enforcement of anti-conversion laws by several Indian states which were made specifically to prevent people from leaving Hinduism and converting to other faiths,&lt;ref&gt;[[Freedom of religion in India#Laws against conversions|Laws against conversion from Hinduism in India]]&lt;/ref&gt; even though freedom of religion in India is supposed to be a fundamental right guaranteed by the country's constitution.

Indian Christians have alleged that "radical Hindu groups" in [[Orissa]], India have forced Christian converts from Hinduism to "revert"&lt;ref name="revert"&gt;the word ''revert'' is used in this context; not ''convert''; see [http://www.jstor.org/stable/4413900 Older than the Church: Christianity and Caste in The God of Small Things India] by A sekhar;[http://www.washingtontimes.com/news/2010/mar/11/proselytism-on-the-table Washington post article]&lt;/ref&gt; to Hinduism. These "religious riots" were largely between two tribal groups in [[Orissa]], one of which was predominantly Hindu and another predominantly Christian, over the [[Murder of Swami Lakshmanananda|assassination]] of a Hindu leader named [[Swami Laxmananda]] by Christian [[Maoists]] operating as terrorist groups in India (see [[Naxalite]]).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hindujagruti.org/news/5576.html]&lt;/ref&gt; In the aftermath of the violence, American Christian evangelical groups have claimed that Hindus are "forcibly reverting" Christians to Hinduism.&lt;ref name="revert" /&gt; However, some local Christian groups have dismissed these allegations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url= http://news.rediff.com/report/2009/aug/14/orissa-christian-leaders-disagree-with-us-report.htm|title= Orissa: Christian leaders disagree with US panel's report|date= 2009-08-14|publisher=Rediff News}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the past few years there have been numerous reports of religiously motivated violence and forced conversions inflicted on Indian Christians, where at times even the state itself was supportive of the Hindu extremists.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.compassdirect.org/english/country/india/24929/ Hindu atrocities against Indian Christian community]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Islam===
In 2001 the [[Indonesia]]n army evacuated hundreds of Christian refugees from the remote [[Kesui]] and [[Teor]] islands in [[Maluku (province)]] after the refugees stated that they had been forced to convert to Islam. According to reports, some of the men had been circumcised against their will, and a paramilitary group involved in the incident confirmed that circumcisions had taken place while denying any element of coercion.
&lt;ref&gt;Maluku refugees allege forced circumcision, BBC News Online, Wednesday, 31 January 2001 [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/asia-pacific/1146224.stm]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2004 [[Coptic Christian]]s in [[Egypt]] occupied the main Coptic cathedral in [[Cairo]] for several days, angry at the disappearance of a priest's wife in a village in the [[Nile delta]], who, they alleged, had been forced to convert to Islam. The [[BBC]] reported that allegations of forced conversions of Copts to Islam surface every year in Egypt.&lt;ref&gt;Heba Saleh (BBC News, Cairo), 'Conversion' sparks Copt protest. BBC News Online 9 December 2004.
[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/4080777.stm]&lt;/ref&gt;

Other notables among these have been the cases of Iraq's [[Mandaeans]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/6412453.stm Iraq's Mandaeans 'face extinction']&lt;/ref&gt;, Egypt's [[Copt|Coptic Orthodox Christians]], Christians of Pakistan &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,273075,00.html Taliban Tells Pakistani Christians: Convert or Die]&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Assyrian Christians]] of Iraq&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.abc.net.au/rn/religionreport/stories/2007/1937124.htm Christian Minorities in the Islamic Middle East : Rosie Malek-Yonan on the Assyrians]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.iht.com/articles/2007/05/08/opinion/edisaac.php The assault on Assyrian Christians]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aina.org/news/20070518111715.htm Told to Convert or Die, 21 Assyrian Families Seek Shelter in Baghdad Churches]&lt;/ref&gt; who have faced coercion to convert to Islam.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/asia-pacific/1146224.stm | work=BBC News | title=Maluku refugees allege forced circumcision | date=2001-01-31 | accessdate=2010-05-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/4080777.stm 'Conversion' sparks Copt protest]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2006 two journalists of the Fox News Network had been kidnapped and forced to convert to Islam at gunpoint. After conversion they were made to read statements on videotape proclaiming that they had converted, after which they were released by their captors.&lt;ref&gt;[http://edition.cnn.com/2006/WORLD/meast/08/27/fox.journalists/index.html Kidnapped Fox journalists released]&lt;/ref&gt; In 2007, Mahant Nritya Gopal Das, a right-wing Hindu leader in India, received a letter from [[Jaish-e-Mohammed]], threatening him with death if he did not convert to Islam.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/India/Ram_Janambhumi_trust_chief_threatened/articleshow/2562582.cms |title=
Ram Janambhumi trust chief threatened|date= 22 Nov 2007|agency= PTI|work=Times of India}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In May 2007, members of the Christian community of [[Charsadda]] in the [[North West Frontier Province]] of Pakistan, close to the border of [[Afghanistan]], reported that they had received letters threatening bombings if they did not convert to Islam, and that the police were not taking their fears seriously.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,273075,00.html Report on Fox News, from AP]&lt;/ref&gt; Although eventually no actual action was taken on that threat by the terrorists.

There have been numerous reports of Islamic attempts to forcibly convert religious minorities in Iraq.  In Baghdad, Christians have been told to convert to Islam, pay the [[jizya]] or die.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aina.org/news/20070518111715.htm Told to Convert or Die, 21 Assyrian Families Seek Shelter in Baghdad Churches&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.iht.com/articles/2007/05/08/opinion/edisaac.php The assault on Assyrian Christians - International Herald Tribune&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.abc.net.au/rn/religionreport/stories/2007/1937124.htm The Religion Report - 30 May 2007 - Christian Minorities in the Islamic Middle East : Rosie Malek-Yonan on the Assyrians&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; In March 2007 the BBC reported that people in the [[Mandaean]] religious minority in [[Iraq]] alleged that they were being targeted by [[Islamist]] insurgents, who offered them the choice of conversion or death.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/6412453.stm BBC News on-line 7 March 2007]&lt;/ref&gt;

On [[October]] [[2009]] it was reported that Muslim groups in the [[India]]n state of [[Kerala]] have been engaging in a "[[Love Jihad]]", whereby [[Muslim]] men were trained to [[seduce]] college-going [[Hindu]] and [[Christian]] girls to marry them and forcibly convert to Islam.&lt;ref&gt;[http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/india/Love-Jihad-racket-VHP-Christian-groups-find-common-cause/articleshow/5117548.cms]&lt;/ref&gt;. Both Hindu and Catholic Christian groups in the state expressed alarm at this trend and have been working together to protest this trend. The [[High Court]] in the state has resolved to probe the matter. The primary Islamic group currently being held responsible for this is the [[Islamic extremist]] front [[Popular Front of India]], a conglomeration of radical Islamist groups disguised as civil rights groups that are dedicated to implementing [[Islam]]ic [[Sharia]] law in Hindu majority India.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.indianexpress.com/news/kerala-hc-wants-probe-into-love-jihad/523630/]&lt;/ref&gt;. The Catholic Church in Kerala has joined up with Hindu groups in order to combat this trend.&lt;ref name="ucanews.com"&gt;[http://www.ucanews.com/2009/10/13/church-state-concerned-about-love-jihad/]&lt;/ref&gt;. Such cases of "Love Jihad" have reportedly started to occur in the neighboring state of [[Karnataka]] as well.&lt;ref name="ucanews.com"/&gt; 

Sikhs in Pakistan, concentrated in the Lahore area, have been constantly under a threat to convert to Islam&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nationalpost.com/news/canada/story.html?id=2605482 Father pleads for help after kidnapping]&lt;/ref&gt;. As ''[[jizya]]'' was legalized by the Government of Pakistan in 2009, the [[Taliban]] have been kidnapping minority communities to claim this tax&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sikhnn.com/modules.php?op=modload&amp;name=News&amp;file=article&amp;sid=704&amp;mode=thread&amp;order=0&amp;thold=0 US Religious Freedom Commission to Pakistan: Protect Your Sikhs]&lt;/ref&gt;; while officials use a significantly pro-Islam constitution to encourage conversions without direct participation.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dawn.com/wps/wcm/connect/dawn-content-library/dawn/the-newspaper/columnists/12-rafia-zakaria-persecuted-by-all-420--bi-07 Persecuted by all]&lt;/ref&gt;.

==See also==
* [[Apostasy]]
* [[Religious conversion]]
* [[Religious intolerance]]
* [[Forced circumcision]]
* [[Covenant of Umar I]]
* [[Freedom of religion in Saudi Arabia]]
* [[Apostasy in Islam]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Forced Conversion}}
[[Category:Religious persecution]]
[[Category:Religious conversion]]

[[ja:強制改宗]]
[[ru:Принудительное обращение]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>