<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20111026074838|457449366" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="7079135" pageid="7079135" ns="0" title="Forced conversion"><revisions><rev timestamp="2011-11-04T01:35:15Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">A '''forced conversion''' is the [[religious conversion]] or acceptance of a philosophy against the will of the subject, often with the threatened consequence of earthly penalties or harm. These consequences range from job loss and social isolation to incarceration, torture or death. Typically, such a conversion entails the repudiation of former religious or philosophical convictions.{{Citation needed|date=October 2007}}

==Christianity==
{{see also|Christianization}}
Forced conversion was a key factor in the Christianization of the Roman Empire. In 392 A.D. the emperor [[Theodosius]] I instituted a law making Christianity the only legal religion of the empire, and forbidding Pagan practices by law:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
It is Our will that all the peoples who are ruled by the administration of Our Clemency shall practice that religion which the divine Peter the Apostle transmitted to the Romans....The rest, whom We adjudge demented and insane, shall sustain the infamy of heretical dogmas, their meeting places shall not receive the name of churches, and they shall be smitten first by divine vengeance and secondly by the retribution of Our own initiative''" ([[Codex Theodosianus]] XVI 1.2.).&lt;ref&gt;http://penelope.uchicago.edu/~grout/encyclopaedia_romana/greece/paganism/paganism.html&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
This law led to the destruction of most pagan temples in the empire, and contributed largely to the demise of [[Paganism]].

During the [[Saxon Wars]], [[Charlemagne]], [[King of the Franks]], forcibly Christianized the [[Saxons]] from their native [[Germanic paganism]] by way of warfare and law upon conquest. Examples include the [[Massacre of Verden]] in 782, during which Charlemagne reportedly had 4,500 captive Saxons massacred upon rebelling against conversion, and the ''[[Capitulatio de partibus Saxoniae]]'', a law imposed on conquered Saxons in 785 which prescribes death to those that refuse to convert to Christianity.&lt;ref name="CHARLEMAGNE"&gt;For the Massacre of Verden, see Barbero, Alessandro (2004). ''Charlemagne: Father of a Continent'', page 46. [[University of California Press]]. For the ''Capitulatio de partibus Saxoniae'', see Riché, Pierre (1993). ''The Carolingians''. [[University of Pennsylvania Press]]. ISBN 9780812213423.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Pope Innocent III]] pronounced in 1201 that even if torture and intimidation had been employed in receiving the sacrament, one nevertheless:
&lt;blockquote&gt;...does receive the impress of Christianity and may be forced to observe the Christian Faith as one who expressed a conditional willingness though, absolutely speaking, he was unwilling. ... [For] the grace of Baptism had been received, and they had been [[confirmation (sacrament)|anointed with the sacred oil]], and had [[eucharist|participated in the body of the Lord]], they might properly be forced to hold to the faith which they had accepted perforce, lest the name of the Lord be blasphemed, and lest they hold in contempt and consider vile the faith they had joined.&lt;ref&gt;Grayzel, Solomon, ''The Church and the Jews in the Thirteenth Century'', rev. ed., New York: Hermon, 1966, p. 103&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The "[[New Christian]]s" were inhabitants of the [[Iberian Peninsula]] ([[Sephardi]]c Jews or [[Mudéjar]] Muslims) during the Middle Ages and the Early Modern Era who were baptized under coercion, becoming [[Converso]]s or [[Morisco]]s. In spite of their new faith, they were suspected by the "Old Christians" of being [[Crypto-Jew]]s or [[crypto-Islam|Crypto-Muslim]]s. Jews were expelled from Spain in 1492 and from Portugal in 1497.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.home.earthlink.net/~benven/annivers.html 500 ANNIVERSARY OF THE FORCED CONVERSION OF THE JEWS OF PORTUGAL&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

Religious persecution took place by the Portuguese in [[Goa]], India from 16th to the 17th century. The natives of Goa, most of them Hindus were subjected to [[Goa Inquisition|severe torture and oppression]] by the zealous Portuguese rulers and missionaries and forcibly converted to Christianity.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.co.in/books?id=RS1uAAAAMAAJ Of umbrellas, goddesses, and dreams: essays on Goan culture and society‎] Robert Samuel Newman, 2001&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[The Goa Inquisition (book)|The Goa Inquisition, Being a Quatercentenary Commemoration Study of the Inquisition in India]] by Anant Priolkar, Bombay University Press&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.co.in/books?id=hSnn_kDUI6AC&amp;pg=PA69 Everyday Nationalism: Women of the Hindu Right in India‎] Kalyani Devaki Menon, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.co.in/books?id=ftS1AAAAIAAJ Journal of the Asiatic Society of Bombay] 1967&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;M. D. David (ed.), Western Colonialism in Asia and Christianity, Bombay, 1988, p.17&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.co.in/books?id=INWSqBXundYC&amp;pg=PA137 Between ethnography and fiction: Verrier Elwin and the tribal question in India‎] Tanka Bahadur Subba, Sujit Som, K. C. Baral, North Eastern Hill University. Dept. of Anthropology - Social Science&lt;/ref&gt;

==Judaism==

Forced conversions are rare, but are reported to have happened under the Hasmonean Empire. The Gentile Galileans, Samaritans and Idumaens were forced to convert to Judaism, (either by threats of exile, or threats of death, depending on the source.)
For the forced conversion of the Idumaeans under John Hyrcanus, see Flavius Josephus Antiquities 13.257-258. For the forced conversion of the Ituraeans under Aristobulus, see Flavius Josephus Antiquities 13.319.  
In Eusebíus, Christianity, and Judaism  Harold W. Attridge  says that “there is reason to think that Josephus’ account of their conversion is substantially accurate.”  He also writes, “That these were not isolated instances but that forced conversion was a national policy is clear from the fact that Alexander Jannaeus (ca 80 BCE) demolished the city of Pella in Moab, “because the inhabitants would not agree to adopt the national custom of the Jews.”  Josephus, Antiquities. 13.15.4, 397
&lt;ref&gt;{{cite |url=http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=jVyzbHAJ_hAC&amp;pg=PA374&amp;dq=Ituraeans+forced+conversion&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=dNUATu3BAciv8QORmPTHDQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=2&amp;ved=0CC4Q6AEwATgK#v=onepage&amp;q=Ituraeans%20forced%20conversion&amp;f=false |accessdate=2011-20-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Maurice Sartre has written of the "policy of forced Judaization adopted by Hyrcanos, Aristobulus I and Jannaeus”, who offered "the conquered peoples a choice between expulsion or conversion,” &lt;ref&gt;{{cite |url=http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=9y7nTpFcN3AC&amp;pg=PA15&amp;lpg=PA15&amp;dq=Ituraeans+forced+conversion&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=hxTELYx1Vd&amp;sig=_EhvKuhvcja0F7ZTkGcW6ET6nG8&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=lMwATsfQOcmn8QO41syeDQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=7&amp;ved=0CD8Q6AEwBg#v=onepage&amp;q=Ituraeans%20forced%20conversion&amp;f=false |accessdate=2011-20-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

And in 'The early Roman period, Volume 2', William David Davies has written that. “The evidence is best explained by postulating that an existing small Jewish population in Lower Galilee was massively expanded by the forced conversion in c.104 BCE of their Gentile neighbours in the north.” &lt;ref&gt;{{cite |url=http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=MA-4VX5gWS4C&amp;pg=PA599&amp;dq=Ituraeans+forced+conversion&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=f9MATobdEMiW8QPYpqyTDQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=6&amp;ved=0CEMQ6AEwBQ#v=onepage&amp;q=Ituraeans%20forced%20conversion&amp;f=false accessdate=2011-20-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Islam==
{{See also|Islamization|Conversion of non-Muslim places of worship into mosques|Safavid conversion of Iran from Sunnism to Shiism}}

Early Islamic scripture and law forbids forced conversion.&lt;ref name="W53"&gt;Waines (2003) "An Introduction to Islam" ''Cambridge University Press''. p. 53&lt;/ref&gt; In opposition to forced Islamization, verse of the [[Qur'an]] ({{cite quran|2|256|expand=no|style=nosup}}) is frequently cited, reading "let there be no compulsion in religion".&lt;ref&gt;Sir Thomas W. Arnold, ''The Preaching of Islam''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Marshall G. Hodgson, ''The Venture of Islam''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Albert Hourani, ''A History of the Arab Peoples''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Ira Lapidus, ''History of Islamic Societies''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;L.S. Starorianos, ''A Global History, the Human Heritage''&lt;/ref&gt;

However, in practice, forced conversions have been very common throughout all Islamic history, although it was but rarely official government policy.&lt;ref name="W53"/&gt;&lt;ref name="conseq"&gt;Lewis (1984), p. 17, 18, 94, 95.&lt;/ref&gt; Noted cases include the conversion of [[Samaritan]]s to Islam at the hands of the rebel Ibn Firāsa,&lt;ref&gt;M. Levy-Rubin,  "New evidence relating to the process of Islamization in Palestine in the Early Muslim Period - The Case of Samaria", in: ''Journal of the Economic and Social History of the Orient'', 43 (3), p. 257-276, 2000, [[Springer Science+Business Media|Springer]]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Fattal, A.(1958) ''Le statut légal des non-Musulman en pays d'Islam'', Beyrouth: Imprimerie Catholique, p. 72-73.&lt;/ref&gt; conversions in the 12th century under the [[Almohad]] dynasty of North Africa and [[al-Andalus|Andalusia]], as well as in [[Persia]] under the [[Safavid]] dynasty where [[Sunni]]s were converted to [[Shi'ism]]&lt;ref name="conseq" /&gt; and Jews were converted to Islam.&lt;ref name="JadidAlIslam"&gt;http://www.fis-iran.org/en/irannameh/volxix/mashhad-jewish-community&lt;/ref&gt; A form of forced conversion became institutionalized during the [[Ottoman Empire]] in the practice of [[devşirme]], a human levy in which Christian boys were seized and collected from their families (usually in the Balkans), enslaved, converted to Islam, and then trained for high ranking service to the sultan.&lt;ref&gt;'''Conversion''', Tijana Krstić, ''Encyclopedia of the Ottoman Empire'', Ed. Gábor Ágoston and Bruce Alan Masters, (InfoBase Publishing, 2009), 145-146;"''As a part of their education, devşirme children underwent compulsory conversion to Islam, which is the only documented forced form of conversion organized by the Ottoman state.''".&lt;/ref&gt;

There is dispute amongst scholars as to whether the famous Jewish philosopher [[Maimonides]] converted to Islam in order to freely escape from Almohad territory, and then reconverted back to Judaism in either the Levant or in Egypt.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.nysun.com/arts/the-great-rambam-joel-kramers-maimonides/86437/&lt;/ref&gt; Maimonides wrote a book on [[apostasy]] wherein he advocated accepting forced conversion rather than suffer martydom, and to then seek refuge afterward at a place where it was safe. [[Sabbatai Zevi]], an Ottoman Jew from Smyrna, was forced to convert to Islam,
and had no opportunity to return to Judaism. Sabbatai, a charismatic figure, had many followers,and ultimately claimed to be the messiah. He went to Constantinople where the Sultan placed him in a prison in Abydos. He gained his freedom by accepting Islam, along with his wife, and was then further forced to take a second wife to verify his true conversion.

[[K. S. Lal]], alleged in his book ''[[Growth of Muslim Population in Medieval India]]'' that between the years 1000 and 1500 the population of Hindus decreased by 80 million in the [[Indian Subcontinent]] due to forced conversion to Islam and widespread slaughter of Hindus who resisted conversion.&lt;ref name="fg5"&gt;[http://www.enotes.com/topic/Growth_of_Muslim_Population_in_Medieval_India]KS Lal&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Muhammad Ghori]] committed genocide against Hindus at [[Kol]] (modern [[Aligarh]]), Kalinjar and Varanasi. According to Hasan Nizami's Taj-ul-Maasir, 20000 Hindu prisoners were slaughtered and their heads offered to crows.&lt;ref name="ak9"&gt;
{{cite book |last= Rashid |first= A.|title=Society and Culture in Medieval India, 1206-1556 A.D. (Excerpt from Taj-ul-Maasir)|publisher= Firma K. L. Mukhopadhyay |year= 1969}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="gh"/&gt; Hasan Nizami's Taj-ul-Maasir records that in Kol (Modern Aligarh), "those of the horizon who were wise and acute were converted to Islam, but those who stood by their ancestoral faith were slain with the sword.&lt;ref name="gh"&gt;[http://www.jame-ghor.com/english/muhammad_of_ghor.htm] Muhammad of Ghor&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="ak9"/&gt;  

Mughal ruler [[Aurangzeb]] cherished the ambition of converting India into a land of [[Islam]]. For this, he encouraged forced religious conversions and destroyed thousands of Hindu temples during his reign.&lt;ref name="bb3"&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/religion/religions/islam/history/mughalempire_1.shtml#h5]Intolerant ruler: Aurangzeb (bbc.co.uk)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="bbc6"&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/religion/religions/sikhism/people/teghbahadur.shtml]Guru Tegh Bahadur (BBC.CO.UK)&lt;/ref&gt; 

During [[Tipu Sultan]]'s invasion of [[Malabar Coast|Malabar]] in the late 18th century, he forcefully converted over 400,000 Hindus to Islam.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | last = Goel| first = Sita| title = Tipu Sultan: villain or hero? : an anthology| publisher = Voice of India| year = 1993| page = 38| url = http://books.google.co.in/books?ei=TYMYTPfXCse0rAf8-62tCg| isbn = 9788185990088}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | last = Sharma| first = Hari| title = The real Tipu: a brief history of Tipu Sultan| publisher = Rishi publications| year = 1991| page = 112| url = http://books.google.co.in/books?ei=TYMYTPfXCse0rAf8-62tCg}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | last = Purushottam | title = Must India go Islamic?| publisher = P.S. Yog| url = http://books.google.co.in/books?ei=TYMYTPfXCse0rAf8-62tCg&amp;ct=result&amp;id=MLvXAAAAMAAJ&amp;dq=tipu+hindu+malabar+4+lakh&amp;q=%22over+4+lakh+Hindus%22}}&lt;/ref&gt; During the [[Moplah Riots]] of 1921 in [[Kerala]], Muslim [[Mappila]]s forcibly converted thousands of Hindus to Islam&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | title = Hindu culture during and after Muslim rule: survival and subsequent challenges| publisher = M.D. Publications Pvt. Ltd.| year = 1994| page = 103| url = http://books.google.co.in/books?id=wVr_f_gXOX4C&amp;pg=PA103| isbn = 9788185880266}}&lt;/ref&gt; and killed all those who refused to apostatise.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
 | last = Besant
 | first = Annie
 | authorlink = Annie Besant
 | title = The Future Of Indian Politics: A Contribution To The Understanding Of Present-Day Problems P252
 | publisher = Kessinger Publishing, LLC
 | isbn = 1428626050
 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Twenty-first century allegations==
===Buddhism===
Forced conversion is not permitted in Buddhism and is rarely if ever attempted for religious reasons. However, in Burma in recent years the military dictatorship has strongly encouraged the conversion of ethnic minorities, often by force, as part of its campaign of assimilation.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.co.in/books?id=O3KwXCBdE_kC&amp;pg=PA120 Burma at the turn of the twenty-first century p.120] Monique Skidmore&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.co.in/books?id=-bm19c5kqrMC&amp;pg=PA29]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Christianity===
The [[Baptist]] Church of Tripura is alleged to have supplied the NLFT with arms and financial support and to have encouraged the murder of Hindus, particularly infants, as a means to depopulate the region of all Hindus.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | first =Subhir | last =Bhaumik |title = 'Church backing Tripura rebels'| url =http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/south_asia/717775.stm | publisher =[[BBC News]] |accessdate =2006-08-26  | date=April 18, 2000}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2009, the Assam Times reported that about fifteen armed [[Hmar people|Hmar]] militants, members of Manmasi National Christian Army, tried to force Hindu residents of Bhuvan Pahar, [[Assam]] to convert to Christianity.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.assamtimes.org/social/3112.html Christianity threat looms over Bhuvan Pahar] Assam Times - June 23, 2009&lt;/ref&gt; Few Christian evangelists in India have been accused forced conversion of Hindus.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bosnewslife.com/12022-india-pastor-jailed-for-converting-hindus India Pastor Jailed For Converting Hindus, Corpse Exhumed]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.persecution.org/suffering/newsdetail.php?newscode=8289 Indian couple detained on forced conversion charges]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Bernard Blasius Moras|Archbishop Moras]], refuting these allegation of forced conversions and the charges of conversions against the Christian missionaries, said ''"We do not believe in forced conversions"'' ''"It is easy to charge people with wrong allegations but difficult to stop evil powers that are working against Christians"''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://mangalorean.com/news.php?newstype=broadcast&amp;broadcastid=98889 Satisfied with govt action- Archbishop Moras]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Hinduism===
Indian Christians have alleged that "radical Hindu groups" in [[Orissa]], India have forced Christian converts from Hinduism to "revert"&lt;ref name="revert"&gt;the word ''revert'' is used in this context; not ''convert''; see [http://www.jstor.org/stable/4413900 Older than the Church: Christianity and Caste in The God of Small Things India] by A sekhar;[http://www.washingtontimes.com/news/2010/mar/11/proselytism-on-the-table Washington post article]&lt;/ref&gt; to Hinduism. These "religious riots" were largely between two tribal groups in [[Orissa]], one of which was predominantly Hindu and another predominantly Christian, over the [[Murder of Swami Lakshmanananda|assassination]] of a Hindu leader named [[Swami Lakshmanananda]] by Christian [[Maoists]] operating as terrorist groups in India (see [[Naxalite]]).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hindujagruti.org/news/5576.html]&lt;/ref&gt; In the aftermath of the violence, American Christian evangelical groups have claimed that Hindu groups are "forcibly reverting" Christians converts from Hinduism back to Hinduism.&lt;ref name="revert" /&gt; However, some local Christian groups have dismissed these allegations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url= http://news.rediff.com/report/2009/aug/14/orissa-christian-leaders-disagree-with-us-report.htm|title= Orissa: Christian leaders disagree with US panel's report|date= 2009-08-14|publisher=Rediff News}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Islam===

====Indonesia====
In 2001 the [[Indonesia]]n army evacuated hundreds of Christian refugees from the remote [[Kesui]] and [[Teor]] islands in [[Maluku (province)]] after the refugees stated that they had been forced to convert to Islam. According to reports, some of the men had been circumcised against their will, and a paramilitary group involved in the incident confirmed that circumcisions had taken place while denying any element of coercion.
&lt;ref&gt;Maluku refugees allege forced circumcision, BBC News Online, Wednesday, 31 January 2001 [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/asia-pacific/1146224.stm]&lt;/ref&gt;

====Middle-East====
In 2004 [[Coptic Christian]]s in [[Egypt]] occupied the main Coptic cathedral in [[Cairo]] for several days, angry at the disappearance of a priest's wife in a village in the [[Nile delta]], who, they alleged, had been forced to convert to Islam. The [[BBC]] reported that allegations of forced conversions of Copts to Islam surface every year in Egypt.&lt;ref&gt;Heba Saleh (BBC News, Cairo), 'Conversion' sparks Copt protest. BBC News Online 9 December 2004.
[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/4080777.stm]&lt;/ref&gt;

Other notables among these have been the cases of Iraq's [[Mandaeans]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/6412453.stm Iraq's Mandaeans 'face extinction']&lt;/ref&gt; Egypt's [[Copt|Coptic Orthodox Christians]], Christians of Pakistan &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,273075,00.html Taliban Tells Pakistani Christians: Convert or Die]&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Assyrian Christians]] of Iraq&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.abc.net.au/rn/religionreport/stories/2007/1937124.htm Christian Minorities in the Islamic Middle East : Rosie Malek-Yonan on the Assyrians]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.iht.com/articles/2007/05/08/opinion/edisaac.php The assault on Assyrian Christians]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aina.org/news/20070518111715.htm Told to Convert or Die, 21 Assyrian Families Seek Shelter in Baghdad Churches]&lt;/ref&gt; who have faced coercion to convert to Islam.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/asia-pacific/1146224.stm | work=BBC News | title=Maluku refugees allege forced circumcision | date=2001-01-31 | accessdate=2010-05-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/4080777.stm 'Conversion' sparks Copt protest]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2006 two journalists of the Fox News Network had been kidnapped and forced to convert to Islam at gunpoint. After conversion they were made to read statements on videotape proclaiming that they had converted, after which they were released by their captors.&lt;ref&gt;[http://edition.cnn.com/2006/WORLD/meast/08/27/fox.journalists/index.html Kidnapped Fox journalists released]&lt;/ref&gt; 

There have been numerous reports of Islamic attempts to forcibly convert religious minorities in Iraq.  In Baghdad, Christians have been told to convert to Islam, pay the [[jizya]] or die.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aina.org/news/20070518111715.htm Told to Convert or Die, 21 Assyrian Families Seek Shelter in Baghdad Churches&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.iht.com/articles/2007/05/08/opinion/edisaac.php The assault on Assyrian Christians - International Herald Tribune&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.abc.net.au/rn/religionreport/stories/2007/1937124.htm The Religion Report - 30 May 2007 - Christian Minorities in the Islamic Middle East : Rosie Malek-Yonan on the Assyrians&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; In March 2007 the BBC reported that people in the [[Mandaean]] religious minority in [[Iraq]] alleged that they were being targeted by [[Islamist]] insurgents, who offered them the choice of conversion or death.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/6412453.stm BBC News on-line 7 March 2007]&lt;/ref&gt;

====India====

In October 2009 it was reported that Muslim groups in the Indian state of [[Kerala]] have been engaging in a "[[Love Jihad]]", whereby [[Muslim]] men were trained to [[seduce]] college-going [[Hindu]] and [[Christian]] girls to marry them and forcibly convert to Islam.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/india/Love-Jihad-racket-VHP-Christian-groups-find-common-cause/articleshow/5117548.cms | work=The Times Of India | title='Love Jihad' racket: VHP, Christian groups find common cause | date=13 October 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Both Hindu and Catholic Christian groups in the state expressed alarm at this trend and have been working together to protest this trend. The [[High Court]] in the state has resolved to probe the matter. The primary Islamic group currently being held responsible for this is the [[Islamic extremist]] front [[Popular Front of India]], a conglomeration of radical Islamist groups disguised as civil rights groups that are dedicated to implementing [[Islam]]ic [[Sharia]] law in Hindu majority India.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.indianexpress.com/news/kerala-hc-wants-probe-into-love-jihad/523630/]&lt;/ref&gt; The Catholic Church in Kerala has joined up with Hindu groups in order to combat this trend.&lt;ref name="ucanews.com"&gt;[http://www.ucanews.com/2009/10/13/church-state-concerned-about-love-jihad/]&lt;/ref&gt; Such cases of "Love Jihad" have reportedly started to occur in the neighboring state of [[Karnataka]] as well.&lt;ref name="ucanews.com"/&gt; 

In 2007, Mahant Nritya Gopal Das, a right-wing Hindu leader in India, received a letter from [[Jaish-e-Mohammed]], threatening him with death if he did not convert to Islam.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/India/Ram_Janambhumi_trust_chief_threatened/articleshow/2562582.cms |title=
Ram Janambhumi trust chief threatened|date= 22 Nov 2007|agency= PTI|work=Times of India}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;b&gt;Jammu &amp; Kashmir&lt;/b&gt;- The [[Ladakh Buddhist Association]] has said: "There is a deliberate and organised design to convert Kargil's Buddhists to Islam.  In the last four years, about 50 girls and married women with children were taken and converted from village Wakha alone.  If this continues unchecked, we fear that Buddhists will be wiped out from Kargil in the next two decades or so.  Anyone objecting to such allurement and conversions is harassed."&lt;ref&gt;Tundup Tsering and Tsewang Nurboo, in: ''Ladakh visited'', Pioneer, 4/12/1995.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tribuneindia.com/2000/20000113/j&amp;k.htm#2 ''The Tribune'', Chandigarh, India - Jammu &amp; Kashmir&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[1998 Prankote massacre]], 26 Kashmiri Hindus were beheaded by Islamist militants after their denial of converting into Islam. The militants struck when the villagers refused demands from the gunmen to convert to Islam and prove their conversion by eating beef. &lt;ref name="jk9"&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/1998/06/20/world/gunmen-kill-25-hindus-in-kashmir-attacks.html]26 Hindus beheeaded by Islamist militants in Kashmir&lt;/ref&gt;

====Pakistan====
Around 25 Hindu girls are abducted every month and converted to Islam forcibly in Pakistan, as reported by Pakistani media.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thenews.com.pk/TodaysPrintDetail.aspx?ID=231616&amp;Cat=4&amp;dt=3/31/2010]25 Hindu girls abducted every month, claims HRCP official] The News, Tuesday, March 30, 2010&lt;/ref&gt; 

In May 2007, members of the Christian community of [[Charsadda]] in the [[North West Frontier Province]] of Pakistan, close to the border of [[Afghanistan]], reported that they had received letters threatening bombings if they did not convert to Islam, and that the police were not taking their fears seriously.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,273075,00.html Report on Fox News, from AP]&lt;/ref&gt; Although eventually no actual action was taken on that threat by the terrorists.

In June 2009, [[International Christian Concern]] (ICC) reported the rape and killing of a Christian man in Pakistan, for refusing to convert to Islam.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,526126,00.html |title=Christian Man Raped, Murdered for Refusing to Convert to Islam, Family Says |publisher=FOX News |date=June 13, 2009 |author=Nora Zimmett|accessdate=June 11, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In August 2009, ICC reported that four Christians working to help orphans in Somalia were beheaded by Islamist extremists when they refused to convert to Islam.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,539129,00.html |title=Al Shabaab Reportedly Beheads 4 Christians, Rips Gold Teeth From Locals' Mouths |publisher=FOX News |date=August 12, 2009 |author= |accessdate=June 11, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Sikhs]] in Pakistan, concentrated in the Lahore area, have been constantly under a threat to convert to Islam.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nationalpost.com/news/canada/story.html?id=2605482 Father pleads for help after kidnapping]&lt;/ref&gt; As ''[[jizya]]'' was legalized by the Government of Pakistan in 2009, the [[Taliban]] have been kidnapping minority communities to claim this tax;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sikhnn.com/modules.php?op=modload&amp;name=News&amp;file=article&amp;sid=704&amp;mode=thread&amp;order=0&amp;thold=0 US Religious Freedom Commission to Pakistan: Protect Your Sikhs]&lt;/ref&gt; while officials use a significantly pro-Islam constitution to encourage conversions without direct participation.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dawn.com/wps/wcm/connect/dawn-content-library/dawn/the-newspaper/columnists/12-rafia-zakaria-persecuted-by-all-420--bi-07 Persecuted by all]&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Apostasy]]
* [[Apostasy in Islam]]
* [[Covenant of Umar I]]
* [[Crypto-Paganism]]
* [[Forced circumcision]]
* [[Freedom of religion in Saudi Arabia]]
* [[Religious conversion]]
* [[Religious intolerance]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{Religious persecution}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Forced Conversion}}
[[Category:Religious persecution]]
[[Category:Religious conversion]]
[[Category:Persecution]]

[[ja:強制改宗]]
[[ru:Принудительное обращение]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>