<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20181118033811|869363064" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="7079135" pageid="7079135" ns="0" title="Forced conversion"><revisions><rev timestamp="2018-11-18T03:56:50Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Forced conversion''' is adoption of a different religion or irreligion under [[Coercion|duress]]. Some who have been forced to convert may continue, covertly, with the beliefs and practices originally held, while outwardly behaving as converts. [[Crypto-Judaism|Crypto-Jews]], [[Crypto-Christianity|crypto-Christians]], [[Crypto-Islam|crypto-Muslims]] and [[Crypto-paganism|crypto-Pagans]] are historical examples of the latter.

== Religion and power ==
In general, [[anthropologists]] have shown that the relationship between [[religion and politics]] is complex, especially when viewed over the expanse of human history.&lt;ref name=Firth&gt;Firth, Raymond (1981) [https://www.jstor.org/stable/676754 Spiritual Aroma: Religion and Politics]. ''American Anthropologist'', New Series, Vol. 83, No. 3, pp. 582–601&lt;/ref&gt; While religious leaders and the state generally have different aims, both are concerned with power and order; both use reason and emotion to motivate behavior. Throughout history, leaders of religious and political institutions have cooperated, opposed one another, or attempted to co-opt each other, for purposes both noble and base, and have implemented programs with a wide range of driving values, from compassion aimed at alleviating current suffering to brutal change aimed at achieving longer-term goals, for the benefit of groups ranging from small cliques to all of humanity. The relationship is far from simple. But religion has often been used coercively, and has used coercion.&lt;ref name=Firth/&gt;

== Judaism ==
Forced conversions occurred under the [[Hasmonean dynasty|Hasmonean Kingdom]]. The [[Idumea]]ns were forced to convert to Judaism, by threat of exile or death, depending on the source.&lt;ref&gt;Flavius Josephus Antiquities 13.257–258&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Aristobulus I|Aristobulus]]&lt;/ref&gt;
In ''Eusebíus, Christianity, and Judaism'', [[Harold W. Attridge]] claims that "there is reason to think that [[Josephus]]' account of their conversion is substantially accurate." He also writes: "that these were not isolated instances, but that forced conversion was a national policy, is clear from the fact that [[Alexander Jannaeus]] (around 80 BC) demolished the city of [[Pella, Jordan|Pella]] in [[Moab]], 'because the inhabitants would not agree to adopt the national custom of the Jews.'" Josephus, Antiquities. 13.15.4.&lt;ref&gt;Harold W. Attridge, Gōhei Hata (eds). ''Eusebius, Christianity, and Judaism'' Wayne State University Press, 1992: p. 387&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Maurice Sartre]] has written of the "policy of forced Judaization adopted by [[John Hyrcanus|Hyrcanos]], [[Aristobulus I]] and [[Jannaeus]]", who offered "the conquered peoples a choice between expulsion or conversion,"&lt;ref&gt;[[Maurice Sartre]]. ''The Middle East Under Rome''. Harvard University Press, 2005: p. 15&lt;/ref&gt; William Horbury has written that "The evidence is best explained by postulating that an existing small Jewish population in Lower Galilee was massively expanded by the forced conversion in c.104 BC of their Gentile neighbours in the north."&lt;ref&gt;William Horbury. ''The Cambridge History of Judaism 2 Part Set: Volume 3, The Early Roman Period'' Cambridge University Press, 1999: p. 599&lt;/ref&gt;
In 2009 the [[BBC]] defended a claim that in AD 524 the [[Yemen]]i Jewish [[Himyar]] tribe, led by King [[Dhu Nuwas]], had offered Christian residents of a village in what is now [[Saudi Arabia]] the choice between conversion to Judaism or death, and that 20,000 Christians had then been massacred. The BBC stated that "The production team spoke to many historians over 18 months, among them [[Nigel Groom]], who was our consultant, and Professor [[Abdul Rahman Al-Ansary]] [former professor of archaeology at the [[King Saud University]] in [[Riyadh]]]."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thejc.com/news/uk-news/historians-back-bbc-over-jewish-massacre-claim |title=Historians back BBC over Jewish massacre claim &amp;#124; The Jewish Chronicle |publisher=Thejc.com |date=2009-09-18 |accessdate=2014-06-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; Inscriptions documented by Yousef himself show the great pride he expressed after massacring more than 22,000 Christians in [[Zafar, Yemen|Zafar]] and [[Najran]].&lt;ref&gt;Jacques Ryckmans, La persécution des chrétiens himyarites au sixième siècle, Nederlands Historisch-Archaeologisch Inst. in het Nabije Oosten, 1956 pp 1-24&lt;/ref&gt;

== Christianity ==
{{See also|Christianization|Classical antiquity}}
[[Early Christianity|Christianity]] was a minority religion during much of middle [[Roman Empire|Roman]] [[Classical antiquity|Classical Period]], and [[Persecution of Christians in the Roman Empire|the early Christians were persecuted during that time]]. When [[Constantine the Great and Christianity|Constantine I converted to Christianity]], it became the dominant religion in the Roman Empire. Already under the reign of Constantine I, [[Heresy#Christianity|Christian heretics]] had been persecuted; beginning in the late 4th century, the [[Persecution of pagans in the late Roman Empire|ancient pagan religions were also actively suppressed]]. In the view of many historians, the [[Constantinian shift]] turned Christianity from a persecuted religion into one capable of persecution and sometimes eager to persecute.&lt;ref&gt;see e.g. John Coffey, ''Persecution and Toleration on Protestant England 1558–1689'', 2000, p.22&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Late Antiquity ===
{{See also|State church of the Roman Empire}}
On 27 February 380, together with [[Gratian]] and [[Valentinian II]], [[Theodosius I]] issued the decree ''Cunctos populos'', the so-called [[Edict of Thessalonica]], recorded in the [[Codex Theodosianus]] [[:la:s:Codex Theodosianus – Liber XVI#I.2|xvi.1.2]]. This declared [[Trinitarianism|Trinitarian]] [[Nicene Christianity]] to be the only legitimate imperial religion and the only one entitled to call itself [[Catholic]]. Other Christians he described as "foolish madmen".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fordham.edu/halsall/source/theodcodeXVI.html|title=Medieval Sourcebook: Theodosian Code XVI|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; He also ended official state support for the traditional [[polytheist]] religions and customs.&lt;ref name="KaylorPhillips2012"&gt;{{citation|author1=Noel Harold Kaylor|author2=Philip Edward Phillips|title=A Companion to Boethius in the Middle Ages|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=B_secKlFKB0C&amp;pg=PA14|accessdate=19 January 2013|date=3 May 2012|publisher=BRILL|isbn=978-90-04-18354-4|pages=14–}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The ''[[Codex Theodosianus]]'' (Eng. Theodosian Code) was a compilation of the [[Roman law|laws]] of the [[Roman Empire]] under the [[Christian]] emperors since 312. A commission was established by [[Theodosius II]] and his [[Tetrarchy|co-emperor]] [[Valentinian III]] on 26 March 429&lt;ref name=Oxf&gt;"Codex Theodosianus" in ''[[Oxford Dictionary of Byzantium|The Oxford Dictionary of Byzantium]]'', [[Oxford University Press]], New York &amp; Oxford, 1991, p. 475. {{ISBN|0195046528}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/secondary/SMIGRA*/Codex_Theodosianus.html LacusCurtius • Roman Law — Theodosian Code (Smith's Dictionary, 1875)&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; and the compilation was published by a constitution of 15 February 438. It went into force in the eastern and western parts of the empire on 1 January 439.&lt;ref name=Oxf/&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;It is Our will that all the peoples who are ruled by the administration of Our Clemency shall practice that religion which the divine Peter the Apostle transmitted to the Romans.... The rest, whom We adjudge demented and insane, shall sustain the infamy of heretical dogmas, their meeting places shall not receive the name of churches, and they shall be smitten first by divine vengeance and secondly by the retribution of Our own initiative (Codex Theodosianus XVI 1.2.).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=The Theodosian Code and Novels and the Sirmondian Constitutions |year=1952 |translator-last=Pharr |translator-first=Clyde}}, qtd. in {{cite web |last=Grout |first=James|url=http://penelope.uchicago.edu/~grout/encyclopaedia_romana/greece/paganism/paganism.html |title=The End of Paganism |date=1 October 2014 |accessdate=9 May 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

[[History of Jewish conversion to Christianity|Forced conversions of Jews]] were carried out with the support of rulers during [[Late Antiquity]] and the early [[Middle Ages]] in [[Gaul]], the [[Iberian peninsula]] and in the [[Byzantine empire]].&lt;ref name=soyer&gt;{{cite book|author=F.J.F. Soyer|title=The Persecution of the Jews and Muslims of Portugal King Manuel I and the End of Religious Tolerance (1496-7)|date=2007|publisher=Brill|isbn=9789047431558|url= http://booksandjournals.brillonline.com/content/books/9789047431558|subscription=yes|via=Brill|pages=3–4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Medieval western Europe ===
During the [[Saxon Wars]], [[Charlemagne]], [[King of the Franks]], forcibly converted the [[Saxons]] from their native [[Germanic paganism]] by way of warfare, and law upon conquest. Examples are the [[Massacre of Verden]] in 782, when Charlemagne reportedly had 4,500 captive Saxons massacred upon rebelling against conversion, and the ''[[Capitulatio de partibus Saxoniae]]'', a law imposed on conquered Saxons in 785 that prescribed death to those who refused to convert to Christianity.&lt;ref name="CHARLEMAGNE"&gt;For the Massacre of Verden, see Barbero, Alessandro (2004). ''Charlemagne: Father of a Continent'', page 46. [[University of California Press]]. For the ''Capitulatio de partibus Saxoniae'', see Riché, Pierre (1993). ''The Carolingians''. [[University of Pennsylvania Press]]. {{ISBN|978-0-8122-1342-3}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

Forced conversion that occurred after the seventh century generally took place during riots and massacres carried out by mobs and clergy without support of the rulers. In contrast, royal persecutions of Jews from the late eleventh century onward generally took form of expulsions, with some exceptions, such as conversions of Jews in southern Italy of the 13th century, which were carried out by Dominican Inquisitors but instigated by King Charles II of Naples.&lt;ref name=soyer/&gt;

Jews were forced to convert to Christianity by the Crusaders in Lorraine, on the Lower Rhine, in Bavaria and Bohemia, in Mainz and in Worms.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Abraham Joshua Heschel, Joachim Neugroschel, Sylvia Heschel|title=Maimonides: A Biography|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ki6a7WsZYwMC&amp;pg=PA43|page=43|publisher=Macmillan|year=1983}}&lt;/ref&gt; (see [[Rhineland massacres]], [[Worms massacre (1096)]])

[[Pope Innocent III]] pronounced in 1201 that if one agreed to be baptized to avoid torture and intimidation, one nevertheless could be compelled to outwardly observe Christianity:

&lt;blockquote&gt;[T]hose who are immersed even though reluctant, do belong to ecclesiastical jurisdiction at least by reason of the sacrament, and might therefore be reasonably compelled to observe the rules of the Christian Faith. It is, to be sure, contrary to the Christian Faith that anyone who is unwilling and wholly opposed to it should be compelled to adopt and observe Christianity. For this reason a valid distinction is made by some between kinds of unwilling ones and kinds of compelled ones. Thus one who is drawn to Christianity by violence, through fear and through torture, and receives the sacrament of Baptism in order to avoid loss, he (like one who comes to Baptism in dissimulation) does receive the impress of Christianity, and may be forced to observe the Christian Faith as one who expressed a conditional willingness though, absolutely speaking, he was unwilling ...&lt;ref&gt;Chazan, Robert, ed., Church, State, and Jew in the Middle Ages, West Orange, NJ:Behrman House, 1980, p. 103.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

During the [[Northern Crusades]] against the pagan Balts and Slavs of northern Europe, forced conversions were a widely used tactic, which received papal sanction &lt;ref&gt; Christiansen, Eric. The Northern Crusades. London: Penguin Books. pg. 71&lt;/ref&gt;. These tactics were first adopted during the [[Wendish Crusade]], but became more widespread during the [[Livonian Crusade]] and [[Prussian Crusade]], in which tactics including the killing of hostages, massacre, and the devastation of the lands of tribes that had not yet submitted &lt;ref&gt; Christiansen, Eric. The Northern Crusades. London: Penguin Books. pg. 95&lt;/ref&gt;. Most of the populations of these regions were converted only after the repeated rebellion of native populations that did not want to accept Christianity even after initial forced conversion; in Old Prussia, the tactics employed in the initial conquest and subsequent conversion of the territory resulted in the death of most of the native population, whose [[Old Prussian|language]] consequently became extinct. &lt;ref&gt;''The German Hansa'', P. Dollinger, page 34, 1999, Routledge&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Early modern Iberian peninsula ===
{{main|Forced conversions of Muslims in Spain}}
{{further|Morisco|Marrano|Spanish inquisition}}
After the end of the [[Al-Andalus|Islamic control of Spain]], Jews were [[Alhambra Decree|expelled]] from Spain in 1492.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Lowenstein |first=Steven |title=The Jewish Cultural Tapestry: International Jewish Folk Traditions |year=2001 |publisher=Oxford University Press |page=36 |url=https://books.google.com/?id=EWToS3VyqVMC&amp;dq=jewish+cultural+tapestry|isbn=9780195313604 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Portugal]], following an order for their expulsion in 1496, only a handful were allowed to leave and the rest were forced to convert.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=F.J.F. Soyer|title=The Persecution of the Jews and Muslims of Portugal King Manuel I and the End of Religious Tolerance (1496-7)|date=2007|publisher=Brill|isbn=9789047431558|url=http://booksandjournals.brillonline.com/content/books/9789047431558|subscription=yes|via=Brill|pages=182}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Muslims]] [[Expulsion of Jews and Muslims from Portugal|were expelled]] from Portugal in 1497, and they were gradually forced to convert in the constituent kingdoms of Spain. The forced conversion of Muslims was implemented in the [[Crown of Castile]] from 1500–02 and in the [[Crown of Aragon]] in the 1520s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Harvey |first=L. P. |ref=harv |title=Muslims in Spain, 1500 to 1614 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=7QJygx-jbKcC |date=16 May 2005 |publisher=University of Chicago Press |isbn=978-0-226-31963-6 |p=64}}&lt;/ref&gt; After the conversions, the so-called "[[New Christian]]s" were those inhabitants ([[Sephardi]]c Jews or [[Mudéjar]] Muslims) who were baptized under coercion and in the face of execution, becoming forced converts from Islam ([[Morisco]]s, [[Converso]]s and "secret Moors") or from [[Judaism]] ([[Converso]]s, [[Crypto-Judaism|Crypto-Jews]] and [[Marrano]]s).

After the forced conversion, when all former Muslims and Jews had ostensibly become Catholic, the [[Spanish Inquisition]] targeted primarily forced converts from Judaism, who came under suspicion of either continuing to adhere to their old religion or having fallen back into it. Jewish conversos still resided in Spain and often practised [[Judaism]] secretly and were suspected by the "Old Christians" of being [[Crypto-Jew]]s. The Spanish Inquisition generated much wealth and income for the church and individual inquisitors by confiscating the property of the persecuted. The end of [[Al-Andalus]] and the [[Alhambra Decree|expulsion of the Sephardic Jews]] from the Iberian Peninsula went hand in hand with the increase of Spanish and Portuguese influence in the world, as exemplified in the Christian conquest of the Americas and their aboriginal Indian population. The [[Ottoman Empire]] and [[Morocco]] absorbed most of the Jewish refugees, although a large majority remained as Conversos.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110108184056/http://www.thejerusalemconnection.us/news-archive/tag/inquisition |title=3000 Years of Sephardic History |website=The Jerusalem Connection, International |url=http://www.thejerusalemconnection.us/news-archive/tag/inquisition |dead-url=yes |archive-date=8 January 2011 |last=Neese |first=Shelley |date=17 November 2008 |access-date=9 May 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Colonial Americas=== 
During the [[European colonization of the Americas]], forced conversion of the continents' indigenous, non-Christian population was common, especially in [[South America]] and [[Mesoamerica]], where the conquest of large indigenous polities like the [[Inca]] and [[Aztec]]Empires placed colonizers in control of large non-Christian populations. Historians broadly agree that most native populations that converted did so under the threat of violence, often because they were compelled to after being conquered, and that the Catholic Church cooperated with civil authority to achieve this end. &lt;ref&gt; Fisher, Ian. "Pope Concedes Unjustifiable Crimes in Converting South Americans". June 24, 2007. New York Times&lt;/ref&gt;
===Eastern Europe===
Upon converting to Christianity in the 10th century, [[Vladimir the Great]], the ruler of [[Kievan Rus']], ordered Kiev's citizens to undergo a mass baptism in the Dnieper river.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The Cambridge History of Russia: Volume 1, From Early Rus' to 1689|publisher=Cambridge University Press|year=2006|editor=Maureen Perrie|page=66}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 13th century the pagan populations of the [[Baltics]] faced campaigns of forcible conversion by crusading knight corps such as the [[Livonian Brothers of the Sword]] and the [[Teutonic Order]], which often meant simply dispossessing these populations of their lands and property.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Ef2cAAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA48|title=Estonia, Latvia, Lithuania, and Poland|publisher=Britannica Educational Publishing|page=48}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Latvia: A Short History|author=Mara Kalnins|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=vHpeCwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT55|page=55|publisher=Oxford University Press|year=2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After [[Ivan the Terrible]]'s conquest of the [[Khanate of Kazan]], the Muslim population faced slaughter, expulsion, forced resettlement and conversion to Christianity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The Cambridge History of Russia: Volume 1, From Early Rus' to 1689|publisher=Cambridge University Press|year=2006|editor=Maureen Perrie|pages=319–320}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 18th century, [[Elizabeth of Russia]] launched a campaign of forced conversion of Russia's non-Orthodox subjects, including Muslims and Jews.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The Cambridge History of Russia: Volume 2, Imperial Russia, 1689-1917|editor=Dominic Lieven|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=NzR0cmnP3J8C&amp;pg=PA186|page=186|publisher=Cambridge University Press|year=2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Goa inquisition ===
{{Main|Goa Inquisition}}
The Portuguese practised religious persecution in [[Goa]], India in the 16th and 17th centuries. The natives of Goa, most of them Hindus, were subjected to [[Goa Inquisition|severe torture and oppression]] by the zealous Portuguese rulers and missionaries, and forcibly converted to Christianity.&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=RS1uAAAAMAAJ Of umbrellas, goddesses, and dreams: essays on Goan culture and society], 76-120, Robert Samuel Newman, 2001&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[The Goa Inquisition (book)|The Goa Inquisition, Being a Quatercentenary Commemoration Study of the Inquisition in India]] by Anant Priolkar, Bombay University Press&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=hSnn_kDUI6AC&amp;pg=PA69 Everyday Nationalism: Women of the Hindu Right in India] Kalyani Devaki Menon, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=ftS1AAAAIAAJ Journal of the Asiatic Society of Bombay] 1967&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;M. D. David (ed.), Western Colonialism in Asia and Christianity, Bombay, 1988, p.17&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=INWSqBXundYC&amp;pg=PA137 Between ethnography and fiction: Verrier Elwin and the tribal question in India] Tanka Bahadur Subba, Sujit Som, K. C. Baral, North Eastern Hill University. Dept. of Anthropology – Social Science&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1567, the campaign to destroy temples in [[Bardez]] met with success, with 300 Hindu temples destroyed. Prohibition was laid from December 4, 1567 on rituals of Hindu marriages, sacred thread wearing and cremation. All persons above 15 years of age were compelled to listen to Christian preaching, failing which they were punished. In 1583, Hindu temples at [[Assolna]] and [[Cuncolim]] were destroyed by the Portuguese army. "The fathers of the Church forbade the Hindus under terrible penalties the use of their own sacred books, and prevented them from all exercise of their religion. They destroyed their temples, and so harassed and interfered with the people that they abandoned the city in large numbers, refusing to remain any longer in a place where they had no liberty, and were liable to imprisonment, torture and death if they worshiped after their own fashion the gods of their fathers", wrote Filippo [[Sassetti]], who was in India from 1578 to 1588. An order was issued in June 1684 for suppressing the [[Konkani]] language and making it compulsory to speak Portuguese, on pain of severe penalties. All non-Christian cultural symbols and books written in local languages were also ordered to be destroyed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.scribd.com/doc/28411503/Goa-Inquisition-for-Colonial-Disciplining |title=Goa Inquisition for Colonial Disciplining |publisher=Scribd.com |date=2010-03-15 |accessdate=2012-11-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===World War II===
During World War II, Orthodox [[World War II persecution of Serbs|Serbs were forcibly converted]] to Catholicism.&lt;ref name="Ramet2011"&gt;{{cite book|author=Sabrina P. Ramet|title=Serbia and the Serbs in World War Two|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=gkiEDAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA237|date=31 October 2011|publisher=Palgrave Macmillan UK|isbn=978-0-230-34781-6|pages=237–}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Yeomans2013"&gt;{{cite book|author=Rory Yeomans|title=Visions of Annihilation: The Ustasha Regime and the Cultural Politics of Fascism, 1941-1945|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Yxv4-iqVe2wC&amp;pg=PA21|date=April 2013|publisher=University of Pittsburgh Pre|isbn=978-0-8229-7793-3|pages=21–}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Hindus in India ===
In 2009, the ''[[Assam Times]]'' reported that about fifteen armed [[Hmar people|Hmar]] militants, members of the [[Manmasi National Christian Army]], tried to force Hindu residents of Bhuvan Pahar, [[Assam]] to convert to Christianity.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.assamtimes.org/social/3112.html Christianity threat looms over Bhuvan Pahar] Assam Times – June 23, 2009 {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090626130437/http://www.assamtimes.org/social/3112.html|date=June 26, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Islam ==
{{See also|Islamization|Apostasy in Islam#Punishment}}
Although Islamic law prohibits forced conversion, following the Quranic principle "[[Al-Baqara 256|no compulsion in religion]]" (2:256),&lt;ref name=bonner&gt;{{cite book|author=Michael Bonner|title=Jihad in Islamic History|publisher=Princeton University Press|year=2008|pages= 89–90|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Qxq7eykoJgoC&amp;pg=PA89|quote=To begin with, there was no forced conversion, no choice between "Islam and the Sword". Islamic law, following a clear Quranic principle (2:256), prohibited any such things [...] although there have been instances of forced conversion in Islamic history, these have been exceptional.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Winter, T. J., &amp; Williams, J. A. (2002). ''Understanding Islam and the Muslims: The Muslim Family Islam and World Peace''. Louisville, Kentucky: Fons Vitae. p. 82. {{ISBN|978-1-887752-47-3}}. Quote: The laws of Muslim warfare forbid any forced conversions, and regard them as invalid if they occur.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{cite book|last1 = A.C. Brown|first1 = Jonathan|authorlink=Jonathan A.C. Brown |title = Misquoting Muhammad: The Challenge and Choices of Interpreting the Prophet's Legacy|date = 2014|publisher = [[Oneworld Publications]]|isbn = 978-1-78074-420-9|page = 92|chapter = 3. The Fragile Truth Of Scripture|quote='No compulsion in religion' (2:256) was a Qur'anic command revealed in Medina when a child from one of the Muslim families who had been educated in the town's Jewish schools decided to depart with the Jewish tribe being expelled from Medina. His distraught parents were told by God and the Prophet in this verse that they could not compel their son to stay. The verse, however, has been understood over the centuries as a general command that people cannot be forced to convert to Islam.}}&lt;/ref&gt; episodes of forced conversions are recorded in the [[history of Islam]]. Historians have qualified such instances as "rare"&lt;ref name="W53"&gt;Waines (2003) "An Introduction to Islam" ''Cambridge University Press''. p. 53&lt;/ref&gt; or "exceptional".&lt;ref name=bonner/&gt;

While scholars like [[Abu Hanifa]] and [[Abu Yusuf]] stated that jizya should be imposed all non-Muslims without distinction, some later and more extremist jurists do not permit jizya for idolators and instead only allowed the choice of conversion to avoid death.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|journal=Proceedings of the Indian History Congress|volume=9|title=Political conditions of the Hindus under the Khaljis|publisher=[[Indian History Congress]]|author=[[Kishori Saran Lal]]|pages= 232}}&lt;/ref&gt; Out of the four [[madhab|schools of Islamic law]], the [[Hanafi]] and [[Maliki]] schools allow the ''[[dhimmi]]'' status for polytheists except Arab polytheists. The [[Shafi'i]] and [[Hanbali]] school however only consider Christians, Jews and Zoroastrians to be eligible to the category.&lt;ref name=Bowering&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=zaqgBQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA128|editor= Gerhard Bowering|title=Islamic Political Thought: An Introduction
|year=2009|publisher=Princeton University Press|pages=127–128 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Wael Hallaq]] states that in theory, Islamic religious tolerance applied only to monotheistic "[[People of the Book]]" like Christians, Jews and [[Zoroastrians|Magians]] if they paid the ''[[jizya]]'' tax, and pagans faced only two choices between conversion to Islam and fight to the death. In practice, the designation "People of the Book" and the [[dhimma]] status was extended even to non-monotheistic religions of conquered peoples, such as [[Hindus]], Jains, Buddhists and other non-monotheists.&lt;ref name=hallaq&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=eVJsAAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA327|author=Wael B. Hallaq|authorlink = Wael Hallaq|title=Sharī'a: Theory, Practice, Transformations|year=2009|publisher=Cambridge University Press|pages=327–328 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In recent times, forced conversions have been threatened or carried out in the context of war, insurgency and intercommunal violence. Cases affecting thousands of people are reported to have occurred during the [[Partition of India]], the [[Bangladesh Liberation War]], in areas controlled by [[Islamic State of Iraq and the Levant|ISIS]], and in [[Pakistan]]. Disputed allegations of forced conversion of young women have generated public controversy in Egypt and the UK.

=== Early period ===
The [[Ridda Wars|wars of the Ridda]] (lit. apostasy), undertaken by the first caliph [[Abu Bakr]] against tribes who had accepted Islam but refused to recognize his caliphal authority have been described by some authors as an instance of forced conversion&lt;ref&gt;{{cite encyclopedia|title=Conversion|author=Richard W. Bullient|editor=Gerhard Böwering, Patricia Crone|encyclopedia=The Princeton Encyclopedia of Islamic Political Thought|publisher=Princeton University Press|year=2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; or "reconversion".&lt;ref name=lewis2002&gt;{{Cite book|first=Bernard|last=Lewis| authorlink = Bernard Lewis | year=2002 | title=Arabs in History|publisher=Oxford University Press (Kindle edition) | page=50}}&lt;/ref&gt; The action of these tribes was less a relapse to paganism than termination of a political contract they had made with [[Muhammad]].&lt;ref name=lewis2002/&gt;

Two out of the four schools of Islamic law, i.e. Hanafi and Maliki schools, accepted non-Arab polytheists to be eligible for the ''dhimmi'' status. Under this doctrine, Arab polytheists were forced to choose between conversion and death. However, according to perception of most jurists, all Arabs had embraced Islam during the lifetime of Muhammad. Their exclusion therefore had little practical significance after his death in 632.&lt;ref name=Bowering/&gt;

In the 9th century, the [[Samaritan]] population of [[Palestine (region)|Palestine]] faced persecution and attempts at forced conversion at the hands of the rebel leader ibn Firāsa, against whom they were defended by Abbasid caliphal troops.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Moshe Gil|title=A History of Palestine, 634-1099|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=tSM4AAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA822|publisher=CUP Archive|page=822|year=1992}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Almohad dynasty ===
There were forced conversions in the 12th century under the [[Almohad]] dynasty of North Africa and [[al-Andalus|Andalusia]], who suppressed the [[dhimma]] status of Jews and Christians and gave them the choice between conversion, exile, and being killed. Christians under their rule generally chose to relocate to the Christian principalities in the north of the peninsula, while Jews decided to stay in order to keep their properties, and many of them feigned conversion to Islam, while continuing their religious practices in secrecy.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite encyclopedia| author=Maribel Fierro | entry=The Almohads (524 668/1130 1269) and the Hafsids (627 932/1229 1526) |title=The New Cambridge History of Islam|volume=Volume 2, The Western Islamic World, Eleventh to Eighteenth Centuries |publisher=Cambridge University Press |ref=harv |year=2010 |editor=Maribel Fierro|page=86}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the Almohad persecution, the Jewish philosopher [[Maimonides]] wrote his ''Epistle on Apostasy'', in which he permitted Jews to feign apostasy under duress, though strongly recommending leaving the country instead.&lt;ref name=fine&gt;{{cite book|author=Lawrence Fine|title=Judaism in Practice: From the Middle Ages Through the Early Modern Period|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ohYOD34VlXEC&amp;pg=PA414|page=414}}&lt;/ref&gt; There is dispute amongst scholars as to whether Maimonides himself converted to Islam in order to freely escape from Almohad territory, and then reconverted back to Judaism in either the Levant or in Egypt.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nysun.com/arts/the-great-rambam-joel-kramers-maimonides/86437/ |title=The Great Rambam: Joel Kraemer's 'Maimonides' – The New York Sun |publisher=Nysun.com |date=2008-09-24 |accessdate=2012-11-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; He was later denounced as an apostate and tried in an Islamic court, but the [[Qadi|judge]] ruled that his conversion had been forced and therefore invalid.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author= Bernard Lewis|title=The Jews of Islam|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=c0S4lOyfKSYC&amp;pg=PA100|page=100|publisher=Princeton University Press|year=2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Yemen===

In the late 1160s, the Yemenite ruler [['Abd-al-Nabī ibn Mahdi]] left Jews with the choice between conversion to Islam or [[martyrdom]].&lt;ref&gt;The Epistles of Maimonides: Crisis and Leadership, ed.:Abraham S. Halkin, David Hartman, Jewish Publication Society, 1985. p.91&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Festschrift/&gt; Mahdi also imposed his beliefs upon the Muslims besides the Jews. This led to a revival of Jewish [[messianism]], but also led to mass-conversion.&lt;ref name=Festschrift&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Dk6hAwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA181|title=Jews, Christians and Muslims in Medieval and Early Modern Times: A Festschrift in Honor of Mark R. Cohen|publisher=Brill Publishers|year=2014|page=181}}&lt;/ref&gt; The persecution ended in 1173 with the defeat of Ibn Mahdi and conquest of Yemen by the brother of [[Saladin]] and they were allowed to return to their faith.&lt;ref name=Festschrift/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ehlbFPJPPgQC&amp;pg=PA489|title=Moses Maimonides: The Man and His Works|author=Herbert Davidson|publisher=Oxford University Press|page=489}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to two [[Cairo Genizah]] documents, the [[Ayyubid dynasty|Ayyubid]] ruler of Yemen, al-Malik al-Mu'izz al-Ismail (reigned from 1197-1202) had attempted to force the Jews of [[Aden]] to convert. The second document details the relief of Jewish community after his murder and those who had been forced to convert reverted to Judaism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=d58QQocrWVkC&amp;pg=PA21|title=The Jews of the British Crown Colony of Aden: History, Culture, and Ethnic Relations|author=Reuben Ahroni|publisher=Brill Publishers|page=21}}&lt;/ref&gt; While he didn't impose Islam upon the foreign merchants, they were forced to pay triple the normal rate of poll tax.&lt;ref name=Festschrift/&gt;

A measure listed in the legal works by [[Muhammad ash-Shawkani|Al-Shawkānī]] is of forced conversion of Jewish orphans. No date is given for this decree by modern studies nor who issued it.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Vjg1NuC_kr0C&amp;pg=PA76|title=History as Prelude: Muslims and Jews in the Medieval Mediterranean|editor=Joseph V. Montville|publisher=Lexington Books|pages=75–76|chapter=On Muslim Curiosity and the Historiography of the Jews of Yemen|author=Ahmad Dallal}}&lt;/ref&gt; The forced conversion of Jewish orphans was reintroduced under [[Yahya Muhammad Hamid ed-Din|Imam Yahya]] in 1922. The [[Orphans' Decree]] was implemented aggressively for the first ten years. It was re-promulgated in 1928.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=S-nu8Z6yNIMC&amp;pg=PA67
|title=The Road to Redemption: The Jews of the Yemen, 1900-1950|author=[[Tudor Parfitt]]|publisher=Brill Publishers|pages=66–67, 69}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Ottoman Empire ===
[[File:Janissary Recruitment in the Balkans-Suleymanname.jpg|thumb|Registration of boys for the ''[[devşirme]]''. [[Ottoman miniature]] painting from the ''Süleymanname'', 1558.]]
{{See also|Devşirme|Christianity in the Ottoman Empire#Conversion}}

A form of forced conversion became institutionalized during the [[Ottoman Empire]] in the practice of [[devşirme]], a human levy in which Christian boys were seized and collected from their families (usually in the Balkans), enslaved, converted to Islam, and then trained as elite military unit within the Ottoman army or for high-ranking service to the sultan.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite encyclopedia |article=Conversion |first=Tijana |last=Krstić |title=Encyclopedia of the Ottoman Empire |editor1-first=Gábor |editor1-last=Ágoston |editor2-first=Bruce Alan |editor2-last=Masters |publisher=InfoBase Publishing |date=2009 |p=145–146 |quote="As a part of their education, devşirme children underwent compulsory conversion to Islam, which is the only documented forced form of conversion organized by the Ottoman state."}}&lt;/ref&gt; From the mid to late 14th, through early 18th centuries, the [[devşirme]]–[[janissary]] system enslaved an estimated 500,000 to one million non–Muslim adolescent males.&lt;ref&gt;A. E. Vacalopoulos. ''The Greek Nation'', 1453–1669, New Brunswick, New Jersey, Rutgers University Press, 1976, p. 41; Vasiliki Papoulia, The Impact of Devshirme on Greek Society, in ''War and Society in East Central Europe'', Editor—in—Chief, Bela K. Kiraly, 1982, Vol. II, pp. 561—562.&lt;/ref&gt; These boys would attain a great education and high social standing after their training and conversion.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=0HWKMh3p9JwC|title=The Janissaries|author=David Nicolle|page=12|isbn=9781855324138|date=1995-05-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 17th century, [[Sabbatai Zevi]], a Sephardic Jew whose ancestors were welcomed in the Ottoman Empire during the Spanish Inquisition, proclaimed himself the [[Messiah]] and called for abolishing major Jewish laws and customs. After he attracted a large following, he was arrested by the Ottoman authorities and given a choice between execution or conversion to Islam. He chose the latter option.&lt;ref name="tnr.com"&gt;[http://www.tnr.com/book/review/the-other-secret-jews Adam Kirsch, "The Other Secret Jews", review of Marc David Baer, ''The Dönme: Jewish Converts, Muslim Revolutionaries, and Secular Turks''], ''The New Republic'', Feb 15, 2010, accessed Feb 20, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

During the [[Greek genocide|Persecution of Greeks in the 20th century]], there were cases of forced conversion to Islam.&lt;ref name="Persecution_of_the_Greeks_in_Turkey_1914_1918"&gt;{{cite book| title = Persecution of the Greeks in Turkey, 1914-1918| url = https://archive.org/details/persecutionofgre00consrich| publisher = Constantinople [London, Printed by the Hesperia Press]|date=1919}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Persia ===
{{See also|Safavid conversion of Iran from Sunnism to Shiism}}
[[Ismail I]], the founder of the [[Safavid]] dynasty, decreed [[Twelver Shiism]] to be the official religion of state and ordered executions of a number of Sunni intellectuals who refused to accept Shiism.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite encyclopedia|authors=Savory, R.M., Gandjeï, T.| year=2012 | title=Ismāʿīl I|encyclopedia=Encyclopaedia of Islam| edition=2nd|publisher=Brill |editors=P. Bearman, Th. Bianquis, C.E. Bosworth, E. van Donzel, W.P. Heinrichs|volume=4|page=186}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite encyclopedia| author=H.R. Roemer| entry=The Safavid Period |title=The Cambridge History of Iran|volume=Volume 6|publisher=Cambridge University Press |ref=harv |year=1986 |editors=William Bayne Fisher, Peter Jackson, Lawrence Lockhart|page=218}}&lt;/ref&gt; Non-Muslims faced frequent persecutions and at times forced conversions under the rule of his dynastic successors.&lt;ref&gt;Lewis, Bernard (1984). The Jews of Islam. Princeton: Princeton University Press. {{ISBN|0-691-00807-8}}. p.52&lt;/ref&gt; Thus, after the capture of the [[Hormuz Island]], [[Abbas I of Persia|Abbas I]] required local Christians to convert to Islam, [[Abbas II of Persia|Abbas II]] granted his ministers authority to force Jews to become Muslims, and [[Sultan Husayn]] decreed forcible conversion of Zoroastrians.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book| last = Lapidus | first = Ira M. | authorlink=Ira M. Lapidus | title = A History of Islamic Societies | publisher = Cambridge University Press (Kindle edition) | year = 2014| isbn=978-0-521-51430-9 | pages=385–386}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1839, during the [[Qajar]] era the Jewish community in the city of [[Mashhad]] was attacked by a mob and subsequently forced to convert to Islam.&lt;ref name="JadidAlIslam"&gt;{{cite web|first=Jaleh |last=Pirnazar |url=http://www.fis-iran.org/en/irannameh/volxix/mashhad-jewish-community |title=The "Jadid al-Islams" of Mashhad |work=Foundation for Iranian Studies |location=Bethesda, MD, USA |publisher=[[Foundation for Iranian Studies]] |accessdate=2012-11-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===India===
In an invasion of the [[Kashmir valley]] (1015), [[Mahmud of Ghazni]] plundered the valley, took many prisoners and carried out conversions to Islam.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The History and Culture of the Indian People: The struggle for empire|author=Ramesh Chandra Majumdar|authorlink=R. C. Majumdar|year=1951|page=12}}&lt;/ref&gt; In his later campaigns, in Mathura, Baran and Kanauj, again, many conversions took place. Those soldiers who surrendered to him were converted to Islam. In Baran (Bulandshahr) alone 10,000 persons were converted to Islam including the king.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=India 2001: Reference Encyclopedia, Volume 1|page=29|author=Catherine B. Asher|publisher=South Asia Publications}}&lt;/ref&gt; Tarikh-i-Yamini, Rausat-us-Safa and Tarikh-i-Ferishtah speak of construction of mosques and schools and appointment of preachers and teachers by Mahmud and his successor Masud. Wherever Mahmud went, he insisted on the people to convert to Islam.&lt;ref name=imwat-1&gt;{{cite book| title=Indian Muslims:Who Are They| first=K.S. |last=Lal |chapter=1 |year=2004 |isbn=978-8185990101 |asin=B003DRH2FI}}&lt;/ref&gt; The raids by Muhammad Ghori and his generals brought in thousands of slaves in the late 12th century, most of whom were compelled to convert as one of the preconditions of their freedom.&lt;ref name="imwat-1"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Habibullah, ''The Foundation of Muslim Rule in India'', (Allahabad, 1961), pp.69 and 334&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hasan Nizami, ''Taj-ul-Maasir'', II, p.216&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Titus, Murray. ''Islam in India and Pakistan'', ([[Calcutta]], 1959), p.31&lt;/ref&gt; [[Sikandar Butshikan]] (1394-1417) demolished Hindu temples and forcefully converted Hindus.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Kashmir: Valley and Its Culture|author=Shiri Ram Bakshi|publisher=Sarup &amp; Sons|year=1997|page=70}}&lt;/ref&gt; Christianity thrived along the west coast during the 15th and 16th centuries following forced conversions carried out by Portuguese colonists.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Encyclopedia of Race, Ethnicity, and Society - Volume 1|page=797|publisher=SAGE|author=Richard T. Schaefer}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Aurangzeb]] employed a number of means to encourage conversions to Islam.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=A History of Modern India, 1480-1950|author=Claude Markovits|publisher=Anthem Press|page=108}}&lt;/ref&gt; In a Mughal-Sikh war in 1715, 700 followers of [[Banda Singh Bahadur]] were beheaded.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Ranjit Singh: Maharaja of the Punjab|page=22|first=Khushwant|last=Singh|publisher=Penguin UK|year=2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Every day, 100 Sikhs were executed and not even one of them apostatized from Sikhism.&lt;ref name="Rachel Fell McDermott, Leonard A. Gordon, Ainslie T. Embree, Frances W. Pritchett, Dennis Dalton 2014 9"&gt;{{cite book|title=Sources of Indian Traditions: Modern India, Pakistan, and Bangladesh|page=9|publisher=Columbia University Press|year=2014|author=Rachel Fell McDermott, Leonard A. Gordon, Ainslie T. Embree, Frances W. Pritchett, Dennis Dalton}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Banda Singh Bahadur]] was offered a pardon if he converted to Islam.&lt;ref name="Kristen Haar, Sewa Singh Kalsi 110"&gt;{{cite book|title=Sikhism|author=Kristen Haar, Sewa Singh Kalsi|page=110|publisher=Infobase publishing}}&lt;/ref&gt; Upon refusal, he was tortured,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Banda Singh Bahadur and Sikh Sovereignty|page=226|author=Harbans Kaur Sagoo|publisher=Deep and Deep Publications|year=2001}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Singh|first=Ganda|title=Life of Banda Singh Bahadur: Based on Contemporary and Original Records|year=1935|publisher=Sikh History Research Department|page=229}}&lt;/ref&gt; and was killed with his 5 year old son.&lt;ref name="Rachel Fell McDermott, Leonard A. Gordon, Ainslie T. Embree, Frances W. Pritchett, Dennis Dalton 2014 9"/&gt; Following the execution of Banda, the emperor ordered to apprehend Sikhs anywhere they were found.&lt;ref name="Kristen Haar, Sewa Singh Kalsi 110"/&gt;

18th century ruler [[Tipu Sultan]] persecuted the Hindus, Christians and [[Mappilas|Mappla Muslims]].&lt;ref name="alexander"&gt;{{cite book|title=India: History, Religion, Vision and Contribution to the World, Volume 1|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=y7GKwhuea9kC&amp;pg=PA404&amp;dq=tipu|first=Alexander|last=Varghese|publisher=Atlantic Publishers|year=2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=Thomas|last= Paul|title= Christians and Christianity in India and Pakistan: a general survey of the progress of Christianity in India from apostolic times to the present day|publisher=Allen &amp; Unwin|year=1954|page=235|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=0UegAQAACAAJ&amp;dq=Christians+and+Christianity+in+India+and+Pakistan%3A+a+general+survey+of+the+progress+of+Christianity+in+India+from+apostolic+times+to+the+present+day&amp;focus=searchwithinvolume&amp;q=tippu}}&lt;/ref&gt; During Sultan's [[Mysorean invasion of Kerala]], hundreds of temples and churches were demolished and ten thousands of Christians and Hindus were killed or converted to Islam by force.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The Ocean of Churn: How the Indian Ocean Shaped Human History|page=188|author=Sanjeev Sanyal|publisher=Penguin UK}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Citation needed|reason=Reliable source needed for the whole sentence|date=June 2018}}

=== Contemporary ===

==== Bangladesh ====
In [[Bangladesh]], the [[International Crimes Tribunal (Bangladesh)|International Crimes Tribunal]] tried and convicted several leaders of the Islamic [[Razakar (Pakistan)|Razakar]] militias, as well as Bangladesh Muslim Awami league (Forid Uddin Mausood), of [[war crimes]] committed against Hindus during the [[1971 Bangladesh genocide]]. The charges included forced conversion of [[Bengali Hindu]]s to Islam.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title= Bangladesh Islamist's death sentence sparks deadly riots|author=Anis Ahmed|url=https://www.reuters.com/article/2013/02/28/us-bangladesh-tribunal-idUSBRE91R0AN20130228 |newspaper= [[Reuters]] |date= February 28, 2013 |accessdate=March 1, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title= Clashes Kill 35 in Bangladesh After Islamist Sentenced to Hang|author1=Arun Devnath |author2=Andrew MacAskill |url=https://www.bloomberg.com/news/2013-02-28/bangladesh-sentences-islamist-leader-to-death-amid-dhaka-protest.html |newspaper=[[Bloomberg L.P.]] |date=March 1, 2013 |accessdate=March 1, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title= Death Toll From Bangladesh Unrest Reaches 44 |author1=Julfikar Ali Manik |author2=[[Jim Yardley]] |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2013/03/02/world/asia/death-toll-from-bangladesh-unrest-hits-42.html |newspaper=[[New York Times]] |date= March 1, 2013 |accessdate=March 1, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;
==== India ====
In the [[1998 Prankote massacre]], 26 Kashmiri Hindus were beheaded by Islamist militants after their refusal to convert to Islam. The militants struck when the villagers refused demands from the gunmen to convert to Islam and prove their conversion by eating beef.&lt;ref name="jk9"&gt;[https://www.nytimes.com/1998/06/20/world/gunmen-kill-25-hindus-in-kashmir-attacks.html] 26 Hindus beheeaded by Islamist militants in Kashmir&lt;/ref&gt;
During the [[Noakhali riots]] of [[Hindu]]s in 1946, several thousand Hindus were forcibly converted to Islam by Muslim mobs.&lt;ref name="khan68-69"&gt;{{cite book |title=The Great Partition: The Making of India and Pakistan |last=Khan |first=Yasmin |year=2007 |publisher=Yale University Press |location= |isbn= 978-0-300-12078-3 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=i9WdQp2pwOYC&amp;q=Noakhali#v=snippet&amp;q=Noakhali&amp;f=false |pages=68–69}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Fatal flaw in communal violence bill |author= |url=http://www.rediff.com/news/column/fatal-flaw-in-communal-violence-bill/20110602.htm |newspaper=Rediff.com |date=July 2, 2011 |accessdate=August 2, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Pakistan ====
{{see also|  Religious discrimination in Pakistan | Minorities in Pakistan | Human rights in Pakistan}}
The rise of [[Tehrik-i-Taliban Pakistan|Taliban]] [[War in North-West Pakistan|insurgency]] in Pakistan has been an influential and increasing factor in the persecution of and [[Human rights in Pakistan#Discrimination against religious minorities|discrimination against religious minorities]], such as [[Persecution of Hindus#Pakistan|Hindus]], [[Christianity in Pakistan|Christians]], [[Sikhism in Pakistan|Sikhs]], and other minorities.&lt;ref&gt;[http://mobile.nytimes.com/2014/07/16/world/asia/militants-in-pakistan-make-inroads-in-the-diverse-and-tolerant-south.html?_r=0&amp;referrer= Extremists Make Inroads in Pakistan’]&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[United Nations Human Rights Council|Human Rights Council of Pakistan]] has reported that cases of forced conversion are increasing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.refworld.org/docid/51826ef842.html|title=Refworld – USCIRF Annual Report 2013 – Countries of Particular Concern: Pakistan|author=[[United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees]]|work=Refworld |date=30 April 2013|accessdate=May 5, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Immigration and Refugee Board of Canada"&gt;{{cite web | url=https://www.justice.gov/sites/default/files/eoir/legacy/2014/03/04/PAK104258.E.pdf | title=Pakistan: Religious conversion, including treatment of converts and forced conversions (2009–2012) | publisher=Government Research Directorate, [[Immigration and Refugee Board of Canada]] | work=Responses to Information Requests | date= January 14, 2013 | accessdate=January 17, 2018| archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20170504144820/https://www.justice.gov/sites/default/files/eoir/legacy/2014/03/04/PAK104258.E.pdf| archivedate=May 4, 2017 |deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt; A 2014 report by the Movement for Solidarity and Peace (MSP) says about 1,000 [[women in Pakistan]] are forcibly converted to Islam every year (700 Christian and 300 Hindu).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=1,000 Christian, Hindu girls forced to convert to Islam every year in Pakistan: report|url=http://indiatoday.intoday.in/story/1000-christian-hindu-girls-forced-to-convert-to-islam-every-year-in-pakistan-report/1/353608.html|website=[[India Today]]|date=April 8, 2014|accessdate=January 19, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Reema|first1=Abbasititle|title=Pakistan needs a law to protect Hindus from forced conversion| url=http://www.dailymail.co.uk/indiahome/indianews/article-2601827/Pakistan-needs-law-protect-Hindus-forced-conversion.html |website=[[Daily Mail]]|date=April 11, 2014|accessdate=January 19, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Anwar|first1=Iqbal|title=1,000 minority girls forced in marriage every year: report|url=http://www.dawn.com/news/1098452|website=Dawn|accessdate=25 July 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Dunya|first1=Author|title=India ruling party chief urges law against religious conversions|url=http://dunyanews.tv/index.php/en/World/251054-India-ruling-party-chief-urges-law-against-religio|website=[[Dunya News]] |date=20 December 2014|accessdate=20 December 2014|location=New Delhi |agency=[[Agence France-Presse|AFP]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2003 a six-year-old Sikh girl was kidnapped by a member of the [[Afridi]] tribe in Northwest Frontier Province; the alleged kidnapper claimed the girl was actually 12-years-old, and had converted to Islam so therefore could not be returned to her non-Muslim family.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=[[Annual Report on International Religious Freedom]], 2004|year=2005|publisher=[[United States Commission on International Religious Freedom]], [[State Dept (US)]], [[Senate Committee on Foreign Relations]] (US)|page=667|chapter= Pakistan |chapterurl=https://books.google.com/books?id=04dlwzB2SvcC&amp;pg=PA667|ISBN=0-16072-552-6}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In May 2007, members of the Christian community of [[Charsadda]] in the [[Khyber Pakhtunkhwa|North West Frontier Province]] of Pakistan, close to the border of [[Afghanistan]], reported that they had received letters threatening bombings if they did not convert to Islam, and that the police were not taking their fears seriously.&lt;ref name="Fox News"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,273075,00.html|title=Taliban Tells Pakistani Christians: Convert or Die|work=[[Fox News]]|accessdate=May 5, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In June 2009, [[International Christian Concern]] (ICC) reported the rape and killing of a Christian man in Pakistan, for refusing to convert to Islam.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,526126,00.html |title=Christian Man Raped, Murdered for Refusing to Convert to Islam, Family Says |publisher=FOX News |date=June 13, 2009 |first=Nora |last=Zimmett|accessdate=June 11, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Rinkle Kumari, a 19-year Pakistani student, Lata Kumari, and Asha Kumari, a Hindu working in a beauty parlor, were allegedly forced to convert from Hinduism to Islam.&lt;ref name="fridaytimesrinkle"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thefridaytimes.com/beta2/tft/article.php?issue=20120413&amp;page=9 |title=Opinion: Rinkle Kumari – the new Marvi of Sindh by Marvi Sirmed |publisher=Thefridaytimes.com |date= |accessdate=2012-06-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://pakobserver.net/detailnews.asp?id=151043 |title=SC orders release of Rinkle Kumari, others |work=[[Pakistan Observer]]|date= April 19, 2012|accessdate=2012-06-05 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140221063358/http://pakobserver.net/detailnews.asp?id=151043 |archivedate=2014-02-21 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt; Their cases were appealed all the way to the [[Supreme Court of Pakistan]] where they said that they wanted to live with their parents and not their 'so called' husbands.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.dailytimes.com.pk/default.asp?page=2012\04\19\story_19-4-2012_pg7_3 |title=Leading News Resource of Pakistan |work=[[Daily Times (Pakistan)|Daily Times]] |date=2012-04-19 |accessdate=2012-06-05 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120604015903/http://www.dailytimes.com.pk/default.asp?page=2012%5C04%5C19%5Cstory_19-4-2012_pg7_3 |archive-date=2012-06-04 |dead-url=yes |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Sikhs]] in [[Hangu District, Khyber Pakhtunkhwa|Hangu district]] were being pressured to convert to Islam by a government official in 2017.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://tribune.com.pk/story/1585150/1-sikh-community-hangu-forced-convert/|title=Sikh community in Hangu 'being forced to convert' |date=16 December 2017|publisher=[[The Express Tribune]]|accessdate=16 January 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hindustantimes.com/world-news/sikhs-in-pakistan-complain-of-pressure-to-convert/story-945AGLoXUjfEam6dZo2KBJ.html|title=Sikhs in Pakistan complain of pressure to convert|date=16 December 2017|publisher=|accessdate=16 January 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.rabwah.net/sikhs-told-convert-islam-pakistani-official/|title=Sikhs told to 'convert to Islam' by Pakistani official|website=[[Rabwah Times]]|date=December 16, 2017|accessdate=16 January 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.voanews.com/a/pakistan-sikh-minority-forced-conversion/4177063.html|title=Authorities Investigate Cases of Forced Conversion of Sikh Minority in Pakistan|first=Madeeha|last=Anwar|publisher=[[Voice of America]]|work= Extremism Watch Desk|date=December 23, 2017|accessdate=16 January 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Indonesia ====
In 2012, over 1000 Catholic children in [[East Timor]], removed from their families, were reported to being held in Indonesia without consent of their parents, forcibly converted to Islam, educated in Islamic schools and naturalized.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://vaticaninsider.lastampa.it/en/world-news/detail/articolo/indonesia-12401/|title=Indonesia: thousands of Catholic children kidnapped and forced to convert to Islam|publisher=|accessdate=May 5, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other reports claim forced conversion of minority [[Ahmadiyya]] sect Muslims to Sunni Islam, with the use of violence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thejakartapost.com/news/2012/11/06/sampang-shiites-forced-convert-sunni-kontras.html|title=Sampang Shiites forced to convert to Sunni: Kontras|publisher=|accessdate=May 5, 2015|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150430142144/http://www.thejakartapost.com/news/2012/11/06/sampang-shiites-forced-convert-sunni-kontras.html|archive-date=2015-04-30|dead-url=yes|df=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/feb/07/indonesia-inquiry-ahmadiyah-muslims-killed|title=Indonesian president condemns mob killing of Ahmadiyah Muslims|work=the Guardian|accessdate=May 5, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://law.unimelb.edu.au/__data/assets/pdf_file/0007/1547791/crouch_final_website1.pdf |title= Indonesia, Militant Islam and Ahmadiya |first=Melissa |last=Crouch |year=2010 |publisher=University of Melbourne, Australia |archiveurl=https://www.researchgate.net/publication/228298140_Indonesia_Militant_Islam_and_Ahmadiyah_Origins_and_Implications |archivedate=2017-12-21 |dead-url=no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2001 the [[Indonesia]]n army evacuated hundreds of Christian refugees from the remote [[Kesui]] and [[Teor (island)|Teor]] islands in [[Maluku (province)|Maluku]] after the refugees stated that they had been forced to convert to Islam. According to reports, some of the men had been circumcised against their will, and a paramilitary group involved in the incident confirmed that circumcisions had taken place while denying any element of coercion.&lt;ref&gt;Maluku refugees allege forced circumcision, BBC News Online, Wednesday, January 31, 2001 [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/asia-pacific/1146224.stm]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2017, many members of the [[Orang Rimba]] tribe, especially children, were being forced to renounce their folk religion and convert to Islam.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=https://www.bbc.com/news/world-asia-41981430 |title=Indonesia's Orang Rimba: Forced to renounce their faith |first=Rebecca |last=Henschke |work=BBC|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20171117121109/http://www.bbc.com/news/world-asia-41981430|archivedate=17 November 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Middle-East ====
{{Further|Persecution of Yazidis by the Islamic State of Iraq and the Levant|Persecution of Assyrians by the Islamic State of Iraq and the Levant|Abduction and forced conversion of Coptic women}}

There have been a number of reports of attempts to forcibly convert religious minorities in [[Iraq]].  The [[Yazidi]] people of northern Iraq, who follow an ethnoreligious syncretic faith, have been threatened with forced conversion by the [[Islamic State of Iraq and the Levant]], who consider their practices to be [[Satanism]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=O'Loughlin|first1=Ed|title=Devil in the detail as Yazidis look to Kurds in withstanding Islamic radicals' advance|url=http://www.irishtimes.com/news/world/middle-east/devil-in-the-detail-as-yazidis-look-to-kurds-in-withstanding-islamic-radicals-advance-1.1898441|accessdate=16 August 2014|work=[[Irish Times]]|date=16 August 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; UN investigators have reported mass killings of Yazidi men and boys who refused to convert to Islam.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|publisher=New York Times|title=ISIS Committed Genocide Against Yazidis in Syria and Iraq, U.N. Panel Says|author=Nick Cumming-Bruce|date=June 16, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; In Baghdad, hundreds of [[Assyrian people|Assyrian]] Christians fled their homes in 2007 when a local extremist group announced that they had to convert to Islam, pay the [[jizya]] or die.&lt;ref name="Radio National"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.abc.net.au/rn/religionreport/stories/2007/1937124.htm|title=Christian Minorities in the Islamic Middle East : Rosie Malek-Yonan on the Assyrians|work=Radio National|accessdate=May 5, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; In March 2007 the BBC reported that people in the [[Mandaean]] ethnic and religious minority in [[Iraq]] alleged that they were being targeted by [[Islamist]] insurgents, who offered them the choice of conversion or death.&lt;ref name="news.bbc.co.uk"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/6412453.stm|title=BBC NEWS – Middle East – Iraq's Mandaeans 'face extinction'|publisher=|accessdate=May 5, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Allegations of [[Coptic Christian]] girls being forced to marry Arab Muslim men and convert to Islam in Egypt have been reported by a number of news and advocacy organizations&lt;ref name="Shanahan"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.theaustralian.com.au/news/world/no-going-back-for-egypts-converted-copts/story-e6frg6so-1226059884457|title=No going back for Egypt's converted Copts|last=Shanahan|first=Angela|date=May 21, 2011|work=The Australian|accessdate=September 13, 2015|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110823004408/http://www.theaustralian.com.au/news/world/no-going-back-for-egypts-converted-copts/story-e6frg6so-1226059884457|archivedate=23 August 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.ipsnews.net/2013/04/missing-christian-girls-leave-trail-of-tears/ |title=Missing Christian girls leave a trail of tears |first=Cam |last=McGrath |work=Inter Press Agency |date=April 16, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.refworld.org/docid/519dd4ca61.html|title=Refworld – 2012 Report on International Religious Freedom – Egypt|author=United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees|work=Refworld|accessdate=May 5, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; and have sparked public protests.&lt;ref&gt;Heba Saleh (BBC News, Cairo), [http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/4080777.stm 'Conversion' sparks Copt protest]. BBC News Online December 9, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt; According to a 2009 report by the US State Department, observers have found it extremely difficult to determine whether compulsion was used, and in recent years no such cases have been independently verified.&lt;ref name=us-state-dept&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.state.gov/j/drl/rls/irf/2009/127346.htm|title=Egypt|work=U.S. Department of State|accessdate=May 5, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2006 two journalists of the Fox News Network were kidnapped at gunpoint in the [[Gaza Strip]] by a previously unknown militant group. After being forced to read statements on videotape proclaiming that they had converted to Islam, they were released by their captors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://edition.cnn.com/2006/WORLD/meast/08/27/fox.journalists/|title=CNN.com – Kidnapped Fox journalists released – Aug 27, 2006|publisher=|accessdate=May 5, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Africa ====
In August 2009, [[International Christian Concern]] reported that four [[Christians]] working to help orphans in [[Somalia]] were beheaded by Islamist extremists when they refused to convert to Islam.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,539129,00.html |title=Al Shabaab Reportedly Beheads 4 Christians, Rips Gold Teeth From Locals' Mouths |publisher=FOX News |date=August 12, 2009 |author= |accessdate=June 11, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the early 2010s, the Nigerian extremist group [[Boko Haram]] is reported to have forced a kidnapped Christian woman to convert to Islam at knifepoint.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.foxnews.com/world/2013/11/19/convert-or-die-nigerian-terrorist-group-boko-haram-tells-christian-women/ 'Convert or die,' Nigerian terrorist group Boko Haram tells Christian women] Fox News (November 2013)&lt;/ref&gt; A Christian woman in 2018 was raped repeatedly by a Boko Haram terrorist for refusing to convert to Islam and her son was killed.&lt;ref&gt;https://www.christianpost.com/news/islamic-radical-drowns-christian-womans-baby-rapes-and-impregnates-her-219457/&lt;/ref&gt;

==== United Kingdom ====
According to the UK prison officers' union, some Muslim prisoners in the UK have been forcibly converting fellow inmates to Islam in prisons.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Withnall |first=A. |url=https://www.independent.co.uk/news/uk/home-news/britain-s-jails-facing-growing-problem-of-forced-conversion-to-islam-officers-warn-8892645.html |title=Britain's jails facing 'growing problem' of forced conversion to Islam, officers warn |work=The Independent |location=UK |date=20 October 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the ''[[Daily Mail]]'', in 2007, commissioner of police Sir [[Ian Blair]] stated the police were targeting extremist members of the Muslim community who were allegedly forcing vulnerable girls to convert to Islam in response to claims made by the Hindu Forum.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Police protect girls forced to convert to Islam |url=http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-437871/Police-protect-girls-forced-convert-Islam.html|publisher=Daily Mail|accessdate=19 August 2013|date=22 February 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2007 a Sikh girl's family claimed that she had been forcibly converted to Islam, and they received a police guard after being attacked by an armed gang, although the "Police said no one was injured in the incident".&lt;ref name=bm2007&gt;{{cite web|last=Cowan|first=Mark|title=Police guard girl 'forced to become Muslim' |url=http://icbirmingham.icnetwork.co.uk/mail/news/tm_headline=police-guard-girl--forced-to-become-muslim-%26method=full%26objectid=19253457%26siteid=50002-name_page.html|publisher=Birmingham Mail|accessdate=19 August 2013|date=June 6, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In response to these news stories, an open letter to Sir Ian Blair, signed by ten Hindu academics, argued that claims that Hindu and Sikh girls were being forcefully converted were "part of an arsenal of myths propagated by right-wing Hindu supremacist organisations in India".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|publisher=[[Islamic Human Rights Commission]]|title='Forced Conversions' Myth Mongering By British Police|date=Feb 25, 2007|accessdate=Jul 4, 2017|url=http://www.ihrc.org.uk/show.php?id=2511}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!-- I can't find it at https://www.theguardian.com/tone/letters/2007/feb/25/all, but it's also at https://www.mail-archive.com/sacw@insaf.net/msg00559.html --&gt; The [[Muslim Council of Britain]] issued a press release pointing out there is a lack of evidence of any forced conversions and suggested it is an underhand attempt to smear the British Muslim population.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite |author=Muslim Council of Britain |date=8 March 2007 |title=MCB calls for evidence of alleged 'forced conversions' |location=London, UK |publisher=Author |url=http://www.mcb.org.uk/mcb-calls-for-evidence-of-alleged-forced-conversions/ |access-date=4 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

An academic paper by Katy Sian published in the journal ''South Asian Popular Culture'' in 2011 explored the question of how "'forced' conversion narratives" arose around the [[Sikhism in the United Kingdom|Sikh diaspora in the United Kingdom]].&lt;ref name=Forced&gt;{{cite journal | title = 'Forced' conversions in the British Sikh diaspora | first=Katy P. |last=Sian |date=2011 |journal = South Asian Popular Culture |volume=9 |issue=2 |p=115–130 |doi=10.1080/14746681003798060}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sian, who reports that claims of conversion through courtship on campuses are widespread in the UK, indicates that rather than relying on actual evidence they primarily rest on the word of "a friend of a friend" or on personal [[anecdote]]. According to Sian, the narrative is similar to accusations of "[[Human trafficking|white slavery]]" lodged against the Jewish community and foreigners to the UK and the US, with the former having ties to [[anti-semitism]] that mirror the [[Islamophobia]] betrayed by the modern narrative. Sian expanded on these views in 2013's ''Mistaken Identities, Forced Conversions, and Postcolonial Formations''.&lt;ref name="Sian2013"&gt;{{cite book|first=Katy P. |last=Sian |title=Unsettling Sikh and Muslim Conflict: Mistaken Identities, Forced Conversions, and Postcolonial Formations |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=-9AZ2atcd-kC&amp;pg=PA55 |accessdate=15 June 2013|date=2013|publisher=Rowman &amp; Littlefield|isbn=978-0-7391-7874-4|pages=55–71}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Hinduism ==
Indian Christians have alleged that "radical Hindu groups" in [[Orissa, India]] have forced Christian converts from Hinduism to "revert"&lt;ref name="revert"&gt;the word ''revert'' is used in this context; not ''convert''; see [https://www.jstor.org/stable/4413900 Older than the Church: Christianity and Caste in The God of Small Things India] by A Sekhar;[http://www.washingtontimes.com/news/2010/mar/11/proselytism-on-the-table Washington post article]&lt;/ref&gt; to Hinduism. These "religious riots" were largely between two tribal groups in [[Orissa, India|Orissa]], one of which was predominantly Hindu and another predominantly Christian, over the [[Murder of Swami Lakshmanananda|assassination]] of a Hindu leader named [[Swami Lakshmanananda]] by [[Maoists]] operating as terrorist groups in India (see [[Naxalite]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hindujagruti.org/news/5576.html |title=We killed Swami Laxmananda: Christian Maoist leader – Attack |publisher=hindujagruti.org |date=2008-10-06 |accessdate=2012-11-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the aftermath of the violence, American Christian evangelical groups have claimed that Hindu groups are "forcibly reverting" Christians converts from Hinduism back to Hinduism.&lt;ref name="revert" /&gt; It has also been alleged that groups have converted poor Muslims and Christians to Hinduism against their will and through allurements.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.bbc.com/news/world-asia-india-30429118|title=Indian Agra Muslim fear conversions to Hinduism|work=BBC News|accessdate=May 5, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.catholicherald.co.uk/news/2014/12/30/cardinal-protests-against-forced-conversion-of-christians-to-hinduism/|title=CatholicHerald.co.uk » Cardinal protests against forced conversions to Hinduism|publisher=|accessdate=May 5, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly Hindus claim that Christian missionaries used money and free education to lure Hindus for conversion. There are many conspiracy theories used by church for conversion of Hindus.&lt;ref&gt;Popular Christianity in India: Riting between the Lines, 259, Selva J. Raj, Corinne G. Dempsey, SUNY Press&lt;/ref&gt;

== Atheism ==
[[File:St. Teodora de la Sihla Church, Chişinău.jpg|thumb|300px|"[[St. Teodora de la Sihla Church|St. Theodora Church]] in downtown [[Chişinău]] was converted into the city's Museum of Scientific Atheism".&lt;br /&gt; —[[:ro:Andrei Brezianu|Andrei Brezianu]]&lt;ref name="BrezianuSpânu2010" /&gt;]]

=== Eastern Bloc ===
Under the doctrine of [[state atheism]] in the Soviet Union, there was a "government-sponsored program of forced conversion to [[Marxist-Leninist atheism|atheism]]" conducted by Communists.&lt;ref&gt;Religion and the State in Russia and China: Suppression, Survival, and Revival, by Christopher Marsh, page 47. Continuum International Publishing Group, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Inside Central Asia: A Political and Cultural History, by Dilip Hiro. Penguin, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Adappur2000"&gt;{{cite book|last=Adappur|first=Abraham|title=Religion and the Cultural Crisis in India and the West|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=44DYAAAAMAAJ|accessdate=14 July 2016|year=2000|publisher=Intercultural Publications|language=English |isbn=9788185574479|quote=Forced Conversion under Atheistic Regimes: It might be added that the most modern example of forced "conversions" came not from any theocratic state, but from a professedly atheist government — that of the Soviet Union under the Communists.}}&lt;/ref&gt; This program included the overarching objective to establish not only a fundamentally materialistic conception of the universe, but to foster "direct and open criticism of the religious outlook" by means of establishing an "anti-religious trend" across the entire school.&lt;ref&gt;Statement of Principles and Policy on Atheistic Education in Soviet Russia, translation from Russian, Stephen Schmidt, S.J., transcribed P. Legrand, page 3&lt;/ref&gt;  The [[Russian Orthodox Church]], for centuries the strongest of all Orthodox Churches, was violently suppressed.&lt;ref name="Viking p.494"&gt;[[Geoffrey Blainey]]; ''[[A Short History of Christianity]]''; Viking; 2011; p.494&lt;/ref&gt;  Revolutionary leader [[Vladimir Lenin]] wrote that every religious idea and every idea of God "is unutterable vileness... of the most dangerous kind, 'contagion of the most abominable kind".&lt;ref name="MartinAmis"&gt;Martin Amis; Koba the Dread; Vintage Books; London; 2003; {{ISBN|1400032202}}; p.30-31&lt;/ref&gt; Many priests were killed and imprisoned. Thousands of churches were closed, some turned into hospitals. In 1925 the government founded the [[League of Militant Atheists]] to intensify the persecution.&lt;ref&gt;Geoffrey Blainey; A Short History of Christianity; Viking; 2011; p.494"&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Bezbozhnik u stanka 22-1929.jpg|thumb|left|upright|1929 cover of the USSR [[League of Militant Atheists]] [[Bezbozhnik (magazine)|magazine]], showing the gods of the [[Abrahamic religions]] being crushed by the [[first five-year plan|Communist 5-year plan]]]]

Christopher Marsh, a professor at the [[Baylor University]] writes that "Tracing the social nature of religion from Schleiermacher and Feurbach to Marx, Engles, and Lenin...the idea of religion as a social product evolved to the point of policies aimed at the forced conversion of believers to atheism."&lt;ref name="Marsh2011"&gt;{{cite book|last=Marsh|first=Christopher|title=Religion and the State in Russia and China: Suppression, Survival, and Revival|date=20 January 2011|publisher=Bloomsbury Publishing|language=English|isbn=978-1-4411-0284-3|pages=13}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Jonathan Blake of the Department of Political Science at [[Columbia University]] elucidates the history of this practice in the USSR, stating that:&lt;ref name="Blake2014" /&gt;

{{quote|God, however, did not simply vanish after the Bolshevik revolution. Soviet authorities relied heavily on coercion to spread their idea of scientific atheism. This included confiscating church goods and property, forcibly closing religious institutions and executing religious leaders and believers or sending them to the [[gulag]]. … Later, the United States passed the Jackson-Vanik amendment which harmed US-Soviet trade relations until the USSR permitted the emigration of religious minorities, primarily Jews. Despite the threat from coreligionists abroad, however, the Soviet Union engaged in forced atheism from its earliest days.&lt;ref name="Blake2014"&gt;{{cite book|last=Blake|first=Jonathan S. |title="By the Sword of God": Explaining Forced Religious Conversion|date=19 April 2014|publisher=[[Columbia University]]|language=English|pages=15, 17}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Across [[Eastern Europe]] following [[World War II]], the parts of the [[Nazi Empire]] conquered by the Soviet [[Red Army]], and Yugsolavia became one party Communist states and the project of coercive conversion continued.&lt;ref&gt;Peter Hebblethwaite; Paul VI, the First Modern Pope; Harper Collins Religious; 1993; p.211&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Norman Davies; Rising '44: the Battle for Warsaw; Vikiing; 2003; p.566 &amp; 568&lt;/ref&gt; The Soviet Union ended its war time truce against the Russian Orthodox Church, and extended its persecutions to the newly Communist Eastern bloc: "In [[Polish anti-religious campaign|Poland]], Hungary, Lithuania and other Eastern European countries, Catholic leaders who were unwilling to be silent were denounced, publicly humiliated or imprisoned by the Communists. Leaders of the national Orthodox Churches in [[Religious persecution in Communist Romania|Romania]] and Bulgaria had to be cautious and submissive", wrote Blainey.&lt;ref name="Viking p.494"/&gt; While the churches were generally not as severely treated as they had been in the USSR, nearly all their schools and many of their churches were closed, and they lost their formally prominent roles in public life. Children were taught atheism, and clergy were imprisoned by the thousands.&lt;ref name="Viking p.508"&gt;[[Geoffrey Blainey]]; ''[[A Short History of Christianity]]''; Viking; 2011; p.508&lt;/ref&gt;

In the [[Eastern Bloc]], Christian churches, Jewish synagogues and Islamic mosques were forcibly "converted into museums of atheism."&lt;ref name="FranklinWiddis2006"&gt;{{cite book|last1=Franklin|first1=Simon|last2=Widdis|first2=Emma|title=National Identity in Russian Culture|date=2 February 2006|publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]]|language=English|isbn=978-0-521-02429-7|page=104|quote=Churches, when not destroyed, might find themselves converted into museums of atheism.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Bevan2016"&gt;{{cite book|last=Bevan|first=Robert|title=The Destruction of Memory: Architecture at War|date=15 February 2016|publisher=Reaktion Books|language=English|isbn=978-1-78023-608-7|page=152|quote=Churches, synagogues, mosques and monasteries were shut down in the immediate wake of the Revolution. Many were converted to secular uses or Museums of Atheism (antichurches), whitewashed and their fittings removed.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Historical essayist [[:ro:Andrei Brezianu|Andrei Brezianu]] expounds upon this situation, specifically in the [[Socialist Republic of Romania]], writing that scientific atheism was "aggressively applied to Moldova, immediately after the 1940 annexation, when churches were profaned, clergy assaulted, and signs and public symbols of religion were prohibited"; he provides an example of this phenomenon, further writing that "St. Theodora Church in downtown Chişinău was converted into the city's Museum of Scientific Atheism".&lt;ref name="BrezianuSpânu2010"&gt;{{cite book|last1=Brezianu|first1=Andrei|title=The A to Z of Moldova|date=26 May 2010|publisher=Scarecrow Press|language=English|isbn=978-0-8108-7211-0|page=98|quote=Communist Atheism. Official doctrine of the Soviet regime, also called "scientific atheism." It was aggressively applied to Moldova, immediately after the 1940 annexation, when churches were profaned, clergy assaulted, and signs and public symbols of religion were prohibited, and it was applied again throughout the subsequent decades of the Soviet regime, after 1944. … The St. Theodora Church in downtown Chişinău was converted into the city's Museum of Scientific Atheism,}}&lt;/ref&gt; Marxist-Leninist regimes treated religious believers as subversives or abnormal, sometimes relegating them to psychiatric hospitals and reeducation.{{sfn|McGrath|2006|p=46}}&lt;ref name="Froese2008"&gt;{{cite book|last=Froese|first=Paul|title=The Plot to Kill God: Findings from the Soviet Experiment in Secularization|date=6 August 2008|publisher=University of California Press|language=English |isbn=978-0-520-94273-8|page=122|quote=Before 1937, the Soviet regime had closed thousands of churches and removed tens of thousands of religious leaders from positions of influence. By the midthirties, Soviet elites set out to conduct a mass liquidation of all religious organizations and leaders... officers in the League of Militant Atheists found themselves in a bind to explain the widespread persistence of religious belief in 1937.... The latest estimates indicate that thousands of individuals were executed for religious crimes and hundreds of thousands of religious believers were imprisoned in labor camps or psychiatric hospitals.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nevertheless, historian Emily Baran writes that "some accounts suggest the conversion to militant atheism did not always end individuals' existential questions".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Baran|first=Emily|year=2011|title="I saw the light": Former Protestant believer testimonials in the Soviet Union, 1957-1987 |journal=Cahiers Du Monde Russe |volume=52|issue=1|pages=163–184 |url=http://monderusse.revues.org/9325 |quote=Atheist agitators hoped that such stories would help to convince believers and non-believers alike that the search for purpose in life could be solved with the discovery of atheism and communism. Yet some accounts suggest the conversion to militant atheism did not always end individuals' existential questions. To begin with, many former believers joined and left several religious organizations prior to renouncing faith altogether. Their life history could not be simply divided into two halves. One man recounted having joined the Baptists, Pentecostals, and the Seventh-Day Adventists before abandoning religion. Another man had been an Old Believer, Baptist, Pentecostal, and Witness. In other words, many believers had spent time as non-believers, but found life without religious faith somehow unsatisfying. As a result, some former believers admitted to having previously left religious organizations, only to return to them later. Many of them noted how after publicly denouncing Protestantism, they continued to receive visits from their former religious leaders asking them to reconsider. Indeed, atheist propaganda sometimes included complaints that once a believer had been convinced to leave his faith, atheist agitators lost interest in him, viewing the case as resolved.&lt;!--|language=English--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== French Revolution ===
During the [[French Revolution]], a [[Dechristianisation of France during the French Revolution|campaign of dechristianization]] happened which included removal and destruction of religious objects from places of worship; English librarian [[Thomas Hartwell Horne]] and biblical scholar [[Samuel Davidson]] write that "churches were converted into 'temples of reason,' in which atheistical and licesntious homilies were substituted for the proscribed service".&lt;ref name="HorneDavidson2013"&gt;{{cite book|last1=Horne|first1=Thomas Hartwell|last2=Davidson|first2=Samuel|title=An Introduction to the Critical Study and Knowledge of the Holy Scriptures|date=21 November 2013|publisher=Cambridge University Press|language=English |isbn=978-1-108-06772-0|page=30}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Latreille, A. FRENCH REVOLUTION, New Catholic Encyclopedia v. 5, pp. 972–973 (Second Ed. 2002 Thompson/Gale) {{ISBN|0-7876-4004-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Spielvogel2005|Spielvogel (2005)]]:549.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Tallet1991|Tallet (1991)]]:1&lt;/ref&gt;

Unlike later establishments of state atheism by communist regimes, the French Revolutionary experiment was short (7 months), incomplete and inconsistent.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last=McGrath | first=Alistair E. | authorlink=Alistair McGrath |title=The Twilight of Atheism: The Rise And Fall of Disbelief in the Modern World | publisher=Galilee | year=2006 | isbn=978-0-385-50062-3 | url=https://books.google.com/books?id=NVCKDQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA45 | accessdate=9 May 2017 | page=45 |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Better source|reason= source is unreliable, not serious at all|date=November 2013}} Although brief, the French experiment was particularly notable for the influence upon atheists [[Ludwig Feuerbach]], [[Sigmund Freud]] and [[Karl Marx]].{{sfn|McGrath|2006|p=46}}

===East Asian Communism===
The emergence of Communist states across [[East Asia]] after World War Two saw religion purged by atheist regimes across [[China]], [[North Korea]] and much of [[Indochina|Indo-China]].&lt;ref name="Geoffrey Blainey p.508"&gt;Geoffrey Blainey; A Short History of Christianity; Viking; 2011; p.508&lt;/ref&gt; In 1949, China became a Communist state under the leadership of [[Mao Zedong]]'s [[Communist Party of China]]. China itself had been a cradle of religious thought since ancient times, being the birthplace of [[Confucianism]] and [[Daoism]], and Buddhists having arrived in the first century AD. Under Mao, China became officially atheist, and though some religious practices were permitted to continue under State supervision, religious groups deemed a threat to order have been suppressed—as with [[Tibetan Buddhism]] from 1959 and [[Falun Gong]] in recent years.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/111803/China/258959/Altaic#toc258961 Encyclopædia Britannica Online - China: Religion]; accessed 10 November 2013&lt;/ref&gt; Religious schools and social institutions were closed, foreign missionaries expelled, and local religious practices discouraged.&lt;ref name="Geoffrey Blainey p.508"/&gt; During the [[Cultural Revolution]], Mao instigated "struggles" against the Four Olds: "old ideas, customs, culture, and habits of mind".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/111803/China/71854/Attacks-on-party-members Encyclopædia Britannica Online - China - History: Cultural Revolution]; accessed 10 November 2013&lt;/ref&gt; In 1999, the Communist Party launched a three-year drive to promote atheism in Tibet, saying intensifying propaganda on atheism is "especially important for Tibet because atheism plays an extremely important role in promoting economic construction, social advancement and socialist spiritual civilization in the region".&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/world/monitoring/253345.stm China announces "civilizing" atheism drive in Tibet]; BBC; January 12, 1999&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Revolutionary Mexico ===
{{See also|Plutarco Elías Calles|Calles Law|Cristero War}}

Articles 3, 5, 24, 27, and 130 of the [[Constitution of Mexico|Mexican Constitution of 1917]] as originally enacted were [[Anti-clericalism|anticlerical]] and enormously restricted religious freedoms.&lt;ref name="lawreview.byu.edu"&gt;Soberanes Fernandez, Jose Luis, [http://lawreview.byu.edu/archives/2002/2/Sob12.pdf Mexico and the 1981 United Nations Declaration on the Elimination of All Forms of Intolerance and of Discrimination Based on Religion or Belief], pp. 437-438 nn. 7-8, BYU Law Review, June 2002&lt;/ref&gt; At first the anticlerical provisions were only sporadically enforced, but when President [[Plutarco Elías Calles]] took office, he enforced the provisions strictly.&lt;ref name="lawreview.byu.edu" /&gt; Calles' Mexico has been characterized as an atheist state&lt;ref&gt;Haas, Ernst B., [https://books.google.com/books?id=ldKJ_Re6p8AC&amp;pg Nationalism, Liberalism, and Progress: The dismal fate of new nations], Cornell Univ. Press 2000&lt;/ref&gt; and his program as being one to eradicate religion in Mexico.&lt;ref&gt;Cronon, E. David "American Catholics and Mexican Anticlericalism, 1933-1936", pp. 205-208, Mississippi Valley Historical Review, XLV, Sept. 1948&lt;/ref&gt;

All religions had their properties expropriated, and these became part of government wealth. There was a forced expulsion of foreign clergy and the seizure of Church properties.&lt;ref name="ilstu.edu"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ilstu.edu/class/hist263/docs/1917const.html |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2007-03-03 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070303014932/http://www.ilstu.edu/class/hist263/docs/1917const.html |archivedate=2007-03-03 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt; Article 27 prohibited any future acquisition of such property by the churches, and prohibited religious corporations and ministers from
establishing or directing primary schools.&lt;ref name="ilstu.edu" /&gt; This second prohibition was sometimes interpreted to mean that the Church could not give religious instruction to children within the churches on Sundays, seen as destroying the ability of Catholics to be educated in their own religion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.myheritage.es/FP/newsItem.php?s=114433561&amp;newsID=68&amp;sourceList=dir|title=THE DECLINE AND FALL OF THE MARTIN-DEL-CAMPOs Part II|publisher=myheritage.es}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!-- see also http://toolserver.org/~dcoetzee/duplicationdetector/compare.php?url1=http%3A%2F%2Fen.wikipedia.org%2Fw%2Findex.php%3Ftitle%3DState_atheism&amp;url2=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.nairaland.com%2F723007%2Ftai-solarin-life-ideas-accomplishments%2F2&amp;minwords=2&amp;minchars=13 --&gt;

The Constitution of 1917 also closed and forbade the existence of monastic orders (article 5), forbade any religious activity outside of church buildings (now owned by the government), and mandated that such religious activity would be overseen by the government (article 24).&lt;ref name="ilstu.edu" /&gt;

On June 14, 1926, President Calles enacted [[anticlerical]] legislation known formally as The Law Reforming the Penal Code and unofficially as the [[Calles Law]].&lt;ref name="Joes, Anthony James p. 70"&gt;Joes, Anthony James [https://books.google.com/books?id=buHXFDFdeoQC&amp;pg=PA70&amp;dq=plutarco+calles+anticatholic&amp;as_brr=3&amp;sig=fnPEry3_KKxtgC6IdVhGGh8lMG8#PPA70,M1 Resisting Rebellion: The History And Politics of Counterinsurgency] p. 70, (2006 University Press of Kentucky) {{ISBN|0-8131-9170-X}}&lt;/ref&gt;   His [[anti-Catholic]] actions included outlawing religious orders, depriving the Church of property rights and depriving the clergy of civil liberties, including their right to a trial by jury (in cases involving anti-clerical laws) and the right to vote.&lt;ref name="Joes, Anthony James p. 70" /&gt;&lt;ref name="THE CRISTERO REBELLION – PART 1"&gt;Tuck, Jim [http://www.mexconnect.com/mex_/history/jtuck/jtcristero1.html THE CRISTERO REBELLION – PART 1] Mexico Connect 1996&lt;/ref&gt; Catholic antipathy towards Calles was enhanced because of his vocal atheism.&lt;ref name="books.google.com"&gt;{{cite book
|title=Mexico's New Politics
|author=David A. Shirk
|year=2005
|publisher=[[Lynne Rienner Publishers]]
|isbn=1-58826-270-7
|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=WOBRb0wKpocC&amp;pg=PA58&amp;lpg=PA58&amp;dq
}}&lt;/ref&gt; He was also a [[Catholicism and Freemasonry|Freemason]].&lt;ref&gt;Denslow, William R. [https://books.google.com/books?id=dmPato81X9sC&amp;pg=PA171&amp;dq=plutarco+calles+freemason&amp;sig=NsSB9-6KQUn50HmpBT8eh9nx3No 10,000 Famous Freemasons] p. 171 (2004
Kessinger Publishing){{ISBN|1-4179-7578-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Regarding this period, recent President [[Vicente Fox]] stated, "After 1917, Mexico was led by anti-Catholic Freemasons who tried to evoke the anticlerical spirit of popular indigenous President [[Benito Juárez]] of the 1880s. But the military dictators of the 1920s were a more savage lot than Juarez."&lt;ref&gt;Fox, Vicente and Rob Allyn [https://books.google.com/books?id=bLDDf9vi-esC&amp;dq Revolution of Hope] p. 17, Viking, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Cristeroscolgados.jpg|thumb|250px|Cristeros hanged in [[Jalisco]].]]
Due to the strict enforcement of anti-clerical laws, people in strongly [[Catholic Church|Catholic]] areas, especially the states of [[Jalisco]], [[Zacatecas]], [[Guanajuato]], [[Colima]] and [[Michoacán]], began to oppose him, and this opposition led to the [[Cristero War]] from 1926 to 1929, which was characterized by brutal atrocities on both sides. Some Cristeros applied terrorist tactics, while the Mexican government persecuted the clergy, killing suspected Cristeros and supporters and often retaliating against innocent individuals.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.encyclopedia.com/topic/Plutarco_Elias_Calles.aspx Calles, Plutarco Elías] The Columbia Encyclopedia, Sixth Edition. 2001–05 Columbia University Press.&lt;/ref&gt; On May 28, 1926, Calles was awarded a medal of merit from the head of Mexico's Scottish rite of Freemasonry for his actions against the Catholics.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.storialibera.it/epoca_contemporanea/messico_1926-1929/articolo.php?id=508 The Cristeros: 20th century Mexico's Catholic uprising, from The Angelus, January 2002, Volume XXV, Number 1] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090903020244/http://www.storialibera.it/epoca_contemporanea/messico_1926-1929/articolo.php?id=508 |date=2009-09-03 }} by Olivier LELIBRE, [[The Angelus (magazine)|The Angelus]]&lt;/ref&gt;

A truce was negotiated with the assistance of U.S. Ambassador [[Dwight Whitney Morrow]].&lt;ref name="Blood-Drenched Altars"&gt;{{cite |last=Van Hove |first=Brian |date=1996 |title=Blood-Drenched Altars: Baltimore's Archbishop Michael Joseph Curley, Oklahoma's Bishop Francis Clement Kelley and the Mexican Affair: 1934-1936 |publisher=[[Eternal Word Television Network]] |url=http://www.ewtn.com/library/HOMELIBR/FR94204.TXT |access-date=9 May 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Calles, however, did not abide by the terms of the truce – in violation of its terms, he had approximately 500 Cristero leaders and 5,000 other Cristeros shot, frequently in their homes in front of their spouses and children.&lt;ref name="Blood-Drenched Altars" /&gt; Particularly offensive to Catholics after the supposed truce was Calles' insistence on a complete state monopoly on education, suppressing all Catholic education and introducing "socialist" education in its place: "We must enter and take possession of the mind of childhood, the mind of youth.".&lt;ref name="Blood-Drenched Altars"/&gt; The persecution continued as Calles maintained control under his [[Maximato]] and did not relent until 1940, when President [[Manuel Ávila Camacho]], a believing Catholic, took office.&lt;ref name="Blood-Drenched Altars" /&gt; This attempt to indoctrinate the youth in atheism was begun in 1934 by amending Article 3 to the [[Mexican Constitution]] to eradicate religion by mandating "socialist education", which "in addition to removing all religious doctrine" would "combat fanaticism and prejudices", "build[ing] in the youth a rational and exact concept of the universe and of social life".&lt;ref name="lawreview.byu.edu" /&gt; In 1946 this "socialist education" was removed from the constitution and the document returned to the less egregious generalized secular education.
The effects of the war on the Church were profound. Between 1926 and 1934 at least 40 priests were killed.&lt;ref name="Blood-Drenched Altars" /&gt; Where there were 4,500 priests operating within the country before the rebellion, in 1934 there were only 334 priests licensed by the government to serve fifteen million people, the rest having been eliminated by emigration, expulsion, and assassination.&lt;ref name="Blood-Drenched Altars" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Scheina, Robert L. [https://books.google.com/books?id=8aWQ_7oKJfkC&amp;pg=PA33&amp;lpg=PA33&amp;dq=cristero+war+priests+killed&amp;source=web&amp;ots=YNDpLM2ukb&amp;sig=YWccvtnJKnSpaI15bTHCOX3zoyc#PPA33,M1 Latin America's Wars: The Age of the Caudillo, 1791–1899] p. 33 (2003
Brassey's) {{ISBN|1-57488-452-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;  By 1935, 17 states had no priest at all.&lt;ref&gt;Ruiz, Ramón Eduardo [https://books.google.com/books?id=AfdjWl1xKpwC&amp;pg=PA392&amp;dq=Tom%C3%A1s+Garrido+Canabal&amp;as_brr=3&amp;sig=HkfPtdqMt3qrdcMuprgfjnfnq60 Triumphs and Tragedy: A History of the Mexican People] p.393 (1993 W. W. Norton &amp; Company) {{ISBN|0-393-31066-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
{{portal|Religion|Human rights}}
{{Wikiquote}}
{{Commons category|Forced conversion}}
* [[Al-Baqara 256]]
* [[Covenant of Umar I]]
* [[Crypto-paganism]]
* [[Kakure Kirishitan]]
* [[Love Jihad]]
* [[Problem of hell]]
* [[Religious conversion]]
* [[Religious intolerance]]
* [[State atheism]]

== References ==
{{reflist|30em}}

{{Religious persecution}}

[[Category:Forced religious conversion| ]]
[[Category:Christianization]]
[[Category:Islamization]]
[[Category:Persecution by atheist states]]
[[Category:Religious conversion]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>