<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20130307231305|542698254" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="2900454" pageid="2900454" ns="0" title="Racial steering"><revisions><rev timestamp="2013-09-25T10:54:30Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Racial steering''' refers to the practice in which [[real estate brokers]] guide prospective home buyers towards or away from certain [[neighborhoods]] based on their [[Race (classification of human beings)|race]].  Racial steering is often divided into two broad classes of conduct;
# Advising customers to purchase homes in particular neighborhoods on the basis of race
# Failing, on the basis of race, to show, or to inform buyers of homes that meet their specifications&lt;ref&gt;Racial Steering: The Real Estate Broker and Title VIII" The Yale Law Journal, Vol. 85 No. 6. (1976) 808 - 825.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Overview==
{{Segregation}}
Historically the [[United States| United States of America]] has been defined by [[racial segregation|racially segregated]] neighborhoods.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas, June Manning "Planning History and the Black Urban Experience: Linkages and Contemporary Implications" Journal of Planning Education and Research Vol. 14 No. 1 (1994) 1 - 11.&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Urban Planning]] up to the 1960s has been documented as one of the causes of this phenomenon. Urban planners have been seen to have practiced early forms of racial steering.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas, June Manning "Planning History and the Black Urban Experience: Linkages and Contemporary Implications" Journal of Planning Education and Research Vol. 14 No. 1 (1994) 1 - 11.&lt;/ref&gt;  Through the use of the [[restrictive covenants|restrictive covenant]], and the establishment of [[zoning]] laws between [[World War I]] and [[World War II]], and the use of [[urban renewal]] between the 1940s and 1960s, urban planners have aided in the development of racially segregated neighborhoods.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas, June Manning "Planning History and the Black Urban Experience: Linkages and Contemporary Implications" Journal of Planning Education and Research Vol. 14 No. 1 (1994) 1 - 11.&lt;/ref&gt;  After the 1960s, through in part by the [[civil rights movement|Civil Rights Movement]], planning efforts were focused more towards advocacy, and community development, rather than maintaining segregation.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas, June Manning "Planning History and the Black Urban Experience: Linkages and Contemporary Implications" Journal of Planning Education and Research Vol. 14 No. 1 (1994) 1 - 11.&lt;/ref&gt;  Although planning practices did change, the racial make-up of neighborhoods did not.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas, June Manning "Planning History and the Black Urban Experience: Linkages and Contemporary Implications" Journal of Planning Education and Research Vol. 14 No. 1 (1994) 1 - 11.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Examples of racial steering==

An example of an urban planner practicing racial steering when developing communities is [[Ebenezer Howard]]. In 1898 after observing [[Traffic congestion|congestion]] and [[pollution]] problems in [[London]], Howard developed a community model, which he would call "garden cities" that would lessen the impact of congestion and pollution.&lt;ref&gt;Levy, John M. "Contemporary Urban Planning. Pearson Prentice Hall. New Jersey. 2006. Page 48&lt;/ref&gt; Howard hoped that the communities "would offer economic and social advances of the city combined with the tranquility, healthful environment, and closeness to nature" &lt;ref&gt;Levy, John M. "Contemporary Urban Planning. Pearson Prentice Hall. New Jersey. 2006. Page 47&lt;/ref&gt; of suburb life. These communities would be set up for Caucasian upper-middle-class people, and "by virtue of quick rail access, they would have close economic links to other cities, but would have enough economic activity within its boundaries so that the majority of residents would not have to commute"&lt;ref&gt;Levy, John M. "Contemporary Urban Planning. Pearson Prentice Hall. New Jersey. 2006. Page 47&lt;/ref&gt; thus lessening the impact of congestion and pollution. "Howard’s work has influenced urban development in dozens if not hundreds of communities" in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;Levy, John M. "Contemporary Urban Planning. Pearson Prentice Hall. New Jersey. 2006. Page 48&lt;/ref&gt;

An example of racial steering occurring in the United States can be seen in [[Detroit]], Michigan. When the [[automobile industry]] opened up new [[factories]] creating many jobs in 1916 - 1917 and again in 1924, many [[African Americans]] migrated to reap the benefits.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas, June Manning "Planning History and the Black Urban Experience: Linkages and Contemporary Implications" Journal of Planning Education and Research Vol. 14 No. 1 (1994) 1 - 11.&lt;/ref&gt; This migration changed the racial, social, economic, and political landscape of Detroit. City officials were faced with racial tensions almost overnight. Racial tensions were maintained by the city officials when they supported movements and laws that allowed [[racial segregation]] and [[discrimination]] in housing, employment and community services to continue.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas, June Manning "Planning History and the Black Urban Experience: Linkages and Contemporary Implications" Journal of Planning Education and Research Vol. 14 No. 1 (1994) 1 - 11.&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==

===Theoretical explanations===

Researchers have attempted to explain the racial segregation seen in neighborhoods throughout the United States.  There are three leading theories. The first "asserts that the phenomenon is really self – segregation, the result of the preferences of blacks, as with other ethnics, to live in segregated neighborhoods. The second suggests that poverty, aided by the inertia of history has perpetuated segregation. The third suggests that the decline of blatant discrimination of the past has revealed pervasive institutional racism." &lt;ref&gt;Pearce, Diana M. "Gatekeepers and Homeseekers: Institutional Patterns in Racial Steering" Journal of Social Problems, Vol. 26 No. 3 (1979) 325 - 342&lt;/ref&gt; John E. Farley, argues that although it is plausible for each of these theories to contribute to the segregation seen, his research lends the most support to the second theory, which bases itself on social class. Farley states that "class largely determines what housing people can afford to rent or buy, and since the gap between whites and African Americans is wide with respect to income (U.S. Census Bureau 2001) and even wider with respect to wealth" &lt;ref&gt;Farley, John E. "Race, Not Class: Explaining Racial Housing Segregation in the St. Louis Metropolitan Area" Journal of Sociological Focus (2000) 133 - 149&lt;/ref&gt; you tend to see people with similar incomes and wealth in the same areas. Diana Pearce, another researcher, contributes the segregation seen in neighborhoods throughout the United States to institutional racism. She argues that "in [the] consumers’ eyes, real estate agents (compared to bankers or builders, for example) are frequently seen as the most expert in nearly every aspect of decision making involved in buying a house." She continues that "as a group they are not only experts, they also control access to housing areas. They are, or can be, community gatekeepers … and a crucial aspect of the gatekeeper role is the screening of potential residents." &lt;ref&gt;Pearce, Diana M. "Gatekeepers and Homeseekers: Institutional Patterns in Racial Steering" Journal of Social Problems, Vol. 26 No. 3 (1979) 325 - 342&lt;/ref&gt;

===Federal laws===

The United States congress passed a series of Acts aimed at combating segregation. The first such act, The [[Civil Rights Act of 1866]], states in subsections 1981, 1981a, and 1982 that all persons born in the United States are citizens regardless of their race, color, or previous condition and as citizens they could make and enforce contracts, sue and be sued, give evidence in court, and inherit, purchase, lease, sell, hold, and convey real estate and personal property. Although this act was passed, it was never enforced on the local, state or national level.&lt;ref&gt;National fair Housing Advocate, http://fairhousing.com/index.cfm?method=page.display&amp;pageid=622, 4 Nov 2007&lt;/ref&gt; A second act, The [[Civil Rights Act of 1964]], through Title VI outlawed segregation in public schools and public places. It also made it illegal to have segregation of the races in schools, housing, or hiring. Like the first act, powers given to enforce it were weak in the beginning, but were later supplemented.&lt;ref&gt;Title VI of the Civil Rights Act of 1964, http://www.hud.gov/progdesc/titl-vi.cfm , 4 Nov 2007&lt;/ref&gt;  A third act, the [[Civil Rights Act of 1968]], subsection 3604, expanded on the Civil Rights Act of 1866. It prohibited discrimination concerning the sale, rental, and financing of housing based on race, religion, national origin, and sex. This section is also referred to as the [[Fair Housing Act]]. This act is enforced at the national level by the [[Office of Fair Housing and Equal Opportunity]] at the [[United States Department of Housing and Urban Development]].&lt;ref&gt;National Fair Housing Advocate Online, http://fairhousing.com/index.cfm?method=page.display&amp;pagename=FHA_3604, 4 Nov 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

===Movement organizations===

Throughout the past four decades since the passage of the Civil Rights Act of 1968, many people have come together to movement organizations that fight racial discrimination in the housing market. One such organization is the National Fair Housing Alliance. It credits itself "as being the only national organization that is dedicated solely to ending discrimination in housing" &lt;ref&gt;National Fair Housing Alliance, www.nationalfairhousing.org, 1 Nov 2007&lt;/ref&gt;  In the greater Metropolitan Area, there are seven local member organizations they are the Fair Housing Council of Central New York, Fair Housing Enforcement Project, Long Island Housing Services, Housing Opportunities Made Equal, Westchester Residential Opportunities, Fair Housing Council of Northern New Jersey, and the Connecticut Fair Housing Center.  A second organization is the Fair Housing Law. They are leading a campaign to "increase public awareness of the Fair Housing Act, and its protections" &lt;ref&gt;Fair Housing Law, www.fairhousinglaw.org, 1 Nov 2007&lt;/ref&gt; A third organization, The National Fair Housing Advocate, aims itself as being "designed to serve both the fair housing community and the general public with timely news and information regarding the issues of housing discrimination" &lt;ref&gt;National Fair Housing Advocate, www.fairhousing.com, 1 Nov 2007&lt;/ref&gt; Each of these organizations share a common theme, bringing up class action lawsuits against people and/ or companies who fail to rent or sell to others based on their race.

===Lawsuits===

Since the enacting of federal laws and the emergence of movement organizations, there have been several lawsuits brought up against individuals and companies for racial discrimination.
# '''Realty Forum vs. New York State Attorney General (1988):''' This case involves the New York State Attorney General suing a Yonkers Real – Estate agency, The Realty Forum in 1988 with racial steering. The Attorney General accused the firm of "providing listings of apartments in particular neighborhoods based solely on a client’s race or color". The Attorney General began investigating the Realty Forum after receiving complaints from the Westchester Residential Opportunities. The Realty Forum has since been found guilty.&lt;ref&gt;Realty Broker Is Sued Over Racial Steering, http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE1DF123FF935A35756C0A96E948260, 2 Nov 2007&lt;/ref&gt;
#'''Corcoran Group vs. New York State Attorney General (2006):''' This case involves the New York State Attorney General suing a real estate brokerage in Brooklyn Heights, New York City with racial steering. The National Fair Housing Alliance following up on a past report found "literal and blatant sales steering… where the agent applied a new trick – he used a map to tell whites instead where they should "flee to".  The alliance then referred the case to the New York State Attorney General which subsequently placed charges against the group. The case is still pending.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2006/10/11/nyregion/11discriminate.html Report Alleges Bias by a Real Estate Giant], 2 Nov 2007&lt;/ref&gt;
# '''Coldwell Banker vs Illinois Attorney General (2006):''' This case involves a Chicago real estate company being accused of racially steering prospective homebuyers by the Illinois Attorney General. The agency was first investigated by the National Fair Housing Alliance in late 2005.  The alliance in their report accused the agency of "blatant discrimination…against African Americans". The alliance continues that white prospective home buyers were shown 36 listings while African Americans who were better qualified were shown only seven. The company denies any wrongdoing and the lawsuit is still pending.&lt;ref&gt;Major Realty Firm Accused Of Racial Discrimination, http://cbs2chicago.com/topstories/Coldwell.Banker.real.2.331468.html, 2 Nov 2007&lt;/ref&gt;
# '''Century 21 Town and Country Vs. The Michigan Department of Civil Rights (MDCR) (2006):''' This case involves the Michigan Department of Civil Rights suing the Century 21 Town and Country of discrimination. The department issued these charges after receiving complaints of illegal steering of white homebuyers to predominately white neighborhoods and African American homebuyers to predominately African American neighborhoods. The complaints were initiated by the National Fair Housing Alliance after their investigation which concluded in July 2005. The case is still pending.&lt;ref&gt;Formal Charge of Unlawful Discrimination Issued Against Century 21 Town &amp; Country, http://www.michigan.gov/mdcr/0,1607,7-138--160790--,00.html, 2 Nov 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

Although individual firms have been accused of Racial Steering throughout the United States and found guilty, researchers point out that there have however been no accusations that would affect a significant amount of the United States population. Diana Pearce states that since "the passage of federal lesilation and a landmark Supreme Court decision, there has not been one large lawsuit about housing... in contrast [to] school desegregation and employment discrimination, where ... laws and court decisions have had compartively more impact".&lt;ref&gt;Pearce, Diana M. "Gatekeepers and Homeseekers: Institutional Patterns in Racial Steering" Journal of Social Problems, Vol. 26 No. 3 (1979) 325 - 342&lt;/ref&gt;  She continues that "as long as it is assumed in the general lesilation and as long as lawyers and judges assume generally that the problem in housing discrimination is that of a few homeowners (or real estate agents who step out of line), practices ... will continue to perpetuate housing segregation".&lt;ref&gt;Pearce, Diana M. "Gatekeepers and Homeseekers: Institutional Patterns in Racial Steering" Journal of Social Problems, Vol. 26 No. 3 (1979) 325 - 342&lt;/ref&gt;

==The debate over racial steering==
{{Cleanup section|date=March 2012}}

Please note: the notion of "a debate over racial steering" should in no way be taken to suggest that racial steering is lawful in the US. It is not. Under US civil rights law racial steering in order to create or maintain segregation is unlawful and has been the target of civil rights reform since at least the mid-20th century.

Is having racially segregated neighborhoods such a bad thing? This is the major question being posed by leading researchers {{By whom|date=December 2010}}. There are two dominating theses. The first thesis suggests that racially segregated neighborhoods are characterized as being blighted, having a lack of educational resources, and having high levels of violence. The second thesis challenges this notion and suggests that these neighborhoods are thriving economically. They have developed protective markets, have strong and stable social networks, and because of these networks, they have built high levels of social capital {{Citation needed|date=December 2010}}.

===The ripple effect in a blighted neighborhood===

Racially segregated neighborhoods have been labeled as blighted. Characteristics of a blighted neighborhoods include rundown homes, streets strewn with garbage, poor lighting, and high rates of crime.  Douglas Massey and Nancy Denton explore this logic in their book "American Apartheid". Massey and Denton focus their research on the effects of residential housing discrimination towards African Americans. They argue that racial segregation of lower income residents, who are only capable of making ends meet, creates a neighborhood that is characterized as going "downhill".&lt;ref&gt;Massey, Douglas and Nancy Denton. "American Apartheid"  Harvard University Press, Massachusetts, 1993.&lt;/ref&gt; Massey and Denton argue that this occurs because of a downward spiral effect: If one homeowner cannot afford to maintain their property and allows it to become run down, then [[Broken windows theory|other homeowners in the area will be less inclined to invest money into their own property]].&lt;ref&gt;Massey, Douglas and Nancy Denton. "American Apartheid"  Harvard University Press, Massachusetts, 1993.&lt;/ref&gt; Massey and Denton also point out that "[[Tipping point (sociology)|at some point, a threshold is crossed]], beyond which the pattern becomes self – reinforcing and irreversible".&lt;ref&gt;Massey, Douglas and Nancy Denton. "American Apartheid"  Harvard University Press, Massachusetts, 1993.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Academic achievement and racial segregation===

Racially segregated neighborhoods have been associated with having low academic achievement rates. Rumberger and Willms have explored this topic. They argue that segregation attributes to minorities under achievement in at least two ways. First, students in segregated schools may receive a poor quality of education. This occurs because schools servicing minorities or low socioeconomic groups may have lower funding levels, inexperienced teachers, and reduced levels of other resources that contribute to the student’s academic achievement.&lt;ref&gt;Rumsberg, Russell W and J. Douglas Willms. "The Impact of Racial and Ethnic Segregation on the Achievement Gap in California High Schools" Educational Evaluation and Policy Analysis, Vol. 14, No. 4, 1992. pages 377 - 392.&lt;/ref&gt; Second, Rumsberg and Willms argue that the residential racial segregation leads to schools having the same composition which can directly affect the student’s level of academic achievement. They call these differences "contextual effects". Contextual effects are defined as peer interactions and the teaching and learning climate in the school.&lt;ref&gt;Rumsberg, Russell W and J. Douglas Willms. "The Impact of Racial and Ethnic Segregation on the Achievement Gap in California High Schools" Educational Evaluation and Policy Analysis, Vol. 14, No. 4, 1992. pages 377 - 392.&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, Rumsberg and Willms state that once a school is experiencing the effects of racial segregation, it is difficult to reverse them.&lt;ref&gt;Rumsberg, Russell W and J. Douglas Willms. "The Impact of Racial and Ethnic Segregation on the Achievement Gap in California High Schools" Educational Evaluation and Policy Analysis, Vol. 14, No. 4, 1992. pages 377 - 392.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Crime rate and racial segregation===

Since the 1980s violent crimes in the United States have been steadily declining. Between 1980 and 1990, the murder rate for the United States fell by 9%, and between 1973 and 1992 the victimization rate of rapes fell by 28%.&lt;ref&gt;Massey, Douglas "Getting Away With Murder: Segregation And Violent Crime In Urban Areas", University Of Pennsylvania Law Review, Vol 143, No 5, May 1995 Pages 1203–1232.&lt;/ref&gt; "Although rates of crime may be going down for the United States generally, they are spirally upward for one specific group of Americans: African Americans.".&lt;ref&gt;Massey, Douglas "Getting Away With Murder: Segregation And Violent Crime In Urban Areas", University Of Pennsylvania Law Review, Vol 143, No 5, May 1995 Pages 1203–1232.&lt;/ref&gt; Douglas Massey argues that the rising of African American poverty and the addition of racial segregation produces a sharp increase in the geographic concentration of poverty. He continues by stating that "as poverty is concentrated … all things associated with it are concentrated, including crime… thus… creating an ecological niche characterized by high levels of violence and a high risk of victimization".&lt;ref&gt;Massey, Douglas "Getting Away With Murder: Segregation And Violent Crime In Urban Areas", University Of Pennsylvania Law Review, Vol 143, No 5, May 1995 Pages 1203–1232.&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, Massey argues that a person living within this niche becomes violent themselves in an effort to deter potential criminals and increase their chance of survival, thus creating a cycle of African American violence which at some point cannot be reversed.&lt;ref&gt;Massey, Douglas "Getting Away With Murder: Segregation And Violent Crime In Urban Areas", University Of Pennsylvania Law Review, Vol 143, No 5, May 1995 Pages 1203–1232.&lt;/ref&gt;

Low income black communities that have been segregated by social forces through city design have higher levels of criminal activity rates. Different methods when applied help us understand how social forces and urban design segregated black communities from white communities. “Shaw and McKay argued that three structural factors- low economic status,ethnic heterogeneity and residential mobility- led to the disruption of community social organization,which,in turn, accounted for variations in crime and delinquency”.&lt;ref&gt;Sampson and Groves "Community Structure and Crime: Testing Social-Disorginization Theory", Chicago Journals, vol. 94, No. 4, January 1989 pages 774-802.&lt;/ref&gt; Radical geography has been searching for connections between “the truths of how capitalism’s political economy structures urban space and the emphasis on the subjective evaluation of safe urban space.”.&lt;ref&gt;Howell, Philip “Crime and the City Solution: Crime Fiction, Urban Knowledge, and racial Geography”, The Crimes of Geography, anitpode 30:4, 1998, pages 357-378&lt;/ref&gt; The geographical structure of a city is designed to keep high income communities separate from low income, generally black communities are formed with this structure. This type of segregation tends to increase rates of intra- racial victimization, but decrease rates of inter- racial victimization.” &lt;ref&gt;Flynn and Shihadeh “Segregation and Crime: The Effect of Black Social Isolation on the Rates of Black Urban Violence”, Social Forces, University of North Carolina Press, Vol. 74, No.4, Jun 1996, pages 1325-1352&lt;/ref&gt; One method of segregating blacks form whites is through ‘gated communities’ which isolates the high income population from the low income by gating the higher status community with fences or bars. The result of this ‘gated’ segregation leads to an unmanageable high criminal activity called a ‘ghetto’ community where “spatial isolation leads to social isolation, which in turn has a variety of negative outcomes including serious crime.” &lt;ref&gt;Flynn and Shihadeh “Segregation and Crime: The Effect of Black Social Isolation on the Rates of Black Urban Violence”, Social Forces, University of North Carolina Press, Vol. 74, No.4, Jun 1996, pages 1325-1352&lt;/ref&gt; Erecting physical barriers such as gates protects the high income community, leaving the black community to be isolated and an island by itself referenced as a ‘ghetto’ community. This can be referred to as ‘Broken Windows’ in which a community,“sends a signal” that it, “does not care about itself” and the community is unable to protect itself from,”criminal invasion.” &lt;ref&gt;Herbert and Brown “Conceptions of Space and Crime in the Punitive Neoliberal City”, 2006, pages 755-777&lt;/ref&gt; By pushing the low income earners out of the gentrified community, the city is creating a large segregated criminal zone within the city. “This divide has, in turn, produced disparate social worlds, in which the interests, resources, opportunities, and concerns of racial groups located in distinct neighborhoods increasingly diverge, ultimately leading to unequal rates of crime.”  &lt;ref&gt;Matsueda, Ross L. “Divergent Social Worlds: Neighborhood Crime and the Racial-Spatial Divide. By Ruth D.”, Scholarly Article Review, 2010&lt;/ref&gt; The ghetto is labeled as an undesirable area to live and the people in that area are labeled the same. “We have also seen that those who commit crimes tend to be from the same groups that are most likely to be victimized.”&lt;ref&gt;Raphael and Sills “Urban Crime, Race, and the Criminal Justice System in the United States”, Act 30, Chapter 30, Jan 2006, pages 515-535&lt;/ref&gt; This causes criminal behavior of the people within the area as “greater racial segregation appears to substantially increase violent crimes such as robberies and aggravated assaults.” &lt;ref&gt;Bjerk, David “The Effect of Segregation on Crime Rates”, American Law &amp; Economics Association Annual Meetings, February 2006, pages 2-31&lt;/ref&gt; However it could be argued that the area that an underprivileged person lives in dictates the criminal mentality of the individual. “Poor individuals are simply more prone to committing property crimes than are richer individuals.” &lt;ref&gt;Bjerk, David “The Effect of Segregation on Crime Rates”, American Law &amp; Economics Association Annual Meetings, February 2006, pages 2-31&lt;/ref&gt; Having so many people displaced into the ghetto region of a city that commit many different types of criminal actives would be a reason why those communities have higher crime rates.

===Protective markets and racial segregation===

Racial residential segregation has allowed businesses to strive economically. Research has shown that these neighborhoods create a protective market, one that is defined as a specialty that caters to the culturally based tastes of its residents.&lt;ref&gt;Aldrich, Howard, John Cater, Trevor Jones, David Mc Evoy, Paul Velleman "Ethnic Concentration And The Protected Market Hypothesis" Social Forces, Vol. 63 No 4, June 1985, 996 – 1009&lt;/ref&gt; Research has also shown that ethnic business owners have an insider’s knowledge of the clientele that they serve because they themselves are a part of it. With such knowledge, it is said that they have created a protective market, one that will thrive if the ethnic composition of the neighborhood does not change.&lt;ref&gt;Aldrich, Howard, John Cater, Trevor Jones, David Mc Evoy, Paul Velleman "Ethnic Concentration And The Protected Market Hypothesis" Social Forces, Vol. 63 No 4, June 1985, 996 – 1009.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Ethnic economies and racial segregation===

Racially segregated neighborhoods have what are called ethnic economies. An ethnic economy is defined as an "immigrant or minority business and employment sector that coexists with the general economy".&lt;ref&gt;Light, Ivan, Georges Sabagh, Mehdi Bozorgmehr, "Beyond the Ethnic Enclave Economy" Social Problems, Vol. 41, No. 1, 1994, pages 65 - 80.&lt;/ref&gt;   Smith argues that an ethnic economy helps in several ways. First, it provides jobs for all able–bodied family members.&lt;ref&gt;Smith, Christopher. "Asian New York: The Geography and Politics of Diversity" International Migration Review, Vol. 29, No. 1, 1995 pages 59 - 84.&lt;/ref&gt; Second, it has been shown that ethnic economies provide more opportunities for homeownership.&lt;ref&gt;Smith, Christopher. "Asian New York: The Geography and Politics of Diversity" International Migration Review, Vol. 29, No. 1, 1995 pages 59 - 84.&lt;/ref&gt; Finally, the ethnic infrastructure that is built up, will allow for future growth of the community, thus paving the way for new residents.&lt;ref&gt;Smith, Christopher. "Asian New York: The Geography and Politics of Diversity" International Migration Review, Vol. 29, No. 1, 1995 pages 59 - 84.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Social networks, social capital, and racial segregation===

Racially segregated neighborhoods have strong [[social networks]]. These networks have been shown to create [[social capital]], which has been linked to having positive effects on minority residents. First, Portes argues that an individual will gain access to power and political positions through the direct and indirect employment of social connections.&lt;ref&gt;Portes, Alejandro. "Social Capital: Its Origins and Applications in Modern Society" Annual Review of Sociology, Vol. 24, pages. 1 - 24&lt;/ref&gt;  He continues by stating that this access to power and political positions, allows for social mobility.&lt;ref&gt;Portes, Alejandro. "Social Capital: Its Origins and Applications in Modern Society" Annual Review of Sociology, Vol. 24, pages. 1 - 24&lt;/ref&gt; Second, Portes states that social capital is generated by social networks of relationships and without the reciprocity, trust, and social norms that come with these networks, a resident who is in need would not be given an opportunity to succeed.&lt;ref&gt;Portes, Alejandro. "Social Capital: Its Origins and Applications in Modern Society" Annual Review of Sociology, Vol. 24, pages. 1 - 24&lt;/ref&gt;

==External links==
* [http://portal.hud.gov/hudportal/HUD?src=/program_offices/fair_housing_equal_opp/online-complaint File a housing discrimination complaint]
* [http://portal.hud.gov/hudportal/HUD?src=/program_offices/fair_housing_equal_opp Office of Fair Housing and Equal Opportunity]

==References==

{{reflist|2}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Racial Steering}}
[[Category:Urban politics in the United States]]
[[Category:History of racial segregation in the United States]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>