<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20101108010200|395455920" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="3229028" pageid="3229028" ns="0" title="Social exclusion"><revisions><rev timestamp="2010-11-08T03:08:48Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Cleanup|date=February 2009}}
{{sociology}}
One [[sociological]] definition of '''social exclusion''' is as follows:

&lt;blockquote&gt;Social exclusion is a multidimensional process of progressive social rupture, detaching groups and individuals from social relations and institutions and preventing them from full participation in the normal, normatively prescribed activities of the society in which they live.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.shababinclusion.org/content/document/detail/558/1 [[Hilary Silver]], “Social Exclusion: Comparative Analysis of Europe and Middle East Youth,” Middle East Youth Initiative Working Paper (September 2007), p. 15]&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Another definition of this sociological term is as follows:

The outcome of multiple deprivations that prevent individuals or groups from participating fully in the economic, social, and political life of the society in which they live.

An inherent problem with the term, however, is the tendency of its use by practitioners who define it to fit their argument.&lt;ref&gt;Understanding Social Exclusion, ed. Hills, Le Grand &amp; Piachaud 2002, Oxford University Press)&lt;/ref&gt; It is a term used widely in the [[United Kingdom]] and [[Europe]], and was first utilized in [[France]].&lt;ref&gt;Hilary Silver, “Social Exclusion and Social Solidarity.” International Labour Review 133, nos. 5-6 (1994): 531-78.&lt;/ref&gt; It is used across disciplines including [[education]], [[sociology]], [[psychology]], [[politics]] and [[economics]].

Social exclusion is evident in deprived communities, it is harder for people to engage fully in society. In such communities, weak social networking limits the circulation about information about jobs, political activities, and community events. But many social workers believe that exclusion in the countryside is as great as, if not greater than, that in cities. In rural areas there is less access to goods, services and facilities, making life difficult in many respects.
==Juridical concept==
There are countries, Italy for example, that have a legal concept of ''social exclusion''. In Italy, "esclusione sociale" is defined as ''[[poverty]]'' combined with [[social alienation]], by the [[statute]] n. 328 (11-8-2000), that instituted a state investigation commission named "Commissione di indagine sull'Esclusione Sociale" (CIES) to make an annual report to the government on legally expected issues of ''social exclusion''.

==Overview==
Most of the characteristics listed in the following paragraphs are present together in studies of social exclusion, due to exclusion's multidimensionality. One of the best descriptions of social exclusion and [[social inclusion]] are that they are on a continuum on a vertical plane below and above the 'social horizon'; they have a ten-phase modulating ("phase" because they increase and decrease [modulate] with time) social structure: race, geographic location, class structure, globalization, social issues, personal habits and appearance, [[education]], [[religion]], [[economics]] and [[politics]]. The following descriptions are very limiting and do not cover the whole gamut of social exclusion and social inclusion.

'''Social exclusion''' relates to the [[Social alienation|alienation]] or [[disenfranchisement]] of certain people within a society. It is often connected to a person's [[social class]], [[educational]] status, relationships in childhood&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.salvationarmy.org.uk/seeds The Salvation Army: The Seeds of Exclusion (2008)&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; and [[living standards]] and how these might affect access to various opportunities. It also applies to some degree to people with a [[disability]], to [[minority group|minority]] men and women of all races, to [[LGBT]] peoples, to the [[elderly]], and to youth ([[Youth Exclusion]]). Anyone who deviates in any perceived way from the norm of a population may become subject to coarse or subtle forms of social exclusion. Additionally, communities may self-exclude by removing themselves physically from the larger community, for example, in the [[gated community]] model.

==Causes==
Whilst recognising the multi-dimensionality of exclusion, policy work undertaken at [[European Union]] level focuses on [[unemployment]] as a key cause of, or at least correlating with, social exclusion. This is because in modern societies, paid work is not only the principal source of income with which to buy services, but is also the fount of individuals' identity and feeling of self-worth. Most people's social networks and sense of embeddedness in society also revolve around their work. Many of the indicators of extreme social exclusion, such as poverty and homelessness, depend on monetary income which is normally derived from work. Much policy to reduce exclusion thus focuses on the labour market:
* On the one hand, to make individuals at risk of exclusion more attractive to employers, i.e. more "employable".
* On the other hand, to encourage (and/or oblige) employers to be more inclusive in their employment policies.

The EU's [[EQUAL Community Initiative]] investigated ways to increase the inclusiveness of the labour market. Work on social exclusion more broadly is carried out through the [[Open Method of Coordination]] (OMC) among the Member State governments.

In some circumstances, transport may be a factor in social exclusion - for instance, if lack of access to public transport or a vehicle prevents a person from getting to a job, training course, job centre or doctor's surgery. Some schemes therefore promote [[accessibility]], for instance:
* By ensuring public transport is available, which is particularly relevant for women.
* By subsidising the purchase of a scooter, which is relevant to young people living in rural areas.

==Quotations==
''“Social exclusion is about the inability of our society to keep all groups and individuals within reach of what we expect as a society...[or] to realise their full potential."''&lt;ref&gt;http://herkules.oulu.fi/isbn9514268539/html/x2692.html Social exclusion in the UK&lt;/ref&gt;

''"Whatever the content and criteria of social membership, socially excluded groups and individuals lack capacity or access to social opportunity.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.shababinclusion.org/content/document/detail/558/1 Hilary Silver, “Social Exclusion: Comparative Analysis of Europe and Middle East Youth,” Middle East Youth Initiative Working Paper (September 2007)&lt;/ref&gt;.

To be "excluded from [[society]]" can take various relative senses, but social exclusion is usually defined as more than a simple [[economic]] phenomenon: it also has consequences on the social, [[symbol]]ic field.

''"Women of [[Pakistan]]i, [[British Bangladeshi|Bangladeshi]] and [[Caribbean]] descent [in Britain] are doing well in schools but are still being penalised in the workplace...80-89% of 16-year-olds from those ethnic groups wanted to work full-time...but they were up to four times more likely to be [[jobless]]."''&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk/5320708.stm BBC NEWS | UK | Career worries for minority women&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Philosophy|Philosopher]] [[Axel Honneth]] thus speaks of a "struggle for [[Recognition (sociology)|recognition]]",  which he attempts to theorize through [[Hegel]]'s philosophy. In this sense, to be socially excluded is to be deprived from social recognition and social value. In the sphere of [[politics]], social recognition is obtained by full [[citizenship]]; in the economic sphere (in [[capitalism]]) it means being paid enough to be able to participate fully in the life of the community.

This concept can be gleaned from considering examples of the ''"social integration crisis: poverty, professional exclusion or marginalization, social and civic disenfranchisement, absence or weakening of support networks, frequent [[Clash of Civilizations|inter-cultural conflicts]]"'',&lt;ref&gt;http://urbact.eu/document-library/virtual-files/childhood/france/situation-of-single-parent-households-headed-by-wo.html Situation of single parent households headed by women&lt;/ref&gt; These relate not only to gender, race and disability, but also to [[crime]]:

''"Social exclusion is a major cause of crime and re-offending. Removing the right to vote increases social exclusion by signalling to serving prisoners that, at least for the duration of their sentence, they are dead to society. The additional punishment of disenfranchisement is not a deterrent. There is no evidence to suggest that criminals are deterred from offending behaviour by the threat of losing the right to vote.....(and) the notion of civic death for sentenced prisoners isolates still further those who are already on the margins of society and encourages them to be seen as alien to the communities to which they will return on release"''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://64.233.183.104/search?q=cache:D-HJsClzBxYJ:www.prisonreformtrust.org.uk/documents/download.asp%3Flvid%3D436%26id%3D790+social+exclusion+disenfranchisement&amp;hl=en&amp;ct=clnk&amp;cd=10&amp;gl=uk Barred from Voting: the Right to Vote for Sentenced Prisoners] {{Dead link|date=February 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Links between exclusion and other issues==
The problem of social exclusion is usually tied to that of [[equal opportunity]], as some people are more subject to such exclusion than others. [[Marginalisation]] of certain groups is a problem even in many economically more developed countries, including the [[United Kingdom]] and the [[United States]], where the majority of the population enjoys considerable economic and social opportunities.

Since social exclusion may lead to one being deprived of one's citizenship, some  authors ([[Philippe Van Parijs]], [[Jean-Marc Ferry]], [[Alain Caillé]], [[André Gorz]] and [[Axel Wolz]]) have proposed a [[basic income]], which would impede exclusion from citizenship. The concept of a Universal Unconditional Income, or social salary, has been disseminated notably by the Green movement in Germany.

In the last few years, there has been research focused on possible connections between exclusion and brain function. Studies published by the University of Georgia and San Diego State University found that exclusion can lead to diminished brain functioning and poor decision making. Such studies corroborate with earlier beliefs of sociologists. The effect of exclusion may likely correlate with such things as substance abuse and crime.

==Social inclusion==
'''[[Social inclusion]]''', the converse of social exclusion, is [[affirmative action]] to change the circumstances and habits that lead to (or have led to) social exclusion.

''Social Inclusion'' is a strategy to combat social exclusion, but without making reparations or amends for past wrongs as in ''Affirmative Action''. It is the coordinated response to the very complex system of problems known as social exclusion. The notion of social inclusion can vary, according to the type of strategies organisations adopt.

Social exclusion is a concept used in many parts of the world outside of the United States to characterise contemporary forms of social disadvantage. Dr. Lynn Todman, director of the Institute on Social Exclusion at the Adler School of Professional Psychology, suggests that social exclusion refers to processes in which individuals and entire communities of people are systematically blocked from rights, opportunities and resources (e.g. housing, employment, healthcare, civic engagement, democratic participation and due process) that are normally available to members of American society and which are key to social integration.

==Crime==
Sociologists see strong links between crime and social exclusion in industrialized societies such as the United States.  Growing crime rates may reflect the fact that a growing number of people do not feel valued in the societies in which they live.  The socially excluded population cannot meet the standards of economic status and consumption that are promoted within society.  Therefore legitimate means are bypassed in favor of illegal ones.  Crime is favored over the political system or community organization.  Young people increasingly grow up without guidance and support from the adult population.  Young people also face diminishing job opportunities to sustain a livelihood.  This can cause a sense of willingness to turn to illegitimate means of sustaining a desired lifestyle.

==See also==
{{Portal|Philosophy}}
* [[Basic income]]
* [[Caste]]
* [[Guaranteed minimum income]]
* [[Heterosexism]]
* [[Homophobia]]
* [[Marginalization]]
* [[Ostracism]]
* [[Poverty]]
* [[Racism]]
* [[Relational care]]
* [[Second-class citizen]]
* [[Social alienation]]
* [[Social firm]]
* [[Social rejection]]
* [[URSPIC]]: An EU Research Project to measure impacts of urban development projects on social exclusion
* [[Waithood]]
* [[Youth Exclusion]]
* [[The Yogyakarta Principles]]
* [[Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities]]

==References==
1. Power, A., Wilson, W.J., 2000, Social Exclusion and the Future of Cities, Centre for Analysis of Social Exclusion, London School of Economics, London
{{Reflist|2}}

==Bibliography==
*Li Yi. ''The Structure and Evolution of Chinese Social Stratification''. University Press of America, 2005, ISBN 0-7618-3331-5
*[[Frank Moulaert]], [[Erik Swyngedouw]] and Arantxa Rodriguez. ''The Globalized City: Economic Restructing and [[Social polarization|Social Polarization]] in European Cities''. [[Oxford University Press]], 2003, ISBN 978-0199260409
*[[Axel Honneth]], ''The Struggle for Recognition: Moral Grammar of Social Conflicts'', 1996. ISBN 978-0745618388
*[[Philippe Van Parijs]], ''Real Freedom for All: What (if anything) can justify capitalism?'', 1995. ISBN 978-0198293576
*[[Gilles Deleuze]], ''[[A Thousand Plateaus]]'', 1980.
*[[John Rawls]], ''[[A Theory of Justice]]'', 1971. ISBN 978-0674017726
*[[Karl Marx]], ''[[Economic and Philosophical Manuscripts of 1844]]''
University of Georgia (2006, November 9). Social Exclusion Changes Brain Function And Can Lead To Poor Decision-making. ScienceDaily. Retrieved February 29, 2008, from http://www.sciencedaily.com­ /releases/2006/11/061108154256.htm
*[[Hilary Silver]], ''[http://www.shababinclusion.org/content/document/detail/558/ Social Exclusion: Comparative Analysis of Europe and Middle East Youth]'', 2007, [[Middle East Youth Initiative]] Working Paper
Giddens, Anthony, and Anthony Giddens. Introduction to Sociology. New York: W.W. Norton &amp;, 2009. Print.
* Applebaum, Richard P., Carr, deborah, Duneier, Mitchell, Giddens, Anthony. "Introduction to Sociology Seventh Edition" 2009.

==External links==
*[http://www.adler.edu/about/ISE.asp Adler Institute on Social Exclusion]
*[http://www.cepr.net/publications/social_exclusion_2006_08.pdf ''Is the U.S. a Good Model for Reducing Social Exclusion in Europe?''] Center for Economic and Policy Research, August 2006
*[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk/5320708.stm Career worries for minority women]
*[http://www.guardian.co.uk/uklatest/story/0,,-6068130,00.html?gusrc=ticker-103704 Black teachers face daily racism The Guardian] - no longer working
*[http://www.cesi.org.uk/ Centre for Economic and Social Inclusion]
*[http://www.gsdrc.org/go/topic-guides/social-exclusion GSDRC topic guide on social exclusion]
{{DEFAULTSORT:Social Exclusion}}
[[Category:Poverty]]
[[Category:Social issues]]
[[Category:Social philosophy]]
[[Category:Political philosophy]]
[[Category:Sociology]]
[[Category:Urban decay]]

[[de:Exklusion]]
[[el:Κοινωνικός αποκλεισμός]]
[[es:Marginación]]
[[fr:Exclusion sociale]]
[[gl:Exclusión social]]
[[it:Esclusione sociale]]
[[he:הדרה]]
[[ja:社会的排除]]
[[no:Eksklusjon]]
[[pl:Społeczne wykluczenie]]
[[pt:Inclusão social]]
[[fi:Sosiaalinen syrjäytyminen]]
[[sv:Utanförskap]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>