<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20201005044125|981918778" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="3875331" pageid="3875331" ns="0" title="Social determinants of health"><revisions><rev timestamp="2020-11-26T04:45:05Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">The  '''social determinants of health''' are the economic and social conditions that influence individual and group differences in [[Health|health status]].&lt;ref&gt;Braveman, P. and Gottlieb, L., 2014. The social determinants of health: it's time to consider the causes of the causes. Public health reports, 129(1_suppl2), pp.19-31.&lt;/ref&gt; They are the [[Health promotion|health promoting]] factors found in one's living and working conditions (such as the distribution of income, wealth, influence, and power), rather than individual [[risk factor]]s (such as behavioral risk factors or genetics) that influence the risk for a [[disease]], or vulnerability to disease or [[injury]]. The distributions of social determinants are often shaped by public policies that reflect prevailing political ideologies of the area.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |url=http://www.thecanadianfacts.org/The_Canadian_Facts.pdf |title=Social Determinants of Health: The Canadian Facts |first1=Juha |last1=Mikkonen |first2=Dennis |last2=Raphael |year=2010 |isbn=978-0-9683484-1-3 |access-date=2015-05-03 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150319082632/http://www.thecanadianfacts.org/The_Canadian_Facts.pdf |archive-date=2015-03-19 |url-status=live }}{{page needed|date=May 2015}}{{Self-published source|date=March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[World Health Organization]] says, "This unequal distribution of health-damaging experiences is not in any sense a 'natural' phenomenon but is the result of a toxic combination of poor social policies, unfair economic arrangements [where the already well-off and healthy become even richer and the poor who are already more likely to be ill become even poorer], and bad politics."&lt;ref name="WHO CSDH"&gt;{{cite book|author=Commission on Social Determinants of Health|url=http://whqlibdoc.who.int/publications/2008/9789241563703_eng.pdf|title=Closing the Gap in a Generation: Health Equity Through Action on the Social Determinants of Health|publisher=[[World Health Organization]]|year=2008|isbn=978-92-4-156370-3|access-date=2013-03-27|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130204024452/http://whqlibdoc.who.int/publications/2008/9789241563703_eng.pdf|archive-date=2013-02-04|url-status=live}} Pg 2&lt;/ref&gt;

== Historical development ==
[[File:Social_determinants_of_health_visualization.png|alt=|thumb|Social Determinants of Health visualization]]
Starting in the early 2000s, the World Health Organization facilitated the academic and political work on social determinants in a way that provided a deep understanding of health disparities in a global perspective.

In 2003, the [[World Health Organization]] (WHO) Europe suggested that the social determinants of health included: the social gradient, [[Psychological stress|stress]], early life, [[social exclusion]], work, [[unemployment]], [[social support]], [[addiction]], [[food]], and [[transportation]].&lt;ref&gt;Wilkinson, Richard; Marmot, Michael, eds. (2003). ''The Social Determinants of Health: The Solid Facts'' (PDF) (2nd ed.). [[World Health Organization]] Europe. {{ISBN|978-92-890-1371-0}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2008, the WHO Commission on Social Determinants of Health published a report entitled "Closing the Gap in a Generation.", which aimed to understand, from a social justice perspective, how health inequity could be remedied, and what actions could combat factors that exacerbated injustices.&lt;ref name="WHO CSDH2"&gt;{{cite book|author=Commission on Social Determinants of Health|url=http://whqlibdoc.who.int/publications/2008/9789241563703_eng.pdf|title=Closing the Gap in a Generation: Health Equity Through Action on the Social Determinants of Health|publisher=[[World Health Organization]]|year=2008|isbn=978-92-4-156370-3|access-date=2013-03-27}} Pg 2&lt;/ref&gt; The work of the Commission was based on development goals, and thus, connected SDH (social determinants of health) discourse to economic growth and bridging gaps in the healthcare system. &lt;ref name="WHO CSDH2" /&gt; This report identified two broad areas of social determinants of health that needed to be addressed.&lt;ref name="WHO CSDH2" /&gt; The first area was daily [[living conditions]], which included healthy [[Physical environment|physical environments]], fair employment and decent work, [[social protection]] across the lifespan, and access to health care. The second major area was distribution of power, money, and resources, including [[Health equity|equity]] in health programs, public financing of action on the social determinants, [[Economic inequality|economic inequalities]], [[resource depletion]], [https://www.cdc.gov/niosh/docs/2015-178/ healthy working conditions], [[Gender equality|gender equity]], [[political empowerment]], constitution of reserves&lt;ref name=":022"&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Cullati|first1=Stéphane|last2=Kliegel|first2=Matthias|last3=Widmer|first3=Eric|date=2018-07-30|title=Development of reserves over the life course and onset of vulnerability in later life|journal=Nature Human Behaviour|language=En|volume=2|issue=8|pages=551–558|doi=10.1038/s41562-018-0395-3|issn=2397-3374|pmid=31209322|s2cid=51881794}}&lt;/ref&gt; and a balance of power and prosperity of nations.&lt;ref name="WHO CSDH2" /&gt;

The 2010 Affordable Care Act (ACA) established by the Obama administration in the United States, embodied the ideas put in place by the WHO by bridging the gap between community-based health and healthcare as a medical treatment, meaning that a larger consideration of social determinants of health was emerging in policy.&lt;ref&gt;Heiman, Harry J., and Samantha Artiga. "Beyond Health Care: The Role of Social Determinants in Promoting Health and Health Equity." Health 20.10 (2015): 1-10.&lt;/ref&gt; The ACA established community change through initiatives like providing Community Transformation Grants to community organizations, which opened up further debates and talks about increased integration of policies to create change on a larger scale.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Leong|first1=Donna|last2=Roberts|first2=Elizabeth|date=2013-07-01|title=Social determinants of health and the Affordable Care Act|journal=Rhode Island Medical Journal (2013)|volume=96|issue=7|pages=20–22|issn=2327-2228|pmid=23819136}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The 2011 World Conference on Social Determinants of Health, in which 125 delegations participated, created the Rio Political Declaration on Social Determinants of Health.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|last=Humber|first=Lee|title=Vital Signs: The Deadly Costs of Health Inequality|date=2019|pages=39–52|chapter=The Social Determinants of Health|chapter-url=https://uknowledge.uky.edu/cber_infographics/4|publisher=Pluto Press|doi=10.2307/j.ctvn5txst.7|isbn=978-1-78680-424-2|url=https://uknowledge.uky.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1003&amp;context=cber_infographics}}&lt;/ref&gt; With a series of affirmations and announcements, the Declaration aimed to communicate that the social conditions in which an individual exists were key to understanding health disparities that individual may face, and it called for new policies across the world to fight health disparities, along with global collaborations.&lt;ref&gt;The World Health Organization, World Conference on Social Determinants of Health, Rio Political Declaration on Social Determinants of Health (21 October 2011), available from https://www.who.int/sdhconference/declaration/Rio_political_declaration.pdf?ua=1.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Commonly accepted social determinants ==
The United States Centers for Disease Control defines social determinants of health as "life-enhancing resources, such as food supply, housing, economic and social relationships, transportation, education, and health care, whose distribution across populations effectively determines length and quality of life".&lt;ref name="USCDC2"&gt;{{cite book|last1=Brennan Ramirez|first1=Laura K.|url=https://www.cdc.gov/nccdphp/dch/programs/healthycommunitiesprogram/tools/pdf/SDOH-workbook.pdf|title=Promoting Health Equity: A Resource to Help Communities Address Social Determinants of Health|last2=Baker|first2=Elizabeth A.|last3=Metzler|first3=Marilyn|publisher=[[United States Centers for Disease Control and Prevention]]|year=2008|page=6|access-date=May 3, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; These include access to care and resources such as food, insurance coverage, income, housing, and transportation.&lt;ref name="USCDC2" /&gt;  Social determinants of health influence [[Health promotion|health-promoting]] behaviors, and [[health equity]] among the population is not possible without equitable distribution of social determinants among groups.&lt;ref name="USCDC2" /&gt;

In Canada, these social determinants of health have gained wide usage: [[Income]] and [[income distribution]]; [[Education]]; [[Unemployment]] and [[job security]]; [[Employment]] and [[working conditions]]; [[Early childhood development]]; [[Food insecurity]]&lt;ref&gt;Arenas, Daniel J., et al. "A Systematic Review and Meta-analysis of Depression, Anxiety, and Sleep Disorders in US Adults with Food Insecurity." Journal of general internal medicine (2019): 1-9. || https://doi.org/10.1007/s11606-019-05202-4&lt;/ref&gt;; [[Housing]]; [[Social exclusion]]/inclusion; [[Social safety net|Social safety network]]; [[Health care|Health services]]; [[Aboriginal peoples in Canada|Aboriginal]] status; [[Gender]]; [[Race (human classification)|Race]]; [[Disability]].&lt;ref name="pmid2088805922"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Bryant|first1=Toba|last2=Raphael|first2=Dennis|last3=Schrecker|first3=Ted|last4=Labonte|first4=Ronald|year=2011|title=Canada: A land of missed opportunity for addressing the social determinants of health|journal=Health Policy|volume=101|issue=1|pages=44–58|doi=10.1016/j.healthpol.2010.08.022|pmid=20888059}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The list of social determinants of health can be much longer. A recently published article identified several other social determinants .&lt;ref name="Islam, M. M 201922"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Islam|first1=M M|year=2019|title=Social Determinants of Health and Related Inequalities: Confusion and Implications|journal=Front. Public Health|volume=7|pages=11|doi=10.3389/fpubh.2019.00011|pmc=6376855|pmid=30800646}}&lt;/ref&gt; Unfortunately, there is no agreed taxonomy or criteria as to what should be considered a social determinant of health. In the literature, a subjective assessment—whether social factors impacting health are avoidable through structural changes in policy and practice—seems to be the dominant way of identifying a social determinant of health.&lt;ref name="Islam, M. M 201922"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Islam|first1=M M|year=2019|title=Social Determinants of Health and Related Inequalities: Confusion and Implications|journal=Front. Public Health|volume=7|pages=11|doi=10.3389/fpubh.2019.00011|pmc=6376855|pmid=30800646}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Ongoing debates ===
Steven H. Woolf, MD of the Virginia Commonwealth University Center on Human Needs states, "The degree to which social conditions affect health is illustrated by the association between education and mortality rates".&lt;ref name="Woolf, S. H 20092"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Woolf|first1=Steven H.|year=2009|title=Social Policy as Health Policy|journal=JAMA|volume=301|issue=11|pages=1166–9|doi=10.1001/jama.2009.320|pmid=19293418}}&lt;/ref&gt; Reports in 2005 revealed the [[mortality rate]] was 206.3 per 100,000 for adults aged 25 to 64 years with little education beyond high school, but was twice as great (477.6 per 100,000) for those with only a high school education and 3 times as great (650.4 per 100,000) for those less educated.  Based on the data collected, the social conditions such as education, income, and race were dependent on one another, but these social conditions also apply to independent health influences.&lt;ref name="Woolf, S. H 20092" /&gt;

Marmot and Bell of the University College London found that in wealthy countries, income and mortality are correlated as a marker of relative position within society, and this relative position is related to social conditions that are important for health including good [[early childhood development]], access to high quality education, rewarding work with some degree of autonomy, decent housing, and a clean and safe living environment. The social condition of [[autonomy]], control, and empowerment turns are important influences on health and disease, and individuals who lack social participation and control over their lives are at a greater risk for heart disease and mental illness.&lt;ref&gt;Marmot, Michael G.; Bell, Ruth (2009). "Action on Health Disparities in the United States". ''JAMA''. '''301''' (11): 1169–71. [[Doi (identifier)|doi]]:10.1001/jama.2009.363. [[PMID (identifier)|PMID]] 19293419.&lt;/ref&gt;

Early childhood development can be promoted or disrupted as a result of the social and environmental factors effecting the mother, while the child is still in the womb. Janet Currie’s research finds that women in New York City receiving assistance from the Special Supplemental Nutrition Program for Women, Infants, and Children (WIC), in comparison to their previous or future childbirth, are 5.6% less likely to give birth to a child who is underweight, an indication that a child will have better short term, and long term physical, and cognitive development. &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|url=https://www.nber.org/papers/w20400.pdf|last1=Currie|first1=Janet|last2=Rajani|first2=Ishita|title=Within-Mother Estimates of the Effects of Wic on Birth Outcomes in New York City|journal=Economic Inquiry|year=2015|volume=53|issue=4|pages=1691–1701|doi=10.1111/ecin.12219|pmid=28503006|pmc=5425167}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Several other social determinants are related to health outcomes and public policy, and are easily understood by the public to impact health.&lt;ref name="Islam, M. M 201922"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Islam|first1=M M|year=2019|title=Social Determinants of Health and Related Inequalities: Confusion and Implications|journal=Front. Public Health|volume=7|pages=11|doi=10.3389/fpubh.2019.00011|pmc=6376855|pmid=30800646}}&lt;/ref&gt; They tend to cluster together – for example, those living in poverty experience a number of negative health determinants.&lt;ref name="pmid20888059"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Bryant|first1=Toba|last2=Raphael|first2=Dennis|last3=Schrecker|first3=Ted|last4=Labonte|first4=Ronald|year=2011|title=Canada: A land of missed opportunity for addressing the social determinants of health|journal=Health Policy|volume=101|issue=1|pages=44–58|doi=10.1016/j.healthpol.2010.08.022|pmid=20888059}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== International health inequalities ==
[[File:Health gap in England and Wales, 2011 Census.png|thumb|Health gap in England and Wales, 2011 Census]]
Even in the wealthiest countries, there are health inequalities between the rich and the poor.&lt;ref name="WHO Europe"&gt;{{cite book|url=http://www.euro.who.int/__data/assets/pdf_file/0005/98438/e81384.pdf|title=The Social Determinants of Health: The Solid Facts|publisher=[[World Health Organization]] Europe|year=2003|isbn=978-92-890-1371-0|editor1-last=Wilkinson|editor1-first=Richard|edition=2nd|access-date=2013-03-27|editor2-last=Marmot|editor2-first=Michael|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130302175438/http://www.euro.who.int/__data/assets/pdf_file/0005/98438/e81384.pdf|archive-date=2013-03-02|url-status=live}}{{page needed|date=May 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Researchers Labonte and Schrecker from the Department of Epidemiology and Community Medicine at the University of Ottawa emphasize that globalization is key to understanding the social determinants of health, and as Bushra (2011) posits, the impacts of globalization are unequal.&lt;ref name="Labonte"&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1186/1744-8603-3-6 |pmid=17578569 |pmc=1919362 |title=Globalization and social determinants of health: The role of the global marketplace (part 2 of 3) |journal=Globalization and Health |volume=3 |pages=6 |year=2007 |last1=Labonté |first1=Ronald |last2=Schrecker |first2=Ted }}&lt;/ref&gt; Globalization has caused an uneven distribution of wealth and power both within and across national borders, and where and in what situation a person is born has an enormous impact on their health outcomes. The Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development found significant differences among developed nations in [[ICU scoring systems|health status indicators]] such as life expectancy, [[infant mortality]], [[incidence (epidemiology)|incidence]] of disease, and death from injuries.&lt;ref&gt;Organisation for Economic Cooperation and Development. (2007). Health at a Glance 2007, OECD Indicators. Paris: Organisation for Economic Cooperation and Development. Pg 25&lt;/ref&gt; Migrants and their family members also experience significant negatives health impacts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Flynn|first1=Michael|last2=Carreon|first2=Tania|last3=Eggerth|first3=Donald|last4=Johnson|first4=Antoinette|title=Immigration, Work, and Health: A Literature Review of Immigration Between Mexico and the United States|journal=Revista DeTrabajo Social UNAM|date=2014|volume=7|issue=6|pages=129–149|pmid=28260831|pmc=5334002}}&lt;/ref&gt;

These inequalities may exist in the context of the [[health care system]], or in broader social approaches.  According to the WHO's Commission on Social Determinants of Health, access to health care is essential for equitable health, and it argued that health care should be a common good rather than a market [[commodity]].&lt;ref name="WHO CSDH"/&gt; However, there is substantial variation in health care systems and coverage from country to country.  The Commission also calls for government action on such things as access to clean water and safe, equitable working conditions, and it notes that dangerous working conditions exist even in some wealthy countries.&lt;ref name=" WHO CSDH"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Flynn|first1=Michael|title=Undocumented Status as a Social Determinant of Occupational Safety and Health: The Workers' Perspective.|journal=Am. J. Ind. Med.|date=2015|volume=58|issue=11|pages=1127–1137|doi=10.1002/ajim.22531|pmid=26471878|pmc=4632487}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the Rio Political Declaration on Social Determinants of Health, several key areas of action were identified to address inequalities, including promotion of participatory [[public policy|policy]]-making processes, strengthening [[global governance]] and [[collaboration]], and encouraging developed countries to reach a target of 0.7% of [[gross national product]] (GNP) for official [[development assistance]].&lt;ref name="Rio Declaration"&gt;{{cite web|title=Rio Political Declaration on Social Determinants of Health|url=https://www.who.int/sdhconference/declaration/Rio_political_declaration.pdf|author=World Conference on Social Determinants of Health|year=2011|publisher=[[World Health Organization]]|url-status=live|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130531170358/http://www.who.int/sdhconference/declaration/Rio_political_declaration.pdf|archive-date=2013-05-31|access-date=2013-03-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Theoretical approaches ==

The UK ''Black'' and ''The Health Divide'' reports considered two primary mechanisms for understanding how social determinants influence health: cultural/behavioral and [[materialist]]/structuralist&lt;ref&gt;Townsend, P., Davidson, N., &amp; Whitehead, M. (Eds.). (1992). Inequalities in Health: the Black Report and the Health Divide. New York: Penguin.{{page needed|date=May 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; The cultural/behavioral explanation is that individuals' behavioral choices (e.g., tobacco and alcohol use, diet, physical activity, etc.) were responsible for their development and deaths from a variety of diseases. However, both the ''Black'' and ''Health Divide'' reports found that behavioral choices are determined by one's material conditions of life, and these behavioral [[risk factors]] account for a relatively small proportion of variation in the incidence and death from various diseases.

The materialist/structuralist explanation emphasizes the people's material living conditions. These conditions include availability of resources to access the [[amenities]] of life, [[working conditions]], and quality of available food and housing among others. Within this view, three frameworks have been developed to explain how social determinants influence health.&lt;ref&gt;Bartley, M. (2003). Understanding Health Inequalities. Oxford UK: Polity Press.{{page needed|date=May 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; These frameworks are: (a) materialist; (b) neo-materialist; and (c) [[psychosocial]] comparison. The materialist view explains how living conditions – and the social determinants of health that constitute these living conditions – shape health. The neo-materialist explanation extends the materialist analysis by asking how these living conditions occur. The psychosocial comparison explanation considers whether people compare themselves to others and how these comparisons affect health and wellbeing.

A nation's wealth is a strong indicator of the health of its population. Within nations, however, individual [[socio-economic]] position is a powerful predictor of health.&lt;ref name="Graham"&gt;Graham, H. (2007). Unequal Lives: Health and Socioeconomic Inequalities. New York: Open University Press.{{page needed|date=May 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Material conditions of life determine health by influencing the quality of individual development, family life and interaction, and community environments. Material conditions of life lead to differing likelihood of physical ([[infections]], [[malnutrition]], [[chronic disease]], and [[injuries]]), developmental (delayed or impaired [[Cognitive development|cognitive]], [[Personality development|personality]], and [[Social emotional development|social development]], educational ([[learning disabilities]], poor learning, early school leaving), and social ([[socialization]], preparation for work, and family life) problems.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Shaw |first1=M. |last2=Dorling |first2=D. |last3=Gordon |first3=D. |last4=Smith |first4=G. D. |year=1999 |title=The Widening Gap: Health Inequalities and Policy in Britain |location=Bristol, UK |publisher=The Policy Press}}{{page needed|date=May 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Material conditions of life also lead to differences in psychosocial stress.&lt;ref name="MarmotWilkinson2005pp6-30"&gt;{{cite book |doi=10.1093/acprof:oso/9780198565895.003.02 |chapter=Social organization, stress, and health |title=Social Determinants of Health |pages=6–30 |year=2005 |last1=Marmot |first1=Michael |last2=Wilkinson |first2=Richard G. |isbn=978-0-19-856589-5 |editor1-first=Michael |editor1-last=Marmot |editor2-first=Richard |editor2-last=Wilkinson }}&lt;/ref&gt; When the fight-or-flight reaction is chronically elicited in response to constant threats to income, housing, and food availability, the [[immune system]] is weakened, [[insulin resistance]] is increased, and lipid and clotting disorders appear more frequently.

The materialist approach offers insight into the sources of health inequalities among individuals and nations. Adoption of health-threatening behaviours is also influenced by material deprivation and stress.&lt;ref name="MarmotWilkinson2005pp224-37"&gt;{{cite book |doi=10.1093/acprof:oso/9780198565895.003.11 |chapter=Social patterning of individual health behaviours: The case of cigarette smoking |title=Social Determinants of Health |pages=224–37 |year=2005 |last1=Marmot |first1=Michael |last2=Wilkinson |first2=Richard G. |isbn=978-0-19-856589-5 |editor1-first=Michael |editor1-last=Marmot |editor2-first=Richard |editor2-last=Wilkinson }}&lt;/ref&gt; Environments influence whether individuals take up tobacco, use alcohol, consume poor diets, and have low levels of physical activity. Tobacco use, excessive alcohol consumption, and carbohydrate-dense diets are also used to cope with difficult circumstances.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Wilkinson |first=R. G. |year=1996 |title=Unhealthy Societies: The Afflictions of Inequality |location=New York |publisher=Routledge |isbn=978-0-415-09234-0}}{{page needed|date=May 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="MarmotWilkinson2005pp224-37"/&gt; The materialist approach seeks to understand how these social determinants occur.

The neo-materialist approach is concerned with how nations, regions, and cities differ on how economic and other resources are distributed among the population.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1136/bmj.320.7243.1200 |pmid=10784551 |pmc=1127589 |title=Income inequality and mortality: Importance to health of individual income, psychosocial environment, or material conditions |journal=BMJ |volume=320 |issue=7243 |pages=1200–4 |year=2000 |last1=Lynch |first1=J. W |last2=Smith |first2=G. D. |last3=Kaplan |first3=G. A. |last4=House |first4=J. S. }}&lt;/ref&gt; This distribution of resources can vary widely from country to country. The neo-materialist view focuses on both the social determinants of health and the societal factors that determine the distribution of these social determinants, and especially emphasizes how resources are distributed among members of a society.

The social comparison approach holds that the social determinants of health play their role through citizens' interpretations of their standings in the [[social hierarchy]].&lt;ref name=KawachiKennedy2002&gt;{{cite book |last1=Kawachi |first1=I. |last2=Kennedy |first2=B. |year=2002 |title=The Health of Nations: Why Inequality Is Harmful to Your Health |location=New York |publisher=New Press}}{{page needed|date=May 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; There are two mechanisms by which this occurs. At the individual level, the perception and experience of one's status in unequal societies lead to stress and poor health. Feelings of shame, worthlessness, and envy can lead to harmful effects upon neuro-endocrine, autonomic and metabolic, and immune systems.&lt;ref name="MarmotWilkinson2005pp6-30"/&gt; Comparisons to those of a higher social class can also lead to attempts to alleviate such feelings by overspending, taking on additional employment that threaten health, and adopting health-threatening coping behaviours such as overeating and using alcohol and tobacco.&lt;ref name=KawachiKennedy2002/&gt; At the communal level, widening and strengthening of hierarchy weakens [[social cohesion]], which is a determinant of health.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1136/bmj.314.7086.1037 |pmid=9112854 |pmc=2126438 |title=Socioeconomic determinants of health : Health and social cohesion: Why care about income inequality? |journal=BMJ |volume=314 |issue=7086 |pages=1037–40 |year=1997 |last1=Kawachi |first1=I. |last2=Kennedy |first2=B. P }}&lt;/ref&gt; The social comparison approach directs attention to the psychosocial effects of public policies that weaken the social determinants of health. However, these effects may be secondary to how societies distribute material resources and provide security to its citizens, which are described in the materialist and neo-materialist approaches.{{citation needed|date=May 2015}}

== Life-course perspective ==

Life-course approaches emphasize the accumulated effects of experience across the life span in understanding the maintenance of health and the onset of disease. The economic and social conditions – the social determinants of health – under which individuals live their lives have a cumulative effect upon the probability of developing any number of diseases, including heart disease and stroke.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Blane |first=D. |year=2006 |chapter=The life course, the social gradient and health |editor1-first=M. G. |editor1-last=Marmot |editor2-first=R. G. |editor2-last=Wilkinson |title=Social Determinants of Health |edition=2nd |pages=54–77 |location=Oxford |publisher=Oxford University Press}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|last1=Burton-Jeangros|first1=Claudine|title=Introduction|date=2015|url=https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK385366/|work=A Life Course Perspective on Health Trajectories and Transitions|editor-last=Burton-Jeangros|editor-first=Claudine|publisher=Springer|isbn=9783319204833|pmid=27683928|access-date=2018-09-06|last2=Cullati|first2=Stéphane|last3=Sacker|first3=Amanda|last4=Blane|first4=David|editor2-last=Cullati|editor2-first=Stéphane|editor3-last=Sacker|editor3-first=Amanda|editor4-last=Blane|editor4-first=David|doi=10.1007/978-3-319-20484-0_1|doi-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt; Studies into the childhood and adulthood antecedents of adult-onset diabetes show that adverse economic and social conditions across the life span predispose individuals to this disorder.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1136/bmj.325.7368.805 |pmid=12376440 |pmc=128946 |title=Socioeconomic position in childhood and adulthood and insulin resistance: Cross sectional survey using data from British women's heart and health study |journal=BMJ |volume=325 |issue=7368 |pages=805 |year=2002 |last1=Lawlor |first1=D. A |last2=Ebrahim |first2=S |last3=Davey Smith |first3=G |author4=British women's heart health study }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1108/13660750310486730 |title=The social determinants of the incidence and management of type 2 diabetes mellitus: Are we prepared to rethink our questions and redirect our research activities? |journal=Leadership in Health Services |volume=16 |issue=3 |pages=10–20 |year=2003 |last1=Raphael |first1=Dennis |last2=Anstice |first2=Susan |last3=Raine |first3=Kim |last4=McGannon |first4=Kerry R. |last5=Kamil Rizvi |first5=Syed |last6=Yu |first6=Vanessa }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Hertzman outlines three [[health effect]]s that have relevance for a life-course perspective.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Hertzman |first=Clyde |title=The case for an early childhood development strategy |journal=Isuma |volume=1 |issue=2 |pages=11–8 |year=2000 |url=http://www.peelearlyyears.com/pdf/The%20Case%20for%20an%20Early%20Childhood%20Development%20Strategy,%20Canada.pdf |access-date=2015-05-03 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160304083057/http://www.peelearlyyears.com/pdf/The%20Case%20for%20an%20Early%20Childhood%20Development%20Strategy,%20Canada.pdf |archive-date=2016-03-04 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt; Latent effects are biological or developmental early life experiences that influence health later in life. [[Birth weight|Low birth weight]], for instance, is a reliable predictor of incidence of cardiovascular disease and adult-onset diabetes in later life. Nutritional deprivation during childhood has lasting health effects as well.

Pathway effects are experiences that set individuals onto trajectories that influence health, well-being, and competence over the life course. As one example, children who enter school with delayed vocabulary are set upon a path that leads to lower educational expectations, poor employment prospects, and greater likelihood of illness and disease across the lifespan. Deprivation associated with poor-quality neighbourhoods, schools, and housing sets children off on paths that are not conducive to health and well-being.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Staying Alive: Critical Perspectives on Health, Illness, and Health Care|last=Raphael|first=Dennis|publisher=Canadian Scholars’ Press|year=2010|isbn=9781551303703|location=Canada|pages=159}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{citation needed|date=May 2015}}

Cumulative effects are the accumulation of advantage or disadvantage over time that manifests itself in poor health, in particular between women and men.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Landös|first1=Aljoscha|last2=von Arx|first2=Martina|last3=Cheval|first3=Boris|last4=Sieber|first4=Stefan|last5=Kliegel|first5=Matthias|last6=Gabriel|first6=Rainer|last7=Orsholits|first7=Dan|last8=Linden|first8=Van Der|last9=A|first9=Bernadette W.|title=Childhood socioeconomic circumstances and disability trajectories in older men and women: a European cohort study|journal=European Journal of Public Health|volume=29|issue=1|pages=50–58|language=en|doi=10.1093/eurpub/cky166|pmid=30689924|pmc=6657275|year=2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; These involve the combination of latent and pathways effects. Adopting a life-course perspective directs attention to how social determinants of health operate at every level of development – early childhood, childhood, adolescence, and adulthood – to both immediately influence health and influence it in the future.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Social Determinants of Health: Canadian Perspectives|last=Raphael|first=Dennis|publisher=Canadian Scholars’ Press|year=2016|isbn=9781551308975|location=Canada|pages=20}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Cheval|first1=Boris|last2=Boisgontier|first2=Matthieu P|last3=Orsholits|first3=Dan|last4=Sieber|first4=Stefan|last5=Guessous|first5=Idris|last6=Gabriel|first6=Rainer|last7=Stringhini|first7=Silvia|last8=Blane|first8=David|last9=van der Linden|first9=Bernadette W A|date=2018-02-20|title=Association of early- and adult-life socioeconomic circumstances with muscle strength in older age|journal=Age and Ageing|language=en|volume=47|issue=3|pages=398–407|doi=10.1093/ageing/afy003|pmid=29471364|pmc=7189981|issn=0002-0729|doi-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{citation needed|date=May 2015}}

==Chronic stress and health==

[[Stress (psychological)|Stress]] is hypothesized to be a major influence in the social determinants of health. There is a relationship between experience of chronic stress and negative health outcomes.&lt;ref name=Gouin&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1177/1559827610395467 |title=Chronic Stress, Immune Dysregulation, and Health |journal=American Journal of Lifestyle Medicine |volume=5 |issue=6 |pages=476–85 |year=2011 |last1=Gouin |first1=J.-P. |s2cid=71850339 }}&lt;/ref&gt; This relationship is explained through both direct and indirect effects of chronic stress on health outcomes.

The direct relationship between stress and health outcomes is the effect of stress on human physiology. The long term stress hormone, [[cortisol]], is believed to be the key driver in this relationship.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1037/0033-2909.133.1.25 |pmid=17201569 |title=If it goes up, must it come down? Chronic stress and the hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenocortical axis in humans |journal=Psychological Bulletin |volume=133 |issue=1 |pages=25–45 |year=2007 |last1=Miller |first1=Gregory E. |last2=Chen |first2=Edith |last3=Zhou |first3=Eric S. }}&lt;/ref&gt; Chronic stress has been found to be significantly associated with chronic low-grade inflammation, slower wound healing, increased susceptibility to infections, and poorer responses to vaccines.&lt;ref name=Gouin /&gt; [[Meta-analysis]] of healing studies has found that there is a robust relationship between elevated stress levels and slower healing for many different acute and chronic conditions&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1016/j.jpsychores.2009.04.002 |pmid=19686881 |title=Psychological stress and wound healing in humans: A systematic review and meta-analysis |journal=Journal of Psychosomatic Research |volume=67 |issue=3 |pages=253–71 |year=2009 |last1=Walburn |first1=Jessica |last2=Vedhara |first2=Kavita |last3=Hankins |first3=Matthew |last4=Rixon |first4=Lorna |last5=Weinman |first5=John |url=http://sro.sussex.ac.uk/2232/1/wound_healing.pdf |access-date=2019-01-30 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170809082558/http://sro.sussex.ac.uk/2232/1/wound_healing.pdf |archive-date=2017-08-09 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt; However, it is also important to note that certain factors, such as coping styles and social support, can mitigate the relationship between chronic stress and health outcomes.&lt;ref name=Cwikel&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Cwikel |first1=Julie |last2=Segal-Engelchin |first2=Dorit |last3=Mendlinger |first3=Sheryl |title=Mothers' coping styles during times of chronic security stress: effect on health status | doi=10.1080/07399330903141245 |pmid=20390642 |journal= [[Health Care for Women International]] |volume=31 |issue=2 |pages=131–52 |year=2010 |s2cid=25006806 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first1=Sheldon |last1=Cohen |first2=Garth |last2=McKay |chapter=Social Support, Stress and the Buffering Hypothesis: A Theoretical Analysis |editor1-first=A. |editor1-last=Baum |editor2-first=S.E. |editor2-last=Taylor |editor3-first=J.E. |editor3-last=Singer |year=1984 |title=Handbook of Psychology and Health |pages=253–67 |chapter-url=http://www.psy.cmu.edu/~scohen/buffer84.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Stress can also be seen to have an indirect effect on health status. One way this happens is due to the strain on the psychological resources of the stressed individual. Chronic stress is common in those of a low socio-economic status, who are having to balance worries about financial security, how they will feed their families, housing status, and many other concerns.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1093/phe/phs022 |title=Behavior Change or Empowerment: On the Ethics of Health-Promotion Strategies |journal=Public Health Ethics |volume=5 |issue=2 |pages=140–53 |year=2012 |last1=Tengland |first1=P.-A. |hdl=2043/14851 |hdl-access=free }}&lt;/ref&gt; Therefore, individuals with these kinds of worries may lack the emotional resources to adopt positive health behaviours. Chronically stressed individuals may therefore be less likely to prioritize their health.

In addition to this, the way that an individual responds to stress can influence their health status. Often, individuals responding to chronic stress will develop potentially positive or negative coping behaviors. People who cope with stress through positive behaviors such as exercise or social connections may not be as affected by the relationship between stress and health, whereas those with a coping style more prone to over-consumption (i.e. [[emotional eating]], drinking, smoking or drug use) are more likely to be see negative health effects of stress.&lt;ref name=Cwikel /&gt;

The detrimental effects of stress on health outcomes are hypothesised to partly explain why countries that have high levels of income inequality have poorer health outcomes compared to more equal countries.&lt;ref name="WP"&gt;Wilkinson, R. &amp; Pickett, K. (2009) The spirit level : why more equal societies almost always do better. London: Allen Lane.{{page needed|date=May 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Wilkinson and Picket hypothesise in their book [[The Spirit Level: Why More Equal Societies Almost Always Do Better|The Spirit Level]] that the stressors associated with low social status are amplified in societies where others are clearly far better off.&lt;ref name=WP/&gt;

==Improving health conditions worldwide==
Reducing the health gap requires that governments build systems that allow a healthy standard of living for every resident.

=== Interventions ===
Three common interventions for improving social determinant outcomes as identified by the WHO are education, social security and urban development. However, evaluation of interventions has been difficult due to the nature of the interventions, their impact and the fact that the interventions strongly affect children's health outcomes.&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;World Health Organization (2013). [http://apps.who.int/iris/bitstream/handle/10665/84213/9789241548625_eng.pdf;jsessionid=97F39CFE3967A7FE93BA46E18B4418E9?sequence=1 The economics of social determinants of health and health inequalities: a resource book (PDF)]. [[World Health Organization]]. {{ISBN|978-92-4-154862-5}}. retrieved 2018-04-02&lt;/ref&gt;

#Education: Many scientific studies have been conducted and strongly suggests that increased quantity and quality of education leads to benefits to both the individual and society (e.g. improved labor productivity).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Hanushek|first1=Eric|last2=Woessmann|first2=Ludger|date=November 2010|title=The Economics of International Differences in Education Achievement|url=https://www.elsevier.com/books/handbook-of-the-economics-of-education/hanushek/978-0-444-53429-3|journal=Handbook of the Economics of Education|volume=3|via=Elsevier|access-date=2018-04-28|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180428182241/https://www.elsevier.com/books/handbook-of-the-economics-of-education/hanushek/978-0-444-53429-3|archive-date=2018-04-28|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; Health and economic outcome improvements can be seen in health measures such as [[blood pressure]],&lt;ref&gt;Cutler, David, and [[Adriana Lleras-Muney]] (2008). “Education and Health: Evaluating Theories and Evidence.” Making Americans Healthier: Social and Economic Policy as HealthPolicy, edited by J House, R Schoeni, G Kaplan, and H Pollack. New York: Russell Sage Foundation.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Sabates|first1=Ricardo|last2=Feinstein|first2=Leon|date=2006|title=The role of education in the uptake of preventative health care: The case of cervical screening in Britain|journal=Social Science &amp; Medicine|volume=62|issue=12|pages=2998–3010|doi=10.1016/j.socscimed.2005.11.032|pmid=16403597}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[crime]],&lt;ref&gt;The Centre for Research on the Wider Benefits of Learning (2002). ''[http://discovery.ucl.ac.uk/10018624/1/WBLResRep5.pdf Quantitative Estimates of the Social Benefits of Learning 1: Crime]'' (PDF). Department for Education and Skills, UK. ISBM 1-898453-36-5. Retrieved 2018-04-05.&lt;/ref&gt; and market participation trends.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Canton|first=Erik|date=2007|title=Social returns to education: Macro-evidence|journal=De Economist|volume=155|issue=4|pages=449–468|doi=10.1007/s10645-007-9072-z|s2cid=154484748}}&lt;/ref&gt; Examples of interventions include decreasing size of classes and providing additional resources to low-income school districts. However, there is currently insufficient evidence to support education as an social determinants intervention with a [[Cost–benefit analysis|cost-benefit analysis]].&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;
#Social Protection: Interventions such as “health-related cash transfers”, maternal education, and nutrition-based social protections have been shown to have a positive impact on health outcomes.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Chunh|first1=Haejoo|last2=Muntaner|first2=Carles|date=2006|title=Welfare state matters: A typological multilevel analysis of wealthy countries|journal=Health Policy|volume=80|issue=2|pages=328–339|doi=10.1016/j.healthpol.2006.03.004|pmid=16678294}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Economic Policy Research Institute (2004). ''[http://allafrica.com/download/resource/main/main/idatcs/00010352:3ca37b223f2ad1b0dc6479ccca726034.pdf The Social and Economic Impact of South Africa's Social Security System] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180428181541/http://allafrica.com/download/resource/main/main/idatcs/00010352:3ca37b223f2ad1b0dc6479ccca726034.pdf |date=2018-04-28 }}'' (PDF). Commissioned by Directorate: Finance and Economics. Retrieved 2018-04-06.&lt;/ref&gt; However, the full economic costs and impacts generated of social security interventions are difficult to evaluate, especially as many social protections primarily affect children of recipients.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;
#Urban Development: Urban development interventions include a wide variety of potential targets such as housing, transportation, and infrastructure improvements. The health benefits are considerable (especially for children), because housing improvements such as smoke alarm installation, concrete flooring, removal of lead paint, etc. can have a direct impact on health.&lt;ref&gt;Breysse et al. (2004). ''[https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC1247625/ The Relationship between Housing and Health: Children at Risk.] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170121085649/https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC1247625/ |date=2017-01-21 }}'' Environ Health Perspect 112.15. pg 1583-1588.&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, there is a fair amount of evidence to prove that external urban development interventions such as transportation improvements or improved walkability of neighborhoods (which is highly effective in developed countries) can have health benefits.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt; Affordable housing options (including public housing) can make large contributions to both social determinants of health, as well as the local economy.&lt;ref&gt;Econsult Corp (2018). [http://www.clpha.org/EconomicImpact ''The Economic Impact of'' ''Public Housing: Ongoing Investment with Wide Reaching Returns''] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20181127064618/http://www.clpha.org/EconomicImpact |date=2018-11-27 }}. Council of Large Public Housing Authorities.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Commission on Social Determinants of Health made recommendations in 2005 for action to promote health equity based on three principles: "improve the circumstances in which people are born, grow, live, work, and age; tackle the inequitable distribution of power, money, and resources, the structural drivers of conditions of daily life, globally, nationally, and locally; and measure the problem, evaluate action, and expand the knowledge base."&lt;ref name="MarmotMichael2"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Marmot|first1=Michael G.|last2=Bell|first2=Ruth|year=2009|title=Action on Health Disparities in the United States|journal=JAMA|volume=301|issue=11|pages=1169–71|doi=10.1001/jama.2009.363|pmid=19293419}}&lt;/ref&gt; These recommendations would involve providing resources such as quality education, decent housing, access to affordable health care, access to healthy food, and safe places to exercise for everyone despite gaps in affluence. Expansion of knowledge of the social determinants of health, including among healthcare workers, can improve the quality and standard of care for people who are marginalized, poor or living in developing nations by preventing early death and disability while working to improve quality of life.&lt;ref name="Farmer2"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Farmer|first1=Paul E.|last2=Nizeye|first2=Bruce|last3=Stulac|first3=Sara|last4=Keshavjee|first4=Salmaan|year=2006|title=Structural Violence and Clinical Medicine|journal=PLOS Medicine|volume=3|issue=10|pages=e449|doi=10.1371/journal.pmed.0030449|pmc=1621099|pmid=17076568}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Challenges of measuring value of interventions ===
Many economic studies have been conducted to measure the effectiveness and value of social determinant interventions but are unable to accurately reflect effects on public health due to the multi-faceted nature of the topic. While neither [[Cost-effectiveness analysis|cost-effectiveness]] nor [[Cost–utility analysis|cost-utility analysis]] is able to be used on social determinant interventions, cost-benefit analysis is able to better capture the effects of an intervention on multiple sectors of the economy. For example, tobacco interventions have shown to decrease tobacco use, but also prolong lifespans, increasing lifetime healthcare costs and is therefore marked as a failed intervention by cost-effectiveness, but not cost-benefit. Another issue with research in this area is that most of the current scientific papers focus on rich, developed countries, and there is a lack of research in developing countries.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;

Policy changes that affect children also present the challenge that it takes a significant amount of time to gather this type of data. In addition, policies to reduce [[child poverty]]&lt;nowiki/&gt;are particularly important, as elevated stress hormones in children interfere with the development of brain circuitry and connections, causing long term chemical damage.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Evans|first1=G. W.|last2=Schamberg|first2=M. A.|year=2009|title=Childhood poverty, chronic stress, and adult working memory|journal=Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences|volume=106|issue=16|pages=6545–9|bibcode=2009PNAS..106.6545E|doi=10.1073/pnas.0811910106|jstor=40482133|pmc=2662958|pmid=19332779}}&lt;/ref&gt; In most wealthy countries, the relative child poverty rate is 10 percent or less; in the United States, it is 21.9 percent.&lt;ref name=":02"&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Smeeding|first=Timothy|year=2006|title=Poor People in Rich Nations: The United States in Comparative Perspective|url=https://www2.hawaii.edu/~noy/300texts/poverty-comparative.pdf|journal=Journal of Economic Perspectives|volume=20|pages=69–90|doi=10.1257/089533006776526094|hdl=10419/95383|access-date=2017-02-01|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160303234002/http://www2.hawaii.edu/~noy/300texts/poverty-comparative.pdf|archive-date=2016-03-03|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; The lowest poverty rates are more common in smaller well-developed and high-spending welfare states like Sweden and Finland, with about 5 or 6 percent.&lt;ref name=":02" /&gt;  Middle-level rates are found in major European countries where unemployment compensation is more generous and social policies provide more generous support to single mothers and working women (through paid family leave, for example), and where social assistance minimums are high.  For instance, the Netherlands, Austria, Belgium and Germany have poverty rates that are in the 7 to 8 percent range.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Smeeding|first1=Timothy|year=2006|title=Poor People in Rich Nations: The United States in Comparative Perspective|journal=Journal of Economic Perspectives|volume=20|issue=1|pages=69–90|doi=10.1257/089533006776526094|jstor=30033634|hdl=10419/95383|url=http://www.lisdatacenter.org/wps/liswps/419.pdf|access-date=2019-12-10|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190430025600/http://www.lisdatacenter.org/wps/liswps/419.pdf|archive-date=2019-04-30|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Within clinical settings ==
Connecting patients with the necessary social services during their visits to hospitals or medical clinics is an important factor in preventing patients from experiencing decreased health outcomes as a result of social or environmental factors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Social determinants of health: What medical students need to know | publisher = American Medical Association | url = https://www.ama-assn.org/delivering-care/patient-support-advocacy/social-determinants-health-what-medical-students-need-know | access-date = 16 Sep 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A clinical study done by researchers at the University of California San Francisco, indicated that connecting patients with the resources to utilize and contact social services during clinical visits, significantly decreased families social needs and significantly improved children's overall health. &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Gottlieb|first1=Laura M.|last2=Hessler|first2=Danielle|last3=Long|first3=Dayna|last4=Laves|first4=Ellen|last5=Burns|first5=Abigail R.|last6=Amaya|first6=Anais|last7=Sweeney|first7=Patricia|last8=Schudel|first8=Christine|last9=Adler|first9=Nancy E.|date=2016-11-01|title=Effects of Social Needs Screening and In-Person Service Navigation on Child Health: A Randomized Clinical Trial|url=https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamapediatrics/fullarticle/2548441|journal=JAMA Pediatrics|language=en|volume=170|issue=11|pages=e162521|doi=10.1001/jamapediatrics.2016.2521|pmid=27599265|issn=2168-6203|doi-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Public policy ==

The Rio Political Declaration on Social Determinants of Health embraces a transparent, participatory model of policy development that, among other things, addresses the social determinants of health leading to persistent health inequalities for indigenous peoples.&lt;ref name="Rio Declaration"/&gt; In 2017, citing the need for accountability for the pledges made by countries in the Rio Political Declaration on Social Determinants of Health, the World Health Organization and United Nations Children's Fund called for the monitoring of intersectoral interventions on the social determinants of health that improve health equity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.2471/BLT.16.184622 |pmid=29147060 |pmc=5677605 |url=https://www.who.int/bulletin/volumes/95/11/16-184622/en/ |title=The need to monitor actions on the social determinants of health |journal=Bulletin of the World Health Organization |volume=95 |issue=11 |pages=784–787 |year=2017 |last1=Pega |first1=Frank |last2=Valentine |first2=Nicole |last3=Rasanathan |first3=Kumanan |last4=Hosseinpoor |first4=Ahmad Reza |last5=Neira |first5=Maria |access-date=2017-11-02 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171102133727/http://www.who.int/bulletin/volumes/95/11/16-184622/en/ |archive-date=2017-11-02 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The United States Department of Health and Human Services includes social determinants in its model of population health, and one of its missions is to strengthen policies which are backed by the best available evidence and knowledge in the field &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://healthypeople.gov/2020/Consortium/HP2020Framework.pdf |title=Healthy People 2020 Framework |year=2010 |publisher=United States Department of Health and Human Services |access-date=2013-03-27 |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130215084008/http://healthypeople.gov/2020/Consortium/HP2020Framework.pdf |archive-date=2013-02-15 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
Social determinants of health do not exist in a vacuum. Their quality and availability to the population are usually a result of public policy decisions made by governing authorities. For example, early life is shaped by availability of sufficient material resources that assure adequate educational opportunities, food and housing among others.  Much of this has to do with the employment security and the quality of working conditions and wages. The availability of quality, regulated childcare is an especially important policy option in support of early life.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first1=Gøsta |last1=Esping-Andersen |chapter=A Child-Centred Social Investment Strategy |chapter-url=https://books.google.com/books?id=OaxGR8yrm10C&amp;pg=PA26 |pages=26–67 |editor1-first=Gøsta |editor1-last=Esping-Andersen |year=2002 |title=Why We Need a New Welfare State |isbn=978-0-19-925642-6}}&lt;/ref&gt; These are not issues that usually come under individual control but rather they are socially constructed conditions which require institutional responses.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Flynn|first1=Michael|last2=Check|first2=Pietra|last3=Eggerth|first3=Donald|last4=Tonda|first4=Josana|title=Improving Occupational Safety and Health Among Mexican Immigrant Workers|journal=Public Health Reports|date=2013|volume=128|issue=Suppl 3|pages=33–38|doi=10.1177/00333549131286S306|pmid=24179277|pmc=3945447}}&lt;/ref&gt; A policy-oriented approach places such findings within a broader policy context. In this context, [[Health in All Policies]] has seen as a response to incorporate health and health equity into all public policies as means to foster synergy between sectors and ultimately promote health.

Yet it is not uncommon to see governmental and other authorities individualize these issues. Governments may view early life as being primarily about parental behaviours towards their children.  They then focus upon promoting better parenting, assist in having parents read to their children, or urge schools to foster exercise among children rather than raising the amount of financial or housing resources available to families. Indeed, for every social determinant of health, an individualized manifestation of each is available. There is little evidence to suggest the efficacy of such approaches in improving the health status of those most vulnerable to illness in the absence of efforts to modify their adverse living conditions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Raphael |first=D. |year=2001 |title=Inequality is Bad for our Hearts: Why Low Income and Social Exclusion are Major Causes of Heart Disease in Canada |isbn=978-0-9689444-0-0}}{{page needed|date=May 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A team of the Cochrane Collaboration conducted the first comprehensive systematic review of the health impact of unconditional cash transfers, as an increasingly common up-stream, structural social determinant of health. The review of 21 studies, including 16 randomized controlled trials, found that unconditional cash transfers may not improve health services use. However, they lead to a large, clinically meaningful reduction in the likelihood of being sick by an estimated 27%. Unconditional cash transfers may also improve food security and dietary diversity. Children in recipient families are more likely to attend school, and the cash transfers may increase money spent on health care.&lt;ref name="doi10.1002/14651858.CD011135.pub2"&gt;{{cite journal |title=Unconditional cash transfers for reducing poverty and vulnerabilities: effect on use of health services and health outcomes in low- and middle-income countries |journal=Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews |volume=11 |pages=CD011135 |year=2017 |doi= 10.1002/14651858.CD011135.pub2 |pmid=29139110 |last1=Pega |first1=Frank |last2=Liu |first2=Sze |last3=Walter |first3=Stefan  |last4=Pabayo |first4=Roman |last5=Saith |first5=Ruhi |last6=Lhachimi |first6=Stefan |pmc=6486161 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

One of the recommendations by the Commission on the Social Determinants of Health is expanding knowledge – particularly to health care workers.&lt;ref name="Farmer2"/&gt;

Although not addressed by the WHO Commission on Social Determinants of Health, sexual orientation and gender identity are increasingly recognized as social determinants of health.&lt;ref name=pmid25602894&gt;{{cite journal |pmid=25602894 |title=The case for the World Health Organization's Commission on Social Determinants of Health to address gender identity |journal=American Journal of Public Health |volume=105 |issue=3 |pages=e58–62 |year=2015 |last1=Pega |first1=Frank |last2=Veale |first2=Jaimie |doi=10.2105/ajph.2014.302373 |pmc=4330845}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{div col|colwidth=15em}}
* [[Adverse Childhood Experiences Study]]
* [[Causal inference]]
* [[Center for Minority Health]]
* [[Diseases of affluence]]
* [[Diseases of poverty]]
* [[Epidemiology]]
* [[EuroHealthNet]]
* [[Etiology]]
* [[Exercise]]
* [[Global health]]
* [[Health equity]]
* [[Behavior#Health behaviour|Health behaviour]]
* [[Health literacy]]
* [[Healthy People]]
* [[Inequality in disease]]
* [[Joint Action Health Equity in Europe]]
* [[Hopkins Center for Health Disparities Solutions]]
* [[Medical anthropology]]
* [[Medical sociology]]
* [[Molecular pathological epidemiology]]
* [[Pathogenesis]]
* [[Pathology]]
* [[Population health]]
* [[Population Health Forum]]
* [[Race and health]]
* [[Social determinants of health in Mexico]]
* [[Social determinants of obesity]]
* [[Social epidemiology]]
* [[Unnatural Causes: Is Inequality Making Us Sick?]]
* [[Whitehall Study]]
* [[Michael Marmot]]
* [[Richard G. Wilkinson]]
* [[Dennis Raphael]]
{{div col end}}

== Notes and references ==
{{Reflist|2}}

== External links ==
{{Wikiquote}}
* [https://www.who.int/hia/evidence/doh/en/# The determinants of health (World Health Organization)]
* [https://www.who.int/social_determinants/en/ Commission on Social Determinants of Health (World Health Organization)]
* [https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC1731785/ A glossary for social epidemiology - N Krieger]
* [http://www.phac-aspc.gc.ca/ph-sp/determinants/determinants-eng.php Key determinants of health (Public Health Agency of Canada)]
* [http://nptel.ac.in/courses/109101007/downloads/LECTURE_NOTES/Module%203/lec3.pdf NPTEL - Socio-economic Status and Health Income Inequality and Health]
* [http://thecanadianfacts.org Social Determinants  of Health: The Canadian Facts]
* [https://www.nichd.nih.gov/vision/vision_themes/behavior/Documents/Braveman_Social_Context_Health.pdf The Social Context of Health Behaviors - Paula Braveman]
* [http://whqlibdoc.who.int/publications/2010/9789241563970_eng.pdf World Health Organization: Equity, Social Determinants and Public Health Programmes]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20050901002506/http://www.phac-aspc.gc.ca/ph-sp/phdd/determinants/index.html Public Health Agency of Canada: What determines health? - Key determinants]
* [http://health-gradient.eu/ Drivers for Health Equity]

{{Public health}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Social Determinants Of Health}}
[[Category:Public health]]
[[Category:Social inequality]]
[[Category:Determinants of health]]
[[Category:Cultural competence]]
[[Category:Social problems in medicine]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>