<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20061112202855|87393186" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1858124" pageid="1858124" ns="0" title="Height discrimination"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-11-12T23:56:21Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Heightism''' is a form of [[discrimination]] based on [[Human height|height]].  In principle it can refer to unfavorable treatment of either unusually tall or short people.  In practice heightism almost always takes the form of unfavorable treatment of shorter people and more favorable treatment of taller people (particularly tall [[men]]); the exception to this being that taller women generally have a harder time dating than shorter women (see [[#Heightism_in_dating_and_marriage|dating and marriage]] section).  Examples of this are the above average heights of the great majority of US presidents and CEOs.

==Heightism and bullying==
Research shows that shorter persons are more likely to be victims of [[bullying]].[http://www.scienceblog.com/community/older/2000/A/200000988.html] [http://bmj.bmjjournals.com/cgi/content/full/320/7235/0/f]  Not surprisingly, a bully will normally target smaller persons on the grounds that they are perceived to be less able to defend themselves physically.  Because bullying during childhood and adolescence often undermines the victim's [[self esteem]], some researchers speculate that the lower levels of achievement of shorter persons (particularly men) in later life may be partly or largely explained by this lower self esteem rather than by [[discrimination]].[http://www.ssc.upenn.edu/~persico/research/Papers/short.pdf]
On the other end of the scale however unusually tall children can often find that their standing out makes them the target of bullying- particularly to older children.

==Heightism in employment==
Some jobs do require or at least favor tall persons, including some [[Manual labour|manual labor]] jobs and many [[professional sports]], and US military pilots have to be 64 to 77 inches and have a sitting height of 34 to 40 inches.[http://www.afrotc.com/admissions/medicalReq.php]  These exceptions noted, in the great majority of cases a person's height would not seem to have an effect on how well they are able to perform their job.  Nevertheless, studies have shown that short people are paid less than taller people, with disparities similar in magnitude to the race and gender gaps. [http://www.ssc.upenn.edu/~persico/research/Papers/short.pdf] [http://www.essex.ac.uk/ilr/eeeg/Conference1/Harper.pdf] Generally, height discrimination takes the form of covert discrimination, with people being passed over for promotion or denied jobs in the first instance.   

A survey of [[Fortune 500]] [[Chief executive officer|CEO]] height in 2005 revealed that they were on average 6 feet tall, which is 3 inches taller than the average American man.  Fully 30% of these CEOs were 6 foot 2 inches tall or more; in comparison only 3.9% of the overall United States population is of this height.[http://www.stlouisfed.org/publications/re/2005/b/pages/appearances.html] Equally significantly, similar surveys have uncovered that less than 3% of CEOs were below 5'7" in height, and that 90% of CEOs are of above average height. [http://www.shortsupport.org/News/0106.html]

Some [[epidemiology|epidemiological]] studies have shown that [[intelligence]] is positively correlated with height in human populations (see [[Height and intelligence]]). This does not imply that many short people are not highly intelligent, or that changes in physical height have a direct effect on cognitive ability. Indeed, intelligence is believed to be influenced by many different factors, and individuals with a wide range of intelligence can be observed at any given height; it may be that good childhood nutrition tends to result in greater adult height, and good childhood nutrition also tends to result in higher adult intelligence. A recent study using four data sets from the [[USA|US]] and [[UK]] found that after controlling for difference in cognitive test scores, there was no detectable independent effect of height itself on adult earnings, indicating that the height premium in adult earnings can be explained by childhood scores on intelligence tests[http://www.slate.com/id/2148759/?nav=navoa]&lt;ref&gt;Anne Case, Christina Paxson. Stature and Status: Height, Ability, and Labor Market Outcomes. National Bureau of Economic Research, Working Paper No. 12466, August 2006&lt;/ref&gt;.

However, others believe that height has a significant independent impact, pointing to specific instances of height-based discrimination[http://somesmallsense.blogspot.com/2006/08/princeton-study-coorelates-height-and.html]. Subjectively, many short persons report they are not taken seriously in the work place or by their [[peer group|peer]]s because of their smaller stature[http://www.shortsupport.org/News/0106.html]. Objectively, surveys of attitudes do reveal that people both perceive and treat people of shorter stature as inferior, [http://poll.gallup.com/content/default.aspx?CI=18454][http://www.shortsupport.org/News/0106.html] and that economic differentials exist which may be the result of height discrimination[http://www.shortsupport.org/News/0301.html] The relationship between height, cognitive ability, and discrimination based on height remains a subject of debate.

==Heightism in politics==
Short candidates are disadvantaged in electoral politics at least in the [[United States]] (where statistics are available for study).  Of the 43 U.S. Presidents, only five have been more than an inch below average height.  Moreover, of the 54 US presidential elections [[Heights of U.S. presidential candidates|only 13 have been won by the shorter candidate]], and only 11 times has the shorter candidate received more popular (as opposed to [[US Electoral College|electoral]]) votes.  Quantitative studies of U.S. Senators and Governors have also shown that they are on average several inches taller than the U.S. population at large.[http://www.straightdope.com/classics/a3_308.html]

Non-electoral politics are more difficult to study as outcomes based on height are more difficult to quantify.  Nevertheless, a number of powerful dictators have been below average height.  Examples include [[Engelbert Dollfuss]] (4'11; 1,50m), [[Deng Xiaoping]] (5'0; 1,52m),  [[Kim Jong Il]] (5'3; 1,60m), [[Nikita Khrushchev]] (5'3; 1,60m), [[Francisco Franco]] (5'4; 1,63m), and [[Josef Stalin]] (5'5; 1,65m).  Contrary to popular impression, [[Napoleon Bonaparte#Misconceptions about Napoleon.27s height|Napoleon Bonaparte]] at 5'6.5 (1,69m) was slightly above average height for the time he lived.  [[Adolf Hitler]] was also taller (5'8; 1,73m) than has generally been assumed from fictional representations and some photographic records.

==Heightism and conflict==
Heightism is cited as one of the underlying causes of The [[Rwanda]]n Civil War, in which approximately one million people were killed. It is believed that one of the reasons that political power was conferred to the minority Tutsis by the exiting Belgians was because they were taller and therefore (in the eyes of the Belgians) considered superior and more suited to governance.[http://www.exile.ru/2003-November-25/war_nerd.html "Heightism rears its ugly head"]

==Heightism in dating and marriage==
Heightism may also be a factor in dating preferences.  For most women, the height of a man is a [[Sexual attraction#Factors determining sexual attraction of men|major factor in sexual attractiveness]].  The greater reproductive success of taller men is attested to by studies indicating that taller men are more likely to be married and to have more children, except in societies with severe gender imbalances caused by war.  [http://jrscience.wcp.muohio.edu/Research/HumanNatureProgArticles/dontwantnoshortshortmanFI.html]
[http://www.findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m1175/is_3_33/ai_62215068]  Quantitative studies of woman-for-men [[personal advertisement]]s have shown strong preference for tall men, with a large percentage indicating that a man significantly below average height was unacceptable. [http://www.shortsupport.org/Research/personals.html]

Conversely, studies have shown that women of below average height are more likely to be married and have children than women of above average height.  Some reasons which have been suggested for this situation include earlier fertility of shorter women, and that a shorter woman makes her partner feel taller in comparison and therefore more "manly."[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/health/2190461.stm]  Consistent with this, taller women are actually more likely to accept a shorter man as a partner.[http://www.shortsupport.org/Research/personals.html]

It is unclear and debated as to the extent to which such preferences are innate or are the function of a society in which height discrimination impacts on socio-economic status.

==Heightism in the media==
In the [[Mass media|media]], heightism can take the form of making fun of short men in ways that would be unseemly if directed at [[skin color]] or [[weight]] (especially female weight).  Examples of characters whose short stature is exploited for comic value are:  
*[[Lord Farquaad]] from [[Shrek]]
*Bob from [[Becker (TV series)|Becker]]
*Louis De Palma from [[Taxi (TV series)|Taxi]]
*[[Married..._with_Children#Bud_Bundy|Bud Bundy]] from [[Married... with Children ]]
*[[Radar O'Reilly|Radar]] from [[M*A*S*H (TV series)|M*A*S*H]]
*[[Spence Olchin|Spence]] from [[The King of Queens]]
*[[Gimli (Middle-earth)|Gimli]] and other dwarves from [[The Lord of the Rings: The Two Towers (film)|The Lord of the Rings: The Two Towers]]

The portrayal of short men in the media is in general negative. Short men are either ridiculously unsuccessful in regards of career and/or romance (e.g. Spence and Bud Bundy) or they are unlikeable tyrants in need of compensating for "something" (e.g. Lord Farquaad). A notable and rare exception are roles played by [[Michael J. Fox]] (especially [[Mike Flaherty]] from the TV series [[Spin City]], where a short man is portrayed as an attractive and likable person, who is successful both in romance and career).

"Archaeology Today" sketch in [[Monty Python's Flying Circus]] deals with heightism[http://metamedia.stanford.edu/projects/PopularArchaeology/176] in which an interviewer humorously admits to assessing his subject's credibility based on their height.

In a [[2006]] cartoon episode of [[Family Guy]], the second coming of [[Jesus]] is depicted, with Jesus very obviously being much shorter than the (modern) crowd he speaks to.  In the show, this causes uncertainty and surprise among the crowd.

In the cartoon series [[Invader Zim]], the alien race of the Irken had a class system based entirely on height, the empire being ruled by those of the greatest stature, literally referred to as the [[Almighty Tallest]].

Similarly, shorter men are often denied leading roles. Although some famous cinema actors such as [[Alan Ladd]] and [[Tom Cruise]] have been short in real life, in their fictional depictions they have been presented as taller.
[[Randy Newman]]'s song "[[Short People]]" deals with Heightism in a satirical, light-hearted manner as a protest against bigotry in general.  Nevertheless, some people find this song offensive.[http://www.shortsupport.org/TheMedia/music/shortpeople-sgoldsmith.html]

[[Fall Out Boy]]'s song "Short, Fast, and Loud" is about a girl who dumps her boyfriend (probably the lead singer) because he is too short for her.

==Resources for short adults==
The [[National Organization of Short Statured Adults]] is committed to the open discussion of heightism and sponsors a free message-board at [http://heightism.aimoo.com http://heightism.aimoo.com] In addition, Steve Goldsmith operates the Short Support website at [http://www.shortsupport.org www.shortsupport.org] which has been providing the short community with valuable resources on heightism related topics since 2000.

Sites that gear towards women include [http://somesmallsense.blogspot.com somesmallsense.blogspot.com], [http://www.the-chic-petite.com www.the-chic-petite.com],and [http://www.shorty-stories.com www.shorty-stories.com.]All of which discuss fashion issues that shorter women face.

==See also==
*[[Human height]]
*[[Discrimination]]
*[[Dwarfism]]
*[[List of famous tall women]]
*[[List of famous tall men]]
*[[List of famous short women]]
*[[List of famous short men]]

[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Prejudices]]
[[Category:Human height]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>