<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20091102140623|323471112" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1858124" pageid="1858124" ns="0" title="Height discrimination"><revisions><rev timestamp="2009-11-15T02:43:29Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Discrimination sidebar}}
'''Heightism''' is a form of [[discrimination]] based on [[Human height|height]]. In principle it can refer to unfavorable treatment of either unusually tall or short people.

==Bullying==
Research shows that shorter people are more likely to be victims of [[bullying]].&lt;ref name="ScienceBlog"&gt;[http://www.scienceblog.com/community/older/2000/A/200000988.html Science Blog: “Short children more likely to be bullied at school”]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="BMJ"&gt;[http://bmj.bmjjournals.com/cgi/content/full/320/7235/0/f “Short children are bullied more than normal sized ones”]&lt;/ref&gt; Because bullying during childhood and adolescence often undermines the victim’s [[self-esteem]], some researchers speculate that the lower levels of achievement of shorter people (particularly men) in later life may be partly or largely explained by this lower self esteem rather than by [[discrimination]].&lt;ref name="UPenn"&gt;[http://www.ssc.upenn.edu/~persico/research/Papers/short.pdf University of Pennsylvania, Arts and Sciences: “The Effect of Adolescent Experience on Labor Market Outcomes: The Case of Height”]&lt;/ref&gt;

==In business==
Some jobs do require or at least favor tall people, including some [[manual labor]] jobs, most [[professional sports]], and fashion modeling. U.S. military pilots have to be 64 to 77&amp;nbsp;inches (163 to 196&amp;nbsp;cm) tall with a sitting height of 34 to 40&amp;nbsp;inches (86 to 102&amp;nbsp;cm).&lt;ref name="AFROTC"&gt;[http://www.afrotc.com/admissions/medicalReq.php U.S. Air Force ROTC: Admissions requirements]&lt;/ref&gt; These exceptions noted, in the great majority of cases a person’s height would not seem to have an effect on how well they are able to perform their job. Nevertheless, studies have shown that short people are paid less than taller people, with disparities similar in magnitude to the race and gender gaps.&lt;ref name="UPenn" /&gt;&lt;ref name="UEssex"&gt;[http://www.essex.ac.uk/ilr/eeeg/Conference1/Harper.pdf University of Essex: “Beauty, Stature and the Labour Market: A British Cohort Study”] (PDF)&lt;/ref&gt;

A survey of [[Fortune 500]] [[Chief executive officer|CEO]] height in 2005 revealed that they were on average 6 feet (183&amp;nbsp;cm) tall, which is approximately 2-3&amp;nbsp;inches (7.5&amp;nbsp;cm) taller than the average American man. Fully 30% of these CEOs were 6 foot 2&amp;nbsp;inches (188&amp;nbsp;cm) tall or more; in comparison only 3.9% of the overall United States population is of this height.&lt;ref name="FedBank"&gt;[http://www.stlouisfed.org/publications/re/2005/b/pages/appearances.html Federal Reserve Bank of St. Louis: “So Much for That Merit Raise: The Link between Wages and Appearance”]&lt;/ref&gt; Similar surveys have uncovered that less than 3% of CEOs were below 5′7″ in (170&amp;nbsp;cm) height ''or'' taller than 6'2" in height. Ninety percent of CEOs are of above average height.&lt;ref name="Jonathan Rauch"&gt;[http://www.jonathanrauch.com/jrauch_articles/height_discrimination_short_guys_finish_last/index.html "Short Guys Finish Last" The world's most enduring form of discrimination. The Economist, 23 December 1995].&lt;/ref&gt;

Others believe that height has a significant independent impact on economic success, pointing to specific instances of height-based discrimination.&lt;ref name="Princeton"&gt;[http://somesmallsense.blogspot.com/2006/08/princeton-study-coorelates-height-and.html  Blogspot.com: “Princeton Study Coorelates ''&amp;#91;sic&amp;#93;'' Height and Intelligence”].&lt;/ref&gt; Surveys of attitudes do reveal that people both perceive and treat people of shorter stature as inferior,&lt;ref name="Gallup"&gt;[http://poll.gallup.com/content/default.aspx?CI=18454 The Gallup Poll: “Perception or Reality? The Effect of Stature on Life Outcomes”].&lt;/ref&gt; and that economic differentials exist which may be the result of height discrimination.&lt;ref name="ShortSupport2"&gt;[http://www.shortsupport.org/News/0301.html Short Persons Support: “Does Appearance Matter in the Labour Market?”].&lt;/ref&gt; The relationship between height, cognitive ability, and discrimination based on height remains a subject of debate.

==Intelligence==

Some [[epidemiology|epidemiological]] studies have shown that [[intelligence]] is positively correlated, albeit very slightly, with height in human populations (see [[Height and intelligence]]). This does not imply that many short people are not highly intelligent, or that changes in physical height have a direct effect on cognitive ability.  Intelligence is believed to be influenced by many different factors.  Individuals with a wide range of intelligence can be observed at any given height.

==In politics==
Taller candidates have the advantage in electoral politics, at least in the [[United States]] (where statistics are available for study).  Other countries may be different, such as Russia, where President [[Vladimir Putin]] is 5' 7.5" (1.71m) and the newly elected President [[Dmitry Medvedev]] is 5'5.5" (1.66m). France's President [[Nicolas Sarkozy]] is 5' 6.5" (168&amp;nbsp;cm). Of the 44 U.S. Presidents, only five have been more than an inch (2.54&amp;nbsp;cm) below average height. Quantitative studies of U.S. Senators and Governors have shown that they are on average several inches taller than the U.S. population at large.&lt;ref name="StraightDope"&gt;[http://www.straightdope.com/classics/a3_308.html The Straight Dope: “Does the taller candidate always win the election?”].&lt;/ref&gt; During the 2004 election, some anti-Bush artwork and political cartoons depicted him as much shorter than he actually stood{{Citation needed|date=October 2009}}, favoring Kerry, who was taller. 

Non-electoral politics are more difficult to study, as outcomes based on height are more difficult to quantify. Nevertheless, a number of powerful dictators have been below average height.  Examples include [[Engelbert Dollfuss]] (4′11″; 1.50m), [[Deng Xiaoping]] (5′0″; 1.52m), [[Kim Jong Il]] (5′3″; 1.60m), [[Nikita Khrushchev]] (5′3″; 1.60m), [[Francisco Franco]] (5′4″; 1.63m), [[Joseph Stalin]] (5′5″; 1.65m), and [[Benito Mussolini]] (5'6"; 1.68m). Contrary to popular impression, [[Napoleon_Bonaparte#Napoleon.27s_height|Napoleon Bonaparte]] at 5′7″ (1.70m) (taller than the average Frenchman at the time) and [[Adolf Hitler]] at 5′8″ (1.73m) were both within the average height range for their times and places.

In the United Kingdom, the influential ''[[Spitting Image]]'' satirical television series depicted [[David Steel]] as a midget. This was credited with undermining his political career.&lt;ref&gt;http://news.independent.co.uk/uk/politics/article346544.ece&lt;/ref&gt; When the [[France|French]] president [[Nicolas Sarkozy]] made a state visit to the UK in March 2008, the British press was uncommonly united in passing comment on the fact that he is a short man and in carrying a closeup photograph showing the sizeable heels on his shoes in contrast to the flat shoes of his taller wife, [[Carla Bruni]].

See also [[Napoleon Complex]] and [[Heights of United States Presidents and presidential candidates]].

==Conflict==
Heightism is cited as one of the underlying causes of the [[Rwandan Genocide]], in which approximately one million people were killed. It is believed that one of the reasons that political power was conferred to the minority [[Tutsi]]s by the exiting Belgians was because they were taller and therefore (in the eyes of the Belgians) considered superior and more suited to governance.&lt;ref name="Exile"&gt;[http://www.exile.ru/2003-November-25/war_nerd.html The Exile: “Burundi: Heightism rears its ugly head”].&lt;/ref&gt;

==Dating and marriage==
Heightism may also be a factor in dating preferences. For some people, height is a [[Physical_attractiveness#Height|major factor in sexual attractiveness]].

The greater reproductive success of taller men is attested to by studies indicating that taller men are more likely to be married and to have more children, except in societies with severe gender imbalances caused by war.&lt;ref name="DontWant"&gt;[http://jrscience.wcp.muohio.edu/Research/HumanNatureProgArticles/dontwantnoshortshortmanFI.html Miami University of Ohio: “Don’t Want No Short, Short Man: The Study Of Height, Power, and Mate Selection”].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="FA"&gt;[http://www.findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m1175/is_3_33/ai_62215068 FindArticles.com: “Tall Men Do Get The Girl — Brief Article”].&lt;/ref&gt; Quantitative studies of woman-for-men [[personal advertisement]]s have shown strong preference for tall men, with a large percentage indicating that a man significantly below average height was unacceptable.&lt;ref name="ShortSupport3"&gt;[http://www.shortsupport.org/Research/personals.html Short Persons Support: “Personals Analyzer”].&lt;/ref&gt;

Conversely, studies have shown that women of below average height are more likely to be married and have children than women of above average height. Some reasons which have been suggested for this situation include earlier fertility of shorter women, and that a shorter woman makes her husband feel taller in comparison and therefore more masculine.&lt;ref name="BBC"&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/health/2190461.stm BBC News: “Tall men ‘top husband stakes’”].&lt;/ref&gt;

It is unclear and debated as to the extent to which such preferences are innate or are the function of a society in which height discrimination impacts on socio-economic status. Certainly, much is always made in newspapers and magazines of celebrity couples with a notable height difference, especially where a man is shorter than his wife (for example, [[Jamie Cullum]], five inches (12.7&amp;nbsp;cm) shorter at 5'6" (1.68m) than [[Sophie Dahl]], though the difference is often exaggerated).

==In the media==
{{Original research|date=April 2008}}
In the [[Mass media|media]], heightism can take the form of making fun of people whose height is out of the normal range in ways that would be unseemly if directed at [[skin color]] or [[mass]]. The portrayal of short men in the media is in general negative. Short men are either ridiculously unsuccessful in regards to career and/or romance (e.g., Spence Olchin and Bud Bundy) or they are unlikeable tyrants in need of compensating for "something" (e.g. Lord Farquaad). Notable exceptions are roles played by [[Michael J. Fox]] (especially [[Mike Flaherty]] from the TV series ''[[Spin City]]'', where a short man is portrayed as an attractive and likable person, who is successful both in romance and career), and [[Kevin Connolly]]'s portrayal of Eric "E" Murphy in [[HBO]]'s television series [[Entourage (TV series)|Entourage]] (Connolly is 5' 5" (165&amp;nbsp;cm))&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.imdb.com/name/nm0175305/bio Kevin Connolly (I) - Biography&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;].&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, although the actor [[Daniel Radcliffe]] was cast in the role of [[Harry Potter]] as a young child, the fact that he has reached an adult height of 5' 5" (165&amp;nbsp;cm) means that the Harry Potter film franchise now also effectively provides a positive portrayal of a shorter male hero. When [[Daniel Craig]] was announced as [[James Bond]] in 2005, intense criticism of the casting decision (made by [[EON Productions]]) included the notion that the actor was too short to play 007, even though at 5' 10" (178&amp;nbsp;cm) Craig is above average height for a white British man.

In 1987 the [[BBC]] comedy series ''[[A Small Problem]]'' imagined a totalitarian society in which people under 5&amp;nbsp;ft. (152&amp;nbsp;cm) tall were systematically discriminated against. The programme attracted considerable criticism and complaints which accused the writers of reinforcing prejudice and of using offensive terms; the writers responded that their intention had been to show all prejudice was stupid and that height was chosen randomly.&lt;ref name="BBC Comedy guide"&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/comedy/guide/articles/s/smallproblema_1299002875.shtml A Small Problem] in BBC Comedy Guide.&lt;/ref&gt;

The "Archaeology Today" sketch in ''[[Monty Python's Flying Circus]]'' deals with heightism&lt;ref name="Stanford"&gt;[http://metamedia.stanford.edu/projects/PopularArchaeology/176 Stanford University Metamedia: “Monty Python’s Flying Circus”].&lt;/ref&gt; in which an interviewer humorously admits to assessing his subject’s credibility based on their height.

In a 2006 cartoon episode of ''[[Family Guy]]'', the second coming of [[Jesus Christ]] is depicted, with Jesus very obviously being much shorter than the (modern) crowd he speaks to. In the show, this causes uncertainty and surprise among the crowd. In the cartoon series ''[[Invader Zim]]'', the alien race of the Irken had a class system based entirely on height, the empire being ruled by those of the greatest stature, literally referred to as the [[Almighty Tallest]].

Similarly, shorter men are often denied leading roles. Although some famous cinema actors such as [[Alan Ladd]] and [[Tom Cruise]] have been short in real life, in their fictional depictions they have been presented as taller. [[Randy Newman]]'s song ''[[Short People]]'' deals with heightism in a satirical, light-hearted manner as a protest against bigotry in general. Nevertheless, some people find this song offensive.&lt;ref name="ShortSupport4"&gt;[http://www.shortsupport.org/TheMedia/music/shortpeople-sgoldsmith.html Short Persons Support: “Music”].&lt;/ref&gt;

On the BBC motoring programme ''[[Top Gear (current format)|Top Gear]]'', [[Richard Hammond]]'s height is usually mocked by the other presenters, particularly [[Jeremy Clarkson]].

==Legislation==
Currently, there is one state in the United States of America, [[Michigan]], that prohibits height discrimination.&lt;ref name="Michigah"&gt;[http://www.michigan.gov/documents/act_453_elliott_larsen_8772_7.pdf Text] of the Elliot Larsen Civil Rights Act of 1976.&lt;/ref&gt; There is pending legislation introduced by [[Massachusetts]] Representative [[Byron Rushing]] which would add Massachusetts to the list.&lt;ref name="Massachusetts"&gt;[http://www.mass.gov/legis/bills/house/ht03pdf/ht03752.pdf Text (PDF)] of Massachusetts House bill 3752, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; Two municipalities currently prohibit height discrimination: [[Santa Cruz, California]]&lt;ref name="Advocates"&gt;[http://www.genderadvocates.org/policy/Ordinances/Laws/Santa%20Cruz%20Ordinance.htm Chapter 9.83] of the City of Santa Cruz code – “Prohibition against Discrimination”, 1992.&lt;/ref&gt; and [[San Francisco, California]].&lt;ref name="NAAFA"&gt;[http://www.naafa.org/fatf/sf_height_weight.html Text] of Compliance Guidelines To Prohibit Weight and Height Discrimination; San Francisco Administrative Code Chapters 12A, 12B and 12C and San Francisco Municipal/Police Code Article 33, 26 July 2001.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[District of Columbia]] prohibits discrimination based on personal appearance.&lt;ref name="DC"&gt;[http://ohr.dc.gov/ohr/cwp/view,a,3,q,491858,ohrNav,%7C30953%7C.asp Text] District of Columbia Human Rights Act.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Ontario]], [[Canada]] prohibits height discrimination under the human rights code.&lt;ref name="Ontario"&gt;[http://www.ohrc.on.ca/english/publications/height-weight-policy.shtml Text] Ontario, Canada Human Rights Code.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Victoria, Australia]] prohibits discrimination based on physical features under the Equal Opportunity Act of 1995.&lt;ref name="Victoria"&gt;[http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/legis/vic/consol_act/eoa1995250/index.html Text] Victoria, Australia Equal Opportunity Act of 1995.&lt;/ref&gt;

Examples of successful legal battles pursued against height discrimination in the workplace include a 2002 case involving highly qualified applicants being turned down for jobs at a bank because they were considered too short;&lt;ref name="Chinese"&gt;[http://www.cnn.com/2004/LAW/05/31/dorf.height.discrimination/index.html Chinese Height Discrimination Case].&lt;/ref&gt; a 2005 Swedish case involving an unfair height requirement for employment implemented by [[Volvo]] car company;&lt;ref name="Volvo"&gt;[http://www.eiro.eurofound.eu.int/2005/11/inbrief/se0511102n.html Volvo Car Company Height requirement for employment].&lt;/ref&gt; and a 1999 case involving a [[Kohler Company]] informal practice not to consider women who applied for jobs unless they were at least 5 feet 4&amp;nbsp;inches (162&amp;nbsp;cm) tall.&lt;ref name="Kohler"&gt;[http://www.dol.gov/opa/media/press/esa/archive/esa99268.htm Kohler Corp. Gender Discrimination Case].&lt;/ref&gt; Height requirements for employment which are not a [[Bona fide occupational requirement|''bona fide'' occupational requirement]] are becoming more and more uncommon.

==See also==
*[[Human height]]
*[[Discrimination]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
* The [[National Organization of Short Statured Adults]] website: [http://www.nossaonline.org www.nossaonline.org]

[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Prejudices]]
[[Category:Human height]]
[[Category:Dispositional beliefs]]

[[pt:Altismo]]
[[zh:身高歧视]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>