<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20051017033315|25709198" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1858124" pageid="1858124" ns="0" title="Height discrimination"><revisions><rev timestamp="2005-10-22T21:37:26Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Heightism''' is a form of [[discrimination]] based on [[Human height|height]].  In principle it can refer to unfavorable treatment of either unusually tall or short people; however in practice heightism almost always takes the form of unfavorable treatment of shorter people and more favorable treatment of taller people (particularly tall [[men]]).
==Heightism in employment==
With the possible exception of some [[Manual labour|manual labor]] jobs and most [[Professional_sports|professional sports]], a person's height would not seem to have an effect on how well they are able to perform their job.  Nevertheless, studies have shown that short people are paid less than taller people, with disparities similar in magnitude to the race and gender gaps. [http://www.ssc.upenn.edu/~persico/research/Papers/short.pdf] [http://www.essex.ac.uk/ilr/eeeg/Conference1/Harper.pdf].

A survey of [[Fortune 500]] [[Chief executive officer|CEO]] height in 2005 revealed that they were on average 6 feet tall, which is 3 inches taller than the average American man.  Fully 30% of these CEOs were 6 foot 2 inches tall or more; in comparison only 3.9% of the overall United States population is of this height.[http://www.stlouisfed.org/publications/re/2005/b/pages/appearances.html]

Subjectively, many short persons report they are not taken seriously in the work place or by their [[peer group|peer]]s because of their smaller stature.[http://www.shortsupport.org/News/0106.html].

==Heightism in politics==
Short canditates are disadvantaged in electoral politics.  Of the 43 U.S. Presidents, only five have been more than an inch below average height.  Moreover, of the 54 US presidential elections [[Heights_of_U.S._presidential_candidates|only 13 have been won by the shorter candidate]], and only 11 times has the shorter candidate received more popular (as opposed to [[US_Electoral_College|electoral]]) votes.  Quantitative studies of U.S. Senators and Governors have also shown that that they are on average several inches taller than the U.S. population at large.[http://www.straightdope.com/classics/a3_308.html]

Non-electoral politics are more difficult to study as outcomes based on height are more difficult to quantify.  Nevertheless, it is surprising and interesting to note that a number of powerful dictators have been well below average height.  Examples include [[Engelbert Dollfuss]] (4'11), [[Deng Xiaoping]] (5'0),  [[Kim Jong Il]] (5'3), [[Nikita  Khrushchev]] (5'3), [[Francisco Franco]] (5'4), and [[Josef Stalin]] (5'5).  Contrary to popular impression, [[ Napoleon_Bonaparte#Misconceptions_about_Napoleon.27s_height|Napoleon Bonaparte]] at 5'6.5 was slightly above average height for the time he lived.

==Heightism in dating and marriage==
Heightism may also be a factor in [[women]]'s dating preferences, as the height of a man is a [[Sexual attraction#Factors determining sexual attraction of men|major factor in sexual attractiveness]].  The greater reproductive success of taller men is attested to by studies indicating that taller men are more likely to be married and to have more children.  [http://jrscience.wcp.muohio.edu/Research/HumanNatureProgArticles/dontwantnoshortshortmanFI.html]
[http://www.findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m1175/is_3_33/ai_62215068]  Quantitative studies of woman-for-men [[Personal_advertisement|personal advertisements]] have shown strong preference for tall men, with a large percentage indicating that a man significantly below average height was unacceptable.[http://www.shortsupport.org/Research/personals.html]

==Heightism in the media==
In the [[media]], heightism can take the form of making fun of short men in ways that would be unseemly if directed at [[skin colour]] or [[weight]] (especially female weight).  Examples of characters whose short stature is exploited for comic value are:  
*Lord Farquaad from [[Shrek]]
*Bob from [[Becker]]
*Louis De Palma from [[Taxi (TV series)|Taxi]]
*Radar from [[M*A*S*H (TV series)|M*A*S*H]]

==Resources for short adults==
The National Organization of Short Statured Adults is committed to the open discussion of heightism and height-related discrimination [http://www.nossaonline.org]. NOSSA sponsors a message-board at [http://heightism.aimoo.com] In addition, Steve Goldsmith operates the Short Support website [http://www.shortsupport.org] which has been providing the short community with valuable resources on heightism related topics.

==See also==
*[[Human height]]
*[[Discrimination]]
*[[Dwarfism]]
*[[List of famous tall women]]

[[Category:Discrimination]][[Category: Prejudices]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>