<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20040708100805|5582323" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="457549" pageid="457549" ns="0" title="Gender Recognition Act 2004"><revisions><rev timestamp="2004-09-01T06:46:48Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">The '''Gender Recognition Act 2004''' is an [[Act of Parliament]] of the [[United Kingdom|British]] [[Parliament]] which allows [[transsexual]] people to change their legal gender.

==Operation of the law==

Most of the Act has yet to come into force - the [[Secretary of State for Constitutional Affairs|Secretary of State]] will make an order doing so after the administration of the recognition process is in place.

The Act gives legal recognition to [[transsexual]]s in the [[United Kingdom]], and will allow them to acquire a new [[birth certificate]]-alike, and be able to marry, as well as afford them full recognition in all areas. The two main exceptions are a right of conscience for [[Church of England]] clergy (who are normally obliged to marry any two eligible people by law), and that the descent of [[peerage]]s will be left untouched. Additionally, sports organisations are allowed to discriminate against transsexual people if it is necessary for 'fair competition or the safety of the competitors'.

People present evidence to a 'Gender Recognition Panel', which considers their case and issues a 'Gender Recognition Certificate'. If the person involved is in a legally-recognised [[marriage]] they will be issued an 'Interim Gender Recognition Certificate', which can then be used as grounds for divorce, but otherwise has no status. After the divorce, a full Certificate will be issued.

The Act requires transsexuals to have [[transitioning (transgender)|transitioned]] two years before a certificate is issued. It will make no requirement for [[sexual reassignment]] surgery to have taken place, although this will be taken into consideration. There is a six month period where only people who transitioned six years ago may apply, from the date the the Act comes into force. Additionally, for two years, people who transitioned six years ago need to submit less evidence.

A Gender Recognition Certificate will be physically indistinguishable from a birth certificate, and will indicate the new legal gender and name. It will be able to be used as proof of identity wherever a birth certificate is used, such as for issue of a passport. The birth certificate showing the previous legal gender will continue to exist, and will carry no indication that there is an associated Gender Recognition Certificate. Certain authorised agencies, such as the Police, will have access to a register showing the links between these certificates, but the link will be invisible to the general public. This is the same way that adoption certificates work.

==Legislative progress==
The Act was drafted in response to court rulings from the [[European Court of Human Rights]] and [[House of Lords]], saying that the law as it stood was a violation of the [[European Convention on Human Rights]] and the [[Human Rights Act 1998]]. The previous precedent dated back to [[1970]], when [[Arthur Cameron Corbett, 3rd Baron Rowallan]] had his marriage annulled on the basis of his wife, [[April Ashley]], being a [[transwoman|transsexual woman]], was not recognized as such under then-current UK law. This argument was accepted by the judge, and the legal test for gender in the UK had been based on this judgement ever since; it had even led to the curiosity of a legal [[same-sex marriage|marriage between two lesbians]] since one had been born male.

The [[bill (proposed law)|Bill]] was introduced in the [[House of Lords]] in late [[2003]]. It was passed by the [[House of Lords]] on [[February 10]], [[2004]], with 155 votes in favour and 57 against. The [[House of Commons]] passed it on [[May 25]]. It received [[Royal Assent]] on [[July 1]] [[2004]].

The Bill faced criticism in the [[House of Lords]], including a [[wrecking amendment]] from [[Norman Tebbit]] (who has described [[sexual reassignment surgery]] as 'mutilation'), and from [[Detta O'Cathain]], who introduced an amendment to allow religious groups to exclude transsexual people. However, this amendment was narrowly defeated after opposition from the [[Bishop of Worcester]] and the [[Bishop of Winchester]].

In the first [[division (vote)|division]] on the Bill in the [[House of Commons]], the vote was split broadly down party lines.  All [[Labour Party (UK)|Labour Party]], [[Liberal Democrats (UK)|Liberal Democrat]], [[Plaid Cymru]] and [[Scottish National Party]] votes were for, all [[Ulster Unionist]], [[Democratic Unionist Party]] votes were against.  The [[Conservative Party (UK)|Conservative Party]] allowed a [[free vote]], and the opposition spokesman [[Tim Boswell]] welcoming the Bill &amp;mdash; however the vote was split with Conservative MPs like [[Ann Widdecombe]] and [[Andrew Selous]] strongly opposing the Bill on grounds of religious principle.

Some concerns were also raised about the Bill by supporters of transsexual rights. The requirement to divorce before recognition was particularly criticised, as forcing people to choose between their marriage and their gender.  The planned [[Civil Partnership Bill]] was supposed to take the sting out of this - but the passage of that now looks uncertain.

'''See also:''' [[List of transgender-related topics]]

==External link==
*[http://www.legislation.hmso.gov.uk/acts/acts2004/20040007.htm Gender Recognition Act 2004 - full text]

[[Category:British laws]]
[[Category:LGBT civil rights]]
[[Category:Topics relating to transitioning]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>