<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20221121011824|1122980807" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="69270395" pageid="69270395" ns="0" title="Diversity, equity, and inclusion"><revisions><rev timestamp="2022-11-28T22:23:07Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|Organizational equality training term}}
{{Multiple issues|
{{POV|date=May 2022}}
{{Context|date=October 2022}}
{{Globalize|1=article|2=United States|date=October 2022}}
{{Too few opinions|date=October 2022}}
{{More citations needed|date=October 2022}}
}}
'''Diversity, equity, and inclusion''' '''(DEI)''' is a conceptual framework that promotes the fair treatment and full participation of all people, especially in the workplace, including populations who have historically been underrepresented or subject to discrimination because of their background, identity, disability, etc.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=DEI Definitin &amp; Meaning Dictionary.com |url=https://www.dictionary.com/browse/dei |access-date=2022-11-20 |website= |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

"Diversity" describes a wide variety of differences that may exist amongst people in any community, including race, ethnicity, nationality, gender and sexual identity, disability, neurodiversity, and others. "Equity" is the practice of providing fair opportunities via personalized approaches based on individual needs, thus aiming to "level the playing field" by taking into account the different starting points of different individuals. Therefore, "equity" aims to achieve fairness by considering each individual's trajectory and context, and should not be confused with the notion of "equality" which aims to treat everyone the same. "Inclusion" specifies the desired outcome, namely, ensuring that individuals find opportunities and spaces to participate, regardless of their differences. 

The term DEI is most often used to describe a training in the workplace. DEI training is utilized to encourage functional knowledge of fellow employees' identities and ways to navigate differences in an organization.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Seven Steps to Successful DEI Training |url=https://www.asaecenter.org:443/en/resources/articles/an_plus/2021/march/seven-steps-to-successful-dei-training |access-date=2022-03-23 |website=ASAE |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; That said, the concept of DEI has a much broader scope of application. The umbrella term "diversity" encompasses not only the awareness about differences but also a set of principles and practices that aim to transform that awareness into safe and positive working environments. Equity involves factoring in individuals' starting points and trajectories. Applying equity means implementing fair opportunities in a way that accounts for the differences that exist between individuals. Inclusion is a step towards integration, where diverse individuals blend into the environment safely and harmoniously.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Diversity, Equity, and Inclusion – A Professional Development Offering of the eXtension Foundation Impact Collaborative |url=https://dei.extension.org/ |access-date=2022-03-23 |website=dei.extension.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Diversity, Equity &amp; Inclusion |url=https://codeforamerica.org/about-us/diversity-equity-inclusion/ |access-date=2022-03-23 |website=Code for America |language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some of the challenges facing DEI have historical roots, with trails into current-time society. Due to the complexity of these issues in society, DEI is not simple or cookie-cutter. Though DEI is best known as a form of corporate training, these angles can be explored in a variety of environments, including but not limited to academia, corporate workplaces, schools, and medical spaces.&lt;ref name="auto"&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Grubbs |first=Vanessa |date=2020-07-23 |title=Diversity, Equity, and Inclusion That Matter |journal=New England Journal of Medicine |volume=383 |issue=4 |pages=e25 |doi=10.1056/NEJMpv2022639 |pmid=32649073 |s2cid=220465926 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Rosenkranz |first1=Kari M. |last2=Arora |first2=Tania K. |last3=Termuhlen |first3=Paula M. |last4=Stain |first4=Steven C. |last5=Misra |first5=Subhasis |last6=Dent |first6=Daniel |last7=Nfonsam |first7=Valentine |title=Diversity, Equity and Inclusion in Medicine: Why It Matters and How do We Achieve It? |journal=Journal of Surgical Education |date=July 2021 |volume=78 |issue=4 |pages=1058–1065 |doi=10.1016/j.jsurg.2020.11.013 |pmid=33279427 |s2cid=227521028 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==In the workplace==
{{Further|Diversity (business)}}
Organizations are now cognizant of the fact that efforts toward Diversity, Equity, and Inclusion produce a tangible result. &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=Stahl |first=Ashley |title=3 Benefits Of Diversity In The Workplace |url=https://www.forbes.com/sites/ashleystahl/2021/12/17/3-benefits-of-diversity-in-the-workplace/?sh=5c280cda22ed |url-status=live |website=Forbes}}&lt;/ref&gt;The purpose of DEI training is to encourage self awareness, cultural competency, and empathy in employees; addressing unconscious bias, as well as promoting an overall safe, welcoming workplace environment for those of all races, creeds, and ethnicity.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Seven Steps to Successful DEI Training |url=https://www.asaecenter.org:443/en/resources/articles/an_plus/2021/march/seven-steps-to-successful-dei-training |access-date=2022-03-19 |website=ASAE |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; The application of DEI training is not ready-made by any means, and proper application and upkeep requires administrative awareness of corporate social responsibility. This specific implementation of DEI training is relatively new, but people have been organically navigating differences for a long time. Because businesses and corporations exist within a larger world, they cannot be completely separated from the issues that exist in society. Thus, DEI is quickly becoming an integral part of human resources in education and prevention. The implementation, monitoring, and upkeep of a DEI informed workplace improves coworker relations and teamwork.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Gill |first1=Gurwinder Kaur |last2=McNally |first2=Mary Jane |last3=Berman |first3=Vin |date=2018-08-16 |title=Effective diversity, equity, and inclusion practices |journal=Healthcare Management Forum |volume=31 |issue=5 |pages=196–199 |doi=10.1177/0840470418773785 |pmid=30114938 |s2cid=52019098 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== In academia ==
{{Further|Diversity education|Equity in education|Inclusion (education)}}
Though the term and application was more prominent in the civil rather than the corporate sector, many of the academic institutions started making commitments to DEI in different ways, including creating documents, programs and appointing dedicated staff members especially in the US.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=University |first=Carnegie Mellon |title=Homepage - Diversity, Equity and Inclusion - Carnegie Mellon University |url=http://www.cmu.edu/diversity/index.html |access-date=2022-03-21 |website=www.cmu.edu |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Diversity, Equity and Inclusion - University of Houston |url=https://uh.edu/diversity-equity-inclusion/ |access-date=2022-03-21 |website=uh.edu}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many accreditation agencies now require supporting DEI.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=Bohanon |first=Mariah |date=2022-03-16 |title=DEI in Accreditation |url=https://www.insightintodiversity.com/dei-in-accreditation/ |access-date=2022-10-01 |website=INSIGHT Into Diversity |language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Diversity and Inclusion in the Standards {{!}} AACSB |url=https://www.aacsb.edu/educators/accreditation/business-accreditation/diversity |access-date=2022-10-01 |website=www.aacsb.edu |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Information on DEI for both students and professors is now widespread in colleges and universities, with many schools requiring training and meetings on the topic. Many scholarships and opportunities at universities even have a secondary purpose of encouraging diversity. Diversity in higher education can be difficult, with diverse students often feeling reduced to fulfilling a ‘diversity quota,’ which can carry a high emotional tax.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Harris-Hasan |first1=Alandra |title=What Is Really Going On: Black Graduate Students in Higher Education |journal=Diverse Issues in Higher Education |volume=31 |issue=18 |date=9 October 2014 |pages=58 |url=https://www.diverseeducation.com/students/article/15095499/what-is-really-going-on-black-graduate-students-in-higher-ed }}&lt;/ref&gt; This said, research is being done across the world to determine the current standpoint of diversity in universities, what is and is not effective, and how DEI practices can be applied in higher education. &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last1=Claeys-Kulik |first1=Anna-Lena |id={{ERIC|ED603495}} |title=Diversity, Equity and Inclusion in European Higher Education Institutions: Results from the INVITED Project |last2=Jørgensen |first2=Thomas Ekman |last3=Stöber |first3=Henriette |date=November 2019 |publisher=European University Association |url=https://www.eua.eu/resources/publications/890:diversity,-equity-and-inclusion-in-european-higher-education-institutions-results-from-the-invited-project.html?utm_source=social&amp;utm_medium=Facebook&amp;utm_name=Facebook-social-19-11-2019 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Another angle to DEI in education considers public schools and general K-12 education. The focus here is on teachers and administrative staff.{{Cn|date=October 2022}} Extending this lens of equity to lower education is duplicating what has already been seen in higher education: the creation and upkeep of a safe and supported environment for diverse students. In [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democratic]]-leaning states, some schools have even created administrative positions focused on DEI and social responsibility.{{Cn|date=October 2022}} Such positions exist with the goal of creating allies for students through resources and staff training in order to support students facing social disparities. &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=Ph.D |first=Jay P. Greene |title=Equity Elementary: "Diversity, Equity, and Inclusion" Staff in Public Schools |url=https://www.heritage.org/education/report/equity-elementary-diversity-equity-and-inclusion-staff-public-schools |access-date=2022-03-23 |website=The Heritage Foundation |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Keshri |first1=Vikash Ranjan |last2=Bhaumik |first2=Soumyadeep |title=The feudal structure of global health and its implications for decolonisation |journal=BMJ Global Health |date=September 2022 |volume=7 |issue=9 |pages=e010603 |doi=10.1136/bmjgh-2022-010603 |pmid=36167407|pmc=9516156 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== In medicine ==
Acknowledging the importance of diversity awareness in medicine and treatment has been a massive step in the medical world. The realm of both academic and applied medicine has been historically white, male, cisgender, and straight, and many diverse individuals have spoken about alienating experiences in this field. &lt;ref name="auto"/&gt; Upon more recent research, it has been found that not only are diverse individuals made to feel unsafe and unwelcome, they may also be experiencing inadequate treatment based on their differences. DEI is vital in medicine as physical differences in diverse individuals in the past have led to improper care and less than ideal interactions with medical staff. It has also been shown that greater diversity can strengthen both research teams and patient relations.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; DEI efforts in existing global health organisations has been criticised for not  being able to dismantle the feudal structure of global health.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Keshri |first1=Vikash Ranjan |last2=Bhaumik |first2=Soumyadeep |title=The feudal structure of global health and its implications for decolonisation |journal=BMJ Global Health |date=September 2022 |volume=7 |issue=9 |pages=e010603 |doi=10.1136/bmjgh-2022-010603 |pmid=36167407 |pmc=9516156 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Revenues==
According to a 2003 estimate{{Cn|date=November 2022}}, corporations in the [[United States]] spend $8 billion annually on diversity. [[New York (magazine)|''New York'' magazine]] stated in 2021 that "the business became astronomically larger than ever" after the [[murder of George Floyd]] in May 2020.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last1=Read |first1=Bridget |title=Inside the Booming Diversity-Equity-and-Inclusion Industrial Complex |url=https://www.thecut.com/article/diversity-equity-inclusion-industrial-companies.html |access-date=21 September 2022 |work=The Cut |date=26 May 2021 |language=en-us}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Affirmative action]]
* [[Environmental, social, and corporate governance]]
* [[Diversity (business)]]
* [[Diversity training]]
* [[Human resources]]
* [[Inclusion (disability rights)]]
* [[Inclusion (education)]]
* [[Title IX]]

==References==
{{reflist}}
[[Category:Multiculturalism]]
[[Category:Affirmative action]]
[[Category:Corporate social responsibility]]
[[Category:Social justice]]
[[Category:Human resource management]]
[[Category:Identity politics]]
[[Category:Intersectionality]]
[[Category:Workplace]]
[[Category:Liberalism]]
[[Category:Left-wing politics]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>