<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20211020174220|1050924792" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="34858143" pageid="34858143" ns="0" title="Transmisogyny"><revisions><rev timestamp="2021-10-20T18:02:24Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|Hatred or dislike of trans women or girls}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2016}}
{{Transgender sidebar}}{{Discrimination sidebar|state=collapsed}}
'''Transmisogyny''' (sometimes '''trans-misogyny''') is the [[intersectionality|intersection]] of [[transphobia]] and [[misogyny]] as experienced by [[trans women]] and [[transfeminine]] people.&lt;ref name="Nadal2017"&gt;{{cite book|author=Kevin L. Nadal|title=The SAGE Encyclopedia of Psychology and Gender|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Mj0mDwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT4197|date=2017|publisher=SAGE Publications|isbn=978-1-5063-5324-1|pages=1728–1731}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Arayasirikul"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Arayasirikul |first1=Sean |last2=Wilson |first2=Erin C. |title=Spilling the T on Trans-Misogyny and Microaggressions: An Intersectional Oppression and Social Process Among Trans Women |journal=Journal of Homosexuality |date=24 August 2019 |volume=66 |issue=10 |pages=1415–1438 |doi=10.1080/00918369.2018.1542203 |pmid=30475682 |s2cid=53729580 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The term was coined by [[Julia Serano]] in her 2007 book ''[[Whipping Girl]]'' to describe a particular form of oppression experienced by trans women.&lt;ref name="Krell2017"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Krell|first1=Elías Cosenza|title=Is Transmisogyny Killing Trans Women of Color?|journal=TSQ: Transgender Studies Quarterly|volume=4|issue=2|year=2017|pages=226–242|doi=10.1215/23289252-3815033}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="transmisogyny-primer"&gt;{{cite web|title=Transmisogyny primer|url=http://www.juliaserano.com/av/TransmisogynyPrimer-Serano.pdf|access-date=10 September 2014|last=Serano|first=Julia}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |title=Sexual deceit: the ethics of passing |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=m4OGpJXp_oQC&amp;pg=PA12 |page=12 |year=2013 |first=Kelby |last=Harrison |publisher=Lexington Books|isbn=978-0-7391-7706-8}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Transmisogyny is a central concept in [[transfeminism]] and is commonly referenced in [[intersectionality|intersectional feminist theory]].

==Framework==
The concept of transmisogyny hinges on two other concepts first described by Serano: traditional sexism and [[oppositional sexism]]. The former is the idea that "maleness and masculinity are superior to femaleness and femininity", while the latter holds male and female as "rigid, mutually exclusive categories". Transmisogyny stems from both these concepts.&lt;ref name="Arayasirikul"/&gt; 

In ''Whipping Girl'', Julia Serano writes that the existence of trans women is seen as a threat to a "male-centered [[gender hierarchy]]".&lt;ref name="whipping-girl" /&gt; [[Gender theorist]] [[Judith Butler]] echoes this assumption, stating that the murder of transgender women by men is "the most [[Toxic masculinity|toxic form]] that masculinity can take", a way for the killer to assert power over the victim in the instant, in response to the idea of the [[Intrinsic property (philosophy)|intrinsic]] nature of his power (ie, his masculinity) being threatened. Butler states that trans women have relinquished masculinity, showing that it is possible to do so.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title = Why Do Men Kill Trans Women? Gender Theorist Judith Butler Explains |url = https://broadly.vice.com/en_us/article/why-do-men-kill-trans-women-gender-theorist-judith-butler-explains|website = Broadly|access-date = 2015-12-24|language = en-US|date = 2015-12-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Instances==
{{Merge to|Trans woman#Discrimination|section=Yes|date=October 2021|discuss=Talk:Transmisogyny#Merging the "Instances" section}}
===United States===
Transgender women face harsher levels of discrimination than other transgender people. A study on workplace experiences after people receive sex changes found that trans women, on average, lose almost one third of their salary, are respected less, and receive more harassment. At the same time, trans men often experience salary raises and greater authority in the workplace.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Schilt |first1=Kristen |last2=Wiswall |first2=Matthew |title=Before and After: Gender Transitions, Human Capital, and Workplace Experiences |journal=The B.E. Journal of Economic Analysis &amp; Policy |date=11 September 2008 |volume=8 |issue=1 |doi=10.2202/1935-1682.1862 |s2cid=51580726 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Laura Kacere (2014), trans people experience a disproportionately large number of hate crimes, with trans women experiencing the majority of these crimes.&lt;ref name="Everyday Feminism" /&gt; The [[National Coalition of Anti-Violence Programs]] (2012) found that police violence is three times higher against transgender people than it is against cisgender people.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=National Coalition of Anti-Violence Programs|date=2013|title=A Report from the National Coalition of Anti-Violence Programs (NCAVP): Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, Transgender, Queer, and HIV-Affected Hate Violence in 2012|url=http://avp.org/wp-content/uploads/2017/04/ncavp_2012_hvreport_final.pdf|access-date=September 17, 2020|website=National Coalition of Anti-Violence Programs}}&lt;/ref&gt; In fact, over half of all anti-LGBTQIA+ homicides were perpetrated against transgender women.&lt;ref name="Everyday Feminism"&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://everydayfeminism.com/2014/01/transmisogyny/|title=Transmisogyny 101: What It Is and What Can We Do About It|last=Kacere|first=Laura|date=2014-01-27|work=Everyday Feminism|access-date=2017-04-21|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the United States, the majority of transmisogyny is directed at trans women of color. The [[Human Rights Campaign]] Foundation (2018) reports significant overlaps between the gender identity and race of anti-trans violence victims: of the known homicides of transgender people from 2013 to 2018, approximately 92% were trans women, and approximately 70% were black.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=A National Epidemic: Fatal Anti-Transgender Violence in America |url=https://www.hrc.org/resources/a-national-epidemic-fatal-anti-transgender-violence-in-america-in-2018 |website=HRC }}&lt;/ref&gt; Kacere (2014) also states that 21% of transgender women and 47% of black transgender women have experienced incarceration, rates that are much higher than those for the overall U.S. population.&lt;ref name="Everyday Feminism"/&gt;

===Ecuador===
A study on discrimination of lesbian, bisexual, transsexual, transgender and intersex women in Ecuador found that transgender women "lack protection against discrimination in both law and practice." As a result, trans women have faced violence, sexual abuse, and discrimination in educational, health and workforce institutions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite document |last1=Almeida |first1=Aline Britto de |last2=Vásquez |first2=Elizabeth |last3=Rodríguez |first3=Mónica |last4=Klein |first4=Guayaquil Dayane |last5=Cordero |first5=Tatiana Mendieta |last6=Varea |first6=Soledad |title=Ecuador: Discrimination of Lesbian, Bisexual, Transsexual, Transgender and Intersex Women |date=2008 |s2cid=154832726 |citeseerx=10.1.1.563.8340 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Sexualisation and harassment ==

Julia Serano has stated that many trans women experience an additional layer of misogyny in the form of fetishization.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine|title=A manifesto for all: Bisexual trans activist and author Julia Serano wants to make feminism inclusive|last=Bianco|first=Marcie|magazine=[[Curve (magazine)|Curve]]|volume=26|issue= 5|date=September-October 2016|pages=28–29|url=http://www.juliaserano.com/av/CurveInterview16.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; She notes that, despite [[Transitioning (transgender)|transitioning]], trans women are still commonly perceived as male; however, they are rarely sexualized as such. In the [[Sex industry|porn industry]], whose target audience is primarily heterosexual men, trans women are largely presented as [[Sexual objectification|sexual objects]] rather than "predatory".&lt;ref name="whipping-girl" /&gt; 

According to Serano, the sexualisation of trans women is not solely because transgender women, by nature of their relative rarity, are viewed as "exotic": she notes that trans women are sexualized particularly much even compared to other types of "rare" women.&lt;ref name="whipping-girl" /&gt; In ''Whipping Girl'', Serano writes on what she calls a "predator–prey dichotomy" where "men are invariably viewed as predators and women as prey." Because of this view, trans women are perceived to be luring men by transitioning and "turning [themselves] into sexual objects that no red-blooded man can resist."&lt;ref name="whipping-girl" /&gt;

==Relation to transphobia==
Transmisogyny is a distinct category of transphobia in that transmisogyny mainly focuses on trans women and other transgender individuals who demonstrate femininity, whereas transphobia is a more general term, covering a broader spectrum of prejudice and discrimination towards transsexual and transgender individuals. Julia Serano states in ''Whipping Girl'' that "[w]hen the majority of jokes made at the expense of trans people center on 'men wearing dresses' or 'men who want their penises cut off' that is not transphobia – it is transmisogyny. When the majority of violence and sexual assaults committed against trans people is directed at trans women, that is not transphobia – it is transmisogyny."&lt;ref name="whipping-girl"&gt;{{cite book |last1=Serano |first1=Julia |title=Whipping Girl: A Transsexual Woman on Sexism and the Scapegoating of Femininity |date=2016 |publisher=Basic Books |isbn=978-1-58005-623-6 }}{{pn|date=October 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Transgender}}
*[[Feminism]]
*[[Kyriarchy]]
*[[Oppression]]
*[[TERF]]
*[[Anti-gender movement]]
*[[Discrimination against transgender men]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
{{Wiktionary|transmisogyny}}

{{LGBT|social=expanded}}
{{Transgender}}
{{Discrimination}}

[[Category:2000s neologisms]]
[[Category:Misogyny|*]]
[[Category:Transphobia]]
[[Category:Transgender studies]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>