<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20150915140719|681154178" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="34858143" pageid="34858143" ns="0" title="Transmisogyny"><revisions><rev timestamp="2015-09-16T04:29:21Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Transgender sidebar}}
'''Transmisogyny''' (sometimes '''trans-misogyny''') is the intersection of [[transphobia]] and [[misogyny]]. It was coined by [[Julia Serano]] in her 2007 book ''[[Whipping Girl]]'' and used to describe the unique discrimination faced by [[Trans woman|trans women]] because of "the assumption that [[female]]ness and [[femininity]] are inferior to, and exist primarily for the benefit of, [[male]]ness and [[masculinity]]",&lt;ref name="transmisogyny-primer"&gt;{{cite web|title=Transmisogyny primer|url=http://www.juliaserano.com/av/TransmisogynyPrimer-Serano.pdf|accessdate=10 September 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |title=Sexual deceit: the ethics of passing |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=m4OGpJXp_oQC&amp;pg=PA12 |page=12 |year=2013 |first=Kelby |last=Harrison |publisher=Lexington Books}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="homofiles"&gt;{{cite book|last1=Battis|first1=edited by Jes|title=Homofiles : theory, sexuality, and graduate studies|date=2011|publisher=Lexington Books|location=Lanham, Md.|isbn=9780739131916}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the way that transphobia intensifies the misogyny faced by trans women (and vice versa).&lt;ref name="transmisogyny-primer" /&gt; Transmisogyny is a central concept in [[transfeminism]] and is commonly seen in [[intersectionality|intersectional feminist theory]]. The suggestion that trans women's femaleness (rather than their femininity) is a source of transmisogyny is rejected by some feminists, who believe that trans women are not female.&lt;ref&gt;Jefferys, Shiela (2014) ''Gender Hurts'', Routledge, ISBN 978-0-415-53939-5, page 8.&lt;/ref&gt;

The term "transmisogynoir" was created to refer to the intersection between transmisogyny and [[misogynoir]], meaning the oppression of black trans women. In it, it composes transphobia, misogyny, and antiblackness. It was coined by Trudy of Gradient Lair, a womanist blog about Black women and art, media, social media, socio-politics and culture.

==Causes==
Transmisogyny is generally understood to be caused by the social belief that men are superior to women. The existence of trans women is irreconcilable with this belief, as trans women are seen as men "becoming women", or in other words, "men choosing a social downgrade".{{cite quote}} Trans women are also viewed as threatening the [[heterosexuality]] of [[cisgender]] men, the idea being that cis men might be "tricked into being attracted to trans women [viewed as men]",{{cite quote}} and as such are a target for violence as a way for men to reassert their masculinity.

==Discrimination==
[[File:Julia Serano at Modern Times (656769363).jpg|200 px|alt=|thumb|[[Julia Serano]] coined the term "transmisogyny."]]
Trans women face an overall higher rate of oppression than trans men.&lt;ref name="ntds"&gt;{{cite web|title=Injustice at Every Turn: A Report of the National Transgender Discrimination Survey|url=http://www.thetaskforce.org/static_html/downloads/reports/reports/ntds_full.pdf|website=National Gay and Lesbian Task Force|accessdate=27 April 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; This is most marked in the typical areas of sexist discrimination, like [[sexual assault]] or [[harassment|street harassment]]. A 2011 survey of 6,456 transgender and gender non-conforming people in the United States found that up to 20% of the trans women surveyed had been subjected to sexual assault. Specifically, 12% of the trans girls and 20% of the trans women prison inmates, who were surveyed, reported sexual assault.&lt;ref name="ntds" /&gt; This compares, for example, to a 2009 survey of 5,446 US college women, most of whom were not trans, which found that 19% of these women had experienced sexual assault during their time at college.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cdc.gov/ViolencePrevention/pdf/SV-DataSheet-a.pdf Sexual Violence - Facts at a Glance] published by [[Centers for Disease Control and Prevention]] (pdf). Retrieved 2015-07-07.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Krebs, C.P. et al. (2009) ''College women's experiences with physically forced, alcohol- or other drug-enabled, and drug-facilitated sexual assault before and since entering college'' [http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19433402], Journal of American College Health, volume 57 number 60, pages 639-47. doi: 10.3200/JACH.57.6.639-649&lt;/ref&gt; "Tranny" and "shemale", the two most common transphobic slurs, are reserved for trans women. A 2008 study of 64 trans women and trans men in the U.S. found that the trans women got a pay cut after transition, but the trans men got a pay raise. The researchers concluded that "male-to-female workers tend to be penalized and female-to-male workers modestly rewarded because of anti-woman, rather than just anti-transgender, discrimination."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=''Before That Sex Change, Think About Your Next Paycheck'' by Catherine Rampell, September 25, 2008|url=http://economix.blogs.nytimes.com/2008/09/25/before-that-sex-change-think-about-your-next-paycheck/|website=New York Times|accessdate=31 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Transgender women are often depicted in media as [[drag queen]]s, [[sex worker]]s, dead bodies, or tragic objects of pity or scorn.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Ryan|first1=Joelle Ruby|title=Reel Gender: Examining the Politics of Trans Images in Film and Media|journal=Ohio Link|url=https://etd.ohiolink.edu/ap/10?0::NO:10:P10_ACCESSION_NUM:bgsu1245709749|accessdate=11 September 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some put forward the idea that this conflation of trans women with sex workers is a reflection of transmisogyny.&lt;ref name="homofiles" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Queer Necropolitics|date=2014|publisher=Taylor and Francis|location=Hoboken|isbn=9781136005282|url=http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=pEXIAgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA135&amp;dq=transmisogyny&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=3uQQVP-eJNLraLfFgKgD&amp;redir_esc=y#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Psychology==
{{Further|Blanchard's transsexualism typology}}
Julia Serano in ''Whipping Girl'' pointed out that [[transvestic fetishism]], a disorder listed in the [[DSM-IV]], only mentions cross dressing by men.&lt;ref name="whipping-girl" /&gt; Similarly, ''autogynephillia'' was a recognised disorder in the DSM-IV, but ''autoandrophillia'' was not.

==Relation to transphobia==
Julia Serano states in ''Whipping Girl'' that "When the majority of jokes made at the expense of trans people center on 'men wearing dresses' or 'men who want their penises cut off' that is not transphobia – it is transmisogyny. When the majority of violence and sexual assaults committed against trans people is directed at trans women, that is not transphobia – it is transmisogyny."&lt;ref name="whipping-girl"&gt;{{cite book|last1=Serano|first1=Julia|title=Whipping girl|date=2007|publisher=Seal Press|location=Berkeley|isbn=1580051545|edition=[Online-Ausg.].}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Feminism]]
*[[Intersectionality]]
*[[Kyriarchy]]
*[[Misogyny]]
*[[Oppression]]
*[[Transfeminism]]
*[[Transphobia]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

[[Category:Feminism and transgender topics]]
[[Category:Misogyny]]
[[Category:Sexism]]
[[Category:Transfeminism]]
[[Category:Transphobia]]
[[Category:Trans women]]
[[Category:Words coined in the 2000s]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>