<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20141025211021|631103121" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="34858143" pageid="34858143" ns="0" title="Transmisogyny"><revisions><rev timestamp="2014-10-27T20:56:21Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Transgender sidebar}}
'''Transmisogyny''' (sometimes '''trans-misogyny''') is the intersection of [[transphobia]] and [[misogyny]]. It was coined by [[Julia Serano]] in her 2007 book ''[[Whipping Girl]]'' and used to describe the unique discrimination faced by [[trans women]] because of "the assumption that femaleness and femininity are inferior to, and exist primarily for the benefit of, maleness and masculinity",&lt;ref name="transmisogyny-primer"&gt;{{cite web|title=Transmisogyny primer|url=http://www.juliaserano.com/av/TransmisogynyPrimer-Serano.pdf|accessdate=10 September 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |title=Sexual deceit: the ethics of passing |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=m4OGpJXp_oQC&amp;pg=PA12 |page=12 |year=2013 |first=Kelby |last=Harrison |publisher=Lexington Books}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="homofiles"&gt;{{cite book|last1=Battis|first1=edited by Jes|title=Homofiles : theory, sexuality, and graduate studies|date=2011|publisher=Lexington Books|location=Lanham, Md.|isbn=9780739131916}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the way that transphobia intensifies the misogyny faced by trans women (and vice versa).&lt;ref name="transmisogyny-primer" /&gt; Transmisogyny is a central concept in [[transfeminism]] and is commonly seen in intersectional feminist theory.

==Causes==
Transmisogyny is generally understood to be caused by the social belief that men are superior to women. The existence of trans women is irreconcilable with this belief, as trans women are seen as men "becoming women", or in other words, "men choosing a social downgrade".{{cite quote}} Trans women also threaten the [[heterosexuality]] of [[cisgender]] men, with the possibility that cis men might be "tricked into being attracted to trans women [viewed as men]",{{cite quote}} and as such are a target for violence as a way for men to reassert their masculinity.

==Discrimination==
Trans women face an overall higher rate of oppression than trans men.&lt;ref name="ntds"&gt;{{cite web|title=Injustice at Every Turn: A Report of the National Transgender Discrimination Survey|url=http://www.thetaskforce.org/reports_and_research/ntds|website=National Gay and Lesbian Task Force|accessdate=10 September 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; This is most marked in the typical areas of sexist discrimination, like sexual assault or street harassment. Over half of all trans women have experienced some kind of sexual violence.&lt;ref name="ntds" /&gt; "Tranny" and "shemale", the two most common transphobic slurs, are reserved for trans women. Trans women get a pay cut after transition, but trans men get a pay rise.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Study of trans people's earnings confirms workplace discrimination against women.|url=http://www.thefword.org.uk/blog/2008/09/study_of_trans|website=Feministing|accessdate=11 September 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Transgender women are often depicted in media as drag queens, sex workers, dead bodies, or tragic objects of pity or scorn.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Ryan|first1=Joelle Ruby|title=Reel Gender: Examining the Politics of Trans Images in Film and Media|journal=Ohio Link|url=https://etd.ohiolink.edu/ap/10?0::NO:10:P10_ACCESSION_NUM:bgsu1245709749|accessdate=11 September 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some put forward the idea that this conflation of trans women with sex workers is a reflection of transmisogyny.&lt;ref name="homofiles" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Queer Necropolitics|date=2014|publisher=Taylor and Francis|location=Hoboken|isbn=9781136005282|url=http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=pEXIAgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA135&amp;dq=transmisogyny&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=3uQQVP-eJNLraLfFgKgD&amp;redir_esc=y#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Psychology==
{{Further|Blanchard's transsexualism typology}}
Julia Serano in ''Whipping Girl'' pointed out that [[transvestic fetishism]], a disorder listed in the [[DSM-IV]], only mentions cross dressing by men.&lt;ref name="whipping-girl" /&gt; Similarly, ''autogynephillia'' was a recognised disorder in the DSM-IV, but ''autoandrophillia'' was not.

==Relation to transphobia==
Julia Serano states in ''Whipping Girl'' that "When the majority of jokes made at the expense of trans people center on 'men wearing dresses' or 'men who want their penises cut off' that is not transphobia – it is transmisogyny. When the majority of violence and sexual assaults committed against trans people is directed at trans women, that is not transphobia – it is transmisogyny."&lt;ref name="whipping-girl"&gt;{{cite book|last1=Serano|first1=Julia|title=Whipping girl|date=2007|publisher=Seal Press|location=Berkeley|isbn=1580051545|edition=[Online-Ausg.].}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

[[Category:Misogyny]]
[[Category:Sexism]]
[[Category:Transfeminism]]
[[Category:Trans women]]
[[Category:Feminism and transgender topics]]
[[Category:Transphobia]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>