<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20231130214704|1187695093" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="73653952" pageid="73653952" ns="0" title="Anti-Afghan sentiment"><revisions><rev timestamp="2023-11-30T22:08:15Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Anti-Afghan sentiment''' is the dislike, hatred, fear, prejudice, resentment or any other form of negative sentiment towards [[Afghans|Afghan people]] and/or negative sentiments towards the country of [[Afghanistan]] or anything associated with it.

The sentiment dates back at least two centuries and has seen a rise in the past few decades across the world with the increase of Afghan migrants, refugees and issues relating to unlawful acts, including terrorism and other forms of international crime that have connections to Afghanistan or Afghan people.

==History==
{{empty section|date=April 2023}}

==By region==
===Australia===
{{See also|Racism in Australia}}
{{expand section|date=April 2023}}
Prejudice towards [[Afghan Australians|Afghan people in Australia]] was first known to be recorded in the 1800s when Afghan migrants first arrived as camel riders in Australia.&lt;ref&gt;Kabir, Nahid Afrose. "The culture of mobile lifestyle: Reflection on the past–the Afghan camel drivers, 1860–1930." Continuum 23.6 (2009): 791-802.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Stubbs, Ben. "Islam in the outback: The legacy of the Afghan cameleers." Griffith REVIEW 61 (2018): 257-265.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Kabir, Nahid. "Muslims in Western Australia 1870-1970." Early Days: Journal of the Royal Western Australian Historical Society 12.5 (2005): 550-565.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Kabir, Nahid A. "The Economic Plight of the Afghans in Australia, 1860—2000." Islamic studies 44.2 (2005): 229-250.&lt;/ref&gt; An anti-Afghan league was even formed in 1886.&lt;ref&gt;Ganter, Regina. "Muslim Australians: The deep histories of contact." Journal of Australian Studies 32.4 (2008): 481-492.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Molloy, Jan. "Teaching and learning history in the twenty-first century: Museums and the national curriculum." Agora 45.2 (2010): 62-67.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Asia and Middle East==

===Iran===
[[Afghans in Iran|Afghan refugees and migrants]] have lived for decades in Iran. However, the crimes associated with Afghans have led to an increase in anti-Afghan sentiment amongst local Iranian citizens and authorities alike.&lt;ref&gt;Yarbakhsh, Elisabeth. "Iranian hospitality and Afghan refugees in the city of Shiraz." Anthropology of the Middle East 10.2 (2015): 101-118.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Naqvi, Syed Fraz Hussain, and Ammara Zaheer. "Iran’s Policy towards Taliban 2.0: A Circumspect Approach for Maximum Gain." Focus (2023).&lt;/ref&gt;

===Pakistan===
{{Further|Afghanistan–Pakistan relations|Durand Line|Afghanistan–Pakistan border skirmishes|Afghans in Pakistan}}
Anti-Afghan sentiment has been reported amongst locals in Pakistan, including public demonstrations with anti-Afghan slogans, resulting from the crime associated with Afghan residents in Pakistan.&lt;ref&gt;Rogers, Tom. "Afghan refugees and the stability of Pakistan." Survival 29.5 (1987): 416-429.&lt;/ref&gt; The past few decades have seen a rise in anti-Afghan sentiment amongst locals.&lt;ref&gt;Downman, Scott, et al. "Human Rights Reporting, War Crimes and Refugee Migration." Journalism for Social Change in Asia: Reporting Human Rights (2017): 119-141.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Jehangir, Ayesha. "Finding Peace Journalism: An analysis of media discourse on Afghan refugees and their forced repatriation from Pakistan." (2021).&lt;/ref&gt;

===Tajikistan===
The presence of [[Afghans in Tajikistan|Afghan refugees in Tajikistan]] incited prejudice amongst local Tajiks, also making it hard for Afghan traders to do business there.&lt;ref&gt;Werbner, Pnina. "Trading Worlds: Afghan Merchants Across Modern Frontiers By Magnus Marsden." (2018): 123-124.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Turkey===
Turkey is currently claimed to be hosting the largest refugee population in the world. With the increase of Afghan refugees and crimes associated with them, public sentiment in Turkey began to turn against Afghans.&lt;ref name="auto"&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.thenationalnews.com/mena/2021/07/29/xenophobia-rising-as-thousands-of-afghan-refugees-reach-turkey/|title=Afghans fleeing the Taliban face renewed anti-migrant sentiment in Turkey|first=Andrew|last=Wilks|date=July 29, 2021|website=The National}}&lt;/ref&gt; The result was a further stepping effort by Turkey's government to further secure its border with Iran to stop a further influx of Afghans.&lt;ref name="auto"/&gt;

However, with the increase in crime and social disruption, anti-Afghan sentiment continued to rise in Turkey.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.theguardian.com/global-development/2021/aug/05/fleeing-the-taliban-afghans-met-with-rising-anti-refugee-hostility-in-turkey|title=Fleeing the Taliban: Afghans met with rising anti-refugee hostility in Turkey|first=Liz|last=Cookman|date=August 5, 2021|newspaper=The Guardian}}&lt;/ref&gt; Social media in Turkey has seen an increase in hate speech against Afghans, even before more refugees arrived.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://turkishminute.com/2021/07/23/hatespeechagainst-refugees-increases-on-turkish-social-media-as-a-new-wave-of-afghan-migrants-arrive/|title=Hate speech against refugees increases on Turkish social media as a new wave of Afghan migrants arrive|first=Turkish|last=Minute|date=July 23, 2021}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==European countries==
{{See also|European refugee crisis}}
{{Expand section|date=April 2023}}
The rise of crime involving Afghan refugees and immigrants has stocked anti-Afghan public sentiment amongst locals across Europe. The worsening situation involving Afghan migrants and refugees in Europe resulted in politicians openly stating that Afghans will no longer be welcomed in their individual countries.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2021/08/18/world/europe/afghanistan-refugees-europe-migration-asylum.html|title=Why Europe's Leaders Say They Won't Welcome More Afghan Refugees|first1=Katrin|last1=Bennhold|first2=Steven|last2=Erlanger|date=August 18, 2021|via=NYTimes.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another Afghan refugee was quoted stating the sentiment against Afghans was so bad that they were better off going back to Afghanistan rather than "facing humiliation" in Europe.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.opendemocracy.net/en/afghanistan-europe-refugees-one-year-anniversary-taliban/|title='The greener side of the same hell': Afghans on a year in EU|website=openDemocracy}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Austria===
{{See also|Crime in Austria}}
The Austrian press reported the influx of Afghan refugees. At the time of arrival of Afghan refugees and migrants, the local authorities and citizens welcomed them. But soon after overstaying their welcome by increasing the crime problems in the country, public sentiment towards Afghans began to deteriorate badly and stir up anti-Afghan sentiment.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://nationalinterest.org/feature/ive-worked-refugees-decades-europes-afghan-crime-wave-mind-21506|title=I've Worked with Refugees for Decades. Europe's Afghan Crime Wave Is Mind-Boggling.|first=Cheryl|last=Benard|date=July 11, 2017|website=The National Interest}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some Afghan refugees accused of sex crimes against minors had previous deportation orders issued against them because of these unlawful acts.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |date=2021-07-01 |title=Rape, killing of 13-year-old shocks Austria, 3 Afghans held |url=https://apnews.com/article/europe-austria-migration-government-and-politics-8194249c84d0c7413ee94b23c09bb111 |access-date=2023-06-21 |website=AP NEWS |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Finland===
{{See also|Afghans in Finland|Sexual violence in Finland|Oulu child sexual exploitation scandal}}
A number of sexual crimes committed by Afghan migrants/refugees has been reported. One of these cases involved the rape of a local fourteen year old girl in the town of [[Kempele]] by an Afghan national. The reported incident sparked public outcry against refugees and even sparked riots, with human shields of local Finnish citizens blocking the borders to prevent refugees from entering. Some Finnish [[member of parliament|parliament members]] even called on refugees not to come to the country.&lt;ref&gt;https://www.helsinkitimes.fi/finland/finland-news/domestic/13631-reports-of-suspected-rape-stir-up-fear-and-resentment-in-kempele.html?ref=hs-art-artikkelinavi&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;https://yle.fi/a/3-8478859&lt;/ref&gt;

A 2018 research report argued that ever since the incidents in Kempele, a surge in affiliating rape crimes with refugees has become a new trend based on stereotypical prejudices.&lt;ref&gt;Saresma, Tuija. "Politics of fear and racialized rape: Intersectional reading of the Kempele rape case." Racialization, racism, and anti-racism in the Nordic countries. Cham: Springer International Publishing, 2018. 63-91.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Germany===
{{See also|Crime in Germany}}
A 23 year old Afghan migrant in Germany was arrested for raping an eleven year old girl. About twelve days after being released from prison, he raped a thirteen year old. He was re-arrested shortly. His previous release and actions, triggered public outcry. German politicians called for any migrant or refugee convicted of such offenses to be deported back to their country. The acting vice chancellor urged German people not to scapegoat migrants and warned right-wing groups not to exploit the incidents for propaganda purposes.&lt;ref&gt;https://www.bbc.com/news/world-europe-38211944&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;https://nationalpost.com/news/world/afghan-migrants-arrest-in-murder-rape-case-must-not-lead-to-rabble-rousing-german-politician-says&lt;/ref&gt;

===Greece===
The rise of crime affiliated with Afghan refugees in Greece has amplified anti-Afghan sentiments in the country. Several incidents involving hate attacks on Afghan residents in Greece have been reported.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|url=https://www.hrw.org/report/2012/07/10/hate-streets/xenophobic-violence-greece|title=Hate on the Streets|first=Judith|last=Sunderland|date=July 10, 2012|journal=Human Rights Watch}}&lt;/ref&gt; In one example an Afghan refugee family were beaten in Greece and set adrift into the sea.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://euobserver.com/migration/151044|title=Afghan asylum family beaten in Greece, set adrift at sea|date=February 25, 2021|website=EUobserver}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Italy===
Italy has grown more and more resistant towards Afghan refugees; especially following public sentiment against the [[Roma people]] which was amplified by the [[European refugee crisis]]. The recent increase of Afghan refugees has strengthened right-wing sentiments in the country against accepting them. There is been a common sentiment in the country with affiliating refugees with crime.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last=Fernández |first=Belén |title=Afghans are the next victims of Italy's war on refugees |url=https://www.aljazeera.com/opinions/2021/10/12/afghans-are-the-next-victims-of-italys-war-on-refugees |access-date=2023-06-21 |website=www.aljazeera.com |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===United Kingdom===
{{expand-section|date=July 2023}}
The United Kingdom (UK) has witnessed increasing incidents relating to Afghan refugees causing backlash from locals. In one of these incidents a local teenage girl was forcefully held and raped by Afghan nationals. The incident went viral amongst local British residents on social media and resulted in violent public protests in which a police vehicle was damaged.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Four teenage asylum seekers arrested in connection with alleged rape of schoolgirl in Kent |website=[[The Daily Telegraph]] |date=13 February 2023 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20230517085223/https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/2023/02/13/teenage-asylum-seekers-arrested-alleged-rape-schoolgirl-kent/ |archive-date=2023-05-17 |url-status=live |url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/2023/02/13/teenage-asylum-seekers-arrested-alleged-rape-schoolgirl-kent/ |last1=Bolton |first1=Will }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==North America==
===United States of America===
Following the 9/11 incidents in 2001, a wave of violent anti-Muslim attacks and other sentiments were directed at Muslim residents. Amongst the slogans were hate speech directed towards Afghans.&lt;ref&gt;Perry, Barbara. "Anti-Muslim retaliatory violence following the 9/11 terrorist attacks." Hate and Bias Crime. Routledge, 2012. 201-220.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Muñoz, Arturo G. "Bent by history in Afghanistan." The Global Obama. Routledge, 2013. 235-252.&lt;/ref&gt;

Separately, anti-Afghan opinions also arose in the US for the country's involvement in the global drug trade.&lt;ref&gt;Collins, John, and Ian Tennant. "Evaluating Afghanistan’s Past, Present, and Future Engagement with Multilateral Drug Control." (2022).&lt;/ref&gt;

More recently, following the [[2020–2021 US troop withdrawal from Afghanistan]], American politician [[Scott Perry (politician)|Scott Perry]], argued against allowing in Afghan refugees without proper investigation; claiming it could lead to a crime hike, including rape crimes against underage girls. He was amongst 16 other American politicians voting against allowing Afghan refugees in without having proper background checks done. His comments drew some criticism. Former president [[Donald Trump]] made similar concerns, claiming terrorists could be airlifted out of Afghanistan.&lt;ref&gt;https://www.insider.com/gop-rep-worried-afghan-refugees-little-girls-raped-killed-2021-9&lt;/ref&gt;

==Cultural criticism==
[[Bacha Bazi]], a cultural tradition sometimes found in Afghanistan, has been gaining critical attention over the decades by foreigners.&lt;ref&gt;Verma, Sreyasi. "Why the issue of Bacha Bazi deserves international attention." (2019).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Schut, Michelle, and Eva van Baarle. "3 Dancing Boys and the Moral."&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*{{cite web|publisher=The UN Refugee Agency|title=Anti-Afghan rioting in Iran|url=https://www.unhcr.org/news/anti-afghan-rioting-iran|work=Ray Wilkinson}}

[[Category:Anti-national sentiment|Afghanistan]]
[[Category:Afghanistan in popular culture]]
[[Category:Prejudice and discrimination by type]]
[[Category:Racism]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>