<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20161116183335|749894417" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="15727067" pageid="15727067" ns="0" title="Racism in Europe"><revisions><rev timestamp="2016-11-16T18:35:05Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2013}}
According to the 2007 [[Eurobarometer]], Europeans believe that discrimination on the basis of ethnic origin is the most common form of discrimination in Europe.&lt;ref&gt;Eurobarometer: [http://ec.europa.eu/public_opinion/archives/ebs/ebs_263_en.pdf Discrimination in the European Union] Published January, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

Racism of various forms is found in every country on Earth, albeit at different rates and nature of incidents.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://web.amnesty.org/library/index/engACT400202001|publisher = Amnesty International|title = Racism and the administration of justice}}&lt;/ref&gt; Racism is widely condemned throughout the world, with 170 states signatories of the [[International Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Racial Discrimination]] by 8 August 2006.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://www.unhchr.ch/tbs/doc.nsf/(Symbol)/208ba1d9617d31d1c1257259003eed53?Opendocument|title = Report of the Committee on the Elimination of Racial Discrimination 68th and 69th session|publisher = United Nations Office of the High Commissioner for Human Rights}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Bulgaria==
On 9 October 1992, the Bulgarian president signed the Council of Europe Framework Convention on the Protection of National Minorities, signaling a new commitment to uphold minority rights.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |author= Human Rights Watch |title= Human Rights Watch World Report 1998 – 1 January |url= http://www.unhcr.org/refworld/docid/3ae6a8a510.html |publisher=[[Human Rights Watch]] |date=January 1, 1998}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2011 the parliamentary party "Ataka", identifying itself as nationalist, attacked the mosque in the center of Sofia during the Friday prayer. In 2013 one of the leaders of another nationalist party, VMRO, Angel Djambasky was put under investigation for calling the people to arm themselves against the immigrants.

At least 6 racist crimes are perpetuated between 3 and 13 November of every year.

A new "Nationalist party of Bulgaria", uniting skinheads, "[[Blood an honor]]", "[[National resistance]]" etc. has been created in November 2017. 112 intellectuals sign a petition to the attorney general not to register them.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dnevnik.bg/bulgaria/2011/05/20/1093480_ataka_sreshtu_mjusjulmanite_v_djamiiata_na_sofiia_video/|title=България - "Атака" срещу мюсюлманите в джамията на София (видео) - Dnevnik.bg|work=dnevnik.bg}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://paper.standartnews.com/bg/article.php?d=2013-11-05&amp;article=471190|title= Стандарт|work=standartnews.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.bghelsinki.org/media/uploads/documents/external/2013-11-13_signal_na_112_grazhdani_sreshtu_neo-nazi_partia.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

==Denmark==
Countries outside Europe criticized Denmark for statements in relation to the [[Jyllands-Posten Muhammad cartoons controversy|Muhammad cartoons controversy]] in 2005.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2006/01/30/AR2006013001316.html Cartoons of Prophet Met With Outrage] ''Washington Post''&lt;/ref&gt; [[Amnesty International]] has previously criticized the anti-drug police readiness to act against foreign citizens.{{citation needed|date=October 2016}} A Nigerian national broke her leg during an arrest and was only attended by a doctor six hours later. No charges were filed against the officers as the Regional State Prosecutor was unable to establish how it happened, but this decision was criticized by Amnesty International in 1997.&lt;ref name=AmD1997&gt;{{citation |url=http://asiapacific.amnesty.org/library/Index/ENGEUR010011998?open&amp;of=ENG-DNK#DEN |title=Concern in Europe July - December 1997 | publisher=Amnesty International |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20081212095215/http://asiapacific.amnesty.org/library/Index/ENGEUR010011998?open&amp;of=ENG-DNK|archive-date=2009-12-12 |access-date=2016-09-16 }}&lt;/ref&gt; As a result of a detention in 1990 where he had been injured, a Gambian national received an economic settlement from the Danish Ministry of Justice.&lt;ref name=AmD1997/&gt;

In relation to a gang war in Denmark, non-ethnic Danish gangs criticized the government&lt;ref&gt;[http://politiken.dk/indland/ECE472795/politi-de-unge-klager-over-racistiske-betjente/ Politi: De unge klager over racistiske betjente], by Andreas Lindquist, Politiken, 18 February 2008&lt;/ref&gt; due to the law that criminals of non-Danish citizenship are deported.&lt;ref&gt;[http://politiken.dk/newsinenglish/article660850.ece Hells Angels: Immigrants must clean up their act], by Julian Isherwood, Politiken (2009-03-03)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://politiken.dk/newsinenglish/article661507.ece Anti-gang package ready], by Julian Isherwood, Politiken (2009-03-04)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://jp.dk/uknews/article1622906.ece Government to double prison terms for gang members], The Copenhagen Post, Jyllandsposten (2009-03-05)&lt;/ref&gt;

==Finland==
{{main article|Racism in Finland}}
Reports say that racial hate crime is a recent phenomenon, and that they are on the rise.&lt;ref&gt;[http://cms.horus.be/files/99935/MediaArchive/pdf/finland_en.pdf Responding to racism in Finland]. European Network Against Racism&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://yle.fi/uutiset/news/2010/11/hate_crimes_against_foreigners_rise_2111368.html |title=Hate Crimes against Foreigners Rise &amp;#124; Yle Uutiset |publisher=yle.fi |accessdate=2012-05-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; The numbers of reported hate crimes in 2003 and 2004 were 522 and 558, respectively. In 2009, they had increased to over 1 000 (including non-racist hate crimes). Racial hate crimes have fluctuated from 858 (2009) to 641 (2012)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.poliisiammattikorkeakoulu.fi/poliisi/poliisioppilaitos/home.nsf/PFBD/AA662EFEA0162E5FC2257C1B0022E970?opendocument | title=Poliisin tietoon tullut viharikollisuus vähentynyt | website=poliisiammattikorkeakoulu.fi |year= 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the typical suspect have been a Finnish-born young man. However, over 60% of the targets were reported to have been Finland-born, although those with foreign-born parents were counted as well. The most targeted immigrants in 2004 were reported to be of [[Somali people|Somali]], [[Kurdish People|Kurdish]], [[Russians|Russian]], [[Iraqi people|Iraqi]] and [[Iranian peoples|Iranian]] origin. One-third of the hate crimes were reportedly aimed at the [[Finnish Kale|Kale]], and only one in six were members of the native population.

In European Social Surveys since 2002, Finns have proved to be least racist just after Swedes. Earlier Finnish scientific data reveals that attitudes had been improving continuously for a long time.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fsd.uta.fi/lehti/fi/28/tietoarkisto09.pdf Yhteiskuntatieteellinen tietoarkisto | www.fsd.uta.fi | 2009].&lt;/ref&gt; Professor of Social Policy and responsible of Finnish ESS, Heikki Ervasti, denies a common thought of increased negative attitudes against immigrants.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tylkkari.fi/ilmiot/kyokkipuheesta-poliittiseksi-voimaksi |title= Kyökkipuheesta poliittiseksi voimaksi | publisher=tylkkari.fi |year= 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A poll made in late 2011 revealed that the majority of the Finns viewed Finland as a racist country.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hs.fi/english/article/Poll+Majority+of+Finns+see+Finland+as+racist+country/1135269860316 |title=Helsingin Sanomat – International Edition – Home |publisher=hs.fi |accessdate=2012-05-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; Two thirds considered the country to be fairly racist, 12% recognised a moderate amount of racism, and 2% admitted to be very racist; 35% agreed partly or wholly to the statement "Islam is a threat to Western values and democracy", and 29% agreed more or less to that "people belonging to certain races simply are not suited to live in a modern society". One in five thought "it needs to be recognised as a fact that some nations are more intelligent than others", and 11% agreed partly or completely to "people whose appearance and culture differ much from those of the Finns are unpredictable and frightening".

==France==
{{main article|Racism in France}}
Jewish leaders perceive an intensifying [[anti-Semitism in France]], mainly among Muslims of [[Arab]] or [[Berber people|Berber]] heritage.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=Colin |last=Nickerson |title=Anti-Semitism seen rising among France's Muslims |url=http://www.boston.com/news/world/europe/articles/2006/03/13/anti_semitism_seen_rising_among_frances_muslims/ |publisher=The Boston Globe |date=2006-03-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1998 the Council of Europe's European Commission Against Racism and Intolerance (ECRI) made a report stating concern about racist activities in France and accused the French authorities of not doing enough to combat this. The report and other groups have expressed concern about organizations like [[Front National (France)]]. In a recent [[Pew Research Center|Pew Survey]], 47% of the French deem immigration from [[Central and Eastern Europe]] (mainly from [[Poland]], [[Slovakia]], [[Bulgaria]], [[Hungary]], [[Serbia]] and [[Romania]], including [[Slavs|Slavic]] and [[Romani people]]) to be a very bad thing. Likewise, the majority of French respondents revealed negative views on the immigration of [[Muslims]] from [[Africa]] and [[Middle East]]. A small minority showed signs of anti-Semitism. Roughly 11% had an unfavorable view of Jews&lt;ref&gt;{{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20091216042207/http://pewglobal.org/reports/display.php?PageID=795 |date=16 December 2009 |title=Pew Global Attitudes Project: Summary of Findings: A Year After Iraq War }} (2004-03-16)&lt;/ref&gt; and 8% felt that US policy was most influenced by the Jews.&lt;ref&gt;{{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20091211125844/http://pewglobal.org/reports/display.php?PageID=803 |date=11 December 2009 |title=Pew Global Attitudes Project: III: Opinions of U.S. Policies: U.S. Image Up Slightly, But Still Negative }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Germany==
{{main article|Racism in Germany}}
The period after losing [[World War I]] led to an increased use of anti-Semitism and other racism in political discourse, for example among the right-wing [[Freikorps]], emotions that finally culminated in the ascent of [[Adolf Hitler]] and the [[Nazi Party]] in 1933. The [[Nazi racial policy]] and the [[Nuremberg Laws|Nuremberg Race Laws]] against Jews and other non-Aryans represented the most explicit racist policies in Europe in the twentieth century. These laws deprived all Jews including even half-Jews and quarter-Jews as well as other non-Aryans from German citizenship. Jews official title became "subject of the state". The Nuremberg Race Laws forbid racially mixed sexual relations and marriage between Aryans and at first Jews but was later ended to "Gypsies, Negroes or their bastard offspring".&lt;ref name="Burleigh1991"&gt;{{cite book | author = Michael Burleigh | title = The Racial State: Germany 1933-1945 | date = 7 November 1991 | publisher = Cambridge University Press | ISBN = 978-0-521-39802-2 | page = 49}}&lt;/ref&gt; Such relations became a criminal and punishable offence under the race laws known as "racial pollution" [[Rassenschande]].&lt;ref name="Burleigh1991" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author = S. H. Milton | chapter = "Gypsies" as social outsiders in Nazi Germany| title =  Social Outsiders in Nazi Germany | editor = Robert Gellately and Nathan Stoltzfus | year = 2001 | publisher = Princeton University Press | ISBN = 9780691086842 | pages = 216, 231}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Hungary==
A EU report found that legal policies that should protect people from racism and xenophobia were "not implemented effectively", and that Hungarian public officials denied that racism and discrimination were a problem in their country, despite evidence to the contrary. It noted that such factors contributed to the increase in extremist ideology in Hungarian politics and media.&lt;ref name="FRA"&gt;{{cite news |url=http://fra.europa.eu/sites/default/files/fra-2013-thematic-situation-report-3_en_1.pdf |title=Racism, discrimination, intolerance and extremism: learning from experiences in Greece and Hungary |publisher=European Union Agency for Fundamental Rights (FRA) |date=December 2013 |accessdate=2014-02-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Council of Europe has also criticized Hungary in a new report, condemning xenophobia and violence against migrants and minorities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.dw.com/en/eu-report-finds-rampant-racism-xenophobia-in-hungary/a-18505689 |title=EU Report in Deutsche Welle}}&lt;/ref&gt;

2013 [[Fundamental Rights Agency|FRA]] online survey shows a middle to high level of [[antisemitism|anti-Semitism]] in Hungary, compared to other European countries.&lt;ref name="FRA"/&gt; The banned [[Hungarian Guard]] and some [[Jobbik]] politicians are sometimes described as xenophobic and racist.&lt;ref name="FRA"/&gt;

As in other European countries, the [[Romani people]] faced disadvantages, including unequal treatment, discrimination, segregation and harassment. Negative stereotypes are often linked to Romani unemployment and reliance on state benefits.&lt;ref name="FRA"/&gt; In 2008 and 2009 nine attacks took place against Romani in Hungary, resulting in six deaths and multiple injuries. According to the Hungarian curia (supreme court), these murders were motivated by [[Antiziganism|anti-Romani sentiment]] and sentenced the preparators to [[life imprisonment]].&lt;ref name="FRA"/&gt;

==Ireland==

Historically, the most serious racial problems in Ireland stemmed from the colonization of the country by the British, and the racist attitude of the colonists to the native Irish. The English considered themselves to be a distinct race from the Irish, who were classified as 'melanocroix', or 'half black' by [[Thomas Huxley]]. Depictions of the Irish in the popular British press throughout the centuries of British colonization were noted for their subhuman portrayal of the Irish (main article: [[Anti-Irish sentiment]]). Laws suppressing Irish culture and enfranchisement, outlawing the use of the language, education, and the practice of the local religion (Roman Catholicism) were enforced during various periods from the 14th century onward (see [[Statutes of Kilkenny]] and [[Penal Laws (Ireland)]]), only being fully repealed with the independence of Ireland from Britain in the early twentieth century (see [[Government of Ireland Act 1920]]).

20th Century

During the second world war, although Ireland was officially neutral, Prime Minister [[Éamon de Valera]] was accused of sympathizing with and supporting the [[Nazi regime]] of [[Adolf Hitler]] in Germany. Following the death of Hitler in 1945 de Valera was one of many who signed a book of condolence and offered sympathies to the German Minister at the German Embassy in [[Dublin]].&lt;ref&gt;''An Irish Statesman and Revolutionary'' by Elizabeth Keane (ISBN 978-1845111250), page 106&lt;/ref&gt; This led to the belief among [[Allies of World War II|Allied leaders]] such as [[Winston Churchill|Churchill]] that de Valera and the Irish in general were supportive of the Nazi regime.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Irish Public Service Broadcasting – 1940s: De Valera and Broadcasting|work=History of RTÉ|publisher=RTÉ|url=http://www.rte.ie/laweb/brc/brc_1940s_a.html|accessdate=2008-10-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; The substantial influx of Nazi war criminals to Ireland following the war and their acceptance into society both officially by the Government of Ireland and by the general public also lead to claims Ireland was tolerant if not supportive of the Nazi regime.&lt;ref&gt;"Hidden History: Ireland's Nazis", broadcast by RTÉ - January 2007&lt;/ref&gt; However, it must also be born in mind that Germany had supplied guns to the Irish war of independence 20 years earlier, and so Irish sympathies to the Germans rather than their long-standing oppressors the British can easily be accounted for in this way, rather than due to anti-semitism. Historically, the Jewish community in Ireland has enjoyed support not enjoyed elsewhere in Europe. (Main article: [[History of the Jews in Ireland]]).

In mid-twentieth century Ireland there was traditionally very little [[immigration]] in general to the Republic of Ireland, and hence little racial diversity, though in recent decades growing prosperity in the country (see: [[Celtic Tiger]]) attracted increasing numbers of [[immigrants]], mainly from [[Central and Eastern Europe]] (primarily [[Poland]]), [[China]] and [[Sub-Saharan Africa]]. Also the absence of colonialist baggage has meant that foreign people are not drawn to Ireland by "[[mother country]]" factors that have affected other European countries. Descendants of [[Irish people]] who emigrated in the past also started moving to the country. Most immigrants have settled in [[Dublin]] and the other cities. Though these developments have been somewhat tolerated by most, there has been a steady rise in racist attitudes among some sections of society. A 2001 survey found that 51% of Irish people surveyed considered the country inherently racist &lt;ref&gt;Liam Collins. [http://www.independent.ie/national-news/ireland-is-a-country-of-racists--at-least-the-irish-think-thats-true-508512.html Ireland is a country of racists – at least the Irish think that's true – National News]. Independent.ie (2001-05-27). Retrieved on 2012-06-02.&lt;/ref&gt; and 60% of those in the 25 to 34 age-group considered "racism" to be an Irish trait. In 2005, Minister of State for Overseas Development, Conor Lenihan famously advised Socialist politician Joe Higgins to "stick with the kebabs" – referring to his campaigning on behalf of [[Turkey|Turkish]] contract workers who had been paid less than the statutory minimum wage. The Minister later retracted his remarks and apologized.&lt;ref&gt;Michael O’Farrell. [http://liveweb.archive.org/http://www.irishexaminer.com/archives/2005/0519/ireland/lenihan-under-pressure-to-apologise-for-kebab-gaffe-626825454.html Lenihan under pressure to apologise for ‘kebab’ gaffe]. The Irish Examiner (2005-05-19)&lt;/ref&gt; A 2008 EU-MIDIS survey of attitudes to minorities in the 27 EU States found that Ireland had the most racist attitudes to Afro-Europeans in the entire EU.&lt;ref&gt;Jim Cusack. [http://www.independent.ie/opinion/analysis/ireland-of-the-welcomes-is-a-myth-2133538.html Ireland of the welcomes is a myth – Analysis, Opinion]. Independent.ie (2010-04-11). Retrieved on 2012-06-02.&lt;/ref&gt;

While most racist abuse in Ireland is verbal, violent hate crimes have occurred. In 2000, a white man was stabbed and seriously injured when defending his [[Jamaica]]n-born wife from racist abuse by a group of adult men.&lt;ref&gt;Tim Healy. [http://www.independent.ie/national-news/four-charged-with-hatred-in-racist-attack-on-father-son-345834.html Four charged with hatred in 'racist attack' on father, son – National News]. Independent.ie (2001-05-19). Retrieved on 2012-06-02.&lt;/ref&gt; In 2002, a [[Chinese people|Chinese]] man Zhao Liu Tao (29) was murdered in Dublin in what was described as the Republic of Ireland's first racially motivated murder.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/1813880.stm Murder sparks Irish racism fears], [[BBC News]] (2002-02-11)&lt;/ref&gt; Later that year Leong Ly Min, a [[Vietnamese people|Vietnamese]] man who had lived in Dublin since 1979,&lt;ref&gt;[http://republican-news.org/archive/2002/August29/29anti.html Rally against racist attacks], [[Republican News]] (2002-08-29)&lt;/ref&gt; was mortally wounded by two assailants who had been racially abusing him.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/world/ireland/article7094192.ece Death of a dream as racism rears its head in Ireland], [[The Times]] (2010-04-11)&lt;/ref&gt; In February 2008, two [[Poles|Polish]] mechanics, Paweł Kalita (29) and Mariusz Szwajkos (27) were attacked by a group of Dublin youths and died outside their home after each being stabbed in the head with a screwdriver. Those [[Anti-Polish sentiment|anti-Polish]] attacks are mostly driven by ethnicity-based racism, however they occasionally involve religion-based hate provoked by the [[Anti-Catholicism|anti-Catholic attitude]] of some [[Protestantism in Ireland|Irish Protestant]] groups.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://lostchildreninthewilderness.wordpress.com/2010/05/07/dublin-drimnagh-man-david-curran-19-found-guilty-of-double-murder-updated/ |title=Dublin: Drimnagh Man David Curran 19 Found Guilty Of Double Murder: UPDATED |website=lostchildreninthewilderness.wordpress.com |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110820070451/http://lostchildreninthewilderness.wordpress.com/2010/05/07/dublin-drimnagh-man-david-curran-19-found-guilty-of-double-murder-updated/ |archivedate=20 August 2011 |accessdate=2011-05-01}}{{unreliable source?|date=May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2010, 15-year-old schoolboy [[Toyosi Shittabey]], born in [[Nigeria]] but brought up in Dublin, was killed. The only man to stand trial for the murder was acquitted on the direction of the trial Judge&lt;ref&gt;Shane Hickey.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Shelta]] or [[Irish Travellers]], a nomadic ethnic group once speaking their own language, have also experienced persecution in past and modern times throughout Ireland.

Recently, the Mayor of [[Naas]] Darren Scully was forced to resign on 22 November 2011 over comments on live radio about the "aggressive attitude" of "black Africans".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.irishtimes.com/newspaper/ireland/2011/1123/1224308000247.html|title=FG councillor resigns as mayor after radio remarks|first=Steven|last=Carroll|author2=Deeney, Lisa |work=The Irish Times|accessdate=2011-11-23|date=23 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.rte.ie/news/2011/1122/scullyd.html|title=Darren Scully resigns as Mayor of Naas|work=RTÉ News|accessdate=2011-11-22|date=22 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Former [[Labour Party (Ireland)|Labour]] [[Teachta Dála|TD]] [[Moosajee Bhamjee]], a [[Muslim]] and Ireland's first and only non-white, non-Irish Member of Parliament, said Scully's remarks represented the "beginning of official racism" in Ireland and described them as "enlightenment" for the "neo-Nazi following in this country".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-2065262/Irish-town-mayor-quits-refusing-deal-black-people.html|title=Irish town mayor quits after refusing to deal with black people because they are 'aggressive and bad-mannered'|first=Ferghal|last=Blaney|author2=Mallon, Sandra |work=Daily Mail|accessdate=2011-11-23|date=23 November 2011|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Italy==
{{main article|Racism in Italy}}

==Latvia==
{{main article|Racism in Latvia}}

==Lithuania==
{{main article|Racism in Lithuania}}

==Netherlands==

In 2006 the [[Dutch Equal Treatment Commission]] got 694 requests to judge if a treatment legislation law had been broken. By far the most cases concerned [[Ageism|age discrimination]] (219), [[Racism|race discrimination]] followed (105) and lesser number of [[sexism|sex discrimination]] cases. The [[Dutch Equal Treatment Commission]] brought out 261 judgements; 46 per cent of the cases were declared discrimination.&lt;ref&gt;{{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20071021035003/http://www.discriminatie.nl/?nieuws=171 |date=21 October 2007 |title=Art.1 – Art.1: landelijke vereniging die zich inzet voor het voorkomen en bestrijden van discriminatie }}. Discriminatie.nl. Retrieved on 9 February 2014.&lt;/ref&gt; In the early 2012 the Dutch Right-wing [[Party for Freedom]] established an [[Anti-Slavic sentiment|anti-Slavic]] (predominantly [[Anti-Polish sentiment|anti-Polish]]) and  [[Antiziganism|anti-Romani]] website, where native [[Dutch people]] could air their frustration about losing their job because of cheaper workers from [[Poland]], [[Bulgaria]], [[Romania]] and other non-Germanic [[Central and Eastern Europe]]an countries. This led to commentaries involving [[hate speech]] and other racial prejudice mainly against Poles and Roma, but also aimed at other Central and Eastern European ethnic groups.&lt;ref&gt;[http://euobserver.com/news/115208 Dutch far right opens anti-Polish hotline: ''"Did you lose your job to a Pole, a Bulgarian, a Romanian, or any other Central or Eastern European? We would like to hear about it".'']&lt;/ref&gt;

In the past years, the Dutch tradition 'Sinterklaas' (Santa Claus) is criticized because of the 'zwarte pieten'(black pete's). Critics say the black pete's are rasism and discrimination because they refer to (the Dutch) slavery. Big red lips, golden earrings and frizzy hair characterizes the slaves. Dutch Prime Minister, [[Mark Rutte]], said in response to the protests: 'I can't change the colour 'zwarte piet', 'zwarte piet' is black, that's the it is'. 
Although there have been several changes to the appearance of black pete, critics said it is not enough. They want to change the colour of black pete to white.
In 2013, a Facebook-petition called 'pietitie' was held. More than 2 million Dutch Facebook-users signed it, which is 35% of all users.
A poll, held in 2013 by a Dutch televisionprgramme, showed that 90% of the Dutch do not want any changes to 'zwarte piet'.

==Poland==
{{main article|Racism in Poland}}

==Portugal==
{{main article|Racism in Portugal}}

==Romania==
{{main article|Racism in Romania}}

==Russia==
{{main article|Racism in Russia}}
{{further|Liberal Democratic Party of Russia|History of the Jews in the Soviet Union|History of the Jews in Russia}}
The term "[[pogrom]]" became commonly used in English after a large-scale wave of anti-Jewish riots swept through south-western [[Russian Empire|Czarist Russia]] in 1881&amp;ndash;1884. A much bloodier wave of pogroms broke out in 1903–1906, leaving an estimated 2,000 Jews dead.  By the beginning of the 20th century, most European Jews lived in the so-called [[Pale of Settlement]], the Western frontier of the [[Russian Empire]] consisting generally of the modern-day countries of Poland, Lithuania, Belarus and neighboring regions.  Many pogroms accompanied the [[Russian Revolution|Revolution of 1917]] and the ensuing [[Russian Civil War]], an estimated 70,000 to 250,000 civilian Jews were killed in the atrocities throughout the former [[Russian Empire]]; the number of Jewish orphans exceeded 300,000.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.britannica.com/eb/article-215022/anti-Semitism|title=anti-Semitism|work=Encyclopedia Britannica|accessdate=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hilary L Rubinstein, Daniel C Cohn-Sherbok, Abraham J Edelheit, William D Rubinstein, ''The Jews in the Modern World'', Oxford University Press, 2002.&lt;/ref&gt;

Racism inside Russia is quite a modern post-[[Soviet Union|USSR]] phenomenon that has been steadily growing in the past decade. In the 2000s, [[Neo-Nazism|neo-Nazi]] groups inside [[Russia]] have risen to include as many as tens of thousands of people.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| title=A gathering storm of Russian thugs | url=http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?file=/c/a/2005/08/14/MNGUSE7N2D1.DTL | work=The San Francisco Chronicle | first=Anna | last=Badkhen | date=2005-08-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; Racism against both the Russian citizens ([[peoples of the Caucasus]], [[indigenous peoples of Siberia|indigenous peoples of Siberia and Russian Far East]], etc.) and non-Russian citizens of Africans, Central Asians, East Asians (Vietnamese, Chinese, etc.) and Europeans (Ukrainians, etc.) is an ever-increasing problem.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.splcenter.org/intel/intelreport/article.jsp?aid=726|title=Racist Violence, Rhetoric Plague Russia|publisher=|accessdate=17 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A Pew Global opinion poll showed that 25% of Russians had an unfavorable view of Jews.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://pewglobal.org/reports/display.php?PageID=795 | title=A Year After Iraq War: Mistrust of America in Europe Ever Higher, Muslim Anger Persists | work=Pew Global Attitudes Project | date=2004-03-16 | archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20061008021739/http://pewglobal.org/reports/display.php?PageID=795 | archivedate=October 8, 2006 | deadurl=y}}&lt;/ref&gt; Racism towards Central Asians is said to be widespread.{{Citation needed|date=December 2007}}

==Slovenia==
[[Romani people]] have become the main target of Slovenian racists in the 21st century as the population is otherwise extremely homogeneous.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.humaniteinenglish.com/article441.html Slovenia: Chasing out the Roma]. Humaniteinenglish.com (2006-12-05). Retrieved on 2012-06-02.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Spain==
{{main article|Racism in Spain}}
[[Romani people in Spain|Gitanos]] are viewed with less sympathy than other groups.&lt;ref name="Gitanos"&gt;[http://www.gitanos.org/areas/igualdad_de_trato_y_no_discriminacion/noticias/26701.html Nuevas encuestas del CIS sitúan a los gitanos como el grupo social más rechazado, mientras que un estudio sociológico refleja los importantes avances de esta comunidad], 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

Racist abuse aimed at black footballers has been reported at Spanish football league matches in recent years. This has led to protests and UEFA fines against clubs whose supporters continue the abuse. Several players in the Spanish league including Barcelona striker [[Samuel Eto'o]] and Espanyol goalkeeper [[Carlos Kameni]] have suffered and spoken out against the abuse. In 2006, Real Zaragoza player [[Ewerthon]] stated: "the Spanish Federation have to start taking proper measures and we as Afro-European players also have to act."&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/sport1/hi/football/europe/4751876.stm Eto'o makes anti-racism protest] BBC News&lt;/ref&gt;

==Sweden==
{{main article|Racism in Sweden}}
In 1922 Sweden established the [[Statens institut för rasbiologi]], or state institute for race biology.&lt;ref&gt;[[:sv:Rasbiologi|race-biology institute]]&lt;/ref&gt; The institute recommended the sterilization by force of the mentally ill, physically disabled, homosexuals and ethnic minorities, which was allowed by Swedish law until 1975.&lt;ref&gt;[[:sv:Sterilisering (ingrepp)|sterilization]]&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the report ''Racism and Xenophobia in Sweden'' by the Board of Integration, Muslims are exposed to the most religious harassment in Sweden. Almost 40% of the interviewed said they had witnessed verbal abuse directed at Muslims.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thelocal.se/article.php?ID=2363&amp;date=20051025 The Local: Muslims face most racism in Sweden]. Thelocal.se (2012-05-20). Retrieved on 2012-06-02.&lt;/ref&gt; [[European Network Against Racism]] in Sweden claims that in today's Sweden there exists a clear ethnic hierarchy when ethnic Swedes are at the top and non-European immigrants are at the bottom.&lt;ref&gt;[http://cms.horus.be/files/99935/MediaArchive/pdf/Sweden_EN.pdf Responding to racism in Sweden]. (PDF) . Retrieved on 2012-06-02.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Sveriges Radio]] reported that the punishments for driving under the influence of alcohol tended to be harsher for immigrants than for Swedes; while over 50% of immigrants were sent to jail for driving under the effect of alcohol, only less than 30% of ethnic Swedes were sent to jail with the same level of alcohol found in blood.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sr.se/cgi-bin/ekot/artikel.asp?Artikel=403326 Harder punishments to immigrants]. Sr.se (2004-04-22). Retrieved on 2012-06-02.&lt;/ref&gt; There has been evidence that the Swedish police used "Neger Niggersson" as a nickname for a criminal in a police training; this was published in Swedish media.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thelocal.se/17424/20090207/ Racist stereotypes used in police training]. Thelocal.se (2012-05-20). Retrieved on 2012-06-02.&lt;/ref&gt; Lately however, many incidents of racial attitudes and discrimination of the Swedish police have led for the first time to the control of racial attitudes of police students under police education &lt;ref&gt;{{sv icon}} [http://www.svd.se/nyheter/inrikes/artikel_3516139.svd Control of police attitudes]. Svd.se (2009-09-14). Retrieved on 2012-06-02.&lt;/ref&gt; A recent research done by the Swedish Confederation for Professional Employees (TCO) found that people with foreign background have much lower chances of finding a job that is appropriate for their education, even when they have grown up in Sweden and got their education in Swedish institutes.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tco.se/Templates/Page2____417.aspx?DataID=8753 Academic immigrants discriminates in labour market]. Tco.se (2009-03-11). Retrieved on 2012-06-02.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2007, there were a total of 3,536 hate crimes (defined as crimes with an ethnic or religious motive) reported to the police, including 118 cases of anti-Semitic agitation.&lt;ref&gt;[http://fra.europa.eu/fraWebsite/attachments/Antisemitism_Update_2009.pdf Fundamental Rights Agency report (pdf)]. (PDF) . Retrieved on 2012-06-02.&lt;/ref&gt; Racism in Sweden is reported to appear within Swedish health-care services as well. A nurse at a Stockholm suburb hospital lost his job after complaining on racial attitudes of the hospital staff to patients with immigrant background. Staff was cited saying "go back to Arabia", "the patient is screaming because it's in his culture."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dn.se/sthlm/skoterska-slog-larm-forlorar-jobbet-1.960497 Nurse speaks out about racism]. Dn.se (2009-09-24). Retrieved on 2012-06-02.&lt;/ref&gt;

Swedish social services have reported on racism in Swedish hospitals as well.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dn.se/sthlm/skoterska-slog-larm-forlorar-jobbet-1.960497 Social services identify racism in Swedish hospitals]. Dn.se (2009-09-24). Retrieved on 2012-06-02.&lt;/ref&gt; A study of statistics Sweden (SCB) reveals that segregation is widespread for Swedish immigrants when there are large differences in the fields of education, housing, employment and politics between immigrants and ethnic Swedes.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thelocal.se/16452/20081218/ Segregation 'widespread' for Swedish immigrants]. Thelocal.se (2012-05-20). Retrieved on 2012-06-02.&lt;/ref&gt; Sweden has been criticized by the UN human rights council for an increasing number of hate crimes which seldom resulted in criminal charges, when more hate crimes are Islamophobic, and homophobic, with an increasing amount of racist propaganda appearing on the internet and in Sweden's schools, for failing to provide adequate health care and education to immigrants, asylum seekers and undocumented migrants and the ongoing discrimination of the Roma and Sami minorities in Sweden.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thelocal.se/23150/20091109/ Sweden slammed for UN rights failures]. Thelocal.se. Retrieved on 2012-06-02.&lt;/ref&gt;

A study was conducted in 2011 about the Swedes attitudes to mixed marriages. The conclusion was that the views in general were favorable, but that there was a strong hierarchy based on which groups to live with. Swedes primarily preferred relationships with Scandinavians, Western Europeans and Southern Europeans, and then Eastern Europeans, Central Europeans and Latin Americans. At the bottom were South and East Asians, Africans, and Middle Eastern people. Older individuals and women, as well as people with less education and people who were brought up outside of [[Malmö]] (the most multicultural city of Sweden), were generally more prone to having negative attitudes. Most were able to accept family members and friends living in mixed relationships, even if they did not want to do it themselves.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Text: Johanna Svensson |url=http://www.mah.se/english/News/News-2011/-Love-aint-got-no-color--Attitude-toward-interracial-marriage/ |title=Love ain’t got no color? – Attitude toward interracial marriage – Malmö University |publisher=Mah.se |date=2011-09-27 |accessdate=2012-05-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Swedish national television (SVT) has reported on a new research done in Sweden which identifies that job seekers with a Swedish name have 50% higher chances to be called for an interview than job seekers with middle-eastern names. The research enlightens that there is not much difference between foreign-born job seekers and job seekers born in Sweden if both don't have a Swedish name; this indicates that ethnic discrimination is the main cause of the variations.&lt;ref&gt;[http://svt.se/2.22620/1.1795381/invandrare_kallas_inte_till_intervju?lid=senasteNytt_275216&amp;lpos=rubrik_1795381 Immigrants are not called for job interviews]. Svt.se. Retrieved on 2012-06-02.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2012, Swedish Minister for Culture Lena Adelsohn Liljeroth was labelled a racist by The Afro-Swedish Society (Afro-svenskarnas riksförbund) because she cut up a cake in the shape of a naked African woman in public. Ironically, the cake was made by an Afro-Swedish artist.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aftonbladet.se/nyheter/article14690952.ab Aftonbladet "Afrosvenskar kräver ministerns avgång" 2012-04-16]. Aftonbladet.se (2012-04-17). Retrieved on 2012-06-02.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2012/apr/17/sweden-europe-news?newsfeed=true Swedish minister denies claims of racism over black woman cake stunt]. Guardian (2012-04-17). Retrieved on 2012-06-02.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-17749533 Swedish minister in 'racist cake' controversy]. Bbc.co.uk (2012-04-18). Retrieved on 2012-06-02.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aljazeera.com/news/europe/2012/04/201241804049897269.html Swedish culture minister in 'racist cake' row]. Aljazeera.com (2012-04-18). Retrieved on 2012-06-02.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Switzerland==
[[Switzerland|The Swiss Confederation]] or ''Confederatio Helvetica'' is a nation composed of four subcultural groups: German-speaking (63.7%), French-speaking (20.4%), Italian-speaking (6.5%) and [[Romansh language|Romansh]]-speaking (0.5%).&lt;ref&gt;{{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20060819110032/http://www.bfs.admin.ch/bfs/portal/en/index/themen/bevoelkerung/sprachen__religionen/blank/kennzahlen0/sprachen.html |date=19 August 2006 |title=Languages }}. Swiss Federal Population Census 2000&lt;/ref&gt;

Swiss "Confederation Commission Against Racism" which is part of the Swiss "Federal Department of Home Affairs"[http://www.edi.admin.ch/] published a 2004 report, ''Black People in Switzerland'': ''A Life between [[Racial integration|Integration]] and [[Discrimination]]'' &lt;ref&gt;{{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20050311063519/http://www.edi.admin.ch/ekr/dokumentation/shop/00019/00142/index.html?lang=de |date=11 March 2005 |title=Schwarze Menschen in der Schweiz. Ein Leben zwischen Integration und Diskriminierung }}. edi.admin.ch (2004)&lt;/ref&gt; (published in German, French, and Italian only). According to this report, discrimination based on skin colour in Switzerland is not exceptional, and affects immigrants decades after their immigration.

[[Swiss People's Party]] claims that Swiss communities have a [[democracy|democratic]] right to decide who can or cannot be Swiss. In addition, the report said "Official statements and political campaigns that present immigrants from the EU in a favourable light and immigrants from elsewhere in a bad light must stop", according to the Swiss Federal Statistics Office in 2006, 85.5% of the foreign residents in Switzerland are European.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bfs.admin.ch/bfs/portal/fr/index/themen/01/07/blank/data/01.html |title=Statistique suisse – Population étrangère – Aperçu général |publisher=Bfs.admin.ch |date=2012-05-03 |accessdate=2012-05-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[United Nations]] special rapporteur on racism, [[Doudou Diène]], has observed that Switzerland suffers from racism, [[discrimination]] and [[xenophobia]]. The UN envoy explained that although the Swiss authorities recognised the existence of [[racism]] and xenophobia, they did not view the problem as being serious. Diène pointed out that representatives of minority communities said they experienced serious racism and discrimination, notably for access to public services (e.g. health care), employment and lodging.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.swissinfo.ch/eng/front/UN_envoy_calls_racism_in_Switzerland_a_reality.html?siteSect=105&amp;sid=6382785&amp;cKey=1137401626000&amp;ty=st |title=UN envoy calls racism in Switzerland a reality- swissinfo |publisher=Swissinfo.ch |date=2006-01-14 |accessdate=2012-05-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/6980766.stm | work=BBC News | first=Imogen | last=Foulkes | title=Swiss row over black sheep poster | date=6 September 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Turkey==
{{main article|Racism in Turkey}}

==Ukraine==
{{main article|Racism and discrimination in Ukraine}}

==United Kingdom==
{{main article|Racism in the United Kingdom}}

==See also==
{{Portal|Europe|Discrimination}}
* [[Racism by country]]

==References==
{{Reflist|35em}}

==External links==
{{commonscatinline}}
* [http://www.coe.int/ecri European Commission against Racism and Intolerance]
* [http://www.enar-eu.org European Network Against Racism]

{{Racism topics}}
{{Europe topic|Racism in}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Racism In Europe}}
[[Category:Europe]]
[[Category:Racism by region|Europe]]
[[Category:Racism in Europe]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>