<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20220907005019|1108922972" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1703917" pageid="1703917" ns="0" title="Gender expression"><revisions><rev timestamp="2022-09-14T19:23:21Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Transgender sidebar}}
{{LGBT sidebar}}

{{short description|External manifestation of gender identity}}
'''Gender expression''', or '''gender presentation''', is a person's behavior, mannerisms, interests, and appearance that are associated with [[gender]], specifically with the categories of [[femininity]] or [[masculinity]]. This also includes [[gender role]]s. These categories rely on [[stereotype]]s about gender.

==Terminology==
Gender expression typically reflects a person's [[gender identity]] (their internal sense of their own gender), but this is not always the case.&lt;ref name="Summers"&gt;{{cite book|last1=Summers|first1=Randal W.|title=Social Psychology: How Other People Influence Our Thoughts and Actions [2 volumes]|date=2016|publisher=ABC-CLIO|isbn=9781610695923|page=232|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=5nF1DQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA232}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="APA2015"&gt;{{cite journal|author1=American Psychological Association|title=Guidelines for Psychological Practice With Transgender and Gender Nonconforming People|journal=American Psychologist|date=December 2015|volume=70|issue=9|page=861|url=http://www.apa.org/practice/guidelines/transgender.pdf|doi=10.1037/a0039906|pmid=26653312}}&lt;/ref&gt; Gender expression is separate and independent both from [[sexual orientation]] and [[Sex assignment|sex assigned at birth]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Gender, Gender Identity, and Gender Expression | publisher = Government of Alberta | url = https://myhealth.alberta.ca/Alberta/Pages/gender-ID-expression-LGBTQ.aspx | access-date = 20 Sep 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt; Gender identity can be expressed through behavior, clothing, hair, makeup and other aspects of one’s external appearance.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Sexual Orientation and Gender Identity Definitions|url=https://www.hrc.org/resources/sexual-orientation-and-gender-identity-terminology-and-definitions|access-date=2021-11-17|website=HRC|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt; Gender expression does not always fall in line with a person's gender identity.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Kirkup|first=Kyle|date=2018-01-01|title=The origins of gender identity and gender expression in Anglo-American legal discourse|url=https://www.utpjournals.press/doi/full/10.3138/utlj.2017-0080|journal=University of Toronto Law Journal|volume=68|issue=1|pages=80–117|doi=10.3138/utlj.2017-0080|s2cid=148583324|issn=0042-0220}}&lt;/ref&gt; A type of gender expression that is considered atypical for a person's externally perceived gender may be described as [[Gender variance|gender non-conforming]].

In men and boys, typical or masculine gender expression is often described as ''manly'', while atypical or feminine expression is known as [[Effeminacy|effeminate]]. In girls and young women, atypically masculine expression is called [[tomboy]]ish. In lesbian and queer women, masculine and feminine expressions are known as [[butch and femme]] respectively. A mixture of typical and atypical expression may be described as [[Androgyny|androgynous]]. A type of expression that is perceived as neither typically feminine or masculine can be described as gender-neutral or undifferentiated.

The term ''gender expression'' is used in the [[Yogyakarta Principles]], which concern the application of international [[human rights law]] in relation to sexual orientation, gender identity, gender expression, and [[Sex characteristics (legal term)|sex characteristics]].&lt;ref name="ypplus10"&gt;[http://www.yogyakartaprinciples.org/principles-en/yp10/ Yogyakarta Principles plus 10]&lt;/ref&gt; The term also designates a criterion for human rights protection in certain countries, including Canada.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | title = Policy Change, Courts, and the Canadian Constitution | last = Macfarlane | first = Emmett | publisher = University of Toronto Press | date = 2018 | page =391}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Confusion between gender expression and sexual orientation ==
		
While gender expression does not necessarily connect to sexuality, individuals often are misinterpreted as more masculine if [[lesbian]] and more feminine if [[gay]], regardless of the individual's gender expression. These beliefs can lead to people misinterpreting an individual's gender expression based on their sexuality. Studies on adolescents conducted by Stacey Horn, showed that gay and lesbian individuals who did not express themselves as their assigned gender were seen as less acceptable. Individuals who expressed themselves with their assigned gender typically faced less social harassment and discrimination. On the other hand, [[heterosexual]] males whose gender expression was more feminine than masculine were the most discriminated against.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Horn | first1 = Stacey S | title = Adolescents' Acceptance of Same-Sex Peers Based on Sexual Orientation and Gender Expression | journal = Journal of Youth and Adolescence | year = 2007 | volume = 36 | issue = 3| pages = 373 | doi = 10.1007/s10964-007-9176-4 | pmid = 27519035 | doi-access = free }}&lt;/ref&gt;

"The heterosexual matrix" theory created by gender theorist [[Judith Butler]] posits that people often assume someone's sexuality based on their visible gender and sex. Lisa Disch states that it explains why people tend to assume someone's gender expression based on their sex and sexuality.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Disch | first1 = Lisa | title = Judith Butler and the Politics of the Performative | journal = Political Theory | year = 1999 | volume = 27 | issue = 4| pages = 545–559 | doi = 10.1177/0090591799027004006 | s2cid = 144841050 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Discrimination ==
People sometimes face discrimination because of their gender expression. Victims of discrimination often culturally express different genders than their gender identity or biological sex. Gender expression-based discrimination can be independent of sexual orientation, and it can lead to bullying, childhood abuse, sexual assault, discrimination, and various other traumatizing hardships.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Lehavot|first1=Keren|last2=Molina|first2=Yamile|last3=Simoni|first3=Jane M.|date=2012-09-01|title=Childhood Trauma, Adult Sexual Assault, and Adult Gender Expression among Lesbian and Bisexual Women|url=https://doi.org/10.1007/s11199-012-0171-1|journal=Sex Roles|language=en|volume=67|issue=5|pages=272–284|doi=10.1007/s11199-012-0171-1|pmid=24003263|pmc=3758810|issn=1573-2762}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Gender expression is a sizable aspect of how a person views themselves, and thus will impact self confidence. When an individual is forced, for personal or societal influences, to portray themselves in a manner they don't personally identify with, confidence can be greatly hindered in turn damaging mental health. A 2017 study reported that when masculine presenting lesbians are made to dress in a feminine style, their confidence suffers greatly.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Henrichs-Beck|first1=Christine L.|last2=Szymanski|first2=Dawn M.|date=2017|title=Gender expression, body–gender identity incongruence, thin ideal internalization, and lesbian body dissatisfaction.|url=http://doi.apa.org/getdoi.cfm?doi=10.1037/sgd0000214|journal=Psychology of Sexual Orientation and Gender Diversity|language=en|volume=4|issue=1|pages=23–33|doi=10.1037/sgd0000214|s2cid=151550839|issn=2329-0390}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Related terms ==
Other, rarer terms exist for aspects of gender expression. In academic sources, a feminine gender expression in a male (of any orientation) may be called ''gynemimesis'' (adjective: ''gynemimetic'').&lt;ref name="Denny2013"&gt;{{cite book |last=Denny |first=Dallas |title=Current Concepts in Transgender Identity |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=jiJMyBGmEkQC&amp;pg=PA414 |date=13 May 2013 |publisher=Routledge |location=London |isbn=978-1134-82110-5 |pages=402, 412–414 |oclc=1100456679}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Weinrich-1987"&gt;{{cite book |last=Weinrich |first=James D. |title=Sexual Landscapes: Why We are what We Are, why We Love Whom We Love |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=X8d9AAAAMAAJ |year=1987 |publisher=Scribner's |isbn=978-0-684-18705-1 |pages=276–277 |oclc=299414370}}&lt;/ref&gt; The converse is ''andromimesis'' (adj.: ''andromimetic'').&lt;ref name="Denny2013" /&gt;{{rp|402}}&lt;ref name="Money2010"&gt;{{cite book |last=Money |first=John |title=Sin, Science, and the Sex Police: Essays on Sexology &amp; Sexosophy |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=MDQIPVyKzGwC&amp;pg=PA246 |date=30 December 2010 |publisher=Prometheus |isbn=978-1615-92830-9 |pages=246– |oclc=1131230541}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Anti-gender movement]]
*[[Bem Sex-Role Inventory]]
*[[Discrimination against non-binary gender people]]
*[[Queer heterosexuality]]

== References ==
{{reflist}}

== Bibliography ==
* Serano, Julia (2016). ''Whipping Girl: A transsexual woman on sexism and the scapegoating of femininity'' (2nd ed.), Berkeley, CA: Seal Press.

== External links ==
*[http://www.juliaserano.com/terminology.html "There Is No Perfect Word: A Transgender Glossary of Sorts"] by [[Julia Serano]]
*[http://genderanalysis.net/2014/12/transition-as-gender-freedom-gender-analysis-03/ Gender Analysis: ''Transition as gender freedom''], by Zinnia Jones, December 1, 2014
*[https://genderanalysis.net/2017/06/identifying-with-a-gender-vs-reaffirming-gender-stereotypes/ Gender Analysis: ''Identifying with a gender vs. reaffirming gender stereotypes''], by Zinnia Jones, June 1, 2017
*[http://www.transstudent.org/gender/ The Gender Unicorn – Trans Student Educational Resources]

{{LGBT}}
{{Gender and sexual identities}}
{{Transgender topics}}
{{Gender studies}}
{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Gender roles]]
[[Category:Gender identity]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>