<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20060806064109|67962769" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="3455302" pageid="3455302" ns="0" title="Genetic discrimination"><revisions><rev timestamp="2006-08-07T17:48:58Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Genetic discrimination''' occurs when people are treated differently by their [[employer]] or [[insurance company]] because they have a [[gene]] [[mutation]] that causes or increases the risk of an [[Genetic disorder|inherited disorder]]. People who undergo [[genetic testing]] may be at risk for genetic discrimination.

The results of a genetic test are normally included in a person's [[medical record]]s. When a person applies for life, disability, or health insurance, in some countries the insurance company may ask to look at these records before making a decision about coverage. An employer may also have the right to look at an employee's medical records. As a result, genetic test results could affect a person's insurance coverage or employment. People making decisions about genetic testing should be aware that when test results are placed in their medical records, the results might not be kept private.

Fear of discrimination is a concern among people considering [[genetic testing]]. Several countries have laws that help protect people against genetic discrimination; however, genetic testing is a fast-growing field and these laws don't cover every situation. 

==See also==
*[[Genoism]]

{{genetics-stub}}

[[Category:Genetics]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>