<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20201029011603|985970111" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="3455302" pageid="3455302" ns="0" title="Genetic discrimination"><revisions><rev timestamp="2020-10-29T01:23:20Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Globalize|article|USA|2name=the United States|date=October 2012}}
{{Discrimination sidebar}}

'''Genetic discrimination''' occurs when people treat others (or are treated) differently because they have or are perceived to have a [[gene]] [[mutation]](s) that causes or increases the risk of an [[Genetic disorder|inherited disorder]]. It may also refer to any and all discrimination based on the [[genotype]] of a person rather than their individual merits, including that related to race. Some legal scholars have argued for a more precise and broader definition of genetic discrimination: "Genetic discrimination should be defined as when an individual is subjected to negative treatment, not as a result of the individual's physical manifestation of disease or disability, but solely because of the individual's genetic composition."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title = Genetic Testing Meets Big Data: Torts and Contract Law Issues|ssrn = 2460891|date = 2014|location = Rochester, NY|first = Ifeoma|last = Ajunwa | name-list-style = vanc }}&lt;/ref&gt; Genetic Discrimination is considered to have its foundations in genetic determinism and genetic essentialism,&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite journal|title = Genetic Data and Civil Rights|ssrn = 2460897|date = 2015|location = Harvard Civil Rights- Civil Liberties Law Review|first = Ifeoma|last = Ajunwa}}&lt;/ref&gt; and is based on the concept of '''genism''', i.e. distinctive human characteristics and capacities are [[genetic determinism|determined by genes]].&lt;ref name="Annas 2003"&gt;{{cite document|last=Annas |first=George |authorlink=George Annas | name-list-style = vanc |title=Genism, Racism, and the Prospect of Genetic Genocide |date=2003 |url=http://www.gjga.org/inside.asp?a=1&amp;action=item&amp;source=documents&amp;id=19 |access-date=2008-07-31 |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110726104538/http://www.gjga.org/inside.asp?a=1&amp;action=item&amp;source=documents&amp;id=19 |archive-date=2011-07-26 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Genetic discrimination takes different forms depending on the country and the protections that have been taken to limit genetic discrimination, such as GINA in the United States that protects people from being barred from working or from receiving healthcare as a result of their genetic makeup.&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt; The umbrella of genetic discrimination includes the notion of informed consent, which refers to an individual's right to make a decision about their participation in research with complete comprehension of the research study.&lt;ref name=":4"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Braverman G, Shapiro ZE, Bernstein JA | title = Ethical Issues in Contemporary Clinical Genetics | journal = Mayo Clinic Proceedings. Innovations, Quality &amp; Outcomes | volume = 2 | issue = 2 | pages = 81–90 | date = June 2018 | pmid = 30225437 | pmc = 6124343 | doi = 10.1016/j.mayocpiqo.2018.03.005 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The idea of genetic discrimination has been combated since the 1947 [[Nuremberg Code]] that was created shortly after WWII, during which thousands of racialized victims died in tests conducted in Germany.&lt;ref name=":4" /&gt; Many countries are still developing policies to combat genetic discrimination in science, law, and everyday life.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Joly |first1=Yann |last2=Ngueng Feze |first2=Ida |last3=Song |first3=Lingqiao |last4=Knoppers |first4=Bartha Maria | name-list-style = vanc |date=2017-03-06 |title=Normative Approaches to Address Genetic Discrimination: Placebo or Panacea? | journal = Trends in Genetics |location=Rochester, NY|ssrn=2911199 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legal status==

=== United States ===
[[File:H.R. 493 - Genetic Information Nondiscrimination Act (GINA) (27946508696).jpg|thumb|On May 21st, 2008, George W. Bush signed the Genetic Information Nondiscrimination Act, protecting individuals from genetic discrimination in health insurance and employment.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://ginahelp.org/|title=GINAhelp.org – Your GINA Resource|website=ginahelp.org|access-date=2019-10-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
Genetic discrimination is illegal in the U.S. after passage of the [[Genetic Information Nondiscrimination Act]] (GINA) on May 21, 2008.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.wired.com/2008/05/the-genetic-inf/|title=Genetic Discrimination by Insurers, Employers Becomes a Crime|work=WIRED|access-date=2018-11-05|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was signed into law by President [[George W. Bush]], and passed in the US Senate by a vote of 49–0 and in the House of Representatives by 414–1.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Feldman EA | title = The Genetic Information Nondiscrimination Act (GINA): public policy and medical practice in the age of personalized medicine | journal = Journal of General Internal Medicine | volume = 27 | issue = 6 | pages = 743–6 | date = June 2012 | pmid = 22314637 | pmc = 3358381 | doi = 10.1007/s11606-012-1988-6 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The legislation bars employers from using individuals' genetic information when making [[Recruitment|hiring]], [[firing]], job placement, or [[Promotion (rank)|promotion]] decisions.&lt;ref name=":3"&gt;[https://www.genome.gov/pages/policyethics/geneticdiscrimination/saponhr493.pdf Statement of Administration policy] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180821041344/https://www.genome.gov/pages/policyethics/geneticdiscrimination/saponhr493.pdf |date=2018-08-21 }}, Executive Office of the President, Office of Management and Budget, 27 April 2007&lt;/ref&gt; GINA also protects individuals from genetic discrimination in healthcare;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Hudson KL, Holohan MK, Collins FS | title = Keeping pace with the times—the Genetic Information Nondiscrimination Act of 2008 | language = EN | journal = The New England Journal of Medicine | volume = 358 | issue = 25 | pages = 2661–3 | date = June 2008 | pmid = 18565857 | doi = 10.1056/nejmp0803964 }}&lt;/ref&gt; however, GINA itself does not define what genetic information is, leaving it up for debate.&lt;ref name=":02"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = McGuire AL, Majumder MA | title = Two cheers for GINA? | language = En | journal = Genome Medicine | volume = 1 | issue = 1 | pages = 6 | date = January 2009 | pmid = 19348693 | pmc = 2651591 | doi = 10.1186/gm6 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Prior to the 2008 GINA Act, individuals could be denied insurance, either partially or fully, based on genetic tests they had received.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Otlowski M, Taylor S, Bombard Y | title = Genetic discrimination: international perspectives | journal = Annual Review of Genomics and Human Genetics | volume = 13 | issue = 1 | pages = 433–54 | date = 2012-09-12 | pmid = 22607273 | doi = 10.1146/annurev-genom-090711-163800 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Although it was passed in 2008 there were 201 cases that cited GINA in 2010 and 333 in 2014. It wasn't until 2013 that a company actually faced penalties under GINA.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Gilbert|first=Natasha | name-list-style = vanc|date=2015-06-25|title=Why the 'devious defecator' case is a landmark for US genetic-privacy law|journal=Nature |doi=10.1038/nature.2015.17857 |s2cid=182253502 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Health insurance discrimination====
In 2008, ''[[The New York Times]]'' reported that some individuals avoid genetic testing out of fear that it will would impede their ability to purchase insurance or find a job. They also reported that evidence of actual discrimination was rare.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2008/02/24/health/24dna.html?_r=2&amp;scp=5&amp;sq=Genetic&amp;st=nyt&amp;oref=slogin&amp;oref=slogin|title=Insurance Fears Lead Many to Shun DNA Tests|last=Harmon|first=Amy | name-list-style = vanc |access-date=2018-11-05 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In November 2016 insurance company GWG Life was found to be collecting saliva samples in order to offer lower rates to people who are epigenetically healthier than others of their age. While this is positive discrimination, this does suggest future potential classification of clients by genetic data.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Dupras C, Song L, Saulnier KM, Joly Y | title = Epigenetic Discrimination: Emerging Applications of Epigenetics Pointing to the Limitations of Policies Against Genetic Discrimination | journal = Frontiers in Genetics | volume = 9 | pages = 202 | date = 2018-06-08 | pmid = 29937773 | pmc = 6002493 | doi = 10.3389/fgene.2018.00202 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

While the 2008 GINA Act does protect against genetic discrimination pertaining to health insurance, it does not protect against genetic discrimination under other forms of insurance, such as life, disability or long-term care insurance. Therefore, patients are enjoying less protection against genetic discrimination in comparison with other peer countries, such as France, Switzerland, Australia and the United Kingdom.&lt;ref name=BélislePipon&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Bélisle-Pipon JC, Vayena E, Green RC, Cohen IG | title = Genetic testing, insurance discrimination and medical research: what the United States can learn from peer countries | journal = Nature Medicine | volume = 25 | issue = 8 | pages = 1198–1204 | date = August 2019 | pmid = 31388181 | doi = 10.1038/s41591-019-0534-z | s2cid = 199448885 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, 2008 GINA offers no protection for home/mortgage insurance or when an employer has 15 or less employees. Excluded from the Act are also parties who are covered under Veterans Health Administration or Indian Health Services.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://ghr.nlm.nih.gov/primer/testing/discrimination|title=What is genetic discrimination? |website=Genetics Home Reference |access-date=2018-11-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Because a variety of medical tests serve as proxies for genetic information, proponents of insurer access to genetic information argue that it does not require specific limiting legislation.&lt;ref name=":02" /&gt; However, this represents an important problem for recruiting participants to medical research according to other scholars stressing that protecting American against discrimination may only happen with the advent of a voluntary moratorium by the insurance industry.&lt;ref name=BélislePipon/&gt;

==== Direct-to-consumer genetic testing ====
Direct-to-consumer genetic testing was first offered in 1997 by [[GeneTree]], a now defunct family history website. These tests are easily accessible on the market and popularized by companies such as [[23andMe]] and [[Ancestry.com]]. These genetic kits are expensive and disproportionately serve wealthy individuals. As a result, when the data collected from testing is sold to research companies, it represents a biased sample of the population.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.cbsnews.com/news/dna-privacy-at-home-tests-23andme-ancestrydna-sell-data-to-third-parties|title=Behind at-home DNA testing companies sharing genetic data with third parties|access-date=2018-11-05|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Food and Drug Administration]] additionally halted all 23andMe marketing in 2013 over unsubstantiated claims 23andMe made regarding disease diagnosis and prevention. The firm was allowed to continue sales after it stopped providing health information to customers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Zettler PJ, Sherkow JS, Greely HT | title = 23andMe, the Food and Drug Administration, and the future of genetic testing | journal = JAMA Internal Medicine | volume = 174 | issue = 4 | pages = 493–4 | date = April 2014 | pmid = 24535082 | doi = 10.1001/jamainternmed.2013.14706 | url = https://digitalcommons.nyls.edu/fac_other_pubs/28 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The shortage of knowledge about and awareness of direct-to-consumer genetic testing is one of the contributors to the limited purchasing of this kind of service.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Charbonneau J, Nicol D, Chalmers D, Kato K, Yamamoto N, Walshe J, Critchley C | title = Public reactions to direct-to-consumer genetic health tests: A comparison across the US, UK, Japan and Australia | journal = European Journal of Human Genetics | pages = 339–348 | date = October 2019 | pmid = 31645768 | doi = 10.1038/s41431-019-0529-8 | volume = 28 | issue = 3 | pmc = 7029038 }}&lt;/ref&gt; As technology has progressed, genetic testing has become a more wide scale practice, potentially affecting the privacy of consumers as a result.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Hoglund-Shen|first=Abigail | name-list-style = vanc |date=July 2017|title=Direct-to-Consumer Genetic Testing, Gamete Donation, and the Law: DTC Genetic Testing, Gamete Donation, and the Law |journal=Family Court Review|language=en|volume=55|issue=3|pages=472–484|doi=10.1111/fcre.12288}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Canada===
The Genetic Non-Discrimination Act received [[Royal Assent]] and became law in Canada on May 4, 2017.&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.parl.ca/DocumentViewer/en/42-1/bill/S-201/royal-assent|title=Public Bill (Senate) S-201 (42–1) – Royal Assent – Genetic Non-Discrimination Act – Parliament of Canada |access-date=2017-05-04|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; Introduced as a [[private member's bill]] S-201 by Nova Scotia senator [[Jim Cowan]], the bill was passed in the Senate and, despite opposition from the Liberal government's [[Cabinet of Canada|Cabinet]] in the House of Commons, it was also passed in the lower house with the support of [[backbencher|backbench]] Liberals and the totality of the [[Conservative Party of Canada|Conservative]], [[New Democratic Party|New Democratic]] and [[Green Party of Canada|Green Party]] caucuses.&lt;ref name="defy backbencher"&gt;{{cite news |last1=Tasker |first1=John Paul |title=Liberal backbenchers defy cabinet wishes and vote to enact genetic discrimination law |url=https://www.cbc.ca/news/politics/genetic-testing-bill-vote-wednesday-1.4015863 |accessdate=10 July 2020 |work=CBC News |date=March 8, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Genetic Non-Discrimination Act introduced amendments to the [[Canadian Human Rights Act]] and [[Canada Labour Code]], and introduced national penalties for entities requiring an individual to undergo genetic testing as a condition for the provision of goods or services, or as a condition for entering or continuing a contract.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt; The Act also forbids anyone from refusing to enter into a goods or services agreement with another person on the grounds that that person has refused to disclose the results of an already completed genetic test. Violations are punishable by fines of up {{CAD}}1 million and/or imprisonment of up to five years. Accordingly, one effect of this legislation will be to prohibit insurance providers from demanding that a prospective client undergo a genetic test—or to disclose an existing test—as a prerequisite to the provision of insurance coverage.

The Genetic Non-Discrimination Act was opposed by the insurance industry and, upon its passage, then-[[Attorney General of Canada|attorney general]] [[Jody Wilson-Raybould]] stated she believed the law may be unconstitutional.&lt;ref name="defy backbencher" /&gt; The [[Supreme Court of Canada]] upheld the law's constitutionality in a 5–4 split ruling on July 10, 2020.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last1=Stefanovich |first1=Olivia |title=Supreme Court of Canada upholds genetic non-discrimination law |url=https://www.cbc.ca/news/politics/stefanovich-supreme-court-of-canada-genetic-information-1.5643245 |accessdate=10 July 2020 |work=CBC News |date=10 July 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== United Kingdom ===
The Equality Act of 2010 prohibits the use of genetic information for employment decisions such as hiring and promotions.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2010/15/contents?view=plain|title=Equality Act 2010|website=www.legislation.gov.uk|language=en|others=Expert Participation|access-date=2018-11-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;  While no formal law exists banning the use of genetic information for insurance policy decisions, the Government of the United Kingdom and the Association of British Insurers voluntarily entered a moratorium from 2014 to 2019 to refrain from using genetic information with regards to insurance.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.abi.org.uk/globalassets/sitecore/files/documents/publications/public/2014/genetics/concordat-and-moratorium-on-genetics-and-insurance.pdf Concordat and Moratorium on Genetics and Insurance].&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Malawi ===
Malawi is the only country in Africa that has emplaced any laws regarding genetic discrimination. Malawi's National Health Sciences Research Committee adopted the policy requirements of the Science and Technology Act No.16 of 2003.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Joly Y, Feze IN, Song L, Knoppers BM | title = Comparative Approaches to Genetic Discrimination: Chasing Shadows? | journal = Trends in Genetics | volume = 33 | issue = 5 | pages = 299–302 | date = May 2017 | pmid = 28365141 | doi = 10.1016/j.tig.2017.02.002 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Australia ===
In Australia, genetic information is less likely to influence health insurance coverage decisions as health insurance is "community rated", meaning that all individuals pay the same amount regardless of their history or genetic makeup.&lt;ref name=":03"&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.nhmrc.gov.au/about-us/publications/genetic-discrimination|title=Genetic discrimination {{!}} NHMRC|website=www.nhmrc.gov.au|access-date=2019-11-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; Since 2008, the amount of insurance applications with attached genetic test results has increased by 90%.&lt;ref name=":5"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Barlow-Stewart K, Liepins M, Doble A, Otlowski M | title = How are genetic test results being used by Australian life insurers? | journal = European Journal of Human Genetics | volume = 26 | issue = 9 | pages = 1248–1256 | date = September 2018 | pmid = 29891881 | pmc = 6117272 | doi = 10.1038/s41431-018-0198-z }}&lt;/ref&gt; Although the community rating allows for a more even distribution of risk and cost to consumers, life insurance companies are legally allowed to “underwrite” when evaluating the genetic risks of applicants; essentially, those with higher risk could potentially be charged higher premiums.&lt;ref name=":5" /&gt; Life insurance companies can require individuals to report genetic testing results if they have already been tested, but cannot force individuals to take genetic tests.&lt;ref name=":22"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Tiller J, Otlowski M, Lacaze P | title = Should Australia Ban the Use of Genetic Test Results in Life Insurance? | journal = Frontiers in Public Health | volume = 5 | pages = 330 | date = 2017-12-13 | pmid = 29322039 | pmc = 5733354 | doi = 10.3389/fpubh.2017.00330 }}&lt;/ref&gt; These companies are able to require individuals to disclose genetic testing results from research and direct-to-consumer tests.&lt;ref name=":22" /&gt;

=== Argentina ===
Genetic discrimination is a rising issue in Argentina.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Valdovinos|first=Carlos Fernandez | name-list-style = vanc |date=2005-11-01|title=Growth, inequality, and social equity in Argentina|url=http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/895241468201589540/Growth-inequality-and-social-equity-in-Argentina|language=en|pages=1–4}}&lt;/ref&gt; Health plans discriminate against those who have disabilities or who have genetic conditions.&lt;ref name=":32"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Penchaszadeh VB | title = Ethical issues in genetics and public health in Latin America with a focus on Argentina | journal = Journal of Community Genetics | volume = 6 | issue = 3 | pages = 223–30 | date = July 2015 | pmid = 25666434 | pmc = 4524838 | doi = 10.1007/s12687-015-0217-5 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In the past decade, however, National Law 26689 was  passed providing patients with the right to not experience discrimination as a result of genetic conditions.&lt;ref name=":32" /&gt;

==Genetic testing in the workplace==

Some people have genes that make them more susceptible to developing a disease as a result of an occupational exposure. For example, workers with beryllium sensitivity and [[Berylliosis|chronic beryllium disease]] are more likely to carry the gene [[HLA-DPB1]] than workers without these conditions.&lt;ref name=":2"&gt;Department for Health and Human Services (2009). ''Genetics in the Workplace: Implications for Occupational Safety and Health''. Washington, D.C.: DHHS.&lt;/ref&gt; By offering optional genetic testing to workers and allowing only the workers to see their own results, employers could protect genetically susceptible individuals from certain occupational diseases. A beryllium manufacturing company initiated a pilot program to test prospective workers for the HLA-DPB1 gene at a university-based laboratory. The company paid for the testing and counseling but received results that did not identify which workers had the gene.&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt;

In 1991, the American Medical Association Council on Ethical and Judicial Affairs suggested that the following five conditions must be satisfied in order for genetic screening by an employer to be appropriate:&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt;

* The disease must develop so rapidly that monitoring would be ineffective in preventing it.
* The genetic test is highly accurate.
* The genetic variation results in an unusually elevated susceptibility to occupational illness.
* Undue expense is needed to protect susceptible workers by lowering the level of the toxic substance in the workplace.
* The worker must provide informed consent prior to being tested.

Several occupational health screening measures similar to genetic testing are already taking place. For example, in 1978, DuPont reported testing African American applicants for sickle cell trait and restricted these workers from exposure to nitro and amino compounds.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Brandt-Rauf PW, Brandt-Rauf SI | title = Genetic testing in the workplace: ethical, legal, and social implications | journal = Annual Review of Public Health | volume = 25 | pages = 139–53 | date = 2004 | pmid = 15015916 | doi = 10.1146/annurev.publhealth.25.101802.123012 | doi-access=free }}&lt;/ref&gt; However, research indicates that workers or applicants would not take advantage of genetic testing due to fear of discrimination. A 1995 poll of the general public found that over 85% are concerned about access to use of genetic information by insurers and employers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Miller PS | title = Genetic discrimination in the workplace | journal = Genetics in Medicine | volume = 3 | issue = 3 | pages = 165–6 | date = June 2001 | pmid = 11388754 | doi = 10.1097/00125817-200105000-00001 | url = https://zenodo.org/record/1230728 | doi-access = free }}&lt;/ref&gt; Likewise, in the case of the beryllium manufacturer described above, so few workers participated in the genetic testing that the company decided instead to pursue an "enhanced preventive model of workplace controls."&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt;

== Race and genetics ==
{{main|Race and genetics}}

State governments in the United States have attempted to combat racial discrimination by barring instances of discrimination by insurers that involve linking specific genetic conditions to race, such as the sickle cell trait in African Americans.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Diver|first1=Colin S.|last2=Cohen|first2=Jane Maslow | name-list-style = vanc |date= May 2001 |title=Genophobia: What Is Wrong with Genetic Discrimination?|jstor = 3312965 |journal=University of Pennsylvania Law Review|volume=149|issue=5|pages=1439–82|doi=10.2307/3312965|pmid=12741378|url=https://scholarship.law.upenn.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3315&amp;context=penn_law_review}}&lt;/ref&gt;

While there exists statistical evidence of genetic differences between human populations—such as mutations within the Duffy blood group&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Barbujani G, Magagni A, Minch E, Cavalli-Sforza LL | title = An apportionment of human DNA diversity | journal = Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America | volume = 94 | issue = 9 | pages = 4516–9 | date = April 1997 | pmid = 9114021 | pmc = 20754 | doi = 10.1073/pnas.94.9.4516 }}&lt;/ref&gt;—research done by geneticist Guido Barujani, looking at 109 genetic markers across 16 populations, "does not suggest that the racial subdivision of our species reflects any major discontinuity in our genome".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = McManus KF, Taravella AM, Henn BM, Bustamante CD, Sikora M, Cornejo OE | title = Population genetic analysis of the DARC locus (Duffy) reveals adaptation from standing variation associated with malaria resistance in humans | journal = PLOS Genetics | volume = 13 | issue = 3 | pages = e1006560 | date = March 2017 | pmid = 28282382 | pmc = 5365118 | doi = 10.1371/journal.pgen.1006560 | editor-first = Hopi E. | editor-last = Hoekstra }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Popular culture==

According to Jonathan Roberts and his colleagues, the media evokes irrational fear among the public about advances in genetic techniques.&lt;ref name=":6"&gt;{{cite journal | vauthors = Roberts J, Archer L, DeWitt J, Middleton A | title = Popular culture and genetics; friend, foe or something more complex? | journal = European Journal of Medical Genetics | volume = 62 | issue = 5 | pages = 368–375 | date = May 2019 | pmid = 30590173 | pmc = 6626485 | doi = 10.1016/j.ejmg.2018.12.005 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In a recent study, participants who were prompted to convey their attitudes about unfamiliar scientific concepts relating to genetics ultimately drew conclusions based on examples from popular culture.&lt;ref name=":6" /&gt;

''Genoism'' is a [[neologism]] coined by [[Andrew Niccol]], director and writer of the 1997 film ''[[Gattaca]]'', used to describe unethical and illegal genetic discrimination. Predictions of physical and mental performance are computed via [[genetics]] from [[DNA]] collected from hair, fingernails, skin flakes, spit swabs, eyelashes, etc.  Upon birth, a number of genetically-induced characteristics are calculated: physical and intellectual capacity, life expectancy, probable successful diseases, and likely causes of death, all determined via [[blood sample]]s and [[genetic testing]]. Job interviews, health insurance purchasing, and even potential dates can be sized up according to the perceived quality of the person's DNA due to advancements in [[genome sequencing]].  This put an ironic twist to [[Charles Darwin|Darwin]]'s [[sexual selection]] for good [[genes]]. According to the movie, "We now have discrimination down to a [[science]]."

{{quote|My father was right. It didn't matter how much I lied on my resume. My real resume was in my cells. Why should anybody invest all that money to train me when there were a thousand other applicants with a far cleaner profile? Of course, it's illegal to discriminate, 'genoism' it's called. But no one takes the law seriously. If you refuse to disclose, they can always take a sample from a door handle or a handshake, even the saliva on your application form. If in doubt, a legal [[drug test]] can just as easily become an illegal peek at your future in the company.|Vincent Freeman ([[Ethan Hawke]])|''[[Gattaca]]'', 1997}}

== See also ==
*[[Dysgenics]]
*''[[Gattaca]]'', the most notable film about genetic discrimination
*[[Genetic privacy]]
*[[Human Genome Project]]
*[[Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act]]
*[[Genetic Information Nondiscrimination Act]]
*[[Genetic Discrimination Observatory]]

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
* http://www.genome.gov/10002328
* {{cite news | title= US Blocks Genetic Discrimination | work= [[BBC News]] | authorlink=BBC News | date=25 April 2008 | url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/americas/7366264.stm | access-date=2010-01-04}}
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20160307050955/http://respondgeneticdiscrimination.com/ Respond Genetic Discrimination]

{{Discrimination}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Genetic Discrimination}}
[[Category:Human genetics]]
[[Category:Medical ethics]]
[[Category:Discrimination]]
[[Category:Science fiction themes]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>