<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20141009000356|628858057" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="335104" pageid="335104" ns="0" title="Human Rights Campaign"><revisions><rev timestamp="2014-11-03T19:59:01Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{hatnote|For other uses, please see [[HRC (disambiguation)]].}}
{{Infobox Organization
|name         = Human Rights Campaign
|image        = Hrc logo.svg
|image_border =
|size         =
|caption      = Official Human Rights Campaign logo
|motto        = Working for Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual and Transgender Equal Rights
|formation    = 1980
|type         =
|headquarters =
|location     = [[Washington, D.C.]]
|membership   =
|language     =
|leader_title = President
|leader_name  = [[Chad Griffin]]
|key_people   =
|num_staff    =
|budget       =
|website      = [http://www.hrc.org HRC.org]
}}
The '''Human Rights Campaign''' ('''HRC''') is the largest [[LGBT]] civil rights [[advocacy group]] and political [[lobbying]] organization in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://articles.cnn.com/2007-08-10/politics/gay.forum_1_lesbian-couples-gay-issues-human-rights-campaign-foundation?_s=PM:POLITICS|title=Democratic hopefuls pressed on gay issues at forum – CNN|date=August 10, 2007|work=[[CNN]]|accessdate=February 24, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to the HRC, it has more than 1.5 million members and supporters.&lt;ref name=wwd&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hrc.org/the-hrc-story/about-us|title= The HRC Story|publisher=Human Rights Campaign|accessdate=November 1, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Structure==
HRC is an umbrella group of two separate [[non-profit organization]]s and a [[political action committee]]: the HRC Foundation, a [[501(c)|501(c)(3)]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=HRC Foundation|url=http://www.hrc.org/the-hrc-story/hrc-foundation|work=hrc.org|publisher=Human Rights Campaign|accessdate=August 24, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; organization that focuses on research, advocacy and education; the Human Rights Campaign, a [[501(c)|501(c)(4)]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Frequently Asked Questions|url=http://www.hrc.org/support/frequently-asked-questions|work=hrc.org|publisher=Human Rights Campaign|accessdate=August 24, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; organization that focuses on promoting the social welfare of [[lesbian]], [[gay]], [[bisexual]], and [[transgender]] (LGBT) people through lobbying Congress and state and local officials for support of pro-LGBT bills, and mobilizing grassroots action amongst its members; and the HRC [[Political Action Committee]], which supports candidates that adhere to its positions on [[LGBT rights]].&lt;ref name=structure&gt;{{cite web|title=Human Rights Campaign Foundation|url=http://www.guidestar.org/PartnerReport.aspx?partner=justgivews&amp;ein=52-1481896|work=guidestar.org|publisher=[[GuideStar]]|accessdate=August 24, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=mission&gt;{{cite web|title=Mission Statement|url=http://www.hrc.org/the-hrc-story/mission-statement|work=hrc.org|publisher=Human Rights Campaign|accessdate=August 24, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Local activities are carried out by local steering committees, of which there are over 30 located throughout the United States.&lt;ref name=steeringcommittee&gt;{{cite web|title=What is a Steering Committee?|url=http://www.hrc.org/blog/entry/what-is-a-steering-committee|work=hrc.org|publisher=Human Rights Campaign|accessdate=August 24, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Leadership===
The Human Rights Campaign's leadership includes President [[Chad Griffin]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Harmon|first=Andrew|title=Chad Griffin Named President of HRC|url=http://www.advocate.com/News/Daily_News/2012/03/02/Chad_Griffin_Named_President_of_HRC/|accessdate=March 2, 2012|newspaper=[[The Advocate]]|date=March 2, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; HRC's work is supported by three boards: the Board of Directors, which is the governing body for the organization; the HRC Foundation Board, which manages the foundation's finances and establishes official policies governing the foundation; and the Board of Governors, which manages the organization's local outreach nationwide. All three boards comprise volunteers from across the country.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The HRC Story: Boards|url=http://www.hrc.org/the-hrc-story/boards|work=hrc.org|publisher=Human Rights Campaign|accessdate=August 24, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Programs==
The Human Rights Campaign's priorities include: prevention of [[hate crime]]s and [[HIV|HIV/AIDS]]; advocacy for healthcare benefits, [[same-sex marriage|marriage]], and adoption rights for same-sex couples; lobbying for a federal [[Employment Non-Discrimination Act]] (ENDA) and [[gender identity]] anti-discrimination laws; combating [[anti-gay bullying|gay bashing]] in schools; and building relationships with [[Straight ally|straight allies]], ethnic groups, religious leaders, and youth.&lt;ref name=issues&gt;{{cite web|title=Issues: Human Rights Campaign|url=http://www.hrc.org/issues|publisher=Human Rights Campaign|accessdate=February 21, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The HRC Foundation provides educational resources and publications on [[coming out]], transgender issues, LGBT-related healthcare topics and information about workplace issues faced by LGBT people, notably the [[Corporate Equality Index]]. It also maintains resources on LGBT parenting, religion and faith issues, immigration, and outreach for youth.&lt;ref name="Human Rights Campaign Foundation"&gt;[http://www.hrc.org/resources Resources]&lt;/ref&gt;

The HRC Foundation's Coming Out Project provides information to people who are in the process of coming out.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hrc.org/resources/category/coming-out Resources: Coming Out]&lt;/ref&gt;

HRC lobbies for anti-discrimination, hate crimes laws, and worked on the passage of the [[Matthew Shepard Act|Matthew Shepard and James Byrd, Jr. Hate Crimes Prevention Act]], which expanded federal hate-crime law to allow the [[United States Department of Justice|Justice Department]] to investigate and prosecute crimes motivated by a victim's actual or perceived gender, [[sexual orientation]], gender identity, or disability.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hrc.org/sites/loveconquershate/about.asp HRC: Matthew Shepard Act]&lt;/ref&gt; Referring to the law as a "historic milestone", former HRC President [[Joe Solmonese]] said its passage represents "the first time that we as a nation have explicitly protected the LGBT community in the law."&lt;ref name="President Barack Obama Signs Hate Crimes Legislation Into Law"&gt;[http://www.hrc.org/press-releases/entry/president-barack-obama-signs-hate-crimes-legislation-into-law President Barack Obama Signs Hate Crimes Legislation Into Law]&lt;/ref&gt;

The organization's work on health issues traditionally focused on responding to the HIV/AIDS epidemic. In recent years, HRC has addressed discrimination in health care settings for LGBT employees, patients and their families. Since 2007, the Human Rights Campaign Foundation has published the "Healthcare Equality Index", which rates hospitals on issues such as patient and employee non-discrimination policies, employee [[cultural competence|cultural competency]] training, and hospital visitation rights for LGBT patients' families.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hrc.org/resources/entry/healthcare-equality-index-2011 Resources: Healthcare Equality Index]&lt;/ref&gt; As of 2013, the medical center at the University of California at San Francisco is the only institution in the United States to achieve perfect scores on the index.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |publisher=Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality |url=https://innovations.ahrq.gov/profiles/inclusive-policies-communication-protocols-and-ongoing-training-lead-culturally-competent |title=Inclusive Policies, Communication Protocols and Ongoing Training Lead to Culturally Competent Care for Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, and Transgender Patients |date=2013-09-11 |accessdate=2013-09-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; Lobbyists from the Human Rights Campaign worked with the [[Presidency of Barack Obama|Obama administration]] to extend hospital visitation rights to same-sex partners.&lt;ref name="Obama extends hospital visitation rights to same-sex partners of gays"&gt;{{cite news | url = http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2010/04/15/AR2010041505502.html | work=The Washington Post | first=Michael D. | last=Shear | title=Obama extends hospital visitation rights to same-sex partners of gays | date=April 16, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2012, HRC announced the formation of its wide-ranging Health &amp; Aging Program, which addresses both the health concerns of all LGBT Americans and the particular challenges faced by LGBT elders, including discrimination, mistreatment and isolation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hrc.org/press-releases/entry/human-rights-campaign-foundation-expands-the-net-of-lgbt-healthcare-equalit|title=Human Rights Campaign Foundation Expands the Net of LGBT Healthcare Equality|date=September 12, 2012|accessdate=March 8, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

HRC lobbied extensively for the repeal of the [[Don't Ask Don't Tell]] (DADT) law, which barred gay and lesbian people from serving openly in the United States military. [[Eric Alva]], a gay Marine who was the first American wounded in [[Iraq War|combat in Iraq]], has since been a spokesman on behalf of the Human Rights Campaign's efforts to repeal the law, and was invited to stand behind President [[Barack Obama]] at the signing ceremony.&lt;ref name="Obama signs DADT repeal before big, emotional crowd"&gt;{{cite news | url = http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2010/12/22/AR2010122201888.html | work=The Washington Post | first1=William | last1=Branigin | first2=Debbi | last2=Wilgoren | first3=Perry | last3=Bacon Jr | title=Obama signs DADT repeal before big, emotional crowd | date=December 22, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Annual indexes===
* [http://www.hrc.org/cei Corporate Equality Index] (since 2001)
* [http://www.hrc.org/hei Healthcare Equality Index] (since 2007)
* [http://www.hrc.org/mei Municipal Equality Index] (since 2012)

==History==
[[Image:Human Right Campaign headquarters.JPG|thumb|Human Rights Campaign headquarters in [[Washington, D.C.]]]]
[[Steve Endean]], who had worked with a previously established [[Gay Rights National Lobby]] from 1978, established the Human Rights Campaign Fund [[political action committee]] in 1980 to raise money for gay-supportive congressional candidates. In 1983, [[Vic Basile]], at the time one of the leading LGBT rights activists in Washington, D.C., was elected as the first executive director. In October 1986, the HRC Foundation (HRCF) was formed as a non-profit organization.&lt;ref name=Bailey-history /&gt;

In January 1989, Basile announced his departure, and HRC reorganized from serving mainly as a political action committee (PAC) to broadening its function to encompass lobbying, research, education, and media outreach.&lt;ref name=HRCJournal-history&gt;{{cite journal|last=Birch|first=Elizabeth|title=The Human Rights Campaign: So Much More Than a Fund.|year=HRC Quarterly (Fall 1995)|publisher=Human Rights Campaign|pages=2–3|url=http://www.glbtq.com/social-sciences/human_rights_campaign.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; HRC decided on a new Statement of Purpose:
{{cquote|For the promotion of the social welfare of the gay and lesbian community by drafting, supporting and influencing legislation and policy at the federal, state and local level.}}
[[Tim McFeeley]], a [[Harvard Law School]] graduate, founder of the Boston Lesbian and Gay Political Alliance, and a co-chair of the [[New England]] HRC Committee, was elected the new executive director. Total membership was then approximately 25,000 members.&lt;ref name=Bailey-history&gt;{{cite book|last=Bailey|first=Mark|title="Human Rights Campaign." Gay Histories and Cultures|year=2000|publisher=Garland|location=New York|url=http://www.glbtq.com/social-sciences/human_rights_campaign.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1992, HRC endorsed a presidential candidate for the first time, [[Bill Clinton]]. In March 1993, HRC began a new project, [[National Coming Out Day]]. From January 1995 until January 2004, [[Elizabeth Birch]] served as the executive director of the HRC. Under her leadership, the institution more than quadrupled its membership to 500,000 members.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Althafer|first=Emily|title=Leading gay rights advocate to speak at UF|url=http://news.ufl.edu/2006/01/23/human-rights-talk/|publisher=University of Florida News: source: Adelisse Fontanet, xxx-1665 ext. 326|accessdate=February 22, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1995, the organization dropped the word "Fund" from its name, becoming the Human Rights Campaign. That same year, it underwent a complete reorganization. The HRC Foundation added new programs such as the Workplace Project and the Family Project, while HRC itself broadly expanded its research, communications, and marketing/public relations functions. The organization also unveiled a new [[logo]], a yellow equal sign inside of a blue square, which has become one of the most recognizable symbols in the [[LGBT]] community.&lt;ref name="HRC Logo"&gt;{{cite web|title=The HRC Story: About Our Logo|url=http://www.hrc.org/the-hrc-story/about-our-logo|publisher=Human Rights Campaign|accessdate=February 22, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2002, HRC purchased a headquarters building in [[Washington, D.C]]. The building, located at 1640 Rhode Island Avenue, was previously the headquarters for [[B'nai B'rith]] International. The organization renovated the building and moved in 2003.&lt;ref name="The HRC Story: Our Building"&gt;{{cite web|title=The HRC Story: Our Building|url=http://www.hrc.org/the-hrc-story/our-building|publisher=Human Rights Campaign|accessdate=May 23, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:ChicagoGayPride2005 1.jpg|thumb|The Human Rights Campaign often has a large presence at LGBT-related events such as the [[Chicago Pride Parade]] as seen above.]]
As part of the activities surrounding the [[Millennium March on Washington]], the HRC Foundation sponsored a fundraising concert at Washington, D.C.'s [[Robert F. Kennedy Memorial Stadium|RFK Stadium]] on April 29, 2000. Billed as a concert to end hate crimes, "Equality Rocks" honored hate crime victims and their families, such as featured speakers Dennis and [[Judy Shepard]], the parents of [[Matthew Shepard]]. More than 45,000 people&lt;ref name="concert-hate crimes"&gt;{{cite web|title=Resources: Hate Crimes Timeline|url=http://www.hrc.org/resources/entry/hate-crimes-timeline#2000|publisher=Human Rights Campaign|accessdate=February 22, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; attended the event, which included [[Melissa Etheridge]], [[Garth Brooks]], [[Pet Shop Boys]], [[k.d. lang]], [[Nathan Lane]], [[Rufus Wainwright]], [[Albita Rodríguez]], and [[Chaka Khan]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=More Artists Added to Equality Rocks:  Michael Feinstein, Chaka Khan, Kathy Najimy and Rufus Wainwright Join Garth Brooks, Ellen DeGeneres, Melissa Etheridge, Anne Heche, Kristen Johnston, kd lang, Nathan Lane and Pet Shop Boys To Benefit the Human Rights Campaign Foundation|url=http://www.nyrock.com/worldbeat/04_2000/041200a.asp|publisher=nyrock.com World Beat|accessdate=February 22, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Elizabeth Birch's successor, [[Cheryl Jacques]], resigned in November 2004 after only 11 months as executive director. In a statement released by HRC, Jacques said she had resigned over "a difference in management philosophy".&lt;ref name="Jacques Press Release"&gt;{{cite web|title=Cheryl Jacques to Leave Human Rights Campaign: HRC Boards Put Transition Plan in Place|url=http://www.hrc.org/press-releases/entry/cheryl-jacques-to-leave-human-rights-campaign|publisher=Human Rights Campaign|accessdate=February 22, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In March 2005, HRC announced the appointment of Joe Solmonese as the president, describing him as having an "unrivaled track record at the nation's foremost progressive electoral powerhouse" and appealing to "Americans across the political and ideological spectrum".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Joe Solmonese Named Human Rights Campaign President: Leader with Unmatched Record to Embark on Heartland Tour during First Week on Job|url=http://www.hrc.org/press-releases/entry/joe-solmonese-named-human-rights-campaign-president|accessdate=February 22, 2012|newspaper=Human Rights Campaign|date=March 9, 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;

HRC launched its Religion and Faith Program in 2005 to mobilize clergy to advocate for LGBT people, and helped form DC Clergy United for Marriage Equality, which was involved in the legalization of [[same-sex marriage in the District of Columbia]].&lt;ref name="Fenty to sign same-sex marriage bill at church in NW D.C."&gt;{{cite news | url = http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2009/12/17/AR2009121704330.html | work=The Washington Post | first=Nikita | last=Stewart | title=Fenty to sign same-sex marriage bill at church in NW D.C | date=December 18, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; On March 10, 2010, the first legally recognized same-sex weddings in the [[District of Columbia]] were held at the headquarters of the Human Rights Campaign.&lt;ref name="First gay marriages in District performed"&gt;{{cite news | url = http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2010/03/09/AR2010030901904.html | work=The Washington Post | first1=Ann E. | last1=Marimow | first2=Keith L. | last2=Alexander | title=First gay marriages in District performed | date=March 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On August 9, 2007, HRC and [[Logo (TV channel)|Logo TV]] co-hosted a forum for 2008 Democratic presidential candidates dedicated specifically to LGBT issues.&lt;ref name="Dems Court the Gay Vote"&gt;[http://abcnews.go.com/GMA/Story?id=3466074&amp;page=1 Dems Court the Gay Vote]&lt;/ref&gt;

HRC spent over $7 million in its "Year to Win" campaign during the [[United States elections, 2008|2008 elections]], the largest electoral campaign in its history to date.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hrc.org/the-hrc-story/our-victories Our victo: Year to Win]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="2008 election"&gt;{{cite web|title=Our Victories (Election Heavyweights section)|url=http://www.hrc.org/the-hrc-story/our-victories|publisher=Human Rights Campaign|accessdate=February 22, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2010, HRC lobbied for the repeal of the United States' ban on [[HIV-positive]] people's entry into the country for travel or immigration, stating the need to "combat the stigma and ignorance that still too often guides public policy debates around HIV/AIDS".&lt;ref name="Ban Lifted"&gt;{{cite web|title=After 22 Years, HIV Travel and Immigration Ban Lifted|url=http://www.hrc.org/press-releases/entry/after-22-years-hiv-travel-and-immigration-ban-lifted|publisher=Human Rights Campaign|accessdate=February 22, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="After 22 years, HIV travel and immigration ban lifted"&gt;[http://miamiherald.typepad.com/gaysouthflorida/2010/01/hrc-after-22-years-hiv-travel-and-immigration-ban-lifted.html#ixzz0sxMtcovD Miami Herald: After 22 years, HIV travel and immigration ban lifted]&lt;/ref&gt;

In September 2011, it was announced that Solmonese would step down from the presidency following the end of his contract in 2012.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://metroweekly.com/poliglot/2011/08/hrcs-solmonese-to-step-down.html|title = HRC's Solmonese to Step Down, Sources Say No Replacement Has Been Selected|author = Chris Geidner |date = August 27, 2011&lt;!-- 3:20 AM--&gt;|publisher = Metro Weekly}}&lt;/ref&gt; Despite initial speculation that former Atlanta City Council president [[Cathy Woolard]] would be appointed, no replacement was announced until March 2, 2012, when [[American Foundation for Equal Rights]] co-founder [[Chad Griffin]] was announced as Solmonese's successor. Griffin took office on June 11, 2012.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://www.advocate.com/News/Daily_News/2012/03/02/Chad_Griffin_Named_President_of_HRC/|title = Chad Griffin Named President of HRC|date = March 2, 2012&lt;!-- 10:59:03&amp;nbsp;am ET--&gt;|author = Andrew Harmon|publisher = The Advocate}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2012, HRC executed its largest mobilization effort ever, raising and contributing $20 million to re-elect President Obama and to advance marriage equality and other electoral priorities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=HRC 2012: Unprecedented Mobilization for Equality|url=http://www.hrc.org/election|accessdate=March 8, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; A day after the election, The Washington Post highlighted HRC's key role in marriage-related victories in Washington, Maine, Maryland and Minnesota, the election of Tammy Baldwin, Obama's re-election and more.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Gay rights advocates welcome Election Day results for a change|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/decision2012/gay-rights-advocates-welcome-election-day-results-for-a-change/2012/11/07/66c48ab6-28a5-11e2-bab2-eda299503684_story.html|publisher=The Washington Post|accessdate=March 8, 2013|first=Ned|last=Martel|date=November 8, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2013, HRC conducted a postcard campaign in support of the Employment Non-Discrimination Act (ENDA).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Eilperin|first1=Juliet|title=Cindy McCain petitions husband to back gay rights bill|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/post-politics/wp/2013/10/25/cindy-mccain-petitions-husband-to-back-gay-rights-bill/|publisher=The Washington Post|accessdate=3 November 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Alaska Senator [[Lisa Murkowski]] credited the campaign for her vote in favor of ENDA.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=GOP Sen. Murkowski Credits HRC Postcard Campaign for her Pro-ENDA Vote|url=http://www.hrc.org/blog/entry/gop-sen.-murkowski-credits-hrc-postcard-campaign-for-her-pro-enda-vote|accessdate=3 November 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Annual fundraisers===
Each year since 1997, HRC has hosted a national dinner that features high-profile speakers and serves as the organization's single largest annual fundraiser. In 2009, President [[Barack Obama]] addressed a crowd of approximately 3,000 guests&lt;ref name="dinner guests"&gt;{{cite web|title=Program Book|url=http://www.hrcnationaldinner.org/programbook/|publisher=HRCNationalDinner.org|accessdate=February 22, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; at HRC's 13th Annual National Dinner. In his speech, President Obama reaffirmed his pledge to repeal "Don't Ask, Don't Tell" and the [[Defense of Marriage Act]] (DOMA), as well as his commitment to passing the Employment Non-Discrimination Act.&lt;ref name="Huffington Post – Obama HRC Speech"&gt;[http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2009/10/10/obama-says-he-will-end-do_n_316524.html Huffington Post – Obama HRC Speech]&lt;/ref&gt; He gave the keynote speech in 2011 as well, reiterating his pledge to fight for DOMA repeal and for the passage of ENDA, and to combat bullying of LGBT youth. Other featured speakers at past dinners have included [[Bill Clinton]], [[Maya Angelou]], [[Kweisi Mfume]], [[Joseph Lieberman]], [[Hillary Clinton]], [[Richard Gephardt]], [[John Lewis (U.S. politician)|John Lewis]], [[Rosie O'Donnell]], [[Nancy Pelosi]], [[Tim Gunn]], [[Suze Orman]], [[Sally Field]], [[Cory Booker]], [[Tammy Baldwin]], and [[Betty DeGeneres]].&lt;ref name="previous dinners"&gt;{{cite web|title=About the Dinner: Previous Dinners|url=http://www.hrcnationaldinner.org/about/|publisher=hrcnationaldinner.org|accessdate=February 22, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===HRC historical records===
The historical records of the Human Rights Campaign are maintained in a collection at the [[Cornell University Library]]. Arriving at Cornell in 2004, the records include [[strategic planning]] documents, faxes, minutes, e-mails, press releases, posters, and campaign buttons. Taking up {{convert|84|cuft|m3}}, the archive is the second largest in the library's Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Human Sexuality Collection. In February 2007, the archive was opened to scholars at the library, and selected records were organized into an online exhibit called "25 Years of Political Influence: The Records of the Human Rights Campaign".&lt;ref&gt;Lowery, George. (January 30, 2007) [http://www.news.cornell.edu/stories/Jan07/humanrightsrecords.gl.html 25 years of gay-rights struggles traced in online exhibit] ''[[The Cornell Chronicle]]'' of [[Cornell University]]. Retrieved July 29, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Cornell University Library]]. [http://rmc.library.cornell.edu/HRC/index.html 25 Years of Political Influence:The Records of the Human Rights Campaign] [[Cornell University]]. Retrieved July 29, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Awards==
The Human Rights Campaign maintains a number of awards for individuals distinguished for their LGBT-related work. In addition to awards from the national organization, local chapters also award their own versions of the awards. These awards are typically presented at national and local chapters' annual dinner galas.

===Visibility Award winners===
* [[Greg Rikaart]] (2014, National)
* [[The Wachowskis|Lana Wachowski]] (2012, San Francisco)
* [[Lee Daniels]] (2010, National)

===Ally for Equality Award winners===
* [[Jennifer Lopez]] (2014, National), 
* [[Sally Field]] (2012, National), [[Jennifer Beals]] (2012, Chicago)
* [[Michael Bloomberg]] (2011, National)
* [[P!nk]] (2010)

===Equality Award===
* [[NAACP]] and its president, [[Ben Jealous]] (2012, National)
* [[Suze Orman]] (2008, National)

===HRC Legacy Award===
* [[Terry Bean]] (2008, National)

===HRC Award for Workplace Equality Innovation===
* [[Boston Consulting Group]] and [[Goldman Sachs]] (2011, National)
* [[Kimpton Hotels &amp; Restaurants]] and [[Credit Suisse]] (2010)
* [[Kirkland &amp; Ellis LLP]] and [[Boeing]] (2009, National)

==Logo==
The official logo of the HRC, adopted in 1995, consists of a yellow [[equals sign]] imposed onto a blue background. The logo was created in 1995 by design firm Stone Yamashita, who attracted then-Executive Director Elizabeth Birch to its bold design.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://www.hrc.org/the-hrc-story/about-our-logo|title = About Our Logo|publisher = Human Rights Campaign}}&lt;/ref&gt; The previous logo used by the HRC (then known as the HRCF) featured a stylized flaming torch.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://rmc.library.cornell.edu/HRC/exhibition/images/570pxw/REX023_091.jpg|title = Old HRCF logo on lapel|publisher = Cornell University}}&lt;/ref&gt; HRC uses the term ''Equality Flag'' for flags bearing their logo.&lt;ref&gt;[http://shop.hrc.org/hrc-equality-flag.html/ HRC Store page selling ''Equality Flag'']&lt;/ref&gt;

===Marriage equality logo===
[[File:Hrc logo red.svg|thumb|right|The HRC equal sign logo reworked in red to show particular support for [[same-sex marriage]].]] HRC shared a red version of its logo – selected because the color is synonymous with love – on [[social network service]]s on March 25, 2013, and asked its supporters to do the same to show support for marriage equality in light of two marriage equality cases that were before the [[Supreme Court of the United States|U.S. Supreme Court]] (''[[United States v. Windsor]]'' and ''[[Hollingsworth v. Perry]]''). The logo went viral, and [[Facebook]] saw a 120% increase in the number of profile photo changes on March 26. Celebrities such as [[George Takei]], [[Beyoncé Knowles|Beyonce]], [[Sophia Bush]], [[Padma Lakshmi]], [[Martha Stewart]] and [[Ellen DeGeneres]] shared the logo with their millions of followers on social network services and U.S. senators, state governors and other elected officials did the same.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Thielman|first=Sam|title=DOMA Nation: The Human Rights Campaign had no idea this was going to happen|url=http://www.adweek.com/news/advertising-branding/doma-nation-148206|accessdate=June 9, 2013|newspaper=[[Adweek]]|date=March 28, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As the logo's popularity took off, countless [[meme]]s were created. Highly recognized brands and [[corporation]]s showed their support for marriage equality with creative recreations of the red HRC logo. Supporters included [[Bud Light]], [[Bonobos]], [[Fab.com]], [[Kenneth Cole Productions|Kenneth Cole]], [[L'Occitane en Provence]], [[Maybelline]], [[Absolut]], [[Marc Jacobs International]], [[Smirnoff]], [[Martha Stewart Weddings]], and [[HBO]]'s ''[[True Blood]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Brettman|first=Allan|title=From Nike to marriage equality, controversy can be a good thing|url=http://www.oregonlive.com/playbooks-profits/index.ssf/2013/03/from_nike_to_marriage_equality.html|accessdate=June 9, 2013|newspaper=[[The Oregonian]]|date=March 30, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Major print and online news sources reported on the success of the viral campaign, including [[MSNBC]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Maresca|first=Cara|title=Seeing red: Symbol for marriage equality goes viral|url=http://tv.msnbc.com/2013/03/26/seeing-red-human-rights-campaigns-marriage-equality-logo-goes-viral|publisher=MSNBC|accessdate=April 18, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Time (magazine)|Time]]'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Yang|first=Mackenzie|title=What Is the Red Equal Sign All Over Facebook and Twitter?|url=http://newsfeed.time.com/2013/03/26/what-is-the-red-equal-sign-all-over-facebook-and-twitter/|accessdate=April 18, 2013|work=Time|date=March 26, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Mashable]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Fox|first=Zoe|title=Facebook Turns Red as SCOTUS Marriage Equality Hearings Begin|url=http://mashable.com/2013/03/26/facebook-red-marriage-equality/|accessdate=April 18, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; and ''The Wall Street Journal''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Neal|first=Mann|title=Gay-Marriage Symbol Goes Viral|url=http://blogs.wsj.com/washwire/2013/03/26/gay-marriage-symbol-goes-viral/?mod=e2tw|publisher=The Wall Street Journal|accessdate=April 18, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Executive Directors / Presidents==
The following people have led the Human Rights Campaign:

'''Executive Directors'''
# [[Vic Basile]] (1983&amp;ndash;1989)
# [[Tim McFeeley]] (1989&amp;ndash;1995)
# [[Elizabeth Birch]] (1995&amp;ndash;2004)

'''Presidents'''
# [[Cheryl Jacques]] (2004&amp;ndash;2005)
# [[Joe Solmonese]] (2005&amp;ndash;2012)
# [[Chad Griffin]] (2012&amp;ndash; )

==Criticism==
Critics of the HRC have accused the organization of favoring the Democratic Party. [[Andrew Sullivan]], a conservative gay political columnist and blogger, has been critical of the HRC, calling it "a patronage wing of the Democratic party".&lt;ref&gt;Sullivan, Andrew. (February 19, 2007) [http://andrewsullivan.theatlantic.com/the_daily_dish/2007/02/the_human_right.html The Human Rights Campaign (Blech)] ''[[The Atlantic Monthly]]''. Retrieved July 29, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Sullivan, Andrew. "My Alliance with the Christianists" [http://andrewsullivan.theatlantic.com/the_daily_dish/2007/03/my_alliance_wit.html Theatlantic.com]&lt;/ref&gt; The organization responded by saying, "There's nobody happier about what Andrew Sullivan is doing than [[Tony Perkins (politician)|Tony Perkins]] and [[James Dobson]]", two [[social conservatism in the United States|social conservative]] leaders and outspoken critics&lt;ref name="tony perkins"&gt;{{cite news|last=Perkins|first=Tony|title=Christian compassion requires the truth about harms of homosexuality|url=http://onfaith.washingtonpost.com/onfaith/guestvoices/2010/10/christian_compassion_requires_the_truth_about_harms_of_homosexuality.html|accessdate=February 22, 2012|newspaper=The Washington Post|date=October 11, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=dodson&gt;{{cite web|last=Dodson|first=James|title=Marriage Under Fire (excerpt)|url=http://www.christianbookpreviews.com/christian-book-excerpt.php?isbn=1590524314|accessdate=February 22, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; of the LGBT community.&lt;ref&gt;[http://groups.yahoo.com/group/transgendernews/message/19553 HRC hits back at blogger criticisms – Washington Blade] originally [http://www.washblade.com/2007/3-16/news/national/10212.cfm here]&lt;/ref&gt;

HRC's endorsement of New York Republican [[Al D'Amato]] in his 1998 campaign for re-election to the U.S. Senate brought more criticism. HRC defended the endorsement because of D'Amato's support for [[Employment Non-Discrimination Act]] (ENDA) and repeal of "[[Don't Ask, Don't Tell]]". However, many liberal LGBT leaders did not welcome D'Amato's many conservative stances, including his opposition to [[affirmative action]] and [[abortion]].&lt;ref&gt;Kaiser, Charles. (July 18, 2000) [http://books.google.com/books?id=Z2MEAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=PA72&amp;lpg=PA72&amp;dq=Kaiser,+Charles.+%2818+July+2000%29+d%27amato+factor+advocate&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=9326I-yZy0&amp;sig=TsN9ngxvE96oRZHCIcpvAux3A6A&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=Qo1ET_bAL-u00QG28e2eBA&amp;ved=0CEkQ6AEwBQ#v=onepage&amp;q=Kaiser%2C%20Charles.%20%2818%20July%202000%29%20d%27amato%20factor%20advocate&amp;f=false The D'Amato Factor] ''[[The Advocate]]''. Retrieved February 22, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

HRC has also been accused of overstating the number of its actual members in order to appear more influential in politics.&lt;ref name="Cookbook"&gt;[http://citizenchris.typepad.com/citizenchris/2007/03/the_nations_lar.html Citizen Crain: Cooking the books at HRC]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://andrewsullivan.theatlantic.com/the_daily_dish/2007/03/hrc_responds_1.html The Daily Dish | By Andrew Sullivan]&lt;/ref&gt; Former HRC President Joe Solmonese responded, saying that "[m]embership is about more than contributions&amp;nbsp;... [i]t's about sending e-mails to elected officials, volunteering time or lobbying members of Congress" and more than half of its members made contributions during the previous two years.&lt;ref name="$1"&gt;[http://www.cross-nation.com/dnf-092008-hrcnumbersgame.html HRC 'members' include all who ever donated $1 – Washington Blade] originally [http://washingtonblade.com/2005/5-6/news/national/members.cfm here]&lt;/ref&gt; Earlier, HRC spokesperson Steven Fisher stated that its membership includes anyone who has donated at least $1.&lt;ref name="$1"/&gt;

Some [[transgender]] people have criticized the HRC for its stance on the 2007 version of ENDA, which enumerated sexual orientation as a protected category but not [[gender identity]] and [[gender expression|expression]].&lt;ref&gt;Schindler, Paul. (October 4, 2007) [http://www.gaycitynews.com/site/news.cfm?newsid=18883568&amp;BRD=2729&amp;PAG=461&amp;dept_id=568864&amp;rfi=6 HRC Alone in Eschewing No-Compromise Stand] Gay City News. Retrieved October 8, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Once the legislation was submitted by Rep. [[Barney Frank]], HRC officially neither opposed nor supported it.&lt;ref name=rose&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://web.archive.org/web/20080919202932/http://www.advocate.com/news_detail_ektid49565.asp|title=Donna Rose on Why She Resigned as the Only Transgender Member of HRC's Board|date=October 4, 2007|accessdate=April 2, 2013|publisher=[[The Advocate]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; This followed a speech by former HRC President Joe Solmonese at the transgender [[Southern Comfort Conference]] the previous month, where he said that HRC "oppose[d] any legislation that is not absolutely inclusive".&lt;ref name=solomonese&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.edgesanfrancisco.com/index.php?ch=news&amp;sc=glbt&amp;sc2=features&amp;sc3=&amp;id=77775|title=HRC's ENDA dilemma: Dine, party or boycott?|date=July 22, 2008|accessdate=March 25, 2011|publisher=EDGE Publications, Inc.}}&lt;/ref&gt; HRC later explained that it could not actively support a non-inclusive bill, but did not oppose it because the legislation would strategically advance long-term efforts to pass a trans-inclusive ENDA.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Sandeen|first=Autumn|title=ENDA Passed Without "Real Or Perceived Gender" Protections|url=http://pamshouseblend.firedoglake.com/2007/11/07/enda-passed-without-real-or-perceived-gender-protections/|publisher=pamhouseblend.com|accessdate=February 22, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, in a letter to [[U.S. Representatives]], HRC did express support for the bill, stating that while HRC is "greatly disappointed that the current version of ENDA is not {{Sic|hide=y|fully|-}}inclusive&amp;nbsp;... we appreciate the steadfast efforts of our&amp;nbsp;... allies&amp;nbsp;... even when they are forced&amp;nbsp;... to make progress that is measured by inches rather than yards."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pamspaulding.com/graphics/LCCR_ENDA_%20Letter.pdf "Letter to U.S. Representatives"]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2014, long-time marriage equality activist Shenna Bellows was nominated for a Senate seat in Maine. HRC endorsed her opponent, incumbent Senator Susan Collins, who had previously lacked a history of supporting marriage equality initiatives.  However, Senator Collins has clarified her view in support of LGBT marriage equality.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2014/06/25/susan-collins-human-rights-campaign_n_5530867.html "Susan Collins Endorsed By Major Gay Rights Group, Despite Not Backing Marriage Equality"]&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|LGBT|District of Columbia}}
*[[Gay community]]
*[[LGBT rights in the United States]]
*[[List of LGBT rights organizations]]

==References==
{{reflist|30em}}

==External links==
* [http://www.hrc.org/ Human Rights Campaign] – official website
** [http://www.hrc.org/cei HRC ratings of corporations on LGBT issues]
** [http://www.hrc.org/resources HRC LGBT Resources Guide]
*** [http://www.hrc.org/youth 10,000 Youth Survey: Growing Up LGBT in America: Key Findings]
** [http://www.millionsformarriage.org/ HRC Millions for Marriage Equality]
* [http://www.hrc.org/americansformarriageequality Americans for Marriage Equality]
* [http://rmc.library.cornell.edu/HRC/ The Records of the Human Rights Campaign at the Cornell Library]

{{LGBT}}

[[Category:1980 establishments in Washington, D.C.]]
[[Category:History of LGBT civil rights in the United States]]
[[Category:LGBT culture in Washington, D.C.]]
[[Category:LGBT political advocacy groups in the United States]]
[[Category:Organizations based in Washington, D.C.]]
[[Category:Organizations established in 1980]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>