<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20071109195746|170394825" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="335104" pageid="335104" ns="0" title="Human Rights Campaign"><revisions><rev timestamp="2007-11-10T01:28:58Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Organization
|name         = Human Rights Campaign
|image        = Hrc logo.png
|image_border = 
|size         = 150px
|caption      = The HRC logo is an [[equals sign]] to represent equality.
|motto        = Working for Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual and Transgender Equal Rights
|formation    = [[1980 in LGBT rights|1980]]
|type         = 
|headquarters = 
|location     = [[Washington, D.C.]]
|membership   = 
|language     = 
|leader_title = President
|leader_name  = [[Joe Solmonese]]
|key_people   = 
|num_staff    = 
|budget       = 
|website      = http://www.hrc.org
}}
The '''Human Rights Campaign''' ('''HRC''') is the largest [[lesbian]], [[gay]], [[bisexuality|bisexual]], and [[transgender]] ([[LGBT]]) [[Social equality|equal rights]] [[organization]] in the [[United States]], with more than 700,000 members and supporters. The HRC "envisions an America where [[LGBT|GLBT]] people are ensured of their basic equal rights, and can be open, honest and safe at home, at work and in the community."&lt;ref&gt;HRC. [http://www.hrc.org/Template.cfm?Section=About_HRC About HRC] Accessed 29 July 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Programs, functions, and actions of the HRC==
The Human Rights Campaign is a visible entity in U.S. [[politics]]. It lobbies [[United States Congress|Congress]] for support of LGBT-positive bills, works to build an LGBT-friendly Congress by funding those politicians that support the [[gay community|LGBT community]], mobilizes [[grassroots]] action amongst its members, and encourages members to employ their [[right to vote]] in every election. 

Through its website, the HRC also assists members in identifying [[state]] and local [[lawmaker]]s, researching state and local laws regarding issues central to LGBT causes, reviewing scorecards of how lawmakers rate on LGBT issues, and drafting and sending letters to lawmakers. 

Additionally, HRC maintains information on how to [[come out]] and information about [[Office|workplace]] issues (in the [[Corporate Equality Index]]).

==History and leadership==
The Human Rights Campaign Fund was established in [[1980]] by Steve Endean to raise money for [[gay]]-supportive congressional candidates. Within three months time, the HRC was registered with the [[Federal Election Commission]] as an independent [[political action committee]]. In [[1983]], Vic Basile, one of the leading [[LGBT]] rights activists in [[Washington, DC]] at the time, was elected as the first executive director. In October [[1986]], the HRC Foundation was formed. As with many gay organizations in the 1980s, HRC's membership was devastated by the onslaught of [[AIDS]] and they spent much of the decade struggling to hold their ground.

In January [[1989]], Basile announced his departure, and the HRC reorganized from serving mainly as a [[political action committee|PAC]] to becoming a lobbying and political organization. The purpose statement of the HRC became, 
{{cquote|For the promotion of the social welfare of the gay and lesbian community by drafting, supporting and influencing legislation and policy at the federal, state and local level.}} 

[[Tim McFeeley]], a graduate of [[Harvard Law]], and founder of the [[Boston Lesbian and Gay Political Alliance]] and a co-chair of the [[New England]] HRC Committee, was elected the new executive director. Total membership was then approximately 25,000 members.
[[Image:ChicagoGayPride2005 1.jpg|right|thumb|300px|The Human Rights Campaign often has a large presence at LGBT-related events such as the Chicago Pride Parade as seen above.]]
In [[1992]], the HRC endorsed a presidential candidate for the first time &amp;mdash; [[Arkansas]] Governor [[Bill Clinton]]. In March [[1993]], [[National Coming Out Day]] became a project of the HRC. From January [[1995]] until January [[2004]], [[Elizabeth Birch]] served as the executive director of the HRC. Under her leadership, the institution more than quadrupled its membership to 500,000 members and purchased an office building for its Washington, DC headquarters. 

The headquarters building was purchased from [[B'nai B'rith|B'nai B'rith International]] in [[2002]] for $9.8 million. A large national capital campaign raised over $28 million for the project. After extensive renovations of the mid-century modern structure, the building is currently valued at over $18 million.

As part of festivities surrounding the [[Millennium March on Washington]], the Human Rights Campaign Foundation sponsored a fundraising concert, Equality Rocks, on April 29, 2000. Over 45,000 people attended at Washington DC's [[RFK Stadium]] to watch [[Melissa Etheridge]], [[Garth Brooks]], [[Pet Shop Boys]], [[k.d. lang]], [[Nathan Lane]], [[Rufus Wainwright]], [[Albita]], and [[Chaka Kahn]]. The event was billed as a concert to end hate crimes and the parents of [[Matthew Shepard]] spoke and other families of hate crime victims were honored.

In August [[2000]], Birch became the first leader of an LGBT organization to address the convention of a major political party when she spoke before the [[Democratic National Convention]].

Birch's successor, [[Cheryl Jacques]], resigned in November [[2004]] after only 11 months as executive director. In a statement released by the organization, Jacques resigned over "a difference in management philosophy". Incidentally, Birch's partner, [[Hilary Rosen]], former chief executive of the [[Recording Industry Association of America]], was named as interim replacement.

On [[March 9]], [[2005]], the HRC announced the appointment of [[Joe Solmonese]] as the president, describing him as one of the "nation's most accomplished and respected progressive leaders".

The Human Rights Campaign also consists of a Board of Directors and a Board of Governors. The HRCF (Human Rights Campaign Foundation), a non-profit entity, also maintains a separate Board. In [[December 2004]], they named [[Michael Berman]] as their Board chair.

In 2006, the Human Rights Campaign came under fire from other nonprofit human rights groups for accepting money from [[Nike, Inc.]], which has received criticism for its [[human rights violations]] in other countries.{{Fact|date=February 2007}}

On May 5, 2007, the [[United States House of Representatives|House of Representatives]] passed the [[Local Law Enforcement Hate Crimes Prevention Act of 2007]], which would expand the 1969 federal [[Hate crime laws in the United States|hate-crime law]] to include crimes motivated by a victim's [[gender]], [[sexual orientation]], [[gender identity]], or [[disability]], as well as remove the existing prerequisite that the victim be engaging in a federally-protected activity.  Solmonese and the HRC have lobbied extensively for this expansion.

===HRC Historical Records===
The historical records of the Human Rights Campaign are maintained in a collection at the [[Cornell University]] [[Cornell University Library|Library]]. Arriving at Cornell in 2004, the records include strategic-planning documents, faxes, minutes, e-mails, press releases, posters and campaign buttons which constitute the second largest collection of records in the Library's Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Human Sexuality Collection area with 84 cubic feet of records. On February 8, 2007, the records were opened to scholars at the library, and selected records pulled into an online exhibit called  "25 Years of Political Influence: The Records of the Human Rights Campaign." &lt;ref&gt;Lowery, George. (30 January 2007) [http://www.news.cornell.edu/stories/Jan07/humanrightsrecords.gl.html 25 years of gay-rights struggles traced in online exhibit] ''[[The Cornell Chronicle]]'' of [[Cornell University]]. Accessed 29 July 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Cornell University Library]]. [http://rmc.library.cornell.edu/HRC/index.html 25 Years of Political Influence:The Records of the Human Rights Campaign] [[Cornell University]]. Accessed 29 July 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Criticism===
[[Andrew Sullivan]] has been critical of the HRC calling them "a patronage wing of the Democratic party, designed primarily to get its members jobs in future Democratic administrations or with Democrats on the Hill (even while Howard Dean treats them like the help)."&lt;ref&gt;Sullivan, Andrew. (19 February 2007) [http://andrewsullivan.theatlantic.com/the_daily_dish/2007/02/the_human_right.html The Human Rights Campaign (Blech)] ''[[The Atlantic Monthly]]''. Accessed 29 July 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

The HRC also angered many of its supporters in New York, and many of its African-American, Asian-American, and female supporters nationwide by endorsing Republican Senator [[Al D'Amato]] in the 1998 elections.&lt;ref&gt;Kaiser, Charles. (18 July 2000) [http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m1589/is_2000_July_18/ai_63398448 The D'Amato Factor - Article Brief at findarticles.com] ''[[The Advocate]]''. Accessed 29 July 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; D'Amato earned the nomination by supporting equal protection in the work place, but his stances against reproductive rights, and affirmative action, and racist jokes he told at the expense of Judge [[Lance Ito]], left many LGBT people angry over the nomination.  (D'Amato was defeated by [[Charles Schumer]]).

HRC has been criticized for supporting a version of the [[Employment Non-Discrimination Act]] which lacks language including protections for transgendered people and gender identity.&lt;ref&gt;Schindler, Paul. (4 October 2007) [http://www.gaycitynews.com/site/news.cfm?newsid=18883568&amp;BRD=2729&amp;PAG=461&amp;dept_id=568864&amp;rfi=6 HRC Alone in Eschewing No-Compromise Stand] Gay City News. Accessed 8 October 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; HRC President Joe Solmonese promised on September 14, 2007 to oppose any ENDA legislation not including trans provisions, and only to support those that did include them, a policy they first articulated in 2004&lt;ref name="Trans Advocate"&gt;Sandeen, Autumn. (6 November 2007) [http://transadvocate.com/autumnsandeen/archives/1157] Trans Advocate Blog. Accessed November 9th 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;.HRC reversed this position once October 2nd, ceasing opposition of a trans-exclusive ENDA, leading to the resignation of board member Donna Rose on October 3rd.&lt;ref&gt; Rose, Donna. (3 October 2007) [http://www.intraa.org/story/DRHRCresignation]&lt;/ref&gt;, and again November 6th to fully support the exclusive version,&lt;ref name="Trans Advocate"/&gt;a change which they attempted to cover up.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pamshouseblend.com/showDiary.do?diaryId=3509] Pam's House Blend. Accessed 9 November 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Leaders===
# Steve Endean, HRC founder ([[1980]]&amp;ndash;[[1983]])
# Executive Director Vic Basile (1983&amp;ndash;[[1989]])
# Executive Director [[Tim McFeeley]] (1989&amp;ndash;[[1995]])
# Executive Director [[Elizabeth Birch]] (1995&amp;ndash;[[2004]])
# President [[Cheryl Jacques]] (2004)
# President [[Joe Solmonese]] ([[2005]]&amp;ndash;present)

==Musical merchandising==
In [[2002]], the Human Rights Campaign, in collaboration with [[Centaur Entertainment]], released an awareness album named ''[[Being Out Rocks]]''. It was released on [[October 11]] [[2002]] to celebrate [[National Coming Out Day]] that year. It features a cross-section of [[LGBT]] and gay-supportive straight artists. Its release was accompanied with signing events at the [[Times Square]] [[Virgin Megastores|Virgin Megastore]] in [[New York City]] and at the HRC Action Center in [[Washington, D.C.]]

On [[February 8]], [[2005]], the Human Rights Campaign released its second CD compilation with Centaur, a 2-disc set called ''[[Love Rocks]]''.

==National corporate sponsors==
{{gay rights}}
As of August 2007, the following companies are the current national corporate sponsors of HRC:&lt;ref&gt;HRC. [http://www.hrc.org/Content/NavigationMenu/HRC/Get_Involved/HRC_Sponsors/Corporate_Sponsors/National_Corporate_Sponsors.htm National Corporate Sponsors] Accessed 29 July 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Abreva]] of [[GlaxoSmithKline]]
*''[[The Advocate]]'' &amp; ''[[Out Magazine|Out]]'' Magazines ([[LPI Media]])
*[[American Airlines]]
*[[Beaulieu Vineyards]]
*[[BP]]
*[[Citigroup]]
*[[Chase]]
*[[Dell]]
*[[Deloitte]]
*[[Ernst &amp; Young]]
*[[Foley &amp; Lardner]]
*[[Harrah's Entertainment]]
*[[Hotels.com]]
*[[IBM]]
*[[Merrill Lynch]]
*[[MGM Mirage]]
*[[Mitchell Gold Co.|Mitchell Gold &amp; Bob Williams Co.]]
*[[Motorola]]
*[[Nike, Inc.|Nike]]
*[[Olivia Records|Olivia Cruises &amp; Resorts]]
*[[Paul, Hastings, Janofsky &amp; Walker|Paul Hastings Attorneys]]
*[[PricewaterhouseCoopers]]
*[[Prudential Financial]]
*[[Replacements, Ltd.]]
*[[Shell Oil Company]]
*[[Showtime]]
*[[Volvo Cars]] of North America
*[[Washington Mutual]]
*[[XM Satellite Radio]]

==References==
&lt;references/&gt;

==External links==
*[http://www.hrc.org/ Human Rights Campaign] (official website)
*[http://www.hrc.org/issues/workplace/ceihome.asp Corporate Equality Index]
*[http://www.millionformarriage.org/ Million For Marriage petition]
*[http://rmc.library.cornell.edu/HRC/ The Records of the Human Rights Campaign at the Cornell Library]
{{LGBT-footer}}

[[Category:LGBT rights organizations]]
[[Category:History of LGBT civil rights in the United States]]
[[Category:LGBT political advocacy groups in the United States]]
[[Category:1980 establishments]]

[[de:Human Rights Campaign]]
[[ru:Кампания за права человека]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>