<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20041031181508|7147626" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="335104" pageid="335104" ns="0" title="Human Rights Campaign"><revisions><rev timestamp="2004-11-06T05:41:44Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">[[Image:Hrc logo.png|152px|right|thumb|HRC logo]]

The '''Human Rights Campaign''' ('''HRC''') is the largest [[lesbian]], [[gay]], [[bisexual]], and [[transgender]] ([[LGBT]]) equal rights organization in the [[United States]]. The HRC "envisions an America where [LGBT] people are ensured of their basic equal rights, and can be open, honest and safe at home, at work and in the community." [http://www.hrc.org/Template.cfm?Section=About_HRC]

==Actions of the HRC==
The Human Rights Campaign is a visible entity in U.S. politics. It lobbies [[United States Congress|Congress]] for support of LGBT-positive bills, works to build an LGBT-friendly Congress by funding those politicians that support the LGBT [[gay community|community]], mobilizes grassroots action amongst its members, and encourages members to employ their right to vote in every election. Through its Website, the HRC also assists members in identifying state and local lawmakers, researching state and local laws regarding issues central to the LGBT cause, reviewing scorecards of how lawmakers rate on LGBT issues, and drafting and sending letters to lawmakers.

==History and leadership==
The Human Rights Campaign Fund was established in [[1980]] by Steve Endean to raise money for [[gay]]-supportive congressional candidates. Within three months time, the HRC was registered with the [[Federal Election Commission]] as an independent [[political action committee]]. In [[1983]], Vic Basile, one of the leading [[LGBT]] rights activists in [[Washington, DC|Washington, D.C.]] at the time, was elected as the first executive director. In [[October]] [[1986]], the HRC Foundation was formed.

In January 1989, Basile announced his departure, and the HRC reorganized from serving mainly as a [[political action committee|PAC]] to becoming a lobbying and political organization. The purpose statement of the HRC became, "For the promotion of the social welfare of the gay and lesbian community by drafting, supporting and influencing legislation and policy at the federal, state and local level." Tim McFeeley, a graduate of Harvard Law, and founder of the Boston Lesbian and Gay Political Alliance and a co-chair of the New England HRC Committee, was elected the new executive director. Total membership was approximately 25,000 members.

In [[1992]], the HRC endorsed a presidential candidate for the first time &amp;ndash; [[Arkansas]] Governor [[Bill Clinton]]. In [[March]] [[1993]], [[National Coming Out Day]] became a project of the HRC. From [[January]] [[1995]] until January [[2004]], [[Elizabeth Birch]] served as the executive director of the HRC. Under her leadership, the institution more than quadrupled its membership to 500,000 members. In [[August]] [[2000]], she became the first leader of an LGBT organization to address the convention of a major political party when she spoke before the [[Democratic National Convention]]. [[Cheryl Jacques]] is the present executive director. The Human Rights Campaign also consists of a Board of Directors and a Board of Governors. The HRC Foundation also maintains its Board.

==Transgender inclusion==
Officially, the HRC represents the transgender community. However, it has previously been the target of protests once due to its refusal to demand the inclusion of the transgendered in the [[Employment Non-Discrimination Act]] (ENDA) bill. These objections changed when the organization announced support for an ENDA bill that was inclusive of gender identity, however sparking charges of "trans-jacking" from the far right.

==National corporate sponsors and partners==
The following companies are the current national corporate sponsors and partners of the HRC:
*Corporate sponsors
**[[The Advocate]]
**[[American Airlines]]
**Beaulieu Vineyard
**BoxOfficeTickets.com
**Capital One
**[[Cingular Wireless]]
**[[Coors Brewing Company]]
**[[IBM]]
**John Hancock Financial Services
**Mitchell Gold Co.
**[[Nike, Inc.|Nike]]
**Olivia Cruises &amp; Resorts
**[[Out Magazine|Out]]
**Replacements, Ltd.
**[[Showtime]]
**[[Volvo Cars]] of North America
**[[Washington Mutual]]
*National partners
**Centaur Music
**PlanetOut Partners

==See also==
*[[Gay rights]]

==External links==
*[http://www.hrc.org/ Human Rights Campaign]

[[Category:LGBT rights organizations]]
[[Category:LGBT]]
[[Category:Political advocacy groups in the U.S.]]
[[Category:U.S. history of LGBT rights]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>