<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20091107000447|324373123" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="335104" pageid="335104" ns="0" title="Human Rights Campaign"><revisions><rev timestamp="2009-11-08T16:34:04Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Redirect|HRC|other uses|HRC (disambiguation)}}
{{Infobox Organization
|name         = Human Rights Campaign
|image        = Hrc logo.svg
|image_border = 
|size         = 
|caption      = The HRC [[equals sign|equal sign]] logo&lt;br&gt;symbolizing equality.
|motto        = Working for Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual and Transgender Equal Rights
|formation    = 1980
|type         = 
|headquarters = 
|location     = [[Washington, D.C.]]
|membership   = 
|language     = 
|leader_title = President
|leader_name  = [[Joe Solmonese]]
|key_people   = 
|num_staff    = 
|budget       = 
|website      = [http://www.hrc.org www.HRC.org]
}}
The '''Human Rights Campaign''' ('''HRC''') is the largest [[lesbian]], [[gay]], [[bisexuality|bisexual]], and [[transgender]] ([[LGBT]]) [[interest group|lobbying group]] and [[political action committee]] in the [[United States]], claiming over 725,000 members and supporters,&lt;ref name="HRC | What We Do"&gt;[http://www.hrc.org/about_us/what_we_do.asp HRC | What We Do]&lt;/ref&gt; though this membership count is disputed.&lt;ref&gt;[http://washingtonblade.com/2005/5-6/news/national/members.cfm HRC 'members' include all who ever donated $1 - Washington Blade]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://andrewsullivan.theatlantic.com/the_daily_dish/2007/03/hrc_responds_1.html HRC Responds | The Daily Dish | By Andrew Sullivan]&lt;/ref&gt; The HRC mission statement is "HRC envisions an America where gay, lesbian, bisexual and transgender people are ensured equality and embraced as full members of the American family at home, at work and in every community."&lt;ref name="HRC | What We Do"/&gt;

==Programs==
The Human Rights Campaign is a visible entity in U.S. [[politics]]. It lobbies [[United States Congress|Congress]] for support of LGBT-positive bills, works to build an LGBT-friendly Congress by funding those politicians that support the [[gay community|LGBT community]], mobilizes [[grassroots]] action amongst its members, and encourages members to exercise their [[suffrage|right to vote]] in every election. The organization overwhelmingly supports Democratic candidates running for office, although HRC supports some moderate Republicans.&lt;ref name="Donor Profiles"&gt;[http://www.opensecrets.org/orgs/summary.asp?ID=D000000158&amp;Name=Human+Rights+Campaign Donor Profiles&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

Through its website, the HRC also helps members identify their [[U.S. state|state]] and local [[legislator|lawmakers]], review scorecards of how legislators rate on LGBT issues, and draft correspondence to lawmakers. Additionally, the website helps members research state and local laws on issues that are central to LGBT causes.

Additionally, HRC maintains resources on [[coming out]] and information about workplace issues faced by LGBT people, notably the [[Corporate Equality Index]]. It also provides resources on LGBT parenting and religion and faith issues.

==History and leadership==
[[Image:Human Right Campaign headquarters.JPG|thumb|Human Rights Campaign headquarters in [[Washington, D.C.]]]]
The Human Rights Campaign Fund was established in 1980 by [[Steve Endean]] to raise money for gay-supportive congressional candidates. Within three months, the HRC was registered with the [[Federal Election Commission]] as an independent political action committee. In 1983, Vic Basile, one of the leading LGBT rights activists in Washington, D.C. at the time, was elected as the first executive director. In October 1986, the HRC Foundation was formed. As with many gay organizations in the 1980s, HRC was devastated by the onslaught of [[AIDS]] and its membership spent much of the decade struggling to hold their ground.

In January 1989, Basile announced his departure, and the HRC reorganized from serving mainly as a political action committee (PAC) to becoming a lobbying and political organization. HRC's new Statement of Purpose became, 
{{cquote|For the promotion of the social welfare of the gay and lesbian community by drafting, supporting and influencing legislation and policy at the federal, state and local level.}}

[[Tim McFeeley]], a graduate of [[Harvard Law School]], and founder of the [[Boston Lesbian and Gay Political Alliance]] and a co-chair of the [[New England]] HRC Committee, was elected the new executive director. Total membership was then approximately 25,000 members.{{Citation needed|date=January 2008}}

In 1992, the HRC endorsed a presidential candidate for the first time &amp;mdash; [[Arkansas]] Governor [[Bill Clinton]]. In March 1993, [[National Coming Out Day]] became a project of the HRC. From January 1995 until January 2004, [[Elizabeth Birch]] served as the executive director of the HRC. Under her leadership, the institution more than quadrupled its membership to 500,000 members and purchased an office building for its Washington, D.C. headquarters.{{Citation needed|date=January 2008}}

The headquarters building was purchased from [[B'nai B'rith|B'nai B'rith International]] in 2002 for $9.8 million. A large national capital campaign raised over $28 million for the project. After extensive renovations of the mid-century modern structure, the building is currently valued at over $18 million.{{Citation needed|date=January 2008}}
[[Image:ChicagoGayPride2005 1.jpg|thumb|The Human Rights Campaign often has a large presence at LGBT-related events such as the Chicago Pride Parade as seen above.]]
As part of the festivities surrounding the [[Millennium March on Washington]], the Human Rights Campaign Foundation sponsored a fundraising concert, "Equality Rocks," on 29 April, 2000. Over 45,000 people attended at Washington DC's [[Robert F. Kennedy Memorial Stadium|RFK Stadium]] to watch [[Melissa Etheridge]], [[Garth Brooks]], [[Pet Shop Boys]], [[k.d. lang]], [[Nathan Lane]], [[Rufus Wainwright]], [[Albita Rodríguez]], and [[Chaka Khan]]. Billed as a concert to end [[hate crime]]s, the event featured the parents of [[Matthew Shepard]], and also honored families of hate crime victims.

In August 2000, Birch became the first leader of a LGBT organization to address the convention of a major political party when she spoke before the [[Democratic National Convention]].

Birch's successor, [[Cheryl Jacques]], resigned in November 2004 after only 11 months as executive director. In a statement released by the organization, Jacques resigned over "a difference in management philosophy". Incidentally, Birch's partner, [[Hilary Rosen]], former chief executive of the [[Recording Industry Association of America]], was named as interim replacement.

In March 2005, HRC announced the appointment of [[Joe Solmonese]] as the president, describing him as one of the "nation's most accomplished and respected progressive leaders".

The Human Rights Campaign also consists of a Board of Directors and a Board of Governors. The Human Rights Campaign Foundation, a non-profit entity, also maintains a separate Board. In December 2004, they named [[Michael S. Berman]] as their Board chair.

On 5 May 2007, the [[United States House of Representatives|House of Representatives]] passed the [[Matthew Shepard Act]], which would expand the 1969 federal [[Hate crime laws in the United States|hate-crime law]] to include crimes motivated by a victim's [[gender]], [[sexual orientation]], [[gender identity]], or [[disability]], as well as remove the existing prerequisite that the victim be engaging in a federally-protected activity. The HRC has lobbied extensively for this expansion.{{Citation needed|date=November 2009}} The legislation passed the [[United States Senate]] on 20 September 2007. The amendment was attached to the Defense Reauthorization Bill and [[George W. Bush|President Bush]] announced he would likely veto the bill if it reached his desk with the amendment attached.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pinknews.co.uk/news/articles/2005-5582.html US Senate passes gay hate crimes law- from Pink News- all the latest gay news from the gay community - Pink News&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;  Ultimately, the House and Senate were not able to reconcile their individual versions of the amendment, and it was dropped from the final draft of the Defense Reauthorization Bill.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.washblade.com/thelatest/thelatest.cfm?blog_id=15561 "House nixes hate crimes"] Retrieved on 2008-08-25.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2009, HRC criticized statements by Pope [[Benedict XVI]] that condom use was not helpful in AIDS prevention and might even be counterproductive.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.outinamerica.com/home/news.asp?articleid=33040 HRC RESPONDS TO POPE BENEDICT’S REMARKS THAT CONDOMS INCREASE HIV INFECTIONS]&lt;/ref&gt;

===HRC historical records===
The historical records of the Human Rights Campaign are maintained in a collection at the [[Cornell University]] [[Cornell University Library|Library]]. Arriving at Cornell in 2004, the records include strategic-planning documents, faxes, minutes, e-mails, press releases, posters and campaign buttons which constitute the second largest collection of records in the Library's Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Human Sexuality Collection area with {{convert|84|cuft|m3}} of records. In February 2007, the records were opened to scholars at the library, and selected records were organized into an online exhibit called "25 Years of Political Influence: The Records of the Human Rights Campaign."&lt;ref&gt;Lowery, George. (30 January 2007) [http://www.news.cornell.edu/stories/Jan07/humanrightsrecords.gl.html 25 years of gay-rights struggles traced in online exhibit] ''[[The Cornell Chronicle]]'' of [[Cornell University]]. Accessed 29 July 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Cornell University Library]]. [http://rmc.library.cornell.edu/HRC/index.html 25 Years of Political Influence:The Records of the Human Rights Campaign] [[Cornell University]]. Accessed 29 July 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Criticism==
===Political ideology===
Critics of the HRC have accused the organization of favoring the Democratic party platform over gay and lesbian equality in regards to gay marriage and ending the [[don't ask, don't tell]] policy.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.indegayforum.org/blog/show/31181.html Independent Gay Forum - Rudy's Run&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://andrewsullivan.theatlantic.com/the_daily_dish/2007/02/the_human_right.html The Daily Dish | By Andrew Sullivan&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.indegayforum.org/blog/show/31113.html Independent Gay Forum - Whose Agenda?&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; The HRC states they are fighting for equality in all areas of gay, lesbian, bisexual and transgender rights.

[[Andrew Sullivan]], a prominent conservative gay political columnist and blogger, has been critical of the HRC calling them "a patronage wing of the Democratic party, designed primarily to get its members jobs in future Democratic administrations or with Democrats on [[Capitol Hill|the Hill]]".&lt;ref&gt;Sullivan, Andrew. (19 February 2007) [http://andrewsullivan.theatlantic.com/the_daily_dish/2007/02/the_human_right.html The Human Rights Campaign (Blech)] ''[[The Atlantic Monthly]]''. Accessed 29 July 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; The organization responded by saying, "There’s nobody happier about what Andrew Sullivan is doing than [[Tony Perkins (politician)|Tony Perkins]] and [[James Dobson]]" who are known for opposing [[LGBT rights]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.washblade.com/2007/3-16/news/national/10212.cfm HRC hits back at blogger criticisms - Washington Blade&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; As of October 2008, HRC campaign donations for the 2008 election have totaled $739,042. That amount includes $705,036, or 95% of the total, to Democrats.&lt;ref name="Donor Profiles"/&gt;

===Membership===
HRC has been accused of overstating the number of actual members in order to appear more influential in politics.&lt;ref&gt;[http://citizenchris.typepad.com/citizenchris/2007/03/the_nations_lar.html Citizen Crain: Cooking the books at HRC&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://andrewsullivan.theatlantic.com/the_daily_dish/2007/03/hrc_responds_1.html The Daily Dish | By Andrew Sullivan&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; HRC refuses to release the count of current, dues-paying members.&lt;ref&gt;[http://washingtonblade.com/2005/5-6/news/national/members.cfm HRC 'members' include all who ever donated $1 - Washington Blade&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

===1998 New York Senate election===
The HRC angered many of its supporters in [[New York]], and many of its [[African American]], [[Asian American]], and female supporters nationwide by endorsing Republican Senator [[Al D'Amato]] in the 1998 election.&lt;ref&gt;Kaiser, Charles. (18 July 2000) [http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m1589/is_2000_July_18/ai_63398448 The D'Amato Factor - Article Brief at findarticles.com] ''[[The Advocate]]''. Accessed 29 July 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; D'Amato earned the nomination by supporting an end to discrimination in the workplace and voting to allow gays and lesbians to serve openly in the military, but his stances against [[abortion]] and [[affirmative action]], as well as the racist jokes he told at the expense of Judge [[Lance Ito]], left many LGBT people angry over the nomination.{{Citation needed|date=January 2008}}  D'Amato went on to be defeated by [[Chuck Schumer]].

===ENDA===
HRC has been criticized by [[transgender]] activists for not opposing, though not supporting,&lt;ref name=rose&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.advocate.com/news_detail_ektid49565.asp|title=Donna Rose on Why She Resigned as the Only Transgender Member of HRC's Board|date=2007-10-04|accessdate=2009-08-08|publisher=[[The Advocate]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; the 2007 version of the [[Employment Non-Discrimination Act]] that enumerated sexual orientation as a category of protection but not [[gender identity]] and [[gender expression|expression]].&lt;ref&gt;Schindler, Paul. (4 October 2007) [http://www.gaycitynews.com/site/news.cfm?newsid=18883568&amp;BRD=2729&amp;PAG=461&amp;dept_id=568864&amp;rfi=6 HRC Alone in Eschewing No-Compromise Stand] Gay City News. Accessed 8 October 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; This was the apparent reversal of a policy articulated in 2004 to always include transgender provisions in such a bill,&lt;ref name="Trans Advocate"&gt;Sandeen, Autumn. (6 November 2007) [http://transadvocate.com/autumnsandeen/archives/1157] Trans Advocate Blog. Accessed November 9 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; adapted to political realities that the bill would only pass without transgender protections.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.salon.com/opinion/feature/2007/10/08/lgbt/|title=How did the T get in LGBT?|first=John|last=Aravosis|date=2006-10-08|accessdate=2009-08-08|publisher=[[Salon.com]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Activists within and without the HRC pressured it to more aggressively oppose the sexual orientation antidiscrimination legislation,&lt;ref name=rose/&gt; and it died in the Senate after passing the House.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.gaypeopleschronicle.com/stories09/july/0703095.htm|title=ENDA is back|first=Eric|last=Resnick|date=2009-07-03|accessdate=2009-08-08|publisher=[[Gay People's Chronicle]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Support of Bush's social security plan===
HRC was criticized by LGBT activists when the group's leaders announced that the organization would be softening its demands for equal rights and consider making political bargains, such as supporting President [[George W. Bush]]'s plan to privatize [[Social Security (United States)|Social Security]] partly in exchange for the right of same-sex partners to receive benefits under the program.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2004/12/09/national/09gays.html|title=Groups Debate Slower Strategy on Gay Rights|publisher=''New York Times''|accessdate=2007-11-24|2004-12-09|author=John M. Broder (9 December 2004) }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/articles/A53579-2004Dec9.html|title=Gay Activists Refuse to Bargain Away Rights|publisher=''Washington Post''|accessdate=2007-11-24|2004-12-10|author=Evelyn Nieves (12 December 2004)}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Presidential forum===
In 2007, HRC and [[Logo (TV channel)|Logo]] sponsored the first presidential forum in history to discuss LGBT-related issues. The event was criticized for excluding Democratic presidential candidate [[Mike Gravel]] from the debate. Gravel said, "According to a HRC spokesperson, I didn't raise enough money and therefore my candidacy did not meet their standard of 'viability.' But that's strange &amp;mdash; [[CNN]], [[Public Broadcasting Service|PBS]], [[NBC]] and the [[National Association for the Advancement of Colored People|NAACP]] invited me to their debates without evaluating my financial viability. Ironically I think the real reason why HRC didn't invite me is that I'm too vocal in my advocacy of gay rights. None of the top tier candidates would have been comfortable facing an opponent who consistently points out their refusal to embrace true equality for gays and lesbians. HRC simply bowed to the star factor. It's just a shame that this travesty was perpetrated in the name of the LGBT community."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.huffingtonpost.com/sen-mike-gravel/why-i-wasnt-invited-to-t_b_55931.html Sen. Mike Gravel: Why I Wasn't Invited to the Debate on Gay Issues - Politics on The Huffington Post&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Senator Gravel was later invited to the forum, where he and [[Dennis Kucinich]] were the only candidates to express support for same-sex marriage.

===Tobacco companies and the Corporate Equality Index===
HRC has been criticized by public health researchers for giving a perfect score on the 2009 Corporate Equality Index to [[Reynolds American]], parent company of [[R.J. Reynolds Tobacco]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.q-notes.com/2009/03/21/stamp-of-approval/|title=Stamp of Approval: Gay researcher questions Human Rights Campaign’s perfect rating of Reynolds Tobacco Co.|publisher=''Q-Notes''|accessdate=2009-03-29||author=Matt Comer (21 March 2009) }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Researchers maintain that the scoring rubric subtracts 15 points for corporate action contributing to LGBT inequality&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hrc.org/issues/workplace/cei_criteria.htm Corporate Equality Index: Current Rating Criteria 2.0 (2006 - 2010). Accessed on 2009-03-29]&lt;/ref&gt; and large [[health disparities]] in tobacco use&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19208668 Tobacco use among sexual minorities in the USA, 1987 to May 2007: a systematic review.] ''Tobacco Control'' Online First 11 February 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; (and resulting [[morbidity]] and [[Death|mortality]]) caused by targeted marketing (including the marketing plan [[Project SCUM]], a.k.a. Project Sub-Culture Urban Market) undermine equality.

===Harry Knox and the Obama administration===
Social conservative groups have asked President Obama to fire former HRC Religion and Faith Program Director [[Harry Knox]] from the advisory council of the [[White House Office of Faith-Based and Neighborhood Partnerships]], arguing that Knox is "a virulent anti-Catholic bigot". &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ontopmag.com/article.aspx?id=3836&amp;MediaType=1&amp;Category=26 Obama Asked To Fire Gay Faith Council Member]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Leaders==
# [[Steve Endean]], HRC founder (1980&amp;ndash;1983)
# Executive Director Vic Basile (1983&amp;ndash;1989)
# Executive Director [[Tim McFeeley]] (1989&amp;ndash;1995)
# Executive Director [[Elizabeth Birch]] (1995&amp;ndash;2004)
# President [[Cheryl Jacques]] (2004)
# President [[Joe Solmonese]] (2005&amp;ndash;present)

==Musical merchandising==
In 2002, the Human Rights Campaign, in collaboration with Centaur Entertainment, released an awareness album named ''[[Being Out Rocks]]''. It was released on 11 October 2002 to celebrate [[National Coming Out Day]] that year. It features a cross-section of [[LGBT]] and LGBT-supportive straight artists. Its release was accompanied with signing events at the [[Times Square]] [[Virgin Megastores|Virgin Megastore]] in [[New York City]] and at the HRC Action Center in [[Washington, D.C.]]

In February 2005 HRC released a second CD compilation with Centaur, a 2-disc set called ''[[Love Rocks]]''.

==See also==
{{portalpar|LGBT|Portal LGBT.svg}}
*[[LGBT rights in the United States]]
*[[List of LGBT rights organizations]]
* [[Gay community]]
* [[Gay shame]]

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
* [http://www.hrc.org/ Human Rights Campaign] — official website
** [http://www.hrc.org/cei HRC ratings of corporations on LGBT issues]
* [http://www.millionformarriage.org/ Million For Marriage petition]
* [http://rmc.library.cornell.edu/HRC/ The Records of the Human Rights Campaign at the Cornell Library]

{{LGBT}}

[[Category:History of LGBT civil rights in the United States]]
[[Category:LGBT political advocacy groups in the United States]]
[[Category:1980 establishments]]

[[de:Human Rights Campaign]]
[[es:Human Rights Campaign]]
[[fr:Human Rights Campaign]]
[[nl:Human Rights Campaign]]
[[pl:Human Rights Campaign]]
[[ro:Human Rights Campaign]]
[[ru:Кампания за права человека]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>