<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20201124030103|990371506" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1943640" pageid="1943640" ns="0" title="Intersectionality"><revisions><rev timestamp="2020-11-27T07:51:45Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Theoretical framework of multidimensional oppression}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2020}}
[[File:Venn's four ellipse construction.svg|thumb|An intersectional analysis considers all the factors that apply to an individual in combination, rather than considering each factor in isolation.]]
{{Discrimination sidebar|state=collapsed}}
&lt;!-- Simple definition and simple example --&gt;
'''Intersectionality''' is a [[Theory|theoretical]] framework for understanding how aspects of a person's [[Social identity|social and political identities]] combine to create different modes of [[discrimination]] and [[Social privilege|privilege]]. Examples of these aspects are [[Gender discrimination|gender]], [[caste]], [[sex]], [[Racial discrimination|race]], [[Class discrimination|class]], [[Discrimination against LGBT people|sexuality]], [[religion]], [[Ableism|disability]], [[Lookism|physical appearance]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Tucker|first=Abigail|title=How Much is Being Attractive Worth?|url=https://www.smithsonianmag.com/science-nature/how-much-is-being-attractive-worth-80414787/|access-date=22 June 2020|website=Smithsonian Magazine|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Yonce|first=Kelsey|date=1 January 2014|title=Attractiveness privilege : the unearned advantages of physical attractivenesss|url=https://scholarworks.smith.edu/theses/745|journal=Theses, Dissertations, and Projects}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Height discrimination|height]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Kimhi|first=Omer|date=22 April 2018|title=Falling Short – the Discrimination of Height Discrimination|url=https://papers.ssrn.com/abstract=3166828|language=en|location=Rochester, NY|ssrn=3166828}}&lt;/ref&gt; Intersectionality identifies advantages and disadvantages that are experienced by people due to a combination of factors.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=What Is Intersectionality and Why Is It Important?|url=https://www.aaup.org/article/what-intersectionality-and-why-it-important#.X4Y9k3hKi3I|access-date=2020-10-13|website=www.aaup.org}}&lt;/ref&gt; These '''intersecting''' and overlapping social identities may be both empowering and oppressing.&lt;ref&gt;Lynn C. Holley, Natasha S. Mendoza, Melissa M. Del-Colle &amp; Marquita LynetteBernard (2016) Heterosexism, racism, and mental illness discrimination: Experiences of people withmental health conditions and their families, Journal of Gay &amp; Lesbian Social Services, 28:2, 93-116,DOI: 10.1080/10538720.2016.1155520&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Zinn, M. B., &amp; Dill, B. T. (1996). Theorizing difference from multiracial feminism.Feminist Stud-ies,22, 321–331.&lt;/ref&gt; For example, a black woman might face discrimination from a business that is not distinctly due to her [[Race (human categorization)|race]] (because the business does not discriminate against black men) nor distinctly due to her [[gender]] (because the business does not discriminate against white women), but due to a combination of the two factors.

&lt;!--Relationship to older concepts of feminisim; who's included? --&gt;
Intersectionality broadens the lens of the first and second [[waves of feminism]], which largely focused on the experiences of women who were both [[White women|white]] and [[Middle class|middle-class]], to include the different experiences of [[women of color]], [[Poverty and gender|women who are poor]], [[immigrant women]], and other groups.  Intersectional feminism aims to separate itself from [[white feminism]] by acknowledging women's different experiences and identities.&lt;ref name=":3"&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://iwda.org.au/what-does-intersectional-feminism-actually-mean/|title=What Does Intersectional Feminsim Actually Mean?|date=11 May 2018|website=International Women's Development Agency|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190423154503/https://iwda.org.au/what-does-intersectional-feminism-actually-mean/|archive-date=23 April 2019|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!--Theory here--&gt;
Intersectionality is a qualitative [[analytic framework]] developed in the late 20th century that identifies how interlocking systems of [[Power (social and political)|power]] affect those who are most [[Social exclusion|marginalized in society]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Intersectionality|volume = 1|last=Cooper|first=Brittney|editor2-first = Mary|editor2-last = Hawkesworth|editor1-first = Lisa|editor1-last = Disch|date=1 February 2016|language=en|doi=10.1093/oxfordhb/9780199328581.013.20}}&lt;/ref&gt; and takes these relationships into account when working to promote [[Social equity|social]] and [[Political egalitarianism|political equity]].&lt;ref name=":3" /&gt;  Intersectionality opposes analytical systems that treat each oppressive factor in isolation, as if the discrimination against black women could be explained away as only a simple sum of the discrimination against black men and the discrimination against white women.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|last=Crenshaw|first=Kimberlé|title=The urgency of intersectionality|url=https://www.ted.com/talks/kimberle_crenshaw_the_urgency_of_intersectionality|language=en|access-date=26 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Intersectionality engages in similar themes as [[triple oppression]], which is the oppression associated with being a poor and/or immigrant woman of color.

&lt;!--Critics here--&gt;
Intersectionality has been critiqued as being inherently ambiguous. The ambiguity of this theory means that it can be perceived as unorganized and lacking a clear set of defining goals. As it is based in [[standpoint theory]], critics say the focus on subjective experiences can lead to contradictions and the inability to identify common causes of oppression.

==Historical background==
{{external media|width=210px|align=right | topic = [[Women of the World Festival|Women of the World Festival 2016]] | video1 = [https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-DW4HLgYPlA ''Kimberlé Crenshaw – On Intersectionality''] via [[Southbank Centre]] on [[YouTube]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite AV media | people= [[Kimberlé Williams Crenshaw|Kimberlé Crenshaw]] | date= 14 March 2016 | accessdate= 31 May 2016 | title= Kimberlé Crenshaw – On Intersectionality – keynote – WOW 2016 | medium= Video | publisher= [[Southbank Centre]] via YouTube |url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-DW4HLgYPlA | archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160610104533/https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-DW4HLgYPlA | archive-date= 10 June 2016 | url-status= live }}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

The term was coined by [[black feminist]] scholar [[Kimberlé Williams Crenshaw]] in 1989.&lt;ref name="Crenshaw 1"&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www.law.columbia.edu/pt-br/news/2017/06/kimberle-crenshaw-intersectionality | title=Kimberlé Crenshaw on Intersectionality, More than Two Decades Later | access-date=9 March 2019 | archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190223111809/https://www.law.columbia.edu/pt-br/news/2017/06/kimberle-crenshaw-intersectionality | archive-date=23 February 2019 | url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Crenshaw 2"&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://philpapers.org/archive/CREDTI.pdf |title=Demarginalizing the Intersection of Race and Sex: A Black Feminist Critique of Antidiscrimination Doctrine, Feminist Theory and Antiracist Politics |author=Kimberlé Crenshaw |publisher=University of Chicago Legal Forum |date=1989 |access-date=7 June 2020 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180513141436/https://philpapers.org/archive/CREDTI.pdf |archive-date=13 May 2018 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt; While the theory began as an exploration of the oppression of women of color within society, today the analysis has expanded to include many more aspects of social identity. Identities most commonly referenced in the [[Fourth-wave feminism|fourth wave of feminism]] include race, gender, sex, sexuality, class, ability, nationality, citizenship, religion and body type. Despite being coined in 1989, the term Intersectionality was not adopted widely by feminists until the 2000s and has only grown since that time.  Intersectionality is a notion that provides reasoning for certain instances of oppression in society.

Intersectionality originated from critical race studies and entails the interconnection of gender and race (Nash 2008). Intersectionality demonstrates a multifaced connection between race, gender, and other systems that work together to oppress while allowing privilege. Intersectionality is relative because it displays how race, gender, and other components that operate as one to shape the experiences of others. Crenshaw used intersectionality to denote how race, class, gender, and other systems combine created intersectionality and shaped the experiences of many by making room for privilege (Crenshaw 1991). Crenshaw used intersectionality to display the disadvantages caused by intersecting systems creating structural, political, and representation aspects of violence against minorities in the workplace and society. (Crenshaw 1991). Crenshaw explained the dynamics that using gender, race, and other forms of power in politics and academics plays a big role in intersectionality.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last1=Cho|first1=Sumi|last2=Crenshaw|first2=Kimberlé Williams|last3=McCall|first3=Leslie|date=June 2013|title=Toward a Field of Intersectionality Studies: Theory, Applications, and Praxis|url=https://www.journals.uchicago.edu/doi/10.1086/669608|journal=Signs: Journal of Women in Culture and Society|language=en|volume=38|issue=4|pages=785–810|doi=10.1086/669608|s2cid=143982074|issn=0097-9740}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As articulated by author [[bell hooks]], &lt;!-- no, that's how she styles herself like e e cummings --&gt; the emergence of intersectionality "challenged the notion that 'gender' was the primary factor determining a woman's fate".&lt;ref name="bell hooks 2014"&gt;{{cite book | last = Hooks | first = Bell | title = Feminist Theory: from margin to center | publisher = Routledge | location = New York | year = 2014 | origyear = 1984 | edition = 3rd | isbn = 9781138821668 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The historical exclusion of black women from the feminist movement in the United States resulted in many black 19th and 20th century feminists, such as [[Anna J. Cooper|Anna Julia Cooper]], challenging their historical exclusion. This disputed the ideas of earlier feminist movements, which were primarily led by white middle-class women, suggesting that women were a homogeneous category who shared the same life experiences.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Davis | first = Angela Y. | author-link = Angela Davis | title = Women, Race &amp; Class | publisher = Vintage Books | location = New York | year = 1983 | isbn = 9780394713519 }}&lt;/ref&gt; However, once established that the forms of oppression experienced by white middle-class women were different from those experienced by black, poor, or disabled women, feminists began seeking ways to understand how gender, race, and class combine to "determine the female destiny".&lt;ref name="bell hooks 2014" /&gt;

The concept of intersectionality is intended to illuminate dynamics that have often been overlooked by feminist theory and movements.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Thompson|first=Becky|date=Summer 2002|title=Multiracial feminism: recasting the chronology of Second Wave Feminism|url=https://semanticscholar.org/paper/7e742ad93c990615a97d8c857597206b6ebaf54b|journal=[[Feminist Studies]]|volume=28|issue=2|pages=337–360|doi=10.2307/3178747|jstor=3178747|s2cid=152165042|ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Racial inequality was a factor that was largely ignored by first-wave feminism, which was primarily concerned with gaining political equality between white men and white women. Early women's rights movements often exclusively pertained to the membership, concerns, and struggles of white women.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Gendered Lives: Communication, Gender, &amp; Culture|last1=Fixmer-Oraiz|last2=Wood|first1=Natalie|first2=Julia|publisher=Cengage Learning|year=2015|isbn=978-1-305-28027-4|location=Boston, MA|pages=59–60}}&lt;/ref&gt; Second-wave feminism stemmed from [[Betty Friedan]]’s ''[[The Feminine Mystique]]'' and worked to dismantle sexism relating to the perceived domestic purpose of women. While feminists during this time achieved success through the [[Equal Pay Act of 1963]], [[Title IX]], and ''[[Roe v. Wade]]'', they largely alienated black women from platforms in the mainstream movement.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.vox.com/2018/3/20/16955588/feminism-waves-explained-first-second-third-fourth|title=The waves of feminism, and why people keep fighting over them, explained|last=Grady|first=Constance|date=20 March 2018|website=Vox|access-date=7 May 2019|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190405172242/https://www.vox.com/2018/3/20/16955588/feminism-waves-explained-first-second-third-fourth|archive-date=5 April 2019|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, third-wave feminism—which emerged shortly after the term "intersectionality" was coined in the late 1980s—noted the lack of attention to race, class, sexual orientation, and gender identity in early feminist movements, and tried to provide a channel to address political and social disparities.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Gendered Lives: Communication, Gender, &amp; Culture|last1=Fixmer-Oraiz|last2=Wood|first1=Natalie|first2=Julia|publisher=Cengage Learning|year=2015|isbn=978-1-305-28027-4|location=Boston, MA|pages=72–73}}&lt;/ref&gt; Intersectionality recognizes these issues which were ignored by early social justice movements. Many recent academics, such as [[Leslie McCall]], have argued that the introduction of the intersectionality theory was vital to sociology and that before the development of the theory, there was little research that specifically addressed the experiences of people who are subjected to multiple forms of oppression within society.&lt;ref name="journals.uchicago.edu"&gt;{{Cite journal | last = McCall | first = Leslie |author-link=Leslie McCall | title = The complexity of intersectionality | journal = [[Signs (journal)|Signs: Journal of Women in Culture and Society]] | volume = 30 | issue = 3 | pages = 1771–1800 | doi = 10.1086/426800 | date =Spring 2005 | jstor = 10.1086/426800 | s2cid = 16690122 | ref = harv |url=https://semanticscholar.org/paper/c3828427404111bcb6ec309eff8bf1b2496e21a5 }} [http://anthropology.msu.edu/anp270-us15/files/2015/05/The-Complexity-of-intersectionality-McCall-2005.pdf Pdf.]&lt;/ref&gt; An example of this idea was championed by [[Iris Marion Young]], arguing that differences must be acknowledged in order to find unifying social justice issues that create coalitions that aid in changing society for the better.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|jstor=j.ctt1fzhfz8|title=Intersectionality: Origins, Contestations, Horizons|last=Carastathis|first=Anna|date=2016|publisher=University of Nebraska Press|isbn=9780803285552|editor-last=Leong|editor-first=Karen J.|editor-last2=Smith|editor-first2=Andrea}}&lt;/ref&gt; More specifically, this relates to the ideals of the [[National Council of Negro Women]] (NCNW).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Mueller|first=Ruth Caston|date=1954|title=The National Council of Negro Women, Inc.|jstor=44175227|journal=Negro History Bulletin|volume=18|issue=2|pages=27–31|issn=0028-2529}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The term also has historical and theoretical links to the concept of "simultaneity", which was advanced during the 1970s by members of the [[Combahee River Collective]] in [[Boston, Massachusetts]].&lt;ref&gt;
Wiegman, Robyn (2012), "[https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=PAC_r_0nXFsC&amp;pg=PA244 Critical kinship (universal aspirations and intersectional judgements)] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171201233014/https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=PAC_r_0nXFsC&amp;pg=PA244 |date=2017 }}", in {{cite book | editor-last = Wiegman | editor-first = Robyn | title = Object lessons | page = [https://archive.org/details/objectlessons00wieg/page/244 244] | publisher = Duke University Press | location = Durham, North Carolina | isbn = 9780822351603 | ref = harv | date = 2012|url=https://archive.org/details/objectlessons00wieg/page/244 }}
:''Citing'':
:* {{cite book | last1 = Hull | first1 = Gloria T. | last2 = Bell-Scott | first2 = Patricia | last3 = Smith | first3 = Barbara | title = All the women are White, all the Blacks are men, but some of us are brave: Black women's studies | publisher = [[Feminist Press]] | location = Old Westbury, NY| year = 1982 | isbn = 9780912670928 | url-access = registration |url=https://archive.org/details/allwomenarewhite00hull }}
&lt;/ref&gt; Simultaneity is explained as the simultaneous influences of race, class, gender, and sexuality, which informed the member's lives and their resistance to oppression.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Johnson|first=Amanda Walker|date=2 October 2017|title=Resituating the Crossroads: Theoretical Innovations in Black Feminist Ethnography|journal=Souls|volume=19|issue=4|pages=401–415|doi=10.1080/10999949.2018.1434350|s2cid=149590053|issn=1099-9949}}&lt;/ref&gt; Thus, the women of the Combahee River Collective advanced an understanding of African-American experiences that challenged analyses emerging from Black and male-centered social movements, as well as those from mainstream cisgender, white, middle-class, heterosexual feminists.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | last = Norman | first = Brian | title = 'We' in Redux: The Combahee River Collective's ''Black Feminist Statement'' | journal = [[Differences (journal)|differences: A Journal of Feminist Cultural Studies]] | volume = 18 | issue = 2 | page = 104 | doi = 10.1215/10407391-2007-004 | date = 2007 | ref = harv }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Since the term was coined, many feminist scholars have emerged with historical support for the intersectional theory. These women include [[Beverly Guy-Sheftall]] and her fellow contributors to ''Words of Fire: An Anthology of African-American Feminist Thought'', a collection of articles describing the multiple oppressions black women in America have experienced from the 1830s to contemporary times. Guy-Sheftall speaks about the constant premises that influence the lives of African-American women, saying, "Black women experience a special kind of oppression and suffering in this country which is racist, sexist, and classist because of their dual race and gender identity and their limited access to economic resources."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://archive.org/details/isbn_9781565842564|title=Words of fire : an anthology of African-American feminist thought|last=Guy-Sheftall|first=Beverly|date=1995|publisher=New Press|isbn=9781565842564|location=New York|access-date=7 May 2019|url-status=live|url-access=registration}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other writers and theorists were using intersectional analysis in their work before the term was coined. For example, Deborah K. King published the article "Multiple Jeopardy, Multiple Consciousness: The Context of a Black Feminist Ideology" in 1988, just before Crenshaw coined the term intersectionality. In the article King addresses what soon became the foundation for intersectionality, saying, "Black women have long recognized the special circumstances of our lives in the United States: the commonalities that we share with all women, as well as the bonds that connect us to the men of our race."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=King|first=Deborah K.|date=1988|title=Multiple Jeopardy, Multiple Consciousness: The Context of a Black Feminist Ideology|journal=Signs|volume=14|issue=1|pages=42–72|issn=0097-9740|jstor=3174661|doi=10.1086/494491|s2cid=143446946}}&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, [[Gloria Wekker]] describes how [[Gloria E. Anzaldúa|Gloria Anzaldúa]]'s work as a [[Chicana feminism|Chicana]] feminist theorist exemplifies how "existent categories for identity are strikingly not dealt with in separate or mutually exclusive terms, but are always referred to in relation to one another".&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{Cite book|title=Doing Gender in Media, Art and Culture: A Comprehensive Guide to Gender Studies|last=Buikema, Plate &amp; Thiele|first=R., L.K.|publisher=Routeledge|year=2009|isbn=978-0415493833|location=|pages=63–65}}&lt;/ref&gt; Wekker also points to the words and activism of [[Sojourner Truth]] as an example of an intersectional approach to social justice.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt; In her speech, "[[Ain't I a Woman?|Ain’t I a Woman?]]", Truth identifies the difference between the oppression of white and black women. She says that white women are often treated as emotional and delicate while black women are subjected to racist abuse. However, this was largely dismissed by white feminists who worried that this would distract from their goal of women's suffrage and instead focused their attention on emancipation.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Truth|first=Sojourner|title='Speech at the Woman's Rights Convention, Akron, Ohio' (1851)|chapter="Speech at the Woman's Rights Convention, Akron, Ohio" (1851)|work=Available Means|pages=144–146|publisher=University of Pittsburgh Press|isbn=9780822979753|doi=10.2307/j.ctt5hjqnj.28|year=2001}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Feminist thought==
{{Feminism sidebar}}
In 1989, [[Kimberlé Crenshaw]] coined the term "intersectionality" in a paper as a way to help explain the oppression of African-American women. Crenshaw's term is now at the forefront of national conversations about racial justice, identity politics, and policing—and over the years has helped shape legal discussions.&lt;ref name="Crenshaw 1" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Crenshaw 2" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":2"&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.newstatesman.com/lifestyle/2014/04/kimberl-crenshaw-intersectionality-i-wanted-come-everyday-metaphor-anyone-could|title=Kimberlé Crenshaw on intersectionality: 'I wanted to come up with an everyday metaphor that anyone could use'|date=2 April 2014|work=[[New Statesman]]|access-date=10 March 2016|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180518120135/https://www.newstatesman.com/lifestyle/2014/04/kimberl-crenshaw-intersectionality-i-wanted-come-everyday-metaphor-anyone-could|archive-date=18 May 2018|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; She used the term in her crucial 1989 paper for the University of Chicago Legal Forum, "Demarginalizing the Intersection of Race and Sex: A Black Feminist Critique of Anti-discrimination Doctrine, Feminist Theory and Antiracist Politics".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://archive.org/stream/DemarginalizingTheIntersectionOfRaceAndSexABlackFeminis/Demarginalizing+the+Intersection+of+Race+and+Sex_+A+Black+Feminis_djvu.txt|title=Full text of 'Demarginalizing The Intersection of Race And Sex A Black Feminis'|website=archive.org|access-date=23 August 2018|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20181229021802/https://archive.org/stream/DemarginalizingTheIntersectionOfRaceAndSexABlackFeminis/Demarginalizing+the+Intersection+of+Race+and+Sex_+A+Black+Feminis_djvu.txt|archive-date=29 December 2018|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Crenshaw 1989"&gt;{{cite journal | last = Crenshaw | first = Kimberlé | author-link = Kimberlé Williams Crenshaw | title = Demarginalizing the intersection of race and sex: a Black feminist critique of antidiscrimination doctrine, feminist theory and antiracist politics | journal = [[University of Chicago Legal Forum]] | volume = 1989 | pages = 139–168 | date = 1989 |url=http://heinonline.org/HOL/LandingPage?handle=hein.journals/uchclf1989&amp;div=10 | ref = harv | access-date = 2 June 2019 | archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20190428063633/https://heinonline.org/HOL/LandingPage?handle=hein.journals%2Fuchclf1989&amp;div=10 | archive-date = 28 April 2019 | url-status = live }}&lt;/ref&gt; In her work, Crenshaw discusses [[Black feminism]], arguing that the experience of being a black woman cannot be understood in independent terms of either being black or a woman. Rather, it must include interactions between the two identities, which, she adds, should frequently reinforce one another.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | last1 = Thomas | first1 = Sheila | last2 = Crenshaw | first2 = Kimberlé | author-link2 = Kimberlé Crenshaw | title = Intersectionality: the double bind of race and gender | work = Perspectives Magazine | date = Spring 2004 | page = 2 | publisher = [[American Bar Association]] | url = http://www.americanbar.org/content/dam/aba/publishing/perspectives_magazine/women_perspectives_Spring2004CrenshawPSP.authcheckdam.pdf | access-date = 14 June 2011 | archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20120118111551/http://www.americanbar.org/content/dam/aba/publishing/perspectives_magazine/women_perspectives_Spring2004CrenshawPSP.authcheckdam.pdf | archive-date = 18 January 2012 | url-status = dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In order to show that non-white women have a vastly different experience from white women due to their race and/or class and that their experiences are not easily voiced or amplified, Crenshaw explores two types of male violence against women: [[domestic violence]] and [[rape]]. Through her analysis of these two forms of male violence against women, Crenshaw says that the experiences of non-white women consist of a combination of both racism and sexism.&lt;ref name="Crenshaw 1991"&gt;{{cite journal | last = Crenshaw | first = Kimberlé | author-link = Kimberlé Williams Crenshaw |title=Mapping the margins: intersectionality, identity politics, and violence against women of color |journal=[[Stanford Law Review]] |volume=43 |issue=6 |pages=1241–1299 |jstor=1229039 |doi=10.2307/1229039 |date=July 1991 | ref = harv | citeseerx = 10.1.1.695.5934 }}&lt;/ref&gt; She says that because non-white women are present within discourses that have been designed to address either race or sex—but not both at the same time—non-white women are marginalized within both of these systems of oppression as a result.&lt;ref name="Crenshaw 1991" /&gt;

In her work, Crenshaw identifies three aspects of intersectionality that affect the visibility of non-white women: structural intersectionality, political intersectionality, and representational intersectionality. Structural intersectionality deals with how non-white women experience domestic violence and rape in a manner qualitatively different than that of white women. Political intersectionality examines how laws and policies intended to increase equality have paradoxically decreased the visibility of violence against non-white women. Finally, representational intersectionality delves into how [[Popular culture|pop culture]] portrayals of non-white women can obscure their own authentic lived experiences.&lt;ref name="Crenshaw 1991" /&gt;

== Three aspects of intersectionality ==
In Kimberle Crenshaw's, Crenshaw Mapping Margins, she uses and explains three different forms of intersectionality to describe the violence that women experience. According to Crenshaw, there are three forms of intersectionality: structural, political, and representational intersectionality. 

Structural intersectionality is used to describe how different structures work together and create a complex which highlights the differences in the experiences of women of color with domestic violence and rape. Structural intersectionality entails the ways in which classism, sexism, and racism interlock and oppress women of color while molding their experiences in different arenas. Crenshaw's analysis of structural intersectionality was used during her field study of battered women. In this study, Crenshaw uses intersectionality to display the multilayered oppressions that women who are victims of domestic violence face. &lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

Political intersectionality highlights two conflicting systems in the political arena, which separates women and women of color into two subordinate groups. &lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; The experiences of women of color differ from those of white women and men of color due to their race and gender often intersecting. White women suffer from gender bias, and men of color suffer from racial bias; however, both of their experiences differ from that of women of color, because women of color experience both racial and gender bias. According to Crenshaw, a political failure of the antiracist and feminist discourses was the exclusion of the intersection of race and gender that places priority on the interest of "people of color" and "women," thus disregarding one while highlighting the other. Political engagement should reflect support of women of color; a prime example of the exclusion of women of color that shows the difference in the experiences of white women and women of color is the women's suffrage march.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=King|first=Deborah K.|date=October 1988|title=Multiple Jeopardy, Multiple Consciousness: The Context of a Black Feminist Ideology|url=http://dx.doi.org/10.1086/494491|journal=Signs: Journal of Women in Culture and Society|volume=14|issue=1|pages=42–72|doi=10.1086/494491|s2cid=143446946|issn=0097-9740}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Representational intersectionality advocates for the creation of imagery that is supportive of women of color. Representational intersectionality condemns sexist and racist marginalization of women of color in representation. Representational intersectionality also highlights the importance of women of color having representation in media and contemporary settings.

The term gained prominence in the 1990s, particularly in the wake of the further development of Crenshaw's work in the writings of sociologist [[Patricia Hill Collins]]. Crenshaw's term, Collins says, replaced her own previous coinage "black feminist thought", and "increased the general applicability of her theory from African American women to all women".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | last1 = Mann | first1 = Susan A. | last2 = Huffman | first2 = Douglas J. | title = The decentering of second wave feminism and the rise of the third wave | journal = [[Science &amp; Society]] | volume = 69 | issue = 1 | pages = 56–91 | jstor = 40404229 | date = January 2005 | ref = harv | doi=10.1521/siso.69.1.56.56799}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|61}} Much like Crenshaw, Collins argues that cultural patterns of oppression are not only interrelated, but are bound together and influenced by the intersectional systems of society, such as race, gender, class, and ethnicity.&lt;ref name="Collins 2000"/&gt;{{rp|42}} Collins describes this as "interlocking social institutions [that] have relied on multiple forms of segregation... to produce unjust results".&lt;ref&gt;Collins, Patricia Hill (2009) [1990], "[https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=icWTAgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA277 Towards a politics of empowerment] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171202203045/https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=icWTAgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA277 |date=2 December 2017 }}", in {{cite book | editor-last = Collins | editor-first = Patricia Hill | editor-link = Patricia Hill Collins | title = Black feminist thought: knowledge, consciousness, and the politics of empowerment | page = 277 | publisher = Routledge | location = New York | edition = 2nd | isbn = 9780415964722 | title-link = Black Feminist Thought | year = 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Collins sought to create frameworks to think about intersectionality, rather than expanding on the theory itself. She identified three main branches of study within intersectionality. One branch deals with the background, ideas, issues, conflicts, and debates within intersectionality. Another branch seeks to apply intersectionality as an analytical strategy to various [[social institutions]] in order to examine how they might perpetuate social inequality. The final branch formulates intersectionality as a critical praxis to determine how [[social justice]] initiatives can use intersectionality to bring about social change.&lt;ref name="Collins 2015"&gt;{{cite journal |last=Collins|first=Patricia H. | author-link = Patricia Hill Collins | title = Intersectionality's definitional dilemmas | journal = [[Annual Review of Sociology]] | volume = 41 | pages = 1–20 | doi = 10.1146/annurev-soc-073014-112142 | date = 2015 | ref = harv | doi-access = free }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The ideas behind intersectional feminism existed long before the term was coined. [[Sojourner Truth]]'s 1851 "Ain't I a Woman?" speech, for example, exemplifies intersectionality, in which she spoke from her racialized position as a former slave to critique essentialist notions of femininity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Brah |first1=Avtar |author-link=Avtar Brah|last2=Phoenix |first2=Ann |title=Ain't I A Woman? Revisiting intersectionality |journal=Journal of International Women's Studies |volume=5 |issue=3 |pages=75–86 |date=2004 |url=http://vc.bridgew.edu/jiws/vol5/iss3/8/ |ref=harv |access-date=1 December 2017 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171202052913/http://vc.bridgew.edu/jiws/vol5/iss3/8/ |archive-date=2 December 2017 |url-status=live }} [http://vc.bridgew.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1543&amp;context=jiws Pdf.] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171202053102/http://vc.bridgew.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1543&amp;context=jiws |date=2 December 2017 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, in her 1892 essay, "The Colored Woman's Office", [[Anna J. Cooper|Anna Julia Cooper]] identifies black women as the most important actors in social change movements, because of their experience with multiple facets of oppression.&lt;ref name=Cooper2009&gt;Cooper, Anna Julia (2017) [1892], "[https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=ONFVDgAAQBAJ The colored woman's office] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171202052813/https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=ONFVDgAAQBAJ |date=2 December 2017 }}", in {{cite book |editor-last = Lemert|editor-first = Charles | title = Social theory: the multicultural, global, and classic readings | publisher = Westview Press | location = Boulder, Colorado | edition = 6th | isbn = 9780813350448 |date = 2016 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Collins has located the origins of intersectionality among black feminists, [[Chicana feminism|Chicana]] and other Latina feminists, [[indigenous feminists]] and Asian American feminists in the 1960s, 1970s and 1980s, and noted the existence of intellectuals at other times and in other places who discussed similar ideas about the interaction of different forms of inequality, such as [[Stuart Hall (cultural theorist)|Stuart Hall]] and the [[cultural studies]] movement, [[Nira Yuval-Davis]], Anna Julia Cooper and [[Ida B. Wells]]. She noted that as [[second-wave feminism]] receded in the 1980s, feminists of color such as Audre Lorde, [[Gloria E. Anzaldúa]] and [[Angela Davis]] entered academic environments and brought their perspectives to their scholarship. During this decade many of the ideas that would together be labeled as "intersectionality" coalesced in US academia under the banner of "race, class and gender studies".&lt;ref name="Collins 2015" /&gt;

A key writer who focused on intersectionality was [[Audre Lorde]], who was a self-proclaimed "Black, Lesbian, Mother, Warrior, Poet".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www.poetryfoundation.org/poets/audre-lorde |title = Audre Lorde|date = 15 May 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt; Even in the title she gave herself, Lorde expressed her multifaceted personhood and demonstrated her intersectional struggles with being a black, gay woman. Lorde commented in her essay "The master’s tools will never dismantle the master’s house" that she was living in "a country where racism, sexism, and homophobia are inseparable".&lt;ref&gt;http://s18.middlebury.edu/AMST0325A/Lorde_The_Masters_Tools.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; Here, Lorde perfectly outlines the importance of intersectionality as she acknowledges that different prejudices are inherently linked.

Though intersectionality began with the exploration of the interplay between gender and race, over time other identities and oppressions were added to the theory. For example, in 1981 [[Cherríe Moraga]] and [[Gloria E. Anzaldúa|Gloria Anzaldúa]] published the first edition of ''[[This Bridge Called My Back]]''. This anthology explored how classifications of sexual orientation and class also mix with those of race and gender to create even more distinct political categories. Many black, Latina, and Asian writers featured in the collection stress how their sexuality interacts with their race and gender to inform their perspectives. Similarly, poor women of color detail how their socio-economic status adds a layer of nuance to their identities, ignored or misunderstood by middle-class white feminists.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |editor-last1=Moraga|editor-first1=Cherríe|editor-last2=Anzaldúa|editor-first2=Gloria |editor-link1=Cherríe Moraga|editor-link2=Gloria E. Anzaldúa | title = This bridge called my back: writings by radical women of color | publisher = State University of New York (SUNY) Press | location = Albany | year = 2015 | edition = 4th | isbn = 9781438454382 |title-link=This Bridge Called My Back}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to black feminists and many white feminists, experiences of class, gender, and sexuality cannot be adequately understood unless the influence of racialization is carefully considered. This focus on racialization was highlighted many times by scholar and feminist [[bell hooks]], specifically in her 1981 book ''[[Ain't I a Woman? (book)|Ain't I A Woman: Black Women and Feminism]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = hooks | first = bell | author-link = bell hooks | title = [[Ain't I a Woman? (book)|Ain't I a Woman: Black Women and Feminism]] | publisher = Pluto Press South End Press | location = London &amp; Boston, MA | year = 1981 | isbn = 978-0-86104-379-8 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Feminists argue that an understanding of intersectionality is a vital element of gaining political and social equality and improving our democratic system.&lt;ref&gt;D'Agostino, Maria; Levine, Helisse (2011), "[https://books.google.com/books?id=dkOypf17LjgC&amp;pg=PA8 Feminist theories and their application to public administration]", in {{cite book| editor-last1 = D'Agostino | editor-first1 = Maria | editor-last2 = Levine | editor-first2 = Helisse | title = Women in Public Administration: theory and practice | page=8 | publisher = Jones &amp; Bartlett Learning | location = Sudbury, MA | year = 2011 | isbn = 9780763777258}}&lt;/ref&gt; Collins's theory represents the sociological crossroads between [[second-wave feminism|modern]] and [[Post-modern feminism|post-modern feminist thought]].&lt;ref name="Collins 2000"&gt;{{Cite journal | last = Collins | first = Patricia Hill | author-link = Patricia Hill Collins | title = Gender, black feminism, and black political economy | journal = [[Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social Science]] | volume = 568 | issue = 1 | pages = 41–53 | doi = 10.1177/000271620056800105 | date = March 2000 | s2cid = 146255922 | ref = harv }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Marie-Claire Belleau]] argues for "strategic intersectionality" in order to foster cooperation between feminisms of different ethnicities.&lt;ref name="Belleau, Marie-Claire 2007"&gt;Belleau, Marie-Claire (2007), "[https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=IuzvBBhq7-IC&amp;pg=PA51 'L'intersectionalité': Feminisms in a divided world; Québec-Canada] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171202053002/https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=IuzvBBhq7-IC&amp;pg=PA51 |date=2 December 2017 }}", in {{cite book | editor-last1 = Orr | editor-first1 = Deborah | title = Feminist Politics: identity, difference, and agency| pages = 51–62 | publisher = Rowman &amp; Littlefield Publishers | location = Lanham, MD | isbn = 978-0-7425-4778-0 | ref = harv |display-editors=etal| year = 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|51}} She refers to different ''nat-cult'' (national-cultural) groups that produce different types of feminisms. Using [[Culture of Quebec|Québécois]] nat-cult as an example, Belleau says that many nat-cult groups contain infinite sub-identities within themselves, arguing that there are endless ways in which different feminisms can cooperate by using strategic intersectionality, and that these partnerships can help bridge gaps between "dominant and marginal" groups.&lt;ref name="Belleau, Marie-Claire 2007"/&gt;{{rp|54}} Belleau argues that, through strategic intersectionality, differences between nat-cult feminisms are neither essentialist nor universal, but should be understood as resulting from socio-cultural contexts. Furthermore, the performances of these nat-cult feminisms are also not essentialist. Instead, they are strategies.&lt;ref name="Belleau, Marie-Claire 2007"/&gt;

Similarly, Intersectional theorists like Vrushali Patil argue that intersectionality ought to recognize transborder constructions of racial and cultural hierarchies. About the effect of the state on identity formation, Patil says: "If we continue to neglect cross-border dynamics and fail to problematize the nation and its emergence via transnational processes, our analyses will remain tethered to the spatialities and temporalities of colonial modernity."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Patil|first=Vrushali|date=1 June 2013|title=From Patriarchy to Intersectionality: A Transnational Feminist Assessment of How Far We've Really Come|journal=Signs: Journal of Women in Culture and Society|volume=38|issue=4|pages=847–867|doi=10.1086/669560|jstor=10.1086/669560|s2cid=144680534|issn=0097-9740}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Marxist feminist critical theory ===
{{Marxism}}
[[W. E. B. Du Bois]] theorized that the intersectional paradigms of race, class, and nation might explain certain aspects of the black political economy. Collins writes: "Du Bois saw race, class, and nation not primarily as personal identity categories but as social hierarchies that shaped African-American access to status, poverty, and power."&lt;ref name="Collins 2000"/&gt;{{rp|44}} Du Bois omitted gender from his theory and considered it more of a personal identity category.

Cheryl Townsend Gilkes expands on this by pointing out the value of centering on the experiences of black women. Joy James takes things one step further by "using paradigms of intersectionality in interpreting social phenomena". Collins later integrated these three views by examining a black political economy through the centering of black women's experiences and the use of a theoretical framework of intersectionality.&lt;ref name="Collins 2000"/&gt;{{rp|44}}

Collins uses a [[Marxist feminism|Marxist feminist]] approach and applies her intersectional principles to what she calls the "work/family nexus and black women's poverty". In her 2000 article "Black Political Economy" she describes how, in her view, the intersections of [[consumer racism]], gender hierarchies, and disadvantages in the labor market can be centered on black women's unique experiences. Considering this from a historical perspective and examining interracial marriage laws and property inheritance laws creates what Collins terms a "distinctive work/family nexus that in turn influences the overall patterns of black political economy".&lt;ref name="Collins 2000"/&gt;{{rp|45–46}} For example, [[anti-miscegenation laws]] effectively suppressed the upward economic mobility of black women.

The intersectionality of race and gender has been shown to have a visible impact on the labor market. "Sociological research clearly shows that accounting for education, experience, and skill does not fully explain significant differences in labor market outcomes."&lt;ref name="arjournals.annualreviews.org"&gt;{{Cite journal | last1 = Browne | first1 = Irene | last2 = Misra | first2 = Joya | title = The intersection of gender and race in the labor market | journal = [[Annual Review of Sociology]] | volume = 29 | pages = 487–513 | doi = 10.1146/annurev.soc.29.010202.100016 | date = August 2003 |jstor=30036977| ref = harv }} [https://www.researchgate.net/publication/249558187_The_Intersection_of_Gender_and_Race_in_the_Labor_Market Pdf.] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171202052740/https://www.researchgate.net/publication/249558187_The_Intersection_of_Gender_and_Race_in_the_Labor_Market |date=2 December 2017 }}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|506}} The three main domains in which we see the impact of intersectionality are wages, discrimination, and domestic labor. Those who experience privilege within the social hierarchy in terms of race, gender and socio-economic status are less likely to receive lower wages, to be subjected to stereotypes and discriminated against, or to be hired for exploitative domestic positions. Studies of the labor market and intersectionality provide a better understanding of economic inequalities and the implications of the multidimensional impact of race and gender on social status within society.&lt;ref name="arjournals.annualreviews.org"/&gt;{{rp|506–507}}

==Key concepts==
===Interlocking matrix of oppression===
Collins refers to the various intersections of social inequality as the [[matrix of domination]]. These are also known as "vectors of oppression and privilege".&lt;ref name="Ritzer 2013"&gt;{{cite book |last1= Ritzer|first1= George|author1-link = George Ritzer |last2=Stepinisky |first2=Jeffrey|title = Contemporary sociological theory and its classical roots: the basics|pages = 204–207|publisher = McGraw-Hill|location = New York|edition = 4th|year = 2013|isbn = 9780078026782 }}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|204}} These terms refer to how differences among people (sexual orientation, class, race, age, etc.) serve as oppressive measures towards women and change the experience of living as a woman in society. Collins, [[Audre Lorde]] (in ''[[Sister Outsider]]''), and [[bell hooks]] point towards either/or thinking as an influence on this oppression and as further intensifying these differences.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last = Dudley | first = Rachel A. | title = Confronting the concept of intersectionality: the legacy of Audre Lorde and contemporary feminist organizations | journal = McNair Scholars Journal | volume = 10 | issue = 1 | page = 5 | date = 2006 |url=https://scholarworks.gvsu.edu/mcnair/vol10/iss1/5/ | ref = harv | access-date = 1 December 2017 | archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171201081159/https://scholarworks.gvsu.edu/mcnair/vol10/iss1/5/ | archive-date = 1 December 2017 | url-status = live }}&lt;/ref&gt; Specifically, Collins refers to this as the construct of dichotomous oppositional difference. This construct is characterized by its focus on differences rather than similarities.&lt;ref name="Collins 1986"&gt;{{Cite journal | last = Collins | first = Patricia Hill | author-link = Patricia Hill Collins | title = Learning from the outsider within: the sociological significance of black feminist thought | journal = [[Social Problems]] | volume = 33 | issue = 6 | pages = s14–s32 | doi = 10.2307/800672 | jstor = 800672 | date = December 1986 | s2cid = 144491582 | ref = harv |url=https://semanticscholar.org/paper/03dd3bed8380886350c5dac7e20297a3c48c67df }}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|S20}} Lisa A. Flores suggests, when individuals live in the borders, they "find themselves with a foot in both worlds". The result is "the sense of being neither" exclusively one identity nor another.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Flores|first=Lisa A.|date=1996-05-01|title=Creating discursive space through a rhetoric of difference: Chicana feminists craft a homeland|url=https://doi.org/10.1080/00335639609384147|journal=Quarterly Journal of Speech|volume=82|issue=2|pages=142–156|doi=10.1080/00335639609384147|issn=0033-5630}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Standpoint epistemology and the outsider within===
Both Collins and [[Dorothy E. Smith|Dorothy Smith]] have been instrumental in providing a sociological definition of [[standpoint theory]]. A standpoint is an individual's world perspective. The theoretical basis of this approach views societal knowledge as being located within an individual's specific geographic location. In turn, knowledge becomes distinct and subjective; it varies depending on the social conditions under which it was produced.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | last1 = Mann | first1 = Susan A. | last2 = Kelley | first2 = Lori R. | title = Standing at the crossroads of modernist thought: Collins, Smith, and the new feminist epistemologies | journal = [[Gender &amp; Society]] | volume = 11 | issue = 4 | pages = 391–408 | doi = 10.1177/089124397011004002 | date = August 1997 | s2cid = 55757598 | ref = harv }}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|392}}

The concept of the outsider within refers to a standpoint encompassing the [[Self (sociology)|self]], family, and society.&lt;ref name="Collins 1986"/&gt;{{rp|S14}} This relates to the specific experiences to which people are subjected as they move from a common cultural world (i.e., family) to that of modern society.&lt;ref name="Ritzer 2013" /&gt;{{rp|207}} Therefore, even though a woman—especially a Black woman—may become influential in a particular field, she may feel as though she does not belong. Her personality, behavior, and cultural being overshadow her value as an individual; thus, she becomes the outsider within.&lt;ref name="Collins 1986"/&gt;{{rp|S14}}

===Resisting oppression===
Speaking from a [[critical theory|critical]] standpoint, Collins points out that Brittan and Maynard say that "domination always involves the [[objectification]] of the dominated; all forms of oppression imply the devaluation of the subjectivity of the oppressed".&lt;ref name="Collins 1986"/&gt;{{rp|S18}} She later notes that self-valuation and self-definition are two ways of resisting oppression, and claims the practice of [[self-awareness]] helps to preserve the self-esteem of the group that is being oppressed while allowing them to avoid any [[Dehumanization|dehumanizing]] outside influences.

Marginalized groups often gain a status of being an "other".&lt;ref name="Collins 1986"/&gt;{{rp|S18}} In essence, you are "an other" if you are different from what [[Audre Lorde]] calls the [[Normality (behaviour)|mythical norm]]. [[Gloria Anzaldúa]], scholar of Chicana cultural theory, theorized that the sociological term for this is "[[othering]]", i.e. specifically attempting to establish a person as unacceptable based on a certain, unachieved criterion.&lt;ref name="Ritzer 2013" /&gt;{{rp|205}}

==Praxis==
{{Globalize|section|USA|2name=the United States|date=March 2017}}
Intersectionality can be applied to nearly all fields from politics,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last = Hancock | first = Ange-Marie | title = Intersectionality as a normative and empirical paradigm | journal = [[Politics &amp; Gender]] | volume = 3 | issue = 2 | pages = 248–254 | doi = 10.1017/S1743923X07000062 | date = June 2007 | ref = harv }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last = Holvino | first = Evangelina | title = Intersections: The simultaneity of race, gender and class in organization studies | journal = [[Gender, Work &amp; Organization]] | volume = 17 | issue = 3 | pages = 248–277 | doi = 10.1111/j.1468-0432.2008.00400.x | date = May 2010 | ref = harv }}&lt;/ref&gt; education&lt;ref name="journals.uchicago.edu"/&gt;&lt;ref name=Cooper2009/&gt;&lt;ref name="Jones 2003"&gt;{{cite journal | last = Jones | first = Sandra J. | title = Complex subjectivities: class, ethnicity, and race in women's narratives of upward mobility | journal = [[Journal of Social Issues]] | volume = 59 | issue = 4 | pages = 803–820 | doi = 10.1046/j.0022-4537.2003.00091.x | date = December 2003 | ref = harv }}&lt;/ref&gt; healthcare,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last = Kelly | first = Ursula A. | title = Integrating intersectionality and biomedicine in health disparities research | journal = Advances in Nursing Science | volume = 32 | issue = 2 | pages = E42–E56 | doi = 10.1097/ANS.0b013e3181a3b3fc | pmid = 19461221 | date = April–June 2009 | s2cid = 26510963 | ref = harv }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Viruell-Fuentes et al 2012" /&gt; and employment, to economics.&lt;ref name="Ladson-Billings Tate 1995" /&gt; For example, within the institution of education, Sandra Jones' research on working-class women in academia takes into consideration meritocracy within all social strata, but argues that it is complicated by race and the external forces that oppress.&lt;ref name="Jones 2003" /&gt; Additionally, people of color often experience differential treatment in the healthcare system. For example, in the period immediately after [[9/11]] researchers noted [[low birth weight]]s and other poor birth outcomes among Muslim and Arab Americans, a result they connected to the increased racial and religious discrimination of the time.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last = Lauderdale | first = Diane S. | title = Birth outcomes for Arabic-named women in California before and after September 11 | journal = [[Demography (journal)|Demography]] | volume = 43 | issue = 1 | pages = 185–201 | doi = 10.1353/dem.2006.0008 | pmid = 16579214 | date = February 2006 | s2cid = 12752541 | ref = harv }} [http://www.rwj.harvard.edu/papers/Lauderdale.pdf Pdf.] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170202111403/http://www.rwj.harvard.edu/papers/Lauderdale.pdf |date=2 February 2017 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Some researchers have also argued that immigration policies can affect health outcomes through mechanisms such as [[Stress (biology)#Overview|stress]], restrictions on access to health care, and the [[social determinants of health]].&lt;ref name="Viruell-Fuentes et al 2012"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Viruell-Fuentes |first1=Edna A. |last2=Miranda |first2=Patricia Y. |last3=Abdulrahim |first3=Sawsan | title = More than culture: Structural racism, intersectionality theory, and immigrant health | journal = [[Social Science &amp; Medicine]] | volume = 75 | issue = 12 | pages = 2099–2106 | doi = 10.1016/j.socscimed.2011.12.037 | pmid = 22386617 | date = December 2012 | ref = harv }} [http://sph.umd.edu/sites/default/files/files/che/Viruell%20Fuentes%20et%20al%202012%20SSM%20More%20than%20Culture%20Structural%20Racism.pdf Pdf.] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170202011018/http://sph.umd.edu/sites/default/files/files/che/Viruell%20Fuentes%20et%20al%202012%20SSM%20More%20than%20Culture%20Structural%20Racism.pdf |date=2 February 2017 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Women's Institute for Science, Equity and Race]] advocates for the disaggregation of data in order to highlight intersectional identities in all kinds of research.&lt;ref&gt;Ryssdal, Kai (2020-06-08). "How's the economy? vs. how's the economy for each of us?". Marketplace. Retrieved 2020-10-09.&lt;/ref&gt;

Additionally, applications with regard to property and wealth can be traced to the American historical narrative that is filled "with tensions and struggles over property—in its various forms. From the removal of Native Americans (and later [[Internment of Japanese Americans|Japanese Americans]]) from the land, to military conquest of the Mexicans, to the construction of Africans as property, the ability to define, possess, and own property has been a central feature of power in America&amp;nbsp;... [and where] social benefits accrue largely to property owners."&lt;ref name="Ladson-Billings Tate 1995"&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Ladson-Billings | first1 = Gloria | last2 = Tate IV | first2 = William F. | title = Toward a critical race theory of education (''id: 1410'') | journal = [[Teachers College Record]] | volume = 97 | issue = 1 | pages = 47–68 | date = 1995 |url=https://www.tcrecord.org/content.asp?contentid=1410 | ref = harv | access-date = 1 December 2017 | archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171201081700/https://www.tcrecord.org/content.asp?contentid=1410 | archive-date = 1 December 2017 | url-status = live }} [http://hs.iastate.edu/wp-content/uploads/2011/01/Toward_a_Critical_Race_Theory_of_Education.pdf Pdf.] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20161005230338/http://hs.iastate.edu/wp-content/uploads/2011/01/Toward_a_Critical_Race_Theory_of_Education.pdf |date=5 October 2016 }}&lt;/ref&gt; One could apply the intersectionality framework analysis to various areas where race, class, gender, sexuality and ability are affected by policies, procedures, practices, and laws in "context-specific inquiries, including, for example, analyzing the multiple ways that race and gender interact with class in the labor market; interrogating the ways that states constitute regulatory regimes of identity, reproduction, and family formation";&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Cho |first1=Sumi |last2=Crenshaw |first2=Kimberlé Williams |last3=McCall |first3=Leslie | title = Toward a field of intersectionality studies: theory, applications, and praxis | journal = [[Signs (journal)|Signs: Journal of Women in Culture and Society]] | volume = 38 | issue = 4 | pages = 785–810 | doi = 10.1086/669608 | jstor = 10.1086/669608 | date =Summer 2013 |s2cid=143982074 | ref = harv |url=https://via.library.depaul.edu/lawfacpubs/705 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and examining the inequities in "the power relations [of the intersectionality] of whiteness&amp;nbsp;... [where] the denial of power and privilege&amp;nbsp;... of whiteness, and middle-classness", while not addressing "the role of power it wields in social relations".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last = Levine-Rasky | first = Cynthia | title = Intersectionality theory applied to whiteness and middle-classness | journal = Social Identities: Journal for the Study of Race, Nation and Culture | volume = 17 | issue = 2 | pages = 239–253 | doi = 10.1080/13504630.2011.558377 | date = 2011 | s2cid = 145104826 | ref = harv }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Intersectionality in a global context===
[[file:Dyke*Line auf dem Jungfernstieg und neuen Jungfernstieg und auf Booten auf der Binnenalster 002.jpg|thumb|Intersectionality at a Dyke March in Hamburg, Germany, 2020]]
Over the last couple of decades in the [[European Union]] (EU), there has been discussion regarding the intersections of social classifications. Before Crenshaw coined her definition of intersectionality, there was a debate on what these societal categories were. The once definite borders between the categories of gender, race, and class has instead fused into a multidimensional intersection of "race" that now includes religion, sexuality, ethnicities, etc. In the EU and UK, these intersections are referred to as the notion of "multiple discrimination." Although, the EU passed a non-discrimination law which addresses these multiple intersections; there is  however debate on whether the law is still proactively focusing on the proper inequalities.&lt;ref&gt;Lawson, Anna. European Union Non-Discrimination Law and Intersectionality : Investigating the Triangle of Racial, Gender and Disability Discrimination, edited by Dagmar Schiek, Routledge, 2011. ProQuest Ebook Central&lt;/ref&gt;{{page needed|date=July 2020}} Outside of the EU, intersectional categories have also been considered. In ''Analyzing Gender, Intersectionality, and Multiple Inequalities: Global, Transnational and Local Contexts'', the authors argue: "The impact of patriarchy and traditional assumptions about gender and families are evident in the lives of Chinese migrant workers (Chow, Tong), sex workers and their clients in South Korea (Shin), and Indian widows (Chauhan), but also Ukrainian migrants (Amelina) and Australian men of the new global middle class (Connell)." This text suggests that there are many more intersections of discrimination for people around the globe than Crenshaw originally accounted for in her definition.&lt;ref&gt;Analyzing Gender, Intersectionality, and Multiple Inequalities: Global, Transnational and Local Contexts, edited by Esther Ngan-ling Chow, and Tan Lin, Emerald Publishing Limited, 2011. ProQuest Ebook Central&lt;/ref&gt;

Chandra Mohanty discusses alliances between women throughout the world as intersectionality in a global context. She rejects the western feminist theory, especially when it writes about global women of color and generally associated "third world women". She argues that "third world women" are often thought of as a homogenous entity, when, in fact, their experience of oppression is informed by their geography, history, and culture. When western feminists write about women in the global South in this way, they dismiss the inherent intersecting identities that are present in the dynamic of feminism in the global South. Mohanty questions the performance of intersectionality and relationality of power structures within the US and colonialism and how to work across identities with this history of colonial power structures.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Mohanty|first=Chandra|date=Spring-Autumn 1984|title=Under Western Eyes: Feminist Scholarship and Colonial Discourses|url=|journal=Boundary 2|volume=12|issue=3|pages=333–358|doi=10.2307/302821|jstor=302821}}&lt;/ref&gt; This lack of homogeneity and intersecting identities can be seen through [[Feminism in India]], which goes over how women in India practice feminism within social structures and the continuing effects of colonization that differ from that of Western and other non-Western countries.

This is elaborated on by Christine Bose, who discusses a global use of intersectionality which works to remove associations of specific inequalities with specific institutions, while showing that these systems generate intersectional effects. She uses this approach to develop a framework that can analyze gender inequalities across different nations and differentiates this from an approach (the one that Mohanty was referring to) which, one, paints national-level inequalities as the same and, two, differentiates only between the global North and South. This is manifested through the intersection of global dynamics like economics, migration, or violence, with regional dynamics, like histories of the nation or gendered inequalities in education and property education.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Bose|first=Christine E.|date=2012|title=Intersectionality and Global Gender Inequality|journal=Gender and Society|volume=26|issue=1|pages=67–72|issn=0891-2432|jstor=23212241|doi=10.1177/0891243211426722|s2cid=145233506}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There is an issue globally with the way the law interacts with intersectionality, for example, the UK's legislation to protect workers rights has a distinct issue with intersectionality. Under the Equality Act 2010, the things that are listed as 'protected characteristics' are "age, disability, gender reassignment, marriage or civil partnership, pregnancy and maternity, race, religion or belief, sex and sexual orientation".&lt;ref name="farrer.co.uk"&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www.farrer.co.uk/news-and-insights/blogs/intersectionality-what-is-it-and-why-does-it-matter-for-employers/# |title = Intersectionality: What is it and why does it matter for employers?}}&lt;/ref&gt; "Section 14 contains a provision to cover direct discrimination on up to two combined grounds—known as combined or dual discrimination. However, this section has never been brought into effect as the government deemed it too 'complicated and burdensome' for businesses."&lt;ref name="farrer.co.uk"/&gt; This demonstrates a systematic neglect of the issues that intersectionality presents, because the UK courts have explicitly decided not to cover intersectional discrimination in their courts.

===Transnational intersectionality===
[[Postcolonial feminism|Third World feminists]] and [[transnational feminism|transnational feminists]] criticize intersectionality as a concept emanating from [[WEIRD]] (Western, educated, industrialized, rich, democratic)&lt;ref name="WEIRD 2010"&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Henrich | first1 = J. | last2 = Heine | first2 = S. J. | last3 = Norenzayan | first3 = A. | title = The weirdest people in the world? | journal = Behavioral and Brain Sciences | volume = 33 | issue = 2–3| pages = 61–83| doi = 10.1017/S0140525X0999152X | pmid = 20550733 | date = 2010 | ref = }}&lt;/ref&gt; societies that unduly universalizes women's experiences.&lt;ref name="Herr2014"&gt;{{cite journal | last = Herr | first = R. S. | title = Reclaiming third world feminism: Or why transnational feminism needs third world feminism. | journal = Meridians | volume = 12 | pages = 1–30 | doi = 10.2979/meridians.12.1.1 | date = 2014 | s2cid = 145668809 | ref = |url=https://philpapers.org/rec/HERRTW }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="KurtisAdams2015"&gt;{{Cite journal | last1 = Kurtis | first1 = T. | last2 = Adams | first2 = G. | title = Decolonizing liberation: Toward a transnational feminist psychology | journal = Journal of Social and Political Psychology | volume = 3 | issue = 2| pages = 388–413 | doi = 10.5964/jspp.v3i1.326 | jstor = 3178747 | date = 2015 | ref = | doi-access = free }}&lt;/ref&gt; Third world feminists have worked to revise Western conceptualizations of intersectionality that assume all women experience the same type of gender and racial oppression.&lt;ref name="Herr2014" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Transnational Psychology"&gt;{{cite book | last1 = Collins | first1 = L. H. | last2 = Machizawa | first2 = S. | last3 = Rice | first3 = J. K. | title = Transnational Psychology of Women: Expanding International and Intersectional Approaches | publisher = American Psychological Association | location = Washington, DC| year = 2019 | edition = 1st | isbn = 978-1-4338-3069-3 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Shelly Grabe coined the term "transnational intersectionality" to represent a more comprehensive conceptualization of intersectionality. Grabe wrote, "Transnational intersectionality places importance on the intersections among gender, ethnicity, sexuality, economic exploitation, and other social hierarchies in the context of empire building or imperialist policies characterized by historical and emergent [[global capitalism]]."&lt;ref name="Grabe2012"&gt;{{Cite journal | last1 = Grabe | first1 = S. | last2 = Else-Quest | first2 = N. M. | title = The role of transnational feminism in psychology: Complementary visions | journal = [[Psychology of Women Quarterly]] | volume = 36 | pages = 158–161 | doi = 10.1177/0361684312442164| jstor = | date = 2012 | s2cid = 53585351 | ref = |url=https://semanticscholar.org/paper/f3d2c24a5a24cb2345772b5538a416de6c32c470 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Both Third World and transnational feminists advocate attending to "complex and intersecting oppressions and multiple forms of resistance".&lt;ref name="Herr2014" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Transnational Psychology" /&gt;

===Social work===
In the field of [[social work]], proponents of intersectionality hold that unless service providers take intersectionality into account, they will be of less use for various segments of the population, such as those reporting domestic violence or disabled victims of abuse. According to intersectional theory, the practice of [[domestic violence]] counselors in the [[United States]] urging all women to report their abusers to police is of little use to [[women of color]] due to the history of racially motivated [[police brutality]], and those counselors should adapt their counseling for women of color.&lt;ref&gt;Bent-Goodley, Tricia B.; Chase, Lorraine; Circo, Elizabeth A.; Antá Rodgers, Selena T. (2010), "[https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=IiRKrWlceK0C&amp;pg=PA77 Our survival, our strengths: understanding the experiences of African American women in abusive relationships] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171202053000/https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=IiRKrWlceK0C&amp;pg=PA77 |date=2 December 2017 }}", in {{cite book | editor-last1 = Lockhart | editor-first1 = Lettie | editor-last2 = Danis | editor-first2 = Fran S. | title = Domestic violence intersectionality and culturally competent practice | page = [https://archive.org/details/domesticviolence0000unse_e7x2/page/77 77] | publisher = Columbia University Press | location = New York | isbn = 9780231140270 | year = 2010 |url=https://archive.org/details/domesticviolence0000unse_e7x2/page/77 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Women with disabilities encounter more frequent domestic abuse with a greater number of abusers. Health care workers and personal care attendants perpetrate abuse in these circumstances, and women with disabilities have fewer options for escaping the abusive situation.&lt;ref name="Lochart_Danis_131"&gt;Cramer, Elizabeth P.; Plummer, Sara-Beth (2010), "[https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=IiRKrWlceK0C&amp;pg=PA131 Social work practice with abused persons with disabilities] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171202053140/https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=IiRKrWlceK0C&amp;pg=PA131 |date=2 December 2017 }}", in {{cite book | editor-last1 = Lockhart | editor-first1 = Lettie | editor-last2 = Danis | editor-first2 = Fran S. | title = Domestic violence intersectionality and culturally competent practice | pages = [https://archive.org/details/domesticviolence0000unse_e7x2/page/131 131–134] | publisher = Columbia University Press | location = New York | isbn = 9780231140270 | year = 2010 |url=https://archive.org/details/domesticviolence0000unse_e7x2/page/131 }}&lt;/ref&gt; There is a "silence" principle concerning the intersectionality of women and disability, which maintains an overall social denial of the prevalence of abuse among the disabled and leads to this abuse being frequently ignored when encountered.&lt;ref name="Chenoweth"&gt;{{cite journal | last = Chenoweth | first = Lesley | title = Violence and women with disabilities: silence and paradox | journal = [[Violence Against Women (journal)|Violence Against Women]] | volume = 2 | issue = 4 | pages = 391–411 | doi = 10.1177/1077801296002004004 | date = December 1996 | s2cid = 56939366 | ref = harv }}&lt;/ref&gt; A paradox is presented by the overprotection of people with disabilities combined with the expectations of promiscuous behavior of disabled women.&lt;ref name="Lochart_Danis_131" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Chenoweth" /&gt; This leads to limited autonomy and social isolation of disabled individuals, which place women with disabilities in situations where further or more frequent abuse can occur.&lt;ref name="Lochart_Danis_131" /&gt;

== Criticism ==

=== Methods and ideology ===
According to [[political theorist]] Rebecca Reilly-Cooper, intersectionality relies heavily on [[standpoint theory]], which has its own set of criticisms. Intersectionality posits that an oppressed person is often the best person to judge their experience of oppression; however, this can create paradoxes when people who are similarly oppressed have different interpretations of similar events. Such paradoxes make it very difficult to synthesize a common actionable cause based on subjective testimony alone.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Reilly-Cooper|first=Rebecca|url=https://rebeccarc.com/2013/04/15/intersectionality-and-identity-politics/|title=Intersectionality and identity politics|date=15 April 2013|publisher=More Radical With Age|access-date=23 June 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171102032315/https://rebeccarc.com/2013/04/15/intersectionality-and-identity-politics/|archive-date=2 November 2017|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other narratives, especially those based on multiple intersections of oppression, are more complex.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | last1 = Kofi Bright | first1 = Liam | last2 = Malinsky | first2 = Daniel | last3 = Thompson | first3 = Morgan |title= Causally interpreting intersectionality theory | journal = [[Philosophy of Science (journal)|Philosophy of Science]] | volume = 18 | issue = 1 | pages = 60–81 | doi = 10.1086/684173 | date = January 2016 | s2cid = 53695694 | ref = harv |url=https://semanticscholar.org/paper/2cd0f304902b2ca69c655411afcb4e57a5850d33 }} [http://www.liamkofibright.com/uploads/4/8/9/8/48985425/causally_interpreting_intersectionality_theory_final.pdf Pdf.] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170822095036/http://www.liamkofibright.com/uploads/4/8/9/8/48985425/causally_interpreting_intersectionality_theory_final.pdf |date=22 August 2017 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Davis (2008) asserts that intersectionality is ambiguous and open-ended, and that its "lack of clear-cut definition or even specific parameters has enabled it to be drawn upon in nearly any context of inquiry".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last = Davis | first = Kathy | title = Intersectionality as buzzword: A sociology of science perspective on what makes a feminist theory successful | journal = [[Feminist Theory (journal)|Feminist Theory]] | volume = 9 | issue = 1 | pages = 67–85 | doi = 10.1177/1464700108086364 | date = April 2008 | s2cid = 145295170 | ref = harv |url=https://semanticscholar.org/paper/00aba0c6117a0f2500427a592197c18be8383192 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Rekia Jibrin and Sara Salem argue that intersectional theory creates a unified idea of anti-oppression politics that requires a lot out of its adherents, often more than can reasonably be expected, creating difficulties achieving [[Praxis (process)|praxis]]. They also say that intersectional philosophy encourages a focus on the issues inside the group instead of on society at large, and that intersectionality is "a call to complexity and to abandon oversimplification... this has the parallel effect of emphasizing 'internal differences' over hegemonic structures".&lt;ref name="Rekia Jibrin 2015"&gt;{{Cite journal | last1 = Jibrin | first1 = Rekia | last2 = Salem | first2 = Sara | title = Revisiting intersectionality: reflections on theory and praxis | journal = Trans-Scripts: An Interdisciplinary Online Journal in the Humanities and Social Sciences | volume = 5 | date = 2015 |url=http://sites.uci.edu/transscripts/2015-archives-2/ | access-date = 1 December 2017 | archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170527145227/http://sites.uci.edu/transscripts/2015-archives-2/ | archive-date = 27 May 2017 | url-status = live }} [http://sites.uci.edu/transscripts/files/2014/10/2015_5_salem.pdf Pdf.] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180219003117/http://sites.uci.edu/transscripts/files/2014/10/2015_5_salem.pdf |date=19 February 2018 }}&lt;/ref&gt;{{efn|''See ''[[hegemony]] and [[cultural hegemony]].}}

Barbara Tomlinson is employed at the Department of Women's Studies at UC Santa Barbara and has been critical of the applications of intersectional theory. She has identified several ways in which the conventional theory has been destructive to the movement. She asserts that the common practice of using intersectionality to attack other ways of feminist thinking and the tendency of academics to critique intersectionality instead of using intersectionality as a tool to critique other conventional ways of thinking has been a misuse of the ideas it stands for. Tomlinson argues that in order to use intersectional theory correctly, intersectional feminists must not only consider the arguments but the tradition and mediums through which these arguments are made. Conventional academics are likely to favor writings by authors or publications with prior established credibility instead of looking at the quality of each piece individually, contributing to negative stereotypes associated with both feminism and intersectionality by having weaker arguments in defense of feminism and intersectionality become prominent based on renown. She goes on to argue that this allows critics of intersectionality to attack these weaker arguments, "[reducing] intersectionality's radical critique of power to desires for identity and inclusion, and offer a deradicalized intersectionality as an asset for dominant disciplinary discourses".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last = Tomlinson | first = Barbara | title = To Tell the Truth and Not Get Trapped: Desire, Distance, and Intersectionality at the Scene of Argument | journal = Signs: Journal of Women in Culture and Society | volume = 38 | issue = 4 | pages = 993–1017 | doi = 10.1086/669571 | date =Summer 2013 | s2cid = 144641071 | ref = harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Lisa Downing argues that intersectionality focuses too much on group identities, which can lead it to ignore the fact that people are individuals, not just members of a class. Ignoring this can cause intersectionality to lead to a simplistic analysis and inaccurate assumptions about how a person's values and attitudes are determined.&lt;ref&gt;Downing, Lisa. "The body politic: Gender, the right wing and 'identity category violations'." French Cultural Studies 29, no. 4 (2018): 367-377.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Psychology===

{{Main|Biases|Heuristics in judgment and decision-making}}
Researchers in psychology have incorporated intersection effects since the 1950s{{Example needed|date=September 2018}}. These intersection effects were based on studying the lenses of biases, heuristics, stereotypes, and judgments. Psychologists have extended research in psychological biases to the areas of cognitive and motivational psychology. What is found, is that every human mind has its own biases in judgment and decision-making that tend to preserve the status quo by avoiding change and attention to ideas that exist outside one's personal realm of perception.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Gorrell|first=Michael Gorrell|date=2011|title=Combining NetLibrary E-books with the EBSCOhost Platform|journal=Information Standards Quarterly|volume=23|issue=2|pages=31|doi=10.3789/isqv23n2.2011.07|s2cid=61688766|issn=1041-0031|url=https://semanticscholar.org/paper/2bf86c0ee1851b9cb678dee377f5f5045cb51ab9}}&lt;/ref&gt; Psychological interaction effects span a range of variables, although person-by-situation effects are the most examined category. As a result, psychologists do not construe the interaction effect of demographics such as gender and race as either more noteworthy or less noteworthy than any other interaction effect. In addition, oppression can be regarded as a subjective construct when viewed as an absolute hierarchy. Even if an objective definition of oppression was reached, person-by-situation effects would make it difficult to deem certain persons or categories of persons as uniformly oppressed. For instance, black men are stereotypically perceived as violent, which may be a disadvantage in police interactions, but also as physically attractive,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | last = Lewis | first = Michael B. | title = A facial attractiveness account of gender asymmetries in interracial marriage | journal = [[PLOS ONE]] | doi = 10.1371/journal.pone.0031703 | date = 9 February 2012 | ref = harv | volume=7 | issue = 2 | pages=e31703 | pmid=22347504 | pmc=3276508| bibcode = 2012PLoSO...731703L }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | last = Lewis | first = Michael B. | title = Who is the fairest of them all? Race, attractiveness and skin color sexual dimorphism | journal = [[Personality and Individual Differences]] | volume = 50 | issue = 2 | pages = 159–162 | doi = 10.1016/j.paid.2010.09.018 | date = January 2011 | ref = harv }}&lt;/ref&gt; which may be advantageous in romantic situations.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

Psychological studies have shown that the effect of multiplying "oppressed" identities is not necessarily additive, but rather interactive in complex ways. For instance, black gay men may be more positively evaluated than black heterosexual men, because the "feminine" aspects of gay stereotypes temper the hypermasculine and aggressive aspect of black stereotypes.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite journal | last = Pedulla | first = David S. | title = The positive consequences of negative stereotypes: race, sexual orientation, and the job application process | journal = [[Social Psychology Quarterly]] | volume = 77 | issue = 1 | pages = 75–94 | doi = 10.1177/0190272513506229 | date = March 2014 | s2cid = 144311164 | ref = harv |url=https://semanticscholar.org/paper/76b4aec78fac73ace101d7ededed1095184adb81 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | last1 = Remedios | first1 = Jessica D. | last2 = Chasteen | first2 = Alison L. | last3 = Rule | first3 = Nicholas O. | last4 = Plaks | first4 = Jason E. | title = Impressions at the intersection of ambiguous and obvious social categories: Does gay + Black = likable? | journal = [[Journal of Experimental Social Psychology]] | volume = 47 | issue = 6 | pages = 1312–1315 | doi = 10.1016/j.jesp.2011.05.015 | date = November 2011 | ref = harv | hdl = 1807/33199 |url=https://tspace.library.utoronto.ca/bitstream/1807/33199/1/Remedios_etal%282011%29.pdf }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Div col|colwidth=30em}}
* [[Black feminism]]
* [[Caste]]
* [[Humanism]]
* [[Identitarianism]]
* [[Kyriarchy]]
* [[Oppression Olympics]]
* [[Privilege (social inequality)]]
* [[Standpoint theory]]
* [[Transnational feminism]]
* [[Triple oppression]]
* [[Womanism]]
* [[Implicit stereotype]]
{{div col end}}

==Notes==
{{notelist}}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
* {{cite journal |last=Crenshaw |first=Kimberlé |title=Demarginalizing the Intersection of Race and Sex: A Black Feminist Critique of Antidiscrimination Doctrine, Feminist Theory and Antiracist Politics |journal=University of Chicago Legal Forum |volume=1989 |issue=1 |url=http://chicagounbound.uchicago.edu/uclf/vol1989/iss1/8}}
* {{cite web |first=Patricia Hill |last=Collins |title=Black Feminist Thought in the Matrix of Domination |url=http://www.hartford-hwp.com/archives/45a/252.html |website=www.hartford-hwp.com}}
* {{cite web |first=Patricia Hill |last=Collins |authorlink=Patricia Hill Collins|url=http://www.hsph.harvard.edu/Organizations/healthnet/WoC/feminisms/collins2.html |url-status=dead |archive-date=11 December 2006 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20061211050851/http://www.hsph.harvard.edu/Organizations/healthnet/WoC/feminisms/collins2.html |title=Black Feminist Thought |publisher=Women of Color Web |year=1990 }}
* {{cite web |first=Patricia Hill |last=Collins |title=A Brief History of Black Feminist Thought |url=http://www.rpi.edu/%7Eeglash/eglash.dir/SST/bft.htm |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100603050033/http://www.rpi.edu/%7Eeglash/eglash.dir/SST/bft.htm |archive-date=2010-06-03 |publisher=Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute |accessdate=16 November 2020}}
* {{cite web |first=Allison |last=McCarthy |editor-first=Deborah |editor-last=Siegel |url=http://girlwpen.com/?page_id=1724 |title=The Intersectional Feminist |publisher=Girl w/ Pen |url-status=dead |archive-date=15 November 2012 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20121115121230/http://girlwpen.com/?page_id=1724 }}
* {{citation |url=https://www.sfu.ca/iirp/documents/resources/101_Final.pdf |title=Intersectionality 101 |first=Olena |last=Hankivsky |publisher=The Institute for Intersectionality Research &amp; Policy, SFU |date=April 2014 |isbn=978-0-86491-355-5|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170423171506/https://www.sfu.ca/iirp/documents/resources/101_Final.pdf |archive-date=23 April 2017 }}

{{Wikiquote}}
{{Wiktionary|intersectionality}}

[[Category:Intersectionality]]
[[Category:Intersectional feminism]]
[[Category:Feminist theory]]
[[Category:Social constructionism]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>