<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20160702105536|727984421" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1298951" pageid="1298951" ns="0" title="Internalized oppression"><revisions><rev timestamp="2016-11-11T08:17:01Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">'''Internalized oppression''' is the manner in [[sociology]] and [[psychology]] in which an oppressed group comes to use against itself the methods of the oppressor.

For example, sometimes members of marginalized groups hold an oppressive view toward their own populations, or they start to believe in negative stereotypes of themselves.

Internalized oppression also exists among some immigrants and their descendants. If the foreigner's ethnic origin, native language or culture are devalued vis-a-vis those of the host community, the person may feel a sense of inferiority. This [[self-hatred]] in turn manifests itself through an exaggerated conformity with the dominant norms, which the individual perceives as superior to his own. As such, in response to ridicule, an immigrant may attempt to compensate via [[Cultural assimilation|assimilation]] and [[acculturation]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Van den Berghe|first1=Pierre L.|title=The Ethnic Phenomenon|date=1987|publisher=ABC-CLIO|isbn=0275927091|page=258|url=https://www.google.com/books?id=esAA9Njteu0C|accessdate=22 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Internalized homophobia]] and [[internalized sexism]] are also categories of internalized oppression.&lt;ref&gt;Leong, F. T. L. Encyclopedia of Counseling.  London: SAGE Publications LTD., 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Internalized racism]]
*[[Learned helplessness]]
*[[Self-hatred]]

==Notes==
{{reflist}}

{{psych-stub}}

[[Category:Psychological abuse]]
[[Category:Social justice]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>