<?xml version="1.0"?><api><continue rvcontinue="20231103195816|1183354239" continue="||" /><warnings><main xml:space="preserve">Subscribe to the mediawiki-api-announce mailing list at &lt;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/mediawiki-api-announce.lists.wikimedia.org/&gt; for notice of API deprecations and breaking changes. Use [[Special:ApiFeatureUsage]] to see usage of deprecated features by your application.</main><revisions xml:space="preserve">Because "rvslots" was not specified, a legacy format has been used for the output. This format is deprecated, and in the future the new format will always be used.</revisions></warnings><query><pages><page _idx="1298951" pageid="1298951" ns="0" title="Internalized oppression"><revisions><rev timestamp="2023-11-05T00:59:54Z" contentformat="text/x-wiki" contentmodel="wikitext" xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|Concept in social justice theory}}
{{Discrimination sidebar|Related}}
In [[social justice]] theory, '''internalized oppression''' is a recognized understanding in which an [[oppression|oppressed]] group accepts the methods and incorporates the oppressive message of the oppressing group against their own best interest.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Pheterson |first=Gail |date=1986 |title=Alliances between Women: Overcoming Internalized Oppression and Internalized Domination |url=https://www.jstor.org/stable/3174362 |journal=Signs |volume=12 |issue=1 |pages=146–160 |doi=10.1086/494302 |jstor=3174362 |s2cid=143567739 |issn=0097-9740 |quote=Internalized oppression is the incorporation and acceptance... for perpetuating domination not only by external controls but also by building subservience into the minds of the oppressed groups.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Rosenwasser (2002) defines it as believing, adopting, accepting, and incorporating the negative beliefs provided by the oppressor as the truth.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Rosenwasser |first=Penny |date=2002 |title=Exploring internalized oppression and healing strategies |url=https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/ace.59 |journal=New Directions for Adult and Continuing Education |language=en |volume=2002 |issue=94 |pages=53–62 |doi=10.1002/ace.59 |issn=1052-2891 |quote=... stereotypes that people outside our group say are true about us. We learn to loathe ourselves, rather than understanding...}}&lt;/ref&gt;

It occurs as a part of socialisation in an oppressive environment. Members of [[Social exclusion|marginalized]] groups assimilate the oppressive view of their own group and consequently affirm negative [[Self-stereotyping|self-stereotypes]]. This creates a detrimental impact on their psychosocial well-being and self-systems, leading them to produce and reproduce stress-induced disadvantageous behavioral responses and habit [[Habit formation|formation]]. As a result, they form and perpetuate an "assaulted sense of self" by not intentionally and deliberately engaging in active responsibility for their own well-being, and by not proactively acting as agents of change that foster their group's well-being (e.g., counterspaces).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last1=Case |first1=Andrew D. |last2=Hunter |first2=Carla D. |date=2012 |title=Counterspaces: A Unit of Analysis for Understanding the Role of Settings in Marginalized Individuals' Adaptive Responses to Oppression |url=https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1007/s10464-012-9497-7 |journal=American Journal of Community Psychology |language=en |volume=50 |issue=1–2 |pages=257–270 |doi=10.1007/s10464-012-9497-7 |pmid=22374370 |s2cid=44866727 |issn=0091-0562}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Hardy |first=Kenneth V. |date=2013 |title=Healing the Hidden Wounds of Racial Trauma |url=https://eric.ed.gov/?id=EJ1023873 |journal=Reclaiming Children and Youth |language=en |volume=22 |issue=1 |pages=24–28 |issn=1089-5701 |archive-url=}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Depending on the form of discrimination, types of internalized oppression include [[internalized racism]], [[internalized homophobia]], [[internalized sexism]], and [[Auto-Antisemitism|auto-antisemitism]].&lt;ref name="auto1"/&gt;

==Types==

Internalized oppression occurs as a result of psychological injury caused by external oppressive events (e.g., harassment and discrimination), and it has a negative impact on individuals' self system (e.g., self-esteem, self-image, self-concept, self-worth, and self-regulation).&lt;ref name="auto1"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Szymanski |first1=Dawn M. |last2=Gupta |first2=Arpana |title=Examining the relationship between multiple internalized oppressions and African American lesbian, gay, bisexual, and questioning persons' self-esteem and psychological distress. |journal=Journal of Counseling Psychology |date=January 2009 |volume=56 |issue=1 |pages=110–118 |doi=10.1037/a0013317 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The trauma of internalized oppression is amplified by repetitive exposure to explicit violence such as segregation and discrimination, as well as implicitly through various forms of oppressive microprocesses and insidious [[Microaggression|microaggressions]] (e.g., privaition of inclusion and peripheralizing).&lt;ref name="auto"/&gt; It may manifest on an individual or group level, and may form as base for in-group conflict and further discrimination that can be hurtful and limiting.&lt;ref name="auto"&gt;David, E. J. R. and Annie O. Derthick. "What Is Internalized Oppression, and so What?." Internalized Oppression: The Psychology of Marginalized Groups., E. J. R. David and E. J. R., (Ed) David, Springer Publishing Co, 2014, pp. 1–30. https://connect.springerpub.com/content/book/978-0-8261-9926-3/part/part01/chapter/ch01&lt;/ref&gt; 

[[Internalized racism]] is about fostering a negative attitude towards one's own race, created by the oppressing race, and nurturing a positive attitude towards the oppressor's race (e.g., [[race traitor]]). As a result, it leads individuals to experience chronic self-hatred and deny their membership in their own racial group.&lt;ref name="auto1"/&gt; Over time, it can be an effect of internalized colonialism. As heirs of ingrained assimilation to the oppressor's truth and by nurturing [[Attribution bias|attributional errors]], the colonized people gradually accept the oppressor's norm as the norm to follow, often unintentionally and without being aware of it. An example of internalized colonialism on self-perception is the practice of [[skin whitening]] (see [[Discrimination based on skin color|colorism]]), which is found in Africa and Asia.&lt;ref name="auto"/&gt;

Internalized [[homophobia]], also known as internalized [[heterosexism]], occurs in the [[LGBT community]] when individuals adopt a culture's heterosexist attitudes. It has a positive correlation with psychological distress and a negative correlation with self-esteem.&lt;ref name="auto1"/&gt; Internalized homophobia is strongly associated with guilt and shame (especially among youth) and has been linked to increased anxiety, depression and suicide.&lt;ref&gt;Puckett, Jae A., et al. "Predictors of Sexual Minority Youth's Reported Suicide Attempts and Mental Health." Journal of homosexuality, vol. 64, no. 6, 2017, pp. 697–715.&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[internalized sexism]], individuals (generally women) adopt oppressive attitudes towards their gender which are held by their culture. An example is [[slut-shaming]], where women criticize transgressions of accepted codes of sexual conduct on themselves and other women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Armstrong |first1=Elizabeth A. |last2=Hamilton |first2=Laura T. |last3=Armstrong |first3=Elizabeth M. |last4=Seeley |first4=J. Lotus |title='Good Girls': Gender, Social Class, and Slut Discourse on Campus |journal=Social Psychology Quarterly |date=June 2014 |volume=77 |issue=2 |pages=100–122 |doi=10.1177/0190272514521220 |s2cid=12935534 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Internalized oppression may also exist among [[Immigration|immigrants]], and based upon the [[transgenerational trauma]], it may affect their descendants as well. If the host community devalues a foreigner's [[Ethnic group|ethnic]] origin, native language or culture, an immigrant is led to feel [[Inferiority complex|inferior]]. This can lead to [[self-hatred]], which manifests itself in an exaggerated [[conformity]] to dominant norms. An immigrant may cope to it by [[Cultural assimilation|assimilating]] and [[Acculturation|acculturating]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Van den Berghe|first1=Pierre L.|title=The Ethnic Phenomenon|date=1987|publisher=ABC-CLIO|isbn=0275927091|page=258|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=esAA9Njteu0C|access-date=22 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Causes==
Internalized oppression "occurs when a person comes to [[Internalization (sociology)|internalize]] oppressive prejudices and biases about the identity group(s) to which he or she belongs".&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Joseph, Valerie and Tanya O. Williams|date=2009|title=Good Niggers: The Struggle to Find Courage, Strength and Confidence to Fight Internalized Racism and Internalized Dominance|journal=Democracy and Education|volume=17|issue=3}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Cross, Jr.|first1=William E.|title=Identity Work: Enactment of Racial-Ethnic Identity in Everyday Life|journal=Identity |date=2017|volume=17|issue=1|pages=1–12|doi=10.1080/15283488.2016.1268535|hdl=2429/66263|s2cid=151785936|hdl-access=free}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Bartky|first1=Sandra Lee|title=Foucault, Femininity, and the Modernization of Patriarchal Power|journal=Feminism and Foucault: Reflections on Resistance|date=1988}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":2"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Liebow|first1=Nabina|date=Fall 2016|title=Internalized Oppression and Its Varied Moral Harms: Self-Perceptions of Reduced Agency and Criminality|journal=Hypatia|volume=31|issue=4|pages=713–729|doi=10.1111/hypa.12265|s2cid=148200668}}&lt;/ref&gt; It occurs when "[s]ocial oppression such as racism, sexism, ableism, classism, heterosexism, gender and religious oppression, and anti-Semitism" are "implanted by and [work] toward the benefit of any dominant group.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; Internalized oppression "depends on [[wiktionary:systemic|systemically]] limiting, blocking, and undermining" the "success, innovation, and power" of oppressed individuals or groups.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; Some individuals will copy (and internalize) "institutionalized rejection of difference," failing "to examine the distortions which result from ... misnaming [these differences] and their effects on human behavior and expectations."&lt;ref name="Age, Race, Class, and Sex: Women Re"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Lorde|first1=Audre|title=Age, Race, Class, and Sex: Women Redefining Difference|journal=Sister Outsider|date=1984}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Effects==
{{see also|Health psychology}}
"If women are surrounded by people who view them as subordinate, incapable, or lacking control over their actions, women are likely to come to understand themselves in a similar way, even if subconsciously."&lt;ref name="auto2"&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Liebow |first1=Nabina |title=Internalized Oppression and Its Varied Moral Harms: Self‐Perceptions of Reduced Agency and Criminality |journal=Hypatia |date=2016 |volume=31 |issue=4 |pages=713–729 |doi=10.1111/hypa.12265 |s2cid=148200668 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Internalized oppression fosters the beliefs that the self cannot be [[Autonomy|autonomous]], is unworthy of wielding power, and is little more than an object of sexual gratification (see [[sexual objectification]]).&lt;ref name="auto2"/&gt; "Psychological oppression can be damaging to a person's moral relationship with the self ... Since those who have internalized oppressive prejudices often engage in behavior that further perpetuates these biases, internalized oppression is not only a symptom of an oppressive social climate, but it also represents a mechanism for its continued existence".&lt;ref name="auto2"/&gt; According to [[University of Massachusetts Amherst]] doctoral students Valerie Joseph and Tanya O. Williams, "Deep racial self-negation[,]&amp;nbsp;... internalized racial hatred [and] internalized oppression&amp;nbsp;... stymied [their] growth as people and scholars [and] inhibited [their] ability to be…profound, strong, and beautiful&amp;nbsp;..."&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; Individuals can be made to feel "implicated in a project of compliance with the values and goals" of the dominant society.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; Internalized oppression may also occur in [[Disability|disabled]] individuals, who may distance themselves from others with disabilities to avoid associating themselves with those who may be viewed by society as "weak" or "lazy".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Fahs | first1 = Breanne | title = The Dreaded Body: Disgust and the Production of "appropriate" Femininity | journal = Journal of Gender Studies | year = 2015 | pages = 1–13 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Nabina Liebow wrote, "[[Person of color|People of color]] who internalize stereotypes regarding [[Crime|criminality]] and moral deviance&amp;nbsp;... can &amp;nbsp;... view themselves as outlaws in the moral community" and may "engage in behavior that further perpetuates these biases&amp;nbsp;... Fulfilling these stereotypes further pushes someone outside the moral fold and intensifies one's damaged moral identity&amp;nbsp;... [I]nternalizing stereotypes about criminality and moral deviance can lead to a pervasive feeling of [[Guilt (emotion)|guilt]]&amp;nbsp;... Persistent feelings of guilt can result in [[Mental health|mental-health]] setbacks such as [[Depression (mood)|depression]]" and "repeated exposure to guilt and similar feelings has been linked with a range of health challenges such as "dysfunctional coping, abdominal obesity, and glucose intolerance complicit in the development of Type 2 diabetes".&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt;

==Manifestations==
According to [[Audre Lorde]], manifestations of internalized oppression include voluntary isolation.&lt;ref name="Age, Race, Class, and Sex: Women Re"/&gt; She describes the relationship between older members of an oppressed group and younger members of the same group as "contemptible or suspect or excess."{{sic}}&lt;ref name="Age, Race, Class, and Sex: Women Re"/&gt; This [[generation gap]] leads to "historical amnesia", with oppressed minorities repeating the learning process and failing to convey knowledge to subsequent generations.&lt;ref name="Age, Race, Class, and Sex: Women Re"/&gt; Lorde cites oppressed individuals as "encouraged to pluck out some one aspect of [one]self and present this as the meaningful whole, eclipsing or denying the other parts of the self";&lt;ref name="Age, Race, Class, and Sex: Women Re"/&gt; they may hesitate to breach the false stereotypes surrounding them or verbalize resistance to violence.&lt;ref name="Age, Race, Class, and Sex: Women Re"/&gt; The most common manifestation is self-hatred.&lt;ref name="Age, Race, Class, and Sex: Women Re"/&gt;

Racial manifestations include "multifaceted and extreme psychological, social, and economic self-sabotage"; a tendency to "defer to [[White people|whites]]", and feelings of being "not [[Black people|black]] enough".&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; The self is viewed as a diminished, deviant, criminal and undeserving moral agent.&lt;ref name=":2" /&gt; [[Sandra Bartky]] identified disturbances in [[body image]], [[gender expression]] and power dynamics as manifestations of internalized sexism in women.&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;

==Remedies==
According to Audre Lorde, "[T]he master's tools will never dismantle the master's house&amp;nbsp;... My fullest concentration of energy is available to me only when I integrate all the parts of who I am, openly, allowing power from the particular sources of my living to flow back and forth freely through all my different selves, without the restrictions of externally imposed definition".&lt;ref name="Age, Race, Class, and Sex: Women Re" /&gt; "To root out internalized patterns of oppression" women must "recognize differences among women who are our equals, neither inferior nor superior, and devise ways to use each other's difference to enrich our visions and our joint struggles …to identify and develop new definitions of power and new patterns of relating across difference&amp;nbsp;... sharpen[ing] self-definition by exposing the self in work and struggle together with those whom we define as different from ourselves, although sharing similar goals".&lt;ref name="Age, Race, Class, and Sex: Women Re" /&gt;

To understand and overcome internalized oppression, Joseph and Williams developed a workshop to "introduce and discuss issues of socialization, stereotyping, internalized oppression, and domination." This "social justice education model&amp;nbsp;... encouraged an agent/target model of leadership" in which representatives of the oppressor and oppressed classes joined together to guide "participants in developing a plan of action to address racism."{{quote without source|date=February 2020}} They recommended that fear "left over about discussing race, racism, and internalized racism" be set aside to "talk forthrightly, honestly, reflectively, and thoughtfully about race", and the "need to voice&amp;nbsp;... hurt, the need to surface realities, the need to shine light on a history that was and continues to be ignored" is greater than the fear of discussing the issues.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; The internally oppressed must learn how they have been indoctrinated, to "engage in a process of rejecting internalized subordination as an everyday choice".&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

==Related theories==

French philosopher [[Michel Foucault]] "has argued that the rise of parliamentary institutions and of new conceptions of political liberty was accompanied by a darker counter-movement, by the emergence of a new and unprecedented discipline directed against the body. More is required of the body now than mere political allegiance or the approbation of the products of its labor: the new discipline invades the body and seeks to regulate its very forces and operations, the economy and efficiency of its movements&amp;nbsp;... the production of 'docile bodies' requires that an uninterrupted coercion be directed to the very processes of bodily activity, not just their result; this 'micro-physics of power' fragments and partitions the body's time, its space, and its movements".&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;

The 18th-century English philosopher [[Jeremy Bentham]]'s [[Panopticon]] is a theoretical model of Foucault's ideas. Its constant state of surveillance, imposed by an oppressive external force, serves {{"'}}to induce in the inmate a state of consciousness and permanent visibility that assures the automatic functioning of power'; each becomes to himself his own jailer".&lt;ref name=":1" /&gt;

==See also==
* [[Internalization (psychology)]]
* [[Learned helplessness]]
* [[Passing (racial identity)]]
* [[Social reproduction]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{Discrimination}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Internalized oppression}}
[[Category:Social justice terminology]]
[[Category:Majority–minority relations]]
[[Category:Social privilege]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>